<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00010c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T08:09:04.293Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Secret. C. 120. a This document is the property of the Secretary of State for India in Council. Memorandum as to Persian Government Loans. [Note. — The paging in brackets, thus (P. 40), refers to pages in the volumes of corresponding date of Foreign Office Persia Prints.] Object of the Memorandum. 1- The question of the indebtedness of the Persian Government falls primarily within the cognizance of the Foreign Office, but from time to time the India Office is called upon to consider it, chiefly (1.) because the Secretary of State for India in Council has advanced money to the Persian Government, and (2) because the main security for the British Government loans to Persia is the customs receipts of Southern Persia, the part of the country with which India is more intimately connected. The Memorandum is intended mainly for de partmental reference, and an index has been added. The Russian Loan if 1900. (£2,250,000.) * The customs of Kennanshah, it may be observed, were to be left out of account, because Her Majesty’s Government neither wished to face the risk of being called on to occupy the Kermanshah customs house, nor desired to see tlie Russians, on their side, in occupation of b. Telegram to Sir M. Uarand, No. 24, 2nd August 1899. (P. 46.) Telegram from British Ambassador at St. Petersburg, No. 17, 50th January 1900. (P. 36. See also p. 43.) t The value of the rouble is slightly above 2s. 2. In 1899 there was much discussion as to the necessity of financial assistance to the Persian Government. A British loan on the security of the southern customs was spoken of, with a Russian loan on the security of the customs of the Caspian Ports.* Communications on the whole subject had passed between the British and Russian Govern ments, when on the 30th January 1900 the official Russian Gazette announced that the Russian Government had decided to sanction a loan to the Persian Government from the Banque des Prets of 22,500,000 roubles,! roughly 2,250,000L, on the following terms :— “ The payment of interest and of sinking fund for the extinction of the loan in 75 years is to be guaranteed by all the customs revenues of Persia, exclusive of those of Fars and the Persian Gulf Ports. “ In case of any delay in the payments of the service of the loan, for which the revenues thus pledged are at present more than sufficient, the Bank is to have the right of establishing a control of the said revenues. The Persian Government engages to extinguish all its previous external obligations with the proceeds of the new loan, and not to conclude without consent of the Bank any fresh foreign loan whatever until the loan of 1900 has been extinguished. The Persian Government grants the Bank the right of placing, if it thinks necessary, on the money market bonds of the Persian Loan proportionate to the unredeemed amount of the debt, and bearing the full guarantee of the Imperial Russian Government.”2 Later on, Mr. Spring-Rice reported from Tehran that a clause had been added to the Loan Contract, on the Shah’s insistence, enabling the Persian Government to pay back the debt, if they wished, after ten years. Fuller particulars as to the loan were contained in a Memorandum communicated to the Foreign Office on the 17th August 1900 by Sir T. Gordon, after a conversation with the Sadr Azam at Ostend, but a certified copy of the contract was not available until it Avas procured by Sir A. Hardinge from M. Nans, the Belgian head of the Customs in Persia, and sent home on the 9th December 1901. The expression used in this contract (Art. 7) as to the security of the loan is “ toutes les douanes de Perse, a Vexception de celles “ du Fars et des ports du Golfe Persique.” The loan could be paid off “ d partir du F r Janvier 1910,” on giving six months’ notice. 3. The British Ambassador at St. Petersburg protested against the conclusion of this Russian loan without the previous exchange of views that the Russian Government had promised. He was referred by the Foreign Minister, Count Mouravieff, to the Minister of Finance, M. de Witte, who maintained that the transaction had been of a financial, ?.e., non-political, character and denied that the Banque des Prets was in any sense a branch of the Russian State Bank. lie explained that the customs revenues from the Persian Gulf ports and the Province of Fars had been expressly excluded from the security of the loan, so as not to interfere with British interests. 4. It may here be mentioned that in 1897 the Persian Government had undertaken not to place under foreign control and supervision the customs of Southern Persia. It had in that year come to notice that a certain oculist, Dr. Ratoul, was arranging for a loan to the Persian Government on the security of the customs of the southern ports of Persia and of Kermanshah, and Mr. A. Hardinge demanded from the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs “ an assurance that under no circumstances “ whatever will the control of the customs of “ Southern Persia be ceded to a foreign power.” He received on the 23rd October 1897 the following official communication: — “ You have written that there was a rumour that the customs of Southern Persia would be placed under foreign supervision and control as guarantee for a loan. 1 therefore take this oppor tunity of informing the Legation that this rumour is absolutely without foundation, and that they will never be placed under foreign supervision and control.” “ (Signed) Mushir-ed-Dowleji, “ Minister for Foreign Affairs.” {See para. 17.) 5. The Russian loan a fait accompli, the importance was recognised of making clear at once Mr. Spring-Rice’s Despatch No. 29 5th April 1900. (P. 36.) Memorandum of Sir T. Gordon. (P. 67.) Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 186, 9th December 1901. (P. 224.) Protest of the British Government. Sir C. Scott’s Despatch No. 70, 10th March 1900. (P. 135.) Persian uidertaking regarding the customs of “ Southern Persia.” Foreign Office Asia Print, 22nd Novem ber, Section 2. Pol. 2590/04. The Customs of Mohammerah.3 Mr. Spring-Rice's Despatch No. 17, 27th March 1900. (P. 26.) Mr. Spring-Rice’s Despatch No. 17, 27th March 1900. (P. 26). Mr. Spring-Rice's Despatch No. 27, 5th April 1900. (P. 34.) Despatch to Mr. Spring-Rice, No. 24, 10th May 1900. (P. 50.) Imperial Bank’s Loan of 1901. (£ 200 , 000 .) to the Persian Government that, in the opinion of Her Majesty’s Government, the customs of the port of Mohammerah were included in the customs of ‘Southern Persia.” On instructions from Lord Salisbury Mr. Spring-Rice communicated to the Minister for Foreign Affairs a pro-memorid in which tne following words occurred :— “ Lord Salisbury thinks it due to the friendship existing between the Governments of Persia and Great Britain that there should be a clear under standing of his views as to the ports of Mohammerah, Bushire, Bunder Abbas, and other ports of the I ersian Gulf. Ibis is the best way to avoid difficulties in the future. “ It is not necessary to remind the Persian Government of the circumstances which make it impossible for Her Majesty s Government to regard with indifference what happens in the ports above named. “ As this Legation has recently stated, the control of these ports by a foreign power might lead to a state of things which Her Majesty’s Government, in the interests of the Indian Empire, would be bound to resist. And this has been recognised by the Persian Government, who, on the 23rd October 1897, gave a written promise that the customs of Southern Persia should never be placed under foreign control and supervision. “ The Persian Government did not fail to bear this promise in mind during the recent negotiations, and, as the Sadr-i-Azam has informed Her Majesty’s Legation, the customs revenues of the above- mentioned ports were specially excepted from those which formed the guarantee of the Russian loan. “ I am to state that Her Majesty’s Government must hold the Persian Government to the strict observance of this engagement.” In reply the Persian Foreign Minister assured Mr. Spring-Rice orally, with regard to Mohammerah, that it was clearly to the interest of the Persian Government to except as many ports as possible from the Russian guarantee, and that he was quite aware that Her Majest} 7 ’s Government would not agree to any interpretation of the Loan Contract which included Mohammerah among the ports on which Russia had a lien. At a later interview, on the 5th April, Mr. Spring-Rice was told by the Foreign Minister that the expression in the Russian Loan Contract was—“ except Fars and the Gulf of Fars,” and he was assured that “ not only in Mohammerah, “ but in every part of Persia where British interests “ are concerned, the Persian Government, before “ taking any steps of importance, would consult “ the British Government.” Mr. Spring-Rice was then instructed that he need not recur for the moment to the matter of the Mohammerah customs unless any fresh incident should arise. 0. The money supplied to Persia through the Russian Government was very soon exhausted, and before the end of the year (1900) there were4 rumours of other loans. At the beginning of 1901 Mr. Spring-Rice wrote that the Imperial Bank of Persia might be asked for an advance of 200,000k on their current account with the Persian Govern ment—an advance which “ would not be a loan “ within the meaning of the clause in the Russian “ Loan Agreement.” The Bushire customs, he remarked, were bringing in about 1,400k a week' 1 ', but he had suggested to the Bank to demand the Mohammerah customs as an additional guarantee, to solve the question raised at the time of the Russian contract. On the 14th March Sir A. Hardinge telegraphed from 1 eheran that the loan had been applied for from the Bank, repayable by 36 monthly instalments, the security being a preferential claim upon the southern customs. The arrangement was carried through in April, and an additional 20,000k Avas lent a little later, making 220,000k in all. The rate of interest Avas 12 per cent. The Imperial Bank, it may be explained, are not allowed by the terms of their concession to lend to the Persian Government beyond the limit of one-third of their paid-up capital of 650,000k, i.e., 216,666k (Appendix I). 7. Still, the Persian Government continued in sore straits for money. They Avere willing to borroAV from the British Government, and they were known also to be endeavouring to obtain a further loan from Russia. On the 28th October 1901 Lord Lansdowne telegraphed to the British Ambassador at St. Petersburg (Mr. C. Hardinge) to draw the attention of the Russian Government to the fact that any arrangement under which Persia Avould pass under the financial tutelage of either Power would be incompatible with the maintenance of the independence of the country, recognised by under standings arm'ed at in 1834 and 1888. A Trench paraphrase of this telegram Avas furnished to the Russian Foreign Minister, Count Lamsdorff, on the following day, its concluding words being as follows :— . / 'UAngletcrre a ton jours reconvu les inter els preponderants de lei Tiussic duns 1c noi’d de lu 1 a se. Dans le sud, an contraire, et surtout aux ports du Colfe Person, autant qu'en Seistan, la Grande- Brctacjne a des interets qiielle ne pent laisser ignorer. “ Lc Gouvernement de Sa Majcste est tout pret d discutcr avec le Gouvernement Imperial, de la jaqon la plus amicale, la possibilitc d'un arrangement par lequel des avances d'argent pourraient simultanement se jaire d la Perse par Vcntremise dcs deux Puissances, qui accepteraient respectivement comme garantie les revenus Persons leves dans les spheres susmentionnees.' Count Lamsdorff in reply informed Mr. C. Hardinge that he had learnt from M. de Witte that, contrary to what he had told Mr. Hardinge before, the Russian Bank had been in negotiation with the Persian Government for another loan, and that a small advance had in fact been already granted. He declared himself as most anxious to Mr. Spring-Rice’s Despatch No. 20, 6th February 1901. (P. 73.) * 72,800/. a year. Imperial Bank of Persia to Foreign Office, 20th September 1901. (P. 205.) “ Financial tutelage.” Telegram to Mr. C. Hardinge, No. 173, 28th October 1901. (P. 56.) Mr. C. Hardinge’s Despatch] No. 304, dated 30th October 1901. (P. 91.) Mr. C. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 314, 3rd November 1901. (P. 108.)maintain the independence of Persia, and denied that a state of financial tutelage existed in that country. Offer of advance from Indian Revenues (£500,000.). Letters of India Office to Foreign Office, 6th and 11th November 1901. (P. 104 and p. 112.) Pol. 2519/01,2541/01. 8. The position being as above explained, it was decided by His Majesty’s Government that the time had come for action. By two letters, dated the 6th and llth ( November 1901 the Secretary of State for India expressed his willingness to advance to the Persian Government the sum of 500,000Z. It was explained in the later letter that the sum was to be advanced from Indian revenues in order to meet the convenience of His Majesty’s Govern ment, and that the principle, recorded in the Report of the Royal Commission on the Expenditure of India, of equal division between the British and Indian Governments of diplomatic charges in Persia, was recognised as applying to the case. The advance of the money was to be subject to certain conditions, which included, together with stipula tions as to the tariff, Seistan, &amp;c., security for the loan on the “ revenue of the customs of the ports of the southern littoral of Persia, including Moham- merah,” and a provision that the loan should not be repayable (unless by consent) within a period of ten years. Delay in acceptance of advance offered. Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 175, 13th November 1901. (P. 157.) Sir A. Hardinge's Telegram No. 80, 28th November 1901. (P. 146.) Despatch to Sir A. Hardinge, No. 2, 6th January 1902. (P. 5.) * For the Shah's reply, see Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 26, 16th February 1902. (P. 115.) Despatch to Sir C. Scott, No, 40, 8th February 1902. (P. 52.) 9. The offer of this advance tvas made to the Persian Grand Vizier, but the question was raised by him whether its acceptance would not conflict with the Russian Loan Contract of 1900. Sir A. Hardinge explained that he understood that agree ment to prohibit a foreign loan in the sense of the sale of Persian securities on the open market, but not such an arrangement as was proposed by Bis Majesty’s Government. The Persian Government still felt themselves, however, unable to accept the British offer, and the Grand Vizier informed Sir A. Hardinge on the 28th November 1901 that M. de Witte had refused to allow the Persian Government to accept a British advance, while practically agreeing himself to grant an advance of 1,000,000Z. On the 6th January 1902 Lord Lansdowne addressed to Sir A. Hardinge a comprehensive Despatch, of which a copy was subsequently furnished to the Shah,* on the political and financial situation in Persia, and on the 8th February 1902 he instructed the British Ambassador at St. Peters burg, Sir C. Scott, to enquire of the Russian Government the grounds of their objection to the British advance to Persia. Reply of Russian Government as to non-acceptance by Persia of British advance. Sir C. Scott’s Telegram No. 17, 28th February 1902. (P. 106.) Telegram to Sir C. Scott, No. 23, 7th March 1902. (P. 126.) 10. At the request of Count Lamsdorff Sir C. Scott supplied him with a pro-memorid drawn up in accordance with Lord Lansdowne’s instructions, and the Russian reply was received on the 28th February 1902. The reply was tantamount to a refusal by the Russian Government to consent to the British advance, on the ground that the security assigned for the loan of 1900 had been represented by the Banque des Prets as insufficient. Further oral explanations, of no satisfactory character,were given to Sir C. Scott on the 5th March, and on the 10th March he forwarded to Count Lamsdorff, in a private letter, a memorandum making further inquiries in the matter. 11. Meanwhile the negotiations had been pro- ceeding for a fresh Itussian loan, and by the beginning of 1902 they had been greatly advanced by^the withdrawal of Russian demands (1) for a concession for a pipe-line across Persia from the Baku oil-wells to Bushire, and (2) for the repay ment by the Persian Government of the sum already borrowed from the Imperial Bank of Persia (see paragraph 6). Finally, on the 9th April 1902, an official announcement appeared in the Official Messenger at St. Petersburg of a new 5 per cent, loan of 10,000,000 roubles (roughly 1,000,0001.) “ sous garantie des memes recettes ii douanteres gut sei'vcnt de garantie a l emprunt “ de 1900 et aux memes conditions que pour cet “ emprunt.” It was not until the 30th November 191)2 that a copy of this Loan Contract was sent home by Sir A. Hardinge. Its provisions were almost identical with those of the Contract of 1900, but by the insertion of an additional clause the 1 ersian Government was prohibited, not only from “ issuing ” (emettre), but also from “ contracting ” (contracter), without the consent of Russia, any foreign loan “ d longue echeance.” The loan was redeemable in 75 years, and, since it could only be paid off “ a partir du ler Janvier 1912,” with six months 5 notice, the ” financial tutelage of the country was prolonged for two years longer, a contingency against which the Grand yi z i er had been specially warned in a note from Sir A. Hardinge dated the 28th March 1902. 12. This second Russian loan concluded, Sir A. Hardinge, on instructions from His Majesty’s Government, addressed to the Grand \ izier on the 10th May 1902 a reminder as to the customs of “ Southern Persia” from which the following is an extract:— “ I am, of course, aware that the customs of a large part of Southern Persia, viz., Pars and the ports on the Persian Gulf, are explicitly excluded from the securities assigned for the second, as well as for the first, Russian loan, and that there is happily no immediate prospect that this security will prove insufficient for the service of both loans. M the same time it must be remembered that Pars and the Gulf ports are only a portion of ‘ Southern Persia ’; that the amount of Persia’s total debt to Russia has just been increased by 1,000,000L ; and that the conditions of the first, and presumably of the second, loan provide, in case of default, for the control and supervision of the customs so pledged by the Russian Bank, with no saving clause as regards those parts of ‘ Southern Persia 5 not included in the term Pars and the ports of the * Persian Gulf.’ Sir C. Scott’s Despatch No. 76, 6th March 1902. (P. 130). Sir C. Scott's Despatch No. 81, 14th March 1902. (P. 216.) The Russian Loan of 1902 (£ 1 , 000 , 000 .). Sir A. Hardinge’s Telegram No. 17, 18th March 1902. (P. 154.) Sir C. Scott’s Despatch No. 124, 9th April 1902. (P. 21.) Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 164, 30th November 1902. (P. 321.) Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 60, 2nd April 1902. (P. 62.) Reminder to the Persian Govern ment as to the Customs of 4 Southern Persia.” Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 83, 11th May 1902. (P. 183).Sir A. Hai-dinge’s Telegram No. 60, 1st May 1903. (P. 104). First Anglo - Indian advance (£ 200 , 000 ) * See printed telegrams attached to Pol 174/03. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 3rd April 1903. (P. 16.) Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 4th April 1903. Pol. 2391/03. Pol. 2488/1903. Sir A. Hardinge’s Telegram No. 55, 9th April 1903. (P. 32). t The posts bring in a revenue after payment of all expenses of 6,000/. a year.” Vide Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 149, 16th August 1904 (P. 34). Presumably in 1910 they are bringing in little or nothing. Pol. 2409/03. “ It becomes, therefore, necessary that I should formally remind ills Majesty the Shah’s Govern ment that its promise that the customs of ‘ Southern Persia ’ (as distinct from those of Pars and the Gulf) shall not be placed under foreign supervision and control, cannot, in the view of His Majesty’s Government, be affected by an} 7- subsequent agree ments with either the ‘ Banque des Prets ’ or the Russian Government, and remains full 3 r binding notwithstanding any conditions which such agree ments may purport to contain.” To this Note the Persian Government made no reply. 13. At the beginning of 1903, after the con clusion in the preceding year of the South African War, important correspondence 0 passed with the Foreign Office and the Government of India dis cussing, in relation to strategical considerations, the method by which His Majesty’s Government should come to the financial assistance of the Persian Government and the quid pro quo to be asked for. 1 here was difficult}' in making a direct loan in view of the engagements of Persia with Russia as to future borrowing, and in the final result it was agreed to advance to the Persian Government, through the agency of the Imperial Bank of Persia, a sum not exceeding 300,0(M, On the 8th April 1903 an agreement (Appendix III.) was signed at Tehran for an advance through the Bank of 200,000L, at the rate of 5 per cent, interest per annum. The Persian Government engaged to repay the advance, capital and interest, in 20 years out of the proceeds of the royalties of the ^ Caspian fisheries (Ap pendix II.) ; if these were insufficient, out of the revenues of the posts! and telegraphs (para. 42), and, in the last resort, out of the revenues of the customs of Fars and of the Persian Gulf. Sir A. Hardinge at the same time reported that in the opinion of the Bank Manager the absence of any clause allowing anticipations was sufficient practical safeguard against repayment before the end of 20 years, and he added that later on the repayments might be transformed into a terminable annuity. The sum of 200,000L was paid to the Bank by the India Office on the 11th April 1903. Remuneration of the Imperial Bank of Persia. Letter of Foreign Office to Bank, 7 th April 1903. (P. 27). Pol. 2400/03. 14. The terms in which the Imperial Bank of Persia were to be remunerated for their share in the transaction are shown in the following extract of a letter addressed to the Bank by the Foreign Office on the 7th April 1903 :— “1 am to inform you that, in the event of a satisfactory arrangement being arrived at, the sum of 200,0001. will be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia by the Secretary of State for India for the purpose of being advanced to the Persian Govern ment, the Bank being the nominal lender, and charging the Persian Government interest at the rate of 5 per cent, per annum, of which 4 per emt.will Le remitted to the Secretary of State for India, the remaining 1 per cent, being retained by the Bank as a commission for its services in the matter. Any sums received in payment of the capital advance will be paid over at once to the Secretary of State for India without deduction.” 15. It was decided that the amount of the advance of 200,000?. should be entered in the Monthly Statements, to be sent to India, of “Receipts “ and Disbursements of the Home Treasury of “ the Government of India,” under the heading “Advances Repayable,” and, later, that the same heading should be adopted in the case of various published statements of the Indian Accounts. Manner of entry of the advance in Accounts of the Government of India. Pol. 2410/03. Pol. 3310/03. 16. The Government of India were far from being satisfied with the arrangements made with the Persian Government in the matter of the advance, and in a telegram dated the 7th May 1903 they observed as follows :— “ Through the whole correspondence we have pressed for the southern customs as first security. It now appears that customs rank only as third security and are confined to customs of Pars and the Persian Gulf, a phrase that we thought extremely ambiguous.” Attitude of the Government of India in the matter of the advance. Viceroy’s Telegram, 7th May 1903. (P. 134.) 17. As a result Sir A. Hardinge gave explana tions in a long Despatch as to the exact financial situation in Persia, discussing the meaning of the ambiguous expression “ customs of Southern Persia,” as used in the Mushir-ed-Dowleh’s note of the 23rd October 1897 {sec paragraph 4), as well as of the expression “Pars and the Persian Gulf.” Did “ Southern Persia ” mean “ Southern ” as distinct from “Northern,” or “Southern” as distinct from “ Central ” as well as “ Northern ” ? And was Mohammerah a “ Port of the Persian Gulf,” being 60 miles up the Shatt-el-Arab ? On these and other points much further correspondence passed, until on the 8th March 1904 a compre hensive memorandum was addressed to the Ain-ed- Dowleh embodying previous notes on the disputed points and calling attention to the fact that in a “ Reglement Douanier ” of the Persian Government no mention whatever was made of the customs of “ Pars and the Persian Gulf” or the customs of “Southern Persia.” “The latter”—so ran the memorandum—“are grouped into three districts, “called respectively ‘Arabistan,’ ‘The South,’ “ and ‘ Baluchistan,’ and before authorising me to “ accept the Customs Regulations in the manner “ provided by the Convention of 1903, His Majesty’s Government desire me to come to some clear “ understanding with the Persian Government as “ to the exclusion of all these three districts, which, “ whether covered or not at the time by the term ‘lars and the Gulf of Pars” 0 are undoubtedly “ covered by the term ‘ Southern Persia ’ used in Subsequent correspondence regard ing the t expressions “ Southern Customs ” “ Pars and the Persian Gulf,” &amp;c. Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 69* 14th May 1903. (P. 289.) Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 61* 30th March 1904. (P. 183.) Pol. 2590/04. * The Persian equivalent for the “ Persian Gulf.”‘‘ the Mushir-ed-Dowleh’s note of 1897, from the actual or potential operation of the Russian Loan “ Agreements.” Intention of the Persian Govern ment with regard to the customs of Pars and the Gulf of Pars. Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 114, 20th June 1904. (P. 40.) 18. It, was not until the 19th June 1904, that the Persian Government replied to the memo randum quoted. Their reply was, in its nature, a compromise, but it contained the important admission that, in excluding the customs of Pars and the Gulf of Fars from the guarantee for the Russian loans of 1900 and 1902, “ the intention of ‘‘ the Persian Government was, without *doubt, to preserve in freedom all its full rights of possession over all the ports of the south.” The reply was a compromise in that it referred to the impossi bility of interpreting the loan contracts “ without the participation of the Russian Rank,” and suggested that the question of Mohammerah might ultimately have to be referred to arbitration. British rejoinder to the Persian Note. Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 165, 3rd September 1904. (P. 103.) Pol. 3214/04. 19. His Majesty’s Government did not consider the terms of the Persian rt'ply to be satisfactory, and on their instructions Sir A. Hardinge presented a note to the Foreign Minister, dated the 30th August 1904, which contained the following words :— ” In order, however, to avoid any possibility of misunderstanding, I am instructed to inform the Persian Government that His Majesty’s Govern ment hold them to their engagement of October 1897. This engagement-is anterior to the Russian loan agreements, and cannot be affected by any of their provisions. I am, at the same time, to state that, as it was admittedly intended by the British and Persian Governments that the term ‘ Fars and the Persian Gulf ’ should include all the customs of Southern Persia referred to in the engagement of 1897, His Majesty’s Government cannot admit a solitary exception in the case of Mohammerah and its dependencies, or of any of the ports of Arabistan, and I am to add that His Majesty’s Government will take the necessary steps to insure respect for their rights in the event of any attempt on the part of the Persian Government to ignore them.” 'I’he omission of the last sentence was after wards asked for by the Mushir-ed-Dowleh, but the the request was not followed up. Sir A. Hardinge's Despatch No. 22, I n signing the Persian “ Reglement Douanier ” 30th August 1904. Sir A. Hardinge made a formal reservation, dated (P- 212.) the 29th August 1904, to guard against the ex- Pol. 3316/04. pression “ douanes du Sud” as therein used, being supposed to be synonymous with the' same expression as employed in the Persian under taking of the 23rd October 1897 (sec paragraph 4.) Second Anglo-Indian advance to the Persian Government (£100,000)- 20. On the 1st September 1904 an agreement (Appendix IV.), was signed for the advance to the Persian Government—through the Imperial Bank, as on the last occasion—of a further sum of 100,000b The securities for the advance remained10 as they were before, but the amount of the loan was combined with the sum of 190,000?. still remaining unpaid out of the previous advance,* and the total amount of 290,000?. was to be repaid in 20 years by equal annual instalments of principal and interest combined, amounting to 23,270?. 7s., the first instalment falling due on the 4th April 1905. It was also agreed that this scheme of repayment should only be capable of modification by consent of both parties. The amortization scheme for the loan is shown in the Table printed as Appendix V. The figure for the annuity (23,270?. 7s.), was taken from Violene’s Tables, and was checked by the Bank in London. The sum of 100,000?. was paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia by the India Office on the 7th September 1904. 21. The Imperial Bank of Persia had pre viously been addressed by the Foreign Office in a letter dated the 30th August 1904, in the following terms :— “I am to inform you that, in the event of a satisfactory arrangement being arrived at, the sum of 100,000?. will be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia by the Secretary of State for India, for the purpose of being advanced to the Persian Govern ment, the Bank being the nominal lender, charging the Persian Government interest at the rate of 5 per cent., of which 4 per cent, will be remitted to the Secretary of State for India, and retaining a commission of 1 per cent., as in the case of last year’s loan.” 22. In the spring of 1905 fresh efforts were made by the Persian Government to obtain money.t The idea was conceived of asking the Imperial Bank of Persia, which had already lent rather more than the terms of its concession allowed (Appendix L), for a sum of 150,000?, as a discount on, or redemption of, the annual royalty of 4,000?, which the Bank had to pay to the Shah. The plan fell through, on account of legal difficulties, and a sum of 80,000?., obtained from the Russian Government, repayable in four years at 12 per cent., was merely a temporary palliative. The assistance of His Majesty’s Government was invoked, and the Secretary of State in Council expressed his readi ness to provide from Indian revenues a further sum of 150,000?., “ subject to the understanding “ that His Majesty’s Government guarantee the “ Government of India against loss on the trans- “ action, both as regards principal and interest, to “ the extent of one-half of the amount involved.” A memorandum was accordingly communicated to the Persian Minister in London, dated the 13th July 1905, which called attention to an earlier British offer of an advance of 100,000?., abandoned through the refusal of the Persian Government to entrust the Karun irrigation project to agents * On 30tli March 1904 the India Office were paid 18,CHXM. by the Bank of Persia, of which 10,000Z. was treated aa repayment of capital, and 8,000/. as interest. Pol. 2442/04. Pol. 3066/04. Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 165,. 3rd September 1904. (P. 103.) Pol. 3066/04. Remuneration of Imperial Bank of Persia for second Advance. Letter of Foreign Office to Imperial Bank of Persia, 30th August 1904. (P. 202.) Pol. 3052/04. Offer by British Government of a fresh Advance (£150,000). t See Sir A. Hardinge's separate Despatch dated the 23rd December 1905, reviewing the existing condition of Persia on his relinquishing the post of Minister. Appendix (A.) sets out the debts and assets of the country. (P. 5.) Letter of India Office to Foreign Office,. 13th July 1905. (P. 28.) Pol. 1152/05. Memorandum to Persian Minister, 13th July 1905. (P. 29.)11 approved by His Majesty’s Government, and then continued in the following words :— “ His Majesty’s Government are anxious to do everything they can to assist the Persian Go vernment. They are therefore prepared to facilitate an advance of a sum not exceeding 150,000Z., to be made in the same manner and on the same terms as regards security and interest as in the case of the two previous loans. His Majesty’s Government do not desire to attach any new conditions to this advance, and will be satisfied with the recapitula tion of assurances to which they consider that the Persian Government are already pledged. “These assurances are (1) that the Persian Government agree in the interpretation attached by His Majesty’s Government to the expression ; customs of Pars and of the Persian Gulf,’ as notified in Sir A. Hardinge’s note to the Mushir-ed- Dowleh of the 30th August 1904; and (2) that railway construction in South Persia (including Seistan) shall, in so far as foreign assistance is required, only be carried out with the consent of His Majesty’s Government.” To Mr. Grant Duff, No. 143, 4th Octo ber 1905. (P. 4.) Pol. 3429/05. Mr Grant Duff’s Telegram No. 164, 1st December 1905. (P. 65.) Pol. 3653b/05. On the 4th October 1905 the Persian Minister told Lord Lansdowne that the Grand Vizier had written to him that he accepted these conditions, but he trusted that the amount of the loan would be made up to 300,0002. ; he added that formal instructions would be sent to him later on. An agreement, however, on these lines was not proceeded with, and later on the Grand Vizier increased his demands to 300,0002. Decision of British Government not to grant a loan. Telegram 1906. to Viceroy, 24th January (P. 66.) Pol. 2569/06. 23. At the beginning of 1906, when Mr. Morley had become Secretary of State for India and Sir E. Grey Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, telegraphic correspondence took place with the Government of India as to the propriety of granting a large loan to the Persian Government on political conditions, and Minutes on the subject were recorded by members of the Political Committee. In the result it was decided not to make a loan, the telegram sent to the Viceroy containing the following words :— “ It appears to His Majesty’s Government that in the present condition of Persia loan would be of no permanent benefit to her and would be granted solely for purpose of obtaining concessions of doubtful eventual value either in themselves or as means of resisting Russian influence in Southern Persia. It is true that application for loan will pretty certainly be made in another quarter. But we have strong reasons for feeling assured that, for an indefinite time at any rate, that application will be refused.” Co-operation with the Russian Government. Mr. Spring-Rice's Despatch (from St. Petersburgh) No. Ill, 7th February 1906. (P. 152.) Pol. 2743/06. 24. On the 5th February 1906 Mr. Spring- Rice addressed a private letter to Count Lamsdorff, informing him of the rejection by the British Government of the Persian request for a loan, and12 explaining that His Majesty’s Government would expect reciprocity on the part of the Russian Government if a similar application should be made to them. The letter concluded with the following words :— “ Si, toutefois, 'pour quelquc raison, le Gouvernc- ment Imperial Ic croit desirable de preter un appui financier a la Perse et quil vent bien considerer la question de concert avec le Gouvernement Bntan- nique, je suis charge d'assurer votre Excellence que Sir Edward Grey est tout pret a entrer en discussion d ce sujet dans un esprit de conciliation.” On the 7th February Count Lamsdorff informed Mr. Spring-Rice orally that the Emperor had expressed his satisfaction at this communication. He added that he was himself cpiite of opinion that an end should be put to the practice under which the Persian Government was able to obtain money from the English or the Russian Govern ment by playing off one against the other. 25. Correspondence passed about the same time between the Foreign Office and the Imperial Bank of Persia* regarding certain cheques of the Persian Government which the Bank had practi cally been obliged to honour, although by so doing it had raised the amount of the indebtedness to itself of the Persian Government to more than 100,000£. beyond the limits of the Bank’s concession. (Appendix I.). The question was asked whether the Bank should accept drafts on the Southern ( ustoms, payable in instalments, iu lieu of immediate repay ment of the Persian overdraft. The Foreign Office declined the responsibility of advising the Bank, but gave a general assurance of diplomatic support at Tehran. Indebtedness of Persian Government to Imperial Bank of Persia beyond the limits of Bank’s concession. * See Letter of Foreign Office to Bank, 3rd March 1906. (P. 167.) 26. In 1905 the Persian Government punctually paid their first instalment in respect of the British advances of 1903 and 1904, the amount received by the India Office on the 5th April being 18,660i. 15s. 2d. On the 14th April 1906 a sum of 5,5001. was received by the India Office, of which 2,176/. 10s. 9d. was treated as repayment of principal, and 3,323/. 9s. 3d. as interest. On the 22nd June 1906 a further sum was received of 15,106/. 4s. lOd. Of this &lt;,032/. 6s. Sd. was treated as principal, 7,925/. 14s. hd. as interest, and 148/. 3s. 9d. as interest on the overdue instal ment, thus completing the payment due on the 4th April 1906. {See Appendix IX.) 27. Meanwhile a new development had taken place through the illness of the Shah, and the necessity of advancing money to the A aliahd in conjunction with Russia, to secure a peaceable suc cession. To meet the situation the Secretary of State consented to advance from Indian revenues through the Imperial Bank a sum not exceeding 50,000/., on substantially the same conditions as governed the advances already made; the British Exchequer becoming responsible for the half of Payments by Persian Government on account of the 1903 04 advances. Pol. 2876/06. Pol. 2867/06. Pol. 3157/06. Proposed Anglo-Russian advance to the Valiahd. Letter from India Office to Foreign Office, 9th June 1906. (P. 139.) Pol. 3068/06 and 965c/06.Proposals for Joint Anglo-Eussian advance to Persian Government. Sir A. Nicolson’s Despatch No. 575, 1st September 1906. (P. 124.) Sir A. Nicolson’s Despatch No. 621, dated 14th September 1906. (P. 38.) * The following 1 telegrams passed with the Government of India on the question of Persian policy :— From Viceroy (2), 19th September 1906, To Viceroy, 24th September 1906. Pol. 15956/06. Sir A. Nicolson’s Despatch No. 628, 17th September 1906. (P. 38.) Approval of Contracts for Anglo- Russian advance (£400,000- £200,000 by each Government, of which half to be paid at once). The Customs Security. Sir C. Spring-Rice's Telegram No. 307, 25th October 1906, and No. 314, 27th October 1906. (Pp. 86* and 90.) Pol. 3644/06, 3658/06. Sir C. Spring-Rice’s Telegram No. 305, 24th October 1906. (P. 84.) any possible loss in respect both of interest and capital. The Shah’s health, however, improved, and action was, for the time being, postponed. ^8. On the 31st August 1900, an important conversation took place at St. Petersburg between Sir A. Nicolson and M. Isvolsky, regarding the intention of the Persian Government to apply to Germany for financial assistance in default of aid from Great Britain or Russia. In the course of this conversation M Isvolsky stated that he wished to act in harmony with the “ tacit agreement ” arrived at with Sir C. Spring-Rice (para. 24), and to consult with His Majesty’s Government as to the best means of affording relief to Persia. Communications followed between the Foreign Office and Tehran, and in the result an aide- memoire was sent to M. Isvolsky by Sir A. Nicolson on the 14th September 1906, proposing a joint Anglo-Russian advance of 400,COOL, or 200,000/. by each Power. The aide-memoire contained the following passage :—“ Le Gouveniement Britannique “ 'propose de prendre commc garanties pour sa part “ deVavance: (1) Une hypotheque, outre celle quit “ possede dejd, sur les douanes des ports dans le “ midi de la Perse et dans le Golfe Persique; et (2) de recevoir du Gouvernement Persan un en- “ gagement quaucune concession pour chemins de 1 fer, routes, on telegraphes, ne soit accordee a d'autres Puissances a Vest d une ligne tragee de “ Birjand d Bunder Abbas.”* M. Tsvolsky was averse to considering, in connection with the advance, the important question involved in the second of these conditions, but he informed Sir A. Nicolson on the 17th September 1900 that he saw no objection to the British Government taking as its security the customs in the south of Persia and in the Gulf. 29. After some further correspondence the text was approved of identic Loan Conventions to be executed by the British and Russian Banks with the Persian Government, stating that an advance of 400,000/. would be made to the Persian Govern- nmnt. of which 200,000/, would be paid at once, in equal shares, by the two Governments. Interest was to be at the rate of 7 per cent., and the Russian and British Governments could demand repayment a year after signature of the contracts, on giving three months’ notice. The Russian advance was “ guaranteed by the revenues of the customs already “ affected to the guarantee of the two loans con- “ eluded in 1900 and 1902,” and the English advance “ by the revenues of the administrations “ of posts and telegraphs, and, in case of insuf- “ ficiency, the revenues of the customs of Ears and “ the Persian Gulf.” As regards the expression “customs of Pars and the Persian Gulf,” the text of a note was approved by the Foreign Office to remind the11 Persian Government that “ His Majesty s Govern- “ ment hold to the interpretation already laid down “ in the note of the 30th August 1904 from this “ Legation ” (paragraph 19). The clause defining the British guarantee differed, it may be remarked, from that of previous loan contracts in its omission of the “ C aspian Fisheries” (Appendix II.). The omission was accepted by Sir C. Spring-Rice at the instance of his Russian colleague at Tehran, in view of the lact that no revenues were being derived from the fisheries. The course of the negotiations is described in Sir C. Spring-Rice’s Despatch No. 280, dated the 9th November 1906, but Sir A. Nicolson in a sub sequent Despatch, No. 773, of the 20th November 1906, corrected Sir C. Spring-Rice’s impression that M. Isvolsky had accepted merely in a personal capacity the guarantee asked for in His Majesty’s Ambassador’s aide-memoire of the 14th September 1906,of “ les douanes des ports dans le midi de la Perse et dans le Golfe Persique.' In telegraphing to Sir C. Spring-Rice Sir E. Grey expressed the opinion that M. Isvolsky s statement on the subject was sufficient for the purposes of His Majesty’s Government. (P. 166.) Pol. 3849/06. (P. 177.) * Sec para. 28. Telegram to SirC. Spring-Rice, No. 193 r 25th October 1906. (P. 87.) 30. On this occasion the Treasury consented to advance from British revenues their moiety (50,000i.) of the first instalment of 100,000k due from the British and Indian Governments. A sum of 50,000k was paid to the Imperial Bank by the India Office on the 4th October 1906. The constitution, how ever, in this year of the Persian National Assembly brought a new force into play, and owing to its opposition the money was not drawn by the Persian Government. Consent of the Treasury to advance half the money. Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office, 1st October 1906. (P. 46.) Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 4th October 1906. (P. 52.) Pol. 3538/06. 31. About this time there were renewed reports of the Shah’s ill-health, and the question again became pressing of making an immediate advance to the Valiahd of 50,000k (paragraph 27). The India Office agreed to hold the money in readiness, but concluded their letter to the Foreign Office with the following words :— “ Lord Morley would, however, suggest for Sir E. Grey’s serious consideration, that the precedent of the financial arrangements of the joint loan with Russia now being made to the Persian Government should be followed in case of this loan to the Valiahd, and that the Imperial Government should provide half the capital sum involved, instead of guaranteeing Indian revenues against loss in respect of a moiety of the advance.” The Treasury did not fall in with this proposal, but guaranteed the interest and capital of one moiety (25,000k) of the advance from Indian revenues. The sum of 50,000k was paid by this Office to the Bank of Persia on the 14th December 1906. Advance for the Valiahd from Indian revenues (£50,000). Letter of India Office to Foreign Office,. 2nd November 1906. (P. 134.) Pol. 3662/06. Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office, 6th November 1906. (P. 141.) Pol. 3699/06.15 Retransfer to Indian Revenues of sum of £100,000 advanced on account of (1) Anglo - Russian advance (£50,000), and (2) the . Valiahd (£50,000). Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 29th July 1907. (P. 94.) Pol. 3371/07. Pol. 3579/07. Pol. 3022/08. Delay in discharge by the Persian Government of its obligations in respect of the Anglo-Indian Advance of £290,000 Suspension of Sinking Fund for three years. Sir C. Spring-Rice's Telegram No. 62, 21st March 1907. (P. 220.) Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 13th April 1907. (P. 57.) Pol. 2877/07. Telegram to Sir C. Spring-Rice, No. 47, 16th April 1907. (P. 59.) Pol. 2927/07. Sir C. Spring-Rice’s Despatch No. 196, 13th September 1907. (P. 336.) Pol. 2745/08. 32. On the 29th July following, the India Office drew the attention of the Foreign Office to the fact that there was no immediate likelihood of the sums set apart from Indian revenues for the Persian Government and the Valiahd being required for their respective purposes :—“ Meanwhile the sum “ of 10O,000Z. advanced from Indian Revenues is “ not available for the temporary loans in the “ London market which the Secretary of State in. “ Council makes from the balances he holds in this “ country. The consequent loss is estimated at the “ rate of about 3,000i. per annum.” It was suggested that the Bank shoidd be asked to re transfer the amounts provided from Indian Revenues, and it was added that “there will be no difficulty in providing at a very few days’ “ notice any sums it may be decided to advance to the Persian Government in pursuance of the agreement with the Russian Government.” As a consequence the Treasury were repaid by the Imperial Bank of Persia the sum of 50,000Z. paid by them for an Anglo-Russian advance, and the sum of 1 00 , 0001 . referred to in the India Office letter was received by the Accountant-General at the India Office on the 7th September 1907. The question was afterwards raised by the Auditor whether any claim should be preferred against the Bank for interest on the sum mentioned during the months it remained in their hands. The Secretary of State in Council decided on the 28th April 1908 that a claim should not be made. 33. On the 21st March 1907 Sir C. Spring-Rice reported that the Persian Government would be unable to pay the annuity due the following month in respect of the Anglo-Indian advance of 290,000Z. With the concurrence of the India Office he was authorised to agree to a delay of six months in the payment of interest, on condition that a clause should be eliminated from the charter of the new National Bank granting it priority in the importation and sale of silver. Later, in reply to a formal request from the Persian Government, a note was addressed to them on the 31st August 1907 by Sir C. Spring- Rice, stating that His Majesty’s Government con sented to “a delay of three years, during which “ nothing should be paid on account of the sinking “ fund, but only interest, in order that the Persian “ Representatives might have time to carry on the “ necessary reforms and to put the income and “ expenditure of the country on a proper footing.” Three conditions were attached to this concession :— (1) that the Persian Government “ would not “ contract any new foreign loan without giving their “ creditors, England and Russia, the option of “ advancing money on the same conditions ;” (2) that they “ should not grant to anyone the “ monopoly of coining silver in the State Mint, and “ that, in the matter of the importation of silver,1G “ all persons, whether Persians or foreigners, will “ be treated equally, and without distinction and (3) that, if reforms were not carried out, “ His “ Majesty’s Goverument should have tlie right to '* demand payment of the arrears of sinking fund “ at any time within the next three years.” 34. The Anglo-Russian Convention was signed on the 31st August 1007. Article V. of the “ Arrangement concerning Persia ” related to the question of Persian indebtedness, and its wording was as follows :— “ In the event of irregularities occurring in the amortization or the payment of the interest of the Persian loans concluded with the ‘ Banque ‘ d’Escompte et des Piets de Perse ’ and with the Imperial Bank of Persia up to the date of the signature of the present Arrangement, and in the event of the necessity arising for Russia to establish control over the sources of revenue guaranteeing the regular service of the loans concluded with the first-named bank, and situated in the region men tioned in Article II. of the present Arrangement, or for Great Britain to establish control over the sources of revenue guaranteeing the regular service of the loans concluded with the second-named bank, and situated in the region mentioned in Article I. of the present Arrangement, the British and Russian Governments undertake to enter beforehand into a friendly exchange of ideas with a view to determine, in agreement with each other, the measures of control in question, and to avoid all interference which would not be in confor mity with the principles governing the present Arrangement.” 35. Prior to the signing of the Anglo-Russian Convention, it was reported by Sir C. Spring-Rice, on the 8th July 1907, that payment in full had been made of the Russian coupon, and that the Director at Tehran of the Imperial Bank of Persia had stated that this had been in part effected by making payments from the revenue of the Southern Customs. Sir C. Spring-Rice explained later, that the receipts of the northern Customs had fallen short by 4,000l. of the interest due the previous week on the Russian loan, and that the amount had been made good from the Bushire receipts. On the British loan nothing had been paid, nor was likely to be paid, while the Bushire receipts, say, 85,000L per annum, were being diverted to other objects. He added that the Imperial Bank of Persia were obtaining their own payments (or rather a portion of them) from the receipts of Kermanshah. On instructions from His Majesty’s Govern ment, Mr. Marling, who was now Charge d’Affaires, addressed a note to the Persian Government on the 15th October 1907, in which he enquired “ w'hat “ satisfactory reasons the Persian Government can “ adduce for diverting to other purposes revenues Anglo-Russian Convention of 31st August 1907. Diversion of Bushire Customs receipts from the service of the Anglo-Indian advance of £290,000. Sir C. Spring-Rice’s Telegram No. 171, 8th July 1907. (P. 67.) Pol. 3264 b/07. Sir C. Spring Rice’s Telegram No. 279, 27th September 1907. (P. 331.) Pol. 3711/07. Mr. Marling’s Despatch No. 236, 31st October 1907. (P. 153.) Pol. 4037/07.which have been formally pledged for the service “ of the British Loan.” The note also reminded the Persian Govern ment that no reply had yet been given as to the conditions that His Majesty’s Government had attached to their assent to the temporar} 7- suspension of the Sinking Fund {?ee paragraph 33). Question of informing Parliament as to the Anglo-Indian Loan of £290,000. Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office, 15th November 1907. (P. 139.) Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 7th December 1907. (P. 225.) Pol. 4011/07. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 11th February 1908. (P. 106.) Letter of Foreign Office to Treasury, 21st February 1908. (P. 223.) Pol. 2901/08. 3(5. About this time the Treasury raised the question whether Parliament should not be in formed of the liability of the British Exchequer in respect of the Anglo-Indian loan of the years 1903 and 1904 (290,000/.), and the Foreign Office, in addressing the India Office, expressed the opinion that, “ in view of the conclusion of the Anglo- Russian Agreement, there is no longer any reason, from the point of view of foreign policy, “ for keeping secret the details of the loan.” The India Office replied that the Secretary of State was “ not aware of any circumstances that would “ render it inadvisable now to bring to the notice “ of Parliament the action which His Majesty’s “ Government have taken in this matter,” and the Foreign Office informed the Treasury, on the 21st February 1908, that Sir E. Grey saw no objection to bringing the matter to the notice of Parliament. They asked for “ the views of the “ Lords Commissioners as to the manner in which “ the communication should be made,” and ex pressed the opinion that, “ in view of the absence “ of any papers which could conveniently be laid “ on the subject, any explanation given should ” take the form of a Statement, and that such “ Statement should set forth the reasons which “ have hitherto rendered inexpedient the publica tion of the details of this transaction.” Financial Adjustment between British and Indian Exchequers. Letter of India, Office to Foreign Office, 11th February 1908. (P. 106.) Letter of Foreign Office to Treasury, 21st February 1908. (P. 223). Pol. 2901/08. 37. In addressing the Foreign Office on the 11th February 1908 the India Office took occasion to invite them “ to agree to a simple procedure by which might be regulated ” the adjustment between the British and Indian Exchequers of any liabilities in respect of the Anglo-Indian loan of 1903 and 1904. A memorandum (Appendix VI.) suggesting the keeping of an “ Arrears Account ” by the Accountant-General at the India Office was enclosed in the letter, and a copy was forwarded to the Treasury by the Foreign Office in their letter of the 21st February 1908, with the remark that, under the terms of the memorandum no claim would be made against British funds “ in respect ‘‘ of temporary and comparatively trifling losses “ such as that occasioned by the delay of six “ months in the payment of interest which w'as ” granted to the Persian Government in April “ last.” {Sec paragraphs 54 and 58.) Renewed representations to the Persian Government, and payment by them of £13,000. Mr. Marling’s Despatch No. 28, 14th February 1908. (P. 233.) Pol. 3008/08. 38. In the meantime, towards the middle of February, Mr. Marling had addressed a note to the Mushir-ed-Dowleh reminding him that “ neither “ has the interest on the British loan of 1903-04, “ due on the 4th April 1907, been paid, nor has any S. 19. F18 “ reply been given to the conditions formulated in “ Sir C. Spring-Rice’s note of the Mist August “ 1907,* which His Majesty’s Government attached “ to their assent to the request of the Persian “ Government for the suspension for three years “ of the sinking fund on that loan . . . . “ Unless that interest is paid forthwith, and a “ formal acceptance of the conditions above al- “ luded to given to the Legation without delay, “ His Majesty’s Government will demand the im- “ mediate payment of the full amount of the “ annuity instead of the interest only.” On the 18th of the same month (February) Mr. Marling telegraphed that the Persian Govern ment had paid 13,000/. as interest on the Anglo- Indian loan, and on the 13th March the India Oilice informed the Foreign Office that “the following “ amounts have been placed to the account of the “ Secretary of State for India at the Rank of “ England, in respect of interest on the advance “ made to the Persian Government :— £ s. d. “ 10,880 16 7 i.e., four-fifths of 13,601/. 0*'. 9d., “ being interest due 4th April “ 1907,on outstanding principal. “ 476 19 4 t.e., four-fifths of 596/. 4s. 2d., “ being interest at 5 per cent, on “ 13,601/. 0s. 9d., for the period “ 4th April 1907 to 18th February “ 1908. “Total 11,357 15 11” The date of receipt of the money by the Accountant-General was the 29th February 1908. 39. The Legation’s note of the 31st August 1907 (paragraph 33), as to the suspension of the sinking fund, was still, however, unanswered, and no payment had been made by the Persian Govern ment of the amount overdue for sinking fund since the 4th April 1907. In a note dated the 24th February 1908, Mr. Marling reminded the Persian Government of these facts, and added the following words :—“ His Britannic Majesty’s Government “ consider that, by failing to effect any payment, “ and notwithstanding the repeated verbal repre- “ sentations which I have had the honour to make “ on the subject, and by neglecting to give any reply “ to Sir Spring Rice's above-mentioned note, the “ Persian Government have tacitly accepted the “ conditions set forth therein.” Finally, on the 25th July 1908, after the occurrence in the 23rd June of the coup d'etat by which the Shah reverted to despotic Government, Mr. Marling addressed a note to the Minister for Foreign Affairs to the effect that “ His Majesty’s “ Government can no longer admit of an}* dis- “ cussion of the terms laid down in Sir 0. “ Spring-Rice’s note ” (paragraph 33). * See paragraph 33. Mi*. Marling's Telegram No. 47, 18th February 1908. (P. 208.) Pol. 2826/08. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 13th March 1908. (P. 272.) Pol. 2826/08. Intimation to Persian Government as to their tacit acceptance of con ditions in British Note as to sinking fund. Mr. Marling's Despatch No. 35, 26th February 1908. (P. 279.) Pol. 3008/08. Mr. Marling's Despatch, No. 200, 10th August 1908. (P. 239.) Pol. 3914/08.19 Reminder of India Office to Foreign Office as to explanation in Parliament. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 5th September 1908. (P. 317.) Pol. 3740/08. Letter of Foreign Office to Treasury, 12th September 1908. (P. 329.) Pol. 3833/08. Subsidy to German School guaran teed from Customs revenue. Despatch to Mr. Mailing No. 14, 17th February 1908. (P. 206.) Mr. Marling’s Despatch No. 53, 15th March 1908. (P. 24.) Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 12, 26th January 1909. (P. 155.) Pol. 2851/09. Question as to collection of the Gulf customs and impounding the Tele graph revenues. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 2nd February 1909. (P. 127.) Pol. 2938/09. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 17th February 1909. (P. 172.) Pol. 2938/09. 40. On the 5th September 1908 the India Office enquired of the Foreign Office whether any decision had yet been arrived at upon the proposal made by the Foreign Office to the Treasury as to an expla natory statement to Parliament regarding the Anglo-Indian loan (paragraph 36). Copy of the letter was forwarded by the Foreign Office to the Treasury on the l^Jth idem. 41. A few months previously a telegram had appeared in the Berlintr Tageblatt that the Shah had promised to pay an annual subsidy of 2,500L to the German School at Tehran, to be guaranteed b} 7- a lien on the Customs revenue. It was ascertained by Mr. Marling that payment of the subsidy was, in fact, to be made from the Customs funds, and correspondence passed with the Russian Govern ment as to a protest to the Persian Government. In the result, His Majesty’s Government decided to act alone, and a note was addressed on the 11th January 1909 to the Persian Government by Sir G. Barclay, who had now become Minister at Tehran, reminding them that the interest on the British loan of 1903 and 1904 was in arrear since the preceding April, and adding that “ if the resources “ of the Persian Government are pledged without “ the consent of His Majesty’s Government so as “ to imperil the security of the British loans and “ advances .... or to diminish the several “ revenues assigned to the service of their interest “ or sinking fund, His Majesty’s Government will be compelled to consider what steps are necessary “ for safe-guarding their interests.” 42. On the 2nd February 1909 the Foreign Office addressed the India Office on the question of the service of the Anglo-Indian loan:—“ Sir E. “ Grey is disposed to think that the collection of “ the Gulf customs by or on behalf of His Majesty’s “ Government, which a demand for repayment “ would probably entail, would be inopportune at “ the present moment, and might be regarded as “ interference in the affairs of Persia, which it “ would be advisable to avoid as long as possible. “He would be glad to know whether it would “ be feasible to impound, by the agency of the “ Indo-European Telegraph Department, the pro- “ ceeds of the telegraph revenues, on which the “ advances are partially secured, should his Lord- “ ship agree that the collection of the customs “ should not be resorted to for the present.” In reply the Secretary of State for India ex pressed concurrence in the view that the collection of the customs would be inopportune, and stated that he was “ of opinion that it would be better not “ to press the demand for payment in a definite “ form till the question of the constitutional and “ financial regime to be established in Persia has “ further developed.” A note was transmitted of the Director-in-Chief of the Indo-European Tele graph Department, explaining that some 3,500L20 Transfer of lien of the Imperial Bank of Persia on the Kermanshali Customs Receipts to those of Bushire. Sir A. Nicolson's Telegi'am No. /2,16th April 1908. (P. 67.) Pol. 3090/08. only could in any case be realised by impounding the telegraph revenues, and deprecating such action as likely to disturb existing relations between his own and the Persian Telegraph Departments. 43. Mention may here be made of a complaint by the Russian Government in the spring of 1908 that the Imperial Bank of Persia had sequestered the customs revenues of Kermanshah (in the Russian sphere) as a guarantee for sums due to the Bank from the Persian Government; it was pointed out that those revenues were part of the security for Russian loans. The Foreign Office ascertained that the action of the Bank had been based on a verbal arrange ment with the Persian Customs Administration, and, the Russian representations being held to be well- founded, a plan was proposed for transferring the lien acquired by the Bank from the customs receipts of Kermanshah to those of Bushire. A note with this object was addressed to the Persian Government on the 4th November 1908, and, in the end, the Persian Government undertook to pay from the receipts of the Bushire customs, as interest on the Bank’s debts, the sum of 30,000 tomans a month (72,000Z. a year) with effect from the 21st March 1909 (the beginning of the Persian financial year) The Bank’s debts, it may be remarked, amounted in all at this time to 52G,000L (leaving out of account the Anglo-Indian loan), or about 310,000Z. in excess of the amount authorised by their concession. Nearly half the debt wns on account of their advance of 200,000Z. in 1901 (see paragraph 6), secured on the customs of Fars and . the Persian Gulf. 44. Subsequently, on the falling off of the Bushire customs receipts, the receipts of the Mohamerah customs were also assigned, with the concurrence of the India Office, to the service of the Bank’s own loans. Sir G. Barclay had explained that the receipts at Ahwaz, Lingah, and Bunder Abbas should amply suffice for the service of the Anglo-Indian loan. 45. In giving their assent to the arrangement described in the preceding paragraph, the Treasury raised the question whether the Persian Govern ment should not be pressed for a further payment in respect of the Anglo-Indian loan. The Foreign Office considered that such action would be useless in the financial condition of Persia, but that the question must be considered when Persian finances “ are set in order, or if a further loan to the “ Persian Government is eventually guaranteed or made.” 4G. The extent of the Persian Government’s Extent of indebtedness of Persian indebtedness at this time had been disclosed in the Gownment; as disclosed in M. Bizot s report of M. Bizot, their Irench I inancial Adviser, dated the 15th March 1909, of which the main Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch, No. 293, 5th November 1908. (P. 138.) Pol. 4195/08. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 326, 30th December 1908. (P 81.) Pol. 2819/09. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 5, 18th January 1909. (P. 149.) Pol. 2851/09. Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 32, 23rd February 1909. (P. 215.) Pol. 3149/09. Additional lien of Bank on Mo hamerah Customs. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 15th September 1909. (P. 379.) Pol. 3946/09. Question of pressing the Persian Government for payment in respect of Anglo-Indian loan. Letter of Foreign Office to Treasury 16th September 1909. (P. 381.) Pol. 4056/09.Aprn 1909 BarClay ’ S Despatch No ' n ' 8th feat »res were explained by Sir G. Barclay in the “ You will notice that, in M. Bizot’s opinion, the need for a loan is indisputable, though he is unable to pronounce as to the amount required. In •my telegram No. 152 I gave it as 2,500,000/. at the lowest estimate, independently of the small advances which would be needed for the reorganization of the Departments which most urgently call for reform, and I should mention that in this estimate I had M. Bizot’s concurrence. Besides the Govern ment s debt to the two banks, amounting in round ligures to some 1,200,000/., which, bearing exorbitant interest, cries loudly for conversion, there are other creditors’ claims which, according to a statement given to M. Bizot, already at the end of 1907-08 amounted to 2,751,638 tomans (550,000/.). These must greatly have increased during the year just ended. There are also the claims for postal and road robberies, &amp;c., filed by the foreign Legations, of which it would be rash to attempt an estimate, but which must represent a very considerable sum. “Assuming that the sum indicated above is approximately sufficient to convert the advances of the two banks, and to settle the claims of other creditors and those presented to the Persian Government by the foreign Legations, Persia’s total indebtedness may be estimated at something British and Indian Government’s loan, with arrears of interest - 300,000 “ To pay interest on this at 5 or 6 per cent, the customs receipts would amply suffice, leaving a very substantial sum at the disposal of the Persian Government, very nearly as large a sum, indeed, as that now left over after paying the interest on the loans and advances as at present secured on the proceeds of the customs. The conversion of the 1,200,000/. owed to the Imperial Bank of Persia and to the Russian Bank, so as to reduce the interest from 12 to 6 per cent., would effect a saving of 72,000/. a year, or nearly enough to pay 6 per cent, on the sum needed to clear off the rest of the floating debt.” like 6,000,000/., i.e.: Russian Government’s loans £ 3,200,000 Required to pay off floating debt, &amp;c. - - - - 2,500,000 £ 6 , 000,000 The Customs Revenue of Persia. 47. In the preceding paragraph mention has been made of the sufficiency of the customs revenue of Persia to meet the indebtedness of the country. In April 1909 Sir G. Barclay sent home the follow- Sir G. Barclay's Despatch No. 90, 30th April 1909. (P. 262.) Pol. 3583/09.24 extract from a telegram addressed to the Viceroy on the 11th May 1909 : — “ His Majesty’s Government are pledged, subject to fulfilment by Shah of conditions imposed, and to safeguards on proper expenditure of funds, to contribute moiety of joint advance by two Govern ments to enable Shah to meet urgent claims, discharge of which is necessary to secure his position on establishment of new regime. Total amount of joint advance is not to exceed 400,000?. in all in accordance with agreement with Russian Government described in my telegram of ord October 190o, which has been treated as holding good in principle throughout subsequent phases of negotiations with Russia. Conditions which made that agreement necessary apply with equal force now, and I recognise that India must in the cir cumstances accept financial responsibility for 100.000?., being a moiety of British share of joint advance. ♦ *•!** *:•’ '•£ “ But as regards any further financial assistance to Persia, India is free from any engagement, and I have made it clear to Foreign Ofiice that, apart from objections on grounds of general Imperial policy to financial and other entanglements in Persia, I cannot admit that Indian interests in Persia are of a nature to justify expenditure from Indian revenues on schemes for establishing reformed government in Persia. Such schemes involve not only financial risk but danger of inter national complications, from responsibility for which it is essential that India should be kept entirely free.” On the 16th July 1909 a new era was entered on in Persian politics by the flight of the Shah to the Russian Legation, and his immediate deposition. Telegram to Viceroy, 11th May 1909. Pol. 412/09. Pol. 3537/06. 51. On the 2nd December 1909 Sir G. Barclay telegraphed that the programme of the Persian Cabinet, including a proposal to apply for an advance of 500,000?., had been submitted to the Medjliss, and he urged that the British and Russian Governments should not be deterred from nego tiating a joint loan by the impossibility of further borrowing on the customs as disclosed in M. Mornard’s statement regarding the “ fixed charges ” (paragraph 49). The Foreign Office concurred in his view as to the desirability of an advance, and, in their letter to the India Office of 7th December 1909 observed that “Sir E. Grey “ attaches great importance to the conversion of the “ debt owed by the Persian Government to the “ Imperial Bank of Persia, and to the Russian “ Discount Bank, which he considers should be a “ necessarv condition of any loan.” Proposal of the Persian Government to apply for an advance. Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 800, 2nd December 1909. (P. 139.) Pol. 4305/09. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 7th December 1909. (P. 145.) Pol. 4305/09. Reluctance of the India Office to 52. In replying on the llth December 1909 the # J B- Secretary of State for India expressed “ his strong join in an advance. “ doubt whether any further financial assistance Po1, 43 '23 # Converted, for this Memo., at the rate of 5 Tomans = 1/. t The calculation is as follows :— £ Charges to be borne by Customs 620,000 Saving by Conversion of Debt - 100,000 Total - £520,000 or 20,000/. less than net customs receipts, as above, viz., 540,000/. 80,000/. of the highest level reached by the customs net revenue, viz., 602,208/. in 1907-08. There were however certain later charges, e.g., the ex-Shah’s pension, which, in Sir G. Barclay’s opinion, would also have to be borne by the customs, bringing up the total of such charges to 620,000/., or 80,000/. more than the previous year’s net receipts, viz. 540,000/. Sir G. Barela}* commented on the position in the following terms :— “ It is quite evident that on the basis of M. Mornard s statement no further borrowing is possible on the security of the customs, and although only the first four items are fixed charges by virtue of engagements undertaken by the Persian Government, the remaining eleven items being merely chargeable to the customs in accor dance with usage, it ^vould be difficult to relieve the customs of any of these latter. The Russian Government would doubtless object to any other security for the payment of the Cossack brigade, and it is important that the salaries of the European Government officers should be well secured. The rest of the eleven items mostly appertain to the customs administration. “ It is thus evident that a condition precedent for any further borrowing must be the conversion of the advances, &amp;e., of the two banks, and even this would, as I calculate it, only leave sufficient margin for a very trifling loan unless it were found possible to relieve the customs revenue of some of those heads of expenditure with which it has hitherto been charged in accordance with usage. The advances of the Imperial Bank of Persia and the Russian Bank carry for the most part interest at the rate of 12 per cent, and over. The debt to the two banks amounts, as I understand it, to be tween 8,500,000 tomans (1,700,000/.)* and 9,000 000 tomans (1,800,000/.), of which I would hazard an estimate that 7,000,000 tomans (1,400,000/.) carry inteiest at the late of 12 or lo per cent. The con- version of this debt and the reduction of the interest to 5 per cent, would effect a saving of probablv o00,000 tomans (100,000/.), in which case, supposing that the customs receipts do not fall below last year’s level and for the first six months of this year they show an increase—there would be a margint for borrowing of 100,000 tomans (20,000/.).” Negotiations as to financial assist ance for the Persian Government. Attitude of the India Office. Persia Print, 26th February 1910, sec. 4. Pol. 3268/10. 50. Meanwhile the question of giving financial assistance to the Persian Government was con tinuously under discussion between the British and Russian Governments. Should both Governments, or one of them, supply the assistance needed, or should both the British and the Russian Banks, or one of them, come to the rescue ? The various stages of the negotiations are set out in a Foreign Office Memo., dated the 26th February 1910, and it is unnecessary here to do more than mention the salient facts. So far as India is concerned, the position in May 1909 is shown in the followinging figures 0 supplied by the Administrator-General of Customs (M. Mornard):— Table showing approximate Total Receipts of Customs for 1908-09 as compared with the previous Year. * Converted, for this Memo., at the rate of 5 Tomans = 1/. — 1907-08. 1908-09. Azerbaijan - £ 106,687 £ 70,000 Caspian Sea ports :— 32,400 Astara - 32,253 Ghilan - 118,000 118,000 Mazanderan - 28,251 34,400 Astrabad - 28,888 22,400 Khorassan - 53,876 60,000 Southern ports :— Bushire | 189,000 ( 100,000 Bunder Abbas - ( 32,400 Arabistan - - 37,800 20,000 Kermanshah - 110,806 110,400 Parcels post (Tehran) - 3,559 4,000 Total - 709,120 604,000 In sending home these figures Sir G. Barclay commented on the greater extent to which British imports had fallen off as compared with Russian. The same result was shown in a table forwarded in the following October comparing the gross receipts of the customs for the first six months of 1909 with those for the same period of 1908. 48. As regards the receipts of the southern ports alone, Sir G. Barclay forwarded in September 1909 the following tablef : — Comparative Statement of the Gross Customs Receipts for Southern Ports of Persia. — 1907-08. 1908 09. 1909-103: (First Six Months). £ £ £ Bushire 134,517 101,880 32,000 Lingah 10,046 9,137 4,400 Bunder Abbas 44,539 32,535 11,000 Mohammerah - Dizful 35,769 ) 19,182 10,680 Ahwaz Shuster * 2,038 1,896 920 Totals - 226,909 164,630 59,000 £ Figures approximate only. 49. In October 1909 SirG. Barclay was supplied by M. Mornard with a statement (Appendix VII.) showing what the latter described as the “ fixed charges” in the customs revenue for the previous year. These amounted to 527.900L, or within Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No. 190 9th October 1909. (P. 56.) Pol. 4242-3/09. The Customs Receipts for the Southern Ports. Sir G. Bai'clay’s Despatch No. 179, 24th September 1909. (P. 18.) Pol. 4133/09. t Figures converted, for this Memo., at the rate of 50 Krans = 1/. Fixed Revenue. charges in the Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch 27th October 1909. (P. 101.) Pol. 4305/09. Customs No. 200,“ ought to be given to Persia out of Indian revenues, or at the risk of imposing a charge “ upon them.” “ It will not be easy, for instance,” continued ‘ in the continuance of constitutional rule in Persia, ‘ and it will be very easy and not unreasonable for ‘ Indian politicians to ask why they should pay for the security in Persia of a constitutional system strictly denied to themselves. It is true, again, ‘ that India is part of the Empire, and should take its share in the burdens of Empire. The moment, ‘ however, is not a happy one for resort to this line of argument, as Indians are now sharply resenting a denial to them of equality of citizenship within the Empire by colonial communities not them selves contributing to its defence. It may be true, indeed, that order in Persia might help Indian commerce. But Lord Morley is not con vinced that improvement in the sphere of Indian trade by means of this kind is assured enough to ‘ justify the imposition of new burdens upon the ‘ general body of Indians. Nor is he convinced ‘ that even the conversion of the Persian debt ‘ would strike either the judgment or the imagi- ‘ nation of the Indian taxpayer as a specifically ‘ Indian interest. “ While, therefore, he is reluctantly obliged to ‘ assume responsibiJity for the loan of 100,(X)0Z. to which he agreed in May last, Lord Morley is not prepared to recommend his Council to sanction ‘ any further advance.” joint advance of 400,(X)0£. They related, briefly, to (1) control of the expenditure of the money, (^) appointment of seven French officials in the Ministry of Finance, (3) formation of gendarmerie or road guards, (4) railways, (5) navigation of Lake Urumiah, and the last condition (6) was worded as follows:— Persan, si les gouvernements de Grande-Bretayne et de Russie consentiraient a cet emprunt. Dans le cas contraire, cette avarice, au taux de 7 pour cent., sera amort ie en dix versements egaux, gar antis par les revenus des douanes et, en cas d'insufjisance de ces demiers, les revenus de la monnaie serviront de garantie supplementaire.” should be paid once more to the Imperial Bank of the letter, “ to show what direct interest India has Persia Print, 14th March, Sec. 1. “ Cette avance constituera le premier versement de Vemprunt sollicite dejd par le gouvernement Sir G. Barclay’s Telegram No. 817, 24th December 1909. (P. 189.) a month. The profits of the Mint, it may be observed, had been stated by Sir G. Barclay to amount to 5,000/. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 19th February 1910. Pol. 2994/10. In their letter of the 19th February 1910 the Foreign Office requested that the sum of 100,000/.I'O Persia from Indian revenues, addin# that the Treasury had been requested to take similar steps with regard to the British moiety of the advance. The India Office consented, and the sum of I00,(K)0L was paid to the Bank by the Accountant-General on the 25th February 1909. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 24th February 1910. Pol. 2994a/10. 54. Iu paragraph 37 mention lias been made of a letter addressed by the India Office to the Foreign Office on the 11th February 1908, suggesting a form of procedure for regulating the adjustment between the British and Indian Exchequers in respect of the Anglo-Indian loan of 1903 and 1904 (290,000k). On the 16th June 1909 a reminder was sent by the India Office on the subject, and subsequently demi-official correspondence^ passed between the Financial Secretary, India Office, and the Permanent Secretary of the Treasury, in the course of which it was calculated that on the 4th April 1909 the liability of the Treasury to Indian revenues was 147,163k 4s. 9d. In assenting to the payment to the Imperial Bank of Persia of the sum of 100,000/., referred to in the last paragraph, the India Office drew the attention of the Foreign Office to the fact that their official letters of the 11th February 1908 and the 16th June 1909 had remained unanswered, and requested an early reply “ with a view of termi- “ nating the present anomalous position in which “the Indian Government are pressed to make a “ further advance, while the Lords Commissioners “ of the Treasury make no effort to discharge their “ liabilities.” A copy of this letter was forwarded by the Foreign Office to the Treasury on the 4 th March 1910. On the 9th April 1910 the India Office addressed to the Foreign Office another strongly worded reminder on the subject. Renewed representations as to financial adjustment between British and Indian Exchequers. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 16th June 1909. (P. 353.) Pol. 3520/09. * To Treasury, 4th November 1909. Ditto, 22nd January 1910. Ditto, 19th February 1910. Pol. 2994/10. India Office to Foreign Office, 24th February 1910. Pol. 2994a/10. Letter of Foreign Office to Treasury 4th March 1910. Pol. 2994/10. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 9th April 1910. Pol. 2994b/10. 55. By April it had become apparent that there ,vas little likelihood of the Persian Government iccepting the Anglo-Russian advance conditionally )ffered (paragraph 53). Accordingly the India Dffice suggested to the Foreign Office, in a letter lated the 15th April 1910, that the Indian payment 100,000/. should be refunded by the Imperial Bank of Persia, adding that “ there would be no ‘ difficulty in providing the sum again at very few ‘ days’ notice.” The money was repaid on the 19th April. 56. Two months later, the question of the advance again became pressing, and two letters dated the 18th and the 22nd June 1910, were received from the Foreign Office proposing that, in the event of a request from the Persian Govern ment, the Anglo-Russian advance of 400,000/. should be made on the understanding that foreign Delay in acceptance of advance bv Persian Government. Refund by Bank of Indian payment (£100,000). Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 15th April 1910. Pol. 2994c/10. Pol. 3244/10. Renewed Proqpect of Anglo-Russian Advance (£400,000). Letters of Foreign Office to India Office, 18th and 22nd June 1910. Pol. 3570 and 3590/10.27 India Office to Foreign Office, 29th June 1910. Pol 3590/10. Amalgamation of the debts of the Imperial Bank of Persia. Inclusion in the scheme of the Anglo-Indian Loan of 1903 and 1904. * Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 22nd March 1910. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 2tfth March 1910. Pol. 3139/10. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 26th March 19)0. Pol. 3145/10. Pol. 3453/10. Despatch from Mr. Marling, No. 92, 8th June 1910. Pol. 3556/10. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 11th April 1910. Pol. 3196-97/10. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 2nd May 1910. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 5th May 1910. Pol. 3283-85/10. experts should be engaged as advisers to the Persian Ministry of Finance, and subject to no further conditions, except as regards security and provision for repayment, if a larger loan were subsequently floated ; the security for the entire advance to be the whole of the Persian customs, and the rate of interest to be 5 per cent, instead of 7. The India Office, while assenting to these proposals, suggested that it should be made clear that the prior lien on the southern customs of the Imperial Bank of Persia, and of His Majesty’s Government, would in noway be affected, and drew attention to the importance of separate accounts being kept in respect of the proposed new advance. A proposal was agreed to that, subject to the prior lien referred to, the “ quasi-fixed charges ” (as they now had been called) on the whole of the customs of Persia should be made permanent. It was added that the Indian share of the advance would be forthcoming when it was known that the Treasury were making a similar payment. 57. In the first half of 1910 an arrangement was carried through, to the importance of which allusion has more than once been made (para graphs 40, 49, and 51), viz., the amalgamation of the debts of the Imperial Bank of Persia. The corre spondence between the Foreign and India Offices* was based on telegrams sent home by His Majesty’s Charge d’Afraires at Tehran and the local manager of the Imperial Bank, and the text of the agree ment arrived at, together with that of three supplementary letters addressed by the Bank to the Minister of Finance (Appendix VIII.), was received in a despatch from Mr. Marling, dated the 8th June 1910. The general character of the arrangements is, briefly, as follows :— Exclusive payment is to be made to the Bank, in the first instance, of the full net eusfoms receipts of the Persian Gulf ports, including Bushire, Bunder Abbas, Lingah, Mohnnerah, and Ahwaz, and from these receipts monthly payments will be made for the service of the Bank’s own debt, and also that of the Anglo-Indian debt, the interest on the former being 7 per cent, in currency, on the latter 5 per cent, in sterling, as before. Xo pay ments on account of the redemption of capital will be made for three years in respect of the Anglo- Indian debt (314,281L 165. 4d. on the 21st March 1910), but thereafter yearly payments will be made, in respect of both interest and capital, of 30,278Z. 125. Id., extinguishing the debt in 15 years, the final payment being due on the 20th March 1928. It was decided by His Majesty’s Government, in the course of the negotiations, not to surrender their lien on the Caspian fisheries (Appendix II.) and on the Posts (paragraph 13) and Telegraphs (paragraph 42).“ Northern Custom *.—The charges are :— * This item varies with the fluctuations of exchange, and the average is rather larger than this figure, viz., 9,820,000 krans. 1. Coupon of the Russian loans - 2. Interest on ex-Shah’s debts - d. Annuity for extinction thereof in ten years 4. Annuity for interest and sink ing fund of Persian Govern ment’s debts to Russian Bank according to agree ment under negotiation (about) - - - Krans. 9,500,000° 1 , 000,000 1,500,000 5,000,000 Total - - 17,000,000 t The returns show that this average as against net average receipts of 21,000,000 krans,t is likely to be exceeded in the current year. leaves a balance of 4,000,000 krans. “ These balances are, however, absorbed by the quasi fixed charges, of which Sir G. Barclay gave an account in his Despatch No. 200 of the 27th October last.” (See paragraphs 49, 51, and 56.) It is of interest to note that, converted at the rate taken by Mr. Marling of 53 krans = H., the amount of the net average receipts of the Persian Customs, for the past five years, works out as follows:— £ Southern Customs - - 150,168 • Northern Customs - - - 396,227 Total - - 546,395 Political Department, 17th October 1910. J. E. F.28 It was also brought forward that the text of the agreement would sufficiently provide against the Persian Government being able to pay off the Government loan except by instalments. Mr. Marling’s Telegram, No. 195, 28th April 1910. Pol. 3283-85/10. 58. In view of the agreement described in the preceding paragraph, it was arranged with the Foreign Office that it was unnecessary at present for any payment to be made from the British Exchequer to Indian revenues in respect of loss through the non-payment of interest on the Anglo- Indian advance of the years 1903 and 1904. The Treasury undertook, if further default should take place, to ask Parliament to make good the British share of that loss, and, pending such default, they considered that it would be well to defer making any announcement to Parliament on the subject. The India Office agreed that there was no reason for such announcement, “ unless attention is called to the matter.” 0 The Auditor, it may be remarked, had made in his Report on the India Home Accounts, dated the 2nd May 1910, the following observations :— “ Interest realised from investment of Cash Balance, &amp;c., 47,236Z. 18s. Id. “ The sum of 10,494L Is. 2d., due to the Revenues of India in April 1908 for Interest on Advances made on account of the Persian Govern ment has not been received, and must be surcharged.” A list is annexed (Appendix IX.) of payments to, and receipts from, the Imperial Bank of Persia in respect of loans or intended loans to the Persian Government. * Arrangement with the Treasury as to British liabilities, and statement to Parliament. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 4th June 1910, enclosing Treasury Letter, 30th May 1910. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 22nd June 1910. Pol. 3498/10. Pol. 3498/10. * The following demi-official spondence also passed :— Secretary, Treasury, to Secretary, India Office, 17th reply, 18th May 1910. Secretary, Treasury, to Secretary, India Office, 20th reply, 24th May 1910. corre- Financial May 1910; Financial May 1910 ; 59. Up to the time of writing (17th October 1910), there does not appear to be any immediate prospect of the proposed AngloRussian advance of 400,000Z. being made to the Persian Government. In a Despatch dated the 15th June 1910 it has been explained by Mr. Marling that the Customs revenues could not be regarded as providing adequate security for an advance of that amount. The following is an extract from the Despatch:— “ Southern Customs .—The charges on these are :— “ 1. The annuity due under the Imperial Bank of Persia arrangement of the 26th May 1910, 3,729,390 krans ; and “2. The annuity due on the sterling loan of 1903-04 of 30,278?. 12s. Id. at 53 krans — 1,604,767 krans, or together 5,334,157 krans, while the average net receipts for the past five years are 7,958,890 krans, 0 leaving a balance of 2,624,733 krans. Prospects of the proposed Anglo Russian Advance (£400,000). Security of the Customs revenue. Mr. Marling’s Despatch No. 102, 15th June 1910. Pol. 3556/10. * The Customs returns so far point to the probability that the receipts for the current year will be considerably below this average.APPENDIX I. (Referred to in 'paragraphs 6, 22, and 25.) Extract from Memorandum as to the Imperial Bank of Persia, enclosed in Sir A. Hardinge’s Despatch No. 38, 29th March 1903. See page 58 of Foreign Office Vol. This Bank was founded in 1889 in virtue of a Persian concession and a British Charter. Its capital paid up was l,000,000i., subsequently reduced by the writing-off of losses, principally in exchange and silver, to 650,000L By the terms of the Charter there is a liability in case of insolvency equal to the paid-up capital. The capital may be increased to 3,000,000/. Bank notes may be issued in Persia to the extent of the paid-up capital guaranteed by a metallic reserve of 33 per cent. The present amount of the note issue varies from 250,000Z. to 300,000L, four-fifths of which is in Tehran alone. Advances to the Government may not exceed, according to the Charter, one-third of the paid-up capital. The majority of the Board is to be of British nationality. Operations of the Bank. The Bank: — (а) issues notes; (б) takes deposits and discounts bills ; (c) buys and sells foreign exchange and imports silver for coinage ; (d) makes advances to the Government ; (e) makes advances to private individuals. Note. —Copy of the Charter and Deed of Settlement of the Bank is printed as an enclosure of the Secretary of State’s Secret Despatch No. 33, 30th October 1903, to the Government of India. APPENDIX II. (Referred to in paragraphs 13, 29, 55, and 57.) Note on the Caspian Fisheries. In his Despatch, No. 23, dated the 22nd February 1903 (P. 352) it was reported by Sir A. Hardinge that the Persian Government had decided to raise money by selling for a lump sum the royalties, or rental on the lease, of the Caspian Fisheries. The fisheries had been leased for many years to a Russian merchant of Astrakhan, named Leonozoff, and the latest of the contracts executed was for an extension for five years, from 1920 to 1925, at an increased rental of 20,000Z. a year. M. Naus estimated that the sale of the royalties for the 22 years should bring in 350,000Z. In a later Despatch, however, No. 149, dated the 10th August 1904 (P. 33), Sir A. Hardinge wrote as follows :—“ The Caspian Fisheries, which “ have hitherto yielded 20,000Z. a year, have ceased to be a real guarantee, “ nor would any banker now lend money on their security, since, under the “ new commercial regime as between Persia and Russia, the Russian “ Government can impose, and has intimated its intention of imposing, upon “ Persian fish the duties authorised by the Russian general tariff instead of “ the old 5 per cent, ad valorem duty. . . . For this year, moreover, “ and for the two following years, the fisheries have already been discounted “ to their concessionaire by the Atabeg-i-Azam.” In a Despatch, No. 299, dated the 22nd November 1908 (P. 207), Sir G. Barclay reported that the Persian Government had pledged the Caspian Fisheries Royalties to an Armenian Banking Firm for a further period of three years—1912, 1913, and 1914. Throughout the correspondence it has been recognised that these fisheries afforded merely a nominal security for the Anglo-Indian loan toAPPENDIX VI. (Referred to in paragraph 37.) Memorandum enclosed in India Office Letter to Foreign Office of 11th February 1908. (See page 106 of Foreign Office Volume). The debt due from the Persian Government having been practically converted into an annuity for 20 years, payable on the 4th April in each year from 1905 to 1924 inclusive (viz.: 21,133L 7s. M. in 1905 and 23,2701. 7s. in subsequent years), the Accountant-General at the India Office will prepare and keep up an “Arrears Account ” showing the amount due from the Persian Government in consequence of any failure on its part to pay the instalments of the annuity in full at the right dates. He will debit to this account the amount by which the payment, if any, made by the Persian Government on the 4th April of each year falls short of 23,270L 7s., will add once a year interest at the rate of five per cent, per annum on the amount at debit, and will credit to the account any sums received in respect of arrears. He will append to the account a statement showing what portion of the arrears represents money that should have been paid to Indian revenues (with interest thereon) and what portion represents money that should be paid to the Imperial Bank (the amount so payable being one-fifth of all payments that should have been made in respect of the interest portion of the annuity, together with interest at five per cent, thereon added yearly). Once in three years he will send to the Foreign Office the account and appended statement, and the Foreign Office will pay to the India Office one- half of the amount by which the debt due to Indian revenues has been increased during the preceding three years. If the debt has been reduced, he will pay to the Foreign Office one-half of the amount of the reduction. India Office, 24th December 1907. APPENDIX VII. (Referred to in paragraph 49.) Statement by Administrator of Persian Customs as to “ Fixed Charges” on the Customs Revenue. (Enclosed in Sir G. Barclay’s Despatch No 200, 27th October 1909, page 101 of Foreign Office Vol.) Defenses Presumees. Budget des Depenses gouvernementales assignees sur la Caisse des Douanes (Depenses fixes). Sommes approximatives. Krans. 1. Amortissement des emprunts de 1900-02 (Banque d’Escompte) - - - - 9,500,000 2. Amortissement de Pemprunt du Chil (Banque Imperiale) - - - - - 1,250,000 3. Interets annuels des avances de la Banque d’Escompte - - - - 5,000,000 4. Interets annuels des avances de la Banque Imperiale - 4,000,000 5. Budget des Cosaques No. 1 - - - 3,000,000 6. Budget des Cosaques No. 2 - - - 420,000 7. Appointements et pensions des fonctionnaires europeens - - - 1 , 200,000 Carried forward35 Brought forward 8 . Service sanitaire (quarantaines, &amp;c.) - - 200 000 9. Constructions et reparations des batiinents gouver- nementaux - - _ - 120 000 10. Entretien et approvisionnement des huit bateaux a vapeur - . . 900,000 11 . Appointements des fusiliers gardes-cotes (Golfe Persique) - - - - 160,000 lz. Kedevances annuelles dues an Gouverneur de T1 Bouchir - - - - . 200,000 13. Kedevance pour le port et les batiments douaniers de Mechedi Ser - 120 000 14. Redevance pour leport et les batiments douaniers d’Astara - ... 125,000 15. Frais de transfert des fonds des bureaux du sud (2 a 3 pour cent.) - - - . 200,000 Total - - . 26,395,000 Ce budget est etabli d’apres les obligations souscrites par le Gouverne- ment, en ce qui concerne les articles l”, 2, 3, et 4, et suivant 1’usage en ce qui concerne les articles 5 a 15. APPENDIX VIII. {Referred to in paragraph 55.) Agreement between the Persian Government and the Imperial Bank of Persia. (Enclosed in Mr. Marling’s Despatch No. 92, 8 th June 1910 — Pol. 3556/1910.) In conformity with the negotiations which have taken place between the Persian Government and the Imperial Bank of Persia, it is herebv agreed that:— 1. 1 he consolidation of the several amounts due to the Imperial Bank of Persia, according to the statement rendered to and accepted by the Persian Government, is hereby effected, and the interest payable thereon from the 21st March 1910, is fixed at the rate of 7 per cent, per annum. 2 . Payment of interest on the loan and redemption of the capital will be effected by the Persian Government paying the yearly instalments amounting to 3,729,390‘95 krans, as set forth in Clause No. 3 , in proportional monthly amounts of 310,782*60 krans covering a period of fifteen years from the 21st March 1910. 3. As seciirit} r for the debt and as guarantee for the payment of the yearly instalment of 3,729,390 *95 krans agreed upon, the full net customs receipts of the Persian Gulf ports, including Bushire, Bunder Abbas, Lingah, Mohammerah, and Ahwaz, are hereby made payable to the Imperial Bank of Persia, and the Persian Government bind themselves by the terms of this agreement to pay exclusively to the Imperial Bank of Persia all such customs receipts with no deduction save that of the actual expenses of administration of the customs of the above-named ports for a period of 15 years or until such time as the debts shall be totally extinguished. 4. The Imperial Customs will pay to the Imperial Bank of Persia, week by week, the above-mentioned Customs receipts of the whole of the Persian Gulf ports, including Mohammerah and Ahwaz, and the Imperial Bank of Persia will render to the Persian Government monthly, on the 21st of each* ! • 36 month, accounts of all such receipts, and the surplus remaining-after due provision has been made from such funds to meet the amount required tor amortisation of capital and payment of interest month by month—shall lie at the disposal of the Persian Government. 5. In the event of the receipts of the above-mentioned ports for any one month falling below the amount required for the service of the debt the Persian Government binds itself to make good any such deticiency from ot aer sources of Government revenue, so as to fully meet the obligation to the bank undertaken by the Southern Customs for the month in question. 6. The Persian Government binds itself to discontinue all drafts on the Southern Customs other than for actual administrative expenses immediately connected with the collection of their receipts until the monthly amount due to the bank shall have been paid. 7. The Persian Government has the option of repaying the whole of the debt at the end of anv one year, viz., the 20th March, and it is agreed that notice will be given in writing two months before the end of any such year in which it is the intention of the Persian Government to take advantage of this option. 8. The Imperial Bank of Persia will allow the Persian Government interest at the rate of 7 per cent, per annum on all funds paid in for the redemption of the loan from the day on which they are paid in to the date on which they are applied for that purpose. 9. And it is further agreed that, as regards the sterling loan of 290,000Z. of 1903 -04, the payment of the interest and redemption of capital amounting on the 21st March 1910, with arrears, to 314,28U. 16s. 4d. shall be paid off in fifteen equal annual instalments of 30,278h 12s. 7d., and in case the other revenues affected to the service of the loan by the convention of the 1st September 1904, should prove insufficient, the Imperial Bank of 1 ersia agrees, and is hereby authorised, to apply any surplus remaining over from the receipts of the above-mentioned Persian Gulf ports after payment of the said monthly instalments (of 310,782-60 krans) to the payment of the annual instalment of 30,278Z. 12s. Id., the payment being made in equal monthly instalments, as provided in Article 4 of the present agreement It is clearly understood that in all other respects the provisions of the Loan Convention of 1904 remain in lull force. Dated this 26th day of May 1910. Vosouk-ed-Dowleu. S. Rogers. Supplementary Letters. (I.) Imperial Bank of Persia to the Minister of Finance, Tehran. Your Excellency, 2nd dune 1910. With reference to the payment to be made by the Customs to the Gulf ports including Mohammerah and Ahwaz, under the terms of the agreement of the 26th ultimo between the Persian Government and the Imperial Bank of Persia, the cost of remitting these payments to Tehran is to be arranged with the Customs administration, and the l ersian Govern ment will receive credit in Tehran value the date on which payment is made to the bank or its agents at the respective ports. We are, &amp;c., For the Imperial Bank of Persia, D. Brown (for Deputy Manager).37 si (II.) Imperial Bank of Persia to the Minister of Finance, Tehran. Your Excellency, 2nd June 1910. In clause 9 of the agreement of the 26th ultimo between the Persian Government and the Imperial Bank of Persia, provision is made for the repayment of the sterling loan of 1903-0-1, amounting with arrears to 314,281 L 16s. 4d. on the 21st March 1910, redemption of capital and payment of interest taking the form of 15 equal yearly instalments of 30,278Z. 12s. 7d., payable by the terms of the said clause. We now beg to confirm the arrangement which has been come to, by which interest only will be payable on this loan for a period of three years, from the 21st March 1910 to ; 20th March 1913, the amortisation in 15 annual instalments of 30,278Z. 12s. Id. covering principal and interest, beginning from the 21st March 1913. Payment of each annual instalment will be made in 12 equal monthly instalments, as provided in the above-mentioned agreement. In virtue of the foregoing modification to the agreement of the 26th ultimo, the sterling loan is to be completely paid off by the 20th March 1928 instead of the 20th March 1925. We are, &amp;c., For the Imperial Bank of Persia, 1). Brown (for Deputy Manager). (III.) Imperial Bank of Persia to the Minister of Finance, Tehran. Your Excellency, 4th June 1910. With reference to the agreement entered into on the 26th May between the Persian Government and the Bank for the consolidation of the several amounts due to the Bank, and, as laid down in clause 2 of the agreement for the repayment of capital and interest by 15 yearly instal ments of 3,729,390'95 krans each, we would inform Your Excellency that, when the capital sum has been reduced to within the limits provided for in the Bank’s concession, there would be no objection to allowing that amount to stand over. We are, &amp;c., For the Imperial Bank of Persia, D. Brown (for Deputy Manager). S. 19. K(Referred to in List of Payments to and Receipts from the Imperial Bank of Persia Anfrlo-Indian Loan of 1903. ! H.M.’s Treasury advanced nothing. (Paragraph 13.) H.M.’e Treasury advanced nothing. This and preceding payment and receipt of March 1904 were con solidated into a Loan of 290,0001. The Indian moiety of first instalment (100,0001.) of H.M.’s Government’s share (200,0001.) of the proposed Anglo-Russian Loan of 400,000/. H.M.’s Treasury also paid Bank 50,000/. H.M.’s Treasury paid Bank nothing, but guaranteed Indian revenues against loss in respect of one moiety (25,000/.). The Indian moiety of H.M.’s Govern ment’s share of the proposed Anglo- Russian Loan of 4&lt;X),000Z. The Foreign Office requested H.M.’s Treasury to make similar payment to Bank.I N 1 Paragraphs. Anglo-Russian Convention - 34 “ Arrears Account ” - 37, App. VI. Auditor, action of - 32, 58 Bank. See “ Imperial Bank of Persia,’* “ Russian Bank.” Bizot, M., Report of 46 Bushire Customs, amount of - - - 6, 47, 48 diversion of - 35 lien of Imperial Bank on 43 Caspian Fisheries, account of - - App. II. omission of, as security for a proposed Anglo-Russian Advance 29 security of, for Loans of 1903 and *1904 - 13, 20, 57 Customs, amount of receipts from - 46, 47, 49, 59 charges against 49. 51, 56, 59 diversion of - - 35, 41 security of, for proposed Anglo- Russian Advance, 1910 56 subsidy to German School from 41 Northern :— amount of - - 35, 59 charges on 59 lien of Russia on 2, 11 Southern :— amount of receipts from 47, 48, 59 charges on - 59 definition of. See “ Southern Persia.” diversion of 35 lien of British Government on - 8, 13, 16, 18, 20, 28, 29, 56 lien of Imperial Bank on - 6, 56 “ Fars,” use of term - 17, 19, 22 “ Financial Tutelage ” - 7,11 “ Fixed Charges ” on Customs - 49, 51, 59 German School, subsidy to 41 Paragraphs. Imperial Hank of Persia— cont. conversion of Persian debts of, 46, 49, 51, 57, App. VIII. indebtedness of Persian Govern ment to 6, 22, 25, 43,46, 49, App. VIII. lien of, on Bushire Customs - 43 lien of, on Kermanshab Customs 35, 43 lien of, on Mohammerah Customs 44 lien of, on Southern Customs 6, 56, App. VIII. Loan of 1901 of - - 6, 11 payments to, and receipts from App. IX. remunei-ation of - - 14, 21, 27 India Office, views as to Persian Loans of - - - 23, 50, 52 Indo-European Telegraph Depart- 42 ment Kermanshah Customs 2, 4, 35, 43 Germany, possibility of loan from - 28 Government of India, attitude of - 16 Imperial Bank of Persia, account of - * - Apj). I. Agreement of, with Persian Government, 26th May 1910 App. I III. concession of - 6, 22, 25, 43, App. I. S. 19. Loans:— Anglo-Indian, projected in 1901 8 Anglo-Indian of 1903 - - 13 Ditto, Agreement for - - App. III. Ditto, entry in Accounts of - - 15 Anglo-Indian of 1904 - 20 Ditto, Agreement for - App. IV. Anglo-Indian, Consolidated, of 1903 and 1904, Amortisation Table of - App. V. future arrangements as to - - App. VIII. repayment of - - 13,57 Anglo-Indian, projected in 1905 22 Anglo-Bussian, proposals for, in 1906 - - - 28,29 in February 1910 - - 53 in June 1910 - - 56 in October 1910 - - 59 Anglo-Russian, proposed, for Yaliahd - - - 27,31 Imperial Bank of Persia’s, 1901. 6 {See aUo “ Imperial Bank.”) Russian, in 1900 - - 2,3 Russian, in 1902 - - 11 {See also Anglo-Russian ” above.) Parliament, communication to - 36, 40, 58 Payments by Peraian Govern ment - - 20, 26, 38, App. IX. Persian Government, delay of, in discharge of obliga tions - - 33, 38, 39, 45 /42 Paragraphs. Persian Government— cont. payments by - 20, 26, 38, App. IX. protest to, as to pledging revenue ... 35,41 ! estimate of total indebtedness of - - - 46 Posts, security of - - - 13,29,5/ Railways in Persia “ Reglement Douanier Russia, Loan in 1900 of - Loan in 1902 of 22, 28 17, 19 Paragraphs. Russia— amt. cooperation with Great Britain of - - 7,24,28,29,53,56,59 opposition to Great Britain of - 3, 10 Russian Bank - - 2, 3, 46, 51, 59 Sinking Fund, suspension of - 33, 35, 38, 39, 41, 57, App. VITJ. “ Southern Persia,’’ meaning of term - - - 12,17,19,22,29 Telegraphs, security of - 13, 29, 42, 57 Treasury, adjustment with 8, 30, 31, 37, 54,58 Yaliahd, advance to - - 27,31 'mmm*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00010c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C120a</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00010c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C120a</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum as to Persian Government Loans'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1910/1910</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-03T21:21:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (21 folios)</extent><extent>The memorandum is divided into two parts: the main body (folios 33-47) and an appendix (folios 48-53). An index has also been included at the back on folio 54.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at f 33, and terminates at f 53, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the item also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum outlines a number of loans and advances made to the Persian Government by Britain and Russia respectively at the turn of the twentieth century; this includes information on the securities pledged by Persia to meet repayments. It also covers British concerns over the definition of the Southern/Gulf Ports of Persia (pledged as security for British loans), and British fears that the customs of these ports might fall under the control of another foreign power, or be used as security for non-British loans. Also outlined in the memorandum are a number of proposed loans that never reached fruition, and a proposed conversion loan in 1910 from the Imperial Bank of Persia in order to consolidate the Persian Government's debt.Information on some of the diplomatic discourse which has taken place from 1900 to 1912 between the Foreign Office, the India Office, and Russian representatives regarding the payment of loans to Persia is also included.The appendix on folios 48-53 contains supporting transcripts, which include:an extract from a memorandum by Sir Arthur Henry Hardinge, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Persia, dated 29 March 1903; it provides background details on the Imperial Bank of Persia (f 48);a note on the Caspian Fisheries (f 48);the text of an agreement for the advance of £200,000 by the Imperial Bank of Persia to the Persian Government (ff 48v-49)a table showing the amortization scheme for the Anglo-Indian Loan of 1903-04; extracted from a report on Persia by Sir Cecil Arthur Spring-Rice (f 49);a statement (in French) by the Administrator of the Persian Customs as to 'fixed charges' on the customs revenue, dated 1909 (ff 49v-50);the text of an agreement between the Imperial Bank of Persia and the Persian Government, dated 8 June 1910, with supplementary letters from the Bank to the Persian Finance Minister, dated 2-4 June 1910; it regards the repayment of debts owed to the bank (ff 50-51);a list of payments and receipts from the Imperial Bank of Persia (1903-1910) respecting loans or proposed loans to the Persian Government (ff 51v-52).Some extracts quoted in the main body of the memorandum are in French, as are a number of the appendices. An index can be found on folio 54.This memorandum is continued in a subsequent memorandum dated 27 November 1912 (see IOR/L/PS/18/C120b).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Persia, Qajar dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Bank of Iran</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Loans</topic></subject><subject><topic>Finance</topic></subject><subject><topic>Public debt</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00010c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>