<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000289_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:05:59.444Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mmFree translation of an appeal issued in Arabic by’Hizbul Ahrar ill Hijazi 1 on 20/21 Rajab, 1351 H. to Great Britain through the Governor of Aden protesting against the reconnoitre by British aeroplanes of the centre of Jehad . Your ;sxcelleneyi Hejaz which having relied on the promises of Great Britain had joined it in the Great War is now being given a very poor return. This is neither in keeping with the loyalty of Arabs nor with the traditional fulfilment of the pledges given by the British Government. It is a fait accompli that melims in general and the Arabs and your allies in particular are disgusted with the present Wahabi Government. It is this bad Government which has made the British Government look vile in the eyes of Muslims, flow that the Society of Ahrar- i-Hejaz and the Chiefs of Idreesia have risen to regain their lost rights and protect them it was the moral duty of British Government to help the Ahrars or at least to refrain from helping the vVahabis who are the enemies of humanity, of Islam and of the West. As our Jehad is free from any foreign influence, the Society strongly protests against the disapproves of the presence of British aeroplanes over the head-quarters of the tujahidin. This interference on the part of British Government might stir and enrage the *hole Muslim world which believes the present Jehad to be a purely religious movement as explained in our statement dated 5th of Rajab, 1351 H. We, in the name of Muslim world and the sanctity of holy places, appeal, therefore, to Your Excellency to keep aloof from these domestic affairs, else the Muslim world will be forced to arrive at the conclusion that the British Government was interfering in religious matters. We hope that Your Excellency will be pleased to remind your Government that we were her allies and trusted friends during the Great War. Kindly accept compliments and best wishes from your sincere friends, the members of ^aiat ul gaurat ul Hijazi* . Sd. Illegible. i Jut.Secret Free translation of the Statement in Arabic issued by *Haiat ul Shoorat i Idreesia ul Jijazi*. Our blessed Society is in keeping with Islamic laws and stands for all that is noble and honourable* It is entirely free from treachery and incapable of murdering women and children and perpetrating atrocities like that. But the \7ahabis are in the habit of committing cruel deeds and shamelessly violating both Islamic and International laws* On being continually defeated, the Wahabis stooped to perpetrate extremely shameless deeds, such as the bombardment, general massacre regardless of age and sex and bo on, as mentioned in our statement dated 26 th of Ha jab, 1351 H. They did not stop there, but having conspired with Johd.Yahya Basahi, the slave of the Idreesia tribe who had turned traitor, they captured Seebia, the Capital of Aseer and ordered a general massacre. Old men, women, children and even pregnant women xxx were butchered. But by the grace of Cod, in the fight which took place between the Wahabis and Mujahidin on Rajab 27 and 28, the former -were completely crushed and their stores fell into the hands of the latter. God, the Avenger thus punished them. Peace and order were restored in the affected area. We issue this statement as a protest against the atrocities perpetrated by Wahabis to acquaint the Muslim world with true facts. Dated Shaban 1351 H. Sd.Ali ul Hasan, Propaganda Secretary.Secret Free translation of an appeal in Arabic issued by *Haiat ul Shoorat i Xdreesia ul Shoorat i Idressia ud Hijazia’. ;4ielini brethrenj Save your Kaba and the tomb of your Prophet from the despotic hands of Kha^erij Wahabis. The cruel and barbarous treatment meted out to the Chiefs of Idaresa and the Ahrar mujahidin of Hejaz has forced them to rise against the Wahabis who have murdered men t women and children regardless of age, demolished their houses, cut off the trees and destroyed the crops. It is on account of these atrocities that the .Mujahidin are now determined to sacrifice their all for the attainment of their ri^ats. It is their firm belief that their sufferings in this connexion will please God and will be rewarded by Him. They are bearing these hardships gladly and patiently with a view to bring peace to the cradle of Islam. But what has annoyed and agitated the Mujahidin of Aaeer and Hejaz is the interference on the part of Sbreign Powers. To help the Wahabis is tantamount to bring disgrace to Islam, and to ruin Arabs. British aeroplanes flew over the centre of Jehad, helped the Y/ahabis and did iiaaense harm to Mujahidin. At protest against this has already been submitted to British Government through the Governor of Aden and a copy thereof is herewith enclosed. British Government and other Foreign Powers have absolutely no right to interfere in the domestic affairs of this country. This we have made clear in our statement dated 20/21 Rajab, 1351 H, The British Government did rx&gt;t stop there, but allowed the Wahabi troops the use of their aeroplanes. The Heja z Government has recently borrowed from the British Government £ 100000 with a view to crush the Mujahidin. The money arrived from London at I Riyaz escorted by Mr. Philby and Hafiz Wahba. The British Government has, in return, got full control of the purse of Hejaz(2) Hejaz Government and appointed Philby as their agent. Philby who poses to be a j-luslim ia a liar. In fact, he i s the chief of wahabis and a British spy. Muslim brethren! These are the facts which have been placed before you for your consideration. We want to know as to how long Muslims are going to tolerate this irreligious and shameless treatment. There i s no limit to your agitation when a Hindu passes your mosque with music; but here the very foundation of your religion is being shaken at the holy places and you are sitting quiet. The heart of the Prophet is shedding tears of blood and you are still asleep. ik&gt;w that the facts have been brought home to you, will you still remain silent? You will have to answer before God and His Prophet if you do not start agitation in tide connexion. How long will you comdnue to live this life of disgrace? How long will you tolerate this insult to Prophet* s tomb, to Keba and to Isla^ It is your duty to busy yourself in uprooting foreign influence and Wahabi rule from the holy Hejaz. It is the duty of Muslim world to liberate the holy places frcia the present shameless Government. We, the Ahrar of Hejaz and the Chiefs of Idaresa have, therefore, after full consideration, declared Jehad in the name of Islam and Arabia wi th a view to save the holy places from disgrace. The Ahrar i Hejaz are prepared to sacrifice their all for the cause. By the grace of God their efforts have, on several occasions, been crowned with success and they are leaving no stone unturned to achieve their goal, as has been repeatedly mentioned in the statements issued by the •Haiat*. We do hope that the Muslim world v/ili be delighted to learn that battles &amp;re being fought at several places between Hejaz and Bejd with a view to drive away these dirty folks from Kara main (Mecca and ?fedina) for ever and ever. And the time is not far distant when we shall gain aa complete victory. Our one appeal to the Juslim world is to ask them to help the Mujahidin oy all possible means in order to enable them to drive away the Wahabis fromHejaz. Muslims! To-day is the day of trial. Gome and save your holy Kaba and the sacred tomb of your Irophet from the clutche of tyrants. JJhow your agitation and evince your enthusiasm. Use the strength of your j?aith and think of the evils and troubles due to the despotic rule of Kharji W&amp;habig inHeja*. Time has come when life should not be considered worth living and property should be given in the path of God. hated A seer, the 15th of dhaban, 1551 H. Sd.Jbhammad Husain, Propaganda SecretaryTelegram dated tne 7tL. February 19 33 From. • • • • Saiyed Mohai^niad Sbabbar, Madraga^ Basiraya, Jaunpur„ To Kis E^celleacy the Viceroy, Ca^p. The Musalmans of Jaunpur assembled in a mass meeting held on February in Madrasa Nasiriya under the presiaentship of Maulaua Saiyed Mohanmed Shabbar Sauib Muj tahid and passed tiie followi-ng resolutions that Kis Majesty's Government be requested througn Kis Uccelleiicy the Viceroy that policy of nonintervention in internal affairs of Hfcdjaz be continued as hitherto and as was declared by Kis Majesty’s Prime Minister Mr. Ran,say MacDonald in x924 and it is further prayed that no help be given in the snupe of arms ammunition men or money to the King of Kedjaz in his present internal war which is going on between him and Mujahideens of Asir that any such help given to the Ming of Hfcdjaz. wound the feelings of Mu salmans of India who are tradit lonally loyal to tne British Government, that copy of the above resolution be sent to Kis Excellency the Viceroy.'T 7 © OF^ICS Cb Trxji KHIVATS SDCHjTTARY Ti^ VICEROY. ITo. ^53 G.P. Vernacular Petition, Transferred to the Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India. 3d. G. 3. Beckett. Regietrar, Office of the Private Secy; to the Viceroy. Delhi, The 10th February 1^33.(Transiation). Copy of Resolution ITo.^, passed at a meeting of tne Anjui-ictii 'TaJnaf fuz-i-Ma , asar Mu talar r ikan M , held at Mohalla ^aziara under the presidentship of Saiyid Muhammad Tahir, E.A., , Advocate, Sita^ur, U.P. on 8th Shav/vval i35i corresponding v/ith tne 4tn February 1933. 'Tnis meeting unanimously and strongly appeals tne Prime Minister oi England and His Excellency txxe Viceroy of India that, in accordance v.ith the policy declared ly Mr. ItacDonald on 1st October i l sh4 in tne House of Commons with regard to affairs in Hejaz and Hejd, the British Government should firmly remain neutral in a purely Islamic and religious issue and anould not give Iln Saud any help in equipping him with navy or military forces or supplying him war materials or affording him assistance in some other way, since such an action on the part of British / Government would severely injure the feelings of tne Indian Mussulmans and a grave sense of feexing ^ about British Government shall give rise to susp i ci on am ong tlx em w . * As agreed, a copy of Resolution Ho.h, passed in the local meeting, is hereby forwarded to His Excellency the Viceroy of India. Certified that it is 'true copy' of the original. Sd. Muhamrnad Tah ir , Dated the Hon # Secretary of tne Anjunan 5th February i9o3. “Tahaffuz—i-Ma , asar Hutabarrihan', Sitapur.. Ho.?. 40-11/33. The Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Maulana Saiyid Mohd. Shahbar Sahib Mujtanid, Madrasah Ka a i ray a , Jaunpur. Hew Delhi, the l- ^ March 1933. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your telegram dated the 7th February 1933, communieating the Resolution passed by the Mussalmans of Jaunpur at a meeting held under your presidentship. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, R* ;V. _iill. Assistant Secretary to the Government of India,From To ^•F.40-^/23. Tlie Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the tforeigti and Political Department, Saiyed Muhammad Tahir, B.A,, L L#B* , Honorary Secretary of the Anjtuaan w Tahaffuz-i-Ma’agar hutaharrilcah', Sitapur, flew Delhi , the^ ^ March 1933. Sir, I am directed to acsknowledge the receipt of a copy of Resolution Do. 2 passed at a meeting of the Anjuman '•Tahaffuz -4- Ma’asar Mutaharrikahheld at Sitapur on the 4th Pehruary 1933 under your president ship. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. R. A. Hill. Assistant Secretary to the Government of IndiaSociety known as Anjuman Immamiah* Sind, Hyderabad, has passed the following resolutions there we also do the same being the subordinates of the above society concerned for the Shias of Sind® to kindly use his good offices with the British Government for taking necessary steps in order to urge upon f Ibin Saud, King of Hijaz, for re-constructing the sacred shrines and monuments of Janatul-Bakia- which have been demolished by him. X X X 2. This meeting requests His Excellency the Viceroy X X XQ0 From ^ 20 The Honorary General Secretary}-) 4 29 All India Shia Gonfere t l &lt; @&gt;30 j ^ m r~ ■ t ^ AUG 1930 To Ar'J i 4 , , Lu ckn o\v ^ His most Excellent Majesty King Raza shah tahlawi of Persia. Dated the 24th May 1930. May it please Your Majesty, I beg to send herewith a copy of a representation which was submitted by me to His Excellency Lord Ir?/in, our most popular Viceroy of India who has got special regards for Mohammedans in general and Shias in particular. I am sure Your Majesty has got as much love for our Holy places as e have, perhaps more. Islam is indebted to Your Majesty for all you have done for Mohammedans in general and your country in particular and Your Majesty’s name will go down to History as the greatest King who rescued Islam from downward degeneration and ruin. Me shall be grateful if Your Majesty will add one more credit to your many achievements by asking your foreign office to cooperate with the British Foreign Office in securing from the Hejaz Government of Kin&lt;^ Ibne- Saud the permission of rebuilding our Holy monuments referred to in the accompanying memorial and in removing jother grievances. We look upon Your Majesty with great —, § 1 ' ^ uj p?; 7^ jlove and veneration and I am sure Your Majesty will not uj id ' ■ 1 --id ^ Disappoint us. Co ^ O CD I l d ^ ^ 1 '^ e sincerely pray Providence may keep your z ~ JO 3 r | Majesty well and happy for a long long time to come. We beg etc., 3d. Syed Mustafa Raza, Bar-at-Law, Honorary General Secretary, All India-Shi'a Conference,Lucknow.I.b. If Your Majesty has already secured the consent of the Hejaz Government, we most respectfully pray that we may also he allowed to contribute towards the building of our Holy monuments. 3d. Syed Mustafa Raz aFrom To The Honorary General Secretary, All-India Shia Conference, Lu ckn Ow. x His liajesty King-Ha 2 ia Shah Pahlawi of Persia, Tehran. Dated the 31st I,'ay 1930. Hay it please Your Majesty, I am sending herewith a copy of a representation which'I have submitted before His Excellency Lord Irv/in our popular and beloved Viceroy. We are smarting under the grievances and the wrongs done to us in Hejaz by King Ibne Saud, which has been set out in the representation. The Shias after centuries of persecution, which is a matter of History have found a refuge in India. The British Government has established a strong Government here which has given peace and prosperity to the people. Above all she has given us religious liberty and we can practice and preach our religion as we like. Never before in the Islamic History were Shias allowed such liberty of faith by a non-3hia power. We have no fear of being massacred only because we are decendents of Hazrat Ali, peace be on him. His Excellency Lord Irwin has got great love and regard for us and we have got great love for, and confidence in him. He could not have done more for us even if he was a Shia. He is taking the iac trouble of writing to Your Majesty and moving the British foreign Office x&amp;xxkxx for us. I am sure Your Majesty being a Shia lias got as much love for Hazrat Fatima, Hazrat Imam Hassan and Hazrat Imam Zainul Abedin and others whose monuments we want to erect, as we have, perhaps more, and I am sure, YourYour Ll&amp;jesty is as much anxious as we are that our grievances in Hej&amp;z may he removed. The Shius of India will he much grate^ful to Your llajesty if you will order that Your Maj estys foreign Office may cooperate with the Government of His Excellency Lord Irwin and the British Government in securing our demands and in removing our grievances in Hejas. I hear that Your llajesty is already in communication with the Hejaz Government and when Your kajesty met King Ihne Saud this matter was also discussed and some understanding has been arrived at. If this is true, I would submit that the Shias of India have got as much right to get the monument of Hazrat Batima their grand mother, erected as anybody else and Your Majesty may be pleased to allow us also in sharing her blessings, by being allowed to join in rebuilding her and other monuments. I am sure Your Majesty will be pleased to hear that the Shias of India are happy and prosperous and the British Government has given them peace and security and Your Majesty may be pleased to thank Lord Irwin personally for all his kindness towards us. With best respects and praying for your Maj estys long life and prosperity. We beg etc., Sd. Syed Mustafa Raza, Barris te r-at-law, Honorary General Secretary, All-India-Shia-Conferen ce, Lucknow(lndia).A /7 £.C.l\o. 7548 -G.L 30th. June 1930 Dear Sir, I am desired by His Exce-i-lency to acivnowledge your letters of 24th and 31st Lay 1930, addressed to His Lajesty King Raza Shah of Persia, but to say that for the reasons given in my letter No.5204, of 8th Lay His Excellency much regrets that he is unable to transmit them to the addressee. Yours faithfully, Sd. G-.Cunningham Private Secretary to the Viceroy The Honorary General Secretary, All-India-Shia Conference, Luc kn ox. 1 ,' ** Extract from a copy of a Resolution passed at a well attended meeting of the Shias of 3ukkur,held on the i4th July 1930 under the chairmanship of Agha Hassan Ali,3.A., LL.3., Advocate* Sukkur. 2. This meeting requests His Excellency the Viceroy to kindly use his good offices with the British Government for taking necessary steps in order to urge upon Ibne 3aud iiing of Hedjaz, for reconstructing the sacred shrines and monuments of ’Jannat-ul-Baqih 1 v/hich have been demolished by him. x _V? By Air Mail • , -16.JI/1 19S0^3&gt; : 17/&lt; J !&lt;^ Lucknow, April 1st, 1930. n Lear Sir, I beg to submit herewith a representation on behalf of a body under us, formed to look after the sacred Mohamedan places, in Hejaz. I took it out of the present address on the advice of the Private Secretary to His Excellency the Governor of U.P. if His Excellency the Viceroy win be pleased to take a little interest for us in it, and get us the permission of rebuilding our monu ments there, we would be able to subscribe lacs of rupees and the buildings may be built under the supervision of a board of English engineers, and we will put a grand statue for H.E. Lord Irwin at Mecca in thankfulness, which will endure till eternity. I pray you may be pleased to lay it before His Excellency. With best respects, I beg to remain, Dear Sir, Yours sincerely, Sd. S.Mustafa Raza, Hony. Genl. Secy., All India Shia Conference. h' /M-. /£- {/o cnj. • • • • • ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter No l7 2 M. Dated ] 4 Jljfil930 Docdve, 25JUM.1930 mm'25, To The Right Honourable Edward Fredrick, Lindis^' Wood, ♦Vi P•C•, G.C.S.r., G•G•X*E•, A Baron Irwin of Kirby Underdalet in the County of York, Viceroy and Governor General of India. May it please your Excellency, We the members of the Anjuman-i- Tahaffuz-i-Massir-i-Mutabarrak, All India Shia Conference Lucknow, beg leave of Your Excellency to make a representation about their long felt gtievances in regard to the question of Kejaz. That Your Excellency may be aware that since the inauguration of Ibni-Saud’s Government in Hejaz, backed up as it is by a large majority of people professing the Puritan Section of the Mussalmans popularly known as Wahabis or Ahl-i-Hadis, the religious susceptibilities of the Mussalmans of other creeds, have been deli^rately and continuously trampled down and the Wahabi tenets of faith have been forced upon the dissen tients by their wholesale and cold-blooded massacres, confiscation of their properties, closing of their c- places of worship, Imam Baras, and mosques, denervation of the holy tombs of their religious preceptors of faith, and several other sacred places of pilgrimage, prohibition of paying homages to the holy places of their own beliefs and the penalisation and punishment of acts of religious rituals in connection with visits to those places. These barbarous and inhuman acts have naturally roused a universal feeling of strong indigna- tion and abho^ence throughout the Muslim World but the feelings of Mussalmans of India and particularly of Shias of all parts of India, on this question, have runfee run very high. Rich and poor, Ulema.s and non-Uleraas, peasants and land-lords, conservatives and moderates, all without exception raised their voice of condemnation and expressed their sense of horror and disgust at the suicide of their of their religious liberty in Hejaz and the demolition of the holy tombs. 2. That they convened the All India Hejaz Conference in 1926 at Lucknow attended by representatives of all sections of Muslims and Ulemas of all Muslim creeds, held largely attended meetings in all parts of India, started several Anjumans to chalk out a plan of action for vindicating their grievances in Hejaz, organised a corps of self-less volunteers known as Reizakar-i-Jannutul Baqie and Khademul Harmain to check any future violation of their religious liberties and remedy the past wrongs, took out Alams and other mourning processions to commemorate the woeful events of Hejaz, particularly Jannatul- B&amp;qi^ , and finally laid down and adopted a programs of self- denial and sacrifices for collecting funds for the restoration of the Holy tombs to their former status and prevention of such wrongs in future. 3. That we most humbly venture to submit that the first call for enrolment of 'Rizakars of Jannutual-Baqia M was so largely responded to by the Shias of all parts of India including British Baluchistan and N.W.F* Province^ that thousands of volunteers enlisted themselves to vindicate their religious liberty, and if our Anjuman had not been cautious enough to prescribe an »v orderly and constitutional program/e of action for them to remedy the deliberate insult to their faith, their religious suscepti bilities might have exceeded limits of rational and peaceful moves. But as we have always cherished an implicit confidence in the integrity end justice of the British Government and its love for righteousness and toleration of religious faiths, we lookedlooked upon the British Government as our saviour and solicited its interventio n by the resolutions adopted at the open Annual sessions of the All India Shia Conferences held et Amroha, Patna, Calcutta and Sukkur and it is in this spirit of mutual confidence that we approach Your Excellency today. 4. That we cannot in detail dilate upon all the grievances we have against the avowed hostile activities of the Ibni-Saud’s Government in this representation but they may with advantage be divided under the following heads: - 1. Desecration and demolition of Holy buildings such as Mbulad-i-llabi (Birth place of the Prophet), Jannutul- '5 mualla (the Bani-Hashing graveyard at Mecca), J&amp;nnutul- ic A Baq^t (the Holy graveyard containing within it the bodies, of the Prophet’s only daughter Hazrat Fatima, of Hazrat Hassan, the Prophet’s grandson and the Shias second Imam, of Hazrat Zainul-Abidin, the 4th Imam, of ^azrat Imam Mohd. Baqir the 5th Imam, of Osman, the 5rd Caliph, and other relatives and Ashabs (True companions of the Prophet), and using of their materials having holy inscriptions at filthy and unclean places. 2. Stopping of visits to these ruined holy places and the reciting of Fatihas(blessings on the souls of the holy dead), Ziayarat(addressing saints and paying respects to them embracing and kissing of the holy graves. 3. Demolition of places of worship such as mosques of Hamza Abu Rashid and other Imambarahs, and forcible occupation of them and their sites by the Saudis. 4. Interference with the performance of customary rituals on the occajsions of pilgrimages. o 5. Forcing the non-Wahabis to confirm to be rituals and rules of practices of the Wahabi faith and compelling them to follow the lead of the Wahabi religious preceptors.6. Maltreatment, persecution, massacre and exile of Sadat-i-Taif, Madina, Ahsa and Qalif. 7. Of all the detestable incidents, the desecration e of Jannatul-Baqi^. has caused much uneasiness and grief in the minds of Shias and made them solicitors for the preservation of the holy tomb of the Prophet and other Imams and their protection from further disgrace# 8. We therefore pray that Your Excellency may be pleased to impress upon the Imperial Government the necessity for an early redress of our grievances through its intervention and diplomatic influence, by conveying to the Home Government the unceasing wailings and the cries of the 20 millions of Shias of India, who want the restoration of these Holy places of worship and pilgrimage and their religious liberty and freedom of worship to their status antequa, even if the costs of their repairs he made to be met out of their purses and the price for their religious freedom be theimives. Your Excellency’s most loyal and faithful servants, Submitted by We beg to subscribe ourselves Hated 1st April 1930 S# Mustafa Raza Bar-at -Law Hony: General Secretary of All India Shia Conference Lucknow(2&lt;? n &gt; .... • Copy of a letter No. 5204-G.M., dated the 8th May 1930, from the Privete Secretary to His Excellency the Viceroy, to the Honorary General Secretary, All-India Shia Conference, Lucknow. • * • • I am desired by His Excellency to refer to the memorial sent by you on the 1st April 1930, on behalf of the All-India Shia Conference, Lucknow, in regard to the question of the Hedjaz. His Excellency has given r ■ careful consideration to your representation, but he . i -■ much regrets that it would not be possible for him, consis tently with the settled policy of His Majesty’s Government of neutrality in religious matters and non-interference n the holy places of Islam, to take action in the manner suggested by you.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000289_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2111</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000289</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2111</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/44 'Hejaz and Indian Muslims. Desecration of tombs by Wahabis, etc.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-04T22:26:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 31; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-29; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file compiles copies of appeals made by representatives of Indian Muslims to the British Government (and in one case, to the Shah of Persia [Reza Shah Pahlavi]), regarding the desecration of various holy buildings and monuments by Ibn Saud's [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd's] Wahabi forces. The nature of the appeals is twofold: appeals dating from 1930 request that the Viceroy of India (Edward Frederick Lindley Wood – referred to in the file as Lord Irwin, succeeded by Freeman Freeman-Thomas) use his influence on behalf of the British Government to urge Ibn Saud to reconstruct demolished shrines and monuments such as those at Janatul-Bakia [Jannat al-Baqīʿ]; later appeals, which date from 1933, call on the British Government to remain neutral regarding affairs in the Hejaz and Nejd, and to refrain from providing Ibn Saud with military, naval, or any other kind of assistance.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Shah of Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Janatul-Bakia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Tombs</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Private Secretary to the Viceroy of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Hejaz and Najd</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Wahabi (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Muslims</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000289#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>