<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00000a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-12T14:58:15.277Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">+ ■■ BRITISH CONSULATE MUSCAT FILE NO: 8/54 NAME OF FILE: MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: AFFAIRS OF MEMBERS OF RULING FAMILY coVIII 16 - MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS. H. STATE PERSONALITIES AND OFFICIALS. I8j. Debts of the members of the Rulirtg Family. From To previous number. 83 rFINANCE MINISTRY^ MUSCAT STATE, Dated -0 The Political Agent &amp; P.P.r's Consul Sir I have the honour in reference to your 66 0 dated X. there is no reason 'beyond custom v;hy the huscat State should act as a debt collecting agency in respect of mortgaged salaries of tie Puling Family. The system was rife 'before my arrival and has hy order and act of mine 'been discouraged. If' other officers of the State have on their own authority lent their signatures to such transactions the latter can if necessary he repudiated hy me. The principals.that after the liquidation of the present debts no more transactions of this he permitted hy the State is ' $ made the subject of CL the Council order. The merchants have during the past six months received little encouragement to go on lending to Ruling members because I have held up repayments. II. As regards para 4 the postal service would he a weekly one along the Batinah to Sahar. This area is at the moment being opened hy motor car and the floating of a motor company is afoot in Sahar to run a weekly passenger and goods service to and from Muscat.2. An /A n Jl postal contract with this coripan^ or some other at a purely nominal cost to the State could, he made. The postal stamp revenue would it is anticipated derive Chiefly from stamp collectors and dealers. The liirJtel scope of the internal service would not require any additional expenditure on staff and buildings either initial or recurring. The only expenditure involved would he in printing postage stamps. V'aterlowd Sons have quoted £ 140/- =L1900/- approximately for 60,000 stamps spread over six denomin ations varying between 1 anna and 1 rupee - Rs. 12687/- in face value : and £ 50/- # L.670/- for repeat orders of the sar.e quantities. This quotation is thought high and a less expensive one will he sought if permission V to proceed with the matter is accorded. The stamp of the 1 rupee denomination would it i thought he useful in connection with the new Bill of Lading tax. I have the honour etc. 0 .?. 'LsUV^-— 1 Finance Minis ter.of ioXitioitl ^tnuy tad K«£*M 9 » Conbul»t « 9 Mwuctit 50th hay 1930. To The tteeretftiry to the hen v bXe the loXitiocd heeldent in the leralan Gull 9 Hir, A 10 Si Helerenoe your Xetter ho«192*&amp; dated 17th April 1930. I attach* here*/ith 9 the Finanoe Mlnleter** Xetter ho.33 dated the ^ rv 27th Kay 1950 oontainlnd hie reuarke thereon. r 2 . A» regarde para 1 of your Xe tter the practice appear® to be an old one. It wee brought to ay notice ehortly after ^ took over thin poet ana X obtained a Xiet of euch deductiona at the ti&amp;au The question of putting a atop to the practice eeeae to have been raiced in 1920 anu a notice waa leaned warning aerchante that they would get no aeeiatanco in reeoTerlng of debte unleae at the tie* the debt waa incurred it wee endoreed by the Council of Klnietere« I aaw thin notice in 1926 but unfortunately It cannot now be traced In wy office. X gakaaaea queetioned kr.Thomae at that time. X gathered from him that the rail of katrah*hie predeoeeeor as Finance Kinleter* Iriad been weak about endoroementa. X preaumed the order wan being carried out and it waa only a question of timr/ before theee aebta were cleared off. An examination of the documenta in the poaaeeeion of the money* •lender* which X recently carried out 9 ehowe that the order has been diuregurded 9 uno documents hare been endoreed by kinletera individually whilat deduotione have been made whether document* were endoreedufc or not. Kr. Thooia* 1 * explanation of the two doouanent* which he himeelf endoreed 1 * that in Ut* on* oace he did *o under instruction* from H.H.the sultan whilst in tiie otiasr case he did *o to «n- •able the laoy to pay a bill of br.aarrlitan for mecloal attendance* 3. Pith regax*u to para .6 o f your letter the proposal ls 9 a* i have »ilr«wdv noint^ri nut. eomewhet premeture end would not furnitohif - i \ any imediata roTecue* 4* bitioe tb® opening of the kuecat-fc&amp;tr&amp;b rood the !&amp;• •port of motor TohioXos into kuooot hao boon proceeding apace* A year ago Uiere vtm one motor oar Aero f nov there are about 18 and more are arriving every week* 14 of theee are belt* need for public conveyance* Xn addition to the work ^ 1 / road construction being carried out by tiie kueoat Infentry,Khnn baiiadur kaeib ie oonetruoting a road up the Wadi Adai te U*bil at hie own expenee; the prieonere under baiyid kahwud are improving and broadening the read through the euburbe of kueoat whilet a party of cooliee,employed by the ownere of tlie conveyances on their own lnltiatlve 9 are at work on the road towards bib* lioade from bohar northwards to #&amp;u bakarah and eouthwarde te Aha- -burah have been oonstruoted by the tali ef bohar* Xt will not be long before regular motor services are running aka along the batinah between kuecat and sohar* At present letters are conveyed to the various towns on the Batinah by favour of the kastere ef the bhows proeeeuing there* er else*if urgent*by camel wm couriers* As soon as a motor eervloe starts*they will undoubtedly be conveyed by car* It will not be difficult then to start a local postal service at seme profit and little expense to the State* X have the honour to be* Sir* Your most obedient servant* kajor* political *gent ana E*b*k's Con 8 Ul*kuscat* oob* *Copy of notice dated issued by the Council of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat# 24th ituharram 1S49 (22nd June 19 Ministers to H.H.the bultan of We hereby notify those who receive salaries from the Government of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat end warn all merchents who deal with them on credit triat the Government Treasury does not accept any dralt figeirist the pay of any person who receives salary ana such dreits would be refused from the date of issue of the notice*IjlJf. mi (25) 3 # D*0*No.298-3 of 1932. Britiah Residency, Bughlre, the 13th May 1932 hris-tiu 1 .um Thanks for your meno^StrrfTTirn. ho. 17/17/435 of the 29th April forwarding a statement of the Muscat accounts. The situation seems to be quite satis factory, more especially as I understand that tne first quarter of the year is normally rather a lean one. I have several times suggested to the Sultan that a committee should be appointed to examine tne debts due to Nasib. From all accounts his charges were exorbitant and the large sum 1 owing to him was susceptible of reduction. I do not know if anythin^, has been done to verify these debts, but if you agree perhaps you could suggest to dis Highness the desirability of going into these debts, ho one wants to deprive Nasib’s heirs oi their just due s ... Lt.Col.T.C.Fowls,C.B.E., Muscat.r ip! - 2 - dues, but on the other hand there seems no reason why they should be allowed to benefit unduly by tne gross laxity which prevailed in former times.COMFIDSMTIAL. D.O.M 0 .C/ 17 V Muscat, 3rd July 1934. Jitj^duuc QloiuJl, Please refer to your confidential D.O.Mo.475-3 ► dated 28th May l^o4* i»s far as can be ascertained only two British merchants are owed money locally by the dtate. These are Hansi Madivji fs 5,000/- and Fragji Batansi 1,600/-. 3. Neither have lodged claims here and the information is from private source. #ts Dull Chand holds the keys of the files concerned and is out on protracted tour, it is impossible to obtain further details, but 1 have heard, again privately, that the State intend liquidating these debts at the first opportunity. j*. further debt incurred by dir fialyid Talmur has only now been admitted. This is a claim for Ik 9,530-13-3 by Bamazan All of Karachi. There was a certain amount of doubt as to the authenticity of dir daiyld Taimur’s sig nature on the bill but this has since been cleared up the dultan proposes to pay by instalments. He has sought By good offices to arrange the amount of these with the firm when I go to Karachi. To The Hon'ble Lieut-Col.T.C.Fowle,B.B.M., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf,c I was under the impression that the State only owed money to Muscat! subjects, and certainly no British subjects, as far as 1 remember, have ever entered in the Agency any debt claims against the Muscat State. In one of our conversations with the Sultan, however, the latter stated that there were some British subjects concerned. You were going to look the matter up. Please let me know the result.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00000a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/235</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00000a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/235</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/54 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: AFFAIRS OF MEMBERS OF RULING FAMILY'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-19T22:05:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (28 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 30; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to the financial affairs of the ruling family of Muscat. The correspondence mainly concerns British objections to an arrangement by which the Muscat State acts as a debt collecting agency on behalf of creditors against members of the ruling family. The system reportedly encourages merchants to lend money to members of the ruling family, with the State then collecting the debts out of the family allowances.Notable correspondents include the following: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Bertram Sidney Thomas, Finance Minister for Muscat State.In addition to correspondence the file includes tables listing details of the debts owed by certain members of the ruling family, covering the period 1923-1930.The Arabic language material consists of a notice issued by the Muscat Council of Ministers.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Council of Ministers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Financial Advisor to the Sultan of Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Family finance</topic></subject><subject><topic>Debts</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x00000a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>