<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-29T09:13:52.901Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">______*■) Vpi? India Office, London, 3rd March 1921. Military, No. 16 To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Loud, 1 forward, for the consideration of Your Excellency’s Government, a copy of a letter, with enclosures, 1 ositton oj i ecfulm military addressed to the High Commissioner, officers employed by the Civil -, r , \ , Government of Mesopotamia in Mesopotamia, in regard to the retention regard to after-war leave. ^7 regular officers of the British Army M. 1395. who are employed by the Civil Govern ment of Mesopotamia, of privileges, notably “after-war leave,” earned by purely military service. The cpiestion was first brought to my notice by the Commander-in-Chief’s telegram of 27th January 1920, No. 1203, to the address of the Foreign Department of the Government of India. 2. I request that you will, in consultation with the High Commissioner, take such action or make such recommendations to me, as you may consider necessary, to regularise, on lines analogous to those followed in the case of British Service officers, the position of officers of the Indian Army employed by the Civil Government of Mesopotamia, having regard to Army Regulations, India, Vol. I., paragraph 69G, and Vol. IL, paragraphs 303 and 304. I I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Edwin S. Montagu.ENCLOSURE India Office to the High Commissioner, Baghdad. India Office, Sir, 10th February 1921. I am directed to forward copies of the marginally noted correspondence! regarding the right of officers of the &gt; India Office to ’W ar Office, 22nd British Regular Army employed by the “'oLhIlAroffiTeAmhV. Mesopotamian Administration to “after- 1S20,121/3/2037 (F. 2 , Ind.). war leave under the terms of Army Instruction, India, No. 320 of 1919. Asa result of oral discussion with a representative of the 1 War Office, of the W T ar Office letter of 10th November, it is understood that by au extended interpretation of the provisions of Art. 102 of the Pay Warrant, officers who have accepted service under the Civil Administration of Mesopotamia (prior to your assumption of the duties of High Commissioner), and more especially officers who signed a contract of service under the Civil Commissioner, are regarded as having dispossessed themselves of any claim to military privileges accruing prior to, but not actually enjoyed before, the date of entry into civil service. Further, though this point has not previously been raised in correspondence, the War Office are disposed to regard service under the Civil Administration as not counting for military pension, except in strict conformity with Art. 102 of the Pay Warrant. Prior to your assumption of duty in Mesopotamia, the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, Mesopotamian Expeditionary Force, was the superior British Officer, and it is presumed that regular military officers could only be posted for service under the Civil Commissioner (and sign a contract with the latter) with the General Officer Commanding’s consent or by his direction.- In order, therefore, to safeguard the rights of British Service officers so employed, not only in respect of their claim to “ after-war leave” under Army Instruction, India, 320 of 1919, but also in respect of service for pension, I am to request that you will be good enough to move the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief to address the War Office after consultation with yourself, in regard to questions of adjustment between Military and Mesopotamian funds, in regard to the seconding for service under the Civil Administration of all regular officers of the British Army so seconded at the date of Sir A. Wilson’s telegram 1203 of 27th January 1920. I am to suggest that the General Officer Commanding should include in his representations a nominal list of all officers affected and recommendations as to their treatment under Art. 102 of the Pay Warrant, as well as in respect of Army Instruction, India, 320 of 1919, and any other military privileges that might be in question. I am to request to be informed in due course of the result of your consultation with the General Officer Commanding. The foregoing applies only to British Service officers. The case of regular officers of the Indian Army has been referred (in the letter of which a copy of the draft is enclosed) to the Government of India, to whom a cop}’ of the present letter has been forwarded. I am to request that you will consult the Government of India in regard to the regularisation on analogous lines of the position of the regular officers of the Indian Army who are or have been employed under the Civil Administration of Mesopotamia. The High Commissioner, Baghdad. I have, Ac., J. E. Shuckblrgh.22^ Annex 1 :—India Office to War Office. O Sir, India Office, 22nd October 1^)20. I am directed b} T the Secretary of State for India to forward, to be laid before the Army Council, the draft of a telegram relative to the application of the terms of Army Instruction (India), 320 of 1919, to officers otherwise entitled who are serving under the Civil Administration, Mesopotamia, which, subject to the concurrence of the Army Council, he proposes to despatch to the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. The Government of India have intimated that they support the Civil Commissioner’s proposal, remarking that it will be for His Majesty’s Government to decide whether the leave allowances in question should be charged to the War Office or to Mesopotamian revenues. The favour of an early reply is requested, since the Civil Commissioner is pressing for a decision on the point. A copy of this letter, with enclosure, is being sent to the Treasury. I have, Ac., I. E. Shuckburgh. The Secretary, War Office. Enclosure in above. Telegram from Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State for India, dated 27th January 1921. 1203. Please see Controller of War Accounts’ telegram of 23rd January, 8191. Consider it quite inequitable that officers should be debarred from provisions of Army Instructions (India), 320, through their happening to be serving in Civil Administration, and see nothing in instructions to justify the Audit interpretation. In any case it is requested that provision of the instruction may be extended to officers otherwise eligible who happen to be serving in this Administration. I will submit proposals as to incidence later. Annex 2 :—1 bar Office to India Office. War Office, 10th November 1920. 121/3/2037. (F. 2 Ind.) With reference to your letter of 22nd October 1920, No. P. 7219, forwarding a copy of the draft of a telegram relative to the application of the terms of Army Instruction, India, 320 of 1919, to officer's otherwise entitled who are serving under the Civil Administration, Mesopotamia, and also a copy of a telegram from Baghdad on the same subject, I am directed to acquaint you that it is considered that — (1) officers who accept a special contract under the Civil Administration, Mesopotamia, should not be granted after-war leave at the expense of Army funds ; ( 2 ) officers who earned after-war leave while they were being paid from Army funds and are temporarily lent on Army pay to the Civil Administration should be considered as eligible for after-war leave at War Office expense ; (3) the reckoning of service under the Civil Administration for after war leave would be for that Administration to decide upon, and if would also be for Civil funds to bear the expense of any leave granted in respect of such service. Cl 1 1 1 V V V_y . y H. C. Glayshek, for the Secretary (Finance). I am, Ac. The Under Secretary of State for India.Register No. Political To Ujjl Letter from Dated 191 . Dee. Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. * Under Secretary.. Secretary of State. Committee / Under S^retary .. / Secretary of State. Council Table. .— .at;'-d '4, Telephone : Victoria 9400. 234?'® All further communications on this subject should be addressed to—■ The Secretary, ; War Office, London, S.W.l. and the following number quoted. WAR OFFICE, b' y o , ; uzmew, j () November, 1920 121/3/2037. (I?. 2.1 rid.) ■ 'r; ) bir, With reference to :rour letter of 22nd October, 1920, No .P .7219 forwarding a copy of the draft of a telegram relative to the application of the terms of Army- Instructions India, 320 of 1919 to Officers otherwise entitled who are serving tinder the Civil Administration, Mesopotamia, and also a copy of a telegram from Baghdad on the same subject, I am directed to acquaint you that it is considersd that - Officers who accept a special contract under the Civil Administration Mesopotamia should not be granted After War Leave at the expense of Army- Funds* Leave at War Office expense, Administration for After War Leave would be for be for IhSfrff Lgpafrt merrfc to bear the expense of Assay leave granted in respect of such service, A-r I am The Under Secretary of State for India, PoliU-c^L _ for the Secretary (Finance). rIn reply please quote P 'C ^ f 6 f ‘ Political Department, India Office, London, S.W. 1 . , lA ^ 1 P 3 ,' ^ ^ r «v- &gt;, fA :aar Mr. Glayshor, 89th ember 1980* » .r^ D&gt; kM tV ’Ve have been thinking over your official letter 181/3/2037 , F*2*Ind.) of 10th ILovember in the light of your conversation rith me the other day. It seems that the question of after war leave - which is primarily under discussion - is of less importance to the officers concerned than the question, not yet overtly raised, of what is their position in regard to service-for-pension (under Bay Warrant Article 102) while they are employed by the Civil Administration. Having regard to the fact that till a month or two ago the supreme officer in Mesopotamia was the Cell era! Officer Commanding in Chief, it seems that the best, or only, way to clear up the questions affecting these officers is to get the Ceneral Officer Commanding dl \ iin Chiefteft report to the ».ar Office as to how he came to hand over military officers to 'civil employment” t with recommendations as to their pension rights and other rights while so employed. If you agree we will ask the High Commissioner to get the General Officer Commanding to do this: the thing will have to be worked out locally between civil and military in the first place. Perhaps you could drop me a line or telephone me (India Office 369) as to your views. Yours sincerely, Irk[P 1493] i^io m Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, 21 th January 1920. 2 {Addressed Foreign, Delhi ; repeated Secretary of State.) si o 1 120 n' P1 , ease see 9 on ! roUer . of War Accounts’ telegram of 23rd January, • . Consider it quite inequitable that officers should be debarred from piovisions of A.1 1 . 320 through their happening to be serving !h' civil administration and see nothing in instructions to justify the audit interpre- 1 4,1 at ' on j any case it is requested that provision of the instruction may be J j CLk e f ende ? t0 officers otherwise eli g ible x who happen to be serving in this b 71 . i administration. I wiir submit proposals as to incidence later Ir-JrJ, t ^ K . —— - . =r— From Viceroy, Foreign Department, 10th February 1920. {Repeated to Civil Commissioner, Baghdad.) IP 1493] 553 Est. A. Baghdad telegram dated 27th January, 1203. Govern ment of India consider your sanction is necessary to extension of special war leave under Army Instruction (India) 320 of 1919 to military officers employed under civil administration. IP 1493] From Secretaru or Stale to Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, 12th April 1920. {Addressed Viceroy, a.nd repeated to Baghdad.) Your telegram dated 10th February, o53. Conditions of Army Instruction 320, appear inapplicable to officers in civil employment. I think it preferable to grant privilege leave concession proposed in your telegram dated 3rd January 1919, Finance Department, and sanctioned in my telegram dated 22nd January. If you agree, please take necessary action, and inform me of the decision arrived at. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, 31st May 1920. . Your telegram dated 10th February, No. 553. Please expedite reply to my telegram dated 12th April, From Viceroy, Foreign Department, 3rd June 1920. {Repeated Baghdad.) FP 44881 2 1 74 Est. A. Baghdad telegram of 19th May, 5980. Please refer to your telegrams of 8 th August 1917, 12 th March 1917, and 30th October 1918, No. 2858. Leave arrangements for Civil Officers in Mesopotamia (para.) Force leave. Full pay leave for three months’ on being wounded or invalided and leave to the United Kingdom, under Army Council Instructions 2327 of 1916 have thus been extended to the Civil Administration with your sanction. We support the request of Civil Commissioner that concession in Army Instructions (India) 320 of 1919, should also be made applicable to military officers of Civil Administration who are otherwise eligible for the leave. It will be for His Majesty’s Government to decide whether leave allowances should be charged lo War Office or to Irak Revenues. P. 4488. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 11th June 1920. Your telegram of 3rd June, 2174 Est. A. Have you taken into consideration my telegram of 12th April, in reply to your telegram of 10th February, 553 Est, A ? Please repeat Baghdad telegram 5980, not received here. From Viceroy, 23rd June 1920. P. 4969. 2486 Est. A. Your telegram dated 17th June, P. 4488. Your telegram dated 12th April was considered when framing recommendations on Baghdad telegram 6980, which was repeated to Secretary of State. My telegram dated 29th April, 1684 Est. A., referred to therein, asked Baghdad if they concurred with your proposal.From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 2nd Jidy 1920. P. 4969. Your telegram of 23rd June, 2486 Est. A. Please repeat telegram 5980 not received here. Baghdad From Viceroy, 7th July 1920. (Addressed Foreign; repeated Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, and Secretary of Stale for India.) P. 5360. 2653 Est. A. Your telegram dated 2nd July, P. 4969. Following is Baghdad telegram 5980, dated 19th May :— “Your telegram dated 29th April, 1684 Est. A. I do not concur in Secretary of State for India’s proposal. Concession communicated in your Despatch dated 1st March 1919, 738 Est. A., is applicable only to officials subject to civil leave rules. Concession in Army Instructions (India) 320 is applicable to officials subject to military leave rules. It would not be practicable to attempt to apply provisions of former letter to latter class of officials as suggested. “ The Civil Administration synonymous with the Political Department of Mesopotamian Expeditionary Force. As such the officers in question are no more in civil employment than officials employed in other departments of the force like Resources, Surveys, Works, Base, and I cannot agree with the view that service (in the?) Political Department should be held to prevent military officers from enjoving the same concessions and privileges as military officers serving m any other department of the force. It would cause much discontent, particularly in case recently transferred from departments. “In the circumstances*! trust that sanction requested in my telegram of 21st January, 203, may be accorded.”\ 2436. Bst. a. Your telegram June 17th P.4488. Your telegram April 12th was considered when framing recommenaations on Baghdad telegram o980. - r hx cii was repeated to Secretary of State. Ly telegram April 29th 1684 Est. A. referred to therein, asked Bagiidad if they concurred with your proposal.mu o ou iig n in 3 iku otiohs S 3 2 7 / /Q v, / / ■' O LEAVE GHAIITBD TO 0FPIGEH3 iiiJD SOLDIERS O./UIG TO EXIGE1IGIE3 GOniJEGTED ,/ITH THEIR CIVIL PROPE331011, BU3IHE33 OP PRIVATE AFFAIRS. A.G,I. 1026 of 1916 is cancelled and the following substituted. Officers. 1 0 An Officer of the Regular Army, Special Reserve of f.F. serving at home, who, during the continuance of active service, requires leave owing to exigencies connected with his civil profession, business or private affairs, may, if tile 0.0.G. in G. is satisfied of the urgency of the case and that the absence of the Officer is abso3.utely necessary, oe granted such leave as the G-.0.0. in G. considers will meet the case, up to, but not exceeding, one month. 2. If, at the time of granting leave or prior to the expiration of such leave, the Officer can satisfy the G.O.G. in G. that an extension of leave beyond one month is urgently required for the settlement of his affairs, the G.O.G. in 0. may, provided the Officer consents to forego the receipt of any pay and allowances from Army funds, refer the case to the v/ar Office with his remarks thereon. Ho extension is to be granted without War Office atthority. 3. In ail cases of extension of leave granted to an Officer under these circumstances, the O.G. his unit will be responsible tnat the Army Agents are notified that such extension is without pay. 4. Leave is granted by the Military Authorities in Prance, Egypt, Aalonika and India at their discretion, and without reference/ ] l ir reference to the War Office, to allow one month in the lnited Kingdom, dating from the date of disembarkation, 'ft/ Leave in excess of one month will be without pay and allowances. All Officers granted leave under this para. Will report in writing to the War Office, stating their unit and home address, date of arrival, and period of leave granted, also any extension that may be given to them. 5. Officers grjinted leave will on no account take servants with them.a the ~ : atioj! t b Put aicay Return to Copy for leminder on t their wamined Registry DRAFT TELEGRAM TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ARMY DEPARTMENT. -I^ETA-RIALGR Send. ^ Sent Date 2858. Prom Secretary of State to Viceroy, -Arniy Department. [Note.—The place to which the telegram is -to be sent must be added by the telegraph clerk.] No. of Telegram §95S . Your telegram dated 6th Sept, leave of Officers in Civil Administration Mesopotamia. Your proposal is approved. t (Form 208.) 10 532 2000 12/191 ' COPY OP From Viceroy (Finanee)• Dated 6,9.18. Received Please refer to Var Office telegram of 7th October last Commander-in-Chief in India and to paragraph 4 of Army Council Instructions £327 of 1916. We request / sanction to extension of similar leave concession to I Officers serving under Civil Administration Mesopotamia and trust our action in granting such leave to Lieut. H.1I. Hopkins,Captain R. Harrs, Captain A.O. Rapier and Colonel 12.Gr. Cregson will he confirmed.and/or this purpose ^to treat any privilege leave enjoyed by them under military rules as if it had been » taicen under civil rules. This would be in accordance with the general principle in regard to civil furlough applied to military officers coming under civil leave rules for the first time (Art.303(ii) ; Civil Service Regulations).January 1203 o Sovammant ox^laMa'-xriti^'-ior your sanction is necessary to extension “C of special war l$av« under Army Instruction ;(India) 320 of 1919 to military officers I employed under civil admmi at ration o Addressed Secretary of State for India and repeated to Civil Commissioner, Baghdad,,COPY OP* TELEGRAM S' Erom Civil C omm i 8 s 1 or a r i; E aghd&amp;fl / ft** S lf r 1JI 2?th January, A.TED ruary p e m 0 please see Controller of Tar Account® 1203 o 23rd January £151 0 Consider it quite -inequitable that officers si should be debarred from provieions of A,.1 9 T * 320 through their happening to be serving in Civil Administration and see nothing in instructions to justify the Audit interpretation 0 Xn any case it is requested that provision of the instruction may be extended % officers otherwise eligible who happen to be serving in this administration 0 I will submit proposals as to incidence later n ' ymm 320 SPECIAL Y/AA LEAVE On the recoiranendetion of the Government of India, tne Right hon 1 hie^ the secretary of State for India has sanctioned the gran or special war leave on the following terms:- 1. Officers entitled to special war leave under this Ins true ti on (a) All regular officers of the Indian Services who are ordinarily entitled to privilege leave, and all permanent subor dinates of the India Unattached List and Indian Departments subject to military rules, who are ordinarily entitled to privilege leave PROVISOS* (1) Officers of less than two years 1 service, who propose to resign their commissions, are not entitled to special war leave under this Instruction. (2j Officers lent to the War Office, who have been granted corresponding leave by the v/ar Office, must set the leave so taken against any special war leave due under this Instruction. (3) Officers holding appointments, on vacating which they would normally revert to unemployed pay on ceasing to be employed, ere not entitled to special war* leave under this Instruction. (b) All regular officers of the British Servj.ce who are ordinarily entitled to privilege leave and have had, or will have, a total of two years 1 service in India between the 4th August 1914 and the 3rd August 1919, both days inclusive. PROVISOS (1) Officers of less than two years’ service who untend to res ign the ir c ommis s ions ar e not en ti tie d to sp eci el war leave under this Instruction. ( 2) Officers holding appointm en ts, on vacat ing which th ey would normally revert to half pay, on ceasing to be employed, are not entitled to special war leave under this Instruction. II. - Total Amount of special v/ar leave admissible. Sixty days. III. - Date by which an entitled officer must complete special war leave (a) British Service officers, who have reserved Indian rights under tile announcement made b. : the Prime Minister in the House of Commons on the 16th September 1914 and who have been serving elsewhere than in India, Mesopotamia and Aden, will only be eligible for special war leave under this Instruction up to such date as may sub equently be fixed for the cessation of twose rights. Dote/- The following officers of the British Service have reserved Indian rights under the Prime Minister’s announcement;- (l) Officers who joined Indian Exp e diti on ary forces A,B,C,D,E or F From the Indian establishment. (2 J Officers who while at home on leave from the Indian establishment were on mobilisation taken for duty on the Imperial establishment and subsequently joined in the field the units to which they belonged in ^ndia, without causing an excess in the Indian establishment of those units. (3) Individual regimental officers specially sent home from India for war service if they were employed on that service regimentally, or if they were employed in staff posts on the British establishment and retained their Indian regimental emoloments. (4j Officers who were seconded from their regiments in IndiaIndie end suoaequently rejoined then while on service in the field without, causing an excess in the Indian establishment of their units. (hi All other officers will under this Instruction up to the all title to it will cease. o e el i gi bl e fo r sp ec ial war 1 eav e 31st Dec ember 1922; thereafter IV. - Leave allowances on special war leave. Officers will draw leave allowances equivalent to the full pay and staff pay of the appointments held on the day on which they proceed on special war leave. PHOVIJO. ./here the appointment ceases to exist on the day on which the officer proceeds on special war leave, he will draw as leave allowances the full pay and staff pay of his substantive appointment. Where the appointment ceases to exist on a date subsequent to that on which an officer proceeds on special war leave but before his special war leave ends, he ?/ill draw - \ (1) during the period that the appointment remains in existence, the full pay and staff pay of the appointment; (2) during the remaining period, the full pay and staff pay ofnhis substantive appointment. Lote. - An appointment ceases to exist for this purpose if it is not again filled after the departure of the officer on leave. V.- Methods of taxing special war leave. Special war leave may be taxen:- (a) In India; or out of India; (b) all at once; or in any number of instalments subject to such orders as may be issued as to the number of occasions on which leave may be granted to an officer - prior to the 31st December 1922; (c) alone; or combined with leave of any other description, subject to such orders as may be issued as the total period of le ve to be granted on one occasion to an officer in, or out of, India. ./here special war leave is combined with other leave, the special war leave will be considered to be taken first for the purpose of calculating the leave allowances of the officer and the emoluments of trie officiating incumbent of his appointment. VI.- Emoluments of the officiating incumbents of appointments held by officers who proceed on special war leav e. (c) Officers officiating in regimental appointments vacated by off 1060 :*s proceeding on special warleave will, during the period of that leave, draw the full staff pay of those appointments. (b) Officers officiating in other appointments vacated by officers proceeding on special war leave will, during the period of thatleave, draw such emoluments as would be admissible to them if the special war leave were privilege leave, or the full pay of their substantive appointments, whichever is greater. VII.- Advances when proceeding on special War leave out of' India.* Oj.fi6ers proceeding on special war leave out of India will receive in India an advance of the full allowances admissible 'to ne during the special war leave and during any privilege leave talcen in continuation of it. privilege leave PROVISO. .. Advances will not exceed the amount due as leave allowances xor tnree monohs. ! -/hen the combined special war end privilege months, the balance of privilege leave of officers exceeds three leave allowance will be paid to rate of exchange current at the Oixicers 1 last pay certificates the them in the United hingdom at time the payment is made. . - - - will show the exaetperiods of special war privilege and. general leave granted to them, the rate 01 allowances ad mis si ole during each description of leave, and are being is* the amount oi advances tahen; and special arrangements pay certificates reach the United made to secure that last ningdom in good time, note.- uhen special war leave is combined with privilege leave, biiis idle supersedes paragraph 43 II (a) of Army Itegulations, India, Volume III. ’ VIII. - L1ISGELLAIIE0US• (a) Officers of less than two speci al war 1 eav e, must reco rd applications ?T I hereby declare that I have commission for two years after the now applied for. Should I do so, years 1 service, in applying for the following declaration # on their no intention of resigning expiry of the special war I undertake to refund to my leave any sums paid to me for the period of special war Government leave” • ib; Officers who have during tne wai been lent to die War Office in applying for special war leave under tnis Instruction, must record the following declaration on their applications:- months ,! I hereby declare that I have received from the oar Office leave corresponding to special war leave under Army Instruction (India) ho.320 of 1919. (019334 (A.G.5.) i t. rNo. 66 op 1919. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. FOKEIGN AND POLITICAL DEPAETMEN ESTABLISHMENT. To Sib, We hare the honour to inform you that in May last, on the recom mendation of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, we sanctioned for Captain C. J. Edmunds, Political Officer of the Mesopotamian Expeditionary Eorce, for the period 2nd April to 21th April 1918, during which he acted as British Vice- Consul at Ahwaz, the grant of the language allowance, sanctioned by your telegram of the 14th September 1916, for proficiency in Persian, viz., Es. 100 a month. Captain Edmunds while holding the appointment of British Vice- Consul, Ahwaz, also acted as Political Officer, and we considered it reasonable that he should be permitted to continue to draw the allowance. By the grant of the allowance Captain Edmunds’ salary was raised beyond the limit of Es. 750 a month and we regret that the necessity of obtaining your sanction was overlooked. We request that you will now accord your approval of the action taken by us. 2. Your sanction is also requested to the grant of the same allowance to Captain E. G. Peel, who assumed charge of the duties of British Vice-Consul at Ahwaz on the 25th April 1918 and whose case is similar to that of Captain Edmunds. Captain Peel has passed the proficiency examination in Persian. THE RIGHT HONOURABLE EDWIN MONTAGU. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 21st August 1919. We have the honour to be, Sib, Your most obedient, humble Servants, a'1 To No. 31 01 1919. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. ESTABLISHMENT. w f 2 6 4 e 1919 The Right Honoheable EDWIN MONTAGE, Mis Majesty 9 s Secretary of State for India* Simla, the 16th April 1919* Sir, We have the honour to forward a copy of the papers cited in the attached list from which it will be seen that we have sanctioned, as a purely temporary measure, the grant of sumptuary allowances to the Civil Com missioner and certain Political Officers of the Civil Administration of Mesopotamia. We trust that you will approve our proceedings. i We have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants,1 List of enclosures in despatch No. SI (Establishment), dated the 16th April 1919, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. S«mlNo. No. and date of paper. Prom whom, or to whom. Letter, No. 5870, dated the 16th July 1918. Memo., No. 2194-Est.-A, dated the 3rd October 1918. Letter, No. 24736—14/4.5, dated the 6th November 1918, and enclosure. Telegram, No. 2297, dated the 24th February 1919. Telegram, No. 775-Est.«A, dated the 5th March 1919. From the Offg. Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. To ditto ditto. From ditto ditto. From ditto ditto. To ditto ditto.Telegram, No. 58/0, dated Baghdad, the 16th (received the 18th) July 1918. From—The Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. *Est. A., June 1918, Nos. 12-14. 5870, 15th. Your 1006-Est. A.,* May 14th. 1 . Class (1 ).—No unfavourable effect on Civil Administration anticipated, provided Government will consider increased remuneration allowances in special tat. B., June 1618, Nos. 396.389. ^aT 20^“ ^ 2 ^ ^ 2 . Recommendations for such will be made in general, when salary of officer, remunerative allowances included, is less than 700 for Assistant Political Officer in independent charge of district or department, or for Assistant Commissioner, Police, and less than Rs. 900 for Political Officer in charge a division or a Deputy Commis sioner, Police. 3. At present several British Service Officers occupying such posts, some married, draw only Rs. 550 which is inadequate in view of expense of maintaining independent establishment, and heavy responsibility; e.g., Suter, in charge Samawah Division, with two Assistant Political Officers, draws Rs. 550. 4. Class (2). —I would ask that order be subject to proviso that officer of Civil Administration should not draw less than he would have drawn in military employ in this country. 5 . Class (3). —No comment. 6 . Class (4).—Would ask that orders be subject to provisions in paragraphs 2 and 4 supra. 7. Class (5). —No comment. 8 . I assume orders do not affect officers recruited in Egypt and elsewhere true m. A., August .918, Nos. 22.30. ^ S P eCial COndition ^ ^9; Mder,* Bal- 9 . I further propose to submit to Government proposals for grant of sumptuary allowance not exceeding Rs. 200 per mensem to officers in outstations whose situa tion involves provision food and accommodation for officers of Military and Civil Departments passing through on business and for notables. 10 . If Government of India see their way to accept above general proposals in principle, specific proposals will be submitted with detailed schedules.2 Memo. No. 2194-Est. A., dated Simla, the 3rd October 1918. From—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To Lieutenant-Colonel A. T. Wilson, C.M.G., C.I.E., D.S.O., Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. Your telegram No. 5870, dated 16th July 1918, regarding salaries of superior officers serving under Civil Administration in Mesopotamia. 2. Government of India accept principles mentioned in paragraphs 2, 4 and 6 of your telegram, subject to following conditions (u) In making recommendations for grant of special salary at Rs. 900 per mensem to Political Officers in charge of Divisions or to Deputy Commissioners of Police, lists should in each case be furnished of all officers who are holding less responsible posts and are drawing salary of over Rs. 1,200 a month, with reasons why none of these could be posted to the responsible charge. (b) For purposes of proviso in paragraph 4 of your telegram, comparison should be between (i) pay and allowances, including Mesopotamia ajlowance, admissible to officer under terms of letter from Govern ment of India in Foreign and Est. A., June 1918, Nos. 12 -H. Political Department No. 1006- Est. A., dated 14th May 1918, and (ii) pay and allowances which would have been admissible to officer if he had been employed regimentally with his substantive military rank. 3 . With reference to paragraph 8 of your telegram, your assumption is correct. 4 . Proposals for grant of sumptuary allowances will be duly considered when received. Government of India cannot admit, however, that entertainment of officers in receipt of travelling allowance is sufficient justification.1 deputy 1 of a! ; salary )ite iployed mi of No. 24736—14/46, dated Baghdad, the 6th November 1918. From—B kfvet-Lieutenant-Colonel A. T. Wilson, C.M.G., C.I.E., D.S.O^ Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Beference paragraph 4 of your No. 2194-Est. A., dated 3rd October 1918. 1. I forward a statement of Sumptuary Allowances for which sanction is requested with effect from 1st October 1918. 2. Political Officers and Assistant Political Officers are continually called upon to accommodate and entertain officers of the various Military Departments, eg., Besources, Irrigation, Agriculture, I. W. T., &amp;o., rone of whom draw Travelling Allowance. This undoubtedly results in more effecth e co ordination between the work of the various departments and hence leaf’s directly to more efficient administration of the districts coneernid. It is highly desirable that this should he so and that officers of all depanments should continue to look to Political Officers for help and hospitality when stranded or in difficulties. Moreover Shaikhs and Notables of the various districts have to he entertained and public receptions and similar entertainments given at intervals by Political Officers in charge of Divisions. 1 have therefore after careful enquiry proposed Sumptuary Allowances for certain Political Officeis and Assistant Politic al Officers in independent charge on the main Lines of Communication and I trust that the Government oi India will be pleased to sanction my proposals and inform me by telegraph. 3. In this connection I may mention that the total payments to Political Officers and Assistant Political Officers on account of Travelling Allowance claims during the six months, January to June 1918, are approximately as follows :— . ' , . , '’ y * 1 ifa. Baghdad Wilayat (including Political Officers and 3,010 ^ Assistant Political Officers in Persia). Basrah Wilayat ... ... ... 7,000 As there are now some 200 Gazetted officers of the senior staff, this averages only Bs. ICO per head per annum, an insignificant amount in comparison with the numerous transfers and almost continuous touring which has to be undertaken by officers of the Civil Administration, the bulk of whom are drawing very low salaries in comparison with the very arduous and responsible nature of their work, and the scale of salaries in Palestine, Egypt and India for similar work. 1 Statement* Civil Commissioner ... Military Governor, Baghdad Assistant Political Officer, Kadhimain Political Officer, Samarra Assistant Political Officer, Tikrit ... Political Officer, Kut ... Assistant Political Officer, Hai Political Officer, Dulaim-Bamadi. Political Officer, Billah Assistant Political Officer, Karbala Political Officer, Shamiyah, Najaf Political Officer, Baqubah Political Officer* KhaniqinPolitical Officer, Kirkuk Political Officer, Samawah, Rumaithah ... Assistant Political Officer, Samawah, Eup hrates Political Officer, Basrah - Assistant Political Officer, Zubair Political Officer, Qurnah Political Officer, Amarah ... Assistant Political Officer, Qalat Salih Assistant Political Officer, Ah Gharbi Political Officer, Nasiriyah ... ••• Assistant Political Officer, Saq-al-Shuyukh ... Telegram, No. 2297, dated the 24th February 1919. From—The Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, To T he Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. My despatch, dated November 6th, 24736. Sumptuary Allowance^ f or Political Officers. Will Government of India be pleased to intimate san i n by telegram. I cannot settle terms of employment for officers until orders have been received on this question and that of temparary rank. // ' 'l ' ' ’ Telegram, No. 775-Est. A, dated the 5th March 1919. From—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. Tout letter No. 21733—14/45, 6th November last. _ Sanction accorded to grant of Sumptuary Allowances to Civil Commissioner an 011 Officers as proposed on understanding that allowances are purely p y pending settlement of future administration of occupied territories.11 ® foi foreign and political department. establishment. ■ ‘.Vi acMtid No. 31, DATED THE 16TH APRIL 1919. Letter to Hie Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. Grant of sumptuary allowances to certain officers of the Civil Administration in Mesopotamia.COPY From Mo, 24736. Office of the^Civil Commissioner, Baghdad,the 6th Movemher 1918. 3b.-Lt„-Colone1 A a T. Jilson, C.M.C., C.I.E., L\b.O,, Officiating Civil Commissioner, 1 Baghdad, The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, DELHI, Sir, Reference para. 4 of your Mo. 2194-Est.A,, dated 3rd October 1918, 1. I forward a statement of Sumptuary Allowances for which sanction is requested with effect from 1st October 1918. 2. T.Os and A. ,0s are continually called upon to accommodate and entertain officers of the various Military Departments, e.g. Resources, Irrigation, Agriculture, I.A.T., etc, none of whom draw T.A. This undoubtedly results in more effective co-ordination between the work of the various Departments and hence leads directly to more efficient administration of the districts concerned, lb is highly desirable that this Ishould be so and that officers of all Departments should Icontinue to look to P.Os for help and hospitality when ! stranded or in difficulties. Moreover Shaikhs and i Notables of the various districts have to be entertained and public receptions and similar entertainments given ■: at intervals by Political Officers in charge of Divisions. I have therefore after careful enquiry proposed Sumptuary Allowances for certain P.Os andA.P.os in independent charge on the main Lines of Oornmunicafcion and J trasb/fche Government of India will ue pleased to sanction my proposals and inform me 'by telegraph. in this connection I may mention that the total .payments to P.Os and A„'„Os on account of T.A. claims during the six months January to June 18 are approximately as follows:- r Bag-Mad • ffllayat(including p.os and A. .Os in Persia^ Rs.3,000/- Basrah ,/ilayat Rs.7,000/- As there are now some 200 Gazetted officers of the Senior Staff, this averages only Rs. 100/- per head per annum, an insignificant amount in comparison with the numerous transfers and almost continuous touring which has to be undertaken by Officers of the Civil Adminis tration, the bulk of whom are drawing very low salaries in comparison with the very arduous and responsible nature of their work, and the scale of salaries in Palestine Egypt and India for similar work. I have, efcc., * ^ Sd. A.?. Wilson, Lb.-Colonel, I.A., Offg. Civil Commissioner.1 s OOPY. Telegram* Prom - The Officiating Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, ^o *“ foreign Secretary to the Covernment of India in the Foreign and Political Department,Delhi, Mo* 2297. Dated the 24th(reed* 25th) February 1919. Iviy despatch daoed November 6th, 24736. Sumptuary allowance for Political Officers. Will Government of India be pleased to intimate sanction by telegram. I cannot settle terms of employment for officers until orders have been received on this Question and that of temporary rank. Telegram. From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department,Delhi, To — The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. No. 775-Est.A, Dated 5th March 1919. Your letter No.24736/14/45, 6th November last. Sanction accorded to grant of sumptuary allowances to Civil Commissioner and Political Officers as proposed on understanding that allowances are purely temporary pending settlement of future administration of Occupied territories.r Telegram from Viceroy to the Secretary of S&amp;ate hated 21st. September 1918. Received 23rd September, 7. 30 a.m. 01 *• PriTOt®. Your private telegram of 16th. Instsmt. filson's duties. Goveminent of India exercise control over payment and allowances of officers in Mesopotamia but actual appointments are left to G.O.C. and Civil Commissioner. This is recaignised procedure and it Ms worked satisfactorily. Wilson is therefore quite ■part^to make such arrangements x || : J| x |||||| 2ja(XKX2 xife necessary to relieve pressure-including the appointment of personal assistant and I see from his telegram to you of September of 17th. September that he nas already taken steps in this direction by appointing Howell as his deputy. I do not think any recommendations from me required. But I may add that in consultation with Tehran we are considering question of relieving Wilson of duties of Political Resident Persian Gulf excepting as regards Koweit, Mohammerah and ppossibly Bahrein.Calegram. P. . ' 1 \ '/^ Q irom - iChe Politioal iiesidant in the Persian Sulf, Basra, Po — i'Be Secretary to tite Government of India in the foreign nnd Political Department* Dellii* Ko. 1402. Datdd the 4th heed, the 5th March 1918^ L i \ i- I ' /* I ; V [ ! 3 i 3 On March 6th following will appear in weekly list of appointments Mesopotamian ^Expeditionary Porce. Begins w Prom March ^st. d^rW temporary, absence of hir P.Gox, is appomteTi u o officiate as CJivil Oornmissio Captain Wilson, Deputy Civil^Commissione^in addition to his other duties* Bnds 0 ^ill foreign Department he pleased to issue such notification as they may consider necessary in Gazette of India* Prom Telegram* P* The Secretary to the Government of India in the Poreign and Political Department, Delhi, To —« The Political Resident, Aden* Mo * 253^&gt;. Dated the l£th March 1918* SB following to he kept for Sir Percy Cox* Begins * Wilson* Me do not propose notifying Wilson as acting Civil Commissioner. Specific appointments in Mesopotamia have never been notified hy us since they are not directly under us* In addition to present emoluments however* we think he should receive a charge allowance of say Rs* 500* Do you consider this would he suitable?* Ends * This is with reference to your telegram 1402 March 4th* Telegram R*. Prom - 'The Hon T ble Major-General Sir P*S«Cox,G*C.I*E,iC.C*S*I*, Aden * To The Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, Delhi* Bo.B/41 Dated the 17th March 1918* Reed* the 18th Your telegram 253-3* I concur# - ; U\!&gt;.'W Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. F. 4696. 191 , Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 22nd May, 191.8. Officers employed under local administration in Mesopotamia - proposals of Government of India regarding pensions etc., For concurrence or any observations. (SD.) W.ROBINSON. 22 . 5. 1918. I concur. (SD.) J.E.SHUCKBURGH. 23. 5. 1918. 1983 1271 1000 2/1: —Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department, 1 Register No. p. 324, 191 Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 29th January 1918. T l'o F.O. 1C/3/15 h 783 ' 17/3/1 rom P. Va/Af (s' s. P. 1071 Iff A \ / \J 23209—2 1 1492 1000 11/17 Proposals of (rov^rnraent of India for wound and family pensions ra officers employed m Mesopotamia, Do concur in the draft? It nardly seems necessary to obtain the concurrence of the Foreign Office as the number of cases cannot be large, and the treatment proposed is on the lines of Indian regulations. 7hat is our understanding, please with them as to obtaining their prior consent to expenditure in the occupied territories of Mesopotamia? (Signed) W. Robinson, the draft. I presume •qrmed of the action , oTTour reference, in the A3 1 : juestion of the incidence Ere a of Deen settled reference to of minor questions of officers under the Ho observations.on Foreign Office will be j.n regards the last paiagra 1918, before the genetal qu 1 cost of the provisional administration t had the Foreign Office agreed that no previous them was necessary in thejjfcase temporary appo in tments, un ,i. e s s Foreign bffice were affected. At a later stage, after the government of India had reported that the'revenue and receipts of the occupied territories were being credited to the imperial Government, which was debited with expenditure other than the ordinary pay etc., of officers lent by India, the T 7ar Office ’were informed (1.0. letter 20th April 1916, P. 1003) that it was not proposed.except in imoortant cases, to seek their prior assent before important cases to seeK tneir prior assent before sanctioning recommendations of the Government of India. 1 ’ * 11 Foreign Office and\the iiy, in + n wi of the ?far Office, expressed we address the Foreign The correspondence was communicated to the i i 1 m . - . _ _ ^ ~ ^ .-1 w .-v I'-x . and the Treasury, who raised no objection, position remains as then explained, except that def erence in their le o the wishes of ^ter of 9/5/16, Office, and not the T7ar Office^ expenditure other than military (3d) J. on questions of fresh r :. Shuckbupgh.KG 191 ? . Reference Paper. — Political and Secret Department. Register No. M. 1327 # Referred to tlie Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 4th January, 1918 Proposals of Government of India for wound injury and family pensions re officers employed under local^administration of occupied territory in Mesopotamia. Do you see any objection to the G. of I's proposals bein^ approved? It would perhaps be more convenient if the'paper were transferred to your Department, (SD.) S.F. STEWART. 4. 1. 1918. It is submitted that in.spite of the great length of the telegram, the Government of India’s proposals are none too clear* The objeet : of u the Government of India is (1) to place on the same footing as Military Officers on military duty ^respect of wound, injury and family pensions, any officers, wno may be transferred to service under the Local Administration in Mesopotamia from permanent or temporary service under His Majesty’s Government or the Government of India* The cost of these pensions, it is said, would be recovered from revenues of the Occupied Territories on a capitalised basis to be determined by the Governiment of India Actuary* So far as this proposal is concerned I venture to think that tha Political Department may support it, subject to its consideration : by, the Finance Department from the Financial point of view* The second proposal i&amp; that the Government of India should be given discretionary powers to sanction, in the case or employees of the Mesopotamian Administration who were not previously in Government employ, and would not be^included m the first proposal, a gratuity not exceeding Rs* 1000/- in any one*' instance, such gratuity also being chargeable to the revenues of the occupied territory. Here again, subject to any criticisms by the Finance Department, the political Department supports the proposal* The third proposal depends on what the Government of India mean by ’’Officers referred to in penultimate sentence of paragraph 1”, The paragraph in the telegrams are not numbered, and strictly speaking ”para&lt; 1” would be the first paragraph in the telegram* ButI HU ♦ But this is clearly not meant* If paragraph 1 terminates with the words ”determined by our Actuary M , then this proposal to extend certain miscellaneous sanctioned concessions is meant to apply to the case of officers in permanent or temporary Government service, civil or military, who have been transferred to service under the Local Administration in Mesopotamia and who may be wounded, injured or may die during or as the result of such employment* In other words, officers of this class are to be treated in respect of these concessions, similarly to officers in military employ* I think there is no doubt that this is the intention - (after discussing the point with Mr Joseph) and on this understanding, the Political Department supports the proposal* The fourth proposal is that 'families of private 'servants of officers employed under the Local 'Administration who may oe temporarily attached to 'military force should be eligible for concession in para, '1075 A*R.I* Vol.l* pensions m such cases being changed 'in the same way as other pensions connected with the 'Indian Expeditionary Force'. It is not quite clear to me what this means, Would it apply in the case of &gt;r the Local' Afimini strati on who Line 24 Council jW Ik id '1075 If private followers of a Civilian employed under t might be temporarily attached to a military force as Political Cfiicer? Or must yhe officer be attached to the force for military duty? The Political Department may concur in either case. It will be observed that it is proposed that all the.concessions should have retrospective effect from the commencement,of the occupation of territory in Mesopotamia, and that the Government of India ask for a very early reply* With reference to Mr Stewart’s suggestion that the file might he transferred to the Political Department, it is submitted that the case is one that might more appropriately be dealt with in the Finance Department to whom it mey be passed, with these remarks, servant class, authorised to be taken on active service, are killed or die of wounds or disease attributable to such active servi within one year of their return from such active serviceg their heirs are entitled to pension at the rate of Rs.3/ p.m m *:: (Signed) E.H.S, Clarke, 15/1/18. ! /e-JMGsmflGitngttnK a O' d - JL * J 4( een COPY OF TELEGKAM. Fbom Yioeroy 3 Finance Department Da™ L 5 g , 7Q Received at India Office 151); lOo^m Please refer to correspondenco ending with your telegram dated 8th August, Leave arrangements officers employed on Civil Administration Mesopotamia,, We propose with your approval concession of a similar kind to civil officers serving in civil capacity with ; Expeditionary Force, Mesopotamia^ ^East Africa^ Aden,Egypt Setstan and the Persian Gulf, Free messing on voyage however has been ruled inadmissible in fuh cases vide telegram o - 0 5t r ' July 1?C68 from S^-Cretar Commander-in-Chief in India and we propose It should bo withheld in this case and withdrawn in case sanctioned in your telegram aboveraentioned.TO To Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee^ Under Secretary Secretary of State Council. n L ^ ' U&amp;, Mint tU- £ AM S' ML i- AM$ cCT? 846 ^ COPY OF* teleg: iamJ 7 I 1 j, MWWi From Viceroy, Finance Departimmi-' Dated 28.? 0 1917 Received at India OeficE; 11 p 0 m •?: ^ a O j . u ^ Military Authorities have authorised ^ant of leave India for the period not exceeding one month in each case from date of landing to limited number of officers serving with Indian Expeditionary Force 'D' who have been in the field for 6 months or have undergone special hardships and whose services can be spared without relief from India or extra expense to State; such officers are eligible for free passage by transport to and from Bombay or Karachi and are exempted from payment of messing charges; those proceeding by mail steamer travel at their own expense^ We request sanction to extension of the concession to all officers employed in connection with civil administration of occupied territories who although not invalids require change and rest; such leave ts count as duty but not for privilege leave and not to count against accumulated privilege leave* Proposal' has support of. JLj* n l' h ' 4 :*/* U31 JUL 1917)3 ■■ r v • isfry 30 Jill R M. V » i » u.' 4 /O f' | CE.v Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. ' | I Register No. M.319. Referred to tire Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 4th January, y Basra administration: control of work in the River to be under Director of later Transport. For information. (SD.) R.H.HEADLEY. 4. 1. 1917. Seen. (SD.) A.HIRTZEL. 4. 1. 1917.; 1 , / 1 // / g &gt;• r 03 ^'CX CJ 1 -) Ct i- of fc letter .uo.5384, dated the 12th August, .516, j*|' rroi the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Judicial Home Bepiirtaent. | 46S6 ] I i'9 i 6 V :—: - J' O' &lt;} CO i C-l m a £3 ^ C7X | o w to U— ■ \ ss: b- O i jT t ** o | £3 O CO! c jC u; ca o tt TJ 1 03 1 c3 ] r'Jl ce “ 1 Political Officer at Pasrsh, the Government of Bomba:’ have cursed to provide aoeomr/iod-fion for long term prisoners from irac l 111 T ’^ ^S'ile ir tie Bombay Presidency until suitable v ia_l accoiji ioaatior is avails,..ie' in Irac[ # Such prisoners on vu.^ijvcu, in nCmnay have hitherto ceen sent to jails other than 9t Prisoners Apt, III of 1900. as that section ' ~ 0k;; • ■ u ° Ox romoay unr.er seeilon/does not a A jr ly to the jails in tl-e Presidency-towns. h. It would be convenient, however, for the Government of -hOthj&amp;y to e complete freedom to order the confineme^'t of 7 * V theifprisons from Iraq in any jail in the Bombay Presidency, including those m the Presidency Town. This freedom is es~ peciaily desiraoie when prisoners liE.ve to oe transferred from one prison to anctther for some reason'or other, Huch as the necessity of relieving tie overcrowd.'ng of jails. Moreover, as the Iraq prisoners arrive first in Bombay ffom Basrah by sea, it would he more convenient and less expensive to con- f:ne them in the first imst? nee in one of the Bombay City Jails. 3. The I.emenbranc-er of legal Affairs to the Government cf Bombay advise? that, if the Criminal Coutts at Basrah are ertp'owered by Order in Council or otherwise to commit prison- rn. sentenced by them to prisons in British India, their committal to a prison in the Presidency Towb/i v/ilj be lawful under section 3 of the Prisoners Act. A copy of his opinion is attached, Tiie Government of Bombay, however, have no information whether .the Basrah Courts have been so empowered, or what Order in Council regulates criminal justice at Basrah, 1 am tnerei ore to request tnat the Cfovernment of India riiay be V moved to favour the Bombay Government with the necessary inf ormation. .-Cl C otiv Opinion of the Keniembrancer of legal Affairs, No. 1471 dated the 6th June 1916. ’ } It the Sessions Court, Basrah, is empowered, by Order in Council or otherwise, to commit prisoners sentenced by it ' A; prisons in rritish India, section 3 of the Prisoners Act, -iwLw, wmi., i turn:., ply ana coKmittal to a prison In the Presidency-town will be lawful. 2, Can the Judicial Department inform me that Order in Council regulates criminal justice at Basrah since the out break of the war? As Basrah is or was in the Ottoman domi nions, the Ottoman Order in Council, 1910 (Gazette of India 1110, part I, p.1273) used to apply, and clause 65 enabled the Supreme Court (At Constantinople) to direct that sen tences should be carried out within His Majesty’s dominions. ■ i hr Phis provision, however, cannot take effect during the war f; ,U:&lt; m 'I Co V X J &lt;0 • ■ i rom r To foive Tope rtrnont, (Political*} P. Booth- ravel; ; Esu, ^ - put; 8ecrett ry to the. P-ovarnnant of India, The Secretary to the dovernnent of Bonbay ,&gt; Judicial I) pertment. Simla. ; the 4th Octo-er 1916. I am directed to invite a reference to your letter ho 5364, dated t e 12th Auyuf.t 1916, ren,iesting infomatior a fKc to the authority exorcioo' hy^Criminal Courts at Basrah to com. it p risoners sentenced by them to prisons in British I: cl 6. reply I an i it of India, are aware no such authority has been formally conferred on these courts, but the;- consider that in sending prisoners to jails in the Bombay Presidency, the Basrah Courts are ^ x ably acting under the general authority of Lis Bajssty '.vithin tiie meaning of section 15 {l] (a) of the Prisoners .Act inotg (ill of 19CC) , and that officers in charge of prisons outside the Presidency towns can therefore give effect to warrants issued by those courts. They do not think, however, tn.t it would be legal to commit such prisoners direct to a ja:j i' tl. Presidency-town 5n the manner contemplated by the Ilemem brancer of LegalMfairs to the Crovernment of Borrbav, as in their opinion the word ,f court ft in section 3 of the Act must be constru meaning only- British Indian Courts. They consider, therefor), that, while the transfer of these prison ers to a jail ; n tie Presidency-town fron: a jail outside can be effected under section 29(2) of the Prisoners Act, not! ing oho a. t of an amendment, ox one Act can autnorise oificers in charge of Presicien&amp;y-town jails to receive prisoners direct from Iraq.,'i In view of the fact that prisoners in c..nd outside the Presidency-towns 6re dealt with in separate parts cf the Prisoners Act, it would be inconvenient to amend sectio: 15 bp itself without touching the construction of the Act as a whole, I these circumstance? I an to say that, while re- cognising the advisability of abolishing the exist ing dis- tinction oetwaien prisons in and outside ^residency-towns. the C-ovem,ient of Indie are of opinion that sufficient necessity dess not exist for immediately revisin'' the Act, and suggest that the existing arrangements, under which these prisoners are committed to jails outside the Presidency town and car ^e su’-ser-ently transferred, if necessary, to jails in it, should be continued until the revision of tine Act can be undertaken. I have, etc., Deputy Secretary to the G-ovarment of India, Sdy - V .'. ootli-C rave ly,Ix 2i004 1 995 10,000 8/16 COPY OF TELEGRAM,, , c_ From Viceroy (Finance Department) Dated 4 Deptomoer Received at London Office 1916, Your telegram dated 21st August regarding languages Lie sopot ami a was repeated to Cox who replies as follows;- Begin©. All records manuals and registers of Turkish Regime are in Turkish and reference to them will be necessary for some time to come. Consider it essential that officers should have sufficient knowledge of Turkish to check translations and reports based on records. For instance Bullard ? s knowledge of Turkish has been invaluable. Besides numerous officials of Turkish Regime now serving us are more familiar with Turkish than Arabic. Not question of encouraging Turkish for any purpose but merely of meeting requirements of existing conditions. Ends . In'above circumstances knowledge of Turkish would appear necessary for some time to come.32s (7wk) \ I V, \s i ^ i O COPY OF TELEGRAM“ FROMYiceroy Finance Department* Dated 16th August 1916* Received at London Office x 20942 1 933 5000 7/16 Language examinations Mesopotamia. Official duties of officers employed in civil administration leave them no leisure to acquire literary knowledge of Persian and Arabic required for examination by the High Proficiency Standard^and thus render concession sanctioned in your Despatch dated 31st March (Political) No. 14 practically nugatory. At the same time no provision exists for examination of civil officers in Turkish. We propose therefore^as purely temporary expedient^subject to reconsideration on conclusion of hostilities^to institute local proficiency examination in Turkish,Persian ; and Arabic^ for all gazetted officers in civil employ.Mesopotamia on strictly practical and colloquial lines^and to suspend locally existing higher standard test in Persian and Arabic rtferza ) iump sum reward of Rs. 1,000 to be given for qualification in Turkish and Arabic^and Rs.800 for Persian^with monthly allowance of Rs.100 for language first passed^and of Rs.50 for each of two subsequent languages^,which will not be drawn however until full reward has been recouped in case of first language and half reward in caae of second and third. Officers already qualified in Persian or Arabic by high proficiency or degree of honour, or who are first class interpreters in Persian Arabic or Turkish,will be debarred from proficiency test^but first class interpreters will be entitle^to proficiency allowances. We attach the greatest importance to practical knowledge of local vernaculars on the part of all civil officers in Mesopotamia^and trust therefore that the above proposalsynrhich have Cox’s support^will receive your sanction. f* I i r r ir^- V / mnr POLITICAL. HO. 14. ir v v TO HIS EXCELLENCY THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE GOVERNOR GENERAL OF INDIA IN COUNCIL. My Lord, Having considered in Council your letter in the Finance Department, No.2, of the 1st January, 1916, I sanction your recommendation that, as a temporary measure and subject to reconsideration after a period of 3 years, the language allowances at the rate of Rs.100 per mensem which were granted to Political Officers in 1904 should be extended, so far as they relate to AraJoic and Persian., to all classes of gazetted officers in civil employ in Mesopotamia, whether temporary or permanent, subject to the condition that the combined allowance for proficiency in the two languages shall not exceed Rs.150 per mensem. I have etc., (Sd.) AUSTEN CHA1BERLAIN.No* 2 of 1916. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. PAY, ALLOWANCES AND FINANC E OFFICERS. Language Rewards and Language Allowances. The Right Honourable AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Delhi) the 1st January 1916, Sir, We have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with the despatch No. 132 (General), dated 28th July 1904, in which the Govern ment of India reported the standard tests that had been prescribed as those which should he passed in order to entitle officers of the Political department serving in certain localities outside India to draw the allowances sanctioned by His Majesty’s Government for proficiency in Arabic, Persian, Chinese, Russian and Tibetan. 2. In accordance with the sanction referred to, allowances for profi ciency in Arabic, Persian and Russian have been admitted to qualified Political officers serving in the following localities in the Persian Gulf and adjoining countries:— Arabic.—Arabia and the Persian Gulf littoral, Persian.—Persia and at Baghdad. Russian.—Persia and the Persian Gulf littoral. It was also decided at the time that, for the purpose of the allowance granted for proficiency in Arabic, Turkish Arabia should he regarded as included in Arabia. 3. The recent occupation of the Basrah Wilayat by our troops and our consequent assumption of the provisional administration of the country have made it highly desirable that the officers of the various civil departments who are at present concerned with the administration should be^ encouraged to acquire a knowledge of the languages spoken by the people. The case of the officers of the Political department is already met by the rules in force, but there are many classes of officers, judicial, police, medical, survey, &amp;c., who are outside the scope of these rules, and it is with a view to encouraging officers of these classes to acquire as speedily as possible a knowledge of Arabic and Persian that we consider that the concession at present applicable to Political officers should be extended to all gazetted officers in civil employ. Arabic is the language of the country, hut Persian is also widely spoken and is of almost the same utility as Arabic. Russian, on the other hand, is in no sense a language of the country and its acquirement by civil officers employed in the ordinary administration of the southern portion of the Basrah Wila} at is not necessary. We recommend, therefore, for your favourable consideration, that • j vij i li % &gt;1the payment of allowances at the rate of Rs. 100 per mensem granted in 1901 to Political officers may be extended, so far as they relate to Arabic and Persian, to all classes of gazetted officers in civil employ in Mesopotamia, whether temporary or permanent, subject to the condition that the combined allowance for proficiency in the two languages may not exceed Rs. 150 per mensem. 4. We propose that this measure be treated as temporary only and that it may be sanctioned up to three years, at the end of which period the matter can be reconsidered in the light of developments in the administration of Mesopotamia, and any necessary modification can be introduced. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servants, (Signed) BEAUCHAMP DUFF. W. H. CLARK. R. H. CRADDOCK. W. a MEYER. C. H. A. HILL. C. SANKARAN NAIR. G. R. LOWNDES.b-’ GOTERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. PAY, ALLOWANCES AND FINANCE OFfC RS. Language Rewards and Language Allowanci i [)3? OF^ 1 lo» 1 * From The GOVERNMENT of INDIA, To The SECY, of STATE foe INDIA. No. 2. Dated Delhi t the 1st January 1916, Deceived Grant of allowances for proficiency in Arabic and Persian to all civil gazetted officers serving in Mesopotamia. F. &amp; P. Dept, Press—No. 1791—23.12.15-54,jrUJT , m. 1. Ti t ill am^mn rm nmirr mmo mm tm oommon €i, OF IhJiA m ^nmn UQT&lt;l t l forward herewith, far the infonmtion of four -AXcelXency* $ i*ovemao«t f a copy of a letter fro t the General i ott office on the subject of an announce oent thro^ch the internatioml bureau of the iotial Union at Berne relative to the tranwraiceion of insured parcels to the British Indian Post Gfflees at certain places in Mesopotamia. i agree with the root Easier General in I con oiler in it mid esi ruble to mkn anno i mcemcn t a through the i ureau in re uiu t,o rasters ox aerau in posmx service^ to places in occupied territory about which there has been no fomal declaration of anneratioru l request, however, that infem^tioa in such mtters my be communicated to this office and the General lost Uffice* 1 tots the honour to be.89696/15, GSfcmi. K)3T QfriCS, U 3 KD 0 K. 19th mY 1916. Sir, 1 am directsd by the Poatmaster General to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in .council, that an announcement has been -tide by tne Indian Poet Office to the effect that injured parcels cannot be transmitted to the British Indian Post Offices at, among other places, Araara, Nateriyeh, 4ulat Saleh and 5uk«esh-8heyukh in Mesopotamia, t’his announcement is addressed, throu,'-h the international Bureau of the Postal Union at Berne, to ioetal administrations participating; in the Parcel Post service of the iostal Union, and is contained in a Circular letter dated the 1st instant. i M intimation appears to liave been received | ' from the Indian Post office of the opening of Agencies at the j places mentioned, althou^ with the exception of .^nlat Saleh j j their names appear in the list of Indian lost Offices given in t&gt;l ‘ 5 A P ril ’ ]&lt; Iition of the Indian Post office Guide for this j ? mr &gt; ai1fl H appears that they are included in the Indian Inland iostal System, In ordinary circumstances, those places would now be due to be included in the Imperial Penny Post: but it seems to the Postmaster General to be of doubtful propriety to riake announcements throu h the International Bureau of the Postal Union at Berne about |5ie under secretary of dtate, matters India Office.231 ^3^ ? m 4- 1 m ■ &amp; | mtter. of detail in the petal service to places in occupied territory about which there has been no formal declaration ol annexation; and in accordance with the iJ ' lentionqd in the letter from this Office of the 19th of October last, ho.217521. concerning the postage on letters for Bushire. no fonsal steps will be taken in the -natter by this Office during tne %r. With the exception of military correspondence which is subject to special rates. i- id probaole that very little correspondence for the places mentioned will be posted in the United Kingdom; but any paid at tne penny rate will be passed without surcharge. a copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. 1 am, &amp;c, (3d.) i. D. FaI’ A.,jL.Reference Pajfer . 1 aWay Letter No. P.W.I 345 . Department. * Referred to Political Secretary vf Rec. 191 20 th May 1916 Transmission of insured parcels to B.I.Post Offices in Mesopotamia . Proposal not to make announcement through the International Bureau of the Postal Union at Berne. Letter from G.P.O lor concurrence or any observations (Sd. )HXA.. Haines I concur, (Sd.) A.Hirtzel. 22.5.16. P</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/516/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/516/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4097/1914 Pt 4 'Mesopotamia: administration; personnel; miscellaneous general questions re allowances, leave etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1921</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-10T16:28:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (107 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.The subject 4097 (Basra and Mesopotamia) consists of 5 files, IOR/L/PS/10/513-517. The files are divided into 7 parts, with parts 1, 2, 3 comprising one file each, parts 4, 5 comprising the fourth file and parts 6, 7 comprising the fifth file.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part of the file contains correspondence relating to the hiring of civilian staff at Baghdad from Egypt or India following the British occupation of Iraq during the First World War.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100054608681.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>