<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000c2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:09:46.633Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Cover for Enclosures in Weekly Letter No. dated from Secretary, Political and Secret Department, India OfiRce, to Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Government of India. * AFGHA NISTAN * - —- . (66754) Wt. 5577—1244 14,000 7;28 H. St. G. 101/19B. (UEGIBENT.)439b 1 mYARD teleoram ! 28599* Allotted to E ^bernalLQl^S arti^int —'' , ii1 ' ^ C OTTPI PS K T'X A Ij GOD JT : TELEGRAM Government of India, External Affairs Department Secretary of State for India. New Delhi* 16*55 hours, 3rd September 1945 14-30 hours, 3rd September 1945. Donaldson from Caroe. Mcynihan has written me on Peel’s advice asking for pur good offices in facilitating his return home via Afghanistan and Persia- There will be difficulties to overcome but I am prepared to try if M. is expected to return to External Department or if for other reason you think there would be public advantage in journey# I Rite. ML. DEPT. | | -{SEPms I INDIA OFFICE!</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000c2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1023</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000c2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1023</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 4395/45 'Moynihan - Travelling facilities'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-05T22:04:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of correspondence between the External Affairs Department (Government of India) and the Secretary of State for India regarding travel plans for Mr Moynihan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0000c2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>