<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100062720639.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-12T17:05:44.221Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100062720639.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 12151</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100062720639.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 12151</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>al-Mufradāt المفردات  Shāhīn ibn Jirjis شاهين بن جرجس</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1700/1799</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-25T22:04:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. iv+152+v</extent><extent>Material: Western laid paperDimensions: 200 x 130 mm leaf [160 x 85 mm text frames]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencil; the tables on ff. 26v-141v, which comprise an opening each, are numbered in red and green ink in the upper edge corners of versosRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 21 lines per page; vertical spacing 14 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Naskh; the scribe is Yūsuf Ṣayfī (يوسف صيفي, see f. 152v, lines 1-5)Ink: Black ink, with headings and punctuation in red and green (some gold on first opening, ff. 1v-2r); and black red, green and blue in tables (ff. 26v-141v)Decoration: All folios with text are framed in red ink (2v-19r, first opening ff. 1v-2r in black and gold);Binding: British Museum half-leather bindingCondition: Minor tide marks at tail towards front of volume, some stains and smudges, all folios guardedMarginalia: Very fewSeals: ff. 1r and 152v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Treatise on medicine and diatetics mostly composed of 115 tables (ff. 26r-141r). The work is preceded by an introduction to the tables and general medical principles. Tables of synonymous drug names are found on ff. 144r-152r. The tables at least are attributed to the otherwise unknown Shāhīn ibn Jirjis (شاهين بن جرجس, see ff. 26r and 152v). A dedication to the
                           amīr‘Alā’ al-Dīn Abū al-Shujā‘ Dhū al-Qarnayn ibn ‘Izz al-Dawlah ibn al-amīr Ghāzī, known as the 'Power of the Prince of the Faithful (i.e. of the Caliph)' (علاء الدين أبو الشجاع ذو القرنين بن عز الدولة بن الأمير غازي عزة أمير المؤمنين, ff. 1v, line 15-2r, line 8).The copy was produced for the principal student of the teacher (i.e. of the author, التلميذ الرئيس للمعلم, f. 1r).The seal and inscriptions of the same Yūsuf Ṣayfī who owned this manuscript are also found in MSS Or. 12142, 12143, 12146, 12149, 12150, 12153, 12154, 12155, 12156 and 12157. Yūsuf Ṣayfī was a Christian: in an inscription dated 1258/1842-3 he states that he is Orthodox (Or. 12146, f.1r), while in an inscription dated [12]62/1845-6 (the same year the present manuscript was completed) he states that he is Catholic (Or. 12143, f.1r).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):إن أول ما افتتح به الخطاب وأجمل ما ابتدئ بهالكتاب التعظيم لله والتنوية بأسمائهوالشكر لآلائه والحمد على نعمائه ...Colophon (f. 152v, lines 1-3):تم المجلدالمبارك الموسوم بالمعلمشاهين المذكور</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100062720639.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>