<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T11:22:10.922Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. LIST SHOWING THE names, titles and modes of address OF THE more important sovereigns, ruling princes, chiefs, nobles, etc., having relations with the indian government. alqabnamah. Corrected up to the 5th October 1935. NEW DELHI: P j RINTEI) BY THE MANAGER, GOVMtNMENT OF INDIA PRESS: IMSCONTENTS. PagM. r '&gt;« t ; ; i-a A.— List of Independent States 2 5 B.—List of Protectorate Rulers 8 17 C.—List of Euling Princes and Chiefs in India 20—i6f f &amp; % $ D.—Miscellaneous no 115 Note. When a Ruling Prince or Chief writes in English only, the answer should go in English only. Wh ^ n ^ , Rul i ng Q Pri r or is o addressed i not » answer to a letter, no Persian translation is to go smlees ordered by the Secretary or Deputy Secretary. IThis does not apply to States outside India.A.—List of Independent States. JLIST OP INDEPENDENT Name of State, 13 SIAM TIBET 4 TIBET Name and address in English. His Majesty Ananda Mahidol, King of Siam, Upholder of the Buddhist Faith. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and cdlour of Crest. Your Majesty. I am, Your Majesty's sincere friend. Crest, Gold. The Exalkd Presence of Lotus-fdioted Golden throne of che Great Kstting Huiuktu, the Eegent of Tihet, the Protector \nd Bene factor of all the Hiving beings of the Snowy Country. y * (/ p fit-fLcCax 0JU. /&amp; Viceroy and Governor-General of India. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhwah. (Gold and silk brocade.) 2 String (Dorij—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) fKs-Seremty-Penehea-E^eH^ Tubden oho hyi nyi.mn G p ip^nam-^takpal-fiabg-po, thn Tfinhi rinma-of-Shigatafl. ¥ett£-S«Fe»ity. 'Vinnrny fi nrrnir I nd ia. Grtsi, Gold. K7 B.—List of Protectorate RulersLIST OF PROTECTORATE a o 52, Name of State or place of residence. BHUTAN . l.r. CHITSAL Name and address in English. /H His Highness Mahagaja ^i Oil grl 8ri Sri-Sir .Tigms WtmjjuLuk,' JT.C'J.Ji'., M&amp;haraja ot— fa^vJAc , /C c /S Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. My friend. I remain, Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita tag—Kamkhwab. (GoJd and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar, (Gold and silk thread.) His—Highimi's—Mohtai 1 Sir SlmliRil-Mlllk. TT (I T 77 , Hat addfuuuud in lui'llgft. , , - J A/ ^ f JCtA**~ocL&lt;L/ W**- ia bag—'White fong-cloth.^i^ String (Dori)—(Silk thread).10 LIST OF PROTECTORATE Name of State or place of residence. HUNZA. Nair.e and addreaa of Ruler in English. C' #■£ Mir jfrif Muhammad Naaim Khan, Mir of- M A SCAT AND OMAN Jc*, ^ % J&amp;c- Hie HIgbneBS Saijid Said bin Swyid Taimur) Sultan of— lot. Commencement and Conclurion of letter in English and colour of Crest. Not addressed in English. Kharita bag—Cloth-lined envelope. My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider ation which I entertain for Your Highness, and to subscribe myself, Tour Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String (Dori)—Purzar. (All gold thread). For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Doril —Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread. T14 LIST OF PROTECTORATE! Name of State or place of residence. a 12 BAHRAIN . 13 14 QATAR Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. His Highness shaikh Sir Persian bin IicJIlciQ. cil~Kh.&amp;liX sfcl My esteemed friend. K.C.I.E. , Ruler of Bahrain. _ -— 1 remain with much consideration, Tour EKooncwcj^s sincere friend. Crest i Gold, KUWAIT . His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmed al Jabir As-Subah. K. C.S.I. 5 K.C.I.E. , Ruler of Kuwait. Ditto* His Excellency Shaikh .all My£rieni bin tibdullah Al Thani, .iuier J Of a tar. I remain, with much ConsideratiOfl/ Your Excellency's sincere friend.16 LIST OF PROTECTORATE 15 16 17 18 19 20 Name of State or place of residence. abu dhabi Name and address in English. a j man DIBAI eas-ul-khaimah shaegah umm-ul-qaiwain Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. His Excellency Shaikh Shakhbat bin Su 11an, Huler Not addressed ia English, of Abu Dhabi. PERSIAN Shaikh Rashid bin Humaid, Ruler of Ajman. Shaikh Said bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dihai Shaikh Saqr bin Mohammed bin Salim, Ruler of Ras- al-Khaimah, Shaikh Sultan bin Saqar, Euler of Shargah n £ * A ./ ♦&gt; Shaikh Ahmed bin Rashid, Ruler of 0mm-al-Qaiwain Zl\ Kplba* 'J ^ /V'(rvv-v ScL^si. Ditto. Ditto. Dittos Ditto. •Ditto.17 RULERS. Highest British authority by ■wLom hitherto addressed. ' No. of Guns. Name and address in Persian or Arabic. a ® fl e8 a ® Personal. Remarks. GULF— contd. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. [Mutatis mutandis for all Trucial Chiefs) *3 t5 * Local. Fired by British ships of war in the Persian Gulf at the termination of an official visit by this Ruler, t F. No. 72-N. of 1929. toUO- — lasvJ) Ditto . U| •3 ... ♦Ditto, Ditto Laj) *5 ••• ♦Ditto. Ditto . . Uj *3 • •• ♦Ditto. Ditto Laj) ♦3 £ 1 ♦Ditto, Ditto . Lajf ♦3 ♦Ditto. J - 4* - // - J19 4 !■ C.—List of Ruling Princes and Chiefs in India with their titles and modes of Address. | ' i I. All personal titles are printed in italics. II. Tlie title of ' His Highness' is prefixed to tlie names of all Rulers enjoying salute of not less than 11 guns.20 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name o£ State. Name and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conchsion of letter in English and colour of Crest. I.-R¥lJN« PRiNCES-ANI) CfH&amp;FS lN~POLITt€AL KALAT jQaptmn* His Highness Beglar Begi/ Mir Ahmad Yar Khan, Kh&amp;nVof— / £•- /-J' LAS BE LA Mir Qhnlam Muluimiaad Khaa, Jam of— I.—BALUCH My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider ation which I entertain for Tour Highness, and to subscribe myself, Tour Highness 5 sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—KarakWab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Doril—Nimzar. (Gold and Silk thread.) My honoured and valued friend. After compliments I write to say that By the favour of God I am in good health and trust that you my friend and those connected with you are in the enjoyment of good health.22 LIST OF RULING PRINCES 525 Name of State. AJAIGARH ALIPURA . ALI-EAJ PUR . BANKA PAHAEI BAONI Commen&lt;!ement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. I.—RUL1NQ PBINGB8 AND-CHIEES M POLITICAL II—CENTRAL His Hi^ Bahadur, Maharaja Sawai.Bhupal Singh ia of— L JiatT Raghuraj Singh, Rao of— : His Highness JStttrfiT' Sir Pratap Singh, K. C. I. E., Raja f of— Diwan Baldeo Singh, Jagirdar of- His Highness A'zam-ul-Uniara Iftikhar-ud- Danlah, Imad-ul-Mulk Sahib-i-Jah Mihin Sardar Nawab Muhammad Mushtaq-ul-Hasan Khan, Safdar Jang, Nawab of— My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My friend. I remain. Your sincere friend. A' v/. r V -Bitto y - . .y Qf^oC oii^a^O-n, / . . -Difeter- my esteemed friend. I remain, with much cons 1 deration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)( 24 LIST OF RULING PRINCES i Name of State. ] 10 11 12 BAEATINDHA * (PATHAB KACHHAS). BARWAN1 BERI • BHAISAUNDA BHOPAL Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencetnent an-l Conclnsion of letter in English and colour of Crest. . JUro Lokendra Singh, Rao of- FRiiSCES AND CHIEFS IN POLITICAL II.—CENTRAL Raja Ram Pratap Singh, Raja of — His Highness Rana Devi Singh, Rana of— i*. My filuiiir Your Hio-hnpa*' &amp;ru syi ^ - Mj friend I remain, Tour sincere friend. Chauhey Govind Pars ad, Jagirdar of— /^yoi Jjivuknunt Ovionil J His Highness Iftikhar-nl- Mulk § Sikandar Saul at § Nawab Haji /SkVlf Muhammad Hamidulla Khan Bahadur, a.C.LE., C .r .O., Nawab of- My friend. I remain, Your sincere friend. Ditto. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Eharita bag—-Kamkhwab. |6old and silk brocade.) String (Dorij—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary: Kharita bag—Eamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar (Gold and silk thread.)26 LIST OF RULING PRINCES a {23 Name and address of Kuler in English. ComiBencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. 18 14 25 17 BIHAT BIJAWAR BUNA CHAEKHARI . CHHATARPUB , I.—Erb-jLl-NG miWEU Al^JJ UHlEJb 1 ^ 1-N—PGtmCAL II.—CENTRAL Rao Bir Singh Ju Deo, Rao of— His Highnes s Mahar aja Sawai &amp;ii fl^WHOit Singh Bahadur, KJJJL i JH -., Maharaja of— Diwan Himmat Singh, Jagirdar of— His Highness Maharajadhiraja Pipahdar-ul-Mulk Arimardan Singh Ju Deo Bahadur, Maharaja His HijshnesiB Maharaja* Bhatrani Singh Baha dur, Maharaja of— My friend. I remain, Your sincere friend. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) Siring (Don)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My friend. I remain, Your sincere friend. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much coneideraticm, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori) —Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary i Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread). My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Khavita bag—Kaml?hw4b. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nirnzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag - Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)28 ci r&amp; S D 28 19 20 21 22 23 24 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Commencement and Conclusion Name of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. of letter in English and colour of Crest. DATIA DEW AS (Seniob Bbakch) DHAR DHUEWAI GAEAtTLI . GA.UBIHAR His Highness Mxharaja Lokendra Sir My esteemed friend. Govind Singh Bahadur, G.C.I.E., K,C.S.I., Maharaja of— DEWAS (Juniob Beanch) AMU LUIEFa IN POLITICAL II.—CENTRAL I remain, with much Consideration, Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhw&amp;h. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. ( (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary: Kharita hag—Kamkhwah. (Gold and silk hrocade.) String (Deri)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) So- My esteemed friend. His Hiehnesa Maharaj^5t/''Tukuji Xiao Puar, K.C.S.I., Maharaja of—- His Highness Maharaja Sadashiv Rao Khase Saheb Puar, Maharaja of— I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwah. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend, I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) 'His Highness MaharajaJ Anand Eacr Puar, My esteemed friend. Maharaja of — Diwan Jugal Pershad Singh, Jagirdaf of— I remain, with much consideration, Your Higuness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold' Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori(—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My friend. I remain. Your sincere friend. Diwan Bahadur Chandrabhan Singh, Jagirdar of— . Pandit Avadhentra Pratap Singh, Jagirdar of— Ditto, Ditto.30 LIST OF RULING PRINCES 'a 0 N ame of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in Englisli and colour of Crest. 25 INDORB . His Highness Maharajadhiraja Raj RajesWar Sawai Shri Sir I Yeshwant Rao Holkar Bahadur,*' Gr.C.LJE., Maharaja of— 26 JAOEA l.-RPLH^Kglg^eis'^P- CHIEFS IH rOLITICAL II.—CENTRAL My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider ation which I entertain for Your Highness, and to subscribe myself, Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String (Dori)—Purzar. (All gold thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) ^Lieutenant-Colonel His Highness Fahhr-ud- Daulah\\ Nawab Sir Muhammad I ftikhar A li Khan Bahadur, Saul at Jang,\\ K.CJ.BT, My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)32 i LIST OP RULING PRINCES Name of State. a &amp; 27 JASO . JHABUA . 29 JIGNI . . 80 31 KHILCHIPUR . 32 KOTHI 33 LUGASI . Name and! address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest, I.—RULING- PRINCES AND CHIEFS IN PQLITiQAL II.—CENTRAL Diwan Ram Pratap Singh, Dhvan of— . His 7?y '/je */&gt; i. Raja of— Rao Bhupendra Yijay Singh, Rao of— KAMTA RAJ AULA . . Rao Radha Krishna, Rao of— Raja* Rao Bahadurf Durjan Sal Singh, Raja of- Raja Bahadur Kaushalendra Pratap Bahadur Singh, Raja of— Diwan§ Bhupal Singh, Jagirdar of— My friend. I remain. Tour sincere friend. My-ttBSa. *~eC I remain, Cewji Your Highness' sincere friend. My friend. I remain. Tour sincere friend* Ditto • Ditto Ditto Ditto33 AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authoriiy oy whom hitherto Name and address of Ruler in Persian, KBLATIQNS WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF INIH-^con^. IND Ik—contd. Agent to the Qovernor- &amp;.gent to tt General. * Ditto . *£ ICe, Ditto . , Ditto . Ditto Ditto Ditto No. of guns. Ph 11 f f ^,1,, ^ L ^b * i J a juo, ♦The hereditary title of ' Raja ' Was conferred on the 4th June 1928. fConferred in 1873 as a hereditary distinction by the Government of India. JPol. A., January 1879, Nos. 73-76. The hereditary title of ' Raja Baha dur ' was conferred by the Govern ment of India on the 1st January 1878. ^Vide Internal A., September 1898. No. 192.34 u &lt;d 'a 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 LIST OP RULING PRINCES Name of State. MAIHAR . MAKEAI . NAGOD ( ob UNCHEHEA) . NAIGAWAN EEBAI NAESINGAEH . OECHHA . PA HE A PALDEO Name and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. I.—EULTNG ritlNUEU Ai^i; CiiilLjjb i^ULiTfe^ 11.—CENTBAL Sir Brij Nath Singh, X.C.LJFJ., Eaja of—* ' jjy friend. I remain, Your sincere friend. Eaja Todar Shah Hathiya Eai, Eaja of— Raja Mahendra Singh, Eaja of— Kunwar Vishwanath Singh, Jagirdar of- His Highness Eaja BingL, Hdjd,—of* jt-d - / *£ ^ - ' His Highness Saramad-i-EajahayS-Bundelkhand Sawai Mahondra Maharaja Shri/^ir Singh Deo Bahadui-jiMaharaja of— .... Chante Laxmi Prasad, Jagirdar cf— Chaube Shiv Prasad, Jagirdar of— My esteemed friend. Tour sincere friend. My friend. I remain. Your sincere friend. Ditto My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness'sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration^ Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary; Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String fDori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My friend. I remain. Your sincere friend. Ditto35 (y AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority i,y whom hitherto ad iresseu. Name and address of Ruler in Persian, EOLATIONS WITH THE QOVEIiNMLNT OP INDIA^u^. INDIA—cc&gt;»/d* Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto No. of Guns. i} r 9» The hereditary title of w Raja' was conferred by the Government of India on the 4lh February 1869, ♦Pol. A-, February 1878, Nos. 464r-468 and Pol. A., January 1879, Nos. 73—75. The use of the title of ' Hathiy^Rai' was sanctioned on the 15th June 1899. Remarks. Ditto Ditto 'V'TfTOY RTld ^'• tTOVr '' v - //•/. Ditto Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto J'Sjy* (jAb,* ' ||i| ixK/» kL ^ jMt 6 wbj — c W ' w r &gt;|^sxoi' dkyL ^ 6 ^ ji) In 1879, the Government of India authorised the style of address used in communications from the Viceroy to the Maharaja of Orehha baing changed to ' Maharaja Siahib Mushfik Mihrban ' (Politicaj A., November 1879, Nos. 851-352). The title of ' Sawai' was confemd on the 24th May 1882, and that of ' Saramad i- Rajah-i-Bundel' khand ' on the 29th June 188Q (I. A., July 1886, Nos. 46—50). The State is in future to be officially designated as Orchha only, and not as Orchha or Tehri (Notification No. 5027-1., dated 2nd December 188f).33 LIST OF RULDCG PRINCES Name of State. 53 42 PANNA 43 EAJGARH . 44 EATLAM Name and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclnsion of letter in English and colour of Crest. His Highness Maharaia Mahendra Sir Yadvendra '• Singh Eahad.r, K.C.SJ; K.C.LZ,, Maha raja of— I.-PRINCES AND CHIEFS IN PQfct^eAL II.-CENTliAL My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Drri)—Nimzar. (Gold and sik thread.) For letters from the Secretary: Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (TVui)—Nimzar, (Gold and silk thread.) His Highness Eaia* Sir- Dk liidra Hiugk, fa JZ&amp;kffLeV^ His Highness Maharaja Sir Sajian Singh, a.CJ.E., K.C.SJ., K.C.y.O r Maha raja J of - r ,v.y jyiana- My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dor!)—Nimzar. (Gold and siik thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Fieri)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)38 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name of State. rO l ^5 45 KEWA Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in Knglish and colour of Crest. P rviNCEg ANU CHi-HF ^ULi'litAL His Higlipes? Mah^rajadhii'aj^* S\r Gulab ^ingh Babadur, ty.C.l.E., K.C.S.J., Maharaja of— II.-CENTRAL My esteemed friend. I remain yilb mucb consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kbarita bag—Kamkbwab. (li old and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters fipm the Secretary : Kbarita bag Kamkhwab, (Gold and silk brocade.) String (D^ij—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) 46 SAILANA 47 SAMTHAR JV kc.'.t- His Highness Raja^Dileep Singh^Raaof — His Highness —Bfthndm' Radita ChafSfi Singh, Jp ea My esteemed friend. I remain, vfith much consideration, Your ^fighness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab (Gold and silk brocade.) Stiing (Dorij)—.Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread ) My esteemed friend. I remain, with mucb confideraticn, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. *yw. (Gold and silk brocade.) Stiing (Dorjj- Nim ar. (Gold and silk thread.; For letters from the Secretary : Khurita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)-Nimzar. &lt; (Gold and silk thread.)40 LIST OF RULING PRINCES S3 Name of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. I.—EgjaiiiitGi rnmc'Efl AITD CHIEFS I:^ POLiTieA^ CJJ II.-^CENTRAL 48 SARILA . . Raja Mahipal Singh, Raja of— A My friends I remain, Your sincere friend. 49 SITAMAU. His Highness Raja'S'tf Ram Singh, K,C.I.E., Raja of— My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwah. (Gold and silk brocade^) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk threads) , w SOHAWAL Raja* Jogendra Bahadur Singh, Raja of— &lt;L My friend. I remain. Your sincere friend. 61 TAEAON , , , . BltW 62 TOEI f ATEHPUE . Bao Bahadur fDiwan Arjun Singh, Jagirdar of— Ditto41 AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. Name and address of Euler in Persian. MBLATIONg WITH. THJlj OF iyDIA--c Qw fr? t INDIA—co»c/&lt;f. Agent to the Governor- General. No. of Guns. Tieoroy amd—Qcivtixirer- //•^ Agent to the Governor- General I&gt;itto l)itto Ph Remarks. 11 The privilege of exchanging kharitas with the Viceroy was -conferred in 1911. * Hereditary title conferred on 12th December 1911. the The Eriler of Tori Fatehpur has some times been called by the title of ' Rao', but that of ' Diwan ' is given in the first edition of the Alqabnamah andis still used by the local authorities. fThe title of ' Hao Bahadur' U personal to the present Euler.AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. Name and address of Euler in Persian. ? T?.T.ATTfWg WTTTT TTTT7. anVTT.P VMPXTT fW T'\ T nT A —ontnlJ STATES. Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto §-£lovomnr nf Bombay-. SfC ft. , Agent to the Governor- General. Viceroy and Governor- General. Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto &lt;^}x* g'jV* tyi/'ts- *•(&gt;&gt; * aitkJI * la*) Clidy* iaik. laiw ^jw &lt;Ujlak. * 0;ljj w.a.U&gt; — *»UJ^ Jo'- ^ ' 'tfWI No, of Guns. 9t 11 19 Betnarks. * P. No. 80-H. of 1934. * Hereditary title— vide ' Gazette of India Extraordinary ' dated 3rd June 1936. t Vide ' Gazette of India' Part I, dated the 26th November 1927. [Pile No. 102 (4)-H. of 1927.] t Hereditary title— vide ' Gazette of India Extraordinary ' dated 3rd June 1935. §Pile No. 236-H. of 1925. His Highness also has a permanent local salute of 13 guns -within the limits of the State of Janjira, fide 'Gazette of India Extraordinary,' dated the 1st January 1921. || Honorary Eoyal Indian Navy rank— vide ' Gazette of India,' Pprfc I, dated 11th August 1934. Honorary Army rank— ' Gazette of India,' Part I, dated ttrt 30th April 1927? File No. 107 (10j H. of 1920r The hereditary title of 'Maharaja' was conferred on the 23rd May 1900( 10 ^ ©t ltu&gt; lih fa^, rtll-z. The State is being administered by the two Chiefs named. The civil and criminal jurisdiction is exercised by Ganpatrao Madhajrao. Zx&amp;e cf) £ c . cow: a t nl rj?fcJa cru SzZL &lt;/] ^ -77AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. Name and address of Euler in Persian. R«M:iON-S-W^TH THlTGiyVETn^tEi^-OF -muiA— STATES—conii. Aprent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto fa Gftvomor of Eomhay No. of Guns. 9» 9* Ull Ee marks. ■fHereditary title conferred on the 3rd June 1922. %Konorary Army rank in Indian Land Forces. -nai /IfY / &lt;r j/-. /= /9(sJ d/jy 4r^ ^Honorary Army Eank 1 Januaii'y IPSO, iMog. I07»rrn4). || Vide Gazette of India, Part I, dated the 26th November 1927. [Pile No. 28 (3)-H. of 1927.] The hereditary title of Eaja was conferred on the 3rd June 1932. # Conferred on the 1st January 1918. ^Honorary Army rank [vide Pile No. 19 (8)-H. of 1931 (Secret).] * File No 85-H. of 1934 XlSvnwui y Aimy J'7u. 10 (G.i n. uf l,-, §§The Euler also has a permanent local salute of 11 guns within the limits of the State of Sawantwadi— ' Gazette of India (Extraordinary) dated the 1st January 1921.4)8 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name and State. Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. JASHPUR KALAHANDI . KANKER . KAWARDHA . KEONJHAR KHAIRAGARH KHANDPARA . KHARSAWAN . KOREA . MAYURBHANJ NANDGAON . NARSINGHPUR NAYAGARH . NILGRI . PAL-LAHARA * I.—BULINQ PRINCES AMU CHIEFS 11^ POLITICAL IV.~EASTERN Raja Bijoy Bhusan Singh Deo, Raja of —- • My esteemed friend. Your sincere friend. Ditto kxrCtvU Maharaja* Bfaja Mohan Boo, 0 S.J?., Maharaja of— Maharajadhiraj Bhanupratap Deo, Chief of- Thakur Dharamraj Singh, Chief of— • Raja Balhhadra Narayan Bhanja Deo, Raja of— RajaJ Birendra Bahadur Singh, Raja of— Harihar Singh Mardraj Bhramarbar Ray, ja of— Raja Sriram Chandra Singh Deo, Raja of— Raja Ramanuj Pratap Singh Deo, Raja of— « aharaja§ Sir Pratap Chandra Bhanja Deo, K.C.I.JE,, Maharaja of— Mahant SoBvoshwar Das, of— Raja Ananta Narayan Mansingh Harichandan — - - ^ Raja of— Paja Krishna Chandra Singh Mandhata, Raja of— Raja Kishor Chandra Mardraj Harichandan, Raja of— Raja' Muni Pal, Raja of— .... Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto DittoAND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. Name ?md address of Rule.r in Persian. RELATIONS wmi 'MJjl GU V EKiN M T OFTinirS=rT77^f. STATES— contd. Agent to the Governor- General. GoT-amnr of 'Rihav .flTid / &amp;-icco Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto No. of Guns. Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto 9t * The hereditary title of ' Maharaja ' was conferred on the 3rd June 3932. tPol. A., February 1878, Nos. 464- 468 and Pol. A,, January 1879, Nos. 73-75. J The title of 'Raja,' conferred at first as a personal distinction on the Ist January 1896, was declared to be hereditary on the Ist Janu ary 1S98. The title of ' Raja ' was conferred on the 4th June 1917, as a hereditary distinction. § Hereditary title conferred on the 24th June 1910. June 1910. 11 Conferred on the Ist January 1918,. '51 AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. Name and address of Ruler in Persian, No. of Guns. 2 a* P-i Remarks. RKum iONS WITH THE GOYBB ?TMiE*rp nff yyrpfA— TATES —concld. yp i (CrUX. C^r /^pe. Z-?^' Agent to the GoTernor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto -■ Go tot nor of Bih*=ted Qguoa.- grOZa Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto Ditto *9 * Conferred on the Ist January 1918. t The title of ' Raja Bahadur,' con ferred on the 8rd June 1929 i« personal. The title appertaining to the Chiefship is that of ' Raja J The title of ' Raja Bahadur', con ferred on Srd June 1918, is personal. The title appertaining to the Chiefship is that of ~ § Conferred on the Ist January 1921 as a hereditary distinction. 11 Conferred on the 1st January 1918. Conferred on the 31st March 1931 as a hereditary distinction. &amp; n-cz. rtr/oji /fv ^ ^LIST OP RULING PRINCES Commeiicement and Conclusion &lt;5 Name of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. of letter in English and a colour of Crest. I—Eftfeftsb mjjCEiS AJMrt?lIIEir3 IN I'OLITfeAL VIL-HYDEB 124 HYDERABA (DECCAN) . 125 JAMMU ANI&gt; KASHMIR . L iouitimnt-General His Exalted Highness Asaf Jah Muzaffar-ul-Mnlk wal Mamalik Nizam-ul-Mulk Nizam-ud-Daula, Nawab Sir Mir IJsman Ali Khan, Bahadur, Pateh Jang Faithful Ally of the British .Government, G.O.S.I., G.B.E., Nizam of— ifu General* His Highness Maharaja &amp;Vt Hari Singh Indar Mahindar Bahadur Sipav-i- Saltanat, G.C.S.I., G.C.LK, K.C.V.O., ArD-C., Mahai'aja of— My honoured and valued friend, v I desire to express the high considera tion which I entertain for Your Exalted Highness as the Faithful Ally of the British Government and to subscribe myselfj Your Exalted Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String (Dori)—Purzar. (All gold thread.) For letters from the Secretary: Kharitd bag—Zarbaffc. (Gold brocade.) String (Dori)—Purzar. (Gold thread.) YIII.-JAMMU AND My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high considera tion which I entertain for Your Highness fend to subscribe myself, Your Highness' gincere friend. Crest, Gold- Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary: Kharita hag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade,) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)58 LIST OF RULING PRINCES 5§ 126 Name of State. BANGANAPALLE 127 128 COCHIN . PUDUKKOTTAI Name and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English ar.d colour of Crest. i.—PRINCES ANircmiFSTOmrrreAL IX.—MADRAS Nawab Saiyid Fazl-i-Ali Khan Bahadur, Nawab of— His Highnea^Maharajaf Sri Sir Boma Vamaik, Uo^-^Oy J' r.&gt; ' h. ^ • His Highness Sri Brihadamba Das Eaja gopala Tondaiman Bahadur, Eaja of— My friend. With best wishes, I remain, Your sincere friend. Crest, Green. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Oold&lt; f Ynnr SigWrnr YftJlT WigliTmnn' fl 'IHIlit i^Uj Xf**) A^ r ^^&gt;160 LIST OF RUUKG PRINCES Name and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclusion o{ letter in English and colour of Crest. 129 SANDUR . 180 131 TRAVANCOEE MYSORE . L-^-RgfrENG rBINCES AND CniBPg-iy-fOH^ICAL IX—MADRAS Eaja Srimant Teshwanta Rao, Rao Sahib, Hindu Eao Ghorpade Mamlukatmadai' Senapati, Raja of— O^ His Highness Sri Padmanahha Dasa Vanchi ; Pala Sir Rama Varma XCulasekhara Kiritapati Manney Sultan Maharaja Raja Eamaraja Bahadur Shamsher Jang, G.C.I.E., • Maharaja of— Qvhmel* His Highnesg Mdhmja Sirf Sri Krish aaiaia-Sadiyar Bahadm, &amp;.C.8J., G.B.JE., Maharaja of' \j/. jy. - t- My friend. 'With best wishes, I remain. Tour sincere friend. My honodred and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider ation which I entertain for Your Highness and to subscribe myself, Your'Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold* Kharlta bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) X.-MY My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider ation which I entertain for Your Highness, and to subscribe myself, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold, Kharita bag!—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)62 LIST OP RULING PRINCES u i Name of State. Name and address of Buler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. a 132 133 134 BAHAWALPUB BILASPUB CHAMBA ; JM&amp;hr*' Hia Highness Eukn-ud-Danla Nugrat-i-Jang, Saif-ud-Daulaf Hafiz-ul-Mulk Mukhlis-ud-Daula wa Muin-ud-Daula Nawab Al'JHaj§ Sir Sadiq Muhammad Khan Ahbasi, Bahadur, K.C.8.L, K.C.V.O., LL.D., Nawah of— ' I. -BITE™ rBINCES ANB-OgQl Ei; ttj xl-punjab His Highness Baja Anand Chand, Raja of— His Highness Raja Haap Singh, Eaja of— My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend, Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. My f*w4. a -^ Y 1 I remain, W Your Highness' sincere friend- Crest, Gold.64 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. Commenceinent and Conclnsion of letter in English and dolour of Crest. 135 JjiiMtmimni'* His Highness Parzand-i-Saadat Nislian-i-Hazrat-i-Kaisar-i-Hind Barar Bans Eaja Har Jndar Singh Bahadur^ Eaja of— £ ./V Mitt (JidiEJj'S Tr^OMTteAL XL—PUNJAB My esteemed friend. 136 ColonelX His Highness * Parzand-i-Dilband Easikh-ul-I'tiqad-i-Daulat-i-Inglishia Raja-i- Eajagan Maharaja Sir Ranbir Singh, Eajdndra Bahadur, G.C&amp;S:, tyO.S.L, Maharaja of— / I remain, with much consideration, Yonr Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. My esteemed friend. I'remain, 'with much consideration^ Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Ddri)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)66 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in Eiiglish and colour of Crest. Colond * His Highness Farzand-i-Dilband Rasikh-ul -I'tiqad-i-Daulat -i -Inglishia Kaja-i- Raiagan Maharaja Sir Jagatjit Singh Bahadur. G.C.8.L, G.C.I.JS., G.B.K, Maharaja of— XL-PUNJAB My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamthwah. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) His IlighntDii Mil Air Navaz Khan Talpur,' Mfe of— My esteemed friend. I remain, with much considorationj Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold.68 LIST OP RULING PRINCES ill! H H ( 1} ' r 4 Name of State. 139 140 LOHAEU . MALEE EOTLA Name and address of Euler in English. Comtnencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Grest. Jfriifiirfn—M'Ti—ih* Mirza Amin-ud-Din Ahmad Khan Bahadur, Nawah of— I.—EHLINe FRINGES AND CHIEFS IN POLlTKfcli XL—PUNJAB My friend. I remain, Your sincere friend. lieutenant-ColonelX His Highness Nawab Sir Ahmad Ali Khan, Bahadur, K.C.S.L, K.C.LE., Nawab of— My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold.70 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name of State. 141 Name and address of Etiler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. MANDI His Higliness Kaja Sir Joginder Sen, Bahadur, K.C.S'I., Raja of— I.—RULING PRINCES AND CHIEFS IN POLITICAi XI.—PUNJAB My esteemed friend. 142 NABHA His Highness Farzand-i-Arjmand Aqidat Paiwand-i-Daulat-i-Inglishia Barar Bans Sarmur Raja-i-Rajagan Maharaja Pratap Singh Malvendra Bahadur, Maharaja of— I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Tour Highiiess' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhwah, (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)72 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. CommeneeiBent and Conclasion of letter in English and colour of Crest, 143 PATIALA . tr—Sfiln UlilM IN ■EQLiriCAi; U4, LiiHti.'Orimyil * His Highness Farzand-i- Khas-i-Daulat-i-Irglishia Mansur-i-Zamau Amir-ul-Umra Maharajadhiraja Rajeshwar Sri Maharaja-i-Rajagan, Sir Bhupindai' Singh Mahindar Bahadur, CtZGiSiT.,-' fin T ft, GLOrPreT G^S., y- SIRMUR INahas) Of His Highness Maharajaf Rajindra Parkasli Bahadur, Maharaja of— XL-PUNJAB My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Tour Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold, r i74 LIST OP RULING PRINCES 146 SUKET 146 ALWAB 147 BANSWAKA N?ime and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. His Highness Baja Lakshtnan Sen, Eaja of— -I. BUIINQ FRINCES AND CHHaFB IN POLIIICAL XL-PUNJAB Hi H 'Highnesa Sowai Maharaj—Sfcw Jny of— Maharaia§ PUjrl** IMS* T His Highneea Sri Rai-i-Rayan Maharawal Sir Pirthi Singb Bahadur, K.C.LE., Mahara wal of- ; My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold, x.—raj My esteemed friend^ I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag - Karokhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary; Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String {Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Eharita bag—Kamkhwdb. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)76 LIST OP RULING PRINCES I Name of State. Name and address of Etiler in English. Commencement and Conclnsion of letter in JEnglisli and colour of Crest. 148 149 A &gt; j- BEARATPUB • 1 His Highness Maharaja Sti Brajindta Satvai Brijendra Singh Bahadur, Bahadur Jang, Maharaja of— BIKANES 1. BULlKQ I'UilTGEij AJTt) GIIIEFB I1T I'OMTIGAL XII-tEAJ My esteemed friend. I remain^ with much consideration, Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters Irom the Secretary: Eharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dorij—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) 'f His . 0 „ w , Eaj Rajeshwar Shiromani Maharaja Shri Si?* Ganga Singhji Bahadur a.o.v.o,, a.s.E., k. c Mahaiaja of— ^ C.v.e. rta^SoXo-La, %■— My esteemed friend. I femaln, with much consideration. Tour Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar, (Gold and silk thread.) I 178 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name of State. 0 JZ5 150 BUNDI 151 DANTA 152 DHOLPUB, N ame and address of Ealer in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. j^IlULIHG ritDTCES A^D CniEFO IN rOLm&amp;lL., |). &gt; XII.—RAJ si 1 His Highness Maharao Raja^ Ishwari Singi Bahadur, Mtthuiau R.tja irf— ,C, /• £. j esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and ail brocade.) String (Dori)—-Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary ; Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) /fV.// *-■ Maharana Sbri Bhavanisinhji HaTnirn'nbjV Mahai-ataf of— Lieutenant-Colonel^ His Highness Rais-ud- Daula Sipahdar-ul-Mulk Maharajadhiraja Sri Sawai Maharaj-Rana Sir Udaibiian Si«^b Lokindar Bahadur Diler Jang Jai Deo, G.CJ.E. t K.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., Maharaj- Rana of— My friend. Yours sincerely. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori) -Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)80 LIST OF RULING PRINCES Name of State. 1 153 DUNGARPUB . 164 Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. -AN^--&amp;5tBi 1 B-4N--EDLIIICAL XI I.-E A J His Highness Rai-i-Rayan Maharawal Sri Sir Lakshman Sipgi Bahadur, K»C•S.Z» i Maharawal of— ' My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita lag—Kam'khwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar (Gold and silk thread.) JAIPUR tfiairi* His Highness 0 Hindustan Raj Rajmdra Sri Maharajadhiraia Sawai Sir Man Singh Bahadur, G.C.I.E., Maharaja of— My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high considera tion which I entertain for Tour Highness, and to Bubacnbe myself, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String (Dori)—Purzar. (All goldthread.) For letters from the Secretary :— Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String CDori)—Purzar. (Gold thread.)82 LIST OF RULING PRINCES a Name of State. Name and address of Euler in English. Commencament and Conclusion of lexter in English and colour of Crest 15B JAISALMEE 156 JHALAWAR J^El^CES AND CHIEtS IN JJULHTCAL XII-RAJ His Highness Maharajadhiraja Maharawal Sir Jowahir Singir Bahadur, IC.C.SS., Maha- rawal of- My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwah. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) Lieutenant* His Highness Maharaj-Eanaf •Daiiadin 1 , Muhuiiaj i Baaa ofrmr &lt;7- My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)84 LIST OP RULING PRINCES Name of State. Name and address of Ruler in English. Cotnmencement and Conclusion of letter in English and coloar of Crest. fjjji CfriA+y^ 1&amp;7 JODHPUR (M abwas) KARAULI , lajeshwar Bahadur, JUmntv&amp;ihfid * Ilia Highness Raj Maharajadhiraja Sir IJmaid Sing ^ Q.C.I.E., KiC.B.I., K. C.F. O^Maharaja of- /ftVC I.—RUiiIN&amp; PRINCES AND CHIEFS IN POLITICAL XII.—RAJ My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high considera tion which I entertain for Yonr Highness, and to fenbscrihe myself. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag - Zarlmft. (Gold brocade.) String (Dori) —Purzar. (All gold thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kaml&lt;hwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String i Don) -Nimzar. (Gold and silu thread.) His Highness Maharaja Svr Bhom Pal Deo Bahadur Yadukul Chandra Bhal, K.C'S.I, Maharaja of— My esteemed friend. I remain, with much considefatioflf Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold, Kharita bag - Kamlchwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary s Kharita bag - Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade^) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread,)86 LIST OP RULING PRINCES CJ Name and address of Ruler in English. Commer. cement and Conclueion of letter in English and colour of Crest 169 KISHDNGARH . 160 KOTAH His Highness Umdae Hajahae Buland Makan Maharajadhiraja Xagyauwewn Biwgh Bahadur, Maharaja of— XIL-RAJ I*--****' Mv esteemed friend. J^hditennntTCnlfltti'l fTlin 'HI^LLUjgH Mahil^ao'^S'?'7• Ilinrd Mingli 13iil.i.K.1m, G-rO.8.1.. Q.C.I.E., Q Tt F, Mfthprag c£ JoJa./jfC - . I remain, with much consideration, Tour Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita hag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary: Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideiatioa, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Cold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary; Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)90 LIST OF RULING PRINCES U Iff I ^ f Name of State. a p 525 164 SIROHI 165 TOUK Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. um AHIL umiiii^ m luLineAL XII.—RAJ His Highness Maharajadhiraja* Maharao Sir Sarup Ram Singh Bahadur, O,C.I.JE., K.C.S.I., Maharao of— His Highness Said-nd-Daula ^Wazir-ul-Mulk Nawabf Hafiz Sir Mohammad Sadat Ali Khan Bahadur, Saulat-i-Jang, G.C.I.E., Nawab of— Jk ^ My esteemed friend. [ remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—TCamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)92 LIST OP RULING PRINCES ss 1 Name of State. Name and address of Euler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. / a /f.—EULTKU AND CHIEFS i^J I'OLlTttTL /JrLtMf XII.-EAJ 166 UDAIPUB (Mswab) . / 'His Highness Maharajadhiraja Maharana Sir Bhupal Siagh Bahadur, G-.C.S.L, K.Cd.E., Maharana of—* - I , ' ' My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high considera tion which I entertain for Your Highness, and to subscribe myself. Your Highness* sincere friend Crest, Gold, Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String (Don)—Purzar. (All gold thread.) 167 SIKKIM . . . K.CS't. His Highness Maharaja Sir Tashi Namgyal, K.CJ.E., Maharaja of— XIIL SIK My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (3old and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. _ (Gold and silk thread.)AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. Name and address of Ruler in Persian. RBfcATION3 WITH THE STATES. yjpBS&amp;y aud (jovernor- Ditto Ditto Agent to the Governor Irjci L c4l*^ (&gt;/&lt;; £xuAo~uj ^wiaroy and Govornor' GeffWill. Ditto Agent to the Governor General. ftoYPi-rnr of Bombay ■j 'iivHi-nnr nr t t/oc tMOs-t tt lAJca^ y 4 d^lox 6 kk) ci&gt;dj* L a. iaak. * dki^A. ^ !; 4J J 3 **)* Ji - J-ii - ^ ^ -^V? ' ^ ^' utT ot-«xi£) V- No. of Guns. Remarks. 13 17 1S|I n ntt 15 131t Hlf IB *The title of 'Maharaja' was con ferred as a hereditary distinction on the 1st January 191!r. The Ruler also has a permanent local salute of 15 guns within the limits of the State of Bhavnagar, vide Gazette of IwHa (Extraordinary), dated the 1st January 1921. fThe title of ' Savai Bahadur' was conferred on the 28th January 1885. jThe hereditary title of ' M aharao ' was conferred on the 1st January 1918. ; /=' /YP - ' The Ruler also has a permanent local salute of 19 guns within the limits of the State of Cutch, vide Gazette of India (Extraordinary), dated the 1st January 1921. Awe § Hereditary title of ' Maharaja ' con ferred on the Ruler on Ist January 1918. IjRaised on 1st January 1918. ^TPol. A.. February 1878, Nos. 464 — 4ti8 and Pol. A., January 1879, Nos. 73-75. ♦♦The hereditary title of ' Maharaja ' was conferred on the 3rd July 192') {vide File No. 39-H. of 1926—^Secret). ffl. A., January 1888, Nos. 218-223 and I. A., July 1888, Nos. 166—169. The salute originally attached to the Scate was 9 guns (Pol. A., January 1879, Nos. 73—75). ^The salute of the Nawab was raised permanently to 13 guns on the 1st \j\jgyijt January 1918. His Highness was r . - J granted a personal salute of 15 guns'' and a permanent local salute of 15 guns on the 1st January 1921, vide Gazette of India (Extraordinary), dated the 1st January 1921. §§Po]itical A., February 1878, N ob. 464—468 and Political A., January 1879, Nos. 73—75. || ||The hereditary title of ' Maharaja ' was conferred on the 3rd July 1926 (vide File No 39-H. of 1926—Secret). ^Political A., February 1878, Nos. 464-468 and Political A., January 1879, Nos. 73—75.97 AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed. ISiaxne and address of Ruler iu Persian. WITH OH 1 STATES— concld. ^Gonoral. Agent to the Governor- General. 'Viceroy mid •Govei 'pcff- / ~&lt;jo»flinoi' eii' Uumbay-- fij-iztd. Agent to the Governor- General. Ditto Ditto No. of gans 13* 9t 13 § 11 n m Eemarks. * Hereditary title and pe manent salute of 13 ^uns vide Gazette of „ Q \ D India (Extraordinary), dated the Ist ' *• January J 918. The Kuler also has U e ' e ; a permanent local salute of 15 guns jKp. i© ; . , within the limits of the State of ^ Navanagar— vide Gazette of India (&gt; i 9k. | (Extraordinary), dated the 1st Jan- ' uary 1921. t Pol. A,, February 1878, Nos. 464— 4t)8 and Pol. A., January 1879, Nos 73-75. t The hereditary title of ' Maharaja ja' was conferred on 1st January 1918. § Permanently raised to 13 guns on * J the 1st January 1918. Pol. A., February 1878, Mos. 464,— 468 and Pol. A., 7anuary 1879, No 8 . 73-75. IfPol. A., February 1878, Nos. 464— 468 and Pol. A., January 1879, Nos. 73-75. ** Granted the honorary rank of Captain in the Army on the 1st Jan uary 1918 {vide S. I., November 1918, Nos. 1—39. ft F. No. 98-H. of 1934. XX His Highness' short form of address is— ' His Highness the Maharana Raj Saheb of Wankaner ' (File No. 128» H. of 1924). §§ P. No. 35(8) H. of 1930 (Sec.).PRINCES Name and address of Ruler in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. BENARES EAMPUR II.—RULING PRINCES AND CHIEFS IN POLITICAL RELATIONS WITH Captain* His Highness Maliarajaf asii^a fcingh Bfthfldar, K. C. /S. J., / M ah a raj a QaftmnX His Highness' Alijah Rarzand-i-Dilpazir- i-Daulat-i-Inglishia Mukhlis-nd-Daula Nasir- ul-Mulk Amir-ul-Umra NawaWSaiyid Eaza Ali Khan Bahadur Musta'id JangwNawab of— KC.Sl LLC. My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Khaiita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String iDori)—Nimzar. Gold and silk thread.) My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nirazar. (Gold and silk thread.) For letters from the Secretary ; Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.)100 LIST Of ruiikg princes Name of State. d ^3 — TEHBI GaehwajI MANIPUS TRIPUEA . jSTame and address of Rtler in English. Commencement And Conoltision of letter in English and colour of Crest. f/JSV Z7 V &amp; Sto^CZ* it—I mPH99TimH Majot *1118 HiglinessjBflijfl Sir Narendra Shah, K.CiS.L, Eaja of— ily friend. I remain, Your sincere friend. Kharita bag—TCamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dotfi)—Nimzar. old and silk thread.) /-Jssh-M ■ III.— EeWSG-FETSlCES AMU CHlEi'S LM POLITICAL His Highness Mahafa^aJ Sir Chilra Chand Siilgh, K.CS.L, Q.B.E., Maharaja of— My esteemed friend, I rfetrtain, with much consideration, Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold. His Highness Maharaja Jitgaddipendra Narayan Bhup Bahadur, Maharaja of— TY T?TrTiT'M r ' Tirpr^'* Awr&gt; I'W 'P«' 1 &gt;TiTTTf !ATi My esteemed friend. 41^ 'His Highness Maharaja§ '&lt;1 „ „, Bikram Kishore Deb Barman Bahadur, K.C.Sjf Maharaja of— I remain, with much consideration. Your Highness* sincere friends Crest, Gold. , UL J&gt; iTy I remain, with much considefStioQy Your Highness' sincere friend. Crest, Gold, JSSSS103 AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hitherto Name and address of Ruler in Persian. No. of Guns. a i la g § a) (S P h WITH TMiLHyUv uuti M mmmtmngiM. GUwarnnr nf the Ptmjab. Ditto • Ditto The title of ' Raja ' was confened on the 12th March 1875. The hereditary title of ' Raja' was conferred on the 4th June 1928. The title of ' Rana ' was conferred on the 28th July 1858, Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Ditto Title of ' Nawah Babadur ' confcri'ed on the 4th May 180 J.107 AND CHIEFS IN INDIA. Highest British authority by whom hithero addressed. No. of Guns. Name and address of Euler in Persian. Bemarks. EILLA t J lu I mo vv im (iuvEiilsMlilN'i' UJTTfiS-PUNd^B -c eld ^fif^YPrBor of-111 J fmijul. £-^3 I Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. The title of 'Nawab' is said to have been conferred in 1806. The title of ' Rai ' was conferred in July 1887. Ditto. The title of 'Kana' wa s conferred as a personal distinction on the ist March 1929.110 MISCEL Name of State or place of residence. 5? Name and address in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. INDORE BOMBAY . His Highness Tukoji Rao III, Q, C. I. JE. t * ex- Maharaja of— Nftwab Sir Amir-nd:din Ahrend; Jviian .Bafaafllirr g.(7.r.77. eg-Nawah of— His Highness The Right Hon'hle Aga Sir Sultan Muhammad Shah Aga Khan, P.O., G.C.S.I., g.cj.je., a.o .r.o. IN My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider ation which I entertain for Your Highness, and to susbcrihe myself, Your Highness* sincere friend. Crest, Gold. Kharita bag—Zarhaft. (Gold brocade) String (Dori)—Purzar. (All gold thread.) For letters from the Secretary : Kharita bag—Kamkhwab. (Gold and silk brocade.) String (Dori)—Nimzar. (Gold and silk thread.) My pigJ l. I 'fClllSuu, ' Ynnr fripnrl. BOM114 MISCEL Name cf State or place of residence. Name and address in English. Commencement and Conclusion of letter in English and colour of Crest. MUHAMMEEAH ZANZIBAR ttu STinilrh fi'r Wr girdfir hrh' ftm- ^ir', illili nT M m I iiiiiiiiiiii will His Highness Saiyid Ali Hammad bin Muhammad, Sultan of— PERSIAN My esteemed friend. I remain, with much consideration. Your Excellency's sincere friend. Cre&amp;t, Gold. My honoured and valued friend. I desire to express the high consider aticn which I entertain for Youf Highness, and to subscribe myself Your Highness* sincere friend,, Crest, Gold.. Kharita bag—Zarbaft. (Gold brocade.) String (Don)—Purzar. (All Gold thread.) ataMMita.117 Form. 120—121 alter No. and date o£ correction slip. Initials of clerk and date of posting. No. and date of correction slip. Initials of clerk and date of posting. GIPD—S2—499(C) F&amp;PD-28-2-36 -30,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/734</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/734</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'List Showing the Names, Titles and Modes of Address of the More Important Sovereigns, Ruling Princes, Chiefs, Nobles etc., Having Relations with the Indian Government, Alqabnamah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-04T11:23:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (71 folios)</extent><extent>There is a list of contents and an alphabetical index towards the front of the volume, on folios 3-5.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at 1A on the front cover and terminates at 71 on the back cover. These numbers are written in pencil. are enclosed in a circle, and appear in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1A, 1B; ff. 10A, 10B. Folio 64 has been attached to the outer edge of f. 63.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume is entitled
                           List Showing the Names, Titles and Modes of Address of the More Important Sovereigns, Ruling Princes, Chiefs, Nobles etc., Having Relations with the Indian Government, Alqabnamah(New Delhi: Government of India Press, 1935). [The Alqabnamah was a register kept by the Indian Government, recording official titles and modes of address.] It is described on the front cover as 'Corrected up to the 5th October 1935'. The volume shows a number of manuscript corrections, additions and cross-references.The volume is divided into lists of independent states, protectorate rulers, ruling princes and chiefs in India, and miscellaneous. Within these divisions information is recorded in parallel columns under the following headings:name of state;name and [form] of address of ruler in English;commencement and conclusion of letter in English, and colour of crest;highest British authority by whom hitherto addressed;name and [form] of address in Persian or Arabic;number of guns [in official salute];remarks.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Aqabnamah</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>