<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000224_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-19T10:23:23.801Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">g j? ,P y. .. .P. p _XJL L E G R A M o Prom Viceroy s Foreign ^ Political Bept„ to S.oi o• xox xiivxia© Dated 28.3»21o Received 29th e^aoCt, C3DCCC««CiL.e i i:Ot.aE.GCtf , 'C3 I oPaOo0CCo 190$r, 454S 0 Your telegram of the 19th January N0o418 o BaKhtlarlo Statement in our telegram of the 28th Septmher 0 1149S 8 was made on authority of Baghdad who made all the arrangements throughoutc Enquiries now ^how that payments were made hy local officers on the authority of Foreign Office telegram No 0 421 August 14th 1918 to Teheran 0 and your telegram of the 15th August. 1918 to Baghdado It was considered that this sanction j held good to the end of financial yeafo Payments were made hy Baghdad Treasury at request of Consul®General 8 Ispeshen, to the Imperial Bank of Persia ShirefccWo.113-1,C. Tour telegram dated Septeniber 15th 1920 11220 akhtiari Sowars^ Treasury refuse to accept our telegram dated 19th March 1915 # 327 as authority for payments in lehr nary and March* Secretary of State for India asks to he informed whether definite instructions were issued to Consuls at Shiraz and Ispahan from any authority* The former would not presumably accept debit for a Bakhtiari payment without special instructions* Addressed Baghdad repeated Tehran* Telegram B’rom - His Excellency the High Commissioner in Mesopotamia, Baghdad* To ~ The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department .Delhi* . * &gt; ■ * i Wo*360* l Dated the 26th (Teed. 28th) January 1921 Tour telegram of 25th January,113-1.0., has been repeated to He si dent Bushir e who will supply information required direct. Iddressed Foreign repeated Tehran* JSL /~——m Telegram, 3. From - Tie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Entire. Tfe - The Foreign Secretarv to the Govemment of India ' m the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Dated 15th fpecd. 15th) February 1921. f ' ' + * 4 i Tour telegram to Baghdad has Been referred to me as all war files regarding Arabist an and Bakhtiaris have been transferred to Residency* Have not been able to trace any definite orders* Consul- * $ G-eneral Ispahan telegraphs.. Begins, According to records here temporary monthly subsidy of 16000 tomans to Sirdar Zafar for payment of Sowars arranged by Captain Peel with Legation’s ■ ■ . - v .* .-■■■- , i sanction but objected to ty H.M r s Government 0 Two payments on February 1st and March 1st 1919 were made as you say by Baghdad^) i Treasury to Imperial Bank of Persia Shiraz at Colonel Haigs zz request, February instalment was transferred here for Bakhtiaris but there is no trace of March instalment having oassed through — ^ •• ■ * * - 1 this Consulate-General we have no account with India except EH&amp;fcxfe escort and that through Legation, Better ask Peel I have no more information here Inds. My records show that Colonel Haig considered retention of sowars very necessary for safety of Ispahan during period in question, and was apparently under impression that Persian Government would take sowars over, Shiraz Consulate does not appear to have had anything to do with matter. Am asking Ahwaz if he can throw any light on the mat ter,SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT.i/ COPY. (C 14652/0869/34) S/5 441. Treesnr^y Oharnber b 1920 flo slr &gt; , _ l Q 'z i I hsve laid before the T/&gt;rds Coi^Tniss5_oners of His Majesty’s Treasury your letter of the 17th ultimo (C 9869/9869/34) transmitting a copy of a letter of the V 27th Oetober last, with enclosure, from the India relative to the payment during the months of February and Marsh 1919 of a forse of 5^0 Bakhtlari sowars. In reply I am to request you to inform Karl Cursor of Kedleston that My Lords aould net regard a general authority to ineur expenditure without sanction as overriding definite instruetions (whleh They assume were given in a@®ordanse with the desision in Treasury letter of 14th December 1918) (42969/18) not to ineur exnenditure on a particular object. /Moreover, the telegram now r furnished is dated the 19th Harsh 1919 and ssmnl in any ease be quoted as an authority for expenditure in February and the early part of ''arch. i In the absence of further information as to the authority whereby this expenditure was incurred, My Lords regret to be unable to assept any portion of the cost as a charge upon Imperial revenues. I am, etc., (signed) R.S, Meiklejohn.0 *E *8 »/BH« 4515 6,0,. I u FROM Viceroy Foreign &amp; Political to S. of Si Dated 18.10.20. Received 20.10.20. 4 p.m. X 1209 S. Your telegram of 13th October last. Though payment ms made by Ispahan we understand amount was debited in Shiraz Consulate accounts. 21 OCT! 920SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. T letter Dated ^ , from I eiegram Rec. 19 • ‘ Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary.. ^ / Secretary of State. Committee. / Under Secretary. . Secretary of State. Previous Papers 10 u. cc ft# ^ Copyto A^C M13 MA i: MAY 1920 iu ' c&lt;*. * J i. FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. &lt;AY. UWA a « y ^C4uy i /f*t' -(§) In any further communication on bJiis subject, please quote No -193799/34. Foebign Officb. and address, not to any person by name, but to— S.W.I. April 30th, 1920 “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.I. Sir: - With reference to your letter P„1200 of the 10th March and to rny letter of the 31st of that month, regarding the Bakhtiari sowars force, 1 am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you, herewith, copies of a letter from the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury and of His Lordship’s reply thereto. 2. Lord Curzon would be grateful if Mr.Secretary Montagu would furnish ham with the information desired by Their Lordships regarding the authority under which the force of five hundred sowars was paid, during the months of February and- March, 1919. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.!dUais..i *auuj r-- 15245 on i%aBury Cha;. ’oers, April 23r;l, 1920, pw 4 J-f ! Liy' - Lord, I have laid before -the Lords Commissioners of his ivlajesoy's Treasury 1.x. Phipps' letter (1E4385/34) Oj. -'laiCn cl. j... v;iph reference to the proposal to raise a force of Gendarmerie among the Bakhtiari tribes in Persia which was submitted to Their Lordships in ;OJ.r Louis Ilallet's letter of November 5th 1918, to vdiich They replied in their letter No.42969 of December 14th 1918. * It is noted that a sum of'Krais.641,500 - was expe,.Licw on one ucheep of a force of Bakhtiari sowars from October 1918 to January 1919. It appears from Lr. Shuckburgh's letter of January 28th 1920, enclosed -with the letter under reply, that the approval of Colonel Wilson’s original scheme for a Bakhtiari levy expressed by the foreign Office in their telegram of 14th August 1918 addressed to Sir Charles Marling was regarded by him as an authority to proceed with the modified scheme which resulted in the expenditure now under consideration, pv Lords would wish to be informed of the circumstances in which this telegram was despatched. ly Lords leave no recollection of having been consulted as to the proposal stated to have been approved therein. • Admitting that Colonel Wilson may have been led to believe that His majesty’s Government had approved his origins **&lt;-&gt;n proposal, which was the subject of the foreign The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. Office/ / mstill clo no‘ Office telegrain referred to clove ? :.y Lord agree that there was sufficient reason for proceeding with the creation of a force of gendarmerie in Brlchtiariste when the military situation which led to Colonel Jilfjon* s original proposal for the creation of a force of 1,500 tribesmen had been modified by the relief of Abed eh. The ground stated by the Government of India is that if was economically end politically advantageous to give the tribesmen a stake in the protection of the Oil Fields and in the maintenance of local law and order generally. No compelling necessity appears to Their Lordships however to have been shown. the circumstances however, on the understanding impossible to maintain that the charge- should Persian Government or on the Oil Companies, 11 not refuse sanction to the charge to ds of a moiety of the expense of 641,500 ns incurred between October 1918 and January 1919 inclusive. In conclusion I am to refer to Colonel Wilson* s felewra: No *17479 dated 17th Sepoemoer u;&gt;l~ : , a copy Oj. which was enclosed with the letwer uncior ieply , a-id to enquire the authority under which the force of 500 Sowars was paid during the montns o_ leoi arc lurch 1919 out of funds supplied by His Majesty^ i.Iinister at Tehcinn*, I am, etc., i 0-11 *1 -j cJ- m CD that it is impo fall on the Per Ny Lords w ill : Impel ?ial Fa nds yi r&gt; 'w ■d o c- Wnv' XJ ■ j J. 1 &lt; • (bi, : 'jr-6c'.) G.L(JOT) Mo In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. 184385/34 • Foreign Office S.W.l. 25 4 4 March 31st 5 1920 rs. 641,500* In reply to your letter No. P.1200 of the 10th instant on the subject of the expenditure of Krans. six hundned and forty one thousand five hundred upon the Bakhtiari Levy force between October 1918 and January 1919, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herewith, a copy of a letter addressed to the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury recommending the sanction of a moiety of the expenditure in question out of Imperial Revenues. rs. 641,500* I am. Sir Your most obedient humble Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office184585/34 6a) O IK • -O'- .1 '• 1 * &amp;» ^ \ ; * 1 • ■ ..arph 80th, 1920• Sir, v 1 th refereace to -oroign Office letter of November 8th V 3 rel ‘ tln S to * proposal to raise a force of Oendamarl. ©rnoag the Bakhtlari tribes in Persia, to which The Lords .;rrj. of Hi# -ut ; jesty 1 s treasury replied ir. their letter Mo* 40960 of PeceRiber 3.4th 1918, X mi directed by a srl Gmraon of Kecileston to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before Iheir Lordships, a copy of a letter from the Indie Office on the subject stating that a sura of trams* 641,500 - w@.s expended on the upkeep of a lores of B&amp;khtiari sowai*s from October 1918 to January 1919* In the circumstances described by the India Of lice in the final paragraph of their letter. Lore. Ourxon hopes Hut Their Lordships will sanction a moiety of this expenditure as a charge on Imperial gevenues* I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble ■ ervant. (Signed) FRIO PHIFPS* The secretary to the Treasury*/ ; Si ' . r ^ * Under Secretary of State, It is suggested that the annexed Draft might he marked for issue without reference to Committee. A ri4 Political Department, X V $ ?JM 192g_- 695 ' ‘In any far then oamraanication on this subject, please quote so- 174376/W/34 and address. ^ « 'i, tem ' V- Vi not to any person by name, but to- “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. -4 o A ff P52-S n Eokeisn Office. I February 13th 1920 ms . 1,500. a Sir I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. P. 8323 of the 28th ultimo regarding the Bakhtiari Levy Force upon which a sum of six hundred and forty one thousand and five hundred krans was expended from October 1918 to January 1919 by His Majesty^ Vice Consul at Ahwaz. 2. In reply I am to state that His Lordship re grets that he does not share Mr Secretary Montagu's view that the expenditure was justified in the circum stances and is therefore not prepared to approach the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury, with a view to obtaining their sanction to the charge upon Imperial Revenues of a moiety of the expenditure involved. /a Lb _ RE Qj /,Q • / I am, Sir, a \ Your most obedient, 14 Vi 1920 : | humble Servant, •V The Under-Secretary of- State , India Office. Copy T0 iNDis..lj lliLJSO T0 Bagdad..!,.COPY. 180366/ff/34. Foreign Office. November 8th 1918. Ts.6000. 1 Ts.16,000. Sir, With reference to your letter, 2301/17, of the 27th January 1917, sanctioning as a charge against the Imperial Exchequer a moiety of a monthly expenditure of Six thousand Tomans in connection with the proposal to raise a force of gendarmerie in Bakhtiaristan, I am directed By Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, to he laid before the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury, copies of correspondence with the India Office showing the modifications which have been introduced in the original proposal. A Memorandum which was recently prepared by the India Office on the subject is also enclosed for * Their Lordship’s information. 2. Their Lordships will observe that the scheme for a gendarmerie force which was authorised in January,1917, was not proceeded with and that it has been replaced by a proposal that the Ilkhani should be invited to maintain a force of one thousand, five hundred men. In view of the increased cost of maintaining such a body it is now suggested that this force should be reduced to five hundred sowars at the rate of Sixteen thousand Tomans a month, on the under standing that these rates of payment are temporary and due to famine conditions. 3 Mr. Balfour desires to support this amended -oro'oosal, which he considers will have a valuable influence - ' in/ The Secretary f to the Treasury.in Bakhtiaristan, and I am to enquire whether Their Lordships would oe prepared to accept as a charge on Imperial Revenues one-half of the expenditure involved* I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Louis Mallet.r ' f! ■”2' r 1 . . ■- .• -v ''' T' li A'S V To « No. 464 of 1919. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. j FINANCE DEPARTMENT.*' 8323 1919 4Gcj/ 17 (g) } SALARIES, ESTABLISHMENTS, etc. Political. q-i i (M ■ h iy 5i?1a / * / ( * /’ .f li ^ The Right Honotjeable EDWIN MONTAGU, His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, !E l§ Delhi, the 28th November 1919, Sib, We have the honour to invite a reference to the correspondence ending with our Foreign and Political Department telegram No. 1077-S., dated the 23rd July 1919, regarding the force of Bakhtiari sowars maintained in the Bakhtiari country in support of the Illkhani, Sardar Zafar. 2 . The scheme originated with your telegram, dated the 6 th July 1918, conveying the request of His Majesty’s Government to urge on the local Bakhtiari Khans the _ necessity for relieving our troops besieged at Abadeh during the Kashgai rising last year. Representations were immediately made to the Illkhani and ended in a scheme for raising a force of 1,500 picked tribes men at a monthly cost of eight to ten thousand tomans. Meanwhile Abadeh had been relieved and the Kashgai situation had eased, but in view of our other important interests in the Bakhtiari country and in Ispahan, it was considered desirable to proceed with the scheme, which was approved by His Majesty’s Government, vide your telegram, dated the 15th August 1918. 3. It was subsequently found impossible owing to famine conditions to carry out the original scheme within the estimate sanctioned, and a revised scheme, providing for a force of 500 sowars at a monthly cost of 16,000 tomans, was proposed by the Political Resident, Baghdad, and recommended by His Majesty’s. Charge d’Affaires, Tehran, for reasons with which we agreed in our Foreign and Political Department telegram, dated the 20th October 1918, to your address. 4. But the Treasury was unwilling to sanction the revised expenditure without the clearest proof of the necessity for the force, and you enquired whether we could, if we still considered the force necessary, suggest any further arguments in support of it. In agreement with the views of the Political Resident we represented that it was economically and politically advantageous to give * the tribesmen a stake in the protection of the Oil Fields and in the maintenance of local law and order generally. Colonel Wilson subsequently, on his return from Europe, visited Ahwaz and reported in May 1919 that in the absence of specific sanction to the proposals he had approved of certain payments being made to the Illkhani between October and December 1918 to enable tjie latter to maintain a small force of sowars, but that the Bakhtiari position had changed materially during the last few months, and that the payments on account had consequently ceased.2 T * h with enclosures. 2. Telegram No. 17479, dated the 27th Septem ber 1919. 5. The question now arises of the adjustment of the expenditure which has been incurred and we have the honour to enclose copies of two communi- i. Letter No. 15224 , dated the 2 ist May 1919, cations received from Colonel Wilson, and noted on the margin, in which he requests sanction to the payments already made. As stated above, the original idea emanated from His Majesty’s Government and the first scheme received their specific sanction; it seems therefore at least a debatable point whether His Majesty’s Government should not be debited with the whole incidence, and this is the view which Colonel Wilson appears to take. Nevertheless, on the analogy of the previous Bakhtiari Levy scheme, the cost of which was held to be divisible between the Imperial and the Indian Treasures —vide Treasury’s letter to the Foreign Office, dated the 27th January 1917 (copy received with your Political Secretary’s letter No. 8 , dated the 22 nd February 1917)—we feel that we ought to agree to share with His Majesty’s Government the expenditure incurred, though we could in no circumstances admit the liability of Indian revenues for more than a moiety of the cost. 6 . In order to be able to adjust and close this outstanding account at an early date, we request that the orders of His Majesty’s Government may kindly be communicated to us by telegram. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servants, (Signed) C. C. MONRO. 9i C. H. A. HILL. 91 G. R. LOWNDES. 3t » W. H. VINCENT. it MUHAMMAD SHAFI, » W. M. HAILEY.&gt; ■sswesq^s; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Enclosures to despatch No. 464 of 1919. Enclosure No. 1. No. 15224, dated Baghdad, the 21st—22nd May 1919. From— Brbvet Lieutenant-Colonel A. T. Wilson, C.M.G., C.I.E, D.S.Q. Acting Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia, * ' ’ ,f T° Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart* ment, Simla. — r In continuation of my letter No. 22606, dated 18th October 1918 I have the honour to submit herewith a statement^ Special War Expenditure incurred by His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Ahwaz, from AugusKto • Not enclosed. December 1918, together with vouchers in original . 315 The bulk of the expenditure has been incurred in connection with the entertainment of Bakhtiari sowars at Ahwaz, vide my telegram No. 6193 of July 27th, 1917, with entirely successful results. All expenditure of this nature has now ceased, and His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul is at present not expending sums in excess of his pre war budget (allowance being made for the depreciation of the Kran). I am satisfied that this expenditure was necessitated by the special circumstances existing at the time and request that sanction may be granted thereto, as before, vide your memorandum 491-Est. B of February 12th, 1919. VThe Deputy Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, in account with Bis Britannic Majesty*s Vice-Consul, Ahwaz.f Enclosure No. 2. Telegram, No. 174)79, dated the 27th (received 28th) September 1919. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf:, Baghdad, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Tour telegram August 26th, 1243-S. British Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, f reports that after 31st January he made no further payments on account of Bakhtiari sowars, hut pay of these sowars for February and March was met by British Consul-General at Ispahan who has been provided with funds for this purpose by British Minister at Tehran. The Persian Government provided fundi fox April and May, at the end of May payment ceased altogether.^cliGdiile of papers. 1. letter from the Acting Oivil Commissioner in Mesopotamia, Noa5224, dated the 21st lay 1919 and enclosure* 2* Telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Baghdad, Ho*17479, dated the 27th September 1919.o Copy. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. SALARIES, ESTABLISHMENTS: Political. i, Ejc. f Feom The GOVERNMENT o? INDIA, The SECY, of STATE for INDIA* No. 464. Dated Delhi, the 28th November 1919, Deceived Incience of the cost of the force of Bakhtiari sowars maintained in the Bakhtiari country in support of the Illkhani, Sardar Zafar. &amp; P. Dept, Press—No, 2062-22*IM9—53,f u ?fs. &gt; y - V* I w ■j p ’'7 I 1:7 i :::J X. /4~ 3(53^ C^v i'elt^-^am from Viceroy, Foreign Department, to the Secretary of State for India. D ated 23rd. July 1919. Recvd.26th. 7 p.m. 1077 S. Secret. Your telegram of the 30th. June. Bakhtiari sowars. Baghdad has made following further comments. Begins. Successful termination of war has completely won over hostile elements in Bakhtiari itself. Secondly situation in Fars has been restored and brigands of Ispahan district wiped out. Thirdly, At a recent conference in Ispahan Bakhtiari Khans composed most of their differences with each other and their general attitude towards ourselves is eminently satisfactory. Fourthly, Ir as is probable plans now being made for future Government of Bakhtiari mature, Khans themselves will raise and equip a small permanent force of sowars and will ask lor services of British officer(s). Ends^ In altered circumstances £ras] agreejablel payments ^hotJTd~ce^sK ^ ✓ ✓ / v v igQ 1 \ \ Addressed to Secretary of State, repeated to Teheran. )%jINDEXED In any farther communication on this subject, please quote No ' &gt; 8297l/W/34. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1, Foreign Office. ^ 44 ': 5th 1919. . Sir, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to refer to your letter of the 2nd ultimo, No.P.2083, regarding the proposed payment for the upkeep of a force of Bakhtiari Sowars in Persia, and to transmit to you herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran on the subject. 2. In the circumstances reported by the Civil Conmissioner, Baghdad in his telegram of the 20th ultimo, in the terms of which Sir P.Cox concurs, it appears to Lord Curzon that no further action is necessary in this matter for the present. 3. I an to enquire whether Mr. Montagu concur r- in this view. r&gt; **-: „ 1 T. / ~&lt;s JUN I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State India Office.Si “ • opy. (82971) I POL IT ICAL. Decypher. Sir P. Cox (Teheran) May 26th, 1919. D. 4,25 p,m. May 26th, 1919. R. 2.30 p.m. June 2nd, 1919. Mn Your telegram No. 263. I concur in views expressed in Bagdad telegram No. 5657 to Secretary of State for India May 20th including last paragraph. Addressed to Foreign. Office No. 382, sent to India, repeated to Bagdad.■i Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary. . Secretary of State. Committee Under Secretary. . Secretary of State. If. C Jv~&gt;. jT w 7.kr./f ' o&lt; . 'o-v-t ' /-&amp;Asij C ” ,, '“ F-o. 2^&gt; •'-* FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. f\!o &amp;: k £■ f.u j- 2^- ^ $1 L JL~~ lul^^ 'Hh^ (&lt;l r hJ)j Ui^ h LZ; ^ hjtZy; X. X4o&lt; ^ Lr (f-t-sxA ^ -^.. &lt;. s k.%, ^-3^ Previous Papers :— 23210 I 1493 1000 11/17 jx, r&lt;; A a fr“ i ls v LsdJi u^~ , &lt;~~S u-Jv. ^ f (^oA ^.rtm - i&lt;r^-o ^ ^ 4Vw ^ ‘^~ ^ ijr,p^h^ !&gt;■&lt;-- -■ ■:•- !%**-*&lt;*+*-&lt;■ [y^-* ce-o * (=1Telegram from Political, Baghdad. \ Dated 20th May,1919* Received at 1,0. 11 p.m.,27th 5,657. My telegram N8. 537, 15th January. I have now visited Ahwaz and discussed situation fully. Troops have been withdrawn from oil-fields and garrison at Ahwaz reduced to ? regiment one xagKabtxsx of cavalry with a squadron at Shuster. / Uc H.M f s Consul at Ahwaz in absence of specific sanction of H.M’s Govt, to proposals made in my telegram of 23rd September, 7,920 made with my approval agreement for payments to the Ilkhani between October and December to enable the latter to maintain a small force of sowars, but did not commit Govt, to a continuance of these payments which were of the nature of secret service expenditure. These payments ceased entirely in March, 1919 so far as H.M*s Treasury is concerned and will not be renewed without prefious authority of H.M8s Govt The Bakhtiari position has changed considerably during last few months and may be considerably affected by pending^^ negotiations with Persian Govt. H.M’s Vice-Consul rtoreksaii. visit Teheran in July or August to confer with H.M's Minister. In the meantime no special action seems called for. Addressed India Office repeated General, Teheran !) k ^ • i&amp;f - tfcPH SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. P. ' Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee &lt; /U'&lt; ^,0^'Telegram from Wilson, Ahwaz Dated 18th May 1919* Received 24th at 10 p*m 8 u i i 1,9.19- ^ | I have had long and satisfactory interview with Sheikh of Mohamnerah at Ahwaz and am submitting details hy post. I have also discussed Bakhtiari and Aratdstan question fully with Tice Consul at Ahwaz and will reply pending references on subject of Bakhtiari on my return to Baghdad. Both in regard to Bakhtiari and in Arabistan it has been possible to make very considerable reductions in our expenditure and I do not think that any more can be done in this direction this year, as these reductions have synchronised with great reduction of military strength in this region and a great increase in activities of the Anglo Persian Oil Cos^any. This amazingly fertile region is in better order and more prosperous than ever before and provided that we maintain our present supervision over the local Government its progress is likely to be even more rapid in future. Both in Bakhtian and Arabistan the political barometer is I hope 'Set Fair' for next twelve montne* Addressed to Indie Office.repeated to Tehr™, Stola, Baglai..In any further communication on this subject, please quote So . 63090/W/34. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The'Under-Secretary of State, • Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. INDEXED t £&gt;■ r ^ ^ 0 ^ y h / $ l-m Foiieign Office. 9 til 1919. Ts. Sir, I am directed by Sari Cu/zon of Kedleston to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 2nd instant, No.P.2083, respecting the proposed maintenance of a force of five hundred Bakhtiari Sowars at an 16*000 estimated cost of Sixteen thousand Tomans a month. 2. I am to state, in reply, that Lord Gurzon does not consider - on the material before him - that the moment is opportune, for approaching the Treasury on the subject. 3. A telegram is, however, being addressed to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran calling ioi his observations on the subject and as soon as his reply is received a lurther coiflmunication will be MAY 1919Your telegram ITo *103 (of 8th. February) o India Office have asked the Civil Commissioner Baghdad to supp]y further report on question of effective support to Bakhtiari Ilkb$,ia promised in his telegram Bo *537 » What are ycur views regarding proposed maintenance of 500 Sowars?7of3 Teleqram from Political, Baghdad Dated 28th April 1919 o- Deceived 11 p.m. (IstMay &gt; # : uWvO ? V# \ *■* / . (? / r 4 ^^ Your telegram o- the 23ro. April* Telegram repeated as requested 'Please refer to Foreign end Political Dept, of the Govt, of India’s telegram 450. Wilson will no\ doubt supply further report required while in London . Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Simla. r lb 4 1 / /v DRAFT TELEGRAM. Des] -+ ''\ SECRETARY OF STATE • I l^h TO JIVIL COmUSSIOJ^ER, BAUDAU(ZAFANDO) to soe repeated zq to De repeated to VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) Government of India’s telegram received 17th April. Bakhtiari Sowars, When may I expect further report promised in your telegram Bo.527, 15th January 0 Supply of machine guns to Sardar 2afar was authorised in February last see War Office telegram 75410, 18th February, addressed to G-.O.C. Baghdad and repeated commander-in-chief, India^ Addressed Bagdad, repeated viceroy.tm*- T Telegram from Ticerey, Undated, deceived 1.0. 17 April 1019. 5 p.rWl ol Secret. Tour telegram of the 28th l T arch. Bakhtiari Sowars. We agree generally 'dth views expressed in Baghdad telegram 537, dated January 15th. Protection of oil-fields bv means of levies is an economical form of protection and V has political advantage/ of giving Bakhtiari xxx an additicna/stake in their security and local law n hd order generally. But we are still suiting further •enort promised by Baghdad -and decision on question of xoaonsd machine guns fo February 18th. to Baghdad. Sardar Zafar vide my telegram/ of Addressed to Secrets.:^ ofSt[TJ^s Document _»s the Property of His Britannic Majesty^s ^ove^nment, awd should ba returned to the Fepetgrc Offlcb If not required fot« official use.] * Cypher telegram to Sir p, Cox 3 (Teheran), Foreign Office, February 22nd, 1919, 6*30„p e riu No,116 0 Your telegram No,103 (February 8th, Sirdar Zafar). War Office have informed General Officer Commanding Mesopotamia thut provision of two machine guns as proposed is approved. General Officer Commanding will decide whether' they should he supplied from oil fields or elsewhere. rcEiveo\ ■: Vjp.. 'I'iiwpru. If6294 vmi07 50,000 3/18 DSG(52105) i Form No. 3. WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W. 1. Any further communication on this ^ subject should be addressed to The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W. 1. j and the followins number quoted. | q / to* JiL The Secretary of the War Office presents his compliments to &lt;) v&gt; and is commanded by the Army Council to transmit for the information of )lc-£] a copy of the document noted in the subjoined schedule on the subject of CU\ylWkJMih&amp;\ Date 1 . ta From l^an Description ** cjv'At&amp; uJ)£ ~ v»Letter Telegram from Dated Dec. Formally acknowledged 191 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary. . Secretary of State. Committee / Under Secretary. . Secretary of State. n ~kA. Copy to ^0, Q / FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. £&gt;*-n 'll ' l d l l U J Previous Papers :— y 23210 I 1493 1000 11/17&amp;ro ' \ ■ ' : (2^981/W. 34) $ Ur, The Act ' in s Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs px - esenus his compliments to the Under Secretary of state for India, and begs leave to transmit to him herein a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister in Tehem^urging that two machine guns with ammunition should be supplied to Sirdar Zafar Bakhtiari. uraham is to state, oy direction of ^arl Curzon of Kedleston,, that in His Lordship’s opinion it is desirable to give effect to this xecommendation and hopes that Mr, Secretary Montagu will share his view. L - 30 » Sir i. Graham is to express the hooe that the necessary.instructions will be issued to the Military Authorities concerned. 4. A similar letter has been addressed to the Director of Military Intelligence, ^ FOREIGN OFFICE. , w &gt;g February 15 th 1919 , \{ TELEG-RM FROM CIVIL COMMISSIONER, BAGHDAD, JUTOTi 1 FS+.h .TATJTTAPV^ 1Q19 4 ,3 537. Reference to your telegram No, 10 S repeats telegrara from Secretary of State for India intimating Treasury unwilling to sanction the expenditure on Bakhtiari sowars, I have discussed with G-.O.C.tnChief question of withdrawing troops from Oil fields and have formed opinion^with which G-.Q.C, in fihief concurs that change in situation makes it possible to withdraw troops from vicinity of oil fields as soon as improve ment to road communication between Ahwaz and oil fields now in hand are complete, (Undertaking) agreed it would be most inad visable to withdraw troops from Ahwaz, a very healthy Station where they are well housed in modem lines, and we attach scarcely less importance to maintenance of a detachment at Shush near Dizful and I understand in the post bellum garrison one cavalry Regiment is ear marked for this area. If troops are withdrawn from oil fields, as I think they should be, and if S,P, Rifles cease, as they probably will, to be a factor on which we can reckon in future to stabilize situation from time wo time in Ispahan I am of opinion that in the interests both of oil fields and of our trade between Ahwaz and Ispahan and of our position at latter place we must be prepared for present to give effective support to Ilkhani on lines already proposed. It may be possible to effect some reduction on previous estimates of expenditure and on return from Bakhtiari country of H.M, Uice- Consul I will visit Ahwaz again and discuss the question with him and perhaps the Bakhtiari Khans and submit further report. Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of State for India and Tehran, Copy to General Bagdad who has seen before despatch., SECRETARY OF STATE J TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla)/ ' £ ry sv $ In any further oommunica- t,;n on this subject, please quote Ia Ho, W.Jf /1018, 'V' ^ ddr, c Unrler-Secretary of State, F&lt;.reign Office, London. Jtf- It , w 1 O !CmS ! THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper, Foreign Ojjiee, A-C A , 1918. Reference to previous correspondence : to Letter F Foreign Office : 4^41 f faA-Zf'A A Description of Fnclosure. Name and Date. Subject. £ / M*- A I G !3 K ' ■ -o.nl, iteid beipre tl-ie JuprdB Coum38ioners of ///j 'v^,'m*zvy dir Louis kallet’a letter of the ^ ' /, f ^'bSrtOiT . £&gt;3) ■9 ' * liltiiiiO V /&gt;/M; propotiir^ that a subsidy of /£ , pOO toioaxis a ti^oiald be granted from Indian and ^ ferial funds to th# llknani b^rdar Lafar in order to enable him to maintain a force of 5uu sowars in Bakhtiari territories. In reply 1 am to request you to inform kr. Bearete*y Balfour that my Lords are unable to sanction expenditure. It appears to Them to be indefensible / r\ -the circumstances of the present time to incur an patlay of over £60,0UU a year in order to create and maintain a new force of native soldiers in Persia, without the clearest proof of the necessity for such a course. as mr. Balfour is aware, this chieftain is already in receipt of a subsidy, which however ceases at the end of the war, and the expediency of the additional subvention now proposed appears from the memoranda submitted to have been the subject ol considerable misgiving on the part of His majesty’s kinister at Tehran. The authority given by Treasury letter 2301/17 of the 27th January 1917 for a monthly payment to the Ilkhani of 6000 tomans must now be regarded as having lapsed J'X/*-'— (sdjl.K.. A.,* ^ ./C*..' * ry of State, ice.■ ■ —™ TELEGRAivl FROM VICEROY (FOREIGN) ^ &amp;j DATED 20TH OCTOBER, 1918. ; ^ q (RECD. 21st OCTOBER, 10.30. a.m.) Secret. Your telegram of 30th ult. Bakhtiari Sowars Please refer to Baghdad telegram of 10th October or this question. We support amended proposals. Cox who was consulted agrees. It should be made clear that present rates of payment proposed are temporary and due to famine conditions and that these rates will be reduced later whan circumstances admit.— ; !. v •&gt; tL -J ' • J 1 ■ * 3 x. U-Xco Telegram from Political Officer, Baghdad, to the Secretary of State. v Dated 10th. October 1918. Received at I.O., 11th. 8. 50 p.m. 8577. 10th. Your telegram 21378. Oct 8th received 9th. October enquiring whether recent events of war affect proposal(s) made in my/telegram of 23rd. September last 7920. Anarchy in Persia is always with us and will not stop with the war nor will the Oil Fields be appreciably less vital to our needs after the war. In the absence of a policy of reconstruction throughout Persia under European supervision I think we must go on ‘ subsidising elements who will keep open roads and maintain some sort of order in sphere where we have important interests. We shall no doubt be obliged to retain some forces in Arab!stan after the war but provided we maintain a friendly and effective Ilkhani in office it should not be necessary to retain a garrison on the Oil Fields. Addressed to Foreign repeated to Teheran and Secretary of State for India.w'n' 1 !! / Jv ? TELEGMi FROIG POLITICAL, BAGDAD. DATED 23rd SEPTEMBER, 1918. (EECD. 24th SEPTEHJBER, 1518, 11 a.m.) i L vgj a a, '' -J / ?o ; ; Q ' pnf / i /'OG is telegraphs from Ispahan, September 20th;- 'Present harvest has only partially relieved scarcity in Bakhtiari, barley being nor 8 hrans for 12 pounds. In these circumstances it is impossible to maintain properly equipped force for less than one toman per sowar daily. 500 sowars would thus cost 15,000 tomans monthly exclusive of 1,000 tomans pay of 4 headmen chosen from ruling family, making total of 16,000 tomans. Pay of sowars would be reduced by one Kran daily for each fall of one Kran in price of barley but no considerable fall is expected. Consul General, Ispahan, is/eonsidering employment of Bakhtiari sowars on Ispahan roar- in which case sowars from above force could, be utilised and their pay met by Ispahan Governor. I think such a force would give all support at present required by Illkhani. In order that force may be supplemented at short notice men should not be recruited from frmm armed retainers already in service of Illkhani. I will take steps to (?raise) sowars on receipt of your sanction to above mentioned expenditure.'' I recommend that sanction be accorded and request in structions. The cost estimated in my 6193 July 27th was 10,COO tomans. I do not think a force of less than 500 mounted men would be of use. Addressed Secretary of State, repeated Forei^J Tehran.connected correspondence. Proposal that'British officers and non-coimiiesioned officers should be sent to Khans was put forward in hard-, last and rejectee vide correspondence ending with Foreign Office telegram Ho lal April 6th to Tehran. Reasons which lea G.C.C. Force h local officers to regard suggestion with disfavour still hold ^ good. 4 . regards lo» ot a section of r.omtain sans. Sue eeoiojtf „ sionld be in,Hed?S e t»o gone that «r. nith hi, to Istei- nee very fully considered at Conference at Bafhdadreyerted in try tele-re, of 27th Julyni 6192 end r; ith concurrence in-Chief it definitely decided not to sutadi this oroposel for approval of Government for following reasons. +Vin + a a-oecific request should come from (1) It was essential tnau a speonit. i si^, _ , , - r r- r f-rnri')S with woulo. oe ixsh Ilkh ni. (2) Presence of bru-on-sn troops - ion - liable to arouse suspicions of ulterior aoti.es of British Sort, in Bakhtisri country to »hich Jouneer Khans ere , , . „„ „’ n 4 r g h a ve had far-reaching efiects h.n particularly prone and ..nicn n,n. It Pars.fud Jeci It is not improbable that a demand inay be received later o A * 'from Ilkhsjai under circumstanes which may appear to justify Sj of runs and should tactical situation permit the G-.O.C.-iii-da^ would -be inclined to look ” r ith favour on. their despatch subjejU to VTar Office approval. i Situation is being very carefully watched by H.M. 7: . -Coni Fho follows Ilkhani to high country on 28th inst.and he iiiay be f relied on to initiate further proposals if additions at Ispahaj render this necessary, . Addressee, oo Secretary of State for India repeated to Fore Tehran and Khw^z,J'l*' * • I COPY OF TELEGEAM. Secret- Bakhtiarig We^va repeated Seorstaiy State for Foreign Affairs telegram No 435 dated 20th August to Baghdad in oar telegram Mo.1013 3 and added. £seias° So long as the Brit;.;'' officers and non- commissioned officers are limited to those actually v ? section Mountain Artillery then we see no difficulty, hut if H M G proposes to attach additional officers under pretend of being on strength of Mountain Aiti^Ieiy then we feel that proposal is open to following objections = (1) prolonged presence of British officers and non-commissioned officers might be construed as relieving Zafar and ouher Khans of full responsibilitv for protection of oil fields etc-; y i) (2) it might prove a source of friction particularly with younger Khans and lead to trouble; (3) it might afford a handle to Democrats at Teheran against new and presumably friendly Government and give ground for suspicion that we were introducing So? oR (COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Dated Received at India Office SoPoHo scheme into Bakhiiari country^ (4) there may fee difficulty in sparing really suitable officerso If however after consideration of proposal in all its bearings Sardar Zafor cordially puts it forward, these objections would probably fall to the ground. Please discuss matter with &amp;_0 = C. Force '0' and telegraph views repeating to Secretary of State for India, Teheran, Endso»HP' UJJ From Political, Baghdad, Dated 15th August, 1918, Reed. 17th 11 a.m. 6702. My telegram August 12th, 6612. Following from Consul, Shiraz August 14th:- 5'LAj6 / £&lt;Vt/'V 'News received that rumoured- Kazem Khan with (1000?) Darashuris has occupied Abadeh and Soulat- es«*Sultaneh also is said to be approaching that town. As your Deputy Governor has taken his departure (group undecypherable) would it be possible to get force of 500 Bakhtiaris to move to Semirun to threaten Darashuris families? If they went could they be relied on not to join enemy? Ilbegi (?under the circumstances) returns to Shiraz from Firuzabad to-day and whatever action he takes is certain to be dilatory. Capture of Abadeh will have very (4 groups undecypherable) effect on tribe generally, Governor-General will take such steps as he can from here. Addressed Ispahan 124 repeated to Tehran 150, Bushire, Government of India, Bagdad'* In view of possibility of renewed disturbances on Ispahan-Shiraz road I trust decision of His Majesty 1 s Government on the subject of Government of Indians telegram 877S July 31st will be communicated as soon as possible.i /'A | %Jr XaT W *•* rThis Pocum-aret is the Property of His Bpitsmnic be ^turned to the Ferci^n QfTice if not Irequi^ed Majesty’s 4: \ j 5 iiH Gyoher telegram to Sir 0. Marling (Teheran) , foreign uttice. Augnet 14th.1918. IG.r.m. No. 481. Your tele:gramNo. 664 (of July 30th.Sir Jar Zafar.) Hi a Majesty’a Government have given careful consideration to your view that uronosea arrangement ••-j-qy conceivably nroluce tribal jealousy and thereby jeonarlize secutiry of Almaz read; but in all the circumstances they consid&amp;r that nrobable advantages of the arrangement will outweigh this uossible risk, qnl have decided to adont the recommendation* — —# embodied in Bagdad izBlegram Ho. 6193 of July 37th. You 'should therefore instruct His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz to concert v rith Doctor. Young -as to be y st means of giving effect to these arrangements. It has been suggested that in viewy of the excellent effect nroduced on the BoMbtiaris by tne Mountain Artillery Alii ch. co-operated with them against, the Kuhgelus, it would he advantageous tor a section to be- made -available .-tor use ’Vith the proposed levy, ,vad this might enable a few British officers and non- -^g,} officers to . be attached. It seems however most de ;'it_r-. tnat_ ^_ r gther than with originate with rakhjtian tneraeeiv.. &gt; U&lt;3 ' I should be gled of your views on this noint. Here a.ted bo Indi^.U^fer from Secret Department. Dat Bee Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. To Under Secretary... w Secretary of State... f 'tiM SUBJECT. (X_ Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State CgVjjLA.c^MsV^- .ill) The Political Secretary The proposal is strongly supported by the Military Department for the reasons given by Captain Wilson-al so attention is dravn to a paper addressed to War Cabinet dated 28th July 1918 signed by General Sackville West.Versailles Council. In the eventuality discussed in that paper at page 8 paragraph 4 we may find that a levy force of this kind which can live on the country and move with little or no transnort would be invaluable* There seems little prospect of equally good levies being successfully raised in Jtocxfe West Persia and we are not likely to get as good an offer again. I think that no'time should be lost in accepting it,especially as it would be largely a mounted Force. In view of the excellent effect / produced on the Bakhtiaris by the Mountain Artillery section which co-operated with them against the Kuhgelus it might perhaps be possible to arrange for a section to be made available for use with the proposed levy^and this migit enable a feiv British officers and IMon-commissioned Officers to be attached. These should be available from Dunsterforce. In addition to the advantages of such a Force / as given in telegram dated 27th July 1918,No.6193,from Political Baghdad / it would be valuable for protecting the South West portion of the Kasr-i- Shirin-Ehzeli Road and possibly might supply detachments for service beyond it. It will be remembered that Bakhtiari detachments under one of the minor Khans served with the Turkish Forces on the Kermanshah road,and were intercepted and disarmed by our troops when returning to- their own country.Also such a force would keep the Kashgais in check along the Shiraz-Isfahan road. It must be remembered with reference to the 3.P.R. that the recent trouble was wholly in the Shiraz Brigade largely composed of men who had served in the former Gendarmerie officeredofficered by Swedes and who had previously acted against us at Shiraz. Moreover the S.P.R.is composed of units with huropean officers whilst the proposed levy would be under their own tribal chief who would be personally responsible for them. Cj^ August, 1918. h Ji m Ji u IptiI P Vh f v^, V PERSIA ivJ? JvjJ. bf- Bakhtiari Offer of Military Assistance. (Note by Political Department, India Office.) of His* SiElgXSSSXtm a Si'' ‘ST — ft. csitaw rsstra®?* r*.- ,k t s - “ i. SwSrJ y h“r s esH S”IS=t‘? ‘TrA~'2y£ * ss±r- sas&amp;^SSsKl^ “ t v A P The p! ;° iect was r T’ ive - d in March 1918, when it was suggested that some of be sfOo tbe BakhHr iSSI0 T d ^ Hcel i S ° f the ori S inal Punst^ilk M'SNXuU Sn G. Marling, the,Government of India, or the military and political a,nhoHties u Mesopotamia and it was not proceeded with. The “ forward nioyement fioni Slnraz to Ispahan never materialised. 3 The objections to the proposal of March 1918 were mainlv ha^ed nn tLa Umt the dfA 1 !, ° f * e Bakhtians themselves. Thus, Sir C. Mailing-considered t] t . . Nkans Mould strongly object to appearance of officers and non commissmned officers m Bakhtiaristan; the Commander-in-Chief in India mged t ie piltnaJ / fdct( ? L 18 tliat we should do nothing to alienate the Bakhtiari Khans B r-’-l ^ ind ®P'f 13 dent, powerful and sensitive regarding outside interference' the Civil Commissioner, Bao-hrlnrl tEp.^o-Lf A. ,• VC 7em e Baghdad, tho ic N h i 'T^VnT kJi T' LV '' 1 ’ J -’ u a uu ^ u 5 uioiight mat me suggestion would not be acceptable to Ilkham at present. The project now under consideration is clearlv differentiated from its predecessors in that it is based on a spontaneous offer on‘the part of the Bakhtiari Chiefs. It arises out of a proposal made by the Ilkhani to the idh Bdv 1C “?° a aZ ’ T ) transmitted 1 i,i Gaptaiu Wilson’s telegram of the bth J uly, to taise at once and place at our disposal 5,000 good cavalry for service agamy the Kashgais or elsewhere.” Captain Wilson has since discussed the Ilkhani s offer personally with the Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, and Dr. Young the medical officer at the oilfields, who has a long and intimate acquaintance with Bakhtiari affans. As a result, he has formulated the following concrete proposals : (1) ^ lat Nkhani (Sardar Zafar) should be invited to maintain a force of 1 500 men (J ,000 of them mounted) under his own command; (2) I hat another 300 rifles with 100 rounds apiece should he given him for the purpose (though this is not considered essential for the present) • (3) That these arms should be prepared and sent to the oilfields for' deliverv in the autumn when the Ilkhani returns to the low country (it is not orwwl 01 ' 6 ' ? at any i Jur ! lier arms would be required, except perhaps oO,000 rounds to replenish ammunition expended in the recent Bakhthri campaign against the Kuhgelu) ; (4) Tliat, in order to keep this force in the field, we should be prepared to mv bardar Zafar from 8,000 to 10,000 tomans a month from now until suih time as having regard to the general situation in Persia, the force can be safely disbanded ; ^ ut. S 18 40 8/18 ** o. J(5) That this expenditure should be supervised by the Vice-Consul at Ahwaz, who would not disburse unless satisfied of the proper application of the funds ; and (6) That no fixed sum should be mentioned to the Khans, but that the Vice- Consul should be given discretion to pay out amounts up to the above maximum. 4. The objects of maintaining the proposed force in the Bakhtiari country are summarised by Captain Wilson as follows :— (1) To stabilise situation in Ispahan likely to become periodically precarious unless some such force is in vicinity. (2) To maintain authority of Ilkhani in Bakhtiari territories. This is the one effective means of protecting the oilfields. (3) The above force is a nucleus which could be doubled or trebled in emergency, and could, under the leadership of the Ilkhani, or of his nominee from among young Khans, advance much further afield than Bakhtiari limits if necessary. With Ilkhani in charge there will be no question of force being used by us to acquire political or territorial influence, a possibility to which younger Khans are keenly alive. 5. Captain Wilson’s proposals were submitted with the concurrence of the General Officer Commanding, Baghdad. They have also received the “cordial suppoit of the Government of India, who regard them “as calculated to secure “ continued co-operation of Sardar Zafar and goodwill of bulk of Bakhhari tribe, and to piovide a substantial check on discordant elements at Ispahan and elsewhere ” (Viceroy’s telegram of 31st July 1918). The only dissentient voice is that of Sir C. Marling {sec his telegram No. 664 of 30th July)’' who regards the proposals with ‘‘ considerable misgivings,” and argues that the arrangement contemplated “ is in “ effect an engagement with^ Zafar personally, and . not as Ilkhani, to retain him in u m letmn for which he is to keep up a body of sowars to be employed in our “ interests.” This, m Sir C. Marling’s opinion, is calculated to arouse the jealousies of the other Khans, and to produce a combination against Sardar Zafar which is likely to end m an appeal by the latter for our armed assistance. He apprehends that the proposal will “bring about a split in the tribe, the result of which would be insecurity on the Ahwaz road.” Replying to the Minister’s criticisms, Captain Wilson observed (telegram No. 6270, 31st July) that the objections advanced would “apply t( ec P a lly to any constructive proposals which have for their object the maintenance m power ^ in the Bakhtiari country or elsewhere of a party favourable to British mteiests After discussion with the local officers, he had come to the conclusion that the risk of a hostile combination against the Ilkhani “was remote and could be considered as negligible if he had the 1,500 sowars and our support.” He a-ain mged the adoption or his proposals as “a constructive attempt to stabilise the situation m the Bakhtiari country and Ispahan,” and drew attention to the results PaS ■ m i ' r0mthe po to'°f giving active support t'o tW 6. The question is now ripe for an early decision by His Majesty’s Government On the one hand it may be argued that the immediate emergency which the Ilkhani’s oiler was designed to meet has passed away with the defeats the KashgaL and Te general improvement of the military situation in South Persia ; and that there seems no gieat likelihood of a reversion to conditions m which Bakhtiari military assistance would be essenhal to us Moreover our recent experiences with the South Persia lirfles in the Shiraz area (though less unfavourable than was at one time be eve h can scarcely be regarded as an encouragement to further experiments with id r ? On (he other hand, Sardar Zafar’s offer affords an exceptionally favourable opportunity oi committing the powerful Bakhtiari tribe definitely to our cause Tbi, -l . suc cesses over the Kuhgeln (to which our loan of aVonnVinTunN ectt 1 a.^ Oil Sir C. Marling’s criticisms. ’ on a* S ° m ? to' 161 ' c0 ' n “™ ts the Minister himself, in a telegram dated the 19th July viz that “ the o„lv , P( mcl P le enunciated by is to pay local leaders to use their followers• and 1 e adds tL, lj r °, employ local *»«• Ilkhani and llbegi have a strong party wUli them irenaref to owS TW g . ° hu the provided the proposals go through, the Khans are prepared, so long ns we vrish it toZf’ V ^ with the Russian troops m Ispahan. 8 y visn it, to work m harmonyvA C \ contributed) has not only put the tribe on vorv ovwi + vi 7 had an excellent effect upon our own relations with the Kinns The V'^ p bUt h* Ahwaz declares that the Bakhtiari leaders “tt-p ' + ^ lce -^onsul at •rib.«,»* to*, o™,-: , 1 ,;' v •- ^«. - very pleased with themselves and^eady for anythino-'” ‘I t] ! eKllan ® £ are evidently South Persia Rifles cannot be presld ^ A ^gies drawn from the popularly regarded in Persia as a 1 } he South Persia Rifles are Government against its will; and a handle 1m Thls'Teen'alven ^ P f s ! an and will remain under his per onal colrh md wdl Kn ?geStl01 \ 01 ‘ he 1 i E ad of t]l « ‘^be . Taking all the circumstanksTnto con h era ion he'nf ai \ eUtl ? ly dlfferent P osili “'- to the opinion that the present oppokuni^ oi, it incliued Wilson’s proposals, which have so henw « p m P Pc 10t t0 )e l 08 ?’ an P tllat Captain should be approved by His Majesty’s Governnient ° e * Pert opiulon “ their fav ™ r » Sir Herbert Koi^^- tr ° n8ly SUpp0rted by the Iudia Office Military Department. “ In certain eventualities we may find that a levy force of this kind which can Ine on the country and move with little or no transport would be invaluable raised Rwl ^ ^ 1 prospect of good levies being successfully thinP t a n u e f 6 n0t llkely t0 get; as S’ ood an offer again. I lV a tllafc no tlm ® f oald Pe iost 111 accepting it, especially as it would be aigely a mounted force. In view of the excellent effect produced on the Bakhtiaris oy the Mountain Artillery section which co-operated with them against the Ruhgelus it might^ perhaps he possible to arrange for a section to be made available for use with the proposed levy, and this might enable a lew British ofhcers and non-commissioned officers to be attached. These should be available from Dunsterforce. In addition to the advantages of such a force as stated by the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad [see paragraph 41, it would be valuable for protecting the south-west portion of the Kasr-i- . ^uj^Hnzeli road, and possibly might supply detachments for service beyond d. it will be remembered that Bakhtiari detachments under one of the minor Khans served u ith the lurkish forces on the Kermanshah road and w T ere intercepted and disarmed by our troops when returning to their own countiy. Also, such a force would keep the -Kasbgais in check along the oinraz-Ispahan road. lc It must be remembered, with reference to the South Persia Rifles; that the recent trouble was wholly in the Shiraz Brigade, largely composed of men who had served m the former gendarmerie officered by Swedes, and who had pieviously acted against us at Shiraz. Moreover, the South Persia Rifles are composed of units with European officers, whilst the proposed levy would under their own tribal Chief who would be personally responsible for them.” J. E. S. Political Department, India Office, 9th August 1918.. r JL TELEGRAM FROM VICMRO^-C-J Dated 7th August 1918. Received 9th at 8 a.m* 4f,# ^ ^ ro dHi \^' i~td ! A*'. • * ” • •••••'• / k Secret. Our telegram of 31st July,877S. Persia. ?/ilson telegraphs further comments on Minister’s telegram 664 July 30th. [^Firstly. See my telegram 6191 dated July 27th. Whereas H.M.Minister Teheran anticipated that Sardar Zafar would refuse to undertake operations against Kashkai he willingly offered all assistance in hss power when approached. This has some hearing on H.M. Minister’s estimate of Sardar Zafar ! s (?powers) in present case. Secondly. H.M.Minister telegraphed on July 19 to F.Q. ” 'My Persian friends ..... assure me that .... only way to employ local forces is to pay local leaders to use their followers, &amp;c. 1 ,f . The proposals under consideration are based on this sound principle which has been consistently acted agon in the sphere of this force since the outbreak of war. Thirdly, My information is that present Dakhani and Ilbegi already have a strong party with them prepared to give effect to proposals. They consider that they have support of Sardar Asad and Sardar Jang vide my 5909, July 18. Amir Mujahid i^s also pledged to support Zafar. Fourthly. I understand from Vice Consul, Ahwaz, that provided these proposals go through, Khans are prepared so long as we wish it to work in harmony with Russian troops in Ispahan. M'*“'V Telegram i roi/i /iceroy, Foreign uq^y Dated Slat July,1918, H-® Received at 1.0. 6 p.ra, 3rd August. X Secret. Bakhtiaria. Reference your telegram of the 24th July and Baghdad telegrain 6,193 27th July. We cordially support Baghdad's proposals as calculated to secure continued cooperation of Sardar Zafar and goodwill 0 f bulk of Bakhtiari tribe,and to provide a substantial check on discordant elements at Isfahan and elsewhere. Addressed to S.of 3. and repeated to Baghdad and Teheran.TELEGRM FROM POLITICAL, BAGHDAD. 31st JULY 1S18. ^ (Received 1st August 1918. 2.30 p.m.) V- 6270. Objections urged in Tehran telegram 377 apply equally to any constructive proposals which have for their object maintenance in power in Bakhtiari country or elsewhere of a party favourable to British interests. I discussed this aspect of question with local officers and came with them to conclusion that risk,of hostile combination against Ilkhani was remote and could be considered as negligible if he had the 1500 Sowars and our support. I submit proposals under consideration which are supported by all local officers concerned represent a constructive attempt to stabilise aituation in Bakhtiari country and Ispahan. H.M. Minister makes no counter suggestions and appears to prefer a negative policy. Issue is one for decision of H.M.G. having regard to results attained in Bakhtiari country during past twelve months by policy of giving active support to present Ilkhani. Addressed Foreign repeated Secretary of State Tehran, Ispahan.X mtijs Oocument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Gove™me„t. and ■ ^g- retur,ned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] sfn-ould ■ r \ f n ,^ : -v i M I 19 S 8 EmV ehfir^i), j\iiy 3ot 1 i. 39] De cy-&gt;He r . 31 r c _ ], Iarl ^ :J / D. 4.35.n.m. July 30th.1918. 9 B.O.'i.ni. July 31st,.1918. Nj . 664. .... .. j. oil ui 08,1 Ba,- 2 jv 1 .ad tiOle ^ro'n 'to Secratiory of Stote for In 61a 6193. I ra^ar 6 ^co’ooaal with cow her able miegivinge * Conte-nuiated agreement Is in effect an enyagesient marten u n .49 f •• r, pe r a ow ally y anh .wot os etekhani , to ret air hlm in office in return for which he is to keen up a DQ H y oi sowars to he emloyei. in our interests This is calculated to arouse jealousy of the other Khans who woul^ combine to eject him from ^ekijanishin anf it would not arohably he long before Zafar called on us to give him armed sunnort which means increasing our military liabilities. If any arrangement of this kind is made Zafar must norm a w rtg nledged to carry it out and in my opinion the t-vo who ar - now acting with him do not alone possess the requisite standing or influence. Proposal is calculated to bring about split in the tribe ress.lt of which would be insecurity on the Ah-waz road. Addressed to Foreign Office. 664 repeated to Indi.j. Bagdad and Ispahan. r!UO [This Document is the P^Ojpe^ty of Has Ba^itairiinic IVlaJestys Government, and should be ye turned -to the Foirei^ra Office if not pepuiijed fot* official uae.j Cypher telegram to Sir G fl marling* (Teheran)„ Foreign Office, July 31st»1918 0 IT t 40.p.m. No* 390, Urrent* Please let me hear your observations on telegram of 27th July from Political., Baghdad No, £193 to Government of India respecting Bakhtiaristan proposals.. (.31,7* 8-4) *1/ V r® / J [P 3274 From Political, Baghdad f '27th July 1918. ^ .^(Addressed to Foreign, Simla, repeated to Secretary of State for India, Teh ran, and, Ispahan.) (Received 8 p.m., 28th.) HI.) ()193. ^ Your telegram of 25th July, 852 S. Ilis Majesty s VJce-Oon&amp;id, Ahwaz, and Dr. Young have come at my request to Baghdad, to confer on Bakhtiari matters. Former lias just returned from accompanying Ilkhani on most successful campaign for many | r ears against Kuhgilu tribes, resulting in very complete subjugation of these elusive enemies of law and order. Bakhtiari road is now safe for next two years from Kuhgilu raiders. Ilkhani and Illbegi are elated and ready to co-operate with us to any extent, success of recent operations being due entirely to assistance rendered to them by two mountain guns with personnel lent by General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, to 5,000h given Khans, as reported in my telegram 6220, dated 21st December, and to 300 rifles, with ammunition, given in January 1918. After full discussion with Peel and Young, I submit following proposals, and am authorised by General Officer Commanding-in-Chief to say they have his concurrence so far as he is concerned :— 1. An assurance of continued support to be given to present .Ilkhani Sardar Zafar. He lias made good m spite of adverse cir cumstances and has justified confidence placed in him by local officers; his willingness to co-operate against Kashgais shows he feels himself to be in a strong position always provided we ‘continue to back him. In this connection please see my telegram 5920 dated 18th July. 2. That Sardar Zafar be invited to maintain a force of 1 .500 pi eked men, of whom 1,000 mounted under his own command. This is as many as can conveniently be kept permanently on a war footing. The proposal to raise 5,000 was made to meet an emergency, and this number could not be kept together for very long. Another 300 rifles with 100 rounds each should be given for them but this is not essential at present. Arms should be prepared and sent to oil-fields for delivery in autumn when Ilkhani returns to low country. No further arms would be required except, perhaps, 30,000 rounds to replenish ammunition expended in recent campaign. To keep this force in field we should be prepared to pay Zafar from 8 to 10 thousand tomans a month from now till such time as force can, having regard to situation in Persia, be safely disbanded. Expenditure would be supervised by His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, who would not disburse unless satisfied that funds were being devoted to maintenance of force on above basis. Above sum not to be mentioned to Khans and amounts be paid up to above maximum at Vice-Consul’s discretion. Objects of maintaining this force in Bakhtiari country are as follows :— 1. To stabilise situation in Ispahan likely to become periodically precarious unless some such force is in vicinity. 2. To maintain authority of Ilkhani in Bakhtiari territories. This is the one effective means of protecting the oil-fields. 3. The above force is a nucleus which could be doubled or trebled in emergency, and could under the leadership of the Ilkhani, or of his nominee from among young Khans, advance much further afield than Bakhtiari limits if necessary. With Ilkhani in charge there will be no question of force being used by us to acquire political or territorial influence, a possibility to which younger Khans are keenly alive. /, f ) NTS# O • ^ l &gt; W ' •’Me Telegram from Politics,1,Baghdad Dated 27th July 1918 Received 3 p.m. (28th), X my* fan vV CM I \m) i O'''’ 6191, 7 1 4 a ; d Following was coiiment of H. M. *8 Minister on proposals contained in my telegram of 18th July 5920*/’ ■Sg&amp;fai* I see ( ? no objection) but I anticipate that Zafar will refuse to undertake so formidable an enterprise which w would moreover entail lasting quarrel between Bakhtiaris and Kashgais* I shall say nothing to Kharf's here who would certain ly veto it. Ends . Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State S&gt; ^ ryi KVf- J TELESEIAM from Dated 26th July, 1918 (received I.O. 3.0 p.m. ) Your telegram 5920. July 18th. Demonstration of Bakhtiari co-operation will doubtless have valuable effect. Before considering Ilkhani's offer to raise 5,000 Sowars, Government of India would like to know whether we should be expected (1) to arm them, (2) to contribute to their maintenance, and if so to what extent, and (3) for what purpose they would be employed apart from co-operation against Kashgai which seems required no longer. Addressed to Baghdad, repeated Secretary of State for India, Tehran and Ispahan*9&amp;' ti '-m. ) / / ta Bmi I S h^J f ‘L ^A./t&gt; vv v\ (% . S^'h^P 2 Pram Political, Bacjhclad, 18th July 1918. {Addressed Jo Foreign, repeated to Secretanj of State fo, India and Teheran.) (Received 19th, 8 a.m.) P f t)92(, n ? 11 TT rece l i P fc o£ your telegram of C.tli Jidv I tele^rapbed to 3( ’ HlS M 'V est K S Vice - Ooilsd &gt; who was with Sardm Zafar m u igdu u.anuy, north of Behan, instructing him to discuss with Sardar Zafai measures necessary to, relieve Abadehf, adding that he mioht guarantee him his expenses up to any reasonable limit, and that Genmal 7 f Cei ;°inma 11 (1 111 g- 1 n-( hief had agreed that two mountain guns now with (fif TCw'? ht aCC01 S 1 Pany 11111 • lt was Sl1 ^sted that an advance by Baklitiari ha/erun oi bhiraz was more practicable than on Abadeh, and with concuuence oi IIis Majesty s Munster 1 instructed His Majesty’s Vice-Consul to discuss this with Zafar also. ^ 1 telegraphs^— n *° W reply ' of His Majesty’s Vice-Consul; he ‘’ We have come to the conclusion that any attempt to relieve Abadeh Horn this side is doomed to failure. Zafar has therefore (r wired) to Amir Mujahid and his own son m Chahar Mahal addressing Consul-General Ispahan, to start at once' with 1,000 picked cavalry in order to relieve A badeli. if the garrison can holdout for another fortnight there is everv prospect of their relief, derms of telegram are also calculated to have a restraining effect on Murtaza Knli and his gang. Ilkham and flbegi will leave for the north in a few days and ask me to assure Consul-General, Ispahan, that they are ready to render any assistance he may require. “ Khan expects no reward except that in future we will extend to them preferential treatment over such of their brothers as are now hostile to us. “ Zafar is also prepared to raise at once and place at our disposal 5,000 good cavalry for service against Ivashgais or elsewhere, and I would strongly urge serious consideration of this offer. Point To be emphasised is that Zaiar Aslija and hatch are with us to last man and have tribes at their back. V ith such a force we could very soon restore order in Central and Southern Persia and fill gap caused by partial collapse of Southern Persia Rifles. “ Very early orders on this point are solicited as the Khan leaves for north in a few days.” Above is optimistic estimate of capability of proposed force, but Khans are evidently very pleased with themselves and r eady for anything, and force should furnish useful co-operation in the north with the Bushire force. I request instructions.From C.G.S., India. 1 f D «. M. I e Despatched at 11 p. 16.7.18. Received at 12.30 a*m, 18.7.18. 55428 M.0.1* July 16th. Under date July 3rd further details from Sykes received as follows :~ Kashgais have been informed that under new Ilkhani they couid migrate northwards unmolested. Sykes considered he would soon be able to clear Shiraz Valley of enemy and re-establish telegraph communication. Supplies in excess of consumption o.re being got in slowly. Ke considered Dehbid should be safe . As regards Abadeh report from Ispahan by escaped S.P.R. who left Abadeh July 6th states 250 rebels P.R. f and 300 Kashgais are investing that place, but they are short of ammunition and if not reinforced may disperse • Up to July 6th our casualties were said to be 1 British Officer and 12 men killed. Abadeh he considered in no .immediate danger. Ispahan reports commandant Persian Cossacks unwilling to send relief force for Abadeh until arrival of reinforcements which left Teheran on July 7th. On July 12th reinforcing column from Banderabtas arrived Gakim half way to Saidabad. C .2. Copies to :~ M.I.l .a.Reference telegram from Viceroy,Foreign Dent, dated let July I9IB. In this telegram reference is made to the 0-in~ ‘ haing asked Ceneral ! arshall (not the Resident at lushire) whether i)unBterville , s force could despatch n contingent in care to the relief of our posts, ac have examined this here and have come to the same con clusion as General ''arshall,in the telegram that I sat from him this morning,! o•1992? of 1st July,vis., that it is not a practicable proposition. The cars will have to carry so much ammunition,petrol,and food,thf there will be no room for fighting men. The latter part of the telegram refers to the steps in the political direction that are o In this connection it is fortunate that the A * agmm 547 of the 29th June had been sent before tHI &lt; out break was reported here. It is undfrsheo • that a telegram has gone to our Minister -t r ^ cm giving him what is virtually a free hand ir tiations to conciliate and saci-.'c in# good of the lersian Govt,with n vW to obiainit assistance in quelling the disturbances wh led to the isolation of our military post* however,urge that at the same time the l I should be given a very solemn warning th either cannot or will not bestir itself in this matter,and in spite of our conci deavaur,the inevitable result will be t have to occupy such portions of Tetnii situation demands either without a / or after a declaration of war,and^ not in a position for variously 7try*' ir , %.•***- i tluP^ ^ ' f No^V Jv A &lt;H*' r ' vi ''' 1 ,, » 4.. «fi..,, !K. '*f'i8»W‘ C ^8 operations at prenent^w© shall V.c very shortly, viz., by the beginning of the winter, md even then % : 9 shall be nearer and ?aox'e able to strike than any of our onenies who may wish to intafrfere on ersia 1 © behalf. If political negotiations have no effect,it is impossible to so© how the rescue of the isolated posts can b© effected in time. Fui it ©aems from the telegrams from Teheran that the situation is not quit© so serious ao the Uovt.of India* a telegram would lead one to believe.^ Then discussing the subject of Possible military operations this morning with dir Arthur Idrtzeljw ©u created the possibility of moving through Ahwai by the Lynch road on Ispahan as being in several ways advantageous. The Eakhtia ris are friendly,and,if the situation domandn concessions to theta,could probably be broupiit still more decidedly on our side. lacked by mobile troop© B they are sufficiently powerful to be able to seiss© and ke^v Ispahan and. the province,and, incidentally^© should thus cover what is our most nrociouis ixissoesion in I arsia - the Oil ells. * The total distance from fdiwnr to Ispahan is 281 miles,in 18 stages. This road may be divided into four stages,vis., (1) Plain section,Ahmz to falmioh ... 40 miles (2) Low Hill section,Salmich to I.aleair 69 (3) Mountainous section,ibalnmir to Kharaji 104 (4) Upland section,Kharaji to Ispahan 60 f — 1 N2503 30 *afK r * fiat tfc.» Lynch road was open and safe ns far as a want 44 uiles aouth-west of Ispahan. X colutan of rsiipilar troops operating along the Lynch road beyond Atom* would-be ©(Mpletaly equipped with pack anjla 'transport. 'The cotwunications between J'uharanemh and Ahwa* (about IOC miles) are both by river and road; so ahwas would fona a convenient advance base. I think we should do well to strantfiten our de- tachBsnta at f hwa,i at once,provided that doing so sill not irritate the Pakhtiari clans,and 1 believe tnat if and when operations become necessary it will be or .reran/ advantageous to us to ba able to enter ersie fro J - ushira, from Ahwaz ,and by strong re- connaiasance^tooaiSs Teheran from the nearest point on the Koraanehah--nzeli road, vi*. .Kasvin,which is only about 100 miles from the Capitijl. A combined operation of this kind should cause the complete col lapse of any hostile resistance. (Sd) H.7.C0X. T/7/I8. ■ |Prom: - G.o.c. in c„ Mesopotamia. Deep. 11 .5 p. TO , 1,7.16,. T °' C ' ln Inaia - Rood. 1.50 a„m. 2.7,18, E e pe a t e d Wa: a Office, Teheran •5c Bunsterforce a X 9027, July 1st. It appears that the purport of your olll 7 Today has been already wired by Marling to Dunsterforce. The reply repeated to me. (begins) I am unable to help Abadoh. Even if petrol was available which is not the case none of my armoured oars are in a condition to travel that distance, (ends). 1 am wiring Dunsterf orce to know if ho has any Ford Vans to spare and if he considers he can reach Abadeh and back with them, and to Marling to know if in Teheran there is any petrol available but ?from the map the distance to Abadeh from Teheran is 400 miles, On average roads in Persia in summer a Ford Van can do 15 miles to the gallon therefore a minimum of 540 lbs of petrol per van must bo carried from Teheran gor the double journey. I do not consider the proposition to be feasible as its load is only 600 lbs and as, in addition to petrol, following must also be carried fighting personnel levde ammunition supplies for journey etc. :Document is the Pr operty of His temtannic, M^cesty s Governmenfc, a^d sho M 8d be ^ettar’ned to the Foreign Office if imot pequared for official use.! y Y | ' Nl * 1 ‘ ? I I I I I Foreign Office, July 1st, 1918, S.15 p.m, NO. 353 (K,) oOO 1^r» •• Ifery yrf-ent^ Government of India telegram July 1st, If the facts are as stated in this telegram you ard authorised to make any conciliatory offers which you think necessary or desirable to save the situation, I fear I must leave to you the decision of whether any such offers should be made feeling assured that you Will weigh.well the dangers of yielding to Persian violence what we had refused to their argument. Whatever course you decide to take will have my full support* f 4w * Vom v; Mroij, Foreign Department, 1st July 1913. {Repeated to Tehran and Baghdad.) (Received at India Office, 6.30 p.m.) r n&gt; . pru Tehran has doubtless informed Foreign Office of report that enemv have occupied Abadeh town and telegraph office, that all South PeW 'D h K aVe deserte d&gt; and that British officers and Indian troops are holding out m ban acts, telegraph north of Abadeh is cut. There are about Rai'putVhi fS i an T. UOU r° mlmSS10ned 0ilicers and 3 platoons of 16th J1 A ilili.-, 1 h f y , llare provisions for one month and plenty of ammumtion. D^bid with 2 British officers and 1 platoon of Raipnte is c~s nce i8,h nr r ted “V s , Shira f. « llence '' e no communi cation since 18th June. Early relief from Gulf side is impossible hommander-m-Ohief therefore is telegraphing to DuHtOl repeating to War Office asking whether Bunsterville’s force can despatch a loice m cars to relief. ^ But there appears to us little prospect of such force e'en &gt;t available, arriving m time or being adequate to deal with what appears to be widespread rising. Only hope, now unfortunately but slender of averting serious catastrophe which must involve war with Persia appears to he m getting 1 ersian Government to move energetically in the matter and to send messages by telegram and thence onward by urgent messengers to tribal leaders to cease hostilities pending a settlement Effective^ operation of I ersian Government can only be secured by real conciliation more genuine character than that contemplated in your telegram (? of the 29tli June). ■Document is the Prepe^ty of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] I f n i MILITA5Y. Decypher. Sir C.Marling (Teheran) June 29th, 1918, a D. 4.4c p.in. June 29th, 1918 / 1 'O ^ R. 8 a.m. July 1st, 1918 NO, 589, I \ „ I f •#ooaooto«o Following from Consul at Ispahan June 29th, Begins, Eneiry sending (? reinforcements) Abadeh town and fighting in progress since last night. Borne desertions from South Persia Rifles but others so far remain loyal. Captain Winter shot but whether killed or not is not clear. Communication at present Interrupted, Addressed to Foreign Office No, 589, Repeated to India, Baghdad and General Dimsterville, (1.7 8/4).From:- C. in C., India. To:- D.M.I. Despatched 5.25 p.m. 4th April, 1918. Received 8.45 a.m, 5th April, 1918. 26281. April 4th. Operations. Marshall’s views were asked for on proposal in Foreign Office telegram No.161 to Tehran. Following is his repljr:- views are generally in accordance with your 24895 March 30th just received but I will send a further reply on receipt of information called for from G-.O.C. Karun front and political”. Ends, .and in continuation now wires as follows:- ”1 do not agree with the formation of Bakhtiari levies under British officers and non-commissioned officers. I consider tbrr we should do what we can by means to strengthen the authority of Sardar Zaffar and for maintenance of his collies as a useful ally. The loan of a few British officers to help him might be necessary but Vice-Consul at Ahwaz will shortly discuss Bakhtiari affairs with Sardar Zaffar at Ahwaz and I propose that Vice-Consul should ascertain best means of helping Zaffar on lines acceptable to latter”. Ends.COPY OF TVT.VCTAp ^roia Politieal, Bagdad. Dated 4th April, 1918, Reed. 5th ' 11,45 a.m. ######## ###### vii). 3011. Reference to current telegraphic corrsapondeir between far Office and Military Authorities in India and Mesopotamia regarding proposal made by Foreign Office to Minister for despatch of British Officers to raise levies in Bakhtiari country. Proposal will not bs placed before Ilkhani by His Majesty's Vice-Consul et forthcoming meeting at Ahwaz unless explicit instructions are received by him on subject from His Majesty’s Minister. In view of correspondence on the subject in 1917 and subsequent developments I do not think suggestion would be acceptable to Ilkhani at present. Addressed Foreign, repeated Secretary of State* Teheran, Ahwaz.SECRET. ^L£J R A T I 0 ^ . From C. in C., India. To War Office, Repeated G-.O.C,, Mesopotamia. Despatched 8 20 p.m. 20th March, 1918. neceived 1.25p.m. 21st March, 1918. 24892. March 20th. Reference to Foreign Office telegram dated March 22rd no.161 to Marling regarding suggestion that some officers of Dunaterforce should proceed to Bakhtiaristan to organise levies there. The military value of these levies will be in the protection they will afford to Marshall’s right flank to tne oilfields, ana their effect on Sykes position at Ispahan should he move there. In all these considerations the primary factor is that we should do nothing to alienate the Bakhtiari Khans who as you know are independent, powerful and sensitive regarding -putside interference. Before deciding to ? send strange officers upon an unasked for errand it seems prudent to prepare the way carefully, and I would submit That our first step should be to ascertain from the Khans what would be their views on the levies proposal. Dr. Young who resides in the oilfields knows the Bakhtiari Khans better than any other officer immediately available and would be a good intermediary to place before the Khans the advantages which they could derive, pecuniary, military and political, from the levies. i i»/ _ ■ f; i ! ■ if j ^ 8 ; ifMILITARY. PERSIA. Decypher. Sir C. Marling (Teheran). March 25th. D. 6.30 p.m. March 25th, .1918, R. 2.45 p.m. March 26th, 1918. No. 25G. ####*#*****#*#* Urgent. Your telegram No. 161. Khans would strongly object to appearance of officers and Non-Commissioned Officers in Baktiavistan. In any case no such step should be taken without previous consultation with Ilkani. Frontier attitude of Baktiavis unsatisfactory. They have taken care to keep in touch with both sides and half of Khans here are in G-erman interest. Main effort should be made from Ahwaz to secure support of Ilkani and local Khans. Ilkani should be given guns and money liberally. I think moment is favourable for making definite offer to Sirdar Jang and perhaps Sirdar Mohtashara but we shall have to be liberal.—Document—is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, —he returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] DGcyoher. sir C. Marling (Teheran) 22nd May 1917. D. 8,SO Tnrp. 22nd Mo. 183, K. 10.30 a.m. 23rd /V A A ^ A A V A A ^ May 1917. Colonel Sir p, Cox’s tele gram^1700 July 19th. I readily accept Sir P. Cox’s correction that our proceedings at Shuster and Dizful are in civilian not military hands although I do not see that distinction affects my point. I cannot admit that my description is exaggerated to judge from only official reports before me, namely vice Consul Soanes reports for November December and January last or from a telegram sent by Governor of Arabistan to Persian Government about end of last year to the effect that he took his orders from Sir P. Cox not from Persian Government.[This Document Is the Property of Hfa Britannic Malettv’s Rnv a mm»nt and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done wttT^ required for official use.) ” ■&gt; jQh, ij.-ij Docypliar^ sir p # cox (Bc'gclad) D# 5 4 lo I.jy 20th, 1917. lU 8 .m, i-,'c'y 21s u* 1917. No* 1751. )Y 10 i 6' »■/ &gt;4 Ii3ior.;nc0 to i.Iinister ? s tolegivm No. (172?) to Foreign ollice wnicli h,:s r^eched ,:ac to-clpy 19th having been forwarded from Basra. I agree with hia that owing to new and uncertain situation created 'by Bussiem (group undecyp. arable) and its reaction on their position in Persia, the inauguration of levy scheme h,d better be postponed . I would remark incidentally that the allusion cited in the telegram above quoted to our proceedings at Shuster and Dizful and disregard for Brkhtiari interests are inaccurate and exag; .erated. There are no military authorities proportionate to place. There are political officers who have been exercising not long salut^jy influence over the administration and evolving out of chaos such measures of order and security as have been demanded by military interests and supplying require ments of this force. Addressed to Government of India, repeated to Foreign Off ice. minister, and Basra.Decypher, sir c. No. 178. [c^y to India | — 1 w * liJLI^uTY ‘ -- —■'“ ' • ’Xlins. (Teheran). Hay 18th, 1917 . T. S.SO.p.ri. May 13th,1917. N. 8.0.a.ra. Jfey 19th,1917. 7' y telegram No. 172. mlchtiari IgyIgs. On lurther consideration it appears to me quite impracticable to proceed with scheme at this moment. Attitude which loyalty to Russia compels us to take with regard to retention of Governor of Ispahan is bitterly resented by Khans here who although they my h'um assented to scheme when Noel propounded it to them on ground of necessity of averting possible Russian innerference will now unquestion bly oppose it partly out of presentment) above mentioned and partly as t ‘ ae ' / see ln lt ' commencement of British interference in internal tribal affairs. No lUchnni, whatever promises he might make to us iil h0j(i of seUi ^ office, would honestly endeavour to -dny quo scheme of this (?kind) without full approval senior ichans. Addrecsed'ito Foreign Office and Basrah.r-sy* •^bis Document is the Proper ty of His Britann ic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned tgEIMT foreign Office when done with nnl^ required for official use.l — iHLiiitfaf De 9 jrphor. Sir C* kariing (Teheran) May 15th. * D.. l.So.p.m. May 15th. 1917. E, 11.45 p.ra. liay 16th.1917. NO. 172. i U 1917, Copy to India | M ; r ( ■, ... Bakhtiari LcvlOfs L He as on for which scheme w$s proposed and sanctioned Was necessity for preventing collision between Bussian ^ try ■( ijr t r o op s and tribes - see ray D e sp at ch No* 132 of’l4ovomhe»r lath. By creation of a force under control of British officers which would co-operate with Russians to keep order on boundary. With change in Russia's attitude towards the Persian question and improbability that Russian troops would be used as was formerly possible, 'raison d'etre' of levies seems to have disappeared. Bo far as I am aware little or nothing has been done in way of recruiting but the organizing officers and material supplied by Government of India have just arrived. Leading Khans who originally professed readiness to fall in with scheme are ndw more than likely to oppose it. They have been very much offended that their large interests at Dizful and Schuster where our military authorities have practically taken over local administration have been totally disregarded and they pretend anxiety that levy scheme may prove a preliminary to similar interference with tribes. Ilkhaniis consequently insisting on resigning and only possible successor ! Samatmmatm.successor who is ready to promote scheme is in most othei respects unsuitable and is not approved by the leading Khans* In these circumstances and though levies might bo ox present utility to police road and of future advantage as paving way for introduction of Southern Persian rifles I am disposed to think scheme should be dropped* Addressed to Foreign Office 172 sent to India and! Copy forwarded, for information, to the Secretary to the Govern ment of India in the Foreign and Political Department. Letter from His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, to His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, dated the 27th September 1916. Letter from His Britannic Majesty^s Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, to His Britannic Majestv’s Minister, Tehran, dated the 28th September 1916. Letter from His Britannic Majesty's Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, to Chief Political Officer, Basrah, dated the 3rd October 1916, with enclosures. Enclosure No. 1. Dated Chighakhur, the 27th September 1916, Prom— Captain E. Noel, His Britannic Majesty's Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, To— Sie Charles Marling, K.C.M.O., C.B., etc., etc., His Britannic Majesty's Minister and Envoy Extraordinary, Tehran. I have the honour to address you on, the subject of Bakhtiari-Eussian relations and the necessity of our taking some steps to control them. The Eussians have now occupied Ispahan for some nine months, hut so far their effective jurisdiction extends to within but a few miles of the town. The remainder of the 60 odd miles of Ispahan territory up to the Bakhtiari border, is controlled by bands of brigands. It may be looked on as a neutral sphere dividing Eussians and Bakhtiaris, but into which both parties occasion ally penetrate. In this area collisions have at times occurred between Eussian troops and Bakhtiaris, but on the whole it may be said that that the existence of this zone has ^prevented friction arising between the two parties. This state of affairs cannot, however, continue indefinitely. The Eussians are at present busy raising a force of Persian Cossacks in Ispahan and in time they will be in a position to extend their control up to the Bakhtiari border. When this comes to pass there will inevitably arise a crop of incidents such as the escape of malefactors and political suspects into Bakhtiari territory, boundary disputes, claims against Bakhtiaris, etc., etc. j\s a case in point I would mention that of Dr. Assadullah, a physician to the Bakhtiari Khans. This individual is wanted by the Eussian authorities, Ispahan, who have announced their intention of hanging him if he should fall into their hands. I feel sure that under present circumstances it would not be possible to per suade the Khans to hand him over. It would be folly to expect that with present mutual attitude of suspicion and ill-feeling between the two parties similar incidents likely to arise in the future, will be settled without a dangerous amount of friction. Even if Eussian-Bakhtiari relations become normal, we shall still be confronted with the fact that a powerful, well- organised administration is in contact with a week and ill-organised one. Under these circumstances it would seem inevitable that the Eussians will be forced to interfere sooner or later in Bakhtiari country. In my previous despatches and telegrams I have indicated four measures which, in my opinion, would tend to remedy this state of affairs. I will again enumerate them in what I consider their order of relative importance. (1) Posting a small regular force in Chahar Mahal. (This would seem only necessary as long as Turks remain in Persia or until measure No. (2), referred to in the next paragraph, begins to materialize.) (2) Formation of a Bakhtiari police force under British officers, (81 Strengthening hands of Illkhani and Tllbeod so as fn PnnElo fTiom(4) Effecting a formal reconciliation between the Zill-es-Sultan and the Bakhtiari Khans. At one time it seemed to me that the adoption of course ^3) might prove sufficient, but since my recent visit to Ispahan, and my conversations with Bussian authorities there, I see little hopes of the Bakhtiaris themselves being able to work out their own salvation. The Bussians have suspicions that we are shielding the Bakhtiari Khans for the furtherance of our own poKtical ends and our support of men like Amir Mujahid, against whom the Bussians have definite evidence, certainly lends colour to those suspicions. Sirdar Muhta- sham, though loyal to us, ready to do what he is told and from our point of view probably the best man at present in Bakhtiari for the post of Illkhani is nevertheless not a strong man. It must also be remembered that in view of the strong anti-Bussian and anti-Zill-es-Sultan feeling that exists, it is improbable that any two Bakhtiari Khans would be prepared to take sufficient ly energetic action to satisfy the Bussian authorities. I would strongly urge that we take immediate steps to raise a Bakhtiari police force so that when the Persian Cossack Brigade, now being formed by the Bussians at Ispahan, takes shape and is ready to extend control up to the Bakhtiari border, we shall also be ready to link up with a similar organization on our side. 'While the body in question is being formed, it would seem very desirable to maintain a small regular force in Chahar Mahal as a backing. T his force could, I think, be cut down as low as two squadrons of Indian cavalry with two maxims, provided there are no Turkish troops in Persia. In a further despatch I will put forward definite proposals for the financing and organisation of the proposed Bakhtiari police corps. This letter is being forwarded under flying seal to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan, and a copy is being sent to the Chief Political Officer, Basrah. Enclosure Xo. 2. Dated Chighakhur, the 28th September 1916. From—C aptai!? E. Noel, Hls Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, To— Sir Charles Marling, K.G.M.G., C.B., His Britannic Majestv's Minister and Envoy Extraordinary, Tehran. 'With reference to my despatch, dated September 27th, on the subject of the formation of a Bakhtiari police force, I have now the honour to lay before you the detailed proposals referred to therein. Strength and composition oj force. —The ultimate strength of the force should be about 600 infantry and cavalry in the proportion of 2 to 1. For the present it will be sufficient to form a nucleus of 200 infantry and 100 sowars. Location.—This, at first, should certainly be in Chahar Mahal as the chief object of the force will be to provide an organisation to work in co-operation with the Bussians. Deh Kurd, the administrative centre of Chabar Mahal, would seem to provide a suitable headquarters for the force. Establishment for training. —The services of at least three British officers would be necessary, i.e.. Commandant, Adjutant and Quartermaster. Several of the younger generation of the Khans have spent two or three years in the Officers’ Training Corps at home. It would certainly seem advisable to make use of their services. Lay. —Infantry 8 to 10 tomans a month (to be armed by us). Cavalry 12 to 14 tomans a month (to find their own horses but to be armed by us and their horses to be fed by us). Financing of force. —This should be done partly by the Khans and partly by the Persian Government or ourselves. The method I would suggest would be for us to agree to an increase of the tolls on the Lynch road in return for1 ftS th L^rLsfrf Tn e V 0nfe j bution towards the ex P e “ ses °f ‘te should have praetWly no adverse inZenceC afthe° increase A f l,w + 3 T W0U ‘ d but ^Present 1 per cent, of the present rates of mule hire from overL return 8 fo andWOUld J ?r0ba . bly v bepaidfor b y the muleteers. More- nln+’-r, f j « Ur sauctl0n to this increase, the Khans, in addition to contributing towards the expenses of the force, would, I think, also be prepared to grant us a control of the tolls and the Lynch road “n general S « proper y exeicised, would have the effect of greatly assisting British' trade bv ringing down transport rates very considerably. If ft is not considered asible during the duration of the war to undertake the controll indicated we ZS n C o nte 1 0ur f, lveswi ‘ h obtai mug the consent of Khans to the arrange ment proposed, and leave the question of giving effect to the concession open till we are in a position to undertake it effectively. ^ Consul 1 PenZV 8 ! 1561 ^ forwar , ded flying seal to His Britannic Majesty’s Offleerl’Basrlh.’ Spahan ’ and a C0 I J &gt;’ 18 bein S se nt to the Chief Political Enclosure No. 3. Dated Chighakur, the 3rd October 1916. From— Captain E. Noel, His Britannic Majesty's Vice-Consul, Abwaz, To—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I. K.C.I E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Basrah. I herewith enclose you some correspondence regarding the Faravdun situation. The matter m question is a further illustration of the danger referred to in my letter of the 27th of September. It is certain that the Russians intend taking over the administration of Faraydun when they feel emselves strong enough to do so. I feel convinced that the process will be accompanied by friction and the occurrence of many incidents calculated to give the Russians ample pretext for interference in Chahar Mah-l it se ]f , P 6 s °uthern half of Faraydun is so Bakhtiari in character and so closely connected with Chahar Mahal that if the Russians were installed there 7° ul d Probably discover the need of a consular representative in Chahar Mahal itself. It would seem to me of the utmost importance that in fixing the Russians and British spheres of influence we should press for the inclusion m our sphere of all Bakhtiari elements. The country to the north-west of harayduu is unknown to me, but I believe there are Ilyat there of Bakhtiari origin who extend into the present Russian sphere. Sub-Enclosure No. 1. Dated Ispahan, the 27th August 19]6. From G. Grahams, Esq., His Majesty's Consul-Genera], Ispahan, To— Captain E. Noel, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Ahwaz. SnlJZwZ 6 h ° n T t0 i Qf ° r ® y° u that His p ‘°ral Highness Yamin-us- SMtaneh, G-overnor-General of Ispahan, has again made complaints to me, similar to those which he made at the time when the Bakhtiaris began to levy payment of the grazing tax in Faraydun and substituting themselves for the Ispahan authorities in that district. . . In P roof of this contention His Royal Highness produced a letter in original (copy of which I enclose), purporting to have been addressed by Elias Khan, Sarum-ul-Mulk, to Haji Haider Quli and Haji Ismail, Yanehashmehi calling on them to deliver up to Agha Bahram (a mamour sent by Elias Khan) 5 recalcitrance^ 11 h ° rSe ** ° f t0manS 50 ° ^ VG hundred ) in case of ■ A Royal Highness, in conversation on the subject with me this morning, said that this instance was only one out of many of Bakhtiari intervention in4 Faraydun, but that he had been unable so far to get documentary evidence as to the others. I would request you to be good enough to take such steps as you may see fit in this matter and inform me at your convenience of the result if any for the satisfaction of the Governor-General of Ispahan. Sub-Enclosure No. 2. Dated Junaghun, the 3rd September 1916. From— Captain E. Noel, His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, To—G. Grahame, Esq., His Majesty’s Consui-Geneial, Ispahan. I have thought it advisable to write to you demi-officially m regard to the matter dealt with in your despatch No. 15, before addressing you officially on the subject. The Bakhtiaris frankly acknowledge that they interfere in Earaydun, but are quite ready to stop doing so if we tell them. As luck would have it, I met the other day Ahmed Quli Nhan and his brother Muazum-ul-Mulk, who are the leaders of the Fouj-i- araydun . They tell me that they held the Deputy Governorship of Earaydun for four years under the Zill-es-Sultan when they used, as a matter of course to refer all disputes on the Earaydun border to the Khans for settlement. They tell me that this state of affairs has now crystalized from long custom so that it represents under present conditions the only possible modus mvendi. Moreover, they say that the Zill fully recognised Ibis even m his own time. As an illustration they quote a recent incident when mamours sent from both the Deputy Governor and from Ispahan w r ere unable to effect the release of Haii Mohomed Hassan of Siftgun who has been, seized by Quli Khan Tukhm-i- Abui. Finally, in despair the Earaydun authorities, although both the indivi duals concerned were Earaydunis, appealed to the Bakhtiari Khans who sent mamours. The latter had no difficulty in carrying out the duties entrusted to them. I have not had time as yet to make further enquiries, but quote the above to show that there would appear to be more in this matter than at first meets the eye. Quli Khan and Muazam, who are Earaydunis and not Bakhtiaris, assure me that if the Khans refuse their good offices, the whole of the Earaydun district will immediately relapse into the same state of anarchy that characterises the bulk of the Ispahan province. It would seem to me that in view of. the noto rious incompetence of the Zill-es-Sultan’s Government to maintain even a semblance of order, and the comparative security existing in Bakhtiari limits it is hardly the time to ask the Bakhtiaris to. withdraw from one of the few districts of Ispahan which is more or less quiet, when the Ispahan Govern ment have no machinery to replace that which they wish to get rid of. Another point to be considered is that we are continually asking the Bakhtiaris to send escorts into Ispahan territory to do the work of the Ispahan Government. I refer to escorts for British travellers and to my recent despatch of sowars to follow up the Germans. I hope to come into Ispahan some time this month when I can discuss this matter more fully with you. Sub-Enclosure No. 3. Copy of Ispahan telegram to Minister, No. 283, dated the 15th September 1916. Neel, who arrived here on the 14th of September, wishes to discuss with me question of permitting loyal Bakhtiaris to gain a footing in Ispahan territory more particularly in the Earaydun district, where they claim to have exercised jurisdiction in the Zill-es-Sultan’s time and seek to do so now. Noel is inclined to view such intervention favourably on the ground that ;~ — —„■ ^•■.rUr. i-na Governor-General of Ispahan the Bakhtiaris can maintain order, whereas the is impotent.I am at a disadvantage inasmuch as I have no information as to the reasons for the recall of the Zill-es-Sultan whether he is our choice or the Itussians, whether we are pledged to give him our full support and to protect Ispahan territory from Bakhtiari encroachments or are prepared to close our eyes to them or even encourage them. . T 1 be glad of general enlightenment on the general trend of policy in Ispahan, and on the points above mentioned in particular. GBAHAME. Sub-Enclosure No. 4. i Telegram No. 145, dated the 16th September 1916. From—His Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan. * Secret. Your 283. Question of Zill-es-Sultan’s return to Ispahan just now is at present under discussion between London and Petrograd. I am strongly urging the view of the Persian Government that a neutral governor be appointed for a time in the hope that this may strengthen the ^Illkhani, but Russian Legation and Petrograd, where since combat at Nejefabad, Bakhtiaris are all looked on as enemies without discrimination, will not agree “ to make a concession ”. Although Zill-es-Sultan returned to Ispahan with a pledge of support from both powers, it is obvious that as all his interests are in Ispahan, he must sooner or later lean on Russians rather than on us, but he or rather his party has gone much further and is now actively hostile. As it is thanks to their intrigue wdth Nimtaj that Solet has ventured to take so strong a line against Earman Earma and Sykes’ Mission. In spite of this we cannot in any circum stances encourage the Bakhtiaris against him and so produce an impression of conflict between Russian and British policy. 2 Telegram R., No. 6697, dated (and received) the 9th December 1916. From—S ir P. Z. Cox, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. My endorsement No. 11227 October 28th. Eollowing from Noel, who is at Tehran, No. 517, December 7th. Begins. My letters of September 27th and 28th were forwarded by Minister to Eoreign Office who now reply that India Office favour suggestion (of ?) number 2 and ask for views whether the force should be completely independent of South Persia Rifles or subordinate to a branch thereof. Ends. 3 Telegram P., No. 6699, dated (and received) the 9th December 1916. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. My immediately preceding telegram. Eollowing (sent to Basrah and presumably addressed to Eoreign Office) from Minister, No. 749, December 7th. Begins. Your telegram 520. Success of scheme depends largely on goodwill of Khans if proposed police were at once made part of South Persia Rifles they would be alarmed for virtual of autonomy of their tribe. Noel and I think that it would be better at outset to give force the characteristic of tribal levy under the general supervision of local political officer.6 Persian Government is showing symptoms of objecting to conclusion of agreements with tribes. Hence it would be best to start raising nucleus force in low country without reference to Persian Government. Units thus raised would be transferred to Chahar Mahal at time of spring migration. We might begin with 200 infantry and 100 cavalry with 3 British officers &lt;*i under Noel’s supervision. Exclusive of clothing, equipment and other initial expenditure and pay of British officers and instructors approximate cost can scarcely exceed 6,000 tomans a month. Though Bakhtiari Khans profess their readiness to contribute cost of force, it would be imprudent to count upon any payment from them at outset and until actual creation of force. It is also for consideration whether it will suit our policy to invite them to find any part of expenditure and so confirm and strengthen their local autonomy. Eorce should be organised on lines similar to South Persia Bifles, of which it should eventually form part. Ends. 4 Telegram R., No. T.- 66 , dated the 10th (received 11th) December 1916. Prom—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. (Repeated Basrah.) Beference Minister’s 749 and Noel’s 517. Proposal regarding Bakhtiari tri bal levy has my support and I can suggest officers if desired. 6 Telegram P., No. 6868 , dated (and received) the 15th December 1916. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Telegram of December 13th from Secretary of State for India. Captains Eowle and Greenhouse are the officers referred to by Sir P. Cox in his telegram T.-66, dated December 10th. Eowle is at Ahwaz, Greenhouse at Basrah. Eowle has travelled extensively and both have been in Persia before, have the requiste military experience, speak Persian fluently and are available immediately. The services of a third officer will also probably be obtainable locally. Above is sent at once to avoid delay as Cox at moment out of touch. 8 Telegram R., No. T.-157, dated the 24th (received 25th) December 1916. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I., K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, through General Headquarters, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. (Repeated to Basrah.) Please see correspondence forwarded under my office No. 14719, Decem ber 12th. Minister wired December 21st, 372 as follows :— Begins. Noel has urged necessity for appointing Assistant to officer in charge Bakhtiari affairs to reside in Chahar Mahal, if you have suitable officer available I see no objection to proposed arrangement as a purely temporary measure. Ends. Iadvocaie proposed appointment and if you see no objection, would propose Bakhfiari S&amp;en up them ° 0Uld ^ MahaI ° ffi0er and a,S ° mn 11 Telegram No. 6P30, dated the 17th December 1916. From—The Chief Political Officer, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. .p^tinuatiQn °f my telegram No. 6868 if it is decided to make a start with raising proposed Bakhtiari Force I request that Ordnance and Supply epaitments at Basrah may be authorised to issue on my requisitions the necessary arms and ammunition, equipment and clothing. Short *303 rifles should be issued as long rifles are unpopular with Persian mounted men. ( # oroupundecipherable.) Actual scale of uniform and clothing?* . (tCroup undecipherable.) wiH be fixed after SOUie months’ experience of requirements. To facilitate subsequent adjustment of accounts all issue might be on payment and debited to my accounts with Controller of War Accounts,?f 12 (Received with Army Department memorandum No. 17, dated the 2nd January 1917.) Cipher telegram No. X.-80, dated the 27th (received 28th) December 1916. From—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D”, G. P. C., through General Headquarters, Basrah, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Delhi. ^Repeated London.) Recently I have seen correspondence which has not been sent officially to me from which it appears there is a project in existence to raise Bakhtiari force 300 strong under command of Captain Noel, Vice-Consul for Bakhtiari, and that maintenance of order on Lyn (oh) ? Road between Ahwaz and Ispahan will be the primary function of this force. By Chief of the Imperial General Staff, London, Ao. 23374-Cipher?, dated September 30th, functions of Force “ L ” were extended to prevent incursion of hostile forces south of line i Ispahan-Shustar and conseqeuntly the above mentioned force will apparently f be operating near sphere of my responsibility. I would submit for consi deration grave risk of complications that may arise from existence of such irregular forces acting independently of military control. Within the last few I days we have had instance of this in connection with Sykes’ operations which j now seem likely to involve the employment of troops from Bushire and active operations in Mesopotamia may be seriously hampered thereby. In my * opinion such forces if they are considered necessary should be under the com- 1 mand of experienced and capable military officers and their distribution and 1 movements should be regulated in accordance with general plan of operations. 13 (Received with Army Department memorandum No. 70, dated the 3rd January 1917.) Cipher telegram No. 101418, dated the 50th December 1916. _f The Commander-in-Chief in India, rom ^ The Chief of the General Staff, To—The Chief of the Imperial General Staff, War Office, London. (Repeated General Officer Commanding, Force “ D”, Basrah.) Reference your X.-80, dated 27th December. ;^ '-i r The Political Officer dealtog ■with Bakhtiari affairs submitted the project referred to Tehran, who submitted it to Foreign Office Scheme was sup ported by Political Resident in Persian Gulf, and on 13th December Secretary of State intimated that it had the general approval of Hrs Majesty s Govern ment and asked for views of Government of India. The Government of India concurred in the proposal. At that time Sir P Cox was with G ne al Officer Commanding Force “ D ’, so that General Officer Commanding, Force 1) s attention was not drawn to the matter by me. The police force to be raised will be for employment in Bakhtiari limits. Bakhtiari country must be considered as within the theatre of operations of Force “ D’’ to ensure action in conform ity with the instructions conveyed m your 23374, dated 30th September, so that the organization, equipment, distribution and movements of any forces operating in that area would be regulated by him m accordance with his general plan, under the powers vested in him by Field Service Regulations, Part II, Chapter III, Section 8. Any addition to the number of Officers Commanding, Irregular Forces, who are not definitely under military control is deprecated by me. 14 14719 —67-45, dated'Basrah, the 12th (received 25th) December 1916. p roin —The Hon’ble Ltetttenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I., K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi, I have the honour to forward, for the in formation of the Government of Telegram P., from Captain Noel, No. 472, dated the 24th October 1916. Telegram from Consul General, Ispahan, No. 204, dated the 29th October 1916. . _ • n Letter ^demi-official, dated the 25th October India, COpiCS of the marginally Cited Telegram P., to Captain Noel, No. 6523, dated correspondence which has recently passed ecember 2nd. _ _ „ Telegram from Captain Noel, No. 522, dated T , e2 , ardin2‘ the need of a Political Omcer December 11th. ° Telegram from Captain Noel, No. 523, dated p ^ Chahar Mahal district. December ilth. 2 The question is closely connected with the proposal to raise a force of Bakhtiari levies under British officers, referred to m the correspondence ending with my telegram No. T.-66, dated December 10th, and I forward the correspon dence without further comment at once in order to facilitate discussion by telegraph in due course. For the same reason I am forwarding a copy to the Political Secretary, India Office, London. Enclosure No. 1. Telegram P., No. 472, dated the 24th October 1916. From— Captain Noel, Ispahan, To—The Hon’ble Lieutenant Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I., K.C I.E., Pohtica Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basrah. i r With Kuhsfilus under Bakhtiaris and with the Zill-es-Sultan at Ispahan and with Faraydun and Barbarud questions simmering, there is in my opinion uro'ent need for a Consul with headquarters in Chahar Mahal and a junior officer as his assistant who would remain in Chahar Mahal during the winter. My work here is increasing and scarcely a day now passes without my receiving a communication from Ispahan.Enclosure No. 2. Telegram P., No. 204, dated the 29th (received SOth) October 1916. From— Grahame, Consul-Genera], Ispahan, T° The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. /. Cox KCST it p t t? p vr ^ Hesident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Pol4al ote,’.Basrah ' ° ltlCal (Addressed Basrah, repeated Noel.) _ Importance of area in which Noel has been acting is it is ohvionc o, k,--- -»— This wtth reference to telegram No. 472 from Captain Noel. Enclosure No. 3. Demi-official letter, dated the 25th October 1916. From— Captain Noel, Deh Kurd, T '“ Tl * as rS ss; ss?. r ' 472, LS”“ W™i ,0U to Wh “‘‘ 1 ' , «™ i “ «7 It would seem that the Russians are intent on consolidating their position at Ispahan in the same as they have done in the north and with the process of Spontaneous Russian infiltration’’already well set in at Ispahan, we are faced with an entirely new set of conditions. • S ^ u ?^ 0 . 11 h as T ^ us arisen at Ispahan must also reproduce itself in Northern Luristan as soon as the Turks are driven out of Persia. As a result of these new conditions the centre of gravity in Bakhtiari and Luristan affairs is tending to shift to the north, and will continue to do so till the war is over and some working arrangement with the Russians has crystalised out. . , present the Bakhtiari and Luristan high countries are physically isolated from Arabistan. There is no telegraph or post, and means of loco motion are slow and tedious. Until this is remedied of which there does not appear to be much immediate prospect, it would seem impracticable to expect any real control from Arabistan over Luristan and Bakhtiari affairs. The present tendency is for the control of Bakhtiari affairs to centre itself m Ispahan. In ^my opinion this tendency will be aggravated by trying to exercise supervision from Arabistan under the present unfavourable conditions referred to in paragraph 5. In the case of Luristan the result will be to shift the centre of control to Kermanshah or Burujird. It would seem to me that if we wish to retain Luristan and Bakhtiari in the Persian Gulf sphere, our policy should be to raise the status of our representatives there to that of Consul, and strengthen their hands in every way so as to lessen as much as possible their dependence on connecting links such as Ispahan and Kermanshah. It is obvious that at the end of the war the real and material factors | governing the future development of the Arabistan hinterland must be supplitsd from the south. I refer to railways, posts and telegraphs, trade, etc. Moreover any form of physical suasion must also come from that direction. Theeonr.ee- tion with the north will be purely a political one depending on Russians’ position there. At present, however, it is the political tie which is the paramount one, and which, if allowed to follow its present tendency of taking root at Ispahan, will prove a serious handicap to future schemes of material development initiated from the south. To increase the status and strengthen the hands of our representatives as suggested in paragraph 8 we should grant them the fullest measure of01 independence possible. For an officer in Ba'Atiari or Luristan to know that his proposals were to be criticised by Ispahan and Arabrstan before they reached Tehran and Basrah would have a deadenmg effec on hismr ratrve We should aim at having our representatives m Bakhtiari and Luristan appointed from India, holding rank of Consul, communicating direct with Tehran and Basrah on all matters affecting their own sphere, maintaining their connection with the south by spending the winter “ ^ supplied with an assistant who would remain in the high countiy durrn^ the The above remarks refer chiefly to the general question of our policy m South-West Persia I would offer the following comment on the present Bakhtiarf situation and the need for our maintaining an independent represen tative in Bakhtiari and its dependency, Chahar Mahal. (a) In previous telegrams and despatches I have referred to the fact ( ' that in a short space of time we shall be in contact on the Bakhtiari border with an organization and administration essen tially Eussian in character. We shall then be forced to link up by initiating similar measures on our side of the border. The formation of a police force is the first question which will demand our serious attention, but matters in connection with posts and telegraphs, communications, irrigation will m time also come 1 to the front. (b) There are strong grounds for thinking that the Zill-es-Sultan is V J determined to get some of his own back from the Bakhtians for t the treatment he has received at their hands m the past. It tins is the case the Bakhtiaris will continually he invoking our good offices in the protection of their interests (c) Bakhtiari Khans own large properties in Ispahan territory, and m connection therewith many questions are likely to arise which will have to be referred to the Ispahan authorities through us. (d) The trade connection between Bakhtiari and Ispahan is a very close one. The Bakhtiaris will look to us for the protection of their interests in connection therewith. (e) If the neutral sphere is to go to us, the present arbitrary boundary from Ispahan to Kermanshah cannot be retained. Pnma facie it would seem that we should aim at the inclusion of all Lur elements within our sphere. The districts to the north ot Bakhtiari, viz., Faraydun, Japalak, Burburud in which the question of the delimitation of a new boundary will arise are ones in regard to which we have very little information A representative in Chahar Mahal would be in the best position to collect information regarding these areas, It must also be remembered that as long as a district such as Faraydun, which is predominantly Bakhtiari in character, is left in the Bussian sphere, there will sure to he a crop of disputes, etc., which can best be enquired into and regulated by an agent in Chahar Mahal. (/) As Sykes’ task of restoring order in Fars proceeds the Kughelu question will come much to the front. The Kughelus have always proved the most enterprising and determined robbers south of Ispahan and the most difficult to tackle owing to their isolation. The Bakhtiaris at present are supposed to have control of the tribe, hut in the case of the more south-easterly sections such as the Boir _ Ahmedi and the Bushman Ziari it is of the most shadowy description. Even in the case ot the most north-westerly sections the Taibi and the Bahmai, the Kuans authority is weak, but this to a great extent is due to the Khans mter-tamily quarrels, and the pernicious system of the members of each family having their adherents among the Kughelus, whom they make use of to score on eir opponents.* i. I am f xP 111 !? 11 ,’ i n . ev ? r ^ e less, that the Kugheluis should remain asso ciated with the Bakhtians, because their winter quarters, i.e., Behbehan and the surrounding* country are in Bakhtiari hands. To allow the Kughelu control to gravitate towards Shiraz, would I think he a mistake because the ^ tribes are more get-atable in their winter quarters than in their summer, and it is clear that effective control cannot be exercised over the tribes at Behbehan from Shiraz. In this connection please see paragraphs 5 and 9. (g) Apart from the need of giving shape to measures of administrative reform similar to those the Russians are putting in hand on their side of the border, it will also he necessary to undertake such general measures of improvement and development as will tend to diminish the Bakhtiari economic dependence on Ispahan. The most obvipus solution for this problem which at first sight presents itself is the foundation of a rival city to Ispahan on our ; side of the border. This scheme may seem somewhat Utopian, still I submit that a good deal can be effected in this direction by a suitable development of communications, irrigation schemes, etc. (A) The work of a Consular Officer or Political Agent in connection with the above-mentioned matters necessitates continuous and rapid touring. Even this summer I find that poorness of com munications and press of work have prevented me from visiting several points, where I feel that personal enquiry would be of the greatest assistance to me. (i) I herewith forward a memorandum showing very roughly what would seem to me the main lines on which our energies should be directed towards the future development of the country and the consolidation of our position. It may be objected that many ol the schemes mentioned therein are ambitious and far-fetched, nevertheless it would be of value to collect as much information as possible regarding them. Memorandum giving suggestions for development of Bakhtiari and Qhahar Mahal and the consolidation of our position. 1. Eormation of a Bakhtiari police force. 2. Connection of Deh Kurd with Ispahan by telephone and telegraph and possible extension to oil-fields. 3. Improvement of Lynch caravan road and formation of a transport company which would be given control of the tolls and caravanserais [vide my leiter, September 28th, to Minister). 4. Enquiry into possibility of finding a practicable railway alignment from the oil-fields to M.alamir, Madrasseh up the Karun valley to Bars thence up the valley of the Khirsan or A.b-i-Lurdegan to Lurdegan from which point there should be no difficulty in finding an easy alignment to Simirum and Qumisheh. Lurdegan is on the central plateau and it is said that a carriage can be driven there from Ispahan. 5. Enquiry into the possibility of irrigation schemes in Chahar Mahal, The most obvious ones which suggest themselves are (1) Dam on the Zaindeh Bud above Samun, (2) Earn at the outlet of the Chighakhur valley, (3) Kar- kunan scheme. 6. Construction of a bridge over the Karun to the north of the oil-fields. This project has long been recognised and recommended as likely to give a good return on the capital outlay. As matters stand at present a large number of cattle of the Uyat are lost when crossing the Karun at the time of the biennial migration. 7. Development of a hill station for Arabistan in Southern Bakhtiari. (The Mangasht range would appear to be the most suitable site.)8. Appointment of a veterinary officer in Bakhtiari with special mission to study sheep disease. The ravages of sheep rot and foot and mouth disease in 1914 and 1915 are said to have killed off half-a-million sheep. Ghee and wool have since increased in price from 5‘50 to 100 per cent. 9. Establishment of an experimental farm in Chahar Mahal under a quali- ^ fied officer. Methods of cultivation as practised at present are primitive and wasteful and the range of crops sown is small. f - The locusts from Ears started to invade Chahar Mahal this year, and although the damage done was not great, there is a danger that having laid their eggs here, they will reappear next year in very much larger numbers. Blight (sinn) has also made its appearance and caused some loss. The introduction of sugarcane cultivation on the Khans’ estates in north Arabistan and the popularization of modern agricultural machinery are two of the most obvious openings in this direction. 10 Establishment of a dispensary under a gazetted medical officer in Chahar Mahal. 11. Building a Consulate in Chahar Mahal. Deh Kurd or Chighakur would seem the most suitable localities. 12. Eormation of an agency (possibly an off-shoot of the I. B P.) for taking over the management of some of the Khans’ estates. Now that the Khans have lost, probably permanently, the Governorships of I&amp;pahan, Yezd and Kerman as well as seats in the Cabinet, the problem of feeding and Ik peeping quiet their numerous dependants, now accustomed to a liberal share lo j£f perquisites, is becoming a very awkward one. The. solution which has occurred to many is to hand over their estates to a British agency and repair themselves to India or Europe for a term of years with a view to retrench ment. 13. Establishment of a college for the young sons of Bakhtiari Khans. At the outbreak of the war there were 20 young Bakhtiaris at school in Europe, There are about 80 members of the younger generation of the ruling families. 14. It is very essential that early measures should be taken to bring the Kuhgeluis to order. To do so is likely to involve an expedition and the reduc tion of one or more of the Kuhgelu mountain strongholds as suggested in my memorandum of June 30th, No. T -6. Enclosure No. 4. Telegram P., No. 65£3, dated the 2nd December 1916. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I., K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basrah, To— Captain Noel, His Majesty's Consul, Tehran. I favour your suggestions re need for whole-time officer for Chahar Mahal and am prepared to put matter forward. As however you are at Legation it would be well to ascertain Minister’s views on subject. ***** Enclosure No. 5. Telegram R., No. 522, dated (and received) the 11th December 1916. From— Captain Noel, His Majesty’s Consul, Tehran, To—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C S.I., K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basrah. Your telegram 6523. Minister agrees to appointment provided it is con sidered a temporary one.Enclosure No, 6. Telegram R., No. 523, dated (and received) the 11th December 1916. From— Captain Noel, His Majesty's Consul, Tehran, To—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I., K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basrah. * * * $ * Minister is supporting following scheme. 1. Telegraph line between Ahwaz and Ispahan, foundation of a college in Ohahar Mahal for young Khans. ***** 15 (Received with Army Department memorandum No. 1022, dated 23rd January 1917.) Cipher telegram No. X.-339, dated the 18th (received 19th) January 1917. From—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D”, General Headquarters, To—The Chief of the General Staff. Your 1799 of 9th. With regard to Eowle and Greenhouse, can you please say whether they are capable officers with up-to-date military experience ? On Cox’s return to front, in about (10 ?) days’ time, I will discuss question with him. 17 Telegram R., No, 4), dated (and received) the 30th January 1917. From—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To—-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Please repeat to me your telegram to Secretary of State, January 6th, respecting Bakhtiari Levies. 18 Telegram P., No. 144-S., dated the 1st February 1917. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah. Secretary of State telegraphs on 29th January as follows:—“ Please telegraph * * * estimated by you”. Kindly send by post, with your views, a copy of Noel’s letter, which has not been received here. 19 Telegram P., No. 145-S., dated the 1st February 1917. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Please see your telegram 4 of 30th January. The following telegram 36-S. was sent to Secretary of State for India, on 6th January. “ Powle and Greenhouse were * * * these selections,”—— 22 Telegram P., No. 158-S., dated the 3rd February 1917. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Political Resident in Persian Gulf, Basrah. ft (Repeated to Tehran.) Bakhtiari Levy. Following telegram, dated ROth January from Secre tary of State :—“ His Majesty’s Government wish * * * reference to your telegram of January 6th.” r 23 Telegram P., No. 168-S., dated the 4th February 1917. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Political Resident in Persian Gulf, Basrah* (Repeated to Tehran.) Following telegram from Secretary of State dated 2nd instant:— Begins^ Bakhtiari Levies * * * January 30th. Binds. Please take necessary action and report progress later. This is with reference to my telegram 258-S. Telegram P., No. 923, dated the 7th (received 8th) February 1917. From -The Political Resident in Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Bakhtiari Levies. May I assume that Fowle and Greenhouse have been approved for duty and that the necessary further recommendations on the- subject will be made by the Chief of the General Staff, Delhi, to Army Commander ? This is with reference to your telegram 168-S , February 4th. Telegram P., No. 924, dated the 7th (received 8th) February 1917. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. I request that early action be taken on my telegram of the 17th December, 6930, in order to enable me to proceed with despatch of equipment required.. This is with reference to my immediately preceding telegram. Telegram P., No. 217-&amp;, dated the 16th February 1917. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah. Your telegram of. February 7th, 923. As General Officer Commanding,. Force “ D”, has now received instructions regarding Bakhtiari Levies in consoI Dr., foli'lijjl nSft nance with those from Secretary of State for India which have already been repeated to you, it is presumed that you will have now no difficulty in proceed ing with raising of force. Y our nominations of Eowle and Greenhouse who are already at disposal of this Department are approved. Telegram No. 1250, dated the 18th (received 19th) February 1917. From—The Hon ; ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. My telegram of 17th December, 693. Bakhtiari Levies. Kindly wire if action proposed therein has been taken and necessary orders issued. kf jet 6. G. P. X., Delhi— 02S i 1 &amp; D.—2-4-11-6P 1224] l ' r0m 1 ,eero 9&gt; Foreign Department, 2~lth March 1917 . {Repeated to Teheran as No. 378 S.) (Received at India Office, 10 p.m.j 907 S o e f C 5 e 8 AfaS. ‘tSC W' a 7. ^ aud .telegmm corps of about 1,00() iufaatrr c-ivalrv ind'‘'''i 'f, 1 •°- r f alllse '- 1 J,!vy Seistan and are conside^^i^S b,la11 address you shortly by Despatch. For the !SZF l v v v .1 v.y Cy w no j ^rsian Baluchistan. [P 1224] Otoreiwon? ato^— from CFof . Per8 ’ an is ethnologlc^Uv different 0m iest ol 1 eisia (2) owing to immense distances any real control supenos.on or nxspectxon from Shiraz would be impracticable ; 3) u e W to mil Lastem levies on much more economical lines than South IVrsn biles, and see no object whatever in nniformity, especialh as tnbsfers -ue mpiacticable since lersian Babich will not serve away from home • UltF maintaining order by giving local tribesmen stake in shape of Nolth WesbCntier^ 1 '' actl ° able « Eastem - i« Baluchistan or \\ e suggest that nothing should be said at present to Persian Government and that we should proceed quietly with organisation on above lines. From Secretary of State lo Viceroy, Foreiqn Department 31st March 1917. loreign Secret lour telegram dated 24th instant. Eastern Persia Your despatch will be awaited. You will doubtless consider probability that I ersian Government will not recognise separate force and difficulties t lat will be likely to arise with local Persian Governors in absence oi such recognition. Even Baluchistan levy system would be unworkable in such circumstances. It is not intended that Bakhtiari levies should remain / permanently independent. See Marling’s telegram of 7th December 1910. It is not proposed to make any communication to Persian Government, ^ but airangements you make should take account of possibility that levies must be absorbed into South Persian Rifles at end of war.W 6179-2858 20,000 7/J5 II W V (1&gt; 298/3) j 1J3&amp; 0 '*' 6 Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to— The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W., the following number quoted. ^0. 121/3/429. ! 9 i 7 WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W., 8th ^ebruary 191 7 . ' ! f Hie Secretary of the War Office presents his compliments to Under-Secretary of State for India (Political Bept:) and is commanded by the Army Council to transmit for the information of the Secretary of State for India a copy of the document noted in the subjoined schedule on the subject of Baktiari levies Date 7th ^ eh: 1917 From C.I.G.3. Description raising of Baktiari levies tobe proceeded with at once. Instructions to Seneral^aude.at Q opy of Telegra n Secret* Operations. from;- C.I.G.s. G.O.C., Force ,T D fT . Addressed Basrah repeated India. V &gt;^n 7th February 1917. 29116 cipher M.O. 274B. vvith reference to proposed raising of Baktiari Levies. Vieeroy has been instructed to proceed with scheme at once. Hoel as Commandant, Baktiari Levies will keep touch with you, informing you regarding movements and future plans. You have authority to defer execution of any plan which, on military grounds, you may consider undesirable, but any such action on your part should at once be reported to me.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. w. 2.2,3^ £ and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. u THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1917. Reference to 'previous correspondence : niter m Foreign Office: pAA^AK-awx^ f,. Of T (k P.stoo) Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^jvoaW. lidk&amp;Jbuasi+D&amp;Yv n^xjchx^yyoiy^'ie ffry-cue.. Copy to India 22 djJtr E PTREASURY (JHAi,BER3 2301 •-N 17 / U 2-i Jmu&amp;ry 1917 Confident !xA j t | s , t A s Lord, I have laid before the Lords Comniasioners of Hia Majesty's Treasury Sir M. de Bunsen's letter of the 19th instant (rf.LboL/17) and the accompanying correspondence regarding the desirability of establishing a force of gendarmerie in Bakhtiaristan. , **y nerds note that the new force will consist for the present of 2oo infantry and 100 cavalry, and They presume that it will eventually be incorporated in the South rersia Rifles, the cost of which is to fall upon Persian funds after the war. As requested by i..r. Secretary Balfour, They sanction the charge against Imperial funds of a moiety of the expenditure involved, estimated at 6000 tomafcsa month, on the understanding that the other moiety is defrayed from Indian revenues. 1 am, ^y Lord, Your obedient Servant, i-he Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.*draft telegram. SECRETARY OF STATE TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT (Retamilla) M-/. j} f. vt' /o. 6U‘ CttvCwk. hn, (h^ otficsfy' f 144UJL, ^ /$JcA 'h 21565 I 1548 500 11/16 JoiOysn 4 oajJ' ^Yv Om, 6 W: $c/&lt;&amp;Ccs,^ 'Ciam. //.M.f. U' 6 tf&lt;4- h fouwkcl^ , C(u~ i4- h /0?- ^&amp;^&lt;M 'fix hvJU-Sfaj t(u- U, hwifafa^ h^U' &amp; ■fy 4f IntA^i &lt;f], A- otC^ ^Av ^h'/W^ ^w]]| ^ fiu, fu&lt;I C&amp; £ /■/jn 'jP* ; ^71/2^/* $&lt;S)rMi*£ ^ ^WlfitcsnCL, f *j \^4' ’C (M yfii fa c&amp;fa 4kY -cA^ ^1 I _ ' : r s G-O.t. /Lie. t'hfivmrwfa ca /// &lt;/■ //c^i t 6:0. C. A t/xjL fajLCA^fcfa f S AU K. &amp; Ca Ucu^ai. if fa, hLU-Cfaj jfUSXrfahv (L A OtC, /cA&amp;Cfa LC£ m thMt ^ yXfa Jj- G-.o.c. /l^u f C 0 u 'C Crr^rMUj fa fa Ct/icoUj &amp; f(f€X'ul*In any further communication on the subject, please quote No- ¥.20398/17. /f50 ■ Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. January 31st, 1917. Immediate Sir:- In reply to your letter, P.355, of the 25th instant, relative to the status of the proposed Bakhtiari levies, I am directed hy Mr. Secretary ^alfour to state that he concurs in the terms of the telegram which the Secretary of State for India proposes to address to the iiovernment of India on the subject. I am, ^ • Dir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Ihe Under Secretary of State, India Office.[y his ..„.,j?£9.HSg.?l. is i Jll__ F l Q P ert y M His Britan nic Majesty’s Government a .gj^ 0 jL d . bg ^^^ediTtfaTF^^ required for official use.] / a r r (20398/17) 0’’7 ,Y C/jDher telegraa to tir C 0 ifarling^* (Teheran) Foreigji Oftice, Januvry 29th. 1917. T.O.p.r No. 37. Following Rent to Viceroy, India-~ Foreign secret. Your telegram 6th inetant. Balchtiari levies. His Hajesty’s Government wish it to he understood that force is essentially civil that it is not intended for Military operations and tiiat its movements must he governed hy tiie views of His Majesty’s Minister, Teheran. On matters other than internal economy of force Noel will look to His Majesty’s Consul General Ispahan for guidance, hut he will keep in close touch with General Officer Commanding, Basra informing him as regards both movements and plans and General Officer Commanding will he authorised to defer execution of any plans which he thinks undesirable on Military grounds. Oil the other hand Nukhtiari politics are outside sphere of General Officer Commanding, Basra and Cox should he consulted in his capacity as Political Hesident not as Chief Political Officer.*Register No. To — ,4, i if | v uxXAdJLI;, Letter from Dated 2']_ 7 ^ ^ Bee. Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary... Secretary of State... Committee i 1H 1 ‘U&gt;'H ^ . &lt;/evuc ZiAfovi-Crhyi Jj- bj). a* t j-'-'A srvi JJ- ^nou UJ^ S-.o.C. / Under Secretary Secretary of State FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY.*Xndexeu.. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to— The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W., the following number quoted. 121/3/429 (Ivl.0*2.A, ) . Sir f War Office, London, S.W. 22nd January, 1917. I am commanded by the Army Council to acknowledge the receipt of India Office letter Ho.P.297 of January 18th, and in reply to state that in the circumstances detailed by’ Chamberlain they are prepared to agree that the proposed ilakhtiari B'orce should be regarded as a Police Force, acting primarily under the British Minister at Teheran. -he council, however, trust that having regard to the responsibilities of the General Officer Commanding, Mesopotamian Expeditionary Force as mentioned in their letter of January 16th, the Officer Commanding the Bakhtiari Police may be instructed to keep in close touch with General Maude, ant to inform the latter as regards both his movements and his plans for the future in order that General Maude may have the oppor tunity of considering these in relation to his own operations. The Council are also of opinion that General Maude should have authority to defer the execution of any plans which he may consider undesirable on military grounds, and they agre-o to instruct General Maude to report at once any such action on his part. The Under Secretary of State, Military Department. India Office. S.W. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,p % ' * - - — ~v 1 Any further communication, on this subject should be addressed to— ' 0Q7 The Secretary, mm *** * War Office, London, S.W., ‘ Q 1'/ 1 ' ^nd the following number quoted. j SHCEET War ( 203 121/3/429.(M.0.2.) Sir, London, S.W. 16th January, 1917. I am commanded by the Army Council to acknowledge the receipt of India Office letter Ho.P.116 dated 11th January 1917. enclosing copy of a telegram from the Government of India regarding Bakhtiari levies and a draft of the proposed reply. I am to point out that the instructions of His Majesty's Government to the General Officer Commanding, Mesopotamian Expeditionary Force, as conveyed in telegram Ho.23374 dated 30th Beptember 1916, (a copy of which is attached for easy reference) provide that 'the Mesopotamian Expeditionary Force should ensure that hostile parties do not work down south across the line Shustar-Ispahan' In the opinion of the Council the operations of the proposed police force in the Bakhtiari country would approximate very closely to military operations and should therefore, by above provision, be under the jurisdiction of General Maude. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Military Department, India Office, S.W.is c B E T. N^Proin — C#I«Gr # S» to G.OsG* !Poutgo ,T D rT , 30th September, 1916. 23374 cipher. Following is for communication to Seneral Monro when he arrives at -^asra. Begins n Prior to your departure from England we discussed possible necessity of withdrawing troops to a position somewhat lower down the Tigris. This necessity seemed to exist for several reasons. The chief of these are (a) Defective communications and slow improvement of them, (b) Inability usually alleged or implied by G.Q.C. Force to find detachments when occasionally and temporarily required for employment elsewhere; the most recent instance of this is question of Patiala lancers. (c) Although it is realised the Force is indirectly doing more to secure Persia than merely holding up some 20,000 Turks in the vicinity of Kut we ought to derive greater value than we have hitherto from the large force employed. In other words, the force is sufficiently large to justify us in expecting it to carry out the following mission, which I am directed by the War Committee to communicate to you as being the instructions of His Majesty's Govern ment as decided on the 28th inst.. Begins TTU The Mission of the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force is to protect the oilfields and pipelines in the vicinity of the Karun Biver, to maintain our occupation and control of the Basra Vilayet, and to deny hostile access to the Persian Gulf and Southern Persia. At present no fresh advance to Baghdad can be contemplated, but it is the desire of His Majesty's Government, df and when possible, to es tablish British influence in the Baghdad Vilayet. This further advance should not be undertaken unless and until sanction for it is given but meanwhile the General Officer Commanding should continue to'to improv© tliQ rivsi* ami t* o■? t, rallwnj omumi«atloa, a na n,.i n , a i n .. forward « poem,, as th. , t .„ » f lls ooll „ nnlo a tloo , wlll allow, and as can be made secure tactically without incurring heavy loss, whether caused by the enemy or by climatic conditions Military and political considerations connected with Hasiriyeh and Mautifik and Bani Lam tribes, and the Pusht-i-Kuh Bakhtiari country suggest retention of our present positions if this can be achieved without undue sacrifices, but we desire your views as to the feasibility of this course. Your will no doubt consult Sir rercy Cox as to the effect on the Arabs of any withdrawal . Further, the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force should ensure that hostile parties do not work down south across the line Shustar- Ispahan. You must not expect to receive further reinforcements for the force. On the contrary, it may becane necessary to withdraw the Xlllth Livision, which was sent to the country in order to assist in the attempted relief of Kut.' Ends. His Majesty's Government you will observe wish the Force to be kept as far forward as is feasible and in this connection I wish you you to understand that so far as I person ally am concerned I leave the proposal as to the dispositions of the Force entirely to your judgement. You will also observe that the responsibilities of the Force extend to the Shustar-Ispahan direction but it is unlikely that this will make any material demand on the Force. You should also consider necessity of relieving some of the white battalions by battalions from India. Eegarding feasibility of eventual advance on Baghdad direction I have informed War Committee that in my opinion (a) we have not nor for an indefinite time are we likely to have available the number of troops recuired to seize anc hold that place, (b) Ve cannot hope for a long time to come owing to long and difficult communications to maintain them there even if we had them (c) Their position at Baghdad would in other respects be in a military sense unfavourable and would have no decisive effect • I - ~ ^on the war • Keeping in mind necessity for being as strong possible in decisive theatre, especially nest spring, consider whole situation in all its aspects with Cos and Maude and report your proposals with s ;ecial referent to i reierence to any change in dispositions you deem necessary”* Ends. Repeated to C-in-C. India.In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. W.8895/17. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Immediate. Foreign Office January 15th, 1917. r 7 ! i Sir:- I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to acknowledge the receipt, of your letter, P.116, of the 11th instant, enclosing a copy of a telegram from the Government of India, regarding the proposed Bakhtiari levies, and to state that he entirely concurs in the , terms of the reply which Mr. Secretary Chamberlain proposes to return to the Government of India on the subject. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.*P.S'Jf&amp;o. From Viceroy, Foreign Department, 2ord December 1916. \Fepeatcd to Tehran, Basra.) Secret. Your telegram of the 13th December. Bakhtiari tribal levy. We consider Noel’s proposals generally suitable. As force would serve interests of Khans as well as our own it promises to be successful. Cox suggests (group undecypherable) now at Ahwaz and Greenhouse now at Basra as suitable officers, both being well qualified and immediately available, and thinks that a third officer could also be obtained locally.Do cypher * sir ■ C^-Marilrig. (Teiieran). r^oei^er CL9X&amp; m / &gt; D # 5 0 20 p 0 m, December 7th, 1916, K c 8 a,m c December 8 th, 1916. No. 749 bo*9«,oe*«o Your telegram No. 5(?20), Success of scheme depends largely on good will of Khans who would be alarmed for virtual autonomy of ^ ilC±x tTj.be ii proposed police were at once made part o± Southern Persian Rifles 0 Captain Noel and I think io would be better at outsort to give force character oi tribal levy under general supervision -of local political officer. • As Persian Government, is shoving symptoms of objecting' to conclusion of agreements with tribes it would be best without reference to Persian Government to start raising nucleus of force in low country and units thus raised would he transferred to C&amp;ahar Mahal at the time of spring migration, * Commencement could be made with 200 infantry and 100 cavalry with 3 British officers under super vision of Captain Noel, Approximate cost, exclusive of., clothing, equipment and other initial • expenditure ana payment of ; -British.officers and instructors, can scarcely exceed ’tomans 6000 a month, Baxhtiar.i. Khans pr of ess to her eady to contr ibuto ■ s m Vi'i.is-: . ; r ■ to ■ - • . - J &lt;£ 1 i!,1, J' 1 to cost of force but it would bo Imprudent to ccunt upon any payment from them at outset and until force has actually been creatod, Yve should also consider whether it will suit our policy to Invite them to find any part of expenditure and so confirm and strengthen their local autonomy„ Force should eventually oscuffle p&gt;sirt of Southern Persian Rifles and therefore be organized on similar lines. Sent to Basrah,L DF In any further communication on the subject, please quote *1 A 4 tJL :w W.240038/16. No and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, . London. 510^ \9V Sir, Foreign Office December 5th,1916. ^ a, , 0 ,Y h&gt; A* With reference to your letter P.4746b of I f the 27th ultimo, relative to the present situation in Bakhtiaristan, I am directed by Viscount Grey of Fallodon to transmit to you,herewith, to be laid before Mr Secretary Chamberlain, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran giving his observations on the report from Captain Noel referred to in your letter under reference. I am to state that Lord Grey is in entire accord with the view of Mr. Chamberlain that the organisation of the local force suggested by Captain Noel would be most advantageous, and he would be glad if Mr Chamberlain would consult Sir P. Cox and the Government of India accordingly. A copy of a telegram which His Lordship has addressed to Sir C. Marling is also enclosed herein. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, o ^ The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. 1T\ved o' A 11[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PKH3IA, MILITARY (240038/16), Cypher Telegram to Sir 0, Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, December 4th, 1916, 7,35,p,m, No, 520, Your despatch No, 132, Suggestion No, 2, (of 21st, October Bakhtiari Police), India Office also favour idea. If you have recently discussed question with Noel I should be glad to receive any further observations. Do you consider that force should be completely in dependent of South Persia Nifles or nominally a branch thereof?oi ■•ji .ifc zo i«s he.B ibfc'J i r^cbion. arising be— tw^.i uha wo Parties. flUs strata of affairs cr-n-iot, how- #v«r # cO'iai-'iu# i 5d©li lively* Tb.# Huseia*!® are at# or©i*ertt# bu?-v&gt; mail a bore© of Persian aosgsoles? ii Isfahan and in time they will be X \ a poslbioa t#o exte il their con trol ut&gt; to the .Sa^htiari border. When this eo^es to oass tiiere will i ievitahly arise a crop oh i-.i-ciie its ouch as the escape of malefactors aid political suspects into tarh- tx&amp;ri territory, boundary disputes, olaite against Saiih- tiaris &amp;o. as a case in point I would • .entioo that of Dr. Asaaluilab, &amp; physician to the Jedhtiari Hhais. 'Phis inli- vidual is wanted by the Russian authorities in Isfahan, who have announced their intention of banging him if he should fall into their hands. I feel sure that under nre- ®e it circumstances it would not be poe Bible to nor on©, le the. Ehtais to hand him over. It would be folly to expect that with the ores©.it mutual attitude of suspicion and ill-feel- l hi between the two parties similar incidents likely to arise in the future will be settled without a dangerous amount of friction. 3ven if Bus»ian-Bakhtiari relations baoome normal, wtrt we shall still be confronted -it! «)# fact that a oowerful well-org8iia.il admlnlstratlo i is in contact■ (3) co i&amp;act* wiun. a wmtut aad 1X1 orgr?.ais»&lt;i on©* Unier o«m8^eno#8 it# wouii seem i ievliable tbati the Rassiais win be forced t»o interfere sooner or labor in Bakbbiari coun try. In my previous lesoabcbos and telegrams i have inli- cated four measur©® wnich^ in ^y opinion# would tend to re medy tbis state of affairs, I will a^ai x enumerate tl'iem in tfixat I consider uieir order of relative imoortance* (1) loatiuj: a small ragular force la Cbafar Kahal, ( liils would only mm, necessary as long as Turds remain in Persia# or until meeaure do, 3, referred to in newt nara - graph, begins to materialize,) (3) Formation of a Sebbbiari notice force under Bri tish officers* (3) Strengthening hands of Ilkhani an! Ilbeggi do ae to amble them to leal with Badhtiari internal situation, (4) Effooting a formal reconciliation between the 211 if ■; si os-SuXtan and the Bewcfetiari Khans* At one time it seomod to me that the adoptio.i of ooxites N? V v (3) miyht prove aufdiciont# but siaae my recent visit to Is- . • ‘ \ . ? fahan and my conversations with Russian authorities thoro# Isee little ho^m of the Bakhtiaris thetseislv®^ bsimr able do work out their own salvation. The RuseienB hare cions that we are BhieXding the JakhMariiKhans for the furtherance of our own Political ends, and our euooort of sen like Asiir Mujaliid, against who© the Russians have is— finite avi deice, certainly lends colour to those euericioos , Sirdar Muhtasha©, though loyal to us, ready to do what he is told and f. on; our poiitt of view probably the best ama at rm?- sent in . &gt;rdd; oiori for the oost of Xlkhani, is nevortl-elass not a stronu scan. It rruct aloro to re^eche.cod that in view of the rtronr ~inti-Rucslan and anti-Si 1 l-es-^ultan feeling that exists. It is iimrobable that any two Bakhtiari Hhane would be nrenared to tedee sufficiently energetic action to satisfy the Russian authorities. I would strongly urgr© that w© tsiie ixsaediate etees to raise a Jcusdiulari no lice force so that when the Persian do s sack 3x‘x&amp;aie, now bsi ti foiled by tl.e Ruaslane at Isfaliati, 'tades slxo^oe and is rrady to extend control un to the Bakhtiari border, we shall also be ready to link uo with a similar or* ganiss.tion on our si It. While the body in question U v being formed it would eeegQ very leslrable to maintain a small regular force in Ghahar ImmnmmRNTiU&gt; Ofcafcar as a Tb.Is 'force ooul.1, I tbinlr, be cut dowi as low as two aquadtraia of IiUan cwslvy with two roa^irns orovl-le 1 there are no Turkish troops ii Persia. In a 'furthat* iesoatoh X will rut forward definite rro— ousels for the fiiaiciig ail organisation of the orooosei Bsudtitlarl oolloe coros. This letter Is bei ig forwarded under flyi.ig seal to H. B. M’s to isul Uenisral Isfalu.,!, and a cooy is being so it to the thief Political Officer, Jaara I have the honour &amp;c (signed) U. hoel'** 0iii9t Obj0Cti ot *'* be to W ovu« aa orgR11 _ zatiloi. no work in aoo-.erat.ioi with the Suaeiane. Deb Turd, toe adn.1 Uetranive centre or Ohahar Mahal, would seem no oro- vide a auit»able headquarbera for- t&gt;h&amp; rorc@. j 1 %iz^§J&amp;.,JL QC. J0r®,L'lL !■? t Xae service* or at least three uritisfc. omoers would be necessary, i.e. CostaUaat, Adjutant aid Quarter Hester, several or toe younger generation of the Khans have ooeut two or tores years in toe Officers Tracing Ooms at borne. It ''Oul 3 certainly reaa. advisable to sake use of their eer- vices* I iTa*it&gt;ry 8 &amp;o 10 Toma is a aoiufc (To be armed by us). Cavalry IZ ho 14 Tomaie a naritfo* (To fl id their owa but jo be armed by ue and their horses to be fed by us.) dUv-ifafr, ’bA&gt;Qj;.,,,. ,;r.‘jd,£!Q.9„$, ThlB mould be 1&gt; io partly by oil© VSia is aid partly by tbB Persian Jover me.it or ourselves. ?l3e setboi I would sug gest woul i be for us to aoree to an increase of the tolls 00 the Lynch road in return for which the Thaos would guar antee a coitributio 1 towards the expenses of the force. Aa iacree.seDecypiisr. sir c. iiurijjfe (Teheran) November 5^30 p.m. November 29timl915* B« 11.20 sum. November 30111,1916. No. 729A&lt; Your telegron No. 486. I precume sugoestion ol agreement between Russians and minor Khavas refers to proposal made by Colonel Konnion that he should endeavour to obtain support of Chahnr Lang Bakhtiaris. Alter changing his mind once oi uWa.cc General Baratoff^ so Russian Minister informs me, has decided against experiment. I think decision wise as leading Khans among Chahar gave assistance to German Minister about a yesir «go when latter was on road to Kermanshah and is a very shifty character. Russian Minister knows of no other suggestion for n. mApk any agreement with Bakhtiaris punishment of the Chahar or Haft Lang. I fear it would be impossible to induce Russians to le ave relations of the two powers with tribes in our hands. Even if Russian Minister agrees to it, attitude of Russian Consul at Ispahan which is apparently reflected at ret.jgxau. as so consistently and unreason ably hostile t &gt; tribe that agreement could not in practice be car' cd out. .,sYI aT■PKRGIh ( 224138/16). MILITARY Cypher telegram to Sir C.Marling (Teheran). Foreign Office. November 11th.1916, No.486. Sir F.Oox will be instructed to repeat direct to you his three telegrams of November 2 nd, November 3 rd and November '4th, regarding Bakhtiari. •Any agreement between Russians and subordinate Khans would appear superfluous in view of our agreement with the Elder Khans and might have inconvenient consequences in the future. It is difficult however to press the Russian Government to abstain from action which they may consider necessary to stem the Turkish advance in Persia. ! Might it not be possible to induce Russians to leave to us the responsibility for Bakhtiari relations with the two Powers by explaining to your Russian colleague the scope of our recent agreement with the Khans? Otherwise what means can you suggest for co ordinating British and Russian policy in Bakhtiaristan? Repeated to Petrograd No.2633. ■- \ii I illIFrom Sir P. Cox, Basra, 3rd November 1916. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State for India.) (R.) No. 5677. Summary of information. Bakhtiari. Captain' Lilly with reinforcements and wireless pack station for Sykes telegraphs from Malamir, 1st November “ Khans representative has arrived, and he will continue his journey to Ispahan on 2nd November.” Noel telegraphs 2Sth October from Dehkard, that Salar Masud is moving on Burbur to plunder Zil -es-Sultan’s properties there. Hamadan area. Durie telegraphs from Kasoin, 1st November :—“ Turks have retaken Bijar, 31st October, with three battalions and artillery. Russian casualties 200 ; they are sending rein forcements from main body.” 2A C \From Sir 7\ Cox, Basra, 4:th November 1916. (Addressed Foreign, repeated Secretary of State for India.) (R.) No. 5700. Summary of information. Bakhtiaii. Noel reports 29tli October, son of Sardar Muhtasliam lias arrived from Western Luristan with bulk of sowars and mountain guns. He says 1m returned all revenues recently taken from Chahar Lang and subordinate s receipts lor same. Iskandar Khan, representative of Ilkani family, who was appointed in accordance with Mujahid, has deserted to lurks with 40 sowars, taking with him all revenues exacted. Noel also reports, 30th October, that he lias now received confirmation that about three weeks ago Murtaza Quli Khan, with knowledge and tacit approval of Amir Muhtasham, provided Muazid es Sultaneh (democrat journalist he was sheltering) with 70 sowars. Party left to join Turks. Hamad an area. Durie telegraphs 2nd November from Kas-ora, Russians state Turks have now full regiment at Bijar, about 1,500 Kurdish sowars, and four guns. Two battalions of 1,000 each, one regiment cavalry and two more Russian guns are on way from main body. _ Kennion reports 2nd November, Salar Masud and Sikandar Khan are at Ali Gudar collecting sowars. They have sent detachments to join Lurs in neighbourhood of Sultanabad. Collisions occurred daily between them and Cossacks. From 11 ilson, Basra, Ath November 1916. (Addressed to Foreign, Simla, repeated to Secretary of Stale for India.) (R.) 5721. Summary 12th October information. Bakhtiari. Minister telegraphs 2nd November in view of Murtaza Quli Khan’s action reported yesterday it seems impossible to confirm his appointment as lllbegi. He considers both he and Amir Mujahid should be summoned to Teheran, M§fi!t©l»ii&amp;e office of lllbegi temporarily vacant. He further regards with suspicion reported intention of Hkhani to keep as many as L,500 horsemen and 1,000 footmen in Chahar Mahal this winter on ground of alleged famine prices and scarcity (? groups omitted) preparing to get (sic) on the wrong- side of fence if a pretext presents itself. Enquiry shows, though there is no doubt Indian Frontier shortage of wdieat and barley in Arabistan, prices in Dizful, are, on the whole, lower than last year. Hamadan area. Reference to daily summary 1st November. Minister has telegraphed Kennion that he agrees to scheme, cost of which will be about 12,000 tomans a month, but cannot help to finance it. Colonel Kennion has however already been informed by Chief Political Officer that necessary funds will be provided from this side and is acting accordingly.Basra, BGtli September 1915. uy dear Brant, I attach a copy of a recent demi-official report irom i\ioel on the Bahhtiari - Ispahan situation. The problem is a difficult one and as it is current and recommendations will necessarily be made by telegraph, I do not propose to discuss it at length nere — ine minister wired a few days ago that he was exerting his utmost endeavours to get the Bussian Bovemment to assent to the nomination of a neutral Governor and that will no doubt improve the position. but we shall still be left with une fundamental ciifiiehlty, via. that the Russians at Ispahan seem bent on pursuing a relentlessly anti-3a3ditiari policy, which, is hound to react very detrimentally on our influence and prestige with the iiakhtiaris and consequently on the important British interests with which they are concerned. lours sincerely, Bd. h. Gox. hon T ble hr. A. II. crant, 0.ii*I* # Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department Simla•Dear Sir Percy, OMgliakliur, September lltli. I ba,ve done v*iiat I can to counteract trie ispalian tendency to represent tlie j^ajdiuiaris ana their activities in as unfavourable a flight as possxuie. The position at Ispahan would seem to me that the aiLlns supporters are taking every opportunity to get at the nn^iuiaris, now that the war uad the general unrest give them the .ceady ears ox une liussians. It will be readily realized that this process can only continue at the expense of our interests and prestige, nvery uay I have to espxain to the Khans, in regard to their continuous complaints that the Ispahan Government is putting tne screw on the naMitiaris, that the iiussians have the final say in all matters at Ispahan, and that in war time we cannot interfere or object to any measures of precaution they may see fit to take. The Bakhtiaris argue that the kill is now a man with no particular power, and that even the glamour of his name has to a great extent disappeared. The persistence of the Russians in securing his appointment can therefore only argue their fixed determination to drive out all Bakhtiari influence (i.e. pro-British influence) from Ispahan, and thoroughly Russianize the province in the same way that they have done in the North# It is therefore only natural that the Khans, and a great section of the tribes, should look on this process with feelings of dismay, and that it should go greatly against the grain with them to assist in any way in the establishment of the kill f s Government, a process which they regard as equivalent to the signing of their own death warrant. jay cue is of course to remind them of the Minister 1 s words that Ispahan is lost to them for a while, to point out that until the war is over the question of Ispahan must necessarily remain undeciued, and that, therefore, their best chance is to put their xriendship with us beyond doubt; to act in such a v/ay as to deserve well 01 us, and thus provide us with some argument which we can use with the Russians in their favour# This line of reasoning goes down alright with senior Khans such as Muhtasham and Zaffar, but it is very unpalatable to some of the minorminor Khans as well as the rank and file. You will therefore realise that the task of keeping' the tribes ^uiet is no easy one, and that kuhtasham and haffar have deserved well of us in what they have so far effected* It Vfould seem to me very necessary to put an end to the present impasse as soon as possible, either by effecting a reconciliation between the Bakhtiaris and the kill, the appointment of a neutral Governor at Ispahan, or the establishment of a gendarmerie force in Bakhtiari country under British officers* Yhe present spectacle of the Russians purposely making neavy weather of the position at Ispahan, when by a little give and take they might easily enlist the Bakhtiaris on tneir side, is not eailying© Another question that requires looking into is the governor ship of karaidun. ihe majority of property owners in this district ere Bakhtiaris or their close dependents, and the district naturally looks to the Bakhtiari Khans in all matters of adminis tration* iven in the time of the kill the Deputy Governor of Faraidun referred most matters to the Khans iox - settlement, tills oustoii has hy long usage exystalized, so that at present it represents the only possible '‘'modus vivendi'. MUK i’he hill's Government has hut a semblance of authority in tnis area, ax it tried to interfere, and the Bahhtiaris viii.lidi e,. uu^ii gooH offices, the district would relapse into the same state or anarcny that characterizes the rest of the Ispahan province. let in spite of this I have received complaints from Ispahan or Bakhuiaii interference in MB4IDUN, and I have been asked by Mr. Grahame to press the Khans to cease interfering there. This and many other questions require careful thought and discussion between the Russians and ourselves. Sven if the bakhtiaris have not come up to our expecuatiorrB, the fact remains that they represent the most virile and capable elements in Persia to-day, and we shall suouu. m aeed nr their good will and co-operation in the future development of the country. I would mention that of the coming generation many membersmembers lidve 'been educated in England and some of tliem have served for several years in tlie officers draining Uorps, and volunteer units* These young Khans of v/hom I would mention as examples. Hi Beza Khan son of muhtashaLi, Amir Aussein Khan son of naf far and Quli Khan son of as sad, have produced on me a distinctly pleasing impression. lours sincerely.PERSIA SERIES. Part X* i Telegram P., No. 124, dated the 26th (received 28th) September 1916. From—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Foreign Office sends following \~-Begins. September 25th, No. 437. Your telegrams 623 and 626. Situation at Ispahan and Shiraz is so complicated and variable that it is difficult to pass judgment on it here. Most important thing, however, is to avoid anything like a disaster to Gough or Sykes. It seems to me more prudent therefore for Gough and Farman Farma to withdraw from Abadeh and join Sykes at Ispahan. In all cases Sykes must take his instructions from you except (1) when they are in direct conflict with his views, in which case you should refer to me or (2) when local conditions necessitate immediate decision and action, and there is no time to consult you. You will, of course, make no change of plan without reference to Home Office and will keep me and Government of India informed of Sykes’s views, and on your own proposals and instructions to him. It must be made clear to Russians and to Sykes that as regards Sykes’s present position, his force has a civil and not military character, that he is not to be considered as under General Baratofl’s orders and that he does not form part of Russian forces. I agree with Government of India’s telegram of September 20th. Above all Sykes must be careful not to be drawn into action against Bakhtiari, except in full consultation with you. 2 Telegram It., No. 684 C., dated the 27th (received 28th) September 1916. p rom Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Ispahan, rp 0 _rphe Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated Chief of the General Staff, Tehran and Gough). Following prisoners brought to Ispahan by my Qumishah column: (1) Paschen, Lieutenant of German Army Reserve, ^handed over to His Maiestv’s Consul-General at Ispahan. (-) MiKjor Eath All Khan, Shiraa Gendarmerie. (3) Hussain Khan, Gendarmerie, said to be murderer of British Vice-Consul, Shiraz. (4) Malik Zadch, Ispahani, notorious democrat and enemy of British. These have been banded oyer to Persian authorities. -i f o M fT / 11 ' vj \ ■■ Received on j_&lt;c&gt; kv,- INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY Letter. No. ^r &gt; Telegram R., No. 687 C., dated the 27th (received 28th) September 1916. From— Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Ispahan, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Would it be possible for Yezd gendarmerie who, both officers and men, are most anxious to join new force and who would constitute a most valuable ^nucleus to be handed over to me ? I was much impressed by them and they need not necessarily leave Yezd for the present. Addressed Tehran; repeated Chief of the General Staff. Telegram R., No. 688 C., dated the 26th (received 28th) September 1916. From— Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Ispahan, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to Chief of the General Staff and Tehran). Column from Qumishah returned evening of September 26th and reports no incident either going or on return journey. Telegram R. } No. 689 C., dated (and received) the 27th September 1916. From— Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I E., C.M.G., Ispahan, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated Tehran, Chief of the General Staff and Gough)! Your telegram No. 696, September 24th, and Gough’s telegram No. 10, September 26th. If proposal to take over Shiraz and Abadeh gendarmerie en bloc finally agreed to presumably all negotiations by Gough will be carried out in consultation with me and in my name. Would it not be advisable to offer certain amount back pay to make proposal certain oi acceptance ? Telegram R., No. 101 F., dated the 27th (received 28th) September 1916, From— Lieutenant-Colonel H. Gough, Abadeb, From-—-The^Secretary tojhe Government of India in the Foreign and Political Clmr the line. Soulet and Kawam have given in and are willing to accept Barman Barma on following conditions. They are both to be mam* amed in their present positions as Illkhani of Kashgai aud Chief Khamseh etc., and I have promised them my assistance and protection of life and property as long as they behave loyally to Persian Government and keen their promises to us. I have promised that people of Bars shall not be persecuted .for their past opposition to Barman Barma as long as they behave themselves They asked that Binance Agent and others dismissed by Persia tery%Tolglv S to U this rei h a t n ^ ilTfi m T arrival: 1 told them Objected very strongly to this, but would telegraph to you and ask vou to nlaee slwr liiave^xnr* 1 ^ in . isters / ho would send de finite orders on the naif Tuesday. October Srd ^ t0 Farma acd he is read ? EarmiTsindW n h i nS K Q W .f n C0lne and meefc U9 on roa «l- Earman Deputy Goyernor ^ f ° r S “ Muntazim to take duties finally ofI great mistake to koidTa^nw° V0 ^aL^truT Svk !Cafed l Y' 14 Wol,ld be possible. - 1 al£0 trust s Jtea will follow as soon as Addressed Tehran; repeated Basrah, Bushire and Sykes. ^ ’ N °' ^ 73 ’ ^ (aDd recei ' ,ed ! 2 8 tl&gt; September 1916. From-The Deputy Political Keaident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire To—lhe Secretary to the Government of India ; ^ tb • ^ ’ ment, Simla (repeated Foreign, Basrah a “ d P ° liticaI De P art - My telegram No. 313—1865. ' ' whet^olls^” B^as a,, ' 'if™ 0 ,'’ but 1 do -‘know yet assailants. Ghazanfar has sent our sobbed several times by his 8 Telegram, No. 1108-W., dated the 27th September 1916 Fr ° m ~ T Depart S ‘° m ,^ G '‘ o£ ^ - the Foreign and Political T 0 -Be,g. D i B .g^„.i Si. P. M. Sr..,, K.C J.E., C.M.G., [ w.J.XXrkXXSfstr’ “- c - ^ Addressed Sykes; repeated Minister, Cox and Lorimer. Peceived with Army Department memorandum No. 10578, dated the 27th September 1916 ) Telegram P, No. 23139-Cipher, dated the 23rd (received 24th) September 1916 . Prom The Director of Military Intelligence, War Office, London To—The Commander-in-Chief in India, Simla. «fo P ff e r’ ber 21st Ma;,0 l r •¥ arsh ^graphs that the Russian Chief of the General Staff, Caucasus, emphasised the following points “ * tb lot w he fff. 68 t0 KaJCa 7 in ‘ Tt ' 1,ran wil1 be closed b y Several Baratoff. ,(2) Baratofl s existing force will be maintained up to strenetb it ,„ ]! not be increased, but nothing will be taken from it. ° ’ 4 1 (3) The greater part of the reinforcements required for this reached Baratoff already, but it will be another month before all have arrived, as they have to travel on foot from Enzeli. ,(4) Although war is an uncertain factor, I think that Baratoff will h« to Tehran. 011 ° ^ ^ t0 absolutel y olose th e roads which lead ( 5 ) Tbe a .rmies of the Caucasus at present have to contend with the weight of the whole of the Turkish army and to spare more men than those mentioned above is impossible. The following is added by Marsh. Undoubtedly the Russian Officers have intrigued among themselves with the object of leaving Persia and rejoining the mam army in the Caucasus but on the retention of Tehran the CzJ is fuite resolved. Refer to my No. 22286 telegram. ^ ^ Addressed Basrah; repeated India.(Received witR Army Department memorandum No. 10579, dated the 27th September 1910.) Telegram No. B. M.-19, dated (and received) tke 23rd September 1915. From— General Dyer, Khwasb, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. Tar Mahomedzai lashkars o£ Zulfikar and Pasaod are be com- ing into Khwash to accept my terms m which case I propose releasing Zulfikar and Fasand. , _ n i Addressed Political, Chagai; repeated Agent to the Go vcrnor-Genera.i, Baluchistan, Chief General Staff, and Colonel Dale, Khwas . (Received with Army Department memorandum No. 10577, dated the 27th September 19m&gt; Telegram P., No. 80906, dated tbe 24th September 1916. From— The Chief of the General Staff, Simla, r (1) Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Ispahan. To— &lt; \ (2) The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D ”, Basrah. With reference to your telegram of September 23rd, No. 666-C. Kindly wire which route Noel has taken, also his position at present, and location and strength of the tribesmen who are opposing him. It is most important that you should ruu no risk of becoming engaged with forces which are superior. Addressed Sir Percy Sykes repeated General Officer Commanding, I’orc&amp; * D ”, Basrah. 13 Telegram P., No. 717-S., dated the 29th September 1916. From—The Secretary to tbe Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To— Brioadibr-Generai, Sik P. M. Stkes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Ispahan (repeated to Tehran and Cox). Tour telegram 636-0. of Wth September. It is very unlikely that a cavalry regiment can be spared from Mesopotamia at present. Lack oi mounted troops should, it is considered, be made good by speeding up as soon as practicable recruitment of mounted portion of South Persia Bines. 14 Telegram P., No. 53-F., dated (and received) the 29th September 1916; From—His Britannic Majesty's Consul for Sistan and Kain, To—Ihe Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (sent to Tehran, Baluchistan, Meshed and Kermau). Dehani reports that 30 Afghan gun-iunners passed through Gurg on September 24tb from south to north. On September 26th Lieutenant Wahl attacked them with troop of cavalry and few levies at Kal Amas. Pour Afghans killed, one captured, and it is said that all enemy arms and transport have been captured. Remaining Afghans will, it is hoped, be caught by parties from Sistan. Wahl and one duffadar were killed.18 Telegram R., No. 701-C. 3 dated (and received) the 30th September 1916 - . From— Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Ispahan, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Secret. I am informed by Commander of Russian troops, Ispahan, that General Tchernazonboff five days ago issued orders for combined series of operations intended to solve finally Tukish situation in Persia. Further that in these plans which if successful would take 22 days to carry out, presence of my column as garrison of Ispahan was essential in order to release Russian troops here for employment in combined scheme. One squadron and one gun of Russians left here on September 27th, others expected to leave any time. I gather from tone of information that Russians were not too sanguine of success and that if operations unsuccessful, more active co-operation of my column would be necessary. J Above for information. Addressed Foreign and Tehran; repeated Chief of the General Staff. Basrah, Bushire and Gough. 19 Telegram P., No. 721-S., dated the 30th September 1916. From The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Kerman (repeated Tehran, Sykes, Ispahan and Basrah). &gt; r &gt; , telegram of 22nd September, 120. Government of India have no! t / e ? f ° rCe . m a nt - S Sh0uld proceed t0 Yezd * Utilization of detachment of lOSth Infantry at Sirjanas a temporary measure is concurred in, but it should rejoin its regiment as soon as possible. Recruitment of Kerman portion ol South Persia Rifles should be expedited as much as possible as maintenance of order in localities like Sirjan is properly its r61e. 20 Telegram R., No. 126, dated the 30th September (received 2 nd October) 1916. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political ment, Simla (repeated to Sykes, Basrah and Colonel Gough). Sykes* telegram No. 701-C. Depart- _ Military Attachd thinks that Russian Commander has been drawin« on his imagination In the first place General Baratoff's command is independ^ en and m the second General Chernozubow*s left only reaches Sakiz. Military Attache s expenence shows that Russian local military authorities are kept m ignorance of movements in contemplation. Russian Minister has r.srj,; s £; i rs. I,, “ h *'’ » -hi- » 21 Telegram R., dated the 30th September (received 1 st October) 1916. From—His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, To—The Secretary^ the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- Sykes telegram 701-C., dated 30th September. I beg to press a-ain urgency of situation in Pars. If m y move on Shiraz is dependent on Sy W coming immediately, I trust the latter may receive orders P to start without1 delay. Success or failure of lar^e dependent on presence of 450 men, while failure to^r 6 ^ 8 ^ sc ? reel y be favourable situation in south might land us in grave dfflcuUies g6 ° f P1 ' eSeilt Personally I am of opinion that we could with perfect safpfv o-n r t provided it is understood that Sykes will follow onieldv^ &lt;s T?i, g forward » following in traces and is not likJly to await our arrival h ^^ ot beeu few men and is in great need of mnnpv r a 1V ?^. ^ awam has very us and cannot carry on without us. ^ aimerie 18 n0V7 absolutely for all deference 1 1 Venture' to'^r^^gain 0 necessity With favourable situation, and importance of Sykes’ coming as soonls poJXe^ Addressed Tehran and India; repeated to Sykes, Basrah and Bushire. 22 Telegram R., No. 716-C., dated the 1 st (received 2 nd) October 1916, From Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- Secret. Your telegram No. 126 to India, September 30th. I am unable to disclose more of Russian plans as they were confided to me somewhat unwillingly and under promise of secrecy. I can, however, assure you that they did not emanate from Russian Com mandant as supposed by Military Attache, who forgets that Russian militarv authorities have to receive instructions and information when taking part in operations. ° ^ ^ s /f °P era ^ ons are concerted and have actually commenced, Military Attache s first and second points apparently fall to the ground. I think that in view of facts given in my telegram No. 701-0., General Baratcff should be, it only from military courtesy, consulted before move of column to Shiraz rather than Russian Minister, who is hardly likely to be in possession of all facts of military situation. Strongly maintain view that column should remain at Ispahan until Turkish retreat unquestionable. Addressed Tehran; repeated Gough, Cox, and Chief of General Staff. 23 Telegram R., No. 105-F., dated the 1 st (received 2 nd) October 1916. From— Lieutenant-Colonel H. Gough, Abadeh, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Farman Farma had a personal interview with Soulet and Kawam on telephone yesterday and gave them assurances to same effect as mine quoted in my telegram 101-F., September 28th. Both persons named accepted tnese and in returp protested they were now completely satisfied. I hope sanction may now be received in time to permit us leaving on Tuesday 3rd. Addressed Tehran, sent to India; repeated Basrah, Sykes and Bushire. 24 No. 80 P., dated Yezd, the 24th August (received 26th September) 1916 (Confidential). From— Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Inspector-General, South Persia Military Police, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, I have the honour to give a brief account of the march of the column to Tezd and of the position of affairs at that desert city.2. The column started on 26th July, hut as Major Lorimer had only reached Kerman on 24jth July the staff remained behind until 28tn and over took the column at the second stage. 3. The march lay throughout up the wide, level valley which is ideal country for mechanical transport and at the same time easy to protect against robbers. The question of transport, which had been most troublesome on the march from Bunder Abbas, was comparatively easy, as both the males and camels were properly trained and the marches were easy. The supply question too worked smoothly, a Kerman contractor buying and laying out supplies to the Yezd frontier where Mr. Meriton, His Britannic Majesty’s Yice-Consul took up the task. 4. The journey was uneventful. At Kafsinjan four men were arrested for disturbing the peace by pro-German intrigues, but nothing special being proved against them, they were released. They will probably be careful in future. 5. The march was of value to me as I was able to find out the exact position as to robbers w T bose raids have everywhere increased terribly. Two or three new robber tribes have appeared on the scene. Their home is in Yezd territory which stretches two degrees to the south of Yezd city—a fact of some wolitical importance if the Russians retain Yezd in their sphere of influence, phich I earnestly hope will not be the case. But the Baharlus still retain the doubtful distinction of being the leading robber tribe. It was rumoured that we were to be honoured by an attack by them which failed to materialise and at the time of writing they are attacking Anar. There is no doubt that this tribe must be crushed by regular troops as a preliminary to the restoration of order in Southern Persia. The fact that the Baharlus have abandoned their nomadic life will make the task less difficult. 6. At Anar I was welcomed by the notables, one of whom was the Russian Agent. He appeared to be a worthy man and said that he had enter tained the Russian Consul at dinner some years ago and had been appointed to this post in return, Ihe Russian system of appointing agents at centres where they have no subjects, trade, or other interests gives much scope for intrigue. The one subject of the conversation with the notables of Anar was the terrible scourge of brigandage. 7. At Mehdiabad two stages west of Anar the Germans had written some doggerel lines in English on the walls of the Telegraph Rest House signed by Becker and M. M. B.; the latter designated himself as belonging to the 23rd and 42nd Afghan Uhlan Regiment! 8. Yezd was reached on August 14th, the march of 230 miles bein°- accomplished in 20 days. The reception was most cordial. On previous occasions I have reported the extraordinary position gained by Hr. White of the C. M. S. and his staff and as years go by this position is strengthened. Mr. Meriton, Telegraph Superintendent and British Yice-Consul, is also popular and respected. He has worked very hard on our behalf. The column was welcomed by the leading notables, some of whom I had known for many years and was entertained in a garden. We then marched on to Mehdiabad a village two miles short of Yezd, where guns were fired in honour of the arrival of the column. 9. The Governor, the Zia-i-Hooleh, is a Persian of the old school whose feelings were ruffled at not being saluted by Artillery, but recoverino- from this he was most friendly. He paid the first call and upon returnin°' it°I took the entire force of cavalry through the bazaars. Eater, he gave a really splendid banquet in our honour with fireworks. So far he has done everything I have asked him to do, quite realising his position. Unless we make Yezd safe he will probably resign in true Persian style. 10. I was visited by representatives of the merchants and by the Parsee Anjuman. In view of the wild rumours obtaining credence I explained the Russian situation and remarked that it was purely temporary and need cause no serious apprehension. The community is deeply interested in the scheme of organizing the security of the Bunder Abbas-Kerman route by means of telegraph and telephone lines, by improving the existing tiack and above all by the creation of a new force.11. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General at Ispahan who has earned our gratitude by purchasing 350 mules for the column at the cost of much risk and trouble sent them off from Ispahan at the beginning of August, but in spite of an escort of Indian sowars, they had to return as robbers were too numerous and strong. Starting a second time they were hung up at Nain by robbers holding No Gumbaz the stage to the south. Sixty gendarmes were sent for, but even with this reinforcement the party was attacked by a strong band of 150 Lashanis. The village of Akda was reached and a message was sent into Yezd through the telephone station at Ardekan that the party was surrounded. The cavalry, one hundred infantry on riding mules and two machine guns were immediately despatched to the rescue, but the robbers dis appeared before the cavalry could gain touch with them. The Indian Officer and escort and the gendarmes behaved well and the Brigands apparently suffered some casualties whereas only one groom was slightly wounded on our side. It is to be noted that the telephone station at Ardekan was invaluable, forwarding the news a day earlier than it would otherwise have reached Yezd. 12. Copies of this letter are being sent to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, Sir Percy Cox, His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, and His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Bunder Abbas. 25 No. 8926, dated Basrah, the 10th (received 26th) September 1916.. Prom—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.S.L, K.C.I.B,, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, copy of an interesting letter addressed by Captain Noel, Political Officer with the Bakhtiari Khans, to His Majesty’s Minister on the present Bakhtiari situation and outlook. 2. At the moment the position in regard to Ispahan and Shiraz is in such a state of flux and uncertainty that I see little use in offering present comment and would prefer to wait until the atmosphere is clearer. Enclosure. Dated Chighakhur, the 9th August 1916. Prom Captain E. Noel, His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, To Sir Charles Marling-, K.C.M.G., C.B., His Britannic Majesty’s Minister and Envoy Extraordinary, Tehran. I have the honour to address you on the subject of the general situation in the Bakhtiari country. The remarks which follow have reference only to the Khans. Of the tribes themselves it is sufficient to state that pure y domestic matters loom so large in their horizon as to dwarf all others; that their sympathies and feelings are of the most unsubstantial nature, and that materially t ley are fo dependent on the Khans as to take their cue almost entirely from them. It must not however be assumed that the allegiance ot the tribes rests on any very secure basis or that the present relations between ruled and rulers possess any considerable elements of stability. In treatin'* therefore of the general situation as reflected by the bearing mire ^ Khans it mav make my subsequent remarks more LtllSn I try to explain the ^present attitude oAhe Khans to the role Ihey have played in the past, and to their aspirations and hopes for the present and future. , , , I think it may be safely assumed that the elder and more experienced members of both families hive little doubt that whatever the result ot th*war in Europe, it will not remove the Bakhtiari destinies from our keeping. Of the younger generation there are some such as Salar Masoud who feel that they have burnt their boats, and others such as Sirdar Fateh who cannot acknowledge the logic of facts owing to their pro-Turkish sympathies. In the same way the more sensible of the Khans have now realized that they made a mistake in not throwing in their lot with us definitely at Ispahan, Yezd and Kerman. On the other hand they look on their fault as one of omission and not commission. The Bakhtiari Khans share to such a marked degree the typical Persian characteristics of following the line of least resist ance and waiting to have ones hand forced by the march of events, that often in conversation, after starting by the admission that they failed us, they unconsciously veer round to the argument that they really deserve credit for having run counter to the strong trend of popular feeling to the extent they did. With this frame of mind, they are more or less honest with themselves in arguing that the complete loss of Ispahan as spelt by the Zil es Sultan’s reinstatement is a punishment out of all keeping with the laches on their part which called it forth. With the holders of thp above opinion it is diffi cult but still possible to argue, but the same cannot be said for a considerable section of the younger Khans, of whom I would take Sirdar Fateh as a representative, who lay claim to merit on the grounds that they refrained from attacking the oil fields and allowed us to use the Ahwaz-Ispahan road when our fortunes were at a low ebb. A further trait is the strong impression that the war has only temporarily effaced Anglo-Bussian rivalry in Persia, and that as soon as peace has been declared we will fall back on the Bakhtiaris as a valuable asset in extendino- our political influence. For this reason they cannot understand our not beinS secretly pleased at the success of their efforts to embarrass the Russians at Ispahan. The chief characteristics of the more responsible of the chiefs mav therefore be summarised as a failure to see themselves as we see them and ^ realization that they must stand in with us combined at the same time with a belief that we will wish to use them as a pawn in the game of political rivalry The personal outlook and feelings of the Khans do not, however affect the Bakhtiari situation as much as material facts. The Khans like th‘ tribesmen, are so easily swayed by each fresh development that present itself. For this reason the main pivot on which most Bakhtiari question^ now hinge is the loss of Ispahan and its falling into the hands of their hercdi tary enemy the Zili es Sultan. eui ' The loss °£ Kerman and Yezd they are prepared to take more or ]«, philosophically. These governments were after all perquisites and still retained a good deal of the nature of a windfall. The same may be said tr lesser degree of Ispahan. The loss of the Government of Ispahan th t were perhaps prepared to accept. The arrival of the Zill, however means a good deal more to them than the loss of the Governorship It’ mea in iact that life for them m Ispahan is no longer possible. Durine the i„f few years the Khans have come to look on Ispahan as part and parcel nf the heritage. In addition to their extensive properties in the district and th houses m the town, Ispahan represented to them their link with the cult and life of the outside world. To be cut off from Ispahan is dimly fe t h them to amount to a decree of banishment from the new fields of proeress “ 1 enlightenment which had been opened up to them, and a rude forcm- to the state and ways of the primitive migratory tribes from which they . congratulate themselves on having emerged. So far the Khans have Un quite unable to reconcile themselves to the thought that Ispahan has definite^ passed irom their hands. It is possible to argue with them dispassiona e y that they have brought this calamity on to their own heads, but in the con y of conversation it becomes clear that they look on the restoration of ntf old position as being in the natural order of things. e Whether the Khans will passively accept the fact that the Zill has come to stay must to a great extent depend on the course of events in Persia r. may be safely said that in accordance with their chief characteristic of follow jng the hue of least resistance a section of the Jlakhtiaris will certainly male11 hand, provided affairs in Persia continue to run° in o„r favour ^ , 0th ' , ^ manner as they have been doing for the last few months, there is every TTe- liuood o the Khans natural inertia of character causing the German agitation and the irritation over the loss of Ispahan to die a natural death tt f T ^ a t b ° v a “Nervations refe r only to the question of active oppostion Unfortunately the Bakhfans have it in their power to cause embarras°meni to the Ispahan Government in an entirely passive manner. I refer to them encouragement of lawlessness in the Ispahan district, reports of which have doubtless reached you from various sources. This matter is one which requires some explanation. In the ease of the more responsible of the Khans it would be a mistake to_ accuse them of having definitely sent plunderin'* bands to harry and rob Lenjan and Faraidun. The most notable of the robber chiefs were a thorn m the side of previous Bakhtiari Governors at Ispahan and even m their recent operations they have in many cases failed to respect Bakhtiaii piopeity. On the other hand these predatory bands are only able to operate on their present scale and with their present success owin 0 ” to their knowledge that the Khans approve their activities in so far as they tend to discredit and embarrass the Zill’s Government. The robber leaders ask for no better assistance or encouragement which spells for them the existence of a base from which to carry on their operations. That this is a true representa^ tion of the case is beyond doubt, and the Khans in conversation tacitly .acknowledge it to be such. In this connection I would mention that ,a general meeting of the Khans at which I tried to impress on them the necessity of giving us some tangible proof of their friendship which we could use to disarm Russian suspicions A ir Mujahid came out with the remark that if only the Russians would appoint a neutral Governor, the Rakhtiaris would co-operate with them to such an extent that the menace of Jafter Quli and Reza Khan would disappear in a very short space of time. Of course there is a certain section of the Khans, who may be referred to as the extremist party, who have deliberately sent their adherents to join the marauding bands across the Bakhtiari border. But, on the other hand, we have in pleasing contrast the example of the 111 Begi, Sirdar Muhtasham, who, I have every reason for believing, is doing his best to keep the tribesmen quiet, and counteract the evil influence of the other Khans. The question arises as to whether this passive form of resistance will ako •die a natural death. If left to itself I am afraid there is little chance of tie Khans putting a stop to it. The solution w r ould therefore appear to lie in t) e Russians being able to deal with the present disorder and insecurity in spite of the Bakhtiari Khans, i.e., to ignore their opposition. It would seem to me, however, that our attitude of hands off the Bakhtiari Khans, accompanied by a refusal to take any active measures ourselves will be a difficult one to maintain vis-a-vis the Russians. A further point for consideration is that the Bakhtiaris, owing to their geographical position and close ties with Ispahan, must sooner or later come into contact w ith the Russians and have considerable dealings with them. In this case it would obviously be to our advantage to have the Bakhtiari internal ^situation well in hand, and thus be in a position to guide and control the Bakhtiari external relations with the Russians. It will thus be seen that the present situation in Bakhtiari country has two -aspects, firstly, the danger resulting from the presence of the Germans and the possibilitv of a further Turkish success near Kermanshah giving the Bakhtiaiis an opportunity of seizing Ispahan ; secondly, the probability that toe present policy of passive obstruction to the Ziil’s Government will eventually force us or the Russians to intervene. In my telegram No. 388,^ I suggested as radical remedy for both these states of aft airs, our strengthening the hands of the 111 ivham and 111 Begi by helping them to raise an irregular Bakhtiari force, and our supplying a s 1 e ^- ing of a small contingent of regular troops the object of the latter being to provide a stimulus to keep the Khans up to the mark. It, however, he Turkish success at Kermanshah is considered merely as a flash m the pan, anathat in consequence we run little risk in allowing the Germans to remain in Bakhtiari country, it only remains for us to find a solution for remedying the^ second state of affairs. In the telegram already referred to such a solution was indicated in the alternative suggestion that we should raise a Bakhtiari police force under British officers. Since the expression of those views I have been much exercised as to the question of finding some modus vivendi between the Khans and the Zill e&amp; Sultan, provided the latter is to be a fixture at Ispahan. The only solution that has so far occurred to me is that we should endeavour to effect a formal reconciliation between the Zill and the Khans. I have not approached the Khans on the matter, but I have every reason to believe that the scheme is a perfectly feasible one provided the Zill can be persuaded to settle the blood feud in tte accepted tribal manner by paying the Khans a visit in their country. I am not, of course, in a position to express an opinion as to how the Zill would view the proposal, but I cannot help feeling that if you could see your way to visit the Bakhtiari country this autumn, your presence and influence might provide just the inducement required to persuade the Zili to accompany you and make his peace with the Khans. It would seem to me that this proposal should be considered independ ently on its own merits. It would of course be a fitting complement to the adoption of either of the more redical remedies already suggested, but should not, I think, be looked upon in any way as an alternative measure or substi tute. A copy of this letter is being forwarded to the Chief Political Officer, Basrah. From— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Deputy Political Kesident, Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. In continuation of my telegram No. 1812 of to-day, I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, translations of letters written from Sirjan on 2nd August 1916 by Dr. Sutoras Herr Brug- mann and Obeydullah the Turkish emissary to Herr Seiler at Shiraz, describ ing their position subsequent to their arrest at Kerman by Brigadier-General Sir P. Sykes in June last. 2. The messenger bringing these letters was intercepted at Shiraz by Nejaf Khan, the Intelligence Agent, who managed to get hold of the letters by promising the hearer that he would not be punished, Nejaf Khan got a trans lation made at Shiraz by some one who knew German, and it is no doubt a rough one; I have had no means of checking it, as Nejaf Khan was afraid to send the original letters by post in case they should go astray. 3. The letters form an interesting comment on Sir P. Sykes’ despatches, Nos. 68-P. and 74-P., dated 19th July 1916. 4. A copy of this letter is being sent to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Enclosure Ao. 1. Translation of a letter from Dr. Sutoras to Herr Seiler, dated the 2nd August 1916. As I told you in my last letter, Obeyduilah, Brugmann, Dettmer (torpedo engineer) and Oertel (merchant and technical expert) both of latter being civilian prisoners who have escaped from the Russians arrived in Sirjan the 29th July under Persian escort. Officer in charge of escort, PHnce Husain, has been ordered by General Sykes to remove me and the sick men to Bunder Abbas. I didn t want to go and tried to delay the start by arguing the point hoping to get correct news from Shiraz. I thought this all the more desirable because I heard that you and the rest in Shiraz were free and that Wassmuss was advancing from Bushire to Shiraz. We also get good news here from13 Kermanshah which was perhaps why Sykes ordered oor and Oheydullah’s removal to Bonder Abbas, and why on the 26tb July he himself with all his officers and men left Kerman for Yezd, from which place he means to go to Shiraz. At first he wanted to go to Shiraz via Sirian, hut the mad Z 1 vf d hy o'® Baharlu8 - The Baharlus have also closed 3 the road to Bunder Abbas, and two weeks ago they looted a British Consul at Daulatabad, caught him hut let him get away again, blow Sykes has received news from Kashan and Kermanshah and about the Baharlus blocking the Bunder Abbas-Shiraz road whereupon he retired on Meshed, He does not say so himself I ^ merely think personally that he won’t go to Shiraz at all, but straight iito Khora- san to join the Eussians. He has with him 80 sowars, 120 Indian Infantry and five or six officers. Apparently he has * * * guns. The Indians wept daily with Obeydullah and kissed his hands(?) they are frightfully cut up at his being a prisoner. There must be something going to happen because Adles- Sultan gave me a horse the very day we heard Sykes had left Kerman. We all want to come to you except Obeydullah who will perhaps return to Kerman. If you are in strong enough position in Shiraz, please send us an escort! Prince Husain the officer in charge of escort will try to (help us to) escape so that we may all be free again, though penniless. Brugmann has no money either, Sardar Zafar took all his carpets and private effects. The English examined and tormented Brugmann terribly, Sykes reproached him with all sorts of things that had nothing to do with him. The Persians say Dr. Biach voluntarily surrendered to the English. Sykes continually quoted Biach saying to Brugmann—My friend Dr. Biach told me * * * * I am fed up with letter writing, I have written about fifteen times already and never get any reply. I am now free(?), but Obeydullah, Brugmann (and the Afghans) are very strongly guarded, suppose they will soon be free like you. If possible please let me know how things are with you and whether we can get to Shiraz or not. With most cordial greetings to all, especially to Austrians and yourself, from us all. (The following in the m argin):—Baharlus wanted us to go with them to Darab, no good(?) Enclosure No. 2. Translation of a letter from Brugmann (?) to Consul Seiler, Shiraz, date? As Obeydullah has already told you in his letter, we are now in Sirjan en route for India. The English have cleaned me out completely. I have not yet given up all hope of an attempt to rescue us being made from Shiraz, if possible please do your best; how is Mr. Professor Doctor Zugmeyer, at present ? If he is in Shiraz please tell him of my being a prisoner, and also let him know that Biach is in Bombay and that his last letter to me (mentioned by Dr. Sutoras) never reached me. We shall try to spin out our stay in Sirian as long as possible. I hope you and the other gentlemen aie all in the best of health and send you all greeting. If Mr. Dr. Zugmeyer is there ask him to transmit my compliments to Greisinger and Weding. Hope we shall soon all meet again in freedom. Enclosure No. 3. Translation from a letter written in French from Obeydullah to Herr Seiler, dated 2 nd August 1916. I take this opportunity to write you a line. I knew what has happened ;o you during your voyage and your piesent condition in Shiraz. After your departure I stayed in Kerman till General Sykes arrived. A [ortnight after his arrival I was arrested in the name of the Govern men ^ India, that was June 26th, and on July 16th I, Brugmann and two otherGermans, who had escaped from Russia, started for Bunder Abbas as prisoners of war, we have been at Sirjan a fortnight, recently we heard you were at liberty. These'days we hear many favourable pieces of news. Please let us know how you are getting on, and come and save us from the hands of the English, who have already disappeared after receiving news recently from Kerman. We expect you and news of you with impatience. Compliments to all, &amp;c. ^ Dear Sir. 27 Telegram R., No. 711-C., dated the 30th September (received 3rd October) 1916. From— Bkigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., d.M.G., To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. On September 30th despatched party of 40 cavalry, 1 section of mountain guns, 150 infantry and 1 section machine guns, with approval of Russians who have sent officer and 10 Cossacks, to Kavarukh 50 miles along Lynch road to escort in large quantity of goods held up. Move should aid Noel to some extent. Addressed Tehran ; repeated Chief of the General Staff, and Noel informed. 28 Telegram R., No. 1 , dated the 1 st (received 2 nd) October 1916 . From— Lieutenant-Colonel H. Gough, Abadeh, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. r Your telegrams, No. 104 and 106, dated September 16th and September 17th, respectively. I have caused offer of reward to be published and have addressed Kawam with a view to his taking action suggested. He replied that he has sent necessary orders, but Sheikh Abdul Hassan is Yaghi and that best way to bring pressure on Kohistanis is for Consul, Bunder Abbas, to threaten blockade of their trade with Bunder Abbas. ^^ resse ^ Kerman; repeated Tehran, Basrah, Bushire, Bunder Abba&amp; and Sykes. Telegram P., No. 656-F., dated the 2 nd (received 3 rd) October 1916. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. 1 Clear the line. My telegram No. 646. I propose to authorise Gough to (leave?) on October 4th unless I receive instructions to the contrary as Persian Government are convinced that he and Barman Parma can go to Shiraz at present without risk and are urging strongly their immediate departure and I agree with them. • 1 un ^? stan( * ^ at His Majesty’s Government approve in principle his going to Shiraz although date of his departure is left undecided in view of Your Lordship s authority to conclude arrangement to finance Barman Parma. Longer stay at Abadeh is also made difficult by question of supplies. Addressed B oreign Office; sent to Basrah and Colonel Gough.30 Bated the 3rd (received 26th) May 1916. From -The Officer Commanding Troops/^istan, Kacha, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla, si \ honour t0 forward herewith the original of gned by the Sarhadi Sardars on 30th April 1916. the Agreement {Translation.) AGREEMENT. We the Sardars whose seals and signatures are given below hereby a^ree to accept the allowances fixed by General Dyer, commanding the British foices on the frontier for our Sardars and notables and we agree in return to luliil all the following conditions which we now write down (1) We will always remain faithful and loyal to the British Government. . (?) From to-day neither we ourselves nor our tribe will give any trouble in British territory or to British employes, subjects or inhabitants and we will not harbour any intention of giving trouble either. If by any chance our trite should fail to carry out this promise, we will arrest the man responsible and hand him over to General Dyer, his representative, or the officers in charge at the place where the act contrary to this promise has been com mitted. If any man should be the cause of spreading revolt, the officers in authority at the time shall be fully entitled to punish him as they think fit and no objection will be made to their action and no sardar or notable shall have any right to put forward any recommendation for mercy. In short the British Government shall punish the guilty man in accordance with the criminal law. (3) All the sardars of the district will regard that man who is an enemy to the British Government as their own enemy. If any German or other person should wage war or create a disturbance against the British Govern ment then it will be the duty of us, sardars, to oppose him. If we are not strong enough to oppose him successfully by ourselves, we will at once inform the frontier officers in authority at the time and with our own lashkars assist ing those of Government will do our best to destroy the enemy utterly. (4) If we hear in our district or elsewhere that any German or other spy belonging to a hostile state or parties of them have been trying to spread any form of trouble or discontent we will arrest the same and hand them over to the officers in authority. (5) We promise to bring before the General the 500 young men required by the British Government for frontier work with the levies within 10 or 15 dajs at the latest, and w r e will appoint one man as an officer with each tribe represented among this number. Besides this we will be ready to provide more men, if the formation of further levies is required and will make no objection. The sardars of each tribe will be responsible for the behaviour of the men of their tribe in the levies. They will, moreover, deposit a security for their good behaviour, as is done throughout Baluchistan. (6) We will supply labour and every other kind of help to Government for building operations connected with posts, wherever required, thanas, brickmaking, &amp;c., and labourers will be paid by the British Government at the recognised rates. (7) We will return all property stolen from British territory. If any person or persons in our territory refuse to comply with the above conditions, we will arrest the same or their leaders, as the case may be, and hand them over to the British Government. (8) If Government should require wood, grass, &amp;c., accommodation, fat tailed sheep, goats, fowls, eggs, &amp;c., then we sardars will help to provide them as far as we can, and as regards payment we will hold a committee with a British officer as President to fix the correct rates.(9) The British Government shall build forts and thanas wherever they please and we shall raise no objection. (10) If we carry out the above condi tions in their entirety we shall look to the British Government to further our interests in future. (11) We will scrupulously obey such orders as may be issued from time to time by General Dyer or other frontier officers. Dated 30th April 1916. [Sardar Taj Muhammad Khan, Baiki.] [Sardar Khalil Khan, Gamshadzai.] [Mir Isa Khan, Ismail.] Thumb impression of Mir Nur Muhammad Khan. [Sardar Jiand Khan, Yar Muhammadzai.J [Mir Mirza Khan, Raiki.] Thumb impression of Mir Behroze Khan. Thumb impression of Mir Wall Muhammad, Balozai. [Sardar Juma Khan, Ismail. J [Mir Shasowar Khan.] [Mir Noroze Khan, Karad.] [Chira Khan, Balozai.] Thumb impression of Nur Muhammad, Thumb impression of Khan Muham^ Yar Muhammadzai. mad, Yar Muhammadzai. Thumb impression of [Ibrahim Khan, Raiki.] Thumb impression of Izat Khan. Nazar Khan, Raiki. [Ummaid, Raiki.] Thumb impression of [Mir Ullah Rasan.l Zulaf Kar Khan, Yar Muhammadzai. Signed in my presence this thirtieth day of April 1916 (nineteen hundred and sixteen) at a Durbar held at Kacha. Kacha; ^ R. G. H. Dyer, Brigadier-General, The 30th April 1916. j Commanding Troops, Sistan, 31 Telegram R., No. 127, dated the 2 nd (received 4th) October 1916. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Departs ment, Simla. ^ Your telegram No. 716-C. If Chenozubow is really conducting combined operations he would surely have notified us that he was counting on your force especially as warnin 0, has been given at liflis that your destination was Shiraz to organize South Persia Rifles and that you could not be looked on'as auxiliary to Baratoff. I find it moreover difficult to believe that so small a force as yours can really enter into his calculations. J So long as I am not in possession of Russian Commandant’s information, I must obviously decline to conform my judgments to it, but I personally know no pledge which can absolve Government official from communicating essential information to his own superior authorities, but if you think that it (is necessary ?) to obtain his sanction you should inform him that your move ments are controlled by Legation and that if he wishes for your co-operation fie should allow me to know circumstances confidentially. Addressed to Sykes as 108; repeated to Gough and Cox,17 32 Telegram E., No. 659, dated the 3rd (received «h) October 1916. Prom—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, 6 “sLt. tI,e GOTernment of ^ i the Foreign and Political Depart- Your telegram 444. withLTtt“ n a?iS.° arraD § em e“ts to follow Colonel Gough Addressed London Foreign Office; repeated Basrah and Gough. 33 Telegram R., No. 128, dated the 3rd (received 4th) October 1916. From-His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To-Tbe Secretaryjo the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- mand ifstilUndependent ofThenozubow’s “n^Th^ 6 f aratoff ’ s oom * your co-operationand has no needtodo so 6 “ n0t C0UUtln S Addressed Sykes; repeated to Basrah and Colonel Gough. Telegram P., No. 152, dated the 3rd (received 4th) October 1916. From—His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Kerman, To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- My telegram of September 29th, No. 139. Persian 1 sources^ aSSUI “ ed substantiall y “n-eet, being from responsible u..™T.'L^X5^£*y“d 0, An. ,, ‘'' b * r28 * h ' ,h * “w* •* I.no. Enem ^ isSaid to , bave Iost ab out 10 hilled, number of wounded not vet rSi. .i'. r aS“ 1 “' w ”-‘“ I ' d “ 1 “w. tion at To wiThZw an bearS f ° Ut V n ie , ws 1 bave Previously expressed on cion, do withdraw now part or whole of British at present in Sir (ian ?1 1 I consider be extremslv unwi™ 1 111011 ^ an ■ &gt; situation — X.WVT IJO.J.U Ud \ woulci 1 consider be extremely unwise^ Addressed Cox; repeated Tehran and Sykes. Gough. 35 Telegram R., No. 726-C., dated the 4th (received 5th) October 1916. From— Brigadier-General Sir P. M. Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. 43 Your telegrams 109 and 110 of October 3rd. Column will start for Shiraz, October 10th. Sent to Tehran; repeated Chief of the General Staff, Basrah and Colonel% « in LIT ARY. Cypher telegram to Sir C. Marlii^j. (Teheran). Foreign Office. March 23rd, 1918. 3.0 p.m. No. 161. Urgent. In view of the improbability of adequate forces reaching Harnadan in the near future (see my immediately preceding telegram) the Military Authorities would line to send to Bakhtiaristan viS Ahwaz some of the officers and non-commissioned oificers of the oiiginsl Dunsterville Mission, with a view to raising levies from the tribe and ensuring a friendly attitude on their part in the event of a forward movement being required from Shiraz to Ispahan. It is clearly undesirable that any negooiations with the Bakhtiari should be undertaken from two quarters simultaneously, and I should therefore be glad to hear as soon as possible what action you may have taken recently with the Khans in Teheran or elsewhere, and whether you consider it would be desirable to take the above-mentioned step. I Should also be glad to receive your views on the general cpiestion of Bakhtiaristan. jM.A.Tehran. In view of the dangerous recrudescence of enemy activity in North Persia which will undoubtedly include an effort again to tamper with the Bakhtiari, H.M.Government is considering the precautionary measures which might be taken, including the occupation of Isfahan by a mixed force / of S. Persian Rifles and regular Indian troops. i No decision has as yet been arrived at as to the latter measure, but in view of the fact that the Lynch road may at any moment be of the greatest importance to us as a subsidiary Line of Communication for petrol and other supplies and movement of reinforcements, H.M.Government agree that all possible preliminary measures should at once be undertaken to secure the co-operation of the Bakhtiari. H.M.Government have therefore decided to proceed at once with the scheme for raising Bakhtiari Levies which was postponed last May. For this purpose you should select as many British officers and N.C.O.s. as you think can be usefully employed and safely introduced without antagonising the Bakhtiari. I suggest that some of Dunsterville*s per sonnel at Baghdad might be suitable, as although they lack language qualifications they a re all men who have been spec ially selected for strength of cfiaaracter. The above should proceed a&amp; soon as possible to Ahwaz and you should arrange for the despatch of all necessary equipment for the levies. As regards initial strength of force I would suggest the 600 Infantry and Cavalry in proportion of 2 to 1 as proposed in enclosure to Cox ! s letter 11227 dated 28th October 1916, to Government of India. Cox is receiving instructions as to the selection of % specialI special poXiticaX officer and as regards the poXitical aspects of the question. Terms of service etc. may be settled locally on such lines as will secure maximum co-operation of Khans and esrliest possible formation of efficient force. Addressed G.O.C, Mesopotamia, repeated Dunsterville, C.-in-C., India, M.A,, Tehran.* To- The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. (Addressed Foreign Office repeated Basra) No. 172-F. Dated 15th A *'* i Becd. 16th l May 1917. Bakhtiari levies. Scheme was proposed and sanctioned in order to prevent collision between Russian troops and tribes (see my despatch No. 132 Novr. 10th) by creating a force under British officers which would co-operate with Russians to keep order on boundary. Raison d'etre of levies however seems now to have disappeared with change in 'V Russia's attitude towards the Persian question and the improbability that Russian troops would be used as was formerly possible. I believe that little or nothing has been done in way of recruiting. The organising officers and materiel supplied by Govt, of India have however just arrived. It is more than likely that leading Khans who had ostensibly readily fallen in with scheme will now oppose it. They have been very much offended that their large interestsi interests have been totally disregarded at Dlsfull end Shuster where our military authorities have practically taken over local administration and they pretend anxiety that levy scheme may prove a preliminary to similar interference with tribe. In consequence Illkhani is insist ins on resigning and the onlji possible successor who is ready to promote scheme is unsuitable in most other respects and is not approved by leading Khans. Hence though levies might be of present utility in policing road and of future advantage as paving the way for introduction of Southern Persia Rifles I am disposed to think that scheme should be dropped.Telegram P. '‘•V Prom- His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. To- The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. (Addressed London Foreign Office repeated to Basra.) / / . *i. *(■ No. 178-P. Dated the 18th Reed, the 19th May 1917. 1* on On Ihrther consideration I think it quite imprac ticable to proceed with Bakhtiari Levy scheme at present Khans here bitterly resent the attitude which we were compelled to take by loyalty to Russia with regard to retention oL Governor of Ispahan. They may have assented to scheme when it was propounded to them by woel, in order to avert possible Russian interference, but they will now unquestionably oppose it, partly out of resentment above- mentioned and partly as they see in it commencement of British interference in internal tribal affairs. No 111 Khani would honestly endeavour to carry out scheme of this kind without full approval of senior Khans whatever promises he might make to us in hope of getting office. This is in continuation of my telegram No. 172. ' -. - jI n COPY. 1 Telegram. P. Prom- The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Baghdad. lo- The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. (Repeated Basra, Tehran and London For.Office.) / No. 1751. Dated the 20th f? 1 ■ft, Need, the 21st May 1917. AS tUJ A I have only today the 19th received Minister's telegram No. 172 to Foreign Office which has been resent from Basra. I agree with him that the inauguration of levy staa scheme had better be postponed owing to new and uncertain situation created by Russian upheaval and its reaction on their position in Persia. In passing I would remark that the allusion cited in his telegram to our proceedings at Shuster and Dizful and disregard far Bakhtiari interests are inaccurate and exaggerated. There are no Military authorities there, but only political officers who have been exercising in some respect salutary influence over the administration and evolving out of chaos such measure of order and security as military interests and supply requirements of this force demand.OOPY, Telegram. P* Prom- His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. To- The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, No. 45. Dated the 31st May Reed, the 1st June 1917. My telegram 178-F. Foreign Office telegraph that they agree that Bakhtlari Levy scheme should be postponed for the present.COPY. Telegram. P. Prom- His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran. To- The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. (Addressed Cox 71.) No. 49. Dated the 19th Reed, the 20th June 1917. Prospects of opening a new trade routexlltjugii through } , Luristan and of permanent conversion of Lur brigands seem problematical in the extreme and to ray mind a very poor return for antagonizing Bakhtiaris whose influence here is underrated apparently- and for provoking complaints regarding our interference in Persian internal affairs which it will be exceedingly difficult to explain to Persian Government in present state of feeling here. This is with reference to your telegram 2155.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000224_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/653</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000224</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/653</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 469/1917 Pt 2 'Persia: Bakhtiari affairs. Bakhtiari gendarmerie'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1921</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-20T22:23:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (264 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 469 (Persia: Bakhtiari affairs) consists of two volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/652-653. The volumes are divided into two parts, with each part comprising one volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 264; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains papers (mainly correspondence and India Office minute papers) relating to the Bakhtiari [Baḵtīārī] tribe and Bakhtiari territory in Persia [Iran]. The papers largely concern the proposal to raise a force of gendarmerie, or Levy Corps, under British officers in the Bakhtiari territory, to settle potential incidents of ‘collision’ between Russian troops and Bakhtiaris. These papers include correspondence regarding the decision to postpone the Levy Corps scheme, following the Russian February Revolution of 1917, until the general political and diplomatic situation became clearer. The file also includes papers relating to the Bakhtiari offer of military co-operation with the British, in the form of the maintenance of a force of Bakhtiari sowars in Bakhtiari territory.The main correspondents include: the India Office; the Foreign Office; the War Office; the Treasury; the Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India; Brigadier-General Sir Percy Sykes, Inspector-General, South Persia Military Police; HM Minister, Tehran (Sir Charles Marling); HM Vice-Consul, Ahwaz (Captain E Noel); the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Political Officer, Basra; HM Consul, Kerman; the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad; the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (C.I.G.S.); the Commander-in-Chief (C-in-C), India; and the Chief of the General Staff, India.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>South Persia Rifles, Inspector-General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice-Consul, Ahwaz</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bakhtiari</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Isfahan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Russian Revolution (1917)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000224#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>