<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00021b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:10.147Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">oo [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] [A1 ASIATIC TURKEY AisD ARABIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [July 3.j Section 6. [30802j No. I. Memorandum by Mr. Farkes on British Policy of Non-interference in the Affairs of Nejd. ON the 8th February, 1904, the following telegram was sent to the Viceroy India Office, of India by Mr. Brodrick, Secretary of State for India, with the concurrence of J^ 17, Lord Lansdowne :— ' The previous sanction of His Majesty's Government must be obtained before any steps are taken with a view to entering into closer relations with Nejd, or to sending agents there.' Ibn Saoud, the Wahabite leader, was at the time carrying on a desultory warfare against Ibn Reshid, Amir of Nejd, and the telegram was sent in connection with a proposal to depute a British officer to visit the interior of Arabia (Riadh), as the Government of India wished to get reliable information of the progress of events in Nejd and Riadh. p xt Lord Lansdowne doubted the wisdom of negotiating with the tribes of Nejd, and Sir N. 0'Conor, Ambassador at Constantinople, who was consulted, concurred in the opinion as to the inadvisability of sending a special emissaiy to Riadh oi Nejd. On the 16th December, 1904, the India Office were informed, with reference to the state oi affairs in Nejd, that, in Lord Lansdowne's opinion, ' it should be clearly understood that the influence and interest of His Majesty's Government are to be strictly confined to the coast-line of Eastern Arabia, and that no measures are to be taken, or language used, which might appear to connect them even indirectly with the tribal'warfare now in progress in the interior.' • . . j v Upon receipt of this letter, the Indian Government were instructed by Mr. Brodrick, in a telegram despatched on the 30th December, 1904, that is Majesty's Government wish it to be clearly understood that their interest and influence are to be strictly confined to the coast-line of Eastern Arabia and that nothing is to be said or done to connect them, even in an indirect way, with the fighting going on 111 th Mn Morley, Secretary of State for India, communicated to the Foreip Office on the 10th November, 1906, a telegram, sent by him to the Government of India on the previous day relative to the affairs of Nejd, in which he referred to his predecessor s telearams of the 8th February and the 30th December, 1904, and stated that His Majesty's Government maintained their view ' that our influence and interest shoulc ^ ^EarhAn 1907 an important despatch was written by the Government of India, reviewing the situation in Arabia and discussing the question of British policy, was stated in the covering letter to the Foreign Office that Mr. Morley saw no reason to' alter the policy ' of strictly confining our interests and influence to the coast hne o Eabtern A^ 0 pi n i 011 , W as invited, and he strongly urged that it would be rnn=d unwise for His Majesty's Government to entangle themselves with Ibn baoud, or in any other way interfere m the internal affairs of Arabia. The India Oflice were informed that Sir E. Grey was disposed to concur m this view and a despatch was addressed by Mr. Morley to the Viceroy stating that after carefully considenng, in consultation with His Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, the views expressed by [2985 c—6] India Office, Feb. 4, 1904. To India Office, Feb. 6, 1904. Sir N. O'Conor, No. 129, Feb. 26, 1904. To India Office, Dec. ie, 1904. India Office, Jan. 11, 1905. India Office, Nov. 10, 1906 [37869/06]. India Office, Mar. 27, 1907 [10143/07]. Sir N. O'Conor, No. 198, Apr. 1, 1907 11067/07]. o India Office,Apr. 17, the Government of India as to the general situation in Central Arabia, Hib MajcvU &amp; 19 0 7 Government saw no reason to modify the policy laid down in the telegrams ol the t 1 !, 067 ^ 71 ' 30th December, 1904, and the 9th November, 1906, that British interests and influence Mav6 Ce ' in those regions should be strictly confined to the coast; and that they agreed with 1907 ' Sir N. O'Conor that it would be most unwise for them to entangle themselves with tne [14856/07]. Wahabi Amir, or in any other way to interfere in the internal affairs of Arabia EDWARD 1 AnKho. Foreign Office, July 3, 1913.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00021b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B200</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00021b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B200</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Memorandum by Mr Parkes on British Policy of Non-Interference in the Affairs of Nejd [Najd].’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1913</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T00:25:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>The memorandum is arranged into ten paragraphs, each of which has a subheading, written in the outer margin alongside the corresponding paragraph. The contents of the memorandum are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 7, and terminates at f 7, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and won't be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The printed memorandum, written by Edward Parkes of the Foreign Office, is headed ‘A. Asiatic Turkey and Arabia. Confidential. [July 3] Section 6.’ It summarises past correspondence (dated from February 1904 to May 1907) between Government officials on Britain’s policy of confining their influence to the coastline of eastern Arabia, and not interfering with Ibn Saoud’s [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd (Ibn Sa‘ūd)] affairs in the Arabian region of Najd. The subheadings in the outer margin, alongside each paragraph, indicate the author, number and date of the correspondence being summarised. There is a handwritten addition to the memorandum, written in red ink at the top of the first page, which reads: ‘Memorandum B 200’.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Najd</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00021b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>