<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T16:02:15.330Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IMFP--1701 S&amp;P—(M-2333)—22-5-40—800,000. DEPT. BRANCH. S. 1. Section. Heading. Pros. File No. Serial No. NOTES, 19 Nos. Subject. Notes and Orders. (0 / rr&gt;No. ti&gt;M of 1911. British Heaidenoy and Consulato-General. 1A Bushire ,/$ June 1911. TO a? d) Sir, ± have the honour to forward copies of the papers mar ginally cited in connection with a proposal of the Anglo- Telegram No.S-338, d/l7-o-1909, from} Foreign to Resident. } Persian Oil Company -do- No.848, d/ 19-0-1909, from Re- } sident to Foreign. j -do- No.S-345, d/ 19-6-10, from } to see if anything Foreign to Resident. j -do- No.642, d/ 19-6-10, from Re- } sident to Foreign. } can be made of the Letter from Oil Company to Resident } dated London, 25-5-11, &amp; enclo 5 sure. jj coal deposits in the Sultan of Muscat’s territory. No action with the Sultan can, of course, be taken until the views of Gover.iment have been ascertained, but before placing the matter before them i shall be glad to receive any comment you may wish to maice on the terms of the draft lines for the Concession suggested by Mr. Greenway. I have the honour to be, t Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram - P. From - Foreign, Simla. To - Resident, Bushire. Ro.S-338. Dated 17tli August 1909. An application has been made by Liessrs Shaw Wallace on behalf of uloyd a partner in the Firm of Llessrs i^loyd Acott &amp; Go. who recently opened their premises at Liohammerah for a copy of Oldham’s report on Oman Goal Fields. This report has hitherto been treated as Gonfidential. Please see your letter from Muscat bo.£29, dated hay 1st 1909, in view of the undertaking of the Sultan, is there any ob jection to our sending them a copy confidentially ?. Telegram - P. From - Resident, Bushiro. To - Foreign, Simla. No. 048. Dated 19th august 1909. Please see your telegram No.33o. There seems no ob jection to your sending a copy of Oldham’s report confiden tially to nloyd, and x would suggest that he may also be furnished with a copy confidentially of Von Arafft’s report. Telegram - P. From - Foreign, Simla. to - Resident, Bushire. No. S-345. Dated and received 19th June 1910. With reference to your telegram dated 19th August 1910. The&lt;&gt;■&gt; • ® The Calcutta Company of Shaw Wallaco write that a syndicate has been formed at home, mainly comprised of men intimately associated with the Burma Oil Company and the Anglo Persian Oil Company, to acquire certain concessions in Southern Persia for minerals. If the concession is secured they will require coal and they desire to see Von Kraft's and uldham's reports on the Oman coal fields, iiave you any information about this syndicate ? and in view of the Sultan of Muscat's undertaking (your letter 229 from Muscat) do you see any objection to copies of the coal reports being shown to Shaw Wallace confidentially or to their taking kkxsIxh relevant extracts from them ?. Telegram - p. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Foreign, Simla. No. 642. Dated 19th June 1910. With reference to Foreign Department No.345-S. I have no other information as regards the syndicate than that contained in the papors forwarded under Foreign Department endorsement NO.1049-F.A., dated 21st Lay last. Witn regard to the Coal reports being shown to Shaw Wallace and extracts being taken by them confidentially, ± see no objection.Anglo-Persian Oil Co (^) Winohoater Houso, Old Broad Street, ijondon, 25th Llay 1911 • Dear Colonel Cox, When we met in Mohammeran you suggested the desirability of our group acquiring a Coal Concession over the Province or Sultanate of Miuusxt Oman, and indicated that you would probably have no difficulty in securing the O 0 ncession for us on satisfactory terms. Since ray return to London i have discussed the matter with my colleagues arid as there is a prospect of our being able to utilise Coal in the Persian Gulf for other purposes than in connection with the Mining Concession we have de cided to ask you to kindly put forward an application on our behalf. In the case of the Mining Concession it was arranged that the application should be put forward in the name of Mr, Mathew Tarbett Fleming on behlaf of the Syndicate which was formed to deal with this Concession, and as the Oman Coal Concession would be dealt with by the same Syndicate the application for it could be made in the same name: and should any documents require to be signed in the Gulf in connection with the application a Power of Attorney from Mr. Fleming, either to one of the Consul, or to Strick Scott &amp; 00*8 Manager, could be sent out. But it would be preferable if there is no objection to this, that the application should be made in the name of Strick Scott oc Co., on behalf of the Syndicate. For your guidance i enclose draft of a form of Con cession, based upon the one that was prepared for the Per sian Mining Concession, which might, I think, serve for the Oman Concession. In this 1 have suggested for the Royalty, either 16^ on profits, which is the rate payable to the Per sianr\ sian Govarnment in raapeot of tha Oil Oonoesaion; or 4 d. per ton, wnioli io about the average rate of Royalty payable on Goal in India. The Government rate of Royalty on Goal in India is only 2-g L /o on value at pit^ mouth, which works out to only about 1^ per ton, but in the case of privately owned Goal lands situated in the most accessible districts the average rateis about Ans.4/~ per ton. If you can secure a lower rate say 2d. per ton - it would be a more suit able figure for a district which is at present quite un proved, and where the conditions for worKing are so un favourable as in Arabia. We should also require some Clause relieving us from the obligation to pay Royalities to the Sultan of Oman should he be dispossessed, or his claim to receive tho Royalties be successfully disputed, by the Turkish Government or any other state. Power or Euler. if you can secure the Concession for us on somewhat the above lines we will at once arrange to send out an Expedition to report upon the possibilities of working the Goal deposits remuneratively, and should the report be fa vourable take early steps to develop and work the Deposits. With kind regards. Yours sincerely, (signed) G. Greenway. To C&amp;lonel P.Z.Gox, G.S.I., C.i.E., B u s h i r e.THE CONCESSION granted by the in favour of The following has by these presents been agreed on and arranged namely:- ARTICLu; I. The grants to (hereinafter called the Conoessionaire) by these presents a special and exclusive privilege to search for obtain, develop, mine, raise, trans port from one place to another, export and sell Coal through out the for a term of 60 years as from the date of these presents ARTICLE II. This privilege shall comprise the exclusive right of constructing working and using within the limits of this Concession and up to and upon any point or points on the Coast of the Persian Gulf Railways Tramways Roadways Bridges Warehouses Wharves Piers and any other conveniences which the Concessionaire may deem desirable for economical trans port of the said coal or plant required in connection there with. it shall also comprise the exclusive right of build ing and using in such places as the Concessionaire may se lect all works which the Concessionaire may deem desirable for the purposes of tne Concession as well as all Pumping otations Electric installations Telephone lines Waterways Canals Dams Water services Reservoirs Workshops Warehouses Dwellings for Employees and any other works or conveniences which the Concessionaire may think conducive to the prompt and economical carrying out of the objects of this Con cession. ARTICLE III. grants to the Concessionaire the right to acquire any lands which he may deem necessary or desirable for any of the above purposes and hereby grants gratuitously to the Concessionaire all uncultivateduncultivated lands belonging to the Litate which the Con cessionaire may deem necessary or desirable for any of such purposes. With respect to uncultivated lands belonging to others than the State % of cultivated lands belonging to the State or others^the Concessionaire shall have the right to purchase them at the current values of the Provinces or Districts in which such lands may respectively be situate and without any proprietors being allowed to make demands of a nature to surcharge the prices ordinarily current for lands situate in their respective localities. ARTICLE IV. The course of all Railways Tramsways and other lines of transport and the situation of any warehouses Wharves Piers or other conveniences deemed necessary by the Con cessionaire shall be fixed by the Concessionaire or his Engineers. ARTICLE V. All lands granted by these presents to the Concessionaire or that may be acquired by him in the manner hereinbefore provided and also all buildin s or other property belonging to or used in connection with the operations of the Con cessionaire during the term of this Concession and also all minerals products substances articles or things of every description imported or exported by the Concessionaire under this Concession or intended to be used for any of the pur poses thereof or in connection with any of the operations of the Concessionaire thereunder shall be free of all im ports Custom house duties and other duties taxes royalties and assessments whatsoever except the Royalty payable to the as hereinafter mentioned. ARTICLE YI. The authorises the Concessionaire to form a preliminary Company to exploit this concession the object of which Company after proving the coal deposits to a sufficient extent by working shall(0 (£) be to form one or more Working Company or Companies for the wording of this Concession or any part or parts there of and to transfer this Concession or any part thereof and all or any of the rights thereunder to such preliminary Company and such preliminary Company shall have the right to re-transfer the same to any one or more of such working Companies, The name 'statute” and capital of any and each suoh Company shall be fixed by the Concessionaire. ARTICLE VII. Any preliminary Company that may be formed by the Con cessionaire to exploit this Concession shall guarantee the (4d.^&gt;er ton payment to by each Company which may upon all Coal raised &amp; sold hereafter be formed by this Concession of a royalty of (16 by each such Company, tne in- P 0r O0r i't of the net profits to be derived by each such Corn- tent ion being that in no case pany respectively from working the mines tramways or other shall such Ro yalty be payable property or rights which may be acquired by such Company more than once in respect of t* 10 intention being that in no case shall such royalty be the same coal). payable more than once in respect of the same projfits). ARTICLE VIII. The binds itself to take all and any necessary measures to facilitate and to secure the safety and the carrying o^ut of the objects of this Concession and of the lands buildings and otner property of the Concessionaire and to protect the representatives agents and servants of the Concessionaire and of any Com panies formed to acquire or work the said Concession or any part thereof. ARTICLE IX. in the event of any dispute or difference arising bet ween the parties to the present Concession in respect of its interpretation or the rights or responsibilities of either of the parties therefrom resulting such dispute or differ ences shall be submitted to the Senior British Consular Officialn n Official in the Gulf khose decision shall be final* ARTICLE X. This act of Concession made in duplicate is written in the language and translated into with the same meaning but in the event of there being any dispute as to the meaning the texu shall alone prevail.No. 3205, dated Bushire, the 24th December 1911. jp rom j. H. Bill, Esq., I.C.S., First Assistant Resident (in the absence of the Resident), ^ ^ To—The Secretary to the Government/of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to forward herewith, for the information of the Govern- , ment of India, a copy of the marginally No. 1616, dated 17th December 1911, an notec [ letter which I have received from encosures. the Political Agent, Maskat, regarding the proceedings of certain Madrasi gentlemen in the hinterland of Maskat. It would appear from paragraph 6 of the letter that a further communication may be expected and I w r ould therefore respectfully suggest that action on the pro posal made in paragraph 4 may be deferred pending receipt of the further report promised. Enclosure. No. 1616, dated the 17th December 1911. From— Majoe S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to forward herewith copies of correspondence noted in the margin with reference to the visit of three Madras surveyors to Maskat. 2. I would specially invite attention to the statement of Mr. K. Murthi, the only one of the three whom I have been able to see since their return from the interior. It is very difficult to treat the statement seriously, as it is so vague and Mr. K. Murthi knows little or nothing of the country he travelled over. His notes are lost and he is unable to submit anything more definite. He has, however, given me some samples of the metals he has found which are being despatched to you under separate cover. 1. Office notes. 2. Statement of Mr. K. Murthi. 3. Notes by Ibrahim bin Muhammad bin Jumaa. 4. Translations of vernacular correspondence — &lt;a) Letter, dated 14th November 1911. from His Hi ghness to the Political Agent. (5) Letter, dated 16th November 1911, No. 1486, from Political Agent to His Highness. (c) Letter, dated 19th November 1911, from His Highness to Political Agent. 3. Mr. K. Murthi seems to have suffered from the usual trouble which beset the explorer in Oman. He was not allowed to dig and his escort were chiefly interested in the prospects of discovering gold and silver. I gathered from him that he did not think much of the prospects of the successful working of these minerals with the exception of the corundum. 4. As His Highness has formally applied to us asking whether we wish to take over the working of these mines, the occasion might seem a favourable one for the dopatch of a geologist who would take Shaikh Ibrahim with him and go over the ground followed by these Madrasi gentlemen and submit a regular report giving sufficient detailed information to allow of a definite reply being sent to His Highness’s proposal. 5. These three Madrasi gentlemen have, I understand, under the segis of Ibrahim bin Muhammad bin Jumaa again gone prospecting this time to the Batina. As soon as they return I shall endeavour to get from them a better account of their travels and discoveries. They seem intelligent and enterprising young men and are, I believe, capable of doing much better work than would appear from the present chaotic state of my information about them and their proceedings. 6. I do not, however, think it advisable to delay any longer the issue of this report, but at the same time venture to request that it may only be con sidered an ad interim one. Sub-enclosure 1. Office Note. Three Madrasi gentlemen arrived at Maskat by the B. I. S. N. Kasara on the 25th September. 17252 They stated that they belonged to the firm of Messrs. Hills Sawyer &amp; Co , of Meadows Street, Bombay. Purther enquiries, however, elicited that they are not actually in the employ, but were at their own request, given permission to canvass for orders for motor cars, machinery, especially electrical, and similar goods which they could sell on such terms as they pleased, returning trade prices to the firm and retaining any profit they could for themselves. They proposed to travel from Maskat to Mohammerak, Basrah, Baghdad and Constantinople and thence to England. They also enquired about Kuwait, but were told their chances of doin^ any business there were small. They have no passports for travel in Turkey and indeed bear no official recommendation of any kind. They were warned against prospecting in the hills of Oman on their own account as they proposed to do at first and that the Consul could not, without consulting higher authority, support any request of theirs to His Highness the Sultan to be permitted to do so. Subsequently, however, they applied themselves to the Palace for permission and were granted an escort, as appears from other enclosures attached. They gave their names as follows : — (1) Mr. K. Murthi, a Telegu Brahman. (2) Mr. Munji Topan, Gujrati. (3) Mr. Bayanker Prativadi, a Tamil Brahman. Description : — No. 1 is a tall man and wears spectacles, blood-shot eyes and dark com plexion, wears English clothes and a khaki sola topee. No. 2 a well-built young man, wears a turban with English clothes ; face is pock-marked; fair complexion. No. 3 is slight and thin and rather short, wears a white helmet and English clothes. All three speak English well and fluently. No one of the three has any working knowledge of Arabic. They took a room in the town and proposed to stay for a fortnight. They have been now in Oman nearly three months and talk of making a long stay. They say that they have sent samples of the minerals found by them to England and expect replies from firms who are interested in mining enterprise. Sub-enclosure 2. Statement of Mr. Murthi. Mr. K. Murthi came to-day and produced various samples of the geological specimens he found in the course of his travels. He states as follows:— We went in a boat and reached Bistan. It was about hours’ sail down the coast to the East past Sidap which was about a quarter way. We halted at Bistan a day and a half. There was nothing there. He went up a mountain torrent to a hill about 7 or 8 miles away. I think our course was South and slightly West. We found nothing in that hill. I was accompanied by an Arab, Shaikh Ibrahim, who knows a smattering of Hindustani. Under his guidance we went to the villages of Qabil and Haboobiya. Our compass broke the first day out and we tried to get another from His Highness, but he could not supply us with another. We were out 23 days altogether and stayed at Qabil for 5 days owing to Mr. Munji’s illness and in another place we camped in a river bed and stayed 4 days when I got ill. Thus we did 14 days’ travelling and returned to Muttra on the 1st November. 1 do not think we ever got more than 20 miles away from Maskat. We went out from Maskat, as I have said, South-east and came back to Muttra via Darsait. My notes of the voyage we re taken from me by Shubaili. We never did more than 8 miles a day and on some days only 3 and 4. For instance our last march was only from Darsait to Muttra. A negro slave, a mason, called Sawailim and two local guides were always with us, but Shaikh Ibrahim was too old for prospecting in the hills. In our searches I suppose we covered 10 to 12 miles around our camp. He found traces of corundum, lead and manganese. I think the corundum might3 be worked at a profit. The manganese would not pay owing to cost of trans port. As for the lead superficially there is a good deal, but we were not allowed to dig, and so it is difficult to say whether sufficient exists for w orking at a profit. K. MURTHI. Dated 20t/i November 1911. Sub-enclosure 3. Note by Ibrahim bin Muhammad bin Jumaa. “ Karandam ” (corundum) is found in the village Iti, tw r o hours’ journey from Maskat by sea, right up to Hatat, both in the rocks as well as valleys. “Minjanis ” (manganese) is found (1) in Al-Hootah, three hours’ journey (inland) from Iti and also at about four places in Hatat. “ Rasas ” (lead) is found in Al-Hootah and also in Saadi, Jahloot and Saleel in various quantities at a number of places. Sub-enclosure 4. Translation of letter, dated the 24-th Dhil-Q,a’da 1329 H. = 14th November, from His Highness the Sultan of Maskat to the Political Agent, Maskat. After compliments. —According to the Treaty in the correspondence dated 9th Shaban 1308=20th March 1891, we ask your honour whether you desire the mines which the surveyors with us have discovered and it is also desired from your honour that you inform our honoured friend the Co'onel (Political Resident who was then staying at the Agency at Maskat) about that, for we expect a reply at the earliest possible date. Usual ending. Sub-enclosure 5. Translation of letter No. 1486, dated 16th November 1911, from the Political Agent and His * Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, to His Highness the Sultan of Ma-kat. After compliments.— I write to acknowledge with thanks Your Honour’s letter dated 24th Dhil-Qa’da 1329, winch I have shewn to Colonel Cox as you requested. We are of opinion that Government should no doubt like the refusal of the working of such mines until such time as Your Honour has been able to put them in possession of full information regarding the minerals and of specimens thereof winch have been discovered and we would strongly advise you to under take no serious expenditure until the specimens have been submitted to examination by recognised experts and you have received their report. If you will be good enough to send me samples and a copy of the report of the surveyors, I shall be happy to submit them to higher authority for neces sary actions. Usual ending. Sub-enclosure 6. Translation of letter, dated 28th Dhil-Qa’da 1329 (19th November 1911), from His Highness the Sultan to the Political Agent, Maskat. After compliments.—I received your esteemed letter dated 16th November 1911 in reply to our previous letter to your address and what you observe is understood. As you desire, the sample of the minerals is sent to you and Ave have directed the geologists to go to your honour so that you may take their statement in person. And as to your advice we have not, from the beginning, meant to under take any large expenditure because the expense and performance would lie on whoever undertakes these concerns according to his own exertions and good fortune. This, and w r e await a reply from you at your earliest convenience and conclude our letter with salaam. S. G. P. I.—No. 1725 F. D.—15-1-1912-44—P. M. M.[Confidential.] Sly;; ^ c y/t,.2 n. No. 90, dated Bushire, the 11th (received 23rd) January 1912. From—J. H. Bill, Esq., I.C.S., First Assistant Resident (In the absence of the Resident), To—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Henry McMahon, G.C.V.O., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. In continuation of my letter No. 3205, dated 24th December 1911, regard ing the proceedings of certain Madrasi gentlemen in the hinterland of Maskat, I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, No, 123 , dated 28 th December 1911 .- a copy of a further letter cited in the margin, which has been received from the Political Agent, Maskat, on the subject. No. 123, dated Maskat, the 28th December 1911. From— Major S.. G. Knox, I.A., C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Maskat, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, LA., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General in the Persian Gulf Bushire. In continuation of my letter No. 1616, dated 17th December 1911, on the subject of the visit of three Madras surveyors, I have the honour to report as follows : — 2. On the 27th December, hearing that these gentlemen had -returned, I asked that they should come and see me. Mr. Bayankar, the leader of the party, came in response to my summons and informed me that the party left Maskat on the 10th December and returned on the 23rd December; that they did not go to the Batina but have been staying in the environs of Sib near His Highness, and for the most part spending their time shooting in the neighbour hood. They did, however, reach Nakhal and received from an Arab Munshi, called Zohar, and from another old Arab who had also been a Mullah in His Highness’ employ and is, so Mr. Bayankar thinks, called Khalfan, application for assistance in digging wells. They discovered no new minerals, much less the gold and silver, regarding which, Mr. Bayankar states, His Highness was keenly interested, but they confirmed their previous impressions as to the mineral deposits previously reported. The Arabs, on hearing of Mr. Bayankar’s lead discoveries, at once collected samples of the metallic ore he had pointed out and set about trying to smelt the ore, but, as they were unsuccessful in their operations, they came to the conclusion that there was certainly something shining in the rock but that it was not lead and would be of no use for the manufacture of bullets. Mr. Bayankar states that, while he has been prospecting, His Highness has been paying the expenses of himself and his party and estimates that his various trips may have cost His Highness about Us. 1,000 ; the chief items of expenditure have been donkey and coolie hire. Mr. Bayankar declares that he has been very well treated but his companions again suffered from illness. 3. On this occasion, Mr. Bayankar was exceedingly communicative and gave me the following details of his career which will, I trust, enable higher authority to trace the individual with precision and to form an idea of the amount of reliance that can be placed on his statements. I should like to say that he impressed me favourably. Mr. Bayankar is a man of 33 years of age. He was educated at the Coimbatore College which he left when he was about 17 years old. He has been in the export and import business at Madras since 1900; and gives as his reference in Madras Mr. P. Tirumealeachari, B.A., B.L., Advocate of the High Court of Madras. In 1905, he visited Paris for about a fortnight on mining- business with a Prenchman who paid his expenses. He stayed in Europe altogether about a month and visited no towns of importance except Paris and2 Marseilles. He has never been to England. Mr. Bayankar told me that he had recently written to H. Lnbeck, Eort, Bombay, whose head office is in London with branches at Antwerp, Paris, Hamburg and Bremen. He has acquainted him with his discoveries and had forwarded samples which however, so Mr. Lubeck informs him, have not reached. He has not received any satisfactory reply from this gentleman and proposes to go and see him, on arrival at Bombay. Mr. Bayankar has had business relations with the following British firms among others: Bidge-Beedle &amp; Co., Glasgow; J. Everett &amp; Co., Liverpool; Antwerp Trading Co.; Anglo-Mysore Manganese Trading Co. With regard to the last named, he informed me that he discovered two new manganese mines in the Mysore State, which he handed over to the Company! This Company, he states, is managed by a Miss Dawson, who paid him 5 per cent. Royalty on the product of the mines, sometimes in kind and sometimes in cash, at the option of the Company. Mr. Bayankar tells me that he has had some nine to ten years’ experience in corundum and has seen all the Indian corundum workings. He estimates that about five thousand tons has passed through his hands into the world’s market at prices varying from Rs. 400 to Rs. 3,000, per ton during the last eight to nine years. 4. I was also able to arrive at some idea of what Mr. Bayankar’s views and wishes are as regards his own share and profit in the venture under report. He states that, so far, no written communications have passed between himself and His Highness on this subject and I have advised him strongly not to write for the present and that it would be better for any written communications to pass through this Consulate. He would be prepared to start a British Indian Firm with his own capital for the collection and sale of corundum and he believes that he is in a better position, owing to his knowledge of thjp trade, to supply the corundum market than other competitors. If it was decided to grant the concession to another Company, he considers that he should be rewarded for his enterprise and skill in the discovery of the metal here with a mining Royalty of 5 per cent, in either kind or sale values. 5. Mr. Bayankar thinks that the prospects in corundum are most rosy. He calculates that the ore could be supplied f. o. b. at Maskat at an outside cost of dollars twenty to thirty per ton, packed and ready for transport. He considers that corundum of this quality should fetch in the market Rs. 150 to Rs. 200 per ton at very low computation and that there are enough surface workings to supply twenty-five thousand tons. As regards manganese, this would be a very speculative venture. It lies a good way from the coast and carriage alone to the coast would cost dollars 25 per ton. He is not in a position to say much about lead, until he is allowed to dig, though he thinks it probable that tin also might be discovered. He has seen indications of soil that is likely to bear garnets but has so far failed to discover any garnets. I understand from him that this is another branch of mining in which he has been specially interested and in which he has done business. 6 In conclusion, I add as items of information that may possibly prove intersting that Mr. Bayankar is staying with his companions for the present in a house opposite the French Consul. The house belongs to the well known arms trader Ali Khan whom, however, Mr. Bayankar tells me, he has never seen. He obtained the Ley from Moolla Ibrahim of His Highness* household and does not know yet what rent he is expected to pay for it, if any. He himself and Mr. K. Murtha are leaving for Bombay in about three weeks’ time with a view to supplying boring machines for the wells at Nakhal of which mention has already been made in this report. Mr. K. Murtha will not return probably. Indications were not wanting that Mr. K. Murtha had not altogether given satisfaction. During their absence, Mr. Manji Topan, the third member of the party, will remain at Maskat. ». U, Jk-.i.— F.D.—24-1-12 44.Brioish Residency ^..nd Consulate-General Bush ire, March 1912. I enclose a copy of a. demi-official letter received from Clarke with reference to Foreign Department letter Ko. 407-B.A., of 19th February. I see no reason why you should not inform the Sultan verbally the result of Mr Hayden’s examination of the specimens. &lt; /-m To Political Agent &amp; H.M’s ConsulCopy ox a deirii-official letter dated Calcutta., tile l^tli feby. 1012, from H.-i.S. Clo.rlre, .Csqaire, C.I.O., Dy. Secy, to the (iovt. of India, Foreign Dept. , to Lt-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, h. C. I.E. ,C. S. I. , Political Resident in the Persia.n Gulf. T r e are sending you an official letter today regard in ^ tile visit of some Madrasee gentlemen to Muscat in quest of minerals. The official letter simply says that the specimens of the minerohs which Mnox sent up do not show anything part icularly encouraging, o.nd that the Government of Indio., there fore, o.re not disposed to send a ^eolo^ist o.t present for in vestigation. I write demi-officially in continuation to in form. you that hayden, who examined the specimens, soys they include manganese ore, leo,d ore and quartz schist; he can find no corundum amony; the specimens: the quartz schist, however, has a superficial resemblance to certain varieties of corundum o.nd may nave been mistaken for that mineral. he finds it im possible to say whether the deposits, from which the manganese and lead ore came are of any value, as there is no evidence as to the quantity available. The former however, is mixed with quartz and the galena only appears to occur in thin bands, so that there is nothing very promising about either. I thought you mi^ht like to know this./ of 191 2 . British Residency and Consulate General Bus hire, the /o M'-'-rcli 1912 ■ A copy of the accompanying leuuer is forwarded, with compli ments, to the Political A^ent &amp; IBM’s Consul, Muscat, for in formation and favour of communication of purport to His Highness the Saltan, in continuation of this office endorsement No•3205, dated 24th December 1911. ^ cider, I.C.S., First Assistant Resident. From the Dy. Secretary to the Govt, of India, Foreign Dept, to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Ko. 407-E.A.,dated Feby. 19th/(received 1st March) 1912. S 2300— 1,0001 c N.? \ d^ted Calcutta tiie Copy or a letter Ko. 407-U.A., 1^12, rroir. tiie Oep.i.ty Secretary to the Government tne Foreign Department, to the Political resident in the Per sian Gair. I am directed to aclmowled^e tlie receipt oP your First Assis- ant's letters Kos. 3205 ore ° 0 , dated the 24th December 1011 and 14th January 1912 / respectively, re yarding the visit oP certain Madrasee gentlemen to Muscat in quest oP minerals. 2. Pita rePerence to paragraph 4 oP Major Mnox’s letter Ko. 131'3, dated the 17th December 1011, I am to state that the ex amination oP the specimens oP hue minerals does not show any thing particularly encouraging, and, therePore, the Government oP India are not disposed, at present, to send a ^eolo^ist Por the proposed investigation.British HesidenGy and Consulat 0 ~General. .wo. of 1912 Buahire, ~6 Maroh 1912 To The Bolitical Agent, Muscat I have the honour to refer to your letter ±* 0 . 52 , dated 15th March 1912, on the subject of the lease of mineral depo sits . Please inform the Bultan verbally that on his specifying 2 to you the names of the places at which the particular deposits exist, and the name of the mineral concerned in each case, you will address him the letter he requires (in regard to those de posits of which the samples were sent to India) in reply to his letter of 28th Zilqadsh 1328 H. = 19th November 1911. 3. iou might at the same time tell His highness, that 1 hope he will offer the concessions to Mnglish firms if any wish to tahe them up, and mention especially the powerful group repre sented by Messrs Strict Bcott &amp; '-'O., of Moh amine rah, who have al ready expressed a wish through me to discuss with ^is Highness the terras on which he would give them a concession for handling the coal deposits near Rufseh. 4. He informed mo in November, when 1 mentioned the matter to him, that affairs were too unsettled in that neighbourhood to allow of his entertaining any proposals then but that he would return to the natter later, ^ou might tell His ^ighness that if he fe prepared to discuss the question now, 1 would advise Messrs Strick Scott to send a representative down to see him. I have the honour to be. Sir, four most obedient servant. Lie ut ~C olon e1 Political Resident in the p 0rQia n Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 3665 , dated Bushire, 2 nd (received 12 th) December 1913 . From— Lieutenant Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C S.I., Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Delhi. I have the honour to lay before the Government of India the following observations on the subject of the truculence experienced from ^angs of native passengers travelling at certain seasons on board the British India Steam Navi gation Company’s and other British steamers in the Persian Gulf. 2. On several occasions during the last few years applications for assistance have been made by the masters of passenger steamers to this Residency and the Political Agencies in Gulf Ports in connection with the truculent attitude assumed by their passengers. Such instances have become more frequent and serious of late and have formed the subject of official representations by the local Agents of the British India Steam Navigation Company. 3. I have had the advantage of From the Political Agent, Kuwait to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 3^9 i dated 23 rd September 1913 . Prom His Majesty’s Consul, Basrah, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, \o 31 , dated 20 th September 1913 (in original). discussing the question with His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief and the Senior Naval Officer and in answer to enquiries addressed to the Political Agent at Kuwait and His Majesty’s Consul at Basrah, I have received the marginally quoted communications on the subject 4 I agree generally with Captain Shakespear’s estimate of the causes which give rise to the truculent attitude complained of, but local remedies are unfortun ately not available at less favoured ports, where the local authorities are more supine and less easily accessible It may be hoped that in future the Riverain Commission will be in a position to deal effectively with cases of the kind at Basrah, but, as regards Bahrain and Bushire, which are the other ports principally affected, neither His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief nor I consider that any substantial improvement can be effected until wireless telegraphic installations have been erected on shore. 5. The present difficulty is that owing to the primitive harbour facilities existing in the Gulf Ports and the time it takes for a vessel to communicate with the shore at Bushire, Kuwait or Bahrain, it is not possible without previous warning for the Authorities of the Port to initiate any effective steps from the shore after a vessel has arrived, without undue delay to her and in cases of the kind in point, it is not possible at present to receive any warning in advance to the effect that passengers are giving trouble and assistance is required. This disability, however, will cease to operate as soon as the wireless stations at the ports above mentioned are established, for as the Government of India is doubt less aware almost all the British India Steam Navigation Company’s subsidiary mail steamers (which deal with the bulk of native passenger traffic) are now provided with Radio-telegraphic installations, and the new fast mail steamers which are expected to appear in the Gulf in the course of next year, will be similarly equipped. 6. This being so, it is matter of urgency that we should complete our installations as soon as possible, in order to enable British Shipping Companies to reap the benefits of their enterprise in installing the apparatus on their steamers, which in the case of British India Steam Navigation Company were built especially for the Persian Gulf service. 7. I would add incidentally in conclusion that the only occasion on which the vast bulk of the Arab and Persian diving fraternities inhabiting the shores of the Gulf come into contact with the Englishmen and British authority is during their seasonal voyages on the mail steamers and it is politically damaging to our good name that we should appear to this element unable to lend effective support to the Commanders and officers of British ships when any question arises between them and their unruly burden.2 No. 389 , dated 23 rd September 1913 . From— Captain W. H. I. Shakespear, I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. With reference to your No. 2809, dated the 16th September 1913, regarding the truculent behaviour of Arab passengers on board British ships, I have the honour to submit the following observations. 2 . In the copies of correspondence enclosed with your letter it would appear that the offending Arab passengers have generally been either Basris or Bahrainis, though I observe that the Political Agent, Bahrain, does include Kuwaitis in his report dated the 10th August 1913. 3. My own experience in Kuwait has been that the most troublesome passengers on board ships are usually Basrah or Bahraini Arabs; no case has hitherto come to my knowledge of a complaint against Kuwaitis. I would add that though hundreds of Arabs from other ports come for service as divers with Kuwait Nakhudas, very few Kuwaitis go elsewhere for service. 4 . It will be seen therefore that to approach Shaikh Sir Mubarak-as-Subah in the matter will be giving him the opportunity of the obvious retort indicated above. In point of fact I have no doubt that offending Kuwait passengers would oe dealt with in the most summary fashion by Shaikh Mubarak if a complaint of actual misbehaviour by Kuwaitis should be put forward by this Agency. 5. On an occasion in May 1912 a somewhat similar incident occurred when 300 Basris^proceeded to disembark in Kuwait from the S. S. “ Palitana ” without paying their fares and after threatening the Chief Officer. I happened to reach the ship before they had all left and had no difficulty in securing the Shaikh’s Customs Master s assistance in detaining the whole number at the Customs until they had paid up. A second instance was a quarrel between some Bahrainis and the ship’s Persian coolies, reported in my letter No. 185, dated 10th May 1913. 6 My own opinion, which I express with some diffidence, is that the trucu lent behaviour complained of is largely induced by the want of firmness shown by a few ships’ officers and the casual manner in which local Agents book any number of passengers regardless of possible or probable accommodation. The incident on board the S. S. Bankura referred to in the correspondence forwarded with your letter occurred in Bushire harbour and I cannot understand why in such cases the vessel does not remain in port with a signal for help flying until the necessary assistance from the shore can arrive, even though the delay may necessitate missing a mail connection. The passengers may use threats but are hardly likely to proceed much beyond them. When masters yield to these threats they invite a repetition of the incident on the next occasion that some of the same passengers travel by a steamer. In Kuwait, where I have no guard available, I should have no hesitation in requesting the master of a vessel to remain at anchor until I could obtain a guard from the Shaikh to deal with any number of truculent passengers he might have No. 31 , dated the 2 oth September 1913 . From—C n OTAW F. E. CROW, British Consul, Basrah, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 2811 of the 16th instant with enclosures. I see no objection from a capitulatory point of view to the commanders of British India steamers providing themselves with a Turkish guard while in lurkish waters for the protection of their vessels when circumstances require it, provided they do so through the medium and with the concurrence of this Consu late. Due notice should be given me beforehand in order to enable me to m A \ A# 3 consider the circumstances and make the necessary application to the Vail of Basrah, who resides at some three miles distance from the Consulate. I have drawn the attention of the acting Vali to the occurrences mentioned in your letter and His Excellency has given me a verbal assurance that on receipt of my official application he will supply a guard of police and gendarmes for the purpose. His Excellency also states that he will have arrested and punished any Basrah bound Arabs who misbehave themselves en route on receiving due notice from me of what is required. The important point is that official notice of the mischief apprehended should be given to the Consulate by the commander or the steamer’s agent in time to enable me to make adequate arrangements to meet it. C 127 FD— 44 — 27 - 12 . 13 —GCBP SimlaCONFIDENTIAL, £ / r f IQ. UdlS i.AUS.1813 // : &amp;&gt; / f 6J, No. 2210 , dated Bushire, the 17 th (received 28 th) July 1913 . . ^ p rom Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, j 0 jh e Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. With reference to Foreign Department telegram No I 535 ' E A., dated 10th July, and Sir Walter Townley’s telegram No. 171, dated 25th April 1913 (copy enclosed) I have the honour to submit, for the information of the Government of ' India, a copv of the marginally cited No. 78 - 2209 , dated 17 th July 1913 - despatch, with enclosures, w'hich I have addressed to His Majesty’s Minister regarding the intimation to Foreign Consuls of the present position in the Gulf in the matter of aids to navigation maintained by Great Britain. Telegram P. No. 171 , dated and received 25 th April 1913 . From—His Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. At the end of January it was suggested to the Foreign Office by the India Office that Foreign Consuls should be notified at once about the new gas buoys at Bandar Abbas and Bushire and the dioptric lanterns at Bushire. It was then suggested by me that, until some arrangement had been made with the Persian Government over the general question, we should defer the announcement. ' I do not see any objection now to the course which was proposed, and the Foreign Office direct me to issue instructions to you that the notification is to be made. Precis. No. 78 — 2209 , dated Bushire, the 17 th July 1913 From Lieutenant Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E , C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, j 0 His Excellency Sir Walter B. Townley, K.C.M.G., His Britannic Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, Tehran. I have the honour to refer to Your Excellency’s telegram No. 171, dated 2&lt;th April 1913, authorising an intimation to Foreign Consuls in connection with the improvement of British aids to Navigation in the Persian Gulf.^ Your Excellency will remember that the question of addressing them such an intimation was submitted by me tor iro?to^.Gen«'rB.rtte?\o orders on 13th December _19! 2.* Previous Minister. to the receipt by me ot any reply, my German colleague, as reported in my telegram No. 113—4 18 . dated dth rda , rc J 1 ’ had asked privately to be supplied with the details of recent items and duly received them ; that being the case, and shipping Companies having been duly informed on the installation of each item, it seemed better to delay the official communication to my colleagues until all the items in process of instalment a e time were complete. This stage was arrived at with the exhibition of the Tanb Light on the isth July and I have now issued the circular letter and enclosure, of which I attach a copy, for Your Excellency's information. I avail myself of the opportunity to inform you that the Russian Consu late-General has altogether ceased to hoist its masthead lights, so that t at correspondence may be considered to have closed.2 I am sending a copy of this communication with its enclosures, to the Government of India. Copy of a Circular letter No, 2180-2184, dated 15th July tg 13, from the Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Consul at Bushire. J’ai Thonneur de porter h. votre connaissance que les aides a la navigation (phares, bouees eclairees, et non-eclairees) maintenues par le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste Britannique a Bouchir, a Bender Abbas, k Djask, et aux lies de Bahrein et de Tanb, on ete recemment modifiees et ameliorees, et qu’elles sont actuellement comme indiquees dans la liste ci-jointe. II vous sera peut^tre utile d’tdre en possession de ces renseignements. Veuillez agreer Monsieur le Consul les assurances de ma consideration la plus distinguee. Consul-General de Sa Majeste Britannique. (Sd.) P. Z. COX, Lieut.-Colonel. PERSIAN COAST. Bushire. (1) Lights on the British Consulate-General Flagstaff. Description .—One white and one red lantern, vertical. Order. —6th Order Dioptric. Visible in fair weather .—White light 13 miles. Red light 1miles. arc of illumination ; all round from seaward. Height in feet of centre of each lantern above high water.—*]'! feet white* 54 feet red. Remarks.—-'', op light is hoisted to heel of topmast; the lower (red) light a htte below cross trees. (2) Buoys. Outer anchorage, in 23 feet of water at a distance of 4-2 miles bearing b. S4 W. (T) from Residency Flagstaff. Gas buoy showing an occulting white light ten seconds ; light seven seconds, dark three seconds, 300 candles. Inner anchorage. In 17 feet of water at a distance of 2*5 miles bearing N* 53.W (T) from Residency Flagstaff. Gas buoy showing an occulting red light ten seconds; light seven seconds, dark three seconds, 300 candles. (3) Beacon. Position .—On Ras-al-Marg 15 feet above high water mark. Description. An iron tube with a wooden mast six feet long fitted at the upper end and carrying a spherical shape. Bandar Abbas. Buoy. Position.--Two cables North by West from the position of the old buoy, which has been removed, in 22| feet of water at low water of ordinary spring tides. Description of -Second class conical—diameter 10 feet—length too inches—with cylindrical cage 3 feet in diameter mounted on a staff attached to the top of the buoy.3 si; » Jask. Buoy. Approximately in latitude 29 deg. 39! min. Northflongitude 57 deg. 44 min, East^with the following true bearings : Jask Point South 45 deg. East; conspicuous date clump South 77 deg East. Conspicuous date grove North 84 deg. East; round tree North 43 deg. East. Description of -Second class conical—diameter 10 feet—length i°.6 inches—with cylindrical cage 3 feet in diameter mounted on a stan attached to the top of the buoy. ARAB COAST. Bahrain. The following buoys are now in the positions given below (1) Outer gas buoy. Position. —N. 32! E. (Mag.) 5-9 miles from Khasaifa Island. Character of Light. —Flashing. White. Once every 10 seconds. Visibility.—8 miles. Candle Power 300. (2) Jadum Shoal Gas Buoy. Position. N. 16 W. (Mag) 5 miles from Saga Island. Character 0//^.—Flashing Red. Light 7 seconds. Eclipse 15 seconds. Visibility.—8 miles. Candle Power 120. (3) Khasaifa Shoal Buoy. —Black conical Buoy with Staff and cage. Position. N. 16 W. 3*8 miles from Saga Island. (4) Inner Harbour. —Red Conical Buoy. Position. — N. 36 W. 2*1 miles from Ras Zarwaw Beacon. ( 5 ) red conical buoy formerly located off Jadum Shoal has Variation. i° E. Tanb Island, Lighthouse.—{From 15th July 1913). Description. Braced iron tower, painted white ; situated on Island; tower seventy one feet high base to vane apparatus third order. summit of ; dioptric ig . Light white flashing every five seconds; duration of flasl decimal three five seconds ; duration of eclipse four decimal sh ve seconds; intensity of light one hundred thousand candles* focal plane two hundred twenty nine feet above high water • rang* of visibility 22 miles. ’ &amp; C 43 FD— 44 — 2 S- 13 —QCBP SimlaH /16. ^ ^ _ lS] mftr (3 7 ^ D.O. jno . 388-t&gt; of 1932. j.he Kesidency, i^ushire, the 10th oune 1932. I enclobe a copy of a letter ho. i-'.Z.2855/32 f v / 0 **' £ j\ T ^ • /-s ?l I 1 dated the 17th May 1932, from Walton, with its enclosures, regarding a project for investigating mineral deposits in the neighbourhood of Dhofar. ihere is no record here of any previous attempt at mineral exploration in that region: in 1907 some samples of coal from Dhofar were forwarded to the Government of India but were found to be of no commercial value — vide 1'oreign and Political Department letter no. 4874-K.B., dated the 20th December 1907, to the political Agent, Muscat. Walton mentions that Mr. Lacy’s objective appears to be the Qara mountains. This may be the region behind Kharifot, which is occupied by the q,ara tribe. As you are aware. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat claims sovereignty over this tribe (vide this office letter no. dated 24th 'February 1930;, but £&amp;&amp;&amp;' the question has not ^een determined. Will you please let me &amp;ave your views after con sulting His Highness V 'f ' z 00 *- £ jr\ T ^ • /-s f; I 1 Lieut.-Colonel T.C.W. .Fowle , C.H.-K., Political Agent, Kus c at .P.Z. 285b/32. IIJDIA O^PIGK, Wliitehall, S. v. 1. 17th May 1932. My dear Piscoe, l enclose a copy of corresi.&gt;ondence between the India Office, the Colonial Office and a Mr. Lacy, who is interested in the possibility of discovering mineral deposits in Southern Arabia in the neighbourhood of uhufar and ubar* When he called at this Office, Mr. Lacy wa-s rather vague as to his intentions, but we understand that at any rate he does not propose to make a moVe till next year. You will see that we have informed him that Lhufar is part of the territories of Muscat and that permission would in any case have to be ontained from the Muscat Government befor’e prospecting in that area, nis objective appears to be the c^ara Mountains which lie behind jjhufar and Sohth of the supposed site of ubare 3. Meanwhile we would be grateful if you womid con sider the matter and let us have your views in due course, through the Government of India, on the possibilities of a project such as Mr. Lacy has in mind. 4 -* 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe. Yours sincerely, 5D/ J.C, Walton. The Hon f be It 0 -Col. H.V. Biscoe, The 'Residency,IXJIUA Oi^lCB, 3 . W. 1 P.Z. 2855/32. V/H1 TKi I ALL, l^th May 1932. Confidential. Sir, With reference to your letter of 26th April to the Colonial Office, which has been transferred to this Departnent, regarding the possible presence of mineral deposits in Southern Arabia in the neighbourhood of phufar and Ubar, 1 am directed by the Secretary of State for India to state that the portion of the South Arabian Coast (Phufar) in which you are interested forms x&gt;art of the territories of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. If therefore it were desired to obtain permission to prospect in this area with a view to a possible mining concession, it would in any case be necessary to approach the Muscat Government through the local British authorities. Meanwhile the Government of India and the^oli-c ical Hesident in the Persian Gulf are being consulted in regard to the whole natter, and upon receipt of their views a further communication willbe addressed to you. 1 am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, SP/ j. C. Walton F.B. Lacy, Esq. , 1, Oak Hill Park, Frognall, H.W. 3.P.Z. 2655/32. 98002/32. Colonial Office, Downing Street, 9th May 1932, Fr. Mi'. Lacy 26th April. To do. 9th May. My dear Clauson, I encloee herey/ith copy of the letter from Mr. F.B.Iacy on the subject of Dhufar and Hbar about which James spoke to you on the telephone. I understand that your Department will reply to the question in the last paragraph of the letter regarding the necessity for confirmation by the Inaia Office of any agreements with the local Shaikhs. I also enclose a copy of the letter which has been sent tociay to Mr. lacy telling him what we have done- A copy of this correspondence is being sent to Warner for the information of the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely. K. W.Blaxter. M.J-Clauson, Esq.■■■I 1, OAK HILL PARK, PROffiNAI, K.W.3, 26th April 1932. To H.M Secretary of State for the Colonies. In view of the discoveries by Mr. H. St.John Philby and Mi*. Bertram Thomas the value of Dhofar and Ubar in Southern Arabia become not only of historical importance but with the possibility that the gold mAnes of Ophir were in the Quara mountains. On enquiry at the India Office regarding a map of the district I was informed that one was in course of preparation. May I point out that if this map includes Dnufar ano Uoar as under British Protection it will be a definite proof against any claims that may arise in the future. I have made enquiries at the High Commissioner for India’s office. The India Office and the Crown Agents for the Colonies. There does not appear to be any record in either of these departments as to the boundary of the British sphere of influence extending from Aden eastwards. The 'Times' map however gives a rough indication of the boundary. The Kuria Muria Islands (Whitaker’s Almanack) is in British Possession and lies a few miles from the South of the Arabian Coast, the particular district which is the object of this letter. A question I wish to ask is in the event of agreements being made with the local Shaixhs at Bnular and Ubar will it be necessary for these to be fonfirmed by either the India Office or the Crown Agents for the Colonies. Yours, etc. (Sd.) F.B.Lacy98002/32 Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. 9th May 1932. Sir, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Phillip Cunliffe -Lister to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 26th of April regarding the possible presence of mineral deposits in Southern Arabia in the neighbour- -hood of Dhufar and Ubar. 2. In reply I am to inform you that the question raised in the last paragraph of your letter is not one which concerns the Crown Agents for the Colonies. The question is one for the consideration of the India Office; a copy of your letter is therefore being sent to that Department from which you will receive a communication in due course. I am, &amp;c., 3d/- K.Vv.BLAXEHR. F.B.lAcy, Esq., 1 , Oakhill Park, Frognal, N.W.3.no.K/ 'g of 1932. Political Afency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate,Muscat. Recess Office. No.l70 # Victoria Road, Camp, Karachi, 25th June 1932. To * His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Hiiihness, I hare the honour to inform Your Highness that a certain Mr. Lacy - an Englishman - has been making enquiries on the possibility of prospecting for minerals in the Qara mountain in the Bhofar area, and that the Hon'ble the Political Resident has asked me to approach you on the subject. 2. I presume that Your Highness has no objection in principle to such prospecting being carried out, as if minerals were found in paying quantities the Muscat State would of course benefit under whatever arrangements it chose to make with Mr. Lacy. But there would, I imagine, be practical difficulties in the carrying out of such scheme. I have never visited Bhofar, but I have read Mr. Thomas’s account of his travels there, and from what Xxgx he wrote I gather that the tribesmen inhabiting the Qara mountains are very primitive, and would be very suspicious of any stranger carrying on prospecting or mining work in their country? I presume also that Your Highness’s Wali at Bhofar has little authority over these people who live some distance in the interior? The point to be considered therefore is whether , if Your Highness approved of Mr Lacy’s scheme, the Qara tribes could be persuaded to allow Mr. La-cy to begin his prospects, and to carry it out in reasonable safety. They might perhaps agree if Mr. Lacy were prepared to purchase their good»will? Your Highness has recently yisited Bhofar, and so has had personal. 5 ?)' oase experience on what to j&amp;HHat/your views, which I would be glad to have* 3. Would Your Highness let me know the names of the tribes who live in the Qara mountain? Are they called qara? Your Highness’s sincere friend. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M* Lt-Colonel, &amp; Consul, Muscat*D. 0 .N 9 .K/ 32 . &amp; ' The Political Agency,Muscat. Recess Office. 170, Victoria Road, Camp. Karachi, 7th July 1932. f ot '—• Dear Sir Hugh \ In connection with your D.0.HO.388-S of 10th June 1932 on the subject of Mr. Lacy’s scheme for inrestigating mineral deposits in the Dhofar district, about which I am consulting the Sultan, I came accross your letter No.76-S of 24th February 1930, to the OoYernment of India, sent to Muscat under your office endorsement of 24th February 1930. Did OoTernment ever come to any decision on the ma^cter? There appear^fto be nothing further on the Muscat file with regard to their reply. It would certainly appear logical that, as you suggested, the Political and State boundaries should coincide at Has Dharbat Ali. Yours Sincerely. To The Hon’ble Sir Hugh Biscoe, K.B.D., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Translation of a letter dated 7th Rahi al aw^al £351 (11th July 1932) from His Highness Saiyid Said hin Taimur, sultan of jus cat uu uiiian, to Lt-Colonel T# juowle, G, B.3* , Political Agent &amp; H.B.I rf s Consul, fuscat. After Compliments* In the most auspicious of hours I received in Muscat your letter iTo.K/S dated 25th June 1932 which written in Karachi, on the subject of the Englishman Mr. Lacy, about whom the Hon‘ble the Political Resident ashed you to inform me that he was enquiring as to the possibility of prospecting for mineral products in the mountains of Qara in our district Dhofar. a have already discussed the matter with you verbally after my arrival at Karachi. I am in favour of such investigations being carried out, because if mines are discovered in that part of my country, ^e ' r ould be much S' A-'**- city-t-i. benefited. But^that circumstances do not permit that such investigations be carried out at the present moment. God willing, 1 will let you know whenever 1 see that the time is suitable for carrying out such a scheme. Please inform the Hon*ble the Political Resident that at present the time is not suitable to permit Mr. Lacy to take any action in the matter.wmmmm a iv X).O.Ho,K/^o The Political Agency^Muecat, Recess Office, 170, Victoria Road, Camp, Karachi, 14th July 1932. Dear Sir Hugh ,/jp Please refer to your D.0.KO.388-S of 10th June 1932. I enclose herewith translation of a letter dated 11th July 1&gt;32 from His Highness which explain* itself. In addition to /h&amp;t he Bays in his letter, His Highness informed me verbally that during his visit to Dhodar in last April tnere ms some trouble amongst the tribes of the Qara area, which he managed to adjust successfully. He is afraid, howe/ex, that if prospecting for minerals were carried out now in the Qiara mountains, it might have a disturbing eifect on the tribes concerned. I agree with His Highness that tne scheme had better be postponed for the present. Hr. Lacy does not appear to be in any great hurry to begin hie operations, vide para 1 of Walton’s letter to you of 1 ^ tu May 1932, so this delay should not hamper him unduly. Yours Sincerely. To The Hon'ble Sir Hugh Biscoe, K.B.E., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire.'H -3 CONFIDENTIAL. No. 669-3 of 1932. The Secretary to the HoiTble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to the Political Agent, Muscat and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. ) Dated 1.932. Muscat letter tto. K/40 of Reference to previous correspondence : 14th July 1932* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. P.2. 4832/32 dated 22nd August 1932, from India Office to Mr. P.B.Lacy. 2. Express letter No. P.Z.5351/32 dated 9th September 1932 from • India Office to Eovemment of India, with enclosures. Mineral deposits in Southern Arabia.India Office, Whitehall, London, • Z. 4332/32 22nd August 1932. Sir, In continuation of previous correspondence on the subject of your enquiries about mineral deposits in Southern Arabia, I am directed by the Secretary of State to say that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf now reports that ^is highness the Sultan of Luscat has informed him that local conditions in his view make the present time unsuitable for carrying out prospecting or similar investigation^, ihe Secretary of State would therefore suggest that, in the the0e circumstances, it would be desirable to postpone any project of this nature for the present. I am, Sir. Your obedient servant, sd/- J.G.tfaltonP.Z.5351/32 India Office* Political department Secretary of State for 1 ndia. Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political department. 9tti September 1932. Please refer to Fowle's letter L.O.No.531-^ of 30th July and Metcalfe's letter D.Q.No.F.162-N/32 of 15th August on the subject of Mr.Lacy's enquiries regarding mineral deposits in Southern Arabia. Copy of a letter addressed to Lacy on 22nd August was sent by mail of 25th August. Copy is now enclosed of a further letter from Mr.Lacy, in which he makes suggestions for a mining conces- -sion, together with a copy of the interim reply returned thereto. Icu may think it worth while to bring his sug gestions to the notice of ftis Highness in case it might be possible to consider this or some similar project at a future date, though it may be thought more convenient * that a concession should not in any case be negotiated until after such preliminary prospecting as might be licensed by the Sultan in due course. 2. tilth regard to the area of the concession centem- -plated by Mr. Lacy, I have been unable to identify rt Aas el Wadd M . lf w £as el Hadd w is meant this may be thought to give an undesirably large area for a concession. You will observe that the question of the boundry of Muscat in the Kharifoot area, which still remains un settled, would also perhaps be involved. (Eeference correspondence ending with letter No.C/322 of 11th June 1932 from Chief Commissioner, Aden to Governmentnof India). 3 ...3. A copy of this express letter is 'being sent to the Political resident in the Persian Grulf. The issue of the' above has 'been duly authorised, sd/- J.C.Walton.1, Oak Hill Park, Frognal, N.W.3. 2nd SeptemlDer 1932, J.G.Walton, .Esq.., India Office, Whitehall, 3.W.1 Dear Sir, I have to thank you for your letter of the 22nd kiofrom't and note that His Highness the Sultan of Muscat considers that the present time is inopportune tfor pros- -pecting in Southern Arabia. I must of course follow the suggestion of the Secretary of State and postpone the for- -mation of the expedition for the present, icu will appreciate that it will he advisable before commencing operations that a concession should be applied for. 1 suggest that this concession should be negotiatied on the following basis. To cover the district between Has el Wadd to Kharifoot from the coast to 100 miles inland. That 20^ of the nett proceeds whether mineral, specie, archeologi- -cal specimens, or other marketable goods ^ould be divided as to 20% to the Sultan and balance to explore- -tion syndicate. That the concession should be in force for 50 years. That the Sultan would have the right over and above the before mentioned 20% to claim any archeological specimens he may wish to the amount of 20% of the total value found in, &gt;}*u: ; S.114 , i , X mm , 2 ^. ; r *1 e cf $ J c&gt; X os . .0 6- , ora i i w i * W, o f Xl.^eXx:! t ' “Ik.z-'-x. ,'f6XX sax io MfcJlfci xo i is ox xasify jj sv&amp;i l * v ^'—■ . o ’ ■ - . i'-CC L O - 0 - -J . ' - as. :.’, J . .' .; • ‘ ; ^ v -,-r- ■ -4 • «. £j;p&amp;‘l&amp; .VxSiiXU'GO ' :r -- ; V 6 -’l ro^oqxsco .bnri? ©da^i Xe ^-t.^XeToev e:iX Xo rroiXse-; c;o rot ^roXu iBaqrxe 011$ lo rroi:j.em~ &amp;o o. oc dc: ■nrclsosoaoo aiaX xboX - .si aBCf lm.ilo ’j dti# n.. be ixsiXogen oX b.bB' lo SBrl ass^tecs Xcnj .,.o g.ij ^evoo ol c . - Xi J &gt;i :, -. o ;; ■:• - l 00''0'-0.: 0' ;\J . ‘\ ''; . ItiO-. .! oc ;n- ■ ■..•- - •Jh » • etcaeti 06 tot eotot oi pa' fili/oda oc ieasoaoc aoJ jadl I orj,- &amp;VC-JB 0 ;u&gt; a^vo :.-!; 5 io €• v^.i Xioou cadi xa axe . .;-ru anoo-..oe I ao vao' fnifsXo c X l,OS £»?&gt;noX.tr?©a ..oi jbnuc'iany one year. The valuers to he nominated hy the India Office. If these suggestions could he put forward perhaps the Sultan would he sufficiently interested his to give/support to the venture. Yours etc., (sd) F.B.LACY.P.Z.5351/32 india Office, Whitehall, London. 3.W.I. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 2nd instant on the subject of a mining concession in Southern Arabia I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to sa'y that copies of your letter are being forwarded to the Governmento6f-India and to the Political -resident in the Persian Gulf, and that on rebei!&gt;t of the views of the local authorities a further letter will be addressed to you. 1 am, Sir, Tour obedient, Servant, sd/- J.G.Walton. ^T.B.LACY, Bsq. , 1, Oak Hill Park, Frognal, N.W.3.Confidential. ixj£ 33? Q7./C)- 3 v GOVERNMENT OF JNDIA, Depariment. Pvl 5) •*V- R. This is an 0 RIG IA A L M ESSAGE, sent hy post to sa e leuaraphic expense and undue use of the 'wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as ij it, had been telegraphed. To sate time and' formalities it is worded a d siyt ed as if it had been so despatched.] From Hesiaent, tJushire. To Folitical, Muscat. A r 0 | eOl-S of 1932. Uushire, Dated 20th October 1932 Mineral Deposits in bouthern Arabia. Reference this office printed letter no. 669-b, dated 17th September 1932. 2 . Please ^ost your views as early as possible after consulting His Highness on Mr. Hacy’s suggestions. Si)/ T.C. jjowle, Dieut.-Colonel, jeolitical wesiaent in the Persian uulf. Attested: S dJf yfr JI* Confidential Assistant. ' DCFP—1I07SAP—(G-1254)—24-0 31—4,00,000.Confidential s/ /, A No*C/ /^j '2. of 1932, Th« Political Agency 4 H.B.M*e Consulate* Muscat# 22nd November 1932* To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# Buahire* Memorandum. % ±0 Reference your Express Letter No*301-S dated 20th A October 1932* Captain Alban intervievted His Highness the Sultan who informed him that the situation was still unchanged since y-h His Highness's last letter (vide this office p/o No. K/40 dated 14th Jtily 1932)* The Sultan also stated that he would inform the Political Agent when it is sa&amp;e to allow prospecting for » ^ minerals. Major# Political Agent &amp; H.B.M'a Consul# Muscat. V .NHH 1, HILL PnHK, MOGNAL, JN.^. 3. 2Bth October 19 32. j 4 C. Walton Esq., The In.ia Office, Whitehall, 3.W.I. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter of the 9th September, While I shall be glad to hear the views of the local authorities, circumstances have arisen which make it impossible for me to go further with the matter of an exploration in Southern Arabia. While thanking you for your assistance I am sorry if I have given any unnecessary trouble. Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) E.B. LACY. COPV X *D. 0. fo. F.16 Foreign and Political Deparlznent* Delhi; the March 1933. Please refer to Mr* Lacy’s letter of the 23th October 1932* on the subject of a wining concession in Southern Arabia* a copy of whioh was x'orwarded to the aovemrsent of India by Air Mail under P. 3. 66 41/32. I 3 £i desired to enquire vdiotiler in the ci roumetancea explained by Mr. Lacy any further action in the jaatter is required. Yours sincerely* Sd. W.K. Fraser-Tytl er. J. C. Walton t Saquire* G.B. » M.C. * Secretary* Political Department* India Office* London. Cooy for infoiroation to the Hon’ble Lieutenant uolonel G.W. ’ebwle, G.B.S.* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. By order* etc. * 3d. T .7.K. Fraser Lytler, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. i 5vi if' a QCI-TFID^ITIAL. The Hesidency, I).0.^o.3ta.S of 1933. • CE9X R-0^aeliire t ;he 31st ^rcii 1933. t 9-a/BoIorB Jo vqoc rftlw t rcroO t , *x’9^A XsoltHo^ orft at atrrefiilcnor* iftlw MbfawTo^ ' •no iJem ol nl t o^: , teo auM /“v .•js/yrO vff mi close an extract from &amp; report by Alban of a J^o with the ultan of Muscat •tXnO n J [5l8'te rT erft nl f?long the Bat inch coast, one of the most important areas in ’Oman, and one which in the past has given us, and the luacat State, not a little trouble. The political effect of the tour was apparently excellent and shows how much can be done with Arabs by the personal touch of the Kuler. The tour was on distinctly ’old-fashioned’ lines, even down to the presence of a Court Jester, and Alban’s account of it is entertaining, besides giving a pleasant picture of the best aide of ’oriental* administration. It may amuse you to read it in the intervals of dealing with more serious matters. I am sending a copy of this letter with its enclosure to Walton. -t will perhaps afford some relaxation to him and Laithw&amp;ite from white Tapers and the like. .,«etcnxi e,A-Ssi• § C 4 X * A *, M. \ ? .0. , Foreign Secretary to the Government of Inaia, i»ew delhi. Youre sincerely, C^od.) T.C.Fowle, MM TTo-Extract from ive^ort t dated iiarcii 16, 1953, by Captain H.G#!*;.## Alban, Financial Adviser to tne Huec&amp;t State* *### 3ub.1 ect ; His Ui^neas tne Sultan of unseat 'm tour of the Batineh Coast* In e state like this, wnere the ruler has absolute power in Gave naont, it is certain tiiat a large nuisber of points will always arise which can only be settled by the rxler himself# inconvenient number of these, mostly concerned with revenue matters, having accumulated, his Hi t ;hhe 3 i decided to carry out a eoiaprahennive tour of the Batineh coast, as far as ,ahar* his iIi ^ Jlnes8 , party or Ghoma was cuapoeed entirely of camels, and although only nuinoerin t , about a huridied at this stage of the Journey* it presented an increasingly imposing appearance as it was augmented in numbers from day to day, by the constant arrival of new Uu inhs and their parties* The rest of us, including myself, little Saiyid P&amp;hr His Highness’ youngest brother aged about Q years and doctor H&amp;rdi the stout and cheerful Assistant Surgeon, lent to us by *ind favour of the Political Agent, proceeded in my car* Behind ua came w*i© horris lorry piled with luggage, cooking pots, etc. to resemble a steep mountain around which, like leeches, hung the Boyal cooks, scullions, etc* .Precariously perched at the back was Glia'ar, the Court Jester, clad in an enormous 'Amam&amp;h and a long and e nab by cloak which might have been the I&amp;tect fashion in tne days of the Caliph Karoun al i ashid* These unfortunates had a ver^ strenuous time/- 2 - time as, in ad it ion to being conotantl^r raked fore and aft by the iong thorns of Giinf treeo overhanging the road, they were expected also to push the lorry through the frequent patches of heavy sand as well as assist in sending punctures, etc. Kia iUg.ness* tour occupied about fourteen days and was broken up by halts of from 1 to 3 days at each district head quarters. Outstanding cases were settled and several changes were made amongst thw ^alis. At iiarkah difficulties in collection of &lt;*akat revenue were satisfactorily settled by liis Highnesa’ persc.ial influence with the Smikhe. At tiwaik Hia Highness was entertained and spent the night at the residence of Shaikh Hilal bin hamed, Chief of the Yal head. The arrival of hhoma at each halting place presented a rather imposing spectacle. /^preaching in znass formation upon a broad front, the camels would be hnlted some hundreds of yards before reaching the encampment and indulge in races pair oy pair on the hard sand al ong the waters edge, ijausement was provided Oy the frequent falls at' the competitors and in some cases camels took fright and bolted into the sea to the embarrassment of their riders. iixeept for those places where houses were available accommodation consisted of date palm shelters erected on the beach or other open ground. open axr Bar^a or meeting ,ms held each morning at about 7 &lt;*•*#. this being attended by several hundred oX the local inhabitants for paying of respects and putting forward grievances. heals were taken twice a day, morning and after-noon, and consisted of the usual Arab dishes of rice, fish, chicken, bread, etc. The hearty laughter necessary for the proper digestion of these delicacies was provided/-3- pro%'idfcd by me presence i&lt;t the end of tne table of the Court J eater whose indignant protests and recrimina.tions at the indiani- ties inflicted upon him tne Nubian slaves and his immediate neighbour added further ieat to the horse-play a«i agreeably enlivened the assembly. Occasionally, as a mark of ^reat favour, His Uighnsus would be pleased to select a bare and gnawed bone for presentation to Jrum, shxen the poor lean’s vigorous exhortations repudiation of ouch unseemly gifts and axteKfeihjfta to the i.ultan to reiaeniber his position and dignity would arouse the assembly to even greater heists of merriment. ' Hi© iiigiineoi was met and accompanied by all the important shaikhs owing allegiance to Muscat, and at Sh^wr the Shaikh of Beraimi also appeared. The effects of this tour upon the Batinch as a whole have been excellent and, but for this, it would nave been difficult to curry on the administration during Ua highness 1 projected long absence at hhofar.//&gt;| p,v^ CONFIDENTIAL. No. 398-S of 1933. Tlie Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the underim d &gt;cu- mentjj^f/ for information. Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter Ho.P.Z. 1652/33 of 30th March 1933 to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Depart ment • Project for a Mining concession in Southern Arabia.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/438</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/438</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 14/5 MINERAL DEPOSITS IN DHOFAR'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1911/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-23T23:17:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (55 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 57; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to prospecting for coal and other minerals in Dhofar. Issues discussed include terms of a concession, technical mining issues and assessments of commercial viability of mining the coal seams and ore.The file contains correspondence with representatives of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company on desired terms for a concession and a draft agreement (ff 6-8) relating to coal. Also discussed in the file are the unsuitable conditions for prospecting, such as the hostile reaction of tribesmen in the Qara mountains.Included in the file is a handwritten letter (folio 35) in Arabic (with English translation on folio 36) from the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr] to the Political Agent, Muscat, concerning a possible concession for mining coal. Correspondence (folio 30) from a representative of the Government of Muscat and Oman also discusses the significance of the discoveries by Harry St John Bridger Philby and Bertram Sidney Thomas in Dhofar and their possible connection to the 'gold mines of Ophir'.The file features the following principal correspondents: the Political Agent, Muscat (Trenchard Craven William Fowle); the British Consul, Basrah (Francis Edward Crow); the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Percy Zachariah Cox); the Secretary of State for the Colonies; and the Financial Adviser to the Sultan of Muscat (Reginald George Evelin William Alban).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Coal mining</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for the Colonies, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dhofar</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>