<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001cd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-05T12:12:00.768Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(&lt;£) V-G'-'C A.G. kBtf/50. 30 'November, 1950* / i&gt;car Mlnahall, Wm spoke on the telephone the other day about an outstandii^ air freight charge amounting to £Wl3e*l0d. t on a consignment of Yellow Fever vaccine supplied to the &gt;tate Medical Ofiioer, liahrain, in llay 1946 , I explained that oonaigneenta of this vaccine in 194^ to Bahrain were arranged by the former India Office on behalf of the Bahrain Govcmuent, but owing to a miaunderalanding# the air frelg^xt charge on the particular oonsignaent on 2nd «cjr 1%.6 was not aid at the time. I gathered from our conversation that as the Foreign Office is now res onsible for the United Kingdom Government *• relations dth Bahrain# you would see no object ion to th settlement ox'this air freight charge by your department in the first instance, and/’^je subs©t;uent adjustment laMde with the Bahrain Government* On the acsmmp%icsi that you agree to this course, 1 a enclosing a copy of the relevant correspondence, and you will see from the State Medical Officer # s letter of 20th Bepteiaber, that the charge has not been met by the Bahrain Govemcaent# who are prepared to settle the matter forthwith* X enclose also JonsiguBcnt fiote fto* 04/0/149903 and Air Freight Application Form and waybill ho*210Bl4 on record on our file* Ferhaps you will be gaod enough to oo-nmunioate with the m^h / H* 9# Minahull# £eq* t 6#S*£* Foreign Office, London b.tf.l*CD OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA £ Telephone — Blackpool South Shore 42085. Ext., Address for Inland Telegrams — 8 Indiamen, Blackpool * Any communication on this subject to he addressed THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL. INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL and not to any individual by name. Please quote in your reply .I? SED isrp 0, Dear Miss Odgers, Vaccine for Bahrein The enclosed copy of a letter dated 9th December 1947 from Ilesars. Burroughs Wellcome &amp; Co. to the State liedical Officer, Government Hospital, Bahrain, has been received. Vfe have had no x&gt;revious information regarding this, and as arrangements for despatch of Yellow Yever Vaccine in 1946 were dealt with by you, no doubt you will take any action now necessary. Yours sincerely. Hiss Odgers, External Department, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, London S.ViM • EXT 2307 / 44 ? &lt;mm■anDRAFT LETTER FXT. 6051/U Messrs. Burroughs Welcome &amp; Company, Comnonwealth House, 1-19 New Oxford Street, London, W.C.l. 11 SEP 1946 Gentlemen, This Office has received your letter D(3i/kLW dated 30th August with its ; ) 1 V ' enclosure. As it was incorrectly addressed there has been an unavoidable delay in our reply. You state that you have no standing instructions for the regular despatch of yellow fever vaccine to Bahrein. We would, therefore, invite your attention to our No. Ext.2225A 6 dated 28th March, 1946, and to your reply No. DG^iLW/EX. 6 of the 9th April, 1946. A payable order for £105 to cover the cost of the preparation of monthly consignments of this vaccine was sent to you under our Ext.2591the 30th April, 1946. Finally,/*Copy of letter dated 23rd Aug us i; 1946, ref, DCH/AlIiiT Ex 6 frcm Messrs,Burroughs Wellooipe &amp; Co,, Commonwealth House, 1-19, Hew Oxford: Street, london W*C,1o to The Direotor-General, India Store Deparhaent, Blackpool, We have received a letter from the State Medical Officer, Government Hospital, Bahrein, in reference to supplies of Yellow Fever Vaccine, In this letter they request that we should reduce the order placed through the India Office from 7 phials monthly to 4 phials every two months. We have no standing instructions for the despatch of any quantity of Yellow Fever Vaccine at regular intervals so that we are referring this matter to you for attention, and shall be glad to receive your instructions for further supplies of Yellow Fever Vacqine to be sent to Bahrein, in due course.ICables and Wireless: TABLOID, LONDON BURROUGHS WELLCOME &amp; CO. (Proprietors: The Wellcome Foundation Ltd.) &lt;3V) TEMPORARY ADDRESS Teiegraphic Codes: MARCONI INTERNATIONAL COMMONWEALTH HOUSE Telephone: EUSton 4477 Telegrams: TABLOID HOLB LONDON 183-1 Referee 1-19, NEW OXFORD STREET V.l LONDON, W.C.1 IQ . C LS4b Telephone : CHAncery 8201 --n Dear Sirs, We are enclosing herewith a copy of ^'tir Istt ;r dated 3ijrd xingust on the subject of an order for Yellow Fever Faccine to' be despatched to the Government Hospital Bahrein. We very much regret that while this letter was intended for despatch to your Office, it was inadvertently* addressed to the India Store Department. Looking forward to receiving your news in due course, we are, urs faithfully, BURROUGHS V^LLCOKE L CO. Zone Executive Clarence House, Central Buildings, Whitehall, a I:Cables and Wireless : TABtOID, LONDON Telegraphic Codes: A B C &amp; MARCONI INTERNATIONAL Telephone: EUSton 4477 Telegrams: TABLOID HOLB LONDON 183-W7EUSTON ROAD, LONDON, N.W.l Reference DGH/taV. 30th August 1946 % JC* f t* Dear Sirs, -e are enclosing herewith a copy of our letter dated 23rd August on the subject of an order for Yellow Fever Faccine to be despatched to the Government Hospital Bahrein. V.e very much regret that while this letter was intended for despatch to your Office, it was inadvertently- addressed to the India Store Department. Looking forward to receiving your news in due course, we are, ^ mi —r-.^ur^n-PQ faithfully, BURROUGHS ^ALLCOLL ^ CO. f i / t « — * 1 ms C a Zone Executive I i ^ ft'^ffrrt- f Clarence House, Central Buildings, Whitehall, •w ’ S.v . 1 .Reference DGH/ML?, EX 6 23rd August 1946 Dear Sirs, We have received a letter from the State iledical ’ G T 0vernment Hospital, Bahrein, in reference to supplies of Yellow lever Vaccine. In this letter they request that we should reduce tne order placed through the India Office from 7 phials monthly to 4 phials every two months. he have no standing instructions for the despatch of any quantity of Yellow I’ever Vaccine regular intervals so that we are referring this matter to you for at^entior. , and shall be glad to receive your instructions a or further supplies of Yellow 1'ever Vaccine to be sent to Bahrein in due course. Yours faithfully; BURROJGES WELLCOME &amp; CO. Zone Executive^ -- ^ * ' 12 , RED LION SQUARE r ^ 3 - / LON DON, W.C. I * &lt;^b KFSS^S from 0...^jpir^^L - 7 the sum of. pounds, ~ -- £ / 0 6 ; ; BURROUGHS WELLCOME &amp; CO. (Proprietors: The Wellcome Foundation Ltd.) per. ^ STY. 911% Cables and Wireless: TABLOID, LONDON Telegraphic Codes: ABC&amp; MARCONI INTERNATIONAL BURF^ VTT ^ XJC wFir roME &amp; CO. temporary address (5?) COMMONWEALTH HOUSE 1-19, NEW OXFORD STREET Telephone: EUSton 4477 Telegrams: LOID HOLB LONDON 183-193, LONDON, W.C.l Telephone: CHAncery 8201 Reference DGH/MLW EX 6 *■)&lt;&gt;* O* V wwr * 22nd July 1946' &gt; I Dear Sirs, t s ?/e refer Vo^our letter of—^he 9th April and now have pleasure in sending you herewith our debit note for the fee for the supply of Yellow Fever Vaccine to the Bahrein Government Hospital. We shall appreciate your settlement of this debit note in due course. Yours faithfully, BURROUGHS WELLCOME &amp; CO. lVv$ cCt l , India Office Whitehall, LONDON S.W.l.Cables and Radiotelegrams: TABLOID, LONDON Inland Telegrams : TABLOID HOLB LONDON Telegraphic Codes: ABC and MARCONI INTERNATIONAL Telephone : EUSton 4477 BURROUGHS WELLCOME &amp; (Proprietors: The Wellcome Foundation Ltd.) 183-193, EUSTON ROAD, LONDON, N.W. 1 Associated Houses: New York Montreal Sydney Cape Town Bombay Shanghai Buenos Aires ORDER NO. FO I 4 I 94 CHEQUES CROSSED MIDLAND BANK, LTD. TERMS—NET CASH SOLD TO India office. , Whitehall, London g;.w«l» CONVEYANCE INDEX NO. ex 6 DATE l6th April, 1946. Weight of j product with- i out container i Poids du produit sans | le contenant Weight of product with immediate j container j Poids du produit avec j le contenant : Weight of product with all wrappings Poids du produit avec toutes les enveloppes QUANTITY DATE OF ORDER REFERENCE Peso del | Peso del Peso del producto producco producto con sin el i con el todas las recepticulo receptaculo envolturas To._ Tree for the supply of Yellow Fever vaccine to the Bahrein o-overnment Hospital. AT CONSIGNEE’S RISK FOR OFFICE USE Packages are charged at cost and are not returnable [i]^ Sooret&amp;ry of state for India. « 4 i^olitical 9 Bahrein. Juno, 1 ^ 46 * ixt . 41 06/46 Oo^jy ia enclosed hero with of oorraapondaiics© bet'/oon jjr. Snow and ienioillin Production Control about tte delay in the dcsjyatoh of ponioillin* 4a eagjlaino d in larrison* s letter to Galloway Prom jlr. Snow dated 2cith May. ) Ifo. iixt. 7191/ ^th June, ttiie vteifl To Dr. Snow date d 13t h June ) auo to difficulties with /».ir Prei^it Control. Oonaignrxnts for Ai'iril, May and June havo airice bean do'syetciiod and should liave been received by now. It ahouIA be appreciated that the fin t three ocr^sigunents were sent by India Office bag, but that later packets had to be sortb by air freight throu^i coiXiierclai clmnnels. Airangoiiiexits have 110 ^'/ been made to expedite future despatch by air freight wlasn order ia placed with fim in this country. 2 . please inform Dr. Snow accordingly.ieniciliin roduction Control. Abbey 7788 13th June,1946 y-^&lt; sir. Thank you for your letter of the 28th Vfay egarding supplies of enici ...in, Ao transport la arranged by the India Office we have passed a copy of your letter on to that apartment. You will no doubt be hearing from them direct. Yours faithfully, (Sgd.) A. D. MALLOCH for assistant Controller Penicillin production. Dr#H.K«B.3now, State Medical Officer, Government Hospital, Bahrain, lersian Gulf.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Our Hef. 34/55/65. Your Ref. 325/PEJf/l 11. Government - Hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf, 28th May, 1946. The Assistant Controller, Penicillin Production Control, Ministry of Supply, Portland House, Tothill Street, London, S. W. !• Penicillin induction Ministry of Supply Pear Sir, gg« Monthly Suppms (aiy Freigh^f jP^nlcillin 5a&amp;ra.in, Gpveiament Ho^pita],. In a cable, dated 27.5.46, I intimated to you that no Penicillin has been received here since your last consignment of March 20th 1946* This hiatus of two months has proved serious, because of the vital use to which Penolllin can be out here. The situation up-to-date, since its inauguration in November 1945 has been the following *- Penicillin. (Air freightage) 70 vials 50 ' 70 ' nil 60 vials nil nil received 26.11.45. • 18.12.45. ' 22. 1.46. • Feb: *46. ' 20. 3.46. ' April ’46. ' May f 46. Payment of £133., excluding air freightage, has already been effected for the first 6 months. The January omission is explained by the following statement sent by India Office to the Political Agent, Bahrain on Feb: 22nd :- 'An invoice is enclosed for one packet of Penicillin for the Bahrain Government Hospital. This packet was despatched by sea mail bag on 1st January 1946. Arrangements are being made with the B.O.A.C. for the carriage of these packets to Bahrain by ordin— -ary air freight in future' ( as in Novi Dec:) &gt;v0 No sea consignment has yet been received up to the present date, but the first 2 subsequent air supplies for Feb- -ruary and March arrived in good order asMiown, and now have stopped.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. - 2 - Government - Hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf, V- 28th, May, 1946. India Office in a letter of Feb: 4th to The Ministry of Civil Aviation did however intimate that it would be prefer- -able if the suppliers could send the parcels direct to the transport authorities. Perhaps, therefore the hold up is between these two parties. I enclose two further copies of this letter in case you would prefer to send them direct to The Suppliers and India Office for Information and comment. Yours truly, State Medical Officer, Bahrain. P.S. 5f £&amp;&lt; c JUX.'rJ.' ***! , I should mention that only air travel is feasible, and that the 4 consignments already sent that way came through quickly with no hitch. ^ rK ,.^ T^V S op^- S. M. 0., Bahrain* METFILE cop-. Of: Tel. No.—Abbey 7788. Penicillin Production Control. MINISTRY OF SUPPLY, kxt' h a! ^*7 *«106 Dear Miss Odgdca. 4P PORTLAND HOUSE, TOTHILL STREET, LONDON, S.W. 1 . 13th June,1946. e have received the attached letter from the Bahrain Government Hospital,regarding supplies of Penicillin. The following Orders have been placed; Order No. Date luantity Firm 405 12.11.4#. 7 x Glaxo 445 22.11.48? 5 Boots 552 o 8.10.4#.* 7 Boots 637 25.1.46. 6 Boots 765 19.2.46. 7 . Boots 879 16.3.46. 6 Boots 1043 17.4.46. 7 Boots Delivery Date. At once. During December. January. February. ' f March. ” .,pril. May. It appears therefore that the hold up has been due t transport difficulties. Perhaps you will be ;ood enough to look into the matter and reply to Dr.Snow direct. Miss Odgers, India Office, Whitehall ,3. ,7.1. Yours sincerely,BOOTS PURE DREG COMPANY LIMITED Telephone: NOTTINGHAM 48601 Cablegrams! DBTJG, NOTTINGHAM ENGLAND Codes: A.B.C. 6th and 6th BENTLEY* MAKCOJK v MANUFACTURING CHEMISTS &amp; All comm uni cations to be addressed to MAKERS OF FINE CHEMICALS WHOLESALE AND EXPORT DEPARTMENT BOOTS PURE DRUG CO. LIMITED STATION STREET NOTTINGHAM, ENGLAND »« RJ/AW NOTTINGHAM ENGLAND 3 ^ ft FILE COPY 6th June, 1946. Mr. harrison, External Department India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W. 1. Dear Sir, We are forwarding on to you herewith the instructions received from the Royal Air Force covering the three packages of Penicillin reauired for the State Medical Officer, Bahrain Government Hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Apparently our Chemical Office received direct communication from the Penicillin Control, to forward the above three^cases by passenger train on the 28th of M*y. We trust they have arrived safely and that you have been able to deal with same.»■«» ■ R.A.F. Form 1380. COPY NUMBER r AIR MINISTRY 3-JUNI946 AIR FREIG Serial NoT ( HT WAYBILL. Air Fre ght Application No.: PRIORITY / J Freight Identity Number Destination Airfield 2.11477 PART A DETAILS OF CONSIGNMENT. No. of Packages Type of Packages Case Serial Numbers DESCRIPTION OF CONTENTS Package Weight (lb) Consignment Weight (lbs) Dimensions (in inches) 3 K U L 1 IV 4 Ifcf hi ll&gt; S A # ‘/l * 10 / ox t/vc-b rerceket* TOTAL NUMBER OF PACKAGES TOTAL WEIGHT OF CONSIGNMENT 4a lh PART B CONSIGNOR’S APPLICATION FOR CARRIAGE. CONSIGNOR : Mess vs icaoU Tore Consignor’s Reference Recommended Priority. 7 1, tie Signed Date PART C— Calling Forward Instructions CONSIGNEE : STATF Mcp ICAI OrnuT* The freight identity number and priority shown above must be clearly marked on each package. If there is more than one package in the consignment each package must additionally be marked with a sub-number, i.e. ( ' I. etc.) he packages must then be sent together with Copy No. I of the Form 1380 to :— B. 0. A, G. N ORTHGLT (i PART D FOR USE OF ACCOUNTS. SECTION I (to be completed by sponsor). Cost involved is: 11-* »&gt; irw _ A. Chargeable to &amp;.PP”.*5 Funds (DEPT. GOVERNMENT. Etc.) THROUGH AIR MINISTRY (F.3 (h) ) B. Not chargeable to Government Funds but recoverable from :— Name Address Signature of Sponsor. SECTION 2 (Completed by Carrier) Amount of Charge is : lbs. = .. kilos. at Rate per kilo. £ s. d. = E Despatch Details Fit. No. To Manifest Serial No. F For Use At Destination Airfield Received on Fit. No. Date From Manifest Ser. No. Consignee Notified PHONE/POSTAGRAM/SIGNAL. Person Informed Date and Time Init. of Informant Items Delivered NAME (Block Letters) to Signed Unit IMPORTANT.— In all cases where application is made in respect of 'non-entitled” freight (i.e. freight for which a charge for carriage is made) invoices for goods must accompany this form. The invoices will be forwarded to the Consignee with the consignee's copy of Form 1380.CONDmONS OF CARRIAGE. The Secretary of State for Air, the Air Council, any officer or airman of the Royal Air Force and any other servant or any agent of the Crown shall be under no liability in respect of or arising out of the carriage of the goods consigned and such carriage is subject to the condition that the Consignor of the goods shall not make any claim against the Crown or any servant or agent of the crown for compensation or damages in respect of any loss of damage to or any delay in the carriage of the said goods whether caused or occasioned directly or indirectly by the act, neglect or default of any servant or agent of the Crown or otherwise howsoever and will hold the Crown and every servant or agent of the Crown indemnified against any such claim by any other person. Ci ' ■ .. 'j\ ADVICE NG.e To be posted to Consignee at time of des patch. Form G.980a (Supply) MINISTRY OF SUPPLY CODE ADVtCE TO CONSIGNEE OF GOODS DESPATCHED BY PASSENGER TRAEN. Serial No. A A/ L- ,V r ' Railway Company at Nottinelmini has been requested to receive and forward the undermentioned goods. Station Full Name and Address of Consijnor Measra* Boots Pure Drug Go. Ltd., Station Street, Nottin* / ‘ N-i %. MINISTRY OF SUPPLY Authority for despatch (Quote contract No. If any) 294/24/3/1171 Collection by Chargeable to Consignor’s Signature ’/ir tstry of Supply Date ^ £ Railway 194 Full Name and Address of Consignee TO BE COMPLETED BY CONSIGNOR 318434 Sump of Officer Authorising Carrleg. v From Destination, Station o, and Railway Vr. Ha rri son, External Offrca Vlndtat Offic• f’hit ehall. LQ^IlON'e 3'. . 1, !( 9 00 ^ s ! re rece,v ? d in e 00 ' 1 condition, this form is to be retained by Consignee f the Goods do not arrive, the Rallwey Company must be notified In writing within 23 days of despatch If the Goods are received in a damaged fv-tradie-l^n I 1,7- , . ' No. of | Packages 1 Description and Marks of Goods WEIGHT (inclusive of packing) T. C. Q. Lbs. /del •. Penicillin in Tiaia. /4e - :: 7 „ ' r y / REPORT OFDAMAGE, 4c. Goods received 194 Description of loss, damage 4c. „ 1 / All j musi O* noimea m writing within 23 days of despatch ! » -—.....g within 6 day*'•&lt;. delivery, lelbourne House. Aldwych. London, Have (Uy. Co. been notified ? Signature . —194(MINISTRY OF SUPPLY—FORM No. 112) ISSUE VOUCHER Depot : Voucher Code | No. B*1.24£ Storekeeper must complete all Items within double lines. Issued from Ministry of Supply Depot (address) Messrs.. Boots Bure , firug Cc. Btd. , Island. Bt ..» Nottingham To (Consignee) The B.tate....ii:.a.dlc.al Oiflcer., Bahr.a.in.....G.Q¥..e£nm.e.nt. Hospital, Bahrain , Ppr-nt DESCRIPTION OF GOODS Quantity Issued 7(70 x 100,000unit vials}Penicillin &amp; . Authority for .ssue 3£SA Cn/75/1045 SggkaL, 70 yiialse... Date despatched No. of Wagon or Vehicle No. of Packages Method of transport p&amp;BS6Xl£:&amp;r « Consignment Note No. 3/ DUPLICATE to be completed by Consignee This copy to be sent to Con signee for receipting and return - “Jl Strand, W.C.2, or ~ (b) S.F.8, M.o^i'Ylelbourne House, Aldwych, W.C.2. (Sja^ce' out (a) or (b) as rr ^*^** applicable.) ■■'*''****• Panicilhn Prodi&gt;c«ion Control, Por Received Goods as specified above:— Date Signature On behalf of. House, Totfifll St.'TonVfhn'.' R.W'lv' For Headquarters use only Rate Transport Other Charges ... TOTAL ... £ Value s. ! d. Ledger Posted Initials Date Folio Repayment Inventory Action taken (initials) (date) Branch Signature(MINISTRY OF SUPPLY—FORM No. 112) ISSUE VOUCHER Depot : Voucher _ Code I No'•1246 vQ) storekeeper must complete all items within double lines. Issued from Ministry of Supply Depot (address^.I.«.£ftj&gt; MMfei Go* Md.#..jiLIsXftnc] , ..otti|l£jhame DESCRIPTION OF GOODS Quantity Issued 7 x 100,000 unit vials) Penicillin 70 vial Authority for fj orekeeper’r x itials ii^. Date despatched No. of Wagon or Vehicle No ' of P “ kiges Air transport and Method of transportpaa sengar. train a Consignment Note No _3;?i L-3M- TRIPLICATE THIS COPY TO BE SENT TO THE CONSIGNEE FOR RETENTION. Rate Value £ s. d. £ s. 1 d. Transport Other Charges ... TOTAL ... £ Ledger Posted Initials Date Folio Repayment Inventory Action taken (initials) (date) Branch SignatureADVICE note To be posted to Consignee at time of des patch. , ADVICE TO CONSIGNEE OF GOODS DESPATCHED BY PASSE NGER TRAIN. MINISTRY OF SUPPLY iui wo* JLAlCft The r^ f ’ KottinghRm . , , Railway Company at .as been requested to receive and forward the undermentioned goods. Station Full Name and Address of Consignor Maeers* Boots Pure fhrug Oo. Ltd*, Station street f Mott Authority for despatch (Quote contract No. if any) Chargeable to Ministry of Supply Collection by *^nvti(riaiirrarrftfr/ R ailway N® 318435 Stamp of Officer Authorising Carriage Date Consignor’s Signature Full Name and Address of Consignee TO BE COMPLETED BY CONSIGNOR .194 From Ifr. fterrieor, xt emnl )epnTtSent # India Office^ M t eho ).1. # IjOM DON * S. 7.I. Destination, Station o, and Railway No. of Packages Description and Marks of Goods T. WEIGHT (Inclusive of packing) ’oriXcillih TtnlaXS. f the Goods are received m good condition, this form is to be retained by Consignee. If !he Gnod, th ® Railw, T Company must be notified in writing within 23 days of despatch ’ n^h. ™ ^ | VC I di,mt * ed c ° nd 'tl°n or are incomplete, a qualified signature should be given and the R h W?C 2. f non ' del,ver &gt;'- or shortage, the report should be completed and this form sent to - - R w. LOS. —i i i 1 i | | . T * -y Company notified In wrlt|ig within « days of delivery. ..T. Accounts, Ministry of Supply, Melbourne House. Aldwych, London, REPORT OF DAMAGE, 4c. Goods received |94 Description of loss, damage &amp;c. Have Rly. Co. been notified ? Signature -i»4_(MINISTRY OF SUPPLY—FORM No. 112) ISSUE VOUCHER Depot Code.... Voucher .HB3 Storekeeper must complete all items within double lines. issued from Ministry of Supply Depot (address).^.? 31 : * ^ 2?li S ^ 0# ^ : » # X.S.land at* A To (Consignee).....^.?,,., &amp; &amp;&amp;*!&amp;JhfW/fsm Btit HogpltaX * Bahrain r Persian CJuXP • DESCRIPTION OF GOODS Quantity Issued 6 mega unita (60 x 100 f 000 u lit vials) Penicillin 60vials• Authority for Issue Stmbe' jS Date despatched ^ 4-'&lt;3 No. of Wagon or Vehicle No. of Packages Method of transport AiranC|)OPt end passenger train. Consignment Note No. 7?.! 9 For Headquarters use only Rate d. DUPLICATE to be completed by Consignee This copy to be sent to Con signee for receipting and return (a) C/Store/B, Shell Mex^ourt, Strand, W.C.2^ or (b) S.F.8, Melbourne Aldwych, W.C.2. (Str+k-e -©«* (a) c# -(b) as PenicilfWi Control, Portlai Received Goods as specified above:— Date Signature On behalf of. d House. Tothilt St. B.W.jl, Transport Other Charges ... TOTAL ... £ Value s. d. Ledger Posted Initials Date Folio Repayment Inventory Action taken (initials) (date) Branch!» P»rt 3 P«rt 2 Part ADVICE NOTE To be posted to Consignee at time of des patch. 8 Form G.980a (Supply) MINISTRY OF SUPPLY CODE ADVICE TO CONSIGNEE OF GOODS DESPATCHED BY PASSENGER TRAIN. Serial No« ^ ^ Railway Company at t has been requested to receive and forward the undermentioned goods. Station Full Name and Address of Consignor ^'ecsrs# r;, cots Pure Tru, i'o, Lt d •, /L at i on 3t r e et, Hot i ingh'inu MINISTRY OF SUPPLY Authority for despatch COA/o/ /n ^ 1 &lt;71 (Quote contract No. if any) i -7 t / j.X / .1 Chargeable to MUiletry of supply Consignor’s Signature JL&amp; 194 Collection by * G a ^ vv a ^ Date 194 From 318436 Stamp of Officer Authorising Carriage Full Name and Address of Consignee TO BE COMPLETED BY CONSIGNOR T’yf — f f i c e Jhlt-aha ll t Destination, Station ^ and Railway No. of Packages Description and Marks of Goods If the Goods are received in good condition, this form is to be retained by Consignee. '* ■ ’ tj]® Goods do not arrive, the Railway Company must be notified in writing within 28 days of despatch f f the Goods are received in a damaged condition or are incomplete, a qualified signature should be given and the Rallwa In the case of non-delivery, damage, or shortage, the report should be completed and this form sent to C.T. Accounts W.C.2. WEIGHT (Inclusive of packing) T. C. Q. Lbs. REPORTOF DAMAGE, 4c. Goods received 194 Description of loss, damage i jL &amp;C. - .. ■ T- Have Rly. Co. been notified ? Signature .194—!1 * (MINISTRY OF SUPPLY—FORM No. 112) ISSUE VOUCHER Depot Code l a S') Voucher No = i 5*938 Storekeeper must complete all Items within double lines. Issued from Ministry of Supply Depot (address) f/©S r • 'OOtfl PlTT© .DlTUg Go* Iftrt* ^ Island, l ot t ingiiai To (Consignee) L ' 51 te cal Bahrain Government, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. DESCRIPTION OF GOODS Quantity Issued 7 M.U. (70 x 100,000 unit vials) Penicillin ^ Z3 t &lt;4- 70 vials. Authority for Issue 325/Pen/75/765 For Headquarters use only Rate Date despatched ^ &gt;JrX? No. of Wagon or Vehicle No. of Packages Method of transport Air transport passengertrain. Consignment Note No. 3* DUPLICATE to be completed by Consignee This copy to be sent to Con signee for receipting and return to; aii&amp;o Strand, W.C.2, (b) S.F.8, M.o^f^Tielbourne Hgus^TAIdwych, W.C.2 (St^jS? out (a) or (b) as Pcnicitir^rcrfuc^n Control, Portland House, Other Charges ... TOTAL ... £ Value i s. d. Received Goods as specified above:— Date Signature On behalf of Tothill 8t. London, 8.W.I. Repayment Inventory Action taken (initials) (date) Branch SignatureCONDITIONS DE TRANSPORT. Le vansoort des marchar.dises est soumis aux “Conditions Ctntrales de Transport des Merchandises' et d tous riglemenu barticuliers du ou dcs transporteur(s), dont il peut etre pris connaissar.ee a leurs bureaux de reservation, pour autant que ces conditions et reglements ne sont pas contraires aux conditions et aux stipulations visies ou specif lees ci-dessous. Les “Conditions Ginirales de Transport pour le Trafic-air-fer” sont applicables oux transports combines air-fer. Le “transport international” au sens de la Convention de Varsovle du 12 octobrt 1929 pour/’unification decertaines regies relatives uu Transport Airien International, est soumis au regime de rcsponsabihte 6tabh par ladite Convention. Les expressions “Hautes Parties Contractantes' et 'Haute Partie Contractante employees aux articles I tn 28 de ladite Convention signifient les etats et les pays qui sont lies par cette Convention a la suite sort de leur ratification soit de leur adhesion. Au cas ou les regies, conditions et reglements mentionnes ci-dessus, ou une clause de ces regies, conditions et riglements relative d la responsabilite du transportcur, seraient declares inapplicables par le tribunal competent saisi, il est express6ment stipuli que la responsabiliU du transporteur sera exclue dans la mesure permise. Si I exoneration de responsabiute sus-vuee n'etait ons reconnue. le ou les transborteur(s) beneficiera(ront) de toute limitation admise par la loi du tribunal soisi. 5. 6 . Le transporteur n'accepte pas de marchandises avec declaration speciale d'int6ret a la livTaison tie* in mnrrhnndlsm Hnns un but auelconoue et en bortie aucIconXiue de la lettre de transport ne eons speciale d'interPid la- bxeaisqp. • '-r*. *-! vJf Le transporteur a run. de se substituer un ou plusiers autres transporteurs. 7. Dans le cas ou le transport est soumis aux lois britanniques, il est entendu que le(s) transporteur(s) n est (ne sont) pas up (das) “common cqrrier($)' ct n'acccptent pas les obligations et la repponsabilil6 du (des) ' ‘common carrier(s) . Le contrat de transport n'implique par ailleurs aucune garantie concernant I’aeronef utilise dans le transport ni son aptitude pour le transport des marchandises qui font Tobjet du contrat. CONDITIONS OF CARRIAGE, I Carriage of goods is subject to the “Genera! Conditions of Carriage of Goods' and any special regulations of the carrler(s), which can be inspected at their booking offices, in so far as such conditions and regulations are not incon sistent with the conditions and provisions referred to or stated below. 2. Combined transport (alr-rall) is subject to the “General Conditions of Carriage of Goods by air and rail”. 3. 'International carriage”, as defined by the Convention of Warsaw of 12th October 1929 for the Unification of Certain Rules relating to International Carriage by Air, is subject to the rules relating to liability established by the said Convention. The expressions “High Contracting Parties' and “High Contracting Party”, used in Articles I and 26 of the said Convention, and in the aforesaid General Conditions of Carriage, shall mean States and Territories which are bound by the said Convention either through ratification or adherence. 4 In the event of the rules, conditions and regulations stated or referred to above or any part thereof, relating to the exclusion or limitation of the liability of the carrier(s), being contrary to the law of the State or Territory in the court of which an action is brought, the liability of the carrier(s) shall be excluded or limited in so far as such law permits, and the carrier(s) shall be entitled to the benefit of every exclusion or limitation of liability permitted by such law. 5. In no case are goods accepted for carriage with a special declaration of value at delivery. The insertion of the value of goods, for any purpose, in any part of this consignment note shall not constitute a special declaration of value at delivery. 6. The right to substitute alternative carriers is reserved. 7. In all cases in which the carriage is subject to British laws it is expressly declared that the carrier(s) are not common carriers ami do not accept the obligations or liability of common carriers ; nor is there implied in the contract of carriage any warranty concerning the aircraft engaged in the carriage or concerning its fitness for the carriage of the goods to which such contract relates. /FlL£_COPV GOVERNMENT OF INDU, | I? y r p Department, 3327 EXPRESS LETTER / - — — ; V'-T/as is an ORIGINAL M ESS AGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intetuied to be treated^ on receipt, with the same expedition as xf it had been telegraphed. To save time ami formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] From POLITICAL BAHRAIN. To INDIA OFFICE EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT LONDON. iVo. 1714-2/1. Dated 30th May, 1946. iSfik * Reference your Express Letter No.EXT.2226/1946, March 26th, 1946. 2* Most grateful for the trouble you have taken in arranging the supply of yellow fever vaccine for the Bahrain Government Hospital. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Hgent, Bahrain.INDIA OFFICE, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed.) To Secrafcary of State for India* Political Agent, Bahrein* t&lt;&gt; jaghiro. No. Ext.3867/46 Your S^roee Letter Ho.1659-16/32A. of 2oth Penicillin for Bus hire Residency Hospital. 2. You will have seen from Harrison’s letter to Galloway No. Ext. 3797/46 of 6th June that penicillin is now being distributed oomaeroially, and orders must be placed &gt;?ith firms direct. It would therefore now be possible for Dr. Snow to include order for Residency Hospital in his own order placed coin:ieroial2y• If this is not being done Residency liospital might place its own order with fim in this country (if t.^ey have one regularly supplying them with drugs) requesting them at the same time to send the penicillin to External Department, India Office, for despatch to Bahrein by bag. Alternatively we could ask India Store Department of High Go^i/assioner's Office to arrange purchase on hesidency’s beimlf, if y u will iiidioate manner of accounting, and despatch by India Office bag. ;C HARRISON The issue of the above has been duly autliorised.^6' GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FILE COPY Departmen EXPRESS LETTER EXT 3667 w L [iN, Ti ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGB, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with tits same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To Repeated / INDIA OFFICE, EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT, LONDON. BRITAIN, BUSHIRS. iVo. 1659-16/32 A. bated 26th May- 1946. m Your Express Letter No. 1£XT. 5040/45, November 10th, 1945. Supply of Penicillin for Bahrain Government Hospital. 2. As the present arrangement for getting Penicillin from Tehran for the Residency Hospital, Bushire, has proved most unsatis factory I have, at the request of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, asked Dr. Snow, Chief Medical Officer, Bahrain, to include in his indents on London, an additional 500,000 units of Penicillin fortnightly to meet the requirements of the Residency Hospital. 3. Dr. Snow states that he cannot himself increase his present monthly indents and requests that you be approached on his behalf to increase his monthly requirements of Penicillin by 10 vials (1,000,000 units) which he will on receipt transfer to this Agency for onward despatch to Bushire. 4. Grateful if arrangements for supply of this extra quantity of Penicillin to Dr. Snow can be made. = POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Political Agent^ Bahrain. U: , MFP —601 S&amp;P-M- 820)—23-7-36^-300,000. /iff H/ llD 5th June, 19M&gt;« Dear Hr. Bradla^r, As arrunt^ed tgr telophone with Hr. Angel earlier today, I an sending herewith throe padcots of penicillin for despatch ty air freight, as soon as possible, to the Bahrein Govoronent Hospital, Uoiirein, Persian Gulf. Tlie value of each packet is approximately SZ*! • Yours sincerely, Hr. Bnuiley, iihqjorfc Cargoes Secticm, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Airways Toruinal, Buckingiiata Palaco Road, b.W.1.PAST AIR MAIL Ext# 3797/46. Dear Vould you please refer to India Office egress Letter I'o. 2225/46 of 28th L rch? I an afraid tiicre has been sone delay in the despatch of the inonthly consignnents of penicillin to the Bahrein Govemnent Hospital, owing to inefficiency on the ] art of the Air freight Control people# Ve haTe now writ ten rather strongly to the llini try of Civil /viation and hope that three consignments, those for April May and June, will be despatched by air freight very soon# I enclose a c opy of a letter from the Assistant dated 10th May 1 Controller of Penicillin Production to the india Store Department, from which you will see that penicillin is now being distributed through tra e channels# The Balirein Government will therefore have to place their order with race firm in this country in future, Messrs Boots Pui'e Drug Company of Island street, Nottingham have supr lied them hitherto, and they seem the obvious people# It occurs to me that this is a natter -which night perhaps most conveniently be handled in future through the Bahrein Government’s Supply Agents in tfiis country, Messrs Charles Kendall 81 Partners Ltd* If you agree, perhaps the Bahrein Government night instruct Messrs. Kendall*s to get in touch with us and we will explain the procedure to then# You will appreciate that v/hile we are of course always /ready Lt. Cel# #C# lloway 0#f# Political gent, Bahrein#ready to assist the Bahrein Govcrnramt in obtaining their requirements we are not readly staffed with a view to - dealing: with cor/nereial transactions of tliir. nature. Yours sincerely, F. A. K. HARRISON M&amp;) XJth ajr. 19*6. Bear Sir, tached for your information ia a copy of a press notice, which has been issued this week. As you will see, distribution of ienioillin through trade channels will begin on the 1st of June. Although the armounoement refers specifically to ienioillin for home requirements, the same procedure will apply wit* regard to export and users should obtain their Penicillin from their normal suppliers of pharmaceutical products. If you feel that any difficulty is likely to arise or aqy points require clarification, perhaps you would get in touch with me. Tours faithfully. ^Assistant controller of i eniciilin \ . reduction. The director General, India Store Bepartaient, Blackpool, lanes.(3 PRESS NOTICE DISTRIBUTION OF PENICILLIN hv l St JUhe 192f6, the P resent issue of Penicillin 7 ^ e^ Ministry of Supply through the hospital system v/ill cease. 2. rom the date mentioned, Penicillin will be available to Ho^Di+nl^ trade 0 1 ^ dlC 1 al ^ professions and to Retail Pharmacists though ’ of such p^uck ° UPP Sh0Uld be ° btained fr0m the usual ^PPliers X* +h ^ unaaall;Ln ar] y preparation containing Penicillin may be supplied 2*5 * h ' »&lt;■ * :irti=5 5 cackeffn^^ ° f ^ Peni f illin ** in the form of dried powder ° r '’“p 011103 containing 0.1, 0.2, 0.5, 1.0 mega units. T o maximum retail prices of these packs will be 2/9d, h/jd, lo/6d and 20/- respectively. Penicillin will also be availlble in aA oil-7aT suspension for injection. 5* Pharmacists may use dried Penicillin in dispensing the prescriptions registered jiedical .and Dental Practitioners. As tine &lt;?oos on increasing quantities of Penicillin preparations will become available iron the manufacturers. 6 ' difficulty be experienced in obtaining supplies, advice moL b n S ^ ght 4- fr r 0m i ne Mimstr y of Supply, Penicillin Production Control, To hill otreet, London, S.Vu 1. (Telephone No. Abbey 7788. Extn,A03).v This is a most unfortunate business, ard., I fear, may be partly uy fault. In the first place, although I spoke to Mr. Elliott of the Penicillin Production Control in the sense of your note at Ext.i 4 . 5 i 1 /if 6 , I may not have made myself clear. In any case the Production Control were under the impression that Boots were still sending penicillin to you for transmission to Bahrein, by our bag. Thus, on receiving a telegram from the State Medical Officer, Bahrein, they blew up Boots at once, and told them to send it to you immediately. I had already heard from Boots London Office, on 15th May, that they had one consignment of penicillin which had not been called forward, and another ready to go. I rang up Mr. Wakeling that day, and told him that we Yrere sending him Form 13 GO in respect of the May consignmsnt, and asked him what had happened about the April one. (Most unfortunately I did not make a note of the date in April on which we sent Pom 1380, I will endeavour to do so in future.) Mr. Wakeling replied that the Air Freight Control were in the process of moving, and it was possible that our foms were tenporarily mislaid. He promised to take the matter up with them, and said that the April and May consignments should be off within a week. You will remember that the Ministiy of Civil aviation refused to grant us priority for yellow fever vaccine and penicillin over a period of months, and insisted on the Fom 138 O procedure; it is up to them, therefore, to make it work.I cannot help feeling that while I have been negligent over this, the Ministiy of Civil Aviation, and Air Freight Control, have been grossly incompetent.v cux Ext.3797/46 1946. Dear Wakeling, Will you please refer to your letter of 6th March about the despatch of yellow fewer vaccine and penicillin to Bahrein in the Persian Gulf. In accordance with what you then said we have duly sent to you each month 6 copies of Form 1J80 in respect of both yellow fever vaccine and penicillin. Itafortmately this procedure does not seem to be very satisfactory* The yellow fever vaccine, as you know, has to travel in thermos flasks and to be kept at an even temperature. We find that it is only possible to ensure this by telephone calls to the Wellcome Institute of Tropical Medicine, the Ministry of Civil Aviation, Air PTeight Control and the B*0*A.C., to sure that the relevant forms and the F.C.B.nuraber have reached the persons concerned. As you will realise, this involves a cood deal of trouble. ;ith regard to the penicillin, you will remember that when Miss Odgers spoke to you on the telephone, on 15 th May, about the consignment for April, which as we had heard from Messrs. Boots had not been called forward, you agreed to take the matter up with Air Freight Control, who w^-re in the process of moving at that moo^ant. On the same day we sent you Form 1380 in respect of the May consignment. In ^fche ( meantime,, the penicillin Production Control have heard ft*cm the State Medical Officer, Bahrein, that no penicillin has been J /receiTed Room 305# Ministry of Civil Aviation, 0 ^ 1 $. 4 n , Ariel House, Strand, W.C.2. ..DRAPT LSTTilR i i) D.J, Wakeling, Esq., Room 305, Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, W.C.2. Dear Mceling, 7/ill you please refer to your letter of 6th March about the despatch of yellow fever vaccine and penicillin to Bahrein in the Persian Gulf. In accordance with what you then said we ! hnarl' K have duly sent to you^6 copies of Pom 1380 in respect of both yellow fever vaccine and penicillin sach-fflenih. Unfortunately this procedure does not seem to be very satisfactory. The yellow fever vaccine, as you know, has to travel in thermos flasks and to be kept at an even teriperature. We find that it is only possible to ensure this by telephone calls to the Wellcome Institute of Tropical Medicine, the/the Ministry of Civil Aviation, Air Freight Control &lt; ‘ 6 . ---- v - ^ • and the B.O.A^J., to make sure that the relevant forms and the F.C .B• have reached the persons concerned. As you will realise ; this ll, \rrlv^ *- firry) , ^ns-iaRr -ihl o Tfnfil i f 'T’ ij'l i Ij 1 n timri With re^-rd to the penicillin, you will remember that when Miss Odgers spoke to you on the telephone, on 15th. May, about the consignment for April, which as we had heard from Messrs. Boots had not been called forward, you agreed to take the matter up with Air Freight Control, who were in the process of moving at that moment. On the same day we sent you Form 1380 in respect of the May consignment, y ^Inthe meantime the Penicillin Production Control have heard from the State Medical Officer, Bahrein, that no penicillin has been received there since March. They got in touch v/ith Messrs, Boots, and, understanding that 3 consignments (for April, May and June) were ready for despatch, told Boots to send them to me. They have now arrived, - 1mam'ih X A /&gt; R.A.F. Form 1380, AIR FREIGHT APPLICATION FORK, AND WAYBILL. PRIORITY Freight Identity Nunfbeir COPY NUMBER 3 Serial No. ' Air Freight Application No.: Destination Airfield PART a details of consignment. No. of Packages Type of Packages Case Serial Numbers DESCRIPTION OF CONTENTS Package Weight (lb) Consignment Weight (lbs) Dimensions (in inches) T: liifm '•ty*'.' * •••V hf iT P’TT c —— \ TOTAL NUMBER TOTAL^WEIGHT = ” OF PACKAGES CONSIGNMENT r PART B CONSIGNOR’S APPLICATION FOR CARRIAGE. PART C— Calling Forward Instructions Consignor’s CONSIGNEE : Reference STf‘ Ti : ‘ TC- »&gt; Recommended Priority. W • C t , Signed ^ AV* H fc; fy Date CONSIGNOR : Wt u «•»»»&lt;. The freight identity number and priority shown above must be clearly marked on each package. If there is more than one package in the consignment each package must additionally be marked with a sub-number, i.e. ( / I. etc.) The packages must then be sent together with Copy No. I of the Form 1380 to :— PART D FOR USE OF ACCOUNTS. E Despatch Details For U se At Destination Airfield SECTION I (to be completed by sponsor). Cost involved is: SECTION 2 (Completed by Carrier) Fit. No. : A. Chargeable to ' Funds (DEPT. GOVERNMENT, Etc.) THROUGH AIR MINISTRY (F.3 (h) ) i Amount of j Charge is : lbs. Date B. Not chargeable to Government Funds but recoverable from :— Name i_ Address Signature . f , \ ~: t - ■ of Sponsor Jjf.T?. Rate at per kilo. To Manifest Serial No. Received on Fit. No. Date From Manifest Ser. No. Consignee Notified PHONE/POSTAGRAM/SIGNAL. Person Informed Date and Time Init. of Informant Items Delivered NAME (Block Letters) to Signed Unit Date IMPORTANT. —In all cases where application is made in respect of “non-entitled” freight (i.e. freight for which a charge for carriage is made) invoices for goods must accompany this form. The invoices will be forwarded to the Consignee with the consignee's copy of Form 1380.BURROUGHS^wfettcfoME &amp; CO. (Proprietors: The Wellcome Foundation Ltd.) cables and wireless: -i f) fv TABLOID LONDON Telegraphic Codes: &gt; /\ ABC &amp; MARCONI INTERNATIONAL 183-193, EUSTO Reference DGK/*'L( ^ v Your Reference Ext.2235/1946 Telephone: EUSton 4477 Telegrams : TABLOID HOLB LONDON Deer Sirs, # We thank you for your letter of the 28th March and we understand from Dr. Broom that the first despatch of Yellow *ever Vaccine to the Bahrein Government Hospital has already been made. The Vaccine has not yet been added to our price list and is not yet normally available for commercial sale. No price has so far been established though we know that the cost of production is quite high. We are consequently unable to charge and invoice you for each consignment and we therefore suggest you make a contribution of 100 guineas towards the cost of preparation of the monthly consignments. u We look forward to receiving your agreement to this proposal. India Office, Whitehall, LONDON S.W.l. Associated Houses : New York Montreal STY. 1050file COPt OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA t vr^ ^ Telephone — BLACKPOOL South Shore 42085. Ext. r. Any communication on this subject to be addressed to THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL, INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL and not to any individual by name. Please quote in your reply.. Cv Address for Inland Telegrams— INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL Dear Miss Odgers, 28th March, 1946. Vaccine for Bahrein. Many thanks for your letter of the 14th March, 1946. We have heard from Messrs. Thermos Ltd. who said on the 18th March that the 4 ,1ars would be sent to the Wellcome Laboratories within a few days. We have not yet heard from the Wellcome Laboratories that they have received them but I am making enquiries. Miss Odgers, External Department India Office, Y/hitehall, LONDON S.W.l..^.n, n, , , . Ill I IT }j;3ct^222yi9^6&gt; %£tk March, 19U6* Gentlaaen, • This Office has been requested by the State Medical Officer, Bahrein, (x ersian Gulf) to obtain 7 ampoules of 20 c. c. each of yellow fever vaccine monthly for the Bahrein Government ] iospital. Dr. Broom of the Wellcome Laboratories of Tropical Medicine is making the necessary arrai^jements for the supply and despatch of this vaccine, and I am to request that supplies of the vaccine may be made available, for the account of the Bahrein Government. Payment will be made by this Office on behalf of that Goverrment. I am. Gentlemen, Your obedient Servant, Messrs. Burroughs Wellcome &amp; Co;, lied Lion Square, W.C. 1.■■IV STY. B 18 'a THE WELLCOME LABORATORIES OF TROPICAL MEDICINE Telegrams : WELSCIENCE NORWEST LONDO Cablegrams : WELSCIENCE L^NOONpv^ &amp; Dear Sir, N. Hamilton Fairley, C.B.E., M.D., D.Sc., F.R.C.P., F.RJS., Director FIL • J 0 B PY D., Acting Director EXT —(S) 183-v 946 Telephone : EUSton 4688 RC »AD, LONDON, N.W.l J 25th March, 1946. J Yellow F eve r Vac cine for Bahrein. Many thanks for your letter of 22nd March enclosing the 3.O.A.O. forms of instruction for the dispatch of goods. I note that you vail inform us when you have obtained the necessary air priority for the vaccine. We shall hold the re aired amount of vaccine in readiness for your instructions. Will you please, as a matter of form, send a requisition note to Home Sales Dept., Messrs. Burroughs Wellcome &amp; Go., Red Lion Square, London, W.C.l. and mention that the arrangements for the vaccine have been made with me. L.Harrison Esq., India Office, Whitehall, 3.W.I. Yours faithfully, I.C.Broom.R.A.F. Form 1380, COPY NUMBER Serial No. AIR FREIGHT APPLICATION FORM AND WAYBILL. Air Freight Application No.: PRIORITY 4? Freight Identity Number i,-. • ■ Destination Airfield PART A DETAILS OF CONSIGNMENT.' No. of Packages Type of Packages Case Serial Numbers DESCRIPTION OF CONTENTS Package Weight (lb) Consignment Weight (lbs) Dimensions (in inches) t ii TS v a cc ^ r 6' &gt; V 1 TOTAL NUMBER TOTAL^WEIGHT OF PACKAGES CONSIGNMENT PART B CONSIGNOR’S APPLICATION FOR CARRIAGE. CONSIGNOR : V/L*. I ff**- . Consignor’s Reference Recommended Priority. Signed Date PART D FOR USE OF ACCOUNTS. SECTION I (to be completed by sponsor). Cost involved is: ^ » jtvt ‘ A. Chargeable to Funds (DEPT. GOVERNMENT, Etc.) THROUGH AIR MINISTRY (F.3 (h) ) B. Not chargeable to Government Funds but recoverable from :— Name- Address Signature of Sponsor SECTION 2 (Completed by Carrier) Amount of Charge is : ....lbs. .kilos. Rate at ...per kilo, PART C— Calling Forward Instructions The freight identity number and priority shown above must be clearly marked on each package. If there is more than one pa^laae-io the con signment each package must ad d i t i o na 11 yt beSfinf . packais mus^Yhen ^ *enr togfetl er ^Wtb I of thf FormWB8tf«*t-—* -•*^ ■ ** ■ 2 5 MAR if,■ &lt;4iiR.r\;, E Despatch Details Fit. No. : To Manifest Serial No. F ' For Use At Destination Airfield R ece i vc d' -He-.- From Manifest Ser. No. Consignee Notified PHONE/POSTAGRAM/SIGNAL. Person Informed Date and Time Init. of Informant Items Delivered NAME (Block Letters) to Signed Unit Date IMPORTANT. —In all cases where application is made in respect of 'non-entitied” freight (i.e. freight for which a charge for carriage is made) invoices for goods must accompany this form. The invoices will be forwarded to the Consignee with the consignee’s copy of Form 1380.CONDITIONS DE TRANSPORT. 1. Le transmit des merchandises est soumis aux 'Conditions Gtn&amp;rales de Transport des Merchandises' et d tous riglements particuliers du ou des transporteur(s), dont il pent etre pris connaissance d leurs bureaux de reservation, pour autant que ces conditions et reglements ne sont pas contraires aux conditions et aux stipulations visees ou spicifiSes cl-dessous. 2. Les 'Conditions Gen6rales de Transport pour le Trafic-air-fer” sont applicables aux transports combines air-fer. 3. Le “transport international” ou sens de la Convention de Varsovie du 12 octobre 1929 pour I'unification de certaines rigles relatives ou Transport Aerien International, est soumis au regime de responsabilite etabli par ladite Convention. Les expressions ‘‘Hautes Parties Contractantes” et 'Haute Partie Contractante” employees aux articles I en 28 de ladite Convention signifient les etats et les pays qui sont lids par cette Convention d la suite soit de tear ratification soit de leur adhesion. 4. Au cas ou les regies, conditions et riglements mentionnis ci-dessus, ou une clause de ces rigles, conditions et riglements relative d la responsabiliti du transporteur, seraient declaris inapplicables par le tribunal competent saisi, il est expressiment stipule que la responsabilite du transporteur sera exclue dans la mesure permise. Si / 'exoneration de responsabilite sus-visde n'etait pas reconnue, le ou les transporteur(s) beneficiera(ront) de toute limitation admise par la loi du tribunal saisi. 5. Le transporteur n'accepte pas de merchandises avec declaration spiciale d’int6r?t d la livraison. L’insertion de la valeur de la marchandise dans un but quelconque et en partie quelconque de la lettre de transport ne constiwera pas une declaration speciale d'interit d la livraison. 6. Le transporteur se riserve le droit de se substituer un ou plusiers autres transporteurs. 7. Dans le cas ou le transport est soumis aux lois britanniques, il est entendu que le(s) transporteur(s) n’est (ne sont) pas un (des) “common carrier(s)” et n'acceptent pas les obligations et la responsabilite du (des) 'common carrier(s)”. Le contrat de transport n’implique par ailleurs aucune garantie concernant I'aeronef utilisi dans le transport ni son aptitude pour le transport des marchandises qui font I’objet du contrat. CONDITIONS OF CARRIAGE, 1. Carriage of goods is subject to the “General Conditions of Carriage of Goods” and any special regulations of the carrier(s), which can be inspected at their booking offices, in so far as such conditions and regulations are not incon sistent with the conditions and provisions referred to or stated below. 2. Combined transport (air-rail) is subject to the 'General Conditions of Carriage of Goods by air and rail”. 3 “International carriage”, as defined by the Convention of Warsaw of 12th October 1929 for the Unification of Certain Rules relating to International Carriage by Air, is subject to the rules relating to liability established by the said Convention. The expressions “High Contracting Parties” and “High Contracting Party”, used in Articles 1 and 28 of the said Convention, and in the aforesaid General Conditions of Carriage, shall mean States and Territories which are bound by the said Convention either through ratification or adherence. 4 In the event of the rules, conditions and regulations stated or referred to above or any part thereof, relating to the exclusion or limitation of the liability of the carrier(s), being contrary to the law of the State or Territory In the court of which an action is brought, the liability of the carrier(s) shall be excluded or limited in so far as such law permits, and the carrier(s) shall be entitled to the benefit of every exclusion or limitation of liability permitted by such law. 5. In no case are goods accepted for carriage with a special declaration of value at delivery. The insertion of the value of goods, for any purpose, in any part of this consignment note shall not constitute a special declaration of value at delivery. 6. The right to substitute alternative carriers is reserved. 7. In all cases in which the carriage is subject to British laws it is expressly declared that the carrier(s) are not common carriers and do not accept the obligations or liability of common carriers ; nor is there implied in the contract of carriage any warranty concerning the aircraft engaged in the carriage or concerning its fitness for the carriage of the goods to which such contract relates.BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION Telegrams Telephone Telex: FLYING,' TELEX LONDON VICTORIA 2323 Ext . 145 . VICTORIA 3126 E.CTMC.476b. AIRWAYS TERMINAL. BUCKINGHAM PALACE ROAD. LONDON. S.W.1. 20th March,1946• The Secretary, India Office, External Denartment, Whitehall, S.W. For the attention of Mr. F.A.K. Harrison. Dear Sir, INSTRUCTI ONS FOR DESPATCH OF GOODS. In accordance with our telephone conversation, I am enclosing a supply of our 'Instructions for Dispatch of Goods', which should he completed and sent to us with the Penicillin and Yellow Fever Vaccine, after priority has been obtained. Yours faithfully. G. Angell for Traffic Superintendent, Europe.'^3-- INSTRUCTIONS for DISPATCH of GOODS Name Address Phone No. CONSIGNEE * * The Co..,.gnee’s Address shall be regarded as the place of destination unless instructions to the contrary are received. SENDER SENDERS C.O.D. (Words and Figures) Number of Packages Method of Packing Marks and Numbers Quantity and Nature of Goods Volume or Dimensions of Goods including packing •&lt;g- Gro Ne gm. Value for Customs /2 copies of relative\ ^invoice to be attached ) Country of Origin CHARGES for : TO BE PAID BY (Sender or Consignee) CHARGES for : TO BE PAID BY (Sender or Consignee) Freight Other charges on arrival Cartage on Departure Re-forwarding Other Charges on Departure Other Expenses C.O.D. Fees Insurance Premiums Clearance at Destination Customs Duties Cartage on Arrival Documents attached Special Conditions or Remarks : Sender’s Instructions in case of Refusal by Consignee : The Sender hereby expressly declares that the above particulars furnished by him or his agent are correct and that he is aware of and accepts the CONDITIONS OF CARRIAGE more particularly referred to on the back of this document. Declaration of value for insurance by the Carrier as Agent for the Sender (if desired) (words and figures) The Sender hereby authorizes and requests the Corporation to complete consignment notes, and other documents in connection with dispatch, carriage and delivery of the goods as agents for and on behalf of the Sender under the provisions of Article 4 para. 5 and Article 5 (3) of the General Conditions of Carriage of Goods. Date (See Back) Signature of Sender or his Agent.Form No. 251J. 94528, 'V CONDITIONS OF CARRIAGE Carriage of goods is subject to the “ General Conditions of Carriage of Goods ” and any special regulations of the carner(s), which can be inspected at their booking offices, in so far as such conditions and regulations are not incon sistent with the conditions and provisions referred to or stated below. Combined transport (air-rail) is subject to the “ General Conditions of Carriage of Goods by air and rail.' ‘‘International carriage', as defined by the Convention of Warsaw of 12th October 1929 for the Unification of Certain Rules relating to International Carriage by Air, is subject to the rules relating to liability established by the said Convention. The expressions “High Contracting Parties” and “High Contracting Party”, used in Articles I and 28 of the said Convention, and in the aforesaid General Conditions of Carriage, shall mean States and Territories which are bound by the said Convention either through ratification or adherence. In the event of the rules, conditions and regulations stated or referred to above or any part thereof, relating to the exclusion or limitation of the liability of the carrier(s), being contrary to the law of the State or Territory in the court of which an action is brought, the liability of the carrier(s) shall be excluded or limited in so far as such law permits, and the carrier(s) shall be entitled to the benefit of every exclusion or limitation of liability permitted by such law. 5. In no case are goods accepted for carriage with a special declaration of value at delivery. The insertion of the value of goods, for any purpose, in any part of this consignment note shall not constitute a special declaration of value at delivery. 6. The right to substitute alternative carriers is reserved. 7. In all cases in which the carriage is subject to British laws it is expressly declared that the carrier(s) are not common carriers and do not accept the obligations or liability of common carriers ; nor is there implied in the contract of carriage any warranty concerning the aircraft engaged in the carriage or concerning its fitness for the carriage of the goods to which such contract relates.STY.B 3 doy THE WELLCOME LABORATORIES OF TROPICAL MEDICINE N. Hamilton Fairley, C.B.E., M.D., D.Sc., F.R.C.P., F.R.S., Director J. C. Broom, M.D., Acting Director Telegrams: WELSCIENCE NORWEST LONDON Cablegrams: WELSCIENCE LONDON 183-193, EUSTON ROAD, LONDON, N.W.l Telephone: EUSton 4688 20th March, 1946 Dear Sir, re. Yellow Feve r Vaccin e As requested in your letter of 14th March, I write to inform you that we have received 4 x l/2 gallon thermos flasks for the transport of yellow fever vaccine to Bahrein. The weight of one flask with vaccine and ice is 5 lbs. Vie await your further instructions concerning the dispatch of the vaccine. Yours faithfully, ^ f. J.C.Broom. F.A.K.Harrison, Esq. , India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. /ifo trace. Zt/s 'JLP»rt 3 Part 2 Part ADVrCE NOTE To be posted to Consignee at time of des patch. The Form G.980a (Supply) MINISTRY OF SUPPLY CODE ADVICE TO CONSIGNEE OF GOODS DESPATCHED BY PASSENGER TRAIN. MINISTRY OF SUPPLY /W'G • has been requested to receive and forward Railway Company'at 1 r&gt;f- bnp rd the undermentioned goods. Station Full Name and Address of Consignor • iiam* *nu rsuaress oi &gt;_onsignor Authority for despatch (Quote contract No. if any) OQ/L /OA /[ /T T ryn Mesai's* oots Pure Dru^r ’ t± Hottf&amp;! tatlon Gt,r l-:rr° h° £ §upply ’ Collection by * GoYt./Cyntra ctor/Railway Date 37 a 1941 From Serial No. N? 203869 Stamp of Officer Authorising Carriage OTTINGHAW TO BE COMPLETED BY CONSIGNO Full Name and Address of Consignee Destination, Station and Railway No. of Packages Description and Marks of Goods WEIGHT (inclusive of packing) T. C. Q. Lbs. —^ L.ia-.ruja.i.-H A3TV-. /&amp; External P+paptwnij —India Qffiftii a irhltahi-- ^ ndon. )—— ron-iei ixiir ±n vimis //V If the Goods are received in good condition, this form is to be retained by Consignee. If the Goods do not arrive, the Railway Company must be notified in writing within 28 days of despatch. If the Goods are received in a damaged condition or are incomplete, a qualified signature should be given and the Railway Company notified in writing within 6 days of delivery. In the case of non-delivery, damage, or shortage, the report should be completed and this form sent to :—C.T. Accounts, Ministry of Supply, Melbourne House, Aldwych, London. REPORT OF DAMAGE, Ac. Goods received 194 Description of loss, damage &amp;c. Have Rly. Co. been notified ? Signature iS(MINISTRY OF SUPPLY—FORM No. 112) ISSUE VOUCHER Depot Code ... Vouehg^ 537 No '. Storekeeper must complete all items within double lines. Issued from Ministry of Supply Depot (address) .HiP W» Boots HfrUg Y..9..*. ..^td » # I sland St • 3 Not tin'loan To (Consignee) .T.Bo State. i.iedical Officer j ga^yain Government Hospital.,, Bahrain^ Arslan DESCRIPTION OF GOODS -gulf. Quantity Issued 5 x 100,000 unit vials) Penicillin ihlW Authority for l,,ue5£ S/ M^nyt Wy it i, iiC Date despatched No. of Wagon or Vehicle No. of Packages Method of transport^:.!?* tl'SLnSjDOI't and Passenger train. Consignment Note No .?..9.3..9.§ ?. 60 vials. Storekeeper’s, n ' / / initials For Headquarters use only Rate d. DUPLICATE to be completed by Consignee This copy to be sent to Con signee for receipting and return (a^* C/Store/S/Sheff HexTJSSIe, Strand. W.C.^*^ or (b) S.F.8, $.o.S., Melbourne ^j*Hbuse, Aldwych, W.C.2. (Strike out (a) or (b) as M F iieHIm applicable.) rol, Portlanfa HauW;'Toffirn'^r.'t»««#rr,''t.'W&lt;i'- Transport... Other Charges ... TOTAL ... £ Value s. Received Goods as speeded above:— Date Signature On behalf of. Ledger Posted Initials Date Folio Repayment Inventory Action taken (initials) (date) Branch Signature -/ &lt;£e&gt;6) Air Booking Centre, (Freight Control), 52 Haymarket, LONDCN, S. W. 1. Ref: I^TC/HAr/11. 15 th March, 1946. Dear Harrison, Thank you for your letter of the 14th March, 1946. In accordance with your request, arrangements have been made for this Office to telephone Miss Odgers as soon sis the traffic is required. Officer in Charge, Air Booking Centre (Freight Control)• Mr Harrison, India Office, Y/hitehall, LONDON, 3.W.1.file copy r , OFFICE OF THE HIGH CO IMISsjfoNER 121 f Te/ep/iow—B lackpool South Shore 42085. Ext.....’ Any communication on this subject to be addresfyt THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL^ INDIA ST^R^ DEPARTMENT, and not to any individual by name. ^ ' Please quote in your reply....^..*..5..?P..?Z.'k5 '‘I--* Your i ' 1302/46. ID! A T Address for Inland Telegrgmx — *1 Q Bl^ACKK)OL ’dtO-\ Oil TMENT, ^L^^OOL. 12th March, 1946. Dear Harrison, With regard to your letter dated 22nd February, 1946 about supply of yellow fever vaccine to the Bahrein Government Hospital we have ordered from Messrs. Thermos (1925) Ltd. four ^--gallon vacuum jars and they have promised to deliver these to the Wellcome laboratories immediately. The only question that now remains to be settled is the despatch by air, about which Jenkin wrote to Miss Odgers on the 6th March. Yours F.A.K. Harrison Wsq., India ffice, Whitehall, LONDON S.W.l.Mr. Hi w 1 a/}- tt, b . ' lPi^ £ i' 10 rf -^ Behave--oene raary telephone calls I have, I hope, established some sort of procedure for obtaining priority for the penicillin and yellow fever vaccine for Bahrein. The stages appear to be;- (1) fe fill in form 1380, state only what the consignment consists of; the consignor and the consignee, to whom it is chargeable and the sponsor's signature. It is not necessary to enclose a copy of the invoice. Six cor)ies of this form are then sent to Mr. J.D. Wake ling. Room 305 Ariel House, (Holbom 343*1- Bxt. 1372) who will attach an FOB Ho. (2) In the case of the penicillin the normal procedure will be followed and the consignment will be duly called forward in its' turn. (3) In the case of the vaccine the Air Freight Control (Sq.Ldr. Barnes* Section, 32 Haymarket ^ . . 'Tliitehall 710^) will ring us up when the forms ^ reach them and give us the FOB Hfo. in order that we may tell the Wellcome Institution to send the vaccine to BOAC and warn BOAC that it is coming, giving thanat the same time the FOB No. Apparently this will obviate any delay. I from Miss Short (Dr. BootSecretary at the Wellcome Institution, Telephone No. Buston 4638, Bxb.2) that the Wellcome Institution can supply the vaccine but that the thermos flasks have not yet arrived. She promised to ring me up as soon as they were delivered, we■■■■■■■■■ I 'V \ roust then find out from her the weight of the flask + vaccine and ice. She confirmed that the Wellcome Institution should be given on the forms as the consignor and agreed to the procedure as outlined in (3) above. Mr. angel of BQAC (Victoria 2323, iixt. 145) to whom I also spoke, considers it a great pity that we were not able to get priority covering thisemonthly consignments over a considerable period. He considers, however, that the present arrangements should work smoothly once the routine has been established. With regard to the packet of penicillin at present in this room he says that it is no use sending it to Airways House until we have the JOB No. I gat hated, from him that an HCB No. is a sort of abracadabra hy which mountains may be moved. — iUW I hope this procedure will in fact prove wglccifte. Draft letters are below confinning ny telephone conversations and I hope, tying everything up satisfactorily. o. H /3.» ^V-; - IHiiJT LZTTJR Squadron Leader Barnes, Air Freight Control,. 52, Haymajrket 4 ' S, ?I.f . ^ 14 ^ 4. i:&gt;- I • Dear Barnes, c. •_ /. : I understand that Miss Qdgers of this Department spoke to a member of your Department recently on the telephone about securing -» c • v. air priority for monthly consignments of yellow fever vaccine for the Bahrein Govemirent Hospital, Bahrein, Persian Gulf e , , . QiO/l As the vaccine is to travel in thermos flasks and to he kept at an even temperature v/e are anxious that there should he as little delay as possible in calling it forward for despatch. We should he grateful, therefore, if someone in your department could ring up Miss Odgers (Whitehall 8-140, Bxt. 284)# as soon as you received your copy of fomy 1 'IMBM form 1380, in order that we may warn the suppliers. The Wellcome Institution, to have the vaccine ready, and tell BO^C to expect it. Yours sincerely, A. K. HARRISON.uRaPT LETTER '°) The and Cargo Officeij, B.O. A.C ., Airways Houae. \ 4 uif • l &gt; * o oMi*JUcrv-&gt;, rt'* Dear Sir, With reference to ny letter No. Ext.1397/46 of 27 th Februaiy regarding the carriage of monthly consignments of penicillin and yellow fever vaccine to the State Medical Officer, Bahrein Government Hospital, Bahrein, we have ascertained that export licences are not required for either of these drugs. ^Unfortunately the Ministry of Civil Aviation have not been able to grant priority for thisemonthly consignments over a period of time,and fresh \ v priority will have to be obtained for each consignment. With regard to the vaccine v/hich you will remember is to be kept atS&gt;Er-J^^==: a -cartain tenrperature^ the Ministry of Civil Aviation have informed us that they have arranged for it to be sent direct to Airways Terminal and not to lyneham Air Port. ?/e are writing to the suppliers, the 'iVellcome Institution asking thou to send the Thermos flasks ( when they are ready and priority lias been granted, to your Cargo Section in Buckingham Palace Road. With regard to the penicillin we are assuming that the normal procedure will be jorofcrrea and that on receipt of the necessary forms you will arrange with Messrs. Boots of Station Street, Nottingham, direct about delivery to the Air Port. We have, however, one packet of//'X of i^enicillin which has been sent to this Office. We shall be forwarding this to your when we know the jjOB Yours faitrifully, &amp; A. K. . In,PRISON■r would let us know when you receive them in order that we may complete the necessaiy forms to obtain air priority for the consignment* Could you at the same time let us know the approximate weight of the flasks when full? As soon as we have obtained priority, which I fear will have to be done afresh for each consignment ,we will let you know and we should be grateful if you would then send the vaccine, addressed to the State Medical Officer, Bahrein, Government Hospital, to the Cargo Section, Air,7ays House, Buckingham Palace Road. Should there 'by any difficulty about this, perhaps you would be £pod enough to get in touch with Mr. Angel of the BOAC, telephone No, Victoria 2323, Ex*. 143. Arrangements have been made with BOAC for ice/Your Ref. Our Ref. ETC/8fe9 Tel. No, ESN Miss Odgers, X am enclosing a copy of a letter I have received from the Kxport Licensing Branch with reference to our recent telephone conversation regarding the export of penicillin to the Bahrian Ckjvernment Hospital, You will see from this that no export licence is necessary,as the penicillin in question is Government property, and is being exported by a Government Department. Yours sincerely. Miss M. Odgers, India Office, King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.I.FILL €5' (COPY) BOARD OP TRADE, Export Licensing Branch, 4 Penchurch Avenue, EID. 666 / 4/41 (Hc/aO London, E.C.3. 6 th March, 1946 Dear Elliott, The reply to your letter of 2nd March about exports of penicillin is as follows:- Your statement that 'Penicillin and its salts &amp;c*' is on the Export Control List is correct, but if the actual exporter of these goods is a Government Department, e.g, yourselves, the requirement of an export licence is waived. If, however, the producers of the material, for example, Glaxo, export penicillin at your request and under your authority, an export licence would be required, but would, in these circumstances, be issued provided that your sanction of the export was apparent. If exports of this latter kind have been made, I must express some surprise that Customs have not raised any query about the matter. Yours sincerely. C,A, Elliott, Esq,, Ministry of Supply, Penicillin Production Control, Portland House, Tothill Street, S.W.l.1 / DRAFT D.J, Wakeling, Fsq«, Room 305, llinistiy of Civil Aviation, % Ariel House. 14 MAR 1346 Dear 7/akeling, Will you please refer to your letter of 6 ioarch regarding the antahl-i^hm^ t, of Yellow Fever vaccine and penicillin to the Bahrein Government Hospital, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. I understand that Miss Odgers of this Department arranged with you over the telephone recently that R.A.F. fom 1330 should be filled in in this Office with details of the consignment, consignor and consignee and should be sent to you^and that in the case of the vaccine ±s to be kept at a n temperature/, you will endeavour to ensure that itgalled forward with the least possible delay.I enclose the forms to cover one packet of penicillin which has been delivered to this Office for onward transmission to Bahrein. undent and that BO Ail will be ablj; to carry it as s/on as yore-have- a:iT ti i^uri for thrai-neoosaary 7/e should be grateful tteoreforo if you would let us know the KJB Ho. as soon as possible so that we may inform BOAC of it when we send over the racket to Airways Terminal. Wit Qnjocac&amp;HLttt *JjJL 0*. Cojh, dg l^e . Vie o^c aj&gt;$UAnj I assume that in sufficient for us to send ov^r^'forms di completed in respect of^the x je nic)ill:Ln. towards v x^ &lt;JU&gt;rS ^ ^ ^he end oi every month and that BOAC *»vill arrangea n*.odoAy, with iiessrs. Boots for its delivery to the air fidd. VM ^ v ' •cut CieojY ajltJU, 4o«ot 7e sha^lr not or course be in a position to give the '&lt;f 9M- f e ^ r ' otc^fly exarct weightand measure me nt of the packet • g~rl%aZ' ct^-u^o^rrJs Yours sincerely, *j?iow ^rcx^rJud 'So/e^c ■ &gt; ■ n&gt;j&gt; : F. A. IK ‘ M ' * /v ^»vwv eJUratdL- afi )£*, a^QoJL- ft -oA«ri ^&lt;xcAJL‘ I i*. &lt;£jtJLuLXjc«j£Tel. No. HOLBORN 3434, Ext FILE COPY a \9) MINISTRY OF CIVIL AVIATION, ARIEL HOUSE, STRAND, LONDON, W.C.2. 6 th March, 1946 Dear Harrisoh, V/ith reference to your letter of the 5th instant addressed to Herbertson regarding the dispatch of certain drugs to Bahrein, I regret it is not possible for B.O.A.C* to deal direct vvith the suppliers. It is essential, at least for the present, that the usual forms 15&amp;0 (application for air freight) are used in all cases to ensure priority. Arrangements have however been made that when the freight is called forward for carriage it is f delivered direct to B.O.A.C. at Airways Terminal and not as is customary send to Lyneham Airport. This should result in the saving of several days in the dispatchiig; of the freightage concerned. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street, S. W. 1.DRAFT LiSTESR J.L. Jenkin, Esq., India Store Department, Blackpool. /L * ■_ MAR 1946 Dear C'enkin, Will you please refer to your letter tn ' of 6th March^ reference S .5202/45 JLJ ^regarding the despatch of yellow fever vaccine to Bahrein. We have Been in touch with BOAG who are prepared to cariy the vaccine and to arrange for additional ice to be inserted in the themos flasks en route. We have also arranged V . with the iiinistiy of Civil aviation fer the issue of/priorities dr.-r -Hn-io ^^^4- The Wellcome Institution tell us, however, that they have not yet received the thermos flasks/FIL i flRHk * ** ^ ^'* oviu»v/“ OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA Telephone BLACKPOOL South Shore 42085. Ext. .1.7 • Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — » Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL and HOt to anv indn'idunl hv Msima THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL, INDIA STORE DEPARTMElSr, ; BLACKP( f Dear Miss Odgers, Yellow Fever Vaccine for Bahrein. I notice in a letter from Mr. Harrison to the Mail and Cargo Officer, B.O.A.C. (India Office Hef. Hxt. 1397/46 dated 27th February, 1946) that you may be by now in a position to let us know whether the supply of the Vaccine and its despatch by air have now been arranged. Would .-you kindly let me know in due course what lias been done.** Yours sincerely Miss Odgers, External Department, India Office, Whitehall, LONDON S.W.l.liiTOt l, I jl+b* D«ar ilcrbcrtson, if ould you pie ^se refer to ny letter to Jones, HomiixtmJSy/J^, Qi tiie 4^1 Pehru^ixy regarding tlie despatcii by air freight of monthly oonsi^Baents of penicillin and yellow fever v ccdne to the State nodical Officer at the B hrein ikjvumnient Hoepit^tl, B hroiiu I understocki fron Jones* reply diited 5th February th t you were arr-n ( :ing with BC^C to c rry -hose drugs and tha-*, they would ri' dee the detailed itiTungeoents with the suppliers direct. Vl e Have since b^en in touch with BUkC who amfim tlxat they are ready to o .rry ttiese consignments awi to make tAio detailed arr^aigcrients with the suppliers direct with rqgurl to delivery, etc. It appears however that it is nooei: »iry for BOaC to obtain priority x'or the consignments from the inisxry of Civil vlation. e understand from your ei&gt;.Lrtnent t -.at the norntil procedure woult be for this Office to submit form of .^-liaxticn for priority to your epartawtt in respect of tjaoh sep:xx*ate parcel as it cooes forward. I trust th t it will be possible for sohkj siiapler procedure than tnio to bo op ;lied in the case of these irugs since v/e can certify in advance th t priority is necessary for each monthly ceneigoaent and deliver^' of the vaccine, which has to be kept ut a oonstiint .espenture in thermos flasks, cannot be held Uj.;. ince the drugs are urr;ently re'^uirt^ in b iirein, I should b v&lt;Jiy grateful if you v/ould let me knee as u;cm ..vs ix&gt;i;sible how you su^^jest t*xe dif iculty reg jriing pricrily can best be overaorae so that we cun tell the suppliers and BO lC to go ahOc vd. fours sincerely. Captain .J. . erbertoon, C. • i F. A. K. HARRISONII* EENICILLIN JRODUCTIOfc CqaBOIw ofisupply Your Ref . 14 ® nd House, STREET, WESTMINST|R, S.W.I 194% ' J 26th February, 1946. WMV. ■ £ \ Telephone : Abbey 7788 Sxtj110. Telegraphic Address : Splycontra, Wire, London Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to :— THE SECRETARY, and the following number quoted 325/PENAU y4 ~^&gt;l| .. , r' v &gt; f »•/ y vi Dear air, r f \ TV, i* A0l / f yl 4*s*t*~z* CH*~ • •• I am enclosing a copy of letter from the State Medical Officer,Bahrain, together witl^y a copy of our reply. The Penicillin in question is forwarded in monthly consignments addressed for delivery to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain G-overnment Hospital,Bahrain, Persian Gulf and is packed in outer coverings addressed to you. presumably the cost of air freight is at present borne by your Department ( but perhaps you would be good enough to inform the State Medical Officer direct of the arrangement in force. ;u Yours faithfully, &lt; 2 -. for Assistant Controller. Mf.H arris on, External Department, -V India Office, / _ , . Whitehall, L ondon, S .W. Ip * 2T r ' jtt i j x €- 4-OFfi2^n HMV. PMIGILLIN FiiODUCTXQN COffrHQLi i3rt:110* f Copy. fw: Mr t ^ri l lai rrm&amp;u' 1454 325/mTA^* 26th February, 19 Aj6 # thank you for your letter ITo.47/33/65 dated 16th February,194^ and are pleased to hear that you are receiving the oonaignments of Penioillin in good order. We also tiianic you for the cheque for 2133 ( Pounds one hundred and thirty three only), for which a fomial receipt will be forwarded to you at a later date. The Penicillin in question is being forwarded each month to Mr• Harrison, £xtema 1 Department, India Office, -hitehall,London, S.W.l. for despatch onward to you and the sum of £133 does not(therefore,include the cost of air freight as this charge is not borne by this Ministry. e are,however, writing Mr.Harrison on the matter and doubtless you will hear from him in due course. Yours faithfully, for Assistant Controller. The State edioal Officer, Bahrain Government Hospital Bahrain, Persian &lt; ulf. ir *t Our Ref; Your Ref: No. 47/33/65. 325/Pen/75 1454 948 Gov 3 Bah ? I 6 t 1 jmment - Hospital ain, Persian Gulf, February, 19-4^ • The .. oretary, Penioillin Production Control Ministry of Supply, Portland House, Tothill Street, London,3«W#l« Dear Sir, Re; Penioillin - Bahrain , I am exceedingly grateful to you for your regular consignments which are arriving all in good order. I enclose a cheque for £1^3 (Pounds one hundred and thirty three only) in settlement of the first six months' supply. When you acknowledge the receipt, I w&gt;uld be obliged if you would inform nie whether this account includes the air mail freightage. Yours truly. Sgd. R.K*B*SN0Y7 State Medical Officer Bahrain.3235 A.G B. 20m 10.45. hle copy OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR. INDIA. Telephone — Blackpool South Shore 42085 . Ext.. Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL, It \p INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT,^ BLACKPOOL. and not to any individual by name. Please qi ■ in your reply 1 •'• r'' . '''I 1 ' • Your ref. 1 17 —' r7 T •*Atldms for I * - - -JLNDIA 1 od r A-r inland Telegrams — JEN, BLACKPOOL. 22nd February,1946, Dear Harrison, Supply of Yellow Fever Vaccine to Bahrein, With reference to your letter of the 2nd February, 1946, we have ascertained from the Wellcome Laboratories of Tropical Medicine that they can supply the Yellow Fever Vaccine if we provide the vacuum flasks. It was intimated to us that you had suggested four as a suitable number and v;e are, tnerexore, ' ' ordering four ^-gallon 'THHHMOS' brand vacuum jars from Messrs. Thermos (1925) Ltd. They are available immediately and we are asking Messrs. Thennos Ltd. to deliver them to the Wellcome Laboratories as soon as possible. The cost of these jars will be £5. 5. 0. in all. The Wellcome Laboratories say that they are proposing to charge for the Vaccine but that they have not yet worked out the cost. The first batch of Vaccine can be supplied as soon as the vacuum flask is ready. The Wellcome Laboratories point out that all transport arrangements must be undertaken by the consumer and t this entails the addition of fresh ice to the container whe^Sv necessary en route. I do not know whether the Air Transport Authorities realise that the provision of ice may be Will you take up the matter with them and see ^nece.ssiiry. !t Ov X x whetHe£\the necessary arrangements could be made. V\ 'V ^ -j! if the consumer has to make transport arrangements Vv it fallows that the cost will also have to be borne by /Will you pleas Harrison Fsq., India Office, ^ &gt; •' W hit ehall, S.W.1.i.ill you please say what arrangements you are making about transport and where delivery of the Vaccine should be made. I notice that your letter dated the 4th February,1946 to Major II.Jones mentions penicillin but I presume that you are making the necessary arrangements about that. « »v- -\ 'ioV ft X EXT 1324 y Government of 10 46 , ~T!E WLE copy W~, 0' Ha#'- NDIA, ARJMENT, EXPRESS LETTER [iV, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sane telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, until the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fbom Political Agent, Bahrain. I India Office, London. #*0/175. Dated the 13th February , Reference correspondence ending with your Letter No. Fxt., 5040/45 da t ed the Grateful if you could let me know the air freight charges on penicillin parcels sent to Bahrain for the State Medical Officer, Bahrain. Sd/- A.C.GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. S. 6. MFP—120G S&amp;P—(51-1723)—4-2-36—200,000.Tel. No. HOLBORN 3434, Ext. PILE : o;.v 926 ! 946 ;try of civil aviation, ARIEL HOUSE, U. STRAND, l? /*M LONDON, W.C.2. ^ 5th February, 1946 Dear Harrison, This will acknowledge your letter of the 4th February (Ext, 7b Z/^6J—about the conveyance by B.O.A.C. of small monthly consignments of penicillin and yellow fever vaccine to the State Medical Olficer at the Bahrein Government; Hospital, Bahrein. Herbertson is arranging for to be instructed to cariy these smaLL monthly parcels and.to get into direct touch with Boots with a view to making the necessary detailed arrangements. Yours sincerely, F.A.K. Harrison, Bsq., India Office, King Charles Street, London, S.W.1. SSSfl. PCI. kpt. j r-p 10/1 c / c\kFricE)I* t ;;.t. 787/46. 05.0. ♦A I’obraar/, 19^f6. Dear Jones, We have been asked to arrange on beholl' of the Bahrein Govemnent for the despatch b/ air of . iontliiy consi/^rments of penicillin and yellow fever vaccine to the State Medical Officer at the Bahrein Government hospital, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. This request has our support and we regard it as important that it should be met. 2. The penicillin, which is supplied by Pessrs. Boots Pure Drug Company Limited, Island Street, Nottiiigliam, is in x^ackets weighing about 12 lbs. The yellow fever vaccine, which is needed for the inoculation of air passengers leaving Bahrein, is to be supplied by the .ellcaie lesoarch Institution, 18^, Just on load, i!. V. 1, this will iiave to be carried a half- gallon hier ios ilasks ich we ai'e arra - Ll to oht iiru The Therv.ios flas s, when empty will have to be returned from Bahrein by air in a shuttle-service. 3* he should be most grateful if you would arrange with the ooupetent air transport authorities for these drugs to be transported by air each month. It would be preferable if the suppliers could send the parcels direct to the transport authorities. The cost of transport is recoverable fro; the Bahrein Government, and tills might most conveniently be included b t/ tiie suppliers in their accounts to the Bahrein Government. Major .Jones, Jfi,B.h., Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, ..C.2 . Yours sincerely, F. A. K. HARRISONDraft Paper. Department.f (im &amp; )■ ' EjLIt .Departx-ent. I have discussed with the Wellcome | ,^ Institute who can supply, and ffj±3b~send the necessary instructions to Bahrein, The vaccine would have to go by air in £ gallon Thermos flasks, as used by air crews. t As B,0,A,C. call at Bahrein I imagine there would be no difficulty in transport. It would,however, be necessary to purchase for the Wellcome Institute four £ gallon Thermos flasks, which are unobtainable except through Service channels. '\ Prom: Secretary of State for India. To: Political Agent, Bahrein. Repeated to: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. no. ext.5owA5. 10D£C]945 Reference my express letter No. EXT.5040/45 of 17th November, 3 further parcel containing penicillin for the Bahrein Government Hospital is forwarded herewith by arTairmail bag since it is understood that the penicillin is urgently required. It is suggested that in the case of future consignments the Bahrein Government should ask the manuf acturerc to make their own arrangements for forwarding. F. A. K. HARRISONEXT.5040/45 / 6 ’ c O December, 1945* Dear Sirs, I am desired to acknowledge receipt of a package containing penicillin for despatch to the Bahrein Government together with a letter enclosing the issue voucher for the package. Yours faithfully. Messrs. Boots Pure Drug Go. t Ltd*, Island Street, Nottingham. (V&gt; A 1C. HARRISONAZH/*m 325/Pen/75 PEKICIUilK PTODOCTIC* OCTROI,, @ A c^L^k b h )^ fOth ^eceiiibei* f 1945. iiear Sir, Penicillin inference to your letter of the 24th October and a co^y of that letter datea 24th hoveaber, 1 have to advise you that initial arrangements have been made for monthly deliveries of Penicillin to be .^ade as requested. The first delivery was made on the 12th November through the India Office for onwards transmission by air mail. A Provisional Invoice amounting to -^ in respect of the first six months supply^ is enclosed and we should be glad to receive payment through the has tern Bank, Bahrain, in London. A Provisional Invoice for the subsequent six months supply will be sent to you in due course. Yours faithfully, '-so.) A. G. ROOT for Assistant Controller* The Btate Medical Officer, Bahrain Government hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf.fi * ADVICE NOTE To be posted to Consignee at time of des patch. Form G.930a (Supply) MINISTRY OF SUPPLY CODE ADVICE TO CONSIGNEE OF GOODS DESPATCHED BY PASSENGER TRAIN. Serial No. has been requested to receive and forward Railway Company at tlillflllMM d the undermentioned go&amp;s ' “ N? 203637 JWl 7/a, Full Name and es* of Consijnor Messrs. Boots Pure Drug Co* Ltd., Station Streep HOti inghaza • Authority for despatch . (Quote contract No. if any) /fi/QQg Full Name and Address of Consignee Destination, Station and Railway No. of | Description and Marks of Goods Packages i WEIGHT (inclusive of packing) T. C. Q. Lbs. -Mxu- Jtex 1 laon*. -Londoa S.w.l.- | 11 . /t/n, genlclilln (Cal clum Salt) invials* 44— — $ (f the Goods are received in good condition, this form is to be retained by Consignee. r as ^ _ If the Goods do not arrive, the Railway Company must be notified in writing within 28 days of despatch. . . ^ j . .t / .V. , . / / . If the Goods are received in a damaged condition or are incomplete, a qualified signature should be given and the Railway Company notified in writing Within • days of dellvenr. In the case of non-delivery, damage, or shortage, the report should be completed and this form sent to C.T. Accounts, Ministry of Supply, Melbourne House, Aldwych, London, W.C.2. REPORT OF DAMAGE, &amp;c. Goods received 194 Description of loss, damage &amp;c. : i. 1 Have Rly. Co. been notified f Signature -154—Glaxo Laboratories ltd. GREENFORD MIDDLESEX YOUR REFERENCE PLEASE ADDRESS REPLY TO Export Department TELEPHONE: BYRON 3434- TELEGRAMS : Glaxothe, London CODE New Standard, Bentleys 15th November,1945 Mr. Harrison, External Department, India Office, Vvhltehall, Sdu.l* Dear Sir, Vi/e have sent forward by road this morning one package of Penicillin for despatch by air to Bahrein and we much regret we omitted to enclose the issue Voucher with the parcel. ■ L his is now attached hereto for your attention. The parcel is addressed to you. Yoir s faithfully QIAXG LABORATORIES LTD...•rtOg sxT^mL de tjmzm LEm^i (mhjaxl) jftpctt* Sooretary of State far India To* Political Agent, I-xhrain, repeated to Political ite&amp;ident in the Persian GuSUT* 2&gt;a±cdt /q &amp; emsiber, 1%5* Ext*504iV^5« Copiea as:© cnclOBed of India Office letter to Dr. mow, n'o.E. •0*9 513/1 dated l?th Jotober, 1%3» regarding supply of penicillin to Bahrein Govenssent Medical Department* Ae no order has sgparently been placed wi^i Director of Medical Supolies it eecme that original may not have reached Dr. mow before he left thia country. I should,therefore,^ glad if a copy could now be traaamitted to him. tfvL 2. &gt;r. maw also asked tha^tpenicillin ahould be sent by air mail. Bahrein Gevemaent will no doubt anange this . tlie -selvoa when placing order# I’h© issue of the above has been duly authorised* M f. A. K. HARRISON— 4*r\ - I find that the position on the 'penicillin was set out in a letter from Mr. France to the Chief Medical Officer, Bahrein. I am sorry a copy was not sent to you before but I nov/ attach one for your information. 10COPY. E.&amp; 0. 90373/1. INDIA OFFICE, 4, Central Buildings, Matthew ^arker Street, London, 17th October, 1945. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 24 th September addressed to Lieutenant General Sir E.W.C. Bradfield with regard to the supply of 750 vials annually of Penicillin for the Bahrain Government, Medical Department, I am directed to inform you that the Director of Medical Supplies, Ministry of Supply, is prepared to make this quantity available for the Medical Department, Bahrain Government, subject to the receipt by him of a firm order for the quantity required. An order should accordingly be placed immediately with the Director of Medical Supplies, with whom arrangements for payment etc. should also be made. The address is The Director of ^edical Supjdies, -““inistry of Supply, Portland House, Tothill Street, ^.W.1. and your letter should be marked 'for the attention of Mr. Johnson.” Eat f07 I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) R.E. France, for Secretary, Economic &amp; Overseas Department. R.H.B. Snow, Bsq., Chief Medical Officer, Bahrain, Princes Court Hotel, Prince of Wales Terrace, Kensington, London, W. 8 .o}3 A letter has been sent to the Ministry of Supply with reference to the enquiry from the Bahrain Government Hospital about supplies of Penicillin. I -will let you know the answer as soon as it is received. I have retained a. copy-of .the letter and £# General Bradfield’s recommendation. ftdw, CeM MnuJ ^ ^ ^ tUf mJl) i*J iU 100 vJi &gt;( 100,ow tA &lt;*M k MftlAlt ^ U»*J 1.0, (*■ lUf ^ PH ^ ' r M/wr Mr. Gleory # eternal Affairs Departios: V \ • -y • v ■ : ^ recommend the attached application' from the Gliief Medical Officer, Bahiaiin Govermaent, for 750 vials of Penicillin and it should be supported. Will you please take necessary action v/ith the Ministry of Supply (Directorate of Medical Supplies). (Sgd.) E.W.C.Bradfield. Medical Aaviser. 24.9*1945. 2.cic 0. Secretary. Will you kindly take this up with the Ministry of Supply? We are, of course, in agreement with General Bradfield^ recommendation. J.P.F. 27/9As from Bahrain Gwemc^ent Hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf, 2Ath September 1945# . Lieut,-General Sir E.W.G.Bradfield, KCIE., Office, | Whitehall, London S,W,1, Dear Sir, Re: 750 vials Penicillin annupljLy -- f or the Bahrain Gove ri urgent 1 ^ :,^edical Depai^tment In accordance with our recent conversation regarding Penicillin for Bahrain, I would much appreciate your help in authorising this order through the usual political channels in order that the Ministry of Supply can then deal with it. It is requested that the Penicillin be sent out in quarterly installments, and as a regular annual order of 750 vials, each 100000 units. Burroughs Wellcome &amp; Go. Thanking you, (Sgd.) R.H.B.Snow. Chief Medical officer, Bahrain. Princes Court Hotel, Prince of Wales Terrace, Kensington, London v.8.Aj (M No. tj/f. -19/235. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in t compliments to p.z. 820 \ m « li t m 1939 e Persian Gulf presents his His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India, The India Office, Londo n. v/ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s), for favour of disposal. British Consulate-Geueral, BUSHIRE. Dated..2.4tn, Janua ry. X93 9 . Reference to previous correspondence : Pr i -n-*- ^ ■» c ?r .31-13/235 , dated tne 19 til January, 193 9, from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire, to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. 1. Memorandum No.66-6/43 of the 16th January, 1939, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Indent for medical equipment for the Bahrain Government Hospital. 2. Enclosures to (1) above. LS ' M /!/ ^ V ' 6F£ s/aj9 'N. Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain-6/43. To Political Agency, j Bahrain, the 16th January 1939 P.Z. 1939 The Secretary to tSe HonMble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. Reference correspondence resting with my memorandum No. 17 dated the 8th January 1939. Medical equipment for Bahrain Government. 2. I enclose copies of letters Nos. 1940 and 2034 dated the 26th December 1938 and 10th January 1939 respectively,from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, with copies of the enclosures thereto. 3. Referring to the second of these two letters; lists Nos. 1 and 2 have been sent in by the Bahrain Government on one list, headed “additions to general list of hospital equipment**. The list referred to in the last paragraph of this letter is that headed “details of equipment for Government Hospital**. 4. The Bahrain Government request that their require ments may be obtained as expeditiously as possible. Su/- H. ifeightman Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. 3d/- J.B. Howes Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.Ho. 1940-10. Bahrain, Dated 26th December, 1938. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, ISsquire, C.B.iS., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. cH -r* &gt; I have the honour to enclose herewith six copies of an indent for laboratory equipment required for the new government hoapitaj. and to request you to kindly obtain them at fav^irable rates tlirough the good offices of the India rtore Department. The list V'-as compiled from the priee list of Messrs. Chas. Bearson &amp; Company Limited, Willow $alk, Bermondsey, London, 1. The cost of the equipment is approximately £ 150. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd/- C.Dalrymple Belgrave. Adviser to the GovernmentTrue Copy From No. 2034-10 Bahrain. 19th Dul ^ad,1357 Dated, 10th January, 1939. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Fsquire, C.B.S., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To K. 3, M t s Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Sir, I have the honour to forward a further list of requirements for the Government Hospital inc luding : - 1. A small amount of additional general equipment, value about £ 60/-. 2. Gynaecological and obstetrical instru ments required by the lady-doctor tc be purchased fro t Messrs. Allen b H&amp;nburys, London, B.C.2; approximate value £ 105/-. 3. Anaesthetic equipment to be obtained from Messrs. Chas. King &amp; Co., London, W.l; approximate value £ 150/-. With regard to the general equipment, I am happy to leave the selection of the majority of the supplies to the discretion of the Indian Stores Department, but in the case of the more elaborate equipment, owing to the diversity of types on the market, 1 should be obliged if the apartment would consult me directly before finally placing the . *^ q orders. For their assistance, I enclose a list C? of the more elaborate equipment vith details and I shall be obliged if you will forward it to them with the enclosed orders. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd/- C.Dalrymple Belgrave. Adviser to the Government. Enclos:- B.3.(m) - 3 - 1 x Pelvimeter, Martini, Stainless Steel, Fig*3462. 1 x Pelvimeter, Collin’s, Fig.No.3460. 1 x Simpson’s Perforator, Fig.No.3472. 1 each left and right Perineum Needles, Fig.No.3479* 3 x Boxes Obstetric Sutures, Fig.No.3482. x Willett’s Forceps, Placenta-Praevia, stainless steel, Fig.No.3486. 1 x Publiotomy Needle, Fig.No.3487. 2 Giglis Saws, 50 cm. Fig.No.4189. 1 set Handles for above, Fig.No.4191. 2 x Stethoscopes, Pinard’s, aluminium, Fig.No.3488. 1 packet Perineum Needles, , Fig.No.3480. 1 x Mucous Catheter, Fig.No.3448. 1 x Kidney Pedicle Clamp Forceps, Fig.No.2979. 1 x Female Cystoscope, 10 mm. Fig.No.2338. 1 x female Bladder Sound, Fig.No.2941. 1 Set of 8 Heywood Smith’s Uterine Dilators, Stainless Steel in Pouch. 1 x Junker’s Inhaler, Fig.No.290. 3 x Mouth Gags, Fig.No.421. 2 each two sizes Airways, Fig.No.481. 3 x Tongue forceps, Fig.No.515* 1 x Laban’s Anaesthetic Syrine, Fig.No.539* Uterine Packing Forceps stainless steel as supplied to) The Jessop Hospital for Women. 13/6 pair, x 6 Colporrhaph^ Speculum, Hospital for Vi omen. As supplied to the Jessop 15/0 each. 1.Anaesthetic Equipment From Messrs. Chas. King, Devonshire St.* ~ Operating Theatre Devonshire table plate glass shelves &amp; drawer 1 - aSAGXLL vTT/ , complete with bag mount with 'on” and 'off” stopcock, bag, net, corrugated tube, expiatory valve, facepiece angle, aseptic facepiece and catheter mount 1 - SET BOYLE * S BOTTLES with hotameters for 0 2 N 2 Oand C0 2 . Small chloroform and large ether bottles, Ana water jacket. 1 - ADAM’S 0 2 DEDUCING VALVE, with tank pressure gauge. 2 - f DAM’S h 2 0 REDUCING V LVES, without taps, but with gauges. 1 - ADAM’S C0 2 DEDUCING VALVE. 1 - rOHEGGEH TYPE DDDCUHIAL MABOMETED &amp; SAi F.TY V LVE. 1 - UNIVERSAL KEY S ABNER. 1 - C0 2 Absorption Circuit for Boyle’s Bottles, comprising, soda lime stopcock with rebreathing bag abd gravity directional valves, soda lime canister, corrugated breathing tubes, ”Y” piece with expiratory valve, facepiece angle and large aseptic facepiece. Dental &lt;$ 0. . unit 1 - Floor plate to accomodate 2 x 200 gall. N 2 0 type 8 cylinders Double union 1 - Single union 1 - Two gallon gas bag, vulcanite connection, rubber tubing &amp; gas mount. 1 - Karn Nasal inhaler, with tubing Etc., for dental work , t - Gas bag with 3-way stopcock tubing Etc., for g'tveral O.i . use Miscellaneous 2 - Cylinder keys. 20 - Yards spare tubing. 12 - Face pieces : assorted sizes (air-filling). 1 - Endotracheal adapter. 1 - Doz. Endotracheal tube connections. 2 - Doz. Endotracheal tubes (assorted sizes).DETAILS OF EQUIPMENT FOR GOVERNMENT HOSPITAL. ( Eqpt: already ordered) 1. Operation Table with the following accessories Lithotomy Stirrups, Douche funnel, Anaesthetic screen, Shoulder rests, Arm-rests, Sponge mattress. Adjustable and with oil-pump lift. Similar to A. &amp; II.'s St. Bartholomew’s pattern table type A. All furniture. Aluminium finish (except where otherwise stated). Chromium-plated fittings. Unbreakable glass. The measurements given need not be adhered to exactly, but as nearly as possible. 3. Operation theatre lamp. Shadowless Minimum diameter 28 n , Telescopic Suspension , Emergency bulbs similar to K.B.B. lamp Code LUX. sterilisers : One large horizontal High-pressure Steriliser, • size approx. 20' diam. 36' depth. Oil burner-heated. Similar to Messrs. Thackray’s No.3281 Type 0. 2. Two Sets of water Sterilisers capacity 5-8 gallons. Electrical heating :- consumption should not exceed 5 K.&lt;V. each. Similar to Messrs. Thackray’s No.3269. 3. Two bowl-sterilisers, electrically heated size approx. 24' x 20' x 20'. Electrical heating - current consumption 10 K.W. Similar to Thackray’s No.3244 E. 4. Two instrument sterilisers for theatres size approx. 20' x 10' x 7'. Electric heating - consumption not to exceed 8 K.W. each. Similar to Thackray’s N0.3232E. 5. Eight instrument - sterilisers for wards. Size approx. 17' x 8' x 6'. Electric heating - consumption not to exceed 4 K.W. each. Similar to 'fhackray’s Ho.3231 E. Cystoscope : Examination, Operating, &amp; Catheterising type, Brown Buerger’s or Swift Joly type with all necessary equipment and spare bulbs etc. All surgical instruments of stainless steel.(WFIB^NTIAU; ft 1 - No. - 19/235 . Utiv t (Um. -7-TfV s/ 1339 ,S ? The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, Tne India Office, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. DatedJanuary , 1939. Reference to previous correspondence : Letter Ho .P .Z.7941/38, dated tne 2nd December, 1938, from the India Office, London, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Copy of me mo randum No . 17-5/43 dated the 8th January, 1939, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Secretary to the Hon’blc the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire . 2. Cheque NO.M564515 of the Eastern Bank Limited for £ 3,000/- in favour of the High Commissioner for India. Indent for medical equipment and appliances for the new Bahrain Governnr^nt Hospital.No. 17-6/43 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 8th January 1939 To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• Subject:-Indent for medical equipment and appliances for the new Bahrain Government Hospital, Memorandum. Please refer to India Office letter No. P.Z. 7941/38 dated the 2nd December 1938. (Copy forwarded to me under India Office printed letter No. P.Z. 7941 dated the 2nd December 1938) 2. The Bahrain Government would be very grateful if orders for medical equipment and appliances for their new hospital could be executed through the India Store Department. 3* I enclose a cheque for £. 3,000 drawn in favour of the High Commissioner for India, which amount represents a deposit to cover the approximate cost inclusive of the freight charges and the 3% departmental charge. sd/- J.B. Howes for Political Agent, BahrainW- No. TO S'© -19/235. tfc+t teesi' o 8453 hf-&lt;5. The Hon’ble the Political llesidje^J)^0bhe Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London, V .f) and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s), for faYour of compliance. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..?*th.Hoyembe_r, 1938. Reference to previous correspondence : Demi-official letter Ho. 1927-19/235, dated the 2nd November, 1938, from Sir Trenchard C.W.ffowle to R.T.Peel Bsquire, The India Office, London. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. 1. Copy of letter No. 1831-6/43, dated the 17th November, 1938, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Indent for medical equipment and appliances for the new Bahrain Government Hospital.i Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th November 1938 The Political Agent, Bahrain* To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire• Subject:-Indent for medical equipment and appliances for the new Bahrain Government Hospital. Sir 1 have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with your printed letter No. 1929 dated the 2nd November 1938 and to forward a copy of letter No. 1632/10 dated the 15th November 1938, together with its enclosures, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, regarding equipment and appliances for the new government hospital. 2. I request that the India Office may be asked to pass on the requisitions to any of the firms mentioned in the enclosure, who would allow the Bahrain Government the usual Government discount. I have the honour to be, air, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- H. Weightman Political Agent, Bahrain/TV True copy. No. 1632/10. November lb, 1938. O A ~ v I w T J ! f ,&lt; O lyJO J From C. Dalryiaple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to tne GoverxiDient of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To His Britannic ioajesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to enclose five copies of a list of equipment and appliances which the oahrain Government wishes to purchase for the new government hospital. £. Barnes of various firms who are joiown to the Bahrain Government have been given on the list. The list itself is compiled from the price list of Messrs. John Bell St Croyden, Ltd., but many of the articles are of standard type. 3. I should be very much obliged if you would assist us in this matter, as in the case of previous order, by requesting the India Office to obtain for the Bahrain Government the favourable rates under which such firms are accustomed to sell goods to the Government of India. 4. While in England I discussed this matter with Mr. Peel and with an introduction from him I visited the Indian stores Departments mediaal branch where I was assured of advice and assistance./ r '\ 5* I hope that the wo&amp;ea’s hoapital, which iz&gt; a separate huiiciing, will start functioning early in February ao I would like very jaich to obtain moat of the equipment before then* b* The total co^t of this order, accord ing to price list, is about ii?0U* but I hope that perhaps tiurough the good offices of the India Oflice the cost may be some&amp;hat less. 7. Hegarding my ho. 1S15/10 datea 2nd October 1336, as soon as the prices of the goods on these lists are communicated to us, an order will be placed. Some of the equipment on these lists, such as beds, are urgently needed for the temporary hospital which is now fully occupied and scarcely equipped. I have the honour to be, &lt; oir, Your most obedient sei-vant, Sd/.C.h. belgrave ndviser to the GovernmentThis list of equipment is compiled from an estimate tendered by Messrs. John Bell &amp; Croyden Ltd., VYigmore St., London .1. But the equipment could be obtained from any of the following firms, all of whom have put forward almost identical tenders, if it is considered advisable for any reason. Allen &amp; Eanbury Ltd., 48 Vigmore St., London . 1. Chas. F. Thaekray Ltd., 252 Regent St., London ;.1. Down Bros. Ltd., 21 St. Thomas’s Street London 5.E.1. The list is a rough one and full details would be required with regard to the more elaborate equipment before acceptance. Arrangements can be made to have the equipment examined by an expert in London before shipping.SPLINTS Internal angled arm splints. Set straight Hollowed arm splints. Robert Jone’s arm splints. ditto ditto Abduction. Carr’s Radius splints. Byant’s back leg splints. Thomas’s leg splints. Sliding foot pieces for above. 1 Extension rod and pulley. 1 3iece Goochs splinting. 36” x 36”. 1 Set Liston’s thigh splints. Kichner’s ^ires &amp; drill 3 Stirrups heights &amp; Cords &amp; pulleys.'t '• 1 Sigmoidoscope, Yeoman^. 1 Speculum, Rectal, Simpson Harveys 1 Syringe, Pile, ditto 3 I.R. Rectal Tubes, 30**. RECTAL INSTRUMENTS. 10 c.c. BLADDER INSTRUMENTS Thompson Walker’s Bladder Syringe. Set Liston’s Bougies, Set of 12 in case. Freyer’s S.P. Tubes. Be Pezzer’s trocar and canula. Kidd’s Metal Urethral nozzles. Janet’s All Glass Urethral Syringes. Wyndham Powell’s urethral bougies. Cystoscope - operating and Catheterising with battery outfit Etc., 7ANAESTHETIC APPARATUS 1 Shipway’s apparatus (fit non-return valves). 2 Schimmelbusch 1 s Masks Adults. 2 ditto ditto childs size. 1 Doyen’s Mouth gag SS. 1 Fergusson’s ditto 3 Armold's Tongue forceps, SS. 2 Hewitt’s Airways. 2 Phillips ditto. 2 Junker’s soft metal tubes. 3 Sponge holding forceps, 9i n SS. 3 Mill’s drop bottles, 4 oz. 2 Sets of 5 mouth props. 2 Boxwood mouth wedges.2636 WtP 106/6 10,000 4.38 OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Attdresa fan Inland Telegrams — Telephone — Waterloo 5851. Ext. 2C' o, Any communication on this subject to be addressed td — f\ ,* -4 THE DIRECTOR-GENERaI / J 4 1 INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BELVEDERE R0AD,(34$ffiETH| i 1, ind not to any individual by name. Ax'V* Please quote in your reply S» 6132/38 . WPW. [KDIAMEN, LAMB, LONDON. 29th November 1938. Dir, With reference to your letter No.P.Z.7645/38 dated 19th November 1938 regarding the purchase of equipment for the Government Hospital at Bahrein, it is doubtful whether the special terms obtained by this Department would be granted by the suppliers to other buyers. I am further to mention that no check the prices quoted by the firms could be exercised unless the transactions were carried through by this Department. The High Commissioner would no doubt agree to this Department dealing with the indents and arranging purchase, inspection and shipment on the usual terms, i.e. payment of departmental expenses at the rate of 3/ on the cost of the stores plus freight,provided that the Government of Bahrein are prepared to make a deposit with the Office of the High Commissioner of sufficient funds to cover the estimated cost of the indents including freight charges and departmental expenses. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ^•Direc tor-General, India Store Department. The Under-Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.1. RESd. POL. ll./t. I 30 NOV1938 I INDIA OFFICE*/ r '\ cu.&lt;v\. cc L te ^ No.1639- 6/43, dated the 23rd October, 1938, from Howes which explains itself. I think, if it is possible, we should 2 assist the Bahrain Government in the way suggested and if you agree perhaps you would be good enough to pass on the indents to the firms addressed, and ask them to allow the Bahrain Government the usual discount. 3. I am sending a copy of Howes* letter and of the Bahrain Government Memorandum to which he refers to Metcalfe, and a copy of this letter to Weightman. R. T. Peel, Esq., M.G., India Office, London. becd. pol. dipt. 15 NOV1938 INDIA OFFICE/^Y No. 1639-6/43 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd October 1938 Prom The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire• Sir I have the honour to forward a copy of a memorandum No. 1316—10 dated the 2nd October 1938 and of its enclosures, regarding an indent for equipment for the Bahrain Government Hospital. 2. The Bahrain Government hope that we may assist them to purchase the articles they require for their Hospital on the same terms as those offered to His Majesty’s Government and I think we may do what we can to help them. ?4ay the India Office therefore be requested to pass on the indents to the firms addressed and to ask them to allow the Bahrain Government the usual discount? I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Sd. J.B. Howes for Political Agent, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001cd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3893</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001cd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3893</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/157A 'Medical Equipment and Drugs for Bahrein Government Hospital'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-23T22:00:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (200 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 202; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns assistance given by various British Government departments with the provision from medical suppliers of medical equipment (1938-39) and drugs (1945-50) for the hospital of the Government of Bahrain.The papers include lists of medical equipment requested by the Government of Bahrain. The drugs concerned are penicillin and yellow fever vaccine.The papers include correspondence from medical supply companies, and papers concerning air freightage.There are no papers in the file dated 1940-44.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Medical equipment</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Government Hospital</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Penicillin</topic></subject><subject><topic>Medical supplies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001cd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>