<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100034923818.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T02:49:50.197Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">v ) In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. ^ 7595/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir; - r - - r X —Foreign Office , 1st, July, 1914. 1 am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to v you herewith^, copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Am bassador in Paris covering copies of the French Yellow Book recently published respecting the Muscat Arms Traffic to- / gether with 1/- copies of the Yellow Book itself. I am to state ^with reference to the last paragraph of Bir F. Bertie’s despatch^that Sir E. Grey has no knowledge of the order for machine guns stated to have been obtained by Monsieur Dieu, and that he would be glad to learn whether the Secretary of State for India has any information on the subject. I am, Sir, Copy to India 3 JUL1914 four most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.mmmm mjmmm interest of tne French Govcrnrxnt to of iiis hajeaty’s Government tc submit them to arbitration. In the last doc accept trie oronosal t/he difference between ument published in the Yellow dated April *&lt; */+ 1 *. last, f . ho’umcjrr'ue instructs the French Vice-Consul at Muscat to infoitn the Sultan that, in view of the agreement come to by the French and British — — Covernraents, tno former 'uthdraw tiieir opoocition to tne application to French nationals of Uj?, Decrees of June atii Klh and oroceedc to re vie-; tae negotiations anu the situation resulting; the re f ron. his Excellency mentions the clai rn of M La. S oc i e te f rang ai se do s !. un i ti on s ” t and explains ■my it 'tas not tree tod on a par with the Co{;uyer firm and i. . Louis j)icu. ! . Doumtrgue states, in tnis connection, tnat tne farms established at L.uscat and possessing there .iOaso property, dhows nm stocks of arms wore alone concerned, for tiiey alone suffered losses, on account of the new regulations, for wliich they acre unable to find comoensating ad vantr m s o 1 se ’“he re. It is worthy of note that Hi a Excellency admits tbiat ever r bie re else nere tne traffic in a me mn been forbidden, on a measure of police, in China, Persia and Turtey for instance, no indemnity has been given to traders in anna whateverB r I r rJi — 22 — tannique entre la confiscation des acmes et leur detention dans un entrepot et je serais heureux de savoir quelle reponse elle a juge a propos de donner a I’Ambassa- deur d’Angleterre. Paul Gambon. Annexe. / Sir Edward Grey a M. Paul Gambon. Foreign-Office, 16 november One the 28 th October the French Ambassador suggested as a way out of the difficulty in regard to the suspension of the regulations pending arbitration, that the arms already confis cated might be restored and that there might be a cessation of the import of French arms meanwhile. It was explained to Sir Francis Bertie on the 6 th instant, for the information of the French Government, that no arms belonging to French nationals had so far been confiscated, nor was it intended to confiscate any pending a rapid arbitration if that could he decided upon forthwith. All that had happened was that arms arriving since September 1 st had been placed in the bonded ware-house. It was impossible to agree to a cessation in the import only of French arms because that would imply that the large quantity of arms and ammunitions be longing to French citizens, which have arrived at Muscat since the above mentioned date and which are now in the warehouse, would at once be distributed among persons whose only subject, for the most part, is to foment trouble in Persia and Afganistan. The' fact that no confiscations are at present taking place is in itself practically a serious modification of the regulations and one which cannot continue very much longer. ( TRADUCTION. ) Sir Edward Grey, Principal Secretaire d’Etat pour les Affaires etrangeres, a M. Paul Gambon, Ambassadeur de France, a Londres. Foreign-Office, le 16 novembre 1912. Le 28 octobre, f Ambassadeur de France a suggere, comme un moyen de resoudre la difficulte relative &amp; la suspension des reglements en attendant 1 ’arbitrage, que les armes deja confisquees soient restituees et qu’il y ait cessation de fimportation des armes francaises dans fintervalle. H a et 6 expose a Sir Francis Bertie, le 6 de ce mois, pour linformation du Gouvernement francais, qu’il n’avait pas ete confisque jusqu’ici d’armes appartenant a des ressortissants francais et qu’on n’avait pas non plus fintention d’en confisquer en attendant un recours rapid© &amp; 1’arbitrage si ce recours pouvait etre decide immediatement. Tout ce qui s’est pro-Annexe. Sir Edward Grey , Secretaire d’Etat pour les Affaires etrangeres, a M. Paul Gambon, Ambassadeur de France a Londres. Foreign Office, 2 4 th December 191 3. As you are aware, an officer was recently sent to Paris by His Majesty’s Goverment for the purpose of negociating with the French firms trading in arms and ammunition at Muscat and, if possible, arriving at a satisfactory arrangement with these firms for the cessation of their trade. I now have the honour to inform Your Excellency that these negociations have reached a succesful issue. It will therefore now be possible for the French Government to come to an agreement with His Majesty’s Government as to the future regulation of the trade in arms and ammu nitions at Muscat, and I shall be glad to record by means of an exchange of Notes with Your Excellency the understanding which has been reached as a result of the present nego ciations with regard to the recognition by the French Government of the regulations now in force in the Sultanate and as to the future amendment of the regulations. As soon as the notes have been exchanged the arrangement arrived at with the firms will be carried into effect. E. Grey. ( TRADUCTION.) t Sir Edward Grey, Principal Secretaire d’Etat pour les Affaires etrangeres, a M. Paul Gambon, Ambassadeur de France a Londres. Foreign Office, le 2 4 decembre 1913 . Comme vous le savez, un fonctionnaire a ete recemment envoye k Paris par le Gouverne- ment de Sa Majeste en vue de negocier avec les maisons franchises faisant le commerce des armes et munitions a Mascate et, si possible, d’arriver a un arrangement satisfaisant avec ces maisons pour la cessation de leur commerce. J’ai aujourd’hui 1 ’honneur d’informer Votre Excellence que ces negociations ont eu un resultat favorable. II sera done maintenant possible au Gouvernement francais de conduce un arrangement avec le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste au sujet de la reglementation future du commerce des armes et munitions a Mascate et je serai heureux d’enregistrer par le moyen d’un echange de notes avec Votre Excellence i’accord auquel auront abouti les presentes negociations concernant la reconnaissance par le Gouvernement francais des reglements actuellement en vigueur dans le Sultanat et les amendements futurs k ces reglements. Aussitot que les notes auront ete echangees farrangement conclu avec les maisons aura son effet.— 55 — behalf of French citizens and protected persons the privileges conferred on these persons by tbe Treaty of i 844 between France and Muscat, in so far as such privileges and immu nities are opposed to the Regulations and Laws for the prevention of the contraband trade in arms and ammunition in the dominions of the Imaum of Muscat. I note that, in pursuance of this decision, the French Consul at Muscat will immediateiy receive the necessary instructions to declare to the Sultan that the French Government will no longer oppose the application to French nationals of the Sultan’s edict of June 4, 1912, respecting the trade in arms and ammunition. I further have the honour to inform \ our Excellency that H. M.'s Government agree to the proposal that the two Governments shall concert together with regard to any modifica tion or amendment wich the Sultan of Muscat may desire to introduce into the above men tioned Regulations, in order that the French Government, having satisfied themselves by examination that such modifications or amendments relate solely to the trade in arms and ammunition in the Sultanate, may give their consent to the application of such modifications or amendments to their nationals at Muscat. It is of course understood that H. M. ’s Go vernment will use their influence with the Sultan of Muscat to ensure that French nationals in the Sultanate will, as regards the trade in arms and ammunition, receive in all respects the same treatment as British subjects and protected persons. H. M. ’s Government appreciate very highly the sentiments which have animated the French Government in their consideration of the question of the trade in arms and ammu nition at Muscat, and rendered possible the understanding defined in this exchange of notes. They fully agree with the views held by the French Government as to the dangers which may result from the organisation of a contraband trade in war material in the neighbourhood of distant possessions of European Powers, and I am happy to be able to assure Your Excellency that, in the event of such an illicit trade being established in the neighbourhood of any of the French Colonies or Protectorates, H. M.’s Government will be prepared to assist, in so far as they may be in a position to do so, in the suppression of the traffic. [traduction.) Foreign Office, 191 4 - I J roje t de Note d M. Gambon. Monsieur i’Ambassadeur, J’ai 1 ’honneur d’accuser reception a Votre Excellence de sa Note en date decejour me faisant connaitre que le Gouvernement francais, en raison des relations de cordiale amitie qui existent si heureusement entre la Grande-Bretagne et la France, renonce au droit d’in- voquer en faveur des citoyens et proteges francais les privileges a eux conferes par le Traite de i 844 entre la France et Mascate en tant que ces privileges et immunit^s sont opposes aux lois et reglements tendant 4 empecher la contrebande des armes et munitions sur le territoire du Sultanat de Mascate. Je prends note de ce que, en execution de cette decision, le consul de France a Mascate va recevoir immediatement les instructions necessaires pour faire connaitre au Sultan que@) In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no- iq y) u/a- and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, ^ London. ) { V r-. | J *• I'J?. I ' :y W J A The Under-Secreta ry oj State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop'll of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1914 . Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. l Subject. [ 12 1[ 12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote 2 No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 1 ^ ■a I The Under-Secretary oj State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cof of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, (kfiAA/ ^ 1914 - Reference to previous letter : J.d. ctf^u p. Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. $0 tkdl Zap , Subject.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] *' ARMS TRAFFIC. CONFIDENTIAL. [17658] No. I. Sir Edward Giey to M. de Prelle. Foreign Office, April 24, 1914, ON the 7th ultimo Count de Lalaina: enquired whether, in view of the recent exchange of notes with the French Government on the subject of the arms traffic at Muscat, His Majesty’s Government were disposed to take up again the questions dealt with at the Brussels Conference of 1908-9 respecting the arms traffic in Africa. I have the honour to observe that at the termination of the conference the French Government still maintained their objections to numerous provisions of the draft agreement, and, in the opinion of His Majesty’s Government, the recent settle ment of the Muscat question still leaves a wide divergence between their views and those of the French Government on several of the points on which the conference failed to arrive at an agreement. There docs not appear to be any reason to believe that a resumption of the discussion would be likely to lead to a satisfactory settlement of the matters left outstanding in 1909, and it is therefore not proposed to proceed any further with those matters at present. I am, Ac. E. GREY. C $3 [April 24,] Section 1. [2100 aa — 1 ] /and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. In any further communication on the subject, please quote Xo. t, please quote 10659/14. £ . Sir:- 1 I am directed t&gt;y Secretki^y iSir. E. Grey to inform you that the Belgian Minister called at this Department on the 7 th. ultimo, end mentioned the question of the Arms Traffic and the effect of the recent exchange of notes with the French Government. Count de Lalaing observed that the question of the illicit traffic at Muscat came before the Brussels Conference of 1908-9, and that the want of agreement between Great Britain and France on this point was the principal obstacle to the conclusion of the projected agreement. In these circumstances the Belgian Govern ment would be glad to be informed v/hether the recent understanding on the matter would in any way modify the views expressed by His Majesty 1 s Government in 1909, and lead to the question being reopened. As the Marquess of Crewe is aware the French Government at the time of the termination of the Brussels The Under Secretary of State India Office.(10659/14) Brussels Conference st/ixi adhered 'to 'their objections to numerous provisions of the draft agreement, and it appears to Sir E. Grey that the settlement of the Muscat question still leaves a wide divergence between the views of His Majesty's Government and those of the French Government. He therefore sees no reason to believe that the French Government would be willing to follow their surrender on this point by further con cessions in regard to the matters still outstanding. In these circumstances Sir E. Grey does not con sider that any useful purpose would be served by taking up the question again at the‘present moment, and he proposes, if Lord Crewe concurs, to reply to the Belgian Minister by explaining the situation as indi cated in the forgoing paragraph. I am Sir Your most obedient humble ServantIndia. In any further communication on the subject, please quote ;o. 12904/14. X and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office ^ March 27th, 1914. Sir:- f A ' ri &lt;,. G* j ^3 »4 regeivld SO MAR 1914 iKUiA With reference to your letter No. P.1085 of the 21 st. Instant, respecting the publication of papers in connexion with the Muscat Arms Traffic, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that it has always been his intention, if the French Government consented, to publish the despatch to Sir F. Bertie recording the verbal declaration made by the French Ambassador at the time of the exchange of notes. The consent of the French Government to the publication of this document is given, subject to the postponement of the date on which the papers are laid, in the communi cation copy of which was enclosed in my letter of the 19th. instant. Copy of the note which I have addressed to Monsieur Gambon is enclosed herewith. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, ^r The Under Secretary of State, India Office.i -y , S.lii904/l4 TOREIGH OFFICE, f'arch {.7th, 191 . Your rxcaliency:- In th© comunicatlua you were good enough to Wiv publication of the notea exchanged between Your Excellency and nyeelf on the subject of the Muscat A ms Traffic, together with the despatch to His Majesty* s Ambassador at Paris- dated the 4th. February 1914 should bo postponed pending the publication of the sane document© by the French Gcvemuon 4 . that I agree to the postponement of the publication of these documents, as suggested by Your Excellence, but T would ask that timely warning may be given of the Issue of the proposed livre janne in Paris, in order that / publication may take place simultaneously in both countries. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration. Your Excellency’s most obedient, humble Servant, 1 have the honour to inform Your Excellency (Big y fils Excellency Monsieur GambonIn any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 11369/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- Foreign Office jth. Liar oh, 1914. I 1 0!R j i ij o D i L j 9 i 4 / Vdth reference to Foreign Office letter of the 27th. ultimo (8446/13) 1 am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a memorandum communicated cy the French Ambassador respecting the question of the publication.of the recent exchange of notes with regard to Muscat. ,, n, ■' '■■■ air E, Grey proposes to inform Monsieur Gembon that he agrees to the postponement of the publication of these Docu ments as suggested, on the understanding that timely warning will ue given ol the issue of the proposed livre jaune in c ’ r i‘- , » 1Xi ° r C'.er that publication may take place simultan eously in both countries. air E. Grey would be glad to learn whether the Marquess of Crewe concurs in the adoption of this procedure. * COPY TO !NDr\ \ he Under Secretary of State, India Office.No. 12 ^. foasicai otnoti, March 9ih f 1914. (8446A4) i/r i 2ir:- With reference to my despatch No.97 of the 26th ultimo, 1 have to infona lour excellency that the French Mabassador hs,s now requested that the papers respecting the agreement oetween his majesty’s Government and the irenci Government on the subject of muscat may not oe laid before Parliament until after the french elections which it is understood are to oe held in &gt; ay next. The publication oi these papers will accordingly oe postponed until the elections have taken place. I am, with great truth and respect, dir, r Tour excellency* a most ooedient, humble Servant, {For. the See., f Q , ' StateJ* (Bigncd) , 7 '. Langley. xiis Excellency The hi'ht honourable ^irr. dertie, G.C. &gt;., G.u.^.C., uc., uc., kc #V In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote frUl+bllLi- Idress— / The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. N and address P IV), ( if b 7 India. f 1 '' ' m V ‘ COPY TO IN Di .^ 1 ! ^Jteatefab;._i3i ' The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copf of the under-mentioned paper. Ji Foreign Office, iFz , 1 Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. F f ~) • 27: ... . L ijf- r 12 ] vv0 y97. B‘ 46/14). 1” TORKiaV (FFICE, Fefcnir.ry 26th, Prtnoh (Suufl 4*Attains stated to-day that h« had raferrad to hie OovamHwnt the proposal which I had mtido that tha notes axciauig'xi on the a’lbject of tho regulation of the arms traffic at Muscat should bo publlahed shortly. H« thought that th« French b-ovemnwnt would vory likely suggest that publication of these papers should 6 * pOVtpoiUMlt •■■'baps until htey. th t ono of the French fims Interested in the trade had boon making iliffic ilti.- &gt; r.n&lt; threatening to brin cr in action against the hovemraent. 1 «n, with great trith and respect, 31 r, Your Excellency's roost obedient, humble Servant, /Ibr the Secretary of State). is Excellency (Signed) W Langley. Tho Fight Honourable Sir F. Bertie, 3 .q.b., d.c.M.d.,In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 5 TL and address— 1 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, 1 he Under-Secretary of State fov Foveigu Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secret ary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary \ of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. \ Foreign Office, Fct , igi 4 . Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. l/li '-( ■ f c e 'X-«a ^ 1 ^ 27 FEB if! C 12 ][This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government.] ARMS TRAFFIC. [February 4] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 3. [5567] No. 1. SiV Edward Grey to M. Cambon. Your Excellency, Foreign Office, February 4, 1914. I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Excellency’s note of to-day’s date stating that the French Government, in view of the relations of cordial friendship at present happily existing between Great Britain and France, renounce the right of invoking, on behalf of French citizens and protected persons, the privileges conferred on these persons by the treaty of 1844 between France and Muscat, in so far as such privileges and immunities are opposed to the regulations and laws for the prevention of the contraband trade in arms and ammunition in the dominions of the Imaum of Muscat. I note that, in pursuance of this decision, the French consul at Muscat will immediately receive the necessary instructions to declare to the Sultan that the French Government will no longer oppose the application to French nationals of the Sultan’s edict of the 4th June, 1912, respecting the trade in arms and ammunition. I further have the honour to inform your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government agree to the proposal that the two Governments shall concert together with regard to any modification or amendment which the Sultan of Muscat may desire to introduce into the above-mentioned regulations in order that the French Government, having satisfied themselves by examination that such modifications or amendments relate solely to the trade in arms and ammunition in the Sultanate, may «*ive their consent to the application of such modifications or amendments to their nationals at Muscat. It is of course understood that His Majesty’s Government will use their influence with the Sultan of Muscat to ensure that Irench nationals in the Sultanate will, as regards the trade in arms and ammunition, receive in all respects the same treatment as British subjects and protected persons. His Majesty’s Government appreciate very highly the sentiments which have animated the French Government in their consideration of the question of the trade in arms and ammunition at Muscat, and rendered possible the understanding defined in this exchange of notes. They fully agree with the views held by the French Government as to the dangers which may result from the organisation of a contraband trade in war material in the neighbourhood of distant possessions of European Powers, and I am happy to be able to assure your Excellency that, in the event of such an illicit trade bemg established in the neighbourhood of any of the French colonies or protectorates, His Majesty’s Government will be prepared to assist, in so far as they mav be in a position to do so, in the suppression of the traffic. I have, &amp;c. E. GREY. [2054 d—3]' j C 9 3 I ? A \ll ^ X t- ' rC-k cr. C Department. n \t rp r A K V NOTICE. Session 191^. ~ o Date. Initial. HOUSE OF COMMONS. Under Secretary Parliamentary Under Secre tary. Secretary of State fa 2 3 zr ^LAA ?.U). H OK. Question by j _ D . For • lA 191^ -&gt;•57. Sir J. D. Rees, — To ask the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, whether he can inform the House of the terms of the Anglo-French agreement regarding the suppression of the traffic in arms in the Persian Gulf and the neighbouring waters.THE ARMS TRAFFIC, FRENCH RIGHTS UNDER THE MUSCAT TREATY. The following communication is issued by the Foreign Office :— An exchange of Notes took place on the ' 4th inst. between Sir Edward Grey and the French Ambassador by which a settlement has been effected with regard to the Muscat arms traffic. By this settlement the French Government undertake no longer to claim for their nationals the privileges and immunities secured under the treaty between France and Muscat of 1844, in so' far as those privileges and immunities conflict with the regulations for the prevention ; of the illicit trade in arms and ammunition in the Sultanate. In other respects the treaty of 1844 remains in force. The Notes exchanged will be laid before Parliament at an early date. The settlement above officially announced is a satisfactory conclusion to a controversy long pending between the British and Indian | Governments and representatives of French interests. The interests of France were based on rights proceeding from the French Con vention of 1844 with the Sultan of Muscat, and the Declaration signed by Great Britain and France in 1862, by which the two countries engaged reciprocally to respect the independence of the Sultans of Muscat and Zanzibar. The gist of the controversy was the expedi ency, not to say the necessity, of placing on a regular and legitimate footing the contraband, traffic in arms between Djibuti and the North- West Frontier of India, for which Muscat had long been an entrepot. On July 12, 1912, the Sultan of Oman issued a proclamation regu lating the traffic in arms and establishing an “ Arms Warehouse,” in which all weapons and ammunition were to be deposited, pending i their sale, under special licences, to accredited purchasers. The French Government regarded this proclamation as an infringement of French trading rights under the Declaration of 1862, “■ u (9 “fob-.C'sff c^~ s~ y In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote i( N“- and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. If J o ~. * ■ oar-o f ;&gt;-/» CfeV ; &gt;' : *-df '' J? 'fv^y to !nd!a 13 FEB 1914 The Under-Se£r£Mr^3j^StAte for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^ ? , i 9 h. Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. y* JiM. CLy^Ihis &lt;sUiFnyarf' ( 2 ^yy^tion on this subject, please quote n 0 . 2922/14. In any further communica- 2922/14 and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office February 4th, 1914 Sir With reference to your letter No. P. 213 of the 20th. ultimo, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state that the French -Ambassador has now agreed to the terms of the proposed British note, so that only the formal signature and exchange of the notes remain to be carried out. With regard to the verbal declaration to be made by the Ambassador, I am to state that this declaration will be recorded in a despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Paris. i am Your most obedient Sir humble Servant The Under Secretary of State, India Office.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 3136/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. l”\nedlate. Sir: &gt; — ..:L L na Foreign Office January 22nd, 1914 i fv With reference to your letter of the 20th. inBt&amp;nt respecting the Muscat Arms Traffic, I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a memorandum communicated hy the French Embassy on the 20th. instant, respecting the form of the declara tion to he made hy the French Ambassador in connexion with the proposed exchange of notes. Sir E. Grey considers that a declaration in these terms might be accepted, and I am to enquire whether the Marquess of Crewe concurs in this view. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, j i The Under Secretary of State, India Office.arms traffic. [January 17.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1, [2049] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir F. Bertie. (No. 26.) Sir, Foreign Office, January 17, 1914. ON the 19th ultimo the French Ambassador communicated to me a draft note respecting the arms traffic at Muscat. In this draft no mention was made of the power of the Sultan to execute the arms regulations in the territorial waters of Muscat, a point to which the Government of India attach considerable importance, and the attention of the French Embassy was accordingly drawn to this point. On the 14th instant M. de Fleurieu communicated to me a memorandum, copy of which is enclosed,- dealing with this question, and I am now enquiring whether the course proposed would he acceptable to the Government of India. M. de Fleurieu also suggested an alteration of the draft note, and a copy of the draft note as amended is enclosed for your Excellency’s information. I am, &amp;c. E. GREY. * Memorandum communicated by M. de Fleurieu, January 14,1914. [2026 r — 1 ] Copy to frsd'a 30 JAN 1914V In any further communication on this subject, please quote ■. m No. SCt, plUO^SG QTlOtG 2049/14. Immediate. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office January 17th, 1914. M i --~i- Sir:- h/l^. ^ I am directed dy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith the draft of a note respecting the Arms Traffic at Muscat which was conmunicated privately hy the French Embassy on the 19th. ultimo. As the result of verbal communication with your Department the attention of the French Embassy was called to the fact that His Majesty's Government desired to obtain powers to deal with the traffic in the territorial waters of the Sultan of Muscat, as well as on land, and that this point was not covered by the draft note. Monsieur de Fleuriau called at this Office on the 14th. instant and communicated a Memorandum, copy of which is enclosed, indicating the extent to which the French Government are prepared to meet the wishes of His Majesty's Government in regard to this question of - Copy &gt; '■ uiF'a 13 JAN 1914 the JA S (* 19 vi K 4 'f The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(2049/14) the territorial waters. Sir E. Grey is of opinion that in the circumstances it will he advisable to accept the proposed verbal declaration, after private communica tion with your Department, but it has been suggested to Monsieur de Fleuriau that the words Mans les eaux territoriales de 1*Imanat' should be substituted for the phrase 'dans le port ou sur la rade de Mascate'. Monsieur de Fleuriau also suggested an alteration \ of the section of the French draft note dealing with future amendments of the Muscat Arms Regulations, and a copy of the new reading which appears to be unobjection able is enclosed herewith. Sir E. Grey would be glad to receive any observa tions which the Marquess of Crewe may wish to make on the enclosed documents. Should he consider the proposals of the French Government to furnish an acceptable solution of the question. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether he concurs in the terms of the draft reply to the French Ambassador, copy of which is[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] ARMS TRAFFIC. [January 17.] n [ DENT1A L. Section 2. No. 1 . Foreign Office to India Office. Foreign Office, January 17, 1914. M directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith the draft e respecting the arms traffic at Muscat which was communicated privately 'rench Embassy on the 19th ultimo. die result of verbal communication with your Department, the attention of ich Embassy was called to the fact that His Majesty’s Government desired to lowers to deal with the traffic in the territorial'waters of the Sultan of as well as on land, and that this point was not covered by the draft note, de 1 leuriau called at this Office on the 14th instant and communicated a idum, copy of which is enclosed, indicating the extent to which the Erench cmveminent are prepared to meet the wishes of His Majesty’s Government in regard to this question of the territorial waters. Sir E. Grey is of opinion that in^the circumstances it will be advisable to accept the proposed verbal declaration, but it has been suggested to M. de Eleuriau that the words “ dans les eaux territoriales de I’imanat ” should be substituted for the phrase “ dans le port ou sur la rade de Mascate.” M. de Eleuriau also suggested an alteration of the section of the Erench draft note dealing with future amendments of the Muscat Arms Regulations, and a copy of the new reading which appears to be unobjectionable is enclosed herewith. Sir E, Grey would be glad to receive any observations which the Marquess of Crewe may wish to make on the enclosed documents. Should he consider the proposals of the Erench Government to furnish an acceptable solution of the question, Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether he concurs in the terms of the draft reply to the Erench Ambassador, copy of which is also forwarded for Lord Crewe’s approval. guerre dans I’imanat de Mascate. En consequence, le consul de Erance a Mascate recevra incessamment les instructions necessaires pour declarer au Sultan que le Gouvernement francais cesse de s’opposer a Fapplication a ses nationaux de 1 ’edit mascatais du concernant le commerce des armes et munitions de guerre.* ment de la republique, qui, apres avoir examine ces nouveaux rbglements et constate * II s’agit ici du ou des edits mis en vigueur le l er septembre, 1912, et dont la date exacte serait a rechercher avec le Foreign Office. I am, &amp;c. W. LANGLEY. Enclosure 1 in No. 1 . Draft Note communicated by French Embassy. Mon Gouvernement, desireux daffermir les bonnes relations qui existent si heureusement entre la Erance et la Grande-Bretagne, a voulu donner une nouvelle preuve des sentiments qui I’animent et m’a charge de declarer a votre Excellence qu’il renoncerait a reclamer en faveur de ses ressortissants le benefice des privileges et immunites eonferes entre ces derniers par le Traite franco-mascatais du 17 novembre, 1844, dans le cas oil ces privileges et immunites s’opposeraient a 1’application de reglements et de lois destines a empecher la contrebande des armes et munitions VOTRE Excellence m’avait signale a plusieurs reprises les graves inconvenients qui resulteraient de 1 ’organisation du commerce des armes et munitions de guerre dana Timanat de Mascate a proximite de I’Empire indien de Sa Majeste. Si dans 1’avenir, le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste le Roi jugeait devoir conseiller au Sultan de Mascate une modification des reglements mascatais concernant le commerce des armes et munitions de guerre, il voudra bien en informer le Gouverne- v [2026 r— 2 ]Registry No. Draft. Monsieur Gambon* i gib* Your Excellency:- 1 have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Excellency* s note of te-- : ay 1- a stating that the French Govern- ment, in view of the relations of cordial friendship at present happily existing between Great Britain and France, renounce the right of invoking on behalf of French citizens and protected persons the privilege conferred on these persons by the Treaty of 1844 between France and Muscat, in so far as such privileges and immunities are opposed to the Kegulations and Laws for the preven tion of the contraband trade in arms and ammunition in the dominions of the Imaum of Muscat* I note that, in pursuance of this decision, the French Consul at Muscat will immediatelyimmediately receive the necessary instruc tions to declare to the Sultan that the French Government will no longer oppose the application to French nationals of the Sultan 1 s edict of June 4th, 1912, respecting the trade in arms and ammuni tion* I further have the honour to inform &lt; Your Excellency that His Majesty's Govern ment agree to the proposal that the two &lt; Governments shall concert together with regard to any modification or amendment which the Sultan of Muscat may desire to introduce into the above-mentioned regu- lations, in order that the French Govern ment having satisfied themselves by examination that such modifications or amendments relate solely to the trade in arms and ammunition in the Sultanate may give their consent to the application of such modifications or amendments to their nationals at Muscat. It is of course understood that His Majesty's Government willwill use their influence with the Sultan of muscat to ensure that French nationals in the Sultanate will, as regards the trade in arms and ammunition, receive in all respects the same treatment as British subjects and pro tected persons* his Majesty’s G-overnment appreciate very highly the sentiments which have animated the French Government in their consideration of the question of the trade in arms and ammuni tion at Muscat, and rendered possible the un derstanding defined in this excharge of notes* They fully agree with the views held by the drench u-oveminent as to the dangers which may result from the organisation of a contraband trade in war material in the neighbourhood of distant possessions of European Powers, and I am happy to be able to assure Your Excellency that, in the event of such an illicit trade being established in the neighbourhood of any of the French Colonies or Protectorates, His Majesty's Government will be prepared to as sist, in so far as they may be in a position toMinute Paper. Register No. $170 Secret Department. Dated Dec. „ Zif 1913.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, _ London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs present* his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for — ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Vh - s* 3 • Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^Lu&gt; UcJl OLSmaai ^ (Similar letter'^ent to )nil ITU m** Docmnent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's G-oyemmesst*] ARMS TRAFFIC. CONFIDENTIAL. [57891] Sir Edward Grey to M. Gambon. [December 24.] Section 2. Your Excellency, Foreign Office, December 24, 1913. AS you are aware, an officer was recently sent to Paris by His Majesty’s Govern ment for the purpose of negotiating with the French firms trading in arms and ammunition at Muscat, and, ii possible, arriving at a satisfactory arrangement with these firms for the cessation of their trade. I now have the honour to inform your Excellency that these negotiations have reached a successful issue. It will therefore now be possible for the French Government to come to an agreement with His Majesty’s Government as to the future regulation of the trade in arms and ammunition at Muscat, and I shall be glad to record, by means of an exchange of notes with your Excellency, the unde)standing which has been reached as a result of the present negotiations with regard to the recognition by the French Government of the regulations now in force in the sultanate, and as to the future amendment of these regulations. As soon as the notes have been exchanged the arrangement arrived at with the firms will be carried into effect. I have, &amp;c. (For the Secretary of State), W. LANGLEY. [1979 aa—2]* $ I do not any sum .LOU Telegram P„ No. 125 , dated (and received) the 1st August 1913 Prom—The Political Agent, Maskat, To-The Foreign Secretary, Simla (repeated to Bushire). Please refer to your telegram* No. 270 S. of the 31st ultimo • Serial No. 177 . see how French can claim any sum exceeding seventy thousand pounds ster- t Serial No. 1115 . “S » s compensation. Tliese £i., ures ar0 June, and allow full value for old and new !f“ T tel ^ am + N «- 90, dated 17th French are concerned merely as agents ? f these casea years 1910 to 1912 for France and Behdn’m ,L i flud that trade statistics for a hundred thousand pounds for the two years TotF ap P roximat0 total of profit(s) on this for one year, we Lt fiveThnno, ^ ng i en per cent - ( of the) pr°flt(s) on genuine French trade. On British fv nnUal pr ' spective another thousand pounds yearly as the “ 7 ,! and Gormarl goods allow them a total of five years’ profit The total Fm° a = f enc J P r °fit(s) and grant would be £63,000 or in round numlrs £70,000 ° f COmpensati “ P a yable '' i 181 Telegram P. No. 1347, dated (and reeeived) the 1 st August 1913. rom The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To-The Foreign Secretary, Simla (repeated to Political Agent, Maskat). Keferenee telegrams* from Political Agent, Maskat, Nos. 122 and 125 * Serial Nos. 174 and 180 . Knox s figures seem equitable: but it £100,000 as absolute maximum from the bbckt^ point vlw^Wkh t Serial No. 9 , Part mi. regard to stocks being locally ebecked I No. 1442,14th December 1912, penullimate parigrapt” 1 ' 00 t0 tele S ra “’t 183 Telegram P., No. 128, dated the 1 st (reeeived 2nd) August 1913 . From The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. French 'consul ^^tS^the^atFer^a if askat . received a letter from the Jibuti more ammunition and arms from the warohoTsF ^ Sbip t0 details whatever. I should ordinarily ^ etter gives no that the application cannot possibly he lonFiderod bl^im until ^ S h° U ^ repiy he receives a satisfactory reply to his letter of th* q?u ^™ ^ 1 Su . ch tlme as of good modern cartridges are produced bv Monn m un til 108 cases house. These cartridges to be^aminpd L tn S 6 f . r ° m his P rivate ware- house and shipped by warehouse officials under seaf ° f the Ware ' tnd arms on board the steamer. d 1 Wlth otlier ammunition thought ^advisable,^IweTeih mFfdy toTirioFlf” 8 , comperisa tion it may be drop complaints. ' rely to shlp K oods u “ d ef proper precuations and (Addressed to Sir P. Cox.)192 Telegram P., No. 278 S., dated the 5th August 1913 . From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, T° The Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bnshire (repeated to Political* 10 197 Telegram P., No. 1369, dated the 5th (received 6th) August 1913. Prom—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Reference Knox’s telegram No. 128.* Comment on this telegram has * Serial No. 183 . teen dela y e(i owing to my absence. It ■would appear that hitherto His Highness has not felt able to take steps towards carrying out search or confiscation in pursuance of Government of India Foreign Department telegram No. 163 S. of 13th Junef and to do this now in all probability complicate negotia tions. ^ In the circumstances, I am inclined to support the course suggested by Political Agent in the last paragraph of his telegram referred to above. f Serial No. 95. 198 Telegram P., No. 282 S., datod the 6th August 1913. From—-The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Please refer to my telegram,* No. 244 S., dated the 16th ultimo. Follow- * Serial No 156 in ^ tele g ram ^ om His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India:— Begins. Laubenburg will accept invoice value * * (serial No. 186) * * Are you aware of this fact? Bnds. Will you kindly instruct Knox to act accordingly? Do you know what Ali Khan means by endeavouring to place orders in Europe and how future consignments, if received by him, will be disposed of ?[This Document is the. Propert y of His Britannic ARMS TRAFFIC. CONFIDENTIAL. [January 15.] Section 1. [2176] No. 1 . (Confidential.) ^ 15 ) „. ^ HAVE laid before the Lords Commissioners of His’ MaiesVy’^Trenrarv Sir W. Langley’s letter of the 7th instant relative to a nronosnl M ® ^ Government, together with the Government of India should underHho , ila J e f^ s such rifles and cartridges the property of foreign firm^L wL 'mpoHe d into^Mus^t before the recent decree of the Sultan relative to the control of fhl pvmc into force on the 1st September last. My Lords note that the expenditure ren^red 60 ’ 0 ° 0/ -’ ^ ° f ^ M 10 £Tm1 r /o re P! y i. 1 r eq uest - vou to ''Aorm Secretary Sir E. G.-ev that whilst their Lordships defer to his views that a scheme for compensating foreign traders mav be necessary m order that a general agreement may be arrived at with the French Government, they are naturally most reluctant to sanction so large an expenditure on this object, lam accordingly to enquire whether the purpose Sir F. Grey has in view could not be secured by an undertaking that, if the traders will take hack these ri es, Ac., from Muscat, they shall receive a payment calculated to represent a reasonable profit on the value of their goods. This scheme, my Lords conceive would not necessitate the heavy expenditure involved by that suggested in the letter’ under reply, and would at Hie same time meet quite adequately the claim, such as it is for compensation put forward on behalf of the traders , as it is, tor I am, &amp;c. T. L. HEATH. [2778 p—1] 10 FEB1913 rv aX/ / Cr TO r '' ! A 14 FEB 1913 REG::' 7Formally acknowledgedIn any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 38895/13. Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. August ^ ^ 1913. Sir:- With, reference to your letter of the 13th. instant respecting the Arms Traffic at Muscat, I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to state for the information of the Marquess of Crewe that Monsieur de Fleuriau called at this Office on the 21st. instant and suggested that it would he difficult to settle the question of the indemnity payable in respect of the French stocks until the inventory taken hy the British and French Consuls had been received. Monsieur de Fleuriau had therefore been instruct ed to propose that the Consuls should be directed to ^ telegraph the results of the inventory taken, and I am the necessary instructions in the matter should be sent to Muscat by telegraph. 26 AUu 1913 suggest that, if Lord Crewe agrees to this proposal I am. Sir humble Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office.[ 12 u. In any further comniunica- tion on this subject, please quote No - and address— | The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, 4k London. %JF ^ %J £ ■ I I Q \ ! - 8 v3 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ——* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Cf of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, X / , Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. LAs ( Simile Subject.&amp;c ., &amp;c . , &amp;c . No. PQHtSION OF?ICE, August Xf , 1913. (38211/13) Wit!) reference to my (Sespatch No.39 Africa of the 26th. June last, respecting the Arms Traffic at Muscat, I have to inform Your Excellency that Monsieur de Jleuriau called at this Department on the ?th. instant to hear the answer to his proposal that in return for the surrender by the French Government of their rights under the Treaty between France and Fuseat of 1844 so far only as the arms traffic with Muscat is concerned we should come to terms with them about the Wadai-Darfur frontier. lie was informed that his suggestion to this effect had been communicated to me but that I did not consider that the French Government could ask for territory in return for an arrangement respecting the arras traffic; and in the second place that His Majesty’s Government could not ;ht Honourable Sir F. hertie, G.C.B., G.C.M.G*(38211/13) not in return for an advantage ©Isewhere give up rights that belong* d to Kgypt as well as to this country, as both the British and Egyptian flags flew in the Soudan. His Majesty's Government would, however, be ready to meet the French Government if they only wanted facilities or communication with the Kaut Ub&amp;nghi. Vonsieur de Fleuriau agreed to drop the question of the frontier out of the Ifuscat negotiations. As, however, apart from those negotiations he had instructions from the French Government to accept our proposal for arbitration about the frontier, and at the some time to discuss the question with a view if possible to arrive at a compromise, he proposed to call upon Sir L. Mallet for that purpose. As regards the arms traffic he agreed with the view which Sir A. Kirtzel had put forward that the British and French Consuls at Muscat when taking an inventory of the arms in the warehouses should decide, without reference home, such minor questions as whether the arms should be sealed up, and he was also satisfied that there would be no use in trie British(38211/13) British Representative going to Paris to negotiate with the arms dealers until the two Governments had received the reports of the Consuls respecting the stocks. I am, with great truth and respect. Sir, Your Excellency’s most obedient, humble Servant,In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote n °- 37 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. H £ 1 91: The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for -——— * and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop if of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 2 . / , 1913 . Reference to previous letter RECEIVED 21 AUG 1913 hWiA OFFICE. Description of Inclosure.(272^1^). hv-divXimu only with uia approval of hie lajaaty f a Uovam* Ui ma -^ r could not bo left to tiio uncontrolled v*ii^ ol tie uultan* lie explained, ivowever, that tli© tion* iQnmtion would into the pockets of the coalers and would onl ^ P rovida the extinction of their private rights. Tiiero were also the Vreov riJnU of franco to bo considered. H was explained to him that those rights would not be ex- tin ;ai eaod, except in no far us the an re traffic rna concerned Tr.:ie ; ' Oidd bo dealt with and ro-alatoa separately, but he maintained that when the deal was rarde public it would be necessary ;or tao Ifiecnch Jovun; * w o enow tliat taoy iiad ^ obtai led souc cmici )ro hud for mat u.uy were giving up. 'ffoy were ready and anxious to ( pivc up their Treaty ri^its *cr ;o peneatic® else- •./hui o lie iu.c u su^.; j'uution uo unhu. it was pointed out that Uio majesty 1 a aovomuent vauru very u»ja-diliiv; to mix this question up with otiiers: that had teen trioa wiU the ex perience timt negotiations only aragged on and resulted in no egreeiaent( 37284 / 13 ) agrownent Luaing raachdti* oaaiour do :• lauriou adhorad lo i.ia point and balievsd that if an srr&amp;ngeaxmt could be ijic. prooontod cut and oriad to the iVench Oovornnient with out tho neoeuaity of first consulting tha French Colonial Office an nvprovtl could be obtained. /•part tro' nev-otintions }.e was instructed to discuss with the 'roper Departraer.t of the Foreign Office the (meetion of the ’ adr i-barfur frontier. 1 is 1 ejoaty* s Gov ern?- rt hnd proposed rrbitraticn on that, bat if he wore Bt aver the frontier with Biepa with aoM one in tho (!o?&gt;crtnent, end the maort was fcvourablo &amp;a Lord Kitchener wae in iocdon, he believed that tarsia could be arrar^jed 'aid the crr'n-enor.t on arrived at could be present- ed no the jaUil-irQJWa. for the abendonraent Of French fi-eaty n;;!-t,c in ; uect.t. Ionic of the territory hich his Ujeaty*8 i/ovornreent wished to retain was at present being edoinis- tcrod by i-Yonch Officers, one: even if Croat Britain were to win the arbitration it woa iwpoeaiblo to contempleta this territory being handed back to tlie unenlightened rule of the .Ail ten of bar fur.U762VL5). oir W. Longley and dir A* wore rot in i posi tion to discuss this auoation, and it was therefore only po k- si bio to arrange that the * ritiah and French Consuls et * usoat should bo instructed to take an invoutory of the aj ..is at present in the wultuihs warehouse and tlio privato i ranch \n rehouses at -uscut* '*« i tii cat truth ant respect § wir iour excellency's most obedient,[ 12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, ^ Foreign Office, London. 3181 U,$. 15/? The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for /ySLc^ and, by direction of the Secretary of h&gt;tate, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter /. v L 15AUG1913 %, V 'S F Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. t Subject. (SiMil&amp;r letter seniStrIn any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 32812/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. [mmediate* i i i . .4/? V j. M V/ith reference to your letter of the 16th. in stant I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state for tne information the Liarcjuess ox Crewe that he concurs in the terms of the draft telegram to the Groverament of India respecting the negotiations with France regarding the Muscat Arms Traffic. 1 am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, he Under Secretary of State, India Office.?.!!) ] In any lurther comiiiuiiica tion on this subject, please quote Put away with No. 30 1 ? &gt; and address— .. //3 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. i U 1 1 o 1 3 i. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper A Foreign Office, &gt; ms- Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 7 o v^vc ^ 3 I'CX.lv C 1 (f 1 3o •ttCopy* FOREIGN OFFICE, 13th June, 1913 Dear Fonsieur de Fleuriau:- We have been carefully considering your letter to me of the 31st ultimo in regard to the arms traffic at ‘uscat. Before saying anything definite in reply to it we should like to be quite certain on the following two points. (l) We assume that the undertaking which the French Government would give in regard to the arms dealers applies to the whole extent cf the Sultanate of Oman. Is this assumption correct? (?) Was it the intention of the French Government that we should buy up the arms at present held by the French dealers or that we should allow them to remove these arms to Europe? I quite agree with yov that a solution of this troublesome question seems at last to be in sight. No one will be more pleased them myself when the matter is finally setuled. (Signed)— )0 'A In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 29672/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir: - Foreign Office i g , k *&gt; &lt;C&gt; j Q I I 4 K.J n June 30th, 1913. 4 I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to trans mlt to you herewith for the Information of the Par- i j ^quess of Crewe copy of a despatch to His Majesty's GjO : ^ ^ M Charge d'Affaires at Paris respecting the Arms Traffic ■ at -'useat. It will be seen from the last paragraph of this despatch that it has been suggested that in return for compensation to the French firms concerned the French Government might adhere to the Regulations, and that these might he made more stringent. Sir E. Grey is disposed to think that these proposals offer a possible solution of the question, and he would be glad to 4 JUL1 learn the views of Lord Crewe on the subject. I am. Sr* LY f f 1 l' 0 \ A v ■ Li L. ^ ^ ^ ^ X. /fX Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, ■ 8 - T uder Secretary of State, India Office.Sir: - rica. ■ft. I * &gt;672/l 3 . f '■f ( ■ Nr Monsieur Pi chon, in the course of this conversa tion that he and Monsieur Csnhon had ,vith Sir Arthur Hlcolaon and me this morning, spoke of the question of as when he last left the French “k&gt;r&amp;i^n Office. It was now suggested that we should compensate the two French firms engaged in the arms trade, L said that perhaps t! is might he done, hut it would not he sufficient that the French should merely promise not to encourage other firms, I thought that their Treaty rights with Muscat should he so modified as to exclude any protection to the arms trade. Monsieur Camion suggested as an alternative that, If the two French firms were compensates, the French Government should definitely adhere to the regulations about the arms traffic which had 1 .m /• 'omulgat^d in Muscat. * Honourable I..D. Camegie, M.V.O I{2Z&gt; (imiz/iz). &gt;v t said that this see^d to me a possible, course. but os the regulations now exist in*: had been tirwm up very carefully and moderately, in order to avoid in- fringing French Treaty rights, it might be necessary for us to make some rather more stringent regulations. to which the French should adhere in return for com pensation to their two firms. It was a question on which the India Of fice must be consulted, and T would con 3 ult that Fffics. I am, with great truth and regard. Your most obedient.The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for a and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned fiaper. f 12 l Foreign Office, Af-l-vX 2-&lt;7 ( jg f j Reference to previous letter Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. k ^ - bcvtui . -• .. 4 -. JT X V , .j X, a T--; . -Ximti/n) ? ir: Itu'i French d* Affaire# c-all^a by inc-traction on in® 2 i*t inetant to my timi im Prmok Qov^rmwnt found tfimt it mm *o difficult to come to «a fWpN^lg the Muftoat Aim Traffic that tncy foared that the auoetioa must gp to arbitration imoioar do Fiourioa added on hi* om account that he still did not despair of fiiadiog aoi^e solution of the difficulty• there aero only too firm® at present ec^aged in the traffic* If it could be arrayed that they enoula receive CMpeneation the question mi^ht be euelved for the moment mm the larger question of U^e extinction of Franca ri^ht** under the Treaty mi^ht be left for settlement in aay general ne^otiatione mdcu mitJut take place later* In a eoweehat similar case France had paid etfeneation to Hie Excellency The Ri^ht Honourable tar F* Dertie, G.C*H. f CX.M.G 4*15 • | he • | 4 tC •From Viceroy, 17th March 1913. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of the 3rd March. Maskat. We agree to pay share of cash compensation both for existing stock and extinction of trade. It is difficult to estimate latter, but if necessary we will telegraph what we consider adequate figure. As regards Pondicherry we cannot agree to cession of territory there to France unless we receive some territorial exchange in India in return, and would still press for Chandernagore and Loges. To grant cession ofjBritish territory to France in India without such exchange would inevitably rouse public feeling and give weapon to dis affected persons in a manner that would prove embarrassing to Government. We still agree to offer made in paragraph 5 of India Office letter to Foreign Office, dated 1st April 1911, provided that this includes cession of Chander nagore and Loges to us by French. Should cession of territory at Pondicherry either with or without compensation be eventually decided on, we urge that a stipulation should be made that no wireless installation should be erected in French India without previous concurrence. As regards negotiations for option of lease of part of Musandim peninsula, Cox wires on 7th March as follows :— “ If there is the least chance to repeal Declaration of 1862 in the near future, it is of the highest importance that we should not excite cupidity of France, or alarm Sullan by allowing it to be supposed by them, that any present negotiations with Sultan are connected with contingency of its repeal. We need to proceed with all the more caution because although French are often a nuisance to the Sultan, I am pretty sure that he values their presence and the existence of the Declaration of 1862 as preserving him from the dreaded fate of Zanzibar, and he would not welcome its repeal. “ Consequently whatever we need to get from the Sultan at the present juncture should be sought on some other basis. I would suggest that we first negotiate lighthouse question only. We could say we find Little Quoin too inaccessible, and that we want his permission to put the light on Musandim, and will be glad to pay him rent if he desires. Having established light, we should say we need to put it in telegraphic communi cation and propose to re-establish telegraph station at Maklab as we are entitled to do under Article I. of Telegraph Treaty, 1862. Having done that it will be only a step further to put some coal at Khor Kawai as we have already done at Hen jam. Meanwhile if we should succeed in getting rid of the Declaration of 1862 and the French we could adopt a much bolder line.” Undoubtedly abrogation of Declaration of 1862 would greatly alarm Sultan and at the same time would remove one of our present safeguards against intrusion of other Powers into Muscat. Could not Franee be induced, without abrogation of 1862 Treaty, and notwithstanding our interpretation of that treaty in Bandar Gisseh case, to admit our right, under our Muscat Agreement of 1891, to take steps necessary for establish ment of naval station in R+ms^al-Jibal peninsula ? Sultan would undoubtedly be more favourably disposed to such undertaking if Declaration of 1862 were maintained.&lt;y-&gt; Departments are requested, if they suspect that there is any mistake in this telegram, to communicate immediately with the Private Secretary to the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State. COPY OF TELEGRAM. F ROM[ 21 ] ■I /« /OQ Confidential, The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the 'Stx/iZ, ^rri , and is directed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to transmit the accompanying sections of printed confidential correspondence. Foreign Office, JLo ,i9tZ o&gt;~[This Document is the Property of His Britannic o^&gt; I ARM. TRAFFIC. [February 27.J CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1, [4108] No. 1. Foreign Office to Colonial Office.—(Received February 27.) (Confidential.) . ^ ^ Foreign Office, February 27, 1913. WITH reference to my letter of the 10 th instant respecting the French proposals for the regulation of the arms traffic on the West Coast of Africa, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state, for the information of Mr Secretary Harcourt, that the reply of the French Government has now been received to the proposals made by His Majesty’s Government as regards Muscat. From the enclosed copy of a letter to the India Office,' it will be seen that it has proved necessary to abandon the suggestions made for the settlement of the Muscat question, and that it is proposed to renew the negotiations on a fresh basis. In _ these circumstances Sir E. Grey regrets that there will probably be no opportunity of introducing into these discussions the questions of the trade in West Afiica and at Jibuti. I am, &amp;c. W. LANGLEY. [2813 dd—l] * To India Office, February 2 G, 1913 [ 9087 ]./ors t ' AE .1S TKAFFIC. [February 26.J CONFIDENTIAL. Section 3. [9087] ' No-1- Sir Edward Grey to Sir F. Bertie. (No. 15. Africa.) Sir, Foreign Office, February 26, 1913. WITH reference to your despatch No. 66 , Africa, of the 26th November last, I have to inform your Excellency that M. de Fleuriau called at this department on the 21 st instant to reply to the proposals made hy your Excellency for the settlement of the question of the Muscat arms traffic. M. de Fleuriau stated that the French Government could not accept these proposals, which they did not consider adequate. They would prefer some arrange ment which would extinguish their rights in Muscat altogether, but it would be necessary for His Majesty’s Government to give compensation to the traders for the loss of a trade which, though open to criticism, was certainly not illegitimate, and also to the French Government for the loss of their treaty rights. M. de Fleuriau further stated that his Government attached no importance to the Algerian transit trade to Morocco, and had no objection to British competition there, though it might lead at first to a certain amount of contraband goods coming back again into Algeria over the Morocco frontier. The French Government could not concede the demands of His Majesty’s Government respecting the import of cotton goods into Tunis. They would possibly continue the present state of affairs for a considerable time longer, subject to the condition as to six months’ notice, but they could not at the present time inform the Chamber, as it would be necessary to do, that the arrangement of 1897 had been extended tor a period of fifteen years. From some observations made by M. Gambon it is understood that it might be possible to settle the question of Muscat by means of a rectification of the frontier of Pondicherry, and copy of a letter which nas been addressed to the India Office on this subject is enclosed herewith for your Excellency’s information.* I am, &amp;c. E. GBEY. [2813 cc—3] * To India Off^e, February 26 , 1913 . ([This Document is the Property of His Britannic Maj esty’s Government.] ARkS TRATTIC. CONFIDENTIAL. [February 26.] Section 1. [9087] No. 1. Foreign Office to Board of Trade. ^Confidential.) Foreign Office, February 26, 1913. WITH reference to your letter of the 8 tli ultimo, respecting the negotiations for the settlement of the Muscat arms traffic in connection with the questions of the transit trade through Algeria to Morocco and the Tunis cotton duties, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to state, for the information of the Board of Trade, that M. de Bleuriau, of the French Embassy, called at this department on the 21st instant and said that these proposals were not acceptable to his Government. . , M de Fleuriau further stated that the French Government attached no import ance to the Algerian transit trade, and had no objection to British competition. As regards Tunis he said that the demands of His Majesty s Government could not be conceded. The French Government would possibly continue the present state ol aitairs for some time longer subject to the condition that it could be terminated at six mo n|h s notice, but they could not at the present time inform the Chamber as it would be necessary to do, that the arrangement of 1897 had been extended for a period of In^the circumstances there would appear to be no use in again approaching the French Government in regard to a settlement on the lines suggested, and Sir E Grey is therefore consulting the India Office with a view to finding some other set-off for the extinction of the arms traffic. . x am, &lt;xc. W. LANGLEY. [2813 cc—1] C n A I SE C N C I 2and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Q n v*. u J. h.. - I an directed by Secretary Sir i). drey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter P.873 of the 11th. instant respecting the proposed issue by the Sultan of Muscat of a notice dealing with the question of the transhipment of arms in Muscat waters. I am to inform you in reply that Sir E. Grey concurs in the Marquess of Crewe's opinion that the Grcvernment of India should be informed that a notice may be issued in the sense proposed in their telegram of tne 5th. December last, discretion being left for the adoption of the alternative course under which the Sultan would be encouraged to deal with cases of transhipment on the assumption that Rule is held to apply I an. Sir, TTl oN S,AUV1 qIIODB'Iour most obedient, £161 MV 81 VKiN! Oi AdOO The Under Secretary of Stab India Office. humble Servant,Private and Coi^Udential. FOREIGN OFFICE, February 26th, 1913. We are writing officially about the French answer as to Muscat, and suggesting that we should try a rectification of the frontier at Pondiciierry and payment of a lump sum as compensation against the surrender by the French of their Treaty rights. Gambon implied that a settlement on these lines might be made, and de Fleuriau also mentioned Pondicherry though he had no instructions to make a proposal, but to make the offer with any prospect of its acceptance we think that we must exclude anything else, i.e., that we must not say any thing in, our proposals about Chandernagore and the Loges, or the French will be certain to ask for something else in some other part of the world.In any further communication on this subject, please quote ^ 9087/13. Foreign Office 3^ Confidential. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. February 26th, 1913. Sir — With reference to my letter of the 4th instant respecting the proposals made to the French G-overnment for the settlement of the question of the Muscat Arms Traffic, I am directed by Secretary Sir S. Grey to state for the information of the Marquess of Crewe that Monsieur de Fleuriau called at this Department on the 21st instant to give the reply of his G-overnment to the proposals made by Sir F. Bertie. Monsieur de Fleuriau said that the French Government were prepared to agree to arbitration on the question, and to consider with us the conditions of such arbitration; or they would agree to a compromise; but that they were unable to accept the offer made by His Majesty’s Government which they did not regard as adequate. From some observations subsequently made by the French Ambassador it is understood that the French Government are VJ really Fne Under Secretary of State India Office.( 9087 / 13 ) really anxious to dispose of the question of Muscat, and might be prepared to agree to abandon their Treaty rights in exchange for a rectification of their frontier at Pondicherry and the payment of compensation in respect not only of the stocks of arms at present at Muscat but also of the extinction of the trade. Sir E. Grey considers that, if Lord Crewe thinks it possible to agree to a rectification of the frontier of Pondicherry, a possibility which has more than once been discussed, it would be advisable for His Majesty's Government to put forward as l soon as possible proposals on these lines for the settlement of the question, and so to take advantage of the present disposition of the French Government if an arrangement can be arrived at which they could defend in the French Chamber to abandon rights which have been the cause of so much difficulty, expenditure and even danger to the Indian Empire. As regards the compensation payable I am to suggest that it would be best to offer a lump sum, wuthout going into details of the value of the stocks or of the future trade. This sum would be paid over to the French Government(9067/13) Government for distribution by them among the firms concerned. If Lord Crev*e concurs in these views Sir E. Grey would be glad to 1earn what definition should be given to the proposed frontier rectification and what amount His Lordship would suggest should be offered by way of compensation. The consent of the Treasury would then be asked to the payment of half the amount from Imperial funds. I am, Sir Your most obedient, humble Servant,India Office, 1st April 1911 * To Governor-General, dated 29th December 1910. From ditto, dated 30th January 1911. To ditto, dated 20th February 1911. From ditto, dated 25th March 1911. Sir, With reference to your Secret Letter No. 7846, of 3rd March, regarding negotiations about to be opened with the French Government for the ex tinction of all those French rights at Muscat under which the arms traffic is carried on, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs copy of telegrams' :i: ' that have been exchanged with the Government of India on the subject. 2 . Viscount Morley understands that it will be impossible to satisfy the desire of the French Government k ‘ that the negotiations should embrace “ a wide field and should not be confined to any “ local exchange of advantages,” and that the burden of payment is therefore likely to fall mainly upon India. But before discussing, what India has to offer he desires to place on record the following general observations. 3. He is fully aware that the French rights are secured by Treaty and that they are a valuable consideration, the surrender of which it is not reasonable, as an ordinary matter of business, to expect except in exchange for another valuable consideration. But that is a doctrine which may easily be pressed too far ; and in Lord Morley’s opinion a Power that has rendered to civilisation such services as France has rendered has not the right—and His Majesty’s Government should be very careful not to admit any -such right—to press that doctrine to its extreme limit. Even on the lower plane of an ordinary business transaction the right cannot be admitted without reservation. There is, it is true, a perfectly legitimate trade in arms at Muscat, for the extinction of which the French are entitled to full compensation. But it is important to remember that the legitimate trade would not pay by itself—as is shown by the fact that most of the dealers, when restricted to it by the activity of His Majesty’s ships, have been obliged to withdraw from the market; and it would be as unreasonable for the French Government to press a claim to compensation for the loss of the illegitimate trade as it would be for the owner of a public house to expect to be compensated for loss of profits that had accrued The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.because his premises were incidentally used for gambling purposes. It is further to be borne in mind tiicit (cis hcis often been stated befoie) a-lthongh the distributing agency is mainly, if not entirely, French, the French manufacturing interest con cerned is very small. Idle figures for the last four years are as follows :— — 1906-07. 1907-08. 1908-09. 1909-10. Total value of all arms and ammunition imported into Muscat. 112,338 279,050 237,644 103,862 Value of French arms and ammunition. 5,995 26,343 19,914 15,389 It cannot therefore be argued that the extinction of the trade involves the dislocation of an important French industry: and, in fact, the damage falls far more heavily upon British industries, seeing that the value of arms of British origin for the same four years was 52,327L, 101,432h, 82,017?., and 23,785?. severally. Lastly the value even of the distributing trade has been reduced to an insignifi- cent figure, and will be still further reduced, by the well devised measures of His Majesty’s Navy. 4. Lord Morley trusts that these considerations may be strongly urged upon the French Govern ment in mitigation of damages, and I am now to state what he is prepared, if necessary, to offer in behalf of India :— (1.) Territorial compensation. —(a) In their letter No. 88 (Secret), of 30th June 1910, the Government of India proposed the cession to France of villages in the neighbourhood of Pondicherry, covering an area of about 138 square miles (88,426 acres), with a population of 98,314, and bringing in a revenue of about 2f lakhs (18,333?.) a year. But they regarded the cession by France of Chandernagore and the other French possessions (except Pondicherry) and loges in India as an essential element in any such transaction. These settlements have an area of 88 square miles, and a population of about 99 , 000 . In Lord Morley’s opinion this is a reasonable offer. In 1857, when a similar exchange of territory was under consideration, but no question of Muscat was involved, it was proposed to cede 65 British villages, covering an area of 60,759 acres, with a population of 36,195, and a revenue of Rs. 1,07,712. The difference, therefore, represents the price of Muscat under this head, (b) But from the Government of India’s telegram of 25th March it will be seen that they are now prepared to offer, if necessary, 140 villages, with an area of 216 square miles, population 160,000, and a revenue of about 4^ lakhs.Beyond this, Lord Morley, who view T s the handing over of British subjects to France with extreme distaste, is in no circumstances prepared to go. (2.) Extradition. —In this connection I am to invite reference to Mr. Campbell’s letter of 23rd September last, and to say that his Lordship is prepared to agree to a modi fication or repeal of Article 16 of the Treaty of 1876 on the conditions mentioned in paragraph 5 of the Government of India’s letter No. 117, Secret, of 4th August last. (3.) For some years past the French have been anxious to build a railway from Pondicherry to Tirupapuliyur in British territory. The line would probably divert a certain amount of trade from British to French ports ; and partly for this reason, and partly because of difficulties connected with construction, man agement, and rates, the Madras Government have not been able to accept the proposals of the French authorities. Lord Morley believes that a modus vivendi might be found, and is in communication with the Government of India on the subject. ( 4.) Direct money payment for existing stocks of arms at Muscat. —It appears from the Government of India’s telegram of 25th March that (leaving out of account certain small quantities lying unclaimed at the Custom house) the estimated value of these is about 18 lakhs ( 120 , 000 L). 100 , 000 L would probably be sufficient to offer as a round sum. 5. These are the Indian assets, and, apart from any concessions that Sir E. Grey may have to propose in other regions, Lord Morley is of opinion that the first offer should not exceed (1) (a) and (4), it being clearly understood that the latter is in full satis faction of all claims whatsoever, whether of the French Government or of firms or individuals of French nationality or under French protection connected with the trade. If that proves insuffi cient, ( 2 ) and ( 3 ) should be offered in that order; but ( 1 ) (b) should be kept in reserve and not put forward except in case of extreme necessity. 6 . The Government of India mention that the Political Agent at Muscat telegraphed on 4th March that further large quantities of arms and ammunition were arriving by steamer. Lord Morley does not think that any claim can equitably be advanced to compensation for imports made nf'tpr M. Gambon’s communication referred to in your letter under reply, since it has been open to the French Government to warn those concerned that they would continue to import at their own risk. In this connection I am to refer to para graph 4 of the letter from the Naval Oommander- m-Ohief, dated 18th February, regarding recentlarge imports of German arms. Germany has no treaty rights at Muscat, and Lord Morley trusts that any attempt to establish a German “ interest,” whether commercial or political, will be firmly resisted. And with reference to paragraph 5 of the Admiral’s letter, I am to point out the im portance of insuring that the Sultan of Muscat obtains a free hand to prohibit the import not only of manufactured ammunition, but also of the raw material. 7 . ^conclusion I am to say that nothing less than the complete extinction of French rights arising out of the Treaty of 1844 and the joint declaration of 1862 is worth any substantial sacri fice of territory, and Lord Morley trusts that the French Government will be under no misappre hension as to the power and intention of His Majesty’s Government to destroy the trade if these negotiations fail. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, (Signed) R. Ritchie.- if 7- r. V From Viceroy, 25th March 1911. Foreign Secret. Negotiations with France in connection with Muscat. V\ e are awaiting letter from Government of Madras, but have received a summary of their recommendations. ( 1 ) They are prepared to cede 140 villages round Pondicherry, revenue about 4J lakhs, population 190,000, area 216 square miles. In 1857 it was proposed to cede 65 villages in Madras Presidency, covering an area of 60,759 acres with population 36,195, and a revenue of Rs. 1,07,712. Madras Government however would be glad to see the actual cession as small as possible as being distasteful to inhabitants of territory to be transferred, but should high imperial considerations necessitate it, more territory north of Pondicherry could be ceded. ( 2 ) Your assumption with regard to question of extradition is correct on the understanding stated in fifth paragraph of our Despatch No. 107, Secret, of 4 th August 1910. ( 3 ) Madras Government adheres to objections to Pondicherry-Tirupapuliyur Railway, but is prepared to subordinate them to imperial interests, provided conditions specified in letter from Governor of Madras to the Governor of Pondicherry, dated 27th July 1907, are fulfilled. (4) I have no other sugges tions to offer. (5) Value of stocks of arms at present at Muscat may be estimated roughly at —arms 12 lakhs, and ammunition 6 lakhs. There are in addition lying unclaimed in the Customs House 1,000 rifles, and 200,000 rounds of ammunition, and, telegraphing on 4th March, Political Agent at Muscat stated that further large quantities were arriving by steamer.• \ . From Secretary of State to Viceroy, 8 th October 1912. Private It is thought desirable in view of our not improbable failure in Muscat arbitration to have preliminary agreement with France as to tern tonal compensation to them for either the abrogation of the Franco-EnS Declaration of 1862 and the establishment of our Protectorate over Muscat and abrogation of the French Treaty with Muscat of 1844, or the modification of ^ Treaty so as to enable the Sultan to regulate the trade in arms. b.at are your views as to possibility of such compensation in India ? Personally I see great difficulty m any transaction which does not gtee us Chandernagore and the loges, though if we are also to obtain advantage in Muscat the cession of territory to France at Pondicherry would have to be argely m their favour. _ Would not public opinion in India resent any cession at Pondicherry without some compensation in India itself ? From Viceroy, 18th October 1912. Private. Youi piivate telegram of the 8 th instant. I think modification of the French Treaty with Muscat of 1844 is preferable to abrogation of this Treaty and Franco-English Treaty of 1862 and establishment of British protectorate over Muscat. Latter course would undoubtedly be resented by the Sultan and his people, and would give the impression in Gulf generally that co-operation with us leads to the loss of independence. As icgards compensation in India, question was fully discussed last year, and we have nothing to add to the offer summarised in Sir R. Ritchie’s Letter of the 1 st April 1911 to Foreign Office beyond the addition of 42 villages, area and revenue not yet ascertained, north of Pondicherry. This cession of Indian territory would undoubtedly raise serious resentment in India unless coupled with some corresponding advantage to India such as the surrender of Chandernagore and loges on which we rest great importance. As there is reason to believe that the French would not accept this arrangement even on its own merits, there is therefore still less reason for supposing that they will accept it as including also compensation for Muscat, and it would seem futile to re-open the question on these lines, because we cannot safely make larger concession in India. It would seem far preferable to maintain our present firm attitude and make the French understand clearly that we intend to support the Sultan in regulating arms traffic. Hereafter, if arbitration goes against us, we should obtain assessment of necessary compensation in cash. k f)r\y el/, /(j// ^ C dxJL Fm i Cmx'trM SwUVUj ^ CcJid hVr ^ i/ton vC / ku) J.o. Av r di'JL k ^ ^ Sj- Z&lt;j : ZncAik!/// : s. w/,J lA/A hr. C fa- i '7 22 IllsIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, No. T/te Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, i , ipii . Reference to previous letter : Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 14 JAN1913 (Similar letter sent to r 121Copy. io. 55666/12. Your Excel!&amp;aey:~ rmmk mic&amp; 9 January p 1913. Eiiii raforaace to the ora t&gt;oaal eo; tunica ted on tne IBtb ultimo by l on&amp;ieur fleuriau for re^ulatiiig provisionally the treatment of the stocks of anas belong in* to Frencinaen in Ivuseat, p«n&lt;li% the settlement of the question at issue by arbitration, I have the honour to inform you, that Hie Majesty*e Ooverti .out re* ret tuat they ara unable to accept tne proposal m affording; a eatiefactory solution. In tne opinion of his majesty * s Grovermaent euou a nro^osal v?ould mean a complete suspension of the regulations so lately issued by the bultan. Hitherto the regulations have been only partially carried out, which in effect neaus that both the frmien and Britirn bovem .ents nave conceded something of their full contentions. Whereas if tne pr^seni •oro;&gt;osal-were adopted all ine cohcecrious %ould come from His majesty*! bovem-eat* I ar;&gt;, however, in hopes that the arrangement orooosed on berialf of his kajesty’s Qover&amp;ment by his Majesty*s Excellency V:on s i eur Gambon, 4 &amp;C • , &amp;C • , i*-C •No. 55680/12. ^basrador at Paris for mutual political md coamarcial eoncaaoions will prove acceptable to Urn Imnch Government and so terminate without the oeceaaity of recourse to arbitration iuo question ehieh has ©o lo%; boon at issue. 1 have the honour to he, with the hi^hast consideration, lour ’xcellency’s met obedient, bumble barwant.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100034923818.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/238/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100034923818.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/238/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 868/1912 Pt 4 'Arms traffic: Muscat regulations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-02T16:11:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part of the volume contains telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda and notes relating to the arms traffic in Muscat and arrangements for its regulation.Issues discussed include:the request by the French Consul for permission for Menache, a French arms dealer to ship a portion of arms and ammunition in the Muscat warehouse to Europe or Djibouti;discussions between the Foreign Office and the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100034923818.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>