<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000166_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:52:55.647Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">4 J adent in the Persian Gulf presents his com- r / ^ ( y &lt;£- 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State j 7? r-^for India, London. / _ f Ar ( L Ou-* 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. ^ 7 7/P- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, Name and Date. Letter No.C/586-21/24 of 10th June 1S34 from the Political Agent,Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Bahrain ,ice No. 14th July 1934. Subject. Assessment of Customs duty on goods imported into Bahrain by air.■ CoaTidential. rv No:C/bB6-2l/24. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th June 1934. Froru:- Lieut-OolcnQl Oordon loch, i.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. To:- The Adviser to the Baiiram Government, Bahrain. Sir, 7vith reference to the Director of Customs and Port Officer ! s letter No:MPC/lA/lO/245 aatea the 5th October 193S (15th Jam&amp;d al Thani 1352} and to my conversation with Hr.C.D.Belgrave on the 7th January 1934 regarding the method of assessing customs charges on goods imported into Bahrain by air, I have the honour to inform you that enquiries have been made in the matter and that, in view of the high cost of freight by air as compared (in many cases) with the value of the goods carried, it is suggested, for the consideration of His Excellency Shaikh Reraad bin T Iss Al Khalifah, ihat it would De wise and equitable to include only one-third of the air freightage for the purpose of assessing customs duty. 2. Concessions of this nature nave already been made in Uganda and the Sudan. 3. It is requester thst you rill kindly inform me whetner this suggestion comaends itself to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad and, if so, that steps may be taken to bring it into force. I have the honour to be Sir,_ Your most obecient servant, ocl/— o. Loch. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain* INoJ8/136 THE CUSTOMS HOUSE, Bahrain* 14th July 1934* 1st Rabi* al Than! 1353. N 0 T I C L. On and after the 11th July, 1934, the assessment of value upon imports into the State of Bahrain by air, will include the value of the import plus the expenses of despatch, but only one-third of the cost of the air freight will be taken into account, for the purpose of assessing Customs duty* Let this be known. Sd/- C.C.L de Grenier, Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. Copy to:- 1) . H.B.Mtg Political Agent, Bahrain. 2) . The Adviser, the Government of Bahrain. 3) . The Agents, Imperial Airways Ltd, Bahrain.&lt;5 I a GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depariment. EXPRESS LETT A i o ILiI\ [N, B % —This is cm ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with tlce same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it Jtad been so despatched^ € v/c From Britconsulf Bu shire. To Repeated to Jolitical, Bahrain, Secretary of State for India, Icndon, Foreign, Simla. -i A'o. 3^ 549-S of 1934. Dated ©•Ui June 190 Suhject : Customs duty on value of gooda imported by Air into Bahrain. Reference my Express Letter To. C/209 of Jj5th May 33 and Gtovernment of India telegram Hb. 1340, dated 8 th June 1934, copy of which is enclosed. Please take action accordingly^ od. T. v-r* ii'o wle, It. •Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. ATTESTS!) . c REGD. POL BE 1 9 JUN 1364 for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. c.e* DC* P- lOSBS&amp;P- 57-8*£2—£.GC,CCt.rN if C NFIDENT 1AX.« GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTERS 31 MAY 1954 0 &gt; N'( IN . B % —This is an ORIGIA AL MESS AG TV, sent by 'post to sore telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to be treated, on receipt,' with the same expedition as if it had been, telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To ioliticr 1 Resident F olit leal Agent, B/.HRAIN. Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London* Government of India, SIMLA* / A V 1 xx 3° K Nr, ’C/2Q9 of 1934. Office of the folitic&amp;l Resident in the Tersian Gulf, ,7 H.M.S.-Bideford - at Sea. rjated 15th May ^?4. Subject» Customs dety on value of goods imported by Air into Bahrain. Reference India Office letter Bo.y.2.2578/34, dated the 20th April 1934, copy of which I enclose, subject to the views of the Government of India, please advise the Shaikh accordingly. /TTLSTLL . sd. T.C.Fowle, Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.2531 5000 2.34 I«b y otf Draft Paper. .1,- ItTV P. 2 ^5^6 ^lAJL pol iti cal Department. 0 D1 The Hon 'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. /•0-4/je tdr - CCl ( &lt;K (V/'y LlXXLk* 4- (rULAAy •'T4.(. ENCLOSURE IN Wt£K r Y ! No. 17, 26 APR. 1954 FROM SEGRETARY, POLITICAL ,v„y SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE ■T. Sir, r ■■ , — S&gt; o APR W54 1 am airected hy the Secretary of State to acknowledge receipt of your confidential despatch 107-3 of 2nd February on the subject of the request put forward by Imperial Airways tnat customs duty should not be charged on the full c.i.f. value of goods imported by air into Bahrein. 2. In reply I am to say that after po f —- / Jfc consultation with the/'Air Ministry 'tlie Secretary of State^agrees that H.E.. Sheikh Hamad should be advised to take the assessment for duty as the declared value of the goods plus a third of the air freightage. From r m the Air Ministry letter of 16th April of which a copy is enclosed, it will be seen that the two countries in which a concession of this nature hao already been made are Uganda and the Sudan. A ' w=3 0 LA i —*/——£*£**—&gt; Sc+Jr \ v ^ J. G. LAITHWAITE,mmmmm i © r&gt; -iV p. z. POREIGH OFFICE, S.W.l. 2578 17th April, 1934. (E 2062/1401/91) \ 19 3 4 J Zith reference to your official letter No.P.Z.1361/34 of the 29th March, we have no points to raise in connexion with the request of Imperial Airways that customs duty should not he charged on the full C.I.F. value of goods imported by air into Bahrain. Subject to the observations of the Air Ministry and the Government of India, we see no objection to your proposal to approve Fowls’s recommendation that the Sheixh should be advised to agree to duty being assessed on the declared value of the goods plus a third of the air freightage. I am sending a copy of this letter to Bertram at the Air Ministry. J.G.Laithwaite, Esq..INDEXED Tel. No.: WHITEHALL 7171. 313964/34. Dear Laithwaite, With reference to your letter of 27th March, P.Z.1361/34, I have been in communication with Imperial Airways and find that the two countries to which reference was made by the Near East Manager of Imperial Airways were Uganda, where duty is only assessed on the actual cost of the goods, and the Sudan where the duty is assessed on the actual cost of the goods plus freightage calculated at a flat rate of five Piastres (say a shilling) per kilogram with a minimum of ten Piastres. I agree that the suggestion made by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that the Sheikh of Bahrein should be advised to agree to duty being assessed on the declared value of the goods plus a third of the air freightage (instead of on the full C.I.P. value of the goods) is very reasonable and should be approved; this is also the view held by Imperial Airways. Yours sincerely. J.G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, London, S.W.l. 16 APR 1934 HD A OFFICE4 ./ Confidential Ion sulate-General, BTJ3HIRE, the 2nd February 1934 Ba.107-5 of 1934 3*rom - The Hon’ble Lieut•-Colonel T .C.3'o'wle &gt; C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ITo• 27/21/24, dated the 7th January 1934, with enclosures, from the p olitical Agent, Bahrain, regarding the request of Imperial Airways that customs duty should not be charged on the full C*I.F.Yalue of goods imported by air into Bahrain. 2* I consider that there is much to be said in faYour of the contention of Imperial Airways that air frei^it is in most cases out of all proportion to the value of the goods themselves and that some consideration should be given them in the matter. 3. It is clearly of importance that the use of air freight should be given every encouragement, but under the existing system of customs assessment importers are frequently heavily penalised since duty has often to be paid on more than double the value of the goods them selves • T© His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London Sir I have the honour to forward a copy of letter'1 - 2 - ■ ' &gt; •&lt; ; ^' j —7 A 4. The Hsr.a^er, Near '$ast Area, Imperial Airways, states that in the case of two countries, the names of which, however, he does not give, it has 'been agreed that the assessment for duty will he taken as the declared value of the goods plus a third of the air freightage. 5 # Unless His Majesty’s Government see any objection I recommend that His Excellency Shaikh Hamad he advised to make such a concession in Bahrain. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. w Lt.-Colonel, 'Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.* — /i or letter ^//4/xu»ct&amp;tca the August 1^55 rroci the Managert £iear *bht Area» uairo, to th • Me&amp;opotamia nereis uorporstion ilmitea» Bahrain* I than* you tor yeur fuemorandum 1a/*62&gt; or the ^nd August »ith regard to the question ol the declared value or eur atorea thich are ol’lloaded at ^iiTain* ihe point you raise i&amp; really M on£thlch has caused ue quite a considerable amount of difficulty in the past, and X thins, it should te tackled now in the right manner in oracr to get the matter settled aatie* factor!ly in the future. Nearly all the austoms Administrations charge duty on c.i.r. ^/f value of the goods imported* inis n«a caused a certian account of annoyance to casignees in the case oi freight* as owing to the hi^h rates psud fur air freightage the c.i.f. value goods sent qy air is increased enormously and it is necessary sometimes: to pay duty on more than douoie the value of the goods themeeidee. Very often in fact, in the case of cheap goods which are urgently needed and are there fare sent cy air* t majority of the duty p»io has oean on the actula freightage on the goods* the declared value itself oei .g a very email pr • portion* -cat u us toms Administration have admitted that this state of affairs is quite definitely unfair* as it penaliset goods sent by air and subtracts to a gieat extent from the value xxsx££x jc&amp;lx&amp;xx ol our services for freight* In two mttancct* therefore we have managed to get them tc agree to assist ing duty on the declared value 01 me ^oods plus a third of 'he air freightage* this proportion being scout tq^al to the Height rates which would have turn been sent xp*x;k.*jls eurxace tran^. rt« 1 thinh it might oe s)iggested to the Erector of uustoeis at iX'hrain tliat he should adopt the same procedure* Actuellt* of course* with regard to stores, we do not pay iieightege on these goG&lt;ds/wmmmmm r cop^ ul lex-uer is®. JLA/b^l oatea u* ^4^ August i irom tne Agones, imperial Airwave xiitiixea, ijaJaraic x© tiit director of uu8temb 9 iiahrain* © with reference to xhe questian raided in regara t® the declared value ©f et«ree etc*, imported on account of imperial Airways, we enclose herewith a copy of ® letter received from the company in this connection* we shall oe glad to receive ^ our views on the points riased in their l®tter.. . • { ©1 Xe t otr .k#* MPcyiA/10/&lt;i4&amp; oaiea uctouer 1^35 iroiti XpJb B|rcctor ©f onistome aiid port uliicer, ^aiiTain Persia, to the mc sppetettiia/uerporation i.imiteel, lifefcrain With reference te your letter i»o*lA/5kl of 24th Aug~a t 1935, Ae tir whal® questicn of rent for landing grounds and arrangements regarding customs is atill unsettled 1 will postpone making a definite decision on tie points raided in the letter which you enclese from mperial Airways until their position in Bahrain has oeen piacedjtn a regular footing rt is a year now since the imperial Airways first use# the rahrain Aerodrome and as perhaps yoji ar c aware, no agreement with the imperial Airwajp has seen made and the (iovernment has so far received no rent or landAxg fees, I think under the circumstances it is hardly a suitable moment ior tne imperial Airways Oay to ask for futner coneess iens.I uopy tf &amp;/6/V/6»18/M/iL cUited nil I roia the jkanager )&gt; i^ear jc«aet AL v ea» heli6poli8 9 te the j«ie sopotaniia Persian uerp^ratian i,iiiiiteci 9 Bahrain. In reply t® yeur iA/h09 el the 11th instant with attached letter Iran the idreci-er ©i 0u8t©DiS f w^really taicen tninjt that this tiatter shauid i.ave ueen zsu/up with the political hesitant and left te him te deal with the hgcal Cub tarns Administration and ± suggest that you yevert ta our s7/4/10*o97/ t rwSjcS of the 8th August and put the whole matter as contained therein, helore the political resident so that he may intervence on our Denali* up. and that the political »a*ajmfc«ri/ is quite au lait with our requirements*Copy of letter jmq* 26 dated tfa 7th January 1934 from the political Agent, xsahrain, to the Agenta, imperial Airvaye Limited, ±Ahrai &amp;» I dag to refer to your letter a©* ik/ooZ dted the ^th hoveiriber 1933 and to our converaation on the 4th i^aemder 1935 and to say that the .Bahrain uoverniaent are prepared to consider max ing some concession in the matter of customs duty payable on atticles imported oy air provided that such a concession is usual in other countries* xhe matter juas been referred te the Honourable the the political 'esieent in sd^persian uulf*I \ • * _</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000166_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3791</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000166</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3791</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/74 'Bahrain: Qn. of customs duty to be charged on goods imported by air into Bahrain.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-17T22:05:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 26; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Condition: the top of portion of folio 3 has been torn off and is missing, entailing the loss of some (non-essential) text.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns a request to the Political Agent, Bahrain from Imperial Airways Limited (made through their agents, Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, Bahrain) for a reduction in customs duty charged on the c.i.f. (cost, insurance, and freight) value of goods imported by them into Bahrain. The issue arose from the company's contention that the cost of air freight was in most cases out of all proportion to the value of the goods. The papers show that there was initial resistance to the proposal from the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain, because Imperial Airways had not up to that point paid rent or landing fees for the use of Bahrain Aerodrome. However, agreement was reached in 1934 by the British authorities and the Government of Bahrain that the state should thereafter take into account only one-third of the cost of air freight in the assessment of customs duty on the value of imports.The abbreviation in the file title appears to stand for 'Question'.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Air freight</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs duty</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000166#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>