<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:03:29.390Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/{ a fz In any further communication on this subject, please quo No - £r W&gt;/IHW/Zk and address— no/ to any person by name, ljut to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. £ IND' DIRECT^ P. A. s presents his djOjtx^ THE Under-Secretary of State f &gt;r Foreign Affai compliments to Z^^xLxaJ. * &gt; C , V and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop li of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ft o 9A^J 19 ^ v ^ Reference to previous correspondence : Name and Date. Description of Enclosure. Subject. \PtK fL. 3j4. h tk Od ■ t*\. Similar letter sent to 14 6x30 20111;;o. 380. (ooSi/a/39) Ky Lord, With reference to my despatch Ho* 305 of the 20th September, enclosing copies of a memorandum on the Persian press, I have the honour to report that as fro^a the loth October all news reaching the Agenca pars must first be submitted to the police, who censor it, and then hand it over to the Censorship Department, whence it is sent to the newspapers* 2* It is not known why the police authorities should wiah to censor news before it reaches the Censorship Department, and it is alleged that the x&gt;resa i® as yet ignor ant of tnis new practice# There appear to be two possible explanations* Firstly, as is general in oriental countries where Government is despotic and the masses are illiterate, on undercurrent of rumour and suspicion is chronic and inevitably increases in wartime; and it is the police on whoa the 3hah primarily relies for observation of this undercurrent* secondly, since the police are thus enabled to control both the published and unpublished news which reaches the f&gt;hah, they probably wish to impose their control at as early a stage as possible and thereby increase their power and influence with the 8hah* *s pointed out in tho final paragraph of the memorandum enclosed in my despatch Ho* 306 under reference, toe police have in the past sum arized the prees and submitted these sora^ariea to the Shah: this censorship of all news by the police is, however, a new development. /3. The Hight Honourable The Viscount Halifax, K# 0* , G*0. * . • , G*C# • '.* , etc# , etc*, etc*, ^OrT-.IGN 0 FI08.«* 2 «* X aua sending copies of thie aeepatch to the finistry of inforfflation^ the Mi die est intelligence Centre ana the government of India* I have the honour to he with the highest respect. My llara. Your ;,orf; snip * s most ohedient, hufflhle servant, ( :gd) fU J. v:e/.uour ■■</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/322</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/322</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 8058/1939 'Persia: censorship of news'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-05T22:04:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 5; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This letter was sent from Horace James Seymour (British Minister at Tehran) to Viscount Halifax (Foreign Secretary), and details the practice of, and possible reasons for, police censorship of the news in Persia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Censorship</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0002c5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>