<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:08:47.448Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FILE MO. 18/1 (VOLUT/B ORDINARY REPAIRS TO AGENCY BUILDINGS Ml Ni STK' OF VVo/^KS.Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO Telephone : 51241, 41217, 43830 \*l I { ' CD MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 50aA3, 1 9th April, 1948, (D Sir, X have the honour to inform you that as from 1st ^11, 1943 the Ministry of Works will assume full responsibility for the maintenance of Political Agency buildings at Bahrein. Details of proposed accounting procedure are now being discussed by this office with Ministry of Works Headquarters, Dondon, and when decided on will be communicated to you. DWC/MH Copy to Political Resident, Bahrein.No. mss' - 4/4 S fuliIXIOAL Aa^NCi BAHRAIN 1st May, 1948. *lo The Manager, iiaaterii Bank limited Bahrain. Dear Sir, I should be grateful if you would k'i ndly open account in the books of the Bank styled: 'BAHBAIN AGMCY - MINISTRY OF WORKS ACCOUNT* to which account please transfer a sum of Ks.2,000/- (two thousand only) from the Bahrain Agency - Foreign Office Account. The new account will be operated by the Political Agent, the Assistant r Political Agent or the Indian Assistant, severally. / 2. Kindly supply me with a passbook and a book of cheque forms. Yours ftithfully,© NO. 1240-93/2( A The Secretary to .His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Muscat, and is directed to transmjE^to him a copy of the under mentioned document, with/^ference to hii the Ministry of Works letter - No. 504/48/1 of Anril 9th, 1948, ■' ”■ Anr fr _ 'StHT'T948: W4S/1 of April 9th, 1948. Reference to previous Correspondence- Description of enclosure. Name and Date. Subject * D.O. No.50/48/15 dated l the 26th February, 1948, } from Mr. J.A, Douglas, Ministry of Works, Cairo, j[ to His Excellency the Political Resident in the j Persian Gulf, Bahrain. J MINISTRY OF WORKS ACCOUNTS PROCEDURE.No. 50/48/15. MINISTRY OF WORKS, BRITISH EMBASSY, CAIRO. Dated the 26th February*48. Dear Sir Rupert, Further to our discussion during ray receipt visit regarding procedure for future and maintenance works on the Jufair Residency buildings after the 1st April, 1948, the following points may be of assistance to you:- (a) Normal day to day maintenance repair items in regard to building and engineering matters where urgently necessary may be put in hand without prior reference to this office, and while it is difficult with present day costs to fix a maximum figure, the sum of £ 15 might be taken as a guide for individual items. (b) A monthly statement on Form W.61 o4/such day to day maintenance costs should be forwarded to this office. (c) Requirements for all other additional work, redecoration, etc., should be submitted for prior approval to this office before the work is put in hand. (d) A quarterly statement, in duplicate, together with supporting vouchers or receipts for each item of expenditure should be submitted on Form F.D. 51,•indicating the total expenditure on behalf of the Ministry. This statement will be passed through our Cairo office and any enquiries referred'back, if necessary, before the accounts are forwarded to London. (e) The sum expended each month by the political Resident should be included in your Foreign Office accounts as advance on behalf of Ministry of Works. This sum is then notified by the Foreign Office to the Ministry of Works* Finance Division, London. Any adjustments found necessary in the quarterly accounts submitted to this office can be corrected in the following quarter*s advance statement. (f) In the cases of new works requiring Head quarter’s financial approval, such approval will be notified to you and authority for advances to contractors and for materials will be certified from this office for payment in due course. 2. The quarterly statements should, of course, include running costs of electrical plant and air-conditioners, and wages for industrial staff agreed and at present engaged, 3. Should you have any uncertainty regarding liability of cost in connection with these accounts I shall be only too pleased to give you further information, but a reference to the regulations relating to the accommodation of Embassy and Legation houses, the property of or leased by His Majesty's Government contained in the Foreign Ofrice list will form a general rsais guide to the normal procedure in regard to this post. A supply of forms W.61 &amp; F.D.51 are enclosed. Yours sincierly, Sd/- J.A. DOUGLAS.POLITICAL AGENCY, No.R-43-13/1 BAHRAIN, The 12 th :4ay, 1948 To The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. idBiJORANDUM Reference your printed letter No.1240 93/2(a) dated 6th ;iay 1943. W.61 and F.D.51 which I believe have been received by you from the .Ministry/of Works, Cairo, with their letter No.50/48/15 dated the 26th February 1948. letter quoted in paragraph 2 above, mention is made of certain regulations relating to the accorazaoda- tion of Embassy and Legation houses. In case you are ordering some copies of these regulations I should be grateful to have two sets, one for this Agency and the other for Sharjah. I should be grateful for a supply of forms 3. In paragraph 3 of the Ministry of Works For Political Agent, Bahrain NNRD.O.No.R-44.13/1 The 12th May, 1943 Will you please refer to Douglas' letter No.50/48/15 dated 26th February 1948 to Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.d., C.S.I., regarding accounting procedure for Ministry of Works expenditure. On your suggestion we have opened an account in the Eastern Bank under the style 'Bahrain Agency Ministry of Works Account' transfe/ing a Siam of Rs.2000/- in the first instance from the Foreign Office account. However, it would now appear from a reading of Douglas' letter under reference that Ministry of Works expenditure can be met direct from the Foreign Office account showing the total monthly expenditure as advances recoverable. I should be grateful to know if I should now close the new Ministry of Works account and retransfer the balance to the Foreign Office account. Yours sincerely, A.J. Johnson, Esq., Administrative Officer, The Residency, Bahrain. 6 UTO, CONSTRUCTION AND MAINTENANCE CONTRACTORS J/o. U01/48. rain~^ 16th JiAY,1948. (Persian Gulf) H.B.M'S. THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. Sir, Tflith r©l) 3 i'snc 8 to your lottor dutod 12 th li^&amp;y,1948,rogarding rspair of the Agency pier and new painting etc,we beg to inform you that we will do the same according to your choice,and our estimate for the sa:;e will be R$.6,000/- (Rupees six thousand only). * ' / Above estimate includes as follows m Repair of the Agency pier and 1 ft cement plaster on both sides. 12 ) New painting and colour washing of internal and outside walls. (3) Making sky light in room No.2. Yours faithfully, K)R CONSTRUCTION &amp; MAINTENANCE CONTR iCTORS, SiSmN UCHT? -t /(yo*&gt; TPB.21st Hay 1948 D.0*No.1599 ecw I have been asked by Felly to let you know about two matters (a) Air Conditioning Units and (b) Annual re pairs .to the Agency. As regards (a) I have just confirmed with .ir. Yateem that he has two 3/4 ton A.C. units cost Rs.2,950/- each available and that he is reserving them for us for another two weeks. I should be most grateful if sanction could be obtained to purchase these two units now. * With reference to (b) I am attaching the contractor's rough estimate of annual repairs required for the Agency. Felly asked me to consult you as to how we can obtain sanction to have the work put in hand and paid for. I am afraid the estimate is not in great detail but I can get the contractors to submit a more detailed estimate, if required. Yours sincerely, G # C.Kim, iisquire, The Residency, Jufair S] CTelegram From To No. 408. Dated 2 . proceed En Clair’. Political, Bahrain Prodrome, Cairo The 15th June, 1948. For Kim from Pelly Grateful if you will telegraph whether we may with repairs ±h Agency buildings. = Political =A' 6 0 Telegram No. 429. Fn Clair f Banks, Cairo Pelly, Political, BaBrair. The 18th June, arl r» cei led the 10th Jinn^. — Ji % On asmumption/KJjat your tplegram of 15th June rofe to Horners letter of Ninth June to Kirn and that total cost vi not, exceed L50 you may proceed with items given in paragraphs one and two. Items in paragraph 3 approved except cut particulars of which must he suppli-'-d to voo’- 1 supplies officer. = Banks = r . ^ IR 197.\ Telegram From To No. 418. En Clair Political, Bahrain. Prodrome, Cairo Dated The 20th June, 1948. f For Kim from Pelly. istt Deference your telegram 18 th June. 2. My telegram of IStTfJune referred to estimate of Rupees Seven Thousand for Agency repairs handed to ydu by Hudson when you were here. I have not seen Horner^ letter referred to by you. = Political =Tele grain From To No. 442. Dated Sn Clair Banks, Cairo political, Bahrain. The 23rd and reed, the 26th June, 19^3. ?? s ‘ ,0 ' Douglas is returr&gt;ifig to Cairo in few cays and will then advise you ooncernMg repairs to Agency requested in your tilegran, dated SOth^June as reported previously to Kim. - Banks - IR 206 f ^ V(5&gt; Telegram En Clair From Political, Bahrain. Banks, Cairo To No.445. Dated The 10th July, 1948. f ? Yrtel'442 June 23rd Repirs to Agency buildings. 2. Grateful for early sanction as no annual repairs have been done since 1945 and as Kim is aware building is sort which requires them. = Political =. -J-' \r Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO Telephone! 51241, 41217, 43830 5Qfl/48/6 ,U MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 1st July, Dear Pm,, With reference to your telegram of the 20th of June requesting approval for repairs to the Agency building and jetty for the total sum of Rupees 7000* As this work has not been financially approved in the present year* s financial Vote, I am requesting Headquarters* approval for this expenditure and will notify you as soon as this is obtained# As the responsibility for the maintenance of the Agency buildings at Bahrein was accepted after the preparation and approval of our financial Vote submitted last year, I should be obliged if you would inform me if there are any other items which in your opinion eheuld require urgent attention before the 1st of April 1949. Any other information you may have in connection with the total expenditure for Day to Day maintenance costs in connection with the buildings, will also be very helpful* These details will enable me to submit a covering case for financial approval up to the 1st of April 1949 and possibly avoid individual submissions for financial approval* Having seen the buildings, I appreciate the difficulties in giving accurate details but a general guide would be very useful. Yours Political Agent, Bahrein. JAD/AK.■pr*' construction A.ND, T. TOMINNA &amp; S. UCIli tr^y v2j) *\y»«n maintenance contractors P. O. B.„ TeZ. /Vr&gt;. L 111 /- 8 ^yi (Persian Gulf) 0i&gt;. 21st July, 1948. TO, THE POLITICAL AGEKT, BAHRAIN P.OTLF. 2 .JUL !948 ©AHRAl^' Sir, and (1) Colour vrashing inside and outside (including scraping of.J o existing colour wash and replacement in some cases by oil and distemper ixed ;, m painting of all wood work, cleaning and oiling of all windows and doors, patching cement and base of walls where worn or corroded,and painting all ceilings, ($) Repair of the Agency pier and 1 ft cement plaster on both sides. ( 4 ) New painting and colour washing of internal and outside walls. (5) Making sky light in room No.2. Above estimate excludes new screens for the windows. yours faithfilly, nmT.Q'TOTTP'prn'NTS A*. T.fATMTENANCE © NTHiCTORS. 0 ic.Letter, T.P.B.fb S~\ Colour washing inside and outside (including scraping off of existing colour wash and replace ment in some cases by oil and distemper mixed), '£**■4*-. painting of all wood work, cleaning and oiling of all windows and doors, patching cer® nt and base of walls where worn or corroded, ‘ 1V f n D.O.No. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 29th July. 1948. Dear Colonel Galloway I give you herewith an extract from a letter I had from Douglas of the Ministry of Works at Cairo, the letter being about repairs to the Agency building. 'Major expenditure I cannot authorise at present until I have received financial authority from London but as the reconstruction of the Bahrain Agency as new Offices to combine the Political Resident*s requirements are being considered in London, I doubt if we shall embark on any major alterations. n proposals are under consideration for the 'reconstruction of the Bahrain Agency as new Offices to combine the Po litical Resident's requirements'. If any such proposals are being considered, I think I might have been informed of them. 2 I should be glad if I could be informed what Yours sincerely, s His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE, QBE, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.J Telegraph : Telephone : PRODROME, CAIRO 51241, 41217, 43830 AG£ a ,% /. * 9 /% A ill / MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 15th July, '[9h&amp;* Further to w letter of the 1st July, I liave received your telegram of the 11th July requesting repairs to the Agency Buildings. As it may appear that we have been slow in dealing with your Maintenance probiems, I must give you the sad etoryo our staff here. On his return from Bahrein, Kim was tahen into hospital with complicated appendix trouble and has been away for five weeks. Juld was suddenly recalled to London on official matt errand will not be returning until the 20th July. Two other illnesses with the staff have necessitated Banks and awav from Cairo for arrangements in other posts and almgethe itlms ™en possible to coordinate knowledge of the requirements for the Bahrein Agency. However, I hope we shall shortly be in a position to give you satisfactory attention. Major expenditure I cannot authorise at present until I have received financial authority from London but as the reconstruction of the Bahrein Agency as new Offices to combine the Political Resident 1 s requirements are being considered in London, I doubt if we shall embark on any major alterations. However, flay to 3ay maintenance will have to proceed and the sundry maintenance matters on the building can oe puo in hand where such work is essential. Homer, who is the Ministry of Works* representative in Bahrein, will assist you in these matters and I am, therefore, sending him a copy of this letter for his information. In submitting costs for approval to this office, would . you please give these as costs for individual items where Possicle Sd Homer can no doubt assist you on this point, so that I can inf cm you of the items which can be approved from this office as opposed^to those which I have to submit to London for financial authority. For example, while we can proceed with repairs to skyli^it, wi-pp pauses window glass, plumbing and electrical repairs, «*t item* f he Agency pier and entire ^eternal redecoration.^ require/ financial authority from Headquarters. Yours / ' C.J .Felly, Esq.,0.B.E. Political Agent, Cx A / ’ 1 RoV&gt;Y'i=n Y\~. YoursT. TOMINNA &amp; S. UCHI CONSTRUCTION AN Q maintenance contractors, P. O. B Tel No.. •o n (Persian Gulf) cJ\ y *U-H ui-^: 3rd Au gust^19 Ms TO, H.B.M’S. THE POLITICAL AOTT, BAHRAIN. P • GUL F. /. /t % r 'fc/ r - r- y r , Dsar Sir, with reference to your letter regarding repair of the AG©ncy pier and new painting etc, we beg to inform you that our estimate for the following jobs will be Rs.ll,000-0-u (Rupees ele-ren thousand only ),as detailed under ( 1 ) Colour washing inside and outside (including scraping off of existing colour wash and replacement in some cases by oil and distemper mixed. ( 2 ) (3) (4) or corrded. painting of all wood work. Cleaning and oiling of all windows and doors, patching cement and base of walls where worn ( 5 ) painting all ceilings. ( 6 ) Repair of the agency pier and 1 ft cement , plaster on both sides. (7) Making sky light in room NO.3. Rs. 3,000-0-0 Rs # 3,000-0-0 Rs. 1,500-0-0 p s# 500—0—0 Rs. 1,500-0-0 Rs. 1,000-0-0 Rs# 500-0-0 Tslii’ooo-o-o' Above estimate excludes new screens for the windows as not available in the market. yours faithfully; POR CONSTRUCTION &amp; MAIN TENANCE CONTRAPTORSi).0.No.323X-ia/l Dsar Douglas, i Thank you for youi* letters llos.fiOV^VS dated 1st July 1943 and 50/V4$/7 da tod 15th July 19**3 regarding re &gt;alr.j to the Agoncy building* 2* 1 not? enclose a full ttoiaisod list In t ie aooy of the Contractor's letter herewith and should be glad If you would sanction or obtain sanction for those worses and telegraph ae that there la no objection to getting on with thou* With the exception, perhaps, of the sky light which Is an 'original work” X suppose, ail the others are isalntenance and I can assure you that they are neces sary* The Bahrain weather including h* av&gt; duststorms has been particularly severe this year, and where It has not sand-blasted the paint away, it has p.ttod it with dirt, so that the whole building looks Tory shabby ind od* suppose it la the oainting and colour waabin:; call 'entire external redecorat ion'* but I think you will agr«e that It is routine raaintenanee for decency's sake In a place like this, as indeed are al the other items with the one ex caption noted* Tou will see that the extrac tor has now staooed uo his quotation by Ps*4,0 , )0/-* think X hare given you all the iteias which require urgent attention before the 1st of April 1949* The 4th August 1948, 3 # In the oast average total expenditure per year on this building was about Bs*3 f 000/- oer annum but that Includes figures from tho days when things were much cheaper than now and the amount of work required this year Is to some extent due to the fact that for the oast two years maintenance has, for one reason or another, b‘;en neglected n some respects* 4 # I am afraid that your suggestion about cay taking help from Horner in this matter Is Impracticable. As you will sue from ray Demi-official letter Ho*32J?7-lh/14 dated the 31st July to Kim he has not even time to\ attend %e the A* • here much lo;i3 to anything else. \ SftkliV) 5 # I hope this letter gives all the details required and that you will be able to lot me go ahead soon. 6. I am sending a copy of this letter to Uomer and to Colonel Galloway (who has taken over as P*b.) as he asked me what was being done about the repairs* Yours sincerely, J*A*Douglas, Hsquire, 'ilnlstry of Works, British Embassy, Cairo.^■1 T. TOiilNNA &amp; S. UCiil, * NO.L113/48 Bahrain, 3rd August 1948* H.B.IjPs Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter regarding repair of the Agency pier and new painting etc., we beg to inform you that our estimate for the following jobs will be Rs.11,000/- (Rupees eleven thousand only), as detailed under*- 1. Colour washing inside and outside (including scraping off of existing colour wash and re.lace- Rs.3,000-0-0 u 3,000-0-0 M 1,600-0-0 ' 600-0-0 ' 1,600-0-0 ' 1 , 000 - 0-0 ' 600-0-0 Rs.11.000-0-0 Above estimate excludes new screens for the windows as not available in the market. ment in some cases by oil and distemper mixod 2. Painting of all wood work 3. Cleaning and oiling of all windows and doors 4. Patching cement and base of walls where worn or corroded 6. Painting all ceilings 6. Repair of the agency pier and 1 ft. cement plaster on both sides 7. iiaking sky light in room No.3 Yours faithfully, For Construction &amp; Maintenance Contractors. (Sd.) T. Tominnal 1 ? REPAIRS A DEMANDS FROM THE MINISTRY OF WORKS. There has been some confusion and inconvenience in the past in the arrangements for carrying out repairs* chiefly because the Ministry of works under the Assistant Resident Engineer has a very small stai'f at Bahrain. In future* the following procedure will be followed»- 1) All officers requiring repairs to bt ried out in their offices or residences ehouldapply in writing to the Assistant Resident Engineer, whose office is situated by the high water tank opposite the Residency office. 2) The remainder of the staff should applyln a similar manner through theljr head of of^e. The Residency staff should apply through the Secret.iy. 3 ) The Assistant Resident Engineer will keep a Register of Demands and will enter them strictly in chronological orders 4} He will mark argent work for priority and ’ao it tSUt but .u »&gt;b.r.ort.lUb.=«;rl- out in rotation according to the entries in tne Register 9 ao far as is practicable# ^ M .;r t‘s^tst?'«ti'ss 1 .: t tt •. 6) c ompiled 1 iith S rfisoriblj Jui^kly^they* shSld“ddress the Assistant Resident Engineer# ecretary to the politiCful sident in the Persian Golf# Copy toi political Resident# ^/political Agent# Administrative Ofticer# Assistant Secretary. Residency Surgeon. Assistant Resident Engineer#No. B/376 (98/8 ) PEPSIAN GULF PESIDFNCY £&gt;Ce-4&gt;--ir BAHRAIN the 10th August 1948 1&lt; Will y©tr*‘please refer to your demi-official letter No.P-204 dated the 29th July, 1948. We have nothing on record supporting Douglas’s statement quoted in your paragraph 2. As against that, / the plans we have here of the proposed Besidency buildings in Jufair include no office accommodation. By Inference, therefore, we can assume that his statement 3s correct. I propose to write for details. 3. As regards your paragraph 1. You only require repairs to be carried out, whereas Douglas renlies in terms of ”major alterations'. Possibly the Ministry of Works consider repairs 'major expenditure'. I do not know what you are trying to get done and so cannot be more helpful. J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHRAIN 'LB' 1 ConfoAen^ 1 - TsoiD.O.No. 3360— / ^ ) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 17th August, 1948 \ Dear Douglas Horner showed me your memoranda No.60A/48/8, dated the 29th July, 1948, in which you refer to re pairs to the Agency jetty, but presumably that in cludes repairs to the Agency as well, as repairs to the jetty were only one small item, 2. I was a little surprised to see your memoranda, as I gathered the impression from your letter 50A/48/7, dated the 15th July, 1948, that I, and not Horner, was dealing in the first place with the repairs and indeed, as the correspondence will show, I have been doing so since May last. 3. You had not then of course get my letter D.O.No. 3281-18/1, dated the 4th August, 1948, giving the con tractor's estimate but such a time has passed since I first took the matter up, that I hope you will be able to sanction or get it sanctioned without further delay. The firm is a reliable one, I think, and although Horner said you wanted three different estimates and your memoranda asks for ’’competitive estimates if obtainable”, I do not think you will get the latter in Bahrain where as an oil-rush town there is too much building and too few contractors. Indeed Horner told me that they are not interested in ’’small stuff” such as the Agency re pairs. 4. I appreciate quite well your anxiety that I should work through Horner as Ministry of Works' Representative hex’e, but I must again assure you that he has so much work on hand that to ask him to get done or even supervise the Agency repairs would merely mean postponing them sine die . 5. Could you let me have a telegram sanctioning the estimates forwarded with my letter referred to in para graph 3? Yours sincerely, J.A. Douglas, Esquire Ministry of Works, CAIRO. * \D.O.No. R-236-18/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 16th August 1948 ny) ' Dear Colonel Galloway, When you wrote your D.0.No,B/276, dated the 10/llth August, 1948, you may not have seen the copy of my D.O.No.3281-18/1, dated the 4th August, 1948, to Douglas and its enclosure. I forward again, for ready reference, a copy of the enclosure showing the contractors estimates for repairs, etc. to the Agency which I have been trying to get sanction for since May. Under the Government of India consolidated central grant system these repairs would have teen carried out without any reference to you or any one else. I have written yet another letter to-day to Douglas asking for sanction to go ahead. You will agree, I think, having seen the Agency that the repairs proposed are the minimum re quired . 2. I do not suppose that the Secretary’s undated order headed ’’Repairs and Demands from the Ministry of Works” applies to requisitions already a subject of correspondence with the Ministry of Works, Cairo. In any case, it would postpone the Agency repairs sine die if Horner were expected to undertake them. I have also mentioned this in my letter to Douglas. Yours sincerely, LNo. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Doted 16tb August, 1948 To The Assistant Resident Engineer Ministry of Works, Jufair. Memorandum . Reference your letter dated the 14th August, 1948 2. The plan of the Agency building received there with is dated 1920 and shows the Agency building as it then was and apparently the alterations then pro posed. It does not appear either to show th° Agency* building as it now is or any alterations or additions which may now be under consideration. The plan is returned herewith. ^ 3. As regards memoranda No.50A/48/8, dated the 29th July, 1S48 (also returned herewith) from Mr. Douglas. Mr. Douglas has again been addressed in continuation of my D.O.No.3281-18/1, dated the 4th August, 1948, a copy of which was sent to you; and has been asked to sanction the estimate forwarded therewith.• Until a reply is received to this request, no action on Mr. Douglas memo randa seems to be required. (SGD) C.J. FELLY Political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED f e. aanrrin. ■*&gt;/Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : 51421, 41217, 43830. MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY 5OAA0/1O CAIRO. 2nd Septenber, Dear iiany thanks for your letter D*0*ITo.32o1-1 8/1 dated of iUigust enclosing copy of r i?orainna t s estimate ]To»L#113,A-8 dated the 3rd of August. In his recent report to this office Horner has informed £ us that he is obtaining an alternative estimate for the items as reciuested and I have today v/ritten him asking to put the v/ork in hand as soon as the alternative estimate is received# It is unfortunate that Homer is unable to give you all the attention we should like but I note from his reports to us that the maintenance of the generating plant at Bahrein is a full time headache and his terms of service really are for engineering maintenance. not be tied down so much as he is undoubtedly at present# For information I am sending a copy of this letter to Col. Galloway and to Homer. Kim is endeavouring to get help for him so that he will Your: . for J.A. DOUGLAS, Senior Architect# C#J. Felly, Esq. jO.B.E., Fblitical Agent* Bahrein. JAD/AKD.O.No. r.283 -18/1. Dear Colonel Galloway, When Kim was here in May last I had, as far as I remember, to go away, but I got Hudson to write to him sending a rough estimate for repairs to the Agency pier and annual repairs to the house prepared by Torainna &amp; 3. Uchi, the local contractors? Hudson asked him how he could obtain sanction to have the work put in hand and paid for, and said that if a more detailed estimate was required we could get one. This was on the 21st May. On the 15th June, I sent a personal telegram to Kim asking him whether I might proceed with the repairs and received in reply a telegram from 'Banks, Cairo' referring to a letter of Horner*s, which 1 had not seen, and not to the estimate I had given Kim. I again re ferred to him on the 20th June, and Mr. Banks replied to me th-t Douglas was returning to Cairo in a few days and would advise me concerning repairs. By the 10th ^ July, I had heard nothing and again asked by telegram to 'Banks, Cairo' for early sanction,. On the 12th July, I received a letter D.0.Nc.50A/48/6-jr dated the Ist^July, 1948, from Douglas at Cairo referring to the repairs to the Agency building and jetty for the total sum of Rs.7,000/-, and going bn to say 'as this work has not been financially approved in the present year’s financial Vote, I am requesting Headquarters* approval for this expenditure and will notify you as soon as this is obtained.' This appeared to be satisfactory enough even though it had taken six weeks for the Ministry of Works to ask for Headquarters' approval. 5 f ^ 2. On the 26th of July, I received another D.O. letter No.50A/48/7, dated the 15th July, 1948, from Douglas, which contained the sentence which I quoted in my D.O.No.R-204, dated the 29th July, 1948, to you, and went on to say 'However, day to day maintenance will have to proceed and the sundry maintenance matters on the building can be put in hand where such work is essential. Horner, who is the Ministry of Works’ representa tive in Bahrain, will assist you in these matters and I am, therefore, sending him a copy of this letter for his information. In submitting costs for approval to this office, would you please give these as costs for individual items where possible and Horner can no doubt assist you on this point, so that I can inform you of the items which can be approved from this office as opposed to those which I have to submit to London for financial authority.' To this His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE, QBE, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 14th September, 1948.- 2 - To this I replied in my letter D.O.Uo.3281-18/1, dated the 4th August, 1948, of which’I have already sent you a copy. 3. About the 14th of August Horner showed me a memo from Douglas, which, I think, asked him to obtain esti mates for repairs to the Agency jetty and it was perhaps some days later that he appeared in ray office with one ^ { of the al Moayyeds saying that he hod come to get ^ estimate from him. I then wrote my D.0.No.3360^i87l, 1 dated the 17th August, 1948, of which I enclose a copy.^ It would seem to have crossed Cains (?) D.0.NO.50A/48/10, dated the 2nd September, 1948, of which you were sent a copy. 4. The story up-to-date is that after seeing the last quoted letter in your office a day or two ago, I met Horner and asked him when he was going to get on to the Agency repairs. His reply was that he had to go to Muscat from which, as are both aware, his date of return may be quite some period away# I should perhaps explain that I asked him not to get an alternative estimate for repairs here until I had a reply to my D.O# ,3281-18/1, dated the 4th August, 1948, to Douglas. o. The correspondence, I think, speaks for itself and you will doubtless observe that had I been asked to obtain an alternative estimate, I could have done so three months ago, though, as I have written to Douglas, I do not see much point in doing so, 6. I did everything possible to get Horner to look after the air-conditioning units in this Agency and as he failed to do so, I must reiterate at the risk of being tiresome that it is qui + e unrealistic tu expect him to take on the Agency repairs. I imagine that when he comes back from Muscat he will have plenty to do at Jufair. I shall therefore be glad if you can do anything to help to get the estimate forwarded by me sanctioned and allow the contractor to get on with the work. 7. The roof of the Agency is in a very bad state and in order to prevent it being flooded in the v/inter, I am getting a separate estimate for this, and shall have to trouble you with it as neither by correspondence with the Ministry of Works nor/my efforts with Horner to do the work, I am able to achieve anything. Yours sincerely,(61/4) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 20th September, 1948. H.E. Col ' ^ '’tp impp'i Political Resident, Persian Gulf Major A.L.A. Dredge, MBE., Secretary to' H.E. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Mr. A.J. Johnson, MBE., Administrative Officer. Col. W.J. Moody, Residency Surgeon. Mr. C.G. Horner, Asst. Resident Engineer. Mr. E. Thomas, Assistant Secretary. Reference Ministry of Works letter and form Will you please state v/hether you will require any minor alterations painting etc,, to the building occupied by you during the year 1st April, 1949 to 31st March, 1950? Copy to 1) The Political Agent, Bahrain, 2) The Political Agent, Kuwait, 3) The Political Agent/Muse- J - Lfs. T^-L Q.H '0. t ^ y for early completion and return please. Staff Mr. Farrell. Mr. A. Braganza Mr. Smith. Mr. MacPherson. Mr. Mani. Mr. Oldham. Mr. Bainbridge Mr. Domingo, Mr. Christdas. Mr. Shafiuddin below Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegraph; ’’Travaux, Wire, London 1 ' Telephone; Reliance 7611 Ministry of Works, Lambeth Bridge House Albert Embankment LONDON - SE.l July, 1948 Sir, ESTIMATES FOR THE YEAR ENDING 31st MARCH 1950 I am directed by the Ministry of Works to ask that you will be good enough to furnish particulars of any services for which, in your opinion, provision should be made in the Estimates of^this Department for the financial year beginning 1st April next. Particulars should be stated on the enclosed forms and a full explanation should be given as to the necessity for any special requirements. 2 4 It will not be possible, except in cases ( of urgency, to carry out any services for which provision is not made in the Estimates. It is essential therefore that the forms should contain a complete forecast of your requirements for the year. 3* Where furniture requirements can be met locally, the estimated cost of local purchase should be indicated, 4* The completed forms should be returned not later than 31st August next to Senior Architect, Ministry of Works, British Embassy, CAIRO. . I am, Sir, obedient servant Your Sd/- P.AURIOL BARKER 8022 (TRUE COPY)POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 28th September, 1948 I am returning separately to you the re quisition form sent by the Ministry of Works and received with your memorandum No.(61/4), dated the 20th September, 1948. 2. Would it be a great nuisance for you to ask your wife to fill in the estimated cost of the curtains required for the drawing room? I estimate that about 54 yards of material will be required. Estimated cost should, of course, include that of ’making up' the curtains. 3. You indicated in our discussion this morning that Horner would fill in the estimated cost of the items requisitioned by us. So I have not attempted to fill it in. Yours sincere^ v Vlc- t-, i Major A.L.A. Dredge, MBE, Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. /v 4 toPUB LIC H I ILDINGS OVER SEAS WORKS bP,i?VIC3S - . II V Statement of peg uireme nts for consideration i n c onnectlon with l -I e Estimates for the year be g inning Is t_Ap ril, 1949 . PREMISES: P9PJTICAL. AG?N?Y } . pAH^IN. :*v } l 1 l i 5 5 l L (a) (b) Istinajod cos'; Special requirements (additions,^ Washing place for clothes, alterations or improverents) J Servants’ bath house, arid Decorations, painting and major repairs (c) General repairs, ct Servants bath house, flush latrine As decorations, painting and repairs are being • done thoroughly under these heads“this year only £200/- need be budgeted for under these, heads for next year. . J NOTES: 1) Where there is a local Architect or other representative of the Ministry of Forks he should be consulted in the preparatio; of this form. 2) Attention is invited to the Regulations relating to the occupation of Embassy and Legation houses and to the Rules forming Annex 2 to Chapter V, dated June 1925 of the General Consular Instructions. 3) A certificate should be given as to condition in. the case of Consular buildings. In the absence of a competent technical adviser, this should bo signed by the Consular Officer in occupation. 4) Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the tire of the annual test. ; k 8022or PUBLIC _FTJtING 3_ CTEP Rf.SIDprT “A L F f JRNJTI T A C X\J_/ &gt; Statei nent of^requir ements _for consideration in co nnection 'y'/ith o ne Estimat es for the' year '~be ' p;inni ng li,t Apri. 1 ^ A4b PREMISES; P . 0 . L . I . T . I . C A L . A . G . E . N . C . Y e ’, BAHRAIN. L. I Room {Articles beyond {repair which {should be {replaced I i i i i Y y i j i A I i Hall and Stairs Dining Room Drawing Room Ballroom Study Brineipal Bedrooms. Dressing' Rooms etc. Servants Rooms 1 Sofa and 2 Chairs Curtains Supplementary arti r les cons:* iored nccei iary Remarks x Estimated local cos' 3 office chairs with cane seats 3 Spring mattresses . e V o Not repair^ Sofa and able locally Chairs not though they available might be l locally, in England- Curtains might be available for £ y v Not available v locally X iQTE; j.} Services which it is de-siren Anovld receive priority should be marked with an as torisi, 2) Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of 'Works a certificato suou]d be riven as the condition of the appliances cc the time of the An... .1 testn toSeptember 16th, 1948. To H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I am prepared to undertake repairing the Agency Roofs at an estimated cost of 9600/-. The work will consist of the following Filling the cracks with cement &amp; plastering the roof with l£' layer of Ruffa mud and straw. I should be grateful if I could be informed if my offer is acceptable. (Sd.) A.R. Turani, Manama, Building Contractor.Bahrain: Dated 17th October, 1948 Political Agent, Bahrain. n db.31 Dear Sir, . ^‘ith reference to your letter of the 16th October, 1948, my tender for repairs to the roof of the Acrency to the specification mentioned in your letter under reference is Rs.6500/- (six thousand, five hundred). A.R. Tureni, Building Contractor BahrainTelegram: From: To: No: Dated En Clair Political, Bahrain Prodrome, Cairo 628 23rd October, 1948 For Judd from Pelly. Cheapest contractor now refuses to do Agency roof repairs. Next lowest price rupees fivethousand. Current repairs being done to house at considerable expense will be spoilt if it rains through roof which may happen any day. Please cable approval. =POLITICAL= J ^ — KYMTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT CONFIDENTIAL (15809) ( 1942 ) REGULATIONS RELATING TO THE OCCUPATION OF EMBASSY AND LEGATION HOUSES THE PROPERTY OF, OR LEASED BY, HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT The following Regulations in regard to the occupation, use, and maintenance of lands, buildings, furnishings, &amp;c., held by His Majesty's Government in foreign countries for the use of the Diplomatic Service, are issued under the joint authority of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of Works and Planning. * f General Definition of “ Officer-in- Charge.” 1. For the Purpose of these Regulations the description “ OlTicer-in-Charge 'is used to denote an Ambassador, a Minister, a Charge d'Affaires, or any other occupant of an official residence. The Officer-in- ( barge to sign an undertaking. Disputes. 2. The Oflicer-in-Charge shall be held responsible for such charge in the manner prescribed by these Regulations and, on entering into occupation, he shall be required to sign an under taking in the form shown in the Appendix. o. The Minister of Works and Planning shall, after consul tation with the Officer-in-Charge when necessary, decide all matters relating to the maintenance and preservation of Government property and to the expenditure of moneys thereon from public funds. If, however, the Officer-in-Charge should be dissatisfied with the decision of the Minister, it shall be open to him to appeal therefrom to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Should the Secretary of State concur in the decision of the Minister, such decision shall be treated as final and conclusive. In the event of the Secretary of State dissenting from the decision of the Minister, the matter in dispute shall be referred to the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury, whose decision thereon shall be recognised as final and conclusive by all the parties concerned. 4. At each residence shall be kept inventories of the furniture and other properties belonging to His Majesty’s Government, and copies of all instructions and regulations relating to the manage ment of the same. Duplicate copies of such documents will be retained in the Ministry of Works and Planning. Unauthorised alterations or additions to buildings, furnishings, &lt;fcc. 5. The residence and its fittings and furnishings shall be deemed complete and suitable in all respects and no alteration or addition of any kind whatsoever to buildings, fittings, or furnishings nor any additional hiring shall be paid for from public funds, unless such alteration, addition or additional hiring shall have been previously approved by the Ministry of Works and Planning. Should alterations or additions be made without such approval, the Officer-in-Charge shall be held responsible not only for the expense of the alterations or additions, but also for the expense of restoring such buildings, fittings, or furnishings, to their original state. Inspections by the Ministry of Works and Planning. 10364 6. From time to time the Minister shall cause a survey of the buildings, fittings, and furnishings to be made by one of his repre sentatives. Note will be made of any deficiency, misuse, or damage in respect of Government property, and the cost of replacing any missing article, or of making good any damage or defect arising from neglect or unfair or improner use, will be recovered from the Officer-in-Charge. [33277] b! - 2 A j / ft u ^8 Care of buiidiugs furnibhings, &amp;c., during absence 01/ leave. Change of occupation. Custody of buildings, furnishings. Ac., pending arrival of new Offioer-in- Ch arge. Custody of buildings, furnishings. Ac..- where there are two residences. * Precautions against fire, damage by storm flood, Ac. II Contagious or infectious diseases: vermin 7. Proper arrangements shall be made by the Officer-in-Chaige for the safe custody and care of the buildings, furnishings, &amp;c., and for the upkeep of the garden during his absence on lea\e, and he shall be responsible for the cost of the measures taken to tills end. 8. On change of occupation, the outgoing Officer-in-t barge shall inform the Ministry of Works and Planning of the probable date of his departure and shall leave the premises in a clean and habitable condition. The incoming Officer-in-Charge shall inform the Ministry of Works and Planning of the probable date on which he will take up occupation, and, on arrival, he or his representative shall at once check the inventories and certify that the fittings and furnishings are in good condition (fair wear and tear excepted) and complete; or. alternatively, report to the Ministry of Works and Planning at once any deficiencies or damage so that, if arising from neglect or unfair or improper use, the cost may be recovered from the outgoing Officer-in-Charge. In the absence of such a report, the incoming Officer-in-Charge shall be held responsible for any damage or deficiencies noted at a later date. To facilitate the checking of the inventories, the outgoing Officer-in-Charge shall cause all articles temporarily moved from room to room to he returned to the positions indicated in the inventories and all keys to be attached to their respective articles. 9. During the interval between the departure of the outgoing Office-in-Charge and the arrival of the incoming Officer-in-Charge, or on the death of the Officer-in-Charge, the Officer-in-Charge of the post for the time being shall be responsible for the proper custody of the buildings, fittings, and furnishings. The arrange ments made to this end shall be reported at once to the Ministry of Works and Planning, who will authorise any necessary expenditure pending the arrival of the new Officer-in-Charge, such as the cost of caretaking, heating, lighting and the upkeep of the garden, &amp;c. 19. At posts where there are two official residences for the use of the Offioer-in-Charge, the cure of the residence which is unoccupied as well as the residence which is occupied, together with the fittings and furnishings, shall be the responsibility of the Officer- in-Charge, but the caretaker's wages shall be a charge upon public funds. 11. The Officer-in-Charge shall be held responsible for the safe custody of the buildings, fittings, furnishings, &amp;c. He shall take all reasonable precautions against hre and damage by storm or flood and he shall be held responsible for the care and periodical testing of the fire-fighting equipment supplied by the Ministry of Works and Planning. A certificate as to the condition of the fire fighting equipment shall be forwarded annually to the Ministry of Works and Planning. , In the interests of safety he shall consult the Ministry of W prks and Planning before installing any electric lighting fittings involving additional wiring or any additional electrical appliances, and in no case shall wiring “flex” be permitted to run along skirtings or picture mouldings. ^ Incinerators provided by the Ministry of Works and Planning shall be used for the destruction of old papers, &amp;c., in quantity. Loss or damage by fire, storm, flood, theft, &amp;c., shall be reported at once to the Ministry of Works and Planning. 12. Whenever, in consequence of the occurrence of a contagious or infectious disease in the household of an Officer-in- Charge. disinfection has become necessary in order to protect the health of the inmates, the Officer-in-Charge shall be responsible for providing that the premises are sufficiently disinfected, and, if requested, for procuring from a medical officer a certificate that this has been done. The Officer-in-Charge shall be responsible also for the eradication of vermin and for seeing that the residence is kept free from vermin.Interieiince with rights appertain ing to (Govern ment properties. Occupation by unauthorised persons. Hirings. Auctions. Kequisitions and annual require ments : minor ledecorations and repairs. Shipping arrangements. Addresses for correspondence 13. The Otficer-in-Charge shall take all steps to protect the rights and amenities appertaining to the property of His Majesty s Government and shall report to the Ministry of Works and Planning at once any proposals affecting the same. 14. In no circumstances shall the buildings or lands or any portion thereof be lent or sublet to or occupied or used by persons who are not entitled to accomodation at Government expense without the previous sanction of the Ministry of Works and Planning. 15. New premises shall not be hired or existing hirings renewed without the prior sanction of the Ministry of Works and Planning. 16. The holding of auctions of private effects in or upon the premises is strictly forbidden. 17. All requisitions for the erection of buildings, for altera tions to buildings or for maintenance services (see paragraphs 20 and 23), or for the purchase or hiring of property, or for the supply or maintenance of fittings and furnishings (see paragraphs 30 and 32), shall be sent to the Ministry of Works and Planning accom panied by full particulars of the requirements and their estimated cost in local currency and the sterling equivalent. So far as possible, such requirements shall be communicated to the Ministry of Works and Planning in reply to the enquiry issued by that Department annually in June as to the requirements of the post for the following year, so that, if approved, provision may be made in the annual Estimates; for, in the absence of the necessary provision in the Estimates, it will not be possible to grant requests involving any but the smallest expenditure, except on grounds of urgency. Where there is a local representative of the Ministry of Works and Planning (e.g., at Shanghai for the Far East, except Siam; at Istanbul for South-East Europe and the Middle East; at Tehran for Iran; and local Architects at the majority of the posts elsewhere), such officer shall be consulted by the Officer-in-Charge before submitting requisitions to the Ministry of Works and Planning. The local representative has delegated authority to order ordinary minor redecorations and repairs to both buildings and furnishings. At posts where there is no local representative, the Officer-in-Charge will be given such delegated authority. Note. — Officers of a rank below that of Head of Mission should submit their requirements through the Head of Mission. 18. Goods sent by the Ministry of Works and Planning should be unpacked at‘ once and any damage or loss should be reported immediately to the local agent of the shipper and to the Ministry of Works and Planning. Should it be necessary for bills of lading to be endorsed before the goods can be examined, the endorsement should be qualified by a note explaining the circum stances, e.g., “ signed in order to obtain delivery.' The advice note (sent independently of the goods) states to what point delivery is to be made by the shipper, and care should be taken to avoid paying any charges properly payable by him. Usually the shipper bears all dues and outgoings (except customs duty) to the point shown in the advice note. 19. Communications to the Ministry of Works and Planning should be addressed as follows :— (a) If they are in reply to communications from that Depart ment, in accordance with the directions given at the head of the Ministry of Works and Planning s note- paper. b 2 [33277 ]4 Upkeep of buildings, Ac., by the Ministry of Works and Planning. Cleaning: cost of heating, lighting, water, &amp;e. Responsibility for repair of defects arising from neglect, Ac. {b) By Officers-in-Charge at all posts (including Siam) else where than in the Far East if they refer— (1) to MATTERS OF IMPORTANCE— The Secretary, Ministry of Works and Planning, Lambeth Bridge House, Albert Embankment, London, S.E. 1. (2) To MINOR matters concerning the maintenance of buildings or grounds (including electric light fittings)— The Director of Works, Ministry of Works and Planning, Lambeth Bridge House, Albert Embankment, London, S.E. I. (3) To MINOR matters concerning furniture (exclusive of electric light fittings)— The Controller of Supplies, Ministry of Works and Planning, Lambeth Bridge House, Albert Embankment, London, S.E. 1. (c) By Officers in-Charge in the Far East (except Siam) on all subjects— The Divisional Architect, H.B.M. Ministry of Works and Planning, British Consulate-General, Shanghai. Buildings 20. The fabric of all Government buildings (including Chancery offices), together with the fixtures and fittings, boundary walls, entrance gates and approaches, shall be kept in repair by the Ministry of Works and Planning, who shall be responsible also for periodical painting, papering and distempering, and for the repair and renewal of the sanitary, water, heating, lighting, refrigerating and cooking installations, except that, where cabinet refrigerators are concerned, the Ofhcer-in-Charge shall be responsible for the costs of cleaning, adjustments and minor repairs, including the replace ment of small parts. In the case of hired buildings, the Ministry of Works and Planning shall be responsible for such of the foregoing services as are not the landlord's responsibility. 21. The Offfcer-in-Charge shall be responsible for the cost of ordinary and periodical cleaning, including the sweeping of chimneys and the cleaning of kitchen flues and boilers, tanks and cisterns. He shall defray also the cost of fuel and stoking, gas water, oil and electric current. Where water is supplied from wells or waterworks controlled by His Majesty's Government the cost of raising or otherwise handling the water for all purposes shall, except where other arrangements have been authorised, be borne by him. Where an independent electric lighting plant has been provided, the Ministry of Works and Planning will bear the cost of running the plant subject to the payment by the residents of a fixed charge per unit for current consumed as may be decided upon from time to time. 22. The Officer-in-Charge shall be held personally responsible for the due preservation of the official fixtures and fittings and for the cost of repair of defects arising from carelessness, neglect or unfair or improper use on the part of the members of his household or his guests or from the keeping of animals and birds.* 5 Sanction for repairs, &lt;ftc.: urgent repairs. Frequency of redecorations. Damage by storm, fire, &lt;ftc. Preparation of schemes involving payment of a fee. Mosquito proofing. Responsibility for upkeep of gardens, grounds and tennis-courts. * Alterations. Furnishing of residences. Upkeep of official furnishings: cleaning, &amp;c. 23. The sanction of the Ministry of Works and Planning shall be obtained before redecorations, repairs or renewals are effected (see paragraph 17), but when these are urgently necessary the Officer-in- Charge may have the work done, subject to the covering approval or the Ministry of Works and Planning. The Officer-in-Charge shall, however, report the circumstances immediately and be prepared to prove the urgency and necessity of the work. 24. External painting or colour washing shall not as a rule be done more frequently than once in every three or four years, nor internal redecoration more frequently than once in every six or seven years.but any necessary redecoration will be done on each change of occupation. Such work at other times than these shall not be paid for from public funds unless specially authorised beforehand by the Ministry of Works and Planning, who must be satisfied that the need for it has arisen only from fair wear and tear. 25. In case of damage by storm, fire, or other casualty, the Officer-in-Charge may order urgent repairs to be executed at once, bearing in mind the landlord’s responsibility in the case of hired buildings; but where the damage is extensive he shall obtain the approval of the Ministry of Works and Planning before ordering any but the most indispensable repairs. 26. The Officer-in-Charge shall obtain the approval of the Ministry of Works and Planning before giving any instructions for the preparation of schemes or estimates involving the payment of a fee if the work is not proceeded with. 27. Buildings will not be mosquito-proofed except at posts where malaria is prevalent. A medical certificate shall accompany all requisitions for mosquito proofing. Grounds 28. The Officer-in-Charge shall defray all expenditure / necessary for the care of maintenance in good order of the garden and grounds, including the cost of water, the provision of tools, &amp;c., I except where, owing to exceptional circumstances, special arrange- | ments are in force. The Officer-in-Charge shall be responsible also for the upkeep of the tennis-court where one has been provided exceptionally. 29. The approval of the Ministry of W orks and Planning shall be obtained before any trees (except such as are of small size and value) are cut down or removed, and before any alterations are made in the garden lay-out which are likely to increase the cost of upkeep. Furnishings 30. Each residence shall be provided, at public expense, with the necessary furnishings, such as reception room and bedroom furniture, curtains, carpets, loose covers, table and standard lamps and other lighting fittings, fans and refrigerators, bdt not articles of a decorative character, such as pictures (other than portraits of Their Majesties and other portraits or pictuies exceptionally), clocks ornaments, &amp;c., nor pianos, wireless sets or billiard tables. Table linen, bed linen, &amp;c., blankets, bedspreads and valances, &amp;c., crockery china and glassware, cutlery and other table-ware except silver in some places, kitchen utensils, vacuum cleaners, laundry aonliances and other articles of domestic equipment shall be the responsibility of the Officer-in-Charge as also the provision of o-arden furniture and of additional tables, chairs and hat and coat racks awnings, &amp;c., required on the occasion of large recep- dons' &amp;c. Chancery furniture is provided and maintained by the Ministry of Works and Planning. 31 The official furnishings shall be maintained by the | Ministry of Works and Planning, but the Officer-in-Charge shall be responsible for the cost of ordinary and periodical cleaning and6 * Sanction for repairs and renewals. Responsibility for repair of defects arising from neglect, &lt;fce. Removal or storage of official furnishings. Damage to silk, ttc., wall coverings. Furnishings hired with premises. Existing non official furnishings. Identification marks. i i Payment of a rent for use of official furnish ings by officers of a rank below' that of Head of Mission. Service of plate. Disposal of sur plus or worn-out articles. K Officer-in-Charge to defray local expenditure: funds. polishing, the beating of carpets and the cleaning or washing of curtains, loose covers, &amp;c. 32. The sanction of the Ministry of Works and Planning shall be obtained before repairs or renewals are put in hand; but small repairs arising from fair wear and tear may be ordered by the Omcer-in-Charge up to a maximum of £2 in any one case and a limit or £5 in any one year (see paragraph 17). 33. The Officer-in-Charge shall be held personally responsible for the due preservation of the official furnishings and for the cost of repair of defects arising from carelessness, neglect or unfair or improper use on the part of members of his household or his guests or from the keeping of animals and birds. 34. The Officer-in-Charge shall be required to use the official furnishings as part of the equipment of the post, and such furnishings shall not be removed from the residence nor stored without the consent of the Ministry of Works and Planning. In any event, the cost of making good defects arising from storage exposure to the attacks of moth or vermin, &amp;c., shall be borne by the Officer-in-Charge. 35. Pictures shall not be hung nor brackets, &amp;c., fixed on walls covered with silk or similar material. Should this rule be disregarded, the Officer-in-Charge shall be held responsible for making good any damage caused thereby. 36. In the Case of hired buildings the Officer-in-Charge shall be responsible equally for the due preservation of any furnishings hired with the premises, whether such furnishings are of the kind ordinarily provided or not. 37. Existing articles not now provided at public expense shall be withdrawn. Alternatively, the cost of repair shall be borne b\- the Officer-in-Charge. 38. The various items of official furniture, &amp;c., shall be numbered or otherwise marked to enable such items to be identified in the inventory and the Officer-in-Charge shall be responsible for seeing that these identification marks are maintained, and that the copy of the inventory at the post is kept up to date. 39. The use of official furnishings (including refrigerators) by an officer of a rank below that of Head of Mission shall be subject to the payment of a rent of 7^ per cent, per annum calculated on the cost of the furnishings exclusive of freight. The rent (including that for periods of ordinary absence on leave) is to be deducted quarterly from salary. 40. Where an official service of plate has been provided the Officer-in-Charge shall be considered personally responsible for seeing that it is properly safeguarded at all times and kept in good condition and intact. The cost of maintaining it shall be borne by the Ministry of Works and Planning, but any losses or injuries due to neglect, negligence or unfair or improper use shall be made good at once by the Officer-in-Charge. The plate shall frequently be checked with the inventory and a certificate as to its completeness and condition shall be sent to the Ministry of Works and Planning immediately after the 1st January each year. 41. Worn-out or surplus articles shall not be discarded or otherwise disposed of without the previous sanction of the Ministry of Works and Planning. Accounts Note.— Officers of a rank below that of Head of Mission should not defray or account for expenditure direct, but through the Head of Mission. 42. The Officer-in-Charge shall defray, on behalf of the Ministry of Works and Planning, all expenditure incurred locally in accordance with these Regulations. 47 Accounting. procedure. * * Receipts from sale of land. Ac. Payments on account. \ For this purpose he shall obtain funds from time to time, as required by one of the following methods : — (1) By drawing a bill on the Ministry of Works and Planning at three days’ sight, the balance in hand to be kept as low as possible, consistent with immediate requirements. On the day the bill is drawn, he shall notify the Ministry of Works and Planning on the form provided for the purpose, and at the same time forward a certificate, bv a banker or a merchant, of the rate of exchange at which the bill has been drawn. (2) By the use of Foreign Office funds in approved cases. I he transfer of such funds to meet the Ministry of Works and Planning expenditure shall be recorded in the accounts rendered to each Department. (3) By application to the Ministry of Works and Planning for telegraphic transfer where it is not possible to obtain funds ar described in (1) or (2) above. 43. The Officer-in-Charge shall account to the Ministry of Works and Planning for all receipts obtained and payments made in accordance with the preceeding paragraph. This shall be done quarterly, in the form prescribed, immediately following the 30th June, the 30th September, the 31st December and the 31st March. Each quarterly account shall be a complete statement of all receipts and payments made during the quarter and all payments shall be fully supported by receipted bills, estimates, &amp;e., which shall relate solely to the items in question. Receipted bills for freightage, customs and other duties should state the date when the consignment was received, the number of packages forming the consignment and the numbers and marks on the packages. . The various receipts and payments shall be shown in local currency, but in the case of a Bill of Exchange the sterling amount also shall be given, together with the rate at which the Bill was negotiated. . . . A brief translation shall be given of any item appearing in the account in a language other than English or French. The inventory number should be quoted in the case of furniture. Should no transaction have taken place during the quarter an account shall be rendered, nevertheless, stating that fact. The Officer-in-Charge shall, so far as possible, ensure that tradesmen’s bills are rendered and paid promptly; and that every advantage is taken of discounts for prompt payment. In no case may funds be entrusted to a third party for the pavment of tradesmen's accounts. These should be paid direct b\ the Chancery, on the Certificate where applicable of the local lepie- sentative of the Ministry of Works and Planning. 44 Receipts arising from the sale of land, buildings, &amp;c., shad be disposed of as directed by the Ministry of Works and Planning. 45 In order to meet the requirements of the Comptroller and Auditor-General, the following conditions of payment shall be strictly adhered to :— (a) When a payment on account is made in connexion with 3 .n.v service for which &lt;x contract hcis not heen concluded, the receipt shall invariably be accompanied by a certificate to the effect that, at the date of payment, work had been completed, or materials delivered, to the full value of the amount of the advance. (b) In the case of contracts which provide for definite payments to be made at certain progressive stages of the work (e q so much on the completion of foundations, a nirther sum on completion of walls, &amp;c.), these payments shall be supported by certificates stating that the woik has been executed in accordance with the terms of contract, and that the contractor is entitled to payment of the specified amount.Examination of accounts by Ministry of Works and Planning. (c) When a contract does not provide for definite payments as the work proceeds, certificates shall be furnished as detailed at (a). (d) When a contract provides for an advance payment on signing, or whenever a payment is made before com mencement of work in accordance with local custom, the next payment shall be supported by a certificate to the effect that, at the date of payment, work has been executed, or material delivered, to the full value of the two payments. 46. In the event of an account requiring amendment, the Officer-in-Charge will be informed as soon as possible, and subject to his observations (which must be made at once) the amendments shall stand; but, should the Officer-in-Charge be dissatisfied with the decision of the Ministry of Works and Planning, he shall have the right of appeal as provided in paragraph 3 above. [January 1, 1940.] APPENDIX Undertaking to be Siqned by Officers-in-Charge in accordance with Paragraph 2 I HAVE received a copy of the “ Regulations relating to the Occupation of Embassy and Legation Houses the Property of, or Leased by, His Majesty's Government,' dated the I have read the said Regulations and I Undertake to recognise as a legal claim on me, or on my estate, the liability to repay to the Minister of Works and Planning the cost of making good such deficiencies or damage as may be decided to be properly chargeable to me under the said Regulations.COP Y j (ES0/4O/Bah.lO3) MINISTRY 0^ WOPYS, PA^PAT V , 15th October 194R. Dear Major Dredee, As a result of our conversation on the 14th October on the subject of Mlnlstrv o** w orks responsi bilities at Jufair, I think that it would be as we' 1 ! to let you have a written summary of the position, with which you may not be too familiar. This Is as fo'Hows:- 1) XXX 2) No additions or alterations to buildings or services should be made without written authoritv from the Ministry of Works representative (^orei^n Office regulations for the occupation of public buildings overseas refers). 3) No expenditure should be incurred on the Minis- try of Works account without prior approval from the Ministry of Works Office, Cairo, except in the case of maintenance work of an urgent nature, when the cost of one item in any one month should not exceed £15. 4) Applications to Cairo ^or approval o** expendi ture on buildines or services should, whenever pos sible be accompanied by competitive tenders. I hope that this makes things clear, but T will, be glad to answer any other questions. Yours sincerely, Sgd. (V.Noble) Major A.I..A. Dredee, M.B.E., Secretary to Nis Excellency the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat.Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : 51421, 41217, 43830. 50 A/48/14 MINISTRY OF WORKS \G 3 BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 27th October, 1%8. With reference to your telegram No* 628 /C dated 23rd October, we have today cabled Noble asking him to obtain further information regarding the proposed repairs to the Agency roof. Noble is due back here shortly and as soon as the question has been discussed with him we will communicate with you again. &gt; / K.W. Judd. for Senior Architect. C. J* fbddjf j Esq. ,0.B.E. , Political Agent, Bahrein. KWJ/AK.Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : 51421, 41217, 43830. &gt;0i iD \ * MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 50 .A/W 15 . ( 3 - 1 ) 5th November, 1948. C.J. Pelly, Esq,, O.B.E., Political Resident, Bahrein. The following telegram was sent to you on 2.11,48:- n Telegram No, 825, Your telegram 628. Bitunen roof repairs to Agency with ‘''N specification left hy Noble agreed. Please put in hand. Ends. Judd.” ESI/EO. for D.W. GAIN, Ministry of Works, Cairo. 4th November, 1948. yu,.fJD rg No Dfited 1st Decerrt-r, 194F Dear Ministry of Works We enclose bills for Rc.340/- aiid Rs.45/- for two electric fans and some sofa covers, respectively. The former has been paid for by us, but we write to ask whether the amount ma^ I e debited to tie Ministry of Works account, and the latter may be paid from the same source. * We siould explain that 1 afore the purchase of these fans there were no liana fans whatsoever in this Agency. The Ministry of Works, CAIRO.&lt; ‘; Telephone 76 Ai. Every House Needs WESTINGHOUSE (9 FOLIO No. 48. October 2, 194 8. ■Mr..,. C. J» Pelly, p,D,E,, I.C.S. Agent. Bahrain. ‘Dr. To THE MODERN ART STUDIO DEALERS IN Westinghouse Radios, F^ins, Refrigerators, Tubes and Household Appliances, Royal Typewriters, Spare Parts for Radios and Typewriters, Keystone Movie Cameras, Projectors and Telephoto Lens, Decca Gramophones and Pickups Decca and Brunswick Records - Monthly Consignments Conway Stewart Pens and Pencils All Photographic Supplies, etc., etc., etc. BAHRAIN. WTele grams TOORAHI BAHRAIN 0 0 R A N 1 C*dl y*ir MERC HANTS &amp; (jij-* r R.A C T 0 R ot j —* i; if I'I Debit Note. Political Agent. Bahrein• To. Cost of repaire to the Agency Building and Jitty, including painting, white washing etc. ,r Cost of repairing the roof of the Agency Building with bitumen and sand. ' n Cost of repairing the roof of the J.A T s Court and Servant Quarters including white washing, painting, and varnishing. ” Cost of lying a pipe line to Servant Latrine tT Cost of repairing of Tennis Court walls Tf Cost of painting the Tennis Court walls with double Coating of green paint. ff Cost of 20 Chandles for t e Tennis Court. Rs. 12000.0. (Rupees Twelve Thousand). Has been paid to me, being thebalance to my credit. (Rupees Seveh Thousand Seven Hundred Sixty only). Rs. 10225. 0. ' 5000 . 0. ” 3500 . 0. ' 100 . 0 . ' 550. 0. 350. 0. ' 35. 0. Rs. 19760. 0. ' 12000 . 0 . RsT 7760. O'. Please note, in addition to the above, the following extra works have been carried out by P.Als verbal instructions. Recementing the Agency floor, replacing where necessary all the broken Glasses of the windows Upstairs, Downstairs, Garage, and cooks residence and installing two windows in Superintendent’s Office and repairing water courses in the Gardens, and covering the northern side of the Agency with Shells, and Building a wall near the Agency and the labour charges on replacing the wire Gauge and plating the Fender of the Fire Mantle with Brass. S'/? E. &amp;. 0. E. Bahrein. Jan. 2&amp;th, 1949 .U\ Tele grams T00RAK1 BAHRAIN A. R. T 0 0 R A N I GENERAL MERCHANTS &amp; CONTRACTOR (Jl^ C-Jljil; O’- 'OtG. . . T s* Politic at# Bahr in. To. Co of re poire to the Agency hull in ( r anh Jitty, inclurliny point in-, t. ite \:a ain^ etc . n cJo ,t of repairiny the roof of the Agency Building iith bit' uoon an' 3 an • Cost of repair!:i- t o roof of the J.A* s Court and servant Quarters inducing v/hite wash in , painting, and v mishing# Cost of lying a pipe lino t Servant Latrine Cost of repairing of Tennis Court walls ” Cost of paint nr -ciie Tennis Court walls with Coublo Coatin ’ of preen naint. Co :&gt;t of 20 Chandlos f r t e Tennis Court* is. 1 225* . 5000 . 0 . f • 35 J. . 10. , 550. o, 350 . 0 0 Ss. Tf wO . 'cs. 12 -00.0. (hupees Twelve Thousand). Has be or paid to ne, being th balance to my credit. (Rupees boveh Thou a nd Jeven Hundred uisrty onl; ). Plea: e note, in addition to the above, the foxlowinn or j have been carried out by P#Als verbal instructi» Rocement,n the Agency floor, replacing where necessary all t- hen Glasses of tee win do-, s l petal as, o'not irs, s Garage, and cooks residence and installing two windows in Superintendent’s Office and repairing -ter courses in the Gardens, and covering the northern side of t e Agency *' ith shells, and Building a vail near t e Agency and the labour charges on replacing the wire Gauge and platin * tV- Tea or of the Fir I .antic with raos# 19700 . 12 l -’U0. ns. r* Pp ri c* •U • ( 7 , . 'w . • ^ . Bahrein# Jan# 2 th, 19AS1S.O.No. R-JM' ‘^l 1 ! U°&gt; POLITICAL AOEKCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 20th March, 1949. Dear Powell I enclose a copy of a telegram No.181, dated the 9th March, 1949, from the Ministry of Works, Cairo, and should he grateful if you could advise as to what is re quired in replv to it. The first advance of Rs.5,000/- was made with Noble’s agreement as you will see from the copy of the minute which I attach. The sanction order for the second was, my Accountant tells me, sent to the Ministry of Works with the quarterly account. 2. As far as I car find out from my papers, Toorani's original estimate for repairs to the Agency and the jetty was Rs.10,225/-, hut,as he dealt with Horner about this, the sanctioned estimate or a copy of it is probably in your office. Can you produce this? 3. For the repair of the roof I have the Ministry of Works’ letter sanctioning an estimate of Rs.5,000/-. 4. If you think that what is required is a list of the work done against the payments made, then I supoose we could get Toorani to make it and perhaps you would help in checking it. Yours sincerely, H.S. Powell, Esquire, Ministry of Works Representative Bahrain.3T- JM Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO Telephone: 51241, 41217, 43830 Ref. 50A/49/6 MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 24th March, 1949» Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your M.O.W. Account for the Quarter ended. 31st Deceofcer, 1948, and wish to make the following observations Vouchers 1 (pt) &amp; lo(pt). As advised in Cairo letter 50V4 8 / 2 0 of 18th Decani)er 1948, cleaning costs are not chargeable to the M.O.W. Vote and it is requested that Rupees.20.00 be refunded in your current M.O.W. Account. Vouchers 10(pt) &amp; Ms. The Resident Bigineer has queried the necessity for the retention of an attendant for the Air Conditioning plant after Septenfcer when the plant was shut down. The expenditure is passed by this Office but without prejudice to any decision which may be reached by M.O.W. Headquarters, and your observations would be appreciated. lx* • Vouchers 8 &amp; 16. A3 requested in our telegram 181 of 9th March 1949 further information is required regarding the advances to Toorani of Rupees.12,000. j I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Senior Architect and Director of Works and Services. H.M. Political Agent, Bahrein. DWC/LBPMOW.12/49/112 b MINISTRY OF WORKS, POLITICAL RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 23rd. April, 19^9- Dear Agency, Reference your R • 193 l°th April 19^9 • I eni afraid I am unable to advise you y on this matter since the work was carried out '* before my arrival in Bahrain. Further to Mr.Pelly's letter R-132-16/1 dated 20th March 19^9, I informed Ministry Of Works, Cairo that the work detailed in Toor^ni's statement has been carried out £ while Cairo appear to have been advised of Toorani's estimatej I am unable to find any record in this office of their approval for the work to be carried out. Ministry of Works, Representative.50.A/W/9. H.M. Political A^ent Bahrein. Accounts 2.C. With reference to the Bahrein P.X. Accent for the December Quarter of 1948 and to Cairo memo 50.i/49/J of 22/3/49 and copy of Cairo letter 50. V49/r of 24/3/49 to the Arency. In the light of further in arnation supplied by the Agency the Deputy Resident Engineer is prepared to acceot as a charge to M.O.W. the wages of the attendant for the A.6. plant - Vouchers 10 (pt) and 14 refer. The Agency has requested that vouchers cover in; the expenditure not chargeable to M.O.W. (Vouchers 1 (pt), 10 (pt) - Rupees 20) should be returned and has stated' that the refund will be made upon receipt of these vouchers.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, S,0.No.R-286 The 21st June, 194S. Dear Mr. Powell, The Agency swimming pool is leaking badly and urgently needs attention* accordjng to an estimate by a Contractor, Mr.Barkat Ali* I should be grateful for your aporoval. Repairs would cost Rs.150/- Yours sincerely, H. S. Pov/ell, Esquire, Ministry of Works, Jufair *COPY Reference MO.'/. 7/49/317. 1st Secretary, Polltjcsl Residency, Bahrein. Reference our conversations the work on Mani 1 s qnart Q rs has heen carried ont and separate meters fitted. Sd/- C.G.Horner Assistant Resident Engineer, Persian Gulf. 30th June, 1949.h ? V O ' $■ Reference. E^D/^9/6 Bahrein Agency Accounts . Horner With reference to your minute MOWI 3 / 49 / 2 99 of i5th June, the cost of electric lamps for use in the Agency hss now been accepted as a charge against M.O.W., as in’the confusion c'uping your absence it is quite likely thrt the Political Agent did hot realise that stocks of lamps were held at Jufair. - \ With reference to the payments to Sayed Amin, these should be continued for the time being . Mr. Waters will investigate the necessity for the continuation of these payments on his forth coming visit. V A Sd/- V.Noble. for (0.Waters) Engineer , Ministry of Works. Cairo. 25th June, 19^9• Copy forwarded to the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein for information . (C . (r&lt;Horner) Assistant Resident Engineer. Persian C-ulf. ?th July, 19^9•■Ts - : filA Reference....M 0 W... 12 /.k 9 / 3^2 Political Agency, Mr.P.D.Stobert. /■* Swlmmlnp: Pool ■ A . J / I refer to your S.O. No.R-286 dated 21st. June-49, and oue conversation of the 24th June-49. Barnet All, Contractor has been instructed make good to the worst cracks in the sides and bottom of the swimming pool where it is thought the water may seep through. As I pointed out the reoairs cannot be guaranteed and at a later date the whole of the pool will have to be 1 'cemented. (H.S.Powell) Ministry of Works, 25th June- 1 49. (849) Wi 1 5323/2639 590,000 5/46 JC&amp;SLtd G P 736/2i0 (REGiMITE)Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : 49700 50A/49A2 MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 30th June, 1949• Sir, I have to inform you that with my return to the U«K« on -transfer, Mr. G.W. Pollard, A.R.I.B.A., is taking over this Post as Senior Architect, Director of Yforks and Services (.JLddle East) as from the 1st July, 1949* I am, Sir, your obedient Servant, Se^ or 'Arclii t act, G.J. Pelley, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agency, BAHREIN Director of Works &amp; Services (kiddle East)8;2 Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : 49700. i W) 50.A/W/12. MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. st July, 19A9. Sir, I have to inform you that as fran today I have assumed responsibility for the direction of this Post fran Mr. J.A. Douglas, A.R.T.B.A., Senior Architect, who is returning to the U.K. on transfer. I am. Sir, Your Servant, Pollard) Senior Architect, Director of Works &amp; Services (Middle East) . C.J. Pel ley, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, BAHREIN. gwp/eoTelegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY b-9700 21st June, l%-9' Sir, I refer to your letter 1130-18/l.of 27th April, 19A9, and to Cairo letter 5QA/k9/9 of 10th May, 19^-9. I enclose extracts of Vouchers 1 and 10 in your 14 0. W. Account for the December Quarter, 19A8, and should be obliged if you would credit the Ministry with Rupees 20 in your current 14 0. W. Account. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant. for Director of Works &amp; Services. H.B.24 Pc Bahrein. DWC/RLTelegraph: 'Travaux, Wire, London' Ministry of Works, Telephone: Reliance 7611 Lambeth Bridge House, Albert Embankment, Ref: A.S. 15/1 LONDON, 3.E.1. 16 th Jul y&gt;. 1% - 9 Sir, Estimates for the year ending 31 st March, 1951 I am directed by the Minister of *Vorks to ask that you will be good enough to furnish particulars of any services for which, in your opinion, provision should be made in the- Estimates of this Department for the financial year beginning 1st April next. Particulars should be stated on the enclosed forms and a full explanation should be given as to the necessity for any special requirements. \It will not be possible, except in cases of urgency, to carry out any services for which provision is not- made in the Estimates. It is essential therefore that the forms should ' contain a complete forecast of your requirements for the year. 3. Whore furniture requirements can be met locally, ‘the’ estimated cost of local purchase should be indicated. 4* The completed forms should be returned not later than 31st August next to . Director of Works and Services (Middle East), C.J. Pelley, Esq., O.B.E., H.M. Political Agent, A H R E I N . IwietTy. WPF&amp;s* British Embassy, CAIRO, I am, Sir Your obedient Servant,8022 M.O,W, 1891 PUBLIC BUILDINGS OVERSE AS RESIDENTIAL FURNITURE Statement of requirements for consideration in connection ^ y/lth the Estimates for the year beginning 1st Aprils _ ^^ All Residential Preioises H.LL Political .Igency, Bahreiji Room Articles beyond repair which should be replaced Supplement ary articles considered necessary Remarks Estimated local cost -'No''' ' Mall and Stairs Dining Room Drawing Room Ballroom i Study principal bedrooms, Dressing Rooms, etc. / Servants Rooms i Note: 1. Services which it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2 . V/here fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the Annual test.% M.0.W.1892 PUBLIC BUILDINGS OVERSEAS WORIIS SERVICES Statement of requirements for consideration in connection with the Estimates for the year beginning 1st April, iqSA ~ Those owned by H.M.G. an d hired by Ministry o f 'Torks PKEUvCLSES : - KM* PoLiticaL Jygenoy^ BLahr^m*. &gt; (a) Special requirements (additions, alterations or improvements). (b) Decorations, painting and major repairs. (c) General repairs, etc, 8022 See Notes overleafNotes 1. 'Where there is a local Architect or other , representative of the Ministry of Works he should be consulted in the preparation of this form. 2. Attention is invited to the Regulations relating to the occupation of Embassy and Legation Houses and to the Rules forming Annex 2 to Chapter V. dated June 1925 of the General Consular Instructions. 3. A certificate should be given as to condition in the case of Consular buildings* In the absence of a competent technical adviser, this should be signed by the Consular Officer in occupation* A. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as. to the condition of the appliances at the time of the annual test. 8022(**&gt;87 8022 M.O.W, 189^ PUBLIC BUILDINGS OVERSEAS OFFICE FUBNITURE Statement of requirements for consideration in connection with the Estimates for the year beginning 1st April, Wso PREMISES .All Office Premises Political Agency, Bahrein Office Furniture, Floor Coverings, Blinds etc. Room Articles beyond repair which should be replaced. Supp 1 erne ht ary articles considered necessary. Remarks Estimated local cost f Note : 1. Services v/hich it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the Annual test.No. -18/X. Political Agency, Bahrain, September 24, 1949 Memorandum I should be glad if you could arrange for the early replacement of burnt-out bulbs in the Agency. H.d. ,Taking Political Agent. The Assistant Resident Engineer, ^Ministry of V;orks, Residency, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.wmm MHM Political Agency, Bahrain, October 6, 1949 Memorandum I see that according to the letter sent from London on July 16 our requirements for the 19 estimates had to be in Cairo by August 31 last. As in addition this came in a letter addressed to Mr.Pelly personally you will judge what chance we have had of complying. I suggest you should tell your Department to give us reasonable time in future and to address all official correspondence to the post concerned and not to any particular person. So far as estimates for repairs and main tenance are concerned I presume that you and Mr.Horner will cover the ground. My own suggestions are that on the balcony the wooden screens between the pillars should be taken away so as to give more light. The Agency gets very little direct sunlight and now that it is air conditioned there is no point in keeping it so dark. I suggest that the second panel on the right hand side of the fireplace should be turned into a recess to correspond with the left hand side where the air conditioner has been brought in. (Drawing Room) Also that the wall above the fireplace ^ should be repaired and the ceiling repainted cream all over (cutting out the dark strips that give the present Old Tudor Tea Shoppe effect) and the walls colour washed in a cream that, lanlike the present ochre, does not clash with the colour of the ceiling. (Drawing Room). H.G.Jakins Political Agent* H.S.Powell, Esq., Ministry of Works, Bahrain. NNR1 Telegraph : PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone : 49700. E.S3V50/5 k MINISTRY OF WORKS BRITISH EMBASSY CAIRO. 15 th February, % Dear agency, May I remind you that annual returns showing the ~ state of your fire fighting equipment are now due. I enclose ^ 3 copies of M.O.W. Forms VST. 90b and W.906A. On completion, they should be signed by a responsible officer and endorsed with the official stamp of the post, one copy being retained on your file, the remaining two being transmitted to this Office. Yours efcer. Ministry of Works. ■ H.B.M. Political agency, BAHREIN.No,1149-18/1 Dear Ministry, 7 $, We return herewith, duly completed, two copies each of forms W,906 and W.906A received with your letter No.iii,83A/50/5 dated the 15th February 1950. Could you kindly send us some more copies of these forms for submission of our future annual returns to you. Political Agency, Bahrain, 4th April 1950 Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. The Ministry of Works, British Embassy, Cairo.T ':’.906 (X 5909/3921/503) DItLQ.iATIC A il CONSULAR BUILDINGS EiTURK OP PIRD.-PIGHTING EQUIHIENT Post Brief description of buildinn; (number of storeys, construction, &amp;c.)« - P ^ J^,q■ a t? ^ J’tr, d- ~~ fco? &lt; .aJrtY*. 'fit dj l\ny special fire risk. hVen^Jt Means of raising an alarm. ' Whether local brigade available? (Give brief remarks on equipment and efficiency of brigade*^ Jr. Ac~ iL*. ' &lt;l*rtx^£AJr&amp; 4H^ £a£l . rtU ^ Means of communicating with brigade, / ' ( (c.J\/ y - c tKLir 'f*r\U*&gt; . C4MA^ Fungus — Manual, Corridor or Bucket Pumps - type and number. Number of hydrants - (a) Internal. j&amp;ttornul. Do hydrant connections correspond v/ith those used locally? Length of hose available. AC A / P.T.O.Banariis on condition of hose* (Give d 0 to of supply, if possible..) Is Vfe.ter pressure nde^uite? (Give stntic pressure, il possi^l^#) ^ro water mains liable to freeze? ( l&lt; ‘ yo jo ■ jSxtincteurs {see-sapex-ite sheet). • • Number of Fire Buckets* Number of Band Pails i Details of other equipment held. Whether periodic tests and practices are carried out; if so, the me thou employed # Reslut of test. ■ i General Remarks and Recommendations* ✓ Sicnod Date_ CIRCULAR No. 20 Restricted 3/r 7’ Request for Detailed Information on all Government Office Buildings Abroad and their Contents k/sX Dear Consulate, / We are endeavouring to compile in the Department a complete record of information regarding the buildings occupied at each of our posts abroad and it will be a very great help if you can assist us. We have hesitated very much before asking you to do this, and have sought to obtain all the information at this end. But we have found that in some cases there is no information available, in others it is buried in individual files, and in others again it is in one or other of two separate Departments of the Ministry of 7^0 Works; and to rely entirely on the searches in all these different directions would take a very long time, and the result would be ^ largely inaccurate. Meanwhile it becomes every day more clear what an enormous help it would be could we get such a record complete, tabulated and in one place. A good deal is happening—slowly, but happening nevertheless— in the whole question of buildings, furnishing and equipping. In principle it has been agreed that the Ministry of Works as the estate manager for the Government shall gradually take over all hirings now handled by the Foreign Office. Secondly, as you know, the whole question of issue of furniture and equipment right down the scale is a very live one and one which we are trying our best to push into practical effect. Thirdly, just because both housing and furnishing is such a desperately difficult business in so many parts of the world we are constantly being referred to by those who are posted abroad for information as to what they are going to find on arrival. There is no doubt whatever that from all these ^ points of view we shall be able to give a very great deal of help in many directions when we are in the position in which we ought to be, in that the Department responsible for buildings and supplies should be able to answer at once any query regarding any post. An index has been compiled in which every post has its own card, and in order that the information may be correct and up-to-date we are asking each post to make the initial entries on their card for us. (Instead of sending the actual card which has on it some other information, we are sending a gummed slip which will be pasted on to the card). His Majesty’s Consular Officers v [P.T.O. 15982 38341—3a2 In order to show what we are aiming at we attach to this letter proforma d«tails of an imaginary post bringing in as many varieties of information as we can in order to illustrate the sort of answer which in one entry or another may be expected on your card. Will you please confine your entries to ticks except in those columns where in our example we have shown otherwise. The remarks column is intended really for two purposes. First to show the occupation of the several buildings, and secondly to record some essential fact, the omission of which would completely alter the interpretation of the entry concerned. We would emphasise particularly that the buildings to be shown in this index are solely those where His Majesty's Government is the owner or the lessee. It makes no difference whether the lease is held by the Ministry of Works or by the Foreign Office. In either case it is held by the Government. But what should on no account b&lt;? included are premises where the lessee is a private individual even though he may recover the cost of his rent in the form of an allowance. It is the Government-held buildings only with which we are concerned. The column headed “Floor Area” applies only to premises used as offices. It may well be that you cannot assess this without more trouble than we think we ought to ask of you. But if by chance you are in a position to make an assessment of this, so much the better. The figure given should be the overall floor space gross, including passages, &amp;c. The column headed “ Servants’ Quarters ” does not apply to such things as maids’ rooms in some European capitals. What this refers to is quarters adjoining for native servants in certain parts of the world. “ Offices ” refers not to “ usual offices ” but to rooms used for working purposes. In almost all cases, of course, these will have furniture. , a . .. The furniture, equipment, glass, crockery, silver, cutlery, all refer to that provided by the Government or provided by public funds whether in the form of a direct issue of Government-owned gear or by the hiring of this gear as part of a furnished tenancy. The point is that by whichever method provided, this stuff is provided and therefore does not have to be produced by the occupant. „ ^ ^ “ Equipment,” as distinct from Furniture means such things as blankets, linen, kitchen gear, Hoovers or similar appliances, refrigerators and so on. , i We shall be glad if you will return the slip with your particulars as soon as you conveniently can. ^ . r Please take care not to obliterate any of the information on the slip by punching holes or otherwise defacing it. A similar circular has been addressed to His Majesty’s Chanceries (as No. 024). Yours ever, Conference and Supply Department,mm mm 1) The P.O.T.C. , Sharjah, 2) The Political Officer, Doha. No.1213-18/1 feith the conpliraents of TJie Political 10 Sncl:- F.O.Cir.No.SO of 16th *lar* 1930 re •Request for Detailed Infortaation on all Govt. Office Julldings abroad anti their contents. Political Agency f Bahrain, 12t)i A ♦ril I960*&amp; MINISTRY OF WORKS, MIDDLE EAST. BRITISH EMBASSY, CAIRO. Telegraph: PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone: 49700. /''r-sX} ' ’ '' A Ref. S.8W5QA9 fr? 16th May, 1950. Dear Agency, Thank you for your letter No. 1149-18/1 of the 14th April, enclosing your annual returns of fire fighting equipment. Unfortunately you omitted to have the forms signed by a responsible officer and endorsed with the official stamp of the post. I am therefore returning the forms to you for completion. Will you please let me have them back when the signature and stamp have been added. When you return the completed forms, will you please let me know if the four Underwriters Laboraties Inc. extincteurs are of the foam or soda acid type. If you have difficulty in obtaining this information, Mr. Homer will be able to help you. I enclose blank copies of forms W906 and 906 A for future use. Yours ever. Ministry of Works, Middle Hast. Political Agency, Bahrein. if H&amp;Jh t'-v-f-U- _Jk_ VTf/RL i kfNo•1691/18/1. Dear Ministry, POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 25th May, 1950. The forms sent under cover of your ( letter No.E.83A/50/49 of 16th May 1950 are returned herewith duly signed. The ommission -v in the first instance is regretted. 2. The four extincteurs are of foam type. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. The Ministry of Works, British Embassy, Cairo.MINISTRY OF WORKS, MIDDLE EAST. BRITISH EMBASSY, CAIRO. Telegraph: PRODROME, CAIRO. Telephone: 49700. Ref. E.8JV50/53 2nd June, 1950 Dear Agency, Thank you for your letter No. 1691/18/1 of the 25th KQiy enclosing signed copies of your annual fire fighting returns. I am asking my London Headquarters to send out to you 12 refills for soda-acid extincteurs and eight refills for foam extincteurs. I will let you ( have instructions for testing the equipment when I hear that the refills have been despatched. I suggest that you should purchase locally^ a small number of soda acid and foam refills to provide you with a reserve until supplies arrive from^the U.K. Perhaps the Manama fire brigade will be able 00 help you here. Yours ever. Ministry of Works, Middle .East. 9 ^ British Political Agency, Bahrein.Political Agency, Bahrain, No.^75 -18/1 27th June 1950 Dear Sir, I would be grateful if you could manage to supply us on payment three each soda-acid and foam refills for our fire extincteurs, to enable us to operate them until refills arrive for us from the United Kingdom. Yours faithfully, Political Agent The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain.IRECEIPT OF YOUR LETTER N0.2U75-1Q/1 DATED the 27th June, 195U. 2. I HAVE REQUESTED NY STOREKEEPER TO ARRANGE FOR THE DELIVERY OF THESE ITEMS to the Agency. I HAVE THE HONOUR TO BE, G. F. W. Farmer Station Manager.' 2. It mil not be possible, except in cases of urgency, to carry out any services for which provision is not made in the Estimates. It is essential therefore that the forms should contain a complete forecast of your requirements for the year. 3. i Where furniture requirements can be met locally, the estimated cost of local purchase should be indicated. ■ * f' 4. The completed forms should be returned not later than 31st August next to *\ ‘ ^ ■ ■ H.3.M. Political Agent, The Political Agency, Bahrein. Director of Works &amp; Services (middle East), . British Embassy, I am, Sir Your obedient Servant, 4/ 3050I! j ■+ +- Telegraph: 'Travaux, Wire, London' * Telephone: Reliance ?611 Ref: A.3. 15/1 Ministry of Works, Lambeth Bridge House, \ : A ^ Albert Embankment, V?«&gt;r ^ lh£' L sir ’ Estimates for the year LONDON, S.E.1• H 4th Aus^ist, 1 95^ at March, 195^ I am directed by the Minister of Works to ask that you will be good enough to furnish particulars of any services for whicn, in your opinion, provision should be made in the ^stimates of this Department for the financial year beginning 1st April next, particulars should be stated on the enclosed forms* 3050 /2. fli l V y * ^ ■ 1 V \ '.1 2, It will not be possible, except in cases of urgency) carry out any services for which provision is not made in the Estimates, It is essential therefore that the forms should contain a complete forecast of your requirements for the year. 3, Where furniture requirements can be met locally, the estimated cost of local purchase should be indicated. 4, The completed j/orms.^should be returned not later than 31st August next to • \ ,/ Director of Works &amp; Services (LtLddle East), V- ; llwiisfciy. of. Wort?# British Snbassy, QmQ H.3.1I. Political Agent, British Political Agency, BAHREIN 3030 A I am, Sir Your obedient Servant,7861 POLITICAL AMCTs BAHRBUJ r ^ • e f TM.O.V/. 1893 x^lJBLIC BUILDINGS O^/EiRSEAS OP?ICE PUENITUHB Statement of requirenonts for consideration in connection with the Estimates for the year beginning 1st April, 1951 PREMISES ALL OFFICE PKEL1I3ES Office Furniture, Floor Coverings, Blinds etc. / \ Room Articles beyond t repair which should be replaced Supplementary articles considered necessary Remarks Estimated local cost and equivalent in sterling A.p.^ y Vk--p * yVfe*' ’ ' v t*- - TfrJTT' if tsLu i » i } cA^aji l A Vf - { *^c O* AL- £ -5 oi lAtiU VrTXTTJjTW'Tr &lt;■' pf ►'V* 5 ’- Z- (r* ^ ^ f I dL &amp;-* v &gt; ' ^0 - - Note: 1. Services which it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the Annual test.7861 ^o.v;..i89i POLITICAL AG-KMCYa BAHREIN PUBLIC BUILDINGS OVERSEAS H5SIDMTIAL FURNITURE Statement of requirements for consideration in connection with the Estimates for the year beginning 1st April, 1951 PREMISES: - ALL RESIDENTIAL PREMISES Room Articles beyond repair which should be replaced Supplementary articles considered necessary Remarks | Estimated local cost and equivalent in sterling Hall and Stairs Dining Room Drawing Room Ballroom ''Lay *\j.\ 'j i * L&lt;r\ t . S t* *- r/ 'Tts^ /x—4 (i -j 'f - ^ &lt;p f''' *J_t&gt;ryrc\ ax 4 Q # C&lt;A- ('Zjt-4* ^ Cl* A^9 C*~ Principal / Bedrooms, Dressing Rooms, etc. Servants Rooms &gt;-CCc*&gt; c&lt;^L C A^rv u ( 1. A / - A, ^7° t C C( i As ■C'-w St*--**. ■(,( W/ ^ ^ c/c^, 3 LaJCa- ih. x ^ / ^ ‘•'-c ^ r Note: 1, Services which it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the Annual testNotes 1, I7here there is a local Architect or other representative of the Ministry of Vorks he should he consulted in the preparation of this form. 2. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the annual test. 7861No. R.3 if-/ -18/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 23rd August, 1950. Dear Powell, I enclose herewith a letter in original together with its enclosures received from the Ministry of Works, London, in respect of ’’Estimates for the year ending 31st March, 1952”. 2. ' As you are in close touch with the conditions of the Agency Buildings etc., I believe you will be in a better position to submit more accurate details and I should be grateful if you would call at the Agency with the enclosure so that we can thrash out the final form of the indents which, as you see, must be returned to the Ministry of Works before th? end of this month. Yours sincerely, sd.J.E.Hartley. ''W' H.S.Powell, Esquire, Clerk of Works, Ministry of Works, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.BRITISH Rj&amp;SIDENCX, BAHKAlR• 35V7/bO 18 th 1950. Dear Ministry of Works, jrlease refer to your letter 5D..&amp;/50/16 of the 29 th July. 2. lour Mara^rawh 1. There seems to have been a misunderstanding as the Political ngent, Bahrain, was under the impression that the condition of tne agency building was mentioned to Mr. shepherd when he visited Bahrain in March last; and that in any case, Ur. ohepherd would hsve seen the condition of the building for himself. 3. l our oara^ra^h 2. The expedient mentioned still involved the use of an 'j^lsan' which can hardly be regarded as satisfactory. i 4. four parc^ratn 3&gt; It is true that unfortunate ly adequate InforLiatiori as to what was required in the Political kger^cy was not given by the Acting political Agent last year, and it is realised that it was difficult to make financial provision during the year because of this. This will, however, be fully remedied this year ana we trust that financial provision will be made for the items required. 5. lour oara^ra^h 4 . kr. Bvans reports that he reported two needs to the Ministry of V^orks during his visit to oairo, viz (1) extra lavatory accommodation and (2) painting, colour-washing etc. of the exterior of the agency. as regards (1), it is noted that the extra lavatory accommodation estimated to cost x. r /5 was author ised. as regards (2), hr. mvans reports that Mr. Pollard stated that the work could be proceeded with. It has oeen carried out. 6. lour uara^ratju b. We are glad to see that a considerable sum will be budgeted -or in next year's estimates in order to carry out essential repa_rs to the Agency building. fours ever, residency. Ministry of Works, Middle Bast, British embassy, CalBO.-4 '!) COPY OJ Vt'O.iKS 9 MIDDLE ^aST, bhli'IuH ^kBiiooY, CalRO. 50.a/50/16. 29th July, 1950. Dear residency, Political agency Bahrein With reference to your 367/2/50 of the 8th July. It is regretted that this memo addressed to the Foreign Office contains an incorrect statement. When I visited Bahrein in March last I did not discuss the condition of the agency build ing. The only matter referred to me was the question of improved bathroom accommodation for an agency clerk recently married. In the circumstances, I had reported that this would be investigated by my representative Mr. Powell who would report. Mr. Powell did report that as an expedient this bathroom ana lavatory accommodation could becarried out at an estimated cost of £15 with which the occupant woulu have been satisfied, but to improve the existing lavatory and bathroom accommodation to any appreciable degree would cost at least £250. This expedient could easily ana speedily have been carried out by earlier reference to Mr. Powell. Mr. Powell further reported several requests made by the Political agent totalling more than £400. It is unfortunate that when the estimates were prepared from information provided by the post last year, no single item referred to in the recent requests was incluaed. The circumstances are therefore that no allowance has be^n made for any one of the present P.A's requests in this year's budget which as we all appreciate must be adhered to in these days of stringent economy. However, during Mr. i^vans's recent visit to Cairo, one special item only, namely the extra servants lavatory accommoda tion estimated to cost £75 was authorised. The need for this work having arisen apparently due to lack of supervision and discipline in maintaining these quarters in a hygeinic condition. In the circumstances therefore, Mr. Powell at this stage has been instructed to carry out only essential urgent works but later, should the circumstances arise whereby savings are effected on monies voted for Jufair, to execute any further overdue requirements at the agency where a considerable sum must be budgeted for in next year's estimates if the structure of this building is net to suffer further depreciation and extend beyond repair. Yours ever, Ministry of Works, Middle Bast. s? ■No. 9 . 7 /£ -18/1 POLITICAL AGElfCY, BAHRAIN. 23th August, 1960 Dear Sharjah, v'e enclos&lt; sreln Ministry of orks forms and a copy of their letter to us of the 4th August on the subject of furniture and other requirements for the year beginning 1st April, 1961. 2. Please would you complete these forms and return them to us for onward transmission to Cairo as soon as possible. Yours ever Bahrain Agency The British Agency, Sharjah.— r v . &gt; No.a 7^7 -ia/1. POLITICAL AOiJKCY, BAHRAIN. 28th August y I960. ^3 Dear Doha, We enclose herein three Ministry of Works forms in triplicate in which you should state your estimated requirements for the year beginning 1st April, 1951. Please let us have two copies duly completed, as soon as possible and we shall pass them on to the Ministry of Works people in Cairo. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. ^ m l Sy A The British Agency, Doha.Ig M.0.W.1391 BRITISH AGEN CY. DOHA PUBLIC BUILD IHQS OVP.RSEAS RC .3 IDEtl TIAL I TT’RE ment of r&lt;qulrements for consideration in conn e with fche estiiaa£es for the year beginning 1st AprfU PREMISES*- ALL RESIDENTIAL PREMISES Room Hall and Stairs fining ioom Drawing Room Ballroom Study Principal ^ N «drooms f ..res sing Rooms, etc, Servants Rooms Articles beyond repair which should be replaced T Supplementary artivies considered necessary Remarks Estimated local cost and equivalent in sterling Notei, 1. Services which it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2. ^'here fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the Annual test. j fPOLITICAL AGENCY, (F.149-17/1) BAHRAIN. 2nd September, 1950 Dear Pullan, The Persian Gulf posts now that they have passed under the wing of the Foreign Office are, as you know, in a period of transition and, where this particular post is concerned, part of my duties are to see that the oflice organisation Is brought into line more in accord with Foreign Service practice. 2. This will take time. I have only been here a fortnight and I would have preferred time to get a more detailed Insight into the work performed here. Much of the work Is the same as at a normal consular post, and the volume of it is considerable. To take only one examples we issue between sixty and seventy visas per day , in addition there are plenty of extra-consular duties to perform because of the special treaty rights enjoyed by H.M.G. here. 3. However, the opportunity to get certain things going on Foreign Service lines on January 1st next must not be missed, otherwise another twelve months will be lost. I am thinking particularly of the reorganisation of the filing system, of the visa work and of the registration of persons under the Political Agent's jurisdiction. 4. All this means that certain stationery applies, - particulars of which are enclosed herein, - must reach this Agency by mid-December and the purpose of this lec-er is to enlist the cooperation of your department to this end. I apologise for Inflicting this on your staff (they must get many such requests), but I do hope you will appreciate the necessity for this present one. 5. Our urgent requirements of office furniture mpm the subject of our separate letter to you of today's date (F150-18/1) to which you night like to refer. Yours ever, (J.E.Hartley) A.J.S.Pullan, Esquire, Conference &amp; Supply Department, Foreign Office, London.No.F. I5&amp; -18/1. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN• 2nd September, I960. Dear Conference and Supply Department, It may perhaps be useful If if is letter m « ^ ^ p w ^ -tr ^ HP A «4b V W W w %p * in conjunction with Mr.Hartley's letter of 2nd September to ^r.A.J•b.Pullan. 2. V7e enclose herewith a copy with its enclosures of our today's letter to the Ministry of Y?orks at Cairo on the subject of the requirements of this post and we should be extremely grateful if you would point out to Ministry of Works, London, that certain items, specified hereunder, are required urgently. 3. First and foremost comes the question of lavatories for the staff of the Agency. At present there is none apart from a shocking place without running water used by whoever can face iti These are required straight aways one for the European officers, one for the Indian Contract staff and one for the local menial staff. In all there are over thirty people involved, apart from numbers of the public. The local Ministry of Works Representative has been consulted. He wants around £300 for the job. He has so far been authorized the sum of £76, with which he can do nothing. 4. Just as important is that the office furniture marked with an asterisk should reach here by mid-December. It is hoped to bring in the Foreign Service system of filing and archiving &lt;Ln the 1st of January, but whether this happens or not the post is most inadequately provided with these essential items of office equipment. 6. The third pressing matter is the proper furnishing of the Assistant Political Agent's house. The items under this head which are required urgently are at least three of the four air conditioning units in order to make his living room, dining room and one bedroom habitable before the next hot season starts, that is, before June 1951. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. The Conference and Supply Department, Foreign Office, London.POLITICAL AOSMCTT, no. 2 ~) 6 l - 1 V 1 . BAIJEAIN. 2nd Sopteaber t 1950 Th« Director of Vorka and Service# (Kiddle Hast), Ministry of Works, British Enbassy, Cairo* U.S.IAA) fro “ the Minister of Works calling for estimates for the financial year beginning 1st April 1951, I enclose herein an estimate of this post 1 # requirements* 2* The requirements of the Political Officers at Sharjah and at Doha, who are under my supervision, will follow as soon as possible. 3. There are certain requirements, long overdue, which should be undertaken immediately and I enclose a copy of ay letter of today*s date to the Conference and supply Department of the Foreign Office on this subject* Sir, / In accordance with a Circular of the 4th August X am, Sir, four obedient Servant, (J.E.Hartley). for Political Agent*mmmm MM a £ K.0.-.X891 . i-'Q^IVIGAL AUUiCg. 3AFIRAIH BUILPIiii iki iL w: wants for consllara tion In eorj^c^oq ror tha ,-H,r PRBMISK81- ais PAj;;sKf‘a ^jEUfs r^idsucs ROOM Hall and Stairs Dining Root?. Drawing Room Principal *N Bedrooms, / • rressing % x Rooms, etc, i |j f Servants Boom Kitchen ARtlCLES REQUIRED — Hll. Nil. 7 New Curtains and Covers. . New CurJ§ and Plre creon {r Standard and Table Lamps (3 of each) IU. One Table Lamp. New Curtains* 3 Booms. Three Cheats of drawers. Three V^ardxobes. One dressing table. Two bedside lamps. One dozen snail lampshades. Nil. Complete sets of kitchen equipment, China, Cutlery, glass and household Linen are required. -JfrRafrluor.tor 3^ X 4s ft.II. 0.11.1891. y,.^ T^ T r/.i. Ar.r.ISCY. BAI3UIK i uhlic uui i.! t ?1qs r c rT • ilMk ytiHMTUB re^al8 * 8, ' m This poaldtnce, tHe property of the ImliralnOovernaeut, ia about to bo loasot) by Hla ilajoety's Ooverruaent Tot a; &gt;r-o of aavan years. ?ho furaltura in It (the property of---® Oovarnaant of India) Is Inade j-ate and ha* »»•“ l^Ur days. An indication of the size of the nouse is given ^lov*. Ground floor: Entrance Hall and Stairs* Pining room* Sitting room* Btud/ ( Kitchen ^umrtsrs. First floor: Hall* 1st Bedroom with Dressing room and Bathroom. 2nd Betroom with dressing room and Bathroom. Verandah (large) In compound Air conditioning Servants* -quarters. ■Jfryour - 14- ton units ra-iulract for dtu iuc sitting room and the two bedrooms (of which 3 units re^uireo urgently)• Local price per unit...11.0.?;. 1893. POliriCAL AOi;- CY. BAiiliAD? Ovyrrc*: Sta la.-.ant of r .-jUlrc 3 e .t8 for co nsl/'oratloa In connocclor, »lth tU f or the year baginning 1st A^rll. \ Hoorn Requirements Assistant Political Agent’s Office 'lyawert »*a-l4v earwe One Carpets Size of Hooia 14X20 ft. One two-drawer index cabinet with lock to hold cards 5xS inches. Assistant Political Aunt's \ altlne roc* Pour chairs. SuDcrlntezdcnt's Office One Chair. Oenoral Ofx^ice One typist*a chair Visa and Passport Office One Key safe (interior measureaents 18'X13'X24') with one drawer. -£*3 four-drawer index cabinets to hold cards 5X8 inches (for visa cards and registration car s). •y2 four-drawer index cabinet s to hold cards Sjcaxiuteiuui 4X6 Inches it or -a ^ ort and ^is«'i f.I.) Wiv * Ivfo Chairs. two wooden benches about 8 f3*t long. ugtiinsjr Registry ^1 four-drawer index cabinet to hold cards 6X9 inches. ^c4 steel fi ing ca inets to hold files of foolscap size with cloth supports for files. \ tationcry and Store 4 steel presses, size 1X3X6 f^et. Interpreter 1 steol press, size IfXSxfi feet. 1 chair.* 0I ' 0145/2/29 % British Agency, Sharjah, £ y&gt; £&gt; 5th Sept.1950, i n SEP WO &lt; bl G Dear Bahrain, —f?jYour 2718/18/1 of 28th August, 1950 about furniture. 2. The completed Ministry of r Works forms are returned herewith. N 1 ! r /V. tpo-J. Yours ever, Sharjah.V j, i Telegram : Enclair. From s follard, Minworks, Cairo* To ; Political, Bahrain. No. 605. Dated the 14th and received the 15th September, 1950. AS is/Uof August; 4th for Sharjah and Qatar (Doha) now urgently required. If not already despatched please telegraph details. - POLLARD MINWORKS ■«»w-***AMS' V U. .&gt;891 BRITISH AGENCY. DOHA PUBLIC BUILDINGS OVERSEAS RESIDENTIAL FURNITURE Statement of requirements for consideration in connection with ihe estimates ^or the year Beginning 1st April, 19oi » PREMISES:- ALL RESIDENTIAL PREMISES Room Articles beyond repair which should be replaced T Supplementary articles considered necessary Remarks Estimated local cost and equivalent in sterling Hall and Stairs \ ^'^^Ining Drawing Room Ballroom Study ^‘J^ncipal ^ .^ooms, Dressing Rooms, etc. Servants Rooms B-athrooms Kitchen 3 Doormats 5 , x5 f 1 Table 1 Stick Stand Complete furnishing Complete furnishing 2 large &amp; 1 small Complete furnishing 2 A.C* units. Complete furnishing for two sevants Floor mating in lieu of tiles 2x3 , 6 ,, x10 , 8’ Complete furnishing, All items, initial issue and, needed urgently Note: 1. Services which it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of the Annual test.i M.O.W.i.893 . BRITISH AGENCY. DOHA PUBLIC BUILDINGS O^/ER .'ICAS OFFICE FURNITUnE Statement of requirements for consideration in connection with the Estimates for the year beginning 1st Anrll, 1951. PREMISES:- ALL OFFICE PREMISES. Office Furniture, Floor Coverings, Blinds etc. Room Articles beyond repair which should be replaced Supplementary articles considered necessary Remarks Estimated local cost and equivalent in sterling Office Clerks* Office Waiting Room Office 1 Press 1 Desk 1 Desk Chair 4 Guest chairs 3 Teapoys 1 Carpet 3 Sets Curtains for windows 5 , x5* 2 Table fans 2 Presses 1 Desk 3 Tables 1 Desk chair 3 Chairs 1 Screen I0 , x6* Matting 14*21 * 1 Set Curtains 5*^5* 2 Desk lamps 2 Table fans 1 Filing Cabinet 2 Book shelves 1 Bench 1 small safe 2 Teapoys 1 6 3 Table Chairs Benches Matting 14*21* Strip Matting 21*x6» Book Shelf Carpet 18*x12* Bell System Refrigerator Water filter Doormats 3*x5* All articles needed for initial xxA issue all needed urgently. for Post? Office Rs.90/- Essential for cold hundreds Note: 1. Services which it is desired should receive priority should be marked with an asterisk. 2. Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as to the condition of the appliances at the time of uhe Annual test. &lt;| ✓BRTT T SH AGE NCY, DOHA &gt; * ' - ^ \f &gt; »1392 PUBLIC BUILDINGS OVERSEAS Vf ORKS SERVICES Statement of requirement s for c onsirid ration_ in connection v/ith t he Esti mates for the'year Begin n ing' Tst AprilV 1951 • PREMISES:- Those owned by H.M.G. t ! * t t t f (a) Soecial requirements (additions, alterations or improvements). (b) Decorations, oainting and major renairs. Estimated local cost and equivalent in sterling (c) General repairs, etc. t Notes 1. Where there is a local Architect or other representative of the Ministry of v&gt;orks he should be consulted in the preparation of this form. 2 , Where fire appliances have been provided by the Ministry of Works a certificate should be given as co the condition of the appliances at the time of the annual test. — —— —-— yNo.jW* -18/1 Sir, Political Agency, Bahrain, 18th Sept.1950. S5T/? My letter of the 2nd September enclosed the estimated requirements of Ministry of Works supplies for this Agency for 1951/1952, and I now enclose state ments of the requirements of the Political Offices at Sharjah and Doha for the same period. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant (Sd.) J.E.Hartley. for Political Agent. Director of Works and Services(Middle East) Ministry of Works, British Embassy, Cairo.79A/3Q/18 TELEC-RAI/I COIJFIIu.IATION . S'ZIO H.M. Political Agency, BAHREIi:, The folla.ving telegram was sent to you yesterday, n Telegram No. 603 , Annual estimates for 1951/32 as in our H, Q. letter A.S.15/1 of August 4th for Sharjah and Quatar (Doha) now urgently required. If not already despatched please telegraph details. Pollard Minworks.”(© The roof of the Agency over the verandah a few yards after entering upstairs is sagging very badly in the place through which it rained very heavily last year. There seems to me a danger of the roof falling down, particularly when the rains come. I should be grateful if you would take mepsures to prevent this. Mr. Powell.No. SiLOLf-/ / Political Agency, Bahrain, 25th October, 1950 Dear Ministry of Works, Your local electrical engineer states that the wiring in this Agency is so defective that it may cause a fire at any time. The house is old and the walls are panelled in wood so that if a fire did start the building would probably be a complete loss. You will no doubt wish therefore to re-wire the building as soon as possible. 2. We are sending a copy of this letter to Mr. Horner. Yours ever Bahrain Agency. The Ministry of Works British Embassy, Cairo.J*n I A\) The following items,about some of which I wrote to you before, require to be seen to at the Agency: (1) The repair of the drain from the kitchen to the sea. The. planks placed over these are not satisfactory. (2) The repair of cement on steps and in various other places. (3) The Flag Staff. This requires re-painting and the shrouds should be tarred and parcelled. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie have recently had theirs done so that it furnishes an example of what is required. The cleat holding the yard should also be repaired. A new gaff should be fitted in the fitment existing for it and the canvas protectors removed from the head of the shrouds. When will these jobs be done? (4) The A.P.A*s office is very dark and should be painted cream colour. (5) The pier, and particularly the slip-way, should be repaired where needed. (6) The Drawing Room requires painting. Oil paint or oil paint mixed with distemper would be better than the present distemper. (7) The road from the front of the Agency to the main gat * pairs. Mr. H.S. Powell, M.O.W. Representative, Jufair. 9 ^Mr. Powell / I really must ask you again to do some thing about the drain crossing from the north west side of the Agency to the sea. The wood covering it is in worst, condition tl an ever and in any case never lasts where the cars cross it. The place around looks more unsightly every day and gives cars a considerable Jolt. I should be grateful if some effective repair could be expedited. 14-11-50. / //• A”*.2 5 a &lt; s cn ^ x Z LU I— H 5 111 03 O H 0 z 1 h o z Minutes. '3 Reply to Mr. Turner’s letter has issued as below. 2. I intend now to remind Mr. Banks regarding the maintenance and such minor new works as were requisitioned for this Agency -k*#for% next year. Put up the copy of the requisition form sent to the M.O.W. by Mr. Andrew. Also put up copies of the various requisitions made to Mr. Powell here. A.P.A. is not concerned as far as his residence goes as it is maintained by the Bahrain Government, but I should be glad of any suggestions he has to make though a unless they are of works of^very minor nature, I doubt whether it is any use asking now that they should be done. 13-1*1-50. A.Erf-sT A*P. /&amp;A7UjSl % A* &lt;£&gt; huu, jo/ Ihdi /fcvca* iLtryjri U U jru^cd. UeJxAt j Af jlkrv* . n V jncltZv, O^JL Q ^ (fjuut* Corvee /ikjt i** CK^J. /Jt-wl t 8 18/j . /3LAA- d^ jr §5 ^ tilts .’vf 4 til K 1' &gt;i ;Minutes. Letter below to issue to Mr. Banks. We ought to remind in three weeks or so if no reply is received. It is as well to keep at the M.O.W. I have mentioned A.P.A's requirements of furniture and air-conditioners in my letter. As regards the electric lighting, I think it would be best if he took the matter up with Mr. Brammer, the State En gineer. I am fairly certain that the A.P.A. suffers from being on H.H's line as the demand from the palace at Ghadhabiyeh is very heavy. 19-11-50 A, t . i-i(Conference &amp; Supply Dept), 17, Carlton House Terrace. 10th November, 1950. FOREIGN OFFICE, S. W. 1. (XC013/91K1/1850) UNCLASSIFIED. * 9 igso The Ministry of Works have written to us in reply to a letter which we addressed to them enclosing a copy of Political Agency/s letter No. F 150-18/1 of the 2nd September, 1950, about furniture. 2. They promise\ to supply replacements and additional items of residential furniture as soon as possible. They say that domestic equipment has already been despatched. 3. A Complete consignment of office furniture was shipped in the s.s. 'CITY OF ROCHESTER' which sailed on or about 30th September, 1950. Card index cabinets and vertical filing cabinets were included but wooden presses for stationery were supplied instead of steel ones. 4. ^ No mention was made in the Ministry of Works* letter about repairs etc., referred to in paragraph three of your letter of the 2nd September, but that may be because repairs are dealt with by a different department in the Ministry of Works. I am, however, sending them a reminder that we are still without a reply about the lavatories. 5. At your convenience perhaps you would let me know whether there has been any demand for the return of the office furniture and equipment which belong to the former Government of India. When the office furniture arrives I assume that you will be in a position to meet any demand for the return of urniture to the Indian Government, or any representative of that Government who may require it in Bahrain. ' C. J. Pelly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agency, BAHRAIN. //■j-I n: Political Agency, Bahrain, 19th November, 1950 Unclassified. No. 3447-18/1 Dear Banks, Turner wrote to tell me about the change of policy in the Ministry of Works whereby in future all major new works are being dealt with from London while works mainte nance, minor new works and general matters still remain the responsibility of Cairo office; and that you are in charge of the latter as re-organised. I am therefore writing to ask you if you would let me know whether your office has received this Agency letters Nos.2767-18/1 and 2900-18/1 of the 2nd and 18th September, respectively, giving estimates of requirements of works etc.,for .this Agency and for the sub offices at Sharjah and Doha for the financial year beginning 1st April, 1951. If so, I should be glad to know (a) our chances of our having these esti mates sanctioned, and (b) your estimate as to whe^after sanction^ the works will be carried out and supplies delivered. In particular, I am anxious about the refrigerator for the Political Agent * s house and the furniture and air-conditioners for the A.P.A* s house, and should be grateful If you would pass on my request for news about them to the right quarter. Yours sincerely, A J.T. Banks, Esq., Architect in charge, Ministry of Works, British Embassy, Cairo. Cl ill j I — * I - BPolitical Agency, No.F-206-18/1 Bahrain, 28th Nov. 1950. Dear n'illson, ✓ Thank you for your letter of the 10th November (XC013/91K1/1850) and for your continued efforts on ray behalf. It is all somewhat puzzling, and you will see why if you read ray letter of today*s date to the Controller of Supplies, Ministry of Works, a copy of which is enclosed herein. 2. His letter to me came out of the blue, refers to no previous correspondence and what he is sending me ranges from desks and chairs to wastepaper baskets and door mats. It is all grist to the mill. 3. Hartley’s letter of the 11th Nov. (F-190-17/1) to Pullan about certain supplies we badly need before the end of the year from H. 1.Stationery Office. If you can find a moment to enquire whether suitable action has been taken, I should be extremely grateful. Yours sincerely, T.Willson, Ssquire, lii.B.ii., Conference &amp; Supply Dept. Foreign Office, London.No. 3601-13/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, 3rd December, 1950. Dear Banks IO(f Will you kindly refer to the correspond ence ending with Horner’s letter No.M0W7/50/823 of the 15th July, 1950, on the subject of re frigerators and be good enough to le« me know when my refrigerator here will be replaced.- It is in very poor condition now. Yours sincer (C.J.Pelly) J.T. Banks, Esq., ^ Ministry of Works, British Embassy, Cairo.No.3774-18/1 Gentlemen, Political Agency, Bahrain, 73rd Dec.1950. 'O.H.M.S. British Political Agent Bahrain” - 2 Cases / furniture ex s/s”SHAiIRISrAN”. I enclose Bill of Lading, duly endorsed, for the above consignment which has arrived on the s/s 'SHAHRISTAN” and I should be grateful if you would clear through Customs and have the two cases delivered to the Agency as soon as you pos sibly can. 2. If this can be done before the New Year it would be of great help. I am, Gentlemen. Your obedient Servant, sd. J.E. Hartley foriolitical Agent. Messrs.Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.Ltd.. Bahrain.’ i an % O Translation of letter dated the 26th September 1948, from Abdullah bin Yuruf a Building Contractor, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I have surveyed the’roof of the Agency Building and I am pleased to submit my estimate for the repair thereof for Rs.5,500/-. Repairs will be done with cement, sand and lime mixed together. Usual ending. HiREPAIRS TO AGENCY BUILDINGS - ORDINARY RKPaIRS (D Letter No.50a/48/1 cUted 9th April 1948 from M of W. Cairo. f May await detailed accounting procelHi^e promised. Meanv^hile, however, Mr. Johnson has authorisefcKQpening of a new account in the Bank under the style ''MinistryvQT v/orks Account' transferring a lump amount (say Rs.2000) frS&amp;K^be v F.O. Account. This will be done n&amp;w as usual monthly payment.4 have to be made which used to be paid from C.C.G. May file? &gt; dk- U S' © Affec A/o. 13^' 'V / ^ (£) _ p. L. A'C IXl 1 0-&lt;l3jx\ei)*&gt;l b ■ The detailed accounting procedure promised in S.l. has L nov- arrived. From thi^ it would appear that prior sanction is required for all items of Expenditure other than normal day to day maintenance and repair work and a financial limit of £ 15/- (Rs*200/-) has also been imposed. * , The forms F.D.51 and W.61 have not been sent by the Residency. May ask for same? D.F.A.l. The opening of a new account for Ministry of Works is ^ not envisaged in this procedure but as this has been done with )• the approval of Mr. Johnson may continue operating same. How- ever take Mr. Johnson*s advice on this matter. D.F.A.2. The running costs of the electrical plant at Sharjah are 4 to be borne by the M of W. Suggest we include same in' our accounts until Sharjah operates as a separate accounting unit. May request iResistency to put us down for two copies of the regulations,mentioned in para 3 of the D.u.c..when they make their indent for same. D.F.A.l. It is now clear that the cost of the pump and motor can not bet met from M. of W. funds without prior sanction. .May therefore make a case to the Residency in the first instance- regarding this expenditure? File 18/11 lihketi. No . (R. U.h - Dt j ■ h iPlease ask contractors (I suppose 'Uchi and Turani would be the best) to prepare within the next day or so the estimates for the repair of the Agency pier and for annual repairs In the Agency - these in cluding^ era ping of internal walls of rooms, new painting and colour-washing, colour-washing and painting outside, and repairs in cement and plaster fabric where needed - also making of a sky-light in room No.2 which is at present pitch-dark./f The estimates need &amp;nly. be rough but it is essential that these be ready before the 16th of May on which date Mr. Kin of the Ministry of Works, Cairo, is to visit here. The estimates must be readv to be shown to him. ' / h ltd. C.J.P. 12-6-48. L /’LiT'Ur —• . 'V(s. iLi- k^-a- CU^&gt; c?-, y ^ , xiy si P? Lr^L. • ^ 2. tC !»Aw C I .1/V / 5S patching cement and base of walls where worn or corroded are required and it is necessary to know whether Mr, Uchi's contract includes this. When we know what it does include I may think of someoother items. This replies to para 33 above. - m _ * * * a As A.P.A. states information regarding para 34 should be collected from office. The case should be O •&gt; 6 « 6 9 «f # a* • w • kept on the move.• &gt;; ltd. C.J.P. 13-7-48. / 0 G c^u^cus Cuueu: / O-yX (r 'CyjO. t, &lt;1 / 3' /V V J I I il &gt; X 3', &lt;i o ‘ 1 / S ^ ti£K~-p^ yi _ C^-tC&amp;AXr Unr 4-&lt; , I sent for Salman Uchi and haviig shown him the J P.A’s noting,^asked him to submit a detailed estimate. He said he would do that. . /ice/ ^€. '-o-/,'/*»w;j4 ^ During the years 1946-47 and 1947-48 we have expended &amp;n the Agency building ( including white-washing and other petty repairs etc.) Rs.2445-15 and Rs.5021-6-3 respectively as detailed below. These expenditure were met from our Central Contract Grant. From April 1948 onwards we are debiting all such expenditure to the Ministry of Works Account and up to the end of June 1948 we have expended under this head a snm °f h5 ? ?6 There is one repair much more important than the others,which I forgot to get an estimate for and to forward to the Ministry of ,/orks, viich in spite of prolonged correspondence has not yet sanctioned the list I did send them. The roof of the Age-cy is ir a very bad state and the house will be flooded if not put right before the winter rains. Please get an estimate for repairing it so as to make it water tight and let me have it as soon as possible. ltd. C.J.P. 8-9-48. S. ^ 5 c ^~~ ) * . (U* A- / j2-« /’ w-v y ^ — y ^ li- $ -*arrr t'hlhf.The forms and D.O. to issue to Major Dredge. As verbally directed, would H.M. please make an extract from each of the three letters forwarding estimates giving the cost of repairing the roof? They should be sent with a covering D.O. to Major Dredge. This should issue to-day or to-morrow and should no t wait completion of the form and issue of the other D,0. In any case the form should go to the Secretary within the next few days or so. The above note may be regarded as cancelled. I have giv«n separate orders to Steno regarding pletion of the forms after consultation with him.(Major Dredge) ltd. C.J.P. 27-9-48. the D.O. to Major Dredge and revised the corn- ltd. C.J.P. 28-9-48. * ■' - A,' k\H' l / a .'T’ha nk The lett er below with two $6 bills Id issue t n th e It 1 nistry of Works, Cc irO . i i ulte cert a in wl etl er we should • ■* ^ . &gt; have gone to the '1 ocal Finl '“try of V orks Representa- five' firs t, hut we • will awa it reply. / * d. C.J. n . • - 1- If-48 % &gt; ■* | ■ / * j. t • ^ (L.k. Arodr. 'I'j •/*JV *fc !o •**£'.. S / 4^ ' ■ ci? y/&gt; /vo.. rsis- £/l'tt--Li$ k H. W. C^a'-^O - ’ I have consulted Mr. Brocklehurst who says that the i0 4 ^ ‘ amounts for the fans and sofa covers in S.38, and Fazal 'Mohd. Tailor's bill for Rs.38/- (placed below) may all be debited to our quarterly account with the Ministry of Works. The amount of Rs.340/- should then be refunded to the 'Amenities Fund'. I notice that the letter at S.38 has been_addressed to the 'Ministry of Works' without the addition of 'British Embassy' and will therefore presumably never be delivered. Mr. Brocklehurst has supplied me with the following ^ ^ information regardlhg the set up in the Ministry of Works .V ... 'v British Emba ssy, Cairo , i.e., names, offices, and subjects dealt with. They are: Mr. Douglass * Senior Architect . Building Decoration Repairs Gardens Mr. Kim Mr. Noble Resident Engineer Electrical Work Fans, Stoves Air-conditioning * SHjspkisx tounxixkiHgX Mr. Leat Mr. Brocklehurst Supplies (furnish- Furniture, Bedding, ing) repairs, kitchen equipment</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1632</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1632</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 18/1 III ORDINARY REPAIRS TO AGENCY BUILDINGS MINISTRY OF WORKS'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-21T01:59:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (162 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 163; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-87; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding repairs and maintenance to the Political Agency building in Bahrain. Correspondence at the beginning of the file concerns the transfer of responsibility for this to the Ministry of Works in the British Embassy in Cairo and the establishment of accounting procedures. The remainder of the file contains work requests for repairs and maintenance. It also contains correspondence between Cairo and Bahrain regarding administrative procedures, details and progress of work requested, and payments. Requests include repairs to the Agency roof, furniture, tennis court and swimming pool, the purchase of new fans and the maintenance of fire extinguishers.From 1950, estimates for work required during the next financial year were required from Sharjah and Qatar (Doha). Also from 1950, all major new works were dealt with from London while general maintenance and minor new works remained the responsibility of the Ministry of Works in Cairo.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>