<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001f4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T00:30:23.425Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. &gt;* 7 ^ W and address —not to any permit by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 883 fii ~ Affaii •J 2 9 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign ' Affairs presents his compliments to th* l ^cOc. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^- of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 2&gt; ^ 3 , 192^ . Reference to previous correspondence : }-VX« Description of Enclosure.'' a r i\ y .. In any furlher communication on tins subject* please quote » | (I { 1 J— ^ and address —net to atyy person by name\bw\. to— -’f “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. r. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ijransmits herewith cop_*J of the under-mentioned paper. 1 Foreign Office, a.u - 192 ^ Reference to previous correspondence :' 1 ■ ' In any further communication on this subject, please quote N °- v^aott yitb {os and address —not to any person b]^ tame, but to— ' . V‘ ^ ^ “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreigr Office, London, S.W. i. S | s *» * i,' THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to . i.'tsL, ^(L-c^ and, by direction of the si transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, '' , 192- - 'll ‘1 JI &lt;1 r \%*-**in any further communication on this subject,/please quote &gt;r^ n »'X' 3H.K| ?llp i s &lt;3'3 . and address —not to any per soy. by name, put to— / 4 The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. X. O comp THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign-Affairs presents his compliments to jfc, (H and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ansmits herewith cop-4^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^kX , 192 r, . ^■ f - 28 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. 4 # V J V .L.T' 1 ft tfO Name and Date. Subject. fLhoL~t o| *« -eh^In any further communication on this subject, please quote No*ohf*&lt;l . and address—wc/ /a any \&gt;&amp;rso\ name, tut to- u The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. 1 n * Vy THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to Cu\At d ^ *Aj an ^’ ^ direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop 1 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, j idL /) I - t , 192*. lh lU j l ' : Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. 1^4 k) -3 MAY 1928\ ■* In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. &gt;&lt;. 2./W / S' 1 ' f‘S03 and address —to any person by name, but to— \“The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. 1 5 4 I 14 * THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ ^ y^v/ $by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, . v.» * 'r ?_&gt; it ptfipd a nr b ' Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. y/v*rw Jj'StK. 'ou; sfyj. 76 — / 5 * &amp; IkIn any further communication No. \ and address —not to any person by name, but to “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London ^ - cation on this subject, please quote :-.C ^ 1 .^ 1*1 SI 4 / J l *•/ 503 \ • s fJ SO ^ THE Under-Secretary of State fo» foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^(JIa. ^^(Iz^AjLyto^Aj ^ ^to^A. 4-0^ J by direction of the Secretary of State, ■ v v __ transmits herewith cop y of the under-men|iioned paper. ' rU T AWAX WITH I &lt; * * Foreign Office, , 192 S ■ Reference to previous correspondence : -o'!P-Zc, lo. I'fZL 7 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. X**-' ft f*-&lt;&gt;■ 'f ri /lOr In any further communication on this subject, please quote No.* and address —not to any person by na?ne^ but to—■ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I, 5371 r -y ! :*••&gt; _ j THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. PUT AW A* WITH Foreign Office, V**- , 192 Y. 'X e Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Jf -A. IS'L Y Qtc'lff L WLcUV^ ^ ■D In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. X &lt;*' 7 ^/Oo 3 /d '0 3 1 and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i&gt; 5 i~~- .'-'i j THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. PUT AWAY WITH Foreign Office, dsJ. ? 192 . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. &lt; 7^0 . i y r . fgzu J' frV'. m jit0 (Ttrv Leio f&gt;yp\l^ay Otryif 1 i?fr /Hh a/- Similar letter sent to, v 14 (14964) 8/26 (2) (16184) S / 2 7 CoiC u.&amp;t/'ixr).ny further communication on tjiis subject, nlease quote No. Xfloa'sIbozJ'S'Ol) and address —not to any person py name, bit to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London .4.4239 f Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. THE Under-Secretary of Staiia-.for lForei gn A ffairs presents his compliments to ^ &gt;£boCtj} s£^/ f and, by direction of the Secretary of State, wansmits herewith cop 1 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, / « liitllK »6 o£P m Subject. ^ U ^ ] y % JL&lt;xJk V \ | rf'S/ ^(U^KA^tr.. — In any further communication on this i v n subject, plea^ qu^te , No. 3 c 3 C 5 and address —not to any person by “XJ 16 Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Lond^ , but toX- i r ' - T n,sAr. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to k ^ ( and, by direction of the Secretary of State, mits herewith cop AJj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 1921 ,j, In any further communication on this sufcject, pleaie quote ^ N °- X3qo^fbo3.KI)3^ and address —not to any pehon by name, but t( &gt;— ‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Loi do„ |S .w.j .9 2 7 PUT AWAY WF lilt h THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to i and, by direction of the Sefetarj/ of State, ransmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. kn Foreign Office, &amp; r i -a , 192 Y-1 ^ Iia any turther communication on this subject, please quote No - HXi) leOj 1 and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. j !!• 9 7 3 l i i ^ ^ Fli i h)M ri i THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ \ * y l &gt;/ and, by direction of tb^ Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 192 V. I ' Reference to previous correspondence : H jl( Descriptio7i of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. i f ! 0^/iJ -J A w —i' 1 0, U fC j 1 dJL | ACCOUNTI GEr^L fa U \F7 Oh 4 &amp; 14—(463? f) 2500 10/20 Si^TViFdfTelifer^nt'to pc L t f- 28 , FEB I927j fo, J »Uv ivt/*&gt; In any further communication on this, subject, please qu te imumcation on thi&amp; subject, please q M ' x°y $ 3 . 0^1 ^ and address —not to any person b% name, but to-- London, 4 5 \* “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, 5 .W. i. 1 *M’« PHT THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to OjijL' (y-Jl and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Jj of the under-mentioned paper. Fof'eign Office, Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. BO DEC Name and Date. Subject. $ c. FfcdiHltf X ^ «s : lL tetA, )2q */ * GEN-fe| ^£L Similar letter sent to 14 (14964) 8/26 (2) ^ /-^ 4, u L&gt; 1In any further communication on this subject, please quote No and addres not to any far son. by name,, but to The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Othce, THEi Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^JLl Q j ' ’ , . OP , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop u of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. vS» ^vCkiu_. Jflvo I &gt; cd m-v „ o /) CC3H | /~crr /^6 (^cE^Cenr^ ^ A &amp; JLXiO -CCOUN 3£NU O'tErf'of- t ^MM1^' * I * “ —J on this subject, please quote |I' In any further communication no xasoa ^QPo and address— not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. n THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to 0^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copx^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Itt k. w . i . 1921 Name and Date. ft t ^/ 'P&gt; ^ ^ | Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Subject Jxpv^MV . 'Hjr rIn any farther communication on this subject, please quote no. ^ and address—' 1 not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,'’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. PUT AWAY WITH THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his pliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^cj, of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, JkjtO. , 192 (T. f.1StS Reference to previous correspondence Name and Date. vo 'A». 3 ( 9(0 oT Am) 11 ^ 1 accoun. genl\ . 13165 1 9 9 5 Similar letter sent to 14—1344 F.O.P. [10484] 10m 5/24 [11526] (4) v/ ^ Description of Enclosure. ^y^yu,A}‘ j (Lma ^.v/^K trvihrvUic^ W' M \2 v / v&lt;'N In any further communication on this subject, please quote n °- xsyA-l, (© 54 - and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State/’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ AfcoJiji Vtff and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ,192 0“. Reference to previous correspondence : Name and Date. i&lt;Xs1rj dU- an Subject. ■MujAvve+JI' f t, CKro Ae. X&gt;vo&lt;_A- - ''V ff 28 hU6 1925j r/ i+iofvr^^/ ■ Oi 28/lH &gt;1 SEP 195 14 r— 1344 F.O.P. [10484] 10m 5/24 [11526] (4) Description of Enclosure.K t*£? CJD o In any further communication on this subject, please quote ho- and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,' Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. LUyz/uV THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to Lt/wcta. - ^^cajJoa^ cQ ^ I'HcLtc, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Lj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^o^Oju^u.K ,192 S'. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure.?S Tf In any farther communication on this subject, please Wote No.X'Oyal C KV 530 and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State/’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. P 13t; L„ 1{ ‘ ^ AWAY WITH THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, . Of/ -1925: O ’ Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure.ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO “the manager’/ g 9 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS*,- OREIGN-PEHLEVI, LONDON’! AND-PEHLEVI, CANNON, LON DON? TELEPHONE NUMBERS:- CENTRAL 5760 ( 5761 . di/ag. tm/.. 31st March S4£..5 -E’.C.#. By Hands The Accotmtant Generali India Office, ^gSk? 6f% S.W.l. Dear Sir, (■ 1 APR 1925 V ^^ Vp/ A Q^ V We confirm a telegram received from our Teheran Office to-day reading as follows 'Telegraphic Bill 1 receive from India Office £5,000 '(five thousand pounds) account British Legation# 'T.T. 12 credit us with.' We shall he pleased if you will arrange to pay us this amount immediately. Tours faithfully, .ipi tA' 33 Sub-Manager. / 75 'A ! 0/ ! y n APRT32Sll cen YjAUC COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO “THE MANAGER’’ TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESSi- FOREIGN-PEHLEVI, LONDON 1 .’ lLAND-PEHLEVI, CANNON,LON DON!’ TELEPHONE NUMBERS: CENTRAL (|7|Q DI/MS India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. Dear Sirs, We confirm a telegram received from our Teheran Office to-day reading as follows: 'T.B. 15 receive from India Office £5000. (flv© thousand pounds) account British Legation, T.T. Ho* 11 credit us with' 7/e shall he pleased if you will arrange to pay us this amount immediately* Yours faithfully. '*1In any further communication on this subject, please quote and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,' 1 London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvjko of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ,1925. '• 1 ’'V.'.: *i 23 JAN 16 Reference to previous correspondence : 1 ’ O.'rt Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. oir - geiml!| [ ii IPG L [92 5 _J(to2\ ;■ If In any further communication on this subject, please wuote this subject, please vpiote \ No. address— \ 1 and address— not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Seoretary of State,' Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. XU THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents, his compliments to and, by direction' of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvlho of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 192 U(. (A QFFyA ^ ' •TtSui w\ Reference to previous correspondence : a t. &lt;S^- ulfe^o V«&gt; ^ \' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. \\vjuwto^XA ^ifiuvcwv Vo C. 1324 ; f- Subject. Q(XU^Jf ^ ^ ^ t ^T0 ijT .*AX&lt; kj&amp;rJLsvd: ftsr tfk term LaJ ItUx U^Sh^VUCt fcthrsk d. tUl^U ; I ■ \ 11 AIn any further communication on this subject, please quote n °-* and address— \ \ not to any person by name, ut to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 9 % f: 9 *&gt; wt •*»# s' ^ '■ / J ITH i iilf’ I if AWAV \a/i * k f f O | | £ %. \gys ty i, THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs present? his compliments to iij, Ujv\cLl^' ^wAl(X n and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvCx&gt; of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, d\ Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. ^ 'Ll oX l/- Vm 4 29 / - M,li» any further communication on this subject, please quote No. X PGO/f ! *66 'so$ and address— | V not to any person by name, 1 1 but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 483 924- pUT /....Vi WITH -v t&gt; 'lo* THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, jy- , 1924'. Reference to previous correspondence: n LgF? (x 4 50 9- / 4 6&gt;&lt;6 /S 03 \ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /Vo •• /o/t /F[This Dooument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and shou ld be returned to the Foreign Office i f n&amp;t-reqrmxtL^n use.] 49 i 0 Decode Do 2 C 20 p.m. 20 th December, 1923. R. 12.55 p.m* 20th December, 1923. No. 421. (H ) 0 1 Sir P. Loraine (Tehran). 20th December, 1923. My telegram No. 393. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia the sum of £5,000 for current expenses of this Legation. Please telegraph transfer 10 1923-1924.[This Docume nt is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if n ot required for official use. Decode. Sir P. Loraine (Tehran). November 29th, 1323. 12.5 p.m, November 29th, 1923. 11.5 a.m, November 22 th, 1923. (R). &lt;1- u My telegram No. 382. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of the sum of £ 2,000 for current expenses of this legation. Telegraph transfer 9 1923 1924 0 i* •. * r ■'&gt;In any further communication on this subject, please quote . and address— \ ' not to any person by name, ut to— “ The Under-Seoretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. i O Q : O AY WITH W 1 } THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs ^resei^ts his At a compliments to UnJl and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Y under-mentioned paper Foreign Office, ,4- Cyw\, 192 ^ % Reference to previous correspondence : Description of E?iclosure. Subject. t lc\ OLOXO. 13?3 CFFV\ [This Decument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not reqaa Decode. No. 184. ■ NQ DISTRIBUTION . Sir P. Loraine (Tehran). 12th June, 1923. D. 2.00 p.m. 12th June, 1923. R, 5.35 p.m, 12th June, 1923. (K), My telegram Ho. iifi. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £10,000 for current expenses of this Legation. Telegraph transfer 2 1923-1924.e URGENT In any further communication tiis subject, please quote No, r a \ Stt'i and address— not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. \ Foreign Office THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to VLvveLxA Q^[/\ ^fV\cLlCH and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper.— r I This Document is the Property of His Bil&amp;tafiie' Maje^y’s Crovemment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] HO DISTRIBUTION Decode. Sir P, Loraine. (Tehran via Warsaw). April 23rd, 1923. D. 9.15.p.in, April 24th, 1923. S.SO.a.m. April 25th, 1923. Ho. 119, (B). —--oOo i..y telegram Ho, 89. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Panic of Persia stir, of £8,000 for current expenses of this legation. Telegraph transfer number 1,URGENT \^r.) ‘kl \ u any further communication on this subiect, please quote » No. and address— not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. 117 7 15)23 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ||ml ^wcUc\ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, \WcDv , 192% . Reference to previous correspondence : O, Oja 6 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 5 APR 1923 % - ■ 4202 (JT IsU ^ f ^ ^ 14— (463? f) 2500 10/20 29 MAR 1923)^ &gt;'&gt; DEP&amp;F Similar letter sent to X 'iKM-yX \ t r&gt; vJ I * / vP P f any lurther communication . on t subject, please quote. N°. and address— * ' person by name, rut to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 7/8 C, 0 q r&gt;' ' t u- THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ijiut IWdu ' ^ ( and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous correspondence:, * O/ Description of Enclosure. 'A 28 FEB 1923 y ; Name and Date. Subject. yuK • ^WvwX pj /f 14— (4537 f) 2500 ]0/20[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office i! not required for official use,] HQ DISTRIBUTION Decode. Sir P. Loraine (Tehran). 13th November, 1922. D* 5.00 p.m. 13th November, 1922. R, 10.50 a.m. 14th November, 1922. No. 413. • • • • ily telegram No. 359. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £5,000 current expenses of this legation. Telegraphic transfer No. 3 1222-23.I 636/558/503) i * The Imperial Bank of Persia, 25, Abchureh lane, London, E.C.4. 1922. Sir, We have the honour to in je have today received a telegram from Teheran, dated 14th January, as follows:- 'Claim from Foreign Office £10,000, per 'Legation wire of 12th January'. We shall he glad therefore to receive at your earliest convenience your cheque for the above sum. We have, etc.. For The Imperial Bank of Persia, (Signed) Sub-Manager ie Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.Vv.l.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be l IIMIW ■ i ■IMM —mui'M'iMW'MMiw.M , L u . I hi, L] -1 n ! ■np l i _____ returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] ¥ I l *1 NO DISTRIBUTION . Decode. Sir P. Loraine (Tehran) January 12th. 1922. D. 11.a.m. January 12th, 1922. R. 11.20.a.m. January 16th, 1922. No. 23. ' Legation telegram of 3rd. December. please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £10,000 for current expenses of this legation. Tele graphic transfer No. 3 1921/22,fcv H /, « la any further communication on this subject, please quote l&lt;flt . V^cc'rj r vi [ ilV(? f / No. and address not to any person by name, but to—- '^he Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.VV. 1. 'iO /l^O THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to JtaM- , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned pap£r. Foreign Office, 9- , 192F . , ■ % 4, pi 10 dec - Reference to previous correspondence : • /r^O ' (f I} Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. s Subject. Similar letter s &gt; 14-F.O.F. 10000 10/21 (7032)E 13356/405/34) THE IMPEEIilL BAHK 0E PERSIA, 25, AH church Lane, London, E.C.4. Dec emb er 5th. 19 21 * Sir We have the honour to inform you that we have to-day received a telegram from Teheran, dated 3rd. December as follows:** 'Claim from Foreign Office £10,000 per Legation telegram of 3rd. December. v e shall be glad therefore to receive at your earliest convenience your cheque for the above sum. We have &amp;c., (Signed) Sub-Manager. Che Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office,[This Do cument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returne d to the Foreign Office if not required for official userid ^ 'if [!■ u-f iV) Decode, R. Mo* 669* HQ__. DISTRIBUTION . Mr. Bridgeman (Tehran) 3rd December 1921. 11.15 a.m. 4th December 1921. 8.45 p.m. 4th December 1921. •*«***«*»’*»*•»***»«««»•+*•*«•«*«*»**»* My telegram of September 8th No. 500. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £10,000 for current (? word omitted) overdraw! this legation. Telegraphic transfer two of 1921/22. r- '/In any further communication on this subject, please quote . no. and address— l+oa not to any person by name • The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to Asb' ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copxjki of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, (0 , 192 / . !\ ^ Reference to previous correspondence : yo. 7. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ACC^UiUT QHNt 462 r). ' 't X&amp;rfCnre ptA^rrut^yb ^ . yY\&lt; fru^rJejO o-i- 280 f Lr~u cxy* I 14— (5030) 10000 12/20 Similar letter sent to (L - L\~tIn ^ny further communication on this subject, please quote ' No cn&gt;&lt;&lt;!:&lt;jh7fh&lt;&lt; and address— / / not to any person by name, but to— ! The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to &amp; ^./ o-Y / v and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop uj of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 192^ . Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. » Out 1‘4 —(4794) 10000 11/20 Similar letter sent to10 DISTRIBUTION. Decode, Mr, Norman (Teheran) D, 5.10 p.m, 4th December, 1920. R. 10.50 a.m. 7th December, 1920, No. 788. My telegram No. 760. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia the sum of £20,000 for current expenses of this Legation. Telegraphic transfer No. 12 of 1920/21.For THE IMPERIAL BANK OF PERSIA. Manager Th.e Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l. We have the honour to inform you that we have today received a telegram from Teheran dated 4th December, as follows:— 'Receive from India Office £20,000 'per legation telegram of the 4th 'December.' We shall be glad therefore to receive at your earliest convenience your cheque for the above sum. We have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient ,humble Servants, ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO “the manager’/ TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS;- REIGN-PEH LEVI, LONDON.’ ID-PEHLEVI, CAN NON. LON DONT TELEPHONE NUMBER:- (V'.NTRAL 8898 I . Sir,I In any further communication on this select, please quote and address— / / not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 1 o / ! O ' THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ Ck^ y4nr -— and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop 0 f the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, JL$ 192 ^ ( ^ T I li' 11 ■ j J .4 i f Reference to previous correspondence : O'/S J ^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. — Subject. yL-'0j r~U- ; ( ' l Of H- '/f r ^ /nr • y(? 0 - • HS % i-: 14 — (4794) 10000 11/20 Similar letter s&amp;ht to V,[This Docu ment is the Property is Britannic Majesty's Government, and No, 760. W telegram No, 739, Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £10,000 for current expenses of this Legation, Telegraphic transfer No. 11 of 192C/21. ba returned to the For eign Office if not required for official use ] Decode. Mr. Norman (Teheran). D. 5 p.m, November 22nd, 1920. R. 5.-5-p.m. November 24th, 1920.h, any further communication on this subject, please quote No. ft// and address not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. -yr THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, /cfay/ffi , 192 ^. Reference to previous correspondence' * J Description of Enclosure. 14—f) Similar letter sent toJ4 In any further communication on this subject, please quote / No. aftd address—' not to any person by name, but to— “The T' ’■er-Secretary of State,” jreign Office, London, S.W. I. 1 1 7010 19^0 PUT AWAY WITH I * •T THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ' &lt;u ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ of the under-mentioned paper. / Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /i^r- (eC^y '* tm wo ^ y ^ r 14— (4243) Similar letter sent toDecode telegram from Mr.Norman, (Teheran), October ^3rd.l920, D. 11.30.a,m. October 23rd. 1920. R. 11.0.a.m. October 26th. 1920. No.699. PI6a.se pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £9,491. 10. 3. on account of extraordinary accounts of Legation for quarter ending 30th June 1920.ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO 'the manager’/ TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS.- FOREIGN-PEHLEV!, LONDON.’ LAND-PEHLEVI, CANNON, LON DON.” TELEPHONE NUMBER:- CENTRAL 8898 e==5=5=5==s Sir, v/ ^5. We have the honour to inform you that vie have today received a telegram from Teheran dated 15th September as fol1ows:- 'Receive from India Office £10,000 'per Legation telegram No.9.” We shall be glad therefore to receive at your earliest convenience your cheque for the above sum. /C ' &lt;&gt;-y * C&gt; f c r . 7 / * We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient,humble Servants, Nor T^TMPERIAL BANK 0'^ PERSIA. Manager, The Accountant Greneral, India Office, m.m. i.i; * ' ^ C.J w bi4 41 — ^ Tl e Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. URABtr THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments an d, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, A , 192 C . Reference to previous correspondencewmsp*'' r In any further communication on this subject, please quote ' no. CJ?3/c2 - ' address— not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. H *7 hit- l ^ O THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and ’ h y dire ction of^the Secretary transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, y , mo. Reference to previous correspondence : iq?n i 1 • ■ \j — S '- * -■ ; . :■ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. /fvvU j 14 — F.O.r. 5000 6 I 20 (3516) VIn any further communication on this subject, please quote /no. and address— / J not to any person by name, but to— &lt;! The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. Foreign Office, 8 dot S‘&gt;C , THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his ' compliments to tL rtf ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper.. /''' ' f ' V J Reference to previous correspondence : -bn*. f. 0,FOREIGN SECRET TELEGRAMS.ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO 'THE MANAGER? TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS FOREIGN-PEHLEVI, LONDON.’ IIAND-PEHLEV1, CANNON, LON DON! TELEPHONE NUMBER:- r 'NTRAL 8898 5 'dCjL+.L^, N * Sir, We have the honour to inform you that hy telegram received to-day from our Teheran Office dated 13th instant, we are instructed to receive from you the sum of £20,000 (Twenty thousand pounds) per British Legation wire No. 5. We shall he glad to. receive your cheque for th^ above mentioned amount. We have the honour to he. Sir, Your obedient Servants, for TFF IMPERIAL BANK OF PERSIA Jl Manager. Wy Ths Under-Secretary of State, ^ccountant-Q-eneral' s Dept. India Office, S.W.. 1 i o O f f A V » i i • IViMi I’JaUALL COMMUNICATIONS JO BE ADDRESSED TO “the manager’.’ Hj TELEGRAPHIC AD D R ESS foreign-pehlevi, LON Dan'; NLAND-PCHLEVI, CANNON,LONDON!’ TELEPHONE NUMBER:- CENTRAL 8898 ^r.4. We have the honour to inform you that hy telegram received to-day from our Teheran Office, dated 1st May, we are instructed to claim from you the sum of £20,000 (Twenty thousand pounds) per Legation wire No.4. We shall he glad to receive your cheque for the above-mentioned amount. We have the honour to he. Sir, Your obedient Servants, For THE IMPERIAL BANK 0E PERSIA Manager k The Under-Secretary of State, Accountant General’s Department. India Office, S.W.l. -4~MAY1920/ - -C' / /Taj r '''' ' Hi 11| ^ i W i'l • sb : ' si i.cr&gt; / - : cm COMwll N ICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO '/ “THE MANAGER’.’ GRAPH I C ADDRESSi- tREIGN-PEH LEVI, LONDON.' AND-PEHLEVI, CANNON,LON don! telephone number.-- ENTRAL 8898 We have the honour to inform you that hy telegram received to-day from our Teheran O-fTice dated 28th instant, we are instructed to receive from you the sum of £10,000 (Ten thousand pounds) per British Legation wire No. 3. We shall he glad to receive your cheque for the above mentioned amount. We have the honour to he, Fir, Your obedient Servants, for THF IMPERIAL BANK OF P^FI^A Manager The Under-Secretary of State, Ac countant-General's Dept., India Office, s.w. 1.THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State foi the-Colonies-, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of ^ telegram , as marked in vr the margin. \ y' V ID X \ Foreign Office,Tills DOCUMENT IS THE PKOPMiTY OT 1 his bhitahhic Aajest y s s GOVEHNMMT AM) SHOULD BE BBTUHEED TO..,.T,HE....EQ^Ldr OFFICE UHLESS ItEQfUIBED FOE OFFICIAL USE, NO DISTRIBUTION. Decode* Sir P» Cox. (I e lie ran) * D 0 April 28111 , 1920 . B 9 April 30 th ; 1920 * No e 230 . My telegram No* 218, Please aslc India Office to pay Imperial BanL of Persia Gum of £ 10 j 000 for current expenses of this Legation* Telegraphic transfer No* 3 of 1920 /^ 1 *ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO ‘‘THE MANAGER’.’ TELEGRAPHIC ADD R ESSi- F'OREIGN-PEH LEVI, LONDON. INLAND-PEHLEV), CANNON,LON DON’ TELEPHONE NUMBER:- CENTRAL 8898 A- rv/K/s/// a v Sir, We have the honour to inform, you that hy telegram received to-day from our Teheran Office, dated 21st instant, we are instructed to claim from #ou the sum of £100,000 (One hundred thousand pounds), per Legation wire lTo.2. We shall he glad to receive your cheque for the ahove-mentioned amount. We have the honour to he. Sir, Your ohedieit Servants, For THE IMPERIAL BAKE OF PERSIA * v ^ Manager The Under-Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l. R lo \ ?NDl &lt;gUD jinh...(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE: PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT AND SHOULD BE RETURNED TO THE 'FOREIGN OFFICE IF NOT REQUIRED FOR OFFICIAL USE). j . s£.s' c~~ rs I _&lt; .1 J&gt; 1 l . ,1 ! NO DISTRIBUTION Decode. Sir P. Cox (Teheran). D. 8th April 1920. B. 9th No. 184. My telegram of 31st March No. 157, Please ask India Office tp pay Imperial Ba.nk of Persia- £20.000 for Legation current expenses. Telegraphic transfer No. 1 ox year 1920v21* (9.4 8-4)allcommunications TO BE ADDRESSED TO 'the manager’.’ TELEGRAPHIC AD D R ESS foreign-pehlevi, London! NLAND-PEHLEVI, CANNON,LON DON! TELEPHONE NUMBER:- OENTRAL 8898 V, &lt; :A Bir, We have -the honour ho inform you that, hy telegram received to-day from our Teheran Office dated 8th instant, we are instructed to receive from you the sum of £20,000 (Twenty thousand pounds), per British Legation wire No. 1. We shall he glad to receive your cheque for the above mentioned amount. We have the honour to he, Sir, Your obedient Servant?, for THE IMPERIAL BANK OF PERSIA The Under-Secretary of State, Accountant-General's Dept., India Office, S.W.l.all COMMUNICATIONS TO B‘E ADDRESSED TO “the manager. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESSi- FOREIGN-PEHLEVI, LONDON': INl AND-PEHLEVI, CANNON,LON DON” /^’'s’.PHONE NUMBER:- | ...ENTRAL 8898 Apr il, /-9 9ir, We have the honour ho inform you hhah hy telegram received to-day from our Teheren Office Iinmni-Ti ~ i it'i ;n'i - dated 2nd instant, we are instructed to receive from you the sum of £10,000 (Ten thousand pounds), per British Legation wire No. 14. We shall he glad to receive your cheque for ,the above mentioned ©mount. We have the honour to he, Sir, Your obedient Servants, for THY IMEFRIAL BANK OP PERSIA ij .«e 7/ Manager. The Under-Secretary of State, Accountant-Heneral 1 s Department, India Office, Whitehall, S. W. 1.(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PHOPEHTY OP HIS BK oorssmm and should be istuhked to the IP NOT iLQUIKED FOB OFFICIAL USE) . IIaNNIC MAJESTY' POKE ION Oi'PICL b Decode. Sir P. Cox, (Teheran) * D. 12th March 1920, H. 25th No* 121, My telegram No, 96. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia sum of £10,000 for Legation current expenses. Telegraphic transfer thirteen of 1919-20 * ry | irpir v,'v&gt;- iv&gt;'y d/ii. (26.3 8-4)In any further communication this subject, please quote No. d address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, __London, S.W. 1. &lt;&lt;? f .W j v». THE Under-Seoretarv of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to transmits herewith of the under-mentioned paper, , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, Foreign Office, *7 , 1920. X&lt;6 S ' : /o; \ &gt; : i U &lt; \ ^ V Pf&gt; Mar 1920 Reference to previous correspondence : to Letter e Foreign Office Irom &amp; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Kic/ x v y. Subject. •C, Similar letter sent to:-TELEGRAPHIC ADDR ESS i- FOREIGN-PEHLEVI, LONDON. LAND-PEHLEVI, CANNON.LON DON! TELEPHONE NUMBER:- ‘NTRAL 8898 Sir, We have the honour to inform you that we have to-day received a telegram from Teheran, dated 12th March, as follows We shall he glad therefore to receive at your earliest convenience your cheque for the above sum, with interest in respect of the period between the receipt of telegraphic advice by you and the date on which payment is made to us. 'Heceive from Foreign Office £10,000 per Legation telegram We have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient,, humble Servants, For THE IMPERIAL BA33K OF PEHSIA Manager The Under-Secretaiy of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l.C^l * ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO BE ADDRESSED TO “the manager’/ TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESSi- FOREIGN-PEH LEVI, LON DON. NLAND-PEHLEVI, CANNON. LON DON.” TELEPHONE N UMBER.•- CENTRAL 8898 Sir, We have the^ho nou'r inform you that hy telegram received to-day from Teheran, ^ated the 3rd instant, we are instructed to receive from you the sum of £10,000 (Ten thousand pounds), per Legation telegram No.IS. We shall he glad to receive your cheque for the above amount. We have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servants, For THE IMPERIAL BANK OF PERSIA Manager The Under-Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.i. .1 A ^ /s, JVIA$ 1^0 j ■ ) /- . j . ! ■ •.1, t In »ny further commumca- tiw on this subject, please quote \\0'3 l.' 191 ; W3^ and addrese— The Under-Seoretary of State, Foreign OfBoe, London, S.W. 1. &lt;&gt; $ The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for CjvidxA, and y by direction of the Secretary « * of State, transmits herewith cof^ of the 'under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous correspondence :— Letter Foreign Office : A ^ ^ ■^\w D4, S .COPY. OgJ103) The Imperial Bank of Persia 25, Abchurch Lane, London.* E.C. 4. Sir, 25th February 1920. Under telegaphic instructions received from our Teheran Branch, we are asked to receive from you on the 16th March £10,000 (Ten thousand pounds) per Legation wire No. 11. I have the honour, etc, (Signed) Sidney Rogers. Manager. The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l./ 179756/^/34* m i'X -&lt;arch 1 st, 19 a,. bir:* p c/ ^ V' o ,&gt; With reference to your letter of tWeth ft.iuci.wu 0 ttltlao relating to an advance of une hundred thousand Tomans by your Uiiaf Office to His majesty's Minister at Tehran for vshich you claim a aura of I46.144.U4 forty six thousand one hundred and forty-four pounds twelve shillings and four pence payable on the 26th ultimo, I am directed by nari turzon of Kedieston to infom yax that the _-ords CoOTBissioners of iiis majesty's ireaaary having now asked that the f outer system of drawing by telegraphic trans fers may be reverted to on the understanding that you are paid, as from the 18th ultimo . interest at one percent below the Bank rate (i.e. the difference between Bank rate and your charge for Uoranission) in respect of any period between the receipt of telegraphic advice by this department and payment to ihe manager, you imperial u&amp;nk of iersia, 2t abchurch Lane, U.'C.you in Lone on* s, t^olegroia has b e 8 ii aclcir@ss. 8 d bo nis majesty *s minister at rah ran informing him of this decision. .1 am* Lir, Your most obedient humble Servant *Docypher. Sir p, Cox (Teheran) January 29th 1920. D. 8,20.ajn, January 29th 1920. R. 12,30.p.m, February 3rd 1920. No. 39. (R)&lt;, U /v 7* A* Your telegram No 0 29* Difficulty of reverting to former practice ©f \ drawing bills is oxtrome irregularity of communications by post or Foreign 0ffice ; bag which sometimes take two or throe months to reach London* Consequent uncertainty as to date of payment of bills Y/ould greatly inconvenience bank on account of large amounts now drawn monthly. I propose therefore to continue drawing by telegraph but will make each amount payable on fixed date one month after date of telegram interest for one month Bank of England rate will be included in exchange rate at which Imperial Bank of Persia, Teheran buys these bills from me* 3^ (4-12.) Ntte d ■(172636) Decode. Sir P. Cox (Teheran) D« llth January 1920. H. 23rd No. 24 Please pay Iniperial Bank of Persia P,12127.4s.3d. on account of extraordinary accounts of this Legation for quarter ending Decoraber 31st.1919.Sir, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herein, to he laid before Mr.Secretary Montagu, a copy ol a telegram from His Majesty^ 110,000. Minister at Tehran asking that the sum of Ten thousand / pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia in / London for the current expenses of His Majesty's / Legation, and I am to request you to be good enough to act accordingly. I am Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, lie Under Secretary of Sta India Office &gt;tate, , j^O f O~o-0 h tv - fck&gt; D'Vl'isp As fycisvisk, (yf - ^ ^ i'/z/ioi'ifts but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l — 140 ? H ’ In Sny farther communication on this subject, please quote ' „ °’161549/W/34. and address, Foreign Office. not to any person by name, /; c v :c December 17th 1919. ■ »e'€ &gt;t £ 10 , 000 . hrr ^ I am directed by Sari Curzon of Kedleston transmit to you herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran asking that the sum of Ten thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation and I am to request you to be i ■ood enough to act accordingly, I am, Sir, Your most obedient humb 1 e S e r v an t.. ■ 23- , The Un der S e cr e t ar 3 / jjO'O- 0-0 bcoa&lt;u^d Jj&lt;y-r fz 3 to tAji Xvi ihe \ &lt; £ India Office. f&amp;h'OA ix lA JC f V fUke JcficfReference Paper. Register No. A. G, , Political and Secret Department «. f ■ ;; Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department. 13th October, 10 304 n408 lo0() 11&gt;;i8 ESTIMATES. Secretary in the Political and oecret Department be so good as to say what b ® include? in the Home 3 Estimates 3ect of jesty’s n x ■* r r' *-r iiaxA-year to olst March next and also during the year 1920- The payments during the half-year to 30th September last were £10E&gt; a GQ0» In January 1919 the Political Secretary estimated the paymentsjat an average of about £40,000 a month, or £480000 for the financial year (P.92/19). ' (SD.) R.Gr. JAQUET, The payments seem to be lessening considerably and it is suggested that a sum of £120,000 for the remaining half of the current financial year would be a fair estimate. For 1920-21 it is suggested that a sum of £250,000 should be estimated. (SD.) L.D.WAKELY,In any further communication on thi? subject, please quote No, \u\4V\£l /w.3)^ '•■it «f-3 ■■ -'-*&amp;*?*• and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Ofhoe. London, S.W. 1. 1319 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction oi the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1919 . Reference to 'previous correspondence : Letter ^ Foreign Office. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. l\ / t lSS l &gt; Similar letter sent to :—t opy. 144118) 21st October, 1919 bir We have to inform you that by telegram received to-day from Teheran, dated 16th October, we are requested to claim from you the sum of £15,000 (Fifteen thousand pounds) account the British Legation. In conformity with the arrangement between the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury .and the Bank the equivalent of the sums advanced to His Majesty’s Legation in Teheran in Krans is repayable in London immediately on receipt of telegraphic advice. We shall be glad, therefore, to receive your cheque for the above amount. We have the honour to be, &amp;c., for THE IMPERIAL BANK OF PERblA. (bigned) Manager. he Under-Secretary of state, Foreign Office, S. W. 1.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No . 1.43045/W/54. and address, not to any person- by name, but to- “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l 15.000 I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran asking that the sum of fifteen thousand pounds, may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation and I am to request you to be good enough to take action accordingly. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, 6r ,/ft' 5 The Under Secretary of State, India Office.VY In any further communication on the subject, please quote , 0 . 98161/W/34* V fe ■ N( and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, Londo Foreign Ofeuce July 8th, 1919. Sir:- I am directed by Sari Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you, herein, to be laid before Mr.Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran asking that the sum of Ten thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation and I am to request that you will be good enough to take action accordingly. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, he Uader-Secretary of State, India Office. ^ • f/O&amp;VO to-r k&gt;CXAj-yyl£*«Z o~n f\ 1 \% ct£ ^TeA&amp;r- CVlAs . 4 .i “ c* ' \ V i ^ Juhj(98161) tinj? ii 1919 j PILES ONLY. Decypher, Sir P. Cox (Teheran) HSth June, 1919. D, 3,0 p.m. 28th June, 1919. R. 10.15 p.m. 4th July, 1919, NO. 451. (R) My telegram No. Please ask India Office to pay Imperial Bank of Persia, London, a sum of £10,000 tor current expenses of this Legation. Please telegraph transfer number 5 of 1919 (7th April) (sic) 20.Jn any further commanioation on this Jhbjeot, please quote no. 86737/ii/34. and address, not to any person by name, but to- “Tho Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1, ■ x ^ '« V » v Vfci- ^ ^ v ** Foreign r)FFicE. June 14th 1919. -yio. ^ ^ Sir, I am directed oy Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herein, to he laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran asking .that the sum of Ten thousand pounds may he paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia fop the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation and I am to request that you will he good enough to take action accordingly. r I am, , „ Sir, r ['1 Your most obedient humble Servant, ftaLk, oj Pr^u*. fvJ Ofc Y H-IH- State [A/tAje (ct \ /Jn any further communication on this subject, please quote f no. 86737/1V/34. and address, / not to any person by name, bat to— “The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1, Foreign Office. June 14th 1919. CfL 1&gt; £ 10 , 000 . Sir, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran asking.that the sum of Ten thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the current expenses of His Majesoy's Legation find I am to request that you will be good enough to take action accordingly. Under Secretary of State India Office. r I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, jIn any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 85978/W/34. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,’ Foreign Office, London, S.W, l Sir £ 10 , 000 . I am directed by Earl Gurzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister'atJehran regarding the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation. 2. I am to request that the sum of ten thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia accordingly. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. 17 JUL^ 9In any further communication on thrj^mbject, please quote INDEXED atnl !;dr7^011/W/34. / net to any person by name, / i / hut to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l, 'i , sc 1 r ' y '' Tf /^f -X • ’ Aiu. jd J Foreign Oeeice L |May 23rd, 1919. Blr:- 12 JUH 19 £15,000 I am directed by Earl Curzo'n of Kedleston to transmit to you, herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran respecting the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation. 2. I am to request that the sum of fifteen thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia accordingly. fl ! : v i i i k I 4t. V l y ^t/SooO W 1 tq/cj. The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant,In any farther communication on this ^ A T o. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.I, ^ vr-*- t f * ** * With reference to my letter of January 11th respecting the current expenditure of His Majesty’s Legation at Tehran, I an directed hy Sari Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you herein, to he laid before M r# Secretary Montagu, a copy of a further telegram from Sir P.Cox, No*288 of the 18th instant. 2. I am to request that the necessary measures £50,000, may he taken to pay the sum of Fifty thousand pounds tothe Imperial Bank of Persia. I am, bl c ’ yv. Your most ohedien* humble Servant v^yigpuiu.,, 4vejJL 1 iriQ iJ nder Secretary of State i/ India Office.A- ^ In any further communica te on this subject, quote tnd addins— The Under-Secietaiy of State, Foreign Office, London. ■V, \ 1319 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secret at \ ol k^tate, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Ojjiee, lb . 19K Reference to previous correspondence : Letter to Foreign ( )ihce en Description of Dodos nr e Name and Date. l Mz ;&gt;'l ■- 3* j Wf-i \m'\ \%j l &gt; 7 ^ h f % - iFi dtttl itr 1 cttc-r- sciit.Jo.mm — , 7 mIn any rurtlier communication on this subject, please quote / tl °- 3225/17/34. j and address, mot to any 'person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. t f-\ ' F ' 'v V..J5 i v../ t Poheign Office Jcuiuary 11th, 1919 Sir, With reference to my letter of the 5th ultimo relative to the curreht expenses of His Majesty’s Legation at Teheran, I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit to you, herewith, to he laid before Mr Secretary Montagu, a copy of a further telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at that capital. 2. I am to request that the necessary steps may be M0,000. taken to pay the sum of Forty thousand pounds to the Imperial Bank of Pe^Ma /W (■ i' 7 aan, Sir, oo-o /q/cj Your most obedient humble Servant, 7 ’ - V » % 110 Under Secretary of State, A 13 JAN 19191 *! f* India Office.on In any farther communication ' lti ’“ bj ^38^/3 4 . No. »'►' No. »'► .dres3 : not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State, nffino Foreign OlSce, Loudon, S.W.l. r a ^ p I '5k &gt; /, i. f Sir, ^ , .• &lt; With reference to the letter fmr th-i« n irom this Department ox ho 12th ultimo, I am Ulroctea ty Mr. Secrets.,, Balfour to trmanlt to you, herewith, to he law hefor. ' 3eCretel y . copy of a further telegram from Hie Majesty's Minister at Teheran, relative to the current expenses of His l\/te i c , r riJ '' esty’s Legation at that capital. L 2 ‘ 1 6131 t0 reqUest that tha necessary steps may £30,000 be taka! to pay the sum of Thirty thousand pounds to the Imperial Bank of Persia. I am, ^ V r-O 1 'VI ^ _ J, . i Under Secretary of State -J_ India Office. Xv /7 /O'At. V re. /L •' ^ t In any farther oomrannication on this subject, please quote ^ 18497 6/W/34. and address, ^ot to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,“ Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir, Witii reference t»o the letter from this Office of October 31st, No.180054/W/34, I an directed by i.r. Secretory Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, . ’ u0 be lald before Mr,- Secretary Montagu, a copy of ^ a further telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Teheran, relative to the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation at that capital. 2* I am to request that the necessary steps *100,000 may be taken to pay the sum of One hundred thousand sounds to the Imperial Bank of Persia. I am, Sir, Your most obedient h'-u 1 ) Tfl e Under Secretary of State India office. 4 100'(rtrvjia Mirl /tv h ^ to titc l A oj fil'ooK-a hum ble S e rvant, \\k f c gNcrv&gt; f ft ,&lt; Z' .In any further communication this subieefc, please quote '” tl “;“ bi lbg05l/i/34, 1 and address, not to any person by name, yA) k* but to- “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Toreign Office, rs London, S.W.l. / 4 '‘V * VJ *.»? : ■■ i 18 Foreign Office Qhtober 31st, 1918. £ 100,000 sir:- ..j.th reference to the letter from this Department of the 18th instant, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, to he laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu a copy of a further telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at Teheran, requesting that a sum of One hundred thousand pounds may he paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the current expenses of His Majesty’s Lection, 2. I am oo request that, if Mr, Montagu concurs, uhe necessary payment may he made accordingly, if this has not already been done. I am, „ Sir, frpfJ — y o ur most obedient V’ 1 / humble Servant The Under-Secretary of State,. ^ India Office. { { - ^ I &amp; dHAff '****' \%V i iAj /2cuJi ’ ' )toJ-,Sa Ajs(i*jhajcx {&gt;Ju^T f JiW ^ 7 Aw (CjitUt-'L k i In any.further communication on this subject, please quote no- 171606A/34. V and address, 4 not to any person iy name, f but to— / The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. li \ 9 \ 8 Mi i / /? ^S' Foreign Office ictober 18th, 1918^ Cr^t y. : o7oJ¥ Sir £50,000 With reference to your letter, P.4435, of the 12th instant, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a further telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Teheran, requesting that a further sum of Fifty thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation. I am to request that, if Mr. Montagu agrees, the necessary payment may be made accordingly, unless this has already been done. The Under-Secretary of State, India Office, n humble Servant, USx^Luen. AIn any further communication 0D this subject, please quote Iio, 165052/W/34, a;id address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. - Eoreign Office i October 7th, 191S. ! ...J r-’i &lt; J Sir: •TS T; ^ ^ With reference to your letter, p.3295, of the 5th uluirao, relative to the payment of th^ current s-’-psnses of His Majesty's Legation at Teheran, I am ^ directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, a copy of a telegram fl’om His Majesty's Minister at that capital, requesting that a further sum of Fifty-thousand pounds may be paid to the Imperial Bank of Persia for the above-mentioned purpose. I am 10 request that, if Mr. Montagu concurs, the necessary payment may be made accordingly. I am, Sir, £50,000 — 4*tJ i» j J~ : ■* i J“ *- t*-: ' /■ ac^ui d^yfk* alnL&amp;sUj' izw Your most Oc-l/iojU f ^ M tJftfiMa. o-_ U' (faU ^The Under-Secretary of State, Tvs ,-5 4 r».J to-t^Vy/S 1 ‘ QL 'f ‘So&amp;-drCi i* w'. ^ India Office.■■n 148877/.;. 34. AUUDli^! A Iv r '7 r\ •'-&lt; ^ I M AOfc Bepteuiber 2nd, 1918, *''■***' '.'*v*' «•» ■ ,:ith reference to my letter of the 19th ultimo relative to the expenses of His i.lnjesty 1 s Legtxtion et I aa directed hy ' r Secretly Balfour to trenrait to you, ho.: r-ith, to he ^)^J ) ^P re • • fl r Secretary Montagu a copy of a teiegrs Majesty’s Minister at Teheran requesting the payment of Seventy thousan4 pounds by your olfice to the Imperial Bank of Persia on account of current expenses of the Legation at that capital. I m to- request that payment muy te WtB ^ accordingly* &lt; I am, air. Your most obedient humble Servant ‘be Under secret ary of State, India Office. medj -*■''' u .ham*In any further communication on this subject, please quote &gt; n»- 133470/W/34. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, ^ London, S.W.l. £25,000 With reference to my letter of the 30th ultimo, enclosing a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran requesting that a sum of Twenty- five thousand pounds might be paid for the current expenses of His Majesty's Legation, I am directed oy Mr* secretary Balfour to transmit, herewith, the accompanying copy of a letter from the Imperial Bank of Persia on the subject and to enquire whether this payment has yet been made* I am. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, ftie Under-Secretary of State, India Office*COE^. The Imperial Bank of Persia, 25, Ahchurch Lane, London, E. C. 4 . 31st July, 1918. Sir: ± have to inform you that hy telegram to hand to-day fioiu Teheian. oated 29th duly^ we are reciuested to receive from you the sum of £25,000 on account of the British Lega« tion. I shall he glad to he informed if you are prepared to pay us the amount. I have. etc. ( Sgd.) SYDNEY ROGERS. The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. W.i.Immediate and Confidential IV. i igi8.) Reference :—Letter If Foreiqn Office I I t*tti The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of ^ telegram , as marked m the mar Pin So reign Office,Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department, Hi Wster No. ii'inancial 191 Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 7th February, 1918 \ 2884 Bills drawn by His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran on the India Office. •*»##**»*»»#**»###•# For any observations* Gan you inform me (1) Whether the Hills are drawn on account of expenditure wholly borne by the Government of India in the first instance (ii)If the rei the nistory of the arrangements 1 should also be glad to see the correspondence with India referred to in Mr. Badock’s Mote. (SD.) W*ROBINSON. see in particular Mr. nrunyate’s letter of 23rd December, iyi6, with reference to the nature of the expenditure involved* 1 have no information on the subject beyond what is contained in these papers.1’M qs Document is the Property ot His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment. mid should be rtytuincd to the Eorsign O iflcg when done with unless required for oflicial u se. ] PLMila DEpAKTiVii'TJTH T, . Cyphei tele^mn zo bir C.I,iarling (Teheran.). Foreign Office. January 15th.1917. 9.15 p.m. No.19. (B). India Office Btate that you draw Bills on them in respect of disbursements made by you on account of the Government of India, .amount so drawn in the last two years has very greatly increased, and for the purpose of India Office estimates they enquire whether any fore cast is possible for 1917-18. ./hat can I reply? •r ■n.o.no. 1743 -P. ear sir, 283 1 arn desired to ackno\iled.ga.: irtiier' receipt of your letter No .P.-2884,dated the 27 th July 1916 , asking for a report on certain points raised by the Accountant General,India Office,regarding the bills drawn by His Majesty*s Minister at Tehran. 2 . we have ascertained that the heavy drawings during the current year to which the Accountant General calls attention, are chiefly due to the requirements of the geistan Consulate which is.supplied with funds by the Tehran Legation, and to a heavy fall in exchange. The drawings on behalf of geistan have been abnormally large owing to the expenditure of the geistan Field Force,which is financed by the consulate,and to large Special gecret Service disbursements, among which are at present included the cost of the geistan Levy Corps. You will readily understand that it is at present impossible to forecast how long the demands on these accounts are likely to continue, but it may be assumed that there will be no material reduction in them in the near future. 3 . with regard to the fall of exchange, the following ligures may be of interest:- Between April and December 1915&gt; ra te never fell below 54.25 krans to fl and in August 1915 was as high as 65 krans to £ 1 . gince January IQlo, there has been a practically continuous fall, and in July last the rate of exchange was only krans to £ 1. Since July we understand that there has been a still more rapiddepreciation,and the present rate 'i s. probably below 30 krans to £1. In present circumstances, it is, 1 an afraid, impossible to expect any immediate recovery in Exchange, and this cause of heavier drawings by the Legation seems likely to remain in force. 4 . 1 am to add with regard to paragraph 2 of the Accountant General’s note that the Minister at Tehran sends us complete y accounts every month wherein he shows all his receipts, including funds obtained by drawing on London, and all his disbursements duly supported by vouchers. The account works from balance to balance, and is subjected to the same check as an ordinary Treasury account, a certificate of balance from the Imperial Bank of Persia taking the place of the usual cash balance report. The credits on account of bills drawn on London are passed on by the comptroller, India Treasuries through the Remittance account to England, where it is presumed, they are checked with the actual drawings as recorded in England. Yours faithfully, X) SIR ARTHUR H1RTZLL, C / SECRETARY,POL1 r J 1 CAL BEPARTRENT, 1 HD IA OERl CE , L0ND01J.v^^ference Paper. Political and Secret Department ^nce tj a nkofk e credits!- imtrnliB :i “i ilri ings as Register No. A',. G, 3181 ♦ Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 3rd January, ^ U] 10 1 ■ / /Ud (Uck Estimates. Bills drawn by His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, \ 4 ^ -fhfA ajbrrA ■ Government of India’s reply has no?/ been received and is attached. The Foreign Office have telegraphed to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, as to forecast for 1917-18.COPY OF TELEGRAM. 4 iW / / o From Viceroy, Forei^i Department. Dated 8. 1, 17. Received at London Office 99 Hirtzel* Your telegram dated 4th January 1917. Bills drawn by British Minister Teheran, Reply sent on 23rd December last - vide Brunyate*s demi-official letter 1743 F. A reference to Teheran is suggested as regards probable drawings in England.*i ^ , r. Political and Secret Department, I append a copy of a Financial Despatch to India ho. 5, dated 16th January 1864,[which authorised His Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotenti:, in Persia to re-imburse himself for outlays on account of the Government of India by drawing Bills on this country instead of on Bombay. The Minister in Persia has continued since that time to draw annually constiderabl amounts of Bills on the Secretary of State which have h * accepted by the Accountant General and paid, and the payment charged in the Remittance Account. The accounts of the actual disbursements on Persia are no doubt rendered to the Government of India and the items charged under the various heads to which they relate but they cannot be exactly identified in the Finance ana Revenue Accounts, though they are probably mainly on account of the expenses of the Persian Mission and Consulates, and include disbursements on account of the Indo-European Telegraph Company, ihe payments in this country have tended to grow gradually, and the amounts for the last 7 years have b^n as follows: 1909 - 10 48,000 1910 - 11 60,000 1911 - 12 64,000 1912 - 13 80,000 1913 - 14 . 72,000 1914 - 15 ,54,000 1915 - ' 16 . fit jmIn the Home Budget Estimate for 1916 - 17 £56,000 was inserted on this account. Bills amounting to £81,000 have however already been presented here for payment since 1st April 1916, and this may foreshadow payments three ar four times greater in 1916 - 17 than in previous years. I have no option but to accept these Bills on presentation, but no Estimate is received by me of probable outlay. Presumably the Government of India have a system of control over the supply of money to the Mission, additional to the examination by them of accounts subsequently rendered. It would be natural to look to the disturbed condition of Persia for an explanation of this sudden increase, but somewhat similar conditions prevailed ::n Persia in 1914 - 15 and 1915 - 16 without affecting drawings in this way. * Has the Secretary in the Political Department any information which would explain the increased drawings or which would indicate whether they are likely to continue? (Signed) Walter Badock. Ac coun tail t- General, See letter to Government of India below, has been sent to the Foreign Office. A further nmunieation will be made to you on receipt of Go#ern#nt of India’s reply. A copy the , di.gned) A. Hirtzel i. : Z&amp;/ 7 M. ±*a3tS:</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001f4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/605</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001f4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/605</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2884/1916 Persia Tehran Legation Expenses'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-10-27T22:33:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 Volume (336 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 338; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This bound volume contains expense accounts, receipts and correspondence for the British Legation in Tehran, Persia. The volume contains numerous receipts by the Imperial Bank of Persia as the crediting bank for the legation, and to which payments are made by the India Office for expenses incurred by the Legation in Tehran.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Bank of Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001f4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>