<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00015f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:04:13.420Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\ MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEGif idential) . a a 5. JUN.181 J QUETTA. ray 1913. People are getting very inquisitive about the possi bility of finding oil in Baluchistan, and incidentally T have bsen asked to give a map Of the Gv/adar -T ^a lat boundary. As far as T can rrake out the boundary has nev r been demarc-ited or even defined, but from what T^eyes, who was recently Assistan. Pol ti- cal Agent in ^akran^tells me, the boundary Is fairly well known locally. Tt seems to re rr]OBt des-rarle tc Cje* tie -c nd.r definitely settled and marked before any valuable rmerals are found in an area which rrght be disputed. Do you se any rea son .vhy T should not officially suggest that the boundary shc-ld be defined and demarcated next cold weather? Tf not T v /ill raise the quest ''on. T should have no difficulty in gett^.r a representative of Kalat, and the Assistant Political e -- coi Id overlook things generally. Tf the parties on botr: sides be care tc an agreement nothing more would required, but m case of a difference of opinion could it be arranged, as far as you are concerned, that disputed points should be settled by trie Political Agents of Kalat and Muscat? 'Dew, the present Politi cal Agent in Kalat is pretty sure to go down tc v akran next winter and probably there would be no difficulty in arranging for 'Knox to meet him. ^ave 3 r ou any surveyor available or should I have to provide him? Kalat would pay half the costs. ''ould there be any difficulty about Muscat paying the other half? T f 'uscat would be likely to object T daresay we cc Id get over the difficulty.•w 15th June 1913. ^S: 'C uhaa —1^ // Please aee your letter of 22nd Hay regarding the Kalat- Gwadar boundary question. Prom the same point of view from which you advocate it f I agree, subject to any observations which Knox may wish to make, that it would be convenient to get the bound ary settled, but there is, I imagine, no documentary material to go upon and there has been such wide divergence of view in the past as to where the boundary is that I think we need to narrow the issue down, if possible, to some definite zone of uncertainty before taking the matter up officially ? For ready reference I attach a rough tracing from the 8m to the inch Survey Sheet, showing approximately the 3 known versions of the frontier which have been heard of:- (i). the frontier said to be claimed by Baluch sub jects of the Sultan. (I should think we might rule this out to start with, if it is revived). (ii). the Kalat version. (iii). the Gwadar version. Uould mrnmm.® 3 Would you approve of the respective Political Agents en deavouring to get from the Sultan and the Khan of Kalat privately, ostensibly in connection with the Railway Gur- vey f their p^per version of the boundary ? Then we can see roughly what the task is we are likely to have to tackle* I am sending copies of the papers to Knox and if you can wire me concurrence in the above proposal he can go ahead.15th June 1913. Ploaso see the enclosed copies of correspondence ex changed with Colonel Ramsay regarding the Kalat-Gwadar bound ary, but do not take action except to make any observations you may wish, to me, until we get a reply from Quetta. Major S.G.Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent, Muscat.Telegram - En .cl. From - A.G.G., Baluohistar. Quetta To - Resident, Bushlre. Demi-official• Dated &amp; received 24th June 1^13. h Your demi-official of 15th June. I concur in your Baluchistan. no IZwariay 'hnnrirlnr'v *?Telegram - P« From - Hesldent, Bushlro. To - Political Agent, Muscat* Demi-orf icial • N H fe '] ^ Dated ttiSWrt&amp;T 1913. V /ith reference to the Gwadar Boundary. I think you night now tell the Sultan privately, unleGB you ceo any objection, that in view of the possible con struction of a Railway, the Agent to the aovernor-^eneral in Baluchistan has informally suggested to me the import- ance of having the boundary defined during the next cold weather, and that you and I would be glad to know iiis High ness # views before proceeding an^y further in the matter. % You might, if he responds, discover from him what his own ideas are as to the most satisfactory method of finding out the boundary and of fixing it. Cox.—v conf identi al .no : 144.Demi O fficial. Brltlali Agency &amp; Consulate . 11.8.13. Percy, f Tlie ttanslatlon whlCji I give 'below of a letter from myself to the ^ultan hae reference to your demi official telegram lie: 1167 dated 30.6.13. and I hoioe explains itself. When I found His Highness was ready to Entrust his interests in this matter to the British Government, I thought it well to have that down in writing . I am sorry to have heen so long in taking action 'but we have really quite a lot of work hand . ' Masqat , dated 10.8.13. to His Highness the Sultan of Masqat ' After compliments, With reference to the possibility of the construction ' of railways on the MeXran coast the P.P. in P # G« xias informed « m e hy telegraph that an informal suggestion has reached him ' from A.Q.G. Baluchistan representing that it is important to 'settle the 'boundaries 'between Gwadur and Kalat . ITow I mentioned • this affair to your Highness and informed you that the p.R. ' and myself would be glad to know your exalted opinion before ' doing anything in this affair and Your Highness was good ' enough to reply to me,if I have understood you correct^aly , ♦that Your Highness thought it well to place your rights in ' this settlement at the discretion of the British Government. ' And, in order that there may be no misunderstanding in this^ ' I shall be obliged if Your Highness will oe good enough to 'inform me whether I have understood your views correctly '. No reply has yet been received „ It would be too soon to expect one but I think there is no doubt it will be in the affirmative As you know, I dont half like being in charge of H.^s inter- (2) (1) ests, so there can be no pressure of question . I will of course send the reply on as soon as received. Yours sincerely.CONFIDENTIAL. Demi official 145. BRITISH AGENCY AI-ID CONSULTS. MASQAT August 12th: 1913. Dear Six Percy, \ In continuation of my demi official No: 144 dated the translation of 11 8 13. I forward herewith the reply of His Hi2^n eBP ^he • • 9 » * j ! tUftLsU**. Sultan to ray letter a'oout the Kalat- r &gt;orclor 'boundary . Ae HiB Highness has placed himself so unreservedly in our hands in this matter ,1 think that, if it is decided to proceed on these line% it is important that the Baluchistan authorities produce an equally committing letter from the Khan of Kalat , so that, what ever reserves may 'be made as to the revising powers of our chiefs and of the Government of India in regard to any settlement arrived at 'by Dew and myself , there shall 'be at least no room for remon strances on the parts of the States concerned . To, Lieut Colonel Sir P.Z.Cox, I.A.,E.C.I Political Resident K. Consu'.-General in the Persian Gulf. BUSHIRE. Yours sincerely,confidektial TRANSLATION of letter dated the 7th: of Ramzan 1331 .h «11.8.13.from r .-ir HighneBE the Sultan of Masqat to the Political Agent, Has .at. After complimentB, i an honoured in the receipt of your letter dated the 6thi of Ramzan 1331 aio.8.13. and your friend har understood what you mention^ therein that the Resident in the Persian Gulf has informed you of the settlement of boundaries 'between Gwadur and Kalat to the end of what you mentioned in youi lettr. Now we say that we do not know in that af. air more than what the great Government lenows nor is there anyone here to whom we can refer for information about that and we make our opinion in the settlement of those boundaries conform to the opinion of the great British Government as I have already inforned your honour because we believe that the truth of that matter is not hidden from them and they will not be satisfied with our boundary unless it is complete , And as for the Khan of Kalat he would like the diminution of aforesaid boundaries and the honoured Government will inform us on uhau day ai. what settlement their high opinion has arrived au in tne fixing 01 unat boundary and we are convinced of their regard for us , (Sd:) Zaisal bin Turki. Usual ending TRUE TRANSLATION Major Political Agent ^ e.B.M's Consul. Masqatis (Conf idential). QUETTA. J(7 September 1913 ^-7 h l^ ^huka. Ojki&amp;n. Your demi-official of the Slst. August on the subject of the Gwadur-Kalat frontier. I have written derni-officially to *. Mcilahon and enclose a copy of my letter of the 22nd. September to him, from which you will see that I have enlarged my original proposal for the delimitation of the Gwadur 'boundary. Nothing more will, of course, be done in the matter until I hear from McMahon, and I shall ^ta|^ yairier steps^without letting you know. D ' 1 a r Percy. Z. Cox, K.C .I. IS., C • S • X • | cal Resident . Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e.' '&gt; I'fQ Copy of a demi-official letter dated the 22nd. September 1913, from the HonMole Lieut. Col. J. Ramsay, C.S.I., C.I.dl., A ^ent to the Governor General in Baluchistan, to the Hon'ble Lieut. Col. Sir Henry McMahon, G.C.V.O., K.C .I .S., C.S .I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Depart ment, Simla. I am v/riting to ask whether the Government of India would have any objection to the re -opening of the question of the rendition of Gwadar by Maskat to Kalat. The question was raised by me in my confidential letter No. 31 dated January 20th., 1904, and in Ruseell's official letter Ko . 2613-E. A., dated August 15th., 1904, Yate was informed that the Government of India did not propose to take any action in the matter. The question is almost certain to arise in some form in connection with a railway or the dis covery of mineral oil near Gwadar, or both, for tne boundar ies of the Maskat enclav e on the northern shore of the Gulf of Oman have never been determined, and the opinions of the parties as to their position differ widely. It appea^ to me that it would be far simpler to arrange, if possible, for the rendition of the tract, than to tackle the thorny question of a disputed boundary, and though eastern prejudice against the cession of territory is strong, there are circumstances in the case of Gwadar which should, I think, incline the Sultan to consider favourably its rendition for a consideration. I do not believe that our Engagement of 1862 with France^ regard ing the independence of Maskat in any way precludes the raising of this question, for I cannot find Gwadar mentioned by name in any public document as an integral part of the Sultan's dominions. If we can arrange for the reniflition of Gwadar, we will try to get the document worded to read that the Sultan is returning to Kalat what has always belong ed to it, and not that he is disposing of what has hitherto formed an integral portion of Maskat territory.5P I do not propose to trouble the Government of India in this matter until I can. submit definite proposals acceptable both to the Sultan of Maskat and to the Khan of Kalat. All that I require at present is permission to open the question with a view to ascertaining, through the Political Agents concerned, or otherwise, on what terms the Sultan would be prepared to restore Gwadar and whether these terms would be acceptable to the Khan. I am sending a copy of this letter to Sir Percy Cox. F.C.U.Confl uent it 1^' foreign ©fficc, Simlat the S ~ October 191 3. £rX. Please see Co isy' b demi-orficlal letter dated the 22nd September last, a copy of which he has sent to you direct, to the address of Sir Henry McMahon, on tne question of the rendition of Gwadar to the Khan of Kelat. It is obvious that in view of Saiyid Faisal's death and the fact that the hold of the Huler of Oman over the hinterland is threatened by a serious rebellion while our jyLxskat relations with France as regards their treaty witii/ are still unsettled, the present is not an opportune moment for reopening the question of the I/t the rendition ot Gwadar. I am, however, to request you to keep the matter in mind should a suitable opportunity for initiating negotiations present itself. Lieutenent-Colonel Sir P.Z.Cox. K.C. i.e.. O.S .i.. Political Reeldent in the Persian C- u I l, B u s h i r e.CONFIDENTIAL* Ttie Reaidency# Buohlr9f let November 1915 h } i i Please refer to Colone ^'RamBay 1 e denl-offlclal letter of 22nd September 1913, to Sir Henry McMahon, In regard to the Owadar-Kalat frontier, a copy of 4 which I gave you during my recent visit to Masqat. I now send you a copy of a demi-official letter dated 8th October from Reynolds which dleposes of the question for the time being. ajor S .a .Knox, C.I .E., Political Agent, Masqat.37 Telegram. From Ramsay, Pasni. To Resident, Bushire. Words 112. Dated 18th (received 19th) January, 1914.(8.30 a.m.) 3 Please see my demi-official of twenty ninth September to Cox. I should much like to discuss \ question with you also questions of Persian 'border politics. Shall be between Jewnri Pishukan and Gwadur from fourth February to tenth or eleventh February when steamer leaves Gwadur for Karachi. Could you conveniently come In Lawrence and meet me. Sorry I cannot offer to cone to Bushire. Cypher telegram sent with this explains main object of visit. If you can meet me and see fio objection kindly issue cypher * telegram to Foreign in my name after reading it expressing youragreement. I only have one code in Camp. \ RamsayTelegram. \ Prom Resident Bushire To Ramsay Pasni. No. 103. Dated 2!*rd January 1914 (9 a.m.) Your two telegrams of 18th January. Very sorry I cannot leave Bushir . at present so am not sending your telegram to Foreign. Were it in any rSssible, I would come. Lorimer.'-infl Political v.^ Stttiqn' Qttit*, 6i) Delhi, the ?/e have recently reoeived r. letter from Mr. H. ~ . Heath Eves, of the Burma Oil Company, in which he mentions that the Company are anxious to examine Gwadur territory ana to obtain from the Sultan the right to work any oil that mi^ht be found there. He is being asked to Gornm .unicate with you c'lroot ir 4 :he matter. In dealing with any reference that may be made by him it may be useful to you to know that the Company are at present carrying out survey work in certain parts o_ ^ al no hist ,n in .lalat and Las Bela territory and that prospecting licenses are now being dra^/n up by the Agent to the Governor-General in consultation with the Chiefs and the company. Xno Government of India have also said that they will have no objection, if the Company desire it, to allow them to -take up hereafter uncer mining leases a larger area than the 10 squares miles ordinarily by the rules pcrnittcd ^ rovide( eir action under the prospecting licences is such as to show that they are in earnest inTo in their intention to develop and work the oil field. Two conditions ire to be inserted in the nsreonents viz: - fl) that the Burma Oil Company and their Associntes. the Anglo-Persian Oil Company will maintain tho purely British character of their undertakings in Persia and elsewhere, and should the Anglo-rersian Oil Company oease to be a purely British ^oi-ipany the Burma Oil Company will he required to work independently any concession that might be granted to then• (2) that the Company will undertake to give the British Admiralty the first call upon all fuel oil produced md to supply such oil at a reasonable price. J'U £L . J J. G. Lorimer, Esquire, C. I. , Political Resident in the Persian Oulf.13th February 1914. Y V In case it may be of use, I seid for your information a copy of the enclosed demi- official letter dated February 5th, received from the Foreign Department regarding the desire of the Burma Oil Company to examine Gwadar territory and obtain from the Sultan the right to work any oil that might be found there. • ■ •&gt;. /4r t y K ajor S.G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Agent, Maeqat. R.F. 4 ) !■ lFrom G, C. Whigham, General Manager in India, The Burmah Oil Coy Ltd. The British Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. B U S H I R E. 5, Council House Street Calcutta, 18th March 1914. i in- I have the honour to submit herewith a map showing an area in the Sultan of Muscat's territory at Gwadur over which a license to pro spec t^Petroleum oil is required 'by my Company. A detailed note of 'boundaries is attached to the map. As you are possibly aware, my Company an ^ allied Company - The Anglo-Persian Oil Coy - are under contract to supply large quantities of Fuel Oil to the British Admiralty, and my Company has recently 'been permitted to make a thorough geological examination of Baluchistan with a view to ascertaining whether there is any possibility of oil being found there in workable quantities and whether that country is likely to contain a further possible source of- Fuel Oil supply. In making this examination we have undertaken to give the British Admiralty the first claim on all Fuel Oil produced. It is with a view to ensuring the working of any petroli ferous area that might be discovered in the Sultan of Muscat's territory at Gwadur by a strictly British Company with adequate capital and experience and of securing for the British Admiralty a further possible source of Fuel oil supply that this application is now made and I trust therefore that it will receive your -favourable-\ -2- favourable consideration and that the Sultan of Muscat will see his way to grant my Company the prospecting license asked for. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,{ 4 ) be void and of no effect and in case it shall appear to the said Local Government that its consent to the said grant assignment arrangement compact or under standing was improperly obtained or that the licensee or grantee or assignee of the licensee or the Trust Syndicate Corporation or person with whom such arrangement compact or understanding as aforesaid has been made with the cognizance consent or connivance of the licensee made any improper use of his powers under such assignment agreement compact or understanding the license shall forthwith be terminable by a notice in writing signed by one of the Secre taries of the Local Government and delivered to the licensee or left at the lands for which this license was given. 3. It shall be lawful for the said Collector at all times to apply the said iter amount de- security deposit of Rs. or any portion thereof or any further i e ?eaHibh 1edin ' lim . w ^ c ^ ma y deposited under the provisions next hereinafter contained in 1 making good and satisfying the claim of any third parties in respect of any damage or injury abovementioned done by the licensee and also in indemnifying the Secretary of State against any claims by any such third parties in respect of any such injury or damage and all suits and proceedings instituted against the Secretary of State for or in respect of any such damage or injury and all costs and expenses relating thereto. 4. Provided that if upon the determination of this license or of any renewal thereof the amount for the time being in deposit with the said Collector or so much thereor as shall not be required by the said Collector to be applied as above- _ mentioned shall if the licensee shall become the lessee of any mining lease of the JL ^ said lands or any portion thereof under the provisions hereinafter contained be carried to his credit as part of the rents and royalties payable under such lease or . ^ he shall decline or fail to obtain any such lease as aforesaid then the same shall be returned to the licensee provided also that if the Collector has reason to antici pate that any such claims as aforesaid are likely to be made by third parties he may retain the amount of the said security or such portion thereof as he may think proper for a period not exceeding six months beyond the determination of his license or any renewal thereof as aforesaid. Covenants hy the Secretary of State. T he SECRETARY of State hereby covenants that if upon the expiration by effluxion of time of the term hereby granted the Local Government is satisfied that the licensee has been prevented from completing his search of the said lands by any cause other than his own default then the Collector may with the sanction of the Local Government and at the request and cost of the licensee in writing renew this license for such further period or periods not exceeding two years in the aggregate as the licensee may desire from the expiration of the term hereby granted subject to the like conditions in all respects as are herein contained except this covenant for renewal and also that on or before the determination of this license the licensee shall in the case of mineral oil or minerals other than it be given by precious stones have a right (subject to the rules prescribed by the Government • leraHn Council' ^ or granting mining leases) to a mining lease of so much of the said lands not ses for oils and exceeding the area specified in the said rules as the Local Government may think ioS stonesIvi'i ^ to g rant an ^ ^ ^e case of precious stones shall have a right (subject to the given by the said rules) to the first offer of such mining lease as the Governor-General in Council il Government, may think fit to grant. Additional clauses. And it is hereby agreed and declared that every mining lease which may hereafter be granted to the licensee whether under the provisions of this license or ^ ^ of any other license heretofore granted to the licensee shall (subject to the Rules prescribed by the Government for granting mining leases) contain such considerations and stipulations as the Local Government may consider necessary and that every lease of oil wells heretofore granted to t he licensee shall be deemed to contain— (i) a covenant by the licensee that the licensee will duly observe and perform all the restrictions and conditions imposed upon him by such lease including all such restrictions and conditions as may be imposed upon him in exercise of the power hereinafter defined; I ote .—A lease precious stones———— (go Government of Inciia, leter Ho. 467-1;.,^-^ dated lat December 1926. Proposed rendition of Gwadur to the Klian of llalat. Submitted with file 22/i6. J.C. 23/12 ''here is nothing here on the actual point now in issue, i.e. Kalat 1 s legitimate claim to Gwadur. B.S.H. 24/12. I put up also transferred Baghdad file 8/32 on this subject containing, inter alia a D .0. letter, dated 14/7/20 from the A.G.G., Baluchistan, to the Foreign Secy, Simla. The history of Gwaaur is at pages 601 ff. of the Persian Gulf GazetLeer vol. I, Part I, the claims of Kalat being dealt with at pages 604-5. I have looked up the Imperial Gazett- -eer of India, mentioned in the footnote at p. 603 of the Persian Gulf Gazetteer, but can find nothing beyond the paragraph at p. 415 of Vol !XII. Sabzabad Registers do not go back beyond 1904. 1 have given the 'own Office all the references I have been able to find in the correspondence, but they have not been able to trace any papers. In the circumstances our best course appears to be to pass on to Muscat a copy of Govt, of lndia T s letter, giving a list of all the references available here, and asji for copies of early correspondence.(® q-j COK F ID 1 K TIAL No. 66-P&gt;. of 1927 British ReDidency and Consulate-General Bushlre. 11th ^irch 1927 A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for information, and with a the request that he will study the question and put his views in writing before the Hon'ble the Political Resident on his approaching visit to Muscat. By order Capt., Secretary to the Political Kesiaent in the Persian Gulf. Subject : Proposed rendition of Gwadur to the Khan of rlalat. Letter No. 467-H., dated the 1st December 1926, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, with enclosures.* 4th April 1914. I send to you to save time X copy of a letter written by Ransay to poor Lorimer* It went to Kiroan and has ^uet been returned by his brother. You are probably # from your .lalat expeidences, a good deal intoreated in UTradOr and will now froa the office coiafidentlal files in : aaqat have an opportunity of seeing the asqat point of view. I thin-c that Hie i .i ^hnees will, in s^ite of hia father*© ffer to place hinself entirely in our hande in thia matter, be very re luc trait to give u &gt; Gwadefcr*. . x; Ui© sar^e time, I think it would be nossible perhaps for you very cautioutily t to convey the idea, ahould you think it necessary, that Foreign interference in Gwad^r would alruost certainly lead to its being taken away and/what Saiyid Faisal gave mc to understand sojae raonthe before Ills death, should be a powerful we&amp;oon In our hands. I shall be writing to Hansay myself and will of course let you Lieut-Colonel Be ji , know 1 Political Agent, ..asqat*a know what I aend, but you ml^ht find time perhape to let me have a note on the aubjoct giving youps and the . asqat point of view. The best man to give you information with regard to 4 nuc.bered question* of Ramsay's would be uhaazrad Renoo. fie domes over to .iasqat every now and then and ie Hio i'i^i nes8 t C-.fit .a.s far:aer» He is registered Iti aaqat Consiilate as a British subject. I shall not be able to answer questions 1, S and 4, but will try to ^et hold of S and reply to the general letter# I don 't think the matter presses and it Tiay be sone time before I can deal with it. Ba:uohistan has for years wante r to swallow Gwadar. It is quite likely that you were yourself a rena advocate of this view. I shall be interested to see what you think of it now.V o, 1 (Cc Vidential). • QUETTA. C April 1914, h ^0 I encloae ^'copy of a demi-official dated the February 1914, which Colonel 11 th Ramsay wrote to poor Lorimer. Would you very Kindly supply us with the Information we seek? liven if you cannot supply us with it all, you can probably let us have a copy of the official customs Tariff at Gwadur, To Major S. G. Knox, C.I.i!., i'Ciitical Kesident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. '.C.U. W r&lt;3q Copy of a demi-official letter dated, Sibi, the 4th. 11 th. February 1314, f roi' 1 the Hon 'ble Lieut. Col. J. Ramsay, C.S.I., C.I.E., Agent to the Governor Generla in Baluchistan, to J. G. Lorimer, Zsquire, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I am very sorry that you were not able to come to Eushire for I should much have liked to discuss with you the question of N Gwadur and the Persian frontier. As the Persian Government has ceased to exist in Persian Baluchistan it seems to me that we ought to try and get some hold over the trans- border people and I see no means o/ doing this except by attracting their trade to routes v/hich are under our control; this can no doubt be done by the expenditure of money a.nd trouble, but under present circumstances this will be all for the benefit of Hascat for it would be difficult to take the trade away from Gwadur. Is there anything to prevent foreign nations having treaties with Mascat from claiming in Gv/adur all the rights they claim in other pa.rts of Llascat Territory? If not, very awkward questions for us might arise at any time. I should have liked to be able to discuss the question fully with you before writing to Government, but I must now do just the best I can. It would, however, help me if ycu coulo answer my question above and if you could kino.ly send me any ava.ila.ble documents ~ * £/iowing 1 ne trade of Gwadur for 3 years. Showing the trade of Charbar. T le rate of export and import duties levied at Gwadur both by land and sea. The annual value of Gwadur to Kascat. he Y/ali of Gv/adur is a very pleasant fellow.Office of the'ron'Me the A.G.a , . $In BalucMs*.»».ri. ' v &lt;2^ Dated CiUeVL' ^ ' May 1914 risasc refer to your D.O. letter of the 17th: April on the subject of prospecting licenses for oil.- Thc draft of the licenses to be granted to the Burmah Oil Company for work in ralat and Las Bela is at present under consideration 'by the Government of India, tten the orders of Covernnent are received I will have o copy s«nt to you..ao.//2 4 of' WW* Brltiah Realdanoy and Ounnulate -Genarnl, uohiro, f Q Apt-il 1914. Tlio Political 'leftidciit in the Persian 3^ To G.C# Whlgham, Eb quire. General Manager in India The Burmah Oil Oorapany Ltc 1 . 5, Council House Street, OALOUTTA. Sir, I hare the honour to a o'S the receipt of your letter dated 18th March, 1914 f in regard to the licence decired by your Oompony to prospect for oil over a certain area of Hie Bighness th© Sultan of Masqat f 8 territory in Gwadar. The natter is lender consideration, and I hope to address you definitely shortly. I 1 I I have the honour to be ■/-X Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Offg; Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,■ m VH'/4/4 17th April 1914* 'Ts in a cieni -ol fici il 1 tt r dated 6th February, 1914, to the late r. Lorlmer, Gr nt writes as follows:- f It may be use fill to you to 'now that the ConDany ( rar' h il) are at preaont c rrying out survey m rlr in certain parte of J^uchiatan in ^alat and Las bela territory and that pros-neotins licenses n,re now being drawn up by the Agent to the Governor General in consultation with the Cnlofa and the Comp ny'# I should be nuch obliged if you would kindly send me a blank prospecting license, as it seems likely that we aay need to issue such Uklngs here, bu tails rautandis* it -Colonel C, Archer, Agent to the Governor-General in Baluchlrtan, Quetta* akf NTelegram, R. From ^enn, Ka»qat. To Resident, Bushire, Repeated Foreign. No. 94. Dated 19.4.14. received CO.4.14 (7.30 ) * » * * ♦ Thirdly . His Highness said he hoped that a British forwe wpuld be sent to punish rebels. I told him I could not give any definite assurance on this point. I explained the scheme and details of subsequent organisation as outlined in your telegram. Sultan generally approved of the scheme, I referred to cost of British expedition alao, if one were cent. His Highness demurred at suggestion that Maiqat cuetome should be managed ander our advice. In this connection h« said *. I will give the British Government Gwadar or Dhufar as compensation for the expenses of expedition instead'. * * ♦ * # Benn. l 'y d8* ♦/S'V / v j. : *'? i 4 \} 3, Council House Street, Calcutta, 28tli April 1914. G.C. Whighsn, Genernl Manager in India, The Burmah Oil Co., Ld«, Major S.G. Knox, C.I.E., British Political Resident in the Persialf Gulf, BUSHIRE• Sir, I hare the honour to acknowledge with thanks your letter No. 1124- of loth inst* md shall be glad to receive the further com munication which you hope to make shortly. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant.- 1 'Ockct/ Te3 ezra^i. Bern Political A^ent Muscat. Prom To Ilnox Resident Bushire. No. 470. T ated 9th 3914. PJease see Burma Oil Company's application lor prospecting license at Gwadur dated lath March 1914 to your ?iddress of which copy was sent to me.I have taken no action thinkinij that . l should hear Ifrom you on the subject. ±t no objection may I proceed with the application ^ • &gt; Lieut-Col oneli ■ If / 11 - * VL it 1» 3^ Confidential. Docket Telegram. From Knox,Resident Buohire. To Benn f P.A.Maaqat. O, //jil Dated /6% y 1914. Your docket telegram 470 of 9-5-14. Am making enquiries as to form license takes in such ca^es but meanwhile should be glad of any observations you nay have to offer. I: ItTelegram, From Knox, Bushire. To Benn ,Llasqat. Dated 2nd June 1914( X. P» m *) Kindly reply my D.O. letter 4th April enclosing letter from Ramsay. ivnox.I t o-rfi c 2 zoo 2nd Juno 1914* Ploase rofdr to your donl -ofTlclal letter of 7tli April, 1914,regarding G^wadar^to which I have not ropllod before,ao I awaited an answer from Benn, whom I consulted and who has had a pretty busy time lately* In the meanwhile,however,I enclose an extract from the Bushlre trade report shoving the figures from chahbar for the last 3 years. •Bray,Esquire,V U- Deml-offIclai . /&gt;! /S6 th« June /14 My dear Knox, Kindly refer to your demi-official Confidential letter of 4th Afiril .914 with which you enclosed a copy of a letter dated 4/11 February from Ramsay to Lorimer asking for certain information acout ^wadur. ! must apologize for the delay that has occurred in replying to it j tout as you know we have been kept pretty busy since I arrived here. From what I can gather from, the Mascat files it seems that on every occasion on which the subject of the ' rendition ' of Cwadur has been raised, the conclusion arrived at has been that it would not be n judicious.to raise the question at the present time 11 - not so much from any fear of opposition from the Sultan, but because of the apprehensions that were felt that the French would raise objections &amp; an embarrassing sit uation would result. At the same time the Gov. of India seem to have been of the opinion that the difficulties of such a situation were not insuperable. During the short time I have been in Mascat the Sultan has more.than once gratefully acknowledged his indebtedness to to us for thxjt assistance that we have given him, especially during the last few weeks, in connection with tne Imam's rebellion which has received so serious a set bacK in con sequence. I celieve that H.H. -in his present frame of mind at any rate- would be willing to consider any suggestion that we might maKe regarding the lease or rendition of Gwadui to the Khan of Kalat)6Jt5 ; ; but it would,of course,rest witn us to justify his action if objection were raised by the French. I mention this only to show that the present would probably be an opportune moment to reopen this question, should it be thought desirable to do so. As regards Ramsay 1 s question Is there anything to prevent Foreign nations,having treaties with Mascat, from claiming in Gwadur all the rights they claim in other parts of Mas- cat territory ', I take it that the onl^ Foreign power hav-2. . . if-} &lt;9 -ing Treaties with Mascat who would prefer any such clainr~ would be France* There is nothing to prevent Franc %4alinins m such rights as Ramsay mentions, but, in view of. the principle laid down by the Gov. of India ( vide next para ) it is ex-' tremely unlikely that such a claim would ever come to any thing. In the first place we may,I think,. taKe it as pretty certain that the present akiltan would not nesitate ika to refer the question to us &amp; iHi&amp; leave the matter in our handsjB. ^ and in the next the Gov. of India have already signified by a warning conveyed te the late Sultan in 1902 ( Gov.of India letter No. 159 dated 4th.Sept. 1902 to Secretary of State ).their ' det -' ermination to prohibit any association of that portion of his ( the Sultan's) territory C Swadur ) with and this determination has been approved &amp; confirmed by the Sec. of State for India X vide Seficet Letter No. 47 dated 21 :Nov. 1902 to the Gov. of India ). It seems then that though the SultaJ? might find it dili- icult to oppose a claim sucn as Ramsay mentions, we may ass- - ume that, owing to the above mentioned determination of the Gov. of India, no Foreign Power would ever be able to obtain a foothold in Gwadur territory. I will, as you suggest, cautiously convey to H.H., if necessary the idea that Foreign interference in Gwadur would certainly lead to its being taken away from him. I will now reply to Ramsay T s questions (1) (3) &amp; C4) (1). Trade of Gw arinr for ^ years. .Trade figures for Gwadui are not recorded separately in this office &amp; consequently sep arate statistics of trade between Mascat Gwadur are not ob tainable. The Karachi Customs.Trade reports also do not re cord separate trade stltistics for i^wadur. A rough estimate, however, made in my office with.the assist ance of Messr. Towell &amp; Co. puts the total export &amp; import sea borne trade cetween ^waaur &amp; ^as^at at Rs. 30,000/ annually, made up as under s- Py steamships Imports from Gwadur to Mascat ^ Exports from Mascat to Gwadur Other sundry trade with Gwadur R s_. 5000 Rs. 200003. Brt. over. ^ s# ' EV native sa iling craft Imports &amp; Exports ( no reliable information available) estimated at Rs. 10,000 nn'r&gt; 1 Approximate value of Annual Trade Rs»30 # 000 This takes no account of Land bo me.trade for whicn no figures are available* (2). Cdustoms Duties at Gwadut. (a) On Imports 5 X ad valorem leviable (b) On Exports. nil (J). Annual v ^lue of Gwadur to HftgCftt CV The Customs of Gwadur are farmed out annually. .The present farmer pays Rs. 60,000/_ annually to H.H., so, that this amount minus cost to H.H. of administration of Gwadur C Rs.6000/ approximately ) represents the present annual value ox Gwadur to H.H^. - Rs. 54,000/. 1 It must of course be worth con- sideoably more than.the above suirn for the fanner must make his profit. Two years ago the late Sultan is said to have been offered 70,000/ for the contract , but refused it as ne did no wish to deprive.the present man, Maliomad Renmoo, of it. Yours sincerely f W' firln/ 14th Juno 1914. ^7 Qv v . , : 1- • , I have Just receiv3d the anower fron Benn to yWhlch I alluded in my last demi-official letter of 2nd June to you on the Gwadar Question, c \ p V ^ y J f rhese are the replies to Rarasay ^a questions (l), (3) and (4) but 1 am afraid that our information on the sub ject io very meagre and i cannot understand how (1) and ) go together. The figures of (4) are Drobably accurate enough but one would think that in that case, the figures -'or (l) should be considerably higher. ^ 1)# Trade of Gwadar for S years . Trade figures for Gwadar are not recorded separately in this office and consequent ly separate ntatisties of teisde between ilasqat and Gwadar are not obtainable# he Karachi Customs Trade reT)orts a so do not record semrate trade statistics for Gwadar. A rough estimate, however, made in Masqat office w'th the aoslotance of eeors Towell &amp; Coy puts the total ex port and imnort sea borne trade between Gwadar and Masqat at As 150,000 annually, marie up as under*- y otoamships . inmorts from Gwadar to Masqat. Exports from Masqat to Gwadar. Other sundry trade with Gwadar. Rs 5,000 '10,000 ' p f 000 8 20,000. I3y native sailing craft . Imports and exports (no reliable information available) estimated at ^proximate value of annual trade ' s 10,000 Rs 30,000 This de Bray, Esquire, F• A• to A•G.G• Quetta.• (O. This ta.ceo no account of lancJ-borne trade for which no figures are available. (2 ) Cur&gt;tO' n at Gwadar * (a) On Imports 5^ ad valorem leviable* (b) On Fxports Nil. v r . sj (4). Annual value of Gwadar to Masqat by land and aea . a / rhe Cuntom of Gwadar are farmed out annually# The present farmer pays Ro 60,000 annually to Hlo Highness, so that this His amount minus cost to/Highness of administration of Gwadar (RsB^OOO/) approximately) represents the ^resent annual value of Cwadar to His Highness * Rs ^4,000 . It must of course be worth considerably ■ ■ * more than the above sum, for the farmer must make his profit- Two years ar;o the late Sultan is said to have been offered 70,000/, for the contract, but refused it a® he did not wish to deprive t ie present man, i .luhamnad Rehrrru, of it. I doubt myself if the sultan gets much more than the last figure out of Gwadar but he will probably sot a high sentimental value on it and i rather inagine that his thoughts occasionally turn to it as a possible harbour of refuge when Arab rebels and Foreign Powers get too much for him. Ramsay asks 'Is there anything to prevent Pore^gn nations, having Treaties with Masqat, from claiming In Gwadar all f he rights they claim in other parts of Masqat territory? ,, France is the only Power that in this particular gives usi any trouble. Individual traders are a nuisance and France herself annoys us on principle with a view to ma ing a satisfactory ex- chan .e of her 'power to tease' for more substantial benefits elsewhere* I can hardjey imagine her playi ig the same game at Gwadar. It is too hemmed in |Lnd she would be afraid there of England taking charge, ha would be rowerless to prevent it and it would be obvious to the sultan that this had been the remitHi M result of Pronch folly and she would lose ground with him at Masqat• Benn thinks sultan would be not unwilling to consider question of lease or rendition. I am not so certain once we came to t .e point. Another thinr; is that, whereas if Kranoe got to interfering in uwadar, we could probably turn the question of lease or rendition in our favour, while she stands aloof, she raif^it give us some trouble ae protesting t at our action v/ae contrary to that agreement of 1862 between Great Britain and France to respect the independence of Masqat* e used that with some effect when the Sultan was rea^y to lease France Bandar Jissah and she will not be slow to retaliate.^71 c SO h ^ r Docket Telegrara. Prom Knox, P.R. Bushire. To Benn, P.A. Masqat* D.O. Dated 14.6•14. Many thanks for your D .O. No. 136 on the Gwadar quest- ion* I quite realise that you have not had much time to deal with such matters. I enclose copy of my D .O. letter to Bray based on yours. Of this D«0. to you I keep no copy. fx mam1 a Confidential foifinn ami IWitial Jfiiiivltiunt, rf\V- /r - ^ Simla, the / 1&gt; June 1914 ''ill you kindly ^r&amp;fer to yuur demi-official let ter of the 30th of 'f ay regarding the application of the B'unaa Oil Company to examine Gwa,da.r territory? In vie.v of the hint recently dropped 'by the Sultan ml Political Agent Muscat's telegraiii &gt;J'o. 9^ of 19th April 1914. uf Muscat in conversation with Benn to the ef fect that he might in certain circumstances 'be prepared to cede v wadar to the British Government^ and of the fact that the question of the TTian of Falat obtaining a lease oi ( v/adar from the Sultan has recently oroached oy the 'aluchistan authoritiesj we think it cusira^ble, if possible, to avoid for the present any examination@ exainination of nwadcir territory in respect of oil springs. It vvould, ubviously, greatly enhance the figure of the lease or purchase of Gwadar if an oil «pring '.yere tapped within the Sultan's limits. Would it r. w c oe pusiril:le, for the present, tu ignore Mr. 'hirnaa's letter, or to put him off wit^h the reply t:at as the question of prospecting in Gwadar involved a Political considerations, which would have to e referred to the Government of India, you could for the time being give him no definite reply g„ the subject 'but that you would do so later as - as soon as those considerations have teen disp sposed of.0/{ c 27,6.14. Dear Mr. Whigham, I much regret the delay that has taken place in giving you any definite reply to y ur letter of the 18th March about prospecting for oil in the Sultan of Masqat's territory at Gwadar. The question of prospecting in Gwadar involyes a number of political considerations which I have been obliged to refer to the uovernment of India and I am therefore, for the time being, unable to give you any definite reply on the subject. I will do so later as soon as the considera tions I speak of have been disposed of. Yours sincerely, b.G* Knox.&lt;7/4 2*! ob Confidential# S7•6•• Dear Mr. Grant, Your confidential D *0. of the 16th June 1914 regarding the a-oplioation of the Burma Oil Company to exanine Gwadar territory• 1 saw no difficulty in rerdying to Mr.Whigham on the lines of the second suggestion in your letter and hare done so accordingly. Yours sincerely, S «G« Knox*No. 7552—7581—121. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY DEPARTMENT I GEOLOGY AND MINERALS. Simla, 15th September /p/j. RESOLUTION. In supersession of the rules published with Resolution Nos. 18—17—2, dated the 20th May 1899, the Governor-General in Council is pleased to prescribe the following rules for regulating the grant by Local Governments of licenses to pros pect for minerals and the grant of mining leases in British India :— Rules for the grant by Local Governments of Licenses to prospect for Minerals and of Mining Leases in British India. The following rules regulating the grant by Local Governments of licenses to prospect for minerals and the grant of leases of mines and minerals have been made by the Governor-General in Council, and sanctioned by the Secretary of State for India in Council. Part I. —General. 1. No license to prospect for minerals or lease of mines and minerals can be granted by any Local Government otherwise than in accordance with these rules, except with the previous sanction of the Secretary of State for India in Council, or with that of the Governor-General in Council under any general or special authority which he may have received in this behalf from the Secretary of State in Council. 2. In these rules :— Collector' means the Revenue Officer in charge of the district ; ' Local Government ' includes a Chief Commissioner; and 'Person' includes, besides individuals, a public company registered in India or in the United Kingdom, having a duly empowered agent resident in India, or a syndicate, partnership or private firm of which one or more of the members reside in India, or which has a duly authorised agent resident in India. 3. A license or lease under these rules may be granted to any person ; in case of the death of the person or any of the persons to whom it is granted, it shall inure for the benefit of his legal representatives. 4. For the purposes of these rules the Local Government may, in Provinces where there is a Board of Revenue or Financial Co.nmissioner, delegate to such authority all or any of the powers conferred on Local Government by these rules. 5. Nothing in these rules shall apply to minor minerals such as slate, build ing stone, limestone and clay, the extraction of which will continue to be regulated by such separate rules as the Local Government may lay down in accordance with local circumstances and requirements. 320CID6. The issue of exploring licen?es authorising the surface of land to be searched for minerals having been discontinued, the surface of unoccupied and unreserved land which is the property of Government may be freely searched without authority. In the case of occupied land search can be made only with the consent of the occupier. Provided that in the case of Baluchistan and the North-West Frontier Province, no operations for the exploration of the surface of land for minerals shall be carried on, except under a license granted on such terms as the Local Administration may prescribe. Certificate of approval. 7. No prospecting license or mining lease shall be granted except to a person holding a certificate of approval from the Local Government, within w hose jurisdiction the land lies for which the license or lease is asked. 8. A certificate of approval shall have effect from the date thereof, and shall expire at midnipht on the 31st of December next following; provided that a certificate issued in the last quarter of the year shall be valid until the 31st of December of the year following. Only one person shall be named in the certificate. The fee payable therefor shall be Rs. 50, and the certificate shall cover applicalions in respect of minerals of all kinds. 9. A certificate of approval may be renewed at the discretion of the Local Government on payment of a fee of Rs. 10, if the application for renewal is received within one month after the date of expiry of the original certificate. Otherwise the full fee of Rs. 50 shall be charged. The Local Government may delegate to any officer not below the rank of Collector, the power to renew a cer tificate of approval on payment of the prescribed fee, in any case in which the certificate holder has carried on operations under a prospecting license or mining lease within the jurisdiction of the officer to whom the power is delegated. 10. The names of persons to, whom certificates approval have been granted shall be published in the Local Government Gazette, and every applica' tion for a prospecting license or a mining lease shall contain a statement of the number and date of the Gazette notification of the certificate of approval. 11. Before considering an application for a prospecting license or a mining lease, the Collector shall verify the Gazette notification quoted, and shall refuse any application for a license or a mining lease from a person not in possession of a valid certificate of approval : provided that the Collector may at his discretion require the production of the original certificate of approval. 12. Licenses or leases previously granted may be held by a grantee who is no longer in possession of a certificate of approval. Part II.—-Prospecting Licenses. 13. A license to prospect for minerals or mineral oil, called hereinafter a prospecting license, shall confer on the licensee the sole right, subject to the condiiions contained in the license, to mine, quarry, bore, dig and search for, win, work, and carry away any mineral or mineral oil lying, or being within, under or throughout the land specified in the license. Provided that the right to prospect for reserved minerals shall be exercised only by British subjects. 14. A prospecting license shall be granted only in respect of land in which the mines, minerals, or mineral oils are the property of Government. 15. Every application for a prospecting license shall, unless the Local Government shall in any case otherwise direct, be made to the Collector of the district in which the land or some part of the land with respect to which the license is required is situate.16. Every such application shall contain the following particulars, namely :— (a) The name, profession and residence of the applicant, if he is an individual ; or if the applicant is a company, syndicate, partner ship or private firm, its name, and nature and place of business ; and if the place of business is outside India, the name and resi dence of a member or duly authorised agent resident in India. (d) A description, illustrated by a map or plan, showing as accurately as possible the situation, boundaries and area of the land with respect to which the license is required. 17. Should the applicant for a prospecting license desire the Collector to prepare for him the map or plan required by the foregoing rule, or should the map or plan presented by the applicant be insufficient, the Collector may prepare the map or plan required, and may, if he so order, recover the cost from the applicant at such rate or rates as the Local Government may by general order prescribe. 18. The Local Government may declare, in respect of any specified area, that in lieu of presenting an application containing the particulars required in rule 16 above, the applicant for a prospecting license shall adopt the procedure set forth below, or such modification thereof as the Local Government may prescribe :— (1) He shall, before forwarding his application to the Collector, demarcate the area applied for in the following method (a) At every angle or corner of each boundary line or as near thereto as is practicable, he shall fix pegs of substantial material, stand ing not less than 2 feet above the surface of the ground, and being not less than 3 inches square or 3 inches in diameter. (d) If pegs be not obtainable, he may use instead cairns of stones or mounds of earth, having in each case a height of not/ less than 2 feet and a diameter at the base of not less than 2 feet. (c) The direction of the boundary line on each side of each peg, cairn or mound shall be indicated with reasonable care by a trench having a length of 4 feet, and a breadth and depth of not less than 6 inches : provided that if trenches cannot be conveniently cut, the direction of the boundary lines shall be indicated by finger posts, or in any other manner suitable for the purpose. (^) The pegs, cairns or mounds shall bear or have affixed thereto some distinguishing mark which shall be described in the application. (e) In the case of an application for land on the seashore, it shall not be necessary to mark out the land bel-ow highwater level. (/) No peg, cairn, mound, or other mark employed in marking out the land applied for, shall be removed or defaced after the application shall have been filed, without the permission of the Collector. (2) The application to the Collector shall contain the following particu lars, vtz. :— (а) The name, profession and residence of the applicant, if he is an individual; or if the applicant is a company, syndicate, partnership or private firm, its name, and nature and place of business, and if the place of business is outside India, the name and residence of a member or duly authorised agent resident in India. (б) A description, as accurate as possible, and illustrated by^ a sketch, of the situation, boundaries and area of the land with respect to which the license is required.{c) A description of the distinguishing mark on the pegs, cairns or mounds constructed to mark out the boundaries of the con cession applied for. (d) The date of marking out the concession applied for. (3) The application shall be accompanied by a deposit at such rate or rates as the Local Government may by general order prescribe to meet the cost of survey of the area. (4) Unless the Collector is of opinion that it is not expedient to grant the license, he shall, as soon as possible after the receipt of the . application, cause the land applied for to be surveyed at the expense of the applicant, and the area and all other details ascer tained in the course of such survey shall be presumed to be correct. Provided that the Collector may at his discretion dispense with such survey, if the boundaries of the area applied for conform to boundaries already ascertained in a Government survey, ^he boundaries of survey numbers in a revenue survey. 19. On receipt of any application under rule 16 or rule 18 the Collector, or such officer as he may authorise to do so, shall note thereon the date and hour of its receipt, and shall deliver to the applicant an acknowledgment stating the date and hour of receipt. 20. The Collector shall then, as soon as practicable, inquire whether the grant of the license applied for is inexpedient, either on the ground that the land described in the application is required for a public purpose or otherwise. 21. Should the Collector be of opinion that it is not expedient to £rant the license, he shall refuse to grant it. An appeal shall lie from the order ot the Collector to the next higher revenue authority. 22. Subject to the control of the Local Government, the Collector, if he finds that the applicant is in possession of a valid ceitificate of approval and that there is no objection to the grant of the license applied for, may grant the applicant a license in such form as may be prescribed. 21 In the case of two or more applications affecting the same land, the prior right to a license shall, subject to any^ order to the contrary which the Local Government may in its discretion pass in any particular case, be deemed to lie with the applicant, who being the holder of a valid cert.Hea e of approval and after compliance with the procedure prescribed by the rules, shall have been the first to file his application with the Collector. 24. Every applicant shall, before the license is granted, deposit as security in respect of such license, a sum of Rs. 100 per square mile or part of a square mile of the area covered by the license, or, with the Co lector s permission, giv security to a like amount to the satisfaction of the Collector. 2( r Subject to such deduction on account of compensation for surface damage penalty, or otherwise as the Collector may order, the amount o any deposit made under the foregoing rule, should the depositor afterwards be &amp; An ' ed a mining lease, will be carried to his credit as part of the rents, royalties or deposTt monev payable under the lease. Or should he dechne to receive or fad to obtain any such lease as aforesaid, the amount will be returned to him en his satisfying the Collector that the condition in rule 30 {vtn) has been complied with and on his furnishing the Collector with the information required by rule 33. 26. If a license is not executed within three months ^ ft f r Iea ^ e , h ^ s granted for it, the right of the applicant to such license shall be held t0 ^ lapsed, unless the Local Government, for special reasons consents to grant the same notwithstanding the delay or considers that the delay is not attnbutabl to the applicant.i \ ^ / a J 27. A register of applications for prospecting licenses shall be kept in English in the Collector's Office, specifying— (1) Serial number, (2) Name of applicant, (3) Residence of applicant, (4) Date and number of certificate of approval granted to applicant, (5) Date of application, (6) If application received incomplete, the date of completion, (7) Situation and boundaries of the land, (8) Estimated area, (9) Date of license, if granted ; (or date of order of refusal), (10) Period for which granted, with note as to renewal or extension, (11) Fee and royalty payable under rule 30 (iz) and (m), (12) Amount of deposit, and (13) Particulars of disposal or refund of deposit. 28. 1 he register shall be open to inspection by any holder of a valid certi ficate of approval or his duly authorised representative, on payment of such fee as the Local Government may prescribe. 29. A return of licenses granted or refused shall be submitted by the Collector at such Intervals and to such authority as the Local Government may direct. 30. Every prospecting license shall contain such conditions as may in any particular case seem necessary, and shall in all cases contain the following conditions:— (/) The term for which the license shail be granted shall be one year or such shorter term as the applicant may desire. The license may be renewed by the Collector for a further term not exceeding two years, whenever he is satisfied that a longer period than one year is required in order to enable the licensee to complete his search of the land: Provided that, when the licensee has, before the terminaticn of the period of the license, applied for the grant of a mining lease, the Collector may further extend the period of the license until a mining lease is granted or for such time as he may deem fit. (it) The licensee shall pay a fee not exceeding one rupee and not less than one anna per acre of the land covered by the license. When a license is renewed under the last foregoing condition, a fresh fee shall be payable, subject to the same maximum and minimum charge, for each year or part of a year for which the license is renewed. But no fee shall be payable for an exten sion of the term of license under the proviso to that condition. {tit) The licensee shall pay royalty at a rate not exceeding 15 per cent of the value on all precious stones won and carried away, and a royalty at the rates specified in Schedule A in Part IV of these rules on all other minerals won and carried away over and above such quantity as is allowed in Schedule B to be taken free for purposes of experiment. {tv) The licensee shall make and pay such reasonable satisfaction and compensation, as may be assessed by lawful authority in accord ance with the law in force on the subject applying to the lands over which the license has been granted, for all damage, injury or gaoCIDI disturbance which may be done by him in exercise of the powers granted by the license, and shall indemnify the Government against all claims which may be made by third parties in respect of any such damage, injury or disturbance. Note .—The powers necessary for the proper enjoyment of minerals, the property of Government, together with the methods according to which such powers are to be exercised by Govern ment or by its assignees, are governed by the law for the time being in force in each province. Where the law confers such powers on the Local Government or its assignees, the Local Government may make local rules indicating the conditions on which licensees shall have right of access to minerals, the right to use of water in connection with the working thereof, and the like. {v) The licensee shall not cut or injure any tree on unoccupied and unreserved land without the permission in writing of the Col lector, or of such officer or officers as he may appoint: nor, with out the permission of the Collector, shall he disturb the surface of any road, or enter on any public pleasure ground, burning or burying ground, or place held sacred by any class of persons, or interfere with any right-of-way, well or tank. (vi) The licensee shall have power to assign his license or transfer any right or interest thereunder to a person holding a valid certi ficate of approval subject to the following conditions :— (a) No such assignment or transfer shall be made in favour of any person who, by himself or by those joint in interest with him, already holds a mining lease or leases over ten square miles within the territories administered by the Local Government within whose jurisdiction the land lies for which the license has been granted. The actual position of the transferee in this matter, if not known to the licensee should be ascertained from the Local Government. (b) Every such assignment or transfer shall be reported to the Collec tor within one calendar month from the date of its completion, together with full particulars of the transaction. (r) Every such assignment or transfer shall within a further period of two months be registered in the office of the Collector on payment of a fee of Rs. 50 : Provided that in the case of any particular mineral reserved by order of the Governor-General in Council, the previous sanction of the Local Government to the assignment or transfer shall be required. The minerals reserved at present are petroleum, chromite, and ores of man ganese, vanadium, molybdenum, nickel, and tungsten. Provided also that in the North-West Frontier Province and Baluchistan no transfer or assignment in the case of any mineral whatever may be made without the consent of the Agent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner. {vit) In case of any breach on the part of the licensee or his transferee or assignee of any of the preceding clauses, the Collector may summarily revoke the license, and thereupon all rights conferred thereby or enjoyed thereunder shall cease ; or, should he see fit, he may, in lieu thereof, declare to be forfeited to Government, the whole or any part of the deposit made by the licensee under rule 24. An appeal shall lie to the Local Government against any such order within thirty days from the date of its communi cation to the licensee. (viii) Save in the case of land over which the licensee shall have been granted a mining lease on or before the determination of the license, he shall within six months next after the determination of the license or the date of the abandonment of the undertak ing, whichever shall first occur, securely plug any bores andfe) r 7 fill up or fence any holes or excavations that he may have made in the land to such extent as the Collector may require, and shall to the like extent restore the surface of the land and all buildings thereon which he may have damaged in the course of prospecting: Provided that the licensee shall not be compelled to restore the surface of land or any buildings in respect of which full and proper compensation has already been paid under condition (ry). (**) Should any question or dispute arise regarding the license, or any matter or thing connected therewith or the powers of the licensee thereunder, or the amount or payment of the fee or royalty made payable thereby, the matter in difference shall be decided by the Local Government whose decision shall be final. 31. All operations conducted under the authority of these rules within a reserved or protected forest shall be subject to such conditions as the Local Government may by general or special order from time to time prescribe. It shall be a condition of every license granted under these rules that, before the commencement of prospecting within a reserved or protected forest, 30 days' notice shall be given to the District Forest Officer of the intention to commence operations, and that the operations shall be conducted subject to any conditions regarding the use of fire that he may prescribe. 32. On or before the determination of his license, the licensee shall have a right— (a) in the case of a mineral oil or minerals other than precious stones, to a mining lease in accordance with the terms contained m the rules for mining leases; (^) in the case of precious stones, to the first offer of such mining lease as the Governor-General in Council may think fit to grant. Such lease may include so much land, comprising the whole or a part only of the area for which the prospecting license was granted, as shall not exceed the area specified with respect to mining leases in rule 45. 33. If so required by the Collector, the licensee shall, before the deposit made under rule 24 is returned to him, disclose confidentially to the Collector, all information acquired in the course of the operations carried on under the license, regarding the minerals contained in, or the geological formation of, any area not taken up by him under a mining lease. P art III—M ining L eases. 34. Every application for the grant of a mining lease, not being a lease of a mine of precious stones, shall be presented to the Collector in whose district the land or some part of the land with respect to which the lease is required, is situate. The Collector shall forward the application through the proper channel to the Local Government. 35. A mining lease shall be granted only in respect of land in which the mines, minerals, or mineral oils are the property of Government. 36. With the application, the applicant shall deposit as security in respect of preliminary expenses such sum, not exceeding Rs. 500, as the Collector may determine, or with the Collector's permission, give security to the like amount to the satisfaction of the Collector. If the application relates to an area for which the applicant holds a prospecting license, any amount held in deposit under rule 24 in respect of such prospecting license, will be carried to his account. 37. The amount of any deposit made under rule 36, less any expenses in curred by or on behalf of Government, will, if the depositor be granted a mining lease, be carried to his credit, as part of the rent or royalties payable under the lease, or if he declines or fails to obtain any such lease as aforesaid, will be Teturned to him.8 38. Every application for a mining lease shall contain the following parti culars, namely : — (a) the name, residence and profession of the applicant if he is an individual, or if the applicant is a company, syndicate, private firm or partnership, its name and nature and place of business, and if the place of business is outside India, the name and residence of a member or duly authorised agent resident in India ; (b) a specification of the mineral or minerals for which the applicant intends to mine ; (c) a description, illustrated by a map or plan, showing as accurately as possible the situation, boundaries and area of the land with respect to which the lease is required ; {d) a statement showing all areas within the jurisdiction of the Local Government already held by the applicant or by any person joint in interest with him in prospecting or mining right; {e) the period for which the lease is required. 39. Should the applicant for a mining lease desire the Collector to prepare for him the map or plan required by the foregoing rule, or should the map or plan presented by the applicant be insufficient, the Collector may prepare the map or plan required, and may. if he so order, recover the cost from the appli cant at such rate or rates as the Local Government may by general order prescribe. Note .—It shall be competent to the Local Government by genenl order to direct that an accurate survey be made at the expense of the lessee of all land granted on mining lease, if a map or plan has not been already prepared by the Collector. Such survey may be made at any tim«s after it is decided to grant the lease, the object being to secure an authoritative record of the area covered by the lease. 40. The Local Government may declare in respect of any specified area, that -in lieu of presenting an application containing the particulars required in rule 38 above, every applicant for a mining lease over an area, in respect of which he is not already in possession of or has not submitted an application for a prospecting license, shall adopt the procedure set forth below, or such modifi cation thereof as the Local Government may prescribe: (1) He shall, before forwarding his application to the Collector, demarcate the area applied for in the following method;-- {a) At every angle or corner of each boundary line, or as near thereto as is practicable, he shall fix pegs of substantial material standing not less than 2 feet above the surface of the ground, and being not less than 3 inches square or 3 inches in diameter. (^) If pegs be not obtainable, he may use instead, cairns of stones or mounds of earth, having in each case a height of not less than 2 feet and a diameter at the base of not less than 2 feet. (c) The direction of the boundary line on each side of each peg, cairn or mound shall be indicated with reasonable care by a trench having a length of 4 feet, and a breadth and depth of not less than 6 inches ; provided that if trenches cannot he conveniently cut, the direction of the boundary lines shall be indicated by finger posts, or in any other manner suitable for the purpose. (d) The pegs, cairns or mounds shall bear or have affixed thereto some distinguishing mark which shall be described in the application. (&lt;?) In the case of an application for land on the seashore, it shall not be necessary to mark out the land below high-water level. (/) No peg, cairn, mound, or other mark employed in marking out the land applied for shall be removed or defaced after the application , shall have been filed without the permission of the Collector.(2) The application to the Collector shall contain the following particulars, viz. :— {a) The name, profession and residence of the applicant, if he is an individual; or if the applicant is a company, syndicate, partner ship or private firm, its name and nature and place of business, and if the place of business is outside India, the name and resi dence of a member or duly authorised agent resident in India. {b) A description, as accurate as possible, and illustrated by a sketch, of the situation, boundaries and area of the land with respect to which the lease is required. (c) A description of the distinguishing mark on the pegs, cairns or mounds constructed to mark out the boundaries of the concession applied for. {d) The date of marking out the concession applied for. {e) A specification of the mineral or minerals for which the applicant intends to mine. (/) A statement showing all areas within the jurisdiction of the Local Government already held by the applicant or any person joint in interest with him in prospecting or mining right. {g) The period for which the lease is required, (3) The application shall be accompanied by such deposit, in addition to that prescribed in rule 36 above, as the Local Government may by general or special order declare to be required to meet the cost of survey of the area, (4) The Collector shall, as soon as possible after the receipt of the applica tion, cause the land applied for to be surveyed at the expense of the applicant, and the area and all other details ascertained in the course of such survey shall be presumed to be correct. 41. On receipt of any application under rule 38 or 40 above, the Collector, or such officer as he m^y authorise to do so, shall note thereon the date .and hour of its receipt, and shall deliver to the applicant an acknowledgment stat ing the date and hour of receipt. 42. In the case of two or more applications affecting the same land and presented by applicants who are not in possession of, or have not applied for, prospecting licenses in respect thereof, the prior right to a lease shall, subject to any order which the Local Government may pass in any particular case, be deemed to lie with the applicant who, being the holder of a valid certificate of approval and after compliance with the procedure prescribed by the rules, shall have been the first to file his applitation with the Collector. 43. A register of applications for mining leases shall be kept in English in the Collector's office specifying, as far as may be, the matters prescribed by rule 27 for the register of applications for prospecting licenses. 44. The register shall be open to inspection by any holder of a certificate of approval or his duly authorised representative on payment of such fee as the Local Government may prescribe. 45. On receipt of the application from the Collector, the Local Government may, if the applicant is entitled to a lease under rule 32, or if it considers that the applicant should be granted a mining lease, grant the same in accordance with these rules over such area as it may think fit: Provided that no mining lease shall be granted by the Local Government under these rules, so as to cause the total area held under mining leases for minerals of whatsoever kind by the lessee or by those joint in interest with him to exceed ten square miles within the territories administered by the Local Government. 46. If a lease is not executed within six months after leave has been granted for it, the right of the applicant to such lease shall be held to have 320CIDIO lapsed, unless the Local Government for special reasons consents to grant the same notwithstanding the delay, or considers that the delay is not attributable to the applicant. N ote .—Every lease shall before it is executed be approved by the Advocate General or other legal adviser, if any, appointed for the Province. 47. Without the previous sanction of the Governor-General in Council, the length of an area held under vhe mining lease shall not be allowed to exceed four times its breadth : Provided that this rule shall not apply to areas in river beds held on lease for dredging purposes, in respect of which the Local Government may, with the sanction of the Governor-General in Council, make rules as to the dimensions and shape ot areas for which such leases may be granted. Provided also that the Governor-General in Council may delegate to the Local Government the power to grant exemption from the opera tion of this rule, in respect of specified minerals and subject to such restrictions as to limit of length or otherwise as he may think fit. 48 The boundaries below the surface of all areas given out on mining lease under these rules shall be considered to run vertically downwards towards the centre of the earth. aq . The term for which a mining lease may be granted shall not exceed 30 years but the lease may contain a clause permitting renewal for a period not exceeding 30 years, on a dead and surface rent not exceeding twice the original dead and''surface rent respectively, the royalty payable being that which may on the day next following that on which the original lease shall determine, be in force under the orders of competent authority. co Every mining lease shall contain such conditions and stipulations as the Local Government may in each case consider necessary; and shall in every case contain the following conditions, namt.l\ ; (i) The lessee shall pay a rovalty or royalties at the rate specified in the lease which rate or rates shall be those fixed for the particular mineral or minerals in Schedule A in Part IV of these rules ; and if any other mineral shall be discovered by him, then the royalty shall be paid therefor at such rate, not being less than 20 per cent of the value thereof, as the Local Government may determine, until a mining lease has been obtained in respect of such mineral ; but the lessee shall be entitled within twelve months from the discovery of such mineral to require and obtain such lease for the term then unexpired of his original lease; p - ovided ^that, if he declines to take a lease as above provided, the Local Government may give a lease in respect of such mineral to any other person. (it) The lessee shall also pay for every year after the first year a fixed yearly dead rent at a rate not less than that laid down in Schedule C in Part IV of these rules ; providea that no lessee shall pay both royalty and dead rent in respect of the same lease, but only such one of them as may be of the greater amount. (Hi) The lessee shall also pay for all land which he may take up, use, or occupy for the purpose of the mine a surface rent at the rate specified in Schedule D. (tv) The lessee shall at his own expense erect and at all times maintain and keep in repair boundary marks and pillars according to the demarcation to be shown in a plan annexed to his lease. (») The lessee shall make and pay such reasonable satisfaction and compensation, as may be assessed by lawful authority in accordance with the law in force on the subject applying to the lands over which the lease has been granted, for a amage, injury or disturbance which may be done by him m exercise ot11 the powers granted by the lease, and shall indemnify the Govern ment against all claims which may be made by third parties in respect of any such damage, injury or disturbance. Note .—The powers necessary for the proper enjoyment of minerals, the property of Government, together- with the metho is according to which such powers are to be exercised by Government or by its assignees, are g iverned by^the law for the tims being in force in each province. Where the law confers such powers on the Local Government or its assignees, the Local Government may make local rules indicat ing the conditions on which lessees shall have right of access to minerals, the right to use of water in connection with the working thereof, and the like. {vi) The lessee shall not cut or injure any tree reserved in the lease. (yii) The lessee shall have power to assign his lease or transfer any right or interest thereunder to a person holding a valid certificate of approval subject to the following conditions :— (a) No such assignment or transfer shall be made in favour of any person who, by himself or by those joint in interest with him, already holds a mining lease or leases which is or are, or which with the addition of the area now pro posed for assignment or transfer will be over ten square miles within the territories administered by the Local Government within whose jurisdiction the land lies for which the lease has been granted. The actual position of the transferee in this matter, if not known to the lessee, should be ascertained from the Local Govern ment. {b) Every such assignment or transfer shall be reported to the Collector within one calendar month from the date of its completion, together with full particulars of the transaction. {c) Every such assignment or transfer shall within a further period of two months be registered in the office of the Collector on payment of a fee of Rs. 50: Provided that in the case of any particular mineral reserved by order of the Governor-General in Council, the previous sanction of the Local Government to the assignment or transfer shall be required. The minerals reserved at present are petroleum, chromite and ores of manganese, vanadium, molybdenum, nickel and tungsten: Provided also that in the North-West Frontier Province and Baluchistan, no transfer or assignment in the case of any mineral whatever may be made without the consent of the Agent to the Governor-General and Chief Com missioner. 1 {viii) Unless prevented by reasonable cause of which the Local Govern ment shall be the judge, the lessee shall commence operations within one year from the date of the execution of the lease and shall thereafter carry them on effectually in a proper, skilful and mining-like manner. Should the lessee cease without such cause to work the mine for a period exceeding two years in such a manner as to produce sufficient mineral to earn a royalty at least equal40 the dead rent, it shall be deemed a breach of this condition. Note .—For the purpose of the first part of this condition, such measures as the erection of machinery for the purposes of working the mine, although not necessarily on the Lnd covered by the lease, or the construction of roads or tramways in connection with the mine, shall be deemed to be sufficient compliance with the requirement of commencing operations. (* a ) The lessee shall keep correct accounts showing the quantity and particulars of all minerals obtained from the mine and the number of persons employed therein, and also complete plans of12 the mine, and shall allow any officer authorised by the Local Government in that behalf at any time to examine such accounts and plans, and shall furnish the Local Government with such information and returns in respect of the aforesaid matter as it may prescribe. (a:) The lessee shall allow existing and future license or lease-holders of any land which is comprised in or adjoins or is reached by the land held by the lessee, reasonable facilities of access thereto. (xi) The lessee shall allow any officer authorised by the Local Govern ment in that behalf to enter upon the premises comprised in the lease for the purpose of inspecting the same. {xit} The lessee shall without delay report to the Collector the discovery on or within any of the lands or mines demised by the lease of any mineral not specified in the lease. (*m) Should the royalty or rent reserved or made payable by the lease be not paid within two months next after the date fixed in the lease for the payment of the same, the Local Government may enter upon the said premises and distrain all or any of the minerals or moveable property therein, and may order the sale of the property so distrained or so much of it as will suffice for the satisfaction of the rent or royalty due and all costs and expenses occasioned by the non-payment thereof; and, if any royalty or rent remain at any time unpaid for six calendar months after the date on which it is due, the Local Government may deter mine the lease and take possession of the premises comprised therein. (xiv) In case of any breach on the part of the lessee of any covenant or condition contained in the lease, the Local Government may determine the lease and take possession of the said premises; or, in the alternative, may accept payment of a penalty, not exceeding twice the amount of the annual dead rent, from the lessee. {xv) At the end or sooner determination of the lease, the lessee shall deliver up the said premises and all mines (if any) dug therein in a proper and workman-like state, save in respect of any working as to which the Local Government may have sanctiohed abandonment. (xvi) Should any question or dispute arise regarding the lease or any matter or thing connected with the mines and minerals leased or the working or non working thereof or the amount or payment of the royalty or rent reserved or made payable by the lease, the matter in difference shall be decided by the Local Government, whose decision thereon shall be final. 51. All operations conducted under the authority of these rules within a reserved or protected forest shall be subject to such conditions as the Local Government mav bv general or special order from time to time prescribe. It shall be a condition of every lease granted under these rules that before the commencement of work within a reserved or protected forest, 30 days' notice shall be given to the District Forest Officer of the intention to commence operations, and that the operations shall be conducted subject to any conditions regarding the use of fire that he may prescribe. 52. Every mining lease which includes any portion of a reserved or protected forest shall, if it authorises the lessee to fell timber for mining purposes, specify the area within which, or the quantity up to which, and the terms and conditions upon which, he may exercise that authority. 53. No lease of a mine of precious stones shall be granted except by the Governor-General in Council. The procedure for obtaining, and the conditions'3 of, such lease shall be those prescribed by rules 34 to 50, read as if the Governor-General in Council were substituted for the Local Government. 54. The lessee shall be at liberty to determine the lease at any time on giving not less than twelve calendar months' notice in writing to the Collector: and upon the expiration of such notice, provided that all sums due on account of the lease shall have been paid, the lease shall be determined. When a lessee exercises his option of determining a lease, he shall not be granted subsequently a new lease over a portion only of the land covered by the original lease. PART IV.—RENTS AND ROYALTIES. S chedule A. Royalty—Rule 30 {tit) and 50 (i). Coal, exclusive of dust and coal used on the works ... 5 per cent on the sale value at the pit's mouth, with a mini mum of 2 annas per ton. Coal dust ... ... ... ... Half the rates fixed for coal. Mica ... ... ... ... 5 per cent on the sale value at the pit's mouth. Oil ... ... ... ... ... 8 annas per 40 gallons or 5 per cent ad valorem on gross value. Gold and silver ... ... 7i per cent on the profits*of each year taken separate ly or 2\ per cent on the gross value, at the option of the Local Government. anna per ton of iron stone. per cent on the net profits of each year taken separately (for mining leases only). per cent on the sale value at the pit's mouth, or on the surface, of the dressed ore or metal, convertible at the option of the Local Govern ment to an equivalent charge per ton to be fixed annually or for a term. • Profits shall be taken to mean the excess of ihe revenue which is wholly derived from the sale of the mineral or minerals specified over expenditure, after all costs and expenses chargeable to the actual working and management of the mine shall have been included. But neither depreciation nor amortization nor Direc tors' fees, nor any revenue or expenditure obtained or incurred on account of share or capital transactions, or by trading, shall be brought into the account, provided that the fees of such Director or Directors as may actually direct technical operations and are specifically denoted as Managing Director or Managing Direc tors may be included in expenditure. Schedule B. Maximum quantities removeable free of royalty—Rule 30 {iiij. Class A.—Separated gold, platinum and other precious metals occurring in Nil the native state. „ B.—Auriferous rock and gravel ... ... ... 2 tons. „ C.—Metalliferous ores such as those worked for aluminium, iron, 10 „ manganese, „ D.— Metalliferous ores, such as those worked for antimony, arsenic, 5 „ bismuth, chromium, copper, lead, nickel, tin, titanium, tungs ten, line. Iron ... ... ... ^ Precious stones ... ... ... 30 All other minerals not specified above ... 2\14 Class E.—Metalliferous ores such as those worked for cadmium, cobalt, 2 tons, mercury, molybdenum, silver^ thallium, vanadium. „ F.—Compound ores containing the metals of class E in smaller quan- 5 „ titles than those of class D. „ G.—Concentrates of the ores enumerated in classes D to F ... 2 cwt. „ H.—Coal, lignite ... ... ... ... ... 50 tons. „ I.—Petroleum ... ... ... ... ... 200 gallons. „ J.—Minerals of the so-called *' rare earths,' such as minerals worked 1 ton. specifically for caesium, cerium, columbium, didymium, erbium, gallium, germanium, indium, lithium, niobium, rubidium, tanta lum, thorium, uranium, yttrium and zirconium. ), K.—Minerals used in agriculture and chemical manufactures, such as 10 tons, bauxite, gypsum, iron pyrites, and pyritous shales. „ L.—Minerals used in various arts, such as barytes, bitumen, borax, corundum, emery, felspar, fluor spar. ,, M.—Asbestos, graphite, mica, and native sulphur » N.— Precious stones and gems such as agate, amber, amblygonite, amethyst, aquamarine, beryl, chrysoberyl, chrysolite, diamond, emerald, garnet, jade and jadeite, jasper, lapis lazuli, moon stone, opal, ruby, sapphire, spinel, topaz, tourmaline, and turquoise. Schedule C. Minimum Dead Rent—Rule So {it). , Mineral. Dead rent per acre (minimum). (1) Coal, lignite, minerals used in agriculture and chemical manufac tures, such as bauxite, gypsum, iron pyrites and pyritous shales. 4 annas per acre. (a) Gold and silver, precious stones, and all minerals [not included in (1) above, except iron-ore]. 1 rupee per acre. (3) Iron-ore 1 anna per acre. Note.—These minima are purposely fixed low: but they are liable to be largely exceeded, according to the value of the deposit and degree of development of the country. Schedule D. Surface Rent—Rule $0 {Hi). The rent rate assessable under the revenue and rent law of the Province, or, if no such rent is so assessable, the rate which may be fixed by Government, subject to a maximum of one rupee and a minimum of four annas per acre. ORDER. —Ordered, that a copy of this Resolution be forwarded to all Local Governments and Administrations for information and guidance, and that a copy be forwarded to the Foreign and Revenue and Agricultural Departments, to Chambers of Commerce, and to the Director, Geological Survey of India, for information. Ordered, also, that the Resolution be published in the Supplement to the Gazette of India for general information. J. F. GRUNING, Offg. Secretary to the Coixernment of India, 320CID—aioo—ag-gMS—GCBP Simla i ton. I cwt. Nil.(f® X J Land Revenue IV Mineral 9 PROSPECTING FORM C. To be stamped under Article 5(c) of Schedule I of the Indian Stamp Act, i8gg. LICENSE FOR MINERAL OIL gn Indenture r .adethe day of 19 BETWEEN the Secretary of State for India in Council hereinafter called the Secretary of State (which expression is intended to comprise as well the Secretary of State for India in Council as his successors in office and assigns unless the context shall be repugnant to such construction) of tha one part and of hereinafter called the licensee (which expression is intended to comprise as well the said as his execu ors administrators and assigns unless the context shall be repugnant to such construction) of the other part. Whereas the licensee has applied in accordance with the rules prescribed by the Government for the granting of prospecting licenses to ti^-Coiiector of the District for a license to prospect for Mineral Oil in the lands specified in the Schedule marked A hereunder written and has submitted to the said Collector a certificate signed by a Secretary to the Local Government of Bi ma showing that the licensee has been approved by the said Local Government and has also deposited with the said Collector as security in respect of such license the sum of Rs. being the sum determined by the said Collector for that purpose as required by the said rules AND WHEREAS the said Collector has found that there is no objection to granting the said license NOW THIS INDENTURE WITNESSETH as follows:— In consideration of the rent and royalties covenants and agreements here inafter reserved and contained on the part of the licensee to be paid and observed the Secretary of State doth hereby GRANT and DEMISE unto the licensee the sole right and license (subject to the conditions hereinafter contained)— (1) to enter upon the lands described in the said Schedule A and to mine quarry bore dig search for w r in and work all or any mineral Oil lying or being within under or throughout the said lands without any interruption claim or disturbance from or by the Secretary of State or any other person or persons rightfully claiming from or under him (2) to carry away and dispose of the produce thereof to and for the use and benefit of the licensee (^ for the purposes aforesaid to clear undergrowth and brushwood and (with the sanction of the Collector previously obtained in writing) to make and use any drains or water-courses on the said lands for clearing the said lands or any oil-wells within them from any water which may flow or accumulate therein (4) and with the like sanction to erect and bring upon the said lands all such temporary huts sheds and structures steam and other engines machinery and conveniences chattels and effects as shall be pro per and necessary for effectually carrying on the prospecting operations hereby licensed or for the workmen employed therein. reserving nevertheless to the Secretary of State full power and liberty at all times to enter into and upon and to grant or demise to any person or persons whomsoever liberty to enter into and upon the Soid lands for all or any purposes other than those hereby expressly conferred upon the licensee and particularly (and without hereby in any way qualifying such general power and liberty) to make on over or through the said lands such roads tramways and railways as shall be considered necessarv or expedient for any purposes and to obtain from and out of the said lands such stone earlh or other materials as may be necessarv or requisite for making repairing or maintaining such roads tramways and railways and to pas s Note —All blank spaces must be fill ed up in this form before signature. Name. Words and figures.( ) * Date. Enter number of days. Enter the amount as stated in the preamble. and r pass at all times ov. r and along such roads tramways and railways to, all purposes and as occasion slia require, To HAVE and .0 hold the said right and license and other thepremis-s nr.' y granted and demised with their appurtenances unto the license^ o* tno t—n of O ne Y : ar from * RENDER! JC AND PAYING therefor free and clear from a rat. s tax. s -hargt-s and deductions the u nts ana royaltLs in Schedule B hereto specified subject to tne right of the licensee to win use and take fr^e of royalty fo tie pu,poses o experiment or as specimens the quantities mentioned m Schedule C hen to. Covenants by licensee» The licensee doth hereby covenant with the Secretary of State as fo.lows , The licensee will pay to the Secretary of State the said rent and l oyalties and will work and carry on the operations hereby licensed in a fair oiamly smUu and workmanlike manner and with as little damage as possible to the surface of the said lands and to the trees crops buildings structures and other property thereon. . . i r • 2 He will not enter upon or commence prospecting in any reserved forest included in the lands specified in the Schedule marked A hereunder written without days' previous written notice to the divisional i'orest O, icer nor without obtaining the sanction in writing of that Officer upon such conditions as such Officer may in his absolute discretion prescribe and more particularly without restrictin' the generality of the words preceding he will not cut or fell any eak or othe 'reserved t?ee exceeding .8' in girth at 4' 6' from the ground or any mreserved tree exceeding 3' in girth at 4' 6' from the ground without firs obtain- in' the written permission of the Divisional Forest Officer and vvill pay royalty upon all timber cut bv him orbv his employees or agents according to the rates prescrib ed by the Divisional Forest Officer and will observe all rules and instructions laid down or o'iven by the Divisional Forest Officer in respect to fires and will not within any reserved forest clear any one area exceeding i acre of lorest giowth and the areas cleared by him shall not exceed 10 acres m a. . * He will not enter upon any lands in the occupation of any person v, .tliout the consent of the occupier nor without the consent of the owner thereof cut or n any way injure any trees standing crops or buildmgs huts or other structures or property of any kind of any occupier of the said lands or any part thereof or of any other private person. _ • r n . j.T e w ^| m ake and pay reasonable satisfaction and compensation tor all iiiiurv which may be done in the exercise of the powers conferred by this license and will whenever the said security deposit or any portion thereof 01 any uj'tiier sum which may be deposited shall be applied as hercmaft. r mentioned forthwith denosit such further sum with the said Collector as may be required to bring the amount for the time being deposited up to the required sum of ivs. He will at all times indemnify the Secretary of State against all claims or suits which may be made or brought by third parties in respect of any such damage and iniury and against all costs and expenses relating thereto. He mil simul- faveotisly with the grant of this license enter into a bond in t he sum of Rs. 10,000 {Ten Thousand Rupees) to indemnify the Secretary oj State for any linage caused foihe reserved forest by any act or negligence done or suffered by hunselj or . .... ., no any employee or agent acting or purporting to act on his reserved forT uTnduded ia the behalf and against all area granted brought by third parties in respect of any such damage and iniury and against all costs and expenses relating thereto. . 6. He will not cut or injure any timber or tree on any unoccupied or un reserved land without the permission of the said Collector in writing. 7. He will not grant or assign any interest under this license to any irust Syndicate Corporation or person or come to any arrangement compact or uncer- standing with any Trust Syndicate Corporation or person whereby he is or may be directlv or indirectly financed by or under which ms operations or undei ta.angs are or may be carried on directly or indirectly by or for the benefit of or subject to the control of such Trust Syndicate Corporation or person save and except curing the pleasure and with the preyious consent in writing of the Loca: Government.( 8. He will well and truly measure or cause to be measured upon some pan of the said lands the whole produce which shall be so von as aforesaid of M ineral O il at least &gt; in everv .svw . . , -U'te hvtp and as many other times as occasion may require and days ? notice in writing of everv such measuring shall be given to the said Collector in order that he or some person on his behalf may be present at such measuring ami attend to the proper conduct thereof and no part of the said produce shall on any account be taken away from the said lands until the same shall have been so measured. 8A. He will in any area which he now holds or may acquire whether by lease or license from the Secretary of State or by purchase or otherwise and whether in the Native reserves of Twingon and Beme or elsewhere to the satis faction of the Collector or such officer as he may appoint on this behalf or should a Warden of the oil field be appointed to the satisfaction oi such Warden keep all wells in good repair work them in an economical and workmanlike manner pay proper attention to the exclusion of water from the oil sands and will not abandon any bore until he shall have given at least fifteen days' prior notice in writing to the said Collector or Warden of such his intention and will thereafter plug the same with seasoned wood or clay in such manner that after each section of the pipe is removed the hole thus left shall be plugged before the next section of pipe of larger diameter above is removed. 8B. No new bore or well shall be^ade or sunk within the land described in Schedule A within' a horizontal distance of 100 feel from the boundary or within a horizontal distance of 150 feet from any existing well on land outside the boundary. 9. He will report to the Collector within one month of the occurrence the discovery or removal of any precious stone found by him or by his agents upon the said lands and will within the same period pay royalty of 15 per cent, of the value of such stones to Government thereupon being permitted to retain the same he will ascertain the value of all such precious stones in such manner as the Local Government may from time to time prescribe for the purpose of determining the amount of royally payable in respect thereof. 10. He will upon the expiration or sooner determination of this license or the abandonment of the undertaking hereby licensed whichever shall first occur with all convenient speed remove all such buildings structures engines machinery and other property and effects erected or brought by him upon the said lands under the provisions hereof. 11. He will within six months after the expiration or sooner determination of this license or the date of the abandonment of the said undertaking whichever shall first occur securely plug all bores and fill up or fence all holes and excava tions that he may have made in the said lands to such extent as the said Collector may require and will to the like extent restore so far as may be to their natural or original condition the surface of the said lands and all buildings and structures thereon which he may have damaged in the course of prospecting. Powers of Government. 1. If the licensee shall at any time refuse or neglect to observe or perform all or any of the conditions herein mentioned and on his part to be observed and performed the said (ollector may by notice in writing signed by him and delivered to the licensee or left at the lands for which this license is given sum marily declare that the license hereby granted shall thenceforth determine and thereupon the license and all rights and liberties conferred hereby or enjoved hereunder shall forthwith determine without prejudice to the rights and reme dies of the Secretary ot htate in respecjL, of any prior breach or non-performance of all or any of the conditions hereof on the part of the licensee and except in respect of the covenants on the part of the licensee herein mentioned to be performed after the expiration or sooner determination of this license or after the abandonment of the undertaking hereby licensed. 2. It s ail be lawful for the said Local Government ai any time by written notice under the hand of one of the Secretaries to the said Local Government to revoke its consent to any such grant assignment arrangemtnt compact or under taking in clause 7 of the licensee's covenants mentioned and upon such revoca tion such assignment arrangement compact or, understanding shall ipso facto( 4 ) iter awount de- ted as stated in brea mble d. J ote .—A lease precious stones st be given bv Governor- leral in Council, .ses for oils and erals other than ious stones \vi I given by the Government. be void and of no effect and in case it shall appear to the said Local Government that its consent to the said ^rant assignment arrangement compact or under standing was improperly obtained or that the licensee or grantee or assignee of the licensee or the Trust Syndicate Corporation or person with whom such arrangement compact or understanding as aforesaid has been made with the cognizance consent or connivance of the licensee made any improper use of his powers under such assignment agreement compact or understanding the license shall forthwith be terminable by a notice in writing signed by one of the Secre taries of the Local Government and delivered to the licensee or left at the lands for which this license was given. 3. It shall be lawful for the said Collector at all times to apply the said security deposit of Rs. or any portion thereof or any further ? um which may be deposited under the provisions next hereinafter contained in making good and satisfying the claim of any third parties in respect of any damage or injury abovementioned done by the licensee and also in indemnifying the Secretary of State against any claims by any such third parties in respect of any such injury or damage and all suits and proceedings instituted against the Secretary of State for or in respect of any such damage or injury and all costs and expenses relating thereto. 4. Provided that if upon the determination of this license or of any renewal thereof the amount for the time being in deposit with the said Collector or so much thereof as shall not be required by the said Collector to be applied as above- mentioned shall if the licensee shall become the lessee of any mining lease of the said lands or any portion thereof under the provisions hereinafter contained be carried to his credit as part of the rents and royalties payable under such lease or if he shall decline or fail to obtain any such lease as aforesaid then the same shall be returned to the licensee provided also that if the Collector has reason to antici pate that any such claims as aforesaid are likely to be made by third parties he may retain the amount of the said security or such portion thereof as he may think proper for a period not exceeding six months beyond the determination of his license or any renewal thereof as aforesaid. Covenants by the Secretary of State. T he S ecretary of State hereby covenants that if upon the expiration by effluxion of time of the term hereby granted the Local Government is satisfied that the licensee has been prevented from completing his search of the said lands by any cause other than hi-s own default then the Collector may with the sanction of the Local Government and at the request and cost of the licensee in writing renew this license for such further period or periods not exceeding two years in the aggregate as the licensee may desire from the expiration of the term hereby granted subject to the like conditions in all respects as are herein contained except this covenant for renewal and also that on or before the determination of this license the licensee shall in the case of mineral oil or minerals other than precious stones have a right (subject to the rules prescribed by the Government for granting mining leases) to a mining lease of so much of the said lands not exceeding the area specified in the said rules as the Local Government may think fit to grant and in the case of precious stones shall have a right (subject to the said rules) to the first offer of such mining lease as the Governor-General in Councii may think fit to grant. Additional clauses. And it is hereby agreed and declared that every mining lease which may hereafter be granted to the licensee whether under the provisions of this license or of any other license heretofore granted to the licensee shall (subject to the Rules prescribed by the Government for granting mining leases) contain such considerations and stipulations as the Local Government may consider necessary and that every lease of oil wells heretofore granted to the licensee shall be deemed to contain— (i) a covenant by the licensee that the licensee will duly observe and perform all the restrictions and conditions imposed upon him by such lease including all such restrictions and conditions as may be imposed upon him in exercise of the power hereinafter defined;( 5 ) (ii) a covenant by the licensee that the licensee will not assign or sublet the premises demised by such lease or any part thereof or the rights and privileges thereby granted or any of them or transfer any right or interest hereunder without the consent in writing of the Secretary of State under the hand of a Secretary to the Local Government first had and obtained and that the licensee will not without such consent so indicated as aforesaid come to any arrangement compact or understanding with any Trust Syndicate Corporation or person whereby the licensee may be directly or indirectly Imanccd by or under which the licensee's operations or undertakings may be carried on directly or indirectly by or for the benefit of or subject to the control of any such 1 rust Syndicate Corporation or person; (iii) an agreement and declaration that it shall be lawful for the Secretary of State at any time by notice in writing under the hand of a Secretary to the Loca Government to revoke his consent to any such assignment sublease transfer arrangement compact or understanding as aforesaid and upon such revocation such assignment sublease transfer arrangement compact or understanding shall forthwith cease to be of any effect and that if the Local Government shall be satisfied that such consent as aforesaid was improperly obtained or that the licensee or his assignee sub-lessee or transferree or the Trust Syndicate Corporation or person with whom such arrangement compact or understanding as aforesaid was come to made any improper use of his or its powers under such assignment sublease transfer arrangement compact or understanding then it shall be lawful for the Secretary of State to determine such lease by a notice in writing under the hand of a Secretary to the Local Government delivered to the licensee or any of his Managers or Agents or left upon the premises demised by such lease; (iv) an agreement and declaration that notwithstanding anything in such lease contained it shall be lawful for the Secretary of State by notification by the Local Government or by notice in writing under the hand of a Secretary to the Local Government from time to time to impose upon the licensee vary and rescind such restrictions and conditions as to the Secretary of State may appear necessary or desirable for the purpose of securing the refinement in British Indian territon of all oil which may be won from the oil-fields demised by such lease. If at any time during the continuance of this license or after the determination thereof any question or dispute shall arise regarding this license or any matter or thing connected herewith or the powers or duties of the licensee hereunder or the amount or payment of any rent or royalty then and in all such cases the matter in difference shall be decided by the Local Government whose decision shall be fina'. In witness whereof the said parties hereto have set their hands hereto the day and year first above written. Signed by for and on behalf of the Collector of District acting in the premises for and on behalf of the Secretary of State for India in Council in the presence of Names and addresses of') witnesses. J Signed by the abovenamed in the presence of Names and addresses of witnesses.( 7 ) Schedule B. Rent and Royalty reserved. (1) Surface rent for acres at Rs. - annas per acre totalling Rs. annas to Le paid on the 19 at the office 01 the. _ - (2) Royalty of annas eight per 40 gallons of oil to be paid on the 191 and on the— 191 at the office of the-— for tke oil won. Signatures of parties WitnessesQuantity which may be taken free of royalty Forty gallons of petroleum Signatures of parties Witnesses jk H - v- G. B. J. B. P.—No. 761 A, Stock, 7-i2-)ci2'- 800. Mm T ■ -&lt;IZ, •r&lt; ® 66 The Bu&amp;^&amp;h Oil Company, Limited, m QRBAT BRrTAIS 3 • COUNCIL MOUSE STREET, OFFICE OF GENERAL MANAGER IN INDIA. wi!jui, POST BOX 459. codes useo; A. B. C. 5th EnmoN Private Code, tel. ad .; ' RIGS.' Telephone N o . 1075. BUSHIRE REStOE - r -»- NGY, RlO No D « t E • J i tf j CliNFlOuNllAL ttCQHOS. i ■^LiiauaiL JJUPUL, ^Oa/ctcrta, 23rd July 79 f A* Dear Major Knox, We have Just recently been engaged in drawing up our programme of geological work for next cold season and I think it as well to let you know that one of our staff will 'be going to Baluchistan in October. His work there should only occupy some two or three weeks and if our application for a Prospecting License in the Sultan of Muscat's territory at Gwadur be granted, we should like him to proceed to Qwadur to map the ground there on a large scale. Should our application be granted, you would perhaps be good enou^i to let me know in due course what arrangements it would be necessary to make before sending our geologist to Gwadur and with whom, if any one, it will be necessary to communicate* kJtc tf- Yours sincerely, a,! -lb 8th August 1914. Your suggestion of writin- to T^hlgham was adopted by me and he acknowledged my letter very pro- grow perly, but he is evidently not going to let the graBs/ under his feet for a week later, on the 2^rd July, he returns to the charge with his programme of geological worl: for next cold season# ^ne of his staff is going to Baluchistan in October but his work there will only occupy him two or three works and, if the Company f 3 application for a Prospect* ing License in Uwadar territory be granted, he wants him to proceed to Gwadar to map the ground there on a large scale. This rather forces our hand and I am, with some reluctance to worry you with such matters whai big t lings must be keeping you very busy elsewhere, writing to ask if you think that there is any hope of purffciing the A•H.Grant, Esquire, C.I.E. deputy Secretary, : orei pi &amp; Political Department, SIMLA.—Pi-IV. ® of the question of the lease of Gwadar permanently froin fie Sultan. You will not have forgotten Benn^ telegraa on the subject No. dated ^V\ryw/ . It may be useful to you to know that Beiin puts the anmial value to His Highness at Rs 54 # 000* 'hen the wrangle over the payment for the Levy Corps cones on the tapis, it might be worth while to treat for Gwadar for an arm al subsidy of He 6,000 per mensen. Perhaps Ramsay could find the money from Kalat and let the district go back to its true owner who could malce profitable torrns with the li|U'mah Oil Company. But the payment would have to be guaranteed by the British Government. I'he idea of reddition to Kalat comme ids itself to me because we should be in a very strong position via a vis foreign encmirfcrs. We could say that, by strict historical right, the dis trict belonged to the iChan of Knlat to who returned from a usurper who has made a very decent bargain over the business. I will raise the matter officially if you think there is any hance of our being able to vush it through in thesethese troublouo times• I do not anticipate any great local difficulty on our aide. I.e. Persian Gulf. If o orybody io too busy 9 I think Whigham ohould be told definitely and as soon as possible that we cannot permit any prospecting or even raapmaking in Gwadar next cold weathor.^QirTlcential. ***■:, f BUSHtRE RESIDENCY. fordijn ami political pciravfmrnf, Simla, the Sj't August 191 4., f] qJx) R £ G No-y - i o *' t - CCNFlOLNTiAL fiEGORDS. IV Please refer to your demi-official letter dated the 8th August 1914, regarding VThlgham's desire to have the ground at Gwadar -napped out next cold weather. Archer has promised to let us have his proposals for the rendition of Gwadar to Kalat as soon as possible, and until the question has been carefully considered, It would not be advisable to allow any mapping to be done there. You may, therefore, infoxm Whlgham as proposed In the last paragraph of your letter under reply. Archer'£ ■j^oposals will be referred to you In due course for an expression'expreGsion of your views, so there is no need for you to raise the question officially at present. /&gt;7 4 / To Major S. G. Knox, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, rv Bushire. 5.Doer Mr VYMrham , Yo^r letter of the ^!5rd July necessitated another refor^nos to ■^ef i .d-q'»iartere , which aocotjmts for my delay in rep3 : r ing: • I an sorry to have to tell you that vre cannot permit any prospscting , or even ^ap-making in Gwad^r next cold weather. I should like to add that the prohibition is general and is , of course , not directed against your Oonpany in particular • I ha^e overy reason to hope that consideration of yonr proposals is only deferred • Yours sincerely , G.O.Whigham Esq: General Manager The Burmah Oil Oompany , Linited • 3 • Ooumcil House St: Calcutta •V- ft R •; g N I 2 T he B urmah O il C ompany, LiMrrEiXr . 3, COUNCIL HOUSE STREflT, OFFICE OFjycQRpQpATEn IN OKEAT BKITAlS NERAL MANAGER IN INDIA. POST BOX 459. codes used: A. B. C. 5th Edition Private Code. Tel. Ad. ; '' RIGS.'' Telephone No. 1076, ' 1 1 UHUMUUIBIIL LUUJim, foa/cufaa, O ■ o 0. tjth September 4. Dear Major Knox, With reference to our recent correspondence and especially to my letter rf 23rd July last to you, I now write to inform you that one of our geologists Mr. Phillips is now on his way to Baluchistan to complete some geological work there* This should take him about a month and on completion of the work he will return to Karachi* If by that time you can kindly see your way to allow him to examine the area at Gwadur, over which we have applied for a prospecting license, I should be very much obliged 9 as 1 am most anxious that he should complete this work before returning to Burmah. If you will kindly let me have a reply, I will forward the necessary instructions to Mr. Phillips. Yours sincerely f To Major 8. G. Knox C. I. S., British Consul General, B U S H I R g.■ j2- ' The Burmah Oil Company, Limited. 3, COUNCIL MOUSE STREET, I , UAIIJI I I HI U PtUU\f' a '■■WgMUUJIL TOPfffff, OFFICE OF GENERAL MANAGER IN INDIA. iJHLOktOtiATED LN ORLAl BRITAIN* * t POST BOX 459. codes used; A. B. C. 5th Coition Private Code. T el. A d . ; '' RIGS.'' TELEPHONE No. 1075. a/ctt&amp;a, Dear Major Kno*, 1 have to thank you for your letter of 18th August* I regret that circumstances will not permit of pros** pecting or map-making at Gwadur during the coming cold wwather but trust that later on we may be given a license to prospect in the area applied for* Yours 8incerely 9 r Major 8*a« Knox, British Resident in the Persian Gulf 9 B U S H 1 RTelegram R From Knox Eushire To Resident Easrah no. PRIVATE dated and reed ^an i8tli Q9i5 I have bren placed in a position by a irom Sir H Barnes sKlng me why oil prospecting at Gwadur has l'een stopped. Is there any objection to 111$ telling him the reason confldentia Lly.K? KNOX Teleg am From Sesldent Bnsrah To Knox Bushlre no 75 B dated 18 i 15 Your private telegram 18th Are there any par ere on tiie subject. If so please send. them. COX•v - a I mTelsgram .xi. From - Knox, Bushire. To - Cox, Basrah. No. Nil. Dated 18-1-15. Private. I have bean placed in rather a quandary by a private letter from my old Chief Sir Hugh Barnes asking me why Oil prospectirg at Gwadur has been stopped. Is there any objection to my telling him the reason confidentially. Knox. i i7? 22i 22/16. ^ 3y/n. i / Telegram From To No., Dated P. Political Bushire. Foreign and Political Department, Government of India 811. April 22nd, 1920. Demi-Official. Would the Government of India view favourably the .idea of leasing or purchasing Swadar fromfcan the Sultan of Muscat? vVingate tells me that His Highness would probably be willing to come to some arrangement about it, when he finds a^ o^oa will, that he can no longer get loans on the Gwadar Customs and that the place is no more than a tax on him. I thought,however, that it would be best to ascertain if the Government of India think it desirable to acquire the place before I tell him to carry on. Trevor. i,,. • ' /' 6 g / 31 ./ CONFIDENTIAL British Consulate and Political Agency . ,, RfSiDfsn. Muscat 37th April 1920» From W To « i * &gt; . _ &lt;X C (iwNfiQEMIiAL IttuQfm R.E .L .Wln ^ate Esq, I.C.S. Political Arent and H»E»M ! s Consul, Muscat The Deputy Political Resident, Bushlre. Sir I have the honour to Invite your attention to the question of the status of Gwadar and of the present situation there as reported to me. Gwadar Is a small town with what Is for the Meier an coast a good harbour. In the territories of the Khan of Kalat, but owned by and forming part of the territories of f , the Sultan of Muscat. The boundaries between Kalat state Imcx * ar.d R«x«rx]as«Kx«x*Klt3ytxjtMiWK*isix the possessions of the Sultan of Muscat have never been exactly demarcated^but they aeem to be fairly weil known and never to have formed the basis of serious dispute. A very fair volume of trade for the Interior passes through Gwadar, and there Is large colony of British Indian h- subjects both Khoja and Hindu resident there. T he Sultan's government and effective authority Is represented by a Wall and seventeen 'asker'. The actual authority Is In the ^ = of one Mohamed Remoo. an Aghakhanl Khoja and formerly the Sultan's director of customs In Muscat, to whom the customs have been farmed by the Sultan. This man Is a resident of Gwadar, the agent of the B.I.Company for the Hekran coast ports and the chief merchant In the place. He Is also the 'wazlr' of the Agha Khan for the Persian Gulf. He Is a British subject. Under the terms of the loan the control of the customs In Gwadar and Dhofar Is especially exempted and the director of customs for Muscat and Oman has no authority there.reason for this is that the Sultan's privy purse as far as the revenues of Muscat and Oman are concerned is strictly controlled. His idea was to retain Gwadar and in a lessor degree Dhofar as private estates on which he co-il^ draw a't will. The former he left in the hands of Remoo who had been his chief creditor in Muscat, The revenues of Gwadar are no longer paid into the state treasury, they are not even farmed for a definite sum per year. The Sultan simply draws cheques on Remoo who honours them at nis own discretion, return-Remoo does what he likes with tne G-wa ar customs an^ rules the wali, the British and tne Arab subjects as he thinka fit. The result is not creditable. There are continual complaints from the British subjects, especially the Hindus whom it is assumed Remoo does not favour. The .-ali is povrer- -less. Law and order seam to be almost nonexistent. It is almost Impossible for tae Political A^ent to brin^ an^ effective pressure to bear, and the Director Persian o-ali Telegraphs is in no better position. The Sultan on representa- -tion in any particular case instructs the wali. The latter replies with a non-possumus on the ground that the particular matter concerns the administration of Remoo. T xe Sultan tied hand and foot to Remoo is then unable to do anything atall. The Sultan wit.i his somewhat rudimentiary ideas of finance seems to have had the theory that the finances of Gwadar in the hands of Remoo were inexhaustible. Remoo also seems to have thought that Government would in the future pay the Sultan's debts as they had in the ^ast, an5. that in consequence he could with safety involve the ultan as much as he liked. He has now however been informed that G-overnraent will on no account assist anybody who len^B to ohe Sultan to recover a penny. The immediate result of this has been that he has refused the Sultan's latest requests for money.f \ \ S v 15 /' ? The valueKxsjbc&amp;KadtacK of the revenues of G^a, ar it it difficult tb estimate accurately^as no records exist^and in view of the peculiar way in which it is now run it is quite impossible to obtain any. In 1914 it was ascertained that the customs were farmed for Re.60,000/- per year, and that of§ers had been received for more than this sum but had iDeen refused as the Sultan was anxious to keep them in the hands of Remooe At present it is possible that the Sultan receives actually less than Rs.60,000/- owin^ to his assumed indebtedness to Remoo, It may at least be assumed that the customs are v^ortii Xxxlxxi Rs» 1,00,00/- a year to Remoo i^xpusixxa. The possibility of the lease or cession of G-wadar by the Sultan of Muscat has on more than one occasion been considered by Government. In 190i the Government of India owing to the position of the town with regard to the arms traffic ,and the possibility that other powers might take an Interest in the place which was surrounded by territory under British control, suggested that an attempt should oe lade through the Khan of Kalat to obtain the cession of Gwadar on reasonable termsCSecret letter No.159 dated 4/9/C^ froa ! ..e G of I to the S of S for Inlia). The Government of India were also of opinion that the Anglo -French declaration of 1862 did not present a bar to such a transaction. however negatived the suggestion on the grounds that it would almost certainly be strfcngly opposed by the French. At the end of 1913 the question of the possible rendition of Gwadar was again raised over the intention to demarcate the boundary between Gwadar and Kalat. In this connection the Sultan Sayld Faisal placed the Matter of the demarcation of the boundary entirely in the hands of the British government. Ix Owing to 3 ay id Faisal's ' eata vm afterwards and the fact that our relations with France as regards the treaty were still unsettled the question was dropped. It was however raised the next year again oj one A.G.Q-. in Baluchistan, but again seems to have been shelved.The reasons which from the Muscat point of view male previously the cession or rendition of G-wadar desirable are no longer operative, but in their place hasr arisen an entirely new set of circumstances which ,1 venture to surest, makes the cession of G-waiar by the Sultan very desirable. The reasons which may make the acquisition of Gwadar desirable by Baluchistan through the Khan of Kalat are beyond my purview, but presumab|r they are still cogent now. The reason;- fr&gt;i the Muscat point of view are;- (1) The control of Gwadar by Muscat is ineffective and the cause of frequent complaint and friction# (2) The situation by which the Sultan uses an important possess!:m in the British sphere as a private estate when the only income is of an essentially administrative kind, namely customs, and hanle over this possession to the complete control of an Indian merchant who shamelessly loots him, is , | j not one which v/e should lightly tolerate* (3} The Sultan has openly stated to Government his wish to abdicate provided he should be allowed a certain income in India. Provided hfe is even only moderately compensated for Gwadar he is therefore not likely to place obstacles in our .way as regards the possible rendition of the town on the ground)that such action interferes with his independence. (4) Government have lately taken in hand seriously the reform of the administration in Muscat itself, and have cleara off the Sultan's debts by a loan. This naturally handicaps the state, as though there is every reason to suppose that the state will be able to repay the loan without difficulty, yet with the necessarily limited sources of income it is very difficult for the state to undertake certain necessary works and reforms without* which real progress cannot be made. (5) The fact that Remoo has not supplied the Sultan with all the money the latter hoped he would will make tne Sultan far more inclined to look at any offer from us© It is clear that any action on the Gwadarquestion by us must depend on our attitude towards the Sultan on the question of his abdication, and the present attitude or the French government towards Muscat affairs. The former has been made the subject of a separate communication by me # I would however in any case mc'ie the following proposals. (1) the .Sultan of Muscat Sayid Teimur should be approached, in whatever way the Government of India should think fit on the subject of the rendition of Gwa4«r, (3) A price should be offered for the place cash down in the neighbourhood of six lakhs of rupees. The price proposed by the Government of India in the correspondence above quoted was four and a half lakhs. (3) Of this price if accepted one lakh should be paid to the Sulatn himself in the event of his abdication being agreed to by government, and the remainder should be paid in'fc) i the state treasury. Thfct would form an excellent fund for financing various essential undertakings. There is no doubt that t the present moment the possession of Gwadar is a disadvantage rather than an advantage to the state of Muscat. At tlie same time it is raoidly becoming as far as the Sultan's own poc-cet is concerrt^ -ed considerably less profitable than he had originally hoped» There are therefore reasol|nable grounds for supposing that he may view a proposal to cede Gwadar in a not un avourable light. Should therefore the Government of India still hold the view that the cession of Gwadar is derlrajle, the present is a suitable time for opening the negotiations. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant tuv I.c.s. Political A«ent, Muscat Copy to the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad,22/16. Telegram P. From Foreign Simla. To Civil Commissioner Baghdad. ♦ * Repeated Political Bushirs• No., 907-S. Dated July 81st roceivecl 22nd 1920. Agent to ths It is strongly urged by the/Govemor-General in Baluchistan That in Return for payment of F s 6,00,000 the 'rendition' of Gwadur to the Khan of Kalat should be made Foreign.marnrnm I fl ? ] 22/16. Te' 1 . egram From To Repeated No., Dated R. Civil Commissioner,Baghdad. Foreign Simla. Political Bushire. 3895. July 23rd and received 24th 1920. Your telegram no*907-S., of July 21st. I think it is common (corrupt group) that Rsn rendition of Gwadur is desirable. I am unable to express an opinion as to amount to be paid in return but six lakhs appears to be adequate. I do not consider Anglo-French declaration .arch 10th 1862 can be prevent such rendition without formal previous concurrence of French Government, though H.M.Government will no doubt give them some intimation beforehand. British Legation noticed on rKfisrrBnKX reference to the Gazetteer of Persian Gulf that 27 negotiations regarding the annulment of lease by Sultan* of Muscat of Bunder-Abbas and its dependencies between 13B8 and 1879 were conducted without reference to the French Government. Civil Commissioner.•*- O S) SO 1 . ~ ■ - Ktro/ v &lt;-« Confident 1. inch- |ord(in aiul golilial 5xpdt»rtif, D,Q,i.o. ^ : OQ / IT 1 I.ovember iPi£l BUSHiRt .... i &gt;r** Subject:-Proposed rendition of G'vadur to the Khan of Kalat. m r .ith reference to your demi-official letter {]o.289-S. &gt; dated the 16th October 1921, I am desirod to say that it has been decided net to proceed '.vith the question. The iiultan of ^iaskat has signified his intention to include Gwadur in the iiaskat customs control, and this solved the problem from the ilaskat point of viev since it rould greatly increase the revenue of the State and do a vT ay 'ith the regi .ie of Llohammed Hemco. The sale or rendition of G^vadur thus became unnecessary from the point of vie'- of Maskat and it v ould be difficult to lake out a case on the sole ground of resultant benefit to the Kalat State. It vas indeed the essence of the case to shc v ; first and fore lost th^t benefit Tould accrue to -laskat fro i the rendition, and, failing this, it was feared that any attempt to pre^s the matter v. T ould only be classed as another instance of land-grabbing on the part of the British Government. (TUAuo ft 'i The ilon'ble Lieut .-Colonel A. ?. Trevor, O.S.I., O.I.ii., Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, ii u s h i r elb ConfiJeiiti- 1 170. 467-1', ■^iRE RieiOENCY. ^ fo. . .. ... fS'/z , Prom OUKflOEMi'.L RECORDS. TO The Deputy Secretary to the Governiaeiit ox Inc.ia in the ?oreic:n and Political Department» The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Pe'rsian Gulf ♦ v Dated Delhi, the /^' December 1926, Proposed rendition of Gv /adur to the Khan of lalat. / / / Sir, ,( i h With reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram iro»8395, dated the ^ 3rd July 19 ^,0, I am directed to forward a copy of the Memorandum from the Hon'ble tbe .^ent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner in 3aluchistan, ? o»477 -P, dated the 13th October 1926, with enclosure. marginally cited * 1 papers for your information. The proposed revival of the Ilian of I^ulat's long dormant claim to Gwadur should not be communicated to the authorities of the Kaskat State, but 1 am to ask that the Goverm ent of India may be furnished with any contrary argurents that you may be able to adduce from your records, without having recourse to those of the llaskat authorities. I have the honour to be^ Sir, Your most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the Government Ox India. Copy, for information, to the Kon t ble the *xgent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner in 3aluchistan. \¥Copy of a memorandum 1I0.477-P, d^ted w uetta, the 12tli October 1926, from the Kon'ble the Agent to the Governor Genera! and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, to the foreign Secretary to the Croveriiment of India, ?orei^n and -olitical Department&gt; Simla. Status of Gwadur, I forward herewith for the orders of the Government of India a copy of a comniunic^tion received from the Political Arent, Kalat, regarding the rights of His Highness the Khan of Kalat and the Gitchkis in the port and revenues respectively of Gwadur. 2. It will be seen from Colonel Keyes* letter that His Highness 1 claim is based on the ground that T'ir ITasir Khan the Great, gave the port of Gwadur to Sultan Said as laintenance, only until such time as he could regain his own kingdom; while the Gitchkis contend that the Khan of Kalat only alienated his own share of the Gwadur Revenues and that they are entitled to half of them less a deduction for cost of collection. 3. .s mentioned in Colonel Keyes* letter the question has been before the Government of India on several occasions and as lately as 1920 the rendition of Gwadur to Kalat was urged in the interests of Huscat State; but owing to a subsequent change of circumstances the proposal was dropped. 4. In 1903 however at the instance of His Highness the Khan, the status of Gwadur and the origin of the grant to ZTuscat were exhaustively examined by this Administration and the claims of the Kalat Durbar were put before the Coverrrnent of India in Major (now Sir John) Ramsay's letter ITo.31, dated the 20th January 1904, together with such documentary and other evidence as it had been found possible to obtain in support of them. In reply this Administration was informed that the Government of India did not at that time propose to take any action in the matter. Colonel Keyes informs is that no further informationJkT 1^1 Izzformatlon has since b .en obtained regarding the terms on which Gwadur \/a£ assigned to Sultan Said, and that Is Highness bases his claim on the same grounds as were placed before the Government of Tndia by Sir John Ramsay. It is unnecessary there Tore for me to add anything; to what he has already written^ 5. It is possible that international or other difficulties may have rendered the consideration of these claims inopportune at that time, but as mentioned by 3ir John Ramsay the evidence which has been obtained constitutes^at any rate, a strong priiQLi facie cat. e in support of the ITian* s contention. I trust therefore that recent chan :es in the political situation will permit of the c se being considered on its merits. Should io be ultimately decided that the Kalat Durbar have established their claims to Gwadur, it will not be necessary to consider the claims of the Gitchkis, since they will have to settle the matter with their own suzerain. If however, for any reason the Kalat claim is held to be inadmissible I would request that the Gitchkis' claims may receive consideration, and that I may be informed in due course of the decision of the Government of India in respect of it. Copy of a confidential letter l'.o.3761, dated T'astunr, the 3rd September 1S26, from the Political .^'ent, Kalat, to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Acent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, ^uetta. Status of Gwadur* I have the honour to address you on the subject of the ri ;hts of '''is Highness the Sulean of ' 'uscat in Gwadur. I do not think that the raising of this question by lis Highness the I' lan of Kalat and the Gitchl-is has any direct connection with the matter of 'Sunrg' in the Dasht district of Makran- y Makran v/hich h^s recently been raised by the 1'uscat auth ..rities. believe that the question has been brought to the fore by the regularization of the I'akran revenues and the -..atchfulness which the ^itchkis consequently exercise on the Pacni customs. The death of Sarfaraz Fhan has also caused the Gitchkis to ex-inine the anciexit shares of revenues. 2. The Gitch^is, who were assembled in Ealat for Jir as last month, had made a formal request for the half share of the Gwadur customs which they used to receive and His Highness the Ilhan, whom the Git chic is also approached, has requested le to obtain the recognition of his sovereignty over Gwadur• 3. Tl;ey oase their claim on the -■rounds that'i:ir Hasir Khan the Great permitted Sultan 3aid, who had been driven out of Muscat, to live in Gwadur and enjoy the Khan's share of the revenues thereof until he regained his own kingdom. They state that, after returning to Muscat, the Sultan retained Gwadur and continued to enjoy the Khan's share of the revenues, but paid the Gitchkis their share for a considerable time. The Gitchkis have Maintained ever since our officers first beran to make enquiries in Fakran that the Gwadur revenues which amounted to about 7,')00 dollars, were divided To the Gitchl;is 5,000, to the Sultan of Muscat 3,000 while 1, 300 was allotted to the expenses of collection. They state that they . have sanads to prove that payments were made by Sultan of Muscat to Citchkis upto the recent times. This state ent is su ported by a report from Major Ross, who, in 1358 found 3ibi Uiriam, a lady of Buledi origin, but married to a Gitchki, living, as he believed, on the charity of the Sultan of Muscat, but, as the Citchkis state, on her share of Gwadur revenues. ''he Khan's evidence ai to payments of tribute by the Sultan is more recent. Slaves presented to i'han Khudadad by the Sultan were alive in 1902. 4. The purchase of Gwadur by His Highness the Khan was suggested in 1902 by the Government of India as a solution of certain difficulties, and in the course of the enquiry the claims of His Highness the Mhan and the Gitchkis came to li-'ht. Their ... .—— 1-&gt; T -^V loS Their claim was presented to the Crovernaent of India by tne Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor General in his 51 of 20th January 1934, but, apparently, the acquisition of Gwadur by Talat no longer interested the Government of India, and the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor General was informed (2623- of 15th August 1904y that the Govern] ent of India did not propose to take any action with regard to its rendition. ]'o opinion was given as to the claims of the Gitchkis or the Khan. yt t it. rn he matter was again raised in 1920 by the Resident in the Persian ulf who considered that the acquisition of Gwadur by Kalat was very desirable from the Muscat poin of view (897 of ft 7th iioril 19C0), The Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor General again favoured the proposal, but the Government of India decided not to proceed with the question, 5» Cn both these occasions the decision of Government appears to have been arrived at on grounds connect .:■! with Iluscat policy, and the claims of the Khan of Kalat and of the Gitchkis have never been answered. 6. I am unaware as to whether the State of affairs in Muscat permits the question being raised but trust that the Hon'ble t-.e ei- J : to the Governor 'eneral 7/ill consider that the Gitchkis are entitled to a reply to their claim to a half share of the Gwadur customs. As regards His Highness the Khan, his memory is still excellent and his natural shrewdness is unimpaired. He has, ever since enquiries were instituted in 1902, claimed sovereignty over Gwadur, and nov/ considers th^.t the Gitchkis * claim is so good that his own claim must gain force from being attached.to it• I have the honour to request that I may.be furnished with the decision of the Government of India to convey to His Highness. Superintendent, foreign and Political Department. %r ■ v ' . I'b Conf identifcjL. 19 DO From To political Agency and n.is.M's Consulate, liuseat 18th ii*r«h 1927, jiDHNCV I ?(&gt; X'/9 * Re% No. Uu-v. major G« P. Murphy, CONFlOtHTlAL RECORDS. Political Agent and Uonsul^ltuseat, The non'ble the Political Resident in the Persian (xulf, BUSH IRE » Sir, With reference to your letter no.66-b dated tne 11th March 1927,1 hare tne honour to submit tne folloiving report on tne question of the proposed rendition of Uwadur to the .Riian of Aalat« I hare the honour to 'be, air, Your most obedient servant. major. Political Agent and ru-b.m's Consul,Muscat® mmr* FZcptstrb REPOR T OK THE REUDITION OJ* GWADUR TO THE KHAH 0'»? KALAT. 3$ Gwadur is the sole Burriring possession of muscat outside Oman# It is the third largest port in the atate and furnishes about one fifth of the revenues# At the present moment there is in addition the prospect of oil concessions which might prove valuable• It appears to hare been granted to aaiyid Sultan in 1784 'by ITasir Khan Ruler of JRalat and annexed 'by Saiyid Sultan on his ' i establishing his power at Muscat in 1792# It is said to hare been an insignificant fishing Tillage at that time# ATTEin^TS TO RECOTSR The following is a short summary of GWADUR BY yORCE. attempts made to recover Uwadur between 1792 and 1861 taken from Lorimer's Gazetteer of the Persian txulf;- iSndeaTours were made by the ^rahuis from time to time to recover Gwadur but the weak rulers who followed flasir Khan were incapable of carrying the matter to a successful issue# .Between 1804 and 1807^ it is said^Mir Dostain the Bulaidai Chief of barbaz took possession of Gwadur during the confusion that followed the death of Sai^id Sultan but if the statement is correct he was ejected after a short time# About 183^according to Makrani tradition v shaikh ^asim Gichki threatened Gwadur and succeeded in obtaining payment of the Gichki moiety on account of two years# 0 In 1847 Fakir Jiuhammad the JNaib of Aaij ^tested Gwadur with a force of 1000 men.'His object was to extract from iiaiyid Thwaini a customary annual grant which had been withheld for 2 years# He was kept off with idle promises and small payments till the arrival of a force from Muscat obliged him to relinquish the s*&lt;ge# In 1857 an expedition was organised by Nasir Khan II partly with the object of recovering Gwadurjbut was apparently bought off by the Arab Governor who presented a number of slaves,aW 4 sword to the Ruler of Aalat and possibly a sum of money vs well* (These may be the slaves referred to in para#3 of the Politicali^gcnt Kalat's letter;. ' 'hi o. Another ejjpedition against Gwadur waa by Ahuda Dad Ilhan 'but hatd to be abandoned* ATTEJSiTS TO KECC^nilR The claims of the iQian of &amp;alat to Uiradur GWADTJR THROUGH THE BRITISH GOVERHUEHT. appear to hare been represented to Gorernment for the first time by Major Henry Grecn # C»-B ## Politi«al Agent,Ralat # in his unnumbered despatch dated liarch 27th 1861^ a copy of which is in the Agency records. It was then contended by the Ruler of Kalat that the town and port of Gwadur had been lent to aaiyid Sultan, the Imam of Muscat about the middle of the eighteenth century to enable him to quell an insurrection in some of his territories on the coast to tjp® west- -ward,after which it was to be restored to its owner; but that the then Khan dying and the country falling into a state of anarchy the successors of Saiyid Sultan had taken adrantage of those cir- -cumstances to retain possession of Gwadur. In his official report iso.9 dated 3rd of June 1861 # the Rrrd .G.P. Badger states that the Tgyanrt most probable account of the manner in ^hich Gwadur fell into the hands of tJaiyid Sultan was gifen him by an old iseloochee Chief at Muscat whose relatiyes had been in the serrice of the Imam for seyeral generations and whose narratiTe of facts correspond^generally with the natife chronicles of those ± times. He stated that Saiyid Sultan,the fifth but the braTest son of Ahmed,the first of the reigning Muscat dynasty,haying rebelled against his father, repaired to the Khan of iLhelat and sought his aid in dethroning him. The Khan,wishing to hare a friendly power possessed of a naTal force to protect his coast,and foreseeing that Sultan would erentually succeed to the muscat soTereignty,sc far Tolunteered him assistance as to gire him in perpetuity the town and port of Gwadur,the only attached condition being that he should alway* defend the place against the enemies of Khelat. Considering the unimportance of Gwadur at the time and the HhanU inability from want of ships to guard it from attack,the ReTd. -Badger thought / there was no improbability in this story / seTeral of the faots on which it was founded being supported by contem- -porary Arabian historians./e7 (rOTernment considered that the title of the Muscat State to dBr{ve4 Gwadur»whether ralld or othervriso originally,ho.d doy^rTod a prescriptiTe force from mere lapoo of time# in April 1863 the Commiooioner in bind was informed by the CjoTernment of .Bombay that the 5iian*B claim to Gwadur was as littlo sus- -tainable as his claim to Karachi and as little deserring of countenance.(Lsrimer ? s Gazetteer of the Persian Uulf V#l, I page 605 j. Lieut«Colonel A report no.5 dated 22nd January 1864 fron^/tloryy ■t^Tssa^ay i*.J»Goldsmid,on special duty,to the Gorernment of Bombay states;-' In paragraph 17 of my report dated the 19th ultimo^ quoting from a diary of one naji Abdul nabb^I mention- -ed the 'fSrahuis^ half of ijwadur H as haying been giren in grant by Mir Bussir Khan to Saiyid bultan'# In explanation an^, I may add,in confirmation of this assertion it is now stated that,in former days,Gwadur was in the hands of the folaidi Beloochis. aussir Khan , in consolidating his dominions of Belooohistan into one Gorernment,demanded the whole rerenue, but a compromise was admitted under the terms of which he restored half of the colleotions to these -Bolaidis# When the Imam was put in possession,he also paid this half to the same claimants; but after a time,finding his power more deeply rooted^he refused to acknowledge the obligation and the JSolaidis were thrown out of possession altogether* I am not sure that the claim of Khelat or of J(edje,upon Gwadur,BO fre- -quently discussed of late,would not^if thouroughly sifted / be found to originate in this former right of the -Beloochie to half the rerenues raised by the imam,and not to the town itself,which was a free gift,with the other half rerenue. In this riew,our right to raise the question of reriral of claim on behalf of Khelat would not,it is presumed^ ie recognized by Gorernment or contemplated for a moment#' The aboTe report^a copy of which is in my records)shows that both Kalat and the Gichki Chief of Kej were claiming thtee rerenues in 1864,and discounts somewhat the eTidence of the UtchJcis and the Rhan oontalned in the latter half of para 3/ ■ @ of the Political Agent Kalat'e letter which tries to show that they were enjoying rexenue and tribute subsequent to that date* In this connection I would also refer you ^to the report by llajor F*J»Goldsmid&gt;^ Assistant Coajaissioner in S±nd # on his siission to i&amp;ekran dated 22nd February 1862 paragraph 95 et seq* He states ' Mr John i^Leod in his letter Ho»457 of the 14th HoTember 1853 submitted a representation on the part of the mercantile ✓ coaaiunity of Gwadur,addressed to the Coamssioner in Sind.co*- -plaining of oppression and praying for protection# It was stated that J^aqueer Mahoaed of Kedje had within the previous seven years,appeared before the town with a force for purposes of plunder# 500 Reals had been levied froa the iiunyas to defend the place of which 200 had been paid to the Chief of Kedje to induce his withdrawal# Other specific cases were cited# In his notes to the petition// wr HacLeod. enters into details on the above-aentioned raid or the Salooch soldiery', Mr MacLeod^ object in aaking this representation was to obtain the interference of Governaent in securing protection to the petitioners whoa he looked upon as .British subjects.all connected with our province of Sind# He did not consider that the petty chief who held CJwadur for the la&amp;a of Muscat had any interest beyond the confines of his own town,and thus merchants and traders were 'obliged to secure the goodwill of soae one of the independant^ J3elooch Chiefs in the part of the country they wish to trade in#' A correspondence ensued upon the aatters reported,with the Political Superintendent of the frontier,the late Brigadier General,then Major Jacob; but it was not thought advisable to agitate the question further'# The above report raises a suspicion that the claias ot the Gichxis and Las Bailah to a share in the revenues of LJwadur aay be founded on payaents aade by the iJanias to buy/o @ th«M off when th«y raiied the place and that the eanada in the possession of the Gichkis may 'be connected with the aboTe-aen- -tioned payaents# SeTeral proposals hare been put forward to the (ioTernment of India since then for the acquisition of Owadur; notably in 1885 by Sir R.Sandeaan,in 1891,and in 1900-02 when the interests of Russia and France nade the matter appear desirable# These proposals seen to hare had the result of reTiring the claias of the Khan of Kalat (in 1903) and the Jaa of Las .Bailah (in 1904 )• In 1920,when the 3tate was in financial difficulties one of my predecessors again raised the question of the sale of Gwadur as a solution of these difficulties# 1 would point out that Huscat is an independent so- -Tereign State so that the question cannot be decided by the GoTernaent of India as paramount power in the same way as siailar questions arising amongst tji# JNatire States of India# It would presumably hare to be submitted to the League of nations for arbitration under International Law#By the general law of nations and immemorial usage a peaceable and uncon~ -tested possession of more than half a century would appear to constitute a strong presumption of right by prescription. (Wharton's International Law 3rd edition 1S89 (^168). I submit that the possession of Gwadur by Muscat since 1792 constitutes a xery strong title by prescription which would be hard to shake eren though^ payments may hare been aadtuc extracted from the State at odd times during the first half of the last century by means of expeditions and threats* Political Agent and Consul Muscat# (U*-)Hendition of Gwadur. .;o9 I ciiii not certain v/.iether you v/ish, to taJce up the case until the Air J .oute situation is clearer. ihe f» ox I, ■ -&lt; -\fe asicec us to ^jrociuce contrary arguments to the rendition of Gwadur, and as wejhave nothing in our oi'iice which goes back 'before 1913 ( J uscat used forLierl^ to correspond direct v/ith Govt. ) we have, had ' j o &lt;-osix one _ ,A, ,uscat !so report. His report is below and covers the ground fully, I do not see what xuore \.e can do than forward it to the G .of I. with perhaps a few reiaarks. The situation is perlectly clear. If in 1865 the Governixent of Bombay informed the Gorrjiiissioner in Sind that the Khan's claim o0 rwadur was as little sustainable as his clt-^ to JCarachi, and as little deserving of counte nance, it must be obvioms that in 1927, 64 years later, without the discovery 01 any fresk and convincing evidence we cannot make out any case for Kalat, other than that sel± in terest may die Gate. The Ivalat cl^ixi^so 1 ur as it has ^e put forward by the P.A. in the letter that govt have forv/arded to us, has beun fulij dealt Vv'ith by the P.A.muscat, but as v, e are not in possession of the full case, which was detailed in letter ITo, 51 from the A.G.G. Baluchistan bo the G.of I. aa^ed dated the 20tk of January T 04 we are somewaht in the dark sea about ta its naisxs:, x or they , .ust rely on something better than the P.A.Kalat has put forward in his lette r to combaj* nearly 150 ^ears of adver possession. In the meantime we may forward the re port to Govt; ^^vV }oS From Ho. ^67-N. The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The lion^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. BUSHIRE R&amp; f ^NCY fteg. No 4.7/ j t&amp;hflDENTIAL [,. u ji08. Dated Simla, the May 1927. Proposed rendition of Gwadur to the Khan of Kalat. Sir, directed to refer to Major Parsons* letter Ho. 467-N, dated the 1st December 1926, and to enquire when a reply may be expected. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. With 1 spare copy./ 0 ^ \\lj 140. X9b&lt; L«? of 1927. British Hesidenoy awl Contjuiate-Ccneral, ^uahlre. bth June 1927. -c . Prom 'he Hon^le Lleut-Cqi. L.B.H.Hfiworth, I.A., olitical Resident in the eryian Gulf. r he Foreign Secretary to the CoTernnent of India in the Foreign and olitical J^epartment, Binila. of Yoposed rendition of C\isadur to the iCharv/Kelat. ir. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your reiainder Ko. 4C7^i. # dated 8tth iiay 1^2? # on the subject of the proposed revival of the .haii of iCelat's long dorraant claim to 0*adur. ''he doournento sdi on tl.is oubjecc are iminly to be found at .uscat or with the Govermoent of 3kMi;bay since at the ti « KKiien corresj^ondence on this subject took place . uscat was directly unaer chat Governioent and not under the residency at I'uohire. he olitical A ^ent y * uscut, has sent xac a report on the question which is not however sufficiently full and I an: addressing the Governnient of Borabay for copies of certain papers. he Bia.ter would however appe^ix to have been die- •posed of by the decision of the Covermaent of BoisIMl in 1665 when they stated that the Than *3 claim zo Cwadur was as lit tie I sustainable as his claim to Karachi unu as little deBervin^ of 0 countenance. 'he following year, on the 22nd June ibOA, uleut-Jol. ?.J.Goldsmid^ on special duty, states to the Governracnt of Bombay/®7 (@ Bombay w In thlu vien, our rinht to raise the queetlon of **revival of oXaim on beliaJLf of KeXat wouia not, it is preourat;d 9 be recognised by Coverniacnt or oontempiated for a raoxaent. H . It may be noted that the cue tons duties of Cwadur were in 1661 worth 4 t 000 dollars. AM the vioyerty was given to the future Sultan of Muscat in 1764« its value at the tine of gift laust have been very oaall. Todc^ these duties are worth Ks. 1,20.000• Unless some very new evidence has been discovered it would appear hardly likely that a claim so definitely dismissed after careful enquiry 64 years ago would be sus- -tainable today, when possession of 145 years can be clained, but I am looking up records and asking for those to which reference is made which are not in my poesossion. It would in any case be desirable to delay any final decision on this point until we know whether we desire to purchase Gwadur vide para^ra^is 26~8 of despatch Ko. B3 -3., dated 19th February 1927, Cur purchase, should we desire it, could probably be made to satisfy both j^arties* I I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. rdi-* 1 h 1 v 'vV. Lieut»CoX., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* m Or/^f COKFlir ir;iAL . Ho. 196-^. of 1927• British Heaiclency and Conouiate-Generai, Buahlre, bth June 1927. (® From he Hon'ble Lieut-Col. L.B.H.Haworth c I.A., Political Peoident in the Persian Gulf. 'he Chief Secretary to the CoTermnent of Boiabay. Political ]DeiJartincnt l Bir. 1 have the honour to state that at pa^e 605 paragraph 1. Vol I, ^art I (Historical) of Loriiaer's Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf will be found the folloving statement M and in April 1863 the Cozrs&amp;issioner in aind was informed 'by the Government of Bombay that the Khan's claim to 'Gwadur was as little sustainable as his claim to Karachi and as little deserving of countenance.' I should be much obliged if you could send me a copy of the letter of which this is an extract and also if possible the document showing the enquiry upon which this decision was arrived at. I have the honour to be 9 Sir, Your most obedient servant^ 7 - PC Lieut-Col. t Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.uopy. From io foreign Department rolltical. Sir, .,o. 878 G: U. Aitchison, esquire, O.S.i., secretary to tile trovernment of xndia# u, (ionne, esquire, oecretary to tne uovernment of j^omDay. Dated Port William, tlie 11 tii April 1872, lj xn reply to your letter ino , 194^ dated 30tJi &amp;iarcjti last m 7;ni on xiis Excellency tne governor m council suggests tnat tiie assertion of sirteep Ibrahim Ahan as to the question of sovereignty of uharbar navmg been determined oy the English and rersian commissioners last year snouid be brougnt to tne notice of tne rersian uovernment, l am directed to state that this suggestion had 'been anticipated by tne uovern- -ment of xndia, 2, ^n the 2btn December last tne .oritisn xainister at ieheran was informed tnat tne ngnts of Muscat in uharbar were in no way affected by tne iyieicran arbitration, ne 'was again so informed by teiepnone tne 6tn juebruary lb72 and m a message dated 2ytn February he was told that as muscat was a State in long and fnendiy alliance witn tne British uovernment no . aggression upon ner by rersia or any otner powercould be countenanced or encouraged. 3,. me (jovernment of India has furtner expressed its willingness to mediate between rersia and muscat m reference to unarbar, if requested to do so by botn parties, xhere seems therefore no room for apprenension that tne good faitn of tne j^ntisn uovernment can m any way be called m question. j.he present correspondence will be forwarded to n.M's Minister r at Teheran. i have the honour (&amp;t be vsd} u.U.Aitcnison uecretary to u QVt. or P.T.O.no. 2355. roiitical department, joombay Castle, 21st April xoi'S. memorandum from the Comtsaioner m sind xso. 347 dated 6tli April 1872 - suggesting that orders be issue • by uovernment that clerks or members of tne xelegrapn Department on the reicran uoast be prom bi ted from receiving political communications from native chiefs.- resolution.- ihe commissioners co^umcation to tne director Me^ran Coast and Sut -^rine Telegrapn, should be approved - and the mdo-European Telegraph Department requested to issue strict orders to tneir employes in accordance with Sir William niierewetiier * s views.- vsd) C. Gonne secretary to uroverniiient. To The Coiiimisal oner m oind, The indo -auropean xelegrapn department v for issue oi orders to ^r. Walton ). True Copy. Ud) G.C.Gilder for Asst Secretary. irue Copy Ud) Jas. Chas. Edwards Asst. Hesdt. in the rersian uuli.Conf ic'ential . No.0/43C8-C. (&gt;7 i^rom Political Department, Bombay Castle,^ 7 / ' July 1927. J. 1&lt;. Martin, Esquire, C.I.E., Chief Secretary :o the Government or Bombay, Political Department; To The Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. c3% Y COIrflUt: 'isL KCC Guhject:- supply of cojies of official doc^jments. Sir, A r ith reference to your letter No. 196-S., dated the 5th June 19 27, regarding the claim of the Khan of* Khelat to Gwadur, 1 am directed 'by the Governor in Council to enclose copies of the following; letters:- (l) letter from the Commissioner in Sind No.4i, dated the 9th A^ril 18 63, letter from the ( 2)/Government of Bombay, Secret Department, No.95, dnted the 13oh looo, and to invite yuur ut tension to paragraph J of the latter document. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. ^ Zcrf Chief Secretary to tfie Government of Pomtay U '/f ^f/f Political Department. / i&amp; r ^ * je ■ ar-^n en t. From The ConiL'-i33-C£*3r in Sind- To Hi3 Excellency tne HonoralDle 3ir H. B. E. Prei^e, K.C.B., Governor and President in Council, ±Jom bay. Dated 9th April 1865. Honorable sir, v I nave tne honor to enclose a letter to Your Excellency * s address rrom His Highness the Imaum of Muscat, and tlx re e de spat dies from Captain BLslDrowe bo the Chief Secretary. I also forward copies of a letter and accompaniment adciressed 'by Captain Bis'browe to myself. These papers were -- sent to me express 'by one of the Imaum * s vessels of War. 2. His Highness the Imaum asks to 'be furnished with instructions from the G-overnment of Bombay as to the course ishich he should adopt with reference to the threatening letter addressed to him 'by rbrahim Khan, the Persian Governor of Bunpoor. in this letter Ihrahim Khan insists upon the Imaum preventing tne English from carrying the telegraph line to G -wader , and as an alternative, threatens to occupy Gharbar, which he describes as lent by Persia to Muscat, and to advance himself to G -wader, and put a stop to our proceedings. 3. The statement that Gharbar was lent by Persia to the Imaum, I 'believe to 'be false. The* I I The Reverend Mr. Badger in his report to Government No. 9 of the 3rd June 1361, writes, 'Charbar was taken 'by Seyzed Sultan, grand-father of the present ruler of Muscat, alDout a century ago, and has since remained in the an disputed possession of his suc cessors' . But whether the statement he false or true, the merits of the Question are not affected. The Pe r si an G-o ve mm en t i t se 1 f coul d n o t summ aril y re sume territory of whicii it ha.d placed the Imaum in posses sion; a for t iori , such a proceeding by a subordinate orficial, proiBssedly acting without orders from his Government, would be a most gross outrage. 4, i nave little doubt tnat the Governor of Bunpoor acts under secret instructions from Tehran. This view is confiimed by a letter which I have just received from Major Henry G-reen, C.I.3. From this I learn that this same Governor of Bunpoor has sent an Elchee to the Khan of Khelat, nominally to complain of one Az ad Khan of Khar an, 'but, 'his real ohject'. Major G-reen writes, 'is to obtain a pretext for / advancing towa.rd3 Beloochistan.' 6. These proceedings, coupled with the recently avowed deteimination of the Persians to interfere in the affairs of Herat, suggest a fear that the time is not distant when we shall 'be again 'brought into collision with Persia. It may 'be as well to con sider at once how we can 'best fortify ourselves against such an event. 6. It is, I think, most desirable that we should obtain Gwader from the Imaum, either by purchase or on lease. Your Excellency is already well aware of the advantages which this position would give us, and it is therefore unnecessary forme to ennumera,te thorn. II have coinmunicated with Captain Dishrowe on the subject, and hope in a few clays to 'be in possession of the Imaum's views. 7. I would now urge upon aovemment the advisability of at once despatching a small 'body of troops to Gwadur , provided that we can obtain the consent of His Highness the Imamn to our so doing. Doubtless, the Persian Government will protest a.gainst such a proceeding, 'but the conduct of the Governor of Bunpoor has furnished us with a conclusive reply. 'You yourselves', we can answer, 'have forced us to do as we have done. We -were peacefully employed at Gwadur with the full consent of the ruler of the country, when suddenly a Persian Governor threatens to lead an army against us, and prevent us 'by force from carrying on our work. How can you compla.in oi our taking measures to protect ourselves ?' 8. Another question which will doubtless engage ijiie serious attention of Your Excellency in Council, is, whether we should give any assurance of assistance to the Imaum, in the event of his territory oeing invaded oy the -- Persians. It appears to me dirricult to avoid doing so, seeing that the calamity will 'be drawn dom upon him solely in consecjuence of the assist ance which he has rendered to us. As his threaten ed possessions lie along the sea, boa.rd, it will be easy for us to give him efficient assistance. 9. i beg that I may be favored with instructions with the 1 ea.st possible delay, and I will then at once sta.rt with the pei^nission of Your Excellency in Council for the Coast of -- MekranMekran and Muscat, should Your Exceiienoy agree with me as to the advisaMlity of despatching troops to GwacTur, I 'beg that you will telegraph to the Officer Commanding the Division, desiring him to place at my disposal as many men of the 1st Belooch Regiment as I may think necessary. I consider that the Beloochees will l3e far more useful than men of a regular Native Infantry Regiment. 10. In considering the question of the expediency of purchasing Gwadur, I have not alluded to the claim which the Khans of Khelat have from time to time made to the possession of that place. In their letter to Sir Charles Wood, No. 44 of the 12th July -- 1861, the Government of Bom 'bay have expressed their opinion that this claim is untenable; an d I do not -- myself think that either the Khan of Khelat or any of his feudatories would raise any objection to our pur chasing Gwadur, especially if they were made to under stand that our object is to check the advance upon their own territories of their hated enemies, the Persians. A long lease might 'be less likely to excite their jealousy than an absolute purchase; 'but on the whole I consider that there is no ground of apprehension sufficiently strong to induce us to forego the manifest advantage s of independent p osse ssion . 11, I append to this letter a copy of my replies to the Imaum and to Captain Dishrowe. I have the honor to 'be, Hon* hie Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, Sd/- Commr. Office, ) Kurrachee, _ ) 9th April 1363. j 3. Mansfield. Commissioner in Sin d. P.S. Major Green has infoittied me that it is impossible for him to spare any troops from Jacohabad.I &gt;10. 93 of 1863. Secret Department. '3° © To S. Mansfield, Esquire, Comraissioner in Sin d. Sir, I have the honour 'by direction of His Excellency the Governor in council to acknowledge the receipt of jjrom tne cominissioner in Sin d. No. 41, dated, tne 9th April 1863, enclosing a letter rrora His Highness tne Sultan of Muscat, and three letters from Captain BLs'browe to (xovemment, with copies of a letter and. accompaniment^ addressed, 'by that Officer to the Commissioner. From the commissioner in Sind. No. 42, dated the 9th idem, with enclosures. From Ditto, No. 43, dated the 9th idem, with enclosures. your letters, and their se^veral ac companiments, entered in the margin relating (1) to a threaten- in g comm un i ca t i on addressed hy the Persian Governor of Bunpoor to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, regarding the extension of the Telegraph works to His Highness* port of ChoWbar-, (2), to the deputation of a Persian lichee to the Court of the Khan of Khalat, and (3) to an intima tion received from the Political Agent at Muscat, expressive of His Higimess the Sultan's willing ness to pennit the occupation of Guadur 'by .British trooDS. 2. His Excellency in Council approves ^ en or ally of your proceedings, as now reported, and requests that you will proceed to act on the views expressed 'by you for the protection of the telegraph. I am however desired to state that nothing in the shape of Military occupation 'beyondbeyond what is necessary for the eTfeotual protec tion of the wolfing parties of the Telegraph within the Khalat territory and the possessions of the 3u 11an of Muscat should 'be attempted without express orders from the Governor General in Council. 3, when on the spot you will 'be the best Judge of what number and description of men will he required for the purpose of protection; 'but His Excellency in Council requests that you will 'bear in mind that there is probably a good deal of empty 'bluster in the letter from the Governor of Bunpoor. 4. It is certainly not for the want of will that the Persians have hitherto abstain© d from attempting to possess themselves of the Sultan * s ports on the Melaran Coast, and if the Persians did not feel disposed to -- meddle with the Sultan when he stood alonQ, it is not likely they will do so now, when the attempt would he an act of direct hostility against the British Govern ment. 5. You will probably find that if you leave at Guadur, the Officer whom you have 'been authorized to select as Assistant to trie Political Agent at Kheiat, with a small personal escort such as the Officer would under any circumstances require, nothing will 'be seen of any Persian force, and even should any attack 'be attempted, the Sultan's Governor, with the moral -- support which the presence of a British Agent and his escort, assisted 'by the Telegraph Officers and their guards will afford, would doubtless 'be able to protect our Telegraph parties from 'being interrupted. 6. His Excellency in Council anticipates that you will 'be able to leave at Guadnr a Gunboat ^fiiich will be useful to communicate with the work in g parties on the coast, as well as with Muscat and Kurrachee.7. As regards our o-m position at Guacljar, you have already 'been famished with instructions to treat with His Highness the Sultan for the pur chase or lease of such portion of his possessions there as you may find on visiting the spot, to 'be necessary for the perfect security of the Telegraph. Any arrangement you may make in this way will of -- course oe subject to the final approval of the Governor General of India and H.er Majesty♦s Govem- men t. 8. His Excellency the Governor in Council does not see any present necessity for discussing the question raised in paragraph 8 of your letter No. 41 of the 9th instant. The Sultan has proDahly no apprehensions that he will 'be a loser, or suffer detriment in any dispute with nis neighbours, occa sioned 'by his willingness to aid us in the matter, and such 'being the case, it does not appear necessary formally to decide the question raised 'by you. 9. As for any clam of the Khan of Khelat, His Excellency in Council scarcely deems it necessary to place you on your guard against giving it the slightest countenance. It rests on precisely the same footing as His HigJiness the Khan's claim to Kurrachee, and after a dispossession verging on a century, His Highness cannot 'be surprised at our declining to take the slightes notice of it. 10. I am desired to enclose under flying seal, the instructions which iiave 'been communicated to Captain Disbrowe on the important subject under consideration. No time will 'be lost in furnishing you with any farther instructions which may 'be receive dreceived rrom the Govemor General of India or HBr Majesty's Govermnent with whom the final decision of all the questions raised in the present corres pondence must rest. I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most oheclient servant, 30/- H. L. Anderson, Chief Secretary to Oovemment, Bom 'bay. Bombay Castle, 13th April 1863. True copies for SuperintendentConfidential From y ZutAm k ? v^M- N0.94-S. C#' !■ A The Hon^le Lieatensnt Colonel H.B.St. John ,0# I.E. tC.B.E. Agent to the Governor General and Chief Gomnisgioner in Baluchistan. Sir 'Denya Bray, K.C.I.S. ,3.3.1. yC.B.E. » Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. . .. Date4 Sibi, the 8th February 1928. • i In continuation of my telegram No. 10-S, dated the 9th January 1928, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a note by Lieutenant Colonel T. Keyes, C.S.I. , C.M.G. , C.I .ii., Political Agent, Kalat, on Oil on the lekran Coast, for the info mat ion ..of tiie Government of India. I concur in the views expressed by the Political Agent. I have, etc., 3d. R. 7/ingate, for Agent to the Governor General in Baluchistan.$. J ^ I t A telegram froc the Rcsicert in tre -ergian Gulf was received by t e ^gent to tne GoTern &gt;r General on January 3rd informing hir tbr-t an Anglo-Persian Oil Co» party was landing at Giradur and wished to survey along a certain line in Kalat ZiaJcran. The Agent to nh Governor General replied that, though Kalat State was willing to consider the grant of a regular exploring license for the coastal area, oanction could not be accorded to casual exploration of this sort; and that a regular exploration would require the sanction of the Governi ent of India# Meanwhile the Anglo-Persian Oil Company^ geologist hac' c-rrived in Gwadur and asked the Assistant Political Agent Makran for escorts telling hira that the Resident had arranged for his exploration. I directed the Assist; nt Political Agent to recall the escorts which had started for Gwadur, and- telegraphed to the geologist not to enter Kalat territory. The Resident wired to say that he was awazed to find thf?t; the Anglo-Persian Oil Company had not got an exploring license for Kalat as he had raised this point 9 months ago. The geologist wired saying that there was no intention of exploring for oil in Kalat State, and that the only reason for the survey was to exanine the geological conditions underlying Gwadur. The Anglo- Persian Oil Company wired from Basrah as follows:-- 'We venture submit following for favourable consideration. \7e hold exploration concession from 3ultan Muscat for Gwadur area which expires Hay this year. It was intended make geological reconnaissance there last winter and we sent map showing area to be traversed to Political Resident Persian Gulf January 1927. In response his request we ostponed reconnaissance 12 months and again notified Resident Bushire August December our intention. He replied conditions were normal did not anticipate anyany difficulty. Ve thereupon deapatohed geological party Gwadur early January but have now ascertained that permission proceed beyond confines Gwadur can only be sanctioned by you. We wish make brief reconnaissance in Kalat territory only in order correlate geological evidence obtained Gwadur with that in contiguous territory. TTot desired obtain exploration license nor undertake detailed work there. Understand Resident Bushire has forwarded our sketch map showing traverses geologists wish make. 3hall be grateful if you yri i kindly grant permission for traverses indicated on map as our geologists are held up Gwadur. If direct sanction not feasible may we request you forward application urgently Government of India tor favour necessary permisjion.^ The following reply was sent with the concurrence of Agent to the Governor General;-- 'Regret delay in answering due to necessity consulting Agent to the Governor General and Khan. Regret Khan unwilling 7 permit casual exploration as indicated in your telegram but as already stated he ie willing to consider grant of exploration license for whole of liakran coast should you be prepared to guarantee serious operations in Makran. In circumstances an not prepared to press Khan. Agent to the Governor General reporting matter to Government. H The possession of G'wadur is the matter in whicn His Highness the Khan takes the greatest interest, and I believe he thinks th?t I have not pressed his case with sufficient vigour. His Highness is also extremely jealous of the 3 lakhs which he has heard that the iiugti Tumandar has received for an exploring license. He has the crude idea that oil flows down hill, andl f Salfc and Iphur especially* and 'believes that any oil tapped in Gwadur would be Kalat oil which had flowed in from t^e 1 akran hills. Nothing therefore would induce him to agree to granting any facilities in Kalat to a Company which was trying to work oil in Gwadur# He would look on t-^is as assisting the Company to take his oil for which they would pay the Sultan of Muscat, and thus appreciate the value of Gwadur and toke it unlikely that the Sultan will agree to restore it to hiru Crude as these ideas arei there is something in them. It is more than possible that if there is oil under Gwadur the dome lies in Makran; and the mere rumour of oil in Gwadur will no aoubt iiake the Sultan less likely to agree to render it to the Khan. • It is thus unreasonable to expect the Khan to a^ree to grant, the Anglo-Persian Oil Company any facilities unless they obt: in a regular exploring llcenss, and give guarantees to carry out serious operations in his territory. This last proviso seems imperative in view of the habits of the Oil Companies which have explored Baluchistsn. I had already discussed with the : ,Vazir-i-Azam the desirability of offering e monopoly for exploration for oil in the State to some Company that wo^ild guarantee to undertake serious work, and was in coix.unication with the Council of the Geological Society with a view to obtaining a geological survey of the State. The rueation of the development of the geological * resources of the State at the same time as its agricultural and commercial resburces is of the utmost importance; and the ;re ent proposals of the Anglo- Persian Oil Company cut across the combined schemes for the&lt;• the -&gt; ^Daaht Rivor area where the development of Irrigation» oil and sulphur working and the carrying trade from Gwattur Bay go hand in hand. In these circumstances I trust that no pressure may be brought to bear on His Highness to gr .nt to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company any facilities which may prejudice our present schemes for the development of this important tract on the Persian frontier# 3d. T. Keyes, 28-1-28.CO HF IDEi:T IAL • ho. 467-lu From •i&gt;7 (S) Tiie Deputy Secretary to tiie GovernLient of India in the Foreign and Political Department, The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Bulf. // &amp; Dated New Delhi,the /b February 19^8. PROPOSED REHDITIOH OP GV^ADUR TO THE KHA1T OF KALAT. Sir, BUSH!' E RBGIO^NCY. Reg. No. ... Dai? / ' 3 'T- lOhriDEl i i&lt;&gt;L. fslv., w .;3- I am directed to refer to the corresponaenee' enaing with ^ jcrti • your letter No. 195-S., dated 5th June 1927, and to request that I the Government of India may be informed whether you have been able to adauce any contrary arguments from your r^coras as requested in major Parsons 1 letter Ho. 467-1^. , dated 1st December 1926. . I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most ooedient servant, n Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. hn 'si-vVw ? Confidential. ^ ^ M 220-3. British Residency and Consulate-General# Busairei the 2nd Juna f 1923. From. The Hon'hle Llout-Col. L#B # H»Kaworth.,It Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To. The Foreign Secretary to the ^vernment of India in the Foreign and Political Deptt f Simla. I'ropoaed rendition of c ^wa ^ur to tag Ki^n .i?f .Kflal- Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your letter No 467-N dated the 16th February, 1928, I have the honour to state that it has not heen possible to adduce from my records or those of Muscat any further arguments against the ?Chan of Kelat's claim to Gwadur. This is not surprising in view of the fact that the claim was definitely dismissed 'by the Oovernnent of Xtombay afiiar careful enquiry so far hack as 1863.- i I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Col., Political Hesident in the Persian GulfT-'v/ © „ (3? ' 7fJ ^0.^.467-11. A copy oi' the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information, with reference to the correspondence ending with his letter J:*o.228-S, dated 2nd June 1928. By order, etc.. v v CJLV ■ 6 M for Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Department Simla. The July 19ii8. Letter to the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor- General and Chief Gommissloner in Baluchistan, i;o.P.46 r /-i;, dated 18th July 192b. (With 1 spare copy)CCI^IJK T L &gt;L. No. J 1 .467-lf. JTom The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, To The Hon^le the Agent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan. Dated Simla, the .18th July 1928. Proposed rendition of Gwadur to the Khan of Kalat. \ Sir, With rel'erenoe to the correspondence ending with my endorsement iso.467-11, dated 25rd June 1928, I am. directed to say tha't ^the Government of India, on a careful considera tion of Colonel Keyes' restatement of His Highness of Kalat claims to Gwadur revenues and those of the Gitchkis, con sider that it is impossible now to reopen a proposal definitely rejected so long ago as 1863. The observations then made by the Bombay Government are of equal or greater force today :- 'As for any claim of the Khan of Khelat, His Excellency in Council scarcely deems it necessary to place you on your guard against giving it the slightest countenance; it rests on precisely the same footing as His Highness the Khan f s claim to Kurrachee, and after a dispossession verginr on a century His Highness cannot be surprised at our declining to take the slightest notice of it H , 2. The finality of this decision has perhaps been obscured to some extent by the fact that the Government of India did not withhold consideration from proposals made(S) made subsequently from time to time to acquire Gwadur from His Highness the Sultan in teturn for a quit rent or other consideration, and to hand it over for management either co the Khan of Kalat or the Baluchistan Administration, vuch consideration by the Government of India however res tea on the recognition of the Sultan's right cv possession, did not in any way imply a departure Irom the originot.1 decision of the Government of Bombay. v he Government of India consider that the claim whether of His Highness the Khan or of the Gitchkis is wholly untenab le. I have, etc., Sd/- J.G.^cheson, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. *</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00015f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/378</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00015f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/378</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 22/16 I (A 41) GWADUR, Oil, Proposed Cession and Ownership'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1928</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-12-20T00:17:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (159 folios)</extent><extent>Contains an index of six topics at the front of the volume.Arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use is the sequence of numbers appearing in a circle in the top right-hand corner of each folio. An original foliation sequence (not circled) links the folio numbers in the index at the front of the volume.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to proposals to prospect for oil at Gwadar (mainly referred to in the papers as 'Gwadur'), and discussions over the ownership and proposed cession of the area, which was in the territory of the Sultan of Muscat.The file includes the following papers:correspondence concerning demarcation of the boundary between Gwadar and Kalat, 1913-1915papers relating to the Sultan of Muscat's sovereignty over Gwadar and the claims of the Khan of Kalat to Gwadar, 1913-1928, including correspondence between Lieutenant Colonel R A E Benn, the Political Agent in Muscat, Major Stuart George Knox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and D de S Bray, Quetta, dated April-June 1914, discussing the possible cession of Gwadar by the Sultan of Muscat and noting possible objections on the part of the French; trade statistics for Gwadar and Muscat for a period of three years, June 1914; letter from R E L Wingate, Political Agent, Muscat, to Lieutenant Colonel A P Trevor, Deputy Political Resident, Bushire setting out reasons for a possible cession of Gwadar by the Sultan of Muscat, 27 April 1920; papers discussing the history and relative strength of the claims to Gwadar by the Sultan of Muscat on the one hand, and the Khan of Kalat and the Gitchkis on the other, 1926-1928proposals by the Burmah Oil Company Limited to prospect for oil in Gwadar, 1914, including a map of territories (scale one inch = four miles) over which a prospecting licence was required by the company (folio 33), with description (folio 34)statistics of trade for the years 1910-1913 relating to Chahbar, 1914rules for the grant of mineral leases, 1914details of trade statistics relating to Gwadar, 1914report on oil on the Makran coast by Lieutenant Colonel Keyes, Political Agent, Kalat, 28 January 1928.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Burmah Oil Company Limited</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00015f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>