<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00028a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:30:03.619Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDOtUROPEAN TELEGRAPH—PERSIA'SS^VICX TiLiORAM. FROM SIMLA, DAT if) 20TM SiPTiMBSR 1 888 . FROM FORiTOTI. TO BUSMIRi. ro Has t d smt. CONF I DiTT T I AL. YOJR TaLSORAM OF I7T«. FOLLOWIMG FROM SSCR2- TARY OF STAT £ B iG IMS * * YOUR LORDSRIP^S TSLiiGRAM DATiiD I5T^ S iPT iMB »£R. OMAN- TURKISH INFLUENCE PAPERS SENT BY POST 7TB OF SEPTEMBER. WRITS TELSGRAPKS 6TH OF SEPTSMBER GRAND VI^I^R STATE THAT THE PORTS DID NOT INTEND aNY SERIOUS MOVEMENT AGAINST OMAN. WALI OF r ^ /' BAGHDAD HAS MERELY ADOPT ED CERTAIN MILITARY MEASURES TO RE-ESTABLISH ORDER AMONG ARAB TRIBES BETWEEN BUSSORA aT(D ^lEJD. EfTDS . COULD TIOT BAHRAIN AND TRUCIAL CHIEFS BE TOLD TO REFER ANY PERSON DEMANDING TRIBUTE TO YOU.? DO YOU CONSIDER WE NEED INTERFERE IN CASE OF LAND ATTACH.? IF SO, HOW ? BY SEA WS SHOULD DOUBT LESS MAINTAIN THEIR IND EP END STIC B . MUSCAT- HARDLY POSSIBLE TO RECOGNIZE SEYYID FEYSAL YET. HE AND I BRAHE EM MIGHT BE ^WARNED OF FOLLY OF QUARRELLING IN PRESiNCi OF NEAR ADVANCE OF COMMON ENEMY.Postponement of the recognition of Seyyid Fey sal as Sultan of Muscat, No. 7 (Secret), dated India Office, London, the 8th March 1889. From—The Secretary of State for India, To—The Government of India. I have to acknowledge the receipt of Foreign (External) letters of Your Excellency’s Government, Nos. 9 and 10 of the 22nd January, on the subject of affairs in Oman, and, in reply, to state that your proposal, based on the recom mendation of your Resident in the Persian Gulf, to formally recognise Seyyid Eeysal bin Turki as Sultan of Muscat, has my approval. Telegram, No. 760-E., dated the 15th April 1889. From—Foreign Secretary, Simla, To'_-Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Secretary of State agrees to formal recognition of Seyyid Eeysal. Do you still think this desirable, and, if so, wouldjou attach any warning or conditions ? Telegram, dated the 16th April 1889. —Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—Foreign Secretary, Simla. Yes, I think best (to) recognize Eeysal and without conditions or warning. If Government approve and will authorize me at once by telegram, I shall pro ceed with Stratton to Muscat, and if situation (is) unchanged, convey Viceroy’s message with usual ceremony. Telegram, No, 20-R.E., dated the 20th April 1889. From—Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. . Your telegram, 16th. Muscat. Please act as proposed and inform Seyyid Eeysal that Viceroy hopes Muscat will enjoy peace and prosperity under His Highness’s rule. Telegram, dated the 2nd May 1889. From—Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—Foreign Secretary, Simla. I have visited Muscat and consider it advisable to defer formal recognition of Eeysal for the present. Report by letter. ExdA~P. K. B.mmCONFIDENTIAL TELEGRAMS FROM SIMLA.DATED I5TH APRIL 1889. PROM FOREIGN. TO BUSHIRE, TO RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF SECRETARY OF STATE AGREES TO FORMAL RECOGNITION OF SYED FEYSAL. DO YOU STILL THINK THIS DBSIRABLE;AND IF SO, WOULD YOU ATTACH ANY WARNING OR CONDITIONS ? FROM BUSHIRE,DATED I6TH APRILI889* FROM RES IDENT.PERSIAN GULF, TO SIMLA, TO FOREIGN, YESj I THINK BEST RECOGNIZE FEYSAL AND WITHOUT % ANY CONDITIONS OR WARNING. IF GOVERNMENT APPROVES AND WILL AUTHORIZE ME AT ONCE BY TELEGRAPH, I SHALL PROCEED WITH STRATTON TO MUSKAT AND IF SITUATION UNCHANGED CONVEY VICEROY*S MESSAGE WITH USUAL CEREMONY. COPIES FORWARDED TO THE OFFG J POLITICAL AGENT AND CONSUL MUSKAT FOR INFORMATION. no: 90 OF 1889, BUSHIRE, POLITICAL RSIAN GULF. COLONEL, 1889.\f ^ BRITISH R2SIDSMCY &amp; CONSULrAT £-GENERAL* # BUSHIRS, 4 ^ AY 1889. FROM COLONEL, E. C. ROSS , C. S. I . r POLITICAL* RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF &amp; H.M* S CONSUL-GENERAL FOR FARS f TO SIR H.M.DURAND K.C.I.EJC.S.I SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT* SIMLA * SIR, WITH REFERENCE TO MY TELEGRAM OF 2ND INSTANT,IN V/HICH I INFORMED YOU THAT I HAD VISITED MUSKAT AND HAD CONSIDERED IT ADVISABLE TO DEFER THE FORMAL RE COGNITION OF H.H.SEYYID FEYSAL, AS SULTAN FOR THE PRESENT• I HAVE THE HONOR TO REPORT AS FOLLOWS I- * * LAWRENCE * * ACCOMPANIED BY LIEUT STRATTON TO MUSKAT ARRIVING THERE ON 26TH. MY INQUIRIES ON THE SPOT INTO THE POLITICAL CONDITION OF OMAN, LED ME TO THINK THAT CONSIDERABLE DANGER EXISTS OF A SERIOUS RISING OF hin-ashtr tribes of SHARKIYAH against seyyid fsysal. it APPEARS THAT HIS HIGHNESS SEYYID ABDUL AZEEZ AND SEYYID IBRAHIM BIN KAIS ARE IN INTIMATE CORRESPONDENCE. A LEARNED ON GOOD AUTHORITY ARE TAKING STEPS TO RAISE 2 ON THE 22ND OF APRIL I PROCEEDED HENCE IN THE MONEY&gt; V 4. AT MY LAST iHTSRVtalfc SiYYID FSYSAL HIS HIGHNESS ASKED ME IF I HAD AH Y SPECIAL ADVICE TO OFFER HIM,AND I TOOK OCCASION TO RECOMMEND THAT HE SHOULD ENDEAVOUR TO ARRIVE AT A 'MODUS VIVENDI WITH SEYYID IBRAHIM,AND THAT HE SHOULD INFORM SHAIKH SALIH THAT PROPOSALS FROM SEYYID ABDUL AZEEZ WOULD BE ENTERTAINED. I ALSO POINTED OUT THE INCONVENIENCE IN MANY WAYS OF HAVING NO CONFIDENTIAL AND TRUSTED OFFICIAL TO BE THE CHANNEL OF COMMUNICATION WITH THE POLITICAL AGENT. TO ALL THESE POINTS SEYYID FEYSAL PROMISED ATTENTION AND SAID THAT MOHAMMED-BIN-AZZAN, A SUITABLE PERSON, WOULD BE AP POINTED TO THE POSITION INDICATED. I ha ve SD E.C.ROSS,COLONEL, POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULP. /- /t~ yi rteo /-jL ■fj f 1 '/'» \ / £c&lt;* 4 c 0^/1 C/ /&amp;_ y frzLy . y r tC^C cy ^// x ^ ^ $ ^ tC^yf ^ ^ ^ j &amp;util ^ ~it ' C^C\, A^. Ca^c-t h/b^ustai^ tlv'hj’ n~ h-ttt/CJC) &amp;-x, hUjil. Co-^ CCCyifJ^ oCl^ J , UfCn£) ^ h* 1 ' ^ ^ /uC /it A- ' . ^ iryu ^ &lt;’ 4. ctBuij /'fcw^h 4 ^ . ^ -AtX hvCfeeZe C^y i dJi 4} H+'C a Cfi-o e c&lt;? ye^^ &amp; (r yi ^ jz /t^ a&lt;^_ j atb A/fcltC j . W^. Ae, h-tC LviU. X ^CiwiAf Ct&lt;jc '/aa (Z/y{^ * / ^ U ' ^ * ytj ^ cn^/iS . Uiv^/l h x»</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00028a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/50</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00028a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/50</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File XXXIII/1 Affairs of the Ruling Family Succession and Recognition of Saiyid Faisal, 1888.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1888/1890</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-01T23:05:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (44 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 46; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains telegrams, and reports regarding the issue of the succession to the Sultan of Muscat, Turki bin Said al-Bu Sa‘idi and the discussion on whether to recognise his son Faysal as a ruler or not, and the fear of the rise of the Sharqiyya tribes led by Shaikh Salih bin Ali al-Harthi.A large part of the correspondence is in the form of a report (ff 14-38) between the Political Residency in Bushire and the Political Agency in Muscat, which states the reasons why the British Government think that Faysal is unfit to govern. The report also discusses the desired terms of succession from the perspective of the British Government, the political climate in Muscat and its relations with the Omani tribes, and the claims to power being made by different candidates. The report also includes a summary of the relationship between the British Government and local leadership and a review of the current Commercial Treaty and subsidies between the British Government and Muscat.The file also includes translated letters of Abdul Aziz bin Said al-Bu Sa‘idi (ff 40-44), in which he gives his own vision regarding Oman and its people and regarding the issue of the succession.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ṣāliḥ bin ‘Alī al-Ḥārthī</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Abdul Azīz bin Sa‘īd Āl Bū Sa‘īd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Hināwī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00028a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>