<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000157_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T04:56:00.790Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/461-4/1S Rl IQMfn ^ v-/ ^ ii j r ' » - or ,, | A I L _.coiinoani «.'®o3r~| The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to :■ \ y j The Honourable the Political Eesldent in the Persian Gulf, Bmshire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated..... 19th .June.. 19.3.7... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Agent,Bahrain 1 s note dated the 19th June 1937. Zubarah. i'p-V\ SwJ J The r epres e at at tres of Q&amp;t&amp;r ee.ae to see »- tr.ia Boraing sad stated that ShaiMi. lasir had Just rotumed from Doha and that SiaiMi Abdullah had rejected the Ba'arain OoTernEent*s suggestions that the mtter be deferred for one year. The representutiires are infor®- ing the Bahrain aoirernro^nc of the c-itue felon to sorrow *]} . I eel out to the Qetsr representc ti^es that no progress had. been made and that they appeired to have contented themselves with rejecting every proposal that had been pat forward by the Ruler of Bahrain's represeatati¥es ana had. Eiade no fresh suggestion on he- half of ShaiMi .Abdullah fhey coiffixLaiiied that Bahrain that the liala were eoELdtting was tirsstng the Ifela and ■-- ^v r Tarious acts milch eere not in eonfor-shty with the under- ta^iag mmB hj thea to the Besident* I'hey ^era f however, unable to Bent ion hy r*&amp;m r^nyone 1^0. h€.d. suffered at the . h,,^/r : s '■ ' ' ' r . hands of the «aim or anyone who had actually seen dhows # anannition or rifles io*-ving ffri.... certain ^-arllfce deaaastrations occurred in laharraq and I understand that there is § certain aaount of truth in this stateaent as 8halkii SshaMsad has been being silly 1 1 ' 1 111 '''' altheu^i the Baler of Bahrain has is,-;.aea ^ery clear s»js5assffe»w«si§ais^^ orders and the occurrences complained of had ceased. ^ _ y L&amp;u&amp;s -■ ■ ■ Sd/~ T.H. 19-6-Bf.19/243 Telegram K.17 prons Political Agent, iiahrain. 'x'o jfolitical He side nt, -ouahire. Mo • 138 Dated and received 22 nd June 1937 • important iour telegram of 15th June, So. 560* lour presumption correct, i sent the letter by special Agency I have had no reply. messenger on 21 st June. isS C^' % I ^ I lU** r ' Enclosure to my printed Letter l ^o.'j/l5 of 26 th May. Jiahrain Gov eminent informed me to-day that they suggested following amendments (a) Article II. Delete 'according to the terms of the agreemen t Minor additions to Article IV. (c) Part 2, ' Article 1» to be reconstructed to read as follows: 'As long as the •U above conditions are carried out without alterations i agree to withdraw my claim to Zubara and the iMaim but should there K \ \ rw 1 i J pe n any thing co n trary to the c o ndi tions my claim returns as before.* 4, Qatar representatives refbsed to accept suggestions on the ground that they could not agree to less than complete withdrawal of -oatirain claim to Zubara and the xiaim. They refused to oo n- -suit Shaikh Abdulla or convey letter to him. 5, later they interviewed me and con- -firmed2. confirmed above to me. Shaikh isasr handed me , ^ &gt;;&lt;&lt; ^ . , v: ,,„^ ■ r-m jr a letter from Shaikh of Qatar dated June 15th for- -mally informing me that negotiations were at an end and that he withdrew his undertaking given to you. 1 told representatives tlra t they should remain at Bahrain pending instructions from you and that Shaikh Abdullah withdrawing his undertaking could not be accepted until you had considered mat- -ter and communicated with him and that he would be responsible for any breach of undertaking given to you until you had formally released him. 6* (a) a informed Shaikh of Qatar in writing of the tiovernment of .Bahrain's latest offer and the attitude adopted by his representatives. (b) x informed Shaikh of Qatar in reply to hi s letter ^my paragraph 5) in the same terms as already communicated to his representatives. (c) Permitted his representatives to leave with the above mentioned letters. 7. if Shaikh of Qatar refuses to accept this generous offer of the Shaikh of Bahrain and will not accept suggestion contained in my letter mentioned in paragraph 2 above then x am afraid nothing remains but to inform both the Shaikh of Qatar and the J^aim that their undertak ings have been annulled as from a fixed time on a date to be specified by you. 8. shaikh of -Bahrain interviewed me on 2C th June and on 21st June. xie ¥ra.s very anxious and3# and in the event of hostilities breaking out between ^haikh Abdulla and the ivaim there my be a formal claim to Zubara from the Shaikh of Bahrain with the request for our protection of Aa^m as hi fe subjects pending a decision of his claim* .Po li ti cal19/243 Telegram From ■ To No. 159 Dated and IMMEDIATE My telegram of 22nd June No. 138. I have now received reply from Shaikh of Qatar / • , to the Shaikh of Bahrain's proposal that their respective relat ives should meet. Shaikh of Qatar has agreed to proposal and suggested village of Ghariyah as the place of meeting. ■ I have informed Bahrain Government and Adviser informs me that they will send immediately to the Shaikh of Qatar to fix the date of meeting. This is very satisfactory. 2. My messenger, my Head Farrash, informs me that he saw 700 men leave Riyan and that Bedouin were being issued with arms in his presence that the number of Shaikh of Qatar* s followers who have collected is 5000 and they are said to be proceeding towards Zubarah and that pearl, fishers have been recalled from the banks. A general state of war appears to exist. He further reports that Bedouin have been raiding Nairn . recently. 3. Pending instructions from you I do not propose to let Qatar representatives depart. Saleh bin Mana might try to interfere to prevent meeting. \ -Political- 17. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. received 23rd June 1937.' -• ■ - * * . ■19/243 Telegram 17. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No* 615 Dated 23rd June 1937« IMPORTANT I agree with paragraph 3 of your telegram No. 139 of 23rd June and with paragraph 3 of your telegram No. 140 of 23rd June. ^ v ^ Britconsul. &lt;%•19/245 Telegram 17. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 145 My telegram of 2ord June No. 140. SMikii of Bahrain is most anxious to have Belgrave accompany his representatives. 2. I can see no objection provided that he is not present at the meeting$except by personal invitation of the Shaikh of Qatar. -Political- /19/243 Telegram From To No. 624 17. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 25th June 19S7. IMPORTANT BELGRAVE. by you Your telegram No. 145 of 24th June. I agree subject to proviso mentioned Britconsul. cOS19/242 Telegram 17. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 148 Dated and received 25th June 1937. IS . 't Your telegram of 2Srd June No. €15. I have received two letters to your address from Shaikh of Qatar. They will be forwarded by sea mail. He complains of detention of goods in the Bahrain Customs. I have asked representatives for details and will enquire into matter and am informing Shaikh of my action. Shaikh also com plains of doings of Nairn. 2. I have received third letter to my own address asking permission for his representatives to return and in view of this I do not think we can detain them further. 3. The Bahrain representatives leave for Qatar tomorrow. Political© Telegraia From To 19/243 17. Political Agent, Bahrain, political Resident, Bushire. Ho. 152 Dated and received 27th June 1937. IMPORTANT My telegram of June 25th 148 paragraph 2. I have received another letter from Bhaikh of Qatar asking for return of his representatives. i suggest that they may be permitted to go. •Political-19/243 Telegram 17. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Wo. 636 Dated 27 th June 1937. '■Hi \ &lt; gil IMPORTANT Your telegram Ho. 152 of 27th June. I agree. Bri taonsul19/243 Telegraa K. i7 iToia Political Agent, isahraln. To Political Resident, isushire* jNO *154 Bated 28th received 29th ^uiie 1937 • My telegram -wo •152 of 27 th June. 'Ihe Shaikh of the i^alm has written to me complaining of acta of agression against them by the Bhaikh of Qatar. There seems to be some truth in the report and i am making enquiries from a v/ounded man who is said to have arrived here. 2. x am informing the aaim that J. arn communicating with you. ir'oli tical19/24 3, Te3e gram R. 17. From Political Resident, ±susiiiire. ''-'o Political Agent, Bahrain. JSo. 645, 7)ated 29 th June 1937. Your telegram ^lo. 154 of 28th June, if Shaikh of Qatar has actually attacked mini to extent of inflicting casualties this is important as it shows he has broken the truce. jfleas confirm from your enquiries. i3R IT CONSUL.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/464-4/13 7/ I j( r-&gt; f 'Of J I The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Golf. Dated... SiLst*• June* ■ ■ * Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Political Agent, Bahrain 1 s Note dated the 20th June 19371 Letter No.C/462 dated the 20th June 1937 to the Ruler of Qata Zubarah. (Lrl*- /I had an Interview this upraing with His Highness the SiiaiMi of Bahrr-. in, Shaikh Bohamad bin f lsD. s Shaikh • ♦ Abdullah bin *lsa and Shaikh Salaas bin Haaad. Mr. Bel- grave the Mviser was present. After general matters had been discussed the question of aiberaii was raised. I showed Sis Highness a copy of a letter I was sending containing his proposals to Gii-v.iMi Abdullah bin Jassia of Qatar. His Highness raised, the cfuestlon of the possi- biiity of Shaikh Abdullah attacking the lain and I told hia that in agr opinion Shaikh Abdullah would not be so foolish as to break the agreesent wliieh he had giToB to the Honourable the Political Resident. It seemed to m that they placed little hope la Siaish Abdullah bin Jtsslm agreeing to sending his near relatives to aeetist^. ShaUdi Abdullah bin f Isa and ShaiMi Sslman bin fiaaad. They ware very perturbed regarding the course to be pursued in the event of Shaikh Abdullah refusing to continue negotiations^ It seemed to m that Shaikh Ifohewsad bin f Isa was anxious for his brother to sake an appeal for arbitration to 31s Maiestyls floimi'llliilll Bad also to ask for us to interfere hearing on behalf of the Nairn pending the fnoooOnxg. of such an appeal. Shaikh Abdullah bin 'Isa and Shaiid:! Efclsan bin Haa &amp;d rather advocated taking no action but letting the Mais and Shaikh Abdullah bin JassiB settle their differen ces. I think that they were prepared to, and would if '■—-Til.n—- *'■' ' accessary, take vaatevt-r aetioh was possible to assist the Maim from. Bahrain without doing- anything openly. After His Highness considerable discussion 1 tola jom that I would send the let aer containing His Highness' proposed meeting to Shaikh Abdullah bin Jassis and that In the aeantlae they should consider/-2/- .. Copy of letter No. C/462-4/13 dated the 20th June 1357 from Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Poli tical Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh *Abdullah bin Qassim Al Thani, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar. After Compliments: j I have been desired by His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'Isa al Khalifah, the Ruler of Bahrain, to address you with regard to the present negotiations which are taking place between your representatives and the representatives of His Highness. His Highness isj as you know, most anxious that the present unfortu nate difference of opinion with regard to 'Zubarah should be overcome as soon as possible. He has informed me that he believes that if there could be a meeting bet ween his brother Shaikh 'Abdullah bin »Isa and Ijis eldest son Shaikh Salman bin Hamad and two of your near relatives such as your brother or your son, an agree- menfc might be arrived at. He has requested me to put this matter to you and with the approval of the Honour able the Political Resident I am now doing so. His Highness attaches great importance to the place of meet ing and afeile naturally he realises that you would pro bably not agree to your relatives coming to Bahrain, he is not himself agreeable to sending his relatives to Doha, and has, therefore, suggested that he should send his representatives to your Coast and hopes that your representatives would meet them there. The exact point at which the meeting should take place has not been de finitely suggested but possibly Khwair would be a con venient place or if you prefer it, further south towards Zubarah.&amp; g, i should be very grateful if you would consider carefully the suggestion put forward by His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain and trust that you would be able to see your way to deputing two of your relatives to attend the suggested meeting. I think it most essen tial that this unfortunate disagreement should be sett - led as speedily as possible and you naturally would be anxious from your side to do all that you can to bring about a happy solution to the problem. I feel thafc the meeting of this nature between the near relatives of yourself and His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain will probably do more to restoring the good friendship which has always previously existed between you than will be achieved by meetings between persons who are not actual members of your respective families. I shall be grateful if you will inform His Highness directly of your answer to his suggestion or will send me your reply to be conveyed to His Highness. Usual Ending® 0O0CONFIDENTIAL. 5-9 fyKj* i J^bJ rr'' '■« bushire residency. No. C/468-4/13 COi-JFJDENTJH RECORDS r7 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agenot, BAHRAIN, Persian Gdle. Dated,.. 22nd # June 1937 Eeference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. Political Agent, Bahrain* Kote dated the 21st June 1937. Zubarah.SimiMi Kasip bin Itieh .and Saleh bin Ham called to see me. this asornlog To^rcxrig the question of Eubareii. i—i^h bin W-Tk&amp;. recapitul^.ted the course of the negotia tions and eventually stated that tiiey had recdiocl the end of their tether and t'mt they could do no sore and were anxious to return to Qatar* He showed, wb a letter froa ghaiMi &lt;Abdullah bin Qasal* in tfeieh it was stated woBt clearly that Im #89not to give on the cjuesfeloB of the withdrawal of t'&amp;&amp; Bahrain claim. He told m that they were waiting for one aore aeetiag with the Bahrain representnti^es and ^cre anxious to have it as soon as possible. I told hia that I would inform the Bahrain Government of their requireaents end trusted that it would be possible to have the following dc&gt;# ; ikh Hasir inferred ae that he had a letter from ShaiM: # lhdullah which he m s prepared, to deliver to Els High ness the Baler of Bahrain as soon as they had, coae to an agreesent. He said that he thought that Shaikh ■'Ahdxillah had gone a long WK&amp; tovs«r&lt;3s aeeting Bahrain with regard to the cuestion, of the Haim end that it was time that His Bt&amp;BBS&amp;etB the Huler of Bahrain inada an endeavour to met Sha3.ich &lt;Abdull« i h regarding the elalas ■a- ■ barah.. I iapressed upon him th-at in ^ opinion ■ they should do all they could to bring about a solution to the problem before they left* Sd/- T. H. 31-6-3?.CONFIDENTIAL. ^7 Ho, 1 7 /WJ 5 I (* C/470-4/13 ■ .'■■.'Wjat-'.jj!'—'xaaaEiiaaaai;- -r-asgr-- bush!re residency. V1% r. CONFiDENTlAL REC3^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHEAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated . .SScd. June .1957 Keference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. 1. Letter No.549/Sf-9A dated the 20th June 1937 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Gov ernment. 2. Letter No.559/SF-9A dated the 22nd June 1937 from th^ Adviser to the Bahrain Government, 3. Letter Ko.C/469 dated the 22nd June 1937 to Shaikh Nasir bin Atieh, at Bahrain i Subject. ZUBARAH. The Honourable the Political R e sident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Copy of letter No.C/469-4/13 dated the 82nd June 19S7 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh Hasir bin ^Atiyah, at Bahrain Copy of this letter given to Saleh bin Mana. After Compliments: With reference to your meeting with me this morning and the letter handed to me by you from Shaikh Abdullah bin Jassim, Ruler of Qatar. I am conrnunica- ting with the Honourable the Political Resident and pending instructions from him you and Salih bin Mani* should remain in Bahrain. With regard to Shaikh Abdullah bin Jassim's statement that he withdraws from his undertaking given to the Honourable the Poli tical Resident not to interfere with or tike action against the Maim during the negotiations, I inform you that his withdrawal cannot be accepted until the Honourable the Political Resident has had time to consider the matter and Shaikh Abdullah bin Jassim will be responsible for any breach of his undertaking until he has been formally released by the Honourable the Political Resident. I am communicating with the Honourable the Political Resident by telegram imme diately and will coimmnicate with you on Receiving a reply. L j Usual Ending.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/478-4/13 (fl^ ' &gt;6 J &gt;0 i'^T- ?iTlAl RECORDS iiw iiOni' The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to; The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. / 0? W ML m 1 I m M and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHEAIN, Persian Gulp. Dated.. . JJWm. .1.9 S 7. Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. 1. Letter dated the 9th June 19S7 from the Ruler of Qati 2. -do- -do- dated 14th June 3« -do- -do- dated 21st June 4. Letter No*0/469 dated 22nd June 1937 to Shaikh Nasir bin Atiyah, at Bahrain, 5. Letter dated the 22nd June 1937 from the representatives of the Ruler of Qatar. 6. Letter No.C/473 dated 23rd June 1937 to Adviser to the Bahrain Government. 7. Political Agent's note date 23rd June 1937. d Subject. Z U B A R A H. 8. -do- note dated the 25th June 1937.dS?' l l| Translation of letter dated g9th Rabi Awwal 1556(9.6.^7) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qassim al Thani, C .l.E., Ruler of Qatar, to Captain T. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. ' I After compliments; I* have the honour to bring to your kind notice the question of Zubarah. I have repeatedly pointed out to you ny disapproval of the encroachment done to us by the Bahrain people by their imaginary claim which has neither set upon a foundation nor is according to any rule of intellect and logic. This is the claim which they created about Zubarah which is my land and one of the Qatar Coasts. You asked me when you visited Dohah to send two representatives in order to negotiate and investigate the case of Zubarah with the representatives of His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain. I was quite cer tain that there was no necessity for negotiation in a clear matter but I could not disagree with your wishes. And in accordance with your desire, I sent my two rep resentatives to Bahrain for negotiation under your super- vision. My representatives produced ititidctmck evident proof that Zubarah is an inseparable part of Qatar territory. In conclusion proposals were put forward by the representatives of His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain to which form I could not agree as I considered it the very claim created by them, but being anxious to preserve the friendship existing between me and His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain and in order to stren gthen the neighbourly relations I inserted certain modi fications and submitted them as explained to you in the modifications. I pointed out to you and I also wrote to the Honourable the Political Resident that that was the extreme limit possible for the agreement but/-but I leaarnt that the Bpresentatives of His Highness are adhering to their own views and still want to en croach upon my right, attempting to cut a part from my land and a coast from w coasts. I am certain that my proof is clear even to the High British Government because demarcation took place long ago and this fact is known to the High British Government since the time of their treaty with the Bahrain people and the grant of protection to them over their frontiers. There is no doubt they know that Zubarah has no connection with that® The High British Government also granted us pro tection, over land and sea of the whole Qatar without exception and recognised the independence of all Qatar territory under my Ruling Flag. Is it possible that the High British Government had any doubt about Zubarah • - • ■ when they granted me protection and did not make it iit%Mr'i»iifiifaitciWBifrfKMfeWfe'gCii^ ''*** ' ' ^ - . ?■. ■■■■ ■■ ■'.•••V.VAO--?; clear to me or drew ny attention to it. And lately negotiations took place between me and the Anglo-Iranian •' ■ . - i -Ar— - • W&gt; • Oil Con^ny Limited for a survey of the whole Qatar terri brrv&amp;eH, H. rntilltrT|'ti'»r|5'^|[ I —|—- ■ |( I ) ^ iijTiiif3jiTiir&lt;i TW.JI wriiirTnirmrgTTr tory, its lands, boundaries and coasts and for the explo- ration of oil there. An agreement was concluded with the uuantui wtilN**'''' 1 ri'WW - Oil Company in this connection with the assent of the High British Government. The survey in question was carried out by the said Oil Conpany on all Qatar lands. Zubarah etcetera and a map was drawn covering all these '' '' w '^ L ' ja ^* a ** 1 * i 'fili'irii'Wiai &lt; ii I r ' &amp;gVpigBtig»0*li ■•-r/-- ,'n&gt; ' VV • ' . «a68p!&gt;i : «^*''' s ^'' ?r ■'W*'!fl'i''inM'NIlN,!^ -jKni.ijumniitiu.mntc rmrriwirr areas of Qatar territory including Zubarah. This was '' ' • ■--Si. - going on for some years during which period the negotia tions with the Company were concluded with regard to oil development in all the places in Qatar as shown on the map. As I saw that that was in accordance with the views of the British Government and was accorded with their approval, I agreed to the terras of the Company and signed the/- My-5- the concession accordingly for the said CorDpany as laid down in the agreement concluded between us. All these / « mi ■HTinrii were carried out under the supervision and the considera- ' nm mrrr- 1 ' ' _,. L . m) — tion of the Representative of the British Government in \ the Persian Gulf. This came into effect after it had n hi iimiii i r 'rriiiif'^^' 1 •• • been countersigned by the Representative of the High British Government which was concluded covering the whole Shaikhdom of Qatar including Zubarah in accordance with the plan attached to the agreement. The Representative of the High British Government made the countersignature on all that without any hesitation. It is very surprising that such a claim should now be created by His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain about Zubarah after treaties were made between ms and His Majesty's Government and conclusion of negotiations and the granting of concessions over all Qatar, Zubarah etcetera without exception. If the Bahrain people had the least claim or a slightest doubt, they would not have kept quiet all this time. I, therefore, decided that according to proofs put forward about which you are aware, that you would see that this their claim is useless and they have no least connection with what they claim nor there is any truth in their claim. I hope, that while administering justice in the case, you will kindly consider a way for settling this matter and putting a stop to this dispute as the claim of the Bahrain people to my limits is a mere step of encroachment and aggression. I am certain * that you do not agree that my rights should be affected and that you are Inclined to follow the right wajr and give the right to their owners. I also beg to invite your atten tion to the friendly relations and treaties existing between me and the High British Government which are known to you. I am the same friend who still adopts the lines which meet with the satisfaction and approval of the British Government «ao Usual Ending.Translation of letter dated the 5th RaM al Thani 1356 (=14th June 19S7) from Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Qassim al Thani, C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A* C a I beg to state to you with regard to the question , ... of Rashid bin Muhannnad and his followers. You are aware that they are w subjects and under me formerly and newly and they are from Qatar tribes; there are clear proofs in t this connection. I have explained clearly about this and waited all this time with a hope that their return may be obtained in a satisfactory way, that they should submit ✓ to me and return as they were, obey my orders and avoid useless things which do not conern them in a peaceful way for the sake of their safety and peace for all. Rut I do &gt;*- *-•' — , not see but my toleration would increase their arrogance — — -isr and declaration of hostility against me. Why they should show hostility to me and spoil my subjects when they are - I my subjects. Now the case had reached to a stage where no toleration could be expected. I am better aware of my subjects and of wcountry. If they submit to peace between - ■ me and them then I wish them safety and if they refuse to anything but dsstest and corrupt ion and continue making dis turbances as they do now I shall be conroelled to make them return to my submission and obedience by any means by the strength of God. But the people of Bahrain always send them helps in any way even arms which they collect from everywhere inside and outside and send to Nairn. And to any foreign subject they come across they give him money and / send him secretly. I have heard that they sent certain subjects of Bahrain etc. to Nairn to instigate subjects to raise against me and to fight with me. I therefore make/--2 make it clear to you that I would not be responsible for anything which may occur to the subjects of Bahrain who went and joined the Nairn in order to fight with w sub jects in w country. And I request you to issue orders to Bahrain subjects who joined the Nairn to disperse and return to Bahrain and leave the Maim alone as they have no connection with w subjects. AM when you receive ! this letter then the armistice concerning Nairn is termina ted and I have ordered my representatives jdogc that when i they receive this letter and cannot arrive at an agreement with His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain to w last pro posals to return to me as soon as possible as the negotia tion has taken a long tim e without any result. U.E.f»tion of letter dated the ISth Rabi Thani 1556 (=21 st June 1937) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Oassim a! Tbani, Ruler of Qatar, to the Political Agent, Bahrain® After ^conplimentSe , uV At a best hour I had the pleasure of receiving your esteemed letter dated the 11th ®abi Thani 1556 eauivalent to the 20th June 1957 and noted what was it- - ' mentioned you especially that His Highness Shaikh Hamad bin ®Isa al Khalifah^ Ruler of Bahrain, has re— a uested you to address me about the present negotiations between His Highness 9 and ray representatives. That His Highness is anxious that the present difference over Zubarah should be overcome as speedily as possible. That His Highness has informed you that he believes if there had been a meeting between his brother Shax^ih * Abdullah bin 'Isa and his elder son Shaikh Salman bin Hamad and two of my near relatives such as ngr son and brother, an agreement might be arrived at. That he has requested you to submit this matter to me and that he does not agree to the coming of his relatives to Doha as I also do not agree that my relatives should come to Bahrain. That he has suggested to send his relatives to ray coast to meet my relatives there. That the suggested place for holding the meeting may be Khuwair or Zubarah. These two places are not suitable for the meeting at present. If His Highness Shaikh Hamad bin 9 Isa, Ruler of Bahrain, likes to send his relatives referred to above for discussion over the question of Eubarah with ny relatives, we, in order to restore the friendship and to preserve the old amity and 'bon voisinage'&gt; agree to this if he agrees. The place for the meeting should/-should be Ghariyah village or near it on its southern coast as this place, owing to the present circumstances, is nearer and 'better for holding a meeting than those places. If His Highness desires that a meeting should take place between the relatives, please let me know soon via Ghariyah. The meeting should be held as soon as possible. Usual Ending.No. C/469-4/13 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd June 1937. SBo Shaikli Nasir bin ♦Atiyah, at Bahrain. After Corapliinents. With reference to your meeting with me this morning and the letter handed to me by you from Shaikh Abdullah bin Jassim, Ruler of Qatar. I am comnpnicating with the Honourable the Political Resident and pending instructions from him you and Sslih bin Mani* should remain in Bahrain, With regard to Shaikh Abdullah » i bein Jassira*s statement that he withdraws from his undertaking given to the Honourable the Political Re- t sident not to interfere with or take action against the Nairn during the negotiations, T inform you that his withdrawal cannot be accepted until the Honourable the Political Resident has had time to consider the M watter and Shaikh Abdullah bin Jassim will be responsi' ble for any breach of his undertaking until he has v.; v . ^ - V, Pt ■ , been formally released by the Honourable the Poli tical Resident. I am commanicating with the Honour able the Political Resident by telegram immediately and will commnicate with you on receiving a reply. Usual Ending. Sd/-T. Hickinbotham, Captain Political Agentj Bahrain. Copy to: Salih bin Manlt, ■ ^ i at Bahrain.Translation of letter dated 13th Rabl al Thani 1556 (= 22nd June 1957) from Shaikh Nasir bin Atayleh and Salih bin Mani», Representatives of the Ruler of Qatar, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Corapliments;- * Jr We have .the honour to acknowledge the receipt of y your letter dated 2Snd June 1937 corresponding to 13th Rabi al Thani 1356 and noted what was mentioned by you. We have already informed you in our meet ing with you that we have been ordered by His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah to leave as soon as we deliver the letter to you because our negotiations terminated, but you prevented us from doing so. As regards your intimation about (matters) which concern him and we are not supposed to be bound by any such matters as we are not interested in them. This is a thing wMefe between you and him and he must have mentioned it to you in his letter. Usual Ending. oOoCopy of letter No. C/473-4/13 dated the 23rd June 1937 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. ■tf I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 520/SF-9A dated the 12th June 1337, paragraph 2. 2. I informed Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Qassim Al Thani, . tr . . ~ ■ a ''*■ C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, of His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain®s proposal with regard to a meeting between His Highness* relatives and the relatives of the Ruler of Qatar. Yesterday afternoon June the 22nd, I received „ a reply from the Ruler of Qatar. He states that he was pleased to receive ay letter conveying His Highness* suggestion and that he was willing for a meeting to take place as has been suggested. He stated that he was not agreeable to the meeting taktisg place being at Zubarah or Khwair but he suggested that the parties should meet at the village of Ghariyah or some other spot further • ■ ■ ■ tV' ITT Km Ml^llnlil'l^mUflllfrt't'r • ¥; '' — ^ ^ south. He is particularly anxious that this meeting [ nitf a, should take place with the least possible delay and has requested that he may be informed whether His Highness agrees as soon as possible. He has further requested t that this information be conveyed to him via Ghariyah. I should be grateful if you will let me know #or the information of the Honourable the Political Resident what His Highness intends to do with regard to this matter.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/484-4/13 n .. i PfTQI L z'/lQfM . t Si'd nn^MTI AI 'V'^J iiLrCili 1 SHi RFPnrr^ r |r^ I The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to; The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHEAIN, P ersian G olf. L Dated .... S6th. June- • -IQS?-. • Reference to previous correspondence : J Description o Name and Date. 1. Letter dated 13th Rabi Than 1356(=SSnd June 1937) from the Ruler of Qatar to the Hon'ble the Political Re sident, in original* 2. Letter dated 15th Rabi Tharii 1356(=24th June 1937) fromj the Ruler of Qatar to the Hon^ble the political Re sident, in original, 3* Letter dated 24th June 1937 from the Ruler of Qatar to the Political Agent, Bahrain 4. Letter No.C/275 dated 25th June 1937 to the Ruler of Qatar. 5. Demi-official letter No.56e|/ SF dated the 26th June 1937 from the Adviser. Subject. Z U B A R A H.Translation of letter dated tne 13tn Rabi Ttiani 1356 (22*6-37) irom Snaikh 'Abdullan bin ^asini al Txiani, C .i .E., Ruler ol Qatar, to tne Honourable Lieut-Golonel Sir Trencnard Powle, K.C.I.S., lolitical Resicient in tne Persian Gruli, Busnire. After Compliments. At a best time I received jour letter dated tne 9tn Rabi Thani 13bb equivalent to 18tn June 1^3? and noted what you nave mentioned. Your Honour particularly reierred 0 to your letter No.451 dated 10tn June 1^37 equivalent to 1st Eabi Tnani 13b6 whicn is a reply to my letter dated 13tn Rabi Awwal 1356 equivalent to 24tn May 19bV. Yes, tne lettei in question was received by me and altnougn 1 learnt from it tnat you nave already wrote to tne Naim ordering tnem to disperse and not to inter!ere witn any ol my subjects, tney are increasing m arrogance and in snowing Hostilities to me. r ihey inter!ere witn all my suojects and as an instance | of this tney sent some armed men of tnemselves who raided on ^ tne water well called 'Al Th.agiIb ,, and occupied tne palace I there, in is water well is used by my subjects and the people [j of Knuwair village. There are also date-palms belonging to my subjects Al Dusoom. They took away tneir fruit and cut down some of tnem. They take away all camels and cattle ^ Ill HBIIII linn ' ol ray subjects which they come across. They slaughter and eat some and retain the rest which tney treat as a booty. There was no step ol inteference, aggression and corruption whicn they did not take. How can I bear this corruption ol' tneirs whereas they are my subjects and within my territory ? When 1 saw tnat they were doing more mischief and corruption, I wrote to the Political Agent, Bahrain and intormed him that 1 terminate tne truce with Rashid bin - - . , ... xJuhanimad al Jabur and his followers and that nobody is to intertere in my subjects and in ray territory. Tuat I can cieal witn thera and cannot leave thera on tneir persistence ■ m showing hostilities and corruption to me. I had already4 2. tolerated raucii. Being anxious for their safety and for tne comfort of all, I tolerated for about 3 montns hoping that they would submit to me in an amicable way, but this my toleration did not do anything but made them show more arrogance and hostility and spread a spirit of corruption ♦ amongst all my subjects. I, therefore, terminated the truce with Rashid bin Muhammad and his followers. Your Honour also stated that you have heard from the Political Agent, Bahrain, that the negotiations are still going on. It may not be mdden from Your Honour that these negotiations took a long time and the representatives of His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain are insisting in their hostile claims against me, my town and my boundary. Ly representatives are staying in Bahrain in the hope that His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain may agree to my proposals but it is regretted that they contempted my representatives, closed down the guest house which you ordered tor them and turned them out ol it in an indecent way. They *** wrJ ^' '* .•!•&lt;?4. v-.r.: ^, /V- , | i ;n wrote a letter to my represetatives which indicates that they are terminating the negotiations on their side, a copy of which is enclosed for your perusal. Later my representatives remain ed for some days during which period they subject to cruelty and contempt. No result has^ been achieved out of these lengthy negotiations. Your Honour also said that I must have received, long prior to tnis date, the proposals ol His High ness the Ruler of Bahrain to the elfect that one of his relatives may meet with two of my relatives in connection with these matters. Yes, on 20th June 193? equivalent to 11th Rabi Thani 1356 I received a letter irom the Political Agent, Bahrain on this subject. It reached me one night before this your letter. Your Honour said that you presume tnat it reached me long before the receipt ol this your letter, but there was n o space ol time between that letter and your letter save that ■•^ich I mentioned above, i sent him a reply saying that if Highness the Ruler of Bahrain, as he(Political Agentjsaid, he 0 ^ce^mg ou uw htid between his brotner Shailch ^bdulla hll o i.i.X obin 1 1sa and his elder son Shaikh Salman bin iiamad and two ol my near relatives, I, in order to restore the friendly relations witn His Highness and to preserve tne ola amity and good neighbourly relations, agree to tnis, and hope that a happy discussion may taJce place in sucn a meeting which settles tnis Ig dispute. I, however, inlormed him that this meeting should be held as soon as possible and the speediest means may be made for hoi dins: it. ! Usual Ending. mtranslaTIJ:.. To, Nasir bin Abdallan bin ^tiyaii and Saliii al* Culaiman at I&amp;ini ? , representatives of tne Ruler of Qatar. After Compliments. .'ie understand from you tiiat you are not m a position to agree to tne modifications which we sent you with our previous letter dated 24tn Habi ^wwal 13b6(4th June 193?}. tie ,therefore, inform you that we cannot agree at all to the withdrawal of our claim to Zubarah and Nairn tribe. T&gt; jk. lease acknowledge the receipt of this letter m writing. Usual Ending. Si Id. Abdullah bin ? Isa ' Salman bin Hamad. Representatives of His Highness the Ruler 01 Bahrain.uujllu ux ciuxf jjicuu-uuxuxicx O-J-X xxcxx^xxaxu ru^± K.C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Resident in tne Persian Gull. After Compliments. ^ I have sent you a letter on 13tn Eabi Tnam 13b5 in reply to your esteemed letter dated 18tn June 193V ^^eq_uivalent to 9tn Eabi Thani 1356. I hope that it has reached you and that you are in full happiness and comfort. I beg to inform lour Honour that it has been ascertained by me thai a few days ago goods and merchandize were prevented from being shipped to Qatar from -Hahram. Even that some goods belonging to my subjects were presented at the Customs Pier at Bahrain for shipment from there, but were prevented. i am much surprised at sucn an act. What is the reasons lor it ? Is action ot this sort permissible? I am also surprised to notice the acts which are being done in Bahrain now-a-days ♦ ; • v/hich I consider to be contrary to the laws and rules. I see that supplies are sent from Bahrain to the rioters and • i. insurgents of my subjects, such as goods, arms and ammunition. These are all hostile deeds which the circumstances do not permit. I draw your kind attention to this fact because you are from those noble and brave men who do not agree to act except in accordance with justice and equity. Usual Ending.• - . ' ■ «. - ■ - ■ ■ &gt; - - , - f - ' ' -Translation of letter dated 15th RaM Than! 1356 (24-6-1937) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Than!, C.I.E-, Ruler of Qatar, to Captain T. Hickinibo than. Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments: I beg to state that it has been ascertained by me that some five days ago (orders) were issued to the effect that goods and merchandise should not be shipped to Qatar from Bahrain. Although some goods belonging to my sub- a jfllfl ii ii ' ' '' jects arrived at the Bahrain Pier for shipment, they were detained. I am quite surprised at such an act. What is the reason for it and on what grounds they have been de tained? Is it admissible to tike such an act? I am also surprised to notice these actions going on these days in Bahrain which are against the laws add rules. I ob- t| serve supplies being sent from Bahrain to the rioters and insurgents of my subjects such as goods,., arms, men and ammunition. These are all hostile deeds which the cir cumstances do not allow. It has also been ascertained ( by me that nay representatives Salih bin Mani* and Nasir bin Abdullah bin Atiyah were prevented from leaving to my side after they had terminated the negotiations which took a long time without any result or avail. I did not understand for what reason they were prevented from lea ving. I therefore request you not to keep my above-men- tioned representatives at Bahrain and that, on the re ceipt of ray letter, you will permit them to come as their prevention is considered as an insult to them without any reason. I am to draw your kind attention to consider these inconsistent acts as I believe you are from those brave and noble persons who prefer to follow the right and equitable way and to see to nothing but .lustice. Usual Ending-Copy of letter No, C/S75 dated the 25th June 1037 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to ithe Ruler of Qatar, After Compliments: I have received your letter dated the 15th Ratal Thani 1356 equivalent to 24th June 1937. I asked your representatives sho interviewed me this morning to inform me of the particulars of the goods which have taeen detained in the Bahrain Customs and I will immediately enquire into the matter. Usual Ending.Copy of demi-offieial letter Ko. D.0.568/SF dated th 26th June 1937 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Govern ment to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have enquired about the matter of the house occupied by the Qatar representatives. The arrange ments for their entertainment were in the hands of His Highness® steward, Abdullah bin Jabr. He informs me that . the servants provided by us were left in the house after t Nasr returned but on the Friday in question they locked the front door and left the back door open. Nasr return ed with noney intending to tip the servants but found ■ ' • c the door looked and went straight to his launch where he remained. Abdullah bin Jabr assumed that negotiations had ceased and that Nasr was no longer an official guest5 the house was then locked up. Ho mention was made of the matter to the Bahrain representatives by Nasr, had he let Miem know they would of course have seen that the former arrangements were continued. It is nost unfortunate that this misunderstanding should have occurred. His Highness of course knew no thing whatever about it and would I know be most dis tressed at any reflection on his toospltalitv.19/245 Telegram R.17. STom political Agent, Bahrain, rp 0 political Resident, Busnire. Uo. 156. Dated and received tne oOtn June 1937, I1CPOHTAFC , A' Your telegram of 29tn June wo,64b, 2. I will reply later to your telegram under reference 3, I am concerned about tHe situation at uHAHxfAH, I have h a^ no news since June 26th, I am sending my launcn as it is the most sea\\fortny at once vvitn .'/ater etc. ihe Snaiicn nas asked if a sloop could vaid and I shall be grateful if this could be arranged as tnere nas been a very neavy animal this last six days and I expect tnat tney are unable to return owing to tne weatner. -Political.n n, // r w h b 19/245 Telegram From To No. 158 17. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated and received 30th June 19o7. IMPORTANT r I i l i . / . 4 ■ ^ .' My telegram of June 50th No. 156 paragraph 2. 2. Wounded man states that he was travelling from Althaghb to Akhday four miles north of ? Shieiha on the coast to fetch his family when he was ordered to surrender his arms by three unknown cavalrymen of Shaikh of Qatar. He refused and was shot in the shoulder. He is a Nairn and was in my opinion outside Zubarah area. t 5. I have no doubts that Shaikh of Qatar is nmiiiim»ii»nni|iiiii Hli'mwii—illtn &gt; ' harassing Nairn as Eiuch as possible and I consider his action in permitting his Bedouin to interfere with the Naim will amount to a breach of his undertaking not to interfere with them. It would be very difficult to prove any indiv idual case. Political.19/243 Te le gram itoin To lo. 162 17. Po 11 ti cal Agent, Baiirai n. political Hesident, Jsushire. Dated and received 1st July 1937. IMMEDIATS My telegram of 1st July Wo. 160. 2. Adviser has informed me that the negotiations failed and that there is a state of war prevailing with loot ing of villages containing saim and their adherents taking i place. Shaikh of Sjatar's forces were 15 miles southwest of Ghariyah on June 30th. to 3. Shaikh of Bahrain requests that ahaikh of C^atar may be restrained from making war on Bahrain subjects who reside in the Zubarah area which he claims to be his territory. He further reports s^zure by order of Shaikh of Qatar of Bahrain dhow visiting Doha for commercial purposes &lt; and requests that Shaikh of Q,atar may be prevented from % siezing such vessels. 4. I have now received July 1st a letter from Shaikh of Q^tar again withdrawing his undertaking in no uncertain terms as the negotiations are terminated and he proposes to take what steps he considers necessary to deal t with his recalcitrant subjects. Me ends by saying that he will not be responsible for anything that may now happen. 5. 1 request that imperial Airways and Royal Air l^orce may be warned not to fly low over i^atar. political.I 19/243 Te le gxara 17 From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, iiushire iMO. 245 Bated and received 1st July 1937 IMMEDIATE jmrther to my telegram of July 1st. ZUBARAH. Although I realise that it is not the policy of His Majesty's Government to interfere in the internal affairs of the Shaikh of -Qatar x feel that it would not be wrong, in view of the special circumstances in this case and the necessity for a settled country for oil development, if an endeavour were made to mediate between Shaikh of Qatar and the Haim with a view to prevent bloodshed and a possible major disturbance in Qp.tar. I therefore suggest that i ambsent to Qjatar with in- _ structions to endeavour to bring about an understanding between Shaikh of Q^tar and the jwaim. political.3 19/245 G.T.C. Political Resident, Eushire. Air Officer Commanding, Britisfi Forces in f Iraq, Einaidi. Officer Commanding, No.203(FB) Squadron Basra. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 1st July, 1957. IMPORTANT. I Political Agent reports that there are disturbances in Qatar between Sheikh and Nairn tribe. Imperifcl Airways and the Royal Air Force should not fly low over Qatar Political Agent, Bahrain should warn local Imperial Airways Agents at Bahrain and Sharjah. Telegram From To Repeated Britconsul. \If 19/245, I political Hesident, Eusnire. Secretary of State lor India, London. (iovernment of India, External Aft air a Department , Simla, rolitical Agent, Bahrain, Air Officer Commanaing, Br it is n forces in Iraq, riinaia i. Senior jtfaval Officer, Persian Gulf. Dated the 2nd July 1937„ IMPORTANT T. My telegram ^o,616 of 23rd June U^t repeatea to Air Officer Commanding and Senior uaval Officer), 2UBAEAH, Political Agent reports tnat negotiations between Bahrai n and C^atar nave finally Droicen down and tnat nostilities nave brolcen out between snaiicn of ^atar and tne iNiaim tribe, 2, Political Agent and 1 nave been at considerable pains to induce Banrain and (^atar to negotiate, to keep tnese negotiations going for nearly two montns, and to arrange a truce meanwhile between tne Snaikn of ^atar and tne Maim whicn i Shalkn of qatar nas now denounced as ne states tnat JMaim nave not kept tne peace, 3, In these circumstances tnere is no course now open to us except to let nostilities take tneir course vide paragrapn ^3 of my telegram No,T/71 of 26tn April, ^ () Q h * I 3 a . 3 9 4, uil Company (see paragrapn 3 of my telegram JUo, T/86 of 3rd May) will not resume operati ons until tne Autumn and before that dispute between Shaikn of qatar and tne Maim snould / Td egram From To Repeated Uo, 662oftp HI — -2- ■ . snould mve been settled# 5, Our present concern is witn safety of Britisn Indian subjects at Dona (tnere are none at Zubaran). I tmnk it unlikely tnat tnese will be in any danger but Political Agent Bahrain snould as soon as possible address letter to Snaikn of qatar reminding nim tnat ne is responsible ior tne safety of British subjects and tneir property in nis territory, political Agent Balirain snould also address a letter to tne Nairn warning tnem that they will be neid responsible for any injury to tne persons or property of British Indian subjects caused by tnsa» 6, I would be grateful if benior j&gt;4aTal Officer could send a sloop to Dona to remain tnere for tne present witn tne object of (a) ensuring safety of Britisn Indian subjects and (b) keeping Political Agent Banrain ana myself informed Oy wireless of developments. Ho intervention except for purpose of (a) is called for# -Britc onsul.19/243 Tele gram From Political Resident, J3ushire To political Agent, Bahrain Repeated to Secretary of State for india, London Government of mdia, Simla. Senior iMaval officer, Persian Gulf. Ho. 663 Dated 2nd July 1937. N I ZIJBARAH It is possible that there may be some demonstrations in Bahrain in favour of the mim especially if latter are worsted by the Shaikh of Qatar. 2. Please therefore address a letter to the Bahrain Government reminding them that in this event they are responsible for protecting the lives and property of British and foreign subjects and should take adequate measures to thi s e nd. Britconsul19/243 if (3 Te le gram From To 1TO. 6 65 Political Hesident, j^ushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 2nd July 1937 I My tele'grain m.663 of 2nd July. please see correspondence mentioned in my telegram Mo. 443 of 4th June 1936 and prior's demi-official letter So *0/111 of 3rd July 1932 and consult with ±selgrave regarding measures to 'be taken by Bahrain Government for safety of individuals concerned. Britconsul.19/243 7^ Telegram inter. ■prom political Agent, Bahrain. 5-0 political Resident, ±5usMre. Repeated to Senior mval officer, Persian Gulf Division. -■ A fl NO • lo w f-t) Dated and received 2nd July 1937. BMBDIATB My telegram Ho. 164 of 1st jruly not repeated to Senior mval Officer. 2, Adviser has just received reliable inform ation that Shaikh of Qatar attacked Zubarah area early morning 1st July and fighting still proceeding. 3, About 100 laim and adherents reported killed including number of personal followers of Shaikh of Bahrain who normally live in Zubarah. I 4, tiefugees are reported to be landing on coast of Bahrain. \ ' 5, (considerable excitement here and I am expecting Shaikh to visit me at any moment. 6, i have asked Adviser to send out police patrol to look after any refugees landing. 7, I have requested M.S. Deptford to remain pending instructions instead of proceeding to nuwait as per scheduled l consider presence of sloop here most desirable 8, i am making medical arrangements for any wounded who may arrive. political.% 19/243 TeL egrajm R. 17 To ora Political Agent, Balirain. Political Resident, Busnire Ho 0 167. :Dated and received tne 2nd July 1937 BCPSDIATh] My telegram, of 2nd July H o »16d. * 3haiicn nas called. He was ill ana very upset, tie complained tnat SJiaikh of Q.atar nad toy nis attach on i!iaim jaroken his agreement with His IViCi, J esty's (iovernraent and tnat Nairn by keeping tneir promise naa been placed at a disadvantage He expressed fear for tne safety of isolated villages ot tne Bahrain coast. 2. Bahrain Government asked if tnere was any objection to withdrawal of tneir pearling boats fisning near qatar to prevent incidents and I said tnat tnere was no objection. 5, 1 have endeavoured to reassure snaikn and promised to let nim Have news as soon as I nave it myself. 4. I shall be glad if a flignt of Royal Air i'orce machines could be sent nere. Tneir presence will nave a reassuring effect even if tnere is no otner work for tnem. t». Paragrapn ;No.3 of telegram under reference* number of killed is probably exaggerated. - Political.19/245 Telegram Inter, From Political Resident, Busnire. ?o yenior aval Officer, Persian uulf. Repeated Political Ageit, Bahrain, No, 670, . Dated the 2nd July 1937, Important , Paragraph 7 of Bahr a in telegram .No, 165 of 2nd J uly. i. concur tnat presence of sloop at Bahrain i most desirable and would be grateful if you could arran accordingly, - Br i tconsul.19/243 Tel eg ram 3.17 • From political Resident, Busnire. To Political ,4gent, Banrain. i&gt;iO, 571, Dated the 2nd July 1937. Important * Your tel eg ran JMo e 167 of 2nd July. Your paragrapn 1, I imagine it is six of one and naif a dozen of tne otner vide complaint of Saim aggression contained in Snaiicn of Qatar's letter of 22nd June enclosure t&gt;ne to your Printed letter of 26tn June. 2. iour paragrapn 2. It is for tne Bahrai n Govern ment to decide but presence of large number of out of work and probably discontented pearlers in Banrai n will doubtless add to difficulties of Banrain Government in keeping order, Snould latar boats attack Bahrain boats at sea tnis would be a breacn of tne Maritime Peace of 1803 (Aitcnison page 252) adnered to by ^atar by Article 1 of Treaty of 1916 (Aitchison page 2b8). Por Banrain see Article 2 of Treaty of 1861 (Aitcnison page 234), 3. iour paragrapn 4. unless you can give me definite objects for Royal Air Force to carry out, wnicn I can pass on to Air Officer Commanding, I do not tnink tnere would, be mucn object in asking lor tnem. -Brit cons ul. /70r ' \ '■ i | (Original on Bundle «3, File xMo.,323-1-Vol. 14 - 'Balirain gr Affairs - October 1374 to llaron 1370'. i ( \ ' gsRsaB j\ L/ copy * So. 564 of 1874. To - Shaiicn ®Bau ben All, Oiiief of Bahrain# Bated 2nd ^elkaaaa 1291 . 12th jeceraber 1874. A/0* xon till recollect that when I had the pleasure of an interview with you on otn flovember 1874 at Bahrain you spoke on 24th H&amp;mazan 1291 tiie 8 udJ set of Zobar ah and your wish to assist in defending it. On timt occasion 1 informed you that though I would not interfere with the despatch of reinl orcssients n purely for aefence that it was a matxer for .your own consideration as to tiie expediency of the measure as affecting your interests and tnat the Brit isn Government could not undertajce responsibility for results if you interfered on tn?i saainland and got mixed up in complications tnere, I took tne opportunity to repeat to your the advice you have bo often received iroia tne British Hesident to Keep clear of the feuds on the mainland and especially to avoid giving offence to the Turkish Government. Having reported the nature of this conversation to the Sovernment oi India, I am instructed by Grovernment tnat if vou any should take^part m complications on tne mainland tne British Government will not guarantee you protection. As tnis is a matter of importance, I have deemed it in accordance witn friendsnip to inform you at once of tne decision of Government and therefore have deputed Captain Eraser to proceed in a (Government vessel on a visit to you, with this letter, in order tiaat you may fully understand the decision of Government,, i * trust you are well and that you will inform me of your welfare in all respects and of all occurrences wnenever opportunities offer. sd. S.C.Ross. Xi t # 0 ol on 6 X • H.B.M. 's Political Hesident in the | | Persian Gulf. *'■ 0 Awarded to the RecrRi'STv ^ . Y jowign Department un-lSr u f° TerntI,ent of India, dated tne 19tn December 187^ Kesideof. letter Ho. 1487 * 301t „ : v {Origi n£i l on bundle Fi3.e XJo«323-I-Yol # 14 - 'Ba-tirai n Affairs - October 1374 to March 1875'}. Tranalat ion , Gopy* 4 jiHin I' i m prom - Sbaikh T3asu bin 1 All, Chi ef of Banra in • fo - Lieut.-Golonel S .G.Ross, British Resident, 7th AMI ^'da 17tn December 1874, rece ivea 19,12,1874, A/C. I have had the honour of receiving your letter of the 12th December forwarded by Lieut^Fraser and I understand its contents especially with reference to my wish expressed to you while you //ere in Banrain on tne 24th Ramazan, regard! ng tne relief of ^obaran 3 for it belongs to us and is one of our dependencies. You int imated there would be no object i on provided I did. not go bsyono. that and this course I trnTe pursued. After considering tne consequ ences I saw no narra in such course for ray object is to aefsnd and protect our islands and not to encroach on foreign possessions. This policy I will always pursue and will myself abstain and prevent ray dependents from interfering in wnat has no advantage for ue or tends to offend tne Turkish Grovernment whom I wish to propitiate in all ways. regards tne G-oTernor ^aneral's orders I am ready to obey tne British GoTernment, hoping for favour and indulgence from tne same for we are connected with and dependent on it. At all events I beg you will forward tne contents of tnis to His ixcellency and express our great obligations to nim. will ever iceep faithfully to our word and we trust to obtain protect ion. Copy forwarded to Secretary to Governnent of India, Foreign Department, under Political Resident's letter Ho,1433 dated the 19th December 1874, 306'(r&gt;y iainal on Bundle 'ftZ, file ^0.323-1-Vol. 14 - ' ^ a lira in &amp; f a irs —Oc to tier 1374 to Marcn. 16. 7 COPSL- J I ' /' '? Mo» 60 of 1875. To The Chief of Bahrain. Dated lotn iionurram 1292 . 22na February 1675. A/0, I nave requested ray frieiid Captain ITraser Assistant Resident to proceed on a visit to yop in H. M.S. 'Brit on' 4 and to deliver tJals letter to you,^ ^ ^ i J t | ^jj T ri jr^i letter Mo.564 dated Sncs. iiilk'aadan. I&lt;i91 (12th December 1874) I communicated to you tne wis nee of tne British ■ ■■ ■ ' .. . - t Government of India on tne sabj ect of your connection with the mainland, and intimated tnat if you take part in complications on tne mainland Government would not guarantee you protection. In your letter dated 7tn silkaadah 1291 (17tn. December 1874} you explained your reasons for helping tne people of Zobaran, and intimated your readiness to be guided by policy of tne Brit ish (xovernment. Your letter nas been laid before our aovernment of India. It is satisfactory tnat you snouia aeciae to ce guided by tne advice of government, and xais is wnat is expected in return for the support wnicn is being afforded you. So long as you adhere to Treaty obligations tne British Government will protect you and will if necessary help you to repel attacks by sea or frustrate a threatened movement from tne minland against your islands, but if eacn protection or assistance is to be accorded to you, you mass be most careful not to undertake measures which may involve you in complications on tne mainland of which are considered unadvisable by the British Government. With best wisnes for your welfare end prosperity. sd. E.G.Ross, Lt .Colon el. H»B#M. 1 s Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to Secretary to Government of India* foreign department,under political Resident's 1 et tier . 357 ol 20th March 1875,(Original on 'Bundle ^3, file No.323-I-.Vol.14 - ' Baiira i n Affairs - October 1374 to Marcn 1875''). Translat ion^ • I cm.' frcm - Snaifcli Saau bin All, Oaief of BaJorain. To - Colonel Ross, . , ■ Political Resi dent, Busnire. Dated 25tii JuharraM 129 2 4tii\MPrcii 1875, a/O* Your letter of tne 15tn Monurram is r ece ived and its contents are understood especially wiiat I told yoa in my letter f- dated 7th Zulkaada . We continue as Heretofore in tnat matter and we hope trusting in G-od taat all our actions will De acceptable to the Britisn Government for s is my desire and endeavour. with reference to tne desire of Government that we -* i , should not Interfere in affaire on tne mainland, verily we will refrain from these proceedings for we stand not in need of such except our city Subarah for tnat is our property and has been. It and its innabitarrte are dependent on us and all are dependent on tne Brit isn Government. we feel certain tnat tne Br it is ii Governfaent would never , wish us to abandon our possessions and allow the enemy to seize them. Copy forwarded to Secretary to Government of India, foreign Department, under political Resident's letter Mo.337 of the 20th larch 187b, 90(Original on Bundle 35, file Mo.323-I-Vol. 14 -'Bahrain 4ffaira - October 1374 to Marcn 1375?) copy, ' _ Mo.95 of 1875. / } /V-/ / J ' To Shaikh masu ben All A1 Khal if an, Chief of Bahrain. i Dated 4th Buffeir 1292 12th mron 1875. A/ C* I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letters dated 25th and 28th Mohurram 1292 which I nave attentively persued and considered. I am unable to perceive that tne matter contained in tnese letters differs fro® wnat nas previously seen submittea by me to Goverrmient and tnerefore tnere is no ground for expecting tuat tne arguments stated will cause any change or modification in tne course which Government have considered it advisable for you to adopt as regards affairs of tne mainland. The reports I have recently received induce me indeed to think tnat the state of affairs generally snows an increased necessity for avoidance of all int erf er ence on the mainland - wnet nor at 20 bar ah or any ot ner place/no exception is made/ and this course I have no hesitation in again urging on you as tne most friendly advice I could give* I trust you will look on tnis as tne advice which my Govern ment with a sincere desire for tne welfare and stability of your Goremment of Bahrain instructs me to offer and tnat you will give it tne earnest and grave cons iderat ion it requires and 1 nave no doubt you will always aanere to tne resolution you communicated in your letter dated 7th Zilkaada 12 91 of being guided by the wishes I'/th December 187/* of the British Government. I beg you will also consider this as coming from your well- wisher who will always give ready ear to all matters on wnicn you ®ay seek advice. || s d. . G. Ros s, Lt.Col. H .B.M .'s Political Resident in the Pers ian Gulf Copy forwarded to Secretary to Government of India, Foreign department, under Political Resident's letter 10.337 of 20th March 1875. 90™/ r /A&gt; t /3 ( n. VL (Ofiginal on Bundle jmo.33 -file i ^o .32o-Vol, 15-'Barirain Affairs - Marcn 1875 to June 1876'}. 023^-2- Translation. ¥***\ o n fr om fhe Chief of Bahrain Shaikh :»au To - Colonel Ross, political Resident, Persian irulf, 15tn Safar 1292 . 23rd March 1876. Receivea 26th iarca 1875. A/ C» ¥our esteemed letter of the 4th 8afa r xias been 12tn March 187o received and its contents understood. You tell me to abstain moretimn ever from interference in affairs of tne mainland and tims we acquainted you before in our letter dated 26ta Mohurram 4th March 1875. Verily we have acted according to your letter of toe 2nd Z ulfraada 12tn Deer.1874 that is according to your saying to us that 'we wll not prevent you if it be your wish to send forces for the defence of that place simply e.g. ^obarah,' and Your Honour knows that tne wh&gt;le of Katr is subservient to tne Ruler of Bahrain and tn Colonel felly's time (they) paid us zakat (tribute) and for the sake of tne English Power we have restrained ourselves from them but £obarah we have told jfour Honour it is ours (or our country) and it is not possible we should be negligent about it (or tne expression may mean «give it up*). fe trust to your assistance in tne representation of our case to the British Government and that we shall not be compelled to give up our possessions# Copy forwarded to Gov ernment of India under Political India Office lesident's letter No*406 of 3rd April 1875 inmn mimimiiKiwiii no i 1 ^ &gt;*-&lt; ******* •. 106 No, 417 * « «' 55 40f 'Vicinal on Bundle i s io» do,1 il .e vox • 15— 33ikhin Affairs - March 1375 to June 1B7 6'). Aft copy* Mo. 114 of 1875. To - ShaiKh Bsau bin All, Gttief of Bahrain. 3 )ated 23rd _Ji &amp;far 129_2« 51s c March 1B75, A/C. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated I5th 3afar 1292 (23rd March), You inform me that you have acted in accoraance with the advice which was contained in xn^v letter dated tne 2nd ^.ilicaada iSth Uecemoer 1929. This is indeed wnat would be in accordance with tne IHf? wishes of Governraent. You allude however also to tne words I used in a conversation I nad with you previous to the date of that letter namely oth November 1874 to the effect that 1 I would 24th Pamaaan '1291 not then prevent you sending reinforcements to isobar ah' . I hoped that from my letters of 2nd ailicaada 1291 and 4th Safar 12th -December 1874 12th March 1292 you would iiave clearly understood taat tne advice contained IW5 was communicated to you under orders direct trom His Excellency tne Viceroy and Governor General of India in Council and tnat it was to those letters you s no old look f or tne expression of the views of Government of Iniia. I hope you will have now no mis apprehension on tnis point, and tnat you will carefully read my letters dated 2nd Zilkaad a 1291 and 4th 8afar 129 2 an d be i2th December 187*4 12tn'March 1875 guided solely by tnem in tne matters referred to and that you will not consider this tenor in any way affect ed or qualified by ary previous communication of any sort. I ifeve thougnt from tne wording of your letter of 15th Safar 1292 23rd March 1875' that it is necessary to inform you as above# ®lth the expression of my friendship and best wishes. sd. E.G.Ross. lit »-• 0 ol« H«B«M. * s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Oopy forwarded to Government of India under Political Secretary of State for India Resident's letter Wo.406 ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ -or ,. dated tne 3rd April 187o. 417 » do »• 40■&gt;?o) ( Or ig ina X on Bundl© jno ^ 5 *5 9 i i»x 0 jm 0• J oX ♦ 1 o-* Beth. 1 cii n Affairs -Marcn 1875 to June 1876'. ), qsst' To - Ho, 20 8 of 187t), Sh4ikn Esau bin Ali, Onief of Baiirain. i )ated 25th Rabl el Tnani 1298 K' Slst Ma^ 1875, a/o. Under orders of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor General of India in Council I have the honour to again call your attention to the correspondence on tne subject of your interf ere?ice wi tn affairs of the mp inland of Guttur and in particular t net own of ZobjU'ah,vi25&lt;, my letters dated 2nd Zilicaada 1291( 12th December 1874) and 4th Safar 1292 ( 12th March 1875)* From your letter dated tne 15th Safar 1292 (23rd March 1876 last) I apprehended tnat you had failed to realise the full meaning of the communications I had addressed to you on t his subject and the Importance to yourself of entirely dissevering yourself from tne affairs of tne mainland, interference in which might any day lead you into complications, I therefore addressed you a further communioet ion dated the 23rd Safar 1292 ( 31-at March 1875). I cannot doubt tnat you must nave fully comprehended now the views and advice which I have tendered you by order of the Government of India, [ But notwithstanding this it appears that you still take proceedings with regard to Zobarah which 0 bviously entangle you in the affairs of the rta inland*- As then the advice you received through me must nave been quite understood by you, and as you do not as yet appear to have fully abided by it, it becomes necessary uni er orders of the Govern- raent of India to explain to you as clearly as possi ble that if you thould decide to persist in a course opposed to the advice of tne government of India and are thereby involved in complicat ions on the mainland, tne consequences will be upon yourself, an d the ritis i Government will hold themselves free to take such measures with /with respect to you as tney raay think necessary. My feeling of friends nip aid. m sh for your welfare and good, prompt me to desire that so important a eommuni cat ion as this should reach you as early as possible, and also that you should have every facility for fully coraprenend ing it, I am therefore sending Captain Fraser my Assistant in a Government t ess el to visit you and entrusting to him tnis letter which he will deliver to you with ay earnest and friendly rec omcenda- 11on tnat you will give its contents tne consideration their importance deserves. Trusting you are in good health and prosperity. sd l.G.Boss, Lt *-001 on el. H« B. M. 5 s Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to Government of India urh er Secretary of State for India Polit ical Resident's letter No, 657/171 dated 7th July 1875, 710/il dTtto{Original on bundle lTo.53, file JM0.323-Vol. 15-'Bahrain Affairs -Maron 1875 to June I876 rt .). Trans lat ion* —- Copy# .■^/ frcxa - Shaikh isau bin All al Khal if a, Chief of Bahrain, To - Lieut.-Colonel S.G.Ross, H.B.Mf's Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf. Bated Bahrain 9th Jamadi ul Awal. After Greeting, Let it be known to you that your esteemed letter of the 25th Rabi al Thanl, favoured by Captain Eraser your Assistant, tea reached us and its contents have been understood# Your expressions of friendship and goodwill render us deeply grateful as also your counsels whicn are replete with benefit. After receiving your letter we called on Gap t-, in Fraser who made clear to us the meaning and purport of your letter whicn we understand to be that Government having * in view our gooa and advantage had deemed it advisable to prohibit interference in affairsoia the mainland and especially at Zobarah. We have obeyed, and followed txie order, and will not endeavour except in subjection; and our purpose is, in conformity with your order, to abandon tne affairs of Zobarah, and interference tnerein, completely. God willing we will not, so long as we live, engage in any matter disapproved of by Government, nor will we do anything that may involve us in trouble. But the British Govern ment weife.ve neither asylum nor protector. The reason of our not interfering in the affairs of Zobarah aw tnia time is simply obedience to the orders of Goreminent, not that our rights nave become invalid or extinct. We trust that tne British Government will be propitious to Us and permit us to possess it (Zobarah) again for it has been ours f rom ancient times and we nave now yielded of necessity. That t.ieae matters may be made manifest to you we have sent our /our brother Shaiicii AJamad bin ♦ Ali to you on a vie it. we consider Jaim as oars ell' in all tmngs and iie will explain to you certain of our wants and wishes for tne information of Government, We trust you will always continue to be favourably .&lt; 1 disposed towards us, Bahrai n» June 14tii 1875 e | , i f . _ ■ , Copy forwarded to Government: of India under Secretary of s^ate for Iniia olitical Resident's letter Mo« 667/171 of 28th June 1870, 710/61 of ditto.(Original on bundle ^o .53, f ile iM0.323«Vol, 15 -'Bahrain Affairs -March 1875 to June 1876',), / 4 copy. The wishes and requests of Shaikh »Isa bin 'All which I am ordered by him to represent to LI eut,-Colonel 15,0,Ross, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, **-*» *-* 1, I hare been ordered to proceed to Bus hi re and obtain a special interview with you and to express ray obligations on his behalf for tne favor and kindness you have exhibited towards him and the friendly counsels you Have tendered for his benefit, 2, Our object in thas troubling you is to represent certain circumstances connected with affairs on the mainland especially Zooa ^an, ani the orders issued by Government regarding our abstention from interference with aobarah. We have no alternative but resigna tion and obedience to those commands, but it is necesaary we should infom you m respect to oar agreeing to abstain from interference in the affairs of iobarah and tne consent enoes whicxx -/ill ensue, that we have frequently represented to you ttiat our coxinection with Zobarah and the Naeem tribe whom we have ordered to dwell there was, for various reasons, an imperative obligation and necessity- as you are aware, When we waive this obligation in respect to tnat garter it oehoves us to devise other plans for the protection of Bahrain and such plans cannot be accomplished or perfected in a short ■ pace of time. Shaikh ' Isa tneref ore trusts tnat you will allow him respite till t ie expiry of the PeadL diving season and the gather- iog in of the date harvest, for ycu are aware that during this period i. e 0 pearl diving season, all men who can be relied on are dispersed and absent, and our town is empty. For this reason our enemies and workers in mischief, even though few in number, will be | e to come to Bahrain and slay, rob, ana ravage to tne full of their desire. But men the pearl diving Season draws to its close, 4 montne nc e, and the divers return to their homes, Shaikh *188, will abandon Zobarah, forbid all those residing tnere and the Haeem /faeem tribe who are subject to ua to rema in, and ordee tnem to take up tneir abode in our possessions. Those who are not our subjects can do aa they liJce, and will not obtain our support or assistance for when we quit Zobarah we cannot protect them if they be oppressed# 3 b mat is of most urgent necessity for tne defence of Bahrain is that an English vessel should be present tnere especially in tne pearl divi g season otherwise with wnat means shall we be able to strive in tne defence of our country ? fithout a British vessel all is in vain and tnere can be no security,, If tms request cannot be complied with, Bahrain will of a certainty he conquered and taken possession ot by tne enemy and we fear tnat feuds and battles such as tooic place in tne times of our ancestors will recur especially wnen it becomes kno .m tnat Sobarah nas been given up. (our enemies) will tnen collect tnere and await tneir opportunity of attaching us» we hope tnat Government will not ■ ^ ,, permit any of our foes to resiae tnere for it is situated close to Banrai n 9 4. Shaikn * Isa begs tnat you will let me return as soon as possible for he has not anyone there to aid nim in his affairs# I hope you will send me baoic in a Government vessel whicn will ce a source of additional dignity to us and tne cause of security and tranquility in Bahrain# When my anemies hear I have travelled in a G-overnment vessel tney will despair and give up tneir mischievous schemes. i 5« Shaikh 1 Isa trusts tnat his abstaining from Interference with ^obarah yill not be considered as (involving) loss of rignt to it for It Is our possession and tne possession of our fore fathers from olden times and we beg tnat our claim will be held in recollection by Government till such time as they deem it advisable 0 grant permission to us to again occupy it. We /(Original on Bundle 53, file J&gt;io.323-701.lb-'♦Bahrain Affairs - MarcJi 1875 to June 1876'.] copy * ¥0, 253 of 1875. To - Siiaikh Ssau bin All, G&amp;ief of Bahrain, Dated 22nd Jaraadi al Awal 1292» I ' mm ; June'' 187b'. A/0* iour esteemed letter of 9tn Jauiadi al Awal nas been received, and I shall nave much pleasure in submitting it to tne Government of India feeling sure it will cause satisfaction to Government to learn tnat you are prepared to follow the friendly counsels tendered to you without any further delay. Your brother, my esteemed friend Shaiich Anmed bin All, arrived here in safety and will return in a aovernment vessel as he preferred doing so. He has informed me of all tnat you instructed nim to say and will inform you no doubt of my replies to nis communications. SnaiJch Ahmed represented your wishes about a vessel* i replied that though I cannot keep a vessel of the British lavy continuously at Bahrain, i shall do tJae best I can to have the Island visited frequently by cruisers. sd. S.O.Hoss, Lt.Gol. H# B. M a 1 s Pol it i eel He si d en t in the Persian Gulf. nopy forwarded to Governme nt of India under Secretary of state for India Political Resident's letter flo. 667/171 of the 28 th June 1875. 710/61 cf ditto^idinal on Bundle 55, file wo 8 323_Vol. 15-'♦Bahrai n affairs -March 1875 to June ISVe'*) C0pyo lo*4S0 of 1875. f» 0 . Sba ikn Ssau bin Al i» CM ef of Balirai n. Dated 28th Staaban 1292. 29th Septaatoer 1875. A/C a I hear from Captain ifraser Assistant Resident that in a conrersation you recently nad at Bahrain you mentioned that you had received no reply from OoTernment to tne r epr esentat ions you made through your brother Shaikh Aimed. I beg to remind you tnat I informed you tnrougn Snaikh Abmed that Government having already consider®! tne whole circumstances had ordered me to communicate their final views for which I beg to refer you to my letters Mo.208 dated 25th 31st Habi al Sani 129 2 aid Mo&lt;,253 dated 22nd Jaaaai al Sani 1292 May 1875, ''26th June '1875. I informed Shaikh Ahmed that tne instructions above referred to which I nad received from Government admitted of no further discussion or delay. Lest you should iiave any misapprehension in the matter I deem it right and friendly to write to you now and repeat U i that tne views of the (rovernment of India remain unaltered and are as expressed in ray letters above quoted. sd. E.C.Ross. Lt«-Col on el. M.B.M. 1 s Jrolitical Resident in tne Persian Gulf.19/243. Telegram From To Repeated G.T.C. Senior Naval Officer, H.M.S. Shore ham, Bahrain Radio. Commander, H.M.S. Deptford. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho.1714. Dated 2nd received 3rd July, 1937 j H&amp;H I V J* IMPORTANT. H.M.S. Deptford is to proceed forthwith to Doha. Instructions follow Senior Naval Officer 3/719/243 I r, Telegram R. 17. T'rom To Uo. Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, .Busnire. Bated and. received tne 3rd July 1937, 1$ Your telegram of 2nd July X4 0,67l 2. Your paragraph 1, In my opinion althougn ■ sf tnere nave most probably been minor acts of aggression the snaikn of tne Nairn nas on tne wholejtcept nis agreement with us. The Shaikn of qatar is reported to nave on occasion raided Nairn and nas now attacked tnem after renouncing nis obligation t o us wmle tnej 'were s ^ ill bound by tneir agreement and nad not been warned of tne termina- tion of negotiations. wwitiMltxHiWMmii j.in M««i»n*vsws«W.'' 3, Your paragraph 3. In view of course of action decided ucon tnere is no object in aircraft coming nere. - Political,19/245. jtfio Telegram 1 .17. From To Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Heaident, Busiiire. No. 173. Dated and received tne 3rd July 1937. Imports, nt. My telegram of 1st July iNo .162. \ Ity paragrapn 3. A formal request in v/riting was lodged by His Highness on July 1st and will be forwarded to you by sea rnail. Relevant portion runs as follows:- 'We request tne British Government to restrain Shaikh Abdullan from ma icing war against our aibjects who live witnin our bounaaries at Zubara'. I am being pressed by His Highness for information regarding what action is being taken on nis request to safeguard wnat ne considers his territory and people. I shall be glad to be informed &lt;//hat reply I should give to His Highness. 3. Refugees Have been arriving in small numbers. 4. Belgrave informs me tnat ne nas received information tnat besieged iiaim in Al Tnagnac nave surrendered and tne Snaiicn of qatar is reported to be advancing on Zubaran fort (Ummrear). The Uaim are running out of ammunition. - Political.tnat I &amp;e autnorised to reply to tne 3nail&lt;n or Bahrain in tne following sense. 5, Tnat on tne evidence before then His Majesty's Government are of opinion tnat Zubaran belongs to tne Sna ikn of qatar, and in tnis connection tney point out tnat as long ago as i87b tne Ruler of Bahrain was informed by tne government of India tnat ne snould not interfere in tne affairs of ^ufcaran vide letter dated the 31st kay 187v&gt; liom Hesic^aat to Ruler Bahrain.. Further tnat in tnis connection it should De noted tne action taken in 1895 by His Majesty's Sloops in destroying nostile dhows at Zu bar ah was to prevent tne invasion of Bahrain from Qatar and in no way supported tne claim of Banrain to Zubaran. i'nat in tnese circumstances His Majesty's Government regret tnat tney are unable to intervene on Denall' of tne nsxm f 4n Zubaran, 6. This decision will I am afraid have the effect mentioned in paragrapn 13 of my Express letter but I see no alternat ive. ' C 'h ^ / -Britcons ul.I n 19/243 Telegram prom To Ho. 1406 G. T.a. 7 aenior mval officer, Persian Gulf. Political Resident, Bushire« Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated and received 3rd July 1937. H.M.S. Shereham and H.M.S. Fowey have ) gone to the assistance of an Admiralty oiler who is aground and I therefore regret that for the moment I am unable to detail a sloop for Bahrain. one will be sent as soon as possible. SE1TI0R FAVAL OFFICER. 'h ■ . \Tele grain from To 19/243 •36. Officer aoramanding, H.M.S. Deptford Political Resident, Buahire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated to Senior laval Officer, Persian Gulf. Ho. 1951 Dated 3rd July received 4th July 1937. IMFORTAFT 10 r Senior ifeval officer*3 telegrara bo. 1744 of July 2nd. Result of visit to shaikh*s representative Bin Salim is as follows. (a) Only Indian subject is a Baluchi barber who has been here twenty years. He has Indian passport. (*) Bews of fighting has either not come through or is being withheld probably latter. i hope to get more tomorrow. Shaikh and son accompanied by Secretary are at north end of peninsula with about seven thousand armed men v/i th about forty rounds of ammunition each. All men have been stopped from pearling to fight, only fifty armed men being left in the town which is quiet. As supplies from Bahrain have been stopped they i are being obtained from Debai. DEP TFORD.19/ 243 Telegram G .T.C From Political Resident, BusMre To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Senior Naval Officer, H.M.S. Shoreham, Bahrain Radio. Commander, E.M.S. Deptford, Bahrain Radio No. 683. Dated 4th July, 1937. As Shaikh of Qatar has worsted the Nairn there would seem to be no danger of disturbances at Dohah, and H .m .S. Deptford could therefore return to Bahrain which is at present without a sloop vide Senior Naval Officer*s telegram No.1406 of 3rd July. ^ //6 2. If you concur please telegraph Senior Naval Officer repeating to H.M.S. Deptford and me. Britconsul19/243 '13 if Telegram from To No. 174 17. political Agent, Bahrain, political Resident, Bushire. Dated and received 4th July 1937. important A / lly telegram of July 3rd no. 173. (iasulties during the engagement at Al Thaghah would now appear not to exceed 20. iieporte now state that the two forces are facing each other and that shaikh of Qatar has called on laim instructing them to surrender and they have refused. 2. Situation here is quiet but the ruling family are disquieted and I believe feel Kaim have suffered unjustly. 3. I hear majority of iTucial Shaikhs have written to His Highness expressing their sympathy for him. POLTTICAi #19/243 Telegram 17 from To political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, iiushire No. 176 Dated and received 4th July 1937 IMPORTANT i My telegram of July 4th Mo. 174 I have received a secret reply to my letter to Shaikh Rashid of the .Nairn regarding safety of British sub jects. He complains of Shaikh of Qatar's attack and says that he has been ordered to surrender by today otherwise he will be attacked. Shaikh Rashid asks us to intervene to prevent Shaikh of Q^tar from attacking him. POLITIOAL19/24 3 Te le gxam 17 From Political Agent, Bahrain To political Resident, Bushire Ho. 178 Dated and received 4th July 1937 BttCSDIATE My telegram of 4th July jvio. 176 I have received two letters from ohaikh of Bahrain requesting (a) an ans\Yer to his request for protection of his subjects of laiia (h) appealing to His Majesty^ Government to protect his subjects at Zubarah as he is not allowed to do so himself, (c) stating that provided His Majesty^ Government have no objection he proposes to permit those Haim now at Zubarah who may so desire to come to Hahrain. 2, He again claims Nairn as his subjects and points out that they also claim Bahrain nationality. 3, As we do not propose to intervene betv/een ■ Shaikh of Qatar and the Haim I do not see how we can refuse to permit Faim coming here. 4, i shall be glad to know the answer i should give to His Highness Political19/243 / 1 b ^le gram From To •36. Officer Commanding, H.M.3. Deptford. political Resident, Buahire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated to Senior Naval Officer, Persian {3ulf. HO. 1951 Dated 4th July received 5th July 1937. IMPORTANT interpreter reports that notables are asking I ; II reason and duration of our visit as apparently they cannot believe it is for the purpose of protection of one Indian subject only and suspeot other reason. This intensifies difficulty in getting information, and has lowered enthusiasm for our presence in spite of assurance of impartiality and object of our visit. Bin Salira himself seems friendly and has verbally assured safety of interpreter when ashore but Town guards consist of lawless Bedouins from the interior. Following information believed to be reliable was obtained from a merchant. A well at nhasab has been captured by Qatar forces who sustained casualties ( omission ) Killed eighteen wounded on July 2nd. Ihe Indian subject Mahoromed son of Samma has married the wife of merchant at Doha and doss not think his family would let him go in the event of trouble. ! DSPTFCRD.* 19/243 ' HI Tele g^stra 17. From Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Baiirain. ITO. 685 Dated 5th July 1937. IMPORTANT Your telegram wo. 178 of 4th July. Your paragraph i. (a) and (b) will have to wait on reply frorn India Office to my telegram Ho. 680 of 4th July. /oj 2. With regard to (c). Shaikh of Bahrain should ' I he informed thatlaira can be permitted to enter Bahrain but it ia entirely responsibility of Bahrain Government to keep them in order. 3. in this connection influx/of pearl divers as well as Kaim may lead to trouble. Have y€u informed Bahrain Gov ernment of paragraph 2 of my telegram wo. 671 of 2nd July ? Since Shaikh of qatar has apparently withdrawn his divers risk of incidents on the pear} banks would appear to be very slight. BRITGOKSUL. t0 19/243 I j &lt;2 Telegram ]?rorn To Repeated to Ho. 252 G.T.G. political Agent, Bahrain. Senior mval Officer, Persian Gulf Division. Political Resident, Bushire. Officer Coiamanding, H .m .S. Deptford. Dated and received 5th July 1937 IMPORTANT flfr Political Resident's telegram lb. 683 of JUly 4 th. My latest information is that ahaikh of Q^tar is treating v/i th Maim and no maj or engagement has taken , place. I believe Shaikh of 'Qatar will come to an understanding with Haim and he is already reported to be collecting rifles he had issued to Bedouin. The Shaikh of Q^tar is re£&gt;orted to have told that they are free to leave Q^tar or remain and abide rule of the state. 2. I do not consider it necessary for H.M.S. Deptford to remain at Doha. H.M.S. Fowey has arrived here and there is no indication of any disturbance being likely ■ / to take place. political19/243 1% &gt; Telegram I'r oro To Ho. 182 17. politioal Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Buahire. Dated and received 6th July 1937 important Your telegram of 4th July iio. 680 paragraph 6. I consider that it is most desirable that ahaikh. I of Bahrain be given ? opportunity to state his case even if only as a matter of form. He will then not be able to say that he was judged unheard and ill disposed persons will not be able to make capital out of it. political•/&gt; 19/243 Telegram H. IV. From Political Resident, 'Busnire. Captain Hickinbotnam, Siiarjan., Fo.697. Dated the 7th July 1937. 6^ / loxxv telegram ^o#182 or 6tJi July# Your telegram No#l r ?3 of 3rci July clearly indicated tnat you considered tnat LSiiaikn or Baiirain should be given an immediate reDly. -his can only take tue iorm ox psiagraph 5 of my telegram ^o.680 of 4tn i&gt;aly. 2. iou now suggest tnat tihaikn should ce given opportunity to state his case i.e. presumably before His Majesty's Government's decision is conveyed to nim. mis stating of case will of coarse take time and cannot be put up by telegram. If Shaikh is to be given immediate reply he obviously cannot have opportunity of stating nis case, and vice versa. 3. What do you now suggest ? -Bri tconsulCONFIDENTIAL. |M No. C/500-4/13 I Rl RESIDENCY, f Sfo 6-7' 2)1 i Date. 7 CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS \ n -5) The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to :■ The Honoui'able the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s), T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G dle. Dated ..??.'l.JulX..19.3V Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. m 1 1. Copy of letter Ko.C/488 dated the 28th June 1937 to the Ruler of Qatar. S. Letter dated 27th June 1957 from Shaikh Rashid bin Muhammad al Jabur. 3. Letter dated 27th June 19 57 from Shaikh Rashid bin Muha n- mad al Jabur to His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain, 4. Letter No.C/489 dated 28tji June 1937 to Shaikh Rashid bin M u haiiimad al Jabur. 5. Letter No .C/490 dated 28th June 1937 to His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain. 6. Letter dated 25th June 1937 from the Ruler of Qatar. 7. Statement of Juma'h al Ch^'bi Subject. Zubarah. V.T&gt; Copy of letter Ho. C/488 dated the 28th June 1937 to Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, CIE. &gt; Ruler of Qatar. ■ After Con^liraentss Thank you for your letter of the i6th Rabi al Thani 1356« I have now received instructions from the Honourable the Political Resident and your Representa tives are returning. I naich regret the delay. I am enquiring into the case of alleged delay in the Bah rain Customs. Although I have twice asked your Rep- I resentatives for particulars I have received none from them, but one man cams ano. complained to me in person and as I have said I am making enquiries into his case. I trust that the negotiations are proving successful and once again the old friendship between Qatar and Bahrain will be restored. Usual Ending.Copy of letter dated i8th Rabi Thani 1356 (= 27th June 1937) from Rashid bin Mihammad al Jabur to the Political Agent, Bahrain, After Compliments. 1 ,• I beg to inform you that some important matters took place here. That you prevented us from doing anything even if the eneay transgresses upon us. We obeyed! your orders all this time. Now some incidents took; place which could not be tolerated. Abdullah bin Qasim sent some cavalry men who raided on the people of Al Thaghb, a place known to your men - the men of Shaikh Hamad. They fired at and wounded one of them. But they did not fire i»ack at them. One day before, a car also came and fired at them but they did not return the shots. We tied up our hands until this day. They also took away camels from us and we did not make any demand from them lest your orders may be disobeyed. I hope that you would not agree to any loss to us®Copy of letter dated 3.8th Rabi Thanl 1356 (=27th June 1937; from Rashid bin Muhammad al Jabur to His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain, After Conqaliments, I beg to inform you that I received your es teemed letter on Sunday night and noted that we should not do anything which may be taken as a plea by the enemy. We are obedient to your orders. But on Sunday morning some cavalry men raided on the people at iSJL Thaghb and fired at them feut they did not fire back at them. They wounded Juma«h bin Mohammad bin Mani» al Ka , bi. Also a car went to them on SAnday night and fired at them but they did not fire back at them. Their highhandedness has now increased and we have tied up our hands. This is bad for us that our hands should be tied up and their hands be open to us. As regards their assault to the said wounded person who was returning from Thaghb people, the cavalry men over took him and demanded from him to throw his gun but as he refused to do so, they fired at him and wounded him.Copy of letter Ho. C/489 dated the 28th June 1957 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh Rashid bin Muhammad al Jabur. After compliments. I have received your letter dated 18th Rabi al Thani 1356 (2?th June 1957) and am communicating with the Honourable the Political Resident. I trust the events you allege will not occur again and that the present negotiations will be successful. Usual Ending.Copy of letter No. C/ 490 dated the 28th June 1937 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to His High ness the Ruler of Bahrain. Thank you for sending me the letter from S|| Shaikh Rashid bin Mohammad which I am returning. I am communicating with the Honourable the Political Resident. I expect these happenings are the doings of uncontrolled bedouin. I hear that a wounded man has been brought here and would like to see him. If he is in hospital I will go and see him. Usual Ending. A.CrSv) Statement of Juma'h al Cha f bi who is lying in the hospital under treatment. On Sunday the 26th June 1937 I left my conpanions who were camping at Al Thaghb and proceeded alone on foot to Akhday to bring my family back to Al Thaghb where 100 men of my conpanions of the Chibisha tribe were camping at a Fort built recently by us when the i&amp;ibarah trouble broke out, IBhen there was 15 minutes* walk (about 1 mile) to reach Akhday, three cavalry men of Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim's army overtook me and asked me to throw my gun and go with them to Shaikh Abdullah. As I refused to do so they fired at me but the shots missed me. Then one of them dismounted and fired a shot at me which hit me on icy right shoulder. I tried to fire back at him but failed owing to thw wound I sustained. I at once picked up my gun and ran back to Al Thaghb to my companions whom I asked to take me to Rahid al Jabur who was at Lishah. They did so and from Lisha I was brought to Bahrain and amijtted in the Hospital® All the inhabitants ofxAtaSkag&amp;M Akhday are the followers of Al Khalifah and also the Thaghb. 30/6/37,CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/501-4/13 bushire residency. tM -Tr- £ aaa—jgg—Ba—Wl i WSgWnWTM■ T Date.:. &amp;:.7 :.37. ''confidential records _ii—iiiiii The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to :• The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. D a ted ... .2nd.. July - • 195.7 Reference to previous correspondence ; Description Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated 29th June 1957 from the Ruler of Qatar. 2. Political Agent's -note dated 1st July 1957. 3. Letter dated 1st July 1957 from His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain, barah. U '7 WmmmmV i Translation of letter dated SOth Rabi al Than! 1556 (29th June 1937) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al Thani, I Ruler of Qatar, to Captain Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. j ^fter Compliments, With reference to your letter dated the 11th Rabi al Thani 1356 (20th June 19S7), I accepted the suggestion made by His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain on the subject of the meeting of his relatives with mine. This meeting was actually held, and I did all I could to settle this difference, but we could not obtain a satisfactory result, I regrefe to inform you further to my intimation to you in my letter'of 5th Rabi al Thani 1356 (14th June 1937) that the meeting was dissolved and the negotiations terminated without result. The representatives of His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain left after the negotiations had been terminated and everything ended. As regards the Nairn who are iry subjects, I have already written to you sufficiently about them. And now relying on the letters C p, dated 9th May 1937 and 30th Safar 1356 (12th May 1937) which were exchanged between me and you on behalf of the Honourable the Political Resident regarding the termination of the undertaking of non-interference with the Nairn on the termination/ of the negotiations, I therefore do not consider icyself bound to any undertaking of the sort because that had ended by the termination of the negotiations. As position does not allow me to wait further I shall take steps to rectify the corruption made by m disloyal subjects in any way that I deem suitable. I am writing this letter for your information and henceforward I shall not be held responsible for the steps which I find necessary to take in the present circumstances. Usual Ending.Stateaent of Hameed bin Ibrahim, Bakradii su '^ot, living at Has xiunaan, i ^ansiaali, diver. I left Jakrain last moatii, dived for sojie days, X got some good pearls and took them to Doliah, I arrived there aboat 14 days ago. la the boat -..dtli me -ms ^ansoor bin ^axirus (Bahrain subject of ^anaiaah) Bin Darv/ish came to us as .we laaaod on the shore with four armed men g&amp;d asked where we came from. • When he heard we came from Bahrain, he took as to Shaimh iibdullah. bin • Jasim at his fort- we told him had' come from Bahrain, diving, end oaiao to bay food. lie said, 'you are not divers, you are spies of ..jJirain Government M 3haikh iadallah ordered us to :o to prison, in the fort, for ten days. do gave us - no f ood but one man called mbdul Aziz, v ;hom ■.-.e do not know, took pity on us and , ave us food. ..hile we were there another man from Ja lira in, Jesim bin oas, was brought and )ut into prison with us. £e was imprisoned because he refused to ive Shaikli Abdullah some rifles ®hich he owned. His wife lived at Dohah. After the fee.;, aays the jailer let us go* .ie vent to Jin Jar..dsn and asked for our oods, our ooxes and our cooking . of pots and pearls Ifhloh had been taken out/our boat* Abdullah bin Derwish said first we must get two men from Bahrainfrom those living in hohah, i s witnesses to our statement that we naci never been in prison, before he could give us our belom in s. le pretended to agree to this* ®h® owner of tfe* joliboat then came iS^Bahrain and we tola aim about our case, he told us not to sign any papers out to inform our own government. »e got away secretly — Osecretly in a dahxaia boat and went to (rariyah because m heart tkat soiu.© of our people were t^ere. uur joilboat ana our belongings were kept in iohali and are still tkere. fke boat yeloai&gt; to xiassan bin ^abmood oi 1 ^anamii, it &gt; is registered in oakraia# «e Lao the boat ti from him on the 'Q-alata' system, ^.e gave proportion of tke catck to the owner. «■* «*«■»«»» &lt;Mft Statement of Hassan bin kakiood, Bahrain subject, boat owner, resident of ^aaamah. ■v •. '! 1 own joliboat Mo. E45/42 registered in iiahrain. I lent my joliboat to Hameed to go diving, ^Mjenaa' (snore diTing)• ii . ent diving. lie returned today and informs me ' x 1 1 that my boat lias been seized by the govenaaeat in ^attar.V Copy of a demi-official letter dated the 2nd July 1937 from Mr. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, G.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain, to Captain T. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. A boat-load of women and small children have come in from Furaihah - which was taken last night. Two or three more boats full of women are said to be on the way The nakhuda, a Bahrain Arab, saw the fighting and says they have a machine gun on a lorry which fires hundreds of shots and swings round in a circle. He o imitated it very realistically. The Nairn Shaikh tried to hold back his men even when Abdullah's horsemen advanced but they disobeyed him and went out against Abdullah, the nakhuda says if they had stuck together they might not have got hit so hard. He rushed off with the women before the fighting ended and at sunset it ¥/as still going on. He can give no account of casualties.JCY.J© TI, i immiw m—'1 f^/^3 Uo. C/508-4/3-3 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd July 1937. In / From To Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire MUBARAK Sir, I have the honour to report that on July the 2nd His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain accompanied by Shaikh 'Abdullah bin 'Isa, Shaikh Salman bin Hamad, and the Ad viser to the Bahrain Government Mr. C.D. Belgrave, C.B.E., called to interview me. 2. His Highness who was suffering from a severe cold looked extremely worried. They stated that they were very Mich concerned about the events taking place in 'Zubarah and that they were most anxious to know what action His Majesty's Government were taking with regard to the pro tection of Bahrain subjects residing in Qatar Peninsula. His Highness pointed out that he understood that an under taking had been given by the Shaikh of Qatar not to inter fere with the Nairn during the course of the negotiations and that similarly Shaikh Rashid bin Muhammad and the Maim had given an undertaking not to interfere or molest the people of Qatar during the course of the negotiations. His Highness stated that from information which he had received from reliable sources the Shaikh of Qatar had attacked the Nairn living in the Zubarah area on the night of/--s- yv of July the 1st and had inflicted casualties on them. That the Maim had been previously restrained from inter fering with Shaikh * Abdullah bin Qasim^s forces by their leader Shaikh Rashid bin Mihammad, as he was anxious to keep his covenant with His Majesty*s Government. In His Highness' opinion this attack on the Naim amounted to a breach of the agreement which he understood existed bet— ween the Shaikh of Qatar and the Honourable the Political Resident, and His Highness pointed out that by this action the Shaikh of Qatar had obtained a distinct and unfair advantage over the Naim. 3. His Highness further expressed fears that the followers of the Shaikh of Qatar might endeavour to land and attack the isolated villages on the Bahrain Coast. I assured His Highness that in vy opinion there was not the slightest likelihood of this event occurring. His High ness stated that in his opinion anyone who was mad enough to break an agreement with His Majesty's Government was mad enougti to do anything. I told His Highness that I did not for one moment believe that there was any possi bility of Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Qasim authorising or per mitting his followers to come to Bahrain. Although I firmly believed that what I said was correct, at the same time I was doubtful whether my word was carrying as nuch weight as it should have done in view of the fact that I had previously informed His Highness that I did not con sider that Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Qasim would renounce his undertaking with us to the extent of attacking the Naim. 4. Mr. Belgrave informed me that he was generally in agreement with the views His Highness expressed, but that he was sure that no attack on Bahrain would be made but he thought it possible that the followers of the Shaikh of/--3- 0 f Qatar might follow up 'boats bringing Nairn fugitives to Balirain, and he further stated that he was in agree ment with the views which I had previously held to the effect that Shaikh * Abdullah bin Qasim would not renounce his agreement and he was very much surprised at Shaikh * Abdullah bin Qasim* s action. 5, After a considerable amount of general conversa tion regarding the present disturbance, I assured His Highness that I had reported the facts to yourself and that as soon as I had information, I would inform him what action, if any, was being taken. His Highness stated that he was proposing to come in again in the evening in order to find out from me personally ahether there was any further event, and I informed him that if I had any comimnication of importance I would rather telephone to him or else myself come and interview him. Practically the whole of His Highness 1 relatives were present in the Agency grounds together with the leading merchants of Bahrain during the course of this interview. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient ser¥aiit. political Agent, Bahrain. u(&amp;9 CONFIDENTIAL. ^ C/509-4/13 I The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to- The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSH I RE and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G olf. Dated.I?.?? Reference to previous correspondence ; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter dated the 3rd July 1937 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. ZUBARAHCopy of a demi-official letter dated the 3rd July 1937 from Mr. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain, to Captain T. Hickinbotham, political Agent, Bahrain. I am writing from the Palace. His Highness requests you to send the message which we discussed to the Resident, referring to His Highness' letter in which he asked for protection over his people the Nairn at Zubarah against the attack by Shaikh Abdullah bin Jasinu Further news is that the fort which was besieged has surrendered having finished their ammunition, this is sure, it is reported but not absolutely sure, that Abdullah bin Jasim is advancing on the old fort itself at Zubarah and if so he will cut off the Nairn from sea. I am kept up here - all the Bahama leaders, Arabs n -p Muharraq and Hedd and many others have come to ofter services to His Highness*CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/510-4/ f n* ''YstP 4 ^ U.i»i. H L'A ■jiw.'.-mtJ.ma-i, '- IUJWII bushir e residency. / A/n /(d Date ^ CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS (\ , &lt;0 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ^ TJ 3 H I R E. . and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. Dated... 3rd... July... .19.32 * Reference to previous correspondence : Descripiwn of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No.584/SF-9A dated the 3rd July 1937 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain• Subject. ZUBARAH Oi&lt;2 Hi O rGoiu'icLentiiil L v \ % Ho. 584/^-^i - of 1356 Office of the Adviser to the Govemaent, Bahrain. Dated, iyfhany £4, 1356 July 3, 1937 j. Dalrymple Balgrave, iisq .uire, , Aaviser to the Govermaent of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. oir, i.xth reference to the Ztubara dispute, 1 have the honour to acquaint you with the happenings at Gariyah. Three ueetin^s took place, on she suore, between Sha l iibdullah bin isa and Jhaiiiii ouliaan bin and Shaikh Eamad bin Abdullah bin Jasim and Bhaikh Ali bin Jasia, the son and brother of the Kuler of ^atar. At the first meeting the ^atar shaiidis appeared reason able and anxious for a settlement, at the two later meet' ings their attitude entirely changed. iUter the first meeting they asked us to send them a new draft • 3 ® fte . what shorter and more concise than the mrious draft agreements discussed in Bahrain. ifc seGOn ^ mee ^^ n ^ they said they would agree to no terms except their own «nn they added several fresa clauses to their o.&lt;n ori 0 i a draft agreement among them being one to the effect that th fluler of Bahrain should hand over all the Arabb other than Nairn who had joined the Maim at Aubara. E -— 3 - fhe Baiiraixi representatives finally agreed to the . v atar proposals iaeluding the unconditional withdrawal of their claim provided that the agree- ment was accompanied by an exchange of letters to the effect that if either side broke the terms of the agreement all the clauses in the agreement, including the withdrawal of claim, would automati cally become null and void. The jitar represen tatives definitelyrefused to agree to this proposal - 'kr-v. ' ^ ■ ■ • ■ * V v -- '-J, - '■■■* V ana sent a message, to this effect, by word of mouth of a clerk* iifter this final refusal a number of ^atar not- ables, including Shaikh ,di bin Jasim and mohomed . oin l- j C uHt til - l vitttki c . uniinaouiiced, to call on Shaikhs Abdulla and Sulman and begged them to accede to the duler of % atar's wishes. They were told that Bahrain could give way no further. On one occasion Jhaikh Abdullah bin Jasim visited the tent of the Balirain representatives accompanied oy about 200 armed iurabs , in three motor lorries, ana foui^ cars full oi relations find notables He draik coffee with the Bahrain representatives but during the meeting, which lasted about an hour, scarcely any words were spoken on either side# bhaikh Abdullah, when departing, mentioned that he was et finding it difficult to restrain his Arabs from attacking the i^aim. Actually attacks on several villages by cavalry and camelmen had already been made and during our stay at Gariyaii several refugees came to the camp and reported that their houses had been burned and their belongings looted by mounted raiders from the ^atar forces.I took no part in the actual conversa tions but was present in tbe tent during part of one 01 the meetings by invitation of both parties. I have the honour to be, air, i lour most obedient servant, .\ v V v lo. 587/Si ? , -9i. - of 1356 Of rice of the iidviser to tile Govermaent,, Bahrain. Dated, B/Tiumy 24. 1356 July laa^. ¥ From G. Dalrymple iielgr ave, Ssquire, U.jj.iSi., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, iiahram. * .ir, I have the honour to acknowledge your letter Ho. 505-4/13 dated July 3, 1937 and to inf'orsa you that His iiighness fully realises his responsibility for pro tecting the lives and properties of British and foreign &gt;• subjects within his territories. liis Highness sees no reason for supposing that demonstrations or civil coiamotions will take place in Bahrain. His HiJmess instructs me to request you to ask the Hon * ole the Political Resident for a reply to his letter dated July 1, 1937 complaining of the attack on Bahrain subjects in the iiubara area by Jfeaikh Abdullah bin Jasim of % atar f s military forces. jm His id;_hness is not permitted to protect his own subjects at ^ubara he appeals to the British Goveinment to lestrain the Huler of Qatar# 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, a? Adviser to the Grovernment.Ho. 589/3?-9i - of X356 Qliice of tiie Adviser to th© uovsKMent, Bahrain Dated, .VThany E5 f July 4, 1937. from 0. Dalrympla Belgraire, esquire, iidviaer to the Goyermient of Bahrain, Baiiraia. His iiritaniiic majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that His Highness has instructed me to inform you that he proposes to allow any of the Maim tribe who are now at £ubara to come to Bahrain if they wish to, provided that the British Government lias no objection to his allowing these, his subjects, to return here, JbB you are aware ; the Maim are claimed by his liighnses as his subjects and they all claim to be Bahrain subjects. I have the honour to be. Sir* Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the GovernmentW /; ■ A &lt;*' l &gt; 1/ Translation of letter dated the 25th BaM al Thani 1356 (4th July 1937) from Shaikh Eashid bin Muhammad al Jafcur to the Political Agent, Bahrain* I have received your esteemed letter and noted con tents. lou warnec us that British subjects and their pro perty should not be endangered by my peqple, I beg to inform you that we did neither do anything to your subjects nor to others. We desisted from doing anything; we were sitting quiet in the place you know and did not move from there. But Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim did not leave us and transgressed upon us. You must have seen his deeds towards our people whom we sent to the doctor at Bahrain. The deaths are more than those who came to Bahrain. We did not desist from doing anything but by your orders. Now he (Shaikh Abdullah) has sent telling us to surrender our arms on Sunday otherwise he will fight with us. I request you to stop him from doing anyhting against us in any my you consider best. Usual Ending.VI rvmfi dent ia l. Urgent » No.C/516-4/13 i Political Agency, Dated the 4th July 1337. Bahrain From 6-7-37 Captain T, Hickinbotham, I.A,, Political Agent, Bahrain. To Sir, The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire I have the honour to state that the Adviser to the Bahrain Government has informed me this morning July 4th, that he had reliable information to the effect that Shaikh Mohammad Rafi, the agent of Yusuf Khun^i, and one Ahmad bin Ebrahim Bu Kamail, and Mbhammad bin Abdur Rahman Ahwazi have been stating that it is the intention of the British Government to cause unrest among the Al Khalifah in Bahrain and among the subjects of the Shaikh of Qatar in Qatar with a view to eventually taking over control of these terri tories. 2. I am sending for Shaikh Mohammad Rafi and Mohammad bin Abdur Rahman, who are Persian subjects, and will warn them that I have heard it rumoured that they have been making statements to this effect but that I trust it is not true and that they should realise that it is extremely unwise for them to make any comment of any sort with regard to the political situation in Bahrain or elsewhere. 3. The third individual is a Bahrain subject and I understand the Bahrain Government are warning him. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. U Captain, PoliticaX Agent, Bahrain,' '^HIRE -^5 -Seency; **- 5^' : (mWIDEIMAL 7 / From To ^cro j£afG RECORDS •C-^PVa ■ 'l'. 1 . |^. ijyjgLpjfc. No. C/517-4/15 Mil —H Political Agency, Bahrain, the 4th July 1337} Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire Sir, I have the honour to refer to your telegram No. BSi dated the 4th July 19S7 and to enclose a very rough sketch map of the Zubarah peninsula, I have underlined the points which I know to be claimed by His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain as being within his area. The names of these places which are incorrectly given on the sketch map are as follows j — Al Thaghab Fureiha Ain Muhammad Umm al Sheweel Al Zubarah Qala Umm Rear Al Rabaija Halwan Lisha Masuchhi Al Maharaqa 2» I have asked the Adviser to the Bahrain Govern ment if he can confirm that these are the only places and he has stated that at such short notice he is unable to do so, I think it advisable to point out here that the Bahrain Government did make an application to us to be given time to prepare their case before any adjudi cation was made by His Majesty^s Government with regard to the ownership of the Zubarah area, 3. I enclose aerial photographs of the wells and also/— U j—33—- also of the ruined toim of Bibaraii and the Fort of Umm Rear. I have marked these lightly in pencil. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.V ( Q # 1 ItLt 1 fe?) i i : Telegram jt om To Government of India, External Al'i'airs Department, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated Political Resident, Buahire, -lo» ioo2# ^ • Dated 6til received 7tn July, 1937. 2. Bushire telegram Jiio«680 of July 4tn, ZUBARAH. Reference paragrapn 4. We agree witn opinion of Political Resident regarding ownersnip of ZuGarah. 3. ,vitn reference to paragrapn 0. We suggest tnat reply to Shaikh of Bahrain mignt pernaps be rendered less unpalatable to nim if opinion regarding ownership of iiubaran were omitted. It would be sufficient pernaps if Shaiicn is reminded of pronibition against interference on mainland and told tnat on tnis account his representations cannot be accepted. -FOREIGN. : ( ill lliffli nl\\&amp; 19/245 Telegram R.17. om To Political Agait, 'Banrain. Political Resident, Busnire. Ho. 133, Dated and received tne July 1937, ik /- My telegram of 6tn July No. 182, Adviser nas enquired on benair or anailcn waen claim to ^ubarah will De considerea and by wnom, His Hignneas is desirous o.t consulting London solicitors and oriel ing counsel London. If necessary he is prepared, to send a representative to Europe. 2. . Adviser nas been naving a difficult time trying to restrain SJiaiJsn from writing ill-advised letters. His Highness and nis family are very upset and inclined to be cnild ian. i 3. 3o far Nairn nave shownrjo inclination to come iiere and nave not been communicating. Humours state tnat ♦ they nave submitted to snaikn of Qatar, -POLITICAL, jl -Jji I n I'WIm hi I i, ^ ■h-Ct y -m -1^1 i-ele gram From To Ho. 186 19/243 17. political Agent, .Bahrain, jeolitical neaident, j^uahire. (po Dated 7th July receiYed 8th July 1937. Your telegrara of 7th july . 697. ; 2. My telegram of lat July xo . 162 paragraph 3 \(jr^ and ray telegram of 3rd July jmo. 173 paragraph 2. i reGeive(d) a request that Hi a Majeaty f a uovsrnment would reatrain shaikh of j|atar from making war on people living in Zubarah area whom the *** ■- 1 • Shaikh of Bahrain claimed aa hia aubjecta. ^xhia amounted to a reiteration of ohaikh of uahrain'a claima to zubarah). i meant to indicate clearly that an immediate reply ahould be given to hia specific request for intervention and not on the merits of his claima to Zubarah. 3. i auggeat that shaikh of Bahrain be told (a) that his claima will be heard by you as represent ing His Majesty's Government and that he should adduce hia proof a by a date to be fixed by you. ^b] that pending a deciaion Zubarah must be considered a part of Q,atar and the people living there must obey the laws of ^,at. av but tnat tnoss persona v/ho claim Bahrain nationality may reikurn to Bahrain ahould they so deaire. 4, i auggeat (a) that the Shaikh of Q^tar be in formed of \a) and \b) above and be ordered to let Biaim depart in peace to Bahrain if they deaire ao to do. (b) that the Shaikh of ^atar be called on to produce evidence in reouttal of the Shaikh of Bahrain'a claima if you should consider it nece aaary political.\-1f I (l n wmmmmm- 19/243 Telegram -K. 17. prom Political Resident, Busiiire. • T® Captain iiickinbotnara, snarjan. No. 709. Dated tne 8tn July 1937. jtour telegram iio # 186 of 7tn July. Last sentence of your paragrapn 2. i#h©le difficulty is that Shaikh's request for intervention is definitely linked with his claim to Zubaran. Only entirely adequate reason His Majesty^ urorernment can give for non-intervention is tnat tiiey do not consider tnat zubarah belongs to Bahrain. If they, were of the contrary opinion obviously tney would nave interven ed, however we will await His Majesty's (rovernment• s reaction to my telegram Ho.680 of 4tn July. /a . I ® J I f - Britconsul% i 19/243 and 19/212 Telegram jj'ron] io HO. 187 17. political Agent, jsahrain. political resident, jsuahire Dated 8 th july received 9th july 1937. IA lour telegram of 7th july mo, 705. ueneral duty on all cargo entering .Bahrain i is 5 per cent whether for re-export or not. xrans-chip- ment of cargo farr aaudi Aratia enjoys a special privilege and only pays duty at the rate of It per cent. xrans- shipment of cargo for Qatar enjoys privilege and pays duty at the rate of 2 per cent ahaikh of uahrain does not propose to prohibit entry of goods for trans-shipment to Oatar into Bahrain hut is withdrawing privilege of a reduced rate of duty. ^atar goods will in future pay duty at 5 per cent i.e. the ssone rate as all places in the uulf except aaudi iirahia. ii: POLITICAL. ^, iv 1 H' &lt; V Telegram jrom To K ep ed Political Kesident, Buanire. Secretary of state for India, London. (iOTernment of India, Sxternal Affairs Department, bimla* Copy by post to Political Agent, Banrain. ffo. 71D # Dated tne 9tn July 1937. Paragraph 3 of uoTernraent of India telegram ao. lt )D2 of 6tii July. t ffB SJoaikh of Bahrain naa now enquired ^a) by whom and (b) when his claim to Zubarah will be considered. Shaikh is desirous of consulting London solicitors and briefing counsel in London, and if necessary is prepared to send a representatire to Europe. 2. Hegarding (a). As far as I can see only competent authority is liis Majesty's Gorerrment. 3. Regarding (b). It is obvious from tne way the Sia ikn*s mind is moving tnat hia case will taice time to prepare. This being so I suggest tnat instead of tne communica tion proposed in paragrapn 5 of ray telegram Mo.680 of 4tn July u Shaikh should now be informed as follows. 4. That with regard to (a) tne only competent autnority is Mia Majesty's Grovernment. Tnat witn regard to (b) His Majesty's Government note that His Highness wishes to submit nis \ case. They would therefore be glad to icnow when it will be ready for submission. Tnat in the meantime nis Majesty's Govern- fflent cannot intervene in tne question of ziubarah. 5. This procedure nas tne advantage tnat before a final decision is given by His Majesty's Government tne Shaikn nas the opportunity of putting up nis case in full. -BRITC02JSUL. n J,19/243. Telegram R'l?- ^ rom Political He31 dent, Busnire. 10 Asiiatant Political Agent, ^anrain No, 726. Dated 11tn July 1937. Paragrapii Mo, of your t el eg ram Mo. 173 of 3rd July and paragrepn no, 1 of your telegram no. 183 of 7th July. W w' i *, Please inform the Sna ikn of Banrain that I JaaTe referred His requests to Mia Majesty's Goveroaent and hope to be able to give nim a reply snortly. RESIDENT.Telegram j&amp;Tora TO Ho. 189 19/243 17. Asaiatant tolitioal agent, Bahrain, political tie aident, rsu shire . Dated and received 12th July 1937. j. r.. _. it that this weelc confidential mails for Bushire missed the boat. . 2. There v^as no correspondence of immediate importance except ^a) a letter from the shaikh of .Bahrain terminating intercourse with Q,atar and (h) another asking when his claim to Zubarah is to be considered. \ , b' 3. The gist of both these letter has been sent telegraphically by Political Agent Bahrain. ASSISTANT POLITICAL A®FT.- - .i rn n Telegram q. prom To Political Hesident, Busiiire. Secretary of state ror India, London Repeated Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Copy by post to Political Agent, Baiirain. lo. 733. My telegram Mo•630 of 4tn July. 2UBARAH. Por information. Situation is as follows, (a) Altliougn tnere is a good deal of local feeling from tJae Siiaikii downwards in sympatny witn. tne mim and in connection witn Batirain claim to 2ubarali, Political Agent does not anticipate any anti-Britisn or anti-fo ' Isturbances. In tnis connection see telegram jso .663 of 2nd July. (b) It is rumoured tnat saim nave submitted to Shaikn of ^atar. A few JNaim refugees nave been arriving. Otnerwise so far isiaim nave shown no inclination to take refuge in Banrain. (c) SJiaikn of Banrain nas witndrawn special privilege transit due rate nitnerto enjoyed by Qatar and has pronibited entrance of s^atar subjects into Banrain. Dated tJne 13th July 1937 -Britconsul. (codv salt to Bahrain under P.L.lIo.53S,S of 13/7/37),n\ 7 *f :&gt; j Ho CONFID5NTIAL* POLITICAL AGENCY, D.O.No.C- KtMAIT. The 29th June 1937, /^JLoc The Shaikh told me today that he had written to the Shaikhs of Qatar and Bahrain encouraging them to patch up their differences as quickly as possible. He thought this could do no harm and might do good, think His Highness's motive in doing this and informing me so that you would hear of it is the same as that which induced him last year to ask if he could be any help in the Palestine troubles i,e, that he wishes to improve his standing in the eyes of both the Arabs and His Majesty's Governrnent, The Hon'ble Lt,-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle,KCIE., Political Readent in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRS, co &lt;c«. &lt;acj \kajd^' ^-o ^ 'l 3 /19/243 0 Telegrais From To Re peat ed Secretary of State for mdia, Loixion, Political Resident, Bushire • Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. jfolitical Agent, Bahrain. Ifo • i 9 G • Dated 15th received 16th JULY 1937. IKPORTAllT. Your telegram imo .7 i 5 of July 9th. ZUBARA. His Majesty 1 s Government agree that they are '-' 1 i 'I 'i' ' competent authority. They are aiixious hoiisever not to give Shaikh of Bahrain impression that they admit he has a prima Jgftriwri i, m facie claim ^incidentally this would logically involve them in restraining Shaikh of Qatar from any action at Zubarah until claim has 'been adjudicated). Ihey therefore feel that reply should be on the following lines. M 2. His Majesty*s Government is ultimate authority for deciding questions regarding ownership between Shaikhs. They are of course always ready to listen *to any representa tions which Shaikh of Bahrain may wish to submit on any matter which he regards as affecting his interests but in the meantime they feel compelled to point out that so long ago as 1875 isee your telegram Mq,6QQ of July 4th) Shaikh of Bahrain was informed that he should dissever himself entirely from affairs of Qjatar including Zubarah. 'ihey accordingly regret with reference to letter from Shaikh referred to in paragraph 2 of your telegram of July 4th that they are not prepared to intervene between Shaikh of Qatar and the mim I tribe • 3. /3» If UovertaBQnt of mdia agree and unless you see objection you should reply to Shaikh on these general lines, actual terms of ooranuni cation are of course left to your discretion. 4 # i assume you are keeping Air Officer comniandi ng and senior mval officer informed of situation. : -SECRETARY OF STATE FOR T1DIA*Telegram from To Repeated to Ho. 1602 19/243 q Government of India, External Affairs Depart ment, Simla. Political Hesident, isuahire• secretary of State for india, London. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 16th July received 17th July 1937 C Secretary of State»s telegram &amp;o. 1903 of July 15th. ZUBAHAH. 2. Reference paragraph 2. Government of India agree. GOVE RIME .NT 01? IWIA.- Te le gram From To Political resident, iiuahire. Political Agent, uaiirain. i»opy hypost to iseoretary of btate fn-p ' of Mo • T 51 ' ^ Dated 17 th July 1937, w Uorreapondeace ending with uovernment of India telegram Bo. 1602 of 16th July. ztTOjffiAH. Please adress letter to ahaikh of Bahrain quot ing hi a relevant references and stating that you have been directed by me to communicate to him the reply of Ma Majesty's Government. This would be as in paragraph 2 of India Offic telegram Mo. 1903 of 15th July. ^ Unb • HRITC0233UL. t |) I' • i Forwarded under p.i, Ho. 546 of 1? .7.37 to mdia Office and Govt, of india. 9:.. - -/•» '•'-if ■ i i-fM'inii it m 1 SI Translation o: 1 ' ? ette- catec the 26th r? .abt Than! 1356 (4.7.1937) from Shaikh A^cullah bin ' asi'i 4? Tbani, ■ G.I.^.5 ''uler of '-atar to Captain '''ickrnbotha^ Political Accent , Bahrain. O After Co '■a-iirnents. I hac ! the honour of receiving your letter dated 3rd July 1937 corresponding to 24th Eabl A1 Thani 1356 and, noted what v/as nentiored. by you. I know the obligations referred to by you and there is not at present any British subjects in the tovm. ■ fi th regard to the disturbed state of the country to which : ir ou have referred 7 shall • Cod willing, put an 1 end to these disturbances in any way T see necessary ^or&gt; t v e present condition so that, b the grace of Cod, ... tranauility and peace be restored. Usual Ending.m. 593/^-9A --of UfxicQ ol' the ..Uiviser to taa u-werciaent, Bahraaa. Datea, J/fliaay -27, July 6, 1937 Froei m io Ualrymple Jelpmve, ^s^uire, Mviser to the Goremaieat of Bahrain, Bahrain. His Britaanic Uaj©sty's Political ^at, . ihrai ii. ? I have the honour to iafStm you tk„l ids iiigliaess Shaikh 3ir Hamad- bin Isa al-^alifah, has asked me to ascertain from you whaa his claim to the ^ubara area will receive consideration and the matter will be examined. Ee wishes to obtain the best legal advice avail able to assist him to put forward Mo case and in order to do this he proposes to consult solicitors in London and to employ counsel. If necessary he is also prepared to send a representative to iiurope to act on his behalf. i have the honour to be, r % # lour moat obedient servant, .iuviser to the Government.f\\ CONFIDENTIAL. I /*j ;; 8') No. G/545-4/13 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident r . ■.■ii—iui.i.1 i nwaai OUSHIRE RES ' D ENCY. No.. Dato. ■■■. fir. 7:37. CONFlDE^TiAL RECORDS in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). ( 0- F T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G dlp. ✓ Dated ..ISth. .J.uly. .19.3.7 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency telegram No. 726 dated 11th July 1937. I | Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. fv Letter No.C/544 dated the 13th July 1937 from the Poli tical Agent, Bahrain, to His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain Subject. Zubarah.No. C/544-4/13 of 1957 Dated 13th July 1937. To His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'isa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I. f Ruler of Bahrain. After compliments: y\ ^ (; I have the honour to refer to Your Highness' letter of July the 1st in which you requested the British Government 'to restrain Shaikh Abdullah from making war against our subjects who live within our boundaries at Zubarah' and also to your Adviser's letter No. 593/SF-9A dated the 6th July asking when your claim to Zubarah will be considered and by who the matter will be examined. I have been instructed by the Honourable the Political Resident to inform Your Highness that he has referred your request to His Majesty's Government and that he hopes to be able to give you a reply shortly. Usual Ending. Sd.- T.Hickinbotham, Captain. Political Asent. Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. NOk C/553-4/13 in 5^ 1 / The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G olf. ■ ? I I 101 j I I Dated...^.^ Juiy.iaa?. Reference to previous correspondence : Q/f Y J Description o Name and Date. Political A^ent, Bahrain's'' note dated the 13th July 1937. 2. Statement dated the 13th July 1937 made by Shaikh Rashiji bin Muhammad, Chief of Nairn tribe. Subject. Zubarah.Shaikh of Bahrain called o* said that he you do if I to see I s&amp;U I was under &gt; n &lt;? g to ' QL a' few ^ rt * lBll&gt; tTebur. the leader IM t i to m that he hid of Qatar and that iie had agreed to obey the laws of Qatar utiile /s2 lat^r* 0iaiMi 1 Abdullah bin JassliB that he was at liberty to leave Qatar if he ges ikli of Qa that His of the country of the that he had left the Subsrah &lt;-u* rtxco. with his €* h he was living near Uma al ^i and that he was by the bedouins ^ao he stated were of/-) with regard to formed HisRaskld leaving his country, and to obey tils Zl to live orders*. His Highness that in ordei ■ I would, send Rash id -this in Qatar qy ening to t&amp;isie, s, note of' during the episode-fro a Siaiidi R&amp;shid* s 13 Sd/- T.H. &gt;37. •v . A &gt; ■:St at eiJient made by Shaikh Rashid bin Muhammad,, Chief of Nairn tribe. Recorded in the Palace at Bah rain on the 13th July 1937. We had at Thsghab in the Qasar 40 armed men. A messenger came from them saying that they were fear ful and that they wanted camels and water be sent to them so that they should ride and come to us. We sent S6 men mounted on camels and four horsemen as guards in order to bring them. When they reached near the Qasar Shaikh Abdullah's arn^y appeared. They were in cars and on horses (4 cars and about 30 Norsemen) and more than 250 camel riders. When our people saw Shaikh Abdullah's folloirers, they returned and did not go to the Qasar. On their return the cars and the horsemen overtook them so they were obliged to make their camels kneel down. Shaikh Abdullah's men fired on them and killed four men among them was ny buother Hamad bin Mxhammad. They also killed 4 horses, wounded three men and killed 24 camels. Then they captured the Qasar and demolished it. They also occupied the towns (Faraihah, Arish, Akhdai^ Qasr al Thaghab and Khuwair) took away all the foodstuff and plundered those who were from our followers, such as al Akbesah and Bu Ka'aban, carrying away their clothes, mattings, pots, cows, donkeys and the hair tents. They also tool? away the sails and the ropes of the boats. Afterwards Shaikh Abdullah marched and halted near Morair fort which belongs to Zubarah. One of the Arabs (Hasa' bin Khalil, Shaikh Hamad's man) wrote asking him (Shaikh Abdullah) to refrain from shed' ding the blood of the Muslims and also from demanding anything from them. He (Shaikh Abdullah) then sent a letter with his brother saying that he wanted to see me lAI interviewed him because our foodstuff had exhausted and the way was cut as Shaikh Abdullah stood between us and Bahrain, ihen I went to him in the camp Shaikh Abdullah told me that he would not give us security unless m have snrendered our ferms. We surrendered our arms as we were forced by hunger to do so and be cause we did not do anything as ordered by the Politi- wrtl Agent. Then they themselves wrote a document and took my seal and sealed it. it ran as follows:- II That as long as I am residing in Qatar I should not do anything against Shaikh Abdullah and should not fight with him and if I want to leave Qatar and go to any other place he will not prevent me and my followers and all connected to me such as property etc., to do so 11 . The property taken away from us by Shaikh Abdullah;- lhat I handed over personally to Muhammad bin Abdul Latif bin Mani« 9g rifles. Taken from the people of Thaghab 40 rifles, from Muhammad al Nafaihi 10 rifles, from Bu Kawwarah 12 rifles, from Ka»aban 11 rifles, from Haza* bin Khalil 3 rifles. Also taken 40 camels., 120 sheep, 100 donkeys. 10 camels were taken away by bedouins. Shaikh Abdullah sent horse men to pursue the bedouins and restore them, but they have not yet returned. These ten camels were taken away by Bedouins after the peace.a Extract of letter No . C/562-4/in dated th^ High ness Shaikh Sir Hama d Tin Tsn -ITlrhZTi Ruler of Bahrain After Compliments. letter No. 593/SF-9A dated the 6th July li I have been directed by the Honourable thfl to inform you of His Majesty's Government' raised by you. 2 » His Majesty's Governmenl for deciding questions regarding ownershi) 3. His Majesty's Governmeni ready to listen to any representation wh; on any matter which you regard as affectii the meantime His Majesty's Government fee.' that so long ago as 1875 the Ruler of Bah: informed that he should sever his connect; affairs of Qatar including Zubarah. His accordingly regret that with reference to the 1st July 1937, they are not prepared the Shaikh of Qatar and the Nairn tribe. I hiiv e the honour to ref h PoliticaNo. cy562-4/13 dated'the 19th .Tnly, 1Q37 tr&gt; xr* q Highness shaikh Sir T ^.i I k .! C.S?I.^ Ruler of Bahrain' 1 After Compliments. » rvf JL have the honour to refer to your Adviser's letter No. 593/SF-9A dated the 6th July 1937 and to state that I have been directed by the Honourable the political Resident to inform you of His Majesty's Government's reply/to the questions raised by you. 2• His Majesty's Government is the ultimate authority for deciding questions regarding ownership between Shaikhs. 3. His Majesty's Government are of course always m ready to listen to any representation which you may desire to submit on any matter which you regard as affecting your interests but in ' the meantime His Majesty's Government feel compelled to point out that so long ago as 1875 the Ruler of Bahrain at that time was informed that he should sever his connection entirely with the affairs of Qatar including Zubarah. His Majesty's Government accordingly regret that with reference to your letter dated the 1st July 1937, they are not prepared to intervene between \ the Shaikh of Qatar and the Nairn tribe. \ „ . r Usual Ending. political Agent, Bahrain.^-01 19/243 Telegram From G.T.C To Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire, at Shiraz. Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, Simla. Air Officer Commanding, Hinaidi. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Copy by,post to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1/114 Dated 24th July 1957. ZUBARAH. Shaikh Rashid of the Nairn has entered into an agreement with Ruler of Qatar to obey him as long as he resides in Qatar. g. This closes the dispute between the Shaikh of Qatar and the Nairn. FOWLE Forwarded under P.L. No. C/157 of * to Political Agent^ BahrainConfide ntiaX* D.CUNo.C /156 of 1957. I KJ (%o4 Office oi' the Political resident in the Persian Gull', at 5hiraz« Dated the 24th July, 1957• r Could you please reier to correspondence ending with my telegram l^o. T/114 dated the 24th wuly 19o7. According to itashid* s report the 'war' between tne isneiKh of Qatar and the Kaim all hulls down to one SJiirmi sn at A1 Tnasnab in which the Nairn lost 4 Killed and 5 wounded out of a total of ou, ana tne bneiiui of Qatar had at.his uiaposal some horsemen and 4 cars* caiiel riders, SC 1PI 2, It ^srould be interesting to itnow if the above figuxes are more or less correct, ana can you confiriu? Barly rumours indicated a large number of casualties, I ' ' ' ' more or less severe fighting, ana 7,000 men taking the field for the bheika of Qatar, see JUeptfords report Ho,1951 datea tne ord Jialy 19o7, wnich naturally only passed on local Arab gossip. 5. In one of the subsiaiary letters connected with the Qatar Oil Concession we promised the Bheikh assistance in case nis territory was invadea on a large scale from outsiae but stipulated that he woola nave to take his part to the best of his ability. It wouicx therefore be interesting to know now many armed men, judging from his Nairn operations, he could at a pinch put into the field and how many rounds per rifle. In the Leptfora telegram quoted above the number was given as ^0 rounds, which seems to me reasonable. Arab {sheikhs do not dish -/out c ^Ptain T. Hickinbotham, I.A. Political AKent» Bahrain.. ■ f I *</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000157_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/370</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000157</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/370</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/243 II (C 72) Zubarah'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-29T15:34:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (212 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>A bound correspondence file. Foliation starts on first page of text, top right hand circled number. Ends on last page in volume. A second foliation penciled, uncircled from folio 1a-209.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>File contains correspondence related to hostilities that occurred between the forces of Shaikh Abdullah bin Qassim Al Thani of Qatar and the Al Naim tribe that took place in June and July 1937.At this time, the Al Naim tribe was allied to the Al Khalifa ruling family of Bahrain who claimed Zubarah as a part of their own territory (the family had been based there before their conquest of Bahrain in 1783). The British authorities did not recognise the Al Khalifa's claim to Zubarah and did not intervene on their behalf. Hostilities ended in July 1937 and Shaikh Rashid bin Muhammad, Chief of the Al Naim tribe, agreed to recognise the rule of the Al Thani family over Zubarah.The file also contains a map of Qatar (folio 164) and four aerial photographs of Zubarah (folios 160-163).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Na'īm (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Thānī (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Zubarah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000157#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>