<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000247_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-03T10:44:11.978Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Pf SEEN VHAT GODS ORDER MAY PE. PLEASE COD I WILL GIVE NEWS TO SOME- ONF FLbF MLL AND THFN A G^EAT CALAMITY -VOULD HAPPEN ^ ^ ^ TO ALL. I THEREFORE ^RITE TO LET YOU KNOW OF TH K&gt; MATTER AND HOPE THAT IN LOME WAY OR OTHER I MAY BE GRANTED AID FROM THE BRITILH GOVERNMENT IN TH.b UNDERTAKING AND YOU ARE A TRIED AND TRUbTY SERVANT OF THAT GOVERNMENT. I AM AWARE THAI bUCH FELLOWSHIP AND FRIENDSHIP IN A MATTER OF THIS KIND HAS NEVER HITHERTO OCCURRED BETWEEN US NOR DOES IT EXIS. AND THEREFORE IF IT BE NOT POSSIBLE FOR ThE GOVERNMENT To GIVE ME ASSISTANCE IN THIS MATTER I PEG,AT LEAST, ThAT YOU VILL MOT GIVE ASSISTANCE AGAINST ME. IF I SIT APART FROM THESE PEOPLE AND DO NOT CO-OPERATE WITH THEM THERE IS NOT THE SLIGHTEST DOUBT BUT THAT SOME ONE ELSE ‘JILL JOIN FHf ANL , THE CHANCE, OF, RULE WILL ESCAPE ME,AND I AM AFRAID THE AFFAIR VILL ASSUME LARGE PROPORTIONS AND BECOME DIFFICULT FOR ALL P A R FIF S. THERE ORE WITH THE HELP OF GOD I PROPOSE TO MAKE AN ATTACK uUlCKLY WITH A NUMEROUS ARMY ANL WITH THE MEM ()F GOD. AS MUSCAT IS FULL O' BRITISH SUBJECTS AND THEY HAVE MUCH PROPERTY THERE,AND AS MY MINI IS IRREVOCABLY MADE UP, TO THIS ATTACK, ON ACCOUNT OF, THE (Jll)TREi»S OF TnE TRADERS, I FEAR LEST WHEN GOD HAS APPOINTED THE DAY AND I ATTACK MUSCAT IT WILL PE AN OPPORTUNITY FOR THE FOREIGN MERCENARIES TOWN AND THE ACCUSATION OF THESE AC T^ BE THROWN UPON MY TROOPS . FOR THIS REASON I PEG YOU WILL TELL MAJOR GAANT,POLITICAL AGENT \ 1 AT MUSCAT,THAT WHENEVER I GIVE HIM NOTICE THAT I AM ABOUT TO ATTACK MUSCAT HE SHOULD ORDER THE BRITISH SUBJECTS TO EMBARK ON THE SEA WITH THEIR PRO PER T f FOR A FEW UAYb UNTI L ITAI^Z-&lt;7 *I *</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000247_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/15</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000247</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/15</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Political'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1882/1882</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-11-16T18:03:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (61 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 63; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between Sayyid `Abd al-Aziz bin Sa'id, the Sultan of Oman's cousin and competitor, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf about Oman affairs. Specifically, the exchanges discuss whether the Sultan at the time, Faisal bin Turki, was fit to rule. The file also contains letters about a dispute between Arabs of Khasab and Kumzar and the 1882 Administration report and trade returns.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000247#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>