<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:48:33.779Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">: J . 2794/21 (4) &amp; (6) Bahrein oil concessions. P. 2794/21 (7) M 11 (Import Duties) P. 2734/21 (3) , : - t* it ii (Radio-telephones) ?. 27 94/21 (10) ' »» m (Oil Refinery). P. 2794/21 (12) tf If ff (Acquisition of land on Sitrah Island). Coll. 30/141 Persian Gulf - Proposed development of port of Ras Tanurah. Coll. 30/167 :- Persian Gulf Lights and Buoys - Bahrein: Buoyinc of approaches on Behalf of Bahrein Petroleum Co. Coll, 30/168 Persian Gulf Lights and Buoys - Proposed levy of light dues at Bahrein. Coll. 30/169 Persian Gulf Lights and Buoys - Buoying of approaches to Ras Tanurah on Behalf of California Arabian Standard Oil Company. Coll. 6/89 Saudi Arabia:- Approaches to Jedda Harbour - Interest of Standard Oil Company.,&lt;*&gt; M. 06515/38. • r ±1 Cn f\r , 7 '8 ■'338 J COKPI DiSNI 1 1AL. Military Branch ADMIRALTY, S. ¥• 1. m- { t&gt; 18th November, 1938. Dear Gibson, Will you please refer to your letter to y/z? Baggallay, F.Z.'i t Lie/38, of the 22nd October, concerning the approaches to Jedda Harbour. I have ascertained that the enquiries of the California Standard Oil Company at the Admiralty did not go beyond the inspection of certain charts which they could in fact have purchased. There is no ODjection to the approaches made from our point of view. As regards the further question of the advisability of the Oil Company improving the approaches to Jedda it appears to us that if they are prepared to spend money on such a project we could have no oojection. I am sending a copy of this letter to Baggallay. ’ S $ X *\ C \ J.P. Gibson, Ssq., INDIA OPPICS, 3. w. i.INDIA OFFICE REcsj. POL 19 NOV1938 Til1938 FOREIGN OFFICE, S. W. 1 4th November, 1938. (E 6240/438/25) My dear G-ibson, Many thanks for your letter of the 22nd October, about the Standard Oil Company’s wish to improve navigational facilities at Jedda. and do not see that we could have any ground for raising objection to an attempt by the Company to improve the harbour at Jedda. 3. As agreed on the telephone v/e have sent a copy of your letter and enclosure, and of this reply, to Starling at the Petroleum Department. o We entirely agree with the attitude you adopted, Yours ever. j NOV1938 INDiA OFFICEJ j. p Gibson, Esq.COPY Rear-Admiral J.A. Edgell, C.B., O.B.E., Hydrographer of the Navy The Admiralty, London, S.W.l. 14th October, 1938 Dear Sir, On October 24th we are expecting the arrival of I®-. J.C. Stirton, Chief Engineer of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company in San Francisoo. Mr. Stirton ex pects to spend a few days in London and then to proceed to Arabia where, among other things, he intends to familiarise himself with the Company's marine and terminal problems. It is very likely that Mr. Stirton will wish to have an opportunity to meet you while he is here and to have the benefit of any suggestions that you may care to give regarding these problems. He expects to be here about a week and Mr. Smith, of the Company's Marine Department, will be in London at the same time. I am sure we could arrange to call upon you at any time that might suit your convenience while they are here. The Company is considering the possibility of in stalling some storage tanks and other facilities at Djeddah and in this connection I have recently had a letter from Mir. Smith, who is now in Arabia, in which he says that in look ing over the charts for that vicinity he notes a considerablearea to the TTorth of the town that seems to be either sur veyed incompletely or to be rather free from coral shoals. Does the Admiralty have any unpublished data on the area concerned which Mr. Stirton and Mr. Smith might have an opportunity to examine. Mr. Smith has also asked me whether I can secure any information about the waters in the vicinity of the mouth of the Koeboe river in Sumatra. Can you possibly help me in any way in this respect? Yours faithfully, for CALIFORNIA STANDARD OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. R.L. If you could conveniently see Mr. Stirton and Mr. Smith while they are here, I am sure they would appreciate it very much. The questions I have raised regarding Djeddah and Sumatra could be dealt with at that time and I am merely mentioning them now so that if you can see Mr. Stirton and Mr. Smith you can be anticipating some of the questions they may wish to ask you. cc - Mr. H.R.Ballantyne, London RL/T.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2161</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2161</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/89 'Saudi Arabia: Approaches to Jedda Harbour. Interest of Standard Oil Co.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-23T09:59:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the California Arabian Standard Oil Company's interest in erecting storage tanks at Jedda, which would involve making improvements to the harbour's navigational facilities in the process. The file features the following correspondents: the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, the India Office, the Foreign Office, and the Admiralty's Military Branch.Also included is a list of several other Political and Secret Department files, most of which appear to also relate to the construction or improvement of port facilities or infrastructure.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Storage facilities</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty Secretariat, Military Branch</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Jedda</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002bc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>