<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000147_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T04:38:26.760Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">h /T- CONFIDENTIAL. j-— - ■ -i.i iwoiOuMUY. 3 i' ^ Ho. Date.. Xi/ffay co^f:dewt3aFrecoros No. C/485-4/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th June 1957- ^ - 'ii From Captain T. Hiekinbotham, I,A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to refer to iqy letter No. C/ 430-4/1 dated the 4th June 1937 forwarding copies in triplicate of the Bahrain State Budget Estimate for the year 1556. 8. I regret that I have been unable to comment be fore on the Budget as I had not the necessary file with me on tour at Sharjah and therefore delayed a careful investigation until I returned to Bahrain. 3. Please refer jtcr* paragraph 5 of Mr. Belgrave's letter No. 435/SF dated the 31st May 1937 forwarding the Budget Estimate, 'Notes on 1355 Expenditure*. It will be seen that out of the budgetted expenditure in the 1355 Budget for Rs. 9,36,000/- an amount of Rs.9,22,000/- has been expended. In addition to this there has been a further expenditure of Rs. 1,64,000/- for which pro vision was made in the Supplementary Budget for Special Projects of the year 1355. There is, however, a further expenditure of Rs. 69,000/- for which no budget allotment was/- /I II 0 ' ^ I 3 --8- was madpsin 1355• Mr. Belgrave points out that on page 5 of his Budget Report for 1356 he envisaged a further expenditure under the head Supplementary Bud— get. A reference to his statement at the top of page of the Budget Report for 1355 (forwarded with my letter Ho. C/267-4/1 dated the 29th May 1936) shows that a sum of Rs. 1,11^000/— was set aside for unfore seen expenditure or to be expended later by another Supplementary Budget, and presumably this sum of Rs. 69,000/- has been expended from that sum. A sum of Rs. 1,11,000/- is naich too large a sum to set aside for unforeseen expenditure and when it was intended to expend a sum of Rs. 63,000/- from this amount a further Supplementary Budget should have been prepared. With regard to the item of Rs. 56,000/- which was spent on the new customs house and enlarging the pier space, I note that in the Supplementary Estimate for Special Projects for 1355 under Public Works a sum of only Rs. 35,000/- was estimated for the new customs house. The amount expended, therefore, shows an in crease of Rs. 21,000/-, This amount should have been foreseen as it is an increase of 60^ on the original budget allotment. There is an item of Rs. 49,000/- whlch was spent on building shops on Government land in the bazaar, on two new dispensaries, a barrack room at the Fort, a wall round the Manamah Palace, reclama tion of the sewer in Hedd and various other works. According to the Special Projects Estimate, the only items budgetted for appear to be the barrack room at the Fort, the Palace wall, three dispensaries under ar id the building of the sewer at Hedd. The total/-3® -3- total amount budgetted for for these projects amDunt to Rs. 22,500/- whereas an item of Rs. 49,000/- as previous ly pointed out has been expended. There is again a tre mendous increase of expenditure over Estimate. There are various other items of like nature which could be pointed out but I think the above illustrate a point which I shall make later in this letter. y . c * 4. Turning to the statement of Revenue and Expenditure ft •' for the year 1S55 which forms an enclosure to ngr letter^ under reference it will be noted under Expenditure - State Protection, there is an expenditure of Rs. 1,67,356-3-11 whereas the budget allotment under this item for 1355 was Rs» l,40,000/-» There has been an increase of Rs. 27,956—3—11. Similar increases can be noted under such heads as Customs Department, Medical Services, Contingen cies, etcetera. I could find no note in Mr. Belgrave's Report to explain how these increases have occurred and on what the money has been expended. 5. For a Budget to be of any value it should show as nearly as possible the amount that it is expected to re ceive from income and the amount it is anticipated will be spent on the general running of the State. There must necessarily be two forms of Expenditure i.e. Recurring Ex penditure and Non-recurring Expenditure and I think that these two categories should be kept apart so that it should be possible to see at a glance exactly how much it is ex pected will be required for the normal running of the State and hov/ much it is intended to spend on Special Projects. In the present Budget it is true that the Special Projects have been put together at the bottom of the page which deals with Expenditure for 1356 but there/tTeems to me to ' - fi, I'? *' ■© It ■ ^ !■ be a tendency to Include special works in the current expenditure. For instance, there is no indication that the amount of Rs. 1,67,956/- which has been expended on State Protection is solely a Recurring Expenditure, It is possible that the increases already noted in my para graph 3 may be a Non-recurring Expenditure or it may be that the increase is due to an increase in personnel. Again it may be noted that the expenditure on State Pro tection is now estimated to be Rs. 7,956-3-11 less than it was in 1355 and there is no explanation why this is so. I consider that the Budget as at present submitted is not satisfactory and there appears to be a tendency on the part of the Bahrain Government to depart from the Budget figures on the Slightest excuse whereas Budget fi gures should only be departed from after careful consi deration and for matters of extreme urgency. The Budget should be much more accurate than it is at the moment and when a report is submitted regarding the Expenditure of the previous year and the estimated Expenditure of the present year it should clearly show variations which have occurred in the previous year 1 s expenditure and should give clear explanations of the causes thereof and at the same time there should be an explanation of any estimated increase or decrease in Expenditure for the current year. 6, I have not discussed this matter with Mr, Belgrave before addressing you on the sub.lect as I thought it desi rable to put my point of view to you before raising it with the Bahrain Government. My own inclination would be to return the present Budget asking for explanations for the variations in expenditure over estimated expenditure for the/-the year 1355 and also requesting the Bahrain Govern ment to explain the increases or decreases in the pre sent year 1 s Budget. At the same time I think it would be desirable to point out to the Bahrain Government that they should consider very carefully the question of departing from the Budget Estimate, in previous years when the Revenue was small it was probably neces sary to have a very elastic Budget but now when the Revenue is increasing^ all the expenditure under recur ring heads can be accurately foreseen and I see no reason why the Budget should not give a fair estimate of the amount that it is intended to spend during the current year under the various heads* In view of the yearly increase in the Oil revenue it is not possible for the Bahrain Government to forecast with any degree of accuracy the gross income, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, ' Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.IV/ u mw?IIiaH'TIAL . U j I jt /y f. I 1 From K© •© • 2564-1/37. T© The Deputy Secretary to the Government of Indii in the External Affairs Department» The Hon t 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf» Dated SIMIA the ? July 19 37. Sir, BAHRAIN STATS BUDGET FOR THE ARABIC YEAR 1356 » I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your memorandum iro»459—S of 19 37, dated the I4tii June 1937, forwarding the Bahrain State budget for the Arabic year 1356, and to say that the Government of India note with satisfaction the continued improvement in the financial position of the Bahrain State. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the Gover/ment of India. (k*, p. L. Vo . i£\ 0 -S S. 37 K ip, ft. float- ^ S-c * x i*CONFIDENTIAL. No- 0/556-4/2, h nt&gt; 1 ^ (!) / The Political Agent, Balirain, presents his compliments to :■ :H!RE RESIDENCY The Honourable the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bushlre. | t 0 ^ Date.. qb.t .11:1:51.. CONFIDENTIAL records and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Peesian Gulp. Dated. 1? th. .CCUrly. .1QS, Eeference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. Statement of Revenue of the Bahrain Government for the of the Arabic Year 1956 . (=l^th and Expenditure first three months larch to 9th June 19S7) Subject.^ /3 Air Mail. gonf ideat ial. The Residency# Buehire, the 24th August, 1937* T). Q.Ho«635»3» IL Could you please refer to correspondence ending with sir Trenchard ?ov»le*8 demi-official letCer N d .567-^, dated the 2nd August 1937, regarding Bahrain State 'budget Estimate for the Arabic year 1356# I am desired to enclose for your caament a copy of a note dated the 2l8t August 1J37 by Mr* Oaroe on the subject. AW Captain T.Hickinbothara,lA.• Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi. %lit Note dated tne 21st August 1937 by O.K.Garoe Esquire, CIE.» Officiating Political Resident in tiie Persian Ciuli. Subject: Bahrain State Budget Estimate for the Arabic year 1356. There seems to be no process - (a) for watching progress of actuals against allotments; (b) fcr securing sanction to excess expenditure; (c) for audit generally; Or is the new Treasury Officer to do all this ? With the vast increase of prosperity in Bahrain, reflect ed in budgets which suggest that expenditure will be hard put to it to keep place with income, it seems essential to get Bahrain finances strictly overhauled and placed on a more regular lystem. Sir Trenchard Fowle touched on this in a conversation with Mr.Belgrave and myself just before his departure on leave, and I will try to make an opportunity for seme discussion with Mr. Belgrave during the coming months. The point to remember is that there is perhaps more peril, though of a different sort, in bursting money-^ags than in empty ones. One sugges tion was to put an Officer wiith experience of the control of finance in Indian States on specikl duty to overhaul Bahrain administrative organization. A copy of this note might be sent by demi-official letter to Captain Hickinbotham for ccrament. Id. O.K.Caroe.o ® li /i&gt; D.O. No. T/124-4/1. With reference to yc ember 1^37. s!-:' r ^ n?J imcy. • V fAUv** Date. 2 '- T - 37 cpFi^J':: ^, . , . , ., - Fial Assistant's demi-official letter No. 635-S dated August 24th 1937. I am entirely in agreement with the views put forward in your note of the 21st August. There is no system in Bahrain and there is much too much money being dealt with now to permit of the old method of budgeting being continued with safety. The new accounts man would be quite capable of running a system but I am doubtful if he will be able to initiate one. I suggest that a skilled accountant be obtained for a short period to overhaul the system as you suggest and if the Government of India cannot produce anyone then possibly the Colonial Office might be able to provide a man from Palestine or Trans-Jordan. They have a special finance service I believe and would be accustomed to dealing with the finance of small places like Bahrain. We must avoid becoming over officered like Zanzibar was and I do not advise the creation of any more permanent posts. The Honourable Mr. O.K. Garoe, G.I.E./I.C.S., Political Resident in the Persian Qulf» BushireV CONFIDENTIAL. No ' C/6 72-4/1 n I/it BUSH1RE RESIDENCY. fa). Date. •5: CONFIDENTIAL RECOSDS The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Golf. Dated September 1937 Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. STATEMENT OF REVENUE UNDER PERIOD ENDING JMAD-AL-THl COMPARED WITH THE SANCTION 1356 OF THE BAHRAIN GOBERl Subject. BUDGET HEADS FOR THE SI, 1356 (6 MONTHS) ED BUDGET FOR YEAR MENT. |«$i V&gt; NV v v Confidential, D.O.No,0/856-6/4 /3 (X^Xxt ; Date | co. :.. fUL | The 13th November 1937. m The other day while I was looking into the question of the creation of a State Reserve Fund it struck me, as no doubt it has struck everyone else, that a very difficult situation may arise when the flow of oil royalties ceases by reason of the simple fact that His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain may be unable 6r may decline to readjust himself to the four or five lakh standard of living after the plea sures of a 15 lakh interval. Accordingly I enquired from Belgrave whether His Highness is putting anything aside J* from his share of the royalties and he told me, much to my relief, that he had induced the Shaikh to invest 5 lakhs this year. It may be remarked in parenthesis that His High ness is thoroughly disgusted with the miserable interest accruing from British Government Stock as he had apparently expected at least 10 per cent on his money' However, the money has been invested this year, and Belgrave intends to do his best to induce His Highness to continue the good work in future. So long as he is successful it is, of course, neither necessary nor desirable that we should butt in officially; but I suggest that we should make unofficial enquiries every year from Belgrave and should be prepared, if His Highness declines Belgrave's advice, to exert all possible effort ourselves to ensure a steadily mounting private reserve. 2. Though no action is necessary at present, it is, I think, desirable to ensure that this particular matter is kept prominently in view. 'he Hon'ble Mr. O.K. Caroe, C.I.E., I.C.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire,I found| on my first examination of the Bahrain State Finances} that no very serious attempt had been made to put on paper an estimate of the amount of money which the State would draw in the form of royalties from the Bahrain Petroleum Company or to prepare a preliminary programme for the purpose of building up a Reserve against the day when oil ceases to flow and for the expansion of public services meanwhile. It is clearly impossible for any progress to be made so long as these matters are dealt with in a haphazard fashion without any definite objective, and without a clear realisation of the amount of money that may bee cane available from time to time. ..v I have 9 therefore, recorded the attached note which is intended to be a preliminary effort to clear the air. I have throughout taken the most pessimistic view pos sible and I have little doubt in my own mind that the sums which will come to the State in the form of royal ties will very greatly exceed the figures which I have adopted. In the first place the estimate of a 15 year life for the oil field as its present boring depth is, I believe, far behind the expectations entertained by the Company themselves; though it is impossible to in duce anyone in the Company to offer anything like a firm opinion. Quite apart from this, even Mr. Deacon is pre pared to admit that the deep boring so far undertaken is really hopeful, and I understand that three more deep bores are to be undertaken feero in the near future. Then again I have made allowances for local consumption of oil (on which royalty is not paid) fa ' in excess of the average quantity so used up-to-date. Similarly I have assumed as an average future State income from sources/--2« sources other than oil a figure lower than any reach ed in the past? and it is hard to believe that condi tions will ever 'be quite as bad as they were round about 1932, Finally I have assumed a rate of interest from investments which should be exceeded by at least and possibly without much difficulty# I might further mention that at the present moment there is a sum of Hs, 10 lakhs in the so-called Consolidated Fund (a sort of Treasury Reserve) t which together with the royalty investments due before the end of the financial year will make it possible to invest at least Rs. 15 lakhs more this year, making a total investment for the first 'effective' year of no less than Rs. 20 lakhs* 2. I contemplate, therefore, that within a compa ratively short space of time it will be possible revise my figures upwards quite considerably. Never theless I have thought it desirable for immediate purposes to take extremely conservative figures, and as will be seen, even these show as much money as can be comfortably handled to begin with* 3. Once some estimates have received official or even semi-official approval, it will be possible to commend them to the Bahrain Administration and to press them to undertake the preparation of a consider ed scheme of expansion of their public services. As I have suggested above it is hopeless to attack the problem piecemeal and in a haphazard manner, parti cularly here in Bahrain where the Administration is accustomed to living more or less from hand to mouth and where the habit of spending generously though wisely has not yet been assimilated. It is at the same time essential that the A'dviser should have an Assistant/--3- Aasistant with the least possible delay in order to relieve him of routine detail, which at present oc cupies an absurdly high percentage of his time# It is most important that he should have sufficient lei sure to enable him to prepare intelligent programmes of expansion and to ensure that real value is obtain ed for the very considerable sums of money which must be expended in the immediate future. I under stand that an offer has been made by India of a Police Officer for this purpose and I need only say here that I trust there will be no undue delay till he arrives to take up his duties in Bahrain. 4. I should have mentioned above that I have discussed my figures with Mr. Belgrave and that he is in substantial agreement with my estimates. 22nd November 1937.% M Formation of a Reserve Fund for Bahrain. 0O0 ♦ The indica tions at pre sent are fairly hopeful. X. Data . ♦ (a) Excluding the possibility of new oil deposits being found at greater depths than the present pro ducing wells and of other deposits in the Unallotted Area, we must first make a guess at the possible yield ffom the existing Bapco Field. Bapco people are very chary of offering any estimate f but we have the following &lt;i) A Refinery is already workingf capable of dealing with roughly one million tons of oil per annum, and it seems to be the general impression that it will be working for fully 15 years. Actual ly the indications are that more than one million tons of crude oil will pass through the guages this year, and consequently a million tons a year is pro bably a minimum figure. It is believed that the Com pany has sunk £4 millions, and they would not have done that if they feared any possibility of an early dry-up. Thus allowing for a minimum yield of one million tons for 15 years, royalty on 15 million tons (allowing for deductions for local use) can be put at Rs. 440 lakhs. (ii) In January 1937 Colonel Loch was told by Mr. Herron, President of Bapco, that the estimated amount of oil available was 100,000,000 barrels. Incidentally he himself estimated the life of the field at 15 to 20 years, confirming the assumption made in (i) above. Again allowing for local use, we might convert Kr. Herron 1 s figure into 12£ mil lion tons paying royalty. This again gives a rough total of 440 lakhs of rupees in royalty. (b)(i)/-III./- i (n&gt; i trnQm (to) I (i) In the worst year I can find, Bahrain - State income from all sources excluding oil was I amounted to Hs* 6 t 71 # 000# We should, therefore, be safe in taking Rs, 6^ lakhs as the worst pro bable income when oil closes down. (ii) Excluding special items of new expendi ture (non-recurring) and His Highness* share of oil royalties, the current year 1 s expenditure bud get is roughly Rs. 10 lakhs# This budget was framed in the comfortable knowledge that there would be is no shortage of money and A -herefore not a 'pinched' budget. But expansion of Public Health, Agricul ture and Education Departments — and probably Public Works (recurring) is inevitable and a nor mal expenditure budget should not be anticipated at less than Rs. 12£ lakhs. This will allow for something to come and go on, but seems to me a fair figure. IX. Deductions # (a) It follows from (b)(i) and (ii) above that Bahrain, to be on the safe side, requires an additional permanent Income of R#. 6 Xakhs per annum. (b) If Government stocks or other gilt-edged ♦ + Present invest- (trust) securities can be purchased to yield 8% ments yield 3^%. on capital, the sum to be invested in order to pro duce an income of Rs# 6 lakhs is roughly Rs# 200 • . *' : , rj lakhs. Existing investments total roughly Rs# 13 lakhs leaving Rs. 187 lakhs to go . (c) The expected minimum total royalty is Rs# 440 lakhs, of which ^ goes to His Highness the Shaikh, leaving roughly Rs. 293 lakhs for the State.-3- @ ii Adviser con firms this figure. Rs. 3! lakhs on Adviser's compu tation. III. Other Considerationa . A. It is clear from the above that given freedom from war, premature failure of the oil field or other major calamity, the future of Bah rain can b e comfortably assured. But we have not yet considered what portion of the royalties is required for current expenditure while the Reserve is being built up. Though we might accept the figure in I(b)(ii) above for normal recurring expenditure during this period — i.e. Rs. X2&amp; lakhs, we can safely take a better figure than that in I(b)(i) for income. During the period now under consideration oil will be flowing and money will be easy in Bahrain. Consequently Cus toms receipts will be high, in fact pretty well what they are at present. I should estimate nor mal income from all sources except oil to average % not less than Rs. lakhs (more probably Rs. 9 lakhs) per annum during this period. Thus, to meet the average expenditure budget of Rs. 12j lakhs, Bahrain must divert Rs. 4 lakhs annually from oil royalties. This is, as suggested above, probably more than is actually necessary but could be regarded as an outside figure. B. It is clear enough that heavy non-recur ring expenditure must be contemplated in the next few years. There is much to do in improving Pub lic Health (Sanitation, Hospitals etc) Agriculture, Communications and Education. Not only is it right to spend freely on such services, but circumstances will drive the Bahrain Government to do so. There will be pressure both from outside and from within, and the safe course, which no doubt coincides with inclination/-V/- Alternatively Hs. 3§ lakhs and Hs* 3 lakhs, ♦ i.e. excluding His Highness* share. inclination, is to forestall criticism or agita tion. It may take some time to work out program mes, but to begin with it would be as well to con* template an annual expenditure for several years of Hs. 2%lakhs on new schemes. Actually the figure may vary greatly from year to year, but I suggest this as a working figure. C. It follows then that while the Reserve is being created over a period of - say - 15 years, the State will probably be charging an average of ♦ ♦ Hs. 4 lakhs plus Es. 2^ lakhs against (i) oil ro yalties and (ii) interest on invested royalties (the latter being an annual^ increasing sum). IV. Suggestions . I suggest therefore that, for the purpose of framing a programme, the following assumptions be drawn: - 1. Total State* receipts from Royalties over probable period of 15 years # « # # • 2. Total sum required for investment, « 3. Total sum required to balance budget during 'building' period of 15 years. « 4. Total sum available from Royalties for expenditure during period in which Re serve is being created. 5. Expected total interest in same period on invest ments (not including sum Invested to end of last financial year as this is already taken into account in current budget) - not less than , 6. Balance (4 plus 5 minus 3) wKksdts&amp;±K±scmdatMfor unfore seen liabilities and defici encies - roughly ., Rs.293 Lakhs Rs.187 lakhs Hs. 97£ lakhs. Rs.106 lakhs Hs. 40 lakhs Hs. 49 lakhs.V. Final Hemarks . It is unlikely that the flow of receipts from oil royalties will b e a steady figure every year and the length of life of the field,apart from the guess work involved, clearly depends on the vol ume of oil extracted annually which in turn depends on markets and numerous other factors# Thus some adjustment will b e necessary every year in the amount to be invested, but it seems clear that the figures to b e aimed at are t~ 1* Diversion of a maximum of Hs. lakhs annually from royalties for current expenditure, until increasing receipts from investments make it possible to effect a progressive reduction in this figure. 2. Investment of Hs. 14 lakhs annually as a minimum average figure. It may be difficult to reach this figure in the first year or two, but ^ should be exceeded by a progressively increasing sum thereafter as the flow of interest accelerates. At this average, the requisite reserve figure will be reached in just over 13 years, thus providing an additional factor of safety. 3. At a fairly early stage it might be con sidered whether say Rs. 20 lakhs or the surplus of He. 49 lakhs assumed in IV (6) above should not be anticipated and invested in agriculture (improvement and conservation of land and water) in the definite expectation of - say - a 2%% return. This might involve some small postponement of 'security invest ments' but not necessarily if oil production exceeds average in the early years, as appears probable. Even so, there should be a balance of Hs. 29 lakhs which can be used for useful purposes such as macadamising all/-@ -6- all roads in Towns | and possibly all through the two Islands. The above can, I think, be reasonably re garded as the most pessimistic possible fo ecast. The present oil field may well be 100% more pro ductive than assumed, and deeper boring may also double p oduction. But more optimistic forecasts should await events and for the-^ime being there is as much money in sight as can/comfortably handled. Jd . (4 • fa ■ 22-11-37. ^ &lt; ^' u ^ Q kvw . ^ d u l-e-P-kKo —^AJC_ ,fl^ CONFIDENTIAL . njnh Xo - C/S98-4/1 BUSH I RE RES IDENCY /fyo' Date COWFiOENTJAL RECORDS^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Peesian Gulp. Dated.. 193?. Reference to previous correspondence : Description Name and Date. 1, Memorandum No.C/881-4/1 dated the 30th November 1937 to the Adviser to the Bahrain Goveriji nuant, 2. Letter No. 1450/2-B dated the 8th 3ecember 1937 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Go vernment. S £ Subject. Formation of a Reserve Fund for the Bahrain Adrainistration.--. @ Copy of memorandum No. C/S81-4/1 dated the 30th November 1937 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Formation of a Reserve Fund for the j- „ ^ Bahrain Administration, * ^ I have already sent you unofficially a copy of a Note dated the 22nd November 1937 which I record ed on the above subject, and we had some conversation with the Political Resident on the subject yesterday, 2. I should be obliged if you would be good enough to inform me officially whether the Bahrain Government accept the conclusions drawn in my Note, and are in general agreement with the figures which I have suggest ed. Stu.t- 'UQ ^ bucUa* ^ ^ ^&gt;'0 * S ( ffi • CHud, ' &lt;A. ,Copy of letter No. 1450/2-B dated the 8th December 1937 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Govern ment to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note on the formation of a Reserve Fund for the Bahrain Government. I agree with the conclusions drawn in the note and the figures which you have suggested. C&amp;fiy Stoi--tfc C| ^ X-eUa as* O'C. \f.. 8 J i-i 5 , Jia.U.oLNt&gt;. C/100-4/1. ConfidentM 3U BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. /Vo Date M CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS Tlie Political Ageut, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to : The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send Mm a copy of the nnderxnentioned document ( b ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Da ted 5 th - Februar y 193-8, Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Name and Date. 1. Statement of Revenue and Expendjl ture at end of Ramadhan 1356 (9 months). ; 2. Memorandum No. G/85 dated the 1 29th January 1938 to the Advi ser to the Bahrain Government, 3. Memorandum No. 1779/3.P. dated the 31st January 1938 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Govern ment. Subject, Bahrain State - Finances3? Copy of memorandum No. C/85-4/1 dated the 29th January 1938 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Adviser tothe Bahrain Government, Bahrain. •ith reference to your Financial Statements for the period ending Hamadhan 1356, I would request that, if you have no objection, you will be good enough to let me have a few comments on the following items where there is a substantial variation from budget figures. Would you also inform me in each case whether it is anticipated that the excess or short age will be adjusted before the close of the year? Expenditure Budget . 1. btate Protection ... Excess Fs 9837 2. Secretariat Department... Short Rs 16299 . j . iiledical Services ... Short Rs 8853 4. Contingencies ... Excess Rs . 8885 _ Would you be good enough to Inform me of the obiects on which expenditure under this head is incurred and, in view ot the excess over the budgetted figure for the whole year, how expenaiture is allocated between this head and 'Un'^o^e- seen Expenditure'? o. bnforeseen Expenditure... Excess Rs 37990 6. Special Projects &amp; Public Works. Short Rs 53454 Am 1 right in presuming that this is due to the lack af progress witn the project for a new palace? 7. Iran sport Department ... Excess Rs 7777 -his is apparently a new budget head inserted since ™?,n P ?r tl0 V f ^ he B ^ d f et forth ® y ear I would re! quest a xew explanat/ory details• 2. The two other new heads In the Expenditure Budget, namely Electric Department (feeoverable) and New Vegetable Market (re coverable from H.H. Shaikh Hamad) apparently relate to Recover able Loans, vide the Statement of Revenue and Expenditure, and should therefore properly not be included in the Statement of Expenditure under Budget heads, 3A.Uo 3. In the Revenue Statement I observe that heads ii, iii and iv in the statement attached to your letter Fo. 435/SF l ^ated the 31st May 1937 do not appear. Is this due to the fact that up-to- date there have been no receipts? 4, In regard ' lo the Balance, would you be good enough to in form me whether any d ecision has yet b een taken in regard to the possible investment before the end of the year of some part of the present Consolidated Fund amounting to Hs. 9 lakhs odd.Copy of memorandum No„ 1779/3F dated the 31st January 1938 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. With reference to your memorandum No, C/85-4/1 dated 29th January 1938 I am giving below my comments on the items where there is some substantial variation from budget figures. (1) State protection. The present excess is owing to the increase in the strength of the police by about 19 men also the purchase of new tents for which no allocation was made in last year's budget. The expenditure under this heading will show a consider ably greater excess over the budget figures by the end of the year as it will include the cost of the new rifles and ammuni tion amounting to over is, 40,000/-. (2) Secretariat Department . Provision was made in the last budget for the pay of an Accounts Officel? and a Factor to His Highness for the whole year. These two persons were not enlisted until about four months ago. Provision was also made for some additional staff which was not engaged. The short age under this heading will be partly adjusted by the end of the year. (3) Medical Services . The allocation for cost of medicine etc was much in excess of the actual amount spent. When prepar ing the budget allowance was made for expansion in medical ser vices which, owing to lack of staff, did not take place to the extent which^was expected. The shortage will be somewhat reduced if the cost of the malaria expert is paid during the current year. (4) Contin gencies . This item normally covers stationery, office equipment and furniture, printing and revenue stamps etc. -tn addition oo normal furniture etc. the government pur chased steel filing cabinets for the law courts and the Land Department/-Department and goverment offices to replace loose wooden shelves, costing approximately Rs. 5000/-. During the year all proclamations have been printed soci instead of being hand written or typed. The excess under this heading is likely to be about Rs. 5000/- at the end of the year. (5) Unforeseen Expenditure . This includes cost of audi tor Rs. 4000/-, certain bills outstanding in connection with His Highness' visit to England, Hs 3500/-, cost of a new launch used by the Quarantine Medical Officer Rs. 4700/-, grants made by the Government for building the Juma mosque ard Ras Ruman mosque Rs. ^UuO/-, payment of cost of land acquired from an indi vidual and included in land sold to His Majesty's Government Rs. 8200/-, and certain sums paid by order of His Highness as compensation to persons whose property and belongings were des troyed in Qatar, this amount was approximately Rs 23000/-. ^ ^ Special pr ojects and public works . One lakh v/as allo cated for the construction of a new palace and one lakh for new hospital. No work was done on the palace but ?/ork on hospital was commenced after the 9th month of the year. As it v/as deci- ded that ohe palace should not be built certain other public works were commenced including, two flats above the law courts, school workshops, Budeya School, a new girls' school in Maharaq, transport garage, additions to old customs building now convert ed into a Rest House and police station, rebuilding tov/er and walls of the Fort. The shortage under this head will be less at the end of the year than as shown at present, .^ansport Department. This consists of the new govern ment garages in charge of a motor engineer who deals with all to overnruent and municipal motor vehicles including the fire en- gine, roller etc. Previously all vehicles were attended to by local motor-dealers which was xat most unsatisfactory. With/-US ■3- Sith reference to your paragraph 3. r-earling licenses boat licences and miscellaneous revenue collected by the Cus toms Department are shown under one heading as 'Customs Collect ions' . The total shown in the budget for revenue from these sources is Rs» 700)000/-. Reference paragraph 4. Since the statement for the nine months was compiled a further Rs. 200,000/- has been invested increasing the amount invested during the current year to Rs. 16,00,000/-. It is proposed to invest a further Rs. 300,000/- before the end of the year.Ub Confidential . j ^ j f I Political Agency, No. C/323-4/1. Bahrain, the 19th May 1938. hp o i- From H, Weightman, Esquire, I,C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. N$. Dite.. 1 cmfidential rectrds To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Sir, I have the honour to forward here¥/ith a copy of a 'LettevNo. 557-21 dated the 15th May 1938 received from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, together with a copy of th© Bahrain State Budget for the year 1357. 2. In the absence of the report on last year's Revenue and Expenditure and the note on the activities of the various departments it is a little difficult to criticise the Budget in detail, but I make the following preliminary remarks, which will be subject to revision on receipt of the Adviser's annual report. 3. In the first place it will be observed that the Budget heads have been changed somewhat, and I think it is undoubt edly a change for the better, since they serve to set forth more clearly the different sources of income and the services and objects on which the income is expended. The totals on both sides of the Budget are almost fantastically in excess of previous figures due to the great increase in receipts under Oil Royalties, and to the consequent expansion of the public services. 4. So far as the main heads of the Revenue Budget are concerned, I have not much to say. I consider that the figure taken for Oil Royalty is quite considerably under- il estimated, since actual receipts from the last two half \c : *1^ u' yearly/- ^ v^ e ■j. •+@ u-1 -2- yearly royalty payments have aggregated Rs. 34,34,000/-, and I should be surprised if the next payments showed a de cline. Revenue under head II. Customs Receipts is estimated some Rs. 3,40,000 more than last year, 'but judging by the monthly average actuals for the first nine months of 1356 the estimate of Rs. 10,00,000 is more than fully justified. I venture to suggest that the figure taken under the head Customs Duty should be of particular interest to the Govern ment of India as indicating the existence of an expanding market in Bahrain, of which India might well take fuller advantage t han it has done hitherto. 5. The Expenditure Budget is obviously an expansion bud get. With the single exception of the figure under head Kb) Allowance to the Ruling Family — Civil List, where there is an unexplained increase of Rs. 36,000 I see no cause to cri ticise any of the figures taken on the ground that they are too high. My only fear is that the Public Works programme may not be completed within the momths, and were it not for that apprehension I should have felt it my duty to ad vise the Bahrain Government to increase their budget allot ment under the head ,! C - ROADS - Metalling of Roads in Mana- mah' in the Schedule of Public Works. I do not, however, exclude the possibility that in the course of the year part of the Public Works funds under the Schedule head 'A - NEW WORKS - MAJOR' may be diverted to this particular sub-head. The increased provision under major head II Adminis trative Services reflects the increased activities of the Bahrain Government end is not in my opinion excessive for present requirements, though in due course I anticipate that it should be possible to e ffect some reduction under this head/--3- head when new services and departments reach equilibrium,. Similarly the figure under major head III Public Health includes a considerable sum for equipping the new hospital and consequently does not represent the true cost of the Medical Department, I should anticipate that the ultimate recurring cost of this department willb e in the neighbourhood of Rs. 1,00,000, this being on the assumption that the anti-malarial measures in prospect are suffi ciently successful to justify comparatively small future expenditure under this head to maintain permanently the stand ard of immunity which it is hoped will result from these mea sures. Under major head VI Education there is a very large increase in the funds provided. I find it difficult at this stage to make any forecast of normal expenditure in future and I must content myself with observing that improvements in Education are being financed on a generous scale. In regard to the provision under maj or head VIII Pub lic Works I need only say that the list of works detailed in the Schedule contains no single item which is not urgently ne cessary. This remark applies even to the first item of Rs. 1,30,000 for a new Palace. As you are aware His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad has never been enamoured of the Qudhaibiyah Palace and there can be no doubt that very adequate use can be made of that building by the State if another palace is built more to the liking of the Shaikh. The programme of work listed for the current year is, I think, within the capa city of the existing Bahrain Government organisation, though there can be little doubt that in the near future it will be necessary to call in outside advice and assistance in dealing with the closely inter-related problems which must necessarily arise/-l-f 1 -4- arise in regard to irrigation (i.e. production of water), control of water so used (i.e. anti-malarial measures), and drainage both in urban and rural areas. The investigations so far made by the Malarial and Agricultural Experts lent by the Government of India have convinced me that the en gineering work to be done must be taken as a unified pro ject if the maximum advantages are tobe derived, and such a project would be beyond the resources of the Bahrain State Services. 6. In examining the Budget now presented in the light b 'luMr of ray Note of ! the 22nd November 1937 in regard to the forma tion of a Reserve Fund, I find that the programme postulated for that Fund has been fully provided for. As is shown in ^ p,5 *v the final paragraph of the Adviser 1 s letter there is every reason to hope that the minimum sum of Rs. 14,00,000 to be placed to Heserve will be exceeded, and there is the more reason for this expectation in that I believe that the re ceipts anticipated in the Budget from Oil Royalties are much under-estimated. On the other hand a sum in excess of the amount I had anticipated has been taken from Oil Royalty re ceipts for expenditure during the year. In considering the true State Budget for the year we should exclude on the Re venue side the following:- (a) Oil Royalty ... Rs. 30,00,000 (b) Oil Gauging Payments ... Rs. 45,500 thus reducing the Revenue proper to Rs. 11,56,500. On the Expenditure side we can omit the following:- (a) -J Oil Royalty to the Ruling Family ... Rs. 10,00,000 (b) Oil Gauging ... ... ... Rs. 18,000 (c) Loan to Electric Department ... ... Rs. 60,000 (d) Reserve ... ... r s . 12,00,000 TOTAL ... ... Rs. 22,78,000 This/-s ■- 5 - ' This reduces the Expenditure Budget proper to Hs. 19,24,000. Thus the State is expending Ks. 7,67,500 from Oil Royalties during the year, as c ompared with the sum of Rs. 6,60,000 v/hich I had anticipated. Though this in itself is not a serious matter since it is already clear enough that normal (i.e. non-oil) income is a great deal more buoyant than had been presumed in ray Note, it is nevertheless necessary to con sider whether developments now in progress will not involve a higher ultimate recurring Expenditure Budget than was antici pated a few months ago. Without going into details I think it can be deduced from the Expenditure Budget presented this year that, after excluding oil altogether, normal annual expenditure mill tend to average closer to Rs. 14,00,000 than to Rs t 12,50,000 v /hich at first seemed a probable figure. This in turn will necessitate an increase of some Rs. 40,00,000 in' the State Reserve, and if we continue to assume that royalty payments should remain steady for a period of 15 years it seems desirable that the Bahrain Government should be advised to increase their minimum annual transfer to Reserve to Rs. 15^ or Ij^lakhs. I am satisfied that this is well within the bounds of possibility, since, as observed above, non-oil re venue is considerably more buoyant than anticipated, and even the conservative figures taken in my earlier Note of November 1937 showed a probable balance after meeting all requirements of Rs. 49^00,000 (cf. item 6 in paragraph IV of Note of 22nd November 1937.) I have the honour to be P'L- Mo ^ hi** • Your most obedient se3.-vant, 'c&amp;p'j9' l- stawl' i© 0^ajvvo-lv . —. Political Agent, Bahrain.t4*\ No. 557-21 of 1357 Office of the adviser to the Government, Bahrain Bated, 15th H/kwal, 1357 l5th may 1938. From The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to forward for your in formation a copy of the Budget of the Bahrain State for the year 1357. The Annual Report containing full details of last year's revenue and expenditure and notes on all Departments, Diving Industry, Law and Order, etc., is not yet complete but will be sent to you as soon as possible. I regret the delav. 2. This is the thirteenth Budget which I have had the honour to present. 3. There are certain items in the Budget which may now require some explanation as the detailed notes do not accompany it. (a) On the revenue side the item Oil Gau ging Receipts represents payments made to the Government by the Bahrain Petroleum Company in return for the services of Mr. Furber, the Bah rain Government's Official Oil Ganger, who in addition to gauging oil for royalty purposes-2- gaugejfs and tests oil which is exported. (b) Reserve Fund . In this Budget the Rese rve Fund is shown as being Rs 18,00,000/-. Interest is assumed from a further Rsl4,00,000/- which is to be invested during the year. Half of this amount is to be invested at the beginning of the year and half is to be invested six months later. Of the Rs 14,00,000/- the sum of Rslg,00,000/- is to be obtained from the 1357 annual revenue as shown in the Budget and the remaining Rs2,00,000/- is to come from the surplus existing at the end of 1356. In actual fact during the first month of 1357 the sum of Rs 11,00,000/- was added to the Reserve Fund, increasing it to Rs 29,00,000/- and it can be reasonably assumed that before the end of the year the total contribution to the Reserve Fund will amount to considerably more than the Rs 14,00,000/- which is anticipated in the Budget, j I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Sefvant. Sd/ C. Dalrymple Belgrave. Adviser to the Government. R.Z.( t?| 17k 6'; Confiaential . To \ no # ii9d-s» Britisli Resiaency ana Consulate-General, V Busnire, the May 133b, The Political Agent, Banrain. Subject s Baarain Government Budget. mtmoxandnm. 'w . x F ,lf&amp; % Reference your- letter No,0/383-4/1, dated 19th May 133a, Wiilch I have read with much interest, I note from i your paragraph fc that your present remarks are preliminary ana will be subject to revision on receipt of tne Adviser's Annual Report, Sd, T.C, Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ATTESTED /fad Ite for Sccrcy/ary to the Poxitical Resident in the Persian Gulf,Confidential* \qlnuHfi~ y No. 0/392- busi-'te regsd^n gy. Date., f ''^onrdhtial p.ecords / &amp;)\ Political Agency, Bahrain, the 15th June 1938. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Bahrain Government Budget. Memorandum . Ji ^ Reference correspondence resting with your confidential memorandum No. 295-S dated the 27th May 1938 on the above sub ject. 2. I have now been informed by the Acting Adviser that the Adviser's Annual Report is unlikely to be available for at least six weeks as it is with the printers and the proof will be sent to Mr. Belgrave for his personal approval, 3. Infomation which has reached me in the last few days indicates that the supply of Crude Oil from the Bahrain Petro leum Company's Field is considerably less than the Refinery capacity. This is due to anxiety in regard to encroaching water in the shallow horizon and disappointing results from drilling to the deeper horizon. It is, therefore, likely that there may be some reduction in the total figure for Oil Royal ties this year, though ©n a rough calculation there is good reason to hope that the figure will not be below Rs. lakhs. Since there is still a possibility of improvement in Crude pro duction I do not v/ish at this stage to revise the remarks made towards the end of my report on current year's Budget, Jl/K Political Agent, Bahrain.n lnL 0 CaaLLden ti.aa^ j'c!JS!^RE RES 'DENCYr} /r ^ fw-' From To Ho JJ .3026-1J/38. 1 ^ CoiFlDiNiiALRicORDS j C. , . The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External affairs Department, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf» Dated Simla, the // ^ iugust 1938* Bahrain State budget for the Arabic year 1357» Sir, 1 am directed to acknowledge receipt of the papers forwarded with your printed letter No.439-S, dated the 21st July 1938, and to say that the U-overnment of India note with satisfaction the great improvement in the financial posi tion of the Bahrain State. 2. 1 am to add that a copy of these papers is being forwarded to the India Office as there is no indication that a copy of your letter under reference has been sent. I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the G-overnment of India. [Copy sent to P.A.Bahrain under P.L.No.G/564 of tne 23/8/38).Confidential No. C/8-4/1 BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. No.- Date t/f*) CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send; him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHKAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 5th January 1939 Refeirence to previous correspondence: Description of Name and Date. Summary of Revenue and Expendi ture for the first nine months of year 1367 (March-November 1938) Subject. Bahrain Finances.iljnt D.O.NO.297-3 The Residency, Bushire, the 3rd April 1939, Some years ago when Loch was Political Agent at Bahrain,at his suggestion »« approached Shaikh Hamad and suggested that out of the oil royalties, which were then beginning to come in, he should give a certain proportion into the Government Treasury. We did not suggest any special proportion but the Shaikh not only agreed to the principle,but agreed to give quite a considerable fraction to the State. I do not recollect what this fraction was, and as I am writing this letter to catch the mail by Howson, I have no time to look the correspondence up in my files. Am I coreect, however, in saying that the Shaikh's present income frora oil revenues is about €.250,000/- per annum, of which he gives £.200,000/- to the State and keeps t?.50,000/- for himself 7 Please let me have a reply by next mail. If you are not back from Dubai in ti.ae Hcues can answer this letter. H.Weightman, Ssquire, I.C.S Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential D.O. No. C/229-4/1 b 3 Dated the 6th April 1939 VL nes'pency. /*» Dsto •■ L ' 1 cof&lt;fli)entwl rec0ros Will^you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 297-3 dated the 3rd April 1939 ? 2. The arrangement is that the Shaikh retains one third of the oil royalties, and hands over two thirds to the State. (The Shaikh's share is, of course, in addition to the Civil List which comes to about 4-g lakhs annually). 3. The oil royalty for 1938 was Rs 35,02,184, or just over £ 260,000; of this the Shaikh takes £ 87,500 and the State gets £ 172,500. Yours sincerely. K Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.No. l\ob ^(r The Political Ageat, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- \y i, 2. 3« The lion r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (V) The Agency, BAHBA1IN, Persian Gulf. Dated Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Name and Date. Subject. V Vv tM * Bahrain Governmen-jJ' s Annual Report for the year 1357 (March 1938 — February 1 39)„C onx id ent ia 1 . K'o.C/456-4/1. m &gt; t v&gt; Political 1 Bl No ■ ■■'■■■■ Dare.-.--- c&gt;. i -- -■ • - - t. Bahrain, the 26th July 1939 u«2» From H. Weightman, Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. /| /„ 'x To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ✓ jd dir, y / I have tjafe honour to invite your attention to / the fact that the Bahrain Government Annual Report for the y^ar 1357, (forwarded with my Printed Letter Ho.0/455-8/9, dated the 26th July 1939) contains a review of the Sevenue and iilxpenditure for 1357, i.e. March 1938 - February 1939 and also the Budget proposals for 1358 i.e. February 1939 to January 1940. X regret that in the stress of Cil Negotiations etcetera I over looked the non-arrival of the State Budget, but I have now requested the Adviser to ensure in future that his Budgets are sent to the Agency at the proper 'Lime. 2. The year 1357 was most satisfactory financially, receipts being considerably in excess of budget expectat ions and enabling no less than r .s.l9 lakhs to be added to the .eserve. On the Expenditure side there were large excesses under (1) Allovi/ances to the Huling Family, due solely to increased oil royalties, of which one third is paid to His Highness the Shaikh. (2). Public Protection, since (on my recommendation at the time of the abortive &gt; Bahrain ''agitation') an addition to .the strength of the Police was made. At the sam. time it was decided to re- , arm/ 3 C-2' arm the Police. (3) Unforseen, due largely to the purchase of lands from Persian subjects under the terms of the Bahrain Property Lav/. There were large savings under the following heads (1) Public Health. Mainly due to the fact that no large- scale anti-malaria measures were undertaken, and the new hospital was not ready before the end of the year, thus reducing establishment charges. I may add that I have taken steps to ensure that more effective anti-malaria measures are carried out this year. (2) Public iorks. Mainly because the project for building a new Palace for His Highness has been temporarily abandoned. It will be observed that the Public Vorks programme underwent considerable revision during the year. I do not consider any grave objection need be raised on this score, since elasticity is essential in a period of rapid development, and the Department has still much to learn in framing estimates xor work in Bahrain, 3. In the result Revenue exceeded estimates by roughly 6 lakhs and expenditure (excluding sums placed to Reserve) exceeded estimates by 1 lakh. The invested .evenue at the end of the year amounted to .s.40 lakhs. 4. In regard to the estimates for the current year, I have the following comments to make. Revenue . (1) I have no doubt whatsoever that Gil 'loyalty receipts will exceed estimates by 10 % at least. i need not give detailed reasons for this view which is based on existing production and knowledge of the Company's policy for the immediate future. (2) Customs Hecaiots are also much under-estimated. That the opening of Has Tan^pg^ )ort on the mainland will gravely affect collections on transhiooed cargo is undeniable, but it cannot affect collections on goods imported for consumption in Bahrain. I expect receipts to exceed the estimate under this head by not less than Hs.2 lakhs, since trade is — and has been/been — very fair* (3) The receipts under Interest on Reserve Fund are already beginning to reach a very pleasing figure. I understand that even His Highness was impressed. lilxpenditure . (1) Administrative Services. The increased expenditure here is fully explained by the Adviser, I regard this as inevit able in view of the expanding activities of the Bahrain Govern- ment* (2) Public Health. I sincerely trust that the estimate of Hs.6,000/- for Anti-I.alarial Lleasures under this head will be greatly exceeded. 1 have made it my business to ensure that a comprehensive programme of work for the elimination of mosquito-breeding areas is inaugurated and the Adviser has undertaken go provide funds generously as they may be required. Otherwise this head of the Budget, in conjunction with the Hedical share of the P. .D. budget, is one on which Bahrain- may congratulate itself. (3) Public Protection. Ho particular comments. Equipment charges are high owing to the increased size of the Police Force. I have considered whether, in view of the increased Police strength, a part of 'the Hatur Force might be reduced, but have come to the conclusion that this would be an error in policy, at any rate for some years to come. (4) Education. As you are aware, I..r. Vallance has recently , visited iSahrain to conduct a critical examination of education in Bahrain. This report is expected shortly and will almost certainly involve increased expenditure. It is futile to at-oempt to forecast how great this increase will be, but it should be anticipated that the Budget Allotment will be exceeded. Hon-Itecurrent Expenditure is exhibited separately in this Budget, and calls for the following comments. A. investment in ieserve Fund. The provision of Rs.ll lakhs for this purpose is inadequate, particularly in a year when a Special/7&lt;? - 4 - Special leceipt of Ks.4,00,000 /- is expected as the result of Oil Concession Negotiations. Its inadequacy is partly due to the heavy cost of the Budget to complete the Manama-LIuharraq Causeway (the Adviser's figure for this is an underestimate) and partly to over-conservative estimation of Revenue. It is true that there is a balance of Rs.S lakhs from 1357 for investment in the current year, which brings the total anti cipated investment to Its. 14 lakhs but, quite apart from this, I am convinced that the state can and should invest Rs.15 lakhs at least during 1358. I propose, unless otherwise instructed, to take up this matter vith the Adviser when 9 months' actuals are known. B. As stated above the c est of the Manama-Muharraq Bridge will exceed the Budget figure, but in all probability the major part of the expenditure will come next year. The contractors will start work in October and since they will be unable to finish this task before the end of the Arabic year they will presumably only draw running bills. C. An extensive lublic ..orks programme is again contemplated. On the experience of last year I doubt if the Bahrain P. .D. will be able to complete it. 5. As framed the Budget appears to indicate the beginning of e decline in prosperity in Bahrain. In the light of my re marks above, however, it will be evident that there is little cause for anxiety on this score. Nevertheless it is becoming more and more apparent that all previous estimates of anti- capated normal expenditure on the administration of Bahrain require radical revision; and fresh sources of income must be found. The whole problem may be simplified by new oil discoveries in (or rather below) shoal waters, but such optim ism makes too heavy demands on a beneficent Providence, and the development of other industries is becoming an urgent necessity. As I have indicated in demi-official correspond ence/correspondence I believe that other industries can be developed here. Investigation proceeds and I shall revert to this whole problem on a later occasion, I have the- honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, Sd. H. ?/eight man. Political Agent, Bahrain, 'co-ja^ $ cju-i' ajb j.6- ^ cj. ~ . c&lt; w klo • c oJrcJL ^Confidential No * C/552-4/1 nh v 'V f BUSH 1R ^ ggJDENCY . ■ i a/o .. 7^ oihu. idafe. | coiifidentsal records The Political Ageat, Bahrain, Presents his complimenis to: — The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated L7th September 1939 Reference to previous correspondence: Des&amp;ription of Name and Date. Subject. Summary of Revenue and Expenditure for the first half of year 1358. Bahrain Governments Finances.C onfidential , No. C/790-4/1. n /7b rgusHin F fer.' ^NCY . i a/fii tX- t: ^ ^ u: ' 2c0?\03 Hi 1/ The Political Agent, Bahram, presents his compliments to;— } A The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf D ate d 2nd December 1939, Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Name and Date. Subject. Statement of Revenui end of Ramadan, and expenditure till 1358 (9months).*Confidential D.O. No. C /2S5 - 4/1 A ^ ^ 0 f * q f -j f ; p 't r: f'; i n p fsj q y. U- Uo cor 1 j ; ':,. /:; - f'. -jo^ds Dated the 6th April 1940 Si ^^ /xAsv^ 1 I enclose herewith a copy of a curious letter which His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain has written to Shaikhs Abdullah and Salman and Belgrave together with a copy of a highly inaccurate account which he has enclosed therewith, 2. The immediate cause for this letter is His Highness' objection to paying their allowances to two of his sons, Shaikh Da f ij and Shaikh Ahmad, from his share of the oil money ('olease refer to Loch's letter No. C/449 dated the 28th April 1934). The two sons themselves would also much rather be on the ordinary civil list which they regard as guaranteeing a greater degree of permanence. 3. Behind this is His Highness' wastefulness and utter incapacity to manage his money affairs. Many years ago when Shaikh Hamad was Regent and was overspending his eivil list of of Rs. 12,500 per mensem the Political Agent said that even if he had a lakh a month he would still be in debt. Nov/ he has the lakh a month, and sure enough he is always overdrawn. We can go a step further and say that even if he had a crore a month he would still waste the lot and be always short of ready money. 4. So far as the specific issue of the two sons' allowances is concerned I have told Belgrave that if the Shaikh pursues the question (and he may very easily forget all about it) he should remind His Highness that he has an agreement with the Agency not only to keep his share of the oil money down to one-third of the total royalties but also to pay Da'ij (at any rate) out of this share, and that if he wants to follow up fhe Hon'ble /_ Lieut-Colonel C-G. Prior, C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire .- 2 - the matter he must address me. I think it would be as well to decide now the attitude we should adopt if he does address me and also to consider rather more broadly the whole question of the Shaikh's share of the oil royalties. In theory there is no very sound reason why Da'ij's and also Ahmad 1 s allowance should not go on the regular civil list, but this merely means that there will, be another 7000 or 8000 a year to go dov^n the drain via Shaikh Hamad. It is not a serious sum of money in these days in Bahrain, but waste is waste whether the sum be large or small. 5. Belgrave has written to me saying that the senior Shaikhs constantly talk to him about the whole money question, and that 'they all disapprove of the way His Highness is spending money but are all agreed that none of us can mention the matter to him without making him very angry. They talk freely about the enormous sums of money which he is spending on boys — cash presents, cars, houses, land on which he pays for labour etc., etc., and they and his sons resent this even more than they resent his increasing and misplaced generosity to undeserving Bedu from Qatar and elsewhere. There is quite a lot of local feeling about these Bedu outside the Khalifah Family. Local people who are some times deserving are given nothing but no Bedu goes away empty-handed'. 6. I cannot really say that resentment either inside or outside the Family at Shaikh Hamad's wastefulness has yet produced a serious situation in Bahrain, but I should hesitate to say that it will not do so in five years' time. Without going into details I should estimate that Shaikh Hamad takes in something over Rs 13 lakhs a year. Of this he pays out as a regular thing close on 3 lakhs a year to the A1 Khalifah Plus some unspecified portion of his old civil list allowance of Es ij- lakhs a year. I suppose it costs him about Rs 3 to 4 lakhs a year for household expenses, upkeep of properties, ent er t a inmen t/2^ - 3 - entertainment of distinguished guests and so on; and the rest is wasted on Bedu and undesirable young men, 7. So far as Da'i.j and Ahmad are concerned I should have suggested making a bargain with him by which they go on the State civil list and he meets some other charge, but I cannot think of any bargain he is likely to accept. I suggest, there fore, that if he does follow up this question our attitude should be one of hurt surprise that he should even think of going back on an agreement with us and a blunt statement that he can very well afford to pay two of his sons. 8. The main question however to my mind is whether we should sit back and watch the best part of £ 50,000 being wasted every year. At the time when the agreement was negotiated that he should retain one-third of the oil money and pass tv/o-thirds to the State I am pretty certain that no one anticipated that royalties would reach their present total. I think I am right in saying that isahrain was expected to produce somewhere round 10,000 barrels of crude oil daily whereas it has averaged about double in the last three years and will probably continue at a rate between 18,000 and 20,000 for many years to come. My own feeling is that sooner or later we ought to ^et the Shaikh, whoever he may be, to reduce his own share to one-fifth, (One ought of course to contemplate a reduction to about one- tenth, but that is, in the circumstances of Bahrain, a dream of 'Utopia) • rhe question on which I cannot make up my mind is whether we should aim at this in Shaikh Hamad's lifetime or whether we should wait and develop our attack on his successor. If I could foresee how long Shaikh Hamad will be with us I could answer the question, but with a diabetic it is useless to guess. - n y suggestion to Shaikh Hamad that he should reduce his income would of course produce a tremendous explosion; he has worked himself up into the belief already that he is hard up and you can imagine the puzzled resentment he would feel if I suggested to him that he should deliberately cut his own income by about four /-3 four lakhs a year. On the o-oher hand we do not want this one-third and two-thirds proportion to continue for ever, partly 'because it is wrong in principle for us to connive at waste and partly because there will sooner or later be trouble about it in Bahrain. 9. It sounds like shirking the issue but on the whole I think we might hold our hand for the moment while carefully watching for any signs of increased resentment in Bahrain at wasteful extravagance, and while simultaneously starting on propaganda with one or two of the senior members of the family ^you will realise why I am not more explicit) in pre paration for a formal proposal that the next Shaikh should signalise his succession by reducing his own share of the royaloies to one-fifth. Even if Shaikh Hamad lasts longer than one might expect and local ill-feeling about waste and extravagance grows more rapidly than I personally believe it will, we shall still be in a better position to exert influence ii we can manage to convince the senior members oi the Family in advance that a change must come, in their own interests. Yours sincerely,ST Translation of a letter from His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain to Shaikhs Abdulla and Salman and the Adviser. After Compliments: Reference our conversation with our brother Shaikh Abdulla, I wish to inform you about something which is in my mind about increased expenditure and its increase day by day. Altogether I am not surprised at the increase ^hich is due to those who come to Bahrain. These people come due to my name and position and is a custom followed in the past and cannot now be checked. I give details of amounts paid from my private funds, apart from what has been spent andlis still being I spent on my private buildings and the Masjids which are being constructed for the benefit of Moslems as the present mosques have no sufficient income, from wakfs, and these facts we wish you not to forget, and thank you. Seal. 10th Safar.Pay Bs 12,500 Amount paid monthly to certain members of the fsjmily, and to Bedouins and servants. 12,425 Balance 75 Amount paid to Shaikhs Mohammad, Abdulla and Salman every six months 60,000/-, in a year Amount paid to members of the Khalifah, the Bedouins and others 19,000. In a year (Double of 19,000 is 38,000) Amount paid every six months to our servants and servants of our brothers Bs 5471/- In a year Approximate amount of 'Musaadat' Approximate amount of 'Sharahat' 1,20,000 36,000 10,932 1,60,000 1,20,000 4,46,932»7 &amp; Confidential* The H«8ldenoyt BueMre, the 15th April, 1940* d,o.ko.169-s» Wy dear Weightiaan, Will you please refer to your demi-official letter So«G/285»4/it dated the 6th April 1940 1 A 2* As fax' au Ba*lJ and Ahmad are ooncerned I agree with the proposal la paragraph 7 of your letter# If we mention the agreementf the Shaikh will probably be slightly pussled as his meraory is always weak when it is in his interest to forget, but he la unlikely to pursue the matter further* 3# As regards the wider question, I entirely agree with you that it Is unpleasant to think of so ©uoh money being wasted in such a way and on suoh undeserving people* think, however, that we should feel our way carefully before we try to get the Ruler's quota reduced, for at the time it was considered that the Shaikh was being rather generous In giving such a high percentage of the royalties to the state I Of course, as you say, no one anticipated that they would reach their present figure. I entirely a^ree with the proposal in paragraph 9 of your letter* We should get little support for an immediate attack on Shaikh Hamad 1 s one*.third, but we ou^ht to tie down the next Ruler in advance by getting letters from the senior members of the Family saying that they think the Ruler's share ought to be one-fifth of the royalties* If, then. Shaikh Hamad shows signs of living indefinitely we might, after a little Judicious propaganda, bring some pressure to bear on 4* As regards reducing the Ruler's share to one-fifth, / him H•Weightman Esquire, I.C.S., .Political Agent, Bahrain*&amp;) him to roakt the reduotlon, but so long ee the general public remain comparatiftly dumb and the Family are afraid to face him, X do not eee that it is worth our while to piok the oheet* nuts out of the fire for them* 5* Do you think it would do any good if wrote to Shaikh Hamad and eaid that now that he was getting these enormous sums I hoped that he was laying away a large portion of It for a rainy day ? If we keep on reminding him that he has a very great deal of money, it will* at any rate t prevent his trying to sorew any more out of the State I Yours sinoereJy,l v Confidential. 5a s 3 2 -u o &lt; D.O.No.C/322-4/1. Dated the 16th April 1940 I am sending you separately a rather lengthy discussion of the Bahrain State Budget, and I should be most grateful if in due course you would inform me whether so detailed an examination is required. Last a 67 year's State Budget and my report on it elicted no comment from any quarter I Yours sincerely, The Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel C, G. Prior, C.I.E,, Political Residant in the Persian Gulf, i; Bushire *Confidential * ^jo Political Agencv, Ho.C/323-4/1. Bahrain, the 16th April 1940. V From Rl ISH'RE RBG^DENCY. &gt; xc i 'cOislFlDEriT-L RECORDS To H. Weightman, Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Bahrain State Budget, Sir I have the honour to forward herewith the following papers A. 1. Final figures of Revenue and Expenditure of the Bahrain State for the year 1358, together with a Summary exhibiting details of the State Reserve. 2. Notes by the Adviser on Revenue and Expenditure for the same year. B. 1. Revenue and Expenditure Budget figures for the year 1359, together with a schedule of public works. 2. Notes by the Adviser on expected Revenue and Expenditure. 2. In regard to last year's figures I need have little to say. On the Revenue side Oil Royalty and Customs receipts greatly exceeded Budget expectations, as I forecast b&lt; ^ they would in paragraph 4 of my letter No.C/456 of the 26th July 1939. In point of fact Oil Royalty receipts were slightly less than I had anticipated as production had to be rather more rigorously controlled than originally expected in order to prevent the undue inflow of edge water. On the /-- 2 - the other hand neither the Bahrain State nor I foresaw that the approval of His Majesty's Government to the draft lease for the Unallotted Area would be so greatly delayed that the consequent payment of Rs. 4 lakhs 'by the Company would not be made before the close of the year. Abnormal receipts under Land Revenue are explained in the Adviser's letter. On the Expenditure side the main items calling for comment are the following (a) Public Health The excess here of roughly Rs.11,000 was largely due to anti-malarial measures taken in the second half of the year. The excess was foreseen in my letter referred to above and would have been greater but for the departure of the State Medical Officer before the close of the year. (b) Education There was a saving of rather more than Hs.15,000. During the year Mr. Vallance visited the State to examine educational methods and necessities in Bahrain, and develop ment was wisely delayed pending the receipt and examination of his report. An unsatisfactory Inspector of Education was discharged and not replaced. The temporary halt in expenditure and progress is however fully compensated during the current year. (c) Public Protection The great excess over the Budget figures here (roughly Rs.41,000) was mainly due to special defence measures taken on the outbreak of war and to the purchase of essential equipment to put them into operation. This special equip ment was in addition to the rifles and ammunition for which Budget provision of Rs.30,750 had been made under the head Non-recurrent Expenditure - State Protection - Armaments. (d) Kin&gt;? Ibn Saud's visit The expenditure of Rs. 28,000 on King Ibn Saud's visit requires /-- 3 - C|v requires no comment except to note with some satisfaction that this visit involved the State, as apart from His Highness personally, in so little expenditure. (e) Cost of Rice Rs.1,36,000 was an item of unforseen expenditure / incurred at the outbreak of war when there was doubt whether foodstuffs would continue to reach Bahrain in normal volume. The State has however been able to sell this rice during the current year. (f) Public Works The variations betv/een budget figures and actuals under the head Public Works are, with one exception, fully explained in the Adviser's notes. This exception relates to the cost of the Manamah Customs Pier Extension, which exceeded the estimate by close on Rs.34,C00/-, due mainly to excessive subsidence and the need for providing a greater wharf area than originally contemplated. The State Public Works Department has now gained some experience in framing estimates and these should in future be rather more accu rate. The main items on which expenditure was incurred but which had not been contemplated at the time of the budget were (a) the construction of a new rifle range, which was rendered necessary by the purchase of machine guns and Cb) a Police Post, Jail and Tower on Jedda Island to provide for the better guarding of long term prisoners and for certain defence measures. 3. In commenting on the budget figures for the current year one must necessarily allow for the fact that budgeting in wartime may be rendered entirely nugatory by circumstan ces beyond local control. In the Revenue Budget for in stance one would expect/the Oil Royalty and Customs receipt figures to be exceeded if the war goes well, but it must be /-- 4 - P IV. /- be recognised that tanker shortage may gravely affect the former. Roughly 75 % of the oil exported from Bahrain has hitherto been carried in Norwegian and Danish tankers, and at the moment the future of the tanker fleets of these two nations is obscure. Similarly an extension of hosti lities might gravely affect shipping in the Gulf and there by render the estimates under Customs totally illusory. One may however express the pious hope that the item 'New Oil Concession - Rs.4,00,000' will mature this year. 4, On the Expenditure side, I make the following remarks on the assumption that there will be no major interference with the normal administrative life of Bahrain. ii. Administrative Services . The provision made here is likely to be in excess of requirements. For instance if the Air Ministry perchance reach a decision on the suggestion to employ Captain Byard as Defence Officer the post of Assistant to the Adviser will become vacant and need not be refilled during the war: it may well be unnecessary to fill certain vacant posts in the Customs Department; while the provision under (c) 'Judicial, Wakfs and I inors Departments' includes a sum of Rs.10,000 for remuneration to a legal expert to codify law in Bahrain, and this sum will, i believe, be found excessive. Public Health. The provision here greatly exceeds last year's budget partly because it allows for the staff required for the new hospital and partly on account of increased pro vision for anti-malarial measures. i think it is unlikely that the former will be required in full and i fear it will involve considerable effort to ensure that t he latter is fully expended.- 5 - 3 IV. Public Protection . In providing Rs.50,000 for special defence measures i.e. for a special police force to guard the Oil Field and Refinery, the Adviser has not taken into account the reduction in strength which might w£Ll be made in the normal State Police and Natur strength, I have drawn his attention to this and my personal belief is that expenditure under this head should not exceed Rs. 3 lakhs, even allowing for the increased cost of rations in wartime. V. Educati on Sub-head (a) includes the Bahrain Government's share of Mr. Vallance's pay and sub-head (b) provides for a very desirable expansion of the Technical School. I shall be reporting separately and more fully on the pro gress of education in Bahrain shortly. VI. Public Works I have no particular remarks to make on the schedule of public works though I feel bound to say that I shall be surprised if the full amount provided for hospital buildings is expended during the year, 5. It will be seen that the Budget allows for a surplus for investment of roughly Rs. 13 lakhs, which ordinarily I should describe as an inadequate investment, particularly in view of the expected receipt of Rs. 4 lakhs due on the completion of the Lease for the Unallotted Area and of the investment of only Rs. 10 lakhs last year. As will be - seen from the remarks in my letter No.C/456 dated the 26th July 1939 under the hea^ 'Investment in Reserve Fund' I anticipated that a total of Rs. 18 lakhs might be invested last year. The expected receipt of Rs. 4 lakhs for the Unallotted Area did not however accrue and the war cost Bahrain in one way or another roughly Rs. Sf lakhs. Consequently /-- 6 - (§) &lt;)s' Consequently last year's investment of Bs. 10 lakhs was a most praiseworthy addition to the Reserve. This year, provided oil shipments are maintained and provided there is no interference with customs receipts as the result of the war, I should anticipate the Revenue to be close on 4 lakhs more than has been anticipated while Expenditure may well be from Rs. 1 lakh to 3 lakhs less than the Budget figures. It is conceivable therefore that there may be Rs. 18 or 19 lakhs for investment this year and this possibility will be borne in mind for discussion with the Adviser later in the year. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain.v Mote on Expenditure 1358. Estimated expenditure for 1368 was Rs 31,41,000/-, actual expenditure was Rs 36,75,000/-. The difference between actual and estimated expenditure is mainly owing to the following reasons. His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad gave Rs 4,00,000/- to the British Government towards the cost of the war. The Bahrain Government purchased a large supply of rice, half of which was sold during the year. The value of the remainder at the end of the year was Rs 1,36,000/-. Although this sum is included in expenditure for 1358 it may be regarded as an item of revenue for 1359 and has been shown in the estimated revenue for that year. The expenditure on public protection was appro ximately Es 41,000/- more than the estimated cost. The oil royalty amounted to more than the anticipated sum and therefore the one third which was paid to His Highness^ Privy Purse was more than was provided in the 1358 budget. In spite of heavy unexpected expenditure the Reserve Fund was increased by Rs 10,00,000/-. iJ.lowances to the Ruling Family. Rs 15,16,662. One third of the oil revenue paid direct to His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad amounted to Rs 10,78,427/-, the remaining 'L 4 ,38,235/- represents Civil List pay ments to the Ruling Family. The total amount about Rs 1,00,000/- leas than last year owing to decrease in oil revenue. .adviserate. Rs 66,499/-. Expenditure was approximately Hs 7,000/- less thanthan the amount which was anticipated. Provision was made for an Assistant Adviser but the appoint ment was not made until after the beginning of the year. Customs Department. Rs 80,903/-. Several vacant appointments in the customs staff were not filled and expenditure was approximately 8s 5,000/- less than was expected. Judicial, Awakaf and Minors Departments. Ks 54,177/-. Expenditure was less than estimated but approxi mately Rs 7,000/- more than last year. The Minors* Department which was started during the course of 1357 had to be paid for during the whole year in 1358. The salaries of the Bahrain Court Magistrates were increased during the year by one third. Public Works Department. E3,273/-. Expenditure was Rs 6,000/- less than the budgeted amount but Rs 4,000/- more than 1357 expenditure. Land Department. Rs 40,172/-. Expenditure was as estimated in the Budget. Passport Department. Rs 13,344/-. Expenditure exceeded the Budget by approximately Hs 1,000/- and was approximately Rs £,000/- more than during the previous year. Oil Gauging. Rs 13,530/-. Expenditure exceeded the budget by Bs 2,000/-. Transport Department, fts 5,661/-. Expenditure was less than the budgeted amount. Public Health. Rs 1,36,160/-. Expenditure was Rs 7,000/- more than the budgeted amount. Special additional expenditure on anti--3- anti-malaria measures was sanctioned during the year. Education. Rs 84,67?/-. Last year it was proposed that certain new schools should be built and provision was made for them. The matter was postponed. The Inspector of education was discharged at the end of the 1357 school year and there was a saving in respect of his salary. Expenditure was approximately Rs 15,000/- less than the budgeted amount. Municipalities. Rs 60,807/-. Expenditure was Rs 3,000/- less than the amount provided. ■agriculture. Rs 16,346/-. Expenditure was almost double the estimated amount. The experimental garden was enlarged and new land was put under cultivation. Departmental expens es. Rs 14,£05/-. Approximately Rs 7,000/- less than the estimated amount, Unforseen. Rs 4,27,315/-. Included under this heading is the sum of 4 lakhs gifted to the British Government. Public Protection. Rs 2,93,823/-. Expenditure was Rs 1,000/- more than during last year and approximately Rs 40,000/- more than the amount provided. This covers the cost of special defence measures and additional transport, motor bicycles etc.iirmaments and Equipment• Ss 29,956/-. Expenditure according to budget. Transport. Rs 6,833/-. Expenditure according to Budget. King Ibn Saoud's visit. Rs 28,101. Not provided for in the budget, food Supplies. (Rice). 8s 1,36,186/-. Hot provided for in the budget.Public Works. Tha sum allocated to Public Works in the 1358 budget was h 7,70,600/-, the actual expenditure was Rs 6,35,300/-, of this amount, Rs 5,91,000/- was spent on works which were Included in the budget, and Rs 44,000/- on new work approved and sanctioned during the year, but not provided for in the budget. In most cases the expenditure exceeded the esti mated amount but this was frequently due to additions to and extensions of the original plans, especially in the case of the hospital buildings and the pier extensions. 1* Manamah-Muharraq Swing Bridge. Rs 59,463/-, The contract was made during the current year, a sum of Rs 3,00,000/- was provisionally included in the budget before it was known how much the bridge would cost# The contract price was Ss 3,82,000/- of which Es 59,000/- was paid during 1358, A sum of Rs 35,000/- was budgeted for extending the two ends of the sea road to the pier terminals. The work was done by the Manamah and Muharraq munici palities and the cost was Rs 61,376/-. lach side cost approximately the same amount, 8, Hospital Buildings, is 2,35,000/-, The amount provided in the budget was Rs 2,57,000/-. The dispensary was entirely completed, the women's hospital and staff quarters were almost finished and considerable progress was made with the me^s hospital, foundations of the administrative building were finished and various additional buildings such as boiler house etc. were completed. The cost of building was very much more than was-2- was estimated owing to the need for deep founda tions, in part of the ground it was found necessary to build twelve feet deep before reaching solid ground. The work which is still to be done consists of completion of men's hospital, the adainistratiye block which includes operation theatre etc. and various walls and outhouses. Manaaah pier extension. Rs 1,01,588/-. The explanation of the additional expenditure and work is given under Public Works Department. Pier Trolley Lines. Rs 16,718/-. The trolley lines were purchased and the old lines repaired but the new lines have not yet been laid. Fort. Rs 29,070/- . Rebuilding the N.l. tower was not completed at the end of the year, the eastern wall was rebuilt, a new barrack room was constructed also a kitchen and a mess hall. The main entrance and guard room were repaired and re-roofed and a light roof was erected over the bathing tank. Education Department. Es 3,998/-. Two additional rooms were added to the Manamah boys' school and another room and a yard were built at the western end of the Technical School. Transport Department. 8s 12,379/-. The expenditure includes the cost of one large additional garage and two flats above the Transport Building. The flats are occupied by staff of the Electric Department.-3- Passport Office. Hs 13,416/-. The existing passport office was converted into a Post Office and let to the Indian Postal Depart ment and a new Passport Office was built at the western end of the Custoiihonse facing the square. The building consists of one large office, a small office and a record room# The reconstruction of the Post Office entailed more expense than was anticipated. Miscellaneous. 8s 4,296/-. A flight of stone steps was built in front of the central tower of the Palace and the old wooden stairs were removed, a steel folding door was put ' into the archway at the head of the steps and a wooden door was fixed on the back stairs so that the Majlis and guest rooms could be locked separately. Mosque at liawar. Ik 3,E50/-. A small mosque was built in the northern village at Hawar and various water cisterns were repaired. Kosabia House, lis 4,485/-. Outstanding bills on account of the house at lozabia which is let to the assistant Political iigent. Budeya garden drainage. R e 2,546/-. The extension of the experimental garden at Budeya necessitated mors drains for surplus water. iinnual Repairs. Rs 17,770/-. Various special repairs not anticipated in the budget were carried out and including under this heading. Road Repairs. Ss 19,298/-.mm ^ B in This includes the cost of metalling the Customs square and part of the sea road. Expenditure on works not included in the budget but sanctioned and carried out during the year amounted to &amp; 44,000/- and included the new Rifle Hangs and shed at Safra, buildings at Mari spring, a new police post, jail, pier and tower at Jida, additions to Bawar fort and alterations to the old rifle range and enlargement of Budeya police post and public water tank.. Mote on Revenue 1358. The estisiatod revenue was lis 4S,41,500/- t the actual revenue was Rs 45,78,600/-. With one exception the actual receipts from all sources equalled or exceeded the estimated amounts. The sum of h 4,00,000/- which was expected during the year on account of the oil concession over the addi tional area was not received during 1358; customs receipts however amounted to Rs 4,28,000/- more than had been anticipated and the oil royalty produced U£,35,000/- more than the estimated revenue. Total revenue was Ss 2,33,000/- less than in 1357. The oil royalty decreased by approximately Rs 3,00,000/- and customs receipts .ere Es 60,000/- less than in 1357. Bone of the sources of revenue requires particular explanation except Land Revenue a 75,000/-, which is abnormally high owing to the receipt of Kr 34,000/- from the ^ir Ministry on account of outstanding rents of the aerodrome and the price of land at Mabarraq, sold to the Royal Air Force of which the price of government land was approximately Rs 18,000/-.r% f; III Budget - 1359• Notes on Revenue. I. Oil Royalty. Hs SO.OO^QQ , The royalty on oil is estimated at the same amount as in last yeai^s budget which is fis 2,00,000/- less than the actual amount received in 1358• 8s 16,00,000/- is due to the government at the end of March 1940 for the six months which ended on 31-12-1939. I have assumed that during the first half of 1940 produc tion will be maintained. ZmCustoms Receipts. Es 7,00,000/-. last year a serious decrease in the customs revenue wlb anticipated. The actual decrease was only Rs 60,000/-. Total revenue from customs sources last year was ks 10,28,000/- but owing to the uncertainty of trade and war conditions I am net assuming on more than Bs 7,00,000/- from the customs. 3# Passport Receipts, fis 10,000/-. Passport receipts last year produced Rs 18,000/- but this income will not be maintained. Stricter enforcement of regulations, especially in the case of Persians resident in Bahrain and the cancelling of steamer passes for visitors to mail boats will reduce this source of revenue very considerably. 4. Judicial Receipts. h 8,000/-. There is no basis on which to estimate this revenue which depends upon the type of cases made in the courts. 5. Motor 'Vehicle Taxes. Rs 25,000/-. The revenue last year was &amp; 28,000/-. a reduction in the number of tax paying cars on the roads has been anticipated.6 * Revenue, fe £5,000/-, This inoluides registration fees, leases, s^les of land and aerodrome rent. Last year there were certain abnoraal payments such as the price of land bought by the Hoyal dr Force. 7. Interest on Reserve, to 1,89,000/-. This consists of interest at 3i^ on £378,550., and interest for six months on Rs 11,00,000/- which it is proposed should be added to the reserve during the year. 8. Oil Gauging fees. 10,000/-» fees paid for gauging oil which is shipped on tankers other than Bahrain Petroleum Company's own vessels. 9. Oil Concessions payment. h&gt; 4,00,000/-. It has been assumed that the preliminary payment on the concession over the additional area will be received during the year. 10. Miscellaneous. m 1,40,000/-. Of this emount 1,36,000/- will be received from sale of rice bought by the Government as an emergency measure during the war.jp» Budget - 1359. Notes on Expenditure. it ^llowanoes to the Ruling Famil y. Ks 14,40,000/-. This consists of one third of the estimated revenue from oil as well as the Civil List. E« Administrative Services. Hs 3,36,780/-. The actual expenditure last year was k 2,97,500/- against an estimated expenditure of Hs 3,E4,00Q/-. Addi tional expenditure has been provided for in the Adviserate, Customs and Judicial departments to cover the cost of leave passages. Assistant adviser, increase in Magistrates 1 salaries and the services of a legal expert to assist in compiling a code.. The purchase of some additional equip- aeat for the Government garage has been allowed for. 3« Public Health. h 1,98,800/- . Included under this heading is Es 45,000/- to be spent on anti-malaria meaaures. Medical services provide for carrying on the medical work which is being done now, the existing dispensaries and staff acd also for a State Medical Officer, nurses, dressers etc. for the Women*s Hospital for ten months and for the Men's Hospital for six months. It also includes the contribution to the \ ictoria Memorial Eospital. m quarantine expenses include the rent of the Quarantine, Es 4,800/-, which is paid to His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad, and the pay of the quarantine staff and running costs of the quarantine launch. Hospital diets have been calculated at the rate of fifty in-patients for eight months. About Rs 20,000/- of the sum provided for drugs and dressing is payment for goods which were ordered during 1358, the remainder is for new stock.Equipment includes linen and replacement of perishable medical stores® 4. Public Protection. ft» 3,37,100/-. The sua of 8s 50,000/- has been provided to pay for the additional naturs who are now employed on defence work and for the proposed new force of special police consisting of fifty men, MOQs and one Arab Officer. It has been assumed that the special police will be paid for ten months of the year 1359. Equipment and Uniforms include Is 8,000/- being part of the cost of motor bicycles purchased in 1358. The cost of rations is higher than last year and the strength of the regular police has increased. 5. Education. h 1,30,000/-. In addition to the sum allotted for recurrent cost of education Hs 20,000/- has been included under Special Public works 1 for enlarging the Technical Bchool and purchasing more equipment. Provision has been made for the existing schools throughout the year and also for additional staff for separate Infants 1 School and enlarged Technical ochool for the first four months of the next school year which begins in October. Special Education is the fee paid for the two sons of Shaikh Mohomed bin Isa Alkhalifah who are being educated at Government expense in Beyrout. 6. Municipalities B 60,400. Manumah and Muharraq municipalities receive a grant of h 2,000/- per month from the government and Rs ii00/- per month is paid to iuharraq Municipality for work at Hedd.id' (1g) i . f' Half the proceeds of Gar fax is divided between tiie two Municipalities, 7. .agriculture. Rs 10 # 000/-. This includes wages and upkeep of garden, seeds, transport etc. It can be reasonably expected that about half this amount will be recovered from sale of produce. 8. Contingencies. Bs 25 # 000/-. Includes printing of revenue stamps, government forms, publications in the local newspaper and office furniture and equipment. 9. Publia Works. Hs 20,000/-. Upkeep of government buildings and repairs to roads. Provided that oil and customs revenue continue to be normal and there are no unexpected demands on the revenue a surplus of its 13,00,000/- is anticipated which will be added to the Reserve. Special Public lorks. Ss 6 ,2 1 ,000/-. 1. ^anaaah iuharracj. Bridge. Rs 3,90,000/-. It is expected that the bridge will be completed in September. The balance of the contract price is Rs 3,40,000/-. .ai additional ia 50,000A has been pro vided for raising the approaches on each side of the bridge and for filling in or bridging the space on each side between the present ends of the sea road and the terminals of the bridge. 2. Hospital Buildings. 1,50,500/-. Provision has been made for completing all the hospital buildings though it is doubtful whether itit will be poasibls to do this during the year. The work includes finishing the Women's Hospital and Burses* quarters, completing the Ifca's Hospital with one large ward on the first floor connected with the Operating Theatre, building the surgery block which includes Iray rooas, operating theatre, stores, etc. and coapound walls, gates, garages aad staff quarters. 3. Fort, h 15,500/- . Work was commenced on last Wall last year; this is to be completed and the North last Tower is to be finished. A new Armoury is being built in the tower and an office on the first floor. Ihe West iall is the only one which needs re-building ii p rl provision has been made in case this work is undertaken in 1359. Police Lines. Es 24,000/-. additional houses are to be.built in the married lines; these are needed owing to the increase in the police strength. Tne old houses are in many c^ses ruinous and insanitary, they were built out of bad material over fifteen years ago. 4. Customs. Hs 13,500/-. Extension of the Trolley Lines on the new part of the pier and additional pier lighting ana a small office at the main gate have been allowed for, also repainting of customs sheds. 5# Technical iichool. iis £0,000/-. It is intended that the Technical School shall be enlarged during the year and some additional plant will be needed. Details are to be provided by the report on Technical Education by the Director of thethe Baghdad Teohnioal School. The building itself is not expensive as owing to the nature of the ground little foundation is needed. Religious School. Is 2,000/-. The Shia Religious and Law School is held in a hired ttouse, it was intended last year that a small building should be built for this purpose, but the work was postponed. 6. Spring. h £,500/- . Shelters are to be built around the women's bathing places on the water channel. These have previously been screened with barastis which cio not last more than one season. The barasti coffee shop is to be replaced by a stone building which will produce a good rent during the season. V. Badeya Uaroen. sis 3,000/-. It is possible that a new water channel will be built fro® the garden to the sea to carry off surplus water. The amount includes cost of sheds for cattle.^ . ■ IP Confidentia l* Ho*3S5-S of 1940. British Rtsideao^ as Ooneulate-General, mishire, the 28th April, 1940• frosB • The Hon'bXe Lieut«»Oolonel o.G.i-rior, Political Resident in the iereian Gulf, To » The Secretary to the Oovermaent of India» External Affaire Department, Simla* Subj e ot iBahrain ^tate Budget* le Sir, 1 have the honour to forward for the informs tion 7 [d of the OoTernnient of India a letter Bo#G/3S3«4/l, dated the 16th April 1940, from the Political ..gent at Bahrain, (together with its enclosuree), #iich explains itself* 2* The state is carrying out an excellent prograraiae of puhlie works, and a project for the extension of technical education is now under consideration and \vixl» it is hoped, he put into force during the year# 'x'he general financial strength of Bahrain is eminently satis factory, and the reserves are already reaching a very substantial figure* 1 have the honour to toe. Sir, Your most otoedient servant. Political Resident in the Persian Qulf * tOj-- 2.3/v/vo '(3 Confidential* The Hesidency, Bushlre, the 28th April, 1940# D.O.Ho,226-»S # My dear welghtman. jp-W Pleaee refer to your deml«»offiolal letter Ho» C/322-4/1, dated the 16th April 1940• of the Bahrain Budget of great Interest I last year*8 edition was sent to the Governsent of India Just before war broke out so they were probably occupied with weightier matters, it would be very awkward if they did suddenly turn a keen eye on it, for there can be few instances of a more scandalous waste of public funds by a Ruling Family I 3. 1 ehould have thought that even Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa would have hesitated to debit hie eon's education to the tate • 2, I can only assure you that I find your review Yours sincerejyt H.w'cightman iis^uire, I.0»S» t Political Bahrain*Dw c6?iRU£NTIAL RECORD! D.O.No.C/347-4/1 Dated the 23rd April 1940. Will you please refer to your demi-official letter k -^'1 No.169-3 dated the 15th April 1940 ? 2, His Highness the Shaikh has said no more about Da'ij's and Ahmad's allowances and there is now a good chance that this particular trouble will die a natural death. 3. I think it would be an excellent idea if you would inr write to Shaikh Hamad as you propose in paragraph 5 of your letter. I wish it were possible to go a little further and to suggest a sort of Shaikh 1 s Fund which he and his successors should create by periodical invest ments} the proceeds of which would be for the sole use of the Shaikh at the time, and which would descend from Shaikh to Shaikh undiminished by gifts, legacies or divisions by Shara law. However I am afraid this is not a practical idea in Shaikh Hamad's time. 4. I propose, unless you see any objection, to make your letter to Shaikh Hamad the opportunity for opening my discussions with the senior members of the family. I doubt if I will be able to get letters from them saying that they think the Ruler's share should be one-fifth, but if I can get them to agree to the principle it will probably be sufficient to tell them that I am communicating their views to you by letter. Yours s incerely. The Honourable Lieutenant Colonel C. G. Prior, C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.From to The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Hon'ble the Political Resid ent in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the ^ ' May 1940, Subjects- Bahrain State Budget. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your ✓ b- iff letter No. 225-3., dated the 28th April 1940 and enclosures, and to say that the Government of India agree with your comments. 2. I am to add that a copy of this correspondence is being forwarded to the India Office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to the, Government of India si c ' fc&lt;Sl A/! ' ctj: £ 'fa8o»37&amp;*S» 6th Juq« # 194$§ To Bis Highneas Shaikh Sir Hamad 'bin ♦lea al Khalifah, E»0 *X »l *t c • s • s • § anicr of Bahrain. My eetaeatd fritnd, «hen I was last in Bahrain I asant to speak to Your HighnesB about your finaneeSfr but 1 was indisposed and had no tiise* Nothing gives me greater pleasure than to hear of the prosperity of the Bahrain Stat© and 1 a® glad to know of the vast revenues derived from the Oil Gompany# What I wished to say was this* The oil is gradually toeing used up and will never return and 1 sincerely hope that Your Highness is investing as large a portion ae poseible so that when the oil and its revenues are exhausted there will still he something left* When one has had a great deal of ' I money it is very unpleasant to he reduced to a small inoome and the heet way of avoiding it is to put aside as much as poesihle while one still has it* 1 desire to express the high consideration which I entertain for Your Highness, and to subscrihe myself Your Highnes&amp;*g sincere friend, Political ' tlie Persian -19/176 Telegram Q, From Eolitical Agent, Bahrain. To political Resident, Bushire. No. 17 6 Dated ISth received 14th June 1940. f-'' ' Your demi-official letter dated 6th June, Ho. 379-S. Presume you wish parallel Arabic to Toe inserted By us in your letter dated 6th June No.378 to Shaikh of Bahrain. Please confirm. - POLITICAL - b:. %D.O. No. C/534-4/1 the 27th June 1940. My dear Prior, I am forwarding to you separately His Highness the ^ i&gt;3 Shaikh's reply to your letter No. 378-S dated the 6th June regarding the investment of some of his share of the oil 11 ' money. The letter can scarcely be described as effusive or revealing and it certainly tells you nothing that you did not know already. 2. So far I have not had time to do more than inform Shaikh Abdullah and Shaikh Salman that I intend to talk to them very seriously about the whole question of finances. We have all been preoccupied with the Additional Area Con cession and the war situation lately, but I intend to have my first meeting with them in three or four days' time. Meanwhile a somewhat unpleasant situation has arisen. His Highness has demanded that the sum of fe 4 lakhs paid by the Bahrain Petroleum Company on signature of the new concession personally. should be handed over to him/ Belgrave has done his best to resist this and has reminded His Highness that this sum of Es 4 lakhs is shown as a revenue receipt not only in the current State budget but also in last year's budget (when it was expected it would accrue). He has reminded His Highness that both these budgets were passed by him and that the last one at any rate has actually been published. He has further reminded His Highness that the gift of Rs 4 lakhs to His Majesty's Government for war purposes was to be covered by this particular receipt. His Highness has become more and more /- Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel C. G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.more impatient and ill-tempered and yesterday sent Shaikhs Abdullah and Salman as his 'Ambassadors' to Belgrave to settle the matter. Both of them fully appreciate Belgrave's points, but in true Arab manner say that perhaps half the total sum of is 4 lakhs might be handed over to the Shaikh 'to make his heart glad'. Belgrave managed to talk out the discussion yesterday but it will no doubt be resumed. As a last resort, if pressure is maintained, he proposes to advise His Highness to discuss the matter with me and to this I have agreed. 3. If His Highness does discuss the question with me I shall of course repeat Belgrave's arguments - perhaps in more forcible language than Belgrave could afford to use. I intend to remind him that although he is constantly pleading poverty he has in fact enormous riches, sums far beyond his wildest dreams a few years ago. I shall remind him that the whole honour and glory of the gift of fe 4 lakhs to His Majesty's Government accrued to him personally and that his present demand in effect means that that gift will be charged solely against funds which are intended to be expended for the benefit of his peo ple. I will tell him that when His Majesty the King makes a gift he pays for it from his own Privy Purse and does not ask the Government to meet it. And finally J.will remind him that though he claims to be hard up he has nevertheless managed to loan Es 2 lakhs to the Qosaibis, servants of Ibn Saud, which he will probably never see again, and is at the moment thinking of a loan of &amp; 1 lakh to Haji Yusuf Kanoo which will most cer tainly never be repaid. 4. It is more than likely that he will still remain obdu rate as in money matters he is stupid, obstinate and selfish. And I should be most grateful if you would let me know (by telegram if possible) whether you think that in the final resort he should be told, with as bad a grace as possible, that /-- 3 - that his agreement with the Agency precludes his demanding more than one-third of any oil money and that this amount he may claim if he thinks that his private needs are greater than those of his State. Yours sincerely. \wink Oonf identlal The Residency, Bushire, the 10th July 1940. P.O.Ho.490-3 My dear Weightiaan, Please refer to your demi-official letter So. 0/534-4/1, dated the 27th June 1940. 2. Shaikh Hamad*a letter can, as you say, scarcely he described as effusive, in fact it is so curt as to be almost impertinent. 5. X need hardly say that you will receive the fullest support from me for the arguments you propose to use in your paragraph 3. There is no justification whatever for a loan of two lakhs to the Qusaibis, who have never benefited Bahrain in any way, and whose interests lie outside it, though there may be some political gain in a loan to HaJ i Yusuf Kanoo. 4. You will have received my telegram agreeing to the action proposed in your paragraph 4. I wonder if a suggestion that His Majesty's Government might feel moved to refund the £.30,000 if they heard it was going to be taken from the publics money after all, would have any effect. The only trouble is that as His Majesty^ Government have already parted the vestment with the Government of India it would be impassible to carry the threat into executionJ Yours sincerely, %■ i Weightman, Esquire, I.G.3. Political Agent, Bahrain .D.O.No.C/606-4/1, Dated the 23rd July 1940 4- c//v^ r ^ ^ill^^m please refer to your demi-official letter Ko. 490-3 dated the 10th July 1940 regarding Shaikh Hamad's money affairs ? 2. bhaikh Hamad had not pressed his demand for a share of the Rs. 4 lakhs concession payment for some considerable time and I was beginning to hope that he had dropped it when he suddenly wrote to Belgrave on the 20th July definitely instructing him to pay over to his Privy Purse one-third of the Rs. 4 lakhs. Simultaneously he retreated to his island Umm riasan where he is supposed to be in sanctuary. 3. I accordingly sent for Shaikh Abdullah and Shaikh Sal man as his representatives and went over with them the various arguments set out in my demi-official letter No.C/534 dated the 27th June 1940. The ground being thus prepared I proceed ed to act on the suggestion made in paragraph 4 of your letter and requested them to inform His Highness from me that I saw only two courses before me; the first was to inform His Majesty's Government that Shaikh Hamad repented of his gift of £30,000 and wished to have one-third of it back; the second was to inform His Majesty's Government that not one single beza of this gift came from Shaikh Hamad himself but that the whole of it was from t he Government and people of Bahrain. The two Shaikhs were of course horrified and I applied a little soothing balm by saying that I was sure His Highness had not realised the consequences of his action. I asked them to see him at once and to explain to him what I Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel had /- C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.■ ■ . ■ ■- 2 - I had said and they undertook to do so and to bring a reply which they were certain would be satisfactory. 4. ... then went on to talk to them at great length about reducing the Ruler's share of the oil royalties to one-fifth when the next Shaikh comes along. I need not describe all the arguments I used and of course I did not demand an immediate reply. • But we arranged that we would continue the discussion later when they had had time to think it over their lirst reactions were by no means unfavourable. Yours sincerely,Confidential D.O. No. C/623-4/1 in 10' , Dated the 28th July 1940. Will you please refer to the correspondence restin? sh - iy&gt; ' with my demi-official letter No. C/606 dated the 23rd July 1940 in regard to Shaikh Hamad's demand for part of the Oil Concession payment of Ss 4 lakhs ? 2. Shaikh Abdullah and Shaikh Salman duly delivered my message to Shaikh Hamad and reported that Shaikh Hamad now realised that it was a mistake to make this demand and was dropping it. Yours sincerely. jh The Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel C. G. Prior, C^ I. E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire .4 1 1 h fl is I R, \ i fa i Confidential D.O. No. T/104-4/1 r A 7/ td Ziarat, the 16th August 1940 * Will you please refer to paragraph 4 of my demi- y'L &gt;$%' official letter No. C/606 dated the 25rd July 1940 ? 2. I had intended to have another talk with Shaikhs Abdullah and Salman before I left for recess, but I am sorry to say that I was unable to do so. During the first part of my last week in Bahrain the Shaikhs were totally disorganised by Shaikh Mohammad's return and during the last three days I myself was out of action with a bad throat. I will return to the attack immediately I get back to Bahrain. Yours sincerely. The Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel C. G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire,r^nfidentlal /&lt;?/*?&amp; COuFiOENTlAL RECORDS D.O.No.C/757-10/1. Dated the 7th October 1940, A, A fa* /u-^/ Will you please refer to the correspondence regarding the possible reduction by the next Shaikh of the share he retains of the Bahrain Oil Royalties. (I regret I cannot quote the reference as my file has not yet arrived from India). On the eve of Ramadhan I had a further long discussion with Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa and Shaikh Salman bin Hamad. I reminded them of our previous discussions and said I hoped they had given the matter careful thought. It was evident that they had not thought about it much, but they seemed to be in a malleable frame of mind. After I had repeated my previous arguments at full length and had discoursed on the necessity of being at least one jump ahead of the critics at all times, they remarked that the major difficulty was the appalling drain which Arab customs of hospitality and aid to old friends and adherents impose on a Shaikh's finances. They thought that economy might be effected by preparing an annual 'Privy Purse Budget' which would contain a definite, limited provision for Musa^dat (the Bahrain Shaikhs are inclined to confuse a Budget with Actuals, and to forget their propensity for ignoring it once it is framed). I encouraged this idea which at least has a certain amount of promise in it, but developed the theme that a provision of Rs. l£ lakhs for Musa'adat was ample. I then pointed out that the e xisting Civil List (apart from the share in Oil Royalties) amounts to almost exactly^ 4-1/3 lakhs annually. The Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel C.G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf including /- Bushire.including the Ruler's old personal allowance of Rs. lakhs. I know that Shaikh Hamad gives the whole of this lit 4-1/3 lakhs to the A1 Khalifah, whether in fixed allowances or in additional 'dollops', and I did not imagine that any- future Ruler would satisfy the Family with less. But Oil Royalties should average round about Rs. 32^ lakhs at a conservative estimate, and one fifth of this is Rs. 6^ lakhs. Deduct the Musa'adat provision of Rs. l^s- lahks and the Ruler is left with Rs.5 lakhs for his own personal enjoyment and gratification. How many A1 Khalifah Shaikhs had ever been able to rattle 5 lakhs in their pockets, knowing that not only the Family but also the honoured guest and the importunate beggar# were provided for separ ately ? It was evidently a startling thought, as was the follow-up that a confident Shaikh could reply to unconscion able demands on Shaikhly generosity - 'I am giving my people 26 lakhs every year from Oil Royalties. I give them tranquility and good order within my state (N.B. I had pre viously bean discussing the reorganisation of the Police); I give them a well-devised scheme of Education; I give them a high standard of Public Health; I give them good roads and a pure water supply in their towns (N.B # a now not too distant prospect); I give them (almost) free trade; I give them a fair administration and a freedom almost unknown in the Middle East from the tyranny and exactions of petty officials. Go, then, and make what you will by your own honest effort'. High-flown possibly, but unquestionably palatable. Less comforting, but not without effect was a reading of the article sent to me with your D.O.No.C/330 dated the 2nd September. , j ^ By this time the Shaikhs were becoming somewhat exhausted (we had already discussed other subjects) and Shaikh /-- 3 - /3&lt;t Shaikh Salman, in asking that they might go, delivered a somewhat obscure speech which appeared to indicate that while they fully understood the need for change in a changing world,and that the Ruler of Bahrain could undoubtedly do very well on a much smaller income, changes must be gradual. The new Shaikh, when his time came, must settle himself in ( an interesting remark in the light of other correspondence on a cognate subject) and when secure should unquestionably proceed on the advice which I had given in these two discuss ions. I am afraid that owing to the brief interval between my return from recess and the beginning of Ramadhan I cannot claim to have brought the affair to a definite conclusion. But I believe that it could now be clinched without undue trouble if you yourself would be prepared to receive Shaikh Abdulla and Shaikh Salman for a final discussion on your next visit here. My successor might not find it easy to embark on a discussion of such delicacy until he has been in Bahrain for some months and it would be well, I venture to suggest, to strike the final blow while the iron is still warm. Yours sincerely$ l ui&gt; Confid entlal No. C/768-4/1 b-;^: ■• ^re rgs 5 ^ncy.' a/a.. &amp;*,%, Dafe m/.tJ* The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to;— # CJNFiDSN liAL RECGP.DS The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 10 th October^.1940 Reference to previous correspondence; Description dj Name and Date. Subject. Summary of Revenue and Expenditure for the first half of year 1359 - (March - August, 1940)■Confldeatlal » B.O. BO# G/542» i^flce of the iolitical Ee^iient in the i^reian Golf# QampKuwai t 9 D€ce©t&gt;«r iOth 1940 • 7tb October 1940* I ass afraid i not able to take up this question when I tsao in jjahmln, but would like to dieauoa it with yon on roy next Tiait, when you will toe more au fait with the state's finanoes* i lease refer to Weightwan»8 derai official letter Bo. 0/ dated the Yours sincerely, or E*@#W» Altoan» o»E.n# f ■political Agent, Bahrain.h|nk 4 'i'elegram s. From Political Resident, at Bahrain. Government of India, x^ew Delhi. Repeated secretary of State for India, London, Ho. T/113. Dated the Si^t March 1941. I am having trouble over finance with Shaikh who wishe a to help family at expense of State Reserve. I hope to overcome this hut have just discovered that whole of reserve shown in rupees in budget is actually in sterling and now amounts to 661I' lakhs. Similary bulk of Shaikh*s private fortune of 12 lakhs is in sterling loans. Of these sums IS lakhs and 2- lakhs respectively have been remitted since war broke out. 2. Undesirability of reserves in currency subject t depreciation by exchagge is obvious and as they have been built up at our insistence Shaikh would expect us to make good any loss. Moreover in view of possible damage to oil fields they must be readily accessible and not subject to possible restrictions on movements of capital. Since Government of India have repatriated very large sums of capital I presume there will be no objection to Bahrain tr&amp;nsferring their investments into rupee securities and I propose to advise them to do so. 3. I understand Government of India allow States to invest in certain stocks without deduction ol income tax and would be glad of advice in due course as to what securities I should suggest to State. - Resident. , W.L.Translation of letter dated 13th Safar, 1360 from His Highness Shaikh Hamad tain Isa A1 Khalifah to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. After Compliments, It is not hidden from you that after we met at Sakhir with our brothers Shaikhs Mohamed and Abdulla and our son Shaikh Salman and after fully discussing our opinions the least possible estimate which can be taken as a basis at present is that we should take 2 lakhs from the middle third of the oil royalty and set aside from it 1 lakh for enter tainment and the other lakh to make up what is lacking in the A1 Khalifah pay. Your friend is convinced that the great and the small of the family are adversely a ffected. I am sendirg tEiis letter to you by the hands of our brothers Shaikhs Mohamed and Abdulla and our son Shaikh Salman and I trust that you will conclude this matter so that all may have rest after this trouble. Usual Ending.COPY ujnis CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS D.O. C/567-2/WL Bahrain, March i94i. Dear Alban. With reference to your letter dated «ist March 1941 on the subject of the State Reserve. The total investment up to date amounts to £500,000, and is in sterling. Of this £ ±34,750 was invested since the outbreak of the war. The Shaikh's investments are also in sterling and amounts to £ 90,8&lt;:7-^-l0. Of this £ j.4,814 was invested since the outbreak of war. 3. I shall consult you before making further investments. Yours sincerely, 8d/- C. Dalrymple Belgrave Major R.u.E.W. Alban, O.B.K. H.B.M's political Agent, Bahrain.110.185-S. British Reeidenoy &amp; oonsulate.Oeneral, mehire, the 10th ^pril, 1941# To Hie Uighneae Shaikh Sir Hamad bin lea aX Khalifa, K,C.I.B.»C,S.I., Ruler of iiahrain • My dear Friend, i f o)t will you please refer to your letter of the 13th Safar 1360 to the AdTieer ? I dieouesed this matter with Your Highness 1 brothers, but am sorry I did not have time to speak about it before my departure from Bahrain. I am therefore replying by letter instead* I must say that I am very dis appointed that this question has been raised again and i had hoped that with the tremendous increase that had been made in Your Highness' and the al Khalifa's incomes that the matter had been settled for ever. Major Daly onoe said as a joke 14 years ago that if your income was increased ten times you would still be in want. It has now increased seven times and it seems as if his Joke will come true. Then , no one thought even in a dream that ithat the inoome would inorease eevtn times, but now that it has happened I cannot understand why it should not suffice. 2» Your Highness will see from the - i ■ attached memorandum that your income has increased from ^8.1,65,000/- in the year 1351 to Hs#12,93,000/- in 1359, in other words an increase of over seven times the amount formerly enjoyed* in the last 5 years this increase has been very rapid and has amounted to its.56,30,000/- as against an income of Hs.10,92,000/- in the preceding 5 years. I think you must be one of the most fortunate men in the «• East for not only do you enjoy an income of over 13 lakhs a year, which must be one of the largest incomes in the East, but you have no taxes, rates, rents or similar expenses to meet which others have to. let us ccopare this Family with other Families in India. As you are aware,in India Ruler b restrict themselves and their families to 10 per cent of the country* s income whereas in this State Your Highness and the al Khalifa together receive 35 per cent of the total revenue. 3, Last year Your Highness and the / FamilyFamily received the huge sum of Re*18,54,634/- from the State. The al Subah of Kuwait who are a family as noble as the al Khalifa and as numerous do not receive a quarter of this sua. While in Bagdad I enquired the amounts received by the Royal Family there and His Excellency the ximbassador told me that the late King Ghazi used to receive 20*000/* a year, about Rs.lS lakhs, and the Regent now receives only £ 12,000/- or R b.7,80,000/-. in other words lour Highness receives as much as the King of a country with thirty five times the population of Bahrain, and yet this is not enough. Is the money poured into the sea I knew Bahrain before all this wealth came and apart from a few more motor cars, and a few more gold swords and some new houses 1 cannot understand where it all goes. The al Khalifa are not more numerous, they pay no taxes, they do not even pay for their sons' education, and those who work receive an additional 28,440/* rupees for their trouble. 4. It will be seen from the attached memorandum that the payments to the Family for the last 5 years / havehave reached a total of Re.lSf77,000/» or Rb «2»55,400/- per annum in addition to the ordinary Civil List of Rs* 2#88,254/ In the previous 5 years they only reoeived Re.26,000/- in addition to the usual Civil List* This is, of course, an enormous increase, and if they organise their affairs carefully like othexjpe ople they should toe more than satisfied with this amount. If Your Highness wishes to increase this still further I can only suggest that the amounts be paid from your own income Which had a balance of 3 lakhs last year and has a large balance at the moment. Your savings now amount to over 17 lakhs iihich should suffice ior any present needs, and also a reduction could now toe made in the Rs.l,14,000/- paid to Bedouin. As recently as 1355 only 118.30,000/- was paid, and large numbers of people who do not belong to Bahrain and who have no claims whatever on it are now receiving large sums of money. I am afraid, however, that the more you give the Family the more they will want from you. 5 # we do not desire anything exoept the prosperity oi Bahrain. When the Utate was poor we regretted /itit# and now that it ie rich we rejoice with yon, hat riches have brought danger ao great ae the poverty of former times* While you have grown rich your euhjeote have grown poor, and oid ng to the decay of the pearl trade moot of the Bahrain merchants have been ruined* I am aware that Your Highness is not responsible for their ruin, but when they see a family already very wealthy crying out for more and more money their discontent will increase until it becomes dangerous Last year there were attacks on Bahrain in the Iratjti Press, where they said that the Shaikhs of this coast received great sums in oil Royalties and did nothing for their subjects* In fact X had to ask His Excellency the iuosbassad or to check these attacks* This year when Shaikh Muhammad bin Xsa went to the mainland at the Zd a merchant said to me **10ok, he has bought two new motor cars, but he has to go to the mainland to escape Id expenses here'* I do not care to hear remarks like these and told him so but I am afraid there are many who think in this way* 6* It would be very dangerous to touch the one third set aside for the reserve, for if it is once touched it / willwill soon cease to be the reserve• This is the anchor of the State and you will need it in the storms that lie ahead of us# Byery year tremendous quantities of oil leave the soil of Bahrain, never to return, and it is essential that some of the profits should be kept for the future. Apart from this, the income itself is very vulnerable for a bomb, which God forbid, or a fire or even lack of ships may reduce it or perhaps stop it altogether and then Bahrain will be left with an income of ten lakhs or less from Customs, which itself would soon dwindle away now that the pearl trade is ruined• I myself have always thought that the one third share now enjoyed by Your High ness was too great and was about to ask you if you could see your way to reduce it • in Iraq, as you are probably aware, the oil revenues are only used for capital expenditure e.g. on bridges and railways, and are not used for normal expenditure at all* 7. To conclude, therefore, if Your Highness wishes to increase the emoluments of the al Khalifa ( whose / income/ income has already been doubled in the last fire years) I hope that yon will do it from the one third of the Royalties now enjoyed by you or fro® the amount now spent on Bedouin# I trust that the reserve of one third will not be touched in any way, but left intact so that it may hold the ship of the State firm in the hour of need* This is what had to be said and may you be preserved. I desire to express the high consideration which I entertain for Your Hi^iness, and to subscribe myself Your Highness 1 sincere friend. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. . \\ ■ v - \So, 184 ••S • British Residency k Coneulate-General, Bushire, the 10th April, 1941. To His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin lea aX Khalifa, C«S«X*, My dear Friend, I have been much ensbarrassed to hear of these requests for larger sums for the al Khalifa following so soon upon lour Highness* first gift of R8.4 lakhs to His Majesty's Government and the more reoent one of R b .30,000/- which you gave me for the Persian Gulf fighter Fund. 1 am therefore asking the Political Agent not to receive any sums from the al Khalifa for the Fighter Fund lest they should subsequent^ make this the basis of further demands upon the State« Z desire to express the high consideration which I entertain for Your Highness, and to subscribe myself Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Ruler of Bahrain. Your Hig * sincere friend.S0.185 -S of 1941• British He&amp;idenoy &amp; Consulate •General, 3ugiiire # the 10th iiprilj. 194!• To The Political Agent, Bahrain* Subject i Bahrain Finances. ,l«° ,4-1 Meiaoranduia » / f Unclosed are two letters to the Shaikh of Bahrain, Hos»i83»S and 184&lt;-S of todays date* Could you kindly have the Arabic version filled in before forwardiiig them to His Highness* 2. Copies of both for your records and a copy of Ho*l83~S for the Adviser, Bahrain Governaent, are included, also an additional copy of each letter which taay please be returned after the Arabic version has been entered thereon* sd* 0.0.Prior* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Attested * &gt;7 /c? . CA v^/ . for secretary to the lolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf*CONFIDENTIAL . No. 187-S Of 1941• The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tiic S8or«1»ary to the Govermaent of India.* iixteraial iiffairs Dspartwent, Hew Delhi* 1 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BTJSHIRE. Dated.... Reference to previous correspondenc : Politioal Beeident's telegram Uo#T/li3 of 23rd March 194!• Description o Name and Date. Subject. 1* O Tranelation of letter dated. 13th Safar,1360, from the Shaikh of Bahrain to the Advieer to the Bahrain, Government• a# Letter Ho«l83-S of 10JJ 1 April 1941 to the Jhaikh of B hrain, with enoloeore Cosy forwarded # with oom Political Agent, Bahrain Finances• pliroentSf to the Bahrain*19/176 Telegram Prom To Repeated Ho. 1681. Dated 10 Personal. Following for JPrior repeated Peel# Your telegram T/113 March 23rd. Bahrain InTestmente. E. Reasons given for transfer do not appeal to us here. There appears to be no grounds for expecting depreciation of sterling relative to rupee. You may be thinking of depreciation of sterling and rupee in common relation to gold and dollars owing to war. 3. Government of India have repatriated their liabilities whereas question here is of assets. We are also aware of no stronger reason to apprehend restrictions on capital movements from United Kingdom than from India. General practice is to adopt similar measures more or less simultaneously throughout sterling area so far as countries outside sterling area are concerned while maintaining free exchange within area. 4. Finally transfer would no doubt lead to loss of confidence in Bahrain by suggesting insecurity of British Governments funds, in the circumstances we consider it undesirable that proposed advice should be given to Shaikh and no reply is therefore being sent to paragraph 3 of your telegram « - POBEIGH. S. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Resident, Bushire . Secretary of State for india, London, th received lith April 1941.Telegram S. I?rora to Repeated to lo. 242 Dated 14th Ap±il 1941 Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, Hew Belhi# Secretary of State for India, London. Personal. Following for Garoe repeated to Peel*- Bahrain investments. Your telegram Ho. 1681 of April 10th. 2. I am not thinking of depreciation of sterling and rupee vis a vis gold and dollars and cannot agree that there are no grounds for expecting depreciation of sterling in relation to rupee. Britain is incurriiag indebtedness at a much greater rate than India and it is ohvious that this alone threatens her financial structure. 3* At end of last war Government were unable to control rupee which rose to 2/10. If this happens again state will find their reserve reduced by half and years of patient work to induce Ruler to save will be wasted. It would be useless tell Shaikh that Government had repatriated liabilities whereas he would have been repatriating assets, 4. Unless therefore you are prepared to indemnify state against any loss by exchange only honest course is to allow them to turn sterling into their own currency viz. rupees. Otiierwise, with respect, it appears to me that you are being patriotic with other people's money. 5. I believe Belgrave has already commenced / movemove. Shaikh has ftot so far as know been told but woulu attach little inrportance to it. -Britconsul•19/176 Telegram q From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain# No.274. Dated the 18th April 1941* My letter Ho*185-S lOth April. Bahrain Finances. Please let me know result by mail. BRITCCffTSUI. C.V.A.19/176 Telegram From Political Reaidtant, Bushire. Government of India, New Delhi. Ho• 275 Dated 13th April 1941,. Last instalment of royalties leaves Bahrain Government with large rupee balance which they wish to invest in Government of India loan. Glad if you would kindly indicate loan in which States are allowed to invest money without payment of income tax. 4' /4' Britconsul drf/ ft* 19/176 Telegram S. ii'rom Government of India, Me?/ Delhi» To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London. Ho. 1863 Dated Slat received 22nd April 1941. / 3^' Personal for Prior repeated Peel. k / p Your telegram No. 2 42 of April. 2. We consider your arguments misconceived and we maintain view already expressed in our telegram v &lt; Ho. 1631 of 10th April. \V* - V li&gt;D 3. ' We do not understand significance of your phrase 'allow State to turn sterling into rupees', le understood from your telegram Ho.T/113 of 23rd March that you proposed to advise State to adopt this course. We repeat that we consider such advice injudicious and if Belgrave is in fact acting on advice given by you we must ask you to inform him that it is not repeat not endorsed here. foreignConfidential No. C/336-4/1. of L 'h BUSH IRE RESIDENC Y. a/o lfri-z Date. '¥/*/ 1 'MWVD-mV. cecghds | ^ Political Agents Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- h^r h The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) and to request instructions as to the reply to be given, T he agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 17 th April 194 1« Reference to previous correspondence: 1 Description dj Name and Date. 1. Letter No.577-2WL dated April 14, 1941 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the PoliticafL Agent, Bahrain. 2. Letter No.578-SE 1/2 dated April 14, 1941 from Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Politica Agent, Bahrain. Subject. State Reserve, INo.577-2V.TL Bahrain, dated April 14, 1941. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, State 'Reserve I have the honour to inform you that the Bahrain Government wish to invest a further sum of seven lakhs of rupees to be added to the reserve and to request your advice in the matter. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government. From ToNo.578-3E1/2. Bahrain, dated Apriih 14th, 1941. C, Dalrymple Relgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Advrlser lo the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that His Highness Shaikh Hamad wishes to invest one lakh, Rs. 1,00,000/-, of his personal income. I have informed him that investment in rupee currency, not steling, is recommended / and he wishes me to obtain your advice as to where the money would be best invested, taking into consideration the question of ineome tax. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government From Toi Confidential No. C/341 - 4/1 t ^\ n nc BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. Date 'co^ro^tia 'records The Political Agents Bahrain, Presents his compliments to;— J* I The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) T he agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 19th Apr il 1941 Reference to previous correspondence; U In continuation of Bahrain P.L. Ho. C/336 dated the 17th April 194x Description of Name and Date. Subject. Letter Ho. 604-2.W.L. dated the 17th April 1941 from the Adviser |«^t o the Bahrain Government, y State Reserve - Bahrain Finances. r J «. - ^j %&lt; 3 sled.No* Office of the Adviser to the Governjaent. Bahrain. Dated, R/Awal 20. 1360 ii.pril 17, 1941. from G. Dalrymple Balprave, Esquire, Adviser to tne ixovernasnt of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour t© refer t© the conversation which I had recently with the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Colonel 0. G. Prior, on the subject of the Reserve fund of the Bahrain State, This fund, with the approval of His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Alkhalifah, has, from the beginning, been invested in British Government securities, War Loan and Government of India stock. His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad's own investments amounting t© £90,837. ir-also in 3^ War Loan. These invest ments in the past have been made with the knowledge of Hie Britannic Majesty's Politioal ..gents in Bahrain and have been referred to in annual reports and in quarterly financial returns. I would not assume the responsibility of investing over half a million pounds sterling belonging to the state and its Ruler without first obtaining the opinion of the Political igent as to in what loans it should be invested.C o I oeq I Prior was unaware that the Reserve fund was invested in sterling stock and he very strongly recomended that it should he withdrawn and transferred into rupee investmentHe was of the opinion that the money could not easily ho converted from sterling into rupees. I enclose a copy of a letter from the Manager of the Eastern Bank in Bahrain, from whieh it appears that this transfer is possible. 3# The government holds £450,000 in War Loan and £50,000. in Government of India stock. The former was quoted in London on 6th April as standing at 104f. If it was sold at this price it would realise approximately £468,000. I do not know at what price the Indian loan is standing at present but assuming that it is at par the total investment if realised would produce £518,000. This converted into rupees is approximately fis. 69,04,940/-. The original cost of the whole stock was 66,50,864/-, the difference would be approximately fis 2,54,000/-. This, in itself, appears to be a profitable transaction. 4. I have examined lists of Government of India gilt edged securities and there does not at present appear to be any investment which would give as good a yield, free of income tax, as the present investment. I do not know the position of the Bahrain state regard ing liability for income tax or investments in India. Colonel Prior mentioned certain Government of India stock which might be obtained without liability of income tax in which the funds of some of the Indian states are invested. I snould be obliged if you could obtain the advice of the Government of India about this stock. The state wishes to invest a further 7 lakhs new —3—lakhs now and His Highness wishes to invest 1 lakh so I should be obliged if advice could be given as soon as possible, 5» With regard to the half million sterling invested in London, the Bahrain governaent can instruct its bankers iimediately by cable to sell all or part of the investments u.nd to transfer the capital to India but before doing so I should like to be assured that it is the opinion of the Government of India that this step is to the financial advantage of the state. I have the honour to be, 3ir, Your most obedient servant, Mviser to the Government,Copy of a letter dated 17th Aoril 1941 from the Mamager t Eastern Basic, Limitea, B?ihrain, addressed to ilie Aaviser to the Bihrain U-OTeruienx, Bahrain# (Private and Qonfideatial). year Sir, lith refereuce to your personal letter No. 496 of the 5th of April to the undersigned, we give below a copy of a telegram dated the 15th of April we have received from our London Office in reply to your enquiry regarding the sals of Doth the governments and His Higtoess's Sterling Securities•- ^Tours 6th no official restriction here on transactions mentioned s*i;op Bahrain govern ment holdings in our name we could elfeet immediate sale stop Shaikh Hamad stock his name cannot sell till arrival transfer deeds we forward Dlank deeds todays maii M * Yours faithfully, Sd/ M« Gunn. Manager*19/176 Telegram ^rom Political Resident, Bushire • To Political Agent, Bahrain, lo. 295. Dated the 25th April, 1941. , |M Your Printed Letter Ho.C/34l April 19th 1941. Do your records show any reference to Residency 'before investments were made - Britconsul. .l.19/176 Telegraja S, Srom Political Resident# Bushire. To Government of India, Simla* Repeated to • Secretary of State for India, London. Ho. 297 Dated 25th April 1941. ■Personal for Garoe repeated to Peel. Your telegram Ho. 1863 of April 2131. 2. I have just received formal appli- -cation from Belgrave regarding State investments which I am forwarding with comments 'by mail. Bri tconsul H.L.19/176 n 1. Te legram From To Repeated No#4662 Dated 26th received 27th April 1941. S Secretary of State for Indie » London# Government of India, Simla. Political Resident, Bushire. Personal. For Ceroe from Peel repeated Prior- yh Your telegram Ho.1863. Bahrain Securities. We quite agree. Secretary of State.19/176 Telegram 'Q,'' .b'rom uovernraent of xndia, blmla. political Resident, uustiire mo* 0 9 Dated 26th receired 27th April 194 lour telegram 275 April 18th. investment ol' Bahrain rupee tJalanee# mant of India loans will be exenipt from income tax. atate may therefore invest its rupee balance by purchasing securities ol any government of mdia loan in market or by direct subscription to current 3^ Defence .Loan 1949-52. Secretary of Reserve isank of India should be consulted direct it amount to be invested is large as Bank may be able to maxe arrangements that will avoid rise m prices owing to possibility of market heing short of particular loans desired. Position has been explained to Reserve Bank of india^ All investment by Bahrain (iovemment in liovern— - FORSJION - p. (U, c-o a., 2-7r,j,i7* 19/176 Telegram Q,. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire . No.95. Dated and received 28th April, i94l. Your telegram Ho.295. According to our records no reference has ever been made to Political Resident before investment. General mention of amounts already invested has been made in budgets and statements for past years forwarded to Political Resident. -Political. W.L.Saifei*. ,.r. c. n /ni Confidential . N0.273-S of 1941. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 1st May, 1941. From - The Hon , ble Lieut.-Colonel C.G.Prior, C.I.B., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Sir, f.ll' C'fC I have the honour to enclose for favour of orders a copy of a letter, Ho.604/2.W.L., dated the i7th April 1941, from the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain to the Political Agent asking for advice regarding the investment of the State Reserve. 2. The balance of the Bahrain Government was originally placed on fixed deposit with the Eastern Bank, hut about the s year 1934, acting apparently upon the advice of the then Political Agent, Colonel Loch, Mr.Belgrave began to invest a Reserve Fund in British 3i^ War Loans and Government of India Stocks and investment in these sterling Stocks has been proceeding since that date without consideration of whether altered circumstances made conversion into sterling advisable or not. 3. The procedure for political officers who are consulted regarding the investment of State funds is clearly laid down in Section 17 of Chapter II of the Political Department Manual. This prescribes that if advice is asked for in the investment of Government Securities (other than Government notes in the special form mentioned in paragraph 53(2} of the Government of India Security Manual of 1921) a political officer should, if the Ruler agrees, place the whole /conduct-2- conduct of affairs at once in the hands of the Auditor General. If this procedure is not agreeable to the intending investor he should decline to have any part in the trans action. 4. It is unfortunate that not merely were these instructions ignored, hut that no reference to this Residency was made at any time before the advice mentioned by Mr. Belgrave was given. I cannot find any papers to show that my predecessor was aware what currency the investments were in and his demi-official letter iro.C/785 of the 15th October 1938 to the India Office he mentions them as being in 'Government of India War Loan Bonds at which does not appear in any Stock Exchange List. I regret that I was throughout under the impression that the State Reserve was in rupee Stocks since the Reserve was always expressed in rupees. However, when collecting material to combat Shaikh Hamad's desire for more money, an item caught my eye, in which the amounts were expressed in sterling, and I discovered to my surprise that the entire Reserve was in sterling. I enquired from Mr.Belgrave how, as Financial Adviser, he came to consider a currency other than its own for the State Reserve, particularly in wartime, and he told me that the original investment had been recommended by Colonel Loch and had appeared good at the time. A possibility that the suitability of an investment might change in 7 years does not appear to have entered Mr. Belgrave »s head. I told him that in my opinion the appropriate currency for a State entirely dependent upon a rupee currency was a rupee security and he has now formally applied for advice. 5. It is obvious that the appropriate currency for a State Reserve is its own, more especially when dealing / with/ 7* IS' -3- with an ignorant Ruler who is unaware of such matters as the depreciation of currency. It will be recalled that the present Shah of Persia took the depreciation of the dollar when the United States of America left the gold standard as a personal affront, and placed a special import tax upon American motor vehicles to recompense himself for the loss he had sustained. We need not expect any more enlightened attitude on the part of Shaikh Hamad and the Al Khalifah family. During the last War the Government of India were unable to control the rupee which rose to 2S.lOd. and was finally fixed at lS.6d. instead of the previous rate of lS.4d. Even a small alteration in price would affect the State very seriously and a loss in the Reserve would completely undermine the Shaikh's confidence in it and lead to immediate demands to enjoy current profits and the work of years would be undone and the financial structure of the State over thrown. 6. It is nearly 20 years since we assumed control of the finances of the Bahrain Government and the Shaikhs have accepted our advice, unwillingly at times, and have relied on us implicitly regarding their investments. Any loss caused by this will naturally reflect very seriously upon our credit, and I feel that it should be intimated to the State that the appropriate currency for their Reserve is the currency of the State itself. If the rupee depreciates in value, they will then have nothing to say, whereas if sterling depreciates in value they will have a very great deal and will say it at the fullest pitch of their lungs. If we deliberately retain the State Reserve in sterling, we should be prepared to indemnify them if the State is ultimately involved in loss as a result of our policy.7 It is possible that the Government of India may be reluctant to advise the Bahrain Government upon a course which may be construed as reflecting upon the stability of sterling. In that case it appears to me that the least we can do is to inform the State that the question of the currency in which to keep their balance is one for them to decide, but/^if they wish to make rupee investments the mode of iaavestraent has already been intimated to them, as I have stated above, however, I recomrnend that the State should be advised to keep their Reserve in the currency which is employed in the State» 8. I am sending a oop| of this letter to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India by special air mail. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. that Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ♦sent under Printed Letter No.274-S of 1st May 1941./s? Uonf identia.U The Kesidency, d.o.i4o.27b-'a. UuaiUre, the let Hay 1941 Bear Aiban, I enclose a copy of a telegram from the Uovemment f&gt;'IW of India in reply to my telegram Ho, ol' the 18th April 1941^ of which oopy is also enclosed. 2* The simplest course appears for the shaikh^ own oalance to be invested with that of the utate, as by this means he will escape paying income tax and his heirs will avoid any difficulty over succession or estate duty. if this proposal does not commend itself to the Bahrain Govern ment then £ will apply for permission for him to purchase notes in the special form governed by paragraph 53(2) of the yovernment securities iianual 1921. 5. Please let m know if my assistance is required} otherwise it would appear in order for Belgrave to deal direct with the Secretary of the Keserve Bank of India. Yours sincerely. *ajor H.ti.W. Alban» O.B.ii;., Political -agent, Bahrain.No. nj ik BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. C/350 - 4/1 No .^7 ......... Date com 35 n ttal re53f, ds —— vPi^v The Political Agents Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:« The Honoyrable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy ©f the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 21st A P ril 1941 Reference to prsvious correspondence: Resident's memorandum No. 185-S dated the 10th Zpril 1941 Description df Name and Date. ^ '' c Letters No. 18o-S and No. 184-S dated the 10th April 1941, with Arabic versions rilled in. Subject. 1 Bahrain Finances., bush ' | RE R EsinRNi-vn No.... ./.v.jz^/ CONFIDENTI AL RECORDS Political Agency, Bahrain, the 7th May 1941. Jl L9 l- *! Confidential D. C. No. x ' JDj&amp;CISeJtsuuJ Your telegram No. 274 dated the ISth April 1941. 2. As requested in your memorandum No. 185-S dated the ICth April 1941, your two letters Nos. 183-S and 184-S were translated and sent to His Highness. 3. His Highness has now replied and I enclose his letter together with a translation. I also enclose a copy of Belgrave r s note to me on the reactions of the Shaikhs, one of the things that has stung them (and Belgrave) is that a merchant should have had the temerity to voice a criticism . I may say here that during the last few years the policy has been to allow the A1 y Khalifah to keep on increasing their ascendancy over the public and to deprive the latter of any means of voicing grievances either to the Adviser or to the Political Agent. Belgrave is inaccessible to the public, complaints against the administration are not allowed and, even to this day, visitors to the Agency are strongly discouraged in various ways such as being called 'Agency spies' etc. It is not therefore surprising -f that the Shaikhs and Belgrave have had somewhat of a shock. 4. At the Joint Court this morning Shaikh Hamad spoke to me on the subject. at the suggestion contained in your letter No. 184-S that/- Th e Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel He said he was much upset C. G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . iis y- 2 - that he had given the donations to the Fighter Fund in order to ask for more money. He said that he and his family were reedy at all times to give all the help within their power to the British Government and that his request for increased allowances was only made in view of the rise in the cost of living since the war which had nit those memtiers of the family v /ho get the smaller allowances. J. replied that the Political Resident had the welfare of the State at heart and that he certainly would not wish to accept any subscriptions from the Shaikhs if this meant that they would ask for increased allowanc e s aft erwards. 6. vie have, however, the Shaikh^s assurance that he will not for ohe duration of the war. at any rate, make any inroads on the ■jlrd revenue. Yours sincerely,\ Translation of letter dated the 8th Habi-ul-Thani 1360^ (4th May 1941) from His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Hos. 183 and 184 dated the 10th April 1941 and read all that you wrote in connection with ray letter to Mr. Belgrave about the Bahrain revenues and the arrangements necessary for this year. Your Honour, I appreciate your valuable advice and the sorrow you expressed for past years when the revenues were small and insufficient to meet the expenditure and your pleasure when conditions improved. The reason for my wishing to increase the allowances of my family, the /\1 Khalifah, is the apparent increase in prices of all things. There are also certain individuals of the family for v /hom no allowances have been made and others whose allowances are small but I agree that we should not touch the -^-rd reserve under the present 1 thank you for telling the merchant who told you about something which does not concern him that you do not care to hear such things. We shall try as much as possible to order our expenses in a proper manner. I repeat my thanks to Your Honour for your good intentions towards my country and myself. After your two letters difficult circumstances. Usual EndingConfidential 6 th May 1941, Dear Alban, i&gt; i The Shaikhs were very upset 'by Prior 1 s letter. It was not so much the fact that he did not approve of H.H's suggestion - I have told them both before the matter became official and afterwards that I was sure he would not approve - but the style of the letters hurt them. Shaikh Salman has taken it most to heart. They think that some of the remarks in the letter originated from criticisms of the Shaikhs made by Yusuf Kanoo, Khalil Moayad and one or two others who, they think, hope to profit by making trouble between the Shaikhs and the Agency. I think Y.K. has been making some rather silly remarks which were repeated to the Shaikhs, They don't agree with all the figures of H.H's expenditure saying that the amount spent on Bedu etc. includes some other items and I think the three senior Shaikhs feel that before I sent the figures to you there should have been a discussion about the amounts with them. As you know I told H.H. that you had asked for details and that I was sending them but I did not discuss the figures with the other three Shaikhs. The letters have been seen by some of the sons and a number of the servants and hangers on at Sakhir. H.H. himself shows great reluctance to discuss it, he wrote the replies without consulting anyone, in fact I have not seen his answers. Major R.G.E.W. Alban, Political Agent, Bahrain, Yours sincerely, 3d/-C. Dalrymple Belgrave i f |Confidential* The futsidency, Buehire, the 21at May, 1941• D &gt;0,I? o »328»S&gt; / Dear Alban. t/c Please refer to your demi-official letter Ho*0/418- 4/1, dated the 7th May 1941, regarding B^irain finances. upon his sagacious move and hope that you will have no further difficulty now. I intervened in the matter myself so as to save you the unpleasantness of coming into conflict with the Huling family at the outset of your time as Political Agent, but these matters are normally your pigeon ami 1 now return the ball to you, 3. As regards the hurt feelings, I may say that I have a very long experience of finaacial arguments with the al Khalifah and I have never yet seen money kept away from them without some •misunderstandings' 1 or hurt feelings arising somewhere• once, when money was far scarcer than it is now and I oomplained that though the al Khalifah kept on increasing the Civil Mst could not be expected to keep pace, shaikh Muhammad bin Isa claimed that I had advocated birth control which was contrary to the Holy Q.uran 5 sr 4« If you refer to my letter No*184~3 of 10th April 1941 to Shaikh Hamad, saying that I do not wish to receive oontributions from the al Khalif^h to the Persian Gulf Fighter Fund, you will see that the reference was to the al Khalifah (who have so far not contributed a single cent) aad not to His Highness, Would you kindly make this clear to him and 2, I enclose a reply for the Shaikh complimenting lite / aay Major u*Q»Alban, Political Agent, Bahrain•way that I had, of oouree, no Intention of reflecting on his generosity which has been most marked and for which we are vary grateful indeed* Yours sincerely. Copy sent to G .of India under d. o.P.L.lTo.335-S of 22•5.41, copy of bare P.L. sent to Bahrain.Ho*329.S of 1941. British Easidenoy &amp; Consulate-Gen ciral. Bushire, the 21st May, 1941• To Hie Highnese Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifah, K.O.I.B., o.s.i. # Ruler of Bahrain. letter dated the 8th Kabi-ul-Thani 1360 on the eubjeot of the Bahrain revenues. I m rery glad that Your Highnese has decided not to touch the one-third now allotted to the Reserve and congratul ate you upon this wise and far-seeing Step. It is most important to think of the future, and 1 am sure Your Highness is acting in the best interests of Bahrain by doing so. As regards certain individuals of the Family for whom no allowances have been made and for those whose allowances are small, it will be possible to provide for than within the limits of the one-third now enjoyed by Your Highness* With sincere wishes to Your High ness and assurances of my deep and perman ent interest in Bahrain, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 1 ' (Copy sent to G.of I .mnder d.o. P.L.iro.335-S of 22, 5,41, copy of bare P.L, sent to Bahrain. i remain, Yo ncere friend.Ii ni Confidential* Ho*330*3 of 1941. British Hcaidency &amp; Goneulate-Genaralt Buahire, the 2lst May 1941• To The Political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandum. Piease hare the Arahio Ttreion filled in before forwarding letter Ko•389-Sf dated the Slat May 1941# to the Shaikh* Gopy ia encloaed for your record, alao a aeaond copy which may please be returned with the Arabic Teraion* By Order* A- •y'4^/ for Secretary to the Political Heaident in the Peraian Gulf*19/176 Telegram q From Political'Res identBushire To Foreign, Simla- ITo.667 Dated the 16th June 1941# 4- rri i My letter Ho.273-S of May 1st. Bahrain State Reserve. I should be glad if reply' could be sent to me by air mail at Bahrein. BritconsulH copy. | . iJ^^L ltr mail . ft'] i'. 1$ ^ a'-' brrklTTIAL. , 1 ITo;D.2098-F/41. From • 1 &gt; The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, ^ o ifcfjipir pircjnrmc y His Majesty's Under Secretary of 3tate ' ^ for India, London. ' ^ v - ll&gt; L •&gt; Dated Simla, the 6th June 1941. F Investments of the Bahrain State Reserve, I am directed to refer to the letter from the lolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf No;273-S, dated the 1st May 1941 of which a copy was sent to you direct, in which the Resident recommends, in effect, that the Bahrain Government should he advised to transfer their present sterling securities to rupee securities and in future to maintain their reserve solely in rupee currency. 2, The Government of India are of opinion that this is a matter in which the final decision as to the advice to be given to the .Bahrain State must rest with His Majesty's Government, but they believe that it may be useful to place their own opinion on record. In the first place, the Government of India are unable to endorse the Residents deduction that the Persian Gulf Residency was not informed of the advice given to the Adviser to His Highness the Shaikh to invest the Bahrain balances in British 3^-% War Loan and 3*r% Government of India Sterling Stock. Though the late Resident evidently misnamed these investments^ || in his letter NojG /785, dated the 15th October 1938 to the i0 [ India Office (of which the Government of India have no copy), it is sufficiently obvious that he must have been aware of the real nature of the investments. They have,**no reason to criticize the advice given in 1934, and in their opinion the securities selected are, from the point of view of the Bahrain State, as sound today as they were then. The Government of India do not share the Political Resident r s apprehensions about what he considers the probable depreciation of sterling in terms of the rupee and do not see any reason to believe that the experience of the period immediately following the last war will necessarily be repeated after the present one. Nor do they think it axiomatic, as the Political Resident believes, that a State 1 s reserves can be appropriately invested only in securities in its own currency. Apart from the fact that in many circumstances external reserves held in a currency with international value like sterling are very useful, the close connection between sterling and the rupee and the practical interchangeability between the two at present make it unnecessary to draw any distinction between sterling and rupee securities for investment so far as Bahrain is concerned^ 4,, In the opinion of the Government of India, therefore, there is no reason to advise the State to change its existing securities. As regards any further sums that may become available, they may be advised there is no objection to invest ing them in rupee securities if they so desire on the assumption that the contingency which the reserve is supposed to guard against is a shortfall in revenue, in which case what the State will require will be funds in rupee currency. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Since there must be some interval before the final advice of His Majesty's Government can be •» c ommunicat ed,communicated, the Political Resident is being instructed to inform the Adviser to the Bahrain Government that the matter has been referred to His Majesty's Government, but that pending the receipt of the views of His Majesty's Government they would strongly deprecate any action to dispose of the State's sterling securities. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. O.K.Garoe, Secretary to the Government of India. Copy to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with the request to proceed as indicated in the concluding paragraph of this letter. By order, etc., Sd. H.Weightman, Deputy Secretary to the Government of MAIL* SJFIDENTIAL. No :D, 2737-^/41. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. Dated Simla, the 18th June 19 4 1. A copy of the foregoing paper is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with reference to his telegram Not667, dated the 17th June 1941, ^ By order, etc.. ► for Assistant 'Secretary to the Government of India. &lt;V^Y &amp; P'C\ - Pi. ft. w-jTT I 1.v r; r - Confidential ' v ffc- No ,0/645 -4/1 , The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to *0 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gi Camp, Bahrain and has the honour to forward herev/ith copies of the under mentioned documents. t ? ^ The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 23rd June 1941. ~ Reference to previous correspondence Political Resident's D.O.No. 275-S dated the 1st May 1941. v Description of Enclosure Name and Date 1, Memorandum No.C/409 dated the 6th May 1941 from the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. 2. Letter No.784-WL dated May 10, 1941, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Secretary, Reserve Bank of India, Bombay. Subject Bahrain State Reserve.I Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th May 1941. I I ■ i To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. STATE EESEEVE Memorandum Reference your letter No. 577-2WL and 578-SE 1/2 dated the 14th April 1941. 2. All investment by the Bahrain Government in Government of India loans will be exempt from income tax. It is therefore recommended that the State in vests its rupee balance by purchasing securities of any Government of India loan in market or by direct subscrip tion to current 3% Defence Loan 1949 - 52. The Secretary of the Reserve Bank of India, to whom the position has been explained, should be consulted direct as^Bank may be able to make arrangements that will avoid rise in prices owing to the possibility of the market being short of particular loans desired. 3. As regards investments by His Highness, the simplest course would appear to be for the Shaikh 1 s own balance to be invested with that of the State, as by this means he will escape paying income tax and his heirs will avoid any difficulty over succession or estate duty. If however this proposal does not commend itself to the Bahrain Government /- Confidential No.0/409-4/1.Government, then the Hon'ble the Political Resident is prepared to apply for permission for the Shaikh to pur chase notes in the special form governed by paragraph 53(2) of the Government Securities Manual 1921. 4. Would you kindly let me know if any assistance is required; otherwise it would be in order for you to deal direct with the Secretary of the Reserve Bank of India, Sd. R. G. Alban. Political Agent, Bahrain,No. 784 Bahrain, Dated May 10, 1941, From To C* Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. The Secretary, The Reserve Bank of India, Bombay. Sir, The Government of Bahrain has a Reserve Fund amounting to approximately £590,000. sterling now invested in War Loan and about Rs.7,00,000/- in the Eastern Bank, Limited, Bahrain. The Govern ment of India have recommended that the Reserve Fund should be transferred from England and invested in Government of India securities. 2. I am informed by His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent in Bahrain that all investments by the Bahrain Government in Government of India loans will be exempt from income tax. 3. The Bahrain Government would like to invest the v/hole amount in Government of India securities which will produce a yield of as near as possible 3j%. I understand that there is a 3% loan, 1963 - 65 now standing at about 94^. This appears to be the most suitable investment. 4. I should be very grateful if you would advise me whether you could make arrangements for this investment /-- 2 - investment, possibly by degrees, in such a way that a rise in prices could be avoided owing to the market being short of the particular loan which is required. I am informed that the position has been ex plained to you and I should be much obliged for your advice in the matter. Yours faithfully, Sd. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government.iijn^ v Confidential Ho .0/225 of 1941. Office of the Political Resident in the lersian Gulf, Oamp Bahrain. Bated the 27th June 1941. From To Sir, The Hon'hle Lieut.-Colonel G.G.Prior, C.I.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The Secretary to the Government of India in the iSxternal Affairs Department, Simla. 'i C / n [0* I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with Government of India letter lo.D.2098-1/41, dated the 6th June 1941, regarding the investments of the Bahrain State Reserve. It will be recalled that two questions were in- 4 volved, one ^which is dealt with in the above mentioned letter, namely, the question of the transfer of the Reserves tiWt' held in sterling to India, and the other, the investment of the balances which have recently accrued and which are held in rupees. 2. The latter question was referred by the Mviser, Bahrain Government, to the Political Agent in his letter li'} /ic No.577-2 W.L., together v/ith his letter lo.578-SBl/2, both dated the 14th April 1941, copies of which are en closed. The matter was referred by me to the Govern- ment of India in my telegram Ho.275, dated the 18th April 1941, and their reply was received in Government of India telegram /5. / Im 2 telegram Ho.25 C, dated the 26th April 1941. OopJes of these two telegraos are also enclosed for ready reference. It will be seen that the letters of the Bahrain Government refer only to the investment of rupees and in my telegram to the Government of India and in their reply this transaction was throughout referred to as the investment of the State's tt rupee balance 3. The orders of the Government of India were correctly passed on by the Political Agent to the Adviser in his confidential Memorandum Ho.0/409-4/1, dated the 6th May 1941, which read as follows! ' Memorandum Reference your letter Ho.577-2rfL and 578-SE l/2 dated the 14 ch -«.pril 1941. 2. All investment by the Bahrain Government in Government of India loans will be exempt from in come tax. It is therefore recommended that the State invests its rupee balance by purchasing securities of any Government of India loan in market or by direct subscription to current Defence Loan 1949 - 52. The Secretary of the Reserve Bank of India, to whom the position has been explained, should be consulted direct as Bank may be able to make arrangements that will avoid rise in prices owing to the possibility of the market being short of particular loans desired.*3. m 5* Mr. Belgrave underetood this to refer to the entire amount of the Heeerve Fumd including the Heserves held in sterling, and having been informed that the Bank should be consulted direct, he concluded the transactions without further reference to the Agency or this Residency, I only learnt upon ray arrival that the entire Reserve had been brought out from England and had been re-inveet- ed in India. It appears that Mr.Belgrave consulted the Shaikhs, who approved of the transfer in writing, and that the whole transaction resulted in a net profit of 2 lakha of rupees. While, therefore, I regret that it is not possible to carry out the orders of the Government of India contained in their letter of the 6th June 1941, it appears that the transfer was entirely due to a mis understanding which has, however, been profitable to the Bahrain Government. Majesty's Secretary of State for India and the Political Agent, Bahrain. * I am sending a copy of this letter to tKE His I have the honour to be. Sir Your m lent servant. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. * sent under P. L.So.0/226 dated 27/6/41 V \ \Confidential No. C/564 si T The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) T he agency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. Dated,. 9th June 1941 Reference to previous correspond spondence: Tf 1^3 Resident 1 s memorandum No* 330-S dated the 21st May 1941 Description dj EnclostiTZ* Name and Date. Letter No* 329-3 dated 21st May 1941, with Arabic version filled in. Subject. Bahrain Finances.Confidential Fo. C/591 From jt/ni Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th June 1941. Major R.G.S.W, Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain, To The Honourable the Political Resident . in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. » Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith the following papers (1) A comparative statement showing receipts and expenditure for the years 1358 and 1359 and the budget estimate for the year 1360. (2) Final figures of Revenue and Expenditure of the Bahrain State for the year 1359, together with a summary exhi biting details of the State Reserve, (3) Notes by the Adviser on Revenue and Expenditure for the same year. (4) Revenue and Expenditure Budget figures for the year 1360, together with a schedule of public works. (5) Notes by the Adviser on expected Revenue and Expenditure. 2. Receipts &gt; During the year 1359 receipts dropped by Hs 3,22,734; this was due mainly to drops of Rs 1,55,888 in Customs receipts and Rs 82,843 in Royalty on oil, due to some shortage of tankers as a result of the war. The drop in Customs revenue is the beginning of a decline due to the reduction in activities of the Oil Companies and the poverty and unemployment prevailing in the Island. These irw fluences are continuing in an aggravated form during the current year and the Adviser has rightly allowed for a further drop of about Bs 2 lakhs in Customs revenue and about Rs 6 lakhs in Royalty. 3. Expenditure Expenditure in 1358 was Rs 36,75,434 and in 1359 it amounted to Rs 29,14,372. Deducting the Shaikh's gift ofRs. 4 lakhs towards the cost of the War, the net reduction in expenditure was Rs 3,61,062. Of this the most important item was a decrease of Es 3 lakhs in Public Works expenditure due to the non-completion of the Manama - Muharraq bridge. For the current year it is estimated that expenditure will amount to Es 29,55,000, but there is likely to be an increase under the head 'Experimental Farms' (which might be replaced by the more usual head 'Agriculture'), on the arrival of the Agricul tural Expert from Egypt as, in addition to paying him, it will be necessary to form a small department in order to enable him to function at all. If the new Principal of the Technical College arrives a further increase under the head 'Education' will result. The most outstanding point is that the Ruling Family is likely to take a reduction in income of about Rs 2 lakhs in the current year. 4. Investment Surplus My predecessor, in his notes on last year's budget, considered that the estimated sum of Rs 13 lakhs for investment would be exceeded and this has proved correct, as it was possible to add a sum of over Rs 16^ lakhs to the Reserve at the end of 1359. The present situation is not favourable for making fore casts but it is possible and even probable that the estimated surplus of Rs 6 lakhs for the year 1360 will be exceeded by 2 or 3 lakhs. 5. Submission of the budget has been delayed owing to errors in calculation of figures by the Adviser which necessi tated his rewriting part of the notes. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Agent, Bahrain.Revenue 1359. The estimated revenue in the Budget for 1359 was Rs 45,07,000/-# The actual revenue collected was Hs 49,01,499/-, The actual revenue exceeded the anticipated amount by Bs 3,94,449/-• The actual revenue in 1358 was Hs 45,78,765/-. Revenue in 1359 exceeded that of 1358 by The 1359 receipts however included two abnormal items amounting to Rs 5,61,972/- being the payment made by the Bahrain Petroleum Company on signing the oil con cession over the additional area and the price obtained by the government from the sale of rice which had been bought in 1358 as a special war measure. If these two items of abnormal revenue are not taken into con sideration the revenue in 1359 was Rs 43,39,527/- which is Ss 2,39,238/- less than the revenue during the previous year. Customs revenue was approximately li lakhs lower, oil royalty was approximately Rs 83,000/- less and there was a decrease of approximately Bs 48,000/- in land revenue. This last item in 1358 included some abnormal receipts. Other sources of revenue produced slightly less than in the previous year. During the year Rs 16,52,745/- was added to the Reserve fund and invested in War Loan.Expenditure 1359. The total expenditure during the year was Rs 29,14,372/- excluding the amount paid into the Reserve Fund. Approximately one half of the total expenditure was paid to the Ruling Family in the Civil List and one third of the oil revenue. The amount spent on special public works, mostly of a non recurrent nature was Rs 3,18,000/-. This about three lakhs less than the budgeted amount ©wing to the non completion of the Manamah-Muharraq. bridge. The cost of administration whioh includes the various government offices, courts, education, medical services, municipalities and recurrent public works was approximately 7 lakhs. Unforseen expenditure, Rs 46,000/-, includes the cost of bazaar property amounting to Rs 39,000/- which was purchased by the government when sold by a Persian subject. Total expenditure in 1358 was Rii 36,75,434/- and in 1359 it was Us 29,14,372/-, The expenditure in 1359 was approximately Rs 7,61,000/- less than during th« previous year. In 1358 a contribution of Es 4,00,000/- was given to the British govern ment towards the cost of the war and Hs 1,36-,000/- was spent on purchasing rice; excluding these sums the normal expenditure in 1358 was approximately 31,39,000/- and the 1359 expendi ture was about 2i lekhs less tiaan during the previous year. Special Public Works, The expenditure was 3 lakhs less than the amount anticipated in the budget for 1359; in this budget provision was made for is 6,21,000/- to be spent on special public works whereas the actual expenditure was Rs 3,18,000/-, The chief expenditure on special new works during the year was on the Manamah-Muharraq bridge and the government hospital. The bridge was expected to have been finished during the year but owing to the war it is not yet complete. The entire super structure and machinery for opening the bridge was ready for shipment from England many months before the end of the year butoadag to transport diffioultiea it f^ilea to arrive. Three piers and the reialorced concrete dolphin mm coAploied and makof the reinloroeo oonar^t© extension built. tk»piles ana about of tiia ustck of tkvdolpkia were finished during the ye -r. it is esti&amp;ateu that it «ill take about five ikonths from the date of arrival of the material to ooiuplete the who is eork. Loaal labour used in the construction work uaaer the supervision oi British loreaen. Arab divers iters speoially useful in fixing # the central submarine, o&amp;ssion. % The nomn 1 &amp; hospital m&amp;completed ^nd opened on May So, 1940 (Eabi althany Id, 1359) and the mer^s hospital was brought into 'use some months later. The ground floor wells of the adaiaistrative building were built and the hospital, kitchen, male nurses 1 quarters, walls, gates and cess room were completed during the year. The administrative building will contain two operating theatres, X-aay rooms, stores, laboratory and oificee. The two hospitals hate a combined capa city of 10C oeds but in case of emsrgenoy a considerably larger number of patients could be acoosaodated. The expenaitura during the ye&amp;r on the «foman y s hospital was 'isib,b00/- and on the laen's hospital Rs 49,000/-. The expenditure on the administrative building, staff quarters, kitchens etc. was S ji 32,800/-. The total cost of the mu 1 * hospital including electric, water and sanitary Installations aacunted to approximately^ i,32,000/- The nurses 1 quarters and the Lady Medical Officer^ flat and Matron's flat cost approximately 8* 86,000/-. approximately &amp;s lo,500/- was spent on the -Manuaah Fort. all the outer -walls ana the four corner towers have now bsea rebuilt. The north east tower containsa largo office on tmfirst floor a store the groacd floor, this and the eastern wall ana the north eastern tower were oulit aaring the year. 4iaaiiion»i iairiat* mmmae mix the iiidide garden ma fenced. »»ork was cosuenceu, but not cumpleteu, on the new Teohnicai school workshop• The ouildint, wnich is l^Q 1 x 40* is adjacent to the existing feohaioal bcliool and its disansions are aocoruing to the recomendations of Mr. 0. I. Hntchings, Principal of the Baghdad 'Xach- nical ichool, who visited Bahrain in order to advise the uovern&amp;aat on technical aducstlon. the roof Is carried on reinforced concrete oe^as supportea by rein forced concrete pillars. Owing to tne price, of steel Ceaas and the difficulty of obtaining them this method of construction was adopted for the first time in Bahrain. Ihe old builcing together with the new workshop will provide accomodation for about 100 boys. The amount spent on tms Ouilaing ms 8s 13,000/-. oom®improvements were made to the customs premises during the year including an office at the entrance to the pier and trolley lines and lighting on the pier extension. The cost of this was ipproxiaiately 10,000/- Uther work incluuea additional government garages, additional class rooms in the ianaaah school, an exten sion to the Haim dispensary, enlarging the jail at Jida, builaln , st&amp;bles for the government cattle, building coffee shop una a bathing shelter at ^dari ana the upkeep and repairs of government buildings, roads ana bribes.oil coriedssioa and 1,69,000/- »as raceifsd froa tha price of rice w &amp;ich ms, sold by tiie stato to local sarolmats. oil royaltj is «sti*atei at k&amp;g l&amp;ktoa* This payiueEt is made twice yearly, the amount Que for thft first payaent is knom end the seeoad inatalnsiit lias been estimated at ^ less the first instal- aeat. 1 tn ^t it aou I u be mwise'to sssuoe a larger revenue froa oil o*ing to the unsettled con ditions eno the lack of turner transport. Custoias revenue nas been estiasteo et approxiaLitely «£ l«khs less than ie 135'^. this is 4 cocservLtive estimate but the reduction of the activities of the California srabian i^tandaru Oil Uoapiiny, iaoreasea iaport trade through Kuwait and the aaount of uneaployaent in Bahrsia affect the volusae of the iaport trade in Bahi'ain. uther sources of revenue do aoi Uiffer greatly froa 1 st year. iu vii the expenditure side the Civil List and one third of the oil royalty which is paid to tas Euler amount to lis. 12,90,000/-. Thi* figur® is liable to vary according to the amount of tae oil royalty. fhe cost of administration is approxia&amp;tely tae same as in last year's budgat. 4. ^xpenaiture on public health is higher than l.^st ye^r. It ineiuues special aati-a&lt;slaria »ork, quarantine services ana pro/ision ior the hospitals sorkin . at full oapsalty throughout the year. In ioo9 tiae hospitals ^ere only in use curing part ox tae year. 5. Public rrotection includes the State Police at full strength, the nu ur force new special Folice force *hich did not exist in 1359. The Special Police are providea with uniform ana rations. -ben the defence scheme eus inaugurated the unties now carriad out aj thetii@ ^peol&amp;l Folia© »«re a&amp;aarlakdn by naturs who were not given r-Uons or uuii'orm. o. Claer reourrent dzp^&amp;aiture on iaueatioi*, lunicipsiilias etc. dooa not differ to ny extant from last year. A surplus of lis. 6,09,000^- is ^nticipatad •rfhiah will bs added to tibe leservs, itiasi together with pert oi tho surplus balance from 1359. 7, ;.«osi of tn@ non-roem-rsnt ©xpenaitur© on publia *ork3con^isl^ oi completion of .voris as, in itend sucn/tas surgery ouilaing in tna nodpitai, tno Jaii£sah-.&amp;ak.rrafi oria^e hmthe now technical Softool, Provision iias been aaae for new marriad polio# qn&amp;rtars at the iiort ^nu far d&amp;icin^ pt&gt;riaun&lt;#nt tba nsw cre»in froa south east of MLnv.mli to %h» The building ocoupiaa by the enatofiH clerks, behind the post office is in e dilapidated condition and it is proposed that the ground'lloor should m converted into shops and quarters built on the first floor, 6. ..t present the bulk of tne state's revenue is froa I'm oil royalty -which is likely to decraase amd eventually ce^se* it *111 be ssen froa ths budget that rsvanuti i'roa oil is eatlaated at lakhs .and other revenue at approxiastely 10 l&amp;khs* ^incs the oil royalty began to oomin it has been the object of the state to build up a reserve «hich aill proviae incoae in the future that will compansata for the future uiminishing oil royalty. In this year's buagel the norxaal recurrent expanditui'e, deducting the third of the oii ruvenue, the contribution to the .asorve rand, special public works and allowing ^ lakh# only for public111 Dated the 14th June 1941. Confidential D.O. No. C/692 Please refer to your demi-official letter No. 328-S dated the 21st May 1941. 2. I duly handed over your letter referrred to in paragraph 2 to Shaikh Hamad and also 9 as desired in paragraph 4, explained that in your previous letter you had not been referring to him in any way but to the A1 Khalifah. Shaikh Hamad said that he quite understood and that he was very grateful for the sentiments you have expressed to him and your care for the welfare of the State. He smiled faintly when I explained that it was the A1 Khalifah whom you had * in mind, who had not contributed a single y' towards anything and who are the people who always worry His Highness about increasing their allowances. His Highness again thanked you and asked me to convey his respects to you. Yours sincerely, The Hon 1 ble (Copy aant to Govt.of India ur*ier P.L.No. Lieut-Colonel G/294 of 11.7.4i,oopy of bare P.L.sent C.G. Prior, C.I.E., to P.A.Bahrain). ^ Political Resident in the , | ' Persian Gulf, Bushire. i f'' :The Political Agent Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— I The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentfbfl'ed document ( s ) The agency, BAHR &amp;tN, Persian Gulf. Dated 14th June 194 1 Reference to previous correspondence: Description oj Name and Date. Statement of Revenue and Expendi ture at end of R/Awal 1360 months) Subject. Bahrain Finances.ll (it i OOKglDS'TIAl . ao.0/292 of 3,94i# Office of tJie iolitical Kesid«nt in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Bated 194 J.. Fx-om • The Hon^le Lieut.-Oslone 1 0,G,Prior, Politiaal Resident in Persian Gulf, To - The secretary to the GoTermsant of India, External Affairs 'Department, Simla* if*! Sir, * I hare the honour to forward for the information of the GoTsrnoient of India a eopj a letter Ho*C/59l, dated the 12th June l§4i, froa the Political Agent, Bahrain,(to gether with ite enclosurcE) which explains itself. 2. it «dll be seen frcai the Adviier's letter Ko,6l9*gl of 1360, dated the 17 tli April 1941, that His EighnesB Shaikh Hamad had aontewplated making further raids on the public funds in ordfct to relieve ^want # aacngst the al Khalifah# This difficulty has been met and ©vercoue and the al Fhalifah will content their)aelvee for the coning year with the sums provided for in the budge t • I have considered at various times whether the aiaounta allotted to this ' araily should rot be still further reduced but have corae to the conclusion that it is not practicable at present. At the time the present Ruler agreed to give up two-thirds of the oil Royalties and retain only one*third for himself it was ooa^ldvred that he was toeing extreraely generous, and public opinion would not support us in any further attacks on the Privy Purse# 1 have sown tne seeds for an eventual reduction of the one-third to one-fifth, but the idea has aade little headway so far and i ff i / sinceaince the State has all the funds it requires the natter ie aot being pressed# Tdth Muherraq will be opened to the public? in four to five months tirae, and this striking public work will bring about a great iasproreiasnt in ooraraunications# Substantial iaproveraenta in racdiaal and educational facilities arc being provided and the State ie talcing its full share in defence arrange ma ts• 3. The electrically worked swing bridge connecting Manama I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient ssrTant, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# a-/ /cP.G.HL.. &lt;— fiL.fto.&lt;z/it}}</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000147_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/354</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000147</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/354</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/176 V (C 81) Bahrain Finances'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (254 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.There is an index of the topics contained in the file on folio 2. The index uses page numbers relating to the uncircled foliation system that begins on folio 3.</extent><extent>A bound correspondence volume. Foliation starts on first page of text, top right hand circled number, and ends on the last page of text in the volume. The volume has a second, uncircled, foliation system from folio 3 - 241.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains detailed financial records and Bahrain Government budget, revenue and expenditure reports for the years 1937 until 1941 (hijri years 1356 - 1360).The file contains extensive correspondence regarding the alleged profligacy of Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa (and his request for an increase in the size of his and his family's allowances) and a discussion regarding how the state's oil royalties are allocated.The establishment of a national reserve fund for Bahrain is also dicussed at length in the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000147#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>