<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000122_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T18:03:26.938Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">•v. m _ L^— POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 0 The 14th of January, 1943. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document. This is a translation of one of two leaflets both said to be to the same effect and to have been given to Mr. Eden. A copy of the other is not available. Description of Enclosure: Leaflet No.4 issued by 'HOME FRONT' %I &amp;il, J . 19/204 S. INDIV (CYPHER TELEGRAM OTP SECRET) Political Resident, Bahrain. Commonwealth Relations Office, London. Telegram From To No. 55 Dated the 14th January 1948. t*V f-UJ' Reference my telegram No 54 January 14th. 2. Eden is said to have been presented with two leaflets by Home Front though it is net known if he actually received them. One leaflet copy of which has come to hand demands legislative council, trade union and*dismissal of Belgrave and threatens request for annexation of Bahrain by Persia if H.M.G. * does not assist in obtaining demands. = HAY * l.C.H. CONFILENTjAL No. 125-5 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, dated the 14th January 1948♦ Copy forwarded with compliments toi- The Political Agent, Bahrain. /*/// uC v ■■ y * . / ...J Confidential. BAHR \ 1 'T Rv^KTPT., 0 ? nu. —/v=H 3‘^1 7. P. A a © Yesterday the Near East Broadcasting Station . o at Haifah, Palestine, broadcast a news said to have been received from Tehran to the effect that a delegate from the National Party in Bahrain had arrived in Tehran and put up as a guest on the Tehran Government. The delegate stated to the Government of Tehran that the Nation^ Party in Bahrain appreciate the idea of Bahrain islands being annexed to IranTehran - (Rueter)• A representative of the Bahrain National party has arrived in the capital of Iran. He interviewed certain members of the Persian Parliament and informed them that Bahrain people would like to re-join Persia as soon as possible. Bahrain is a group of Islands; is an Amirate which has treaty relations with Britian. About one million tons of oil is produced yearly. The oil concession is given to one of the American oil companies.IMMEDIATE . CONFIDENTIAL^ ' POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. No. C/ 117. The 22nd January 1 194 g. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his coraplinents to: The Hon*ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) . it is reported that the announcement below was broadcast yesterday (21st of January) from the Near East Broadcast ing Station, Haifa, Palestine. ♦ REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: Description of Enclosure. NAME &amp; DATE! ' T SUBJECT. ? — * Broadcast about Bahrain :u laTSDIArE . CONFIDENTIAL. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No ' C/l ^ • Dated the ^2nd January ’ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). Actlon as requested by the Shaikh nay please be C£lK6n# REFERENCE ‘TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: “ Agency Printed Letter No. C/117 dated the 32nd .Tannar.-^ 1Q4R Description of Enclosure . NAME &amp; DATE. SUBJECT. 5 i Letter dated 22nd January, 1948, U from His Highness the Shaikh of jj Bahrain, to the political Agent, 3 Bahrain. ♦ I. Persian Claims to Bahrain. I?*'/ NS.S.4 (Cypher telegram - O.T.P - Political Resident, Bahrain. Commonwealth Relations Office, H.M's Ambassador, Tehran. Telegram from To Repeated No.96. Dated the 26th January, 1948 SECRET) London. My telegram No.94 January 23rd. Bahrain National Party representative at Tehran. 2. According to further information obtained here National Party representative was Abdullah Zireh. He appeared at Majlis on January 18th and asked for occupation of Bahrain by Persian troops and holding of elections there. He was told by Majlis President that Persian Government was anxious to recover Bahrain but it was premature to talk of occupation by force. Zireh was asked to produce evidence that he represented pebple of Bahrain but could only reply that he had none as his organisation was working underground. 3. Shaikh of Bahrain hbs asked for issue through Haifa broadcasting station and also in Arabic broadcast from London of a strong denial by himself that a deputation has gone from Bahrain to Persia to discuss political or any other matters. He suggests that it should be stated that Bahrain is an Arab State in treaty relations with the British Government. 4. I suggest that statement might issue to effect that the Shaikh has repudiated in strong terms the claim of the so called representative of the Bahrain National Party to represent the people of Bahrain and reaffirmed Bahrain’s position as an independent Arab State in treaty relations with the British Government. f L» l - HAY - SECRET PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, doted tiie £6th January, 1948. Copy, with copy of telegram under reference, forwarded with conplimento to:- The Political Bahrain. ^ Confidential. Bahrain receipt. / 0 S..J20 Due #/m.Telegram S.4 (Cypher Telegram - O.T.P - SECRET) Political Resident, Bahrain. Commonwealth Relations Office, London. H.M's Ambassador, Tehran. From To Repeated No.94. Dated the 22rd January, 1948. On January 21st Near East Broadcasting Station at Haifa broadcast message attributed to Reuters to effect that a representative of the Bahrain National Party / had arrived in Tehran. He interviewed certain members of the Persian Parliament and informed them that Bahrain people would like to re-join Persia as soon as possible. 2. Strong representation has been received on subject from Shaikh. imprimatur should have been given to this message by its being attributed to Reuters and broadcast from a Station under British control. 4• Grateful if Tehran Embassy would ascertain and telegraph identity of Bahrain National Party representative Consider it unfortunate that British ; referred to. To C. R.O. only. See my telegram No.55 'LB* HAYl&gt; P. A. AMullah Az-Zairzh is a Bahrain subject by birth. His age is about 20 odd years. H e got his schooling in Bahrain _ 1 Government school in Manamah. After he had left Bahrain he joined the service of P.C.L., Bahrain, until some 10 months'ago when he resigned to embark on smuggling business. H e le^ft. recently for Persia for smuggling and for the purpose of getting married there. He l as two brothers in ''ahrain - one named Sa’ld Az-zairah a clerk in the Advisorite and the other named Isa who ‘does business In Bahrain. The latter was a smuggler during the la^t war and has been to Persia for that purpose several time{ He has a Persia lady In marriage. As rerards the tendency of Abdullah Az-Zalrah, nothing can be said with confidence, but whatever It may be^the man is not important socially. It may be worthy to note here ^c^that the Pro-Persian tendency of thn ^bdullah Az-Zairah is not amazing, the more since all the Shi’as of Bahrain, by reason of religion and origin, have strong feelings towards Persia.SECRET . No. C/135. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. URGENT. ^ © The 26th of January, 1948. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments The Hon'ble the Political Resident w '' in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of a report on Abdullah Az-Zairah as verbally requested by the Hon’ble the political Resident.COt.FIDLMTI^L D.O. K0.229-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENC BAHRAIN . the 25th January, 1948 0 ■X ? 3 -) Please refer to your Printed Letter No.0/118 dated the 22nd January, 1948.^^ ^ 1 forward herewith a report received irom an inimpeschable source. If you see no objection please inform the Shaikh of the name of the so-called representative of the National Party as stated in the report. C.J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., Political Agent, RaHRaIN (L£( Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. .ll The following infomastion ht.s been received *y pe from an unimpeachable sourc*: The Press in Tehran are living much publicity to the arrival there of a person claiming to be the representative of the people of Bahrain. His name is Abdullah Zireh and he is reported to speak Persian with an Arabic accent. He appeared at the session of the Majlis on Sunday but was not permitted to enter the House although he talked with various Deputies outside it. He asked that Bahrain should fee occupied immediately fey / Persian troops and that elections should be held there for a Deputy for the Majlis. Hikmat the President of the Persian Majlis is said to have told Zireh that although the Persian Government were most anxious to recover Bahrain it was too early t© t # alk of sending troops there. When Zireh was called upon to adduce proof that he represented the people of Bahrain he is si ad to have replied that he could not produce any proof as the organisation he represented was an underground one. There is considerable excite rnent over the Bahrain question especially as it is coupled with news recently received that Persian troops have reoccupied the island of Ashuriyah which is cff Bandar Shah in the Caspian after • it has been under Soviet control for six years. The Press calls upon Government to take similarly decisive stemps to recover Bahrain and states that the Prime Minister has already entered into negotiations with the British on this subject. 24th January. 194RCmtom« sac«iint« (setareh 19.1.48). © fil« 1 77^*901 ^^on 1 raolth * enrrent year Cuetoaa Raeaipta totalled Rl..1,775,201,715.9 0 as eoapared with Rle.l,075,890,741,20 for the lame period lii«&gt; year. The increase of Rla.699,310,974.70 Is due to the Increased relume f exports and ixporto and also to vigilanco exercised by Customs officials in eolleotiag ths receipts, Council of Minliitora&gt; , f **r m * 1 of ^i«ters, at their sitting of 26,10,26, decreed that all permits issued by the previous Government for export of monopolised goods and for cutting trees in the forests and which are still out standing *~«ss*taa** partly or wholly shall be treated as cancelled, * r anoll J, flatoalB RSPraafiBtflUTg RiQeiYSd by Malless Deputie s (Iran ^ f* 1 ? £T** w 3r T? t#pdAy » Abdollah Zireh, the representative of ths people of Bahrain called at^tfae Majless and after some infernal talks with Abbas Eskandari and others, h»-' as usjered to the office of the President where the Vice President, Amir Heasein Zafar, acting for the Preaident, received bin and held talks with him in the presence of a number of deputies* Zireh said |« r , r^prosent th, 'Hezb-1-M.lU' of Bahrain and, in fact, the whole peopl, of Bahrain and am charged to bring to the knowledge of the Iranian Parliament how we are anxious to Join the geographical unit of Iran, we are prepared to do anything to be annexed to our motherland and should we be assured of yeur support and action, we shall not fail te hold nestings and demonstrations to give vent to our desire. 176 highly appreciate the appropriate speeches made by Wr« and we all confinn his views and actions* * Eskandari On being asked what document he had to establish his authority to speak for the people of Bahrain, Zireh said that his party was still an underground organisation wit » tn f principle to render the adhesion of Bahrain to Iran possible and that any credentials required could be asked for from them. He then handed to Mr,Eakandari a letter, for presentation to the House, requesting the authorities to,further their activities foi rec aiming Bahrain and to dirsot the people of Bahrain^ihow they ean best render their service and assistance. Other requests made in this letter are as follows* «• 1- Admission in the House of a deputy for Bahrain. 2- Extension of educational facilities te Bahrain and acceptance of students from Bahrain in the Teheran university 0 3- Setting up offices in Khorramshahr to facilitate the entry to Iran of peoolc from Bahrain* 4- Inclusion in the wireless transmissions from Teheran of a special programme for the people of Bahrain, ^ £ * /4*-i 4 f* f /'Vo Confidential. D.O. No. c/^of Bahrain, Feby.4, 1948. ConfideatiaL It may be of interest to you to have some details about Abdullah Zeera, the man who the Persians claim as representing the 'national party” in Bahrain. He is a Shia Bahraani, aged 22, from ivianamah. He was educated in a Covernment school, he worked for some years in Messrs Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., as a farrash and was eventually promoted to the post of a junior clerk through the influence of Naama, Packer’s head man. He was not a success as a clerk and was dismissed by Lermitte because he overstayed his leave in Iraq. He was con cerned in various transactions with Naama. He has been several times in Iraq and to Persia and did some broad casting in Baghdad. His talks were harmless. He was not a success at school though he had a great opinion of his own abilities. He considers himself well educated and is politically inclined. He quarrelled with his three brothers, one of whom works in my office, the other two have shops in the bazaar. He has no following in Bahrain. He belonged at one time to the Aruba Club, the least political of all the clubs, but left it some time ago. He is however connected with Saad bin Shamlan, father of Abdulaziz Shamlan, tlsese two are among the most mischievous people in Bahrain. He apparently sold his belongings before he left Bahrain. It is said that he has married a Persian wife, of good family, in Teheran. Shortly before he left he was reproved by his elder brother for talking so much about politics, the brother• %brother told him that he was a nobody of no consequence, to which he replied 'Hitler started life as a painter, and Mussolini as a journalist.' He was accustomed to walk in the evenings up and down the sea road or along the Jufair Road, with a book in his hand, indicating his erudition. He was a protegee of Ibrahim al Arayad, also employed in Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., who is by way* of being &amp; M 9 poet but, in my opinion, quite harmless though very con ceited. U After the a^air copies of a statement on the matter/ which was published in an Indian newspaper, in English, were posted to a large number of people in Bahrain. I believe these letters were sent out by the Muharraq Club, whose President is Abdulaziz Shamlan. Some of the mem bers assured His Highness that the Arabs had nothing to do with Abdullah Zeera and that they had no wish to help the Persians. The affair has aggravated the feeling between Shias and Sunnis in Bahrain, especially between the Khalifah and the Bahama. Stories are now being cir culated that during the summer a petition was signed by thousands of Shias which was then conveyed to Persia. I do not believe this. Do you think it would be a good idea if I sent some thing on these lines to the Times? 'Abdullah Zeera, who was reported on - by Reuters, Teheran, to have contacted members of the Persian Govern ment representing himself as the leader of the Bahrain national party, is a youth of 22 years old. He was until recently a junior clerk in a conunfimi a! -Pi-pm. Ho is a man of no political : C.J.Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., I.C.S., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 4th February, 1948. D.0. No. C/161 Dear Sir Rupert, As desired in your demi-official letter No. 929-S, dated the 25th January, 1948, T have informed the Shaikh of the name of the so called representative o: the 'National Party'. As you will see, however, from the extract which I enclose from a letter of Bolgrave’s to me, the Shaikh by now knows about Abdulla Sairah. Is there any objection to BQlgrave reporting to the 'Times' as he suggests? perhaps a reference to the Embassy, Tehran, is necessary before doing so. 2. I also enclose a translation of an extract from the newspaper 'Iran, Ma' regarding Abdulla Zairah's visit which is of interest. Yours sincerely The Hon'Dle Lt-Col. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.T., political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bahrain.Rxoract from demi-official letter No. C/701 dated 4 2 194.8 Bahrain. After the affair copies of a statement on the matter, which was published in an Indian newspaper, in English, were posted to a large number of people in Bahrain. I believe these letters were sent out by the Muharraq Club, whose President is Abdulasi* shamlan. Some of the members assured His Highness that the Arabs had nothing to do with Abdullah Zeerah and that they had no wish to help the Persians. The affair has aggravated the feeling between Shias and Sunnis in Bahrain, especially between the Khalifah and the Bahama. Stories are now being circulated that during the summer a petition was signed by thousands of shias which was then con veyed to Persia. I do not believe this. Do you think it would be a good Idea if j sent some thing on these lines to the Times? Abdulla Zeera, who was reported on - by Reuters.* Tel.eran, to have contacted members of the Persian Government representing himself as the leader of the Bahrain national party, is a youth of 22 years old. He was until recently a junior clerk in a commercial firm. He is a man of no political Importance and has no following”.CONFIDENTIAI.. 2-M @ POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. D.O. No. c/156. T} le 4 th February, 1943. Dear Sir Rupert, I enclose, for your information, a note on the Bahrain Clubs which you asked me about one day. Yours sincerely, 4f/ The Hon’ble Lt-Col. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E*} C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. NS.In compliance with E.A’s verbal instructions, I pive below a brief note about the clubs in Bahrain. Muharraj : 1 . Bahrain Club is an old club. The strength of its membeership amounts to about 200 and consists in the main of the educated class of Muharraq population. The president is Abdul Aziz bin Shamlan, head-clerk of the Imperial Bank of Iran and the secretary is Ibrahim bin Hasan Al-Kamal, the so- called secretary of His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa Al-Khallfah. The club is a cultural one by principle. My personal opinion of the club is that it is political the most active club in Bahrain, though clandestinely. 2 . Pvhalifah Islah Club : This club is a juvenile one in that the majority of its nearly 120 members are school students. The aim of the club is to promote culture among the member and of course little importance can be attached to this club as far as politics is concerned. MANAMAH: 1 . 'Urubah Club : This club which is in Manamah consists mainly of the educated class of the Shia Community, such as ifcrahim Irayidh, Interpreter of P.C.L., Hasan Jawad Al-Jishi, 4 * Head master of Bahrain primary school, and Ali Tajir of P.R.O. formerly but now in the employ of P.C.L. The president of tte club is Duwaighir, Superintendent of Minors’ Department. The number of its membership I cannot dogmatise on; but it is believed to be well over 100. Though the object of the club is to promote culture, politics constitute^a part of the activities of the club. 2. Ahll club: The club consists of Sunni and Shia and a negligible number of foreigners (Persians). It is a culture, club. Its president is Ali Wazzan and the Secretary is Muhammad Al-Mardi. What M the strength of its membership cannot be said. Like the other club, it dabbles in politics. 3. Tha^ afah Club : Is a culture and sports club by principle. The membershln strength is not knwon to me; the members are mixed of Arabs and others. The president is2 5Mk Ibrahim Qambar. This club consists of a fairly high percentage of foreigners as compared with the other clubs; and so it is believed that it is far from any sceng of politics, 4: Firdowsi c]ub is a Persian club in ^anamah. it is a sport and culture club. Little is known about the activities of this club as it is not so old or so important as the other clubs, Hidd (Muharraq) 1. Nahdha club in Hidd is a culture and sport club. The members of the club are naturally from Hidd. Little importance can be attached to it politically.© EXPRESS LETTER . From - Political, Bahrain. To - Repgu, Bahrain. No. C/166. Dated the 5 th February, 1948. 7th Reference correspondence ending with \ my demi-official letter No. C/161, dated the 4th February, 1948. Abdulla Zireh. 2. Broadcast from Persia in Arabic stated yesterday (4th February) morning that Abdulla Zireh would broadcast - no time was given. Effort to have service monitored is being made. Sd./- C.J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. AT TEG TED. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. NS.From Commonwealth Relations Office, London. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. 40 Repeated H.M*s Ambassador, Tehran. No. 40 Dated 7th and received Bth February 1948. a I . Your telegram No 96 of January 25th. Bahrain National Representative at Tehran, 2. Haifa Broadcasting Station were instructed dfi January 30th to issue statement on the lines of para 4 of your telegram. B.3.C. Asiatic Service has hitherto made no reference to report broadcast by ?iiaira . It is considered that to issue denial now would serve merely to give unnecessary publicly (?publicity) to original report, = SBCRO = I.C.H.f \ ’■n CONFIDENTIAL D.O. No.341~S 20 PERSIAN GULF RESIDEN CES) BAHRAIN the 7th February, 1948 - r Please refer to your demi-official letter No.cf/161 dated 4th February, 1948, about Abdullah Zairah. 2 , I see no objection to a message on the lines proposed being communicated by Belgrave to the Press, though it is a bit late in the day. It might perhaps be passed on through Meikle. Political Agent, B AHRAIN LB'z lAl C jNFlJLNTliiL D.^. No. 365-S Persian Oulf Residency, Bahrain, Dated the 10th February, 1948. i 5 - lw Please refer to Commonwealth Relations Office telegram No. 40 dated the 7th February 1948, a copy of which has been forwarded to you separately, on the subject of Abdullah Zireh’s activities. 2. In view' of this telegram and^of the fact that so far as I am aware no mention has been made of Abdullah Zi^eh in the British Press I consider it prej/er- able that no message should be communicated to that Press on the lines proposed by Belgrave. 3. This cancels my demi-official letter 'No. 341-3 dated the 7th February. C.c. Felly, Zsquire, u.B.m., Political Agent, Bahrain. ML. BAHRAT Confidential. yPERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to:- The Political Agent, Bahrain, X / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents:- PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, dated the 10th February 1948 Reference to previous correspondence: 1) Letter dated 9/2/48^ ^ from Mr Meikle, Bahrain. 2 ) D.O. No 366-S, dated J V 10/2/48 to Mr Meikle,' ' SITUATION IN BAHRAIN. Bahrain. X 3) Residency telegram 138, dated 10/1/48 No. f ' ' Confidential — —Copy of letter dated February 9th 1948 from lir Eeikle to Sir Rupert Hay, P.R.P.G. I attach a telegram addressed to me by Reuter London and should: be glad to have your guidance as to how I should reply. I do not know anything of the subject or parties referred to. Copy of telegram dated 9/2/48 from Reuters London to Ur Meikle, Bahrain. 21039 Received from RabitalT Alshabab Youths Union telegram saying public resent appointment Abdullah Zeera two (?to) negotiate w'ith Iran on Bahrain question. Appreciate 100 words explaining what this about.g^O. Ho. 36b~S PEHSIAii GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, dated the 10th February 1948. I acknowledge with thanks your letter of the 9th February and its enclosure and hope to let you have a reply shortly. (Sgd) W.R. IAY. V.. Meikle Esq., Manager, Gray Lackenzie and Company Ltd., Bahrain. I.C.H. .I.C.ii. Telegram From To No. 138 Dated the 10th 5 INDIV (CYPHER TELEORAL OTP SECRET) Political Resident, Bahrain. Commonwealth Relations Office, London. February 1948. IMPORTANT Donaldson from Hay. Reference your telegram No 40, dated February 7th. 2. Reuters have telegraphed their correspondent here to the effect that they have received telegram from ¥outh Union Bahrain saying public resent appointment Abdullah Zireh to negotiate with Iran on Bahrain question. Reuters ask for 100 words explaining what this is about. 3. 1 do not know what publicity if any h- s been given to incident in home press. Urateful for advice whether correspondent should be furnished with material for reply. Alternatively you might consider furnishing material to Reuters or press generally from Commonwealth Relations Office. 4. Fro® purely local point of view I see no harm and some advantage in statement being given to press provided Abdullah Zireh*s youth and lac$ of standing and support are emphasised also Shaikh*s attitude. = HAY =The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents. information. Advisers Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No /'//-. Y**- IS* Dated February 11, 1948. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Translation of^article re: Bahrain in v Iran-e-ma”newspaper, issue No.924 of 19th January 1948. Reference to previous correspondence :— No Confidential. BAHRAIN -k.,..IRAN-E-MA Issue No. 924, Monday 23th Dima, 1326, 19th January 1948. Yesterday Abdulla Zeera, representative of the people of Bahrain, attended the Majlis. Members of the parliament welcomed him. Ha/said the people of Bahrain were im patiently waiting for the action of the Majlis. He submitted a letter to Abbas Askandari, a member of the Parliament. Askandari has delivered to the Majlis the letter from Abdulla Zeera which has been welcomed by the Parliament. The Iranian Government should call to Teheran students of the Iranian School for higher education. The capital should arrange a programme on the radio especially for Bahrain. Yesterday at 4-15 in the afternoon, Mr. Abdulla Zeera, representative of Bahrain in the company of Mr. Ra-id, went to the Iranian Parliament. In the Parliament Mr. Abbas Askandari, a member, welcomed the Bahrain representative. A few minutes later some members of £’ ar ^ amen i requested the Bahrain representative to take rest in one of the chambers so that they could discuss matters officially. The representative of Bahrain with members of Parliament, among them Messrs. Askandari, Maki, Ishtiani Zadeh and Damavandi, entered the chambers. There they had conversation. The Bahrain representative spoke in Arabic and Mr. Ra-id interpreted. The Bahrain representative said the r, Tudeh t, of Bahrain these days are in a state of discontent and commotion (tashwish and idtirab) owing to the oppression of the strangers. Every moment they are waiting for the measuresbe taken by the parliament and the Iranian Government in connection with the return of Bahrain to Iran. Mr. Damavandi said that they were fifteen members who had prepared a memorandum and they hoped that their memorandum would meet with the approval of the Majlis, and that the % desire of the people of Bahrain would be attained. Mr. Abbas Askandari explained that all the members of the parliament were their brothers and all desired the return of Bahrain to Iran. In achieving this goal they would leave no stone unturned. After this discussion the members entered the chamber of the Prime Minister who was not present at that moment. # The Deputy Prime Minister Mr. Amir Husain Zafar Bakhtiari welcomed the Bahrain representative. The Bahrain representative ‘ was made to sit on the right of the Deputy Prime Minister, and Mr. Ra-id again interpreted. The members of the par liament sat around the table of the Prime Minister. The Bahrain representative said that it was three weeks since he was in Teheran. He said, 'I, as the representative of the National party which in turn represents the tf Tudeh M of Bahrain, have come to contact the Iranian parliament so that the National Party and the 'Tudeh' of Bahrain could take steps so that Bahrain could rejoin Iran at the earliest possible moment. The 'Tudeh' of Bahrain were ready to do anything the Iranian Government would ask them to do. The moment the Iranian Government decides to obtain the rSturn of Bahrain, the people of Bahrain will start action. Since this matter has not so far come up officially the Bahrain people cannot come out publicly, owing to the fact the present Government of Bahrain will oppress the Av people and send them to jail or deport them.” The Bahrain representative added that the statement of Mr. Abbas Askandari in connection with Bahrain Islands has 3/—reached the ears of Bahrain people and they appreciated it much, tf/hat the Bahrain people desired ?£r. Abbas AsKandari has mentioned in his statement, the Bahrain representative of the National Party spoke about the secret activities of the underground party. Then his letter containing the desires of the Bahrain people was delivered to Mr. Abbas Askandari so that through him it could be put before the Majlis. The Persian version of the letter is as follows 'Teheran, 26th Dima 1326. Mr. Abbas Askandari, After compliments. I beg to state that three months ago I came to Teheran. I contacted the Foreign Ministry. I stated that the 'Tudeh* of Bahrain have a keen desire that the High Iranian Government should claim its right. In one of the memoranda# submitted by me there contained 114 points which explained fully the policy #£ and economy of Bahrain. The Iranian Government was pleased with this memorandum. I returned to Bahrain and got in touch with the members of the underground movement which has been in action for years for the liberty of Bahrain and its return to Iran which is its rightful owner. We discussed the matter and here are what the 'Tudeh' and the National Party of Bahrain desire«U 1. Your statement in the Majlis about the return of Bahrain to Iran has met with the approval of the people of Bahrain. This statement has been received with thanks and they endorse it fully. You are known for your clearness of expression and your straight-forwardness. We hope that with your help the desires of the 'Tudeh' of Bahrain in the matter of Bahrain’s liberty and its return to its mother country which is famous for its damocratical principles and justice^will be achieved. 2. We have also great confidence that the members of the Iranian Parliament in the matter of obtaining the rights of Bahrain people will Aave no stone unturned. We are sure#' that we will not be disappointed in achieving our desires. If the Iranian Parliament will take the matter up seriously success is sure. 3. As for the followers of the 'Tudeh” of Bahrain I assure you that both the National Party and the 'Tudeh” of Bahrain are impatiently waiting for your action in regard to Bahrain, and are only waiting for your signal for action and your instructions will be carried out very carefully and we are fully confident of your assistance.4 t * 0 4* The ^Tudeh” of Bahrain which represents the National Party will raise their voice asking for help that the Bahrain islands should be delivered from the Imperialistic power«, They are confident that their voice will not be left unheard and that the Iranian Grovernment and the 'Tudeh' Party of Iran will immediately make the p^ant for the return of Bahrain to the motherland and the Bahrain people think that today is the best opportunity to achieve this, because the fires of the feelings of the 'Tudeh' of Bahrain have been ignited. If the Great GovernuBnt of Iran with the help of the 'Tudeh' of Bahrain takes no action now the fires will be extinguished. Je are hopeful that this golden opportunity will not be disregarded. I am waiting for the instructions of the parliament and its leaders. Sincerely, Abdulla Seera. ' The Bahrain representative in the following way forwarded his demands to Mr. Abbas Askandari who took them to the Majlis 'To Mr. Abbas Askandari, After Compliments and respects. I submit the four demands put forward by the National party of Bahrain through you to the Iranian Parliament. Surely these demands are only few but the main object is the return of Bahrain to its mother country, Iran. • Abdulla Zeera. ' The Bahrain representative will be presented before the Parliament. It is clear that this representative’s person is important for establishing firm and close relations between the whole of the inhabitants of Bahraih Islands including the 'Tudeh' and the Iranian Government. The School which is at present in Bahrain and which follows the curriculum of the Iranian Education Ministry is not sufficient for Bahrain. It is essential that education in Bahrain should be expanded, in addition the Iranian Government should accept students from Bahrain 5/— iilTT—r' il-nfor higher education at Teheran at Government expense. The Iranian Government should appoint special officials at Khorramshahr to welcome those who come from Bahrain, so that Bahrainis who arrive will be able to easily and in a better way get in touch with their Government. In this manner unity can be established. The Directorate of Information should arrange to broadcast special programmes in Arabic to the people of Bahrain and to the Arabs of the Gulf, so that they can better enjoy the Iranian programmes. The Bahrain representative said, 'Fewmonths ago I came to Teheran and got in touch with the Government of Mr.. Qavam Bs-Sultaneh and presented to it through the Foreign Office every- thing about Bahrain. These steps which were taken by me were welcomed by the Government. Afterwards I returned to Bahrain and discussed the matter with the followers of the National party of Bahrain. The I came back to Iran as its representative. Immediately I got in touch with Mr. Hakimi’s Government through the Foreign Office. Besides what I wrote I personally placed before him the above facts. I have been promised that if it became necessary I would be called. Now I came to the Majlis so that I could express directly to the Majlis, and state that now is the best chance to obtain Bahrain back. The people of Bahrain are ready to make any sacrifice in this connection. ff The Deputy Premier asked him what documents he possessed to prove his representation. The Bahrain representative in reply said, 'Because the National Party is an underground one and in the matter of Bahrain still has not received anything definite from the Iranian Government, the members of the party did not think it wise to give a signed document, but, one member of the party is now with me, so that if became necessary he will return to Bahrain and will bring the necessary documents'. As the time for the session ff the Majlis had arrived, further talk was then postponed.- Im CON^D^TIaL. 2.0.110.^10 -3. • 1 ? THE RESIDE1TCY, BAHRAIN, 17 th February 1948. (jSi © ft ^ ^ A Flea ae ref er to correspondence ending 'with ray d^o. letter No.set-S dated the IDth February. , 2. a fe^ days ago Meikle forwarded me the enclosed telegram from Reuters and asked me for guidance how to reply. I consulted K.M.G. who have replied as in the enclosed copy of a telegram. 3. I enclose a draft of a message which I suggest might be given to Meikle. If you agree will you kindly pass it on. There is no objection to your consulting Belgrave If you would like to alter or amplify it substantially would you kindly consult me. C.J.Felly Esquire, O.B.E., Polit ical Agent, BAHRAIN. RHL. Confidential BAHRAIN R'CEIBT.y p Li*- Date '.MM—v Telegram iSn Clair, From Reuter London, To Msikle Gray Mackenzie Bahrain. Ko. 210 39. Dated and received 9th February 1948. Received from Habitat Alahatoab Youths Union telegram saying public resent appointment Abdulla Zeera to negotiate with Iran on Bahrain question. Appreciate hundred words explaining what this about. REUTBR -rv' 19/191 © Telegram S. INDIV (CYPliEii TELEGRAM OTP SECRET) From Commonwealth Relations Office, London. To Political Resident, Bahrain. Mo. 46 Dated 14th and received 16th February 1948. IMPORTANT Your telegram No 138 February 10th. Bahrain National Representative at Tehran. Matter has received no attention in Home Press and it seems undesirable to issue any statement here. Best course would be for you to give brief statement to Reuter as requested. Importance of affair mi Ci ht be minimised. = SECRO = I.C.H. 1 r* r\wish to be taken over by Persia* Zireh is 22 years old and was recently junior clerk in commercial firm* He is a man of no political importance and has no following. His action has been strongly condemned by Shaikh and repud iated by Bahrain public.- CONFIDENTIAL . D.O. No.C/209. The 17th February, 1948. / Dear Melkle, Sir Rupert Hay ?ias asked me to pass you on the enclosed message for forwarding to Reuters. Yours sincerely, v Meikle, Esq., Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain.Qsimp znn&amp;f Political Agency, Bahrain. The 17th of February, 1943. © Zno. No.C/210 Doar Sir Rupert; I have passed on unaltered to Veikle, the press message received with your demi-official letter NO.420-S dated the 17th February, 1948 - for forwarding to Keuters. The Hon'ble Lt-Col. ilr Rupert Hay, political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Yours sincerely.t./L The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to : H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. j. Adviser’s Office, No . Manamah, Bahrain. Dated February 16, 1948. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Reference to previous correspondence :•2 /— IRAN-E-Ma. © Issue No, 927 - Thursday 1st Bahman 1326 22nd January 1948. Abdulla Zeera, representative of the people of Bahrain who is now in Teheran, explains the political situation of Bahrain for our readers. How the English have established a firm control over Bahrain. Explanation. This is one of the series of the articles which the Bahrain representative, Abdulla Zeera, who has come to Teheran has written for our readers:- 'In today’sarticle I wish to draw the attention’ of the Iranian Government to the way in which the British Government established itself in Bahrain during the rule of Shaikh Isa bin Ali (the previous issue of this paper contained the tyranny and cruelty for which that rule is known) by treaty. I want that the Iranian Government should pay special attention to the clauses of the treaty so that in its future efforts it should know well the previous political history of Bahrain. In the year 1867 Shaikh Isa bin Ali became a faithful servant of the British Government^ on one sideband on the other his tyranny over and encroachment on the poor people of Bahrain reached its climax. Some people of $ influence watched the actions of Shaikh Isa and through their influence were able to minimise his tyranny over the people.Shaikh Isa complained to the British Government. The British deported those people^, so that the ground would be cleared for them to attain their objects in Bahrain. Afterwards in the year 1870 another treaty between the British Government and Shaikh Isa bin All was concluded. The said Shaikh as the Governor of Bahrain and Colonel Ross and his assistant Sir Lewis Pelly on behalf of the British Government signed it. In this treaty it was mentioned that the Political Agent in Bushire had full powers of supervision over the islands of Bahrain. The most important clauses of this treaty were:- a. To protect Bahrain from attack by foreigners. b. To trade. c. To protect public rights: from this it is clear that the contents of this treaty have given complete authority over Bahrain islands to the British and the weak Bahrain State could no longer resist their power. The object of the first clause was to get complete control over affairs in Bahrain. The object of the second clause was to show their justice, friendship and their interest for the country. The object of the third clause was also a pretence to show they wished to protect the rights of the public and in this disguise to interfere with the affairs of the people. Here it is correct to say that the British policy during those years tried through various means to create misunderstanding between the Persian and Arabic speaking communities. The British Political Agent- 3 - also published that he was responsible for public security and that all disputes and cases should be referred to him for decision. The British Political Agent was successful* Persians who had some self respect did not approve of this and openly critisized, which was resented by the British. Slowly he tried to overcome these criticisms and in the end the influence of the British over Bahrain was complete through Shaikh Isa who submitted all the affairs in their hands. Shaikh Isa had no complaint against the Iranian Government* He saw that the British Government established a regular Governmentand handed over all the affairs to them and whatever this master ordered him to do he did. He did not know that a day would come when the Iranian Government would demand its rights in Bahrain and the injustice shown to the people and the 'Tudeh' of Bahrain who are striving to attainliberty will be blownoff the horizon by sO the shouts 'Death to the Coloniers'. » • 118th FEBRUARY, 1948 Many thanks for yotfr D.0.No*c/209 of yesterday^ date with enclosure which enabled me to telegraph Reuters yesterday evening. Yours sincerely. C. J. Felly, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrein. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEi; ,D ite.C ONFIDENTIAL . No. C/ 228 • y POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 21st February? The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: Ihe Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain,* and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: Description of -Enclosure . NAME &amp; DATE. SUBJECT. Translation of an article in | the Teheran newspaper IRAN-E-MA J by Abdulla Az Zairah of Bahrain. « Bahrain. NS. * R I— SEGRct H°. C/3o 0 . *1 v '; POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 30th March, ^he Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to* The Hon’ble the Political Rest lent in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, , 194 3 . and has the honour to send him a copy of the under- mentioned documenc(s) f or information. ( Reference to previous Correspondence! Description of Enclosure. Name &amp; Date Sub.j ec t Translation of an article published by the M A1-Arab World', in its is ue No.11, dated the 10th February. 1948.Translation of an article published by the 'Al-Arab ^orld'7 in its issue No.11, dated the 10th February, 1 Q 48. bfu ixtalP -LoLtiK-Jo CGiurLfiliM OF BxilTtilN : Ne have received a message from Bahrai n under the signature of a zealot commencing it with reference to the move advanced by a number of the Persian Parliamentary members demanding the annexation of Bahrain Islands to the Persian Empire on the consideration that they are lying in thei’Persian Gulf, opposite to the southern coast of Persia and to the statement made by Mr. Ernest Bevin, Britain's Foreign oecretary of State, in the British Parliament, in reply to such claim and his sayings that there are political and ecconomical relations binding Britain with Bahrain, which she (Britain) regards as an incieoendent state with sovereignty and that Britain does not see any reason to justify any change in the p olitical status of Bahrain. The ardent writer adds that although the Bahrain leader do not agree to annexation to Persia or to any other country, yet it is imperative to point out that Mr. Bevin's statement has not pleased many of the leaders of this island; for it was devoid of many facts yet to be asserted, the first being that Britain does not look at Bahrain through the same angle that Mr. Bevin declared in his statement, that is to say, as an independent state with sovereignty. On the contrary she treats0 • • • o 2 Bahrain as Mandate or a Colony, since she has there an v adviser, Belgrave by nane, who is nore of a governor than an adviser - leave alone the fact that all the governmental posts are held by Englishmen who dispose o'C the country's resources as they will and exploit to the utmost and take away all its produce of the black gold (oil) - which is its most important export - without bargain. The writer goes on to say that this kind of disguised imperialism plays a great role in spreading illetracy in the country and in resisting all attempts made by the national authorities tb rehabilitate the social, the scientific, or the literary life, with a view to enabling poverty, illetracy and ill-health to have a tight grip on the nation so as to justify the Britiah domination to linger on there. The writer concludes his article inviting the attention of the Arab League to the condition prevailing in Bahrain Islands and requesting it in the name of all the people of these islands to exert all its influence ard respect with the British High Authorities in the way of removing the cuases for resentment for the British domination, which is repugnant to the text of Mr. Bevin's statement that Britain respects Bahrain's independence and sovereignty.r n _., Extract from Press and Radio SumrLary No. 185 dated 17th March, 1948, issued by the British Embassy Information Department, Tehran. (1) BAHREIN IKAN-I-MA. (Left) This paper reproduces an article from an Egyptian paper about Bahrein, in which it is said that the British authorities do not allow any workman to leave the Island and go to Dahrun where higher wages are paid in the oil fields. This caused a strike, after which the British were obliged to lift this ban and bring Indian labour to Bahrein. This has been done in order to put the Bahrein people in a minority if the Iranian and Iraqi claims on this Island assume a serious aspect and the matter comes up before U.N.O. The paper then says : As we see the British authorities in Bahrein are now carrying on a very dangerous policy to bring labour from India in large numbers in order to create a majority in their favour. . u ^ U ^ ur Gove rnment has shown such weakness in dealing with tnis vital question that even Iraq is now raising a claim to Bahrein. We call on the Foreign Minister to lodge a strong protest against British activities in this Iranian territory. In the meantime, this paper publishes the feext of two letters written by Abdullah Zireh to Eskandari, and the Speaker of the Majlis. In his letter to Eskandari the writer thanks him for his activities regarding Bahrein, which unfortunately, he says, have been unsuccessiul. In the letter to the Speaker he expresses surprise at the indifference shown by the Government to the requests of the Bahrain people, who insist on oeing freed Irom the rule of foreigners. No-* B/54 Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 24th April, 1948. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to , The Political Agent, Bahrain ‘i X VThe Political Agent, Bahrain. WITH THE COMPLIMENTS OF HIS MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY 10th October, 1949. BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHREIN, PERSIAN GULF. 37433—5British Embassy, TEHRAN, G.282/15/49 20th September, 194 CONFIDENTIAL Dear Residency, You may be interested to see the enclosed translation of a notice which appeared in the semi-official newspaper ITTILA 1 AT at the head of a page of advertisements by various Persian associations urging people to vote for their favoured candidates in the Senate elections. The signatory, Abdulla Zireh, was the subject of corres pondence resting with your telegram No.112 of SCth January, 1948. The list now published by the Electoral Supervising Committee giving the names of all who received any votes in the first stage of the Senate elections in Tehran dels' not include any of those mentioned in the enclosure. The 'candi dates” are quite unknown to us. We are sending a copy of this letter to the Eastern Department. Yours ever, CHiiNCERY. The Residency, Bahrain.ITTILA'AT of Saturday 5th Shahrivar 1328 (27th August 1949) Candidates from Bahrain Irj trie electiars of Senate Lr. Abdullah Zireh, representative of the people of Bahrain in Tehran, has sent the following letter to be printed in ITTILA'AT. Mr. Abbas Mass'oudi, Director of the newspaper ITTILA'AT. After offering my compliments I enclose here in a list containing the names of prominent and experienced Bahrain personalities. It is requested that it may be printed in the newspaper. Compliments. Abdulla Zireh, representative of the people of Bahrain in Tehran. As the undermentioned gentleman are the eminent personalities well able to serve their country, I request that all Bahrain nationals may elect them to the Senate. 1) It. Ibrahim Ariz 2) Mr. Ali Vazan 3) Colonel Ali Mirza 4) Mr. Ahmad Umran 5) Mr. Narayin 6 ) Professor Ali Tajir 7) Mr. Mirza Khushabi 8 ) Mr. Mohammed Saleh Shutur 9) Mr. Purchutan 10) Khan Sahib Mohammed Khalil Abdulla Zireh, Representative of Bahrain in Tehran.Confidential. No.C/R-478. Political Agency, Bahrain, October IB, 1949. V Dear Residency, Your complimentary slip No.231/5/49 of October 10. 2. We propose to send a copy of the enclosure to Tehran Chancery's letter unofficially to the Adviser for information. Do you see anv objection please? y Yours ever, Agency. The Political Residency, Jufair. *PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, ’ 21 £ t Lctober, 194S./fo'fj (231/7/49) Confidential Dear Agency, Your letter C/B-478 of the 13th October. V/e have no objection, Yours ever, RESIDENCY. ~C. The Political Agency, Bahrain. — C* 36 • Confidential BAHRAIN p CCEIPT OCT ^49Confidential. No.C/L-393. Political Agency Bahrain, October 26, 1949 Dear Eelgrave, You will be interested in the attached translation of a notice that has been sent to us by the Embassy in Tehran. 2. It appeared In the semi-official newspaper ITTILA’AT at the head of a page of advertisements by various Persian associations urging people to vote for their favoured candidates in the Senate elections. 3. The Embassy added that the list published by the Electoral Supervising Committee giving the names of all who received any votes in the first stage of the Senate elections in Tehran did not include any of those mentioned in the enclosure. 4. The 'candidates” are quite unknown to the Embassy. Yours sincerely, H.G. Jaklns C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.35 ^ 77 - Adviserate, November 6, 'yybV* Reference your No.C/L-393 dated 26th October 1949. His Highness has asked me to enquire whether it would be possible by any means to cause the return of Abdulla Zeera, who poses as the represen tative of Bahrain in Persia. I am personally aware that as long as he is in Persia we cannot enforce his return to Bahrain but His Highness wishes me to write to you on the subject. J.A.F. Gethin, Esquire, H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential. No.C/R-524. Dear Residency, Political Agency, Bahrain, 10 th November, 1949. Please refer to your letter No.231/7/49, dated the 21st October, 1949. ’ 2. We passed on a copy of the enclosure to Tehran Chancery r s letter to the Adviser and in reply from him received an enquiry of the Shaikh 1 s as to whether it would be possible by any means to cause the return of Abdullah Zireh, who poses as the re presentative of Bahrain in Persia. The Adviser added that he is personally aware that as long as Abdullah Zireh is in Persia we cannot enforce his return to Bahrain, but added that the Shaikh neverthe less wished him to write to us on this subject. Tehran might hcve some ideas on the subject so, if you think it worth while, you will doubtless pass the Shaikh^ request on to them. Yours ever, Agency. The Political Residency, Jufair.l 23179749 The Persian Gulf residency, Bahrain. Plst November 194-9. Please refer to your letter No. C/B.-524 of 10th November regarding Abdullah Zireh. 2. Bince tae man is a Persian, there are no means of compelling him to return. We therefore consider that no useful purpose will be served by addressing Tehran. C.J. Pelly, baq. , O.B.B. , The Political iigent, ■(^0, Bahrain. r -V ! ! r 'i ^OAQ i_&gt; s. J 5 ) Lpt Confidential, Political Agency, Bahrain, No,C/L-437. 1 st Decemter, 3949. Dear Belgrave, ^ ^ / Your letter No.l30-9A, dated the 6th November, 1949. 2. Since Abdullah Zireh is a Persian, the Political Resident considers that there are no means of compelling him to return to Bahrain. C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.- ■B GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN Reference ybur Confidential letter No.C/1-437 dated 1st December ^ Abdulla Zeera is not a Persian SU m?? Ct * . He ls a subject, a Snia, his brothers are Bahrain subjects, one of them being my Head C.J. Pelly, Esquire, M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. © CONFIDENT I AT,. Adviserate, T\ O ^ -v-* -4 1 ) • O« I * 7 ' Political Agency, {^ 7 i\ Bahrain, 'O 1 11 th Decenher, 1949. No. C/B-574(36/7) uO Dear Dredge, ' ^ Your letter No. S31/9/49 dated the 21st Noveffiber, 194S. 2. Abdullah Ziveh is not a Persian subject, he is a Bahrain subject, a £&gt;hia, his brothers are Bahrain subjects, one of them being BeJ grave* s feed Clerk. Yours sincerely, A.I.A. Dredge, Esq., MBE., The Residency, Jufair.DEPT. BSANCH. Section. Heading. Pros. NOTES 19 . Nob. Subject. File No. Serial No. 1 . Notes aud Orders. Cl) Translation of iio, 4 d&amp;f^d the 14/1/-^3 from Home Front Copy to P.R. for information under P.L. endorsed 'This is the translation of one of two leaflets both said to be to the same effect and to have been given to Mr. hden* a copy of the other is not aval able. ^ XK, e/?/. /A - ' ^ 0 .A'v ^ (? ^ • 7 ^ 0 -' lc &gt;lt \ PbFP—6549&amp;P^G'^07V-e4 t l I -'31—8,00,000</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000122_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/851</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000122</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/851</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 35/7 Agitation for Constitutional Reforms in Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-09T12:15:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (75 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 75; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio; an additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-71; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The majority of the correspondence in this file discusses the activities of a Bahraini named Abdullah Zeerah (also spelt Zireh). In 1948, Zeerah travelled to Iran and announced in front of its parliament that the people of Bahrain wanted Persian rule to be re-established over Bahrain. The file contains translations of articles in the Iranian press regarding the incident. It also contains a typed copy in Arabic (with English translation) of an article about Britain's role in Bahrain that appeared in
                           Al-Arab Worldon 10 February 1948.The file also contains correspondence concerning demands for the formation of a legislative council in Bahrain.On folios 25-26, the file contains a list of political and cultural clubs active in Bahrain with short political assessments of each one written by Britain's Political Agent in Bahrain, Cornelius James Pelly.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Political reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sovereignty</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000122#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>