<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000272_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T10:06:56.514Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">~i FT—Teay &amp; INDEX to FILE 86/2-17 vol&gt; 0=M' BA.HRAIN OIL. FEOM 1,E.33 TO 50.6»53 ANGrLO -PERSIAN OIL Co*3 activities 88,168-70,177-80,185- -7,195-8. BAHRAIN TERRITORY, extent of, 112.14,127. CUSTOMS EXEMPTION, 37-42,52,183. DRILLING, progress of, 150,159, 163. HOLMES, Absences from Bahrain, 31-4,45,165. Communicating direct with Bahrain Governmt: ADVISER 65,111. Unfitness for post of C.L.R.138. JANSON, Chairman of E.&amp; G-.Synd. 30. MINING LEASE, form of, Memo; hy Petroleum Depart: 99-104. MINING LEASE, proposed modifica- -tions 8-11,15,18. NATIONALITY of EMPLOYEES. 19-22,35,49,148,163. NAVAL BASE. 106. PRE-EMPTION, right of, 106. PE0SP3CTING LICBNSB, amendment of ! Clause IX. 23-27. do ..extension of, 60,149,155. j PUBLICATION of figures, 4,23,26. REMAINING AREA CONCESSION. 60-4,71-87,115-144, 173-5,188-93. ROYALTY, currency of payment, 43,51,57. SPELLING of Bahrain. 146.r tf P.Z.7690/1932, Subject: MHKIH OIL GONC SSIOM, 98035/32. Reference to pr^Tioua correspondence: Letter from the Petrol man Department of the 25rd December, 1952. Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State ^Kjt iviin gijy for the Colonies. .mM W- w* ■ ' A copy ha« also been ^ent to the Petroleum Departoeni Admiralty Foreign Office, Colonial Office, Downin, Street, 30th December 1933. To. 1.0.2.7785/52 PETROIOT WmMFM, (MIHSS DM SI'ANLSY STRBiff, MILLBAHK, '.ISSTMIHSTjiH, LOKDOH, 8.1.1 v 23rd BecsKiber, 1932. ^ \ '/ V Dear Ldith^ite, _____ I enclose for your information copy ______ of a letter to Flood end also official letter to the Colonial Office in rogftrd to the revision of the Bahrein Petrolem Company'a concession. Yours sincerely, Cn.) F.C.STARUNG, J.C.Laith-aite, aq., Iixiia Office, S.W.II t •.2.7785/1932. mikes mmam, DMM STANLEY STRHEf, ^ 21, Part 3. S.W.I 23rd Dec crab- r, 1932. A' k t • '?&amp;' * Bear Flood, With reference to your -official letter of the 20th December, I now enclose our official reply to jonr recent letters on the Bahrein Oil oormmnioru I hare no dealt in that latter with the frngg^tion mad© in Mr« Skinner's letter of the 3rd December that we might agree to their uBing the oil, now beim- produced, for the purpose of tfe^ir operations, pending a settleiseBt of the supplementary agreanent# On the whole 1 think we had hatter try to that Agreement out of the way, ^ith the alterations I have 1 mi^sted, hocau^e the main point lf&gt; that thoy rsu^t have this alteration or they have imt to pay for the oil they u^e* Thin represents a concession to them* I cm let you have pretty early in the New Year our other points* Une of these will raise again the question of the Sheikh being allowed to publish figures of output, ill though we grive way on this point in regard to the prospecting licence 1 do not consider that we should accept the view of the Company that their trading, interest® would be adversely affeoted by the publication of f?uch figures after they get their Mining Lease. That if another reason Ay I should prefer not to have the meaeuring clauses carried thorugji to the lining Lea^e now* You will see that in the Iraq Petroleum Coriipai^r'e Agreement with the Irs^ Government the Govenment hat the power to publiish any of the information made available to them under the Convention which they consider necessary* ^i ^-O^ (To) \ y / P. 2; • 502/33 • Enclosures in Colonial Office Covering letter,Dated 24.1.SS, Ko.18135/33. Dear Starling, ^ ^ f ■_ .r-- • - yv pi* With reference to your letter to Flood of the 31st of December (Mo»P#D.21 Pt«3) about the Bahrein oil concession, I enclose a copy of further correspondence with the Company regarding the supplementary Agreement, together irein Pet .Co .30*12♦32. ) with a copy of a telegram to the io. 2* 1*33. ) io. 16. 1 .33* } Resident in the Persian Gulf on this lo. 19. 1.33. ) &gt; Resident Persian Gulf. ) subject. 19. 1.33. ) You will have saen from flood's letter of the 29th of December (Eo.98035/11/32) that three of the modifications to the mining lease set out in paragraph 4 of your official letter of the 23rd of December have been communicated orally to Ballantyne. We feel, however, that we should not delay much longer in informing the Company officially exactly what amendments His Majesty's Government desire, and it will be a great help, as a first step, if you could see your way to preparing a memorandum setting out in detail the required amendments. An inter-departmental meeting could then be called to discuss this memorandum, and the best method of putting it to the Company. We hope very much you will agree to this procedure. I might add that during a recent interview here Ballantyne explained that the somewhat uncompromising wording employed in the Company's letter of the 2nd of January was only intended to maintain the principle that the Company cannot Starling Bsq.cannot be compelled to accept amendmenta to the mining lease, wliicli must be tiie subject of negotiation and agreement Copies of this letter, with the enclosures, together with copies of Flood's letters of the 29th and 30th of December, are being sent to Earner, Laithwaite and Rivett-Carnac• Yours sincerely, (Sd# )K.W .Blaxt er • P*Sm The letter of 12th January referred to in Ballantyne^ letter of 16th January relates to a different matter and we will deal with it separately* mmm98035/11/32. Downing Street 30th December,1932- Gentlemen, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe- Lister to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the ,30th of December in which you state that the suggested alterations in the Modifying Agreement are accepted 'by the Company* A further communication will be addressed to you in due course with regard to possible alterations in the Mining Lease. 1 am &amp;e., (Sd*) J.iUW.nood. The Bahrein Petroleum Company LtdThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. 19, Moorgate, London,S.C ,2* 2nd January, 1933. I have to acknowledge receipt of your letter (Reference 98035/11/32) dated the 30th December,1932 and to inform you this Company is pleased to note there is no suggestion on the part of His Majesty^ Government that the form of Schedule 3 to the Concession Agreement (the Mining Lease) is open in any shape or form. I am &lt;lcc., (Sd.) H .H.Ballantyne. The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London,S.W.l•1 -V^ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd, i9, Moorgate, London,E.C ,2» 16th January, 1933* Sir, VIr * * Your Reference 98035/32. ' f . Following my letter to you of the 12th instant, I would refer further to my interview with Mr.S.I.James on the 11th instant. This Company expects to have the proposed Supplemental Agreement ready for completion not later than the end of this month. Might the Company, therefore, ask you to he good enough to request the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to take all such steps as may be necessary to ensure there will 'be the minimum of delay in the execution of the document by the Shaikh of Bahrein. As I think I explained to Mr.James, one of the urgent needs of the Company at the moment, as I understand it, is the testing of one or more of its Wells at Bahrein, and it would therefore be of great convenience to the Company to have the Supplemental Agreement completed at the earliest possible date. I am &amp;c., (Sd.) H.R.Ball ant yne. The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, S.W.I.. '''■N (ij) Colonial Office. 18135/33# 19th January 1933. I I Is ;.j , ' Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Gunliffe-Lister / to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 16th of January regarding the proposed Supplementary Agreement modifying the terms of the Bahrein Oil Concession and to inform you that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has 'been advised 'by telegram of your desire that the Agreement should 'be executed with as little delay as possible. It is anticipated that the Hesident will telegraph as to the position in a few days and on receipt of his telegram a further communication will be sent to you* I an ^c., (Sd.)0•U.K.Williams• H.K.Ballantyne Esq18135/33 TKL-SGHAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Acting Hesident in the Persian Gulf. {Sent 12»50 p.m. 19th January,1933) Concession. Company are anxious that supplementary agreement should be concluded as early as possible in order not to delay testing operations in 'Bahrein. Can you take steps to ensure its execution not later than the first week in February? Telegraph reply early. No .1 Confidential My confidential despatch of 5th January .Bahrein Oil93055/11/32 Downing St 29th December,1932. Dear Starling, Many thanks for your letter of the 23rd of • - •'? December Ko.P.D«21 Part 3, and for the official letter ' about Bahrein oil which it covered. The alterations in the draft Agreement seemed trifling, so I sent off an official letter to Ballantyne, of which I enclose a copy* You will note that 1 have thought it expedient to add a paragraph warning them that there might be modifications in the mining lease. This excited Bailantyne, who came round to see me in a state of panic. He said that the alterations proposed in the draft Agreement were quite reasonable and would be accepted at once, but with regard to possible alterations in the mining lease, he would not admit that the Company ought to be placed in the position of having various conditions hurled at them #iich they could be told to take or to leave• I said that, so far as I could see, it would not be practical politics to hold a pistol at their heads, and that the alterations, which we did not think would be of a very serious character, would obviously have to form a matter of agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company. This appeared to satisfy him and he will write in and say that he understands accordingly. 1 mentioned to him points (a), (b) and (d) in paragraph 4 of your official letter, but did not mention (c) and (e) t which can be dealt with later on. I told him that there would be correspondence, but I couldn't be quite sure what form it would take. If they agree to the modifications proposed, as they will do, then I hope to get the thing off by air mail this weekend, telling the Resident in the Persian Gulf that His Majesty's Government have no objection to the G.Starling Esq. conclusionconclusion of the Supplementary Agreement, subject to the modifications embodied in the correspondence. That should satisfy them. Yours sincerely,V CONFIDENTIAL. No. 141-3 of 1933 The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political A^ent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for inforraation. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 15th February 1933 /y ' Reference to previous correspondence : ushire Memorandum N0.8Q -S of 25tu January 1933. Description of Enclosure. p. it / 1. Petroleum DepartmenttMines Department) letter -No.nil, ^dated 23rd December 1932 to / the India Office, with first enclosure only. 2. Colpnial Office letter So. 4.8135/33 of 24th January 1933 to the Petroleum depart ment(Mines Department),with enclosures. B/.Hi :AIN OIL CONGKSSIOM SUPPIa EMENT AR Y AGHiiaiyoi::.:T.P.z. 431/33. 5428/32. / l Bte !? f—a '&gt;5 . ^' .-id,. I Pit' j Sir, Adniiralty, S.W.I. 20th January, 1933. ffe- | L if'j: T am coffinmnded by My Lords Goiamissioners of the Admiralty torefer to letter from the Petroleum Department to the Colonial Office, No.21, Part 3, of 23rd December, ^^1932, and to paragraoh 5 of Colonial Office letter to the r IBahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, No.96035/Part 11/32, of 29th December, 1932. 2. Fy Lords attach the grestesb imoortance to the inclusion of the pre-emption and refining safeguards as proposed in paragraph 4(e) of Petroleum Department letter of 23rd December, as a step towards the inclusion of the / * f i &amp; ' /* ■ full safe^ards if and when the Company aooly for an extension of their area. 3# With reference to paragraph 4(c), My Lords consider that in view of the reoort on page 47 of the Administration Report of the Persian Gulf for 1931, to the effect that of the e )loyees only Major Holmes and a few Sikhs are British, it would be desirable to draw the attention of the Bahrein Petroleum Company to Condition D / t V' iy ' 1/ - . A 1 ' .&lt; of their agreement. f. 4. Copies of this letter have been sent to Petroleum Department, Foreign Office and India Office. I am, etc., (Sgd. ) J.3. BARNES /%. Uo . /6S'6 J. /r-2'S3 ' ^ Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, S.W.I. O r* ' o L egret llS ■ V *Ov \ IN GULij\ m T TIAL. Sir, b*k' s OH*- rta * Downing Street, 3 / */' January, I933. /w-/ ISfs l/'JC-i' /H I have the honour to invite your attention to Condition B in the Schedule; to the Agreement dated the 12th of June, I95O, between the Shaikh of Bahrein and the Bastern and General Syndicate Limited, which lays down that as many of the employees of the Bahrein Petroleum Company in Bahrein as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Shaikh of Bahrein. 2. In view of the statement on page 47 of the Administration Report on the Persian Gulf for I95I to the effect that, except for Major Holmes and a few Sikhs, all the employees of the Company are non-British subjects the question has been raised whether the Company are carrying out the obligations imposed on them by Condition D, and it has been suggested that the point might be brought to the Company T s notice. In order that this suggestion may be considered by His Majesty r s Government, I shall be glad to be furnished with your views as to whether the existing facts would justify representations on the subject being made to the Company. ^ C ' 3. I take tliia opportunity to point out that copies of / the Agreement 01 the 12th of June, 19j)0, as actually signed, have never been sent to the Colonial Office, and to request that I may be furnished with twelve copies thereof for record in this Department and for distribution to the other interested Departments of His Majesty T s Government. DURABLE POLITICAL HBSlDgNT •1 THE PERSIA! GULi?.iq f 4. It has also been brought to my notice that the copy of the Supplementary Agreement, enclosed with your despatch No. 51 of the 22nd of December, 1952, bears no date, and I suggest that, if the original agreement is undated, the omission should be rectified. I shall be glad to be informed of the position in this respect. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humb 1 e s e r \ran t,I Q i, &gt;\/ CONFIDENTIAL * Ho.176-3 of 1935. 'British, riesidericy ^ Consulate-iener. l, Buohire, 21st February 1 j 33, y.^\ c^ r To The Political Agent, BAiiRAlN. BAHTiAl. ' OTL GQNGSB^IQN . Memorandum. 4j | I. A copy of Colonial Office despatch i'.u.Confidential, dated the 31st January 1933, is forwarded herewith in continu ation of correspondence ending with this office printed letter N0.165-S, dated the 17th February 1933. 2 # Could you please let me know what is the total number of employees under the Company in 3ahrain f with their nationalities. Prima facie I am inclined to think that per haps existing facta do not justify representations on the subject being made to the Company. Oil operations,whether this is actually indicated in a Concession or not, progress ttroujh three stages: Jixploring, Prospecting, 'lining, in the first stage only a few experts - chiefly geologists - would be employed. In the second drilling is begun and in addition to expert drillers employment is given to u comparatively few manual workers to carry out the actual drilling, for road making, etc. It is not until the third stage - Mining - is reached that labour is employed in any large numbers, and even when this stage is reached I imagine that a Compny would be Justified in keeping posts demanding special technical or clerical qualifications in their own hands. The Bahrain ietroleum ...-2. Petroleom Company is at present only at the second stage, and I suppose the employment they can give to non-Americans is limited# »Vhen they reach the Mining stage there should be scope for employing local labour, whether British (British Indiari or Bahra^ni, ana quite apart from other considerations, it will be economical for them to do so. Please let me have your views* 3# Reference paragraph 3» Copies will he forwarded from Bushire. 4. Keference paragraph 4. If the original of the Agreement referred to is undated please have the omission rectified and report date of signature. Lt.-Colonel Political Resident in the Persian GulfyC's. P. P.—L (ill) 126—500-4-31. No. c -73 hhhuHHHH C41 V V The Agency, Bahrain, From The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. *93 3. m W50&lt;^fN€_Y ( b*i '&lt;■ - ^7 V hi* n/vf^-b To §Wm^TUL HEQOim The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, tf-i/Z, i I nave tne nonour xo refer to your letter Lo;8C-S dated the ^5th January 1933 ana to enclose live copies of the Indenture amending Clause IX of the Second Schedule of the Concession Agreement of the Bahrain Oil Concession dated the ^nd December 192b, duly completed. I have tiie honour to be Sir, lour most obedient servant. Lieut Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain.(F) BOHrrDBNTIAL . 1 No - 193-3. of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to ^he Foreign Secretary to the Crovemneit of India, Wew TS, el'hi , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Dated.... • SV/bruary.. 1.933. Name and Date. Subject. despatch Ho. 18 of 24th February 1933 to the Colonial Office, London, wit-i enclosure. Bahrain Oil Concession.Telegram G.T»C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Eesiaent, on H.M .S. ^BIDEFO^D' » No- 95. Datea ana received 6th March 1933. Janscn, Chairman of Eastern 8c General Syndic- -ate, and Holmes would like to see you. They cannot land at Bushire as they have no visa but propose travelling by slow mail leaving here 11th March. Please telegraph if you will be on board and willing to see them. POUT ICAI. / )/} i &gt; Telegram G.T.C. Fro* Political Resident, on H.M .S. ''BILEFORD'. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T-&lt;;6. Dated 7th March 1933. Your telegram llo, 95. T shall be on mail arriving and leaving Bahrain 11th March. Will be glad to see Janson and Holmee. RESIDENT.\ - ^ I A V 36/33. Downiag Street, v 1 1 , February, 1933. c&gt; 31 w{^v^ In his confidential letter (D.O. No .446S) of the 1st of July, 193E, Biscoe wrote to me regarding Condition C of the Schedule to the Assent given by the Sheikh of Bahrein to the assignment to the Bahrein Petroleum Company of the oil concession w granted to the Eastern General Syndicate limited, and pointed out that, in his opinion. Holmes was not fulfilling the provisions of this Condition. ^.As a result of that letter we took the matter up with Ballantyne, and a copy of the letter 'addressed to him was sent to the Persian Gulf in our official despatch of the 16th of August, 193E. We have had no formal reply to that letter, but as a result of reminders to Ballantyne he called to see me a little while ago with Lombardi and Hamilton to discuss EMNT COLONEL T. C.i^'OWLbi, C.B-E. i 2,2 - M/h^ldiscuss the position, and at my request wrote me a semi -official letter on the matter, a copy of 3ra_j which I enclose. ^ You will see that the contention of the Company is that Holmes has been in Bahrein at all the material times - that is to say, that he lias always been available when the Ooriipany recj^-ixed to communicate with the Sheikh and the local authorities. At the interview Ballantyne, however, volunteered that, owing to the extended activities of the Company, the time was coming when the presence of Holmes would be needed for longer periods. Before we consider the matter further, I should be grateful if you would let me know whether the Company r s contention is correct, or whether there have been times when communication with the Company has been impeded owing to Holmes's absence. b Incidentally, Ballantyne seems to be trying to place the narrowest possible interpretation upon the wording of the Condition. When I saw him he said, in effect, that all that Condition C provided for was that there should be a Chief Local Representative forfor the purpose of maaiiiig any communi oat ions from the Company to the local authorities, whereas, if the Political Agent or the 'local authorities' wanted to get into touch with the Company and Holmes was absent, this would not be a contravention of Condition C, as there was no provision for this contingency! Our view is that such an interpreta tion of the Condition is impossible, and I am not at all sure that Ballantyne (who is a reasonable sort of person generally, so far as I know) would really take that line seriously and commit himself to it officially. For the present, I have merely sent an interim acknowledgment of Ballantyne's letter.■f ■ THE BAHREIN PETHOLKUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, Moorgate, London, E, 3rd February, 1933. Dear Mr. Parkinson, Following our conversation on the 1st instant, I write to record the view I then expressed, that down to date this Company has fulfilled to the utmost its obligations under Condition 'C'^ s Major Frank Holmes, as the Company^s Representative for the purposes of Condition T G T , has been in Bahrain at all the times required by the Company for communications with the Shaikh of Bahrain and the Local Authorities. ^ I should, perhaps, remind you that whilst Condition f C l provides for the approach of the Company to the Local Authorities through the medium of a Representative persona grata to His Majesty T s Government,- i.e. it decides the medium of approach, it leaves to the Company, as necessarily it must, the decision when and for what purposes the Company approaches the Local Authorities. I venture to hope that the foregoing explanation answers any question there may still be outstanding concerning Condition I C t from His Majesty T s Governments Yours very truly, (Signed) H.R.Ballantyne. C.C. Parkinson, Esq., C.M.G.,O.B.E., .ssistant Under-Secretary, Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.I.(2) ^i 2 - ( t) ^ Confidential * r- iX • 1 ■ .'u- r&gt; No:C/102» Political Agency, K../2.A ^77 ^ I ' &gt;•' 1 nfiuctncvrill inrnn~n] From:- OOHFIQENTUl feOMi rain, the 8tii March 1933 • To:- Lieut Colonel Gordon Loch.I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. Tne Hon T pie the Political Resident in the Persian Culf, Bushire. /A t ' Sir, I nave tlie uonour to reier to your Memorandum No ciVo-S dated me tlst February 1333 regarding the aifairs of tne Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. Steps are oeing taken to nave the aate,the 13th December 1932,inserted in the copies of the Sub-Agreement extending the Prospecting License of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited for one year from the 2nd Decemoer 1932.in the possession of ine Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,the Banrain Government and the Agency as directed in tne fourth paragraph of your Memorandum. ^ It is impossible to state precisely ihe number of employees of the Bahraxn Petroleum Company Limited and their nationaii ties,asiced tor in the second paragraph of your Memorandmr., ■ witilout making a specific enquiry from the Company. As it is not clear whether His Majesty's Government intend to approach tne Company,I have not made any enquiry from them pending- furtner orders,as to do so would at once raise, the question which might be embarrassing. In the meantime,! can say that I nave visitea the Field a number of times,ana nave casuallyseen most ol xhe personnel* The Fields Manager and his Secretary or Accountantj and 'che drillers and riggers (some eight m all) are citizens oi the United States of America* The lower works personnel comprise some Sikhs,an Anglo-Indian, a Burman and two Indian Clerks. The Head Cook is a Chinese I I am not certain about a lew men who nelp work the drills and so on - the j may oe anything. There are a number of local guards and coolies,though I near that the coolies are mostly Persians or ^ajais. I understand that a further party of drillers is expected shortly irom the United States of America 4. I have neard that the Company are making enquiries as 10 tne terms ol the contracts used oy the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited and other Companies employing Indians and others; and I have myself brought to the notice of the Fields Manager the T Indian Emigration Act 5. I hardly thimi. that the cii^cumstances would justify a representation to the Company at this stage# I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut Colonel. Political Agent,Bahi-ain.JTo • 269 • () u Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th March 1933, From W' m liosetj ■To Sir, Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain* The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE . I have the honour to enclose a copy of the 1.Letter dated 31st January 1933 from 5 marginally noted the Chief Local Representative of the I Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, to { correspondence regarding the Financial Adviser to the Bahrain 1 Government. { the interpretation of 5 2.Letter Fo. 1023/20 dated 4th February 5 Clause V of the First 1933 from the Financial Adviser to the $ Bahrain Government, to the Chief Local i Schedule of the Representative of the Bahrain I Petroleum Company Limited. }• Concession Agreement datec I 3.Letter Ifo.1061 dated 16th February 1933 I the 2nd December 1926 from the Financial Adviser to the 5 Bahrain Government, to the Political 5 between His Excellency Agent, Bahrain. I — — —{ Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah, C.S.I, and the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited. 2. 'jq/ £ Clause V of the First Schedule reads:- A 'Free importation of all material apparatus and machinery of every kind necessary for the work carried out by the Company including office requirements but not including personal requirements of employees.' 3. The wording of Clause V, as it stands, appears to Justify the contention of the Bahrain Government that house hold furniture is not included in the exemption from the payment of import duty, for otherwise there would seem to be no point in the specific reference to 'office requirements 4. Article IX of the Agreedfient dated the 2nd December 1925 provides for arbitration in the event of a difference in respect of the interpretation of the Agreement, but I would recommend that, in the circi^stances of the present difference- 2 - difference of opinion, the views of His Majesty^ Government and the Slastem and General Syndicate Limited in London should first be obtained* It is possible that it will appear from the records of the proceedings leading up to the final Agreement whether the exemption of house furniture from the payment of importy duty was, or was not, con temp lated* I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant, .jieut-Colonel F itical Agent, Bahrain* A.J.Copy of a letter dated the 31st January 1933 from the Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited to the Financial Adviser to the Bahrain Government* Some confusion with the Bahrain State Customs has recently occurred as to the Bahrain Petroleum Company^ rights and privileges as expressed in Clause V of the First Schedule of the Concession Agreement of the Bahrain Oil Concession dated December 2nd ? 1925» It thereforej appears to the Company, that it is indicated that the time has arrived when a more clear understanding should be reached on the question of Customs. Clause V as referred to above treats with the question of Customs, and it reads as follows:- 'Free importation of materials, apparatus and machinery of every kind necessary for the work carried out by the Company including office requirements, but not including the personal requirements of the employees'. The degree of immunity from Customs duties that may be enjoyed by the Company under Clause V has come specifically into question in the case of a shipment of furniture, fittings and materials - recently imported by the Company from England - to be used in furnishing the Bahrain Petroleum Company's house and offices situated in Manama. The furniture and other articles imported for the above mentioned house and offices are not in any manner 'personal' to any one employee but are for the use of employee or employees as the Companys requirements demand. Such articles as ffcrniture, fittings and materials imported by the Company form part of the normal equipment of the Company. All is - in common with other equipment - necessary to place the Company in such circumstancl as will enable its employees to perform the multitudinous operations called for in developing the Company's Oil Concession. ihe articles in question come under the same category with such equipment as tools of all kindQ • x K;Lna s&gt; housing facilities, motor cars 1motor cars, or any portion of the normal equipment placed for the use of the employees in order that they may be able to carry out the duties allotted to them and for which they were engaged^ There is no vestige of 'personal ownership' in tools or furniture, nor is there in this particular importaticc in so far as the employees - apart from the Company - are concerned. All equipment imported by the Company and 'considered necessary for the work to be carried out' by the Company - to which description the equipment under discussion- in the opinion of the Company - conforms, is solely the property of the Company. The mere fact that furniture, tools or machines are iadba: being used or operated by any individual employees during the regular performance of his daily work does not constitute or carry with it - in any sense - the implication that the employees is in possession of a 'personal requirement'. You will gather from this letter that the Company's view is that the Company is within the meaning and intention - in spirit and in fact - of Clause V in holding that no Custom duty is chargeable on furniture and similar articles imported by the Company when such articles are to be used and form part of the equipment of the Company as is the case with the importation under consideration. I shall be pleased if you will deal with the points raised in this letter as early as convenient to you. May I request that the goods which are now held up in the Customs be released without delay subject to adjustment, if any, being made when you announce your decision^ I am sending a copy of this letter to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for his information.Copy of letter No.1023/20 dated the 4th February 1933, tram the Financial Adviser to the Governenmt of Bahrain to the Chief Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated January X^Sl, 1933, dealing with liability of your Company for customs dues on certain imports. It is not doubted that the goods in question are not the property of the Company. According to clause V of the original agreement the Company enjoys 'free importation of materials, apparatus and machinery of every kind necessary for tie work carried out by the Company including offic e requirements but not includin g the personal requirements of the employees.' The meaning of the clause V is ambiguous; it does not imply that all goods imported by the Company, although actually belonging to the Company, which are used for the 'personal requirements' of the employees, are not liable for duty. It is reasonable to infer that because this clause specifically mentions 'office requirements' which ordinarily would consist of files, typewriters and office furtinure such as tables, chairs etc., that similar items of furniture which are not office requirements are not fi-ee from customs liability. For this reason I suggest that furniture, other than office fUmiture, is liable for duty. I understand that the words 'office requirements' were added at the time when the concession was drafted. This being so I propose asking the Political Agent to ascertain from the Colonial office and inform me what is the correct interpretation of clause V in respect of imports of furniture which are not covered by the words 'office requirements'. In the meanwhile, as suggested in your letter, I have given instructions that the imports in question should be released from the Customs subject to adjustment when the question of liability has been sett^led.Vj^ U ^ Copy of a letter No.1061/20 dated 16th February 1933 from the Financial Adviser to the Bahrain Government, to H.3«M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to refer to the previous correspondence relating to the Bahrain Petroleum Company's freedom from customs duty ending with my letter Ho.1023/20 addressed to Major Frank Holmes a copy of which was forwarded to you on 4th February 1933. A question has arisen as to the Company^ liability for payment of customs dues on furniture imported by the Company for the use of certain of their employees. The wording of the clause granting exemption is as follows 'Free importation of materials, apparatus and machinery of every kind necessary for t&gt;he work carried out by the Company including office requirements, but not including the personal requirements of the employees. ,, The meaning, in my opinion, is ambiguous and in order to avoid future misunderstandings I request that I may be furnished with your views of its correct interpreta tion. It appears to this government that owing to the specific mention of 'Office requirements' being free from duty it is implied that similar requirements not for the offices do not enjoy freedom from customs duties» The words 'office requirements' cover office furniture; the disagreement which has arisen concern house furniture and this government consider that according to the wording of the clause house furniture is not exempted from duty. &gt;Confidential ♦ No:C/lOii. Prom:- Political Agency, Bahrain, the llth March 1933. To:- Lieut Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. The Hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, fj t ■, ul p s ^30 rn'C: I have the honour to refer to jour telegram No:84 dated the 31st January 1933 replying to my telegram No:0/^4 dated the £7th January 1933,asking whether it would not be possible to link with sterling the currency in which payment of tue royalty on oil in Bahrain is to oe made,and also about safe-guarding the landing ground. After the receipt of jour telegram,there arrived post your letter No:80-S dated the 2bth January 1933 regarding the Subsidiary Agreement,which was subsequently signed by His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifah and by the Chi el Local Representative of the Company on the 15th February 1933. C ' ^ :L ^ 11 % 3. Prom the correspondence enclosed in your letter No:80-S it appears (from paragraph No:4(d) of letter No:P # D.21, Part 3,dated the 23rd December .1932 of the Petroleum Department to the Colonial Qliice) that His Majesty^ Government will arrange to safe-guard the landing ground. The site of the landing ground for Imperial Airways Limited has not yet been decided upon, though the Royal Air Force wish to make a new (2) fi )agreement permitung them to use the ground at Muharraq. 4. I recommend that the opportunity should be taken, when the terms of the Mining Lease are being discussed,of linking with sterling the rupee currency in which the royalty of Rs*3/8/- a ton is to be paid in order to protect Bahrain against a fall in the value of the rupee• The matter may oe of vital importance to Bahrain: for if,for example, the rupee should oe fixed in the w** future at is.4d it would at once involve the neavy loss oi seven pence in sixty-three pence or just over 11 per cent. On a production of many nundreds of tons a day,the loss would be very serious. The controversy which nas raged of recent years around the question of the rupee exchange shows that this is not an idle fear. 6. If the rupee were ever to depreciate further,the loss might well oecome calamitous and,in the event of financial difficulties overcoming Bahrain,His Majesty^s Government or the Government of India may find themselves compelled by circum stances to come to the nelp of the Island. '/• But tor His Majesty t s Government and the Government oi India,there is a moral consideration,which out-weighs any question of monetary loss. The Ruler of Bahrain has placed himself in our nands in these matters,and it is essential that there should De no opening nereafter for any imputation, whether deserved or not,that we have iiot,in our fiduciary capacity, watcned over nis interests with the most scrupulous care. I have the nonour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, c. ^ Lieut Colonel. Po itical Agent,Bahrain.v» ^ VI- ll; C 0 1 Dij IIT1AL « D.O.H®.247-3 of 1955. Tne Residency, Busnire, ziw 21st :»larcn iy55, I -4' i /u y y Please rel'er to your le&amp;ter i^o, 1515^/^5, oi 17tn February 1^55, on tne subject or Holmes ias unief Local Kepresentative } not fulfilling tne provisions of Condition A (c) of tne Schedule, rei staying in Banrain for a reasonable period each year, I nare nad the opportunity of talking the matter over with Loch, who has just visited me. 2. With regard to tJie query contained in paragraph 4 have been no times of your letter. As far as we know therel wnen Holmes 1 absence has materially impeded communications with tne Company, So I do not tnink tnat any protest can be put in on this particular ground. 5. On general principles, however, Ballantyne*s contention lyour paragraph d ) is - I quite agree ^ nonsense, erhaps he could be iniormed accordingly, more or less politely, and tne following warning added ? If at any time tne Company wish to approach tne Banrain Government, or tne Political Agent, or tne lolitical Kesid^nt - and they can only do so th o gh Holmes - on some urgent matter, [ as they have had occasion to do in the past), and Holmes is not present, both the Bahrain Government and ourselves will of course refuse to consider any representations made through other channels, and any loss or inconvenience which the Company incurs will be entirely their own fault. Conversely, however, if the Bahrain Government or ourselves wish to communicate/ G.G.Parkinson,Esq., C .M. G., 0. B «iij., .Che Colonial Office, London. S.W.I.comriiunicate urgeLtly with tne Company, and are unable to do so because of tne absence of Holmes, botn tne Bahrain Government and we hold ourselves entirely free to take whatever action we think fit. This may bring Ballantyne up with a round turn, especially since - as far as I can see - the boot is on their leg not ours, i.e. generally speaking they will want to communicate urgently with the Bahrain Government or with us more than the Bahrain Government or we will want to communicate with them, and in any case, apart from the particular point at issue, I think it important that we should - if possible - impress on the Oil folk that when necessary we intend to take a firm line. 4. At the same time Loch suggests, and i agree, that Ballantyne, or his confederates, might be informed, perhaps verbally, th t we are out to be helpful and give them a square deal, in fact treat the whole business on the basis of a 1 Gentleman 4 s Agreement', provided they reciprocate, (however much we may object to an American concern establishing itself in Bahrain, once established - as it is - this is really the only sensible policy to pursue}, but that if they prove ocstrucuive and concoct pettifogging arguments, such as Ballantyne has produced, we shall have no choice but to pursue similar tactics, and they will probably come off worst in the exchange. b, i3y the way , on my way back from Muscat the other day I stopped at Bahrain and met Janson and his American colleague Lombard! who had been paying a visit to Bahrain. Loch and Belgrave told me tha.t there had been a row between the four oil officials with the English (Holmes and Janson) on/r rffi! , V 5- on tne one aide, and tne Americans (Lombardi ana Skinner) on the other, the exact cause being unknown. Skinner is a pleasant individual, and both Loch and I like hiiA. The Anerican drillers too, who have hitherto come to Bahrain, seem a decent lot, though their quality may deteriorate when they come in larger numbers. I am sending a copy of this letter together with a copy of yours and the enclosure from Ballantyne to Metcalfe and Laithwaite. J jnsilsZ IvV Y r ^ z ^L ■u Q0NF1 ifc] . h'h * J!lo.21 of 1933, British i esidency &amp; Consulate- Creneral, Bushinre, the Slat March 1933, I SUBJECT : nationality of employees in Beiirirain of the Bahrain Petroleura Company# Sir, / #ith reference to paragraph 2 of your despatch Persian Gulf Confidential, dated 3lst January 1933, I have the honour to enclose herewith extracts from my memorandum dated the 2l3t February 1933 to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and from his ^ f&gt; reply, dated 6th March i933« I subsequently discusti&gt;-.ly question with Colonel Loch, who concurs in the views expressed in my memorandum* I am Bending copie® of this despatch and of its enclosures to the Government of Indi#. *aent under P.L, N0.245-S of 21/3/33. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, c lit • • C ol on el, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. His Megesty* s Secretary of State for tne Colonies, The Colonial Office, London* S • • !• Wo.2tf9-S of 1933. Copy with compliments forwarded to the Political A^ent, Bahrain, for information. order. &lt;1 e **/3. . for Secretary to the Political Resident 1 in the Persian Gulf.rll-3/ ikS W C-fi r i d qOITPIDEHTI.a Britian Residency G on a ulate-General, Buahire, the 2lat Marcn 1933. ^©•22 of 1933. Sir, / / i r With reference to paragraph 3 of your deapatch Peraian Gulf Confidential, dated Slat January 1933, I hare the honour to encloae herewith twelve copies of the Agreement of the 12th June,1930, aa actually signed. J? o 2, sixth reference to paragraph 4 of the aame despatch, I have the honour to state that the Political A^jent, Bahrain, is taking steps to have the date of execution &lt;• the 13th Deceniber •&lt; 1932 - inserted in the copies of the Supplementary Agreement referred to in the possession of the Bahrain petroleum Company, Limited, and the Bahrain Government, and to request tnat the omission may be rectified in the copies in the possession ol His majesty 1 s Government. !i I am sending s copy of this letter and oi its enclosure to the Government of Inditf. ^sent under P.L. No.ajg-S of 21/3/33. X s-o- I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble aervant. jc Lt.*Colonel, political Resident in the Persian Gulf. His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, The Colonial Office, London* P.T.O.Islo,2bl-S of 1933 Copy with compliments forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. By Order. for Secretary to the Political Heaident in the Persian Oulf.GONFIDSIiTIAL. JSio.23 of 1933. British Residency &amp; G jrisulete-Gteneral, Bushire, the 24th March 1933. uub.j ect t Customs exeraption under the Bahrain Oil Concession. Sir, ' J f b'n t I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a / letter ^o.269, dated the 9th iiarch 1933, and of its enclosures r 7 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, regarding the interpreta- I i tion of Clause V of the Pirst Schedule to the Bahrain Oil Concession Agreement dated 2nd December 1925. 2. I do not consider the present difference to be sufficiently important to justify a reference to arbitration as provided for in Article IX of the Agreement'and agree with Colonel Loch that it would be preferable to attempt to settle it, snould you concur, by discussion in London between your department and the representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. The clause in question follows the draft received under cover of Colonial Office despatch .No. Persian Gulf 17, dated 3rd September 1925, and the Colonial Office records may contain correspondence which might assist in determining the degree of exemption contemplated under the clause. 3. Personally, I am inclined to think with Colonel Loch that the specific reference in the clause to 'office requirements'/ His Majesty^ Secretary of State for the Colonies, Colonial Office, LONDON. S.l¥.l.life. -2- requirementsupholds the content ion of the Bahrain Government that household furniture for the use of the Company's employees was not intended to be covered by the exemption granted under the clause. I am sending a copy of this letter and of its * enclosures to the Government of India. ,ilc *3ent under P.L. N0.272-S of 24/3/33. I have the honour to be, Sir, ut Your most obedient, humble servant. 4. Lt.-Colonel, Political Hesident in the Persian iulf• No.273 -3 of 1933. Copy with compliments forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. 1 c I^y Order )Khe Politic for Secretary to^the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ; &lt;%COITFlajj-.TI AL . ®«nsEg»., t »^9Siio:i ;; ''Js; 3135/33 . &gt;lb Colonial Office, Dovming Street, S .W .I. JT;, March, 1933. •SS^U QOfiffOENTlAi mm. May I trouble 1 'lafux 1 m the 55 1 % 881 /* Supplementary Agreement betv/een the Shaikh of Bahrein ■s^ii jcse* s-srg.oi tj.v, V;;C&gt; and the Bahrein Petroleum Company, a copy of which was enclosed in your confidential despatch, 1.o. 51 of the 22nd December, 1932. ' ■? C ~f A printer^ error appears to have occurred in the last sentence of the English text, the third line from the end. I think that the word 'as' should probably 'be 'in'. It does not seem necessary for a new Agreement to be prepared to put this right; an agreed alteration of all the copies should suffice. If you agree, would you arrange accordingly? A small point to trouble you with, but as it has been raised I suppose I must! fAKT COI.OHEL T .C . FOVOB, C.B.B.c tv p COITPIDEN 'IAL. D.O.No.296-3 of 1953. VtrlC'145. f ' Mi- The Residency, Bushire, 29th March 1933. Please refer to your letter 110 .18135/33, dated 4th arch 1933. I agree that an agreed alteration of all the x: copies of the Suypleraentary Agreement of 13th December 1932 should suffice and an taking steps to have the copies in the possession of the Bahrain Government, the Bahrain Political Agency and the Bahrain representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company altered accordingly. .ould you kindly do the same in respect of the copies held by His Majesty's Government and the London representative of the ^ a .iirain Petroleum Company ? v- A. C. C. Parkinson, Esq., C. M • Cr • | 0 . B . B •, The Colonial Office, London. S.W.I# A} /mtmmmm 1 CONFIDENTIAL, Tv *•*)' No. 297-15 of 1955 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis com pliments to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. 0 J;' 3 ia*jo o The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment 00- for information* / for necessary action. &amp; ^ ' &amp; British Residency and Consulate-General, BTJSHIRE. v'- ^ ^ ft Dated... .gg t h- Ife r cii- ■ l-»33 ; Reference to previous correspondence ; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Letter No.16135/33 of 4th March 1933 from the Colonial Off ice, London. 2. D.O.letter No. 296-3 of 29th March 1933 to the Colonial Off ice,London. bahkaiu oil c0hce3si0n. ■S£ 1 i r I f J Kf v:1.1. p.80. On the 2nd December 1925 an Agreement was reached between Shaikh Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifah, Shaikh of Bahrain, and the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, which gave the Company certain rights to search for and eventually to exploit oil and its allied products in Bahrain. The Agreement ■1 - arranged terms for these distinct stages of work: (a) Explora-^ |l tion, (b) Prospecting and tc) Mining. *11. I ( iv t o f i f i /3. Extension of Prospecting Licence wag then granted for a period of two years up to and including the 2nd day of December 1932, and by a further Supplementary Agreement this period was extended with effect to the 2nd December 1933. It should be noted that the Company asked for an extension of . two years, but the Ruler was unwilling to grant more than an extension of one year. It is not yet known whether the Company will again apply for an extension of the Prospecting Licence, or whether they will enter upon their Mining Lease period on 2nd December 1933. i ■If 1 i I i0 - ^ S'o 4. In the meantime Certain Modifications have been bade in the original Concession Agreement* (1) Article VI of the Mining Lease, which formed the Third Schedule to the Concession Licence, was modified in order to exempt the Shaikh from responsibility in the case of commissions or acts of theft or damage in certain cir cumstances in which he could not reasonably be held responsible* (2) Article IX of the First Schedule to the Concession Agreement was modified and a new Article IX (a) was insert ed. The modification was made in order to enable the Company to try out their wells and also to obtain oil to use in their drilling machinery, heating apparatus, etc. without being forced to enter upon their Mining Lease.5. Extension of Areas* Dmring the jrecent visit of Messrs.Lombardi and Janson to Bahrain, it became apparent that the Company were anxious to obtain rights over the whole of the I^iand for the pur- ■ Iposes of their Mining Lease, but although the subject was tentatively approached they withdrew from certain informal ' • jconversat ions between themselves and the iBahrain Government, The Company are apparently anxious to arrange for the extension of their territory, it is also necessary for us to obtain a settlement of a number of points which have cropped up in regard to the Mining Leases among other matters are the safe-guarding of the aeroplane landing ground, the question of linking the currency in which the royalties are |to be paid with gold, the amount of royalty, and the important question of * exploitable quantity* (see para (6). It might be possible to get some of these points settled in our favour,i.e. in favour of the Bahrain Govt,^ using the extension of territory as a bargainings counter.6 ' Exploitable Quantity . Shis is a most important point. It willbe necessary to come to some understanding about the meaning of the words 'Exploitable quantity' in order to prevent t.he possibility of the Company making success ful borings and then capping their wells in order to be able to say that they were not taking oil in commercial quantities, even though the oil might be there. This is not an impossibility in view of the number of new oil fields which are spring- in up in the world and also of the fact that the U.S.A. fields are at present under a governmental restriction of one- third of their return. What is apparently wanted is an authoritative definition of the term * exploitable quantity 1 . In the present state of the world oil markets the Company may well find it difficult to sell the oil they win from Bahrain, but presumably will not have the right - on this account - to deprive the Bahrain Government of their royalties. In the term * exploitable quantity* presumably the emphasis is on the Quantity' s that is t o say when sufficient quantity of oil is being pro duced from the wells the Company will have to pay royalties irrespective of the fact whether they can sell it or not. But the exact qunntity which is to be considered 'exploitable 1 is now nowhere laid down in the'Agreement, it waswas perhaps to cover this point that the amount 100 tons per well was laid down in Clause IX, but this figure has now been excised, (paragraph 4). Presumably the term * exploitable quantity* is in common use in Oil Agreements, and precedents from other fields can be f ou n d • i 1 J i ! I'GoaiiaenUal. OOHHOENTUl HtOOSOS iifr i li.O.MotC/ . J Political Agency, Bahrain,the Yth April iitob. /tus he^U-f Will .you jtindly refer to your aemi oiiicial letter No:262-S oated the &lt;i&lt;dnd March 1933 regarding xhe fj * | currency in which royalty under the Bahrain Oil Concession is to ue paicu I nave discussed the matter with Beigrave ana, indeed,had none so very tentatively and conlide&amp;tially before writing to you on the subject. He is fuiiy aiive to the possibility of a loss in this direction (indeed,! fancy I unci that is his reason for wishing his own provident/money to be invested m Sterling),and thinlssthat it should be guarded against. It is true that the Bahrain G-overnment agreed to the rupee rate of royalty,but their agreement in oil matters has been largely a question of signing documents of an highly technical nature,drawn up in London and accepted by them on a basis of trust that we are securing their interests. More over, this possibility of loss due to currency is one perhaps hardly apparent,unless one has been in contact with the vehement demands put forward oy the protagonists of the ls/4d rupee (quite apart from extremists who would deliberate ly debase the rupee). 4. It is true that a large proportion of Bahrain^ trade is conducted with India on a rupee basis,but much of that trade with India,such as sugar,is of a transit nature so would oe susceptible to a depreciation of tne rupee. (2) &gt;n f ble Lieut Colonel T.C .W .Powle,C.B.E., Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf, Bushire.2. s. But ray point is,in any case,that such a loss will inevitably become known,and I feel that,should tnere be a loss irom this cause,our good faith would be gravely called in question. y /(2) No:C/l47# Political Agency, Bahrain, the 7th April 1^33 Confidential* From:- Lieut Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. ent. To:- The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf, Bushire* Sir I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter dated the 4:th April 1933 from the Chief Local Representative,The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,in which ne applies for an extension ox the Prospecting License for one year as xrom the ^nd December 1933 under Clause 4 of the Concession Agreement, and also puts forward an alternative proposal involving an extension of the area in Bahrain over which the Company nopes to ODtain rights. c. I nave sent a copy of tne letter to the Bahrain Government and have asked for an expression of tneir views on the proposals contained m it. 3. In the meantime,! would only observe that the Cnief Local Representative words the third paragraph of nis letter in such a way as to suggest that the Company is entitled to an extension of the Prospecting License. I nave examined the 31, ^ wording of Article 4 of tne Agreement oetween Shaiida Hamad Din Isa A1 Khalifah,Shaiidi of Bahrain,and the Eastern and G-eneral Syndicate Limited,dated the 2nd Decemoer 192b and Clause d of P' /r fMthe Second Scnedule (Privileges to be enjoyed by the Company under the Prospecting License) attached to that Agreement and I do not think that tne Company can be neld to oe entitled to an extension of the Prospecting License,but consider that thequestion of any further extension of the Prospecting License must be treated on its merits. 3. The Chief Local Representative's letter is dated at Kuwait on tne 4th April 1933 and reached me on the ?th April. He has since,! understand,left Kuwait for Cairo or Jeddah,but he has not communicated his movements to me and the Fields Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited tells me that he does not know his address. The Manager of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited tells me that the Cnief Local Representative was at Shepherd's Hotel,Cairo,but that he thinks that he is now on nis way to Jedaaii. Tne Chief Local Represent ative demands an answer to nis letter by thirty days from the 20th April,but has disappeared,so that I have no one with whom I can communicate on any points ( such as the use of the word 'entitled 11 ) which may arise or on which the Bahrain Government may wish to nave fuller information. I have the nonour to be Sir, lour most obedient servant. Lieut Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain.UiA P vloj UL GOHFIiffiHTIAlL. Britisn Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Busnire, tne I7tn April, ly^5. o • 2 6. Sir k r u vith reference to your deapatcn Confidential, \ - ^ dated 27tJ:i October 1^32, I Jaave tne nonour to enclose a copy hm of a letter 0.0/147, dated 7th April 1933, from tne Politi cal Agent, Bahrain, with whicn he sends a copy of a letter dated tne 4th April 1933, from tne Chief Local Representa tive of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, applying under Article IV of the Concession of 1^2b for a further extension of the prospecting licence for one year as from the 2nd December 1933, and also putting forward an alternative pro posal involving an extension of tne prospecting licence until the 2nd March 1935 and an increase in tne area in Bahrain over which the Company hopes to secure mining rignts. A copy of the letters has been sent to the Honourable Lieutenant Colonel T.C^Fowle, in case he wishes to discuss tne contents witn you while in .London# 5 # a copy of tnia despatch and of its enclosure is being sent to the Foreign Secretary to tne Government of * India. sent under P.L. Jsio«384-S of 17/4/33• (Hef.our p # l,No.937-S of 22/12/32) ^ 1,1 ' 1 nrve the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. Lt.-Colonel, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian G -ulf. lis Majesty's Secretary of State for tne Colonies, THE COLONIAL OFFICE, LQIxDON . • f ' I 11N, /^A4 Confidential. !)• 0♦ Ko« 386-S of 1933« tr: 0 WU k lS^9i||, iff 4. J '' i ' •J' 1 3i]i? t 9ut If, 9 Tij 0 V: alslfi. ii30ig ii:] ;; lOS£SOii rloTiii lojuij an? lift 370 OIH' ,a:' The Besidency, Bushire, 17th April 1933* In continuation of my letter of 10th April ( as Political Agent, Bahrain }, 1 enclose a copy of a despatch Ho. 26, dated the 17th April 1933, to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. w- 'n h r 2. I should perhaps have explained, when writing a sisss the enclosure as Political Agent, Bahrain, that Major Holaies had sent a copy of his letter dated the 4th April 1933 informally to the Adviser, Bahrain Oovernment. I, therefore, judged that the hest course was to ask for the views of the Bahrain Governfiient at once, so that no desire to delay matters, or to hide them from the Huler of jaahrain, should he imputed to us Isy the interests involved. By doing this, Major Holmes has violated Td- C'5' Condition 0 of the Schedule to the Supplementary Agreement /' dated the 12th June 1930 concluded 'between the Shaikh of Bahrain and the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, which lays down that ftI98 3-^ 5^ m &amp; iass ^ y f , ''All communications which that official may desire on rn C'5l 'hehalf of the said Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited i no aadress to the Shaikh of Bahrain shall he made 'through the British Political Agent in Bahrain. 14 I think ( I write from memory ) that this practice of * sending informal copies of letters to the Adviser has been ' adopted in the past on one or two occasions, hut I think that it would l)e well for the Political Agent, Bahrain, to * The Hon•hie Lieut-Col. T.G.Fowle, O.B :ojo ^z to draw Major Holmes' attention ( verbally In the first Instance ) to Oonditlon 0 and inform him that it would he preferable for him to desist from this practice in future / x 3. It may te of use to you to know that Els iiixcellenoy Shaikh Hamad is strongly against a further extension of the irospecting Licence. Me will, I believe, also he against giving a wider area to the Bahrain ietroleum Ooiapany without first getting the Anglo Persian Oil Oonipany to hid against them, hut he is desperately in need of money.CONFIDENTIAL. ) / ^o-385-S of 1933, t g The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliraents to The -Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). f or information. 4*^ 1 ^ 'Cy \ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 1.7 .th . Apr .i.l.. 19.3.3.. Reference to previous correspondence ; letter ^o.C/1.47. of 7th April, 1933. Description of Enclosure. Bahrain Name and Date, j ^ ^ Subjec!. ^-4 - 1. Despatch ^o.26 of 17th April 1933 to fits Majesty* a Bahrain Secretary of State for the Oil Colonies, London. Concession. 2. Demi-official letter Ho. 386-S of 17th April 1933 /to the Hon*ble Lt.Oolonel / T.G.Fowle, G.3.S.,London. •■ft • - \ |s| iRSIM GOLB 1 . L 2 2c/ 0 I ^ Downing Street, March, 1933. 1 BUSH IP' PHBIDSNCY. Am''- 7 Olic- / ?3 h OQNflOEHTIAL SEQ0R05. J Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch Ho. 18 of the 24th of February forwarding copies of the Supplementary Agreement concluded on the 15th February between the Bahrein Petroleum Company and the Sheikh of Bahrein and to request that I may 'be furnished with four typewritten copies of the agreement (Arabic and English) for distribution to the interested Departments of His Majesty's Government, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, iONOURABLE THE POLITICAL RESIDSUT IH THE PERSIAH GULF. 4 / 1HCOMglDBMTIAL. Mo. 593-S of IV33. British Residency &amp; Consulate-GenerKl, 3USHIRS, tne 19tli April, 1933. o A copy of the undermentioned v^per is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with the request that four more copies of the Supplementary Agreement executed on the Ibth February 1935 may be furnished. 2* It is requested that you will ask Major Holmes* oil'ice if they can supply four more of the printed Agreements. If not, the copies should be supplied in type. They need not be signed by His Excellency Shaikh Hamad or Major Holmes. By Order. 6 c &amp; for Secretary to tne Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. / 6^ Colonial Office despatch Persifcn Gulf -£*0.2, dated the 29th March 1933» joilli (J ***si Gonticieniial* / Ku r^- H! B£r 'EaMNerT Mo:C/ ^ . fA &lt;( From:- To:- G2 / ! im Political Agency, Bahrain,the 15tn April i&amp;to Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy Elhashimi, Indian Assistant i/c Current Duties, Bahrain. The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the Political Agent f s letter No:C/l47 dated the Vth April 1933 and to enclose a copy of a further letter dated the 11th April 1953 received from tne Chief Local Representative,^ Bahrain Petroleum Company Limitea. The letter is dated 'Kuwait. 11th April i^ !! ,Dut was received oy air mail xn a cover posted at Cairo oil txiat aate. It is signed:- 'Prank Holmes per Mohammad' 1 . 3. Attacned to the letter is a slip giving Major Holmes* address as follows:- A France Holmes, Apt 4:4 Smm C. 140 Sh Emad al Din, Cairo (Egypt). I iiave the xiouuur to oe Sir, Your most obedient servant, 'p r *1 S &lt;u . 'I /'pus-' c; ] d Indian Assistant, BaJiram.Copy ot* letter dated Kuwait 11th April 19S3 from Major F.Holmes,Chief iiocal Representative,The Ba&amp;rain Petroleum Company l»iinited,to the Political Agent,Bahrain. I have the honour to refer to my letter of 4th Instant and to enclose herewith one copy of the Indenture covering the proposed agreement between His Excellency the Shaikh 01 Bahrain and the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. This Indenture covers the proposition referred to in the second paragraph of my letter under reference.INDENTURE . Between SHAIKH HAMAD BIN SHAIKH ISA AL KHALIFAH,Shaikh ol Bahrain, (hereinatter caiied }f the Shaikh') acting on the advice ot tne British Political Resident in tne Persian Gruif of the one part and THE BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED (heremaxter caiied n tne Bahrain Ooiapany t, ),a Oompany incorpor ated under 'cue Laws ol tne Doininion of Canacuox tne otlier part. WHEREAS this Indenture is supplemental to tne Concession Agreement dated tne second, day of December One tnousand Nine nundred and Twenty-five and made between the Shaikn of tne one part and Eastern and G-eneral Syndicate Limited of tne other part and now vested by assignment in tne Company which Agreement has oeen extended and modified by an Indenture dated tne twelfth day of June One thousand Nine nundred and Thirty and further extended by Agreement to the Second day of December One thousand Nine nundred and Thirty-three# Now tms Indenture Witness^eth tiiat it is nereby agreed and declared tiiat tne said Concession Agreement snail oe lurther moditied in manner nereinafter appearing, tnat is to say:- 1. In lieu ot the right to select up to 100,uUO acres in not more tnan 3 blocks,as now provided in tne Concession,THE BAHRAIN COMPANY shall nave tne right until March ^nd,193b,to select up to 200,000 acres in not more than o blocks# Tne present Prospecting License is,therefore,extended to March ^Ld ? i935. In return for tms THE BAHRAIN COMPANY undertakes as follows (a) THE BAHRAIN COMPANY will pay THE SHAIKH Rupees Ten Thousand (Rs#10,000/-) within thirty days after the execution of tne AGREEMENT. (b) The annual payment of Rupees Ten tnousand (Rs.10,000^-) now provided to be paid to the SHAIKH under tne Prospecting License shall be changed hereafter to RUPEES TWENTY THOUSAND (Rs #20 ,000/-).]U -2- (o) The minimum annual payment of RUPEES THIRTY THOUSAND iRs..3U,U0U/-j as now provided to be paid THE SHAIKH commencing with tiae year after tiae aate of tne aeclaration that oil has oeen found, in commercially quantities shall be cnanged to RUPEES SIXTY THOUSAND (Bs.60,000/-). (d) Durxiig- the continuance of tne Concession out in no event lor more than TWENTY (20) months,THE BAHRAIN COMPANY will advance x to THE SHAIKH Rupees Nine thousand (Rs»^,000/^) each month,commencing with the month following the date of the execution of the Agreement* These monies so advanced may oe recovered by THE BAHRAIN COMPANY (without interest) from oil royalties due THE SHAIKH in the following manner and not otherwise If and when the royalty due THE SHAIKH for any one year exceeds Rupees Sixty thousand (Rs.60,000/-),THE BAHRAIN COMPANY may deduct and retain an amount up to ONE-FOURTH of such excess for every such .year until the total of tne amounts so deducted and retained by THE COMPANY is sufficient to satisfy the monies advanced to THE SHAIKH by THE BAHRAIN COMPANY. Dated bHaiJtti ol tlanram. BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. M Its Attorney m xact. Before me,dential. No. ^ of 1351 Office of the adviser to the Government. Behrain. D&amp;ted, Dil IIe,j 27. 1351 April 22, 1933 From The Financial adviser to the GoYernment, Behrain, Persian Gulf. To H. B. IPs Political Agent, Bahrain. h ^ Sir, I hove the honour to refer to your G/l46 dated Vth April 1933 enclosing a letter dated 4th April 1933 from the Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, who applies for an extension ol the Prospecting License for one year and who makes an alternative proposal. The whole matter has been carefully considered by His Excellency Shaikh Hamad and it has been discussed very fully with Shaikhs Mohomed, Jadullah and Sulman. The opinion which was finally arrived at is expressed in the enclosed letter addressed to you by H. E. Shaikh Hamad. Briefly this government is not disposed to grant the extension of one year which it considers it has the right to grant or refuse. The fact that last summer, when the Company applied for an extension of two years of which only one year was granted, is taken as a definite indication that2— that this government has the right to grant or to refuse siioh an application. If however this govern ment is informed by the British Government that accord ing to the meaning of the Concession it is not within this governments power to withold the extension then it will be reluctantly compelled to give way. It is unwilling to grant this extension as it would result in postponing the increased payments (Rs 30,000/- per annum) which become due when the Company enters the Mining Lease. If however this government is definitely informed by you that its attitude, which is based on its own interpretation of Clause IV, is tenable,-it is then prepared to allow the extension on conditions that the Company in return for being given an extension, to which they have no definite right, make a loan to the government from its future Royalties. In the case of the Chief Local Representative T s second proposal; this government is prepared to consider granting a mining lease over the second 100,000 acres if the Company will pay a more adequate amount. In bcth these matters H. E. Shaikh Hamad is anxious to hear the opinion of the British Covernment as soon as possible. The financial situation is at present serious and it is likely to become more serious owing to the probable loss of the R. E. trade and it would be a very great relief to H. K. Uhaikh Hamad if he could count on an increase in the revenue of the State from payments % from the Bahrain Petroleum Company. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant C(j) 1 t Behrain, 26th Dil Haj 1351 From Hamad bin Isa aUTMlifeh, To Lieut Col. Gordon Looh. H. B. M's Politioel /igent, Bahrain. Mo. C/146 dated April 7, 1933, addressed to the Adviser eaolosing a letter from Major Frank iiolmes, Uhief Representative, Bahrein Petrolwn Co., Ltd. We are sur prised at the absence of Major Hoiaes from Bahrain during the discussion of such an important matter. We should be obliged if you would inform the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf of the following facts. We understood that the Company wishes us again to extend the Pros pecting License for another year. The Company asked us last year to extend the prospecting license for two years and after considering their request we refused to extend He have received your letterC ^31 j-o c-ll I extend it for two years, but we tsgreed to exteua it for oue year, eadiBg Sad December 1933, corres ponding with 14tb Sbaebaa 1352. It appears fro® the letter of Major lioxraea tbat the Company considers tbat it has the right to another year. although we agree that the Coopeny has earried out its work to the best of its ability and without delay, we think that according to the meaning of article 4 of the Concession the Company has not the right to another year in case we ere not pleased to grant another year. iirticle 4 of the Concession is as follows.- 'The prospecting license referred to in the preceding ..rticle may be extended for a further period of two years on the Company's showing to the satisfaction of the Shaikh, acting on the adrice of the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf that such an extension is justified.' r /e previously refused to grant the Company two years and now we see no reason for changing our decision. If however, the meaning of ..rticle 4 is not as we uudurstand it and we are obliged according to the ConcessionGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. 1**1 22nd a p^I y \ \ ^33 ear Colonel l-och, I enclose a reply to your letter about the oil question as well 3 a long letter from the ^ha-'kh on the subject. As you know what the Shaikh wants js money and he was inclined to slcome any offer v/h -1 ch would bring in some cash at once. was Tr er y &gt;&lt; moyed that the Company should go back on their offer which was made len the directors were in ^ahrain, he suggested that this m^ght be mtioned in the letter but I thought perhaps it was better not to jfer to it. They pruned down their offer a great deal and I think lis is the result of Lombardl and the Americans re^considering the itter after uhey left here. o&gt; c **- 1 am not at all sure how we stand o^er the question of the Coy's right ' to the extension, when we examined the Agreement the Shaikh id Mohammed and Sulman said tney considered that the Coy had no ' Right' it Abdulla did not entirely agree with them on this point. If oney are it entitled to it the idea is to let them ha^e it for a consideration, &gt; amount is mentioned in the letter but we thought it might be possible o &gt; get a loan olt of them ui say Rs 60,000 repayable yearly o^er four fi^e years from the royalty exceedlng,say, one lac each year. If Holmes had made the same offer that he did when he was here I link the Shaikh would ha^e been ^ery much inclined to accept it and to ltr e them the extra area. Rumours of many oil companies collecting at ledda has reached us^nd this has opened the Shaikh's eyes to the ^ssibility of playing off one company against the other, also Haji i-lliamson is here and I think he is doing some propaganda, Skinner is -ry worried about his being in Bahrain and I am sure he thinks he is r ying to negotiate with us. Williamson is calling on the Shaikh today, ^oo came to tell me tins morning assuring me that he would go with him that it was entirely a call for salaams, but 1 ha^e my doubts. The news about Ibn Saoud's boat is ^ery disturbing and it makes the haikh all the more anxious to get some money from oil.Wmf' | ) ■ I 'i: 1' I dont know what you will think of the Shaikh s letter, fi discussed it and decided what to say, hen ' .rote the letter it into Arabic and then we went o-er it carefully again and adj few bits, the result is what 1 send you now. Yrs sincerely. b ■H . mmw86/2 Telegram XX. Ifrom Political Hesident, BuBhire. To Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, No • 9. Repeated Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, No• 321. Dated 27th April 1933. My despatch of IT'th April, No. 26. Bahrain Government are not disposed to grant without quid pro quo further extension of ir'rospecting Licence for one year as it would result in postponing increased payments of Hs. 30,000 which become due when Company enters on Mining Lease. 2, They regard Concession as giving them right to grant or refuse such an extension. Interpretation is not however quite free from doubt and Bahrain Government state that if they are informed by His Majesty's Government that according to the meaning of the Concession it is not within their power to with-hold the extension they will be reluctantly compelled to give way. If, however, Kis Majesty's Government agree that the Bahrain Government's interpretation is correct they are prepared to give extension on condition that Company make loan to Bahrain Government to be recovered from future royalties. 3 e Bahrain Government consider that additional area has greater value than area originally given as it is now known that ail exists and they think that offer of Company is inadequate. They are uneas:/ about question of declaration of commercially exploitable quantity and write M on this matter we desire to know the truth as to when the Company will begin to exploit the oil'. Bahrain Government a re not satisfied with terms of loan repayment suggested. Finally they write that 'it is unlikely that we would grant the Company the additional area/ ' 1; la Iarea which they request ue for unleBs we are sure that the conditions that it offers to us are suitable and adequate to us and the public good'. They think that it would be just to give the Bahrain Petroleum Company first refusal of additional area but point out that if they (Bahrain Government) offer additional area to another Company they might get more favourable offer from that Company* They clearly expect to be consulted as to their wishes before any arrangement is concluded with Company. 4. In Skaikh/s letter he expresses surprise at Holmes* absence from Bahrain at this juncture and astonishment that Company should demand answer in a matter of such importance as additional area in a short t ime. 5, Information at my disposal is insufficient to enable me to gauge adequacy of Company's proposals, which I understand are less favourable than those which con versations during Lombardi^ and Janson^ visit led Bahrain Government to suppose might be made: but following informa tion may be helpful to you:- (a) Bahrain Government and Shaikh personally are % sorely in need of money. (b) They are alive to commercial and strategic advantage of oil field on Island near sea as opposed to, for example, Iraq field. (c) In view of rumours of large sums accruing to Iraq Government and offered for rights elsewhere they are anxious lest they may not get full value for their field. (d) It is understood that Bahrain Petroleum Company propose to market their oil in the Sast so will escape Buez Canal dues. Pll U ti f: |!l| 6. Kindly give a copy of this tele green to Fowle. 4 '5 if 4' I • HE SI DEM*.'V- Telegram P. From Political Hesident , Bushire. To Secretary,of State for India, London. No. 322. Dated the 27th April 1933. t7 / for J 'owle , Lalthwaite from Loch. Following 'begins. Secretary of State for the Colonies has been asked hy me to give you copy of my Bahrain oil telegram of the 27th April. 2. I am privately informed that Bahrain Govemment in return for one year's extension of Prospecting Licence i have in mind loan of Rs. 60,000 repayable, at a time when Royalties exceed one lakh yearly, over three to five years from Royalties; also that if offered really good terms by the Company the Shaikh might be willing to grant the additioal area. 3o I would beg that the importance of doing nothing over oil or air liable to give Shaikh idea, rightly or wrongly, that Bahrain is being sacrificed to other interests, may be impressed on His Majesty's Government. The fact that we imposed, in favour of Ibn Saud, two per cent, transit due is still remembered and, as you know, adverse comments are being passed on Arab littoral comserning events in Kuwait and Mohammerah. Ends. - RESIDENT.Telegram Jrom Political Resident, Bustiire# To Secretary of State for India, London. no. 3a} Dated the 27tji April 1933* LaitJiwaite from Lociu Following for Powle begins:- 1. Haji Williamson was to call on Sheikh on 22nd April and Skinner is very worried at his presence in Bahrain, thinking that he is trying to negotiate with Bahrain (iovern- ment. Yusuf Kanoo came to assure Belgrave that it was entirely a call for salaams, so presumably it was more I 2. Rumours of many Oil Companies collected at Jedda ha\e strengthened Shaikhs idea of possibilities in play ing off one Company against another. 3 # News of Bin Saud's ship has made Shaikh all the more anxious to get money out of oil. PISRSOHAL. Grateful if you would let me know when your date of return is finally fixed. Ends.s t r*- 'A s I 8 , ' CONFIDENTIAL. No. 436 - S of 1933 ^ i u The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, s&gt;v» and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the nndermeniioned docu ment (s). for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Jr.. 19.5.3 Reference to previous correspondence: BUSHIRE Printed Letter ^o.SSS-S of 17th Aprul,1933 Description of Enclosuw. Name and Date. p' i. Ul 2 - 3. Bushire telegram Ho,9 of -27th April 1933 to Secretary of State for the Colonies. Bushire telegram ^0.322 of 27th April 1933 to Secretary of State for India. Buahire telegram 1^0.323 of of State for India. Subject. Bahrain Oil Concession.CONFIDENTIAL. ^ 27/437-U of 1933. Tho Hon bio tli© Political R6sid6nt in fcliG Persian Gulf presents his c( pliments to His liajesty's Secretary of State for tiie Colonies, Lcaridon. The Foreign Secretary to the Govern ment of India, tiiiala. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency v and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. ^ rv g fn t-f X. Bahrain letter So.C/154, dated the 15th April 1935, with enclosure. 2» Bahrain letter No«C/l61 # dated the 22nd April 1933 with enclosure. Copy with compliment Political ^gent, Bahra Bushire telegr^im Ho.9 (Ho.321 to Ocverranent of India) dated the 27tn /pri 1 1933, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date.86/2. ZISJ3 ? Telegram G.T.G• • trcrD {Decretory of btate for Colonies, London. rj -' 0 political Kesident, i^usiiire. unnumbered. lasted ist aria received on the ana may x95^. xour telegram 9. Please repeat part 1 first paragraph from 'grant to further', .fart 2, 5 (bj from 'sea to Iraq'. Telegram XX ^rom Political Resident, Bushire. To Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. ITnnuinbered. Dated 2nd May 1933. \ IMPORTAK ^. Your telegram of 1st instant. Required nart of telegram repeated as requested, t? ar ^ * 'grant.! without quid pro quo further 1 *. Part II ^5 'sea as opposed to, for example, Iraq* 1 . 4'' 9 - HRSIDCTT.m % / .A CQniiaeniial &gt; No:0/l69. To, Political rain, the ijytii April iyisii. Memorandum. The Secretary to the Kon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian &amp;uii,Bushire. % Please refer to your Endorsement No:39^-S dated the 19th April 1933. I enclose lour type-written copies of tne Supplementary Agreement executed on tne iDth February 19^3 oy His Excellency the Shaikn of Bahrain and the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. It nas not oeen possible to uotain printed copies ol the Agreement as Major Holmes is not in Bahrain. 'i Indian Assistant, In charge of Current Duties, Political Agency,Bahrain.3jj t « 1i UU ,1 liW * v_ Copy ol letter aated the Z6th April 193b irom Major Fraxiiv iio±mes,Ghiei Local Representative,The Bahrain Petroieurn Company Limited,Kuwait,to the Political Agent,Bahrain. I am sending you nerewith lour additional copies - v»itn Araoic translation — oi my letter to you dated Kuwait ^tth April 19o3,being an application for an extension of the Prospecting License of the Bahrain Oil Concession (Dec.2.1925) also an alternative offer in lieu ox an extension oi the Prospecting License. By mistake a translation oi the suggested agreement in the form of a Deed was forwarded to you. This Deed was cirawn up in order to iiave the Arabic translation ready in case His Excellency Shaikh Hamad should prexer it to tne extension. If you should oe in a position to reply to tne enclosed letter,would you send it c/o Mr.Russell,Mespers, Bahrain,who will forward it to me immediately.ty &gt;y a ::m mt u. Artioie ♦ After um words 'oach right, however, shall not include the exclu^lv# right to s&gt;ell such prodsactft within the leased ar-€« w , insert the ro 11c wings ~ 'The Lesfceete aha.il at their own expense forthwith eiect and at ail &amp; maintain and k&amp;ep in repair substantial houadary ssarK.® at Um comers of the leaded area accord! rig to the e mare at ion shown in the plan he.retc anaexed ©o that the hounaariea of the leaded area my at all timea b® e1aa r 1/ d#fined'• Article ? .1. j t rai-a£raph* After the words 'At the ex .iry oi the Agreement the grouna and all la movable property left by tfte Coiipsny aheXX be handed back to the sheiith' add. * ai 1 productive weila and 'ooriiiaja ahsil he hanuec over In good, ©rtier and repair ana fit for further working '• Articl e qi. After the words 'in cofls^erciei ij expioitahie quantities' add 'in addition to the maounts rei furred tc in the- preceding art of thia Article the company a hall pay a royalty at th^ rate per ton provided in Article VTII. on all net crude oil ^on and saved (i.e., after redacting water and foreign substance® and oil requii^ed as fuel for drilli^Mi purposes in the Bhtlkh s territories sua for pulping to field storage) • This follows the saeadaent recently «aue m Article IX- of tne second schedule to the Agree.afnt./V) D Articles Jit and x* i!MHlimi*li I iup W W&gt;i WWWXWWWi i 11 &lt;* ml wliiwu immn i j i t should be noted that the mmml dmmd vent p»yabie b/ the Company regains at r:». 10• 000 per aaauua Cor rive years, or until the Co-.no an/ declare® that oil hm* been i oun^l in co.a ie rc i a.i 1 © jrp.ioit&amp;l^Xe ^uantitieiii ictiTter 1 which the -ead rent heco.iee r®. 50#000. in view or the extensiont which have l&gt;e«n granted to the company and the fact that oil haa already- been proved in two weile, it is perhaps worth considering wh*. th^r they could not be ssssked. In return for the further extension of the prospecting licence which they are now deiaanciing, to raa^e an annual payment of k». 30.000 at an earlier aate than that provided in the for a of lease* as at pit ^ent provided the company need not make the declarstion until five years fro a the date of the raining lease* Article Y« The Meaning of the paragraph beginning ,? .f the Company' &amp; work ifc aelayed by such events are mentioned in thife Article^ aoee not seeia very clear# It appears as if the word 'of' htm been omitted after the word t# explratlon M » nrticle VUl. After words 's«. 10.000 provided for ia Article *TI' c n in edd M (l)^ instead of 'for/the cuetossary operations of the Co.apanjr's installations' &gt;/^oil required at fuel for /v drilling purposes in the j heiich* s territories and lor pimping to field storsgo'# (2) w a royalty of 4 annas per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas sold by the lessees and calculated st an ab^iutts o pressure of one atsaosphere and »t a temperature ox oj F# (3) A royslty of 1 anna per gallon in resfiect oi all casing head\ &lt;y copy sent \ ^ [J &gt; - i ^ J Dear Starling,' O OtiHOtSTUi ^iiillica j I have been looking into the question 01 the area covered by the Sheikh of Bahrein's dominions, consequent on discussion with Giffard, with the 2. The Sheikh maintains a rather nebulous claiis to certain areas on the Arab coast, with which it is unnecessary to deal here. His dominions may be regarded as consisting of the Bahrein archipelago. The Bahrein archipelago consists of the Island of Bahrein, and of the adjoining islands of Muharraq, Itan Na'assan, Sitrah and Nabi Salih. The area of the Bahrein Island is 208 square miles, its maximum length being 30 miles and its maximum breadth 10 miles. The area of i.ftdiarraq is 5i square miles. This island is f.c. Starling Esq. separated following result (Copy forwarded to BaJirain under P«L«No*b23-S of l9/b/33J« JNo ref./ ILI separated from Bahrein by a strait li miles broad; and its superficies is stated to be almost trebled at low tide by broad flat reefs of Coral, while the rocky spit of Ras al Khasaifah runs out nearly 4 miles to seaward from the North West corner, Umm Na 1 assan is about 2 miles off the West coast of Bahrein Island, and measures less than 4 miles in length from North to South by about 2i miles in breadth: while Sitrah which is separated from the East Coast of Bahrein Island by a narrow and shallow channel, measures 4i miles from North to South and tapers from the North, where it is H miles broad, to its Southern extremity. Nabi Salih is situated in the large inlet of Kabb on the Eastern side of Bahrein Island, off the North West corner of Sitrah Island. It measures about i mile in each direction. 4. The existing Bahrein Petroleum concession is I understand in respect of areas in Bahrein Island only. 5. The information above, which is I fear rather scrappy, is taken from Lorimer's Gazetteer. The PersianPersian Gulf Pilot suggests that the archipelago is surrounded by reefs running out to a considerable distance and banks to which the Sheikh would no doubt lay claim if any question arose; and in considering any grant of a concession in repect of his 'dominions' or 'Bahrein' it would seem necessary to have a clear understanding as to precisely what ife covered: and in addition to the special safeguards we are anxious to secure on stragetic grounds, to ensure that no rights are conceded either in respect of, or of such a character as prbjudicially to affect, pearling banks in the Bahrein area or elsewhere in which the Sheikh may have an interest either in his own right or in common with the other Arab rulers of the Gulf. 6. I am sending copies of this letter to Parkinson, Rendel and Moore. I am also suggesting to Moore that the Admiralty representatives might bring a chart of Bahrein, which would give a clearer idea of the position than the rather scattered information above,to this afternoon's meeting. Yours sincerely, U. Q, LAlTHWAHfcBusMre , the 18th Kay 1933. BUSHif-F RESIDENCY^ ' „ ^ 1 tr ' . 9 7 ' t■:, *i.{u\una. i' f Ah Pi I V- C OiiFIt'.'iTiAL iuiiaSQS^ ] ' ^ ^rom Lieutenant-Colonel Grordon Loch, I .A,, 'Political Agent, Bahrain, To The Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to enclose, for your information, a copy of a letter dated the x^th Kay 1933 from the Chief Local Hepre sentative of The Bahrain 'Petroleum Company, Limited, rcgaroing certain proposals which he has placed before His Ebccellency Shaikh Hamad 'bin Isa A1 Khalifah. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, oLrcX Lt•-Colonel, ^'Political %ent, Bahrain.TH E BAHREIN PETROLEUM GOMPAFY LIMITED , Bahrein Islands, Persian Gulf. 17th May 1933• His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein• Dear Sir (i) I have the honour to refer jrou to my letter dated April 4th, 1933 (copy of which is herewith enclosed). His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrein requested me to call at Sakhir to discuss with him the subject matter of the ahove mentioned letter. His Excellency informed me that - taking into consideration the stage reached in developing the Bahrein Oil Concession - he had formed the opinion that the Bahrein Petroleum Company's offer - as expressed in my letter of y/ April 4th - was inadequate. After considerable dis cussion - at which Shaikh Sulaiman was present - the result of which was that His Ebccellency Shaikh Hamad agreed (subject to the approval of the Political Resident, the Political Agent, (Bahrein) and the Financial Adviser to the Bahrein aovernraent) - in con sideration of the payments hereinafter reserved and con tained in exercise of hi$ powers as Ruler and Sovemgn of his Dominions for himself his Heirs and subjects - to grant unto The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited the exclusive right and easements whereby the Company shall be entitled throughout the whole of that portion of His Excellency the Shaikh^ Territories - including all the Islands and all the Territorial Waters - remaining after excluding ®ii and apart from that area already covered/. 2 - v 1 ' covered Ky the Concession Agreement dated December 2nd 1925, to explore and search the surface of the ahove mentioned area as described in this Resent upon the fol lowing terras and conditions:- (a) Upon the day Kis aicoelloncy Shaikh Hamad Bin Esa A1 Khalifah, Ruler of Bahrein signs and seals • 5 ,, th© Deed Instrument covering the area (described in Ell para one \l) hereof) an Initial Payment by the Company of the sum of Rupees Forty Thousand (40,000) shall be made for the primate purse of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad, and in additionid the Initial Payment of Rupees Porty TJiousand 1 (40,000) ^ . v ryy^viv mentioned in this Present the Company shall pay for the private purse of Hid Excellency Shaikh Hamad Twenty (20) Monthly Payments of Rupees 'rhree Thousand (3,000) each the First of such Monthly Payments of Rupees Three Thousand (3,000) each' shall be made one (l) month from the date of the execution of the Deed Instrument covering the area (para One (l) hereof) and the remaining Monthly Payments of Rupees Three Thousand (3,000) each shall be made on the same date of each subsequent month until the whole of the Twenty (20) Monthly Payments have been made. ■ I ,0 t tixl c&gt; .'4^4 y , (b) Twenty Monthly Payments of Rupees Ten 2.. Thousand (10,000) will be iosde to the Bahrain Govern men t ♦ The First of su ch T w en t y (20) v K io n v f Monthly Payments of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) to be paid within Fourteen (14) Da3 r s of the execution of the Deed Instruments The remaining MontMy Parents of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) to be made to the Bahrein Grovemment on the same date of each, subsequent month until the whole of the Twenty (20) Monthly Payments have been made# .Pfr' (c) The Concession granted covering the whole of the additional area including all the Islands and all the Territorial Waters of the Shaikh's Dominions ahall be governed in all ways by the terms and conditions as laid down in the Concession Agreement of December 2nd 1925, and the additional area shall, aoiyx upon execution thereof, become an integral part of the Concession Agreement of December 2nd 1925, excepting certain payments which shall be increased as set forth in the following ' paragraph (d)• (d) The Payments to be made on the additional area- aa^regards annual rental and minimum Royalty • shall be the same a.s laid down in the Concession Agreement dated December 2nd 1925, and such payments shall be in addition thereto, and the same shall apply to the Deed Instrument covering the whole of the remainder of the available Territory of Bahrein including all the Islands and all the Territorial Waters (paragraph One (l) hereof). The Prospecting License for both areas upon the execution of the Deed granting the additional area/ shall ipso facto continue current for a period of Twenty (20) Months from the effective date of such Deed, and thereafter the Mining Lease (Schedule III) shall become operative. (e) Major Holmes shall place the above terras before/3 • te.ore the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, and he shall inform the -Political Agent, Bahrein, either b '{ letter or by cable within Twenty One 121) Days wiener the Company are prepared to agree to this 8 ^oeHency Shaikh Hamad Bin Esa A1 Khalifah - or othe rwise» completion of the Twenty (20) Monthly Payments Mentioned in paragraph, (b) hereof ^he Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited is willing to make a loan or loans to the Bahrein Government against future Hoyau. .ies on Oil which may 'become due from time to timej moreover the Company is prepared to make a specific loan to the Bahrein Government of Hupees Two Hundred Thousand (200,000) or part thereof in Twenty Monthly Instalments of Hupees Ten Thousand (10,000) each. The Pirst Monthly Instalment/ of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) of such specific loan to 'become due in One Year and Nine Months from the date of these Presents, PROVIDED ALWAYS that the world market for Oil and the development of the Oil rosources of the Bahrein Concession during the above mentioned period of One Year and Mne (21) months continue to 'be such that they present a reasonable pros pect of making the recovery of such specific loan possible / but given unfavourable prospect of recovery the Monthly Payment may cease or be suspended by the Company until conditions become normal. (3) The Recovery of the ibove mentioned loan or loans may only be made from any Royalties on Oil - which may become due - in excess of Rupees Eighty Thousand (80,000) in any Calendar Year, (4)' I have promised His Ixcellency the Shaikh to inform the London Office of the Company of the subject matter of this letter and to request a decision with regard to the offer of His Excellency with the least possible delay. I am, Sir, « tn / -n_ i Your, obedient servant, SD/ .^rank ^ » Chief I^ ocb I Representative THE BAHREIN HSTROLEIM COMPANY LIMITEDCOP Y. J? (xOvspjPMm OF BAHRAIN *&gt;% /, HiJZH CL&amp;tu* J C ' Dear Colonel Loch, In great haste as mail is closing and, I have isaj been all the morning with the Shailch, Holmes, Abdulla and Sulinan • I want to let you know certain developments re oil. 1« Holmes has ibade us another offer which sounds very much 'better than the former suggestions and which the ohaiich is anxious to accept. He is writing to you giving details. 2. I have seen a map of Bahrain,made 'by oil company surveyors, on which 100,000 acres is marked; it is startling, instead of being half the area, as we always supposed, the 100,000 acres is about 3/4 of the whole area of Bahrain Islands. Can you possibly ascertain the area of Bahrain from any sources in Bushire ? 3. Shaikh liamad will readily agree to accept 1/3 of the 3/8 Ro3ralty for himself, the rest to the Government; he would I am sure accept Re. 1/- out of the Rs, 3/8 if suggested, but one-third for himself would entirely satisfy him. I feel that this 4s a very big roatter so 1 let you know about it at once. Some arrangement could be made about Civil List, etc., roughly based on this percentage. Yours sincerely, SD/ C, Dalrymple Belgrave86/2 \ &lt;A r ■ Telegram H. From Political Hesident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain, ITo. 415. Dated 26th May 193 3. Imnortan t. Demi-official . ,1^ i Your letter of IRth May. Is assurance forthcoming from Shaikh that 'offer w was from Holmes, and not from himself? I should like, if possible, to send letter to Government hy this mall with my comments. - Jfowle.86/2 i\lO Telegram R. From Political Agent, Bahrain. Political 'Resident p Bush ire. No • 180 t Dated 87th (received 20th ) May 1933, Pemi-Of ficial. ^« r Your telegram of 26th instant. 1 hope to send letter from Shaikh with Master of Slow Mail. l^lease ask Mespers to collect. Offer was from Holmes hut Shaikh's letter is likely to contain interesting matter, -Please await Before commenting to London,nnWIDSNTIAL. ' British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUSHIi.B, tne 2nd June 1933, Sir, I hare the honour to enclose herewith copy of , a letter, dated tiie 17tli Hay 19S3. received by tHe Political Agent, Baiirain, from Major Holmes, which raises some important oonsideratlons. It will be observed tlrnt - in the last paragraph of his letter - Major ixOlmes reters to the proposals contained in his letter as the 'offer of His Bxetllency' (the Shaikh). It is obvious ttiat the latter is quite incapable of drawing up such a ^ complicated document, and I have received a brief telegram L.l^ from Colonel Loch that the 'offer' came in fact from Major Holmes. Unfortunately a further communication from Colonel Loch, mentioned in his telegram as being sent by post, has been over -carried to Basrah, it being too rough here for the steamer to land the mails. I hope to be in possession of the letter by next week when my detailed comBients will lollow* I am sending a copy of this despatch, with enclosure, to the Government of India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, Lt,-Colonel ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf His Majesty's „ , Secretary of State for the Colonies, The Colonial Office, .L, London# Jv- ICONFIDENTIAL . No- 596-S of 1933; The Hon ble tho Political R^sidont in the Persian Gulf presents his cjom- pliments to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s^ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 4 Dated '2nd' 'June' '1*93^ ' Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Bu shire despatch ^o.33 of 2nd June 1933 to His Majesty Secretary of State for the Colonies, with enclosure* Subject. Bahrain Oil Concession, Copy with copy of enclosure forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent,Bahrain, for information./ / X noyrFinsFT i 'Uj . irotCA® 8 ', : V ' , ' POLITICAL AGiillCY, i 1 Bakrain,the 29tli May 1933. Prom: - ^ ^ Lieut.Colonel Gordon Loch,I,A., / Political Agent, /^p BeJirain. ^/0} To:- I _ JOKHPfrM ijpKjg- ' The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, lib I have the honour to refer to my letter dated the 18th May 1933 and to say that I sent His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifah a copy of the letter dated the 17th kay 1933 from the Chief Local Represent- atiye of Uhe Bahrain Petroleum Corapaoy Limited,in which he states certain proposals regarding the desires of the Company for an additional area in Bahrain and regarding other matters» 2. A copy is enclosed of a letter dated the 28th May 1933 (equivalent to the 4th Safar 1352) from His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa. A1 Kha.lifah,in which His Excellency gives his views on the contents of the letter in question, 3, His Excellency^ letter deserves careful study, but it is well to note certain points which emerge.- (i) the first overture appears to have come from Major Holmes and not,as he states,from His Excellency Shaikh Hamad: (ii) His Excellency Shaikh Hamad denies that he agreed to any proposals or that he made any offer to the Company,and (iii) His Excellency declares that certain important matters, which appear in the letter were never (2) ■sSc* k- &gt;t SC V W' ''' ■(3) 1 mentioned to him at all: in particular tlie inclusion oj . t'ie -Territorial Waters (wliereas the conversation referred to Bahrain Island onlv) and the proYision that the question of the loan' (or 'better advance) mentioned in the second paragraph of Major Holmes* letter should he dependent on the world market for oil. 4» Major Holmes is again away from Bahrain (I 'believe in SngLEUid),so I have had no opportunity of discussing matters with him or of hearing ar^rbhing that he may have to say; and I am not, therefore, in a position to form an opinion on this curious affair,hut, on the face of it,I think that he should 'be called upon to explain:- 3' ^ (a) the infringement of Condition H C tt of the jP Schedule attached to the Indenture het7/een S3ialkh Hamad 'bin Isa A1 Khalifah and the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited dated the 12th June 1930 in approaching and endeavouring to negotiate direct with His Excellency Shaikh Hamad, (h) the apparent misrepresentation of what passed 'between himself and His Excellency Shaikh Hamad,which seems to he of a natiu-e which can hardly be attributed to faulty inter preting or to genuine mi sunderstanding,and (c) the inclusion in his letters,as agreed to 'by His Excellency, of matters which were not apparently discussed with His Excellency. 5, His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifah is most anxious to have the matter settled as soon a.s possible and,in view of the financial situation,to secure what benefit he can from the oil at an ea,rly date. He feels that the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited have some claim to first refusal of the remaJning area (and, I think,fears that he might fall between two stools if it were to be given to another Company); and he would be willing to let them have it provided that he felt assured (a) that he was getting fair terms and (t) thatthe Company would agree to suitable conditions in euIds ... • », ' teis® He is jJiowever,getting inipatient at the length of time which is elapsing without his obtaining any substantial smn of money, I have counselled patience,and have reminded him that the matter is an important one,and that it is to 'be hoped that the ultimate 'benefit will justify slow and careful handling of the matter, 6, I have no means of gauging the adequacy of the terms mentioned in Major Holmes* letter (assuming that it is to be treated as a basis for discussion),but it seems clear that the Company attach considerable value to the additional territory and I think that they might be induced by negotiation through responsible channels to mrke a better and more clearly defined offer, 7. There is one point on which I should give a serious warning. The phrase 'all the Islands and al' 1 the territorial waters' is a dangerous one,for besides the well known Islands of Bahrain (the main Island, Muharraq,Sitrah and one or two islets) claims are still made to other islands and to areas on the (4atar coa,Et (and possibly even on the Hasa coast). That these claims axe not regarded locally a.s dead and gone is shown by the fact that I have heard mutterings that the explorers of the Anglo -Persian Oil Company Limited in Qatar have examined places to which the Ruler of Qatar ha.d no right to allow them to go, and which people from, Bahrain frequent to this day a.s a summet xesort, indeed, it is said that as late as last year (1932) the Ruler of Qa.tar admitted in public that certai n areas on the Qatar coast pertain to Bahrain. I Lave refrained from making enquiries,but the fact of my having heard (4)V V ' r ; ? -4- of the matter shows that an awkward incident might arise at any time,unless the area allotted to the Company is carefully laid down. I have the honour to 'be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Li eut.Colonel. jr'oli t i c a 1 Ag en t, Bahr ai n.,. ' o—2»^ . S li-b J-» Lv 'J tP »l ylli ' ' Ll&gt; i jS*£^ ^ 2. ' i—^' fiJD _ / f—' ^Jzjlj IJ ) ^ ^ii/V&lt;0^XLt' ' 2\£^5 J J '-'Irf '&gt;'^&gt;1 U \kj~^Jajj- li j-&gt; — ^Tj^Lr'J^ 11&gt;-JU ' D I y^li, f 9ua*^aJ?\ Z- _ S ^XU i) I c—-'^ .^r 11 Ll-t- 6 - i i ,, * —^ • • ' . * ^ I L ~U^ Llf^u ' d-f^i 1 i -j Ji- ^ ^ LJ' 1 J ' ^ U -U^ U&gt;l £1^* l** « — He visited us twice at Sakiiir and both times Shaikh Salman was present. We did not request Major Hojjnes to visit us, but he visited us of his omi accord. Major Holmes mentions in his letter that we decided, during one of his two visits to us at Sakhir, to give to his Company the additional area, according to the conditions mentioned in his letter. Yes it is true that conversation took place about the additional area at Sakhir but we did not decide to give this Company the additional area, either at Sakhir or at any other place. Major Holmes infers that it was we who suggested the conditions mentioned in his letter, but in reality these conditions were sug gested by Major Holmes himself, not by us, but during the conver sation we made certain comments on his conditions and we said to him that the conditions and the sums he offered to us were not enough and we demanded more from him. On one occasion we asked of Major Holmes double the sum which he'&gt;0 I ' jxi\^i&lt;L*!.Ci ^Jb U U&gt;) ^ liii^ u -V ^ j\j&gt; \'Jj I . •jZ^ ^ Ll«- J L» -C /- Q'' % i t * ^ \ r y^^&gt;j&gt;' ej* ^ J ar' 2^ *J&gt;sC' aJ ^1-^ ^y^AJ 1 ^ ^ I ** &lt; ^ CJ 2 U-~ '* *' I / I ♦ J~ . ♦ 'J ♦ i a J&gt; U' , ( J-^ C^ \ £ i , l3'_^-^3-^ ^ ^ 2. J) ^\\ vV j KJ \\, &lt;-&gt; &lt;xl&gt; Ul L^&gt; \c^[L&gt; l/^Lr** 3 'c^ ^LJ-Oi'u^&gt;i&lt;jC-&gt; ir* I '-^ ' j-lc ' ljt&gt; JSU J*\y j&gt;J&lt; JX) -&gt; i L&gt;f ^ • ov L^ ^ _/- U^ U he offered to us. Another time a discussion took place that the Company should pay to us one third of the Royalty and should pay to our govern ment the remaining two third, but the Major does not mention this point in his letter at all. Moreover Major Holmes asserts that we agreed to some condi tions which were never mentioned to us. How is it reasonable that we should have agreed to something which we never knew about? He says that the Company has the right, accord ing to one of the conditions which Major Holmes mentioned in his letter to dig for oil in all the territorial waters. In truth there was no mention of territorial waters in our conversations. Our conversa tion referred to the additional area of Bahrain island only. It now appears that the addi tional area does not amount to more than 38,000 acres, includ ing towns, cemeteries and gardens. Also Major Holmes says that if the world market of oil' ^ • 0 jr^^ ji) 2 U ~*J&gt; jr&gt;LO '' ^ 'crL'' A^ U&gt;^ 'X^ ' ^ 4 - j o^J —'c— * * U^ U' ( • A—* IX-' I jxiil^ 1 ^ ju'^ l li'iufeJ c^UkJ* &gt;I&gt; ' I i XS j J j, . —-- J ^r yw^' c-^ Lli-^ ^/--' O ' &gt;' ' ^aXl—J- 1 du? J-fi- •^p'! 1'' ^C^cs* \j j o • [r^ ^A^fsZ&gt; U J t^ '-&gt; 1» ^^ u^ &lt;_-— Uo^ &amp;-ypJj «jj'»i&gt;ui' ' ' - A-* J\J&amp; -lJ '—Li— 3 ' bJJ d &lt;&gt;2^ aI^'/ * ' 4 ^ tJ _!-' i CC-?^ —■A-Lr—' plj' J&gt; ( - - - LJ' &lt; i-LJ' 1 in his hends pearls whose value he Joes not know but there ere experts xrom whom he can ascer tain the worth of his pearls, -Perhaps there are experts in London fron whom we can know the real value of the additional area. In this matter we ask help and advice of the British Government. As far as we are concerned this matter is not a political one but entirely a commercial matter so we are asking the advice of the govern ment about a corairtereial matter. We cannot afford to pay expenses of experts in this matter, but perhaps if the circumstances are extdained to them they will be able to advise us on the value of the additional area. If the offer of the Company is not suitable to us we will offer the extra area to the An^lo Persian Oil Company or the Iraq Petroleum Company, but in truth we should prefer the additional area to be the lot of the Bahrain Petroleum Company as they have some claim to pre emption provided that they pay a suitable amount and accept\ tiU6 aH RF.810«NCY . i },■&gt; -Jo ^ f « ich'l Jonf idiintial . ' ___. SoSiet'iTiM- B.0.No:G/l85. ^ ^ POLITICAL AGKHCY. Bahrain,the 29th laay 1933. &gt;rr . , iflP y r' With reference to ray letter No:C/183 dated the 29th May 1933, T think that it might 'be well for you to know more exactly what has happened. I discussed the matter of Major Holmeg' letter of 17th May 1933 with the Adviser,who then had a number of conferences with His Excellency Shaikh Kamad,Shaikhs Muhammad and 'Abdullah (his brothers^ and Shaikh Salman (his son). As a result they produced a draft reply to my request for His Excellency's views,which was practically the letter which I have now forwarded to you, ?• i went out to Sakhir to see a horse race and so on with His Excellency Shaikh Hamad on the 27th May 1933 and he asked me if he might come and see me the next morning to consult me in the matter. He came with the Adviser,Shaikhs Muhammad and 'Abdullah and Shaikh Salman and brought the draft which I mentioned above. They went into the matter in detail and promised to send the letter as soon as possible. At this interview they only made some small alterations in wording on their own initiative. 3, T took the opportunity when Shaikh Muhammad read out the second paragraph in the letter in which His Excellency Shaikh Hamad says that 'we did not decide to give this Company the additional area,either at Sakhir or at any other place';to emphasise the danger which would have arisen had he done so, I explained that the British and L2. and American GDverruaentg were friendly,but that their Oil Companies were as if at war: if His? Excellency were to ^romipe snwethin^ to an American Oil Company,provided the British Government agreed,the Company would get its Govern ment to say to the British Government 'Only you stand 'between our Company and what the Shaikh has proraised them, and for the sake of our friendship please remove any opposition'. It would them be difficult for the British Government to obtain more favourable terms for His Excellency. I 'rubbed 1 this into Shaikh. 'Abdullah et a favourable moment by saying that when,for example,Shaikh Ahmad bin Jabir writes privately to Shaikh Hamad and asks him to be kind to a debtor (this is a well known local case!),it is then very difficult for His Excellency to refuse to be kind to the debtor. Shaikh 'Abdullah picked up the idea at once, 4, Major Holmes may make use of the agrument t be went to the Shaikh because there was no Political Agent here. That was not the case for arrangements had been made for carrying on my work,and he was definitely pre cluded from approaching the Shaikh under the terms of Article 'G w of the Schedule atta,ched to the Indenture between Shaikh Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifa*a and t,. l st^ru and General Syndicate Limited dated the 12th June 1950, 5. His Excellency Shaikh Hamad assured me tht he did not agree to eny proposals, or make any offei , he added that at times (as in buying a horse) Major Holmes would say one lakh and he would cay two lakhs,or v /hatevor it might be,in the way of discussion of the problem, T think, however, that we may safely accept the position that the Shaikh did not make or accept any definite proposal. (3) .rUQ rej trence to one -third and two-tiiirds of the Royalty is a little obscure, I gather, however,that His Excellency Shaikh Hanad was very anxious that kaj or Holmes should state in any proposals that the division of the Royalty should 'be one -third to him and two -thirds to his Government. Major Holmes, quite correctly, said that was not a matter which concerned him. Shaikh Hamad may have had various reasons for his insistence on this point - 'but personally I welcome this definite pronouncement which was made, I understp .nd, or his own volition (save perhaps that the seed sown in the conversation reported in my A L x ^Jretter No:C/90 dated the 4th March 1933 may have 'borne !on»'ble Lieut-Colonel T .C .W.Powle, C .B.l., Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire,i * 11 COH1IBE123AL. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUSHI'RE, the 12th June, 1933. No.36 of 1933. SUBJECT ; Bahrain Petroleum Company, Sir, 1/1% In continuation of My letter Ho*33, dated the 2nd June 1933, I haTe the honour to enclose a copy of a letter, hfi Ho• C/182, dated the 29th May 1933, from the Political Agent, i Bahrain# The letter coTers two main points: Major Holmes* action in the matter of the offer of the Company, and the merits of the offer itself. 2. Reference paragraphs 3 and 4 of Colonel loch's letter. Major Holmes' conduct in the matter can he criticised on the following points: (a) His infringement of Condition 'C* of the Schedule attached to t e indenture between Shaikh Hamad 'bin Isa A1 Khalifah and the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited dated the 12th June 1930 in approaching and endeavouring to negotiate direct with His Excellency Shaikh Hamad. (h) His statement that the offer contained in his letter of 17th May to the Political Agent came from the Shaikh (paragraph 4 of the said letter) which His Excellency flatly denies. (c) His statement that the Shaikh agreed to certain proposals (paragraph (l) of the letter). His Excellency denies that he agreed to any proposals at all* (d) His statement with regard to certain particular matters: (l) inclusion of Territorial Waters (paragraph (l) of the letter), and (2) the provision that the loan - or advance - mentioned/ His Majesty*s Secretary of State for the Colonies, The Colonial Office, _L__o ^njij^ns.(1^4j -s- mentioned in paragraph 2 of the letter should tie dependent on the world market for oil. His Sxcellency states that neither (l) nor (2) were mentioned to him at all. »ven allowing for a certain anount of- genuine misunderstanding in the course of conversa tion - especially with an Arah Shaikh, I do not see how the differences between Major Holmes' and the Shaikh's account of their discussions can he reconciled. Major Holmes' statement (h) is ahsurd on the face of it. Shaikh Hamad is, if course, quite incapable of drawing up such a complicated document. Major Holmes' object in stating that the offer came from the Shaikh is, of course, obvious. He wishes to represent the Shaikh of Bahrain as having made an offer to his Company, and therefore to put His Majesty's Govern ment - if they should object to any features of this offer - in the awkward position of interfering between the Uiaikh and what the latter thinks to he for his own benefit and that of his State. 3. Nor are Major Holmes * iBis-statement s confined to the matter of Bahrain Oil. In the matter of Kuwait Oil he has only recently made a statement which His T xce lency Shaikh Ahmad bluntly stigmatised as a lie, (vide my des- , j V ; . ! , , ; ' , patch Ho.34, dated the 8th June 1933, copy to Government of India under Bushire Printed letter Ko.631-S o^ same date). 4. Major Holmes' unfitness for the post of Chief Local 'Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company has heen the subject of some correspondence of late, chiefly on account of his long absences from Bahrain, and as Colonel loch points out in paragraph 4 of his letter Major Holmes is again absent. In the present instance Colonel Loch sugge st s/u^t) i' 0 &gt;3- auggests that Major HolmeB 'be called upon for an explanation for his action under (a) - (d) mentioned a'bove. I doubt whether much practical good would result from a request for this explanation infomed I suggest rather that the Company be , ^y'-. ' \ j • U (1) that Major Holmes is absent from Bahrain for long periods, and that he is again absent now when a discussion of the Company's offer may be essential at any moment; (2) that he infringed Condition'C 11 as explained in (a) above. The fact that Colonel Loch was absent in Bahrain at the time (acting for me at Bushire) was of course no excuse# The Indian Assistant in the Political office had been left in charge, and Major Holmes could have approached him, or conversely have sent his proposal to Colonel Loch at Bushire; (3) that in his letter of 17th May to the Political Agent Major Holmes made various statements as to his discussions with the 3haikh which the latter denies*; (4) that in these circumstances from our point of view, and doubtless also from that of the Company, it is no longer desirable that *ajor Holmes should continue to hold the post of Chief Local Representative and that somebody else must be appointed# Colonel Loch - with whom I had the opportunity of discussing the question - would be quite willing that Mr» Skinner, the Company's fields Manager at Bahrain,/ i II / ■ o 5. -4- Bahraln, should occupy this post, and from what I have seen of Skinner I concur in this sugges tion. With regard to the merits of the offer itself. A comparison between the offer and what the Shaikh and the Bahrain Government would receive if they (as they have the right to do) forced the Company to take out the Fining Lease as from 'Hecemher 1933, ^ives the following results. A. Payments hv Company if Mining Lease ie. t aken out in Dec e mber 1935 . (l) On grant of Mining Lease, under Article III (s) On each anniversary (Article III) until Company declares oil in commercially exploitable quantities, for which, under Article X, they have 5 years (3) Thereafter, annually, minimum Royalty (Article IX) .. •• •• •• B. Payments under terms of offer. (l) On signature of deed. To Shaikh, forthwith 40,000 fo) « w « « ♦♦ M in 20 monthly instalments 60,000 200 f 000 20,000 20,000 60,000 (3) ^ State, (4) On grant of Mining Lease, J^O months later, twice the payments shown at A above, i.e. On grant of fining Lease • • • • Annually until Company declares oil in commercially exploitable quantities .. •• •• •* Thereafter, annually &gt; *• vide paragraph l(d) of j-ajor Holmes letter.f !&lt;; &gt; ^ -5- Re. (5) 20 months after signature of deed, possibly (dependent on condition of world market for oil) a loan to State in 20 monthly instalments against future Royalties. .. .. 200,000 Notes: 1* Reference B (4), Similar sums are offered for the additional area as for the area as laid down in the present Concession. 2. Under the terms of the offer(paragra]Ai 1(d) of Major Holmes * letter) Mining Lease will ccwmence 20 months after agreement has 'been signed. 3. 'i'he proviso that the loan to the Bahrain Government from the Company will depend on the ep( state of world market for oil, etc. Iparagraph 2 of Major Holmes' letter) lessens the attractiveness of the terms of the offer. $ • 6« It will he seen, therefore, that B is probably considerably more profitable to the Shaikh's private purse, I and to the Treasury of the Bahrain Government, than A. I say 'probably', since if under A the Company produced a large output of oil, the royalties to the Shaikh might make up more than payments under On the other hand, if it suited the Company, owing to difficulties in marketing their oil, to produce as little as possible, it would be very difficult I imagine to force them to produce more, and under the Mining Lease they could go on producing a minimum of oil and paying the minimum annual rental of Rs»10 f 000 /-(vidc Article III of the Mining Lease) fora period of 5 years (Article IX of the Mining Lease)# 7, llie reason why the Company are prepared to make offer B is presumably that they foresee great difficul ies in marketing their oil. That they are influenced by some powerful/powerful motive is evident from the lucrative nature of the offer# Bo*e time ago (vide Major Holmes' letter dated the 4th April 1933, enclosed with my despatch No. 26, dated the 17th April 1933) in return for the two concessions now asked for they offered the loan only . 8» 'Hie two concessions asked for hy the Company from the Bahrain Government in return for their offer are: (1) An extension of the Prospecting period 'by 20 months. (2) An extension of the Mining Lease area to cover the whole of Bahrain territory. 9» With regard to (l). Subject to the opinion of His Majesty 's Government I see no particular objection in view of the substantial financial benefits contained in the Company 's offer. It may be possible as suggested by Colonel Loch (paragraph 6 of his letter) to get still better terms from them. 10. Concession (2), however, raises various serious and important issues. ^he pros and cons of conceding the whole territory to the Company were discussed at the Inter departmental conference held at the Colonial Office on ^he 26th April 1933. One difficulty lies in the fact that the territory of the Bahrain State is not definitely known (vide paragraph 7 of Colonel Loch's letter^* I will endeavour in conjunction with Colonel Loch to clear this poin -1 ' up. ll # In considering the whole question of the Bahrain 'etroleum/Petroleuffi Company, the possibility should not he lost sight of that they do not intend to exploit the oil field them selves, provided they can sell the Concession at a profit to themselves to some other Company. I am sending copy of this despatch to the Government of India* I have the honour to he, Sir Tour most ohedient humble servant Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian GulfCONFIDENTIAL. No. 645-!? of 1933. C o The Hon bio tli© Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to The foreign Secretary to the Oovernraent of I tk 1 la, Simla, com- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dccu- ment {$/// .# % /' British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSH1RE. Dated. 12th « f unct 1933» Reference to previous correspondence : HO.696-^ of JTJH^ 1935, ^ js \ t-M . Description of Enclosure. * \ i Name and Date, Subject. Bu«hire despatch Ho.36, dated the ISth »Tiine 19;53 # to Hin Majeat^'s Secretary of ^tpte for the Colonlea. Bahrain Petroleum Corapany. Copy, with copy of encl cowplinen^s to the ''oli^i inforraat osure, forwarded with cal Agent e Bahrain, for ion.f 5 ■''. UOP v SENT TO. P.Z.2717/33. ffjrtt V 'h ■JH jjNOLQ-31'i^ji. Hi CCLCNLiL QPi^I CCVL^TTS^ NO, 18135/33 D.lTED IQth ^ 1 9^^. TiiE BiiHHEIN F ^ TAOL a VL X LFiiMY LlilTED, 19, IVDORGATJ:, BUSH IRE RE8IDSNCY *$i A /O?^ tL ( OONFIIiEViiAL WW LON DON, 2. 13th iipril 1933. Sir, ii. certain aRiount of confusion is 'being caused, 'by the fact that the name of this Company differs in its spelling from the officially accepted, spelling 'Bahrein'. The Company thinks it might a,voia such confusion by passing the necessary Resolutions to change the name, such change being, in effect, merely a change in spelling so that the Company's name would be 'Bahrain' instead of as at present 'Bahrein'. I am to ask you if such a change would, be desirable from the point of view of His Majesty's Government. If the answer is in the affirmative, and you will let me know, the Company will then consider whether it is a practicable matter for it to jmke the change. i have, etc. (3d.) H.R. Ballantyne. Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, 3. ;v • 1. ntion: J.xil .w. Flood, Esq.ft&gt; s% . Q BUsn^T^^^Wlng Street. fin Oi ' n /(£&gt;( CO'iFltlE'iTMl iEOMM. 2 May, 1933, (/ith reference to the Acting Political Residents . • despatch, No. 27 of the E8th of April, regarding the Bahrein oil concession, I have the honour to transmit to you a copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Bahrein Petroleum Company on the subject of their applica tion for an extension of their prospecting licence. Z. I take this opportunity to enclose a copy of .$0^^92)3. correspondence with the Treasury Solicitor regarding the interpretation of Article IV of the Company's Concession Agreement. This correspondence was initiated in accordance with the decision recorded in paragraph 17 of the record of the meeting held at the Colonial Office on the 3rd of May. A further communication will be addressed to you when the Company have furnished the further information asked for, and when the advice tendered by the Treasury Solicitor has been considered in consultation with the other interested departments of His Majesty 1 s Government. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. I i IE HONOURABLE THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF.(!W 35/11 /33. Downing Street, ( xj^c^e) ^ — '* L ^ V J■ O - f J /$ , Jl ■./%. A# . /0)9 — Cifyy^t U (bd** CyJoJ. A' I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Gunliffe- Lister to request you to be good enough to furnish him with your advice upon the following matter. 2. On the P.nd Jecember,19?/), the Sheikh of Bahrein granted an oil concession to the Eastern and G-eneral Syndicate/Limited. On the 12th June,1930, the Sheikh gave his assent to the transfer by the Easternfand G-eneral Syndicate to the Fahrein Petroleum Company of all the rights of the former Oompany under the aforementioned concession. This transfer took place on the 1st August, 1930. 3. Certain Articles in the original Concession Agreement and the First Schedule thereto and certain Articles of the Agreement of the 12th June,1930,provide for the grant of an exploration licence and subsequently of a prospecting licence and lay down the conditions under which these licencesmay be extended. f 4. By a Supplementary Agreement dated the 28th November,1931, the Sheikh granted a prospecting licence from the 2nd Jecember, 1930, to the 2nd Decemoer,.! ■ . , ruid by a subsequent Supplementary Agreement dated 13th December,1932, the Sheikh agreed to extend the prospecting licence for a oeriod of one year up to and including the End December,1933. On the 4th April,1933, the Bahrein '^etroleum • Company applied under Article IV of the original Concession Agreement fHSASU® SOLI 01 TOR.Agreement for a further extension of the prospecting licence up to the 2nd December,1934. A copy of the letter from the Company to the British Political Accent at Bahrein is enclosed, and it will be observed that the Company have so worded their letter as to imply that they are entitled to this further extension. 6. In forwarding a copy of this letter to the Political Resident in the D ersian Gulf, the Political Aprent at Bahrein observed that he did not consider that the Company could be held to be entitled to an extension of the prospecting licence, but that the question of any further extension must be'treated on its merits. He has ; subsequently reported that the Bahrein Government are not disposed to grant a further extension of the prospecting licence for one year without a mid sro quo as itwould result in postponement of increasedpayment of Rupees 30,000 which would become due when the Company enter on the mining lease; that they regard tne Ooncession as giving them the right to grant or refuse such an extension; but that the interpretation of Article IV of the Agreement of the 'nd December 1935 is not quite free from doubt, and that if they are informed by His Majesty's Government that it is not within their power to withhold the extension, they will be reluctantly compelled to assent, but that if His Majesty's Government agree that their interpretation is correct, they would be prepared to promise the extension on certain conditions. 7, At a recent interview at the Colonial Office a representative of the Bahrein Petroleum Company stated that in his opinion the Company were entitled to a . further year's extension; that it was customary in concessions&gt; f f ooncesoions Ox onis kind to allow the maximum extension of the prospecting licence (i.e. in this case two years from the 2nd ■)eceiiioer,1932) it it could be shown that the extension was necessary; that in the present instance he felt that the loinoany had made out a clear case for the necessity; he had himself just made a survey of the whole position in Bahrein and he was satisfied that further test drillinp v/as reouired before the Company could decide either the depth or the extent of the area for which they should seek a mining lease. 8. There is no reason to think that Article VIII of the second Schedule to the Agreement of the End December 1925 could be invoked. The question at issue therefore depends upon the interpretation of Article IV of that Agreement. 9. Sir Philip Ounliffe-Lister would be glad to have your observations generally on this matter; and in particular I am to request'that you will be good enough to advise whether, assuming that the Company can sho?/ that a further extension of the prospecting licence for one year is justified, it is open to the Sheikh of Bahrein to refuse such extension or to make conditions upon which the extension would be granted. 10. A set of the relevant papers is enclosed. I am etc., (Sd) 0.G.R.Williams.M 17486 Treasury Solicitor, 18th May,1933. Sir, I have to acknowledge the receipt of Mr.Williams 1 letter (1813 5/11/33) of the 11th instant on the question whether the Bahrein Petroleum Company are entitled to demand an extension of their prospecting licence under the Agreement entered into on the 2nd December,1925 between the Sheikh of Bahrein and the Company's predecessors in title, The Eastern and General Syndicate Ltd. which this Agreement provides may be granted either, under Article IV of the Agreement or under Article VIII of the second Schedule thereto^ It is, as I understand, not alleged by the Company that they have been prevented by causes beyond their control from carrying out the work of prospecting,and consequently it is not necessary to consider the effect of Article VIII of the second Schedule, The question therefore falls to be determined under Article IV of the Agreement itself,which provides that 'the prospecting licence..may be extended for a further period of two years on the Company showing to the satisfac tion of the Sheikh, acting on the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,that such extension is justified'. I assume that the condition precedent to an extension prescribed by the proviso to this Article has been fulfilled and that no question therefore arises with regard to it. English law is to apply to the solution of any disputes which may arise between the parties to it, but I can, of An extension of the prospecting licence for The Agreement does not expressly provide that course,/ course, only advise on the matter on the assumption that the rights of the parties are governed 'by principles of that law. On this 'basis it is clear that where the rights one party to a contract are expressly declared in the contract to depend on something 'being done to the satisfaction of the other or on that person being satisfied as to a certain state of affairs, the second party is not entitled to act in an arbitrary or capricious manner, or to declare himself as not satisfied by a set of circumstances which any reasonable man would regard as sat is fact ory # He must take into consideration all the facts of the case and form an honest conclusion on the matter; but provided he does so no Court will seeii to suds citute its ov '/n standard of satisfaction for that which the parties have, by the express terms of their contract,agreed to accept. In the present case, therefore, provided that the Sheikh acting on the advice of the Political Resident, fairly taA .es into consideration all the circumstances urged by the Company in support of their application, he is entitled to form his own conclusion whether those circumstances are such as to justify the extension for which the Company ask* It will appear from what I have said that in my opinion the ultimate answer to the question put in Mr,Williams letter is not primarily one of law, and that unless the Company are in the event able to show an unreasonable course of conduct on the part of the Sheikh they would have no remedy against the Sheikh if he were to come to the conclusion that the circumstances did not justify an extension of the prospecting licence* Subject however, to the reservation that the ultimate decision is for the Sheikh acting on the advice of the PoliticalPolitical Resident, the folicwing considerations seem to me to be relevant* Tne reasons put forward by the Company in support of their application for an extension are, as I gather, to be found in their letter of the 4th April 1933 addressed to the Political Agent. In this letter the Company point out that they have in commission powerful and modern drilling plant and are proposing to add, or have added, a second plant of the same character. They further state that the Company is considerably ahead of the drilling programme prescribed by the second Schedule to the Agreement, I may perhaps observe that these considerations appear to me to be directed primarily to the condition precedent to an extension prescribed by Article IV, which I have already assumed to have been satisfied; if this be so they can hardly be taken into consideration for the purpose deciding the further question whetner the circumstances justify an extension of the Licence. The Company then observe that the prospecting work already done stresses the necessity for much additional information before the true value,extent and location of the oil bearing formation can be ascertained, and they state that to secure this information an extensive drilling campaign over a considerable area is necessary and that this work must oe done 'oefore the Company can be in a position to develop the concession to the utmost advantage of all interested. The circumstance, therefore, on which the Company appear to rely in support of their demand for an extension is that they have not so far been able to obtain as much information as they w ould desir e to have respecting the territory in question before selecting particular areas for the purposes of the mining lease which they are entitledentitled to demand under Article V, I am not, of course, acquainted witli the territory in question, nor with, the difficulties which may have 'been encounted by the Company in the cou-use of tueir operations, and it is therefore with some diffiaeiiCe that I express any opinion on this contention, but so far as I can appreciate the matter it does not appear to me to be a very conclusive one. The effect of granting a further extension of the prospecting licence would be to postpone the receipt by the Sheikh of tne royalties for which a mining lease would provide, and if the Sheikh should come to the conclusion that a further postponement of these payments is not justified in all the circumstances, bearing in mind the time which the Company have I already had for their preliminary work, I do not think such a conclusion could be challenged. On the other hand I do not think that the Sheikh is entitled to demand any payment from the Company as a condition of granting the extension, or, in purporting to act under the contract, to impose any condition which would substantially increase the burdens assumed by the Company there under; in coming to a decision on the matter he can, in my opinion, only take into account such considerations as are expressly or by necessary implication envisaged by the terms of the contract itself. There is, of course, nothing to prevent the parties from « w.. |||||| , || | ■-. m irn nr wr. » if *' 'V™** making by mutual consent an entirely new agreement in susbstitution !for the existing one, and in negotiating any new agreement the Sheikh would be free to suggest such conditions whether of a financial character or otherwise as he might think appropriate. I am etc., (Sgd) M. Gwyer. folder Secretary of State, Colonial Office, downing Street,S.W.I. GSK/DW^ ! ■\yU jp \\\b U 18135/33 , ^olonicl Of rice, ^gU8HiffF Pf€»&lt;€&gt;ff HeY? 3wni ^ Street, 3 # ;/.l. ^-S ' i.L;;y, 1935, OONHCEHTIAL fcmm We are seeing you by tiais mail an official despatch regarding the Bahrein oil concession, from v/hich you will sea that there has beon a development li; tiie position since the meeting held on the 3rd May. At recent interview which I had with Ballantyne and Lomloardi, the latter asked whether there was any further information required from the Company as to how they had fulfilled the requirements 01 Article IV, After consultation with the Petroleum Department, we have taken the opportunity to ask the Company for the further particulars shown in the first enclosure to our official despatch. We must therefore now await their reply 'before taking any further action. i (x iEMT-COLOlSL T.C. C.B.EBritish ■Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUSHIKB, the 15th June, 1933. Ho.58 of 1933 fc Cs f !S Sir With reference to paragraph 6 of Colonial Office letter Ho.18135/11/33, dated the 11th May 1933, to the Treasury Solicitor, received under cover of your despatch Persian Gulf Confidential, dated the S5th May 1933, I haw the honour to point out that/the increased payment of Rb .30,000/- will become due not when the Company enters on the Mining Lease hut (under Article IX thereof) when it has declared that oil has heen found in commercially exploit able quantities, to make which declaration the Company has (under Article X) a limit of five years. I have Indicated this in paragratfi 5 A (2) of my despatch Jo. 36, dated the 12th June 1933. I am sending copy of this despatch to the I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient, humhle servan t, Lieut,-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gull His Majesty'' Secretary ofCONFIDENTIAL. No iN0 * 665-B of 1933. i i / io The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to ^he foreign Secretary to the rrovernment of India, Biala. 3, ec 1 bas tlio liononr to trBiisnjit to bim fi copy of tli© nndcrniGntionGd docu -i ment British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. c k'H&amp; Dated.., 15th June, 1933, Reference to previous correspondence: Bush ire despatch No.38, dated the 15th June 1933, to His Majesty's Secretary of 3tate for the Colonies, London. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. BAJTUIH OIL CQfTCISSHIOH. Subject.p 7.2861/55. j &gt; ■ i 0 Enclosure m covering slip from Mr. Starling, Petroleum Department. Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, Westminster dated 16th May, 1933. gy -ipc ?■ p 'j r 21. Part 3. 117^0 ih/^ I ^ 16th May, 1S33. My dear Slaxter, ^j^. r / Many thanks for your letter of May 9th, enclosing note of a talk with Lccioardi and Ballantyne. In view of the conclusions reached at the last interdepartmental meeting neld at the Colonial Office, I agree that we need not press the Company further at the moment as regards the employment of British drillers, especially as they have arranged to send out to Bahrein two young British engineers to be trained and assist locally in the work. At a suitable opportunity we might make it clear that we shall expect them to take other British personnel as the work grows, end that we do not accept their contention that there are not competent British drillers available. With regard to detailsjof the work carried out by the Company, we really know very little of what they have done. . In a letter frcsn the Fields Manager, dated January 24th, voijC n a 1933, to the Financial Adviser to the Bahrein Government, the former said that well Ho. 2 on a short production test made 64-g- tons of oil in 7 hours and that it appeared to be better than No.l. Although there is no specific provision in the Agreement of 1925 with the Eastern and General Syndicate • covering this point, it is usual for concessiona,ires to supply information and you will rememoer that in Slood's letter to Ba.llantyne of October 26th, 1932, it was stated ^^*6 that we would be prepared to reconsider the question of granting/ &amp;.W .Blaxter, Esq., Colonial Office, //&lt;?/• \ Downing Street, S.W.I. ( ' J(w granting an extension of the prospecting licence beyond December 2nd, 1933, on condition that the Company furnished detailed information of the progress made and of the Company* s immediate drilling programme. This they hp.Ye not ^£3. done. In Holmes* letter of April 4th, 1933, in which he made application for an extension of the prospecting licence, he merely said generally, that the Company had in canmission a modern and powerful deep-coring drilling plant which had been in constant operation since October, 1931, and that they had now pxlded a second drilling machine of the same character, and that further extensive drilling was necessary. As Lanbardi asked to be informed in regard to additional information we required, I think we should ask for a report covering the following points:- (1) Geological work carried out and areas examined. (2) Drilling . Particul a rs of wells drilled. (3) Personnel . Description and nationality. (4) Buildings, tankage, pipelines , etc. erected or laid. A report on these lines would enaole us to judge how the Company are carrying out their wors, and give us a better idea of the probaole value of the concession, ano they might, I suggest, be asked to supply a similar report, bringing previous reports up to date, ever^ six montiis on the 31st December and the 30th June. Such a report would be on the lines of those furnished by the Iraq Petroleum Company to the Iraq Government. There are also other precedents of which particulars can be furnished to you if necessary. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) F.C.Starling. under Bushire P.L. Copy forwarded to P.A Bahrain No. 680-S, dated 17.6.33 (a) Location of wells (indicated on map). (b) Date of commencement and completion. (c) Depth reached to date. (d) Occurrences of oil met with and depth. (e) Result of production tests, if any. (f) New locations selected or projected.pjr.. 3008/33 18136/33, r 3S / ^ QQpV SE.N ) 1Q. / u / 4 • ■ - 7 f , ) • - ; ?• f &gt;Y.G0L01IAL OFFICE, DOWHIHG STREET, S.W.I. / -J\ 20th M ay, 1953. Benr Walton, In connection with the Bahrain oil conces«1 on, we have been going carefully into the question of Major Holmes 1 residence in Bahrein, in the light of the recent discussions, ^nd Parkinson has asked me to let you know our views. These are, briefly, that t^e esse agsinst Major Holmes on specific points is not s. very strong one, and that on general grounds it would probably be better to let matters rest where they are for the present. As you know, the Company hold that all that is required of them under Condition C is that their local representative should be on the spot when there is any business to be transacted. While it seems clear thr^t this contention is contrary to the wording of Condition C, the fact remains th^t we can only point to one specific instance of his absence at a material time, namely, his departure for Jedda after submitting the Company's applicrtion for ^n extension of their prospecting licence, snd it is not clear, even in this case, that his presence has, in fact, been necessary. It mupt not, however, be assumed fras the above that we have any strong desire to maintain Major Holmes in his capacity of local representative. This is not the case, but we feel that it might be advisable not to bring this ofuestion to a head and risk a certain amount of friction, at a. time when there are other more important things for discussion with the Company. C.talton, Jsq., C.B., M.C. ( /, &lt;2 C In(iiT) \ tj&gt; 2. Lb We should therefore be to know whether you agree with us that (unless something occurs meanwhile which necessitates bringing this up) the matter might be all ©wed to rest until the other questions, viz. extension of the prospecting licence and amendment of the mining lease, have been got out of the way. I an sending a similar letter to Bendel, Starling and Moore. Yours sincerely, (Fgd) K.W.Blaxter. CoBy forwarded to P.A., Bahrain, under Bushire P.L. No. 630-3, dated 17.6.33. .Telegram Jrom To No. 218 Dated 21st received 22nd June 1955. E 27 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political He si dent, shire. I have received letter dated June 21st from Sampson on 'behalf of Anglo-Persian Oil Company saying that in regard to territories of Bahrain which are not yet allocated for oil development company would like to come to an arrangement with Shaikh 'wherehy company shall have sole right over a period for negoti- -ating for an agreement for development of such areas'*. Period was not specified. 2. Shaikh came to see me on June 21st and said that he had 'been approached informally and had replied that he must consult Political Agent. He asked for the advice of Government. 1 showed him ahove mentioned letter which l had just received and he asked me to inform you of contents 'by telegram. iie asked what period was specified, evidently wondering if he was 'being rushed. He spoke again of enormity of holmes in misrepresenting him hut is more or less indifferent whose money it is as long as he gets money from some company. May I enquire views of Bahrain Govern- -ment on this proposal officially just as has 'been done in the case of proposals of Bahrain Petroleum Company ? I can hardly delay...r« z. delay doing so withouti incurring reproach from 'both sides. Bahrain Government would hardly 'be alDle to give u sole right' as Holmes proposals are already 'being considered,'but communicating this letter would put them in official touch with Anglo- -Persian Oil Oompany and clear the way for 'bargaining It might also 'be useful fuom other point of view. Political.Telegram From lUtl Political Resident, -Bushire. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, To Copy 'by post foreign Secretary to the G-overnment of India, Simla. No 15 Bated 22nd June 19SS. Political Agent, ^ahrain, wires that Sampson has addressed him letter on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company that in regard to territor- -ies of Bahrain which are not yet allocated for oil developement y company would like to come to an arrange- -ment with Shaikh H wherehy Company shall have sole right over a period for negotiati^tgfor an agreement for development of such areas' 1 . Period was not specified. 2. Shaikh who was approached informally replied that he must consult Political 4gent and now asks for advice of C-overnment. S. Political Agent,, suggests that he should enquire views of Bahrain Government officially on Anglo- *Persian Oil Company s proposal. I concur as this will put Company into official touch with Bahrain G-overnment and details such as period will then 'be elucidated, when proposal can he considered on its merits. 4 # It seems to me there are ohvious advantages in having second competitor, especially British, in the field. / .Resident.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 702-s of 19S3 The Hon'ble the Political Resident iu the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to com- 1. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of india. Simla. J The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dccu- ment (^. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Datea -22a'd-3rune'l'S'gS' Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Telegram No. 15, dated 22ncl June 1933, from the Political -cLesident, Bushire, to the Secretary of otate for the Colonies, London. Anglo-Persian Oil Company's interest in Bahrain oil resources.' i % .A P.Z.3142/33. 4 1? DAl'aD 29 th k/.Y me Bahrein Petroleum Company Liplteci BUtHIW REWOINCy 1 hi '• PiU... 19, Moorgate, London, ..C.2. mmiHTIAL IIEQOSM i|A4 A 12th May 1933. .- .iihii,„i ■ ti A, .■■■• ^ ,4^ Dear Mr. Biazter, v ^ &lt; h* 4 I have to acknowledge the receipt of your letter (18135/33 Ft. II) of the 10th instant in which you draw my attention to the word ^as* before the words •the original Agreement tt in the last line but two of the ■Agreement of the 13th Dacemher last, which should be •in'. I noticedthis little mistake at the tinie, but t&amp;ou^ht it so obvious that I left it, as 1 did not like to suggest that the document having once been signed should be altered. I am passing your letter on to San Francisco. They may take an objection to altering: if so, it would only be on the basis that a document once si^ed must remain unaltered or altered in a formal, legal method. Obviously, the correct word is 'in® or 'of H . The Arabic translation might be correct. It looks like a printer 's error. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) H.R. Ballantyne Blaxter, Esq., lonial Office, Downing Jtreet, 3.W. 1. ( / iC Copy sent ot Bahrain under Bushirel P.L.No. 707-3 of 23rd June 1933. Ja f \ ( Telegram ^ Tom Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. No. 2ZZ Dated 25rd received 24th June 1933 My telegram of 21st June. 1 am sending 'by next mail Holmes* letter of June 15th which maintains, indeed elaborates fiction of Shaikh's offer and contains Company's countei offer. 2. Chief modification is that Company consider that the twenty monthly payments to Bahrain t ih '7 G -overnment, (h) of Holmes* letter of May 17th, should 'be recovered from royalties like paragraph No 2 of /IS that letter. 3. Holmes* letter must 'be communicated to Bahrain Government hut I would suggest that I should he permitted at the same time, hut in a separate letter, to communicate to Bahrain Government request of Anglo- -Persian Oil Company. 4. On June 22nd, just before I received Holmes' letter Skinner came to see me saying that he appreciated that Holmes was proper channel of communis -cation hut that he was much disturbed hy activities of Haji Williamson, which he felt unfair as he was debarred from countering them. I listened...listened and emphasised absence of Chief Local representative out was placed in a very awkward and unpleasant position, r5# 1 feel that as contm5lling Shaikh s oil deals it is incunil^ent on usj in order to avoid ctiarge of lack of good faith (a) to communicate 'both above matters to Shaikh without d^lay and ('b) inform -Bahrain Petroleum Company (who suspect even if they do not know for certain, what is going on) at the same time on Shaikh's 'behalf, that communioation has heen received from another oil interest expressing wish to negotiate for remaining territory after Bahrain Petroleum Company have chosen their 100,000 acres. I gather indirectly that while Holmes' local knowledge is valued arrangements for Skinner to 'be local representative would 'be welcomed and Skinner himself would 'be happier. 6. iour letter of June l£th, Uo 36, if Holmes ceases to 'be Chief Local Representative I would suggest vise to return to Bahrain, 'be refused ( it would he desirable to specially warn Baghdad, lasrah and Kuwait.) PoliticalTelegram Prom To H. irolitical Besident, ■ti'usM.re. secretary of State for the Colonies, London* Copy Dy post Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. No. 16 Dated 26th June 19S5. V ^ My telegram No. 15 of 22nd June. Political Agent, Bahrain, wires that he has received a letter from Eoimes dated June 15th which elaborates fiction of Shaikh's 'offer* and con- -tains Company's 'counter offer* chief modification in which is that Company consider that twenty monthly payments to Bahrain Government, (h) of Holmes' letter ^ ! ^ of May IVth^ should 'be recovered from royalties as in paragraph 2 of that letter, j, JI 2. Political Agent suggests that this letter he communicated to -Bahrain Government simul- -taneously with Anglo Persian Oil Company letter^para- -graph 3 of my ahove quoted telegram. I concur# 3* Political Agent also suggests that Bahrain Petroleum Company^who already suspect Anglo- -Persian Oil Company activity, should 'be informed 'by us on 'behalf of Shaikh, of Anglo-Persian Oil Company i proposal,in general terms,as coming from •another oil interest -sian Oil Company and I suggest that Bahrain Petroleum Company he informed accordingly, Anglo-Persian Oil Company Headquarters, London, 'being informed first. Sent under P.L.No. 721-S fo 26/6/33 to Governmentjtf Only other oil interest is Anglo-Per-% iV CONFIDENTIAL. No. 721-S of 1933 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his o pliments to !• The iToreign Secretary to the GroverTinient of India. Simla. S' ,1 *; ^ '.7 \ SV,^ ..o £. The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the imdermenlioned docu ment (9^. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated.. £6 fcU. .ImQ., Reference to previous correspondence : To I. anq g. Bushire P.L.No. 702-S dated 22nd June 1933. Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Political Besident's tele- -gram No. 16, dated 26th. June 1933, to the Colonial Office, London. Subject. Bahrain Oil and Anglo-Persian Oil 0o.*s interest. \86/2. Telegram H S7. l?Tom Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, Buehire. No. ^30. Dated and received 26th June 1933, IMPORTAIT? . Anglo-^ersian Oil Company Limited inform me Chisholm arriving by air June S9th, I propose to take action tomorrow Tune 27tli as in paragraph 5 of my telegram 22?. of une 23rd, otherwise Anglu-^ersian Oil Company Limited will reproach us for delaying their request and Bahrain Petroleum Company for allowing Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited to intrigue. If I am not to take action deprecate Chisholm's visi t. Telegram P.. £?'?. ?rom Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bali rain, No. 499. Dated the 27th June 1933. IMPORTAHT. . — Your telegram 230. Delay of fev/ days should not make any practical difference. Please await His Majesty's Government's instruo. tions before taking action.'HELEGRjat ?r03! No. 17, Dated the 27th June 19:33. tf In view of fact that CFIISHOBc of Anglo- ^arsian Oil Company Limited arrives Bahrain S9th June Political Agent Bahrain, in order to avoid iraputation^from Bahrein T?etroieum Company that he is holding up their offer in order to favour Anglo-'Persian Oil Company Limited, is anxious to make to Bahrain Crovernment before Chisholm's arrival commurji cat ions referred to in paragraphs 2 and 3 of ray telegram -'o»16 of 26th June* I concur.CONFIDENTIAL No, 725-P of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to 1» ^orei^rt Secretary to the ^overnnent of India, Binla. The Political Afrenl:. Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the nndermenlioned dccu- ment British Eesidency and Oonsulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated,.., SfJf tJa. June,. 19,33.*.. lieference to previous correspondence: y To (l). Bushire tinted letter Ho.721-B of S6th June 1933. To (S). Bahrain telefrram Ho.SSO of ??6th Jvine 1933. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Political Resident's telegran Ho.17 of S7th June 1933 to His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. Subject. Bahrain Oil.$35/33. Ft. II. Downing Street luth May,1933. i)ea r Mr. B al 1 anty n a, A small error has been discovered in the Supplementary Agreement between the Sheikh of Bahrein and the Bahrein Petroleum Company of the 13th December, 1932. In the last line but two, the word ^as'* before the words f, the original Agreement 11 should be n in n . When we noticed this small mistake, we wrote to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and he has now informed us that the copies in the possession of the Bahrein Government the Political Agent and the local Representative of the Bahrein Petroleum Company have been amended. Steps are being taken to amend the copies in the possession of His Majesty 1 s Government and we should be grateful if y ou w oul d have y our co py, ore opi e s, amende d al so. Yours sincerely, (Sd) K.W.Blaxter. (Co'ov forwarded to Bahrrtin under r .L.No. 762-S of ZV/e/ZZ). Kef. our P.L.TTO. of 23/6/33) •1&amp;LLAHTYN3, ESQ.m gulf , idential , I- rv % v* Ct C\~'- \ is ' | f S ■' ^ k&gt; I Downing Street, 5NCY. f Jane, 1933. Lid *• - -t Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Confidential despatch No. 23 of the 24th of March regarding the dispute which has arisen between the Bahrain Petroleum Company and the Bahrain Government as to exemption from customs duty on a consignment of furniture fittings and materials for use 'in furnishing the Company^ house and offices situated in Manama'. 2, In accordance with your suggestion, the records of this Department have been examined, but no information can be found as to what the intentions of the parties concerned were at the time when the concession was being negotiated, and I feel some difficulty in taking the matter up with the Company in London until I am in possession of more detailed information as to the contents of the shipment in question, and as to the purposes for which it is proposed to use the various articles. 5. I shall be glad if you will obtain and forward this information, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. honourable 3 political RSSIDENT the persian GULF. /. r. )CONFIDENTIAL. No * 763-S of 1953. . i .i.' \ The Hon'ble tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the nndennenlioned docu- with a request that he will obtain and forward the inforrsation required by the Colonial Office. • x V \ British Residency , &lt;&lt;»\\ and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire B»florsei!en1l: jf 24th March 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Colonial Office despatch '^eraian Oulf Confidential of 8th June 1933. Custoras exemption under the Bahrain Oil Concession.(2) No;C/223-10/l Confidential Political Agency, Bahrain,the 24th June 1933 Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch,I,A*, Political Agents Bahrain• To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. Sir In continuation of my telegram No:C/218 dated the 21st June 1933,1 have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter dated the 21st June 1933 from Mr•A.C .Sampson,on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited. 2. The conversation referred to was to the effect that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited would llfce to maice an offer for the unallocated territory of His iSxcellency Shaikh Hamad bin ^sa A1 Khalifah, 1 reminded Mr .Sampson that the matter was one in which His Excellency Shaikh Hamad should be approached through the Political Agent (or higher authority). 3. I showed Mr •Sampson^ letter to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad,who came to see me about oil,just after I had received it,as I felt certain that he either knew,or shortly would know,that a letter had been sent to me. 4. I think that the letter should be communicated officially to His JSKoellency Sliaudi Hamad Tain 'Isa A1 JQialifab witiiout delay, and I alsoteel (as stated in tiie eigiith. paragraph, of my / letter Ho:C/224-XO/l dated tiie 24th June 1-33) that the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited should 'be informed,also without delay,that a coiamunication has been received from another oil interest expressing a wish to negotiate for the territory remaining after the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited have chosen their 100,000 acres. I have the honour to 'be Sir Your most obedient servant Lieut-Colonels Political Agent,.Bahrain.Copy of a letter dated the 21st June 1933 from Mr, A*3,Sampson,Bahrain&gt;to the Political Agent,Bahrain, with copy to the General Manager, Messrs Anglo-Per si an Oil Company Limited,Abadan. i hare the honour to refer to our conversation regarding the development for oil of those areas in the territories of Bahrain which are not yet allocated for such development,and confirm that my Company,Messrs Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited, would like to come to an arrangement with H,E the Shaikh of Bahrain whereby the Company shall have the sole right over a period for negotiating for an agreement for the development of such areas* I shall be obliged if you will let me have your reply in due course•Confidential , Ho:C/224-10/l Political Agenoy, Bahrain,the 24th June 1933 From: - Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch,I # A« # Political Agent, Bahraino To: The Hon , 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire # Sir In continuation of my telegram ito:C/222 dated the 23rd June 1933,1 have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter dated the 15th June 1933 from Maj or Frank Holmes,Chief Local Representatiye of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,regarding the affairs of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited in Bahrain. 2© In this letter Major Holmes maintains the fiction of the offer of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad 'bin ♦Isa Al Khalifah,and indeed elaborates it,as for example in the first paragraph where he writes R and tentatively agreed hy me with His Excellency the Shaikh • 3, There has 156611 a change in the personal payments for His Excellency Shaikh Hamad - in place of a payment ol Rs.40,000/- down and Rs»3,000/- a month for 20 months it is proposed to offer him Rs.50,000/- down and Rs.2,500/- a month for 20 months: the total in each case being Rs.100,000/-. 4. But the main change is tnat it is proposed to recover the twenty monthly payments of Rs.10,000/- to the Bahrain Gorernment (which were to have been a payment not (2);gf 2, a loan) from the royalties on a scale to be agreed on between the parties. 5* The recovery of the payments to the Bahrain Government renders the proposal definitely less favourable than it was,but a cunning endeavour has been made to render the Company's offer attractive to His ilxcellency Shaikh Hamad by increasing the initial lump sum payment to him personally from Es # 40,000/- to Rs»50,000/-c 6. There is also a modification of the point at which the recovery of a loan from the royalties may be started. In Major Holmes♦ letter of the 15th May it was stated that the recovery might be made from:- ^, tRoyalties - which may become due - in excess of Rupees Eighty thousand (80,000) in any Calendar year M . The Company have modified this to;- M .Royalties on Oil - which may become due - in excess of Rupees Sixty Thousand (60,000) in any calendar year,but the Company shall not be permitted to recover the above mentioned loan from Royalties that may become due on Oil at a higher rate than twenty-five per cent (25^) of any excess over Rupees Sixty Thousand (60,000) in any calendar year'. 7. I recommend that I should be authorized to send a copy of Maj or Holmes 1 letter to the Bahrain Government and to ask for their views. It is desirable that we should avoid any delay which might suggest that time is being given to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited. 8. In amplification of the fourth paragraph of my telegram Ho:C/222 dated the 23rd June 1933,1 would say that the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited appear to be most apprehensive of the activities of the Anglo -ir 'ersian Oil Company Limited, and it is most important that we should not appear to them to be favouring the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (3) ■ n a—r&lt;—— (f\f)n) / i ' 3 Limited. I, therefore,strongly recommend,from the local point of ^ieWjthat I should 'be authorized to inform (Terhally, on the ground that he is not the Chief Local ReprssentatiYe) mt •Sicinner,fields Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited,on hehalf of His Excellency ShaiJch Hamad bin 'Isa A1 Khalifah,that a communication has been received from another oil interest expressing a wish to negotiate for the territory remaining after the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited have chosen their 100,000 acres. The official approach of the Anglo- Persian Oil Company Limited cannot,in the nature of things,remain confidential (even if it is still that now) for more than a few days,and I should prefer knowledge the of/written communication of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited to come to the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited from me (or through His Majesty's Government),rather than that it should come to the ears of Mr• Skinner and that he should then approach me on the subject. 9. I would request telegraphic orders on the seventh and eighth paragraphs of this letter. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel Political Agent,BahrainCopy of letter dated tiie Ibto June 1933 from Major i'ranic Holmes,Chief Local KepresentatiYe t The Bahrain ^etroTeiim Company Limited,Millhill, sandon,Hear Chelmsford,Essex, to the Political Agent,Bahrain. 1. The Board of directors of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited have now had an opportunity of studying the offer of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifah, Ruler of Bahrain as contained in my letter to you dated May 17th 1933• It will 'be noted from the terms and conditions defined later herein that several modifications have 'been made,as to the manner of payments and the recovery of such payments,but not as to the total amounts discussed and defined in my letter of May 17th 1933 and tentatively agreed by me with His Excellency the Shai}ch,but subject to the approval of the Hon* The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Board of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, 2 # I have been instructed by the Directors to make the offer as expressed below # The Directors agree generally the amount of the Loans to the Bahrain Government and the payments to be made to the private purse of His Excellency the Shaiich (as per my letter 17»5»33.) but the Directors consider that the payments (bel7.5,33 a ) - as well as the Loan (para 2. 17»5.33.) requested by the Bahrain Government - should also be subject to recovery from Royalties on oil, 3, In consideration of the payments hereinafter reserved and contained in exercise of his powers as Ruler and Sovereign of his Dominions for himself and Heirs and subjects - to grant unto the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited the exclusive right and easements wiiereoy tiic Company shall be entitled throughout the whole of that portion ol His Excellency the Shaikh's Territories - including all the Islands and all Territorial Waters - remaining after excluding and apart from that area already covered by the Concession Agreement dated December 2nd 1925 - to explore and search the surface for oil and cognate products of the above mentioned (2)W'* \ ' ,/&gt; . 2. area as described in this Present upon tlie following terms and conditions:- (a) ^cellenoy Shaikh Hamad bin -Isa A1 Aiial11an,Kuler ol Bahrain signs and seals the Deed Instrument coirering the area (described in par *3 hereof) and Initial Payment 'by the Company of the sum of Rupees 5'ifty Thousand (50,000) shall he made for the private purse of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad and in addition to the Initial Payment of Rupees Fifty Thousand (50,000) mentioned in this present the Company shall pay for the private purse of His Excellency Shai}ch Hamad Twenty (2o) Monthly payments of Rupees Two Thousand Pive Hundred (2,500) each the First of such monthly payments of Rupees Two Thousand Pive Hundred (2,500) each shall he made one (1) month from the date of the execution of the Deed Instrument covering the area (para.(3) hereof) and the remaining monthly payments of Rupees Two thousand Pive Hundred (2,500) each shall he made on the same date of each subsequent month until the whole of the Twenty (20) Monthly Payments have been made, (b) Twenty Monthly payments of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) will be made to the Bahrain Government. The First of such Twenty^ (20) Monthly payments of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) to be paid within Fourteen (14) days of the execution of the Deed Instrument. The remaining Monthly Payments of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) to be made to the Bahrain Government on the same date of each subsequent month until the whole of the Twenty (2o) Monthly Payments have been made. This Loan,as mentioned in this Present to be subject to recovery on Royalties on Oil which may become due from time to time,the rate of recovery to be on a scale to be agreed between the parties to this Agreement, but the recovery of the above-mentioned loan may only be made from Royalties due in excess of Rupees 60,000 (Sixty Thousand) in any calendar year. (c) The Concession granted covering the whole of the additional area including all the Islands and all the Territorial Waters of the Shaikh's Dominions shall be governed in all ways by the terms and conditions as laid down in the Concession Agreement of December 2nd, 1925,and the additional area shall,upon execution hereof,become an integral part of the Concession Agreement of December 2nd 1925,excepting certain payments which shall be increased as set forth in the f o1lowi ng paragraph (d)« (d) The Payments to be made on the additional area — as regards annual rental and minimum Royalty - shall be the same as laid down in the Concession Agreement dated December 2nd 1925,and such payments shall be in addition thereto,and the same shall apply to the Deed Instrument covering the whole of the remainder of the available Territory of Bahrain including all the Islands and all the Territorial Waters© The Prospecting License for both areas upoii the execution of the Deed granting the additional area shall ipso facto continue current for a period of Twenty (20) months from the effective date of such^Deed,and thereafter the Mining Lease (Schedule III shall become operative)©y 3. A. Furthermore,after the completion of the Twenty (20) Monthly Payments mentioned in Paragraph (b) hereof The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited is willing to make a loan or loans to the Bahrain GoTemment against future Royalties on Oil which may 'become due from time to time; moreover the Company is prepared to make a specific loan to the Bahrain Government of Rupees Two Hundred Thousand (2^0,000) or part thereof in Twenty Monthly Instaaments of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) each # The First Monthly Instalment of Rupees Ten Thousand (10,000) of such specific loan to 'become due in One Year and tn nine months from the date of these Presents, PROVIHBiD ALWAYS that the world market for oil and the development of the oil resources of the Bahrain Concession - during the above mentioned period of One Year and Mne (21) months - continue to he such that they present a reasonable prospect of making the recovery of such specific loan possible, but given unfavourable prospect of recovery the monthly Payment may cease or be suspended by the Company until condition become normal. 5« The recovery of the above mentioned loan or loans may only be made from any Royalties on Oil - which may become due • in vwrwi excess of Rupees Sixty Thousand (60,000) in any Calendar Year,but the Company shall not be permitted to recover the above mentioned loan from Royalties that may become due on Oil at a higher rate than Twentyfive per cent (25%) of any excess over Rupees Sixty Thousand (60,000) in any calendar year. 1/5&gt;/ z'Telegram From Secretary of State for the Colonies, London» Political Resident, Busliire, V' c) ti) Ck] (S) CCJ TO lTo» 9. Dated the 28th i received 29th | June 1935. m/iEDIA?E . EAHRAI1T CIL. Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited can only take interest in Bahrain 'by pemission of or as Agents of ! IraQ Petroleum Company. Matter has not yet been discussed between these Companies and decision cannot he taken before V next Board Meeting of 'Iraq Petroleum Company on 20th July. Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited are not anxious to take any definite action until after that date. Position was explained yesterday by Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited to tlceir local people by telegraph* Tn these circumstances Political Agent should suspend communication to Bahrain Government of Anglo -Persian Oil Company Limited offer. There is no objection to his communicating to Bahrain Government Holmes* letter of 15th Jun^but we think it very desirable to clear up at once position regarding offer alleged t o have been made by Shaikh and to ascertain what attitude Shaikh adopted at interview with Holmes. It is, in our view, important to get this aspect of the matter cleared up without delay and, if as is probable, no such offer was made by Shaikh, that Holmes should be confronted with the true position. I shall be glad, however, if you will report to me what Shaikh says before any ccromunication is made to Holmes, It would, as you will appreciate, be much more/more satisfactory from our poinrt of yiew if remainder of island ^ere to be developed 'by Anglo-Persian Oil Company ■* :i or Iraq Petroleum Company, though acceptance of American offer raay possibly 'be inevitable if no offer is made hy tae oi l ..i.er interests# Inless you see objection Loch fA&gt; should therefore inform Selgrave confidentially that he umers taric.t3 oiiat Anglo-^ersian ^il Company Tjiiaited are awi.-lvc-^.y interested hut cannot reach decision as to competing , 'W or another month; that our advice regarding American offer must necessarily to some extent turn on whether or not there Ctj is substantial competition in the field ancl that in the Shaikh 's own interest it is most desirable that he should avoid committing himself in any way to Holmes pending receipt of our advice. ^ Loch would no doubt impress on Belgrave the confidential nature of the above information as to attitude to Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited, The foregoing refers to your telegrams Nos. 15, 16, and 17 of 22nd, 26th, and 27th June. / 1 /■/?3 fpi' r' 77 -Secretary of State for the Colonies - 'I i; ■; / v / V ql 86/2 Telegram P. From To No. 510 Bated 29tii June 19 33 Political Besident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. IMPQBTAHT . y] , \ 1 1 My telegram No 501. Seply received from His Majestys Government as follows:- (1) ^ Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited can only take interest ...communicating to Bahrain Grovernment Holmes* letter of 15th June. 1 * (2) ^ It would, as you will appreciate information as to attitude to Anglo- Persian Oil Company, Limited. w Please take action accordingly. Besident86/2 Tel egram Pram B. Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of'state for the Colonies, London. To No 13 Bated 29tfcL June 1933. / Bahrain Oil. I have repeated your telegram to Politic Agent, Bahrain, and have asked him to take action accor- -dingly . 2. Position of Holmes and the Shaikh was made clear in my despatch No. 36 of 12th June sent 'by 'bag from here on 14th June 3 Holmes is now in England. The foregoing refers to your telegram No 9. Besident, fCONFIDENTIAL. No-775-3 of 1933 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis com* pliraents to ^he foreign Secretary to fhe Government of India, Bimla 9 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment [fy,/ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated.. ^9t3a., »I uej 8 ,. 193,3 ...... Reference to previous correspondence _ • , Bushire ^rinted letter No»77S-B of 29th June 1933, Cfi^- Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Political '.eBidejrt's telegram No.18 of S9th June 1933 to His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colo^ies,London♦ Subject. BAHRAIN OIL,CONFIDENTIAL. ^ 0 - 774-S of 1933. m » . • r Ui I Ihe Hon hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis com pliments to ^'he Political Agent, Bahrain 9 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. C Dated•»J• «1 , 938' »• Reference to previous correspondence Bushire telegram Ho,510 of ^9th June 1933, L ut] Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. 1. Secretary of State's telegr lTo.9 of f?6th June 1933, 2. Political He8ident , s telegr; Ho,18 of 29th June 1933 to Secretary of Btate for the Colonies. urn am A Bahrain Oil \Please have typed flrafts made. I will send the the subsidiary information to Col.Powle 'by d.o.,which shd go by Air if that is the quickest route. 14.4, 33 P Drafts submitted in Eype . /?• Issued despatch ^o.26 of 17/4/33 to Colonial Office. p.l. Ho.384-S M to Govt, of India. p.l. No.385~S ** Bahrain. D.O. No. 386-3 H to Gol.Fowle, London . , ; 71 r A Jolonial Office despatch Kzx Persian Gulf No. 2, dated the 29th Llarch 1933. P.H. -Ve have not got an Arabic typewriter here in working order so I submit draft memo to Bahrain 19-4-33 As amended. If there are any further agreements it would be well to take these extra copies now asked xor into consideration when stating the number required. But H.E. Shaikh Hamad dislikes signing large'•liifl, : V numbers ol copies and it would be convenient if the the P.A, were to be told how many of the copies required by Govt, must be signed. 9.4.33 Icj Issued Memo. jao.393-S of 19/4/33 to P.A.^Bahrain. India, ae, idon. 1-7' f w 15. 16 • 17. iter ■Hz p.176 .10 BAHRAIN letter Ho.0/154 of 15/4/S3. No.G/161 of 22/4/35. Letter dated the 22Tid April 193S from the Financial Adviser, Bahrain State. Ref. 15 . The terms are the same as those mentioned in Major Holmes* letter of 4/4/33. Ref. 16 . In this connection please see para 3 of your demi-official letter Uo#386-S of 17/4/33 to Colonel Fowie. V * As regards the question of the extension of the Prospecting Licence, please see the penultimate para of Petroleum Department's letter ^o.21 Part 2, d/-13/lo/32, and Colonial Office letter No. 98035/32, dated 26-10-32 to the Bahrain letroleum Coy. 26-4-33. Issued telegram 110.311 of 26/4/53 to Bahrain. Issue telegrams. Then we shd send on corjies by mail. 27.4.33 / VI' -'Issued tel. No. 9/321, d. 27-4-33, addsd. S. of 3. for Colonies, rptd* India 322 ' to S. of Sjt for India. 323 H S. of S. for India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000272_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/652</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000272</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/652</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 86/2 IV (C 43) Bahrain Oil; Eastern and General Syndicate Limited’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-03T11:43:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (227 folios)</extent><extent>The volume’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest items at the front to the latest at the rear. Office notes at the end of the volume (folios 210-16) mirror the chronological arrangement. The subject index at the front of the volume (folio 2) refers to the uncircled numbers used by the volume’s original foliation system.</extent><extent>Foliation: The main foliation sequence begins on the front cover and ends on the last folio, and uses circled pencil numbers located in the top centre of each recto. A second foliation sequence is present between ff 3-209; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The following foliation anomalies occur: 1, 1a, 1b, 2, 2A, 2B, 2C, 117 and 117a.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains letters, telegrams and memoranda relating to ongoing exploratory oil drilling being undertaken in Bahrain by the Bahrain Petroleum Company (hereafter BAPCO). The volume is a direct continuation of ‘File 86/2 III (C 42) Bahrain Oil, Eastern and General Syndicate Limited’ (IOR/R/15/1/651). The principal correspondents in the volume are Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Gordon Loch, Political Agent in Bahrain, and Major Frank Holmes, Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company.Key subjects discussed in the volume include:Discussion amongst British officials in Bahrain and London over whether BAPCO are fulfilling conditions C and D of their contractual obligations in the concession agreement, respectively: the long periods of absence from Bahrain of the Chief Local Representative of the Company (Holmes), and the proportion of British to non-British workers employed by BAPCO;A dispute over exemption of duty on equipment imported by BAPCO;Whether oil royalties should be paid in Indian rupees or Sterling;A request by BAPCO for an extension of the prospecting license, including Holmes’s offer of terms and a draft indenture (folios 68-72), and the Ruler of Bahrain, Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah’s rejection of Holmes’s offer (folios 86-91);A map of the prospective location of the British naval base at Bahrain (folio 117a);Enquiries by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company after a concession for those parts of Bahrain not covered by the existing BAPCO concession.The volume also contains a set of notes which provide a concise overview of the Bahrain concession to date, including details of the commercial viability of Bahrain’s oil, under the heading ‘exploitable quantity’ (folios 58-64).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company, Chief Local Representative</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sitrah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Bahrain</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum products</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000272#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>