<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:06:04.159Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Pros. Serial Noj f Subject. PROPOSAL TO PURCHASE A MOTOR CYCLE FOR AGENCY DESPATCH RIDER. Pwvwms EeJerencos, . j Later Relereaew. MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEG i a. ^7 Si VP 'MO ■&amp;.&amp;. 4V~l,.000,&lt;Xib-Ifo. 2344 -:L 7 / 26 * To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 7th June, 1945* The Hdci&gt; Y ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushire* I think the day hsjs come v/her this Agency should be provided with a motor cycle despatch rider for the local delivery of uiails to the vaiiou^ offices, which as you know, are dispersed over a considerable area of the island* - At present we possess twr&gt; &gt; bicycles for the delivery of telegrams, mails etc., which have proved, in practice, to be unsatisfactory in many cases and in nearly all in any urgency. 2. If you have no objection, I propose contact- ing some agent in the United Kingdom to find out if a light weight motor cycle Is available and if so, will you please confirm that there is no objection to my incurring expenditure up to R^ISOO/- on this account when I will ircli?de this sum in my statement of anticipated savings and excesses in N ovenber, 1945.I Tolegran From To No. Dated -h; ® v- »*-ft55.3^. siixuu' G.T.G. Political Resident, Bushire. Political A^ent, Bahrain. A/1002 27tli received 28th June, 1945. i /f- Your memorandum No .2344-17/26 dated June 7th. 2. Please telegraph annual amount required for the maintenance dff motor cycle. 3. From experience in Bushire I suggest that you ask for motor cycle and side i car. =DHITAIM= AMOT pi Telegram From To No. Dated 1945. 2 . G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram A/1002 of 27fh June, io.1000/- half 2000/- annually. ^POLITICAL*Telegram From To Ho. ' la ted I would r ft r • • Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. 480 5th July, 1945. Your telegram A/1032 July 3rd. prefer motor cycle and side car. =POLITICAL='I&lt;r GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No. S870-19/267 „ Dated To fobktgn, new mim. 16th July mx. rtf* LOCAL OET.TVEKY OE WALLS to wm ypw POTT^TCAL A(TENCT f PALATE, The PoUtlral Agency* Bahrain^ T*o»? ! *e ,, »5es only two hi cycles for the local rfellverv of teleprams, malls etc. to the offices of the Bahrain Ooverntnent, the Naval Base at .Tufalr. the A.L.P. at '^har^aq, British Overseas Airways Corporation Ttn #? the Bahrain Petroleum Co*. Petroleum Tcnceftsions^t^e ^astern Banv, the Tnnerial Bank of Persia, the Post Office f Ne«sers Cable Ireless Ltd*, an r7 various other offices and concerns vnich are dispersed over a considerable area of the two Islands of Nanama and Noharrsk. method of local delivery of walls Inevitably leads to delays in many cases and is nrovinr most unsatisfactory* T therefore recommend that the Covernmant of India sanction for the Political Agency* Bahrain the onroh*»ee of one motor cycle and side car and one motor cycle at an estimated cost of Hs* 4 , 000 / /«* The cost of the motor~b!cycles and their maintenance charges amounting to Bs* 1 , 000 /- ner annum will if possible be met by rearnronriation from the existing budget grants of this Residency, failing which the amount will be Included in the statement of excesses and Savings, • PPTTATN . The issue of the above has been authorised. hQ . .-‘‘T’A Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. CrSL v No. 2871-19/267 Copy to the Political Agent, 'Bahrain with reference to his telegram No. 480 5th July, 1945. &gt; /n S. 44. MFP—1015 S«&amp;P—{M-1870i—9-2-39—20,000. {Designation&gt; (tf' No. 4370 - 30/16. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. © and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. Bahrain Receipt No -sjLte Dated .. November,, 1945 • Reference to previous correspondence: Residency endorsement No. 2S71 - 19/267 dated the 16th Juljr, 1945, Description of Enclosure, Memorandum No. F.141 - A/45 dated the 8th October, 1945, from the Under Secretary to the Government 6f India in the External Affairs Department to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire. Local delivery of mails to and from Political Agency, Bahrain rv u G.A.M.From - The Under Secy, to tho Grovornmant of India in tho internal Affairs Department, To - • The Hon*ble tha Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUdHIR^ . Memorandum No* F.i41-A/45 0 Dated ciimla, the QV/t October 1945«, oUBJdCT:- Local Delivery of Mails to and from Political Agency, Bahrain, 5 Reference your express letter No.2870- 19/267, dated the 16tn July 1945. 2* The Government of India do not usually sanction motor cycles for local delivery of dak and as the work in Bahrain has all along been done by cyclists, they have not been able to accept the proposal to substitute ordinary cycles bv motor cycles. It is, however, considered that' the delay involved in the delivery of dak may be eliminated, if the area of beat of the existing men is decreased by engaging another cyclist temporarily for such time as the work is heavy for two m0n o (3D/- P.N. Krishnaswamv,) * Under Secretary to the Govt, of India*A / l\) o\xyfo{ ^ C\. C^Cc^jC % CA**-* C^J • CX- ' i^\ CA^ C^Ci j^y J _ ^ /wVl^W* t Cv C-/ % A. //? ♦ O^y^r'Z^i^AA^i /At izr}-*~A- /fAttt-^ VT r z ^ 7 Mr. Hamad. Have you found out yet whether any motor cycles are available? Itd.R.E.H.B. 17/5 There is only one British motor-cycle which is workable and is possessed by a mechanic in the Bahrain Govt garage; but he has not yet given me his definite word about selling it. He states that he has another ^ motor cycle for which he requires tyres, which if he could secure he will sell us, please. Itd.H. 19/5 If you wish I could ask him to bring it for inspection. Itd.R.E.R.B. -P.A. 19/5 Thanks Itd.C.J.P. 19/5 Please do so Itd.R.E.R.B. 19/5</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1627</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1627</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/26 PROPOSAL TO PURCHASE A MOTOR CYCLE FOR AGENCY DESPATCH RIDER'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T18:05:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (11 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 13; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-9; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the Bahrain Political Agent's proposal that the Political Agency should be provided with a motorcycle despatch rider for the local delivery of mail to and from the Agency.In a letter to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, dated 7 June 1945, the Political Agent opines that the current practice, whereby mail is distributed by two cyclists, is unsatisfactory. In a copy of a letter to the Government of India's External Affairs Department, dated 16 July 1945, a request is made by the Secretary to the Political Resident for two motorcycles (one with a sidecar) for the Agency. In a copy of a response from the Under-Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, dated 8 October 1945, the request is turned down and it is suggested that another cyclist should be deployed 'for such time as the work is heavy for two men'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Motorcycles</topic></subject><subject><topic>Bicycles</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>