<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000169_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:05:59.371Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No.234-17/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. 7th February, 1942. To The I/anager, ^. _ The Times Printing &amp; Publishing Co., Basra• Dear Sir, I shall glad if you will please supply this Agency with two rubber stamps, as per samples attached, at your earliest convenience. 2 . The rubber stamps when ready should be sent here by aix' mail* 3 # The cost will -e remitted to you on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain. forNo•1676-17/1 Political Agency,Bahrain. 19th September,1942. The Manager, The Times Co*, Printing &amp; Publishing Ltd., Basra. Bear Sir, I enclose herewith a Bank Draft for I.D.l-OOoin settlement of the bill received with your letter No.792 of 6th September 1942. Please I acknowledge receipt. I Yours faithfully,TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. 5/-+7B &gt;i^rfinted in England. Aug. 1941. (-40750 pads.) , CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk's Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. Official Instructions 'Via Jhryi&amp;ualZ No. Words Time Instructions to be _Signaned ; __ To Him BOOKNGTKS Address BOMB--Y IT'QUIRK 1000 SHEETS GCX«J QUALITY NOTE PAPER EMBOSSED THE AGENC-Y BAHRAIN ‘IN TVO LINES AND 1000 ENVELOPES EMBOSSED ON THE FLAP STOP APPLY FOR EXPORT PERMIT IfME^lATRLY POLITICAL 363 I rtquMt thst tht tk.vi T»l»|r»in may ba tarwarbad wbjact to tha condition! printad on back ot thia farm by which I afraa to ba bound. T»«I^Qy,XJCALAafiMCY&lt; BAHREIN Signature of Sender Address (Not to be telegraphed) P.T.O.r » ^ 7 i I , 'T*' vV 0 , CONDITIONS 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph . Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although ^ it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error r-\ or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission', non-delivery, detay, 1 error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE. Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International * Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, ^ must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company's Branches.The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :—The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed ip and Official instructions—if any. ' QV40N SANSORIGINE 10 NIL NL IRC VIA KR LC POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN STATY READY LICENCE NOT SANCTIONED NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDCO TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.No lo? -17/25 POLITICAL AGENCY, C. BAHRAIN. ThOot?/^ Mnrch l^t4. To Messrs. Thneker &amp; Co., Ltd., Bombay. Dear Sirs, On the 10th October 1943, I placed with you a telegraphic order for the supply of 1,000 sheets of good quality note- paper and 1,000 envelopes, vide my telegram No. 363 dated the 10th October 1943. In your telegram dated the 9th November 1943 you informed me tliat the stationery ordered by me was ready but that it could not be despatched for lack of cxpoit 2. On the 11th. November 1943 I telegraphed to the Export Trade Controller, Bombay, to permit you to export stationery and informed you telegraphically to this effect. c,n the 13th. January 19^4 I telegraphed you asking what was the position with regard to the supply of the stationery anc having received no reply I again telegraphed you on the 28th February 1944. In reply to this telegram 1 received your telegram dated the 1st. Parch 1944 informing me that index cards would be sent within the next week. As I had not ordered for index cards I sent you * telegram No. 167, dated the bth. Parch 1944 asking when I should expect stationery ordered in ray telegram No.363, dated the 10th October 1J43. To this I have not received a reply so far. licence. 6 th March 1944, respectively have remained unanswered. _ . , _I_ _x».. n 4 ^* ,r^,i t»» -4 1 n lr-4r«aiv 1 o+. nn knOVJ bv to above. Yours Faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.THACKER £? Co. ltd. CABLES a TELEGPAMS: 'BOOKNOTES' BOMBAY. Cade BENTLEY’S COMPLETE /■ /C J a f S / (T- T. ? f n) TELEPHONES BOOKDEPAPTMENTN®. 3071Z STATIONERY N® 30613 PRINTING WORKS No. 20343 ACCOUNTS DEPT. No 30722 BOMBAY £ k• t.API*i 1 1_944,« 194 . O »0O ) GMT/SCM/16020. The Political A^ent., Bahrain, ' PE R RBGIGTKK ED AIR ivIAIL. Dear Sir, We acknowledge receipt og your letter No.908/17/25 dated the 29th Ultimo. ' 1^ On turning up the previous correspondence relating to this order we Bind that this order has got mixed up with other export orders of/similar nature. We much regret the apparent neglect to your reminders and telegrams. Ihe Assistant in charge has Been severly reprimanded for this state ox' affairs. We are now arranging for Export licence with the Export irade Controller j Bombay, and will despatch the goods or write you aga^n in about a week ! s time. With apologies for the annoyance caused. ECM/GMT. 5.4.1944. Yours faithfully, Thacker &amp; Co., Ltd., Secretary &amp; Manager. P.Ss- This Office Assistant called this afternoonpthe Office of the Export Trace Controller, Bombay* and was given to understand that there was no receipt of any telegram from your office for export lic*ice. We are further informed that under the existing orders export of Stationery to Bahrain is prohibited. We therefore recommend you to kindly apply . direct to the Under Secretary to Government of India, Depfrti, of Commerce, Delhi Secretariat, Delhi, from yhom you have - generally obtained permission, and instructions to the E.T.C. Bombay, to grant us the export licence. lECHfiTARY &amp; MANAGER*air ma.il POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The tt April If; -1 No// 2.6 -17/25 ei To f^cssrs. Thacker Co., P.O. Box 190, Bombay. Memorandum . iieference your letter No. GNT/ ICN/l-O^O, dated the 6 th April 19C4. 2 . _ I^bave to-day wired to the Government o? India for issue of an export permit for 1,000 sheets note paper and ], 0 C 0 envelopes to be sent direct to you. 3. On rcccint of the p: mit nlense despatch at once the stationery ordered in ny telegra b No• 363, dated tne ICth October L 43 (cop., 1 ' attac h 'd and advise ne by air nail. 4. I nru making enquirie a ro the uqoort Tirade Controller, Bombay, about non-recoiv)t of r telegram doted the 11th Novo iber 1943 requestii • ^7 him to issue an export permit for the stationer- ordered by you.By Air I-Iail No - 17/25 POLITICAL ACC?rCY, BAHTA P r - The /trtt: Anril 1944 To The Bxport Tmde Controller, Bombay. Memorandum. In October last I placed a telegraphic order for supply of 1,000 sheets note paper and 1,000 envelopes with Messrs. Thacker &amp; Co., Ltd., Bombay, and asked them to apply for an export permit. On the 10th November 1943 they r wired me that the stationery was ready but that license was not sanctioned . On the 11 th Novem- 1943 I sent you'^ telegram No. 435, a copy of [-- which is enclosed herewith, and informed Messrs. Thacker &amp; Co., that you had been requested tele graphically to issue an export permit. 2. After waiting for five months for the stationery, during which period several telegra phic reminders were sent to the Company, I have now been informed by them that their represent- i ^l£ative visited your office on the 6 th April 1^44 for export permit but was informed that my tele gram No. 435, dated the 11th November 1943 had r^\ not been received by you and that the export of stationery to Bahrain .vas prohibited. 3 . 'ill you please confirm tliat my telegram referred to above was not received by you so that I may make enquiries from the Cable and tireless Ltd., Bahrain, about this. 4. In the meantime I have wired to the Government of India for issue of an export permit . for the stationery ordered from Messrs. Thacker and Co., Ltd., for Political Agent, Bahrain21 f Where delivery of such silver to the owner is withheld merely by reason of such amount not being paid, the Collector shall, upon such deposit being made, cause such silver to be delivered to such owner. If upon such appeal it is decided that the whole or any portion of such amount was not leviable in respect of such silver, the Collector shall return such amount or portion (as the case may be) to the owner of such silver on demand by such owner.” 4 (Hi) After clause 16, insert the following clause :— “ 17. Every appeal and every application for revision under clau^ 15 shall be accompanied by a copy of the order in respect oi which the appeal or application is made.” [F. D.'(C. R.), Notfn. No. 24-C. Exc., dated the 28th February 1942.] No. 324. Page 54 — To sub-clause (1) of clause 5, add the following proviso :— “provided that before the order of summary assessment is made effective- the owner of the silver works shall be given a reasonable oppor tunity to state his case.” [F. D. (C. R), Notfn. No. 25-C. Exc., dated the 28th February 1942.]. No. 325. Page 56 — (i) In clause 15, as amended by correction slip No. 75, after the words “ Central Board of Revenue ”, insert the following :— “ but if the Collector by w hom the appeal would otherwise be heard had himself as Assistant Collector passed the order appealed against he shall report the circumstances to the Board and the Board shall hear and dispose of the appeal.” (it) After clause 15, insert the following clause :— “ 15-A. Where the order appealed against relates to any duty or penalty leviable in respect of silver, the owner of the silver if desirous of appealing against such order, shall, pending the appeal, deposit into the local Treasury or any other Treasury approved by the Collector the amount demanded bj^ the Assistant Collector. ^ Where delivery of such a silver to the owner is withheld merely by reason of such amount not being paid, the Assistant Collector shall, upon such deposit being made cause such silver to be delivered to' such owner. If upon such appeal it is decided that the whole or any portion of such amount was not leviable in respect of such silver, the Assistant Collector shall return such amount or portion (as the case may be) to the owner of such silver on demand hy such owner.” (in) After clause 16, insert the follow ing clause :— ‘ 17. Every appeal and every application for revision under clause 15- shall be accompanied by a copy of the order in respect of whichi the appeal or application is made.” [F. D. (C. R.), Notfn. No. 25-C. Exc., dated the 28th February 1942.] I l M /Vi&lt;i. fe .3 •} q CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED, ao ffr/UU (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) ^ (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— Prefix Letter* and Number of Message. Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. CircL Cleric’s Name. Time Received. 7 A.TiRIF 1940 883 KV 235 /U S/0 1 5_N I L 1545 LC POL I TICAL AGENT POL I EXPORT PERMI T FROM GOVE AWAITED THACKERS «girv MARK YOUR REPLY 'Ifta Jm/ieSuaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.TSUEOftAMS SOOKNOTtS BOMBAY O 3~L( is (zZS Book Department no 30^22 Stationery no. 30613. Periodical Dept Printing Works ACCOUNTS DEPT. NO. 30722. NO. 203 SB. NO. 30722. v 7 TWACKER BOOKSELLERS. PUBLISHERS. STATIOMERS PRIMTERS. ETC. Please Quote no GH!/l»4eO. |^cimpar&gt;t Row, 80 M SAY 27th April, 1944, The Political Agent, Political Agency, BSfera&amp;u . yH 2 xi' 11 Ref* your Bo.1186-17/85 dated 80th 4pril,44. * our Ho.GVT/ICU/16020 dated 6th April,44 Dear Sir, le note you have applied GoTernment of India, Hew Delhi, with a request that the Export Trade - «. Controller^should grant us an E* T. C. licence • lonediately we receive a letter from the Govemment of India, Hew Delhi, we will proceed to obtain an E* ?• C« Licence from £• T. C. Bombay, end on receipt will despatch the articles.Printed in England. Sept. 1941 (4,100. pads .) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED The first line of this Telegram Prefix Letters and Number of Message. 0 Official instructions—if any. Clerk’s QV15/D SANSORIGINE 34 NIL QK KR ANTEN = LC POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN AGENCY BAHRAIN = REFCE YOUR TELEGRAM 360 EXPORT TRADE CONTROLLER BOMBAY HAS NOT RECD INSTRUCTIONS FROM GOVT OF INDIA STOP TAKING THE MATTER UP WITH BOTH PROVINCIAL AND CENTRAL GOVTS ' i /u-/UL A&amp;ua./£. = XHACKERS = / ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.fib ^ TeteoA^Me ~j?/ £.,}), /’Book Department no 30722 . KNOTES BOMBAY” ! STATIONERY NO, 30613. TELEPHONES &lt; PERIODICAL DEPT. NO. 30722. I Printing Works no. 203sb. ^ ACCOUNTS DEPT. NO. 30722. TWACKER A. Co.. Limited. BOOKSELLERS. PUBLISHERS. STATIONERS PRINTERS. ETC 1719014; Row, BOMBAY PLtAst Quote mo 1 . Glklx The Political i&gt;geut lahrain^ 16th 24ay 1944. Dear Sir, Eeference ycur letter No'. 1126/ 17/25 dated 20.4.1944.for expert of 1000 Sheets Note - Papers and 1000 Envelopes. tii th reference to above, and your telegram received this corning, we have replied you hy wire to I5he following ef£e- c t : - . &gt;L t &lt;] % 'Export'Permit from Government of India, Still awaited' We note from ycur above letter that ;fcu have wired to the Govt.of India, to issue instructions for Export Licence, hut regret to note that we have sc far recei ved no letter from New Delhi. Immediately cn receipt of sace, we will des;atch the goods. Yours faithfully Thacker &amp; Cc.Ltd. c-gCI'c Lary 6 c LanagePOLITICAL AGENCY, (£v PAHPAIN. The 6th August 1944. Our stock of the enclosed form is nearly exhausted and the local press asks the oxhorbitant price of hs. 80/- for 1,000 copies. It would be mucl more economical if we could have 2,000 copies of it printed in India and have them sent here. I would be grateful if you could manage to arrange for this when you are in Karachi. e 7eP. Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.T3., O.3.B., C/o M. Gunn, Esquire, ^ Manager, Eastern Bank Ltd., Karachi.POLITICAL AGE7TCY, BAHRAIN The icK Sept emb er, 1944 No. m -17/25 To The Manager, The Tiaec Printing Publishing Co. Lt Basrah No. ^ 72450, dated the 28th Sept sober, 1944 for Iraqi Dinar one and fills one hunored and fifty only in full settlement of your bill No. 107/R, dated the 15th August, 1944 in reject ot Rubber Stamp supplied to this office. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Dear Sir I enclose herewith a Bank dralt j ~ Yours faithfully for Political Agent, BahrainGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. EXPRESS LETTER N. B .—This is an ORTGINA'L MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the vires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the tame expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. S. 6.NO. ^ 17/25 To Messrs Keale &amp; Co., Elphiaistone Street, Karachi * POLITICAL AlijtfJCY, BAHRAIN, OCTOBER, 1944. Dear Slrf, Reference my order for supply of 3000 copies of printed forms for use in Bahrain Agency. 2. The Government of India have been requested to issue export permit for the above forms and to send it direct to you. On receipt of the permit please despatch at once the printed forms as ordered and advise me by air mail. mj Yours faithfully, Yc.. Political Ag Wr ent, Bahrain.*No.2013-17/25. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 16th May, 1945. To Messrs. Thacker &amp; Co., Ltd., P.0. Box No.190, Bombay. Dear Sirs, Please send me as early as possible a sample of each of the enclosures in white note paper, embossed in black, with one envelope for each size similarly embossed on the flap. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.•'Telegrams •*BOPk£|OTES BOMBAY.” Book Department no 30722 Stationery no.-sobis Telephones Periodical Dept. no. 30722 Printing Works no. 20355 accounts Dept. no. 30722 TWACKER Co.. L-itJ. ^ BOOKSELLERS, PUBLISHERS, STATIONERS. PRINTERS, ETC. Row, BOMBAY. Please Quote No. AD/2'7395 # 2nd JlUlG 1945# n'TA - v.' The Political Agent, political Agency, Bahrain# „„ Dear Sir, ' ..... With reference to your letter No#2013- -17/25 dated 16/5/45, we regret we have no die of n POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN' in stock. Will you please send us the die or shall we engrave the die and send you the proofs as required. To supply the Stationery it is necessary to have the Export Permit, without which we cannot despatch# Will you please arrange to obtain this Permit in the meanwhile Awaiting the favour of your further instructions # wmmm—mm’ No* 2905-17/25* To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 16th July, 1945. L'ie n3rr.* Th acker &amp; Co., Ltd*, Rampart Ko», LoilI ay. Dear Sirs, y-M ' 6 ^ith reference to your letter No. /D/27395 dated the 2nd June, 1945«, I shall be glad if you will engrave the die and send me the proofs by air mail.*■* A Mil No. - 17/2b. To POLITICAL AG^HCTI, BAHRAIN. The 7th November 1945. 'T^c. Messrs. Thacker &amp; Co.* Ltd.j Ramoart Row, B0M3AY. Dear birs, I shall be glad if you will quote for printing 30 booklets of 100 forms each of the enclosed specimen Way Bill for use in this Agency. /0 Yours faithfully, f\ oS- KJiiC for POLITICAL AG^NT, BAHRAIN. J»sBAHRAIN WAY BILL NO ■ ’ Correspoadtact despatched by Registtred to Aik If ah. POST on . _ Express Letter Not. Civoutat s N os. : Prioted Letter Net. Demi-Officials Nos. \ / : Mswor&amp;odA Mss. Endosseoassts Nss. Letter No. ‘ Yowr way bill No. dated ; Miscellaneous Received by Date received kkdly receipt this dsemeat aid rctsva t# Political A goat Babrak,No. C/1103. To Bahrain, The 1st December 1945. • Messrs. Thacker and Company, Limited, Dear Sirs, I enclose one specimen piece of your pre-war note paper, and shall be glad if you will print four dIocks of the pos&gt;t octavo size as amended. I also require four blocks with the address printed on the post 8vo on Basildon’s Bond paper of the size of the attached blue piece. please also supply the requisite number of envelopes. Bombay . \ /I &lt;1' Yours faithfully, r ■&gt; H (A.C. GALLOWAY) political Agent, Bahrain. ( v- f 7 H &lt; hr /. '&lt; i.i'lLm-.i $ A —urn TELEGRAMS “BOOKNOTES BOMBAY N&lt;AD/27'J9b. r ! 7 /j v' (£»)4 / ’VVViACKER Co., Limite/ ^ TCLEPHON ^ BOOKSELLERS, PUBLISHERS, STATIONERS, PRINTERS, ETC. RAMPART ROW, BOMBAY. BOOK DEPARTMENT 30722* STATIONERY ,, 30613* PERIODICAL DEPT* 30722* PRINTING WORKS 20356* ACCOUNTS DEPT* 30722. 29th December 1945. Paforam Receipt The Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, As requested we enclose herein proofs of note paper with addresses duly stamped* We note that the Envelopes should also bear the stamps on the flaps. The delay is very much regretted which was inevitably due to heavy seasonal rush. Ycurs faithfully, THACKER &amp; CO.LTD. E. C. Mur HG. , aGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, X Department EXPRESS L [Ns B. — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save' expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be receipt, mth the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ From Political, Bahrain. To Repeated Britain, Bushire. Foreign, New Delhi. No. 362- 17/ 2o. Dated 29th January, 1946. An order for 1000 repeat 1000 sheets embossed note paper and 1000 repeat 1000 envelopes has been placed with Thacker &amp; Co., Rampart low, Bombay, for this Agency, bequest Government of India be asked to issue export permit direct to the latter. - Political - The issue of the above has been authorised. !) Assistant Political ^igent, Bahrain. S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.No. To 5?V 17/25 Political Agency, Bcthrain, The 29th January, 1946. £{®r_ Messrs Thacker &amp; Co., Ltd., Rampart Row, BOMBAY Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter Ho.AD/27396 of the 29th December, 1946, the die Political Agency, Bahrain* may please be engraved on the extreme right as marked in the samples returned herewith. Kindly arrange to supply me with 600 sheets of each size with suitable envelopes as early ^s possible. The Government of India is being requested to issue the necessary export licence direct to you. Yours faithfully, Pi $ for Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ ' /It? /&gt; S - ^ t J -Jf ***GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAtb^ [N.B .—This its an ORIGIN A L message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 708-80/26. Dated Sim New 13th Ftbruary 19 46.. To FOREIGN, NEW DELHI l/REPEATED POLITICAL, BAHRAIN © ^5 Bahrain Expraas Lattar No.262-17/25 datad tha 29th January 1946, copy aant to you dlract. Stationary. I racommand issua of axport parmit. 2. =Britain= Tha issua of tha aboVa has baan authorisad, j for Sacratary to tha in tha Parslan Polltica: Gulf. tical Rasidant No- ^ ^ Ttf vt-t //t W - i S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P--(M.1870;—9-2-39—20,000. (Signature) (DesignationNo*693.0112 Lc,Lea 3oth June, 1946. To, The political Agent, Bahrain. &amp; ^ British Agency, Sharjah. LemoranJuia . I shall he grateful if a rubber stamp reaaing 'political officer Trucial Coast* Sharjah be inaentea for ana sent to this office. / captain. political officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. -C \■n No* 17/25 Political Agency, Bahrain, The //4C J uly, 1946. To Messrs Lotia Stores, Slphinstone Street, KARACHI. Dear Sirs, Will you please supply by air mail to the Political Officer, Truclal Coast, Sharjah, two rubber stamps (specimens attached) under intima tion to this office. Your bill may be sent to this Agency for payment in due course. Yours faithfully,Number ^peciaon required* 1. 2 . POLITICAL OPFICiiR, Trucial Co&amp;st f One Sharjah# ♦ Instead of •H.B.iPs Political Agent, bahr*in% the words should be 'Political Officer, Xrucial Coast’*.To Messrs* Thacker and Company, Limited, Rampart Row, Bombay* Dear Sirs, I should be grateful if you would kindly supply me, as early as possible, with 1000 sheets of note-paper, in pads of 100 sheets each, the quality, size and colour to be the same as that of the sample attached* The address should be printed on the righ hand top corner as in the sample, special care being taken to spell the word BAHRAIN correctly* 2* Please also supply 1000 envelopes to match, with the address printed on the flap, as shewn. 3* The Government of India are being requested to send you the necessary export permit* Yours faithfully. for POLITICAL AGBNT, BAHRAIN.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depaktmbnt, EXPRESS LETTER [iy. L, This is an ORIGIM AL MESS AG 12, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sat e time and formalities it is woi'ded and signed as if it hud been so despatched,] Repeated FOREIGN, NiSW D3LHI. No. 975 - 17/25. Bahrain. [) a t e( i the 26th March /$p : - 1947. An order for 1,000 sheets of note-paper and 1,000 envelopes has been placed with Thackor and Coiapany, Rampart Row, Bombay, for this Agency. Request Government of India be asked to issue the necessary export permit direct to the firm concemeti From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To RdPGU, BAHRAIN. POLITICAL The issue of the above has been authorised t C Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. KUS ys *y vS. f&gt;. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M- 820)—23-7.36—300,000.PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN* /C EXPRE SS LETTER, From To Repeated REPGU, BAHRAIN* FOREIGN, NEW DELHI. POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. NO. ~?£Z - BQ/S6. n ' Dated the 2nd April, 1947. Reference Bahrain Agency expxe&amp;s letter No. 975-17/2^ of the 26th March, 1947. Export of note paper and envelopes from India. 2. I support. * REPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised. 0 'Government of India. External Affairs Department. EXPRESS LETTER * From - Foreign, New Delhi 3. To - Repgu, Bahrain. Repeated- Political, Bahrain. NO.D.1883-BPG/47. Dated the ''April 1947. Subjecti- Export of note paper and envelopes required for the Bahrain Agency. Your express letter 762-80/36, dated April 7th. 2 # Exporters have been asked to contact Export Trade Controller, Bombay, who has been instructed to permit export. The issue of the above has been authorised. (S.J.L.Olver) Under Secretary to the Government of India. Mehta” 14/- . •. •£ l+x BY AIR MAIL. NO. IfcOtr -17/25. r\l-V'' To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, April, 1947. Messrs Thacker &amp; Co. Ltd., Rampart Row, Bombay , Dear Sirs, \ Please refer to my letter No. 974-17/25 dated the 26th March 1947 requesting the supply of 1000 note paper and envelopes for this Agency. 2. Government of India inform me that you have been asked to contact Export Trade Controller, Bombay, for permission to export these articles. Please do this and forward the stationery to this office as early as possible. t&gt;[U luu: Yours faithfully, u for Political Agent, Bahrain, pAPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No. \y4, -17/25 The 15th January, 1943. To Messrs. Thacker and Co.,Ltd., Rampart Row, Bomba y. Dear Sirs, I should be grateful if you would supply me, at your earliest convenience, with 1000 sheets of note paper in pads of 100 sheets each and 500 envelopes to match;the quality, size, colour, printing etc., to be the same as supplied before, vide my order No.974-17/25, dated 26th March 1947. A sample is also attached. N j y') 2. The Government of India are being requested to send you the necessary export permit. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain MMAGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER I [N,B % 1 his is an OHIO I SAL MESSAGE^ sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with lice same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and fo nrialitits^it'-^wo'rd ed and signed as if it had been so despatched,] \ i \ \ y) From POLITICAL, fLvHhAIN • To RJiPiiATiiDs LiiPGU, BAHRAIN. FOREIGN, NEW DELHI. Datedth* 15th Jiinuary, #3. s An order for 1000 sheets of note paper and 500 envelopes has been placed with Messrs.Thacker &amp; Co.,Ltd Rampart Row, Bombay, for this Agency. Request Government of India be asked to issue the necessary export oernit to the fi2T4 direct. = POLITICAL = The Issue of the above has been authorised. assistant Political Agent, a Bahi a in.\ V 4 To - FOREIGN, New Delhi. Repeated POLITICAL, Bahrain. No. 146-30/36. Bahrain 17th January, 1948. i ^ Reference Express Letter No. 147'Q7/£' dated 15th January, 1948 from Political Agent, Bahrain. Stationery from Thackers, Bombay. 2. I recommend. = BEPGU =Ho. 733 -17/25. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHhAIN To 4th March, 1948 Messrs. Thackef* A Co., Ltd., Rampart Row, Bombay. Dear Sirs, I enclose herewith a bank draft for Bs.54/- in full settlement of your bill No.8037 dated 5th February 1948. Kindly acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainNo. /Tjy.-17/25 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN 4th March, 1948 ■% • To The Manager, Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you will kindly issue a draft for Ics.54/- on your Bombay office in favour o ( f Messrs. Thacker A Co., Ltd. Tne chargesaay please be debited to this Agency Treasury account under intimation to me. Yours faithfully for Politiclf‘Agent,Bahrain 4I &gt; COVEKNiViKNT OF INDIA, Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations. xtexxxxxxxx e r «■« i [iV, B ,—This is an 0R1G11S AL ME TRACE, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Foreign, New Delhi 3 Repgu, Bahrain. Eo % F.4l(5)-G/48. Reference Foreign express letter No.4l(5)yG/48 dated 16th February 1948. Stationery from Thackers Bombay. Bahrain express letter No.147-17/4 dited 16th January 1948 since received. Arrangements are being made for export permits as requested. Dated the ^ ^February 8 A £ .a* The issue of the above has been authorised. RESIDENCY RECEIPT No,...fl.P.. Date.. ... Assistant Secretary to the Govt, of India. DCFP—1107S&amp;P—(G-1254)—24-6-31—4,0J,000.k /i, POLITICAL AGS'JCY, BAHRAIN, Tho 11th August 1148 Messrs* Thacker &amp; Co*Ltd., Rampart Row, Bombay. Dear Sirs, T should be glad if you would please supply this Agency, as early as possible, with three rubber stamps as per sample below. They should be despatched by air mail when ready. 2. The cost will be remitted to you on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, % &gt; For Politicafjj^Agent, Bahrain. No.3306-17/25 To« Messrs. Websters&gt; 44, Dover Street, London, W.l. Dear Sirs, I enclose herewith an exact replica of a page from my 'Visitors Book', and should be grateful if you would kindly sunply me, as early as possible, by air freight, a book bound in blue leather, containing 200 pages in thick art paper. The outer cover should show the words 'AGENCY, BAHRAIN'. These words and the edges should be gilt. 2. Your charges will be paid on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, % FOR POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. NNR - 5 ^I■M NAME ADDRESS -d) WEBSTERS A WEBSTER &amp; COMPY., PICCADILLY LTD. T. W. HOPPER L. E. POULTON STATIONERY ENGRAVING PRINTING SILVER AND LEATHER GOODS 1st September, 1948 ESTABLISHED 1780 TELEPHONE a TELEGRAMS REGENT 4411 TWH/ER 44, DOVER STREET. OFFICE OF THE BADMINTON PICCADILLY, LONDON, W.l. The Political Agent The Agency, Bahrain, Persian £ulf. Sir v/e have your order No3450 of August 25th for Visitors Book as the description given, with ruling and printing of leaves as the replica enclosed. You mention ’’Art paper” for the leaves and we think this is an error for all art paper is for printing work and, in fact impossible to write on, it has a polinhtfiurface. We therefore supply our usual paper for such books this having a proper writing surface. It should be ready for dispatch in about fourteen days time but we cannot be certain as special work has to be used in the binding for a hot climate.No. 4602-17/26 To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHJ AIN, The lit i September 1948. Messrs. Dear Sirs, A. Webster A Co.Piccadilly Ltd., 44, Dover Street, Piccadilly, London, W.l. b' With reference to'your letter No.TWH/ER, it is confirmed that we only want ordinary good quality paper. Yours faithfully, * FOE P OLITI CAL AGENT, BAHnAEN.No. -17/25• Political Agency Bahrain. Dated the 20th September,1948. To The Eastern Bank Ltd.* Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you will kindly issue me a Bank dra r t for Rs. 14/12 in favour of Messrs.Thacker &amp; Co.Ltd., Bombay, debiting the cost to this Agency Foreign Office Account under intimation to this office. Yours faithfully, w olitical Agent, Bahrain.No. 47/7 -17/25. Political Agency, To Bahrain. Dated the 23rd Sent.1948. si Messrs Thacker &amp; Co.Ltd., Bombay. Dear Sirs, Please refer to your Advice Note No.2072 dated the 30th August, 1948. 2. A Bank draft No.93938 dated the 22nd September 1948 for Rs. 14/12 is enclosed herewith in full settlement of your above mentioned bill. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. W'VJ-'g' H.B.M’s POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN (Persian Gulf), 25th September, 1948. To 0 Messrs. Philip Rees, Ltd., Stationers, Pall Mall, London, S.W.l. Dear Sirs, Kindly quote by ’AIR MAIL’ for the supply to me of invitation and 'AT HOME' cards worded as shown in the enclosed drafts. While doing so, please send a proof of each. They should be about the size of the paper 'A' also enclosed. Envelopes to fit will also be re quired . 2. Could you also please let me know what would be ~*V tL* 'S' the cost of an embossed crest (of which I would supply the die). 3. I also enclose a Christmas Card. Would you also quote for the supply of it with the address amended, the date omitted, and the crest in green. The ribbon should be red and bli Yours faithfully, (C.J. PELLY) fy K.B.M* s Political Agent, Bahrain.- is''1 ■■mH STATIONERY ENGRAVING PRINTING SILVER AND LEATHER GOODS TWH/SR OFFICE OF THE BADMINTON WEBSTERS A. WEBSTER &amp; COMFY., PICCADILLY LTD T. VV. HOPPER L. E. POULTON © 14th September, 1948. ESTABLISHED 1780 The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain, Pursian Gulf. Dear Sir, TELEPHONE &amp; TELEGRAMS REGENT 4411 44, DOVER STREET. PICCADILLY, LONDON, W.1 5^ We refer to your order No.3450 25/8/48, for Visitors book: and report that the book will be ready for posting by Air next week. As you refer to payment we enclose our account as requested, if payment can be made at once it will facilitate clearance by exchange control here, or if not made at once will you kindly let us know by what method payment will be made i.e. on what bank etc. It will help us if we can have this information before actually dispatching the book.—/o- to A'WEBSTER &amp; COMPANY T. W. HOPPER Stationery Printing Engraving Publishing Silver, Fancy Leather Goods (PICCADILLY) Ltd. Established 1780 L. E. POULTON Reference 1241-48 link 44 • DOVER STREET LONDON • W • I Telephone &amp; Telegrams : Regent 4411 Badminton Publications Game Books Hunting Journals Sporting Records 10 % CHARGED ON ALL OVERDUE ACCOUNTS ,i 3 / ? // 5Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 26th Sept.1948. The Ka stern Bank I.td., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be grateful you will kindly Issue me a Bank draft for £ 9/ll/3 in favour of Messrs.Websters 44,Dover Street, London W.l., by debiting the amount to this Agency Foreign Office Account under iutimation to th5s office. No. LflS'l -17/25. To Yours faithfully, Political Agfent; Bahrainzg No . 47 /25 . POLITICAL AOESCS, BAHRAIN, The 30th Septe.nber, 1948# To Messrs* A. Webster &amp; Company, 44, Dover Street, LONDON. W.l Dear Sirs, I forward herewith a Bank Draft for £.9-11-3 (Pounds Nine, Shillings eleven and pence three only) in sottlement of your bill No.47/376 dated September i948 - Yours faithfully,^31 -17/26 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 23rd October, 1948 To Messrs. A. Webster &amp; Co., Picadilly Ltd., 44, Dover Street, Picadilly, London, W.l. Dear Sirs, I regret that a mistake was made when order ing the Visitors Book received from you. You should have been asked to have the following letters printed on the face of the book: of the existing words on the cover of the book (which is returned herewith) will you please have the word THE stamped on the cover before AGENCY, BAHRAIN? It would, of course, be preferable if the present wording could be erased and the words THE AGENCY, BAHRAIN substituted as shown above. Please return the book by 'AIR MAIL* . THE AGENCY BAHRAIN 2 If it is not possible to do this now instead Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain $a/,. ^ $ 5o/3 &gt;/e beg to advice that the above Case have been shippd -ed to you per S.S.'BAM0RA'V.352. We enclose herewith a Bill of Lading No.2., receipt oi which please acknowledge. i(Ori2* nals sent to Residency on 5-1-49 under PL-3-17/25. Btt) ^ No.743/3/42 British Consulate-General, ahwaz. Khorranshahr, dated 13th December, 1943, Dear Agency, We have expended Rials 405/- as under: Shinping Charges on one case stationery ex s.s.Banora V.352- 405^00 Total 405-00 We should be glad if you woulc refund the above sum in due course. The following documents are enclosed herev/ith. Debit Note dated 14-11-42 with a cony of bill of lading. Yours ever, Consulate-General. The Political Agency, Bahrain. Seal ConsulateNo.3-17/25 BAIffiAIN, The 5th January, 1949. to: - The undermentioned paper? are forvarded The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, for favour of direct disposal. Letter no. 743/3/42 dated the 13th Decern er 1948 from the British Consulate- General, Ahwaz, with enclosures, in oripinal. MNR Cony to the Consulate General, Briti?h Consulate, , Ahwaz, Khorramshahr, «ith ref rence to HCU+ &amp;Q 0 r“\ettt-T K0.743/3/42 dated the 13th Dec.1948.0 ($) No. ^ 7 -17/25. To .0' Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the March, 1949. The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you nill kindly issue aae a Bank draft for f 3/16/f. in favour of Messrs.A.Webster * Company 44 Dover Street, London, by debiting the amount to this A^eno Foreign Office Account under Intimation to this office. Yours faithfully, PoZ i ti ca-^ Jigent, Bah)‘a ;.n.No. bSP -17/25. €&gt; 7l Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 19th March,1949. To Messrs. A. Webster &lt;* Company Ltd., 44 Dover Street London W.l. Dear Sirs, I enclose herewith a Bank draft No.101857 dated the 16th March 1949 for £ 3-16-6 in full settlement of your bill No,P/343 dated 10th Marcl 1949. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, , : t?) Political Agent, ' Bahrain.( i l No. 3/7 - 0112 72 British Agency, Shar jah• The 23rd March 1949. Dear Agency, We shall he grateful if you will kindly supply us the rubber stamps with the following inscriptions (one of each) for the use of our office and of the quarantine Medical Officer: 1 # ” No. Dated: Valid for the journey to 2 . No. Political Officer, Truci&amp;l Coast, Sharjah. Dated: Valid for the journey to within a period of one year from the date hereof (provided the passport is so long valid) No. Dated: Valid for any numbers of journeys within a period of one year from the date hereo. (provided the passport is so lorr valid) 4. ' Political Officer, Tmcial Coast, Sharjah ' » quarantine Medical Officer, Dutoi, Trucial Oman ' Yours ever, AGENCY . tyn The’ Agency, Bahrain t ^ \ *-*3ga&gt;* * ? .. .4r &lt; r No.817-17/25 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 30th iMarch 1949 To Messrs. Thacker &amp; Co. Ltd., Rampart Row, Bombay. Dear Sirs, I should be glad if you would please supply this Agency, as early as possible, with five rubber stamps as per sample below. They should be despatched by sea mail when ready. * 2. The cost will be remitted to you on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, °/c FOR POLITICAL AGENT,BAHRAIN. 1. No. Dated: Valid for the journey to Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. A 2 . No. Dated: Valid for the journey to within a period of one year from the date hereof (provided the passport is so long valid). 3. No. Dated: Valid for any number of journeys to within a period of one year from the date hereof (provided the passport is so long valid). 4. Political Officer, Trucial Coest, Sharjah. 5. Quarantine Medical Officer, Dubai, Trucial Oman. ■KTTCmPRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS TO H.M. QUEEN MARY. 0 WS/MP GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED PRINTERS, PUBLISHERS AND STATIONERS TO THE SERVICES THE WELLINGTON PRESS * ALDERSHOT ' HANTS TELEPHONE ALDERSHOT 2 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS “POLDEN. ALDERSHOT' CHRISTMAS CARD AND DIARY DEPARTMENT 1st April, 1949 MANAIiAH, ^B atiraln. Dear Sir, We sriould esteem it a favour if you would let us know if you are interested in ttie above for the coming season. If so, we shall be delighted to send you a folder of styles specially manufactured for Embassies Consulates etc - Awaiting the favour of your reply. Yours faithfully, . GALS &amp; P0LD3N LIMITED. Christmas Card Manager.0 Ho. 1 &lt;^(-17/25 . POLITICAL AGENCjT, BAHRAIN. The 13th Anril, 1949. To The Christmas Card iluna^er* Jdassr? Gale &amp; Polden Llnited, The Wellington Press, Aldershot, v ants* Bngl&amp;n d.. Dear Sir, ! \ rSlV '' I aia in receipt of your letter ftS/itP of the 1st April, 194S, and should be glad if you would kindly arrange to send me a folder of styles of Christmas cards specially manufactured for Embassies, Consulates,etc. Yours faithfully, / FOK. POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KVA' Wo. ' M il7/2§. POLITICAL AGENCY, 3AHBAIN. The 26th April, 1949. © Dear British Agency* S* 'T We forwaro herewith five rubber stamps as required by you in your letter No*319»0?-12* dated the 23rd March* 1949. i YOURS SViiB* AGENCY./ vn /L yf4? PRIMTERS AND PUBLISHERS TO H.M. QUEEN MARY GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED PRINTERS, PUBLISHERS AND STATIONERS TO THE SERVICES THE WELLINGTON PRESS * ALDERSHOT * HANTS TELEPHONE ALDERSHOT 2 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS 'POLDEN, ALDERSHOT CHRISTMAS CARD AND DIARY DEPARTMENT WS/MP 27th April, 1949 Pollctical Ae ent » Political Agency, Bahrain. Dear Sir, ( 4 Tn reolv/to your letter of the 13th Instant reference 101 ''s/ 17/£5 . We have pleasure in enclosing fold . of* Christmas CaPTs'specially prepared, from wnich we nop to be favoured with your esteemed order. With regard to the prices, your cards wiU not be subject to Purchase Tax, therefore the Jed prices a ^ substantially reduced. The cards priced a / j? will be 5/9d per dozen and the other prices . ro a a. We should greatly appreciate your order by Air Mail, so that we can get the work in hand and ensure d.Uve y in good time for* your requirements. Assuring you of our best services, Yours f e.ithfully , GAL'S &amp; BOLD'S!! LIMITSD. Christmas Card Manager. to77 AIR MAIL . H.B.M's POLITICAL AGENCY Bahrain (Persian Gulf) 2nd June, 1949. To The Christmas Card Manager, Messrs. Gale &amp; Polden Limited, The Wellington Press, Aldershot, Hants, England. Dear Sir, Reference your letter WS/MP, dated the 27th April, 1949. cimen E9 of your folder. The arms and ribbon should be the same as those shown thereon while in the right hand corner instead of 'British Embassy, Washington, D.C. n there should be 'H.B.M's Political Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf'. The legend on the fourth page 'All good wishes for Christmas and the New Year from' should be exactly similar to that shown in your specimen. The photograph of which the negative and one print is enclosed should be enlarged and should be on the fifth page as is the photograph of the British Embassy, Washington, in your specimen. 3. Please acknowledge by 'Air Mail* and confirm that you will be able to complete the order and despatch the cards here in good time for next Christmas. You should note that it may take over two months for the cards to reach here by sea mail so that they should be despatched not later than August next. *19r 2 Please supply 200 Christmas Cards as at spe Yours faithfully, H.B.M's^olitTca^ Agent Bahrain.No, Dated» Valid for che journey to... Politic.'! 1 Off’cer, Trucial Coast, SLarjali t ( / No, Dated i Valid for the journey to whith’ i a period of one year from the date hereof &lt; provided the passport is so lo valid No, Dated i 'V alid for any numlber of journeyi ^ 'whithin a period of ov^rrrr from the date hereof ( p’X/jded the passport is so loner valid). S Political Officer, Trucial Coait, Sharjah. Qnftrantir.e Medical Officer Dubai, •* r ’ 1 cial Oman. /No. If 0 7 -17/25 POLmCAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 15th June, 1949. To The Manager, The Eastern Bank Ltd., BAHRAIN # Dear Sir, I shall he grateful if you will kindly Issue me a Bank Draft for Bs.20/8/- in favour of Messrs#Thacker &amp; Co# Ltd., Bombay, by debiting the cost to this Agency 1 s Foreign Office Account ** under intimation to this office. Yours faithfully, /S' flj^JOLITICAL AGfrNT, BAHRAIN. i ^ ^ m KYMHo.-17/25. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 22nd June, 1.949* ^ To Messrs. Thacker &amp; Co. Ltd., Rampart Rov?, BOMBAY . ^ Dear Sirs, Please refer to your bill No.B/l28 dated the 4th May, 1949. 2. I enclose herewith draft No.92669 dated ~ the 18th June, 1949 for Rs.20-8-0 (Rupees Twenty and annas eight only) drawn in your favour on the Eastern Bank Ltd., Bombay, in full settlement of bill referred to above. 3. Kindly acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, 'pr POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. KYM.GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED PRINTERS, PUBLISHERS AND STATIONERS TO THE SERVICES THE WELLINGTON PRESS * ALDERSHOT ’ HANTS TELEPHONE ALDERSHOT 2 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS ‘POLDEN, ALDERSHOT” CHRISTMAS CARD AND DIARY DEPARTMENT W3/MP . • 14tn June, 1949 . H.B.Ms Political Agency, BaHrain ' Persia n Gul f' Pear 3*r, .'79 We thank yon for your letter of the 2nd inst. reference 1411-17/25. We very much appreciate your order for 200 Christmas Cards, Vour i nstr-'ct!ons are q^ite clear and we have put in hand with a view to get the Cards manufactured and despatched by t/.e end of July. We are ma v ing the block from the prints you sent us and we are returning herewith the negative in caoe you need it. Assuring you of our best services. Yours faithfully, GAL3 &amp; POLDEN LIMITED. Christmas Card Manager. EftOAL 2^-Wo. / ^7-17/25. POLITICAL AGENCY, Bahrain, The 22nd June, 1949. i To The er The Eastern Bank Ltd*, 4 / j Dear f / ! J BAHRAIN* I shall be grateful if you will issue r, / \ me a Bank Draft for Rs*32-14-0 (Rupees Thirty-two ; \ andA annas fourteen only) favouring the Manager, Bombay Port Trust Books, Bombay, debiting cost thereof to this Agency Foreign Office Account, under advice.to me. / Yours faithfully, rl KYM 0k Ba To I (§) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 25th January, 1949« JuAfUt-y The Deputy Manager, Bombay Port Trust Docks, BOMBAY . Dear Sir, Please refer to your memorandum No.HK/296 dated the 16th May, 1949# 2, A draft No.92618 dated the 23rd June, 1949 for Es.32-14-0, drawn in favour of the Manager, Bombay Port Trust Docks, on the Eastern Bank Ltd., Bombay, is enclosed herewith, in full settlement. 3. Kindly acknowledge. Tours faithfully* for POLITICAL AGENT* BAHRAIN.mmALDERSHOT 2 (5 lines) Telegrams r POLDEM, ALDERSHOT A BOUGHT OF GALE &amp; POLDEN LTD THE MILITARY PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS WELLINGTON PRESS, ALDERSHOT fH.B.M's Political Agency. iLIrI Bahrain, 'v/ Persian Gulf. J i . L. No receipt recognised except on our author ised printed form. 91185 © L OUR REF. X359. July 5th 200 Christmas Cards - Specially Manufactured 0 th July,1949. £9 11 Per Foreign Office Bag. KINDLY ENCLOSE THIS INVOICE WHEN REMITTING 8 NET,Ko. -17/25. Dear Sirs, Political Agency, Bahrain* September 10, 1949. I forward herewith a bank draft Wo. 502761y(61/454) for £.9-11-8 in settlement of your bill 91185 of July 20 for 200 Christmas cards. Yours faithfully, H.G.Jakins. Political Agent. Messrs. Gale &amp; Polden Limited, The /ellington Press, Aldershot, Hants, England.&amp; Telephone No. V X \Y Bankers: THE EASTERN BANK LTD. BAHRAIN. Telegrams: ABDULNOOR BASTAKI ABBUINOOR M. BASTAKI (general cM.erc^an{s i BAHRAIN P. Gulf 29th August 1949. 194 11/41 H. B. M’s Political Agent. Bahrain. Dear Sir: ^Vtical Ac^&gt;, ( O' Mo l a I - SEP !3&lt;9 ) 1} V ' We offer you subject being unsold the following goods at a very compititive price and hope you will send your valuable orders for same. Swan Ink Blue Black in bottles of 40 oz. © 30/- per dozen. of 20 oz. 18/- per dozen. Parker Quink. in 4 oz bottles. © 10/8 per dozen. Awaiting your esteemed orders whx h 7/ill have our usual attention. We remain, Yours faithfully, Abdulnoor M. Bastaki pay' 1No. Political Agency, Bahrain, 10th December, 1949. Dear Dredge, I was grectly touched to receive the en closed Christmas Card fro.u the Ministry of Pensions but at the same time could not help reflecting that as it is presumably prepared at the expense of the Treasury, there is doubtless no objection to this Agency's card being paid for from the same source. Could you kindly confirm this? If you are not able to do so, perhaps Sir Rupert would agree to make a reference to the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely, A.L.A. Dredge, Esq., The Residency, Jufair.%PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN S) 7 13th December 1949. Please refer to your letter No. 531 of December 49th about Christmas cards. 2. Sir Rupert made inquiries from various sources in cluding Jeddah regarding the payment for Christmas cards V but was told that^F.O. would not meet the cost of Christmas cards sent out personally. 3* We are however addressing the F.C* unofficially to get this point confirmed. Your Christmas card and envelope are enclosed C•J. Pelly) Esq. O.B.E.j Political Agent, BAHRAIN.% l V W3/PB. PRINTERS, PUBLISHERS AND STATIONERS TO THE SERVICES THE WELLINGTON PRESS • ALDERSHOT • HANTS TELEPHONE ALDERSHOT 2 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS “POLDEN, ALDERSHOT” CHRISTMAS CARD AND DIARY DEPARTMENT January 26th 1950 H.3.M. Political Agent, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir, ✓S'7* We have pleasure in enclosing the original photograph lent, to us for reproducing in your Christmas Card for 1949. We hope it will reach you safely, and that the cards gave you every satisfaction. Your order for next season will be greatly appreciated. May we suggest you let us know your requirements as early as possible? The earlier v/e have your order, the better attention we can give to it, and ensure that you have prompt delivery. Assuring you of our best services. Yours faithfully, GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED. oj\ i7P' ,1 w: STATEMENT PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS TO H.M.QUEEN MARY. p* . ^ a ..HOU950 Ct^..e*vfc..,. ^^^/&gt;r5vv»v..» \ ■9'K^v^^v- GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED PRINTERS, PUBLISHERS AND STATIONERS TO THE SERVICES THE WELLINGTON PRESS, ALDERSHOT, HANTS TELEPHONE ALDERSHOT 2 (y LINES) TELEGRAMS POLDEN ALDERSHOT I.' Kindly return tnis statement when remitting 195... Terms: Monthly Net Cash To A/C Rendered w To Goods Q. 00 SS J % / . ALDERSHOT a 10888 Receivedfrom date ‘ With Compliments and thanks for GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED. \lv PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS TO H M. QUEEN MARY. rt 6 ] STATEMENT 6 3«s . HU* 1950 'i^rvC I .^'&lt;*^$rcw?!V..i ? f A • GALE &amp; POLDEN LIMITED PRINTERS, PUBLISHERS AND STATIONERS TO THE SERVICES THE WELLINGTON PRESS, ALDERSHOT, HANTS TELEPHONE ALDERSHOT 2 (y LINES) TELEGRAMS POLDEN ALDERSHOT Folio Kindly return tnis statement when remitting .&lt; Terms: Monthly Net Cash ^■90 To AjC Rendered To Goods r\ U V 28ailS WOTDWIJJ3W 8 ^ . .... . ./r 7^No. &lt;5? 17/25. Sirs, Political Agency, Bahrain, 20th September, I960. With reference to your invoice No.20088 of 11th July (Your reference X 371), I enclose herewith a bank draft for £8.19.2d. in full settlement and should be glad to receive your official receipt in due course. I am lirs, Your obedient servant, J.B.Hartley, for Political Agent. Messrs.Gale &amp; Polden Ltd., Aldershot, Hants.XO.0&lt;f7-\7/26 Political Agency, , Bahrain 20th September, I960* Sir, I should be glad if you will let me have a sterling draft on London in favour of Messrs.Gale &amp; Polden Ltd*, Aldershot, Hants, for £8-19-2d* 2* the cost of the above draft should be debited to this Agency* s , *Agency Funds Account” with you, under advice to me as to the rupee equivalent debited. Sir, Your obedient servant, J.£*Hartley f for Political Agent. The Manager, The British Bank of Iran &amp; the Middle East, Bahrain.Please order early A Selection of Christmas Cards specially designed and produced for the Diplomatic Corps and the Consular Service BY GALE &amp; POLDEN LTD THE WELLINGTON PRESS, ALDERSHOT KINDLY RETURN SPECIMENS WITH CARD SELECTED CLEARLY INDICATEDOFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR THE UNITED KINGDOM WELLINGTON, N. Z. With Best Wishes for Christmas and the New Year from Ministry of Df.ffnceWith Every Good Wish for Christmas and the New Year from British Consulate-General New YorkThe Compliments of the Season and All Good IVishes fromHP*Ministry of Df.ff.nce With Best Wishes for Christmas and the New Year from—- CL/ III §ood Wishes or Gfiristmas and the A ew -dear l r fromPrices NOT including Purchase Tax Please order early SPECIMEN E5 250 500 1000 (PER DOZEN) Crest embossed in Gold OR single colour only 41- 3/6 3 Crest embossed in Gold and one colour 4/6 4/- 3/6 Crest embossed in Gold and two colours 5/- 4/6 4/- SPECIMENS El and E3 Crest embossed in Gold OR single colour only Crest embossed in Gold and one colour Crest embossed in Gold and two colours SPECIMENS E2, E4 and E6 Crest embossed in Gold OR single colour only Crest embossed in Gold and one colour Crest embossed in Gold and two colours 250 500 1000 (PER DOZEN) 9h 6/6 5/9 9/6 7/- 6/3 10/- 7/6 6/9 250 500 1000 (PER DOZEN) 9/6 7/- 6/- 10/- 7/6 6/6 10/6 8/- 7/- EACH CARD IS INSERTED IN A PLAIN ENVELOPE Extras ADDRESS DIE. If embossed on cover (as specimens E2, E3 and E4) an extra charge of 9d. per dozen will be made. No extra charge will be made for printing address on greetings page (as Specimens El and E5.) REPRODUCTION IN COLOUR. Reproductions of non-copyright original paintings can be made in any suitable card. Rates will be quoted on receipt of full particulars. Style These are samples of dummy cards, specially prepared, and merely intended to show designs and suggest ideas to our customers. Any alteration in crest, ribbon, wording or style of type can be made to suit customers’ wishes without extra charge. Illustrations Illustrations appearing in sample cards are to show style of reproduction only and will not be reproduced on orders unless specially requested. Non-Sterling Areas In order to avoid delay in the execution of orders owing to Exchange Control Regulations, please state the method to be employed when effecting payment. If the account will be settled from a sterling account held in this Country, it will be necessary for us to obtain permission from the Bank of England to waive receipt of Foreign Currency. Alternatively your local bankers could be instructed to forward a sterling draft drawn on an authorised account in London. BY APPOINTMENT PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS TO H.M. QUEEN MARY A Selection of Christmas Cards specially designed and produced for the Diplomatic Corps and the Consular Service BY GALE &amp; POLDEN LTD THE WELLINGTON PRESS, ALDERSHOT NO CHARGE will be made for making and printing one single colour block when a minimum quantity of 500 cards is ordered, provided the size of the block does not exceed 14 superficial square inches. Smaller quantities than those shown cannot be charged at the same rate REPEAT ORDERS WILL BE TREATED AS NEW ORDERS AND CHARGED AT THE RATE SHOWN FOR THE REQUIRED QUANTITY. Delivery All orders are executed in strict rotation and orders should be placed as early as possible. We can accept no responsibility for late delivery due to postal or other delays after goods have been despatched. KINDLY RETURN SPECIMENS WITH CARD SELECTED CLEARLY INDICATEDStyle These are samples of dummy cards, specially prepared, and merely intended to show designs and suggest ideas to our customers. Any alteration in crest, ribbon, wording or style of type can be made to suit customers’ wishes without extra charge. Illustrations appearing in sample cards are to show style of reproduction only and will not be reproduced on orders unless specially requested. In order to avoid delay in the execution of orders owing to Exchange Control Regulations, please state the method to be employed when effecting payment. If the account will be settled from a sterling account held in this Country, it will be necessary for us to obtain permission from the Bank of England to waive receipt of Foreign Currency. Alternatively your local bankers could be instructed to forward a sterling draft drawn on an authorised account in London. All orders are executed in strict rotation and orders should be placed as early as possible. We can accept no responsibility for late delivery due to postal or other delays after goods have been despatched. Illustrations AreasB.M.M. (G) AND ADM. STAFF, GREECE With Every Good Wish for Christmas and the New Year FromWith Best Wishes for Christmas and the New Year fromThe Compliments of the Season and All Good Wishes from BRITISH CONSULATE BAHIA, BRAZILWLIJAN KOKHOKAN WITH THIS SEASON’S GRKRTINGS ANH AT,I. GOOD WISHES FOR THE COMING YEAR FROM PKOVINCKPrice List including Purchase Tax SPECIMEN E10 250 500 1000 (PER DOZEN) Crest embossed in Gold OR single colour only 5/- 4/6 4/- Crest embossed in Gold and one colour 5/9 5/3 4/9 Crest embossed in Gold and two colours 6/6 6/- 5/6 SPECIMENS E9 and E12 250 500 1000 (PER DOZEN) Crest embossed in Gold OR single colour only 12/- 8/6 7/6 Crest embossed in Gold and one colour 12/9 9/3 8/3 Crest embossed in Gold and two colours 13/6 10/- 91- SPECIMENS Ell, E13 and E14 250 500 1000 (PER DOZEN) Crest embossed in Gold OR single colour only 12/6 91- S/- Crest embossed in Gold and one colour 13/3 9/9 8/9 Crest embossed in Gold and two colours 14/- 10/6 9/6 EACH CARD IS INSERTED IN A PLAIN ENVELOPE Extras ADDRESS DIE. If stamped on cover in addition to crest an extra charge of 1/- per dozen will be made. REPRODUCTION IN COLOUR. An extra charge of 1/6 per dozen will be made for printing insets in colour. Cost of colour blocks extra. Quotation will be sent on receipt of full particulars. NO CHARGE will be made for making and printing one block when a minimum quantity of 500 cards is ordered, providing the size of the block does not exceed 14 superficial square inches. Smaller quantities than those shown cannot be charged at the same rate REPEAT ORDERS WILL BE TREATED AS NEW ORDERS AND CHARGED AT THE RATE SHOWN FOR THE REQUIRED QUANTITY Illustrations Illustrations appearing in sample cards are to show style of reproduction only and will not be reproduced on orders unless specially requested. Reproductions in colour Any non-copyright coloured original, can be reproduced facsimile in colours on the inset of any of these cards. Our artists can prepare coloured originals for reproduction from rough sketches and details supplied by customer. Style These are samples of dummy cards, specially prepared, and merely intended to show designs and suggest ideas to our customers. Any alteration in crest, ribbon, wording or style of type can be made to suit customers’ wishes without extra charge. Delivery All orders are executed in strict rotation and orders should be placed as early as possible. We can accept no responsibility for late delivery due to postal or other delays after goods are dispatched. Please order early PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS TO H.M. QUEEN MARY A Selection of Christmas Cards specially designed and produced BY GALE &amp; POLDEN LTD WELLINGTON PRESS, ALDERSHOT KINDLY RETURN SPECIMENS WITH CARD SELECTED CLEARLY INDICATEDiyasiaiial Illustrations Illustrations appearing in sample cards are to show style of reproduction only and will not be reproduced on orders unless specially requested. Reproductions in colour Any non-copyright coloured original, can be reproduced facsimile in colours on the inset of any of these cards. Our artists can prepare coloured originals for reproduction from rough sketches and details supplied by customer. Style These are samples of dummy cards, specially prepared, and merely intended to show designs and suggest ideas to our customers. Any alteration in crest, ribbon, wording or style of type can be made to suit customers’ wishes without extra charge. Delivery All orders are executed in strict rotation and orders should be placed as early as possible. We can accept no responsibility for late delivery due to postal or other delays after goods are dispatched.We should very shortly v/ant a new Visitors' Book. I think a replica of the old one will do perfectly well though it should he bound ip blue leather as the red fades so quickly - with the words'Agency, Bahrain' stamped on the cover - no arms. It should be ordered from Websters, 44, Dover Street, London, W.l. An exact replica of a page should be made by drawing lines on a paper and typing the headings and sent with the letter. I would like to see the draft. The number of pages should be specified and should be the same as in the old book. Edges should be guilt. ltd. C.J.P. 16-8-48. • / %</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000169_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1626</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000169</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1626</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/25 Stationery purchased from firms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T18:05:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (185 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 187; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-66; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists largely of correspondence concerning stationery supplied to the Political Agency, Bahrain. Items ordered include rubber stamps, notepaper, envelopes, and printed forms. Much of the correspondence relates to the details of orders and the granting of export permits (from the Government of India) for those orders. Correspondents include the following: the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah; the Times Printing and Publishing Company Ltd; Thacker and Company, Bombay (booksellers, publishers, stationers and printers); the British Consulate, Khorramshahr; Gale and Polden Limited (printers, publishers and stationers).In addition to correspondence the file includes two folders (requested from Gale and Polden by the Political Agent) of specimens of Christmas cards produced for embassies, consulates, and other diplomatic missions, as well as colonial protectorates. In a letter, dated 2 June 1949 and addressed to the Christmas Card Manager at Gale and Polden (folio 105), the Political Agent requests 200 Christmas cards, similar in style to the card for the British Embassy, Washington DC, which features in one of the specimen folders. The file contains a photograph (and its negative) of the Political Agency, Bahrain. In the aforementioned letter, the Political Agent specifies that this photograph should be included on the Christmas card.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Times Printing and Publishing Co Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Thacker and Company Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>A Webster and Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gale and Polden Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Christmas cards</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Khorramshahr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Stationery</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000169#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>