<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:58:27.693Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CCHFnjENTIAL . D.O.No.G/ (5'0. l$ISl ■r«st Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate I BU8WJRF RF SiOUH-. imscatf 4th July 1923. I 0 ''- ^-7- 3- f Please refer to your confidential demi-official letter NO.700-S dated 22nd June 1932. 2# The only coimnent of note that I have is that Alhan states in his opening paragraph of instructions to R.S^ Duli Chand that he is entirely responsible for the finances of the State• 2. During his absence should anyone attempt to / embezzle money or defraud the State it seems arguable, by the same token,, that Alban accepts the responsibility, 4. Alban however seemed confident that any such contingency was practically impossible there being so many people each watching the other* His orders seem to be autocratically definite and at the same time to provide for contingencies* 6. XjEVIES, As regards the Muscat Infantry orders for the interior economy of the Corps are clear* At the same time the Subedar Major, in case of neaessity, has orders to report to me • 7• Incidentally, I have heard quietly since I have been back that the Corps is thoroughly discontented and dis gruntled - chiefly through being slave driven on the cons truction of the new Customs jetty and repairs to the Sultan's (Palace) landing stage* Stories have reached me of fatigue parties being at it not only all day but at night also - as well as being on guard duty &amp;c* Che Hobble Lieutenant-Colonel T. C. Fowle, C.B.E*, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B TJ S H I RE- 2— x / ^' 5 9» There was a slight ,t eme4tte tt I hear, just before I returned, when several N^C.Os. and men ^downed tools H in protest. I gather that the ring leaders were sacked and other punishments dealt out. 10. I met two Mekranis who boarded the mail boat that I arrived in. Both were askaris that I knew and I thought they were leave men* They told me, however, that they had cut their names being 'thoroughly fed up with the reduced pay and being used as coolies morning,noon and night 1 *♦ They told me that the whole Corps would do the same to-morrow if only they could get work elsewhere* ll* What truth there is in their statement I do^t know but there seems a good deal from what I ha to gathered on shore in these few days. !£♦ The I.us. are naturally reticent on the subject - not wanting to displease the higher authorities ~ or to let the cat out of the bag. 13. 1 am somewhat surprised that Alban made no mention of any of this trouble to me before leaving. 14. Most of the men are on leave now, including two fellows ndao were in hospital for over two months badly injured during blasting operations and subsequently badly treated by Dr* Ghei. I do not therefore anticipate any active trouble and if such were brewing I think one 03^ other of my friends in the Corps would quietly put me wise. i iC0KFIDEMTIA1. ^ j I if W of 193 3. PoXitic&amp;l Agency &amp; tuB.M's Consulate, poiitical Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat* To The Hon^le the Political Reeiaent in the Persian Gulf, Buehire* Sir I have the honour to report that on the 20th instant Saiyid iiadir bin Jj'aisal, brother of His Highness the ex-Sultan Taimur and uncle of the present Sultan requested an interview with me# me a grievance concerning his reduction in salary* ne had previously mentionea the matter casually to me in the course of a polite call shortly alter my return from leave* aban 1337 (2fld May 1S19) issued to him by his brother Taimur assigning him and his heirs in perpetuo the monthly sum of 0 1000* Later, on the conversion of dollar sala ries to payment in rupees this sum was fixed at Es 2500/- by a subsequent amendment dated 10th Jamada el &amp;khar 1338 (2nd March 1920J, signed by Saiyid Taimur* 4«. On the succession of Saiyid Said to the Sultanate he endorsed his father's sanad in writing on the 3rd Shawwal 1350 (11th February 1932). 5o With effect from 1st July 1933, in accordance with the general scheme for effecting economies and re ductions in the State Budget, proportionate reductions were introduced in the salaries of all those borne on the Muscat Civil List* In the case of Saiyid isiadir this reduction The object of his interview was to lay before Saiyid .Nadir produced a sanad dated 1st Sha--2- U{ 7 v amounted to Es 820/-. ?• Saiyid Hadir f s present contention is tiaat this reduction in iiis salary is in direct contravention to the terms of his sanad® he sought my assistance and intervention in the matter &gt; more than hinting that I should write to the Council of Regency and order full payment to be made to him» 8» I explained to him, much on the lines of Mr® Vingate f B reply to the ex-Sultan when discussing this same matter (vide this office confidential jao»150 dated 28th January 1921 to the address of the Hon^le the Political Resident) that the matter was not one in which I could in terfere as the matter was not the concern of my Government® 9® I pointed out to him that if he felt he had a grievance (and strictly in the terms of the sanad he would certainly appear to have a justifiable cause of complaint) he should apply to the Council of Kegehcy, but that I did not think they were empowered to set aside His Highness's orders® iO® Saiyid Badir,however, does not intend to apply to the Council, nor has he done so hitherto® He stated that he would decline to draw his salary in future and that under the circumstances he could not continue to live in Muscat® 12® To this I replied that it was purely a matter of his own choice whether he drew his salary or not, and that as regards leaving Muscat it was a matter between himself and the Council according to His Highness's orders® 13® I very strongly advised Saiyid Sadir not to do anything which could and would be misrepresented by his detractors, but to await His Highness^ return patiently and as became a man of his position® Thereafter he could maice full representation to the Sultan® I am of the ppinion, which I expressed to Saiyid Uadir, that His Highness forgot the existence of the above quoted sanad when contemplating reductions in salaries® Saiyid Kadir thanked me for my advice which he said he would abide by and told me that he certainly did not3 contemplate doing anytning foolish but would probably retire to Sib or some Batineh port till His Highness^ return. local respect and has intimate connections with Oman, I do not anticipate that he will commit any oirert act or lay him self open to any charge rendering himself liable to the forfeiture of his sanad* rt for information only M , of Saiyid ifadir's call on me and of the ooject of his visit. They will tnus be in possession of the facts, though I learn privately from one of the mem bers, that they have already heard of his proposal to refuse his salary in future. 16. Although Saiyid jsaair commands considerable 17. I am informing the Council of Regency, however^ 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Political ^gent and H, , 1, Muscat.acr U 'j, '-K. •■o c. ■, IXo.K/ i+l of 1933. m Political Agency h H.B.M's Consulate,Muscat. Recess Office, Killarney Hotel, Gamp, Karachi, 31st August 1933. LBUSHIR? ^ESIDSNCY. To 1 fc V- toi$ n • gonwjewiXL ttoom. The Hon 1 hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire# f A \ - \\ Memorandum# In continuation of my memorandum No. 17^17/697 dated 7th June 1933 I enclose herewith statements showing revenue and expenditure for 6 months ending 30th June 1933. Statements showing the progress of loans and debts for the quarter ending 30th June 1933 and the cash balance of the S&gt;fiate Treasury as it stood on 1st July are also enclosed. Revenue. 2. Column 5, actual collections for 6 months, shows Rs.337268/-. Column 6, proportionate estimate for the same period shows Hs.320750. There is therefore a surplus of Rs.16518. Expenditure. 3, Column 5, actual expenditure for 6 months shows Rs.331336/11. Column 6^ proportionate expenditure for the same period shows Rs.308875/-. There is therefore an excess of Rs.22511/11 on the proportionate expenditure. Ac tuals. Actual revenue for the 6 months is Rs.337268/- Actual expenditure for -do- .Jl 331386/11— 4. Excess of revenue over expenditure 5881/5 Political Agent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul, Muscat. ^7 Major,MM ■M*' C0OTIDE1ITIAL. lit I (ik No. C/ 5106' of 191 Feom V Major G, S. U. Bremner, M,C,, To Political Agent and H. B. M.'s Consul, Muscat, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire# A m- hu 2://- S3 OOtiHOWTUi J£00(t0&amp; British Agency and Consulate. Muscat, the ^4th October /#33 Subject.- Complaint of Saiyid Nadir on reduction of his pay Sm, In continuation of my ]\ T o,C/l66 of 21st July last, I have the honour to submit the following further report on this subject, 2 * O n the 26th instant. Khan Bahadur Ahmad Shubailli, His Highness the Sultan's Secretary, who has returned from India on a short visit to Muscat, called on me. He said that he had been deputed by His Highness the ex-Sultan to consult me on certain matters# ^ . X ^ ne primary matter concerned a letter that Sir Saiyid Taimur had received from Saiyid Nadir concerning the reaucoion of the latter*s salary. This letter (written some two months ago) which K.B.Shuoailli read to me, was Most improperly worded and its whole tone had incurred the strong resentment of Sir Saiyid Taimur. The latter desired to w r ite a strong and suioaole reply to it, but before doing so wished to have my opinion as to the lines on which it should be w r itten. S. G. P. I.—247 P. A. &amp; H. B. M, Consul Muscat— 6-12-11. 500.Of) 5. I pointed out to K. B. Sliubailli, as I had pre viously made clear to Saiyid INTadir, that the question Was not one ^hich concerned fay Government, 'being purely a matter 'between His Highness and members of his family, 6. The Khan Bahadur however said that Sir Saiyid Taimur would much appreciate my personal advice. Having therefore made it clear beyond doubt that I spoke in a purel-u personal and private capacity and NOT with any official authority, I outlined w hat had taken j^lace at my interview with Saiyid ITadir in July last, and offered the following advice. 'j 7. Sir Saiyid Taimur should reply to his brother saying that he was pained and surprised to learn from his letter how devoid of any public spirit Saiyid Uadir was. Further that a man of his social status and in such affluent circumstances should have set an example to all others in the State by surrendering voluntarily 50% of his salary, instead of adopting his present attitude. y 8 « As regards the tone of the letter, and the rexerences therein to Saiyid Said^s bad faith, I considered Sir Saiyid Taimur fully able to deal with this himself without my advice. I have however pointed out to K.B.Shubailli the Weakness of the original sanad granted by Sir Saiyid Taimur to Saiyid ITadir in that whereas the sa,lary was granted in perpetuo tor loyalty and past good services, the sanad contained no proviso that the continuation of such pay ment would be subject to the continued loyalty and good conduct of the recipients in the future. ••hether Sir Saiyid Taimur win seek to have this defect remedied by the present Sultan is an open point. It ' ould be to Saiyidadvantage to do so. ^ ^ iave only had occasion to see Saiyid ITadir once since my return from recess, when he paid me a formal call and made no mention of the subject to me. He has spent/ Y spent the majority of the hot weather at Grhalla and with exception of the present letter to his brother has, I under stand, taken no further action about his allowances. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat,NEWFOUNDLAND ROYAL COMMISSION REPORT ASSISTANCE ON CONDITIONS SUSPENSION OF AUTONOMY Comprehensive, thorough, and immediate remedies to cure the distresses from which New foundland is suffering are made in the Report of the Royal Commission, issued last night; and a White Paper published simultaneously shows that his Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom are prepared to act upon the recommendations. In order to avert the financial collapse with which Newfoundland is threatened, the Com mission recommend the suspension of the exist ing form of government, and the vesting with I executive and legislative authority of a special I Government Commission, composed of three &gt; members drawn from Newfoundland and three ; from the United Kingdom, presided over by the Governor. ' The White Paper issued by Mr. J. H. Thomas I (Stationery Office, Cmd. 4479, price 2d.) con- I tains a memorandum by his Majesty's Govern- . ment in the United Kingdom and an exchange ; of telegrams between Mr. Thomas and Mr. 1 Alderdice, Prime Minister of Newfoundland. 1 Mr. Alderdice, on November 15, asked whether Mr. Thomas could give any indication of the attitude of his Government which would assistv Telegram From To Ho 1106 Dated the 9th D e ceinber 1933 IMPORTANT Enclair, Colpnel Fowle, Bushire. Cox &lt;Sc King^s Agent, Karachi. Grateful if you would send by to-morrow's mail copy of London Times of November 22nd to Politi cal Agent, Muscat. Matter urgent. -POWLE-35/137 Telegram Enclair. From Colonel Fowle, Bushire. To L|oyds Bank, Karachi. No 1107 Dated the 9th December 1933 IMPORTANT Urgent. Please wire when period for con- Tersion of Newfoundland Government Stock to Sterling Stock guaranteed by His Majesty's Government expire^, -FOWLE-vViH (v) G.^.Go Political Resident, iBushire Political Agent, Muscat, ^elegraw From To tfo ,1108o Dated the 9th December 1933 l- *~y&gt; A V§ Reference your memorandum N o. H /42 of 31^t August- HfuB cat Government £ 3,000 in Newfoundland Guaranteed Stock. 2, 'This investment was made without reference to me presumably by Albany I presume that Stock guaranteed only by Newfoundland Government. I suggest for consideration of Muscat Government whether they should^iot now take opportunity of converting existing stock into new Sterling stock guaranteed by His Majesty's Government, See page 15 London Times November SSnd. I am telegraphing Lloyds Karachi asking tfhen period for conversion expires and will telegraph you on receipt of reply, 3, Please wire your views,, 4, In case you dont take in ^imes I have wired Cox's Karachi to send you a copy by tomorrow's mail. - Resident - iz(. fs. /(&gt;*&gt;, ^ vo/.y?? : U t]/ Air Mail. Cnnfldertlal . T ).0. H o .190 S -3 of 1933. \r\ j The Hesider.cy, Btishire, 13th Becemher, 1933, ♦I On examining the Muscat State treasury Balance, the Hon'ble the Political Resident noticed the item £ 3,000/- (approx.) invested in Newfoundland Government Guaranteed Stocks. f&gt;, The Political Resident directs me to say that he ■presumes that the Investment was made after consultation with His Highness the Sultan, 'but as it was made without previous reference to him, and as the Sultan is at the moment in Phofar - quite inaccessible, he does not know the exact nature of the Stocks in which this money is Invested and how this InvestAent will stand in the lifcht of the recent collapse of the Newfoundland Government finances. An article published in the Tlmefi* of November PPnd contains the report of a Hoyal Commission which investigated the financial affairs of the Newfoundland Government. ^is Commission made certain recorarapndations for the assumption of responsibility of the nubile debt and offered the opportunity to holders of certain Newfoundland Guaranteed Stocks to exchange their existing bonds or stocks into a new Sterling stock, the offer to renaln open for a period of one month after the passing of the necessary legislation in the United Kingdom. 3. The situation therefore is this, ^e Sultan is ■-i inaccessible in Hhofar. We know that the Muscat State holds certain/ Captain '.G.IS.W. Alban, I .A., c/o Grindlay's Bank Ltd., Parliament Street, LONDON,certain Ffeirfcmndland Oovemcient Stock but not the exact nature of^he__Stpck. We do not know who, if anyone, holds the Suit an *8 Pbwer of Attorney, hut presume that you will I be the most likely person to hold it. Could you telesraTJh Inmedlately you receive this letter (the cost of telegram will of course be refunded to you)and let us know (a) do you still hold the Sultan's T'ower of Attorney, (b) the nature ©f the Stock, (c) does this Stock fall under the head of that f^tock for which the offer of an exchange into a new Sterling Stock lies open, following up the telegram with a more detailed answer to +he8e enquiries by the next Air Mail. 4. In the meantirae the Political Agent, Muscat, is being comnunicated with, but to save time this letter is also being sent to you. eje n' ^ t t|CONFIDENTIAL. No -1903-^ of 1933 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Major C.lS^TT.Brewner,H*C., ^oli^-ical Aper) i, Mub cat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s, British Consulate-i Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Beral-offi cial letter No., 190J2-S of 13th T )eceTnher 1933 to Captain TUO.JiMV,Alba Name and Date. London. Subject.35/137 k f ! \ &lt;\r&amp; Telegram G.T.G. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat. No 1183. • Dated the 29th December 1933. ^ v „ Your telegi 'rm 1631. , Co I concur. Advise Stte^t^ke necessary action and assist them to do so in any way you c«n. My telegram 1108, paragraph 2. Lloyds Bank, Karachi, feplied that ihLformation was not available. It may however now be. Suggest you get into touch with them. See also enclosure to my Printed Letter No 1903^of 13th instant. -RESIDENT-35/137. u 1 telegram G-«T.G. From Political Eesident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1 187o Dated the 29th Decemher 1933. j/j is i My telegram 1183. now received Following telggram/from Alhan referring to enclosiure to my Printed Letter No .1903-3,oegiiis. (a) Yes . ('b) Newfoundland Power Paper debentures 5t per cent B 1970 Government guaranteed. (c) Not convertible, no default either in Sinking Fund or interest. Market price 95/96. Ends. 2. Please inform State and let me know what action they are taking. - Resident -c ^ W ' .w ^/|57 /0&amp;3 elegrams; IIA, KARACHI. phone N? 329 5E MARK REPLY Stock Lloyds Bank Limited, - (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND^ Cox s 8c King's Bran^TK M c Leod Road, Post Box N9 27. Karachi. ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE MANAGER. January IJth, 193h» It, Col. T. 0. Powle, The Residency, Bushire Dear Sir, ! a n j Of'A ^ i i mi *** it With reference to our cable of the 11th December last aixd in reply to your enquiry regarding Newfoundland Government Stock we have now been informed that the position of the 5^ B.1970 Newfoundland Po?/er Paper Debentures remains unaltered and that these Debentures are not included in the Conversion scheme. We presume your enquiry was in this connection and trust the information now given is what you require. Surs faitJi^uJLly, Manager.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 61 -3 Of 1934. A-'' « O ) J ^ i , J /I I The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s ).f-r the information of His Highness the Sultan. 2. It is requested that he will kindly let the Political Eesident know what action the Sultan is taking. . British Consulate-G-eneral, BUSHIRB. 1 5' M 1 Dated...25tU.Ja.puarx.lgi34, Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident's telegram No.1187 of 29th December 1953. Description of Enclosure, (I Z! Name and Date. 1. Letter dated 29th Decernh 19«5o from Captain B.Gr.Al London. 2. Letter No.Stock dated 13 January 1934 from Lloyds Bank Ltd.,Karachi. n. n i Subject. er ban, Muscat Finances - Newfoundland Grovemment th Guaranteed Stocks. ■ ;■i ^ I X'' I ' &lt; \ No» of 1934» \Jy Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, 16th January 1934. .•V ^ ' « a. 1 ^ $ % ¥ f 6 * i / I !»,. From To ■'ti *w % Major C.E.U.Bremner, M.C., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat* The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subjects- Muscat Finances# Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith for your information (a) the Report on Muscat State Financial year 1933 (b) Budgets Estimates of the Muscat and Oman Govern ment for the year 1934 and (c) Explanatory Notes by the Financial Advisees assistant on these estimates, as handed to me by the Ministry of Finance. 2 # The foregoing have been prepared in the office of the Financial Adviser and my remarks and criticisms, in the form of a note, are attached herewith for your perusalo This note deals with each subject seriatim and calls for no other preliminary comment# 3^ I understand that a copy of these papers haB^ been submitted to His Highness the Sultan at Dhofar* I have the honour to §e. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat#fuC Note by the Political Agent, Muscat, on the Report of the, Muscat State Financial Year 1933# I (1) The Year's Working^ The actual balance of receipts over expenditure shows a credit of Hs 1,07,881 which is a credit increase of Rs 43,283 over that of the previous year's surplus. Though there are undoubtedly signs of a slight revival in trade and merchants are, generally speaking, less pessimistic, the above surplus balance can in no way be taken as a safe indication that the crisis is past* The fact has been lost sight of that whilst the local price of dates remained fairly high, the slump on the Bombay market later in the season in the price of Bishr dates, i*e» the inferior quality which is the staple export of the Ba- tinah, will react most unfavourably on the population of that area who are already reduced to a state of penurious beggary• 2* If the German market for Kasha is closed permanently it will undoubtedly have a most adverse effect locally till other adequate markets are found* This matter is having the attention of the State. 3» The importation of rice calls for no comment# 4. Allusions to revenues will be made under appropriate headso II. RETRENCHMENT AND ECONOMIES. 5. Though considerable retrenchment was introduced by His Highness the Sultan with effect from July there is still room for further reductions. This remark is particularly applicable to the Civil List, to salaries paid in the Finance Department and to expenditure on Gwadur Customs. These points will be referred to in dealing with the ensuing budget. 6. The disposal of the 'El Saidi' has undoubtedly 1undoubtedly relieved the State of an expensive incub^us. The State was fortunate however to receive even the moiety realised by her sale as the 'El Saidi' narrowly escaped being sunk in a gale en toute to Bombay. ) 7 0 The remark in the Report that the 'outlook of trade has been promising ,, is somewhat ^ optimistic and hardly barje's comparison with the opinions of the chief merchants. Their attitude is one of 'hope for improvement' based on the present slight trade revival® 8. The hopes evinced in this paragraph are fxm fervently shared by all concerned. 9 0 I am not prone to share the presumption of the assistant to the Financial Adviser concerning accumulated capital. Little of this commodity is visible in Muscat and the trading community are still very loathe to liquidate an; capital till there is a definite all round improvement in £ conditions. The remark concerning trade values is none the less correct. The situation may }&gt;e possibly attributable to (a) opportunity being taken by traders of prevailing poverty to buy up export produce cheapo (b) to decrease in import values. 10 o The decrease in imports is largely attributable to the amount of Japanese cloth and dry goods reaching the country. IV. ZAKAT. n . The remark that the 'collections • •. • • had been very satisfactory ' does not tally with the verbal report made by Rai Sahib Duli Chand to the Political iigent in November last when in lieu of Rs 60,000 anticipated only Hs 27,000 had been collected. The actual receipts none the less exceed the paper estimates for the year but, since they include large items of arrears due from 1932, it is fictitious to represent that the figures are the true revenues due for 1933.The figures given below present the situation as it actually is:- (a) Wilayat of Sohar (including Sohar, Soham, Shumaliyah and Liwa) Demands. Collection Deficito 1932 43,814) kS. in ) 42,000 * 1933 43,814) (b) Quriyat, Sib, Birka and Khabura. 1932) ) 46, 302 27,000 19,362 ♦ 1933) ♦ The Assistant to the Financial Adviser states that owing to farther collections in December the deficits under ' f (a) and (b)^ decreased to Rs 31,000 and Rs 13,000 respectively. Thus by quoting an estimate well within what is due for collection in any particular year, of which only a portion is ever collected, and adding to this portion any arrears due from past years that can be squeezed from the indigenous population, a fictitious 'bumper' surplus is produced for inspection purposes. The solvent condition of the State budget under these circumstances can never be taken as an indicator of the prosperity or otherwise of the population® At the present time the condition of the weaker to tribes, from whom only taxes are recoverable, is pitiable. Their improvident habits, coupled with the prevailing custom of mortgaging their date^ crops and other assets in advance to the shrewd trader, does not tend to ameliorate their condition or to release them from a steadily increasing- burden of debt. VI PUBLIC DEBTS. 16o The repayment in toto of the Government of India loan is most creditable but, apart from the payment of a trifling amount, no serious efforts appear to have been made to liquidate the debts due to local creditor^l.7\ creditor firms. Facts that lie outside the sphere of this note have largely contributed to this unfortunate situ ation. Though no allotment has been made in the Budget Estimates for 1934 for the purpose, it is hoped that e proper endeavour to settle these debts will be made, in the ensuing' year# VII INVESTMENTS. view of the situation in Newfoundland the investment of Rs 37,697 in any stock pertaining to that Colony was most unfortunate and unwise. The investment was made without the consultation or assent of either the Hon'ble the /Political Resident or the Political AgenU&amp;teps have been taken by the Political Agent to ascertain the best measures to be taken to avoid any financial loss to the State. The sum involved, would appear to be safe but cannot be deemed a readily realisable asset in case of emergency# VIII SUMMARY. v * I 0 ■ 17. The opening balance for 1933 of 3s 93,470 now quoted disdoses an excess of Hs 53,470 over the figure of Rs 40,000 furnished by the Financial Adviser at the com mencement of the year. fT In the absence of the Financial Adviser the discrefuacy cannot be explained# Assuming that the figures supplied are correct and that the credit forecast for 1934 is realised, it is not understood how it is anticipated that the State will be two lakhs in credit at the end of the present financial year. After deducting the local public debt of Hs 99,430 from the accepted credits, the balance would appear to be Hs 1,26,926 and not Rs 2,00,000# These lightly quoted approximations may look well on paper but are of little value in facing hard facts and actual figures.figures. -U A further iteci 'tiio.'t has 8.ppa,ren.'tXy escaped observation and has not been brought on to account is a sum of ffc 16,000 (figures quoted verbally by Rai Sahib Dull Chand) advanced to His Highness in connection with his Dhofar tour. The verbal ^statement that the Sultan^ orders are awaited on the subject appear to be no valid reason for the item not being anywhere included in the statement of the State's account, and would certainly not be acceptable to a business firm of Auditors. IX STAFF. On the departure on leave of the Financial Adviser, Rai Sahib Duli Chand applied verbally to this Agency to be addressed officially as Financial Adviser. As verbal instructions to the contrary had been left by Captain Alban the request could not be complied with. It has since been ascertained from His Highness that he has issued no authority for Rai Sahib Duli Chand to be considered as either Financial Adviser or Assistant to the Financial Adviser. The remaining retoarks under this heading call for no comment.U HOTS BY T-IE POLITIC.aX AGSIfT. KUSC/.T, OK THE MUSCAT BUDGET ESTIMATES AED 3JOTE. ; 3 THEREOK. Expenditure * 1 • Civil List . The estiiriistte of lis.2,31,180 under this head is excessive in the extreme, Inspite of previous retrenchments end of possible political repmrcussions, it would appear highly desinble for the nettle to be firmly grr sped nd a further saving effected by curtailing the allowances of the higher paid drones on the civil list. The decease of any one of these should automatically imply ^ proportionate decrease in the allowances p&lt;iid out. At present, ny such allowance c0tttcn±lex' is p&amp;l£ in toto to the 'Gu rdirn 1 ' of the offspring or to the next of kin of the decersed. The amount is either dissipated by the happy 'gu-rdian' for his own ends or contributes to strengthen the he bit of complete indolence in the next of kin. - The allowances paid to certain ladies of ■ the household, whose servints and animals are already paid for, is out of all proportion to similar allow ances in other countries. 1 G e n e r c 1 . ydm i n i e t r r t i o n . Interior Department. The pay of Shaikh Ebr-rhlm el Baruni * continues to be paid inspite of the fact that the latter is on indeiinite leave (no leave being due to him)suffering from periodical insmity. 3alim bin Pudhail boatman drrws a'pension' I I of 32/-p.m«Hi£ duties consist of producing a boat's^ crew, on an averrge twice yearly, to conduct the Mrjlis or other officials on ceremonial visits. His appointment is a sinecure. I 3^llFinance Department.3o Fine nee Dep a rtmentt Off i ce rmd Treasury . (i) It is worthy of comment to note thot whilst during the last two ye?rs every individual, whether offioirl, pensioner or drone, h&amp;s been subjected to a reduction in salary or allowrnces, owing to the drastic necessity for economy, R; i Sahib Duli Chi nd # s p.: y and emoluments have increased from i ; vs.350 in 1931 to i{s.550 plus .vs-iOO charge allov /i nee in I933-34, This 66;^ increase would hardly appear to be justified either in the light of the Staters finmcirl condition or in ecuity to others on pittrnce who hrve contributed to the betterment of these conditions by devoted service. This outstanding incident hrs given rise to much dissatisfaction nd recrimination. (ii) Audit . Ho comment xsxnKEJgiiSxry other than that provision has rlso been mrde (later) for pi.y of a Qurrrntine Inspector on Rs.50. -The present auditor, v/ho i performs the duties of Q,u; rrntine Inspector, is stated to be ) not in receipt of this allowsnce-rHis duties as auditor c^ nnot permit of him effectively conducting the dual role md where-s an appointment rs Quarantine Inspector is apparently not contemplated by the strte, the allowance for the item id not a just charge rgrinst expenditure. Revenue (Zakat) Under the present arrangement the entire receipts and expenditure on this head would appear to concern merely Sib, Birlc; , Khcbura, Boshrr end Q,uraiyrt. This is in fact not so rnd revenue receipts and expenditure in districts north of Birkr. are merely shown under a general terminology of ^Tilryat of Soh; r H , -his prectice is questionable rnd leaves much to be aesired since neither expenditure on Zakct revenue/ 7 Za.ks.'t revenue collections ('to which 'the present, head is at,*' tribu table) nor the actual receipts are readily traceable. ( t (iv) Customs Department * The outstanding points that attract notice are the Gwddur and Sur Customso No details by ports of receipts for the past year were submitted by the office of the Financial Adviser, till called for# Gwadur, Reference to the receipts for 1933 shows a decline in revenue of Rs 6200 jWhereas the expenditure on the Customs establishment maintained at this port is out of all proportion to that incurred elsewhere• The following table of expenditure and receipts for the year 1933 for the two main ports of the Sultanate com- Bared with that of Gwadur is enlightening*— Expenditure • Receipts * Muscat ^ 8080 Hs 1,71}068 Matratu ^ 8172 Rs Gwadur. Rs 7440 Rs 76)928 Under the existing circumstances and in view of the working of the past year there seems to be no justifi cation for the post of Assistant Amin at Gwadur and the post should be brought under reduction. If it is considered essential to retain the post for a further year^ experiment there are many local personages eligible for appointment to it, whose services could be ob tained at half the salary of the present foreign incumbent. The report of the Financial Adviser's assistant that a considerable amount of Gwadur trade is now being de flected to Pasni would lend further support to the proposed reduction in the Gwadur establishment. Sur* This port is considered as the third port of the Sultanate. In spite of this fact, and the large trade it plies, its customs receipts only figure 4th on the list.hM on the lists. A certain improvement has undoutedly mc nilestcci itseir ot l^te but much tightening up of the admimstrc tion is indicr ted ii* o c^uotri in pro portion to its resources is to be collected from Sur. The Ju^tii ice tion 1 or the payment of certrin s,1cries in rupees &amp;nd certain in dollcrs throughout the Department is not apparent# 4 ' , Department of J ustice, ITo comment. 5. Prison (J; lali Fort} '■ ^ X The average number of xnrisoners through- out the yerr is 15 per mensem. Two annr s per diem is the allotment '11owed per head for feeding them. Taking into consideration • further infinitesm; 1 daily gr.nt allowed to the prisoners, it is not under stood why the sum of ; ,.1,172 is allotted under this head. 6. Pol ice » Ho comment. 7 ot^.ff ^nd Aekr ris ^ (a; j-he ex-v r t li o^ oib who has been removed 1 roni service continues to drew j2 100 per mensem.This payment should obviously come under the he-d of 'Pensioners'. (b; The fe:,ct of there being two Valis of -ishgrn (Gwadur) is attributeble to the fact that the governor ol the jail (Sirdar Rustrm Khrn) draws a Political r How nee under this he^ d. ( \ ' ^■clur schoolm' ster . The Financial Advisey' Adsistunt is not awore of the status of the Gw; dur school, nor has its existence been brought to the notice of the Political Agent, The school is believed to be purely for elementary Quranic ociuection, in which esse the salrrjh V e salary of the school master would ? ppe-r to be excess 8. Defence (Muscat Infantry) A seperate report is being submitted under this heod but it may be observed here that the main tains nee of the armoured Gar, which w&lt; s purchrsed for revenue collecting purposes solely, is not a justifiable charge under this he ding and should be shown as chaggerble against Zi k t. 9 . Public '■■ /orks Department . The payment of 1^45 per mensem to the present ancient incumbent of the post of 'Telephone Operator*' hovers between the sublime £ nd the ridiculous. The appointment is perhaps in the nature of a sinecure• 1 Q. Quarc ntine . The allotment of KS »50/-per mensem for a oU' r ntine Inspector has already been dealt with under heading 3 (ii }. i^' Pensioiyo As no reasons are afforded for the pensions it is impossible to comment on this head apart from the fact that the list contains the names of the ex- Walis of Gwadur and Sur, both of whom have been dis missed the service for inefficiency and failure in their duties, in spite of which fact they draw re- munaratiwM pensions* 13* Miscellaneous # V. Ifo comment* IV• Municipalities* Matrah. Khamis bin Ismail who is well known to the Council and the Finance Department as a corrupt and worthless rogue, continues to be retained in the State f s employ, to the detriment of the State and the Matrah community in general.M ^ l ft Tiae details of trie Budget having been criticised in detail there remains little tc add e 2o it is however worthy of note that no allotment has been made for the liquidation of local 'public debts', referred to in the comments on 'The Report of the Financial xear 3o J-f it is intended to make an effort to off all or any of these debts a definite allotment should have been included m tne .budget. Such allotment would materially affect trie figures quoted in the Finance Department 1 s 'pro posed budget for 1954 f, . 4o Taking the Budget proposals for 1934 as a whole, read with the'Eeport for the Financial Year 1923', it would certainly lead to the conviction that they would not stand scrutiny by competent auditors* 5. Details of Expenditure and Receipts have in no case been shown side by side to Justify present, or to modify future, Expenditure* m many cases no details at all are forthcoming, whilst the Report is filled with extraneous 'padding' which has no bearing on the object of the Report and would appear to be inserted merely to compensate for essential dificiencies. The elimination of such material from Reports of this nature wou Id s e em de si rt,b le o • Ihe non-inclusion of allotments to set off against such items as Es* 9^,000 odd of Public Debt and Rs«. 15,000 advanced to nis Highness in connection with the Dhofar trip 'tfould appear open to serious Audit ubjection«» St &gt; The inclusion of problematic appointments such as 'Quarantine inspector' which do not appear to have been sanctioned would also appear objectionable. y&lt;&gt; Tiie scale of pay of the Financial Adviser's Assistant showing increiiient due, Bhoilld have been shown together with thosethose of other officials to whom increrients are also presumably due 4t tiae proportionate rates. Jrolitical xigent 8c H.B .lv 's Consul, MuscatBoport* on i^ubcat S tot# Tlaaaclal year 1933, (52) 3 80it The years vvorklngg. Financially the year 1933 has Wen cowparatlvely hettei t an 19,'.2. There have heen slgae of revival and the reneral oon tinuea of I'lnaaelal stringency wan leas felt, '■'■•he suspicion of very unsettled conditions of trade dlaappeared to mom extent. The prices of dates of 193a crop rote high In the; htflnnlnf; of the year and merchants isade good profits. The prlc. of dates continued to remain eteady and all the avllaahle dates were exported to India. a. The local prices of Kasha - fish manure remained same as auzlng the year i93fci with slight fluctuation, it le however feared that the country may lose all Ite trade in jcaeha as the Oeraaa Governr.ient prohlhlteu Its import Into Ceraany which is the chief country of Its Import. 3. large purchases of rice sere made during the first 3 •fflsk 2 0fthe y ®* r 1933 du * t0 t:b ® of prices in India. MH&amp;tt huslnoss '.raa transacted and In some cases the mercUuitt. :sade good profits as the prices rose after/ards. 4. The progressive revenue of the f-tate month ty month during the year 1933 as oomparod with the year 193*. has 'been:- Month« im is* 1953 to. January 64 # 50U 53,700 Felaruary 47,900 58,600 March 56 # D00 85,500 April £6, id 00 53,900 nay 55,800 40,700 Turn 46,000 45,300 Jtily 48,600 53,900 August 48,BOO 51,400 septeielmr 69,600 69,000 Oeto'ber 75, 600 90,900 November 7Q f ^00 67,900 D ©ceEi *ber 7^.600 5«i| 100 as estliKitHd Total 7,1*,Q0Q 7,i.3,0uu11. Batreactoaupt aoa econoialea . 8. A. soheme of eeoaomise proposed and sutxaitted to —4 ^ f ■! tiaHighness th« Sultan early in February to oeet the anticlpata leas of fe. 1,00,000 Aras Traffic subsidy. The seheae was BSrtly •tMj a#.. J j ' approved -by the sultan and brought into force fro* 1st July, 1938, H By this achome a saving of about is.16,000 has lieen effected ^ 0 »li|| jturiag the year under report. * • '•'Jii «, the old State's launch '41 saldl' whloh was oonsldered n Si si) unfit for further service and which has become surplus hy clos ing dovm the state's Marine Department »as sent to BomhayiIndia): f ®Wtosai for sale. She made a good Journey to Bombay and was finally sold for a. 4,S70/-. ? (ayhl 7# The position of ^tate as regards trade is shown hy the following figures;- )n.iMkUi . Mverse trade ^SSffF^h .JEiXorts halanoe. •SWfil 1931 - 3S &amp;. 37,37,lis 17,07,3^7 S0,SS,791 { r^toil WM • 33 b. 34,71,618 a0,S7,334 14,44,^84 ii iaaiSiKf Ml The outlook of trade has teen promising* The fall In tlon loot I the value of total imports as compared with the last year has jrjtf.» n du ® to the cheapness of the goods and not to the quantity ^ v.* ? Imported, Jhc quantity of articles imported has heen more than ,1/iicI ^ laEt year. There has,therefore,'been a revival of Import trade. jgPl The value of articles exported during the year la 909 fc# Ztk-OtOQft more thaxa tt^g value of artlcela exported during the ii ' years 1931 - 3fc. ®ie improveaent in the export trade has heen Un very encouraging and it is toped will he maintained. i ts The position» therefore, la that the adverse trade salaace still stands at a very fcigh figure sf is, i4,44,«84. It msy 'be encouraging to note that the adverse balance has decreased by &amp;. 5,65,807 as oovpared with the year 1931 - Sa. I* lo satisfactory explanation is fortheomlng as to the source fJroa here the country's loss in trade Am values is being met. Vi' ,t It is presumed that the accumulated capital amassed during the prosperous days is being utilised. This, however, cannotm 'torn, •vn kw i| '••mil m* h k MUnm ^ Illoo id: tu \vnm Wtfrlii (i i' t fiOTllMll u t»inlk I .Vao.Jj VUBiB tun ,« tdtvfiib jM II « 91 It I 4. J @ month estimated. Tlgures may 1)0 exceeded 'but will not be less than shown. 13. referring to the ahove table, it will appear tiiat the estimstea sine 1931 have been prepared with greater care than previously done. The loss has been due to no regular accounts having been kept during this i &gt;eriod of either revenue or expenditure and it is not poeslhle to give figures previous to 1931 with accuracy. ince 1931, however, greater attention has 'been paid and accurate accounts are being maintained. Tit r^s. 14. The amount of public deht including Governaent of India loan which has 'been paid in full, on Slat December of the year 19^9,1939, 1931,1932 and 1933 has heen as under;- m9 i&gt;. I,50,i74i to. a ( 04 !,704 Rt. 1,99,390 fe. l,5S,ii04 Si. 99,430. 15. It will apt&gt;ear that a sum of R . 53 ,774 has been paid during the year. The Government of India Loan has 'been paid in full with interest. it is further hoped that it will be possible to pay away the balance now due vis. 99,430/-, after scaling down by mutual agreement, during the year 1934. Til, investments. 16. l sum of fe. 37,697/8 has heen invested in ♦B' ' ortgagc febenture f took of the Newfoundland power paper Co. 1930 1931 193£ 1933 ltd. which is guaranteed by the Newfoundland Government. 4 sum of Si. 619/- has Wxeady been received as interest. The \ original value of the stocks on which interest is payable is' € 3000/- and the yearly interest will come to about te,«4,«»00/-. The recent press reports about the finance of Newfoundland Government are not very satisfactory and it is feared that Btfteks may depreciate in value. There appears no real danger and the object with which the investment was made viz. ftot 1^ (5^ vis. realization of more money lay interest Is hoped, to 'be doliieved. Vl?lt -UW*WI 17. The opening 'balance after the close of 1982 has been £.93,470/- on 1-1-1933. Of this amount fe. 62,774/- has heen paid afattet public dehts fiuring the year 1953. it is hoped tiiat the year 1933 will close with a oalanoe of ahout h, 1,50,000 including the Inrcstment made (para 16 . The 'balance of public debts still due Is ft. 99,430/-. This Is the only liability of the State which is hoped to tie paid in full after scaling down by mutual agreement.during the year 1934 (para 15). The state will have no liability in 193B and will be self-supporting, it will mean that by the efforts mde during the last 3 years the rtate has been able to success fully cope with the financial stringency. The anticipated saving on the working of 1934 will be fc. 76,355/- and we my be able to close the year with a balance of about &amp; lakhs. M* staff. £. 18. Captain m.G. Alban I.A. was relieved of duties of Financial adviser by P.3. ifallk ntii ehand on »Bth gar ch.1933 on his taking over as Political igent * F.l.iu's Consul, Muscat iver since r -.s. Malik Bull chnsd has been in ohsage of the State's Finance pepartaent. 19. Ahead Effendi Haadi, the uislstant Birector of Custons and next senior man in the department was transferred to Tinanclal Adviser's office to be in charge of the customs branch and act in the place of 'C.s. 'alik pull ''hand during his absence on tours etc. This arranrement has worked very satisfactorily. HO. further Improvement has been made in the organisation of the Finance Department by dividing it into four sections (I) ceneral office (Jt) Treasury (3) Customs section (4) Audit section, lore accomdatlon is necessary for proper working of all the sections. I. Appendlees . &amp;1. Appendix I is a comparative table showing the valueThe ^esideucy, 3U3HI.ES, 1st February 1934, !)• 0,No»92-S of 1934. Please refer to paragraph 16 of the r' jA enclosure to your Ho.63 of the 15th/i6th January 1934. 'iou will liave received our Printed Letter ( ly H o .61- d enclosing Alhan # s last letter, from which it will appeal' that^stock is quite a good one and can he sold at ahout the same price at which it was 'bought. If this is so, presumably you wish to have your criticism expunged. 2. Cclonel Fowle presumes that you have shown the copy of Alhan^s letter to tLe Muscat G-overnaient, and would he glad to learn what action you are taking in the matter. Major G.i2l.lJ.Bremner f k.G ., Political A^ent, Euscat. v5 X x +1 1L S 3 - jl E T T ill R To From Political Muscat Britconsul, Bushire ^/'' l3nu ' .f - i ] iAi afefiom, j liuscat, the 24111 January 1954 SUJB j SSCT s - XJEvTFuU^IH^M) STOCK KEID BY MUSCAT GuVEHliikiSl;T. |o h I Reference your tele^xam 1163 and 1137 of 29th December 1932. 2» Lloyds iBank, Karachi was consulted concerning stock held by Muscat GoTernment and was authorised to cable home for latest available information if necessary. 3. Their cabled enquiry to London elicited following reply 'losition of debentures unaltered not included in conversion scheme'. 4. This would appear to indicate that investment remains safe although tied up for inordinately long period as no buyers at favourable price likely to be forthcoming at this Juncture. Subject your confirmation propose advising Council to let investment stand meanwhile informing them of result of my enquiries from Lloyds. 6 Solicit early confirmation Political A&amp;ent &amp; onsul, Muscat a jor35/157 Telegram G-.T', 0. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat. No 133. Dated 6th .Fe'bruary 19 34. Your memorandum dated ttie 24tti January* Newfoundland Stock. You will have received my Printed Letter No 61-3 dated 25th January and have presumatlv' oommunicated enclosures to Muscat Government, who are now in possession of all available information and must do what they think fit. -HSaiDENT-CQNFIDMTIAL &gt; D#0•Mo.C/78. /! 1 (lot Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, 3rd March 1934. ^zcxa. j x Please refer to your D.0.No.92-S dated 1st February 1934. 2. The fact that the Newfoundland stock in question has turned out sound is most fortunate. It would however in no way appear to 41ter the grounds of my contention which are that when, over a long period previously, New foundland finances had been notoriously rocky and unsound, it was unfortunate and unwise to invest a large sum of money belonging to a State slowly recovering from virtual bankruptcy in any stock pertaining to that country. 3. Such being the case there would seem to be no reason to withdraw my criticism, which I still adhere to. I think Alban is to be congratulated more on his good luck than his good Judgement. 4. I may mention that His Highness the Sultan in the course of a recent conversation verbally expressed his strong resentment and indignation about any investment at all having been made without the late Financial Adviser having either consulted him or taken his orders 5. From His Highness's attitude at the time I fancy | it will not be the last we have heard on the subject as he stated he proposed representing the matter officially, tf i 1 jor R. P. Watts, I.A*, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian U ulf, Bushire.Cnnfident lal T).n.Wo.3g«-3 of W34. The 'ReBr'deroy, the ISth A^rll, 19 34. VmiT clal let+er Nf*.0/7« of ? f arch 3rd, 1!)34. -he Btatewetit in |iaragra#i 16 of your Adminifitration Hewort that 'he Imreotwert nas wade without the cor aw It at 1 on of either the Healdert or the Political Affent 1« correct, 'but the authority AlTian should hare consulted nore than either of thera vas the Bulton. f&gt;. Yaur statement thot the Investment vas unfortunate and umtlse Colonel ^o^sle Is unalsle to a^ree ^Ith since the parti cular ^toclc invested in is aii)?arently quite sound and should the Tfuscat Oovernwent like to sell they can f^et a^f^oxlnately ^hat they isaid for it, 3. In any case an Administration ^eitort is not the correct vehicle for the conveyance of controversial matter and Colonel ^vle is therefore exipunprlni? the passage in quest!or frow your ^eraort. 4. You can pursue the mtter in a sem^ate letter if you choose 'but Colonel ''o^le nvill discuss it nlth you when he visits Muscat, #ii ch he ho^es to be able to do ahotit the middle of ?lay. '^ajor 0.T5.TJ.'Brenner,H.C Political Agent, m .u j c a. t,.'/t CONFIDENTIAL From No . C/ (?/. of 19B4. Maj or G» '&amp;• U. Brecmer, M.C., P olitical A gent and H. B. M,' s C onsul, M uscat, he Hoi ^ble the Political Resident iii-the Persian Jaulf, B u shire. 7^ B eitish A gency and C onsulate. Muscat, the 5th April 70134 Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith the trans lation of a letter received from His Highness the bultan of Muscat concerning £ 3,000 worth of Newfoundland stock purchased for the State# 2 # As you are already aware this stock was purchased by Captain Alban, the late Financial Adviser, without the consultation of either yourself, the oultan or the Political Agent, Muscat# 3. Fortunately it has not gone the way of most New foundland investments but the fact that the transactionj comprising £ 3,000 of the State's hard won savings, was invested without either his consultation or authority, has aroused the Sultan's very justifiable indignation, which was expressed to me verbally in polite but very poignant language by His Highness,. ^ ip-^g the second instance ol large sums of State money being Invested by Captain Alban without so much as intimating L let ^lone^rece^^^uthority from, theSultan for doing so. 5, rtS the first investment involving Rs 12,600/- for the purchase of a most unsuitable and wholly unusable 'armoured car' (which is now lying rotting at Bait-el-Falaj), can be regarded as a dead loss, there certainly appears to be considerable justification for the Sultan's indignation, which can be guaged by his somewhat piquant question , 'Is my British Financial Adviser there to advise me or merely to squander my »itate • s resources without so much as my consultation'. 6 # In the present instance His Highness has asked, both verbally and in writing, as to who would be responsible for reimbursing his btate with the £ 3,000, had this un authorised investment been lost. 7 # Presumably, since he made the investment on his own authority, Captain Alban would have been required to do so. As I am unable to answer this question on my own authority, it is referred to you with the request that I may receive early instructions as to what reply should be given to His highness. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Agent and H # B. k^s Consul, Muscat# I uLetter dated 7th Dhil dejjeh 1362 (23rd March 1934) from His highness ^aiyid baid bin Taimur, oultan of muscat dc Omanj to kajor C.^.u .jbremner, m • 0. 5 Political Agent oc H.b., Consul, Muscat* When X was at uhofar, rny representative after having heard from you with regard to the Newfoundland stock which was bought for £ 3000^sent me some communications and 1 also received a letter from you on the same subject# I state that these shares were bought without my permission and knowledge, i^'irst of all 1 request you to let me know as to who is responsible for that amount if it is lost, I shall be grateful if you will inform me of the result of your communications with regard to this amount• U.E. mms -&gt; ^ ^ ^ • ^ &lt; A \ J ■ S* C&lt; o y - , • &gt; -.8 ' 1 •2 1 Ho. of 1934. Political Agency &amp; H. 13.II 1 l Consulate, Muscct, the / J lit: ' t* rch 1934# From To Major C.E.U.Bremner,M.C. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Museat. The Secretcry to the Pollticiil Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Muscat Strte Finances. Sir, n In continuation of my memorandum Ho.-527 dated ! the 5th December 1933, I have the honour to forward herewith for the informition of the Hon'ble the Political &lt; Resident (a) statements showing revenue and expenditure for the year ending 3-st December 1933, ('b) stiitement showing the progress of loms and debts for the 4th quarter ending 31st December 1933, (c) the cash bilance of the State Treasury as it stood on -st January 1934, i. nd (d) a note on llusci t State Finances. 2. As since His Highness the Sultan has Ulcen over ft * all Finance himself and as he is heavily engrossed in ^ affrirs of State, it has not been possible to reconcile the discrepancy in the note (d)• I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Ms?J or, Pol it icr-1 Agent &amp; H.B .11 ♦ s Consul, Huscrt. GHKHOTS ON MUSCAT 3TaT3 FIMCI33. The Strtement of Receipts shows that it was estimrted that the receipts for j. 933 w T ould 'be whereas actually was pollected that is more than what they had anticipated. The statement of Expenditure shows that they anticipated to spend during 1933 But their actual expenditure was Therefore they exceeded their 'budgeted amount 'by 3,053-13-0 Taking the actual amount collected iL. 7,36,495-13-0 and the actual amount spent we find thrt the gross savings have 'been Of this amount, they have paid debts and their net savings have therefore 'been To this, if we L:dd, the State's last ; year ? s savings we /have the total 'balance in the Muscat Government Treasury But, according to the statement it is This 'balance is made up of cash, investments etc. and if the btnte were to pay her delfts amounting to The State's Ix-ltnce would only mount t(w 74.995-11-0 The discrept'.ncy 'between the State's given bultnce i^nd the 'balance orrived ».t by me can only he explained hy the Financial Adviser.BusVu i.nv- 7*7 | sh'? - No. I -p., 7S^ Dated the . at JLa^4.^ ^ ^ 25til olf Zil-Qada, 1352. From Nadir bin Faisal bin TurKi, Muscat, To \\o^ a *' y ']/ / ' 7 The Honyable Lt.Gol. T.G. Fowle, Tlio Bi i tich Ke si dent and Consul—General in tlie Persian Gulf, Busnire, Vc- I beg to bring to your Kina notice that from the month of July to February I have not been a.ble to get my allowance which was fixed by a written agreement contracted between my brother the late Sultan Taimur and m,B and ratified by my nephew the present Sultan Said at the time of his accession. The reason for the cessation of payment is that I received a letter from the Council of Regency (info/|raing me about) curtailing part of it bj the Sultan's order. But as this imfringament is prima facie contrary to the bond executed between usValidated, by duly signed documents and recorded in His Britannic Majesty f s Consulate and Political Agency, Muscat, in the time of Mr. Wingate vide his letter HoI7 of 1921,1 refuse to recognise it at all. I(also take this opportunity to) remind you of the talk ^liad with y©u and the fears I expressed ta) you prior to the accession of the present Sultan and the reply you gave which was the greatest factor in the satisfaction of my mind. But now the very thing of which I was afraid has (actual- ;| -ly) taken place and so I deemed it obligatory to bring it to your notice as I explained it fully to tjie present Consul Major Bremner With full confidence in your former assurances, I, with our doors hope wide open,/tiaat you would come to my rescue and do me justice. Always relying upon you, I am, Your friend, Nadir bin Faisal.^ i V// &gt; / Copy, D»0«Ko#C/96. Political Agency &amp; H .M .M.Consulate, Muscat, 6th April 1934. ¥ Dear Alban. Please refer to your letter of 7th March 1934 forwarding various papers tn connection with the New foundland stock purchased by you from the Muscat Budget surplus, 2. I am awaiting HisHighness the Sultan's return from tour to discuss the matter with him, 3. It seems however, in view of the fact that you are no longer Financial Adviser to the State, that His Highness v/ill hardly be prepared to sign a letter to the Imperial Bank of Indlaauthorising the securities and shares to stand in your name, unless as a very temporary expedient, 4. The fact of you having tendered your resignation with effect from expir^ of your leave in December would legally renderit impossible for him to authorise any such proposal, 5. I will let you know what His Highness decides in due course. Yours sincerely, sd, C,E.U,Bremner, Cf&gt;pt ,R«G#E#W,Alban, c/o Messrs, Grindl ay &lt;Sc Co., 54 Parliament Street, London*S,W,-i '12 7 AIR MAIL . Confidentlal . I ).0. M o .G/228 of 1934. f f O Office of the Political Reaident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, MUSCAT. 18th May 1954- A li Please refer to your letter of 29th December 1933 to Stewart on the subject of the Newfoundland Stock which you in the capacity of Financial Adviser purchased for the Muscat Government. 2. I enclose a copy of a letter from His Highness the Sultan,dated 23rd March 1934, and my reply. 3. As you will see. His Highness is perturbed that you bought the shares without, as he maintains, his per mission or knowledge. I would be glad to know why you did so. 4. Please refer to s demi-official letter to you, Ho.C 96 of 6th April. His Highness is writing to you a letter instructing you to take steps to transfer the securities and shares in question to the name of the Muscat Government, to be operated by him. Ac Captain R.G.E.W.Alban, , c/o Messrs.Grindlay &amp; Co., /] 54 Parliament S1n:eet', It on don, S.W. (copy forwarded to Major Eremt^er underP .L.No.C/229 of 18/5/34).I I ' M' V-n Ho.0/233 of 1934. ' - / Office of the political ^sideatj^er.uulf• Camp| Muscat# May, 18th| 1934* To Hia ^ighneaa ^aiyid ^aid bin Taii^ur, oulum of ^uacat 4 O^an# your Highnessi I have the honour to refer to your letter dated 7th iihil UaJJ 1352 (2ard -arch 1934) to Major arecuner, M«C # | political i^ent Muscat, who has forwarded me a copy thereof* 2» I delayed in replying thereto in view of ny impending visit to Muscat, where occasion would afford ®f discussing the matter with your Highness* This we did yesterday* 3, your Highness confimed what you had said in your letter i*e* that Captain Alhan had bought the shares in question without your penaission or knowledge* 4 # with regard to Xour Highness 1 question as to who would have heen responsible if loss had occured through the transaction, this is an hypothetical question wnich I am unable to answer* your Highness asked me in the course of our conversation us to what steps you could take to prevent a re- occurence of a similar incident* I gave it as opinion that Xour «ighness could liii.it the financial powers of ^ny of thosserving Your Hlghneae 1 8 Government to whatever extent you ©aw fitf intiioation of ajoy auch oraers being sent by you to Xour Highness*8 Bankers* 6* Your Higimeas alao aaked ^y advice as to whether to sell the atook now or to retain it* I regretted that I was unable to adviae Xour uighneaa on thia point but pointed out that you would receive Tor the au&gt;ck today practically the same aa waa paid i 'or it and in the meantime you had received %• I desire to expreaa the hi^h consideration which 1 entei'tain for your iiighnesa and to subacribe n^raelf Your iiighneaa's sincere friend* Lt^CoXonel f political resident in the ^eraiem Mulf# ek \ Copy given to P.A.Muscat unMer P.L. No.C/229 of 18/5/34).Letfeer dated 7th Dhil Hejjeh 1352(23rd March 1934) from His Highness SaijUd Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, to Major G.E.U.Bremner,M,G., Political Agent and H.3.M, Consul, Muscat, After Compliments, When 1 was at Dhofar rny representatives afterhaving heard from you with regard to the Newfoundland stock which was bought for £ 3000 sent me some communications and I also received a letter from you on the same subject, I state that these shares were bought without my permission and knowledge. First of all I request you to let me ic n ow as to who is responsible for that amount if it is lost, I shall be grateful if you will inform me of the result of your communications with regard to this amount. Usual Ending,gonfldeotial &gt; The ke8idenoy 9 Busiiire, the 26th May 1954* With regard to the State debt to merchants* I wae under the Ixupreseloii that the State only owed money to Muecatl eubjecte, and certainly no British subject8» as far as I remember t have ever watered in the Agency any debt claims against the Muscat State# la one of our ./ conversations with the Sultan, however 9 the latter stated that there were some British subjects concerned. Xou were going to look the matter up. Please let me know the result*^nfideotUl. p | n T Ko.476-S of 1934. 0(c ?1 r 1 The Eesidency, Bushire, the 28th May 1954* When I w&amp;» In Maseat you Informed me that Knabinahue had asked for the budget figures c of the Muscat State* We asked the Sultan whether he had any objection to supplying these and he replied that he would let us know* Please let me know what his decision has been* Kaior G.E.U.Bremner f M.C. # Political Agent, Muscat*5 &gt; | 15 i V nONVIDKNrlAL . Ho.496 -S of 1934. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUSHIKS, the 30th Hay 1934. To c The Political Agent» MUSCAT• Subject * MUSCAT FIHASGSS. Memorandum » Please refer to your letter Ho«65 f dated the 15/l6th January 1934. As you will see from my letter Ko»486'»Gf dated the 29th May 1934,to the Government of India X have quoted some of your remarks in support of my request for the coiitinuance of the Arms Subsidy; but when I was in Uuscat the k &gt;ultan produced a new budget for 1934 of his own# ^he one sent under your ebove quoted letter was made out by the xrector of Revenues in His Highness^ absence and presumably differs from His Highness^# Please let me have a copy of the latter with your comments. sd« T.C.Fowle, ATTBSTm lit Colonel § Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Major, Secretary to the Political Reai^® 11 ^ in the Persian Gulf#UNOFFICIAL. li 5? @) Muscat, 25th May 1934. ulhvty ^ v I am sending herewith a c®py of a note on Sai/id Nadir's interview with Colonel Fowle in case you would like 'to keen on your record.Note on interview with Saiyid ^adir. The Hon^le the, Political Resident accorded Saiyid Nadir bin ^'aisal an interview today (19th May 1934) at the latter's request# Saiyid Nadir stated that contrary to the terms of the Sanad held by him from the late Sultan, Saiyid Taimur and endorsed by His Highness Saiyid Said on his accession, his salary had been reduced. He sought the intervention of the British Government in the. person of the Hesident to rectify this glaring injustice. He repeatedly endeavoured to elicit a reply from the Resident as to legality or illegality of the action of the Muscat Government in thms cutting his salary. The xion'ble the political Hesident clearly and definitely pointed out to oalyld ifedir that the ma -ter was not one of which His Majesty's Government could take cognizance or in which they could or would interfere. The non'ble the Political Resident told Saiyid Nadir that if he sought his personal advice (as Colonel Fowle and as friend to friend) he would give nirn the same. Colonel Fowlej in his private capacity as a friend, expressed surprise and regret that ^aiyid Nadir, as a senior member of the Ruling Family, instead of setting an example by the voluntary surrender of a portion of his salary or at least of accepting the order which affected all from the highest to the lowest in the -tate, should have aaopted hxs present contumacious attitude. As Saiyid Nadir persisted in seeking the official interference of the xion'ble the Political 'esident m an affair which was purely the concern of the ^ultan and not of the British Government, the interview was brought to a close, Saiyid 'adir being again informed finally and for good that His Majesty's Government would not interfere. Major, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. 19/5/34.Mo. D. 204 9-^/34 . From ''he Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To ^he Hon Hole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, o3©''P V lit... '7 !*•••— 1 Simla, the /f May 1934. Petition from Saiyid Nadir bin Faisal bin Turkey, uncle of present Sultan of Muscat, complaining against reduction in his allowance. oO o Sir, T am directed to forward in original a petition dated 20th April 1954, from Saiyid Nadir bin Faisal bin Turkey, addressed to His Excellency the iceroy Ox India, and to request that the petitioner may be informed that His 'Excellency is not prepared to interfere on his behalf in a matter which concerns the Internal administration of the Fuscat State. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India / )f f 'S. | \ c i \ -' y Muscat da^ed ?&gt;Oth April 1934,, ?o His Kxeellencv the Viceroy of India Simla» Mat it Please Your 75rcellency. I the undersigned nadir 'bin Faisal bin Turkey the eldest uncle of preae^ 4 : Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the v®unge^ brother of late Sultan of Muscat and Oiaan f era ire the liberty of repreaentlnf? the fpllowinp: subrniBsion nith a Tievi to rvceiire the necessary ana i stance for the mtter be lot; set forth;- Hiat I received an official letter from The Council of Regency of H.H, Sultan of Muscat and Oman g stating that under the arrangement of State finance ^epartmen 4 ' and bv the instruction of Sultan of Muscat and Oman, a sum of *s 8S0/- is reduced from mv monthly allowance riz, Hs 2600/- nhich is fixed by the late Sultan of Muscat and Oman and confir med by present Sultan of Muscat and Oman. IVom the enclosed papers vour Excellency would notice that my alio nance is no + in any way or account liable t® any reduction and therefor since July last up to date 1 have not dra v in the allowance. Befor* placing my request before Your Excellency I interrlewed Major GIT« Bremner M.C* The Political t Muscat 0 asking his assistance 'or the recovery ny a 1 iof?« ance and shoen him the original o^ the agreement and, the corres pondence relating to itb which is in my possession. Similarly Colonel '-C. T?owle The Hon'ble Political Resident in Persian Gulf has b^en represented thr act of putting the reduction upon my allowance and + h&amp;t under my letter of l oth March 1924 0 It is regretted to sa^ that neither of them have rendeeed any assistance in recovers of my allowance nor the latter has has) ^ has acknowledged for ray letter* TTnd^r the circumstances, it is requested respect- fully 9 the favour of Your Excellency, rendering the assistance in recovew of ay allomnce at the earliest opportunity* I beg to remain 9 Your Excellency's most obedient servant Sd/- Madir bin Faisal bin Turkey. I 1 m f af^P apers fi led *a n 'ran slat ion of original of the aprreewent Un Arabic) pasaed b«ti«efn myself and late Sultan of Muscat and Oman and cdnfirr^ed by the presen 4 - 3ultan of Muscat and Oman. 'B* ^ranalatlon of an official letter Un Arabic; from late ^ultan of Muscat and Oman addressed to Mr Win^ate, l.C-S. •'he late l^olitic^l Afrent Muscat and reply from the Politl cal Afrent Muscat addressed to H.H. Sultan of Muscat, bearinf? officially Kumber 1^/19^1. Sd/- Wadir bin Faisal bin -t^rke 1 M«A« translation the original agre^iaent IfVom falraur bin Faisal, the- Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Nadir bin ^alsal. e* •** -m *m -rm r* 3».a«b** ?•.»• =■*»-. sn-^ear ■** am ^ Be It known to nil nVio maycone aorosa tftls our writing that w 'mre itaaigned to our dear brothrr , Madir bin Walaal, as his Monthly salary One THOTISA3ID T)OTjLAT?3, which h^ Is to receive from the Muscat Custoa', Ca t .ltal of our Tiowlnlon of Oman. We haTe wade this a standing and perpetual conce?8l«n for him and for his descendants after him, unch.vtreable nor deceasahl until God Inherit the Earth and that Is thereon. 'his concession from us to him is a recofmltion of his steadfast attachnent to and well-hehaviour towards us and a remuneirMon for the energy he exerted in mr caseo and accomplishment of m' orders. Among the qualities which ent Itles him from us this concession the pecuniary aaslstance he rendered to us at s time where we were much indebted t« h him for his good deed and asn recompense for the loss he auatalned, through the foil' of our employee 'he Director of Customs, Mahamed Heimo©, in falling t4 hand' over his pearls to Ms Agent in Bombay whom they were meant for and for «hic^ he was to come litigation with us but » greed to comproral?e with him at our request and advice to him as we thought it wss In our interest to come to settlement at the time. He lef* the matter entirely in o4r hands and acted upon the our desire to the great loss he underwent. TMb entitled him from us this recomsense he deserved in every respect. We order thnt this should be payable to him whereever he may be and to his descendants. 1 hope, rather and confident that hip career towards me and to my successors shall continue to be the same a praiseworthy one, as has Ven hithertofore. 1 declare that this shall be binding on mv and on my sucoes sors and ttet it shall take effect as from 1st day of Shaban 1337. Written by his slave. Tashid bin Azeis in his own hand ( ^he Qhadi of Muscat State J('he '-'hadi of Muscat Stated Seal of H.H. r5ult»ii { n^rt Sultan ) l a^ree to what is viritten ahove whether for me or against me . ( Sd) Hadir Mn ifeisal, H»H« The Sultan has asked me to bear witness to v;hat Is conceded to the 'brother lladir bin ^alnal and hip children aner him and I mn their brother, Hamed bin Faisal in his own hand* H,H. theSultan has aslced me to bear witness to this and JL do hereby bear witness thereto, sg: . Alii bin 3alim in his own hand c Be it known to the readers of this that re hare froie Ist March 1920, corresponding to Jaraad el Akhar 1338, changed all the salaries which us^d to be paid in -ollars by ou'* -overnraertt to rupees, therefore what has been granted to our brother Madir bin Faisal namely 1,000 j; dollars r.e have changed then to Hs 2,500 Hupees two thousand five hundred onl^, no more no less, Sf ?d H,H. the Sultan 10th Jamad el Akhar 1338. the signature of H.H. 8ultar? has been certified by His Hi^thn^ss Wazir Mackalan. Written by ^ashid bin Azelz ( the chief OJiadi of Musca State) in his own hand. Version of the assurance of Saiyid Said bin ^aimur, 'Hie Sultan of Muscat and Oman. We haTe fixed for our uncle Saiyid Wadir bin ^'aieal the two thousand am 1 five hundr-* rupees for mensem whldh m^ father' 'alraur 'bin Faisal the Sultan had fixed for him, vide this document and 1 am the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. spd. Said bin Taimur. Written on the 3rd Shawwal 1350. Correspondinfr 11th February 193f? aTranslation o' the original letter addressed to the British Consul Mr Wlngate fron H.H, ^ultan of Muscat and Oman. After corapliwerts and enquiring afteryour health, as I have informed you verbally ahout assigning to our 'brother a monthly salarv as per document passed hy us in his favour anrl his descendants a^ter hin dated in Shahan 153 7 mhlch T ;as before the reformation of the Gustoms in 133P yie changed all nalarles from dollars to rupees and i^ rras likevrise necer'sary to change the amount in the docu ment passed 'bv us to our brother and that the due date document is as we have informed yon personally and pray that it nay he preserver- with ' r ou that thev may not arise any ques Ion against brother hereafter nhich facts he asked us to point out to you and so ve do and endorse the sarpe . In conclusion we give reiterate our best ceu- pliments to vou. sgd ''aimur bin Faisal the Sultan, copied by Hashid bin Aseir? ( the chief Q.hadl o^* Muscat S^ate) in his o^n hand, Heplv of the above letter addressed to H.H, Sultan of Muscat and Oman from H,B M's Consul Muscat No 465 of 10f?l T 5 ©!i ti cal Apen cy and H.^« M* s Consiilate Muscat the IRth March 10&lt;&gt;lo H«Tf. Saivid ^aimu? - ' bin ^alsal Sultan of Muscat and Oman Muscat, After Compliments. I hp ve received your letter datfd r, th Tamadi II 13:59 and un erstood what It contained regarding your brother Saiyid Hadir.CONFIDENTIAL. Xo. 566-S of 1934. /f-.n The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned doco- for necessary action. men British Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. '6 1 1 Dated, 20th June 1934. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department letter No.D .2049-K/3-r of Subject. Petition from Saiyid Nadir Bin Faisal bin Turkey, uncle of present Sultan oi . _ T ^ 4-r-. i rr acrnnr.fil letter No .D .2049-N/3i of ; K use at, complaining against 19th toy 1934, with enclosure. rtion in h i s allowance, in original. — 'bCopy- r-'a-r?.- c/o Grindlay &amp; Go.Ltd., 64 Parliament Streetm London.S iWvi. 11th June 1934. Deajr Colonel Fowle, ' ^ ' I have just received your D.O. dated May 18th and enclosures . 2. The reason why I bought the Stock in question is that it is generally accepted that surplus funds of a State govern ment etc . should be made to earn interest rather than remain idle. 3. H.s HighnessWws this and has never voiced any i ob.-ection to the principle. I therefore proceeded to choose a stock the purchase price of which was somewhat more reason- aaLe than thut of the general run, having' regard to its security and its previous good record* 4. I would be grateful if you could inform His Highness that nothing was further from my mind than to cause him any perturbation and I tender my sincere regrets to him on this account. My move was made with the otgect of benefitting the State financially and the result is entirely satisfactory as will oe seen below. 5. The price of the stock has been slowing rising since DecenToer, when I last wrote j when it was about £ 96 until it is now worth £ 101-102 per share. ■ The State-bought at about £ 98 and woula make about £ 100 profit on a sale in addition to the £ 82 half year's interest already received. If therefore His * Highness has any objection to'this stock he has only to orderhis bank to disposeof it, subject • to a reserve of say £ 101. 6. I have received his letter asking me to transfer the/-2- r-i. the stock to the Muscat State and have written to the Imperial Bank to do so. 7 # In conclusion I should like to tender my sincere regards to His Highness and to say that it always gives me the greatest pleasure to 'be ajle to ^ssist him in any way, ■—With' ■best wishes to yourself , Yours sincerely, sd • H • G • rvloan •Confidential. D.0.RO .607-S of 1934. Hf- The Hesldency, Bushlre, the 30th June 1934. deliver to the latter. Major C.U •Bresooer 9 M •€ • 9 Political iige&amp;tf Moacat* With reference to cox^respondence ending with ay letter of 18th Mcy to Alban a copy of which was aent to you* I enclose a copy of a letter which I have received from Alhan 9 and a letter from me to the Sultan which please IrnwFTDENTIAL« D.O.N O .C/^'? Muscat, 19th June 1934. '1 / ^ith reference to your D»0«476-S of 28th May. 2, The Sultan says he has no objection to letting Mr. Knabenshue know the Budget figures privately on the strict understanding they are not for publication. 3, Whether Mr. Knabenshue is likely to abide by these conditions or not I do not know. I suggest, if you agree, that after quoting His ^ighness's wishes on the subject, we say M The Budget figures for 1933 were approx imately Income — Expenditure '• 4 # Will you let me know whether under the circums tances I should inform His Excellency or not#on these lines. J? o -&lt;r Ehe Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel T.C.Fowle, , Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire. /&gt;'identical* D.O.No.624-3 of 1934t The Residency, Bushire, the 6th July 1934. t There is a matter which for a time gave me some anxiety lout which has now been cleared up* -ou snoulci however know of it and I am reportaccord • 2. Some time ago I noticed in the Statement of Accounts of the Muscat Government received through Bremner that a ^ 3d sum of £3000 was invested in Newfoundland stock. I ieared that this might be one of the 3^% Sterling Loans of 1905, )c • 1910 or 1912 which would have been a distinctly ris^y IH investment. Communication with Aloan, however, who had invested the sum when Financial Adviser to the Muscat State, showed that the stock actually purchased was the Newfoundland Power Paper Debentures B 1970 Government guaranteed. 'This is quite a sound investment in itself, and if the State sold out to-day they would be gainers on the transaction. 3. On the other hand Alban had made this investment without consulting the Sultan, and the latter was naturally perturbed at this. 4. When the investment was actually made the Sultan was away at Dhofar and not within easy reach, but even so, unless the Sultan had given Alban definite power invest State funds, which he had not, I am not of opinion that/ The Hon'ble ^ « t r t Mr.H.A.F.letcalfe,C .S .I. '^Aovernment Foreign Secretary to the Governm^ Simla.r Ja •BIS. i.. 51 '&gt; that Alban had the right to make such investment. The powers of a Financial Adviser are obviously limited. If the investment had not turned out successfully Alban would I think have placed himself in a veiy awkward position, and might possibly have had to make up to the State aiij loss which had occurred. Actually the State has gained and not lost, and the investment was undoubtedly made in good x'aith, and in what I Alban considered ifc to be in the interests of the State. 6. This being so in all the circumstances I think it would I be sufficient for me to address Alban a letter, allowing for the action in good faith, etc., as explained above, but expressing my disapproval of his having taken action without the consent of the Sultan. Do you approve of this sugges tion? 6. I enclose copies of the correspondence noted in the margin, 1. Letter Sated the 23rd March 1934 from the Sultan of Muscat to the Political Agent, Muscat. ' *1 2. Letter Ko.C/228 of 18th May 1934 to Captain H.G Alban, London. 3. Letter No.C/233 of 18th May 1934 to the Sultan of Muscat. 4. Letter No•607-3 of 30th June 1934 to with enclosures. which ) further ) ) explains ) ) the ) or Bremner,) situation ) as seen by I 1*1 the Sultan and by Alban.Xo. 62S-S of 1934. &amp; l C The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian (Julf presents his com pliments to Major C.E.U.Bremner f M.C., ^Political Agent, Muscat. I ■ I 1 : and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment /{/y. V 1 British Consulate-General, yM BUSHIRE. Dated 6th July 1934. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No.624 -S of 6th July 1934 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, without enclosures. Subject. Muscat Finances f v i\'U( ? 35/137 Telegram K.27 JTrom To i olitical Resident, i3ushire # Political Agent &gt; Muscat# Io»6l3 Dated 5tli July 1934 Important * Please refer to your letter of the 7th March No.299• Your paragraph 2. Presumably you have now had time to clear up matter v/ith the Sultan. As Alban handed over financial charge to Juli Chand in March 1933 vide paragraph 18 of Hep or t for financial No• 63, and as he left Muscat altogether in June personally I do not see how he can be held responsible in any way for the deficiency - at the close of the year. with regard to this or any other items in the Muscat finances please do not proceed on recess till you have gone into the matter thoroughly with Sultan and latter 1 s present financial assistant and are in a position to submit a detailed report. year l932|enclosed with your letter of 15th January 1934 If however you are of a different opinion Bri tconsul35 137 U U Telss^siii From To Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bushire No. 943 Dated 6th (receive! 7tli) July 1934 Your telegram No.613 I have at. no time suggested nor do I now that A lb an is responsible for deficiency quoted. Assistant it cannot be doubted that Duli Chand is always consulted. Sultan regrets inability to recall latter at this important season of year from ^atineh where he has been deputed on special duty collecting revenue and carrying out important assessment revisions on standing crops, -ms wij.1 take till at least mid-September. 3, Sultan cancelling former 1934 budget has now made new one showing approximately same totals but difierenu heads It appears studiedly incomplete and is very inaccurate. Am doing utmost for submission of a true budget but with Duli Chand in the background and in the aosence of reliable expert supervision doubt success of obtaining true figure^. 2 'ahilst Sultan states he has now no financial i-oliticalJ 35/137 &amp; 13/168 Telegram From To iso. 623 Bated 9th July 1954. H.27 Political Resident, £&gt;ushire Political Agent, Muscat. Your telegram j ^ o . 943 and letter of the 27th J une .fro.892. —— There is of course no need for you to postpone your recess on account of Sultan's new budget but i would be grateful for this with your oonanents as soon as possible. 2. My telegram of the 4th July fo.609 regarding medals. nave you approached oultan V I Britconsul35/137 Telegram 3?rom To No 624. Dated the 9th July 19 34 0 Political Healdent, Bush ire, Political Agent, Muscat. A Your letter of 19th June 0,157. Your suggestion approved. CONSUL- i/i/ 35/137 &amp; 13/168 fj M H. 27 Political Agent, Muscat. Political Kesident, Buahire. Te le gram From i To Ho. 184 Dated 30 th received 11th Jujtjr 1934. V / 7 Hi v V. dfijt r ,{n Reference your telegrams ^os.6l3 and 623 of 5th and 9th July respectively# in view of orders contained in former all my arrangements were cancelled and I commenced hearing important criminal cases. In interests of public and accused presume that these should 'be concluded before proceeding on recess. 2. Sultan awaits befitting public occa^son to present medal(s). Political ll Ox v' / I 3:' Mi36/137 Telegram R527. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat . No.629. Dated the 11th July 1334. V % Your telegram of 10th July, 184, paragraph 1. 1 said nothing about criminal cases in my telegram 613 and you must deal with them as you see fit* - Resident - 1 .&gt; I &lt; m V ICOEIBTIIIIAL. i o.C /173, of 1934. Political Agency &lt;?- II.B.r 's Consulate, Muscat, 29th June 1934. A From Ior C • TC.U. '-rennpr, M.C,, Political Agent Sr. Consul, Muscat, ■ iO The ITon'ble the Political Hesid' in tie Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject?- Allowance o^ Saiyid Fadir binlF^rr]., ^ ^ Sir, tZ3E2 V ' L T h^ve the honour to ^e^iort that in snite of what has hitherto transpired and of that the fact that only .|j&gt;- recently you personally inrorerred on Saiyid Nadir that the question o^ his allowances was not the concern of His Majesty's Government, this individual still nersists in addressing me on the subject. 2. I enclose copies of two letters recently received from him and my reply thereto. Letter A, was tynewritten in English and arm ears to be a translation (with minor omissions in the penultimate paragraph) of letter B, which was wrlt.ten in Arabic. These letters are indicative o^ the mulish attitude adopted by Saiyid Fadir, who seems incapable of understanding a. clear answer, o'^t rereated, anc endorsed to him personally by yourself. 3 # His Highness the Sultan informs me that Saiyid Nadir has, in the same way, repeatedly raised the question with him in spite o^ being consistently informed both- as to the reason for the reduction in the allowance and that while the State finances are still in their present condition Sa.iyid Jadir cannot exoect a restoration 0'^ -he cut. U Saiyid Nadir has also apparently communicated his ^ . 1 -u -r +V e. 1 n ttpr* ' P. ' 'grievance' to the Omam Shei . m ■m-2- son i^oha.'mnad, \.lio sg visi't 'bo Muscat, lias be011 re'nopt.ed. seDarately, raised the matter deferentially during one of his conversations with the Sultan, ^ ,3^ 5. 'Reference to Mr. ^/ingate's confidential No.160 dated 28th January 1921 shows that in replying to Sir Saiyid Taimur, that the matter was not the concern of His Majesty's Government's added a proviso i.e. 'subject to the condition tha.t the salaries granted are nart of the accepted civil list, that the State 'inpnces admit o^ ra^mient beinp- mad** 6. Should Saiyid Nadir nersist in again addressing myself or the Sultan on the subject and since he so consis tently endeavours to wilfully misconstrue Mr. Wingate's knowledge of the original transaction as a guarantee that Government would act as an arbitrator in case of any subse quent dismite, I would propose, with your concurrence, to bring the terms o^ this proviso to his. notice, stating that they constitute the only roints which interest Government. 7. This information could be conveniently conveyed to Saiyid Nadir in the Sultan's presence and might, if anything can, persuade him of the futility of persisting in his Drese nt contumacious attitude. I should be grateful there fore of your early orders on the suoject. 8. Finally I would add that the Sultan has informed me privately that Saiyid Nadir has darkly hinted his inten tion of proceeding to Dibai to take up his residence there in the event o^ his case not being 'amicably settled'. This baleful threat I regard as typical Arab bluff, unlikely of fulfillment. Should Saiyid Nadir carry it out it will be to his own detriment and not to tha.t of Muscat, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Poli Major, tical Ag^nt &amp; N.B.M's Consul, Muscat, ASN, ■ihhmhhLetter 'V, *j7 j io Translation. ■ Tl^e Political Arent o T T .' .H f s Consul, I'uscat • / /f After con^ 1 ±m ents, A*' J 'have the honour to acknowledp*e the receipt of your letter dated 2- 0 rd May 1 0 34, and to state that my allowance, as you know, is not like the salaries of the State's emnloyees. It was decided between Sultan m aimur and myself and fixed on the quantity referred to as a liability from him to me, Eis communication with Mr. Wingate, the then Political A.p-ent &amp;. F.P.M's Consul at Muscat on the subject, his request to the British Government to intermediate in case o'^ any future objection or cis ute ps is goinp* on now in the matter and the renxy O' the above Political Agent to him are all nroo^s showing that the British Government had concurred to allow that which the Sultan had desired. Under the circumstances I take the liberty o^ requesting the British Governmen' a^ain through voir- rood- self to settle this matter in a reasonable I f ee i J am confident that this matter cannot be settled excent th^ourh ^our good-self. I shall be rlad to have an early renly. Sd/- Nadir bin Faisalro.C/168 of 1934, |3 ^ Politic?! Agency f H.?.T'&gt;s Consulate, Muscat, 29fb June 1P34, To Saiyid Nadir bin Faisal, Muscat, A-ft er C omn 1 pnt s. I have the honour to ? 5 c v nov/ledp , e the receint o^ your letter o^ ^abi al avAval and its translation in Inflish, 2, My friend, as the Hon'hie the Political Resident has nersonnlly informed ^ r ou, an^ as I myself have been at pains severe! times to imnress on you, the matter o^ a.ny a Howe nee or salary neid to vou bv IH s Hip-hness the Snltan is not the c concern o - ^ m' ,r Government but is a matter purely restinf between l is Highness and yourself. 3. T Vhen His Highness Sir Saiyid Taimur originally mentioned to I r r. T 7ingate the then Political Agent, hi a proposal to make you en allowpnoe, Mr. •yingate returned him the same reoly that I now, end so often In the past, have given you. further than this I heve nothing more to add. This Is what had to he said and salaams• 2c /- C. F. • T • Mremn er, I a i o ^ Political Agent ^ H.B.K's Consul, Muscat.r^fidential 4 ' • 1 To No.674-3 Of 1934. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bush ire, the 16 th JULY, 1934* The Political Agenti _K_u_8_c_a_t i Allowanc a of Saivid Kadjr bin yaleaj,. Memorandum. Reference your letter Ho«C/173f dated the 29th June 1934* I concur with the action proposed in your para graphs Kos.e and 7. 2. If Salyid Nadir shows real signs of implementing his threat to proceed to Dibai, please infa m me by tele gram, as it may not be desirable that he should go there in such c ircumstances ad. S. Loch, Lieut.-Colonel, Officiating Political^Kesident in the Persian attested tL'V O tor Secretary to the roll Resident in the Persian ^-u - •CONFIDENTIAL. dated 28th May IS34. 2, As far as can be ascertained only two British merchants are owed money locally by the State. These are Nansi Madivji Rs 5,000/- and Pragji Ratansi Rs 1,600/-. is from private source. As Duli Chand holds the keys of the files concerned and is out on protracted tour, it is impossible to obtain further details, but 1 have heard, again privately, that the State intend liquidating these debts at the first opportunity. 4. A further debt incurred by Sir Baiyid Taimur has only now been admitted. This is a claim for Rs 9,630-13-o by Ramazan Ali of Karachi. There was a certain amount of doubt as to the authenticity of Sir Saiyid Taimur s sig nature on the bill but this has since been cleafced up and the Sultan proposes to pay by instalments. He has sought - my good offices to arrange the amount of these with the firm when I go to Karachi. 3 Neither have lodged claims here and the information The Hon f ble Lieut-Col.T.C.Fowle,B.B.ii., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf B u s h i r e.CONFIDENTIAL. No.C/ j of 1984. F rom To Major C. E. U* Bremiier, M.C., P olitical A gent and H. B. MA s C onsul, M uscat, The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf^ Bushire. ' l/^f 'JPl^Tkl^ I / B ritish A gency and C onsulate. . ' 1 f i . / f(*r ■nm* W Jr ' Muscat, the 10th July /.9S4 Subject:-Petition from Saiyid ^adir bin Faisal bin Turkey uncle of present Sultan of Muscat, complaining against reduction in his allowance. S ir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your printed letter No•556'^ dated 20th June 1934 and to inform you that the petitioner has been informed of the contents of the Government of ^-ndia letter through His Highness the Sultan of Muscat® I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B .M 's Consul, Muscat. ASN. S. G. p. i. 247 p. A. A H. B. m. Consml Muscat—6-12-11 500COWIDMTIAL. ^ . S imla, the 14th July 1934, clc&amp;x ^aurfjl I ^ | y IB ^ Thanks for your letter No.624-S of 1934, dated the 5th July 1934, regarding an investment made by Alban when acting as financial Adviser to the Muscat State. I agree with you that Alban should have obtained the Sultan 1 s consent and approval before making this investment unless he had been given some general power by the Sultan of investing the State surplus at his discretion, I gather from your letter that he had no such discretion, so that his action was technically wrong. At the same time it seems quite clear that Alban acted both in good faith and with proper financial prudence, so that I can not regard the offence as anything but extremely venial. The letter which you propose to address to him would seem to be suitable, but I think in expressing your disapproval you might lay stress on the technical nature of the mistake rather than on any other aspect. 2. I do not propose to take any further action in the matter. ^ 4 vvvo The Hon T ble Lt. Col. T .C .V. ; .Fowle,C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire,Air Mall. Confidential. d.C .H q .717_ S of 1934, The He&amp;ldeucy, Bushire, the 26th July 1934# V- I enclose a copy of Metcalfe's demi- official letter dated the 14th July -9S4(and of 0 yours to him). I would not worry you with this during your leave, hut the form of a rehuke of this sort is so very x&gt;s^sonal a matter 5 and it is possible that you may meet Alban. The Hon * ble Lieut.-Colonel T*C.^owle,^#-.^f C/o Lloyds Bank Limitecii 6 »all all 5 London *3 •W»l# fmm 1IW' pr 6 S 6 il o i. O j . li • i'ito }.d ^hn C S iiLkS jCliiiiClSd. HI 6 fa si ^JaL'JCiii 't© J.y Si \ ? O private note to ho win; xkx what he states to 'be the total assets and liabilities ci* the Muscat Government• A copy of this note is appended ior your information# 5. The totals of receipts and expenditure in His Ei^hness 's oud^et approximate closely tc those of A.b. Duli Chaa.&lt;l 1 s budget c. nd heye- •/id. a shulfle round of posts, conse quent on the creation of the new Department ''Dewan-i-oultan' ,. there appear to 'be no new points calling fox* spec -id notice. 6,, j-0 provision Las 'been made for uie payment of public dcots (L3. 16,130-13-0) due to British subjects, nor has any provision been rade for -repayment ^x to the Treasury of the advance (of 1:;, 15,000) taken by His Highness last his year in connection with/Onofar trip (vide paragraph 7 of General Comments forwarded with office letter hc,9o dated r 15/16th January 1934). 7, His Higimess has explained verbally tnat he propo ses to pay off the whole of the first item uais j^ai if possible and 'will do his best' regarding the second. Regard ing the non -provision of funds for the purpose, the bult^ states taut lie expects a lar^e excess this year over 'anti cipated revenues', out of which he pi-opose® to apportion oixe ginounts required. Hence ae has n-aae no actual ^loviv-j-on. 3, The Budget as a balaiice sheet shov&lt;ing ax a glance the btates total assets and liabilities, is useless, an annual atateEient of actual and anticipated receipts ana ex- . x - + t h.* State, if unencumbered, would be penai ture it shows wat ^ne .. 44-ti c-y -v* ** r~i ryyici in ^ creait oal anc e a ^ e able to pay its way with a reasonao-e end of the year. I have the honour to be, bir. Your most obedient servant. Ai : .a^ or. I'oj-itical As en ZI. nt ^ H.B.mSs Consul, Muses toSr. i C V ^otea on REVENUE (a) Unless a further extension of the Arms Traffic subsidy is granted, this item will be reduced in 1935 byjRs. 100,000/- (b) Decline due to fall in value of goods imported, this despite increase in Tariff introduced in 1933. (c) The comparatively large figure for 1933 fs due to collections in that year of arrears from 1932# (e) Explanation similar to(c) above. EXPENDITURE . (2) and (3) The total of these two items is approximately the same. (4) Saving due to sale of fc&gt;tate launch 'AL SA1D1 ,, (10) H.H. the Sultan hopes to discharge during 1934 the debts due to British subjects, amounting to about R8 .16,000/- but no specific provision has been made. ■i . UDated 5ra RaMa-us-Thani 1353 ! c ITrom. To. 16th July 1934* ' ~ ^[19% His Highness Sayed oaid 'bin Taimur Jul tan of Muscat and Oman % Muscat % The Hon # l)le Lieutenant Colonel T.CJ.fowle Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf Bash ire • p^&gt; iLTter Oompliments, In a most aus^ioious time I received your esteemed letter No, 180 dated the 3(Jth June 1934 / y * written to me in continuation of your No C/233 dated 18th May 1934 corresponding to the 4th 3afar 1353, regarding the £3000/- which dap tain ATban ,in his capacity as my Financial Advisor invested in the purchase of shares known as B-1970; Newfoundland shares on 'behalf of my Government. I understood what you told me verbally when you visited Muscat last month and what you have mentioned in your two letters quoted ahove• I also understood Captain Alha^s reply on the subject. I entertain no douht as to the correctness of your statement that CJapVain Alhan took the step with no other idea except to ootain pecuoiary Denetit for my 3tate and that the result aimed at haa turned out to oe satisfactory as explained oy you. Praise 'be to God for that. But what I desire to draw your attention to is the fact that no order was obtained ♦ from me for the purchase of the shares. Had the sum been lost Captain Alban, would have been,undoubtedly, responsible for it for he took the action without o the r . . „ consulting me. I have nonobjection as I know it lor certain that the said Oaptain Alban f s intention was good in this connection. Some time ago I informed Your Honour that I had the intention of selling these shares and deposit ing the proceeds in a Bank. I have since decided to carry this idea into eiiect. As soon^thereiorejaow I receive a letter from the Imperial Bank of Persia that these shares have been transferred to the Government of Muscat and have he en placed at my dlspoal 'by Oaptaln Alhan, I shall order the 3ank to sell them- . I have accepted with much pleasures the compliments from Captain Alhan and request you to genuine convey my/compliments to him if* you write a letter to hiic Usual Ending 29-7-34 7W—, ^ ^ fa •kCONFIDENTIAL. 709-S of 1934. /rh The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Di« Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to toff&amp;jait'-jfluiuttua, awuu *&amp;rid ~d *&amp;i- -Utfilt.ii)-acknowl«dg« receipt of the «0Ter from Hi a Highnesa the Sultan of Muscat forwarded with the Political Agent 9 a memorandum cited below* British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE 1 Dated .. 26 th. July . 19,3.4 •. Reference tocorrespondence : ending with Political Agent 1 a memorandufflmBb. 1023, dated the 17th July 1934. V^| Description of Enclosure. IIS Name and Date. Subject137^7 il U /M p.k.n-n*'* '''' ^ 5 ? 7A k wU ^ Il(~ 'z-gf % * l^uh-vvvimsiji La*. hvl^^u*^ fh £ '$'£-£/- prccsx^*-^ Without the Arms subsidy there will be a deficit of Rs24,000 on the Sultan's figures, which do not incikiide repayment of debts to Indian merchants. 2, I do not quite see how the Sultan's visit to India is going to be financed - I think that we shd tell the P.A. to keep his eye on this. 3. If the Arms subsidy is not continued , it will not be easy to balance the budget and impossible to /inance schools and so on. /y 29.8.34 to djl^u^ ' t i\ ^ x i i '&gt;</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/450</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/450</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 35/137 III (A 63) Muscat state budget’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (216 folios)</extent><extent>The volume’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The contents page at the front of the volume (folio 3) lists subjects in alphabetically ascending order, alongside the corresponding folio numbers. The office notes at the end of the volume (folios 201-07) mirror the volume’s chronological arrangement. These notes are numbered in red and black ink, which refer to the red and blue pencil numbers marked on some papers in the volume, which refer to received and sent correspondence respectively. Some items of correspondence have pencil annotations indicating the folio numbers of other, related papers in the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using circled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of rectos. An earlier foliation system, using uncircled numbers in the top-right corner of rectos, runs intermittently throughout the volume. The following foliation anomalies occur: 1a, 1b, 3a, 36a. The following folios are fold-outs: 10, 11, 13, 24, 25, 27, 58-82, 84, 85, 89-98, 111, 112, 143, 144. The following folios are inserts: 18, 118, 140.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence and other papers relating to the financial affairs of the Muscat State Government, including quarterly submissions of statements of revenue and expenditure, progress of loans and debt, and the cash balance of the Muscat treasury, for the period between July 1933 and July 1934. The chief correspondents in the file are Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and Major Claude Edward Bremner, Political Agent in Muscat.The volume contains papers relating to the following topics:An investment of £3,000 made by the Muscat State Government’s Financial Adviser, Captain Reginald Alban, in Newfoundland Government stock. News of the bankruptcy of the Newfoundland Government, as reported in
                              The Times(a press cutting of which is included in the volume, folio 18) led to British representatives in the Gulf seeking assurances of the security of the investment from Alban, who had by now resigned his post, and to the indignation of the Sultan of Muscat, Said Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr] who had not been consulted by Alban over the investment;Repeated complaints and petitions made by the Sultan of Muscat’s brother, Nadir bin Faisal bin Turki [Nādir bin Fayṣal bin Turkī] to the Political Resident, over a reduction in his monthly salary from the Muscat State Government, which he claimed broke the terms of an agreement made between himself and the Sultan. The Resident ruled that the complaint was a private affair, and not one demanding British intervention;A report on the Muscat State financial year for 1933, with budget estimates for 1934 (folios 39-99);A revised budget, submitted by the Sultan of Muscat, in the absence of an appointed Financial Adviser, following Alban’s departure and subsequent resignation (folios 170-190).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Financial Advisor to the Sultan of Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Financial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>State budget</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001a7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>