<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000213_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T09:45:41.493Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(E 4800/305/91) Dear Peel, With reference to your letter to Baxter, P.Z.5515/38 of the 12th August, regarding the payment of certain Muscat taxes by British subjects, I write to say that we agree that since the new treaty will probably be brought into force in the very near future and Powle is strongly of opinion that the position should be left as it is until then, we can &lt; postpone any action to regularise the existing taxes. This is written on the assumption, however, that the treaty will come into force soon.0 3.0.HQ.1415 file copy The Residency, M ^ S BU3h-i3fe-v -SSth July 1938. / # / * v ? hh (f 3?7, ~ i a •&lt;? - ! \ J 93 S- Could you please refer to correspondence ending with your letter N 0.2.Z.3251/38, dated the 14th May 1938, on the subject of regularising the payment of certain Muscat taxes by British subjects. 2 ‘ 1 ll0 P e 1 a* 1 not being stupid but I still do not see tne necessity or desirability of regularising now the taxes in question. 3 * ^ke situation is that until the new treaty is brought into force, which will be very shortly, there are certain taxes the legality of which is doubtful under the existing treaty, but which British subjects had been paying to the Muscat Government without any complaint until about a year or so ago, when the new treaty came on the tapis. 4. Under the new tceaty the Sultan obtains fiscal autonomy and can imjose what taxes he likes, which may' or may not be the present ones: in point of fact I expect he will overhaul his present fiscal system. Sven if we regularise the present taxes before the new treaty comes into force as suggested by the foreign Office thi q in n . o uxi ice, oins m no way restricts the Sultan's powers to change them. Would it not be simpler therefore to wait until the new treaty is in force, see what taxes the Sultan actually imposes and then take action under Article lb of the new treaty to regularise them ? v/atts. I am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and tJ-Uc/V} F ^ J.j?. G-ibson, Esquire, India Office, CJR0. PHI. Ik rf. London ^ 8 AUG 1938 INDIA OFFICE ^v^vLa “T. c - * sent under P.l.No.Ul? of 23 / 7 / 38 .r (E 649/305/91) P. Z. ) K 7 19 ppRSION OFFICE, S.Vf.l. 6th May, 1938. ft u 0 ' My dear Gibson, You my recollect that Beckett mentioned to you the other day - when discussing Muscat Treaty matters - the question of regularising the position under v/hich for many years past British subjects in Muscat have been paying certain Muscat taxes and municipal duties. This question has formed the subject of correspondence between the India Office and ourselves resting with your letter P.Z. 610/38 of the 2nd February to Baggallay. 2. In view of the provisional agreement which we understand has now been reached with the Sultan on the text of the new Treaty with Muscat our views may be set out as follows. 3. Under the treaty as now proposed no laws or regulations of the Sultan of Muscat or of Muscat municipalities,/ —municipalities, including laws and regulations imposing taxes and customs duties, will be enforceable against British subjects in Muscat until their text has been posted up at the office of the political Agent, though we have undertaken, in the case of legislation imposing taxes and duties, municipal regulations and customs duties, to post the text of the Muscat regulations more or less automatically and without delay. 4. In view of the foregoing it now seems clearly desirable that the position with regard to the duties and taxes referred to in paragraphs 6 and 9 of Beckett f s minute, a copy of which was enclosed in Baggallay^ letter S 6399/689/91 of the 5th November to you, should be regularised as soon as possible. The duties and taxes affected are those shown in the Political Resident s letter No. 1412/35/116 of the 22nd July to the Government of India as municipal taxes (a) to (e) but excluding (b), in place of which a new municipal tax is being imposed, and the state taxes (g) (h) and (i). 5. The position must, we suggest, either be regularised before next February, when the prolongation of the existing treaty with Muscat comes to an end, underm the existing procedure of King’s Regulations, or after February next, when the new Treaty will come into force, under the new procedure of posting. l&lt; T e suggest that as far as possible all these duties and taxes referred to above should be regularised before February next under the old procedure. In the case of those duties however which are to be regarded as customs duties we should wait until after February next when on the coming into force of the new treaty the political agent will have to collect and post all the Muscat laws with regard to customs duties in order to start the new regime with a clean sheet in this respect. At present, customs duties need no action by us to be enforceable against British subjects (see paragraphs 8 and 9 of Beckett’s minute to which I have already referred).jT s? &amp; FllE COPY CONFIDENTIAL _ p . . ' '■ Ci c o « w\. W 7 ^ No. C/258 I y 2 . C K 1 M f. WWa,,# ^ f .N. • ' Ttt The Hon’ble the Political Reahkatu'in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to ^ 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, ^ S' Lond on. 2. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bahrain. BKit!^£lioxx)adad3e36iKixxxk^8:t[^B£b«Bt - ^ l&lt;v- Dated...20th .April. 1938. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency letter Ho. 67/35/116 of 13th January 1938, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. (1) Muscat Municipal Notification No.1 of 1356. (2) Notification of 13th March 1938 by Political Agent, Muscat. Subject. Muscat Municipal Taxation ireco. 27, APB 1938 |lNDlAOFnC&amp; — —TRANSLATION Notification From Shahab bin Faisal. By an order issued by His Highness the Sultan, Saiyid Sa* id bin Taimur, His Highness’s Notification is hereby republished. Notification to all the residents in Muscat and Matrah. The public are not unaware that at present there is no regular department to consider matters of organisation of the roads and houses of both towns of Muscat and Matrah, as is the case in all other countries of the world. As the existence of such a department is an indispensable necessity in modern times, We have decided to establish a special department to carry out this project which is one of advantage to both the country and its people. This department will be independent in the enact- menu of its own regulations and the carrying out of its duties as provided by them, and whatever comes under this, such as (the issue of ) Notifications etcetra. It is, however, well known that the maintenance of such a project requires an adequate contribution. Therefore, We have imposed one anna on each package which is liable to customs duty in Muscat and Matrah. This Notification will be known as Municipal Notification No.l of 1356.NOTIFICATION A_J » O &amp; Q ^ Sc/ V* Under the powers conferred on him b^t ^i»g^s Regulation No.l of 1935 the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is pleased t o direct that within the limits of 'The Muscat Order in Council 1915' the provisions of Muscat Government Municipal Notification No.l of 1356 (corresponding to 1937-38) shall be binding on the persons specified in Article 8(l), (2) and (3) of the said Order. Sd. R.P. WATTS, Major, I.A. Political Agent and H.B.M. Consul, Muscat. Dated the 13th March 1938k &lt; # D.O. No. 67 /35/U6 A 4&gt;V &lt; ~ X ^ Q-' A Carffp, Kuwait*- . Zjdate^d the 13th January, 1938, r~y 610 1933 cCcart ^ &lt;XA^yu ie- 5 1*1 )l Please ref^r to correspondence forwarded uncler India Office Printed Letter No. 7246/1137, dated the 17th November, 1937, on the subject of the taxation of British subjects in Muscat and containing Becketts* interesting minute on this subject. 2. I have now been able to go into the question, and the following are my views on the various heads of the taxation levied on British subjects: (l) Levy of an import duty of one anna per package. Our agreement is essential to its imposition in view of the promise we have made to the Sultan and our draft notification will be issued directly the Sultan has issued his. In this connection, so Watts informs me, though the Sultan said he would havethis done before his departure on his travels, his Representative has done nothing in the matter. The latter is away on tour, when he returns, Watts will tackle him on the subject. i j Municipal Taxation. This is made up of the taxes (a) to (e) inclusive in paragraph 2 of iqy despatch No. 1412/35/116 dated the 22nd July, 1937, with the exception of (b) which is being abolished. The initiative here also/- J.C. Walton Esquire, GB., MC. , The India Office, London. »ECd. POL BEPl. 2 8 JAN 1938 INDIA OFFICEalso lies with the Huscat Government and as soon as a list of taxes they propose to impose is submitted to and approvec by me, the list can be exhibited under Kings Regulation 1 of 1955. My own opinion, however, is that considering a new treaty is about to be negotiated shortly with the Sultan, in which the whole question of taxes of all sorts will be raised, there is little advantage in having these taxes which have been paid for many years now by British subjects and which have the force of custom if nothing else behind them, put on a formal and legal basis. If I thought that their regularization would in any way strengthen our position with the Sultan over the new treaty, I would of course fall in with Becketts' opinion at paragraph 7 of his minute that they should be formally regularized. I do not see that we actually gain the advantage, ja&amp;L/in any case I can do nothing until the Muscat Government submit this list for my approval. (3) State Taxation. Taxes (f) to (j) in paragraph 2 of my above cited letter. My remarks on Municipal taxation apply with even greater force tc these taxes, more particularly as their legal imposition would involve the making of a new Kings Regulation. Here again these taxes have been paid by British subjects without demur for many years, and I would prefer to leave them alone. am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and Watts. -C-hvSZcGopy-ag , fir ; 7432 | 1957 j IT/PJi(./VH„ (179 groups,) DECT yii S R. o 7 e l e g r a. m Fr ODi 4999 COPISS CIRCULATED) Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulp to Foreign Secretary to Government of India,External Affairs Department*and repeated by the former tc Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Risher,13th November,!93?„ Received IP.15 p„mo, 13th November,1937 1104 o Addressed to Foreign, New Delhi repeated to Secretary of State for India 0 Following is repetition of my telegram No o 1096, November 6th, to Political Agent,Muscat. Begins 0 jndia Office telegram No.2678, November 5th 0 iiuscat treaty and 2 e I must leave moment^Por approaching Sultan with request for prolongation mainlvj^your discretion (see paragraph N0o4 of my telegram No. lOT^fbut it seems desirable to broach matter before you re^Delhi. You may ^Iso find useful argument from Sultan s d^Tt Article NOoIc ou can now link request for prolongatj. on of ea 1; ’ L ' £ ;re ' to municipal taxation , emphasising that tax ii ^ i: • i'', i Oiii m st be regarded as temporary foundation of ‘ :i !l • ?a ' :ni J - tore, and may have to be recast by committee when .’uisoitu ed, on should also make clear that details of the constiuubion, byelaws,etc, will have to be further considered by permanent $,e si dent. Please keep me informed of action taken and rssu] Eruls 0 i ol Lovvj.ng is repetition of telegram T, /§ iPtt ■ 0- -1 or, ! 01 Pol bical Agent, Muscat. Beg ins, Tour telegram 109f 6th November, Muscat treaty, I have had two long discussions with Sultan following the line indicated by you, Sultan has set his heart/heart on rapid realisation of fiscal and tariff autonomy and is most reluctant to prolong the present treaty at all r . I think however I have made him realise the practical impossibility of completing the new treaty before the expiry of existing treaty and the necessity of avoiding interregnum,, However I have great hopes of being able to finally persuade him in Delhi before he leaveso Ends 00 ^ \ v &gt; (E 6399/689/91) Immediate. * : / n I 7243 ! j Ci 7 POREIGK OFFICE, S.W.l. 5th November, 1937. ff Dear Gibson, I am sorry that we have not been able to reply earlier to your letter P.2. 7052/37 of the 29th October enclosing the draft of a proposed telegram to the Political Resident about the taxation of British subjects at Muscat. The question of Muscat taxation is, however, exceedingly complicated, and Beckett has felt it necessary to go thoroughly into the question before expressing an opinion upon the action which is now proposed. The result is what is, I think you will agree, an exceedingly valuable minute, of which I enclose a copy. 2. In the circumstances, I suggest that the telegram should be sent as drafted by you, but with the following additional paragraph: ’’Furthermore, the position with regard to 'municipal taxes ought to be regularised as soon as possible/ j. p. Gibson, Esq. IN ' 6NOV1S37 DiA &lt;jrf }QE’•possible thereafter by means of formal approval by ’’Political Resident under King’s Regulation No. 1. ”of 1935 of those of existing taxes which are, or ’’should be, municipal taxes (i.e. (a), (c), (d) and '(e) in Political Resident’s letter of the 22nd ’’July) and of the proposed new tax as soon as it comes ’’into force, and by exhibition at Agency as prescribed ”by King’s Regulation of the Regulations imposing them 3. You will see that Beckett has also expressed the opinion that the question with regard to the rest of the taxes ought also to be regularised, notwithstanding the fact that a new treaty is on the point of being negotiated. Since the negotiations will probably take some time, this certainly seems desirable, and we should be grateful if you would consider this and let us know in due course whether you see any objection. Yours evermm t Copy (K 69^9/669/ Uoc;„y IaX..tion There axe variola i.ointa arising oit of this file of papers about which I wish to say aoaething, but I will begin with the question of aunioipal taxes which ia the point which actually arises on this particular paper# I gether froa the des t ,ttch of July 22nd from the Political Keaident thet thexe have been five s ecles of taxes (lettered (a) to (e)) which hcve been levied on British subjects etc# in .?iaoat now for a long period, and which are taxfi of a character which. If there were organised municipalities and their proceeds were devoted to munici^ &amp;1 purposes, would be properly classified as municipal taxes* am a matter of fact, as I mderatand the papers, there are no municipalities at present in the State of iusoat, though there ia some prospect now of their being organised. It is not aiade clear on the pe; era whether the proceeds of these taxes simply go into the ordinary State Treasury or whether they ere specially devoted to the provision of what woulo ordinarily be called municipal services, sanitation, water, etc* 2. There is s s ; ecific article in the 1891 Treaty wtlth Uscat with regard to municipal duties, namely Article 19, which reads as follows: ’’It is hereby agreed between the two high cont parties, that, in the event of an agreement being after arrived at between His Highness the SUta o Auaeat and the various Powers with which His Highness shall be in treaty relations, including Great Britain, which must be a consenting party, whereby the residents of/of a district or to«i shall* witho it distinction of nationality* !&gt;« m de subject to the ayraent of loeal taxes* for municipal f*nd sanitary p irposes* the same to be fixed and administered by or under the control of s a. eciel bot rd* nothing contained In this treaty shell be understood so as to exempt British residents from the payment of s ich taxes'*. Under this article. If the Sultan of Muscat and H.4.0 and the other towers who have treaties with Unseat (via. France and the U.s&gt;.^.) agree to the levy of a certain tax for municipal purposes, and it Is arranged that the ttxes shall be administered by a board, British subjects shall be made liable for these taxes. It is perfectly cleer therefore that British subjects are not liable for these taxes unless H. \. 0 .consent. 4. In l»d5 a King’s Regulation was mace called the Miueoat Municipal Regulations 1936 mud under this King’s Regulation 'rules issued to and taxes in osea on lusost subjects by the Muscat State Government for the pro er conservancy and sanitation of the towns of Muscat and Muttra nay with the approval of the 1 olitioal Resident and with such modifications as he may think fit to make be made applicable to end leviable from all persons f, who ere subject to British Jurisdiction in Muscat*. The rules and taxes approved by the olitical Resident are to be exhibited at the office of the Political Agent in Muscat and ere not enforceable unless and until exhibited. &amp;• do far as I can understand it (slthough I should add that I have not been able to secure the Political Resident’s aemorandm of July Rnd* 1936* which he refers to in his despatch of July 2knd and which apparently gives some explanation as regards the whole position of British subjects in Muscat with regard to taxation) in spite of the Treaty article/article unu in aplte of the King’s Regulation, which xeally enbodiee a aodlfloatlon of the teeaty article to the benefit of the Muscat Gover ment (seeing that It eliainetea the necesaity of the consent of Prance and the U.b**# and the constitution of a hoard), none of these five aunlcli&gt;el taxes (a) to (e) have hecn approved by the Political Resident or posted at the office of the Political Agent, but we seen to have siia ly gone on allowing them to be levied without either objecting to them or else taxing the proper procedure under the King's Regulation for making them applicable to British subjects* This discloses a state of siTalrs which from the legal point of view is somewhat odd, although perhaps the absence of protest from British subjects until &lt;iuite recently and the failure of the Muscat Government to establish municipalities are partially res fc onsible. Still if folitioel ^gent knows the taxes are being levied he does not have to welt for the Individuals to protest* u* how. If 1 understand It, the Idee is that a municipality will be formed and that a new municipal tax ahell be levied (oduly enough in the form of an addition to customs duties), while one of the five municiyalatexes mentioned ©bove is to be dropped and the Gultan undertakes that he will not levy at present any municipal taxes other than the four old ones and this new one; and that this Is what we ;re now asked to assent to* I assume that the proceeds of these taxes will now go to the ‘’Conservancy and sanitation of the towns of Musoat ana Muttra*'* 7* I think our reply should be that we agree that these proposals should be assented to; and that the Political Resident ehoula in consequence immediately formally approve the four old minicipel taxes which are being retained and the new one ©s soon as it comes into force end should exhibit at the office of the i olltioal Agent the regulations la. oslng these taxes in the manner prescribed by King's Regilatton No*l of 1955* It/It la laport&amp;nt to get bade «e aoon aa «e oan to the yroviat ona of Article 19 of the Muaoat Treaty of 1891 ea aodiilea by the King’s Regulation No. 1 of 1956 and begin to try am tl&lt;ce these things once aore upon a regular footing. 8 . Then the question la Uiaoiaaed as regards other taxes which the hultan oi' Mueoat haa been levying for years on British subjects, etc., that ie to say, taxes which cannot be regarded as municipal taxes. The first question la whether he is debarred from doing this under the Treaty of 1891. There la no specific provision In this treaty about texes and if he is debarred from taxing British subjects without H.^.a’s consent it is under Article 13, which provides that British a objects enjoy the rights of exterritoriality. In principle exterritoritaity does imply x'reedom from all local direct taxation on personal property (unless assented to by the exterritorial power) bit not from indirect taxation, viz. * cisterns duties. This interpretation is reinforced as regards Mascot by the provisions of Article 19 with regard to minicipal taxes becsvise if the Multan h*&gt;d the right to impose taxation on Britiah subjects in general it 1 b clear that article 19 could not have been framed In the way it was. ho far «e customs duties ore concerned, however, the rights of the tfultan ore agoin limited, but this time by Article of the Treaty imposing a 6 . limit and by the a.f.n. provision in that article coupled ' with the U.tt.A. and French treaties. (It occurred to me at first that we might be prejudicing our rights under Article z, in assenting to this new municipal tox which I have discussed above, because it appears to take the form of an additional customs duty raising the total no doubt above the 6 • I think that this is all right, however, if It is clear that this is only imposed when we have assented to it.)9* The t&amp;*es which the Multan hee imposed other than amiolpal taxes arc in (r) to Q) or the letter or July 22 nd end it la I think rightly stated that of these, (f) Is not a tax hut rent* (j), Weighing charge, is in ay opinion indirect tax more in the net ire of a customs duty and therefore has to be considered rather in relation to Article 6 than with regard to the &lt;£aestion of exterritoriality* Customs duties and the like do not need King*# Regulations to be made applicable to British subjects. (g), (h) *nd (i) are t*xes whleh the Sultan has no right to impose on British subjects unless we have assented to them and made the appropriate King’s Regulation* It is quite reasonable to at such taxes should in X'act be levied, but it is curious that during all these years we have not taken the prOi er course of formally assenting to them and making the King’s j Regulation, and I should have tho ight that even now, if we have no objection to them, we ought to regularise the position end nuke King’s Regulations* 10* I see that in connexion with the renewal of the Treaty ou 1891 the bultan of Muscat aske for tariff autonomy* This means the abrogation of Article 6. 1 would point out in this connexion, however, that the mere abrogation of the limit of customs duties in Article 6 of our treaty will not affect the purpose immediately if we retain m.f.n. rights (as I imagine we certainly will) because of the siailar limits in the Treaties with Rrance and the U*S*A* I have raised the question elsewhere whether we should in the treaty negotiations with the French about orocoo attempt to obtain their agreement to the abrogation of the customs limit with Muscat in the French treaty* X think it is clear the French will not give ip their limit, at rny rate unless we do too* Further, it occurs to me that they may try and object to our trying to negotiate things for the sultan of Muscat/iattCttt $a pert of our Morocco negotiations on the ‘basis of the inde enaence or Muscat in the 1662 declaration, bit I do not icnow whether they will. 11* The Multan or iusoat elso esks for fiscal autonomy, that is to say, tne free right to tax foreigners and we a psrently take the view that it mey be right to give him this, bit that we must retain oir exterritorial rights. Actually the H alts on his ilscal a itonoiay arise out of the exterritorial rights so that what we mean is that we are prepared to agree to the waiver of Just this part of our exterritorial rights, while retaining the remainder. The d^afion, however, is not free from teohnical diiilculty because the taxes ia. oseu on British subjects etc. by the Multan oi Muscat would hive to be emarced through our court ena it is really desirable that before Muscat Regulations etc.; imposing texes should be enforceable through our courts they should be covereu by a iiing’s Regilation. This . oint might be met best, if we «.re prepared to agree in principle, by our undertaking to mike King’s Regalationa ana enforce Muscat tfxes on British subjects, etc. provided th* t they are not discriminatory. (We can thinx later if we want to frame some other safeguard.) Xu, in the papers the question was raised as to whether the Sultan of Muscat should ask for and be given formally British protection and this suggestion was for the moment turned down. In this connexion I would drew attention to whet is after all a most important ^oint in this connexion, namely, whether the French would tnd ooild object to this on the basis of the 1362 declaration. (ogd) w.E. Beckett. 4th liovem b er. 1^57 .DEC &lt;,.T sO*' r\ fkb/cwp/aw. (COPIES CIPCULATED) Prom Acting Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Dated Risher, 26th October, 1937. Received 26th October, 1937, 4*15 p.m, X 1024. 27iOC 3JBI( j OFFiOfij Addressed to India Office repeated to Government of . \ India and Muscat. Your telegrejn R p.2590, 25th October. Muscat., Political Agent anticipates difficulty in persuading Sultan to agree to prolong treaty, and urges that the task will be greatly facilitated if speedy assent can be given to the new municipal taxation proposed by the Sultan. 2. Pursuant to Powle T s letter to the Government of India Doo1412 , 22nd July, Sultan has now produced scheme for the (? municipality), of which taxation (? basis) is surcharge of one anna per package liable to customs duty, to be imposed by notification on Muscat and British subjects alike. Tex is not included in those listed in Powle’s letter, but Sultan states i Harrasi will be withdrawn simultaneously with imposition of new tax, and no further municipal taxation imposed at present. Tax, in my opinion,is in principle unobjectionable and in accord with Gulf practice. 3. I had wished to leave the question of municipal organisation end taxation until Fowle f s return. As, however, municipal taxation on British subjects is regularised by King’s Regulation ho. 1 of 1935 and in view of the Sultan’s real interest in the question and the importance of the time factor, I propose, if Fowls has no objection, to authorise this tax forthwith in the hope of obtaining readier co-operation in treaty matters. 4 0 In other respects the Sultan’s municipal scheme, thoughf /f~\. c - 2 - though not entirely in accordejice v/ith Powle T s suggestions, beers the mark of careful thougxrt. Proposed committee is to be joint for Muscat and Mattra, and to consist of President and 8 members (including 5 British subjects) nominated by the Sultan for fixed % period. There is provision for annuel budget. In authorising taxetion f it could be stipulated that approve! to details of constitution would have to await further consideration on Powle f s return.from The in the eternal .kffaira Jepartwent* ylM~ To The Hon'ble the Political iieeiuent in the i eraian Qulf* liated iimla# the \^&gt; U ♦epterabar 1937* Taxation of 3ritiah aubjecte at Uuecat* air* pr ^ -ith reference to your letter Ko*1412/3t/116, dated the 22nd July 1937 1 I ara directed to aay that in the cireuroetances explained the Government of India accept the aur^eationa in regard to both municipal and dt&amp;te taxes contained in paragraphs 4 to 7 of your letter under reply except in so far as weiring charges are concerned. 2. No similar charges are recovered in Iidia, and the /Overament of India consider that if possible steps should be taken when the freaty is under revision to ensure that British subjects are in future exempted from them* as, however, they are very small, the Government of India do not desire to press the matter unduly if it is likely to give rise to difficulties and so long as their present incidence is not raised. 3* A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. I have the honour to be 9 Your mout obedient servant Sd/-.».H. Kay. deputy oecreWy to the Government of India.Minute Paper. political Department. The extra-territorial rights of British subjects in Muscat are based on Article 13 of the Treaty of 1891 - copy flagged at A below. privilege of immunity from taxation is correct. But this privilege is not so much a specific treaty right but rather the consequence of the immunity of British subjects from Muscat jurisdiction, i.e. of the fact that such taxation cannot be enforced upon them by legal process either in the Muscat Courts (to which they are not amenable) or in the British Courts (which, in the absence of specific legislation, have no legal sanction for taking action in the matter). been recognised, since by a King’s Regulation issued in 1935 (see Colin.25/17) all persons resident in Muscat who are subject to the Muscat Order in Council of 1915 are required to pay certain municipal taxes- No steps have, however, been taken in regard to other forms of taxation, and, in the absence of some instrument such as the King’s Regulation referred to above, British subjects can to the position in China where British subjects enjoy to Chinese taxation generally is nowadays governed by the / Off*** terms or tne I’reaty/of January 1927 in which H.M.G. offered to accept as payable by British subjects all regular and non-discriminatory Chinese taxation paid by Chinese throughrut China. V/hile^ except in a few cases of Municipal ta 2- I believe Sir Trenchard Powle’s assumption that the grant of extra-territorality carries with it tu. 3. That such immunity is hardly reasonable has already 4. legitimately claim immunity. 4. In this connection it may be of interest to refer extra-territorial rights. The attitude of H.M.G. in regardsteps have not yet been taken to render-such Chinese national taxation formally binding on British subjects, the attitude nowadays is to acquiesce tacitly in its payment provided it is reasonable,.regular and non- discriminatory, and to advise British subject^ with a view to avoiding friction with the Chinese Authorities, accordingly. 5. The position in Muscat appears to be that hitherto British subjects have not objected to paying all regular Muscat taxation which has been paid by Muscat subjects, and, pending a revision of the existing Treaty, it seems ty- (V/vc&lt; desirable^that British subjects should be advised to continue to pay the taxes provided they are reasonable, regular and non-discriminatory.Wo. M/A /35/116 28 SEP 1957 ft ofl th ® ^ ^ /i*d July # 1^37 ' 5267 H ‘^'37 Sir, To ''Vom Th« n^crwtnry to the Goyermneot of ^Ttemnl A^ffelrs De-pertment, £ The Hon # hle the Polltloel *R©sifler)t In the Perelen r^nlf. Oration of British suhjeets J I heve the honour to inform you that there are a number of taxes imposed by the Muscat Government which British subjects have been paying for many years past without raising any objection* 'Recently however, perhaps because the taxes are now being enforced more rigorously under Bi P Highness the Sultao f s present regime, objections have been raised by the British subjects affected* 2. The taxes in question are as follows a T 5 octroi tax of 5# afl. valorem on dates and other produce brought into Muscat or Matrah for sale. BaxrasJL* A tax ranging from i to 2 Haria Teresa dollars (present rate fe* 135 to 100 dollars) per mensem from owners of shops in Ma trail (but not Muscat) for the payment of night-watchmen in the bazaar. ^ ^-Qtor-car tax* A registration fee for taxis R%50 per annum. ■Registration fee for private ears- fe. 25/- P©r annum. 'Driving licence - fc*lo/- per annum* el-pal sh0T3 tax . 80 Balsas (totalling 2 annas) per mensem per shop in Kusoat and Matrah. J2 ^ ^Indow tsx &gt; A. few ftr^'nni! om eecb naflltional wlnflow opened in e shop - non-recurring* (t) 3iaUi_aUIaI. a sum not exceeding 3 do Hers per ennum according to the sise and value of the property (see also paragraph 6 helow). (g) 'akat . b% of the estimated annual yield of each rard an. ZlalLJiax. afl. valorem on all fish landed in Muscat territory. A further 5^ for hrolcerage on those edihle varieties which have to he sold hy puhHc auction. r Hiere is no tax on 'qaeba', the fish which is exported in large nuantities for manure after having been dried. H.8h 1 n g »h q p t tan; ■ 8 to 30 dollars a year accord ing to the size of the vessel. '.1) I^^.lTIg.-.shalCgL^iA anna per 20 Muscat mounds '18^ lbs) on all imports from foreign countries. 3. Taxation can he divided into two categories!- Of the list in the previous paragraoh taxes lettered ^a' to ^e) f inclusive, should he municipal taxes and (f) to state taxes. 4. ^he orirclole of municipal taxes has been regularised /3'S. in King’s Tegulation w o. 1 of 1938 , (see correspondence ending with this -eBi^ency memorandum ^o. 1488/18/54 of the 22nd T uly t 1935,) f and when muni cl pa li ties have been formed by the Muscat Hovernment, and the list of taxes has been submitted to me, I will consider them. Tith regard to these taxes there is no doubt that until they have been formally approved by me, as provided by the King’s Begpin ti on mentioned above, they are ultra xi£fia. However, as they (l) Municipal '2) State. have/ i3- h*vs for tb© last 45 yaars or so and as the Treaty is due for revision in February next year, I do not pronose to raise any objection to their continued Imposi tion at present* 5. w ith regard to state taxest on the broad issue, whether British subjects should pay taxes or not depends on whether the rieht of exterritoriality, which they enjoy under Article 1$ of the Treaty of friendship, Commer ce and Navigation between Great Britain end Muscat, 1891, ^Aitchlson Vol.'H, page 314), gives in itself total exemp tion from all taxes* This I assume to be the view of His *aJe«ty f B Government since otherwise there would have been no need to pass the special Hlng*© Regulation, (vide correspondence ending with my memorandum No* 14^8/lB/54, dated the ©nd Tuly, 1933,) in order to maVe municipal taxes apulicable to British subjects* If my assumption is correct then no taxes can be applied to British subjects ( unless they are specifically allowed in the Treaty* 6* however, as state taxes are being paid it remains to examine each on its merits, since their continued payment is bound to arise in connection with the revision of the Treaty* ^e Gultan will almost certainly press for con tinued payment* (f) HeJLt al Tn the time of Hohammad the term Beit al v al meant the Government Treasuryt i*e* the whole |i of the revenues of Government* Tn Muscat, however, accord ing to the Sultan, the term denotes a particular form of payment, nnmely, the rental on crown-lands leased out* The tax is not claimed from persons, amongst whom there are several British subjects, who hold their land in free hold, but only fYom those who are in occupation of crown- lands. This rental is one of the payments to which British subjects^ ^ t-4 subjoctii oT&gt;J©ct# It eeemB clear to me, however, tbet their ohjcctlor caoTiot he eupportefl, alrce the payment 1 b e rental enfl not e tax. %afr?»t . The parent of this t»x f which corresponds to lend revenoe, turns on the answer to the question of whet exemption is conferred hy exterritoriality (see para- ffreph 5 above)» (h) The fish tex turns upon the seme principle as that of (*) t except that it is possible that the produce may not be cau*ht in Muscat territorial waters, but on the hiffh Seas. ?art of this tax, i.e, the brolreraffe, seems to be municipal* (l) '’be boat tax is a pain a ouestion of exterritorial riyhts. ^here are about 9 boats owned by British subjects. (J) ’ eight tic chwrgea . This lo charged hy the Muscat Otistoms department• 'Hie second paragraph of Article 6 of the ^Yeatv states as follows*- 'This duty, once paid, shall cover, from all other charges on the part of Bis Bighness the Hulten, goods of whatever description coming from foreign countries by sea, whether these are intended for local consumption or for transmission elsewhere in bulk or otherwise, and whether they remain in the state in *4iich they are imported or i have been manufactured*. Tf this is to be read strictly then it would appear that the British subjects are not liable to extra weighing charges. On the other hand, I believe that such charges are made by the ^stoms Depart ment in other countries and if such charges are made by the Indian Customs, e.g. at Karachi and Bombay, it might be argued that they are similarly applicable in Muscat. 7. T d1sc\?ssed the question of these taxes at length with ^is Highness the Sultan and with Bajor Batts on my recent visit to The Sultan contended that these taxes/tares Itj could Tbo le^nlly cTrpllcd to Brltiuh flut&gt;Jocts, T loforwod His Wlghneas tb«t T would report tbe whole wettm* to t T ip ’XiestvV ^OTemment «od obteio their deelsloo oo the wetter eod that in the ween time British subjects could continue paying the taxes without prejudice to the final settlement of the question, 1 was Influenced In this view by the fact that the payment of the taxes Is a cun tom which has h^com© firmly established In the course of time and suddenly to stop their payment would have been Imnolltlc. T surest that there ahould be no change In the ata tus quo until the provisions of the new Treaty have been agreed upon. T am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s Seeretpry of Rtnte for Tnflls nofl the Political Aftent, Kenent T bpve the hoeowr to ho, Sir, Your most obedient servsnt, for Polltieel Pesident in the Persian Culf. MNOTICE. 'i he following Regulations, made by His Britannic Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and allowed by one of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State, are published for general information. T. C. FOWLE, Lieutenant-Colonel, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bush ire, July 18, 1935. Kino s Regulations under Article 78 of the Muscat Order in Council, 1915. No. 1 of 1935. Municipal. In pursuance and by virtue of the powers vested in the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf under Article 78 of the Muscat Order in Council, 1915 :— 1. King’s Regulation No. 2 of 1911 (Municipal) is, under Article 88 (2) of the Muscat Order in Council, 1915, hereby repealed. 797 &gt; 116462 /TV, 2. The rules issued to, and the taxes imposed on, Muscat subjects by the Muscat State Government for the proper conservancy and sanitation (including the preservation of buildings in a condition not dangerous to the public) of the towns of Muscat and Muttra shall, with the previous approval of the Political Resident and with such modifications, if any, as he may think fit to make, be applicable to ^ and leviable from all residents of those towns being persons referred to in Article 8 (1) (2) and (8) of the Muscat Order m Council, 191d^, Rules and taxes, approved with or without modifications by tlv Political Resident, shall be exhibited at the office of the Political Agent at Muscat and shall not be enforceable under this article until so exhibited. 8. The Political Agent, Muscat, is hereby empowered to take such action as he may deem necessary to ensure the observance of the said rules in regard to property within the said towns owned by any persons referred to in Article 2 above who are without the limits of the said Order in Council. 4. All proceedings for the enforcement of the said rules and taxes against persons, to whom they are made applicable by these Regulations, shall be brought before the court of the Political Agent. Subject to the proviso contained in Article 8 (2) of the Muscat Order in Council, 1915, the court may make such orders as may be necessary for this purpose, and may, in addition, inflict for the non- observance of the said rules, or non-payment of the said taxes, a punishment of imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one month or with fine which may extend to 200 rupees or with both. 5. These Regulations may be cited as “ The Muscat (Municipal) Regulations, 1985.” T. C. FOWLE, Lieutenant-Colonel, I{ift Britannic Majesty's Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bush ire, -July 18. 1985. Allowed : SAMUEL HOARE, One of His Britannic Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State.■ STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS, 1922, No. 765. JL . FOREIGN JURISDICTION. The Maskat (Amendment) Order in Council, At tlio Court at Windsor Castle, the 1st day of April, 1922. Present, The King’s Most Excellent Majesty. Mr. Secretary Shortt. Sir Frederick Ponsonby. Mr. Bridgeman. Whereas by treaty, capitulation, grant, usage, sufferance, and other lawful means, His Majesty the King has jurisdiction within the territories of His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman : Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890, (a) or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of his Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows :— 1. This Order may be cited as “ The Maskat (Amendment) Order in Council, 1922,” and shall be read as one with the Maskat Order in Council, 1915,(b) hereinafter called “ the Principal Order.” 2. The following provisions are substituted for Articles 51 to 59 inclusive of the Principal Order :— (1) A register of British subjects shall be kept in the Political Agency. (2) Every British subject resident within the limits of this Order shall, in the month of January of each year, be registered at the Political Agency. A British subject arriving within the limits of this Order must apply for registration within one month after his arrival provided that a person who fails to apply for or to obtain registration within the time limited by this ! Article may be registered at any time if he excuses his failure to the satisfaction of the Political Agent. (3) Where a person is in possession of a valid British pass port, the Political Agent shall, on the first registration of any such person, endorse without further fee than (a) 53-4 Y. c. 37. (b) S.R. &amp; O., 1915, No. 132. 1 . [Price Id. Net.]that provided i'or in sub-article (6) hereunder on the passport a certificate of registration in such form as may be prescribed by the Secretary of State. Where any such person applies for the renewal of the regis tration and produces his passport, the renewal of the registration shall, without further fee than that pro vided for in sub-article (6) hereunder be endorsed thereon. (4) Every person who has not previously been registered applying to be registered under this Order shall, unless excused by the Political Agent, attend personally for that purpose at the Political Agency, but any person applying for the renewal of his registration need not attend personally unless directed by the Political Agent so to do, provided that the registration of the wife or wives of a man who is registered under this Order may, if living with him, be effected without their personal attendance being required, and pro vided also that the registration of minors, being his relatives in whatever degree, living with the head of a family who is registered under this Order, may be effected without their personal attendance being required. (5) A person registered in any register of British subjects established under the provisions of any Order in Coun cil which have been repealed shall be registered under the provisions of* this Order, unless the Political Agent is satisfied after enquiry that the previous registration was erroneous or that such person is not entitled to registration under the provisions of this Order. (6) Every person shall, on every registration of himself and on every renewal of the registration, pay a fee of one rupee or such other fee as the Secretary of State from time to time appoints. The amount of the fee may be uniform for all persons, or may vary according to the position and circumstances of different classes, if the Secretary of State from time to time so directs, but may not in any case exceed 3 rupees. (7) Where any person applies to be registered, he shall be entitled without a fee, to the assistance of the Political Agent in the preparation of any affidavit that may be required. (8) The Political Agent may require the production of such evidence that an applicant for registration is entitled to the status of a British subject as he may see fit, but subject to such directions as may be issued by the Secretary of State. (9) If any British subject neglects to obtain registration under the provisions of this Order, he shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British sub ject within the limits of this Order, and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding 25 rupees for each instanceof such failure, but he shall although not registered, be subject to the jurisdiction of the Courts established by the Principal Order. 3. From and after the commencement of this Order, Articles 51 to 59 inclusive of the Principal Order are hereby repealed but such repeal shall not prejudice any rights, obligations or liabilities accrued thereunder. 4. —(1) This Order shall take effect as soon as it is first ex hibited in the office of the Political Agent, and that date is in this Order referred to as the commencement of the Order, (a) (2) For that purpose the Political Agent shall, on the receipt by him of a certified printed copy of the Order, cause the same to be affixed and exhibited conspicuously in that office. He shall also keep the same so affixed and exhibited during one month from that first exhibition. (3) Proof shall not in any proceeding or matter be required that the provisions of this Article have been complied with, nor shall any act or proceeding be invalidated by any failure to comply with any such provisions. Almeric FitzRoy. (a) This Order came into force on July 4th, 1 ( .*22. LONDON: PRINTED &amp; PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased through any Bookseller or directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: Imperial House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2, and 28 Abingdon Street, London, S.W.l; 37 Peter Street, Manchester; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; and 23 Forth Street, Edinburgh. 1922 (14911-ltf) Wt. 10-1* 2 500 7/22 H. Su 0.8# AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE, The 3rd day of February, 1915. PRESENT, THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY LORD PRESIDENT. VISCOUNT KNOLLYS LORD CHAMBERLAIN MR. SECRETARY HARCOURT MR. ARTHUR HENDERSON SIR WILLIAM MACGREGOR LORD JUSTICE BANKES. % ^ T^HEREAS by Treaty, capitulation, grant, usage, sufferance, ▼ ▼ and other lawful means His Majesty the King has juris diction within the territories of His Highness the Sultan of Mask at and Oman : NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Act. 1890, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows :— Part I.—Preliminary and General, 1. This Order may be cited as “ The Maskat Order in Council, 19IB/' 2. The limits of this Order are Oman and the coast and islands of the Gulf of Oman, being within the territories of the Sultan of Maskat and Oman, including the territorial waters of Oman adjacent to the said coast and islands, and all territories, islands, and islets which may be included in the territories and be the possessions of the ruling Sultan of Maskat and Oman, together with their territorial waters. o 0. 0. 2673. A9 3. This Order is divided into parts as follows : — Parts. Subject. Articles. I. Preliminary and General -------- II. Application of Law of British India and of the United Kingdom 11-13. III. Criminal Matters - - - - - 14-34. IV. Civil Matters ---------- 35-43. v. Maskat Subjects and Tribunals 44-50. VI. Registration - -- -- -- -- - 51-07. VII. Miscellaneous Provisions - - - - -•- Schedules - -- -- -- -- - 08-88. 4. In the construction of this Order the following words and expressions have the meaning hereby assigned to them, unless there be something in the subject or context repugnant thereto, that is to say: — “Administration” means letters of administration, including the same with will annexed, or granted for special or limited purposes, or limited in duration. “ Maskat ” includes all places and waters within the limits of this Order, “ Maskat subject ” means a subject of His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman, or the subject, resident at Maskat, of any other non- Christian Powers not represented by a Consul at Maskat. “ British ship ” means a merchant ship, being a British ship within the meaning of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, and, except where the context otherwise requires, includes a ship belonging to any British subject as hereinafter defined. “ British subject ” includes a British-protected person. “ Judicial Assistant ” means the Officer for the time being holding the Office of Judicial Assistant under the provisions of the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907. “ Chief Court ” means a Court held by the Political Resident as hereinafter defined. District Court ” means a Court held by the Political Agent or by the Judicial Assistant. “ The Court ” means a Court held by the Political Resident, the Political Agent, or the Judicial Assistant to the Political Resident. “ Qazi ” means any official Qazi appointed by His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman and accepted by the Political Agent. “Foreigner” means any person not a British or Maskat subject. “ Imprisonment ” means imprisonment of either description as defined in the Indian Penal Code. “ Month ” means calendar month. “ Oath ” or “ Affidavit ” includes affirmation or declaration. o O. C. 2U73.“ Offence ” means any act or omission made punishable by any law for the time being in force. “ Person ” includes corporation. “Political Agent” means His Majesty’s Agent at Maskat appointed by the Governor-General of India in Council, including a person acting temporarily with the approval of the Governor-General of India in Council for such Political Agent. &lt;f Political Agency ” means the Office, Residence, Court or other appointed place of business of the Political Agent. “ Political Resident ’ means His Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, including a person acting temporarily with the approval of the Governor-General of India in Council for such Political Resident. “Rules of Court” means rules of Court made under the provisions of this Order. “Secretary of State” means one of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State. “Sultan of Maskat and Oman,” hereinafter called “the Sultan,” means tho ruling Sultan of Maskat and Oman, or his duly accredited representative for the time being. “ Ship ” includes any vessel used in navigation, however propelled, with her tackle, furniture, and apparel, and any boat or other craft. “ Treaty ” includes any capitulations, convention, agreement or arrange ment made by or on behalf of His Majesty with any State or Government, King, Chief, people, or tribe, or to the benefits of which His Majesty has succeeded, whether the Sultan is or is not a party thereto. “ Will ” means will, codicil, or other testamentary instrument. Expressions used in any enactments applied to Maskat or in any rules, regulations, or orders made under this Order, shall, unless a contrary intention appears, have the same respective meanings in this Order. 5.—(1) In this Order words importing the plural or the singular may be construed as referring to one person or thing or to more than one person or thing, and words importing the masculine as referring to the feminine, as the case may require. (2) Where this Order confers any power or imposes any duty, then, unless a contrary intention appears, the power may be exercised and the duty shall be performed from time to time as occasion requires. (3) Where this Order confers a power, or imposes a duty on, or with respect to, a holder of an office as such, then, unless a contrary intention appears, the power may be exercised and the duty shall be performed by, or with respect to, the holder for the time being of the office or the person temporarily acting for the holder.4 (4) Where this Order confers a power to make any rules, regulations, or orders, the power shall, unless a contrary intention appears, be construed as including a power exercisable in the like manner and subject to the like consent, and conditions, if any, to rescind, revoke, vary, or amend the rules, regulatiojj|* or orders. (5) This article shall apply to the construction of any regulations, rules, or orders made under this Order, unless a contrary intention appears. 6. Where this Order refers to any specified Act or Acts of Parliament, such reference shall, unless a contrary intention appears, be deemed to include anv Act or Acts amending or substituted for the same. t! O 7. In the event of the death, incapacity, removal, or absence from Maskat of tiie Political Agent for the time being, all and every the powers, authorities, and immunities by this Order granted to him shall, until His Majesty’s further pleasure is signified through the Governor-General of India in Council, be vested in the Political Resident. 8. The powers conferred by this Order shall extend to the persons and matters following, in so far as by Treaty, grant, usage, sufferance, or other lawful means His Majesty has jurisdiction in relation to such persons, matters, and things, that is to say :— (1) British subjects, as herein defined, within the limits of this Order. (2) Maskat subjects registered in the Political Agency as being in the regular service of British subjects ; with the proviso that all cases wherein such Maskat subjects are concerned shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of Part V. of this Order. (3) Foreigners with respect to whom any State, King, Chief, or Govern- - ment, whose subjects, or under whose protection they are, has, by any Treaty as herein defined or otherwise agreed with His Majesty for, or consented to, the exercise of power or authority by His Majesty. (4) Muskat subjects and foreigners, other than those within sub-articles (2) and (3), in the cases and according to the conditions specified in this Order and not otherwise. (5) The property and all personal or proprietary rights and liabilities within the said limits of British subjects and of Maskac subjects within sub-article (2), whether such persons are themselves within or without the limits of this Order. (6) British ships with their boats, and the persons and property on board thereof, or belonging thereto, being within the limits of this Order. 9. All His Majesty’s jurisdiction exercisable within the limits of this Order for the hearing and determination of criminal and civil matters, or for the » O. C. 2673.? maintenance of order, or for the control or administration of persons or property, or in relation thereto, shall be exercised under and according to the provisions of this Order, so far as this Order extends and applies. ^ 10. Every judge and officer of the Courts established under this Order shall, as far as there is proper opportunity, promote reconciliation and encourage and facilitate the settlement in an amicable way, and without recourse to litigation, of matters in difference between persons subject to this Order, or between persons subject to this Order and persons who are not subject to this Order, within the limits of this Order. Part II. —Application of Law of British India and of the United Kingdom. 11. —(1) Subject to the other provisions of this Order, and to any Treaties for the time being in force relating to Maskat, His Majesty’s criminal and civil jurisdiction in Maskat shall, so far as circumstances admit, be exercised on the principles of, and in conformity with, the enactments for the time being applicable as hereinafter mentioned of the Governor-General of India in Council, and of the Governor of Bombay in Council, and in accordance with the powers vested in, and the course of procedure and practice observed by and before the Courts in the Presidency of Bombay beyond the limits of tl&gt;e ordinary original jurisdiction of the High Court of Judicature at Bombay, according to their respective jurisdiction and authority, and so far as such enactments, powers, procedure, and practice are inapplicable, shall be exercised in accordance with justice, equity, and good conscience. (2) The enactments mentioned in the Schedule to this Order shall as from the commencement of this Order apply to all persons subject to this Order. (3) Any other existing or future enactments of the Governor-General of India in Council, or of the Governor of Bombay in Council, may be applied to Maskat by King’s .Regulations under Article 78 of this Order. (4) Any Act of the Governor-General of India in Council, or of the Governor of Bombay in Council, whether passed before or after the commence ment of this Order, amending or substituted for any Act of either of those Legislatures which applies or may be applied to Maskat, shall, subject to the provisions of this Article, also apply to Maskat. (5) The Court may construe any enactments in force hi Maskat, under the provisions of this Article, with such alterations not affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper to adapt the same to the matter before the Court. 12. The enactments described in the first Schedule to the Foreign Juris diction Act, 1890, shall apply to Maskat, as if it were a British Colony or o o. c. 2&lt;;7x A 3 o o. c. 2&lt;;7:5.G Possession, but subject to the provisions of this Order, and to the exceptions,, adaptations, and modifications following, that is to say! (i) The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is hereby substituted for the Governor of a Colony or British Possession, and the Chief Court is hereby substituted for a Superior Court or Supreme Couf?, and the District Court for a Magistrate or Justice of the Peace of a Colony or British Possession. (ii) For the portions of the Merchant Shipping Acts, 1854 and 1867, referred to in the said Schedule, shall be substituted Part XIII. of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894. (iii) In section 51 of the Conveyancing (Scotland) Act, 1874, the Court of the Political Agent is substituted for a Court of Probate in a Colony. (iv) With respect to the Fugitive Offenders Act, 1881 :— (а) So much of the 4th and 5th sections of the said Act as relates to sending a report of the issue of a warrant, together with the information, or a copy thereof, or to the sending of a certificate of committal and report of a case, or to the information to be given by a Magistrate to a fugitive, shall be excepted, and in lieu of such information the person acting as the Magistrate shall inform the fugitive that in the British Possession or Protec torate to which he may be conveyed he has the right to apply for a writ of habeas corpus or other like process. (б) So much of the 6th section of the said Act as requires the expiration of fifteen days before issue of warrant shall be excepted. (c) The Political Resident shall not be bound to return a fugitive offender to a British Possession unless satisfied that the proceedings to obtain his return are taken with the consent of the Governor of that Possession. (d) For the purpose of Part II. of the said Act, Bahrein, Maskat, the Persian Coast and Islands, and all other places on the shores of the Persian Gulf or the Gulf of Oman, Aden, and British India, shall be deemed to be one group of British Possessions. 13. Where, by virtue of any Imperial Act, or of this Order, or otherwise, any provisions of any Imperial Acts, or of any Law in force in India, or of any Orders in Council other than this Order, are applicable within the limits of this Order, or any forms, regulations, or procedure prescribed or established by or under such Act, Law, or Order, are made applicable for any purpose of this Order, or any other Order relating to Maskat, such Acts, Laws, Orders, forms, regulations, or procedure may be construed or used with such alterations u O. C. 2t&gt;7Hi and adaptations not affecting the substance as may be necessary having regard to local circumstances, and anything required to be done by, to, or before any Court, Judge, Officer, or Authority may be done by, to, or before a Court, tjpdge, Officer, or Authority having the like or analogous functions, or by, to, or before any Officer designated by the Secretary of State or by the Court (as the case may require) for that purpose; and in case any difficulty occurs in the application the Secretary of State, or with his previous or subsequent assent the Governor-General of India in Council, may direct by, to, or before whom and in what manner anything is to be done, and such Act, Law, Order, Form, Regulation, or procedure shall be construed accordingly. Where, under any such Imperial Act, Law, or Order, any publication is required to be made, as respects any judicial proceeding in any “Gazette” or otherwise, such publication shall be made by such mode as the Court shall think fit to direct. Part III.— Criminal. 14. —(1) Subject to the other provisions of this Order, the Code of Criminal Procedure and the other enactments relating to the administration of criminal justice in British India for the time being shall be applicable to Maskat. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf shall hold and form a Court, to be called the Chief Court, which shall have all the powers of a High Court of Judicature; the Political Agent at Maskat shall be deemed to be the District Magistrate and Sessions Judge; the Judicial Assistant to the Political Resident shall be deemed to be the additional District Magistrate and additional Sessions Judge; and the powers of the Governor-General in Council and of the Local Government under those enactments shall be exercisable by the Secretary of State, or. with his previous or subsequent assent, by the Governor-General of India in Council. Notwithstanding, in any case triable by a subordinate Magistrate under Chapters XVI. to XXIII. inclusive of the Indian Penal Code, if both the complainant and defendant are Mohammedans and are acquiescent in such procedure, the Political Agent may order the case to be tried by a Qazi, a representative from the Agency attending to record briefly the proceedings. In such suits the judgment passed by the Qazi cannot be carried into eflect until it is ratified by the Political Agent, and the Political Agent is empowered to revise the finding and sentence as if the Qazi were a subordinate Magistrate, or to return the case for retrial to the same or another Qazi. The sentence of the Qazi, when ratified by the Political Agent, shall for all purposes be regarded as if it were the decision of the Political Agent in the District Court. (2) Any jurisdiction exercisable by the Chief Court in criminal matters under this Order may be exercised by the Judge of that Court either within the limits of this Order or elsewhere. 15. In cases in which the Code of Criminal Procedure requires the sentence of a Court of Session to be confirmed by the High Court, the sentence shall a 1 O. &lt;J. 207:5.9 over any person to whom this Order applies who is charged either as a principal offender or as an abettor as if both such criminal act and the death had happened in Maskat. A (2) In the case of any offence committed on the high seas or within the Admiralty jurisdiction by any person who at the time of committing such offence was on board a British ship, or by any British subject on board a foreign ship to which lie did not belong, the Court shall, subject to the provisions of this Order, have jurisdiction over such person as if the offence had been committed within its jurisdiction. (3) In cases tried under this article no different sentence can be passed from the sentence which could be passed in England if the crime were tried there. (4) The foregoing provisions of this article shall be deemed to be adaptations, for the purposes of this Order and of the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890, of the following enactments, namely :— The Admiralty Offences (Colonial) Act, 1819 ; The Admiralty Offences (Colonial) Act, 18G0; The Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, Part XIII.; and those enactments shall apply accordingly, and be administered in Maskat. 20. Where a person is convicted of an offence, the Court before which he is convicted may, if it thinks fit at any time before he is discharged, require him to give security to the satisfaction of the Court for his future good behaviour, and for that purpose may, if it thinks fit, cause him to come or be brought before the Court. 21. —(1) Where it is shown by evidence on oath, to the satisfaction of the District Court, that any British subject has committed, or is about to commit, an offence against this Order, or is otherwise conducting himself so as to be dangerous to peace and good order, or is endeavouring to excite enmity between the people of Maskat and His Majest] 7 , or is intriguing within the limits of this Order against His Majesty’s power and authority, the Cour may, if it thinks fit, by order under its seal, prohibit that person from being within the limits of this Order, during any time therein specified, not exceeding two }’ears. (2) The Court, by order in writing under its seal, may vary any order of prohibition (not extending the duration thereof), and may revoke any order of prohibition or removal. (3) r l he Court shall forthwith report the order and the grounds thereof to the Chief Court, which shall forthwith report to the Governor-General of India in Council every order made under this article, and the grounds thereof, and the proceedings thereunder. # O. C. 2673. . r10 22. —(1) If any British subject fails to give security for good behaviour or for keeping the peace when lawfully required to do so, or fails to comply with an order of prohibition made under this Order, the Chief Court or the District Court may, if it thinks fit, order that he be deported from any plac^ within its jurisdiction as prescribed by this Order. (2) If the order of deportation is made by the District Court, it shall forthwith report to the Chief Court the order and the grounds thereof. (3) Thereupon the person ordered to be deported shall, unless the Chief Court thinks fit otherwise to direct, be as soon as practicable, and in the case of a person convicted either after execution of the sentence or while it is in course of execution, removed in custody under warrant to the place named in the warrant. (4) The place shall be a place in that part of His Majesty’s Dominions, or in the British Protectorate, to which the person belongs, or the Government of which consents to the reception of persons deported under this Order. (5) The Court, on making an order of deportation, may, if it thinks fit, order the person to be deported to pay all or any part of the expenses of his deportation, to be fixed by the Court in the order. Subject thereto, the expenses of deportation shall be defrayed as the Secretary of State, with the concurrence of the Treasury, or, with the previous or subsequent assent of the Secretary of State, the Governor-General of India in Council directs. (6) The Chief Court shall forthwith report to the Governor-General of India in Council every order of deportation made under this Order, and the grounds thereof, and the proceedings thereunder. (7) If a person deported under this Order returns to Maskat without permission in writing of the Chief Court, or the Governor-General of India in Council, or the Secretary of State (which permission the Chief Court, or the Governor-General of India in Counci], or the Secretary of State respectively may give), he shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two months, or with a fine which may extend to 1,01)0 rupees, or with both. (8) He shall also be liable to be forthwith again deported under the original or a new order, and a fresh warrant. 23. An appeal shall not lie against an order of prohibition, of removal, or deportation made under this Order. 24. —(1) Where under this Order a person is to be sent or removed or deported from any place within the jurisdiction of the Court as prescribed by this Order he shall, by warrant of the Court sealed with its seal, be detained, It necessary in custody, or in prison, until a tit opportunity for his removal or deportation occurs, and then be put on board a vessel belonging to, or in the service of, His Majesty, or, if no such vessel is available, then on board some other British or other fit vessel. o 0. C. 207.!.11 (2) The warrant shall be sufficient authority to the person to whom it is directed or delivered for execution, and to the Commanding Officer or Master of the vessel, to receive and detain the person therein named, in the manner j^erein prescribed, and to send or remove and carry him to the place therein named, according to the warrant. (3) In case of sending or removal for any purpose other than deportation, the warrant shall be issued in duplicate, and the person executing it shall, as soon as practicable after his arrival at the place therein named, deliver, according to the warrant, with one of the duplicates of the warrant, to a constable, or proper officer of police, or keeper of a prison, or other proper authority or person there, the person named in the warrant, to be produced on the order of the proper Court or authority there, or to be otherwise dealt with according to law. 25. If any person to whom this Order applies does any of the following things, namely :— (1) Wilfully by act or threat obstructs any Officer of, or person executing any process of, the Court in the performance of his duty; or (2) Within or close to the room or place where the Court is sitting wilfully misbehaves in a violent, threatening, or disrespectful manner to the disturbance of the Court, or to the intimidation of suitors or others resorting thereto; or (3) Wilfully insults any member of the Court, or any assessor, or any person acting as a Clerk or Officer of the Court during his sitting or attendance in Court, or in his going to or returning from Court; or (4) Does any act in relation to the Court or a Judge thereof, or a matter pending therein, which, if done in relation to a Superior Court in England or in India, would be punishable as a contempt of such Court, or as a libel on such Court or the Judges thereof, or the administration of justice therein; such person shall be liable to be apprehended by order of the Court with or without warrant, and, on inquiry and consideration, and after the hearing of any defence which such person may offer, without further process or trial, to be punished with a fine not exceeding 100 rupees, or with imprisonment not exceeding twentv-four hours. \ A Minute shall be made and kept of every such case of punishment, recording the facts of the offence and the extent of the punishment. Provided that, if the Court thinks fit, instead of proceeding under the preceding provisions, it may direct or cause the offender to be tried in a separate criminal prosecution or proceeding, in which the offender shall be liable to any punishment to which he would be liable if the offence were committed in relation to the Court of a Sessions Judge in India. a G « O. C. 2(173.12 Nothing herein shall interfere with the power of the Court to remove or exclude persons who interrupt or oostruct the proceedings of the Court, 26. If any person to whom this Order applies smuggles or imports into or exports from Maskat any goods whereon any duty is charged by payable to the Sultan, with intent to evade payment of the duty, he shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two months, or with a fine which may extend to 1,000 rupees, or a sum equal to treble the value of the goods (whichever shall be the greater), or with both imprisonment and fine. 27. If any person to whom this Order applies smuggles or imports into or exports from Maskat any goods the importation or exportation whereof is lawfullv prohibited, he shall be punished with imprisonment for a term whicli may extend to one year, or with a fine which may extend to 2,000 rupees, or to a sum equal to treble the value of the goods (whichever shall be the greater), or with imprisonment and fine. 28. Any act which, if done in British India, would be an offence against the law for the time being in force in British India, relating to trade-marks, merchandise marks, copyright designs, or inventions, shall, it done in Maskat by a person to whom this Order applies, be an offence punishable with imprison ment for a term which may extend to two months, or with a fine whicli may extend to 1,000 rupees, or with both. 29. —(1) If any person to whom this Order applies— (i) Publicly derides, mocks, or insults any religion established or observed within the limits of this Order ; or (ii) Publicly offers insult to any religious service, feast, or ceremony established or kept in any place within those limits, or to any place of worship, tomb, or sanctuary belonging to any religion established or observed within those limits, or belonging to the ministers or professors thereof; or (in) Publicly and wilfully commits any act tending to bring any religion established or observed within those limits, or its ceremonies, modes of worship, or observances into hatred, ridicule, or contempt, and thereby to provoke a breach of the public peace; he shall be guilty of an offence, and on conviction thereof liable to imprisonment, which may extend to two years, with or without a fine not exceeding 500 rupees, or to a fine alone not exceeding 500 rupees. (2) The Political Agent shall take such precautionary measures as seem to him proper and expedient for the prevention of such offences. .*30. Any T person being within the limits of this Order may be proceeded against, tried, and punished under this Order lor piracy wherever committed. o C. C. 2S73.13 31. If any person subject to this Order violates, or fails to observe within the limits of this Order, any stipulation of any Treaty between His Majesty, his predecessors, heirs, or successors, and the Sultan, for the time being in ^rce, and applicable to such person, in respect of the violation whereof any penalty is stipulated for in the Treaty, he shall be deemed guilty of an offence, and on conviction thereof under this Order shall be liable to a penalty in accordance with the stipulations of the Treaty or the provisions of this Order. 32. The Foreign Jurisdiction Neutrality Order in Council, 1904, shall apply to all persons and to all property subject to this Order. 33. Where a person entitled to appeal to the Chief Court from any judgment or order passed in the exercise of criminal jurisdiction under this Order desires so to appeal, he shall present his petition of appeal to the Court which passed the judgment or order; and the petition shall with all practicable speed be transmitted to the Chief Court with certified copies of the charge (if any) and proceedings, of all documentary evidence submitted or tendered, of the depositions, of the notes of the oral testimony, and of the judgment or order, and any argument on the petition of appeal that the appellant desires to submit to the Chief Court. 34. The Court against whose judgment or order the appeal is preferred may postpone the execution of the sentence pending the appeal, and shall, if necessary, commit the person convicted to prison for safe custody, or detain him in prison for safe custody, or shall admit him to bail, and may take security, by recognisance, deposit of money, or otherwise, for his payment of any fine. Part IV. —Civil Matters. 35. —(1) kSubject to the other provisions of this Order, the Code of Civil Procedure and the other Indian enactments relating to the administration of civil justice and to insolvency and bankruptcy, shall have effect as if Maskat were a district in the Presidency of Bombay. The Political Agent shall be deemed to be the District Judge, and his Court shall be deemed to be the District or Principal Civil Court of Original Jurisdiction in the district; the Judicial Assistant to the Political Resident shall be deemed to be an additional District Judge, and his Court shall be an additional District Court of Original Civil Jurisdiction; the Court of the Political Resident shall be deemed to be the highest Civil Court of Appeal for the district, and the Court authorized to hear appeals from the decisions of the District Court; and the powers, both of the Governor-General in Council and the Local Government under those enactments, shall be exercisable by the Secretary of State, or, with his previous or subsequent assent, by the Governor-General of India in Council. (2) Any jurisdiction exercisable by the Chief Court under this Order in civil matters may be exercised by the Judge of that Court, either within the limits of this Order or elsewhere. a 7 v O. C. 2673,3G. When a suit between persons to whom this Order applies is filed in the Political Agency, the Political Agent shall enquire from the several parties whether they desire that proceedings shall be instituted in accordance with the Code of Civil Procedure and the Indian enactments made applicable tf* Maskat, or in accordance with local usage, and shall record their replies. 37. When any of the several parties desire that the suit shall be determined in accordance with the Code of Civil Procedure and other enactments made applicable to Maskat, the District Court shall forthwith proceed to decide the suit in accordance with the provisions of such enactments, as far as local conditions permit. Nothing in this section shall prevent the District Court from referring any matter in the progress of a suit which involves a point of Mohammedan law to a Qazi for decision, or from sending any party or witness, being a Mohammedan, to a Qazi for the administration of an oath ; or from referring any matter in the progress of a suit between parties belonging to the same community which, in the discretion of the Court, is a fit and proper subject for the decision of the local leaders of that community, to a punch or jama’at of the leaders of such community ; or, in commercial cases, from referring any matter in the progress of a suit which, in the discretion of the Court, is a fit and proper subject for the decision of the principal local merchants to a punch or jama’at of such merchants. 38. —(1) The Foreign Jurisdiction (Admiralty) Order in Council, 1910, shall apply to Maskat, and the Chief Court shall have the jurisdiction conferred by Article 4 of that Order, and the District Court shall be deemed to be a Provincial Court, and the Registry thereof a District Registry within the meaning of the said Order. (2) Admiralty actions commenced in the said Registry shall be tried in the District Court, unless the Chief Court is at the time sitting within the limits of this Order, or unless all parties agree that the action shall be tried in the Chief Court sitting elsewhere than within the limits of this Order. (3) The duties of the Registrar and of the Marshal, either of the Chief Court or of the District Court, under the said Order shall be performed by such Officers as the Political Resident shall direct. (4) Nothing in this Order shall prevent the Political Agent from exercising all such jurisdiction in matters arising out of the Slave Trade as is conferred on him under the Slave Trade (East African Courts) Acts, 1873 and 1879. 39. —(1) The District Court shall endeavour to obtain, as early as may be, notice of the deaths of all British subjects leaving property in any place within the jurisdiction of the Court as prescribed by this Order, and all such information as may serve to guide the Court with respect to the securing and administration of their property.15 (2) On receiving notice of the death of such a person the Court shall put up a notice thereof at the Courthouse, and shall keep the same there until probate or administration is granted, or, where it appears to the Court that j®obate or administration will not be applied for or cannot be granted, for such time as it thinks fit. (3) The Court shall, where the circumstances of the case appear so to require, as soon as may be, take possession of the property left by the deceased in any place within the jurisdiction of the Court as prescribed by this Order, or put it under its seal (in either case, if the nature of the property or other circumstances so require, making an inventory), and so keep it until it can be dealt with according to law; perishable articles being disposed of as the Court may consider best in the interests of the State. (4) All expenses incurred on behalf of the Court in so doing shall be the first charge on the property of the deceased, and the Court shall, by sale of part of that property, or otherwise, provide for the discharge of these expenses. (5) When a British subject dies within the jurisdiction of the Court, as prescribed by this Order, intestate, his property, or so much thereof as is within those limits, shall, until administration is granted, vest in the Political Agent. 40. If a person to whom this Order applies, who is named executor in a will, and to the establishment of whose title as such it is necessary to obtain probate of that will, takes possession of and administers, or otherwise deals with, any part of the property of the deceased, and does not obtain probate within one month after the death, or after the termination of any proceeding respecting probate or administration, he shall be liable to pay double the amount of any tees chargeable on obtaining probate, and he shall also be liable to a fine which may extend to 1,000 rupees. 41. If any person to whom this Order applies, other than the person named executor, or the administrator, or a person entitled to represent the deceased without obtaining probate or letters of administration, or an Officer of the Court, takes possession of and administers, or otherwise deals with, any part of the property of the deceased, he shall, as soon as practicable, notify the fact and the circumstances to the District Court, and shall furnish to the Court all such information as the Court requires, and shall conform to any direction of the Court in relation to the custody, disposal, or transmis sion of the property or the proceeds thereof, and, in case of any contravention of this Article, he shall be punished with a fine, which may extend to 1,000 rupees. 42. — (1) When the peculiar circumstances of the case appear to the District Court so to require, for reasons recorded in its proceedings, the Court may, if it thinks fit, of its own motion or otherwise, grant letters of administration to an Officer of the Court*16 (2) The Officer so appointed shall act under the direction of the Court, and shall be indemnified thereby. (3) He shall publish such notices, if any, as the Court thinks fit, ^ Maskat, the Persian Coast and Islands, Bombay, the United Kingdom, and elsewhere. (4) The Court shall require and compel him to file in the proper Office of the Court, his accounts of his administration at intervals not exceeding three months, and shall forthwith examine them and report thereon to the Chief Court. (5) The accounts shall be audited under the. direction of the District Court. ^6) All expenses incurred on behalf of the Court in execution of this article shall be the first charge on the estate of the deceased as dealt with in accordance with the provisions of this Order; and the Court shall, by the sale of that estate or otherwise, provide for the discharge of those expenses. 43. In cases where parties are Mohammedans the District Court may refer any question concerning probate of wills or administration of property of deceased persons to whom this Order applied to a Qazi for settlement under the general supervision of the Court. Part V.— Maskat and Foreign Subjects and Tribunals. (a) Criminal. 44. —(1) When any person not subject to this Order desires to institute a complaint against a person to whom the said Order applies, the Political Agent shall entertain the same, and shall (a) himself hear and determine it in his District Court, or (6) if both parties are Mohammedans, refer it, with their consent, to a Qazi for decision, sending a representative of the Agency to record briefly the proceedings. Such decision, when endorsed by the Political Agent, shall for all purposes be considered as if it were that of the District Court. (2) Provided that the Maskat subject or person not subject to this Order, if so required by the Court, first obtains and files in the proper Office of the Court the consent, in writing, of the competent authority (if any) on behalf of his own nation to his submitting, and that he does submit by writing, to the jurisdiction of the Court, and, if required by the Court, gives security to the satisfaction of the Court, and to such reasonable amount as the Court thinks fit, by deposit or otherwise, to pay fees, costs, and damages, and abide by and perform the decision to be given by the Court or on appeal. (3) A cross suit shall not be brought in the Court against the plaintiff, being a person not subject to this Order.(4) When a person to whom this Order applies desires to institute a complaint against a person not subject to the said Order, who is a subject either of the Sultan or of some other non-Christian power not represented l^- a Consular Official in Mask at, the Political Agent shall entertain the same, and, after satisfying himself that primd facie grounds for complaint exist, shall cause the matter to be brought before and decided by the highest authority of the Sultan, or some person specially delegated by him for the purpose. The proceedings and dual decision in a case shall not, however, be considered legal unless notice has been given and an opportunity afforded for the Political Agent or Officer appointed by him for the purpose to attend at the hearing and final decision. (b) Civil. 45.—(1) When any person not subject to this Order desires to bring a suit against a person to whom the said Order applies, the Political Agent shall admit the complaint, and may {a) hear and determine the suit in his District Court, or (b) with the consent of the several parties, may refer the case to one or more arbitrators for settlement. (2) Provided that the Maskat subject or person not subject to this Order, if required by the Court, first obtains and files in the proper Office of the Court the consent, in writing, of the competent authority (if any), on behalf of his own nation, to his submitting, and that he does submit, by writing, to the jurisdiction of the Court, and, if required by the Court, gives security to the satisfaction of the Court, and to such reasonable amount as the Court thinks fit, by deposit or otherwise, to pay fees, costs, and damages, and abide by and perform the decision to be given by the Court or on appeal. (3) A cross suit shall not be brought in the Court against a plaintiff, being a person not subject to this Order. (A) When a person to whom this Order applies desires to institute a suit against a person not subject to the said Order, who is a subject either of the Sultan or of some other non-Christian Power not represented by British Officials in Maskat, the Political Agent shall admit the same, and after satisfying himself that primd facie grounds for bringing a suit exist, shall cause the matter to be brought before and decided by the highest authority of the Sultan, or some person specially delegated by him for the purpose. The proceedings and final decision in a case shall not, however, be considered legal unless notice has been given and an opportunity afforded for the Political Agent, or Officer appointed by him for the purpose, to attend at the hearing and final decision. , (5) The award of the Arbitrator under sub-article 1 (6) shall be final, and shall not be open to appeal unless the same shall within a reasonable time have been ordered by the Political Agent to be set aside on the ground that it is not final, or is defective, or that the Arbitrator has exceeded his authority, or has been guilty of misconduct in the matter.18 (0) Nothing herein mentioned shall prevent the District Court from referring any matter in the progress of a suit which involves a point of Mohammedan law to a Qazi for decision, or from sending any party or witness being a Mohammedan, to a Qazi for the administration of an oath. 4b*.—(1) Where a person to whom this Order does not apply obtains, in a Court established under this Order, a decree or order against a defendant being a British subject, and in another suit that defendant is plaintiff and the person to whom this Order does not apply is defendant, the Court may, if in thinks fit, on the application of the British subject, stay the enforcement of the decree or order pending that other suit, and ma} r set off any amount decreed or ordered to be paid by one party in one suit against any amount decreed or ordered to be paid by the other party in the other suit. (2) Where a plaintiff, being a person to whom this Order does not apply, obtains L decree or order, in a Court established under this Order, against two or more defendants being British subjects, jointly, and in another suit one of them is a plaintiff and the Maskat subject is defendant, the Court may, if it thinks fit, on the application of the British subjects, stay the enforcement of the decree or order pending that other suit, and may set off anv amount decreed or ordered to be paid by one party in one suit against any amount decreed or ordered to be paid by the other party in the other suit, without prejudice to the right of the British subject to obtain contribution from his co-defendants under the joint liability. (3) Where in a suit a person to whom this Order does not apply is co-plaintiff with a British subject, who is in Maskat, it shall not be necessary for the Maskat subject to give security under this article as regards fees and costs, unless the Court so directs, but the co-plaintiff British subject shall be responsible for all fees and costs. 47. —(1) Every agreement for reference to arbitration between a person to whom tiiis Order applies on the one hand, and a person not subject to the said Order on the other hand, may, on the application of any party, be filed for execution in the Office of the Court. (2) Ihe Court shall thereupon have authority to enforce the agreement, and the award made thereunder, and to control and regulate the proceedings before and alter the award in such manner and on such terms as the Court may think fit, in concert with the Sultan or his representative. (c) General. 48. —(1) Where it is proved that the attendance of a person, to whom this Order applies, to give evidence, or for any other purpose connected with the administration of justice, is required before a Maskat Tribunal, a Court established under this Order may, if it thinks fit, in a case and in circum stances in which the Court would require the attendance of that person before the Court, order that he do attend as required.(2) If the person ordered to attend, having reasonable notice of the time and place at which he is required to attend, fails to attend accordingly, and does not excuse his failure to the satisfaction of the Court, he shall, inde- j^pdently of any other liability, be liable to be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two months, or with a fine which may extend to 1,000 rupees, or with both. 49. When a person to whom this Order applies invokes or submits to the jurisdiction of a Maskat Tribunal, and engages in writing to abide by the decision of that Tribunal, or to pay any fees or expenses ordered by that Tribunal to be paid by him, the Court may, on such evidence as it thinks fit to require, enforce payment of such fees and expenses in the same manner as if they were fees payable in a proceeding in the Court, and shall pay over and account for the same, when levied, to the proper Maskat authority, as the Court may direct. 50. —(1) If a person to whom this Order applies wilfully gives false evidence in a proceeding before a Maskat Tribunal, or in an arbitration between a person to whom this Order applies, on the one hand, and a person to whom this Order does not apply, on the other hand, he shall be guilty of an offence, and shall, on conviction, be liable to be punished with imprison ment for a term which may extend to two months, or with a fine which may extend to 1,000 rupees, or with both. (2) Nothing in this article shall exempt a person from liability under any other British Indian law to any other or higher punishment or penalty : Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence. Part VI.— Registration. 51. A register of British subjects shall be kept in the Political Agency. 52. —(1) Every British subject resident in Maskat, being of the age of 21 years or upwards, or being married, or a widower, or a widow, though under that age, shall, in the month of January of every year, register himself, or renew his registration certificate, at the Political Agency. (2) A British subject arriving in Maskat must apply for registration within one month after arrival in Maskat: Provided that a person who fails to apply for or to obtain registration within the time limited by this article may be registered at any time if he excuses his failure to the satisfaction of the Political Agent. 53. The registration of a man shall comprise the registration of his wife or wives, if living with him ; and the registration of the head of a family shall comprise the registration of all females and minors, being his relatives, in whatever degree, living under the same roof with him at the time of his registration.20 54 . (1) The Political Agent shall, on the first registration of any person, issue to him a certificate of registration signed and sealed. (2) On the renewal of a registration the old certificate of registration shall be produced, or its absence accounted for to the satisfaction of Political Agent. (3) The renewal of a registration shall, unless the Political Agent thinks fit to issue a new certificate, be effected by an endorsement on the old certificate. (4) Where a new certificate is issued, the Political Agent may require the old certificate to be delivered up to him. (5) The names and descriptions of females and minors whose registration is, under the provisions of this Order, comprised in that of the head of the family, may be endorsed on the certificate of the head of the family. 55. Every person, who has not previously been registered, applying to be registered under this Order shall, unless excused by the Political Agent, attend personally for that purpose at the Political Agency; but no person applying for the renewal of his registration need attend personally unless directed by the Political Agent so to do. 56. —(1) Every person shall, on every registration of himself and on every renewal of the registration, pay a fee of 1 rupee, or such other fee as the Secretary of State from time to time appoints. The amount of the fee may be uniform for all persons, or may vary according to the position and circumstances of different classes, if the Secretary of State from time to time so directs, but may not in any case exceed 2 rupees. (2) Where any person applies to be registered, he shall be entitled to the assistance of the Political Agent in the preparation of any affidavit that may be required for the purposes of such registration without a fee. 57. If any British .subject neglects to obtain registration under the provisions of this Order, he shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British subject in Maskat, and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding 25 rupees for each instance of such failure; but he shall, although not registered, be subject to the jurisdiction of the Courts established by this Order. 58. —(1) A person not of Asiatic or African descent arriving in Maskat and applying to be registered as a British subject shall be so registered if the Political Agent is satisfied, after such enquiry as he may deem fit, that he is entitled to the status of a British subject. (2) A person of Asiatic or African descent arriving in Maskat and applying to be registered as a British subject shall be so registered if he (a) produces a passport as a British subject from British India or a British Possession or21 Protectorate ; or (b) files an affidavit or sworn declaration showing that lie was born within IIis Majesty’s Dominions or within the territory of any Prince or State in India under the suzerainty or in alliance with His Majesty, or in a J^itish Protectorate, or that he has been naturalised in the United Kingdom ; and (c) in either case gives satisfactory evidence of his identity. In the case of a person of Maskat origin his registration shall be subject to the proviso that the Sultan has no reasonable grounds to claim him as a Maskat subject while in Oman territory, or consents in writing to his beimx registered as a British subject. 59. —(a) A person born in Maskat, being the child of a British subject, may be registered as a British subject if it is proved that the father (1) was registered as a British subject, or (2), being entitled, was prevented from being so registered by causes for which he was not responsible. (b) The Political Agent may, without fee, register any British subjects, being minors, living in the houses of foreigners or Maskat subjects. 60. —(a) Britisli subjects and British-protected persons are prohibited from alienating to or acquiring from any person of whatever nationality any land or household property within the dominions of the Sultan, either bv gift, purchase, mortgage, or other form of conveyance, without due execution of signature and registration previous to the transfer of such property by the Political Agent. Any British subject charged with any breach of this paragraph shall be liable to, and on conviction punishable under this Order by, a fine up to 500 rupees, or to the total value of the property purporting to be so transferred, or imprisonment up to one calendar month or both. (7&gt;) Any such deed, or instrument of gift, purchase, mortgage, or other form of conveyance, purporting to transfer property otherwise than in accordance with the provisions of 60 (a) may, on that ground alone, be declared void and of no effect by any Court acting under this Order. 61. A register of companies incorporated or registered in the United Kingdom or in any British Possession, and carrying on business in Maskat, shall be kept in the Political Agency. 62. On the registration of a company at the Political Agency, there shall be deposited and filed a copy of the certificate of incorporation of the company or other document corresponding thereto, a statement showing the nominal capital of the company and the amounts thereof which have been subscribed and paid up respectively, and, if the company has been incorporated under a law which provides for the periodical filing of a list of the shareholders, a copy of the last list so filed.2 -? G3. The Political Agent shall, on the registration of a company at the Political Agency, issue to the person making the registration a certificate, signed and sealed, that the company has been «o registered. 04.—(1) Every company registered under this Order shall register name and address of the manager or other chief local representative in Maskat, and shall from time to time, as may be necessary, register any alteration of the representative of the company or in his address. (^2) Pules of Court made under Article 68 may provide that service of writs, notices, or other documents upon the person registered under this article, or at his address, shall be good service of such documents upon the company. 65. Registration of a company under this Order shall not require to be renewed annually, but may be renewed from time to time as the parties may desire, and must be renewed when any change takes place in the name of the company. 66. On every registration of a company under this Order, and on every renewal thereof, there shall be payable a fee of 10 rupees, and on every registration under Article 64 (1) there shall be payable a fee of 1 rupee. 67. —(1) A company shall not be entitled to be recognised or protected as a British company unless it is registered under this Order, but shall, although not so registered, be subject to the jurisdiction of the Courts established by this Order. (2) Nothing in this article shall affect the right of the Secretary of State to direct that the British protection shall not be accorded to a companv, even though it has been registered under this Order. Part VII.—Miscellaneous Provisions. 68. Subject to the control of the Secretary of State, the Political Resident may, from time to time, with the previous sanction of the Governor-General of India in Council, make rules of procedure and other rules, consistent with tins Order, for the better execution of the provisions herein contained in respect of any matter arising in the course of any civil or criminal case, including insolvency and bankruptcy proceedings. 60.—(1) Subject to the control of the Secretary of State acting with the concurrence of the Treasury, the Political Resident may from time to time, with the previous sanction of the Governor-General of India in Council, make rules imposing fees leviable in respect of any proceedings in, or processes issued out of, any Court established under this Order. (2) But a Court before which any matter is pending may, in any case, if it thinks fit, on account of the poverty of a party, or for any other reason, dispense in whole or in part with the payment of any fees chargeable in respect of such matter.70. —(1) All fees, charges, expenses, costs, fines, damages, and other money payable under this Order, or under any law made applicable by this Order, may be enforced under order of the Court by seizure and sale of goods, and, in default of sufficient goods, by imprisonment as a civil prisoner for a term lA exceeding one month, but such imprisonment shall not operate as a satisfaction or extinguishment of the liability. (2) Any bill of sale or mortgage, or transfer of property, made with a view of avoiding such seizure or sale, shall not be effectual to defeat the provisions of this Order. (3) All fees, penalties, fines, and forfeitures levied under this Order upon a British subject, and fees, other than actual Court fees, that may be levied under the provisions of this Order, on a person to whom this Order applies, shall be paid to the public account, and shall be applied in such manner as the Secretary of State, with the consent of the Treasury, or, with the previous or subsequent assent of the Secretary of State, as the Governor-General of India in Council, may direct. 71. Whenever an Acting Political Agent or Acting Judicial Assistant has commenced the hearing of any cause or matter, civil or criminal, he may, unless the Political Resident otherwise directs, continue and complete the hearing and determination thereof, notwithstanding that his authority to act as Political Agent or Judicial Assistant has otherwise ceased by reason of the expiration of the time for which he was appointed to act, or by reason of the happening of any event by which his authority is determined. 72. —(1) If an Officer of the Court, employed to execute a decree or order, loses, by neglect or omission, the opportunity of executing it, then, on complaint of the person aggrieved and proof of the fact alleged, the Court may, if it thinks fit, order the Officer to pay the damages sustained by the person com plaining, or part thereof. (2) The order may be enforced as an order directing payment of money. 73. —(1) If a Clerk or Officer of the Court, acting under pretence of the process or authority of the Court, is charged with extortion, or with not paying over money duly levied, or with other misconduct, the Court may, if it thinks fit, enquire into the charge in a summary way, and may for that purpose summon and enforce the attendance of all necessary persons as in a suit, and may make such order for the repayment of any money extorted, or for the payment over of any money levied, and for payment of such damages and costs as the Court thinks fit. (2) The Court may also, if it thinks fit, on the same enquiry, impose on the Clerk or Officer such fine, not exceeding 50 rupees tor each offence, as the Court thinks fit. (3) A Clerk or Officer punished under this article sha 1 ! not, without the leave of the Court, be liable to a civil suit in respect of the same matter; and24 any such suit, if already or afterwards begun, may be stayed by the Court in such manner and on such terms as the Court tniuks fit. (4) Nothing in this article shall be deemed to prevent any person from being prosecuted under any other British or British Indian law for any ^»t or omission punishable under this article, or from being liable under that other law to any other or higher punishment or penalty than that provided bv this article: J Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence. 74. The Political Resident or the Political Agent may exercise any power conferred on any Justices of the Peace within His Majesty’s Dominions by any .Act of Parliament, for the time being in force, regulating merchant seamen or the mercantile marine. 75. Where under the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, anything is authorized to be done by, to, or before a Consular OtHcer, such thing may be done in any place in Maskat by, to, or before the Political Resident or the Political Agent. 70. The Political Resident and the Political Agent shall each be entitled in Maskat to act as a Notary Public. 77. The Court shall have jurisdiction from time to time to make an order requiring a person to whom this Order applies to contribute in such manner as the Court directs to the support of his wife, or to the support of his oi lier child, whether legitimate or not, being, in the opinion of the Court, under the age of 1(J years. Any such order may be made in a summary way, as if the neglect to provide for the support of such wife or child were an offence, and any failure to comply with any such order shall be deemed to be an offence, and shall be punishable with a fine not exceeding 10 rupees for anv one default, and the Court may direct any penalty imposed for such offence to be applied for the support of such wife or child in such manner as the Court thinks fit. 78. The Political Resident shall have power to make Regulations (to be called King’s Regulations) for the following purposes (that is to say) :— (a) For the peace, order, and good government of persons to whom this Order applies in relation to matters not provided for by this Order. (&amp;) For securing the observance of any Treaty or arrangement for the time being in force, relating to any place within the limits of this Order, or of any native or local law or custom, whether relating to trade, commerce, revenue, or any other matter. (c) For applying, amending, modifying, or repealing with respect to Maskat any Acts or enactments which apply, or are made applicable, or have been brought into operation in Maskat, by or under any of the provisions of Article 11 of this Order.25 0 {d) For regulating or preventing the importation or exportation in British ships, or by any person to whom this Order applies, of arms or munitions of war, or any parts or ingredients thereof, and for giving ^ effect to any Treaty relating to the importation or exportation of the same. (e) For requiring returns to be made of the nature, quantity, and value of articles exported from or imported into Maskat, by or on account of any person to whom this Order applies, or in any British ship, and for prescribing the times and manner at or in which, and the persons b} r whom, such returns are to be made. (/) For the governance, visitation, care, and superintendence of prisons. 79. —(1) Any Regulations made under the preceding article may provide for forfeiture of any goods, receptacles, or things in relation to which, or to the contents of which, any breach is committed of such Regulations, or of any Treaty or any native or local law or custom, the observance of which is provided for by such Regulations. (2) Any person to whom this Order applies committing a breach of any such Regulations shall, in addition to any forfeiture prescribed thereby, bn liable, on conviction, to imprisonment for a period not exceeding three months or to a fine, or to both. (3) Any fine imposed for a breach of Regulation shall not exceed 1,500 rupees: provided that in the case of any breach of any native or local law relating to customs law, or under which the importation or exportation of any goods is prohibited or restricted, the fine may extend to a sum equiva lent to treble the value of the goods in relation to which the breach is committed. 80. -(1) King’s Regulations shall not take effect until they are allowed by a Secretary of State, or, with his previous or subsequent assent, by the (Governor-General of India in Council : provided that in case of urgency declared in any such Regulations the same shall take effect before such allowance, and shall continue to have effect unless and until they are disallowed by the Secretary of State, or, with his previous or subsequent assent, by the Governor-General of India in Council, and until notification of such disallowance is received and published by the Political Resident, and such disallowance shall be without prejudice to anything done or suffered under such Regulations in the meantime. (2) All King’s Regulations shall be published by the Political Resident in such manner and at such places as he may think proper. (3) In this Order “ breach of the Regulations ” includes the breach of any native or local law or custom, the observance of which is required by any King’s Regulations.2f&gt; 81. Judicial notice shall be taken of this Order and of the commence ment thereof, and of the appointment of the Political Resident, Political Agent, and Judicial Assistant, and of the constitution and limits of the Courts and districts and of the seals and signatures, and of any rules and regulates made or in force under this Order, and no proof shall be required of any of such matters. 82. Nothing in this Order shall deprive the Political Resident, or an Officer subordinate to him, of the right to observe, and to enforce the observance of, or shall deprive any person of the benefit of, any reasonable custom existing in Maskat, unless this Order contains some express and specific provision incom patible with the observance thereof. 83. Nothing in this Order shall- (i) Affect any power or jurisdiction conferred by, or referred to in, the Act of the Governor-General of India in Council, entitled the Foreign Jurisdiction and Extradition Act, 1879, (Act XXL of 1879), or in the Indian (Foreign Jurisdiction) Order in Council, 1902; or (ii) Affect any jurisdiction for the time being exercisable by the Political Resident under any Imperial Act other than the Foreign Jurisdiction Act, 1890; or (iii) Prevent the Political Agent from doing anything which His Majesty’s Consuls in the Dominions of any State in amity with His Majesty are for the time being, by law, usage, or sufferance, entitled or enabled to do. 84. If a question arises whether any place is or is not in Maskat for the purposes of this Order, it shall he referred to the Political Resident, and a certificate under his hand and seal shall he conclusive on the question, and shall he taken judicial notice of by any Court established under this Order. 8o. Not later than the 31st day of March in eacli year, or such other day as the Secretary of State, or, with his previous or subsequent assent, the Governor-General of India in Council, directs from time to time, the Political Resident shall send to the Governor-General of India in Council, for transmission to the Secretary of State, a Report on the operation of this Order up to the 31st day of December in the previous year, or such other date as the Secretary of State, or, with his previous or subsequent assent, the Governor-General of India in Council, directs from time to time, showing for the last twelve months the number and nature of the proceedings, criminal and civil, taken under this Order, and the result thereof, and the number and amount of fees received, and such other information, and being in such form as the Secretary of State, or, with his previous or subsequent assent, the Governor-General of India in Council, from time to time directs.27 86. (1) A printed copy of this Order, and of all Rules of Procedure and other Rules for the time being in force under this Order, shall be kept open to inspection free of charge in the Office of the Political Agent and of each C&lt;^rt established under this Order. I-') Piinted copies thereof shall be sold in Maskat at such reasonable price as the Political Agent from time to time directs. 87. —(1) This Order shall be published in the “Gazette of India” within such time after the passing thereof as the Secretary of State may prescribe, and shall come into i force on such day, (in this Order referred to as the commencement of this Order), within six months after that publication, as the Governor-General of India in Council may, by notification in the said “ Gazette,” appoint in this behalf. (2) But any appointment under this Order may be made at any time after its passing, and no proof shall, in any proceedings, be required of any of the matters prescribed by this article. 88. -(1) As from the commencement of this Order, the Order in Council mentioned in the Second Schedule to this Order shall be repealed to the extent therein mentioned; but this repeal shall not— {aj Affect the past operation of that Order, or any appointment made, or any right, title, obligation, or liability accrued, or the validity or invalidity of anything done or suffered under that Order, before the making of this Order ; (b) Interfere with the institution or prosecution of any proceeding or action, criminal or civil, in respect of any offence committed against or forfeiture incurred or liability accrued under or in consequence of any provision of that Order, or any regulation confirmed by any such Order or made thereunder; (c) Take away or abridge any protection or benefit given or to be enjoyed in relation thereto. (2) Notwithstanding the repeal of the Order aforesaid, all rules and regulations approved or confirmed by or under such Order so repealed shall continue and be as if this Order had not been made ; but so that the same may be revoked, altered, or otherwise dealt with under this Order, as if thev had been made under this Order. (.3) Criminal or civil proceedings begun under the Order repealed by this Order, and pending at the time when this Order comes into operation, shall from and after that time, be regulated by the provisions of this Order, as far as the nature and circumstances of each case admit.28 And the Most Honourable the Marquess of Crewe, K.G., and the Right Honourable Sir Edward Grey, Bart., K.G., two of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, are to give the necessary directions herein as to them may respectively appertffti. ALMEKIC FITZROY. FIRST SCHEDULE. India Acts applied. Acts XXXV. and XXXVI. of 1858 relating respectively to lunatics and Lunatic Asylums. The Indian Penal Code (Act XLV. of 1860). The Whipping Act, 1864 (Act VI. pf 1864). The Indian Succession Act (Act X. of 1865). The Indian Divorce Act (Act IV. of 1869), except so much as relates to divorce and nullity of marriage. The Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, (Act XIV. of 1869), except sections 6, 15, 23, 32, 33, 34, 38 to 43 (both inclusive), the last clause of section 19, and the last two clauses of section 22. The Indian Court Fees Act, 1870. The Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (Act I. of 1872). The Indian Contract Act, 1872 (Act IX. of 1872). The Indian Oaths Act, 1873 (Act X. of 1873). The Indian Majority Act (Act IX. of 1875). The Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887 (Act IX. of 1887). The Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1890 (Act XI. of 1890). The Indian Pilgrim Ships Act (Act XIV. of 1895). The Code of Criminal Procedure (Act V. of 1898), except Chapter XXXIII. So much of the Indian Post Office Act, 1898, (Act VI. of 1898), as relates to offences against the Post Office. The Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Act V. of 1908). The Indian Limitation Act, 1908, (Act IX. of 1908), so far as it applies to appeals and applications. And the enactments relating to insolvency and bankruptcy for the time being in force in the Presidency of Bombay beyond the limits of the ordinary original jurisdiction of the High Court of Judicature of Bombay. SECOND SCHEDULE. Title of Order. Extent of Repeal. 1867 - Maskat Order in Council - - - - - The whole. Printed by Eva*! and Spottiswoodk, Ltd., Printers to the King's nioat Excellent Majesty. l'Ji5. For His Majesty’s Stationery Office.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000213_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2987</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000213</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2987</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/27 'Muscat: Taxation of British subjects'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-13T22:26:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (57 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 59; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, minutes, and memoranda concerning the taxation of British subjects in Muscat and Oman. The file contains copy of the Muscat Order in Council, 1915 (folios 46-59), and subsequent amendments in 1922 (folio 45-45A) and 1935 (folio 44).The correspondence is between officials at the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Government of India (External Affairs Department), India Office, and Foreign Office, and includes minutes and memoranda on the questions of what taxes British subjects are currently liable for, whether this should be more formally regularised, and what effect the renewal of the treaty with the Sultan of Muscat may have on the tax situation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Taxation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000213#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>