<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00027b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T10:20:27.236Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. P.Z.7622/34. 17th December 1934. A Dear Mr. Ballantyne, ^ ' I write In continuation of my letter of 14tb December, numbered as above, to say that we nave now heard from the political Agent, Bahrein that the redrafts provisionally agreed between us of Article I sub-paragraph 2 and Article II, sub-paragraph 1 of the Mining Lease have been aiscussed by Colonel Loch at a meeting at which Messrs. Russell, Hamilton, Davles, Belgrave and Worth were present, in the light of which the redrafts were agreed, subject to the following observations.- (a) A lire containing municipal areas to be drawn after check, to be carried out at once, by representatives of the Sheikh and of the Company, (b) Ihe radius of the circle in the case of Sakhir is 300 yards, (c) It vias thought desirable to place on record at once, lest misunderstanding should arise in the future, the areas privately owned by the sheikh other than those in or covered by (a) and (b). (d)/ Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein petroleum Co.Ltd,, 19, Moorgate, E.C. 2.(d) It was agreed that these areas were: the hunting lodges at Rumaithah; Umm-al-Talah (including palm plantations) ? Acirj and Sakhir garden; respectively 5, 20 s 10 and 23 acres or thereabouts. There are also uncultivated areas of ahout 3 miles (, subject to further check) 'by one-eighth mile adjoining Sakhir where the ,sheikh exercises his horses ? and 4,000 acres or thereabouts at Zallaq. (e) It appears that the Company already use at Zallaq an area of 18 acres for their water supply and a strip 20 yards wide for a water pipe line, which will be shown by a blue line on the map, (f) It was agreed that the areas mentioned in (d) s of which the positions are roughly known, should be surveyed by representatives of the sheikh and of the Company and placed on records after acceptance by the Sheikh,by an exchange of letters between the chief Local Representative and Colonel Loch. Colonel Loch remarks tnat this work need not delay the signature of the Mining Lease. I mentioned to you that there is a reference to compensation in the Political Agent's telegram. This is, however, corrupt, and I have asked for a repetition, I will write to you about this later.- 3 - $ u. 3. Colonel Loch aacls that to save time the Adviser has been given a typewritten copy, in English and Arabic, corrected up to date, so that he will he in a position to discuss the matter with the sheikh at leisure. 4. It was suggested that it would he convenient if an English and Arabic text, with the alterations caused hy the present redraftings were to he printed in London and sent out hy the air mail leaving England on 22nd December. I have discussed this with you and we have agreed that, as the Political Agent will have by the middle of this week the Arabic texts which Mr. Arberry kindly produced of Article I, sub-paragraph 2 and Article II, sub-paragraph 1 9 and also the carbon copy snowing the various corrections which Mr. Arberry has inserted to bring the Arabic text into conformity with the English text, the simplest course will be that the lease should be signed on a text typewritten locally. Copies of this could be sent home and the Company could no doubt arrange to have the necessary prints in English and Arabic produced at leisure, we are telegraphing to the Gulf accordingly, The political Agent further suggests that the extra scnedule mentioned in Article II, sub-paragraph 1, as/- 4 - as redrafted ? will entail a consequential addition on page 14 ox the printed draft lease* This is, however, I think, a misunderstanding. The extra schedule to which reference is made in Article II ? sud -paragraph 1 is identical with the existing second Schedule of the lease, which contains the map, and, as I understand it, what we have in mind is that the map on which the leased areas are shown should also contain the markings referred to in the redraft of Article II, suh-paragraph 1. perhaps you would he so kind as to confirm that this is trie case? Yours sincerely, J. G LAiTHWAITE.By Air Mail. P.Z . 'V- ' ^i' hi&gt; W'' 3 ' ■ ■ Hi HlBWItTtAl ^DMM. j INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 21 DEC 1934 Forwarded with the conipliineiits of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to Q by Mail. - 3*&amp; c, C ^Flio Foroiffli Soorotary, Govornmont of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057'7 P.Z.7667/34. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM GO. LTD., » « 19, Moorgate, London, E.G. 2. 20tia Decemtier 1934. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, ' * /- '' Tiiank: you for your letter PtZ»7667/34 of the 19th instant. I observe it appears tnat the meeting referred to in paragraph 2 of your letter of the 17th December, * P.Z.7622/34, agreed that the properties mentioned in paragraph i(d) of your letter under reference are sufficiently safeguarded by tne necessity under the redraft of article II, sub-paragrapn 1 for paying compensation in tne event of their acquisition by the Company. I take tnis advantage of mentioning the fact that according to a cablegram we have received from Bahrein, it was agreed at a meeting of Colonel Loch, .Mr. Worth, Mr. Belgrave, Mr. Hamilton and Mr. Davies, that there should be no compensation in respect of the use of the zellak Water well and ri^ht of way for the existing pipe-line. You may have received by this mail news to the same effect. Yours sincerely, H.R. BALLANTYNE. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, 3•W # 1.By Air Mail. P.z . HlZ 19 7^ ^ h Ciismf JRSItXElCY, &gt;ui INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, DEC 1334 Forwarded with the coinpliuieuts of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to &gt;'£ Mail - Tin, Fuuhuu Q^rctary, Government of The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057V INDIA OPPIGi A JHALL ? 3 • ji • I • P.Z.7715/34, 17th Decemtier 1934. Iv^ dear starling, I write in continuation of previous correspondence to say that we have now heard ironi Praser that the negotiations oetween the I,P.G. and the standard Oil of California regarding marKeting or other arrangements in respect of Bahrein oil are now definitely broken off. Praser conjectured that the standard Oil of California hoped to find a market for their Bahrein production in Japan. 2. I am sending copies of this letter to Rendel at the Poreign Office and seal at the Admiralty. Yours sincerely, J«G. LAITHWAITE. P.C# Starling j E sq., Petroleum Department, Mines Department, Dean Stanley street, 3 * W1»By Air Mail. P.Z. 19?v INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 21 OEG 1934 Forwarded with the compliineuts of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. Tlic For^iffii Soorotary, rinvrrnnnnnti of Tnriia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057INDIA OFPlGi, 'JHITSHALL, ^ VJ 1 • n • J- » p#z. 7806/34. 21st December 1934, Dear Mr. Ballantyne, feny thanks for your letter of 18th DecerriDer ah out the Mining Lease. I now write to say that we telegraphed yesterday to the Political Resident ana political Agent to explain that Arahic texts of the redraft contained in our telegram of ^ . 12th Deceniber were sent direct to Bahrein hy the air k mail of 15th DeceiLher s together with a carbon copy of the Arabic text of the concession containing emendations to meet the points taken in Mr. Arherry's * ^ note of 23rd November, we added that we had agreed p' with the Company that the lease should be signed on a copy typewritten locally and embodying the redrafts and emendations in question ana that it could be reprinted here at leisure. 2. we further informed the authorities in the Gulf that we had discussed with the Company the question/ Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein petroleum Co. Ltd., 19, Moorgate, E.C. 2.question raised in paragraph 5 of ray letter of 17th December, p,Z.7623/34, and that the Company were now arranging with Mr. Davies to Inset a small map showing the head of Muharraq Island, the town of Muharraq and its urhan boundaries on the map referred to in the present schedule II. There would he no necessity in these circumstances for an additional schedule or for any alteration in the text of Article II, sub-paragraph 1 as redrafted in agreement between us. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAITS.P. Z.7806/34. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM GO. LTD# ? 19 3 JViborgate, Loncion ? E.G. 2. 18th December 1934. Dear Mr. Laithwalte, Thank you for your letter p.Z.7622/34 of yesterday's date from which it would appear that there is now unanimity in Bahrein concerning Articles I and II. I observe that there is some question concerning compensation wnich nas yet to come forward. It is a kinaly action on the part of Colonel Loch to put the Financial Adviser to the sheikh in a position to discuss at leisure witn the sheikh, the proposed Lease; it is much appreciated hy the Company. I note and confirm that the Lease is to he typed in Bahrein for execution and to he printed in London subsequently at leisure to supply the necessary copies. After very careful consideration I agree with you that there is no need for an extra schedule; it is true that the town of Muharraq is not shewn on the so-called Selection Map which is to constitute the Second schedule to the Lease hut we here think it would be much the hest plan to have inset on such plan a small nap shewing the head of the Muharraq Island with the to'wn of Muharraq and its urhan boundaries. We are telegraphing accordingly to Mr. Davies at Bahrein asking him to see that this is done. It should be quite a simple matter and I think it will be found that it involves/- a - involves no alteration anywhere. I had thought at first that to refer to the Map forming tne secona schedule for reference to the boundaries of Muharraq would he misleading as to the area selected; I find this is not so. You may take it, therefore, that I confirm that the extra schedule to wnich reference is made in Article II 9 suh-paragraph 1 is identical with the existing schedule to the Lease which contains the Map and that what we havein mind is that the Map on which the leased areas are shewn, also contains the markings referred to in the re-draft of Article II, suh-paragraph I. Yours sincerely, H.E. BALLANTYNE. J.G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, 3.W. 1.I 1 —66/2 ( Telegram R 27 From ' Politiaal Agent, Bahrain. To Political Hesident, Bushire, Ko. 11 Dated and received 9th January 1935* Article in Loa Angeles 'Times 11 middle November states that (a) local Standard Oil executives say that tank-ship W.S.Rheems v/ill make one voyage Bahrain to Japan but (b) that other sources report she will make at least two voyages and that other Standard Oil tank-ships v /ill be added to new service. Poli ti cal ST.. to 35 ■ / He. vCONFIDENTIAL. No. 57 -s of ±935 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. 2, The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. Dated January ±936 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Telegram No #11 of 9th January 1936 from the Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain Oil Copy forwarded, with compliments, to the rolitical Agent, Bahrain, for information.■ ! Ifidential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. depar rment, EXPRESS LETTER [A T . L 1 , This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended io be treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been m despatched,] From Political, \ Bahrsin. ' 7 To:- Resident, Bushire. I // | 1 ^^OiUlAT ^OolcjL ' j Repeated J - ^o= Secretary of State for - L ndla, London, Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New ^elM, AdrC/.^-lO/l. Dated 5 th January By Air Mail. By Air Mail. P 1 Laithwaite 1 s letter No:P.Z. 7061/34 November 2-3rd, 19-34. Callibration arrangements in Bahrain. 2, I have discussed matter with Adviser, who has been shown hov 1. 1 the arrangements work, ^tate Engineer is to be sho?;n also and we think 4- • 1 that it should be possible for him to do the checking of readings on behalf of the Bahrain Government. ^• 1 tnink that vOtate Engineer might do this for a few (say I half a dozen) shipments and then report exactly how he exercises the check in practice and whether he is satisfied that his check is sufficient to secure the interests of the Bahrain Government. iieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. S. 6. MFP—785S&amp;P—(M.10U)—18-8-33—2.00.000.l-c, Confidential GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. , Department. 1 !i t * ' This 18 m OnIG!A AL MESSAGE, sent hy post to save telenravldc expense and undue use of ike wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, mth the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time arid formalities it is worded and signed as if it had hem s&amp; despatched*] From To Political, Bahrain Resident, Bushire. il&amp;HW mmmmy. fan M4t stwtnwui mm Dated 6 th Janu; 393 Begins. Your Express fetter of December 26th, irtfe-S. Bahrain Oil. Repetition paragraph 6 of my telegram of December 15th, 976. Ends, A I 'V r e agree that these areas are hunting lodges at Rumaithan, ITmm al Talah (including palm grove), 'Arnr and Sakhir garden, respectively five, twenty, ten and twenty-three acres or thereby; and th&lt; t these properties are sufficiently safeguarded by necessity for paying compensation for their acquisition. 0 There are also uncultivated areas of about three miles (subject to further check) by one-eighth mile adjoining Sakhir where Shaikh races his horses and of four thousand acres or thereby at Zallaq.' Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain, r s.6. mit—785s&amp;p—(m-1014j—18-8-33—2,00.000.• &lt;) /'C- ■ . A remedv is for thf Company to appoint a suitable Chief Local n s it t ive, hut a -an of ; stc !. ~ :j. ? v er , ong j. (i) for tj'.e Politios I Agent tc have co aliags - itli him t s repress■ ting tie ^irm an (ii) for him to be able to stand up to the manager, »ouid involve paying a large salary to an inriivjyua], Y .ho would have but little v ork• tJ * ' [ ' 1, Vl I k . surne^cee; thr:t the Comv.r ny migbt train one taeir rltish employees to be eventually Assistant manager a •. also cf-.: Representative. At pre seat, how- i: vc:&gt; 1 oi.'.-t :,:.,e v . ,v( arr v &gt;itiph subject uited to this position, Moreover, the Assistant Onager would always be very distinctly a subordinate and it is undoubtedly desirable tbau trie Political Agent should deal with the real head of the affairs of the Company, either a Chief Local Representative senior to the Onager or the Manager. There are no doubt advantages in keeping alive the ■' ^ ^ionalit y 0 ° tne Chief Local Representative, but now that the Atiniiig i;■ signeo and the work beconies more ■ A comiierci&amp;j. s .c administrative and less political, the dis- advantages outweigh the advantages from the local point of view. There is, o' course, the possibility that the eldestion of tne remaining ares (see Captain C-astrell f s letter ^o:C/37l-lo/l dated the Trd August 1j3? and connected correspondence) may now come up again 0 hlch might stress the political side of the work), but in such a case I would, from the local point of vievv, be quite i-repareo to deal with cir.-avies. In view, however, of the large proportion of the island covered by the Company f s Mining Lease its location, i eel doubtful whether the remaining area will attract any other interests. I would, therefore, suggest for consideration, that, now /thatthat the lining &gt;-• ■ .1 is si'.. •• • ' the act I.vil ;.cs of th.e Company become more o^ &lt; co-uiiercial and aoministrative than a poiiticai matter, we might agree to accepting the Manager as Chief ijocai Representative so long as he continues to be oersona grata to His Mi j sty f 5 Government, ihis proviso would afford us 'an opening for action in case any Manager were to prove really unsuitable or ocgection-hle. 9. Should the Shaikh raise an objection X would suggest explaining tla change i.i the situation (from political to commercial anh a mliistr .live) and saying that we think that, as long as the ^ane::er continues to be aersona 'rate to His Majesty 1 s Government, ve think that this will adequately safe guard his i iterests. 1 have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel Political Agent, Bahrain,GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D epartment. [N *B, —This is mi ORIGIJS AL M JESS AGE, sent hy 'post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sure time and formalities rt is worded and signed, as if it had been so despatched,] Froh Political Resident, Buahire» T@ Repeated Ketaxandufc, London* foreign. New Delhi, Political, Bahrain. No. 7 .-3 of 1936. Dated 14 th January JBSs,* fn Correspondence ending with Loch*s impress Letter Ho # C/3»10/l, dated 5th January 1935• Calibration arrangeMents in Bahrain* I concur* Sgd* r *C.FOWLS, Lieut«»Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ATTESTS)* //tL for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Hi*- S $i dc f p—1666s&amp;p—(m-1821)—27 • 9-32—^2 1 fi0,000.&lt;\ p /v CQMFIDJiiNTI AL 4' b N0.84-S of 1936. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 16th January 1936. To The Political rigent, BAHRAIN Subject : Chief Local Representative for The Bahrain Petroleum Company. Memorandum. &amp; / &gt;S Your letter Ko .C /13-10/1, dated the 6th January 1936. I appreciate the practical arguments which you put forward for having as Chief Local Representative the Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, and therefore an American. There is, however, the psychological objection, (and when dealing with Arabs objections of that nature, whether reason- able or not from our point of view, must be counted as important) that only recently the Shaikh and his family (vide my Express Letter No.C/193, dated the 8th April 1934) express- ed strong objections to an American Chief Local Representative, and I think it would be distinctly impolitic to force an American upon them. Amongst other objections, being Araos, they would probably think we had done so under American pressure, which would be most undesirable. 2. The Company may not, as you point out, like dealing with confidential and technical matters through a person not a member of the firm, which has been the case with Mr. Russell and would be again if his successor were appointed, A but that is the Company^s concern, and the lact remains, as stated /stated in paragraph 3 of my Express Letter quoted above, that no distinct advantage would be gained either from our point of -i view or that of the Shaikh in having an ^merican Chief Local Representative. 3. Personally I have no objection to an American as Chief Local Representative so it really depends on the Shaikh ana his family. As you point out, now that the Mining Lease is sign- - ed the activities of the Company are more of a commercial ana administrative than a political matter, and if this - as ^ou suggest ~ were explained to the Shaikh he might withdraw his objections• I hope to visit Bahrain before very long and would like to discuss the matter with you, and then with the Shaikh. sd. TiC .Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested Resident in the Persian GulfCONFIDENTIAL. No - 86-S of 1936. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to (/'■&gt;' 1. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London• 2. ThevForeign Secretary to the Government of India New Delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Cs). - 5 British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated, 3' 16th January 1936 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter No.67-S of 11th January - l 936. ^— ' jo .lb Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Telegram No. 16 of 12th January 1936 from the rolitica Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded, with compli4 Agent,Bahrain, for info Subject. Bahrain Oil. ents, to the Political at ion. rmNo.D.5345-K/34. 1% J * Prom The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. O ^ Dated Hew Delhi, the / January 1935 Question of levying light dues at Bahrain from the vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Sir T 7ith reference to your letter ]N T o« 1123-S of 1954, dated the 29th Kovemher 1934, I am directed to say that the Government of India agree that the Bahrain Petroleum Company should be approached again as suggested by you. They will be glad if, while communicating the Company f s reply, you would also furnish your views on the question of the desirability or otherwise of levying light dues on the Company 1 s vessels. \ I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant Deputy Secretary to the Government of India kJ ( I. ift / £ &lt; J1 CONFIDENTIAL. No. 113-S of -1-935. c ,iW IS 7 CI The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his coin- pliments to The rolitical Agent, Bahrain and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned doca- ment (/). with a request that he will (a) approach the Bahrain Petroleum Company next month and report result (b)furnish his views on the desirability or otherwise of levying light dues on the Company's vessels. British Consulate-General, X BUSHTRB. ll Dated. . .«7 anuary. .+.9,36.. i •• ■ * w S'-nk* Reference to previous correspondence Residency Printed Letter ^0.1124-3 of 29th November 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department letter No.D.5343-N/34 of 9th J anuary 1935• Subject. Question of levying light dues at Bahrain from the vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Company.*2 f j u Air Mail. P. Z. 7144/34. INDIA 0FFIC1, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S .W. 1. U- My dear Garoe, / \ ' \ 23rd November 1934, ( v . A Y \ f Would you please refer to the Gfovemment of India's express letter, F.17 -N /33, of 17th September 1934, about Bahrein buoying and to my d.o. to Ballantyne, P.Z.5916/34, of 26th September, copies ±sl of which were sent to India, Bushire and Bahrein by the air mail of 28th September? I now enclose copy of further d,o. correspond ence with the Company, which is, I think, self-explanatory. Would you let us know whether it has now been definitely decided to place the lightship in the position described in my letter to Ballantyne of to-day's date? (Compare correspondence enclosed in Fraser-Tytler 1 s d.o. of 20th April last, F.282-K/33). . / , // Yours sincerely, : /(,i Sd/- J. Gr. Laithwaite. ). K. Caroe, Esq., G.I.E,, yoverranent of IMia X ±M.Xl wX X \J JL JU Axvi* •*- vA&gt; y oreign &amp; Political Department.P.Z. 7144/34. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S. W. 1. 23rd November 1934, Dear Mr. Ballantyne, i / Many thanks for your letter of 20th November about the Bahrein lightbuoy, a copy of which is being sent to the G-overnment of India. 2, As regards the position of the lightship, we understand that it is proposed to place it in the position on the ten fathom line which was originally suggested for the outer buoy of the Company's proposed approach to Khor Khaliya, (viz. latitude 26° 31 f N., longitude 50° 5%* S.). The above position is described as being 22 miles from the outer lightbuoy of Bahrein and 32 miles from the proposed oiling berth, a direct course leading to each. Yours sincerely, Sc\. J. G. LAITHWAITS.P.Z,7144/34. THE BAHREIN PETROLSUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19 9 Moorgate, London, E .G. 2. 20th November 1934. Dear Mr. Laithwaite,** C\ ^ &gt; \ ■ I have received instructions to reply to your letter P.Z 1 .5916/34 t of tixe 26th September. As I informed you at our meeting on Friday last, the Company note, with pleasure, that the Government of India have ordered a Lightship for Bahrein Harbour for the Persian Gulf lighting service and that when this Lightship is placed in the position in which it is at present proposed to put it, the Lightbuoy required by the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited will no longer be necessary. Assuming, as the Company do, that when the Lightship is in position it will not be necessary any longer for the Company to maintain the Lightbuoy at present on loan to them, the Company will then be able to return it. Perhaps you could indicate to me some time, the precise position it is intended the Lightship shall occupy? In the meantime, I am instructed to ask you to thank the Government of India for its kindly offer of the Lightbuoy which, it is observed, is a new one, and to say that if, in the events which might happen, it is desirable for the Company to have a Lightbuoy, they will be pleased to accept the offer of the Government to retain the Lightbuoy at present on loan to them. As you assume, it is not the wish of the Company to proceed, at present, with the proposal to provide a new buoy. Yours sincerely, Sd. H, R. BALLANTYNS. J.G. Laitoa^|,^sq.,'BY AIR MIL' Foreign and Political Department. Delhi; The //// ' January 1935. D.O. No.F.17-N/33. ^ith reference to your demi -official latter No. ?• 2.7144/54, dated the 23rd November i9M f regarding the position of the lightship for Bahrain harbour, I am desired to inform you that the Government of India have now definitely decided to place the li^itship in the position described in your letter to Ballantyne of the 23rd November 1934, No. P.2, 7144/34 ^ Yours sincerely, 3d/- 0. K. Oaroe. To J. G-. Laithwaite, Isquire, C.I.I., India Office, LONDON.►0^ .MSI INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 3.W» 1 • 18th. January 19 (. C ; sfi,, JoBis'' Air toil . p.z. 598/35. ]Vi/ dear Fowle In continuation of previous correspondence on the subject of arrangements for oil measurement, etc. at Bahrein, I enclose copy of a letter from Ballantyne and of its enclosure, which is, I think, self-explanatoiy. 2 C I am sending a copy of the letter and of its enclosure to Loch and a copy of the letter, hut without the enclosure, to the Government of India hy to-day's air nail. Yours sincerely, SI ~ The Hon'hle Lt.Gol.T.C. Fowle mhd.h n o IT U » D • Hi « , The Residency, Bushire. nlIf! 19, MOORGATE, LONDON, E.G.2. 17th. January 1935. Dear Mr.Laithwaite, Oil Measurement - Terminal facilities. As I promised you at our last talk on oit measurement I now send you a copy of the Diagram of the Sitrah terminal pipelines and valves, with a Memorandum in explanation thereof: two additional copies are included - if you want any more, let me know and I will arrange for you to have them. Copies of this Diagram are, I understand, being sent to the Sheikh and his Advisers for their consideration in the light of the inspection on the ground 1 'believe they have already made of the means of checking, for royalty purposes, the outflow of oil from the Sitrah t anks. I now await the views of the Local Authorities on the operations suggested 'by the Company as necessary or advisable for checking the outflow of oil. I have mentioned to you also that a question would undoubtedly arise one of these days on the displacement of oil from the pipeline by the discharge of ballast water from an incoming tanker. I am told by the Company that such an operation is not likely to happen often; so far as can be foreseen no?/, it could best be dealt with by the allowance from, the oil measured for royalty of an agreed quantity of oil. I mention this now because the question is being taken up locally in Bahrein and I may be asked/ J.G.Laithwaite , Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I. P.Z.598/55. THE BAHREIN PETROLEIF COXPANY LIMITED.V asked shortly to put the views of the Company before you for your consideration and decision. The point is not likely to arise in respect of the shipnent to the 'Rheem'. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) H.R.Ballantyne. &gt;u M K M 0 R A H D U M subject J The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited lermlnal Facilities, Loading and Oil Measurement Methods; Si trail Island j Bahrein. For the guidance and convenience of all concerned, there is attached hereto copy of a chart which illustrates diagrammatic ally the installations of The. Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited at their terminal on Sitrah Island, Bahrein. This chart is believed to be practically self -explanatory. However, the following supplementary description, to be used in conjunction therewith, may be found useful to those having no prior experience of oil storage and measurement- It will be noted that the text is divided into two parts: I Description of Facilities, and II Loading and Oil Measurement Procedure.I 'lMiiWPfMiifti umiiii - 2 - i - P j-schiptioh of facilities Tank's There are three steel oil tanks, equipped with Wiggins floating roofs. One of these has a calibrated capacity of slightly less than 80,000 barrels, the other two a calibrated capacity of slightly more than 84,000 barrels each. They are referred to as Kos.80-1, and 85-2 and 85-3 respectively. There is also a bilge water tank of approximately 8,000 barrels capacity, to be used to receive ballast water on occasions when it may be necessary for tankers to discharge such water. The 'Barrel* referred to here has a volumetric content of 42 u.s. gallons, or 9)7^2 cubic inches. Pipelines and Connections The pipelines at the terminal, and the purpose for which each is intended, are as follows; (a) Lines connected to the three oil tanks: 1. Incoming line, size 8 n , through which oil is delivered to the tanks from the field. 2. Suction line, (main tank outlet), size l6 w , through which oil is delivered from the tanks to the pumps. Circulating line, size 6', by means of which oil may be returned to the tanks from the pumps, or oil or water may be delivered to any of the oil tanks from the sea loading line. 4. Drain line, size 8', by means of which water may be drained from the oil tanks and carried to the sximps as illustrated# (b) Other linest 5» Ballast line, size S 1 *, for delivery of ballast water from ships to the bilge water tank. 6. Skimming line, size 3 rt , together with a separate pump, by means of which oil may be skimmed off the bilge water tank and delivered to any of the oil tanks through the 6 W circulating line. i~ 3 - U s 7* Sea loading line, size 12 tt , extending from the pump house to the Sitrah tanker anchorage, through which oil is delivered to the ships,and through which ships 1 ballast water may be pumped ashore if necessary. There is also a 2 ,, water drainage line leading from the control house and pump house to the sumps♦ Tank Connections The manner by which lines 1, 2 and 3 referred to above are connected to each of the three oil tanks is shown in the diagram in the upper left hand corner of the accompanying chart. Both the 8 W incoming line and l6 ,,,, suction line are connected directly to each tank, while the 6 11 circulating line is joined to the 8' incoming line a few feet from the tank. The 8 W line is fitted with a gate valve between the tank and this junction, and a second gate valve on the opposite side thereof. The 16* line has a gate valve near the tank, while the 6 tt line has such a valve near its junction with the o' line. Short l 11 lines, fitted with valves and check valves, bi- passing the large gate valves in the 6% 8 ,: and l6 ,, lines, act as a relief for expansion in the larger lines when the large valves are closed. The drain line is not connected directly to the oil tanks. For water drainage purposes, a line, fitted with a gate valve of the same size, leads from each tank, to a concrete box to permit observation of the drainage stream. From each observation box the B** line leads to the sump. The 4 W line referred to is, in each case, connected to the bottom of the tank, being turned to a vertical position at point of connection. Pumps Four centrifugal pumps, in series, draw the oil from any of the tanks via the 16* suction line and deliver it to the 12 t, sea loading line. Between the second and third pump, the oil goes through a heat exchanger, as indicated in the chart. When oil or water are returned ashore from or through the sea line, it will ordinarily be done by means of the ships' pumps, and the land pumps will not be required for this purpose except possibly in emergencies as mentioned below.- 4 - '-'f V' 1 Valves a izroup of three valves in the control house permits rHversion of the oil stream coming from the land pumps, or fiverllon of oU or «ater being displaced from the sea loading line, into either the circulating or the ballast lint,, desired* In addition to the above, on the suction side of the pumps, thpre is a gate valve in the 16' line, also a connection between thif line and the ballast line. This connection is closedby means of a blank flange which can be removed if necessary to permit suction being taken on the sea line by the land pumps, the contents being delivered into the c...icui^iit&gt; line. This arrangement is designed principally to ^eet y emergency that miiht arise, and it is not contemplated ordinarily to employ it. 't &gt;«Uk II - LOADING &amp; OIL MMSm^MENT PROCEDURE Preliminary Steps In loading a tanker, usually twOj sometimes possibly only one, of the large oil tanks will be drawn on. Thus there will always be at least one tank which will not be involved in a loading and which may at the time be receiving oil from the field. Prior to loading, a short test run will be made, during which oil will be drawn from one of the tanks and returned to the same tank via the circulating line. The purpose of this test is primarily to warm up the pump engines at idling speed, to examine the piping for any possible leaks, and to note pump pressures etc.- generally to ascertain that the plant is in proper operating condition. It also permits a certain amount of stirring up, as it were, of oil in.the tank involved and tends to equalize any temperature differences. ^t this time new charts will be placed on the recording pressure gauge and flow meter, the instruments wound and set at the correct time and the pens inked. The remote throttle control will be tested and any other tests made to satisfy the operator that the entire system is in order. During or prior to this test the incoming oil stream from the field will be diverted to a tank not to be used in this loading, and water drained from the loading tanks; and before gauges are taken the proper valves at the tanks will be closed and sealed, as explained below. Gauging and Sampling When all is in readiness to commence loading, oil in the shipping tanks will be gauged, sampled and tested for temperature in accordance with the accepted practice, as will the bilge water tank in case it contains oil which is to be run. Immediately after loading is completed and the pumps are stopped, the tanks are again gauged, and tested for temperature. The various factors upon which computation of the amount of oil shipped depends are recorded at the time they are determined, namely the 'high* 1 and ^low' gauges, and the thermometer, hydro meter and centrifuge tube readings. Reading of the steel gauging tapes, and of the instruments referred to, is a comparatively simple matter, and when the Shaikh's representative is present to check the measurement he need oniky be concerned to see that the readings are correct, and correctly recorded. The correctness of these data being assured, correctness of the result is assured.Computation of the gross amount of oil withdrawn, determined from difference in gauges in conjunction with volumetric tables for the tanks involved, and correction of such gross amount by- reduction to volume at 60 F. and deductions for water and other foreign substances, are arithmetical calculations only which can be carried out, and/or checked, at any time after the shipment. Sealing of Proper Valves To insure correctness in measurement of oil shipped precautions must be taken that (1) no ungauged oil is permitted to enter the pumps during loading operations and that (2) between gauges no ungauged oil is permitted to enter the tanks from which shi^ents are being made nor to be withdrawn from these tanks except to the pumps. The above can be safeguarded against provided the following gate valves, which might otherwise permit unintended diversion of oil, are kept closed and sealed during loading operationst At the tank or tanks not used in the current loading i The 16 H valve on the suction line, to prevent oil in the tank from draining into that line. The 6 W valve on the circulating line, to prevent oil from the field line being diverted to one of the other tanks via the circulation line* The l w valves in the small bi-pass lines around the above. At the tank or tanks from which current shipment is bein^ made &lt; The 8 n valve in the incoming line on the field side of juncture of this line with the circulating line, to prevent oil from the field to enter either the tank or the circulating line. The l w valve in the small bi-pass line around the above. If there is oil in the bilge water tank, when loading is commenced and if this tank is not to be drawn on or used in the loading, the outlet valve of this tank also should be closed and sealed.- 7 - It is incumbent upon the operators, of course, to see that any valves that would permit wastage of oil, or time, such as those in the drainage lines, are kept tightly closed between gauges. Otherwise, a study of the chart will show that if proper precautions are taken with respect to the valves mentioned above, the opening or closing of other valves in the system will not affect the measurement. Hence, the order in which, and the times at which, such other valves are opened or closed may be left entirely to the discretion of the operator in charge. The above description makes no attempt to explain details such as the exact manner of taking tank gauges, or of samples, or as to the reading of instruments; nor the precise order in which the various steps are taken; nor as to the method to be used in sealing closed valved. Obviously, familiarity with these details can be acquired by observation, experience and consultation with the Manager*. Their essential simplicity obviates any difficulty in understanding them./ INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, 3.W, P. Z.399/35 IiJ/ dear Powia, i '--f Ail 3^ (? IStii January 1935 Tlae I enclose copy of correspondence with Ballantyne, which is, I think, self-explanatory, about the Bahrein Mining i^ease. We have so far received no copy here of the Lease as finally signed hy the sheikh and would he grateful, if no ohjection is seen, if Loch could arrange for the sheikn's copy to he sent home, as suggested hy the Company, for comparison with the counterpart which has heen received hy them from their manager in Bahrein. We will then arrange with the Company for the printing of the necessary spare copies. I need not say that we shall lose no time in returning it and that all necessary precautions in connection with its custody will he taken. 2. • I understand from Ballantyne that the Company^ desire to compare the documents is partly due to the fact not only that they have noticed one or two small alterations from the Lease as provisionally agreed here, hut/ Hon'hle Lt.Col. T.C. Fowle, G.B^E., Ihe Residency, Bushire.- 2 - 'but/ that the copy which they have received is unaated. 3. I am sending copies of tnis letter to Loch and to the Government of India. Yours sincerely,j9/55. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, MOORGATE, LONDON, E.G.2. 17th January 1935. Dear Mr.Laithwaite, Mining Lease. As I have told you, I have received from the Company's Manager in Bahrein, the Mining Lease duly sealed and executed, but 'before I forward the document I have to San Francisco, I would like to have an opportunity of comparing it with its counterpart reserved for the use of His Majesty's Government. I have in mind particularly that this would minimise the loss of the Company's document in the last stage of its journey and provide here an authentic document from which copies can 'be made. The Government's part has not, I understand, yet reached you. Might I suggest that it should now Toe sent to you so that we might examine our respective documents against each other: I could then forward the Company's part to San Francisco for the Company's archives there. If this could be conveniently arranged soon, I should appreciate it as I think the Company should have the document without delay. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) H.R.Ballantyne. J.G.Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I.if INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL 5 3.W. 1. p.z. 299/35. 18th January 1935. Dear Mr. Ballantyne, Thank you very much for your letter of the 17th January about the Lining Lease, as I explained hy telephone, the counterpart is in fact the sheikh's copy ana not a copy reserved for His Majesty's Government, the Lease being one given by the sheikh (with, of course, the approval of His Majesty's Government) to the Bahrein Petroleum Company. 2. I am, however, sending a copy of your letter (and of this reply) to the political rtesiaent in the Persian Gulf and to Colonel Loch by tomorrow's air mail and asking that, if no objection is seen, arrangements may be made to let us see the sheikh's counterpart for the purpose of comparison ana with a view also to the preparation of prints of the Lease as signea. I will let you know at once as soon as I receive a reply. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAHHWAITE• H.R. Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Co.Lta., 19, Moorgate, E.C. a./ M/t- y -s Telegram S'rom G»T,G. Political Resident, 'Bfiahire. Political Agent, Bahrain. (Copy 'by post to Secretary of State for India, London. G-ovemment of India, New Delhi.) Ho 136 Bated the 30th Januarv 1935. Your letter of 5th January C«6 paragraph 3 and India Office letter of IPth January P.Z. 399, Please forward third original of Mining Lease to India Office. BRI r ?GOHSTJL Jl- *{1 (Copy forwarded to India Office and Govt.of India under P.L-Ko.166-S of 30/1/35). ■1 I 11; i: ll3 / Confidential . No;C/31-10/1• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 13th January 1.-/65, Froffii- Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, 1.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To:- ^ &lt;r ' •' The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Sir, 1 have the honour to refer to ii?y letter No:C/542-10/l dated the 24th May 19M (Sth Safar 1353) to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin ! Isa A1 Khalifah, with which I forwarded % a copy and translation of a letter dated the 10th May 1934 from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, regarding the method of measurement of oil for the purpose of calculating the royalties payable by The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited. A 2, The proposals embodies in paragraphs Nos;6 to 8 of the Chief Local Representative^ letter dated the 10th May 19S4 provide a satisfactory procedure for assessing the quantity of crude oil for royalty purposes and 1 write to enquire It His Excellency approves of them. 1 have the honour to be Your most obedient servant. o( /— Lr. • »C Q • Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.Copy of letter ^io: b22/2Q dated the :3th Sham al 1^53 (1.4th January Ire 5) from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to refer to your letter No: C/: 1-10/1 dated the Icth January 1955 and to inform .you tnat His Ixcellency Siic: jjch Sir .ic.inad bin * Xss. A1 Khalifah a groves of the method of assessing ruantity of crude oil as described in the Chef Local Representative's letter dated the 10th May 1^34.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER jAIR MAIL). [n.b.— Thia is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means oj communication more , expeditious than the ordinary mail and ts cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. C/70-10/1. the 30th January ~ 9 35: xTTT TTT ~LTf''V IZJJ w To Resident, Bushire.^ ^ _ _ j Repeated:- Secretary of State for India, London, Foreign Secretary to the Governinent of India, New Delhi. Reference^ letter No:C/6-10/l January 5th, 1955. Bahrain Oil. ^.1% 2. I regret that the date was omitted on the last page of the Mining Lease. The place was left blank as it was not known on what date His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin f Isa A1 Khalifah would seal it and I fear that I forgot to insert it. 3. Messrs Russell and Davies have suggested a suitable authority, which has now been sealed by the Shaikh, signed by them and witnessed by me, permitting the Company to insert 'SSth' in the blank space. /) ' Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. (Signature) (Designation) S. 44. MFP—825S&amp;P—(M-1070)—14-9-34—10,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPR ESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). is an OKIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department,] No. C/102-10/1. Dated Me 10th February ^35* To Resident, Bushire• Repeateds- Secretary of State for india. 8. London* lUier^ ei « n Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. / ^ H ;3 My telegram of January Igth, 13. Bahrain Oil. Company report Tankship Rheem will definitely return to Bahrain first fortnight of March to take second shipment of oil of approximately same quantity as last shipment. —'fc'* X • C • S • y for Political Agent, Bahrain* (Signature) s. 44. MFP—825S&amp;P—(M-1070)—14-9 34—10,000. (Designation)By Air Mail. p.z. 19^ y INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the coiupliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. ta Soorota ry, Gov^riuni-iilj uf fnHfi. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057V INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. p.z. 892/35. 7th February 1955. Dear Mr. Ballantyne, You kinaly let us know a little while abO that it was probahle that a further shipment of 100,000 barrels of oil would fee made from Bahrein early in ferch. If it is not too much trouble to the Company we should he much interested if you would he bood enough to keep us in touch with such shipments as there may he from time to time. It is not only of general interest to usj but also has 9 of course 3 a direct relation to the finances of the gtate. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAmiWAlTS. H t R, Ballantyne ? Esq., Bahrein petroleum Co.Ltd., 19, Moor^ate, iii« C • .By Air Mail. P.Z. V A DIA OFFICE, LONDON, ASfffc 1955 Forwarded with the coinpliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. SriGfoiwy, (juvcrrmwn-iL uf In^ra. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL j 3.W. 1. P.Z .83E/35. 11th Fetiruary 1935. Dear Mr. Ballantyne, I write to confirm that we hope to see you here at 11 o'clock tomorrow to check through the sheikh's copy of the Mining Lease. a. From colonel Loch's despatch intimating the signature of the Mining Lease I note that one small alteration in the draft was made hy mutual consent. The alteration in question is that the north-east corner of the sheikh's house, instead of the centre of the house, was taken as the centre of the Green circle drawn at Sakhir. The Political A&amp;ent remarks that this corner is clearly defined and unlikely to he ^changed and it would have 'been inappropriate to have had to endeavour to lix a centre in the sheikh's house itself. 3. On a further point, you will have seen that 'by agreement between the representatives of the Company and the authorities in Bahrein, the date 'aQth' /lay of December 1954/ has now been inserted in Article XXIII on/ .R. Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Co. Ltd., 19, Moorgate, tti n Oon page 26 of the draft Mining Lease, the insertion in question having been regularised by the separate authority dated 27th January 1935, of which copies have, I understand, now been received by you. The figures and letters '•SQth' have been inserted in the ordinary Enbiish form in the Arabic text of Article XXIII and have not been spelt out or translated into Arabic. 4, colonel Loch also asks that when the Mining Lease has been printed up he might be supplied with 24 copies for the use of the Bahrein Government themselves# 5, I understand that you now contemplate that there shall be a number of photostats of the Lease, which will probably be made in San Francisco, and that,In addition to these, prints will be made of the English, but not of the Arabic, text of the Lease. 6, In addition to the copies for which colonel Loch has astced, the Government of India, the political Resident, and the interested Departments here would also wish for copies. If we might have so many as 75 in all, without inconvenience to the Company; it would be of much assistance to us. Yours sincerely, J.G. L/tlTHWAITS•f INDIA OFFICS, LONDON, 3.W. 1. B y Air Ivlail . P »Z.924/35. 16th February 1935. jViy dear Powle, V /e duly received under Bahrein printed letter // ^ 0/72-10/1 of 31st January 9 copies of which were sent to il Bushire and to the Government of India 3 the ^eikh's copy of the Mining Lease of the Bahrein petroleum Company and the document authorising the insertion of a date in the Mining Lease. These have now been compared tiy the Company with their own copy and they are entirely satisf ied. v 2. On one ^uite minor point we observe that the date of signature of the Lease has not heen inserted in the Second schedule. This raises no question of substance. The Company have inserted '291121 11 in their copy ana perhaps Loch would be so kind as to arrange for a corresponding insertion in the Sheikh's copy and in the third copy. 3/ he Hobble Lt.Col. T # C. Fowle, C#B.S., The Residency, Bushire.* 2 lb 3 0 We should 'be glad if the third copy couid in due course he forwarded for record here 0 ihe position wouia then he that there would he one copy in Bahrein in the possession of the Sheikh, one copy in the India Office in the possession of the Secretary of state, and one copy in the possession of the Company, all three having equal validity and available for reference in the event of any dispute arising^ 4. I understand that the Company would he willing to supply us with a number of photostats, which will, of course, include hoth the English and the Arabic texts, and also with a number of printed copies of the English text only. We will sena a supply of these to you, Bahrein and the Government of India as soon as we receive them. 5. I am sending a copy of this letter to Loch, together with the Sheikh's copy of the Mining Lease and the document authorising the addition of the date in Article XXIII of that Lease, by to-day 1 s air mail under the letter of which I enclose a copy. A copy is also being sent to the Government of India. Yours sincerely,INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, 3.W. !• T^ y Air Mail . p 4 Z#924/25. 16th February 1935 0 jVIy dear Loch, I write witli reference to your printed , 1 letter, c.72-10/1, of 31st January, to thank you i for letting us have so promptly the sheikh 1 s copies of the Mining Lease ana the appended document authorising the insertion of a date, which I return herewith, together with a copy of a letter which is heing sent hy to-day's air mail to the political gesident. 3 0 perhaps you would he so kind as to let me have an acknowledgment of the safe receipt of the Lease, etc &lt;, Yours sincerely, J »Gr# LAITHWAITE. ieut.Colonel P.G* Loch, The Agency,. . Bahrein.By Air Mail. P.Z. 19 J - »'' C-y ^ n DIA OFFICE, LONDON, 2 3 FEB 1935 Forwarded with the coiiipliineiits of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Ail Mail. Tlio Foroiffli Socretar} 7 , frnvernmRnt of Tnrij,a. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057'h f / r «fm iiuk dep h m skt . (iilNiJ DliPAtTi J.-T), DSAN JfAl^iL.Y arSSST, &amp;1ILLBANK, 3.W. 1 *■« Jt 19th Petoruary 1935 Daax LaitAwaite Ulth reference to your letter, reference p,a,750a/34, of 7th December 1334, enclosln t ; a letter Iroui Ballantyne of toe Bailie uate, in wnicii he reported that toe Bahrein ^11 aonipany ware proposing to ship 100,000 barrels of oil Irom Bahrein, I have just heard that the oil tanker ' ^eam' left Bahrein on 18to January ;.nu arrived at Yokohama on Oto February. It loo its as though toe Bahrein petroleum company is hoping to establish a uarket for toeir oil in the Far East, at any rate for the present, but so far as Japan is concerned tois may be affected by toe negotiations which are now being conducted by the British and .ousrican oil interests with toe Japanese iovsmment. The position in regard to Bahrein oil is being closely watched. Yours sincerely, (3d.) F.G. ilTA 'iLING' G. Lalthswits toweite. ., Sh « , India office, fthltohallIdentl&amp;l* GOVERXMENT OF INDIA, — D epartment. 7^ f t.v. V.~Tlm is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE. telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, 101th the same expeddmn ./ u sae time a;d formalihes it is^oned a d siy, ed as if it had beea so despatched.] r ^ From Political^ Bahrain. To Resident, Bushire. C/151-10/1. Dated 5rd March J$&amp;.. Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. yfJO Reference your Memorandum No:84-S dated the 15th January 1935 and our conversation during your recent visit to Bahrain. S. I asked Shaikh whether he had any objection to Mr. Devies as Chief Local Representative. After talk with Shaikh Abdullah he said that he knew Mr. Davies and he was a TT good man', so that he had no objection to him even though an American, but that if anyone else were to be appointed in his place (i.e., as Field Manager) this acceptance should not apply to him. 3. I recommend that Mr. Davies be accepted as Chief Local /Representative U C C- S 6 MFP-400S&amp;P—{M-480 —26-7-34—2,00,^0.^ / A' Representative as a special case.If the precaution seems desirable, the acceptance might take the form of letting him act as Mr. Skinner did. Sd/- G. LOCH, Lieut-Colonel Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. (written by the Political Agent before departure on tour). Additional Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain.I y Confidential . No:C/l67-10/l H/ 0 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th March 1935. From:- Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, T.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To;- fit m &amp;v H-C Y . —n i.he Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire• mm*! - Sir, Bahrain Oil T have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter No:PA-183 dated the 11th February 1335 from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited regarding the procedure to be followed, and the disposition of oil with which the sea loading line is ordinarily to be kept filled, when ships must discharge ballast water ashore, and to enquire whether 1 may forward it to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin f Isa A1 Khalifah and what advice I should tender to him. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant,lis Bsfircb ^ m. February 11, 1935 • nls ^ri tannic Bjeaty'a oiltleal ;^ent, Bahrein* Bear Sir; J 4 u s •/Ith ti :eir letter PA-160 of .tanuar^ 13, 1935, Hie Bahrein PetroleiBii Oanpany Limited sent yon a chart end explanation illustrating end descrlbi^ the (kM-aparor* s facilities on Sit rah Islaad and methods to be used in r/ieasuriag and shipping oil, Itde, it is hoped, has supplied any irtfor ^tion deeirad for an understanding of the oil -rieastir^r ^ent prohleiru Hi are still renins to be dlscu^sea, however, cm© otter operation that tmy oeeasiomlly required, narnely, the procedure to be followed, and the disposition of oil with which the sea loadiJig line is ortiiRarily to be kept filled, when ships must discharge ballast water ashore. As now eontemplated, this operatlen will probably rarely be aece- amry. Obviously, after a ship will have ptaaped ballast ashore through the sea loading line the Urn will be left filled with water wnich isust be taken back aboard when ifce vessel is loaded with oilj hence there will be no advantage in discharging ballast unless there rmy be more water in the ship 's tanks than Urn capacity of the mm line - about P.,BOO barrels. It is? believed that in the majority of cases vessels will be able to reach the anchorage with little or no more than that mount aboard. This my not always be possible, however, and when it is not olacharse of the excess to the shore will probably be required. the procedure of pumping ballast water through mm sea loadinn line and the ballast line to the bilge ^ater tank at the terminal by means of the ships* pu^jps is a simple one and the only point that requires particular consideration is disposition of the oil wit^ wldch the sea line, in most cases, will be filled. IM s oil will have been measured out of the ?ltrah oil tanks and royalty thereon due to is xoellency accounted for; hence if returned to these tanks the amount of oil so returned imst he deducted from the current royalty account. aie procedure which the Corapany propose to follow ssay be brie i outlined as follows: \s ballast water is puraped through tiie sea line ttm the ship, puahiw; the oil aHorwnird, the latter sill be dirootod through th© oirculat- lag line into th. oil taak got to be drawn on In that partic Jin i-.r.ijwonw.Direction of the straa In that turner will cx&gt;ntinuD until all of the oil, and possibly a small amount of netsr, have been returned to this tank, whertmpon the water strear: will be diverted through the ballast line and into the bilge witer tank. hen discharge of brdlast vatcr is eompleted, about 50 barrels of oil id 11 be drawn frora one of the other oil tanks and pusrped by means of the land puiaps through the circulating line, displacing water left in this line into the same tank into which oil frota the sea line had been placed, whence s.ich water ray subsequently be drained off, 'This entire operation will be completed before gauging of the tank*-, froti which shipaent is to be made or before any of the steps in oil raeasurement described in theiaemorandum on that subject are taken. ifter full and careful consideration, the Company feel that the imethod above outlined will be the siraplest and moat practicable one for handliaf oil displaced frcffij the eea line, Ihe only possible objection to the method is that it does not Demit a direct measuroment of the amount of oil returned to the Bitrah oil tanks nor hence the amount of deduction required in the oil -royalty account, 4 direct laeasur^neat of oil so returned, however, is not necessary in the interests of practicable accuracy, as the volume of the sea loading line can be closely eomputed by a siiaple calculation, the length of the pipeline itself, frors the 12' valve in the control house to the sea end is 15,975 feet, inclusive ot expansion bends, and its internal diameter 11 #875 inches. There i® also the aea hose, 175 feet in length and 8 inches in internal diameter. [tie conbined capacity of the two can be readily com puted as 2,199,15 TJ. , barrels {9,702 cubic inches per barrel.) In order to provide against any possible loss of revenue to ie ixcellency, however, the Ca&amp;paay proi&gt;ose a figure of E,160 barrels as the assumed amount of oil returned to the tanks when the mam is displaced tvm. the sea loading line. It ie believed that the amount of 39.15 barrels subtracted from the vdliaae figure above computed will amply provide for {X) a reasonable amount of error, (2) a correction of the oesaputed volume of oil to volurae at 60° F, and (5) a email amount of oil that mic^t rer?iain lodged in the pipeline. Ihe Cdapany further fRiggest an even amount of *s94 tons as beinr^ the assumed weight of the 8,160 barrels referred to above, as this is approxiisately the weight of that amount of oil with an gravity of ^).9 0 , which is thought to be a fair average for the Bahrein oil. Hie Company propose, therefore, that on occasionr, when oil in the aea loading line ~iust be re? turned to the Pitrah oil tanks they follow the procedure outlined above and deduct frosi the evrailative amount of oil on which royalty is currently due to His xcellency an a&amp;iount of S94 tons, -ending a period of observation and trial in actual practice, the Coiapany suggest uiiat the foregoing proposal be agreed upon initially with the understanding that either the Conpany or Ills 1 xcellency may be free to reconsider anci re -open the question at any time in the future when it may appear necessary or advisable to either of thaa.copies of this latter are bein^ sent jmx and the rorspany request t- at one copy be forwarded to is Kcellenoy t ^elkh sir iiataad bin lea al liallfah, « C. - ., c. ?, r. Both t e eetaal physical operation at; the? erminAl and the proposed method, of figuring the tonnage of oil to bo deducted frop the royalty account Imve bee« dis cussed with r. elgrave and r r. teel© and it is tho gill that they are quite fa., dliar with thsn« If there is anything which is not entirely clear to 'you or to them, the Company will be pleased to explain them further at any time. A letter simlar to tliis will be sent to the India Office by t*r. Ballant/ae. Tours very trulyp,Z• ISQQ/Sb* BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. 19, MOORGATE, LONDON f E•G• 8• 28th February 1935♦ Oil Measurement. Dear Mr.Laithwaite. As I think I have warned you would be the case, after approval of the Company* s oil measurement system at the Sitrah Terminal, comes the question - What procedure is to be followed and what disposition is to be made of oil with which the sea-loading line (from the Terminal to the Anchorage) is to be kept filled when ships discharge ballast water ashore? As now contemplated, this operation will probably X'arely be necessary• Obviously, after a ship will have pumped ballast ashore through the sea-loading line the line will be left filled with water which must be taken back aboard when the vessel is loaaed with oil; hence there will be no advantage in discharging ballast unless there may be more water in the ship^s tanks than the capacity of the sea line - about 2,200 barrels. It is believed that m the majority of cases vessels will be able to reach the anchorage with little or no more than that amount aboard. This may not always be possible, however, and when it is not, discharge of the excess to the shore will probably be required. The/ 3. Laithwaite Esgt* &gt; C. I.E., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I*v 2 - The procedure of pumping ballast water through the sea- loading line and the 'ballast line to the 'bilge water tank at the terminal by means ol* the ships' pumps is a simple one and the only point that requires particular consideration is disposition of the oil with which the sea line, in most cases, will 'be filled. This oil will have heen measured out of the Sitrah oil tanks and royalty thereon due to His Excellency accounted for; hence if returned to these tanks the amount of oil so returned must be deducted from the current royalty account. The procedure which the Company propose to follow may be briefly outlined as follows As ballast water is pumped through the sea line from the ship, pushing the oil shoreward, the latter will be directed through the circulating line into the oil tank not to be drawn on in that particular shipment. Direction of the stream in that manner will continue until all of the oil, and possibly a small amount of water, have been returned to this tank, whereupon the water stream will be diverted through the ballast line and into the bilge water tank. When discharge of ballast water is completed, about 50 barrels of oil will be drawn from one of the other oil tanks and pumped by means of the land pumps through the circulating line, displacing water left in this line into the same tank into which oil from the sea line had been placed, whence such water may subsequently be drained off. This entire operation will be completed before gauging of the tanks from which shipment is to be made or before any of the steps in oil measurement described in the Company's memorandum on that subject are taken* After full and careful consideration, the Company feel that the method ahove outlined will be the simplest and most practicable one for handling oil displaced from the sealine. The only possible objection to the method is that it does not permit a direct measurement of the amount of oil returned to the Sitrah oil tanks nor hence the amount of deduction required in the oil-royalty account. A direct measurement of oil so returned, however, is not necessary in the interests of practicable accuracy, as the volume of the sea loading line can be closely computed by a simple calculation. The length of the pipeline itself, from the 13' valve in the control house to the sea end is 15,975 feet, inclusive of expansion bands, and its internal diameter 11.875 inches. There is also the sea hose, 175 feet in length and 8 inches in internal diameter. The combined capacity of the two can be readily computed as 2 ,199.15 u .S. barrels (9,702 cubic inches per barrel). In order to provide against any possible loss of revenue to His Excellency, however, the Company propose a figure of 2,160 barrels as the assumed amount of oil returned to the tanks when the same is displaced from the sea loading line. It is believed that the amount of 39.10 barrels subtracted from the volume figure above computed will amply provide for (l) a reasonable amount ol error, (2) a correction of the computed volume of oil to volume at 60° F. and (3) a small amount of oil that might remain lodged i nit he pipeline. The Company further suggest an even amount of 294 tons as being the assumed weight of the 2,160 barrels referred to above, as this is approximately the weight of that amount of oil with an A .F .I, gravity of 30.9°, which is thought to be a fair average for the Bahrein oil* The Company propose*- therefore, that on occasions when oil in the sea -loading line must he returned to the Sitrah oil/4, oil tanks they follow the procedure outlined above and deduct from the cumulative amount of oil on which royalty is currently due to His Excellency an amount of 294 tons. Pending a period of observation and trial in actual practice, the Company suggest that the foregoing proposal be agreed upon initially with the understanding that either the Company or His Excellency may be free to reconsider and re-open the question at any time in the future when it may appear necessary or advisable to either of them. A letter similar to the foregoing has been sent already to His Excellency through the medium of the Company 1 s Chief Local Representative in Bahrein. Yours, &amp;c., {Sgd.) H.R. BALLANTYNE.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. f nnf identiai . Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N'B- This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mai( and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb his, treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had ieen telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated hy the signature of a responsible officer of the Department,} OfiiCiS Of 'til© POlit.iCaX HeS jLCieilt» C/50 oi 1935. in the Persian Gulf, No. n ,, Camp, Bahra iii • Dated 19th Larch, lJ 36. XX To 1° From - Political Resident, at Bahrain. To - Secretary of State for India, London. Re &gt;eated Government of India, New Delhi. m y Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject ; Cliief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Situation is that Mr.Russell, a British subject, local Manager of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, is the Chief Local Representative - vjde correspondence ending with Political iO N ^ Agent, Bahrain's Printed Letter Ho»C/707, dated the .26th July 1934. He is however shortly going on leave and his successor has to be appointed* Since the Shaikh has no objection to the appointment of Mr.Davies (the local Fields Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company &gt;5 vide Political Agent, Bahrain^ Kspress Letter Ko. 0/161, dated the 3rd March 1936, copy enclosed, and since now that the Mining Lease problems and difliculties have been - f settled bo that the work of the Chief Local Hepresentative will be of routine nature, I agree with Colonel Loch that Mr.Davies \ U V might / {Signature) s. 44. DCFP—1124S&amp;P™(M'13W)—4-8-32—12,000. (Designation)-2- might be accepted in that capacity as a special case. The 'acting 1 precaution would hardly seem Xiecessary. sd, T»C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, antlal* D epartment, ^ 7 [N.B.-msismOBIGINAL MESSAGE, expense mul undue use of receipt mth the same expeduion as if it had b,en telegraphed. To sare hrm a.d formalities it is worded a..d siy,.ed as if it had been so despatched*] J From Political, Bahrain To Resident, Bushire. N&lt;K C16 9-10/1. r : yU Dal^d 11th March I*J 5. My Express ^etter C/151-10/1 ^larch 3rd. Chief Local Hepresent- ative. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. 2. In a private letter dated 15th February 1955 Mr. Skinner writes, n I hope she (Mrs. Loch) will be able to join you soon, at least by the time we are ready to return'. This suggests the possibility of his coming back to Bahrain, but Mr. Davies says that he has heard nothing and that Mr. Skinner promised to let him know at once if anything was settled. 3. If there is any question of one or the other acting Chief Local Representative, Mr. Davies would probably fit in the better of the two. C .o Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. S 6. mfp— 400s&amp;p—(m-460'—26-7-34—2,00/xah\ Telegram R.27. From Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, at Bahrain. No•963. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No.964. Copy by Air Mail to Government of India, New Delhi. Dated 22nd (received 23rd) March 1936. Bahrain Petroleum Company request approval to appointment of S.G.Young, learner on their Bahrain staff, to act as Chief Local Representative from April 1st in Russell^ absence on leave. Please telegraph whether you see any objection. Young is a British subject. -Secretary of State for India.fp V TeiegramS- R/27. From?- Political agent, Bahrain. To:- fiovernment of India, New Delhi. NoS- 50. Dated?- 23rd Inarch 1J35. Following for Political Resident In the Persian w ulf from Secretary f ^tate for India March 2^nd, 963* Begins: 'Bahrain Petroleum Company request approval to appointment of S .G.Young^ leanner on their Bahrain Staff, to act as Chief ^ocal Represent ative from ivprii 1st in Russell's absence on leave. Please telegraph Yvhether you see any objection. Young is a British subject.' Buds. ' 2. Your Express better C/50 March 19th about Davie* should reach London March S5th. I do not consider it appropriate nor I think would Shaikh that so junior and inexperienced an employee should carry on relations of Company with Shaikh and Political Agent. Copy given to the honourable the olitical Resident In the Persian ^ulf, at Bahrain.1A &gt; Telegrams~ il/27. Froms* Colonel Fo;le at Delhi. Tot- India Office, London. Repea fced * •* Political Agent, Bahrain Copy given to Government of India. Woi- 1/D. Dated:- 85th March 192&gt;5. '7 0 / iour telegrftffi of the ^2nd March, 963. Political Agent &gt; Bahrain, is of the opinion that Young would be rather too junior and inexperienced for billet and that Shaikh would probably think so too. In all the circumstances I think that Davies would be the best choice vide ay air mail Express better of March 19th. UX - Fofcie - Cop\ : ended t j tiie honourable t-e i, .ol._t c.. Pers: an ^ulf f't Bahrain. 1Telegram:- R/27. From:- Secretary of State for India, London. To:- Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Delhi. Repeated:- Political Agent, Bahrain. No:- 997. Dated:- EGth (received 27th) March 1935. P 0 Your telegram of 25th March, D/l. &lt;»e .uite recognise advantage of appointment of Davies but for political reasons at this ena which have been explained confidentially to Bsliantyne it is essential that Chief Local Representative continues to be a British subject thought we should be uite willing that ne shoula combine post witn some other post in Oofflpany ! s local organization. Aoula you like me to suggest K G Meikle or any other British subject in Bahrain to act for Russell. It is we gather confidentially just possible tnat Russell may later enter Company's employment. If so he coula be confirmed as Chief Local Representative. 2. Please give copy to Government of Inaia. 1 i ■i Secretary of State for inaiaC onfidentlal # No;C/190-10/l(f). Political Agencv, Bahrain, the 18th March 19-55, From:- To: Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A. } Political Agent, Bahrain, The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Grilf^ Bushire. Collection of light dues from Tp.nkships of The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited. O 4 ir I have the honour to refer to letter No:D.5343- N/34 dated the 9th January 1855 from the Government of India regarding the question of levying light dues at Bahrain from the vessels of The Bahrain Petroleum Company. 2* On the 7th March 1935 I enquired from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company, whether it was now possible to give an estimate of the number of tsnkships which were likely to call at Bahrain annually in connection with their operations. On the 11th March I received the following reply ru Is • n TT I would refer you to our letter of November 15th, 1934, and beg to advise that the situation as regards the information you desire has not altered since that time. The Company still regret that they are unable to give any such estimate as you request,' 3. Local gossip has it that at least five tankships are expected this year* 4, I see no objection to light dues being levied at Bahrain from vessels of The Bahrain Petroleum Company provided I'fsJ2 provided that the Bahrain Government are informed of what is being done and acquiesce in the collection of the dues by their Director of Customs and Port Officer» 5. It is just possible, however, that the Bahrain Petroleum Company may say that if they had been told of this proposal before, they would have preferred to have their own lighted buoy off Bahrain, but I do not think that they would press this point• No figure of the amount to be levied has been quoted, but I think that the Company is likely to object to paying the same dues as are levied at Basrah as, so far as T am aware (though I do not know on what course their ships steer), their tankships will only make use of the lighthouse at Quoin Island and the lightship (not yet in place) at Bahrain, I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, BahrainGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, —_ D epartment, 4 : EXPRESS LETTER [N. B .-This is an OIUGINAL MES expense and undue use receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa e time and formalities it is warned and si,/t,ed as if it had been so despatched,] F rom To:- Political, Bahrain. Resident, Bushire. ^gpeated;- Secretary of State for India, London. Foreign Secretary to the Government of ^ndia. New Delhi. f I ^C/l 78-10/1. 14th March 5. My Express Letter of February 10th, C/lOS—lO/l. Bahraxn Oil. 2. Tankship 'W.S.Rheem' arrived Bahrain March 5th and sailed March 6th with just over 15,000 tons of oil. Destination under- stood to be Japan. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. S 6 MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-480'—26-7-34—2^00,000.Identlal. GOVERXM EXT OF INDIA, D epartment, EXPRESS LETTER This is an 01UGI1S AL MESSAGE, sn/t hy pout to sare telegraphic expense aim undue use of the wires, bat intended to he treated, on receipt^ with the same expeddioti as if it had bten telegraphed. To sa e time and formalities it is woraed a d si,. u ed as if it had been so despatched,] From To:- Polltical, Bahrain. Resident, J Bushire, Repeatedt- fe Secretary of State for India, London. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, 'New Delhi. ^ C/198-10/1. Dafei 28th March 5# Bahrain Oil, CMef Local Representative informs me Tankship Tf W.S.Rheem' will take two more shipments of crude oil. 2* First shipment will be made early in May 1955 and second in July 1935. Captain, Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. S 6 mfp—400s&amp;p—{m-480 —26-7-34—2,00, ! xo.s. •&gt; n -■: ^ / (&gt; Telegram R. From Political Resiaent, at Bahrain. To Secretary Ox State for India, London• Copy sent by Air Llail to Government 01 India, New Delhi. Gopy given to Political Ajent, Bahrain* K o .T/93 Dated the 1st April 1935. Your telegvam of March 26th, 997. Chief Local Representative. BAHRAIN OIL Heiklc is not in Bahrain. I suggest G.W♦R.Smith, local Agent for Mespers as Chief Local Representative, have noL yet approached Smith but will do so if you approve. -Resident. (Copy given to Political Agent. Bahrain, (Copy sent to Govt.of India under F .L.ITo.C/60 of 11Forwarded with the cornplirnents of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to b y M ail. /v c fk The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057ji PETROLEUM DEPARTM3NT (Mines Department), P.S .180U/35 Cromwell House, Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, London, B.W.!• lUth March 1935* Dear Laithv/aite, Y - 1 Bahrein. , ^ r / With reference to your letter of the 3th March, P.S-1399/33? 021 ^ ie Question of the procedure to 'be followed and the disposition to he made of oil with which the sea loading line is to he kept filled when ships discharge ballast water ashore, 1 agree that, if the sea line is kept full of oil, and it has been agreed that it is qaiue reasonable that it should, it wi11 be laii to aliox a deduction to be made for purposes of assessing royalty in respect of any oil in the pipeline which may he returned to the Sitrah tanks so as to enable ballast water to oe pumped ashore. I have had the figure of the capacity of the Pipeline checked on the data supplied by the Company and it A' is correctly given. Subject to the conditions mentioned in the penultimate paragraph of Ballantyne's letter of 28th February, I think you would be Justified in expressing concurrence m the procedure proposed. But, of course, it is necessary to make/ G. Laithwaite, Esq., C.I-S.j India Office, King Charles Street, S.W.I.make sure that the pipeline is full of oil before the discharging operation begins, and this is a point which ought to 'be checked by those responsible for the checking of measurenents in Bahrein* Yours sincerely, P. 0. STARLING. DMH.T P. INDIA OPFIG^, WHITEHALL, LONDON, 3.W. 1 P.Z. 1804 R'v Air iv IStti Ukrcla 1935 f IVly dear Fovyie, I enclose copy of a letter&gt; P.D.21/3, of i4th iviarch, from sturlin^ on the CiUestion of the procedure to tie followed in disposing of oil with which the sea-loading line is to te kept filled when ships Discharge ballast water ashore. You will see that, subject to tjae conditions which he mentions* he thinks that we would l^e justifiea in expressing concurrence in the procedure proposed dy the Company, tmt that he adds that it is, of course&gt; necessary to make sure that the pipeline is full of oil 'before the discharging operation begins and that this is a point whicb ought to be checked by those responsible for the checking of measurements in Bahrein. Political Agent, Bahrein, and to the Government of India. s I am senain^ copies of the letter to the Yours sincerely The Hon'ble Lt.Col. T,G, Fowle, GBE.,Ho. PA -198. Maroh 31, 1935 His Britannic Itajesty^s t^litical Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: - I take pleasure in handing you herewith seven copies of 'ABSTRACT OF ACCOUNTS OF OIL MEASURED DURHK* 1954, ITOSR ARTICLE IX OF THE SmOW SCHEDULE OF AGRESMSNT DATSD DECWBSB 2, 1925, AS MODI FIED FEBRUAKY 15, 1935, AHD AS MODIFIED BY SLTFPLJiM'SlTTARY ASSSSIOTT Of NOTOSKR 21, 1933' and ten copies of 'STATil.tSHT OF ROYAI.TY DUE HIS EXGELLMCY WE SKEIKIi OF BAHRAIN FOR TIT?! YEAR 1934, IINDFR AGREEIfMT DATED DECISvBER 2, 1925, AS SUBSSQ,{JEMTLY MODIFIED', and would request that you tran® ait the requisite number of copies to His l^ellency sheikh Sir Haiaad bin Isa al Khalifah, K* C. I* 0 • S • X • You will note the inclusion of three additional copies a£ the statement of Royalty with appended acknowledgments, fill you kindly ask the Financial Adviser to sign these three copies and return them to the Company? yours very truly. Chief Local Representative, THS BAHREIN PET^OLEUi' COMPANY LBTITED. End: mmmQ Y- ~ - o ^- &lt;1. Mm c % is!,;! iauy v Me^ ai v t fl9i;3rtj snmtB flilloMO oJ Wasi lequ nl !:m'y THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED STATEMENT OF ROYAL TT DUS HIS EXCELLENCY THE SHAIKH OF BAHREIN FOE THE YEAR 1934, UNDER AGREEMENT DATED DECEMBER 2, 1925, AS _______ SDBSgQUENTLY MODIFIED __ Tons ROYALTY PAYABLE OIL CRUDE SHIPMENTS To Ttie Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd., March 10, 1954 to S. S. 'EL SEGHNDO* June 6, 1934 Samples April and July, 1934 Total shipped during year EXEMPTION UNDER ARTICLE IX ( AS AMENDED) OF PROSPECTING LICENSE Royalty payable oil for year 1934 Royalty due 3,300.315 Tons @ Rs.3-8-0 per ton 7.292 5,390.513 2.510 3,400.315 100.000 3,300.315 RS.11,551- 1- 8 ... ■' 0 ^ All of which was included in payment of Rupees twenty thousand only paid on January 31, 1935, being minimum royalty due to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa al-3£halifah, k . C. I. E« &gt; C. S. I., under paragraph 3 of the supplementary Agreement dated November 21, 1933. Balance Royalty due for the year 1934 NONE l&amp;HiC tC ^ B * * ' iootB of ' !0 Manager, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. ■p- m BJJ rIs cossmsiMk GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. 1 EXPRESS LETTER (AiR MAIU. [Jf.B*—This is an OliK .i JNAJ/ message sent hy AIR MAIL which ^provides % meaiu of communication inor$ expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate forynalitxes it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticited by the signature of a , t , f on,Me officer ofHeBvarlM.,.] 0ffice of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, B^HRAIH 5th April 19 35' No.c/92 of 1936 Dated &amp; From the 0 „ Political Resident, at Bahrain. To Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. Secretary of State for India, London. Government o f India, New Delhi• Subject: Bahrain Oil - Abstract of Accounts of Oil measured during i.934. Reference your letter No April 1936. j .c/236-10/1, dated the 6th 2. No objection to your forwarding the accounts in question to His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf attested ^ (o * ** ' for a^cretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gull. {Signature) S. U. (Designation) MFP—825S&amp;P—(M-i070)—14-9-34—li 0,0(0.£vz.jop'/ 19 r\ \ \ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, J Forwarded with the cornpliineuts of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. ) \y A copy has been sent to by Mail. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057i c P. 2075/35. THE BAHREIN ESTBOLBOM COivIPAHY LIMITED. 19, Moorgate j London, E.G. 2. 22nd March L935 Dear Mr. Laithwaite Unofficially^ you may be interested to know that two further cargoes of Bahrein Crude Oil are contemplated^ each approximately 110,000 barrels The first cargo s I believe ? will be in May and the second 5 I think, in July. Yours sincerely : horo ballaintylle m A i ■ 1: I '1 J.Go Laithwaite, Esq., O.I.E. India Office, Whitehall, S 0 v7 u 1., | \\T) frftncffidential . From - The Hon^le Lieut•-Colonel T «C.Fowle f C.B.ii*, rolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Xo - The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 1 1 1 Copy to the rolitical .igent, Bahx 'ain. Klemoranduni No •332-S of 1935. Bushire, the 26th April ±936 Gub.iect : Question of levying light dues at Bahrain from the vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Reference correspondence ending with Foreign ana Political Department letter No.D.6343-N/34, dated the 9th January 1936, i enclose a copy of a letter No.C/190, dated the i8th March 1936, from the iolitical Agent, Bahrain# .u ! 2. It. will tie seen that while the Bahrain retroleuu Company is still unaole to give an estimate or the number of tankshiys likely to call at Bahrain annually, it is expected that about 5 visits will ue made during the current . year. i\ 3. I see no reason why a commencement shoula not now be made with levying light dues on such vessels of the Bahrain Petroleum Company as visit Bahrain. 4. With regard to the method of collection of ti.cse dues. i am not in favour (vide paragraph 4 of my Memorandum No.988-3 of 29th October 1934) of these being collected by ^ the political Agent, Bahrain. The alternative authorities are: /are: or (a) The Port Officer of the Bahrain Governaierit (vide the same paragraph of my Memorandum just quoted) (b) The Lighting and Buoying Committee themselves who could do so in direct correspondence with the Company^the latter supplying the Committee with the necessary details of each visit. sd. T*C«Fowle f Lieut•-Colonel• } olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf A Vested# for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf..2414/1335 THE BAHKEIH PETROLEUli COMPAST LIMITED, 11, Birchin Lane, London, E.G.3* 4th April, 1935. Bear Mr. LaiUiwaite, Yo 1 ^ niay 'be interested in knowing that a further cargo of 110,000 barrels ox Bahrein crude has 'been arranged for August, or round about that month; this will make the fifth cargo. Yours sincerely, (Sgd,) H.R. Ballantyne. .G. Laithwaite, Esq., ndia Office, 'hitehall, S.W.I.PeZ. 2517/35. THE BAHREIN PETHOLSUM COivPANY LIMITED. 11, Blrchln Larie, London, E.G. 3. 8th April 1935. Dear Mr. Laithwaite, Chief Local iiepresentativft . Seisrriiig to our recent corrmiunications herein and in particular to your letter adaressed to me of the 2nd April on this subject, I arn instructed to suggest that Mr. G.W.R. smith should temporarily fill the post of Chief Local Representative of the Company in Bahrein qui ing the absence of Mr. J«M« Russell on leave. This suggestion is to replace the suggestion that Mr. s,G # Young should act temporarily as Chief Local Representative. I understand that Mr. smith is at present acting Manager for the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd. at Bahrein.. We are told he has heen with that Company for about nine years, that his age is thirty-one^ that he is a 'baciielor and that he has 'been with the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd. in Kut, Bagdad&gt; Basra and Bushira Would you be good enough to let me know, in aue course, whether His Majesty's Government approve the appointment proposed in oraer that the appointment may be confirmed by communication to the Company's Manager in Bahrein. Yours sincerely ? H.R, BALLAWTYNE Laithwaite, E sq., c .I .E., India Office, Whitehall, S • W • 1.INDIA OFFICE, 'iHI TEHALL, 3.W. 1. p.Z.2517/35. 10th April 1935. ; / Dear fcr. Ballantyne, Iviany thanks for your letter of the 8th April. i write in reply to say that approve the appointment of Mr. g .W.3. smith temporarily to fill the post of Chief Local Representative of the company in Bahrein during the absence of Mr. J#M. Russell on leave. Yours sincerely, j.g. laithwaite. h.i^. Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Co.Lta.^ 11, Birchin Lane, E .g. 3.#&gt;l &gt; ' GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. nfiden tia.-k» EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. 7 his 1 Al- message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more 1 i0 . u f an he ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on rec^tp . un h itie same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate forma hies % u i rafted tn the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] ll No .C/g35-10/l. Dated^^,the 9th April iP35, To Resident, Bushire Repeated5 Secretary of State for India, London. ranjrr Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, 'New Delhi X My Express Letter of 'arch 28th, C/I98-10/1. Bahrain Oil. Manager, Bahrain Petroleum Company, informs me unofficially that he has been advised by his San Francisco Office that tank- ship 'W.S.Rheem' will take a third shipment of crude oil from Bahrain in latter half of August 1935. Captain, Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. S. 44. MPP—825S&amp;P—(M-1070)—14-9 34—10,000. (Signature) {Designation)CONFIDENTIAL No. C/252 ' /' . The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honour: ble the ^oljtic.l Resident .n the Persic, n Gulf, Busnire. L BUS '-'.'PF RE^TZNTy' Iff .Jrt ias fehe honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document and to request instructions. T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G clf. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter fror. the -/lane.ger, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, No :P/-£01 of the 16th April 1935. Dated... 1.7th I..1.335. Subject. The Bcl.rr In Petroleum Company nu Limited - Chief Local Represent ; : ative.CONFIDENTIAL. /&gt;- No, r /o«7»y«i ^ /i V'/ - J ( The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—- The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian G ulf, / Bushire. H.M T s Secretary of State for Indie,, London. The Foreign ^ecretari^ to the Government of India, Si nils . and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). BUSH!F E8!DEN—N. T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G dlf. 'h P~ n O Dated. . 24 tli.. Aural. .1925. Reference to previous correspondence : India Office Printed Letter No:P.Z.?517/^ of 12-4—1935, Descriptiini of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No:C/255 dated 20-4-55 to G.W.R.Smith Es Quire. Letter No:C/256 dcted ^0-4-35 to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. Subject. Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd. ■do-Ji. 7' •' 0, GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Departmsskt, 'nnfidential [A T , B, — This is an ORIGINAL MUSI expense and undue me of receipt, with the same expedition „ save time and formalities it is so despatched*] €o save re^ 'dui mtmded to be treated, on it h&amp;d been telegraphed. To ^ , ^ m if k had hem Office of the Political Hesideirt in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. F rom Political Resident, at Bahrain. T© Political Agent, Bahrain. C/154 of 1936 Dated 14th May $03 6 Sub.1 ect : The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited - Procedure to be followed and the disposition of oil with which the sea loading line is ordinarily to be kept filled, when ships must discharge their ballast water ashore. / Your letter No •0/308-10/1, dated the 12th May 1936 2. No objection to the Bahrain Petroleum Company being informed as suggested. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. rl AttfaS i&gt;0Q. . for secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. s. e.CONFIDENTIAL. ft-THE BAHREIN PETR OLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Oulf, 1934 ANNUAL REPORT This report gives the status of all wells and a list of buildings that have either been constructed or are in the course of construction, as well as a statement as to the nationalities of all of the Company^s personnel in Bahrein. All of this information is as of 31st December, 1934. There is also included with this report a copy of the Company*s map of Bahrein Island on which there has been marked in addition to the well locations, the Company's various facilities, pipe lines, pump stations and camp sites. Most of the buildings shown as being in the old camp will be abandoned and dismantled after the construction work at the new camp has been completed. In addition to the wells that were completed during the year and the construction of the camps there was also completed during the year an oil gathering system in the field with a pump station to pump the oil to the Island of Sitra, at which point terminal facili ties were completed consisting of three large storage tanks, pump house, etc., as well as a submarine line extending into the Persian G-ulf. The Company have not given any details in this report concerning the facili ties at Sitra or the submarine line as plans and a description of these facilities have already been furnished. There was also constructed during the year a topping plant which is located near tank battery No. 1 as indicated on the general plan included herewith. The work of constructing the gathering system terminal facilities at Sitra and submarine line was done by a force of trained men who were sent to Bahrein on a tanker. After the completion of this work the crew sent for that purpose departed and the tanker left with a cargo of Bahrein crude which was the first one shipped from this field. At the end of the year 1934 plans were under way for the sale of additional cargoes oi crude oil approximating 110,000 barrels each (two cargoes have since been transported and sold and it is anticipated that three more cargoes will be shipped within the next six months). You will note that the Company have not included a complete roster of the employees by classifications since such rosters are furnished periodically. At the end of the year the Company were still continuing drilling operations on several wells, as will be noted from this report.^onfiaential . / / 5 ■ K '- ' 7&gt; No .0/ 162 of 1936. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp 9 BAHRAIN• Dated the 16th May, i.936» To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN• : i / Memorandum , Subject; Bahrain Oil. Your letter of 16th May 1935, No.C/321-10/1. 2. A copy of the Annual Report of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited for the year 1934 may be forwarded to the Bahrain Government for the information of His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut. ..Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested * ft- for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. i-i! OR MAIL. p.z. 3285/35, INDIA OFFICE, LONDOH, 3. ¥. 1. IVth May 1935. / / I enclose herewith two photostatic copies of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's Mining Lease with attached plan, which have been received from the Company. The r / Company also propose to send us shortly a supply of printed copies of the English text of the Mining Lease, we shall distrioute these on receipt and send Bahrein the 24 copies for which Loch asked in his letter to you of 5th January last, No.G/6-lO/l. \% 2» In this connexion would you please refer to your » r \ &gt; telegram No. 136, of 30th January to Bahrein in which you instructed the Political Agent to send the third original of the Mining Lease to the India Office for record? ¥e have not yet received this and would be glad if Cole could send it on. 3. I am sending copies of this letter to the ion 'ble. Lt.Gol. T.G^Fowle, , 'o. The Political Agent, Bahrein. Government/f 2. Government of India (with 1 copy of the enclosure) and to Bahrein (with 2 copies of the enclosure)*1 ts V ^ 'J I Ji f—- ji i—^-r-Jl J j Lw ^ U^y-^A^-JT ^ ' ^}» ' ;j^ n JI V &gt;&lt;^% ( Jij*A» ( aVL* — ^ ^ f—' c^j^SJUVL. ^pJi U(3-^' ^ ^-tr&lt; ^ 41« ^-^&gt;j ^ Oj J i5ir?'yr^i&gt; 4t5J ^ t&gt;* ^ i-^&gt; J^U -A -^vjJ^ I U~ ■^xj 4^&gt;-y o' J- 1- *? jl^illj^^Jl Jxrr 11 'OHy -iJloU-L^JI J ' O-l—Jl^ iiitll jiOl Ijj.Lr'Jj-vJ'iy li-t- livyj! j-^'iy *9— Li^o'V V 1 ' J^U*)! •j-*^ru' 'ir' s^i * v?-yJ , ** L - J1 ^ b J^, j^i-'O 1 ^ !J-UJ j Ujj '-&gt; U,il Li/^E made Bet^aen Hi a Excellency SHEIKH R6R1AD BH. 3IIEIKK I3SA AL KKALIFA SHEIKH OF BAHREIN of the one part, hereinafter called ,T the Sheikh' (acting on the advice of the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COLDPANY LH.IITED herein after called 'the Company' (a Company incor porated under the laws of the Dcciinion of Canada) of the other part* WITNESSES as follows:- Article I_. TEE Sheikh hereby grants to the Company on behalf of hie self and his successors the exclusive right for a period of fifty-five years froan the first of January One thousand nine hundred and thirty-five to prospect and for # extract, treat, refine, manufacture, transport and deal with petroleum products, naphtha, natural greases, tar, asphalt, ozokerite, and other bituminous materials within the area or areas described in words in the First Schedule to this lease and delin eated on the map attached as the Second Schedule thereto. Such right, however, shall not include the exclusive right to sell such products within the leased area. He also grants the Company the exclusive ri^it to i' _ r __ jL^ Ji iJU, Wli tlfj* ' J^&lt;y o?^ '-H-t t 0»li»ij i ujla J i ij # CH'-H * ^tJI Jk^jl juLJI U^ r 1^1 tf W1 — '-^w I Liji^^lJUV L^l ^k^l SgjJL, I ^1 tyi3/&gt;^ I IL^ ii^Jl Zi^iJl #&lt;U* i AgJ UAJ 1 4^ J^j I ^4 a^^JH j+j* *JL; ^r*^l ^ I J*^n( b-^ L^J I j l-i*J I iU^&gt;J 1^ JU^uVl^U 4^ ^ I caJ^-H c J Jw. #jj| ^4 j^LJl p—J^r- ' Xir U^vl^V I ^j -A 4^Jl J^'» ; - 3 . i u D i/v -U^ La*4^4-^*31 jixJi b-fc ^ ( IJ-^ iVyJl 4i; 1 UjU^''b 1 ^ 1 * J -* ^•i ojk pj^iy 'i'-H- 1 -^ cr^ demarcation shown in the plan hereto arinezed, so that the boundaries of the leased area may at all times throughout the tenn of this lease be clearly defined. Article II. Sheikh grants gratuitously to the Company all land uncultiTated at the date of this lease in any part of the territory under his control which may be needed by the Company for their operations, excluding, however, the land within the municipal boundaries of Muharraq and Manemah (as de fined by a red line on the map attached and foiming the Second Schedule hereto) the land within a radius of 300 yards from the northeast corner of the Sheikh's Palace at Sakhir (as defined by a green circle on such map) PROVIDED ALWAYS that to the extent and for the period to and for which the Company shall use any uncultivated land belonging to the Sheikh in his private capacity and falling within the land not excluded in the preceding provisions of this paragraph (other than the pieces of land used by the Company at the date of this lease and shown on the map attached hereto and bounded by a blue line) the Company shall, if so requested by the Sheikh, pay. _ I _ ^0\j y i J VL, t;L^I p i+r-Ul *jjk s &gt;5j£Ui ^ jU;^' I J* ^ 2 ^ 4 JJ^' * Ji-ftJl \jjk Jm 4&gt;tC{1 l-j-A * jjbJl Ujfc 5j^ lS^dlcJ\ 2^JU1 J If Ufi wU^I I LaJJ If^jiwi.l i Ajju*^ ^f'Jl |^J-l-» ) wUJJl j^yAjl 1 li—,.?-^^^ ( lii ^I am . VI ij}* ^ j I a-* ^ u J fifl to the Sheikh compensation for the use and occupancy of such land. Any such compensa tion shall not exceed a fair and reasonable recompense to the Sheikh for the dispossession of his right to the surface of such land and having regard to the prices ordinarily current for similar land situated in the locality; failing agreement as to the com pensation payable to the Sheikh the matter referred to and determined by arbitration in the manner provided by Article XXII hereof. In the lands so granted the Company shall for the period of this lease enjoy full proprietary rights. The Sheikh also recognizes that the Company have the right to acquire all and any other lands and buildings necessary for the said purpose with the consent of the proprietors (including the Sheikh in his capacity as private lendoimer) on such con ditions as may be arranged between the Company and the said proprietors without their being allowed to make demands of a nature to surcharge the prices ordinarily current for lands and buildings situated in their respective localities. lAv^' 111Jjlb jJUil \j~* J*. p- ^ i^AJl if*S &lt;^i^4 ^ ^ I Ji; ,1^1 Ijua # lf*»l XA^^^UVI # J»A ij^?iA^ LmA •J-s jX«J1 |j^ 4^ jyJt JL^eu^JleUU^ J^ 1 r^ H ijtydC*^ t Jj^-«J If (jg^C» &lt; aW*» vdij |J • j JLJI U-a^ l^jf. J#JI L^J Jf^JI vj ^■UJ* U tiUvj v I v^UVIi^ V jfti* &lt;Ji If ■■*'■ ^ L^J^^iiUg U c$^ Uj L^ I IJ^ ^ ^ dUUy ij I \jkjM . JO^JI Ijj^ J^^JiSJl^SJI ^y ir^y*^ i&gt;.L-JI qU- urvu^ji^Ui- 'icju vVi^ 1 J* gAJt^lJt 3^Ailcu»li^I««&gt;i At the tennination of this lease the ground and all Immovable property left by the Company shall be handed back to the aelkh; all borings (including casing therslnj 'bich the Company hare not abandons shall be handed oTer in reasonably good order and re pair; and all other property of the Canpeny nay he rmoved by the Company free of all taxes and duties, provided however that for ' a period of thirty days following the ter mination of this lease the Sheikh shall have the 'igbt to purchase such property at a price equal to the replacement value at that date, less depreciation, which price in the absence of agreement shall be settled by ar bitration in the manner set forth in this lease* It is however understood that within the leased area the Company shall be entitled to acquire only such land as is necessary for their pipe—lines, refineries, offices other works and that save, in so far as it is necessary in order to enable their pipe lines and railways to pass freely to their destination, they shall not acquire as pro vided by paragraph 3 of this Article any lend outside the leased area which might otherwise be leased for the production of oil to a third y\. e &lt;:_ n _ .... - 6 - U ^ j^JI Z^mM (j I tyjl y ix^Jljl JJUJUjjk ^Atik, J*#W^r Li&lt;l S&gt; k; JJLaJI Ujfc J f&gt;*V^ ^C? 4 ^ (&gt;* St »* Uj£ i • Jjuil OjkSjoUJ* V-JJ^I ^ jJbJ i J djl&amp;l fj~j 0*ijL** U^J &amp;SJJ ^ 1 J dUli 1 J»^JU&gt;- •&gt; ijju 1 ^ Ul nil ^ LLa jJt+ij*} •UVI li-A . • JuUll •^yiju^l u * ^ * t ■ *''* ^ i^J U J i|»giir j* j i^AJ I OiU*JLw 1 * J AI^IUJ ld» i |. ^11 I ptIty, u,:less th ey can satisfy the Sheikh that no other land suitable for their pur- pose is available. Article TTT . all lands granted by this lease to the Company or that may be acquired by the Com- 1 pany in the manner provided for in Article II of this lease as also all products exported shall be free of all imposts and taxes during the tenure hereof. All material and apparatus of every klnS necessary for the exploration, working and development of the deposit and for the con struction and development of the pipe-lines including also all the works specified in the first paragraph of Article I hereof and office requirements but not including the personal requirements of employees shall enter the said territory free of all taxes and custom house duties. This privilege shall continue in force for a term of ten years from the date hereof. Article TV. THE Sheikh undertakes to give all the protection in his power to the Company and to their staff and laborers in any part of his AkAM J' (P -V V— Y_ jUU JV, ^AJI J^.jJULi J^U JtrK V** ■'■*■''■' ♦ Ij-* eremta as are mantionad in this Articla op b7 any causa beyond the Company's control arising in Bahrein than the period ah all be added to the period for nhich thia lease is granted and the animal mlnisum royalty of Rs. 75,000 provided for by Article Tin «hall not be payable in respect of such delay. Article V. FOR the above purposes it is agreed that the Canpany in connunication with the Sheikh shall appoint permanent trustworthy guards under a reliable man of good family whose pay and that of the guards shall be prorided by the Canpany and who ehall remain there summer and winter* If in spite of the efforts of the aaid guards thefts should occur, the Sheikh under- takes to recorer the property stolen and to I compensate the Company for any damage sustained in his territory. In the event of non -reCorery I *sU\ J U V I sI J1 Jwia^o) I S^U; &lt;**&lt;&gt;• {J* jJlj V^ijl JJU g^«Jt JJ 4«a l^JD territory from thefts, highway robbery, assault, &amp;c. Similarly the Sbeikh undertake# to Protect ell the property of the Company and of their employees which may be exposed to wilful damage or to poasible loss by theft. If the Company's work is delayed by such lit ,&gt;1 JL^ M^V 1 - 1 pa&gt; oX^ 41/-^ 1 i ; - r =^Ci K ^XA&gt;Vje_ -v) .• ^01 2^1 Jp ^jJI cr^ (V-^J 1 #^U| V, a^JI V ^ ^ ^ CJL^^I ^0^ jJ^JI^i^U^JI^ I a J Jl 2^-JI p-J u' • dUU V 'N yfy*i UllU 4? I l«A-^t MTT kmJj M If iuJ^UI ^I^Jt j\ LjJ ft* fym y» vi Ij ^ i^UJI 'liil I j o^C ^ J ^4 l+tj I iy*} \ t /»jxtjj i^lic^Jl LlXjfJl w&gt; I &lt;U U-^ J^U; V^mi L*J i JULfJ I t&lt;i«A *****&lt; JJ* LS ^ J ^ p|/&gt;* (J' 4 ^ Ul( O cUiJi Ijjfc ^ Iv^^-S a; MU i l^nn 2 ^ cW &lt;&gt; k/*-^ iJX&gt;JIcj^ta SUiip l^t^-^yLyl ( ^ ) J I tjyfj*} I A^JU.11 p** l^«J 3^AJI ^lUl ^jj- I^Wlol^l jXpll^y JJ 4; I j tf)UI p jJt U^^L?-1 - 8 - of the stolen property, the value thereof shall be deducted by the Company from any sums due to the Sheikh by the Company. The number of guards at any place whe^ the Company may operate shall be fixed by the Company. It shall be the duty of the above- mentioned head of the guard to keep order in the areas in his charge to such extent as the Company may order him, he shall har# no right to interfere in any disputes among the Company's servants unless asked by th* Company to do so. The Company hereby agree that so long as the provisions of Bahrein Orders in Council 1913 and 1922, or any Order in eon~ solidation thereof or in substitution therefor or supplementary thereto, remain in fbrce, and Jurisdiction over certain foreigners in the State of Bahrein is exer* cisad by His Britannic Majesty, the provisions in the second paragraph of this Article V shall not apply in respect to coanissions of any acts of theft or damage by any person (1) if, on aich person being arrested, it is found that he is a foreigner over whom juris diction exercised by His Britannic Majesty under the said Orders in Council has been— 1 — j cr H ^jr ^ j 1 jAJl *4^* J LiJ i JtiLfJl ojjui y*H4jjLj\ •ui ui U I# * p—AJ jMC dl|j il f *~\jpim3 ^11 JUJI ikLJI * J i^i iJ v^ii jruji jxji Ul^OU^I I • ftl-J^I «^UI • J £J&gt; Jf£*vjLaJ)d'lp&lt;&amp;3b CT) QA&amp;wi^L# p U&gt;J^ •Ul (y* 5 fS/&gt;y ^ ^ -9. ortonded, or (2) if, m tlie eT(lnt of ^ arr9St8 mafl9 . It is prored to the sat- lefaction or the Ccapany. or if necessary the Political Agent, that the offender Is ouch a foreigner as abo T8 mentioned, and that he !ias left the territory gorerned by the Sheikh and has not to the knowledge of the Sheikh or hie officials returned thereto, ana that no arrest could therefore be made. Article VI. IN ease of nleconduct the said guards are subject to dismissal or fine by theCon- ' peny. In the erent of any heaTier punishment being needed, the offender shall be handed orer to the representatiTe of the Sheikh, and the Sheikh undertekes that punishment shall be inflicted end to use his utmost endeavours to uphold the authority of the Company's mnployees thereby aroidlng unnecessary troubles to both parties to this lease. Article 711 . TEE Company agree to pay to the Sheikh the following royalties, namely:- (a) Rs. 3e8e0 per ton of net crude oil got and sared (i.e. after deducting water and foreign substances and oil required for the customary operations I aa -^_ I • _ IfSit****/ ^ l^J Ui ^iJ 1 iuiiJ \ u* {»iLr^' jUJI (&gt;• jjk U j\*'\*-r\~&gt;&gt;'ij L^i^b-^l JA\ J* tSytfl Cs*^ O* j-^^^kJljUJl^Wy^i |U3 J^ Uy ^cr j'J-oUJ^O^ ir 4 ^-^UJl • Jjl^j ^ ««j l^'il I l^J UP 1 u'a^ Cf^'c^!;'&lt;/ ^ U 5J i?5 u**~j4~ ^r*. Q-^ 1 —' •^kJljUJIo- f f,^ - 10 - of the Company*s installations in the Sheikh's territories), vb^ Rs• 3,8.0 per ton of casino—head petroleun spirit extracted by the Company from natural gas where the average recovery from the gas treated from the various wells oyer the relative period of accounting is under two imperial gallons per One thousand cubic feet of natural gas at a pressure of one atmosphere and at a temperature of sixty degrees Fah renheit and Hs. 7,0,0, per ton of the casing-head petroleum spirit so recovered where such average recov ery is two imperial gallons or more. No royalty shall be payable on the casing-head petroleum spirit required for the customafry operations of the Company^ installations in the Sheikh*s territories. It is under stood that the Company shall be under no obligation to extract casing-head petroleum spirit from natural gas. #)UI 4*k u ^»*J I «jLU Ij Lr I (j I JtJi ^ ^-r ^ J ^ ^ O#^'J** f 1 'j JUoW^u'lv -H) V# The foregoing royalties reserved by Clauses (a) and (b) are subject to revision at the end of fifteen years* payment and in default \ of agreement either party shall have the right? w « A &lt; r x - M _ ^ ^ I aJUfc • JjLJl Ua^ ^ ( (j) ^JJUJI^y 41a#w^JJI I ;LJI ft^^ Q^Lmh' ^11* M^l * ^ *■■• #J 4 C5^ 6 ^ lefaij^y t oacjcw A^J i ^UJl^JUl p* -^c J 4jLw«hJUA# &lt;JlPL# #X('I ^wtj v/t 5 ^ -^i U- ^IaJ I p l^J I j^juJ I cj* } ^ ***■ (J/* Jil^jjly^l O-j -^4) Jl&gt;J i^y ^j^S—JI Ji^ iu-ouc Ji' ♦kS 1^ ( #/i r ji U * 4Lw ^ ^ J ^ (jJtjd I (&gt;»{ ^U.l i p j«w 1 m^&gt;- */%** I 41mJ I 4J-t i* LyJ y£z J-Y~ I i» ^ &lt;J X^^y J' t*±3h - n - to demand that the question at Issue shall be submitted to arbitration in the manner pro- Tided in this lease. (c) A sum equal to one-sixth of the field price received for the sale of any natural gas recovered by the Company, it being understood that the Company shall be under -no ^ obligation to produce, save, sell, or otherwise dispose of any natural gas nor shall the Company be re quired to pay any royalty on natural gas used in the Company^ installa- i tions in the SheikMs territories. The above royalties are payable on the basis of calendar half-yearly periods (i.e. from January first to June thirtieth and from July first to December thirty-first of each year) and in respect of such net crude oil and casing-head petroleum spirit as may be run from field storage (subject to the above-mentioned deductions) during each half- yearly period and in respect of such natural gas as may be sold during each half-yearly period. Settlement of royalty accounts shall be made between the parties within three months after the end of each half-yearly period. |U v (LtU - ' f- »T _ UJ&gt; ' fv cf J j * f UJI J^aJ \ i^Aj 1 J ILaU J^ (J^-eLnJ I il^kJL.jlt'X I ?^ ^ giwwil^ .Ua;II &lt;JL»oXiw».1 I K /^§ O ^ ^ ii^J JokLoJ J—i- JU4 cr-^^ «&gt; J~^l ^ it U Iw l#i* ij ^ I j I i-i-A 4^JUJ ilfyAJ1^ ^0 ^ &lt;3^^ g'&lt;11» lU)i tj^^J U U 1^ l^sSk: a J^j^Ul^lgiJl ^ j^jjlviuli v^lm jXftl J ^j ^ J&lt;^i&gt; k/v^ M* ^m JI j A J^Jlo.Vl^ iH -&lt;»*&gt; I* ^Jl ^Utl ^U- JU^viUlj JLA^ c^ ^ ^ ^ u ^ yi* •*■•' j 1 4&gt;li^l jJ-,5 ' ** ^ Ij l J Cr*^ &lt;&gt;• ' -&gt;?• J ««*« &gt;* j-t^*' ^ ^ ^ ^ *^ f»j (J&lt; u -* j J ..i^» ja aii^i jb^l o^' ^ ^ a JU j I 6 1 J^lc^YT ii^ Sj^dDU C^C*^ *\jj r -\ JJ* j^ljJI &lt;&gt;• J^ ^r^ - 12 - FOR the purposes of such royalty pay ments the Company shall measure by a method custoraarily used in good oilfield practice all crude oil won and saved and casing-head petroleum spirit extracted and the Sheikh by his representative duly authorized by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf itwn have the right to examine such measuring and to examine and test whatever appliances may be used for such measuring. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance ahaxl be found to be out of order the Sheikh may require that the same be put in order by and at the expense of the Company if such requisition be not complied with in a reasonable time the Sheikh may cause the said appliance to l)e put in order and may recover the expense of so doing from the Company and if upon any such examination as aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance such error shall if the Sheikh so decide after hearing the Company's explanation be considered to have existed for three calendar months previous to the discovery thereof or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of three calendar months and the royalty shall be adjusted 111 \A M-AM ( tX- ' &gt; ; i_ ir_ Lt ^ y y UA:.i i^tvJ U*»9^j t^/?^^' ^JU* Jl ^ jJl ^A ^i^J Ii«Jjb«JI ijyeJl, N* U,) 4^*, p-^c yJ I (J^*^ ( i^y 1^*1* (J^^&gt;J I ^liJ^lc.ljVlJ^ &lt; y J&gt;JI 4J^j-JI 1 i ^AJ I ^ I ca »' ip I j5 U J JI ^ylr^vA^ y 1 i^&gt;J I aJ j w L(1wJ 1 &lt; i-A ^U ^T^mJ I j sfiUlj Ju»^_&gt;- 1, ^4 *jjt y'Ji f J ''' i^UJl i^slk; ju^ yfc ^ **' Itlw^JI v^ 5 ^'* 6 WVh ^m^Jimi J^ iti^j gAJJ &gt; lj H i 1 A^Uil 1 p» j ^-r 4 olfL^yJI «jj^ • I 4i-Jlouc J* ' or^' U^-iJ i p 13; V I cS ^ • • ^wi xgi -Hr^ Ji&lt; V igOJ I p-y (&gt;*• ii i* x ^i! V^ - 13 - accordingly. If the Company desire to alter any measuring appliance it shall gire reason able notice to the Sheikh or his representa tive to enable a representative of the Sheikh to be present during such alteration. THE Company shall keep mi and correct accounts of all crude oil and casing-head petroleum spirit measured as aforesaid and of the natural gas sold (including the field price received for it) and the said represen tative of the Sheikh shall have access at reasonable times to the books of the Company containing such accounts and shall be at liberty to make extracts therefrom and the Company shall at their own expense within three calendar months after the end of each calendar half-year deliver to the Sheikh an abstract of such accounts for such half-year and a statement of the amount of royalty due to the Sheikh for such half-year. Such accounts shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh with the exception of such figures therein as he may be required by law to publish. Article Till . SUBJECT to the 'delay' exception men tioned in Article IV of this lease the Company hereby undertake that the amount «/ ■in* ■■i ■'; Jii1 ■■ ■ - Il_ 1 JX a JI I j «a ^ I j U 2^ jjts - ^ y^kJ I J-A^- U I VI • Jjull J^l •j- ui j^gi J*-Jl ^ |&gt; UXA I (J^j | U» Jji»- f-t '''* ^11 ( ^ i i (J/* c^twj I t O-iiimJ J Cj ^ UJ UfW JJLAJ 1 Ijjfc i.^.U'WfyJI 4^4mJmm|JI ^ I • A^gUI I -UkJ 1 ill UJ 1 JjVI IJjfc J jum jL» ^ «i «J y ij£— (—1 •*-«* J**4^ ^aiijaviu^s^Jiji^icr. ^ »• • LJ I JtMfJ ^ i^ajI|^)i p—J ^ ^ ii_JlJii:oiw cy- I Vx&gt;3: •• «—»-» i.» *»V «&gt; '^7 I - 14 - received by the Sheikh in respect of royal ties shall not bo less than at the rate of Rs. 75,OCX) in every calendar year in nhich this lease continues in operation# Article EC* THE Company shall carry on work within the leased area in accordance with good oil field practice and with all proper zeal ai th ] diligence and shall maintain at least two strings in continuous operation (allowing a reasonable time between the ccmpletion of one well and the cocmencement of the new) until a sufficient number of wells hare been drilled within the productiTe area covered by this lease to meet the requirements of V ' ■-, ■ ■ r good oilfield practice* Provided, however, that such obligation to maintain at least r • •• ■ . two strings in continuous operation be suspended during such time as the wells then drilled are capable of a total daily average production of at least one tons of oil* y Article I, ^ ) IN the event of the Company failing within six months of the end of any half-year to pay to the Sheikh the royalties . 1 .■I -- I • — ^.Jl U- a i_ rj «- ^ J ^ll&gt; U^jJk^dUlj ^ pi u #J-A ^ ■'■'' ^ O ^ I ^it) Ur^* or^v J 4 - 1 ^ I ij£i UJI ^r-^J 1 -UJ I ^ O'-} lp I •j-^^jUJI jjgi y ^ ^ S^AJU gau 1^ v^lmj ^ i jjl a ji j in ^ vi 3^iJ I fj* b* JY~ \ ^^6^ Ji V ' Jli y^5Ll&lt;«iI IJ-A *1 |,.V I -XiP^ d)J i-t ^ iJ 1 1^ jXAJ I LL^- J^J i J)LJ IvdUU (j* %#z~t 6 ^ IS'V - 15 - due in respect of that calendar half-year or failing, save for causes beyond their control, to carry out their obligations under this lease ; the Sheikh shell have the power to teminate this lease in which case the provisions of the last paragraph but one of Article II shall apply. Article :Q. THE Company shall have the ri^it to ter minate this lease upon giving not less than three months' written notice to the Sheikh of the intention of the Company so to do, and accordingly upon the expiration of such notice this lease shall absolutely determine upon the date fixed for determination in such notice, save as regards matters to be done at or after such determination. • y^jixgi J.UJI^UuJI^ J^SJI jjj; Uiiil £ ^ Uj— t 'tj *MJ I ilffell 0' j i/' j*** ' j** ■*** * -Iv'* IJoiJIy It ||'i; • - r Article XII . THE Company shall take all practical measures to prevent an injurious access of water to any oil bearing formations which may be encountered either while operations are in progress or upon the abandonment of any well and to prevent any uncontrolled flow of oil. A_ n _ i- *j&lt;i ^ ^ cU'* jy*t y Ijjk yj iJ&amp;^-J I V j I ^ • J&gt;1~ J-^Jl J^U l^JI i)U*J 1 141 ^fjfi 5jj Ag« IJ s5/^J I I ^ IUm V ^v-{ J^ 5 J Ojfc 6 ' /A gj^j ^ iJ I *i'«.I.»J l^r LW/t J-?^-t 1 ^■* 4 J 1 (^{ i^gV-jiyL^Jl ik-. IjJ I iJ^eiUl 4^U*J l^y SJX^J 1 «&gt; r v &gt;-L &lt;o • j A *^ j * A i&gt;J i Ju^j I **f+% J^Ai) 4w&lt;&gt;J I J^-l tjjj J AfwLpJl^ Ik^ Lit J Uj£*0 ' [ftJ* * ilX^J **£&gt;- (* J* J ilX^Jlv-^-ltf ^4 5^l-ii«» V * J^AJl J-^O^yt ^ I IJ l^* I 2J^ U OAfi* j - 16 - Article XIII , 1HS rights granted by this lease «h«Tl not be conveyed to a third party without the consent of the Sheikh acting under the advice of the Resident in the Persian Gulf. Such consent ah all not be unreasonably with' held. Article XIV. 1ES Company as assignees of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate Limited shall be and remain a British Company registered in Canada but shall maintain an office in Great Britain which shall at all times be in the charge of a British subject who shall be the recognized channel of com- munication between the Company and His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. Article XV. OF the five Directors of the Company one Director shall at all times be a British subject who shall be persona grata to His Majesty's Govermient. His selection for appointment as Director shall be made in consultation with His Majesty's Govern ment and his salary as Director shall be provided by the Company. A reasonable time • (' r '''K -- 1V_ wij r-JijiX yP^Jipi Ji»JI '^UJI JiUJl^ yXfJIw^u ^ jji 3^*11 i (j~»ji^j* :»ujic,iu«ji^, jr &gt;( i^ulo^ jjji ♦ l.\jCr i rM f )li£.£ J (jA- JI It-U-v lUfc^J I Ujk I ^ Jjs y It-^i J^AJ I *1 l*J I, I t&gt;V»v'v^ V' *J) JJI jy^i L - aj,t i u i -^i^i^ji •yu^oij^ji 0 - J ' U^' t ^ ^ i&gt;* Ov 5 ^ It- ^ O^c ^ l«l*j • U ^ Wg* - 17 - shall be allowed for the replacanent of the British Director in the event of this post falling vacant. Article XVI . THE Company shall at all times maintain in Bahrein an official to be called the 'Chief Local Representative' of the Company whose appointment shall be approved by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and who shall be the sole representative of the Company empowered to deal direct with the local authorities and population in Bahrein. All comnunications which that official may desire on behalf of the Company to address to the Sheikh of Bairein *h»n be made through the British Political Agent in Bahrein, A reasonable time shall be allowed for the replacement of the'Chief Local Representative' in the event of this post falling vacant. Article XVII . # AS many of the employees of the Company in Bahrein as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking, shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh of Bahrein. , # J'* 1 Article XVIII . Je ^AJ1 ^ I ^AJI f Ji the coffi?aily at thelr oto oo3t&gt; ll 1 -*r l\Uctvcu _ '4 ~ IA_ I UJ1 ^ !a&gt;* i *^ JL ' ^ J^ iti^J JL^ r-h ^^^ijuvi U*rc j^gi jUI U^v-^y^ i^yjl i&gt;.L^i) 21^ t ^ • i&gt; ^ I qtAJU ^ J 1&gt;J| p^Jl 6 i Jt^ Ji-J I li-^ J*-»J I ^^jl; I U Ij I *&gt;•»«« ^1 Jj^i\j\^mi\jjJ\J ICrlAiJl^^. O - f ji ^ IfcJl Ic-U^L^JI vl»)lj i-uj A« y- I 1J -A ^|JJ | Ot-^t l^-J 0 1 • JJLJI LL^ J^l it*** V-Ua^- J I 3^ 1 Jfij U+4t j Ci I iii^J ^ajJ lo-X^w |y.&gt;J j. ') 1 ^Sf**- 4*|^A4 I *UJI - 13 - four ^3 aftar ^ 9na of aach calendar yaar. ahaU th9 ^ ^ report of '-hair oporations together with a Plan ahowlng the location of all walla irilled. Such reporta ahall be treated, aa confidential to the Sheikh. Article XEC . ■EE Ccopany aUgn k9ep ^ ^ rect geological plana, aaps and recorde rs'atlng to the territory the subject matter of thle lease, together with copies of any geological reports which may be made frcm time to time. On and after 1st January 1940, or if this lease be sooner terminated then at the tine of such termination, the Sheikh or his duly authorized representative ahall be en titled to inspect and take copies of all such plans, maps, records or reports, pro- Tided, however, that the information so obtained by the Sheikh shall, in the event of this lease not being terminated, be treated as confidential to him for a period of three years from the date he obtains it. The Company shall also keep accurate records of the drilling logs of all wells, showing all casing inserted and any water horizons passed through, which shall be open » I- M- I j J. »«110' VI ii K' • lijAM U^l^lwss^ ^JJ # C/tjA-*l 1 jj^JI j 1 ^r-UJ ^ ^ i^i^J Icr Uj'i 1 • i^Aj I i^w p^-t yr-' ^ JJUJ i J U» I ^*0- * I j J^-^J I jjjJ | y L{ 4wjuJ ( 3&gt;JL l-ilutiL&gt;x U&lt;4 ^ I •&gt; ^ &lt;^ ' ^-^''■''t j jJLJ 1 lj-A&gt;^&gt;-jMC, liJ ij^J I »U:i. I, ^&gt;J IUL-J l^y iUIj ^ C'lgfAL? ^ IJ 1^ l^T 1^ i. V i i3&gt;JI lj^ o I &lt;0 LaIO I«—^&gt;*1 '-i ^p'J I J J I Up-iC J I 1/*^ V-r^t J 0 j ' J JjL&lt;J I 1J J^ i^J ^J1 ^JUJ1 ^4 i^OU;^ I Ji^k,J IJ-y-i ^j I^J I i~j Im Juit «'«&gt;JJ 1&lt;»^-»I&lt; ^4 IJ * 4.»it:.! a- ^AJ t I ^ J JI &lt;J j^pM J I I (^ iJ I 1 I j-A Ijjfc ^jyeJL, \J^ dU li^ uj£* ^ ^ j 1 dL# J^ ii)J IJ j ' • o^*J I ' ^-ir* - 19 - to inspection by the SheiMi or hie duly authorized repreaentatire at all reasonable times. Such records shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh. Article XX . THE Sheikh or his duly authorized representatiye shall be at liberty at all reasonable times to inspect and examine all field works carried on by the Company. Article XXI. THE Sheikh reserves the ri^it to search for and obtain any substances or products, other than those exclusively granted under this lease, within the leased area, except lands occupied by wells or other installa tions of the Company, provided that the right thus reserved by the Sheikh shall be exercised so as not to interfere with endanger or hamper the operations of the Company or interfere with or abrogate any of their rights hereunder, and also provided that a fair and reasonable compensation shall be paid to the Company for all damage the Company may sustain through the exercise of the right so reserved by the Sheikh. In any grant of such right so reserved by the Sheikh the grantee shall likewise be bound ^ tlU LA - y f )r xUI V U 1 ('I) 1^4 I ^IvJ^ ij-^-s v&gt;&lt;JiLc«J I I jji 4j^jj| iU AJ^IjjUJIU-A 4^-C^^l^l I cr* u 11 *-» I J-«^e j^J IJ li L: ly !dU 1J I (j^A^jJ I iW-^ i L*j t t+hisy+j* i J v&lt; ^ o' 0 &lt;&gt;• J l^ i^.&gt;&lt;J t ^C/ 0 i^'*' I — 1 m-&gt;J1 4it AJL}# &lt;^* k*&gt;&gt; '» Cf*-** ^ UUJ^Jl^ V^X ^ p-^4 0^** J *iXJ Li (&gt;#-*; j-&gt;-l «* t ~L» ^ * llwdi^y^U (^5^X1 I Li-A p p-J L) i ( ^ ) ^aA&gt;JLr^lPC^ 4 {j* ^**4 C/+-*t CJ ^oc' ^*4/^ ^ ijr+** Cj* J** V^ ^ • * jJt l^ f -20- by the previsions of this Article and a note thereof shall be endorsed on every document creating or recording the grant. Article mi . (a; If at any time any difference or dispute of any nature whatsoever shall arise between the parties hereto or their respec tive representatives touching these presents or concerning the interpretation hereof or anything herein contained or in connection herewith or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the seme shall, ^i^-ing a settlement by agreement between the parties hereto, and subject as herein after provided, be determined by a Tribunal (consisting of one or more persons not being more than three persons) constituted on the occasion of each Reference, as follows, that is to say:- (i) each of the parties hereto shall be at liberty to appoint one person as its own Representative as a Member on the Tribunal pro vided such appointment if thereto fore not voluntarily made be made within sixty days from the delivery of a request in writing so to do by one party to the other; /S 7 ^ ^L-\K.j»J b b ( r) fytCj# * 0+** 0 ' J.UJI JLa^J^ pk) ff 0 * v*** iS/*-&lt;jjJl Jt-Jk jA*l\ A^L^%i 1^ ^ 4^ ^ l **^ ^UJ^JJ^lg Ljj jjft y I J+*: uU^iJI^Vi Li-A^y L»4 «J 'jJ*tifjJI'f*J\j *±&gt;2 JImJI (/#2^aL) \»j U uj£t J^Wl I Jf+J I U j* CwSykl^Vs * uiu u^JU« o ^ a : ii U-^ l~J\j O*-** Iy»^ 1^ ^»-U ( 1) (ii) failing any such -appointment the British Political Resident for the time being in the Persian Gulf may appoint a Representatire fop the party so failing as aforesaid to appoint its Representatire; (iii/ should the British Political Resident fail to appoint a Repre- sentatire within thirty days after being requested so to do, the Representative who has been appointed shall be and shall act on behalf of both parties as the sole Manber of the Tribunal in the Reference before it and the pro- Tisiona hereinafter contained for the appointment of President shall not have any relation to the Refer ence to such sole Representative and the Award of such sole Repre sentative Aall be as binding on both parties as if he had been appointed sole Representative by mutual consent; (iv) in the event of two Representa tives being duly appointed they shall appoint a third party to act . -a. &gt;v vr &lt;s_i_TT_ p—J IJ I j fft {-• ^ *)i c, J.U^ &lt;Jr** &gt;10^-^ O'* U-A ' J-&gt;-l vii 1«^ J I k S j* I ' I * L-^l; ' - 22 - K.i 11 Jm&gt;- 1 ^ LJ* ^ ^ ^ (*) *■'&gt;-* ^ ^ {j* j i *« jjb«j i ijpoj tj (^ j-J' ^ ^ jI j\ j-U*^IA&gt; i.«» Cf+** u ^ I ^^azJ I IJ-A p ^J I j I !&gt;• f/icrt 1 -' s^ij tjpij+J I 4 \jy} I j \ jj»t~*J I j jpLuU V I J^^SJUJIj^J &gt;Jl Jyi ^U ( lj-»-l) t &gt;&lt;-^ 0 ^ u? Ifj I ' V-XU^- I Ijf* ii I ^r+y** ujft J*-*) I (jjj i p |^L&gt;» I I • &lt; Wm- ' J t^m yjQps ^vv.v»- , - Ll as President of the Tribunal on the Reference before it but if such appointment shall not for any reason be made within sixty days of the date of the appointment of the Representative lastly appointod the 1x3rd Chief Justice of England for the time being may 'be called upon by either one or both of the parties to appoint a President; (v) if either of the said Representa tives appointed as aforesaid refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting or dies, the party who appointed him shall appoint someone in his stead and if such further appointment shall not take place within sixty days after such re fusal, incapacity or death as afore said, the Reference to the Tribunal shall commence or proceed, as the case may be, before the remaining Representative and President (if one shall have been appointed) pro vided that in the event of such re maining Representative and President disagreeing, the decision of the Representative shall prevail and alone be taken into account; ^ f r L ' ._Tr_ I I U I (1) c-U ^ i I (j*' y&gt;*' j i Cj+*t iSjr ^* I ' • 4-U-^^y jj^\ L^\j Ij I^ i I J j*: I if* L) ^jjl p-£*J i* c r&gt;t5 jp I j J^mJI ^Ui&gt; I &lt;L1 UI A4^«J I ^ ' •****' ^ipi IJ J. ^ I ^UXI ♦ (j»E,« J1 j W&gt;M^4 iol^l tj^5j ( 4jiw*Jly^^MiJJ 1 *4 m &gt; ^Ji^jjl 0^jJ | ufii ^ ^ ^ c)^ I J 1 •dUli^i^^y U -A^y p U I \yi+*imx (j 1 ' Xj ij* I I *jy a^ v -J I * {j^ U-*J 1 i^hSl)lcJT^&gt;-V I kl ( I ) ^^SyjJI ^11 j \*£*J\ JloX-.l^Jl I U6 - 23 - (vi) should a President refuse to act or become Incapable of acting or die the said Lord Chief Justice of England shall appoint another President in his stead, (b) The decision of the Tribunal shall in the case of a sole Representative or In the case of a Representative and a President disagreeing, be the decision of the Repre sentative and in the event of there being the President with two Representatives, such decision shall where it is not unam- imous be that of the majority of such President and Representatives. (c) Except where herein otherwise pro vided the procedure of the Tribunal shall be that laid down by the Tribunal for the purposes of dealing with the Reference or References before it» (d) The parties may be represented by agents or officials and they may have the assistance of counsel or other advocates before the Tribunal, (e) The procedure shall consist of two parts, written and oral; (i) the written proceedings shall consist of the contnunication—T i_ ajl^ Uj V^JU 6 |f |WJ J l^UJI (T) 4^)1 ^ ^ ^O''^ ******* {j* OJLtf^ ^U imt I(&gt;&lt;*'.'t# a ^W£Jlii-1^U-J1 UK i) ^ujij ^Jij -&gt;&gt;^iJ ^J| •6v^l 0 ^ ^ fiU L&gt;-i VI ^L m ^J &lt;»U&gt;J^JLJ &lt;&lt;5L»&lt;i.l jJ^ f ^ jhe^xu^ i^»k«uU^&gt;*ll 1^ j? UjJ p JJ? I C- i J J J I &gt;^l 1^ L»yj I ^ l^l» l^ Lm^J 1^ 1 nri^ •tf^'if ly^ (j I &lt;#i»J J IrJj I iy^J I cX J &gt;.1\ •Ul W^JI L^h^- j3 s fJ\ i Sjj^\ • I ^L m J t Ul (j) UJl j^UI to the Tribunal and to the parties of Cases Counter-cases and if necessary Replies; also all papers and documents in Support; (ii) these conmunications shall be made through the person and in the order and within the time fixed by the Tribunal; (iii) a certified copy of every document produced by one party shall be comnunicated to the other party; (iv) the oral proceed ings shall consist of the hearing by the Tribunal of witnesses, experts, agents, couhsg X and other advocates# if) The parties and all persons claiming through then respectively shall submit to be examined by the Tribunal in relation to the matters in dispute and shall subject as aforesaid produce before the tribunal all books, deeds, papers, accounts, writings and documents within their possession or power respectively which may be required or called for and do all other things which during the proceed- % ings on the Reference the Tribunal may require, (g) The witnesses on the Reference shall, if the Tribunal think fit, be examined on oath or solemn affirmation. m* r- Vx \Jt- 1 — &lt;&gt;&lt;-i J {s U-i ^Ll ^ u^yj-i Lpu^ •^1^1 I (j^J; ^J io^j |^ ^ ^ 1 u^ ^ 1^ j»—J^l I^c^I^LmJ|^&gt;j l^-i^J I ^k ts) J V*^'' t/' 4 ^ U*-*- 6 ' j\^\ ,J* '^jl^l^Ju^iJlo^Jl .^inJtdJJtj j** t J IJ^S» UJU-n-^JaJliiUlj i * ^ ' J-t* j\J^^ «3*t^ Ct* (J iJ I (J^^J 1^ o ^ Cth ^ I i Cil) uy^ J^Vl ^ J&gt; ^' uj - ' ^ k (J 1 *-*-! ^ Ot^s QJ) *lAi; jJ^J \&lt;^L*j\j*J If la» UJI J^L-J I ^rv** iSj*' ^ v - , '* , ^?• ^ ^ ^ ^ p »fCw» ^ I jJ^*- * J^Sk) I 4 JJk (^4 *«jJb&gt;«J ^ya^uJI ^J^jjk# - 25 - (h) The Award to be made by the Tri bunal shall be final and binding on the parties and the persons claiming under them respectively. There shall be no appeal against the Award. (i) The cost of Reference and Award shall be in the discretion of the Tribunal who may direct to and by whom and in what manner those costs or any part thereof shall be paid, (j) In giving a decision the Tribunal shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to confOim to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (k) The place of the Tribunal shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. (l) English law shall apply to wi1 matters of procedure arising in connection with any arbitration or other proceeding under the foregoing provisions of this clause. IThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Linited, 225 Bush Street, San Francisco, California, U. S. A. Having regard to the provisions of Article Y of the Concession jkgreenient dated the 2nd December 1925, made between His Excellency Sheikh Hamad bin Sheikh. Isa A1 Khalifah and The Eastern &amp; General Syndicate Limited, and pursuant to the application made by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (who at that time held the Agreement in the place of The Eastern &amp; General Syndicate Limited), dated 2ath December 1934, a Ifining Lease was granted by His Excellency Sheikh Hamad bin Sheikh laa 11 Khalifah, acting on the advice of the Honorable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Th.e Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited on the 29th December 1934. This lease having been sealed by His Excellency Sheikh bin Sheikh Isa A1 Khalifah, signed by ?. A* Davies and J. M. Russell, attorneys in fact for The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, and wit nessed by Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch, British Political Agent in Bahrein, on 29th December 1934, but the date having been omitted from the blank space provided for it on the last page of the said Mining Lease, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited are hereby authorized to insert in their original copy of the Lease the figure w 291^1' in the blank space before the words n day of December 1934'* in the last line of the second pcmi£P^apli on the last page (page 26) of the said Lease* HIS EXCSLL2KCY SHEIKH SIR HAMAD BIN SHEIKH ISA. 1L KHALIFA m Attorneys In Fact for THE BAHREIN PETROLETM COIPANY LIMITED -»»j. Bahrein, 27th January, 1935• Vk*. ' , BRITISH PCEmCAL AGENT IN BAHREINp.z. 38D0 /35. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, S. ¥. 1. ^th June 1935. qui k-7h!&gt;~ .'/ould you please ref^f^to Lait^waite's letter of 17th May, No. P. Z. 3285/5&gt;rabout copies of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's Mining Lease? I enclose herewith 5 printed copies of the English text of the Mining Lease which have now been supplied 'by the Company. 8. With reference to paragraph 2 of Laithwaite's letter, the political Agent, Bahrein, has now sent us the third original of the Mining Lease. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Government of India with 5 copies of the print and to Behrein with 85 copies. Hon'ble. Lt.Gol. T.C. Powle, CBE. , i.B.M. Consulate-General, Bushire. Uno His Excellency SHEIKH HAMAD BIN SHEIKH ISSA A L KHALIFAH SHEIKH of BAHREIN — AND — THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. [CopyI E'cast§ ! f xllbi made B etween H is E xcellency SHEIKH HAMAD BIN SHEIKH TSSA AL KHALIFAH SHEIKH of BAHREIN of the one part, hereinafter called 'the Sheikh' (acting on the advice of the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED hereinafter called ' the Company' (a Company incorporated under the laws of the Dominion of Canada) of the other part. WITNESSES as follows: — A rticle I. THE Sheikh hereby grants to the Com pany on behalf of himself and his successors the exclusive right for a period of fifty-five years from the first of January One thousand nine hundred and thirty-five to prospect and drill for, extract, treat, refine, manufacture, transport and deal with petroleum products, naphtha, natural greases, tar, asphalt, ozokerite, and other bituminous materials within the area or areas described in words in the First Schedule to this lease and delineated on the map attached as the Second Schedule thereto. Such right, however, shall not include the exclusive right to sell such products within the leased area. He also grants the Company the exclusive right to construct and operate refineries and storage tanks within this area and also the right, but not the exclusive right to construct, erect and operate pipe-lines, refineries and storage tanks, railways, wharves, and jetties, tramways, roads, buildings, machinery and telegraph appa ratus of all kinds in any part of the territory under the control of the Sheikh so far as may be necessary for the purpose of their business. For the purposes of their work the Company shall have the right, but not the exclusive right, to prospect for, collect and use free, but not to export or sell: (a) anywhere within the leased area: stone, gypsum, salt, sulphur, clay and wood; and (b) anywhere within the territory under the control of the sheikh; waterThe selection of routes and sites for aucl works and the course of the pipe-line sha rest with the Company. The Company shall at their own expert maintain and keep in repair the existin and all other necessary boundary marks { the corners of the leased area, according | the demarcation shown in the plan herel annexed, so that the boundaries of tl leased area may at all times throughoi the term of this lease be clearly defined A rticle II. THE Sheikh grants gratuitously to tl Company all land uncultivated at the da of this lease in any part of the territoi under his control which may be needed \ the Company for their operations, exclu ing, however, the land within the municip boundaries of Muharraq and Manama ( defined by a red line on the map attach and forming the Second Schedule heret and the land within a radius of 300 yar from the northeast corner of the Sheik! Palace at Sakhir (as defined by a gre circle on such map) PROVIDED ALWA^ that to the extent and for the period and for which the Company shall use ai uncultivated land belonging to the Sheil in his private capacity and falling with the land not excluded in the precedi provisions of this paragraph (other tht the pieces of land used by the Compai at the date of this lease and shewn on t map attached hereto and bounded by blue line) the Company shall, if requested by the Sheikh, pay to the Sheil compensation for the use and occupancy such land. Any such compensation shi not exceed a fair and reasonable recoi pense to the Sheikh for the dispossession his right to the surface of such land ai having regard to the prices ordinari current for similar land situated in t locality; failing agreement as to the coi pensation payable to the Sheikh the matt shall be referred to and determined arbitration in the manner provided 1 Article XXII hereof. In the lands so granted the Compai shall for the period of this lease enjoy h proprietary rights.n ^ 3 ihe Sheikh also recognises that the Company have the right to acquire all and any other lands and buildings necessary for the said purpose with the consent of the proprietors (including the Sheikh in his capacity as private landowner) on such conditions as may be arranged between the Company and the said proprietors without their being allowed to make demands of a nature to surcharge the prices ordinarily current for lands and buildings situated in their respective localities. At the termination of this lease the ground and all immovable property left by the Company shall be handed back to the Sheikh; all borings (including casing therein) which the Company have not abandoned shall be handed over in reason- ably good order and repair; and all other property of the Company may be removed by the Company free of all taxes and duties, provided however that for a period of thirty days following the termination of this lease the Sheikh shall have the right to purchase such property at a price equal to the replacement value at that date, less depreciation, which price in the absence of agreement shall be settled by arbitration in the manner set forth in this lease. It is however understood that within the leased area the Company shall be entitled to acquire only such land as is necessary for their pipe-lines, refineries, offices and other works and that save, in so far as it is necessary in order to enable their pipe lines and railways to pass freely to their destination, they shall not acquire as pro vided by paragraph 3 of this Article any land outside the leased area which might otherwise be leased for the production of oil to a third party, unless they can satisfy the Sheikh that no other land suitable for their purpose is available. A rticle III. ALL lands granted by this lease to the Company or that may be acquired by the Company in the manner provided for in Article II of this lease as also all products exported shall be free of all imposts and taxes during the tenure hereof.4 All material and apparatus of ever kind necessary for the exploration, work ing and development of the deposit am for the construction and development o the pipe-lines including also all the work specified in the first paragraph of Articl I hereof and office requirements but no including the personal requirements c employees shall enter the said territor free of all taxes and custom house dutief This privilege shall continue in force for term of ten years from the date hereof. A rticle IV. THE Sheikh undertakes to give all th protection in his power to the Compan and to their staff and laborers in any par of his territory from thefts, highwa robbery, assault, &amp;c. Similarly the Sheik] undertakes to protect all the property c the Company and of their employee which may be exposed to wilful damag or to possible loss by theft. If the Company's work is delayed b; such events as are mentioned in thi Article or by any cause beyond the Com pany's control arising in Bahrein then th period shall be added to the period fo which this lease is granted and the annus minimum royalty of Rs. 75,000 provide for by Article VIII shall not be payable i respect of such delay. A rticle V. FOR the above purposes it is agreed tha the Company in communication with th Sheikh shall appoint permanent trust worthy guards under a reliable man c good family whose pay and that of th guards shall be provided by the Compan and who shall remain there summer an winter. If in spite of the efforts of the sai guards thefts should occur, the Sheik, undertakes to recover the property stole and to compensate the Company for an damage sustained in his territory. In th event of non-recovery of the stole property, the value thereof shall by ns 5 deducted by the Company from any sums due to the Sheikh by the Company. The number of guards at any place where the Company may operate shall be fixed by the Company. It shall be the duty of the above-men tioned head of the guard to keep order in ^he areas in his charge to such extent as the Company may order him, he shall have no right to interfere in any disputes among the Company's servants unless asked by the Company to do so. The Company hereby agree that so long as the provisions of Bahrein Orders in Council 1913 and 1922, or any Order in consolidation thereof or in substitution therefor or supplementary thereto, remain in force, and jurisdiction over certain foreigners in the State of Bahrein is exer cised by His Britannic Majesty, the provisions in the second paragraph of this Article V shall not apply in respect to commissions of any acts of theft or damage by any person (1) if, on such person being arrested, it is found that he is a foreigner over whom jurisdiction exercised by His Britannic Majesty under the said Orders in Council has been extended, or (2) if, in the event of no arrests being made, it is proved to the satisfaction of the Company, or if necessary, the Political Agent, that the offender is such a foreigner as above mentioned, and that he has left the territory governed by the Sheikh and has not to the knowledge of the Sheikh or his officials returned thereto, and that no arrest could therefore be made. A rticle VI. IN case of misconduct the said guards are subject to dismissal or fine by the Company. In the event of any heavier punishment being needed, the offender shall be handed over to the representative of the Sheikh, and the Sheikh undertakes that punishment shall be inflicted and to use his utmost endeavours to uphold the authority of the Company's employees, thereby avoiding unnecessary troubles to both parties to this lease.A rticle VII. THE Company agree to pay to th( Sheikh the following royalties, namely:- (a) Rs. 3.8.0 per ton of net crude oi got and saved (i.e. after deducting water and foreign substances am oil required for the customan operations of the Company'i installations in the Sheikh'i territories). (b) Rs. 3.8.0 per ton of casing-heac petroleum spirit extracted by tb Company from natural gas wher* the average recovery from the gai treated from the various well; over the relative period o accounting is under two imperia gallons per One thousand cubi feet of natural gas at a pressure o one atmosphere and at a temper ature of sixty degrees Fahrenhei and Rs. 7.0.0. per ton of th casing-head petroleum spirit s» recovered where such averag recovery is two imperial gallon or more. No royalty shall b payable on the casing-heai petroleum spirit required for th customary operations of th Company's installations in th Sheikh's territories. It is under stood that the Company shall b under no obligation to extrac casing-head petroleum spiri from natural gas. The foregoing royalties reserved b; Clauses (a) and (b) are subject to revisioi at the end of fifteen years' payment and ii default of agreement either party shal have the right to demand that the questio] at issue shall be submitted to arbitratio] in the manner provided in this lease. (c) A sum equal to one-sixth of th field price received for the sale c any natural gas recovered by th Company, it being understoo* that the Company shall be unde no obligation to produce, sav( sell, or otherwise dispose of an; natural gas nor shall the Com pany be required to pay an;7 royalty on natural gas used in the Company's installations in the Sheikh's territories. ihe above royalties are payable on the basis of calendar half-yearly periods (i.e. from January first to June thirtieth and from July first to December thirty-first of each year) and in respect of such net crude oil and casing-head petroleum spirit as may be run from field storage (subject to the above-mentioned deductions) during each half-yearly period and in respect of such natural gas as may be sold during each half-yearly period. Settlement of royalty accounts shall be made between the parties within three months after the end of each half-yearly period. FOR the purposes of such royalty pay ments the Company shall measure by a method customarily used in good oilfield practice all crude oil won and saved and casing-head petroleum spirit extracted and the Sheikh by his representative duly authorised by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf shall have the right to examine such measuring and to examine and test whatever appliances may be used for such measuring. If upon such exam ination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Sheikh may require that the same be put in order by and at the expense of the Company and if such requisition be not complied with in a reasonable time the Sheikh may cause the said appliance to be put in order and may recover the expense of so doing from the Company and if upon any such examination as aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance such error shall if the Sheikh so decide after hearing the Company's explanation be considered to have existed for three calendar months previous to the discovery thereof or from the last occasion of exam ining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of three calendar months and the royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company desire to alter any measuring appliance it shall give reasonable notice to the Sheikh or his representative to enable a repre sentative of the Sheikh to be present during such alteration. z'THE Company shall keep full and correct accounts of all crude oil and casing-head petroleum spirit measured as aforesaid and of the natural gas sold (including the field price received for it) and the said representative of the Sheikh shall have access at all reasonable times to the books of the Company containing such accounts and shall be at liberty to make extracts therefrom and the Company shall at their own expense within three calendar months after the end of each calendar half-year deliver to the Sheikh an abstract of such accounts for such half- year and a statement of the amount of royalty due to the Sheikh for such half- year. Such accounts shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh with the excep tion of such figures therein as he may be required by law to publish. A rticle VIII. SUBJECT to the ' delay' exception mentioned in Article IV of this lease the Company hereby undertake that the amount received by the Sheikh in respect of royalties shall not be less than at the rate of Rs. 75,000 in every calendar year in which this lease continues in operation. A rticle IX. THE Company shall carry on work within the leased area in accordance with good oilfield practice and with all proper zeal and diligence and shall maintain at least two strings in continuous operation (allowing a reasonable time between the completion of one well and the commence ment of the new) until a sufficient number of wells have been drilled within the productive area covered by this lease to meet the requirements of good oilfield practice. Provided, however, that such obligation to maintain at least two strings in continuous operation shall be suspended during such time as the wells then drilled are capable of a total daily average pro^ duction of at least one thousand tons of oil.iMK - 9 Article X. IN the event of the Company failing within six months of the end of any calendar half-year to pay to the Sheikh the royalties due in respect of that calendar half-year or failing, save for causes beyond their control, to carry out their obligations under this lease, the Sheikh shall have the power to terminate this lease in which case the provisions of the last paragraph but one of Article II shall apply. Article XI. THE Company shall have the right to terminate this lease upon giving not less than three months' written notice to the Sheikh of the intention of the Company so to do, and accordingly upon the expiration of such notice this lease shall absolutely determine upon the date fixed for deter mination in such notice, save as regards matters to be done at or after such determination. Article XII. THE Company shall take all practical measures to prevent an injurious access of water to any oil bearing formations which may be encountered either while opera tions are in progress or upon the abandon ment of any well and to prevent any uncontrolled flow of oil. Article XIII. THE rights granted by this lease shall not be conveyed to a third party without the consent of the Sheikh acting under the advice of the Resident in the Persian Gulf. Such consent shall not be unreasonably withheld. Article XIV. THE Company as assignees of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate Limited shall be and remain a British Company regis tered in Canada but shall maintain an office in Great Britain which shall at all10 times be in the charge of a British subiect who shall be the recognised channel of communication between the Company and His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. Article XV. OF the five Directors of the Company one Director shall at all times be a British subiect who shall be persona grata to His Majesty's Government. His selection for appointment as Director shall be made in consultation with His Majesty's Govern ment and his salary as Director shall be provided by the Company. A reasonable time shall be allowed for the replacement of the British Director in the event of this post falling vacant. Article XVI. THE Company shall at all times main tain in Bahrein an official to be called the ''Chief Local Representative' of the Com pany whose appointment shall be approved by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and who shall be the sole representative of the Company empowered to deal direct with the local authorities and population in Bahrein. All communica tions which that official may desire on behalf of the Company to address to the Sheikh of Bahrein shall be made through the British Political Agent in Bahrein. A reasonable time shall be allowed for the replacement of the 'Chief Local Repre sentative' in the event of this post falling vacant. Article XVII. AS many of the employees of the Com pany in Bahrein as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking, shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh of Bahrein. Article XVTII. THE Company at their own cost, within four months after the end of each calendar year, shall furnish the Sheikh with an annual report of their operations together with a plan showing the location of all wells drilled. Such reports shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh.11 A rticle XIX. THE Company shall keep in Bahrein correct geological plans, maps and records reiatmg to the territory the subject matter or this lease, together with copies of any geological reports which may be made from time to time. On and after 1st January 1940, or if this lease be sooner terminated then at the time of such termination, the Sheikh 0 L it 1 *! &lt; ^ u ly. authorised representative snail be entitled to inspect and take copies of all such plans, maps, records or reports, provided, however, that the infor mation so obtained by the Sheikh shall, in the event of this lease not being terminated, be treated as confidential to him for a peroid of three years from the date he obtains it. The Company shall also keep accurate records of the drilling logs of all wells, shewing all casing inserted and any water horizons passed through, which shall be open to inspection by the Sheikh or his duly authorised representative at all reasonable times. Such records shall be treated as confidential to the Sheikh A rticle XX. THE Sheikh or his duly authorised lepresentative shall be at liberty at all reasonable times to inspect and examine all field works carried on by the Company. A rticle XXI. THE Sheikh reserves the right to search -Or and obtain any substances or products other than those exclusively granted under this lease, within the leased area, except lands occupied by wells or other installa- tions of the Company, provided that the right thus reserved by the Sheikh shall be exercised so as not to interfere with endanger or hamper the operations of the * 0r .interfere with or abrogate any , ri § hts hereunder, and also provided that a fair and reasonable com- P® ns J^ l0n shall be paid to the Company for all damage the Company may sustain through the exercise of' the right so reserved by the Sheikh. In any grant of such right so reserved by the Sheikh the12 grantee shall likewise be bound by the provisions of this Article and a note thereof shall be endorsed on every document creating or recording the grant. A rticle XXII. (a) If at any time any difference or dispute of any nature whatsoever shall arise between the parties hereto or their respective representatives touching these presents or concerning the interpretation hereof or anything herein contained or in connection herewith or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing a settlement by agree ment between the parties hereto, and subject as hereinafter provided, be deter mined by a Tribunal (consisting of one 01 more persons not being more than three persons) constituted on the occasion oi each Reference, as follows, that is to say (i) each of the parties hereto shall b( at liberty to appoint one person af its own Representative as i Member on the Tribunal providec such appointment if theretofore not voluntarily made be mad( within sixty days from the deliver] of a request in writing so to do bj one party to the other; (ii) failing any such appointment th( British Political Resident for th( time being in the Persian Gul: may appoint a Representative fo] the party so failing as aforesaid k appoint its Representative; (iii) should the British Political Resi dent fail to appoint a Representa tive within thirty days after bein^ requested so to do, the Representa tive who has been appointed shal be and shall act on behalf of botl: parties as the sole Member of th( Tribunal in the Reference befor( it and the provisions hereinaftei contained for the appointment o; President shall not have any rela tion to the Reference to such sole Representative and the Award o: such sole Representative shall b( as binding on both parties as ii he had been appointed sol( Representative by mutual consent13 (iv) m the event of two .Representa tives being duly appointed they shall appoint a third party to act as President of the Tribunal on the Reference before it but if such appointment shall not for any reason be made within sixty days of the date of the appointment of the Representative lastly appointed the Lord Chief Justice of England for the time being may be called upon by either one or both of the parties to appoint a President; (v) if either of the said Representa tives appointed as aforesaid refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting or dies, the party who appointed him shall appoint someone in his stead and if such further appointment shall not take place within sixty days after such refusal, incapacity or death as aforesaid, the Reference to the Tribunal shall commence or proceed, as the case may be, before the remaining Representa tive and President (if one shall have been appointed) provided that in the event of such remain ing Representative and President disagreeing, the decision of the Representative shall prevail and alone be taken into account; (vi) should a President refuse to act or become incapable of acting or die the said Lord Chief Justice of England shall appoint another President in his stead. (b) The decision of the Tribunal shall in the case of a sole Representative or in the case of a Representative and a President disagreeing, be the decision of the Representative and in the event of there being the President with two Repre sentatives, such decision shall where it is not unanimous be that of the majority of such President and Representatives. (c) Except where herein otherwise provided the procedure of the Tribunal shall be that laid down by the Tribunal for the purposes of dealing with the Reference or References before it. (d) The parties may be represented by agents or officials and they may have the14 assistance of counsel or other advocatp before the Tribunal. (e) The procedure shall consist of tw&lt; parts, written and oral; (i) the writtei proceedings shall consist of the communi cation to the Tribunal and to the parties o Cases, Counter-cases and if necessar Replies; also all papers and documents ii Support; (ii) these communications shal be made through the person and in th order and within the time fixed by th- Tribunal; (iii) a certified copy of ever document produced by one party shall b communicated to the other party; (iv) th oral proceedings shall consist of th hearing by the Tribunal of witnesses experts, agents, counsel and othe advocates. (f) The parties and all persons claimin through them respectively shall submit t be examined by the Tribunal in relation t the matters in dispute and shall subject a aforesaid produce before the Tribunal a] books, deeds, papers, accounts, writing and documents within their possession o power respectively which may be require or called for and do all other things whic during the proceedings on the Referenc the Tribunal may require. (g) The witnesses on the Referenc shall, if the Tribunal think fit, be examinei on oath or solemn affirmation. (h) The Award to be made by th Tribunal shall be final and binding on th parties and the persons claiming unde them respectively. There shall be n appeal against the Award. (i) The cost of Reference and Awan shall be in the discretion of the Tribuna who may direct to and by whom and h what manner those costs or any par thereof shall be paid. (j) In giving a decision the Tribuna shall specify an adequate period of dela^ during which the party against whom th&lt; decision is given shall conform to th( decision and that party shall be in defaul only if that party has failed to conform t( the decision prior to the expiry of tha period and not otherwise. (k) The place of the Tribunal shall b( such as may be agreed by the parties anc in default of agreement shall be London.15 (1) English law shall apply to all matters of procedure arising in connection w itn any arbitration or other proceeding under the foregoing provisions of this clause. Article XXIII. IN the event of any disagreement regard ing the meaning or interpretation of any thing hereinbefore contained the English text shall be regarded as correct. Dated this 29th day of December 1934. and executed in three parts all having equal validity. The First Schedule hereinbefore referred to. ALL THAT the territory delineated and described as to measurements upon the map or plan attached hereto and forming the Second Schedule hereto. i The Second Schedule hereinbefore referred to. See attached plan sealed and signed by the various parties hereto. His Excellency The SHEIKH OF BAHREIN. (SEAL.) THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. By (signed) J. M. RUSSELL By (signed) F. A. DA VIES Its Attorneys-in-Fact Before me G. LOCH British Political Agent in Bahrein.* U.' Confidential . No:C/384-10/1. j : ■ ■ ■ ' ' Political. Agency, _ Bahrain, the 2nd ^uly 1955. Captain G.A.Cole, J.A., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire Bahrain Oil. To:- Sir, i J i have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter Ho;302-20 dated the 20th June 1935 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government and to request you to interpret the correct meaning of Article III, paragraph 2, of The Bahrain Petroleum Company's Mining Lease in its application to local taxation. s. The point at issue is 'Does Article III, paragraph 2, /^exempt the Bahrain Petroleum Company from paying taxes such as license fees on motor cars?' 3. In my opinion it does not and the Company are liable to pay all such taxes. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant. ,/Z ^*4 Captain. Officiating Political Agent,ivo. ^ / jjj| Uffi g© o.i' t:^ .i,c I tiser to t -w ■ overa ^en «, Bahrain# Dated, Juae ^0^ 1935 From The vdviser to the ^OTern.aeui of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic ...gesty's Political Agent, Bcihrai a • jir, I bira the aoncm- to racpest your opinion as to the meaaia^ of a ,ortion of one of the sections of the iuia^, Lease between His Jxcel- lency jhuiih ^ir : in,md uad the Baiu^ia Detroit on Coajjany. E. in article ^3' ptura rt H t? , it is written:- rt All aatericd aad -rhtua of a&amp;? kind neoeasary for the ai^loraiion. working una development of the deposit and for the construction and djevelop lent of the pipe lines including also all the works specified in the first ^rujraph of article '1 ? hereof,end office require- mntB but no- including the pemonal requ ire \eat s of eaployee3 t sha 11 on ter the laid territory free of all taxes and custom house duties• ' f Am I correct in interpreting the aean- in t of this paragraph to 'be that the ooapany are not liable for payaaeat of any taxes or duties which would ordinarily be leviable on their Taatcrial aad apparatus at the tiiae ol import, such as cusioaa duty, pier tax, etc? This, in uiy opinion, seams obviously implied oy the parti cular use of the word 71 enter^ I do not understandunderstand the paragraph to •lean that viie company is free from all taxes of uny kind but only that they are free from taxes on eatry. 4* la the pa at Urn ociJipany have paid the uau.%1 license fees on lotor -vehicles, raU I understand uaofficially that they have now decided thai this .j&amp;ymni should not have been aade .3 according to the lease they ore free fro:^ ell taxation* Before diacussin.: the question I should he obliged if you ould advise s on the subject* I have the honour to Oe, olr, Your obedient servant, idviser to the Govera:5ont»X — ^ ■■ A 1 CONFIDENTIAL No. 0/390-10/1. &gt;1*V Ci. V The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bushire. H.M's Secretary of State for India, London. orelgn Secretary to the Government of ^ ndxa, Simla. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). rF ; | The Agency, CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS \ BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated... bth. .ixQrJ. .1935... Reference to previous correspondence ■ • Description of Enclosure. Letter No;PA~225 of S8-6-193c) from the ^hief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. Bahrain Oil.No. PA-225 June 28, 1935. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: At meetings held at the Agency in December 1934, at which Colonel Looh. Mr. Belgrave, Mr. 7orth, Mr. Hamilton, Mr. navies, and to. Russell were present, it was decided that, for purposes of record, e Bahrein Government and The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited wou d jointly survey the Municipal boundaries of Manama and Muharraq and the areas privately owned by His Excellency sheikh sir Hamad bin Issa al Khalifah, K.C.i.E., C.S.I. The latter are the Rumaithah iiunting Lodge, Unm al Talah Hunting Lodge including the palm grove, 'Amar Hunting Lodge, Sakhir Ga.rden, Sakhir Race Track, and an area at Zellaq. ^ I am sending herewith two letters addressed to His Excellency with the descriptions of all these areas attached, requesting notifi cation that he accepts them as correct and confirmation that the privately owned tracts described are all that he owns in his private capacity other than Sakhir and within the boundaries of Manama and Muharraq. Will you kindly hand these letters and descriptions to His Excellency. Copies for your record are also being sent. Yours very truly. a. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. End:J'une 28, 1935. His Excellency .Sheikh sir Haraad Sheikh of Bahrein, Bahrein. bin Issa al Khali fail, K.C.I.E., C. Your Excellency: The Municipal boundaries of Manama and Muharraq are in seated by red lines on the map forming the second Schedule o x.e Mining Lease made between Your Excellency and The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, dated 29th December, 1934. . . r ^ ne boundaries oi the two Municipal areas were surveyed jointly by the Bahrein Government and The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Descriptions of the surveys are attached hereto and the Company will appreciate it if you will kindly confirm that they are correct. Sincerely yours, y /bHLS&amp;Z' a. w. r. si-ltth, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. End:i aUMM OF THE MUMICIPll RO UMDAHXES OF M6MA1.1A fc t.liminPAn Method of Survey; The survey is tied to the triangulation system established by the British Admiralty for their hydrographio work. The origin of this systan is described as being a nail in the roof of the Political Agency in Manama. All boundary points ha -ra as markers cement and rock monuments 14 to 18 inches square and 2 to 4 feet high. With the exception of four markers at the eastern end of Manama, all were set or reset during this survey and are marked M.B. for Municipal Boundary, Manama Municipal Bot^ndary Beginning at a point on the beach at approximate high tide mark in a locality known as Ghosaibai to the South and East of Ivknama, this point being S. 5492.0 feet and E, 336E.71 feet from the Admiralty origin of coordinates: Thence S 78 c 51 f W, 965.67 feet to a point plus or minus 18 feet East of the Ghosaibai cemetery wall; thence S 10056*20 ,, E, 333.23 feet to a point plus or minus 18 feet Southeast of Southeast corner of the cemetery; thence S 50 o 56 , 10 ff W, 447.04 feet to a point plus or minus 20 feet South of Southwest comer of the cemetery; thence S 0 o 05 t 50 n W, 531.06 feet to a point; thence S 85O44 t 40 n E, 109.03 feet to a point; thence S lloil^O' W, 556.69 feet to a point; thence S O^S^O* W, 530,87 feet to a point (these last four points embracing the area occupied by the buildings of Sheikh Abdullah Mohamad); thence N 27 0 34 , W, 2407 .37 feet to a point plus or minus 15 T South of the Southeast comer of the garden to the West of Sheikh Sir Hamad bin Issa al Khalifats to ^sn Palace; thence S 69 o 55 , 30 B W, 462.96 feet to a point plus or minus 15 feet South of the Southwest comer of above garden; thence N 20 0 24 , W, 505,60 feet to a point in the garden fence; thence S 74 o 45 , 30 ,, W, 435.53 feet %-2- ■1 ( r ^ 'J 1 ^ es mi ^54, J totmiw: Wfi &gt;C JMfMlhs ^ aii io m td iw ECIIJ Jatojjjj • 'or^ism 16 fSina x?:.;2 '.'mwimit . mdt I '^i^io^3!. , i sru aiJ iM'3 ,1 la is®; &amp; sni t'M iM M a oq z oi $■ to a point at the Southeast cornsr* of the ts To-« «. corner the thence along the cemetery wall S 74 o 48 f 20 ,T W, 131 ■p«o+ + | w, 131.13 feet to a point at an angle in the { ^ N 13O22,50 ' ^ ^ ^e cemetery wall, 189.18 feet to |. a point at an angla the cemetery wall; thence S 73 o 51»40' W, 845,73 feet po^nt at an ang .e m tne c^neteiy wall; thence N Sl^O^lO' w. along the canetery wall, 503.38 feet to a point at an angle in the cemetery wall; thence 516.82 feet along caaetery mil to a point plus or minus 200 feet West of Southwest comer of the cemetery; thence S ll^lO' E, 235.61 feet to a point; thence S 82^4' W, 478.35 feet to a point; thence S 76O06^20» W, 545,16 feet to a point near garden fence (the aboye three points defining the boundary where it passes to the South of the Bahrein Fort and buildings pertaining thereto); thence S 23 o 42»50' W, 180.28 feet to a point; thence S 4 o 34»20» W. 221.76 feet to a point; thence S 81O02»10' W, 104.28 feet to a point; thence S 2 o 31»40 ft W, 386.38 feet to a point; thence S l o 56 f 20 rt E, 167,66 feet to a point; thence S 64 o 05»40« W, 447.31 feet to a point at the Northeast corner of the garden of Hodgi Mansoural Arayeadh (the above six points define the j boundary as it passes to the South of Sheikh Sir Hamad's old Palace, North of the Saghayea gardens) ; thence S 82O50»30' W, 2093,35 feet to a point at the Southwest corner of the Insane Asylum wall; thence N 31 o 57 ? 20 M W, 169.01 feet to a point at an angle in the wall; thence N 23 o 59 , 30' E, 920,18 feet to a point at the Southeast comer of a garden wall; thence N IS^O'SO' W, 1414«02 feet to a point; thence N 3 o 07 ? 40 ,f V.' , 174 o 07 feet to a point; thence N 17 o 06 t 50 ,, W , 252 .05 feet to a point on the South side of the Mene Road (the above three points lie to the West of Gosaibi's gardens); thence S 69 0 35* W, along road 243,17 feet to a point of junction of side road from Suwaifia; thence N 35014*40' 413.74 feet along side road to a point at an angle in the garden fence; thence N 42 o 12 , 10 n V/, 145.70 feet along the garden fence to a point at the Southeast W,.™., « . ,0. o, tt .„. s W „. M . ^ t&lt;&gt;t time ^ ^ l ^ ^ ^ rOW 01 h0aSeS t0 POint at thQir So ^^est comer; thence N I20o 2 too» W, 103,69 feet more or leq&lt;5 tr&gt; a ^ 0n the beaeh at tlle Horth end of Bahrein I Island in the locality known as Suwaifia at the approve high tide line; thence Easterly following the line of the beach passing to the North of Manama and j following the beach as it bends Southerly am continuing until reaching the P of be b xmung on the beaeh at Ghosaibai. The aboTe -described lines consti- tute the Municipal boundaries of Manama and enclose aU the Municipal lands pertaining to the said city of Manama. Miharraq Municipal Boundaiy Beginning at a point approximately at high tide level on the beach at t.^e Souths limi . Tillage o Besateen, said point being N 10971.26 feet and K 7850.40 feet from the Admiralty origin of coordinates. Thence S 87°12 '10' E, 431.21 feet to a point plus or minus 200 feet West of an old unwalled grave yard; thence K 31-:.3'X0' E, 839.99 feet to a point plus or minus 120 feet South of the Southwest corner of a garden of Besateen; thence K 74 o 55'40' S, 984.84 feet to a point plus or minus 60 feet Southeast of the Southeast corner of the garden of Besateen; thenoe S 16 o 51'50' E, 4438.46 feet to a point on the beach; thenoe Southerly following the curves of the beach passing to the South of the town of Muharraq and then northerly still following the beach to the q' j69l i&gt;91 '• point of beginning near the village of Besateen, The aboTe described lines or - 3S 3 • 5i i gno J ■ | constitute the Municipal boundaries of Muharraq. and enclose all the Municipal lands pertaining to the said city of Muharraq,JUne 28, 1935&lt;, Sheikh of Bahrein, Bahrein. aeiS 0 ^ 1 ^,' 91 ^ Sir 3811103 15111 Issa Khalifah, K.C.I.S., C.S.I Your Excellency: Lodge, Saldiir G-arden, sakhir Race Track, and an area at Zellaq, have been jointly surveyed by the aoverimient and the Company, Hie descriptions of the various tracts are herewith. Will you kindly advise the Company whether you accept these descriptions as correct and confirm their understanding that these areas comprise all the lands privately owned by you outside the Municipal boundaries of Manama and Muharraq and the circular area around the Palace at Saichir having its center at the Northeast corner of the palace and a radius of 300 yards. Sincerely yours. C, W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. End: S 6rrro wn-nrr mr™ OF Li^ffOS PBIYATSLY OWMFH KV HIS EXCEILEUCY SHEIKH SIH HAMAD BIB IS3A Al KlLS. I. C. I. E . .c. S . t. Msthod of Survey ; Triangulation wes uaed whei-ewr poselbte and convenient, transit and rtrtln elsewhere. All comer and boundary points are marked by short lonsths of 3' pipe set in concrete. One such point of each area *as chosen as a starting point and its position determined with respect to Trlangulation Station fio.l of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. This station is located on the highest point of the Jebel Mchan hills is uaed as a triangulation point by the British Admiralty for their surveys in and around Bahrain, Rumaithah Jfontln g Ijodge non . i. Hum ■ukssw.-hhii i i| Beginning at a point 42589,9 feet South md 3845.6 feet East from tri angulation station fo .l. Thence K 49 0 35 , K, 618 feet; thence N 15049 ♦ w&gt; 750.9 feet; thence S SSOS? 1 w, 624,0 feet; tiience S 18° 48* 1, 855,8 feet to the point of starting. The above described boandari .es embrace an area of 10.9 acres. Ifega al Telah Hunting Lodge Beginning at a point 42194.6 feet South and 6820.7 feet West from tri angulation station Ko .l, Thence n 5 0 Z9' E, 1314.0 feet; thcjnce N 67 0 26* W, 1194.9 feet; thence S 82°43' W, 1252 ,9 feet; thence S 67 0 17» 1, 1580,5 feet more or less to the point of starting. The above described boundaries embrace an area of 40,0 acres.-2- iW ' Aaar Hunting Lodc^ Beginning at a point 17528.7 feet South and 5287.4 feet West from tri angulation station IJo.l. Thence S 7059- W. 646.9 feet; theme S 67&lt;»39' E, 1262.5 feet-, thence N 2 0 48' W. 975.7 feet; thence N 81 0 55' If, 1040.5 feet aore or less to the point of starting, me above described boundaries embrace en area of SO,5 acres. Bakhlr Garden Beginning at a point 6415,2 feet North and 6525,2 feet West of tri angulation station No.l. Thence N 82 o 27 t 50 w S, 1150.4 feet; thence H 5 o 57 , l0 n W, 1754.7 feet; thence S ?g o 23 ? 50 M W, 1095.1 feet; thence S /) O 0V 9 lO 1 ' S, 1567,1 feet more or less to the above sssntioned point of starting. The above described boundaries embrace an area of 42,2 acres. 3 akhir Race Track Beginning at a point 4871.8 feet Horth end 6057.9 feet West of tri angulation station No. 1, Thence N 74 o 04 ? W, 589 .1 feet; thence Southerly following the Westerly limit of the flat ground to s point S SPlS* E 11878.6 feet fro© the above mentioned point; thence N 75 o 20 , 20 w 1, 971.3 feet; thence N 4 o 09 T W, 11492,3 feet more or less to the point of starting. The above described boundaries embrace an area of 200 acres (approx.}^gll ag Area Begimln et e point on the beech to the South of the Tillage of Z,U.q mrked by a 3' iron pipe set in concrete slightly above high tide nerk, ssid point being 5895.9 feet South anfl 218S9.0 feet West of triangu- laticm station Ho.l. Thence S 84034' E. 8574.9 feet; thence S 84035' K, 7239.9 feat to the ruins of an old Mesjid; thence N IS 0 ^' E. 7656.91 feet; thence 12025' w, 4551.9 feet; thence N 3 0 52' E, 1734.7 feet; thence H 4PGZ' W, ^53..) feet to a point to the Southeast of Chulaib; thence N 28 o 01 W, 1&amp;S3.4, feet to a point laet of the Chulaib cemetery; ttenoe M ' w, 2883.5 faet; thence H 80015' W, 2771.5 feet to a point plus or minus 50 feet Northwest of a large walled in spring; thence following the water tunnel to a point S 69 0 21' w, 2709.0 feet from the aboTe; thence ^ 5 1500,9 i.'eet to s point on the bank of an Saat Waat irrigation dit&lt;di; thence following the ditch to a point S 77 o 07 t W, 3313,1 feet from above , this last point being on the beach to the Northwest ol the Northwest corner of a stone wall around Sheikh Hataad* s garden» said point being zaarked by a short length of 3 W pipe set in concrete at approximete high tide level; thence following the curves of the beach Southward to the above mentioned point of starting. The above described boundaries of the 2ellaq area ambrace approximately 4000 acres.A V i cmhTDmTiAL 0^ f No.496-S of 1936• British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire 9 the 10th July ^936. f''' \ 1 0 From - The Hon'ble The iolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf To - His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. Copy to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* Political Agent, Bahrain. I I i 'Li Memorandum Bahrain Petroleum .Company 1 s Mining Lease Article III. I enclose copy of a letter No.C/384, dated the 2nd July 1^36, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, and of its enclosure, and would be grateful for a rulin^ on the point at issue. I, personally, entirely agree with the inter pretation of the Article held by Captain Cole and Ur* Belgrave. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested . sfc ft, m-i* for Secretary to the Political%i ^ ! T 4 v Confidential, Ho.497 - S of 1935. British Residency &amp; Consulate•General| Busfiire, the 10th July 1935. To The iolitical Agent f Bahrain* Bahrain Oil • Survey of boundaries of municipal and private areas* Your impress Letter No.C/aSi-lO/li dated the 6th July i.936. 2* as survey was Joint I see no objection* Please torward to India Oifice and Government of India as well copy of your communication to Shaikh* sd* T* C* Fowle, Lieut *-Colonel* Political Resident in the irersian Gulf* Attested * Cfc ^n/7. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf#M i 36/2 ^ Tel e gram r 27 Vrom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Aishire. Repeated to H.M's Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by air mail Government of India, foreign and Political Department, Simla# no. 120 Dated 13th received 14th July 1935. Bahrain oil. Davis leaves for United Kingdom 18th July. Dale Mx will act as mangier during his absence or until further notice. Political h 1CONFIDENTIAL. C;/452-10/1.. ..'2 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to- Trie Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire. His Majesty's Secretary of■State for India, London. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated.. £. .1535». Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. s . Name and Date. Letter No:PA-24? of 17th August 1935 from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited.I I Uv tJUu* VUI n o- No. PA-247 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein, August 17, 1935, I Dear Sir: Will you please reserve for The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, 10 aores of uncultivated land as shown on the attached sketch. The corners of this land are described as follows: The Northeast corner is 54330,0 feet North and 83712.69 feet East from triangulation station No, 1, The Southeast corner is 33670.0 feet North and 23712.69 feet Sast frcn triangulation station No, 1. The Southwest corner is 33670,0 feet North and 23052.69 feet East from triangulation station No. 1. The Northwest corner is 34330.0 feet North and 23052.69 feet last from triangulation station No. 1. This land is required for the purpose of drilling and operating one or more water wells. Yours very truly, 0. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Sncl: * s «Confidential. f GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Depaktmknt, express letter £ Z, ? ,77 so despatched.] * From Political, Bahrain. To Resident^ , Bush:re. ti&lt;K C /453-10/1. Dated 22nd August IS3 5,. My Printed Letter C/45S August g2nd. Bahrain Oil. S. S-ai you please let me know If I can forward a copy of the Chief Local Representative's letter to the Bahrain Government. There does not appear to' be any objection to acceding to the Company f s request. Captain, Officiating Political Agent Bahrain.Qonffidentia,^. No .C /267 of 1936• Office of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp f Bahrain. 30th August 1936. o To The jc^litical Agent, Bahrain. Request of the Bahrain Petroleum Company for reservation of certain land. A iSl Memorandum. A Reference your Express Letter No.C/463-10/1 dated the 22nd August 1936. 2. Provided that the land in question does not fall within the areas reserved under Article II of the M i ning Lease, the Company^ request should be communicated to the Shaikh. This should be done by a self -contained letter. 3. Action may be taken by the Assistant Political Agent to save delay of reference to Karachi. sd. G.Loch, Lieut.-Colonel. Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested^ fur Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gull.86/2-xiii I- India Office P.^.. 7622/34, dated 21.18.54. r-r' 3.' do 7667/54, -do k f 3. „-do 7715/34, do 4. do 7806/54, do- 10°] J P.R. 1-4. File ? ltd. J.C. 3.1.55. ltd. T.G.F(owle). 8.1.35. • 5. Bahrain telegram No. 11, dated 9.1.35. P.R. Post copy to India Office and India ? As news of this tanker was reported in the Bahrain Diary, paragraph 157 of 1934, also in an India Office paper sent to us ana to Bahrain, the necessity for telegraphing is not apparent. ltd. J.G. 9.1.35. U.S . Copy by post to India Office s,nd Govt, of India. ltd. T.G.f(owle). 10.1.55. ISSUED P .L .No. 57-3, d. 11.1.35 to India Office and India ltd. W .l. Bagdad despatch Ko.275/13/34, dated 28.12.34. Bahrain X.L.Ko.G/5 - 10/1, dated 5.1.35. do despatch Iio.G/6 - lo/l, dated. 0.1.35 . do D.O.Ko.G/7 - 10/1, dated 5.1.35. 40t --X.L.N o* G/11 - 10/1, --do- 6.1.35. do despatch l^o.G/13 -10/1, dated 6.1.35. fa? XA 11 ■ S</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00027b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/661</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00027b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/661</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 86/2 XIII (C 61) Bahrain Oil’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-03T11:43:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (218 folios)</extent><extent>The volume’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The office notes at the end of the volume (ff 209-13) mirror the chronological arrangement. There is a subject index, arranged alphabetically, at the front of the volume (f 1A), the numbers of which correspond to the volume’s foliation.Many items of correspondence in the volume have pencil annotations, which refer to related items of correspondence found within other parts of the Bahrain Oil subject file. These annotations include the related confidential file number and the page number.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume is foliated from the first folio to the last folio, using pencil numbers written in the top-right corner of each recto. The foliation sequence switches to pagination between ff 171-186. Numbers written in red or blue pencil are part of the volume’s original filing system, and correspond to the office notes index at the end of the volume (ff 209-13). The following foliation anomalies occur: 1A, 1B, 1C and 1D; 187 and 187A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains letters, telegrams and memoranda relating to oil production in Bahrain, being undertaken by the Bahrain Petroleum Company (hereafter BAPCO). The volume is a direct continuation of ‘File 86/2 XII (C 54) Bahrain Oil’ (IOR/R/15/1/660). The principal correspondents in the volume are the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Fowle, the Political Agent in Bahrain, Lieutenant-Colonel Percy Gordon Loch, and BAPCO’s representatives in London (Hamilton Ballantyne) and Bahrain (Messrs Russell and Smith).The subjects covered by the volume are:Finalisation of BAPCO’s mining lease, and its signing on 29 December 1934 by the Ruler of Bahrain, Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah, and representatives of BAPCO. The volume includes a photostat [photocopy] of the original lease (in English and Arabic, folios 137-67) and a printed copy (English, folios 170-87), both of which contain a map (folios 164 and page 186 respectively) showing the 100,000 acres designated by BAPCO for the mining lease;Discussion over the status of land reserved by Shaikh Hamad and the ruling family for leisure purposes within the concession area (palace and gardens, hunting, racing), with a scientific survey of the areas in question (folios 191-99);Details relating to the transfer of oil from storage tanks on land to tankers off the coast of Sitrah Island, including proposals for procedures to be followed relating to oil in the sea-loading line and the discharge of ballast (folios 77-79, 81-84) and a diagrammatic plan (folio 50) of the tank installation, attached to a detailed description of the tank facilities (folios 43-49);The appointment of Mr Smith as Chief Local Representative for BAPCO (folio 119), pending Mr Russell’s planned absence from Bahrain;Speculation over the extent of oil exports from Bahrain, and Japan as a key market, with an anticipated five tanker visits during 1935 (folios 110-11);An abstract of accounts for oil measured in 1934 (folios 102-04), including details of the amount of oil produced and shipped, the amount of oil in storage, and royalties paid to Shaikh Hamad;BAPCO’s annual report for 1934 (folios 127-34), with details about the status of BAPCO’s wells, a description of the oil camp buildings, and a breakdown of the nationalities of the Company’s 589 employees;An application by BAPCO to reserve uncultivated land for the drilling of water wells, including a map of the area under consideration (folios 204-05).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sitrah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Bahrain</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum products</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00027b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>