<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000146_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T21:29:33.544Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram From, S (PAD) Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To. No. 589 Dated the 25th November 1845. Hannah the Vice-President of Standard Oil and Administrative Director of BAPCO informs me that Sir John Frazer, Elkington and Pattin^son may visit Bahrain early next month. During their stay in Bahrain he proposes he conduct them on a visit to Dhahran on which he has had invited me to accompany them. 2. I think that even if Minister Jeddah has no objection I should not repeat not accept the invitation since Dhahran is outside my charge and in Saudi Arabia. I therefore propose to decline unless you see to the contrary POLITICALTelegram From S(Pad). Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated H.M.'s Consul, Bushire. No.1024. Dated 26th received 27th November, 1945. I MPORTANT CTBLBX) Your telegram No.589 dated 25th November. Visit of Sir William Fraser and party. * 2. I do not know anything about ,, proposal ,, . What is its nature ? LSI PRIOR =Telegram S(Pad). From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Kuwait. Repeated H.M's Consul, Bushire. No. 591. Bated 27th November, 1945. I MPORTA NT. Following for Resident. Your telegram 1024 of the 26th November. 2. I have no information other than already- telegraphed in my No.539 dated 25th November, 1945, which is:- (a) that I hear from Hannah that Fraser and party propose visiting Bahrain (b) that he proposes to conduct them to Dhahran returning the same day. 3. Grateful for confirmation that it would be advisable for me to decline Hannah*s invitation to join in (b). LB I POLITICAL =Telegram From To No. 1029. Dated 29th received 30th November, 1945. Following f-rflfciResident. I think it would probably be best if you refused invitation. 2. For your information Sir William Fraser asked me how he could call on you without appearing discourteous to his American hosts. I said I would reply later but intend to suggest he pays visit when leaving Bahrain. Perhaps simplest p|an would be for you to ask him to a meal on his v return from Dhahran. He has a delicate stomach and usually drinks Malvern water. = POLITICAL = S (Pad). Political Agent, Kuwait.!. Political Agent, Bahrain.&amp; Arabian American OilCompanv J . M AC PH ER SON VICE PRESIDENT AND RESIDENT ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICER D H A H R A N Saudi Arabia December 4, 1945 Colonel A. C. Galloway Political Agent Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf Dear Colonel Galloways May I express to you ray appreciation for the invitation you extended me to be with you Sunday night in company with Sir William Fraser and his party. As probably Mr. Hanna explained, our plane landed here at Dhahran prior to going back to Bahrein and I, therefore, did not go back to Bahrein. I was also sorry that you were unable to accept our invitation to come to Arabia with this party. May I now extend you a personal invitation to visit me any time you wish. If you will let me know a little in advance so I can get permission, as I had already done in the event you had come over, it would be beneficial. Another subject I hope Mr. Don Hanna mentioned to you was regarding the two launches. I was greatly humiliated to find that the two boats I thought were in running order had been robbed of their spare parts. We have two launches in good shape except for this condition and to say that I was quite embarrassed after Mr. Hanna said we would send them over for a few days running around, is putting it mildly. I have explained the circumstances to Mr. Hanna. I am watching this boat situation and as soon as I have one of these boats in running order I will see that it is sent over to you and that someone stays with you to show you have it runs.D.O. No. C/1129 The 22nd of December, 1945 Thank you very much for your letter of the 4th of December. I was sorry |not to have seen you and hope one day to accept your kind invitation to visit Dhahran. I had thought of suggesting round about the New Year, but I now find that I have official functions to perform. As regards th? boat, I am sorry that you and Don Hanna have been put to so much trouble.&gt; I shall be glad to see it when it can b$ sent over. I enclose a pass for some Christmas cheer which I hope you will find of use. The compliments of the Season. Yours sincerely. J. MacPherson, Esq., Vice-President and Resident Administrative Officer, Dhahran. Saudi Arabia.C/1160. 0 I The 31^c of peconber, 1945. My dear MacPherson, I received your Christmas Greetings with great pleasure and also those of Mr. Ohliger and Mr. Smith. It was very kind of you to send me the fruit and other things which are most acceptable * . and I thank you. The Best of New Years. yours sincerely, J. MacPherson, Esq., VlC Resld^ e M^35 r ‘‘ tlve _ 01 ‘^ c * r » Dhahran. Saudi Arabia.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000146_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/883</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000146</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/883</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 39/13 (10/13) Visit of APOC officials to Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-22T20:58:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folio 11. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Political Agent at Kuwait and the Political Resident at Bahrain, concerning visits of Anglo-Persian Oil Company (APOC) representatives to Bahrain. The file also include a letter from J MacPherson, Vice-President of Arabian American Oil Company, declining the Agent's invitation to Bahrain and sending season's greetings on his and on two colleagues' business cards, enclosed.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company, Vice-President</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000146#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>