<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000206_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T09:44:49.839Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">''WBRM?**’3. Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to:— . / THE SECRETARY, Air Ministry, Adastral House. Kingsway, London, W.C.2. and the following number quoted :— '250 AIR MINISTRY, '‘LONDON, W.C.2. 'S.29948/S.6. /o// January, 1935. Sir Y/ith reference to India Office letter No.P.Z.7748/34 of the 24th December, 1334, I am commanded by the Air Council to acquaint you, for the information of Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare, that as the fire engine available for disposal at the Muscat Coal Depot would not be effective against a petrol fire, they do not desire to take advantage of the offer of the Government of India. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under-Sec ret ary of State, Political Department, India Office, S.W.l.i Stores. S 7748 L Nos 180-N. ; Government of India. J i 7 Y DEPARTMENT. NEW DELHI, the 27th November 1934. THE SECRETARY, Political Department, India Office. Royal India n Navy c oal depo t at Muscat . With reference to the correspondence ending with Navy Department letter No: 80-N., dated the 1st November 1934, on the above subject, I am directed to state that there is a fire engine at the Mus-cat coal depot belonging to the Royal Indian Navy which was sent there from Bombay in 1929. As this* engine is no longer required owing to the closing down of that depot, I am to request that an enquiry may be made of the Air Ministry as to whether they would be prepared to purchase the engine for Rs. 200/-. M.P.C.\w Sto res • NSW DELHI, the' 1 st November 1934. TO THE SECRETARY, Political Department, India Office* Royal Ind ian ftavy c o al depot at Muscat /yO 1 Sir, 'with reference to the correspondence ending with. Secretary of State*s express letter (Air Mail) No: P*Z#5296/34, dated'the 17th August 1934, I am directed to forward a copy of the orders (Navy Department letter No: 75-N., dated the 30th October 1934) issued by the Government of India on the above subject, and from which it will be seen that the Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy, has been authorised to hand over the administrative and financial, control of the remaining coal depot building at Muscat to the Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq* I am, Dir, Your most,obedient servant, Asstt. Decy-/to 4S ^he Govt, of India. fee i A ^ td M.P.C® &amp; Stores. NAVY DEPARTMENT* NEW DELHI, the 30th October 1934. No: 75-N* Government of India* TO THE FUG OFFICER COMMANDING, Royal Indian Nav} r . Roya l Indian N avy coal d epot at Muscat , Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with Marine Department memorandum No: 644-M*, dated the 27th June 1934, I am directed to convey the sanction of the Government of India to the closing down of the Royal Indian N&amp;vy Coal depot at Musc&amp;u, with effect from the 1st November 1934, and to the abolition from that date of the following posts: maintained at the depot 2* Sanction is also accorded to the discontinuance, with effect from the 1st September 1934, of the allowance oi Ks* 25/* per mensem hitherto paid from the Royal Indian iMavy Estimates to the Agency Clerk at Muscat, 3 . The site on which the coal depot stands has been trans ferred to the Air Ministry, and It is understood that the open coal sheds there have been demolished to make room for a. petrol store which the Royal Air Force authorities propose erect on the site of the depot. The administrative and financial control of the remaining coal depot building should be handed over to the Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq, 4, Marine Regulations, India, Volume i, will be amended in One fire engine and coal txndal* One peon. One night watchman. due course. I am, Gir, lour most obedient servant, Sd/~ J.t.B. GARDNER, stt, &amp;ecy. to the Govt, of India. Military Accountant General, the Director of Army Audit and the Controller of Naval Accounts. Sd/- J.W.3. GARDNER, Asstt. Secy, to the Govt, of India.X \ Tel. No. Holborn 3434. Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to :— THE SECRETARY, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, W.C. 2. and the following number quoted :— ^ '.29948/S.6 . V /^August, 1934. IQ34' J Sir I am commanded by the Air Council to refer to your letter P.Z•5050/34 of the 4th August and to previous correspondence on the subject of the Muscat Coal Depot, and to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that they have been informed by the Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in 'Iraq, that the open coal sheds at Muscat have been demolished to make room for the proposed petrol store. The only remaining building is in a state of extreme dilapidation^having no roof ? and the walls being on the point of collapse. prepared to accede to any instructions which the Government of India may desire to issue regarding the disposal of this building. I am to add that the Air Council are fully I am, Sir Your obedient Servant The Under Secretary of State India Office, S.W.l.FILE COPY FRB/DIA- (52 grou .ps) CJ£JL,I*E.JJ.JLB—Q_Z From Ll (COPIES CIRCULATED) Government of India, Army Department, to Secretary of State for India, Dated Simla, 3rd August, 1934c Received 3rd August, 1934, 6 pdn, 7 (Ap s SECRET V.7T] /uJL 50• , j 278 ’ fo.) iSM-a-bi. ^ rkrtlft Arwiv /*/M / XXX liSS&amp;o Afmy-DeparlMQt, 1 Reference Foreign and Political Department®a telegram dated June 2n d, 1304, Maskat coal depot. While there Is no objection from Royal Indian Marine point of view to the Air Ministry proposal that the coal depot !-&gt;ul!.dlngB (*? need not he) maintained by them, we consider charge of buildings should be handled (sle, handed\ back to the Public Works Department independent Persian Gulf J^goSfd’T, Bushire. Please telegraph urgently whether the Air Ministry have any objection to this course.indexed CONFIDENTIAL. No. 622-S of 1934. JjiDIA DIBEG' A O ( H v vv - * | The Hon’ble the Political Re^i^iS^iglthe Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to V.— v ' / 1. His Maje sty's Secretary of State for India, London. 2® The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 3. The Air Officer Commanding,British Forces in 'Iraq, Bagdad. 4. The Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf,H.M.S.'Shoreham'. 5. The Senior Officer,Persian Gulf,H.M.S.'Bideford' and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, Name and Date. Subject. Mokalla Coal Depot. Letter No•C/165 of 27th June 1934 from the Political Agent, Muscat, with enclosure.coflsiPffireiAii P. / O ^ L. No C/165 of 1934• .Bps Lon^i^teJ Political Agency &amp; H Muscat, 27th June 1934* ]?ram Major C.E.U* Bremner. M.C, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat • To The Hon f hie the P 0 litical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Subject:- Mokalla Coal Repot “* *' i Sir, In continuation of my Ho C/148 dated 12th June 1934, I have the honour toenclose herewith a copy of the translation of a letter received from His Highness the Sultan on this subject. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Major, Sd/- C.E.U. Bremner Political Agent 8c H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.&amp; 0 Translation of a letter dated 3rd Babi al avnRal (l6th June 1934) fron His Highness Saiyid Said hin Taisur Sultan of Muscat and Oman, to Major C.E.U. Breraner, M.C. Political 1934 I state ttet ^ith great pleasure I accord permission to the Koyal Air Force of my friend the British GoYernment to use petrol store at Mokalla *?hich you propose to 'build near the Coal Depot in the same manner as the Coal Depot was used by the British Davy• Agent, Muscat, A*C. U,E.v INDEXED y M/m. (D ® DECYPHER OF TELES RAM. Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India repeating telegram addressed to Foreign Secretary to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department 0 Dated Bahrein, 12th June, 1934, Received 1 p 0 m 0 , 12th June, 1934„ T/l38o Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of 3tu.te for India, Air Officer Commanding, Baghdad, Senior Baval Officer, Persian Gulf. Tour telegram of the 2nd instant, 1304 o Muscat coal depot. Sultan of Maskat has informed Political Agent verbally that he has no objection to continuance of free use of concession to Royal Air Force. Political Agent is obtaining written confirmation.oXED UP To Sir, uak r I &gt; / rARY DEPT ' jpcirro $ »v-.i . ) U i r; n 37 5 R fils. copyT-fg, Gonfidenti al» No*5l4.-M^ vernment of India* DEPARTMENT, P^* R I N E Simla, the 17th May 1934. The Secretary, Military Department, India Office Subject:- Muscat Goal Depot* a y y &gt; ‘ / I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending with Marine Department letter N0.384-M, dated the 12th April 1934, on the above subject, and to enquire when the Grovemment of India may expect to receive a reply to their letter No*270-M, dated the 15th March 1934, I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Asstt.Secretary to the G-ovt. of India. MiINDEXED SECRET PJM/AW, (83 groups) 3304 PSCYPHBH OF TBLSGKAM , Prom Goyernment of India, Foreign and Political Department; to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and repeated by former to Persian Gulf; sent to (sic) Secretary of State for India* India Office air mail letter No # P* z« 3218« 34, 18 inst (sic)* Muscat coal depot&lt; Government of India have no objection to use of site being transferred to Air Ministry from 6 inst, f but understand that ooal stacks will not be cleared till August, 1934. It is presumed that employment of depot as oil fuel store furnishes sufficient pretext for continuance of concession should question ever be raised (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, 2nd June, 1934, Received 2nd Oune, 1934, 6,40 p.m. Dated Secretary of State for India XXX :V304. Addressed to Political Resident in the (reference paragraph Ho. 12 of Brenner* August, 1933)* Please confirm. ? s letter Dc.K-lO, 15th - «■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■INDEXED MINISTRY, 1 1934 ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, W.C.2. My dear Laithwaite, 22nd May, 1934. With reference to our telephone conversation this afternoon on the subject of the Muscat Goal Depot, I enclose herewith a copy of the telegram from Air Officer Commanding, Iraq to which I referred together with draft of one which we propose sending in reply. We would be grateful if you could send a telegram to India explaining v/hy an early decision is required and requesting that the decision should be communicated to the Political Resident by telegram. you concur, as I will not despatch our telegram until I hear from you. Will you please let me know by telephone whether Yours sincerely J.G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.To:- 3»Q« t Iraq. From:- Air Ministry. Your Z. 168 of 19/5. Government oi India have been informed hy India Office in letter dated 18/5 and sent air mail that Air Ministry wish to take over coal depot site so long as it is a free concession and buildings need not be maintained and in that event would undertake any administrative and financial responsibility which might be involved. Government of India have been requested if Air Ministry proposal is acceptable to take steps to hand over site to you. Gopy of letter referred to being sent to you next mall and a copy has been sent to Foli*ical Resldent.wWi ■whew 'UDvennweiit ..n .In Is will , n.,i1 nubt eqinitiUHt’UaUu. /Viruj* ' : v Registry (Telegrams ). Please despatch the above in cipher. F.0.3 • 22/5/34 . Copies to:- B.D.O.I. F .0.3 . 1 «D. P .0 . 8.6 Time of origin:-(•2334) VVt. 28381—163? 23,500 4/31 T.S. 1 18 A.M. 759 R.A.F. Form ARt Serial No SECRET. F CYPHER MESSAGE. This message must be circulated under cover and must be locked up when not in use. It must not be placed on any but a secret file and all drafts or copies of the original which may have been retained by the originator must be burnt on receipt of this copy. This message must not be referred to in clear or code messages or in any RC non-secret correspondence. To— Air Ministry. Date Time of From— Headquarters, British Forces, Iraq System Time of Origin 1230) Time of Receipt 2251) 20.5.34. My ^.11004/10 April 30th. Party arriving Muscat June 6th to carry out petrol store on asbestos coal depot same time. Request authority may be granted as soon as possible for R.A.F. to take over depot in order that work of building new petrol store may commence in June. Registry (Telegrams) Copies to:- D.D.0.I.(3) action copy. N© action is to be taken on this telegram without reference to the holder of the action copy. GMT.) Z.158 19/5. /X INDEXED -ftocL. Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to:— THE SECRETARY, Tel. No. Holborn 3434. 3218 | 1954 | Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, W.C. 2. and the following number quoted :— S.29948/S.6 1 2. May, 1934. V. Sir, I am commanded by the Air Council to refer to India Office letters P.2.2235/34 and P.2.2875/34 dated the 20th April and 2nd May, 1934, respectively, forwarding copies of correspondence from the Government of India on the subject of the Muscat Coal Depot and to acquaint you, for the information of Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare, that on the assumption that the Coal Depot will continue to oe a free concession and that the existing buildings need not be maintained, the Air Ministry will be glad to take over the site. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office and Admiralty. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.lIft / f f 1 [ £ j '/ 1 i -3 CONFIDENTIAL.*^ fir)-, dJO $ yy^ Ai/ * j. TO 0 : A&gt; 287 ^ V j q 3 /l Grovfrnment of India. MARINS DEPARTMENT. New Delhi, the 12 th April 1934. :/.k The Secretary, Military Department, India Office. Subject.- Muscat coal depot. Sir, In continuation of Marine Department letter No. 270-M, dated the 15th March 1934, I am directed to forward a copy of the marginally noted Letter from the Air Officer Commanding, Iraq, No. S.11004/10, dated the 26th February 1934. Letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf No e C/132 of 1934, dated the 28th March 1934^ communications that have since been received on the above subject. L r I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3 /rC^. r*y S A-*, ^ &amp;-£po~ Cp(. Secy. ^ K 0, ^ N. So overnment of India.COPY. Reference; a 110 04/10. 3EC Air Headquarters. British Forces in f Iraq Hinaidi. 26th February— v | &gt; n t Muscat, 2875 ; i 9 5 4 | Sir, I have the honour to refer to my letter Ho*Al004/10, dated llth January, 1934, and to state that it would be much appreciated if you would let me ivnow as soon as possible whether you agree with the recommendations maae therein* 2. It is understood that the Goal Depot has been in the past a free concession to the Navy from the Muscat Government and Major Brember suggested in paragraph of his letter No.K/10 of 1933 dated 15th August 193o, that Hie employmait of the Depot as an oil or fuel store would furnish a sufficient pretext for the continuance the concession should the question ever be raised. of 3. Musca t on th e her and As I consider the present fuel and oil store at is unsatisfactory I propose to build s new one site of the Goal Depot m close proximity to the waterside, provided you -^ ?i on s tha t Hi e from the Navy* agree Royal Air Force should wi th rny r ec Oi.rni en da • take over this site 4 # I am anxious to communicate with the henior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf on this subject as early as possible in order to make arrangements lor taking over the Depot from the Navy and trust that yon v/ill be able to arrange with the India Government 1 or trie si ue to be taken over by Hie Royal Air Force as soon as po ssibl e. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d* G.S. Burnett. Air Vice-Marshal, Commanding British Forces in*Iraq. The Honible Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRS*I Confidential, * t •S' No.C/132 of 1934. Office of the political Resident in the Persian Crulf, Camp, BAHRAIN. 28th March 1934. From - To The Hon^le Lieut.-Colonel T.O.FoYjLe y C.B.E., political Resident in the Persian (pulf^, ^ ^ 2875 ' The Air Officer Commanding, f Iraq^ Command, Baghdad Sir, With reference to correspondence ending Bith your letter No.S.11004/10, dated the 26th February 1934, I have the honour to state that as far as I am concerned I agree with, your recommendation that the site of the existing coal depot at Muscat should be transferred to the Royal Air Force. 2. A copy of your letter No.S.11004/10, dated the lath January 1934, was forwarded to the Sovemment of India, to vJiom as well as to the Senior Naval Officer I am forwarding a copy of your letter under reference and my reply. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- T.C.Fowls, Lieut.Colonel, political Resident in the Persian Gulf.INDEXED Stores TO THIS SECRETARY, :r V' ^ Military Department, India Office touacat floal UsEoi. V’ 'X \ x V Si r, / I am directed to say that the Government of India have under consideration the abolition of the Muscat Coal Depot, and, in this connection, I am to forward a copy of the IT correspondence cited on the margin * Letter to the Hon f ble the Political) 0 r ,, . , x x , r Resident in the Persian Gulf No. ) lhe coal ^Pot at Muscat D.2775-N/33, dated the 18th July 1933* Express letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf No• 1905-S., dated the 14th December 1933, and enclosures. Endorsement from the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf N 0 3 167-S., dated the 10th February 1934 and enclosure. is no longer required for Royal Indian Marine purposes, and both His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, and the poli tical authorities, have no objection to its being closed down. Before arriving at a decision in the matter, however, the Government of India would be glad to know whether, in view of what is stated in letters Nos. S.11004/10, dated the 22nd September 1933 and the 11th January 1934, from the Air Officer Commanding, ‘Iraq Command, the Air Ministry desire to retain the depot. In the event of their so desiring, it would be necessary for them to undertake full administrative and financial responsibilities for the depot. 3© Should the Secretary of State see no objection, I am to request that the Air Ministry may be approached in the matter and their views communicated to this Department at a2 very early date. I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant, i.}, Lieut.-Colonel, Deputy Secretary to the Dovt. of India. • P.C.Copy of a letter No. D.2775-N/33, dated the 18th July 1933, from the Deputy Secretary to the G-overnment of India, in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, to the Honlble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Question of the abolition of the Goal Depot at Muscat. I am directed to inform you that in consequence of the withdrawal of H.M.S. 'Triad'*, the only coal burning subsidised naval vessel in the Persian Gulf, the Marine Department have intimated that the Goal Depot at Muscat is no longer required for naval purposes. Unless its retention is justifiable on political grounds in which case full administrative and financial responsibilities will probably have to be undertaken by this Department, it is therefore proposed to abolish it. 1 am to request that the Government of India may kindly be furnished with your views on the matter. Gopy to Army (Marine) Department.4 C ONFIDENTIAL Government of India* fl W£S S_L, SH ,SB* From - Resident, Bushire* To - Government of India, New Delhi* Repeated to Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, (with the request Air Officer Commanding, 'Iraq Oommand( that should (they have any (further comments (make these should (be conveyed to (me as soon as (possible* Political Agent, Muscat* No*1905-5 of 1933* Dated 14th December 1933* Reference Government of India, Foreign and Political Department Express Letter No*F*199-n/ 33, dated the 1st December 1933* 2. I enclose copies of the marginally noted correspondence* 1* Letter No*K/10 of 15th August 1933 from the Political Agent, Muscat* 2* Letter No.3.11004/10,dated the 22nd September 1933, from the Air Officer Commanding, 'Iraq Command* 3. Letter No.54/246, dated the 6th December 1933, from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division. 3* The Political Agent, Muscat, considers the retention of thq uoal Depot desirable chiefly on the following grounds: (a) To maintain a permanent pied-a-terre in Muscat territory in the event of unforeseen emergencies* (b) To afford a convenient depot for Royal Air Force Stores, fuel, etc. in anticipation of the opening up of the Basrah-Aden Air Route* With regard to (a)* Major Bremner refers to the possibility of the evacuation of henjam. Should this occur, however, the alternative Naval Station on the Arabian Coast will not be at Muscat, and I think any other possible emergency is too un certain to be taken into consideration. With regard to (b). Seeparagraph 5 below.\ 4. The Senior Naval Officer in his letter of 6th December concurs with (Jolonel Loch, who has addressed him in his capacity as Acting Political Kesident, that some permanent P%d-a-terre should be maintained for H*M*Services in Muscat, buo does not feel justified in recormiending any expenditure from Naval funds towards the up-keep of the buildings, or share in the maintenance of a watchman, and is of opinion that the use of the buildings will be confined solely to the Koyal Air J^’orce* 5* The Air Officer Commanding, f Iraq Command, would like the Coal Depot to be kept up and is prepared to recommend that Rs*200^ per annum should be paid from Koyal Air Force funds, but would like the buildings to remain the responsibility of the Navy* 6* Brefly^ the situation is as follows I do not consider that the retention of the Coal Depot is justifiable on political grounds and therefore I am not of opinion that Item (ii) should be paid by the Political Department - vide paragraph 14 of the Political Agent, Muscats letter - when the Depot is abolished. The Naval authorities are apparently not prepared to incur any expenditure from their funds towards its retention, and it appears that the only authority really interested in the maintenance of the Depot is the Royal Air Force, who are willing to spend Rs*200/~per annum* This is i sufficient for a watchman but not of course for the annual repairs to the buildings which come to about Rs*l,400/-* 7# I suggest therefore that,from the point of view of the Government of India's responsibility, the Coal Depot be abolished. $d/- T.C.Powle, Lieut.-colonel. Political Resident in the Persian liulf. Attested* Sd/-A*C. Stewart, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.7 (%1) 0 Co m FIDSNTIAL. No*K/10 of 1933o Office of the political Agent,muscat On Kecess* KiHarney notel, Karachi ♦ 15th August 1933. Politficai Agent and n.B.M.'s Consul, Muscat. With reference to your letter no. 937-S, dated 28th July 1933 forwarding Crovernment of India letter No.D- 2775-N/33, dated 18th July 1933, I have the honour to submit my views herewith. 2. Although the Makalla Coal Depot is no longer required for the purposes of a naval coaling station, I consider its retention desirable on the following grounds (a) To maintain a permanent pied-a-terre in muscat territory in the event of unforeseen emergencies. (b) To afford a convenient depot for R.A.F.stores, fuel, etc. in anticipation of the opening up of the B.asra-Aden 3. Although it is at present impossible to forecast future eventualities and policy, the possibility of the evacuation of Henjam is a point for consideration. 4. Should certain factors contribute to the desirability of such a course of action, then 1 understand that no other suitable base exists in the Eastern area of the Persian Gulf and that Muscat, remote as it is, would furnish the next best substitute. 5. In such eventuality whether the Makalla Depot(at muscat) or the establishment of a barge depot in Matrah Bay would be best, is a technical question which can only be answered by the competent Naval authorities. 6. From a persual of the Senior Naval Officer's confidential memorandum No.15B/150/45/8, dated 17th August 1929 to the address of the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, it would appear that the Matrah Bay scheme is the more favoured project. iJrUil Aj u # v-J X UIl w JL UrtJjUOII) X • f Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:-Question of the abolition of the Coal Depot at Makalla. Sir t Air Route.14 7* None the less, should emergency arise it would seem likely that a land depot for stores might also be required* Matran does not afford facilities for such purposes and Makalla appears to be uhe only alternative* 8* To give up the present Makalla Station and later to have to seek for a renewal of the concession, might lead to possiole difficulties (and delays) with the Muscat (rovernment* £ 9. Should the opening up of the Basrah-Aden Air Koute be speeded up in the near future, it seems probable that Muscat, being the last point of contract with 'civilization' in the Persian (iulf area, will be developed as an advanced base for stores from aasrah. 10. Aviation fuel for K.A.F.Flying Boats is at present stored in the Makalla Depot and should the supposition in paragraph 9 materialise, this and other storage will presumably be greatly developed. 11. For the foregoing reasons therefore 1 am of the opinion that whilst its function as a cealing station will cease to exist, it is desirable to retain the Makalla Depot against emergency* 12* I consider it unlikely that the Muscat Grovernment would contemplate a cancellation of the existing concession if Makalla ceases to be used as a coaling depot, but its employment as an oil fuel store, even if nominal, would furnish a sufficient pretext for the continuance of the concession should the question ever be raised* 13. The cost of maintenance at present is Rs*792/-per annum Minpx comprising: (i) Pay of clerk (ii) Pay of peon (iii) Pay of watchman, whilst small annual sums are required for maintaining the depot pier and sheds in good order*A Item(i)would automatically disappear whilst item(iii) would presumably be found by the Departments using the depot* I consider however that item(ii) should stand in order to maintain ^ the Political Agent's political control over the Depot in view a vis of dealings via/the Muscat G-overnment. 15. Petty annual repairs would also be found by the Departments using the Depot, thus leaving an annual sum of Rs*300/- to be found by the Government of India. 16. To retain this pied-a-terre at such infinitesimal cost would I consider be politically desirable and for the foregoing reasons I recommend for the present the retention of Makalla. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- O.E.U. Bremner, Major, Political Agent and H.B.M's. Consul,Muscat.Copy Reference S.11004/10• SE0RET&gt; Air headquarters, f Iraq Command, Royal Air Force, ninaidi 22nd September 1933* &gt; Question of the abolition of the coal depot at Muscat* Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter wo*117Q-s, Ox 1933, dated 5th September 1933, dealing with the question of the Uoal Depot at Muscat* 2* I concur entirely with the Political views set forth by the Political Agent, Muscat, and I presume that the Naval autnorities will not give up the site for the political reasons mentioned in Major Bremner’s letter* 3. The R.A.F.petrol store is a necessity for us,and I am willing to agree that this shall be maintained and kept up in the normal manner by the Chief Engineer, 'Iraq Qommand. 4. With regard to the watchman, 1 think the cost of this man s services should be shared between the K.A. i'.and the Navy,but i am prepared to recommend that we should pay Rs.200/-per annum from R.A.F. funds., 5. As Major Bremner points out in his letter, it is desirable that the Navy should retain their buildings in the Depot,as they may be required in the future for storage of naval supplies, and therefore, 1 think that they should remain the responsibility of ■ the Wavy* The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian 4 Culf, The Residency, Bushire* I have, etc*, Sd/- A. D. Cunn ingham, Air commodore, for Air Vice Marshal, Comnanding *iraq Command.Copy * Confidential * M*M.S. 'Shoreham', ' At Kak Khasaab Fid# 54/246. 6th December 1933. /-&gt; Sir, With reference to your letter of 4th October 1933 (No.1277-3), i have the honour to inform you that i concur that it is desirable that some permanent pied-a-terre should be maintained for jf H.M.Services in Muscat, in case any future need should arise. 2. The existing Royal Indian Marine coal stock, however, is at present being utilised by h.M.S. ,, Ormonde tt by arrangement with the Admiralty, in order to dispose of it. When it is exhausted (or when M 0rmonde H requires no further supplies) there will be no further Naval need for the coal sheds and it is doubtful if they would be required again even if a Naval Depot at Muscat were found necessary in the future. In consequence, their use will be confined solely tc the Royal Air Force. 3. In these circumstances 1 do not feel that i should be justified in recommending any expenditure from Naval funds towards ft keeping the buildings in repair or sharing in the maintenance of a watchman. I have etc., Sd/- J . V .(Jreagh. (Jap tain. Senior Naval Officer, Persian (iulf The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian (iulf, Bushir e./ zmivmuL No.I67-S. wmmuk* The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf presents his compliments to The Foreign Secretary, Governnent of India, w ew Delhi* The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned (nraiHHfcx document. British Consulate-General, Bushire. Dated 10th February 1934* Reference to previous correspondence: Express letter No*1905-S, dated 14th December 1933* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject* No.S.11004/10, dated the 11th Coal Depot at Muscat* January 1934 from Air Head quarters, ’Iraq.9 * Reference Air Headquarters, •Iraq Command, 3.11004/10* Hinaidi. 11th January 1934. SEOBEI. Question of the retention of the ji Coal Depot at Muscat. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter N0.19Q5-S of 1933 dated 14th December 1933. 2. I agree with the views of the Senior Naval Officer and Colonel Loch given in paragraph 4 of your letter and aankH consider that the site of the Coal Store should be retained for the Royal Air Force for possible future requirements. 3. The Royal Air Force is not prepared to pay for the upkeep of the buildings on the site of the Coal Depot. Therefore, it is recommended that the buildings be left as they are at present and no expense devoted to their upkeep. 4. It is also recommended that the responsibility for the Depot be transferred from the Indian Grovernment to the Royal Air Force. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant, Sd: C.S.Burnett, Air Yice-Marshall, Commanding f Iraq Command. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, The Residency, BUSHIREFILE COPY 6 COMflP.iii'.Xi -,L. Government of India. EXP:R£3bS LETTER* Prom - Resident, Bush ire. To - Government of India, New Delhi. Repeated to senior Naval Officev Persian Gulf. )with the jreguest that Air Officer Gonimanding, *Irag Command. shoul3- they have any further comments to ma^e these )shouii he jconveyed to me as soon as possible. political agent, Muscat. T ~o• 1905 -S of 1933. Dated 14th December 1933. Reference Government oi India, foreign and Political Department Jxpress Letter No.P. 19 9-N/33, dated the 1st December 1933. 2. I enclose copies of the marginally noted corres- 1. Let ter No.K/lO ol 15 th August 1933 from the roli ti- ; Don* cal agent, Muscat. . 2. Letter No. S. 11004/10 dated the 22na September 1933 j irom the Air 01 Nicer Commanding, ^rag Command. i derne* 3. letter No. 54/246 dated the 6 th December 1933 from ; the Senior Naval Of fi cer, Pe rsi an Gulf jJivis ion. ; 3. The Political agent, Muscat, considers the retention oi' the Coal Ifepot desirable chiefly on the following grounds: (a) To maintain a permanent pied-a-terre in Muscat territory in the event of unforeseen emergencies. (Id) To afford a convenient depot for fioyal ^ir force stoics, -.uei, etc. in anticipation or the opening up ENCLOSURE IN !) INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S | Letter 5 | It J*1914 JAM. 1S34V of the Basrah-Aden Air Boute. With regard to (a), Major Breinner refers to the possibility of me evacuation of Henjaiii* onould this occur, however, the alternative Naval Station on the Arabian Coast will not be at Muscat, and 1 think any other possible emergency is too un certain to be taKen into consideration. With regard to (b). See paragraph 5 oeiow. 4. The Senior Naval Officer in his letter ol 6th December concurs with Colonel Loch, who has addressed him in his capacity as Acting Political Besident, that some permanent p^i^d-a-terre should be maintained for H.i . Service s in Muscat, but does not feel Justified in recommending any expenditure from Naval funds towards the up-keep of the buildings, or share in the maintenance of a watchman, and is of opinion that one use of the buildings will be confined solely to the Boyal air force. 5. The Air Officer Commanding, ’Iraq Command, would like the Coal Depot to be kept up and is prepared to recommend that Rs.SOO/- per annum should be paid from Boyal Air force funds, but would lime the buildings to remain the responsibility of the Navy. 6. Briefly, the situation is as follows: I do not consider that the retention of the Coal Depot is Justifiable on political grounds and therefore 1 am not of opinion that item ( ii) should be paid by the Political Department - vide paragraph 14 of the Political Agent, Muscat* s letter - when the Depot is abolished. The Naval authorities are apparently not prepared to incur any expenditure from their funds towards its retention, and it appears that the only authority really interested/interested in the maintenance of the jJepot is the Boyal xiir fbrce, i^ho are willing to spend ^s. 200/- per annum. This is sufiicient for a watchman hut not of course for the annual repairs to the buildings which come to about Rs* 1,400/-. 7. I suggest therefore that, from the point of view of the Government of India's responsibility, the Goal Depot be abolished. 3d/- T. 0. Towle .ut. -uoionel Political xtesident in the Persian Gulf, At tested for Secretary to the Political Pesident in the Persian Gull.No.K /10 of 1933 Copy. dopfidential. Office of the Political .agent, Muscat* On Eecess. KiHarney Hotel, Karachi, 15th August, 1933, Prom - Maj or 0,E. U, Bremne r , I • G . , Political Agent and H.B.I/. *s Consul, h us ca t • To - The Hon* Die Lt.-Colonel G.Loch, i.a., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Suhject:-Question of the abolition of the Coal Depot at Taka11a. Sir, With reference to your letter io.957-3 dated 28th July 1933 forwarding Government of India letter No.D. 2775-N/33 dated 18th July 1933, I have the honour to submit my views herewith. 2. ’ Although the Makalla Coal Depot is no longer required for the purposes of a naval coaling station, I consider its retention desirable on the following grounds;- (a) To maintain a permanent pled-a-terre in Muscat territory in the event or unforeseen emergencies. (b) To afford a convenient depot for B.A.P. stores, fuel, etc. in anticipation of the opening up of the Basra-Aden ^ir Boute. ^ 3. although it is at present impossible to forecast future eventualities and policy, the possibility of the evacuation of Henjam is a point for consideration. 4. Should certain factors contribute to the desirability of such a course of action, then I understand/ &gt;understand that no other suitable base exists in the Eastern area of the Persian Gulf and that Muscat, remote as it is, would furnish the next best subs ti tute. 5. In such eventuality whether the Makalla Depot (at Muscat) or the establishment of a barge depot in Katrail Bay would be best, is a technical question which can only be answered by the competent Naval authorities. 6. Prom a per^il of the Senior Naval Officer’s confidential memorandum No. 15B/15G/45/8 dated 17th August 1929 to the address of the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, it would appear that the latran Bay scheme is the more favoured project. 7. None the less, should emergency arise it would seem likely that a land depot for stores might also be required. Matrah does not afford facilities for such purposes and MaKalla appears to be the only alternative. 8. To give up the present Mamalla Station and later to have to seek for a renewal of the concession, might lead to possible difficulties (and delays) with the Muscat Government. 9. Should the opening up of the Basrah-.aden Air Route be speeded up in the near future, it seems probable that Muscat, being the last point of contract with 'civilization** in the Persian Gulf area, will be developed as an advanced base ibr stores from Basrah. 10. Aviation fuel for R. A. F. Plying Boats is at present stored in the Makalla Depot and should the supposition in paragraph 9 materialise, this and o the r/other storage will presumably he greatly developed. 11. For the foregoing reasons therefore I am of the opinion that whilfst its function as a coaling station will cease to exist, it is desirable to retain the lakalla Depot against emergency. 12. I consider it unlixely that the Muscat Government would contemplate a cancellation of the existing concession if Kakalla ceases to he used as a coaling depot, out its employment as an oil fuel store, even if nominal, would furnish a sufficient pretext for the continuance of the concession should the question ever he raised. 13. The cost of maintenance at present is 792/- per annum comprising: (i) Pay of clerk (ii) Pay of peon (iii) Pay of watchman, whilst small annual sums are required for maintain ing the depot pier and sheds in good order. 14. Item (i) would automatically disappear whilst item (iii) would presumably he found hy the Departments using the depot. I consider however that item (ii) should stand in order to maintain the Political Agent*s political control over the Depot in view of dealings vis a vis the Muscat Government. 15. Petty annual repairs would also he found hy the Departments using the Depot, thus leaving an annual sum of &amp;.3QQ/- to he found hy the Government of India. 16. To retain this pied-a-terre at such infinitesmal cost would I consider he politically desirable/r desirable and iox* utia doregoing reasons 1 recommend for the present the retention of iCakalla, I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/~ C.jS.U. Bremner, lajor, Political Agent and H.B.ii. *s Consul, Muscat.Gopy. Be f 9 re n ce •vcyS. 11004/10. S3CRST Sir, Air Headciuarters, •Iraq. Go mm and, Royal xiir ibrce, Hinaidi. 22nd September 1933. Question of the abolition of the ooal deDOt at 7/uscat. I have the honour' to refer to your letter ho® 1170-S, of 1933, dated 5th September 19 33, dealing st with the question of the Goal Depot at luscat. 2. I concur entirely with the Political views set forth by the Political agent, Muscat, and 1 presume that the Naval authorities will not give up the site for the political reasons mentioned in Major Bremner's letter. 3. The R.A.F. petrol store is a necessity for us, and I am willing to agree that this shall be maintained and kept up in the normal manner by the Chief Engineer, ’Iraq Command. 4. With regard to the watchman, I think the cost of this man’s services should be shared between the R.A.P. and the Navy, but I am prepared to re commend that we should pay 200/- per annum from R.A.F. funds. 5. As Major Bremner points out in his letter, it is desiraole that the Navy should retain their buildings in the Depot, as they may be required in the future for storage of naval supplies, and there fore, I think that they should remain the responsiblLi* ty of the Navy. I have, etc., Sd/-A. D. Cunningham, Air Commodore for *.ir Vice Marshal, Commanding ’Iraq Command. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Residency, Bushire.Copy. Copfidentia 1 . No.54/245. H.M.S. 'Shoreham H , At iCtiassal) 6th December 1933. Sir, With inference to your letter ol' 4th October, 1933 (No.1277-3), 1 have the honour to inform you that I concur that it is desirable that some permanent pied-a-terre should be maintained for H.r. Services in Muscat, in case any future need should arise. 2. The existing Royal Indian Marine coal stock, however, is at present being utilised by H.M.S. 'Ormonde' by arrangement with the Admiralty, in order to dispose of it. When it is exhausted (or when 'Ormonde' requires no further supplies) there will be no further Navalineed for the coal shede and it is doubtful if they would be required again even if a Naval Depot at Muscat were found necessary in the future. In consequence, their use will be confined sorery uo the xsoyal ^ir Force. 3. In these circumstances I do not feel that I should be justified in r e commending any expenditure from Naval funds towards rit keeping the buildings in repair or sharing in the mainte nance of a watchman. I ha ve etc., Sd/- J.V. Greagh. Gaptain, Senior : aval Officer, Persian Gulf; The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushi re.Confidential. from To HO.D.2775-H/3S. :m z . 42 w !G j . ^ _ . P 0 4« 05 ,^tir v ■w r » The Deputy Secretary to the Goyemment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Ur* &gt; 1 U ■fjfs &lt;rt The Hon’Ule the political -Resident in the Persian Gulf. v, Dated Simla, the July 1933. Question of the abolition of the Coal Depot at Muscat. Sir, X am directed to inform you that in consequence of the withdrawal of H.M.S. 'Triad*, the only coal turning ! subsidised naval vessel in the Persian Gulf, the Marine Jepartmsj 1 * have intimated that the Coal Depot at Muscat ' is no longer required for naval purposes. Unless its retention is justifiable on political grounds in which case full administrative and financial responsibilities .ill probably have to be undertaken by this Department, / lt is therefore proposed to abolish it. I am to request that the Government of India may kindly be furnished with your views on the matter. ~ I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd* B.R. Burnett, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. RY’S 1 X ENCLOSURE IN A fOREISN SECRETARY Jttor No [108 t- f 20JDL W33 AUG 1933</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000206_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2974</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000206</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2974</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/17 'Muscat: Coal Depot: Question of transfer to RAF authorities'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-22T00:04:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (55 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 57; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to the transfer of administrative and financial control of the site of a coal depot at Mokalla, Muscat, from the Royal Indian Navy to the Royal Air Force (RAF). The papers deal with questions of cost, the building of a new petrol store, securing concessions for the site from the Sultan of Muscat, and what to do with the old fire engine. The main correspondents include officials of the Government of India (Foreign and Political Department and Marine Department), Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Air Headquarters, Iraq Command, RAF, Hinaidi, Air Ministry, and the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Military facilities</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Navy</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Air Force</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Marine Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Forces in Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000206#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>