<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-04T10:11:05.512Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">.N •? T4f •.(iOVEKNMENT OF INDIA- MBTBO^IOOICAL Department. EXPRESS LETTER P TVl io i s an OTIIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue ^ u^e of Gie wires] but intended tg be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as i it had been telegiaphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if had been so despatched. / Dated Karachi the $th May )• O.S.No. ^ 194 6 . &gt; . ' / ^' X The Political Ageat, &amp; H.M.B’S Consul, ' Muscat. Subject:- Establishment of a Pilot Balloon Observatory at Muscat (Bait-ul-Ealaj) / I&amp;Jl ’ Sir, ‘ 4 I have the honour to state that it is proposed to re start a Pilot Balloon Observatory at Muscat. The reouireme- nts for such an observatory are given below Accomodations. for office 8c Observatory:- (i) Three rooms for office „ and one store room for storing Hydrogen gas cylinders. , (ii) An ouen plot of land ViO* x 30* ) without buildings and trees^rhr Pilot Balloon Observations and erecting Stevenson Screens, Baingauge and _ wind instruments. '^B) Eo r Besidential Purposes: - ^ Eive Besidential quarters for Superior Staff and two quarters (Sot inferior staff (Balloon Makers) • I shall be highly obliged if you would kindly let this P T O' MFP 275 S&amp;P—6768—(M-676)—27-7-43—],000,000. •this office an early ^t during the years ^Uafio^^oled above An early reply will be greatly appreciated. ! &lt; £ I have the honour to 130, Sir, Your most obedient sarvant, Director, ■Regional Met. *^ ohl&gt; *-1 JN0.886- 22/1. To MSMUHANUUM POLITICAL AGENCY AND HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, the 2nd June, 1946. The Military Advicar to His Highnesa the Saltan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. deference correspondence resting with Mr. Hertram Thomas' demi-official letter «o.J/ 33/142 dated the 16th Ouly, 1946, regarding arrangements for Meteorological^Observatory at Baii-el-Jfalej. 2. A copy of an Express Jbetter No.u.S.MPB /4190 dated the 9th May, 1^46, from tne Meteoro logical Department, Karachi, regarding proposal for re-opening of the Meteorological Observatory at Joait-el-Falej is forwarded herewith with the request that this Consulate may kindly be informed at an early date whether the requirements men tioned therein can be met by the Muscat Government| and if so, on what terms. His Britannic majesty’s Consul, / Muscat. NKD a IT' I .jV No•17/G/46 M.I., Bait-al-PaleJ. The 4th. June, 1946$ The Political Agent &amp; P.B.M’s Consul, Muscat, Sir, P***' If Reference your letter No.885-22/1. dated 2nd.June, 1946. ifi t-rfm. &amp; Ve have no trace in our office of D.O.No.J/33/142 dated 16th July, 1946(it is presumed that this should read 1945 ? ) As regards the arrangements for the Meteorological Observatory I am afraid we can be of little help. 1. 'Ye have no accommodation available. 2. There is plenty of open ground available. 3. There are no electric connections. 4. There is no telephone other than of field telephone which is used for Military purooses. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. ^-re c? Sub .Maj or 0 .B. I., Offg.Commandant Muscat Infantry.■MBS '4 , I &gt; Copy for information to H.H. The Sultan together with H.B.M's Consul -s letter in original for perusal and return please, . ■/ A copy of Mot. jQeptt. let tor v copy of which was forwarded to the Military Ad/iser, Muscat) and a copy of Military Adviser's reply are attached. !• gc cgrngiod at ion If accommodation cannot he provided by the M.A., in the absence of any other suitable accommodation aeavfey, construction of the required accommodation for office and residential purposes by the State on rental basis appears to be the only alternative, provided both the parties agree to the arrangement. Perhaphs you may like to discuss the matter with the M.A. at Karachi. 2 * ft pan Plot No comments. 3. klectrjc Connect j one Met. ^eptt. may be informed accordingly. 4* lelwphone The field telephone can be utilized by the Observers after necessary extensions. P.A., Muscat camp, Karachi \ \A copy of Met. iDeptt. letter ; copy of which was forwarded to the Military Adviser, Muscat) and a cor;y of Military Adviser's reply are attached. 1. c ammo a at i on If accommodation cannot be provided by the M.A., in the absence of any other suitable accommodation searfey, construction of the requ.ii/ed accommodation for office and residential purposes by the State on rental basis appears to be the only alternative, provided both the parties agree to the arrangement. Perhaphs you may like to discuss the matter with the M.A. at Karachi. 2. Qpcn Plot No comments. • 3. Electric Con n ection s Met. -^eptt. may be informed accordingly. 4:. Teliaohone The field telephone car be utilized by - the Observers after necessary extensions. p.A., Muscat camp, Karachi( 3 ) Copy of an express Lott or i^o. ©. S. MPB/4190 datod the ^th May, 1946, £rom the Meteoro logical .Department, Karachi, to the rolitical Agent, Muscat. Subject; establishment of a rilot balloon ubservatory at Muscat ^Lai-el-ralej) 1 have the honour to state that it is proposed to restart a rilot aa-Lloon uoservatory at Muscat, xhe requirements for such an observatory are given below Accomno dat 1 on ia) For office and ubservatory ; (1) Three rooms for office and one store room for storing Hydrogen gas cylinders. v.2; An open plot of land 40 *x 20* without buildings and trees nearby for rilot balloon observations and erecting otevenson bereens, Haihgauge and wind instruments. (b) For Residential rurposes Five Residential quarters for superior staff and two quarters for inferior staff (balloon makers) 1 shall be highly obliged if you would kindly let this office know at an early date whether the accommodation mentioned above could be made available at or near the Military Barracks at Bait el Falej, where the inaia Met. Deptt. Observa tory was located during the years 1927-1935, orelse where. The approximate lent fox- the accommodation mentioned above may also kindly be intimated, rhis office may also kindly be informed whether telephone and electric- connections could be arranged at the proposed site. An early reply will be greatly appreciated.Copy of a letter Wo.l7/Ci/46 dated the 4th dune, 1946, from the Military Adviser to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman to the political “gent, Museatj with a copy to H.H. the Sultan. ■Reference your letter ^0.885-22/1 dated the 2nd June, 1946. “e have no trace iiS oijr office of D.O.' ,, o.J/33/ 142 dated the 16th duly, 1927, (.it is presumed that this should read 1945V) As regards the arrangements for the Meteorolog ical Observatory 1 am afraid we can be of little help. 1. «&lt;e have no accommodation available. 2. There is plenty of open ground available N 3. There are no electric connectrons. 4. There is no telephone other than of field telephone which is used for Military purposes.Subject : Opening - of Pilot Balloon and R ad io-Soud e Station at Muscat, Information has been received by me that the I eteo- rological Department, India, in consultation with the Air Ministry, London, are proposing to open a combined pilot balloon and Radio-Soude station at Muscat, for which purpose accommodation for the office and for residential purposes of the staff is needed. 2. I would be grateful if the Residency could request the Political Agent, Muscat, kindly to make preliminary investigations as to the availability of a suitable building on hire. The office accommodation needed is at least (i) Four medium sized rooms (say, 15* X IP’) (ii) a store room and (iii) a flat terrace having a free view of the sky for balloon observations. 3. It will be essential to have electric connections to the building. It would therefore be preferable to have it as close to the Agency as possible, so that it could be served by the Agency electric plant, unless the city electric supply is fairly reliable. The Residential accommodation needed will be for a staff of about five assistants and three inferior servants. 4. There will be no objection to have a combined building for office as well as residential purposes. Proximity to the telegraph office will be very much welcomeA as this would facilitate speedy despatch of data. 5. The meteorological Department will endeavour^to send down an officer to Muscat to make final selection of the buildings in consultation with Agency, but if some preliminary arrangements could be made in the meantime, it would be m6st helpful. 6. If any results materialise, the same may very kindly be communicated to the Director, Central Meteorological office, Me Leod Road, Karachi. X His telegraphic address is METCENTRE KARACHI ). Sd. Mohammed Aslam. 15-5-46. Meteorologist ( On tour ).No.R.12. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, (Camp) Karachi, Dated 17th June, 1946. From To R.I. Hallows, Esquire, Political Agent, Muscat,(camp) Karachi. The Director, Central Meteorological Office, Me Leod Road, Karachi. Sir, With reference to your express letter No.O.S.MPB/4190, dated the 9th May, 1946, on the subject of an observatory at Muscat, I have the honour to say that the Military Adviser to His Highness the Sultan regrets that it will not be possible for him to accommodate the personnel for the observatory at the Military Barracks at Bait al Falaj as was done previously. The question of accommodation at Muscat is a very difficult one and before anything is decided I would suggest that a re presentative of your office be sent to Muscat in order to see the type of accommodation wh5 ch can be procured, its location and the facilities wh: ! ch exist in the way of communications etc. 2. I myself shall be at Karachi for the next two months l or so and shall be glad to discuss the matter with you at the Central Hotel (Room No.10) during any morning except Sunday. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Muscat.All Communications to be Addressed to— MACKINNON MACKENZIE &amp; CO. BRITISH INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION COMPANY, LIMITED. Agentt, B. I. S. If. Co., Ltd., KARACHI- Telegraphic address:— MACKINNONS- Telephone:—Karachi 2838- (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) Post Box No. 40. © No. P/JTO3/317. ^ 12 th Mar ch , ^ 7. The Commander, Dear Sir, s/s ,, Bamora ,l , Karachi Harbour We append below an extract - of a letter received by us from the Regional Meteorological centre, Karachi •I write to inform you that in connection with the inspection of the Met.Observatory , Mr.S.M.N.A.Chishty, ASstt.Met., Karachi, will be carrying with him four mercurial barometers on board the s/s*BAMOBA*« AS these instruments are very delicate and require very careful handling, it is requested that arrangements may kindly be made to have them kept in their own boxes in the Captain’s cabin on the date of sailing . The measure nent of each case is x S* x 5* and weighs approximately 20 lbs. Please advise us as to whether or not you can accommodate this request. Yours faithfully, Pro.Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co sd/- d.M.W ilson Agents. Copy to:-The Direct or,Regional Meteorological Centre, Karachi, ref. their letter No.QS:M-PB: 1957 of 10/3/47. a PlfcL.M.M.&lt;s/\CONe.263-22/1 Political Agency, Muscat. The 27th March 1947. Messrs, (iray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., MUSCAT. Dear Sirs, Mr.S.M.N.A. Chishty, Assistant Meteorolo gist, Karachi will be carrying with him four mercurial barometers on board M^S.^Durara' 1 from Muscat to Karachi. As these instruments are very delicate and require very careful handling it is requested that arrangements may kindly be made to have them kept in their own boxes (each measuring 3^ feet X 6 ,t X 5 fl and weighing approximately 20 Ibsj in the Captain*s cabin. It may be mentioned that similar special arrangements were made by the Commander s.s.'’Bamora 11 for these barometers on board s.s• ,, Bamora ,, during her voyage from Karachi to Muscat on 19th/22nd instant./ 7 No.OS: Eagional Uet Centre, Mclieod Eoad,Karachi. 4th ilarch 1947. From Dr.S.K.Pramanik, il.Sc., Ph.D., D.I.C., Director, Begional Ifet Centre, McLeod Koad, Karaclii 1. To The Political Agent, Mi scat. Subject:- Starting of a Meteorological Observatory at Miscat. .Sir, With reference to your letter No.E. 12 dated the 17th June 1946, I have the honour to state that the matter wae discussed with R.I.Hallows, , during July 1946 when he was at Karachi last year. He suggested that an officeq of the I.Met.D. might visit Muscat for selection of a suitable site and office and residential accommodation. I am deputing Mr.S.M.N.A.Chishty, Assistant Meteorologist, Karachi, who will discuss the Question with you on arrival there. Mr.Ghishty is expected to sail for Mascat about the middle of this month. The exact date of his sailing for Muscat will be communicated to you telegraphically. I shall be greatly obliged if you will kindly extend to him the necessary facilities. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, i 4 'P' u Director, KarachiPrinted in England Nov. 194-5.(l5,000padq) 5/-168 CIRCUIT CLERK S NAME TIME RECElV|p AN SN ' 1450 (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) : CABLE &amp; WIRELESS LTD VIA 5 The first line of this Telegram contains the following particular^/me order named: Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number ol -3 • L? ISSUING OFFICE I (\ / KSNM 5 OW KARACHI 20 19 1515 “ OBS POLITICAL MUSCAT = REFCE MY 1858 OF FOURTH AAA MISTER CHISHTY ASSISTANT METEOROLOGIST LEFT TODAY FOR MUSCAT BY BAMORA = METCENTRE = Enqty^ ' respecting this telegram should be accompanied by this form and may be made at any of the Company's offices-Zif ■ 310.1?/V136 ' it-al-^le.i. ^fU 7 •oh, 1947. _—-—• 33 . (Vi The Polit'.c-il .v^-ant *.B .r * s Consul, Hu seat. I have today taken I'r Ohisty of the Indian I?eteor»clop , ical Observatory to Bait-al-Fale,i and shorn him round. I informed him that (a) fe have no aecomo lation ave'Table in the n? ort Bar* -eehs, and that I considered it /ould be unsuitable to have any more buildings constructed v/ithin the ^ io-- l-^ale.i enclosure. (b) That ou&amp; 'v/ater sup;&gt;ly v s very liro’ted mi that he could not count ort usin /. ter frora our /ells- T -r 'fhisty has tentatively chosen a site mr the construc J ^mn 0 ^ the Observatory 150 ya ois SOUTH of the main mte to/a' 1 Is the aerodrome. This are he states would suit his purposes very veil, and “ have no objection to this as it /ould not interfere vith the Uu 0 cat “n^artry or aerodrome, and is close enouyh to be secure tactically. ' suggested that as the /ater su]. ly /as very limited that the observatory offices only sho Id b built out here and than the Personnel sho i ld live in T 'attr^h. . ' tT is Highness Hie Sultan's permission will have tc but I presume that you /ill do this and that His Hi dmess already bem informed of the proposed visit o • tUs &gt;- ■ Sty obtain 'd ■’’irst must h 0 n d th e e 0 ^ e r '’ e . I have /ritten to the Secretary of this letter regarding ! T '‘ Chi sty’s to VH fhe dultan today 'Cuka* visit an i his selection of a site. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant.tn) !• _ O.S.No.M-PB ■ t 4] T ]^T? r jn*QTQL0G~' C T ' DEPABT'' 1PITT iXPHEGS LETTER Froi T* O ■•ubjects ir ? Inviting a reference to this office letter 0. r h T o. -PE/1858 of the 4th March, 1947 and the letter 40.17/0/126 dated the 23rd March, 1947 from the Commandant, Muscat Infantry, Baital FaleJ to your address (copies enclosed). I have the honour to state that during his visit to Muscat last year** Mr* Chishty selected some sites for the^hove purpose but reported the three ±h storey building at Kuttrah belonging to M/S. Mhim/i Ramdas as suitable for the establishment of the Pilot Balloon Observatory at Kuttrah. I shall be grateful if you will kindly let this office know whether the building in question could now be available on rent to tills department. An early reply will be greatly appreciated. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most ooedient servant, * V Enel: Refd,to ,'' AR/11 * 9 for Regional Director, Regional Meteorological Centre*Copy of I T o .0S./858 dated 4th March liegional ^'et.^entre, Karachi to the Political 1947 from the ‘Director Agent, Murcat* Duhlect:- i-^artino of a Meteorological Ohrerv r 'tor;/ at 'rr cat. with R.J.Hallows, last year. T Ie sup T ith reference to your letter ?To # K.12 dated the 17th June 1946. 1 have the honour to state that the matter ' rT es discussed 'isq., during J^ly 1949 when he war at Karachi jested that an officer of the I.Ket.D. night visit Muscat for selection of a suitable site and office and residential accommodation. I an deputing Mr. D.M.T T .A.Chishty, Assistant Meteorologist, you on arrival there. * * f Mr. ^hisHTy s enpectedi to sail for Muscat about the middle of this month. The exact date of hir sailing for Muscat will be cormuricated to you tele~ranhicaTly. m: m t- I shall necessary * be greatly obliged if you will hindly extend to facilities. Copy of letter ^0.17/0/126 dated 93rd March 1947 from the Commandant, Muscat Infantry. M.I.Baital-Fsle^ to The Pol it:, cal / gent, and T J .^ r| s Consul, Muscat, and copy to Mr. Chishty.for information and return please. I have today . r '' ^''htj 7 ’ of the T ndiar ^'^t. Observatory to Baitai-^^lej and sho^m him round. I informed him that (a) we have no acco mmodation available in the Fort or barracks and that I considered it would hr unsuitable to have any more buildings constructed thin the Baital-Falej enclosure. (b) That our water supply was very limited and that he could not count on using water from our wells. hr. Chishty has tentatively c 1 osen a site for the construction of the observatory 150 yards south of the main gate towards the aerodrome. This as he stated would suit his purposes well and I have no objection to this as it would not interfere i T it4 the I Infantry or aerodrome, and r'Trur enough to be secure tactical^, p suggested that as the water supply TT as very limited that the ^observatory off:' ces only should be built out here arid that 1 should live in Kattrah, K. T 4 the Sultan*s perm! ^ion will have to be obtained first but I presume that you will do this and H.P T must have already been informed of' the proposed visit of Mr. Chishty and the scheme. I have written to the Secretary to H.H, the h-ltan today on the lines of this letter regardin' - - v &gt;. ChMsh^Me visit and his selection of a site.Messrs Khimli Hamdas, MUSCAT. I am, Sirs, Your obedient Servant, l IV ( 5 ) * No. { 22 / 2 ') Political Agency, Muscat, October 16, 1948, Sir*, Mr. Chisty, Assistant Meteoroligist, Karachi visited Muscat in March 1947 to select some sites for the purpose of establishing a pilot balloon Observatory and it is reported that a three storey building at Muttrah belonging to you was selected for the observatory at that time. As the Meteorological Department, are anxious to establish an observatory, I shall be grateful if you will kindly intimate this office whether the building in question is new available on rent to the department. — Ji *^ K, KNIMJI RAM DAS Muscat the 16th October, 1948 To, The Political Agent, Muscat. (0 r v y Revered Sir, In reply to your Honour 1 s,office letter No. 179 ( 22/2 ) dated today, we are glad to inform you that we are ready to rent our Muttrah building to Meteorological Department. Thanking you in anticipation, W e beg to remain, Sir, Your Honour 1 s most obedient servants for Khimji Ramdas*No. 190-22/2 Political Agency, Muscat, October 20, 1948* Sir* I have the honour to refer to your letter No* O.S. No. M-PB of the 16th September about the establishment of a balloon observatory at Muscat and to state that Messrs. Khimji Ramdas of Muscat have agreed to rent the three storey building selected by Mr. Chisty in March, 1947. 2. I should be glad to learn whether you wish me to request His Highness 1 . permission and to make enquiries about rent. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Director, Regional Meteorological Centre, KARACHIz , From To No. O.S.No.Ivx F.B. / PAKISTAN METEQAOLOGIJAL DSPART^NT The Director, Meteorological Services, Karachi. The Political Agent, Political Agency, Muscat. , Karachi the November 1948. S ir / I have the honour to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of your letter No.190-22/2 dated the 20th October, 1948. I shall be very grateful if you will, kindly arrange to obtain K.H. The ^ulta^s permissxn for the establishment of a pilot balloon observatory of this Department in Messrs Khimji’s building at Muttrah and also to make enquiries about rent. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, HDK91148. for Director, Meteorological Services. /,From 6«t i*\&lt;^ To 0•&amp; 0—9 PAKI STAN MET E OROLOGICAL DE P AHTLENT . The Director, Meteorological Services, Karachi. The Political Agent, and Honorary Superintendent, Meteorological Observatory, Muscat, MUSCAT. Karachi the 6th November, 1948. Subject:- INSPECT ION OF METEOROL OGICAL OBSShVATO RY. Sir, I have the honour to state that the Pakistan Government has been pleased to depute Mr.S.M.N.A.Chishty, i^sstt. Meteorologist, Karachi to visit Muse atshortly and carryout the inspection of the meteorological observatory. The exact date of his arrival at your station will be communicated to you telegraphically. I shall be greatly obliged if you will kindly extend to him necessary facilities. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, f Director, Meteorological Services. HUK61143.No. 280-22/&amp; British Consulate, My dear Friend, Muscat. December 31 t 1948, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that Mr. S.M. Chisty, Assistant Meteorologist, Karachi is expected to visit Muscat shortly in connection with the establishment of a Pilot Balloon Observatory in Muscat. 2. As Your Highness is aware Mr. Chisty visited Muscat in March 1948 and after consultation with the Commandant and Your Highness* Secretary, selected tentatively a site 150 yards south of the main gate towards the aerodrome for the Observatory. 3. Mr. Chisty also selected a building owned by Messrs. Khimji Ramdas in Muttrah for the Meteorological staff. 4. The Meteorological Department has now asked me to approach Your Highness for the necessary permission to establish the Balloon Observatory in Khimji Ramdas* building at Mutrah. 5. I shall be grateful for Your Highness* decision. Your Highness* sincere Friend, His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, MUSCAT.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/469</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/469</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 22/2 Opening of Pilot Balloon and Radio-Sonde Station at Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-12T10:13:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 26; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the Political Agency in Muscat and the Regional Meteorological Centre in Karachi regarding the establishment of a pilot balloon observatory in Muscat.Some of the correspondence concerns a visit to Muscat made by Mr S M Chishty of the Indian Meteorological Observatory (the Pakistan Meteorological Department after August 1947) and the subsequent rental of a property in Muttrah in which to establish the observatory.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Regional Meteorological Centre</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Meteorology</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000f4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>