<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002d5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:28:55.166Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. of 1351 Office of the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain, Dated. 8th J/Thany 1351 8tn Gctr. 1932. H. 3. ?! f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have beer instructed by His Excellency Shaikh Hamad to forward to you three netitions from some of his subjects v/ho are living in Persia who complain of the ill treatment to which they are subjected to by the Persian Government. The petitions ere incorrectly addressed to tho Adviser, but their evident intention is to constitute an appeal to the Government of Bahrain. H. E. Shaikh Hamad wishes me to draw your attention to a comnarison of the conditions of his subjects residing in Persia and those of Persian nationals resident in Bahrain. Persians in Bahrain enjoy equal privileges and rights to the Shaikh’s own subjects. They are allowed to have their own schools, which are notor iously hot-beds of anti-Bahrain propoganda, they occupy positions on councils, they sit on Courts, they are at liberty to buy and possess property,© uj— they are free to some and go and they are treated with justice and consideration, in fact with kindness• The lot of the 3aharna living in the Persian towns of Moharaerah, Hashah etc. is very different. These people, subjects of H. E. Shaikh Hamsd, are deliberately onpressed by the Persian Government which makes every possible effort to force them to renounce their n tionality. They are threatene with forcible conscription and made to wear a foreign heed dress which is repugnant to them. Owing to their ill treatment many have fie i to Iraq and at present an embargo has been placed upon their coming to Bahrain to visit their hems villages and their relations. It may be argued by the ersian Govern _ /their long residence in Persia they have forfeited their nationality. There is no such assumption in the case of innumerable Persians long resident in Bahrain. B. S. Shaikh Hamad believes that some representa tion was formerly made to the Persian Government on this subject, but with slight effect. He thinks perhaps that the position now calls for the adoption of a somewhat different policy by the Bahrain Govern ment towards the Persians living in Bahrain. Persians would no longer be appointed or elected on public bodies, their schools, if allowed to continue, would be subject to inspection and the control of the Department of Education, the wearing of Pehlevi hats would be dis- todis-encouraged and perhaps measures would be taken to prevent the permanent alienation of property into the hands of ersians; but before considering any action E. E. Shaikh Hamad would like to be informed of your views on tne subject. In this connection I would add that the recent- flood of newspaper articles in the i'ersian Iress dealing witii the Bahrain question has had a most undesirable effect on the local Persian community who now consider that the Persian claim is definitely proved all of which is distustful to H. E. Shaikh Hamad'. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, Adviser to the Government.(9 *~j\ ¥ Translation of petition dated 29th August 1932, from Bahama residents of Persia now at Busrah, addressed to The Adviser, Bahrain Government. e are your subjects, B h^rna fugitives who fled from ■’.'ohemmereh, at present residing in Busrah, on account of the oppression of the Persian Government and forcible conscription of our sons. Te are your subjects and believe that you will not leave us scattered everywhere. We beseech you to free us from their tyranny, as the son always belongs to the same nationality as his father. ,,T e observe that Persians are free in B hrain, and how is it that we, your subjects, are oppressed in their country? 'e re u.est your aid to release us from their tyranny. e are anxiously awaiting a reply. ********* 111 =4© We seek your aid tc free us from the oppression and ill treatnent of the Persian Government. are oppressed for remaining subjects of our Government. ’ Tr e beseech you to rescue us. You are freeing slaves, but how is it that you leave thousands of your sub jects enslaved? The Persian Government issued a proclamation giving names of some of the sons of Brherna to be taken for compulsory military training, alleging that they are registered as i ersian subjects. You must know that if any Bahrani has e’Sejl*, it was forced on him. How could it be that our sons are forcibly taken and we are your subjects. The son naturally belongs to his father’s nationality. 'e are getting much trouble in asbah, os the British Consul is far from us at Pohamaerah. T ”e deserve to hrve a Consul here as we are a big community and we if we get ve*y little free iom you will find numbers of your subjects in Qasbah. The Persians are enjoying in Bahrain, they and their sons are free and their properties are srfe. We, your subjects are oppressed in tneir country, and God forbid that you should leave us thus lest we should be ruined. I ✓' 1 f » ; 4 *********** SAmum l iv Treastation of a letter from Shaikh All biri Hasan al-Musa of Saaabis to the Political i^eni,Bahrain, oatei 3ra,j/Thani,iSS”/. . *™ • ■ After Compliments. I am sennin^ you herewith two petitions from your subject, the Bahranis resident Qusbuh* I request Jour Excellency to assist them andsave « them from the hands of the oppressors as it is your custom to reliexe the oppressed. I ask the Almighty to give power to “the- British Government and to vanish its enemies. Wishing you every prosperity and victory in your 1 Usual Ending. &gt; If, J.M. ♦ : % • 'I AFrom tho Bahraais liTiag ia usbi.a To the Political i^oat. After Compliments. Wt the Bahranis y jreur subject,most respectfull/ be^ to state that the Persian Gore ram eat constantly treats us contrary to the manner in which you are treating their subjects in your country. Vie see that they are free in their daily life an* bate full control o*er their properties although you hare power to treat them ia the manner in which we are being treated but your justice woule not allow you to breat people except in confirm!ty with justice. The following are our grievances:— Firstly:— The Persian Government compelleu us to wear their clothings which differ from ours but still we have obeyco the oruers. Secondly:— he heve been always asked by the same Government to register ourselves as their subjects but we have refused because we no not accept to follow any other Govt but our own. Thirdly:— The same Govt excercises force upon us to join the military service and consequently a lot of us have fled away for that fear. Itnio understood that the son follows the nationality of his father. in view of the above,we humbly request Your Excellency to save u£ from this grave danger so that we may live comfort- aoly in our houses and attend to our dntxnn properties. The Govt of Quobah is continuously treating us with severeness and insult If there were a representative of the British Government in our slue we would have complained to him about our condition every time. Th liohammerah is far away and therefore the Persians find it a good chance to molest us as tnere is no British representa tive or agent to protect us. Save us from these calamities as you are just. Great Britain has always been setting the x&amp;islaves free why not extend freedom to free people. We are your subject and ask your assistance. Save us from the h&amp;nas of these. U.E. Dated 24th,Rabi-el-Thani,1351. (1) Seals and thumb impressions of ;~ Sayen Talib bin Sayeu Muhammad al-Musawi Bayed A’asim bin Sayeu Sharaf al-Musawi n ayer Makki bin Abaun Nabi iiaji Muiisin bin iiahui and 51 others. (2) Seals ana thumb impressions of :— Haji Najim bin Abaullah Habib bin Muhaisin !4ahmua bin Ramadhan M&amp;hdi bin Ma’tooq ana 61 others.L 1 Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp Bus hire , the 29th October 1952* fy: ■' • prom Captain C*G* Prior, Political Agent, Bahrain, at Bush ire. To The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahir e. /&gt; / p (-5 if * I ha7e the honour to enclose forjyour information in original letters I have received from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government and the elder Shiah i^adhis of Bahrain. The letters explain themselves, and the Adviser has set forth the State’s point of vice at length. 2. The Bahrain Government have continually before them the glaring contrast of the security and liberty enjoyed by Persians living in Bahrain and the insecurity and oppression meted out to their subjects in Persia. It mill be seen that the State are now considering whether the game is wolrth the candle and whether their good treatment of Persians resident in Bahrain is not out of place. 3. The situation is complicated by the nebulous and indeterminate nature of the U status quo”. This appears to justify anfr Persian act of aggression against Bahrainis in Persia even to conscripting them for the national army or their forcible registration as Persian subjects, while creating an obstacle against effective retaliation against Persians domiciled within the limits of Bahrain. This is indefensible. 4* It must be realised however that there are two classes of Bahrainis in Persia, those who own agricultural land/ i\ Vto (9 - 2 - land and those i&amp;o do not. Tor those who own agricultural land and hare no intent ion of returning to Bahrain we can do nothing for we have never disputed the Persian law that Ter si an s alone can own agricultural SM&amp;fc property in Persia. These persons must make up their minds on which side of the fence they wish to live, and it will be open to the State to restrict the ownership of agricultural land in Bahrain to Bahrainis should they so desire. 5* The floating population of Bahrainis in Persia is however entitled to a full measure of our protection and our reluctance to make certain that it is accorded them is unfavourably commented on in Bahrain, le have enjoyed un exampled facilities in Bahrain which have either been refused us elsewhere or bought at a high price, we are by treaty bound to protect the territory of Bahrain and equally its subjects overseas. 6. To sum up: while securing every advantage for Persians lx at Bahrain we have failed to secuewelief for Bahrainis abroad. The Behrain State xwixk realise that this is inequiable and propose to restrict the advantages now extended to Persians ^ Within their jurisdiction, and their right to do this is in my opinion incontestable. X have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential * uv^ n JNo.842-3 Of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 3rd November 1932. The Hon*ble Lt.•Colonel T.C.Rowle, C.B.B., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject * 111 treatment of Bahrainis in Persia. * 4 Sir, 1 % 1 I have the honour to refer to your letter of 29th October 1932 on the above subject, with enclosures. 2. The wrongs suffered by Bahrain subjects in Persia are of course self-evident, and I quite realise the feelings of His Bxcellency Shaikh Hamad, and hi a people, on the subject, more especially since - as is pointed out in the enclosures Persian subjects in Bahrain enjoy equal privileges and rignts with the Shaikh’s own subjects. It is only natural there fore that His Excellency should wish to institute reprisals, and doubtless such might legally be justified. But all things that are lawful are not expedient', and it is really on-the grounds of expediency that this question must be considered. 3 . Then we discussed this matter here during your visit, my views were that while such reprisals as were possible in Bahrain against Persian subjects would certainly 1 «• • •.-2 (g) certainly annoy the Persian Government, they would not attain the object the Bahrain Government and our selves had in view* the better treatment of Bahrainis in Persia* The Persian Government - I was inclined to think — were not kind-hearted enough to be materially affected by the hardships of their subjects in Bahrain. We also - I pointed out - have to take into account that treatment of Bahrainis by the Persian Govern- ment* in the matter of conscription, our chief cause of complaint, is bound up with the Persian claim to Bahrain* Bahrainis are conscripted because the Persian Government choose to regard them as Persian subjects, and if the Persians refrain from conscripting tlieia they weaken their case. As far as I remember you agreed with these views, which are also generally those of His Majesty’s Government. 4. I think in reply to His Excellency’s complaint there fore you had better explain to him, verbally at the present stage, how the matter stands. That while I fully sympathise with the hardships his subjects have to undergo in Persia, and with his feelings on the subject, I do not think that such reprisals as are possible against Persians in Bahrain^ will bring about the end which His Excellency has in view* the better treatment of Bahrainis in Persia. You had better quote me, and not His Majesty’s Government, as I do not think His Excellency has ever been informed of the latter’s views. You might further inform His Excellency that I hope to discuss this matter with him when I visit Bahrain next month. 5* There is, however, another aspect of His Excellency’s proposals. ^uite apart from the question of reprisals, prima facie it might well be desirable for more control to be exer cised over the Bahraini Persian community, who are troublesome at times, than is done at present. If, for instance, the Persian .. •.-3- Persian sehools in Baiirain are, as stated by His Excellency, hot-beds of anti-Bahrain propaganda, then some control would seen to be advisable. His Excellency's proposals are four in number. (1) Persians would no longer be appointed or elected on public bodies# (2) Their schools, if allowed to continue, would be subject to inspection and the control of the Depart- ment of Education^ (3) The wearing of Pehlevi hats would be disencou-aged* (4) Perhaps measures would be taken to prevent the permanent alienation of property into the hands of Persians# Prom the aspect indicated in this paragraph please let me have your views on each of these proposals, purely from the point of view of the expediency of putting them into practice. If you are in favour of (l), (2) and (4) for example, kindly let me have details as to how the State proposes to carry them out. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ' Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf#® 1 ru.tL GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. 6 A?-F-of 1352 Office of tne Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, J/Thany, 7, 1352 Septr. 27, 1933. The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. H. B. M r s Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to inform you that I recently received a visit from Syed Aloui bin Syed Rathi, and Hussein bin Haji Saleh, both Bahrain subjects, resident at Qasbah, Persia, complaining that the Persian govern ment has recently adopted a more severe attitude towards Bahrain subjects resident at Qasbah. In particular they informed me that Bahrain subjects are forbidden to visit their own country unless they first make a solemn declaration that they have adopted Persian nationality. Certain persons are allowed to visit Kuwait but they are forbidden to visit Bahrain or Iraq and are thlguij prevented from visiting the Holy cities.2. The persons mentioned above informed me that there are nearly 2000 Bahrain subjects who are anxious to obtain nationality certificates from Bahrain government but are prevented from getting to Bahrain. They themselves came to Bahrain from Kuwait. Syed Aloui is one of the leading men of the Bahama community residing at Qasbah and stated that he came as a representative of his fellow countrymen to lay the matter before the authorities in Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government.Confidential. — D.0.Io:C/47Y-i.a/2. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 21st October 193B. -&gt; S./Yc. *8? Dear Belgrave, Whilst looking for previous correspondence /V*: !(&gt; in connection with your letter No:607/3.F dated the 27th September 1933 regarding the harsh treatment of Bahrainis in Fersia.I came across Prior’s confidential _ P.m _ 1 letter No:C/197 of the 26th November 1932. 2. I cannot find any reply thereto and wonder whether any was made by you,but,if so,would you kindly let me have a copy of it to complete my records. Yours sincerely, Dalrymple Belgrave Esquire, Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. -No. 1351-3 of 1933 20) S' do: /. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political \p , ert, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docii- ment (4/ for infornation and favour of renprt, regarding thi fanilien desirous of settling in British Basidu, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 20th October 1933. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. elegran No.1256 dated the 19th October 1933 from the Officer of the Ouard,Basidu, to the Senior TT aval Officer, Persian Oulf Bivision. Subject. Desire o^ Bahrain Arab - Abdulla bin 41i - to settle in British Basidu. \ &gt;V 0 'U&gt; o.r.c. Officer of the tfuf.xd, Basldu* Senior Havtl Officer ,, Shoreham ,, Buehire Radio* Ko 1256* Bi ted the 19th tnd received the 2Cth October 1933. I was vieitea this morning by /caulIs bin All he le r good cl es B htain Areb* Ke wiehee to settle in British B&amp;eidu witn 4 other f miliee st present et Cherg?h. The reason given is that Pereiene are forcing them to become Persian subjects, they do not wish this and want British protection* I saidil would let him know if thills permissible in o day or two* They h ve heard rumours that we are going to Improve British Basidu i nu hinted at a prospect of brisk trade, possibly with Havy. Have names of other f miliesv -O/yiC® GUARD-1 fins Ai'aC&amp;fiut ^ ?&lt;&gt; ^o. U4 Reference Officer in charge Guard,BASIDU, message 1256 of 19/10/33 to S.N.O.P.G. Political Bahrain grateful for following further details re: ABDULLAH bin ALI. (1) . Family name. (2) . Adaress in Bahrain or other information to enable identification. 1^(5). When did he go there. (6). Address of family there. (8). Names and particulars of 'other families' M V- present whereabouts.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. CONFIDENTIAL No. D.0.C/|°3 of 1352 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 6th Rajah, 1352 0ctr,26, 1933. r\ / Dear Gastrell, 27th September 1933 , 1 do not anpear to have replied to this owing to the fact that we discussed it after the letter and I gathered that it was not then an opportune moment for instituting any of the suggestions I made. 2. I agreed that it would be as well to drop sug gestions U) and (,4) but 1 continue to think that it would be advisable that all schools should be subject to inspection by the department of education, as is the custom in other countries. The department would require a pro gramme of work and a list of books which are used in the schools to be submitted to it and the Inspector of education would have the right to attend schools occasionally and listen to the lessons being taught. 3. The wearing of Pehlavi hats would be discouraged by the imposition of the heavy imuort duty on all such hats, whether new or old, brought into the country, and no permission would be given to their manufacture locally. Yours sincerely, Captain E.H.Gastrell, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain.&lt;9 RNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. 61 STS' of 1352 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, 10th Rajah. 1352 Octr. 30, i93j. H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum I enclose for your information a renort from the Passport Officer, Bahrain, relating to a Bahrain subject who was compelled by the Persian Consul, Basrah, to take a Persian passport and wear a Persian hat. Would it be advisable to protest against this action v/hich appears to be an infringement of the status quo? (iStsCJL^s Advise^ to the Government '^Persian Passport 37873 Ilm al Tvhabar &lt; Renort in original ^rom Passport Officer, Bahrain.45 4 *! Adviser Mohammed bin Hasan Bahrain subject holder of Bahrain book- passport No 115 of 1349 arrived from Bushire per yesterdays domi boat Band*a, bearing Persian passport No 3787 2/4&amp;1 /^.He was per mitted to land. About the end of last September Mohammed bin Hasan intended to go to Bushire from Basrah,and thus he had to appear before the Persian Consul,Basrah who ordered him to obtain the above referred to Persian passport wherein Mohammed bin Has^n have been described as an 'Irani' persian(with a phalawi cap on)# The above referred to Persian passport and Jlme-khaber have since been impounded and submitted for your insepction,please. Ehfeammed bin Hasan has managed to keep his Bahrain book- passport from the Persian clutches and on that authority he was permitted to land. Submitted for Information passport officer.No. C • »'of 1352 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain* Dated, Shawaal 18. 1352 February 3,19d4 . ft Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to state that I am ins tructed by His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al-Khalifah, C.S.I., to inform you that he has received information fr 9 m a reliable source that his subiects residing at Qasbah, on the Persian coast, are being oppressed andimpri^ soned by the Government of Persia, their nationality documents which were handed to them in Bahrainare being taken away from them and attempts are being made to force them to adopt Persian nationality. 2. His Excellency strongly resents this action of the Persian Government which he regards as unfriendly and unwarrantable. He requests that an immeaiate protest should be made on his behalf to the Government of Persia, and that it should be required to treat His Excellency's numerous subjects who are residing in that country with the toleration and benevolence which is accorded to Persian subjects living in Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government. rn D.O/C Bahrain, Feby. 3, Dear Colonel Loch, I enclose copy of the telegram regarding Bahranis of ^asbah received by me last evening. The sender is one of the leading men of the Bahrani community. Many hundreds of these have come down to Bahrain during the last few years and after proving before the Shara that they were born in Bahrain nationality documents have been issued to them. I discussed the matter this morning with Shaikh Abdullah, before hearing from Shaikh Hamad, and he y too, strongly resented the action of the Persian Government and considered it a matter which we should complain about officially, The question has been boiling up for some time. During the last fortnight I have heard several reports of the increased persecution b^ r -A. „ the Persian Government of Bahrain subjects resident on that part of the coast. Yours sincerely, Lieut. Colonel G. Loch, H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.7 Copy of telegram No. Df/23. from Fao received at 1511 on # 2nd Feby. 1934 from ^bdulrasool Haji Ibrahim, addressed to Mr. C.D.BelRrave, Financial Adviser, Bahrain. AH Bahraini subjects residing Cusbah molested by Persian Government forcing to be Persian subjects nationality documents taken by Persians now imprisoned.Telegram:- X/27. From:- Political Banram. To:- Resident Busin re. No:- 73. Bated:- btn February 1934. Bahrain Government report serious recrudescence ol oppression ot Bahrain subjects at *asbeh. Fuller information is being obtained and will De sent by next mail. Political.Confidential No:C/100. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 17th February 1934 From:- Lieut-Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A Political Acrpnt. To:- The Adviser to the Bahrain Government Bahrain. Sir, Ajivi I have the honour to refer to your letter No:C/114 dated the 3rd February 1934 (18th Shawwal 1353J regarding the protest of His Excellency ShaiKh Hamad bin T Isa Al Khalifah,C.S.I.,concerning the treatment of his subjects residing at Qasbeh by the Persian Government and to enquire whether it is yet possible to furnish me with fuller information on the subject. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent,Bahrain.'he Kon ’hie the '’oil Meal ^rnident at Buahire••• •32ft• His MaleBty’fl VI ce- Consul.MohjurmernJi. Ho. 330. ^ith cormliwent s 'b Connul for Khu*i atan at iVhvas. British Conaula^e, Aim3. 6th February,. 1034. Oir, With reference to ny telegram Bo.? of the 1st instant, regard In*? the action of the n ernian authoritie« at Qushah vsith regard + o Bahrainis resident there, I ha ye the honour to forward herewith conies of two desnatches received fron His Kajewtv’fl Vice Consul a* Bohan?!**rah on this subject. It will be &gt;tp&lt;ed that the Oovemor Qusbah has au?feed '-o s + ay his hand for ten davn and I hope that instruction!! M?ill be received fron 'ehran in the meanwhile t?nat he is to leave them alone for the present. I have conveyed the subs ance of vo?ir teleirram No.8 to the Governor General who informed me that he will enquire into the matter. /j&gt;. a b you a^e no doubt aware, the Bahraini community a* ^ . Mohartnerah and at Ousbah has been settled there 'or the most nart (for several generations. ''houfth possibly 'Mieribk? from theiv Bahraini oririn for the inrue of Bahraini papers of nationality, - and Car tain ChRurcy reports that some ►hree or four hund^ed at Qusbah, o?it of a total of four thousand , are in posseoe ion of such papers, - i f appears + o me a these people are, with a few posnible exceptions, of dual nationality in accordance with the Borsian Nationality Law of September f7 , 1929. Gi nC e the cornier into force of tha* Law, the title of His Hajcnty’s Gover?*nent to protect them in ^ersia would seem *o be limited to prood offices similar to those afforded to o‘her pernors of dual antionality. 3./ 8 ir Bef?inald H.Hoare,K.C.V.f ., Hie Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc., etc., etc., British Le^ation, r &gt;hran.1 -9. 3. I Torture to nto* thfit, vftten a oomreniont raomflnt arrlven, the '’ersiarj Croverrmert riifrW- he repeated to hand over *he Bohmln docunc?nto of nationality *hich have been confiscated frow many of these neonle, in -etnrn for an assurance that vie will acquiesce in the issue to such of them as are Persian subject* by birth of a 3ijil-i-Ahwal similar to that which the authorities are endeavouring to nersuade the various other Arab tribes in this district to take. 4. A copy of this despatch is bein# sent to the Honourable the ''oli+icnl Resident at '^ushire (Ho.3J?9)* I have the honour to he, H&gt;ir, Your most obedient, humble servant, sd. ‘ n J. v/ a tkir'son . H.H.Y.’s Confsul for ^hAsistan. m H!'Vleffrara xx ^rom K.W. *b Consul, ttn*az. To K,M 0 ’o Wininter, '«&gt;rr«n. NodO^ nevt.Hted to Political ^tiohire. Ho.S. T)at«?d l.Tth (received 14th J^ehruarjr 1934Q T -eferring to my deepatch Ho.10, February 6th. According to informution received frora Hohurwerah Governor continuen to terroriee village and to threaten reprisals for any who report to Consulate. * (ftame time?) physical violence in hei np used to compel Bahrainis to put thumb print on documentn of Persian nationality and more have been imprisoned and their / Bahrain documents confiscated. I have asked for the ffood of^icea of the Governor General bu f he stated that he must have instructions from r&gt; ehran. -Bri toonsul-GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. ///6-SF. 0 { 1 352 Office of the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain. Dated, Dil Qaaa 14. 1352 February 28,1954 The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, With reference to your letter No. C/lOO dated February 17,1934, I have the honour to inform you that I am awaiting fuller particulars with names and dates etc. from Qasbah; upon receipt of these particulars the matter will be referred to you again. From Bahrain To Bahrain Sir, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government.1 C/56 of 1SS4 Ohcc 4 Ucc : 4^* 3? The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Rritiah- Residency -rind Conijulato Gonm'nl, Dated...9,t,,.iCai.ch f 19^ &gt; Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. despatch No. 2G2-S of 6th March 1S24 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, * T ew Delhi, with enclosures ( 2 ) to (7). Subject. Ill-treatment Bahrain subjects in Persia. ^4 (l ,Telegram XXX From HoM’a Consul, Ahwaz© To H.M*s Minister, Tehr?*® Mo 0 15 Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire Bo® 5 Dated 24th receired 25th February 1934® Your telegram of the 15th Febraary No* lo Molestation still continues as before* victims are bei% advised to confirm to desire of local authorities# I consider action if any must be taken in Tehran# BRITCONSULCopy to the Hon 1 ble the Political Resident at Bushlre &lt;&gt;• •»&lt;&gt;••••• o • U 0 o 394 With compliments from Consul f Ahwaz© Noo 11 BRITISH CONSULATE, AHWAZ« February 15 th, 1934&lt;&gt; Sir, With reference to your telegram No. 8 of the 5th instant and to mine of today’s date, No. 10, regarding the treatment of Bahrainis by the Givernor of C^usbah, I have the honour to report that, according to information given to His Majesty’s Vice-Oonsul at Mohammerah, the persecution of these people continues® One informant exhibited marks of a lash which he stated Ihd been inflicted by an Amniah Official and h reported that similar treatment had been met with by others. It would appear , therefore, either that the Governor has gone back on his promise to stay his hand until instructions are received from Tehran, or that he has received instructions approving of his actions. 2. In accordance with your instructions I called on the Governor General and ±kx£x informed him of the reports received by me and ofjiour action inthe matter and of our desire to avoid a despute the present time. I said that I by His Majesty’s Government to be under their xmx protection and the confiscation of documents of nationality issued by the authorities in Bahrain to subjects of that country proceeding or resident abroad. had at was bound to report the artest of persons who are considered Sir Reginald H.Hoare, K.C.M.G., His Britannic Majesty’s minister, etc., etc., etc., British Legation, TEHRAN.© ' r U 4J - S l 3* I also informed the (iovernor General that it is a* longer the practive of British Consular Officials in Persia to issue papers to Bahrainis , who must obtain them direct from Bahrain, and that, in return for this forbeai -ance it was perhaps reasonable to axempt that the Persian Government shoud refrain for the oresent from giving them Persian papers until the question of their status in Persia had been decided between/the two Governments* 4* His Excellency said that he did not see that anything could be done in the matter locally, but that he would lo^k into it* I then reminded him that, according to my information, instructions wert sent to Jinx his predecessor a few years ago that the question of registration of Bahrainis was to remain in abeyance pending t;.e result of negotiations and that they should be left in peace* I am forwarding a copy of this despatch to the Honourable the iolitical Kesident at Bushire No394* 1 have the hononr to be,Sir, Your m^st obedient humble servant, A.E. WATKINSON* H.B.M's Consul for Khuzistan* fCopy to: The Hor^ble the Political Resicent. Bushire. No.396. With compliments from H.B.M.Consul, fa: Khuzietan at Ahwaz. British Consulate, AHWAZ. No. 12. February 14 th, 193&lt;±. £lr * With reference to my despatch No.11 of yesterday's cate, wnich will leave here by the same mail, I am glad to be able to report that the Governor General informed me later in the oay that the necessary instructions haa been given. I h.^ve already telegraphed to you tin this sense. As His Excellency's message was received within two hours of our conversation, it r'oulb srem th&amp;t he had found guidance in his own files, as he haa not poseibly had time to refer the matter to Tehran. 2 . I have thought it as well, for purposes of record, to allow my previous despatch to go forwaro, though this appears to be a satisfactory development. According to Captain Chauncy'e information the present Governor of Gusbah was reprimanded in lingah for carrying out a similar policy and neglecting to take ro tice of instruc tions to cease fire. I can only nope that the Governor General's present instructions are sufficiently precise ana will be obeyed. 3. A copy of this deep tch is being sent to the Honouraole the Political Resident at Buehire (No.396). I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, hurob] * servart , sd. A.E.Watkinson. H.B.M. Consul for Khuzistan. Sir 'Reginald Hoare,K.C .M.G., His Britannic Majesty's Minister, ate., etc ., etc., British legation, Tehran.ToThe Hon*ble the Political Resi dent.Bufihire(w/o enclosure) With coxoplirnentfi from Consul, Ahv.az. ^©.13 British Consulate AHWAZ. 21st February 1934 Sir Witf» ’'•fsrence to my despatch No. 12 of the 14th instant, regarding the quer»ti©nof Bahrainis resiuent in Persia, I have the honour to forward herewith a further report received from His Majesty^s Vice Consul at Moharameran. 2 . I entirely agree with the advice given by Captain Chauncy to those who came to see hio. A copy of thl*J despatch without its enclosure is being sent to Bushire, (No.427). Sir Reginald H.Hoare.K.C. # His Britanic Vajesty’s Minister, etc. , etc., etc., British Legation, Tehran. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. so. A.E.Watkinson H.B.M.Consul for Khuzistan —— —No. 2/29/139 British vi c e-Consulate # Mohammerah. February 12th, 1934. Sir, In continuation of my despatch No. 2/29/106 dated the 3rd February 1934, I havet he honour to report that several Bahrainis have againcome to me to say that after leaving them a;pcie for about a wee* the Governor of Gushah has again commenced to harass them. In addition these men report that there are two clerks from the Persian Census Department who, assisted by Ambieh Guards, arc forcibly taking their th.mb prints on declarations of Persian Nationality, and issuing them with “Bijils” accordingly. Several men who have resisted have been Jcaa beaten. One of the men who appeared before me showed me marks on his chest which he stated were the results of blows from the Amnieh Guards • They assert that they have been warned if they come to me again, their houses will be bufcnt down. 2 . 1 have informed these men who &lt;ame here that I have reported the whole matter, and that, pending its settlement if they are harassed any more thay k must take Sijils to protect themselves, but to do so only as a last resort. I pointed out tkxi that provided they have registered themselves in Bahrain, the fact ol taking Persian Sihils now under pressure should not prejudice their **mi claim to Bahrain nationality when the whole queetion ^ is settled, moreover that with a Soj il there is nothing to prevent their going to Bahrain should they wish to do so, and once in Bahrain they could throw away their Sijilis a d be Bahrainis. I stressed the point that as Bahrainis they could not hold landed property in fereia, so that they must weigh up the case forthemselves, ana decide whether their property and Ihie in Persia are worth becoming a Persian subject for, er whether they could afford to 6 ive up everu thing to be Bahrainis. ?). I was very careful to say that the forgoing was my own idea on the subject and no one else's and that no guars nteewent ;f Uh u * U was 8 lm P 1 y present t:.ey were receiving illill-treatment at the hands of the Persians and that if this continued and it cecame imperative to do simething at once, in my own opinion what I had said was the test thing to do, sj since nothing else could be done quickly enough, I aoded that the only drewbac&amp; to taking a aual nationality was that while they remained in Persia their sons would be faced with two years* complsary service in the Persian Army, and that si ce all their interests lay in Persia, this was a very small price to pay for what they received from Persia • I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. P.C.L. ChAUNCY, Uaptain, His Majesty* s Vice-Consul-© No. 2/29/142, Copy forwarded, with c ompliment s, t ethe Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, in continuation of this office Ksutaxjmenxxjk endorsement Ne* 107 dated the 3rd February 1934* Sd. F.C.L. CHAUNCY, Captain, Kis Majesty’s Vice, Consul*Copies to BUSHIRE No.21 AHWAZ ^ 9. 5th February 1*?&gt;4 My dear Minifiter, I have Just learn^t from Hif- llajeety'e ConBul at Auwaz that three Bahraini living at Oueoah have been imprisoned for not having Persian nationality papers ana the t a number of others have been threatened with a similar fate. 2. Your ^celleney will find in the aria ives of the Ministry a voluminous but not very recent covrenponoence on the subject of pressure brought to Dear on Bahrainin living in Persia t© accept Persian papers. I can say with confidence that the only effect of tnis pressure has been to cause inconvenience to perfectly harmless people and to arouse Indignation in Bahrain. I am also confident that Your Excellency will share my view that the present is a singularly inopportune moment to revive a course of action which is bound to leac t© controversy and I therefore trust that you will maa use ye?r influence t© secure ^ the release of the three men who have been imprisoned and to protect other Bahrainis from being oisquieteo. (signed) B.H.Hoare Hit Excellency Mirza Seyyid Bagher Khan Kazemt, Minister for Foreign Affaire.XX H.M.'e Coneul, Abwa^. H.M. *e Minister, Tekiran. No.16, Repeatea to Political Reeioent, Bushire. No.7, Bated btd (receivea 6th ) Marcn 193^. Witd reference to wy telegram No.15. One Balirain suoject Ifiae died at as result of beating by authorities ana another is eaic to be in a serioue conditim. In spite of aovice sent from Consulate through a compatriot from Monammerah many of these people refuse to accept Persian papers ano a petition is reported to hive been sent to Bra ikh of B&amp;nrnin. A despatch follows. - Britconsul -From No. Usfl Office of il s,r of 1352 he Adviser to The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have today received information from a reliable source regarding recent happenings in Qasbah. Hy infor mant arrived this morning from Fao where he had interviews with many of the people of Qasbah. He reports as follows. 2. TT From 13th Shaaban the Persian government officials at Qasbah have oppressed the Bahama very severely and have been forcing them to adopt Persian nationality, though in most cases they are in posses sion of Bahrain nationality certificates issued to them in Bahrain. The Persians seized the Bahrain documents and destroyed them saying that they were now of no use. 3. The Persians who carried out this work are Merthutha, Abdul Karim, Mirza Hussain and an Arab- 2 - J Arab, Abdul Redha bin Haji Salman, who works with the Persians• First they sent for the leaders of the Bahama and ordered them to give up their papers and sign Persian papers. They put police (amnia) in all the quarters of the town and the police collected the people and in one quarter the police fired shots at the baharna. This was in the Ferij Ma’liq, but nobody was shot through many people were beaten. The Bahama were driven to the government office. The following Bahama, who are important men, refused to sign any papers, Syed Jaafar bin Syed Khammis, Mahdi al lfe f atiq, Saleh bin Juma, Syed Khalaf bin Syed Taleb, and Syed Shaab bin Mahdi. Because of their refusal they were beaten and thrown into prison and on seeing this the other Bahama were afraid and fearing the same fate they submitted to the orders of the Persians, in spite of this many of them were beaten. 4. Syed Hussain bin Syed Juma, one of the Bahama, refused to give up his Bahrain paper. The Persian official Merthutha set upon him and beat him so badly that the next day he died from the wounds. Zair Mahdi and Syed Ahmed bin Syed Majid were also seriously injured as well as Mullah Abood bin Mullah Hussain of Burri (Bahrain). Eventually the Persians took almost all the Bahrain papers from the Bahama.-3- 5. The Bahama are prevented by the Police from going to Mohammerah to complain to the Consul there. 6. Some of the Bahama were taken away and sent to the Army to become soldiers. 7. The chief men of the Bahama wish to come to Bahrain themselves and appeal to Shaikh Hamad for help, they have sent a peti tion (enclosed) to him now asking him to protect them. 8. Although the Persians destroy their nationality papers and make them sign Persian papers yet the Bahama would rather die than become Persian subjects. w I gather from my informant that the Persians are anxious that their neighbours in ’Iraq should not know what is taking place as the Persians take every opportunity of assur ing ’Iraq officials that nothing whatever has occurred. During the trouble the Persians frequently asked the Bahama whether they ^ thought they were English and therefore should be protected by the English. The petition, a copy of which I enclose, is signed by the chief men of the Bahrain com munity in Qasbah. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, /f ■ Adviser to the Government.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/^oy-l.a/^. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— Tne Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gull*, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). V The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated.. the.. 14.th. .March. .19B4r. Reference to previous correspondence t ^ 2^ Political Agents Printea Letter No:C/99 of iy-2-1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No:lltfb/S.F dated 14-3-1934 from Adviser to Batirain Government. Subject. Treatment of Bahrainis at Qusbah.CONFIDENTIAL. No -G/ 119 of 1934 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Toll Meal Afrent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (JtfJ for in fo xmaMon* * 'S;,. /^/ k\ mr* Office of the -Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, CaTnp, Bahrain. mmmm. AGEN op 2 7 MAR. 1934 Mmm-, pi Dated.. 36 Reference to previous correspondence : Political Resident’s Printed Letter ^o.C/58 of 9th March 1934, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ' Subject. Despatch No.2-T dated the 20th March 19 34 to the Ill-treatment of Bahrainis Fore! 531 Secretary to the in Persia, Government of India, / r [) t 1 \ X 1 • \ v** '*The Hon’ble Lt.Col. T.C.W.Powle, CBE., To Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. The Foreign Secretary to the Govt.of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi. r / \ Dated Camp New Delhi, the 20th March 1934 Subject: Ill-treatment of Bahrainis In Persia. i 31r * I have the honour to refer to my letter No. 302-S of 8th March 1934. Before giving my views on the present situation as reported by His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz, I should like to take this opportunity of review ing the whole question as It appears to me personally. His Majesty's Minister has already been unofficially Informed of my views. 2. The oppression by the Persian Government of Bahrainis consists in conscription, the forced accept ance of Persian nationality, the confiscation of pass ports and other fonts of pressure, of which the most acute Issue Is conscription. 3. The Bahrainis who are most affected live In the Ahwaz consular district which Includes Mohammerah. The number of Bahrainis who live In this district is approximately about 8000, of which about 2300 own agricultural property, thus leaving about 5700 non property owners, namely, Mohanmerah 1700, Gusbah and suburbs Including Abadan about 4000, the balance beingbeing women and children. Those who own agricultural property have no claim on our assistance unless and until they divest themselves of their property. Should they wish to retain their property under the Persian Law they should become Persian subjects. The others, however presumably should/be protected by us so far as we are able. 4. Since our protests to the Persian Government on behalf of Bahrainis have been unavailing the question of retaliatory measures against Persian subjects in Bahrain has been considered in the past by various atthorltles from time to time. For instance, in para* graph 10 of his letter of 5th May 1931 Sir Hugh Blscoe VY* Proposed that Persians in Bahrain should be treated as Bahrain subjects. Mr Dodd in his letter of 9th Septem- ber 1931 said that this was not logical. Sir Hugh fJ' 1 Blscoe, however, in paragraph 2 of his despatch of the 6th November 1931, explained that all he meant was that the Persians in Bahrain should be subject to the Juris diction of the Bahrain courts in exactly the same way as British subjects are subject to the Persian courts. This proposal Sir Hugh Blscoe made with the object of bringing pressure to bear on the Persian Government to give better treatment to Bahrainis in Persia. Prlma facie it would be quite reasonable for us to say to the Persian Government: 'In spite of our poptests you continue to oppress the Bahrainis in Persia who are under our protection. It is unreasonable for you therefore to expect us to protect your subjects in Bahrain. And in fact we are going to do so no longer. The Jurisdiction of our Political Agent over than will be removed and they will become subject to the Juris diction of the Shaikh. He, and his people, are extremely angry at the treatment which you have been meting out to his subjects in Persia, and it is possiblepossible that he may adopt retaliatory measures, but that is your affair not ours.* Before we made this announcement - or threat - to the Persian Government, which of course we should be fully prepared to carry out, we would have to consider: (a) whether such a step suited us in Bahrain; (b) whether it would have the desired effect on the Persian Government. 5. Mr Dodd brought out one Important point in paragraph 4 of his despatch, l.e. that the claim of the Persian Government to Bahrain was involved in their treatment of Bahrainis. *To ask the Persian Government to exempt the Bahrainis (from conscription) is to ask them to abandon their claim in favour of that of His Majesty's Government.* In other words if the Persian Government do not conscript Bahrainis they acknowledge them to be foreign subjects. This being so, there is no doubt that the Persian Government will persist in their efforts to turn Bahrainis into Persian subjects, and if we are to influence the Persian Government by renrlsals, the latter will I think have to be severe and prolonged, and of such a nature that neither His Majesty's Government, nor Indeed the Shaikh, who is a humane man, could countenance. 6. As pointed out in my previous letter this question has again reached a critical form, the Persian Government having renewed their oppression with appa rently greater severity than ever, which has resulted in brutal treatment of Bahrainis causing the death of one and the maltreatment of another. Whatever may be the Persian Law in the matter there is certainly no law by which such treatment can be meted out to Individuals Presumably His Majesty's Minister would be on veryvery strong grounds In protesting most severely against such action. If no satisfaction Is obtained from the Persian Government I venture to suggest that ths advisability of using the threat of publicity, as was done In the case of the British Indian subject who was flogged^at^Charbar (yj;.dg correspondence ending with the Govt.of/letter to H.M.'s minister at Teheran, ^ No * p,148 - n of the 4th January 1931) might be con sidered. -^.i&gt;idLv_yj2.» I am of opinion that such reta liatory measures as are practicable would certainly annoy the Persian Government but would not achieve the end ve have In view, l.e.the stopping of the •ppression of the Bahrainis In Persia. With regard to the present recrudescence of Ill-treatment of Bahrainis, the only course I can suggest Is that a strong protest be addressed to the Persian Government, and that in the event of their not responding the question of suitable publicity might be considered. In conclu «loa, however, I must point out that the benevolent rule of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad under which Persians flourish In Bahrain, and the brutal treatment which Is meted out to His Excellency’s subjects In Persia, (for the protection of idiom His ajesty's Government are partly responsible), form a glaring contrast to which His Excellency Shaikh Hamad has nnt Infrequently referred, and which has an adverse effect on our prestige along the Arab littoral. I have the honour to be, Your most obedient servant, i faxcllr. Iaa Hoz, (X/vq CjvJ^ •/ ivvu‘« m, CONFIDENTIAL. No.C/125-of 1934 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- Office of the Political Residenl Reference to previous correspondence : Political Reoident’s Printed Letter Uo,C/ll9 of 1. ^ehran telegram Mo.43 of 8th March 1934. 2 . .Letter No.17 dated the 6th 3. ^ehran despatch No.112 dated the 5th March 1934 to the Foreign Office, with encloBuren. 4. Tehran despatch No.117 of 9th March 1934 to the Foreign Office. pliments to The Political Agent Bahrain and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). information. in the Persian Gulf CampN Bah mi n . 26th March 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. March 1934 from His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz to His Majesty’s Minis ter,^ehran. Ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia.To The Hoto’hle the iPolitiw-al Re si dent # Bush ire. His Wajesty’n Tf ice Consul a+ Foharnmerah. Mo.554. With compliments fran Consul at Ahv;az. BRITISH COTT^LAT^, No ,&gt; 17 o AHWAZo ITarch 6th, 1934. Sir, With reference to my telegram Mo. 16 of yesterday’s date regarding Bahrain subjects at Gusbah, 1 have the honour to report 4 hat, according to information given to Hia Majesty' s VIch Consul by Bahraini residents in Mohamrerah, a certain Seyed Hussein, claiming to be a subject of the Shaikh of Bahrain died a few days ago as the result cf beating by the -Ambieh authorities at Gusbah. Another, Sair 3aleh, is said to he in a serious condition after s imilar treatment. 2. I am now informed that the petition to the Shaikh of Bahrain referred to in my telegrrm has actually been sent . 3. On receipt of these reports 1 sent my Mead MubbM to see the Governor General, Mirza \li Mohammed Khan Oveisy expressed doubt as t o the possibility of such proceedings against Persian subjects and told the Munshi that he had already giver instructions to the 3i ji 1-i-Ahwal Beuartmen t in Ahwaz that no further att empt sr-were to be made to make the Bahraini community at Gusbah take out Persian papers until instructions had been received from Tehran. He pointed out, however, that it is a matter of great difficulty for the author i** ies to d i f f erenti ate between one Arab and another Arab possessing no document of identity, and that they all put forward claims to foreign nation ality. Sir Reginald Koare ,K.C „M.O., His Britannic Majesty's Minister, etc. ,e+ c. ,etc .,nationality. It seans possible that the Gove'nor General’s instructions were never coinrnunicated to Gnsbah, as there v;as no postal or telegraphic service from Ahwaz ■for sane days after I last had occasion to see him* 4 e Oveisy telephoned yesterday to the Governor of Abadan in the presence of my Munshi instructing him to go to Gusbah at once and to report ihe whole question of the treatment of ^ahraihis and other Arabs, and in particular as to whether any had beer, imprisoned or beaten, or had died. If so, he v.as to inform the Governor that Persian subjects could not be so treated.. He was further to instruct the Governor of Gusbah that no further measures are t o be taken by the 3ijil-i-Awal authorities pending the receipt of further instructions from 'ehran . 1 presume in view of this that the Governor General is himself referring the matter to Tehran. I am forwarding a copy of this despatch to +he Honourable the Political Resident xn at Hushire ltfo.553J. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, ed. A. 13 .Wat kin son . f s Consul fo r Khuzis tan .CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/360-1 .^/E. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gull', at Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated... S' 1 Reference to previous correspondence : This petition (in Arabic) was attached to the Adviser to the Bahrain Governments letter No:118b/S.F datea the iwarcn 1934 (see Printed Letter No:C/^09-l/a.B datea the 14th March 1934 from the Political Agent.Bahrain. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Translation of petition dated the 13th uhil Qa T d 13b^ from the Bahrain subjects residing at ^usbah to His Excellency Shaifh Hamad bin T Isa Al Khalifah. Subject. Ill-treatMiiii of Bahrain subjects in Persia. V '' !73 7S R- CONFIDENTIAL. No. 349-3 of 1934. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The -Political Aerent, Bahrain r and has the honour to transmit to him a co ment (s). ^ or information* British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. docu- Dated.. . A?. 5 ; *1 19 34. Reference to previous correspondence '-f 4o Political Resident’s Printed Letter No,C/125 of R7th March 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Despatch No. 21 dated the 12th March 1934 from His Majesty’s Ill-treatment of Consul, Ah v?az, to His Majesty’ 3 Minister Tehran. Bahrainis in Persia. Despatch No.22 dated the °7th March 1934 from His Hajestv’s Consul,Ahwaz, to His Majesty’ 3 Minis ter Tehran* • • a, l (i&gt;/MThe H 0 n’hie the -^oliMcal ■^©Bident, ^ushire. Mo*600 o Ifie Majesty’s ^ice-Consul, Mohamnerah. No.601. With conplinrnts fron Ti.T’.K. British Consulate, Consul for Khtizistan at Ahwaz. AHWAZ. No. qi. 12th March IP34, 3ir, With reference to ray despatch No*17 of the 6th instant, re^ardinp the nonition of Bahraini residents at Gusbah, I have the honour to report that the Govern or General no-w tells rae that the Governor of Abadan has been to Gusbah and he states that no oersons have been beaten or imprisoned and no Bahraini has died or been injured. The Governor General therefore has ashed ne to supply further information regarding the men who are alleged to have been ill-treated. I have been able to supply the name of the man who is said to have died, which is Seyed Hussein, son of Seyed Tun*ah. According to Captain Chauncy’s information, which he is perfectly satisfied is based on good authority, the man was in possession of a document of Bahrain nationality issued the authorities there. Captain Chruncy is equally satisfied that the incidents complained of have actually taken place. 2. 1 ^ot consider that anv useful purpose would be served by a personal visit to Gusbah either on ray part or on that of Cant* in Chauncy until it is known whether the -Persian Government in ^ehran does or does not agree to maintain the status quo in accordance with their former undertakings or unless the interests of the Shaikh of Bahrain require specific information fron Gusbah. 1 have advised Captain Chauncy accordingly. In the meanwhile the Political Agent at Bahrain/ Sir Heginald H.Hoare,KCMG. , His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc. etc. etc. , British Legation, TEHRAN.Bahrain is 'beinfr asked to verify the details of the documents of the dead man, Seyed Hussein, son of Seyed ^um'ah, and of the injured man, Zai r 3aleh, son of Haj i iTun’ah. 3. A copy of this despatch is heing sent to the Honourable the Political Hesident in the Persian ^ulf at '^ishire (No*600) e I have the honour to he, Sir, Hour most obedient, humble servant, sd. A„E.Watkin son, H.H.H.Consul for Khuzistan.Hie Kon’ble the Political ^esidett in the Persian Oulf.'Bughire.i'Jo^^? ^is Majesty*g Mice Consul, Wohanmerah. No.B7« e Vith cornplinent s from H, 'B.M. Consul for Khuziatan at Ahwaz* 'British Consulate, AHWAZ* ^’’th March, 19 34. With reference to your d h Wo.?4 of the 9th instant and to nine of the 13&lt;h (No. SI). I have the honour to report that the Governor General still insists that the incidents reported as having occurred at Guubah are without foundation. he has no doubt reported accordingly to “Tehran and the re-ly to any representations made to the &gt;*ereian Governnent win he based on this report. A reply has now been received from the Political Aaent at Bahrain from which it appears that 3eyed Hussein, son of Geyed .Tun’ah, and Zair Saleh, son of Haji Jun’ah, were both born in Bahrain and were both in possession of papers of nationality issued by the authorities there, .there is therefore no question of dual nationality in those two cases. 3. Zair Gal eh reported to His Majesty’s v iC( . Consul at Moharmerah a few days a*o. I happened to be there and saw him. He is an elderly nan of respectable and serious appearance. He stated that his documents were taken from him four -rears apro but he hasnot been furnished with Persian papers. As he is one of the elders of the communtty endeavours were made recently, first in a friendly wav and la+-r bv threats, to induce him to persuade other younger men/ r p -e£inald H*Hoare,KClfG., His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc B , etc. , etc. t British -bepation, '’eh ran.wen to 'olace their thiinb prints on applications for a Persian H sj,iil T, 0 H© y;as ■oromiaed further exernntion himself if he would do so,, He refused. Ix e was later ordered to sipn these applications as a witneos and ap:ain refused, whereupon he was knocked down by four Arabieh fria^ds in the presence of the nead o^ the '♦^ijil*’ department and was struck with the butt of their rifles. He reported all this to Captain C^auncy in a perfect!- coin and dispassionate manner, and there seems no reason for doubtinp that it is an exact description of what has been occurring recently. A signed statement is in Captain Channel's possession, ^e was examined by Dr.T) f Souza, the Consulate doctor, who found no traces left of any bruises. Others have exhibited marks probably caused by blows. 4. Zair Saleh further reported that he was unable Owing to nis injuries to attend the funeral of Seyed Hussein, hut that manv Persons in Ousbah were present. Seyed Hussein was a man of fifty five who succumbed four or five dav 3 after he had been treated similarly to himself. 5. Since the visit of the Governor of Abadan to Gusbah an officer of Amnieh took a statement from Zair Saleh which he was not asked to sign. H e reports that from then onwards there has been no further trouble at Gusbah, and no more complaints have been received through other channels. 1 have the honour t o be, Sir, i -our most obedient, humble servant, sd. A.TU.Watkinson, H.P.M.Consul for Khuzistan.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. 7 No. J? - s ' 0 f 1353 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Bated, Muharram l',?-, 1353 April 1?^ 1934 Prom The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. r&amp;9B2M&amp;2&amp;L AXX BnhttrnKli of 4j,4tG : -. ;xvh Bio BsooUtnoy Zl&amp;iMki HomA bio Uoa ol JQuOifcai # Ruioo of Bahrain. Vi ill duo reo^ooto* In continuation of our proTious potition wo bog to submit in tOin petition Uut wo t your oubjooto who nro rooiding in ^oabaH 9 etiii on^riiinoo troubio from Uio uo i^oroiuno wOo foroibiy rogiotor/ond «ri«n cugr one of uo refua 00 to do ao they boot dim and put him in prison. *e hure already imonaoo you of too amount of trouble uni oh they created to us. They nttooicod us in our houses and toon nwoy our nationality doeumento, ami wo are disturbed about tnsir iutentiun and are afraid lost they might taae away our sons for UBiOi(military service). 0 9 4ust 9 yon fivro our Eulor and would not agree that your subjects bo maltreated when their subjects are enjoying peace and order in your country. **e request you to eavt us soon from this trouble and to prevent the tyranny exercised by this tyrannical Coveroaent against us. hen from among us hove died and our sons have dispelled on account of fright. O’ just, have mercy on uo ana save your subjects from the unjust for Ood will help you ae you help us. *e request you to save us soon. Bated the 13th haul fiijjah 135£(i.e. Steth oar oh ie94)« Sd. 3aiyid uallh sin halyld Xusuf al Uusawl uaiyid dbmad bin ^aiyld h«gid HajjI 9 Isa bin H*s^i Badr hajji Ibrahim bin &gt;bgji Badr ^air Ta f qub bln rusuf Baiyid as wad bin ^aiyid Hasan ihir Kajab bin 9 Abdullah Thumb impression oft* huhammad bin &gt;alih O hu Husain f Ali 9 all us*oaiih Kadi Hcgji iiuiuiin i»aiyid Talib Uiiyid Hajid i p.t.o.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/423-1, a/2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Eonourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahkarn. vLJ and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). 2. Endeavours are being made to ascertain (a) if all the signatories are Bahrain subjects and (b) how many of them are land-holders. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated... 22n&amp;. April . .1.934,.. Reference to previous correspondence : Residents Printed Letter No:349-S dated 13th April 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Translation of two petitions submittec to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Usa Al Khalifah by the Baharnah of Ousbah. Ill-treatment ol Banrain subjects residing at i^usbah p{f- ~ - I re: \#v 3 1 Hi r wV w r ' «' r /No:C/429-l.a/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd April 1934. To, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. / Memorandum . ' A’ith reference to your letter No:9/S.F dated the 2nd Muharram 1353 (the 16th April 1934) enclosing two petitions irom the people of Qasbeh and to my conversation with the Adviser before his departure, I should he glaa if you would inform me whether all the signatories are Bahrain subjects ^and have Bahrain nationality papers and how many of them hold land in Persia. 2. In the meantime a translation of the two petitions has been sent to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. tifo Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. i. i &gt; V If! rMS So. S.101.S/34. The for«ign Sooretary to tbo OoTerment of India, Tha Under Secretary of State for India, Solitlcal Department, India Office, LOXOOS. Sated Sew Delhi, the / April 1954. ?.a I am directed to refer to Despatch Ho* 2-Te, dated the 20th March 1934, from the Political Hesideat in the Persian Gulf to my address (with copy to the Secretary of State for India) on the subject of ill- treatment of Bahreinis in Persia. After perusing this Despatch and also Tehran Despatches Hos. 112 and 117 on the same subject, the GoTernment of India are of opinion that no final solution of this question is possible unless and until the Persian Gorexnment abandon their olaim to Bahrein and adait the separate existence of Bahrein nationality. It is clear that such an admission can only be secured as the result of the conclusion of a general treaty between His Ifejesty’s Government and the Persian Government, which appears unlikely to be achieved in the near future. It therefore rasa ins to be considered whether any effective action oan be taken to prevent the officials of the Persian Government from ill-treating Bahreinis resident in Persia in the meantime. As His Majesty's Government will remember the expedient of retaliatory aotion against Persian subjects in Bahrein was considered in 1932 and it was then decided that it cohid not be usefully adopted. The Political Resident now 4 /J• 2 • 6 aow suggests that, as an alternative to retaliatory action, protests, if they prove ineffectual, should fce followed by a threat of publicity, which proved efficacious on a previous occasion. The Government of India feel that the circumstances, in which the threat of publicity was used before, were very different and they fear that the Persian Government night even welcome publicity in the case of Bahrein in order to ventilate their own grievances. They do not therefore endorse the suggestion and agree with His Majesty's Minister that nothing can be done except to make further protests. They also agree with the views expressed in paragraphs 6 and 7 of Tehran Dee fate h Bo. 112 as to the attitude which Bahrein subjects permanently residing or owning land in Persia should be advised to adopt. Copy for information to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf By ., A copy of this letter is being sent to Hie Majesty's Minister, Tehran and to the Hon'ble the Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. (with one s.c.)A No. W/*r' Of 1353 Office of/the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Maharam, 14. 1353 April, 29, 1934. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum With reference to your letter No. C/429-la/2 dated 22nd April, 1934, I should be much obliged if you wouldAeitner send me copies of the two petitions from the people of Qasbah^or return me the petitions in original in order that I may go into the matter. 2. The petitions were forwarded to you in original and no copies were kept in my^office. fxj^Adviser to the Government. V , a 7 ~~Confidential. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd May 1934. iNo: C/480-1, a/2. To, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum. ^ « Your Memorandum Ko:48/SF dated the 29th April 1934. The two petitions received with your letter i\’o:9/SF anted the 17th April 1934 are returned in original. It is requested that they may be carefully safeguarded and returnee to me in case it may be necessary to produce them at some later date. V Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent,Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No -. 7*?/S ' F ' o? I2b3 Office or ahe Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, ?!aharam 25, 1353 May 10,1934. 'Tith reference to your letter No. c/429-l/a/2 dated 22nd April, 1934, all the signatories are Bahrain subjects and own property in Persia. aII of them have nationality papers with the exception of a few against whose names I have put an asterisk. Their names could not be traced in our register. I am returning herewith the two petitions. H. B. M f Bahrain. M T s Political Agent, Memorandum: CoT' Adviser to the Government. Enclos.Confidential. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th May 1934. No:C/524-1.a/2. To, The Adviser to the Bahrain G-overnraent, Bahrain. Memorandum. Your Memorandum iNo:79/S.F dated the 10th May 1934. whether it is quite certain that those persons whose names are marked with asterisks in the two petitions (enclosed for reference) are Bahrain subjects. If there is any doubt, it would be better to say so, as if it is stated definitively that they are Bahrain subjects and if subsequently doubt is shown to exist, the case for helping Bahrain subjects would be weakened. It is requested that you will kindly inform me Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.&amp; n Csi GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. Confidential: H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN. THIS SECRETARIAT, BAHRAIN. 2^rd May, 193^., 8th Safar,.l3^*&gt; MEMORANDUM t- ^ In reply to your No«C/524—1 .a/2,, of the ^6— which relates to the signatories of the two enclosed petitions; I have referred the point which you kindly raise to the Shiah Qadhi of Sinabbis, who, I understand, is the best acquainted with these individuals. I enclose herewith for your inspection his reply to the effect that there is no doubt that these signatories are Bahrain subjects. for Adviser to The Government of Bahrain. -A -vCONFIDENTIAL GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER IN % B,—This is an GRJGJjS AL MTzSSAGJU, sent by 'post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities il is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] of 25th April 1934 to the Foreign Office, copy of which I enclose. I presume that Sir Reginald Hoare’s assumption is correct and that the Bahrain Government will not deprive of their Bahrain nationality those Bahrain subjects who in order to continue owning land in Persia, become Persian subjects. It would appear that these individuals would possess a dual nationality, Persian in Persia and Bahraini outside it. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, H.M.S. w Bideford M at Sea. From Repeated to Secretary of State for India, L To Political Resident Political Agent, Bahrain. Government of India, Simla. His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz, with reference to Minister’s request to send copies of Bushire letters on the subject of Bahrainis in Persia to this Officer. No. C/210 of 1934. Dated 15th May lOTi 4 . Subj ect x Treatment of Bahrainis in Persia. Reference paragraph 2of India Office letter ^o.P.Z.2569/34 ATTESTED . sd. T.C.Fowle, Lt.-Colonel,• Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 7 f.6 DCF V- 156SS&amp; P— (M-l82 1)— 27-9-32—2,60,000.P. Z. 2569 / 3 A-. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, S. W. 1. 25 th April Sir, Jit With reference to corre&amp;pondence ending with the G-overnment of India's letter of Jth April a copy of which w as forwarded w r ith India Office printed letter P* S. 2569/^4-&gt; of 19 th April, on the subject of the ill- treatment of Bahreinis in Persia, I am directed by the Seci’etary of State for India to s ay that after careful consideration of the views of the Pelitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, His Majesty's Minister at Tehran, and the Government of India, he agrees with the Government of India that no action can usefully be taken intthe matter vis-a-vis the Persian Government at the present time, except to make further protests. Sir Samuel Hoare would therefore suggest that if the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs sees no objection, His Majesty's Minister at Tehran should now be instructed to make strong representations to the Persian Government against the recent ill-treatment of Bahreinis by the local Persian authorities at Gusbah which resulted in the death of one Bahreini and serious injury to another, and te remind the Persian Government, if he sees no objection, of the promise made by the Minister of Court to Sir Robert Clive in 1929 . On the other hand, Sir Samuel Hoare, while in favour of immediate action on these lines, equally shares the opinion of the Government of Indik that no final solution of the/ The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, V s. vu 1?7 the qiestion of the position of Bahreinis in Persia is possible unless and until the Persian Government abandon their claim to Bahrein and he does not consider the present case of sufficient importance to justify His Majesty’s Government in pushing matters to such extremes as to provoke a serious rupture with the Persian Government* 2. Prom the despatch of 6th March from His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz, a copy of which was enclosed in Tehran despatch N».117&gt; of Jth March, it seems possible that the action of the local authorities to compel Bahreinis to take out Persian nationality documents may for the present at any rate have ceased. While the Secretary of State considers that His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran should continue in future to protest against any case of persecution of Bahreinis in Persia by the Persian authorities, he agrees with the view of the Government of India and His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran that Bahrein subjects permanently residing or owning land in Persia would serve their own interests best by accepting Persian nationality - particularly if the Political Resident confirms Sir R*Hoare’s assumption that this will not involve forfeiture of their Bahrein nationality. He considers however that it would be preferable, with a view to avoiding any misunderstanding of our attitude in the matter, that advice to this effect which may be given by His Majesty’s Consular Officers should be given informally on the lines adopted by Captain Chauncy and reported in his letter of 12th February to His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (S&lt;U J. c. WALTON.iiiT -* 3 * rv vonfiCBnti&amp;l . No:C/547-l.»/2, &lt;s&gt;_ 9jg Political A^eac/ t Bahrain, the 2hth iajr 1934« Lieut-Golonel Gordon Loch. i.A Political Agent, . earain# The Honourable the Political Heaiaent in the Persian Gulf, Bashirs* abject :- ill-treatment of in Persia. 'I £3 1 hare the honour to refer to the second paragraph of a/ Printed Letter No:C/423-i/a.2 dated the 2£nd April 1934, enclosing a translation of two petitions received bj His Lxoeileuc/ Shaikh iiaaad bin Usa Al Khalif&amp;h froa Bahrain subjects residing at ^usbah. 2. The Bahrain Government state tnat ail the signatories Bahrain subjects and tnat the,y own propert/ in Persia. 3. The majority are known to be in possession of Bahrain nationality papers, but the following cannot be traced Bahrain Government Register:- 51 ;d; Abood bin Stilish Husain. Majid bin Abid. m bin liumeid. Jasim b: , iialli Jasia al Mullah Hus&amp;in&lt; 'All bin Pair Radhi. Khalil bin v 0b&amp;id. J'.aadhan bin Ibrahim. J&amp;sim bin Husi&amp;id. Haaaadi Hajji Cousin, nyub bin rusuf. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Political Lieut-Colonel, Agent, Bahrain. rCONFIDENTIAL. N'15-B/bl5.3 of 1934. IS' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. Hie Majesty'a Minister, Tehran* /^. /S--/&amp; 2. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London* 3* The Foreign secretary to the GoTernment of India, Simla* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. Dated. 2nd JUKE 1934. Reference to previous correspondence: r ^ Residency Printed Letter Ko.l2-B/413-S of 1st Lay 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. w Letter No*C/&amp;47&lt;-l*a/2 dated the 26th May 1934 from the Politloal Agent, Bahrain* Copy forwarded, with com] Agent, Bahrain, for Subject. Ill-treatment of Bahrain subjects residing at qUSBAH* pliments, to the Political information* Ijwf jv|i&gt; —- ; r - CONFIDENTIAL. X 0 . 545-S of 1934. /(yo Tlie Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment {/Y for favour of his views. British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated, 8th June 1934. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Government of India, Foreign and Political Department Express Letter Ho.F.10l-N/34 of 30th May 1934. Subject. Ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia. (&gt;Caufliisaiial GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Foreign and Political T , DEPAR 1'MENT. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B % This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa&gt; e lime and formalilies it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] From foreign, Simla. To Britconsul, Bushire. H No. F.101-N/34. DatoJ the ^ May ^4 Please furnish your views at an early date on Foreign Office letter No2633/1561/91.dated 9th May 1934,regarding the ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia, a copy of which has been sent t6 you by the India Office under their printed letter No. P.Z.3144/34,dated 18th May 1934. THi ISSUf OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Sd.0„K.Garoe, Deputy Secretary to-the Government of India. s. 6. M FP —785S&amp;P—(M-1814)—3 8-8-33— 2 . W,000.m «l •V CONFIDENTIAL. C/241 of 1934. to^. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, Dated 12th June 1934 f. 100 s Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter Ro.545-S of 8th June 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject- Foreign Office letter No.E 2633/1561/91 of 9th Ill-treatment of Bahrainis May 1934 to the India in Persia. Office. T~l«m «r* l»«wa t mkR wrald net be ^ueeeeafniiy ahailenc»A in the event of *n a^penl to an Int*rn*t1oaai tribunal. A* Meanwhile, looking at the aatter froa oaite wether oarl*. St tenet be rentoberetf that even If contrary te exjwotntloa. the Perelaa Oevernneiit la enoh elrcmmetanoee fnllet to uum thle argtment, «M ngreoA to rtf«r« the 'Sahrolale” la m foreigner*, the 1 me late ef fect - iouIA be to deprive of their a*&lt;ut* of livelihood the not Inoonctderable proportion of theee people who owa ogrloaltarol property, since foreigner* are not aUewed to hold real •state la Ptrola, r. It lo ooaoe Ivable that la the proposed &gt;uielo- lertlaa general treaty »ettlew«nt, ehonia It ^S-'b* oonoloded, a epeaial olimee might be laeerted, enabling peraons (of whatever age) reatdent la 3P*rala utd olalain Bahraini fleeaeat oa the father•• »id« to opt for the rellasnlutewnt of Perolaa nationality within a given period, Sat in view of the Jemima 'JovernHent*e preooeapotion with * e proble» of ' :«an»power*, and of their natural objeotioa to the jreaenoe of large peraamat ooloale* af forelgaem oa sf,,lir e®H# It may be taken a* oertaln that a proposal to Invert onoh a olsnee wonld Inoresae oonsldorably the already formidable difflonltles of the treaty aegotlatlona, h, the national ctatao af three wo«eall«d bahraialo' appe am. then, to be briefly that whtU their right to alaim tahrolni nationality 1* In the majority of oaaea very doubtful, their Pemlan nationality In the eyen -Rlen law la ladlepntable now. and would be equally indisputable were Mrala ta withdraw her alaim to Bahrain, At beet, n oertaln proportion of them are of dual nationality whioh one be of little benefit to thorn elnoe their 'mnater nationalityINDIA OFFICE, LONDON, ,2s 1 3 jijn. lysi Forwarded with the eornpliments of tlie Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by ^ Mail. rietuP.Z.3604/34. FQREIGH OPPICE, S.W.l (E 2953/1561/91) 2 9th 1934. My dear Gilbert, We sent you privately on the 14th May a copy of Ho are f s latest despatch (No.182 of the 12th April) on the subject of Bahrainis at Gusbah. In the Ahwaz despatch (No.22 of 27th March) enclosed therein, paragraph 2, Watkinson says tint there is no question of dual nationality in the case of the tv/o principal victims, Sayid Hussein and Zair Saleh. It certainly seems most probable that these two people were in fact Bahrainis and were not Persians, but it is perhaps worth pointing out nevertheless that, on the fact available, this is no more than a probability. If the fathers of these two men were born in Persia, and resided there at the age of eighteen, the sons (i.e. the victims in the present affair) would by Persian law be Persian subjects not withstanding the fact that they were born outside Persia. 3. In other words, the victims may possibly be of dual nationality quite apart from the Persian claim to Bahrain. 4. Very likely this point has already occurred to you independently, but as you will shortl^be replying officially to our letter No.E.2633/l56l/91 of the 9th May it seemed worth drawing your attention to it. Tours ever, (SD.) GEORGE EENDEL. J.G.Laithwaite, Esq.Translation. »Ve beg to inform your honour that we have been subjected to a great trouble and aggression by the Persian Officials. They confiscated our papers (Nationality certificates ?) which were given to us by the Bahrain government and in the absence of our sons they got them registered. They (Persians) regist ered some by force, attacked them in their houses, imprisoned and beat them® A witness by name Saiyid Kusain bin Jum f ah who was born in Bahrain was killed. Petitions were previously submitted to you requesting that you will save us from the trouble which they have been creating for us and to defend our case, an act of kindness lor which we would be grateful, he expected to get the pass or that an advocate is appointed to defend us against the trouble to which we have been subjected oj them(persians) who have also threatened to do more harm to us. he are now like prisoners on account of the threat anclinsult whicli have received whereas their subjects are enjoying peace and rest in your country. Luring the last five years we never enjoyea rest or peace and we have no mere patience and no hope for anything, he know that you can settle our matters with them and that any one who is under your protection will not be subjectioAo humiliation and trouble, ^ut to our bad luck you appear to have over looked our case. If we have no one to defend our case and no pass witn us and that we cannot seek protection under you, we request you to obtain permission for us to remove our - ^milies from dersia and thus leave our properties oehind and go to any place which you fix for us, where we can settle down and live with our families rather than to leave our nationality and become Persians and have our sons embrace the Persian nationality. By the Bahranah of *asabah,Persia Bated the ICth Labi-al-Auwal 1353(the 28th June 1934). P.TO.. tv, @ T^iislation of letter dated, the 30th Rabi *-al-Auwal 1353 t- e '“j ^ 19^4; from His Excellency Ohaikh Hamad bin ah,C.o. 1.,Suler of Bahrain to H'.,(orth Hs.uire, i*C.S., Political agent,Bahrain. After Compliments, This is to inform you that I have received a petition fiom my subjects who are residing in ^asabah, Persia, in which tney complain of the treatment of the Persians. I enclose, .iere.;ith, the petition and request that you will assist them in any manner which you may deem fit. Usual Ending.Translation. H'rv » To Lated the 15th n&amp;bi T al Auwal 1353(27.5.1934) his Excellency shaikh liamad bin f Isa al Khalifah After due respects, «Ve are your Bahrain subjects who are residing in ^asabah,Persia. Previous to this we wrote you petitions and asked you to save us from the trouble and harm which the Persians have been doing to us. They purposely try to create all sorts of troubles for us and we anticipate to get more harm, he are also afraid that they will take away our sons for military service as they have registered most of them in their absence. They also killed Saiyid Husain bin Gaiyid Jum T ah because he refused to get himself registered as a Persian. This is what has happened to him. he trust that you will not agree that your subjects should be subjectec to humiliation and aggression and injustice. Before this we wrote to you and to the Adviser that we cannot enjoy rest unless there be some one to defend us or that we be given pass in our hand from the Consul in Uuham;.iarah, but nothing was done for us. You are aware that we were imprisoned, beaten, attacked in our houses and our nationality papers, which you gave to us, v/ere taken away, while we did not change our nationality, he find that the Persian subjects are enjoying peace and rest in your country, he expect that a person who considers you to be his father(over-lord) and who is under the British protection will not be subjected to injustice and that his rights will not be lost nor any one will venture to do harm to him. h^ however, did not get any assistance or given protection by you which fact we attribute to our bad luck. If you cannot see your way to protect us in Persia we request you to let us know and to obtain permission for us to leave our properties and dwelling places —— ■places and to emigrate to any place which you fix for us to live in with our families. have no more patience and no power to defend ourselves any longer. Luring the last five years we tried, to defend ourselves 'but the result was that we have suffered all this trouble. By your Baharanah subjects who are residing in v^asabah, Persia. ° ^ahmud bin T Abdullah Saiyid la T pub bin Laiyid Yusuf T Abbud bin hajji T Ali Jasim bin Ilumaiyid / Ahmad bin Salih ^ Shawi bin T Abdullah Suwaiyid bin Jasim f Abdul hasan bin T Abdun Labi ^ T Abbud bin Ibrahim LIusa bin^ Ibrahim lihalil bin Ibrahim iluhammad bin Badhwan T Abbas bin Salman Llusa bin Ahmad v Ahmad bin Ilajii T Ali Jabir bin T Aobas' / T Ali bin T Alwan Zair Yahdi bin^La T tu^ / Yusuf bin Ilajji Ilasan ^ T Abdullah bin Uakki J Ibrahim Uakki xSiu.ioi C-jnf Iccatl; 1. NoJC/GTJ’-l.a/a. Polltloel Agency, Bahrein, the 15th July le - '-*. Frocs- To:- Sir, No:C/ai0^dated the 15th '»&amp;? iyS4 r&lt;jigArding the ill-tp#et»ent of iiahp&amp;inls In Persi*. S* I Hl» ExceileRcy Ehtlkfc *ii*KUiQ bi:i , Is» Ai &amp;h*lifah this nornlng (3 5th July) *nd put up to hiE the suggestion R»cie in the letter froin His Kt.jtfSty^ Vice-Consul, Moh^?tinfer6h, lto:£/@u/lS9 deted the 12tt February 1^X4, regRrcing the adoption of i‘ersl*n nationality hy IVihrainia settled in Persia. Kla 3 xceilt ncy *tfr«ed thet It aes the tost aultuble answer which could have been given and he also said trust he would still consider as his subjects any Bahrainis trno had registered as Persians. 5. Afterwards 1 sew three Belireinis of Qusbah netted, Zair 'Abood, £aiyid Hsdi and Saiyid ’Alawi. These threa mn had previously seen Capt&amp;in Chiursccy at Mohsaasrah* I repeated his suggestion to the® end carefully refrained froa expressing any hopes that the matter would be settled quickly, but I suggested to them that in view of tho fact that they would not lose their Bahreini status outside Persia and that they would &amp;• fcorth Esquire, I.C.S., Officiating rolitic&amp;l Agent, Bahrein* The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Tll-trefitmrnt of Batobittls itt Ijiral^. I h^re the honour to refer to your Express setter— © I w be rflieved of trouble inside Persir, t*o years 1 military service which their sons would hav# to undergo might be worth cons leering* 4. They asked mo why subject* of &amp;lng Bln Sa f ud were not treated in the same way as they had been and why they should be considered as Persian subjects and often registered a* Persian subjects without their \nowlcdg©# Before I replied I iound that they knew of the dispute between the British aovernment and Persia regarding the status of Bahrain* I endeavoured to explain to them the Persian Nationality u. w and that their position was maae sore difficult by this dispute* X am afraid that they did not seem to understand waat was a^ant by a nationality law ana they considered that as thc?y were the subjects of iii« KxcciU.ncy ohaikh Hamad bin f Iu* A1 khaiifah arid under our protection they could not be I ersian subjects as well* f ^ 5* I am forwarding under Printed better two further petitions received regarding the treatment of Bahrainis in Persia* I have the honour to be \b3 CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/673-1.a/2. IT-' $7 0 tO'r The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—■ The honourable the Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf7 Bushire• and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated. .L5.th ..July. 1934.. Reference to previous correspondence : -if /K&gt; Political Agent f s letter iNotC/672-1.a/2 of 15-7-1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ^ P»' v 1). Petition dated 87/7/34 submitted by Bahrain subjects residing at Qusbah, to his Excellency Shaikh hamad bin •Isa A1 Khalifah. 8 ). Petition dated 88/7/34 submitted by Banrain subjects residing at Qusbah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Ill-treatment of Bahrainis residing In Persia. -do- I \—— — 3 Translation of petition dated ihe 11th Rabi’-al-Auv/al 1353 (the 24th June 1934) from the Baharnah of Qasabah to Colonel Loch, Political A^ent,Bahrain® After due respects, We beg to inform you that we have suffered ill-treat ment and trouble by the Persian G-overnment. They took away our nationality papers which we got from the Bahrain Government. They beat our notables and imprisoned them because they refused to register themselves as their subjects and we are still afraid that they will take away our sons for military service, me are sure that the just British Government are able to save us from this tyrannical Government and,there fore, request you, 0, just, to have mercy on us and to give our case a kind consideration as we have no one to hel^us besides God and yourself. The Persians are enjoying peace in your country whereas we suffer inj^utice. 0 ? just, do help us and oave us Irom the hands of the unjust and you will no doubt be compensated by God for your kind act. We request vou to reassure/lor we have properties, for which we are in possession oi documents from the Persian Government that they shall have no interference with the uai^ranah, copy of which was sent to the Adviser. We request you to give us an assurance to enable us to live in our places and to save our sons, as you are able to -ciVl us, you are responsible before God about us. Zair^Muhammad bin oalih s Haiji Ibrahim bin Hajji Badr y Zair Rajab bin T Abdullah* Baiyid Balih bin oaiyid Yusuf* Saiyid Ahmad oaiyid ^ajid^ Saiyid nandal bin Saiyid f Ali* Zair f Ali bin Salih J ’Isa bin hajji khan.,* Saiyid ’Alawi Saiyid Radhi* ’Abdur R&amp;sux haiji ibrahim^ Hajji ’.sa bin gajji Baar- Zair Husain bin Muhammad* Zair Ahmad Hajji ’All ^ Muhammad ’Ali ’Alwan bin Ahmad - Salman bin_Ahmad ’Abbud Laiji Hasan Saiyid falib Saiyid Majid Saiyid Hashim Saiyid ’As^ur Salman bin Hajji MuhsinCONFIDENTIAL. No. C/679-1.a/2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Busnire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated.. i7tbrJuiy*i934 - : Reference to previous correspondence : Political Agent’s Printed Letter I»oiC/673 of 15-7-1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Petition signed by twenty Bahrain subjects residing at Qusbah. Subject. Ill-treatment of Bahrainis residing in Persia.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. — This is an OHIO INAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary matt and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, imth the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.] J 661-3 of 1934. Doled 13th July 10 34. Political Resident, Bushi Governaent of India, Simla. Refe*&amp;cg* l '* cd Secretary of State for India, London, i olitical A^ent, ^&gt;alirIi*. \r Subject: Ill-treatment of Bahrainis — in Persia. ; fbt Reference Foreign and iolitical Hepartmeiit .x Letter ro.F#101-N/34, dated the 30th £3ay 1934. 2 • The laain point at issue dealt with in Forei gn i v c letter referred to is the extent to which His Majesty *s Govern ment can espouse the cruse of Bahrainis in t'ersi^ who arc ill- treated by the i ersian Government. 3. as is pointed out in paragraph 2 of tha foreign Office latter No.a 2623/1561/91 of 9th Kay 1934 certain assumpUons have of recent years been made in this cora.ectio.. »,jiich are summarised as follows: (1) That His Majesty’s Government were legally justified in espousing the Ccuse of tiie Bahrainis residei^t in Khu^istan, (Signature) V 'dr\ ( 2 )/ S. 44. DCJFP—11243&amp;P—(M'1314)—4-8-3212,000, ( Designation)(2) That the troubles of these Bahrainis were attributable chiefly If not wholly to the dispute regarding the Persian Government's claim to Bahrein, and (3) That these people would cease to oe molested If the Persian government could be Induced to renounce that claim* 4* What does, as pointed out In Foreign Cilice letter under reference, nullify these assumptions is the fact that by the Persian Nationality Lav (paragraph 4 of Foreign Office letter) even If the Persian claim to Bahrain were withdrawn, It would still be open to the Persian Government to claim Bahrainis In Persia under the said Law. From another point of view, too, (Foreign Office letter, paragraph 6)ev*n if the Persian Govern ment agreed to regard the Bahrainis In Persia as foreigners, those concerned who own land would lose their me^ns of liveli hood, since foreigners are not allowed to hold real estate In Persia* 6* Ther^ is no actual Bahrain Nationality Law. Neverthe less It may bs assumed that even without such a law Bahrainis (on the analogy of 'Jus soli') have a claim to be Bahrain subjects* This, however y does not help very much, since, whatever their claims may be, as pointed out in paragraph 8 of Foreign Office letter, most Bahrainis In Persia would be of dual nationality and while in Persia their master nationality would have to be Persian* 6* There must be however some Bahrainis who come to Persia temporarily, like any other foreigner, to seek work as coolies, small shopkeepers, etc* These individuals would not/-3- not hav« dual nationality but aould ba Bahraini*, and it la on their behalf that Hi* Majesty's Governmeixt could preaiuoably make representations. But it is this class of individuals that the Persian Government claim as their subjects on the basis or their claim to Bahrain* sd* T# C« Bowie, Lt•-Colonel| Political iiesldent in the Persian Gulf*CONFIDENTIAL. No. 758-S *f 1934. 150 ' ) The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1* His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London* 2* The Foreign Secretary to the GoTernnent of India, Simla* 3* His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaa* ^/4* The Political Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). — British Consulate-General,Confidential. Ibl © From To No. 17-B of 1934. British Residency &amp; Conuililate General, Bushire,the 6th August 1934. The Hon’ble Lieut.-Colonel Cordon Loch, I.A., Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Oulf® His Majesty’s Minister, British Legation, Tehran* Sir, I have the honoi^r to refer to Colonel Fowle’s Express Letter No. C/SICT, dated the lt&gt;th May 1934 and to enclose a c opy of the marginally noted papers regarding th&lt; lltreatment Letter No.C/672-l7a/2, dated the Ibth July, 1934 from the Political Agent, Bahrain. Printed Letter No.C/673-1.a/2,dated the Ibth July 1934 from the Political Agent, Bahrain and enclosures® j ^ Printed Letter No.C/679-1.a/2, dated the 17th July 1934 from t e Political Agent, Bahrain and enclosure. of Bahrainis in Persia® 2. His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin *^sa A1 Khalifah will not deprive uf their Bahrain nationality those Bahrain subjects who, in order to continue owning land in Persia, become Persian subjects® 3® Tile sent with the Printed Letter No. C/673-l.a/2, dated the 15th July 1934 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, put forward a new request - that permission emigrate may be ontained for the petitoners to xmxgfcx/ and that they may be given a place in which to live with their families ® 4. As political Agent, Bahrain, I have considered (though I have naturally never mentioned itto the Shaikh) among other courses the possibility of emigration, which would/would mean migration to Bahrain, as a solution of the troubles of those Bahrain subjects who live but do not own or are prepared to give up land in Persia; and the possibility of financing such a migration and the settlement in Bahrain ol the families concerned by a tax on Persians living in Bahrain* I fear, however, that the numbers concerned (which may be some thousands) and the political and economic complications which might ensue, make me doubtful whether such a course would be practicable at present, though it might aiford an appropriate remedy if it were desired at any time to take a strong line with the Persian Government* Though I cannot make any definite statement wi thoug concult ing the Shaikh of Bahrain, it occurs t o me that, if it were desired to find a place for these Bahrain subjects and if other difficulties could be over come, there are certain houses and lands on thewest side of the Island, which were abandoned some years ago for political reasons and which might be made available for this purpose* I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s ^ecretc«ry of State for India, the Foreign secretary to the Government of India, His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz and the Political Agent, Bahrain* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (Sgd) G. Loch* Lt.Colonel, -c iat ing r'olitical Kesident in the lersian &lt;iulf 0^ A 1 CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1014-3 of 19 34 IZz $Ka/0% The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Lieut*-Colonel Gordon Loch, I«A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment for information. 2. Colonel Fowle is replyin British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated.. . Zr . d . Nov emb e r 19 34 Reference to previous correspondenpe: Residency Printed letter No.758-S, dated the 6th August 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Government of India demi-official letter No. F.101-N/34, dated the 18th September 1934, and enclosure. Subject Ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia (CONFIDENTIAL. D.O.No.F.101-N/34 ®) S iinla, The 18th September 1934 V Jjo My dear Loch, ' Would you please refer the c rrespondence regarding ill-treatment of Bahrain's in Persia ending with your printed letter No.758-S of 6th August 1934, enclosing a copy of a letter written by you to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. As you will remember we ask ed for Fowle’s comments upon the Foreign Office letter No.E.2623/1561/91, dated the 9th May 1934, a copy of which # was forwarded to you and to us by the India Office with their endorsement No.P.Z.3144/34 of 18th May 1934. Fowle’s comments were contained in his Express Letter No.661-5 I'lt) of 1934, dated the 13th July 1934, in which he merely suggested that His Majesty’s Government could appropriately make representations on behalf of Bahrainis temporarily resident in Persia, who seek work as coolies and small shopkeepers. It seems doubtful whether this is the class which the Persian Government usually oppress, and it does not seem to us that Fowle’s comments take us mueh further. We have been considering the matter again in consultation with Prior who spent some years at Bahrain. I enclose for your information a copy of a note which Prior wrote on the subject at my request. As you wil^ see he draws a distinction between the several classes of Bahrainis affected, which appeats to us to be sound. He also suggests the possibility of retaliation on certain lines. I feel extremely doubtful whether in present circumstances His Majesty’s Government would be prepared to sanction any action of this kind, since it is clear that for the moment they are all out for maintaining the status quo and avoiding v, any-v -’•-e wm*- Xh\ cr - 2 - any kind of provocative action against the Persians for fear the latter will turn and rend us over Henfejjm and Basidu, where they are on very strong ground and could demand our withdrawal, if they wish to be really nasty. Apart however from the question whether any such action is admissible on political grounds, it has also to be considered whether retaliation of the kind su gested by Prior would be practicable e and effective. It is on this point that I would n like your opinion before we deciue whether to make any recommendation in this sense to the India Office. 2. We should also be ^Ld if you would explore further your interesting suggestion for the settlement of 'Persian** Bahrainis on the west side of the Island (presumably in the lands at Budaiyya deserted recently by Dowasir tribe). No oriental ruler likes to,.lose subjects, even though he may dislike them , and, if the Bahrainis had an alternative of this kind to fall back on, the Persians might be induced to give better treatment. At the same time this project would enable the Shaikh to meet the complaint of Persian Bahrainis that he was prepared to do nothing for them. I'he propsect of an improvement in the finances of Bahrain and of the development of irrigation from artesian wells, seems to offer an excellent opportunity for consideration of a pq^ject of this kind, and we shall be glad to hear whether on further review of the details j you still think your scheme to be practicable. 3. I may add that so far we have not been asked to comment on the Foreign Office letter referred to above nor have we seen any reply from the India Office to the Foreign Office. But I imagine that our views will be askedasked for before the India Office reply is sent 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to tfalton and would suggest that &gt;ou should also send him a copy of your reply. Yours sincerely, H.A.F.METCALFE. The Hon’ble Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Loch, Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.COPY OF NOTE We may divide persons of Bahrain origin in Persia into three categories:- (1) Those who own landed property, (2) Bahrainis born in Persia, and (3) those who were born in Bahrain, As regards the first we can do nothing for them and the -re is no objection to telling them sc on every possible occasion, nor can there be any difficulty in explainir^ this to the Shaikh. As regards the second, since Bahrain has now published a proclamation that persons born in Bahrain of foreign parents would, unless registered in the Agency, be considered as subjects of the Bahrain State, we could, I think, persuade the Shaikh that it is unreasonable to expect us to do anything for Bahrainis born in Persia, since I do not think that these people have any real claim on us. They intend to remain in Persia, they are usually married in Persia and since they are born there, Persians have every risfht to consider them as sons of the soil. It is true that foreigners in Bahrain can register and avoid Bahrain nationality, but the fact remains that Persians do not. We are now left with the third category oi persons born in Bahrain who genuinely belong to it and for these we must make anattempt to do something. 2. The question or retaliation was taken bp by Sir Hugh Biscoe in his despatch No.23b-S., dated the 5th May 1931 wherein he suggested that we should withdraw the Capitulations from the Persians in Bahrain and subject them to the local courts. I told Sir Hugh «t the time that I thought his idea was mistaken and that it would hit us more than the Persian Government in as muah as it would reduce the power of the Political Agent over an important section of the community, and that it was impracticable in that most of the Persians in Bahrain spoke only Persianand could not be subjected to courts whose officers spoke nothing but Arabic. I also pointed out that since the act of withdrawing Capitulations could only take place once, it would have only a temporary effect and that once the Persians had forgotten about its effect would be lost. I suggested on the other hand, that in allowing the Pahlavi cap, a visible sign of raodBrn Persia, and Persian schools leven one subisdised from Persia) in Bahrain, we were allowing a valuable concession that Persians would never tolerate in their territory and which would affect their pride deeply if withdrawn • It must be remembered that the Persian Government have few scruples concerning their subjects arid care little for what lo. s they cause them in supporting their pride. In fact in cutting off their nose to spite their face, they are past masters. They would not, therefore, worry very much about retaliation that only affected their ressortissants pockets, but retaliation that effected their national pride would make them squirm. Moreover, such retal iation would be a continuous one and every Pahlavi cap removed would be a fresh reminder of the Shaikh’s power over their nationals in Bahrain. Sir Hugh, however, disagreed with my views and did not forward my dispatches and his own suggestion/ was abandoned, I think quite rightly, on the ground that it would do us more harm than good* 3. I would suggest therefore that we should not abandon the possibility of retaliation. We should allow the Shaikh to say that if Bahrain subjects in Persian with Bahrain wifcte nationality papers ( we would understand this as referring only to persons of the third category) were molested he would consider the withdrawal of the privilege of allowing Persians to maintain separate schools in Bahrain and also thethe would abolish the Pahlavi cap as an emblem which had become intoler able to him. If this was conveyed to the Persian Government at the right moment, it would, I think, have a deciddd effect.3 for they know that they are powerlecsto interfere in what happens in Bahrain. If the persecution continued, the school- s (which are a confounded nuisance) could be closed one by one and the question of the Pahlavi cap could be taken up later, I think that these twoi and particularly the Pahlavi cap, would have a real effect on the Persian Government and if the Minister were to drop a hint to this effect verablly it would be possible to gauge its effect without having to put it into writing and so enable us to resile from the position if we found that the weapon was 1 likely to be useless. Indealing with Persians their pride must never be lost sight of, and sense recognised as only a subsidiary factor in their compostion. To sum up - 4. (l) rle admit that we can do nothing for Bahrainis with landed property. There is no objection to telling both them and the Shaikh of this. (2) We must get round the clash between our normal obligation to protect the children of British protected pubjects and the provision of the Persian Nationality lirw mentioned in sections 4 and 5 of paragraph 5 of the Foreign Office letter by explaining to the Shaikh that we have accepted this position for our ,wj6n subjects and that moreover the new proclamation in B; j.rain has mueh the same effect. We should also explain that since Bahrainis born in Persia have obviously every indention of remaining there it i s in their own interest to accept Persian nationality, though they would still be entitle d to Bahrain nationality should they ever return to Bahrain . I see no objection to the Consul at Mohammerah explaining their position under the Persian nationality law to Bahrainis and advising them privately to accept Persian nationality under protest. (3) We must make a genuine attempt to pr tect Bahrainis torn in Bahrain and th.reaten retaliation if our calim to do / this- 4 - A this is not admitted, (4) »'/e should make no public announcement of our policy regarding those mentioned in (2) and if retaliation shows itsell to be a successful weapon, we w \°uld extend our protection to border line cases in this category, bid. G.G. .Frior. 11.7.34.f Lhe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to N\ J. C. Walton, Esquire, C.3., M.C,, India Office, London, ^.Lieut-Polonel Gordon Loch, I«A., Political Agent, .ahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (^k). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Canq), Bahrain, British Consulate-General, BUSH] HE. Dated 17th. Nqvaber .1934. pf ; i( &gt; - , &lt; 1 'W. - /'fa - N ^SHis; Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Demi-official letter No. C-303, dated 17th November 1934, to The Hon*bio JAr. H.A. Metcalfe, C.S.I., C.I.E., iu.V.O., Foreign Secretary to the Government of j.ndia. Subject. Ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia*D«0»Ho*308«C of 1934• JU CONFIDENTIAL » Persian Gulf. caap t Bahrain, the 17th November, 1934* Office of the Political Resident in tL^ f ref«r to your d«ml-official l#tt«r No.F.101«ir/34 t dat*d th« 18th Sapttabsr 1934, to Loch, ..no handed it to me on my taking over from him, together with Prior'a Rote, which I read with interest, on the sut oi the ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia* 2. with regard to a policy of retaliation as advocated by Prior. Though with the introduction of the Persian Nationality Law ( see paragraph II below) it can no longer be said that the claim of the Persian Government to Bahrain is involved in their treatment of Bahrainis (see paragraph 6 of my letter No. 2 T of 20th March 1934) I am still of opinion that such re tali a. tions as are possible, while doubtless annoying to the reraian Government, v.huld not achieve our main object, i.e. the stopping of the oppression of Bahrainis in Persia (paragraph 7 of my letter No.2 T.). (a) the torbidding of Pehlavi caps in Bahrain; (b) closing of Persian schools. doubtless these, as pointed out by Prior in a S ra Pb 2 of his note, would make the Persian Government 'squirm', but that - though it would give me great pleasure - is not our main object, (see paragraph 2 above), The Honourable Mr. H.A.F.M etcalfe, . ^ •d*X», C.l.g., -•oreign Secretary to the Government of India. New Delhi, 3 Tb* bwo retaliatory measures advocated by Prior are » andiiS © and I do not nysalf sae tht Porsian CJov«rnm«nt giving battar traatmant to Bahrainla In Poraia maraly bacauaa tha Bahrain Govemaant for cad Persians In Bahrain to abandon the Pahlavl cap. Moreover (a) suffers under the following disadvantage. No government In tha world, as far as I know, forbids foreigners wearing what clothes and head-dress they fancy, sfhat the Persian Government, for Instance, does in Persia Is to order Persian subjects to wear a certain sort of cap. For the Shaikh of Bahrain to be in a plausible position to legislate on the subject of the head-dress of Bahraini Persians, such ^ individuals would have to be considered Bahraini subjects, and put under the Jurisdiction of the Shaikh, but this is what Prior, in paragraph 2 of his note, is strongly against. ^ 5. with regard to (b), I am not of opinion that the Bahrain Govammant would hava a good cast in taking the drastic step of closing the Persian schools* What they eoula do ( and have for some time been considering), not as a measure of retaliation but as one of administrative convenience, and for various political reasons, would be to put such schools under the control of their Department cf education* At present the Persian schools are under no such control* I have discussed the matter with Loch and will address you separately on the subject in due course* b. with regard to a proposal of Biscoe that we should .. ith-^raw the Capitulations from the Bahraini Persians and subject them to the local Courts, which Prior mentions in paragraph 2 of his Note, but of which he was not in favour* I do not think this idea is impracticable for the reason that Prior givest that most Persians in Bahrain speak only Persian and could not be subjected to Courts whose officers speak nothing but Arabic, All over the world foreigners ar atIl at a disadvantaga from the language point of view when appearing in local Courta, which difficulties they get over ae beet they can - by the use of interpreters, for instance^ and in any case whatever inconvenience that Persian Bahrainis might suffer in their appearances in the Bahrain Courts is not a matter which need worry us* Moreover, an increasing number of local Persians know sufficient Arabic for practical purposes* 7* I agree, however, with Prior that there would probably be disadvantages in handing over the Persian subjects en bloc to the Shaikh, and even if we were to threaten to do so, I do not think that it would achieve the object at getting better treatment for Bahrainis in Persia* In connection with Biscoe's proposal one must remember that it is now generally agreed - vide correspondence ending with India Offica lattar No.P..,.5811/34 of 5th October 1934 to tha Foreign Office - that it would be a good thing to allow the Persians in Bahrain to come gradually under the Shaikh’s jurisdiction* 8* There is another measure of retaliations that 7 ? suggested by Loch and referred to in paragraph 2 of your letter* I discussed this with Loch and he is going to examine the question further and 3* t me have his opinion* Here again, however, I doubt whether the action suggested would force the Persian Government to treat the Bahrainis anj better, though the scheme inltself has, at any rate from the Shaikh's point of vlsw, a good deal to recom end it* 9* The following general consideration has also to be borne in mind* The best kind of retaliation from our poln of view would be one which could be turned off and on at will* That is to say the Persian Government would be indue to become reasonable by the knowledge that when they ceased their objectionable conduct we would likewise cease being objectionableobjection* bl« to them* But all the above su ^esteu latlone (as prior quite truly points out with regard to tn particular one of the withdrawal of Capitulations) can only be done once* tfe could only intimate to the Persian Government, in whatever way was thought desirable, that if they did not cease their ill-treatment of Bahrainis, the Bahrain Government would take such and such measures* If the Persian Government did not respond to these threats, vhlcl personally I do not think they would, the Bahrain Government would then have to put tnem into force, and having done this could hold out no further inducement to the Persian Gove^ nment that the measures would be relaxed if the Persian Government ceased their ill-treatment of Bahrainis* 10* ,YhAt is wanted is some form of suitable retaliation which does not buffer under the disadvantages explained above^i The only one I cam think of is that the Shaikh should issue a proclamation prohibiting ownership of land in Bahrain t&gt;y Persians end ordering that rersians who already own land in Bahrain fcgc will be allowed a period of, say, two years, within which to acquire Bahrain nationality, or, if they do not wish to become Bahrain subjects, to dispose of their property. This follows the measures t; ken by the Persian Government prohibiting the ownership of land by foreign nationcils, appears to be a form of retaliation suited to the case, and generally makes the punishment fit the crime* If at any time the Persians ceased their ill-treatment of ftahpai Bahrainis - which they are not likely to - the measure could be relaxed* There may, however, be practical objections to the introduction of such a measure, and I shall address you further on this point* 11* If we assume that retaliations are out of the question, the only action which we can take on behalf of Bahrainis are protests* As pointed out in paragraphs 3 and 4 of my Express Letter No*661-S of 13th July x934, certain assuiqptlons which of recent years had been made in connect ion8 ^ wmmm &lt;S,N 'J - 5 - ion with th« question of ill-tr«atm«nt of Bahrainis in isrsia, s«em to havo b«en controvertod by tho Foroi^n Off ice - vids thwir Isttwr of 9th Way, No •£• 2633/ i. 516/91 , and in ^articular th# aseunption thcxt His Majesty's Govsmmsnt are legally justified in espousing the cause of B; hrainia in general, this change having been brought about by the introduction of the Per eian Nationality Law, In para graph 6 of ay express Letter quoted above, I give the opinion, however, that there was still e certain class of 3ahrainis with regard to whom His Majesty's Government's position was not affected by the Nationality Law, and it is on behalf of these, and these only, that it seems to me Hie Majesty's Government c*n protest# 12# Protests in general, as we all know, have remarkably little effect on the Persian Government , and I have little hope that any protests made on behalf of the class of Bahrainis in question, will produce results# The position is of course humilating to His Majesty's Government and galling to Shaikh Hamad (vide the last sent ence of paragraph 7 of my letter No#2 T)# 13# &lt;Vith regard to what we should say to the Shaikh# we should explain to him that there are four classes of Bahrainis concerned* (1) Bahrainis born in Persia who own landed property there# (2) Bahrainis born in Bahrain who own landed property in Persia# (3) Bahrainis born in Persia who do not own landed property there# (4) Bahrainis born in Bahrain who do not own landed property in iersla but are employed there in casual occupation, such as shopkeepers, coolies etCe we could go on to explain as follows&gt; With regard to (1) we can do nothing by reason of ths Persian Nationality Law and even if these indlvldu* ale(g) /w7 • 6 • a ls gave up tufcir land th«y would still rtmain Persians. Miwii i egard to (2) tliat If* these Individuals g-ve up their land they are in the same juridical - position as (4). iu regard to (3) these are Persian subjects \ under the Persian Nationality Law. With regard to (4) these are the only class of Bahrainis on whose behalf Hie Majesty’s Government can take any action, such action being limited to protests. (Unless His Majesty's Government decide on a policy of retaliation). I am sending copies of this letter to Walton and Loch. Yours sincerely, Sgd. T.C. FOWLH.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. NZ Phono Dated, Shaaban 14 No. 6 IS/s f of 1353 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Shaaban 14, 1353 November 22,1§34. H. B. M Bahrain M f s Political Agent, Memorandum:- I am informed by Syed Hashim bin Syed Hussein, of Senabis in Bahrain, resident 18 years in Mohammerah, where he owns a small house only, in which he lives, that he and all other Bahrain subjects have received written orders to hand in their Bahrain passports and to register themselves as Persian subjects. This order is issued oy the Persian Passport Officer of Mohommerah. 2. Syed Hashim holds a Bahrain passport which was issued to him four years ago. He is well known to the British Consul in Moham merah and recently supplied information to the British Consul regarding number of Bahrain subjects in Mohammerah. 3. He enquires whether he should hand in his Bahrain passport, as ordered to do or refuse to obey this order. He wishes to leave on Saturday. Could you inform me what advice I should give him. 7 _CONFIDENTIAL. C/921-1.a/S. © /!/ The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—• His Majesty’s Vice Consul, Mohammerah. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Golf. Dated... November 1954 • Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter i^o:C/920-1.a/,2 of 24-11-1934 to The Honourable Ill-treatment of Bahama the Political Resident in in Persia. the Persian ^ulf, -^ushire. ^ */c A. ^ A (!*;&gt; {*■ b V 'Vt 5 =2S| ' Jn \&lt;f — wCONFIDENTIAL. No. 59-S of 1935. oV &amp; The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com. pliments to 1. His Majesty* s Secretary of State for India, Indiapffice, London. 2 . The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India New Delhi. ' The Political Agent, Bahrain. HDfi has the honour to transmit to him 3 copy of tho u□ dermootionod ductt- ment i i British Consulate-General, BUSH IKE. Dated... 11 th .. Januar y 1935. Reference to previous correspondence: I Description of Enclosure. / Name and Date. Mohammerah despatch No.1003, dated the 23rd December 1934. Subject. Condition of Bahrainis in Persia.I f Ko, 1002 Buehlre 1003* British Vioe-Con8ulate f Mohammer, h* Dated the 23rd December lv34. Dir 9 1 htve the honour to report that tro Bahrainie v presented theiueelvee cefore u.e a few days ago. They stated that they were merchants living Ir. 1 ; ohamatrah* Both were in poesession of Bahrain paesporte* They had been instructed by the Perui&amp;n authoritye® to la^ce out Dersxan Nationality p&amp;pera and had replied that they weir for elgncrs and in poseeealon of foreign pnsoporta. They t i#erc # accrdinfe,ly t requested to produce their paaeporte for inspection. before doing so they decided to approach me and ask sy adviceas they wished to know what to do in t. e event of their passports bein*. confiscated. The present Governor of Abadan has only recently been appointed, I seized the opportunity therefore of under a covering letter fiom this office asking for their return when inspected by the officials concerned. I sent say Interpreter with my letter and the pass, arts to the Governor and instructed him to explain all the troubles of the pest and the situation in general, and told him to say th&amp;t I was only sending the passports myself to ensure that the Bahrainis did not try to create trouble by throwing the passports away themselves. ( 1 actually suspect certain persons of doing this or at any rate persona who never have had documents of saying that they have been confiscated.) L —^The Governor sent for the official of the r' SIj11 Ahwal Department and instructed him not to confiscate such documents but to issue the ieieian 'bijil* and allow these individu la of dual nationality to carry both documents* He explained that Bahrain claimed to be independent while Persia claimed Bahrain and that until this question was settled all lahrainis in Persia must have 'Sijil' but that they coaid also keep their Bahrain documents so that when the time came they could establish their identity as Persians or Bahrainia &amp;s the case might be* He sent his kindest regards to me and informed me t;:nt this was the manner in which he proposed to d eal with the problem* I sent a reily to the effect t at we were giving tie same advice to the Bahrainis and that if he could make the dijil Department keep to this arrangement we might consider the matter closed as far as he and I were concerned. 1 think that instruction must have come trrou^h at lAot and that the Bahrainis will be molested no longer provided they do not resist taking, out rersian papers* &lt;thile the Bahrainis themselves are beginning to take more kindly to our advice ano* that they understand that they have to choose between conscription and losing their property* As a matter of interest i would also report that I discussed ihe subject with my Iraq colleague* he informed me that he is having the same trouble over certain persons living in Kohasimerah who claim tc be Iraqis whilst the Persians claim them to be Persians. He maintains that all of these are eimply trying to avoid corscrivtion. They visi t Irao m d get a few friends to vouch for them and obtain Iraqi passports- 3 - (£) IS! passports and then return to }'ersAa 9 ano try to evade conscript, on on the grounds trjit they are Irav a abject a • Their paeep rts are then seized and thej complain to the Iraq Consul. however the Iraq Government is shortly passing a law for conscription and the Iraq Consul does not conteafipl&amp;te any further trouble. There can be no doubt that many of the per*sons claiming to be Bahrainis are playing the same game, whilst even the real Barjrainis would probably gi*c up tneir claim to Bahrain nationality if there was conscription in Bahrain. 1 am convinced that there is no question of any of them giving up their property or interests in Persia to return to Bahrain even without conscription. Bo long therefore as they are not molested I can see no useful purpose in trying to do anything further for these so-called Bahrainis who will certainly not take Bahrain nationality un ess they can keep their property. In fact to satisfy them it *ould bt more n ces^ary to change the Persian Law regarding the holding ct* property by foreigners then to establish Bahrain*e independence in the eyes of Persia, 1 am eending a copy of this despatch to Bsuhxre. xxtexaxiocMxajMuixacxtaxipey I am, %ir. Your obedient Servant, bd. P.K.Chauncy, Captain, Hie liajesty’s Vice-Consul. \ \No. 60-S of 1935. The Hon’ble the Politica] Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his coin- pliments to The Political A^ent, BAHRAIN. 1 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned doc» rnent British Consulate-General, BUSH1RE. Dated. 11 t.h. 4 ahUAry.. .1.9. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Despatch No. 2/29/1015, dated 23rd December 1934, from His ilajesty’s Vice-Consul, Mo hammer ah. Bahraini oppression in .ersia,© No. 2/29/1015 British Vice-Consulate Mohammeraii. jJecember 23rd, 1934. From Captain F.C.L. Channcy, I.A., His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. To The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf With reference to despatch No.C/920-l-a/2 dated the 24th November 1934 from the Political Agent, Bahrain to your address, cj&gt;py of which was sent to me by the Political Agent, Bahrain I have the honour to state that the individual referred to is one of the two Bahrainis who reported to me. He has only the property which he claims, and it is possible that in his case a protest might be made. B u s h i r e. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient Servant Sd. F.C.L.Chaimcy, Captain His Majesty's Vice-Consul.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 126-S of 1935. Vto) 1 J The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Loch,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. -p . ^ 24th January 1935. Reference to previous correspondence : . Political Resident’s Printed Letter No.C-309 of 17th November 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject India Office letter No.P.Z. 159/35 of 11th January 1935 to the Foreign Office. Treatment of Persians in BAHRAIN•f INDIA OFi'ICS P.z. 159/35. LONDON, 3. W. 1. 11th January 1935. Would you please refer to your letter of 5th January to Crombie, No.E.5175/2369/91, about the treatment of Persians in Bahrein? 2. I fear that we have not made it clear that it is on the wider question of the Bahreinis in Persia that we are awaiting the Government of India's views in the light of their further consultation with Fowl© (see my letter to you of 19th October, P.Z.5678/34). As regards Motamedi’s note of 15th May last about Persians in Bahrein, we are inclined, on the whole now*, to think that unless the Foreign Office see objection, the best plan would be to return no reply to the Persians unless they revert to the matter both in view of the lapse of time and on the ground suggested by Loch in his letter of 17th July to Tehran (copy/ H.L. Baggallay Esq., Foreign Office,2m (copy enclosed in our printed letter No»P» Z»5125/34, ol 10th August) that it would he preferable to avoid entering into any discussion of local affairs in Bahrein with the Persians if it is possible to avoid doing so. Perhaps you could let me know whether the Foreign „ mtHWAVT-* G. V-At rm Office agree?The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document/ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. the.. . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure.t ion o ** p!. ^uo^ttan .No 139^ 1 Date^ T) &lt;&gt; cenb e r l^fh. 1954 ^he Ipsugs of the i-hp+t ul Aral: a n ^ Bahrai n b efore the league of i.ations « ’That is deranded by Iraq and wbat is demanded by T’ersis . are mcTe men^s in the Persian Gulf the 2hatt ul A~ab Baghdad and ^ehran which are on -he verge of creating disturban ces and trouble in the minds of the Arabs of the norrth and which, if one put +hen toge+her strung +hei^ component parts together amd wen + deep in studying their causes and ^ac+o-s, one would see ‘‘■hey owe + hei r origin +o fou 1 ' basic sources, namely l. ^he refusal o^ ^^rsta ‘♦■o organise her noHMcal relations with Iran in sui + e o-^ the fa ctp that fourteen ^rears have elapsed since the establishment of + he Iraq Government, that 'ersia has recdgnised Iran since ten years and that she agreed to enter into a pact, which was contracted by ‘‘■he two countries sever years ago, to + he effect that Persia would hasten to organise her relations with Iraq, ?. r he desire of Persia to occupy a portion of the Iraqi She tt ul Arab and the interference on the part of her officials there with the Ira^i officials from time to time, 3. ''he desire o^ Persia to take possession of the Islands of Bahrain and annex them to her dominions on the ground that they belonged to her in clden times and hat she did not accept up till now thei- independence and Fe-ne^^ + ion from her*. 4. ''he secret desire o^* Persia to extend her influence over the western coast o^ the ^ersiar Gulf which is inhabited by + hs Arabs and is comnosed o^ a few well-Inown stages connected by pact and o+her ties with + he British Government on the nrincirle of re cognising their independence bu 4- 'estweining them fro^ entering into pacts wi + h o^her powers, with ^he exception o^ the ^audi Government which is one of the governments of + he ’ersian Gulf / andenjoys crannlete independence rfi+h no Enplish influence whetever. . PrepaiUit ioneof the British in the Gulf . These ere the real causes, in +he eye of '-he majority of the peo ple, which have led +o the dirturher ces and direuiet in thr Persian r hil + , ^he Shett ul Arab and on + he Iraq-'^ersian borders. m o + hese owe '“heir oripin such actiyi + ies nn ^-atherinf? together British fleet in + he Gulf, its raoveraentp to and fro and/its arrival a+ Basrah; stetioninp o^ an infantry brigade by the En glish in Bahrain; +he fortification of Muscat; +hr establishment o^ a centre for coal in Bahrain itself and the recent complaint o^ Iran to + h e Leapue o^ Nations about the encroachment of her neiph.out* jersia and her lack of oblipation to the poverrmen + pacts arul apreementR. That does I^aq expec t? ^nd + he Iraqis ex-oec + , when the cere haf been before the League of Nations and Persia is a meiriber of it and both the Parties are b^und t 0 how +o its^rbitra + i on as binding Tipon themselves that an e-d may be put to this sta^e of affairs and the Persians rp y desist from their encroachment upon +heir ^rentiers and the fron tier zones and a^ree to contract agreements do indispensable for settinp political relations in order tn the vs y adopted by the powers in their intercourse. The- say that they always entertain towards their neighbours the most sincere sentiments of friendship ate always keen on strengthening what relations of time rhonoured brotherhood exist there and realise that -hey will not be affected in any way bv this incident as it is one of those every dav diffe rences which crop up between brothers. Thev also say -hat their reruest to J -he league o r Nations, knocking at its door ^nd desi ring it* arbitration all Prove their sincerity of Purpose and that thev do not like to oppose its action in any wav; and what they want is -hat their care may be set-led wi+h Persia in such a way as would please bo-h of then and ham neither party because no thing is better than arbitration so long as they are members of -he same League which was decisively meant for arbitrating in such circumstances.r lie issue Bahrain arc 1 its origin . ^ere is also disapreenent on the issue of *he Irlends of Bahrain arhich is l^iufr before the League of Nations for con siders tion and ifhich it is the Persians and not the English or the Arnir of Bahrain who submitted for consideration, ‘''he crux of the matter is that +he two issues which constitute the subject of discord in +he Sv»r + + ul A-^ab and the Persian Oulf are Iving before '•'he League o^ Bations for se'l'*'lement. Vnd Just as '•'he Iraqis T:an + ■•■o stem Persia from encroach ing uid or “^heir borders and to mRke her recognise + he borders fixed between their country and her territo^ies, the Persiens exnect the Lea Pike of Nations to have Bahrain r^tm^ned to them on '•■he ground that was under their sway formerly. ‘J’he first time when the Persians claimed supremacy over these islands and demanded their return to^hem was in the ’’’ear 19P^ following i the conclusion o^ the Jiddah ^rea^y between England and Ibn ^aud. r1 hus in the mon + h o^ November of f hrt Persia sent a memorandum to the League o** Nations claiminp- that Bahrain be longed to her, that she did not renounce her claim to it and that she regarded what was mentioned in the Jidda? 'reaty a? a blow to her rights of supreme cy. Or the ^9th o^ flovem&gt;er England sen + a memorandum in reuly saying tha + she dir ho + k^or of nrv ground on which ^e^si^ had a righ+ to base her cl^im to the«^e islands, which were neither a up rt o^ Persia f^om geo- grauhical uoir^ o*'' view ror wehe inhabi + ed bv '■he oeople of Persian element, and +het she knew that the 'Vrsian troous once during + he l^th and + he la s + pr o^ + he Ifl+h centuries raided Bahrain and occupied it but the Arab tribes a+tseked it in 'he year 1^83 under ■'■he !U-eadershin A1 Khalifah, its present rulers turned the 'Persians out took possession of A hr islands and are still there. _ Persia renews the complaint ^Persia rcne^a cormpla int. 'he Shalhh of Bahrain in + he month of laet May ^ave concession 1/ for extracting petrol in the island to ar vtnerican concern. Persia protested against this concession on the 13th of Jure, last claiming that the netrol in Bahrain belonged to Persia, queen of the island. But ling land fetorted at once that she found her protes^ out of piece. T yhat do thf Pers isns want 7 The arguments point out that + he Persians want to inter connect the two issues and make them ♦he suhjec 4 - of bargain, so that they may get something from Iraq o^ from Tlrn'land 0 ^ f^ora Bahrain. And we n^ed not say that the Iraais would not show ♦he sligh + es + relaxn + ion to the Persians and similar wo’ild he ♦he case wi + h the people of Bahrain. 'That do the wise pe opl e wan^ ? \nd what we want, in ♦he end, is ♦hat ♦he Persians should deviate ♦‘rom this policy on accoun 1 - 0 “ ♦he effect it has on ♦he minds of all the *rshs , act for mutual understanding with these two Arab Governments and put their hands in the hand? of the Arabs of Iran and the Arabf of the Persian Gulf wor king for strengthening thf old established relations. That is better than, and preferable to, this polic''- which will never bring them ary mrterial good- leave alone what effec^ it will leave on the minds of the people- and the wise try, on every occasion, to win h^^ts and please ‘‘'hem. •a******CONFIDENTIAL. Xo ‘ 117 - S of 1935. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to !• J.G.LaithWdite Esquire,C •! 9 The Inal.. Ofiice, Lenaon. 2. H.M.Knutchbull-Rugessen y ^ 8 quire,C.^.G *9 His Majesty's Minister, Tehran• and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (jy). Reference to previous correspondence: iolitical Resident's Printed Let er O.1202-J oi 26th December 1934. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter No* H16-3 of 2j-st January 1.936 to the foreign Secretary to the Government of India. arbitration with the Persian Government over Bahrain. i Copy, with copy of enclosinr compliments, to Lieut .-Col political Agent, Bahrain. Printed Letter No.l2Q4-S o e, forwarded, with inel Gordon Loch,I.A., Ref.Political Resident's 28th December 1934.lenflooMU-.i . S or L936* n-i The HonidoaC/i auai*ir« f 21*t J«nu«o*y 9 936» Could you isluftse reier to my dml*orriolfltl letter Ko«12Ql* i 9 a. tuu th« 2utii v*c«t*:ber .934 9 on ti:e oubj^ct of arbitration with tft* * orolan Government over Bahrain. 2m At the end of the loot pora^r of ti.at letter X urew attention to the uniortuaate effect which an Interaction «1 coiamieai,n f sitting at tianraln 9 ana Investigating on the spot wiiether Bahrain did or did not belong to Urn Snai .h 9 would have not only on the raos of tiie Gull 9 but throughout the « rah world. in this connection an article which appear ed in wh^t is probaoly the leading Arab newspaper, the fuqattam of Cairo y is of eome signiiicance ae indlcatiiig tne inter eat which is taken in oulr alfaire by tL« Arabs outside it. 3* The article in question, which appeared in £o«13971 of the 'uqattam for &gt;ecember 17th 9 waa entitlea 'The Issues of the Shatt al ^rab and Bahrain before the League of Nations. wh«t is demanded by Iraq, and what is demanded by tarsia*. The article enumerated the question# at issue as oliowes 1. The refusal of Persia to organise her political relations with Iraq. The desire of Persia to occupy a portion of tha Iraqi Ghatt al ran and tne interference on uie part of her official# there with the Iraqi officials from tiao to time. 3. / The lon^le ^r.f.A. .uetcalie, C .5 X • I» • V • «, oreign secretary to the uevemtuent of Imla, Hew ^elhi.-2- a. 4 • Th# or &gt;oral«t to take poeseasion of the Ialand* of Bahrain. Tha desire of orala to axtand her lnfluei.ee over the i.rah coast of toe &lt; erelen Oulf # 4« After ueellliii, at eome len^ti; on these ^oints Ui« article went on to sa^ s M rr©» tiie above It will appear t*iat ti^e ereiatiS wish to link u- Uie two questions (!•«• Iraq and liahrain) and make them tlie subject of * bargain, so that tuey fiteiy extract sowethiii^ from Iraq or from upland or from Bahrain# It ia hardly necessary xor us to say that the Iraqis will certainly not give in to the ersi mSf any more th a will the people of Baiirain#' ? I ar* ending copies of t*«is letter to Lalthwaite anu Knutchbull-t ugessen# yours sincerely, sd.ThC.Fowle.The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Name and Pate. Subject. . Foreign Office letter No. (E 5175/2369/91) of 5th January 1935 to the India Office . Ill-treatment . Foreign Office letter No. of (K 272/4/91) of 23rd Bahrainis January 1935 to the India in Office. Persia. . India Office letter No. P.Z.6238/34 of 20th October 1934 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. • Government of India,Foreign and Political Department letter No.F.101-N/34 of 1st February 1935 to the India Office. F *© 110 Copy. P.Z.159/35. (E 5175/2369/91). Foreign Office, S.W.l. 5th January 1935. Dear Crorabie, Would you kindly refer to India Office letter No. P.Z.5125/34 of the 10th August 1934 and to previous correspondence about the treatment of Persians in Bahrain. I understand that before considering further the reply to the Persian note of the 16th May, a copy of which was sent to you in our letter No.E.3681/2369/91 of the 2nd July, the India Office wished to consult Fowle about the views k expressed in his absence by Loch. Could you let me know if the Residency has expressed any further views on the subject^ After this lapse of time it may not of course be necessary to send any reply at all. Yours ever, sd. L.Baggallay. G.E.Crcmbie Esq. 1 VCOPY. P.Z.534/35. (E 272/4/91). Foreign Office,S.W.l. 23rd January 1935. My dear Laithwaite, Many thanks for your letter P.Z.159/35 of 11th January. 2. We agree that it is unnecessary, after this lapse of time and on the general principle that it is undesirable to enter into detailed discussions about Bahrain with the Persians if this can be avoided, for the Legation to return any reply to Motamedi’s letter of 16th May,1934, to Trott about the treatment of Persians in Bahrain. tfe are informing ftiatchbull-Hugessen accordi ngly. 3 . I am sorry if I mistook the point upon which you are awaiting the views of the Government of India and note that it is a question of the treatment of Bahrainis in Persia. We are, of course, hoping to hear from you on this subject also in due course. sd.Lacy Baggallay. J,G.Laithwaite Esq.,CIZAIR MAIL. No. P.Z. 6238/34. My dear Metcalfe, p I write with reference to your demi-official F.101-N/34, of 18th September to Loch about the ill treatment of Bahreinis in Persia. We were anxious in the first place to ascertain Fowled views on the situation generally and we now propose to postpone a reply to the Foreign Office letter of 9th May until we have the conments of the Government of India and any further observations which Loch may make in reply to your letter of 18th September. We should, however, be grateful if we might have these in the near future. 2. Our own provisional view at this stage is that, in the light of the legal position as described in Foreign Office letter of 9th May, we can do nothing for Bahreinis 7 who enjoy Persian nationality under the Persian Nationality Law. This probably covers the great bulk of the Bahreinis in Persia. In the case of a Bahreini who is not in fact covered by the provisions of the Nationality Law and who is the victim of an incident, it will of course remain open to us to make a protest, and it ma^ on general political grounds be desirable that we should do sc, even though in practice the chances of securing adequate reparation from the Persians are probably relatively small. But on this point, as well as on the question generally, we should welcome the observations of the Government of India. 3. I make no cornnent at this stage on the suggestions put forward in Prior’s very interesting note. Fowle did mention while he was here that the Persian schools in Bahrein, which he gave us to understand were centres of disaffection, were not under the control of the Bahrein Education Authority, and that the same is true of the schools controlled by the American missionaries. There seems a good deal to be said for remedying this state of things INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, S. W. 1. 20th October 1934. I'|V' ©things so far as the Persians are concerned, though if we were to bring them under the control of the Bahrein Education Authority it would, of course, be necessary to do the same for the Americans. But action on these lines ought, on the face of it, to be easy to justify on general grounds, either to the Persians- or to the United States Government. This point might, therefore, perhaps be considered in connection with the general question. Yours sincerely, Sd/- J. G. Walton. The Hon’ble Mr. H.A.F. Metcalfe, CSI., GIE., MVO., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, NEW DELHI.' BY AIR MIL* . Confidential. D.O. No.F.10i-H/34. Foreign and Political Department N3W DELHI. Please refer to yo&gt;ar demi-official letter No. P.2. 6238/34, dated the 20&amp;1 October 1934, regarding the ill-treatment of Bahrainis in Persia. I must apologise for not hating given you our views before, but as you will realise we have been rather pressed with other work of contained in his demi-official letter No. 308-0 of 1934, dated the 17th November 1934, of which &amp; copy was sent to you. &lt;«e all now appear to be in general agreement that nothing effectual can be done on behalf of Bahrainis who have acquired Persian nationality by virtue of the Persian Nationality Law, and that our efforts must be confined mainly to protests on behalf of casual Bahrainis who were born in Bahrain and not in Persia and own no land, nor have any permanent interests in Persia. It is probable that these protests will not have much effect unless some form of retaliatory action can be taken. As you will see, Fowls does not approve Priori suggestion regarding Pahlavi caps and in this we feel bound to agree with him. The other proposal for bringing Persian Schools under the control of Bahrain Educational authority appears to be desirable on administrative grounds apart from its effect as a measure of retaliation; Fowle is however still examining the practical implications of this and also of the proposal to settle Bahrainis, who wish to leave Persia, on the west side of the Island, Powle's own suggestion in paragraph 10 of his letter would seem to imply a measure of discrimination greater urgency. You will have seen Fowle’s comnents against• 2 • y\r&gt; ' 'S ' gainst Persians as such, unless the Bahrain Government 'were to make a similar prohibition against ownership of land by any foreigner. Fbr that reason it seems to us objectionable and could hardly be defended against Persian protest. 2. I am afraid that the net result of all this is to leave us vary much as we were before, but we have just received a copy of a Uohammer&amp;h Despatch No. 1002, dated the 23rd December 1934 (copy sent to you with the Political Resident’s printed letter No. 59-3 of 1935, dated the 11th I K i January 1935) which suggests that at Abadan at any rate where most of the trouble has arisen in the past the Persian authorities are likely to take a more reasonable view than they have done in the past. It may therefore be hoped that our protests have had some effect and that in future it will be unnecessary to continue such protests. 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Fowls. Yours sincerely, 3d/- H.A.F. Metcalfe. To J C. Walton, Esquire, C.B., M.C., Secretary, Political Department, India Office, LONDON.CONFIDENTIAL. 327-S of 1935, Jl6 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1* Kio Majesty * a Secretary of State for India, London* The foreign Secretary to the Government of India Simla* 3* The Political Agent t Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment (s). | ► J . - . 4 i ^ 1To Tho Hon*tie the Political Resident in the Persian Sulf 9 Bushire* Ko«643 ' H.M*s Vice-Consul, Kohammerah, No.644 BRITISH CONSULATE, fith compliments from K.B.M’s Consul for Khuzistan at Aheaz* AHliAz. 12th April 1935. y o. 27 . N Sir, With reference to previous correspondence regarding treatment of Bahreinis in Persia, I have the honour to forward herewith copy of a despatch dated the 10th Instant received from His Majesty's Vice-Consul at Moh&amp;mmerah regarding the conscription of three persona of Bahreini origin holding Iranian 'sijila' Issued at ^usbah. 2. It is presumed that you do not desire any action to be taken locally. Any such action, in my opinion, would merely create further difficulties for the remainder of the community. \ \ 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the 'Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushlre.^No.643) • I have the honour to . Sir, \ Your most obedient, humble servant, Sgd. A.£. WATKINSON. .1 i “• i H.B.M's Consul for Khuzistan. H.V. Knatchbull-Hugessen, Esquire, C.U.G., His Britannic Majesty's Minister, etc., etc., etc., British Legation, TEHRAN.COPY * British Tics Consulate, Moh&amp;mmer&amp;h* April the 10th, 1935* /7S Ho* 346 Sir, I have the honour to enclose copies of statements made to me by three persons, namely i• !• fcaj im bin 4air Abood Bahrein! 2* All bln ^air Abood Bahreini 3* Pli bin Khalil Bahreini. 1 have personally seen their Bahreini documents which are certificates of Bahrein nationality bearing the seal of the Financial Adviser to the ' over nine nt of Bahrain* I have also seen their Iranian nationality documents. From appearance all three appear to be over the age for recruitment, though the date of birth shown in the Iranian documents brings them within the age for conscription* Again, from their appearance, none of them look as though they would pass the physical standard, if any, required for the army. The discrepancy regarding age is probably explained by the fact that when these persons originally took Iranian nationality papers they gave their ages to escape conscription on the ground of youth, hoping that the Bahrain question would be settled,before they 'came of age'. I am informed that several other 'Bahreinis' are being called up. 1 am, Sir, Your meet obedient servant, Sgd. F.C.L.CH/UHCY, Capt., Hie a a j ci ty , e Consul for Khuaistan, His Majesty*! Vict-Consul.\ J © If Najim bin iair Abood Bahreini of ^uabah took the Pereian Nationality document (Sijil Ko.204 dated the 27th fiahman 1312) and have now been Informed by the Persian Authorities that I have to be taken for conscription although 1 am in poeaeesion of Bahrein Nationality Certificate Ko. 159 dated the 29th February 1930. L.T., of H&amp;Jim bin Abood. Kohammerahf the 8th April 1935. I # Ali bin £air Abood Bahreini of Guaba took the Persian totlonality document (sij 11 Ko.284 dated 25th Khurdad 1312) and have now been informed by the Persian authorities that 1 have to be teken for conscription although I am in possession of Bahrein Nationality Certificate So. 256 dated the 27th November 1930. L.r #9 ol Ali bin /bood. * Mohammerah the 8th April 1935. 1 . Ali bin Khalil Bahreini of Gusba took the Persian Nationality document (Sijil No. 184 dated the 17th Urdibehesht 130 Si and have^been informed by the Persian Authorities that 1 have to ee tn for conscription although I am in possession of Bahrein Nationality Certificate No.472/*NC dated 8th October 1932. MOHANPiRAH the 8th April 1935.mmm CONFIDENTIAL. No. 352 -S of 1935 -i lio lion ble thG Political Rosidcnt in the Persian Grulf presents hi? pliments to s cora- y The Political Agent, Bahrain. A- and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (aj. •» British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. 30111 1935 Reference to previous correspondence : . f 'V f Residency Printed Letter N0.59-S of 11th January 1935. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Foreign Office letter No. S 843/843/91 of 16th April 1935 to the India Office. Subject. Treatment of Bahrainis resident in Mohammerah.S 843/843/91 (12) Itoth April, 1935• 3ir I am tiir&amp;eteft by Mr* Stanley Baldwin to raqueat you to intom ^aorotary Sir 3anuel Hoara that the report by Hie iiajeet^'a Vioe*Com»ul at Moh'^raarari upon the treatnent of Bahraini a resident In hie district, of which n copy was enclosed in India Office letter y. :* &amp;&amp;&amp;/&amp;&gt; of the t&gt;th February 1^36, hue been retd with interest in thie department. £• The arran ^' v nt come to between Japta in Jhauncy ^nd the Governor or Abadan seems to hare been most arpropriate to the oiroumatances of the cni?e, and Mr. Baldwin considers that Captain haunoy*s eotlon should be approved. 3. If 3ir Sarfuei Renre aserees Mr. Baldwin will instruct Hi a ;5©J« sty’s Minister » t Tehran to inform Hi &gt;3 iinj^sty 1 s Consul at Ahwas eeoordin^ly. I am. 3ir Tour obedient Servant -ci.) G. W. HuNC The Undex-.secretary of 3tat&lt; India Office.ITW# CONFIDENTIAL. I he Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agont, BA HP A Itf 0 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment jty. Office of the Political Reeiaent in the Persian Gulf. Camp, Bahrain. Reference to previous correspondence : ^ PeBiciency p » L - No » 327-S, dated 26th Mpril 1935 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Tehran despatch No. 15, dated let May 1935* to His Majesty’s Consul, Subject. B/HRAINI CONSCRIPT ION. Ahwaz»CONFIDENTIAL. No. 777-fJ of 103D. k&lt;i Ihe Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to s com- 'Tie Political A^ent, Bahrain♦ aud has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- raent m British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated l 7 th u ctober 1935. Reference Residency Printed to previous correspondence h letter !To.3J&gt;^-3 oT^fith April 1935. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter Ho. ^.Z.3431 / /35of 12th Au^uat 1935 to the ?oreii?n Office. Hl-treatnent of Bahrainia in Persia.na)i a oypxca. P.Z.3431/35 J WHITEHALL, S.W.1 12th August, 1935. My dear Baggallay, Would you kindly refer to Foreign Office letter of tie ay, 1934, No .JS. 2633/1561/91 and correspondence regarding the ill-treatment of Bahreinis in Persia. We have never ar.swered this letter officially, though we have been on the point of doing so several times and we have had a good deal of inconclusive correspondence with India and the Gulf on It now seemsthat the problem has receded into the background, but it may be well if I summarise the position as it appears to us at present. be done on behalf of Bahreinis who have acquired Persian nationality by virtue of the Persian Nationality Law, but there is still a category, probably a small one, of a reinis who do not fail within the scope of the Persian Nationality Law (viz. presumably, Bahreinis born in Bahrein who possess no land in Persia). In regard to these the India Office 'view still is that it is desirable to protest in cases of ill-treatment if only to avoid the appearance of themselves, are lively to be unavailing) by retaliatory action has been considered at some length with the Government of India and the Resident and no very satisfactory suggestions have emerged. The only two suggestions which the subject with copies of which 1 need not trouble you. We are all now agreed that nothing effective can acquiescing in the Persian claim to Bahrein. The question of backing such protests (which, by still/ H. L. Baggallay, jgsq., Foreign Office, S.W.l. i^qpy sen t ' 0® Itil 2 . still appear to hold the field, and on which we do not know the Resident’s final views, are (a) a scheme for bringing Persian schools under the control of the Bahrein Educational Authorities (a scheme which may, in any case, be desirable on administrative grounds), and (b) a suggestion that persecuted Bahreinis should be removed from Persia and settled on the west side of Bahrein where, apparently, there is vacant space. On this, however, the question arises whether even persecuted Bahreinis in fact wish to leave Persia. This is as far as we have got up to the present. But it would now appear, e.g. from Ahwaa Despatch to Tehran No.27 dated 22nd April, 1935, that there is quite a good chance of no further trouble arising in this connection. We are therefore proposing to do no more at present unless Fowle, London, has any suggestions or views. The question of a Nationality Law for Bahrein which has come into this discussion is, of course, a separate matter and is, I believe, being dealt with on your side by Ward at the moment. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON. * j £No. 56 /- IS Bahrain, Dated, ^pril 27, 1929. From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, /». Persian Gulf. To V i* A His Britannic Majesty T s Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to inform you that Kis Highness Shaikh Hamad has desired me to forward to you the enclosed petition from certain of his subjects who are now living in Basrah and who were formerly living in Iran. His Highness wishes to know whether anything can ue none to assist them to retain their properties in Iran. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government. EnelA &lt;y \ &lt; Translation of a petition sent by Bahrainis living at Basrah to the Adviser, Bahrain Grovernment. x Petition dated 14th Safar 1358 (4th April 1939) tie the undersigned, Bahrainis who have Bahrain nationalities and passports, beg to state that We emigrated from Mohammerah five years ago. Most of us now live at Basrah. We left Iran when the Iranian Government issued the order that ’our VomM should not use°. he ils. V We had left our houses and properties in the hands of some Iranians and some in the hands of some of our relations who were forced to remain at Mohommerah. We had thus suffered heavy losses. Our properties have been ruined. Some of us could not rind anyone to trust with our properties which we had left. An Iranian comes and hires the property of pne: after two or three months he takes possession of it and makes it his own: when our agent files a case, the case is not accepted; the government does the same as when a government employe hires any of our pro- perties, he takes possession of it as soon as possible. y This happens because we cannot go to Iran; the government does not allow anyone carrying a Bahrain passport to enter Iran. y During these days a commission has been sent by the government to prove the ownership of properties, tie are in a fix because we cannot go to Mohommerah; if we do not go our properties will be taken. i. We request your honour, if we are considered as ‘ Bahrain nationals, to look into our matters with those of others who are still there, suffering treble and insult. They are compelled to take Iran nation ality: there is a section which had taken Bahrain passports but were yet compelled to take Iranian nationality. tie are now confronted with two problems, namely, (i) when the neriod of our passports expire wer have to renew them again either at Mohommerah or at^ Bahrain: this is impossible as we are not in Bahrain, and we cannot go to Mohommerah for want of a visa. Besides if we want to come to Bahrain we shall have pend about two months and pay a fee of Rs 5/-, ain. These two problems makes things very difficult for us because some of us have no money and some have no chances. Cy . We told the Consult at Basrah about all pur diffi culties and he informed us that no Bahrain nationa lity could be given except from Bahrain. - We request your honour and kindness that our peti tion be considered and arrange that our passports should be visaed by the Persian Government. H• Awaiting an early reply through the Consul at Basrah. we cannot get nationalities unless we go to«&lt;mi i iiiwi.B' Confidential D.O. No. C/322-1.a/2 Dated the 14th Kay 1939. *1 Will you please refer to your official letter No. 567-15 dated the 27th April 1939 with which you sent me a petition from certain alleged Bahrain subjects in regard to their property in Iran ? 2. I am afraid that it is quite impossible to do anything to assist these people to retain their properties in Iran. It has been general knowledge for years that Iranian Nationality and Property Laws make it impossible for foreigners to possess property in Iran # and indeed it was this that led to the issue of the Bahrain Nationality and Property Laws in retaliation. 3. I suspect that most of the signatories of this petition are people whose families have been resident in Mohammerah for generations, and though it is of course possible for such people to possess dual nationality they must recognise that in respect of property in Iran their ”master nationality 11 must be Iranian. Yours sincerely f L C. Dalrymple Belgrave f Ssquire, C.B.B., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, B AiLR A. ? , N . 0/cNo.&amp;2.C» - IP. y !&lt;&lt;]&lt; (/ / / The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. in duplicate and is directed to transmit to him a copy^of the undermentioned documents. for transmission to Bahrain State Authorities, British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. Reference to previous correspondence : s Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Copy of translation of a peti tion submitted to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, from Basrah, dated the 4th April, 193 9. Subject. Bahrain Subjects in Basrah.(Copy of Translation) Basrah, 4th April, 1939. &lt;§&gt; To The Hon'ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . Your Honour, we the undersigned, are the subjects of the Bahrain State according to the Passports obtained by us from the Bahrain Passport Office/tand which we hold. Most of us live in Basrah, Iraq, having immigrated there from Muhammerah and other towns five years ago or even before that period, at the time when the Iranian Government ordered the discard- 1 n e tne veil. we had to leave our houses and landed properties in the hands of foreigners or in charge of those of us who were unable to immigrate. During this period we have suffered great losses in damages done to our properties or their being forsaken as some of us could not find reliable persons to entrust their properties to them. Now it so happens that an Iranian leases a house or a shop and after the lapse of a period of two or three months ne would claim i t to oe his property and when the agent of the owner oi the property goes for litigation nis petitions would not be heard. Borne of our property have been given on rent by the Iranian Govcrntrient tnemselves and at this they oecotne the properties of the lessors. The cause of this state of affairs is the fact that we cannot visit Kuhammerah as the Iranian Government do not allow anybody to ca i ry Banrain nationality papers nor would they endorse such docu ments to enable us to enter Iran on the same. Lately a Committee has arrived at Muhammerah to register landed properties there. We are at a loss to understand what to do. vve cannot visit Iran and should we delay cur properties would be lost to us. we therefore request you kindly to give our case be lost to us.con si derat i on: if v; e your favourable consideration: if vie are your protected subjects protect us like one of yourselves and relieve those of us, the Bahrainis in Iran, who are being threatened to lose their nation ality and adopting the Iranian nationality. In fact some of them have been already forced to obtain Iranian nationality papers and have adopted Iranian nationality. We have two difficulties in our affairs namely:- (1) . At the expiry of two years we have to renew our passports in Bahrain or a t Muha mmerah. We cannot visit Muhammerah as the Iranian authorities would not endorse visas on our Banrain pass ports and if we were to get the renewal in Bahrain it will take at least two months oefore this could be done, and that on payncnt of Rs. 5/- each. (2) . We cannot get our nationality endorsed for us unless we sent somebody on our behalf to do this for us then he himself alone will get his paper endorsed. These are things which are hard for us to do, because there are amongst us persons who cannot do the voyage for want of time and others who do not possess money enough to p a y the expenses of the voyage. we referred, on this subject, to the British Consul, B a sr a h, and he informed us that he could not issue us nationality papers which we can get only in Bahra in. We request you to give our case your kind considerations and solve these difficulties tne important one of which is the endorsing of our passports by the Iranian authorities. \t the same time we request you to inform us through H. B. M * s Consul, Ba srah. (The following persons have affixed their signatures and those marked (*) have also affixed their seals to this petition.) Say id Muhsin son of Sayid Has a n *H a ji Ubaid son of Kaji Abbood al Kadhim. Mahdi son of Ha j i Ashur . Sayid Hasan son of Sayid Majid Darwish Ali Mulls Ali son of Ali(Jom icient iai. U* O..NO. 164-b 'ii The Residency, hushire, the 17th December 1941. i forward herewith a copy of a note which was recently given to me by Dredge. i understand bahrainis usually find ways and means of getting in and out of Khorramshahr and Abadan when they wish to and i do not propose to take up this particular case unless you see special reasons for doing so. i have already suggested that advantage should be taken of present circumstances to induce the Persian (iovernment to adopt a reasonable attitude vis-a-vis Bahrain in all matters vide my telegram No.T/716 of the 30th November 1941 enclosed with my Printed Letter ho.C/606 dated the 30th JMovember 1941. Major R.Cj. Alban, u.n.E. , Political Agent, .Bahrain.Office Not e. in the late half of November 1941 two Bahraini subjects, Sayed Jafar bin Sayeh Majid and Bayed Jafar bin oayed Haasan, holcers of Baliraim passports hoe• 24 and 42 respectively, approached the Iranian Consul at Basra for the necessary permits to proceed to Khorramshahr which according to their' statement v;ere ref usee. The two Bahrainis then entered Khorramshahr without any permit from the Iranian Consul at Basra. 2. On the 30th November 1941 these two men went to the Khorramshahr Police Ctation to obtain exit permits for their return to Basra. The Police authorities detained the two Bahrainis and confiscated their passports. They were released on bail after being retained one night in cus tody. 3. On the 2nd December 1941 the tv/o men presented a joint petition to this Vice-Consulate. On the 4th December trie /ice-Consui ordered the Consulate Munshi to approach the Governor and ask him to obtain the return of the two passports ana to allow the two Bahrainis to return to Basra. 4. ihese passports-v/ere eventually returned on the 11th December and travel permits authorising their departure from Khorramshahr were issued by the local authorities to the two men, who have now proceeded to Basra. b. Tiie Governor of Khorramshahr regretted the matter and suggested that the Vice-Consul should take up the quest! with the proper authorities so that definite instructions could be obtained for the future. 6. The Iranian Government do not admit the independence of Bahrain and claim it as an integral part of their territory. 'Elme Khabars' (Travel Permits; are issued tothe iraniana who travel from one port in Iran to another port in Iran. This covers Bahraini subjects, who from the Iranian standpoint are considered “Iranians'. The local authorities are authorised to issue 'JSlme Khabars' to “Bahrainis' resident in iran who wish to proceed to Bahrain, but it appears that the Iranian Consular authorities abroad have been forbidden to issue “Elme Khabars- to Bahrainis wr.o wish to enter Iran, although they are regarded from the Iranian point of view as Iranian subjects. 7. it is most unlikely that the Legation will take up the “old chestnut- of the status of Bahrainis vis-a-vis the Iranian Government. All that is required for the present is an order 1 rom the Iranian Government to the Consul at Basra to give travel permits lElme Khabars; to Bahraini subjects authorising them to enter Iran without interference by the Police or Passport authorities. This procedure would appear to compare with that in force in 1931 vide paragraph 4 of a letter ho.23b-S/31 dated the 5th May 1931 from the 1 olitical Resident to the foreign Becretary to the Government of India. 8. As local pressure has secured the release of the men and their return to Basra, the matter is no longer urgent, but in order to obviate future incidents, it is suggested that a Bavingram be issued from the Political Resident to the Legation giving them a very brief account of the facts and asking them to intervene. Sc. A.L. A. Dr eel £6 12/12/41. V ice-Consul.Confidential D. 0. No. C/83 Dated the 17th January 1942 Please refer to your demi-official letter No# 164-3 dated the 17th December 1941# 2. Kajor Alban has recorded the opinion, with which I agree, that there are no special reasons for taking up this particular case in the manner suggested by Dredge# Yours sincerely, I 1 / r^The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel W• R• Hay, C# X# n*#, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire#X S 0 ' - - \ ' r &gt; v,f 'Basrah 26th Dace ber, 1944 ^ His Excellency, II.B.M's Consul-General, Bushir e. . n submitted that we are merchants of Bahrain, which o a r uish Protectorate, have resided in Khormmahshahr(Persia) since a very ].ong time. But when the previous Government p^rT £ he .Persian people in general'and the subjects of the British Empire in particular very severely, we were compelled to emingrate to Iraq and leave our properties and residential quarters in the hands of foreigners. ?{ 1 khe event of the Allied Forces having entered the i^ersian soix, we were able to go and return to and from Iran Thf ? Urp ? se of observing our properties and other business. The Persian Government in the first stage disregarded our entry to Iran, due to the fact that we were provided with passports of oreign Government, but later the case has been reversed and very strict observation was imposed on every nan of our community on t 6 pretext that they were pursuing gangsters who are entering Iran irom the foreign countries. Whenever we produce our pass ports which were not endorsed with the Iranian Visa, we were dealt with very severely. In view of the fact that we are in a very urgent need ior travelling to Iran as to observe our properties and business there, we found ourselves in a very critical position and a very obsecure problem has arisen which cannot be solved except by your Excellency. f ac t that we are loyal subjects to tne British Empire we shall deem it a very great favour if you intervene with the Iranian Consulate in Basrah to grant us tiie necessary visas in order to enaole us to proceed to Iran in an official manner. \r ^?, we Q-iJ-b 0 aware of your magnanimity, we hope tnat you will not hesitate to consider our case favourably and arrange to settle this matter with your kind energy. For this act of kindness we shall be very grateful. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servants. Mr.H.Obaid Salih Bahraini. Mr. S. Adman S. Ahmed Bahraini Mr. H. Razi Sulamn. Bahraini Mr. Abdul Hassan.H Mr. Sayed H. S. Miksin Oraran H. Nasir Sulam H. Maiidy Sayed Kassim S. Hashira Mohamed Hassan H.S. Sayed Jomma S. Jawiad. S. Kazin S. Alavi. Mohammed Haji Her. Naera Hassan. Sayed Jaffar S. MaJ[id Bahraini Hassan H. Abb^od. Bahraini Mr. Sayed Mohsin S. Hassan. Haji Mohamed.R Mohammed Haji Mahdi. Sayed Husain Ali. V S Mohd. Haji Molla N Ali Haji Obaid. Abas Haji Obaid. S. Jassim Sayed Alaive. Haji H. Mazouk. Haji Mahdy Abda Ali. Ali Ebrahim. CON^IDEJIIA L NO.233- S British Residency, Bushire, the 17th February,1945 Copy forwarded with compliments tos- ,^aVLF Majesty's Consul, KHORRAMSHAR for favour of' . ;;/ (1 J. jne: Political Agent, BAHRAIN /'for information. SO&lt;7 1° Noe2^0 -2/29. British Consulate, ^hormpshahr 22nd March 1945. Comoran ium • The Secretary to the i-on'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. . . - f Reference your endorsement No. 233-S dated 17th February 1^45 on the subject of Bahrain passports. 2• Most of one persons referred to aisposea oi their properties some years ago when the Bahrain - Persian nationality question first became a serious issue. /Uthougn during the first year of our occupation the passport problem remained doimoit, the Persians are slowly reimposing a control and j- cannot see tnat the condition of these persons has in the meantime undergone any cnange. They are in fact of dual Persian - Bahrain nationality and while they can use a Bahrain passport outside iran, they must travel on a Persian passport to enter Iran. ^ ^ copy of this letter is being sent to the political Agent, Bahrain. c^V-^-A His majesty's Consul, Rho rramshahr. -°Py &gt; with compliments, forwarded to the political Agent, Bahrain.o.Wo.16 was discussed with, the Political Resident ana the Adviser on the 2bth November 1933. It was decided that the time was not suitable for measures of retaliation against the Persian Government. It was, however,thought that the question of bringing the Persian schools under the Lepartment of Education should be taken up and dealt with on its merits. 35-11-1933.Letter No:C.114 oi b-2-ly3^ xrom Aaviser to Banram Govt. Letter No:C/llb of 3-^-1934 from Mr.Belgrave. Please see P.ll wmch contains tne Resiaent’s views on the last protest submittea oj the Bahrain Government regarding tne treatment oi Bahrainis in Persia. Earlier file is also submitted. Telegram No:73 of o-iS-iyB* to Resident,Busmre. Printed Letter No:C/yy oi 17-^-1934 to Resident,Bushire. Letter No:G/100 of 17-2i-1934 to Adviser to Bahrain Govt. Preisent f s Printed Letter No:330-S of ^4th February ly34. Letter No:1116-S of Edth February 1934 from Adviser. P.A . Submitted. Adviser expects a man hack with a fullreport by next mail. He will let me have it as soon/rf as possible after it reaches him 3.3.34 Residents Printed Letter No:C/58 of 9th Kiarch 1934. -i' &gt; st&gt; Adviser T s letter No:118b-S.F of 14th March 1934. -f Xtf Printed Letter No:C/30y of 14th March 1934 to Resident. P.A. /l P.A. Submitted.I spolce about the ^estion of the ill-treatment ol Bahrainis m Persia with the Adviser on the k£nd llarch ana asked him whether Kis Excellency Shaikh Hamad had taken the question up. He said that the Shaikh had not himself spoken to him but that Shaikh T Abdullah had. Shaikh T Abdullah apparently feels strongly on the subject,not because ol the murder of any particular Bahraini m Persia but because he regards the gradual buying up of land in Bahrain by Persians as dangerous to the State and ne personally does not like the Persians. Eictated on ^4-3-1934. Residents Printed Letter No:C/119 of 36th Inarch 1934. File? z&gt; ^ Residents Printed Letter No:C/lBh of 37tn inlarch 1934. rile? lie,, dr s \ 1 ■ j : ; ^ 4 , ■ 'i\.p.a. Translation of the attached petition made and submitted Both petitions have the came wording and datej and with the exception of the mimes of persons signed by them, there is no difference between them. 17.4.34 c j Ouyr SjL fl&amp;u Residents Printed setter Ko:349-S dated 13th April 1934. Aaviser T s letter No:9-S.F uated 18th A r ril 1934. p X . A * Rubmittea. '{jU H ~ c ^ ^ ^ /v^- w '- P.A . May forward translation of the two petitions to P.R by P.L adding a second para - 'Endeavours are being made to ascertain (a) if all the signatories are Bahrain subjects and,(b) how many of them are land-holders'? /. U&lt;0. 2., ^ &lt;^c—L «• ' tr • fJvwc Vv^ 4 l 2i W i^+ZY' 'S.No:85. Printed Letter No:C/423 of 22nd April 1934 to Resident. S.No:86. Letter rJo:429 of 22nd April 1934 to Adviser. S.No:87. Resident's Printed Letter No:40d-S of 28th April 1934. S.No:88. Adviser's Memorandum No:48/SP dated 29th April 1934. P.A. S.No:87 . S.No:88. S File? Draft submitted for approval. 1 S.No:88. Resident's Printed Letter dated the — No: P.A. File? A S.D T o:90. Adviser T s Memorandum No:?9/S.F aated 10th May 1934. ■D A a . ii Draft to P.R submitted for approval. # I have slightly altered the form of the dra. t. But before issue we must make certain that the Bahrain Govt, know that the exceptions ,who have no nationality papers, are actually Bahrain subjects - it is much better to say so if there is any doubt in the matter. Issue memo. / \ 15.5.54 2.No:91. Memorandum No:C/524 of lS/b/1934 to Adviser, Bahrain State(m) r .ii. LIulla Hasan bin ash-Shailch has come to say that three of the Baharnah of ^asabah named(l) Zair T Abbud,(2) Saiyid Hadi and (3) Saiyid T Alawi have sent him to ask if it would be convenient to you to see them today or any other day. He says that they want to speak about the treatment of the Persians to them. For orders,please. 1^.34 % ^ iC- 10 '4? P.ii. The above three persons are present,please. u cu h 15.7.34 ■At* , Li &lt;h- —(71*+ ' 'l Petition from SS Bahrain subjects residing at Qusbah. Letter dated 18/7/1934 from Shaikh namd bin 'Isa. — r P.A . Submitted. S.No:99 and S.No: 100 are the same in substance. N.No:99, which is addressed to P.A is signed by SSpersons and S.No:100 addressed to Shaikh Hamad is signed by 21. Letter No:C/672 of 15/7/1934 to Resident, Bushire. Printed Letter Wo:C/673 of 15/7/1934 to Resident, Bushire. Draft to Shaikh hamad confirming your conversation of yesterday submitted for approval. (o H') Letter No:C/675 of 16th July 1934 to Shaikh iiamad. Petition signed by 20 Bahama of Qusbah. May forward translation to P.R in continuation ^ of Printed Letter at P.122 (S.No:102)? i, * nh , 1 - n nl- Printed Letter No:€/679 of 17/7/1934 to Resident. Residents Express Letter No:661-S of 13th July 1934. May file? iVT Res dent's Printed -fitter *'os758-S of Cth August '934 F led.oJ &amp; Resident’s Printed letter No*126-S of 24th January 1935 Secretary’s Printed better No:173 of 26th January 1935. Resident’s Printed Letter Ko:117-S of 21st January 1935, P.A. S.Ho sillS -ll?. S.KoM09. (*■ ■ 3f&gt;. Submitted. Resubmitted bide note on pre- page. File. But put up S.R.109 for discussion with P.R. 2. So far as Schools arc concerned w e are thinking of taking them all e'se?? under the Bahrain Govt, in co connection with/ the Baherinah trouble. 4.2.35 r Discussed with P.S. on the 23.2.35. Settlement of Bahrainis from Persia at Buda'ya might be useful if Shaikh wished to peBse as the protector of his subjects,but might mean a lot of poverty stricken people added to an hard-up population. W e had better drop if for the present. In any case we shd have to let H.M.G. know before we broached it. We shd at present concentrate on the Nationality Law proposal. // 24.2.35 S.No:118. Resident’s ^Tinted setter No:220-S dated 27-2-1935. P. A. Submitted. ^3(3 I a. y- it. w a. a—^ tt--</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002d5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/486</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002d5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/486</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 12/2 Treatment of Baharna in Persia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-23T00:12:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (220 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-220; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding the mistreatment of Bahraini nationals resident in Persia at the hands of the Persian Government.The file contains a number of petitions (in Arabic with English translations) sent to the Government of Bahrain and Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah by these groups of Bahrainis requesting assistance (ff 54, 81, 82, 118 and 126).The correspondence between British officials also discusses possible punitive measures against Persians (ff 144-149) resident in Bahrain and broader issues regarding Bahraini nationality (ff 174-177).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002d5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>