<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003e3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-15T15:10:20.041Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Copy of letter dated the 17th November 1940, from Consul, Muscat, to Sheikh Hassan Remah, Shihuh, Dhibah. I am at Kalba. I have heard that there is some disagreement between you and the people of Kalba. Barut will bring this letter• Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad is returning to Kalba, You should make a truce for fifteen days and inform the Wali of Khassab of what has happened. He and Sheikh Khalid will arrange what is best for you. The Jawisim have said they will take no action against you and you should take no action Leave against them. the matter to be settled by His Highness^ representative.— © Telegram GTC Prom Palitical» Sharjah To Politicalf Muscat* No 638 Dated the 25th November 1940* Addressed Political Resident repeated to Political Agent, Muscat. Regent Kalba leaves here tomorrow for Kalba on account of trouble at Diba. He reports that his subjects at Diba have Killed 3 and wounded 3 Shahuh..Telegram From To No* Dated TELEGRAM. - G*T.C. H 7 Political Agent, Muscat* Political Agent,Bahrain, reptd Pol* Sharjah. C/664. December 6th, 1940. Sultan instructed Wali of Khassab to proceed to Dhibah some days ago. Have you any news of present situation as Sultan is anxious for the latest information before decid ing whether or not to send Wali of Sohar who is here to Dhibah to deal with the situation. —December 8th, 1940* Hi My dear friend, I enclose a copy of a telegram which I have just received from Sharjah. In my opinion Sheikh Said of Dubai should mind his own business unless he is invited by both sides to intervene. If you will let me have your views I will reply to Sharjah. Will Mudhaffar go to Dhibah? Your sincere friend, Sd./ T.Hickinbotham. —* H.H. Saiyid Said bin Taimur, ✓*\ Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman.Telegram - G.T.C. From - Political Agent, Muscat. To - Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated to - Political Resident, Kuwait, and - Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. No. - C/661. Dated - December 8th, 1940. Y * &lt; P 0 R T A N T. Reference Political Officer's telegram 675 of December 7th to the effect that Sheikh of Dubai is leaving today Decem ber 8th for Dhibah. Sultan is sending influential represent ative by car to Dhibah today. He does not wish Dubai to interfere and asks that he may be stopped from doing so. I am in agreement and request that Dubai be induced to confine himself to Dubai affairs.Telegram From To Repeated Dated No. Date reed - Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. - Political Resident, Persian Gulf. - Political Agent, Huscat. - December 7th, 1940. - 1532 Z. - December 8th, 1940. Following received from H.M.S. Falmouth begins Wali Khasab reports fighting out between Jawasim and Shihuh tribes at Dhibah. Some casualties and damage to property. Wali is on his way to Dhibah to settle the dispute and states assistance not required. He requests following message may be forwarded to Sultan of Muscat as soon as possible begins 'Your servant is on his way to Dhibah'. Ends. Intend H.M.S. Falmouth to remain inactive at present.CONFIDENTIAL* No. C/663. Muscat, the 9th December,1940. To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Your Highness, I received telegraphic information yesterday through the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, from the Commander of H.M.S. Falmouth to the effect that the Wall of Khassab had informed the Commander that fighting had broken out between the Shihuh and Jawasim tribes at Dhibah, and that there had been casualties and damage to property. The Wali asked that Your Highness might be informed that he was on his way to Dhibah to settle the dispute. He informed the Commander that he did not require assistance. Your Highness^ sincere friend, Major, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.3TM ■ ■ CONFIDENTIAL No. C j 67. The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u shire, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s), Political Agency and British Consulate, H Reference/to previoji i^correspondence: My telegram C/661 dated the 8th December, 194Q. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. A T *Extract from a note on an interview at the Consulate with Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal on Sunday the 19th January, 1941. ' DHIBAH . The Regent of Kalba, Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad, has replied to the Sultan's suggestion that no strong post be built on the boundary between Jawasim and Shihuh territory at Dhibah to the effect that the lawless character of the Shihuh renders the construction of such a post necessary. Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal has informed the Regent of Kalba that the Sultan is away and asked that no action be taken until the Sultan returns when he will himself answer Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad's letter.' h*CONFIDENT IAL. No. 122. ( 4 ) The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document^). My printed letter N 0 . C/67 dated the 21st January 1941. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. 1, Extract from a note on an interview with Saiyid Shahab bin Situation at Dhibah. Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat, on February 1st, 1941,at 10 a.m. at his office.Extract from a note on an interview with Saiyid Shahab » bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat on February 1st, 1941, at 10 a.ra. at his office. 'S. Saiyid Shahab informed me that he had been informed through the Kalba authorities that the Shihuh at Dhibah had killed one she ass and had broken down a small wall both the property of the Jawasim. Saiyid Shahab has written to the Wali of Khassab to make enquiries and at the same time instruct ing him to warn the Shihuh that any overt act on their part would be looked upon with the gravest dissatisfaction by the Muscat Government M .!(&gt; CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/23 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to olitical Agent, [uscat. mrrr* r- r r&lt;. ; t ;aL Rtt * r r' '•/ I - j 11 ;&gt;?. t) lO-i-Hl , ; 53 t I ’ 1 _ im l l« and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (x), with the request that the proposal of Shaikh Khalid may be put to the Sultan. 2. A copy of the note sent with Muscat Printed .better No.C/67 dated the 21st January 1^41 has been sent to the Political Agent, Bahrain under Residency Printed Letter No.C/24 dated the 20th February 1^41. A a Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, BAHRAIN. Dated.2Qt&amp; .F?.l?r^ry..l^41 Reference to previous correspondence: Muscat Printed Letter No.C/67 dated the 21st January 1^41. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Bahrain memorandum No. C/135-22/11 dated the 12th February ltJ41. Subject. Situation at Dibah. V&gt;Confidential, No•C/135-22/11 POj-.IT ICAi. AGU.NCY, BAHhAIN, the 12th February 1^41. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . Memorandum. With reference to the recent troubles at Diba it is understood from the Political Officer Trucial Coast that the Sultan of Muscat wrote to Shaikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba, asking that the small tower, erected by the peojble of Biba against the Shahuh, should now be removed. The Political Officer Trucial Coast now reports that he has seen Shaikhs Khalid and Rumaid and that they have signified their willingness to leave the tower, which is incomplete, in its present state provided that the Sultan of Muscat gives suitable guarantees that he will control the Shahuh to the extent that he will pay compensation for any damage or injury they may cause to the property of the people of Diba. The Political Officer Trucial Coast considers this to be eminently reasonable. Shaikh Khalid stated that he hoped that any such agreement might be made under British auspices, to the extent that he would use our good oil ices to ensure its enforcement. 2. The building of fortified towers is a very provocative step and is, I think, to be discouraged whenever possible, but in this case Shaikh Khalid has stated that the Shahuh, who number some 10,000, had been very troublesome and had committed aggression without notice and were still committing thefts in his territory. If, therefore, it is possible to obtain the Sultan of Muscat's agreement to the guarantees asked for without the condition of complete removal of the tower, the affair will be settled and if the Shahuh should cause no further trouble during the next year the Shaikh of Kalba could be asked to remove the tower completely.Li Extract from a note on an interview with Saiyid Shahab^*! bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, M n scat, at the Consulate on April 9th, 1941, at 10 a.m. 2 * Saiyid Shahab told me that he had heard that renewed fighting had taken place between the Jawasim and the Shihuh at Dhibah and that he was told they had possibly ta en Ba'ah. He thought this could only have happened if the Shihuh were dis united which he thought was the case. He blamed the Wall of Khassab for most of the trouble as he was said to be lazy and not looking after the Shihuh interests, nor was he hearing cases, -aiyid Shahab is awaiting a messenger who he believes to be on the v/ay and in the meantime I have telegraphed to Sharjah and Bahrain. I told him that if the matter was really serious I would probably go there m self to see the position provided the Muscat Government had no objection. Saiyid Shahab will wire the Sultan when he has more reliable news.MW&gt;9 r* Translation of letter dated the 12th Rabial Awal,1360 (10.4.41) from Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat to H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. After Compliments. Reference our conversation of yesterday regarding the Shihu and the Qawasim. I received a letter last evening from the V/ali of Bahar, Mudhafar, enclosing a letter from the Nayeb of the Sahikh of Fujairah. The purport is that there was disturbance between the Shihu and the Qawasim in Dibah and that the information reached Kumaid bin Abdullah who sent 40 men of his and captured Wadi Madha without any fighting. I think that the renewal of the disturbance between the Shihu and the Qawasim is on account of the tower. Surely there must be more informations there than what have been mentioned by the Nayeb of the Shaikh of Fujairah or other chan what he has said. I am therefore thinking of sending Ali bin Mudhafar, the Wali of ohanas to that side to ascertain what is there and to inform me of the facts. I hope that you have received reply from the Hon’ble the Political Resident. Usual Ending. JTelegram - GTC From Tc No. - Brita^ent, - political, Muscat. - 319 Dated the 9th Ajjril 1941 (Reed. U.4.4i) Important. Addressed Bahj?€un repeated Muscat. Muscat telepram 759^A^ril 9ta. Batest news confirmed by Repent of Kalba, Wadi Madha over whom Q,awasiiL lost influence for many years reverted ' Qawasim of their own accord after recent attack by reverted in my memorandum No.G 302 A^ril 2nd. 2. Recent leaving for Kaiba in a day or two. No fighting or encroachment by eitner siae are reported. JNote on an interview with Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat, at 10 a.m. at the Consulate on April 12th, 1941. Saiyid Shahab brought a file of letters with him which had been received from the Wali of Sohar and the Shihuh. He was worried and at first rather excited. He informed me that he had now been informed by Sheikh Sultan bin 0 f that the Jawasim had taken over control of the Wadi Mahda, Gona and Haji and that this had been accomplished without blood shed. It seems the Shihuh guards were bribed and later imprisoned in Kalba. He said that it (/'/as a fact he thought that these areas had many many years ago belonged to the Jawasim. He further stated that since heikh Sultan bin . had left Dhibah he had received a report that four of the Shihuh had been killed. The Shihuh maintained that they had not in any way provoked an attack and that they had done as they were told by the Muscat Government. ; c^iyid. ^hanah thought that on this occasion the Shihuh were in the right and asked that the Jawasim be stopped from continuing their aggressive acts. The Shihuh had appealed to the Muscat Government for arms and ammunition and he found it difficult to refuse their request in view of the attitude of the Jawasim. In answer to my enquiry he said it was probable that Ali bin Mudhaff- ar, ..ali of Shinas, had not been able to carry out his instruct ions which were to visit Dhibah and report on the position. I asked him what he considered the reason for the action now taken by the Jawasira and he said he thought that it was due to dislike of the Sultan’s objection to the construction of the tower at Shibah and the Sultan’s construction of a tower near the Wadi al Qaur. We discussed the whole subject carefully and Saiyid Shahab showed me and read to me extracts from letters written to the Wali of Khassab by Sultan bin Sagar and Sultan bin Salim who have A interested themselves in a matter with which they have no concern. I promised to telegraph to the Resident regarding the situation and told Saiyid Shahab that I would myself go to Dhibah and examine the position and would take with me any representative ^2 2L Note on an interview with Sheikh Sultan bin al Shihuh on April 12th, 1941, at the Consulate. The Sheikh said he had come to seek aid from the Muscat Government. The Jawasim had occupied Mahda, Gona and Faji by bribing the guards. These areas had been under the Shihuh control for many years and were inhabited by the Shihuh. The Jawasira who had occupied them were not solely from Kalba but also from Ras-al-Khaimah and Sharjah. The tower at Dhibah over which there had been much controversy was still being built and work had not ceased as I had supposed. Sheikh Huinaid was at the root of the trouble between the Shihuh and the Jawasim. They had got on very well with Rashid bin Ahmad but coufca not get on with Humaid. He maintained that the Jawasim's move was unprovoked. When he left no fighting had taken place and he had only learnt since his arrival of the four persons said to have ^een killed. of the Sultan that he might appoint to examine the situation and report to the Muscat Government. My own part would be to see what had happened and what the present position was. Saiyid Shahab said he would send the Wall of Sohar with me and would not send any aid to the Shihuh pending ray return. [v/ 2y •1)- Telegram - GTC From - Political, Muscat. To - Britcnnsul, Bushire Repeated to Political, Bahrain. Political, Sharjah. No. - 790 Dated the 12th April 1941. Addressed Resident repeated Bahrain and Sharjah. Jav/asim Shihuh. 2. Sultan’s Representative has received disturbing messages and appeals for help from Shihuh who complain Jawasim have occupied M aSha, Gona and Hajar after bribing and later r imprisoning Shihuh guards. Shihuh state they have had four killed in a fight ten days ago. Rumours reaching here speak of Shihuh attack on Jawasim. 3. Representative asks that Jawasim be prevented from father aggressive acts. I am leaving for Sohar and Dhibah April 14th to examine the position. Wali of Sohar v/ill accompany me to Dhibah to investigate on behalf of Muscat Government. Representative has agreed not to send aid to Shihuh pending my return to Muscat. 4. Suggest the Jawasim be warned not to commit further acts of aggression and that if possible Residency Agent, Sharjah meet me at Dhibah to discuss a settlement of the situation about April 15th.Telegram - GTC From - politic el, To - roliticni, Muscat, No. - 75 Dated the 13th A^ril 1941, V' 0 15 Muscat telegram 790 Ajjril 12th. If approved Residency Agent might be sent to meet the Political Agent at Dibah but will not reach for several days. Regent Kaibo might also be ^resent. proposal, mi^ht be sent to me for comments before confirmation. Jawassim will be warned but it a^^ears that Shihuh have committed aggression and should be proceeded against vide my letter No. 305 April 5th. Your instructions awaited, Vm Telegram - GTC From Britconsul, Euanire To Political, Muscat. No 247 Dated the 14th A^ril 1941. , (Recdd. lo.4.4l) Addressed Bahrain me^ated Muscat. 2. Your telegram 75 A^rii 13th -.vhich Muscat shoulc iiQ^oae. 3. I see no objection to ^resencte of Regent Krlbn. and to settlement on the lines of his ^ro^osal reported in your memorandum No. C/l35 February 12th. 4. Please give co^y of current telegraphic correspondence to Senior Naval Officer and send a co^y to Muscat of your memorandum No.C/305 A^ril 5ti..Copy, 19/4/41. My dear Friend, » Tennis and other forms of exercise are probably as beneficial and certainly no more expensive than other correct ives. I am glad to hear that you have nearly finished with your treatment and am looking forward to seeing you again. I have just returned from Dhibah where I have been to look into the renewal of hostilities between the Shihuh and the Jawasim. A two months 1 truce has been arranged and I will discuss the question with you when we meet which will probably be in Karachi. All is well here. I got back from Dhibah last night and am writing in a hurry to catch the mail. Your sincere friend, Sd./ T.Hickinbotham. H.H. Saiyid Said bin Tairaur, Bombay. rJ. Mil ii-J An j je I jii^ji nu j,^i n ,&gt; • in* j^-yi ^ v i cr' ^vLy— -V-J* V-*^ Jwj*«n4 • pr^* 31 No. 336 of 1941. His Britannic Majesty*s Consulate, Muscat, the 19th April, 1941. I *^4^1 J U ^yl * ^ ^ ft* &lt;y ■.■^.^juJL DUJl { j* 111) &lt; • J&lt; O' 1 ^ To Saiyid 3hahat bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat. After Compliments. I returned last evening. I am enclosing a letter addressed to you by the Wall of Sohar. I suggest that I call on you at a time convenient to you on the 21st April and give you the position in detail. I have also heard from His Kighnes the Sultan who hopes to arrive here early in May. Usual Ending. Major, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.Translation of letter datea the l^th Rabial Awal, 1360 (17.4.41) from the Tali of Sohar to oaiyid Shahab bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat. After Compliments. I received your letter^nd understood what you said in it. I accompanied the Consul to ciba and found your servant Ali bin Mudhaffar present there according to your orders. A truce has been effected between them for two months. Te saw the ohihus gathered there from hills and sea. Muhammad bin Ahmad of Bukha sent his nephew Hamdan and his son. '-e found the tower built by Qawasims in Diba nearly completed. Ali arranged that they should not renew building till the tine of the truce expires. Syed Abdur Rezzaq, Resi dency Agent, Sharjah arrived. The Qawasims Khallj. and Humaid are in Kalba at present. The truth you will know from the Consul. Ali Jfey write to you on the subject. Te did not stay here more than a few hours. Usual Ending. This letter has been written in Kalba landing ground as Sahib ^Consul) could not stay.wmmm* WHflUKHTlAl, No. C/328. Political Agency &amp; H.L.M’b Consulate, ^ s Muscat, the 22nd April, 1941. © ' To From Major T. Hickinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• Sir, I have the honour to refer to my telegram No. 834, dated the 18th April, 1941, and to inform you that I visited Dibah on the 17th of April accompanied by the Wall of Sohar who had been instrucVj ed by the Muscat Government to proceed there and to furnish a report on the situation. At Dibah I met the Sheikh of Fujairah and Ali bin Mudhaffar, Wall of Shinas, who had already been sent by the Muscat Government with instructions to endeavour to terminate the present hostilities which instructions, I am glad to report, he had been able to carry out before I arrived with the aid of the Sheikh of Fujairah. I visited the Jawasim section of the area and conversed with Barut, the Wall, afterwards inspecting the unfinished tower which has been the cause of much of the trouble. Later I went on to the Shihuh area and talked with the Shihuh Sheikh, Hassan bin Rahmah ; and various tribal leaders from the hills of the Masandam Peninsula. As I was returning from Dibah to Khor Fakkan I met Khan Sahib Abdur Hazzak, Residency Agent at Sharjah, and had a full discussion with him. Late the same evening after we had returned to Kalba we had a lengthy interview with Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, and his nephew Sheikh Humaid bin Abdullah. 2. There have been changes in the political situation in the If area affected by the recent incidents since the Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf was produced by Lorlmar In 1908. Mad-hah CLorimar' Volume II /Volume II page 1696) is much the same and is visible from Khor Fakkan but appears to be only about four miles away* uhunah ('Lorimer” Volume II page 1696) has altered little as far as I know and the same applies to A1 Hair ( ,, Lorimer f, Volume II page 1696), but in Dibah there have been important changes* The original village of Dibah now belongs exclusively to the Sharqiyin and it is the vill age of Bai'ah with which this despatch deals. The Jawasim have been ousted from Dibah and now inhabit the southern section of Bai’ah from the dividing Wadi mentioned by '•Lorimer” at page 463 of Volume II for a distance of some six hundred yards to the north. Using the term Dibah to indicate the whole area as is generally done nowadays it will be noted that the Sharqiyin own the lower half while the Jawasim and the Shihuh are uneasy neighbours in the upper half of which the Shihuh have the larger share. The area is no longer in the Ras-al-Khaimah district of Sharjah. 3 . The immediate cause of the trouble between the Jawasim and the Shihuh is the Regent of Kalba's endeavour to manage his own affaire in Dibah and to protect his subjects from acts of brigand age. The Shihuh are of a peculiar and aggressive disposition and until recently did practically anything that they wished in the Jawasim area even, I understand, to the extent of liberating persons from the Fort and nothing was done to check their highhand ed behaviour by the Jawasim Wali nor I regret to say by the *ali of Khassab in whose wilayat the majority of them live. As soon as the Regent of Kalba took action to end this state of affairs there were immediate and explosive reactions from the Shihuh. The position between the two tribes is not eased by the fact that their common frontier,is, like so many frontiers in Arabia, ill defined. Between what is without doubt Jawasim territory and what is equally certainly Shihuh there is an area covered with date gardens some six hundred yards in length parallel to the beach, which is inhab ited by a small tribe known as the Dhuriyin who live with the Shihuh but pay half their Zakat to the Jawasim and half to the Shihuh /3 &amp; ^ ■: r. Shihuh, Neither side can lod^e euiy certain claim to the area ao it remains a 'no man's land*'* The first encounter occurred in November and came to an end -vlion the Sheikh of Fujairah and the a alia of Khassab and Sohar inter vened and succeeded in terminating the actual hostilities. The Jawa- sim then commenced to build a tower on the beach some hundred yards on the Chi huh side of the Jawasim fort and at the edge of what they can undoubtedly claim as their own territory, whereupon the Shihuh object ed and petitioned the Muscat Government to press for its removal or permit them to construct an opposition tower. The Sultan refused to permit them to build and negotiations were entered upon with the obj ect of persuading the Jawasim to remove their tower in return for a guarantee by the Sultan that he would control his subjects and accept responsibility for their acts and pending a decision the Regent! | of Kalba agreed to discontinue work on the building but he placed a small garrison in it. On the 28th March the Shihuh attacked the garrison and shots were exchanged but the action was inconclusive. The Jawasim exasperated by the action of their neighbours seem to have decided to accept an invitation to resume control of the villages of Mad-hah, Ghunah,and A1 Hair,whose inhabitants akin to the Beni Saad sub-saction of the Shihuh living between Shinas and Sohar have been paying ~^akat to the Shihuh for a number of years although I understand they originally paid Zakat to the Jawasim and were indeed according to Lorimer (Volume II page 1694) in 1908 part of the then disinteg rating Jawasim Sheikhdom of Sharjah. I am told that the invitation to the Jawasim was made owing to the inhabitants' mistrust of the Shihuh and the uncertainty of the situation. The Jawasim were not opposed in their undertaking although shots continued to be exchanged between the two tribes in Dibah. On the Shihuh side the question of the tower looms very large indeed and was the immediate cause of the outbreak last month although their resentment at the Regent of Kalba's wish to be master in hie own house is the real reason for the whole disturbance. The Shihuh knew that / V y •4 ^7 kne*i that the work of construction of the tower had ceased pending the result of the negotiations in progress and they considered that the Jawasim were not carrying out the spirit of the arrangement by placing a garrison on the foundations of the tower, and reports that the construction was actually being continued were believed by them* The occupation of territory which they considered rightly belonged to them, I refer to the Jawasim action at the villages of Mad-hah, Ghunah,and A1 Hair,further irritated them and the Ghihuh from the hills were summoned to protect the ancestral lands and messages with the corner dramatically burnt off as a sign that the contents affect ed matters of life and death were sent to Muscat calling on their overlord for help* The total casualties during the recent hostilities are one killed on each side and one man wounded but I am in doubt If this last was a Jawasim or a Shihuh* 5* The Jawasim have every right to object to the attitude and actions of the Chihuh and the Muscat Government are certainly at fault in not taking adequate steps to control their subjects but the i Jawasim are also at fault for, as the Regent acknowledged to me, they made no complaint to the Muscat Government prior to the hostilities in November and so did not give the Sultan an opportunity to regularise the position* This failure to communicate with Muscat was due to the fact that for many many years the Jawasim have dealt direct with the Shihuh over tribal matters and do not seem to have considered Shihuh territory as Muscat ten itory. The tower is strategically useless, politically highly undesirable, and has already caused trouble enough, and although I do not believe the Shihuh statement that the work of construction was continued after it had been agreed that it should cease, I consider that the estab lishment by the Jawasim of a guard on the building was not in accordance with the spirit of the agreement between the Regent and the Sultan* The occupation of the villages of Mad-hah, Ghunah and A1 Hair was /Hair w&amp;6) “to say the least of lt y carried out at a very ill chosen time by invitation though it may have been. There is no doubt if the Muscat Authorities ha d exercised propur control in the Shihuh area the present situation would not ha -risen so that there is really very little to chose between the two parties and I suggest that the past be not disturbed any further than it has been already and our attention be concentrated on the future. A truce has been negotiated to last two months during which time it is hoped that the questions of the tower and the villages of 4ad-hah, Ghunah,and Al Hair will be satisfactorxly settled and provided the Sultan returns in time I see no reason why this should not be done and even if it takes longer than two months to complete the negotiations there could be no objection to the truce being extended. 6. I suggest that the Sultan should undertake to control his subjects in Dibah and that in return the Regent of Kalba should re move the tower. As regards the villages of Mad-hah, Ghunah,and Al Hair the actual sovereignty should be determined between the two parties or if they prefer or fail to agree between themselves it should be referred to arbitration. If the decision goes against the Sultan then there is no more to be said and if the decision goes against the Regent then he can always say that he went there by invitation under a misapprehension and withdraw gracefully. These suggestions are on the whole acceptable to the Regent but he did not actually agree to the immediate demolition of the tower on the Sultan’s guaranteeing the good conduct of his subjects but preferred to retain the unfinished structure for one year to act mention the question of the method of determining the ownership of the area in dispute if they should be unable to agree on this ques tion. However I should prefer to see the tower removed and feel that Sheikh Khalid would not really raise any strong objection. I time I / : -i * ; UM ‘time X propose t»o press him *to put his own representative into Dibah, a course of action which would do much to reassure the Jawasim and would be beneficial to the Shihuh though it would possibly not be altogether appreciated by their Sheikhy Hass an bin Rahmah, who I trust will b» replaced by a more reliable person. I have discussed the question fully with Khan Sahib Abdur Razzak who is I understand in agreement with ay views on the situation. I have also had an opportunity since writing the major portion of this despatch of discussing the matter informally with Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal, the Sultan's uncle and Representative. He considered the Shihuh to blame and spoke of the Jawasim as being oppressed by them and viewed with much favour the appointment of a representative of the Muscat Government at Dibah (Shihuh) • He seemed little interested in the three villages and I can only trust that his nephew's views will be as acceptable and conducive to the speedy settlement of the whole question. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat.Confidential No. C/331-22/11. / The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to send him a flOffy'^Tthe uSa«rmentioned document ( s ) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated JttheL...16 tli~ADrilr-4^41. Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident's telegram No.247 dated 15th April i^l. Description of Enclosure. '*^ m ' \ a Name and Date. Memorandum No.C/305-22/11 dated the 5th April 1941 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to th-^ Political Resident, Camp, Bahrain, Subject. Situation at Dibah. \ ■ * 1 'No.C/305-22/11 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th April 1341 To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Can^, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference correspondence ending with your Printed letter No.C/81 dated the 1st March 1041. 2. The copy of a memorandum No.C/302-3/5(g) dated the 1 2nd April 1941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, with 'j enclosure is forwarded herewith. 3. It is suggested that the Muscat Government might be asked to take energetic steps to prevent such aggress ions by the Shahuh. Sd. R. G. Alban. Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential No.C/302-3/5(g) British Agency Sharjah. 2md April 1941. To The Political .Agent, Bahrain. I-’emorandur I enclose herewith copy (with translation) of a letter dated 4th Habi* al Auwal 1360 (i.e. 1st April 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Begent of Baiba, who is now at Dhaid. 2. Ahmad bin Rashid referred to in Shaikh Fhalid’s letter is the latter's nephew and former Shaikh of 3iba- Hisn (Oawajimi) who retired owin^ to his incapability to deal with the Shahuh. Barut is the Oawasim '’^ali at Diba-Hisn. Kurnaid bin 'Abdullah nephew of Shaikh Phalid left Ajman for Kalba on 30th March 1941. Sd. A. Rezzaq. Residency Agent, ^harjah.Translation of letter dated 4th Habi f al Auwal 1360 (1.4,41) from ihaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. ******* ****** After Compliments, I arrived at Dhaid safely. Today T received a message from our son'' nephew) Ahmad bin Rashid at halba stating that they received a message rom the s ervant Rarut to the effect that the Shahuh got reinforcements from Muhammad bin Ahmad of Rakha. That on the night of their arrival they attacked the ’Turabba’ah' (tower) and exchanged shots with the people of the 'Murabba^h' but were repulsed. Hostilities have been resumed. T am writing this to inform you of what has happened. rr, he messengers crossed our son (nephew) Humaid. Usual Ending.No. Confidential C/345-22/11. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— 1. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to send him a copy^d ^J^ntioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the “20th April 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No.C/321 dated 10th April 1941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. with enclosure. Situation at Dibah. 5 ' [I■ ' \ m Confidential No.C/321-3/5(g)• British Agency, Sharjah, 10th April 1941. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memoranduir. Reference my telegram No.319 of 9th April 1941 on the subject of Shahuh/Qawasirr/Diba situation. 2. I bag to enclose copy (with translation) of a letter which I received from the Regent of Kalba when I was actually replying to Muscat telegram. According to independent enquiries made by me which were subsequently confirmed by the Regent of Kalba, the people of Wadi Madhah (consisting of three villages - Madhah, Grhuna and Hayar Bani Hamid) in the Shamaliyah District appealed to Shaikh Humaid bin ’Abdullah, when the trouble first broke out at Diba, for safe conduct and protection which was granted to them through the Shaikh of Fujairah. Being afraid of the Shahuh they pressed Shaikh Humaid bin ’Abdullah for mentto protect them. This was given to them when Humaid was on his qay to Kalba on 30th March. He sent few men to each village and re-established the Qawasim authority over that area which, for many years past, was under the influence of the Shahuh on account of the ®awasim waekness. 3. The Shahuh sent a messenger to Dubai from where he went to Abu Dhabi asking for help. It is unlikely that they would be able to get any help from these two Sheikhdoms. Sd. Abdur Rezzaq. Residency Agent, Sharjah\ r\ &amp; Translation of letter dated 12th Habi 1 al Auwal 1360(12.3.41) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba to the Resi dency Agent, Sharjah. After Compliments, I write to inform you about the Shahuh agressive acts which are known to every one. On 28th Safar 1360 (27th March 1941) Muhammad bin Ahmad the Amir of Bakha by previous agreement with Hasan bin Rahmah the Amir of the Shahuh at Ba^ah, decided to send (a force of) 60 men. On the night of 28th Safar at about 8 Arabic at night they arrived at our town Diba when the people were quietly and unaware as they relied on the peace entered into between our son Shaikh Humaid bin *Abdullah and the Shahuh through the mediation of Saiyid Badr bin Sa’ud, Wali of Khasab. On reaching our town they fired at once on the residential quart ers and the Marabba'ah (tower). They also caused great damage to t .e date gardens, having spoiled the fruits and cut some of the trees. These are the savage acts of the Shahuh who do not abide by their pledges and undertakings but rely on treachery and cheating to which may be added thejtr agressive acts against the poor people. I also write to inform you that the people of ladi Madhah who were out sub jects from the olden time appealed to our son Shaikh Humaid for protection against the oppressive treatment they received on the hands of the Shahuh. He sent some men to protect them, the fact which I pass on for your information. Usual Ending. '5 V Confidential No. C/398-22/11, ' \ r: J ■ The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— 1. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf f Bushire. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to send him a copyj 1 document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated, the 29 th„ April.. 1941 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. / Name and Date, Memorandum No.C/331-3/5(g) dated the 22nd April 1941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject. Situation at Diba. f I ifI * I (ii) /- Confidential British Agency, Sharjah, 22nd April 1941 No,C/331-3/5(g). To The Political Agent, Bahrain. V . Memorandum Reference your telegram No.79 of 15th April 1941, I beg to report the following on the subject of Shahuh/Oav/asim/ Diba situation:- (i) ’Ali bin Mudhaffar, Wali of Shinas, ari'ived at Kalba on 13th April accompanied by Muhammad bin Nasir, Shaikh of Abu Baqarah (Muscat). After discussing the situation with Shaikh Humaid bin 'Abdullah, nephew of the Regent of Kalba, he proceeded to Khosf Fakkan. As a result of their discussions, the v/ali of Shinas was authorised by Humaii to enquire both on behalf of the Muscat Authorities and the Oawasim and arrange what he considered best for all concerned. Humaid also agreed to the suggestion made by the Wali of Shinas to ask the Shaikh of Fujairah to accompany him and assist in putting an end to hostilities. On the 14th the Wali of Shinas left Khor Fakkan for Diba, accompanied by Muhammad bin Hamad ash-Sharqi of Fujairah. The Shaikh of Fujairah remained at Hisn-Diba while the Wali of Shinas and the Shaikh of Abu Baqarah went to Bai'ah. On 15th the Wali of Shinas with the help of the Shaikhs of Fuhairah and Abu Baqarah succeeded in arranging two months truce pending final agreement on return of the SultaA from India.(ii) On 14th Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, arrived at Kalba from Ajman In order to meet the Political Agent, T'uscat. (iii) On the morning of 16th, the Political Agent, Muscat, arrived by car and after remaining for a short while ^ &amp; in the landing ground proceeded to Hhor Fakkan from where he embarked on a dhow for Diba. He was accom panied by the Wall of Sohar, Mudhaffar bin Suwailim. Owing to strong Shamal they were compelled to take shelter at Dhadnah (about half way between Khor Fakkan and Diba) where they spent the night. On 17th morning the Shamal calmed down and the Political Agent left Dhadnah for Diba, (iv) I left Sharjah on the night of 15th and arrived at Kalba on the evening of 16th. I travelled via Siji and Wadi Ham. On the morning of l^th I left Kalba, accompanied by Shaikhs Khalid and Pumaid, for Khor Fakkan and from there left by sailing boat for Diba.. Owing to head-wind we could not make much progress and at about 1 p.m. we met the Political Agent and the Valis returning from Diba after visiting Ba^ah and Hisn-Diba. We all returned to Khor Fakkan and then proceeded to Kalba. (v) On the night of 17th, a meeting, attended by the Political Agent, Muscat, Shaikhs Khalid and Humaid and myself, was held at which the whole situation was re viewed and discussed in details. The upshot of it was that Shaikh Khalid is willing to take no reprisal action against the Shahuh in the future before informing the Muscat and Political Authorities provided the Sultan of Muscat undertakes to control the Shahuh and pay compensation for any damage or injuries the Shahuh may cause to the property and subjects of the Qawasim. ShaikhA w /'N - 3 - Shaikh Khalid admitted that the 'Murabba*ah' had been completed. He explained that the Shahuh attacked Diba-Hisn on the night of 27th March. That on the night of 28th ? T arch the Wall of Diba-Hisn restarted the work on the “Murabba*ah' which he considered necessary for the protection of the inhabitants. He said that he was within his rights to build any number of towers within his territory for the protec tion of his subjects without prejudice to the inter ests of the Muscat authorities who were at liberty to d do what they liked in their territory. After one year from the date on which the Sultan undertakes responsibility for the Shahuh, Shaikh Khalid agreed to raise the 'Murabba’ah' to the ground if the Shahuh’s behaviour is satisfactory during this period. (*i) Regarding Wadi Madha. Shaikh Khalid said that since he became Regent of Kalba, the inhabitants of Wadi Madha have been pressing him for protection against maraudings by the Shahuh but in order to keep friendly with the Shahuh so that they may not create trouble for Diba he used to keep them off from time to time. As the Shahuh did not appreciate his good intentions and, contrary to tribal customs, attacked Diba-Hisn without ultimatum, he waw no alternative, in view of the repeated appeals made to him by the people 6f Wadi Madha, than to protect them. He said that Wadi Ma^iha paid Zakat to the Qawasim for about 100 years or more and the inhabitants were always considered as subjects of the Qawasim. That when Flijairah revolt ed against the Qawaaim, the people of Wadi Madha we^e compelled by circumstances and owing to lack of c Qawasim influence in that area, to seek the prote^Hion of /-- 4 - « ' * of the 3h©huh. That although the people of Wadi Madha paid tribute to the Shahuh in return for protection, in no time did the Muscat Authorities receive Zakat from them. That the Qawasim are in possession of a document signed by the Muscat autho rities defining their boundaries and therefore the return of V/asi Madha to the Qawasim should not be considered by the Muscat Authorities as an act of agression directed against them. (vii) Shaikh Khalid said that the Shahuh sent false reports to the Muscat Authorities with the main object of in citing them against the Qawasim. In support of this he said that in the first attack on 27th March they had no casualties but they sent a special messenger to Muscat that they lost four killed. That only in the attack made about the 12th they had one killed and one v/ounded and one killed on the Qawasim side. From enquiries made by the Political Agent, Muscat and myselfbnly one killed and one wounded on the Shahhh and one killed on the Qawasim. (viii) The Political Agent, Muscat said that owing to the absence of the Sultan of Muscat in India it would not be possible for his Representative to decide anything. He expressed hope that a suitable solution would be m made on his return. On the 18th morning the Political Agent left for Muscat by car. (ix) From enquiries made by me which were corroborated by the Shaikh of Abu Raqarah, the Shahuh numbered about 1500 when he and the Wall of Shinas arrived at Bai’ah- Riba on 14th. Most of them left for their villages in the hills after tihe truce on 15th. When the Political Agent arrived at 3ai’ah there were about 400 and /-• 5 - and about 70 arrived in sailing-boats from Bakha at the time the Political Agent arrived there. The force of the Oawaaim was about 200* I returned to Shar/jah via Wadi Ham, Masafi and Sifti on the ni 'ht of 21st. 2. Both the Political Agent and myself are of opinion that unless the Muscat Authorities appoint a Wali at Bai^h- Diba there can be no peace in that area and the Muscat Authorities would find it difficult to control the Shahuh. Sd. A. Hezzaq. Besidency Agent, Sharjah. r iDated Repeated TELEGRAM. - 'G'lT.c, - Political Agent, Bahrain. - Political Acrent, Muscat. - 119. - May 8th, 1941. - Political Resident, Bushire. Following from Residency Agent Sharjah begins Regent of Kalba who is now at Ajman reports that he has received messages from his nephew Humaid at Kalba to the t effect that on the night of May 2nd Shihuh raided, and demolish ed wall and occupied strategic positions round Dibuh . Next morning Shihuh imprisoned one Qawasim subject and his wife but managed to escape. Qawasim then imprisoned one Shihuh as reprisal.J - i t Vi British .agency, Sharj ah, 10th May 1941. Sir, JJegmrence your telegram No.821 of 8th May 1941» I an sending the launch of Nakhudha Ahmad tonight with instructions to wait for you at J&lt;dior Kakkta until Friday night the 16th May 1941. 2. I have arranged with the iMakhudha that he should r receive Hs.250/- to Khor Fakkan and Khor jawai. If you finish with the launch at Khor Ouwai you may permit him to go where he liked. If you decide to go back on the launch to Khor Fakkan then^extra sum of Ks.100/- may be paid to him. thus making a total of ris.350/- to Khor Quwai and back to Khor Fakkan* 3* I have also asked him to take extra K.oil in case he may be wanted fa? extra wark there for which he can fix the hire with you. If you have not the money, you may give him a 4etter to me and I xxm will pay him here and you can remit it to me from Muscat. 4. Shaikh Khalid informed me that the Shahuh again started trouble at Diba and the man in charge of Diba Hisn was given strict instructions not to do any thing which might spoil discussions and that he should only be on the defence side and not comrait an aggression. He also informed me that the shanhuh imprisoned one of the c^awasim and the ^awasim imprisoned one on the Shahuh side. You^havj received copy of my report to Bahrain about this matter. I think it^a storm in i&gt; er-eup of tea. Keys current here that after yam* return oo Muscat 3aiyid Shahab has changed his attitude towards the Qawasim and Khiid attributes this to your good offices. He has been sending strict instructions to his nephew to do no act which might in any way be displeasing and that their men at Diba should confine themselves to defence and leave the :&amp;ahuh do what they liked. I hope that you are in good health and had no trouble on the way to Muscat. I am very thankful to you for the telegram you sent to the office which was very helpful Major T.HickLnbotan,O.B.E. • 7No. C/481-22/11. A' The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- 1. The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, at Ziarat. V and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The agency, BAHRAIN, PERSIAN Gulf * Reference to previous correspondence; Bahrain telegram No•139 dated 13th May 1941* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No*0/375 dated 13th May 1941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to Political Agent, Bahrain. at Dibah.^cnficiential British Agency, No•C/375-3/5(g) Sharjah, 13th May 1941• To The Political Agent, Bahrain, Memorandum Reference correspondence resting with my telegram No, 368 of 11th May 1941. 2, I beg to enclose herewith copy (with translation) of a letter dated 14th Habi* ath-Thani 1360 (l,e. 11th May 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, 3, The Wall of Shinas, who was informed by Shaikh Humaid bin 'Abdullah of the 3hahuh ? s action, is reported to have sent a special massage to the Shahuh to cease hostilities and refrain f’om further aggression, 4, Affairs in Diba are reported to be very quiet. Sd, A, Rezzaq, Residency Agent, Sharjah,Translation of letter dated 14th Kabl* ath-Thani 1360 (i.e* 11th &amp;ay 1941) from Shaikli Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba to the Residency Agent, Sharjah^ rt ii tm it it i» it it After Compliments f I write to inform you that the incident which took place at Diba on 6th R&amp;bi f f II, 1360 (i.e. 2nd May 1941) between our subjects and the Shahuh has now bean settled through the mediation of the Sharqiyin of Ghurfsh, V : e released the man imprisoned by us and the Shahuh released our subject who was imprisoned by them. Situation has now been restred to normal# Usual Ending.CONFIDENTIAL 30S-S V'' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in compliments to \ | Q ersian Gulf presents his The Political Agent&gt; Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (s). \ v \ob British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated.... A 5th .¥?.?.. 1 341. Reference to previous correspondence : Muscat telegram No.c/365 doted 9th Moy 1941 Description of Enclosure. J J • 11 # rG.T.C Te legrem Prom Political Agent, Bahrein. To Political Resident, Bushire* Ho #139 Dated 13th received 14th May 1941# Following from Residency Agent Sharjah begins. My memorandum No#C-360 May 7th regarding DIBA situation# Matter settled locally through mediation of neighbouring SHARQIYIN# Prisoners released by both and situation restored to normal. PoliticalThe Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— \ v !• The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, at Ziarat, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Reference to previous correspondence: Bahrain telegram No.119 dated 8th May 1941* Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No*C/360-3/5(g) dated 7th May 1941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah to Situation at Diba.4Nb No.C/360-3/5(g) The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference my telegram No.359 of today's date. 2. I beg to enclose copy (with translation) of a letter dated 9th Kabi’ath-Thani 1360 (i.e. 6th May 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, on the subject of hostilities at Diba. 3. Shaikh Khalid has issued strict instructions to his men at Riba to avoid trouble with the Shahuh and to confine themselves to self defence. He says that according to rumours from Batinah the Muscat Government intend to occupy Khatm Malahah and thus threaten Kalba. That he did ' \ not believe these rumours but is afraid that the delay in settling the dispute with the Muscat Authorities might encourage the Shahuh to create more trouble when hearing such false rumours. He therefore requests that the Muscat Government may kindly be urged to settle matters with him at an early date so that peace and order may be restored in that area. Sd. A. Rezzaq. Residency Agent, Sharjah. V&gt; ITranslation of letter dated the c: &gt;th Rabi* ath-Thani 1360 (i.e. 6th May 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahnad, Regent of Kalba, to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, After Compliments, Last night at 4 o'clock (Arabic) a messenger came to me with a letter from my son (nephew) Shaikh Jlumaid bin ’Abdullah to the effect that on the night, of 6th Rabi* ,11 (i.e,2nd May) at 7 o’clock the Shahuh launched an attack from their town on our town. They took position of defence posts and demolished walls. At daybreak they remained in their positions. After sun rise they imprisoned one of our followers together with his wife. The wife escaped and gavew arning to the town people. By chance our followers met one of the Shahuh and imprisoned him. The Shahuh then opened fire on the town and our followers took position in their defence posts. They are now in a state of war with them (Shahuh). These are the treachery acts of the Shahuh about which I am writing to inform you. Usual Ending.Political A^ent, Muscat,repeated to Political Resident. No.?01. Dated,14th June, 1941. Residency Agent Sharjah reports Khanis bin Junah Adhani was killed by Shihuh in Dibah May 31st member- -g-hin during period truce mentioned by Political Agent Muscat in his despatch C/?81 Ai ir ii ?.?nd -nara 5. Muscat authorities should presumably pay compensation to heir of deceased.Telegram: -From To No. ^ated G. ?. C. ^ajor Hickinbothan, ^iarat. Political Bahrain* Repeated, to The Political Resident, -Bushire. T/70. 15th June, 1941, Your telegram °0l June 14th. u TThat nationality was the deceased, and what were the circumstances of hie death. Until I know the facts of the case T cannot give any opinion regarding the liability of the Muscat authorities for compensa tion but a claim by the Jawasim will almost certainly result in counter claims* VITELEGRAM - G.T.C. - Major Hickinbotham, Ziarat. - Treasury Officer, Muscat, - T/69. - June 15th, 1941. - Political Resident,Bushire and P.A.,Bahrain Confidential . Following for His Highners the Sultan begins f, I have been informed by the Political Agent, Bahrain that one Khamis bin Juma Adhani was killed by the Shihuh at Dibah on May 31st. Through the agency of a breach of truce . I shall be glad if Your Highness will let me know facts of the case and what action has been taken with regard to persons concerned. I urge the despat ch of your representative to Dibah as soon as possible.” Ends. ooOoo-VA CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/411. Muscat, the 16th June, 1941. To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to forward, herewith, a copy of a message I have received from His Majesty^ Consul, Muscat at Ziarat. The portion underlined was received mutilated and I have asked for its repetition, which I will communicate to Your Highness as soon as received. Your Highness’s sincere friend, for His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat. J IP*j***JltJL P.A, jvo, A a Following for Major Kickinbotham H.B.S^s Consul, Muscat at Ziarat begins: Your telegram regarding Diba stop Just received letters from Walls Khasab, Shinas and Shaikh Khalid about/enewed hostilities but do not give adequate information. Am leaving for Sahar on Friday the 20th instant and wil^send a party of/representatives from there. Said,a w G.T.C. Political A^ent, Bahrain. Major Hi :kinbothan, ^iarat. Telegram Pron To No.PlO. Dated, 17th June. 1941. Repeated to Politi:al Resident Your telo^ran T/70 dated 15th June. Sheikh Khalid reports deceased was one of his subjects and was killed during an attack on Dibah by Shihuh on May 31st. 1 IJ CONFIDENTIAL. No. 304-S The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent&gt; Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- mtnt £0- f QT f 8V our of comment on the euggestione in para graph 6 of enclosure* British Consulate-Genera), BUSHIRE. Dated l-Sth tfay .1.9.41. u/ Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. v. - \\ •; Name and Date. Subject. &gt; Muscat letter Ho.c/328 dated 22nd April 1941* » Dibah Situation. y Copy forv«arded ftith complime for information# A copy to tne Political Agent, Bah nts to Political Agent, Muscat, &lt;i&gt;f enclosure should have been sent rain#r CQi^FIDENTIAL. No. C/413. Muscat, the 18th June, 1941, J To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to refer to my letter No. C/411, dated the 16th June, 1941, and to forward, herewith, a correction to the mutilated portion of the message enclosed with my letter referred to above. Your Highness^ sincere friend, for His Britannic Majesty's Consul,Museat. 1 *CQNFIDgOTIAt No. C/414. Muscat, the 19th June, 1941 J To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Onan. Your Highness, I have the honour to refer to ray letter No. C/411, dated the 16th June, 1941, and to forward, herewith, a copy of a message I have received from His Majesty^ Consul, Muscat at Ziarat. Your Highness's sincere friend, / for His Britannic Majesty's Consul,Museat. / I- V s Confidential No•C/447-3/5(G) British Agency, Sharjah, 12th June 1941. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum yv In continuation of my telegram No. 446 of today’s date, the name of the man killed on the Qawasim side during the attack on Diba on 2nd June 1941, is Khamis bin Juma’ah Adhunain. 2. According to a letter received from Shaikh Humaid bin ’Abdullah by his father, the Shahuh collected a large force and resumed their attack on Dibe.-Hisn on 5th June. They were repulsed after suffering four casualties, namely, three killed and one wounded. 3. Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba left for Kalba on 9th June. Sd. A. Hezzaq. Residency Agent. Sharjah. No.C/609-22/11. Political Agency, Bahrain, dated the 16th June 1941, Copy of the above memorandum is forwarded to 1. The Hon’ble Political Resident in the Persian Gu! Bushire 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, Camp, Ziarat, , VI » tConfidential No.C/449-3/5(g) To The Political Agent, Bahrain. V British Agency, Shrajah 13th June 1941. Memorandum In continuation of my memorandum No.C/447-3/5(g) dated the 12th June 1941. 2. I beg to enclose herewith copy (with translation) of a letter dated 17th Jamad al Auwal 1360 (i.e. 13th June 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, on the subject of Diba disturbances. Sd. Abdur Rezzaq Residency Agent, Sharjah. No.C/627-22/11. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th June 1941. and enclosure Copy of the above memorandum/is forwarded, with compliments, to 1. The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, Camp, Ziarat. in continuation of Political Agent, Bahraini telegram No. 210 dated the 17th June 1941.* !* translation of a letter dated 17th Jamad al Auwal 1360 (i#e# 13th June 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Talba to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Residency Agent, After Compliments. I write to inform you that I have arrived at Kalba and found our son Humaid at Kalba. He had sent our servant Barut with reinforcement to Diba. On 14th Jamad ( 10th June ) fighting took place with the Shahuh at which one of the Shahuh was killed in Diba territory. Fighting was also resumed on 15th (11th Ju£s) and hand to hand fighting took place, in one of the date gardens belonging to Diba people, at which the Ihahuh lost eight killed besides the wounded of which we have no information. On our side two had slight injuries. This information was brought to me by our servant Suhail bin Barut who took part in the fighting. Usual Ending. Vi P ri j / ' , V' GOViilKNMENT OF INDIA, % Djbpaktminx, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B. —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGF&gt; sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the upxssr-Mut intended to be treated, on / receipt, with the same expeditions if it hUd been telegraphed. To save time and formalities ft is worded ana\igned as if it had been so despatched,] From To Repeated Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Gamp Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat,^ith copy of Bahrain Express Letter No. C/590, dated 12.6.41. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. C/223 of 1941. Dated 27th June 1941. 19&amp; . \ '• « Subject: Jov/asim - Shihuh disputes. Reference your letter No* C/328 dated the 22nd April 1941 and connected correspondence. 2. Your suggestion that the Sultan should maintain a representative at Dibah (Shihuh) is acceptable. As regards the Jowasim tower, it can be left standing provided it is not again occupied. Please take up the matter with Sultan on these lines. To Bahrain. The suggestion in Paragraph 3 of your Express Letter quoted above is approved. Sd/- C. G. Prior Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, s. 6 . MFP—501 S&amp;P-(M-820)—23-7-30—300,000.CONFIJjUTTIAL SXPKSS3 LSTTEH From The Political Agent Bahrain To The Political Resident Bushire No. 0/590 Dated 12th June 1941 Reference your Printed Letter No. 304-S dated the 15th May 1941. 2. Residency Agent and Shaikh Khalid agree that appointment of Sultan’s representative in Dibah would be beneficial provided he confines himself to controlling Shihuh. I agree and hope this can be arranged early, as whole trouble is due to Shihuh being out of control. 3. As regards the removal of tower I do not see how Khalid can be asked to remove this before Muscat Government s. ow their ability to control the Shihuh (Residency Agent reports th-t on the 31st May Shihuh killed another inhabitant of )ibah). When they have shown that they can do so then he can be asked to remove the tower which, in any case, v.ould have lott its importance. 4. as regards his entering into control of t^ree villages, this was very ill advised and Khalid might be informed that any retaliation by the Shihuh / in thatCONFIDENTIAL. f; i'^') No. C/288 of 1941. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, ^ British Consulate-General, Camp Bahrain, Dated..LLth..J.uly..i3Ai,.. Bahrain Printed Tetter Bo. 0/731-2^/11, dated 9th July, I94i to Political Resident, together \vith enclosures. BIBA SITUATICFgonfid e n tial No. 3/731-22/11. The Political Agent, Bahrain presents his compliments to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, with the remark that it has already been suggested to Shaikh Khalid that he might settle the dispute over Wadi Madha in direct communication with the Sultan of Muscat. P.u.c. was v/ritten before receipt of Political Agent, Bahrain* letter. Political Agent is, hov/ever, sending a message to the Residency Agent, reference p.u.c., asking him to advise Shaikh Khalid to meet the Muscat representative and try for an amicable settlement of his differences with the Shihuh. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 9th July 1941 Reference to previous corre ..pondence Description of Enclosure Name and Date Subj ect Memorandum No. ^/476 dated the 2nd July 1941 from the Resi dency Agent, Sharjah to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with enclosures.^ Diba Situation. ■i _ —Confidential No.C/476-3/5(g). British Agency, Sharjah. 2nd July 1941. To The Political Agent, Bahrain Vemorandum I beg to enclose © copy (with translation) of a letter dated 1st Jaxnad ath-Thani 1360 (i.e. 27th June 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahjnad, Regent of Kalba, on the subject of Diba. Sd. Abdur Rezzaq. Residency Agent, Sharjah. * V' Jr iX Translation of letter dated 1st Jamad ath-Thani 1360 (27.6.41) from Shaikh Khalid hin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, to the Residency Agent, Sharjah# hN % After Compliments: I write to inform you that I have received a letter from Saiyid Sa’id bin Taimur dated 29th Jamad al Auwal 1360 (25#6.41) per hand of Shaikh Ghusn bin Selim al Ma f mari, copy of which is wnclosed. He deputed Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim to act as his authorized representative in the affairs of Diba and invited me to be present at Diba. In his letter, Saiyid Sa 1 id bin Taimur said 'The existence of the tower and of the Wadi remaining in your possession are undesirable' from which words I draw a conclusion that he is taking the side of and neiping the Shihuh and therefore feel suspicious about his intentions. The tower is in our country. Is it not therefore strange that we should be told not to do what we want in our country ! The Wadi formerly belonged to the Oawasim and its inhabitants came to us of their own accord and choice being tired oj the Shihuh they are free people and not slaves. I reouest you to communicate the above to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf with the hope that the advice of the Honourable the Political Resident to the Muscat Government would lead to the good of both of us. Usual Endings• i » ******************* *********************** ********************** Trorslatio- of letter dated 29th Jamad al Auwal 1360 (25.6.41) from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman to Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba. After Compliments : This is to iilform you that I have received your letter in which you mentioned the incident which took place between /the- 2 - the people of Diba and Shihuh. For this reason I am sending my brother Ahmad bin Ibrahim to that area in order to enquire in all the matters that had taken place and have authorized him to do what is good. I, therefore, request you or Mumaid to meet him at Diba and to come to agreement v/ith him in a manner which would improve things and establish good under standing. I also hope that my brother would be able to appoint during his stay, another Shaikh for the Shihuh. I have written this letter to you in a brief manner but wish to repeat for your knowledge that the e xistence of the tower and of Wadi Madha remaining in your possession are undesirable for they would not lead to satisfactory results and good neighbourhood between you and the Shihuh. However, my brother Ahmad bin Ibrahim is coming to you and is in possession of all facts. I am sending this letter to you per hand of Shaikh Ghusn bin Salim al Ma'mari while my brother Ahmad bin Ibrahim would be leaving, if God is willing, after two days. Usual Undings.A? m CONFIDENTIAL Xo. C / 446 / The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his fornpliments to (1) The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire, (2) .The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit tothfcm the undermentioned document(/), Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. d 8th August ^ ^ 4.1 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Copy of a letter dated 11th Jamad ek Akher from Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Regent of Kalba, to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Dibah Affair.Copy in translation of a letter dated the 11th Jamad el Akher 1360 from Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad f Regent of Kalba, to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. I received your letter and noted the contents. I have also seen Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim to whom I sent my son Humaid to meet at Dibah. Negotiations took place and the matter was settled satisfactorily. We pray to God that he may settle affairs of Muslims. Facts will be told to you verbally by Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim. I shall be glad if I can be of any service to you. My son Humaid sends his salama to you. N.B. I am quite agreeable to what Sheikh Ghausn bin Salim has taken responsibility for.Letter dated the 11th Jamad el ittracl 1360 from Khalid bin Ahmed Al-qasmi, to H#H.the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman* After compliments, I received your letter and noted the contents* I have also seen Saiyid Ahmed bin Ibrahim to whom I sent my son Humaid to meet at Deba. Negotiations took place and the matter was settled satisfactorily. We pray to God that he may settle affairs of Muslims. Facts will be told to you verbally by Saiyid Ahmed bin Ibrahim* I shall be glad if I can be of any service to you* My son Humaid bin Abdulla sends his salaams to you. N.B. I am quite agreeable to what Shaikh Ghisin bin Salim has taken responsibility for. U.E. | / 4* • t Am &lt;•&lt;&lt; r \toy TRIBAL AFFAIRS * 160. Dibah. Reference paragrapb No. 131 of Muscat* Intelligence Surnmary No. 10 of 1941. A meeting occurred between Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, Minister for Internal Affairs, and Sheikh Humaid bin Abdullah of Kalba at Dibah. With the consent of the Jawasim the Sultan’s men occupied the Shihuh fort and the Jawasim tower which has been the cause of so much trouble before the conversation took place. The whole question seems to have been amicably settled on the following lines (a) . Sheikh Hassan bin Rahmah of the Shihuh has been deposed and the tribe have been called upon to choose a successor. Hassan bin Rahmah has been brought to Muscat and is being detained here a under surveillanc e. (b) . The Shihuh and the Jawasim have agreed in writing to cancel any feud which might exist after the recent disturbances. (c) . The Jawasim have agreed to evacuate the Wadi Mad-hah and Sheikh Humaid bin Abdullah is to come to Muscat to discuss the final terms in one month’s time. (d) . Pending the selection of a new Sheikh the Shihuh fort is being held by soldiers of the Wali of Khassab. Should the Shihuh fail to agree on a Sheikh then the Sultan will probably appoint a representative but he would prefer not to have to adopt this alternative as it will raise such questions as the provision of a garrison and the collection of Zakat. (e) . The Jawasin tower remains in the hands of the Sultan’s men under Sheikh Ghausn bin Salim al Awamir and by agreement with the Jawasim the Sultan can,if he so desires, destroy it. He will probably not take any action until Sheikh Humaid bin Abdullah has paid his expected visit. /The Sultan The Sultan told me that owing to the truce which was made by Ali bin Mudhaffar, Wali of Shinas, being signed by a number of the Shihuh Sheikhs he found it impossible to fix the blame for the breach of the truce on any particular man.Confidential No.C/9 77-22/11. D ^ j Jlo^ ., 11 ^ i..U : u WSM ' •. Tha Political Agent, tiatiraia, Preseats his corapliments to j-* !• The Handle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. and has the hinoar to seni him a copy of the undermentioned document ( 8 ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Z^l fo Datedl4tb October 1941, Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject Memorandum No.C/664 dated 26th September 1941 from Diba Situation. the Residency Agent, Sharjah. — '/Jr- • ‘/-mp k / I11 &gt; * ' |o6) ML ConfidMltlal No •C/664-3/5 (O) . British Ag«ncy f Bh«rjah f 26tl* September 1941. To The Political Agent f Bahrain. KUttOMflBtt Heferenoe correepoiKlence resting with your memorandum Ko. C/782 dated the 22nd July 1941. 2. shaikh Khalid, Regent of Ralbe 9 left for I'd neat on 16th August ami returned to Kalba on 2nd September. He arrived at AJman on 22nd and cam* to Sharjah on 23rd. 1 hen he came to Sharjah he called on me and informed mo that he spent 11 days in Ivfescat during which he had two interviews with the Sultan 9 namely # on the second day of his arrival and on the day before hia departure. jJiscusslona were conducted through Salyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim but without any raeulta. According to Shaikh Rhalid f Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim asked Shaikh Khollti f on his arrival 9 to tell the Sultan when he meets him that he authorises him to do what he considered best about the tower at Dlba and Wadi Uudhu 9 as by doing so the Bultan would be pleased.:and when Shaikh Xhalid asks anything book the Sultan would comply with his request. Shaikh Khalid refused to do this on the ground that if he did this and the Sultan refused to meet Shaikh Khalifa demands, then he could not go back against his word or make any demand. Shaikh Khalid states that Saiyid Ahmad appears to have made the Sultan believe that Shaikh Khalid would set in accordance with his wishes and for that reason he tried to induce him to tell the Sul won that he would leave matters for him to decide. The .... . . ..- — ■ lou 7 \M 7 - 2 - Th# Vu3cat ^utihorltte* nt!«d “ttie removal of tho tower end the return of ifedhs to the Shahoh* shaikh Khelid did not a^ree to remove the tover before the aultan appointed a | Proper ; «ii and took responeioility for the Shahuh. The Sultan said to bhalkh hhalid that he haa already appointed a x representative at B«i , ah by name Mubarak a relative of the Veil of Khrsab end i« appointing Shaikh Muhammad bin Ahmad of Bakha who is himself a '*hahhi and would undoubtedly take the aide of the Shahuh. The Sultan would not change his decision on this point* As regards Vadhl Wadha. The .Sultan linaiatad on its return to the Shahuh whereas Shaikh Ihalid contests the Shahuh * s claim to it and asked that the matter may be decided in accordance with the Sharo 1 , tribal law or documentary evidence but the Sultan would not listen to any argument on this point* As no results were achieved during the long discu«slon« f both parties agreed to postpone the matter until after 7amadhan when both hope to settle the matter amicably* parties have thus extended the truce for another two months* J .v lNo. /jy / -14/247. C ONFIDENTIAL To The Political Agent, Muscat. Memo random. British Consulate General, Bushire. Dated the/S^t December 1941. PCLTuAL ACE ' :• .flLENTi-'L REuO^D Date. R ’ '. o: -J H. S-'il’ii our&lt;uijL a i l f. - g ^ Reference paragrapITTT rTfinteT'TT^ter No.C/977- -^2/11 dated the 14th October 1941 from the Political Agent, Bahrain on the subject of the Diba situation. 2. Please furnish a further report. By order, j* Secretary to the r Qlitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain with reference to his printed letter referred to above.. !°k | Copy of a telegram from Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, Minister for Internal Affairs, Muscat, to His Highness the Sultan, Dhofar, Hamdan installed as Sheikh. Murakaa demolished^ Wadi restored to its people. Fresh guarantees concluded. » r i ' r11 j*“'L &lt;0^ CONFIUENTIAL. No. C/24. Political Agency, Muscat. January 8th, 1942. To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BU 3 H I R E. \V\/ _yLs 'Nik Memorandum, Your confidential memorandum No. 1377-1V247, dated the 18th December, 1941. Dibah affair. 2. I met Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim near Saham on his way back from Dibah yesterday. He told me he had obtained the following settlement *- The Jawasim fort has been demolished M to the level of a godown'. No Wall will be appointed by Muscat, but the place will continue to be under the Wali of Khassab. Hamdan bin Ahmad, nephew of the previous appointment, has been made Sheikh. The Wadi Midha has been left to the Beni * Sa 1 id, who acknowledge the Sultan^ supremacy. The Zakat of the Wadi, Saiyid Ahmad said, was negligible; and he had not concerned himself with it. 3» His statement has been confirmed by a telegram to the Sultan at Dhofar, seen in censorship by the Treasury Officer during my absence. 4. A settlement so satisfactory to Muscat leaves me wondering at what financial expenditure it was obtained.CONFIDENTIAL. '^TT '•no / I s&gt; K-. C/ 25 The Political Agent and His Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned document(s). ?, M V. * ^ it' ‘ (El Jk ; Vi t l o- Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. \MS D a t 8th January ^ 42 Reference to previ«ftcj&gt;yEespondence: 0/977^2^ Bahrain Printed Letter No. C/97'?-22/i*«^datea the 14th October, 1941, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Copy of memorandum No. C/24, dated the 8th January, 1942, from the Political Agent, Museat,to the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dibah Situation. itINDIA, ..Department, ; EXPRESS LETTER Confidential IN. B. — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sare telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed To sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] •1 From FuliticaX Ag**nt f Bahrain* To Politic iil Resident, Rush ire Repeated Political Agent, LiuscetJ^/ No &gt; c/*s Dated 10th t r c Hilary 194&lt;#$3 • Please refer to Printed Better No* C/977 dated the 14th October 194i. A copy of a confidential letter No* 0/896 doted the 29th December 1941 fro/a the eaidency Agent f Sharjah, is forwarded herewith. 2. According to yo^ir Letter No* C/223 dated the 27th June 1941 to the Political Agent, Muscat, copy to me, the Sultan had to appoint a representative at Ribah (TJhihuh) and the 'aw a sin tower could be left standing, orovided it vas not again occupied. 3. It now appears that the Rultan*s representative is to be one Hnmdan bin Mohafnniad, a -hihi, who is to be both 'haikh and Vali (Sultan 1 s representative) at Bel* ah (Dibah - Shihuh) • 7he whole idea of the Sultan appointing a representative atpai’ah was to have an impartial official on the spot who would prevent a recurrence of the incessant fighting between the awasim and , K Shihuh ' MFF— 400S&amp; I*—(M-480)—26-7-84—2,00,000.- 2 - v Shihuh and for the Suita it a Hhihi therefore is contrary to the intentlo J in paragraph 2 of your Express T.etter TTo. C/2^3. I suggest that the p olitical Agent, Muscat, might take up this matter aga:Ln and request that a representative other then a Shihl he appointed* 4* As regards the tower, it aopears that heid 'hmad bin rbrahim, representative of the Muscat ^tnte, h^s demanded that it be deinoiishea. It the tower had besn left un occupied then he h/&gt;c) no grounds for making such a request. t do not myself, ho 1 ever, believe th t the tower has been left unoccupied pnd a certain amount cf justification for its occupation exists owing to the unsatisfactory way in which the huae^t q t;- ts » treating the ^hihuh question. I suggest therefore thr-t the State be asked tc drop the question of demolition of the ourabbe and that Jheikh hhalid be instructed to see that the lower remains unoccupied* 5. The Political Agent, Muscat, might also enquire regarding the allegation th*t parties of armed men ere being sent by the Wu«cet 'tete from the Batineh to ^ai'ah, presumably with the intention of assaulting the ewasim. If there is any truth in the report, as there possibly is, the State might be required to atop doing this and withdraw the men e'lresv' u ' 6. s regards tho&gt;£di Wadha, please cee my Express Letter No. C/690^aated the 12th Tune, n«rn&gt;Araph 4. :'haikh ^adi Madha was very unwise and that we are not going to help him if any trouble results therefrom; but, as regards the Residency Agent’s report, that shaikh Humaid bin Abdullah, Shaikh fChalid’s nephew, is trying to instigate the Beni ^stab, etc., against the Muscat authorities, in snticipation of your sanction I am instructing the Politicala - 3 - Officer, Trucial to send for .'hoikh Khalid and to warn him severely against any such action either on his part or on the part of his naohew and others. 7. I think Shaikh Khalid is acting in an unsatisfactory way* Fe is officially the Regent of Kolba but lie spends practically all his time in the vicinity of Sharjah instead of attending to hie business «w Kalb©. 'haikh Khalid used to be the Shaikh of Sharjah until he was turned out by the present Shaikh and the only interpretation which can bo placed on hie constant residence in the vicinity of Sharjah is th«t be is up to some intrigue agrinst tee present shaikh: in this connection vide correapondenee ending with my ner*or &gt;ndiim &gt;To. C/1145 i *tcd the 8tb b^cenhar 1941* ^Tie whole district of dhawfclyiah comprising Kplba, Tujairsh J 1 hor Fakkan, etc*, on the east coast of Jusandun is practically entirely cut off from the wast coast, as X found on my recent visit there, and there is no valid reason why Phaikh Khalid should constantly absent himself.f |/2* Copy of memorandum Tvo. C/896 dated the 29th December 1941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference correaoondence ending with my memorandum No. C/664-3/5 (G) dated the 26th September 1941. 2. I beg to enclose herewith copy (with translation) of a letter dated 4th Hhul Hijjah 136C (i.e. 24th December 1941) which 1 have received from Shaikh Khalid, Regent of Kalba, on the subject of the 3hahuh/ r 'av;a3im dispute. As the letter was ambiguous, I saw Shaikh, who was suffering from malaria in nubai, and asked him to explain to me his real intention. Re said th«t 'uhammad bin Ahmad of Bakha did not agree to become Shaikh of the 'hahuh, that 3aiyid Ahmad bln Ibrahim, 'eoresentetive of the Muscat Govern ment, intends to apooint Ramden bin Muhammad of the &gt;hahuh as Shaikh and w ali at Bai^.h, that the Representative demanded the demolishing of the Murabba’ah and return of wadi Madha without hearing any argument in&amp; that the Muscat authorities are send armed man from Betinah in 20 and 30 every day *nd concentrating them at Bai’ah. Ghaikh Khalid said' that as Hamdan bin Muhammad was Shahhi himself, his appointment would lead to more comolications instead of putting an end to the trouble no. existing end therefore the action of the Muscat Government is contrary to the agreement concluded in July. That he would not demolish the Vurabbah before the Muscat Government comply with the terms of the agreement, namely, appoint another all not from the Ghahhuh and v«aive their claim against V,adi Mudhafor which they have no right to claim. Having heard that Shaikh Humeid bin Abdullah, who is now conducting negotiations with the Muscat Representative, waa tr ing to incite and instigate the Bani la tab, Khavotii' and Hu 1 aim tribes against the Muscat authorities, I .dvised Shaikh Khalid to try ami settle matters by peaceful mssns and refrain from doing any act which might provoke trouble. Shaikh Khalid left for Dhaid on 26th and I have not heard from him since. Translation of letter dated 4th Dhul Hiftjah 1360 (i.e. 24th December 1941) from Shaikh Khalid bin Ahmad, Repent of Kalba, to the Residency Agent, Rhnrjah. I write to inform you that Belyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim Representative of the Muscat Government, arrived at Diba in connection with the previous matters oetween us and the Shahuh. The attitude of the said person (Saiyid Ahmad) is one of injustice and aggression. He is also supporting and taking the side of the Shahhuh• His way of dealing is against justice and equity. Therefore, I request you to communicate to the Fon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf our complaint. It is the High British Government whose help is sought in order to preveht injus tice and help the oppressed. &amp;11 tnese parts are indebted to them for their help and good treatment. 1 therefore hope and recuest the Hon : ble the Politics L Resident in the Persian Gulf to give our case his careful consideration lest matters might lead to complications and trouble which we wish to avoid.Tele grain - OTC From - Britconeul7 To - Political, Muscat No. - V53 Dated the 22nd January 1942 Addressed Muscat repeated Bahrain. Reference Bahrain Express Letter No.c/48 January 10th. Tf you see no objection please take action on lines suggested in paragraph 3 to paragraph 5. 3. T will ask Bahrain to instruct Shaikh Khalid ag suggested laet sentence of paragraph 4 on hearing from you that Muscat State is taking action to keep Shihuh in order.TELEGRAM. - G.T.C. - Political Agent, Muscat. - Political Resident, Bushire - C/100. - January 26th, 19a2. Your telegram No. A/53 dated January 22nd. 2. In view of memorandum No. C/24 dated January 8th from Political Agent, Muscat to you no further action appears necessary at present.Translation of letter No.1 dated from oaiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, to I&amp;yor a.G. Alban, His Bn After CoiLjjiiments. I have received a iett harram 1261 (3-2-42) r Internal Affairs, s Consul, Muscat. Minister for External Affairs, Saiyid Ehahab bin Enisal, under No. 24 doted 14 th d (rtTK-t Moharram (1-2-42) enquiring^he rumour conveyed to you in resyect of the Qa.vasim ajsd. forwarding to me a co^y of your letter to him No.C/iuV of 27th January 1^42 to which I sent the necessary re^y. four enquiry on the subject caincided with the arrival oi Ahmad bin A-ti Af ohaixh A1 ohinhi accompanied by some leading members of the ohihuh tribe detailed on behalf of their onaixh, Hamdan bin Alimad, bringing 2 letters which I sena them to you and to in form you further that according to the agreement concluded recently by me between the Shihuh and Q,awasim, the latter admitted in general that they would leave V7adi J^adha and give its inhabitants their liberty to carry on under the oreer of His Highness the oultan as before. Thereupon the ^eo^le oi Yadi Iladha toox charge of their wadi and left some of their men as Asxaris there. rlease now see what the fawasim 'wrote, their undoing with the agreement and their enorts to cause trouble. I ho^e you will consider this matter and mere is no doubt tnat you will try for all which may bring haziness in the matter and su^ress what niay lead to disagreement. Usual Ending. Translation of a note dated 17th Dhil Hijjah 1260 i roi. Ahand bin Ahumd, to Aoaid bin iluhaminad. ^ to inforc you that you nave involved yourself in all Government worn and you shomd refrain from doing so. .7h a t you did before was of your own accord. fou should not .tee,, Astaris in the fort and you should withdraw them. Day afjier tomorrow our servants and astarts will come and you should not interfere2 Translation of a note dated 17th Dhil Hijjah 1360 (0-1-42) I ro/ii all iiien oi tne wadi to uhaj. Kh Hamdan oxn Ahir^ad and all tne ohiruh men. ;/e nave to inform you tnat we have received a letter from Shaikh iChalid bin Ahmad asking us to withdraw the assarts whom we :ce^t in the iort at once and he will send his own as^aris as mentioned in tne letter sent herewith. //e are jjoor jjeo^le and have no strength. If you have anything in view please do the needful as early as possible. This is for your information.TELEGRAM. Telegram From To Repeated to No. - G.T.C. - Political Agent) Muscajr. - Political Resident) Bushire. - Political Agent) Bahrain Political Officer Trucial Coast, Sharjah. - C/162. Dated - February 7th, 1942. Paragraph 6 Bahrain Express Letter No. C/48 January 10th and ray No. C/24 January 8th. Dibah affairs Understand Khalid bin Ahmad is again aggressive in Wadi Ma&amp;ha. Grateful if he is warned to abide by . 151 - agreement recently arrived at.i' 1 ^ 11 MWfflUW . || / / /-s Telegram From To No. Dated G. T. C. His Majesty’s Consul General, Bushir* The Political Agent, Bahrain, A/95. 3rd February 1942. A i^o Paragraph 3 of telegram A/52, January 22nd. No action is necessary as Jowasim fort has been more or less demolished. BRITCONSUL. /SHis Majesty*s Consul General, Bushire. The Political Agent, Bahrain, via Muscat. A/107. 9th February 1942. v ^” Reference Muscat telegram No.C/l62, February 7th. Dibba Affair. Please act accordingly.(w Telegram From To Copy givenoto - Political Agent, Bahrain. No. - T/136. Dated - March 18th, 1942. Date received - March 19th, 1942. V-^ Your telegram No. C/162 February 7th. 2. Khalid denies aggression on Y/adi Madha and states he has not yet received Rs. 600/- promised by Muscat party in compensation demolition tower. 3. Please make enquiries regarding this payment.n '*N TELEGRAM, Telegram From To No. Dated - G.T.C. - Political Agent, Muscat. - PoliticalResident, Bahrain. - March 23rd, 1942. ■ V Your telegram No. T/136 March 18th. 2. State deny any promise by their representative to compensate Sheikh Khalid for demolition of tower. 3. Copies of Sheikh Khalid’s letter threatening aggression being forwarded by post.CONFIDENTIAL EXPRESS LETTER 10 l7 F From - Political Agent, Muscat. To - Political Resident, Bahrain. No. C/293. Muscat, the 23rd March, |om' The Sultan's Reference my telegram No. C/292 dated March 23rd. I forward herewith copies of the marginally noted correspond ence 1. Copy of letter dated the 17th Dhil 2. Hijjah (5th January, 1942), from Sheikh Khalid bin Ahmad to Sheikh Abaid bin Mohammed. 2. Copy of a note dated the 17th Dhil Hijjah (5th January, 1942), fr m Sheikh Hamdan bin Ahmad of the Shihuh. Representative here has advised me that Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim - who was sent on behalf of the Sultan to settle this matter - is not dependable. All the parties concerned appear to be involved in intrigue to defraud State and unless some British interest is involved the matter might be left pending for the time being. 3. i agree with this view and suggest no further action at present. L Major Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/177. The Hon’ble the Poll compliments to v'V I esident in the Persian Gulf presents his The Political Agent, Bahrein. The Political Agent, Muscat, V and has the honour to transmit to h,ijn--a'-tJOpy'^of the undermentioned document(s). ^ ' I’ll ; i . ■» A Office of the Political Resident in th Persian Gulf, Camp BAEoEIN. Dated 18th. March 194E . e c r h ■ :4s&gt;, Reference to previous correspondence: ^ ft «U ^ To Bah:eln - Bahrein Letter No / '’l dc ted 15th Karch 1 I ^ JK t ' - u ” u x To Muscat - Political ^e5:ident»s tele gram No. T/lX€rfaaied 16/6/1 ±k 9 Description of Enclosure. . C/o^l, Name and Date. Subject. To Bahrein, Telegram No. T/l£6r dated 18/^/«4Jd, from Political Resident to Political Agent, Muse* tj. To Muscat - Letter No. C/3^1, dated 15/3/«4:., from Political Agent, Bahrein, to Political Resident. \,rn Khalidts alleged agression on aai Madha.CONFIDENTS,. No .C/321. © il . ^ The Agency, Bahrain, the 15th March 1942 To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain* Memorandum* Reference your telegram No*107 dated 10th February 1942* 2. The Political Officer Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent htm visited Kalba on the 7th March and interviewed Shaikh Khalid (Regent of Kalba), Shaikh Abdullah (the Regent •s brother) and Shaikh Hhmaid (the Regent's nephew)* Pelly informed Shaikh Khalid that the Political Resident had received a report that he, Shaikh Khalid, was being aggressive in the Wadi Madha and had directed that he should be warned to abide by the agreement recently arrived at. Shaikh Khalid replied that (1) in December 1941 he agreed with the Muscat party to demolish to a certain level the tower which has featured in the case (2) that he had fulfilled wholly his side of the agreement and the Muscat party admitted that he had done so (3) that the Muscat party had agreed to pay him Hs 600/- In compensation for his demolition of the tower but, so far, they had failed to make this payment, and (4) that since the agreement he had not aggressed in any way in the adi Madha nor. / / 'tit \ - 2 - had there been In his relations with the Muscat party, anything which even savoured of hostility. 3* Shaikh Khalid produced documents which corroborated his statement and the Political Officer Irucial Coast therefore refrained from administering any further warning. Sd. E.B .Wakefield. Political Agent, Bahrain.Office of the Political Resident No»C/460» in the Persian Gulf, L*T. »Nearchust March 1G4£« 8» When I was at Sharjah the Residency Agent informed me the t Shaikh Khalid stated that he had been told in writing to apply to the wall of Khassab If he had any trouble with the Shihuh* According to Shaikh Khalid the W&amp;li had Informed him that he had nothing to do with the matter and had told him to apply to Ahmad bin Ibrahim if necessity arose. I spoke to the Wall of Khassab when I saw him on the 23rd April. He completely denied the story and said that if Shaikh Khalid complained to him regarding the behaviour of the Shihuh he would certainly go into the matter. 4. I agree that we should not interfere in these petty intrigues at present. The situation should however be care~ fully watched by all concerned so that early action can be taken should a dispute of a serious nature seem to be impending Sd. W.R. Hay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. /C-f- for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.(J jJ ' &lt;SJJI ■1 ^ ^ i) ^ OJI u l-»ais jj ^ Li-. J ^ ^ i*Ls ^jup i . U&gt;- I i L 5' o? ' J-^ j ^ ^ ^ 5 ^ ■■* ‘l” ^— ■*■' cj?— ^ ^ ; ^ ^ f'**' ^ ^ i Translation of letter Uo.353/1 dated the 1st September, 1943, from the Minister for External Affairs, Muscat to His Britannic Majesty f s Consul, Muscat. After compliments, I enclose herewith a copy of A* letter from the Minister for Internal Affairs, Muscat and shall he grateful if enquiries are made and steps are talcen to make the Jawasims abide by the terms made by the Minister for Internal Affairs when he went to their place to settle the dispute. The result of your enquiries may kindly be intimated to me as soon as possible• U.E(\&lt;rO) . *. Translation of letter Fo.1036/3 dated the 8th Rajah, 1362 from the Minister for Itemal Affairs, Muscat, to the Minister for External Affairs, Muscat. After compliments. On the 17th Jamad el Thani I received the foilwing complaint from Shaikh Hamdan hin Ahmed Al-Shuhi and his trihe f s men against their neighbours the Jawasim:- (1) Rebuilding of the tower which they formerly agreed to its dismantling and that it should not be built higher than it was after dismantling. (2) Construction of various buildings in contrary to the stipulations which prevent the construction of building of mud and stones. (3) The Jawasim show reluctance in recovering debts due from the Jawasim to Shihus. (4) The Jawasim arrest, without the knowledge of the -hihus any person of them known to have committed a crime. I, after hearing these arguements from them decided to send two representatives to make enquiries in the matter and to keep namdan in Muscat till they return. Accordingly Shuwain bin Amir Alhousani and Rrshid bin Salim Alnamari who were in the company of the Minister for Internal Affairs when the agreement between these two tribes was made proceeded there. I enclose for your information a copy of their report. Ahmed bin Hasan one of the Jawasim 1 s leading men was present when the two representati ves sent by me saw that the wall of the tower was made higher, the construction of the new surrounding wall* and the building of two new stores, he said to Shaikh Humaid that all these construct-, ion were new. As regards item 3 and 4. These are to be decided according to law. The building of the tower and the other new constructions are however considered to be an offense from the Jawasim and a breach of the terms to which both the tribes had agreed. Each tribe possesses a copy of this agreement. It is there-fore requested that you/please write A- to the Consul on the subject, so that the Jawasim should keep on their boundaries and remove the stores and new buildings they have made. Both tribes should adopt a way that would ensure safety and peace between them and should try their utmost to avoid sucn moves whicn might lead to a^fereat trouble in the long run.J (y?) IP Copy of the report submitted hy representatives Shuwain 'bin Amir Alhousani and Rashid 'bin Salim Almanari on the offense carried out hy the Jawasim against the Shihus in Deha. These two representatives have reported the matter to Shailch Husraaid hut with no result. 1. Rebuilding of the tower and the construction of a surrounding wall. 2. Construction of two new stores. 3. Debts . , Humaid states that there is^a certain time for collecting debts and that he wilirresponsible for all that£d-iie from his men, provided his men receive their debts also. 4. Arrest of convicts . Humaid states that they find tnemselves bound to do that in order to bring the convict to Ram&amp;an to see him and got aserei*i i * 3 i!red. Shuwain bin Amir Alhousani. IVIII-F/1 TelegraTi From To No.C/1144 Dated the 8th September 1943. A.P.A., Muscat. Mr. Pelly, Sind Club, Karachi. TOWBR AT DIBBA. ' 1. Saiyid Shihab has forwarded complaint from Sheikh Hamdan of Al Shuhi complaining that Sheikh Khalid of Kalba and Jawasimi have rebuilt the tower ana erected other buildings contrary to agreement. 2. Point at issue seams to be whether Muscat State promised to pay lb.600/- compensation for demolition in December 1941 as Sheikh Khalid maintains.they did. I think you saw the documents in Kalba in March last year. 3. I have as yet not reported this to Political Resiaent or Bahrain and Saiyid Shihab having asked for an urgent reply now announces his intention of leaving tomorrow for Batinah presumably with no other intention than to avoid Ramdhan fast. - Bird -No.C/1244. Political Agency, Muscat. Dated the 28th September 1943 To Copy to The Hon'Die the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . The Political Agent, Bahrain . MEMORANDUM Reference correspondence resting with your memorandum No.C/460, dated the 24th April 1942. s 181 2. I am forwarding Letter No.353/1, dated 1-9-43, \ from the Minister for External ft herewith copies of the Affairs, Muscat, to H.B.M.*s Consul, Muscat, with enclosures.{ marginally noted correspondence. 3. If you agree, I propose discussing this matter with the Sultan on his return to Muscat and in the meanwhile shall take no other action. Political Agent, Muscat.VIII-F/1 Tele^-arn From To Repeated G.T.C. Political, Baiirain. Political Resident, Bashix-.e. Political Agent, ...ascat. No.1321 Dated 15th, receive l 17th December IDaB Reference yoar endorsement No.d/12September 28th DI3AH DI3PJTE. 2. Political Officer Tracial Coast will be visiting Kalba on December 20th and Dibah December 21st. I suggest rlus cat Government depute a representative to meet him at bib ah and point out objectionaele construction.i I No,1827. His Britannic i.lajesty's Consulate ? Muscat, the 17th December 19^3. r T‘c ^ &gt; Sai/ii Shahab bin Faisal, Minister for External .C'fairs, rlu^cat State. Af ter co mp1iments, -I have^Che honour to refer to your letter No.353/1 dated the 1st September 19a;3 on the disoute between the Shihuli and Qawasim and to inform vou that the Political Officer Trucial Coast is visiting Kalbaon the 21st December. It is Suggested there- 1 ore that you kindly depute a representative to meet him at Dibah and point out the objectionable constructions. i 2. a. very early reply is requested. Usual ending. So. R.D.Metcalfe. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.■■■■■ mmmM Translation of letter i^o.441/5 dated the 18th December, 1943, from the M.E.A. » kuscat, to Consul, kuscat. After compliments, i thanic you for your letter ho. 1827 dated the the 17th December, 1943. 2* In Bayah there is a Bhaiich named Ham dan bin Ahmed and I suggest that the Political Officer Trucial Coast who is visiting Deba on the 21 st December, may enquire from the said Shaikh about the disputed constructior which was made against the terms between the two parties. Shaikh Hamdan will be sufficient to inform the r.O. T.C. what the latter wishes to icnow about the construction. U.E.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER N. B .—This is an ORTODJAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and nndue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it, had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No 1888-14/247 Dated Dushlro POLIiTGJKL, MERAJH Repeated: y POLITICAL| MUSCAT* the 15th NovemLerui 3. d* ?7 M b, Reference Muscat Memorandum No*C/l244 of 28th Septemher 1943 regarding the Jawasim Shaikhs* 2* Please ask Political Officer Crucial Coast to enquire into the allegations hy the Muscat State* Rritconsul* Attested* Secretary tp the Polit: in the Persian Gulf. 6 . MFP—179 S&amp; P—6708—fM *64^—11-7-42— 800,U0o. ResidentI No. C/164. Political Agency, Bahrain, 20th January, 1944. The Political Agent, Bahrain, pre sents his compliments to:- The political Agent, Muscat and has the honour to transmit to him a copy ol the under mentioned document(s). o \&lt;0 _ Reference to previou^^er re3 P ondence: Bushire Express Letter No.188B~14/247 dated 15th Nov. 1943. No. and date of Enclosure : Subject Letter No.C/117 dated 15-1-44 from Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Hon 1 hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gull* Bushire. /. /nyi' Codv to the Hon’ hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ~ v* rv ^ XAL No.C/117. Political Agenc/i Bahrain, loth January, 1944. From , * To Major T. Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.xi., Political Agent, Bahrain. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, A Dlba PlsDUte I hr&amp;ve the honour to refer to your Express Letter No. 1888-14/247 dated the 15th November 1945 and to enclose a report which I have received from the Political Officer on the Trucial Coast. 2 . The Shihu are a restless people and the Jawassim very rightly suffer from an inferiority complex. There will never be peace between the middle third and the upper third of the village of i)iba until the Sultan of Muscat appoints a Wali to control the Shihu lands and that part of diba whi h lies within his frontiers. Khassab is far too remote from Diba for it to be practica ble for the Wali of Khassab to direct the affairs of diba&gt;though it might be possible for the Wall of Khassab to reside at Diba leaving a Naib at Khassab to look after the wants of tho Royal Navy. This solution would possibly prove acceptabla to the Sultan of Muscat as it would be the most economical arrangement, and I believe that the Sultan*s principal objection to the creation of a new Waliat is that the salary will have to be found for the Wali*and the Shihu would be unlikely to offer to contribute. 3. Arbitration has been tried in the past without success, the settlement of these disputes by mutual agreements has also been tried and the agreements haye never been kept; a firm and heavy hand is what is required to keep these people in order . / ICOPY British Agency, Sharjah +.h** #T*nnflr»xr 1 Q4.A . Dated the 4th January 1944. From To No. The Political Officer, Trucial Coaat, Sharjah. The Political Agent, Bahrain. C/17-3/5(G) Subject : Diba Dispute Sir, -f I*' I have the hono^ir to refer to your endoraement No.C/1638 dated the 29th November 1943. It aaweara from the penultimate oara of letter No.1036/3 dated the 8th Rajab 1362 from the Minister for Internal Affaira, Muscat, to the Miniater for External Affair*, Muscat that the question which the Muscat Government wish to have taken uw with the Qawasim is that of the tov/er and other buildings only and not that of collection of debts or arrest of wrong-doers. The agreement referred to by the Minister for External Affairs in his covering letter (No.353/1 dated the 1st September 1943^1.1* presumably that reached on December 1941, of which a cony is annexure&amp;,to this letter. 2. On the 21st December I visited Diba and inspected the tower. It is no longer demolished down to the Kab s t&gt;ut a has been built up to nearly twice that height and loonholed. No surrounding wall or stores have, however, been constructed. It is clear therefore that the cswasim have broken the agreement^entered into by their representatives on 28th December 1941. f\ 3. On my pointing out to them the extreme impropriety of this action they gave me the following reasons for it;- (a) They contend that the Muscat authorities have not fulfilled complementary agreements entered into by their representatives on the same or allied subjects. In support of this they have oroduced a document a copy of which is annexure B, showing that they had been promised Rs.600/- in consideration of demolishing the tov;er (The Political Agent, Muscat*s telegram No.T/136 dated the 24th March 1943 refers)» They state that the tower was demolished down to the Kaba and its condition was inspected and approved by Muscat representatives about a year after the date of the agreement. Shaikh Kh.^id claim, that th. Muscat ^^ 4 „ . u thorlt: agr.adto rafrain from interfarenct in tha *'adi t!adha but that thay have since aant their agent* there and collected zakat, but the docu ment* ha produces in support of this do not ^rove that any such agreement was reached • ! * (b) The object of constructing the tower waa (a* is made quite clear in the Political Agent, Muscat 1 * lett-r No. C/328 dated the 22nd April 1941 to the Hobble the Political Resident) to keer» the Oawasim part of Diba safe from the marauding* of the 3hihuh, nnd according to the agreement, thia was to bo attained by placing them / under the control of the Wall of Kha*ab. According to the ~&gt;awaaim this expedient has been a complete failure and they get no redres* for the thefta frequently committed by the Shihuh in and around their village; and this is hardly surprising as they have no com munication with Khasab by land and communication by sea is slow and uncertain. It is difficult not to sympathise with the wish of the Qawasim to protect themselves from the Shihuh and I think it is fair to stress the purely defensive character of the tower. It is scar cely 100 yards from the Qawasim fort and I would estimnte the dis tance from it to the creek which forms the boundary between the Dhuriyin and the Shihuh at 1000 yards and it is another 500 yards to the nearest houses of Bi»ah where the Shihuh live. (c) Finally Shaikh Humaid bin Abdullah told me that the agree ment would never have been signed by the Falba representatives but for the necessity of feeding the 800 men whom the Muscat seonle brought with them to Kalb*. Nearly Rs.2000/- had been spent on food during the three days of the negotiations before the Kalba finances began to run low and the Shaikhs signed the agreement as the only alternative to disgrace. I cannot vouch for the truth of thia story but it seems not unlikely that same such pressure was used. 4. Shaikh Hamdan bin Ahmad as Shihhi, 'Wali' of Bi'ah came to see me on 29th December and put the Shihuh case. I’heir main ob is that it is built on ground belonging to the Shihu. Thia of course jaction to the tower/^s hotly disputed by the Oawasim and aarears on the face of it unlikely as the tower is so very close to the fort and within the Qawasim village and because the documentary evidence which the Shihuh claim existed has been 'los$'. The Shihuh deny that the Qa^asim have been able to prove that any thefts hnve been committed by them. The R «fie nt of Kalba has been asked for details of the illegal acts of the ^Shihuh felted.-3- i&amp;Ac 5. I h»v« th« honour to submit th« following observations and raoommtndationa. i'ha original comalaint of the Qawaaim that the Shlhuh commit thafta and acta of aggrosaion in thair village remains unaltered and their original demand that the Kuscat authorities a^voint a non-Shihhi ^ali in Diba is a re^- sonable one. The expedient of appointing a Shihhi as local re presentative of Muscat and of olacing -biba undar tha distant V/ali of Khasab has not been successful and tha beat solution of tha problem is still that Muscat should appoint a non-Shihhi Wali in Dibs. If this v;ara dona I undarstand that tha '•iawaaim would gladly M damilitarise M their towar by da^ioliMhing it down to tha kaba. Should it not prova possibla to indue# tha Muscat Govarnmant to appoint a wali I conaidar that the onus of proving that the con- struction of this tower is an aggraaaion upon tha right# of their aubjacta rest# with tham. Tha submission of tha mattar to ar bitration with the following tarms of rafaranca aaama to ba the best solution;- (a) Can the Shihuh prova that tha towar has baan constructad upon land balonging to tham ? (b) If not where does the Shihuh boundary lia ? V.hen tha Shihuh-Oawa*aim boundary has baan dacidad I can saa no objection (and tha ^w#aim hava non#) to tha Shihuh constructing a towar within thair limits. I hava the honour to bo, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. M.P.O’C.Tandy. Political Officar, Trucial Coast. *translatiok INTERNAL AFFAIRS DSP ART? •ETn’. SULTAN OF MUSCAT &amp; OMAN. Praia• ba to Allah, Yi/hoae baneficonca completaa all 4 »ood undartakings; and paace ba on Hia aroahet and hia diaciplaa ua to the day of raaurraction. It Is heraby, atatad that on tha evaning of Id Alduha, 1360, an agreamant waa reached, with regard to tha affal-a of tha town of Daba, to pull down the Mur aba (square c'astla), built by Shaikh Hamid bin Abdullah bin Ahmed Alkasami, dp to tha part called ^abaa* (that part of the tower filled with mud), Ha, Shaikh Hamid bin Abdullah bin Ahmed Alkaaami, is free to use tha *Kabas f as it is or gat it unfilled and use it as a store house, ’i’he Oasamias (resident a of HisanJ and tha people of Baya are forbidden from building any new castles or forts of war-like nature, but they are free to undertake repairs of known and ancient forts and nothing more. The ^haies* will guarantee that they will refrain from surprise raids and acts of aggression and their affairs will be dealt by the Governor of Khasab, who will receive all correspondence, having bearing on the affairs of the people concerned. The agreement has b#en arrived at through, th e Director of Internal Affairs, to His Highness ^ayid Sa'aid bin Taimur, sultan of Muscat and Oman, bayid Ahmed bin Ibrahim and in the presence of the folloing persons Saqar bin Abdullah, Hamaid bin Abdullah, Sayid Ahmed bin Ibrahim. Director, Internal Affairs. Witnesses. Yarab bin Kahtan, Gusan bin u alin, Shareon bin A*amir. Housi. Hamad bin Ahmed Hayai, Ibrahim bin Sa’aid Alabri. Sea. Muhammad bin Ahmed A1 SharkiTRANSLATION /s^ 1 # Shaikh Ghusan bin Salira bin i’arhoon Al-Muamari, state that Sahikh Humaid bin Abdullah bin Ahnad A1 Kasani is legally entitled, in all circumstances, to Rs.600/- (silver) as his right when the Muraba (square castle) which lies in the town of Dabs, is pulled down upto'the ^abaa*. He confesses to that. V/ritten by Ibrahim bin Sa*aid Alabri. Dated 11th Dul Hijah I860, Sd. Gushan bin Salim^No.322-14/247 BRITISH EESIJE1TCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL BUSKIRE The 4th Eehruar3 7 ',1944. A copy of. a letter No. C/117 dated the 15th January, 1944, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, together with its enclosures is forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat. I It is requested that your comments on the S 0] proposal contained in paragraph 2(a) of the letter referred to ahove may kindly he forwarded and that it may he ascertained whether the proposal will he acceptable the Sultan. By order, Secretary to the Political Residents in the Persian Gulf— •4^! &lt;^oM '. v 'L iB'l■ Agency, Shaikh. Dated the 4th January 1944. The Political O^’icer, ,ri ruoial 0 oms t, SliHriah. lie Po' 1 tic;- t'HMh, Pa) 'ra l)i C/17-3/5 (a). Subject;- Piba Dispute I have the honour to refer to your endorsement No .0/1 '' 13. 7 + a 1 ff the penultimte pa^a of let f er ho. 1036/3 dated the 8th Rajah 1362 from the ''inister fo v Internal Affairs, Tr uscat, to the T 'inister for External If^aiuc, ‘ uscat that the l question vhich the ■ 'uscat Governr ent v.ish to have taken up with the Qawasir is that of tin tower and other buildings only and not that of collection of debts or arrest o 4 ' wrong doers. The apreer ent referred to by the Pinaster ^or External Affairs in his covering letter (No. 353/1 dated the 1st Cepterber 1943) is presumably that reached on 28th Decerher 1941, which a copy is annexure A to this letter. On the 21st December I visited Diba and insnected the towe^. 1 t is no lonpcr derofished down to the dab s but has been built up to nearly t\ ice that height and loop- holed. T ' T o surrounding wall or stores have, } o v 'evcr, been constructed. i t is clear therefore that the 'a 1 asin have broken the agre^eent entered into by their representatives on 28th December 1941. i On my point inn out to ther t^e extreme irproperiety this action they gave me the foil owing reasons for it:- (a) They contend that the l r uscat authorities have not fulfilled complementary agreements entered into by their /their represent/tiveu on the e or ' II led subjects. In supT brt this they have produced a docurent a cory o r ‘ which is annexure 13, showinr that they had been pror ised Hs. 600/- in consideration of derolishinn the tower ( the Political A,pent, 1 'uscat’s trlegrar n o. T/136 dated the 24th ? arch 1943 refers). r ’hey stc te that hhe tower was derolished down to the / ^ is and its coimition was inspected and approved hy Muscat representatives about a year a^ter the date of the agreement. Shaikh Tfhalid c]airs that the T'uscat authorities agreed to refrain fror interference in th- ^adi rat(aa but that they have since sent their agents there an 1 col-ected ^aka. , &gt;ut t::0' (h.)C’'J'le] i u. ! .r )Von' (j., &gt; i h ' v.oi + of this do not prove that any such agreement was reached. (b) The object of constructing the tover was (as is made quite clear in the Political Agent, ! f uscat’s letter Mo. 0/328 dated the 22nd April 1941 to the Hon’hie the Political Pesident) to keep the 2auasir part of Diha sa e from the rar udings of the in , ancaccordin^ 7 * to i the agreement, this was to he attained by placin/r them under the control of* the v ali of Khasab. According « to the 'awasir this expedient has been a corplete f 'ilure and they get no redress for the thefts frequently corrifcted ’\y the 'huhnh in and '■.round their vill- ^e; and this is hardly »urprising as + ! ey have no cormanication with Khasab by land and con unicatior by sea is slor and uncertain. -t. is difficult not to syrpa.thise ritli the wish of the fawMsir to protect themselves from the Chihuh and I t: ink it is fair to stress the Purely defensive ch-rmeter of the to 1 er. tt is scArce_ v ‘ 1 .)0 girds ^rpr the lavasim fort and ^ r ould estimate the distance froi it to the creek which forms the boundary between the Dhuriyin and fhe Shihuh at 1000 yards and it is another 500 yards to the’ nearest houses of Bi T ah where the fhihuh live. (c) Finally Shaikh Humaid bin Abdullah told me that the agreement would never have been signed by the KalbaKalba repreaentn tives but for the necessity of feeding the 800 nen 7 hor the reseat reo-ole broi;.;d f ' i-’ t}a r to Kalba. Nearly Rs. 2000/- had been spent on «’i r : jr f,h.e three days 0 ^ the negotiations before the Kalba finances be-ann to run 1 ov and the dhaikho • t i - r ’.e 1 the n ‘re i-’e d. as I,’.: no! y eJ?L%ra Co ckXoj&gt;r&amp;-ct- / Inn^-cA. ftyr fcriAjH** ^5-^Vuc^&gt; s tor r b. i.t. .i-t* j ■.] a i jt’uu'L 1 5 1 ‘ :' J : 0 f ( :,!•( ’ :*rrrrrr.e v.as rs.n . • Harden bin Abrad as °hihhi, ''ali” Bi’o.h cane to see re on 29th Decerber and put the ohihuh case. Their min objection ^ to Jt,he tower is that it is built on /'•round belonrinr to the OliLbu. m his of course is hotly disputed by the 'avasir and ap v ear• &lt; on the face of it urd ikely as the: tower is so very close to the fo/'t and within the dawasir village and’ because the documentary evidence which the 3hihuh clain existed las Veen 'lost”. The Shi huh deny tint the favasir 1/ave been a bl e to prove that any thefts have been con itted by then. The Regent o r Kalba has been asked for detail ; of ti e 1 ■ 'oral ac + s of 3hihuh and the ~e are- aw a i te&lt;: p j • t h •• our.to submit the following: observations and recorrendatLons. The original corplaint of the pawasin that the Shiliuh corr if thefts and acts of aggression in their villa-e rerains unaltered and their original derand that the Huscat authorities annoint a non- ohihhi nali in Diba is a reasonable- one. The expedient of appointing a 3hih ! i as local represent tive of Kuscat and of placing Diba under the dist mt rT ali of Tha r ab has not been successful and the best solution of the probier is still that Tr uscat should appoint a non- ri bih ! i ^VT i in Diba. If this v ere done I understand that the Qnvasir would gladly M der il itarise' their tower by dei olishing it down • to tb £ - tabs. °hould it not prove possible to induce the Governmeni to t c) sider that the onus proving that the construction of this to^er is an aggression 'upon the rights of tbeir subjects rests ^it 1 : them Them he gnbnission the ratter to arbitration \ r i f h the ^ollo v ’ina: tens o~ reference seers to be the best solution:- (a) Gan the bhiho.h prove that the tcwer has been constructec’ upon land belonp-inr to then? (b) If nod where r-oes the ^hi huh boundary lie? ” r }i6n the ohihuh-'awasir boundary has been decided I can see no objection (and the ' cvasir have none) to the dfiihuh constr ictin^ a tower within their lirits. I have the honour to be, •Si-, Your r ' 0 ?t obedient servant, sd. r.P.O'C Tandy. Political O^'^icer, r Yucial Soast.TRANSLATION INTERNAL A?o;. TR t :~^a r AR^ &amp;NLTAN OF INTSCAT ^ OToAn Frais© be ,o ^llah whose be?ie' icence completes all pood 'undertakings: and peace be on Nis prophet and his disciple up to the day o^ re- surrection. It is hereby stated that on the evening of Id Alduha, 1360 an agreement was reached, with regard to the affairs c^ town of paba, to null do^vr the Nuraba (souare castle) built bv Shaikh Hamid bin Abdullah bjn Ahmed AlVaSami, up to the part called 'Fabas* (that pare o^ the tower r 511ed with rv 1 ). N e , Shaihk Hamid bin Abdullah Mn Ahmed Albasami, is free to use the^Fabas* as it 5s or pet it unfilled and use it as a store house. The Casamies ( resident of* Hisan ) and ^ any new castles or undertake repairs of 'Shales* will auarantee acts of aggression of ir hasab,'”r^o the people of Baya are forbld^n from buil d5na forts of war-lil&lt;e nature, but they are free to Inown and ancient forts and nothing more. The that they will refrain from surprise raids and ct/io ^ their affairs will he dealt by the Governor reciye an correspondence, having bearing on the affairs of the )eop±e concerned, nha agreement has been arrived at through the rector of Internal Affairs to His Highness Sayid Sa^aid Mn Taitmir ^ -, • •- ( ■- 1,s cat air' (man, -^ayid 1 ’^med hin Ibrahim and ■!tv»e rr°seuoe of the following persons :~ Saqar hin Abdullah, Hamid hin Abdullah, Sayid Ahmed Mn Ibrahim. Director of Internal Affairs. Wit] Yarab bin Fahtan, ^usan bin Salim, Shareon bin A&lt; Housi amir. Hamad Mn A hmed Eayai, Ibrahim bin Sa'aid Alabri. SEAL. Muhammed bin Ahmed A1 SharVi.Telegram S From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bushire. No.C/i/ii Dated the 29th March 1944. Your endorsement No.322-14/247 February 4th did not reach me until it was too late to discuss the matter with H.H. 2. M.E.A. says that he agrees that the proposal to shift the headquarters of the Wall of Khassab is sound but that he first requires the Sultan's instructions. These now cannot be obtained until he returns from the Middle East. 3. The compensation of fts.600/- for demolishing the tower was promised by MIA without the authority of his Government. Again therefore H.H.'s instructions are required. iJ p&amp;Ux' /r^ 3 ^ tTj % ^ 4&gt;y The gist of the case is below-r Dibba comprises of ti*o villages. One occupied by the Shihuh tribe, whiiahxix who are His Highness’s subjects and tne other occupied by ^awasimi tribe who are protected by tr.e Ruler of Kalba. The main cause of their dispute seems to be the ill defined nature of their frontier. They both try to be the right!u± owners of the 'no man’s land' lying oetwe^n their two proper villages and which contains a numbed last trees. rne/settlement of the dispute was done somewhere in 1941 between the Shaikh of Kalba and the Sultan on the fola.owin to terms: ^awasimi will demolish the tower built by them on the Shihuh frontier and its height will not exceed that of a godown ^ Kuscat government will pay them Rs.bUQ as compensation, but kuscat Government do not now agree to this and say they never promised this. Tnat Sultan of kuscat will appoint somebody responsible to control the Shihus so that they do not oppress the Qs. ^ The ,Vadi to be handed over to the Shihus which had forcibly been taken over by the Qs. The trouble now appears to be about the item No.2. Sine kuscat would not pay the sum of Hs.600 the Shaikh of Kalba has not only refused to demolish the Tower, but has rebuilt it made some wall round it and built some godowns. T The Shaikh,Hamdan appointed oy kuscat in view of 3 above has aoaed some more causes of the resumption of hostilities. This is an important matter and must be brought to tho notice of P.R., P.A.? Banrain, P.0.Sharjah and kr. Peliy who has had discussions with'the Shaixh of Kalba about this very trouble Before taxing any action on this, I sug 0 est we ask for tkax a copy of the agreement referred to in the enclosure to the P.U.G. We have no copy of the said agreement and I am suife neither P.R. nor P.A. Bahrain has any. This copy will show what has actually be^n agreed upon and then we can explain this in our report to Bucnire etc. I will draft if a.P.A. a to r^es A.P.A. P i CJ! • l um, &gt;, &gt;U7 \</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003e3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/220</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003e3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/220</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/38 Muscat State Affairs Qwasimi Shaikh of Dhibba and his Relations with the State'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-18T23:51:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (173 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 175; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file, like the preceding file in this sequence [IOR/R/15/6/219] concerns an ongoing dispute between the Jawasim [Āl Qawāsim] and the Shihuh, two tribes residing at Diba [Dibba, transliterated in various ways throughout the file].The correspondence, which discusses reports of aggression on both sides, features the following principal correspondents: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Residency Agent, Sharjah; the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Sa‘īd]; the Regent of Kalba [Shaikh Khālid bin Aḥmad bin Sultān Āl Qasimī]; the Government of Muscat and Oman's Minister for External Affairs.Much of the correspondence revolves around the contentious issue of a recently constructed tower in the part of Diba inhabited by the Jawasim. Related matters of discussion include the following: the occupation by the Jawasim of villages in the Wadi Madha, which is defended by the Regent of Kalba as an act of protection rather than one of aggression; a reported settlement in late 1941 between the Regent of Kalba and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman; the demolition of the tower at Diba, and the Regent of Kalba's claim for compensation; reports that, contrary to his agreement with the Sultan, the Regent of Kalba has rebuilt the tower.The Arabic language material mainly consists of correspondence between the Political Agent and Consul at Muscat and representatives of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Regent of Kalba</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Qawāsim (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Shiḥūḥ (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Diba</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003e3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>