<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0002fa_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:47:27.523Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/\ This document is the property of Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Confidential. 1898 . Memorandum on Makran by Sir W. Lee-Warner. (Letter from India, No. 214 (Foreign), 17th November 1898.) The time seems to have arrived for testing by the light of experience the * Enclosure 12 to Secret Letter from India, policy of Kelat responsibility introduced No. 65, of 25th April 1894. in 1894. In their Letter,* No. 637 E, dated 10th March 1894, the Government of India, having abandoned the half measure of unauthorised political control, determined to look to the Khan to uphold his authority in Makran. Turning from the other alter native, the oft repeated and as oft rejected proposal—that a British garrison in Makran should support a British administrator—to the narrower question whether British troops are not necessary to preserve internal order, they observed that the Kelat treaty agreements do not impose upon the British Government the duty of maintaining internal order, “and until the Khan “ has made a real attempt to restore order to the districts of Makran “ conjointly with the Sardars according to the constitution of the State, the “ question of any appeal to the British Government to assist His Highness “ in maintaining his just authority does not arise.” Sir Steuart Bayley, in noting on this letter, observed, “ I think it very doubtful whether order will “ be restored and maintained without more active interference on the part “ of the Government of India,” but he approved of the question of appeal being deferred until the experiment mentioned above had been made. Sir Alfred Lyall predicted the failure of the new policy in these terms : — “ I am afraid that the experiment of imposing on the Khan of Kelat the task of controlling the Makran tribes is destined to fail inevitably. It could only succeed if the Khan were able to establish his authority over the province; but this was never accomplished, if it was even attempted, by his predecessors, and Mir Mahmud has neither the money, nor the means, nor the personal influence that is necessary. If he were, like the Afghan Amir, an able and powerful despot, well furnished with arms and subsidies, he might be able to overawe the border tribes; but he is only the head of a confederacy of Baluch tribes, among whom the Khan never pretended to maintain internal order, and the present Khan is young and inexperienced. “As soon as the border shall have been demarcated, the Persians will undoubtedly expect us to be responsible for keeping the peace on it, and we shall find Mir Mahmud a very ineffective agent for that purpose.” Since this Minute was written the border has been demarcated. As regards Afghanistanf we have lined it out from Nushki to the Koh-i-Malik-i- Siah, south of Seistan. As regards Persia^ we have filled in the yawning gap between Seistan and Jalk. We now at length know the political limits of Baluchistan and Makran, and if we choose we can develop the trade routes to the ports of Gwetter, Pasni, or Ormara, which in ancient days were highways of Eastern commerce. Before discussing the fate of the scheme introduced in 1894, I propose to give a short retrospect of our relations with Makran, and a brief account of that country. t Secret Letter from India, No. 149, dated 11th August 1896. t Secret Letter from India, No. 168, dated 8th September 1896. 2. Makran is estimated to contain an area of some 32,000 square miles, with a thin population of some 200,000 persons. In physical aspect it consists of alternate parallel ranges of hills running from east to west and intervening valleys. Of these valleys that of Kej is the most important, and it is said that they offer facilities for a good road from the coast to Seistan or Kelat. There are five coast districts, Ormara, Pasni, Kolanch, Gwadar attached to Maskat, and Juni, while the inland districts areKolwah,Dasht, Panjgur, Kej } S. 54. A2 Tump, and Mand. An article in the “ Geographical Journal ” for April 1896 gives an interesting account of the great port of Tiz, and the ancient history of Gedrosia or Makran. It is enough for present purposes to revert to the 8th * Aitchison’s Treaties Vol IX n 397 of Vecember 1876, when the Govern- (edition 1892). ’ - P- ■ ment of India* undertook “ to aid the “ Khan, in case of need, in the maintenance of a just authority and the protection of his territories from “ external attack by such means as the British Government may at the “ moment deem expedient.” At that time Persia still coveted the Mashkhel districts, and the frontier from Jalk to Koh-i-Malik-i-Siah was not settled. But Makran was an integral part of Baluchistan, and as wo undertook to protect the Khan we also became responsible for Makran. 3. Our first attempt to fulfil our treaty obligations took the shape of spasmodic intervention to settle disputes without the means of super vision or of enforcing the settlement. Such a policy was doomed to tailure. The population of Makran consists of two classes, the patient long suffering herdsmen and tillers of the soil, for the most part unarmed, and the clans vho have acquired dominion in the various districts. The clans in turn are of various races, of which two stand pre eminent, the Gitchkis and the^ Nausharwanjis. The Gitchkis are not Biahuis, they are of Bajput origin hut converts to Mahomedanism. In the middle of the last century they ousted the Boledas, and became rulers of Kei and of the greater part of Makran. Conquered in turn by the Khan of Kelat, Isasir Khan, the Gitchkis were still strong enough to retain certain lights. Iheir administration was conducted by their own chiefs, with whom was associated a Naib representing the central authority of the Khan, who received a share in the revenues. Thus arose a fertile cause of dispute. If the Khan’s authority was weak, the Naib became a nobody, and ofttimes he has become a prisoner or a fugitive. As to the Nausharwaniis who were established in Kharan, being Persians by origin, they soon acquired authority in Panjgur, and by judicious marriages extended their influence and rights to Boleda and Kolwah. This process naturally led to quarrels with the Gitchkis, while it did not increase the authoritv of the Khan The Chief of the Nausharwanjis was Mir Azad Khan, who was in course of time succeeded by Nowroz Khan. 4. Prom time to time affairs drifted into civil war, and the Government of India had to interfere. Under one great settlement effected in 1884 Azad Khan M Kharan was reconciled to the Khan, and took his place in the Brahui confederacy. A Jagir in Panjgur was awarded to him, with a subsidv from the Government of India. At the same time Amir Jan was recognised as Gitchki Sardar of Panjgur, and his uncle was appointed as the Khan’s Baib. There soon appeared a rival claimant to the Sardarship and Naibship of Panjgur, and the Nausharwanjis took part in the disturbances which followed. In kej and Tump other disorders ensued, and the Persian Government complained of attacks on caravans and on its subjects. It was clear that empty settlements which we took no pains to enforce merelv increased disorder and opposition. Therefore in 1891 a British officer was established in Makran, with a sufficient escort to support his authority. f See India Foreign Proceedings, October V\ e Governm ent of Indiaf consented to 1891, No. 53 (External), para. 20 . ^ ls as a temporary measure, and the policy of “let alone” came to an end. 5. The new departure was, however, not allowed time to become a policy. t lbid. % No. 86 (External). letter da ted 5th September x the Government of India! decided that they would not take over the administration, hut they did not show the courage of their convictions until ] 8 9B On various pretexts the Agent § Secret Letter from India, No. 104, retained the escort, and at last, on 23rd May 1893, Enclosure 3. p l 'd March 1893, the Governor General .,, , , in Council § peremptorily ordered its withdrawal, adding that the Government “cannot consider themselves “ responsible if the line of action adopted by the Baluchistan Agency ha« “ resulted in the creation of rights and obligations in Makran which now3 prove to be a source of embarrassment.” Lord Kimberley thought this a pitiful confession, but the India Office did not commit itself to any official reply. 6. A crisis now occurred in the central government of Kelat. Mir Khudadad Khan was forced to abdicate, and was succeeded by his son Mir Mahmud Khan. The occasion was suitable for the introduction of a new policy of centralised government and of enforcing the Khan’s responsibility. As soon as the policy was put into action the Government of India and the Secretary of State began to mistrust it. The policy was thus described in a letter from the Government of India* * E ' clos ' , ' e No. 1 in Secret Letter from ^ its A „ ent dated 28th August 1893. India, No. 59, of 30th March 1894. f T i. • * c i, ft It is incumbent on the Khan, as our “ ally, to provide suitably for the protection of that part of the frontier “ which is entrusted to his care.” An adequate military force w r as needed, and the Khan’s troops were to be re-organised. On the 10th of March 1894 the Government of India wrotef to t Ihd., Enclosure 2. their Agent. “ The Government of “ India have an interest in seeing that the country is pacified, because “ internal dissension has a bad effect on the border, and, as has often been “ the case with the Rinds of Mand, may give rise to aggression and “ lawlessness on the Persian side of the border which might again require “ the interposition of the British power.” The Government of India cast a glance back at the old policy when they added that “ the Sardars share the “ responsibility for keeping the peace and should share the cost, and the “ Government of India desire to see arrangements made by which this * l conjoint duty shall be adequately discharged.” But they came to the practical point when they ordered the Agent to call the serious attention of the Khan” to his duty.J “ You should lose no “ time in pointing out to His Highness “ the necessity for raising and main- “ tainim? in Makran a sufficient bodv of “ disciplined troops to ensure punctual raids or punish raiders.” These orders were reported home in Government of India Letter, No. 65, dated 25th April 1894, but again no action was taken here. The policy of Kelat responsibility was quickly tested and immediately abandoned. The Rinds fell out with the Persians, and obviously an international complication required our settlement. An officer was despatched, and the settlements made by him in two seasons were reported home and approved. Meanwhile, the Khan proceeded to strengthen his military position, and to undertake “ his duty,” an officer, Mr. Le Mesurier, was lent to him. The Khan also declared his intention to tour in Makran; the Government of India were hopeful of the “ best results,” and the Secretary of State on 14th February 1896§ broke a long official silence, and congratulated the Government of India. He went beyond this, for he gave a caution hoping that the organisation of a military force would not depress the status of the Kelat nobility. Already fears began to be felt of the centralising policy and its effects. Events proved that the fears were justified. The Khan did go on tour, although the Government of India did not by letter report the result. Disorders, however, resumed their course. The notorious outlaw, Mir Shahdad Khan, proceeded to business until he was at last surrounded, and finally on January 1898 the whole policy of relying upon the Khan fell to the ground. The country rose in rebellion, headed by Mir Baluch Khan Nausharwanji, and Mir Mehrab Khan Gitchki and other Chiefs. The Khan’s Nazim, Diwan Udho Dass, supported by the Khan’s re organised troops, as suggested by the Government of India, was taken prisoner on 6th January at Turbat in Kej, and with difficulty escaped. The greater part of Makran was in revolt against its ruler. The defiance of the Khan’s authority w r as not the only difficulty. A party of surveyors appointed by the paramount British power to map out thecountry of the protected State of Makran, was attacked and dispersed. A column of British troops was at once despatched, and after a smart action on olst January last, in which the two leaders mentioned above were kiLed, the rising was suppressed, at a S. 54. A 2 J Letter to Agent to Governor-General, No. 537 E, dated 10th March 1894. Enclosure No. 12 in Secret Letter from India, No. Go of 1894. collection of revenue and prevent § Secret 1896. Despatch to India, No. 4 ofcost to British revenues which 1 cannot ascertain, but Rs. 120,000 are entered in the Estimates for the current year alone. The causes for the rising were as follows :—Nausharwanjis, Boledas, and Gitchkis, had a quarrel about the Bit fort, and a decision given by the Governor General’s Agent was distasteful to some of them. The leaders of Kej disapproved of the Khan’s system of levying the rents due to him, and for which the Govern ment of India had themselves suggested the use of disciplined troops. The Khan s Kazim was personally unpopular. We were informed of these facts by Government of India Letter No. 163, dated 15th September 1898, and noted on the gravity of the situation. As it was supposed that the Government of India would consult the Secretary of State before embarking on a new policy, a mere acknowledgment was sent by Despatch, No. 123, dated 3rd November 1898. 7. The expectation was not realised. Without even aw ? aiting our acknow ledgment, the Government of India have plunged into a fourth policy, which may be described as a sort of irresponsible home rule. Their proceedings were reported in a Letter, No. 214, dated 17th November 1898, and are. described as “an efficient administration based on the Brahui system of Sardars and ^Naibs, with a representative of the Khan of Kelat to superintend “ the Naibs, and advise both Sardars and Naibs.” The centralising policy is abandoned. “ The Nazim should have no direct hand in the administration “ and collection of revenue, but is responsible to the Khan that the levies are paid, and that the Naibs do their duty and account for the revenue •* collected.” The Nazim is to keep the Khan informed of what goes on. Mir Mehrulla Khan, a man of a sullied reputation, is to be the new Nazim. The infantry portion of the reformed troops (the essential feature of the late policy of 1894) is to be disbanded, and the new levies are to be under the Nazim. The people, Gitchkis, Nausharwanjis, Bands, and others w r ho have never agreed to live in peace are to be told not “ to expect or look for further visits by the Political Agent.” Dewan Udho Dass is withdrawn to India. The responsible advisers of the Government of India, w r ith the exception perhaps of Lieutenant Knox, are against the scheme. In the w r ords of Colonel Wylie, w r ho advocated the establishment of a Political Agent in Makran supported by a small escort to restrain the Naibs, and to settle disputes,—“ I believe that all officers in any way responsible for this “ agency have agreed that this arrangement is the best that can be devised, “ both tor the good of Makran and for ourselves, especially wdien we “ consider the rapid advance southward of Russian emissaries, and of the “ manner in which Persia is falling under the control of that Power. But “ as the Government of India have authoritatively declared that it does not “ approve of this plan, it has to be discarded.” No loyal official could write more seriously or adversely to a policy. 8. The Secretary of State has not yet expressed any opinion, and therefore I venture to point out the objections to the plan, which seems to me a policy absolutely doomed to failure. i. It does nothing to compose the racial disputes of Gitchkis and Nausharwanjis and Boledas, or to give peace and justice to the native population, who are ground between their mill-stones. The local Chiefs of Makran and Kharan have certain independent rights which we are bound to recognize as w r e recognize those of the mediatized chiefs of Central India. No one but an Agent of the Government of India can hold the balance. ii. I he authority of the responsible ruler of Makran will rest upon a few inefficient tribal levies, and yet the Government of India has con demned the policy advocated by Sandeman and “ all officers in any way responsible for this Agency” which would at least support our just settlements by an impartial Agent on the spot and an efficient British escort. iii. The Nazim, who controls the levies, is to have nothing to do with the administration. Will he not therefore be responsible, yet incapable of applying a remedy ? iv. He is to report his own and other people’s doings to a distant ruler, and there is nothing to keep him in order or in check. The people5 v. VI. J 56 even the British Government will send no Political Agent to visit them. Vital British interests on the coast and on the Persian border are neglected. I refer to these interests in the next para°Taph While the scheme does nothing to fulfil our obligations to the 1 rotected State of Kelat and its subjects, it affords us no guarantee for the peace of the border which we have lately settled with 1 ersia, and no means of fulfilling our international obligations. 9. What are our interests in Makran ? L The port of Gwadar open to commerce and situated near to the .British frontier forms part of Maskat, and France claims a ioint protectorate with us oyer Maskat. It is true that we obtained from Maskat an order in 1891 prohibiting the import of arms and ammunition into Gwadar, hut there is reason to fear that the order could not be maintained if it were challenged by France. Our only remedy then would be to isolate Gwadar, but if we have no influence in the interior we cannot do that. .II. Peace and order in -Mastartrare requisite, because we must interfere it there is disorder, and because our policy and our relations with the JNatiye States require internal peace. This is not a case of trans-frontier advance. The sea which borders our Makran 1 rotectorate limits any further advance. III. Internal trade has been destroyed by constant disorders in Makran, but its former history and its physical features would, with peace ensure a revival of trade. r ’ IV. The collapse of Persia, Russian intrigues, and railway possibilities render it desirable to increase our supervision and our influence on the borders of Southern Persia and Seistan. V. krom Makran to Karachi, avoiding Quetta altogether, there is an easy route winch is practicable for a railway. A complete recon naissance of such a line was carried out in 1892 by Captain Mackenzie, R.E., with these results. From Karachi to Lus Bela a nne of 1 2° miles was estimated to cost Rx. 1,270,000; from Lus Bela to Nal 140 miles, Rx. 2,330.000, and from Nal to Kharan, 105 miles Rx 1 428,000. From Kharan or Nal to Panjgur there is an interval of about 160 miles. From Kharan to Nushki there are 83 miles, and the estimated cost of a railway is Rx. 1,176 000. lliese figures show that Karachi is no far cry from the heart of Makran. ^ From Karachi to Gwadar is a distance of about 380 miles and Pasni, an important port of Makran, is about 270 miles distant from Karachi. I do not presume to discuss strategical questions, but the facts and figures given above show that our vital interests m Karachi might easily be affected by indifference to the fate of Makran. ui 0 ™ 11 } conc ? usion I ma J observe that the whole account of our dealings with Makran since 18/6 shows that we have fitfully tried four different policies without any satisfactory results. The scheme now being introduced, without the authority of the Secretary of State, appears to me self condemned. It rests upon the conduct of a single man of most doubtful antecedents repre senting the Khan with a weak tribal force. It shirks our responsibilities for the peace of a [protected State, whose boundaries march with two foreign powers, Persia and Maskat, the former being under the thumb of Russia, and the latter under the recognised joint protectorate of France and k Great Britain. I submit that such a settlement demanded the consideration and approval of the Home Government, and I draft for approval a Despatch ex P lain and justify the Secretary of State’s telegram dated 8th December 1898. At present our hands are tied by the precipitate action of the Government of India. But as soon as the inevitable breakdown appears on the horizon, we shall, I hope, follow our well-established pohcy towards all Native States and accept our evident responsibilities in Makran. ■p ■pj* ■« , c . *. , W. Lee-Wabner. Political and Secret Department, 21st December 1898.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0002fa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/A136</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0002fa</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/A136</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on Makran by Sir W. Lee-Warner (Letter from India No. 214 (Foreign), 17 November 1898) 21 Dec 1898.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1898/1898</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-19T09:40:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the first folio and terminates at the last folio. These numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a report by Sir William Lee-Warner (1846-1914) written during his tenure as Secretary to the Secret and Political Department. It is a critique of the Government of India's current policy towards Makran, which he claims has not been authorised by the Home Government. This policy depends on the Khan of Kelat, Mir Mahmud Khan, maintaining stability in the region; it is the author's opinion that he does not have the means to do so, and more direct British intervention is required.The report contains a brief account of Makran, covering its geography, recent history, and relations with Britain. It also explains how British policy towards the region has developed, and the interventions that have been instigated as a result. It also outlines what the author considers Britain's interests in the area to be.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Khan of Kalāt, rulers of Kalāt</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Makran Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kelat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial policy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000788.0x0002fa#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>