<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T09:46:46.662Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Km Telegram Prom To No. T.90 Dated 25th(received 26th) September 1933 Enclair Resident, Head-Munshi,Bahrain care Residency,Agent,Sharjah C/o Airways Please enquire from Residency Agent about individ ual of whom Wali of KHASAB spoke to me and ask Residency Agent to report to Political Bahrain by letter with copy to me.^ . A-&lt;? * V When the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf visited KHASAB on 20*9.33(at 6 P.M*) the Wali made the following request:- u One by name FARAJ bin SUB AIT of KHASAB went for diving with one SALIM BIN MUSABBIH of DIBAI and earned Rs.450/- which was not given to him. Two years ago he took a letter from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat to the Shaikh of Dibai requesting him to help FARAJ in getting his money from SALIM but the Shaikh used to put him off from one day to another until he got tired and returned to KHASAB. No letter, was taken from the Political Agent, Muscat, but the Residency Agent,Shargah knows about this man^ case. 'I shall be grateful if the Hobble the Political Resident uses his good offices and help this poor man in getting his due si*. The Hon*ble the Political Resident promised to enquire from the Residency Agent,Shargah about this man's case and ordered me to make a note of the Wali's request. On arrival at Dibai the Hon'ble the Political Resident was very busy and had no time to enquire from the Residency Agent. He ordered me to ask the Residency Agent about this case and make a note of his reply. On the evening of the 23rd September 1933 I told the Residency Agent of the above. He said that he did not remember of any such case but that when he goes on shore he will make enquiries and report the result to the Hon'ble the P.R. On receipt of the attached telegram from the Hon'ble the P.R. I again informed the Residency Agent and asked him to send a report to the Political Agent, Bahrain and send copy to the Hon'ble the Political Resident^ SKxfexxzx Before leaving Dibai the Residency Agent told me that he enquired from SALIM MUSABIH who informed him that he settled with the above sailor in the presence of Shaikh SA'ID bin MAKTUM, the Shaikh of DIBAI l and that he is not 12 . s 3 indebted to him for any money. He also stated that he has taken a document from the sailor FAKAJ to the effect that he has no futfter claim against him f which was attested by SA^D bin MAKTUM, the Shaikh of DIBAI,and promis^ed to ask the Shaikh to give it to him and show it to the Residency Agent, Shaikh SA'ID bin MAKTUM happened to call the Residency Agent at the moment he was speaking to SALIM MUSABBIH and he too corroborated the statement of SALIM brother, She Residency Agent then asked SALIM to search for it and give him a copy of the said document, which he promised to do. The Residency Agent is sending a report as ordered by the Hon'ble the Political Resident,as soon as he gets the document of which he wants to take a copy. Submitted for information. 3 ,ly/ ^ No. J he Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to # a The Political Agent, B A H R A IB. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents/^/ W 1 - &gt; &gt;’• 4 &lt; v' -' British Residency and Consutate-General, BUSH IRK. Dated. the L i' November 1933* * Reference to previous correspondence Bahrain P.L. No. 986/V.O., dated the 5th October 1933. /jesrription of Enclosure.No. 527. A ® Dated 5th October 1933. From. The Residency Agent,Sharjah. To. The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. A ,C. , 1 beg to state that on the 22nd September 1933 when the Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf arrived at Debai in H.M.S'.'Shoreham' Bayed Abdur Razzaq the Munshi to the Political Agent Bahrain was accon^anying him and the latter after the Political Resident had left, informed me that Farhan al-’Oud, a subject of the Sultan of Muscat, had a claim against Salem bin Musabbah for the sum of .is.400/ being his earnings from diving and which had not untill then been paid to him by the said Salem. Maktum Ruler of Debai. He informed me that the said Farhan had already complained to him and tha-t he(the Shaikhj summoned Salem bin Musabbah and some other persons who effected a settlement between the parties and the claim was compromised for a sum of as. 300/- which was paid to Farhan against his receipt showing as to how the claim was decided. ordered Salem bin Musabbah to show it to me. The latter made me a paper showing that the case was settled by a compromise effected between Farhan and Salem bin Musabbah. I submit it herewith for your information. I therefore represented the case to Shaikh Sayed bin searches for it but could not find it. The Ruler therefore sent I then asked the Ruler for th^ receipt and he U.L.? 30-10-33.Certificate dated the 14th Jamda-ath-Thani 1352 (5th October 1933) signed and sealed by Shaikh Said bin Maktum Ruler of Debai. Let all who may happen to read this document know. That Farhan al-*Oud applied to us on the 19th Rabi’a-uth- Thani 1351 (13th September 1932) and preferred a claim against Salem bin Musabbah. That we summoned the said Salem and the case was discussed between them in a council (of certain persons). That the members of the Council ultimately affected a settlement between them thus that the sum claimed was compromised for Es.300/- Salem bin Musabbah paid the sum to Farhan against his receipt showing that the case was settled for fis.300/- and the paper was handed over to Salem bin Musbbah. That now when we asked Salem bin Musbbah to produce the document he could not do so as it had been lost. That.for this reason we wrote this Certificate to explain matters. That Shaikh Ahmad bin Muhammad bin Hilal and Mattar bin Khamis who are our subjeats are witnesses to the proceedings in the case and God ic the best of all witnesses.C’s. P. P.—L (m) 980—300-12-29—c. No -ZiL£2 / v.o. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to t&lt;nG Political Agent, Muscat and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents, for i nTorma'tion# The Agency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 193 Reference to previous correspondence. Description of Enclosure. Name and date. Subject. Note dated the 3rd October 1933 of Head IMnahi, Bahrain Clai y n for Pc # 450 /- of .# ForaJ bin Bubalt of Khasab against Salim bin r.usabbih of Dibai^'Site: l Stu* Telegram No.T.90 dated 25.9.33 from the Hon'ble the PoliLxcal Resident. Subject:- Claim(Rs.450/-) of FARAJ BIN SUBAIT of KHASAB against SALIM BIN MUSABBIH of DIBAI. P.A., When the Hon’ble the Political Resident visited Khasab on 20.9.33, the Wall asked the good offices of the Hon'Die the P.R. for the recovery of the above claim and the P.R. promised to enquire from the Residency Agent Shargah. I submit a note on the subject, whiefy subject to your approval # may be sent to Bushire and a copy kept for our record. SuDmitted for orders. 3.10.33 Vco S- A—^ /cJL 78 ((Vq.$) ■ £ . , ^ 7A* Printed letter No.2275 dated the 4th November 1933 from the Secretary Bushire forwarding a copy of letter No.527 dated 5th October 1933 addressed to him by Residency Agent Sharjah and a copy of certificate dated the 5th October 1933 signed by Shaikh Sayeed bin Maktum. may the papers be filed plaase »Plea se put up the case about t&amp;e slave about whom the Wall of Khassab asked me. I want it while Major Bremner is here. H.M. L 11.11.33 r ./v. The papers are submitted please. &amp; 11 . 11 . 33 . I had meant a copy of this to go to you • Ordinarily I shd have (as P.R.) told the Wall of Khassab to approach you , but as I was going to Sharjah next day and thought that there would be no harm in saying that I would enquire. The matter seems to haae beens ettled. Would you like a copy of the note ? copy o 11.11.33 P.A. Masqat ^ t^im 'JpL i+*~ a ^ ^ ex &amp; jfc a /CieL er/ / / ' /// ^ ^ ^ c CL 4 _g ‘ ^ • //. JJ . (L tlua l P.A. Printed letter forwarding the note to the Political Agent, Muscat is submitted for your signature please.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1969</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1969</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File K/14 Claim of Faraj ibn Subait of Khasab against Salim ibn Musabbih of Dubai (Trucial Coast)</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-13T22:25:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 17; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-5 and ff 9-13; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding a monetary claim made by Faraj bin Subait of Khasab on Salim ibn Musabbih of Dubai for diving work conducted during the pearling season of 1933.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Trade disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>