<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:23:57.627Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">J-C. ND KEY. be taken to Uni er Secretary of State . Hj ■ c.* . L yi~Mc, J • rfcfaieaJkA kxtC We recently suggested to the Foreign Office that they dUv^ pa. should ask Sir R.Bullard to leave open for further examination, in the light of developments in the Persian situation, the p^ /t/ \T. Viceroy^ proposal for the appointment of a i|n^or British Official to tour Consulates in Persia 7 (fenS-Ext. 3681 / 42 ). It will be remembered that I4r .Holman, while in charge of the Tehran Legation, had expressed the opinion that no such appointment was necessary. The Viceroy was informed that we were trying to keep the door open, and he has since telegraphed that he is grateful for this, and* that he hopes Sir R.Bullard may be sympathetic. He adds that he has little doubt that much the best man for the job would be Colonel Hay. This ignores the objection raised by the Foreign Office ,and passed on to the Viceroy in the Secretary of State’s Private and Personal telegram No*739 of June l?th, viz. that the appointment of a Serving Consular Officer to investigate work done by other Consuls might cause friction. It would be difficult to persuade the Foreign Office to waive this objection, or to suggest means of overcoming it. Even if Colonel Hay were to be up-graded so as to give him a status above that of the most senior Consular official, there would still remain the objection that H.M.Consuls in Persia might resent inspection by someone who had so recently been one of their number. (It might, of course, be argued that the same applies to Mr .Squire, but there was at least an interval of sane months between his appointment as Additional Counsellor at the Legation and the beginniig of his touring activities). Moreover, any insistence on our part upon the claims of Colonel Hay might be interpreted by the Foreign Office as prompted by the desire to increase unduly the 'Indian' element in the Legation. Already the Additional C&lt;|isec 6 ar and Military Attache are members of the Indian services; and the Government of India have recently proposed the appointment of an Indian First Secretary. In fact, however, one reason for the Viceroy's preference for Colonel Hay may be that the Government of India are having difficulty in finding for him a sufficiently high grade appointment when he ceases to officiate as Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the return from leave of Colonel Prior. (With regard to /thethe Ahwaz Consulate, to which the Viceroy refers, we have just passedaxto the Government of India a request from the Foreign Office that Major Falconer, now Consul,at Kerman, should be made available for this postj. We,have;also received frcm the Foreigp Office a letter --saying'that they have received a .telegram from Sir F.Bullard whici renders unnecessary a telegram to him such as we had suggested. The Foreign Office have not seen fit ,to send us a copy of Sir R.Bullard’s telegram, but from the suinaary given in their letter it seems clear that Sir R.Bullard still adheres to the opinion he expressed when in this country, viz., that the idea behind the Viceroy’s suggestion is a valuable one. (Mr.Holman may have been misled by the words 'if he can be spared' in Foreign Office telegram No.977)• Sir R.Bullard clearly agrees that Mr .Squire should do as much touring as possible, and this seems to meet our and the Viceroy's wishes in the most essential particular. It is therefore proposed that the Secretary of State should send a private and Personal trlegram to the Viceroy, as in the draft which follows, pointing out that Sir R.Bullard is prepared to adopt the substance, if not the form, of his proposal; but making it clear that we do not wish to pursue the question of utilising Colonel Hay for this purpose. A short draft letter ..to. the Foreign Office is also submitted. al care may of this docu- J /• i/Mf . «|r a* ' ^ ^ ^ u ^ *^7 iz M/t- *-• r£o. ^ tu * 'H k (r ^ L fc. r f r#v . t ▼ i w ^ r ~ —- * y • ~~ ~ (rra^yi fa &gt;■&lt;- Uu L~ AV- •• Uj - ^ k W ‘ L ^ 1 ] ^ i*' cO ivwO fa) ** ^ 'c^ ^'1,^ ‘ 1 A (Mi&gt; ^wv ^ ^ x/ ' , r / ’. a ,Draft letter I.T.M.Pink*Es&lt;l*» Foreign Office* AUG Dear Pink, Your letter to Lumby of July 31 s ' fc » E* 4389 / 144 / 34 » about the suggested appointment of a §enior British Official to tour our Consulates in Persia* We agree that in the circumstances there is no need for you to telegraph to Tehran as we had suggested* We are passing on to the Viceroy the substance of Bullard's telegram^ as described in your letter. Yours sincerely. (Sgd.) R.Draft telegram From? Secretary of State. To: Viceroy Dated 5,8.42. 14 ■ r/S- © j ^ Before coy suggestion open|had been^passed Officejreceived from Private and Personal. Your Private and Personal telegram!No.2222-S of iTuly 29th.Inspector'Generaii for Persia. that/question should be 1 left on to : ^|])ird t Foreign him | telegram fshowing that J had heed under sok^; misapprehension: as to\what was/required .[ Bullard, exp la iijs that; Squire has been fully occupied! in/ dealingj with food (supplies! and the triba]j question^ and for some (time!was acljing as Director of Public Relations^ Bullard/quite 1 agrees that|Squire! should |visit |provincial ! Consulatejs when his heavy /duties (permit,^ in order (tofenquire 4 the/various^matters (which we( had/in mind^ helping to I wake (up the (provincial/administration! into thus ^ /&gt;'* ' . 4 . both^indirectly through \his V own through IconsulS and directly I \ 'll visits to local officials. /WhenFOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l FOREIGN OFFICE, S. (Ext 3681/42) about the suggested appointment of a senior British official to tour our Consulates in Persia. Tehran wnich shows that on his return the Minister found that there had been some misunderstanding as to what was required. He explains that Squire has been fully occupied in dealing with food supplies and the. tribal question, and for some time was acting as Director of Public Relations. Bullard quite agrees that Squire should visit provincial Consulates when his heavy duties permit. He would then be able to enquire into the various matters which we had in mind, and would help to wake up the provincial administration both indirectly through the Consuls and directly through his own visits to local officials. At that moment Squire was at Ahwaz investigating the measures taken to deal with the food situation in Khuzistan. As Bullard evidently shares our view that Squire should make such tours as and when he c an spar e the time it no longer seems necessary for us to 'telegraph to Tehran on this question. It is not quite clear v/hat the misunderstanding was which produced Tehran telegram No. 889, but probably the We have now had a further telegram from appointment/ E.W.R. Lumby, Esq., India Office.appointment of u General Inspector”, and the withdrawal of Squire from his present duties to take up this post Anyway the misunderstanding has now 'been cleared up.504 XXX s*&lt;~ Xs^ ft * UL^ ? ^ ^ Telegram from Viceroy dated 29th iluly 1942 2222-3 Private and personal. Your private and personal telegram of July 23rd, 893. Inspector- General for Persia. I have discussed with Caroe and agree with you that, once consular liaison system is in full operation, some appointment in the nature of an Inspector-General (whatever it may be called) will be necessary if the administrative machine in Persia is to be screwed up by H.L.'s Consuls assisted by consular liaison system; that, for it, an officer of wide experience, with a good knowledge of Persia, and determined to tour with energy, will be needed. I am very grateful TcTyou for keeping door open, and hope that Bullard may be sympathetic. I have little doubt that much the best man for job would be Kay. I gather Bullard has recently suggested that Kay should be sent to Ahwaz. which is likely to become a much more important post and to control line of rail way from the two ports of kohammerah and Bandar Shah- pur up to Dizful. But I think this post will be insufficiently high-graded for man of Hay’s seniority and experience and I feel pretty certain that you would find it difficult to improve on him for Inspector-Generalship. ij vll (kJ- ^ haU fee ua ■ £V^..\/i&gt;^ jfy'i ^ &lt;v y '{'■*** -C-'f ■ &lt;^ ^vt DRAFT TELBGRA1*: © From Secretary of State To Viceroy. dated 22. 7 •42. ^'Vvh \ \ 's Private and Personal . ^ V. ^ V V '' V No.739 dated 17th June. \ \ \ \ \ Lty p. and p. telegram Inspector General for Persia. You will have seen from Foreign Office telegrams repeated to Government of India that proposal, has been put to Tehran who do not consider such appointment necessary for general inspection^ I still feel however that when Consular^Liaison system is in full V N. S \ ^ v, ^ ^ operation, it will be desirable for someone from \ V ^ 'S ^ Headquarters to tour in order to coordinate policy generally, whether or not he is given title of Insp^ctor-Geheral, Imd I am asking Foreign Office tb \ ^ \ v \ suggest to Tehran that matter should be left for further examination in light 'of developments^ Bullard , s who \ \ ^ \ \ \ v N is now fNfe back in Tehran, is acquainted ' sitte] X \ with our views in the matter and, I understand, was N \ \ \ X \ disposed to look favoxirably on idea. - Jiw :Ext.3681/42. Draft letter. I.T.M.Pink,Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.l. is JUL 194 | Dear Pink, With‘reference to'our recent telephone conversation about the suggested appointment of a senior British official to tour H.M.Consulates in Persia, I v/rite to let you know that we feel that Holman has disposed rather lightheartedly of this suggestion, which we still think is a useful one, and, we under stand, had Bullard^ support. t £4 Squire is no doubt too busy at Head- O u CL [JILL p llCXU. XJ Li ,L JLCl JL LA. O \J • (V/e Admit, for the moment Squi quarters dealing with the wheat £ fe oc^ClajcJL situatio'r^ but when the present ^ ft . Am i a difficulties^have been disposed of, there seems to be no reason why /hehe should not continue the touring which he has been doing in recent months, see for instance his report of April 21st on the food situation (F,0.reference No.E.3165/144/34) ; paragraph 2 of Holman^ despatch No.163 of June 1st, and also the enclosure to Holman T s despatch No. 173 of June 8 th, which shows that Squire also undertook a tour in order to investigate the question of the return of tribal lands. We cannot help thinking that general .superintendence of the work of Consular Officers and Consular Liaison Officers - particularly in the direction of gingering up the Persian Administration will be considerably facilitated by touring on the spot and that this method will be far more satisfactory than /leavingfc*-*** {#{*£■ 0* tfeo leaving touch, to he maintained by correspondence and occasional visits ir Officers to Headquar + “ V,Q therefore, suggest that the should not be allowed to die ’, and that something should ) Holman which would indicate the possibility of reconsideration 4n the-light-of future dovclopmeftts, I attach a tentative draft to Holman for P. 0 , consideration. If something of this kind is approved, you will no doubt repeat it to the Government of India. (fflrt ) E. W. R. UIMBVDraft telegram Prom: Foreign Office To: Tehran, repeated to Government of India, Your telegram No.889 of July 10th. (Proposal to appoint a senior British official to tour H.M.Consulates in Persia). 2 . I do not wish to press this proposal at the present time, but it appears from your recent despatches that Squire has already done a certain amount of touring in connection with food distribution and tribal questions, and it may well be that when present difficulties at Teheran are disposed of and Consular Liaison system is in full operation, there will be advantage from point of view of co-ordinating policy if further tours are made either by Squire or some other /member ,© 2 . member of your staff, especially if we assume direct responsibility in wheat administration (see your telegram No*895)» I suggest therefore that question might be left for further examination in light of developments. t[Cypher]. DEPART't'IEMTAL FROM TEHRAN TC FOREIGN OFFICE . .2. ■n Mr* Holman* ^’ rI ! , Hoi 895* ^•° 5 0 2o P*m« 12th July, 1942. Repeated to Foreign New Delhi . Minister of State.Cairo, 12th July, 1942. 12th July, 1942. IMIVEDIATE. Your telegram No* 987 trfcA a j-crO-d f) cAajCa, t Qjfsi Ccr^i^y^f ^ P&lt;r\*foyi~ f l/-£. ( P&amp;+fr&gt;0*r+ I have discussed proposal ! j l ? 0ff ipi ally T ^ t f o Ser n is ed States of America and Soviet col^eague^. The former i personally in favour of some such scheme provided the Persia Rnvprrimpnt ac'ree. He feels that one of the United States of America relief experts who are due here could usefully represent United Stales of America interests on proposed Board. My Soviet colleague cannot express any T 2 p lui°s che ^ e oSt submitting the matter to his Government. If the scheme is to be proceeded with, it will have to be rcierrea oy you to United States and Soviet Government. I agree that central executive power of the Board will not in itself be sufficient and the present administration, •narticularlv in the provinces, may have to be strengthed. Consular liaison officers may in fact have to be increased and Sven executive newer. We are bound to incur, unpopularity if we assume any direct responsiblity in wheat administration but we are already unpopular enough at present even though we are in no way responsible for the present chaos. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong].Jr With the Comp! i rn of the r je-»ntli'V-i R.r-r^£ M as i'k 161 - 1 - ! E$&amp;f M 1942 /- '7 n ( [Cypher] DEPARTMENTAL NO. a. FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE . Mr Holman. D. 2.30 p.m. 11th July, 1942. .r,.„ R * 5 » 50 P- m * llth July, 1942. luth July, 1942. % S*- - c c c Tin JUxet - Your telegrams No. 976 and No. 977. fij fa&gt; I do not think such an appointment necessary for general inspection. We are in close touch with Consuls who pay periodical visits to Tehran and receive frequent guidance by telegram. It would in any case be impossible to spare Mr. Squire who is indispensiole in view of difficulties over wheat. INDIV[This Docui 35 OUTWARD TELEGRAM' 6 % UJT’ ^ ' j* i s the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and sho kept under Lock and Key.] yin £t With the Compliments ;c. wUr * State E 3508/144/34. rnYPIiEHJ for Fo r* iRTMENm NO. 2. IS x r o 9 Co^ No. 976 . 3rd July, 1942, •At Do 1,05 a.m. 4th July, 1942, Repeated to Government of India. Minister ol State, Cairo No. 1451 # Bagdad No„ 652. zzzzzzz Suggestion has been made to us that a senior British official might usefully tour our Persian Consulates in order to co-ordinate and intensify the measures taken by Consuls, political officers, area liaison officers, etc., to deal with such internal problems as the collection and distribution of foodstuffs, control of the tribes, security of the roads, and the direction of our propaganda. Opportunity could be taken to endeavour to put some energy into Persian provincial administration. 2. Please telegraph your observations. REC*. FOL.ueP^I 5 Jul 942 INDfA OFFICE [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong.]AS5&amp; '' 1 405 XXX Telegram from Viceroy dated 12th June 1942. 1771-S Private and personal. My private and personal telegram 1435-3 of May 19th. Now that decision has been reached to withdraw Prior from Cairo, it is possible to pursue further suggestion for making Hay available as Inspector-General of Consulates in Persia. Prior has however asked for leave and amount of leave which could be granted would depend on whether and when Hay is required for appointment in Persia. Prior has asked for three months from July 1st, but should Hay be required sooner this could be considerably curtailed, while (omission) Hay is required at once, I diould have to consider ■whether leave could be granted at all. May I have your views to enable the Department to communicate with Prior about his leave?4- The Under itary of State, The Viceroy’s two telegrams, dated respectively April 19 th and 30 th, urging the need for a 'more positive policy” in Persia seem to have 'been prompted, firstly, by Mr, lyttelton’s memorandum on his visit to Persia; and secondly, by the gloomy prognostications of Colonel Prior who ha^ also recently visited Persia, presumably in his capacity of India's representative on the Middle East War Council, • The first of these telegrams made no specific proposal, though it suggested that a more vigorous line should be taken with regard to the deterioration of the administration and the re-organisation of the Persian Amy, But on hearing from the Secretary of State that the Foreign Office would not resent concrete proposals from India, the Viceroy, in his second telegram, offered to make available a 'highly placed officer as a kind of Inspector 'General for coordinating work of Consuls and other officers in areas under British military administration and influence'. This officer would inspect and control the work of Consuls, Political Officers add Area Liaison Officers in such matters as 're organisation of public opinion and security, distribution of essential foodstuffs, direction of our own propaganda, and checking eneiry propaganda, tribal control and so on'. His appointment would in fact be part of a plan for ^energising Persian administration in the Provinces' through the agency of the Consuls etc. After finding out, by means of informal discussion, that the Foreign Office were preijared to consider the Viceroy's idea, we wrote to them on the subject on May 13th, * * The Viceroy was at the same time told what we were doing; he has since replied thanking the Secretary of State for his support The Foreign Office letter below implies that they accept in principle the Viceroy's su gg estion. But they point out various difficulties in finding the right man for the job. &gt;«**£ and/ft -p ri propose that the question should, he discussed with bir R. Bullard, who is due in London early this month. It has always been recognised here that the success of the Viceroy^ plan would depend very largely on the personal factor, and since the procedure suggested by the Foreign Office will not result in any appreciable delay,*, draft letter is submitted agreeing to its adoption. There does not seem to be anything which we can usefully say to the Viceroy until the discussion with Sir R. Bullard has taken place. It may be useful here to enumerate the candidates whose names have so far been suggested for the post (a) Colonel Hay, at present Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The Viceroy mentioned him when he first put forward the proposal. But he added that whether Colonel Hay could be made available depended upon what decision was reached with regard to the abolition of the post of representative of India on the Middle East i/ar Council; since if it were decided that this post was unnecessary. Colonel Prior would be able to return to the Gulf Residency. (The views of Mr. Casey on whether this post should be retained or abolished are still awaited). In his latest telegram, dated May 19th, the Viceroy speaks highly of Colonel Hay’s qualificationsfor the proposed appointment. He also mentions that General Quinan has a high opinion of him; this is important since the Political Officers and Area liaison Officers, whom the Inspector General would have to supervise along with the Consuls, work under the command of the G.O.C. The Foreign Office, however, take the view that ihe appointment of Colonel Hay or any other serving Consular Officer to investigate the work of other Consuls might give rise to friction; and that it might even be necessary to have the Indian and lAvant Consulates inspected separately by members of the respective Services. (b) Mr. Sciuire of the Indian Political Service, who was recently appointed Additional at the Tehran legation.3. His name was suggested by the Secretary of State in his telegram to the Viceroy of May 11th; though he added that the Viceroy might feel that he needed Mr. Squire permanently at Tehran to keep him au fait with developments. In his telegram of May 19th the Viceroy agreed that Mr. Squire had done very good work at Tehran, but made it clear that he considered that Colonel Hay would be preferable in the new post. The Foreign Office accept Mr. Squire as a possible candidate and point out that, so far as wheat distribution is concerned, he already appears to be fulfilling some of the functions which the Viceroy has in mind. (The report to which they refer is flagged in the attached file). (c) Mr. Urguhart, the newly appointed Consul-General at Tabriz. He is mentioned for the first tiihe in the Foreign Office letter below. The Foreign Office point out that his experience as one of their Inspectors General of Consulates w eiJj, be a qualification for the new post; but that so long as the situation in Azerbaijan continues to give cause for anxiety, they doubt whether he could be spared for a tour of inspection. (From this it would seem that they contemplate that he would combine the post of Consul-General at Tabriz with that of Inspector General. ) u c~~- 0 ^ 4v— C* — &lt;^\Aa^ O-'Wv - fc (^.^ 7 . r t ^ v ) ^ kz CfJ* hsld. ^ tv tasc f UL ^ c^ert ^ j to ^ ^ d^iJr i^J[ ^ ^ ^ ts. hJ} fc if—*- L-~ fc ^ ^ q( ^ t.- l/£r^ VX-CtAy^' 1 - •&gt;-/ CL*—.EXT. 2856/1+2. BRAET LETTER. 5 JUN m 2 C.W. Baxter Esq., C.M.G-., M.C., Foreign Office. Dear Baxter, Thank you for your letter of May 28th, No. E 3022/144/34, about the Viceroy^ suggestion for the appointment of a highly placed officer to work under H.M. Minister at Tehran as a sort of Inspector General. ;ie are glad that the Foreign Office are favourably uisposed towards this suggestion^ and we agree that the question of finding the right man for the post should be discussed with BUllard when he arrives in London. Yours sincerely.PILE copy lU At. V FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 28th^T^'1040' (E 3022/144/34) ^ Ext /2856 -(&lt;a^T e -4 V*- Thank you for your lett br of IjMay (Ext.2079/42) about the Viceroy’s anxiety that positive steps should be taken to improve the Persian administration. Y, r e agree that everything possible should be done to intensify the efforts of consuls in this sphere. The enclosed copy of Bullard’s latest p.l r»r &gt; n'i to consuls shows that he nas emphasized that verbal representations to local Governors are not enough, and that energetic action to ensure the fair distribution of food supplies is essential. As regards the suggestion that a highly placed officer should work under the Minister as a sort of Inspector-General, we had originally thought of using Urquhart (now at Tabriz) for this purpose. Until he was appointed to Tabriz, Urquhart was one of the Inspectors-General of Consulates and has therefore considerable experience of this sort of work. But so long as the situation in Azerbaijan continues to give cause for anxiety, we doubt whether he could be spared for a tour of inspection. I fear that if we were to send Major Hay or any other serving consular officer to investigate the work done by other consuls it might give rise I to friction. Indeed it might be necessary to have the Indian and Levant Consulates inspected separately by members of the respective services. But this difficulty would not seem to apply to Urquhart /in lu* eU,^ / k k: R.T. Peel Esq., C.B.S., M.C., India Office. 9 K't/'in view of his experience as an Inspector-General, nor to Squire in view of his services as Counsellor at Tehran. So far as the distribution of wheat is concerned, it appears from Squire’s report of the 21st April, a copy of which has been sent to you separately, that he is already fulfilling some of the functions which the Viceroy has in mind. As the success of the Viceroy’s proposal would depend very largely on the selection ofthe right man, it might be best to discuss it with Bullard who is due here early next month. Even if we were to telegraph to him immediately he would probably have left before the telegram arrived.u ^ Su~J JtK T/V At. 107 ^ V I have spoken to Hr. Baxter as instructed and foi.uid that the Foreign Office v/ould “be quite willing to consicer the Viceroy’s idea of a touring Inspector General” to co-ordinate the work of the Consuls in Persia. ' 7/e agreed that we ^should put the proposal to the Foreign Office in writing. I made a tentative enquiry about Sir R. Bullard and Hr. Baxter told me that he is now actually in hospital with tonsil trouble. ;7hen he recovers from that it is probable that he v/ill be summoned home for consultation. Whether or not he would thereafter return to Tehran is not at present decided. I put up a draft letter to Hr. Baxter accordingly and a draft telegram to the Viceroy informing him that we are doing this. fc-AecX.1 ‘7 V 0 DRAFT LETTER. G. 7. Baxter Esq., C.M.G-., M.C., Foreign Office, S.W.l. l 3 MflY'! 9 q Our Secretary of State has asked me to let you know that the Viceroy has recently expressed his concern, which is shared by his Advisers, as to the deterioration of the administration in Persia generally and his anxiety that some more positive steps should be taken to deal with the various inter-connected problems* such as the distribution of essential foodstuffs, tribal control, security^, particularly on the roadj-.re-organisation of the Amy, the direction or our propaganda and of counter-propaganda and so on. rYhile fully appreciating the steps that have already been taken or are in contemplation to deal with these problems, e.g. removal of iihe Japanese Legation, action against Persian pro-ijcis propagandists, steps to secure American experts etc., the Viceroy is inclined to think that though much has undoubtedly been accomplished at the Centre, there is still great need for energising the Persian administration in the Provinces/Provinces. As you know it was decided some time ago that the jiigency for dealing with the Persian authorities in the Provinces in such matters as food distribution and security must be the Consuls and Sir R. Bullard has issued instructions to them as to the lines on v/hich they should carry out this work. In reply to a recent enquiry as to the working of this system, he merely said that it was generally effective but that he was reminding the Consuls of the need for energetic action. What the Viceroy is inclined to feel is that there may be a danger that this work may be left too much to be dealt with by correspondence ■ and that what is wanted is some-one to tour round and generally co-ordinate and intesify the work being done by % Consuls 3 and also'Political Officers and A,L,0*s in this t . / / sphere. He suggests, therefore, that it might be useful to appoint a highly placed officer to work under the Minister as a sort of M Inspector General' for this .purpose. If the idea were found to be acceptable and it were desired that an officer should be found from India, the Viceroy hopes that he might be able to make Colonel Hay, now acting as Political Resident/(S^.) n. P£Et Resident in the Persian Gulf, available. alternatively it occurs to us that possibly Suuire, now that the responsibility for propaganda has been taken off his shoulders, might have sufficient time to devote to the necessary touring fhe Secretary of State would be glad if the Foreign Office would consider the Viceroy^ suggestion and if they feel that it might be helpful, would put it to the Minister and obtain his views upon it.DRAFT TELEGRAM. From: Secretary of State, To: Viceroy, Dated llth May, 1942. ^ y c/v / FRIT/ATE AND FEIiSOHAL. I.Iary thanks for your XX ' — — private and personal telegram No, 1169S of 30th April. It is satisfactory^ that since you telegraphed, Bullard has reported In his telegram of the 3rd May, repeated to ^ ^ ^ y ^ ^ ^ ' you as ho. -^gOjthat food situation is now easier and that he is having useful weekly discussions on the subject with tlie Ministry of F^buice. (5n the propaganda side*, about y * s ^ s ^ y ^ — which none of us have felt happy, I understand that Childs Has now taken over in Tehran and the Foreign Office hope that his experience should enable him to~effect a real improvement. Nevertheless I share yourview that there y ^ y ^ ^ ^ y ^ ^ — is still a weakness in the Provinces and probably too nuclh tendency olf the part of our officers to deal with ^ y s' s ^ ^ current problems by correspond^'nce c Your idea of an &lt;—' ^ ' y , Inspector General to tour round and generally 'ginger up' ^ , y ^ s' ^ — the work o_ Consuls etc. therefore seems to me a good one2 S' — and I 4 m asking that the proposal should he examined by tfie Foreign Office who, I have ascertained informally, are ouite ready to consider ft. r ' &lt; ' / 2. I agree that Hay would appear to be a good choice for ^inrtur.,: ^ ^ s- ^ th^proposed appointment asswiing that decision a's to Prior male's it'possible to rel^ac him.'—' In your telegram 1085S / /s''// / ^ ^ —' yotl mentioned possibility of Bullard going. I understand , S' s' tS' ^ S' S' that he is at present iff hospital and that when he recovers s' ^ s^ ^ ^ ^ ^ He v/ill probably ‘oe summoned home for consultation. This may possibly affect consideration of your suggestioiv,for obviously the success of your proposal will depend largely . /• r / /fff r ^ *s s' s s s on the personal equation atfd we should have to make sure that tlie officer designed for the appointment would be ^ /s' / ^ ^ s s z' s '* acceptable both to the l/inister and to the G.O.C. under whom . ^ ^ S S ' s / ,s S the Political Officers and A.L.O f s Y/ork. another ^ / S'' s' s' S' ^ ' possible choice for the appointment might be Squire now that ^ ^ ^ ^ y s propaganda has ceased to be his responsibility. You may of course feel that you need him permanently at Tehran to S s f/ *' s S s s' sS' s* — ' ^ keep you au fait with developments but he might be suitable in many ways and \ r ou may like to consider tliis suggestion. S » S S / , , L * iThe Viceroy’s telegram makes it clear that he is basing his views on Persia on reports received from Colonel Prior after his recent visit. Unfortunately Colonel Prior has a tendency to exaggerate, e, g, his statement that Persia is in process of disintegration before our eyes^ and previous private correspondence from him has indicated that he has a distinct bias against the Legation Staff in Tehran and consequently is inclined to give their efforts to improve matters less than Justice, As regards the wheat situation I understand from Mr, Rumbold that Persia now hasj or will have when supplies from America now afloat arrive, sufficient v/heat to carry on until the new harvest. Telegraphing on the 23rd April Sir R, Bullard said that with the approach of the new harvest the wheat situation had greatly improved. There are no doubt still difficulties as regards distribution but Sir R, Bullard has again impressed on Consuls the necessity for energetic action. (The instructions which he issued to all Consular Officers2 . f in Persia last January will be found flagged in the attached 9 file). /is to propaganda we have not heard the results of Sir W. llonckton's examination of the problem but we may assume that he will have made some constructive suggestions and we know that the Persian Government have recently been persuaded to take effective action against a number of pro-Axis Persian - # V. * • propagandists* The Viceroy was asked to let us have any concrete proposals for fresh action which he had in mind* He now says that though much has been done at the Centre no real plan exists for energising the Persian administration in the Provinces and suggests that what is wanted is the appointment of some highly placed officer to tour round and generally ginger up the Consuls, Political Officers and A.L.O^ working in areas under British administration who are at present without sufficient drive and direction. He suggests that conceivably Colonel Hay might be the best choice for such an appointment though this would have to wait until it is decided whether Colonel Prior can be withdrawn from Cairo to return to the G-ulf as Political Resident* (in a separate telegram the Vieroy has now recommended that Colonel Prior should be withdrawn/3. withdrawn without waiting for Mr. Casey*s arrival). The Viceroy does not explain further what he meant by his offer in his earlier telegram to make changes in Indian Service personnel.now in Persia. There may be something to be said for the appointment of an Inspector-General who would be free to tour and co ordinate the work of Consuls etc. though as stated above Sir R. Bullard is evidently keeping an eye on this matter himself and it is possible that neither he nor the Consular Officers themselves would welcome the interposition of an Inspector-General from outside. There is also the point that the Political Officers and A.L.O’s are working under the Anry authorities and if the proposed Inspector-General is to have any interest in their functions it would be necessary to obtain the agreement of the G.O.C. It will be remembered that he held rather strongly in January that the agency to be employed in Persia for attempts to improve administration should be Consular throughout (see Sir R* Bullard’s telegram of the 16th January, Ext. 658 flagged). Perhaps/nT* sr M- TeJ IaM if* (if&gt; ■ Ws~ t 5 - Telegrarn from Viceroy, dated 30th April 1942. XXX - &gt;- 1169-3 v Private and personal, i-any thanks for your telegram 210.515 v t April 23rd. I most readily acknowledge Bullard^ success in getting rid of Japanese Legation and growing energy now shov/n in other directions. Proposal for American assistance in financial J and economic fields also carries my fullest agreement, and we nave been able to help this on to some extent here by convers ations j;ith Johnson. Nevertheless Prior’s reports on his tour are sufficiently gloomy. Chief items he stresses are that Persia is in worse state than ever/ previously and in processof . .disintegration before our eyes, no real plan exists to secure alleviation of wheat position and areas such as Ahwaz, closte to port, are on the verg'e of destitution; in propaganda field, he draws attention to failure to arrange for inspection and control' i oi work of Consuls and tendency to deal with such matters in correspondence. Axis propaganda particularly in Isfahan in full V blast and British propaganda everywhere failing owing to lack of plan for distnoution. A and §• All onese problems are of course closely inter-related. Bucn are reorganisation of public opinion and security, distribution of essential foodstuffs, direction of our own propaganda, xxx and checking enemy propaganda, tribal control so on. ^Though much has been done at the Centre, no real plan exists for energising Persian administration in the Provinces, and Consuls, Political Officers and Area Liaison Officers lack constant direcoion and drive they need if they are to implement policy in such matters. Argument that this would excite competitive activity by Russians seems to me wrongly conceived.-* Ii as seems probable (see Bullard's telegram No.591, April 23rd) musu agree to some Russian infiltration in ./est r nri we must agree to some Russian iniiltration in Rest and South, ig is the more necessary that we should place ourselves in a failures of Persian administration in n , and not leave it to Russians to obtain control. position to rectify subject to our influence, areas °r . thought that best means of achieving end desired migno oe oo make highly placed officer available as kind of Inspecoor General for coordinating work of Consuls and other oificers in areas under British military administration and influence and uhat hay migho conceivably be best choice for such P 0 SG .r. .p e £&gt; a ^ 1C) fi staff are naturally unable to spare anyone for consuanc &amp;nd protracted touring. Any such arrangement would, however, probably depend on withdrawing Prior from Cairo to replace hay in Persian Gulf and this in turn must depend on decision as oo ^airo post. I would exclude from purview of such a post any area under Russian occupation or subject to pre- ' ris j^tluence. Bkrine is, 1 think, himself competent * looii. cU yei iLasG Persian line, leaving to be covered areas ™ under Bntisn military occupation, Trans-Persia Railway,'the roaa to Bush ire through Isfahan and Kerman. RiVly. PajejC t f'rljni sfy [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on]. [CYPHER ]. ',7AR CABINET DISTRIBUTION FROM PERSIA FROM TKHRM TO FOREIGN OFFICE . Sir R. Bullard D. 2. 30 p.m. April 23rd, 1942. . No: 519 R.' 6 . 15 o.m. Aoril 23rd. 1942. April 23rd, 1942. Repeated to New Delhi telegram No. 220, Bagdad No. 116, Minister of State's Office Cairo No. 79. inn Foreign Office pass to Kuibyshev. Reference to D/2,616 addressed to Middle East by 10th Army. I agree that the question of policy to be adopted by us in regard to Soviet infiltration into - Central and Southern Persia needs careful consideration. Soviet Government have extended their influence by establishment of various Consular posts in that area. Moreover Russian drivers are about to proceed to Bushire to take over Lease-Lend trucks (see my telegram No. 468). Russians are already taking delivery of trucks at Andimeshk and of aircraft at Basra and have established meteorological stations at various points en route. Further requests may follow. 2 . I fully realise the danger to our position in this country from Russian penetration, but on the other hand Russians are our Allies and at this critical stage of the war we ought to give them our fullest assistance against our main enemy. Route to Persian Gulf is one of their main life lines and we should recognise in a realist spirit that this gives Russians right to use it in most efficient way. In adopting this attitude we may possibly be endangering our future [grp. undec: ?position] in this^ country but we must run that risk as it is our main objective 'to beat Germany first. Our position in Persia will depend on general world situation after the war and I therefore feel that whilst our present attitude to Russians here should be firm, as over the management of railway and against illegal activities as in regard to Azerbaijan, it should be reasonable, and not obstinate or based on pre-war apprehensions. In general our object should be to cultivate friendly local relations, trying to allay Russian suspicions which our behaviour may have done gnmRt.hi nc r to encourage and 'above all ensure that there is no excuse for Russian allegations that we are net Mgjtf t0 —- the full. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong]. Jig [Repeated to Kuibyshev under Foreign Office No. 572 of 24th April].that United ^StatJs'l Government; is now] prepared toj proceed with , programme /of/economiciand other!assistance-for Persians* H i 'III i I t 0 ^These ; developments (may jbo /some [extent affect jyour views, but I have other j linefs of- act ion! t o j sugge st i! be if you!have other, lines of’ r action to [suggest il am sure -they would carefully considered, d I ajri IdeeuLingj sex^arately Hvith your jrequest[ for| view of | Prior 1 s ^workj I presume I: 1 * I J under! reply) in viewof | his concern ohjsj I L J J mention i it in Pour tele grail member I of Piddle East War Council jwithPersian t \i findjadditional men tforl Persi to presumelyou concert sls affairs! I note I had I under stood I that this h |your (v/illingness t(^ try was ver.^ difficult matter jf or you^ but ( presume jneedj^ would jar i only Jif it jvvere ^decided tolundertake jv/id^rjfunction^ inj internal( administ rat ion ^ than |have j hitherto ibeen Considered Jpolitic| As regards jyour goffer Ito make 1 changesI in ^Indianl Service|personnel | now in ^ersiaj I am not j clear | whether you) have any/ particular! reasons foi^ thinking that/changes\ are desirable | or jhave any | specif ic| change sj in mnd.j Neither'jvve nor j Foreign Office any) reason] to| suppose jthat those [whom you Vave are not functioning satisfactorily^ have made | available^ ^ VMT. ' 03 ' , vu\l iNTEsymy y/ith mr. caroe, secretary, exteri^al affairs DEPARTMENT ON THE 21ST APRIL, 1942. &amp; PART 2. !• Reactions to the Cripps* Mission in areas dealt with by the External Affairs Department . r*.^ V. ^ •x ^ ^ ' £t,,c .s , ^ 1* Afghan s, Mr, Caroe said that the Afghans had indicated that under y,^ ^ -c- ^ ^ • \S\ - ' • proposals of this sort they felt that there should be a revision of the Durand line on the ground that the tribes on our side of the line should not be under the control of a purely Indian administration, 2, Frontier Tribes , T-^here is no visible reaction at present, but opinion of proposals of this kind takes some time to percolate, 3» Nepal, Nepal has reacted by enquiring as to the position of the Gurkhas under the Cripps * proposals, I asked whether there was any indication that Nepal was unsound on the Japanese question and Mr, Caroe * said that so far as his information went the Gurkhas in the army had fought well and were entirely loyal. He thought, however, if the Japanese were to invade North East India there might be internal trouble in Nepal, II, Persia , Mr, Caroe said that the Viceroy had approached the Secretary of State in private and personal correspondence regarding their • • it},. I-V representation in the Middle East with particular reference to Persia, The Government of India did not feel sure that the position held by Colonel Rrior on the Middle East Council was now as valuable to them as it had been. They felt that some-one with an administrative outlook was required on the staff of the British Legation in Tehran who would devote his time to visiting the various Consuls and seeing that they pushed the administrative requirements of the British Government and the Government of India, For example, where supplies of wheat were provided from India in the face of some political criticism, it was an interest of the Government of India’s to see that this wheat was properly distributed to the workers engaged on road construction etc, for whom it was intended. It is ridiculous that H.M.G. and the Government/2 . Government of India should supply wheat only to let it be cornered by speculators in Persia; Mr. Caroe thought a good deal could be done if there was an officer attached to the British Minister who ♦ had administrative experience and could stimulate the Consuls to push the necessary requirements on the local authorities. Tentatively they had in mind Colonel Hay as a possibility for such a post and if he were appointed, Colonel Prior might go back to the Persian Gulf. III. Goa. The' Portuguese are giving some trouble, for example they refuse to obscure lights or to co-operate in wireless matters on the • ground that to do so would be un-neutral and cannot be done without instructions from Lisbon. They are also refusing to accept port • dues in anything but Portuguese currency, which it is impossible to obtain, thus making it difficult for British shipping to use the harbour. There are four Axis ships in Marmagoa which are said to be about to be sold to Turkey. Mr. Caroe said that Goa was definitely a danger spot. Portuguese troops which were sent to Timor (mainly negroes) are there but* the Japanese might quite well try to seize it. It is a first class port. IV. Tibet . For the past two or three months the Government of India have been trying to open up a pack road to China via Tibet. The Tibetans are, however, being obstructive on the grounds that the gods are unfavourable to this project.Sir D ; I attach a draft private and personal telegram in reply to the Viceroy's telegram of the 19 th April on the Persian situation. I discussed the question generally with Mr. Baxter of the Foreign Office and there is no reason to suppose that the Foreign Office would resent representations from the Government of India though they point out that these will not be particularly helpful unless the Viceroy has some concrete proposals to offer for remedying the situation, which have not already been explored. As regards the Legation's staff, it is the case that Mr• Holman from Baghdad has taken over from Mr • Greenway as Counsellor and there has also been a change of first Secretary. The Foreign Office feel that these changes have been an improvement. As regards the Indian Service personnel in Persia, the Foreign Office have no information which would suggest that any changes are desirable. 2L- ^f A / / DRAFT TEIEGRAi.: » From Secretary of State To Viceroy. — BTORTAFT . Private and Personal. Hany thanks for your private and personal telegram Ko. IC 85 S of the 6r &gt; ^ ; :/Wry * _ r 7 19th April. I agree of course that position in * Persia is unsatisfactory but taking into account all the circumstances I cannot help feeling that v' CiAA^ matters might have been a great deal worse. The ex-Shah did, at least, enforce strong hand was removed it was order and When his inevitable/that there lawlessness and should be a reaction and that confusion should result. : ,To deal with such situation the Persian Government is sadly lacking taking over responsibility ourselves, which it in capable and honest administrators an4 short of U A-*- rL'.. u a. has been generally agreed we Should avoid if possible owing to difficulties in finding personnel and because we should thereby] add to our unpopularity, it is difficult to find a remedy which will produce speedy results. 2. At the same time you will appreciate that various/2; various aspects of our relations with the Persian Government have recently been energetically handled by Bullard, e.g. the removal of the Japanese Legation^and he is proposing with Foreign Office approval (see his telegram No. 47® of the 14th April and Foreign Office reply No. 5^7 of the l?th April) to put further pressure on the • . £ ► / A t 'iCv tJL k/:; VUlkJ v v Persian Government for more adequate co-operation and for the satisfaction of our requirements in regard to currency, Axis propaganda and internment of pro-Axis Persians• I have suggested to the Foreign Office that he should take the opportunity at the same time to press for improvement in arrangements for distribution r wh. of food, a question which was raised in your official telegram No. 2807 of the Jth April in regard to the situation in East Persia. You also may not have seen when you telegraphed y ^ ir -k. Bullard's telegrams Nos. 4®5 an d 4®6 of the 15 th Apr 11^ repeated to you as Nos. 205 and 206 ; in which in view of the incompetence of the Persian authorities and the weakness of the Army, he recommended the posting of two Polish divisions near/i-Uc*. * f- 1 tly' ’ near the lines of communication and an attempt to assist the Persian Government to improve their relations with the tribes. As regards the Persian Army he agrees that the best hope lies in American Advisers and the Persian Government have ^ ((VVa^— fcjcr--*'^ 44 1 |«r. in fact already asked for one American financial Adviser for the Army. Halifax has also reported that the United States Government is now prepared to proceed with a programme of economic and other assistance for Persians. 3« Possibly these developments may affect your views to some extent. Ky own feeling is that ar real attempt is being made to improve the position and I am inclined to doubt whether official ft representations from you at the moment would be particularly helpful, unless you have some A concrete proposals to offer which have not hitherto been explored. I do not however think L/h t fit that the Foreign Office would resent any representations from the Government of India if you feel that you have anything constructive to offer. 4. I note that you indicate your willingness to consider changes in Indian service personnel in/ /.4 t r*. '-*t in Persia and that you ask for Lyttelton's view of Prior's work which I will obtain. I am not clear whether you have any reasons for thinking changes are desirable, ^either we nor the Foreign Office have any reason to suppose that the officers whom you have made available are not functioning satisfactorily, and I should be glad to know v/hether you have anything specific in mind and whether you yourself are satisfied with their sources of information on Persian affairs. (f\Mj .i ^&amp; FILE COPY Allotted to Private Seo&lt;&gt; QgPJ-lig .Sir* D. Monteath. A'A/ ' © fcuo 'AAjfc USc/jr ' “^XT~I fail 20/. '--Id ! ' A /-O 26b. SECRET. XXX TEJjEGRAM from Viceroy “fB 'Secretary of State for India, dated 19th Apcril, 1942. .I MPORTANT . .1085-3 . Private and personal* I have seen Lyttelton*s report to Foreign office dated February 18th on his recent visit to Tehran. Many of the criticisms made in that report are supported in demi-official comment v/hloh we have separately had from Prior who has also just been to Tehran* 2* Publioity and propaganda points are being dealt with by MOnckton. 1 fully agree aa.to their great importance. 3* t find my advisers concerned as to whether we ought not ijto take a more vigorous line as regards deterioration of ** adminiat rati op and 1*0 organisation Of Persian Army. 1 reoognise fully the limitations of India's position in relation to Persia at present time, and though we have of course a very substantial indirect interest in it, it must be for His liajesty ; s Government to reach conclusions as to the case for our taking a more direct hand in administration, though I should welcome your ovm reactions on that matter. If however 1 can be of the very least assistance from^here, eitherby changes of Indian Service personnel or by finding-additional men I shall be only too glad to do all in my power* But realising Foreign Office susceptibilities and the faot that India's locus standi is somewhat uncertain, 1 do not wish to raise these matters offie tally save after this private consultati with you. on I gather, too that not only have the Counsellor and First Secretory in Tehran been replaced, but that there is some possibility of Bullard himself going# That I fully.realise (?may) make the Foreign Office still more touchy about criticism from outside, while the New Minister whoever he is, may want to find his feet and reach his ovm conclusions. But I know you will agree with me as to importance of a more positive policy, i£ His Majesty’s Government judgment ie likely to coincide with that of my advisers in regard to administration and army reorganisation- f Caroe has in view certain changes of procedure so far as Prior’s reports arc concerned, which will result in getting something more definite from him, and I shall bfc very ready to help him with additional staff in Cairo if nooessury* I warned Lyttelton iwhen he took over that Prior had weak, points in his make-up as well as excellent ones and it will be a great help to me if he is able to give me an entirely frank appreciation of Prior*e work and its value, We could at a pinch of course either replace him or close-down the post altogether though my Instinct, as at present advised is against closing down.n . n i [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should he retained pram is oi particular secrecy and should he ret hy the authorised recipient and not passed on] [Cypher], A WAR CABINET DISTRIBUTION , AR CABINET DISTRIBUTION. FROM PERSIA, FROM TEHlh^N TO FOREIGN OFFICE. Sir R. Bullard. No, 485 . 15th April, 1942. D. 8.20 p.m. 15th April, 1942. R. 3.05 a.m. 16th April, 1942. Repeated to Foreign New Delhi No. 205 Minister of State’s Office Cairo No. 68 , Copy to His Majesty’s Representative Bagdad, all Consuls in Persia. //// My telegram No. 424, We have now discussed the question of our tribal policy fully here. Owing to the incompetence of the Persian authorities and weakness of the Persian army it is clear that our policy of relying on the central administration to preserve order, as agreed with General Wavell last Septemher (see my telegram No. 888 or 1941) has not succeeded fully, and if further disorders occur 2. I therefore wish to make the following recommendations. (a) Two divisions of Poles evacuated from Russia should he stationed near'line of communication. They should he armed and trained as soon as possible (Military Attache has already recommended this to headquarters of 10th Amy with my concurrence). These divisions would servo, to stiffen the Persian forces if the tribes proved obdurate and force had to he used in the end. Show of strength would also serve as deterrent to the tribes and make them more amenable to compromise. will be the most difficult owing to the time needed for (a) to mature, I propose not only to press the Persian Government to ( improve on their tribal declaration but to offer the Persian Government our good offices in discussion with the tribes, in the area of [grp.undec ?Khorramshahr] where our interests may be affected, [grp.undec] grievances regarding lands. I would propose to press them strongly to agree and to let the tribes know, so far as possible, that I am doing so. Oriental Secretary knows of a number of real grievances in Kurdistan and if these and others could be remedied by a commission established under the Persian Government's recent declaration of Tribal Policy (paragraph 4 of my telegram under reference) and suitably publicised it would no doubt have a quietening effect. I have abandoned using tho phrase n good offices' as we must try to avoid undesirable responsibilities. If you approved this line I would tell my Soviet, Greek, Iraqi and American colleagues. Situation is particularly difficult in (b) In order to tide over the next few months, which /(d) [sic]^ • l^iTi 942 j [This telegram is of particular secrecy and should he retained hy the authorised recipient and not passed onj. [CYPHER] Sir R. Bullard. No. 486 . 15th April, 1942. 7AR CABINBT DISTRIBUTION . FROM: PERSIA . ■ . ! , 1 . ■ ■ ^ I I —— FROM TEHRAIi TO FOREIGN OFFICE . D, 8.20 p.m., 15th April, 1942. R. 3.45 a.m., 16th April, 1942. Repeated to Foreign New Delhi No. 206, Minister [sic: ?Minstate] No. 69. Copy to Bagdad and all Consuls in Persia. IMMEDIATE . 3 3 3 My immediately preceding telegram. Outlines of general policy regarding tribal areas, following points occurred regarding its local application, 2. Kurdistan. General Shahbakhti has himself proposed grievances (see Kermanshah telegram No, 45) and has suggested joint Anglo-Persian Committee. am not at all'sure what motives have prompted this offer as General Shahbakhti has in practice shown very little previous inclination either to co-operate with us or to appease the Kurds. Since this is first approach we have had from Persian side, however, and since it is supported by the Governor General (which may be good recommendation; I propose to sound the Prime Minister on the lines suggested in my previous telegram and say I would accept it only on the foilovang conditions: (a) Commission should be Persian-Kurdish and a # British representative would be only as friendly adviser and go-between. (b) Persian Government to guarantee safe conduct for Kurd negotiators with our concurrence. (c) Complaints of Army Department limited to questions of land and questions in connexion^with Kurdish independence would be barred. This would not prevent our taking up independently with Persia and without its being known to Kurdistan, any other reasonable complaints that might come to light. 3, Bakhtiari. Chiefs are asking for re-purchase of their oil shares as well as return of their lands and appointment of a Bakhtiari Governor, Persian Government t will presumably oppose the return of shares, Anglo-Persian Oil Companies will consider Bakhtiari chiefs have very little/little control over their Indo tribesmen and even less ovei* more turbulent ones who are causing trouble at present and that military measures by either Persian or British troops would be more, effective method of control* Return of oil shares would however give Bakhtiari chiefs an interest in order in their. : own district and even if they could not altogether prevent disorder it might discourage them from promoting it. It ..would also give us a considerable hold of them. This is most important. Would you like me to pursue the matter with Persian Government? • . .. , 4. Pars. I think we must do our’best by subversive or other means to prevent Kashgai following of Nasis Khan getting too powerful. If necessary I t think we should be prepared to help Persian authorities in this respect. [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong].at ( 2 ) Ootton and Cereals in Egypt Mr. 0, Lyttleton*s Memorandun on Persia. fy-x The following were present:- Mr. S.D. TiTaley in the Chair Mr* J.M. Keynes Mr, N.E. Young Mr. A.T.K. Grant Mr, J,S* Bromley J.Ii'. D, Davidson Miss D, Eyre Evans Mr, A,N, Rucker l»lr, E.A, Armstrong Mr. C.W. Baxter Mr. P.S. Scrivener Mr. W.H. Young Hon, E. Baring Mr. H.A.P, Rumbold Mr. E.W.R. Luiriby l»Ir. W.J. Arkell Mi*.. A,A. Evans Mrr. J.E. Wall Sir E. Benthall Miss IUT&gt;. Shufeldt Mr, J. Rea Pi*ice I'lr. J.H. Hambro Mr. G.Vf. Jone s Mr, C.W. St.J. Turner Cotton and Cer eals in Treasury Office of the Minister of State War Cabinet Offices foreign Office India Office Ministry of War Transport Ministry of Food Ministry of Economic Warfare Surplus Department. Ministry of Supply United Kingdom Commercial Corporation Bank of England. ° i f :ulated - 1^. _ Eucker”empha3i2ed' tte a!!^J h f. C ? t k n ^ cereaI negotiations separate. On uggested that the amount and kinds grown might be depe ated 'tance of it was in tvvo ways ;ton obvious difficulties owing to the^SiWoslTSxiSe! (2) by setting as soon as and an unattractive pric ootton being however. or gher sible an attractive price for cereals cotton, (that for extra long staple than tliat for long staple) taking into^^oS^^^ne^siL^r foiT ^^ ted requirements of Oiza 7 and^tter were fully met oith^ih^ 1 ^ that their requirements ootton acxre^eV It was acreed^n-f- , , lthin the overall restriction of to Cairo*as L should be Pervade the Egyptians that J^ 00 ^ 10 *. however be dimcult oot^^Taoh we d^no^eSe f° ° f “ of much in favour of a purS^e # bv Said that there WOVL2d )0th ° n P0Utical ^ 0 ®ds and because the Egyptians‘would 0 ''' 6 00tt ° n 0r ° P holdi rr . hold out against us on the price of long staple if we had not a/scheiae agreed with Egyptian Government to take all cotton. Mr. Rucl^r felt that if we did this we should have to pay a high price for the shorter staple cotton which we did not need and which the Egyptians should not grow* It was finally agreed that the M.S.S.C. he informed as soon as possible of the Ministry of Supply*s cottoj/needs of each kind and the prices to be paid (here the Ministi^of Supply should allow considerable elasticity in view of the circumstances)* If the cereals negotiations proceeded satisfactorily, a Governmental Commission to deal with the 1942 cotton would need to be discussed at a later date. On cereals the note (attached ajau circulated) pointed out the necessity for raising the production of reals in view of the shipping difficulties and the general shortage in the M.E.S*0* area* Among the points made were:— (l) Ministry of ?JeK&gt;d were interested in purchasing any rice surplus available (2) M*E.?40* v/ere interested in getting an Egyptian wheat surplus for their o#ncr territories and sufficient maize for the local Egyptian demand (3/further deficiency in one cereal would react on surplus of another. 7 For the purchase of -wheat two methods were proposed, (a) Telegram No* 88 ftom the Minister of State, Cairo, suggested (in paragraph 9) that the/Egyptian Government should be given the option of selling us the excesjr above one quantity (to be fixed by agreement) and be obliged to seliy'us the excess above a second and higher quantity* (b) The U.K*Cy5* suggestion to buy as much wheat as possible immediately after the harvest. With the stock so acquired they could quote firm prices/as buyers and sellers thereby (a) taking the speculative interest out of /the market and thus bringing out speculators hoards (b) having a reserve stock under M*E*S.C* control (c) showing by the existence of /cliis stock that reserves were adequate and thereby inducing to give export licences* If possible they wished to get an to give e:port licences from the Egyptian Government before .ses were made* The Ministry of Food thought that these open bases after the harvest would bring in the most wheat# the Egypt undertaki the purci market It was agreed that the .Ambassador should be authorised to open negotiations on the lines auggested in paragraph 9 of Telegram No. 88 and Jt a telegram on these lines to Cairo should be drafted by the Foreign i 1 ice and agreed in draft by the Treasury and U.K.C.C* II* Ll r. 0. little ton* s Memorandum on Persia* , , -^ le ne c©ssity for political reasons, of keeping up shipments of wheat (to 10,000 tons per month for the next four months), sugar and cotton piece goods had already been accepted# The meeting discussed the currency position in Persia. Our objects are (a) an increase in the rial note issue of at least 500 million, ( ) a fixed rate for rials against sterling, which should be the present rate^ of I 40 a £1 (the special U.K.C.C* rate of 170 to be retained if possible), [o) the use of sterling as backing for the currency* following inducements to the Persians were discussed, (ll inclusion in the sterling area (recommended by Mr* lyttleton), (2) a sterling subsidy (not in the indirect fonn of mai ntaining oil* royalties after 1941) (3j a payments agreement (but this might mean that we should have to make available gold in excess of Persia # s current needs) ( 4 ) a change in the rate of exchange which the Persians wished to lower* , j Mr, Grant pointed out that the difficulties in connection with (1) above were the ineffective exchange control which might allow exchangefrom the sterling area and in any case might lead by bad example to less stringent control in countries like Iraq. The Foreign Office were not certain that the Persians would welcome unreservedly their inclusion in the sterling bloc. In connection with (2) Mr. Turner felt the subsidy unnecessary in view of the large sterling balance which the Persians were known to possess, and which would increase as a result of our interests in Persia* Mr* Waley thought that this sterling might be in private hands and not the Government’s and that a subsidy to the Government might still be necessary. Sir R, Bullard should be consulted. Mr. niff was investigating the budget situation and his views should be awaited. Mr. Young pointed out that the shortage of rials might be alleviated if we accepted payment in rials and not U.S, dollars for wheat shipped trom North America to Persia, since we did not pay dollars for this wheat. Mr. Kambro thought we made payment in dollars for coramerical purchases in North America but agreed that, if the purchase was not on a commercial basis, payment in rials by the Persians should be accepted provided we did not lose dollars on the transaction. P In connection with ( 4 ) (an altered rate of exchange,) the U.K.C.C. were anxious not to lose the benefit of the better rate of 175 rials to the £ which they were getting. The Committee generally felt that it would be preferable not to alter the existing rate. Mr. Rucker emphasised the importance of having a long-term programme for all Persian questions. With regard to the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company he agreed with Mr. Waley that it was preferable to grant a direct political advance to Persia (see ( 2 ) of paragraph 1) unconnected with the oil concessions and to keep the Company on a commercial baisis, otherwise there might be political difficulties (the Foreign Office agreed). This should be mentioned in the telegram to Persia. It was agreed that the Treasuiy should draft and agree with Mr, Rucker and Foreign Office a telegram to Sir R. Bullard and Mr. Xliffk putting the Committees views before them and asking their opinion. DOROTHY BYRE EVANS.* a s. r FILE COPY ' it m« wtb ^ o ;'C Corrt«' irn [ CTEHER]. F® r ^*' FROM TEHRAN C DEI'ARUviBilTAL NO.2. 0 FOREIGN OFFICE. Uc R , * Paa£ , 5|*\Jaa C^|a*a. . v;,cmi ^ v ' T Sir R. Bullardo No*410. laroETBlst 1942 1942 D„ 9&lt;&gt;20 poin. R* 4o50 a.m. liarch 51st 1942. April 1st 1942. ^jtyjwxo oAg* vS,* Repeated saving to Kinister of State’s Office Cairo, Government of India^ ys ✓vyv. S'- S' t S\S\S\S\SK/*+*\S\Ss 1 Ymir telegram No.4 18 paragrapt |jL&lt;jlv immediately prececliNg l,alegrar.u k Ib^!^ £ Cl- 4 (Jster ling ( cAa. \^v k rax' If we could Brini our difficulties woult Persia into sterling area, many of Be removed e.g* backing of currency, supply of rials, and liability of fluctuations in rate of exchange. I do not see that Russian occupation need be # allowed to affect the decision; they carry out no financial operations in Persia, sell no roubles and rely for their supply of rials on sales of imported goods and on credits openeo by Persian Government under pressure, their requirements of rials are relatively small. I think Persian authorities might be trusted to operate sterling area system of exchange_contnel; &lt; although it might be desirable to revise the composition of taeir Exchange Contiel Commission to give more representation to banks aud also to include a British official corresponding with Loombe in Iraq. 2. Reference your paragraph 5 (rate of exchange) I agree prices in Persia are on the whole lower than prices in Iraq and that at 140 the pound sterling is slightly over-valued.^ I see no chance however of getting any direct contributipn from Persia towards cost of capital work that we are undertaking in this country and I therefore recommend that wo snoulo keep rate at 140 and so exact indirect contribution (see my Kingdom —-- — t . rate; any variation from official rate may prove awkward debaxing point in negotiations, 3. Reference your paragraph 6 (budget) I am not yet in a position to comment on budget proposals for new financial year, bulk (1 word) figures only are so far available, budget is balanced on paper at approximately o, 100 , 000 ? 000 rials by bringing in oil royalties and cutting out practically all provision for capital expenditure. I note your views on oil ^ royalties; I understand Persian Government have brought them m this year at figure resulting from application of terms of concession. [Copies sent to Mr. Jalcy Treasury and to Mr. Armstrong]. (INDIV). L P RECb. POL. Csiif-T, - 2 APR i 942 INDIA OF«CEf r\ je &gt;:t 1684 [Cypher] DEPARTItSM TAL NO.'ST V % 1 FROM TEHRAN TO FOREIGN OFFICE 942 j P' Sir R 0 Bullard No.409» Mst March, 1942. Do 9.20 p 5 m, Ro 4 C 55 a 0 Ki c 51st.March. 1942, 51st March, 1942, Repeated Saving to Minister of State’s Office Cairo (jovernrnent of India. [][][] Following for Treasury from IIiff* Your telegram No.418o ^cur. Major difficulty we are encountering in our financial relations with Persia arises from lack oi conviction on the part of Persian Government that we are going to win the war and their (Consequent mistrust of pounds sterling especially in regard to its probable purchasing power after the war. They see themselves accumulating larger and larger sterling balances m exchange for which they carrot in present circumstances obtain goods m quantities that they would like. They are reluctant to hold these balances and therefore continually press us either to guarantee them goods now or to consent to conversion into gold or silver. 2. This has been the background against which note issue n u^ 0 ?j a ^ 10ns ^ ave been carried out and my suggestion that they should make up any deficiency in their note cover by purchasing British Treasury bills was very unenthusiastically received, 3. It seems to me to be vital to future of each of our linancial relations that Persia having by treatv hitched her waggon, to our political .tar sho.ua also hitch v u waggon to our she .should adopt a line of f mane j.al'police that will denote confidence in pounds sterling. ^ * -p 4 .v^* into sterling area would he an overt demonstration ol this confidence. I doubt, however, if in present circumstances Persia would consent to enter sterling area unless we are able to exercise some form of direct or indirect pressure. As I see it most advantages from Persia’s admission to sterling area accrue, under present conditions, to us. There will be more reluctance on her part^to enter sterling area than there will be on our part.to admit her. What are attractions that would be likely to convince her ? I should be glad if you could fortify me wixh arguments 0 5. It now seems certain that if Persian Government eject Japanese Legation, United States Government will extend to Luiu^x' jjccit&gt;u~jjuiiu. scneim2 (Cs&lt; H Before this became known, my recommendations would have been that His Majesty's Government should have conveyed to Persian Government our intention that extent to which we should make essential supplies available to Persia would depend entirely on their adopting a line of financial policy that conformed to our general requirements; bui; proposed Lease~Lend arrangements will largely deprive us of the best bargaining weapon we had. It is therefore most important that, if possible^ United States Government should be persuaded to make Lease-Lend supplies dependent on Persia being [? group omitted ? a ] good boy financially, and that United States Government should point cut to Persian Government that United States could not supply goods under Lease-Lend so long as Persian Government (a; were causing grave embarrassment to defence against aggression, e.g. by denying us rials we needed to finance our war [group undec. ? expenditure] and (b) were to follow a line of financial policy which indicated no wholehearted support of Allied cause 0 7. Please seQjy^lLim^iately f-ol-l-owing telegram for replies to points raised in your paragraphs 4 , 5 , and 6 , [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong and Mr. Waley, Treasury]. INDIV.v\ p L q c py R.il.PtxA, OUTWARD TELEGRAM [This Document is the Property of t^s-Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be V.A *v&gt; rs^- - v0&gt; * ' ——r-^-r—r kept ui der Lfeck -and Key.J ' / ' g. 1828/69/34. | , . tl TTJ7 ^T S42 '0^ ’’iU. L i&gt;PHER] _ n ” —“ ’ &gt; f ! 1l[jkRTij3KTiiL HO. 2.^* ^ , FR0I,i FQKEIG-N QI^IGE TO TSIilVU. ce^ o/rfU Y*x^cw Uta 75 look (KC it Ua(K No, 418 &gt; d. 11,10 p.m. 26th uarch, 1942.^ 26 th Liarch, 194 - 2 , Repeated to Minister of State's Office Cairo No, 502 &gt; '• v Government of India id Ola t fld V*^ '‘1 1 JJJJ Following from Treasury 7 for Iliff. We have discussed with Departments concerned and with Rucker the Minister of Production's memorandum written after his visit to Persia, of which a copy is on the way to you. 2 . What we want is to secure that we can at all times obtain rials against sterling and that the rate will not be altered to our disadvantage. The total issue must be increased by 500 millions now and perhaps by more later on. It will be necessary to make sterling a backing for Persian currency and also gold re-valuation seems desirable. 3. No doubt the position should be reviev/ed as a whole so that if any jam is called for it should be administered along with the pill. It would be useful to know whetherthe Russians are experiencing similar difficulties in obtaining rials for their local expenditure, k. Admission of Persia into the sterling area. We should like to avoid this if we can, as we doubt if Persia could effectively administer an exchange control system on the lines of our own. In particular, Russian occupation of part of the country seems to create unsuitable conditions for bringing Persia into the area. We would acquiesce if this proves the only way of obtaining what we want. If Persia does not enter the sterling area we are^ not in favour of attempting to negotiate a payments agreement which would involve troublesome negotiations and a Persian demand for gold. 5* Rate of Exchange. We agree that it is undesirable to alter the present rate. On the other hand it has been suggested that prices in Persia are distinctly lower than prices in Iraq and if you vero to recommend a rate of 120 in order to take the wind out of the sails of the advocates of further appreciation and so ensure final stability we would consider it. The United Kingdom Commercial Corporation would of course like to retain the existing special rate of 175 allowed to th^io -— |R£C* POL.C&amp;f*fJ J 23 MAR 942 ‘ 1 INDIA OFFICEBudget* ie await your views on this. Increased taxation cover any Budget deficit is clearly desirable in the interests ^ Persia in order to check inflation. If any advance is found ^ tfrKjJb* necessary it should be a direct advance to the Persian Government# in sterling. We are most anxious to avoid any prolongation after 19U of the arrangement by which the oil royalties are maintained at a higher figure than that resulting-from the terms of the concession. ♦ [Copies sent to Mr. Armstrong.]Wt.l7780/P.106 6,000 6/40 A.* E W.Ltd. Gp. 685 (16146) Subject: PERSIA, Memorandum by Mr.Oliver Lyttelton. Mr.Lyttelton's memorandum, written after his recent visit to Persia,is submitted for information. On the political side he dis cusses personalities in the Perughi Government, now out of Office, (paragraph 1), public morale (para graph 2), the Army (paragraph 3), relations with the Russians (para graph 5), the Kurdish question (paragraph 7) etc. As regards economics± and financial matters, Mr.Lyttelton's recommendations were discussed at a meeting held at the Treasury on March 17th, a note of which will be found below. These papers also include notes on these matters by Mr.Rumbold and Mr.Baxter. The last two paragraphs of the memorandum deal with propaganda. /A copyA copy of the memorandum has been sent by Fast Air Mail to the Government of India, who have been asked for their observa tions urgently. We have ^so informed the Foreign Office, adding that pending receipt of the Government of India's reply we have no special comments to offer except’ to express agreement as to the imporfiince of eliminating the Japanese Legation as soon as possible, and of improving our propaganda organisation. General Lockhart's note dated March 16th had drawn attention to these and other points. t tf—) AjOv'a 1** Jj-Minute Paper. Department.(11704) \Vt.20090/l'.282 10,000 0/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 The position regarding supplying Persia with her essential needs is at the moment rather more favourable than it has been hitherto. The Middle East Supply Centre took over responsibility for organising this task on 1st March, and there are indications that under Mr. Lyttleton's control they have been able to inspire the Tehran Legation into a nore determined attempt to assess Persia's requirements than^ they have hitherto made. It now looks as if we shall be able to get to Persia almost entirely from North America very nearly as much wheat as the Legation have estimated to be essential. Sugar supplies are going to be rather difficult this side of August, but we shall probably be able to scrape up just enough for the Middle East and Persian Gulf territories. We shall also be able to give Persia from India her reasonable requirements of cotton piecegoods provided that she is ready to accept a lower quality than that to which she is accustomed. Thus, while Persia will have to keep her belt drawn pretty tight her position will probabty be a little more comfortable than it has been during the winter. The chief remaining difficulties are, I think, (a) where a conflict of interest arises between the Red Sea area and the Persian Gulf area in regard to the allocation of shipping I suspect that the Ministry of War Transport have a psychological penchant towards the Red Sea area, partly because the Middle East Supply Centre gives them very detailed estimates of what is required, whereas the estimates v/hich we get from Baghdad and Tehran have hitherto been very sketchy, and while they are no doubt no more unreliable than those which emanate from Cairo, have the appearance of^r^rther hit and miss. I think however that the Ministry of War TYansport are improving in this respect. (b) there is the problem of distribution inside Persia. I am glad to notice that the Foreign Office are instructing the Tehran Legation to press the Persians to give priority in the distribution of imported goods to areas in our occupation where scarcity obviously reacts to our detriment. There is also the difriculty that in distributing the goods Persian officials are influenced by the prospects of a rake-off, and quite apart from this are incurably incompetent. A meeting has been called at if* 15 p*m. to-morrow by the iury to discuss this pi-sblam. I understand that discussionv will concentrate mainly on the 4 sub-headings of paragraph 11 of Mr. Lyttleton's note. Purely political problems are unlikely to be raised. On these specific points I doubt if I am very competent to say anything useful although as the discussion will probably drift on to Persia's import arrangements generally I ^-iiad better go to the meeting. If Mr. Baxter does not wish also »o come to the meeting I would be very glad of his comments on paragraph 11 of Mr. Lyttleton's note. Mr.Lumby , I do not think that there is anything much that can be said on the financial side, from the special angle of this Office 7 on the points in paragraph 11. The Treasury will be in the best position to assess the various factors from the/the standpoint of the sterling area as a whole. if 3- [■ . xo-. - . .. As regards the question of admission of Persia to the sterling bloc, a usual requirement is that reasonably strict exchange control measures should be capable of imposition, but I ^gather that this is of less importance in the present instance, since Persia is about the only country left in which holdings of free sterling remain. . As regards the note issue, I think that the last thing I saw was that the local British authorities apprehended that the shortage of currency would disable them from making payments due to contractors, etc., and that it was suggested from London , that they should make the payments byenncheque, which j would not only get round the immediate difficulty but tend to enrol the contractors in the ranks of those pressing for an increase in the authorised note issue. As regards the rate of exchange, I have no independent information as to whether the present rate is the best, but in this matter the onus is always on those who would seek to alter the status quo, and if the pressure is demonstrably coming from interested quarters/' quarters that would not provide such a reason Two points arising elsewhere in Mr.Lyttelton*s V v rx memorandum may he worth mentioning. In para.7, he refers to the ’’impossibility” of increasing taxation^ without explaining why in Persia (probably alone in the world) such an increase is impossible. In para.8 it is assumed that the revenue from oil royalties will fall to £8 million. As Mr.Lumby points out, present circumstances ought to lead to an increase in production, but I gather that there is no prospect that this will lead to the royalties themselves being pushed up to anything like £4 million, and that the Treasury are unlikely to favour increasing the payment arbitrarily to that figure. I do not think there is any need for me to attend the meeting. (I have already had a word on the telephone with Mr.Young of the Treasury.) In any case, I have another meeting earlier in the afternoon from v/hich I could not be sure of getting away in time.Minute Paper. Department.information a copy of a memorandum on Persia which Mr. Lyttelton has sent to the Secretary of State. I should be grateful for any ^ comments you may have on those points in the memorandum which concern your department. I am also sending copies of the memorandum to Kirwan, War Office; Starling, Petroleum Department; Young, Treasury and Graves Law, Ministry of Information. U\W? K''v C. R.T. Peel, Esq., C.B.E., M.C., India Office. \^Krr. Leix fcECo. POL. \ V1AR 942 INDIA OFFICEo Copy. 16th F 1250 \ IQdP ^ I enclose a memorandum on Persia. ' ^?~a»-jaot quite sure hoe fully the Legation have reported on many of these subjects, so T hope you vill forgive repetitions of what is obvious. I have put in some recommendations. As they concern several uepartaents* will you make the appropriate circulation of the memorandum if you think fit? T have had to do this in rethcr a hurry to catch the bag. The Right Honourable inthony Hficn, ’£.C., M.P., etc., etc., etc., Foreign rffice, London, 5 • - . 1.* JUL .1 the rielc pf repeating ehat le eeii knomn T foreard thle aemomndue upon the situation In Persia ae it appeare to »e after a short but assiduous stud/ of it, T will divide the subject into three parte, political, economic and financial, and propaganda. A*je*o (b *c\o ** Oif'lUL • 't ^ OLAS&gt; «f C/vaI' . f ^ r fwft -1 ^ TV- ^ A. -•‘OLT^TrjAL i i. The Persian overne* nt ie seek and includes too amny ex* | Ministers, Corruption is still rife In certain ainistrlee, notably the inietr/ of Var. Fee blood and more iaportant nee l young blood le needed, and T aa sure can be found from among the? rogreat ive elements. T had »ome conversation eith the Prime inister and tec long discussions vith the inister of Finance. T 'he rime Minister ia eldely respected, but is hardly of stern enough stuff to fc ce the tlmee in ehlch he lives, lit le an admirable but rather pathetic figure rnd becomes laohrymoee when pressed, he inlster of inanc« t ifc frble and having a rich «ife probably confines himself to a small rake-off. He dealt eith me over the financial problem fairly and slth some understanding. At present the figures available on the national econoiay are •inadequate, though T think a generally true impression can be gained. The nee Minister of con muni cations is helpful end a great improvement on his predecessor. I did not have time to see him, but the director of Transportation thought him competent. n ur Pu^ vh * inister for crelgft Affairs is not • very pleasant 0 * , vi c a character and T do not share ulirrd v e rather grudging acceptance o.*i XMt '•y.. . of hi, d.fccte. ^ fU Ux he hah, vhoa sa«, appears to be an earnest youn* ?ian. He speaks French very veil and la certainly loquacious. Tf his character is seek, he appears to be free of vice. £. The bad period through vhich the country has passed, the huge capital expenditure, chiefly on buildings, &gt;aid for out of revenue during the days of the lets Shah, disturbances arising from our Invasion and the ever present fear of the Germans and Russians, have reduced the country to a lov state of morale snd signs of convalescence are not yet to be discerned. si* U t 7Ju's w 31 frtUcvfV &lt; V. to It la thus most desirable that the army should be built a at* te inhere It can play its role ^ln internal security, up — vhilet keeping its equipment and mobility lov enough t| it from becoming a menace if ear reaches Persia. The dl ficultleo are, however, that the Russians vlll hardly accept a British military Mission and thr^t Jpse financial control t the iniatr^ of er appears imperative. r esn only sxi^ ( &lt; b% that an aerlca Innnclal Adviser should be prevent appointed and that as far ee possible the Military Attaohd HVouJLl_ dt/otfi t by dj- . /shculdam v should give advice on the reconstruction of the army, which le of course modelled on French lines* r ihe Military Attach^ inf^coftd m that the ache me of reconstruction on paper le sound me th i. strength equally necessary to hrlng the gendaraerle up to 4. The greater part of the population le doubtless pro- Axle and violently anti-Russian. It Is not necessarily anti- Brttieh for theee reasons. 6. Tt is most remarkable that the soviet Ambassador, «no | A appears a good type of Russian, is told nothing by his Government and can never give an answer to a question and openly admits, when ^ pressed on any particular point, that he has no instructions* He is quite unaware, or professes to be unaware of aany of the activities of his compatriots in North Persia. This is a very serious matter and if we could by representation at the highest level alter It and secure that the Soviet Ambassador had some latitude, it would be the most useful single thing that could be done In the political field. r he most urgent problems, such as the construction of aerodromes in the Russian area, the pacification of the ] urds, the evacuation of the clee and the movement of wheat from the north to the south provinces, might then be tackled. All these are now held up by ^ussien suspicions and Russian alienee. 6. All signs point tc our fesre concerning Kusslm's intention of absorbing north arsis permanently after the &gt;&amp;r being only too j well founded. 7. he recent setback of the Persians at.ssqqls.ls serious and I agree with some reluctance *lth the Legati cm opinion that we must await the rc-establishment of the authority of the Persian Government before any serious attempt at the pacification of the rurds can be made. cnceseicns can only be granted by the strong. The bearing of paragraph 5. upon this la evident. 8. The security measures under C.I.C*?. are skill in their infancy, but T am satisfied that the measures taken are on the i right lines. There will doubtless be considerable obstruction ^ r~~ by the Persian Government over the removal of any senior officials If. and it is urgent that some senior officials should be so removed, h V. B. ECONOMIC A&gt;H3 v TNaNCTA1. 1. The economy of the country requires nursing, and It is particularly desirable to keep up substantial shipments of wheat for the next four months; 10, jOO tons per month will suffice. T have this in hand, but I hope very much th&amp;t my reccuaendetlon concerning the activities of the middle hast Supply centre In regard to Persia will receive speedy approval. (see my telegram To. 66.) tubsldiary problems arise over sugar and cotton pieoe- toods. Tf we can see th,&lt; t the people are fed arid are not in rags and that the rice of bread does not rise, we shall probably avoid bad trouble as long as the Germans do not invade Persia. fc. There was some immediate currency crisis due to the inability of the banks to provide riel notes against our /impending ‘U-CtfKMtvfi/rvJ ~ T TkTxsA t &amp;£&amp;*-) ^ zl \©I [ ispondlng salts of sterling* T here eolved this temporarily by persuading the minister of : 1 nance to Issue the balance of the authorised note issue amounting to Rials 150,000,000• 7k*i (S (Jjv/I*. dj Ir dm by 1 * ■^a&gt;a^ NUVm ^ i^c^&gt;vCcr&gt; V\tuO o IS fa- H -M - ^ • 5* T cannot go far Into elUier the financial or budgetary problems because at present the informa tion is too fragmentary* T can, however, say that there sp ears to be s rough balance ever the next few months between our disbursements of sterling end Persian requirements of sterling for the purchase of wheat, sugar and sundry other commodities* 4 * A Financial Adviser Is urgently required In order to collect comprehensive and more accurate data* t do not feel aur* that the best course would not be to appoint Major rhlsholm to this post, although I Know that Mr* Iliffe is on his way* T happen to know Aajor Chisholm and regard him aa able* He had had seven or eight years pre-war experience of Persia and knows most of the ministers and officials Involved* Vhi1st T do not press for It, T think that the appointment of Tllffe should at least be reconsidered* T could probably use him elsewhere* 5* n the figures thft T have It appears quite possible that sterling credits or even a sterling lorn will become necessary, but further Investigation of all the facts am si precede any discussion of the subject. 6* As an immediate measure T should recommend that an Invitation to join the sterling bloc should be extended to Persia* £uch an invitation will be welcomed, but it will of course raise two immediate issues; first an increase in the authorised note laeue and secondly the rate of exchange* At present the rate of Rlala 140 to the £ is much criticised, especially among the mercantile classes, who are naturally most insistent because a lowering of the rate would fill their pockets* It Is quite true that the rate was arrived at in an arbitrary way, but T should require s good deal of convincing that it was uhfeir* Another reason for leaving it where it is Is that I aid sure that a lower rate would not be reflected In a lower cost of living* then I saw the rime minister and the inlster of Finance on thle subject T preserved our negotietlng position as far as possible by saying that T could he id out very little hope of ay colleagues being willing to reconsider the rate* hinted furthermore that I should find difficulty in getting the full support from Kis Majesty*s Government ever shipments of whort and sugar if we were to be asked at the si me time to move the rate against ourselves* 7. budgetary position is sold by the vinister of Finance to be as follows: expenditure Riels 4,000,000,000 Revenue * 8,000,000,000 The low receipts from customs end the impossibility of increasing taxation will keep the revenue to the figure named. T am not in a position to say whether the figure of /expendltureI expenditure Includes large suns on capital account as it has In the pasty and the vthole budgetary osltlon *111 require detailed analysis by the Financial Adviser. 8. The position Is naturally bound up to some extent with t hegn estlon of oil royalties. The production of /badan has, figuresy fallen from 10,000,000 tons to 6,000,000 tons ptjr nnum, and the revenue to be derived by the Persian Government from this source will consequently fell from about £ 4 , 000,000 p«r| annum to ££,000,000. jjrvodlucAovv Ifr &lt;3L|-oloy\T 9. At present the railway is operated under British control up to Tehran, and both the north east and north western sections are under the Russians. Already con*,cation Is beln £j paused ' tibeoau se the Russians are not operating these two brands efficiently. Tt is said thrt 400 Russian technicians are on their way. The diversion of railway operating staff to the Far . ast would have made It Impossible for the director of ranaportation to have operated either branch, but T cannot help viewing with some dismay the control which Russia has succeeded In obtaining over this lateral communication In Iforth ; ersla. The traffic on the I.railway from the south to Tehran hae been Increased from 800 to * | 1,800 tons per day and rlthough we shall fall p&lt; rheps 6 to 8 weeks 'behind the programme, T believe th&amp;t the target figure of S,4Q0 tons per day will be attained* 10. T nternal civil transport by lorry is « matter of some ^ anxiety. At leae^ we should keep up the supply of spare parte and tyres for the existing fleet, or otherwise there will be a breakdown in the distribution of food. I shall make a separate recommendation on this subject. 11. To sum up on the f^anclel problems T feel strongly that a comprehensive plan embracing all aspects of the subject should be framed as scon as possible. ,Tt should comprise, T suggest: (•&gt; (b) (c) ( 4 ) Admission of ?ersta to the sterling block; An increase in the authorised note Issue bsyond the present maximum of ials' 2,000, XK),000, though net of course sn actual increase in the note Issue until It becomes necessary; Fixing the present rate of exchange; A decision as to whether the Anglo^lrsnian Oil Company is to adhere strictly in payments of royalty to their‘ present agreement. Tf they do. It is all the more probable th.t sterling credits against purchase of staple commodities will become necessary. T regard the liaison man tain ed : $ween the legation and the Anglc-Tranlan Oil Company as unsatisfactory. T think that considering the holding of Bis Majesty’s Government in the A^glc- Iranian Oil Company and tne gre* t part that the Company |ieye in the national economy of Kerala, a common policy should be agreed In London. Perhaps this has been done, but it is not evident in Persia. T would go as far as to suggest that some Increase, but not all the difference in the royalty, might feirly be borne by Anglo-lranlan oil Company because of the company’s intrinsic interest in the stability of the country. n this subject there la something to be said for calling upon Mr. Hies to come home for any discussions /that• EXT 1250 p IKjL ' hx ^ aj 0HJL *1 (U. d^j- 'WtXkva ^ -{&lt;d&lt;L Q/r*f • aJbxJud (fr-bt' W ** 1 1 that arc Inltlatad het^cen Hla Hajeaty’a Oorern^tnt and the company* | IS'? 12. It la Quite obvious that both the rime Inlster and the minister of Finance fear that increases in the note issue, fixation of the rate of exchange end cognate proposals *iH [be rejected by the uejlis. his is another reason*!? • comprehensive plan is necessary and that the syrup should be administered at the sane time as the physio. C. PROPAGATOR ^ We have s greet deal of say to stake up and the pre sent Ltaff is inadeQUatt for^Jth# task. German and Japanese propaganda is vary widely spread and its poison is in the veins of the country. *ihe scheme which wae drawn up by for. i^ee Ashton on a recent visit aeeas on the right lines, but little has yet been done to n&amp;lce it effective. A first rate director of the propaganda organisation should be sent out at once. Mr. Calvert, will, according to my informetion, not i ill i is rOie, though he will be of great uaa In a secondary position. Sir falter Monckton Is taking up these and a number cf subsidiary points, and I urge that immediate action should be taken on any of hi a recommendations. In conclusion I may &amp;ay that I pressed the Prim* minister very strongly on the subject of the Japanese Legation end said that His Majesty^ Government could only regard as ludicrous a situation in which subjects of a country with which we are et war, should be left to carry on activities against us from the sanctumry of sn Allied country. I said that T expected to hear that action had been taken within a few days and hinted that His Majesty’s Government would take a very serious view of any delay. The excuse tor inaction, which I politely demolished, was tlu t the rupture of relations with Vichy had caused the political crisis in 5 gypt. Cairo. 15th February* 1942.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3682</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3682</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/105 'Proposed appointment of an Inspector General for Consulates in Persia: including Mr Lyttelton's memorandum'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-28T14:45:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (37 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 38 ; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the proposal to appoint an Inspector General for Consulates in Persia, and includes a memorandum by Oliver Lyttleton, Minister of State in the Middle East, concerning his visit to Persia (folios 63-67).The file is composed solely of internal correspondence between the Viceroy, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the HM Legation at Tehran, the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Secretary of State for India, and the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister of State Resident in the Middle East</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Employment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>