<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000377_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-08-15T11:28:39.663Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">%CONFIDENTIAL. No. 26-S of 1936, POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL hECORD 2 2 JXV 1936 K'-ir. No ^2.0 3. 3 . :rs - : &lt;*{^ 0 * 1 , The Hon’ble the Political'Hesident in F^iMlun Ollll 1 presents his com pliments to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. J and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment WCONFIDENTIAL. No. 98-S of 1936. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, 3. The Political Agent, Muscat ¥ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document V*^\Residency Printed letter No«26-S of 8th January 1936. POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD • —» *■ IW IJ, f[p &lt; H. 3 . JPS GONStllATI; MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 8th ^ebrufiry 1936. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. LetterUo.174/2/36) «ated the 25th January 1936 from Chancery, British -Embassy, Bagdad. Subject. Nuri Pasha^s visit to the Gulf.Copy. (174/2/36). British Embassy, Bagdad. 25th January 1936. Dear Residency, V Your letter No.25-3 of 1936 dated January 8th. About a fortnight ago Nuri Pasha’s s 0 n was very seriously injured in an aeroplane accident. For this reason we think thrt Nuri Pasha’s visit to the Persian ^ulf is likely to be indefinitely post poned. We will, however, bear in mind your wish for the longest possible previous notice if there ever appears to be a probability of his reviving this plan. Yours ever, The Residency, BUSH3RE.&lt;3 A- —&amp; ; f f P.Z. 3181/36. AIR MAIL• INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.7. 1. 13th June 196 6. ?^gdad despatch of bi’d April, No. 163. / y I enclose a copy of a despatch from Bagdad about a tour of Iraqi notables to Syria, Palestine and Egypt. You will see that mention is made, in paragraph 5 of the despatch, of a similar tour to the Arab principalities of the Persian Gulf. If you happen to hear anything about this project or have any observations to make, you will no doubt communicate with us* I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Caroe, Watts, de Gaury and Hickinbotham. Youre (Sgd.) Nl. J. CUVJSJN Lieutenant Colonel T.C.Fowle, ^ C. B. E. , Consulate General, Bushire.v : r&gt;,- r ‘&lt;WG ETTER JR SIGN OFF5Of _ r 8 M W 1956 iD P.2. 3181/36. No. 163. (294/8/36) BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD• 3rd April 1936. Sir, With reference to my despatch No*101 of February 24th, I have the honour to inform you that a party of fifteen Iraqi senators, deputies and notables left Iraq on March 9th for a visit to Syria, Palestine and Egypt, and returned to Bagdad on April 1st. 2. You will no doubt receive from His Majesty's representatives in these countries full accounts of the events which marked this tour. Judging, however, from the reports which have appeared in the Ira-pi press, it was a great success. Everywhere the Iraqis were made much of, feted and most hospitably entertained. 3. For their part, the visitors worked hard to make the most of their opportunities to strengthen the religious and social ties which link Iraq to these sister Arab countries. They made innumerable speeches in which they stressed the fundamental unity of the Arab peoples and pledged the help and sympathy of Iraq to all their brother Arabs in the struggle for independence which Ira^ had herself won. 4. In some instances, the zeal of the speakers outran their discretion and an oration delivered at Nablus by Said Thabit, a deputy for Mosul, appears to have been particularly violent and provocative. I have remonstrated with both the Prime Minister and Nuri Pasha about this speech and have warned them that Said Thabit's conduct The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P., etc., etc., etc* may/may make it difficult in future for Iraqi visitors to obtain from the authorities the courtesies and facilities which this party enjoyed. 5» There is now talk in Bagdad of return visits to Iraq hy groups of influential men from Syria, Palestine and Egypt, and of a tour of the Arab principalities of the Persian Gulf by another unofficial delegation of notables from Iraq. 6. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s High Commissioners at Cairo and Jerusalem, His Majesty’s Minister at Jedda, His Majesty’s Consul-General at Beirut and to His Majesty’s Consuls at Damascus and Aleppo. I have, &amp;c., (Sgd.) G.H. BATEMAN.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000377_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/176</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000377</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/176</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/36 Foreign Interests: Iraq Minister's proposed visit to Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-29T22:21:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-9; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of correspondence between British officials regarding a proposed visit to Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat by the Iraqi politician, Nuri Pasha [Nūrī al-Sa‘īd].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>State visits</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000377#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>