<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003aa_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T14:58:19.808Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003aa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/31</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003aa</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/31</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Final fair copy of a journal of Lewis Pelly's official journey overland from Persia to India through Afghanistan including Mashhad, Herat and Kabul.</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1860/1860</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-29T00:18:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (238 folios)</extent><extent>The journal entries are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: Foliation runs from the first to last page, using circled pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. The following foliation anomaly occurs: 237a.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Fair copy of the journal taken from both the handwritten journal kept by Lewis Pelly on his journey (F126/30) and the draft fair copy of the journal which contains corrections and annotations (F126/31)Journal of the journey which the British Government requested that Lewis Pelly take overland through Persia and Afghanistan in returning to India in order to ascertain the situation throughout the country, to visit the rulers of key places such as Herat and Cabul [Kabul] with a view to the re-establishment of British relations with them, to attempt to gain a sense of how the British might now be received there and to attempt to ascertain details of the Persian expedition to Mero [Merv].The journal covers the period 10 September to 16 November 1860 and documents the geography and landscapes of the regions travelled through, with where known the names of hills and plateaus, the locations of water sources and the distances between each place visited and the overall distances travelled each day.For each village, town or caravanserai visited Pelly recorded its size, any known history, information on the local ruler and his allegiances, observations on trade and agriculture, with particular interest paid to gardens and orchards, and the hospitality they offered to him at each stage of his journey.The journal also records the people who travelled with him, the equipment and provisions they took with them and the gifts and letters they had been requested to take and present to various local rulers.Information of particular interest within the journal includes details of the situation in Candahar [Kandahar] and Cabul his conversations with the Khan of Khaff [Khaf] about England, his visit to Herat and discussions with the ministers and ruler there information on the Turcoman's victory over the Persians at Mero including Pelly's intentions of aiding the Prince Hurnza Mirza [Hamzeh Mirza "Heshmat ed-Dowleh"] and desire to rescue a French photographer who had been travelling with the Persian forces, the Sirdar of Sebpur's plans to seize power in Candahar, a meeting with some Russians travelling in the area, and the civil war in Seistan [Sistan], information on the official reports that Pelly submitted to Government during his journey and an ink sketch by Pelly of a post house similar to the ones he stayed in during his journey.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Governor of Herat</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x0003aa#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>