<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-18T10:43:00.560Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Extract from 'Lupin s Report Eo. 168/25/2 dated 25th ^uguet 1930 to the Senior Naval Officer,P.G# t H.M.S#'Triad' ( received under letter No.11/510* dated let September 1930 from the Senior Naval Officer,P.G. f H.M.S’.’Triad' at Henjam* 11. The Shaikh of Bahai said he had had a letter v from axaikh Ahmed of Khasab complaining that Sayid ao.ik, the Sultan of Muscat’s Wall of Khasab* had issued an order that all disputes involving sums greater than Rupees 5 were to be brought before him, Sayid alik* and rn . the Shaikh, and that Sayid Malik took half of any sum paid in settlement, and that this was causing discontent among the Shihuh. 12. Shaikh Ahmed also said that if trouble broke out as a result of this he should inform the Sultan of Muscat that he didn’t wish to remain Shaikh of Kh&amp;sab and should abdicate.ft V /T\ 4 ; d) 3 No.K/ $0 of 193C. J Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate,Muscat. Recess Office at Karachi. 27th September 1930. Cr 1 Cs^ y jJU? cJ &lt; To The Council of Ministers to His High ness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; O^an, Muscat. • /^ V After Compliments. I have the honour to forward herewith copy of an extract of a report sent by H.M.S. Lupin to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, for information. This is what had to be said and salaams. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.x x X X X Extract from letter No.202/25/D. dated 6 tU Septemder 1930 from H. K. S. 'Lupin', Henjam (received under cover of S. N. 0*s. submission No.13/619, dated 12th September 1930 r~ With reference to paras. 11, 12 and 13 of M Lupin’s' ^ c a letter. Said Malik is reported to have made 50 new laws jpi Lllcl'l o\-y* - while he was V/ali of Khasab, and to have extorted money from the merchants. 9. It is understood that a new Wali has now arrived at Khasab, and that he was requested to repeal the new laws, but replied that he was unable to do so himself but would write to the Sultan of Muscat. 10. On leaving Khasab Said Malik is reported to have forcibly seized three female slaves and to have taken them away with him. 11. The information contained in paras. 3, 9 and 10 was supplied to the Sheikh of Cabal and the Residency Agent by a native of Kumzar named Suliman (this man is well known to Mr. Thomas, Wazir to the Sultan of Muscat). It is considered that it is probably founded on fact but grossly exaggerated. 12. The Sheikh of Cabai stated that on three occasions he had received information that the Shihuh intended to rise against Said Malik, but that he had advised them to « take no action and had written to the Sultan of Muscat concerning it. 13. The Residency Agent also reported that it was rumoured in Cabai that on Said Malikas return to Muscat recently in the Muscat Vessel “Al Said”, he had called' at Cibah in company with one of H. M. Ships, and that Sheikh Saleh of Cibah had refused to come on board. The Residency Agent was informed that the rumour as to the i presence of one of H. M. Ships on this occasion was untrueX V Telegrams From: To: Unnumbered* Dat ed : f) ^ ir- j En clair. Senior Naval Offleer,Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. H Triad n . Political Resident, Patrick Stewart. 24th November 1930. /“* 'Ormonde's” proposed requirements as to landings are as follows:- ,7th December: 28th November: In Jabel Shaam - land one officer for 2 days. Camp to be established on Little Q,uoin. 2 officers and 3 men, some of them will remain for a month. Musandam Island Umalfayarin Island sheltering Khor Khawi. If you consider that Muscat Government should send letters to these places, would you please arrange and detach 'CYCLAMEN' to deliver them from Muscat as convenient. - S. M. 0. - U'Xs Co-ri-Cf r lii. u. ^' U-.' CH^U' , fr Uv-CAj^ O (\' CIff * % m The Commanding Officer, ■FOLKESTONE', at Muscat. 12th January, 1931. The Political Agent, Muscat. The attached signal has been received from H.M.S. ■ORMONDE*. I will be glad to make any reply that you may wish to send.1 Telegram From Ormonde To Folkestone Signal addressed to Council of Ministers Muscat From Wali of Khassab. Sheikh Khasab Ahmed Mohamed died at Dobai. What about Khassab* i ti». t* &gt; Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'a Coneulate, Muecat^the 13th January 1931* Tc The Council cf Hinisters, Muscat* «P 1 /u A* C • I have the honour to inform Your Honours that T have received a copy of the wireless telegram sent by H.M.S.'Onnande' through H.M.S.'Folkestone' on behalf of the Wall of Khasab to you reporting the death of Ahmed bin Muhamed, Shaikh of Khasab. I have also received a telegram from the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf informing me of the sad incident and enquiring whom the Muscat Govern* ment propose to appoint as Shaikh in place of the late Ahmed bin Muhamed. In the circumstances I shall be glad if you will please inform me whom you propose to appoint. U.E. C 0** Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's consul, Muscat. '• • K' A* 1 . •-'A ' qm/ 4 /'12- Khasat through H. !. T . S. ” FOLKEST OKS ” informing us of the death of Shaikh Ahmad bin I r ohd., Shaikh of Beni TTadiyah at Khasab. You have also mentioned that you have received a telegram from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf iniorming you of the sad occurrance and enquiring about the name whom the Muscat Government intend to appoint as Shaikh in place ‘of the late Shaikh Ahmad bin Mohd. V/e beg to state that v;e would like to send a communication to Muzaffar Sulaiman, T .Yali of Khasab, enquiring from him as to the man whom he thinks suitable to be appointed at present in place of the late Shaikh. Please send the message by wire to him if it is possible so that Ve may get an early reply from him. As to the individual Whom we intend to appoint as a Shaikh on Bani T Iadiyah at Khasab, we are of opinion to xKiai select one from Bohha among^ &gt;.he members of the deceased Shaikh’s iamily i.e. one of his brothers or cousins. ^he new Shaikh will be selected there in the presence of one of / I u* l ' J 4 ^ ^—T ^ the members of the Council of Ministers. U.S.Telegram Code. From Political, Muscat. To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 110 Dated 20th January 1931. P 7 Your telegram No.31 Council propose asking advice of Wali of KHASAB on subject. If •'Ormonde” or sloop is in vicinity of Khasab they v/ould be grateful if Wali could be asked by wireless to save timeZl-l-ll (g) Code H.M.3.Cyclamen Henjam itadmo Political, Muscat. Dated 21st January 1931 Immediate. Have you anything to communicate to Wali Khasab if so please reply at once 07.25 21st January Cyclamen ./ Telegram Prom To Enclair. • H.M.S.Cyclamen Henjam Radio Political, Muscat Dated 21st January 1931 iLjnediate. Wali Khasab now on board Cyclamen. To expedite exchange of communications suggest transmission direct by R.A.F.W/T if this is possible 0925 CyclamenTelegram Code. From Political, ITuscat. To ’♦cyclamen” Henjam Radio. NO- I / ^yt) 2 ^ Bated 21st January 1931 Your telegram of 21st Following from Council of Ministers to Wall of Khasab begins, please let us know whom you would suggest in place of late Shaikh Ahmed bin Muhamed ends Grateful if you could send reply by wireless. ITelegram From XxoucxTo Cyclamen Hen jam Radio Political Muscat Uated 21st January 1931 Your 0630/21. Wall recommends Hilal bin Ali and reports that his appointment would be acceptable by the people. He will remain on board Cyclamen for any further communication and shall be g£ad if you will inform me v»hen you have nothing further to communicate. 1045Lett Muses W€ behalf and read Wall of in your I appoints that weLetter No,95 dated 21st January 1931 from the Council of Ministers Muscat to Mhj or T.C.i’ov.le, Pol.Afc,ent &amp; H.L.M*s Consul, Muscat. We have the honour to ihform you that Mr. Abdul Latif came on your behalf with copy of reply from Wall of Khasab. We took a copy of telegram and read its contents, ^e request you to send another telegram to the Wall of Khasab as follows:- * We appoint Hilal bin Ali who was mentioned in your telegram as a temporary Shaimh of Beni Hadiyah. ** Reference the Political Resident’s question as to who is going to be appointed as Shaikh in place of the deceased Shaikh you may now inform him that we have appointed Hilal bin Ali as temporary Shaikh for Beni Hadiyah.Telegram Prom Political, Huscat. To Cyclamen Dated 21st January 1931 h Ji Following from Council of Ministers for Wali of iliasab begins Je appoint Hilal bin Ali wno was mentioned in your telegram as temporary Shaikh of Beni Hadiyah ends Nothing further to communicateTelegram-Code From Political,Bushlre, To' Political, Muscat, No.53. Dated &amp; Received 21st January 1931. A&gt; Your telegram No.110. H.M.S.'’Cyclamen” now Khasab; please communicate with her direct via Henjam Radio.Telegram Code. From Political, Muscat. To Britcongul, Bushire. Bo. 16) Dated 23rd January 1931. Your telegram No.53. Communication made through M Cyclamen M and on suggestion of Wali of Khasab HTLAL bin ALI appointed temporary Shaikh.Translation of a letter dated 25th Babi al Than! 1350 (9th September 1931) from Saiyld Said bin Taimur, President of the Council of Ministers, Muscat State, to Captain R.G« Alban, I.A., Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. After Compliments. With reference to my Tlsit to Khasab which I was able to make through your assistance in one of H.M.S. Ships at the end of the last month, I take the opportunity of expressing my thanks to you. I reached the place and as I had already been informed found it peaceful and the people loyal to the Government of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Knquiries were made as to the appointment of a new Shaikh for the Ban! Hadieh tribe in place of the late shaikh; this however was postponed pending my return to Muscat where I could better judge as to the most efficient among the Shaikhs of the Bani Hadieh for the appointment. A temporary Shaikh has been appointed, but when a permanent ane is selected, the Wall, who is representing us there, will be advised accordingly. There is nothing further to write in connection with this my journey but that affairs are satisfactory and it is hoped that there will be no further incidents. In conclusion I express my thanks to our Honourable Friends the Government for the assistance rendered in subjugating the rebels last year and restoring peace at Khasab. We wish that their assistance and favours towards the Government of the Sultan may continue and our friendly relations be strengthened. I Ho.C-223. Political Agency and H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat, the 29th September 1931. Copy forwarded to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for information. n ' Captain, Political Agent and H.B.M'b Consul.-^&lt;r A - 7-3 2 U) rrom To iso. 21-b* or 1952* .British nesmency ana Consulate-general, bushlre, the 16th January 1952. The tsecretary to the Hon*ble the irolitical nesident in the jrersian Cjulf, The political Agent, mus c at. Sir, i am directed to inform you that during the Honourable the political Kesident*s recent tour on the Trucial Coast Shaikh baid bin Maktum of uebai made representations to Colonel Hiscoe regarding shaikh Hasan bin uuhammad of Khassab, and stated that if the Muscat State would allow shaikh Hasan to reside at Debai he ( Safe Shaikh said; would undertake that he would not return to hhassab. Colonel uiscoe mentioned the matter to the i-resident of the Council during his visit to Muscat, and the latter said that if shaikh said would enter into a formal agreement that he would be responsible for shaikh Hasan, he was willing to allow him to go to uebai, which incidentally would save the muscat State his maintenance charges, xhe Honourable the Political Kesident has therefore obtained a written under taking from Shaikh Said to the above effect, a copy of which i enclose herewith, i am to request that you will kindly approach His Highness the sultan in the matter and, if you see no objection, ask £im to arrange to send Shaikh Hasan to uebai. i have the honour to be. Sir, lour obedient servant. tor secretary xo the Political nesiaent, jr-uuif.iranelatlon f .better dated the 12th ahaban 13b0 v = ^52na jiecemoer 1931) from shaikh said bin Maktum, nuler of i^ebain, uibai, to the non*ble hieut.-Colonel n.v. niscoe, political Kesident in the jrersian uulf, nuahire. After Compliments. i beg to confirm my conversation with your honour in connection with shaikh Hasan when x requested you to give permission that he should leave Muscat and come to me in uebai, and this you promised \to do;. i now beg to trouble you hereby regarding this matter and hereby give you and nis Highness the Sultan of Muscat a complete undertaking and assurance that the Bald Hasan will never go to iihasaab and that he and his family will be made by me to reside in uebai And that they will send an agent to look after their date trees in Hhassab. i therefore request you kindly to make me grateful by conveying permission for his departure from there and to come to me in uebai.Political Agency and H• B. 1/’s Consulate, Muscat, 22*) February 1932. To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. A. C. As I informed Your Highness verbally the other day, T received a letter from the Hon’ble the Political Resident, with which he enclosed an undertaking from Shaikh Said bin Maktum of Debai to the effect that if Muscat State would allow Shaikh Hasan bin Muhammad of Khasab to reside at Debai he, Shaikh Said, would undertake that Shaikh Hasan would not return to Khasab. Your Highness informed me verbally that you had no objection. I enclose a copy of Shaikh Said’s document. Would Your Highness please arrange to send Shaikh Hasan to Debai. U.E. Lt-Colonel, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul.To Isb (3 Lt-Colonel T.G. Fowle, !I.BJ rt s Consul and Political Agent, Muscat. •1 \ Bated 21 st Shawal 1350 (29-2-32). After Comalients. At an auspicious dour I received your letter So .30 of 22nd February 1932 enclosing coj*»y of a document from Shaikh Said bin Faktum of Behai which contains his undertaking about Shaikh Hasan. I have already pointed out to you that I have no objection to Shaikh TIasan bin Muhammad A1 Shihhi’s residing at Debai, if the Shaikh of Bebai undertakes that he would not return to Khasab. As he (Shaikh Said) has now undertaken I shall send Hasan to Bebai by tomorrow’s mail as desired by you accompanied by a man on my behalf. Your sincere friend 3d/ Said bin Taimur9 S *\ . . • S. 1320c. Naval s ’ For use Call in Signal Department only. TO: Text and Time/ T# Sir, / H#.C- /Afif of 1932« The Political Agency 3b H*i3.^ ! a ConauX^ta, Muscat, 27th July 1*32. 3^ owing to a dispute among the Shihuh tribe amen of hasab and Diba with regard to the appointment *£ a new j ^ Sheikh at Diba, ihe Council of Regency, Muscat State, desire to depute a party of 3 men to Has-el*Jab*.I* The Council state that they h:vre learnt that a sloop i* proceeding to Biba. In these circuit*tanceu i have the honour to enquire whether arrangements could kindlyue made to convey the party to Diba leaving one of the men at ;chasab, if possible. I hare the honcur to be. Sir, Your most sbodient servant. Treasury Officer, In the absence ef the Pel.Agent ^ H.B.M's Consul. The Cemmander, H.M.S. ^Shereham' Muscat Harbsur.v/ H.M.S/'Shoreha'ii' Muse it. znh July 1932. Sir, f 7 V/itli reference to your letter of toclay f s date, will you please inform the Council of Recency, Muscat State, that I shill he very pleased to convey their representatives (3 in number) to Dibbah. 2. H.M.S. ,, ShorehaIIl ,, './ill be sailing from Muscat at 2 p.in. tomorrow, Thursday, and it is requested that the representatives may be informed that they should embark by 2.30 p.m. 3. As regards disembarking one of the representatives at Khasab, would you please inform the Council that I am ^ unable at the moment to say definitely whether or not I can comply with this request. 4. According to my present instructions I am to proceed direct from Dibbuh to Henjam arriving there 30th July. This representative could therefore in my case be carried to Hesjam whence he could doubtless arrange a passage to Khasab in some local craft. I am however requesting permission to make the necessary alteration to my programme so that I may call at Khasab, and I do not doubt that this will be approved. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your Obedient Servant, •V' The Treasury Officer, The Politic xl Aeeucy md H.B.M.CoBsalrte, Muscat.S*.0-146 *f 1932. The Pelitical Agency b H«2«M 9 a Cenaulate, Muscat, 27th July 1^32. fa The Ceuncil ef Regency Muscat State* With reference te ytur letter N#*3» dated the 26th July, 1 forward for your information and necteoary action a copy of a letter dated the 27th from the Commander of H.M.S. 'Shoreham' with regard to the 3 reyrooentatiTeo to te conveyed to Dibbah. This lo what had to be said and aalaamo* Treasury Officer, in the absence of the Pol.Agent &amp; H.B.M 9 a Consul.The Comiii in din s Officer, B.M.S. 'Shorehim' 28th July 1052. The Treasury Officer, Muscat State. P w With reference to my comutiBication and our conversation of yesterday, I am now ible to confirm that I shall be ible to convey one of the Stated representatives to Khassab as requested by the Council. Would you please infonri the Council accordingly. Com. tander-in-Command. - 1^gfcNr-- ^ Fvm T« N*.C- /M'S ft 1932. Xhe Ptlitical Agency ^ H.B.K* ■ Ctnsulate, Muscat#23th July 1932. The Treasury Officer# In the Abs.sf the Fsl.Agent &amp; Consul The Csmmanding Officer y H*M«S«' , Shsrehaiii M Muscat Harbour* -e no rand um* 77 G Reference yeur memorandum ef even date f the Ceuncil of Regency have been infermed that their representatives will # be conveyed to 3ha8«ib* Thear names arei- (a) Sheikh Ibrahim bln Mehamed bln Juma# Muscat State official# (h) Salim bin Sahar, Muscat State official# (c) Saiyid bin (hamie# servant ef the above The first two I think are entitled to 2nd class ilietlng* 2. The Ceuncil further request that, in case the representatives find that their presence is not necessary in Dibbah# they may kindly be conveyed to Khasab* 4&gt; A^l 3 . A copy of a telegram dated the 27th July# received from the S.N.O.,Persian Gulf, is enclosed for your information. * t ( 11 &lt;' Treasuryb Officer# In the Abs.of the Fel.Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul#« ZLhS J / £ Telegram- Bn clair From S.1I.O,, Persian Gulf To Pol.Resident &amp; Consul-General,Bushire Repeated to Political Agent, Unseat, Bated 26th Received 2?th July 1932. *T©. (1903/26) Addressed P.R. 2c Consul General, Repeated P.A. llusc&amp;t. 3hei!kii Hassan late of Khasab has brolcen his parole and escaped about midnight 24th July in a sailing jzELSLt* dhow belonging to one of Hen jam Arabs now i settled down in Ras-al-Khaimah. Sheikh of Debar setting off in pursuit in his motor dhow a^out hours later. Residency Agent considers escape was engineered by Kassans relatives at Khasab also that intention is ta*e mm to Bibbah to proclaim him Sheikh of that plac e.»#.C-147 #f 19324 The Pelitioal Agency &amp; 8 Consulit3 # Muscat,27th July 1932* Te The Ceuncll of Regency^ Muscat State* A.« C • In continuation of lay letter K#4C-145 of date* 1 forward for your information and necessary actien, a copy of a ^ ^telegram dated today* received from the Senior Ifavul Officer* Persian Gulf* regarding the arrival of Sheiidi Haesan at Khasab* This is what had to be said and salaams* Treasury Officer* In the absence ef the Pol.Agent &amp; H.B.K* s Consul.Telegram- En clalr Frem S.N.O.Persian Gulf* Te Pelitical Agent* Muscat* Hepeated te Pelitical Resident* Buahire He*1229/27 Dated &amp; “eceived 27th July 1932* My 1908/26. Messenger arrived Hen jam teday Wednesday frem Wall sf Xhasab with request that fellewing telegram be sent te Sultan ef Muscat beginst t 'Hassan arrived Khasab 26th July frem Debai. Request urgent instructions regarding him.” Ends. Sheikh ef Debai intercepted messenger and asked that Sultan be infermed that he will remain at Khasab until he has received His Highness's instruct!ens.J?r om Political, Muscat, To A^ban c/o Poctimster, Karachi, Ay ho.150 Dated 28th July 1932. Reference Uheikh Hassan whs was released by oultan in March last on guarantee of Jheiich ox' Debai given t© Political Accident that he would not return to Khasab. On 26th July S.1T.0. reported that Hassan escaped midnight 24th July in sailing boat Sheikh ox Debai setting off in pursuit in motor dhow about 9 hours later. Residency Agent considers escape engineered by relatives of Hassan to take him to Dibbah and proclaim him Sheikh of that place. On 27th July S.h.O.reported that messenger arrived at Henjam from Vali of Khasab to telegraph to ^ultan that Hassan arrived at Khasab 26th ‘'uly and asking for instructions. This messenger was intercepted by bheikh of Debai and asxced h±±*- to inform Sultan that he will remain at Khdsab until instructions are received from Sultan. Please telegraph whether you want the Khasab file to be sent to yout From Said bin Taimur, Simla To Colonel Fowle, AArachi U. 29th K. 30th July 1932* Following received from our Council telegraphically begins Wali Ahasab states Hasan Shihi escaped from Hobai and arrived Khasab particulars follows stop i have posted letter to you. Telegram ^U-TC) From: Alban, Aarachi To Kesident, nushire Ho. a/82 Dated 30th July 1932. Following telegram received from Sultan begins:- Following received from our x x x posted letter to you ends. I' ihHn ko Telegram (UTC) J«*rom Political Muscat To Alban C/0 Postmaster, Karachi No.149 D. 28th R. 30th July 1932. Addressed to Political Resident repeated to Political Agent Karachi and S.N.O. S.N.0*s telegrams dated 26th and 27th July were forwarded to the Council of Regency and their reply is as follows The Government is aware of the undertaking of the Sheikh of Debai to her respecting the non-return of Sheikh Hassan to Khasab reply ends. 3 representatives are proceeding today Thursday in 'Shoreham' to Dibbah and Khasab in connection with the appointment of new Sheikh of former place.Telegram (GTC) From Political Muscat nbKj it-?&gt; fficj-jliz. To Alban C/0 Postmaster, Karachi No.150 D. 28th R. 20th July 1932. Reference Sheikh Hassan who was released by Sultan in March last on guarantee of Sheikh of Debai given to Political Resident that he would not return to Khasab* On 26th July S.N.O. reported that Hassan escaped midnight of 24th in sailing boat Sheikh of Debai set off in pursuit in motor dhow about 9 hours later# Kesidency Agent considers that escaping engineered by relatives of Hassan to take him to Dibbah and proclaim him Sheikh of that place# on 27th July S.N.O. reported that messenger arrived Henjam from Vali of Khasab to telegraph to Sultan that Hassan arrived at Khasab 26th July and ask for instructions# This messenger was intercepted by Sheikh of Debai and asked to inform the Sultan that he will remain at Khasab until instructions are received from Sultan# please telegraph whether you want Khasab file to be sent to you# Telegram From Alban, Karachi To Resident, Bushire No.K/83 Dated 30th July 1932# Following telegram received from Muscat begins: x x x on 26th July S.N.O. Sultan ends reported that Hassan escaped midnight until instructions are received fromCONFIDENTIAL. f f No. 554-S of 19 32. The Secretary to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to political Agent, Muscat at Karachi and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 6t? h* •August •* 1932 idfp Bushire letter B 0 21-s of Reference to previous correspondence : 16th Jan 1932. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Political Besident's telegram of No. 457-&lt;S? of 28/7/32 2. Telegram No.1514 of 30/7/32 from H.k.S.Shor eham. 3. Telegram No.2214 of 30/7/32 from H.k.3.Shoreham 4. Telegram No. 1504 of 31/7/32 from H.M.S.Shoreham. 5. telegram No.1135 of 31/7/32 from H.M.S.Shoreham. .o« roiit.ical/-^esiaeni^J s telegram No. 464 of 1/8/32 Hassan's escape from Behai./^v f irt Telegram From To G.T.C. Tolitcal Resident, Bushire. Senior Naval officer, 'Triad'. Benjamradio. ,1 No.457 -L&gt;ated 28th July 1932. i^orlani. Your telegram No 1229 of 27th July. T shall he grateful tf'Shoreham' could call at Khasah on her way up, emphasise to Sheikh of Behai his responsibility in matter, and urge him to £ake all steps to effect Hassan*s return to Behai. I shall also he glad of'Shore - -hams' report on situation at Khasah. Resident•'T Telegram Trent To Repeated! 35/141. O.f.C. U.M.ii.' 3horehaa w , Henjaza Senior HaTal Offleer 9 Terelan Gull division. Politleal Resident, Buehlre. 50.1514. Dated the 30th July ( received 31at July ) 1932. Tour 1844 of 28th July. SITUATION AT KHASSAB. Shaikh of Debai together with two sznaller local Shaikhs who are known to be Shaikh Hassan's relations, are working for return of HASSAH. They are however encountering considerable difficulty in virtue of plea that Hassan is unfit to travel. I have impressed on Shaikh of Debai his responsibility for safe custody of Hassan, and informed him that he is to make every effort to obtain possession of him. I have seen some of the more important relations and the present shaikh of Khassab, who is also a relation, and ejcplained conditions under which Hassan was to leave Muscat. 1 have reminded present Shaikh of action which was taken here two years ago and impressed on him his responsibility for controlling his people and that his failure to do so will render him liable to be removed as was his predecessor. Finally I have informed Shaikh of Debai and the two Shaikhs working with him, the Jail and Shaikh of Khassab and relations who came on board that Hassan is to be delivered on board Shaikh of Debai*e dhow or 'SH REHAM' by 1000 tomorrow Sunday. That if this evening hie relatione are etill of opinion that Haesan is unfit to travel I will send my medical officer to see him and that his opinion Is the only one 1 will aeeppt on this point. That if Hassan is unfit to travel by dhow I am prepared . • •- 2 - prepared to consider conroying him to Debai in ahoreham with relatione in attendance# X will make every effort to arrive Henjam p,m. today Monday but request your time of sailing Monday# . SHOiiSHAH •35/141- Telegraxa: G«T«C Froms M Shoreham ‘ • Xpi Senior IJe-Tal icer f Per8ian tiulf i&gt;ivieion. Repeated* Political Resident# Buahire. Bo* 2214 • Dated 30th l received 31st ) July 1932* My 1514 of 30th July. Shaikh of Bakbah one of the local Shaikhs working with Shaikh of Debai reports this evening that relatives refused to allow medical officer to see Hassan under any circumstances* In view of possible Arab susceptibilities I have informed relatives this morning that Medical officer would not enter house or attend Hassan unless they wished* I only wished medical officer to see him and give me opinion of his state. BYidently plea of sickness is only an excuse. Prom information received this evening it would appear that Hassan has larger following than I thought and it is doubtful if he will come off tomorrow Sunday* -SHORBHAU -58/141. Telegram* Front Tot Kopeateds G.T.C. 'Shoreham' 9 Hcnja.:i* Senior ilaTal Officer, Peraian Gulf iilriaion. ~ oiltleal Kesident, Euahire. So. 1504. Dated and received the 31at July 1932, My 2214 of 30th July. I and ny medical officer have seen Shaikh HASSAH in Shaikh of Sakha’s house. He is ill and should be kept quiet for the present. I have told Shaikh of Debai that now I have seen Hassan in his custody I am satisfied. imve told haikh of Debai that I do not insist on Hassan being moved to Debal in his present state but that he the ohaikh of Debai will be held entirely responsible for his safe custody and is to guard him adequately. • SHGREXAl! -Telegram From To G. T.C. H. M.S.Shoreham. Senior iNi aval officer, Persian Gulf. Repeated to Political Resident , -oushire. No. 1135 Rated and received 31st ^uly 1932. ky No. 2214 of the 30th July. Shaikh of Rehai arranged for departure of Hassan at 2330 last ni4ht. Sheikh of Bakkah saw him placed on hoard dhow hound for Bakkah. 1 am proceeding to Bakkah with Shekfcfc of Rehai on hoard. Shoreham. 'i/&gt; © Telegram G.T.G. / -^esedent , -^ushire. T ° Senior 'aval officer. Triad“.“enjamradio Repeated to H.k.S•ohoreham. Ko. 454♦ ^ated 1st August 1932. Correspondence ending with H Shoreham # s 1135. Please convey my thanks to Commander of Shoreham for having got Hassan away from Khassah so promptly where his presence might have led to serious complications as in 4pril 1930 Hassan having 'broken his parole, provided it is not against any guarantees which may have 'been given to him or to Shaikh of Dehai / J would he grateful if Shoreham could take Nassau on hoard and transport him to Muscat there to he interned pending orders of the Sultan. Hailing this Shaikh of Dehai should imprison him at Dehai. Resident.-v -&lt;; ■ •y CONFIDENTIAL. No. 575-3 of 1932. MMb Kfz-so b% The Secretary to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to the Political Agent, Muscat, 1. 2. 4. 1 %. Gi \ and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. vk iy Dated....Jv4.t^.Anguat..L932 Bushire P.L.No .554-3 dated Reference to previous correspondence : 6th August 1932. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Political Resident’s telegram No.433 dated 9th August 1932. Telegram No.1745 dated 9th August 1932, from Commander, 'Shoreham*. Political resident's telegram No.434 dated 9th August 1932. Telegram No. 1210 dated -10th August 1932, from H.k.S.Shoreham. Subject. Hassan's escape from Dehai.Telegram G.T.O. From resident, Bushire. H O Commander, H.LI.3. 'Shoreham* 1 , radio. H©njam No,463 i&gt;ated 9th August 1932. My telegram No 1st August, N 0 .464. What news of Hassan? ^esldent. Dated and received 9th August 1932. Your No.4d3• Shaikh of Dehai has returned to ^ehai leaving Hassan in the custody of Shaikh of Bakhah in whose fort he still lies and I under- -stand still unfit to travel. Do you wish me to gove any instructions to Residency Agent 'before sailing early to morrow Wednesday? Has my 1504 of 31st July 'been received 'by you? “Bhoreham**a ' - * ^ gG ■ticni • 9'iiiieiLr^ , $neb£h&amp;' I«?o;;J ilp I oj bscn j^e*! itvi i/jcfe- to : -‘le .OtT,; I bfr.e sell L &lt; Oil f spxiw aJt 4MMs6. co air ;1alw oot oa IsvcrxJ oJ XXlte bn^Js- a*io Jtt.vl 1 003 ^ vorrabi-cail d w * saoltou iJ2f;X $H£ evo.js- ^ rox Davxace-i oeaX tcTelegram G.J.C. From Political Besident, Bust ire. To Commander, H.M.S '‘Shorebam’* ^enjamradio. No. 484 Bated 9tb August 1932. IKPOBTANT. O' s lour telegram ^o 174b. Please inform Isa to tell Shaikh of Bebai that latter xkiiiichxxf should get hojd of Hassan as soon as possible and keep him in custody pending further orders. Your No. 1504 of 31st July received. Resident. — 0* t No 1210 Dated and received 10th August 1952. Please add to my number 1745 of 19th August: * 3efo e leaving Bakhah, Shaikh of Debai obtained undertaking from Shihuh at Khasab that they would make no attempt to remove Hassan from Bakhah. Kassan also gave undertaking that he would not attempt to return to Khasab. Shaikh of Bakhah has promised to inform the Shaikh of Dibai immediately if anything untoward occurs. * Your No.434 was handed to R.A.P.Works department representative on board the mail steamer at Dibai this morning for delivery to the Besidency Agent. M Shoreham.'&amp; 27/i J 6&amp;' (£) Copies in files ^8/13 r\ Translation of a letter No.124 dated 24th ^ug.x932 from the Council of He^ency,l:uscat dtate, to the jroliticai Agent Jc H.h.LI’s Consul,Muscat (Translation furnished o j the Counci 1 of lieg ency) • Ibrahim bin J.fuha.a.ad has returned yesterday from Khasab by the sloop and informed us that Zaid bin Sinan is still in tne iort oi Dibbah and that the .Camazra ohai^chs had assembled before tlie departure oi Ibrahim from ’Thasab and decided to bring Zaid after 6 aays to the Wali of IGiasab ,.ith a view to arriving at an agreement in connection with the appointment of a new ULeihh at Dibbah. lorahim lur oher has iniormed that oheiich Kassan is still in nuidia. The people of* Chamdha and Jadi have, upon his visi - to them, agreed to request for his return to Khasab. ohaiidi oaid bin I'aictum returnee to Debai at the end of dabi el awwal. In our opinion the stay or Sheikh Hassan amongst the Shihuh is undesirable and will cause a further trouble. His trans portation is desirable from t-.ose places.Letter Ho.204 dated the 14th September 1932 from the Council of Regency, Muscat State, to Captain R.G. Alban, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. After Compliments. With regard to Sheiidi Hasan bin Muhammad al Shehhl who escaped from Debal, we deem it necessary to state that, as you know, he was sent away from Muscat at the suggestion of our friend the British Government to be handed over to Sheikh Sai&lt;$ bin Maktum, Chief of Debai, who guaranteed to the Government that he would not return to Khasab. Sheikh Hasan is now at Bokha which is near Khasab and one of its dependencies. He must not stay at Bokha and His Highness has instructed us to inform you u that Hasan should not Jcept near Khasab. we have Y' already addressed you a letter Ho.124 explaining the seriousness of the matter. Sheikh Hasan should better be removed from Bokha. This is what had to be said and salaamsCONFIDENTIAL. I v&gt; No. 644-h&gt; of 1932. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to jthe political itgent , Muscat, and is directed to him th(&gt; undermentioned document/. r f l/ b o to his address received under cover of his nemoranduin .no. C«lt)7 t dated 26th August 1932. A translation is attached, copy of British Residency which has been retained at Sushi jdo. re. and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated lQlh..»ae.pteiflhex..l932. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. better Mo* 124, dated 24th August 1932, from the Muscat Council to the political Agent, Muscat. hhassab and uibah.Translation of letter No.124 dated 20th lahi al Than! 1351 (24-8-32j from the Oounoil representing H.H. the Sultan of iiusoat and Oman. To Our esteemed friend Oaptain 1.0 H.B.M's Oonsul, Ibrahim bin Muhammad returned from Khasab by a v/arship yesterday and informed us firstly about the shaikhdom of Diba, that.Said bin Sinan bin Yasir is still in the forts of Diba and that while he was departing from Khasab there assembled some of Kun^arah Shaikhs with the 7ali and asked for a respite for six days to bring Said bin Sinan to the Diba may be selected unanimously. he also informed us that it is true that Shaikh Hasan is at bokha* He went to Ghattza and Jadi and agreed with them to the effect that they should address for his return to Khasab. He has now returned to Bokha. Shaikh Said bin Maktum returned to Debai in the end of Rabi al Awal (1st August). According to -/hat we see the stay of Shaikh Hasan in those parts with the Shihuh is not advisable. His stay there might*recrudescence of disorders and it would be more appropriate if he were repatriated from those parts. This is stated for your information. jubair bin Yli 3d. Shihab Illegible. *Telegram (G.T.C* ) 73 fTk) 0 ► From To Political, Muscat, Resident, Bushire. No. - C/175. Bated 14th. October 1932. Sultan requests passage to Khosab whenever convenient to settle question of appointment of Shaikh. Alban'^7 Telegriun (G.T*C.) From - Political, Muscat* To - Britconsul, Bushire* No, - 177. Dated 19th October 1932* r 7 \ Reference my telegram Bo* 175. Suggest Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf be requested to grant Sultan passage in 'Fowey*. Politlealiq.io-t’l- Telegram (G.T.C. ) From - Resident, Bushire. To - Political,, Buscat. No. 670. Dated and received 19th October 1932. /&gt;7V- Your telegram No.177. I am enquiring from Residency Agent what steps Sheikh of Debai is taking to remove Hassan ex Shaikh of Khasob from Bokha rnd until I get reply perhaps Sultan could postpone his visiting Khasab. Resident.Telegram (G.Y.C.) / x ^ 7*.w * From - Political, To *• Britconsul No. 180. Doted 22nd October Muscat. , Bush. ire. 1932. My telegram No.179. Brother of Shaikh of Dubai arrived here. Shaikh of Dubai himself intends visiting Muscat soon. Sultan will not discuss question of Hasson. Polit ical./ ^ Letter dated 17th Jamadi II , 1351 from H.H. Saiyid aid cm 18th October 1352 _ . Toimur, Sultnn of Muscat &amp; Oman, to Captain R.G.Aloan, Political Agent £ : H.BSM’s Consul, Muscat. With regard to Hasan bin Muhammad al Shehhi who is still staying at Bokha, which is a dependency of my town Khasab, the late Council of Regency informed you by my order that I do not agree that Hasan should stay at Bokho, but so far I have not received an answer on the subject. I write again to soy that Hasan must not stay at Bokha after the guarantee which was given by °aid bin Mektoom through the Hon'ble the Political Resident. I expect a favourable answer in this connection c&gt;na I may odd that Said bin ^aktoom is responsible for this matter.(nr/ 7 - D.O. letter dated 20th w airiadi II, 1351 (21st October 1932) from H.H. the Sultan of Lluscat &amp; Oman to Captain R.G. Alban, Political Agent &amp; H.B.K’s Consul, lluscat. A. C. .77 Tjith pleasure I^eceived your letter doted the 20th October i 1932 intimating that you have received a telegram from the Hon’ble the Ai esiaent to the effect that he is enquiring from the Hesidency Agent, Shargah, as to what steps the Sheikh of £ebai is taking for the removal of Hasan £xam al Shehhi from my town Bokha, and that he thinkJit would be better if I postpone my journey to Khasab until a reply has been received. T agree with the suggestion of the Resident and will postpone my journey to Khesab until I hear from you with regard to the said Hasan. . lb*Telegram (G.T.C.) From - Resident, Bushire* To - The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Repeated to Political, Muscat. No. 676. Bated and received 24th October 1932. Addressed to the Senior Navel Officer, Persian Gulf repeated to the Political Agent,Muscat. Shaikh of Dubai has brought Hasan from Bokha to Dubai grateful if Sultan of Muscat could be given passage in sloop to Khosab when convenient. Resident.Demi-off iciaJLg, 2he Political Agency. Muscat* 25th October 1932. My dear friend* A tele^am hae arrived from the Hon’ble the Political Resident saying that the Sheikh of J^cai has bro^t IL^an back from Bokha to ^ebai* 'The Resident has asked the Senior ^Javal Officer to kindly arrange Your Highnessfs passage by a sloop to 'Oiasab* I trust Your Highness ^ill be pleased to hear this news and that it ^ill be convenient to leave for Khasab whenever a sloop is available* I remain Your Highness^ sincere friend* To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur* Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman** Translation of a demi-official letter dated the 2ord Jamadi TI» 1351 (25th Octoter 1932) from His Highness Saiyid Said 'bin ^aimur* Sultan of Muscat 8 c Oman, to Captain H#C. Alban, Political ^gent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. A.C. I have received your letter dated the 25th October 1932 intimating that you have received a telegram from the Hon’ble the Political Resident to the effect that the Sheikh of *^ebai has brought Hasan back from Bokha to ebai and that he has asked the Senior N 0 val Officer to arrange for my passage in one of the sloops to Khasab* I was glad to hear this news and am grateful to the Resident for his assistance in this matter. I expect to hear from you whenever a sloop is available to take me to Khasab. In conclusion I thank you and renew the expression of my high regard, for you and salaams. 4 &lt;s*.or &amp; II / y No.C-186 of 1932. Th# Politioal Agency &amp; Consulate. Muscat, 25th October 1932. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Hfemorandum. 4 ^ . %3 Your telegram No.676 dated the 24th October 1932. I forward for your information a copy in translation of a demi-official letter dated the 25th October ^932 from His Highness the Sultan regarding the ex-Sheikh of Xhueob and the Sultan’s visit. t/ Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.IPb Consul, Muscat.D.O The Politioal Agency. Muscat. 26th October 1932. Thank you very much for your letter and the S,U.O t s message. T have ascertained from His Highness that (a) he woulo like to embark on Friday morning at 8 A.&amp;. if this is convenient to you. (b) he would like to return in a sloop leaving hasab about the 2nd or 3rd of November but he is quite ready to stay longer if this date is inconvenient for the S.N.O., (c) he will be taking 22 followers with him and (d) if convenient he would like to stop at Daba^for one hour on the way back. 2 . I am not particularly fit today but would be delighted to have lunch with you tomorrow (Thursday). As regards accomodation etc. T con give you the following details of arrangements made on previous journeyfc- (a) The Multan is given the spore cabin, (b ) The fultan takes meals with the Captain v (c) A small portion of the stern is^creened off with a canvas awning so that he may sit there in privacy during the day. (d) The followers are usually given places on the upper deck and they will bring their own food merely using the kitchen for oooHing. 3- Generally speaking the Sultan likes to be left fairly quiet; as rcegards meals, he eats all ordinary food and as regards any offer arrungenenta such as landing etc. ho will let you know what he wenta at the time. Embarkation arrangements at Muscat are usually as follows:- servants, followers and luggage usually embark about one hour before the Sultan i. e. in this case at 7 a.K. They will find tn.lt aw* transport that 1 . hooria. An r.««rda the Cuitan. ship* usually send th. motor launch to th. paloc. steps at the time of embarkation, in this case 8 a.M. 4 About salutes, on at least ona occasion recently at Sur2* (%$) » i. ——-—&lt;—^m lll | l■^p| —*&gt;* ■ »' ■ tht Sultan received his salute of guns on landing^the idea being, of course, to warn all the i^cople of the arrival of the Bultan* He flight like to have his salute on landing at Khasab. You could enquire of him before arrival there. ?/hen returning he of course receives his salute on landing at Muscat. I can let you know any other details when I see you tomorrow. ?f the embarkation arrangements deta led above togrt.har with the times ife.e. 7 A.lf. for the servants and 8 A.H. for the Sultan on Friday morning are convenient to you^would you kindly let me know so that I can inform His Highness. He is also willing to embark at any other time which may be suitable to you. To Sir Philip ??. Bowycr-Smyth, Bt., H. H. s. •♦Fowey*. ■HI I I9 111 ao.aoa-j of i*22' British ' eoxaency 4 Consulate-jcneral, Bushire» the 26th October 1932. From The ^on’ble Lt.•Colonel T. C. Fowle, Political J esidont in the i^eroxan Gull, The Foreign Secretary to the CoTenuaent of India, Uew &gt;elhi. sir. *ith reference to correspondence ending with this office telegrais Bo«T.91 of 13th May 1930, I hare the honour to report for y&lt;r-r information that Shaikh .iasran of Khasoab haring surrendered and been taken back to Muscat, had the mild sentence of about 22 months’ imprisonment inflicted on him by the Muscat stats. At the conclusion of his imprisonment Hie Highness the Sultan of Muscat intended that he should remain ae a political detenu in Uusoat. The Shaikh of i&gt;ebai, howerer, intercoded on hie behalf and informed the late Sir Hugh Bisooe that tie (the Shaikh) would gire an undertaking that haoean would stay at lisbai under the surrsillance of the Shaikh if he was all owed to go there. sir Hugh Blecoe passed this request on to the Sultan, who agreed, and iiaeean • haring promised to abide by the terms of the undertaking • was permitted to leare Muscat for 2obal. ho stayed there until some months ago when on the 30th July telegrams were reoelred to the effect that Haesan had left iebai secretly for Khsssab. His presence there, apart from the undertaking which the Shaikh of &gt;ebai had giren, in riew of paet erento was of course most undesirable* The semmi:hm Oomioiinder of 3 # M Shoroimi!ii # worklik^ in oonoert with thm ihaikh of oho had folXowod iteoacm, and some other local Shaikhs, suoocecled In ^ettin^ liassan restored from haosab to Jokha, a aaall port between ihaesab and &lt;Jebal* This prompt notion on the part of the Cotamanuer of U # M«a tt * , shorehaa 4 ' probably averted serious complications, am 1 conveyed him my thanks through the Senior 2»&amp;val Officer, 2, The neat step was to get llasean bank to Debai, Ae v however, the question of establishing the Imperial ^irwa^ys* Host house, etc*, at ^hargah was then urgent, I did not wish to have iiny more irons in the fire on the Xruoial Coast at that particular time* But during my visit to the Trucial Coast at the end of August, X approached the db&amp;ikh of . eb&amp;i on the subject, anu found him inclined to treat his responsibility in the matter somewhat lightly, X enquired who was paying for the upkeep of 'tasean and his family at Bokha, The shaikh replied that Haasan was paying for this himself out of the proceeds of his gardens at -hassab which had not been sequestrated oy the uscat State, X accordingly informed the haikh that if he failed to get baok Hassan to ^ebai in reasonable time, say, at the »nd of October, 1 wo Id have to consider the necessity of suggesting to the Sultan that Haasan, having broken his word, should be deprived of his property, when the fhaikhs of Khassab and Bokha would have to support Hassan end hie family# the shaikh then began to view the question more eeriouely, and a few days ago in reply to a message wh ch X sent to the esideiicy Agent, .ihargah, as to what action the Shaikh of Debai was taking in the matter of Hassan X received a reply that he had sent his brother to get him back, and on the 24th instant X received a telegram from the Hesidenoy Agent to the effect that the ubtikh of Debut had brought Hassan baok to Jebai, This is satisfactoryso far, and I am considering tne desirability of tfte next step of getting Hassan back to Muscat* 1 «« sending a copy of tnis letter to the Senior liaTal Officer, JPersian Gulf division* I nave the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd/- T. C* Fowle, jut ••Colonel, I'olitioal hesiaent in the Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for information. By Order. Confidential Assistant. &gt;:•; a.IranElation of o letter dated 15th Rajah 1351 (15/11/32) from T T # T !.3aiyid Sold hln Suddsa Taimur, Sultan of Hue cat &amp; Oman, to Hajor C.E.U.Bremner # I-olitical iigent &amp; H Coneul, Muscat* /^fi i.. With regard to Hasan bin Huhammad al Shehhi for whom Sheikh Said bin Haktum, Ruler of ^ebai, gave a bond of security through the Hon’ble the Resident that Hasan should remain at Debai* During my recent visit to Khasab Sheikh Said bin Haktum visited me there and iformed me that he wished to return Hasan to Muscat* T replied that I could only accept his proposal through the Political ^esident. because I had sent Hasan to live with him at the request of the Resident. By chance the Resident called at Khasab on his way to Muscat and we all met there. I discussed the matter with Sheikh Said in the presence of the Resident and at last it was decided that 3heikh “^aid bin ^aktum should send Hasan back to us. I accepted this arrangement in the presence of the Resident and I will let you knov/ when Hasan arrives at Muscat. I have written this letter to inform you of the desire of the ^heikh of ^ebai to return Hasan to Muscat and of my acceptance of the proposal in the presence of the Resident. U. E. til d-«-t v i # - ''y — — Translation of a letter 18th Rajah 1351 (18/11/32) from V.' .Soiyid Said hin iPoiitux, Sultan of Kuscat ft. Oman, to Kajor C.E.U*Bremner, rolitical /igent ft IT.P.r’b Consul,Muscat '1 A ‘ G ' kMy Tfith reference to my letter doted the 15th Rajah 1351 (i5th ITovemher 1932) regarding Hasan hin Muhammad al Shehhi Hasan *s in which I promised to inform you of ika 1 / arrivol at Muscat, I have to state that £**£* he arrived from *deboi on the 17th Rajah 1351 (17/11/32). please inform the Hon'ble the Political Resident that Sheikh Said hin liaktum has sent hack Hasan to us as v/as decided in our conversation at Khasah. U. E., XJE!0 iw t Lo i v/ 3 xio.H92«3 6f 19S2. • no i $ jbihto Tnx British residency &lt;sc Consulate-General 9 .lahiO %&amp; Bus hire, the 2nd December 1932 • I'’rom - The Hon'ble jut.Colonel T.C.KowlepC.B.i., Political resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Foreign Secretary to the Government of ^ndia, Bew *&gt;elhi« Subject s Shaikh H&amp;asan of Kh&amp;ssab Sir 7 *) 0 In continuation of my letter iso« -S of 26th October 1932, I have the honour to report that on a recent tour to Muscat I met at Khassab ilis Highness the Sultan f K us cat and the uhaikh of ivebai, The latter had got dis tinctly tired of his troublesome guest, and asked for per mission from His Highness to surrender the bail he had undertaken on his - Hassan*a behalf, and to send Hassan back to Muscat. As this was ejcnctly what His Highness and 1 wanted the former graciously accorded his 8fnotion, and I have now had a communication from the Political Agent ,;.uecat, that ilasoan has arrived there. The iiasean incident may therefore be said to be satisfactorily closed. 2 am sending a copy of this letter to the Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf division. 1 have the honour to be t2ir, Your most obedient servant sd/- T. C. Fowle, Lt.Colonel Political Mesident in the Persian Gulf,telegram- li.T.C « ^‘rom To Resident, -tJushire, Political, Muscat, / 3^ •/ O-l ■ IcrX , Kit V' Ho.207 Dated &amp; deceived 27th inarch 1933. During my last visit to Muscat 1 informed Multan that t thought it would be better for Sheikh Hassan to be brought back to Muscat from (iwadur whence he could easily slip away to Khassab. Please approach tiis highness on subject. Telegram. G.T.C. Prom - Political Unseat. To - Resident, Bushire. No.C-88. Datea the 29th Larch 1933. Your texe e rai*x 207. Hassan brought to Luscat 28th Larch. Pollticai</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/209</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/209</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/22 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: KHASAB – SHAIKH HASSAN SHIHUH'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-20T10:15:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (100 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 102; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-102; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to former occupants of the posts Wali of Khasab and Shaikh of Khasab, in the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. The correspondence primarily concerns Shaikh Hasan bin Muhammad, a former Shaikh of Khasab who was sentenced to twenty-two months' imprisonment by the Government of Muscat and Oman and then sent to Debai [Dubai] by the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, on the understanding that Shaikh Said bin Maktum, Ruler of Debai, would keep Shaikh Hasan under surveillance and prevent his return to Khasab. The correspondence documents Shaikh Hasan's subsequent escape from Debai to Khasab, his removal to Bokha, and his eventual return to custody in Debai. The file concludes with the decision to return Shaikh Hasan to Muscat.The file features the following principal correspondents: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Government of Muscat and Oman's Council of Regency; Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], President of the Council of Ministers, Muscat, and later, Sultan of Muscat and Oman; Shaikh Said bin Maktum [Shaikh Saʻīd bin Maktūm bin Hasher Āl Maktūm], Ruler of Debai; the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf; commanding officers of various HMS ships, including HMS
                           Lupin, HMS
                           Folkestone, HMS
                           Cyclamen, and HMS
                           Shoreham.The Arabic language material consists of correspondence between the Political Agent and Consul at Muscat and various representatives of the Government of Muscat and Oman (English translations are also included).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Council of Regency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Khaṣab</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Imprisonment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>