<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:32:32.874Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IRh'/} © 'V Fe Dated the-v DelDruary 1936 To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Kal Ahmed, a Dresser employed in the Residency Dispensary, has applied, vide copy of his petition attached, about his claim against the late Bilal hin Hamazan of Debai. The facts of the case are as below:- 2. Kal Ahmed had sold dates worth Rs 4000/- to Bilal bin Bamazan on credit and as he was not getting his money back he applied to this Residency some years ago for the recovery of his claim. The matter was referred to the Besidency Agent, Sharjah, who in his letter No. 131 dated the 25th April 1932 replied that the late Bilal bin Bamazan had left assets to the value of Rs 4988/- against total liabilities amounting to Rs 46251/-, and that the creditors would receive a dividend of Rs 10/8/- %, i.e., Kal Ahmed would receive Rs 432/- in full settlement of his claim for Rs 4000/-. Sven this dividend was conditional on the assets amounting to Bs. 4988/- being recovered from the late Bilal bin Bamazan’s debtors. After many reminders the Besidency Agent, Sharjah reported in his letter No. 431 dated the 13th August 1933 loopy enclosed) that the debtors of the deceased Bilal were pleading bankruptcy and that he would prefer complaints against them to the Shaikh of Debai -as soon as he hears that they lthe debtors) had earned-2 earned enough money from diving* Since then nothing more has heen heard in the matter. 3. Would you kindly take over this case and send a report in due course? By Order, ResidentCopy of petition dated Bushire, the 20th January 1936, from Ahmad Gharihi* Dresser, Residency Dispensary, With reference to my previous petitions to •» the Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject of my claim against the late Kilal bin Ramazan of Deoai, As this case has been outstanding for a long time and 1 am hard up nowadays I should be highly grateful if you would kindly recommend my case to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in order that the Residency Agent, Sharjah may be instructed to recover my dues for which act of kindness 1 shall remain thankful to you and pray for your long life and prosperity.-in™ ,J °Py letter No. 431 dated the 13th August 1933 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Secretary to the 1 olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. After compliments: With reference to your No. 267 of the 17th July 1933, on the subject of the estates of the late Rilal son of Ramazan. I 'beg to state that ^ tried to recover seme money from the debtors of the said deceased Rilal but could not succeed as they all plead to be bankrupt and to have not earned enough to pay their new debts while they owe considerable sums of money to merchants. I have therefore arranged to watch the debtors of Hilal son of Ramazan and as soon as x see that they have earned enough money from diving I shall prefer complaints to the Ruler of Debai requesting him to ^ recover money from them. 1 beg to state also that the Arabs of tne Trucial Oman are in a bad monetary state because their earnings from diving have been very meagre. I am nevertheless having the debtors in my mind with a view to do something in this case.7 © JRAtiKLA i' 10.:. No. 384 dated the 10th dune 1936. (20th Rabi Awwal 1355). r o, 'Aisuf* bin I^asii** Aft e r Comp 1 ime n ts • i unders osno. that tb.6 bats *^lian Saliadur Isa bin ’Abdullatif, the then Residency Agent, appointe&lt; you as a judicial receiver for the winding up of the estate of the late Hilal bin Ramadhan al Shumais and the recovery of the amounts due to him,according to his account books which were handed over to you and whicl are still in your possession, so that they may be distributed amongst his creditors. 2 * 1 receiv e&amp; a letter from the Political Agent, Bahrain, enquiring about the nature and the recovery of these amounts. I, therefore, remest you to submit to me as soon as possible a written report containing the following informations- (a) Ihe amount die to each creditor seoaratelv against the late Hilal bin Ramad^f 7 (b) now much each creditor was paid. 10 2 x 1 t. hi. vd)Amounts recovered from each debtor. ' 6) account? rS Whl ° h caused del ay in submitting the Usual Ending. Copy To^,* to tho Mitio,, A OT „t, Bahrain, rit h reference to his letter ilo. S12-B/10-3 dated the 2Sth ih 1936.No.269-B/10-3. Political Agency, Bahrein, the 8th July 1936. To, The Secretary to the Honourable The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R K. Subject: Claim of Kal juunaa Dresser against the late Hilal bin Ramadhan of Dubai. Memorandum. ft, ) Reference your memoranduari^o.237/14/230 dated 2nd February 1936. The Residency Agent has reported that us. 13/- have been recovered from one of the aebtors of the late Hilal bin Ramadhan, which will be divided proportionately among the creditors. The remaining debtors have either died, become insolvent, or taken oath denying the claim. 2. The sum of te.252/- was recovered by sale of effects and passed into the possession of the late Than Bahadur T Isa bin A bdul Latif. It will form a first charge on his estate, and will be proportionately divided among the creditors of the late Hilal bin Ramachan when recovered. r for Offg. Political 4gent, Bahrain.14/230 Dated 31st -arch 1937 o The Political A^reot 'Bahrain Subject*- Claim of Fal Ahmad Dresser against the late Tilal hin Damadhan of Dihai. Deference your memorandum **o.269-B/10-3 dated the 8th July 1936. 2. ”Till you please let me know how the matter stands now. By Order, Secretary to Besident in th f.No.124-B/10-3. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th April 1937. To, The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Memorandum. Reference your letter No.384 dated the lutii June 1936 to Yusuf bin Nasir, Sharjah, of which a copy was sent to me, on the subject of the administration of the estate of the late Hilal bin Ramadhan. 2. We have received another reminder from the Residency, Bushire, regarding the claim of Kal ihimad bresser against the said deceased. 3 . Will you please let me know how the matter now stands. for Political *gent, Bahrain.ll® Political Agency, No*102-B/lU-3. Bahrain, the 6tn April 1938. Reference my letxer No.124-B/10-3 Cated 8th April 1937 regarding the claim of Kal Ahmaa Dresser against the late Hilal bin Ramaohan. Please let me know how the matter now stands. |/J for Political Agent, ^anrain.lyil p m Translation of letter No.300 dated 20tn April 1038 from tde Residency Agent, Sharjan, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Gompliments. Reference your letter No.108-B/10-3 dateu otn April 1938. I beg to inform you that when Hilal bin Rainadan al Shumais died the late K.B.’Isa bin Abdullatiff appointee his cousin Yusuf bin Nasir to administer the estate. Yusut bin Nasir says that, despite his efforts, he was not able to realize out of the assets of the deceased more than ^s.3b3/u/- which he paid to the late K.B.’Isa bin ’Abdullatiff. When Mr.Howes the then Assistant Political Agent visited Sharjan on 29th June 1936 1 informed him about this ana explained to him everything in detail and tnat a sum of ;is.232/6 will be recovered from the estate of the late K.B.’Isa bin Aduullatit he mace a note of this on the file which he brought with him from Bahrain. Ihe estate of the late K.B.’Isa is under the administration of the Ruler of Sharjah. Most oi the estate has been wound up but, owing to the disputes over certain lanced properties ana the considerable amount oi claims, the matter has remained pending until now. The Ruler oi Sharjah promised several times to settle the case as soon as possible The amount will be recovered from the estate as soon as the case is settled. ^sual ^riding.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1870</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1870</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File B/10-3 CLAIM OF KAL AHMAD DRESSER AGAINST THE LATE HILAL BIN RAMAZAN OF DUBAI’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-18T00:49:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (17 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 19; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-15; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to a renewed debt recovery claim in 1936 made by Ahmad Gharibi (also referred to as Kal Ahmed), a wound dresser employed in the Persian Gulf Residency Dispensary at Bushire. His claim is against the late Hilal bin Ramazan (also referred to as Hilal bin Ramadhan al Shumais) of Debai [Dubai] for non-payment of dates sold to him in 1932 or earlier. The correspondence is mainly between the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Residency Agent, Sharjah who investigate and report on the progress of the claim. Included in the correspondence is a petition from the claimant Ahmad Gharibi to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and a letter in Arabic and English from the Residency Agent to Yusuf bin Nasir, the judicial receiver at Sharjah responsible for administering the estate of the deceased Hilal bin Ramzan. Letters between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Residency Agent, Sharjah are also in Arabic and English.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Debt recovery</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Debai</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Claims</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>