<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00016e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:14:29.328Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&lt;n No. 1162.E..A, The DEPUTY SECRETARY to The GOVERNMENT or INDtA, The POLITICAL RESIDENT in the PERSIAN GULP. Simla, the 2oth June 1896. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your * letter No. 44, dated the 25th April 1890, regarding the decision of the Sultan of Maskat not to undertake at present any measures to restore his authority in Dhofar. • A copy of Major Sadler's report therein referred to was received direct. y • 2. The Saltan's recent conduct and attitude in this matter appear to the Government of India, to he most unsatisfactory. It is undeistood, howeveij that you do not recommend any immediate representation being made to His Highness on the subject ; and as no action can be taken at Dhofar until after the monsoon, no present orders seem to be called for. I am to request that the Political Agent may be instructed to maintain a careful watch on the Sultan's conduct and bearing, and to report punctually anything noteworthy which may come under his observation. An early report should be furnished if His Highness gives any intimation of his future intentions as to Dhofar ; if he fails to do so within the next three or four months you should advise the Government of India of the course which may, in your opinion, be most appro- priately adopted, 3. You have already been advised that Saiyid Fadthl, the Moplah outlaw, is believed to be at Constantinople, and that there are no grounds for suspecting that the Turkish Government intend to interfere on his behalf or to raise any claims to Dhofar. I have the honour to be. z?, -h ^ Sir, You most obedient Servant, u ^ t r Uf'.fcZ */*-■** Offg. Dy. Secy. to G. C. PreiB, Simla.—No. 299 F. D.—26-6.96—89 to h L fi vEneloture inUV.et Ko. U, dated tie SVh Jfan Secret Dt'jjurlineut, India Office. India Office, 21tb March 18D6. Sib, In continuation of mv letter of the Crd March, on the subject of affairs at Dhofar, I am desired hy Lord George Hamilton to acquaint you, for tho information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that the \ iceroy telegraphs, under date 22iid March, as follow s : 'Political Resident reports that, if Muscat troops at Dhofar are increased by 150 men whom Sultan is willing to send, and we coerce rebels, they would probably yield without resort to extreme measures; but, unless we coerce, Sultan's troops unequal to retaking or holding province. Rebel Sheikh hoisted Turkish flag, churning protection ; and boats expecUd at Aden with letters for Moplah' (Outlaw). ^ 2 Lord EMn then enquires if Her Majesty's Government will approve of the'advance of the Sultan's force if re-inforced hy the support of the guns of Her Majesty's Ship ' Brisk ' from the anchorage, if the rebels do no., alter forty-Lht hoars' notice, strike their flag, and His Excellency further suggests that the 5 Turkish Government he informed that the Moplah Outlaw will not he allowed to go to Dhofar, which is a dependency of Muscat. 8 Lord George Hamilton would recommend that a reply he sent to the Government of India in the affirmative, and that a eommumcation he made to the Porte as suf^ested, as His Lordship holds that it is expedient m Bn ish interests that the authority of the Sultan of Muscat should be re-established and maintained at Dhofar, and that all foreign interference be exciuued therefrom. I have etc., A. GODLEY. The Under-Secretary of State, Eoreign Office.IBIndia Office, Sir, 7th August 1896. In continuation of my letter of the 1st of July, I am directed to address you on the subject of affairs at Dhofar which have become seriously complicated by the unexpected attitude now assumed by the Sultan of Maskat. From the letter of the — Government of India, No. 123, Foreign, Secret, dated 30th June, with its enclosures, and from the papers forwarded with Mr. Barnes's letter of the 30th of June, it will be seen that the Sultan has become indifferent as to the assertion of his authority at Dhofar, and that the local authorities attribute to French influence this sudden change of demeanour. Major Sadl # reported on the 19th of April that it was rumoured at Maskat that a French man-of- war would shortly visit Dhofar. 2. As Lord Salisbury is aware, Dhofar lies at the extreme limit of the territories of Maskat in the direction of Aden, and just outside the network of Protectorate agreements concluded with the tribal chiefs from Sheikh Sayad in the straits of Bab el Mandeb up to Has Sair in the Mahri country. The intention of those treaties was to prevent any attempt by foreign Powers to establish any station or protectorate between points on the Arabian coast where British jurisdiction was already esta blished, as shown in Sir Julian Pauncefote's letter of the 19th of November 1887. From Eas Sair to the territories of Maskat in the Persian Gulf reliance was placed upon our political relations with the Sultan. Dhofar itself, which is believed to be capable of being formed into an excellent harbour, was added to the Sultan's dominions after the expulsion of Sayed Fadthl the Moplah usurper; and ever since its occupation by Sayed Turki sixteen years ago the district of Dhofar has formed an integral part of the territories and dependencies of the Sultan, with whom an agreement was made on the 20th of March 1891 binding His Highness and his successors not to cede or give for occupation, save to the British Government, the dominions of Maskat and Oman or their dependencies. A copy of this agreement was forwarded to the Foreign Office on the 25th of June 1891. 3. Lord Salisbury has been informed of the attempts lately made by the Moplah usurper to re-establish his influence at Dhofar. The Govern ment of India attaches such importance to the exclusion of foreign encroachment from this part of the coast, tbat, notwithstanding its avowed policy of non-intervention in the internal affairs of Maskat, the Viceroy sought and obtained permis- sion on the 30th of March last to approve of the advance of Maskat troops against Dhofar, and to S. 35.support it by tlic guns of H.M.S. ' Brisk ' from her anchorage if the rebels did not strike their flag at 48 hours' notice. Other measures were taken to meet the danger. As reported in your letter of 19th June 189(3, tlie Moplah Sayed Fadthl was formally warned that he would not be permitted to proceed to Dhofar, and that his agent would not be recognized there. A communication to the Porte to the effect that no foreign interference at Dhofar would be tolerated was approved, but it was not actually made, under circumstances reported in your letter of the 31st of March. To the French Government also a communication on the subject of our intentions was authorised to be made, under the directions of Lord Salisbury, coupled with the assurance, as intimated in your letter dated 27 th March last, that the action proposed in support of the Sultan's authority implied no intention of establishing any protectorate over Maskat. These several measures were taken on the full conviction that the ruler of Maskat, enjoying British pro tection, would take adequate measures to assert and maintain his authority over Dhofar. 4. His disinclination to do so introduces a new difficulty into the problem. The exclusion of foreign encroachment from Dhofar remains as important an object of Indian policy as ever, but the agent, upon whose action the realisation of that policy depends, will apparently not move. The Viceroy proposes to await further information as to the Sultan's intentions before considering the action to be adopted in this emergency, and the prevalence of the monsoon for some weeks to come renders that course feasible. But, in the opinion of Lord George Hamilton, it is desirable that Lord Salisbury should be made acquainted with the facts without delay, so that full consideration may be given to the various courses open to us. 5. The Government of India has long been anxious to assert an exclusive British protectorate over Maskat and Oman, but from your letter dated the 9th of July it is understood that existing conditions are not favourable to the conclusion of such an arrangement with France. It must not be forgotten that the intimation made to the leading Sheikhs of Oman warning them against attacks upon Maskat and Mattrah, reported to the Foreigh Office on 9th March last, has enlarged the exclusive and direct responsibilities of the Government of India; but, on the other hand, the assurance conveyed by the Foreign Office to the French Government that our proceedings at Dhofar did not imply an intention to establish a protectorate over Maskat has emphasised the force of the joint protectorate established in 1862. Such an assurance could only have been thought necessary upon the assumption that Dhofar falls within the scope of the joint engagement, although the place did not belong to Muscat in 1862 ; and it may be supposedthat the rrench Govornment acquiesced in this view, since Lord George Hamilton is not aware that any observation on their part was made to the contrary. If, therefore, the joint engagement is understood at Paris to extend to Dhofar, there would appear to be the less reason for apprehending any serious interference by Prance with the affairs of that place, because the French are hardly interested in committing a breach of the engage ment which would justify our treating it as cancelled. 6. The main point, therefore, which Lord George Hamilton desires to refer for the consideration of the Secretary of State for Poreign Affairs is, whether there is reasonable ground for anticipating intervention at Dhofar on the part of any Luropeau Power. If neither Prance nor Turkey is at present likely to attempt interference or encroachment. Lord George Hamilton would be inclined to the conclusion that the existing situation, although by no means satisfactory, does not call for immediate action or orders; and he would propose to await the further information as to the Sultan's attitude and intentions that is promised by the letter of the 30th June last from the Government of India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) A. G odley.1 (Received with letter No, 42, dated the 4th September 1896, from the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, India Office, London.) Enclosures in Foreign Office covering letter, dated the 21st August 1896. Mb. Heebeet to the Foreign Office. :N0,632 ' Thekapia, My Loed, With reference to Your Lordship's telegram No. 103 of 19th June, I have the honour to transmit to Your Lordship herewith translation of a communi cation which I have received from Seyyid Eadhl, Emir of Dhofar, regretting the decision arrived at by Her Majesty's Government not to recognize his envoy, but repeating his assurances of friendship towards England. I have also the honour to enclose copy of a letter addressed by Seyyid Eadhl to Sir P. Currie on the same subject. I have, &amp;c., (Sd.) Michael H. Herbert. The Marquis of Salisbury, K.G., &amp;c., &amp;c. Enclosures in above. 1. From Seyyid Fadhl to Mb. Hebbebt. The 21st-22nd August 1896. (Translation.) I have received your letter stating that Lord Salisbury has instructed you to inform me that the British Government cannot grant me permission to proceed to Dhofar nor recognise or assist my envoy. After certain verbal communications through a confidential intermediary with Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, I had addressed a letter in a manner determined upon as being suitable, asking that, as a mark of the friendship and amity between us, a recommendation might be given for the emissary I was about to send to Dhofar, solely to renew our old friendly relations, and stating the political course which I proposed to adopt after my arrival at Dhofar -; latterly I addressed a letter to you describing the unex pected proceedings of a British vessel at Dhofar, as likely to inteiieie with t le friendship long existing between us. I have never asked either for permission to proceed myself to Dhofar, nor for the official recognition of my envoy. Eor I am under no obligation to ask of any State permission to go to Dhofar. There are Governments which recognise the official character of my State and functionaries. I have at Dhofar a representative and officials who carry on the government; as for the events caused in my principality by certain persons, since my arrival at Constantinople, these were due to certain reasons and ideas upon a special intimation from myself, and I naturally attach no importance to them. As for the envoy whom I propose to send, I am fully qualified to do so, and have always tried to preserve intact and uninjured the rights of my principality. Moreover, my principality being in the Arab Peninsula, its connection with which is known to all, and as stated m my letter to HisExcellency the Ambassador, as I could never allow that the hoisting of the Maskat flag in my principality in place of the national flag implies any degree of connection with Maskat, even if the recognition or non-recognition of my envoy by England be considered as a political question, yet to admit it will be a proof of her friendship to me and will increase my friendship to her. Thank God, I am known in many countries, and thousands of Mussulmans rejoice at my joy and grieve at my sorrow. However, I beg you to communi cate these remarks of mine to Lord Salisbury, for my ancient and sincere friendship towards England still exists and is even greater than ever. I avail, &amp;c., (Sd.) Fadhl-bin-Alawi, Emir of Dhofar. 2. From Seyyid Fadhl to Sir P. Currie. The 21st'22nd August 1896. (Translation.) While Your Excellency was at Constantinople certain friendly communi cations passed between us, and as both of us desired to extend the amicable relations between Your Government and myself, certain letters were written in a manner approved by you to bring about such friendship, and were presented to you. I received a few days ago, through your representative Mr. Herbert, the Charge d'Affaires, a reply contrary to my expectations and desires. To this I have replied in a suitable manner, but as Your Excellency is, like Your predecessors, Mr. Layard and Lord Dufferin, well acquainted with the truth of the matter, and as you have treated me well and the correspondence has taken place through your intermediary, I have taken the liberty to bring the foregoing to Your Excellency's knowledge. I have, &amp;c., (Sd.) Fadhl-bin-Alawi, Emir of Dhofar. His Excellency Sir P. Currie, G.C.B. (Confidential.J No. 1814.E.-A. A copy of the foregoing is forwarded confidentially to the Political Enclosures in letter from the Secretary, Political Resident in the ^ Peisian Gulf, for in- nnd secret Department, India Office, London, No. 42, formation, in continuation of the endorse- d.ited the 4th September 1896. ment from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, No. 1362E.-A. (Confidential), dated the 4th August 1896. &lt;7 FOREIGN DEPARTMENT; SIMLA, The 20th October 1896. /t By Order, &amp;c., Assistant Secy, to the Govt, of India. Foreigrn Office Press—No. 1251-20.10-96—32, A* 9^ '--y ^ 4 ^ tx ^ J %. stz?* r/'t. fj &gt; &lt; '• -y .No. 819E.-A. F rom T he SECRETARY to the GOVERNMENT of INDIA, To T he POLITICAL RESIDENT in the PERSIAN GULF. Foeeion Dept. Simla, the Mth May 1897, Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letters Nos. 27 and 38, dated the 25th March and the lOth April 1897, respectively, reporting the result of the measures undertaken for the re-estahlishment of the authority of the Sultan of Maskat at Dhofar. 2. The Government of India approve the action taken by yourself and Captain Beville, and trust that the arrangements made may prove satisfactory. I am to request that the Sultan may he congratulated on the success which attended the expedition. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Secretary to the Government of India, Jn Shy A^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00016e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/393</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00016e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/393</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 35/17 I Attack on Dhufar'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1895/1897</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (127 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the system of foliation in use is the sequence of numbers appearing in a circle in the top right hand corner of each folio. In addition some numbers bear page numbers written in blue.Condition: The edges of some pages are broken off with some words missing.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning an attack on Dhofar by the Kathiri tribe. The attack was sparked off by the imprisonment of a tribesman for evading the Sultan's tax on frankincense. Letters discuss the dispatch of an armed force from Muscat to Salalah in dhows, led by Sayyid Saif bin Hamad bin Salim to retake the fort. Captain James Hayes, Political Agent at Muscat, Sadler arrived to effect a settlement between the Chiefs of Dhofar and Sultan Faisal [Fayṣal bin Turkī]. The Chiefs of the Shaikhs of the Al Kathir refused to meet the Political Agent on board the man-of-war
                           Briskbut offered to meet on shore or in the town.Correspondents include Major James Hayes Sadler, Political Agent Muscat, and the Political Resident Persian Gulf. Includes translations of letters from (the original Arabic letters are not included in this file) Faisal bin Turki, Sultan of Muscat; Sayyid Abdul Jalil; Sayyid Saif bin Hamad bin Salim; Mousallim bin Badawi; the Chief Shaikhs of the Al Kathir.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Kathīrī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Dhufar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military operations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00016e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>