<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000161_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-14T11:07:28.447Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\ t - n i : xed f Any reply to this letter should be ^addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. Telephone: Victoria 9310. Telegrams: Minindust, Parl, London. Reference No.:-P.D. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT ■J) ^-' (miSes Department), . . Dean Stanley Street, r y ^ vJ . Millbank, * Westminster, London, S.W.l. , August, 1935^ , ^ / i&gt; b Dear Laithwaite, &gt;^/ v v ^&gt;1 As promised, I enclose for your information a 1 copy of the Agreement in connection with the Turkish Petroleum Company’s coneession,of March 19th, 1914. It will he seen that the question of Koweit is dealt with in Clause 10. Yours sincerely, J. G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street, S. W. 1. HPWG/EW1 COPY. CONFIDENTIAL. I oli 3. ( . ^ J33 Gonca 4z i ;, an £ eia .g nt s for Fusion cf taa Interests in Turkish Pet mi 33sions h taa^'Aroy group and of tae mrkx.g ^tro, onipan II is agreed that the interests shall be divided as follows:- M Fifty per cent* to the D , Arcy group. Twenty-five per cent, to the Deutsche Bank, j. went^y-five per cent, to the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company, and that, in orddr to carry out this division - 1. iuc shares in the Turkish Petroleum Company now h'eld by the National Bank of Turkey shall be transferred in equal moieties to tns Deutsche Bank and the Anglo-Saxon fm Company. T 2. The capital cf the Turkish Petroleum Company shall be increased to r60,GGC/ by the creation of 80,000 new shares of ij each of the same class as those now existing. 3. These 60,000 new shares shall be allotted to the D 1 Arcy group on terms to be agreed upon between the parties. 4. The Board cf the Company shall consist of 6 members, of whom 4 will be nominated by the D'Arcy group, 2 - by the Deutsche Bank, and 2 by the Anglo-Saxon Company. 5. The capital of the Turkish Petroleum Company shall be employed only in exploring, testing, and proving oil fields, a separate public company or companies being formed to work any field or fields the examination of which has proved satisfactory. 6. Such working company or companies shall issue to the Turkish Petroleum Company fully paid ordinary shares as consideration for the acquisition of the rights of the Company to trie propertied to be acquired; such ordinary shares shall carry full control of the working company or companies, which control shall in no circumstances be partedf With by the Turkish Petroleum Company. The woricing capital required bv 1 ^Ci oUu,h working cooiDanv or companies shall be raised k P 7 .... , . by means of Preference shares '° r daDentUreS Wnl ° h Sha11 b9 offered to the public to such extent as the members of tne T urkl sh Petroleum company or any one of them shall elect not to ■ “ ct not to subscribe for themselves. o. The alterations in the memorandum and (or) articles of association of the Turkish Petroleum Company necessary C8rry ° Ut the ab0V9 ^iMons shall be made forthwith. 9 ‘ r- S * Gulbenkian shall be entitled to a beneficiary 5 per cent, interest without voting rights in tne Turkish Petroleum Company, this 5 per cent, being con err bused squally by the h’Arcy group and the Anglo-Saxon Company out of their respective holdings. The shares representing to-. Gulbenkian's interest shall be registered 111 t,ns 1131:163 of nominees of the D'Arcy group and of the Anglc-oaxon Company, and shall be hell by them, but undertakings shall be exchanged between these parties whereby - (1) Mr. Gulbenkian undertakes to pay the calls or the shares, and / \ , r. _ t-o f . shares, and (2) The D'Arcy group and the Anglo-Saxon Company under take that Mr. Gulbenkian shall be entitled to all financial benefits of the shares. If Mr. Gulbenkian snail desire to dispose of his interest, and also in the event of his death, the D'Arcy and the Anglo-Saxon Company shall have tne option of purchasing the interests standing in their names on the terms defined in article 66 (b) of the articles of association of trie Turkish Petroleum! Company.10. The three groups participating in the Turkish Petroleum Company shall give undertakings on their own behalf and on behalf oi tne companies associated with them not to be interested directly or indirectly in the production or manufacture of cruae oil in the Ottoman Empire in Europe and Asia, except in that part which is under the administration of the Egyptian Government or of tne Sheikh of Koweit, or in the ” transferred territories 14 on the Turco-Persian frontier, otherwise than through the Turkish Petroleum Company. Foreign Office, London, March 19, 1914. (For the Imperial German Government), R. von KftHLMANN. (For His Britannic Majesty's Government), EYRE A. CROWE. (For the National Bank of Turkey), H. BABIHGTON SVIUH. (For tne Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company Limited) W. DETERGING, n A LT ER H . S A! !U E L . (For the Deutsche Bank), 0. BERGMANN. (For the D'Arcy Group), C. GREEN WAY. H. S. BARNES. I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000161_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/79</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000161</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/79</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 4668/33 'Turkish Petroleum Concessions'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-18T12:20:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear
to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description (used for referencing) commences at f 66, and terminates at f 70, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Thefile contains papers regarding the 1914 oil concession granted to the TurkishPetroleum Company, which became the Iraq Petroleum Company in 1929. The primarycorrespondent is H P W Giffard, Petroleum Department, Board of Trade.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Iraq Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Iraq</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000161#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>