<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00022b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:32:20.540Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© aL &lt; Q- FILE BEGINS FILE ENDS FILE NUMBER PARTRELATED FILES P UBLIC RECORDS ACT, 1958 (See paragraphs 24, I to 24, 4 of Part D of Digest of Office Procedure) When the officer dealing with this file considers that it is unlikely to be used again, or when the file is automatically closed at the end of a three-year cycle, the Higher Executive Officer (or Officer of higher rank) responsible for the subject should recommend in the appropriate space on the back cover of the file whether the file should be destroyed after a prescribed period or preserved. If he is unable to form a firm view, one of the spaces for “Consider at First/Second Review” should be signed: where this is done, a note must be placed on top of the file as the last paper giving reasons for deferring a decision. CROSS REFERENCED UNDER:— PRECEDENTS NOTED UNDER0 cx/Pirn gbouitds n: P-i'P-i: isi^d, 4 S?h9 site for a camping rollo^vin^ aclvs ''hioh has the -ground is Qadhaihipah plain. ■urvv ants ;es o 1 .r ot r sites in the island*^ omparative fr^edorn from, nos^aitoes -rhioh are very 1 :1 near date proves, w fW t l vtra^a ctv: a ' •&gt; - (2) 1T earhess toV the 'beach. ■ 3) Tavoarable nature of the soil, I.i. coarse shni iiich allows water to percolate readily, and does-not ;:old lew. (4) Comparative cleanliness, and absence of filth-heaps. (.5) P.upuiation of sllnority. f 6 ) fearness of water-supply. This site YZ?! rhich would easily accomodate a division, and with very little clearing would accomodate an •■rrry Corps, dlmost due south lies about ly miles/from the Agency 'etty from which the going to the camp is good. m he water-supply is at TJmm-ash-Bha*um on the south-west side of tin amping-ground^ The water is brackish but drinkable, and tl e supply is copious, and more than sufficient for the requirements of an arrq corps. r,, 'i 0 landing near the camp is not inconvenient, ^oats drawing 5 feet of water can be beached at high tide within about 100 yards of the high tide mark. The beach is firm sand. vj tPage two* that jolly 'boats oan unload at halt water* The chleh advantage of this landing place is that tropps and transport have no defiles through which they must pass* It is slightly further from the camping ground* (c) Grey Pauls compound wall oan 'be used 'by 6 to 8 'boats at exact high tide only, it is on the way from the Agency to the Customs* Animals will probably be landed by tipping the boats over at half or low tide* 100 mango wood planks, average dimensions 8* x 14' x 1 1/8 ' and 100 round baulks of about eachitfehfcy diameter have been supplied, half at each jetty* Disembarkation officers for the Agency jetty can stay at the Agency and those for the Customs jetty at Messrs. Grey Pauls* Signal stations can be erected on the roofs of the a above* Donkeys are largely used for unloading boats at low tide, 100 can probably be obtained. The transpor mules oan probably be used*There are tfhreeeeouroefl of drinklns water In Bahreini-* (a) Surface wells. (!&gt;} wells. (c; Springs in sea. (1} springe in island. (a) Surface .veils may he neslectod; they are scatter ed, liable to contamination and v^ry saline* (h) Deep wells aay he neglected for the present. They ai^e too remote and the supply is too snail and too difficult to get at. Later on it !nsy he advisahle to obtain water for t’-? hospital from the E-m-xi. ‘A r e 11, il miles away. (o) Springs in tiie sea r-iay he neglected owing to their position, saline nature and difficulty of wording. (d) 3p'insu. These springs propnhly are tha out-» flow of the central at ah i an rainfall, the water having passed under land an.’’ s for some hundreds of miles. Thu two which will 'best serve the Expeditionary force are the larger and the smaller Gaseri springs. The laige Gasari spring is situated at a distance of miles from the camp site A. The water is the hast spring water in the island# The supply is practically unlimited. The spring feeds a large pond on the edges of 'thich platforms for lifting water could easily he constructed from split palm trees • The small Gasari spring also enters a large pond hut the water is not quite so good or plentiful and the pond is the dhchi ghat of the town. The large Gasari should he used for drinking waterPage two and the small Gasarl for watering animals* Not only does teh superior quality of teh water make it advisable that the larger Gasari should be u used for drinking water, but it would cause a certain amount of discontent to have the town washermen turned away Tram the smaller Gasari* An Officers picquet might be placed on the large Gasari spring*Note on Camping Grounds. There are two possible camping grounds (a) Large Maidan behind the town. (b) sukh - ul - Khamis. Camp at (a) can be sited to allow a clear field of fire of 200 yards in all directions. The soil consists of a layer of coral, shells and sand about feet deep on coral rock; tell soil does not blow about tp any extent in even the highest wind. Uhe site has a very slight slope. Bain water percolates through the soil at once. Sub-soil water is about feet below the surface. A camp on this site would not be visible from the sea. The site is not commanded by any hills. There is a mud fort and a large house on the raaidan* the latter is nearest to the site - about 300 feards. Date palms grow on two sides whilst open maidan extends on the other sides. The site is fairly clean, but before camping on it lifcdAsffcecbmBieH&amp;edcthat a thorough search should be made for bones etc. The site is 1,100 yards from the mens* drinking water at the Larger Gasari, 900 yards from the horses 1 drinking water at the Canal Pond and 1,000 yards from the smaller Gasari. It is i mile from the bazaar. Just about a mile from the Customs Jetty anfl Just over a mile from the Agency Jetty. The approach to the actual ground offers no difficult ies except through the bazaar which is dealt with in the disembarkation note. The only hill in the island is Jubbul - Dukhan to the South.O- 1 *P ' we (]j; • This site is appro:'iv*iat«ly 2 miles from the kanaraa 3toms jetty f 5 0 from Uam sens 1 drinking water ;e Gasari, ards from the horses drinkig water j t the Smaller G-asari and 400 yards from the OsivOL J ond. nite consists of maidan and inounds ( ruins ) Or. -n o: en T.-r. e, z^y ?, , *n.le ly x mi;* surround W all sides 'by date palsts* In open area are two minaret/^s t a gravir yard and seM hemes to the 3outh. n^ as the name implies is the site of the Thursday mark-et and consequently ir'any areas ere litterd with the remi’ins of animals which have 'been • aoked f:nd consumed - t the faire* The ca/rp ooulfj he pitched so that there would 'be a clear field o^f fire of 200yards in all directions h tin . u 16 have to fee rather .straggling; the? date palms on all side a .offer to a oertaiii extent covered iggprMMMN By pitching tents on the aounds a certain amount ' wnd ecu i gained, . s of these mounds would only take one lino of tsnts, whilst the aides sloue vi ■ 1 1:«- ;C : . A caisp an this site vould wet fee visible from the sea, possibly the tops of tents pitched on tne tops of mounds might just be visible fro® ships. The approach to the site a lens the- North track offers no difficultiesj th-* roa 1 af^fer passing site (a) i-cr.es through da^.'. 'r* up to this sire. Several ditches aro cro«f?ed by oountry bridges 10* wide, spanning about 3*: these uppeer quite strong enough to curry infantry in fours. The approach aloi-g the South track passes over 7 country bridges all of which would have to be repair- ■Pag© three Generally sit e (a) is recommended. It compares unfavourably with site (b) only in its distance from the water supplies but on the other hand it is miles nearer to the sea front, affords greater facilities for protection, is more open, cleaner, more central, should prove to be less moscpi ito ridden, even slope, nearer to the source of supplies in the town, no difference in the soil.Supplies Fuel is very scarce and the greatest economy is recommended* political Resident has 'been warned that 9,000 res* per diem will he required until arrangements can he made from India* In the town t here are the following sullies Polder - hay or hhoosa is also procured from the Persian coast and Koweit, except lucerne of which a small supply is available* Rice*Notes for A* D. M. 8 The hot weather continues longer in Bahrein than anjnfhere else in the CJuif. Unless there le a • 8ha^\l ' i North vrinl ) severe aauu heat may he eapeotcl till the beginning of Novemuer andnthe rtu*gv of teiaporature is remarkably small between uJLdaay and the email hours of the morning* Tlie dew at night is very heavy* i'fever it. prevalent in the autumn and mosquitoes are abundant (speoiallv in the palm groves* lha best water in the island has elements in its composition which wake it liable to purge. The sanitary condition of the town and villages is appaling. Rainfall is very scanty f cn an averj^ge inches a year chiefly in November•Duties of various people when Shaik has 'been informed* (1) Sliaiic Abdulla and Amir of Manama* Preservation of order; m to he settled in conjunction with the Sheik. (2) Yusuf Khanoo* Hire 12 more boats* Btiy ixp fuel and lucerne. (3) Maharaj. Clear Customs Premises. (4) Mr. Grey. Put up g-.&amp;ding flags to water place. (5) Maharaj, zair Hassan, Jaur. Collect data re provisions.V RECOMMENDATION 1 FOR DISPOSAL RECOMMENDATION DESTROY AT FIRST REVIEW SIGNATURE DATE (i.e. within 5 years) DESTROY AT SECOND REVIEW (i.e. after 25 years) PRESERVE CONSIDER AT FIRST REVIEW CONSIDER AT SECOND REVIEW</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00022b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1820</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00022b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1820</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Camping grounds at Bahrain’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-18T13:56:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (20 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 22; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises maps and notes prepared in anticipation of the stopping off at Bahrain of Indian Army regiments that were part of Indian Expeditionary Force D, which travelled from Bombay to Basra in October 1914, and went on to fight in the Mesopotamian campaign of the First World War. The regiments stopped at Bahrain between 23 and 30 October 1914. However, in spite of the preparations made, no troops or livestock left the Expeditionary Force ships which moored off the Bahrain coast.The file contains:three hand drawn maps (one original and two tracings) showing the proposed sites for camps, and planned routes for infantry and animals from the selected disembarkation points in Manama, to the camps (ff 4-5, ff 6-8, ff 9-11);a carbon-copied sketch map of a camp, located one mile south of Manama, with allocated plots within the camp for different regiments, many of which were part of the 6th (Poona) Division (f 3);a general note entitled ‘camping grounds in Bahrain Island’ (f 2);disembarkation notes, identifying the customs jetty, Political Agency jetty, and the Gray Paul &amp; Company jetty, as the three points where disembarkation could take place (ff 12-13);a note on the availability of drinking water in Bahrain, including surface wells, deep wells, sea springs and island springs (ff 14-15);further notes on the two possible camping grounds identified (ff 16-18);a note on supplies, with brief details of fuel and fodder (f 19);notes for the ADMS [Assistant Director of Medical Services] on the climate and sanitary situation at Bahrain (f 20);duties of various people who would be involved in the disembarkation and supply of provisions (f 21).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Expeditionary Force D</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Manama</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military maps</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00022b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>