<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000068_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T16:42:01.454Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">C/940 - 28/20 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 3rd December 1940 Reference to previous correspondence: Descuptidn &lt;?/ Enclosure, l !/ . /V i/r Name and Date. Subject. Telegram No. 1436/27 dated the 27th November 1940 from Admiralty, London. Movements of enemy airliners.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000068_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/711</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000068</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/711</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/20 Movements of enemy airliners’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-26T21:06:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (f 4) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 5; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-3; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a single item of correspondence, a naval telegram dated 29 November 1940 from the Admiralty (f 2), forwarded by the Political Agency to the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf (f 3). The telegraph states that reporting officers in neutral countries should telegraph the movements of enemy airliners (civil aeroplanes, either freight or passenger) to both London and their intelligence centres.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aircraft</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000068#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>