<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000321_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T03:47:36.001Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">P. 4346/19. Si? B. 327. Mesopotamia: Assyrian Refugees at Baqubah. Note by Captain G. S. Reed, dated 1st July 1919. 1. Tt will be remembered that in August 1918 some 40,000 men women and ^ildren, consisting of 30 000 Assyrians from the Plain of Urmia and the district of Hakkari in lurkish Kurdistan together with some 10 ; 000 Armenians of the Van itl U1 ^ Occupied lerntory in an exhausted and destitute condition. Latei some thousands of Armenians from various parts of the Ottoman Empire, camp 130 CO eCte&lt; ^ m T ie ^ osu ^ ^ lla 3 Te t» were despatched and located in the Baqubah T ?' ihe Circumstances which led to the exodus of the Assyrian Christians from me Urmia district are apparently briefly as follows : — 3. In the year 1897 a Russian Orthodox Mission appeared in Urmia and promised political support to all who would accept Orthodoxy. With the exception of the few adherents of the American and French Missions all the Persian Assyrians enrolled, Ult X , n a? pe i° tG( A, pr - 0t ? ctl0ri dld not materialise for some time to come, and until the year 190 1 the Christians of the plain continued to be a contented and prosperous community of cultivators, living on friendly terms with their Persian masters and suilering only an occasional raid from the border Kurds. 4. About this time, some Turkish troops crossed the Persian frontier, and with t ic assistance of the Begzadeh Kurds, expelled the Christians from the district of 1 ergawar. 1 he lurks continued their advance on to the Plain of Urmia, arousing Russian suspicion, with the result that the Consular guard was substantially increased. A mixed Commission sat for some months and eventually the Turks retired to the disputed territory. 5. The Russians thereupon despatched some Cossacks to the village of Mawana for the purpose of repatriating the Assyrians of Tergawar, but they were defeated by the Kurds, who captured and grossly insulted the officer in charge. The repatriation scheme was thus for the moment abandoned, and the majority of the Christians settled on the Urmia plain until the year 1915, when an overwhelming Russian Army compelled the Kurds to vacate the district. (). from 1*108 ontil the outbreak of war the Russians gradually increased their power, until finally the administration of the whole plain was in the hands of a weak Consul and powerful and fanatical Orthodox Bishop. This latter naturally supported the Christians, who in consequence lorded it over, and made themselves generally unpleasant towards, the Muslim population. i. * * * * * * 8 i. 1 he Christians of Ilakkari in Turkish Kurdistan were divided into two classes:— (a) The tribal Assyrians ; (b) The Ryat or subject people. (a) lived in almost inaccessible fastnesses on the upper waters of the Great Zab—simple shepherds, armed with obsolete weapons and acknowledging no lordship other than their Patriarch Mar Shimon and their Maliks or chiefs. ^ The Turks had no direct dealings with them, but when opportunity occurred used all their influence to set the Kurdish tribes against them. The Assyrians, on the other hand, were always ready for reprisals againt the Kurds. (b) The Ryats—unarrfied cultivators—were scattered in villages amongst the Kurds and suffered heavily from raids, direct taxation from the Turks and indirect taxation from the Kurds. 8. Both classes were free from national aspirations, and on that account escaped the Armenian massacres of 1895 and 1896. They remembered, however, with gratitude what the British Government had accomplished for them at the time of the Bedr Khan massacres of 1840, and in time of stress always looked to His Britannic Majesty’s Consuls at Van and Mosul for support. S 48 50 8/J99 In the autumn of 1013 a Russian emissary toured the Assyrian tribal districts, distributing lavish gifts and promising modern rifles for the acceptance of Orthodoxy. The following months were spent in exchanging letters between the Holy Synod at Petrograd and Qudshanis (the Patriarchal residence) and this continued until the outbreak of war, hut without coming to an understanding. 10. In the month of October 1914 (before the declaration of war between Russia and Turkey) a strong force of Turks and Kurds crossed the Persian border, burnt several Christian villages and attacked the Russian troops at Urmia. The Christians of the plain were immediately armed and called upon to assist in the defence of the town—thus the Assyrians of the plain threw in their lot with the Russians. 11. In the following December the Turks attacked again, and this time succeeded in driving out the Russians. Many of the Assyrians left with them, but some 10,000 were trapped. Of these about 4,000 were killed or died of disease while imprisoned in ihe American Mission. 12. In May 1915 the Russians returned to Urmia, and shortly after advanced to Julamerk, where the Commanding Officer interviewed the Assyrian chiefs, and persuaded them to attack the Turks. This they consented to do, thinking that the Russians intended holding Julamerk and supporting them. The Russians, however, withdrew atter a few days and left the Assyrians to carry on alone. Towards the end of the summer, exhausted and without ammunition, they made their way through to Urmia, where they were formed into battalions under Russian commanders and w^ere used to subdue the Kurdish frontier tribes. 13. On the break-up-and withdrawal of the Russian Army the Assyrians (still commanded by Russian officers) carried on a defensive campaign only. The presence of these turbulent mountaineers from Turkish territory was distasteful to the Persians, and the Governor-General of Tabriz sent an expedition to drive them back to their own territory. This was defeated by the Assyrians, but it is to be regretted that many innocent Persians lost their lives in the fighting. 14. In January 1918 a British officer arrived at Urmia and promised to support the Assyrians in their w r ar against the Turks. Shortly after, a French Military Mission was sent, but on account of hostilities on the part of the Persians, shortly after withdrew, leaving behind one officer. 15. Events followed rapidly. Simko Agha, a Kurdish Chief of Kotur, invited Mar Shimon, the Assyrian Patriot, to a peace conference, on the conclusion of which Mar Shimon and his followers were murdered. The Assyrians retaliated, defeating Simko’s force and looting his stronghold. 16. Then followed a massacre of Assyrians at Khoi and a return of the Turkish army to the neighbourhood of Urmia. Fighting continued at intervals for the next few months, during which time the Turks were several times defeated, losing guns and prisoners. The Assyrians at this time, being short of ammunition and hard pressed, appealed to the British for the promised assistance. 17. Early in July 1918 an aeroplane was despatched from Mianeh to Urmia, carrying a letter which proposed that the'Assyrians should break through the Turkish line at Sujbulak and take over a convoy of ammunition and Lewis guns from the British at biain Kaleh. British officers were also to accompany the party back to Urmia and take over from the Russian officer the training of the' Assyrian force. 18. This programme was carried out with the exception of the return journey. As soon as the majority of the lighting men had left for Sain Kaleh, the Turks from the north advanced on the town of Urmia, and the remainder of tbe Christians fled south for protection behind the British lines. The journey of several hundreds of miles was one of panic and horror, the refugees being harassed by the Turks and Kurds until rescued by the British at Sain Kaleh. Thousands were killed or died of disease and starvation, others were stripped and many taken prisoners. •n* ^ 1 ^. mounta ^ n tnbes with the Armenians of Van increased the difficulties by killmg Muslims and looting property, but it is to their credit that they brought through their lurkish prisoners of war in safetvi ‘' J «“ ,l ““ 1 '“»»* it *.. d«w«d to foi . iLgo. Camp iflCS.h loot! dumps were hastily formed at stages along the road and tl,e P Jf J attuba1 '; down m companies of about 1,000 people. ’ ‘ ’ e lelu ff ees sent 21. By the end of October 1918 some 40,000 people were accommodated and Sofa dly 8 1,1016336,1 t0 neai ' Iy 50 ’ 00 °’ the maiEtena “ ce °f ‘he camp costing about 22 As long as the Assyrian country was occupied by Turkish troops, renatriathm 'as entirely out of the question, and ways and means were considered whereby the refugees might be usefully employed. e oj tne an 1 :/'■ T ' V0 f'TT ' vereaf ; nt 0Ut t0 work 011 farms - 0116 of which is still employed and giving satisfaction. Others were formed into labour corps to work on a wav construction and irrigation but on the whole they proved to be sorry workers and them fo. bem « separa 0,11 f heh ; fa ™ il ! es - finally, the scheme of employing them far away from camps was abandoned, but they continue to work on the railway m the Baqubah area and on camp duties. lway 24 On the announcement of the Armistice and the withdrawal of the Turkish hoops from Urmia, proposals were put forward for the people to return to their homes before the winter set in, in order to save their homes and vineyards and assure next year s wheat crop. J bure The refugees returning to Urmia were to proceed via Kifri and Rania and were ;o &gt;e accompanied to that point by a Political Officer and a squadron of Indian cavalry. p , 25 ; T } le ref,J Sees, who from the outset had been petitioning for a British 1 otec orate over them, feared to return without adequate guarantee Tor their future A[, f nE P b r e, T S | SlVen then V an a th ! S scherae ’ 0 “ t]l ? advice of f ]is Britannic Majesty’s risl involved ian&gt; WaS a ^ anc onec1, owl ^g to the disturbed state of Azerbijan and the 20. At the same time a scheme was put forward proposing that the Civil Commissioner should approach His Majesty’s Government with a view to obtaining sanction to set aside as a reservation for the mountain Assyrians a certain tract of country south of Amadia and in the Mosul Vilayet. It was felt that this scheme would no doubt be the most satisfactory in the long run, but it would require very drastic action at first, and would undoubtedly cause great and unwarranted hardship to a number ol Kurds. 1 27. Thus the problem of returning the mountaineers to their original homes was considered and it was unanimously agreed upon that it would never be safe to repatriate Chiistians m the midst of Kurdish tribes unless the Turks were first expelled and stiong gendarmerie garrisons (which were to include the Assyrian battalion of 1 000 trained mefo) placed at Julamerk and Diza Gawar. ^ eiK l i n v ‘ ew two officers were sent to reconnoitre ihe route via Mosul, and to report on the necessary medical and sanitary arrangements. An expert was also appointed to examine into and report on the amount of transport required for the inuxe, and for the feeding of the people after their arrival home and until their fields and irrigation channels had been repaired and the first harvest reaped. Small parties of refugees were located at various points to prepare food dumps, and the move was timed to begin in May after the .Mosul harvest had been reaped. Subsequent unrest among the Kurdish tribes to the north became apparent, and this scheme too, for the time being, was forcibly postponed. 29. At a Conference held on 13th March, on the recommendation of the medical authorities, it was agreed that for reasons of health the refugees from Urmia should be moved to a more suitable climate. Hamadan was suggested, with the proposal that the Persian Government, assisted by the American Relief Commission, should assume responsibility for the maintenance of the refugees on arrival at Hamadan and for their eventual repatriation thence to their homes. 30. The Assyrians were to he responsible for their own protection from the time they left Baqubah, and for this purpose an additional battalion of 1,000 rifles under4 British officers and British officer reserves was formed to enable these refugees to protect themselves on arrival in their own country. 31. The proposition to the effect that the mountaineers and Urmia Assyrians should be repatriated by different routes called for a protest from the latnarch War Shimon, who complained that it would effectually destroy national unity and undo his own position. He also stated that he would be powerless to prevent the mountaineers from accompanying the Urmia party to Hamadan. 32. In addition the Urmia refugees feared that*without adequate protection they would be unable to return via the Bijar-Sain Kaleh road, where they at the leai o the party had already suffered so much on account of the excesses committed by the mountain refugees on the way down. Expert opinion was inclined to the view that if the Urmia refugees were to be sent via Hamadan, the only possible route onwards was via Zinsan and Tebriz. Even this was only possible subject to successful operations being concluded against the Jungalis. 33. The Persian Government, on being approached, definitely stated that “ they “ had strong objections to the refugees being armed, and in the present circum- “ stances they cannot return unarmed, as they would without doubt be attacked by “ the Muslims.” Further, they refused to accept any responsibility in the matter. 34. In addition, the Chairman of the Persian Armenian Relief Commission stated that their funds were insufficient to look after the refugees on arrival at Hamadan. Moreover, the Commission considered that such work was beyond the scope of a civilian relief organisation. 35. The refugees themselves petitioned that they might be allowed to return home via Erbil and Rowanduz or Neri, but on examination this was ruled out on the grounds of the utter impossibility of passing a large body of persons through a country with bad roads and no transport facilities, in addition to the fact that in their more prosperous days certain of the refugees had assisted the Russians in the work of completely devastating the whole area. 36. Intelligence from Urmia at this time was most unsatisfactory. Major Eadie visited the town in April and reported that feeling against the return of the Christians and against all foreigners was very strong. No. Christians could leace the American Mission premises, and, to show the bitter feeling that still existed, he mentioned the fact that the Muslims had been digging up the Christians’ corpses, cutting off their heads, and leaving the corpses thus unburied. 37. A British Vice-Consul left Baghdad for Urmia in June, and, for the present, the repatriation is at a standstill pending his arrival. 38. In the meantime preparation for repatriating the Mountain Assyrians continued, and a party belonging to the Bohtan area actually left for Zakho, but on 21st April the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief announced that, owing to the impossibility of exercising military control outside the Mosul boundary, the occupation of Julamerk and Diza Gawar was no longer contemplated. 39. Investigations were made with a view to ascertaining suitable locations for the tribal Assyrian refugees within our boundary in the district of Amadia. Two officers of the Political Department, accompanied by representative Assyrians, left for Mosul, and reported on several likely districts. Various tracts of land capable of supporting a substantial population were found, but located in districts likely to arouse Kurdish prejudice, and, without a strong protective force, liable to risk permanent disorder. 40. \V ith regard to the \ an Armenians, it has been obvious from the first that any attempt to move them through Kurdish country would be a grave error. Major Noel, travelling in Kurdistan, reported that “the attitude of the tribes may be “ expressed by the statement that their country is at present practically rid of “ Armenians and that they are determined that it shall remain so.” Ihe only possible solution is, therefore, to despatch them to Egypt as soon as shipping becomes available, and to wait there pending the future political arrangements in Armenia.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000321_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B327</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000321</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B327</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Mesopotamia: Assyrian refugees at Baqubah. Note by Captain G S Reed, dated 1 July 1919'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-22T22:07:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 61, and terminates at f 62, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of a document by Captain G S Reed which provides an overview of the history of the Assyrian Christians in Urmia and the circumstances that led to their mass exodus to Baqubah in 1918. Reed also details the difficulties of the repatriation of these refugees back to Urmia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>G S Reed</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Baqubah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Urmia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Assyrians</topic></subject><subject><topic>Repatriation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Muslims</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Refugees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious discrimination</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000321#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>