<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024b_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-03T12:46:08.809Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">©17© Z/0 OR* I tS£b. ■RITISH RFSICEMCY &amp; C^MSULATE-GENERAL, USIf IRE, /O - OCTOBER Idtb. COLONEL E. C. ROSS , C. 5». I . , POLITICAL RESIDENT I f7 THE PERSIAN OULF « H. M* S CONSUL-GENERAL FOR PARS, THE SECRETARY TO^T’^E GOVE RNM EN T 3 p INDIA, POREIGN DEPARTMENT, SIMLA, l HAVE THE HONOR TJ SURMIT AN ACCOUNT OP MY RECENT VISIT TO EL-BIDAA AND INTERVIEW WITH SHAIPH JASTM WIN MOHAMED KIN THANT WHICH I HAVE BRIEFLY REPORTED BY TELEGRAM ON b TH INSTANT. 2. COMMANDER BOLD E RO COMMANDING H. M. S. * f SPHI NX' * K I NDL i RECEIVED ML AND M K A. R. HAKIM ON BOARD TTfE VESSEL UNDER HIS COMMAND ON THE 2ND INSTANT, AND ON THE 3RP WE ANCHORED AT BAHRAIN WHERE I HAD AN INTERVIEW WITH SHAIKH e,SAU BIN AL I THE CHIEF. HIS BROTHER SHAIKH . AHMED HAD BEEN ATTACKED BY SMALL-POX,WHICH IS PREVALENT ON THE ISLANDS. THE SHAIKH HAD NOTHING OP IMPORTANCE TO COMM JNI CA rr_. HE HAD HEARD THAT HIS UNCLE MOHAMMED- BIN KHALEEFAH HAD GONE TO JOIN l BN RASHID AT J EB EL shammak BUT ON NO GOOD authority ON THE 3RD INSTANT WE ANCHORED IN EL-BlDA A PAY ANDW H I L S T ANr I SENT A MOONSHEE ASHORE TO INFORM SHAIKH KHALEE^AH BIN JASIM OF MY ARRIVAL AND REQUEST HIM TO INFORM HIS FATHER T shaikh jasim^ho WAS residing a r PHAAYEN which is aroui AN hour's RIDE FROM EL-BIPAA. A TURKISH NAVAL OFFICER,-** ARt-AKENTLY A SORT OF PORT OFFICER ^CAME ON BOARD THE ''SPHINX** IN A STEAM LAUNCH AND INQUIRED WHAT VESSEL IT WAS WH© WAS ON BOARD AND WHAT WE HAD COME FOR .HE ALSO ASKED IF WE REQUIRED WATER OR SUPPLIES, IN THE EVENING KHALEEFAH BIN JASIM CAME ON FOARD AND INFORMED ME HIS ; FATHER WOULD RE IN NEXT MORNING, 4. ®M THE 4TH SHAIKH JASIM RODE IN TO EL-BTDAA AC- -COMPANTED 5 Y ASOUT 7®© MOUNTED ARABS, CHI EFL Y ON CAMELS^ AND I LANDED AND WAS RECEIVED VERY CIVILLY AT HIS f©rt AND RESIDENCE JUST OUTSIDE THE TOWN. I ANNEX A PRECIS OF THE CONVERSATION WHICH WE HAD . ALTHOUGH JASIM REVERTED TO HIS ALLEGED GRIEVANCES AND RE- I DERATED HIS COMPLAINTS OF HAVING BEEN UNJUSTLY PUNISHED ,HE DTD NOT DISPLAY ANY PERSONAL ILL-FEELING TOWARDS ME. ON THE CONTRARY HE MADE SOME COMPLIMENTARY RE? 'A RK S, WHILST ASSERTING THAT » I HAD BEEN MISLED IN THE PARTICULAR INSTANCES HE RE- -FERREP TO. MY OBSERVATION HOWEVER WENT TO STRENGTHEN MY BELIEF IN JASIM’s ABILITY T© PREVENT DISORDERS AT EL-BIDAA, ©N THE PART OF PERSONS RESIDING THERE O F-v FREQUENTING If ; IF HE IS SINCERELY DISPOSED TO DO SO. I DO NOT ; HOWEVER/ CONSIDER IT WOULD BE RIGHT OR POLITIC TO PRESS RESPONSI B l LI TY/ F©n RECENT CASES OF IRREGULARITY HOME TO HIM BY ACTIVE MEASURES IN EXISTIN''- CIRCUMSTANCE!.WHILST UKGIHG HIM TO CO-SPEhATE WITH US OH THE SITE O^ LAW AT«rr OnrER. T SHALL wot taite aw Y ACTIOW p-OR the PRESENT CALCULATEP TO PISTURW OUR FRIENDLY RELATIONS._ THERE IS LITTLE POU*'! THAT IF THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT COULD INDUCE THE TURFS TO WITHDRAW FROM THE FA TR COAST, WE COULD MAFE SATISFACTORY ARRANGEMENTS WITH JASIM.THIS ■ El NO,HOWEVER, AS I UNDERSTAND OUT THE QUESTION AT PRESENT,WE MAY HAVE TO ADOPT OTHER MEASURES TO SUPPRESS DISORDERS AT SEA. IT IS QUITE POSSIBLE THOUGH THAT THE ADVENT OF I RN RASHEED MAY ALTER OR MODIFY THE FRESEl'TT ST TUA TI ON. 5. SHATFH JASTM PRETENDS TO FNOW NOTHING OF THE I BN RASHEED* S MOTIVE IN PREPARI'TG T© MARCH EASTWARDS J BEYOND THE PROJECTED ATTACF on THE BENI YAS CHIEF , BUT I T IS UNLIKELY I BN RASHEED WOULD MOVE p*OR THAT OBJECT ONLY,AND MY INFORMATION TENDS TO SHOW THAT HE IS IN COMMUNICATION WITH THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT AND AUTHORITIES OU THE SUBJECT OF HIS PROJECTED EXPEDITION. ^ 1 ALSO ENCLOSE A SUMMARY O F NEWS COLLECTED AT EL-BIDAA BY THE RESIDENCY MOONSHEE WHILST ASHORE THERE.. IT IS CURIOUS THAT THE IDEA IS ALREADY AFLOAT .OK ATTACHING RELIGIOUS SIGNIFICANCE TO IBM RASHEEP's f SUCCESSES AND PESIGIIS. HIS CAREER HAS BEEN MARKED BY A COOT DEAL OF BLOOBSHEDDING , AND THE RECENT SLAUGHTER OF THE SONS OF SUOOD CANNOT COMMAND UNIVERSAL APPROBA- - I I ON IN AKAjr/A;BUT THIS WOULD NOT LONG STAND IN THE WAY OF HIS ACCEPTANCE AS AN lI'ISPIf^.ED LEADER, IF THE THEORY BECOMESBECOMES P0PUL.A K 7 . THE PRESENT TURKTSIf GUA RP AT EU-BIPAA CONSISTS OF ABOUT 2t»0 REOUL.A R SOT^r'IERS . I HAP PERSONALLY NO COMMUNICATION WHATEVER WITH ANY PURELY TURKISH OFFICIAL AT EL-BIDAA. I HAVE THE HONOR TO BE, SIR, YOUK MOS' OB EC l ENT, SERVANT SP E.C. ROSS, COLONEL, POLITICAL REST BENT, PERSI AN GULF. NO. OF t 888 . COPY FORWARDED TO POLITICAL AGENT * CONSUL,HUSKAT, FOR INFORMATION.PRECIS OF A CONVERSATION BETWEEN THE RESTTENT AND SHAIKH JASIM AT EL-BIDAA ON THE 5TH OCTOBER Ibbd. AFTER THE USUAL INTERCHANGE OF COMPLIMENTARY EN QUIRIES AFTER HEALTH AC, JASIM SAID HE HAD CERT AIN THINGS TO SPEAK ABOUT IF THE RESIDENT WOULD HEAR HIM. THE RESIDENT ASSENTED,AND JASIM BEGAN BY SAYING THAT AS REGARDS THE MATTER OF THE BANYAS AND THE TREATMENT HE HAD RECEIVED,HE WAS UNJUSTLY TREATED. THE RESIDENT TOLD K IM THE MATTER HAD BEEN SETTLED AND DID NOT REQUIRE RENEWAL. TH EN HE SPOKE ABOUT THE MATTER OF THE OUT RAGES AND DEPREDATIONS OF THE BENI HAJ I R AT SEA*, AND S*AD THAT NOTWITHSTANDING THAT THE GREATER PART OF THE # PROPERTY PLUNDERED BELONGED TO HIM AND HIS SONS, AND THAT HE HAD RESIGNED HIS OFFICE AND POS I TI ON AT EL- BI DA' AND NOTIFIED THE SAME TO ALL THE PEOPLE A N r ' TO THE TURKS, THE RESIDENT LISTENED TO THE STATEMENTS OF PEOPLE AGAINST HIM, AND DETAINED HIS PROPERTY AT BAHRAIN. HE WAS THUS COMPELLED TO GO AFTER THE OFFENDING BEDOUINS INLAND, AND SUCCEEDED IN RECOVE?-* I NG WHAT WAS POSSIBLE; AND THIS CIRCUMSTANCE LED TO THEIR BECOMING Hit; ENEMIES. EV EN NASIR BIN MU BA Rl K BECAME ANGRY WITH HIM AND IF t THEY FU-ID AN OPPORTUNITY THEY WOULD PLUNDER IT I M AND EVEN KILL HIM; THAT NOTWITHSTANDING THE ABOVE RESULTS THE RESIDENT HELD HIM RESPONSIBLE .AT p*IRST HE AVOIDED THE TURKS,BUT WHEN HE WAS TREATED AS ABOVE HE HAD RE COURSE TO them; AND TOLD THEM THAT AT R“TRST HE DID NOT WANT THEM BUT NOW HE DID. THEY REPLIED THAT HE SHOULD \ j \ I 1 V £ iI GIVE THEM A LETTER OF GUARANTEE, SA V T HG THAT HE WILL BE OBEDIENT TO THEIR ORDERS; THAT HE SHOULD ACCEPT A DE CORATION FROM THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT,AND ALSO A SALARY; THAT HE SHOULD NOT CORRESPOND WITH THE ENGLISH ,THAT HE SHOULD NOT ALLOW THEIR VESSELS TO ANCHOR IN THE PORT; I . E. EL- B T DAA NOR ALLOW ANY of them to land. he had accepted all THE l K CONDITIONS AND GAVE THEM IN WRITING WHAT THEY WANTED. THE MATTER WAS REPORTED TO BUS RAH AND THEN TELEGRAPHED TO CONSTANTINOPLE, THEN NAFTZ PASHA CAME TO EL-RIDA WITH INSTRUCTIONS, AND HE HAD WITH HIM THE DECORATION AND MONEY FOR HIS SALARY. BUT HE HESITATED AND THOUGHT THAT IF HE ACCEPTED THEIR OFFERS THEY WOULD BE HIS MASTERS AND WOULD THEN SEIZE HIM. THEN HE REPLIED THAT HE WOULD KEEP HIS PROMISES TO THE?', BUT HE WOULD NOT ACCEPT THE DECORATION, AS HE DID NOT WANT ONE. THAT HE DID ALL THIS BECAUSE THE RESIDENT HAD LISTENED TO WHAT PEOPLE SAID AGAINST HIM; EVEN HIS BROTHER WAS AGAINST HI” AND CHA KG ED H I M W I TIT OR 7 'A T I Tld ’' I SCH I E^ AND DISTURBANCE. THAT NOW HIS OBJECT IS TO KEEP ALOOF from the turks; that he did not want them; that his OBJECT IS TO SETTLE AT ODAIP, AND THAT HE WOULD GIVE A GUARANTEE THAT NO DISTURBANCE SHALL TAKE PLACE AT SEA. THE RESIDENT TOLD HIM THAT IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE approval of the British government odaid belongs to THE CHIEF OF ABOOTHABEE; AND IT WAS IMPOSSIBLE ^OR HIM TO SETTLE THERE. THEN JASIM SAID THAT IF THIS CANNOT BE DONE HE WOULD SETTLE INLANP TO THE SOUTH O^ ODA ID, N EARtt EA R ZlL/&gt; ANT THAT THE HESTDEHT M A V GIVE ORDERS THAT HO ONE SHOULD INTERFERE WITH THE PROVISION BOATS WHICH MIGHT CALL THERE WITH PROVISIONS FOR HIM. THE RESIDENT REPLIED THAT IT WOULD NOT MATTER IF HE DID NOT EXCEED THE LIMITS OF WAHKAH WHICH WAS THE LIMIT O^ THE FATAR ' r* JURISDICTION. JASIM INTERPOSED BY SPYING THAT THE LIMITS OF KATAk EXTENDED SOUTH OF ZIL*, THE RESIDENT REJOINED THAT ir COULD NOT BE ALLOWED. THE RESIDENT THEN TOLD HIM THAT HE WISHED HIM TO BE A POWERFUL CHIEF IN THOS'' PARTS; AND THAT HE HELD HIM AS THE HEAD VAN IN THE DISTRICTS OF F A T A k; AND THAT IN THE EVENT OF ANY MISCHIEF OCCURRIM? THE MATTER SHOULD BE REF^RRE^ TO HIV. THAT THE TURFS HAD ENTERED THr PLACE WITHOUT THE KNOWLEDGE OF THE BRITT SIT GOVERNMENT^ WHO DO NOT RECOG NIZE THE CLAIM OF THE TURFS TO THESE PLACES*, AND THAT HE WISHED TO DEAL SOLELY WITH JASIM AS REGARDS THE AFFAT RS OF EL- B l D A A ( FATR. ) the resident enquired about the movements of I bn RASH E ED. AND SHAIKH JASIM SAID THAT HE WILL COME TO THESE PARTS WHEN THE WEATHER GETS COOLER; HE HAS A LARGE FORCE MOUNTED ON HORSES AND CAMELS, HIS JOURNEY FROM RlADTH TO EL-HASA WILL OCCUPY ABOUT I 5 DAYS, INSTEAD QF IC DAYS AS HE WILL HAVE A LARGE FOLLOWING; HE WILL TAFE ABOUT EL-HADHR IO DAYS TO REACH THESE PARTS FROM EL-HASA *, THAT ALL THE AS PI ST IN.- . ^ -GUI SHED SETTLED INHABITANTS OF TOWNS AND VILLAGES ARE WELL from the F: EDOUINS. AFFECTED TOWARDS HIM. HE HAS CAUSED THREE SONS OF SAOOD TO BE FILLED; THERE IS NOW ONE SON OF S/OOD BYI. n I NAME ABDUL AZEEZ LEFT, WHO IS ft I Til HIS UNCLE ABDULLAH s at hail. the ajman have not as yet tendered their allegiance to i bn rasheed; WITH THIS EXCEPT! ot^ all the other tribes have become obedient to him; and especially THE SETTLED TRIBES, WIT O LIKE HIM f A S THERE IS NO: PEACE, QUIET AND SAFETY IN EVER* PLACE, AND NO AGGRESSIVE MOVE- HEN IS ARE UNDERTAKEN BY ANY TRIBEJ. I BN RASHEED HAS UN- •jt DERTAKEN THE EXPEDITION WITH THE ASSENT AND PERMISSION TO OMAN OF THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT. HE DESIRES TO TAKE ON LEASE^ FROM TUR KISH GOVERN .EL-HASA AND KAiEEF ; AND IF THIS TAKES PLACE THERE WILL MENT. BE SAFETY AND TRANQUILLITY IN THE COUNTRY; SO ALSO ON THE SEA*, WHEREAS THE TURKS ADOPT NO MEASURES FOR 1 ENSURING SAFETY AND SECURITY. ^ \ s AT PRESENT AT KATEEF THE ROBBERS COMMIT THEFTS ' \ . AND ROBBERIES IN THE TOWN ITSELF; THEY CARRY OF^ NUMBERS OF FAMILIES, AND DEMAND A RANSOM FOR THEIR RELEA.SE; BUT THE TURKS DO NOT TAKE MEASURES TO SEIZE THEM, NOTWITHSTANDING THAT THEY OCCUPY KATEEF*, THEY WANT UNDISPUTED EVIDENCE AGAINST ROBBERS, BEFORE ACTING AND S O ON. THE RESIDENT INFORMED SHAIKH JASIM THAT HE HOPED IF THE NEJD FORCE CAME, IT WOULD LEAD TO NO INTERFERENCE WITH BRITISH INTERESTS, AS JASIM KNEW CERTAIN PLACES ^BAHRAIN AND TRUCIAL PQRTS^WEKE PROTECTED BY THE BRITISH. INVASION OF OMAN WOULD RE DI S PL E A SIWG TO THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT f WHICH WOULD HOT ALLOW MUSKAT TO BE INTERFERED WITH. SHAIKH JASIM SAID HE KNEW NOTHING ABOUT SUCH MATTER ; HE WAS ONLY CONCERNED IN ATTACKING THE ABU-DHABI C J-C I EF 0 .17 CHIEF, THE RESIDENT SAID IT WOU'CD BE W El&gt; T -, FOR I BN RASHEED TO UNDERSTAND THAT BRITISH INTERESTS MUST BE RESPECTED BY HIM. SHAIKH JASIM SAID THAT AS THINGS ARE NOW, AND WITH / THESE TURKS IN OCCU P A T I ON , T RAN QU T UL, I TY THESE PARTS CANNOT BE SECUREr; IN FACT MISCHIEF W I L,L, DA I T -y Y INCREASE. THE RESIDENT ASKED HIM WHAT MEASURES H E WOUt^D SUGGEST IN VIEW TO RESTORING SECURITY IN THESE PARTS. HE SAID IF THEY WANTED TO ENSURE THE TRANQUILLITY OF THESE PARTS ONE HUNDRED BEDOUINS OR ARAB SOWARS, AT 6 DOLLARS EACH FOR SALARY PER MENSEM, SHOULD BE PLACED UNDER HIS ORDERS TO WATCH THE COAST FROM BAHRAIN TO ODAID AND HE WOULD THEN GUARANTEE SECURITY AT SEA. BUT THIS ARRANGEMENT SHOULD BE MADE BY THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT, AND THEY SHOULD GIVE HIM THEIR SUPPORT AND PROTECTION. THE RESIDENT SAID THAT IF HE WAS SINCERE IN HTS PROFESSIONS AND DID HTS B ES T / THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT WOULD ALWAYS TREAT HIM WITH REGARD AND CONSIDERATION. JASIM WAS VERY DECIDED IN SAYING THAT IF I BN KASHEED COMES TO THESE TERRITORIES HE WOULD HELP HIM TO THE BEST OF HIS ABILITY,IN VIEW TO TAKING HIS REVENGE FROM THE CHIEFS OF ABOOTHABEE; THAT HE WOULD NEVER GIVE UP HIS REVENGE, AND SOUGHT JUSTICE FOR THE WRONGS HE HAD SUFFERED. AS REGARDS THE AL-BUKUWARAH OUTRAGE AGAINST THE AT boat of THE AMAMERAH n BAHRAIN,JASTM SAID THE OFFENDERS LIVEDl LIVED/SOME at fowfi^kat and others at el-zaayen; that HE HAD NO POWER OVER THEM; THAT THEY WERE A POWERFUL iRlBE.AND HE 'WAS AFRAID OF THEM:HE WAS ALONE AND HIS TRIBESMEN ,THE MAADHEED,LI VED FAR AWAY FROM HIM,AND THESE might KILL HIM. he THEN SAID THAT WHEN THEY BEACH their vessels a^ter the pearlfishery their boats might Be. S'-I^c.D burned; that some time ago when they heard that A MAN-OF-WAR WAS IN SEARCH OF THEM,SOME FOOLISH ONES AMONGST THEM SAID THAT IF THEY ARE FOLLOWED UP IN THIS MANNER, THEY WOULD PUT TO SEA AND PLUNDER VESSELS AND THEN FLEE INTO THE INTERIOR. THE RESIDENT THEN ASKED HIM TO INFORM THE AL AS B UKAWA RAH THAT SO LOHG^THE MATTER WAS NOT SETTLED AND SATISFACTION RENDERED, Bi tAVMENT OF FINE OK OTHERWISE THE WHOLE tribe would be held responsible in THE matter: that 1 -IME WILL BE GIVEN TO THEM TO MAKE PROPER REPARA TION : I F THE, WRITE AN APOLOGY,AND PAY A SUITABLE FINE J THE MATTER MAY BE SETTLED; BUT IF NOT, IT WILL NOT RE fokgotten; and the whole tribe will be held responsible.' SHAIKH JASIM PROMISED TO DO THIS. AS REGARDS THE PIRACY ON THE BOATS OF HAJI BIN AHMED AND HASAN-EL-BASREE, JASIM SAID THAT THE BENI HA JI R OFFENDERS HAD GONE TO THE INTERIOR TO THEIR HOMES BE TWEEN EL-OJAIR AND EL-HASA. AND THEY WERE FAR AWAY from him; that the shaikh of Bahrain had written to him ABOUT THESE CASES, AND THAT HE HAD REPLIED TO HIM TO K&lt;=^\ r. The1 © MtWb Rr.POKr OBTAINED BY M.LKZA ABU T w KASIM AT FD- f A BIDAA. DATED 5TH OCTOBER T 8 bb. SHAIKH JASIM HAS RECEIVED LETTERS FROM IBP RASHEED TO THE EFFECT THAT HE WILL SHORTLY START FROM KIADTH FOR EL-HASA; WHENCE HE WILL PROCEFr TO EL-ZAFRAH A rEPc.NDc.NCY OF SHAIKH Z A EED, WHERE HE HAS TOLD JASIM TO JOIN HIM. HE WILL BE ACCOMPANIED BY A LARGE FORCE, MOUNTED on horses and camels, he is awaiting arrival op LETTERS FROM CONSTANTINOPLE. JASIM HAS A LARGE STOCK OF BARLEY AND WHEAT AND ABOUi 700 OF THE MANASEER; AL-HURRAH, BENT HAJR AND SOME EL-SAHOOL BEDOUINS ARE WITH HI' AND THE FORCES QP I bn RASHEED. IT is SAID. WILL EYCE^D 7,000 MOUNT ED MEN. iHr. WAHAABEE f MATOWWAS* * DECLARE THAT ACCORDING TO THE TRADITIONS OF THE PROPHET, IN THE LATTER DAYS, THERE WILL APPEAR A MAN FROM THE HTJAZ OF THE AL-KAHTAN WHOSE NAME WILL BE MOHAMED BIN ABDULLAH WHO WILL BE THE NORTH CHILDLESS,AND WILL COME FROM EL-SHAM. HE WILL BE A WEST RELIGIOUS MAN. AND PEOPLE WILL BE INCLINED TOWARDS HIM ON ACCOUNT OR HIS JUSTICE AND EQUITY. HE WILL GAIN POSSESSION O F THE LANDS IN ARABIA, AND THE PEOPLE WILL TENDER THIER ALLEGIANCE TO HIM AND HE WILL BRING PEACE AND QUIET TO THE COUNTRIES OF THE MUSLIMS. THE MATOWWAS* say THAT The ABOVE PREDICTION APPLIES TO 3** I BN RASHEED IN EVERY WAY, HIS NAME IS MOHAM ED- BIN ABDULLAH OF THE AL-KAHTAN FROM THE HtJAZ. KSIR, MO . J /6 O F I 8 bb. BRITISH ReSIDSMCY &amp; CONSL!L,AT a-G SNERAL,, ?tr BUSHI RE ,‘ OCTOBER 1888. COUOMEL £.C.ROSS,C.S,I. POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PiRSIATI GULF A H.M'S CONSUL-GENERAL FOR KARS, THE SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT, SIMLA. ■ SI I HAVE THE HONOR TO ENCLOSE TRANSLATI ON,? OF REPORTS RECEIVED NOS. 126 AND 13 I ,DATED . 6 TH AND I2TH OCTOBER I 888 . FROM THE RESIDENCY AGENT AT BAHRAIN, RELATIVE TO THE EXPECTED MOVEMENT OF THE CHIEF OF JE3EL SHAMMAR EASTWARDS. 2. IT WOULD APPEAR FROM THESE REPORTS THAT THE ARABS OF CENTRAL NEJD ARE NOT UNANIMOUSLY FAVOURABLE TO IBM RASHEED, AND THAT, ON SOME AT LEAST, THE RUTHLESS SLAUGHTER OF THE SONS OF SUOOD HAS MADE AN IMPRESSION WHICH MIGHT LEAD TO DIFFICULTIES IN HIS PA T * T . 3. IT SEEMS TOLERABLY CERTAIN NOW THAT THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT AND AUTHORITIES ARE IN COMMUNICATION WITH IBM RASHEED ON THE SUBJECT OF HIS DESIGNS. I HAVE &amp;C, POLITICAL RESIDENT,PERSIAN GULF,*- •. MOHENNA CHIEF OF BOREYDAH.AND TO ZAMIL CHIEF OF ANEYZAH, OF EL-KASEEM, THAT THEY S HO JED PRESENT THEMSELVES IN EL-JSBEL^JEBEl. SHAMMAR jMW THAT THEY DECLINED TO GO, AND REPLIED THAT THEY FEARED LEST HE SHOULD TR S.AT TH iM AS HE HAD TREATED THE SONS OF SUOOD. AND HASAN BIN MOHSNNA and ZAMIL are related to one another and the people of ♦ KASEEIM ARE MORS'POWERFUL THAN IBM RASHEED. THE LATTER ALSO WISH , £D TO TAX TFTS OTSYSAH TRI3l£.W^O DID MOT CONSSHT. IT IS MO T KNOV/M WM^TM'iR IBTI RASMaiD I L,L» ' 'A v ^ A SUFF I C I-iMTLY FRiS MAMD TO PROC»££D AGA I TTST OMAM . AMD MOW THS PEOPLE OF KOWSYT ARE ENEMIES OF IBM RASRiED % AfID V/ISM HIM ILL.0CT03-IR Ibbb. fFOM RiSlDaTTCY AG aNT BAffRAIM, fie t 13 1 DAT*Er l?ZH THE POLITICAL RES I DENT , PERSIAN GU L»F , A KAFI L»AH HAS ARRIVED FRO\5 EL-HASA BY WAY OF OJA I R ; AND IT LEFT EL-HASA FOUR DAYS AGO # A JEW V/HO GOES TO AND FROM EL HAS A INFORMS ME THAT ABOUT I 8 MEN OF THE £L-S.a3AN TRTBE, SENT BY I BN RASH EEC' TO THE COVER NOR OF EL-HASA ; HAD ARRIVED AT EL-HASA FROM JEBEL SHAMMAR AND HAD BROUGHT LETTERS FROM I BN RASHEED TO THE SAID MUTASERRIF,WHO GAVE THEM ALL ROBES OF HONOUR. X: FREQUENT CORRESPONDENCE IS KEPT UP BETWEEN THE MUTASER- RIF AND IBN RASHEED, AND THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT IS FRIENDLY TO I BN RASHEED,AND SHORTLY IN THE COOL WEATHER IBN RASHEED WILL WITHOUT FAIL OR DOUBT ARRIVE AT EL- HASA , AND THENCE PROCEED TO OMAN, AND THIS IS WELL KNOWN AND THE COMMON TOPIC OF CONVERSATION AMONGST PEOPLE OF EL-HASA, AND PRIVATELY AMONGST THE TURKS. INFORMANT SAYS THAT SOME HEWS ABOUT MOHAMED BIN SUOOD IS DAILY SPREAD AND THE ARABS LAY WAGERS. ^THE / TRUTH OF HIS BEING ALIVE DOES NOT APPEAR; THE PRO BABILITY IS HE WAS SLAUGHTERED. IT IS SAID THAT THE CHIEF OF THE AJMAN,NAMED RU KAN ; WHO WAS FOR SOME TIME WITH IBN RASHEED,HAS BEEN ALLOWED TO LEAVE. THERE ARE FOUR SONS OF JALWEE.WHO WAS A BROTHER OF*o T'Tti POLITICAL RSSIDiriT, PfiRS I AM GULP', DATiP 2 1ST OCTOBER iBBB. A. C . A SPECIAL MESSENGER OF JASIM B RT MO' T A^iEP BIN ‘HAN I CAME TO LINGAH, HE STATED THAT * 1 I BN RASH TED 1 ' rl HAD S £NT HIM WITH LETTERS VIA HOWAIT TO JASIM BIN THAN I AT KATAR, THAT HE HAD LETTERS FROM JASIM FOR SHAIKH RASHED CHIEF OF DE3AY,AND SHAIKH SAKAR CHIEF OF SHARGAH AND MOHAMED BIN ALI EL-NAAlMEE OF BAREYMEEjTHE LETTERS, HE SAID, INTIMATED THAT*' I BN RASHEED * *W ILL ARRIVE AT KATAR ON THE 3 I ST OCTOBER IBBB, AND WILL PROCEED TOWARDS OMAN,GOING DOWN AS FAR AS MUSKaT AND J ALAN,AND THAT WHOEVER WILL TENDER ALLEGIANCE TO HIM NOW SHALL BE IN SAFETY,BUT ON THE ARRIVAL OF THE FORCES OF IBN RASHEED IN OMAN, HE WOULD NOT ACCEPT AMY ONE'S EXCUSE, AND WOULD SUBMIT THEM TO SEVERE TREATMENT, AND THAT HE ASI Ml INTENDS SENDING PROVISIONS AND AMMUNITION TO SHARGAH AND DEBAY FOR THE USE OF THE FORCES * T^AT THE MESSENGER HAD INSTRUCTIONS TO DELIVER THE LETTERS PERSONALLY TO THE ABOVE CHIEFS, AND TAKE THEIR REPLIES THE MESSENGER FURTHER STATES THAT JASIM IS USING HIS /* TRAMSLATiD BY A.R.RAKIM. TO f no: 3 1. Off 1889. BRITISH R-iSIDSMCY &amp; COMSUL,AT GETIL,! BUSHIRE JMSTT JANUARY 1889. HIS HIGHNESS SSYYID PEYSAL BIN TOORHI, . MUSKAT. A . O . j I HAVE THE HONOR TO ACHNOWL,EDGS YOUR HIGHNESS* LETTfRQN the subject of THE REPORTS about the smir ibn rasheed i’kAllCH JASIM'S PROCEEDINGS, AND TO ASSURE YOU THAT THE SUBJECT HAS MY ATTENTION AMD THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA ARE BY NO MEANS MY DIFFERENT to ANY PROJECTS f'HICH MAY AFFECT THE TERRI TORIES OF THE FRIENDLY STATE OF MUSKAT AND OMAN. I AM OBLIGED TO YOUR HIGHNESS FOR SENDING THE INFORMATION. ' ■ ' ' * ?- ; v • ,. •••. •• SD E.C.ROSS, COLONEL, POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF. no: f OF 1889 COPY FORWARDED TO THE POLITICAL AGENT &amp; ■ CONSUL,MUSKAT,W ITH REFERENCE TO HIS LETTER NO: 318, DATiD 30 TH: NOVEMBER,1888. BUSH I RE rr JANUARY, 1889. COLONEL, ERSIAN GULF.SaCRaTARY* S NO. 213 . INDIA OFFICri, TO LONDOr!, 7 T^ SEPT 5 M 3 ciR 1 888 ‘Ha SaCRSTARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. SIR, I FORWARD HEREWITH,FOR THE INFORMATION OF HIS EXCELLENCY,THE VICEROY, COPY OF CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE FOREIGN OFFICE REGARDING TURKISH PROCEEDINGS IN THE PERSIAN GULF. TO F.O.DATED I 2 TH JULY I 888 DO DO ? 3 RD AUGUST 1888 FROM _ DO 27 TH .. TO DO 29TH . . FROM, DO DO I HAVE &amp;C, SD EDMUND NEEL, ASSISTANT SECRETARY,POLL &amp; SECRET DEPARTMENT . \ INDIAT I M E INDIA T«E I2TN JUDY 1888. TO THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, FOREIGN OFFICE, 3Y VISCOUNT CROSS TO FORWARD FOR SUB- MI SS I OTI TO T RE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS COPY OF A TELEGRAM FROM TR8 VICEROY OF INDIA OF TRS 2 1ST JUNE REPORTING THAT TRE TURKISH GUARD AT SL-BIDAA ON TRE EL- KAT R COAST IN TRE PERSIAN GULF HAS BEEN INCREASED AND RECOMMENDING THAT HER MAJESTY * S GOVERNMENT SHOULD ADDRESS THE PORTE REGARDING TRE MOVEMENT OF TROOPS TO EL-KATR. 2 . the LATEST INFORMATION Of! TRE SUBJECT OF AFFAIRS AT EL-BIDAA WILL BE FOUND CONTAINED IN TRE ENCLOSURES TO MY LETTER OF TRE 5TH APRIL LAST AND IT WILL BE ©BSaRVED TRAT TRE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN TRE PERSIAN GULF SUGGESTED IN AUGUST I 887 THAT THE WITHDRAWAL OF TRE TURKISH GARRISON FROM EL-BIDAA WOULD CONDUCE TO TRE MAINTENANCE OF SECURITY ON TRE EL-KATR COAST. 3 # THE NATURE OF THE RELATIONS EXISTING BETWEEN TRE TURKS, TRE SREIKR OF EL-BIDaA AND TRE INDIAN GOVERNMENT SINCE 1868 WILL BE GATHERED FROM TRE ENCLOSED DEPART MENTAL MEMORANDUM, SHAIKH J. AS IM WOULD SEEM TO HA V E ACCEPTED TRE POSITION OF AN OTTOMAN DEPENDENT AND TO RAVE INVITED TURKISH TROOPS TO EL-BIDAA IN 1872. FROM / I AM DIRECTED^ ! ' TIM-i TO TIMa SINCa THAT DAT a THa TURKISH MILITARY OCCUPATION OF THAT PORT HAS 3 a all MSNTI Oil ED IN THa REPORTS OF THa BRITISH AUTHORITIES IN THE PERSIAN GULF. NO COMPLAINT, HOWEVER, HAS HITHERTO BEEN ADDRESSED TO THE PORTE AS TO THE PRESENCE OF ITS TROOPS AT EL-BIDAA. in 188? UNDER A THREAT OF BOMBARDMENT, SHAIKH JASIM PAID A SUM OF RUPEES 8000 AS COMPENSATION FOR THE ILL-TREATMENT OF HINDOO TRADERS AT EL- -IDAA AND THE TURKISH GOVERNMENT HAVING PROTESTED AGAINST THaSa PROCEEDINGS AS CONTRARY TO INTERNATIONAL LAW AND CALLaD FOR A REFUND OF THE INDEMNITY EXACTED FROM SHAIKH JASIM WHO WAS STYLED « •S«U 3 -GOUVERNEUR* * OF KATR/EARL GRANVILLE INFORMED MUSURESS PASHA ON THE 7 T H MAY I 083 THAT THE CLAIM OF THE PORTE TO RIGHTS OF SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE KATR COAST HAS NEVER BEEN ADMITTED BY HaR MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT. 5. UNDER INSTRUCTIONS FROM HIS GOVERNMENT THE TURKISH AMBASSADOR REPLIED IN TERMS WHICH RE-ASSERTED THE SULTAN'S SOVEREIGNTY OV iR THE COAST IN QUESTION !N THE MOST UNCOMPROMISING MANNER. IN ANSWER TO THIS FORMAL DECLARATION, LORD GRANVILLE WROTE TO MUSURESS PASHA THAT HER MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT WERE UNABLE TO ACCEPT THE VIEWS OF THE PORTE ON THE SUBJECT. 6 . THE CONTINUED PRESENCE OF A TURKISH GARRISON A EL-BIDAA WOULD SEEM TO INDICATE THAT THE OTTOMAN PORTE HAS NOT ABANDONED ITS PRETENSIONS TO SOVEREIGNTY OVER J THE EL-KATR COAST AND, LORD CROSS WOULD SUGGEST FOR THE CONS ID ERATI ONCONSID3RAT ION OF T^-Ti MARQUIS OF SALISBURY WH 3 T H t£ R TNa TURKISH GOV3RNM3NT MIGHT HOT B3 RSMIHDSD THAT TH 3 POSITION THiY HAV3 ASSUMED IN RESPSCT OF THIS PORTION OF TH3 ARABIAN COAST IS NOT R3COGNISSD BY H3R MAJ3STY»S GOVERNMENT AT'IP THAT THE INCREASE OF TfTE TURKISH GARRISON AT SL-BIDAA AT THE PRiSET’iT TIME CAN OTTI^Y BE LOOKED UPON AS AN UNFRIENDLY ACT AND ONE CALCULATED TO DISTURB THE T RANQU I LI/1T Y OF THE PiRSIAN GULF WHICH THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN AT SO MUCH PAINS TO ESTABLISH. 7 . IN LORD CROSS*S VIEW THE SULTAN’S GOVERNMENT WOULD BE .WELL ADVISED WERE THEY TO ISSU3 INSTRUCTIONS FOR T H 3 WITHDRAWAL OF THE TURKISH GARRISON FROM EL-BIDAA. CONCLUSION, I AM DESIRED TO SAY THAT LORD CROSS ENTIRELY CONCURS WITH THE EARL OF DUFFERIN THAT FURTHER EXTENSION OF TURKISH INFLUENCE IN THE DIRECTION OF OMAN TERRITORY WOULD BE V3RY PREJUDICIAL TO BRITISH INTERESTS ESPECIALLY AT THE PRESENT TIME, WHEN OWING TO THE DEATH OF SULTAN TURKI AND TH£ SUCCESSION OF HIS SON FEYSAL, COMPLICATIONS MAY ARISE AT MJSKAT. SD J.GODLEY, INDIA OFFICE, SIR, r-' 2 3 RD AUGUST 1888. IN CONTINUATION OF PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENTE ON \ THE SUBJECT OF TURKISH PROCEEDINGS ON THE ARAB COAST OFV m / i { { * © THK PiRSIAI! -GULF AND WITN SPECIAL RtCFtiReNCii TO TMti CONCLUDING PARAGRAPH OF MR GOnLSY*S LSTTaR OF THa IPTH ULTIMO, I AM PIR'iCTfciD BY VISCOUNT CROSS TO FORWARD HEREWITH, TO BE LAID BEFORE THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR j*' DATED IOTHportion AFFAIRS, COPY OF A TELEGRAM FROM THE VICEROY AJGUST^/yb OF INDIA REPORTING THAT THE AUTHORITIES IN THE PERSIAN GULF HAVE REASON TO APPREHEND THAT AN INVASION OF OMAN FROM NEJD AND SL-HASA IS IN CONTEMPLATION AND TO / SUGGEST THAT IN VIEW OF THE PREJUDICIAL EFFECT OF SUCH A MOVEMENT ON BRITISH I NTERESTS,THE MARQUIS OF SALISBURY SHOULD TAKE STEPS WITHOUT DELAY TO BRING THE '’ATT ER TO THE NOTICE OF THE PORTE AND TO GIVE THE OTTOMAN GOVERN MENT TO UNDERSTAND THAT ANY INTERFERENCE ON THEIR PART IN OMAN AFFAIRS COULD HOT BE REGARDED WITH INDIFFERENCE. THE ORIGINAL DOCUMENTS WHICH FORMED ENCLOSURES TO YOUR LETTER OF THE I9TH ULTIMO ARE HEREWITH RETURNED AS REQUESTED. SD H. WALPOLE, TO THfi UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, FOREIGN OFFICE, FOREIGNaugust 27T4 1888, TKia UNDaR SiCRiTARY OF STATii, ir T PlA OFFICa, SIR, WITF R2FiRt£NC(i TO YOUR L,2TT2R OF T f T 2 23RP INSTANT R2LATIV2 TO TURKISH PROC 22DINGS ON T H 2 ARABIAN COAS 1 OF TH2 P2RSIAM GULF, AND TH2 APPR2HENSI Ofl ENTERTAINED BY H2R MAJESTY'S RESIDENT AT BUSHIR2 T tT AT AN INVASION OF OMAN FROM N2JD AND EL-NASA IS IN CONTEMPLATION, I AM DIRECTED BY THE MARQUIS OF SALISBURY T G&gt; TRANSMIT TO YOU THE DRAFT OF A TELEGRAM WHICR HIS LORDSHIP PROPOSES WITH THE CONCURRENCE OF VISCOUNT CROSS,AT ONCE TO ADDRESS IO HER MAJ EST Y * S AMBASSADOR AT CONSTANT INOPLE, INSTRUCTING HIS EXCELLENCY TO WARN THE PORTE THaT HER MAJ EST Y * S GOVERNMENT COULD NOT VIEW WITH INDIFFERENCE ANY ATTEMPT on the part of the Turkish authorities to interfere IN OMAN AFFAIRS. SD P.W.CURRIE, COPY OF TELEGRAM RECEIVED FROM FOREIGN OFFIC IN COVERING LETTER DATED 29TH AUGUST I 888 . EL EG RAM TO SIR W. WHITE, } ? OR' OFFICE AUGUST 2 9T t y/B8 NO /&amp;/ /INDIAN GOVERNMENT HAVE RECEIVED TELEGRAM FROM RESIDENT AT BUSHIRE, V.HO HaS REASOT* TO BELIEVE THAT A SERIOUS MOVEMENT IS CONTEMPLATED BY TURKS AGAINST OMAN. THE MAIN ATTACK FROM NEJD V; I T H SUPPORT FROM EL-HASA AND GUTTUR. WE HAVE •ENGAGEMENT WITH FRANCE TO RESPECT IN DEPENDENCE OF MUSKAT. IF YOUR INFORMATION JUSTIFIES APPREHENSION, PRAY WARN PORTE THAT WE COULD MOT SE«: WITH INDIFFERENCE ANY ATTEMPT AT INTERFERENCE OR AGGRESSION. OUR POSITION IS CLEARLY DEFINED. WE RECOGNISE TURKISH JURISDICTION ON THE COAST AS FAR AS KATIF , AND ARE ANXIOUS T LT AT IT SHOULD BE EFFECTIVELY EXERCISED WITHIN THOSE LIMITS, BEYOND THAT POINT WE CONSIDER THE CHIEFS TO BE INDEPENDENT, AND HAVING ENGAGEMENTS WITH THEM WE OBJECT TO ATTEMPTS TO EXT END TURKISH AUTHORITY OVER THEM. INDIA OFFICE, ?9TH AUGUST 1888. TO THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, FORE IGN OFFICE, SIR, I AM DIRECTED BY VISCOUNT CROSS TO ACKNOWLEDGE I THE RECEIPT OF YOUR LETTER O' THE 27TH AUGUST, AND IN REPLY TO ACQUAINT YOU THAT HIS LORDSHIP CONCURS IN THE T ERMSIfh A T&amp;RMS OF TRS DRAFT TtSUttGRAM WHICH THS SiiCRSTARY OF STATS FOR FORSIGM AFFAIRS PROPOSES TO ADDRSSS TO HSR MAJSSTY*S AMBASSADOR AT COHSTAHT IHOPDS INSTRUCT IMG SIR w. CHITS' TO WARN THS PORTS THAT HSR M/\JSSTY*S GOV SRNMSMT COUOD HOT VlSVv WITH INDIFFSRSNCS ANY AT I SMPT ON THS PART OF THS TURKISH aU THORITISS TO INTERFERE IN OMAN AFFAIRS. L»0 RD CROSS WOUOD, HOWSV SR , SUGGEST THAT * 1 OMAN * * 3S SUBSTITUTED FOR MUSKAT* * AS SHOWING THAT OMAN TERRITORY IS THREATENED AND NOT THS PORT OF MUSKAT ONL.Y. SP H.WADPOLS. NO. 2080 S A COPY OF THE FOREGOING IS FORWARDED TO THS POLITICAL, RESIDENT IN THS P ERS FOR INFORMATION WITH RSFERSNCS TO THIS OFFICE TELEGRAM DATED THE 20TH SEPTEMBER I 080 .No. 258, dated India Office, London, the 2nd November 1888. From— Colonel Sir E. R. C. Bradford, K.C.S.L, Secretary, Political and Secret Department, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I forward herewith, for the information of His Excellency the Viceroy, Letter from Foreign Office, dated the 11th October 1888, with enclosure. C( W marginally Enclosures received with letter from Foreign Office, dated the 13th October noted Correspondence Enclosures received with letter from Foreign Office, dated the 17th October ^ith tllG 1 Oieign OfFlCC 1888 . on the subject of Turkish Three copies of letter to Foreign Office, dated the 2nd November 1888. jurisdiction On the Ara bian Coast of the Persian Gulf. Dated Foreign Office, London, the 11th October 1888. From— Sir Julian Pauncefote, Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, To—The Under-Secretary of State for India. With reference to my letter of 24th ultimo and to previous correspondence . respecting Turkish interference in Oman, I am directed by the Marquis ot Salisbury to transmit to you, for any observations which the Secretary of State for India may have to offer thereon, a copy of a further despatch from Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople forwarding copy of a note which His Excellency has addressed to the Porte on the subject. It will he seen that according to the reports of Her Majesty’s Consul at Basra, the Turkish authorities have established coal depots and military posts at Has el Tanurah and El Bidaa, which places are considerably south of Katif, beyond which Her Majesty’s Government do not recognize Turkish jurisdiction, hut that the garrisons were placed there with the ostensible object of carrying out the wishes of Her Majesty’s Government for the effectual sup pression of piracy on the west coast of the Persian Gulf. No protest, Sir W. White believes, has ever been made against the occupation of these places by the Turks, and it would therefore in his opinion he difficult in any representa tions which may he made to the Porte on the subject to lay down Katif as a hard and fast limit beyond which Turkish influence should not extend. His Excellency also asks to he informed as to the limits of the jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat, and an examination will he made of the papers in this office hearing on the subject. I am to add that Lord Salisbury would be glad to receive any information which the India Office may he able to furnish on this point. No. 381, dated Therapia, the 1st October 1888. From— Sir W. A. White, Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople, To— The Marquis of Salisbury, K.G., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. In consequence of Your Lordship’s telegram No. 107 of 19th September, I have thought it desirable to follow up the action reported in my despatch No. 347 of 6th September by addressing a note to the Porte on the subject of the rumoured invasion of Oman, a copy of which note I have the honour to enclose for Your Lordship’s information. In this I have not entered into any discourse on the subject of the extent of Turkish jurisdiction in the Persian Gulf for the following reasons :— In Your Lordship’s despatch No. 269 of 29th August, it was stated that Her Majesty’s Government recognize Turkish jurisdiction on the west coast of the Persian Gulf as far south as Katif, and that beyond that point Her Majesty’s Government consider the Chiefs to be independent and having con tracted engagements with them, they object to any attempt on the part of the 348 F. n.2 V Porte to extend its authority over them. It appears, however, from the reports of Mr. Robertson, the Assistant Political Agent, Basra, {a) No. 123 of 12th March, and (b) No. 135 of the 22nd March of the present year, that Nafiz Pasha, the Turkish Governor-General of Basra, had early in the present year visited Katif and Katr with the object of taking measures for the suppression of piracy in the Persian Gulf, and that he had taken pledges from Sheikh Jassim bin Thani of Katr, and Muhammad bin Abdul, Wahab of Darain, for the security of the coasts and waters within their influence and jurisdiction, and had left with Jassim bin Thani a steam-launch and crew to be used in patrolling the coasts. His Excellency also provided coal depdts at Ras el Tanurah and El Bidaa. Asa further measure for the security of the waters of the Persian Gulf, the Governor-General of Basra also established military posts at Bidaa, and a complete battalion of infantry, numbering about 400 men, was subsequently despatched from Basra to form garrisons for the above-mentioned places. Now all these places Katr, Ras el Tanurah and El Bidaa are considerably south of Katif, and are therefore outside the limits of Turkish authority as laid down by Your Lordship in the despatch previously quoted. The garrisons were, however, placed there with the ostensible object of carrying out the wishes of Her Majesty’s Government for the effectual sup pression of piracy on the west coast of the Persian Gulf, and no protest against the same has, as far as I am aware, been made either by Her Majesty’s Government or by the British Political Agents in the Persian Gulf. It would be difficult then in any representations we might make to the Porte on this subject to lay down Katif as the hard and fast limit beyond which Turkish influence should not extend. The Turks would naturally point out that they had already occupied positions to the south of Katif without (as it would appear) any objection having been made by Her Majesty’s Government. . J I should be glad to learn Your Lordship’s views on the above subject. I would also beg to request that I may be informed authoritatively as to the limits of the Sultan of Muscat, and as to whether he possesses or claims any jurisdiction over the Arabs on the coast between El Bidaa and El Dhabi. Note Verbale. No. 121, dated Constantinople, the 1st October 1888. It has been brought to the notice of Her Majesty’s Government bv the Viceroy of India that there appears room for apprehending a military aggres sive movement towards Oman from the direction of Nejd on the part of Muhammad ibn Rashid, the Chief of Jebel Shammar. It has also been reported, but Her Majesty’s Ambassador cannot brino* himself to believe such a report, that this invasion of Oman was likely to be supported by Turkish troops moving from El Hasa and Katr. Under the circumstances, however Her Majesty’s Embassy feels bound to bring these rumours to the notice of the Porte and to call their attention to the fact that Her Majesty’s Government are under an engagement with France to respect the independence of Muscat; for this and other°reasons Her Majesty’s Government cannot see with indifference any attempt on the part of the Turkish authorities at interference or aggression in Oman. Enclosure received with covering letter from Foreign Office, dated the 13th October 1888. No. 168, dated Gulahek, the 3rd September 1888. From —Sir H. D. Wolfit, Her Majesty’s Minister, Teheran, To—The Marquis of Salisbury, K.G., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. I have the honour to enclose an extract from the Persian paper lit ala on the recent events at El Katr as well as the conduct of the Turkish Govern ment in that locality.3 I made enquiries of the Resident at Bushire on the matter and have the honour to enclose a copy of his telegra phic reply *. Appended to the transla tion is a note by Mr. Churchill to which I venture to call Your Lordship’s attention. (Translation.) Extract from the Persian paper “ Ittalaf of 9th August 1888. Shaikh Zaid bin Khalifeh, Governor of Abu Zeni, sent his son with i about 5,000 cavalry and footmen in order to punish Shaikh Jasim bin v- i'hani, Governor of Katr. This band entered the fort of Katr on the night of the 7th Ramazan and going straight to the Governor’s house without molesting any body else they fought until three hours after sunrise, killing Shaikh Ali, son of Jasim, and 38 men, wounding 40 others, and taking 70 men and women prisoners together with five horses and many camels and much property. Shaikh Jasim fled to Zeayin where he took refuge. The son of Shaikh Zaid sent 600 men after Shaikh Jasim and the result is not yet known. The Turkish Government has sent a man-of-war with 600 men, 400 of whom have been landed at the port of Khatif and 200 more landed at Katr which is now in their possession, and they have organized a custom administra tion on the part of the Turkish Government. We do not know whether the Turkish Government will allow Shaikh Jasim any further interference with the government of that place. NOTE. In October 1887 the Amin-es-Sultan on the part of the Shah communi cated to Sir A. Nicolson a petition from the Persian subjects living at El Katr who had been plundered by Jasim bin Thani and asked for the assistance of Her Majesty’s Resident at Bushire in getting the restitution of the plunder. The matter was immediately communicated to Colonel Ross 'who said that he was powerless to assist as the same Chief had plundered British property and he had only succeeded in obtaining restitution by impounding some pro perty of the Shaikh’s while at Bahrain. The local authorities at Bushire applied to the Turkish Agent there, hut apparently without success. Subsequently the energetic Agents of the Amin-es-Sultan in the Gulf, Haji Ahmad Khan and the Malek-ul-Tujjar, formed the scheme of going over to El Katr and offering Shaikh Jasim Persian protection if he would acknow ledge the authority of the Shah, and in case he refused these overtures he was to he subjugated by force. These schemes were, however, all frustrated by the active and watchful measures taken by Colonel Ross immediately the Persian expedition left the Persian Coast with the result that the doings of his creatures were entirely repudiated by the Amin-es-Sultan. S. Churchill. The 30th August 18S8. Copy of letter, being enclosure in Consul-General Talbot’s No. 25 of 31st Auo-ust 1888, received with covering letter from the Foreign Office, dated the 17th October 1888. Dated Bushire, the 16th August 1888. From —Colonel E. C. Ross, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Her Majesty’s Consul-General for Ears, To—The Political Resident, Baghdad. With reference to my letter No. 192 of 18th May 1888, I have the honour to forward a copy and translation of a letter from the Residency Agent, Bahrain, regarding the unsettled state of affairs at Katif.4 * - Enclosure. No. 78, dated the 6th August 1888. From—The Residency Agefit, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After compliments .—I beg to report that this day Muhammad ihn Abdul 'VVahad arrived here from Darren. According to his statement the Turkish officials at Katif do not adopt any measures for the suppression of pirates. He further states as regards the slave whom the robbers had carried away from the Baggorah of the Bahrain people near Zalloon, as reported in my letter of the 10th May 1888, No. 41; that he, the slave, is publicly offered for sale in th^ bazar of Katif, and that the Turkish soldiers offered 50 dollars as his price ; that Katif and the places outside the fort are unsafe on account of the Bedouins; that two or three townspeople have been wounded and one or two Bedouins slain; that an affray took place at El Hasa between the Arab inhabi tants, during which two men were killed and several wounded; that the pre sent Mutasarif is of no use, and that every one of the Turkish officials consults his own interests, that the Turkish vessel is lying at anchor at lias Tanurah without proving of any good. I have heard such reports from other sources, except the one about the slave. Muhammad Abdul TV ahad is well informed, as he mixes with the Turks, and obtains news from them. No. 573, dated Baghdad, the 27th August 1888. From— Major A. C. Talbot, Her Majesty's Consul-General, Baghdad, To— Sir W. A. White, Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople. Deferring to my predecessor’s letter No. 409, dated 8th June 1888, I have the honour to submit, for Your Excellency’s information, copy of a despatch with enclosure, from Colonel Boss (Political Besident in Persian Gulf) on the subject of the general laxity of Turkish rule in the Katif District. I shall await instructions from Your Excellency before causing any repre sentation to he made to the Vali of Basra on the subject. Dated India Office, London, the 2nd November 1888. From—J. A. Godley, Esq., Under-Secretary of State for India, To—The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. I am desired by Viscount Cross to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 11th October, enclosing copy of a despatch from Her Majesty’s Ambas sador at Constantinople, dated 1st October, in reference to the extent of Turkish jurisdiction on the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf. 2. Lord Cross, having perused the correspondence on this subject which took place in 1879-80, desires me to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for Eoreign Affairs, that he concurs generally in the opinions expressed by his predecessor (Viscount Cranbrook) in the letter addressed to the Eoreisri Office on the 29th December 1879. ° 3. The difficulties attending any negotiation with the Porte with the view of defining the limits of Turkish jurisdiction on that coast, which were pointed out. in 1879, have in no wise been lessened, and the risk of hampering British cruisers,, so far as action against piratical craft is concerned, involvecf in the recognition of any particular part of the Arabian coast and the waters adjacent as Turkish continues equally great. 4. The situation on that coast admittedly is a peculiar one, and was lately noticed in Mr. Godley’s letter of the 12th July last. Her Majesty’s Govern ment have declined to admit the claim of Turkey to sovereignty over the El Katr coast, while the Sultan uncompromisingly asserts ins rights over that Coast. The Sheikh of El Bidaa, on the eastern side of the El Katr peninsula, an mdependent Chief, not a party to the maritime truce, has allowed the Turks5 to maintain a small military post there since 1872, and Her Majesty’s Govern ment have never protested against this assertion of Turkish supremacy on this portion of the El Katr coast. 5. Lord Cross thinks it may he sufficient for the present to acquaint Sir W. White, if the Marquis of Salisbury sees no objection thereto, that Her Majesty’s Government do not consider that the Porte is in effective occupation of the Arabian coast beyond Katif, and that they adhere to the declaration made in 1883 that the claim of the Porte to rights of sovereignty over the El Katr coast is not admitted by Her Majesty’s Government. But as there is no reason to anticipate that any practical result would be attained by provoking a discussion with the Turkish Government as to the extent of its jurisdiction on that coast, it is undesirable to raise the question at the present time. 6. I am to add that, according to Eindlay’s “ Sailing Directory for the Indian Ocean ” (p. 690), Pas Tanurah is the south point of a long strip of sand with sand hills on its outer edge, which forms the north side of Katif Bay. No objection could therefore apparently he offered to the formation of a coal dep6t by the Turks at Pas Tanurah. 7. With regard to your inquiry as to the limits of the jurisdiction of the Sultan of Muscat, 1 am desired to say that the coast line of Muscat territory extends from Pas-el-Khymah up to and beyond Pas-el-Had towards Dhofar, in The Imams and Seyyeds of Oman. Badger’s which dilCCtion it IS believed that 110 Translation (introduction, page 4 ). precise boundary exists. Westward, inland Muscat may be said to stretch as far as the great Arabian desert. No. 2416-E. A copy of the foregoing is forwarded to the Political Resident in the Persian From the Secretary, Political and Secret Depart. Gulf for information, in Continuation 0 £ ment, No. 258, dated the 2nd November 188S, and the endorsement from this office, No. enclosures. 2119-E., dated the 31st October 1888. By Order, &amp;c., 4 ^ Eoreign Dept., SHilliam; The 18th December 1888. (Sd.) W. H. CORNISH, Asstt. Secretary to the Govt, of India,1 No. 17, dated Bushire, tlie 31st January 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. I enclose a translation of a report received from tlie Residency Agent at No. 10 , dated 20 th j.nu.rj 1889 , with ono.ceom. Bahrain on the subject of an expedition of pan!mcut. Shaikh Jasim bin Muhammad lhani against the Beni Yas, and the alleged slaughter by Jasim\s men of a large number of Arabs at a place named El Jowa, which is also called El Zafarh, and is situated some four marches west of Abu Dhabee. No. 10, dated the 20th January 1889. From— The Residency Agent, Bahrain. To— The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—I beg to send herewith copy of a letter sent by Jasim binThani to the Chief of Bahrain,^with a special messenger, who has also brought a number of other letters giving welcome tidings to Mohamed bin Abdul Wahab, Mujbil and ibn Eedan ; and mentioning the number of people who were slain out of the inhabitants of El-Jowa; viz., 520 persons ; and that they took from them large booty and numerous camels, and that Jasim returned safely with his army. I hear from reports, that Jasim lost 8 men killed. Others say 48, others again 110. But as yet there is no correct report, as since arrival of this messenger, no one has come from El-Katr owing to heavy “ shemall” winds. It is stated that Jasim has not yet reached El-Bida. I hear that Eesau bin Zyab, a cousin of Shaikh Zaeed bin Khaleefab has arrived at Bahrain from Aboothabee and interviewed the Chief. According to what he says there are not so many people at El-Jowa, and that Shaikh Zaeed had not received any report of Jasim’s proceeding from El-Katr to El-Jowa, or any other place. I shall make further reports, when I receive any fresh news. Dated the 13th January 1SS9. From— Jasim Bin Mohamed Bin Thani. To— Shaikh Eesau Bin Ali, Chief of Bahrain. After Compliments .—I am grateful to God for his favours and a succession of his gifts, which are bestowed on those who are of good habits. I must communi cate to you the happy tidings of the victory and success which God has favoured us with 'and the disgrace to the evil-doers, and their destruction. When it was reported to me that Zaeed had taken the field, I wanted to meet and encounter him, and when we were abreast of El-Jowa from the east, it became known to us that he had taken refuge in his town, and we entered El-Jowa from the east, and proceeded in a westerly direction, while our men made it their busi ness to plunder, slaughter and burn, right and left as they went along, until they were masters of the whole town. The inhabitants who escaped this slaugh ter took refuge in the fort, which contains two citadels. On the 6th day after our entering El-Jowa we reached the fort. This is the strongest fort in the place. About 120 men were slain in all the districts. When we made a halt before El-Jowa there were about 400 men to defend the fort, and they refused us admission —our people took it by storm, and all the men were slain—it' was impossible to take an account of the slain, notwithstanding that they re peatedly passed by the place. Some of the slaves, who have been captured, state that the men in the fort numbered about 400. The whole town found itself completely destroyed, and enveloped in ruins from east to west, and all its plantations mown down, as if they did not exist the day before. Among the dead were about 15 of the leading men of the Al-bu-Ealah. Our army took possession of all their property, while the women and children fled towards the coast. And we remained there for about 12 days. M e used to assembletogether for our daily prayers, and the “ maazzan” used to call for prayers at the usual hours and this was the place in which for months and years there used not to be heard the voice of a “ Maazzan” nor did the people meet to gether for prayers. During our long sojourn at the place, we did not find in it even one mosque. AY hen they saw our men doing slaughter among them, each one of them began to call aloud for aid from some one except God, some cried out “ Oh Abdul-Kader”; others, “ Oh Abu-Bahlool.” So it is necessary that we and all the Mussulmans should express our joy and gratitude to the Al mighty, for the destruction of the abode of the tyrannous people, and the etTacement of all marks of the evil-doers. AYhen some of our people asked them why they remained in the place, notwithstanding our repeated warnings to them, they replied that neither they nor their fore-fathers had heard nor seen in any historical record that any ituler or Sultan did enter El-Jowa, or did express his hope to that effect. I send you Ahmed bin Majid to convey this happy tiding to you and to give you a verbal account of the affair. I am ‘grateful to God under all circumstances. I hope you are safe, and salaams. Kindly convey my salaams to your family people, brothers and sons of the late Shaikh Ahmed, and to those who feel joyful at the news of our victory. My sons Khaleefah Thani, Abdullah and Abdul llahman and our tribesmen send their salaams to you all. We are now at El-Harf and by the middle of the month, we hope in God that everything will be satisfactorily done, and salaams. No. 20, dated Busliire, the 4th February 1889. ' From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. I have the honor to inform you that the young Shaikh Ibrabim-Bin-Abdal- lah-Bin Abdallah-Bin Thaneyyan of the Al-Saood or Wahhabee Amir’s family lately arrived at Busliire, and called upon me. His father, Abdallah Pasha, resides in Constantinople, where he enjoys high consideration and is a member of the State Council, though probably poor. This young man came from Constantinople some months ago to Muscat where he remained a short time, and went on to Bahrain where he stayed about two months being treated with courtsey and respect by the chief. He informed me his chief object in com ing to the Peisian Gulf, was to endeavour to effect a reconciliation between Shaikh Jnsirn Bin Mohamed Thanee and Shaikh Zaeed Bin Khaleefa the Beni Yas Chief. He visited the former in El-Katr, but found linn intractable, and he spoke of Jasim as a sort of madman. I attach a memorandum of a more detailed statement which “Ibn Thaney yan” made to the Besidency Confidential Agent. News Report by Confidential Agent, dated the 25th January 18S9. 1 had an interview with Ibrahim Bin Thaneyyan, of whom I made enquiries about the object of his coming here from Constantinople. He said the fact is that Jasim, after the quarrel which broke out between him and Shaikh Zaeed resulting in his son being killed, wrote a letter to his (Ibrahim’s) father in Constantinople, giving particulars, and requesting him to represent the matter to His Majesty the Sultan. But his father considered it advisable to send Ibrahim to these parts to effect a reconciliation between them. That he first called at Muscat where he remained for a few days, and paid a visit of condol ence to His Highness Syed Eeysal and his brothers on their father’s death ; that then he went to Bahrain where he remained for a few days, then he crossed over to El-Katr and met Jasim and endeavoured repeatedly to bring about peace between him and Shaikh Zaeed ; hut all ended in failure ; he was obstinate 1 and said that if he could get hold of Zaeed’s son, and deliver him to him to be put to death, then he would be satisfied and allow the matter to drop. Finding Jasim 23 obstinate he returned to Bahrain. Jasim after writing to Ibrahim’s father did not wait for a reply, &amp;c., but at once wrote to Ibn Rashid askin^ his aid in the matter. Ibiahim says he will stay for a time here to allow of winter getting a little mild, because at present it is very cold at Constantinople. After a fortnight or so he intends going to Port Said and thence to Constantinople. No. 21, dai d Busliire, the 4th February 1889. From Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, T° The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. ^ e the honor to enclose translations of the'marginally noted reports No. 7, doted 13 th Jtmnary 1889 . ff 0 ™, tll f 0ffic 1 iati “S Residency Agent on „ 8. „ 18 th „ the Arab coast relating to the recent ex- j«“'i s sr ak '“ er 10 *'■ L “ c “' ^ 25 “‘ P^ition of Shaikh Jasim-Bin-Mohamed- Thani against the Beni Yas and its results. No. 7, dated the 13th January 18S9. From—The Officiating Residency Agent, Shargah, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. . A f fe r Compliments .—I have received a report that about 18 days ago Shaikh Jasim-Bin-Thani started from El-Katr, intending to go to Oman with a lar^e army ; that on this account the Chief of Aboothabee is preparing to march to the interior, and that he has sent messengers to various Bedouin tribes, such as El- Zawahir, A1 Bushamis, Beni Katab, El-Awamir El-daroo and others.’ He lias also sent messengers to the Debay and Ommel-kaiwain chiefs, asking them to meet him in the neighbourhood of Aboothabee, and after they assemble together he will march to encounter Jasim-Bin-Thani. 1 hear that when the Chief of Abooth abee received news about Jasim’s movement, lie wanted to send armed men and ammunition by sea to SiT, in view to encounter Jasim, but owing to bis fear of the British Government he gave up his idea and decided to march by land? No. 8, dated the 18th January 1889. From—The Officiating Residency Agent, Shargah, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments.—’Reports are received from various sources sayin°-tliat Jasim accompanied by Abdul Rahman Bin Feysal, and Ibn Sabhan the Deputy of Ibn Rasheed in the districts of Riadth, and taking a large army with him has arrived atElzafrah and Leevah, which lie within the territories of the Chief of Aboothabee ; that they massacred the inhabitants and cut down date trees • that their messengers had arrived at Baraimee and interviewed Mohamed-Bin- Ali, the head of the Na’aim tribe, and that Ibn Rasheed will send some soldiers to Jasim’s aid. It is reported that the chief of Aboothabee is at a loss what to do as regards the approaching warfare, as lie fears the advent of Ibn Rashid and it is thought that Jasim would not have ventured to come dow n so far’ without the assistance of Ibn Rashid. I I hear that the Manaseer Bedouins and other dependants of the Chief of Ahoothabee and Debay, have come down from the interior to the sea-side between Jibail and Debay ; that other Bedouins of the interior have also moved to the eastern regions, where there are mountains about Ras-el-Khymah, and to the Eastern States. Under the circumstances the whole of the interior will easily fall into the hands of the western people; the Shaikhs of the Beni4 Ghafer tribes will have to tender their allegiance, as they are not strong enough to oppose them, while they are of the same creed as the western people (Jasim Abdul Rahman and Ihn Sabhan). Extract from a note written by the Officiating Residency Agent at Shargah, to Mr. G. Lucas, Assistant Resident, dated the 25th January lbb9. I hear that Jasim and some of the western people, Ibn Rashid’s men, arrived at Zafrah. They cut down date trees, and slaughtered the inhabitants and carried away their camels. They say their messengers had arrived at Baraimee. These Shaikhs are in a state of great alarm, and they do not know what to do, whether they should meet the western people in a friendly manner or offer them resistance and fight. The Chief of Aboothabee has not yet left Aboothabee, while his Bedouins have fled and dispersed. So also all the Bedouins from the interior have removed themselves from west to east and they are looking out for places of refuge. While the litoral Shaikhs, if they find no one to encourage them and instil martial spirit into their hearts, will not be able to co-operate with one another in view to united action. I hear that His Highness Seyyid Eeysal of Muscat has written to the chief of Ras-el-Khymah, asking him to place men to guard the various mountain passes, which yield entrance to Batna. In this way they cannot gain their object, unless they act with firmness and full determination, and spend money. Tiie Chiefs of Debay, Shargah, Ajman and llas-el-Khymah, tell me that the British Government are willing that the western people should take possession of these parts. I replied to them that if Jasim-Bin-Thani is alone concerned, I did not suppose that the British Government will interfere. But if a third party were to interfere, the British Government would not allow its interfer ence on this coast. This appears to be the beginning of disturbances ; and God knows the result. No. 22, dated Bushire, the 4th Februarj' 18S9. From—Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. In continuation of my letter No. 17, dated 31st ultimo, I have the honor to send translation of a further report No. 16, dated 2/th January 1889. r a from the Residency Agent at Bahrain on the subject of the massacre of Arabs by the force of Jasim-bin-Mohamed Thani. Further inquiry will be made as to the alleged slaughter of women and child ren on the occasion. No. 16, dated the 27th January 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—With reference to my previous report by the mail steamer, about the slaughter of the dependants of Shaikh Zaeed at El-Jowa and Zafrah, which news was communicated to Shaikh Esau, Chief of Bahrain, by Jasim bin-Mohamed bin-Thani I beg to say that recently some boats have ar rived, from El-Bida and brought some letters. It is said that a large num ber of the Zafrah people were slaughtered but the number did not amount to 520 as mentioned by Jasim. It seems to be less. They said that those in habitants were living in separate huts, scattered among the date plantations, and that they gradually retreated before the army of Jasim, under a fire from Martini-Henri rifles, and entered their fort with their women and children, and closed the door, which they strengthened with rice bags.5 JT ■ The fort is only an enclosure, made of bricks, and about 6 to 7 feet high, and it contained two citadels without parapets and loop-holes ; they were all crying out loudly, and begging Jasim to grant them safety of their lives,. but they heard them not. They then told them to evacuate the fort under Jasim’s protection. Some of them came out of the fort and they fired a volley on them and charged them, killing them with their women and children. About 12 men of Jasim’s party were slain, and some men were wounded. They then carried away slaves and other booty. They further state that a report was received at El-Bida that Shaikh Zaeed has left Aboothabee accompanied by the inhabitants of Debay and intends to proceed to El-Katr. No. 34, dated Busbire, the 18th February 1889. From—Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. I have the honor to enclose a translation of a remarkable and interesting letter written in June last by Shaikh Jasim-bin-Mohammed Thani of El-Katr to Abdallah Pasha-ibn Thaneyyanof the Al-Suood family of Nejd who now resides at Constantinople and is understood to be a Member of the Council of State at that capital. 2. I obtained a copy of Shaikh Jasim’s letter from Ibrahim the son of ^ „ j a j Abdallah Pasha under promise of secrecy, T\de my letter No. 20, dated 4th February 1889. .-p jiji* e.-i* and I am assured by him that his lather took no steps to place Shaikh Jasim’s views and requests before the Sultan or the Minister of the Porte. It is however, highly probable that Jasim used other channels to endeavour to persuade the Turkish Government to adopt or favour his schemes, which now stand fully revealed so far as he is concerned, as the letter is undoubtedly genuine. 3. Unaided and unsupported it is not in the power of Jasim to undertake the conquest of any districts of Oman. Desultory raids are the utmost in his power and the Beni Yas tribesmen are more than a match for Jasim’s following. He, however, followed up his appeal to the Turkish Government, by a similar appeal to “ Ibn Kashid ” whose power is now paramount in Central Nejd, as well as in the North-Western Provinces of Arabia; and apparently it is only some unforeseen circumstances that have delayed a movement from Nejd on Oman. 4. It may be assumsd as certain that the Turkish authorities and Govern ment have been fully informed of these matters and it seems more clear than ever that it depends on the attitude of the Porte whether or not any serious invasion of Oman is undertaken. It is very probable that “ Ibn Kashid ” is (as reported) awaiting a reply from the Porte before moving. Anyhow a respite, at least, has been accorded, and I would venture to suggest that advantage should be taken of the delay, to consider our relations with the Turk’s and Arabs on the Katr coast, in view if possible, to some understanding with the Turkish Government, which would put a stop to the dangerous border warfare now going on and prevent the possibility of any extensive aggression on the Oman provinces. A friendly feeling between the Turks and ourselves in the Persian Gulf would, I think, be mutually advantageous and might perhaps be obtained by a spontaneous recognition under certain conditions of their de facto position on the Katr coast which would also enable the British Government to hold the Porte more fully responsible for any attempted encroachments on the Oman territories. To His August Highness Abdullah Pasha Ibn-Thaneyyan Al-Suod, dated 28th Ramadthan 1305 A. H.-9th June 1888. After compliments .—After enquiries about your health, I beg to inform you (and may you hear naught but good), that during this long period I have always remembered you although you are distant from us and there has beenno correspondence between us; but friendship for you is deeply rooted in my heart, and distance only increases and confirms it; when, love is rooted in hearts, distance only increases it especially the love of human beings for their fellow creatures. I am confident that your sojourn in those parts, where you are, is beneficial to us. Although I do not trouble you, I am certain that if any reports are received about me there, you will make up for my absence, and do better for me than if I were present, although I do not give you particulars. At present a mishap has befallen me, which has compelled me to inform you about it, and I solicit God’s aid, then yours; and I have good hopes in God and you; and God willing through you and your generous aid I shall gain my object, to wit; since the high Government (Turkish) took possession of the district of Nejd, myself and my followers have been obedient to it, and have given our allegiance to it and have served it without any recompense while other people are not so, they do not serve unless they are paid. In particular, as to myself, during all this time I have been Kaim Makam of the District of Katr, and have set aside all my own affairs, and have attended to the service of the high Government, I have never asked for any salary and have used my best endeavours in the service of the Government and for the benefit of the creed, * As regards Oman, you are well aware * Attention is drawn to this passage. of its condition and the income which can E ,c ' R - be obtained from it and that this territory and its inhabitants are subject to the Government of Nejd.* Ever since Govern ment (Turkish) took possession of Nejd, Oman has been left to itself, no one has taken notice of it, and each township has remained in the hands of its inhabit ants. It is not hidden from you that Zaeed-bin-Khaleefah is one of the inhabit ants of Oman, and he was the first man to pay taxes to you, the Al-Suood. When the Government reduced the power of the Al-suood, and paid no attention to Oman, the above Zaeed rose and began to follow his inclination and created dissensions amongst the people until he acquired paramount power, and be came their master, and seized all the revenues. He oppressed the people and tyrannized over them, while the people were powerless and could not resist him, except by the aid of God and the high (Turkish) Government: and this after the justice and good treatment they experienced from-the Al-Suood. But the Government neglected them, and left them out, as if they were not subject to the Government of Nejd. Then some of the inhabitants of the town and villages came to me seeking my aid and soliciting that I should use my endeavours for them with the Government and arrange that they might be.rid of the jurisdiction of Zaeed- bin-Khaleefah over them, and that the Government may include the territories within the district and jurisdiction of Nejd, as of yore, so that the inhabitants may find peace and rest and be safe against murders and plunder, and be rid of this person, who fears not God, and knows not Ills wrath. I gave them good promises and full hopes, and I represented this matter to every°Wali and Mutaserrif who came to these parts,f and they used to give me fair promises, t N.B.— i.e .—The Walls of Busrah &amp; Governor of 3,11 ^. U ^ n l # USe( l ^0 give similar promises Hasa. to the inhabitants who used to become joyful and hope for relief from God and the merciful Government. But months and years rolled away, and there was no result, and the Government were quite neglectful, which was not proper, as those people were their subjects and included within the jurisdiction of the Government of Nejd. The revenues of Oman equal those of Nejd, perhaps they + are greater^, especially if it comes in the hands of the high Government.^ AT hen Zaeed-bin-Khaleefah came to know about my counsel and endeayours with the officers of the Government, he harboured in his mind animosity against me and instigated the tiibes under his orders, who began to raid our neighbour hood, plunder our property, murder our men, outrage our women, and make slaves of our free people, but since we are dependants of the high Government, I could not do anything, and prevented my tribesmen from committin &lt;&gt; any 6V the ✓ outrages on him* (Zaeed) or his tribesmen, and I hoped that would redress our wrongs * Far from tnfe. him for his violent deeds. t This is absurd. I 30th May 1888. Government and punish And what ever humiliation we have suffered at his hands, and whatever outrage he has done to us, I have complained about the same to the officials of the Govern ment who have been in these parts, and they have given us fair promises and fed us on strong hopes up to date, but no result has followed. On this account when Zaeed found no opposition from the Government, nor any rebuke, he held the Government in contempt and thought that the High Government had no sense of honor and was neglectful of her territories which she would not render secure nor protect her subjects, he longed to seize Katr and its districts and include them in Omanf; accordingly he prepared an army under his son Kbaleefah and brother-in-law, Mohamed-bin- Saif, and des patched them to seize the town of Katr, while we and the inhabitants were in safety and protection of God and the High Government, and we never thought that he would dare to this extent, nay even a great power would not have dared to act thus against a town under the protection of the flag of the High Government and we were all away from the town of El-Katr, and my son Ali and some other inhabitants only were in the town. They attacked them about the time of morning prayer, on the 18th Ra mad than f 1305 A. H. and they were taken unawares. They set up an uproar, and whoever came out of his house in response to the call, was slain in front of the door of his house, and God so decreed that Ali my son was among those who were slain, there were fifty other leading men of the town slain, and an equal number or perhaps more, wounded. The messenger brought this news to us after some time. When they heard that our towns people were about to re ceive reinforcements they plundered what they could, and returned. And I and my tribesmen arrived after the whole thing was over, (as decreed by God), and the enemy had departed. We wanted to pursue them, so that God might grant us revenge, but we feared to undertake any thing previous to referring the matter to Government, which •might not approve our proceedings.§ So we trusted in God and made no hurry, pend ing reference of the matter to the High Government. Indeed this daring act of Zaeed is derogatory to the Govern ment, because I am her servant and under her protection, though before we came to place ourselves under the Government protection he had power to act in this daring manner. So if the Government be moved by the sense of its honor, and guard its sublime position against insult, all well: if not let it shut its eyes against our acts, and give us permission to act against Zaeed, and the territories of Oman. And if I seize him then both I and he will be at the orders of God and the Government. My sense of honor has been moved in view to se cure and keep intact the respect and honor of the High Government and do things which are beneficial to its interests. Because,securing the territory of Oman and including it to her within the jurisdiction of Nejd as it was before, will add the name and honor of the Government, and will prove beneficial her Treasury. But the Government is neglectful of this, and I do not know whether this neglect emanates from herself or that the high officials do not report these mat ters to the Government, in a correct manner. May you for ever continue to be the ornament, enjoying high position and honors, and ever-lasting relic of the renowned families of Arab. I consider your and my condition as the same ; anything adding to my honor, I believe, will give you pleasure in the same way that increase of your honor gives me pleasure. Any loss, is a loss to all of us. With full hopes in you, I have been induce- ed to communicate the matter to you and give all details. I know that, thanks to God, your advice is accepted by the Government. I hope therefore you will re present the matter to the Sultan, and by the favor of God I hope our object will be gained. There must be one of two things, «.e., that the Government will under take the task of seizing Oman, and we shall give our aid in the matter in every § This is an artful colouHng. lway. Or we solicit that the Government may permit us to seize the territory and secure it. By the grace and aid of God and the High Government, I hope to subdue the territories and release the inhabitants from their miserable position and they will pray for the prosperity of the sublime Government. After this if the Government should desire that I should hold charge of it, paying the reve nues to the Government, or that they wdsh to take charge of it themselves, they will be free to choose. I beg you will represent me in every way in this matter, and I hope you will not neglect this matter, and will send me an early reply. Please write to me always, giving news of your welfare, and let me know anything you wish to be done here, and kinly convey my salams to Ibrahim* and his brothers. My sons also send sa lams to you. May you ever remain under •Son of Abdullah Pasha. God’s protection, and may peace and divine blessings rest on you. Postscript of Jasim's letter to Abdullah Pasha Ibu Thaneyyan, dated 28tli Ramadthan 1305, corresponding to 9th June 1888. I beg to inform you (may you not know except what is good) that I have written to you a letter and have given you details in it, which need not be re peated here. I place my dependence on God and you, and I trust in God that my hopes will not meet disappointment, and . I have refrained from taking any action about matters which come upon us one after the other, and I cannot give my attention to them until I hear from you. If I receive sufficient support and justice from the sublime Government, this is what is required, and we shall join the Government and aid her in the undertaking; otherwise the Government should grant us permission to secure the districts of Oman. If it is necessary to write out memorials or send telegrams, or similar things, in connection with ex penses to be met, you will kindly let me know your opinion, and the reply may be given according to the circumstances, and I shall act accordingly, because you know better than us all the ways and rules, and what pleases you, and the directions you give us, shall be final and obeyed. We shall be much obliged to you, and God will rew-ard you for gaining this result, and God willing, you will gain greater honours and superiority over others of your kind. You will have your reward in the world to come. As it is mentioned in the traditions of Moha- med, (may God’s grace and peace be on him), the believers are like a building in which one part gives support and strength to the other, further the believers are like unto a body, when one member of the body suffers pain, then the whole body becomes feverish and suffers from' want of sleep. It is further laid down that no one can be a true believer unless he should wish the same for his Moslim brother as he would have done unto himself. God knows that my belief is that w r hat pains me pains you, and that a strong friendship exists between us. I trust therefore in your worthy self and great friendship, that you will kindly let me know of the arrival of my letter to you, by a telegram, to the care of Jaji Ibrahim Bin Mandeel at Busrah, and you will kindly give me some hint in it about the nature of the reply and other details which I may expect to receive by your letter. You will kindly send your letter under registered cover via Bahrain, and to the care of Mujbil Ez- Zakair, and that you will give me full details in that letter, and salams. Telegram, No. 576-E., dated Fort William, the 14th March 1889. From—The Foreign Secretary, Calcutta, To—The Resident, Bushire. Yottr letter No. 34 of 18th February, paragraph 4. What Turkish rights would you recognise and under what conditions and within what limits. 89 Telegram, No. 4081-E., dated the 15th March 1889, From—The Resident, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Calcutta. Tour telegram of the 14th. If Turkey were willing to respect British interests in Oman and Bahrain, after frank explanations, and engage to co operate in miintaining order by sea and land, I think that we might recognise Bida as Turkish port and Military outpost, statu quo being maintained south and east of that point. No. 37, dated Bushire, the 22nd February 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.l, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Her Majesty's Consul-General for Ears, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. I ha.ve the honour to submit translations of news reports received from No. 12 , dated 3 i*t January 1889. the Residency Agent at Shargah, on the No. 14 , dated 7th February 1889. subject principally of. the hostilities be tween the Chief of Abu-Dhabee and Shaikh Jasim Bin Mohammad Thani. No. 12, dated the 31st January 1889. News Report by the Residency Agent, Shargah. On the 17th January 1889, the Chief of Ras-el-Khymah arrived by land at Shargah on a visit to the Chief. From the 13th to 24th January and 26th to 31st idem there has been a very copious fall of rain and heavy winds prevailed in these parts, and all communi cations by sea were stopped. According to reports of Thani Bin ’Ataish, who has come to Debay from SiF, and whose Mashoa also was employed in taking provisions to Kufareeyah, the expeditionary force of Jasim Bin Thani consists of (1) the Na’ain tribesmen, who are friends of the Shaiks of Bahrain, viz., Naser Bin Jabar and Bashed Bin Jabar; they have about 50 horsemen, (2) the Ma’atheed tribesmen of Jasim, (3) the Beni Hajir, (4) some camelmen and 20 horsemen of the A1 Nurrah, (5) about 25 camelmen of the Bu-Ainaim, (6) about seven camelmen of the Al-Bukawara, and about 70 camelmen of the Manaseer, under Hamaid Bin Mana’, who were before subject to the Chief of Abu-Thabee, and about 100 camelmen belonging to the Mahanic^ah, El-Mazaree, Al Musallum, El Ama- marah, El-Ckabsah, and El-Masallatak. The total number is above 1,000 camelmen. It is reported that a small number of the Manaseer and El-Mazaree, who owned date plantations at Loevah, had fortified themselves in the Fort of Leevah, and Jasim wanted to seize the Fort; an assault was made, and during the engagement about 50 men of Jasim’s party were killed and Jasim’s party suffered defeat. Then Hamid Bin Mana El-Mansoori took promise of safety from Jasim to the people who were in possession of the Fort of Leevah; on this the Manaseer descended from the Fort and then Jasim’s mon made a second attack and took possession of the Fort, and slaughtered about 25 men of the Mazaree tribe who were in the Fort. They took some prisoners and pulled down the walls of the Fort. The above is a report obtained from Muhammad Bin Saef, a brother-in- law of Shaikh Zaeed Bin Khaleefah, while he was at Debay.No. 14, dated Shargah, the 7th February 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Shargah, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Mohammad Bin Saef, a brother-in-law of the Chief of Abu-Dhabee visited Debay, Shargah, Ajman and Ommel-Kaiwan ; he had letters from the Chief of Aboothabee to the Chiefs of the above principalities, and he wanted the Chiefs to aid him and co-operate with him in his warfare with Jasim Bin Thani. It appears that with the exception of the Chief of Debay no other Chief will join the Aboothabee Chief in his undertaking. I hear that the Chief of Debav is preparing to start, and that the Chief of Aboothabee will proceed by sea* to Khore Ghanazah, and meet inland with the Chief of Debay at the encamp ments of the Manaseer, the Mazaree and others, w ho have transferred them selves from the western districts to the neighbourhood of Debay. Mohammad Bin Saef has proceeded from Ommel-Karwan to the Bedouins in the interior, such as the Beni Katab, El-Ghafalah, El-Amamir, El-Daroo and others, who are allied with the Chief of Aboothabee, and whom he has asked to aid him against Jasim Bin Thani. &gt; # ' I hear that the Chief of Aboothabee, bis sons, bis brother and the elders of the Al-bu-faldh, together with the elders of the Al-bu-falasah of Debay, will proceed to Katr, and will not return until they have accomplished their object. I find that the previous report of the arrival of Abdul Rahman Bin Eeysal and Ibn Sabhan, and their joining Jasim Bin Thani, had no foundation. I think the Chief of Aboothabee will send some of his men by sea to Sil’, and horses and camels by land to that port, and thence they wull proceed , towards El-Katr. I hear this from the private conversation of people in Debay, and they argue that Jasim Bin Thani sends provisions and warlike materials* by sea to the places within the jurisdiction of the Chief of Aboothabee ; and say how is it that the Aboothabee Chief cannot send the same within his own limits ? The above is the new s I have heard, and which I submit for your information. * No. 41, dated Bushire, the 1st March 1889. From—Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. I have the honor to enclose translations of news-letters received from the No. g. 13th February 1889. Residency Agent at Bahrain, regarding- »• 26 , „ 20 th . „ the hostilities betwnen Shaikh Jasim-bin- Mohamed Thani and the Ahoothabee Chief. No. 22, dated the 13th February 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain. To—-Ihe Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Jfter Compliments, With reference to the previous report about the slaughter of the dependants of Shaikh Zaeed at El-Zafrah by Jasim-bin-Tiiani’s party, there appears to be some discrepancy about the numbers slain Abu Ghareb, one of the Na’ain tribe who was with Jasim in this expedition, states the number of slain may have amounted to about 100 persons, including adults old men, women, children, and the blind; and that Jasim would not accept any one’s intercession, contrary to the custom of the Arabs ; whilst Jasim lost about 18 men killed and U wounded. ™ /; r . riv J als fr( J m Aboothabe e report that Shaikh Zaeed has learned that about 70of his dependants were sbin, and that Jasim’s party lost about 45 men, that Shaikh Zaeed has sent word to all the tribesmen dependent on him to 10 /V ' \11 join him in view to proceeding to El-Katr; he did not go out to meet Jasim, because they were under the impression that Jasim would not go as far as El- Zafrah without the presence t&gt;f Ibn Rashid, and they further thought that there were only few men at that place. Arrivals from El-Bida report that Jasim has erected towers around El- Bida for protection, and that the people of Wakrah have rebuilt the town wall, as they all fear Shaikh Zaeed. The Bedouins of Jasim have for the present gone to their houses; but it is said that in the event of Shaikh Zaeed attacking El-Katr, they can muster about four to five thousand fighting men. No doubt they will meet him (Zaeed) before he reaches the town. 11 is said that the Turkish soldiers will protect the town and the watering place at Na’aijah. There is a common report that Shaikh Zaeed wants money and arms. The above Abu-Ghareb says that if five hundred of Shaikh Zaeed’s party or even less number had attacked them (Jasim’s party), they would have been totally destroyed. They returned from the place greatly fatigued. No. 28, dated the 14-th February 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain. To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. A fter Compliments .—Arrivals this day from El-Bida report that the inhabit ants are in great fear of Shaikh Zaeed, and keep watch during night; and Jasim is with the Na’aim, in the neighbourhood of Zobarah, and he intends marrying the daughter of Naser-bin-Jaber, and the inhabitants are busily engaged in build ing towers in different quarters of the town; that up to date they havd erected about eleven towers. They daily receive false alarms, and they go out of the town and then come back. The Turkish soldiers are also said to have moved out to Ma’aijah, the watering place about 3 miles distant from the town. They have taken with them ammunition, and if an attack is made they will fight; that Jasim has been giving them money and rice as a bribe to make them fight against Shaikh Zaeed’s party. But according to their regulations they will not proceed inland beyond this limit, unless Jasim forces them, and gives them a written order under his seal, because he is a Kaem Makam, or deceitfully induces the commandant to do so. It is reported that Shaikh Zaeed moved out of Aboothabee, bound for El-Katr. No. 26. dated the 20tli February 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain. To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Af er Compliments .—Arrivals from El-Bida report that all the inhabitants of the El-Katr ditricts are in great fear of Shaikh Zaeed-bin-Khaleefah, and the inhabitants of El-Bida are engaged in building towers around the town, and they intend to build a wall also. They have devoted their full attention to these defensive measures and have given up their ordinary business transactions. The people of Wakrah have repaired the towers and their town w r all, and the Tur kish soldiers have built defensive works along the path leading to the watering place viz., Na’aijah, where they have a fort and a tower. It appears they in tend to defend this spot against their enemy. I hear that Jasim has sent a special man with letters to Basra and Kowait, but his object has not transpired. Intelligence is received that Shaikh Zaeed has moved out of Aboothabee, and is collecting an army, and that the people of Debay and other territories and Bedou ins have joined him. It is said that in the event of Shaikh Zaeed proceeding to attack them they will go out of the town and meet him at some distance from the town.N* No. 47, dated Bushire, the 8th March 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Calcutta. I enclose translations of reports received from the Residency Agent at No. is, dated 19 th February 1889 . feliargali corroborating the accounts re- No. 19 , dated 19 th February 1889. ceived from Bahrain of the barbarities committed by the orders of Shaikh Jasim Bin Mokamed Tkani during his recent expedition. No. 18, dated the 19th February 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Shargah. To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. V After Compliments .—On the 15th February Sheikh Zaeed Bin Khaleefa Chief of Abu Dhabee and Shaikh Rashid Bin Maktum, Chief of Debay met at Khor Ghanaza to consult. It was agreed that on the 25th February the Chief of Debay with the A1 Bu Filasa and all their camel-men and horsemen should go to Sameh, and there meet the Chief of Abu Dhabee with his sons and relations and the A1 Bu Filah with all their camel-men and horsemen; and that the two chiefs should collect all their Bedouins and proceed to Guttar. The people of Abu Dhabee are making preparations to go, and are buying munitions of war, provisions and camels ; and there are now ready at Abu Dhabee 2,000 Ahu Dhabee and Leeva horsemen. f J hese people are very enraged with Sheikh Jasim Bin Thani for having killed women and children. The people of Abu Dhabee blame Sheikh Zaeed for having withdrawn men from Leeva to Abu Dhabee. It seems clear to me that Sheikh Zaeed’s intention is not to return from Guttar until he has taken revenge, or he and all the men with him are killed. This is a .most dilBcult matter. I have heard that in a short time 5,000 horsemen will be collected at Abu Dhabee. Sheikh Zaeed does not wish to take with him any men on foot. He has given notice to all the chiefs of the Beni Ghafir to aid him, and has told them that if they fail to do so, he will not interfere if they have trouble with the Manaseer hereafter. I report what I have heard. No. 19, dated the 19th Februaiy 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Shargah, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—When I arrived at Abu Dhabee, I enquired the par- ticulars of Sheikh Jasim Bin Thani's attack on Ghafra. Two of the A1 Mazari, Juma’ Bin Saif and Khalaf Bin Ghais, were at Ghafra, and Humeyd Bin Mana’ Mansuri spared them and let them go. These two men say that when Jasim approached the fort called “ Khanur” the fight began, and many on Jz&amp;lM’sside were killed and wounded. There were in the fort 80 mm of Leeva, viz., old men and the people who look after the date trees, for the Chief of Abu Dhabee had withdrawn all the fighting-men from Leeva to Ahu Dhabee. Humeyd Bin Mana’ Mansuri came up to the fort, and called out that Sheikh Jasirn would spare any Manaseer who were inside, and who would come out: thereupon 30 men of the A1 Majari went out, and those had no gunpowder or bullets, and they said that they were Manaseer, and Humeyd did not know that they were not so. Afterwards the Beni Hajar went to Jasim and asked him to spare the rest of the people in the fort, but Jasim got very angry and said that he had spent much money in getting there, and since his arrival one had asked him to spare some, and another had asked him to spare others. He then ordered the people of Guttar to attack the fort at once, and the Beni Hajar and other Bedouins did so, and making a breach in the wall of the fort, entered it, and 12killed 45 men ; the A1 Sudan spared S men, but Jasim afterwards ordered his slaves to kill them. Subsequently Jasim ordered the people of Guitar to kill any children they might find, and they killed 30, the eldest, of whom may have been 5 years of age; they also killed IS women who tried to save their children. The Bedouins with Jasim cried out much and represented that no Arab had ever done such a thing as kill women and children, but Jasim did not listen to them. The Bedouins did not kill any women or children, or those men who gave up th ir arms; they killed only those who fought. Jasim captured 30 freed slaves and 30 camels, and 40 camels were killed in the fight round the fort. Jasim afterwards took 2 Kazis of Leeva, Ahmad Bin Ghnis „ and Fahid, and tvinsr Fagots round them • Requires confirmation. . . t i i i. r i (sd.) e. c. b. burnt them alive.* 1 report what 1 have heard. No. 4^, dated Cushire, the 8th March 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i , Political .Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India,Foreign Department. I have the honor to submit translation of the marginally indicated letters 1. From Shaikh Jasim Bin Muhammad Bin Thani, ^ the subject of the hostilities between dated 17 th February u-89. Shaikh Jnsim Bin Mol ammrd Thnni and A FrJgiS Ase ' t ' S0 ' 33 ’ d ““ th,! tioni Yas Tribes under Abu Dhabbi. 3 . From Residency Agent, Bahrain, No. 34, dated 2. It SCCmS boVOml doubt that in his 25 th February 1889. late raid Shaikh Jasim was guilty of atro cious cruelties rarely committed by the most uncivilized Arab tribes. The feeling on both sides is so intensely hitter that no ordinary mediation would avail to effect a truce, and the warfare is likely to assume more serious propor tions and aspects. 3. The only way of restoring peace, appears to me* to be some joint action of British and Turkish authorities; and this can only take place if Turkish juris diction at El-Bida is recognized. 4. I do not propose sending any reply to Shaikh Jasim’s letter of 17th February. Dated the 17th February 1389. From— Jasim Bin Muhammad Bin Tiiani, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—Doubtless it is known to you what acts of oppression were done by the Manaseerand their friends. I heard that these people had built a fortified place, and having besought aid of God I attacked them, and obtained entrance into their refuge; and in that place was collected all the property which theseyieopJ.e had looted at sea and on land, nobody had been able to take this place or to^upture these men, but God aided me against them. These Bedouins are oppressors, and the villagers are worse. When God gave me aid against these people, and broke them, and killed those whom it pleased him, I was glad to give you tidings thereof, for they are robbers by sea and on land. And there is firm friendship between you and me, and I look after those places which you wish, and over which I have power. Be pleased always to give me news of your welfare, what seems good to you is pleasing to me. P. —I am hopeful in God, as he has given me aid against the oppressors, and has revenged the poor and humble, that he will again give me revenge for my son who was killed. ^ I have hope in God and in you that you will not counte nance the intention of the oppressors, and I hope that your subjects and agents in Oman may refrain from interference in that which does not concern them. 1314 No. 33, dated the 24th February 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments. —A man has come from Guttnr, who has given me re liable information about Sheikh Jasim’s army which went to Leeva and Ghafra from Guttar, lie says that many women and children were killed, and that those of the A1 Na’aim who were of the force say 4 women and 8 children of 9 years of age and under killed, and were disgusted that Jasim shewed no mercy to women and children, he also says that they came to a village called “ Shah Baglm!/’and there saw 6 men working amongst the date-trees, who were imme diately seized and bound. These men begged mercy from my informant, and when they were brought before Jasim, begged mercy from him also. Jasim, however, would not listen, and ordered that their throats should be cut. Just then an old and blind man came up led by a child, and asked Jasim for mercy, but the latter ordered that both the old man and the child should be killed. My informant further states that he saw in Leeva a woman whose arm had been cut off ; he enquired how this had happened, and learnt that the woman had a child in her arms, and Jasim’s men w r anfed to take it from her, and on her resisting, they had cut her arm off; and killed the child. The people who were working among the date trees took refuge in the fort called “ Kliunur ”, men, women and children, and barricaded the gate with bags of rice, but Jasim’s men broke into the place at once, and looted the rice. The men in the fort fired at Jasim’s men, and killed and wounded some. There were two towers in the fort, and some of villagers were in them, and some in the main part of the fort, and when Jasim’s men got in and fired, the whole place was filled with smoke, and all the men, women, children, and animals inside were killed ; mercy was shown to none, and Jasim himself did not wish one to be spared. The two tow r ers and their contents were set on lire and burnt. .Nobody has ever acted as Jasim has. My informant says Jasim’s army numbered about 400 in all viz., 150 horse men or perhaps less, and about 300 men mounted on camels. They w 7 ere well equipped with martini-rifles, and had plenty of ammunition, as well as every sort of weapon; they also had provisions with them. The munitions of war and some of the provisions were brought in six boats to Al-Sala*, and in coming and returning Jasim’s men took what they required from these boats. My informant adds that Jasim Bin Thani is much occupied in making warlike preparations. No 34, dated the 25th February 18S9. From—The 'Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments. —I have heard that Jasim Bin Thani has sent a man named Bin Naifa El Hajiri to Ibn Rashid at Jebel with 16 female camels and a letter in which he asks for aid, and in the event of Ibn Rashid himself not being able to come, asking him to send men, for Sheikh Zaeed intends to attack him (Jasim). Jasim has also sent many letters to Oman, in which he informs the people of what he has done at Leeva, and tells them that Ibn Rashid and his men are coming to Oman. Jasim, at first, wished to send his son Khalifa to Ibn Rashid, but ^&gt;entu- ally sent Bin Naifa. It is reported that Jasim has placed men on the look out at sea and on the coast, to give him warning of the approach of anyone. It is also reported that Sheikh Zaeed has sent provisions in boats to A1 Sala’ for his men. No. 54, Bushire, dated the 11th March 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honor to enclose translation of a report from the Residency No. 39, dated oth March 1889. Jasim and the Beni Yas Chief. Agent at Bahrain, on the subject of pre paration for hostilities between ShaikhNo. 39, dit^d the 5th March 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Alter Compliments —Arrivals from Gutter say that a wall has been built from the fort in which the Turkish soldiers are quartered, all round El-Bida : also some The people are in continual alarm about Sheikh Zaeed . sometimes they say that he has arrived close to the place, and sometimes that he is still distant. Jasim Bin Thani has left El-Bida with 80 horses and 150 camels ; some say that he intends to go to El-Odeid, and others that he is going to A1 Sala. The Nakhoda of Alii Bin Rashid’s boat arrived here to-day, and told me that Jasim had buried 2,000 guns at the two above named places, to take them when he required them, and that he has now taken them. Jasim has forbidden the A1 Na’aim to come to Bahrain ; Abu Gharib came here, and the chief gave him a boat, in which to bring his possessions; but when he went back to Guttar, he was not allowed to come, and the boat was sent back. No. 62, dated Bushire, the 16th March 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.n, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India Foreign Department, Calcutta. I have the honor to forward a translation of the marginally noted letter received from the Residency Agent, Arab No. 29 . dated sth March 1889. coast, containing intelligence of the affairs on the Pirate coast. No. 29, dated the Sth March 1889. From—The Presidency Agent, Shargah. To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments.—We Chief of Abu Dhabi has arrived at Sameh, and has collected men there. The Chief of Debny leaves Debay on the 13lh March to join the Chief of Abu Dhabi, and it is their intention to march on Guttar on the 18th idem. The tw r o men, whom the above 2 chiefs sent to Syed Eeysal at Muscat, have returned with rupees 2,100 each ; and Syed Eeysal has promised to send 500 hags of rice and munitions of war by boat to Debay. The Chief of the Beni Ghafar from Shargah to Rasel-Khymah have re fused to assist the Chiefs of Abu Dhabi and Dehay against Jasim Bin Thani. The Chief of Debay has written to the Chiefs of Shargah and Ajman that the alliance made with them in January is no longer binding; and he has written to me that he will never assist the Chiefs of Sharagh and Ajman against Salim Bin Sultan. The reason of this is that the Chief of Shargah has refused to help the Chief of Debny against Jasim. The Chief of Shargah is collecting 10 dol lars from each of his subjects, which he intends giving to his uncle Salim Bin Sultan, in accordance with the arrangement brought about by the Chief of Debay, that he should pay Salim Bin Sultan 400 dollars yearly. No. 70, dated Bushire, the 30th March 1889. From— Coioxel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honor to enclose translation of a letter from the Residency Agent at Bahrain, reporting some inform- - No. 43, dated 13th March 1889. o + ,n-n ronninntpd tn bim nhmit, Shaikh Jasim Bin Muhammed Thani. 2. An agent of Jasim’s is now in Bushire on his way to the Wali of Bus» rah, for whom he has a letter. 1516 No. 43, dated Hie 13th March 1839. From—The Residency A^ent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—Muhamed Bin Ahdul TTahnh says tlmt, Alihough Jasim bin Thani not acting like a wise man lie has good luck; that when he went to Lceva and Ghafn, how did he act ? Would any wise man act in that manner ? That Jasim had 400 or 50 ) men with him, and that when he arrived there, all his men were much fatigued, and tli it if 200 or 800 men had attack ed them then, the.y could have killed them all. That Jasim has his set pur pose and is reckless of all else : his sole desire is to take revenge on Zaeed in any way, by land or by se:i, even going so far as to be prepared to act in opposition to the British Representative, and incase of necessity retire towards Nejd, that he (Mohamed Bin Abdul Wahab) had advised Jasim to change all his money into notes, taking care that they did not get wet, but that he docs not know whether Jasim has done so, or will do so. Jasim has now abandoned everything else, and only wishes to attack Zaeed with the help ol the people of Gutter, he intends to meet Zaeed at a distance of two days' journey from hl-Bida, and has made preparations there for that pur pose, and has arranged many ambushes on the road. He also has sent spies to Al-Sala to ascertain whether any provisions have arrived there for Zaeed. I hear that the people of Guttar disapprove of what Jasim is doing, but are afraid to say anything. A Turkish official told me that the Commandant of the Turkish soldiers has complained to El-liasa and Busrah that Jasim has ruined the place by these hostilities, and that he cannot get food for his men in the Bazaar; for all the men of the place are engaged in constructing towers and fortifications. No. 73, dated Bushire, the 30th March 1889. From—Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Simla. I have the honor to forward a translation of the marginally noted report Ko. 48 , dated 19th March 1889. from ,he U(!sic,e ncy Agent, Bahrain, relat- . ing to the allairs of El-Katr. No. 48, dated the 19th March 18S9. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To— r Ihe Political Resident, Persian Gulf, After Compliments .—Arrivals from El-Bida give conflicting reports, some say th .t Jasim’s spies saw Zaeed’s land sentries and immediately came and reported the fact to Jasirn, who came to El-Bida, and having assembled all the men there distributed arms and ammunition amongst them ; that the men numbered over 2,000, and Jasim went Avith them to a place called Misemir (where there is wafer) between Al-Wakra and El-Bida, Others say that Zaced-bin-Khalifah has reached Al Sala ; others again, that Jasim has received a letter from Shargah, in Avhich he is informed that Sheikh Zaeed had left an l was on his way with the Chief of Debay to attack Guttar. It may be that the Chief of Shargah sent this letter, for 1 hear that he is not friendly towards Zaeed, It is sai l that R ishid-bin M Etum, Chief of Debay, has announced to Jasim that lie will not act in alliance witli him, to which Jasim replied ‘‘ who and what are you.” The Kazi of Guttar, having bi en relieved of his post, arrived here to-day, and he says that Guttar is in a most disquieted state, that the people are in great fear : and that when Zaeed comes, the Turkish soldiers will only guard the water at Na ija. That there is now no ill-feeling between Jasim and the Turkish soldiers, hut that Jasim is always tr ‘acberous. I have heard that when Jasim was going to Leevaand Ghafra, hA gave some money to the Commandant of the Turkish soldiers, and asked him to let him17 have a trumpet and 2 men for the purpose of frightening the people of Oman, but that the Commandant refused. No. 82, dated Bushire, the 7th April 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Simla. I have the honor to forward a translation of the marginally noted report from the Residency A gent, Bahrain, relat- No. 56, dated 2nd April 1889. ing to the affairs of El-Katr. No. 56, dated the 2nd April 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—The latest nows about Katr is that the Naeem have advised Jasim-bin-Thani to shift from Meeseymeer to Meesheyreeb near Bida, on the ground that the former place is about 2 hours distance from Bida while the latter is only 5 minutes. It appears that Jasim has acquiesced in their suggestion. The Naeem have represented to him that the main force of Zaeed’s army will he concentrated on Bida, and that if Jasim finds the enemy too strong to cope with it in an open field, he can then easily battle the enemy from within the fort, by removing his force into it. While at Messeymeer, Jasim sent for some Turkish soldiers who went to him and returned. His object is to sound them as to whether they will join him in the coning struggle. The people at Katr believe as certain that Zaeed has already commenced his march towards Katr with 1,500 men, so Jasim has despatched spies in all directions to watch the approach of the enemy. The rumour is that Jasim has with him about 4,000 men, and 200 horsemen, besides some Turkish sol diers and a portion of the Naeem, the mercenaries of the Sheikh of Bahrain; and the impression is that Jasim’s men will fight to the last. But the majority are of the opinion that his men are not willing to fight, but that they have been compelled to take up arms. It is also said that the Turkish soldiers will not leave their fort, hut others again think that in case of an emergency they might come out and go to Nayjah to protect the wells. Nayjah is more distant from Bida than Meesheyreeb. Owing to strong shammal, no one has come from Katr with news from that place. No. 88, dated Bushire, the 15th April 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honor to forward translations of further reports noted on the No. 62 , dated 28th March 1889. margin, received from the Residency Agent „ 58 , ioth April 1889 . at Bahrain, regarding the impending en- „ 59, „ nth do. counter between Shaikh Jasim and Shaikh Zaeed of Abu Thabee. No. 52, dated the 28th March 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. A man by name Mulhan-al-Hassawee has arrived here to-day from Katr and has brought the following intelligence. It is 8 days, he says, since he leftl c El-Bida, and he reports that at the time of his departure from there he henrd that the spies despatched by Jasim had arrived at that place, and that Shaikh Zaeed had arrived near about. That Jasim had solicited the aid of the Turkish soldiers at El-I3ida and that they were preparing to go to join him. That Jasim at the head of his force had arrived at a place called Sehaleeya about hours* distance from El-Bida. That Jasim has settled his difference with the Turkish soldiers who had now placed themselves under his orders. That he had given them 100 bags of rice and 50 Kerosine oil tins tilled with ghee. Mulham is of opinion that if the Turkish soldiers actually join Jasim in an attack against Zaeed, they are sure to defeat the latter as they are disciplined troops. Mulham also reports that Naeefa a messenger from Ibn Rashid has landed at Mattrah, a village in Hassa, with letters to Jasim and a present of 2 mares and 3 camels, and that Jasim has informed his troops that the reinforcement from Ibn Rashid will arrive within the next two days, and that the Al-Murrah will also lend their aid to him. I am however of opinion that these promises of help which Jasim is hold ing out to his troops are only intended to encourage them. I have seen a letter from Jasim to Mujbil in which the writer says that he is prepared to meet Zaeed and that he is not afraid of his advance; on the con trary that he will .himself march out to attack Zaeed in case the latter should not advance against him. In that letter he also wishes Mujbil to believe that Ibn Rashid will not fail to fuliil his promise. The date of this letter is 17th March. It is apparent that Jasim wrote that letter before the arrival of Naeefa. My own opinion is that if the news about Zaeed’s advance be true, and also that if Jasim be supported by the Turkish soldiers, Zaeed’s forces will have hard vsork before them ; for Jasim is regardless of expense and the Tur-' kish soldiers are greedy, as is known. Their number at El-Bida is 250. No. 58, dated the 10th April 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To——The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—News has reached Bahrain that Jasim bin Thani has marched from Messeymeer to Moosheyrib near Bida. I think that he has taken this step by the advice of the Turkish soldiers as it was not possible for them to join him at Messeymeer which is distant from Bida about 4 hours. I heir official instructions are that they should defend the town and its suburbs, and they are bound to defend the water wells at Nayija at all events, upon the supply of which the inhabitants depend, for the water of Messheyrib is brackish besides being scanty. The distance between Bida and Nayija is about 15 or 20 minutes. It is reported that it is the intention of Jasim on the arrival of Zaeed, to find out the strength of the enemy before risking an engagement; and in the event of the enemy being too strong for him to venture upon an open engagement with them, to order his troops to retire into the town ; and request the Turkish soldiers to open fire upon the enemy from the fort if they come near Nayija. If he finds them weak, and his own men steady and reliable, to go out to meet the enemy. Nothing is yet known about Zaeed’s movements towards Katr as no one has come here from Bida this week. Some Bedouins belonging to the tribe of Naeem have arrived here from Roowayis and Abu Dtholoof. They have hired some boats for the purpose of removing themselves and families to Bahrain together with all their moveables They have been advised to do so by the people of El-Bida. } s supposed that this step has been taken by the Naeem from fear of Zaeed bin Khalifah who they expect will detach some parties against them for the purpose of plundering and slaughtering them.t No. 59, dated 11th April 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Bahrain, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments. —Last night Muhammed bin Abdul TTahab arrived in Bahrain and was the guest of the Chief, and I hear that they held some secret conversation that night.' Next morning Abdul Wahab came to Manamah, and he hired a boat which he intends to despatch to Bida to-night, I do not know on what errand, to Jasim, it may be that he may have some communication to make to Jasim from his own part, or that the Chief of Bahrain may have commissioned him to send some message to Jasim. No one comes to know what passes between the Chief of Bahrain and Abdul Wahab; hut a banian by name Akoo informs me that Shaikh Esa is going to send a letter in that boat. Before the arrival of Abdul Wahab Muhammed bin Khatr and Sultan bin Salamah had an interview with the Chief of Bahrain and suggested to him that he should mediate between Jasim and Zaeed with a view to making peace be tween them. But the Chief replied to them that none of them had given him the slightest hint about reconciliation. I met Abdul Wahab to-day who says that the object of Jasim in entering Moosheyrib and Bida is to avoid dispersion of his troops^ which he feared would take place had he remained in Messeymeer, as the majority of his men are not submissive to him. Once they are in Bida they will net be able to disperse. It is probably Jasim’s intention, if Zaeed comes near Nayija, to despatch Turkish soldiers in front and his other troops in rear. He is afraid that, if his Katr troops enter alone into an engagement with the enemy, they will betray him and go over to the enemy; for they have mostly been forced to enlist themselves for the pending battle. It is not known yet whether Zaeed has arrived at Katr. Should Jasim find the enemy too strong he will retire into the town which is surrounded by a wall: and open fire at the enemy from within. In that case Zaeed will not be able to come near. No. 89, dated Bushire, the 15th April 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Simla. No. 35, dated 23rd March 1889. I have the honor to forward a transla tion of the marginally noted news report from the Residency Agent, Arab Coast. No. 35, dated the 23rd March 1889. From—The Residency Agent, Shargah, To—The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. After Compliments .—I have heard that the Chief of Kishm had arrived on a visit to the Chief of Um-el-Kawain, bringing with him a present of a horse to the latter, and that after a stay of 7 days he had returned to his place. 20th March .—The Chief of Abu-Thabee has started from Sameya to wards Katr. 2Ut March .—Maktoon Bin Hashir, Batee Bin Suheyl &amp; Abdullah Bin Harj, the Shaikhs of Al-bu-Elassah have left to join him with 800 camelmen 19and 25 horsemen, and it is said that the trihe of Beni-Katab will also join him. I have heard that the sons of Ghusn Bin Sinaan have already joined him with 400 camelmen and 16 horsemen; and that the tribes of Al- dowahar, Al-awamir and Al-duro intend to join him at Seykhah, a place within 5 day’s journey of Katr. As the force which he intends to bring in the field will be very large, and there is no sufficient quantity of water along the line of march, the Chief of Abu-Thabee is despatching his troops by detachments to Dubeykhah the place appointed for the rendezvous. The number of troops at present under his command is estimated at 5,000 camelmen and 200 horsemen. The Chief of Debay has not joined the expedition in person at the express desire of the Abu-Thabee Chief. Shaikh Diyah Bin Khalifah has been appointed locum tenens of the Chief of Abu-Thabee during the latter’s absence. The Chief of Abu-Thabee has written a letter to the Chief of Um-el-Kawain urging him to join the expedition. In an interview I had with the latter chief, he explained to me that there was no alliance between himself and the Chief of Abu-Thabee of an. offensive and defensive nature, and that the call he had received was instigated by the Chief of Debay with the object of breaking up the friendship which existed between the Chief of Abu-Thabee and him (Chief of Um-el-Kawain). He further explained to me that the ill-will which the Chief Df Debay bore towards him was the outcome of a dispute which arose between them regarding a certain pearl. This pearl was sold at Debay for a low price by pearl-fishers from Um-el-Kawain. On his be coming aware of it the Chief of Um-el-Kawain demanded the restoration of the same on behalf of his subjects, which was however refused. Hence the ill-feeling between the two chiefs. Since that occurrence, the intercourse between the two places has been stopped. I have seen a letter addressed by Jasim Bin Thani to the Chief of Um-el-Kawain, in which the writer, appealing to the religious feelings of his co-religionist, impresses upon the latter the necessity of his ren dering him help, and expresses his assurance that he will not help his antagonist against him. There is now no friendship between Shaikh Zaeed and the Chiefs all along the coast from Shargah to Ras-el-Kheymah. A fight has taken place between the two sections of the Naeem, Al-Bu- khereyban and Al-bu-shamis. On the 23rd March the Chief of Ajman accom panied by 100 camelmen went to mediate between them. The Chiefs of Shargah and Ajman have entered into a treaty of neutrality. The initiative was taken by the Chief of Shargah who despatched as his ambas sador, Sultan Bin Aweis, the Chief of Hojrah, to the Chief of Ajraan, who in his turn despatched to Shargah, on his behalf, Hamdan Bin Rashid the Shaikh of Naeem. The Chiefs of Ajman and Um-el-Kawain have also, I hear, conclud ed a treaty of neutrality. Two months ago Shaikh Salim Bin Sultan married his cousin, the daughter of the Chief of Ajman. Shaikh Ibrahim bin Sultan has arrived at Shargah on a visit to the Chief. A man by name Rashid has arrived at Um-el-Kawam bringing letters from the Chief of Bahrain to the Chief of Abu-Thabee. It appears that the Chief of Bahrain has asked the Chief of Abu-Thabee not to wreak his vengeance on the Naeem who were with Jasim at the time when the attack on Leeva was directed. Ahmed bin Seif Al-Astanee has despatched 10 earthen vessels filled with gunpowder to Jasim Bin Thani by a special boat. I have received this news from a trustworthy person who was present at their landing. 2021 List of Enclosures in Despatch No. 74, (^ r ) dated the 24th May 1889, f ,om the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, to Her Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Serial No. No. and date of paper. From whom, and to whom Subject. 1 v*-'' No. 17, dated the 31st January 1889. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. Forwards translation of a report re garding 1 an expedition undertaken by Shaikh Jasim bin Muhammad 1 hani of El Bida against the Beni ^ as, and the alleged slaughter of Arabs at El Jowa. 2 ✓ ,' No 20, dated the 4th February 1889. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. Reports on the subject of an attempt ed reconciliation between Shaikh Jasim and Shaikh Zaeed bin Kkalee- fah, the Beni Yas Chief. 3 No. 21, dated the 4th February lb89. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. Encloses translations of reports regard ing the recent expedition of Shaikh Jasim. 4- No. 22, dated the 4th February 1889. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. % In continuation of his letter No. 22, dated the 4th February 1889, for wards translation of a further re port regarding the massacre of Arabs by the force of Shaikh Jasim. 5 No. 31, dated the 18th Febmary 18S9 (Secret and confiden tial.) From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. • Forwards translation of a letter from Shaikh Jasim to Abdallah Pasha ibn r l heneyyan of the A1 Suood family of Nejd describing his relations with Shaikn Zaeed, and soliciting per* mission to attack the latter and the territories of Oman. Offers sugges tions in the matter. 6 ■ &gt; No. 576-E., dated the 14th March 1889. Telegram to the Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf. With reference to the above, en quires what Turkish rights on the Katr coast he would recognise, and under what conditions and within what limits. 7 Dated the 15th March 1889. Telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Replies to the above telegram. 8 No. 37, dated the 22nd February 1889. From the Politipal Resident ig the Per sian Gulf. Forwards translations of reports on the subject principally of the hostil ities between Shaikh Jasim and Shaikh Zaeed. % 9 No. 41, dated the 1st March 1889. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. Encloses translations of news letter’s on the above subject.5rial tfo. 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 13 List of Enclosures in Despatch, fyc., SfC .— (continued.) No. and date of paper. No. 47, dated the 8th March 1889. No. 48, dated the 8th March 1889. No. 54, dated the 11th March 1889. No. 62, dated the 16th March 1889. No. 70, dated the 30th March lb89. No. 73, dated the 30th - March 1889. No. 82, dated the 30th March 1889. No. 88, dated the 15th April lb89. No. 89, dated the 15th April 1889. From whom, and to whom. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. From the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. Snhject. Submits translations of reports re garding the barbarities committed by the orders of Shaikh Jasim dur ing his recent expedition. Forwards translations of letters in re gard to the hostilities referred to. Offers observations, and considers that the only way of securing peace is by joint action of British and Turkish authorities, which can only take place if Turkish jurisdiction at El Rida is recognised. Encloses translation of a report re garding further preparations for hostilities between Shaikh Jasim and Shaikh Zaeed. Submits translation of a letter con taining intelligence of affairs on the Katr coast. Forwards translation of a letter from the Residency Agent at Bahrain, communicating information respect ing Sliaikh Jasim-bin-Muhammad bin Thani. Submits translation of a report from the Residency Agent at Bahrain re garding the affairs of El Katr. Idem. Forwards translation of further re ports from the Residency Agent at Bahrain, relating to the impending encounter between Shaikh Jasim and Shaikh Zaeed of Abu Dthabee. Forwards translation of a news-re port from the Residency Agent, Shargah, regarding affairs on the Arab Coast. (Sd.) n. S. BARNES, Offg. Under-Secretary to the Government of India.No. 74 dated Simla, the 24th May 1889. From—The Government of India, To—The Secretary of State for India. In continuation of our despatch No. 7 (External), dated 15th January 1880, we have the honour to forward, for Your Lordship’s information, copies of the papers noted in the accompanying list, regarding the state of affairs on the West Coast of the Persian Gulf. 2. After considering the opinions expressed by Her Majesty’s Sec retary of State for Foreign Affairs and by Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Con stantinople, the Government of India cannot recommend any further attempt to come to an understanding with Turkey, nor the recognition of Turkish rights over any part of the coast on which such rights have not hitherto been recognised. The present state of affairs, however, is not satisfactory, and it is of so much importance to prevent the spread of disorder among the Trucial Chiefs and towards Oman, that we hope Her Majesty’s Government may find • it possible to take some effective stops in the matter. 'Hm 23Extract from the Persian Gulf Diary for the week ending the 7th April 1889. ******* It is reported that Jasim is about to despatch some boats to Sila with armed men, when it is probable an encounter may take place between them and Zaid’s force either on land or sea. No. 97, dated Bushire, the 26th April 1889. . From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I HAVE the honour to forward a translation of the marginally noted letter from the Residency Agent, Bahrain, con taining intelligence of affairs on the Arab Coast. No. 60, dated loth April 1889. Translation of a letter from the Residency Agent at Bahrain, No. 60, dated the 15th April 1889. A boat has arrived here from Bidaa bringing 15 Turkish soldiers who are on their way to Busrah. Letters brought by that boat say that Zaid has not yet arrived on the frontiers of Katr, but it appears that ‘jasim is encamped with his troops, consisting of towns-people and Bedouins, roundabout Bidaa. Some say that Jasim’s forces number over three thousand men besides the Tur kish troops, but others again put it down to two thousand only. The Turkish soldiers who arrived at Bahrain praise much the equipment of Jasim’s army, which, they say, is supplied with Martini rifles. They say the Turkish soldiers stationed at Bidaa will follow Jasim as far as Naijah. They also mention that Zaid wrote to the Turkish Commandant at Bidaa asking him not to interfere in the pending encounter, as he (Zaid) was not going to ad vance against the town where the Turkish troops are stationed. It appears that Zaid even promised the Commandant to supply him and his soldiers with all the necessary provisions in the shape of water, firewood, &amp;c., which is usual ly obtained from the outlying villages, if he remained neutral. But the Commandant appears to have refused such a proposal, and to have replied to Zaid that he (Commandant) has a duty to perform in protecting the town and the people, and that if he failed in that duty, he would be answerable to his Government. The Nakhoda of the boat above referred to reports that Jasim has issued an order to the Native craft, enjoining the Nakhoda’s not to carry any passengers from the place, and that no one is now allowed to leave that place. The people of Ruwais and Abudhaluf have removed themselves to Bah rain with their families, cattle, and chattels, by special boats from Bahrain, des patched by their tribesmen living there. The Naim from Ruwais and other northern villages have also sent their families with all their effects to Bahrain. It is said that Jasim is constantly renewing his pact with the Naim for fear they might betray him. Some hints have gone to Jasim from here that the Naim are inwardly well disposed [towards the chief of Bahrain, and that they will not help him (Jasim) in time of need. But I do not believe in this. Telegram dated Simla, the 13th May 1889. From—Resident, Bushire, To—'Foreign Secretary, Simla. It is reported that serious fighting occurred between Abu-Thabi and Katr forces, resulting defeat latter. 1S No. 113, dated Bushire, the 16th May 1SS9. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. W ith reference to my telegram of 13th instant, I enclose a translation of a report which I have received from No. 3/, dated nth May iss9. the Eesiclency Agent at Lingah, containing intelligence of fighting having occurred between the forces of the Chief of Abu- Thahi 'and those of Shaikh Jasim-bin-Thani, and the reported crushing defeat of the latter. I expect to receive the accounts from the other side in a few days. Translated purport of a report from the Residency Agent, Lingah, No. 37, dated the 11th May 18S9. A vessel had arrived at Lingah from Abu-Thabi, with letters for merchants and others, in which it was stated that a “ kossid ” had arrived at Abu-Thabi from Shaikh Zaid-bin-Khalifa (the Chief) bearing the news that he had first de tached Tahnoon (his son) with a body of troops composed of Debay and Abu-Thabi men to Karah, and they encountered a number of Jasim’s party composed of Beni Hajir, Al-Morrah and Monasir, and inflicted on them a severe defeat, three hundred of the enemy having been slain, many wounded and the rest put to flight. Much spoil was taken from Jasim’s force, including 2,000 camels. Tab noon’s detachment then returned and joined Shaikh Zaid in the vicinity of Katr. Shaikh Zaid with his own force encountered Jasim’s force on 23rd Shahan (24th April 1889) near Katr (El-Bidaa probably meant). Eighty-five of the Katr men were killed and many wounded, and they were routed and fled to Katr ( El-Bidaa ). Khalifa-bin-Jaym* Than! and Ahmed-bin-Thani (Shaikh’s bro ther) were slain, and a report was received that Jasim himself also was wounded. Besides arms, about twenty horses of Jasim’s were taken, and fifteen killed. Shaikh Zaid remained two days near Katr (Bidaa), but no one went out from the place to encounter him. He then retired towards Abu-Thabi. *A son of Shaikh Jasim. No. 117, dated Bushire, the iCih May 1889. From— Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honour to enclose translations of the correspondence noted on th e „ „ „ , n , . v , , , margin, on the subject of a complaint that soth April 1889 . Shaikh Jasim had sent munitions or war From Shaikh Jasim-bin-Mohamed Thaui, dated sea in furtherance of his Warlike OPCr- 21st April 1889. f. • ai, mi x i ations against Abu-Thabi, to a place beyond the limits of his jurisdiction, and within those of the Abu-Thabi Chief. A precis of the previous correspondence is also enclosed. 2. There is no room for doubt as to the facts alleged, and it has been ruled by the Government of India that Odeyd, and consequently Sila, is under Abu-Thabi, and Shaikh Jasim has therefore made use of the sea to operate hos- tilely against his Beni Yas enemies and invade their territory. 3. Although there is no express undertaking on the part of the Chiefs who are parties to the maritime truce, to abstain from acting against each other by sea, it is well understood by all that such action would be constructively a breach of their engagement to the British Government, and might subject them to penalties. Whilst abiding by this necessary rule themselves, the “ Trucial” Chiefs naturally expert us to impose a similar restriction on the Katr Chief who indeed does not repudiate the obligation, but boldly claims Sila as Katr territory, and further denies having sent boats to that place with war stores.4. I think perhaps the Government of India would not think it expedient in present circumstances to exact a penalty from Shaikh Jasim, which would mean employment of Naval force; hut I think it would he desirable to authorize me to intimate to Jasim the disapproval and displeasure of Government at his action, and to inform him that a repetition of it would lead to measures of a more serious nature. f Ihe delicacy ot the position as regards Katr requires me to seek the instruction of Government in this case. No. 68, dated the 30th April 1889. From—The Residency Agent at Bahrain, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I beg to forward herewith a letter from Jasim-hin-Thani to your address, in reply to your No. 103, in which he says that Sila is within his territories. This is his own assertion, which he makes in order to exculpate himself from blame. He forgets, however, that notwithstanding his wish to reside at Odeyd which is under Sila, and which is distant from the latter place one day’s jour ney, he was not allowed to do so. As regards Sabakha, its soil is covered in some parts with saline incrus tations and in others is sandy. No grass grows on it. It begins from near Sila and ends at Dafrah. Sabakha is one day’s journey distant from either of these places. Jasim says that he despatched to Sila only two boats containing provisions. This assertion goes against him. If Sila is within his territories, and he is prepared to repel even by force of arms any one that might come there, why does he attempt to palliate by saying that he sent there only two boats ? He refers to the incident at Dafrah, and says that Zaid had written to him saying that he (Zaid) had no connection with the people of that place. If so, why did Jasim slaughter them wholesale, and what crime had they committed ? According to his assertion, it is Zaid who is his enemy ; it is therefore absurd of Jasim to wreak his vengeance on them, when they are not in any w r ay connected with the enemy. What he means, however, is that some thieves were infesting Dafrah, about whom he wrote to Zaid, who might have probably said that the matter did not concern him. The fact is that Jasim is now trying by all the means in his power to ex culpate himself. Dated the 21st April 1889. From—J asim-bin-Th a ni. To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After compliments .—I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated 25th Rejjub (28th March) in which you mention that I despatch ed a boat to Kufariyah and Sila. But these places are within my terri tories, and I have told you so before. It is a matter of public notoriety that Sabakha is the zone which separates Katr from Dafrah. A portion of Sabakha on the side of Katr is comprehended within Katr territory ; and it is my duty to repel even by force of arms, any one that encroaches upon Sila and'other places within my territory. I request you to be impartial in the matter. If you have any doubt as to what I say, you can ascertain, and you will find that what I say is true. If you enquire of people who know and are just, you will find that Dafrah is not called so until past Sabakha. Is it ever said that people residing at Sila are residing at Dafrah ? It is an established fact that the limit of Oman on our side is first Dafraln^Tt is Zaid who has invaded my countiy, killed some people, and made others captives, without there being any previous cause, 3 .4i 4 A 4 4 except that I went to Dafrah, the place of the Monasir tribe, the mischief makers both by land and sea. But the country of Zaid is 9 days* journey off. How does he get angry with one who goes to punish the offenders, and expects me not to he so when he invades my country ? It is essentially neces sary that I should rise and march against his country for the purpose of wreaking vengeance upon him. Of course I am waiting for an opportunity, and I am not off my guard. I pray for equity and justice at your hands, for which vou are renowned. Some days past I despatched two boats containing provisions and nothing else. This is what was necessary for me to inform you about. P.S .—I hold many letters from Zaid, hearing on the subject of the crimes committed by the people of Dafrah, in which he disowned them and told me that I could myself call them to account. I have those letters with me now, and should you wish to see them, I shall forward them to you. Precis of correspondence relating to a complaint made by Sliailcli Zaid, that Shaikh Jasim sent stores and munitions of war by sea to Al-Sila and the Bay of Kufariyah, during his expedition against El.Jawa. On the 13th January 1889, the Residency Agent at Shargah forwarded* . TT ,. „ a letter to the Resident from Shaikh Zaid- * Undercovor hisKo.6. . -.-r. pat . . bin-Jvhalira, Cmef ot Abu-1 habi, com plaining that Shaikh Jasim-bin-Muhammad-bin-Tkani of El-Bidaa had sent armed men and stores by sea to Al-Sila, a place included iu his (Shaikh Zaid’s) territories. A copy of this letter was sentf to the Residency . Agent at Bahrain for t Under cover No. 74 , dried 2 ist February investigation and report, and Shaikh Zaid 1889. was informed^ that enquiries were being * No - 73 - dated 21st February 1889 ’ made in the matter. On the 7 th February, the Residency Agent at Shargah forwarded § a letter . TT , u- v dated 23rd January from Shaikh Zaid, § Under cover his iso. 15. i • • p n r • , , ’ containing a further complaint that Shaikh Jasim had sent 5 boats to the Bay of Kufariyah (a place within Shaikh Zaid’s territory), with armed men, munitions of war and stores for the use of his ex pedition against Shaikh Zaid. In this letter the boats and their owners were specified. The Residency Agent also forwarded, at the same time, the state ment of one Thani-bin-Ataish (the brother of the owner of one of the boats specified in Shaikh Zaid’s letter), which is to the following effect, viz., that he, under orders from Shaikh Jasim, conveyed a cargo of dates in his brother’s boat from Wakrah to the Bay of Kufariyah, in company with four other boats laden with stores and spears. The man adds that the crews of those boats told him that they had also gunpowder, lead, and muskets on hoard, and he corro borates the report that Jasim had sent stores by sea to Al-Sila. In reply, || Shaikh Zaid was informed that enquiries were being made on the subject. In reply to the Resident's No. 74, dated 21st February, the Residency ^ No. 36 , dated 4 th March 1889 . Agent at Bahrain wrote^f that lie had heard reports of Jasim having sent men, muni tions of war and stores by sea to Al-Sila. He had questioned two men of the Al-Naim (who had been with Jasim in his expedition), who said that both in going and returning Jasim’s men took what stores and munitions of war they required from boats at Al-Sila ; 25 to 30 armed men of El-Bidaa being left as guards in each boat. The Residency Agent also forwarded a confidential letter** which he had received from one Ali-bin-IIassan-bin-Jamal of El-Bidaa, in which the writer states that 5 boats laden with stores and munitions of war, had gone from El-Bidaa to Al-Sila, and specifies the boats and their owners. On receipt of the above, the Resident wroteff to Shaikh Jasim that he had tt No. 103 , dried 281 b March 1889 . | ie » rd from various sources that lie (Jasim) had sent, during his recent hostilities 5 No. 66, dated 16th February 1889. * # Dated 26lh December 1888.against the people dependent on the Chief of Abu-Thabi, vessels with stores and munitions of war to the Bay of Kufariyah and Al-Sila,—places beyond the limits of his recognized jurisdiction; and called for an explanation. . On the 17th April, Shaikh Jasim wrote to the Resident, making a counter complaint that Shaikh Zaid had sent a boat to Al-Sila, which place he No. 121 , dated 4 th May issj. (Jasim) claimed to be within his territory. In reply,* he was referred to the Resident’s No. 103, dated 28th March, and informed that the British Government consider Al-Sila to he within the territories subordinate to Abu-Thabi. » ■ 4 ' ” No. 118, dated Bushire, the 23rd May 1889. From —Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—ihe Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honour to forward translations of the marginally noted reports No. 65 , dated 30 th April 1889 . from the Residency \gent at Bahrain, „ 69, „ 5th May „ relative to affairs of El-Katr, and hostili- ” ’ ” ” ” ties between Abu-Thabi and that District. The report received from Lingah of a serious defeat having been inflicted on Sheikh Jasim, is so far unconfirmed. No. 65, dated the 30th April 1889. From—The Residency Agent, at Bahrain, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to report that Akif Pasha, the new Mutnserif of El- Ilasa, arrived at Bahrain by the mail steamer. Muhammad Abdul Wahab went on board to see him and took him to Manamah. The Mutaserif remained with Muhammad Abdul Wahab for two days and one night, and then went to El-Hasa in a boat which was hired by Muhammad Abdul Wahab at his own expense, and he accompained the Mutaserif as far as Bideyyia (on the confines of Bahrain). The Mutaserif went to Ojeyr, and from thence to El-llasa. It is probable that Muhammad Abdul Wahab gave him some money. The Mutaserif was informed regarding the pending encounter between Jasim and Zaid. Nasrallah, brother of Ahmed-bin-Mehdy, informed me that Jasim, son of Muhammad-bin-Katr, when he arrived at Busrah, had telegraphed tojConstan- tinople through the Nakib to the following effect:—Zaid with 8,000 troops, and instigated and supported by the British, has come to Katr, which has been a Turkish province for many years.” There was a reply received at Busrah to the above telegram, but in the interval, Shaban Pasha happened to be deposed, and the affair was forgotten. Jasim-bin-Muhammad-bin-Khatr and Nasrallah the above mentioned, re turned from Busrah with Akif Pasha. During the voyage, Jasim-bin-Muham- mad-bin-Khatr was constantly with him, and kept talking about the affairs of Bahrain and Katr. Jasim is a young and light minded man, and it was his own officiousness that prompted him to enter on such subject. Mohamed Abdul Wahab, who is a shaitan and loves disturbance, acquanited the Mutaserif with all that is going on in these parts, and was seconded by Abdul Rahman-bin- Aidan and Mujbil-ad-Dukeyr in everything that he told the Mutaserif. I have heard that on the night of the Mutaserif’s arrival here, Abdul Wahab des patched letters to Katr, and also despatched Ghanim in a special boat to Katr, with letters after the Mutaserif’s departure from here. I suspect two things from these measures of Muhammad Abdul Wahab, viz., (1) that he asked the Mutaserif to write a letter to the Commandant of the Turkish troops stationed at Bidaa, enjoining him to protect the people of Katr against Zaid; and (2) to write a threatening letter to Shaikh Zaid in order to deter him from invading Katr. .&lt; {Abdul Wahab endeavoured to brinp: about an interview between the Muta serif and the Chief of Bahrain, but the former declined to go to the Chief’s place, and the Chief did not like to go to the Mutaserif first. I had an interview with the Mutaserif which lasted for about 20 minutes. He did not speak out his views, but said that Bahrain was not a good place, and spoke highly of Karachi . He remarked in a laughing tone that he did not know why people were so fond of pearls which were a perishable article, and not so of gold and silver which were lasting. I think that he is a hot-tempered man, as he is a Military Olficer and cannot be skilled in administrative policy. Formerly the Turkish officials sent to Hasa, Katr and Katif, when they came here, did not interfere in the affairs of Bahrain and Katr. What they were occupied with was how to make money, but now there are many agitators in these places who win the ears of those officials by their eloquence. Nasrallah, brother of Ahmed-bin-Mehdi, and Mansoor came to Bahrain from Busrah with Akif Pasha, and they paid his passage, and all other expenses besides giving him about Its. 1,400 in cash, including the value of a watch (gold). This is the present which he got to start with. Then Mohamed Abdul Wahab also gave him some. At Hasa, the Mutaserif will get more bribes. After the Ramadan he will come to Katif and get something there too. Such is the conduct of the Turkish officials. But it is to be remembered that those who give them bribes do so for their own advantage with a view to purchase justice. No. 69, dated the 6th May 1889. From—The Residency Agent at Bahrain, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. With reference to my letter No. 65 of the 30th April 1889, I have the honour to report that Ghanim-bin-Ataish returned from Katr, and I had a con versation with him regarding his journey to Katr. It was only by inadvertence that he gave me an account of his journey, and which is as follows :—“ I was the bearer of a letter from Akif Pasha to Shaikh Zaid which was handed to me by Muhammad Abdul Wahab. It was a threatening one, and Zaid was warned in it that any aggressive movement on bis part against the villages subject to Katr, which is a Turkish province, would be promptly acted against. This letter was written under the impression that Zaid had already arrived at Katr, and it was meant that it should reach him there. The letter was open, and I gave it to Jasim for perusal. He said that Zaid had not arrived, and that he (Jasim) had no need of such a letter as he was not afraid of Zaid. Then I brought back that letter, and gave it to Muhammad Abdul Wahab with another from Jasim. Shaikh Esau has seen that letter.” After the departure of the Mutaserif, I had an interview with the Chief of Bahrain, and asked him whether he had heard anything regarding the secret conversation which passed between the Mutaserif and Muhammad Abdul Wahab, and whether he knew what was the object of Ghanim’s mission to Katr, who was despatched there with letters in a special boat. But I was unable to elicit any information from him. I have no doubt that this caution on his part has been enjoined by Muhammad Abdul Wahab. * Probably regarding the attitude be should ob serve in the coming encounter between Jasim and Zaid. From what I have heard it appears that the Mutaserif has not sent any order* to the Commandant of the Turkish troops stationed at Bida. Ghanim-bin-Atai sh was originally a subject of Zaid, and was living at Fuweyrat. When Jasim ordered the abandonment of that place he came to Bahrain, and is nowin the service of Muhammad Abdul Wahab. He informs me that during bis recent stay at Bidaa he heard that Jasim had sent two boats, with 30 or 40 armed men in each, to Sila for the purpose of finding out whether there were any boats lying there belonging to the people of Oman. One of those boats belonged to Khalifa-bin-Nasir-al-Suweydi, called As- samhah ; the other to Sheyban of the tribe of Al-Soodan. These boats on their arrival at Sila saw some boats lying there. In the boat of Sheyban there were 6Z 5 * 7 amongst the armed men some of the Maadid, a tribe to which Jasim belongs, who fired at the boats lying at Sila. Meantime one of the boats despatched by Jasim and belonging to Khalifa returned to Katr and informed regarding the presence of boats at Sila, and that they had seen tents pitched on shore and a number of Arabs. The armed men in this boat were of the tribe of Soodan, and as Jasim had no confidence in them, he put in it some more men of the Maadid and despatched it again to Sila. When it arrived there, they saw there a small boat engaged in pearlfishing, and in which there were only one man and two boys. The men of Jasim seized that man, and said they W’ere going to take him before Jasim. He refused to follow them, but was carried away by force. He observed that he thought the sea was secure against ag gression, and told them that the two boys would not be able to manage his boat, but he was not listended to. They asked him about the boats that were at Sila, and he told them that they were boats belonging to the people of Oman which were pearlfishing as usual, but that they had taken to flight owing to the firing of Bidaa boats, and that it is probable that some of the people in them might have received a bullet shot. The man’s name is Abdullah-bin-Suweyeh Mazroo’ai from Abu-Thabi. He had with him some pearls winch they took aw r ay from him, promising to return to him the same. They then took him before Jasim, who threatened him in such a w r ay that those present thought he would be killed. But the object of this thereat was simply to obtain from him information about Zaid. He said that Zaid had w ith him 2,000 troops, and was marching against Katr; but as for himself, that he was a poor diver. At the time of Ghanim’s departure from Bidaa, this man was there, and it was said that he w'as going to be sent back to his boat if it happened to be at Sila, or else that he w T ould be left in the island of Dalmah. Muhammad-bin-Muhanah-al-Naimi sailed from Bahrain with a cargo of dates for Abu-Thabi, and on his voyage passed by Al-Wakrah. Some people from Bahrain advised Jasim that this boat contained arms for Zaid, so Jasim stopped it, and it was only released through the intervention of the Naim-al- Jabir. It w r as found that the boat had only two guns, wdiich belonged to the boat itself. No. 71, dated the 11th May 1889. From—The Residency Agent at Bahrain, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. With reference to my letter No. 66, reporting the arrival of Shaikh Zaid bin-Khalifa near, Ojeyr, and of his having encamped at Karah, I have the honour to report the following account w'hich I have gathered regarding the fight. The section which is friendly to Jasira. The number of killed were two men of the Monasir* tribe against whom there was a blood-claim ; tw r o men of the Beni Hajir ; a son of Salim-bin-Shafi, one of the Shaikhs of the Beni Hajir, who w r as killed by mistake for Salim-bin- Shafi, is a friend of Zaid, and there is a compact between them ; tw’o men of the Al-Morrah tribe among those who were tending camels. The casualties on Zaid’s side were two killed, and one of the Shaikhs of the Monasirf w ound- ed on the palm of one of his hands. His name is Jereyio. f The section which is with Jasim. Regarding the number of cadaels carried away by Zaid’s troops, the account varies. Some say 800, and others more; and as no one has come this side from those who took part in the engagement, I have been unable to ascertain the exact amount of booty carried aw ay. The camels mostly belonged to the people of Katr, and had been entrusted to the Al-Morrah for the purpose being tended ; some to the Beni Hajir and some to the Monasir. Two mares belonging to one Seif- al-Hajiri, a friend of Jasim-bin-Thani, were also carried away; and two more whose feet were cut.It is said, that Zaid has started from Karah and is marching towards jvatr, hut I think he must have changed his mind and is not going to Katr. I he number of his troops is estimated at 1,200, and even less than that; and it is said that the camels belonging to his transport have been seized with a disease. It appears that when the news of Zaid having started from Karah reach ed Jasim, he marched out with £00 men mounted on horses and camels to trace out the movements of Za id’s army, and that he found their traces at Sila, 11 om v hence they had marched back to their country. Jasim writes to Mujbil to the effect that Zaid has retraced his stens having found out that he (Jasim) was well prepared for him, and that it is now us (Jasim s) intention to despatch against Zaid one expedition after another. From Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, do—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. cn ? ^ ie ^ lonour enclose translations of letters dated 23rd Mnv locf r Shaikh Jasim-bin-Muhammad Thani. It will be observed that lA ™ 1 /A fl0m sertmg Sila to be within the limits of El-Katr. 0 1 clMsts m as ' Dated 22nd Ramazan 13006 (3rd May 1889). From—J asim-bin-Thani, r ^° T h e Residency Agent at Bahrain. I am sending a letter to the address of ihe Resident, which after pernsa * shaikh Zaid-bin-Khalifa. forward to its destination. Probably von edfmm his ^fdon^ 111 ^ ^ ^ that the P eo P le ^ be de W- Dated 22nd Ramazan 1306 (23rd May 1889). From—J asim-bi.v-Thani, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ISOeldth May Sk anThavf per^sedltl ^ 8rd R ama Z ai known to me and to all that Sila is within the limfte of S CoLf 1 '' “ ' WeDt t0 DPaafPeeen t Remained without permanent inhabitants. became deserted.f Put the Bedouins of quent those ports, the Beni Haiir ]dr^ &lt; S F* n S the Katr territory fre- enemies, being included aRe Bedonfns^ fVe^^fl^^ 111 1 have under my jurisdiction and others are not and wh' 8114 t .‘° Se P 01 '* 8 ’ some aro enemy goes thither and joins them. ’ “ er ha PPens to be my without the cognizance of a theChfef ^^^“The bT P ° rt8 eit,ler with or the boat s crew, seize the boat and mil tn qoL c P | ;^ oulns then overpower therefore necessary for you and Shaikl/Ysnn t-r. ' ' f 1 P lra t lc al designs). It is call at those ports. Should any boa find t nl Wam people not to on the voyage, it should call either at Bidaa or DZ/n ta ^. water or provisions Bedouins infesting the Katr Coast - tliov V ee ?‘ lllerG a re numerous to my orders : and I cannot therefore be respomiblo forYbdr a^’ts. 1104 amenableNo. 131, dated Busliire, the 19th June 1889. From Colonel E. C. Ross, c.s.i., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Her Majesty's Consul-General for Ears, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have tlie honour to enclose translation of a report received from the No 52 , dated 1 st June 1889 . Residency Agent at Shargah, containing an account of the.proceedings of the com bined forces of Ahu-Thahi and Dehay, during the recent expedition towards El-Katr. No. 52, dated IshJune 1889. From—The Residency Agent at Shargah, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. .1 have the honour to report that on the 15th May Shaikh Zaid-bin- Khalifa arrived at Ahu-Thahi. On the 17th May, Makthum-hin- Hasher arrived at Debay. I went to Dehay for the purpose of delivering the presents to the Chief of that place and to Makthum-bin-Hasher. Makthum-hin- Hasher gave me the following account of Shaikh Zaid’s expedition. When the expedition arrived at Sabakhah on the frontiers of Katr, they experienced great scarcity of water, which had to be obtained by digging new wells. At Sabakhah Shaikh Zaid held a council of war with the^Cluefs of the-tribes that were with him, at which it was decided that the present was not an opportune moment for a March on Katr, as Jasim was entrenched at El-Bidaa, and as there was no fodder for the animals in the suburbs of Katr. It was deemed sufficient for the present to punish the tribes (who had assisted Jasim) by plundering them. So the expedition started and went to a place called Karah, in the neighbourhood of Hasa, and plundered everything they found there, irrespective of the fact whether it belonged to foe or friend. The expedition then marched to Ojeyr, where the Bedouins of Karah had taken shelter in the fort (at Ojeyr). But Shaikh Zaid prevented his men from investing the fort, as his object was not murder but plunder. The booty taken from the Bedouins at Karah was 2,000 camels, besides much household goods and many arms. After the attack was over, those of the Bedouins who had treaty relations with Shaikh Zaid and whose property was plundered in the affair at Karah, came to Shaikh Zaid, and asked him to restore to them their camels, which he willingly did. So after returning the camels of the friendly tribes, the net booty carried away was 600 camels and 8 horses. The number of killed in the engagement at Karah was 18 men of the Monasir and Beni Ilajir tribes who are under Jasim. A son of Bin-Shafi, Chief of Beni Ilajir, was also killed, but this happened by mistake, as that Chief is the friend of Shaikh Zaid. The friendly Bedouins of Karah have rehewed their compact with Shaikh Zaid. From Karah, Shaikh Zaid (having changed his mind) wanted to march on Katr, but found that the camels were all jaded, and a disease broke out amongst them. The expedition lost only two men in the engagement at Karah. ? j Extract from the Diary of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for the week ending the 21st June 1889. ** ****** 1. It is said that a Turkish man-of-war is expected here shortly from Busrah with troops for the relief of the garrisons of Katr and Katif. I saw a letter from Ibrahim Agha Nasrani, the Turkish Commissariat Contractor at Busrah, written to his Agent at Bidaa, informing the latter that a regiment will go to Bidaa, and asking him to get ready the necessary provisions for them. I {2. Persons who have arrived here from Bidaa report, as authentic news, that Jasim-bin-Thani has despatched a marauding expedition to Oman, com posed of over 200 men. The main body of the expedition is said to consist of men of the tribes who were recently plundered of their camels by Shaikh Zaid-bin-Khalifa. It is stated that the expedition was organised by Jasim owing to the encouragement given him by those tribes, who are longing for revenge. * * * * * * * * * No. 12S2-E., dated Simla, the 5th July 1889. From— H. S. Barnes, Officiating Under-Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your communications* cited Letter No. 97 , dated the ss.tii April 1889. ?“ tlle margin regarding the hostilities Telegram, dated the 13 th May 1889. between Shaikh J asim-bin-Muhammad Letter No. ii3, dated the i6th May „. Thani of ; Itl-Bidaa and Shaikh Zaid-bin- ns’, 23rd ” Khalifa, the Abu-Thabi Chief. ,, 122, ,. 3rd June „ ,, 131, ,, 19th „ ,, 2. The Government of India consider that they would he justified in punish ing Shaikh Jasim for despatching munitions of war by sea in furtherance of his hostile designs against the Chief of Abu-Thabi. Having regard, however, to the vie ws expressed in paragraph 4 of your letter No. 117, dated the 16th May 1889, I ain to request that Shaikh Jasim may he informed of the displeasure of the Government of India, and warned that a repetition of such acts as he has lately been guilty of will entail serious consequences'. List of Enclosures in Despatch No. 112 {External), dated the 2nd August 1389, from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, to Iler Majes ty's Secretary of State for India. Serial No. No. and date of paper. From whom, or to whom. Subject. 1 Extract from the Persian Gulf Residency diary for the week ending the 7th April 1889. From the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Communicates intelligence in regard to the despatch by Shaikh Jasim-hin-Mu- hammad Thani of boats to Sila with armed men, against the forces of Shaikh Zaid-bin-Khalifa of Abu-Thabi. 2 No. 97, dated the 26th April 1889. Ditto ditto. Forwards translation of a letter from the Residency Agent at Bahrain, regard ing the affairs on the Arab Coast. 8 Telegram dated the 13th May 1889. Ditto ditto. Communicates report of se rious fighting between the forces of Abu-Tliabi and El-Katr. i 10List of Enclosures —contd. S erial No. No. and date of paper. From whom, or to whom. Subject. 4 No. 113, dated the IGth May 1889. Ditto ditto. With reference to the above telegram, encloses transla tion of a report relative to the lighting referred to. 5 No. 117, dated the 16th May 1889. Ditto ditto. Forwards translations of cor respondence regarding the despatch by Shaikh Jasim of munitions of war by sea. Communicates views in the matter, and submits suggestions. 6 No. 118, dated the 23rd May 1889. Ditto ditto. Forwards translations of re ports relative to the affairs of El-Katr and the hostil ities between Abu-Thabi and that district. 7 No. 122, dated the 3rd June 1889. Ditto ditto. Submits translations of let ters from Shaikh Jasim as serting that Sila is within the limits of El-Katr. 8 No. 131, dated the 19th June 1889. Ditto ditto. Encloses translation of a re port containing an ac count of the proceedings of the combined forces of Abu-Thabi and Debaye during the recent expe dition towards El-Katr. 9 Extract from the Persian Gulf Residency diary for the week ending the 21st June 1889. From the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Communicates intelligence regarding the affairs of El-Katif and El-Katr, and the despatch by Shaikh Jasim of a marauding expedition to Oman. 10 No. 1282-E., dated the 5th July 1889. To the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Acknowledges receipt of his letters and telegram, and requests that Shaikh Jasim may be informed of the displeasure of Government at his proceedings in des patching munitions of war against the Chief of Abu- Thabi, and that he may be warned that a repeti tion of such acts will entail serious consequences. (Sd.) H. S. BAENES, Offg, Under-Secy, to the Govt, of India. 11No. 112 (External), dated Simla, the 2nd August 1S89. * From—The Government of India, To—The Secretary of State for India. In continuation of our^despatcli No. 74 dated the 24th May 1889, we have the honour to forward, for Your Lordship’s information, copies of the papers noted in the accompanying list, regarding the affairs on the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf. 2. We have caused Shaikh Jasim-hin-Muhammad Thani of El-Bidaa to be informed that the Government of India regard with displeasure his pro ceedings in sending munitions of war by sea for operations against the Chief of Abu-Thabi; and we have directed the Political Resident to warn him that a repetition of such acts will entail serious consequences.SaCRiTARY'S ho: I2B LONDON t 24 TH MAY 1889. TK - SiCRSTARY TO TH 2 GOVSRffMBNT OF INDIA, fors 1 off department, 1 forward herewith, for the information of DATED 15?) HIS EXCELLENCY THE VICEROY, COPY OF A LETTER FROM ^HE may 1889 WITH EN- &gt;ORSIGN OFFICE RELATIVE TO THE THREATENED ATTACK ON CLOSURES. \ OMAN FROM NE.JD. I HAVE &amp;C, SIV E. R. C. BRADFORD, SECRETARY,POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPARTMENT. FOREIGN OFFICE, MAY 15 TH 1889. THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE, WITH REFERENCE TO YOUR LETTER OF THE 1ST' OF DARCH LAST, I AM DIRECTED BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS TO TRANSMIT TO YOU, TO BE LAID BEFORE THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA, COPY OF ADESPATCH AS MARKED IN THE MARGIN, RELATING TO A THREATENED ATTACK ON OMAN BY MOHAMED I BN RASHID SD P.W.CURRIS. NO! 172, COMK IDENT IAb. CONSTANTINOPDE MAY, 9TH 18B9 • THE MARQUIS OF SALISBURY &amp;C &amp;C &amp;C, MY LORD, I HAVE THE HONOR TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE RECEIPT OF YOUR LORDSHIP'S DESPATCH, NO I 72, OF MARCH 5TH, FORWARDING A COPY OF A TELEGRAM FROM THE VICEROY. OF INDIA TO HSR MAJESTY'S SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA REFERRING TO THE WISH OF MOHAMED I BN RASHID TO OBTAIN THE PORTS'S CONSENT TO HIS CONTEMPLATED INVASION OF OMAN . I HAVE.CAUSED ENQUIRIES TO BE MADS AND GATHER THA ABOUT A YEAR AGO H.I.M.THE SULTAN SENT AHMED ESSAAD ON A MISSION WITH PRESENTS TO I BN RASHID AND THAT THE LATTER SENT A RETURN MISSION WITH PRESENTS, V/HICH HAS BEEN LODGED IN AHMED ESSAAD*S HOUSE AT STAMBOUL, AND WHOSE MEMBERS HAVE BEEN DETAINED HERE FOR SOME WEEKS, IF NOT MONTHS. IBN RASHID WHO IS THE DS FACTO RULER OF H SJ D, WISHES, I AM TOLD, THE SULTAN TO PLACE THE PROVINCE OF SL-HASA UNDERI UHDSR KIS JL‘ RISDICTIOM y WftaRSAS THS SULTAN IS BSNT ON turning nsjd into an OTTOMAN VASSAL province. I AM ASSURED THAT THS ABOVE INFORMATION IS CORRECT, BUT I AM NOT ABLE TO VOUCH FOR ITS ACCURACY. NO ANSWER HAS BEEN RECEIVED BY HER MAJESTY*S EMBASSY TO THS NOTE ADDRESSED TO THE S. PORTE ON THE 1ST OF OCTOBER LAST, BUT AS YOUR LORDSHIP WAS GOOD -iNOUGH TO GIVE ME FULL FREEDOM AS TO ANY ACTION I MIGHT CONSIDER IT ADVISABLE TO TARE, I INSTRUCTED SIR A. SANDI SON TO SEE THE GRAND VIZIER AND STATE THAT REPORT HAD REACHED HER MAJESTY*S EMBASSY OF COMMUNICATIONS BETWEEN THE PALACE AND THE TRIBES OF NEJD AND OMAN WHICH MIGHT POSSIBLY RESULT IN HOSTILITIES THERE, THAT HER MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT COULD NOT VIEW WITH INDIFFER- iNCa ANY RESULT OF THIS NATURE AND TO POINT OUT TO H.H. THAT ANY ENCOURAGEMENT OR SUPPORT GIVEN FROM CONSTAN TINOPLE MIGHT LEAD TO SERIOUS DIFFICULTIES. THS ENCLOSED COPY OF A MEMORANDUM BY SIR A.SANDISON CONTAINS THE ASSURANCES OF THE GRAND VIZIER THAT THE PEACE WOULD NOT BE DISTURBED IN THE OMAN, AND AS YOUR LORDSHIP WILL PERCEIVE H.H.DENIES THE PRESENCE HERS OF IBM RASHID'S EMISSARIES, STATING THAT THEY ARE SHEIKHS OF THE SHAMAR ARAB TRIBES. SD W.A.WHITE. MAY 9TH 1889. SIR A SANDI SON TO THE AMBASSADOR. I DID NOT Fail TO COMMUNICATE TO THS GRAND VIZIERYOUR SXCfcCLbSNCY*S INSTRUCTIONS OF THfi 30TH ULTIMO, H.H STATaD IN RaPL»Y THAT Hl£ WAS NOT AWARS OF ANY COMMUNICA TIONS BSTWSaN THa PAI^ACa AMD THE TRIBES IN QUESTION, BUT THAT UNDER AL,L, CIRCUMSTANCES THERE WAS NO FEAR OR DANGER OF THE PEACE B EI MG DISTURBED IN /THE )oMAN. ON THE OCCAS ION OF MY SECOND VISIT AND IN REPLY TO MY OBSERVATION THAT CERTAIN SHEIKHS FROM NEJD ERE ACTUALLY AT CONSTANTINOPLE, H.H.STATED THAT THERE WAS NOTHING NEW IN CONNECTION WITH THEIR VISIT TO CONSTAN TINOPLE, INASMUCH AS THE IDENTICAL SHEIKHS ARAB TRIBES AND NOT TO THOSE OF NEJD HAD BEEN HERE ABOUT 2 OR 3 YEARS AGO. NO; 1224 s. A COPY OF THE FOREGOING RES ID El! T IN THE PERSIAN GULF FOREIGN DEPARTMENT SIMLA, THE 2 bTH JUNE I8b9 IS FORWARDED TO THE POLI FOR INFORMATION. BY ORDER, SD H. .BARNS offg: under secretary to THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. I CAL NO S'cP rt,- OF I889. ; ff ' •si COPY FORWARDED TO THE POLITICAL AGENT &amp; CONSUL, MUSKAT FOR IN FO RMA TION. // ^BUSHIRE* 1 ^jTuly ibb9.)</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/19</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/19</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Political</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1887/1889</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-11-16T22:51:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (75 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 77; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains reports on the contemplated invasion of Oman by the Ibn Rashid clan of Jabal Shammar by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. It also contains discussions on Turkish influence and jurisdiction on the Arab Coast between the Government of India and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Finally, the file also contains the September 1888-June 1889 Administration and trade returns.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Political affairs</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Rashīd (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>