<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fa_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:53:55.365Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No • /£-' -V4. Tbe Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to : — \ Mg r ’a The SecT^etary to the Hon*ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE, and has the honour to send him a copy of the nndermentioned document (s) \ The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dited 5th. February 1938. ITelegram From G.T.C. r / / Polit ioai^e^Lcfent, Bushire, 1° Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 00033 Dated and received the 21at February 1938. f Please telegraph immediately what modifications are necessary in your final review figures on account of pay including Joining time pay and travelling allowance of Lieutenant Bird. ***** Reply Telegram— g.t.C. From — Political Agent, Bahrain To — Political Resident Bushire No — 35 Bated -- 22nd February 1938. Importan t v our telegram ? T o. CC033 Additional excesses are pay of Officers Rupees 113 and Travelling all .vance 910Telegram — G.T.C From — Political Agent Bahrain To — Political Resident Bushire No — 42 Dated — 9th March 1938 v/-/ Your memorandum No. 2379 of 4th December* Please telegraph whether additional funds have been sanctioned* - Political-To 1938. P / No. i&amp;a.nzLlot 1938 £&gt;0/3 $ . Britiala Residency Consulate-General, nfA* Busnire, tne Marcn, 1938. n V / Tiie Political Anent, BAiirain. Tiie Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Vice consul. Bunder Abbas. His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz. His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz. //i Memorandum . Reference this Residency’s memorandum Ho. 2379 dated the 4th December, 1937. 2. The following* alterations in your Budget grants for 1937-38, have since been sanctioned by the Government of India. By Order, Secretary to the Political Resident in tiie Persian Gulf. * As in StatementTelegram -- G.T.C a . 0 V' Prom — Britconsul, Bushire To — Political Agent, Bahrain No — 0072 Mut. csinceo r Dated &amp; received 27th March 1938. t L Residency telegram 53 of 10th March. Balance of additional funds ' sanctioned( ; To Bahrain only. The Political Agent, Muecat, Tne Political Agent, Baiirain.v/ Hiy Majesty's Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, 3andar Abbas. Hie '’ajesty's Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, HemoranUunu 1 Helerence this Residency's memorandum Ho. 440/60/23, dated the 3rd March, 1938. 2 * TJa ® item (sj sho^n as subject to tne sanction has ol the Government of India (have) since been sanctioned.GOVERSalENT OP INDIA, Depar iment. EXPRESS LETTER / ' [N, B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic 1 expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on f • receipt, with the same expedit i&lt;m as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formaUlies it is worded and signed as if it had been f / so despatched.] f P*OM Political, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire. 692/4/4 Dated 15th May 199 ? i Fo. 667 Reference your inemoranduin Fo. 6 d 7/60/23 dated the 9th April, 1938. 2. Against a sum of Rs. 16,500/- asked for in this office memorandum No. 2277-4/4 dated the 3rd November, 1937 (vide also your memorandum No. 2379 dated the 4th December, 1937) under Postage and Telegram Charges the following sums were sanctioned:- (a) As per your ^memorandum No. 439 dated 3-3-1938. Rs. -f 900 (b) As per your memorandum No. 440 dated 3-3-1938. Rs. - 300 # Rs. 600 The total expenditure for the year 1937-38 under this Sub-head is ns. 24,671/1/- whereas the aggregate final appropriation under this Sub-head/ S.6. MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-l 723)—4-2-36—200,000*.Sub-head is only h$. 9,100 (Rs. 8,500 + Hi* 900 - Bs. 300which shows an excess expenditure of fis. 15,571/1/- still to be provided for. 3. vVould you kindly let me know how this excess expenditure is to be adjusted? tj For Political Agent,Bahrain.\J, \ *w GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER ft'—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, stnt by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sace lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Britconsul, Bushiie. To political, /V No* ‘tok /6 0 / 2 3 Gated 20 th May 19b 8, A Reference your Hxpreee Letter Jtfo.692/4/4, dated the 15th May, 19 38• 2. A total additional provision of Es. 16,200/- (made up as follows) has been made to cover the excess expenditure under 'Bahiain- C-4-Contin^encies-3ervice postage and Telegram charges'* in 1937-33 vide . Ou If vvt Jl this Residency’s memorandum lTo*2379, dated the 4th December, 1937, read J n im No . &lt;00072, with this Residency’s telegram dated the 26th March, 1938. v V* 3. (a) Regrant of surrendered allotment under '•Cost of medical equipment and drugs'*. Es*800/- ,/ (b) Regrant of surrenered allotment under ’•Contingencies*’• * “ lOO/-^ (c) Reappropriated vide this office memo randum No. 440, dated the 3rd March, 1938. (d) provided by Government of India, vide telegram cited above. . To tal . -tl6 900/- Ss. + 900/- - 300/- -&gt;-15600/- y being forwarded to you separately S. 6. tfFP—1206 S&amp;P—&lt;M-1723}—4-2-36—200,000GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER IN. IS %—This is an OR1G1S A L M ESS AG 7?, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of ike wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with ike same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if zt had been so despatched,] From - Political Agent, Bahrain. - Political Resident, Bushire• No. 774/4/4. Dated the 28th May 103 8. Final appropriation for 1937-38 . Reference your memorandum No. 908/60/23 dated the 20th May 1938. 2 . I enclose a statement showing the differences between the figures j given by you in the enclosure to the memorandum cited above and those of this office, which have been compiled on the authority quoted agains'- each item. The correspondence etcetera quoted in the remarks column of the statement enclosed with your memorandum under reference does not appear to have been received in this office. If copies have been forwarded to me, would you please quote the numbers and dates under which they were sent. for Political Agent, Bahrain. s. 6. MFP - ^01 S&amp;P —(M- *20)—23-7-36—300,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. [N. B, —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with thx same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sure time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] To Political, Bahrain, So /'v .Vo, loll /60/23 ‘‘ Bated the 10th June 1S‘J 8 Pinal appropriations foi 1^37-58 , Reference your Express Letter ITo. 7 74/4/4, dated the 28tln May, U38. 9 The figures shewn in the statement accompanying this Residency’s memorandum No. 908/60/23, dated the 20th May, 1938, are correct• The discrepancies are explained as follows:- 1. The amounts of Es. 400/- and 2s. 1600/-, shown as minus items in column 3 of your statement, were recanted oy the Govern ment of India and are included in the plus item of Es. 5182/- shown hy you against rt Travelling Allowance”. 2. A further sum of Es. 718/- provided under ''Travelling Allowani vide this Residency’s telegram No. 72, dated the 26th March, \ 1938 has not been shown in your statement. 3. The amount* of Es. 300/- and Es. 100/- shown as minus items in s . e . column 3 of your statement were regranted oy the Government M FP —785S&amp;P— (M-1014)—18-S-33—2,1)0.000. “ ~ “ vXof India and are included in the plus item of Es. 900/- shown by you against 'Service postage k Telegram charges'. 4 The referencesfcited in the 'Remarks' column of the statement accompanying this office memorandum No. 908/60/23, dated the 20th May, 1938, were included only for the information of the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, to whom a consoli dated final appropriation statement for all offices in the Persian Gulf Residency is forwarded. 'Qy n vrl or Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf.r-\ No. lol b -60/42. C Dated the /3 r June, 1938 To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Me morandumi / r r Reference correspondence ending vath your letter No.2485, dated the 1st December, 1937. 2. Please furnish full details and explanation of the expenditure under ycur Launch Grant. 3. The Bushire Launch Grant of Rs.6,000/- is suffi cient to cover the running expenses of the launch (inclu ding repairs) and the pay of the crew which consists of a first class Driver, a ’’Nakhuda' and 3 ’Khalasis’ . The Government of India will probably require explanation for the comparatively heavy expenditure on the Launch at Ba hra in. By order in the Persian Gulf.-P No. \0bk- X, $ l The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to political ^ent, kuaoat. Th3 Political Bahrain. 1/ The political Aa unt &gt; Kuwait. Hi 3 Majaat/'s Consul, Bunder At)baa. Hi3 Hajasty’o Consul, ^erraan. Hiu Majesty’s Vice-Coneui, Khorrauisnanx . and is directed to transmit to him ajjopj^oj; the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated..th&lt;j /b.‘'.y4ine,..1938. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. v One printed copy of the reiev ant Budget grants and appropriations for 1933-39. |yi iSl ' 0 JEXTERNAL AFFAIRS. y9 Actuals, 1936-37. Rs. Budget Estimate, 1937-38. Rs. Revised Estimate, 1937 38. Rs. Budget Estimate, ms-29. Rs. INDIA— contd. B.—CHARGES ON ACCOUNT OF DIP LOMATIC AND CONSULAR SERVICES IN IRAN— contd. Bushire— contd. B. 3.—ALLOWANCES, HONO RARIA, ETC. : Cost of passages granted under the Superior Civil Services Rules, 1924 Sumptuary allowance Travelling allowance . House-rent and other allowances . • • Allowance to Residency Agent Travelling allowance of Political Department, Probationer . Customs compensatory allowance , Total —CONTINGENCIES : Maintenance of launch, etc. Purchase and maintenance of motor cars, boats, etc. Purchase and maintenance of wireless set Service postage and tele gram charges Contract grant for medical expenditure Charges for suppression of slave trade Purchase of portrait of H. M. the King George VI ... • Office allowance Office allowance to Vice- Consul Central contract grant Escort contingencies 3,r,oo 3,000 25,800 6,900 500 12,300 55,907 52,000 6,000 1,500 1,200 70,000 4,000 100 38,600 3,600 17,400 1,000 1,40,663 1,43,400 3,998 4,000 3,500 3,000 25,800 6,900 500 300- 10,000 57,000 50,000 • 6,000 1,000 75,000 4.000 100 1.000 37,700 3,600 17,400 1,000 1,57,200 1,46,800 4,000 4,000 Total B. 6.—SECRET EXPENDI TURE : Secret service money O 24 EXTERNAL AFFAIRS. 107 Actuals, Budget Estimate, Revised Estimate, Budget Estimate, 1930-37. 1937-38. 1937-38. 1938-39. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. INDIA— contd. C.—OTHER DIPLOMATIC AND AD- MINISTRATIVE CHARGES— contd. Kabul Legation— concld . C. 3.—ALLOWANCES, HONO RARIA, ETC.: Cost of passages granted under the Superior Civil Services Rules, 1924 Sumptuary allowance Travelling allowance House-rent and other allowances . Sumptuary allowance House-rent and other al lowances . . Total C. 4.—CONTINGENCIES : Purchase and repair of tents .... Purchase and upkeep of motor lorries and cars . Legation and camp furni ture .... Saddlery and line gear Upkeep of horses Library .... Purchase of medicines and apparatus Liveries and warm clothing Rents, rates and taxes Service postage and tele gram charges Hot and cold weather charges Menial charges Office furniture Office expenses and miscel laneous Replacement of motor lorries Supply of three key-boxes Contingencies of Indian Trade Agent Total C . 6.—GRANTS-IN-AID, CON TRIBUTIONS, ETC. : Contributions for passages of officers transferred to or from other Govern ments, Departments, etc. . . . . 1,800 12,600 4,200 12*600 4,200 12,400 7,000 1,800 3,700 25,100 31,000 28,600 29,300 500 300 41,500 32,500 2,700 200 2,500 500 2,200 200 2,500 500 3.500 2.500 400 3.500 2.500 300 22,000 22,000 14.000 16.000 1,200 13.000 16.000 1,000 11,900 11,300 18,000 700 • • 7,900 1,16,556 1,19,400 1,19,400 1,34,400 2,716 1,200 2,200 2,100 3,18,177 3,38,000 Total for Kabul Legation 3,29,400 3,60,200J Si- demands FOR GRANTS, 1938-39 : Actuals, 1936-37. Budget Estimate, 1937-38. Revised Estimate, 1937-38. Budget Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. MADRAS— concld. C.-OTHER DIPLOMATIC AND administrative CHARGES— contd. His Majesty’s Consul General at Pondicherry— concld. British Consular Office at Karikal— con Id C. 4.—CONTINGENCIES : Rent .... 600 Other Contingencies . 200 Rent .... Other contingencies . . 600 200 Total 800 1,100 800 Total for Karikal Office •• 2,400 1,100 2,400 Total, His Majesty’s Consul General .... 27,074 26,800 31,500 30,700 C. 7.—ESTABLISHMENT CHARGES PAID TO OTHER GOVERNMENTS DEPARTMENTS, ETC. : Establishment charges payable to the Madras Government for work connected with External Affairs Amount paid to Madras Government on account of passport work . 4,700 4,700 28,800 Total 4,700 4,700 4,700 33,500 Total for Other Diplomatic and Ad ministrative Charges 31,774 31,500 36,200 64,200 H.—REFUGEES AND STATE PRISONERS : H. 3.—KABUL REFUGEES AND STATE PRISON ERS : Allowances to Kabul Re fugees and State Pri soners .... 21,867 23,800 23,800 24,000 H. 4.—OTHER REFUGEES AND STATE PRI SONERS : . . . 320 500 600 500 Total for Refugees and State Prisoners 22,187 24,300 24,400 24,500 I.— MISCELLANEOUS : I. 8.—OTHER EXPENSES : Profession tax paid to the cor poration of Madias in respect of the American Consular Officers in Madras 75 200 400 300 Total for Madras 64,036 56,000 61,000 89,000EXTERNAL AFFAIRS. 129 Budget Revised Budget Actuals, Estimate, Estimate, Estimate 1936-.i7. 1937-38. 1937-38. 1938-39. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. PUNJAB—cowW. C.—OTHER DIPLOMATIC AND ADMINISTRATIVE CHARGES — contd. Gilgit Agency— concld. C. 4.—CONTINGENCIES : Grants for maintenance of furniture Purchase of tents Durbar presents Military Stores for Gilgit Corps of Service Kit money and footwear for Gilgit Corps of Scouts Ration and clothing for prisoners Medicines and instruments for Veterinary Hospital . Medicines and drugs for Scouts Ration to Boarders . Medicines and instruments for the Medical Department Scholarships . Prizes and free books Service postage and tele- / gram charges 9,900 * 9,900 Tour expenses Office expenses and mis- 1,100 1,900 cellaneous . 1,700 1,900 Other contingencies Installation of an X-Ray 51,800 53,100 apparatus Construction of telephone 10,700 1,000 lines and maintenance of telegraph line 3,900 3,900 Petty construction and re- pairs 1,000 1,000 Hunza-Mesgar telegraph line 12,200 12,200 Liveries to peons Expenditure in connection 200 with the Farm at Jaglote 500 Total 1,30,154 1 58,900 1,58,400 1,41,500 C. 5.—SECRET EXPENDITURE : ^ Secret service money 1,820 1.600 2,900 2,000 C. 6.— GRANTS-IN-AID, CON- TRIBUTIONS, ETC : 12,215 9,000 19,600 6,500 C. 8.— DEDUCT —ESTABLISH MENT AND OTHER CHARGES RECOVERED FROM OTHER GOVERN MENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC : Block recovery from the Crown Department on account of conduct of re lations of the Crown with Gilgit .... .. —2,00,000 — 2,00,000 —2,00,000 Totai- fob Gilgit Agency . 6,58,303 4,05,200 4,45,400 3,89,800 600 600 200 200 5,600 5,600 21,000 15,000 21,900 17,000 3,700 4,300 400 400 900 900 1,600 1,600 7,500 7,500 2,700 2,700Mo. Political Agency, Bahrain, the f!6th June 1953• To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B G 6 H I K £• Memorandum * V 'V' - Reference your memorandum No* 1076 dated the 13th June 1933 regarding expenditure under the Haunch Grant* 2* Hxpenaiture under this head is divided under three sub-heads: (i) hbTiiB^ldnMHNl consisting of Haunch Engineer •• Pay •• Assistaxit Engineer .. *• Nahauda *. n . * 2 Kiialasies @ Rs*40/- each ^ .* 2 iCh alas leg &amp; Rs# da/- each •• Total or Rs* 150 per mensem Rs* 65 per mensem Rs. 50 p^r mensem Rs. 80 per mensem Rs. 60 per mensem Rs. 405 per mensem Rs • 1860/- per annu In the past daily allowance for journeys on tour has been paid to the launch crew and debited to this sub-head making an average expenditure per annum of Rs. 5000/- (ii) PihaOH Oil : Average annual expenditure under this sub-head has been Rs* 1000/-. (lii) hiQCLi^^AnL^’sb* Average annual expenditure under tills s^b-head has been Rs* 3000/- and includes provision for metal polish, waste cotton, re-charging of batteries, ropes, khalasies 1 liveries and washing charges, cost of flags, spare parts, paint and petty repairs. I have myself incurred fairly con siderable expenditure under this head, since I found on myarrival that the launch was structurally inadequate and did not possess a mast or sails to be used in the event of a break down of the engine, ^iterations have been completed and expenditure under this head should decline as from next year, though some further expenditure is essential this year in ordei to provide lighting. 5. As suggested above tne expenditure under the ’ T Misceila- neous* head should decrease, though ultimately there muse be very heavy expenui-ure in order to mee the cost of a new en gine. The launch is unfortunately under-powered and it would be unreasonable optimism to expect the present engine to last any considcrabl length of time. On the other hand I antici pate that expenditure under t^e second sub-head, i.e. 'Petrol and Oil' will increase. Vith developments in Qatar journeys there by launch v.iii oecome more and more frequent, and X anticipate also t^at it rnty be necessary to use the launch on the Truciai Coast before long. 4. I reauiiy scknovledge that I have no experience of hushire but ay information is that tne Busnire launch is sel dom U3_a except lor taking the political Resident - or occa sionally some other officer - to and from the mail boats. Conditions in Bahrain are entirely different. Thow.gh tbs launch is frequently used for purposes similar to those in Bushire, sea-going voyages are, as X have indicated, already quite comwon ana must become more and more frequent in future# For this reason I cannot recommend any reduction in the annual grant. It would be poor economy to reduce the crew, thereby • risking loss of the launch (ana possibly of the Political Agent also)j and in view of local conditions I regard it as essential to retain an assistant for the engineer in order to take his place when he himself is out of action. I haveon more than one occasion found the necessity for a second engineer from experience. &amp;• I regret I am unable to suggest any economy here. I am impressed by the fact that developments in Qatar will in ail probability involve monthly journeys by launch in the ap proximate future end that it is most important to ensure that the Political Agent is not immobilised by over-economy in his launen grant. Political Agent, Bahrain.nii No. 1022-4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 24th July 1938 To The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Reference your endorsement No. 750-60/23 dated the 4th April 1936. 2. I enclose a statement showing grants, expenditure, etcetera for the year 1937-38. Political Agent, Bahrain.No* Ilj&amp; -4/4* Political Agency v Bahrain, August 18, 1938* Prom, The Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain* To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire• Sir, I have the,honour to forward, in duplicate, the Budget Estimates of this Agency for the year 1939-40 I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ ■ Offg* Political Agent, Bahrain*Ho. Britisn Consulate-Creneral, Busnire, tJie|L| September, 1938, To The political The Political His Majesty's His Majesty's His Majesty's His Majesty's His Majesty's A^ent, Baiirain. ^ ent, Kuwait, Consul, Bunder Abbas* Consul, Kerman. Consul, Shiraz. Consul, Alnsaz. Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, t l Memorandum. Reference para 1(2} of the memorandum of financial instructions accompanying this Residency's - //&gt;■£ memorandum Ho. 750/60/23, dated the 4th April, 1936. 2/ In addition to figures of actual expenditure incurred during the first six months of the current year please telegraph by 3rd October figures of estimated expenditure under the various sub-heads during the re maining six months of the current year. By Order, e Political Resident Persian Gulf.: -VT. Telegram From To No. En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Secretary to the Political Resident, 183. Bushire• Dated the 1st October 1938. Your memoradnum No. 1655 dated the 14th September 1938. I Actual expenditure up to 30th September \ Pay of Officers /y Pay of establishment Travelling allowance \\ House rent and other / allowances j Sumptuary allowance Cost of passages ^ Launch grant C.C. Grant &gt; Rent of Building OPostage &amp; Telegram charges. ^ Office Allowance Rs. 24 , 529-8 Rs. 13, 932-10 Rs. 5,559 - 0 Rs Rs Rs. Rs. Rs Rs RS' 2,258- 5 600- 0 NIL 4,608- 5 628-12 NIL 3,778- 3 6,702- 0 300- 0 .0, Secret Service 3. Estimated expenditure for the remaining 6 months under the above-mentioned heads respectively:- Rs. 24,680 11,948 7.000 2,390 600 NIL 5.000 670 1,620 5,000 9,400 2,700 V V Q LC( v V 0 4. I am not in a position to give Sharjah figures as I have not handled Sharjah accounts in a cold weather. Posting E Statement for September this mail. No. if W' -4/4. Copy by post to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, in confirmation.mV 1/ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, 7 ■. DePAR !'MEXt|[ 37 2-i?/. I ;u. wj&lt;* j EXPRESS LET! [N. R ,—This is an ORIGINAL MJZSSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but i?ite?ided to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] 'V From Political Resident, Bushire. (A lt (t6. &gt;h Political Agent, Muscat Political Agent, Bahrain To - Q Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. A^rHl -60/21. Rated Oc to be r, 193 8, IMPORTANT &amp; IMMEDIATE X Retrenchment in the Budget for 1938-39. / A copy of Express Letter No.D. 1919-A/38, dated the 17th September, 193 8, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department is forwarded for your information and guidance. 2. It will be observed that the Government of India have Reduced the allotments under “Travelling Allowance“ and “Contin- gencies” by 10 per cent and have emphasised that in no circum stances will the amounts so reduced be re-allotted. You will therefore be held responsible for ensuring that excesses over the reduced allotments under your control do not occur. /3. S. 6. MFP—785S&amp;P—(M-l§14)—18-S-38—2,®.\000,/ &amp;• a report oho old be tent iamedlotely to thlo Re&amp;ldtncy regarding the total a mount a under the above htede \fthioh have been reduced under the accompanying order of the Government of India* The amount* reduced under each detailed head of the Sub-head, 'Contingenci ee' should also be reported. RifiSIDSKT The iaauc of the above hae been authorisedCopy of iixprtso letter Io*D. 1919-A./3C, doted the 17th September, 1938, from the Government of Indio in the i£*ternol Affairs Department. Retrenchment in the budget for 193 6-39. In vie* of the present financial situation and the con sequent need for econos^y in expenditure, the Government oi India have decided tc take the foilo*ln&amp; measuiest- (1) 10 per cent oi all allotments in the budget for 1936-39 under 'Travelling Allo**nce* and 'Contingencies' is herety resuioed and in no circumstances «i 11 the amount so resumed be re-allotted. A report should be sent immediately regarding the amounts under these heads ahich have been resumed under this order and for this purpose any amounts ahich have already been surrendered under these heads may be excluded. (ii) yrom the date of receipt of this letter and until further orders, no appointments or re-appointments of outsiders to any vacancy in a temporary or permanent post and no officiating promotions in vacancies of less than three months' duration involving the grant of additional emoluments shall be made. The Auditor General hrt been requested to examine in audit the observance of this order. Any savings that may accrue should be surrendered as soon as they are realised. (iii) Until the receipt ol further orders, no Government servant shall place any order for stores, supplies, etc. or onter into any contract or any such commitment involving expenditure eithout the specific orders of the Government of India even if provision for such items tas been ms.de in the budget. Clvj. Until further orders no commitment shall be entered into involving expenditure on any major or minor aork which is not at present in progress. In addition, expenditure onM - 2 - maintenance and repairs shall be so curtailed as to render possible s reduction ©f 25 per cent, in the budget provision; the consequent savfcgs should be surrendered as early as pos sible. 2. I'mrther orders sill issue in due course in regard to heads not apcclfled in this letter. controlling officers sill be held responsible for ensuring that excesses over the reduced allotments do not occur and the Government of India desire to emphasiat the need for keeping a vary careful wateh over expenditure against the modified allotments under your kind control.A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to:- The Political The Political The Political His Majesty’s His Majesty’s His Majesty’s Agent, Muscat, Agent, Bahrain, Agent, Kuwait, Consul, Bunder Abbas, Consul, Kerman, Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, for information. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Government of India Finance Department Audit Order No.D./3792-B, dated the 5th August, 1938. (Received with JSxternal Affairs Department endorsement No. F.93(11 )-A/38, doted the 7th October, 1938.)So. D/3792-B. Government of India - Finance Department. Simla, the 5th August, 1938. AUDIT ORDniK Surrender of Savings in the Appropriation under , Sxternal Affairs* for 1938-39. The Accountant-General, Central Revenues, is informed that the Government of India have accepted the surrender of the following amounts in the Appropriation under *External Affairs* in the current financial year:- Sub-head A.- External Affairs Department Secretariat . S’. A.^.-Other Contingencies; Purchase of portraits of His Majesty the King G©orge VI for distribution to certain Political Officers Amount Rs. 2,500 B. - Charges on account of Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran. Bus hi re B. 4-Contingencie st ) Purchase of por- 1,000 Bunder Abbas ) traits of H.1S. B. 4-Contingencies t ) King George VI. 100 Kerman ) B. 4-Continue ncie s : J 100 Koweit ) B. 4-Contingencies t J 100 Khorramshahr j B. 4-Contingencie s : ) 100 Khorasan Consulate-General^ B. 4-Contingencies t ) 1,000 C.- Other Diplomatic and Administrative Charges lie. Bahrain 4-Contingencies i Mus ca t . C.4-Contingencies * 100 100 Total .. 5,100 The savings are due to the cancellation of the indent fox His Majesty *s portraits and the indefinite postponement of the supply of these portraits to Subordinate authorities. (Sd.) Mohamad Ali Under Secretary to the Government of India. To The Accountant-General, Central Revenues.sGTC. J Secretary to the. PoliticalnwResident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 213 Dated the 12th and received the 13th October 1938. (Relayed by P.A. Muscat under No. 130 dated the 12-10-1938) A &lt; A I / Reference my Express Letter No. 1777 of October 8th. 10% reduction. Please send report by this week’s mail y f- (a;,/ rZjcV U&lt;JGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER IN. B.—This is an ORIGINAL sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and formalities it is woraed and signed as if it had been so despatched,] 1938. 2. I regret it is an impossibility to make the required reduction under the head travelling Allowance*• badget allotment under this head is Rs. 6500/- and the actual expenditure to-date exceeds this figure by a little more than Hs. 1100/-. This excess requires explanation as follows. Expenditure on tra velling allowance is incurred unddr four heads, vizt- i. Transfer Travelling Allowance ii. Travelling Allowance for tours iii. Travelling Allowance to personnel going on leave iv. Travelling Allowance to officers going on recess ^Expenditure under the first head has already amounted to Rs. 3260/- this year, and this expenditure is, of course, not FfeOM Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. Na ' / &gt; -4/4 Datei the 14th Octoher 193 8 Your Express letter No. 1777-60/21 dated the 8th October s M FP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—28-7-34—2,00,000. within/.(sn — 2 — Is- CO v^ within my control* Expenditure on travelling allowance for touring so far amounts to Ha* 1687/- only. For expenditure under this head I accept full r esponsibility* The major part of the expenditure is due to Trucial Coast tours and a visit to Basrah to discuss urgent affairs with the Political Resident. I should anticipate considerably higher expendi ture during the coming cold weather, especially if the cost of the travelling allowance which Captain Howes will earn on his journeys with the P.C.L. exploration party is to be charged against this Agency* For expenditure under the third sub-head I accept responsibility since leave was granted to two members of my staff on my recommendation. In one case (Dr. Siddiq) leave was overdue; and in the other leave was granted for genuinely urgent private affairs. The total here is Rs. 1229/-* Recess travelling allowance was paid to Mr. Bird, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, for his journey to Shiraz in August. Since he was entitled to recess this expenditure may be held to be inevitable; and it can only be regarded as fortunate that no similar expenditure was incurred on account of the Political Agent. It will be impossible for the Bahrain Agency to carry out its functions adequately unless an additional grant of at least Rs. 4000/- is made. It Is, I suggest, impossible to contemplate a position in which the Political Agent and the Assistant Political Agent are rendered totally immobile; and indeed without an extra grant we must call off Political participation in the P.C*L. exploration during the winter; and in that event I should feel bound to recommend/-3— recommend that the whole scheme of exploration should be abandoned for the current year* I had previously antici pated that an additional grant of Rs. 7000/- would be required and the reduced figure now suggested can only be possible if transfers are reduced to a minimum and all leave is stopped* Also it will not be possible to provide Captain Howes with an interpreter (assuming that the P*C*L* exploration goes forward) since the cost of the travelling allowance cannot be met. 3. Under Contingencies, the total budget allotment for which amounts to Rs. 41,000/-, I take a reduction of Rs. 4180/-. This reduction is taken under the following detailed heads: (a) Rent of Buildings 4. In the light of the explanation given above under the head travelling Allowanee ,, , I would request immediate orders whether or not Captain Howes may proceed to the Trucial Coast, where he should in ordinary circumstances go next week. Budget Grant Amount surrendered Balance of Grant .. • . • . • • ... Rs. 1800 Rs. 180 Rs. 1620 (b) Post and Telegraph Charges Original Grant ... Amount surrendered .• Balance of Grant ••• •.. ... . • • Rs. 13,000 Rs. A Us. Political Agent, BahrainDbpabtmikt, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] To - (Political, Bahrain [Political, Kuwait (/A No. -60/21-III. Dated the 14th October m 8 IMPORTANT &amp; ILOftaPIATj! Retrenclruient in the Budget for 1938-39. From the date of receipt of this letter until further orders no further expenditure should be incurred by you on ordinary repairs under M Central Contract Grant'. 2. The amount of expenditure already incurred under the above grant should be reported as early as possible. . RESIDENT The issue of the- above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. s. 6. MFP—601 S&amp; P-(M-820)—23-7-30—300,000.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dkpartmint, EXPRESS LETTER [.Y. B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded a«d signed as if it had been so despatched,'] From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire• tfa, 1640-4/4. Tjaiti 23rd October 203 8# Subject:-Retrenchment in the budget for 1938-39. 'if 7 Reference your express letter No. 1821/60/21 dated the 14th October 1938. 2. The total expenditure incurred under Central Contract Grant' up to the 16th October will be undertaken under this 1938 was Rs. 1,298/13. No further work Sub-head until further orders from you Attested. l u Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. MFJL’—400S&amp;P—{M-480)—26-7-34— 2,00,000. Sd. H. Weightman Political Agent, Bahrain.Ho. -ao/iW 4&gt;I« October, 1958. The Limoni Agent, Kueont The ^litlccX ;igen1:, Behrnin * The ^oUtiaiil Agent, iSuealt Hie Uajeaty’n Coneul, Bunder Abbas His Majesty’s Consul, Kerwan for Secrete lit!col Heal dent in the SVrBian Gulf. 3lxpreeo letter Ho.F.S40~V3^» dated the 50th Heptetiber, 1958, from the Oovarmiewt of liKlia in the External Affaire Hepartwent. A copy ( &amp; paper is forwarded for in ire to this office Bxprest letter Fo,1777-60/^1, of 6th October, 1936. Jfy ostlerCopy of Express Letter Ho.S’.240-4/38. dated the 30th September, 1938, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. KRTTHBNCHMEHT IN THE BUDGUTT EOR 1938-39. J Reference this Department Express letter No.D.1919- A/38* dated the 17th Septenher, 1938. 2. In regard to the instructions issued in paragraph l(ii) of the Express Letter mentioned above, the Government of India desire to say that the intention is that pending further an* more detailed instructions, officiating promo tions should not, as a rule, be made in vacancies ot less than three months* duration, the current duties of the post being carried on by a junior officer. In cases, however, where officiating arrangements are inevitable due either to the long duration of the vacancy or other reasons, the appointing authority should consider whether in each indi vidual case the officiating pay to be granted to the offi ciating Government Servant cannot be fixed under E.R.35 at an amount 5-ess than that ordinarily admissible. Any such cases which are not within the powers delegated to you under F.R.36 should be referred to the Government of India. It is requested that egery effort may be made to reduce the number of cases involving additional emoluments to the abso- lute minimum.No.1704-4/4. a r/ Political Agency, Bahrain, November 1, 1938. f ihe Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. h L ^ \fH _// Memorandum . Reference your memorandum No.A.B.110-60/42 dated the 7th February 1935. 2. I enclose, in triplicate, the statements of Contract and Fixed Grants for the year 1937-38. for Political Agent, Bahrain. £f: TAT EM ENT SHEWING MODIFICATIONS OF CON f i PACT GRANIE DURING THE COURSE OF I Hi. YEAR 1937-38. OFFICE AOLOWANCE - Sanctioned Grant “I*. IP, 100 Add vide Buehire aeaorandum No.439- tO/23 dated the 3rd arch 1938 ' 3,000 18,100 CENTRAL C '.NVRACT GRANT- Sanctioned Grant &lt;». 1,300 Add vide Bushire memorandum No.439- tO/23 dated the 3rd arch 1938 ' 50011 CV J, GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, DePAR'I'MENT. [N. B, —This is an ORIGINAL MASSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic • expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been, so despatched,'] From To Politleal. Political, Politica1, Brit consul Brit consul Britconsul Bahrain Musca t Kuwai t , Kerman , Bandar \bbas Khorramshahr -60/21-111. Dated the 28th October 8f g IRCUIAR Retrenchment in the budget for 1938-39. A.s the financial position of the Government of India has become extremely difficult, it is specially requested that every effort may be made to economise in every possible direction, and to confine expenditure to inescapable liabilities. 2. \ preliminary review of the situation in regard to the Persian Gulf Residency’s budget indicates that the total budget provision for the current year is likely to be exceeded by approxi mately Rs, 35,000/-, The only way in which this can be met is by saving under:- ( a) S. G. JIFP—785S&amp;P— (M-1#I4)— 18-1-38— 2.# SOOO.to? $1 - 2 - (a) Poet age and Telegram Chi.rges and (b) by certain other economies. It la specially requested that expenditure under (a) above may be reduced to the loeeet poaalble limit. Telegraphic correspondence should be reel rioted to oases of extreme urgency, and the length of telegrams should be curtailed ae much as possible. 4. ^ith regard to (b), appreciable savinge can be effected under other heads, such as 'Travelling Allowance', •Tour Charges' 1 , Launch Grants, Office Contingencies, etc. Tour journeys should only be undertaken shen absolutely essential. ^^ special report should be submitted ns soon as possible indicating shat savings have been effected in compliance with these instructions. This report should reach this Residency by November 21st 3 / Your a'i ention is draivn to paragraph 2 of this Residency’s Express Letter Ho.1777-60/21, dated the 8th October, 1938, in ehich you are held personally responsible for any excess expenditure. Ho excess expenditure over the provision as reduced by the 10 * cut should be incurred by you without the prior sanction of the Political RKSIPKNTGOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS R .—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the. wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Brit consul, Bushire To Political, Bahrain. No % \ c &amp;6S' -60/21-111. Dated the 28th October, 1SJQ , Retrenchment in the budget for 1938-39. Reference your Express Letter Ho.1380-4/4, dated the 14th October, 1938, and in continuation of this Residency's telegram Ho.220, dated the 26th October, 1938. 2. As Captain Hov,es and Interpreter will be provided with free transport by Petroleum Concessions, Limited, no expenditure will be incurred on mileage allowance for road journeys. 3. With regard to the halting allowance, as 1 envisage it, the operations of the Petroleum Concessions, Limited’s exploration Party will involve long halts at various centres for discussion with local Shaikhs and for local geological surveys, and then a ehort march to another centre with another halt. In these cir- /ci rcunstances S. 6. MFP— 785S&amp;P— (M-l#14)—]8-g-38— 2.r»,000.curastancee I am not prepared to authorise the rates men tioned in S.R.73. for every halt v?hich may he made, especially in the present financial crisis* I do not think Hov.es or his Interpreter viill he out of pocket hy thif decision. the halting allowance of Howes and his Interpreter during the whole tour. Howes can submit hills to cover this full amount. If he stays more than ten days in one place and chooses to draw reduced rates for a further period, this rate is fixed at 50 % of the full rates. If the expedition is unduly prolonged I am prepared to consider a further grant. This decision will operate from the time Howes and his Interpreter reach Sharjah, till their return there again after the conclusion of the exploration. 4. Please forward a revised estimate of the anticipated excess under 'Travelling Allowance'. I am however prepared to grant a total sum of Es. 250/- for Sd/ T. G. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.i\io. 1704-4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th Noveph9r 135Bt To The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Husnire* Menoranduia Reference your endorsement No* 750-60/S3 d ted the 4th April 1326. 2* I enclose a statement of anticipated excesses ana savings in the budget grants for the year 1938-29, which has been prepared after the receipt of your memo randum No. 1806 dated the 14th October 1928 to the Government of India in the T'xternal Ai ft irs Dei ?t orient, and your Express letter lo. 1884 dated the 28th October 1938. Political Agent, Bahrain*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbfabtmint, EXPRESS LETTER (.V. I ?.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it ha&gt;I been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded a d signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain* To Political Resident, Bushire. Na ' 1729-4/4. fith Hoveoiber 1:3 8. Subjects-Retrenchment in the budget for 1938-39* su (r* J Reference your Kxpreae letter No* 1884-60/21-111 dated the 28th October 1938* 2* As already reported the expenditure up to date on travelling allowance amounts to tis* 6,600/- (in round figures)* In addition to this sun there is the cost of my recent tour to Dubai and other Journeys performed since I reverted to the post of Political Agent* I will restrict the total bill, by omitting certain claims, to &amp;• 200/-* This then brings the total charges for Journeys performe&lt; to fe* 6,800/-* 3* In regard to the cost of the halting allowance to be drawn bfts.Qaptaln Howes and his interpreter I venture to suggest that as MFi’—4003&amp;P—(M-480;— 26-7-34—2,00.000. the sun/- 2 - @) 5 the sum of «$• 260/- mentioned in your Express letter provides only for 20 days halting allowance at the combined rates drawn by Captain Howes and his Interpreter, it mi^ht be advisable to contemplate the possible doubling of this sum* Even if Captain Howes draws no halting allowance at all after a 10-day halt in any particular place, it is, I think, unlikely that a total of less than 40 days' halting allowance will become due to him and his interpreter under the rules* Since it is my responsibility to ensure that there no excesses occur in the final grant while % I shall not be in a position to restrict the movements of the party, I would most earnestly request that the sum to be ear marked for this particular purpose should not be less than as* 600/-* In addition there will be the cost of Captain Howes* Journey from Bahrain to Sharjah and back which can be put at as* 160/-* The interpreter is already in Sharjah and consequently there is no expense on his account* 4* Since Captain Howes will be in the interior accompanying the exploration party, he will not be available for ordinary work on the Trucl&amp;l Coast* Thus it is essential to provide for visits by myself to the Coast, though naturally I will restrict these as far as possible* Visits to Qatar will also be necessary, since Petroleum Concessions Limited's work there is going ahead reasonably fast and I have not been, able to see the Shaikh of Qatar for several months* Allowing for these Journeys and the very minimum of local touring the lowest safe figure that I can suggest is fis* 1,000/- to meet my own travelling allowance and that of the establishment accompanying me* 5* Finally it would be, I think, unwise not to allow for at least one transfer in establishment* Illness or other causes are more than likely to be responsible for this minimum and as a] i average figure I propose te* 300/- for this purpose* 6* Thus the anticipated expenditure during the balance of the year amounts to tis* 1,960/-, making a total for the year hs* 8,760/-, or an excess of fis* 3,000/- over the allotment* I much regret/— 3 — much regret that it ie necessary to ask for this additional allotmenty hut I have already explained that much of the expenditure charged against this head accrued from reasons out of my control f and I have felt bound to propose a sum which will provide for the Agency to continue to function on a minimum scale of touring* SD/ H. Weightman, Political Agent t Bahrain* Attested*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, .Dkpabtment, EXPRESS LETTER [N , Tj.—T his is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to swe telegraphio expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] 2* The statement of anticipated excesses and savings which is forwarded with my memorandum No. 1704-4/4 dated the &gt; November 1938 has been prepared in the light of these instructions. It will be seen that a further saving is offered under Postage and Telegram charges, and I regret that I cannot suggest addi tional savings under other heads. The position in regard to Travelling Allowance has been dealt with in detail separately? I find it impossible, for reasons previously explained, to make any suggestion for reduction in the Launch Grant, against which there are bound to be increasing charges as work increases in From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, ! .Vo, 1730-4/4 Bushire Dated 5th November J33 Subject :- Retrenchment in the budget for 1938-39 Reference your Express letter No. 1884-60/21-III dated the 28th October 1938 on the above subject. s. e. ME 1 — 40QS&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2^)0,000. Oatar./-- 2 - Qatar; and it is impossible also to reduce the grant for 'Office Allowance' since experience has already shown that this is inadequate. It is only by the practice of the most rigorous economy that it will be possible to restrict expenditure to the amount budgetted, 3. I should have wished to make a still further reduc tion in the provision for Postage and Telegram charges, but the Trucial Coast Exploration is bound to lead to some increase in telegraph charges over normal and I consider it unsafe to provide for less than an average expenditure monthly of about He. 700/- during the cold weather.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DeF.vstment, EXPRESS LETTER [iV. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by •post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Reference your Express letter 2o.l7afi-4/4, dated the 5th November 1938. on halting allowance to Japtain Howes and his Interpreter may be incurred up to a limit of Rs.500/-* anticipated excess under your Travelling Allowance Grant. Bushire Political Agent Bahrai n No. 2.0 Dated 181 h November 193 8 . 2. In the circumstances stated in your letter expenditure 3. The necessary provision is being made to cover the 3d. T.C. FOWLS Political Resident in the Persian Gulf attested vAt' Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf fc. 6. MFP—601 S&amp;P—(M-820)—2S-7-3&amp;—300,000.' ^ Bia Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty*a Consul, Kerman. His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas. His Majesty*s Consul, Shirax. His Majesty*s Consul, Ahwaz. His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. A statement showing the alterations made in your budget grants for 193d—39 is attached for your information. Memorandum By Order Resident Gulf.Ho,Zo^5 -60/21 Dated the 1st December, 1938 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded The Political Agent, Muscat, / The Political Agent, Bahrain, / The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty^ Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, for Secretary to'the Political Resident Copy of Memorandum Ho .p.9(77 )-K/38, dated the 5th Uovember, 1938, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. to: for information and guidance By order in the Persian Gulffr0 “ r '' ' Tna tufe-&lt;kmrjausnt-of-- Ir.fi i«. ■ in tiie External Jiff airs nepartu.ent, To ' The Nnrtr Secretary to the Government of the Mortn est Frontier Province. w b ^ + tlie .‘‘^, ei ? t ^ t 2 tli6 Governor General The Hon^Dle t t^ a p?i 1 ^L?VD as -?^ on ? r . in Baluchistan, His Maieqtv , q U rn?o J h lj n 4J5 *^ Kcnj.aent in the Persian-Gulf, nis i-idjest-y s Consul General for iiiorasan His naiesty s Consul General; Kasli^ar/ xne rolitical Officer in Sikkim. ^ iu? Besiaent in kashmir (for Giinit), The Ccunseller British Legation; ka'oul, K kferf C J+ S | nV ° y E J t I aor ,4inary and Minister Thfi p JBe Court of Ne,,al. T tfor Gartok)^ e8iaeri0 for ths Spates nlS General in the frenen nstaoliBxu.ients in India, Pondicherry. Memorandum No .F. 9(77)-E/38, hated New Delhi, the 5th November 1938, ■*e.g.,if a cadre consists of 26 posts then no re cruitment shall oe made against the first three vacan cies; if of 25 pests then against the first tY\ro vacancies. Filling up^of permanent and temporarv vacancies^ in posts the cost of which is oorne oy Central Revenues. xiefeience this Department express letter No. F.r4C-x/36, darned tire 30th leptender 1938. A' v ^ * ine Government of India have now decided that the temporary orders issued in the above-mentioned letter and in paragraph l(ii) of the express letter No.D.1919-4/38, dated the 17th September 1938, should be replaced by ins- tructions directed to effecting economy which may, without serious detriment to efficiency, continue in operation till Iso April 1940. In supersession of the previous orders, therefore, ohe followirg instructions are issued which xj.ust be read subject to the previsions of the Government of India met ana to any other statute which may be appli cable . 1 * ' a ' : In, perma nent posts , ill recruitment to ueriices Sxiould oe stopped until the number of vacancies in pests on which no officer holds a lien, suspended or otherwise, exceeds Wo (calculated to the nearest vjhole nurber) of the strength of any cadre, vnen recruitment against any such excess may be re-opened. The word 'recruitment'’ should be taken normally2 3 norhially to included also the filling of x jcsts by x jrono tion from a lov/er service. Cases in v/hicn tlie process of recinit^ent for any existing vacancy has advanced to such a stage that tne iiniiediate application of this instruction would be inequitable, should be reported to the Governsnt of India for orders. (b) Italicies_ in temporary post s. \fhen a temporary post falls vacant it should normally remain vacant. ’ hHQ^il.Q.tiQns tp__^e rmaiient vacancies witl iin a o^Cre. It is net pioposed to pr.ohioit promotions within a cadre alenough as started above promotions from one service to another should be subject to the restriction in 1(a) above, hnen permanent promotions \uf.hin a cadx e are in contempla^ ricn, however, it should be considered in each case whether tiie higiier post cannot be held in abeyance or combined with another pest Local Mninistrarions and Heads of Depart- iiienod snould satisiy themselves by obtaining periodical reports from subordinate authorities that these instruc tions are being carefully observed. £ Lime tiQns_tp_pe r;porary vacancies in permanent jos t s . 1 i'_hiot re than 1 month’s duration. No officiating appomcmeiit should be made« The officer who would norma-• ly be expected to officiate, or another officer should be required to carry on the current duties of the post, in addition to nis own, without extra remuneration. (o) Vag^ncie_s^__o f more tiia n 1 month ’ s duration. ^) If it is unavoidable r txie vacant post may be lilied, out \in each individual case the autliWity c cup stent to ex^i uise powers us^der Fundai-.ental A(ile D5 siiould co/iSiae\^ 5 in view of \he urgent need fo\ economy, to wnat expert the assi^iption of duties knu res- ponsioilit\es of greater\importance should be re munerated by\&gt;ff ioiating pay. (ii)t^f ' 1 , .* yte*+J x~+ \T\ZL~j^ x^ \ -jf ) -m n/ ^1 ru i ^ c^.^Q - I, o -: ,'r. -•'i.-rt ^-f ^V*TT^ ue-^ennid-6j^4, bearoi^ j.n mind any statutory restrictions on the combination of posts, whether the officer cannot also continue to perform the duties of his own post. In such cases Fundamental Rule 49 would apply, subject to the Government of India's decision No. 239 dated the 26th of October 1937. In this connect tion, the instructions issued at a time of similar crisis in Finance Department office memorandum ^ ‘ No.F.15(11)~R.I./31 dated the 2nd of June 1931 are relevant. The present circumstances would, however justify the substitution of Wo for 20% in the lant paragraph of that memorandum. (iiy?,) If such a combination of duties is not possible, it may yet be possible to effect a combination of pests, unaer similar conditions,at some lower level in the chain of arrangements. him!* inere may be cases under (a) above where it is necessary on le^al or ether grounds to fill the vacant post. In all such cases the considerations enumerated in clause (i) above will 4. ReJ;ax^ticns_._ It is realised that these instructions may have to be relaxed in rare cases. Sanction of the Govern ment of India will however be necessary for the relaxation of the instructions contained in paragraphs 1(a) and (b) above. 3* The Government of India recognise that the application of these instructions must throw an additional burden of work and responsibility, with little, if any, additional remunera tion on all Government servants. They are convinced, however, bnat they v/ill receive tne v/hole-hearted co-operation of all the authorities concerned .in their endeavour to effect by these and cognateNo.D-5723-B. Government of India © ?£■ Finance New Deliii, the Department 21s to November 1938. From H. A. C. Gill, Ssquire, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India To All Provincial Governments and the Chief Commissioner, Coorg. Subject:- Revised Estimates 1S38-3S and Budget Estimates I am directed to inform you that the Government of India have decided to assume an average rate of exchange of Is. 5 29/32d. for the purpose of the Revised Estimates, IS38-39 and Is. 6d. for the Budget Estimates, 1939-40. Copy forwarded to all Depart ante of the Government of India, the Financial Adviser, Military Finance,• the Finance Officer, Communications, the Crown Finance Officer, the accoun tant General, India Office, the Chief Accounting Officer to the High Commissioner for India, the Accountant-General, Posts and Telegraphs, the Controller of Railway accounts, the Military Accountant-General, the Central Board of Revenue, the Auditor General, the Mint Masters, the Master, Security Printing, and all Civil A.cco\mtants-General and Comptrollers, including the Audit Officer, Indian Stores Department. 1939-40 — Rate of Exchange. Sir I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant Deputy Secretary to the Government of mdia. No.D-5723-B. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.% Please telegraph the figures of anticipated excesses and savings under pay of Officers and pay of establishment, taking into account any variations since the November review. - BRITCONSUL -rz? Telegram From To No. OTC. Politlcel Agent, Bahrain. Secretary to Political Resident,Bushire. 5 Dated the 5th January 1939. v °ur telegram No. 253 (?) dated the 2nd January 2* Anticipated excesses over reappropriated grants. Pay of Officers Rs. oO/- and Establishment Rs* t&gt;bO/-. - POLITICAL -No.H^-V4 The Poiuical Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Secretax’y to tlie Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Bushire endorsement No*750 dated the 4th April 1936 Description of Enclosure. Statement showing Anticipated Excesses and Savings for tke year 193P-39. Dated 4th February 1939 Reference to previous correspondence: Name and Date, Subject,Persian Gulf, Bushire &gt; $ 0 . -60/21 Dated the 26th January, 1939. js£ : A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded toi Agent, Muscat, Agent, Bahrain, Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty|s Consul, Kerman, Consul, Bandar Abbas, Tdce-Consul, Khorraoishahr, The Political The political The political His Majesty’s His Haje sty ’a for information and guidance with reference to tnis o;, fice printed letter Ho. 2083-60/21, aated the 1st December,193B. % order, for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy of D.O.Ho.P.9(77)-li/38, dated the 5th January, 1939, from the Government of India in trie ixtemal Affairs Departmsnt to the Hon’ble the political Resident in thev 'A e? D.O.i o.?.9(77)-3/38. External r.-xrirs Departmen'o L / S- 1 ! The 5th January 1939 Filli/ifc up of pema::. ;:io a temporary vacancies i- pos ; s on cost of vaich is born oy j e-i .revenues. I are desired to refer to the orders of the Government ©f India contained in ^heir jxtem&amp;l Aifairs Department memcrandun iIo.J.9(7^-D/36, ve-eu ohe 5th hovember 1938 ? and to communicate xor youx information and guidance the following supplementary i sx»rucuions about the fixation of officiating pay unuer fundamental Rule 35* In terms of paragraph 3(b)(i) of oho above- mentioned memorandum the authority compcu.in uo excercise powers under fundamental Rule 35 shoulu co_:sidor, in view of uhe urgent need for economy, to what extent one assumption of duties and responsibilities ol greater importance should be remunerated by officiating pay* This discretion should be carefully exercised. In this connection I am to suggest that, as an or^i-ary rule*, when the presumptive pay of the officiating pose (ioC* the pay to which the officiating Government servant would be entitled if he held the post substantively) is less than the substantive pay of the ofiiciating incum bent p lus 1C% of the presumptive pay, he should be given the presumptive pay only* In other cas s the cli iciai/ing pay should not ordinarily exceed the substantive pay of the Government servant plus 1of the presumptive pay of the post whose duties he is called upon to perform, further, where a temporary post or an ofiiciating arrange ment in a deputation or ocher vacancy, originally sanctioned immediately previous to the date of orders referred to above, is continued for a sui-i.iciently long period after they have come into effect, steps should be taken to refix (but not retrospectively) the officiating pay of the individual who bolus that post or is officiating in that arrangement in accordance with those orders. It is howovor ro^isr-v -cacii such ,.,- 2 ~ such case should be considered on its own r.;e its and that considerations both of economy ana equity to the individual concerned should be duly borne in mindo I am to explain in this connection that it is not intended ^nat the temporary restriction on official • ing pay should have a permanently prejudicial effect tn increments and it is therefore desirable that in cases in which officiating pay is restricted by you under Fundamental Rule 35, steps should be taken under Fundamental Rule 27 to prevent a permanently prejudicial effect on increments* C Sd/- &amp;.K.3.Sanaa.ANo. 502-4/4• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd March 1939. Prom The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• Sir, I am directed to say that the Political Agent has received one or two applications from members of the clerical establishment for short periods of leave during the summer. L In addition the following application for leave have been made:- Mr. D.J. Stephens - vide Agency endorsement No. 1924-1/28 dated the 7th December 1938. Mr. Mohammad Abdul Hafiz - vide Agency memorandum No. 1720-1/31 dated the 3rd November 1938. On these orders have not yet been received. 3* The Travelling Allowance incurred on these grants of leave will, of course, be a charge on the Bahrain Agency budget. In view of the budget position last year, the Political Agent ;ould be glad to have any information you may be able to give him with regard to the probable figures for the head of Travelling Allowance this year; in order th* he may keep this in mind when deciding whether he can or cannot grant such periods of short leave. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 4 c Assistant Political Agent, Bahrai’ kS' s No *4b3 -64/238. Dated the Apr! 1, 1939. The Political Agent, Bahrain MdiMOBANDUlC Reference your letter No.502-4/4, dated the 23rd March, 193 9. Mr. D. J. Stephens may proceed on leave on relief by Mr. Thomas about the end of June, 1939. It v*as not found possible to grant leave to ^r. M.A.Hafiz as no suitable relief was available. It is now learnt that Mr. Ghulam Haidar Dar who is on leave at present and whose leave will be expiring about the middle of June, knows enough Arabic to perform the duties of the Court clerk and that in fact, he was the Court clerk in Bahrain for some time. If you are agree able to have Mr. Dar in relief of Mr. Hafiz, the latter may be granted leave in June, 1939. 4. The probable budget provision under rt Bahrain-c-3-Allowances, Honoraria, etc., - Trave11ing Allowancefor 1939-40 is Rs.7,800/-. By order,Files 4/4 and 1/31 Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 87. Dated 25th April 1939. Your memorandum No. 453 dated 8th April Please send confidential reports of Dar by next mail. Political.No . S'S'^ -60/23 BTitish Consulate-General f Busiiire, the 23tli April, 1939 To The Political Agent, Bahrain,/ The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty*s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. I enclose for your information and guidance a statement of final modifications in appropriations for the year 1938-39* Memorandum* Secretary to t^he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.MG 1 PC g5—163 Pol Res Bushire —10-1-39—2,500. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to :~ The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, Letter from the Government of India in the affairs Department Ko -P. 9(77)- . datedthe 19 th April 19 39' E/38 with External AfEair Department endorsement No. 601-60/21 • British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 4th May , 19 39 1 His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khurramshahr, • ^ &gt; for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement By order, for Secretary Cal Resident the Persian Gulf. No. dated the 19 .)9 This ainendmant shall have ef ect from lie Iso ci april 3. Casas in which officiating pay has ceen rosorico^c’. in pcrsaance of the instructions contain so. in '-lie ettisoiiig paragraph 2(3)(b)(i) should be reviewed and the officiating pay refixed, with effect rroa tie 1st, oi April j.939, at a figure viiich would have been allowed but for the- instructions referred to above. Under Secretary to the C-ov emment of IndiaIs~ la , Re*. P, G. 32. No. nc&lt;\ British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 19 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khurramshahr, for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement No. , dated the 19 By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the No. »dated the 19 Department (Received with External Affair Department endorsement N a dated the 19 .) &gt; f. O' ^IQIPO S5—163 Pol Res Bushire—10-1-39—2,500.Copy of letter No »j/ 1762-B s datea Nev; Uelai, the 20th April 1939, from the Deputy Secretary to the G-overnment of India,Finance hepartiiient, to all Provincial G-overniuents and Chief Commissioners. Demands for Grants for 1939-40* i I am directed to enclose the requisite number of copies of the relevant budget grants and appropria tions for 1939-40.118 Id DEMANDS FOR GRANTS, 1939-40 Actuals, 1937-38. Rs. INDIA— contd. Budget Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. C.—OTHER DIPLOMATIC AND ADMINISTRATIVE CHAR GES— contd . Nepal — concld. C. 3.—ALLOWANCES, HONO RARIA, ETC.: Cost of passages granted under the Superior Civil Services Rules, 1924 . . Travelling and other allowances Allowance to escorts . Total C. 4.—CONTINGENCIES : Maintenance and renewal of the Agency and Residency fur niture .... Maintenance of motor cars Medical and hospital stores Petty supplies to escoros Wireless .... Maintenance of the Raxaul Garden .... Purchase of tents Tour charges .... Liveries and warm clothing Service postage and telegram charges .... Medical and hospital contin gencies .... Menial charges Miscellaneous contingencies for escorts .... Office expenses and miscel laneous .... Total C. 6.—GRANTS-IN-AID, TRIBUTIONS, ETC. : CON- Contributions for passages of officers transferred to or from other Governments, Depart ments, etc. .... 8.— DEDUCT —ESTABLISH MENT AND OTHER CHARGES RECOVERED FROM OTHER GOVERN MENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC.: Amount recovered from Defence estimates .... Total for Nepal , . Revised Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. Budget Estimate, 1939-40. Rs. 2,000 10,900 13,500 2,000 12,100 11,600 26,166 26,400 25,800 25,700 1,600 1,000 2,700 4,000 100 1,500 1,000 2,700 3,000 300 800 4,000 300 300 300 3,500 300 3,000 2,500 1,000 1,500 1,000 1,200 4,500 3,400 8,000 3,000 33,060 32,700 27,300 23,700 161 200 200 200 —4,060 —4,400 —4,400 —4,400 1,68,620 1,66,900 1,63,500 1,61,000r EXTERNAL AFFAIRS. 129 I.—MISCELLANEOUS— concld. I. 6.—REPRESENTATIVE TO THE LEAGUE OF NATIONS ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON SOCIAL QUESTIONS : Travelling and incidental charges I. 6.—EXPENDITURE IN CON NECTION WITH TRAINING OF POLITICAL SERVICE PROBATIONERS : I. 6 (4).—PAYMENTS TO THE CROWN REPRESENTA TIVE FOR TRAINING OF POLITICAL SER VICE PROBATIONERS: I. 7.—EXPENDITURE IN CONNEC TION WITH DESTITUTE . INDIAN PILGRIMS RE PATRIATED FROM IRAQ : I. 8.—OTHER EXPENSES : Customs duty on arms and ordnance stores (Nepal) . Education of students from Nepal .... Expenditure in connection with Lhasa Mission Donations for Charitable Purposes.— Persian (Iranian) Lega tion Khorasan Miscellaneous— External Affairs De partment Secretariat (Toshakhana) Cost of proposed visit to India by Mr. Angus Fletcher, Director of the British Library of Information, New York Total Total for Miscellaneous Total for India Actuals, 1937-38. Budget Estimate, 1938-39. Revised Estimate, 1938-39. Budget Estimate, 1939-40. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. rDIA — concld. 3,700 3,700 80,000 80,000 60,000 4,500 4,000 1 4,000 1,500 1,000 • • 1,000 •• 50,000 100 100 200 200 500 500 4,000 57,177 2,300 51,400 56,800 1,26,894 1,82,500 2,28,400 2,23,300 39,23,600 39,76,000 39,01,000 39,69,000 IIDEMANDS FOR GRANTS, 1939-40 182 Actuals, 1937-38. Budget Estimate, 1938-39. Revised Estimate, 1938-39. Budget Estimate, 1939-40. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. MADRAS— conoid. O.—OTHER DII LOMATIC AND ADMINISTRATIVE CHARGES— contd - His Majesty’s Consul General in the French Establishments in India— concld. British Consular Office at Karikal —conoid C. 7.—ESTABLISHMENT CHARGES PAID TO OTHER GOVERNMENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC.: Establishment charges payable to the Madras Government for work connected with External Affairs Amount paid to Madras Government on account of passport work . Total Total for Other Diplomatic and Ad-* MINISTRATIVE CHARGES H.—REFUGEES AND STATE PRISONERS : H. 3.—KABUL REFUGEES AND STATE PRISON ERS : Allowances to Kabul Re fugees and State Pri soners .... H. 4.—OTHER REFUGEES AND STATE PRI SONERS : . . . Total for Refugees and State Prisoners I. - MISCELLANEOUS : I. 8.—OTHER EXPENSES : Profession tax paid to the cor poration of Madias in respect of the American Consular Officers in Madras J. —ESTABLISHMENT CHARGES PAID TO OTHER GOVERN MENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC. : Charges payable to the Madras Government for work connected with Ex ternal Affairs Amount paid to Madras Government on account of passport work . Amount paid to Madras Government for Extra dition work Total 4,700 •• 28,800 .. 4,700 33,600 34,900 •• 38,296 64,200 68,900 34,200 22,239 24,000 25,300 24,000 600 500 500 500 22,839 24,500 25,800 24,600 382 300 300 300 •• 4,700 •• 9,600 .. 2,700 17,000 61,617 89,000 95,000 76,000 'Ojtal for Madras134 DEMANDS FOR GRANTS, 1939-40 Numbers. 1938- 1939- 39. 40. Actuals, 1937-38. Rs. Budget Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. Revised Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. Budget Estimate, 1939-40. Rs. BOMBAY— concld. Charges for passport work done by the Police Department, Bombay. I.—MISCELLANEOUS : I. 1—PAY OF ESTABLISH. ME NTS : I. 8.- -OTHER EXPENSES i Payment to the Aden Colony on account of settlement . Payments to the Commis sioner of Police, Bombay for the disposal of mails sent by the British Lega tion at Jeddah J.— ESTABLISHMENT CHARGES PAID TO OTHER GOVERN MENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC. : Amount payable to the Bombay Government on account of passport branch of the Political Department Secretariat Total for Bombay 6,23,556 52,000 1,76,000 1 1 1 1 Deputy Inspector (275) Clerk (Rs. 60 to Rs. 160) . Duty allowance 3,300 1,100 . 500 3,300 1,100 300 2 2 Total 4,900 4,900 4,700 I. 8.- —OTHER EXPENSES : Travelling allowance . 300 200 Clothing allowance . 100 100 Contingencies . 1,100 1,100 Total 1,500 1,400 1,400 Total for charges for passport WORK, ETC. .... 6,400 6,300 6 ,100, I. 7.- -EXPENDITURE IN CON NECTION WITH DESTI TUTE INDIAN PILGRIMS REPATRIATED FROM IRAQ . . . 300 300 300, 10O Total 5,10,220 1,23,100 10 O for Miscellaneous 5,10,220 6,700 1,29,700 6,500 32,300 53,000138 DEMANDS FOR GRANTS, 1939-40 : Budget Revised Budget Actuals, Estimate, Estimate, Estimate, 1937-8. 1938-39. 1938-39. 1939-40. Rs. Rs. Rs. Rs. PUNJAB — contd. OTHER DIPLOMATIC AND ADMINISTRATIVE CHARGES — contd. Gilgit Agency — concld. C. 4.— CONTINGENCIES: Grants for maintenance of furniture 600 600 Purchase of tents 200 200 Durbar presents 5,600 5,000 Military stores for Gilgit 15,000 Corps of Service 15,000 Kit mtney and footwear for 17,000 Gilgit Corps of Scouts 17,000 Ration and clothing for prisoners 4,300 4,800 Medicines and instruments for Veterinary hospital . 400 400 Medicines and drugs for 900 Scouts 900 Ration to boarders . 1,60;) 1,600 Medicines and instruments for the Medical depart- ment .... 7,500 7,500 Scholarships 2,700 2,200 Prizes and free books 300 300 Service postage and tele- 9,900 gram charges 9,900 Tour expenses 1,900 1,900 Office expenses and mis- 3,000 cellaneous 1,900 Other contingencies 53,100 54,000 X-Ray contingencies 1,000 800 Construction of telephone lines and maintenance of telegraph line 3,900 3,900 Petty construction and re- paire 1,000 800 Hunza-Misgar telegraph line 12,200 12,200 Expenditure in connection with the Farm at Jaglote. 500 Deduct —Probable savings . •• —10,000 Total 1,60,434 1,41,500 1,34,000 1,32,000 C. 5.—SECRET EXPENDITURE: Secret service money 2,698 2,000 2,000 2,000 C. 6 .— GRANTS-IN-ATD, CON TRIBUTIONS, ETC : 10,324 6,500 3,400 3,400 C. 8.— DEDUCT —ESTABLISH MENT AND OTHER CHARGES RECOVERED FROM OTHER GOVERN MENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC : Block recovery from the Crown Department on account of conduct of re latione of the Crown with Gilgit .... —2,00,000 —2,00,000 —2,00,000 —2,00,000 Total for Giloit Auenoy 4,31,454 3,89,800 3,81,000 3,94,000144 DEMANDS FOR GRANTS, 1939-40 Actuals, 1937-38. Budget Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. Rs. SIND— concld. / -N J.—ESTABLISHMENT CHARGES PAID TO OTHER GOVERN- MENTS, DEPARTMENTS, ETC. : Amount paid to Provincial Government on account of passport branch of the Provincial Secretariat . Amount paid to Provincial Government on account of Police Establishment employed on passport work at Karachi . Lump sum charges paid to Provincial Government— Cost of Air Port Police . Total . Total tor Sind . 9,90Q Revised Estimate, 1938-39. Rs. Budget Estimate, 1939-40. Rs. 10,000 4,000 4,000 2,300 2,200 10,200 17,000 16,200 24.000 25,000 24,000No. 1213-4/4. Political Agency, Bahrain, July 15, 1939 To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum . Reference your endorsement No.750-60/23 dated the 4th April 1936. 2. I enclose a statement shoeing grants, expenditure, etcetera for the year 1938-39. / &lt; for Political Agent, Bahrain.Ho* 1401-4/4. Political Agency, Bahrain, August 10/31, 1939. From H.Welghtman, Kequire, I.C.3., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushlre. Sir I have the honoui' to forward herewith in duplicate the budget estimates of this Agency together with a statement of new items of expenditure for the year 1940-41. These estimates follow closely those sanctioned for the current year, save in respect of Hs.300/-for a dresser, which la inadequate. It Is already apparent that the new dispensary at Dubai will attract a very high attendance, and that the Sub Assistant burgeon in charge must have adequate assistance in respect of dispensing and dressing if he is to be able to cope with the flow of patients. The recommends that a compounder be engaged on n*.40/»per mensem in addition to a dresser on &amp;.20/« and with this recommen dation I agree. (D SAfAy qf s mSblM S Pay of compounder. The budget estimate Tor the current year allows (2) C.4.C0NTIMG5NCIS3. (1) Coat of medical enuloment a nd supply of drugs . The allotment for the current year of fis.800/- has proved to be inadequate, and on the advice of the\ . 2 - Residency Surgeon who has rscsntly visited Dubai the provision proposed for the next year has been increased to fe«l t 500/*« It is evident enough that without adequate equipment and drugs the dispensary cannot continue to function* (11) Howoltal contlngenclas« Thera is no provision In this year's budget for contingent expenditure for llghtlng 9 sweeping, washing charges, stationery, etcetera* A sum of Ss*300/- is the minimum estimate of the amount required for this purpose in future years* I have the honour to be, air, Your most obedient servant, L Political Agent, Bahrain* A tC. A. C. 19-A. (See Article 186-A, C. A. C., Vol. I.) Department or Office. Statement of details of provision proposed for pay of f or year 19*1® -19^1 . Establishments Note 1. —Voted and Non-voted items should be separately shown. Note 2. —In the case of temporary establishments, authority under which they are entertained should be quoted. Note 3. —Numbers and amount of provision should agree with the entries in the estimate form. Note 4.—Names need not bo given in the case of officers whose names are omitted from pay bills. Signature of Officer Dated of MFP—1214 Audit—{M-2137)—8-3-39—20,000. 19 V?. Designation of Officer Aeenfc , Bahrain K ej&lt;L / -®ses-Copy of a latter Ho.TA-9-6-694 dutoc the 10th Attipaift 1939 from the Aaeountfint Oeiier«l # Centrttl Ravenuaa, Wan Dollil to the Seeratary to the Kon # hle the ^litittal ^aaident in the ?er*»ian Chtlf, Huahire. Suhjeet:- Btntanente of oxoobuoo over eontraot Krunta. I have the honour to etate thnt aceorciing to th&lt; aviating arrangement, the etatefiientii of axoeaaea over contract and fixed grant» are dua to raaah thia offiaa on the Ihth Dtaemhar eaoh year, for aulwiiooion of th« a an a to tha Ooweriment of India, }5xtemal Affairs 'iapart- aent, Ae, However, the acaounta are now oloood hy the middle of duly inatead of hy the end of Bept«aiher, i.e. montho earlier, it i» oonaidered neeenaory that the above statements should reach this offiee earlier so that they may also he submitted to the Government of India earlier. 8, I would, therefore, enquire th* earliest possible date by which the above atat events may roach this office. The favour of an early reply in requested.No. 1626-4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, September 17, 1959 To The Beoretary to the Hon’ble the Political Reeident in the Pare ion Gulf, Buahlre. Reference your memorandum Ho*1167-60/42 dated the 25th August 1939* 2 . I enclose, in triplicate, the statements of Contract and Fixed Grants for the year 1938-59* for Political Agent, Bahrain tftSTATEMENT OF CONTRACT GRANTS FOR THE YEAR 1958-59. Nam® of Sanctioned office Grant, and Grants. Modifications during the course of the year. Total grant Total Excess ♦ at the close expenditure of the year, as per Saving - statement attached. Political Agency, Bahrain. Office Allowance 15,100 - 16,100 14,955- 7 -146-9 Launch Grant 9,000 - 9,000 9,092- 2 ♦ 92-2 Central Contract Grant 1,300 1,300 1,298-15 - 1-5STATEMENT SHOEING MODIFICATIONS OF CONTRACT GRANTS DURING THE COURSE OF THE YEAR 1938-S9, OFFICE AliLO^iANCE - Sanctioned Grant **#16,100 Modification® Nil CENTRAL CONTRACT GRANT - Sanctioned Grant 1,300 Modifications Nil LAUNCH GRANT - Sanctioned Grant 9,000 Modifications NilName of Office Grant ae fixed by Total expenditure Exceee and Or ant a. the Government of aa per detailed India. atatement. Laving Political Agency, Bahrain. PAY OF ESTABLISHMENT ^cort Chargee N I-L .rv Of GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, EXPRESS LETT ^ * ’ This to an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wwes, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the, same expedition as tj it had been telegraphed. To su' t t ime and formalities it is worded- and signed as if it had been so despatched,] To. politi cal, Bahrain. No. - 14/226. Doled 19th September, ig3 9 Su~b&gt;1 ect : Government Dispensary ^ on the Tructal coBst * f ,ot Reference your letters Nos. 1401-4/4 dated the 10/31 August 1939 and 1484-30/19 dated the 20th August 193^. vyl. Please telegraph anticipated excess during current financial year over Budget provision of fc.800/- for purchase of medical equipment, drugs, and other hospital contingencies. 2. Is budget provision required during ensuing and subse quent years for enhancement of Sub-Assistant surgeon* s pay and allowances up to a total of fc.200/- per mensem as recommended by Residency surgeon ? If so, Political Residents sanction to proposal may kindly be communicated. 3. subject to Political Residents approval, which may kindly be obtained, Budget provision is being requested during A 6. /the A 6. MFP-—1196 SAP—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.)■ ‘ ' the ensuing anh snhsetiuent years for the following. (A) . Establishment . One Compounder et iis. 40/- per mensem. One Dresser at is. 20/- ' * (B) Si^pply of medical equipment, drugs, etc. for ensuing year is. 1,500/- for subsequent years is.500/- (C) Contingencies — Lighting, sweeping, washing, etc. for ensuing and subsequent years is. 300/- BESIDENT The issue of the abo^re has been authorised Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegraphic Addrt&amp;e: Aooounts. All communioatious should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. BY MR MAIL OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI, -Vo. TA. 26-4-807 SfLP &amp; ' ‘^ Enclosures. From To Sir, The ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVEN The Political -agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to state that a sum of fe.37/8/- -vas adjusted in this office by deduction from expenditure under the head H C.6 drants-in-aid contribution etc'. The amount represents write back of the excess passage contribution for the period from 8.2.39 to 28.2.39 of Lt. J.B. Howes due to confirmation in Central Civil from 8.2.39. The figures under this head should accordingly come to fs. 680/- (Rs. 718/- minus is. 38/-) as shown in the draft appropriation accounts instead of Rs.718/- reported by the Bushire Residency. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Tour most obedient servant, £&gt; • N. Bhat tachar yya • 'T* Assistant Accounts Officer, Central Re v fcnues. Copy sent to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, under P.L.No. 1683 dated the 25th September 1939 for favour of necessary action. rtf'// (o*t GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depabtwsnt, EXPRESS LETTER [iV. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegrap hie expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] th* 19th September 1939 and to the Residency Surgeon's inspection report on the Dibai Dispensary (copies enclosed for ready reference)• Surgeon: it is to be remembered that volunteers were called for for the Dibai Dispensary, and Jemadar Nur Ahmad knew perfectly well what pay he would receive and how it would compare with his previous emoluments* He can, therefore, have no complaint on this score* Nevertheless, as it is clearly desirable that some quarantine work should be done on the Trucial Coast (since this was one of the main objects in view in obtaining sanction for the creation of the post) I recommend that he be now instructed to undertake quarantine duty roughly on the lines followed in Bahrain,] and that for this task he be paid Quarantine Allowance of fc. 26/- From Political Agent Bahrain* Political Resident Camp Bahrain* No. 1680-4/4 Bated 25th September HQ . Please refer to your Express Letter Ho. 1285-14/226 dated —J 2. In regard to the pay and allowances of the Sub-Assistant rf I I S. 6. MFP—1190 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000. per mensem/ : 1 /I- 2 - per mensem. Funds for the payment of a quarantine allowance exist in the budget for the current year and provision ha3 also been made in the Budget estimates for 1940/1941. Furthermore, with reference to paragraph (d) of the Residency Surgeon’s report, I see no objection to the Sub-Assistant Surgeon being permitted to make his own arrangements with Imperial Airways Limited and Messrs. Gray, Mackensie and Company Limited for a monthly fee for private attendance on their employees. 3* In regard to the compounder: fresh efforts are being made to find a suitable man in Bahrain to be sent to Dibai and I will report later whether these efforts are successful. If we can find a good man, it may be possible for him to carry out the duties of compounder as well as dresser. Provision for a compounder at Rs. 40/- per mensem, and a dresser at Rs. 25/- per mensem, has been made in the Budget estimates for the ensuing year and I recommend that this be allowed to stand for the time being. I see many objections to importing a compounder from India. Assistant Surgeon has so far received drugs etcetera, to the value of Rs. 731/5/- and a supplementary indent has been forwarded by the Residency Surgeon to carry over this year. This supplementary indent will involve an expenditure of between Rs. 650/- and Rs. 700/-. After consultation with the Residency Surgeon a sum of Rs. 1,500/- has been provided under this head for the ensuing year. Whether any reduction can be taken in this figure in subsequent years remains to be seen. current year’s estimates will be about fts. 700/-, and I am passing on this information to the Secretary by telegram equipment • The Sub- The anticipated excess under this head in the as requested/ ^ - 1 —as requested in paragraph 1 of the Express Letter under reference* 5* There is no provision for contingencies in the current year*s budget and an excess *ill occur on this account of roughly fts. 100/*-. fts. 300/- have been proposed as a minimum sum for future years. Sd/- H. Weightman Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested i ^ V Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. V 6Telegram From Political, Bahrain To - Britconsul, Bushire No. - 197 Dated the 25th September 1939. Your Express Letter No. 1285 of 19th September paragraph 1. Anticipated excess drugs etcetera Rs. 700/- hospital contingencies Rs. 100/-. POLITICAL -K M - No. IU° -4/4. -v »?. I ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, November l^L,, 1939. *N r To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire. Memorandum . Reference your endorsement No.750-60/23 dated the 4th April 1936. I enclose herewith a statement of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants for the year 1939-40. for Political Agent, Bahrain.GTG Britconsul, Bushire Political, Bahrain 201 Dated and received 18th November 1939. 2 &gt; 2 . Please telegraph immediately your figures of excess and savings for the current year. - BRITCONSUL -GTC Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire 270 Dated the 19th November 1939. Your telegram No. 201 of 18th November Statement posted Bankura. - POLITICAL -British Residency and Consulate-General, e Bushire, the 28th Noyi*. 19 39 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, ' The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khurramshahr, for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement No. 2083-60/21 dated the 1st DecemberiQ 38 By order, for Secretary to blitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the Bbct. Affairs Department No. F. 9(77 )-E/ dated the 30th Octr. 19 39 • 38 (Received with External Affair Department endorsement No. dated the 19 .) MGIPC—S5—163 Pol Res Bushire—10-1-39—2,500.Frcm To The Under Secretary to the Government of India m t.ie External .iffai.re*Departaent, Hi- - 5 _ 4 +„ ■ ■ oe-.iO m the rersjar. Gulf, Hio -r.taanic kajesty's Eonsul-G-neral for i^orasar, The Political Officer in si iv-. n Tne Resident in Kashnir (for Lri: •-it • , Th03 counsellor, British LegationT Kabul, 1S RR', ar, + 1 t ta o eSt5, ' S - KVOy Extraordinary and ih.iioter Flenipoten- T’O {.0 “ nS Court of Kepal, Kathmandu. His Britei 9 - th , e Reideut for the Punjab States (for Gartok), ' th3 ——1-^nts Memorandun No.- F.9( 77)-u/36. Dated New Delhi, the 30th October liis. oupject.- Jill.i.ng up of permanent and temporarv vacancies *a 'o-t- tne 003t of '- 7hi ' h is borne by the Central Revenues.' ' Reference this Department memorandum No. F.9(77)-i,/3&amp;, dated ..i,e 5th November 193 8.. : ^ ° Although tne need i or ecocor'' T f t ^ •?&gt;.. vo/o irr^. j economy is m no way decreased by the out- hostilities, 1 . as reougnasad that the maintenance of full establie ment strength may be of paramount importance, particularly in those offices where the v,a- is already imposing a heavy burden of extra work. The necos • sity ioi ro^c-xing the oroers containod in parsgrarh 2 '-f fhp ^ ox tne s.oov^ memoranda. has already been recognised in oasas ./&gt; o-re - -or ^ •’ . t • r ^S^- application would be seriously detrimental to efficiency. The Government of India, while cor- sidering the retention of th.ee orders desirable, have now been pleased to delegate to you the power to relax the orders contained in paragraphs 2&lt;l)( a ; and 2U)(b) of the memorandum in cases where the filling up of a vacancy is considered essential in the interest of efficiency. This authorisation is subject however to the condition that the extra expenditure involved is met from within your sanctioned budget grant .as a whole but if this condition cannot be fulfilled a prior reference to the Government of India should Jt made. In order, however, to avoid supplementary allotments as far as possible, uhe Government of India desire that each ease of relaxation should bo carefully scrutinised on that the of ^ ^ ^ x rtric a r? x- c ~ ■ ■ v ' r y -. c reduced to a minimum. X. V* v /cc .^-1 Under Secretary to the Government of India,No. 1650-B. P.39-40. British Residency and Consulate-General, t t? fCL Bushire, thelBth December 1939 Re*. P, G. 32. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khurramshahr, for information and guidance with reference to -this office endorsement. No. JK 2197 , dated the 20th December^ 39 . /or Secretary to the Pohtical Resident in the Persian Gulf. Circular Lctto from the Government-of India in the Finance Department N°.d. 4512-B » dated the 7 th Hot. 19 39 • (Received with External Afiair Department endorsement No- p.265-A/39 date&lt; i the 27th (?) Hot. 19 39 d MGIPC—S3—163 Pol ResBushire—10-1-39—2,500./ '*0 No .D-4512-B. Government of India, finance Department. New Delhi, the 7th November 1939. from H. 4. G. Gill, Esquire, I.O.S., 1 . Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, . „ To All Provincial Governments and the Chief Commissioner, Goorg. Subject.-* Revised Estimates 1939-40 and Budget Estimates 1940-41 - Rate of Exchange. — —i Sir, I am directed to inform you that the Government of India have decided to assume an average rate of exchange of Ish. 5 15/l6d. for the purpose of the Revised Estimates 1939-40 and Ish. 6d. for the Budget Estimates 1940-41. I have the honour to he, . „ Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. No.D-4512-B. Copy forwarded to all Departments of the Government of the Political Department, India,/tiie financial adviser, Military finance, the finance Officer, Communications, the Grown finance Officer, the Central Board of Revenue, the Auditcr-General of India, the Accountant-General, India Office, the Chief Accounting Officer to the High Commissioner for India, the Auditor, Indian Home Accounts, the Accountant-General, Posts and Telegraphs, the Controller of Railway Accounts, the Military Accountant-General, all Civil Accountants-General and Comptrollers, the Chief Auditor Indian Stores Department, the Mint Masters and the Master/Dated the 18th December 1^39 To The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain*^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman. His Majesty’s Consul,Bandar Abbas. His Majesty’s Consul, Shiraz. His Majesty’s Vice Consul,Khorramshahr. A statement showing the alterations made in your budget grants foi 1939-40 is attached for your Memorandum information By Order Secietaij^to the Political Resident in the Persian 3ulf.210 - 4/4 No. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Secretary to the Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, . Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf ^ atecl --the 1st February-1940. Reference to previous correspondence; Bushire endorsement No.750 dated the 4th April 1956. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. statement showing anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants for the year j 939-40.S) No.-^f /60/23 of 1940. t The Seeietaiy to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). . T* * C ■ v} v ^ n. ^ y —v British Consulate-General, ^ H \ ■'&lt;; BU SHIRE. Dated. . .’f. A40 • Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No.53/60/23 dated Budget Estimates 1940-41. the 18th January, 1940, with enclosure addressed to the Secretary Oovt of India,.E.xternal Affairs Department,New Delhi. 2. Govt of India Mem o. No . 325-A /39 dated the 12th December, 1939.From The Hon f, ole the Political xiesident in the Persian (}ulf, Busnire. To The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Memorandum No.53/60/23 of 1140. Dated Bushire, the 18th January, 1940. Budget Estimates, 1940-41 . Reference your memorandum No.F.325-A/39, dated the 12th December, 1939. 2# 1 forward, herewith, reappropriation statement No.5 for the information of the Government of India. 3• A copy of this memorandum is oeing forwarded to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. sd. A.C.Stewart for Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf._ From To No.0/6694-3. oov^mmn: of India. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. ill Now Delhi, the Ofc December 1939. H.A.C.Glll, Esquire, I.C.S., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, The Accountant General, Central Revenues. u Subject*-Budget estimates - 1940-41 - 36 External Affairs - Persian Gulf Residency. Sir, In continuation of my letter No.D/4972-B., dated the 30th November 1939 I am directed to state that the Government of India have decided to make the following further modifications in Part I of the above estimates 2 - Bah.ra.ija.,,, B.-Charges on account of diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran i B.2.-Pay of Establishments - Medical Establishment 4-2,800 B.3.-Allowances, Honoraria, etc- Travelling allowance 4-400 B. 4.-Contingencies - Hospital Contingencies and Medical equipment 4-1,600 G.-Othar diplomatic and arteH nl qtratlvo Charges - C. 2- Pay of Establishmenus -2,800 y C.3- Allowances, Honorariun - Travelling allowance -400 y C.4- Contingencies - Medical and Hospital Contingencies -100 Cost of Medical equipment and supply of drugs -1,600 I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, H.A.C.Gill Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. No •D/5594-B. Copy in triplicate forwarded to the External Affairs Department. By order, etc•, / A / M-V.Rangachari for Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. 'J 1 ?No. ^7^ /60/23 of 1940. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political -^gent, Bah rain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..J.fh^. 1 ?* 1 .’.. 1340 - Reference to previous correspondence : Lu*/ SHjbij xi, , Description of Enclosure. y~~v J) ‘f Vtf. Name and Date Subject.No.370-4/4 © /V£&gt; I'olitic-’l ^gency f Bahrain* 36th February f 1940. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Heeident in the Persian Gulf f jrahHau, rvNmorandim * Reference my Printed Letter !To*210-^/4 dated the 1st February t 1940* 2* A book debit for the sun of Rs.964/- has been raised against this Agency under 'cost of passages under Superior Civil Services rules N.V.' by the Accountant General, Certral Revenues, New i&gt;elhl* it is therefore requested that the necessary provision for this amount may please be made in th*&gt; budget grant for the current financial year* IA for Political Agent, Bahrain* ^ of cNo. JLtfk /60/HS of 1940 To Biitish Consulate-General, Bushire, the 2nd liarch, 1940. J The Political Agent, Bahrain. / The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty*s Consul, Kerman. His Majesty* s Consul, Bandar Abbas. His Majesty*s Vice Consul,Khorramshahr. Memo randum. In continuation of this office memorandum o.1064/60/25, dated the 18th December, 1949, I enclose ior .your iniormation and guidance a statement of further modifications in appropriations for the year 1959-40. By order, in the Persian Gulf. /il f/60/23 of 1940. No. The Secretary to the Hon’ble presents his compliments to the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf The Political Agent, Bahiain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 9th Maich, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence d Bushiie piinted letter No.274/60/23 dated the 1st ^arch, 1940. 4 Description of Enclosure.°\/ No. 4 / 4 / 60/23 of 1940. / i 6 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Ban lain and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. March, 1940. Dated... Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain telegram No.79 dated the 26th March, 1940. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. memorandum No. 4*/3/60/23, dated Reapproprition of funds, the 29th M arch, 1940, to the Govt of India, New ^elhi, with enclo suie. / 7 1 \Re$. P&gt; G. 32. IP uV' No. 1&gt;S1 -B.F .ly40-41. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, the 14tii -M^y . 1940 T'ST”' ( A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Khurramshahr, for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement , dated the By order, . for Secretar^fo the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the No. , dated the 19 Department Statement showing the detailed distribution of the appropriation under External Affairs for 1940-41. Department endorsement-0.1213-4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain. 23rd June 1940. Prom The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Heaidant in the Persian Gulf C specific instructions as to the natui*e of expenditure adjust- ible tinier iteos ho .3 and 9 of the statement of Special War time expenditure, forwarded with your iixpress-Letter No. 1297- 79/53 dated t&gt;ie 22nd September 1939, it was preeuraed thet both these allotments were intended to meet expenditure on travelling allowance and office expenses incurred by this Agency for war purposes and especially hy the Fo iticnl Officer, Trucial Coast, nharjah, who, obviously lias to tour extensively and to maintain an office. The following expenditure has therefore been incurred and debited to His Majesty’s Government under 'Special War - time Expenditure' incurred in connection with ) the transportation of mails ) 435- 9 268-14 704 - 7 from the Post Office to Agency) and back for censor,the item ) 2 (b) referred to in my ) Memorandum No .1208/4/2 dated ) the 22nd June 1940) ) (item No.9) ; Captain Metcalfe informs me however, that it is clear (item No.8) Office Expenses (includes ) among other miscellaneous ) expenditure i.e. expenses ) from,&lt; 0 fixAj- from the Bushir^ Heaidenoy records that these grants ^Pe fcr the Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and this appears correct from India Office telegram Wo*2762 dated the 4th «Ame 1940 and correspondence resting with India Offic«itelegram Wo*2789 dated the 7th June 1940. further, no provision for travelling allowance and office expenses of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, exists in the printed statement of the sanctioned Budget grants forwarded with your endorsement Wo .667/3 .F. dated the 21st Way 1940* 4 # It is suggested that funds equal to those originally provided for the Publicity officer, Persian Gulf, i.e. approximately te.2,500/- for travelling allowance and &amp;.1,300/- for office allowance be sanctioned. ^ ' I have the honour to be, bir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Af?cnt, Bahrain./&lt; for Political Agent, Bahrain. No. -4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, July 14, 1940. To The Secretary to the ^on’ble the Political iV e&amp;ident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandu m. Reference your endorsement No. 750-60/23 dated the 4th Aoril 1936. 2. I enclose a statement showing grants,expenditure, etcetera for the year 1939-40.Wo.1394-4/4 4^ y Office of the Publicity officer, rereiun uulf, Bahrein* S3rd July, 1940* Fle*ee refer to letter Ko*1213&lt;-4/4 doted 23rd JUne 1940 from Political Agent, Bahrain, regardiiig adjust*- nent of special War Expenditure* 2* an early reply would be couch appreciated aa the Publicity office accounts are already very muddled and also unnecessarily depleted by the Inclusion of debits which are not a legitimate charge upon them e*g* pay of fhrashes on the Truclal Coast expenses on censorship etc* X» this connsction a reference is invited to paragraph 2 (b) of my demi-official ITo.l-a/25 of 9th May 1940. 3 , I am keeping my own private accounts as a chock but until the situation is officially clarified, the Agency Accountant is unable to amend his records* Yours sincerely, To Captain A* C* Stewart, I*A* Political Heeldent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire*From Th* Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Perei&amp;ja Gulf, Bush!re The Secretary to the Government of India, internal Affaire department, Siiale Memorandum Bated the 24th July, 1940. 41 H Adjust^ient of experd iture in connection with publicity ar rangements in the Persian Gulf Reference the oorreepondenoe ending with this ieai- dency’s Kxprees Letter No.952-79/63/6 dated the 24th July, 1940, 2 . Prior to the appointment of a full-time Publicity Officer for the Persian Gulf with eifect from the 17th April, 1940, the preliminary work in connection with the publicity ■ohern* »«• p«i'fonaed by the PoliticaX A«e n t t Strain, aviated by the Political Officer, Truoial Coast. 3. Ihe Political /.gent, Bahrain, now reports that the following expenditure has been incurred by him and by the Poli tical Officer, TrucUl Coast, and decited to His Majesty^ Government a.-inet the grente of £.300/- and £.100/. ..motioned lor ftaveiling AlloMano. and Olfloe Kxpensea respectively, vide items 8 and 9 of the Statement accompanying this Hesidency's Express Letter No.l297-?9/S3, dated the 22nd September 1939. Grant jgxpsnd iture Expenditui e: ln__ 1939-40. in 1940-41^ 2s. As. Ps # 2 s. A a# jp B Total in 1940-41 (1) Travelling Allowance £.200/- 3383. 12. 0. 247. 8. 0. 2s. Aa. Pa ^631. 4. 0 (2) Office iitxpenses £.100/- 435. 9. 0. 268. 14. 0. 704. 7. 04. /7^ A copy ox this memorandum ie toeing forwarded to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, flue Delhi, i Cfcpy to:- 1. The Accountant General, Central Revenaes, New Delhi. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, nl Dbpartmbnt, EXPRESS LETTER [N % B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGF y sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wirts y but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition (u if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,) From Britoonsol y Buahiro. To ?oreigii 9 «i jsJLii* 952 *79/65/5• Dated Bu6h.ire t tho 24th ^uiy 1940* Adjuotneiit oZ oxpondituro in oonneetion with publicity a r rung aments in the Perslm Gulf. Reference Express Letter Ho»y*72~A/39 t dated the 11th June t 194C» from the GorenuBent of India in the External Affairs Department* 2* The sum of £ 200/- sanctioned by the Secretary of State in his telegram No. 1568, dated the 21st August 1939 was intended to cover the travelling expenses of officers and staff employed on duties connected with publicity in the Persian Gulf* The amount is identical with item 8 of the statement forwarded with this Resi dency’s Express Letter Bo. 1297/79/53, dated the 22nd September 1939, and the expenditure is to be borne entirely by His Majesty’s Govern ment. 3* Ths charges which arc to be borne entirely by His Majesty’ S. 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P-(M-2339)—25-5-37—300,000. /GovernmentV Grorernment have hitkerto bean shown, in the monthly accounts sent bj the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, as dsbitable to His Majesty’s Government, and it is presumed that the Accountant General, Central Revenues, passes on the debits to His Majesty's Government as they arise. Provision for expenditure in connection with publicity arrangements in the Persian Gulf for the last financial year was made by His Majesty's Govern ment, vide the Secretary of State's telegram Ho. 1365, dated the 22nd August 1939, aad it is presumed that similar provision . has been made in the current year. Ho steps have accordingly been taken to provide funds for the purpose in the Indian budget. Bssuner The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy to:- 1. The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. JI' V To i!*‘jTfi.sk wfi»Aj© w i JSk - *.* £ v Dated the 13th August 1940 £ !% MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No.1341-4/4 dated the 14th July 1940. 2. Please furnish figures of grants, expenditure, etc., under 'N-Special War Expenditure”. By order.No * l(r)2&gt; _4 /4 Political Agency, Bahrain, 4th September 1940. T*' I*? To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No. 1047/60/23, dated the 13th August 1940. 2 * ^ enclose a statement showing grants, expenditure, etcetra for the year 1939-40 under N-Special ^ar Expenditure. for Political Agent, Bahrain.V No. n(fl -4/4 Political Agency, Bahrain, September 17, 1940* To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident i in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* T Ht Memorandum * I enclose ,in triplicate, the statements of Contract and fixed Grants for the year 1939-40* / A for Political Agent, Bahrain* kTelegram GTC. From Political , Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire. No.269 Dated 22nd September, 1940. Your A/331 September 22nd. Statement posted September 17th via Basra.Telegram From To No.273 GfTC. Folitical, Bahrain. Britdonsul, Bushire Dated 29th September, 1940. li Your telegram No .A/337, estimates first posted August 27th were received back September 14th. Reposted via Basra September 17th.TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE. IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Printed in England. Sept. 1938.(15,559. pads.) 5/-47E. CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) (11 G' To Name Address POLITICAL MUSCAT BaLaM Your memorandum 750 fourth April 1936 stop Actual expenditure upto 30th September pay of officers rupees 28606 pay of establishment 11527 sumptuaryallowance 600 travelling allowance 3925 house rent 2453 launch grant 3173 central contract grant 277 rent buildings 675 postage telegram /•**• ct* “ges 9790 office allowance 6353 secret expenditure 300 stop Dubai Dispensary pay of establisnment 703 travelling allowance 305 contingencies 82 stop estimated expenditure for remaining six months under fox-ementioned fifteen heads 27003 11315 600 6075 2370 300 5827 1022 945 8000 9947 unknown 2270 500 1500 stop special war expenditure political officer 2580 interpreter 1800 house rent 424 travelling allowance political officer 669 language rewards 900 estimated expenditure ior remaining six I request that the above Telegram may be forwarded subject to the conditions printed on back of this form by which I agree to be bound. Signature and Address of Sender (Not to be telegraphed) P.T O.CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants ^ shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International j \ Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches.TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk's Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. Instructions w. ' . Time to be Words Signalled. To Name Address page a months unaer five forementioned heads of war expenditure 6700 1800 840 unknown nil stop newpara reference para four my letter 10^3 Jxne 23rd anticipate 500 under office allowance for remaining six months, stop. copy by post. POLITICAL 1-7/ r \ I request that the above Telegram may be forwarded subject to the conditions printed on back of t^is form by which I agree to be bound. Signature and Address of Sender — (Not to be telegraphed) ' l P.T O.1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International ✓ N \ Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches.f °l G ! No. 1863-4-4 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Secretary to the Hon'b’e the Political lie sj dent in the Persian Gulf, ^ushire • ^ and has the honour to send him a copy 0 f the undermentioned document {4 ) / confirmation. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated . Qctpber , 19^.Q. a Refenence to previous correspondence: In continuation of this office telegram Wo. 279 dated 3rd Descnpl'idn Of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Telegram No.379 dated 3rd October, 1940, fro Political Bahrain, to Britconsul, Bushi re. ar&gt; ' iv - ■ •••. i\ k ■ 1940.Telegram Prom Enclair Political Bahrain To Brltconsul Buahire No.279 dated the 3rd October 1940. 2 . 3. 4. Your memorandum No.760 dated the 4th April 1936. Actual expenditure up to 30th Septemberi- Pay of Officers Pay of Establishment ^ Cost of passages Sumptuary allowance Travelling allowance J House Rent Reward Language \ Launch Grant „ Central Contract Grant v Rent Buildings i Postage and Telegram Charges ,, Office Allowance Secret Expenditure Grants in aid Rupees 28 t 606 11,627 nil 600 3,926 2,463 nil 3,173 277 / 676 9,790 6,363 300 nil 1X J H A. I DISP lISAro y Pay of establishment 703 Travelling allowance ^ 306 Contingencies 82 Estimated expenditure for the remaining six months Pay of officers Pay of establishment Cost of passage Sumptuary allowance Travelling allowance v House Rent v Reward Language Launch Grant ^ Central Contract Grant Rent Buildings v Postage and telegram charges Office Allowance Secret expenditure Grant in aid Rupees y 27,003 11,316 unknown 600 6,076 2,370 300 6,827 1,022 945 8,000 9,947 unknown unknown EPBAI DISPPiNSARY * Pay of establiailment Travelling Allowance Contingencies 2,270 600 is,Qoe» l SPECIAL WAR EXPENDITURE Actual expenditiure upto 30th September Political Officer Rupees 2,580 Interpreter 1,800 House Rent 424 Travelling Allowance Pol.Officer 669 Reward language 900 Contingencies nil anticipated expenditure for remaining six months Political Officer 6,700 Interpreter 1,800 House Rent 840 ' Travelling allowance Pol.Offleer unknown Reward language nil Contingencies 600 - Political-NO. -60/23. Dated the 25th September 1940. MEMORANDUM To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference your memorandum No.1673-4/4, dated the 7th September 1940 2 The figure of expenditure under ”N-3 - Allowances, Honoraria, etc., — Travelling Allowance' shown in the statement accompanying your memorandum under reference is Rs. 3,772-0-0, whereas the figure shown in your ErForm state compiled by the Accountant General, Central Revenues, and accepted by this office, the total expenditure under M N-3- Allowances, Honoraria, etc.' is Ss.4,065-11-0, presumably made up as follows:- The expenditure of Rs.3,383-12-0 under 'Travelling Allowance' has apparently been debited by the Accountant General, Central Revenues, to the Indian budget and not to Foreign Office, as noted in the statement accompanying your memorandum under reply ^* Please reconcile the discrepancy or amend your figures under intimation to this office. By order, ment for March 1940 is Rs. 3,383-12-0. 3 In the draft appropriation accounts for 1939-40 House Rent Rs. 681. 15. 0. ie 3383. 12. 0 . Ji Rs. 4065. 11. 0. Travelling Allowance Total Rs ior Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfNo.1900-4/4 2 S Political Agency, BahTnln. 9th Cctc ber, i (HO* To The Secretary to the Hon’ble *cha Political Rfigivlent in the Persian Gulf, ITeraorandu ia^ Reference your Memoranduia No*1195-60/23 dated the 25th Septemoer 1940• 2 . TUe correct fir ire for expenditure under rt N*3~Allo\vanceg, Honoraria etc - ''ravel: aing Allow ance” Is Bs •3773/- aa reported in ly :ernor^ndun No*1673-4/4 dated the 7th September 1940* The difference of ils*389/4/- relates t tne Travelling AllOA’ancs hill of Captain J*3. Howes, Political Officer, Trucicil Coast, for the month of February 1940, as Intimated by the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, in his No.TAIO-1-435 dated 25th June 1940* / La for Political Agent, Bahrain. kDEPARTMENT, V BRANCH. File No. Scriai No. Draft L etter Memorandum Telegram INLAND i Immediate Class for telegrams important Express Ordinary To he issued on 1 st Reminder 2 nd Reminder 3rd ^minder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures FOREIGN i Immedia te Important Ordina ry Without priority Issued on Telegram En clair. 10 From Political, Bahrain# To Britconsul, Bushire# No.309 Dated 5th November, 1940# Ztxxxxjcxxxxxxxxjcxx . # New -oara) Anticipated savings. Pay of Political Agent Rs.144, Asst. Pol.Agent 300. Cost of passages 1000 Pay of S.A.S. &amp; Dubai 732.War Establishment. Censor ship Clerk (vacant) 1900 Pay of Political Officer Trucial Coast 32 3520 House Rent Censorshin Clerk 400 (Code word for telegrams.) [House rent Pol. Officer Trucial Coast 436. Total anticipated savings Rs. 8432. Anticipated excesses. Pay of Asstt. Surgeon 3153 Indian Assistant 2158 Pay of Clerks 183 House Rent( 0.3. Allowances Honoraria) 228 Rent of [Buildings 20 Postage and telegram Charges 8518 Pay of Dubai Dispenser etc 85 B.3 Travelling allowance Medical [Officer Dubai 907 War Establishment. Contingencies- Transport of mails for censor 200 Total excesses Rs.15452. Detailed statement by post. In. c 5. 5. MGIPC—S5—1TC3 (S&amp;P)MFP—(M-1394'—21D*39 -SO,000 Pad*. PolPolitical Agency, &lt;tto 20 Bahrain, November 7, 1940. lo The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. M emorandum . 1940. 2 . In continuativon of my telegram No. 309 of 5th November I enclose herewith statements of anticipated excesses and savings in the Budget grants for the year 1940-41. / U, fw Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 k(jsj; i No. /3^4 -B.F.41-42. Dated the lat November 1940. b** To The Political Agent, Bahrain. n&gt; MEMORANDUM Reference paragraph 3 of your letter No.1597-4/4 dated the 25th August 1940. 2. Expenditure on travelling allowance and office expenses of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, may be incurred and debited ,, L-3-Allo'.vances, Honoraria, etc. H and ”L-4-Contingencies’ 1 respectively. 3. The sanction of the Government of India to the expenditure will be applied for and funds provided on receipt of your report of excesses and savings for the current year. By order, Copy sent to P.O. T.C dated 13th November, Sharjah, under P.L. 1940, for information. No.2124-4/4J\x. &lt;r&gt;c , I enclose a copy of my ^telegram lio.621 dated ^ c . x,h ilo ember 1940 to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident i n Persian Gulf together with a co &gt;y of his reply No .A. 397 dated the 14th November 1940. ^* 1 understand tnat the expanses of the Residency Agent and my Office are borne by Bushire and, therefore, the only personal expenditure that I anticipate will be on Travelling and a sum of Rs.3,000/- may kindly be alioted under this head for the remainder of this financial year. This estimate excludes my Travelling Allowance from Karachi on return from leave and my transfer Travelling Allowance from Bahrain to Sharjah.Copy of Lele ram Ho.621 dated. ( Jtli no yember 1940 fi*om the roliLical ^f ‘leer,Trueiul Coasx, to uhe Secretary zo the hon'ble the lolitical -iesiaent in the Persian Gulf,Bushire. Ho records are available in this office regarding the iinanees of my post. Please send me urgently copy of my sanct ioned budget'for this year or if this is not available kindly indicate how much I can spend on touring, Office expenses, etc. Copy of oeleg-am !!o.A.3S7 dated 14th November 1940 from the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Hesiuent in the Persian Gulf oo the Political Officer,Trueial Coast. Your telegram No.621 November 10th# Only provision made in sanctioned budget for current year is pay of Officers rupees 12,000, house allowance 1,200/- Anticipated excess under these heads and any other airoicipated expenditure should be telegraphed to Political ^gent,Bahrain, so that provision cane be made in Bahrain Budget#Pc' 1 -* ricr ' rfficer, Trucial Coast, 7&gt;.0. No.2255-4/4 Z/ O )a ued 4kth December, 1940. Please refer to your demi-official Ko •631-1/6 dated the ISth November, 194b• 2 * v'e &gt;iaci realised the necessity for fords under “ravelling Allowance and Office Allowance for you c^d had applied for Hs• 1*500/ and tLi«1300/- respectively un ier these heads. 1 copy of the sanction order received was sent to yr.u iindo 1 ny Printed Letter No.2124-4/4 of 13th 'overher 3ast. 3. A of approximately io.lOCC/- is still available ur.der Travel'’ing Allowance and if your leave is sanctioned there will still be a balance a ter your Travelling Allowance to India and back has been paid. Any anticipated excesses cr ravings nay be reported tc ne by the 1st ^etraai’y next eo ti^at I roay include the figures in my next financial re vie,;. In vie; of the general sanction contained in paragraph 2 of Memorandum ??o • 13n4-B.F.41-42 dated 1st Kovrutber 1940 from tne iecrotary to the Non 1 ble the Political Resident I do net anticipate any difficulty in cashing your Travelling Allowance Bills bc.’ore the sanction of the Government of India has been received. 4. Expenditure incurred by Hesidency .\gent, Sharjah only is borne by Eachire. Yours sinc e roly, Captain 1&gt; . 3* T^etcalfe, I.A.,* 3i * I enclose for your information and guidance a statement showing the modifications in the budget appro priations for the year 1940-41. 2. No provision is being made in the Indian portion of the budget to meet expenditure in connection with publi city arrangements in the Persian Gulf. By order, No. J ? -60/23. Bushire. Dated the/^T^ December 1940 To The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty*s Consul, Kerman ‘ His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Bandar Abbas His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr in the Persian Gulf.(Z€^; zty^ Telegram en clair. Political, Bahrain. Officer-in-Charge, Medical Store Depot, Bombay. Dated 17th January, 1941. Please telegraph total cost of drugs supplied since April last for Victoria Memorial Hospital Bahrain and Government dispensary Dubai each separately debitable to current financial years'budget. From To No. 17— r — Telegram - Enclair, Prom - Political Agent, Bahrain, To - Secretary, Bush ire. No. - 35. Dated the 4th February, 1941. ANTICIPATED S AVINGS . Pay of establishment 95. 336 Kent of buildings It 200 Grants-in~aid M Total Savings it 1156 ANTICIPATED EXCESSES Pay of officers II 1000 S umptuary allowance It 300 Travelling allowance It 3600 Reward of languages It 300 Cost of passages Total Excesses II JOiO DUBAI DISPENSARY. ANTICIPATED SAVINGS Pay of establishment II 190 Travelling allowance ♦l -2m Total S avings. II 490 EXCESSES NIL SPECIAL WAR CHARGES. ANTICIPATED SAVINGS. L.l.Pay of officers ANTICIPATED EXCESSES. It 500.Telegram • • • • G.T.C. From Political Officer Trucial Coast. To Political Bahrain. No. 121 l^ated the 5th February 1941. Travelling Allowance. What is my credit balance ? PoliticalTelegram GTC. 2-IY Prom Political, Bahrain. Political, Sharjah. No .40 Dated 8th February, 1941. Your telegram 121. Total expenditure up to date is fis.2879/-. 7e have applied for another 800 till 31st March. There is no fixed allotmentV ■■■I No. Zs'i?- 2i^ The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the ttndirmentioneidocument (s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 9th February 1°41. Reference to previous correspondence: ^ushire endoraeraent No. 750 dated the 4th Anril 1956. Descnplidn dj Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Statenient showing anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants for the year 1940-41. CThe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf t Buahir$. To Th^ Secretary to the of India A. • External Affairs Department, No* Delhi. Memorandum No.166-14/226 ) f^\] Dated the 6th February 1941. ) SUBJECT : Medical arranger-ents on the Truciai Coast Reference correspondence ending with memorandum No. F.325-A/40, dated the 20th December 1940, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. 2. In view of the great increase in the daily attendance at the dispensary at Dubai, I consider that a minimum annual grant of lb. 1,300/- for the purchase of drugs and lb. 300/- for | contingencies such as sweepia- and lighting, e tc., will be required for the next year; it is anticipated that for subse quent years a further increase in the allotment for the cost .of drugs will be necessary. for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf / Copy, for information, to the Political Agent, Bahrain.SECRET• GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER f ' 'P —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the mres, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it- is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] From Rtiidant, Buuhirt. To Political Agant, Bahrain* L No. 687-S of 1940. Dated tha 20 th Daoanbar 193A0* Refaranca your talegram Ko: 449 dated tha 10 th i&gt;acanjbar, % 1940. 2. A grant of Ra. 3000/~ for Sacrat Sarrica axpanditura during tha currant financial year ia aanctioned, and your iropoeals ara approyad. Sd. C. G. Prior, Political ^asident in tha Peroian Gulf. Copy to -rraaeury Officer, Buahire, for information. S. 6. MFP—1196 SAP—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.No. 237 - 64/5. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents for information. British Residency and (’onsulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ..IBth^Pe bruary 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. GC51-76-5310 dated the 23rd January 1941 from ’-he Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, with enclosure. Capt. H.D.H. Ranee(Copy of letter No. NO 51-76-5310 dated the 23rd January 1941 from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, to the secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.) Ca-ptain N.D. PL R a nee uviioi ui iviiiioary Accoimts, n.a Comand, Leerut, I have the honour to state that the debit of '7 ' mentioned therein has since been passed on to this office oy .ne Controller of iiilitary Accounts, Northern Command in his Account icr September 1940 ana is being adjusted in this office Accbunt as follows:- 35 -external Affairs Department - Other Diplomatic and .^^ministration Changes - Bahrain - Pay of Officers (?,o.D) N./. - is.78/2/- House Rent and Other All owanc e s - Rs. 70/15/- It is requested that necessary funds may please be provided in the budget estimates for the current year. Please acknowledge receipt of this letter. and a copy to this office.) Subject : Pay and Allowances - British Officers. from Rawalpindi, Meerut, A sum of Pi. 141/5/- (as per details account of difference of nay Q f A%iy @ fc. 650/- p.m. /erseas Pay TPs. 150/- n.m. Compensatory allowance Ks.lOO/- p.m. TiTPOO/-— TRtal - IST^OO/- p.m: Less amounts already paid for the period mentioned. (i) as transit pay 9 Fs.630/- o.m. &amp; Ui) familx_allnce l,,j F? 60/- km, S.6$0/- r.m.Total - FsTSSOT 1 p.m. Difference @ Be. from 11/12/39 to 1/1/40 Debits Pay as A/Capt. from 24/1 to 27/1/40 d i sal 1 owed Ps. 7/12/- Net amount - * Fs. 210/- Fs. 149/1/-” to you with this office 1/3209, dated 11-4' may please be compiled to Code 1/108/01 by noted in the margin) on rom 11-12/39 to 1-1/40 vide Accountant General, Cen f ral Revenues, Nev Delhi. No. GC-51/76-1436, dated 26-6-40 is dde to Cant. H.D.H. Ranee, 2/lst (l.R., at present attached to 1 st Nepalese brigade Dehra Dun and may please be paid to him after deducting income-tax at the appropriate rate. Debit for Rs. 149/1/- may please be raised against the A.G., C.R., tx kxx New Delhi, citing reference to his communi cation quoted above. The duplicate copy of the L.P. of the o'ficer was forward •40. The sum of Ps. 7/12/- deduction. (D o.Political Agency Bahrain, let March, 1941 Prom The Political Agent Bahrain. To The Accountant-General, Central Revenues New Delhi. Sir I have the honour to refer to this Treasury Voucher No.29 for the month of January, 1941; and to inform you that according to instructions now received from the .-ton'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, the sum of Rs.3,000/- is being adjusted under 'Bushire B-5-Secret Expenditure'. It is, therefore, requested that the Bahrain 'E' Form for January, 1941; may kindly be amended accordingly. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram - I.W.C. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Accounts, Mew Delhi. Mo. - 53. Dated the 4th March, 1941. &gt;i 'i £ 5 &gt; Grateful if provisional salary slip for Captain Metcalfe, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, is sent to me by air mail to enable me to adjust accounts before March 31st -POLITICAL-■ESH Telegram From To No. GTC. Political Agent, Bahrain. Secretary, Bushire. 54. Bated the 4th March, 1941. My telegram No.35, dated the 4th February, 1941. I anticipate a saving of Hs.2500/- under* Postage &amp; Telegram Charges and a further saving of ;is.l33/- under Bent of Buildings. -POLITICAL-No.326 - 60/23. British Consulate General, Bushire. Dated the 6th March, 1941. To The Political Agent, Muscat ( The Political Agent, Bahrain^ V The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty's Consul, Kerman His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr MEHORMDIM I enclose for your information ajjd guidance a statement showing the final modifications in the budget appropriations for 1940-41. By order 2^ Secretary tothe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram - GTC. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No. - 63. Dated the 12th Tiarch, 1941. Your memorandum No .326-60/23, dated the 6th March, 1941. Budget. (a) Revised grant under Postage and Telegram charges is as.21,500 and not 13,000 (please see your No.1513-60/23, dated the 15th December). (b) Book debits for Ks.191 and 333 under Dubai pay of establishment and travelling allowance respectively are now expected against current year f s grant (my Printed Letter No.263-4/4 of 9th February referes). (c) A sum of approximately fo.2,400/- provided against leave salary of Nr. Hallows and Dr. Siddiq will have to be surrendered if their salary slins do not arrive before March 31st. -POLITICAL-Telegram. s* Code. G.T.C. (ON Prom. Britdonsul, Bushire. To. Political Agent, Bahrain No. A. 82. Dated. 15th April 1941. Your telegram No. 63. (a) Your figure is correct, ^inal grant un^er Post &amp; Telegram charges should read Rs. 19000. (o) Provision is being made for book debit, (c) Please rep ort position under Bay of Officers on March 25th.r f y OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL ^ ^ CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. ^’ith reference to your Cash Accounts for the month of October 194Q(Vouchers Nos. 16 and 39), I have the honour to state that a copy of the order on the authority of which the expenditure under L— Special war - L.4. Contingencies is being incurred, may kindly be furnished at an early date. It may, however, be stated that there appears dget provision for the year 1940-41, under No. TA10-1-1613 dated the From The Accountant General Central Revenues, Sir To The Political Agent Bahrain. CP.K.Bose) Assistant Accounts Officer ■s. Central Revenues. I have the honour to be, nir, Your most obedient servantNo. jfZf The Political Agent. Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Secretary to t,he 1 on’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire • and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( f or direct disposal. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 26th March, 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire memorandum No.1618-60/23 dated the 15th December, 1940. Description dj Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, letter No.TA10- 1-1613 dated the lit March, - 1941, to the Politica Agent, Bahrain. Budget provision for the 1940-41. 1 Copy forwarded to the Accountant General, Central Re^ New Delhi, for inforration.Telegram From To No.74 GTC. Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. Dated 25th March, 1941. Your telegram 82. Anticipated saving under pay of officers rupees 768 repeat 768. 2. Error in total in form E for October just discovered. Figures for L.l. Pay of Officers in my telegram No.35 incorrect. The final grant under this head should be Hs. 10300/- and not Rs.9300/-.Fo ^ -60/23. The Political Agent, Bahrain. X-3 7 British CJonsulate-Oeneral, Bushire. Bated the 18th March, 1941. i9/^ Reference this Residency’s telegram No. a/ 82, dated the 14th March, 1941. 2 • I enclose a statement showing the further modifications ma.de in the budget appropriations for 1940-41. By order, f or Jecreto the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.- The Hon’bie the Politio&amp;i Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre, To - The 3ecret*&gt;xy to the Goyermaent of India 9 External Affaire Depc rtraent, See Delhi. tfemor&amp;ndum No. ^ 607§3 Bushire, the 27th Maroh, 1941. ReaD^ro^riat1 one for 1940-41. I enclose reappropriation st^tenent No.lO f duly sanctioned, for the information of the Governnent of Indi* • 2. A copy of this .memorandum has been forwarded to the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, Ne* uelhi. Copy to: 1. The Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for information. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain-^ for information, with reference to his telegram No.74, dated the 25th March 1941. ’33A?. ROfRIAriOH 3 T.ArBifci.HT HQ. 10. 0 From Sub-head* Amount. To 3 ub-faend. 51 /mount, 2 s. 35-Bxternel Affairs. B-Gharges on account of Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran. BUSH IRS 35-ffxterm. 1 ffairs. L-Special War Expenditure. of officers. 1000 (c) of officers. C-Other Deiploimitic and 'dministrative cJiarges. BA HR -' IN C-»l~Pay of officers 250 (a) 750 (b) 1000 1000 officiating (a) Due to portion of pay of/officers not being adjusted in the current year. (b) Due to provision for leave salaries being in excess of actual requirements. (c) Due to amendment in figures of actual expenditure. for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.) e Issued P.L. No. 187 dated 5-2-38 to Secretary, Bushire. Telegram No. 00033 dated 21-2-38 from Political Resident Draft telegram to Bushire submitted, please. —A* . Issued telegram No. 35 dated 22-2-38 to P.R. Bushire. P. A . We have not received sanction to the additional grants asked for in our budget grants for 1937-38. Draft telegram to Bushire submitted, please. 3] IAA-',*V X /bli'Cr***--*-''. /b*? C ’ y'u^y^ /r* ■’ i., I s/ /L - /'-IS l A Please see also P.U.C. 10 and 11, end stetemekl's attached. We are asked to surrender 10% under Travelling /-v (VOv^ ' l C* s ^ ^ /r Allowance and 'Contingencies”. Under T.A. the position is that we have exceed ed our allotment already: we will probably need at least Rs. 5o00 for the next six months for tours of P.A./A.P.A. to the Trucial Coast and Qatar. Under Contingencies. To be surrendered Rs.410o/- (1) This is ear-marked for the Trucial Coast if end when is appointed tksxx for that sphere. This is unlikely to be the case during the current financial year. There-fore the allotment of Rs. 800 can be surrender ed in toto,thus saving a like sum under (2). (2) P.A./A.P.A. intends touring extensively in the Launch (please see p. 26). If the amount under (1) is surrendered as suggested above we will then probably be able to manage on the original allotment with the strictest economy. (2) and (4). No comments. (5) We will very likely have less telegraphing to do in the next 6 months than during a corresponding period in the three years. We will,Imgrrfnrr * need not more than Rs. 5000/- at the outside. (6) If we surrender a large slice under (5) we could curtail the cut under ifcix Office £llcwance. I have pencilled in figures accordingly. k fkc#. k vuj^' T 'l (y™ j&gt;4') t/rflurJH XL. Iir- / 6 ^° -ufc. ft . 10-'l? lu - t-o- &lt;1 k 'r]»A • P .A • Draft copy of Budget Estimates for 1940-41 is submitted below• As new items of expenditure or increases in old ones cannot be included in the estimates unless sanctioned by Govt, a separate statement is attached showing additional sums required for the Dispensary at Dubai. There is a provisioi of only ris.300/-fcr the pay of one Dresser and of its.800/- for medical equipment and drugs whiKhxdBKs in the estimates which does not appear to be enough. Items marked red are for the Dispensary at Dubai. Proposals for the new items will have to be considered and submitted seperately to the P.R.along with the budget estimates. If you approve the Estimates may be sent to P.A.for his approval and signature. r~- 3&gt;. F A . Hpfw* (O. ^ //- ^ i s) fUS'Q'l-I do not like the idea of providing a quarantine allowance of Rs 50/- per mensem for the Sub Assistant Surgeon at Dubai under the head 'House rent and other allowances' without explanation. I do not think that I have yet seen any remarks by the Residency Surgeon in regard to this quarantine business, though I asked him to the matter on his visit to the Trucial Coast and to let jib know his opinion. It is of course quite impossible for the Sub Assistant Surgeon to do regular quarantine work for the whole of the Trucial Coast and in effect his labours so far as quarantine is concerned^would be restricted to Sharjah and Dubai where ships and aircraft call. Any remuneration that he might receive might equally well be regarded as special pay and I would be inclined to increase the figure under the head 'C.2. Pay of Establishment — Military Sub Assistant Surgeon' by about Rs 500/- in order to allow ff **any special pay £•» that may be sanctioned later on. Since this does not involve Si an excess otfifthe sanctioned estimate for 1939-40 no parti- / cular explanation would be required. 2. I agree to asking for Rs 600/- for a compounder-dresser, 3. In regard to the 'Cost of medical equipment and supply of drugs', I do not know how the figure of Rs 1500/- has been arrived at, but presumably it is based on the Residency Surgeon's opinion after his visit to Dubai. If this is so is necessity to say that much in the draft JL 4. I consider Rs 300/- for 'contingencies' excessive and I have got no details to show how this figure has been reached. At the most I am only prepared to ask for Rs 20/- a month or Rs 240/- per annum. 5. I observe that in the budget figure under 'C.3. Allowances and Honoraria' - 'House rent and other allowances' there is an unexplained increase of Fs 1200/-. I do not know what this is for and it will certainly be cut out in BushireV \ unless it is properly explained. A.P.A. should look into this and if the additional provision is actually required he should add-a'paragraph to l the draft which I place below. 6. I see no particular reason for writing two t , * • • separate letters about this budget and I place below a draft v/hich can issue, signed by A.P.A. for P.A., when the points mentioned above have been put right. 15/8/1939. 1. The reason for the 'Quarantine Allowance' not being included with Special Pay is that the Special Pay which the S.A.S is already receiving counts for leave and pension and is sanctioned as a compensation for the special circumstances under which he works. Quarantine Allowance is a local allow ance paid for extra work and I do not think this could come under Special Pay. Please see F.R.9(25). I discussed the question of quarantine work with the C.M.O who, in general, agreed with my note on the subject and wanted, if possible, that the quarantine allowance should be paid now as S.A.S is, on his present scale of pay, worse off i than he was in India. C.M.0 considers that a Quarantine Allowance of is.50/- p.m., or te.600/- p.a would be fair. 2. C.M.Q considers that in view of the high attendance figures the minimum staff required to run the dispensary properly would be one dresser on R&amp;.20/- p.m., and one A' compounder, who should be a man of some education, on a minimum of as. 40/- p.m., This would mean an annual expenditure of is.720/-. It appears that the budget estimates are sanctioned to the nearest is. 100/- and that if this staff is to be included we should budget for an expenditure of fe.800/- p.a. It might be as well to fix now scales of pay /for Y *v&gt;v i u nv- V ^ ■*^6—r»»v v* ^ 4 ^-% 1^,1 '* A- A?” ^ u T - A kw- X Hr 6 A*— /1 A-'C &lt;1, £for both Dreiser and Compounder. I suggest for the dresser i«.20-2-30 and for the compounder te.40-2-50. C.M.O considers that 1,500/- should be asked for for 'Medical Equipment and supply of Drugs'. This estimate is based on the fact that out of te.800/- sanctioned for this year Es.731/15/- (plus cost of freight) has already been expended and additional indents to the value of over Ps.650/- have been put in. the by the S.A.3 and C.M.O considers all the items in these indents should be sent for. In view of the rising attendance figures,^ 1940/41 will certainly not be less than those for this year. 4. If 8s.240/- provided for contingencies, this will be reduced by P.R to the nearest !&lt;s-. 100/- or to fe.200/-r and Honoraria' is the same as asked for in previous years * and is based on actuals. In this year f s budget this Es.4,700 ^2^ split up by P.F into is. 3,500/- and Es. 1,200/-, the latter being for the S.A.S., Trucial Coast. No House Rent allowance is needed for the S.A.S. The only provision should be for quarantine allowance as noted above for is.600/-. 5 The figure of is. 4^700/- under 'C-$. Allowend&amp;s^ The C.M.O is writing to P.A on his return to Bushire. (C.M.O visited Dubai on 25/8/1939).Budget iistimatee for the year 1940-41 received with Bushire endorsement No. 657, dated the 21st May 1940. Qgvernment Hospital a t Duhai. The Government of India have sanctioned the sum of ^ 500/- a year for one Compounder © ^ 40/- a month. At present v/e have :~ One Dispenser @ ^ 25/- p.m. ^ 300-0-0 One' Dresser © ^ 20/- p.m 9 s 240-0-0 Total for year . .. . .^ 540-0-0 ,.o There will he excess of ^ 40/- under this head. We will ask for extra funds in November bext when the review of the expenditure will be made. Oontingencies. Z'*' We asked 4 a provision of ^ 1800/- under this head as under :- 1. Cost of medical equipment and cost of drugs p* 1500-0-0 2. Hospital Contingencies etc ^ 300-0-0 Total ^ 1800-0-0 The Government of India have sanctioned the sum of ^ 160C/- . If there will be any excess v/e will ask for extra funds in November next. May file. * ^ ^ 4? 3-&amp;-40. Page 10 of the estimates concerns the Medical Establishment at Dubai. It is difficult to understand why w this has been placed under ^ Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran'. The figures of ^ 2800/- for Medical Establishment appears to include Pay of Sub Assistant Surgeon ^ 1800-0-0 Pay of Dresser ps 300-0-0 Total Rupees ....771 2100-6-0Please see page 3 of the note sheets file 36/Z/l linked. Since no mention of a Publicity Officer was made, the item No.8 at page 3 of the above file was assumed to be for the Political Officer T.G. Even P.A T s T.A. for journeys in connection with the War were debited to this item. This was however during the last financial year, when there was no P.0. In the current year there is only one item 0 of Rs.S47/8/- which has Already been accounted for in for April. It will now be seen from the file 'Publicity Officer' (linked below) that this amount originally was/meant for P.0. Captain Howes on his return v £ n the 'E' form ( i.e consolidated stg(ement of acctts)- (^ 3 / Budget Esti m ates 1941-4 2• Our Budget estimates for the financial year 1941-42 are due to be submitted to Bushire now. Following items will be estimated as usual, any changes could be reported in the subsequent re-appropriation. Agency Staff. Pay &amp; Allowances. P.A. A.P.A. 1 .A. 2 special grade clerks 3 upper division clerks 4 lower division clerks Assistant Surgeon. C ffic e ca11owane e T.A • Launch Grant Central Contract Grant Rs. 1,300 Ks•16,300 Rs. 9,000 (plus Rs.400/-for S.A.S.Dubai) Rs. 9,000 Rents P &amp; T Charges Medical Attendance Rs • 1,600 Rs.13,000 Rs. 600 Dubai Hospital . Pay of S.A.S. T.A. Rs .400/- ^ Allowance Rs.50/- p.m. vide page 172 file 30/19 Supply of Drugs and medical equipment Rs.1500/-(p.119 file 4/4) Contingencies Rs. 300/- ' (p.120 “ ' M ) Temporary Compounder Rs.40/- p.m. Please see page 173/- file 30/19. This is only upto the end of February 1941, but 1 presume we can budget for him for another year. The position about the establishment at Dubai is as below(One dispenser at Rs.25/~ p.m. (sanctioned vide page (One dressere at Rs.20/- p.m.(164 file 30/19) One compounder (temporary) at Rs.40/- p.m. sanctioned vide page 173. It means that instead of one dispenser at Rs. 25/- p.m. and one dresser at Rs.20/- p.m., we have to keep one compounder at Rs.40/- and one dresser at Rs.20/-, but our present establishment is as given at ,r X' above. Subject to your approval the estimate for the next year may be prepared for one coumponder and one dresser as per page 173 file*30/19. '.TAR Establishment** Y' Political Officer Trucial Coast. Pay etc as per page 136 of the sanctioned budget grants page 161 file 4/4 T.A. Rs.2,500/- vide page 164 file 4/4 C .A. Rs.1,300/— ^ One interpreter Mr. Jasim. One censor Clerk ( to be engaged by P.0.) Publicity Office r. As per instructions contained in paragraph 3 of p.u.c. flagged (Bushire express letter No.952-79/63/5-submitted below) the budget estimates for the Office of the Publicity Officer/* Actue l expenditure up to 30th September 1940 and estimated expenditure for the remaining six months is as follows Head ■Budget P-rapI;. Actual expendi ture up to 30th Est imate d expenditure, for the remaining 6 months# Remarks Pay of Officers Pay of establishment 51800 22400 Cost of passage Sumptuary alice. Travelling allce. Hous e rent e tc. Rewards Language Launch Grant Cental Contract Gr. Rent Buildings Postage &amp; Tele. Ch. 1000 1200 9000 4700 nil 9000 1300 1600 13000 28606-5 27003 increase due Dr. Holmes promotion. 11527-7 11315 • — 600-0 ,600 3925r0 6075 2453-0 2370 — 300 To be paid R.I.H 3173-7 5827 277-5-6 1022 675-0 9790-1 16300 300 600 Office Allowance Secret Expenditure Grants in Aid _D_U B A I DISPTCN^ APY. Pay of Establishment 3300 Travelling allowance 400 Contingencies. 1600 6353-6 300-0 945 8000 Due to unsatisfactory arrangement of Iran Mail. 9947 Unknown Unknown 703-1 305-0 82-7 2270 500 1500 SPECIAL TAR EXPE ND ITURE. Political Officer, Trucial Coast 12800 2579-13 Censorship clerk Interpreter House Rent for censorship clerk House ~^nt for Pol. Officer &amp; Interpreter Travelling allowance Rewards Language Contingencies 1900 3600 400 1800 6700 Saving is due to '-'apt, J.B.Howes away to Muscat, unknovm 1800 unknown 1700 Nil Nil Nil 423-14 669 900 dc 840 unknown Nil 200 for transport of mails etc. Draft telegram to Bushire submitted for approval.rs Telegram Proiii To No. 2 Dated the 2nd October 40. - Enclair - Political, Bahrain - Britconsul, Bushire Your memorandum No. 750 of 4th April 1936. 2. Actual expenditure up to 30th September Pay of Officers Pay of establishment Cost of passage Sumptuary allowance Travelling allowance House rent Rewards Language Launch Grant Central Contract G r. Rent Buildings Postage &amp; Telegram Oh. Office Allowance Secret Expenditure Grant in aid DUBAI DISPENSAR Y Pay of establishment Travelling allowance Contingencies ps 28606-5 — PS 11527-7 — Nil PS 600-0 ps 3925-0 Ps 2453-0 Nil PS 3173-7 — 277-5-6 - 675-0 9790-1 — 6353-6 300-0 ps PS PS ps PS Nil 2 Q tob // *' 1 ' 1 3/73 *77 ^3/3 7*3 PS 703-1- PS 305-0 PS 82-7 - 3. Estimated expenditure for the remaining six months under the above mentioned heads respectively:- 27003 11315 Niix unknown 600 6075 2370 300 5827 1022 945 8000 9947 Unknown Unknown Dubai dispensary 2270 500 1500 4. Special War expenditure Political Officer Interpreter House rent Travelling allowance of Political Officer Rewards Language contingencies 5. P‘5 2579-13 - 2 PS 1800-0 L. a PS 423-14 - PS 669-0 — p? 900-0 Nil ic remaining x six th# -above—ment ion^rd he-ads- respectively : - 6700 1800 840 Unknown nil _ *30 Politicaljeer is Hs.900Q/- ( r..P./., I./. end ell pcrmmeni esteblishment). n./ . Sherjeh*s expenditure is borne by -ushire., nut P.0,r.C. hes i seperate budget, i.e. his expenses will be debited to Indie, and not borne by tiie present senctioned grent of Bushire. Please see page o07 flagged. This amounts tD c sanction for Rs.2,50o aadr Rs.l^PQO/-;applied for viap ^age ijg± 2dHr-±75. It ffieens that there is still a sue of ns.- (approx) available under T.ii. and aItost ns.ijovjQ/- under 0.£. / copy of page sent to P.O.T.C. ana the application v : ?s shown to bin; here. If you approve may enquire from P.O.T.C. if these allotments won't do for the remaining four months, and if not would it not be advisable to raise this question again by the end of January when our next financial review will be due.(Report to Bushire due in February). fcsxgjgiijGFiKK D.F.submitted. In our 1? st review we thought Rs.i2b7 for T.A.would do. C/A /V&lt; 0 Jy&lt; l b A /A wr r»/. A- — /S' ^ ^ ^ ^ pi ^ / e - 3 ? 2^ .J ?\_ a t ***, 3 S~ V/ ^ &lt;&amp;) WAR CHARGE S. L .I» Pay o f OFFICERS . Captain R,D.Metcalfe remained on leave on halfe average pay for about half a month and therefore the saving of 500/- is expected. Although we.not yet received the leave Salary Slip of Captain Metcalfe from A.G.C.R. A *ew Delhi, his half pay will come to about R 5 467/- per month and it is on this bases that my calculations are based. L .3. ALL OW ANCES. HO NORA RIA. The Expenditure under, this head up to 31st January 1941 is ^ 2878/14/- and a further sum of P 8 800/- ( approx.) more is expected for the T.A.Bills 6f Captain R.D.Metcalfe during the current Financial year. L .4. Contingencies . An excess of ^ 37/- is expected submitted. ' ^ 4-2-1941.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fa_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1123</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fa</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1123</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/4 III Budget Estimates'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T12:01:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (363 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminates with a set of notes at folios 317-364. Circled serial numbers in red ink and crayon, which occur occasionally in the file, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 365; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-316 and between ff 318-340; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains budget estimates for the Political Agency, Bahrain for the financial years 1939-40 to 1941-42 inclusive, and associated correspondence.The correspondence is between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. There is also some correspondence from the office of the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi; the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah (Captain Roy Douglas Metcalfe); and the Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf. Correspondence from the Political Resident also includes correspondence and papers from the Government of India (Finance Department, and the External Affairs Department).The statements of budget estimates cover pay of officers, pay of establishment, allowances and honoraria, contingencies, secret expenditure, and grants-in-aid. The papers also include detailed pay statements, statements of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants, reappropriation statements, and statements of contract and fixed grants. The correspondence also covers individual items of expenditure, retrenchment, accounting instructions from the Government of India, and expenditure under the head of Special War Charges.The date range gives the covering dates of the principal items of correspondence. The last dated addition to the file is an entry in the notes on folio 364v dated 23 August 1941.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food prices</topic></subject><subject><topic>Funds</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Motor vehicles</topic></subject><subject><topic>Cost of living</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air force personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Army</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel allowances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Coffee</topic></subject><subject><topic>Hospitality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fa#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>