<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000183_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:27:43.181Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">r COPY . (E 6946/2956/34) No.1187. O v British Embassy, Washington, D.G. November 6 th, 1934. Sir, 67 ^ With reference to my despatch No. 1018 of 12th September, I have the honour to report that the head of the Near Eastern Division of the State Department recently informed a member of my staff that President Hoosevelt has not yet come to a decision with regard to the ratification of the Anns Traffic Convention. 2. Mr. Murray said that the President was extremely anxious to effect the accession of the United States to the Convention, but that he now fully realised the complications involved by the Persian Gulf reservation passed by the Senate. It therefore seemed likely that Mr. Roosevelt would take steps to have the reservation dropped. 3. Mr. Murray added that the Persian Government had had the effrontery to intimate that, if the President failed to approve the reservation, there would be grave diplomatic rep e reus sions. 4. In the course of further conversation Mr. Murray said that the United States Government were still trying to ascertain the truth of the complaint made by two iunei'ican fliers in the Melbourne air race that they had been detained for twenty-four hours on Persian territory. ihe aviatoxs insist/ The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.G.S.I., K.C.V.O ., etc., etc. , etc.,insist that they were held up but the Persian G-ovemment have formally denied that this was the case. As the incident occurred at Mohammerah, where there is no United States Consular representative, the assistance of His Majesty 1 s Legation at Tehran has “been invoked. Mr. Murray said that if it was established that the aviators had in fact been detained by Persian officials strong representations would be made to the Persian Government. I have etc., (Signed) R. 0. Lindsayof this Re serration* thus showing what misohievous results this apparently meaningless formula might have. The £&gt;vate Department had so far not repaired the President fi s decision; hut Mr* Phillips pointed out that ii the reserYation was not withdrawn,, and if it were definitely decided that it was of a material character and. vrnib required the assent of all signatory partl©s s the whole treaty must lapse, as the assent of the other signatories could obviously not be obtained, and as the adhesion of the United States Government to the eonvention was necessary before the principal arms exporting countries would consent to adhere to it 0 1 have, el©o s (Signed) B.C. Lindsay*— — 98?:. 59Ai/29SG/S4) 1 R v,. / ■'i r 'j ) / KJ l 44 .MUJlOii a'tfic::, £9th jotobcr. 19554. Sir, in j;out Sooiiatoh no. 1016 of tbe 12 tr\ September, rcs-irctin^ tho V£?Qina\ A ull‘ reservation attaohofl the senate ti tho ratification of t:»e international Arise traffic Gonv©j\tion # Tour ?ixcell&lt;mo^ reported the vietve of the un^er secretary of state, ^ho hod oxprceeed to you the opinion that if the reservation irare not vithdrenm the whole treaty must lapse in so far aa the united states wao aoncerneC, sino© the re ©er vat ion would rooalre the asseat of all the other signatory state a, whioh was obviously unlike!;/ to be obtained * 2. TThilo this opinion is no doubt oorreot. the eaere fact that the reservation was attached to on instrument which had never corse into force would not detract from the value of the roeervntlon to the peraion ^overncicnt* It would remain on record as an expression of united states opinion which had never been withdrawn# It ndnht even b© accepted by gome of the other signatory etatoa. however laeanlunless it may bo who 21 critically oxar&amp;ined, its existence would te a standing enoourasament to iersia to pursue inadtaleslbie claims in tho .or si an Gulf region# g. For this reason I shall be sXad will take any suitable opportunity of pressing the .^tatc Department, to ‘Dersovero in their efforts to induce the : resident to /oecurs His 'ixcelisncy ’The Right Honourable sir h on aid Lindsay. O.c.n.”* ** !*% •:&gt;, ii. s 4 ^ s S etR. ©te. etc. Washington,Copy . (E 5646/2956/34 ) 2 E H S I A K S U L F ac8«3*«iJ United States J Reservation to Ratification of ■arms Tran in Conventioii regarding Persian Sovereignty in Persian Gulf, ^ rob on., tile Counsellor of the French Embassy B came to see me this morning with reference to his previous conversation with Mr* G.FoAo Earner on this subject* and explained that he had now received further information from .tar is as to u he attitude of the French Government © The view of the French Government was that* since the part of the United States 5 reservation which referred to the question of Persian sovereignty in the Gulf was in the nature of an 'interpretative reservation' 6 if was necessary that the French Government, as the Headquarters-Government of the Convention* should circulate the reservation to the other signatory powers with an enquiry as to whether they were prepared to accept it* even if the reservation did not in actual fact affect the Juridical position* £« M. Gambon explained that the French Government felt bound to taice this line since, although this particular interpretative reservation might be virtually meaningless and not affect the provisions of the Convention in any way* further interpretative reservations might conceivably be put forward by other .Powers and it would be invidious and indeed impracticable for the French Government to make distinctions between such reservations and forward some to the other /Signatories3^3 48 Signatories for approval on tiie ground tiiat they did modify the Convention while not forwarding others on the ground that their juridioal effect was nil„ their position, in this matter to the United States Embassy in Paris and made it clear that, if the United States Government insisted on this part of their reservation, it would have to b© circulated to all the signatory powers for acceptance or otherwise. On this, the United States Embassy had ashed for time to refer the matter to Washington again, and the French Government were therefore taking no action pending a further communication from the United States Government * 4 c Me Gambon appeared clearly to understand the objections which we ourselves had seen to the United States reservation and asked, what was now the position as xar as wa were oonearnedo I told him that the difficulties we saw had been fully explained to the State Department who appeared He said that the French Government had explained promised to let me know as soon know as soon as the French Government President ^s attitude * I no diff i culty about thl s» {signed ) G° v ' cRendel * FOREIGN OFFICE, 6th September 6 « w i O . 8 •&lt;!» ®/ ication on this subject, please quote E, X&lt;\$\c ' person by name, but to— V / n any further communi catio n on this subject, please quote No and address —not to any “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. THE Under-Secretary of State compliments to ^ J &gt; j ' and, by direction of the Secretary of State, s presents his J S lc\JU6 transmits herewith copi^'i of the under-mentioned Foreign Office, 193 X paper. .ft lny Reference to previous correspondence : P 01 v o lv E. - Description of Enclosure.D. 10.11 p.m. R. 9.30 a.ra. July 12th 1934, July 12th 1934. July 13th 1934. No.233 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA CONFID E NTIAL. Your telegram No.192, I discussed question today with head of Near frank and told me in confidence the following story of origin of the reservation. Department to use their influence to secure adoption hy the Senate of reservation. (He claims that Persian sovereignty extends o^er entire Persian Gulf, including islands). Department refused and told him that request was improper. He then sent for Senator King and with little difficulty, induced him to sponsor local reservation. This Senator is a self appointed champion of small peoples and lost causes; he was a persistent advocate of Armenian national home and in this connexion took the lead in opposing American Treaty of Lausanne with Turkey; similarly he has denounced presence of American troops in Hayti. He readily agreed with Persian Minister’s request and demanded State Department’s assistance in drafting reservation. Persian Minister was once more told oy State Department Eastern Department of State Department. He was very Persian Minister here, Djolal, first asked State that2 i 51 ciioarnsbances to inajority leader, Senator Hobiiison, before adjouemment when the Senate was hastily Shortly before it came up Senator Robinson was summoned to the White House* He therefore asked Senator Pittman, chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, to deal with reservation in his absence, and give all proper assistance; so far from doing so, the latter voted for resolution with reservation* He presumably wished to avoid offending - Senator King since both are members of powerful Silver group in the Senate* There was no explanation, discussion or debate* Story is typical of irresponsible treatment of foreign affairs under American system and of difficulties with which State Department have to contend* The President has not yet signed the resolution and will not do so until his return from Hawaii* But he attaches great importance to ratification of convention and he can only annul reservation by rejecting ratifying resolution* I doubt therefore whether it would be any good trying who undertook to kill it. The ratifying resolution came up amongst a. number of treaties three days ago disposing of accumulated arrears of legislation to00 p6i suecIg him hq u' xtv j gQ p Mr ° Murray ^ t -t. ^ficial with whom 1 talked, was bnt? Amerlcan Le ^ £; '^ cn ^ Tehran from 1922 to 1925* rxe takes a serious of results of passage of 1 eoeivaoion, WiAxca. ^uyaxtment did their test to avert® He ; expects Persians to exploit it to the utmost at teneva. They will proha,bly represent it as considered pronouncement by the Senate of the United states in oapporu of cheir claim to sovereignty ever the Gulf whereas in fact it is only the result of a successful appeal by Persian Minister to sentimentality of a single Senatoro Mr. Murray anticipates that Persians vcill proceed from their success against us over Anglo- Persian concession to press their claim to sovereignty over the Gulf. He would not be surprised to see them make some sort of naval demonstration at Bahrein and then appeal to the League in the event of threats or reprisals on our part* Present American Minister in Tehran owes his position to Senator King* Persian government delivered to him their note of protest ogaMst American oil concession at Bahrein and asked him to cable it to Washington, which he did at considerable expense to United States government. State Department have not acknowledged nor answered the note and apparently do not intend to. Mr. Murray informed me that he was giving me above information, especially his personal views in the last paragraph but one, in confidence, so 1 trust you will treat contents of this telegram as confidential*Copy (K 442/295 6/34) HQ BTSTHTBUTJHH . Cypher telegram to Mr, Osberne, (Washington). Foreign Office, 31st July, 1934, 2.20 p.m. I o. 206. - 0 ~D-o-o-o-O-Q- / r ~, „ ■j / / ( O / ^ ! y ;. j :'i Your telegram Ho. 240 (of the 23rd July: United States ratification of 1925 Arms Traffic Convention)* United States Embassy have no detailed knowledge of general question; Mr. Hull, if directly approached, !?oul&amp; probably plead ignorance of details and merely appeal to his officials. In these circus-stances preferable course 1 b line proposed in penultimate paragraph of your telegram. I assume that recent correspondence is sufficient to equip you for such discussion. If not you have only i to telegraph for further information required.54 , NO DISTRIBlTT inw. (E 4530/2965/34) _ 1 195 4 J Cypher telegram to Wx a Osborne (Washington) Foreign Office, 20th July 1934, 10,00 p.m. No. 199. Your telegram No. 233 (of 12th July - United States ratification of 1925 Arms Traffic Convention). As prospects of treaty settlement between this country and Persia now appear bad, Persian government may be trying to extend their claims in the Persian Gulf. Although United States reservation does not legally affect the situation, political and psychological effect may be serious. For it is likely to be*widely mis quoted in Middle East as implying that Persia has United States support in extravagant claims in respect of Gulf. It is desirable to obtain from United States government some public indication of correct interpreta tion of reservation, making it clear that it does not imply support for any Persian claims over High Seas of Persian Gulf or non-Persian islands therein. I have considered possibility of arranging •exchange of notes with United States government to be published, although this course would have disadvantage that any odium would clearly fall upon His Majesty's Government. Note from His Majesty's Government might enquire meaning of United States reservation and state that thpy^presume * that it implies no recognition of Persian sovereignty over any territory belonging to any ruler with whom His Majesty's Government are in special treaty relations, such as Sheikhs of Bahrein, Koweit, Trucial Coast etc., or of any other independent Arab ruler, and further that it55 2. it does not imply recognition of any Persian rights over any waters of Gulf other than Persian territorial waters, It would ot course he necessary to ensure hy prior discussion with State Department that their reply would he satisfactory and not, owing to fear of Senate, of hedging nature and that notes could he published. alternatively it might he practicable to persuade United States government or State Department to make some puolic explanatory declaration to above effect without indicating that it has been made at our instance or suggestion. This would be preferable from point of view of His Majesty's Government provided terms of declaration were satisfactory, that declaration were unmistakeably authoritative, and that adequate publicity could be secured. Please telegraph your observations on these suggestions Ou. on ciny ctliop inofchod wnich niciy sooni to you prof opclIoIg and equally effective. Matter cannot pest where it is. State Department have allowed something to happen which is at once unwise on their part and possibly injurious to us 3 We cannot accept such a situation.I57 I could sound of No. 233 and I think t have to toll him that prior advice of this 'ficial referred to in my telegram his might he helpful. But I should we wanted a public disavowal and might possibly detract from effec tiveness of request, either in London or here, for action by the President. So I will do nothing unless you authorise me to speak to him. We are clearly entitled to ask for whatcvcr z amends^ administration, whether President or State Department, can offer us, but I do not think that we can hold latter responsible for 'allowing it to happen'. If we blame thorn instead of anomalies of American system of government, we shall probably only lessen their willingness to help.58 J NO DISTRIBUTION x .AMENDED . C OPY- Decypher, Mr. ^sborne (Washington) 3rd August, 1934. D* 2,21 p,m, 3rd August, 1934. R, 9,30 a.m, 4th August, 1934. No. 253. ;i !i u u n n n n n n n u :i u it i! n it ii it n it (i ii ii » li Your telegram No. 205. I discussed the matter fully with the sane official. He ’ appreciates your, wish for a formal and preferably spon taneous disavowal and I understood that State Department were almost equally desirous of annulling reservation and so fore- stalling its exploitation by Persians. I suggested President might issue statement on signature of resolution and added if this or some other form of spon taneous declaration were not feasible we should line an exchange of notes on lines suggested in your telegram No. 199. He thought the former was conceivably possiole and Ghat laoter could be arranged if necessary but he told me lor your confidenoial information that both Secretary of State and Assistant Secretary Judge Moore were anxious to get rid of the reservation alto gether. It is therefore proposed as soon as President returno to try to convince him of the desirability oi this and go ur6e him to send for Senator Pittman and hand him back the reso lution saying it must be passed again at next Session of Congre-ss wibhout reservation. Official was careful to point out that State Department could not be sure wneoher ohe President would be ready to do this or whether domestic President politicalmi,Jit not debar him poa.j.bxcal exigencies not debar him from taking so firm a line. Biro at any rate Department is going to have a Oik/ ct tnis. lie saio. their hands would be strengthened in enproacnina /the President by knowledge of the feelings and wisnes ot His Majesty’s Government* I asked him if it would help if I saw Secretary of State but he said he would record our conversation as strong unofficial Represent at ions^ and the fact they were unofficial would probably be appreciated by Mr. Hull. But he went on to say that they have a further very strong argument to use with the President* On enquiry at Paris State Department had been informed that ^reservation? should have been held to be of a M substantive” rather than an H interpretative H nature and this will require its accept ance by all other signatories. Obviously His Majesty's Government and probably other Governments would demur. Therefore ro is desirable that resolution should return to Senate for passage without reservation* 1 assume this would be mosc satisfactory solution from our point of view end tnat six mo no ns delay would, not gre^tj-.y matter, it is however xar from certain that one Preoident W in defer to State Department or Senate to President, nor the moment we only can await the result of action by State D partment of which official will inform me in due course.(E.4409/2S56/34), i°-jiNimsTA Ms of M Cypher telegram to Mr. Osborne. (Washl^ton). ' i--oieign Office. 9th July. 1934 . 10.0.p.m. * ?. * ’ *■ . &lt;&gt;/ # j-&gt;o * 192* X X Bir i ' , LilldBay ' s telegram N o. 20 6 (of June 18th - hrated States ratification of 1925 Arms Traffic Convention reservation regarding Persian sovereignty in Persian Golf). United states Embassy have now coiminicated to me Senate s reservation, and under instructions from state De partment have made confidential enquiries as to views of Hie Majesty's Government regarding passage about Persian sovereignty. United States Embassy agree that as Persia neither pos sesses nor claims sovereignty over High beas of Persian Gulf, and as no question of infringement of Persian sovereignty over Persian territorial waters arises under provisions (see in particular Articl6 19)oi ConvGntion (although such torrid torial waters are in fast included in special maritime zone), reservation has no real significance and does not of course give Persia any rights which she does not already possess. It has been explained to Embassy, however, that in view of delicacy and difficulty of situation in Persian Gulf, reservation seems open to serious objections, Persia is at present putting forward unsubstantiated but persistent claims to sovereignty over Bahrein, whose independent ruler is in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government, and over certain other independent Arab islands in Persian Gulf, His Majesty’s Government are resisting these claims on behalf of their Arab proteges, and difficulty of situation may well be increased if Persians feel they are being encouragedf V 63 or supportsd in their pretentions Py the 'United States Lr6v« eminent. United States oil interests are also affected in view of Bahrein oil concession held hy the Standard Oil Com pany of California s against validity of which Persian Gov ernment have recently protested in virtue of their claim to sovereignty over Bahrein (see Persia Print June 6th, Section i)« United States Embassy have been unable to give any ex-^ planation of motives underlying Senate’s reservation, 2 and have suggested that matter should be taicen up through you with State Department, who may possess the necessary xmomn^ ticno Please therefore approach United States Coverrmsnr on above lines pointing out objections to reservation from point 0 f view not only of His Majesty's Government but also oi United States holders of Bahrein oil concession. United States Embassy have suggested that reservation is due to pure ly sentimental or psychological reasons, but if those ^ reasons are strong enough to have led senate to thin, xk worth while proposing reservation, they are equally aoroug enough to justify fears of His Majesty's Government ^ co un- fortunate effect which it may have on Persia and m Persian Gillf U avoid givlre «. MP-K- Hls ,,W “ ty ' S » el w “cmmr vodewad to above, « attaob m ch ^po«ance to Uw Repeated to Tehran No. 4 Saving.^eAc^— 1j U ' • ' k *~ t **^ 7 ^cu„ Cly^C^ k sk^ ^ tr. / o ^ ^ kx ^U c^i W- 7 U '&lt;; -M- ^ ^ ^ Please see the F.O. d.o. letter of 25th June t _ A\ ‘Al UcAJa*^ ». ,' / Q . below. It is certainly worth while to try to obtain further light on the obscurities of the U.S. Senate’s reservation, though it would be inexpedient to make too much heavy weather of the matter, as we do not wish to give the State Dept, at Washington the impression that we regard our own rights as in any way precarious. In particular, we do not want them to think that we are perturbed by the latest development of the Persian claim to Bahrein (which is the Persian Note to the U.S. Minister, Tehran, of 22nd May (see paper flagged A on the file). On the question of Persia's territorial waters, the F.O. draft telegram does not quite fill the bill (see papers at P. 2788/25 and 3389/25 - slips B in the volume). It may even be possible that the Senate thmk^ that the Persian objections are reasonable so far as territorial waters are concerned, and that partly for this reason they have made - at Persian instigation, perhaps/perhaps, this comprehensive reservation. A draft letter is submitted. ‘I?. 3y65 Draft Paper. C.F.A. Warner, Esq., F.O. , 'V 5000 2.34 p2 /f-ioj/ Department. ? 0 JUN 1954 Many thanks for your letter of 23rd June, No. 1 + 1*1 !l^if. regarding the reservation attached by the United States Senate to their ratification of the International Arms Traffic Convention of 1925. Sir Samuel Hoare agrees that it would be desirable to telegraph to the Ambassador at Washington with a view, if possible, to obtaining farther light on the obscure wording of this reservation. At the same time, he suggests that it would be advisable to avoid any risk of giving the State Dept, the impression that we attach too much importance to the matter. Is it possible that the reservation may perhaps partly originate in some muddled echo of the Persian Qevt;- 1 -^ ^apprehension that the special zone regime in the Persian Gulf imports some infringement of Persia's sovereignty over her own territorial waters? You will remember that the question ofthe inclusion of territorial waters in the maritime zone was one of the points raised by the Persian M.F.A. with Sir P. Loraine (Tehran telegram No. 217 of 31st July, 1925), and that the latter * wa s instructed in F.O. despatch No. 475 of/ 2531or • Xli V V/JL V w sa • ^ # ^ A* 4^*7 ^ b&gt; st~&amp;^ fc- t of 29th September, 1925, that Persian waters are included in the maritime zone the purpose of the Convention, but that no infringement of Persian sovereignty in them is thereby involved A» c^i U' We would suggest for consideration the following modifications of your draft telegram:- First para .: Omit the words in brackets, and add at the end of the para, some passage in the following sense: 'Territorial waters are included in special maritime zone for the purpose£ of the Convention, but wording of the reservation is unnecessarily wide if it is merely intended as an acknowledgnent of the fact that such inclusion does not infringe Persia’s sovereignty in her owiji waters.’ Second para .,3rd sent. gns.&amp;: Head: ’I not, it might serve to throw light on tiie matter if you mentiorn)to State Dept, that reservation apparently wide enough to relate to possible Persian sovereign rights over high seas of Gulf . . . ’ hast part of this. r)ar.a^..-whe.r-^it refers to Bahrein: Begin: ’You may in addition, if you think fit, explain that reservation also seems to us unfortunat since . . « Lower down, after words ’which H.H.G.Draft Paper. 66 Department. have always regarded as completely baseless’ add ’and which has been rebutted in Sir A. Chamberlain's Notes to the Persian Govt, of 18th January, 1928, and 18th February, 1929, communicated to members of the League of Nations' (with references). y ° Uf,e J, C, WALffOtf/ 2531 5000 2.34 JFOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 25rd June, 1934. (E 4101/2956/34) J.MFEDIATE &lt;c*H, / W Dear Walton, I enclose herein a copy of a Washington telegram, which you have probably noticed already in the Foreign Office printed telegram sections, regarding the American ratification of the International Arms Traffic Convention of 1925. 2. My Secretary of State feels that the phraseology of the Senate's reservation regarding the position in the Persian Gulf is sufficiently odd to warrant our telegraphing to the Ambassador in the terms of the attached draft. Will you be so good as to let me know as soon as possible whether you concur in the draft? I am sending a copy of this to Seal at the Admiralty. J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B. , M.C.[This Docament is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gorernmant, a nd should be returned to the F oreign Office if not required for official use.] ~ From UHIT5D STATES OF AMERICA. Decode* Sir R. Lindsay (Washington). 18th June, 193d. D. 5.30 p.m. 18th June, 1934. R 0 9.30 a.m. 19th June, 1934. No. 206 (R). Senate lias ratified G-eneva Arms Convention of 1925 with the following reservations. That the Convention shall not come into force so far as the United States is concerned until it shall have come into force in respect to Belgium, British Empire, Czecho slovakia, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Sweden and U.S.S.R; and with the further understanding that adherence to the treaty shall not he construed as denying any right of sovereignty which Kingdom of Persia may have in and to Persian Gulf or to the waters thereof.objection? if not , lt , lght serve to do ^ toat you chould mention at state Department * ' ' tHaf^Jeervatlon regarding poaelble Persian sovereign rights over High Beas of Gulf, though obviously not affecting question whether such rights exist, has naturally caused some surpriBe here, eince we can trace no information that I err ia haa evn r put forward bo extravagant a claim, which could have no conceivable hare* Hif? MajeetyOoveroment, apart from their concern to safeguard their own rights of free navigation in Gulf, have special obligation to safeguard similar rights for vrah rheikhs of Gulf (and of c our re their rights over their territorial waters). you ^ I ^ would explain that reservation aleo seems to us unfortunate since it may be thought by Persian Government to indicate favourable United Btater view regarding Persian claim to Bahrain, (which His Ha jo sty f n OovernHient la re always regarded nr completely baseless). hit that claim, as restated in recent c oTfimun ica tion /71 conmunioation from Persiaa Government to United States Legation at Tehran (see Persia print; June 6th, Section 1), involves denial of title of \merican conceesionnaire. Confidential, It is, of oouree conceivable chat erelan Government have made clandestine approach to United rtatee Government or Btandard oil Company of California aBBuring them of favourable attitude in event of recognition of Persian olaim to Bahrain, but no information to this effect has reached us. K\(s 4425/4/91) X PERSIAN CLAIM TO BAHRAIN. In the course of a conversation with me this afternoon, Mr. Francis B. Loomis (see E 4784/2369/91 of 1934) again reverted to the Persian claims in the Persian Gulf. His Company, the Standard Oil of California, had apparently heen much worried hy Senator King’s proposed reservation to the United States ratification of the Arms Traffic of 1925. He gave me a pretty accurate account of this affair, except that he claimed the credit for killing the reservation almost entirely for his own Company, a misconception of which I did not attempt to disabuse him. He was however abviously worried by the Persian activity over this reservation, and said he was nervous lest the Persians might now press their claim to Bahrain even more strongly, e.g. by seizing one of the Company’s tankers. 2. I said that I thought this was in the highest degree unlikely. The Persian claim to Bahrain was not a reality, and the Persians had no case at all. His Majesty’s Government would never admit the claim, and had indeed recently been strengthening their position in Bahrain by the transfer thither of their naval stations in the Gulf. I told Mr. Loomis that I thought that in present conditions he could set his mind completely at rest on this point, and that it seemed to me in the highest degree improbable that the Persians would ever provoke a serious dispute on this question by such high-handed action as he had appeared to fear. (Sgd) G.W. RENDEL. | FOREIGN OFFICE. 17th July, 1935.00?Y, U 3544/E17/34) Mu iieoode. Sir H* hind a ay ( '.■sashing ton). 7th June, 1935. B. 6.10 p.m. t 7th June, 1935. K. 9*30 a.ia. f 8th June, 1906. Ho. 139. (K). i My despatch Mo* 288* Senate yesterday approved rati float ion of 4ms Traffic Convention with the sole reservation of mss&amp;ing its entry into fores as far as United States is concerned depend upon its entry into fore© in other principal Powers concerned.io. 131, 997 Q L.L. I ^ APR *** r” O ^ Britisli Legation, 7eiirua. 33rd raroh, 1955* Sir, U ; . ''■’&gt; p^** I M«v« tha honour to Inform you that tiie Am#rlean . inis tar, in tne oom^s© of conversation with a ?^#mbar of staff a few &lt;la,ys ago* «Mintlo»iw4 that the Arms Traffic Convention haa recently mm ratified hy the Senate without the reservation sponsored by Senator King, he said that he hod found Kazan! very displeased about this development but hud explained that just &amp;g the adoption of the reservation had never meant that the United totes Senate wished to endorse any special rights or claims which the Persian Government possessed in the Persian Gulf, so did the abandonment of the reservation not mean that they now gave their support to any British rights or claims in the Gulf. The Gulf was not an area in which the United States had any special interests and their only wish was to be completely impartial. 2 * Ur. Bornibrook went on to say that Ivasemi had sent round that morning an official of %m Ministry for Foreign Affair® who haa proceeded to argue the question for an hour. The chief burden of his remarks had seemed to be to accuse the Americans of the heinous crime of yielding to British influence. a. Hr. Mornlbruak said that he was afraid that he himself was not very popular here just now as &amp; result of all this, and he added that he thought the withdrawal /of Tm Might Honourable Sir John dimoo, G.C.S.I.&gt; etc* $ etc*, etc., The Foreign officeof %m reservation h&amp;a probably abaictm ^ellal’a position in Washington* 4 * % am&amp;iMg a copy of this despatch to his Mfge sty’s Ambass&amp;dor at &gt; a Kington (Mo. 32/i!). I have the honour* to be with the highest respect, bir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) H.M. Knatchbull-Hugeesen.Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P. ^ 240 V 9 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated Bee. 193 To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Undersecretary Secretary of State.... Date. Initials. SUBJECT. 'C . 4- h. PERSIAN 5I3LF . Sa \SL+Jj Withdrawal of reservation ( Persian claims to sovereignty in Persian Gulf) to ratification hy United States Senate of Geneva Arms Traffic Convention of 1935. Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. please see the minute on P.Z.7778/34 helow. It is most satisfactory that we should have secured the withdrawal of this reservation, more particularly as there is reason to believe tnat strong Persian pressure has been exercised recently to secure its retention and that the Persian Government are concerned at their failure to keep it on record. A/, f * (V-35TCOPY (E 1934/2X7/34) HO•S00• 11 British Embassy, Washington, B.C 15th March, 1935. Sir 333 . ■ ith reference to my despatch Ho. 1305 of December 18th last, on the subject of the ratification by the United States of the Arms Traffic Convention, I have the honour to inform you that the Senate Committee on Foreign Affairs made on the 13th instant a favourable report, subject only to the reservation formerly adopted making United States ratification dependent upon that of the other principal Powers concerned. 2* The Committee voted against including the reservation regarding Persian claims in the Persian Gulf. 3. A copy of an explanatory statement issued by the Chairman of the Committee is attached. I have, etc., (Signed) R.C. Lindsay The Eight Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.3.I*, K.C.V.O*, etc., etc. etc.12 OOPY Washington, D.c. O^PCITT IE... ON FOUIXOH E T XAT10KS OF ^HS ITKITWp STATE'S BKHATE » STATEMENT BY THE CHAIRMAH OF THE COMMITTEE FFGABDIKO THE COMMITTEE 1 8 ACT I OB IK REPOFTIBO- TO THE SEHAT1 EXECUTIVE H. ? 69 th COH0RESS, 1st SESSION, A COHVEHTIOH TOP THE SUP-WIST ON OF TRADE IN AM, AMMHHITXOH, IMPT.^T^S OF FAR, etc. the treaty for the supervision of the international trade in arms and ammunition and in implements of war, with the reservation formerly adopted by the Senate to the effect that the ratification would not go into effect until ratified by Belgium, the British Empire, Czechoslovakia, France, Germany, Italy, Sweden, and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. ■whether the so-called King Reservation should be included. (The King Reservation is as follows; u xx xx and with the further understanding that such adherence to this treaty shall not be construed as denying any right of sovereignty which the Kingdom of Persia may have in and to the Persian Gulf, or to the waters thereof. 11 ) The Committee voted against including this reservation in the resolution of ratification. toward the King Reservation was that the King Reservation was not giVGn the seme construction by the Government of Persia that was intended, and was given to such reservation, by the Foreign Relations Committee and the United tates Senate at the time it was adopted on the former occasion. The Committee, by $uoa reservation, intended to make it clear that our The Committee today made a favourable report on A vote was first taken by the Committee as to Th© Committee’s reason for changing Its attitude GovernmentGovernment would take no part in disputes between governments with regard to sovereignty in the Persian Guxf. It intended to make it clear that our Government noes not deny any sovereignty that any government siay have ia the Persian Gulf. The Committee recognized that there are disputes between governments as to sovereignty in the Persian Gulf» It intended, therefore, to clearly convey the attitude ot the Committee, which is that it would neither admit nor deny any sovereignty thet any government was determined to have in the Persian Gulf. Unfortunately it appeared from matters submitted to the Committee that the Persian Government, or those in high authority in the Persian Government, did not place the same construction upon the reservation that was given to it by the Committee, but rather looked upon it as an expression in aid of the claim of the Persian Government to sovereignty which is disputed by other governments.15 (S 77C8/89B6/34) ;709 4: 19 35 REIGN OFFICE, S«W a X« 29th January ? 1935o Dear Chancery, The une of the phrase 'His m$®ntr'® Government**. 'mst re.tune to he Tsounfl t&gt;y the reaeinrotion*’ in yoni* despatch Ko . 1S 0 £-i of the IPth PeoemhePt 19M» resapfling the reservation attached hy the 'Senate to the ratification of the International Arne Trams convention of 1985 makes us think, that you may find it useful to know what would* la our opinion, he the exact effect of our 'refusing the Tinted itsteo reservation'. The letter is the phrase used in your telegram Ko. 3«8 of the Oth neceafcer, to which wo annonted in our telegram tic gOg of the l«th —^er. , e BPe advised that ih@^oaiti5n is so follows: a. It has -been laid down at Oeneva that reservations, in the proper sense, to international . O r ntlo * Dv effective unless all the other instiPuiftentB ? canuow ^ mn tbi^ -nrlnclpl© e refusal Bleary powers accept them. -n tr.xs oar The JhaneexTsj British Embassyt p nshingtotieINDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please quote No and address —not to any “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1 f i / I . /;. ty person by name, but to— ' .333 , THE Under-Secretary of State for Fop^pi ^ffairsj presents his pliraents to ^4/ ^U^f66x/ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. complimer Foreign Office, /S , 193 Reference to previous correspondence / 0 J 7 •i-rf*- &amp;s&lt;ZL~r sa) Description of Enclosure Name and Date. 7 0 /3o3 ore? . Subject. ( ENCLOSURE IN WEZ.XY No. -3 17 JAN 1935 FROM SEC V:7 . . v- SECELL 1 , LETT 14—6130 10712 (2 Similar letter sent to f] oCua^C^COPY. 20 (E 7762/2956/34) «0. 1305. { ! 3 3 5 Tn I£H EMBASSY WASHINGTON, L.C. 18th I^cember, 1954 Sir iw. I have the honour to refer to previous correspondence regarding the reservation as to Persian Claims in the Persian Gulf attached by the Senate to the ratification of the Arms Traffic Convention; and especially to your telegram No# 502 of December 13th In which you authorized me to say to the Secretary of State that if this reservation were definitely attached to the United States ratification of the Convention, His Majesty’s Government would have to refuse the reservation# 2. In the course of conversation to-day I told Mr* Hull that I wished to speak to him about this reservation* He wrung his hands and. sal d that the matter seemed to take up half his time# He had nad something like a cursing match over it with the Persian Minister, and was now having his difficulties with Senator Pitman (Chairman of the Senate Committee on foreign Relations), and what had I to say about it? Lhe State Department In regard to this question, and that I had not hidden the concern which it had caused my Government; but that I had made no actual represen't-atloas to him about it. I did however now consider it the part of candour to apprize him of a fact which had come to my knowledge through perusal of correspondence received from you. It was possible. I said, that in 3 I said that I had in the past made enquiry at The Right Honourable £ir John Simon, G.C.£•I*, Etc., etc., etc21 1 \ a certain contingency His Majesty’s Government might have to take a definite attitude towards the Reservation. Should this contingency arise His Majesty’s Government would feel compelled to make it clear that they must refuse to be bound by the reservation. 4. Mr. Hull expressed himself appreciatively in regard to my communication and said it was in line with what he had imagined our attitude was likely to be. I have, etc., (Signed) R.C. Lindsay.any further communication on this subject, please quote ° ?k1 broil ZU my person by name, but to— / ' and address —not to any “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. A, 37 22 ( ' O THE Under-Secretary of State Affairs presents his compliments to h and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop t'rV of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, f*f ’ 193 ^ * Reference to previous correspondence : PO. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Tf° 5*1. 0?-* /$ /t^ Subject. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER No. - 3 \ 7 JAN 19i»^ FRC^ U-CR: r i «R. l , U- - AND SECRET C „r f. ILbiA 0»‘HGi u&lt; { -c, ^ \A 3LA Similar letter sent to 14 —6130 10292(2) 4^,K 7783/6803/34) 10 * • BritiBh legation, Tehran, I f December ISth, 1954. Bir, With reference to paragraph 4 of the enclosure to your despatch Ho. 581 of November £8th last I have the honour to report that the American Legation here has protested against the detention of Messrs. Wright and rolando after their forced descent at Mohamaserah in the Melbourne Centenary Air Race. As there is no American Consular representative in i'outh Peraia Mr. Uornibroop requested that His Majesty’s Consul at nhwas be asked to send a report on the subject. A copy of Mr. Watkinson’s despatch Is enclosed, from which it will be seen that the American authorities were somewhat precipitate in instructing Mr* Homibrook to protest. Only the infoi'iaation contained in the first paragraph was communicated to Mr. Hornibrook. 2. 1 learn that the situation was not rendered any easier by the fact that Messrs, fright and olando were again detained on the return flight for a few hours at Bushire. I have, etc., (Signed) H.K.KNATCHBULL HUGHS8 W? . The Fight Honourable Sir John Si man , 0#C# B * I., etc., etc*, etc., The Foreign Office.Ho. 77. BRITISH CONSULATK, AI-tWAE, 6th November 1934. 24 Sir, 11th referfnee to your telegram Ho. 33 of the 2nd Instant, regarding the American aviators who landed recently at Moh&amp;mmerah, I have the honour to confirm my telegram of November 4 as follow© :~ ■‘American aeroplane landed at Nohammer ah with engine tx^ouble on the afternoon of October 23. /ifter short delay ,/right flew to Abadan where technical aeaistance was given by Captain Cummins and M© mechanic©. Pollando having no papers in his possession was prevented from going to Abadan and was detained at Police headquarters at Mohammerah for several hour© until //right returned with their naesports. Mr. .Ford acted as interpreter. There was no question of prison. The aeroplane was detained as the Director of Customs did not understand Foreign Office certificate regarding competitors in the race and he referred to higher authority for Instructions. In the evening both pilots proceeded to Abadan and slept there. The General Manager of the Anglo Persian Oil Company, who has already sent full details to Tehran at the request of the United states Minister, now informs me that the aeroplane was not ready until the following afternoon, by which time permission was given to leave. / Captain Cummin© is now in Kishm. Mr. Ford ha© already given all i nfo rma t i on in his pose ess ion. 2. My information on this subject 1© based solely on the B1r Keginald M. hoare, ft. G «M• G .» Hi© Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc., etc.» etc., British Legation, Tehran.V the statements of various members of the Anglo Persian )il Company. They were the only -uropeans who had any contact with the aviators. The United States Minister is under a misapprehension as to any Consular intervention. ho auch assistance was requested and, in point of fact, the staff of the Consulate was unaware that any incident had taken place until long after it was all over. 3. The General Manager of the agio Persian Oil Company professes great indignation at the broadersting of th© names of isambera of his staff who were connected with this incident. He considers it moat undesirable that they should be identified with any complaints against the actions of the Persian authorities. Mr. Ilfcington is no doubt right if there is any risk of their statements being made use of officially, or, sti11 worse.communicated to the nreee. J have therefore agreed not to press for any further statements. The version of the affair which he gave to me yesterday is perhaps tinged with a certain bitterness against these Americans and their Press activities. I understand that they left Persia with the avowed intention of ’'putting it on 55 the map’% They wex*@ dissuaded from telegraphing their affidavit from Abadan. It is now suggested that their wrath against the delay which undoubtedly occurred owing to their papers being questioned by the local authorities was perhaps a convenient cloak to cover certain deficiencies in their aircraft widen were the cause of their forced landing at Mohammerah and of their prolonged stay in Abadan. I have, etc., (Signed) A, SI* fa tk in son, H.B.M, f S OOHSUL F'R KKIT&amp;I ST AN •,/ / Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P.£. 26 ' SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Date. Initials. Dated Rec. SUBJECT. 193 To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee... 7 . Under Secretary Secretary of State Previous papers :— fcu. i/k BAHREIN . The Itoiteci states' Senate's reservation to its ratification of the Geneva Arms Traffic Convention of ms. Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. please see previous submission on P.Z»42Q7/34, flagged below. It will be remembered that the U.S. senate attached to their ratification of the Intentional Arms Traffic Convention of 1925 a reservation that •adherence to the Treaty is not to be construed as denying any right of sovereignty which the Kingdom of Persia may have in and to the Persian Gulf or to the waters thereof 11 . It was agreed that further enquiry should be made at Washington as to this rather obscure reservation and its source. 2. considerable correspondence has since taken place between the Foreign Office and the Ambassador at Washington, which, on account of its embarrassing nature, was not at,/ 2730 1000 4.34at first circulated to the otlaer DepartcaeBtiS» It will fee seen from Washington telegram of lath July, on P.Z.5747/34, that the reservation is the result of representations made hy the Persian Minister to the State Department; that the State Department having refused to cooperate, the matter was taken up with Senator'King, whofreadily agreed to the Persian request, and who asked for, hut apparently failed to secure, the State Department* s assistance in the reservation. Ihe precautions taken hy the State Dept, to secure the rejection of the reservation when it came up in the Senate proved ineffective, for reasons of internal American politics, and it was in these circumstances that the reservation was passed hy the Senate. Accordingly, our efforts were at first eoncentmted to securing either that the President disavowal the reservation, or that some public explanatory statement, whether in the form of an exchange of notes or otherwise, should he issued hy the WlC/ f ^ United States Government. At this stage it apMaMd that the reservation should properly have been held to have been *of a substantive rather than an interpretative x nature and that this will require its acceptance hy all other signatories. Obviously H.M.G. and probably other governments would demur*. The CounselArof the French Embassy on the 6th September made it clear to the Foreign Office that this view was taken by the French Government. &amp;v f- 3. On 6th December, sir R. Lindsay reported that the President had decided to ask the Chairman of the senate Committee on Foreign Relations to have the Arms Traffic Convention withdrawn completely at the beginning of the next session. The effect of this would be to make it possible for the senate to ratify the Convention without reservation. Even should this fail, the Head of the Eastern Department was of opinion that the President*would neverthe- refuse to sign the ratification of the Convention with the/ % J /Vvs-^. K &lt; \-w. ^ jAV*^ qJVJ'A-, w^JU* ‘vt /!!, ^ ! U t S ^''' : Wvi Minute Paper. 27 3 . Department. the Persian reservation, and he has since teen instructed that will definitely refuse the reservation if it is attached to the United States act of ratification*. '4-' 'hr ottwu*- c%nJX •-/ *Wr^£~+-Jt r n u -gz, (M- tt is very satisfactory to have got matters to this point (as the Foreign office have made clear in their despatch 922 of 29th October to Washington, on P.Z.6782/34, nothing short of complete withdrawal ■ of the reservation would really meet the case from our point of view). Fortunately (paragraph 3 of Washington telegram 362 of 6th December)', the Persians w-A have handled the matter very badly at Washington. Not only at an earlier stage did they threaten the President that if he did not approve the reservation •there would be grave diplomatic repercussions' , (P.Z.7300/34), but their protest against the sale of Bahrein oil to Japan was clumsily handled. The difficulties, too, which appear to have been placed by Persia in the way of two American competitors in the Melbourne Air Race and which led to the very sharply worded note of 9th November (p.z.7593/34) cannot have done much to improve the atmosphere. For the moment we can but await developments. * (T'* &lt;• ft29 % i 77 '/p / / / C l Lj.SP.i- MO DISTRIBUTION. Decypher, D. R. No.582* Sir R. Lindsay, (Washington), 6th December, 1954. 7.05 p.nu 6th December, 1954. 9.00 a.m. 7th December, 1954. -0-0-0~0-0“0-0-0~ Confidential. Yonr despatch No.922. I asked Head of Eastern Department today how matter of Persian reservation stood. He replied that President has decided to ask Chairman of Senate Committee on foreign Relations to have Arms Traffic Convention withdrawn completely at begin- ning of next session. This may not he quite easy as personal prestige of individual senators is involved; hut Head of Department thinks success prohahle. Effect would he to clear the slate completely and make it possible for Senate to ratify Convention without reservation* 2. Head of Department thinks that even if this action by Senate fails to materialise, President would nevertheless refuse to sign ratification of convention with Persian reserve- tion* 5. Persian Government seem to have done nearly everything possible to spoil their own case here. ( Group undea) of first consignment of american oil from Bahrein has just been sold to japan and Persian Government have warned Japanese Government that oil has been wrongfully obtained and that Japanese Govern ment will he held responsible for payment of its value to Persian Government. This clearly impugns validity of American concession in Bahrein. Moreover State Department clearly dislikes Persian claim to 12 mile limit. It anticipates that AmericanAmerican tankers will be frequently visiting Persian Gulf and fears complications involved in this claim. 4. He asked whether His Majesty’s Government would definitely refuse reservation if it was attached to United States act of ratification. 1 said i thought they certainly would, hut that I had no definite instructions from you. He said it would greatly assist administration in its dealings with Senate if I could make definite statement to Secretary of State in this sense. 5. Can you authorise me to speak so to Secretary ol State?copy . (K 7534/2956/34) WO DISTRIBOTIorr . Cypher telegram to sir R. Undeay (Washington). Foreign Office. 13th December, 1934. 3.30 p.ra. No. 302. Your telegram No, 382 (of December 6th: united States reservation about Persian Gulf to United States ratification of 1926 Arms Traffic Convention)• You may speak to Secretary of State as proposed.COPY, (E 7078/6803/54) No. 1209. BRITISH EMBASSY WASHINGTON, D.C., November 13th, 1934 Sir, With reference to paragraph 4 of my despatch No, 1187 o f the 6th instant I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of a communique issued by the State Department, which contains the text of the note which the United. States Minister at Tehran has been instructed to communicate to the Persian Government in regard to the detention of two American competitors in the Melbourne Air Race 2. As you will observe the note is couched in fairljr strong language. I have, etc., f (Signed) R.C. Lindsay. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I*, K.C,V,0«,I DEPARTMENT OF STATE FOR THE PRESS GUN FUTURE ite-VEii 7593 | v!ber 9 , rgl- E C0HFID5HTIAL RELEASE FOR PUBLICATIOI? IH THE MORHIHG I15-.73- PAPER3 OF SATURDAY. NOVEMBER 10, 1934, '.'/KICH DO HOT APPEAR OH THE ST REET S BEFORE 3:30 P.li ., EASTERS STANDARD TIRE, FRIDAY, H0VSL1BER 9. HOT TO BE PREVIOUSLY PUBLISHES, QUOTED FROM OR USED IH AKY 'JAY The Department has instructed the Honorate!e Nilliam H. Hornihrook, American Minister at Teheran, to deliver to the Persian Government a note, the text of which follows, concerning the difficulties experienced by Messrs. John H. Wright and John Polando, American contestants in the handi cap division of the England-Australia air derby, when they were forced to land between Mohammerah and Abadan on Octo ber 23 because af minor engine trouble: n The Government of the United States is reliably informed that when Messrs. Wright and Polando, two of the American flyers in the MacRobertson International Air Race, were forced to land near Abadan on October 23 because of minor engine trouble, their passports were seized and held for nearly twenty-four hours and their plane was detained by Persian authorities until the following afternoon. The seizure of their passports, which bore valid Persian visas, was tantamount to the detention of their persons since they obviously could not proceed without travel documents. Apparently the sole reason advanced by the local director of customs for detaining their plane until the afternoon of^ October 24 was that he did not understand from tne^ certificate issued by the Persian Foreign Office^ tnat Messrs. Wright and Polando were contestants in the^ race and he accordingly referred the matter to higher authority for instructions. 'In view of the official assurances understood to have been given by the Persian Government prior to the race that blanket permission had been granted to al contestants to fly over Persia, ana thau it v/as pre pared to render all possible aid to facilitate t^e race, the American Government is at a loss to under stand the action of the Persian authorities in seizing the passports of the American flyers and in detaining their plane for a full day after they^had seen compellea to make an emergency landing on the direct route of tn^ race. 'It may be added that the lack of consideration shown to these two American flyers under the excep ally difficult circumstances in which they were place has made a most unfavorable impression m the United States.' * * *I* ■■■f In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. £ ua.j,V' and address —not to any person by'namefhxxt to— !• * “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, .&lt;? P. z • sw - 1 - i 7300 THE Under-Secretary of State ^ffairi presents his compliments to ^ S&gt;4w-jri_^ *] and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copiftC of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193^ ' l ^ Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000183_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3819</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000183</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3819</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/100 'Bahrain. (Persian claim to,): Geneva Arms Traffic Convention of 1925:- Reservation of the United States Senate to its ratification'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-08T15:32:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (71 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 71; these numbers are printed, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the attaching of a reservation by the United States Senate to its ratification of the Geneva Arms Traffic Convention of 1925 [the Geneva Protocol]. The reservation stated that adherence to the treaty should not be construed as denying any right of sovereignty of the Government of Persia to the Persian Gulf and its waters. The reservation had serious diplomatic implications for the British Government in view of Persia's claim to Bahrain. The file contains correspondence between the Foreign Office and the British Embassy, Washington, recording British objections to the reservation, the response of the US Government, and the reasons for the attaching of the reservation. The Geneva Arms Traffic Convention was eventually ratified by the United States Senate (without the reservation) in March 1935.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Senate</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Geneva Arms Traffic Convention (1925)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial waters</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000183#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>