<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023442225.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T14:55:18.067Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i E xtract of a letter from Lieutenant General Sir J ames O utram , G. C. B , to the Right Honorable Viscount C anning , Governor General of India, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. Dated Bushire, Srd May 1857. I am most sincerely gratified to be able to announce to your Lordship, that I now find myself fully warranted in carrying out the arrangements which I informed your Lordship on the 6th ultimo, I purposed effecting on the receipt of the instruc tions I then looked for consequent on the expected immediate ratification of the Treaty, which I had hoped would leave me full discretion as to the Troops and positions to be retained in Persia, pending the fulfilment of the conditions. In this I was disap pointed, three months were to be awaited for the Shah's ratification, and no discretion was left to me to weaken the forces in Persia prior to that ratification, consequently I had to take measures to accommodate all the Troops as best I could for that period at least, though much indeed to my regret, and disappointment. The arrangements accordingly resolved on, I reported to Lord Clarendon on the 22nd ultimo, as I in formed your Lordship next day in forwarding copy of that dispatch. On my arrival here, however, I received such positive assurances from the Per sian Commander-in-Chief in this quarter, that the Shah had already ratified the Treaty, as to warrant the confidence that a very few days must bring an Official announce ment of the fact from Mr. Murray, this, coupled with the desire expressed by the Bombay Government, in dispatches, received the night before last, for the return to India of all the Europeans I could spare, decided me to assume the responsibility of carrying out the arrangements I had originally contemplated, i. e. withdrawing the Troops from Mohumra, and leaving its occupation to the Navy alone, and sending to India what Troops are not required to maintain Bushire and Karak. In consultution with General Jacob, I have decided on retaining at those positions only Native Infantry (5 Regiments), all the Artillery now here (one Troop Horse Ar tillery, and two Foot Batteries European, and one Company Golundauze,) and with the exception of the Aden Detachment, all the Cavalry (Srd Light Cavalry, Jacob's' Horse, and Poona Horse.) The Aden Detachment I purpose sending there direct from hence, as at this season the winds are always favorable. Had I had any misgivings, your Lordship has now most considerately relieved me from anv dread of the responsibility I incur, by your Telegraphic message sent to mc, through the Bombay Government, empowering me ' to send back the European Troops at my discretion.' The dispatch containing this intimation, through some mistake was not landed with the rest of the Mail, and did not reach me until after my official dis patch to your Lordship, of yesterday's date, had been written. I need hardly add that it is a satisfaction to me to know that I had anticipated your Lordship's wishes. Thus three European Regiments (64th, 78th, and 2nd Europeans) one Troop Horse Artillery and one Foot Battery (European), and one Native Regiment (Light Battalion) will re turn to India. I send back the Light Battalion, because I am very sensible how very detrimental it must be to the ten Regiments of the Bombay Army, from which it is composed, each being deprived of an entire Company, and three European Officers; it is right that I should state that I myself am responsible for the formation of this Batta lion, it having been embodied at my own special request.Iii my Official of yesterday I mentioned my intention to defer moving the Troops until the ratification of the Treaty is officially announced, but the Naval authorities have since informed me that it will be impossible for the Regiment destined for Belgaum to reach Vingorla, the nearest port to that station, later than the 22nd or 25th of this month, should the monsoon have set in as it usually does about that date. That Regiment is If. M. 64th, whosej families are at Belgaum, any delay in despatching which would involve a further separation of the men from their families, of several months, till after the monsoon, besides putting the Bombay Government to the inconvenience of providing temporary barracks for more European iroops than can be conveniently quartered in nombay and Pooha, which stations only would be accessible during the monsoon. I have determined therefore to embark the 64th at once in the Punjauh and two transports, the order has been issued, and I trust it will be off in 8 days, in time to insure its arrival in ^ ingorla before the commencement of the monsoon. I certainly should have hesitated ere sending back all the European Infantry, and had determined to keep one Regiment here, as calculated to give heart to the Native Troops, though certainly I have never seen our Sepoys in better spirits than those now in 1 eisia, until (loneral Jacob expressed his willingness to remain in command of this Division, if I desirod it, an act ot selt-denial on the part of that noble soldier most truly admirable, for I know he yearns to return to the Sind Frontier now that there is no prospect of active service in Persia. General Jacob's presence here, i.^ ot more importance than the retention of a whole Regiment of Europeans, for where he is, there never can be any want of confidence, all ranks, officers and men, white faces or black, regard General Jacob with equal devotion, and his influence with Troops is such as I have never seen surpassed in the thirty-three years I have served in the Army. But General Jacob should be supreme here, and I shall consider that it will be advantageous to the state, when I can transfer to that officer, all the Military and Political Powers with which I myself am vested. In which confidence your Lordship need have no hesitation in summoning me to India, whenever my services mav be required there. I have, &amp;c., rr r . (Signed) J. O uteam. io The Right Honorable Viscount C anning, Governor General of India. h Kxtuact from an Official letter from Lieutenant General Sir James Outram, K. C B, to the address of the Bight Hon'ble the Earl of Clarendon K. G. and G. C. B., H. M.'s Principal Secretary of State. Dated Bagdad, 2%th May 1857. 1 llave callcd u I' on Brigadier General Jacob, C. for a supplementary list of meritorious services, and as soon as a reply thereto reaches me, I shall do myself the honor of submitting it to your Lordship. At the head of that list, I shall place the name of ioneral Jacob himself, whom I shall most strongly recommend for some adequate re cognition of his well earned claim to a reward. It was at my special request that that i • lssu ' aod th&lt;! Command at Bushire on my departure for Mohnmra, nobly fore going thereby an opportunity for distinguishing himself, which no man would' lightly relinquish 1 he assurance that a man of such renowned bravery and skill held the com mand of that important position, relieved me of a great responsibility, at the same time, !u ,l!ersTt T 7 mCeC !T hiSSmaI, forCe Was by 3,1 Arm y 80 vas % ^rior in nun ,ers, a ask which demanded unwearied vigilance and consummate military skill It was I feel persuaded, the importance and possible danger of the post for which I Pros,! cT of ' hlra ' ^ indU ^ d Genera, JilCOb t0 f0reg0 80 rCad ^ the more rartai ' 1 inspect of winning renown at Mohumra, and I rely with confidence on your Lordship's appreciation of such self-devotion, and on your influence in obtaining for it its due re- waul from Her Majesty's Government, on my being able to submit to your Lordship the Supplementary List above alluded to. *E xtract from a demi-official letter from Lieutenant General Sir J ames O utram, K. C. B., to the address of the Right Hon'ble R. V ernon S mith, M. P., President of the Board of Control. Dated Bagdad, 2%th May 1857. ' I must further depend upon your interest to support my application in favor of General Jacob, as soon as I am able to make any specific request in his behalf. Far from having exaggerated the importance of his services in my despatch to Lord Cla rendon, I feel how very imperfectly I have dwelt upon them; but my earnest hope is that they will be adequately rewarded by II. M .'s Government.' E xtract from a demi-official letter from the same, to the address of Ross D onelly M angles , Esq. M. P., Chairman of the Court of Directors of the Hon'ble East India Company. Dated Bagdad, 2Sth May 1857. «It is unnecessary here to recapitulate the services of those for whom I have solicited rewards, since they are enumerated in detail in the accompanying despatches; but when I am enabled to do full justice to the claims of General Jacob and to make a specific request in his behalf, I shall rely upon the Court to back up my recommen dation. Jacob's name is too well known in the records of our Indian Military Annals, to require any allusion from me to his past services; but those which he has rendered to this Expedition, are such as to demand from me special notice, as I trust they will be deemed worthy of some distinguished recognition.' True Extracts. (Signed) Chas. Hervet, Captain, A. D. C. and Private Secy, to Sir James Outram:. No. 29. The Chief of the Staff, Persian Expeditionary Force. Brigadier General John Jacob , C. B., Commanding the Troops, Bushire. Dated Bagdad, 29M May 1857. S IR) —I have the honor to acquaint you that it is the intention of the Lieutenant General Commanding, to submit to Government a separate recommendatory list of the Force under your command which held the post of Bushire during the operations of Mohumra and up to the ratification of the Peace. T am therefore commanded to request you will be so good as to forward to me with as little delay as possible, the names of such Officers as you may wish to have included in this list, in order that no time may be lost in submitting them together with your own for the special consideration of Government. I have, &amp;c.. (Signed) E. Lugard , Brig. General, Chief of the Staff, Persian Expeditionary Force. From To4 From To Brigadier General John Jacob , C. B., Commanding at Bushire. Brigadier General E. Lugaed , C. B., Chief of the Staff in Persia. Dated Buthire, Ikth June 1857. Sir ,—As directed I have the honor to forward the accompanying list of Officers and men recommended for the decoration of the Victoria Cross, for acts of daring, collective and individual, at Bushire and Ivooshab, 2. I have the honor to forward also the accompanying concise, and excellent re port received from Colonel Trevelyan, Commandant of Artillery, regarding the pro ceedings ol that arm in the action of Kooshab, with reference to which, although I am unable to recommend any individual for special acts of daring, I beg respectfullv to observe that the conduct of the Officers and men mentioned by Colonel Trevelyan, and more especially that of Captains Gibbard and Hatch, appears to me to be well worthv of honorable notice. » 3. I have made the fullest enquiries and have satisfied myself of the correctness of all that I have here recorded. 4. Similar enquiries regarding the proceedings of the Poona Horse at Kooshai have not enabled me to discover, that any individual of that Corps, or the Corps col lectively, is deserving of special commendatory notice, beyond that which they have aheady recened in the despatches of General Sir James Outram. o. In confirmation of this opinion, I have the honor to transmit herewith the report of Colonel Tapp on the subject of the conduct and proceedings of the Corps at the battle of Kooshab, comment on which appears to me to be needles. I have the honor to be, &amp;c., (Signed) John Jacor , Brigadier General, Commanding at Bushire. R eport of proceedings and conduct of the Poona Irregular Horse in the action of Kooshab as called for by letter from the Assistant Adjutant General Pei&amp;ian l^ield Force, No. 260, dated 10th June 1857. The Squadron formed part of the advance guard on the night of the 7th February when the enemy attacked the Rear it was ordered to support the Rear Guard, aud w« agam called to the advance when the enemy made its appearance in that quarter ! Tnd 146 Sabres. having had to detach (30J thirty men during the night, it remained as per margin till the subsequent action was over. ' 1 ' | en . ''? , fofce w 1 as halted the protection of the Baggage, and the enemy had ceased their mght attack, the squadron was drawn up at the left rear corner of the square. , ■ ' ln ul . , ' a ' V t '' 0 ellc |' 1 }&gt; tih then invisible, opened a fire of musketry on my right wbtch, by increasing and rap.dly extending towards its left, showed me that a large body wt there forming up into line There was no time for hesitation nor to await orders' We were much exposed, and the enemy quite secured from any fire by a line of sand Wis which protected them, 1 consequently wheeled a Troop to the righ, and by an oblique and rapid movement reaching the left of the enemy's fire, I wheeled to the loft and charged, my other Proop following as a support, The effect on the enemy wis most astonishing ! They had been taken by surprise, and having no lime to make any orma ion oi icsi, ance, t leir Line soon became a confused mass between the two Troops' t of th Tf remaiued ' and as none 'f the enemy asked for quarter mo5 t them were destroyed . their standard bearer was killed, and the standard of the1st Kushkai Regiment of Fars fas the inscription on the silver hand showed) was taken. Mv men were greatly excited by seeing the head of one of the first of their comrades who fell, cut off and carried away, (subsequently recovered), and as many of their swords had been broken across the muskets with which the enemy attempted to defend them selves, it was with a shout that they received the order to 74 in number. ' out Revolvers,' and almost all discharged their six barrels within a few inches of their foe! And thus was the Kushkai Regiment destroyed, in the centre of the enemy's force. In the meantime the enemy's Cavalry, which had been formed in their rear, moved rapidly off, but an Infantry Corps, on the right of the Kushkai, ' formed square'' which was most gallantly charged by the 3rd Light Cavalry, who nobly took advantage of such an opportunity. The smallness of our loss I can only attribute to the nature of our oblique move ment and flank ' Charge,' which so took the enemy by surprise, as in a great measure to paralyse them. The subsequent movements of the day, when the Cavalry Brigade was pursuing a flying and disorganized enemy, were of minor importance: two guns were taken, one of which was spiked by the Poona Horse. T was throughout the whole period looking out for an attack from the enemy's Ca valry, which had so early withdrawn, but which however unfortunately did not again appear. A number of ammunition mules were secured, and between three and four hun dred stand of arms were picked up by the Cavalry Brigade whilst returning, and were deposited at the Bivouac. I cannot sufficiently speak of the steadiness of the Poona Horse, or of the zeal and vigour with which they acted throughout the day, and where all behaved so well, it is diflicult to particularize. Lieutenant and Adjutant La Touche, most ably and gallantly supported me with the 2nd Troop, and deserved my warmest thanks for his conduct throughout the day. Doctor Rogers was most active and energetic, and his kind attention to the wound ed of the Poona Horse, as well as all others whom he could find, cannot be too highly praised. Khunday Rao Pole (the Senior Native Officer) commanded the supporting Troop in a most efficient manner, and his steadiness throughout the day is deserving of the highest praise. The following Native Officers and men I beg to bring to notice for ' distinguished conduct— Hussain Bux, my Wordee Major, who, charged by my side in front' of the leading Troop, and most nobly assisted me. Russuldar Ahmed Ali Khan, who commanded the leading Troop, with much gallantry and success. Bargeer Goolam Ilussain Khan, killed the standard Bearer, and captured the standard. Bargeer Shumshoo Deen, spiked the gun with a horse shoe nail, driving it in with the butt of his Carbine, which (as we were obliged to leave it during our advance) was a most efficient service. Sillidar Mahomed Ali, when his horse was killed in the midst of the enemy, transferred the equipments to the back of a captured mule, on which he took his place in the ranks, and performed his duties during the remainder of the action. Though called on to report only on the Poona Horse, I trust that I may be permitted to speak of the gallantry and energy of my Brigade Major, Lieutenant Frankland, of the 2nd E. L. I., who, till unfortunately shot by a man whom he was in the act of cutting down, rendered me most efficient service. (Signed) Tjios. Tapp , Lieut. Colonel, Commanding Poona Irregular Horse, and 1st Cavalry Brigade in the action of Kooshab. Camp Bubhire, * 2th June, 1858.6 List of Officers and Men recommended for the decoration of the Victoria Cross for their conduct in the battle of Khooshab, under command of Lieutenant General Sir James Outram, K. C. B., &amp;c. &amp;c on tlie 8th February 1857. JJushire, \3th June 1857. Rank and Names. Major Foebes , Command ing 3rd Light Cavalry Capt. Graves , Command ing 3rd Regiment Bombay Light Cavalry Remarks. At the battle of Kooshab, Major Forbes observing a column of the enemy's Infantry advancing towards him, immediatelv proceeded to attack them. Major Forbes had with him an hun dred and twenty men of his Regiment, that is, a number about equal to one weak squadron ; observing his advance on them, the enemy's column halted and formed square in the most regular manner—the column consisted of one strong Regiment, one side of the square was just equal to the front of Major Forbes' at tacking squadron. The square was formed with perfect regula rity with bayonets fixed and the front ranks kneeling, its fire was given closely, rapidly and steadily ; the enemy's Infantry appeared fully confident in the strength of their array, and there appeared to be no wavering in their ranks. Major Forbes led the squadron at the utmost speed of their horses straight down on the square, and without the least check or hesitation every horseman went through the kneeling and standing ranks. In one instant the square was broken to pieces, great numbers of men who had composed it were left dead on the spot and the remainder dispersed in flight. In closing with the Infantry square, Major Forbes was severely wounded by a musket shot through the thigh: but, notwithstanding liis wound, after executing this destructive charge on the square Major Forbes, with Captains Moore and Wren, and such men as they had been able to keep together, after riding through the Infantry, instantly fell on the Persian Artillery, about 200 yards in rear of the broken square; Major Forbes himself, killed two of the Artillerymen, and Captain Moore, three of the drivers of one of the guns (a brass 9-pounder), which they thus took and for a considerable time kept possession of under a heavy fire of musketry from the Persian Infantry who were all around them. In this encounter. Captain Moore's horse was killed, and this accident alone prevented him from at once carrying oft' the gun they had taken which was ultimately left on the ground. After the fight at the gun. Major Forbes was compelled by loss of blood to leave the field. This Officer succeeded to the command of the Regiment on Major Forbes becoming disabled by his wound. He did most gallant service throughout the day—repeatedly charging the enemy with invariable success wherever and whenever he could get at them, and having been personally engaged in a severe struggle for one of the enemy's guns, which he finally captured after hard fighting. At the commencement of the action. Captain Graves was sent by Major Forbes closely to examine the enemy's line of battle, and lie performed this most dangerous and difficult duty in a manner deserving of the greatest admiration. Commencing at the left of the Persian line.7 Hank and Names. Remarks. Captain Moore „ Wren Lieut, and Adjt. Moore. j, Spens „ Malcolmson Cornet Combe Hill Captain Oldfield Lieutenant Legeyt Cornet Currie Ridino; Master Brooks.... Havildar Rungeet Sing^ 3rd Bombay Light Cavalry. Captain Graves, accompanied by four Troopers only, rode along the whole front of the enemy's army at about 200 yards distance, under a continual fire of Artillery and Musketry ; and, having succeeded in observing everything unhurt, returned, and re ported the result of his observations in the coolest manner possible. These Officers were present with the squadron with which Major Forbes destroyed the Infantry square, they were all, of course, in front, and were all among the first to break into the bayonets ; in effecting which. Captain Wren's horse was shot in three places, one musket ball fired by a man of the kneeling ranks entering the front of the horse's neck, and coming out of his withers without apparently interfering with or delaying the animal's progress in the least. , In closing with the square also Captain Moore's horse receiv ed three musket balls. The horse of Cornet Combe was severely wounded in three places—two balls and a sword cut— and that of Cornet Spens by a bayonet. Lieutenant Moore, the Adjutant of the Regiment, was perhaps the first of all by a horse's length :—his horse leaped into the square aild instantly fell dead, crushing down his rider and breaking his sword as he fell amid the broken ranks of the enemy. Lieutenant Moore speedily extricated himself and attempted with his broken sword to force his way through the press, but he would assuredly have lost his life, had not the gallant young Lieutenant Malcolmson, observing his peril, fought his way to his dismounted comrade through a crowd of enemies to his rescue, and, giving him his stirrup, safely carried him through everything out of the throng. The thoughtfulness for others, cool determination, devoted courage, ready activity shewn in extreme danger by this young Officer, Lieutenant Malcolmson, appears to me to be most ad mirable and to be worthy of the highest honor. These Officers behaved most gallantly throughout the day. Captain Oldfield's squadron took one of the guns which was captured and remained in possession of the British at Kooshab. The enemy fought hard for the possession of this gun, and all those around it were killed before the piece could be finally secured. This man has now been promoted to the Commissioned rank of Jemedar. In the charge of the square was shot through the centre of the breast, the ball entering in front and lodging under his shoulder blade. The wound did not check his progress in the least and he entered the square close to Lieutenant Moore ; after riding through the square he was with Major Forbes in the attack on the enemy's guns, and there received a second wound which immediately took from him the power of using his arms. He however contrived to retain hold of and return his sword, and went on until the men reformed for another charge after the fight at the guns, when coming up to his Commanding Officer, the Havildar saluted him—told him that he was sho'-8 Rank and Names. Trooper Lall Kuan. Remarks- through the chest, and that he knew that his wounds were mortal, but that he did not mind losing his life in the least if his Officers thought he had done his duty bravely. Havildar fnow Jemadar) Runjeet Singh has not yet recovered of his wounds, but is doing well. This man, Lali Khan, was with Captain Moore in the attack on the enemy's Artillery after the destruction of the square, dismounted under a heavy fire, and at Captain Moore's order mounted the leading horse of the Persian Gun, which Captain Moore was endeavouring to carry off from the midst of' the enemy as described above ; and had not Captain Moore's horse just then fallen dead, the attempt would have proved successful. In considering the degree of merit due to Major Forbes and his Regiment on that day, it should be borne in mind—that the particular Regiment that was attacked and destroyed on that occasion was some 800 strong, and was one of the very best in the Persian Regular Army ; that the soldiers composing it were fine, tall, strong, athletic men from Northern Persia, that they were perfectly well accoutred, armed and drilled according to the best European model, that they were formed in square in the most approved regular manner, four deep with two ranks kneeling, that they stood perfectly firm and steady until the Cavalry sprang into their ranks, and on them, that they gave their fire with rapidity and precision up to the last moment, that this fire was such that, of the eight European Officers who were engaged in this Charge,, and their horses, five were either killed or wounded, as they closed at speed with the enemy ; one horse dropping dead as he sprang into the square, and two others receiving three musket balls each, while Major Forbes the leader of the whole, was himself shot through the thigh ; and lastly, that the number of British Cavalry engaged in this particular Charge was, when Major Forbes commenced his attack, one hundred and twenty men, and that, as many men and horses were shot during the advance, not more than about 100 could actually have fallen on the enemy who had thus the odds of 8 to 1 in his favor. After the fullest enquiry, I am myself quite satisfied, that the undermentioned Officers, and men of the 3rd Regiment Light Cavalry, are well deserving of the high distinction of the ' Victoria Cross' for their conduct at Kooshab, on the 8th February 1857, for which I beg earnestly to recommend them. Their order of merit in my opinion being as I have placed their names : Major Forbes, Lieutenant Malcolmson, Lieutenant and Adjutant Moore, Captain Moore, ., Graves, „ Wren, Lieutenant Spens, Cornet Combe, „ Hill, Captain Oldfield, Jemedar Runjeet Sing, Trooper Lall Khan.9 Rank and Names. Remarks. I have further to observe that though not actually engaged in the Charge on the enemy's square, the conduct of Lieutenant LeGeyt and Riding Master Brooke, appears to be worthy of distinction. It is found; quite impossible to specify other individual i instances of distinguished, bravery among the lower ranks of the Regiment, where all appear to have dbne their duty heroically,, but in addition to the list of n^mes giv;en above, I would re spectfully recommend that two Crosses be given to each Troop of the Regiment, according to the provisions of the Thirteenth Article of the Rules regarding the decoration of the Victoria. Cross. Private Kooda Buj , Ma-. | It is possible that the conduct for which these men are-now chee. Private Mctta Kuan , brought to notice, may not be such as is deemed to entitle men Soomra. 1st Compy, 211(1; to the decoration of the Victoria Cross, but it appears to me to. Belooch Regiment., j have been most meritorious and to be worthy of honorable notice, and if the Cross, can be given to.them, I think that tliey will well deserve the honor. After the battle of Kooshab, certain doolies, in which some- sick men- ; of the 78 th. Highlanders were being carried,. : were abandoned and left on the ground by the- bearers. The helpless European Soldiers would in alt probabi lity have been killed had not the men of the Belooch Regiment | volunteered to carry them on in the doolies, which they actually did, although themselves weary with marching. The two men whose names are given above were the first to set the-example* of carrying the doolies of the-European Soldiers, and afterwards, exerted the most themselves in doinjiso. (Signedj John Jacob, Brigadier General, Commanding at Bushire. No. 5/ of 1857. From Lieutenant Colonel Treveltan, Commanding Artillery Brigade, Persian Field Force. To The Assistant Adjutant General, Persian Field Force. Camp Bushire, 13th, June 1857. Sir ,—Having been called upon by Brigadier General Jacob, Commanding at Bushire to ««bmit for his information, the names of such of the Officers and men who composed e Artillery Brigade at Kooshab, under my command, and participated in the signal and ecisive victory gained-there by the Field Force under Lieutenant General Sir James^Outram Jv. C. B on the 8th February 1857, as might be considered worthy of mention with dis- — Z!7n 0 :; ^ 0n th - 0 ~' 1 110 the honor therewith to Stat, that of all the Officers.engaged in that action, none were-more conspicuous for the able and efficient: performance of their duties than Captains Hatch and, Gibhard, No. 3 and o L'ght 1-ield Batteries, the steadiness of whose formations at daylight and subsequent advance the quickness and accuracy of their fire, in conjunction with the rapidity of pursuit by the 3rd Troop Horse Artillery, resulted in the capture of two brass' 9-pou„ders and the destruction of great numbers of the enemy.10 2. In the acoampllshment of tliese results, the Horse Artillery commandecl by Rt. Major TMake, bore a prominent part, and the steadiness of their simultaneous formation with the Light Field Battery, and the efficacy of their fire were also quite satisfactory, and all that could be desired. 3. At one period of the engagement, two Horse Artillery Guns under Lieutenant T. Gibbard, that were detached in support of the Cavalry, attracted attention from the very efficient manner in which they were served, and the precision and eftect of their fire, and it may further be here mentioned, that the above named Officer, commanded with much credit to himself the guns on the rear guard, when the night attack commenced. 4. Captain Pottinger, the Brigade Major of Artillery, an Officer of old standing and much professional experience, exerted himself most 'zealously and usefully from the onset of the night attack until the termination of the engagement, communicating orders to Officers m diffeient paits of the position and Ime, and rendering every possible assist ance to me and the Brigade, that circumstances required, which service proved particularly valuable on such emergency, and tended materially, I conceive, to the attainment of the complete success of the Artillery operations at Kooshab. t). Although I am unable to particularize any act of individual gallantry from the absence of opportunity for such display (as far as concerned the Artillery), all ranks were steady under fire, and evinced a cheerful alacrity in performing the duties assigned to them, and whilst on this subject, 1 may add, that Captains Hatch and Gibbaixfare very desirous that I should bring especially to notice the excellent conduct of their Battery drivers, for exercising those praiseworthy qualities throughout the action. G. Moi co\ ei, the latter Officer, Captain Gibbard, is further desirous that the name of Sheikh Ameer, llavildar of Drivers^ who drove the leading pair of Horses in No. 2 Gun Team of his Battery, should be mentioned with distinction, for conducting himself on the occasion with, the greatest coolness, and at the same time encouraging tho other drivers, to follow his example^ i. AV ith reference to the foregoing, I would lieg to observe that 15 Officers of Artillery (exclusive of Medical Officers) were present at the battle of Kooshab, five of whose names, viz., Bt. Major Blake, Commanding 3rd troop H. A., Captain Pottinger, Majoi. of Brigade, Captains Hatch and Gibbard, Commanding Light Field Batteries, and Lieutenant 1. Gibbard, H. A.^ are&gt; for the reasons I have given, brought promi nently forward in this despatch, and with Sheikh Ameer, Havildar of Drivers, I would Respectfully but earnestly recommend them to the favorable consideration of the Briga dier General Commanding, and to the highest authority. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) H. VY. Theveltan, Lieutenant Colonel, Commandtng Artillery, P. F. F.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023442225.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/19, ff 1-6</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023442225.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/19, ff 1-6</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Extracts of official and Demi-Official letters from Lieutenant General Sir James Outram</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1857/1857</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-06-04T11:42:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The extracts relate to Sir James Outram's work in Persia as head of the Persian Expeditionary Force and discuss the conclusion of the force's work, troop withdrawals and recommendations for medals including the Victoria Cross. The extracts of correspondence include:Extract of a letter to Viscount Canning, Governor General of India, 3 May 1867, written from Bushire, regarding Outram's intentions relating to the withdrawal of troops from Persia, his disappointments at the ongoing delays in regards to ratification of the peace treaty with Persia and his eventual decisions of which troops to return to India and which regiments to keep at Bushire and Karak [Bandar-e-Charak].Extract of an official letter to the Earl of Clarendon, Her Majesty's Principal Secretary of State, 28 May 1857, written from Baghdad, regarding a list of individuals who should be considered for meritorious services and highlighting in particular the work of General John Jacob in having assumed command at Bushire following Outram's departure to Mohumra [Khorramshar].Extract of a demi-official letter to Robert Vernon Smith, MP, President of the Board of Control, 28 May 1857, written from Bagdad, requesting his support of Outram's request for recognition for General John Jacob.Extract of a demi-official letter to Ross Donelly Mangles, Chairman of the Court of Directors of the Honourable East India Company, 28 May 1857, written from Bagdad regarding the services of those whom Outram had solicited for rewards and again highlighting his application for recognition of General John Jacob's services to the expedition. [Letter signed by Charles Herbey, Aide-de-Camp and private secretary to Sir James Outram]Extract of a letter from Edward Lugard, Brigadier General, Chief of Staff, Persian Expeditionary Force, Bagdad to Brigadier General John Jacob, Commanding the Troops, Bushire, 29 May 1857 informing Jacob that the Lieutenant General Commanding of the Persian Expeditionary Force intends to recommend the force under his (Jacob)'s command at Bushire for rewards and asking that Jacob submit the names of any other officers he may wish to have included with that list.Extract of a letter from Brigadier General John Jacob, Commanding at Bushire, to Brigadier General Edward Lugard, Chief of the Staff in Persia 14 June 1857, forwarding a list of officers and men recommended for the Victoria Cross and also enclosing a report by Colonel Henry Willoughby Trevelyan of the proceedings of the Poona [Puna] irregular horse at Kooshab [Khaşab] as part of the Persian Field Force, written 10 June 1857 and supporting Colonel Trevelyan's recommendations in the report of them officers and men from that force that deserve recognition (the list of individual officers recommended by Colonel Trevelyan can be found at folios 3v-5).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023442225.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>