<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000070_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T16:47:20.643Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">© From To Fo. 'elegram , ^3 ,, Cornwallis, Baghdad. Political Agent, Bahrain. 10 Dated 30th; received 31st January 1943. From Bowlby: Please inform California Arabian Standard Oil Company that their offer of three 2000-barrel tanks cannot be accepted owing to poor condition of tanks and amount of recondi tioning work involved. 2. Please thank California Arabian Standard Oil Company for their offer. - Cornwallis -3 © (Origins! at page 227 of Ilisc.File) Telegram Tf ^ ,, i From Political, 3ahrain• To Foreign, Pew Delhi. 3epeated Ambassador. Daghdad. Fo. 704 Dated 19th October 1942. For Petroleum Officer f rom ^ridgemsn. . . ^ , 'here is a large quantity of petrfleum coke available i r. . am but it is mostly in powdered f orn and would have to be shipped in bags. _ .'“'i * r.d'/^dea j. essrs. .-ray llackenzie can spare the necessar^ lighters when required it should be oossible'to load occa- sional cargoes at the rate of 800 short tons of 2000 Ibs.oer horn uay. vessels would need to use their own power and winches for loading. I suggest that if Government of India is interested obey should approach Bahrain Petroleum Comoany direct for supply of sample shipment to ascertain whether this -fuel i&lt; suitable for Bombav mills. ' r“ ^Combustion^problem might probably be simplified if there is briquetting equipment in Bomba'- 7 . Analysis follows by bag. - Political - No. C/1594 To DXPKDSS LDTTDK Political Agency, Bahrain, 20th October 1942. Petroleum Officer, Government of India, New Delhi. Deference para 5 of my telegram No. 704 dated 19th October 1942 sent on behalf of Nr. Bridgeman. ^2, The Bahrain Petroleum Company have given the followin' tigures as being fairly representative of maximum, minimum ° and average tests of coke production Test Volatile Content V.C.M. (%) Sp.Grav. (H o 0=l) Sulphur ' (%) bttt // fax. 27'^ 1.35 5.5 10,000 Pin. 8^ 1.05 4.8 15,000 Averaa. 15.5 1.18 5.0 15,0000 s' Telegram S From Ambassador, Baghdad. To Minister of State, Cairo. No.46. Repeated Political A gent, Bahrain, No.7. Dated 26th received olst January li343. Advisory Following for Dunkley. I note from 27th meeting of the Petroleum Committee New Delhi on December 30th that since no reply had been received from Middle East regarding quantity of coke available from Bahrain for India reminder would be sent. 2. Its use is considered practicable provided price is not prohibitive, storage space could be made available and coke could be supplied to mills in briquetted form. 3. I understand it would need to be shipped in bags from Bahrain. 4. Do you wish me to take any action. - CORMAiiblS -OFFICE OF THE PETROLEUM REPRESENT AT IVI BRITISH EMBASSY, I send for disposal Bahrein Petroleum Co.*s Bill No.L.12-34. P' 5 ' Yours faithfully, A-S. PEIROLEUM DIVIBIO;? BBPRESEOTAIIVE. The Assistant Secretary, Miniatry of Fuel &amp; Power, Petroleum Division, 7 Millbank, LONDON, S.W.l. 20th January 1943. BAGDAD. Dear Sir BAjrCQ Sales to Assam Oil Co Copy to: Political Agency, BAHREIN.OFFICE OF THE PETROLEUM RSPRESSOTATIVE • i 20th January 1943 Dear Sir \gi^ PUHCIIAS.EB Fl,(M CASOC. I send for your information 2 copies of invoice and packing slip relating to material purchased fron Casoc by the Petroleum division. Casoc will later send a complete ir voice including cost of material, packing, marking, trucking and loading: I shall forward this when received. The Petroleum Division Agent, Abadan, will advise receipt of the material. PETROLSUiu DIV Id ION REPRISENTAl IVE Assistant Secretary, Ministry of Fuel &amp; Power, Petroleum Division, Hillbank, Yours faithfully, Copy tn: Uc A i li iu « L0?JD0N,S.Vv.lif V 2,500—5-42. (st.), r&gt; For use in Cypher or Coding Office only. Originators Instructions: (Indication of Priority, AID AC, NOTWT For Exercise). Intercept Group. TO: FROM: ^—T' 'gW—g?JB ,Mr. E. B. Wakefield His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter number C/131 of January 29 , 1943* We regret that we are unable to supply any welding electrodes to help Mr. Bowlby. Tours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL CdvIPANY By.4 THE BURMAH OIL CO. (INDIA TRADING), LIMITED. of 21st January 1943 to The Petroleum Officer, Defence Department, Government of India, New Delhi with purchase orders and invoices for 12 'boxes and 2835 pieces tubing. We have, however, been advised by our Kar ach i office that 12 boxes and 3340 pieces ^ b ci tubing have been discharged there by s.s. M Jalaganga”. We require, therefore, purchase order and invoice for 505 pieces 2 M Ups«t, Tubing to complete the shipment and shall be obliged if you will arrange to provide us with these documents. 14 Singl e Cylinder Engines ) 11,000 ft. 3 W Line Pipe ) We have also been advised by A/c Assam 'Oir~Co.Ltd., Digboi ) our Bombay agents that the above consignment was landed there ex H.T. ”Jalav^era' and consigned by the C.A.S.O.C. and we shall be pleased to receive as soon as possible signed Invoices in duplicate for this shipment. (INCORPORATED IN Post Box No.2039 Telephone cal. &lt;s?jc 7137 &amp; 7138 No.S.435 8, Dalhousie Square, Bast CALCUTTA, 1st February 1943 The Political Agent BAHREIN For attention - Mr.B.B. Wakefield Dear Sir We acknowledge copy of your Express Letter No.C/94 Yours faithfully, THE BURMAH OIL CO.(INDIA TRADING)LTD rlm/mkrTelegram From S Baghdad. To Government of India, New Delhi. No.43. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No.12. Datedith received 5th February 1943. From Bowlby for Defence Department for Petroleum Officer. Your letter dated January 11th. Vital n iut. for Assam Oil Company. Number the items on the list serially _______ in full items 2 15 17 23. 3. Item 7. 25 and 3 quarter inches Baker cement float shoes and 14 old fashioned type with drill-able cast iron back pressure valve. Item 9. 3 12 and 1 eighth inches standard model- reed rock bit heads with 2 Reamer bodies and 26 sets bit head cutters and 6 sets Reamer cutters. Item 13. Wilson 2 and 7 eighths inches roll over tongs. Item 14 can be supplied either 6 inches or 8 inches. Telegraph size. Item 19. Other types of over-shots are available. State sizes to catch and size to run in. Items 20 and 21. 7 and 3 quarter inches with 12 sets of cutters. 4. Telegraph shipping instructions of what you wish shipped. 5. Above excludes Bahrain contribution which will be notified later. - PRODROME _ ^Groups mutilated in transmission; correction to follow.r* e Mr, E. B. Wakefield His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Bear Sir: y Please refer to a letter from Mr. Bowlby dated January 19, 1943 requesting the release of certain drilling equipment for the Assam Oil Company. We regret that we do not have for release any of the items listed. Yours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANYDhahran, Saudi Arabia February 7, 1943 Mr. E. B. Wakefield His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter number C/72 of January l£, 1943. We have received the attached letter from the Burmah Oil Company (I*T # ) Ltd* There appears to be a good opportunity for further con fusing this issue unless you continue to keep the exchange of correspondence in the proper channels* We know nothing of any arrangements made between the Petroleum Officer, Defense Department, Government of India, New Delhi and H.M. Government’s representative* Whatever these arrangements were they should be clarified because, as you point out in your letter, this Company did not incur freight or insurance charges. If we are not correct in our assumption that it will be preferable for you to handle this matter please advise us so we can answer direct to Calcutta. Yours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY ®y , Attach: Copy letter S-432B. 0. C. (I.T.) LTD. / % I G 0 P Y Post Box No. 2039 8, Dalhousie Square, East, 7137 &amp; 713S No.3.432 1st February 1943 AIR MAIL Messrs. California Arabian Standard Oil Co.Ltd., AL KHOBAR Dear Sirs, DRILLING EQUIPMENT FOR ASSAM OIL CO.LTD..DIGBOI We would refer you to arrangements made between Petroleum. Officer, Defense Department, Government of India, New Delhi and H.M. Government’s representative in Abadan and would reouest that you air mail to us immediately two signed copies C.I.F. Invoices covering shipments already forwarded. Please also arrange to send this office by air mail all ''Shipping documents covering future shipments (irrespective of Indian Port consigned) including specifi cations and signed C.I.F, Invoices in duplicate. As a result of non-receipt from you of Invoices we have had to pay provisional customs duty on shipments already received, to be adjusted later on production of signed C.I.F. Invoices. Yours faithfully, THE BURMAH OIL CO. (INDIA TRADING) LTD. (Sgd. Alex. S. Teviotdale) For GENERAL MANAGER. Copy: The California Arabian Standard Oil Co.Ltd., Bahrein PMI/MKRDefence Officer, Awali. Dear Six', Shipment of 5,000 Barrel Steel Tank ex * Caaoc for j.D.A.« Abadan» e confirm having advised you chit the above material was shipped from Bahrein to Abadan per d .s.'Baroda’ 1 on 10th instant, and we have advised u . .T., Basra., by signal through the Naval authorities. JKLskka; Yours faithfully, Copy toj- Casoc 1. political Agent.. 3 . M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. ^^edfCnce Office Persian Gulf,Bahrain. No Def/S-27/ 33 / 43. Dated 1Ath February 1943* VL ^ M I forward in original which please return a request from Burma Shell Bombay, for invoice and certificate of origin in the case of 4 Welding Machines shipped to Bombay on S. S. Barala. I am not in possession of either of these documents, but your office may be able to assist. *), to ^ -p Your letter No-i C/1782 dated 26 Nov A2 refers. GDJ/ r* /_ w; Jt ^ 4 ^ ^ Lieut.Col. , Defence Officer Persian Gulf,BRN. (3D H.T.Hewitt).■Bki COPY iaT) v o ^^ BUBMAH SHELL Oil Storage and Distributing Co.of India Ltd. D/Sh. Bombay, 28th Jany., 1953• The Defence Officer, Bahrein, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir, 4 packages Telding I^achines £ *? With reference to the above consignment covered by your Shipping Advice and Delivery Note Manuscript No. A.F.W. 5175 dated 13th ultimo, will you please send us the relative Invoice and Certificate of Origin to enable us to meet the Customs requirements at an early date. Yours faithfully, 3d/- Illegible for Burmah Shell Oil Storage &amp; Distributing Co. of India Ltd.Dftahran, Saudi Arabia February 10, 1943 Mail Address: Bahrein Island Persian Gulf RENTAL OF WSLDIHG MACHINES W INDIA File: 069.2 OFFICE OF THE GENERAL MANAGER Burraah-Shall Oil Storage and Distributing Company of India, Ltd. P•0. Box 686 Bombay, India Pleas© refer tc your letter A/P.L.5 D/0 , DC f of January 4, 1943 to which was attached two copies of an approved Requisition covering the rental of four welding machines from us. The arrangements being made by you with the Chartered Bank of Indie, Australia, and China to remit hire charges direct to our San Francisco office is satisfactory. How ever, we would appreciate being advised of the dates the remittances go forward. Hire charges commenced on December 8, 1942, the day the equipment was shipped from our A1 Khobar terminal. e propose billing you quarterly for the rental of the machines. Three copiesof certified invoices will be mailed to the above address marked for attention of Mr. Donaldson. Flees© advise if our proposed billing program is not satisfactory. cc - 1etroleum Officer, Defence Department, Lew Delhi. A.Q&gt;U.G. (S.F.F.), New Delhi. HBM Political Agent, Bahrein Island \y Dear Hire: Yours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY By ORIGINAL SIGNED F S’. W. Oiiliger(§) No. C/257 Pclitical Agency, Bahrain, 23rd February *43 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A HBAIN I enclose a copy of a letter dated the 1st February 1943 which I have received from the Burmah Oil Co. (India Trading), Limited, Calcutta. The 12 boxes and 2835 pieces of tubing discharged at Karachi by s.s. ' f Jalaganga ,! were supplied by the California Arabian Standard Oil Company who sent me for transiaission to India the covering purchase orders and invoices. The question now arises about the purchase order and invoice for the balance of 505 pieces of 2' Upset Tubing discharged by s.s. ,, Jalaganga ,f at Karachi. These 505 pieces were, I believe, sup plied by you. Will you please confirm that this is so and let me have the necessary purchase order. I take it that the relevant invoice is No. F.V.12-32 dated 31st December 1942 of which a copy was sent through me to Mr. Bowlby. 2. In regard to the second paragraph of the enclosed letter I am making enquiries from CASOC about the 14 Single Cylinder Engines and 11000 ft. 3 ,f Line Pipe but shall be grateful if you will confirm that you have no knowledge of this consignment. Dear Sir, o.^ P | - Yours truly,No. C/258 Dear Sir, © Political Agency, Bahrain, 23rd February 1943 The Resident Manager, California Arabian Standard Oil Co., Dhahran. 9 . \\ I enclose an extract from a letter dated the 1st February 1943 which I have received from the Burmah Oil Co. (India Trading) Limited, Calcutta. I have no record of this consignment and do not think that it was shipped from Bahrain. Will you please confirm ? Yours truly, Political &gt;fgent,Bahrain. *CALIFORNIA. ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPAI'jl ,*14 / Dhahran, Saudi Arabia S / y February 22, 1943 SHIPMENT OF PIPE ^ ^ ETC.. TO ABADAN File: 620.52^ MR. S. B. WAKEFIELD, K. B. M f s Political Agent, 3 conies of enclosures sent to I’r. Manama, Bahrein Island. Bowlby under P.1,.No. C/270 dated 27th February 1943. Dear Sir: We are sending you, herewith, ten copies of our^ final invoice, covering cost of pipe* valves etc., and marking trucking and loading costs, on shipment recently made to Abadan * ■gill you kindly forward these invoices to the interested authorities as was done on former occasions. Yours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY Enel:OO-IO-I CA (11-41) December 31, 1942 CHARGE TO H. B tt M 9 a MINISTRY OF FUEL AND POWER, TERMS — CUSTOMER’S ORDER No. NV. No. SHIPPED TO_ FROM VIA _DATE_ _F. O.B. DESCRIPTION Amount due for materials shipped to Pctrciauin Daviaiu A...i; 4 as per our Invoice 12-8 (Copy attached) Harking, trucking and loading costs on materials billed on our Invoice 12-8 WE CERTIFT THAT THIS BHlL TH/iT PAT14ENT THEREFORE HAS fiOT CONDITIONS OF PURCHASE APPLICABLE TO THE TRANSACTION HAVE SEEN COMI 3 LIED WITH. SB:ZH QUANTITY PRICE AMOUNT t 26 , 654 .CB 3,753.80 &gt; 30.607.82 IS JtBT AND COHRBCT, BEEN liECEIVii , AND THAT ALL QEN'SRAL IHHAQER TOTALDhahran, Saudi Arabia, Dec ember 12, 1942 CHARGE TO avi J ' ' ' ABADAN! I B A H, ITT O' TERMS CUSTOMER’S ORDER No. I NV. No. 12 —S SHIPPED TO_ ■ T-,,- ■; ,.i ' . . from i,l Khobar VIA Bahrein Island _DATE_ fo b storeho use D hahran DESCRIPTION QUANTITY PRICE AMOUNT TOTAL Electric welded black line pipe, threaded end coupled, weight 11 lbs. per ft. Grade B, in random lengths varying from 28 to 32 ft,, 4' sis© (474 Joints) 15,008 rt .59 8,354.72 Sea 3 black line pipe, threaded and coupled, weight 11 lbs, per ft. Grad© G, in random lengths varying from 18 to 24 ft, 4 H sis© (441 Joints) 10,018 Ft, •65 0,5X1.70 Spiweld galvanized portable pipe with special couplings and gaskets for quick assembly and disassembly. Pipe is in 20 ft. lengths weighing 65 lbs. per joint 4” size (250 Joints) 5,000 Ft, 17.50 a joint 4,375*00 Seamless black line pipe, threaded and coupled, weight 3,75 lbs, per ft. Grade G, in random lengths varying from 18 to 24 ft, 2' size (411 Joints) 10,001 Pt^ .23 2,300.23 4 W yale portable pipe x 4' male pipe thread eep*»*ntors 2 l£&gt;t 5.40 4 n Female portable pipe, x 4” male pipe thread connectors 2 Lot 5.40 Gate valves, screwed, 250# per sq. inch steam working pressure, iron body, bronze trim, union bonnet, 4” 40 54.43 2,177.20 Nordstrom plug valve, screwed, 125# per sq, inch steam working pressure, iron body.a” 100 11,45 1,145.00 Globe valves, screwed, 150; per sq, inch steam working pressure, iron body, bronze trim, union bonnet, renewable nickel alloy seat and disc, 2 n 75 10.37 . 777.75 Carried ovej e e 26,152.40 QO-IO-I C A (3-41)■ Dhahran, Saudi Arabia* December 12, 1942 Sheet #2 of 2 yt f CHARGE TO fmmmu divisiom janr AB^DAtl. IliAH CUSTOMER’S ORDER No. NV. No. TERMS shipped t o the above addreas FRO M Al Khobar VIA Bahrein Island DATE. _F. O. B. Storehouse Dhahran DESCRIPTION QUANTITY PRICE AMOUNT TOTAL Brought 1 orward *. Globe Yalree, serewed, 125# per eq* In* steam fsorking pressure, serened bonnet. Integral •eats end renewable bronse disc* 2 M 1 H x §0 ft* Steam hose with 1” male pipe couplings at each end* Hon Is manufactured by the Goodall Rubber Products Go. in the U.S.A* (This hose is manufactured for steam service, and therefore the liners are not made of rubber products resistant to oil or gasoline. hile the hose could be used in gasoline service, it is doubtful if the service life would be very long.) 4” Rubber portable pipe gaskets 26 , 152.40 25 10 5.38 35.06 147.00 350.06 275 * # Price of 25 only charged. The rem&amp;indjer 250 included in price of 4 B portable pipe, COUNTRY OF 0RI0IK A HD MAH! IF A SPECIFIED HEctEIH IS THE U!IITET) certify that this bill is Just and correct, not been received, and that all conditions of transaction have oeen complied with. He G. K. DAVIS Kssimm uxmm cruriE •; or I . At. tha pure /? j. o. a Storekeeper G. A. Kl ■ a .i i t’A mn m Lot THE or it payme Hiase api, 4.56 MATERIAL AMERICA. nt therefor has licable to thn IX OO-IO-I CA ( 3 - 41 )Dhahran, Saudi Arabia February 27, 1943 Mr, E, B, Wakefield His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Dear Sir*. /HP Please refer to your letter C/25$ of February 23 rd. -f i' 35 We are as much at a loss as you are to explain the two items of equipment that letter S from the Burmah Oil Company (India Trading) Limited, Calcutta indicated that we shipped to Assam Oil Comoany, Digboi. We did, of course, send 25000 feet of 3 ” threaded line pipe, and it seems possible that Assam Oil Company reconsigned a portion of this pipe to Digboi. As you probably recall, the materials we shipped to the Assam Oil Company were as follows: 4400 ’ - 2 ” tubing Z % *—- j 23000 ’ - 2 j” tubing ^ ^ &amp;.3o^ s / 25000 ’ - 3 ' threaded pipe 1 * _ $ /7 ! 20000 ’ - 2 TT tlireaded pipe ^ | ' ...... xo o/&amp; 75 - 3 Tt valves 100 - 2 ?? valves ^ 5^ W., Yours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY By.^ r -2- $/■&gt;-* Telegram Q r r' r r Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Bahrain. From To No.17. Dated 26th received 28th February 1843. From Bowlby. Please refer to list equipment required for Assam dated January 19th. Any contributions. - CQRNWAhhlS.-( 34 ) Nq. C/285 Political Agency, Bahrain, 1st March 1943 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, Dear Sir, I understand that you were given by Mr. Bowlby a list of drilling equipment urgent ly required by the Assam Oil Company. The list was dated January 19th but a copy has not been sent to me. I have now received a telegram from Mr. Bowlby asking what items in the list the Bahrain Petroleum Company is able to release Would you kindly let me know as soon as possible what reply I should send. Yours truly, Political w it, BahrainTHE BAHREIN PETROLELi! OOiVlPAtJY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Please refer to your letter No. C/285 dated March 1, 1943. Mr. Bowlby T s list of requirements for the Assam Oil Company was received by us February 4, 1943. We immediately reviewed this list and have referred the matter to our Principals in New York. We will inform you immediately a reply is received. 7 7 « Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.No. C/322 Political Agency, Bahrain, 6th March 1943 To The Burmah Oil Co. (India Trading), Limited Post Box No. 2039, 8, Dalhousie Square, Kast, Calcutta. Dear Sir The California Arabian Standard Oil Company, A1 Khobar have forwarded to me for disposal your letter No. S.432 dated the 1st February 1943 in regard to invoices ancl shipping docu ments covering consignments of drilling equipment for the 2. 1 presume that you have by now received a copy of my Express letter No. C/94 dated the 21st January 1943 (with enclosures) addressed to the Petroleum Officer, Defence Department, New Delhi, which disposes of the matters raised by you in your letter under reply. 3. Any further correspondence in regard to shipments by the California Arabian Standard Oil Company for the Assam Oil Company Limited may kindly be addressed to me in future and not direct to the Company at A1 Khobar. Assam Oil Company Yours truly Political Agent, BahrainNo. C/323 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th March 1943. To f i | ; The Resident Manager, ^ California Arabian Standard Oil Company, Dhahran• \ _ . i . Dear Sir, Please ref eat to your letter dated the 7th February 1943. 2. I enclose for your information a copy of a letter which I have today addressed to the Burmah Oil Co. at Calcutta in reply to their letter No. S.432 dated the 1st February 1943. v 9 5 u a ~ 3 ^2 € £T \\- 3. I also enclose for your information a copy of my Express letter No. C/94 dated the 21st January 1943 to the Petroleum Officer, Defence Department, New Delhi, which was sent on receipt of your letter dated the 20th January*- ^ I i /£/Yours truly, Mfc'' Political AKent. BahrainConfidential No. C/334 Political Agency| Bahrain, 7th March 1943 To The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have been asked by Major Kankin, the M.E.S.C. representative at Baghdad, to let him know what the position is in regard to supplies of coke at Bahrain. He would like to know how much is available, what the price is and whe ther a sample could be sent to Basra for test. I understand that it is required to eke out bunker coal. 2. I believe that you have already had coke experts visiting you and it is possible that all the information Major Hankin requires is already available in Iraq. If this is so will you please let me know to whom Major Hankin should apply for the information he requires ? If the information required is not already available in Iraq would you kindly supply it now ? vburs truly, Political Agent, BahrainPA-760 lAiiruiiXj.-: Jrjii ix-cOL^i Ujvi vJvJi'/jiPAi.’'-* £ .uliviX x^ii) Aw all , Balire in i alaiid ; i’ersi iu Gulf b&lt; Late March 8 , 1943. 7 Please refer to your letter No. C/334 of 7th March requesting information on coke for the use of Major Hankin, M.E.S.C. representative H. B. M f s. Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir; / informati at Baghdad. I am attaching a memorandum which you can pass to Major Hankin for his information. We will he pleased to send him a sample on request hut believe he can procure a sample with less delay from the G-ray Mackenzie j. organization at Basra or Baghdad. I understand they have been marketing our coke in that area. c&gt; ^' ah Tours ve: W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.^ISIvIQI&amp;NDTJH - OCKZ 1 . Amount Coke Available I Arch 9, 1945 Coke production is not weighed nor are there any facilities avail able for weighing. Accumulated figures from monthly stock statements indicate approximately 240,000 tons of which QOfo of the rile should be recoverable. However, a recent survey of the pile indicated 120,000 tons (2,000$) available up to the roadway. This assumed a weight of 45$/C.F. which is conservative. The degree of packing in the pile due to trucking over it is an unknown factor, so there can easily be more coke available than the above figure would indicate. The actual figure, no doubt lies between the limits indicated. He suggest, for safety in any plans made, that the lower quan- titjr be used. 2. Current Production The current production of coke under normal conditions varies over a wide range and is controlled by economic considerations and stock out lets. In addition, at the present, due to the necessity of operating . under blackout conditions, coking operations are restricted so that drums are cleaned only during daylight hours. This is considered necessary from a safety standpoint. Under normal operating conditions, when operating to maximum coking consistent with the capacity of our units and taking into account normal operating factors, we estimate coke production at 13,000 tons/month. The amount actually produced would therefore lie somewhere between zero and this quantity dependent on economic factor. 3. Poke Analyses The following figures are submitted as being fairly representative of maximum, minimum and average tests of coke production; V. C. M. w 27* 8 * 15.5 Sp. G-rav. (HgO = 1) 1.35 1.05 1.18 Sulfur w 5.5 4.8 5.0 btu/# 16,000 15,000 15,600 Ash .7 .1 0.4 Moisture w 1.5 0.4 1.2 Wt. #/c.f. (loose) 50 44 46 Wt. ' ipaok:ed) 74 (est. ) 65 (est.) 68 Note; * Based on production sample analyses. Of 1,400 analyses 3&gt; are'below 8 VC' : and 6.7$ are above 27 VCM. The high sulfur content precludes the use of this coke for blacksmith or forging work.2 4. Coke Handling Proposals &lt;11 ■■i' 1 In 1938 some preliminary estimates were made as to the probable cost of various methods of handling coke for export shipment. Equipment was figured on the basis of 500 Tons per day with a maximum rate of 3 Tons per minute when drilling. No means of bulk handling have been installed to date but a brief description of the methods that have been considered are as fol- 1 ows: Trucking: Construct a direct road to Sitra Pier and employ Ford dump trucks for transportation. A 4.4 mile round trip haul is involved and 18 trucks were considered necessary. Native drivers would be used operating 24 hours per day. The coke would be piled at Sitra instead of at the Refinery. It would then be loaded onto barges for transportation to sjitpfs side, using a specially constructed feeder and belt conveyor system*between the coke pile and the pier. Barging equipment etc. are the same as for the railroad discussed below. Re ilroad Install a small railroad from the Refinery to accomplish the same thing as by trucking above. A trestle would be provided at Sitra to permit dumping the gondola cars and loading from pile to barge would be the same as with trucking. An engine and sufficient gondola cars to handle 180 tons coke at one time would be minimum requirements. For a 10,000 Ton cargo vessel which was assumed it was figured that a loading rate of 2,000 tons per day should be provided and that the shin would be capable of 25 ton lifts. Barges were estimated to handle 100 tons each split into four 25 ton compartments and to have a maximum draft of 4’. On the above basis 4 barges and 4 tugs are required. The belt conveyor was computed to load 100 tons in 13 minutes. A 36 tf width belt was assumed. In both of the proposals above, a new pier was considered essential. Flight Type Conveyor; As an alternate method to barging from Sitra pier to offshore boat, coke could be conveyed the entire distance from the Refinery to boat. A few figures were set up which indicated that this method would cost about twice as much as other methods, hence was not given further consideration. 5. Present Handling Facilities Lacking the above considered plans, it is necessary that the coke either be sacked at the pile or at some other^location on the^island, vor the short hauls, to Arabia, Iran and Iraq, native dhows ar6 being liaed Thev load the sacked coke at the Ifanama pier. it might be possib„e to arrange' bulk loading in these dhows either at the Manama pier or off shore at Sitra by using only hand loading methods.t - 3 - UNDDH PRESENT PLIHDLI^ I'CSTHCDS M u\ _ + Pa /n T v e C 0 J e is sold at the pile, on a run-of-the-pile basis, at Rs 10/0 per long ton of 2240 lbs. The cost of sacks, filling tra^s portation to Sitra pier, lightering to ship and loading on ship Is at present ^about Rs. 20/ ton, making a total of Rs. 30/0 per ton on ship, inis price will vary considerably depending on cost of sacks which at present market prices are Rs. 0/8 each sack holding about 150 lbs. Unless otherwise stated all tons shown are of 2,000 lbs.EXPRESS LBTTBR From - Political Agent, Bahrain* To - Major Hankin, Minbranch, c/o British Embassy, Baghdad• No* C/359 Dated 13th March 1943. f As desired by the Political Resident I enclose herewith a note on the coke position in Bahrain,supplied to me by the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. 2. The Company will be glad to send you a sample of coke on request but they think that you could procure a sample with less delay from Messrs. Gray Mackenzie at Basra or Baghdad. This firm have been marketing the Company^ coke in Iraq. Political Agent, BahrainCONFIDENTIAL, THE BAERSin PETROLEUM OOMPAX.Y LIGHTED ' Awali, Balirein Island, Persian Gulf Date March 17, 1943, No. C/PA-57 , His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. n •xtR # Dear Sir: / With reference to your letter No. C 285 of March 1, 1943, and our reply in letter No. C/PA-29 of March 2, 1943. Today we have received a reply from our Principals in New York regarding the release of drilling equipment to the Assam Oil Company, as requested by Mr. Bowlby in his letter of January 19, 1943. We wish to advise that we are able to release 10 - 6-5/8” Baker Cement Retainers for this purpose. We regret that we are unable to supply any of the other items of equipment requested. Our New York Office has instructed that we secure authorization for reimbursement in dollars in New York, as all of this equipment originally was shipped from the United States. Will you please inform Mr. Bowlby accordingly. Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. XDhahran, Saadi Arabia April 8 , 19A3 MAIL ADDRESS: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, RENTAL OF mDIHG MACHIHES TO INDIA __-g_ OFFICE OF m GSNBRAL MANAGER, Bur/nah-Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company of India, Ltd., P. 0, Box. 688 Bombay, India ■ie are in receipt of your letter of March 12, 1943 and vdsh to thank you for your telegraphic transfer of February 26th., to our San Francisco Office. Tour proposal that your next recdttance should cover the remainder of the period for which you should be liable for rental charges is entirely satisfactory to us. Upon arrival of the Welding Machines here in Arabia we shall forward to you a final statement of charges. Tours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY cc- Petroleum Officer, Defense Department, New Delhi. A.Q.U.Q. (S.P.P.), Hew Delhi. / H.B.M's. Political Agent, Bahrein Island. \/ Dear Sirs ' ^ . I t Wj ajuCALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY Dhahran, Saudi Arabia April 10,1943 MR. E. B. WAKEFIELD J H.B.M's. Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: We are sending you, invoice, covering cost of tank and dismantling, handling and marking costs on shipment made to Abadan February 10, 1943 via S.S. BARODA. Will you kindly forward these invoices to the interested authorities as was done on former occasions. SHIPMENT OF 5000 BARREL BOLTED STEEL TANK. File: 620.52 herewith, ten copies of our final F Yours very truly, A Wv '-’ t *' r *'*^CALIFORNIA. ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY d- aJL / f.L /S'. 4. 43 Enel: //1^1 o Telegram From To Repeated 28/28 u ? ( 4 i Ambassador, Baghdad. Tolitleal Agent, Bahrain. Government of India Defence Department lor Petroleum Officer telegram No. 103 from Bovvlby. No. 25 Dated and received the 13th April, 1943 Your telegram 230. Please ask Bahrain Petroleum Company to sh^p cen, s^x and live eights inch Ba/(er cement retainers consigned to Assam Co. Calcutta complete with invoices shipping documents e^c• so what articles can be cleared on arrival. o - AilBASSADOB - NCJ IJJdl iz/ct vThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited COHFIDSNTIAL Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. * No, PA~850 April 18, 1943. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir: xf-&gt;'• Through an unfortunate oversight your letter No. C/257 dated February 23, 1943, has remained unanswered. Tubing discharged by s.s. 'Jaladurga' at Karachi was supplied by the Bahrein Petroleum Company. In addition to this tubing, 3 Gas and Oil Separators and 3 boxes containing parts for these separators, were also Authorities and copies of our Shipping Notice No.11-8 dated November 9, 1942 (2 sheets) were handed over to Lieut-Colonel Hewitt for necessary distribution. You are correct in your assumption that Invoice No.F.V.12-32 dated December 31, 1942, which was sent to Mr. Bowlby through your Office\ covers the ^quipment included in this shipment. As regards the purchase order, our only authorization covering the purchase of this equipment is contained in your confidential letter No. C/1510 dated October 5, 1942. the 14 single cylinder engines and 11,000 ft. 3' line pipe mentioned in the second paragraph of your letter. May I take this opportunity of apologizing for the delay in answering your letter. I wish to confirm that the 505 pieces of 2” External Upset included in the consignment. The handling of this shipment was done by the local Military Also, I wish to confirm that the Company has no knowledge of Yours very truly W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED,THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED COIOTDENTIA1 Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. r No. PA-851. April 18, 1943. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Bahrein. •7° Dear Sir: I wish to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. C/527 dated April 15, 1943, requesting the shipment of ten 6-5/8” Baker Cement Retainers In the case of the previ the Assam Oil Company, you will recall that I requested information regarding the method of billing in my letter No. CON-325 dated'November 8, 1942. In your reply, letter No. C.1712 dated November 9, 1942, you stated that the question had been referred to Mr. Bowlby. Because no further information was received on this subject, our Invoice No. F.Y.11-32 dated December 31, 1942, was sent to Mr, Bowlby through your Office. Since that time we have had no confirmation if this method of billing was satisfactory or not. rization for reimbursement in dollars in New York for the present material (refer last paragraph of our letter No. C/PA-37 dated March 17, 1943), I would be glad if you would obtain confimation of this method of payment and also confirm the method of billing. If a purchase order is required by the consignee, as would appear to be the case from your letter No. 0/257' dated February 23, 1943, may I point out that our only authorization for the shipment of this material is your letter No. C/527 dated April 15, 1943, and to the Assam Oil Company, Calcutta Inasmuch as our Principals have instructed that we obtain autho- suggest that you take up this matter with Mr. Bowlby.' In the meantime, the equipment will be made ready for shipment and all necessary documents prepared in accordance with your present instructions. Yours very truly W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDNo. C/581 To Political Agency, Bahrain, 29th April 1943. -1 i \ The Burniah Oil Co. (India Trading), Limited, Post Box No. 2039, 8, Dalhousie Square Kast, Calcutta. e.\\ Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. S.435 dated the let February 1943. 2. I enclose a copy of the invoice relative to the consignment of the 505 pieces 2' upset tubing ex 3.3. ^Jalagahga**, and a copy of the Shipping Notice. Please note that the consignors were B.A.P.C.O. and not C.A.S.O.C. 3. There is no Purchase Order, but the Bahrain Petro leum Company arranged shipment of this material on the strength of my letter No. C/1510 dated 5th October 1942 to them. I enclose copies of the relevant correspondence for your information x | ( 1. Extract of paragraph 2 of telegram No. 3^' dated the 23rd September 1942 from the Petroleum Division Representative, Baghdad. -T 2. Telegram No. 40 dated 2nd October 1942 from Petroleum Division representative, Baghdad. 3. Letter No. C/1510 dated the 5th October 1942 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the j Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. 4. Reference paragraph 2 of your letter. Neither C.A.S.O.C. nor B.A.P.C.O have any knowledge of thisf^ consignment ex H.T. M Jalaveera*. . Yours truly, for Political Agent,Bahrain, 4 itf vpoints arising in connection wi+h the shipment of this and other material. Extract of paragraph of telegram No. 34 dated the 23rd September 1942 from Mr. Bov/lby, Petroleum Division Representative, care of British Embassy, Baghdad, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. * *** *** 4** ** ** «« 2. Your 4260. I am arranging for military autho rities to ship to Calcutta for Assam Oil Company the following obtainable from CASOC except where particularly stated t- Two inch tubing 4400 feet end 15,000 feet from BAPCO. * v * *** *** Copy of telegram No. 40 dated 2nd October 1942 from Mr. Bowl by, Petroleum Divison Rep resentative, Baghdad, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. My telegram No. 299 to Government of India repeated to you as telegram No. 34. Petroleum Divison has not telegraphed dis agreeing with disposal of material listed. 2. Please inform BAPCO and CASOC and ask them to prepare goods for shipment to Calcutta marked CYB. AOC• 3. I cm communicating with 0 Movements for slipping facilities as military stores. Copy of letter No. C/1510 dated 5th October 1942 from the Political Agent,Bahrain, to the Chief Local Reoresentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co.,Ltd., Bahrain. My Bowlby has informed me that he is in communication with Q Movements in regard to f aeilitj»s for shipping to Calcutta for the Assam Oil Company the following material from the Balirain Petroleum Company;- Two inch tubing - 15000 feet Gas separators two and three 2. Will you please prepare these goods for shipment marked CYB.AOC. 3. Mr* Bridgeman is expected to arrive in Bahrain on October Sth and will be prepared to discuss any® THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. April 28, 1943. CONFIDENTIAL 1 NO. PA-872 H. B..M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: Further to my confidential letter No. PA-851 dated April 18, 1943, I now wish to inform you that the ten 6-5/8” Baker Cement Retainers are ready for shipment to the Assam Oil Company, Calcutta. Manama, together with shipping papers and F.O.B. invoice (copy of which is attached) with instructions that these documents together with the Bill of Lading be air-mailed to the Assam Oil Company when the material is shipped. Inasmuch as we do not have the necessary authority, may I suggest that you instruct Messrs. Gray Mackenzie 8 c Co. Ltd. to ship the material and indicate to them who will pay the freight (i.e. 'freight collect' or charge Mr. Bowlby’s organization through your office). This method of handling i,s x the only one which will comply with the instructions in your letter No. C/527. If we handle the shipping it will be impossible to prepare the invoice until the freight costs are known. encing due to the lack of specific instructions to the notice of those concerned in order that they may be eliminated in any possible future releases of material. An order from the purchasing company together with detailed shipping and billing instructions would fulfill our requirements. in my letter No. PA-851 at your earliest convenience in order that we may complete our account The material will be delivered to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., I would be glad if you would bring all the difficulties we are experi In the meantime, I would be glad to receive the answers to the queries Attach: W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED v- . , ■ ~ WThe Assam Oil Company, CALCUTTA . April 29th, 1943. A \ ^6 V--.. Vt 1 ?.7. 4-33 To Cost of 10- 6-5/8 n Baker Cement Retainers supplied to you per H#B.M»s Political Agent's letter Ifc. c/527 dated ^)rll 15, 1943 (Including transportation charges to Manama) ... ... ... $ 1,782.90 (One thousand seren hundred eighty two &amp; 90/100 Dollars only)fi Telegram From To Fepeated Dated 1st Ambassador, Baghdad• Government of India, Few Delhi political Agent, Bahrain. Fo. received 2 nd Fay, 1943. . Fo. 113 30 i' Following for Defence Department for Petroleum officer from Bowlby. Your telegram 1819. BAPCG request confirmation of payment in dollars in Few ^ r ork. 2. Political Agent Bahrain should instruct Fray Fackenzie to arrange shipment. FCJ - AMBASSADOR - l( Lfl'U IMemorandum To: Political Agent, BAHREIN, 0 Office of the Petroleum Division Representative. British Embassy, Baghdad. 1st May, 1943* (g&gt; L i r Copy to Petroleum Officer, Defence Department, 1 Government of India. ' % ^ , f. I refer to your telegram No.307 of April 26 th and confirm my telegram No.25 of April 13th wherein I requested you to ask the Bahrein Petroleum Co. to ship to Calcutta ten 6 5/3“ Baker Cement retainers which the Assam Oil Co. wish to purchase. The retainers will be shipped by Gray Mackenzie, and not as military stores, and I suggest that the Bahrein Petroleum Co. bi3.1 the Assam Oil Co. direct at 8 Dalhousie Square, Calcutta. 2. I have telegraphed to the Defence Department, Govern ment of India, seeking confirmation that payment will be made in dollars in New York. /tv ^ ^/; — © to Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Lto. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADFNHALL STREET, LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AM A RAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUN DAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS L1NGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BA I SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO.. L/281. 19 43 .: &gt;51 © £ O -t ;r The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We hav£ to acknov/ledge receipt of your letter No.C/647 of date, and on receipt of the Cement Retainers we will arrange shipment to Calcutta, sending you our bill of charges in accordance with your instructions. In the meantime, kindly advise us if the shipment is to be insured. Yours faithfully, a •--r~ mKA.'vNo. C/669 To Political Agency, Bahrain, 18th May 1943( Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, ■Reference your letter No. L/281 dated the 13th May 1943 regard ing shipment of Cement Retainers. 2. The shipment may kindly be insured. Yours.truly, Political Agent,Bahrain.Bhahran, Saudi Arabia May 19, 1943 Return address: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf Bunnah-Shell Oil Storage &amp; Distributing Company of India, Ltd Imperial Chemical House Ballard Sstate Bombay, India VISIDIMG MACHINES Gentlemen: The bad condition in which the four welding machines reached you, described in your letter A/P.L«5 B/0 , DC I of April 26, is as disconcerting to us as the report of j^our Chief Engineer on their condition must have been to you. It was not our intention to( s^nd equipment that could not be used, and accord ingly the following cable was^ispatched to you May 17th: ”REGRET MACHINES ARRIVED UNUSABLE stop THEY URGENTLY REOUIRED HERE PLE/IjE CONTACT CAPTAIN SMITH CALTEX BOMBAY MO WILL ARRANGE SHIPMENT WE WILL desire to help the Allied War Effort in evety way possible. They were old, however, and when Mr. Wakefield, Political Agent, Bahrein inquired about obtain ing welding machines from us we pointed out that the only ones we had had seen a considerable amount of service. We did tell hi®, however, that they were still in serviceable condition. the time they were shipped. Two of these three had been returned from Bahrein only a month or so previously, where they had been on rental to the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited and used throughout a rush construction job. The fourth had been inactive for a number of months prior to shipment. All of them had been tuned and cheeked in our shops before sending them on to you. They are f the same age, and have had about the same amount of service, as all of our other welding machines, and all of them are in active service now. Arabia to Bombay were handled by military authorities. They were picked up at A1 Khobar by a sailing dhow arranged by the Military, and we were not to be res ponsible for any handling from that point onward. They were trans-shipped at Bahrein. It appears to us that the machines were damaged both by salt water spray and by theft while enroute. They Eiay have been subjected, also, to a certain amount of deliberate tampering, as indicated by the punctured tires and the tube being in ribbons. and encrusted with salt, indicates quite definitely that they were subjected to salt water spray somewhere enroute* The damage to the voltage regulator, which you say could not be moved, may have been due, also, to salt water spray, he know that all of the regulators were in working order and that none of the machines were encrusted with salt when they left here last December. ABSORB EXPENSE' |C| Our only purpose in renting these machines to you was a sincere Three of the four machines sent to you were in active service up to All arrangements for shipping these units from Al Khobar, Saudi Your statement that two of the machines were soaked with salt water yn.n'.w#2 W® are unable to account for your statement that one of these machines looked as though it had been on fire* To the best of our knowledge none of them had ever been in a fire. The hoods over the units, however, had become somewhat battered and damaged during three or four years service on construction work, and they did not look good* It may be that their damaged condition gave the appear ance of having been on fire, but we do not understand even this. fie can only account for the missing governor control spring on one of the machines, the missing high-tension wiring between the magneto and the spark plugs on another, and the fact that there were only six welding cables instead of the eight shipped by us, by the probability that these items were stolen enroute. These machines were tested, and operated, just before they were shipped, and our records indicate that they were complete and serviceable at that time. Your complaint about the poor condition of the tires does not surprise us greatly. Three of the machines were equipped with 9x13 low pressure sand tires which were in relatively poor condition* V-e, however, would have expected to have gotten considerable life from them in their intended service. The fourth machine was equipped with high pressure tires which were in relatively good condi tion. Hone of the tubes in these tires were punctured, and none in ribbons, as you report they were received. The relatively poor condition of the sand tires, we might explain, is due to our practice of transferring worn tires from automotive equipment to welding machines and other similar equipment, where the tires get little wear, and where deterioration results primarily from sunlight, heat, and oxidation. The 9x13 sand tires are inflated to 3 - 12 pounds pressure only, and at these low pressures they give months of service with thin carcasses or broken side walls. Gould it be possible that someone unknowingly attempted to inflate these low pressure tires to 30 or 40 pounds, pressure, which they would not be expected to withstand? Even high pressure tires in such poor condition would blow out imme diately. Ic presume that your comment on the lack of ’’screens, glasses, etc.” refers to what we call ’’masks” and ’’goggles”. In American practice such items as sasks, goggles, and gloves are considered to be part of a welders personal equip ment, and not part of the equipment supplied with welding machines. It never occurred to us that you had made no provision for such consumable items. While it may not be economic to return these machines to Saudi Arabia, they are the only kind of welding machines we have, and we are depending on them to carry on our work. We have not received any new machines since before the war, and we do not anticipate receiving others for the duration. Consequently, we are prepared to pay the cost of returning them, and we presume you have contacted Captain I. B. Smith of Caltex (India) ULmited, Bombay, as requested in our cable, so that he can arrange early shipment up the Persian Gulf. We regret that the welding machines which we provided for your emergency program were of no use on arrival. We do not feel, however, that it would be fair for us to commit ourselves to a settlement for their hire until we have had an opportunity to review the damage they sustained since leaving our hands. Yours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY ORIGINAL SIGNED Bl cc-Fr.E. B.Wakefield,Bahrein B Y F. W. OLliger A copy of Burmah-Shell’s F. W. OHLIGER letter on this subject is General Manager attached for your information.BURMAH-SHELL OIL STORAGE &amp; DISTRIBUTING COMPANY OF INDIA, LTD. Imperial Chemical House Ballard Estate Bombay, India In Reply Please Refer to A/P.L.5 D/O 26th April, 1943 *DC« Messrs. The California Arabian Standard Oil Co., Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. &lt;/’ Dear Sir, ^ WELDING SETS ON HIRE . We refer to correspondence regarding the 4 welding sets hired to us for a Government Project by an arrangement made through the Quartermaster-General in India. This rests with your letter to us Ref. 069.2 of 10th February and our reply dated 12th March, the position being that we have paid hire up to the end of February in accordance with the Conditions of Rental which we accepted# In the circumstances of a rush job, it was overlooked at the time when this payment was made thaj/ihe sets had arrived in such bad condition that it was only possible to make limited use of one out of the 4 machines. We enclose copy of a report dated 11th March from our Chief Engineer which describes the condition of the machines. Apart from the fact that we did not obtain service from these machines, you will note that he concludes by saying that they are hardly worth the expense of returning them to you. Under these circumstances, we should be glad to have your confirmation that you wish the machines returned. Alternatively if you wish, we could see what price is obtainable for the machines in Bombay. There is a shortage of such equipment in India and it is possible that an Engineering firm with facilities for overhaul might be able to offer a good price having regard to their condition. As regards payment, we have no doubt that your management was unaware of the condition of the machines when they were shipped, and as we on our part have delayed in informing you about this, we suggest, for your consideration, that despite the agreed Conditions of Rental, the payment already made should be allowed to stand but that any further expenses in connection with these machines should be for your account. We shall be glad to have your view of these suggestions, and if you could kindly advise us by cable it would assist in disposing of the matter. Yours faithfully. BURMAH-SHELL OIL STORAGE &amp; DISTBTG: CO.OF INDIA LTD. (SIGNED) For GENERAL MANAGER IN INDIA. c.c.A.Q.M.G.(POL)-Ref his E-in-C 1 s Branch E4A., p.O*(DD), New Delhi. 82003/q. 1(P0L) of 21st April. G.H.Q.,New Delhi. E.\ N 0 TE C 0 p Y GENERAL MANAGER: Re Four Welding Sets ex Saudi Arabia * The four sets arrived *in a deplorable condition. Main faults can be enumerated thus s Set No.l appeared to have been on fire, and also well soaked with salt water. Governor control spring missing. Tyres, and tubes unserviceable. Set No.2 encrusted with salt water. Tyres and tubes unserviceable. Voltage regulator could not be moved. Engine will run but no regulation of welding current can be obtained. Set No.3 Rather better looking. Lacked High Tension wires from magneto to plugs. Tyres fair, tubes all punctured. Set No.4 As No.3&gt; rather better looking. One tube in ribbons. Equipment consisted of six cables only - no screens, glasses, etc., ~ without which the sets could not be used. Of the three sets which we have sent out only one is capable of welding. We did not consider it worth while to undertake proper overhauls, as they would certainly have been expensive both in time and money. As the sets stand they cannot be classed as much better than ^unk*. In our opinion, it is definitely uneconomic to ship these sets back to Saudi Arabia - or for that matter anywhere out of Bombay. They can only be used with advantage in a workshops where time can be spent on complete overhauls. Sd/~ Marr Grieve. Chief Engineer, Bombay i 11»3»43 » Bombay/Bhusawal Pipeline Construction . PCPBY AIR MAI L. ■It - w- y ■ *&gt; Gray, Mackenzie &amp; 1 %? i) o y (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) 122, LEADEN HALL STREET, LONDON, E.C.3. TELE GRAPH tC ADDRESS'. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSRE M. AM ARAB. KUT. KHORAMS HAHR AHWAZ (for BAN DAR-SHAH POUR) BUS H I RE. RAS TANURA BRANCHES: BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. D UBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. S2/34 Bahrain, 2nd June 19 43. Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Clearing and Forwarding Depart-nent, Bombay. Dear Sirs, Assam Oil Co., 10 Crates Cement Retainers Calcutt a 1/10’ Bapco ^hi^ngJtfoUce rn would advise having shipped the above crates to your port per ss. a Baroda r V.349 and snail be obliged ij. you will kindly arrange to clear and forward same to the Assam Oil Company,Calcutta f by the first available opportunity. ^ inclosed we hand you herewith relative original Bill of Lading Noi? together with one copy of dhipplng ^otice No:4~12 and one copy of suppliers* invoice lio.L-4-^18. Duplicate copy of the Bill of hading will be sent to you by the following air mail. We have insured the goods Bahrain/Bombay and have to request you to insure Bombay/Calcutta. All your charges in this connection may be debited to us,under advice. MS. cc.(1) ( 2 ) (3) (4) Yours faithfully, For GUAY, I ■ ' ^7' ' ' ' Bapco - Bahrain, i ( ref.their letter GM-444. The Polifeical Agent -Bahrain, y/ ref .his letter No.C/647 fp, ^ L 1 The Assam Oil Co.,Calcutta, v with 3 copies of 3/N 4-12 and one original invoice No.i^-4-18. Mr. W.H.Pinckard - New Yorklegram om To No. 334/6 Dated 4th Q Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Bahrain. received 5th June, 1943. From Bowlby. Assam uil Company urgently need 100 coupling for 3 inch standard tubing 11£ thread API. 2. I would much appreciate if BAPCO could assist by providing these even if second hand as other oil companies are unlikely to have them. COHNWALLIS -S'* Mammmmmmmrn ©'7 1 I No. C/769 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th June 1943. To The Chief Local Bepresentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have had a telegram from Mr. Bowlby at Baghdad saying that the Assam Oil Company urgently need 100 couplings for 3 inch standard tubing 11*5- thread API. He says tha^, as other oil companies are unlikely to have these couplings, he would very greatly appreciate it if you could assist by providing them, even if they are second hand. 2. Will you kindly let me know as soon as possible whether you are in a position to help ? Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrain. mmNo. C/791 To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th June 1943. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., ltd., Bahrain. Baker Cem ent Retainers oer s.s.'Baroda 11 Vov .349 to Bombay Dear Sir, Receipt is acknowledged of your letter No. 1/335 dated the 7th June 1943, with enclosure. Yours truly, Political Agent, BahrainNo.11/8D \ s'/)/' Office of the Petroleum sfy r Division ^Representative. / ' British Embassy, BAGDAD. ® &lt;z I 3rd June, 1943 . Dear Sir, i£L I now forward one signed an&amp;^dne duplicate copy of final invoice for the above tank. Your Agent at Abadan has advised me that the tank has been received conplete, and is in good condition. Would you please arrange settlement with D«A»E*O.C«? Copy to Petroleum Division A| ' M Political Agent, Bah: Yours faitJifally, H. S. BOWL BY Petroleum Division Representative. Assistant Secretary, Ministry of Fuel and Power Petroleum Division, IQ HDQa . E . 1 .* Dhahran, Saudi Arabia June 23, 1943* m. S. B. WAKEFIELD His Britannic ifej©sty’s Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Dear Sir*. Please refer to your letter Ho. 0/810. In order to keep you fully infoimed in regard to the Welding Machines rented to the Burmah-Shell Oil Storage &amp; Distributing Co. in India, we are attaching herewith three copies of two additional letters just received from Burmah-Shell, dated - (r ^sr ^# ^0 ^ h to May 18th. and May 28th. respectively. »ve presume you may wish to send coiipies of this correspondence on to Mr. Bowlby. For your information the welding machines have not yet arrived from India. CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANYHJHMAH - SHELL OIL STORAOS &amp; DISTHIBUTBfg CO. t OF INDIA, LTD. In Heply Please Pefer to 0/0 Bombay, 18th May, 1943. CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL CO., LTD., B A H R S IN. Dear Sirs, I'our .'•elding; Machines On Hire . •te thank you for your telegram of 15th May reading as follows •- ' your letter a/p.l.5 regret machines arrived unusable THEY URGii2:TLY REQUIRED HERE PLEASE CONTACT CAPTAIN SMITH CAL TEX BOMBAY WHO WILL ARRANGE SHIPMENT r 1E WILL ABSORB EXPENSE.' V7e are accordingly arranging to deliver the machines to Captain Smith of the Caltex Company here, who will arrange shipment. Yours faithfully, BURMAH-SHELL OIL STORAGE AND DISTRIBUTING CO. OF INDIA LTD. (Signed By P.D.M.Lingeman) For GENERAL MANAGER IN INDIA . Copy : Caltex for attention Captain Smith. RM‘ G ' 0 P Y OIL STORAGE mmm - shell &amp; DISTRIBUTING CO. t O F INDIA, LTD, In Reply Please Refer to W.P, D/0 'DC' BOMBAY, 28th May 1943. Ivlessrs. California Arabian Standard Oil Co., Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Saud i Arabia, Dear Sirs, YIELDING MACHINES : We thank you for your letter dated 19 th May under this heading and thank you for your full explanation of the matter which we are passing on to our Chief Engineer in case he has any further comments to offer. If available his comments will be forwarded with this letter.* At the moment we are making every endeavour to get three of these machines away by a ship which is sailing very shortly, but vie have been considerably hampered by export control and customs formalities and it is not xjuite certain whether we shall be able to get th^away by this opportunity. The fourth set was in use up-country and is unlikely to catch this steamer, but *wili be sent along with the others if this proves possible. As regards settlement, we feel that as we have had so very little use from these machines the suggestion made by us was a very fair one, and we trust that yon will be able to inform us of your agreement at &amp;n early date, as the accounts for the Project in question will shortly be closed. PDML:PCP Yours faithfully, BURMAH-SEELL OIL STORAGE AND DISTRIBUTING CO. OF INDIA LTD. (Signed By - P.D.M.Lingeman) For GENERAL i^ABAGER IN INDIA, * Our C.E. has nothing to add to his previous report.The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named x Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. 5/-16I Printed in England. Aug. 1941. (9,000 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in enoland.) Clerk’s . Time Circuit. Name. A Received. A \ 2133 DM493 S BAG H DTD TT/d^O 26 1955 F IL F AO ETAT BG POLITICAL BAHREIN (?' , ■ ■ 0 j 726 FROM VAN SICKLE YRTEL 425 YES CORNWALLIS t ± » MARK YOUR REPLY Jhn/ietuaC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY..fiafcr.ain.*..... .27th June.1943. i 9 _ IQ-Crates Baker Cement retainer to Assam Oil Coy,Calcutta Further to our letter Ko.L/335 of 7th inst,we send you herewith our debit note lffo*C&amp;F/675 being insurance charges on the above packages. Yours faithfully, EnelojD/Note &amp; Insurance Policy No.1276. C£B.N0.4-5/8D &amp; !T/ A &amp; i Office of the Petroleum ^^ Division Representative. British Embassy, BAGDAn. P'J 25th June, 194-3. My dear d/90? Thank you for your Memo G. 890. of June 13 th sending me copies of corres pondence about the C.A.S.O.C. welding machines. I fear that these machines received a buffeting and damage from salt water in transit: I know Ma* 1 #lGrieve, the engineer, and he is a man'of some directness 1 . ■ • ' v ' . I am shortly leaving Baghdad and do not expect to be back until the end of September; meantime van Sickle will reign in my stead. p) With kind regards, v fje } Yours sincerely, 'c E.B. Wakefield, Ssq. , I.C.S., Political Agent, BAHREIN. (TJiTkiPS/ *5// Bahrain, 7th July 43. 'A f The Assam Oil Company, Calcutta. Dear Sirs, Under instructions from H.B.M's Political Agent,Bahrain, we send you herewith Certificate of Origin covering shipment of Baker Cement Betainers, and trust same will be found in order. Yours faithfully, cc• The Political Agent, ref.his letter C/882 of a 1/7/1943.No. 3* 2950• MEMORANDUM. ® 41 * Dated, _ 88 th June.., 1943 .. From THE BURMAH OIL CO. (INDIA TRADING) LTD. (Incorporated in Scotland). P. O. Box 2039. 8, DALHOUSIE SQUARE, EAST, CALCUTTA. TblephoNe Nos. Cal. 7137 &amp; 7138, To The Polical Agent, BAHIIMN. Dear Sir, 'p We acknowledge receipt oDkyour Air hail letter No.C/811 of 13th instant handing us a Debit Nq#q received from lessrs. Gray, . lackenzie &amp; Go., Ltd., Bahrein, No.C. a F.639 for Rs.26/14/- being shipoing charges incurred on ten 6.5/8 u Baker Cement retainers shipped from Bahrein to Bombay. We have asked our Accounts Department to settle this amount. he also note that a further bill for insurance premium and for forwarding expenses from Bombay to Calcutta will follov/. Yours faithfully, TUB BUIIIAH OIL CO. (INDIA TRADING) LTD: For GCNBRAL hANAGBR SO- /f /7NA it&gt; /? /Lj. A-rJi ' &lt;- No. S«3232• MEMORANDUM. From THE BURMAH OIL CO. (INDIA TRADING) LTD. (Incorporated in Scotland). P. O. Box 2039. 8, DALHOUSIE SQUARE, EAST, CALCUTTA. Tblj ' JONE Nos. Cal. 7137 a 7138, Bated, _ Mth...July, 194 3.. To The Polltical Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We acknowledge receipt of your Air Mail letter No.C/883 of 1st instant handing us a Debit Note received from Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrein, No.C &amp; F/675 for Rs.120/- being insurance charges incurred on ten Baker Ces^ent Retainers shipped from Bahrein to Bombay. Our Accounts Department will arrange settlement • §£1 Yours faithfully, THE BURMA^tlL COY. (INDIA TRADING) LTD: MANAGER. j For GENERAL MANAGER. * /*-OFFIGS OF 1ES GENERAL Dhahran, Saudi Arabia Septester 29, 1943 RENTAL OF WELDING MACHINES TO INDIA MANAGER File:620 # 50 Buraiali Shell Oil Storage and Oistributing Coa^&gt;any of India, Ltd., P* 0* Box* 688 Mail Address: Bahrein Islands, Persian Gulf. Bombay, India Dear Sirs: ATTENTION: AE. DONALDSON We enclose, herewith, three copies of our invoice covering rental of our Welding ^ichine No. A 6x9, which was shipped to you on Decemoer 8 th, 1942. This invoice covers the period March 1st - September 30th, 1943 at the agreed upon rate of $100.00 U.S, Currency, per month. In view of your statement that the welding machines arrived in India in poor condition we agreed to cease rental charges on March 1st, and to pay for the immediate return of the machines to Arabia, with the understanding that all four machines would be returned as promptly as transportation could be arranged* Three of the machines were returned. We waited several months to hear from you regarding the fourth machine and on August 2nd we cabled you requesting that you expedite the return of this machine. Since we have heard nothing further in regard to your intentions as respects this machine, we are billing you in accordance with the Conditions of Rental, and would appreciate receiving your remittance either here or at our San Francisco Office. Since as stated in your letter W.P. D/0 ’DC* of May 28, I 943 that the 'project in question will shortly be closed', can you advise the approximate date on which the machine in question will be returned to us? be have an urgent need for welding machines at present and this need will continue for some time. Tours very truly. Copy forwarded to Pe droleui^^g^ ARABI an STANDARD OIL COMPANY DIv. Representative,Baghdad, under endorsement No.C/1319, dated 6-10-43, in continuation of me/no. No.C/880 dated 1- p.- OMC-IWT, SIGHS F. W. OHLIGSR General Manager Enel: cc- R.B.ids Political Agent, Bahrein -BURlftH SHELL OIL STORAGE AND DISTRIBUTING OOMPANT OF INDIA, Ltd., | ■■* 'IJf! 3 10/1 Telegram Inter *0* From Ambassador, Cairo. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Consul-General, Basra. Ambassador, Baghdad.) cavtimp M inister, Tehran. ) No. Mides MLsc 512. Dated 29th received 30th October, 1943. IMPORTANT. For Bahrain Petroleum Company. Question of briquetting coke in Egypt is again under urgent consideration, mut. we require a 500 repeat 500 ton parcel for trial. ? We a re in touch with ? Ministry of War Transport Cairo who require this parcel in bags (which will be supplied) to facilitate shipping. Explanatory letter follows by air but in meantime please telegraph following information urgently. 1. Minimum time for japatj. after receipt of bags. 2. Loading rate. 3. Current f.o.b. price. - Charge D f Affaires - NCJ /r /tjo Zo/loJk-Z r-* fc ‘ —IS ' ' 5 CUHFIDEMTIAL Ko.C/1463. \$\ To Political Agency, Bahrain, 30th October 1943• The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum C@#, Ltd., Avail* MBIaORAKDUM The following telegram has been received for you from the British Ambassador in Cairo:-* Question of briquetting coke Is again under urgent consideration in Egypt. 500 tons of coke are required for trial. ministry of War Transport in Cairo require the parcel in bags (which will be supplied) to facilitate shipping. Please telegraph the following information urgently (a) Loading rate (b) F.o.B.price . (e) Minimum time required for preparing aftaijfceceipt of bags. Explanatory letter follows by air.' ^vz/o Political Agent, Bahrain \28/28 Telegram inter ‘'O 1 * From Ambassador Cairo, To Political Agent* Bahrain. No. MIDES MISC 531 Dated and received the 4th November* 1943. IMMEDIATE . For Bahrain Petroleum Company. London pressing urgently reply to our MAST MIDES 512 in order to arrange ? shipment . - Charge D ! Affaires - NCJ )R 106'U-the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Awali Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. Wo. PA-522 H. B. M*s Political Agent The Agency 3AHEEDT Dear Sir: Noveraher 2, 1943 Pile: 565 s f I’Ol Please refer to your confidential memorandum No.C/1463 of 30th October 1943 transmitting a telegram received from the British Ambassador in Cairo requesting the following information on coke: (a) ' Loading Bate * It is assumed that the Ministry requires rate from shore to over ship’s side. Messrs. Gray Mackenzie would handle this portion of the work and their estimate is 2 days for 500 tons. (b) “ P.O.B. Price ' 0. 0 per ton (2250 lbs.) 8 . 0 ' ' ' 8 . 0 ' ' ' 8 . 0 ' TOTAL Ps.21. 8. 0 ' ' (c) 'Minimum time required for preparing after receipt of bags' 3 Days. Receipt of the letter referred to is awaited with interest and, in the meantime, the foregoing details will probably serve for purpose of estimate. Loose coke at pile Rs.10. Pilling and sewing sacks 2. Transportation from pile to Manama 2. Gray Mackenzie charge for off loading trucks.lightering to ship (estimated) 6. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative THEBHREIN PETROLSUM COMPANY LTD.,S. 1320f. NAVAL MESSAGE. For use in Cypher or Coding OiT.ce only Originators IrfStructions* Intercept Group, (Indication of Priority, Personal, NOTWT For Exercise). \ TO: From: Book or Table to be used for Initials of Cypherer or Coder 1 ime of Receipt in Cypher or Coding Office Date. Cyphering or Coding. Recyphering or Recoding St 2002 A. H. P jttifer. Acting Government Printer. T — * ■ -w... % . nm28/28 Telegram From To No. Dated IMMEDIATE Political Agent, Bahrain PA1C. Basra 772 11th November 1943. Your telegram MESC/72307 November 11th. 2. Please repeat reference number and date of telegram to v/hich reply desired Political28/28 01 Telegram XXX From P.A.I.C. Basra To Political Agebt, Bahrain *Jo. BB 698 Dated and received November 11th 1943. Your 772 of November 11th. Deply desired to E.K.S.C./71425 of 6th which is repeated herewith. Begins• ,T „ r , T ° Polios * 1 2 '“S* 31111 * Bahrain, from M.K.S.C. (i) P.A.I.C. NO.M.E.S.C./71425 November 5th 1850. It is planned to ship 500 repeat 500 tons of coke now held by Bahrain Petroleum Company for Briquetting in Egypt. This will necessitate provision of 10,000 repeat 10,000 sacks. • * ,; Please signal prospects q£ Bahrain Petroleum Company buying necessary quantity of second hand grain sacks locally. Grateful for assistance as no prospect of provision from other sources and experiment regarded as important. SECRET rTo.C/1558. Political Agency, Bahrain, 14th November 1943. Copy to: 1. The Chief LocalKepresentative, Bahrain Petroleum Company, Bahrain and 2. The Director of Customs, Bahrain, I understand that the sacks will be available and I have so informed middle East Sunply Centre. Perhaps Mr. Bussell Brown will deal direct with mp. G.W.R. Smith in this matter•IP025CM/ASD/5 Middle East Supply Centre, General Headquarters, Middle East CAIRO. 23th October, 1943. Dear Sirs, Petroleum Coke . .Further to our priority telegram No. 512 Hides Mise of today*s date. It will be remembered that the utilisation of the coke in your stock pile and of your current production was fully investigated at the end of 1342 and that early in this year attempts were made to bring a trial parcel to Egypt for briquetting. Non-availability of direct shipping from the Persian Gulf to the Gulf of Suez prevented the carrying, out of our briquetting trial at. Port Said. At the same time it was found that the supply and shipping position was such that little or no advantage would have been gained by drawing on the Bahrain supply. The matter was therefore dropped. in view of the somewhat changed conditions obtaining at the present time we again approached the authorities in London who* have telegraphed that the scheme is of interest. Upon receipt of this directive we contacted Messrs Savon of* Port Said, .wno were about to dismantle their plant and have been fortunate'in persuading them to postpone action pending the briquetting of a trial parcel of 500 tons of clke^ providing that the matter be dealt with urgently. Ministry of War Transport, Cairo will endeavour to arrange early shipment, details of which will be arranged on receipt of your reply to our above mentioned telegram. / « It is considered that such a small tonnage will be more easily handled in bags and these will be supplied to you, Messrs Savon have been asked and have agreed to treat the purchase on a normal commercial basis. Should the briquetting trial be sucessful and the pro-r cessed fuel prove suitable under conditions of essential use, we propose to discuss bulk shipments with you in Bahrain in the light of conditions obtaining on the island at the present time. - Yours faithfully, ?.?. Davidson, for Assistant Director, Industrial production. ‘The General Manager, Bahrain Petroleum Coy. Ltd., Aw all, Bahrain. PERSIAN GULF.-3 7 Telegram From 28 / 28 . Inter ‘0 *. H.M’s Ambassador, Cairo To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated to Consul General, Basra K.M 1 s Ambassador, Baghdad• H.M’s Minister, Tehran• ho. Hides Misc* 557. bated 15th and received 16th November 1943. V llviPUHTANT . For Bahrain Petroleum Company. Understand second hand grain sacks available with Gray Mackenzie on Bahrain. 2. Arrange reservation of sufficient sacks for 500 tons of coke. Telegraph urgently reply Vwhen arrangements are complete. HOT Charge d' Affaires I-R..NO: totiSi &amp; 'i r. / ! :. / A CCNFIDSNTIAL Political Agency, No•C/1574. Tfo Bahrain, 16th November 1943• The Chief i*©cal Hepresentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., Bahrain. MmiOR/NDU^ The following urgent message has been received for you from His Majesty's Ambassador CairoT- Mides Misc.No.557 dated the 15th November 1943. * 1 i. 3 It is understood that second hand grain sacks are available with Messrs. Cray Mackenzie &amp; Company, Bahrain. Please reserve sufficient sacks for 500 tons of coke and telegraph when arrangements are complete. {v/ty'i Political Agent, Bahrain.i.' 4 - 12^0 Office of the Petrolem Division Representative? British Bmbas^y 5 Bagdad. 27th October 1943. My dear CAS PC Wel ding Outfit , 'N: ■ X hesitate to invokt your aid in domestic matters between oil companies, but I attach for your information a ( opy of a letter sent to me by the Political Agent Bahrein irom CAS OC to Buraah-Sheil Bombay• It relates to a wefding outfit which v;as obtained throuc-h me to help India in laying ttie Boabay-Bhi^awal Pipe Line. Subsequent correspondence between the panics revealed that the outfit arrived at Bombay m poor or useless condition, and a crisp import by ..arr Grieve may have rather upset CaSOo. anyhow, CiwtC agreed to curtail rental charges and asked for the outf-w watch was alwaysloan, to be returned. There may be some grounds for dispute over the rental charge, but I can conceive no possible reasons why the outfit has not been returned and why the co. muni cations from CASOC have not been acknowledged. Perhaps you could drop a line to Guy Cooper and ask him to insert a ston ca dynamite under Lingeman or someone. For your own information British relat ions'nips with have always been cordial - and this cannot be said of BAPC&lt; - and I an particularly anxious for reasons oi waioh you probably know that there should be no unnecessary source^ Irritation between us in the Gulf at the present time. l4ad a useful and restful time at Home and was not f of zeai to return l I hope you thrive and nmy I effer be icon|^&amp;tulations on your C.I.E.. - 7 salaams to C*W.A*,pi *acV: Baylor Isq.C.I.E. Yours sincerely, &gt;/ ft YI COPY OP LETTER DATED 29*9.1943 PROM THE GENERAL MANAGER, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY DHABRAN, SAUDI ARABIA TO THE OFFICE OF THE GENERAL MANAGER, BTTRMAH SHELL OIL STORAGE AND DISTRIBUTING COMPANY OF INDIA, LIMITED BOMBAY (Copy to H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain). We enclose, herewith, three copies of our invoice covering rental of our Wleding Machine No. A 6 x 9, which was shipped to you on December 8th, 1942. This invoice covers the period March 1st - September 30th, 1943, at the agreed upon rate of $ 100.00 TT.S. Currency, per month. In view of your statement that the welding machines arrived in India in poor condition we agreed to cease rental charges on March 1st, and to pay for the immediate return of .the machines $© Arabia, with the understanding that all four machines would be returned as promptly as transportation could be arranged. Three of the machines were returned. We waited several months to hear from you regarding the fourth machine and on August 2nd we cabled you requesting that you expedite the return of this machine. Since we have heard nothing further in regard to your intentions as respects this machine,we are billing you in accordance with the Conditions of Rental, and would appreciate receiving your remittance either here or at our San Francisco Office. Since as stated in your letter W.P.D/O 'DC” of May 28th, 1943* that the 'project in question will shortly be closed', can you advise the approximate date on which the machine in question will be returned to us ? We have an urgent need for welding machines at present and this need will continue for some time. Charge COPY CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY September 30th, 1943. to Burmah Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Co., of India, Limited, P.O.Box 688, Bombay, India. FV. 9-34-43. Rental of Wielding Machine No. A 6 x 9 for the period March 1st to September 30th, 1943, @ # 100.00 U.S. Currency per month. 0 700.00 WE CERTIFY THIS BILL TO BE JUST AND CORRECT AND THAT PAYMENT THEREFOR HAS NOT BEEN RECEIVED. SIGNED CHIEF ACCOUNTANT jcl n 'crKTCH') a t m a &gt;.t0 \&gt;&gt; D hah ran, ^&gt;audi Arabia Hoveiaber 21, 1943 OFFICE OF THE GENERAL MANAGER Burmah Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company of India, Ltd., P. 0. Box. 688 RENTAL OF WELDING MACHINES Files 069*2 Bombay, India Gentlemens Please refer to your letter W.P. D/0 of October 19, 1943 in which you gave the reasons for the delay in returning welding machine No. A 6x9 to us. machines were finally returned to us and considered the probable idle time when setting our rental rates. Office the amount shown on the invoice presented with our letter of September 29, 1943* Final billing will be made when the machine is received by us in Arabia. welding machines A 6x2, A 6x5 and A 6x7 we quote from our letter to you of May 19, 1943; ,,! Ae 60 not feel, however, that it would be fair for us to commit ourselves to a settlement for their hire until we have had an opportunity to review the damage they sustained since leaving our hands”. them over and have to report that they were not necessarily, as stated by your Chief Engineer, “much better than junk'. We refer to the mechanical condition of the machines, not their appearance. All three of the machines were placed in service immediately by us after re placing the piiferred parts and damaged tires. At this date all of the machines are still in continuous service. prepare billings for the three machines rented to you in accordance with the terms of the ”Condition of Rental” forwarded with your letter A.P. L.5 D/0 of January 4, 1943 except that we will not bill you for the freight costs incurred in returning these machines. See your letter D/0 of my 18, 1943 in which you quote our cabled instructions to ya We realized that delays would be experienced before the In view of the above, will you please pay our San Francisco Regarding our decision on the matter of rental charges on Upon arrival of the three machines we immediately checked In view of our findings we have no alternative but to *00*-• 5* * !3P Telegram From 28/28. Inter »C» 0* Ambassador, Cairo, rolitical Agent, Bahrain. No. Mides Misc 578. Dated 27th received 28th November 1943. IMPORTANT . Bahrain coke. M.W.T. inform us they can probably arrange space 500 tons bagged coke middle December. - \\ 2. We have replied to M.W.T. that coke will be ready for shipment November 28th. Telegram No.793^from Bahrain refers. 3. Bahrain please confirm your arrangements mean that coke Vfill be ready ? bagged . KWD. ^ • A/t&gt;: 3 7own JtoutJiA, &amp;A ^o:?oS ~ i.r.Nq, nnNovember 21, 1943 RENTAL OF WELDING MACHINES TO INDIA Files 069*2 OFFICE OF m GENERAL MANAGER Barash Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company of India P.O. Box, 688 Limited Bombay, India Gentlemen: ^ Pursuant to our letter File 06f*2, dated today, we enclose, herewith, two invoices, each in triplicate, one of which covers rental of three Welding Machines from March 1st to June 29 th, 1943&gt; and the other to cover rental of A 6x9 for the period October 1st - November 30th, 1943, Ull you please send your remittance covering these invoices to our San Francisco Office, lours very truly, CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY ORIGINAL SIO. iSD ** C. B. Davis By ^ F. W. OBLIGEE GENERAL MANAGER Enel; cc- s Political Agent, y Bahrein*O o-io-l CA (8-42) flgymbar 30th n —194&gt;tr CHARGE TO OFFICE OF TBS, MAMAOER, B imah Sh ell O il Storage &amp;iri distributing Company of India 9 Limited., F« Oo Beae 688, Baaboy, India, — TERMS CUSTOMER'S ORDER No. NV- No. SHIPPED TO_ FROM _DATE_ _F. O. B. Rental of Welding Machines Hes 0 t 6x2 A 6ec3 s A MF W the period Marsh 1st, 19h| to June 29th, 1943, $ $ iOOoOO per m&amp;ohlne per mmiho March Rental April Rental May Rental June Rental (29 days). MB CERTIFY THAT THIS BILL VS JUST A HD CORRECT, AND THAT PfQCENT, THBR3SPORE, HAS NOT BEEN RECEIVEDo■ 300oOO 300o00 300o00 290oOO I l.WoOO CHIEF ACCOUNTANT rt)/jp , UL HAHAGER EBjMAW VIA DESCRIPTION QUANTITY PRICE AMOUNT TOTAL XJHALDSOH( £&gt; J IX - / - 3 ’ ^ Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : 122, LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON, EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH1RE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LI NG AH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE Bahrein, 8th December, ^3. S 5CRBT The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, 500 tons Coke in bags, Bahrein tp Port Said We have been requested by M.//.T., Basra, to ^ advise you that trie above shipment will be lifted by the SS. r, THEVINCE H due here about third week in December. Yours faithfully, Copy sent under endorsement No.C/1741 dated 13th December 19h3 to the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, for information.The first line of this Telegrem contains the following particulars in the order named Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Printed in England. Aug. 1941. (9,000 pads) &gt; i CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in enoland.) 5/-168 Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. HAB^® /do e’ ,, LV12/S S CAIRO 59 14-0346 BGETAT , s , IMP! POLITICAL BAHREIN.. 605 MIDES MISC FOR PETROLEUM COMPANY OF FOB PRICE WILL BE PAID BY SAVON OF PORT SAID TWO FREIGHT AND INSURANCE BY Jf. IOXEY SAVON OF LONDON THREE PLEASE CONFIRM THAT QUOTED FOB PRICE OF TWENTY ONE RUPEES 8 ANNAS (21*) INCLUDES COST OF BAGS FOUR IF NOT PLEASE SIGNAL URGENTLY THE FULL \ FOB PRICE * =AMBASSADOR= • ^ 14 V YOUR REPLY *?m/ietuaC k * , NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.yto.c/nifif To Political Agency, Bahrain, 15th December 1943• The Chief Local 'Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. MaMORAKPOM The following telegram No.605 Mides Misc dated the 14th December has been received from His Majesty’s Ambassador, Cairo:- 'For Petroleum Company of FOB price will be paid by Bavon of Port Said two freight and insurance by Moxey Savon of London three please confirm that quoted FOB price of twenty one rupees 8 Annas (21^) includes cost of bags four if not please signal urgently the full FOB price.' for Political Agent, Bahrain, iy&lt;s .PA-440 A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. December 18, 1943 H.B.M. 1 s Political Agent, The political Agency, Bahrein. SHIK'.ENT 0? 500 TCP3 COKE TO PORT SAID File #565. Dear Sir, We acknowledge your letter No*1744 dated 15th December 1943 and would advise that the quotation of Rs.21/8/- does not include the cost of bags which amounted to Hs .7,291/1/-* The full F.O.B. price will therefore be Es.2l/8/- per long ton, plus revenue stamp Pjs.0/8/- and Bill of Lading fee Re.l/- plus Rs .7,291/1/-. value and freight and shall be glad if you will cable Messrs. Moxey Savon &amp; Co., London, urgently requesting them to effect whatever insur ance cover may be required. In view of the early arrival of the steamer on which the coke is to be shipped, the question of insurance should be handled immediately. Said and London the relative documents and invoice#. Please advise whether payment will be made locally or in London. We note your instructions regarding collection of F.O.B. We shall in due course pass to you for forwarding to Port Yours very truly, W. P. ANDERSON CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.BVM— Telegram j?rom JlO Tile i^o&gt;28/28 , &amp; Political Agent, Bahrain* Amb as sado r, Cairo. Bo. 859. j^atecl the 20 th veceiibcr 1943. IMPORTANT Reference Mides •, isc 605 nee a her 14th. Coke shipment. 2. Bahrain Petroleum Company have informed me that quotation of Rs. 21/8 does not repeat not include cost of bogs which amounts to Rs.7291/1. Full TOB price will be Rs.21/3 per long ton plus revenue stamp Annas 8 and Bill of nading fee Re.l/- plus its.7291/1, 3. In view of the early arrival of the steamer Bahrain Petro leum Company request that Messrs. Moxey Bavon u: Co, London effect whatever insurance is required inr.edio.tely. -POLITICAL?*Iti) ^ a i c h b ? GM-%m Await, Bacambar 18, 1943, Maaara, Gray, Itock&amp;nzU k do,, Ltd,, Bahrain , gBIHTJIT OF SOQ fp?^ OQKI IK , . . B4HHFIH TD H5IW 3A.1B Dwstw, -fixT ^v We haTe reoelred fpoa It.B.M.** Politioal Agency, Bahrein, a eony ^ 0ur to tham da tea 8th Deoaasbar, advising that the above shipaent will be lifted by the B.5. M TIOTU3CE W {Haines steaaahlp Company of Cornwall. England) due here about third week of this month* ahould appreciate your handling the shipping of this consign- meat, and for your information we are now trucking the coke to Hitra ?ier in readiness, f# presume the vessel will be instructed to proceed to Sltra, Iho consignee will be Messrs, Savon, port Said, and we would ask you to forward one Original Bill of lading via carrying vessel and pass the be lance to us including one Duplicate Original which we will forward via air mall through the Political Agent, Bahrein, together with our invoice. Bill of Lading should be isnrked 'FHEIGIIT PREPAID'. w ® tshould appreciate receiving your invoice for freight and shipping charges at the earliest possible moment in order that we my complete our papers immediately the ship sails, in this connection we confirm our telephone conversation in which you quoted Bs.6/8/- per long ton, plus revenue stamp A*.8/~ end bill of lading fee Ke.l/- as in th* case of previous coke shipments. Irrespective of whether the vessel re ceives the coke at Panai^s or Bltra - for shipping charges. On the subject of insurance we would advise you that we have requested the ik&gt;litioal Agent to advise Messrs, Money Savon, London, to effect whatever insurance cover they wish placed. Tours very truly, BAHRKXK PETHOlStfti COMPANY LIMITED cos H.B.M,*6 Political Agent, Bahrein, original S1|C5NE ® ,V. p. ANDERSON W.P. mmWN- 0EKK5ML KAKAGEStv cO' Pa-491 The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited A w a 1 i , Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. H.B.M. , s Political Agent, January 11, 1944. The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir, SHIPMENT OF 500 TODS COKE TO PORT SAID File $565 Please find enclosed herewith documents covering the shipment of 500 tons Coke to Port Said. ?/e shall be obliged if you would kindly forward relative documents to addressees. Tours very truly. Wv [z h| l W.P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited vq-v\ir \i ■&amp;o.5'8 / ~ 5 ^ of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the G-overnment, Bahrain Dated, 24th R/Awal, 1363 March 19, 1944. Memosandum: - I enclose two statements regarding an incident which took place at the causeway gate on 16th March, 1944. I understand that the Officer whs one of the two who are quartered here, living with Mr. Rodstrom. As you are aware we have been having some diffi culty with vehicles, especially those driven by Europeans, passing the gates and the bridge. I consider that action should be taken in order to prevent similar incidents, which might be more serious, occurring in future. H. B. M f s Political Agent Bahrain. Adviser to the Government S.ZStatement of No.109 Policeman Isa bin Rashid. On the evening of Thursday 16th March 1944, I was on duty at the causeway gate. Some time after sunset an American Officer came to the gate in a Jeep car. He told me to open the gate, I asked him for his ticket but he would not give it to me. He got out of the car and struck me on the chest, but not hard. In the past he has always refused to give up his ticket which he thdpW&amp; on the ground. Sometimes he has driven the front of his car under the gate and then lifted the gate without getting out. He throws his tickets away. Statement of Mohamed Hussain, Toll clerk. I was on duty at the gate on the 16th March/in the evening an American Officer, a Lieutenant, came in a Jeep car from Moharraq and stopped at the gate, which was shut. He told the Policeman, Isa bin Rashid, to open it. The Policeman said 'Give me your ticket, Sahib'. The Officer did not give the ticket but made signs that the Policeman should onen and hit the Policeman wno was standiiig at tne gate, where it swings. He hit him on the chest but not hard. He threw his ticket on the ground. Next day j he again refused to give up his ticket when I asked for it and threw it on the ground. The tickets are required for counting. Saleh bin Hassan, a local shopkeeper, was at the gate on the 16th and corraborates the statement the gate. He was very regarding the incffent.T 21st March 1944 D.O.No.C/514. My dear Chase, I enclose a copy of a letter with enclosures which I have received from Belgrave. 1 sha11 be Stateful if you can cause enquiries be made with a view to discover ing the officer concerned*a view of the incident, - Yours sincerely, ^ 7 y » ( /1 Sq./Ldr. V/.A. Chase, Air Liaison Officer^ Bahrain. P. ts ? t. i H \ v._ \ \ it IP 02504/ASDyS' 1 MIDDLE EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, 10, SHARIA TOLU MEAT, CAIRO. March, 1944 Political Agent BAHREIN. • •99 Petroleum Coke - Bahrein. 7e enclose herewith, a copy of Major Boyd’s report on his recent visit to Bahrein, undertaken for the purpose of establishing a bulk loading scheme f \j JDB r 1 —Object of Visit . Whilst I was in Persia information was telegraphed fron? Cairo that the briquetting tost on the ?00 ton parcel of petroleum colte had been successful. I there fore proceeded to Bahrein, arriving there on 21st i ebruary 1944, and began negotiations for shipping coke in bulk. Conditions on the Island are substantially different from those which obtained at the tiro my last report - September 1942. i*ie Petroleum Company is busily engaged on three * priority undertakings. 1. The construction of a 100 octane refinery 2 . The construction of a drum plant 3. The construction of a long loading jetty. T1 is affects the bulk loading orogranase b' ir reducing the labour and staff available, by utilis ing the loading jetty at Sitra and all harbour craft io capacity in oriloading construction material. . —■ • ■■ ll ■ I mil* i I ■■VI ■■■■■■IInformation vns received that the Government of India f 1/'iro retro---m ; ■ :dotsicn oerreo^ot-tivo, Iraq and through Messrs* Gray Mackenzie, is interested in taking 6 * OCX) tons per raonth* The U.S* urny, who in recent weeks 9 l^d been negotiating for certain tonnages, have now abandoned their scheme* It was therefore decided that the Indian and ■ Egyptian schemes should be treated- as one and proposals formulated accordingly. The total requirement would then bo as follows 8 - Government of India through h ^x./r.onth Gray Mackenzie, Dec. 194*3 Government of India through Petroleum Div* Hep. Feb. 1944 ~ 6,000 Egypt through r.E*S.C. Feb. 1944 2,000 3,000 Totals It was learned that vessels of 3,500 to 5,000 tons capacity would probably be provided. After discussion it was agreed that the loading scheme should be based on 800 tons per day to ship.Allowing for tie handling of 1*000 tons uer d' e . = 62.5 tons per hour .62*5 tons d 4p lbs. per cu. ft. = lip cu. yds/hoar Provision should therefore be rade for £ belt elevator capable of raising 150 cu. yds. per hour to o 1 eight of say 2 r feet. This belt should discharge into a blinker of about 1,000 cu. yds. capacity from v-uich veficdes could i-e* ouped.ltlr-ualy yV * As it was considered unlikely that a special uthorin:; - 1 oa0ipp 'd.--,vutor \ xd...; . -.u-dU it was agreed that a bulldozer would be required for the purpose of keeping the bolt sup with ‘ial. use' between the sstockpile and the landward end of the jetty was turned down for the following reasons 1 - X. Lack of facilities for construction of long ramp necessary le gain height for forming stockpile on Sitra Island. 2 . Lack of facilities for construction of piled causeway across Sitra Channel. 3 . Practical impossibility of adapting the scheme to fit the new causeway when constructed. 4. Tho .anagnnent 1 f? pi^f^renca for motor transport over rail transport. ■ • ZHangE ort .fr p! 5._£toejaAI g.. to Jetty . Our original suggestion that decauville should be. _ / . • . ... As Sitra Jetty is being used to capacity it is cons tdereC -veer -; sary .o :,rcvi-,b: 'rytvi • • feet ; ... - coi . ' i. v ' c raiaps to facilitate dumping from lorry to barge* The Company is iecirons of purcb^sing and instal ling a lorry ^.mLphbrCcpa to -las' rn.tl eoko traffic* A suggestion that they should be satinfled ^itb ships / .easurorients v?:.ts not acceptable to then* Handling from Jetty to C - JLSSSSi- Pun to the fret that craft can only accost ire jetty at certain states of the tides Messrs* Gray Mackenzie* shipping agents Bahrein, are of the opinion that eight 200 ton barges and four tugs will be required* These numbers would cater for repair and maintenance* In tie opinion of »?« and I.h.T* the coke should 'he handled from barge ay shipb tackle In 3 G cu.ft. capacity reed/bamboo wirehound baskets of the type being used in kersian Gulf Ports* These are obtainable from In.,: la thr. ugh i' * v * T * Messrs* Gray Mackenzie can guarantee to load BfC tons per day by this moans an:- t wit! i -riance they could improve on this figure* The Petroleum dorp any would be unable to cove with '' ,li 1 jt \ ■■ —1‘h© Bahrein Petroleum Coffigmay quote Rs 10 oer ton ol coke at stockpile ? kut attention 'ira vn to the fact that this figure applies to- local sales, the Gex. • anager agreed to approach his Head office with a -/let to obtaining a reduction. o ;p n,y a yr; . - _ ■ ‘ ;; r ’oacing into trucks, transporting to jetty and dun ing into barge until the type, condition and cost of equipisent is known* The shipping agents quote an informative price of s* to 4 Ks. for loading vessels, excluding shi - ■ hv: do r rpcny requires a firrx cojitract for at ‘least ' t -r - ' ■ - - , ' - : T : - . - ' :: ' ' cat Im t rai whJ : w© say be expected to be interested in the sc He welcomed* 1 .put tcho ns into O perati on * It is estimated that, after receipt of the equipment a bo i* 1 easting could be c-r •..:&gt;.?nced -rit\ In tuo months* It is emp ised, •. ] irr-uired far handling coke would be essential to the ' - . ■ r - ; i :t : ./ ' ■ JHt*. 30 ft* vr-.dr cause,-ay some 12 ,£K l yards long and rallel t ting pipe track, is to be construe to t • e ly place of litrra Jetty and is to be us ad for ' ■ - Id this causeway will be in 6 foot of water at low tide and lo« li from, this position w 3 m independant of tides*for the present sehe- T i l‘V‘‘ : l Tugs 14 8 4 20 5 3 sufficient vehicles to cater for the increased requlrraos J :n 25th February 1941 X -et hr. TJ-iter and Mr* Fifost ana them au fait with our pro iae. fljfayrr Qn February 1944 3 9 a on Lt. Col. Cortarci • a v (, iscussewitl hii the question of harbour craft for eraf used in that area and f - c ■’ • he stressed the point that he had no surplus craft fcnd that should release of the above units be agreed, they wou...d have to be replaced by other craft.Major in charge confined ti -minion. . ' ■ , -'•er consultation wit:-- mi Director of Movements stated that any release of handling cr towing craft from the Z»W«?» fleet could only be made sated release, therefore, was a question of priority tc be decided by War Office* I Wtt£ of tb- lion that rf i •. ■ ier from IndJa * b e iforce * On 27tl febxi.uirj/ 1904 1 enquires f - bichards whet; -.ay of the m it reufaired was available in Paiforce. Pe stated that in the Command tier- are 30 bull dozers surplus to require.-ents and that . rnlt'’ loading conveyor of suitable capacity was available* This conveyor was formerly used at a gypsum factory and is at present in sections. 3 Palforce* t: ; -. • ■ . ■ r : , our pro;:. P out tbe availability cf tie mechanical equipment. brought rp tl.o cuesticr. cf rot-cr tr^nz-ori and was informed that Paiforce has no suitable vehicles surplus to requirements but that t; 1 reserve jm at ?(' Canadian Dodge trucks* Col. Darker stated that upon :U5CCivfn;; u;: u:f. fir rz u-,;.-- of c ah oz P^ ''-mP' ; consult War Office who might authorise withdrawal the abovementioned re s o rve .'’aediate action was promised on receipt of our request backed by a resume of our schema and reference t o th o f * -. * T • telegrai ; auther 1 s .1 no 11 . e pro^ra re. fn 27th i ebruary 1944 I informed hr. 3o-lby of Bi ‘^rein t .iggested schcrve for shipping coho In bare to India sho-uo be nooifioa and that consid ^ration should be given to shipping in bulk. Ms was agreed and the suggestion to dew Delhi. X made Hr. Bowlby au fait with the steps X had taken and intended to take for the release of equipment which I pointed out ms ■ for the hand!: of both th© Egyptian and Indian tonnages. hr. Bowlby agreed and requested Hew Delhi to communicate with us on the subject. It was agreed thit all future corrf? 5 ?rendenc© on ■ . .■ hou ; i he repeat! with each schema. L«f ( f) , r : ,;4ifor ce. Ihe I*iaIson Officer was represented at most meetings ur Baghdad and fully inferred of the aspects discussed at others.L CiH (&lt; f yV&gt; iHl DO/WAC/12/42 f.. ff^cJrA^y br£&amp;&lt; CO*^-! 26th March 19^. • fl j-ri c r B f I thank you for your D0 /g/ 5'‘4 dated 21st March 1 and the attachment thereto. Confirming my conversation with you yesterdayj the Officer to whom the report refers has admitted that he was involved in this incident and tenders his sincere regrets. * I In conversation with him, he stated that it was one of those occasions when an aircraft arrived unexpectedly and conseq uently he was in a great hurry to reach the Airfield. Both the policmen and th.e toll-gate keeper on duty at the time were extremely slow In allowing his vehicle to pass. The Officer tended his money immediately for his ticket which was not forthcoming, as the toll-gate keeper apparently had no small change. It would appear from the Officer’s remarks generally and from the statements from the Bahrein Government that there was provocation on both sides. However, this Officer has expressed his sincere regret and has informed me that he will be most careful in future. In addition, he is making every endeavour to place his transport on the season ticket princiiDle in order to eliminate the necessity to request and tender tickets at each end of the Causeway. Major T. Hickiribotham C.I.B., O.B.B., H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrein - Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government for information under endorsement No.C/555 dated the 28th March 1244 with reference to his memorandum No, 581-23SF dated the 19th March 1944.28/28 x Telegram From To Repeated to Inter *0' M.E.S.C. Cairo Politleal Agent, Bahrain M.E.i.C. CL) PAIC Saving No. 8 Dated 28th received 29th Larch 1944. IMPCRTAI7T For Bahrain Petroleum Company. 1. Further to our telgram No.6 saving Preliminary arrangements have been made for supply to your account of Savon sufficient bags for 2000 tens. 2. We would be grateful for an indication of your probable programme stating: (a) What takings are available on Bahrain, both second hand and on loan pending replacement from supplies to be procured by us. (b) Probable date on which first parcel ?(containing) 500 tons could be ready for shipment. 3. An urgent reply would enable us to complete our arrange ments without undue delav.URGEMT 1 V Political Agency, CONFIDKNTIA L Bahrain, 30th March, 1944. No.C/561. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. MEMORAIiDUM Following is the text of a telegram, No .8 dated the 28th March 1944, I have received from the Middle East Supply Centre, Cairo. ’’For Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited: 1. We have made preliminary arragements for the supply of bags for 2000 tons to Savon on your account. (Our tele gram No .6 Saving refers). 2. Kindly let us have your probable programme indicating:- (i) When the first parcel of 500 tons will be ready for shipment? (ii) What is the position regarding the availability of takings in Bahrain, both second hand and on loan? Those taken on loan will be replaced by us from supplies we will procure. 3. We shall be grateful for an urgent reply so that undue delay in the completion of arrangements may be avoided. ,, / 2. If you send me your reply I shall have it telegraphed to the Middle East Supply Centre. for Political Agent, Bahrain.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. # PA-200 April 1st, 1944, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Pile No.565 Dear Sir, Please refer to your confidential letter No. C/561 dated 30th March, 1944, quoting telegram No.8 from the Middle East Supply Centre, Cairo. I shall appreciate if you will kindly send the following message to the M.E.S.C., Cairo through your facilities. The charges in this connection may be debited to the Company’s account. To: M. E. S. C., Cairo From: Bahrein Petroleum Company, Bahrein. Begins tt Y0UE TELEGRAM NUMBER EIGHT MARCH 28th HATE PURCHASED SUFFICIENT BAGS FOR ACCOUNT SATON FOR FIRST FIVEHUNDRED TONS Y/HICH WILL BE READY FOR SHIPMENT APRIL 20th. stop SUPPLY SACKS HERE LIMITED BUT POSSIBLE MIGHT PURCHASE SUFFICIENT FOR SECOND FIVEHUNDRED TONS AT RUPEE ONE EACH stop NONE FOR LOAN ” ends. W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. ^ • f * ' A lO T *V28/28 Telegram From To Repeated to 3*1 Do t ad v. From Bahrain Petroleum Fomoanv Inter ,f 0 n Politiea1 Agent, Bahrain Prodrome, Cairo for rvd.T.F. M.F*F.F. CL) PATC (Saving) 2nd April 1944. / Your telegram of/March 28th ho.8. First 500 tons will / / / / / be ready for shipment April 20th, for which fcsgx sufficient bags I ( I / / have been purchased for account Savon./ Might be able to Courchase ( sufficient sacks for senond'500 tons at Hupee one each but though / / . . / / / supply of sacks here limited. No stacks are available on loan. Politicalf O- isf) \H^ . c Copy of telegram No. nil dated 30th Ma'reh' 1944 from senior Naval Officer Persian Uulf to Political /gent, Bahrain. The Master of ’’Cromarty'* has reported that several cases of small arms vvere broken f during unloading operations at Sharjah on the 27th and 28th March. About -?000 rounds Y?ere recovered as result of a search of native labour. / 2. It appears that no European supervision was provided by Shore Authorities during these two days. I understand Army Movements, Basra are taking this up with k.A.F. Sharjah. SECRET No .C/573. Political Agency, Bahrain, 2nd April 1944. Copy forwarded with compliment® to the Political Officer Trucial Coast, Sharjah, with the request that he will make immediate enquiries and report.H.B. Ivi. Politi&lt;fel Agent Bahrein STATION CX&amp;IMAND BAHREII^ No. SO/S-27 / t Marcn 19^r4 There is in our Armoury a .455 Pistol. It has 'been here for a long time, and from history it appears that the Civil Police who used to he here obtained it from the Agency, though no record is in this office. The pistol in question is not required by this H.Q. as »455 Pistols are now obsolete as Army Y/eapons. If you would like it I will hand it over to you. Lieut-Col., COMMANDER. (Sgd.H. T.HEWITT)No. C/580 Political Agency, Bahrain, 2nd April 1944 To The Statiom Commander Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No.SC/S-27/113 dated the 31st March 1944. 2. Many thanks for the suggestion but as I already have a fine collection of obsolete weapons I suggest that the sea is the best depository for your.055 pistol. Political Agent, BahrainReference your endorsement jmo.o/ 573 dated the 2nd April* 2» It is understood that the 3Cromarty discharged the following packages short:- 1 case (1298 rounds; *303 tracer ammunition, .3 cases r »capsules, relay 1 ** in addition one case was dropped in to the sea and lost ana 1 case of fuses was landed surplus. The search of native labour was apparently carried out on board the ship where the theft*, must have occurred as all the cases of .303 ammunition landed -ky- the R#A*F. were complete® 3* I have received complaints against the conduct of Captain Anderson of the 8*3.Cromarty while his ship was discharging at Duoai. h@ is said to have refused to give the labourers water to drink (a customary courtesy here) and to have refused them any assistance or instruction in fixing the slings when unyoking motor vehicles, a task to which they are not accustomed. It has been generally remarked that his attitude contrasted most f favourably with the courteous and helpful conduct of the Captains and officers of American ships which discharged about same time* Political officer,Trucial uoast. . M ^ 4 oO/t -a/., to kZ&lt;? cCa&amp;J 2. i'A-'4*1 •SXPHSSS-L^CTEH. prom - political. Sharjah. To - political, Bahrain. No. - 616-6/3(B) Dated the 10th April 1944. Reference my Express-Letter No. 0/582-31/5 dated the 5th April 1944. Theft of ammunition* 2. The R.A* F* have, at my instance, since carried out an examination of the boxed ammunition unloaded from the Cromarty, and have discovered that the a small number of rounds have been removed from each of the boxes so that^the total now missing is 2,238 rounds, investigations are proceeding. ^ “ C / t'll 2 _ 4 _ l,._TELEGRAM - G.T.C. From To No. 283 Dated the Political, Bahrain. Political, Sharjah. 19th April 1944&lt; / r Your express letter No616 April 10th. 2. Were the seals on the ammunition boxes intact when handed over to the Royal Air Foiree.■£irox0 mmomm cokb * ForB*l*P a C # 0 o 26 cogim (^3 ' ’ W., 'tTBiiYLW D ? loth lar.oii 1944, 1# Application for release of all. equipment for bulk loading has been 2aad® to loudon* . 2* As '.a result of first reports on firing- teats we are anxious to. bri^g :to 'Bgjf'pt. such tonnages as you can bag and •¥*$»3!, can, ahip from now. until the bulk loading programme becomes operative., 3 C - Accordingly SAITOH are ^bmnmyaicat with .you- direct-and wei= have:- for bagp and shipping space. We hare suggested the shipping. . conditions' similar to those applicable- to the piwious 5 00 tons- would be acceptable. '4* would appreciate., your co-operation during this intermediary period* • 4 5, To prevent confusion between petroleum coke anfi metelim’gical ooks pleaee, is future, refer in sll. shipping docuaeuts euiS: declara tions to 'BAHRSXK SMiiS*. IP/JEB, ins fBiaosi ojs s~ rjnsa*i&lt;**-/vv«. amttHvrm** wfi**t«*vn: r :i*'K?**rr J K*n Lusts A «*■ 0 ** h a IP02504/A3B' c® **-11 m 4c i &gt; i ^ ^ ^ '^T Qm iOBLBQ-RAH Copies No. 17 SWING M;. &gt;, \sH \-V m % POLITICAL AGENT BAfIRBIN. mm t s n v &lt; 21 at April 1944 Addressed tc Political Agent Bahrain No, 1? Saving, repeated to M.Fo-Tt Basra Fo, 60 Saving, and MKSC &lt;I») PAIO No., 49 Saving, SBCRETo for B*A.P.C.O, Bahrein Smalls We are pleased to hear from Savon that you have been able to obtain hags sufficient for 3000 tons in addition_tc the 500 tons parcel which you will have ready on 20 April London hopes to ship these 500 tone at the end of the month In order that shipping may be arranged for the balance, we 'tfould be grateful for an estimate of the dates by which yon could have the above mentioned 3000 tons rsady for shipmente Please calculate on 500 tons lots, but since for practical reasons we would prefer larger tonnages, we are asking %.* W*f. . - London whether or not they can lift more uhan 500 tons at a time Tour cooperation in obtaining bags and handling smalls at this time is greatly appreciated. DISTRIBUTION D.Ga LISTS a + E Mr Rcnmfree Cairo. Petroleum Division Rep. c/o M of 3 Pile ho. IP02504/AS3)I ' m Folio No. TELEGRA 6 Copies isCLJ^gent Bahrein— From Middle East Supply Centre M Dated 15th-April, 1944 (fo) — Q ^ skvim X n O^v &gt; &lt;v Bahrein Stalls For B.\•P.0,0* We would be grateful to hear If you have yet received the decision of your Head Office as to the keenest price at which you may offer your by-product coke in bulk* DISTRIBUTION D*a. Mr* Rountree File IF025QVAS2&gt; A'C~v / i e ^ 1 10 IP/JDB, ~ '«. —WiTHE BA H IREIN PETROLE^vl Ca,:PAl']Y LmiTSD ■ • Awali - Bahrein Island, PA-S65 Persian Gulf Date May 1, 1944 The Political Agency, B A. P. R E I N « Dear Sir, nmuiy x-axci- uu wua » ~Z .... shipping a further 500 Tons Coke to Messrs. Savon &amp; Co., Port Said, within the next few days and assume that Messrs* Moxey Savon &amp; Co# Ltd., Ixmdon, will again effect insurance in this instance, VJe shall, therefore be glad if you would cable Messrs, Savon Sc Co. Ltd,, urgently, to effect insurance. Wq shall in due course for-ward to you the relative documents for despatch to Port Said and London. Yours very truly, JvSM/JGC _,W. P. ANDERSON 5HIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED H.B.M’s Politioal Agent, Bahrein. A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Llay 3, 1944. Dear Sir, With reference to the Gable No.17 Saving from M.S.S.C., Cairo received through 3 /our facilities, we shall appreciate 3 ^our sending the following cable in reply at your earliest convenience: To: M. E. S. C., CAIRO. From: BAHREIN PETROLEUM,--BAHREIN. Begins .. 'SHIEPIHJ 500 TOMS BAKR3IN SMillS TODAY (stop) CAilE-IOT MAKE ADDITIONAL SHIPHSNTS TOiTIL BARG3S AND TUGS ARE IAD3 AVAILABLE FOR THIS PURPOSE AS PRESENT SHIPMENT IS SERIOUSLY DELAYING OFF LOADING OF PROJECT MATERIALS (stop) PLEASE INFORM SAVON OF SITUATION. • ... Ends. Yours very truly, fat VI. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COlPiETY LI’UTED.PA-876 11 nis b.a hrp:lim pet holeitm coivpA'Y LEviirM) Aw&amp;li B ahr ein I slan ds Persian Gull?. Date Political Agent, The Political Agency, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, \ / &gt;*• ■f/4 .&lt;r /y May 4, 1944 SHIPMENT OP 500 TONS OOKS TO PORT SAID File #565 / With reference to our letter #265 dated May 1, 1944 we have to advise that the shipment of 500 tons Coke to Port Said has been cancelled. In view of this we shall be glad if you would kindly cable Messrs. Moxey Savon &amp; Go, Ltd., 5 Line Street Square, London, urgently, to cancel insurance. Kindly debit any charges in this connection to the Company^ account. Yours very truly. jvsmAgc W. P. ANDERSON LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDThe Bahrein petroleum Company Limited PA-274 A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. May 4, 1944. FILS: 009.32 II.3.M's political Agent, Bahrein. v t Dear Sir, Reference our letter No. PA-273 of yesterday's date. In view of recent developments, I shall appreciate your sending the appended cable as soon as possible. To: M. S. 3. C., CAIRO. From: BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, BAHREIN. Begins .. 'FURTHER TO OUR TELEORAM OF MAY 3 rd. (stop) VESSEL NOMINATED LIFT 500 TON BAHREIN FINES REFUSED CARGO ACCOUNT POSSIBILITY / DAMAGE TO OTHER CARGO'. ends. Yours very truly,Telegram From To No 409 28/28 Political /gent, Bahrain. H.M’s Ambassador, Pei ©x&amp;d Dated 3rd May, 1944, ^ ' My telegram No 859 December 20th, 1943. Bahrain Petroleum Company are shipping a further 500 tons coke to gavon. Port paid. Company requests that Moxey Fa von, London effect necessary insurance urgently* -POLITICAL- ICETelegram Int. Ord, From Political /gent, Pahrain. To M.E. S. C. Cairo. No 420 Dated 5th May, 1944. IM PORTANT Reference My telegram No 409 May 3rd. (Rent through Ambassador, Cairo) 2. Shipment of 500 tons coke by Bahrain Petroleum Company to Savon, Port Said has been cancelled. Company now ^ requests Moxey Savon, London, not repeat not to effect insurance. 3. Vessel nominated to lift 500 tons Bahrain Fines has refused cargo on account of possible damage to other cargo. ICH -POLITIC/*+ccigiprarri AL No.C/?28. To It Political Agency, Bahrain, the ^th May 1944• The Chief Local Bepr g aentative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain . Memorandum ^ ^ t Loference your recent letters Mos» PA-265, 273, 274) 276 on the subject of coke shipments* rw iko^ ^.!b° 2 I one lose her ev?i th copies of the t?;o tolegrams issued from my office* In view of your telephonic request to cancel ^ f ^7 the t elegram embodied in your letter Ho.PA-273, the telegram was in fact withdrawn before it was actually despatched* The telegrams have been charged to your account* Political Agent, Bahrain.S ■ - l 1 V' 1. Copy of telegram No.409 doted 3-6-44 from Political i\gent, Bahrain to H.M's Ambassador, Cairo. Bcferenco ..ay telegram 859 Bee amber 20th 1943. 2. m?C 0 are shipping a further 800 tons coke to ‘Savon, Port Said. Company raqnosts that ?.!oxoy Savon, London effect neeeasary inauranoe urgently. 2. Copy of telegram No. 420 dated 5-5-44 from Political Agent Bahrain to M.E.3.C. Cairo. Reference my telegram No. 409 May 3rd. / 2. Shipment of 500 tons coke by BAPCC to ^avon, Port Said has been cancelled. Company now requests Moxoy Savon, London, not to effect insurance. . 7 3. Vessel nominated to lift 500 tons Bahrain Pines has refuse# cargo on account of possible damage to other cargo.28/28 Telegram Inter (Pad) / From M.E. S. C. Cairo, y To Political /'gent, Pahrain Repeated No IS Bssrs. Dated 2Srd Received 16th May 1944. IMPORTANT / W For Prhrrin Petroleum Company. . Would be grateful for early reply to our ?telegrsm No 17 Caving. Since shipment of latest 500 tons of ?coke * parcel refused on account of poor condition of bags please confirm by telegram that bags purchased at 8s 1 each are new or if not that condition satisfactory. ?Pepeat reply to second addressee. * 0 ICH - MESCO - | R % 5 7 ' ufs 14 . S' -tiif .@) No.C/741 SBCHET Political Agency, Bahrain, 9th May 1944. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd Bahrain. With reference to your message of 22nd March in reply to theirs of the 10th March 1944, No.QAE 00801, PAIFORCE have signalled me the following message for you numbered QAE 12782 dated the 6th Mey 1944i- I. Aviation Octane Project . Item 1. Already issued* , u 8. Not available ' 9. Aa we cannot supply timber do you require nails? n 10. Dealt with at conference on May 4th. II. Causeway Project . We have received no instructions to provide equipment for this project. You might take up through Petroleum Division Representative. Item 2. Probably not available but might be able to -do- Not available -de ls suing Galvanized corrugated iron not available. -do- Could supply black sheeting but in view of the corrosive nature of Bahrain atmosphere we are advised this is useless. “ 11 —do— do- ' 4 ' 5 ' 6 supply substitute. Understand this now not necessary. Dealt with separately -do- -do- for Political Agent, Bahrain . _THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, PA-324 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 20, 1944 FILE: 009.52 H. B. M»s Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir, To: From: Begins .. I shall appreciate your sending the following cable at st convenience: M. E. S. C., CAIRO. BAHREIN PETROLEUM, BAHREIN. 'REFERENCE YOUR No. 17 SAVING OF APRIL 27th AND No. 13 OF MAY 17th FURTHER COKE SHIPMENTS MUST BE DEFERRED UNTIL ADDITIONAL LABOUR AND EQUIPMENT AVAILABLE stop REFER OUR LETTER CON-171 MAY 15th REPLYING TO YOUR No. 16 SAVING OF APRIL 22nd stop BAGS ARE SECOND-HAND BUT IN SATISFACTORY CONDITION. .... Ends. W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDPA-33.9 THE BA HREIN PETROLEUM CC&amp;PAA1Y LIkITSD Awali - Bahrein Island, E.B.M.*8 Political Agent, The Political Agency, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Persian Gulf Date May 18, 1944, BAHREIN SMALIS Pile #565,3 We have to advise that a shipment of coke, gross weight 485 tons, will he consigned to Messrs* L* Savon &amp; Co«, Port Said, on May 19, per S*S, 'SUKYBATES'. In this connection please forward on our account the following cable to the authorities in Cairo4- Bapco shipping 485 tons Bahrein Smalls to Savon Port Said advise Moxey Savon London to arrange insurance and pay prank Strick £» 1,697- 10- 0 account freight. yours faithfully. a Aer- W. P, ANDERSON CHIB? LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. j \ EM/JGCInter Of# Telegram From Political Agent, Bahrain To MESC0-, Repeated to M*W*T. Fo • ^ 7^ Dated 21st May 1944. Oa iro Basra Reference your telegram Mo.13 of May 17th and Savingram Mo.17 of April 27th, Until additional equipment and labour become available further shipments of coke must be deferred. Our letter Con-171 of Moy 15th is in reply to your Savingram No.16 of April 22nd. Though the bags are second-hand they are in satisfactory condition. (Above from Bahrain Petroleum Co.). Political Telegram Inter Or^t. From Political Agent, Bahrain To MESCO, Cairo Mo. 4?2&gt; Dated 21st May 1944. Following from Bahrain Petroleum Company. Bahrain Smalls. Shipping to Savon Port Said 485 tons per s.s.'^urybates’*. Kindly advise Moxey Savon ijondon to arrange effect insurance and also pay £ 1697-10-0 as freight to Frank Strick. PoliticalCQNFEDSHTIAL CON-166 Avail, 1944 &amp; no Petroleum Division RepresentatIve r British Embassy BAGHDAD• Dear Sir, © SUPPLY OF STOKES fITei161.141 Please refer to our letter of February 17, 1044 our file reference 101al6 to D.Q*M*G, a*H.q t Palforce a copy of which is attached, giving a list of requirements for our project. Under date of April 13 we received the attached letter from Major T. Hiofclnbotham, Political Agent at Bahrein. Attached also is a copy of our answer to Major Hiclclnbotham giving speci fically the use for which we expected the items listed in our letter of February seventeenth. Apparently there ha© been some misunderstanding for the projected use of the requested equipment. We wish to state that of the projects listed the Aviation Octane Project, Drum Plant and Causeway are each part of the entire aviation project, but represent ing individual components, all of which fit together maiclng for a complete operating plant. The Drum Plant is necessary to manufacture containers with which to ship aviation octane gasoline and the cause way provides facilities for handling incoming raw material for con tainer manufacture, and outgoing filled drums. Of the items listed in our letter of March 18th to Bahrein 1 © Political Agent, we endeavoured to enumerate the items needed under each component of the entire project. You should consider the items listed all as part of the Aviation Project with the exception of the heading 'Coke Shipment'. The items for barges and tugs have been covered under separate correspondence and no further mention will be made of them at this time. For the heading entitled 'Coke Shipment', we specified 'Nothing'. By this was meant that nothing shown on our listing in our letter of February 17th was required. However, this was not meant to convey the thought that Coke Shipment could be made from Bahrein without any additional equipment. Major Boyd of ME SC, Cairo during his visit here, was given a complete summary of equipment required for us to handle coke and this equipment is still required if coke in commercial quantities is desired. We hope the above will make perfectly clear the Intent of our communication to the Political Agent at Bahrein who trans mitted the message to you./ May 24, 1944. We have Just received a communication from PAIC through the Political Agent acopy of which is attached, giving the status of each item listed in our letter of March 18th, 1944. To clear up any misunderstanding of what we have received to date against PAIC voucher numbers and what is required, we are enumerating below the status of each item. The section and title will follow the same form as given in our letter of March 18th. AVIATION OCTANE PROJIICT . 1. 3 Busses for 20 People * 2. 3 small trucks or pickups 3. 6 station wagons . 4. 15- 300 amp- 400 amp ) welding machines ) 5. 200 Carpenters tool kits 6. 30 Tarpaulins 7. 15,000 sq.ft. Corr. Galv.) iron sheet iron. ) 8. 100,000 bd. ft. form lumber 9. 25 kegs nails (10. 2 Launches 30- 60 H.P. (11. 2 Construction barges. CAUSEWAY PROJECT . 1. Six 4-yard dump trucks PAIC message indicates that Item 1 has already been issued. To date we have not received any busses and would suggest that you further check this item. PAIC message Indicates that these have already been issued. We have received against this item 3 Chev. pickups Invoiced against PAIC Voucher No.148. PAIC message indicates not available. PAIC message indicates not available. PAIC message indicates not available. PAIC message indicates that they are Issuing these. PAIC message indicates that they can furnish black only. Under the circumstances this item will be deleted from the list. PAIC message indicates not available. This item will be dropped since form lumber is not available. Has been handled as a special item. No mention was made of this item in PAIC message of May 9th. This item is still required. To date we have received six 3-ton 4x2 tippers for the Aviation Project. These were covered by PAIC Voucher No.11581.CON-106. -3- 24, 1944. 0AT7SS/AY PROtTgCT (Contd.) {£. 25 tons dynaxrdte (3. 10C0 Ho.6 or Ho.8 caps mi d 1 © ad s • PAIC message indicates probably not available but might be able to supply substitute. This item is still required and we would like your further advice concern ing the substitute. 4. 5. 6 . 2 tugs .60 HP or upwards Has 2 construction barges 2 launches 50- 60 HP. been handled as a special item, To summarise the position, the following are still out standing and required from PAIC 30 Tarpaulins 6 4-yard dump trucks, or equivalent in carrying capacity. 85 tons Dynamite, or equivalent. 1000 Ho.6 or Ho.8 caps and leads. If coke Is to be shipped in bulk from Bahrein, equipment for handling this coke will be required in addition to the above. It is our understanding that Major Boyd has given you a list of such equipment and has applied for priorities in this connection. Regarding tugs, barges and launches, these items have been dealt with separately. i/e greatly appreciate the help you have already given us for the items supplied and are in great need of the items on which we anticipate shipment. Anything you can do to expedite these items will be greatly appreciated. Yours very truly, THE BAHRAIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. ORIGINAL SIGNED BY W. P. ANDERSON HAA/wm. 'fcV P. ANDEKCGM - GSNKRair MANAGER. go: H.B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrein, w. a.Mi Her. Files: 101.161 565. 655.1 286. Attach:COKFIDM T IAL ♦ TO The MO • 500-S of 1944. British Kesadency &amp; Consulate-General, ±iushlre } the 27th May 1944. Political Agent, .BAHRAIN. \ ■AsA \vv5 &lt;1^ A?' Theft o f H.A.P . MEMQR AHDIM . a romuniti on at Sharj ah. Reference your Endorsement ITo. C/ 671 , dated 24th April 1944 2 . Please send copy of your Endorsement Ho. C/637, dated 14th April 1944, to the Senior naval Officer, Persian Gulf, referred to therein. ATTESTED. Sd. GEOFFREY PRIBE. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. j for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Political Agency, Bahrainj, the lat 1944. The Political Ag ^nt, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- . f . the Hon’ble the Political Resident in tha Persian Gulf- ^ Boshire , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentiond document(s). Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Memorandum No.500-S dated the 27th May 1944* ■ Noo and date of enclosure Subject : § Copy of telegram No,Nil datc^ the ‘ 30th M^crch 1944 from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf to the Political Agent, Bahrain. o Copy of Express Letter No.C/582-31/1 / dated the 5th April 1944 from Political 4 di Of fleer, Trivial Coast, Sharjah to pW Political Agent, Bahrain. Theft of R ,JuF,ammunition atPA-349 (§) BAKRglN PSTHOLEUI^/I COlvp ACY^ L IlVlirSD Awali - Bahrein Island . Persian Gulf Date May 31, 1944. Political Agent, The Political Agency, B A H R E I N. Dear Sir, Y BAHREIN SMALLS File #565.3 We thank you for your telephonic advice of this morning that our letter CON-171 of May 15, to Cairo, has not yet been received and, as requested, enclose one copy of this letter for despatch by diplomatic pouch to Cairo. A further copy of the letter is attached for your records. Yours faithfully, ' W. P. ANDERSON V CHIEF LOCAL REPRESMTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. EM/JGC EncliAwali, COKFICENTIAL. May 15, 1944, CON- 171. Middle Bast Supply Centre, CAIRO (Egypt) BAH' IS. destination. The Company wishes to advise that it can render little if any assistance in the handling of coke shipments at this time, the situation as to labor and equipment having sertouEdydetoriorated since the visit of Major Boyd in February. Even the small shipments in bags now being made are seriously inconveniencing other operations. The barge situation is especially critical. For example, the recent attempt to load 550 tons aboard a vessel which refused to accept the shipment resulted in one half of the available number of barges being tied up in coke service for three days at a time when these barges were badly needed elsewhere. In view of this situation, coke shipments should be deferred until equipment and labor is available. Coke shipments in bulk will require additional jetty space. The Company is building a new causeway and pierhead which will be completed about the first of next year and which might be used for coke. Until this time, wa have no jetty facilities available for bulk coke handling unless an extension were to be built to our present jetty. Such an extension would be excess after the completion of the new causeway and the Company does not wish to build it, since so doing would delay the completion of the causeway and the installation would only be used for a few months and hence not ,/PA/wm File cc:- HNP/KM 565. RAA - 501.8 RO -565. justifiable. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ar ■I. P. ANDER ON - GET: ERA I MANAGER.Telegram 28/28 Int '0' Repeated To i ; x* Oiil © Mo 29 Dated 22nd and Received 23rd June, 1944 Following for B./UP.C.C^ from M SoC.(L) cP.A.I.C Begins Bahrain coke 1 Barges and tugs now released to Has Tanura are available in intervals between U.S. Ships for handling coke, lugs employed in Has Tanura cou^d not operate Bahrain owing to draft but could tow barges to Bahrain where Zenekas and local ci a.i.t could operate between ship and shore. Consider therefore ciaft b#ip.g supplied could assisu export of coke provided intervals between U.S. Ships at least one week. 6 dump trucks 4 cubic yard capacity and one bulldozer type D 4 will be shipped PAIC calling this month. 12230 mid-east has available a^lOO foot belt conveyor and is forwarding blue prints for yohvto ascertain suitability. PAIC has no suitable plant to offer. modification/)! Sitra jetty not justified as per your Con 171 May 15th. that immediate delivery of items in (1) and (2) above will enable you to continue and preferably extend shipment of coke in bags. 4 Due to time already elapsed M.S.S.C. agree to 5 Please confirm to us, copy to M.B.S.C. mid-east 6 Agreed q(AE) PAIC. End, iu2Bid33ADCR o~ ich \EXPRESS LETTER CONFIDENTIAL From To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. The Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. No C/969 Dated the 24th June, 1944. \s V / Following from MESC(L)PAIC Baghdad dated 22nd June 1944. Bahrain Snails. !• The tugs and barges which have been released to Ras Tanura are now available for handling Bahrain smalls between the arrivals of U.S. Slips. Owing to draft the tugs at Ras Tanura will not be able to operate at Bahrain; they could, however, tow the barges to Bahrain and local craft and Zenekas could work between the pier and the vessel. Provided the intervals between the arrivfels of U. S. Slips is more than a week we ere of the opinion that the export of coke could be facilitated if craft is made available. 2. The following will be shipped by PAIC this month:- 1 bulldozer type D 4 6 four cubic yard capacity dump trucks. 3. MESC Middle East are sending you for examination blue prints of a 100 foot belt conveyor which they have available. No suitable plant is available from PAIC. 4. Reference your Con 171 May 15th, MESC agree that Sitra jetty cannot be modified now as much time has elapsed. 5. Would it be possible for you to continue or, better still, to extend shipment. In bags, of Bahrain smalls if items mentioned in paragraphs 1 &amp; 2 are delivered immediately. Kindly confirm with copy to MESC Middle East. 6. Q(AE)PAIC has approved of the above. Political Agent, Bahrain.*1’ To/... the Bahrein petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. #PA-455. July E, 1944. Major T. H.B.M. f s Political Agent Bahrein Island. Subject: Coke. File #565. Dear Sir: Please refer to/your express letter of E4th June, 1944, your reference C/969, relaying a message from M.l.S.C. (L) PAIC., from Baghdad concerning Bahrein Coke. From time to time we have been requested by various sources to furnish information concerning quantities of coke that could be shipped from Bahrein if the progress of our Aviation Project. Full information concerning equipment requirements were given to Major Boyd of M.E.S.C. in February, Under date of April 15, we received a further in quiry concerning coke, and we ansv/ered M.E.S.C. by our letter of May 15, 1944, emphasizing that (1) our barging situation was critical (2) availability of manpower at Bahrein had seriously deteriorated since the visit of Major Boyd, and (3) even a small 500 ton coke shipment had re sulted in interference with our Aviation Project freight handling* Under the then prevailing conditions we recommended that coke shipments be deferred until equipment and labor v/as available. (1) equipment was provided and (2) providing manpower was available, and (3) if shipment of coke did not interfere withSitra/... &amp;) \%\ 2 —-Major T. Hickinbotham, Bahrein: July 2, 1944. To answer the points brought out in M.E.S.C.’s query to you, we will answer in the same order as given in your letter:- 1. The plan of using tugs and barges turned over to Gray MacKenzie for work at Has Tanura and using them for Bahrein coke shipments when not in use there, is possible, but impracticable. The arrival of freight ships'at Has Tanura and coke ships for Bahrein is very uncertain and at present there is no possible way of determining beforehand firm arrival dates. Further all equipment and tugs will probably be used at Has Tanura when large shipments arrive. Since the tugs and barges have primarily been released to Gray MacKenzie for freight work this handling will undoubtedly be given preference to coke hauling which is as it should be. If M.E.S.G. expects to use the same equipment in double service no assurance can be given for loading times or rates and further they can expect and will have delays of unknown length in loading coke boats. The basis upon which the barges and tugs were re leased for our operating area, was for use in freight for Bahrein and Arabia's projects, and for Bahrein's Drum Plant. All of our previous analyses here have shown that for coke shipments an additional eight barges and four tugs would be required. 2. ^ The equipment being supplied only partially covers the requirements needed for coke handling. In our memo- randum to Major Boyd we specified:- (a) 1 loader for coke, capacity 150 ou. yds/hr. (b) 1 Bulldozer. (c) 1 Wooden bunker—skid mounted. (d) 1 set truck scales to weigh coke—capacity say 10-20 tons. (e) 6 trucks of 6 yd. capacity (14 total re quired of which 8 were ordered for Causeway project by Bapco but not yet received. (f) overhanging ramps or chutes for dumping into barges.Commented;/... (§) 3—Major T. Hiokinbotham, Bahrein: July 2, 1944, (g) Sitra Pier extension. (h) 8 barges, 4 tugs (refer to Item No. 1 above). (i) (Xncentete handling equipment, i.e., steel buckets with trunions of about 1 ton capacity or more used on barges to be lifted by ship f s gear to dump into the boat. Of the items mentioned in M.l.S.C.’s message, they mention under Item 3 a belt conveyor. Prints and a letter concerning this were received before your message and we answered directly to M.E.S.O. by our letter of 25th June, 1944. The wooden bunker could probably be made by us. We require the scales which are not included imM.E.S.C.’s materials. Trucks are short. Six 6-yd. trucks gives a total capacity 36 truck yards or if 4-yd. trucks are being supplied, 9 are necessary. Lately we received 6 - 3-yd. dumps from Paiforce for our Causeway. Although we ordered eight 6-yd. dumps from the States for our Causeway project, these have not been received, and it is doubtful if we will get them account of material difficulties. Paiforce trucks have been requested to get on with the project. The six 3-yd. dumps used for our Causeway job (part of the Aviation Project) could be diverted tdhandling coke for infrequent shipments. However, we will still be short of trucks as in our recommendation - we suggested 14 - 6-yd. trucks or 84 truck yards against which we will be available 6 - 4-yd. trucks being shipped from M.E.S.C. and 6 - 3-yd. trucks Bapco is using on Cause way, or a total of 42 truck yards. This is only half the truck capacity needed, and M.E.S.C. must realize that former anticipated rates cannot be met. However, upon completion of the Causeway, which is expected about the first of the year, together with probable availability of dump trucks from our Aviation Project about the same time, T/re believe that sufficient dump trucks will then be available to handle coke at the desired rates. No mention is made in M.E.S.C. f s message of con centrate buckets. How it is proposed to get coke on barges in bulk and transfer it to a ship is unknown. We have no equipment for doing this, nor could we proceed to build any thing for this service at the present time. We would like this point cleared as without proper gear bulk shipments cannot be made.agreement/... 4 Major T. Hickinbotham, Bahrein: July 2, 1944. 3. Commented on above. 4. No comments, except handling coke and freight over same jetty precludes handling of either freight or coke efficiently or inminimum time. 5. Refer to^our notes below on the local labor situation. Dump trucks.are suitable for bulk coke handling, whereas flat beds should be used for sacked coke. We cannot continue or extend shipment of coke in sacks, except for very limited quantities, because of lack of labor. The labor situation is particularly bad and we are short 2,000 natives^for our own project and operations. As you know, we have discussed this problem with'you and have even suggested importation of labor to relieve the severe manpower shortage. Although everything possible is being done to alleviate this condition, the fact is we still are short 2,000 men. Until this shortage is relieved, we cannot undertake to supply labor for coke shipments. We do not wish anything to interfere with the progress of our Aviation Pro ject, as all authorities agree this is of first importance. We are just as interested in disposing of our coke as M.E.S.C. is interested in obtaining it. Under the con ditions of lack of labour, and M.E.S.C. not being able to furnish the necessary equipment, we hesitate to say that we could ship coke. Our only suggestion at this time would be for M.E.S.C. to take over the complete operation ex our coke pile; they to furnish the equipment, operate it, bring in the labor com plete with portable camps to adequately house the necessary workmen, and handle everything connected with coke shipments. We would loan the trucks with drivers that we have procured for our Causeway project during the period of coke shipment. We are agreeable to purchasing now the dump, trucks, truck scales and bulldozer. Although this equipment in it self is insufficient for handling coke, if purchased, we would like to exercise the privilege of using the trucks and bulldozer on our Causeway project to speed its completion, so that we may get on with the handling of coke at the earliest opportunity. We would like M.E.S.C. f s confirmation ofmz ' v &gt; *t / IS) 5—Major T. Hickinbotham, Bahrein: July 2, 1944. agreement. For the coke loader, and other equipment listed above, we prefer not to make any commitment now for its purchase. Deferrment to purchase the equipment should be made until labor is available, and a review undertaken that handling can be underteken to meet the commercial quantities already expressed as desired and needed. . s suggested that you convey the above inform ation to M.E.S.C. We are mailing two copies of this letter directly to them. Yours very truly, W.P. Anderson, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. RAA:MK. oc—M.E.S.C. (E) N.Y. (2)THS BAHlpB: PETROLmiA GOLPMY T.iR tthJT i^ali - Bahrein TsTanr. Persian Gulf Late I t f I f ij'-» »J I Yuly 1944. ( 1 \ Mr. H.M. Eadow, Assistant political Agent, Manama. Subject: Coke/ File $565. Dear Sir, In accordance with your telephone request, we enclose a further copy of our letter No.PA-455 dated 2nd July 1944 written in connection with the Bahrein Coke. Yours very t W.P. ANDLESCN Chief Local ifepresentative TEE BAHHETN PETflCLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. \ttachment—Printed in England. Sept. 1941. (-4,100. pads, f CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (incorporated in enoland.) The first line of thi^ Telegram contains the following particulars in^the-order n Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed Official instructions—if any. , Clerk’s Time Received. Circuit. W 9 P.H. 1700 NSV46/P S CAIRO 39/37 15 1256 BGETAT ANTEN = IMPORTANT POLITICAL BAHREIN = NO 16 FOR BAPC PLEASE DEFER YOUR REPLY TO' OUR LETTER IP02504/ASD/123 OF 8TH JULY 1944 UNTIL RECEIPT OF OUR REPLY TO YOUR PA 455 0 F 2ND JULY 1944 ADDRESSED TO POLITICAL AGENT MESCO . MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ie^uaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.Confidential .. No.C/1069. . \ Political Agency, Bahrain, theioth July The following telegram received on 15th July 1944 f is forwarded with compliments to The ^hisf Lo^al T?opr esentntl ve ? —-Bahrain ,. 1 V# ,, / Tele^rnii No.16 dated 15th July 1944 from For EAPCO. aA ( • i Please defer your reply to our letter IPO 2504/ASDA23 4-1 of 8th July 1914 until receipt of our reply to your PA-455 of 2nd July 1944 addressed to Political Agent. ! ' I■n—rr^ ' . ■ — «flDDL. EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, \C\ 10, Sharia Tolurabat, CAIRO. July, 1944. IP02504/A$D.//^ Dear Sirs .Keference yo-ur letter No, PA-455 of 2nd July 1944 addressed to Political Agent, Bahrein with copy to this Centre. A. To avoid atxf nossibility of misunderstanding, we desire to emphasise that all correspondence on the subject of coke for kiddle East is initiated by this Centre. There is no question of a number of Authorities dealing independently with the matter without complete liaison. The fact that you, from time to time receive communications from N * . Paiforce or from our Baghdad resentative, is occasioned by our either requesting- these officers to write you direct on a particular aspect,or to their re-transmitting to you a message from us after their approval, r *11*1 The communications passed to you by Ji.E.S.C.(L) through the Political Agent in his C/969 comes under the latter category. , / It i^ regretted that the words ,f capable of modification to # cu. yds. capacity' were omitted from paragraph 2, in letter C/969f also that the following paragraph appearing in our original was inadvertantly omitted from same 'Due to inevitable timelag in delivery and installation of equipment we are anxious to effect delivery of such items as are available at once. We cannot justify, however, the equipment lying idle pending receipt of balance”. C. e deal consecutively, hereunder, tfith your comments on our paras one to five, Para One . The responsibility for supplying harbour craft for coke handling lies with London, The ruling that Has Tanura craft should be used was taken by ar Office in consultation with , .. who, it must b© presumed, are fully aware of the reactions, if any, such a scheme would have on the turnround of ocean-going vessels. Para Two . As stated in our para 2 above we considered it desirable to furnish you with equipment as it becomes available for the final scheme. If you have no material suitable for the fabrication of overhanging ramps, please give details of your requirements, when we will endeavour to locate a source of supply. * The provision of suitable baskets or buckets for loading loose material from barge to steamer discussed by Hajor Boyd with M. ,T. Representative Basrah who indicated that supply could be arranged through his office. Will you therefore place your indent on Basrah. Belt loader, bulldozer, storage bins and truck scales have been dealt with in previous correspondence. The question of the adaptability of available dump trucks to the carrying of 6 cu. yds. each was discussed with the appropriate 'ranch of Uaiforce. As the rear door of the truck v 1 J P • T • 0 •\ % - a - 4. ' is binged at the top* the heightening of the sides front and rear of the box v?ould ‘ ' rfere ^ith its operation. In this wished to convey our acceptance of the fact that bulk loading could not start until the completion of your causeway* as per vour con-X?l of 15th iiay 1944, Para ive . trucks for handling material in bags but we feel that no great incovenience would be experienced in using dump trucks for bags especially as bagging is only *a temporary measure. r yonr Con-171 of Ijth May 1944 mentioned that handling of bagged coked would have to be deferred, due to shortage of labour and harbour craft. Since you gave an instance of your difficulties in the latter category we assumed these were of ,, greater magnitude than those associated with labour# It is however a problem with which we are unable to,deal directly. v @ would suggest, however, that.the installation of the bulldozer, belt-conveyor and storage bins as indicated in our even number dated 8th July 1944 would reduce the number of men required by allowing bags to be filled from the bin through simply designed chutes or gates. ^leyoytheless, we are informed by V'ar Office that ?r . • .T. attach the greatest importance to the clearance of coke from Pahrein to lid East and/or India 11 . Following this directive we are anx ous to bring the scheme to fruition. With reference to the penultimate paragraph of your page 4. it is regretted that the undertaking of such a scheme is^impossible within the terms of reference of this Centre. It has always been considered that the scheme would, be best undertaken by your Company rather than by another which would necessitate the establishment of a separate administration. the Political Agent for the importation of labour to overcome your present shortage* but your suggestion that this Centre should handle coke shipments would indicate that the obtentiori of labour is not impossible. If this is so and there are good reasons why you should not operate the scheme as arranged* then we consider that Messrs, Cray Mackenzie should be approached to undertake the handling; but without the facilities which are available to you we feel their difficulties \^ould be great. Summarising the above 5- * . * ' . ♦ • - • • * (a) We accept the fact that bulk-loading cannot commence until the completion of the causeway. (b) We consider that equipment should be accepted as it becomes available. It is admitted that it would be preferable to use flat Our assumption would appear to have been incorreqt. It is realised that your construction programme * ^ commands first priority and we have no desire to retard this wrk. e are unaware of the result of your negotiations with- 3 - \ c \\ (c) We consider that in view of the fact that by- use of the available plant your labour difficulties could be to some extent overcome, intermittent shipments of bagged coke should therefore be possible between now and the end of the present year. We are anxious to come to some finality in this matter and would appreciate your re-consideration of the problem in the light of recent correspondence. If you see your way to assist in the preparation for bulk-loading at the end of txie present year and you can handle bagged shipments in the interim^ (to relieve the present coal shortage and to permit of using the Port Said Briquetting Plant on which considerable outlay has been expended for the operation), we would appreciate an indication of a tentative programme. Upon its receipt we will notify London and Washington of the tonnage of imported coal that we can eliminate and arrange shipment with Yours faithfully, '1.V Messrs, Bahrein Petroleum Coy, Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf , Ltd., Cooies tos MESC Rep. Baghdad - ’Sith copy of PA-455. - Pet. Div. Rep., Baghdad. Pet. Off. Defence Dept., Govt, of India, te’.? Delhi. M. 1. T. Basrah. Political Agent, Bahrein.^ JDB.&amp; Ho.^/1109 Political Agency, Bahrain, 26th July 1944. To J. D. Boyd, Esq., Middle East Supply Centre, 10, Sharia Tolumbat, ^airo• Heferenne paragraph B of your letter No.IPO 2504/ASD dated the 17th July 1944. 2. It is pointed out,to avoid misunderstanding J that the omissions mentioned did not o^cur in this office and must have occurred before the original transmission of the message from ^airo. M&amp;MDHANDOM Politico1 Agent, Bahrain. ^opy for information to: Messrs. Bahrain Petroleum ^o., Ltd., Bahrain.... . IP02504/ASDJ Political Agent, Bahrein, Persian Gulf— MIDDLE EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, 10, SHARIA TOLUMBAT. CAIRO. \c\?&gt; 1 August, 1944. \ n Petroleum Coke. Reference your C/1109 of 26th July 1944. 9 o We realise that the omissions referred to in our even number of 17th July 1944 were the result of incomplete re-transmission from Baghdad and not from your office. It was necessary, however, when informing B.A.P.C.O. of these omissions to refer to your letter C /969 in which form our communication reached thei &lt;■'11 Assistant Director,*** ( 1/ Industrial Production. Copy to: B.A.P.C.O., Awali, Bahrein. JDB. i 1 \THE BAHR EIN P EIROLEUIv: GCL Pa IT LIEITED Awali - Bah rein Isla nd Persian Gulf* Date August 8, 1944. No. PA-64 His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I shall appreciate your despatching the enclosed cover addressed to the Middle East Supply Centre, Cairo, via your facilities at an early date. The charges in this connection may please be debited to our account in the usual manner. W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Enel:cmmmM* mt- m A W A i X, August 1,1944. Assistant Director, Industrial Production, Middle East Supply Centre, 10 Sharia Tolnmhat, GAiEo, nem. Dear Sirt COKE SDPfLl Pile: 301.8 Keference: Your letter of July 17, 1944 subject Bahrein Smalls* IP02504/ASD/1. The following coments follow in the same consecutive order as in your letter: (1} fe have no control over the aarine craft supplied to Gray Msekensle by M # W*f* and we have discussed with them the plan proposed fey the War Office* lour letter presumes that M.W.T. are fully aware of the delay that would be caused to the turn* around of freighters if freight barges and tugs were diverted to coke hauling. Our discussions with Grey Mackenzie Indicated that severe delays in freight vessel turnaround will result if such diversion is practiced* In the past our studies on this subject have shown that additional barges and tugs would be recuired for such an operation* Kefer to our previous letter. However, since Gray Mackenzie will handle the barging and tugging we have again presented your comments to them, for them to answer you directly. (2) We will accept the dump trucks and bulldozer now. The trucks have already been received and we presume the bulldozer is feeing shipped. Overhanging ramps or chutes necessary to dump coke from trucks to barges will be fabricated by us. Concerning suitable baskets or buckets for loading loose bulk coke, we have discussed this problem with Gray Mackenzie* feince it has been planned that Gray Mackenzie would do the lighter ing ex dump trucks at our pier, the buckets would be part of their equipment. Therefore we will not place an indent on M.W.T.,Basrah, for such equipment. Gray Mackenzie has been given full details on this subject and they are studying the problem and will write you directly concerning such equipment.MMsULft Mg.t, Supply Ce.ntye. Belt Conveyort We have your letter of July 8* 1944 with the three prints giving details. Since the original question of loading was discussed we have procured for our Aviation Project a portable gasoline engine driven bucket loader Capacity of this machine Is between two and three yards per minute and is ample for the rate planned for truck loading of coke. It is anticipated that this machine will be available for coke handling about the time when our Causeway is finished. This machine has greater capacity then the belt conveyor you so kindly offered and also affords the flexibility in operation of being portable. We are returning the prints of the belt conveyor that you loaned for our review attached to your letter of July 8th. (3) Mo comments. (4) We confirm that bulk loading cannot be started until completion of the Causeway. (5) Our reason for suggesting that M.E.a.C. take over complete handling of coke ex our pile was based on the thought that you may have access to military labor which would not be available to us. Further f administration of military labor could not under such circumstances be handled by us. We still are short about 2000 natives for our project, ie have on hand 200 tons of sacked coke which we believe could possibly b© shipped after Ramadan. It is expected that after Ramadan the pearl fisheries will not continue in full force and some men may be available to assist in making such a shipment. We have enough additional sacks to make up a further 600 tons but this could not be undertaken until sometime after Ramadan when we could better determine what our manpower problem will he, We will advise you as quickly as we can concerning the possibility of sacking and making ready for shipment 600 tons. Please advise if you are Interested in procuring the 200 tons now available in sacks, * If we find we can continue to make restricted coke shipments in sacks after Ramadan wt will advise promptly to this effect, advising the quantities that can be undertaken. Could you furnish us with sacks for this operation as no sacks are available beyond the amount to handle the 600 tons given above: We believe that the above answers the (a)(b) (c) parts of Uj^^immary in your letter. We are agreeable to (a) and (h) £ l £ On the problem of lighter trig and buckets for bulk shipments Cray Mackenzie will write you directly on what can be done. For (c) we can now ship 200 tons and have enough sacksfclddl* Bast aucjly Centre, August 1. 1944 (top \^1 for a 600 ton shipment sometime after Kamad&amp;n providing labor is available to which we will advise as promptly as we can and will also then advise what may be expected between that time and the completion of our Causeway. You are to endeavor to develop a supply of sacks with which we could make bagged shipments if this can be undertaken. Yours very truly. THE BAHREIN L'jJuil jrA iXVJLt&amp;vm WV4&amp;JE ORIGINAL SIGNED BY W. P. ANDERSON PETEOtEUM C0MPAH1 LIMITED A. P. A S5i.HSOJ^,C^P* Pu\L MMASEkIP 02504/A :-J. JLe Ctutare i&gt; sharia I’ OX'UU : wtl v «L a »-^ j • e-r *■?', m tharik yam for yam* * &amp;{s Au/mst, l^ 4 -. ^ . 204 of 1st ft»fttst y 1944 # /•s stated p^wlously we 4KT# resigned to the fact tint built loading &gt;111 only be possible nnna co.n^I^tien of tba causeway* # arc grateful to learn that 200 ton Ly bagged and that you aVe hopeful of bag aii ship fuTtL&amp;v tomagss some t las ills, are hie to .#*4 After consulting Messrs* a von «&gt;e would prefer to defer sfcipmeat of the 200 ions 1 In question until such tin* as t&gt;ey can he a^4e up to a 500 ton parcel, unless the 200 ton ^reel would be m®T&amp; acceptable to A, *1* Basrah* e feel that local conditions - shipping and otherwise should determine this point* e re e r ‘.leavorring to obtain Bags for further tonnages to accordance with-the request in your parmgrapii 5* In this cotmexioa we would refer to our ' r o• 17 eving of 21st ipril, 1944 in which we reported having htn.rd fees i!ea«rr # Fa von that ad been able to obtain against their account you bags for 3,CKK) tarns ef mml Is would be appreciated# leiwfc I rif teation of the position r e | ire pressing faiforce to deliver the bulldoser and ar# still endeavouring to locate a suitable weighbridge# e look forward to early advice of readiness in respect Of Hie first parcel of bagged siaalls and wml&amp; ask you to use the tern rt ss*alls fl on all documents to overcome difficulties utiorities. e lesire to record our Vmnks for your co-operation in this scheme at a time when you arc so fully occupied in the execution of ath&amp;r high priority work turner difficult condi tions# ours fa It! fully, S 1; - ; -: IlfOTStllAl iroctor, pntmcfim , o •••$“*?♦ ''0A culi Aoy. .t^: # , Awali. Bahrein i ^f?tnd * Co-*y tot- E.f.A.C* A-epresentailve Baghdad# Petroleum .epresent^-tire, -agi iad# ■a^ c A'-' 1 '■ ' * a r ! ' ‘'‘A India mj&amp;r- Aolh 1. * a # 1 p ' ^ srah. •&lt; '‘..i-rpin,V y 00N-S17. So -dk&amp;il. c 'W Middle East Supply Centre, 10, SJdaria Tolumbat, Cairo, Igjrpt, September 3, 1944. re: Bahrein Smalls. File #301.8 Dear Sirs: Attention: Mr. D.D. Davidson . Please refer to your letter of August El, 1944, your IP.03504/A8D. It is planned to start sacking additional quantities of coke as quickly as conditions allow to make up a 500 ton parcel. We will advise you as soon as this has been accomplished, so you may arrange for shipment. Concerning bags, the bags we did receive only hold about 60 lbs., whereas we expected they would hold nearly twice this weight. Many sacks were poor, or broke, or were so bad as to not contain the smalls. These two items have resulted In an estimated sack loss of 1,000 tons. The additional sacks that we expected, we were not able to pro cure. Hence, we have only sacks for handling the quantities given in our letter of 1st August. Any additional sacks you can supply to us for this purpose will bq greatly appre ciated. Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, ORIGINAL signed by W* P. ANDERSON W.£.Anderson, General Manager. RAA:MK. cc—H.B.M. f s Political Agent. 1/ Eng• Files.* I , - ■ 28/28. \ ' ' Telegraa Inter (Pad). Froffi M.E.S.C., Cairo. To Political /gent, Bahrain. No. 18. Dated the 25th and received 26th September, 1944. Following paraphrased telegram No. 311890 from Ministry of War Transport London is repeated to you for information begins:- • Space has been allocated in steamship 'Empire /ddis' for import of bagged petroleum coke. nuantity is 200 to 600 tons and ship is expected to be ready at Bahrain 15th / 30th September. R.M. I.R.856 Dt. 26.9.44. P.T,C.28/28. Telegram From To Repeated Inter (Pad). M.E.S.C. 9 Cairo. Political Agent, Bahrain. Ministry of War Transport, London. Ministry of War Transport, Basra. M.E.S.C., Baghdad. Saving. No. 19. Dated the 2nd and received 3rd October, 1944. # For Bapco. Bahrain Smalls. Ministry of War Transport London advise altering space now available to Egypt as follows: ® October 500 tons November 500 tons December to be notified during October. Savon advise (MUT). Please state possibilities (MUT). R.M. I.R. 893. Dt. 4.10*44. - MESC0 -Wa*. . TEE BAKR3IN PETHOI^UM. 00rI- A.'Y LIMIIED Aw all - Bahrein Island * Persian Gulf PA-241 Gate October 8th, 1S44. Political Agent, Bahrain. $5' BAEIAIP SI ALLS File #565.3 Bear Sir, Kindly forward the following cable in connection wit if the shipment of coke to be made to Messrs. L. Savon &amp; Co., Port Said, per 3.S. 'KLPIHE ADDISON” ”Bapco shipping 200 tons Bahrein Smalls gross 207 tons to Savon Port Said advise Koxey Savon london to arrange insurance and pay Strick Line L.724-10-0 account freight”. Kindly debit any charges in this connection to our account. Yours very truly, CL^\A For W.P. ANDERSON, CHIEF LOCilL HEPRESMTATITE, THE BAHREIN PSTHOLEOl^ COMPANY LI KITED (O- 10' fylf ft. X-k-C/° /a \c°' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. PA-254 Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir: Octoher 8th, 1944. V* S# Pile 009.52 V With reference to your letter PAG/1427, appended 'below is a reply, which I would appreciate your transmitting litL via your faci To: M. E. S. C. Cairo. es at an early date:- u From: The Bahrein Petroleum Company Bahrein. Begins: 'SB TOUHEEL 19 BEFEHENCE BAHREIN SMALLS CABIB RECEIVED BALLY MUTILATED STOP NOW PREPARING 400 TONS FOR END OCTOBER SHIPMENT AFTER WHICH LACK SACKS WILL NOT PERMIT FURTHER SHIPMENTS STOP IF YOU CAN SUPPLY SACKS BELIEVE CAN SACK 400 TONS MONTHLY STOP TO PEEPAEE FOR SHIPMENT 400 TONS END NOVEMBER SACKS MUST BE HERE BY END OCTOBER STOP ADVISE' ends Yours very truly, For W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED %7 X«y M. A/.. s'- X. A /m sU/m }// JA:DBTelegram Int. n O rT ' From. Pol’itical Agent, Bahrain To ‘ M*E.S*C* Cairo' No. HI) Dated 10th October 1944. Following from Bahrain Petroleum company: Bahrain Smalls. Shipping to Savon Port said 207 (half 414) gross tons per s.s.'Empire Aldison'. Kindly advise Moxey Savon London to effect insurance and also pay £ 724-10-0 (half 1,449) as freight to Frank Stride. Political21 The Bahrein Petroleum company Limited A w a 1 i Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 10, 1944. No .PA-247 Political Agent The Political Agency, Man ama, Ba hrein. BAHREIN SI ALLS File ^555.3 -V* Bear Sir Further to our letter No .PA-241 of October 8th, we have to advise that a part of this shipment was shut out. As a result, will you please arrange to despatch the following cables as soon possible to M.H.3.C. Cairo :- (1} 'Cancel previous telegram Bahrein Smalls Quantity shipped 117 tens Advise Moxey ^avon London to arrange insurance and pay Stride Line L.409-10-0 account freight.' (2) M.E.S.C., Cairo, Repeated to M.W.T. Basrah 'Reference your telegram No.18 September 25th EMPIRE ADDISON to lift 200 to 600 tons Bahrein Smalls We had 7500 sacks 207 tons gross sacked barged ready to load Agents now advise 3268 sacks shut out due lack space'. Kindly debit all charges in connection with the above cables to our account. Yours very truly CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.*ffl) f Telegram From To No Dated 11th October 1944. . fsi Int. ,, 0 M Political Agent, Bahraii^^ M.S.S.C. Cairo Following from Bahrain Petroleum company. Bahrain Smalls. Please cancel Bahrain telegram No.928 * October 10th. Shipped 117 tons (half 234)p-e-p—e^c^J.Bmpire^Aad Kindly advise Moxey Savon London effect insurance and also pay £409-10-0 (half 818) to Strick Line as freight. f • / Political V Zo t'lto . S(A) Political Agent, Bahrain M.E.S.C. Cairo M.W.T. Basraft Date&amp; 'i; ftii October 1944. Following from Bahrain Petroleum Company. Reference your telegram September 25th,No.18, s.s.“Empire Addison to lift 200 to 600 tons . 7500 sacks '(207 tons gross) were sacked and barged ready to load. Due to lack of space 3268 sacks shut out as advised by agents. Telegram From. To Repeated, to No'. 9%Z Political0 SECRST No.C/1526, To Political Agency, Balirain, 26th October 1944. Tbo Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum co., Ltd., Bahrain. HBMORAIJDUM I have been advised from Cairo that M.W.T* London , have allocated space for 500 tons of bagged eoJ$:e in 'Samsturdy* 1 expected tarards the end of October. Political Agent, Bahrain. s.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED PA-297 •Aw a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 25, 1944. / H.B.M. f s Political Agent The Political Agency, ■ Bahrein. BAHREIN 3MALI3 File ^ r 565.3 Dear Sir, • ■ . Please find.enclosed here^Jith documents covering siiipment of 117 tons Coke-to Messrs. Savon &amp; Co., Port Said. Kindly forward relative documents to addressees. Yours faithfully, JvSM/tvw Sncl: M 7 'For W.F. ANBSRSOK, CHIEF LOCAL RSPRBS1MTATIY3, THE BAHREIN PSTR0LED1/I C01PMY LTD.CONFIDENTIAL No.C/ V 1 « Political Agency, Bahrain, 5th November 1944* To / The Manager, . Messrs* Gray Mackenzie &amp; Go*, Ltd Bahrain* MEMORANDUM . It is proposed to commence bn3.k loading of Bahrain co]f:e from the beginning of January 1945 and .the M«E«S*C* Cairo have asked me to obtain from you information on the following points (a) Eotlmated labour position (b) Availability of tugs and barges (ex rus Tanura) (c) Suitability of tugs and barges.(ex Has Tanura) (d) Progress in procurement ef loading buckets/baskets (e) Any'other relevant data 2 m I shall be grateful for an early report on the points raised to enable me to furnish them with a reply* Political Agent, Bahrain,1HE BAHREIN PETR0LH3M TOtPANY LBIITg) Awali - Bahrein island* PA-371 H.B.M.’s Political Agent, The Political Agency, Manama* November 12, 1944. BAHREIN SMALLS File #555.3'“ Dear Sir, Kindly forward the following cable in connection with the shipment of coke made to Messrs. L. Savon &amp; Co., Port Said, per S.S. 'SAM STURDY' :~ 'Bapco shipping 422 tons Bahrein Smalls gross 435 tons to Savon Port Said Advise Msxey Savon London to arrange insurance and pay Strick Line £.1,522-10-0 account freight'. Kindly debit any charges in this connection to our account. Shipping 422 tons (gross 435 tons) Bahrain Smalls^ to Savon Port Said by Bahrain Petroleum Go, Kindly pay£ l 3 522~D-0 (half £3,045) to Stricks and advise Moxey Savon London to arrange insurance, - ANDERSON, CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.BF ~ 118 BAP GO SHIPPING 422 TONS BAHREIN SMALLS GROSS 435 TONS TO SAVON PORT SAID ADVISE MOXEY SAVON LONDON TO ARRANGE INSURANCE AND PAY STRICK LINE POUNDS 1,522-10-0 ACCOUNT FREIGHT Copies to : &gt;&gt; o Nj &gt;-F v BAHREIN PETROLEUM 'VO^O =s= h- tjp—■23/28. Telegram Inter (Pad). Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. To -M.E.S.G., Cairo. No. 1023. Dated, the 16th November, 1044. / I IMPORTANT . Following from Bahrain Petroleum Company. Shipping 422 tons (gross 435 tons) Bahrain Smalls to Savon Port Said by Bahrain Petroleum Company. Kindly pay £1,522-10-0 (half £3,045) to Stricks and advise P'oxey Savon'London to arrange insurance. • - POLITICAL . /S '■'t ' / 0 \KM' ! ; jj&gt;t&gt;- n *«« -. ««r&lt;^.!-^ &lt;-M ^•' Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. ltd. ^ (iNCORPORATED JN KNQUANoj BRANCHES! MS A Q OFFICE: SUSREH, BUNDER.ABBAS N REPLY PLEASE QUOTE 122, LEADENHALL. STREET, ^CLv2&gt; AM A RAH, L.INGAH, O LONDON, E.C, 3, » V— ° KUT. BAHREIN. t, N ° TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS; KHORAMSHAHR. KOWEIT. \ .\V GRAY ** AHWAZ (for DUBAI. CODES used: BANDAR-SHAHPOUR.) SHARJAH. BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. B U S H I R E, MUSCAT, BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. RAS TANURA Bahr e in, ..12th Novemb er, 19 44 ♦ C ^ v ^ Tlie Political Agent, BAF-TREIN. Dear Sir, COKE SHIPl'ISilTS FROM We have your letter no. c/ 1578 of the 5th instant, wherein you advise that it is proposed to commence bulk loading of Bahrein coke from the beginning of January, 1945, and that the M.E.S.C. Cairo, have asked you to obtain from us certain information in regard to labour and shipping facilities., Wo have already had correspondence on this subject with the Bahrein Petroleum Company, MWT Basrah and' the actual consignees in Egypt, Messrs. L* Savon &amp; Co* It would appear that the communication you have received from M.E.S.C. Cairo, follows on a letter written by us to M.W.T. Basrah on 30th July last, a copy of which we enclose for your information. In passing on a copy of our letter to M.E.S.C. Cairo, MWT Basrah write as follows *- «The enclosure speaks for itself .... ... It would appear doubtful whether many of these barges will be free of Has Tanura work long enough to be made available for coke, as the schedule of con structional material ships allows practically no gaps’* We will now deal with the points in your letter. k'D is difficult to estimate the labour position, but we believe it is the general opinion that on Bahrein Island the labour position should become easier later on. Cn the other hand we believe that the demand for labour at Has Tanura will continue to increase and that this will affect the position here, in any case we doubt if there will be enough to go round and if labour find employment elsewhere, it is unlikely that they will choose to workMW2/1G6# Bahrein, 3uth July, 44. The Bepresentative, British Ministry of War Transport, BASRAH. -k Bear sir, COKE SHIPMENTS FROM BAHREIN . This afternoon we had a call from Mr. Andresen of the h&amp;hi ein Petroleum Co. Ltd., who informed us that they have received a letter dated 17ta July, 1944, from the Assistant Director of Industrial Productions, M.E.S.C*, a copy of which has been sent to you. Mr. Andresen informs us that the M.E.S.C* are most anxious to arrange for large shipments of coke from Bahrein at the rate of about 800 tons per day. The Bahrein Petroleum Company have been in communication with the M.E.S.C. for s ome time now on this subject, and we under stand have all alon^ explained that they are not in a position to handle coke in addition to their present commitments, but apparently M.E.S.C. have now offered to provide the necessary equipment in the shape of a bull-dozer, trucks and belt conveyor and, provided they could obtain the necessary labour to handle the coke on shore, the next problem is that of lighterage from shore to ship and loading on board the s learner. In the letter referred to above we understand that it is stated that the responsibility for the supply of craft to handle the coke lies with the war Office, who are reported to have stated that the craft transferred from Be sra for the Has Tanura project could be made available for this purpose. Mr. Andresen also mentioned that it is reported that a suff icient suppiy of tubs can be obtained from Basra, and he added that one proposal is that the tubs be filled in barges from a shute on shore and on being emptied at the ship would be returned In the barge for further loading® 'lie understand that the tubs referred to have a capacity equal to one ton of coal, so that they would probably take about 15 cwt. of coke. Assuming that we can get 80 tubs in a barge, this would give about 60 tons coke per trip, but as will be read-- • e the s&amp;Gie rither a little labour llj seen hundreds of tubs would be required depending upon one number of bargee employed, and we very much doubt if tubs are available in such numbers* the alternative would be to snip the coke loose aid for this purpose it might be necessary to sox the barges *in the same way as was done for handling gravel on the ligris), out diis means v/e would recuire laboui* in each hatch of the barges to fill the tubs alongside the steamer and as labour could not fee expected to work right through, ( two or three shifts would be necessary, 'we have had ..risnce. ih t 2 e #hipping of coho, and we know that •,..ikc woraii, w with coke wore than anything else, so much so that ;ve doubt if we could keep them working at it for any length of time, especially in view of the present labour position here* Even if craft were available, we feel that *.-e c Quad not maintain the necessary supply of labour to work continually on coke, and assmuiug that we could, we believe the cost would so ex'tremely high, m any case shipments of cone in anything lino ‘die tonnage suggested could not be considered tilu after completion of B/.PCC f s nev« cause ;ay about the beginning of 1945. However, before considering die matter idrm.er we should so guad to have your* views on this subject, particularly in regard to bhe supply of craft and tubs* Yours faitnfuily, / A.V tHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A W A L I 'V' v' Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. November 16. 1944. Major T. Hickinbotham, H. B. M’s. Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Island. Dear Sir: BAHREIN SMALLS File: 301.8 / Reference your letter of November 5th - C/1579 - enclosing copy of savingram from M.E.S.C., Cairo. In order to provide you with best possible information we have rescheduled our Causeway Project and work yet to be done to handle Bahrein smalls. We will answer the points inM.E.S.C's. savingram in the same order as given: a) Completion of Causeway: Final completion with pierhead, power and lighting system estimated end of May, 1945* b) No difficulty on dump bunkers — this is a small item and portable loader has capacity to handle requirements -- can build in a few weeks if necessary. c) Bucket loader nov*r available. d) Sufficient trucks available but required full time to complete causeway. Cannot undergo coke handling now. e) Labor position improving last half month account pearl fisheries discontinuing seasonal activities. Shortage still exists and we are still trying to recruit 1000 men for Aviation Project. However, expect continued improvement and hopeful importing needed labor. f.l) Extended completion time of Causeway has been occasioned by ( 1 ) shortage of manpower ( 2 ) truck requirements for our Aviation Gasoline Program necessitating withholding trucks from the Causeway Project (3) Later delivery of trucks (4) Construc tion equipment not available account other higher priority work. r2 November 16^ 194-4. It may be possible about first of February to build a wooden temporary barge tie-up spot along the Causeway in water sufficiently deep in high tide to handle bulk smalls. This would permit bulk shipments before actual final completion of the entire project. We will further advise on this about the first of the year. W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED rk* Telegram From G.T.C. No. Dated Repeated To Mesco, Cairo Political Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Basrah. No.72 29th received 30th November 1944. 24 Addressed Political Agent, Bahrain 24 repeated Britconsul, Basrah 72 for Bapco. Reference paragraph 4 of our saving 31. Jones General Manager Savon intends leaving for Bahrain by the first available plane after December 2nd. /ire whether convenient. -ME3C0- AMC.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited *&gt;%&gt;• #PA/443 Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. November 30, 1944 H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Pile #095 Replying to your letter No.3565 of the 30th November, the arrangements set out in the telegram quoted therein are quite convenient. W. P. ANDERSON, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.t T IMM 30. i944 Copy of telegram No*24 dated 29th November, 1944 from Mesco, Cairo addressed to the Political Agent, Bahrain repeated*Britconsul, Basrah. Addressed Political Agent, Bahrain 24 repeated Britconsul, Basrah 72 for Bapco. Reference paragraph 4 of our saving 31. Jones General Manager Savon intends leaving for Bahrain by the first available plane after December 2nd. Wire whether convenient. Mesco. URG-SNT. No. 5'k S' Political Agency, Bahrain, 30th November, 1944. Copy forwarded to the Chief Local Represen tative, Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., Bahrain, for favour of reply. \IP025014/ASD MIDDLE EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, This is to introduce Mr, A.E. Jones, Director and General Manager of Messrs. L. Savon and Company. His firm is handling the 'other end H of the coke scheme. I should he very grateful if you would give him any assistance he may require in order to bring the scheme to a satisfactory conclusion. 10, SHARIA TOLUMBAT. December, 1944* Yours sincerely JDB Major T. Hickihbotham, H.B.M. Political Agent Manama, BAHREIN.SAYim TiiiLaapm 23 copies To i LONBOB (M* W* T* ) Bo. 121 SAVING Hptds WASHINGTON BAGHDAD (MESC RiSP, ) NSW DEM ‘G^of India) BASRAH ( f. T&gt; RSP. ) BAHREIN (Political Agent) No. 43 SAVING No. 1? SAVING -NO. 1 SAVING No. 2 SAVING No. 1 SAVING From: M. S. S. C D. 12th January 1943 SECRET. •, ^Bahrein Smalls^/. Our telegram No. 6436 Saving repeated \/ashlngton 2252 Saving, New Delhi 28S Saving. A. Masers. Savon’s General Manager has now returned from Bahrein and has submitted his report which is given, verbatim, hereunder: • v *1. I arrived at Bahrein on 16th December, 1944&gt; and immediately contacted Mr. Ward Anderson, General Manager of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, (BAPCO), at AwaXi, about 15 miles distant from Aerodrome at Manama. He sent a car for me and we proceeded to view the Colce Dumps and Causeway now being built, in order to see the lay of the land. He informed me his Company was very keen to dispose of the Coke on hand, but bulk shipments could not be effected until completion of causeway, which he thought would be in June next. , 2. Coke stocks . It is estimated there are 250,000 tons now in dump, and they could turn out an additional 500 tons daily, if necessary. 3* Causeway . There is all the stone required for foundation of this, and plenty of trucks are on spot for the transport of stone and other material required. The labour position is improving, but they are still endeav~ curing to recruit more men, and the shortage of men is the reason why it will not be completed before June. When the present scheme is finished, there will be 12 feet of water at end of causeway, and ocean vessels can moor within a half mile of same. It is planned to further lengthen the causeway by building a trestle pier for half a mile, thus enabling vessels to accost and load direct from quay. 4. weighbridge . In the absence of this, it was suggested that weights of shipments should be established on average contents of trucks, but we finally decided to accept weight according to ship’s draught which, although not too satis** factory, should be more accurate than any other system now available. 5* Deliv®3?y « There will be no difficulty on the part of shippers in delivering the coke, in fact they calculated they would be able to deliver up to 3000 tons.per day, into lighters, where their obligations would cease. 6/ Copy sent to P.R. under P.L.No.c/117 dated 24-1-45.*3 *J» 6 * fills Is whsrs th® Shipping Agents earn Xtu OraiTj, Maskensle and Co* &amp;i?e the onl^ firm established at Bahrein, and they of course agents and lighterage operators of all vessels arriving there, as ' also at Has Tamra, a place on the mainland of Saudi Arabia, 50 miles North of Bahrein* At this latter spot, the Arabian American Oil Co. are established, and it will be a bigger ooaoern than BAFOO. There are always vessels lying there, discharging ?md loading, and Cray, Mackenzie &amp; Co* have a fleet of lighter® and tugs working there constantly* They were emphatic in declaring there was no hope of det&amp;ohing any of this plant to Bahrein, for work in rush periods, as the demand at Has Tamra will continue to increase. They have sufficient lighters and tugs now at Bahrein to cope with present requirements, and more lighters and tugs are expected when certain high priority products of BAFOO will ha ready for shipment* The eMpmanta will be on a large scale and will continue until the sad of the war against Japan* Messrs. Oray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. felt confident they would be able to deal with the bulk shipments of boke in June, by drawing on the tugs and lighters expected to arrive* I saw Mr. Almpster of the M*W*T* at Basrah, on my way to Bahrein and had hoped to have had a further shat with him on my return, hut there was no certain acconssodation offering on planes due to leave for Basrah, when I was ready to leave - on 19 th Beceziber * and I was obliged to take a seaplane direct for Cairo* X understand there is a supply of lighters and tugs at Basrah and am writing to Mr* Kin^eter, asking whether it would be possible to transfer sohb ©f this plant to Bahrein, In case of need* 7* labour . The product for shipment is of an oily nature, and 85 ^ is 'fine dust, so that when handling same everything within a radius of 100 yards or more is more or less smothered with the dust which becomes a smear and it la disastrous to clothes, not to mention bodies and faces* Messrs, dray, Mackenzie &amp; Go. were definitely of the opinion that they would have great difficulty in getting mn to load bulk shipments owing to the objectionable nature of the cargo and the great demand for labour from other sources* I suggested that increased wages would overcome the objection of thm man, and Mr. Melkle finally agreed that this would probably meet the case* 8 * Shipments . Both Messrs. Anderson and Meikle agreed with m tha'F'after making one or two bulk shipments, we shall be able to find out all the ?? anags w in connection with same and then arrange a future program. Xt must not be overlooked that we in Fort Bald may have powerful objectors to the nuisance caused by the dust which will spread during discharging operations and the putting of the fuel into Silos. (It is presumed that officers and crews of vessels chartered to carry the fuel can HOT object, although they and their belongings will be In a sorry mtes). 9. Metho d of Loading * The fuel will be loaded into lighters direct frorJlorries, and a few men will be required in lighters for triisaning purpose®. On arrival alongside vessel, the fuel will be loaded into buckets (holding about 16 ewta.) which can be tipped on release of a catch* In order/*srr-~ -r^zs^n:: ■■ ■ i 3 - 2?^) A r : order to l©an«n the dust during thie operation* it is hoped to fit the tme&amp;et® with a release wire attached to the olips* so that they can he emptied at hottom of hold hy someone at top of th© hatch. Messrs, L* Saycm &lt;&amp; Co« Ltd. , will make 15 of these ’buckets for despatch to Bahrain. Our Requirei^nts . Our factory can cope with a maximum of 50,000 tons of fuel per annum, provided arrivals can be maintained at regular intervals at the rate of about 4,000 tons a month or 6^000 tons every six weeks. It is understood that the major part of the briquettes manufactured from Bahrein fuel will be destined to Europe, and we should naturally v/ant assurance from the co^etent authorities that they would pay for suoh fuel, over a certain definite period, before entering into an engagement with BAPGO for a stated quantity. The present rate of freight - 70/- per ton ~ will undoubtedly be reduced in due course - and without notice * and we cannot run the risk of losses resultant of © falling market. 11* Our Price fox* Briqu ettes, The price quoted for the fuel is 10 rupees per ton a'i &amp;ump, and we were quoted rates by BAPCO and Or&amp;y, Mackenzie &amp; Op, for their opex’ations up to on board. Fries at dump « Bps. 10 Transport to end of ceuseway, loading into lighters and loading f o.b. •vessel \ . Freight (at present) Orqaa IriBurance Marine and Y/ar Cus toma duty Discharging, storing and manufacture on ba&amp;is of 3^f000 tons a year and at present prices, roughly Shortage on Smalls Free on rail -trucks at Port Said or Loading and trimming on board ship at Port Said (less duty) £* ©. 13* 17* 10 . 4* 14* 10 . a. d» 0 6 0 0 0 7* 19* 4 8. 4* 5 7 * 10 . 3 Due reserve 'is made for the fact that above, figures are all based on estimated costs, and may work out sub stantially different” in practice. Ho allowance has been mads for our profit in above figures. Port Said, 26th December, 1944* * B, We understand that the utilisation of a wooden temporary barge tie-up ? constructed alongside tha causeway tor shipping bulk smalls in February as suggested by BAPGO Is considered Impracticable, as barging would only be possible au high ^ide, with consequent delay to shipping. C. Reference in para* 10 to a possible losa to davon when freight drops balow the prasexit 70 /-, le explained by 'he of the market price dropping while large stocks, on which former high charges have been paid, ai^e held. ^ D/ /■■■I ** tjr *» ' * D» We ar# in c m e with th&amp; Bgjptian, 0 ow^Bn^nt regarding the poBSlhilit.;f of a modification of the import dutj of 14 /2d. and are hopeful of obtaining a reduction of 6/- per ton. This will., of eonre©* oalF affeet eales within Bg^pi* duty not heing pa;rahlo on uwh a© are 'mea out a id© Egypt* M» We haye d^scuaeed the suhjeot of the last eentenee in para* 11 with Bayon* It appear© that a certain amount of benefit** is included in such items ass Discharging* storing 4 manufacture &amp;i* ® and Shortage on Smalls ®, Sayon© stats that w a fim price will not he greatly different from that quoted in para* 11. H F* It would appear that all arrangements are now complete for the start of hulk loading in June of this year* viith the exception of disposal as mentioned in para* 10* Upon this aspect we should he pleaded to hay© your Tiews so that we smy allay Sayons 1 fears* In this connection we would refer you to our telegram Wo* 177B to London* repeated Washington 1019# requesting Goal Mission to discus© this point with u® in Cairo* BA.SE4 Mm BAGHDAD . Our letter IP 0Z^0k/ABI&gt; of 10th BacembW 1944 refers* ^ . BAHRSXH . Our 31 Saying refers. NEW DETf^I , Please pass to Petroleum Officer* Defence Department* JDB DISTaiBU^IOH . D« 0* Mr* Wooah ridge List 1 Mr. Lev&amp;ngie • v 4 M* W* T* Cairo ) Pet. Dly. Eep* Cairo ) (Eef. our IP0250VASD ) of 10/12) ) Pet. DiT. Hep., BagMefi Pile Ho. 02504 ASDTo ? Rept i ‘AVIHG TELEGRAM Fromi LONDON (M.W.T M*E *S ,C * WASHINGTON Mo No, 9 copiers * 3^ 237? Sairlni Melon Savlm Do 12 Feb, 1945 H, 18 Feb. 1945 'V Gb BAHREIN SMALLS ... “ ^ .. :* V our telegram OT J. -Saving 5 * Saving / 21/1/ repeated Washington 43 1* Messrs Savon®s General Manager®s report has been studied with great Interest* It is regretted for reasons explained in Saving No* A.2353 L 7/2 # y (repeated Washington Melon Saving 31) that the Goal Mission were unable to visit Cairo to discuss the most suitable disposal of the briquettes surplus to the require ments of Egypt and neighbouring countries* i 2® In-view of the acute .1 shd Inalon Coal Committee hope that the estimate that bulk shipments can be commenced in June will prove correct * The most suitable con- mere for the 40*000 tons of surplus briquettes are being con sidered in the. light of the reports which you sent in your Savihg 2968 of the 6th June 1944* When a decision is is hoped that it will be possible enter into a contract with Savon to you fixed quantities of briquettes taken in this regard o arrange for consumers purchase at a price approved This price will* of course* it to by be based on the current rate of freight from Bahrein to Port Said so that no loss to Savon should arise as a result of a subsequent reduction in freight rates® • • W* f H \ ? ' - . , 3. The whole matter is now under consideration of the London Coal. Committee and a further message will be sent you when, their decisions are known, D ISTRIBUTION » MRTwOODBRIdSE l:st e MB 0 LEV ANGIE PET ^DIV *REP c CAIRO PET * DIV „REP« BAGHDAD ¥u W*T* Cairo, INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTIONS - ACTIONIP 02504 /ASD lw' political BAHREIN. * ( 23 $) MIDDLE EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, 10, SHARIA TOLUMBAT. CAIRO. /«$ March, 1: 45• t- T.nrr-V ^eiglibridge for Colce Bu lk Loading Scheme we liave been advised that U.K.C.d., 'peiieran has ^or disposal a Lorry Weighbridge of the following 11 Lorry weighbridge of the Vibrating -P®&gt; Steelyard graduated botn in Hngr 1 - ^ ^ o 1 tCl Indian Standards. Platforms 20 x o . Capacity 20 tons or 500 maunas . 2 would you please contact BAPCO ana arrange j.or them to contact'IJ.K.C.G. iTeheran direct. 3 , we feel that by the above description, this machine exactly fits the requirements oi BAPwO. 4 . we would be grateful to hear of further developments. Assistant Dix^ee” 0 ^* Industrial Production, c.c. MB SC 9.5.45)h CONFIDENTIAL. Political Agency, No. C/ Bahrain, the 1945' ' *v J tos 390 ' 20th March The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum company, Limited, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). , with the request that he will kindly inform this Agency wheth e r he is inuereste d. REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENT @) Name and date. Description “o f E ncl osure. A Su bject. Letter Mo. IP 02504/ASL/245 jj dated the 13th March, 1945, from the Middle last Supply jj Centre, Cairo. fi Lorry Weighbridge for Coke Bulk Loading Scheme. I /Cv: MIDDLE EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, 10, SHARIA TOLUMBAT. r 5 ? CAIRO. Political Resident, Bahrein, Mineral Resources of M.B, Herewith for your retention, please find an extract from a Summary prepared hy Major J.D.Boyd of this Centre, dealing with the Bahrein Petroleum Co he project. LPDSUPPLEMENT / a PETROLEUM COKE . Reference to petroleum and petroleum products has been omitted from this summary, the subject being sufficiently large and important to merit separate treatment. It is considered desirable, hoy/ever, to record the availability of petroleum coke at the refinery on Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, by virtue of the fact that arrangements are being made to utilise this material as a substitute for coal. A scheme due to come into operation in June 19A5&gt; has been developed for the purpose of bringing bulk shipments of this more or legs finely powdered coke to Port Said and other Mediterranean Ports, where some 100,000 tons per annum will be briquetted, using petroleum pitch as a binder. Present stocks of coke on Bahrein amount to a quarter of a million tons, while the monthly potential production is in the region of 7j000 tons. The analysis of the coke and resultant briquettes is given hereunder:- Coke Briquettes Volatiles 15 . 5 ^ 1A.86^ Fixed carbon 80. C% 83 . 00 c? A sh 0, A/c 1.80^ Sulphur (total) 5.0^ 3.5kfo Moisture . \ 1 . 25 ? o.M Specific Gravity 1.18 * Wt/Ft3 (loose) A6 lbs. Wt/Ft3 (packed) 68 lbs. - B T U per lb. 15,600 15,436 Costs relative to the Port Said scheme have been reliably estimated as follows:- £ s. d. Price at dump 15 0 Transport to end of causeway, loading into lighters and loading on to vessel 17 6 Freight (at present) Gross 3 10 0 Insurance Marine and War A 8 Customs duty 1A 2 i % &gt;HHI \ / ' / ~ 78. £ s. cl. ' 'carried forv/ard- 6 1 If Discharging storing o-nd'manufacture on basis of 36?000 tons a year and at present prices s ’roughly 1 10 0 Shortage on smalls (say) : 80 ’ 7 19 4 Free on truck at Port Said 1 8 h 5 or Loading and trimming on board ship at.Port Said (less duty) 7 10 3 It is anticipated that this scheme mil make a valuable contribution to the solid fuel availability for the Mediterranean Basin. \\ CONFIDENTIAL . No. C/ 4i6 . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd April, 1945. Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments' The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and h-s the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) R3FER3FCE TO PREVIOUS COHRESPOKDEKCS s' ' “ “* Agency printed la c ter no. C/117 dated the 24*h January 1945. Des'criptToh 'oT Enclosur Nam e and date . : ^ j ^ iectT Notes on the Mineral Resources1 The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrain Receipt ..Date.X No. PA-309 26th March, 1945. His Britannic Majesty BAHREIN. s Political Agent, ^ © LORRY WEIGHBRIDGE FOR COKE. BULK COKE LOADING Dear Sir file 301.8 Please refer to your letter of the 20th March ^ W J ’wAJ. -i- W KJ ^ \S Jm OJ.J.W 4L.vyvi.JL XVICX X V^JLX J 1945, Ref. C/309, attaching a copy of letter No. IP 0254/ ASD/245 dated 13 th March, 1945 from the Middle East Supply Centre, Cairo, concerning the disposal of a Lorry Weighbridge. We are very much interested in the weighbridge for coke and would you please convey our thoughts to the Assistant Director Industrial Production, M.E.S.C., that we would be interested in the purchase and installation of such a weighbridge for handling coke in bulk quantities. A weighbridge of this size and capacity will be most useful at Bahrein as no such weighbridge exists on the Island at the present time. Will you please develop further information con cerning the weighbridge, i.e. - (1) - Preliminary information or prints concerning its installation so that this may be reviewed. (2) - Cost of weighbridge. (3) - When weighbridge can be made available. Thanking you for this and previous courtesies, W. P. Anderson, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.■I No. c/424 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 3rd April, 1945. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd., 3 A H R A I N. L orry weighbridge for Coke Bulk Memorandum. jv* p, ^ Reference your letter No. PA-3(59, dated the 26th March, 1945. 2. To avoid delay it is suggested that you communicate direct with the United Kingdom Com mercial Corporation, Tehran, as advised in para graph 2 of Middle East Supply Centre, Cairo, letter IP 1945. Q2504/A3D/245, dated the 13th March p. Political Agent, Bahrain NS.Political Agency, -i4£ CONFIDESTIAL . ■ o. c/4''?5 ° /tahrain, tlaa3r r l April ? 1945 The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments The Assiscant Director, Industrial production, The Middle East supply Centre, Cairo, v . it. to 1 and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). &amp; R3FEKSFCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: i\ •' v -; ^ \ i * ^ M.E.S.C. letter No. IP 02504/ASD/245 dated 13th 'arch, 1S45. Desc r xp t Name and date. yofJlnclbsure Subject 1* Letter No. PA-309 dated 26th0 March, 1945, from the Chief jj Local Representative, The (| Bahrain Petroleum Company, Lorry Weighbridge for Coke Bulk Loading Scheme. Limited, Bahrain. 2 . Political Agent’s memorandum No. C/424 da-te'd 3rd April, 1945, to the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Co., Ltd.,Bahrain. I. NSip Telegram From To No. 235#•3. 23/23. S (A). Political Agent, Bahrain. H.M* s. Ambassador, Baghdad. (For M.S.S.C.). Dated the 12th April, 1945. i to Your telegram No. 3 dated April 7th. A Bahrain Smalls. Please telegraph designation in full of authority in Calcutta to whom sample should be sent. - POLITICAL - H.M.D.O. No. q/476. i ■ ■■■■■■■■ v't 1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN* Dated the 22nd April, 1945* My dear Anderson, Will you kindly send me a sample of \ ^ Bahrain Smalls for forvaxxUns by air to India? This request arises from the Middle bast -Supply Centro inquiries regarding this product* Yours-sincerely, i k Mr* W,P. Anderson, The Chief Local H op res enta tive , The Bahrain Petroleum Co., LOn*, Bal strain. NS. ^ f-' . % o f s lNo. C/526. POLITICAL AGET^CY, . BAHRAIN. Dated the 5th May, 1945. To D.D.E,R., CALCUTTA, MEMORANDUM.! . At the request of the Middle East Supply Centre, Baghdad, I am forwarding by air freight a parcel containing a sample of Bahrain Smalls. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. 3. The Middle East Supply Centre thought that Armindia might be interested. Political Agent, BahrainK - i *»• vjw®' &lt;?0 PA* 430 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. May 1, 1945. J[a/ Vi Vl H.B.M* s Political iigent, Bahrein. Dear Dir, &amp; o - ' ^ BAlHElN DjuDiLLD Pile No.301.8 In reply to your letter of ^2 Apfil (D.O. No.0/476) on the above / subject, I am forwarding herewith a 10 pound sample of Bahrein Smalls as requested. GD%/j£EN Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM QCM£MK LIIvilTBD</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000070_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/719</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000070</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/719</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/28-(ii) Military requirements. Purchases from oil companies. Coke’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-26T21:06:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (265 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 254-266) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 267; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-253; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is also present in parallel between ff 254-266; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises copies of letters, telegrams and other papers relating to: i) the export of petroleum industry equipment from the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) at Bahrain and the California-Arabian Standard Oil Company (CASOC) at Al Khobar [Al-Khubar], including: baker cement retainers to the Burmah Oil Company (India Trading) Limited; welding machines to the Burmah Shell Oil Storage &amp; Distributing Company of India Limited; piping to the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (AIOC) refinery at Abadan; and ii) the export of petroleum coke from BAPCO, Bahrain, to Port Said [Muḩāfaz̧at Būr Sa‘īd], Egypt. Correspondents in the file include: the Political Agent at Bahrain (Edward Birkbeck Wakefield; Major Tom Hickinbotham); the Chief Local Representative of BAPCO (chiefly Ward P Anderson and R M Brown); representatives of CASOC (chiefly Charles E Davis and Floyd William Ohliger); H S Bowlby of the Petroleum Division, at the British Embassy in Baghdad; representatives of the Middle East Supply Centre (MESC), Cairo; representatives of Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company, Bahrain.The file includes:papers relating to the shipment of and payment for equipment and supplies from BAPCO and CASOC (packing lists, purchase orders, invoices, shipping arrangements), including correspondence concerning confusion over shipments from BAPCO to the Burmah Oil Company (India Trading) Limited, caused by a lack of specific order instructions;correspondence from May 1943 relating to four welding machines despatched by CASOC to the Burmah-Shell Oil Storage &amp; Distributing Company, their poor condition, with only one machine in working order, the return of the machines to CASOC, and dispute between CASOC and Burmah-Shell over the machines (ff 65-68, ff 84-86, ff 90-91, f 93, f 97, ff 114-117);correspondence from October 1943 relating to the export, co-ordinated by MESC, of petroleum coke (also referred to in the file as ‘Bahrain smalls’) by BAPCO to Port Said, for briquetting and use as fuel. Correspondence includes: a BAPCO memorandum on coke supplies at Bahrain (ff 40-41); an initial export of 500 tons of coke in late 1943; subsequent proposals for monthly coke exports; provision of sacks for the transport of coke; the development of facilities for bulk loading of coke at Bahrain, including a report on arrangements for bulk loading, prepared by Major J D Boyd of the Royal Engineers (ff 135-144); 1944 correspondence between BAPCO and MESC discussing the difficulties of production and bulk loading of coke at Bahrain (ff 185-189, ff 195-196, ff 200-202); proposals for the commencement of bulk loading of coke at Bahrain in January 1945;correspondence relating to an altercation, occurring in March 1944, between an American officer and a policeman and toll-gate keeper in Bahrain (ff 132-133, f 145);the theft of small arms ammunition during the unloading of a vessel (the SS
                              Cromarty) at Sharjah in April 1944 (ff 145-146, ff 154-157);correspondence dated May 1944 relating to BAPCO equipment requirements for the Aviation Octane Project (ff 170-177).The file includes a letter (f 21) which is erroneously dated as 28 January 1953, instead of 28 January 1943.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company, Chief Local Representative</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Middle East Supply Centre</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum products</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Equipment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fossil fuels</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000070#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>