<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000132_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:03:46.278Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">F n-p iV V s ' ^ i W( ; Oopy of letter Ho. 1962 of 1931, doted 20th Sepi^' 1931, from the Hon'ble the Political Reeldent la the ».lf. Satire, to the Horeiga Secretary to Tri tiiweij 2^^ India, Simla. | ^ !)/ : | i’ «».«• mmmmm V&gt; 1?y the Persian Gorermnent of eon trihut ion etc, for the Indian mtemX Officers lent for quarantine duty in the Persian Sulf* t) 5 f 4 With referono© to your letter (oonfidential) lo. f. 331-H/29 dated me 86th August 1931* 2 hare the honour to forward herewith a statement showing in broad details how the sum of Es* 69*967-10-0 in question is made up* 8* As against this, I also submit a statement snow ing me amounts outstanding on each quarterly claim* as tendered by me Acoount&amp;nt CNmemi* Central Herenuee* from time to time for recovery from the .Persian Government* these outstandings have been classified under the following 5 he&amp;ds i - Xm Pay and allowances* 2. Leave salary* 3* Pension contribution* 4# Travelling allowance* 5* Miscellaneous* 3* It will be seen that me total of the first t.ure© heads vis. He. 70*028-12-10 exceeds by only a sm&amp;U amount the claim presented by His Britannic A&amp;jesty* s Minister* Tehran to the Persian Government* and considering me amounts involved the difference might be over looked* 4. m regards the other items - those on account of tie Telling ftllovenoe were left out of fee alala prewnted ^o fee Persian OawrauMRt. The expenditure hem debited W ~ fee Politic! Grant tor trewelling filowenoe. 1® view o® 0 the faot thfet 3 out of 3 Qu-r-ntine ■tedicssl offieere were *P*W Oo.eu^r r«pr***nt*tiTe• and ohangee in th* appoinfe-ente • -g ~«f ftuerantine K*di*al Offioers were B»de wore fox tie •M +-&gt; ... 'owenieneo of the Political admin ietration fe-n oi auar^ntine ■-U 4931 4971 • 5196 : 1 5377 5443 , ! 5852 5926 34()3 6689^ 7079 75481 8088 1quarsHtiia© aanrice, it la not considered advisable to dharge to* «xpenditure on toi* account (i. e . Travelling •Ilowinee) aa recoverable from the i&gt;ereian Uover: 6. In to# above oircuaatanoee, I oonour with the vie# eapreased by Hie Britannic mjeaty'a toarge D'Affaire* that it vouH be best to press for paya«nt of the claim a# already preaented l.e. for Re. 69,967-10-0 7. A copy of tola deapatoh is being sent to itfe Britannic mjeety'e Oharge B*Affaires, Tehzen.■0 o n f identiaL yv on No e F. 331-1M/29 The Foreign Secretary to the Government of indie Cu y To His Majesty’s Fnvoy Extraordinary and Hinistar Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, Tehran Dated Hew Delhi, the Oc t ooer 1931 Claim against the Persian Government for arrears of pension contribution etc*, of officers of the Indian Medical Service lent for quarantine duty in the Persian Gulf. Si r, hith reference to paragraph 2 of letter from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department Ho* F* 3 31 Ml!/ 29, dated the 7 th September 1931, I am directed to refer to letter from the Honhble the Political Resident in the Gulf, Ho. 1962 of 1931, dated the 20th September 1931, copy of which was sent to you direct, and to say that in tne circumstances explained, the Government of India have decided that it is not desirable at this stage to call in cues in on u-e accuracy of the account already submitted to the Persian G by Sir R. Clive* I have the honour to be, Si r, * Your most obedient servant, 34031 6689' for foreign Secretory to the Government of Indio. j_ n vi q letter Ho. 1962 of Copy for information with reference 1 ' Knn'ble the 1931, doted the 20th September 1931, to tne hon Fo 11 tier. 1 Resident in the Pension uiim'. 7019 75481 8088 1IPS W* SEP T93 Oopy of a letter No.239, dated aulhek, 29th July 1931, from His Majesty’s Charge d* Affaires, Tehran, to the Foreign Secretary to ; , 15h^:^k)v^p # nient of India, Simla. * 1 FILE GC 6b4 / t C' J iNCLOSURE IN OREIGN SECRETA r /’S lith reference to your despatch No .F.331-N/29 of July 9th, concerning the claim against the Persian Government for arrears due to the officers of the Boyal Indian Medical Service formerly lent for duty in the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to inform you that the figures on n?hich Sir E. Clive’s note No.181 of April 21st was 'based were furnished by the Honourable the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, whose Secretariat will doubtless be in a position to state fully tbe method by which they were arrived at. 1 greatly fear that to admit at this stage the inaccuracy of the accounts already submitted, and to put in a revised claim for a larger sum, might well jeopardize still further the chances of obtaining any payment at all from the Persian Government, who would welcome any pretext, however feeble, for calling in aue^tion whole' basis on which this claim has been made. That might necessitate the renewed submission of detailed accounts, and I understand from your aespatch that full details are not at the disposal oj. the Ac co un tan b** General* Gen tr a I Bev^jiues. S. AS regards the proposal to waive the claim respect of leave salary and pension contrib •« nnvpmmen.t arc while I agree that the Persia ^ ^ ^ u wQuld likely ever to admit sue. a , » ^ misleading to hold out any hope • p these items to P®J[ duced by the waiver of these i 31*™' “ a '“ 1 DI “ a n.Mtu.1 •« 14SEP. 1931 remainder at the present ^ a D taeir obligations is at unwillingness to meet 5615 5926 3403 6689 1 70T9 I548J 8088 1 'J18 rri. Si? ^Tf , \Z»‘ ll$ •;5Sa aomsnt reinforced 'by their disinclination to provide the necessary foreign exchange, and it is therefore extremely unlikely that the representations of this Legation vri.ll meet with success in the near future. That being so, you will doubtless agree that it would be a mistake in tactics to waive any part of the claim at the present juncture. Jny favourable effect which such a waiver might conceivably create - and it should 'be remembered that the Persian Government are notoriously immune from sentiments of gratitude - would have 'been forgotten long 'before the passing of the Persian exchange crisis or some other factor rendered the prospects of a settlement more hopeful. 3. I propose, therefore, subject to your approval, to continue as 'before to press for payment at regular intervals, and to refrain for the time being from any hint that a part of the claim might be waived. Whenever it is decided to drop such a hint would, 1 consider, be the best moment to broach the Question of a mistake in the accounts hitherto submitted, but before that awkward point is brought to the notice of the Persian Government I venture to emphasise the desirability of a reference to the Political Besident, whose figures do not, it seems, tally with those in the possession of the Accountant-General, and wuo alone would appear to have at his disposal the detailed particulars of the claim*0 r nn H-FIDEHTI ifer No oF*331-N• / 29• * From TO The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in tfce Foreign and Political Department, The Hon •hie the Political Besident in the Persian Qulf» Dated Simla, the August 1931 • Payment Dy the Persian Government of pension contribution etc*, for the Indian Medical Officers lent for quarantine duty in the Persian Gulf. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with endorsement from ttie Government of India in ttie Joreign and Political Department, No. 1.351-H./29, dated tde 9td July 1931, I am directed to forward a coo, v of letter i*roni His Majesty's Charge d* Affaires, Tehran, No»239, dated the 29th July 1931, ahd to request that the Government of India may He furnished with the .*&gt; dc, fiQ 967 / 10 /-, which according details of the sum of Bs.69,9o'/•* ’/ » -.i- flue from the Persian Government, to your accounub xs due ire I have the honour to te, Sir, Your most otedient servant,piL- wOPY 3 0 JUU93' NOiZls. r . z .. 44.8:1 41 sr BBIUSH I*®} ATI ON, TSEBAN, - A®ril 21 1931, His Britannlo Majesty’s Bepresentative presents tls eompliaents to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and has the honour to transmit herewith copy of the document mentioned in the sub-joined Schedule, on the subject of:- claim against the Persian Government in connection with the Gulf quarantine service. saference:- Foreign Secretary's letter NO.F.331-N./29 of the 26 th January 1931. Note to the Persian Government April 21st, 1931. Copy has been sent to the Hon. The Political Besident in the Persian GrulT at Bus hi re*British Legation, Tehran, April 21st, 1931. ! ' Monsieur le Ministre, As Your Highness is doubtless aware, certain expanses were incurred by the British doctors formerly employed in the Persian Sulf Quarantine Service in the performance of their official duties, and in respect of these expanses and of the salaries and allowances of the doctors a claim is still outstanding which has formed the subject of extensive official and semi-official correspondence between Your Highness* Ministry and this negation g. ^ith his letter of Hebr 24th 1S09 (October 16th 1930) to Mr. Bavard, His Excellency Mlrza Ohaffar Khan Jelal was so good as to transmit a cheque for Krans 10800 in settlement of certain items of this claim, namely certain expenses personally incurred by Doctor Unco to of Mohamnerah, amounting to Krans 8,000, and the house and convey ance allowances of the Quarantine Officers at e rwati and Mohammeraa* Bushire* Jask, Bander ADljas a amounting to Krans 5801* ^ 3. I have the honour to recall to Your t, ^ notice that the fo Hewing additional *«** ** outstanding;- leave, (a) On account of pay and tine * motions of tUe Quarantine salary and pension con r ^hazomerahi Officers at 4#tailf4 a000 unt, in Rupees 69,967 Anna • ^ ^ olaim was trans translation, of this pa Note no. 301 of ~ r*r this Legation * mitted under cove Move mb erNovemUer 21st 1928, and ’«111 there lie found set forth in statement 1). (h) Special expenditure on telegrams and boat hire at Jask and Hsnjam in the summer of 1928 during the cholera epidemic: Krans 6013.60. (The details of this part of the outstanding claim were given in this Legation's note Bo.259 of July 23rd 1929 (Mordad 1st 1308). The total amount now outstanding will thus he seen to he Bupees 69,967 Annas 10 plus Krans 6013.60. 4, Your Highness will readily appreciate the inconvenience caused hy the long delay in meeting this claim, which is in respect of expanses incurr ed and salaries earned hy British Officer whose work was of the utmost value to Persia. It will he seen, indeed, that a large part of the sum still owed was directly expended in fighting a cholera epidemic of serious proportions, la these circumstances I trust that Your Highness vd.ll shortly he in a position to inform me that the outstanding claim will he met forthwith, and I should he grateful if to that and the matter might he examined hy the competent authorities without further delay* 1 avail myself of this opportunity to renew Your Highness the assurance of my highest consideration* (Signed) H*H* OUVJi.* ^3 Highness Mirsa Mo framed Ali Khan Ferou^^l Minister for Foreign Affairs*No•169. BKLT13H LKGATION, tkhmn, June 16th 1931. U- His Britannic Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to th© Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and has the honour to transmit herewith copy of the document mentioned in the sub joined Schedule, on the subject of;- claim against Persian Government for expenses incurred by British Doctors in th© Persian Gulf Quarantine Service. Reference 5 ~ Tehran despatch No.77 dated the 21st April 1931# Note to the Persian Government June I6th,l931# i cop, C ».« sent t» tt. Actlw pollUcol in tbi© Persian Gulf* 5926British Legation, CrUltiek, June 16th, 1931 No Monsieur le Ministre, I have the honour to refer to my note No*181 of April 21st last concerning the expenses incurred By the British doctors formerly employed in the Persian Gulf .uarantine Service, and to enquire whether Your Highness will shortly Be in a position to acquaint me with the action taken By the competent authorities of the Imperial Government to meet the claim in questlon* I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Highness the assurance of my highest conslderation* (Signed) B#H# SLITS# His Highness Miraa Mo homed All Kh&amp;n Feroughl Minister for Foreign Affairs*NO.F.331-N./29* yrom ^ The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, To His Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Persia, Tehran* Dated Simla, the July 1931 Payment due from the Persian Government of pay, allowances, leavo salary and pension contributions for the Indian medical officers lent for quarantine duty in the Persian Gulf* Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your memorandum No*169,dated the 16th June 1931, I an dx^cu^d that according to tho account supplied by tae Accountant Central Pevenues , the total amount outstanding against Persian Government on account of pay, axlo vanc-vw, mi pension contributions of the officers of tho Indian services, who were lent for quarantine duoy in the Pe. is Es.74,614/11/2 and not Es . 69 ,967/10/- as statua , T r? r; r\ f, P d th Q 21 S t 3(a) of enclosure to your memorandum No. &gt; April 1931. Tho details of this sum aro, ho.^v-r, ■=-— ^___- 7 - 7 7 —s only in approximate and allowancos Bs .58,1467-/4 J • + hp Lxvo salary Bs. 7.025/3/- ) f .. es aS shorn m the •Imsi on contribution. .» . Bs—/ Margin. I am to add that in viow of the fact that th ■ n'lity fob leave saiaiy Government appear unlilcely to admit la- 1 ^ e decided Tro-rnniGnt of India ° ^ad pension contributions, the Gov . - these . ola xm in respect ox ir you see no objoction to waive - - Government 16 468/10/1°* ^ items which total approximately Es. &gt; 111 5926 5403] 668$ 70T9 7548] 8088'</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000132_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/32</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000132</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/32</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 4814/31 'Persian Gulf: Quarantine Service; IMS officers lent for duty'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-19T15:42:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (17 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description (used for referencing) commences at f 160, and terminates at f 178, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the outstanding payment from the Government of Iran for Indian Medical Service officers lent to the Persian Gulf Quarantine Service between 1923 and 1928. The primary correspondents are: Sir Robert Clive, British Legation, Tehran; Francis Verner Wylie, Government of India, Foreign and Political Department; Mirza Mohamed Ali Khan Feroughi [Mohammad Ali Foroughi], Minister for Foreign Affairs, Iran; HM Chargé d'Affaires to Tehran.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Quarantine Service</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Medical Service</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Employment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000132#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>