<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:04:14.949Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(?' Mm Telegraphic A dcirest: “FAKHROO.” Codes Used: A.B.C. 5th Edition &amp; Bentley’s. YOUSUF ABDULRAHMAN FAKHROO, T' ' B A H R E I M j 25 th Novembt» Colonel G.Lociie E.B.Ivx * 1 s Political xi^ent Bahrein, Bear Sir, I wish, to have an interview with you to give my sal am to you and shall be pleased if you kinaly let me know when and at what time it would be convenient for you to see me„'1' A»&gt; A &gt; Mr.Faiq sdbnhajn, Inspector of fiductation Bahrain, is leaving today for Syria^on leave. He wants to pay his respects to you if you can spare hiiu few minute s, please • For order. 16.6.34 I IJs.aim Kanu has coice to pay his respects to you if you have time to see him. He returned from Hijaz via 'Iraq by the last air mail. 18.6.34 r ^ ^ L -■■ • ii • Yusul ^anu has come and to see you in connection with ^r.Lame's visit to Sharjah it you can ep; re him few minutes. For orders,please. 2S.7.S4 -« —- --T • A • ? Abdul f Aziz as-3alih, Clerk of ^usaibis ? ,has zent the attaches note saying that Kiian Bahadur ’Abdul ’Aziz al Qusaibi(returned from India by the last air-hail) wants to pay his respects to you and wants to know what time it woulc be convenient for you to see him. Cubmittea for'orders,please. ' 21.04 P ^ ( 0 '^' A, ailir F .A. Khan Bahadur ’Abdul ’Aziz al Qusaibi has come, please. ‘ B2.3.34 1X • A • ■Abdul ’Aziz as-3alih, Clerk of ^usa-ibis,. has sent the attaches note sa/in^ that Khan Bahadur T Abdul T Aziz al Qusaibi(returned from India by the last air-nail) wants to pay his respects to you and wants to know what time it would be convenient for you to see him. Submitted for‘orders 3 please. '21.04 - Khar Rahrdur T Ahrii]l iLrr.iv. n 1 ur^rihi Vine; n.nmp &lt; nlpppp.- \ m F.A. /1 &lt;s Khan Bahadur T Abdur Rahman az-Zaiyani has come ;/ith the pearls and says that he wants to see you if convenient, pleasewmemg - / 5 P.A. liajji ^bdun nabi, Bushiri, has come and asks for an interview if convenient to you. ne was in ‘Iraq and Persia on pilgrimage and has just returned. For orders,please. 26.8.34 P.A. ne is a Persian merchant and a member in the Manamah Baladiyah and in the Majlis at-Tujarah,please. 26.8.34 ll&gt;SrZ*r VP.A. Khan Bahadur ’Abdul ’Aziz al ^usaibi ha sent word to the effect that as he intends to go to Egypt via ’ira^ he wishes to pay his respects to you before leaving and asks when it would be convenient to you to see him. He intends to leave by Airmail. For orders,please. 9.10:34 &amp; s it_ LU “U 10 ' io • ■ I - 4 * —Y- - ^Aytt cA)s*\&gt; % V^'-' •”&amp;&gt;{ {/^ &lt;£+'+'s ^2'JL? &lt;*U~i' JjsjJ_jY c^ LY^J^XZ- ^ ' ^-u? 1 ABBUIREBWAH W. ZAYAW. BAHRIEN. V‘\&lt;V&lt;ir , A^i' N&lt;*&lt; U-V^ &lt;• i 1 9 r Translation of letter dated the 30th Rajah 1353 equivalent to the 8th November 1934 from Khan Bahadur ! Abdur Rahman az-Zaiyani to Colonel Loch, Political Agent,Bahrain; After Compliments, I congratulate you on your safe arrival and wish you a happy ana prosperous time. I ask to be excusea for not being able to come and pay my respects to you as I have not been keeping good health for the last few aays ana am still unwell. With respects./6 Please sene, message to Yusuf Pphu tnat the Honourable the Political Resident will be pleased to see him at 11.00 today 14/11. Coffee to be ready. G.L. 14/11 H.M. Khan Sahib Yusuf Kanu has oeen informed accordingly. 14.11.34 s? « *dp A.^.A. Haji Khalil Kanoo says that his presence now in the Bahrain Court is required in connection witn a certain case and as you may not be free to see him now he will come at some other time. 18Til.34 I 4 n .ftUUJ?. KjCi L! A.P.A. Khan Sahib Husain bin Hasan ‘Amad, Minshi of the Residency Agent, Sharjah, has cone and wishes to pay his respects to you if convenient. For orders,please d. 3.2.35 j CmJl* irCL /-•-***. j/v^P.A. Khan Bahaaur f Isa says that if you want K.S.Husain to accompany you to the Trucial Coast he can spare him as he has with him here.his son ana tnree servants* Submitted for orders,please. /$/ / Itfu ^ JO'S. a 4.2.3521 No. YUSUF BIN AHMED KANOO. Codes Used:- Bentley’s and A.B.C. ST? Edn. Bahrein PERSIAN GULF. Dear Lieut Metcalfe, Sheikh Sultan bin Salim, The Ruler of Ras-al-Khaimah, wishes to visit and pay his respects to you and has asked me to write and arrange a rendezvous with your goodself. i shall be thankful if you will kindly let me know when it would be convenient to you to see him. in such cases the shaikh of ^ahnain sends one of nis men. uo arrange ior an interview, xesterda# evening ^.o.xusuf i^anu went to see the shaikh of i.,as-al-^haimah and in is possible that, Yours sincerely, Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo. considering him as a friend or the agency and or himself, the Shaikh of ^as-al-x-jiaimah asked him to arrange for an interview with you. 16 . 10.35d? ■ it) F.A. Ke attached. These people are said to have left the shaikh’s palace few days ago and nothing is known about their whereabouts. They also did not come to the agency since 21.10.35. The orders about the time fixed for the interview could not therefore be communicated to them. fA 26.10.35 it \ ' II. I- ^ -Khan bahadur ‘Abdul ‘Aziz al Qusaibi, '/ho retarned from Qatif yesterday, wishes to pay his respects to y.A, and asked me to enquire from when it would be convenient for him toMan am ah, Dated 7th, June Capt. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain Respected Sir: I v;ould like to pay my respects to you at your convenience and shall be obliged if you will let me know what time v/ill suit you to allow me an interview* Yours obediently, jfyA. £ A&lt;z/*4 MQHAMMSD SAL2H SHATTAR Secretary, Manamah MunicipalityTelegraphic Adclress:- BAMRAmo lltisttf Bin ^Utntpd Bnnoo. CODES USED:- BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE, BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE, LOMBARD. A. B. C 5th EDITION. RUDOLF MOSSF, AND MOSSE CONDENCER, ACME COMODPTY &amp; PHRASE, ORIENTAL 3 LET IER. AND PRIVATE. My dear Capt.Hickinbotham: I wish to pay you a visit, and shall be thankful if you will kindly let me know when it will be convenient Bahrain, 15 th July., (Persian Gulf) 1937. to you. f 0 /{Hn^ n/ini Yours sincerelv. OrUl /oju. irw npi'i ( cnn&gt; Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo.'.A. Haii Yusuf Fakhroo - one of the local merchants ~ nas phoned saying that he wishes to come ana pay nis respects to you and requests to knov; what time he shoula come. 9 3/11/37 O - ^ A / &lt;h~t■iiiiMW—— 11111 1 i 1 ' 11 ^ MHMHV r&gt; a a .il« Khan Bahacur Abdul Rahman al Za/ani, a Banrain merchant, says that he wishes to come ana pay his respects to you ana requests that a time may be fixed for this interview. 9/11/B7 Y v 0 .IP Dear Hr .',7 eight man: I am proceeding to the Trucial Coast hy Air tomorrow and I would very much like to come and wish you good-bye whenever convenient to you sometime today or tomorrow morning, ws If you have any instructions or advice to give me for that end I shall be very much pleased to abide by them. Hy services are at all times at your disposal. Trusting that your goodself and Hrs. 'Veightman are enjoying good health and with my kind regards&gt; v ours sincerely, virgin? but ahtthid kaho’o. J J '^7\ 0 -NO \ v) •i r \ Baiirein, Dated 17th November,1937. Fy dear Fr .'.7 eight man: I called at your office this morning at 9.0 a.m. to see you but I am extremely sorry I could not meet you, for, I was told that you would be able to see me tomorrow morning at 8.30 a.m. As I am leaving for Sharjah by plane arri ving here at 7.30 a.m. tomorrow morning, so I will not be able to come and see you tomorrow at the time given to me. I shall therefore be much obliged if you kindly let me know whether it will be convenient ^ for you to spare time to see me this evening or ^ to-night to enable me to see you before my depar- \ ture to Sharjah. Yours sincerely, Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo. ) ^ H. T 7 eight man Esquire, I. G. S. &gt; | Bahrein. | uP.A, Khan Sahib Haji Yusuf Kanoo has phoned saying that he wishes to come and see you to-day at 9.00.a.m. if it is convenient to you. 17/11/37 a 'OCX - P.A. 7 /^/ He says he will be leaving for the Trucial Coast at 9.00.a.m. tormorrow. and that he will be very glad if you can see him any time before 9.00. a.m. tomorrow. 17/11/37 £ &gt;C&gt; / /? ( 7 ■ y\■Ill ■ P.A Shaikh Khalifah bin k^hammad Al Khalifah who is 1 saving for Nasik India for police training has come to see you for salams. He knows English. 18/11/37Haji Muhammad 'Tayib, an Iranian merchant, says that he is leaving for the Hajj this morning ana wishes to come to see you if it is convenient to you. is/i/ba ^ /&gt; 7tTele 1 graph - t phone. ALQOSAIBI lO-M. J iC* y S* AEDULAZIZ ALQOSAIBI &amp; BEOi JQ*) Code’- BENTLEY’S. £7 BAHRAIN. October 23rd, 1938. Dear Caotain Howes, Ever since you came to take charge of your office in Bahrein, I have remained absent here and had gone to Hasa in Arabia. I was lately suffering from some kind of eye trouble, and now feel much better to pay you a visit. I shall therefore, be much thankful to you if you will give me your most conveninet time, when I should come to meet you. With best wishes, Yours sincerely. &gt;urs sin£er&lt; ABDULAZIZ ALQOSAIBI. To, Captain J. B. Howes, Political Agent, Bahrein. H n xJ* F. B i ?t. ^ t o^. ^ c-VMy dear Mr. Wakefield, Thank you for your advising me that our friend Colonel Prior will be arriving here tomorrow. I wish to send you a small cooked goat (called in arabic Goozi) tomorrow evening at Dinner time,and shall therefore be much obliged if you will kindly accept this. Please advise me at what time I may send this over to you. I hope you will enjoy with this. Yours sincerely, Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1973</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1973</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File K/18 Interviews and visits of Bahrain notables with Political Agent and the Political Resident'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-16T22:04:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (67 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 69; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the Political Agency, Political Residency and various notable merchants of Bahrain wishing to have audiences and interviews with the Agent or Resident. Most of the letters pertain to arranging calls made by various notables to the Political Agent prior to their departure from Bahrain to pay their respects.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Local relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>