<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:31:40.101Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&amp; ESTHER WINGATE AGE 48. Experience Trained at Royal Family Hospital (London School of Medicine for Women) Qualified 1923 L.R.C.P., M.R.C.S. 1924 M.B.B.S. 1924 - 26 House Physician ) Women's Hospital, House Surgeon ) London - E.G.A. Hospital for Women, . S • London* District Obstetrical Medical Officer - Royal Free Hospital* Women's Medical Service. Countess of Dufferin Fund - January 1926 to date 1* Posts held . Medcial Superintendent 100 bed Hospital for Women &amp; Children (General Hospital) Lady Aitcheson Hospital, Lahore* (3 occasions)* Lady Reading Hospital, Simla* State Zenana Hospital, Jaipur Zenana Municipal Hospital, Peshawar (60 beds)* Other posts * 2. Acting P rofessor of Surgery . Lady Hardinge Medical College, New Delhi. 3* Lecturer in Surgery. Women's Medical School, Agra. This post included during 3i- years, periods of acting Principal with charge of maternity, gynaecological block and regular duty throughout the period for obstetrical and other emergencies* Lecturing to Nurses and Midwives has also been required as the Hospitals quoted have been training schools for Nurses*Lady Lyall Hospital, Agra, U.P# India# 18-6-1946, Doctor Esther Wingate has been known to me for the last twenty years. In 1937 she was appointed to my staff as Lecturer in Surgery and Surgeon ir^teharge 'of the surgical unit and held this post till 1941 in the Women*s Medical School, Agra. During this time she was Vice- Principal and acted as Principal for several months. She is a very good general surgeon and has had exceptional experience in midwifing and gynaecological. As Superintendent of various Dufferin Hospitals Dr. Wingate has had considerable experience onitheir adrainstrative and financial control. ' I have found her a very pleasant and loyal colleague and she was very popular with staff and students# Sd. U.M. Martyn, M.D. Lond# M.H.C.0,G#, Principal, Women*s Medical School, Agra.D*0.No. 2026-6/26. 26th June, 1946. My dear Belgrave, Will you please ^efer to your demi- official letter No*1360-10 of the 23rd June, 1946? 2. Colonel Hay is acquainted with a Dr* Esther Wingate who has written to him asking if there is any possibility of her being appointed to Bahrain. 3. I send you extracts from the correspond ence with the remark that Dr* Wingate would appear to me as an excellent choice for Bahrain and from my study of the salary terms the Bahrain Government paid to Dr* Doeg, there should be no difficulty on that score* 4* I should be glad if you would let me hear from you early as to whether the Bahrain Government wish to pursue the matter of her appointment* If you do wish to do so perhaps you would reply to her queries when replying to me* C* Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Yours sincerely, 21. Date of despatch. 2. List of enclosures. DEPARTMENT /OFFICE. Letter Draft Memorandum Telegram No. File No. Serial No. Dated i t ISummer /iew Hotel, LAHORE 16. 6. 46. •Vte' Dear Col.nay, Thank you for sending the notice about the post in paharain Island. I „ . sending a note as to my experience and a testimonial from the Officer under whom I served longest. This is to enquire if an application from me would be considered and to ask for further information:- 1. i&lt;hat is the size of the Hospital and what medical and nursing staff are available? 2. What is the cost of living in the Gulf compared to Indiaf 3. iould a year’s agreement in the 1st instance with a passage to the U.K.^instead of - passage from the u.K. as offered be, consider ed. My present rate of pay is:- Rs.750/- 150/- overseas allowance 56/- dearness allowance Provident Fund warns ffcr.4/- interest. Private practice is allowed. So that less than Rs.1000/- p.m. would not be a comparable g b rye 4. Do you know if, medical attentipn being free, the wives of higher officials and the more wealthy families are very exacting in their denfinds on one’s time. If they are not reasonable and willing to accept what is F.T.O.-2 &lt; 3 &gt; ^ really adequate and conscientious medical attention life might be very difficult. ^ .v- At present I am required to give 6 months notice of resignation - unless 1 suppose if it suited ^h,e authorities to release me. Alternativ ely if i medical woman is available and the need is great it would be possible to ask for my release. I had hoped to see Mrs.Hay as she passed through Lahore the letter came a day too late. Yours sincerely Esther Wingate Ends. 2NAME ESTHER WINGATE AGE 48 EXPERIENCE Trained at Royal family Hospital(London School of Medicine for women) Qualified 1923 L.R.C.P., M.R.C.So, 292* _ M.B.B.S. 1924 - 26 fiaae - rhysician Surgeon ) noaim'e Hospital, London ^ ^ ) cr “ District ubstetrical Medical Officer - Royal^anrity Hospital WOMEN'S MEDICAL SERVICE COUNTESS OF DUFFERIN FUND - January 1926 - to date U w POSTS HELD. LIEDICAL SUPERINTENDENT 100 bed Hospital for Women &amp; children (General Hospital) OTHER POSTS 2 ,ACTING PROFESSOR OF SURGERY to Lady Aitcheson Hospital, Lahore (3 occasions) Lady Reading Hospital, Simla State Zenana Hospital, Jaipur Zenana Municipal Hospital, Peshawar {29* beds) Lady Hardinge Medical College, NEW DE1HI «anen*s Medical School , aGRA 3. LECTURER IN SURGERY This post included 3^ yea re ^periods of acting Principal with charge of Maternity ^Gynaecological Block and regular duty throughout the period for Obstetrical and other emergencieso Lecturing to Nurses and Midwives has also been required as the Hospitals quoted have been v schools for NursesMflXXfiS y • copy Lady Lyall Hospital Agra U.^* INDIA 18.6. 46 Doctor Esther fingate has been known to me for the last twenty years. In 1937 she was appointed to my stajj^ as Lecturer in Surgery and Surgeon in charge of the Surgical unit and held this post till 1941 in the Women*s*Medical School, Agra. During this time she was Vice-Principal and acted as Principal for several months*-the is a very good general Surgeon and has had exceptional experience in fcidwifing and Gynaecological. As Superintendent of various Dufferin Hospitals Dr Wingate has had considerable experience on their adminstrative and ^inancControl. and I have found her a very pleasant/loyal colleague and she was very popular with staff and students.. &gt; » I Sd M. Martyn MjD. Lend. au.R.C.G.G. Principal — women's Medical School,AgraD.O.No. Z3&gt; Adviserate, June 29, 1946. .1 Reference your D.O.No. 2026-6/26 datea 25th June 1946, about Dr. Wingate. Her qualifications are good, similar to the other two lady doctors who have worked here, and she has valuable experience. After discussion with Snow I feel sure that she would be a very suitable person for the post and I should be obliged if you would inform her that the Bahrain Government is prepared to offer her the appointment of Lady Medical Officer. If she agrees to come I think perhaps it would be better if she did not arrive till October when the worst of the hot weather is over. 2. The following facts will I hope give the reply to her questions (a) The Government Hospital consists of four blocks of buildings, only completed during the war, Out patients, Administration with theatres etc., Mens Hospital, 60 beds, and Womens Hospital, 45 beds, both capable of expansion. There is a Mens Isolation Hospital, 14 beds, a Womens In-patient Dispensary, on another island, and several clinics in villages. Girls’ Schools are dealt with by the Lady Medical Officer. The Womens Hospital is at present under staffed, there are two key sisters, one British and one Indian and another British Sister is expected also three Indian trained nurses. There is a British Matron and two highly trained locally recruited sisters who do much of the outside work. The State Medical Officer is Dr. R.H.B. Snow and there are several Indian doctors on the staff. (b) I do not know the cost of living in India, on a European standard, but I am sure that the cost of living in Bahrain is higher than in India. I think that I could safely say that living, including servants wages, dhobi, bazaar and stores etc., should cost about fis.450/- to Rs. 500/- per month for a single person, but perhaps you could supply the comparative cost of living between India and Bahrain. (c) The Bahrain Government would be prepared to offer a two years’ Agreement with passage from India on joining and to the United Kingdom after two years. I think one year would be too short an Agreement. (d) The Bahrain Government would offer a basic salary of Rs. 900/- rising by increments of Rs. 25/- per month after each year, a Provident Fund of Rs. 150/- per month and cost of living allowance at the present rate of 15$ of basic pay, Rs. 135/- per month and leave at the rate of 2-£ months after each year of service. 2/ Confidential. 3BAIIT RECEIPT.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN, MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Ref. No. L. 18 / 60 . Confidential. Government - Hospital Bahrain, Persian Gulf jtcj. oj.mil UUX 27th April, 1941. To, K. B. M’s. Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir, Further to our conversation of April 24th and the letter'which I then showed you, enclosed is reply to the Adviser Government of Bahrain. Kindly file. I am, Yours Truly, LADY MEDICAL OFFICER.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN, &gt;:KDICAI DEPARTMENT. Confidential. Ref. No. L. ir/tO. Government - Hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf, 27th April, I 94 I. To, The Adviser, Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. In reply to D. 0 . c/642—5F* with regard to non payment of my electricity bill; lihile P®«&gt; Tng the bill,l now state in writing, what I have previously told you. The bill was unpaid as a protest against the repeated failure of the Government of Bahrain, to assist me in collecting fees which were owing to myself and the Government, from Arab patients. I refrain from coniment as to your threat of recovering tne amount from ray Provident i*und except to point out that such a course of action is illegal. I must request a reply to my letter L.H/60 of 3rd April within 4 days. LADY MEDICAL OFFICER. Copy to H.B.M’s. Political Agent.No. C/392-6/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th April 1941 To The Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum Your letter No. L.18/60 dated the 27th April and enclosure have been received and recorded. Kindly furnish me with a copy of the reply to your letter when received. Political Agent, BahrainGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN, medical department. Ref. No. L. Government - Hospital, Bahrain,Persian Gulf, 1st May, 1941. To, H. B. M’s. Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Memorandum: In reply to your letter of 30th April, No. c/392-6/26. 1941 Enclosed are copies of replies to my letter L.14/60 sent to the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain on 27th April, 1941. _ ll* ^ ' / LADY MEDICAL OFFICER.No. 679-10 of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, R/Thani 3, 1360 April 29, 1941. With reference to your memorandum L/14-60 dated 27th April 1941. The Bahrain Government is not prepared to adhere to Government of India regulations governing fees etc. in the Bahrain ^tate nospitals. The Government of India scale of charges has however been used as a basis for assessing charges in the Bahrain hospitals; this does not mean that the Indian rules and regulations have been adopted. If it is found that the charges which are now made, referred to by me in my 38/10 of 23rd March 1941, require modification or adjustment they will be altered. As stated in my 38/10 the scale for private ward patients 'a M requires amending by the insertion of a step between persons with incomes of Re 150/- and &amp; 300/- per month. These scales will apply to both men’s and women’s hospitals. I have written to His Highness and the senior Shaikhs regarding the whole question of payment of hospital fees and visiting fees and their recovery. I think it would be more effective if a copy of the hospital bill was sent to this office itt^he case of bills against members of the Ruling Family. The Memorandum:- Th^Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain. Adviser to the Government.No. 691-10/SF of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 3rd R/Thani, 1360 April 29, 1941. I acknowledge -with thanks receipt of your lette dated 27th April, 1941, forwarding therewith a chequ for Rs 1, 220 / 15 /- in settlement of the enclosed bill and enclos herewith Electric Department receipts Nos 23521 and 23522 therefor. The Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum: Adviser to the Government. Enel....s D.O.No. “Ili- '* Dated, 3*L May, 1941. Dear Alban, With reference to your D.O.No. C/386 dated 29th April, 1941, I forward herewith copies of the contracts of Dr. McDowall and Miss Harbottle. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain.dsgr of ICEIttiiAJiJUtt Cf A&amp;ZE&amp;mm made this twentyninth October OiMi thousajaa nim hunarea snci thirty ei^htf Bis ia^ihnoss Shaikh Sir Hamaa bin Isa Alkhalifah, K»€«X«£« f C* *I*t iOilsr of the Bahrain Islanaa, ^ ^rsian Sulf f on behalf of the Governcient of Bahrain* of the one part* ai*-* Dr. h. h. kcDow&amp;H of the other part WITIBsJSSBTH that it is mutually agreed that the said Government of Bahrain will employ the said Dr. h. k. ^-c^ow^ll and the saia Dr. M« M. BcDowall will serve the Govena^nt of Bahrain for a period of four years commencing from the twentyfirst day of February thousand nine hundred aud thirty nine on the terms specified on tlie schedule of teius attaclied. IK WITR-GB whereof the parties hereto have hereunto sigiied their na^es. Sd/- Beal of Bis iiijhneas Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Alkhali fail* K.C.I .K. * C.S.I, Sd/- Signature of Dr. M. E. Bcuowall Pi-ovisioxially signed by Adviser to the Government of Bahrain on behalf of the Government of Bahrain.1 * X 0 et Schedule of usrsis of Service of nr* M* M« ^cijowall i&gt;r. M« k* i.CiJowall sJialX faithfully serve: the Goverwrient of Bahrain as a Radical Officer for the term of this contract *hich is for four ye&amp;rsy terminable by six months* notice on either side y renewable after the expiry of four years, by mutual consent* 2. im* The rate of pay shall be Hs* 800 (eight hundred rupees) per mensem rising by annual increments of Hs. 25 /- (twenty five rupees) per mensem* 3* A sum of lis* loo/- (one hundred rupees) per mensem, or its equivalent in sterling, will be paid monthly into an account with the Eastern Bank Limited representing the Radical Officer*« provident funa, the proceeds of which will be handed over to the todical Officer on termination of the contract* A free furnished house sliall be provided by the Bahrain Government or an allowance of hs* 100/- (one hundred rupees) per mensem shal l be paid by the Bahrain Government in lieu of same* 5 * A car shall be placed at the disposal of the Led!cal Officer with an allowance of free petrol while on duty. (a) /Urlough will be ecumed on the basis of one and a half months per year’s completed and approved active service but shall only be taken in the first instance after two years completed service*0 2 Furioi- h will 220 1 count as active service for the purpose of assessing subsequent service or annual leave* (b) Annual leave 9 for one month* in addition to furlough* will be granted after each year’s completed and approved service! it will be counted as active service for the purpose of assessing furlough due and it r«ay be accumulated up to two months in all* (c) Full average pay will be drawn in respect of normal furlough and annual leave* (d) le&lt; vfc i^ay be granted in special circumstances and when no leave is due* without pay! this leave will not be reckoned as active service under the contract* A first class sea passage, F* &amp; 0*,C, will be provided for the medical Officer from the United Kingdom to Bahrain on taking up first appointment* A si mi lar first class passage to the United kingdom from Bahrain will be granted on final texisination of contract with the Bahrain Government am also when proceeding to, and returning from the United Kingdom on furlough after four years approved service, in the event of the contract being relieved for a further term* A first class return sea passage for the fedical Officer will be provided from Bahrain to Karachi, by the Bahrain Goverroent, after each year's completed service when travelling on annual leave, but in the event of the Bed!cal Officer not taking annual leave the value of this passage or passages may be utilised towards the cost of a passage to -urope on fUrlou&amp;h which under the terms of the Agreement the Bahrain Government is not under obligation to pay* The first class passages referred to above shall be F* &amp; 0* 1st class C frossi Bombay to i^ngland ana first class B*l* with food, from Bahrain to Bombay, or between Karachi and Bahrain*in n and his decision sg -11 be xinal* As as JAr. U. M. lacDowall regains in the service of the Government of Bairain she shall iiot carry on any trade or business on her own or any one else *8 behalf* or receive any remuneration for any services rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Government of Bahrain which must be obtained in writing* Dr. &amp;. * chowall is permitted to undertake private work ;ii on uropean and American women other than wives and families of officials of the Bahrain Governmmt who are entitled to free medical attention. Free medical aVU &gt;.on in case of wives of Bahrain Government officials does not include laterally cases* Dr. i, * *. IcDowall will receive half of the fees which are received by the Bahrain Government from non-Buropean paying patients who are attended in their homes or as maternity cases* Materni y case fees from wives of Bahrain Government* officials win be charged in proportion to the official’s For the purpose of this agreement all dates and periods ghati be those of the Arabic calendar which is the official calendar used by the Government of Bahrain* If any question arises under the contract* whether a« regards the meaning or in any other respect, the question shall be referred for the arbitration of the Political Agent^ V Confidential D.O. No. C/601 lated the 14th June 1941. A I understand.unofficially, that Dr* McDowell is having sane trouble in connection with the collection of her fees for private practice* According to the terms of her contract she is allowed to engage in private prac tice and I presume that her proper course in cases where patients refuse to pay her bills is to sue them in the Courts concerned* This of course cannot be done in cases where members of the A.l Khalifah are concerned* It is possible that she may make a complaint to this Agency in the near future and I should be grateful for your observations in the matter before this happens* Yours sincerely, C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain*Confidential. D,G. No. 1080/10-LM0. Bahrain, June 17, 1941. Dear Alban, With reference to your D.O. G/601 dated June 14, 1941. We have had a great deal of difficulty in recovering fees from patients, both private and non-private. People do not refuse to pay but they postpone payment indefinitely and in the case of the Ruling Family they say that His Highness will pay. The people in Bahrain, especially the Rul ing Family, are inclined to consider that medi cal treatment, including private wards and visits to patients houses, should be free, like education. As far as the Ruling Family is con cerned the position has improved lately as a result of some discussions which I had with the senior shaikhs and I think all their outstanding bills have been paid as well as some outstanding bills against the general public which Dr. McDowall was unable to recover. 1 think Dr. LilcDowall has found that her private practice is not likely to become as large as she expected for some time. Arab women are slow in taking to new doctors and in the beginning most of the patients seem$ to be of the class who are treated free, not the paying type. 2 -&amp; i - 2 - I have not suggested that she should sue people in court, I think it would be undesirable, but when her bills are long outstanding she refers them to me and I do my best to obtain payment and usually succeed eventually. Yours sincerely, Major R.Gr.E.W. Alban, G.iS.E., H.B.M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential No •C/641-6/26. The Political Agent, Bahrain presents his compliments to The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain and has the honour to forward herewith a copy of the undermentioned document for favour of his views. The Agency, BAHRAIN Persian Gulf. Dated the 22nd June 1941 . Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure Name and Date Subject Letter dated the 21st June 1941 from Dr. M. M. McDowall, Government Hospital, Bahrain. Revision of agreement of Dr. M. M. McDowallNo. of 1360 Office or tne Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, J/Thany 4. 1360 June 28, 1941 To His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- With reference to your No. C/641-6/26 dated 22nd June 1941, enclosing a letter frtfm Dr. M.M. McDowall. xis Dr. McDowall is an employee of the Bahrain Government she should in the first place have addressed her letter to the Bahrain Govern ment especially as some of the points raised in her letter are now under discussion. ^ 2. Regarding private practice: according to Dr. McDowall 1 s agreement she was allowed private practice among Europeans, other than families of Bahrain Government officials who are entitled to free medical attention; she was also entitled to receive half of all the fees which the Bahrain Government received from non-muropean paying patients attended by her in their own homes or dealt with by her as maternity cases. The Bahrain Government left her free to charge whatever fees she considered suitable from Europeans and agreed to her holding clinics at Awali for which I believe she receives some remuneration from the Bahrain Petroleum Company. In March this arrangement waswas revised and it was agreed that she should also receive all the medical fees which were paid by patients of the A class (incomes not less than Rs 150/- per month) admitted to the hospital. At the same time a schedule of medical fees and hospital charges was drawn up which was based roughly on charges in similar hospitals in India. I enclose a copy oi^a P letter showing these rates. They were decided upon in consultation with the Senior Shaikhs. 3. It is true that some of the patients, especially the Ruling Family, were inclined to resent having to pay for medical services either at home or in hospital but eventually after further discussion with the Shaimhs His Highness agreed that the family should pay fees according to the schedule. In the past they have paid fees to the American Mission, so the principle is not an entirely new one. It is far more difficult to recover fees from women than from men because they are almost^inaneially^always^r dependent on their menfolk and whereas the men do not mind paying for themselves they seem to resent paying for their women. I realise that Dr. McDowall finds her private practice less profitable than she anticipated but I think she could improve it if she took more trouble to learn Arabic and to get acquainted with xiTab households. 4. Regarding the collection of medical fees: in other government hospitals this isis dealt with by the clerical staff of the hospital and the doctors are not directly con cerned with collecting payments. Because Dr. McDowall found it difficult to recover her fees I suggested that bills should be sent out through this office which would be more effec tive in the case of the Khalif.ah. 1 fail to see why it should be detrimental to the good relations between doctor and patients etc. for the government to deal with the Dills. 5. The charges and fees in the Bahrain hospitals are not governed by Government of India rules or regulations. They were decided upon in consultation with the Shaikhs; we did however use existing rates as a basis. The arrangement in the men ! s hospital is working satisfactorily. 6. The Bahrain public is not concerned with the details of agreements between the govern ment and its European officials nor is it affected by the conditions of service of the State Medical Officer and the Lady Medical Officer. 7. Bahrain Government officials are not provided with free air conditioning. There are Air Conditioning Units in the operating rooms at the hospital and it may be possible in the future to increase the air conditioning through out the building. I have however informed the State Medical Officer that an allowance will be given to the matron covering a certain amount ofof current during the hottest months of the year and during her absence on leave Dr. McDowall will receive the same benefit. 8. Furlough and leave of the medical officers are on the same scale as other Bahrain Government officials have received in the past. The amount of leave and furlough was considered adequate even before the air service functioned. It was intended that officials should spent short leave in Persia, Syria or Karachi; the first two places are now ruled out but Karachi can be reached in one day and from personal experience I think the climate there provides a suitable change after Bahrain. 9. Pay commences on day of arrival in Bahrain, as in the case of all other Bahrain officials. It is not understood what is meant by overseas allowance, anyone serving in Bahrain is naturally expected to work overseas. Over seas allowance is normally paid to people who are sent to a different country from that in which they were employed to serve. Dr. McDowall was engaged to work in Bahrain. 10. Dr. McDowall asks that her present agreement should be revised. Before consider ing this I should be grateful if you could give me any information which you can as to pay terms and conditions of European lady doctors in Indian States or government hospitals in India similar to the Bahrain Government hospital. Adviser to the GovernmentNo. 381 - 10 of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 25th Safar, 1360 March 23, 1941 With reference to my D.O. , ited 25th February, 1941, regarding the collection of hospital fees etc. All fees and hospital charges which are collected from patients admitted to the Government hospital will be credited to the Government account. The Bahrain Government will refund to the Lady Medical Officer the medical fees which are received from patients of the A class, i.e., from patients whose incomes are not less than Rs.150/- per month. The medical fees and hospital charges which shall be charged will be according to a schedule approved by the Bahrain Government. Hospital Fees and Charges . &gt; Persons with incomes under 25/- p.m. Free. This rate will be charged proportionately to the number of days the patient is in hospital. The above charges do not include fees for:- a. Incomes 150/- to 500/- p.m. Hospital Charges. 4/- Half of the normal fees for operations, Confinements^etc. will be charged. In the case of confinements Rs.100/- inclusive. b. Incomes 500/- to 750/- per month. a/_ s The Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain. v Memorandum:- f! tt It of 25/- to 50/- 10$ of salary. ( 5$ food. ( 5$ treatment. it it of 50/- to 150/- 20$ of 20 $ of salary. (10$ food. (10$ treatment. Operations. Confinements. Laboratory. X-Ray. Private Ward Patients. Per day2 The charges for b and c are inclusive except for: - Operations. Confinements. Laboratory examinations. X-Ray. N which are charged for at the normal rate. The normal rate for Operations etc., is based upon the rates charged in hospitals of the same type in India. All Bahrain Government Officials and employees will be given free medical treatment at the Government hospital, but in-patients will be charged for their food. The charge will be 10$ of their salary. All Government hospital staff and families are entitled to complete free treatment. In the case of Women Patients the charges will be assessed according to the income of the patient's husband. Sd/ C.Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government. S.Z.3.0. No. C/689 OntAfl the 1st July 1941. r A question hns ?*r5aen ae to what salary and, conditions of service rre given to European lady doctors in Indian Government Sorvice or Indian states* I expect you have some experience of this and would be prateful if you could give me an indication* v ours sincerely, M»L*A* Steele;, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain*—__ Confidential (&amp;) CK V / No. C/710-6/26. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (/ ) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Da ‘ ed fche 6th July 1941 i Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter dated 3rd July 1941 from the Medi- Pay of European Lady cal Officer, Bahrain to the in India. Political Agent, Bahrain.No. C/740 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th July 1941. To The Honourable the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Eemorandun Reference letter No. D.339-N/32 dated t.he 2nd Inarch 1932 from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, &amp; copy of which iwas forwarded to this Agency under Bushire that’’the Government of India consider it desirable that all cases in which the Rulers of these States show a desire to engage the services of Suropoans (which may be understood as including Australians and Americans) should be reported to us before hand”* 2. I find that the services of Dr. M.M. McDowall, Lady Doctor in the State Hospital, on a salary of ft? 800/- per mensem rising by annual increments of Rs 25/- per mensem, and of Miss N.M. Harbottle as Matron of the said hospital at a pay of Rs 335/- per mensem rising by annual increments of Rs 15/- per mensem, have been engaged by the Adviser without reference to this Agency. Dr. McDowall was engaged from the 29th October 1938 and Miss Harbottle from the 29th December 1939. Both contracts contain an arbitration clause making the Political Agent Bahrain the final arbiter in any dispute which may arise. 3. Such a dispute has arisen between Dr. McDowall and the Adviser over various matters including recovery of fees on account of private practice, scale of fees to be charged etc. The matter is therefore reported for information and instructions. No. 591 dated the 19th March 1932, in which it is stated r s ;?*f Political Agent, Bahrain. / /Confidential. D.O.No. ' /o Bairirain, July 26, 1941, Dear Alban, With reference to Dr. McDowell*s letter regarding the terms of her Agreement and your No. C/710-6/26 dated 5th July, 1941. When the Resident was here he discussed the matter i with me unofficially and said he would let me know what pay and conditions were enjoyed by lady doctors in Indian States and elsewhere. Would it be possible for you to remind him about this matter. I have no means of comparing her terms with other people holding the sane qualifications in similar posts. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidents 1 NcC/800-6/26. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 28th July 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. T 1, D.O.No• 1400-10 dated July 26th 1941 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. r 2. indorsement No.C/710 ^ da^ed §th July 1941, from th^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Dr. McDowall - terms of Agreement of.lTo.G/317 of I94i Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Shiraz Dated the 27th July, 1941. To The Political Agent Bahrain Memorandum Reference your memorandum Bo.G/740, dated the 10 th July 194 1 . Pending official sanction of the Government of India to the contracts of Dr.M.M.McDowall and Miss 1T.M. Harbottle you may proceed with arbitration in the dispute which has arisen between the Adviser and Jl-'.McDowall. Europeans are engaged by the Bahrain Government without a previous reference to this Residency* You should, however, take steps to ensurethat no more ResidentXf-&lt; Confidential D.0 # ^o. IC/34 Karachi, the 28th i^u^ust 1941 A Reference your derri-officlal letter Ho# 1400 - 10 dated the 26th July 1041 aoout pay ana conditions of lady doctors in India* 2 # I passeu the has perhaps given yon the information by now. Yours sincerely, 0# halrympie nei^rave, Esq., w.u.e*, Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BahrainNo. //^-19/235. British Consulate General, Bushire, Dated, the 2^. October 1941 T ° The Political Agent, ( )0/ Bahrain, Memorandum p- ' Reference this office memorandum No.C/317,dated the 27th July 1941. 2. Ex post facto sanction of the Government of India to theemployment of Misses M.M.McDowall i and N.M.Harbottle by the Bahrain State has now been accorded. By order, Secretary »to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confidential D.0.Nae/1020-6/26. Dated the 30th October 1941 ^ 4 - erence correspondence ending with my letter No.K/34 dated the 28th August 1941. The Government of India hove now accorded ex post facto sanction to the employment of Misses M.M* McDowall and N.M. Harbottle by the Bahrain State. The Government of India however desire that all cases where the services of Europeans (including Aus tralians and Americans) are to be engaged shall be referred to them before hand. Yours sincerely, L f C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.4 * To: - H.B.xM's Political Agent, BAHRAIN: Secretariat, Bah ra i n , Persian Gulf. 9th November, 1941., Sir, I very much regret to inform you that our Lady Medical Officer, Dr Margaret M. McDowall, has resigned from this position with the Government of Bahrain, having given six months'/vAraoic calendarJ as from the 18th Shawal 136o., (c/w 8th November, 1941;. Dr McDowall has been appointed to the Chair of Midwifery and Gynecology at Baghdad, and has the distinction of being the first Lady Professor to be so appointed east of Suez. Dr wcDowall is entitled to leave of absence on account 01 ner period or service xiere ; and it is noped to arrange for tnis leave rc expire on the date of the expiry of her notice, and consequently she may depart from Bahrain to Baghdad at an early date. I have the honour to be, Oi y M-/ - * (A , l \ v p v , r eru 'KtvNo* C/1059 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th November 1941 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAH R AIN Memorandum t&gt; - Reference your letter of the 9th November 1941 regarding resignation of T )r* McDowall* 2, I would be grateful to know v/hat arrangements are being made to fill the vacancy of Lady Doctor. L- Political Agent, Bahrain6 ' No&gt; C/1061 The Political Ageat, Hatirain, Praseats his compliments to r The Honourable t»he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain^ and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) A 7 The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated - 12th November 1941 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. / Subject 1. Letter dated the 9th November/] 1941 from the Adviser to th^ Bahrain Government. 2. Memora dum No. C/1059 dated the 12th November 1941 to t|ie Adviser to the Bahrain Government. v \ / &gt;■' A j Resignation of the Lady Doctor Dr, McDowall.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. Bahrain, Novr. 13, 1941. * v? I understand that you have 'been informed about Dr. MoDowall’s resignation. Dr. McDowall was offered the Chair of Midwifery and Gynaecology in the Royal Hospital, Baghdad, this being the first time that any English woman doctor has been offered a post by the Iraq Government. Under the circumstances I feel that we have no course open except to except to accept her resignation. Dr. McDowall has several months leave in hand which she wishes to take now in order to be able to take up her new duties in Baghdad as soon as possible. me. DeGrenier informed.by cable about Dr. McDowall’s A resignation just before I left India and I had an opportunity of making some enquiries from medical people about the possibilities of finding a woman doctor for Bahrain; from what I heard it appears to me that it would be very difficult to obtain an English woman doctor at the present time. I have discussed the position with Snow and agree with his suggestion that we might ask the Mission Hospital if Dr. Barney could do part time work at the Govern ment Hospital for the time being. If we could have obtained Dr. Barney as a permanent doctor she would, I believe, be invaluable. Although her qualifications Confidential. D.O. No. C/2171. Dear Alban, are4 _o_ are perhaps not as high as Dr. McDowall’s she is very well-liked among the people who have known her for many years and she speaks Arabic fluently. Failing Dr. Barnew it might he possible to obtain Dr. Rottschaefer who is, I believe, working in South India; she too is well known in Bahrain and knows the language. It -would be possible to continue normal work in the Women’s Hospital as fortunately the staff are fully qualified to deal with normal cases although any abnormal cases will have to be passed on to a qualified doctor. Yours sincerely, • &gt; Major R. G. 3. W. Alban, O.B.S H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential No. C/1080-6/26 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Pieseats his compliments to :— The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Camp, Bahrain and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document /// with the renark that ' k ooth Drs* Barney and Rottschaefer are well known to iie and would be entirely suitable to fill the post of Lady Doctor, Bahrain State Hospital, if their services are obtainable. Both are American subjects. A further communication will follow. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Political Agent, Bahrain’s P.L. No.C/1061 dated 12th November Dated the 16th N ov emb er 1941 Reference to previous correspondence : 1941 Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject D.O.No.C/2171 dated 13th November 1941, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. Lady Doctor, Bahrain State HospitalConfidential D.O. No. G/SflJ- fe Bahrain, November 15, 1941 Dear Alban Reference your D.O. C/^020-6/26 dated 30th October 1941, I have noted that should there be any question of appointing Europeans for service with this State the matter should be referred to the Government of India first. The two ladies in question were appointed with the knowledge of His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent but their appointments were not the subject of any correspondence. Yours sincerely Major R. G. S. W. Alban, O.B.E. , H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Lr —■-&gt;, (f5 Confidential No. C/1087-6/26. The Political Agent, Satirain, Presents his compliments to :— The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. and has the h in oar to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 1 7th Nov ember 1941 • Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject T7 D.O.No.C/2177 dated November 15th 1941 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. Appointment of Europeans for service in the Bahrain StateNo. filf -19/235. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. for information with the remark that as the figures seem to refer to Indian Lady Doctors they do not appear to be of much use. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated December. 1941 •. Reference to previous correspondence : His printed letter No.C/800-6/26 dated the 23th July 1941. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Ixpress le ,ter Jo. D. 2604-1!/41 dated the 27th October 1941 from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. + Scales of pay of women doctors in Government Hospitals. L /, 4 *15a il. (jovernment of India External Affairs Department Express Letter . From Foreign, New Delhi, To Britconsul, Bushire. No.D.2604-ii/41. New Delhi, tne Novr. 1941. Your express letter No. 1130-19/235 of 21st October. 2. The scales of pay of women doctors in Government Hospitals in some Provinces are as shown below:- Province. Civil Asstt. Civil Sub-Asstt. Surgeons . i£. 75-5-175 60-5-170 75-5-175 60-5/2-75- 5/2-90^10/2- 120 . Lady doctors in Balucnistan draw their pay in the scale of Rs. 150-10-200. Information in regard to other provinces is not readily available . THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Sd/- 1.3. Gonsalves. Surgeons. Ts. Punjab 225-15-450 Bombay 200-40/3-400-50-450 Madras 200-15-350-20-450 Central Provincea200-10-300-15-450 Assistant Secretary to the Govt, of IndiaTelegram From ILB.iC’s Consul General, Busbire. To No. Datod despatched r^oeiveci— Reference your express letter No.D.2604-E/41 November 27th. 2. Please send by Airinail direct to Political Agent, Bahrain (with copy by post to re) inforration regarding the scale of pay of European Lady Doctors in Indian °tates and Government service. Britconsul. Foreign, Lev; ' ; 'elhi. A/418. 20th December 1941 Entisli Oonavlat^-Grrral, BustiTe. No 111iii' I C I I II ■ Copy forwarded by pos^to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information, with reference to this Residency’s printed letter No. nif -19/235, dated the^^J December 1941.AIR LaIL- Frorr To Goveriunent^ of India, xternal Affairs Department. Lv % SXPHS3S lETTIffi. Foreign, New Delhi, Political Agent, Bahrain.'/ (Repeated Britconsul, Bushire). No.F.16(8)-E/41. New Delhi, the /5' v \lan^r\ r 1942. Reference telegram from BritcoK^ui, Bushire No.A-418, dated the 2Cth December^941, regarding scales of pay for European lady doctors in Indian States and Government service. 2. A statement showing the scales of pay of women doctors employed in Mysore, Baroda and Kashmir States is attached/ There are no separate scales for European lady doctors in these States and information'in respect of other States and of Provinces is not readily available. European lady doctors are however employed in the ./omen’s Medical Service for India organised b T / r the National Association for supplying Medical Aid by ./omen to the Nomen of India, and relevant extracts from Rules and Regulations relating to the Service are enclosed. The issue of the above has been authorised. Assistant Secretary to 'the Government of India. G.S. Nns A.' v \ 1 ''* vNo.' C/111 The Political Agent, ttahraiii, Preseats his compliments to :— The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agenc'/, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated -24th -January 194&amp;' Reference to previous correspondence : Adviser’s demi-official letter No. 1400-10 daued the 26th July 1941 Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject Express Letter No. F.16(8)-E/41 dated the 15th January 1942 from the Assistant Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, with enclosures in original. Scales of pay of European lady doctorsConfidential. GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN D.0.No. February 19, 1942. 1 should be obliged if you would give me your advice on the following matter. When I was in India in November our Lady doctor, Dr. McDowall, resigned her post in order to accept a better one in Iraq. She did in fact T, walk out ,T on us. If I had been here I would have asked her to give us moretime but she was allowed to leave about a monxS^fter giving six months’ notice in order to take up her work in Iraq. She had at the time that she left about months leave due to her and she was paid for all leave and passages due to her when she left. Dr. McDowall had a Provident Fund of Is. 100/- per month. This was paid to her up to the time that she ceased serving the Bahrain Government, she did not receive her Provident Fund after she left Bahrain. In other cases when British officials have resigned from service in this State they have drawn all passage money and leave pay which is due to them at the time when they ceased to serve but • their Provident Fund has stopped when thev left Bahrain. Dr. LcDowall has now written to me enquiring whether^she is not entitled to Provident Fund for the period of the leave which had earned. Dr. McDowall ’ s AgreementT^^* ^hich you have a copy, states that the proceeds of her Provident Fund will be handed over to her on termination of the contract. Should it be assumed that the con tract terminated when she ceased to serve this State and entered the employment of another Govern ment or at the expiration of the 6 months’ notice or at the expiration of the leave which she had earned? I enclose a copy of her letter. B.B. Wakefield, Fsquire, I K. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Fsquire, I.C.S.,Copy of a letter dated 30th January 1942 from Dr. M.M. licDowall, 2 Alwiyah, Baghdad, Iraq, to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Your letter No. 2444/10 dated December loth and your letter No. 2464/10 which was received on January 22nd. I am writing to enquire why the date December 12th was chosen to stop my Provident Fund? I am at a loss to understand why I did not receive Provident Fund up to the end of my leave or to the end of my six months notice. It seems that I had received my leave pay and therefore Provident Fund up to the end of that period. Admitted that the Bank had to be informed when the six months notice of my leave ended but I fail to understand why provident Fund should cease before my official service had ceased. I should be. glad if you would discuss this point with Lr. deGrenier. There is nothing in my contract to say it should be stopped like that.Confidential D.O. No. C/230 Dated the 25th February 1942 r 5 Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 249/10 dated the 19th February 1942 ? (P* 2. Under Clause 3 of Dr. McDowell* s agreement her Pro vident Fund was to accumulate during the period of her con tract and the proceeds were to be handed over to her on the termination of that contract. As long y therefore y as Dr. McDowall was in contractual relations with the Bahrain Government i.e. as long as she was in their service, she was entitled to receive Provident Fund benefits. As soon, however, as she entered the service of another employer, her service under the Bahrain Government must be held to have terminated. Dr. McDowall is therefore (in my opinion) entitled to Provident Fund payments the rate of Rs 100/- per mensem up to the date on which she entered the service of another employer. 2. Dr. McDowall seems to be puzzled why she has been given leave pay but denied Provident Fund benefits after leaving the service of the Bahrain Government. The reason is, of course, that her leave pay was earned by her previous service under the Bahrain Government and was payable to her even after she left the service of that Government; but Provident Fund benefits were only to continue until the termination of her contract i.e. until she left Bahrain Government service. \ Yours sincerely, C. Dalrymple Belgtfave, Ssq., C.B.b., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BahrainPersonal. r.-’V' l/l /a V Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 11th March, 1942. The Behrain Government have so far been unable to find a successor to Dr. McDowall who was in charge of the State Hospital for V/omen till December last, although they have applied to various associations. 2. It has occurred to me that amongst tne numerous refugees and grass-widows now in India there must be a number of ladies possessing medical qualifications or previous experience of hospital wor&lt; who would onlv betoo glad of a job of this nature. ~ i 3. The terms offered to a lady possessing suitable qualifications are Bs.SOO/- per mensem plus a car plus a furnished flat plus a Provident Fund subscription of Hs.50/- or Rs.lOO/- per month. 4 . I shall be very grateful if there is anything you can do to assist the Bahrain Government in finding a suitable incumbent. sd. W. R. Hay. H.Weightraan Esquire, CIS.,ICS., Joint Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. Copy given to Mr. WakefieldPIT GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. D.O.No. sl'P'-l* \. % \fi* f Sr Dated, April 6, 1942 j We have now had a letter from Snow f s sister, herself a doctor, who knows Dr. Doeg and her report about her is satisfactory. From this and from the testimonials which Dr. Doeg sent I think she sounds suitable for the post of Lady Medical Officer in Bahrain so I am writing to enquire whether you approve of her being offered the post by the Her conditions of service will be similar to those of Dr. McDowall but without a private practice among the Arabs. This was a source of much trouble and little profit to Dr. McDowall and after discussing the matter with Snow I think it would be better for all parties to exclude it. Our hospital is very full and Dr. Barney who is at present helping us out cannot continue working much longer so I should like to obtain Dr. Doeg as soon as is possible which would not, in any case, be before the end of June. I should be much obliged if you would let me know whether you approve of our taking action. Bahrain Government. • &gt; E. B. Wakefield, Esquire, I.C.S H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential D.O.No. C/441. n / i / The Agency, Bahrain, the 9th April 1942. With reference to your demi-official letter No.575-10 dated the 6th April 1942, would you kindly let me know (if the information is readily available) Dr. Doeg's full names, her age, medical qualifications and present employment. Yours sincerely, C. Dalrymple Belgrave Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.II L 3 D.O.No. &lt; Bahrain, April 8, 1942. With reference to my D.O.No. 575-10 dated 6th April, 1942, regarding the appointment of Dr. I.M.A. Doeg of the Lady Emerson Seth Chatur- bhuj Hospital, Amritsar, as Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain Government, I enclose the suggested terms and conditions of her Agreement. E. B. Wakefield, Esquire, I.C.S., H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. mmDRAFT AGREMaNT Term and nature of ooatraot * Dr* I.M.A. Doeg shall faithfully serve the Government of Bahrain as a Medical Officer for the term of this contract which is for four years, terminable by six months f notice on either side, renewable after the expiry of four years, by mutual consent. The rate of pay shall be Rs. 600/- (Sight hundred rupees) per mensem rising by annual increments of Rs* 25/— (Twenty five rupees) per mensem. Salary commences on arrival in Bahrain. A sum of Rs. 100/- (One hundred rupees) per mensem, or its equivalent in sterling, will be paid monthly into an account with the Eastern Bank Limited representing the Lady Medical Officer*s provident fund, the proceeds of which will be handed over to the Lady Medical Officer on termination of the contract* Accommodation * Free furnished house or a flat. Transport. — A oar to be provided free of upkeep with free petrol while on duty* One and a half earned after each completed year's service not to be taken in the first place till after two years service* Leave one month earned after each year*s completed service* Annual leave counts as service for assessing furlough and may be accumulated up to two months* Furlough Passage s. A first class train and sea passage from Amritsar to Bahrain on taking up appointment* Pa£ Provident Fund Furlough * and leave are on full average pay*A first class passage from Bahrain to the United Kingdom on final termination of service also a first class return passage from Bahrain to the United Kingdom in the event of the Lady Medical officer taking leave after four years if the contract is renewed• A first class return sea passage, Bahrain-KarachJ when taking annual leave, or the equivalent amount assessed . if leave is taken elsewhere. If this is not utilised it may be accumulated towards passage to Surope on furlough which under the terms of the agreement the Bahrain Govern ment is not liable to pay. First class passages are p. &amp; o. 1st class C Bombay- United Kingdom, and 1st class Gulf steamers with food Bahrain-Karac hi or Bahrain-Bombay. Private Practice, Among Europeans and Americans only, Bahrain Government officials* families receive free medical attention except in case of maternity cases. Restriction of trade . As long as Dr, Doeg remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain she shall not carry on any trade or business on her own or any one else*s behalf, or receive any remuneration for any services rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Government of Bahrain which must be obtained in writing. For the purpose of this agreement all dates and periods shall be those of the Arabic calendar which is the official calendar used by the Government of Bahrain, Arbitration . If any question arises under the contract. whether as regards the meaning or in any other respect, the question shall be referred for the arbitration of the Political Agent in Bahrain and his decision shall be final.Confidential. D.O.No. Bahrain, April IE, 194E. V/ith reference to your D.O.No. C/441 dated the 9th April }.94E, Dr. Isabel Mary Agnes Doeg, age 4E, is a graduate (M.B., Ch.B) of Edinburgh University in 1923. She worked for 10 years at a Mission in Baramulla, Kashmir, in charge of a hospital of 60 beds. In 1938 she did one years f Surgical and Obstetric course in Edinburgh. She is now in charge of Lady Emerson Seth Chaturbhuj Maternity Hospital, Amrit sar. E. B. Wakefield, Esquire, I.O.g., H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVER^alEST OP INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To ^ save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had beets so despatched,] Political Agent 9 Bahrain* Political Resident, Camp, Bahrain* C/483. Bate# 14th April 1942jSa CXi Bahrain Governihent propose to appoint as Lady Medical Officer in Dr.Me Dowell’s place Dr.Isabel Mary Agnes Doeg M.B., Ch.B.CEdin.), age 42, at present in charge of Lady Emerson Seth ChaturbhU') Maternity Hospital, Amritsar. Dr. Doeg worked for ten years at Mission Hospital, Earamulia, Kashmir. Terms of appointment are it 800 p.m. with annual increments of Rs 25 p.m. plus Provident Fund E100 p.m. free house and transport. Dr .Doeg is strongly recommended by Deputy Commissioner Amritsar. Bahrain Government are anxious to make appointment at once. I am satis fied that Dr.Doeg is satisfactory choice and if approval of Government of India cannot be obtained telegraphically I request permission to convey approval to Bahrein Government in anticipation Polit^GL Agent, Bahrain. of confirmation. .... MFP—1206 S&amp;P—(M-1723)—4-2-36—200,000^G.T.C. Telegram From To Copy to No.T/308, Dated the 17th April 1942. Political Resident, on Nearchus. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain Government wish to appoint a Lady Medical Officer Dr. I.M.A. Doeg at present in charge of Lady Emerson Seth Chaturbhuj Maternity Hospital Amritsar. She is strongly recommended by Deputy Commis sioner. Terms of appointment are Rs.800 per mensem with annual increments of Rs.25 plus Provident Fund Rs.100 per mensem free house and transport. Please telegraph approval repeating Bahrain. - RESIDENT -iju Telegram G.T.C. From Government of India,,New Delhi. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No.3503. Dated 23rd received 24th April 1942, © - Your telegram No.T/308 April 17th. Doeg. No objection. Foreign.Confidential . D.Q.No.C/516# Political Agency, Bahrain, the 25th April 1942. .1 you please refer to your denii- official letter No.575-10 dated 6th April 1942. 2. There is no objection to the appointment of Dr. Doeg as Lady Medical Officer in Bahrain. Yours sincerely, ejo C.D.Belgrave Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.presents J-RjQL The Adviser to the his compliments to ; Bahrain Government His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Bahr ain. Agent, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for his record.. i Adviser’s Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No:- P- Dated October 12, 1943. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Copy of Agreement of Agreement of service. Dr. I.M.A. Doeg with the ^ Government of Bahrain. Reference to previous correspondence s.z.umonmmi OF AGH3gMKNT mado this twelfth day of June On© Thousand Nina Hundred and Forty Two, B8TWSSM His Highness Ghaikli Saliaan bin Hamad AlKhalifati, Hiaer of Bahrain Islands, Persian Gulf, on behalf of the Govern ment of Bahrain, of the one part, and Dr. I.M.A. Dbe&amp; of the other part. WXT&amp;3S3ETB that it is mutually agreed that the said Government of Bahrain will employ the said Dr. I.M.A.Doeg and the said Dr. l.feUA. Doeg will serve the Ckjvermaent of Bahrain for a period of four years ©o^menoing from the tv/elfth day of June One Thousand Nixie Hundred and Forty ^ro on the terms specified on the schedule of terms attached. IN WITfOCSS whereof the parties hereto have hereunto signed their nmQ&amp;« SBixl of His Highness Shaikh Salman bin Hamad AUKhalifah. Provisionally signed by;-2 . 3 * 4 * 5 . 6 . 7 . of oontraot , DTm X«M«A* Doeg shall faithfully serve the Government of Bahrain as a Medical Officer for the tana of this oontraot which is for four years, terminable by six months 1 notice on either side, renewable after the expiry of four years, by mutual consent« Pay . The rate of pay shall be ha. 800/- (Sight hundred rupees) per mensem rising by annual incrccionts of £&amp;• &amp;S/- (Twenty five rupees) per mensem. Salary commences on arrival in Bahrain. Provident Fund . A sum of Ks. 100/- (One hundred rupees) per mensem, or its equivalent in sterling, will be paid monthly into an account with the Eastern Bank Limited representing the Lady Medical Officer , s provident fund, the proceeds of which will be handed ovor to the Lady Medic**! Officer on termination of the contract. Acoosaaodatlon . Free furnished house or a flat. A car to be provided free of upkeep with free petrol while on duty. Furlough . One and a half months earned after each completed year f s service not to be tacen in the first place till after two years 1 service. Leave one month earned after each year’s completed service* Annual leave counts as service for assessing furlough and may be aeousulated up to two months. Furlough and leave are on full average pay. Passages . A first class train and sea passage from Amritsar to Bahrain on taking up appointment.- 2 - (ft) A first class passage from Bahrain to the United Kingdom on final tenainatiou of service also a first class return passage from Bahrain to the United Kingdom in the event of the Lady Modioal Officer taking leave after four years if the contract is renewed• A first class return sea passage, Bahrain-Karaohi when taking annual leave, or the equivalent amount assessed if leave is taken elsewhere* If this is not utilised it may be accumulated towards passage to Europe on furlough which under the terms of the agreement the Bahrain Government is not liable to pay* • First class passages are F* &amp; 0* 1st class C Bombay- United Kingdom, and first class Gulf steamers with food Rahrain-Karaohi or Bahrain-Bombay. 8* Private Practice . Among Europeans and Americans only* Bahrain Government officials * families receive free medical attention except in case of maternity cases* Restriction of trade * Aa long as Ur* I.M.A. Doog remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain she shall not carry on any trade or business on her own or any one else*8 behalf, or receive any reiauneration for any services rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Government of Bahrain which must bo obtained in writing* For the purpose of this agreement all dates and periods shall be those of the Arabic calendar which is the official calendar ue^d by thw Government of Bahrain* 11* Arbitration . If any question arises under the contract, whether as regards the meaning or in any other respect, the question shall be referred for the arbitration of the Political Agent in Bahrain aha his decision shall be final*- No. of 1365 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 10th R/Thani 1365 March 14, 1946. H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. 13V / 6 3 3.. Memorandum.: - Dr. Doeg, the Lady Medical Officer, is leaving Bahrain on the completion of her four years agreement with this Government. When I was in England I advertised in the British Medical Journal for a Woman Doctor and received some replies but none of them materialised. Since coming back from leave an application for the post has been received, in answer to the advertisement, from Dr. (Captain) J.G. Archibald, R.A.M.C., who is now working in Delhi holding the post of Medical Officer-in-Charge W.A.C. (1). After examining her testimonials and discussing the matter with Dr. Snow I am of the opinion that she ’would be a suitable person to fill the post of Lady Medical Officer which is now vacant and if you approve I will write to her offering her the appointment on the terms which I enclose, which are those that were stated in my advertisement. I gathered, in England, that it is extremely difficult to obtain either women doctors or nurses. fy. iliUCl a ..... . &gt;'The Government of Bahrain, an Arab State in the Persian Gulf, is prepared to receive applications for the post of Lady medical Officerto be in charge of the Women’s Hospital and public health work among women. The Lady Medical Qtiicer will jo under the State Medical Officer (British) but will be in complete charge of her own Department. Previous experience in the Bast would be an advantage. ^ i-l-lO work is mainly among subjects ot II• H • The Shaixh of Bahrain but private practice is allowed among the Europeans living in the islands. Only candi dates with the right sympathies and interest should apcly. The appointment would be for a period of 3 or 4 years commencing March, 1946. Salary^£700- £850 according to age and experience. Copies of testimonials and particulars should be forwarded to Box No..... tT .GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B,—Tins is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sa^e telegraphic expense and undue, use of ike wires, but intended to he. trouted, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hud been teb graphed. To sa e time and formalities it is worded a d siyt cd as if it Jmd been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain, To Britain, Bushlre. So, Ho.881-6/26. V Dated 17th iiarch, 1946. m Reference correspondence ending with Government of N India telegram No.360 E dated the 23rd April, 1942. 2. I enclose copies of correspondence^received from the Bahrain Government on the subject of the replacement of Dr. Doeg, 3. I should be grateful if the Government of India could be asked telegraphically to interview Dr. Archibald and, if they find her suitable in their opinion, accord confirmation to her employment by the Bahrain Government. -POLITICAL' The issue of the above has been authorised. ASSISTANT POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. __— -yiiv,',o S. 6. M P 400S&amp;P iM 480 26 7-34 2. O.AKJ.From Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. Dated A/613 13th and received the 14-th April, 194-6. e.i' Your Express Letter No.881 March 17th. Lady doctor for Bahrain. Please telegraph specific terms and conditions of appointment for information of,Doctor of appointment of India. Terms enclosed with Adviser’s letter No.565-10 March 14th are vague e.g. increment contribution to provident fund, liability for passage etc. are not mentioned. 5^ P ?$ AMO. =BRITAIN=No.1207-6/26. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th April, 1946. To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.565-10 dated the 14th March, 1946. 2. Please let me know the specific terms and conditions on which the lady doctor will be appointed. The enclosure to your letter under reference makes no mention of an incre ment, contribution to the Provident Fund, liability for passage etc. C.No. — of 1365 Office of the adviser to the G-overmuent , Bahrain Dated, 22nd J/Awal, 1365 April 24, 1946. N o ~,§\S.C)$LDate . 2 H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. L r e m) r and uni; - Reference your memorandum No.1^07-6/26 dated 17th April 1946, re; Dr. Archibald. The agreement v/ill be the same as in the case of Dr. Dceg whose agreement was sent to you with my Printed Letter No.1923-5 dated 12th October 1943. p Adviser to the Government.telegram From To No. Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. 268 29th April, 1946. l.'Kl Your telegram A/613 April 13th. Terras and conditions of appointment are same as offered to Doeg- See your telegram T /308 April 17th 1942. Copy of agreement being sent by mail. =POLITICAL= AMONo.1362-6/26. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 30th April, 1946. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. p.*? b Memorandum . ^ Reference my telegram No.268 dated the 29th April, 1946. 2. I enclose herev/ith a copy of the draft agreement. for Political Agent, Bahrain. CX Bahrain Receipt V7S'? Mo— GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. D.O.Ko. Adviserate, May 25, 1946, V/itii reference to my memorandum No. 565-10 dated 14th March 1946, on the subject of the Lady Medical Officer, I have heard nothing More from Captain Archibald, have you any information about her? 2 . In the meantime I have received an application from a Dr. Sawdon, Birmingham degree, aged 31, 2 years House Physician work, including eye work and 2 years with the Friends Ambulance Unit in China. She sounds more suitable than Dr. Archibald and I am writing to her some details of the work and the climate. Her application was in reply to our advertisement. Inciden* * tally she worked in the Lady Chgchtster Hospital in Hove where I know a number of medical people from whom I could obtain details. 3. We need a doctor badly, there is such a lot of work to be done in that line and the Indian woman who we have is not able to take the place of a British doctor. c ^ Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.H., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. \ vnD.O. No.1637-6/26. 27th May, 1946. My dear Belgrave Your demi-official letter No.1126-10 of the 26th of May, 1946, on the subject of Doctors Archibald and Sawdon. - ? 2. I gather that you have not actually offered the appointment to Dr. Archibald - vide your letter No.666-10 dated the 14th March, 1946. Will you please confirm this? 3. The Government of India do seem to have been slow in dealing with the matter and if you have not definitely offered the appointment to Dr. Archibald I see no objection to Dr. Sawdon being interviewed in England and the post offered to C5 more suitable of the two ladies. However, I feel that we cannot ask Dr. Sawdon to be interviewed if the post has already been offered elsewhere. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Yours sincerely, v •i?.’. / JU\ ' Reference your D.O.No, 1687-6/26 dated 27th May 1946, the post of Lady Medical Officer has not actually been offered to Dr. Archibald. Dr. Sawdon’s letter came by sea mail and was dated March 25, so I think it would be best to await her airmail reply to my letter before making arrangements for an interview. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Calloway, O.B.S., H. B. M f s political Agent, Bahrain.M.O Telegram G.T.C. Jj'rom Government of India, &amp;ev) Dellii To Political Resident at Bahrain No • 5358 •^ated 16th and received 17th June 1946* 0&gt;A' Your telegram No# A/703 of M&lt;u/2nd# lady Doctor for Bahrain# 2# Doctor Archibald has declined appointment FOREIGN GiSW Office of the Political Resident^Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bail rain, No .C/308# Dated the 19th June 1946# 1 Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain, RHL. -hrain Receipt ' ? i 12.3 7... Dat. C2-. ^ (D.O.No. 1983-6/26. 22nd June, 19^6 My dear Belgrave Will you please refer to the corres pondence resting with your demi-official letter No.1150-10 dated the 29th May, 1946? 2. I am informed by the Government of India that Dr. Archibald has declined the appointment. 3* Have you heard anything more from Dr. Sawdon? C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Bsq*, C.B.S., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. Yours sincerely,Bahrain Receipt N o .&lt;5^!. Date... Dr. Sawdon did not reply to my letter so I presume she is not interested. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.3., H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.Extract of letter dated the 16th June, 1946* from Dr. Esther Wingate, Summer View Hotel, Lahore, to the Hobble Lt* Col* W.R* Hay, C*S*I* C.I.E., Bahrain. I am sending a note as to my experience and a testimonial from the Officer under whom I served longest. This is to enquire if an application from me would be considered and to ask for further information:- 1. What is the size of the Hospital and what medical and nursing staff are available? 2. What is the cost of living in the Gulf compared to India? 3. Would a yea^s agreement in the 1st instance with a passage to the U.K. instead of - passage from the U.K. as offered be considered. My present rate of pay is:- Rs.750/- 150/- Overseas allowance. 56/- Dearness allowance. Provident Fund earns 4% interest. Private practice is allowed. So that less than Rs.1000/- p.m. would not be a comparable salary.(e) The Bahrain Government provides a furnished flat and the use of a car. There is no income tax in Bahrain. Private practice is allowed among Europeans and Americans, there is a community of about 600 Europeans and Americans in Bahrain and no other women doctors. 3. I enclose, for Dr. Wingate f s information, a note which I wrote when in England about conditions etc., in Bahrain, I hope it does not paint conditions too dartly. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.E., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.£ NOTES FOR PERSONS PROCEEDING TO BAHRAIN. 1. Introductory. 2. Political. 3. Climate. 4. Household. 5. Dress. 6. Medical. 7. Servants. 8. Drink. 9. Recreations. 10. Churches. 11. Language. 12. Office hours. 13. Leave. 14. Food. 15. Miscellaneous. 1. INTRODUCTORY. These notes are written in 1945 when conditions in Bahrain,as elsewhere, are far from normal. Before the war one could buy in '^ 1 ® bazaars of Bahrain almost everything that a newcomer would require, by the end of the war shops had become depleted but it is hoped that grad«- ually conditions will return to the prewar standard. 2. POLI TICAL. ’W Bahrain is an independent Arab State, consisting of a group of Islands half way down the Persian Gulf, in treaty relatin with the Government of India, which is represented there by a Political Agent. _The Ruler of the State is His Highness Shaikh Sulman bin Hamad Al- Khalifah, K.C.I.E. The population is almost 100,000 consisting prin- -cipally of Arabs. The chief industries are oil, pearl diving and agriculture. There is a resident European community of not less than 600 British and Americans. Bahrain is an airport on the United Kingd.n jndia air route and is served by steamers of Liie i.ritish India line. The currency is the Indian rupee. There i^L an Indian Post Office, Indian stamps, surcharged 'BAHRAIN' are used. n ; * CLIMATE. The climate of the Persian Gulf is notorious but in fact it is scarcely as bad as it is made out. The soasons in ^aijrain can o© divided' into three phases; from the -Iddl© of June till the middle of October it is exceedingly unpleasant, though the actual temperature is not very high, when compared with other places in the Middle ..ast, rarely exceeding 103*Pon the coast and 110° in the centre of the island, yet the humidity during these months is excessive and freq uently exceeds 90°. From mid-October till about the °£ February the weather is very pleasant and often cold though fronts are unknown. Thick clothes are necessary at this time of the enr and fires are needed in the houses. The other four months of the year are agreeable. During the second half of May and the first half of June there is usually a cool north wind. The annual rainfall is about 2^ inches, rain usually occurs in December and January. The cultivation in Bahrain, which is mostly date palms, depends upon fresh water springs and irrigation channels for its water supply. . i 4. HOUSEHOLD. Free housing, i.e. quarters for single men, or an allowance in lieu thereof, if quarters are not available, is provided by the Bahrain Government. Officials of the State reside&gt;in Manama a town on the northern coast of the main island which is ohe capital and commeroial centre of Bahrain. The main island, which is about the size of the Isle of Wight is connected at Manama- 2 bjr a couseway to the adjacent island of Muharraq on which the aerodrome is situated. Flying boats anchor off Manama and the anchorage for B.I. steamers is opposite the town. Houses are stone buildings usually built in the form of flats with officers is limited. Electric light, fans and refrigerators are installed in the houses, the occupants paying for the current consumed and for the lamps. Furniture is provided but not curtains, carpets, crockery, cooking utensils, plate or linen. It is inadvisable and unnecessary to incur the e:q&gt;enditure of bringing out any heavy furniture but the addition of cushions, curtains and a rug or two to put on the dement floors, and personal effects, make the house more comfortable. In normal times china, cooking utensils, etc. could be purchased in Bahrain but at present (1945) there is a shortage of these things in the shops. It is advisable to bring sheets, towels, table mats and kitchen and pantry cloths. The glass and china obtain able in the bazaar is of poor quality and if some can be sent from Eir&lt; and it is better, Plate, cutlery and cooking utensils are not jys obtainable in the shops. 5. DRESS. Men - Summer. Shirts, slacks or shorts and sun helmets are worn and light tropical suits in the summbr. In the evening white open-neck short sleeved shirts, white slacks, blaCk socks, evening shoes and black cummerbunds are worn during the hot weather. On official occasions, for dinner, a white dinner jacket and a white soft shirt with a b&amp;ack tie is necessary Aertex or cellular day shirts are the most suitable and cellular vests are useful, not for warmth but for absorbing sweat. Silk is unsuitable in the very hot weather, it becomes damp and creases. Light brown leather or suede shoes or sandals are usually worn. Some can be bought ready made or they can be made by local shoe makers. It is usually possible to buy naterial for shirts and suits in the bazaar. If pyjamas are worn they should be cotton, many people prefer to use 'Lungis' waist cloths,made of locally woven cotton material. Uniform is not worn by officials of the Government of Bahrain. trousers and sports coats, and dinner jackets are used m tne evening, it is cold enough for pullovers and overcoats especially after sunset. Women - Winter. In the cold season women require the ‘fiype of clothing which is worn in England in April and May with‘addition of a really warm coat, some afternoon frocks and a few dinner frocks. Shoes are best taken from England as those on sale in the bazaar are not good. Sun helmets are scarcely worn and can be bought in the bazaar • Mosquito boots are never worn. Summer. 'Washing frocks, preferably cotton, are the best wear in the ver^ hot weather as linen or silft are unsuitable when the temperature is high and it is humid. Light frocks are usually worn from April to early December, one or two washing evening frocks are useful. Hats are rarely worn but on some occasions, such as official parties, a hau is required. In normal times cotton dress materials can be bought locally. Clothes are washed by Indian 'dhobis', washermen, Who keep them for a week. One the whole they wash clothes quite well. 6 9 MEDICAL Officials of the Bahrain Government and their wives and children are ^iven free medical treatment by the State edical Officers. There is a British /MedicalMedical uffleer and a ±Mdy Medical Officer. This privilege does not cover maternity cases for which arrangoraents have to he made with the medical authoriti s. Thor© is not at present a 'ursing Home for Europeans though this projuc'c ia under consideration. There are private wards in the men’s part of the State Hospital. There are practically no poisonous ins9Cts or snakes in Bahrain and no fleas, sandflies, or whit© an ; s. Owing to anti-malaria measures carried out by the Medical Department there are fow mosquitoes in the town of Manana. All houses are not provided with mosquito netting and in the houses on the sea front no mosquito nets are required. Vaccination and T.A.B. innoeu- lations are necessary before departure from England; smallpox is endemic and there have been occasional cases of typhoid, ./hen engag ing a servant it should bo ascertained that he has boon vaccinated. There is now no local prejudice against vaccination. Care should be takers in the house that vessels containing jater are emptied every day to p', vent mosquitoes breeding. Probably the most trying affliction during the summer is prickly Heat, an irritating rash on the skin which is due to the humidity and sweat. Men can, to a certain extent, avoid this by allowing their bodies to become thoroughly sunburned. This has to be don© carefully and by degrees. Prickly Heat is sometimes liable to develop into boils. It can be treated fairly successfully by various powders and ointments. Coloured spectacles are worn in the sunmfrr by most Europeans. There is a Syrian dentist in Manama trained at the American University of Beyrout. 7. SERV-i.TL. Local servants perform domestic duties more or less adequately and are les* expensive and usually moro satisfactory than foreign servants, by which is meant Indians. It may*b© scid, generally, that Europeans get the servants they deserve. If trouble is taken to train entirely raw local bo s they become excellent servants. Most cooks and houseboys are of Persian origin. Mo servants should be. employed without previous reference to the police. The requirements of a single man or a married couple can bo supplied by either one or two serx^ts. wages have risen sharply durinr the war, cocks are paid fy ' .65/- to n80/- p.m. , Mo’ sobo s from .50/- to :.7C/- var'ing acco/ ing to their acccmplisliments. ' oaiiose cooks, iron India, are a luxury; they demand not loss than 3.100/- |^.m. aad moreover they expect to be provided with cock’s boy to accompany them when shopping. Ho servants are provided with food but the employer is expected to get them clothes to wear when on duty. In most casos they live out, in their own homos in the town.* No women servants are employed. As the se vents are all Moslems the question of case does not occur. 8. PRIME . m Bail rain is a Moslem state and officially ’’dry” but Europeans are allowed to Import or purchase a limited amount of liquor on a special permit. Liquor is sold by the firm of Gray Mackenzie, the shipping agents. 1 rices, compared to England and adjoining countries in the East, are cheap as the customs duty is obi 15/3. It is e^enuial that liquor should be kept under lock and key as spirits fetch high prices in the bazaar. Bahrain subjects found in possession of liquor are *v liable to severe punishment in the local courts. 9. REUTEAMIONS. , There is no shooting in Bahrain and the import of arms and ammunition is prohibited. The import of dogs is prohibited unless the owner can produce a certificate from a qualified veterinary sergeon to the effect that the animal has been inocculatod v^ith anti-rabies vaccine Rabies is unknown in Bahrain though very prevalent in neighbouring rountries. Membership of the Gymkhana Club enables members to use the golf course, tennis courts and bathing pool. There is good sea ^jathing at places on the cost and sea /fishing.fishing* fresh water pools abound. r i here is no public library in Bahrain and it is advisable to place an order with a newsagent for periodicals. Aimail letters take about ton days from England, newspapers tako about six weeks, 10. CHbliC-jfc. There is a mission church of the Butch Reformed Church of Jiraerican in Manama and also a Catholic Church with a resident Priest. Anglican services are held occasionally and a project for building on Anglican Chruch is under way. There is a building, used for Anglican and other services, at Awali, the hea^ouarters of thu Bahrain Petroleum Company, -about 12 miles from Manama/fne centre of the island. Service chaplains frequently visit Bahrain to attend to the needs of the Naval Base, which is situated about three miles from Manana and the P-.A.F. who are-^stationod on Kuharraq Island. ' LANGUAGE. The language of Bahrain is -‘Arabic but in the towns a good deal of Persians and some Hindustani is spgken. Most of the shopkeepers speak some English. It is essential that all Europeans in the service of the Bahrain Government should acquire a knowledge of Arabid. Local teachers are evailable for giving lessons in iirabic. The best Arabic book for use in Bahrain is Van Ess’s Spoken Arabic of Mesopotania. The only book which deals exclusively with the Persian Gulf is A.T. Wilson’s Persian Gulf, now out of print. 12. OFFICE HOURS. Office hours vary considerably according to duties. In general, office are open from 8 a.n. till 2p.m. home offices open later in the morning and also in the afternoon. There is a telephone system in Bahrain and automatic telephones are shortly to be installed. There is no local postal service. There are two bakks in Bahrain, the Eastern Bank and tiu. Imperial Bank of Iran. The former fulfils many of the services of Government Treasury. The Arabic Calender is used bythe Bahrain Government; the Arabic year is about ten days shorter than thes* Gregorian year. Moslem holidays are kept. Offices close on Friday, not on Sunday. L2AV :. There is no hill station close to Bahrain where people can go for a change of Air. If home leave is not taken the nearest cool stations are the Lebanon Mountains in Syria, or hill stations in India. These places can be reached by air or by steamer and train but fares are at present extremely high and steamer services uncertain. 14- FOOD* It is difficult under the present changing conditions to give reliable infoiTaation about food supplies. At the time of writing, 19^45, the prices of moi&gt;t foodstuffs are controlled by the Government and cereals, i iduding flour, whe: t and barley, and sugar are rationed at the scale of 2G lbs of cereals and S lbs. of s gar per head per mohth. Meat, consi: tin of &gt;e©f and nuttcn is plentiful, or better uality than in neighbouring countries rid a little cheaper fhan in England. Excellent fish of many different kinds is avaiiaMetliroughout the year. Although Bahrain is the centre of the pearl industry oyst rs are not obtainable as those found are not edible. There is very little fruit apart from melons and fresh dates In the sumner. In the winter European vegetables are grown and in the summer there are local vegetables of rather a dull type on sale In the markets. Poultry is expensive, eggs are about half the size of European eggs. Milk, if the cows are well fed, is extremely good and fres^h butter can be made from it, but the great increase in the demand for milk has caused many of the cattle owners to water the milk. In normal tines the shops stocked large supplies of tinned goods of all descriptions from Europe, America and India but owing to the war stocks of tinne' ’' ^almost dis appeared. Cooking is done mainly on oil stove er is not / i-flfj)- 5 - laid on in most of th® Government houses. 15. ri£CELL.U'jj]OUS. There is no incomo tax in Bahrain. The ohly form of taxation to which officials of tho Government are liable is customs duty upon goods imported from abroad. The rates are 5$ and valorem on all foodstuffs and necessities, 1($ on non-essential imports and 15^&gt; on liquor and tobacco. Worn personal effects are not liable for customs duties. Cigarettes and tobacco are cheap and always available in the bazaar. ■v The local water is slightly brackish, but not unwholesome. Distilled water can be purchased locally. A scheme for a town water supply for M*inama is under consideration; this will include a distilling plant* Bahrain can be reached from the United Kingdon in two days by air, by sea via India* or by sea to Egypt and on by car and train to Basra and thence by sea or air. Air passengers are not allowed more than 44 lbs. of baggage.No. C/709 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 4th July, 1946. The Hon^le the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. dated the 19th June, 1946. j should be grateful if the post of Lady Medical Officer to the Bahrain Government could be offered to Dr. Esther Wingate who has already written to you on the subject. ^ *4 / 3 # x enclose a copy of Mr. Belgrave*^ letter and a note which - though inaccurate in places - I think might without harm be sent on to Dr. Wingate. 4 # i have no information regart :ng comparison in the cost of living in India and in Bahrain. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM. Reference your endorsement No. C/303 Sd/- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. AttestedCONFIDENTIAL. D.O. K&lt;&gt;. C/458 The Hon’bJe the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Lt-Col. A,C. Galloway, O.B.E,, Political Agent, Bahrain. and hap the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document {/). if $ •* «• Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, wmimix Camp Bahrain. Dated... .. 11th July.1946 Reference to previous correspondence: July, 1946. Bahrain memorandum No. C/709 dated the 4th Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter No. C/437 dated the 8th July, 1946, from Lt-Col. V».R. Hay. (Without enclosures). Lady Medical Officer for Bahrain Government.COP Y D-O- Mo. C/437 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. 8th July, 1946. Please refer to my demi-official letter No. C/364 dated the 27th June, 1946 2 Mr. Belgrave instead of replying to you direct has written to me through the Political Agent. He asks me to inform you that the Bahrain Government is prepared to offer you the appointment of Lady Medical Officer. He suggests that if you accept the appointment you should not arrive till October when the worst of the hot weather will be over. v reply to your questions, together with a copy of the notes compiled by him for persons proceeding to Bahrain. not keeping house here at present but should say that the cost of living here is somewhat higher than at Lahore. The figure given by Mr. Belgrave should enable you to assess the difference. whether you are willing to accept the appointment on the terms suggested ? If so we will apply for your services officially 3 % I enclose an extract from his letter giving a 4 With reference to item (b) in the extract I am 5. Would you kindly let me know as soon as possible \ through the Government of India Sd. W.R. Hay E. Wingate, Summer View Hotel Lahore. NCJ Para 2 (a) to (e)/'■'V * u^&gt; 1 / Off ice of the Political Resident, Persian Oulf Cajnp, Bahrain, the 24th August 1946. Please ref er t&lt;f my demi-official letter Bo. C/437 dated the 8th July 19^ to Lr. Wingate, a copy of which was sent to GalloVvayujxfer m y Printed Letter wo. C/458 dated the 11th July 1946.'^^I forward herewith a copy of the reply received from Lr. Wingate. 2. With regard to point (l) in her Letter I understand that the Bahrain Government would like to appoint an Assistant lady Doctor if one could he found. It is possible that Dr. Wingate might be able to recruit one from India. Would you kindly ascertain what terms the Bahrain Government are willing to offer. 3. With regard to point (2). Please let me have material for a reply. 4. With regard to point (3). This appears to be entirely a matter which concerns the Government of India and which I will take up with them if necessary in ;due course. 5. With regard to point (4). This is a point which also will I think have to be taken up with the Government of India unless Dr. Wingate is willing to take the leave now. If she is only seconded from the w.h.S. and not forced to resign she will presumably be entitled to take the leave later. 6 . I have been informed by Belgrave and Gnow that it rnight.be possible for the Bahrain Government to offer Dr. Wingate slightly better terms in the way of pay than those mentioned in paragraph 2(d) of Belgrave ’ s demi-off icial £^.4/ letter Do. 1394-10 dated the 29th June 1946 to Galloway. It might be worth while pointing out to Belgrave that when a Government servant in India is sent on foreign service to a State he is usually given 25/« deputation allowance over and above his ordinary pay. -further if Dr. Wingate remains in the service of the Government of India and is only loaned to the Bahrain Government it will be necessary for that Government to contribute to her leave and pension and in this case, of course, no Provident Bund contribution will be called for and leave taken will not be at the expense of the Bahrain Govern ment. In fact I suggest that the best course would almost certainly be not to try to persuade Dr. Wingate to resign the Government of India’s service and enter the Bahrain Government* service but to ask the Government of India to make her services available to the Bahrain Government on the usual foreign service terms. aptain H.D.H. Ranee, Political Agent, Bahrain Confidential. BAHRAIN REC^' 0 ^ Date....@) ! 0 $ 9 3unny View Hotel, Lahore, Punjab. 1.5th August 1946. v Lear Colonel Hay I apologise for the delay in answer! ig the correspondence but the postal strikes have delayed every tn ing. 1. 1 would not accept tne post without an assistant and take it there is none. 2. Unless the quarters are air conditioned - I understand this is usual in Bahrain Island. offer me here. 3o far I f ve no quarters and have dealt with the hot weather on a bicycle and the hospital is about 5 miles away and emergencies are many. At the moment (hence delay in writing) things are complicated as I was forced to admit to a carbuncle that wasn’t improving and was immediately sent into hospital and x jU t on penicillin. I'll be alright quite soon but I dont know what has been said on my K. Certificate. But from comments here about weather and recurrences; I am afraid the Gulf would be ruled out till the cold weather. I will write witain the next fortnight and of course if the vacancy is filled I fully understand. I dont know - quite frankly - what they’d Yours sincerely, 3d. L. vV lh GATECONFIDENTIAL . D.O.No.C/954. Dated the 26th August, 1946. Dear Relgrave, ^ £ H' ! t Will you please refer to correspondence ending with your demi-official letter No. 1394-10 dated the 29th June, 1946. ^ 2. I attach an extract from a letter which Colonel Hay has recently received from Dr. Wingate, and would be grateful for your comments. With regard to point 1 of this letter I understand that the Bahrain Government would like to appoint an Assistant Lady Doctor if one could be found and that Dr* Wingate might be able to recruit one from India. Would you kindly let me know what terms the Bahrain Government are willing to offer. Point 3 appears to be entirely the concern of the Government of India and, if necessary, Colonel Hay will take it up with them. Point 4 is also one which may have to be taken up with the Government of India, unless Dr. Wingate is willing to take the leave now. If she is only seconded from the Womens PJedical Service and not forced to resign she will presumably be entitled to take the leave later. for the Bahrain Government to offer Dr. Wingat&lt; better terms in the way of pay than those ment paragraph 2(d) of your letter under reference. ± also point out that when a Government servant in India is sent on foreign service to a State he is usually given deputation allowance over and above his ordinary pay, and that though it will be necessary for the Bahrain Government to contribute to Dr. Wingate*s leave and pension if she remains in the service of the Government of India and is only loaned to the Bahrain Government, no Provident Fund contribution will be called for, and leave taken will not be at the expense of the Bahrain Government. 4 # in view of the above Colonel Hay considers that the best course would almost certainly be not to try to persuade Dr. Wingate to resign the Government of India’s service but for the Bahrain Government to ask the Government of India to make her services available to them on the usual foreign service terms.. I understand that it might be poss yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Advisor to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain . JANC.Adviserate, Bahrain. Z, 1946. £)• Fc With reference to your D.O. i. T o.C/954 dated 26th August 1946, about Doctor Wingate. I have discussed the matter with Snow who is the person who would have to work most closely with her. He thinks that there would be a good many disadvantages in having her on loan from the Government of India. There would be the probability of friction over differences in the W.M.S’s regulations and our own. If she cam's for two years during a considerable part of the time she would not be of maximum value as it takes a considerable time for a woman doctor to get thoroughly established among the people here. 2. From her letter she strickes me as being rather too direct and uncompromising and as she is no longer young I think she might be rather 'set' in her views. 3. Snow recommends that we advertise again, many Overseas doctors are now at home and are beginning to be disillusioned owing to the changes in the state of the medical services in England. Captain, II.D.H. Ranee, H. 3. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.D.O. No.C/1012 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 7th September, 1946. Dear Colonel Hay, . ^ M Will yoo/please refer to your demi-official letter No.c/747 dated the 24th August, 1946, to Ranee. Belgrave has discussed the matter with Snow and t.'iey consider that there would be a good many disadvan tages in having Dr. Wingate on loan from the Government of India. There would be the probability of friction over differences in the W.M.S. regulations and those of the Bahrain Government and they would not receive the maximum value from her services if she came for only two years as it takes a considerable time for a lady doctor to become thoroughly established among the people here, she is no longer young and Belgrave is of the opinion she may be rather 'set” in her views. 3. Snow recommends that the Bahrain Government should advertise again for a lady doctor and states that many doctors who have recurned to the united Kingdom from overseas are disillusioned with the state of tne medical services there and are willing to serve overseas again. Yours sincerely, % The Hon * ble Lt-Col. W.H. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain .D.O.’So.Tii'-^ l Political Residency, Bahrain, September 10, 1946. Viiill you please refer to your letter No. C/1012 dated the 7th September 1946. p t°% I forward herewith a copy of a further letter I have received from Doctor Wingate and a copy of my reply. ^ p (O') Captain J.E.H. Hudson, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Confidential BAHRAIN RECEIPT- S..U15. Date.&lt;‘..X-iXas from Sunny View Hotel, Lahore Punjab. 4.9.46. Dear Gol. Hay» Will you inf om Mr. Belgrave that I am not in a position to accept the appointment offered. I do not think I should be released just now, at least it is said that the W.M.S. is short of officers. There is no reason now on health grounds, I am resuming duty on the 14th of this month. When I wrote to you I was aware that I*d problably been signed up as three weeks in hCLspital and 2 months off duty - but equally I was sure it would not be anything like that. As far as I rnyself am concerned if as I said, there is a population of women who have no medical aid unless there is a woman doctor I am willing tnat the W.k.S. should be asked to .lend or release me. Yours sincerely, Sd. SSTHiiR WINGAThJ.D.O. No. 734-S. Political Residency, Bahrain. The September 10, 1946. Dear Dr. Wingate, * Thank you for your letter of the 4th September. The Bahrain Government have also come to the conclusion that your being a member of the W.M.S. complicate matters too much and are advertising again for a Lady Doctor I am very sorry that matters have turned out this ^ay as I had looked forward to seeing you here and I think you would have found the work interesting and congenial. There is certainly a great deal for a Lady Doctor to do here. If at any time you sever your connection with the W.M.S. you might perhaps enquire whether there is an opening for you here. Yours sincerely, Sd. W.R. Hay. Doctor E. Wingate, Sunny View Hotel, LAHORE.D.O. Ho.C/1035. The 15th September, 1946 Dear Belgrave Will you please refer tg your demi-official letter Ho.1869-10 dated the 2nd September, 1946, to Ranee* 2. Dr. Wingate has now written to say that she is not in a position to accept the appointment that was offered her* She has been informed that the Bahrain Government had come to the conclusion that her being a member of the complicates matters too much, and that they are advertising again for a lady doctor* Yours sincerely, C«D« Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain ,D.O. Ko. A- / li 3 ferring to the oorrespendence about/^ Dr. Wingate ending with your D.0. T Tc.C/1035 dated 15th September 194G. I am glad to be able to tell you that in response to a communication from me Dr. Doeg, wlo was Lady Medical Officer^ in Bahrain for 4 years and who went to England about 6 months ago on completion of her agree ment, has agreed to return here and to serve for a further t.io years. This arrangement is entirely satisfactory from our point of view. In her telegram she asks that we should arrange for her passage, preferably by sea from United Kingdom to Bahrain. Her presence is needed here as soon as possible but under the circumstances as she has luggage with her there is no objection to her coming by sea. Could you kindly request the appropriate authorities in England to arrange a sea passage for her at the earliest opportunity' 5 . T 'er address is : 5 Morningside Drive - Edinburgh 10,Scotland* I am cabling to her stating that T am asking your assistance in obtaining a passage. Captain TT .D. TT . Dance, T ~. B. T ' T s political igent, Bahrain. Confidential. nu6EIPT.POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. D.O. No.C/1055. The 22nd September, 1946 Dear Colonel Hay, Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No.736-S dated the 10th September, 1946, to Hudson. 2. Belgrave informs me that Dr. Doeg, who recently completed four years here as Lady Medical officer, has now agreed to return to Bahrain And serve for a further period of two years. 3. The Bahrain Government feel that this is an entirely satisfactory solution of the problem, and therefore, provided you agree, I propose to inform them that there is no objection to their re-engaging Dr. Doeg as Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain. Yours sincerely. The Ifon'ble Lt-Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.K., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.X D.0. No. 3133-54/2. (2 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, The 29th September, 1946 si lt t J I am desired by Colonel Hay to refer to your demi-official letter No. C/1055 dated the 22nd September, 1946, and to say that he agrees with your proposal. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, Political Agent, BAHRAIN. r i Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.D*0» Ho. C/1092 The1st October, X946 you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 1980-10 dated the 19th September, 1946. 2. Colonel Hay has no objection to the reappointment of Dr. Doeg and is asking, the India Office to arrange a sea passage for her at the earliest opportunity. Yours sincerely, \!L- C.D. Belgr&amp;ve, Esq, C.B.E., The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.D.O. Ro. C/1093 x The Dear Felly, y Will you pleas« refer co your demi- official lector No* 3133-5^2 dated the 29th September, 1946* 2* I should be grateful if the India Office could be asked to arrange a sea passage for Dr* Doeg from the U*K* to Bahrain at the earliest opportunity* Her address is 5 Morningslde Drive, Edinburgh, 10, Scotland* Yours sincerely, C^* Felly, Escj, 0*jB*F*, I*C*k&gt;*, Secretary to the political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain*54/2 Teltgram G.T.C From To Political Resident, Bahrein India Office, London. No* a/1143. Dated the 2rd October, 1946 Grateful if a sea passage for Dr. Doeg, Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain, could be arranged from the United Kingdom to Banrain at the earliest opportunity. Her address is 5 Morningside Drive, Edinburgh, 10, Scotland. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain, by hand. Presumably Political Agent, Bahrain, will arrange to have Dr. Doeg informed that she should inquire from the India Office regarding her passage. « REPGU * Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. JSn ...D.O. No.C/1122 The 7th of October,46. Dear Belgrave, Will you please refer to corres pondence ending with my demi-official letter No.c/1092 dated the 1st October, 1946. £\5 i _ 2. I presume you have Informed Dr. Doeg that she should make enquiries at the India Office regarding her passage. C.D. Belgrave, Esq.,C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain .J /&gt;. . a ( Original on Kile 6/34 ) no \v D.O. No.C/1366. My dear Belgrave, The 8th of December, 1946. please refer to correspondence ending with Ranee's demi-official letter No.c/1144 dated the 12th of October, 1946, to you; 2. Since the writing of the above quoted letter passages other than certain priorities (in which Bahrain State officials are not included) have been handed over to the shipping authorities for distri bution. I am not sure whether the India Office have actually arranged passages for Dr. Doeg and Miss Millson and I suggest that your agents in London should now contact the India Office and obtain the required passages. Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Adviser to Esq., C.B.E., the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY. Copy to the Tion’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with reference to his telegram No.1100 dated the 8th October, 1946, to the India Office, London. % ?1946. % d . o . m./t?-'' c (,jii ' ^/3V Adviserate, December 10, cr^r 0 L - L Reference your D.O. No.0/1366 dated 8th December, I now hear that Dr. Doeg is on her way to Bahrain, by sea and is due in Bombay on about 17th of this month. Would it be possible for you to ascertain whether Miss Millson has also been provided with a passage? If she has not left fc l will ask our agents to assist. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.3., H. 3. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. ev Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. 1. . 3 . DateAmok.I'lAyS) No. Of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 17th R/Thani 1366 March 9, 1947. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum;- I enclose herewith a signed copy of Dr. I.M.A. Doeg»s agreement with the Bahrain Government for your record. Adviser to the Government. S.Z. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT* r Date.. —MEMORANDUM OF AGREEMENT made this fifteenth day of January One Thousand Nine Hundred and Forty Seven, BETWEEN His Highness Shailch Sir Sulman bin Hamad Al- Khalifah, K.C.I.E., Ruler of Bahrain Islands, Persian Gulf, on behalf of the Government of Bahrain, of the one part, and Dr. I.M.A. Doeg of the other part. WITNESSETH that it is mutually agreed that the said Government of Bahrain will employ the said Dr. I.M.A. Doeg and the said Dr. I.M.A. Doeg will serve the Govern ment of Bahrain for a period of two years commencing from the fifth day of January One Thousand Nine Hundred and Forty-Seven, A.H., corresponding with the thirteenth day of Safar One Thousand Three Hundred and Sixtysix, A.D., on the terms specified on the schedule of terms attached. IN WITNESS whereof the parties hereto have hereunto signed their names. His Highness Shaiich Sir Sulman bin Hamad AlKhalifah, K.C.I.E., Ruler of Bahrain Islands. Signature of Dr. I.M.A. DoegSchedule of terms of serrice of Dr. I.M.A Doeg, Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain. 1 . 2 . 3. 4 . 5. 6 . Terms and nature of contract . Dr. I.M.A. Doeg shall faithfully serve the Govern ment of Bahrain as a Medical Officer for the term of this contract which is for two years, terminable by six months* notice on either side, renewable after the expiry of two years, by mutual consent. Pa*. The rate of pay shall be Rs.999/- (Rupees nine hundred and ninety nine) per mensem rising by annual increments of iis.25/- (Rupees twenty five) per mensem. Salary commences on 13th Safar 1366. Provident Fund . A sum of fis.100/- (Rupees one hundred) per mensem, or its equivalent in sterling, will be paid monthly into an account with the Eastern Bank Limited representing the Lady Medical Officer’s provident fund, the proceeds of which will be handed over to the Lady Medical Officer on termination of the contract. Accommodation . Free furnished house or a flat. Transport . A car to be provided free of upkeep with free petrol while on duty. Furlough . One and a half months earned after each completed year’s service not bo be taken in the first place till after two year’s service. Leave one month earned after each year’s completed service. Annual leave counts as service for assessing furlough and may be accumulated up to two months. Furlough and leave are on full average pay. 2 /- 2 - ?• Passages . A first class sea passage will be provided for Dr. l.M.A. Doeg from the United Kingdom to Bahrain on taking up first appointment. A first class passage from Bahrain to the United Kingdom on final termination of service. A first class return sea passage, Bahrain-Karachi when taking annual leave, or the equivalent amount assessed if leave is taken elsewhere. If this is not utilised it may be accumulated towards passage to Burope on furlough which under the terms of the agreement the Bahrain Govern ment is not liable to pay. First class passages are P. at 0. 1st class C Bombay- United Kingdom, and first class Gulf steamer with food Bahrain-Karachi or Bahrain-Bombay. Q. Private Practice . Among Europeans and Americans only. Bahrain Govern ment officials* families receive free medical attention except in case of maternity cases. 9. Restriction of trade . As long as Dr. l.M.A. Doeg remains in the service of the Governm nt of Bahrain she shall not carry on any trade or business on her own or any one else’s behalf, or receive any remuneration for any services rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Government of Bahrain which must be obtained in writing. 10. For the purpose of this agreement all dates and periods shall be those of the Arabic calendar which is the official calendar used by the Government of Bahrain. 11* Arbitration . If any question arises under the contract, whether as regards the meaning or in any other respect, the question shall be referred for the arbitration of the Political Agent in Bahrain and his decision shall be final. S.Zpolitical Agency, Bahrain, The 13th March, 1947. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum. c-Lp — Reference your Memorandum No.821-10/5, dated the 9th March, 1947. 2. please send me another copy of Dr. Doeg's Agreement. 3. please send me two copies of all agreements between the Bahrain Government and their European employees in future. Sd./- C.J. PELLY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. for Assistant political Agent, £ Bahrain. ^ NS.' ' ISA A | ... —- &lt;No. of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 2nd j/Awal, 1366 March 23, 1947. Memorandum: - Reference your memorandum No. C/350 dated 13th March 1947. I enclose herewith another copy of Dr. Doeg f s agreement. H. B. M f s political Agent, Bahrain. ^ £ Adviser to the Government. S.ZCONFIDENTIAL. political Agency, Bahrain, No - C/ J{8 8 . The 25th Marchi , 471 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compli ments to: The Hon»ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s)• Reference to previous- correspondence; Residency demi-official letter No.3133-54/2 dated 29.9.*46 . Description of enclosure: NALfE &amp;• DATE. ; SUBJECT Agreement of Dr. I.M.A.Doeg. Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain Government.In addition, Dr. Doeg was allowed priv te practice, ^ and provided v/ith free quarters and transport at Government exnense. Contracts of B.G. enployees are usually for a period ^ ^ of 4 years shorter periods have been known. I.h. leave is not given in the first instance except after 2 years of completed'service when first class passage is provided - but see below. One month’s annual leave is also given together with IV the cost of a first class steamer passage max from Bahrain to ^ Barsc/i and luck. The cost of this passage may be used towards the cost of a passage to the U.K. when- special leave is taker and the Bahrain Government is not under obligation to nay for a U.K. passage. Id - J.A.r.c. 24-6-46*. Dr. Doeg received a.dearness allowance of Bs. 120 p.m. 3°! 15^-and not Ps. 60 at % as previously stated. 'cint was not clear tron i ile but has now been cleared up in a recent conmunication from Adviser. P.A. id. j.A.r.r. 2'' -£^4~6. Id. A^C.G. 25-T-46. 3a ie. to ( ■ n Un €MC ^ Bring on to file, but I think we. have copies. ltd. A.C.G. 30 / 6 / 46 . P.T.O.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS 'Zi c ISo MICROFILM*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/903</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/903</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 42/5 (6/26) Lady Medical Officer, Bahrain Government (1) Dr (Mrs) M.M. MacDowell (2) Dr I.M.A. Doeg'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-13T21:12:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (137 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 137; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-127; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding the position of Lady Medical Officer for the Government of Bahrain. The correspondence is primarily between Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Political Agency in Bahrain; and the Political Residency in Bushire. Much of the correspondence concerns two doctors who held this post, Dr Margaret M McDowall and subsequently, Dr I M A Doeg. On folios 95-99, the file contains a 1945 document entitled 'Notes for Persons Proceeding to Bahrain' that was intended as a brief introduction to the country for recently arrived foreign workers. The document contains information related to Bahrain's political structure, climate, medical facilities, language and food. The file also contains correspondence regarding a doctor named Esther Wingate who was considered as a replacement for Dr Doeg, but not eventually hired.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Medical personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>