<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001ba_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T05:15:42.089Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. ^.8, ISiS-, m MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE ICR NEGTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 4 A w a 1 i, Bahrein I sland , PsasiAN Gulf. PA-369 II if 19th AiJgust, 194B. His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent The Agency, Bahrein. ROYALTY TICKETS - JULY. 1948 File: 075.1 Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two copies each of the following Royalty Tickets:- B-632-2 to B-650-1 (inclusive) These tickets represent the total amount of Crude Oil run from tanks Nos. 131, 152 and 153 to the Refinery, upon which the Royalty for July, 194-8 will be computed, I also enclose five extra copies of the Summary of Oil Deliveries, In addition to the above, please find enclosed one copy each of the following tickets, viz:- A-1417-2 to A-L4^4-l (inclusive) These tickets represent the amount of Arabian Crude Oil run from tanks Nos, 132, 133, 134- and 143. FOR R.M. BROWN T CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Yours very truly. End tC .11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P, 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)., Date (Closing Gauges)^ 19- 19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. I TEMP. A.P.I. 1 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN - . . v- CLOSE . i 9i TANK OPEN CLOSE • | - TANK OPEN 1 • CLOSE ' 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS ■ TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. CPETROUEUM ENGINEER). By—A (REFINERY SUPERlNnSlDENT). vk By. (STATE ENGINEER).mmmsmmm The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OE TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above IDENT),The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)_ -19_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER fle SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN »n /U CLOSE 27 Qg ^5 ■ ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE ' ■ TANK OPEN .. CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By—t ! r By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENQINEER;.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form B.P. 18, ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- b wm Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- Tnlv /-fer J9_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN X23'5&amp;2,«- CLOSE syf\ 73597 r ■ ■ TANK OPEN j 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 | CLOSE | TANK OPEN • . | ' CLOSE . TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 4,991A 00 6715 S 931 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By—&lt; . L __C By. ^ / ^ /'cacrtri MCTDV ci iDtroiM ncKin^KiT) (PETROL ^EUJvl ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER;.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited For/n B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- '74.!, .19_ .19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F,. % BARRELS TANK OPEN iO'7/o 126409,. CLOSE 25 52® 99 S&amp;pi'lK T-s 1,596 TANK OPEN CLOSE | TANK OPEN • 1 CLOSE 1 . TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 00 7113 c 596 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By * ( By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER),- il c.11.' The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIl cmm OIL Form B.P. 18. No- B 637 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude OU in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION O^ NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges).-. Date (Closing Gauges)- July 7th j, July 10th -19_ I _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op- GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 5 LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A .P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN CLOSE / .... i . V •' 52473, * -3 3 ylssst M 3X^-1 3 J c 7 ... , .255 TANK OPEN CLOSE . ! TANK OPEN | CLOSE 1 • TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 35192, ( 30 4781 .255 Delivered Above Received Above '/ ..... Witaessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT KVflM&amp;Kt, By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). B y— i (REFINERY SUPERlNFEKiDENT) By. -irtr. (STATE ENGINEER).cii.*. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B,K 18. No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- J9_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES • GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. o/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE '3*? t TANK OPEN CLOSE : : TANK OPEN CLOSE j | TANK OPEN CLOSE *■ T - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By % Received Above rs (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER;.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.f*. 13. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.. Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges)- .19- _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Gc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN / / - 127102 03 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE . TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By — By (jj By (PETROUEUJyl ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER/'.C.11 .48. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]S[ 0 Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gaugea). 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel ' Gaugeg) 19 ' R (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0 / /o BARRELS TANK OPEN . ■ 66 * CLOSE }/ 3 . *71 6755&lt; TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE . ' TANK OPEN [ CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE l?U , d c 00 : ■ Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By—^ _— £ By. v / ... „ ... „ ^ ^ /otrcr i vie cav ci ioitdi w T-srWiriPKi-r^ (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTE ^bENT). (STATE ENGINEER)C.11.46. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B,P. 18. No- B 6 m*- BAHREBI CBUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- J'.. • V I'/.-' 1 ft I'Mx TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 152 OPEN 51 124.513 &gt;05 CLOSE 19 55213* ' f«;ao3 m ' 70309: 353 95 'O '^l ^0239.? # ma TANK OPEN i CLOSE i 1 TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE % TANK OPEN i I CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 702^0* ^vU Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By— (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), % ^ (REFINERY SUPERINrWibENT) 4. By. (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE tank open close open close open close ; open close total op tanks total crude Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By _4 (REFINERY SUPERINlWoENT) iC* c (STATE ENGINEER), The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.- Forrn B.P. 18. *r? r- . 'M* Vski* TsiITT lAfh AB Date (Opening Gauges) ———— 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel ( Closing Gauges) — -19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 'tank tank tank NET TONSc.11.4fe The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No — MHB i CR0I® OIL Delivered to Refinery following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) - ISt _ Date (Closing Gauges) IS * &amp;li- 19_— TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 'LES A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. WATER Gc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN - ■ - CLOSE IfW § TANK OPEN | . CLOSE | TANK OPEN | CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE * TOTAL OP TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE ill Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- {PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERlNri'i'^ENT). By. Per (STATE ENGINEER).TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- —191 Delivered Above (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). TANK A. P. I. AT 60° F. C.11.4S. Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERlNrfefiUENT). (STATE ENGINEER). A ■ —ir •' MiiimSffSf' ' OBSERVED NET TONS •ma? GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. ,00 BARRELSC.11/* The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 13. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.- Date (Opening Grauges) 19- 3r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel ( Closin g Gauges) ' ' 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. !. AT 60° F. ETC. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE 47503 . ... TANK OPEN CLOSE • ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE ' TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE o 00 103S6. 343 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT B y —— (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). ^ ^ ' (REFINERY SUPERlNrL^ENT). ^ (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.46. Form B .P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.—— Date (Opening Gauges)^^Li^ 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauge8)_^^L£_ 19— (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS | TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt; LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS tank 131 open 0-1/2 £ , 9 § eih *5 close 19 M/S -mm m 38337/ /6 1 17562.! &gt;9 ■6S 33.1 4^56 4753JJ )3 6j if - 111 tank open close ! tank open close tank open j ! close | total of tanks total crude 47515. 00 €377, 111 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT Bv By I ^ ( , By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPER1NTEMDENT). (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERlNTEwUENT). (STATE ENGINEER).' ' • ~ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET form B.P, 18. No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges)- July 24 Svlj 28 -19 -19 IB TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARREUS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0 / /o BARRELS TANK 152 OPEN A-cL . * v? BEi CLOSE 20 3 ■A % iO 35^4 96 o399-. TANK OPEN- CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 6bZ22v _J\J Delivered Above Received Alove By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERlNrejiOENT). E By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT \ &gt;: ti? (STATE ENGINEER). IT ^— ... .. ■ ■ • X . ■Form B.P. 13. c.11.46. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited B-648 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Date (Opening Gauges) !»- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude on in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons OBSERVED A. P. i. AT 60° f. GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS ^ FEET INCHES tank 153 open i 4.3 102 124243, . close M 53433. 50 100 ?6 71734- - 96 32^9 )*15 ■ 71627« 9t25'-- tank open close • tank open close ■ :&lt; . c. tank open close total of tanks * total crude 71627. 328 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. ' r&lt;- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By—^ (REFINERY SOPERINTfciibENT). ivrb E By. — (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.4fe The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P, 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIH Gmm OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS), No- 649*4 Date (Opening Gauges) «&gt;ul 3 19_ Date (Closing Gauges).... I 19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels AT 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A .P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN 43 l?c|r 87784., 86099 yj CLOSE X7 34239..;.- 21 33643. i 93 v « 703S a TANK OPEN : CLOSE . i TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 52403* •PNf 115 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUJyJ ENGINEER). By— (REFINERY SUPER1NrE .V .'dENT) By_ (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL CRUDE NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS H M ; Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No — MBSEH QRUIE OIL /f . Date (Opening Gauges) —— 2±2 19__ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons .per barrel Date (Closing Gauge8) . 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). By By. (REFINERY SIJPERINrfc ...OENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SIJPERINrt..OENT), — , (STATE ENGINEER). TANK TANK TANK l6ol5 00 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT TOTAL OF TANKSForm B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to RefinefV tlie following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPER1NTEiVOENT) I ,The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above fOENT), mmrThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B .P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- b Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges)-. JV l LY j.y _19_ _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS at 60 o F. GROSS TONS tank samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 86307*' ' CLOSE ■ Rl j Ttocv? ' % i % yy 4234^; J23 TANK OPEN . ; - CLOSE i TANK OPEN v j 1 CLOSE •S TANK OPEN ■ ' - 1 l i CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS • . TOTAL CRUDE - 3194/ tW I '■ Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). Delivered Above Received Above By By—( . 6^ B y- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERlNrO &amp;ENT).Form B.P, 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES net barrels TANK TEMP, 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROUEUM ENGINEER),r* £ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN OHuFxl OIL Form 6.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges). No. July m 5-636 July cfch J9- -19 TANK or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6e SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS observed A. P. 1. at 60° F. feet INCHES grav. a.p.i. TEMP. 0 F. % barrels TANK 153 OPEN //* ippr i 126409, 19 15/ fitK ' 3 CLOSE % 7275?-. 10 7UB6J ■7 , J J V.**. IT **' '.'13 f 52935.|93 7113. &gt;596 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE 52936. 00 7113. Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT C petroueum engineer). .. ,.. ■■ ..... ..... . I. ..I.-.-. By^__ (REFINERY SUPERINrkfioENT). By_ * htijii ^ ■ ; - - (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE INCHES TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL CRUDE GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TOTAL OF TANKS 35192^. c.ll.*. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Form fi.P. 12. Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel j) ate (Closing Gauges)—— 19_ net tons Received Aloue. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). Delivered AboveThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE AT 60°F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERlNrSibENT), (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ... -■■..yW -.f '--w 1 %The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. , TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F. grav. a.p.i. TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Ahove Delivered Above XC.11.4g. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B .P, 13. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Bmsm CHTJIE GIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSTON OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- . . 19 | 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GRO&lt; 5S BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 44. M b. ■ , 1 . 66 CLOSE in f J? /o 'iZC/-- TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 , | CLOSE , - j TANK OPEN |_ CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ■ Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By * ^ # . By. fPETROUEUM ENGINEER). ^ ' (REFINERY SUPERlNrEWDENT). (PETROLxEUM ENGINEER). ^ (REFINERY SUPERlNrEWDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).c.11.46 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B,P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel &lt;t* vijuyj? tSkySi UBM- Date (Opening Gauges) ^ 19- JtiiT l/jHi I, (WITH CON VERS, ON OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). ^ 19 - TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMI OBSERVED :&gt; LES A. P. 1. AT 60° fv WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. 1 net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE . 33o~ # w' 1 -' wn TANK OPEN •i v ■ CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i i TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS - 1 TOTAL CRUDE | Delivered Above Received Ahove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By_ By. (petroueum engineer). (REFINERY SUPERINrElNOENT), Li By- (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Forrri 6.P. 18. No- €42 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH conversion of NET BARRELS to NET tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- July L*th 4B _! 19_ Juiy lath, 48 19 tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN .01 CLOSE 1 ' .• 53681 &lt; s 933C, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN • 1 . CLOSE . - TANK OPEN j CLOSE . ■ ■ , ■ TOTAL OF TANKS 1 I i 4 TOTAL CRUDE m Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- Bv_ ( pet ro ueuivl engineer), -( - (REFINERY SUPERlNrEWbENT) By- ■—- (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES tank or line tank temp. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. „ , _ r Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Avetinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel {with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Closing Gauges) 19Delivered Above (petroleum engineer). -V .. ^.Vv • r ,.: gte- v... Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT) A.; 4 r I • tin ■■ml' filiiiin ' • m mm - C.11.46. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET 'DASmPTM ntfttTSR ATT. Porr.-, B.P, 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. TOTAL Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By— (STATE ENGINEER). NET TONS tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK OPEN TANK GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. TANK OPEN CLOSE i CLOSE : TANK CLOSE OPENThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET MHHEIH CRUDE 05L Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion OF net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES tank or line tank temp. °F. at 60 o f. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT J a 2C.11,46. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form 6.P. 18. ]\[ 0 _ MHBKIK CRSESS OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel 22sd J«iy (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges).. : . Date (Closing fta.iiges) _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED :&gt; LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. | | net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN 41 3 0-1/2 &amp; 105 mm,: 6 i CLOSE 19 11-7/8 mm 104 3$33 ! r-' fa 55.6 47515 03 I Wt* m. TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE . | TANK OPEN - 1 CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN ' CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS | TOTAL CRUDE | 47515. 00 €371: in Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- By, CPETROUEUJM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERiNrtTWDENT). ■C.'A'b; By. Fsi 1 (STATE ENGINEER;. aaThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET immm ghose oil Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)_- Date (Closing Gauges)_ No. July 'Pal ■,&gt; -19_ .19! tank or line tank gal jges gross barrels taf^k temp. 0 f. gross barrels at 60 o f. gross tons tank sam observed =i_es a. p. i. at 60° f. water &amp; sand etc. net barrels at 60°f. 1 net tons i | feet inches grav. a.p.i. TEMP. 0 f. . % barrels TANK OPEN | : i 127639 . OFTb &amp;&amp; CLOSE V // 3 w s s &amp; • •' , 32 3 9 66222. 11 Ow TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE 1 1 l TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE | 66222. DO m Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (petroueum engineer). Bv —&lt; -- (REFINERY SUPERINrErlDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).Form B.P. 13. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES net barrels AT 60 o F. TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE GRAV, A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above. Delivered Above dC.11.*. form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]s[ 0 BAHI-ffilllJ CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges)— 19 * , Delivered to Refinery tile following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel /ninaW 0*n «.) 1 A' ; st 1fl (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). ' TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 r . GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN 43 o6099. J9 CLOSE 17 100 2., 5! 55,3 93 is TANK OPEN j ■ CLOSE | • TANK OPEN 1 1 1 CLOSE 1 i , j TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 524,03 ^ 0G 703S ; 115 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. i (REFINERY SUPERINttrtOENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER;.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. JsJo Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)-. Date (Closing Granges)- Till ^ ^ ai -. ,19 43 Anf it _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS tank samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60°F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. 1 ! FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. o/ /o BARRELS , TANK 152 OPEN 1 '10 *70 i CLOSE j | . 1 i . 1 1 •- TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN | 1 CLOSE 1 • 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • fy- 2255--,! Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINf UNDENT). By_ (STATE ENGINEER).■ ■■ f ■ ' liM m l it? fnti 'i Ai'ii i 'i.1iii ' C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- No —- June 30, 19_ Ju ,19 r^o. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS 1 AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60°F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN i t h . CLOSE tt i 1 52225., &amp; 72421* ''XX TANK OPEN i i CLOSE ■■ TANK OPEN CLOSE 6391. TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 52716, 00 6391, .265 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT J J By- —__ (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. -c (REFINERY SUPERINm..OENT). 1L. By- (STATE ENGINEER). —:C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form b .P. 13. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AMBIAH CISJ® OIL No. A 1418 Delivered to Refiliety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- me 30 July 2 I9r \ _I9 1 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 0 F. f net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 43 CLOSE 20 ; 10-3 A 59397* 37 64549c 69 2 00 37,-5 10 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN 1 1 CLOSE 1 i | TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS -• TOTAL CRUDE 63363* 00 3233. 141 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. Arabian Arnertcan OH C q » (PETROUEUW ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERlNTfenDENT) By. (STATE ENGINEER). 1 - C fc ■ ■ s ^ —The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges)——« —— 19 Date (Closing Gauges) — 19—.— Delivered to RefinerV the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP, 0 F, TANK OR LINE net tons at 60 0 F. INCHES TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERlNTt...OENT)mas&amp;tT: ' ^ J ■■■■■.■ - . . ■ ■■ -ftr-'' C.11.-45. The Bahtein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.f 3 . 10. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Arabian Grudo OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). NO- Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- -19- -19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS i AT 60 o F*. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 44- 99 125343&lt;?S CLOSE li 52391** 73- 6 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE . i TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE i 1 i TANK OPEN CLOSE — ■ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE / 73764J )0 ■ 96/&gt;S a 560 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT tr f-^y C petrqueum engineer). By. (REFINERY SUPERlNlfeoENT) By. For (STATE ENGINEER). ^ Ifiini-. -W-.ni ■---*€MtoaiiMiii Miiiltti : ■■•m C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET .mBimi CISIDE OIL form B.P. 13. No. A 1421 Date (Opening Gauges)—_——ri- Deliveied to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19 43 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt; LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER 8i SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /0 BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 10 •• 124267 29 . f CLOSE X/ 9-1/4 50562,; r) 49834c ! S9 74432. |i- TANK OPEN t CLOSE , TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 1 TANK C ? ■ - OPEN i 1 1 CLOSE \ TOTAL OF TANKS | TOTAL CRUDE 7435-3 a ! )0 9714^ 895 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Arabian iunerican (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTv, .DENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER). L I ■■ p'..-- i- - ' , ■iiittni- - 'r. ^ ■Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET O.ulIE Olij Delivered to Refinery, the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). •Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN imgguB. 52437:'^ CLOSE]! TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPER1NI — ■iDENT), . . .r-i.f.. v 'C.11,45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f i , ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARiBiiii CEiian: oil Delivered to Refinety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Form B.P. 13. Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). No.-AM23__ ; — 19. .In lj 4 -19. 48 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS FEET INCHES TANK 132 OPEN JL 70 86961. - 1 i 1 CLOSE 14 3-3/4- ^90X2^ yj^f 90 23614# 5? i ; 50346,. 100 % 1 ^ 5C259. 7615, TANK OPEN CLOSE | TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE TANK OPEN | 1 , CLOSE l j i ! - ' | TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 1 53259, 30 7615 .917 By— Delivered Above Arabian aiiierican (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), By Received Above Jtl. (REFINERY SUPERlNrtEiDENT). By. ■iipiipi! L Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER).WATER &amp; SAND ETC. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE 71563U77 71643.^0 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AHABIAH CIT DE OIL form B.P, IS. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude on in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). ]S^ 0 July_4» ig43_ .July $3 TANK 71.63 TANK SAMPLES 71562*1)0 9372, Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT A. P. I. AT 60° F. C.11.45. Bv ^ —— 1.- — (PETROU^ENG.NEER).' ' (REFINERY SUPER .n ^DENT). OBSERVED Delivered Above TEMP. 0 F. Received Abovetank samples TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL CRUDE C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 13. ft 1 /. ii j Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- JulT Delivered Above (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). TANK OR LINE TANK TANK TANK |j OPEN CLOSE ' ' • I III . 'll . I ' ' ^ TANK jj OPEN j CLOSE | TOTAL I OF TANKS | Received Alow Witnessed'for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERlNftWoENT) {STATE ENGINEER). - .,r V-V-^rfTANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL Delivered Above Beceived AboVe Tty • _ ' f' ———- (REFINERY SUPERINfe^DENT). (PETROUEUiyI ENGINEER). &gt; TOTAL OF TANKS Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^orm B.P. 13. 19- CRUDE Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO MET TONS).The Bahrein Petrojeum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINr6«DENT). ^ - ^ - —j.— -- — ■ ■—.— —The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AMBIM1 CHIDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. TANK TEMP. TANK or LINE net tons TANK OPEN CLOSE 11679 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OE TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (petroleum engineer),-&gt; - mmmmmmSmM C.11,15. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. ABABIAH CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges), No._ 19__ -19— TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. j FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 10-3/4 120442 % 113031,? CLOSE 17 4.933?.: 69176^ 100 mjL m TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN I CLOSE m - TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 69176 W C 9043^ !Q4 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT 'Ry Arabian American nil Ho. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By HBHEBHBBHHHHI —— ' .. &gt; ' - Z 1 ' {'■ v s / (REFINERY SUPERlNrENDENT). By, For (STATE ENGINEER). - .J. 'r-ini'^. i -- r 1 ' i rTTff-nr—^-The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET mmm gmjee oil Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK samples TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE A. P. 1 AT 60° F. at 60°F, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPER1Igmm mmmmmmmmmm Form B.I 3 . 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refiliety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F, TANK OPEN 26892. CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above VHHIc.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery tlle following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)^ Date (Closing Gauges). ___ -19- Ifl TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o f. GROSS TONS TANK samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° f. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 f. % BARRELS TANK OPEN U i 126712., . 25 CLOSE 12 1 ci i . h ?^L, w &lt;2 TANK OPEN | CLOSE ' J TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE I 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE BBQJ3. i 11597.. 967 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By , ; ^ By tPETTROLEUM ENGINEER). './f (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER;.C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 6.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- 9th , i July 11th 19 48 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 4 r/ 1196??., 36 CLOSE 14. 4.0051. 76 ^ 4X5226, 73 X(¥ r w c TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN - CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS J TOTAL CRUDE 79372 00 10369. 910 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By i : —— By . — By , ^ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ./-f (REFINERY SUPERIHTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).Form B.P. 13. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAH CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges), Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinetv the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE at 60°F. AT 60 0 F TANK OPEN CLOSE 87433. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROUEUW ENGINEER),; uM- The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery tile following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges).. Date (Closing Gauges)- No. A U35 Juiy lOy-194^. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMf OBSERVED ^LES A. P. I. AT 60° f. WATER Be SAND ETC. net barrels AT 60 o f. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 f. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN 43 10 S75S7J .0 97 s&amp;m , - i 1 ! CLOSE 6 0* lU99*i 4 94 1131a. &lt;; 1 .6 105 37 6 74 0 .77 74695 s 69 975^.992 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 i ! | : 1 TANK OPEN i CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 74% 00 975% : m Delioered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- n c G, (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- M- (REFINERY SUPERINrEN6ENT). Fttr {STATE ENGINEER;. -- -■msjSS&amp;iM X : I C.11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Form 6 .p. 18. No- A U36 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- July 11, ia 48 Date (Closing Gauges)— July 13, TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET inches GRAV. A.P .i. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN 44 3 127253, 79 103 12475. 62 CLOSE 8 &amp;J- 24258 ,31 93 23892, 01 a 40o0 93 37,5 oa 100 c , 87 100766 ( j74 13172 ,732 TANK OPEN CLOSE | TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE 1 i • TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • 100767 ,00 13172 .732 Delivered Above By- Arabian American Oil Co, C petroueum engineer). By. —tr HHHHHHDS Received Above Jk lU- (refinery superintendent). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT I'O'f (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 13. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.- Delivered to Refinety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)„ Date (Closing Gauges)- „19- _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F, GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o f. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 f. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN 43 CLOSE ' : 9 f\ f\ TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS i TOTAL CRUDE ! 102045* . Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- .j X. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ (state engineer). Foxc.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET mmmi mm oil Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges) I_r] ■rul: I4,th, Date (Closing Gauges) 19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt;les A. A 60° *. 1. T F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK XL?. OPEN ArJ 4-1/4 ■*3 CLOSE i ; , v . .. ..., ' 50 316010.5 5 g , TANK OPEN j ! CLOSE | 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE | ■ ■ i TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ' 9100 ,00 Delivered Above Received Above imbian Amoriean Oil So (petroueum engineer). By. (refinery superintendent). By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (state engineer). m - v -- - —ia^rT»-a*g - - , -v..r —''i '- , C.11.45. ¥ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUISE OIL form B.P. IS. No- A 1439 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude on in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). J^oly 15th, 19 AB J uly 15th, ig AB 1 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES j GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS j AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMP OBSERVED LES A. P. J. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS 1 FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK | 132 OPEN : 7 39093 - 1 95 87648, 61 | 1 CLOSE 1 6 10 -1/ 13115 99 12879. 25 - 1 74769, 37J 71769^ 36 976? „ ji.7 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - - TANK OPEN CLOSE s 1 TOTAL OF T ANTICS | TOTAL CRUDE • 1 74769. OO | 976 |,617 By- Delivered Above Arabian AiaBricarx Oil, 0 Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), By. X (refinery superintendent). By- far (state engineer).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES tank temp. 0 F, tank or line grav. i temp. a.p.i, j °F. inches TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Abovenet barrels at 60 0 f. TANK GAUGES tank temp. 0 f. net tons tank or line TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE GROSS TONS e .-, i Above Witaessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Delivered Above Received Above (petroueum engineer). By. ^ — — * * ^ s—* — .—.. .r-nw inrr-niwi T-Ck.ir-\crKI'r''l (REFIN E r y SUPERiNFENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). | , |, m ■ - ' ■' • * . ' •—— — — TANK SAMPLES &amp;*fQt Jo. 00 m75c The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form b.p. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No ...IW JuXT X/i-liha , Date (Opening Grauges) ———— —19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude OH in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19- (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). a. p. 1. at 60° f. TANK observed TOTAL CRUDE grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. TOTAL OF TANKS■ -' •. . . , ■ „t Mminliaw Form 6.P. 13. C.ll.*. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AMBIAH CT?.UDS OIL Delivered to Refiner&gt;' ^lic following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- No July ISth .19 iaM TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. gross tons tank samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° f. GRAV. a.p.i. TEMP. 0 f. o/ /o BARRELS feet inches TANK i4._&gt; OPEN 121317 • . J CLOSE 18 37 52179.? a37j 5 i 4JO # S 102 37®6 69065,C 1 ^ - to (JO TANK OPEN ' CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE | 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE • TOTAL OF TANKS i ' j • 1 1 ■ 1 1 TOTAL CRUDE - 6906S o 9023, 736 I By. Delivered Above Arabian American Oil {PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- ■-l.* ■ 'J. i • ■ Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). - y MThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). tank samples TANK GAUGES tank or line GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. tank temp. 0 f. A. P. I at 60° f, at 60 o f. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Arabian American Oil Co. (petroleum engineer).C.11.-4S. Form B.P, 13. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET A \IJA Arabian Crude Oil _ . /rt Date (Opening Gauges) ' ' 19_L- Dellvered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TON ^V Date (ClOSUlg GaUgOS) ; ^ tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM OBSERVED PUES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS j FEET inches grav. a.p.i. TEMP. 0 F. o/ /o barrels TANK 133 OPEN 4J (y^/B 125176. 1224.34a ( &gt;9 CLOSE 17489a. ur 171i5 «5 105319. •9i&gt; 37,5 105.32 1052U.J. &gt;3 TANK OPEN CLOSE i TANK OPEN i CLOSE | TANK OPEN . CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ' ■ TOTAL CRUDE i 1 | 105.115: ' »0 13754®: LS:? Delivered Above Received Alove • Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By v By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), ' (REFINERY SUPERINPENDENT). (STAjTE ENGINEER;.- The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). tank samples TANK GAUGES tank or line tank temp. 0 f. TANK 124477® Si OPEN CLOSE 12050 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Aleve Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENTI Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRlFSiS OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. tank temp. tank or line TANK OPEN 17384 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivertd Above tpetroueum engineer),Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AMBIM CBJJPB OIL Delivered to Refinety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES tank temp. tank or line net tons AT 60 o F, L lauuk TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening fta.ngftg) 20th Ju3.y» Date (Closing Gauges) d. ^ ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION of NET barrels to net tons). TANK SAMPLES water a sand etc. tank gauges TANK TEMP. °f. TANK OR LINE grav. a.p.i. TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Dtlivtrtid. Above ■ ' *—C .11.4s. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form b .P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinerv the following Grade Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WtTH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No. A-U51 Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Glosing Gauges)-, 223d July, 24th July, A8. -19 .19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Se SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0 / /o BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN A3 876/0 .98 104 85908 .79 GLOSE 12 l«3/« 23734 .91 95 23355 .15 - 62553 M 39e7 89 37 o5 OoO! &gt; 31028 62522 &lt;&gt;36 8173 „236 TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ' 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE j TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE ♦ 62525 ;.on | 81T lo236 Delivered Above Received Alovt By- By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). r A (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). MMa f^aaMaM iThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. A ARABIAN 0E1JI3E OIL Date (Opening Gauges)—— 19^_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges)— ^ Jvl?,. 19__- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. o/ /o BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN I t ?c»1 /? 127133, k/v v^on7 85 TQ j ■ 1 CLOSE 19 // 40^ 95 HJs 90..^ &lt;J055A, a 9% TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN • CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE 1 . | -fOTAl OF TANKS &gt; TOTAL CRUDE 1 1 00 1 11810 —— Delivered Above Bv— ^ ... J {PETROLEUM ENGINEER), Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By ^—- ^■- 7 * tw I &gt;. ir-r-tw r--l l »-»rr r-&gt; IWI T-crvl ncMT' 1 (REFINERY SUPERINrENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).v mmmm: riiMiiirtiiiriri fiin c.n.^s. I &lt;' ' \ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude. Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Form B.P. 18. No.-*^453 \ \ Date (Opening Gauges) 2jj^d 19- Date (Closing TANK OR LINE i TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS j TANK SAMP OBSERVED LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS ' TANK . 131 OPEN //i L 120£^ im .27 CLOSE - &amp; © =1/ *&gt;9 1^7 / ! Q/.IQI 1 o .s 9A 19 faT.. 12300 92? TANK OPEN CLOSE ! TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE j r TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS l ! TOTAL CRUDE 9409 S©00 1 1230c o923 V \x..- By- Delivered Above (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). Received Above By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. 0 f. GRAV. A.P.I. OPEN 126Z18-^ CLOSE OPEN TANK TANK TOTAL NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS 981% ^9 12841.498 TANK OR LINE CLOSE CRUDE &lt;m.r?*vQ C.11.45 form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No A ' TANK CLOSE OPEN ARABIAN CRD EE OIL Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)J—ft — Date (Closing Gauges) . : CLOSE i OPEN Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (petroueum engineer). B y- j*S-_ (REFINEHY SUPERINTENDENT), By. (STATE ENGINEER).c.11.45. The Bahtein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered to Refinery following Grade Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). _19- _19_ tank or line tank gauges gross barrels tank temp. 0 f. gross barre:ls at 60 o f. gross tons tank samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o f. NET TONS observed A. P. I. AT 60° f. feet inches grav. a.p.i. TEMP. 0 f. % barrels TANK OPEN . CLOSE * M0 b5 TANK OPEN • CLOSE . ■ • • TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Heceived Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By .— By € By (PETROUEUM engineer). * (REFINERY SUPERINfENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f : orni B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAH OBSm OIL Date (Opening Gauges) july 27^ 1 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) ,19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). X 0 b ' TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMf OBSERVED 3 les A. P. I. AT 60° f. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60°f. net tons 1 FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 p. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 143 OPEN 37 &gt;*l/b 107823, 39 1Q4 105661a D4 1 CLOSE 5 L1-7/S 16595, ■ • 16299® 33 i ■ - / 116' TANK OPEN CLOSE . TANK OPEN ' CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 39272, 00 11676, 75s Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By (/f . H By I (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), (STATE ENGINEER).^m A mmm y'^ C.I1.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. N q.^ MS, imwm ortj ® on- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrel.s to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges) g;', Date (Closing Gauges) tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF observed 3 LES a. p. 1. at 60° F. water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. % barrels TANK 13* OPEN 39 5&gt; 77387. 79 CLOSE 0 15717. 42 15437-... 6? . 61950 1 8093. 432 TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN J CLOSE J ' TANK OPEN CLOSE | \ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 61950 00 8998, Dtlivered Above Received Aloof. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By ] II . , (pettroleujm engineer). By sk , iniTMlii (refinery superintendent). By.- ■\1 ror (state engineer). A. ■, . : ^ r_ '- ' ' 'C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET form B.P, 18. No —- fCABmt cswur; ijt Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). rfTrtf) 19— Date (Closing Gauges) .19—^ TANK OR UNE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED *LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK l.:- OPEN jty ff , CLOSE ft Mi i ft TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE , TANK OPEN CLOSE TO 'tAt OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE mS65*{ 50 : . Dtlivtred Abovt By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). %' ' HH 1.—- ,■ - . Received Ahove b y—c- (REFINERY SUPERINrENDENT). By, Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT For (STATE ENGINEER). 1i m s m:' ■&gt; C.11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. No- Dclivcrcd to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- -19- *2A .19- TANK OR i-INE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMP OBSERVED LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATE E: R &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN H'tSlT. CLOSE 18662L. 18337 22 1 oo i fit TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ ' TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 95335. 12471 By. Delivered Above AraMan Ajaorlcan Oil Go, Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT &lt;PETROI-EUM ENGINEER). By—c- ■1 (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). — i . .. --A.C. 11.4V The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 6 .p. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No — ABABIM CRUDE CXL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)_ JEoly i i9_L&gt; Joly _19. 48 TANK or LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF observed 'LES A. P. 1. at 60° F. water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS feet INCHES grav. a.p.i. temp. °F. 0 / /o barrels tank U3 open T7 1071914 10504^ ~ 1C . close 7 &lt;5 21705 mm tank open close ! 1 tank open ! 1 ' | close | tank open close T 6t A l of tanks total crude OJRJ f\ &gt;^00 1096: Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- . (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By •' L (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), By. (STATE ENGINEER).c.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P, 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AmiICMJ GHOUJ OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No. i v/tf- Date (Opening Gauges) Jnly gO— Date (Closing Gauges) Mxi? ; -r— -19-^- -19_4g_ TANK or LINE tank gauges gross barrels TANK TEMP. 0 F. gross barrels at 60 o f. gross tons tank samples water Be sand etc. NET BARRELS at 60°f. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° f. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .i. temp. 0 f. % barrels TANK 132 OPEN 43 87336* 102 ;* CLOSE 5 6-5/'; 10512. 19 '96 2^ T?/. TANK OPEN CLOSE i TANK OPEN i ! | ^ CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS . TOTAL CRUDE 75255, ,00 9337 ,724 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By - By. f i_ ( By (PETROl-eUM ENGINEER). ' 'v, (refinery superinrendent). (state engineer).Form b .P. 18. c.i 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. - Date (Opening Gauges)—i.—^—IL. 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing G^uge8)_JiLZL-—Lt— -19 43 (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). tank or LINE ! TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS tank samples water &amp; sand etc. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons observed a. p. 1. at 60° f. feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. % barrels tank 133 open ' 77 1 97 . close 22 tx ■ ■ 96 6335-' '91 40126 ' tank open ■ ' ■ ' close tank open close - tank open' 1 close total of tanks . — total crude 40037' 524- 34^ Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENTPOLITICAL AuE'JCY, BAliEAIN. . Ko. 34^12-23/5 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments tos The Adviser to the Bahrain Ciovernment, Bahrain, and has the honour to sand him a copy of the under- mentioned document. Dated the 31st August 1948, KitfCLOSURS Suiamary of Oil Deliveries for July 1948. SUBJECT BO'iALTY TICKETS I• I' ■HH K r 0 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ^bZ2 ; j. .. A L -I-5 Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 20th September, 1 C M£. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, The Agency, 1 ^ Bahrein. ; i - x vAh. 'V Bli i ^ k ^OY/lLTY TIGIC JTS - .MJGUST 194. ' ' FILS: #075.1 Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two copies each of the following Royalty B-649-2 to B-668-1 (inclusive) Tickets These tickets represent the total amount of Crude Oil run from , tallies lies. 131, 152 and 153 to the Refinery, upon which the .loyalty for August, 194-3, will be computed. I also enclose five extra copies of the Summary of Oil Deliveries. In addition to the above, please find enclosed one copy each of the following tickets, viz.; A-14.64.-2 to A-l 511-1 (inclusive) These tickets■ represent the amount of Arabian Crude Oil run from tanks Nos. 132, 133, 134 and 143. Yours very truly. ittach; For R. M. BR0WI CHIEF LOCAL REPRESEI^ITATIVS THE BAIIREIK PETROLEDM COITAIIY LrUTED mHi The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. tank temp. tank or line A. P. I AT 60° F. TANK OPEN 34197 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. tank temp. 0 f, tank or line tank open close:. .4 a 0 11257&lt;,(794 tank open close tank open tank open close total of tanks total crude Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. ^ ^ BAHREIN CRUDE OIL ... 3Igt July _ 1( f8 Date (Opening Gauges)- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude on in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel ^ (Closing Gauges )_J?!l--— 19— (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Delivered Above / Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ( t &gt;,. Bv By— WctT ijy ■' - ' (REFINERY SUPERlNrENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER;. (petroleum engineer).— m .. 4f! w ,■ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). tank samples tank gauges tank temp. 0 f. tank or line grav, a.p.i. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ! TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered AboveDBBHUHHi RPHMPhpII C.UM. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET B4.HREIM CRUDS OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No- B 652 Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). 4th August jAS 7th August j &lt;£8 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. °F. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN A4 0,1/8 87889. 18 86087 a 45 CLOSE 16 1 lo5/8 33503 ( 93 103 32877, 41 1 i 34.9 32.7 0,1 53o21 1156, 7152 .251 TANK OPEN | CLOSE 1 ; TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN | CLOSE . TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - 53157 ,00 7152 .251 Delivered Above Received Ahove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- ( ( &gt; (REFINERY SUPER1NTENDENT). By.. ror (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHKEIH CRUDS OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). tank samples TANK GAUGES tank or line tank temp. 0 f. net tons at 60 o f. TANK OPEN 42233 — CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT a . raw.; .'It'1' 11 i-L^C.11.46. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form b .P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No BAHREIN CRUDE OIL 7th August A&amp; Date (Opening Gauges)— —_—__ 19-— Delivered to Refiner V the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ^ Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt; LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 153 OPEN 29 T - -1 . 9J 40 I i - CLOSE 14, *7 fy 4.0670 ,45 42646; ,95 1 1 32c9 0.1 42 o65 42604o; 5725 ,219 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN ! CLOSE I TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 42604® DO 5725, Delivered Above Received Above • Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ( r ) • ; Bv By By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), , (STATE ENGINEER).Form B.P, 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges), Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Reifinety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). 10th August TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. tank temp. NET BARRELS tank or line GROSS TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnesaed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (petroleum engineer), i'i 'jgiJS i'SFB BS'SgiTC.I MS. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. royalty delivery M BHm 3Rm OIL Delivered to Refinery tile following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per (with conversion of net barrels to net tons), ticket No Date (Opening Gauges) 1 ft Date (Closing Gauges) 19J±_ TANK or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS y . ' .' tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMI observed 'LES a. p. I. at 60° F. water 8e sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. % barrels TANK 152 OPEN CLOSE 13 An • L(&amp;2*, 0*5 % 33 &gt;26 «,226 TANK OPEN CLOSE • TANK OPEN \ i CLOSE • TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS &gt; TOTAL CRUDE ■ 4-5353 .00 6091 226 Delivered Above Received Above \ Witnessed for BAHHEIN GOVERNMENT r , # c^l By — By By. (petroleum engineer). (refinery superintendent). (state engineer).I C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to NET tons). No- B 657 Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Date (Closing Gauges). 19 _ tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o f. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o f. NET TONS observed a. p. i. at 60° f. feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. 0/ /o barrels TANK 153 OPEN 1-31 6.7/8 97 104 44 CLOSE i 11.3/8 39582. 105 1 ■ ^ / OO A ,128 TANK OPEN CLOSE i 1 1 TANK OPEN ■' | 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ ' i 1 TOTAL OF TANKS j TOTAL CRUDE | 51071 ,00 6859 ,128 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT r (petroleum engineer). By- ( 1 (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By.. P ot (STATE ENGINEER). 'V' /: tarn ^ ^v. -—i- : ■■ i —————— TThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited C ROYALTY DELI VER\ TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE DIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). 15th kngaat TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (refinery superintendent), (state engineer)Form B.P. 18. Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHKBIH CRtm OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 19 TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. AT 60 o F. AT 60°F. TEMP. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). — J- ..r a..',. - illWmAilM,' tiai;- • 7 IN ■ 'i • MIM 'TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR U1NE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OE TANKS TOTAL CRUDE NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o r. TANK SAMPLES WATER a SAND ETC. GROSS TONS BARRELS TANK '70i; : -.656 A. P. I. AT 60° F. TANK Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHHEIN GOVERNMENT OBSERVED 78.45 C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CR T JBS OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel 1)ate (Closing Gauges) (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). ^ ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By / „ — — . V 1»—r-1 I nr-n I kl-T-rr I~\rr KJ 'fl B} (STATE ENGINEER). TEMP. 0 F. Form 6.P. 18.C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. (( ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET BAHgglg GEUD S OIL Date (Opening Gauges)— 1ft Delivered to Refinery t' 16 following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (OloRino- 10 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). — 1&gt; TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. | NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. I | FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS TANK OPEN ' 1% mJfy 1 CLOSE 1 * . ■ j ^ TANK OPEN i CLOSE TANK OPEN : CLOSE ! TANK OPEN CLOSE , , TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE | • • Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY superintendent). (state ENGINEER).Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROLeUM ENGINEER),Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f ROYALTY DELIVERY ( TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE AT 60°F, GRAV. A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OR LINE TANK TANK TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL OPEN CLOSE CRUDE GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP, °f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. TONS C.11,45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited C ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET ]Sf 0 Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refinery following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closinff Gauges) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 c Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIK GOVERNMENT By By By &gt; (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). &lt;STATE ENGINEER). OPEN | CLOSE A. P. I. AT 60° F. NET OBSERVED BARRELS GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F.I i I !l toForm B.P. 18 Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refiliefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Abovi Delivered Above (state engineer).TANK SAMPLES WATER a SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above C.1MS The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERV TICKET No Tl&amp;TTt5T?TW ATT ■ Date (Opening Gauges)— — 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges)-____ 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS).■ Form B.P. 18 Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DEL1VERV TICKET Bahrein emm OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F, AT 60 o F, TANK OPEN 11176C CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), rrfTMhiilrf- .c.n .4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form b.p. 18. ROYALTY DELIVER&lt; TICKET xt„ B 649 B&amp;HRBIN «Rl IE OIL NO 30th July 48 1 . , t &gt; /* Date (Opening Gauges) 19 JJellvered to Kennery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel jy! August (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Closing Gauges) — 19 tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM observed PLES a. p. i. at 60° F. water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. 1 NET TONS feet inches grav. a.p.i, temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK 131 OPEN 43 Hi 87784. 86 86099. 39 CLOSE 17 31 34197v 03 33571 22 i ■ 52528 17 35o3 93 33 78.79 52449 to 7044 ^280 TANK OPEN CLOSE • j ; ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE - 46 .38 6 |a65 TANK OPEN ; CLOSE TOTAL | OF TANKS| TOTAL CRUDE | 46 .00 6 a 165 Delivered Above Received Alove. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By (petroueum ENGINEER). (refinery superintendent). ' ' fot (state ENGINEERj.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. NET TONS TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered AboveThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^. TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °K. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN j CLOSE TANK CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),TANK SAMPLES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. A. P. I AT 60° F. GROSS TONS TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F. 86087 TANK OPEN {44 CLOSE {16 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE ! OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIK C40VERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER!. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No— BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) A^L- — Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ( Closin g Gauges) 7tn 1^: — {WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Received Above TANK TANK Delivered AboveTANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE 60783oD7 OPEN CLOSE I OPEN CLOSE I OPEN CLOSE TOTAL TANK TANK CRUDE NET TONS C.11.*. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERS TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- Form B.P. 18. B 653 6th Augoat 8th Auguat i g 48 Received Aleve (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). TOTAL 0E TANKS Delivered Above (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). TANKclose NET BARRELS AT 60°F. 42604o?0~ 42604.DO Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER 1 ? TICKET ]&lt;[ 0 B BAHREIN CRUDE OIL 7th August Date (Opening Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel _ _ „ J Date (Closing Gauges) It (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ■ . v v ^ By By— — — By (PETROUEUW ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). * (STATE ENGINEER). TANK OR LINE tank 153 tank tank tank total of tanks total TANK GAUGES close | crude GROSS BARRELS 84983J 57 4U28c 59 TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. 83317 40670 42646 GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES OBSERVED A. P. 1. GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. % BARRELS 42o65 NET TONS 5725.219 5725®219 FEET INCHES open close ; open open i open | closeG.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form b .P. 18. 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No.-_L_ BAHREIN CRUDS OIL Date (Opening Gauges) ^th August 19 4.8 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 10th August ^ 4 ,8 {WITH CONVERSION OF NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES water Be sand etc. NET BARRELS NET TONS observed a. p. r. at 60° F. FEET INCHES grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 F. 0/ /o barrels AT 60 o F TANK 131 OPEN 33 66575o 16 104 CLOSE L 28062o 49 104 38512o 67 37773 o23 35 o2 93 32o9 0 o l 37.77 37735 O46 5070, 938 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS • N TOTAL CRUDE 3773* 8 o 507{ io938 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By_ (PETROL-SUM ENGINEER). By_ (refinery superintendent). By. (state engineer).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL lOthAugust I q 4-8 Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). 12th August TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. tank temp. 0 F, TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered AboveThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DEUVER4 TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL 12th August ^ 4-8 in Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 r. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F. TANK OPEN CLOSE 51070 51147 TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER),3 • Form B.P. 18 C.11.4S Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ll ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS TANK GAUGES tank temp. 0 F. tank or line AT 60 o F grav, a.p.i. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Atove Delivered Above jr'The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET BAHRSIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. tank temp. 'F. T ank or line TANK OPEN 6 X 3 0 3 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received. Above Delivered Above (state engineer),C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET M q B 660 MHRSIIj CRTJDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) lO^iL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) I9tl: Al;y'USt ifl A ' (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES i GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARREUS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F, % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK 153 OPEN ?7 7,7/8 79367 . 77 102 77931c 21 CLOSE Vt Oc5/3 39884&lt; 65 98 39230 5A 38700 , ,67 92 32o2 77 c 40 38623 a 27 5212 o693 TANK OPEN - CLOSE — - 1 TANK OPEN i CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN • CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 38623 00 521; cn o 0 — M — Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROL.EUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C,11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No - Form B.P. 18. BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) 19. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 1 0 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). I TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 c&gt; f. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt;LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS FEET inches GRAV. A.P.I, TEMP, of. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN 8:5/8 87304 7, ais 85558 : CLOSE 17 jS. JJoOl ^05 101 33258 ^32 • 52299 35e4 94 33 cO Ocli 52221 .37 701: ..656 TANK OPEN ' i ■ CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN . 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ♦ TOTAL CRUDE 52221 -,00 701: &lt;&gt;656 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By —— —— J ■ rrKI/—• iMLTcCD i (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).^2 C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- No- i9th 5 -19„ -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. °F. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN - CLOSE . TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 i CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TOTAL | OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Deiivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- By, (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). CREFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By, (STATE ENGINEER). VOj&gt; c.11.4s, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. No. B 663 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with comversron of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- ■U -ae &amp; ' -19- 27th k&amp; -19- tank or uine tank gauges gross barrels tank temp. 0 f. gross barrels at 60 o f. gross tons j tank samp observed les a. p. 1. at 60° f. water &amp; sand etc. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. % barrels feet inches TANK OPEN j 1 CLOSE 3&amp;o9i 1 3s. 01 c f O TANK OPEN j CLOSE ■ 1, t t TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 1 CLOSE | | 1 TOTAL OF TANKS t ■ , f-' [ TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above By- &lt;petrol,eum engineer). Bv, Bv. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). i m KC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18 No.—— Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) ; 19- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. 1 TEMP. A.P.I. 1 0 F. &lt;v /O BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ' CLOSE ! 1 . TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ 1 i ; | ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above By_ By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER).C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET form B.P. 18. No Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refiner v th® following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ^ . J Date (Closing Gauges) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I, AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A. P.*. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i I j I I TANK OPEN ! . | I CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ' By (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). Delivered Above By -— By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER).Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Aiove Delivered AboveCI 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERV TICKET Form B.P. 18 No Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closillg G aU g es ) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt; LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN | CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE V J TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE I TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ II TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 1 1 Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ' ' By (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER), Delivered Above By By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE OPEN | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE NET TONS TANK NET BARRELS AT 60° F'. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Form B.P. 18 Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C1M5. form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited it (jx ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET N 0 Date (Opening Giauges) I Jt ,1% 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel , 1A Date (Closing Gauges) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Gc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 105264 ' 7*9 CLOSE TTBBSc nn ? O. - ' TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE i TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS | i TOTAL CRUDE 00 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER!.Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION Or NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE A. P. 1 AT 60° F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Aleve Delivered Above (PETROLEyjM ENGINEER). 4C.11.45. \ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No 4S4BIA1 CRiBBOIL &gt; « c.:.' ■&gt; r- /ca&gt;ss&lt;'*Bc;«S4-W- . Date (Opening Gauges) ' Hl—j 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19-— (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR UINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /O BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 9 m ' CLOSE 7 . I- . 68 - TANK OPEN CLOSE . . TANK OPEN • CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE , TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 00 8974, 620 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Tw Bv By. * ' '' ' ' .. . ^ fOPTTlMPRV ejUPFRlMrPWDENX). (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERlNfENDENT). (STATE ENCINECR).C .11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( &lt;5 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET ]SJ 0 Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel , J Date Closing Gauges) ! 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN #7083. sfj CLOSE 7 13723 • . ' - m )ol TANK OPEN . ' • CLOSE | ! TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ■ | CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 52198,) 90 01 Delivered Above py (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). Received Aleve Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By - By„ —,— (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE CNGtNEER).C.11.45. form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited X ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No — Ara lBUM CMIDJS OIL Date (Opening Gauges), : 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS | TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /O BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN &gt;78 1187%. ,81 1 | I CLOSE 16703 M ,29 102420 .52 1 !9 a 8 94 51o21 TANK OPEN i I CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 1 ' CLOSE | 1 1 | ' | TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 102369 30 13407. Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT 1MBI&amp;S AMERICA# OIL COWPkM: (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By.wm ■nil mmm . ? m mmm C.II.^S The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited C C ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 1011 36 0 CLOSE • 59 TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE 1 . I j TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN , CLOSE &gt; TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ^5?43 ,00 ■ - ' Delivered Above By- Arabian Asstxc (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- Beceived Above (REFINERV SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). ' ti urmnririiil It0.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( C ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET NQ. Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) | — 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR UINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt;LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE // !.(•'* 72 TANK OPEN | CLOSE ' ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE . TANK OPEN CLOSE ' * TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C 11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited # C ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No BUM CHIB£ OIL » JL if to Date (Opening Grauges) —____ li_- 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN 7376$- ^ ft CLOSE 6 11618. Sit 67150c 73 40o- TO ? / ' yfy i [q Qqi TANK OPEN ■ . CLOSE | i I TANK OPEN / CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 1 •S .00 8778 &amp; Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT B V By By. ^ . —... . ('cpcrmKjp-ov CII ipfrimrFKinPNTV (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ' (STATE ENGINEER).Form 6.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) I9i_ Date (Closing Gauges) 1__ 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS 97891 OO TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Aleve Delivered Aboveform B.f*. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ti m ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET oth Augasti Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges), Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREL.S TO NET TONS). barrel TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT 4MBI4M amnickn oil coMP4inrC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET AMBIkn CRSDS OIL Form B.f 1 . 18. No Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges),. Date (Closing ■ ■ -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 143 OPEN 1069530 35 CLOSE 5 6o3/8 *5264o 03 103 ^o5 36 7 TANK OPEN | CLOSE ■ 1 I TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 89698., 00 11781. 219 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By (PETTROUEUM ENGINEER), By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. FOP (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ii % ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ^0- Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) —,1 19. Ddivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) — 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT .60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN ' ' CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ! | CLOSE | ' TANK OPEN CLOSE / TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 71430^ 50 ggNg &gt;12 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUW ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited w % ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET N 0 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Form B.P. 13. Date (Opening Gauges) -19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) — ISL TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER Se SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN CLOSE ** 'M rr .i f7 L TANK OPEN CLOSE l | TANK OPEN • CLOSE TANK OPEN j CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 106532. 00 13934 345 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By_ (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER;.C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited a % ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ' ]S[ 0 Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Granges) -—--—1. 19_ Delivered to Refiner}^ the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel ^'In^no- Pa,,^ !« (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F, GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN CLOSE &amp; o 19 . $89 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN | | CLOSE ! i 1 1 TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ! TOTAL CRUDE • 84119 DO 11016 983 Delivered Above Received Above Witnesaed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By ^ (PiTTROUEUM ENC3INEER). By_ •&gt; J*? 1 '' &gt;- ' - ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. — (STATE ENGINEER).' I n ■ . ^ r ,-^ . .. ^ .fe .. . ... . , • C.11.-45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited t V ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 13. No- i im Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). in .19. Oth ftsgoftt ig 4^ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN 24 V . CLOSE X'?3BS 90 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE [ ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS - TOTAL CRUDE - ^143^ Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By a By. (PETRQUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER). HSSSB w -.-■smk. I I ■■■■ ■: -C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ik ii ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ^O. Form S.P. 18. cRitpg OIL Date (Opening Gauges) 1 „ JO Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 D TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BAR REUS AT 60°F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN 32 0 CLOSE 9397 ' - S H * 11 1 ■* 4 ttn Git oUo!?o # wi' ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i i * TANK OPEN i - CLOSE V m TOTAL OF TANKS * TOTAL CRUDE 5363« ) 037 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT J5y__ 2 £ By By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. Form B.P. 13. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET K[ 0 . ■ Date (Opening Gauges) £ i 19 Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) i _19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). ^ o o / TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN £ '1 Xfli A ,1 f- CLOSE nan QQ IffTV} ■ 65.73 TANK OPEN | CLOSE | . I 1 TANK OPEN | 1 ' CLOSE TANK OPEN | ■ CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ' TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. {PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By.. For (STATE ENGINEER).J ''TiwplffliWW iiiiiiii r C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited % % ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Form B.P. 18. k UBl Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- 11th August 19 46 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°f. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED ^LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. 1 WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o f. NET TONS feet INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 25 rm i 72791 ►065 CLOSE 5 ilo5/S imi .ol6 • TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE ' | , TANK OPEN CLOSE | ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS 1 ■ \ ■ i TOTAL CRUDE 56661. .00 7406 .979 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- JABLiW AMEKI€4H OIL COMP&amp;fY CPETROUEUM ENGINEER), By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER;. mWB'itTrfatea - ■C.11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (U ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]S^ 0 U82 kMBUS cmm OIL ' Date (Opening Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel ^ ^ ao „ . 1f( (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). ^ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED »les A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK u: V OPEN 1 65681 .24 CLOSE 6 e 16625 .60 110 1 16246 &gt; 24.72 74 TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE | 1 J TANK OPEN I i CLOSE | - TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS 1 • TOTAL CRUDE mi? ym Wfi r m Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. — (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45 Form B.P. 10. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Mo ■-.'j*.-! i ''■■wuiwawir-aawiitinHwa Date (Opening Gauges) -1_ ? 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel , Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER S: SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op % BARRELS TANK OPEN 31 ^ / si • CLOSE 5 9tx2 « ctq ^ 37o3 . 52191 o26 TANK OPEN 1 1 CLOSE - TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN CLOSE i „ &gt; TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE v ooo 686 9g7% Delivertd Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. vxifr. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). B y- By„ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ' ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET ^O Date (Opening Gauges) r '• 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel J Date (Closing Gauges) . 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMI OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN 25 r- ■ CLOSE I rm ■ 13U3 •• : ''?'&gt; . TANK OPEN CLOSE - ( i 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE ♦ 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE « • TOTAL OF TANKS | TOTAL CRUDE | 7485 .261 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By 1. By By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY superintendent). * (state engineer)?C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 13. 0 ^ ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET KIo , ULBI » CH 01 . 13feh Angast 4® Date (Opening Gauges) 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 0 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF . GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARREUS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. o/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN 25 ?2S9$S &gt; (3 . 71166 29 CLOSE XuCtA ^ 5-% 92 170620 % 1 .93 81 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 i | ' TANK OPEN CLOSE i i 1 . ' 1 TANK OPEN « j I CLOSE' TOTAL OF TANKS . TOTAL CRUDE fUOt Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. APABIM AMSR2S&amp;S OIL COWkM (PETROUEUW ENGINEER). By- (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. - (STATE ENGINEER).K M C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ' ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET No- Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- J9JL -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN ! CLOSE I I | TANK OPEN CLOSE , TANK OPEN CLOSE , - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKE1N GOVERNMENT By By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER). jrL'iH^jr ,Hi8The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Abovemmmf The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 4 ROYALTY DELIVER V * TICKET AR&amp;BIAM CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS TEMP, 'F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE mot. 052 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT MBIAN AMERICAN C (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT)., ._ rJ .„— ^ _ i * 0.11.-45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET iMBIAfl CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)_ _19__ _19 NET BARRELS AT 60°F. 1Q4o36 10425S Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By _____ (STATE ENGINEER;. CLOSE TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. CLOSE TANK TANK OPEN TOTAL OP TANKS Delivered Above By (PETROUEUivl ENGINEER). Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). TANK OR LINE TANK 134 OPEN I 4; CLOSE TANK CLOSE | TOTAL CRUDE L= TANK GAUGES OPEN ,| OPEN INCHESThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ;\R4BI4N CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). tank samples TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP, NET BARRELS TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F at 60 o f- TEMP. TANK OPEN CLOSE UOli TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered AboveTANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN TANK Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By_ By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEtR). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). C.11.4$. Form B.P. 16. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel s nTS s CRUDg OIL Date (Opening Gauges) 19 v/ X *-■ ' • K»7 • Jl XO kJCXiX JL \&gt;X (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Dtitii (Closing Gauges) 19—_ CLOSE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS TONS TANK OPEN A. P. I. AT 60° F. OPEN TANK CLOSE OBSERVED CLOSE GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. OPEN CLOSEC.I 1.45. Porm B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ 'ROYALTY DELIVERS? ' TICKET No itTDS OK, r Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Closing GaUgCS) — .19_ tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. °f, GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM observed PLES a. p. 1. at 60° F. water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES grav. a.p.i, temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK 133 OPEN I / CLOSE i 15736 15484. 89 4.0. r -2 99 ■ 777 TANK OPEN . CLOSE I 1 i 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 1 i 108652 ,00' 14219 ,777 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By TfTf (petroleum engineer). By. (refinery superintendent). By- (state engineer).sk i - - • ■ j ■IMiii The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVERY' TICKET Form B.P. 18. No A MBIAN CRUDB OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- i 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8e SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN CLOSE *$' 80 '0*7 1 . TANK OPEN • i CLOSE ■... ■ | h i I 1 1 1 ■ 1 TANK OPEN ! CLOSE &gt; | ^1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE •00 By- Delivered Above MBIAN AMSRIGASr OIL CO'.fPAST (PETROI-EUM ENGINEER). By. Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). - aC.11.4S The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET jsfo Form B.P. 18. AM CF B PS Q Tt ' Date (Opening Gauges) 19. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Closing GailgCS) ■ 19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. 1 t FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE # fv- 0 1 % TANK OPEN A fn. 1 1 ^ id* 1 CLOSE rl ( w r TANK d OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ■ TOTAL CRUDE ' Delioered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET ARABIA?? GRDDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No- Form B.P. Id. U9f Date (Opening Gauges) .19 Date (Closing Gauges). 1ft tank or line tank gauges gross barrels tank TEMP. Op- gross barrels at 60 o F. gross tons tank sam observed ples a. p. i. at 60° F. water &amp; sand etc. net barrels at 60 o F. i | net TONS feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK U3 OPEN Hi 126739 09 103 12JL25 5.00 1 CLOSE 30413 2984 | . | TANK OPEN - , | • CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN ■ • CLOSE V TANK OPEN - ' CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS i TOTAL CRUDE ,00 12329 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- ARilBIAM .alllgtlCAF OIL COMPANY ■ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER),The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refillety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 f. TANK OR UINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER),TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK TOTAL OF TANKS C.l 1.-15. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited „ I ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET No Form E.P. 18. ■*1 jt Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Closing GftUges) 19_ CLOSE TANK SAMPLES OPEN TANK CLOSE i OPEN TANK A. P. I. AT eo^F. ETC. TOTAL CRUDE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ■ % By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. c&gt; —_ f©! — (STATE ENGINEER).TANK GAUGES TANK OPEN CLOSE CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS C.11.45. TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °f. ■ - ■ TANK SAMPLES Witnessed for BA HKKI\ GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). A, P. I. AT 60° F. TANK OPEN j CLOSE | GROSS TONS OBSERVED TEMP. 0 F. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 1 ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges)— 19. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges). 19. (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Delivered Above Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT).Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY' TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVRRNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (STATE ENGINEER),C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY* TICKET No Form B.P. 18. I ,.,r r- Date (Opening Gauges) :—.19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) w (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Gc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A^P. I. AT 60° F. FEET 1NCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 1 .13 CLOSE I.- 41,920. Q&amp; r AO A JQjT ; 84909 1109? TANK OPEN | 1 CLOSE i — I TANK OPEN , CLOSE ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 84909 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT t By J? By_ By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( ROYALTY DELIVERV TICKET Form B.P. 18. AR43IAK CRUDE OIL „ ' Date (Opening Gauges)- 19_ Delivered to Refiner V the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel , % Date (Closing Gauges)- 19- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 0 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER a SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE 7 7516% .. TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE 1 | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS - TOTAL CRUDE - Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. — (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. AT 60 o F, OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). TANK OR LINE Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). NET TONS C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery U /icket N o. Date (Opening Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (Closing Gauges) (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). form B.P. 18. TANK TANK TANK TANKC.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery i picket Form B.P. 18. No Date (Opening Gauges) 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ]Date (Clo8ing Gauges) 19- (WITM CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK or line tank gauges gross barrels TANK TEMP. 0 f. gross barrels at 60 o f. gross tons tank samf observed &gt;les a. p. 1. at 60° f. water &amp; sand etc. net barrels net tons httr INCHES grav. a.p.i. temp. c f. o/ /o barrels at 60 o f TANK OPEN CLOSE 33726 i TANK * OPEN . . ' CLOSE ■■ i TANK OPEN * , CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ■S9T92 11751 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT i .f'f- By- (PKTROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited royalty delivery 1 picket j^ 0 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Opening Gauges) ___19 (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Closing Gauges) .19 tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM observed PLES a. p. i, at 60° F. water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS 1 | feet inches grav. a.p.f. temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK OPEN 1 ( CLOSE | TANK OPEN | * 1 i CLOSE | i TANK m OPEN 1 CLOSE . TANK OPEN [ CLOSE | i i 10 i AL OF TANKS 1 - TOTAL CRUDE | II Delivered Above Received Aboue Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (petroleum engineer). By. Bv. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery P icket Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. NET BARRELS A. P. I AT 60° F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery icket Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). tank samples TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. AT 60 o f, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). -aa'ar nThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery C icket Date (Opening Gauges)_ Ifl Date (Closing Gauges). I 10 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. OR. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT).Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery ^.icket Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSiON OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLEIS TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (petroleum engineer).WATER &amp; SAND ETC. % BARRELS 11984. 1U 1198, U1S4 TANK OR LINE TANK TANK TANK TANK TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL TANK GAUGES OPEN OPEN | ' CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE CRUDE GROSS BARRELS NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. -r 9X45X CLOSE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK SAMPLES itiiiiffliTtfi Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT v...,' .U i.,;-' ^ ,i (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), (STATE ENGINEER). GROSS TONS C.I 1.45. Form B.P, 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited R oyalty delivery C icket No——^ Date (Opening Gauges) i 1 fl Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel _ ^ . Date (Closing Gauges). 19 L_ (WITH COMVERSI ON OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 0 mmtsammm OBSERVED GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. A. P. I, AT 60° F.C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited L oyalty delivery C icket N o. Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Cauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMF, °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED S LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60 0 F TANK OPEN CLOSE 22 i OO gQ ■ 5 i TANK OPEN CLOSE , - | 1 ' . TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE j TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE U833 .00 5873 Delivered Above Received Above ■ Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT tty By By J ~ r-r-^T' r r iiv /, c-Kirsikicctd i ^ ( Rp-PIMPRY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY .SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited L oyalty delivery ( icket AR&amp;SIAH CRUDS OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN 106906 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Abvve Delivered Above ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY m %Bo,F~17 28/5 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: His s Secretary of State for Comruonwealth Relations, King Charles Street, Whitehall y London. ■ The Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the under mentioned document. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 27th Sept. 1948. Description of Enclosure, affl§.^ng_iai§ 4L Summary of Oil Deliveries for Augusti 1943♦ Royalty Tickets#Ko.4740-28/5 u ^ ' The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the under mentioned document. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 27th Sept, f 48. ENCLOSURE li / • / i \ Sumirary of Oil Deliveries for August 1948, SUBJECT /? V ROYALTY TICKETS / :/ h ■7 i / ! \ * e 6- NNBi/1f V^. (105/6/48). / ( J Dear Agency, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain . 12th October, 1948• i We note from your Printed Letter No. F - 17 - a8 /5 of the 27th September, and previous correspondence on the subject of the Bahrain Petroleum Company's oil royalty reports, that these reports are still being sent to the Commonwealth Relations Office, London. Since the Foreign Office are now responsible for the Gulf, would you please send three copies of such reports to them in future ? 2 ' We are sending copies of this letter to the Commonwealth Relations Office and the Foreign Office. [P Yours ever, RESIDENCY.' ' K „ r* r v THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A W A L I, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. N&gt; A i \ \ C \ J n h \ yo &gt; PA-586 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHREIN 21st October, 194^» ^nAL. A; ROYALTY TICKETS - S5PTSM3SR 19/^8 FILE: #075.1 Decl Sir, ^V- I enclose herewith two copies each of the following Royalty Tickets B-668-2 to B-684-1 (inclusive); and B-663 (adjustment ticket) These tickets represent the total amount of Crude Oil run from Tanks Nos. 131, 152 and 153, to the Refinery, upon which the Royalty for September 19^8 will be computed. pU | I also enclose five extra copies of the Summary of Oil Deliveries. In addition to the above, please find enclosed one copy each of the following tickets, viz:- A-l511-2 to A-1558-1 (inclusive) These tickets represent the amount of Arabian Crude Oil run from Tanks Nos. 132, 133, 134, 135 and 143. Yours very truly, For R. M. BROW CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTAT TVS THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ( ENCLS.o (no) No .F-23-28/5 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compllraents to: The Foreign Office, Lon om The Secretary to His Uxcellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send the underraentioned doc inent. POLITICAL iVGBHCY, BAiiHAIII» Dated the 2nd November 1948, Description nf Enclosure . Summary of Oil Deliveries for Sept.l94R, SUBJECT Ends: 3 co &gt;ies to F»0 # 1 cov to Hasidency NNRm 1 / 4972-28/6 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his comnliments to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the under mentioned document. /~N POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated 2nd November 194B, NNR KNCLOSURE Summary of Oil Deliveries for September 1948 SUBJECT ROYALTY TICKETS. h v\Lfc^tagwu.. : -| i 'j^r ji ^ ' ''&gt;,'' ■'•''■ ■ ' ■■ ■'k ' ' C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 6,P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). No.. .8-668'?. Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Date (Closing Gauges) ^ _19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM! OBSERVED &gt;LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % SARRELS TANK 132 OPEN 43 12610; ' r4- ; - 105 . CLOSE 17 ■- ,490?. 103 '■ e 76 (. j04 ■ .33:?; TANK OPEN CLOSE Less ae-'5c ■anted in iugus J i a« ; Vf Tioke 3. 6e B**l 1416&lt; uOG TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i i TOTAL OP TANKS Z'J. J- f - ! » ' 32 ® TOTAL CRUDE OS,.si-Jr „ loQO Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER),C11.4S The Bahrein Petfoleum Company Limited Form 6.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET mtm ' CRUDE OIL Date (Oj)f,nincr Ganges) ' ' ; : 10 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel J Si- Date fClnsinc, ^ ^ iq WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONSV ^ ^ S ^ lt ' TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS | TANK TEMP. 0 f. r~ GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 50° F. j FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. «/ BARRELS TANK OPEN 11 12643) 1 IPC : CLOSE 30 1-3/8 . 1 ■ TANK OPEN • i CLOSE 1 | TANK OPEN | CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS | ! TOTAL CRUDE 39 UU o.. ^'7 Delivered Above (( By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), By- Received Alovs i Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER),C.11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.—— Form B.P, 18. • . BAIffiEIK CRUDE OIL , 3 0 _ 3rd September.. 4S e Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). 0 6 ' tank OR line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF observed 'LES a. P. 1. at 60° F. water 8t sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK OPEN 44 5 8830' 866p S 0/ CLOSE li o-jf/ i ■ //4 bi 75* • 2489^ 9^ 33 aO . 24.90 334i TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK i OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN CLOSE I i TOTAL OP TANKS ] i TOTAL CRUDE . 24£ .00 3 • u Delivered Above Received Above *■/ Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By_ By By. (petroleum engineer). (refinery superintendent). (state engineer).C11.45. The Bahtein Petroleum Company Limited Form B .P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN GBUm OIL No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges), Date (Closing Gauges). 19 oil bf -19- ijo ■ TANK OR : LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 6C 0 F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK ■L52 OPEN 43 i 24,39c CLOSE €*—*1 O^-L/ 72431 51 c !'£ •) C TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 &gt; i TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ... i i 1 | TOTAL OF TANKS ■ TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Atove .-// Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 r. TANK OR LINE AT 60°F. AT 60 o F, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above C11.45. Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No._ - Date (Opening Gauges) : 1 19. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel . n ^ fn]nein) , a, n , crpi .) ic, (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). bC11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. - ' BAHREIN CRUDE OIL , Set)tyElb ^ ^ Date {Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery tlie following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 11.(8. gallons per barrel . J Date (Closing Gauges) ; 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. V GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 5 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN '•*4 /A 8689; ■■9. CLOSE t w . 23S,1 { ? 363^ &gt; $24 .-Oj -r.60 7296 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - - TANK OPEN CLOSE | TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE | JsOO 7196 Delivered Above Received Above , Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT C • ( By By By. ^ r-K • ^ I V i&gt;rr-«-&gt;\ ^E3crcri KIB-SSV CI I DC OI M T*ir KJ &gt;~)PK1*T*\ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ' (STATE ENGINEER),C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ; _ ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ^O B : BAHREIN GURDE CiL Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Dfl.fa* (ninsiiipr ri:t11 ) O O-.ri. 1 &lt;-J (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). ° ® ' ' tank OR line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. °f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o f. GROSS TONS TANK SAMf OBSERVED 'LES A. P. 1. AT 60® F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS feet inches GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 f. % BARRELS TANK 152 OPEN i &gt;2649 ■k pta ; • CLOSE 16 4786 '• *. • - ' 97 .; . ,306 TANK OPEN CLOSE ^ . TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 10364. Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT C ■ ' . . ( , ■ . JV By — By By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ^O BAHHEIi? -G^ODE OIL Dale (Opening Gauges)_^L^1^19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel J si r)ate (Clogi Gauges) ! 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). \ S O / TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 3 -0;5 CLOSE 17 , • 'jiyO ymi i ' •• (0 /-J 9 n,;.; L 76;, 7'■ QC TA^K OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN i I CLOSE ' • TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 7665 i.00 30280 &gt; I Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (' C By By (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ^ (STATE ENGINEER), Delivered Above By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER).Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN C Date (Opening Oa.ngea) : ' ' iq Date (Closing Granges) 1&lt;i TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES WATER &amp; SAND TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. NET TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Atove Witnessed for BAHKEIX GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). hmhhi mrw i I i- m mmmum •— mm — _ ir-kc.11 45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. Id ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL , Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE tank gauges gross barrels TANK TEMP. Gp. GROSS barrels at 60 o F. gross tons tank samf OBSERVED 'les A. p. I. AT 60° f. WATER Se SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o F. net tons 1 | FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 152 OPEN 43 10-3/' 526313 *21 9a CLOSE 17 0-5/5 48620 t 64 93 77692 *57 76402 r .S7 35.3 90 33 o.: L 76.^0 76326 .47 1022 6o811 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN - CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 76326 ■ o o 1023 D 0 311 Delivered Above By I (PETROLEUM ENGINEER) No ^ Date (Opening Gauges) 17th Septeraber j q Date (Closing Gauges) 1__- - ; ' ■' ; ; Received Above . Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT i * ^ | /1 f By By (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).CI 1.45. Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No._— ■i'.... i :.!&gt;&amp;■ 'OXu '^' r. S^irfceafoeTj /B Date (Opeaing Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery foJlowing Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel . • J Date (Closing Gaugea) 19 (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). tank OR line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o f. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF observed »LES a. P. i. at 60° f. water «c sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK 153 OPEN 1?,649 12463' ; .'/O CLOSE 17 0~7/i U71 4W 7664.' . 32. : o. 1 76.65 7657: 1033 4 r 466 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - 7657 ^00 1033 IU466 By_ Delivered Above (petroleum engineer). Bv_ Received Above (refinery superintendent). By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT |0 . (state engineer). wjThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CMJDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the foJlowing Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Delivered Above Received Above (STATE ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). /V- , mm 11C11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.F. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- i m ari -19_ -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 6C 0 F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 4-3 '1 OCT •41 CLOSE • Q/ •93 ' 1 ■ Ov' n /'■C# c .0-03 Ai*; ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE ' i i TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ■ TOTAL CRUDE 80903 .00 10850 Delivered Above Received Alove a Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT * * By. By By / . . \ *- i » ir-f r-ixv f--1 i r»m-» « i''rr fc i t-itr' (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ' (STATE ENGINEER).* • ~ Form 6.P. 18 The Bahfein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.—1—— BAHREIE CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) 19_i_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMf OBSERVED »LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 9c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 153 OPEN ■ 105283 ' 52 103672 .68 CLOSE • 41935 ? 39 61737 =29 VC &lt;- f 8298 TANK OPEN , CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 0 - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - ■ -61676 o o C298 u\ ■ Delivered Above Received Above m Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT &lt; ^ By_ By By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER),TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. TANK OPEN CLOSE CLOSE Delivered Above Received Above ** Witnessed foi' BAHREIN GOVERNMENT - &lt; 0 , ' ' t /;■ - r -i'- ■ r ' • V By By By_ (PETTROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). TOTAL CRUDE C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN C aIIDE OIL Form B.P. 18 3-682 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). 27th Sept 28th Sept,» TANK SAMPLES OBSERVED GRAV. TEMP. A.P.I. op. A. r. i. AT 60° F. WATER 9c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS TANK TANK OPEN j CLOSE OPEN ! TOTAL OF TANKS I 49^79 49 731 &gt;33 66?; u 371 TANK OPEN CLOSEC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.—— BAHREIK CRUDE) OIL Date (Opening Gauges) - ' 19 1 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel * Date (Closing Gauges) Ifl (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 0 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60° F'. GROSS TONS TANK SAMI OBSERVED 'LES A. p. 1. AT 60° F. WATER A; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 152 OPEN 34 \) J} / 978o' • OA/ i o CLOSE • m ' f ; ■■■'.*' 9 A 4401S *39 * .10 . 5243.: ,1C 7035 ;.530 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 . 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE | | TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 5,2.433 .00 7G32 53P Delivered Above Received Alooe , Witnessed for BAHBEIN GOVERNMENT c - By. By By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18 b&amp;hrek; crude oil Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). N 0 .__ Date (Opening Gauges)- 30th Sapt Date (Closing Gauges) : 19 TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TANK 153 OPEN CLOSE 29275 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT 11? fl (STATE ENGINEER). —sasa^ • - J: - —-Form 6. P. 18 Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BftEREIM GRUDSOIL Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinefy the following Crude Oil in built of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE NET TONS AT 60 o f, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above Sf-igiaal slgaod by a Be (STATE ENGINEER). iil ii ^C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CPUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). No.. B 668-' Date (Opening Gauges)., : 19 Date (Closing Gauges).... . 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED ? LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F, % BARRELS TANK 1^2 OPEN 12610; • ... } 3 y0 CLOSE 17 .. % 103 ' 4015? - ; 76 ■'(Wa 95 . ' TANK OPEN CLOSE a&amp;oc un ted in iugusl ; atj ; &gt; ■,- Tieke a-i 1^L6&lt; )c00 190 7.152 TANK OPEN CLOSE - - TANK TOTAL OF TANKS OPEN CLOSE ■ 51 Skjf TOTAL CRUDE • ■:X?J Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. H; | • - N (STATE ENGINEER). ■f' H ftThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Mr!REIN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Ga.ugfta) : iq Date (Closing September , i q 48 TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES WATER «c SAND ETC. TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. °F. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),i V CI 1.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No- B-670 Date (Opening Oa.ngea) ' u ' 1 1Q Date (Closing Gauges) 19 TANK or LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM» OBSERVED a LES A. r. i. AT 60° F. WATER Sc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET inches GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 131 OPEN m j ttajo- 103 866${ &gt; s o; CLOSE 31 o»3/ i 62C2 L74 ■ 99 j ' 6175' 248?: ■ TANK OPEN i CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE | - TANK j OPEN ^ . . CLOSE i 1 TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 2^87: 00 So ■ Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT M By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). M (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. ' (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B-P. 18. / ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL No. B ill Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- 3M 19_ th ©eptfflftb -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. C&gt; F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED »LES A. P. I . AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK U ''.c OPEN 43 101 f « P J CLOSE 2- l J i s y • Oapt* ti sOV -V.-f . TANK OPEN r CLOSE 1 | TANK OPEN j 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN i CLOSE ■ „ | TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE o 4 io&lt; DeLivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT B (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). m (REFSNERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ SSSS .■ - .v.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TE£MP. TANK OR LINE TEMP. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Ahove Delivered AboveTANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE C.11,45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET MHREirORDliS OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Dale (Opening Gauges). Si-h September Date (Closing Gauges) ' ' ' : : ; 19 Delivered Above Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT I v For (STATE ENGINEER). irnirifriiinTirMifMiiWi ■■■■Hi TANK OR LINE TANK TANK TANK OPEN - ''•'*2' CLOSE OPEN I CLOSE OPEN j CLOSE TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELSir 1 ™ Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET 'AEREIN OWm OIL Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE J.0j64-^C. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above■ Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL 12th Septembe^ j/Sth Sepbembe^ iS Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refiliefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE NET TONS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE lorn TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN j CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 10230.7&gt; Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above ir filMti ' 1 v-' - -Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NSTT BARRELS TO NET TONS). .9th gept^nb? tank samples net barrels TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 f. TANK OR LINE at 60 o f, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROLPIUM ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE NET TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witneaaed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (STATE ENGINEER). -MiiiiifTANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL CRUDE C11.4S. form &amp;.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET R-SJjRBIF c:;m OIL No 20th Septembf ^ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NHT BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gaugea)- Date (Closing Gauges) ———19—— TANK TOTAL OF TANKS WATER Ac SAND ETC. BARREUS 1 76.65 NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS , ^66 „ , , i Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Delivered Above , Received Above b H (c( ^ . » ,r—T-,is £-i mc-ol^ITTKir-iCKlT^ B y- ^ &lt;HEriNERY■-'--xpip smsmmmmmm The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET 8AHHSIM CRP DE01L Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) ;; - ; —ai, 19_-_ Date (Closing Gauges) 19 ' TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alovt Delivered Above (STATE ENGINEER).Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET EiHREBI C IIDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK 'OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). barrel TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE GRAV. TEMP, A.P.I. 0 F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alovs Delivered AboveForm B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET 3AHHEIN CRUSE O.CL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) tank samples net barrels at 60 0 f. TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. net tons TANK TEMP. °F, TANK OR LINE TEMP, °f. GRAV. A.P.I. TANK OPEN 34500 CLOSE 49737 49787 TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS 49737 .00 TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (STATE ENGINEER). ■BBaflBBHBBBiForm B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NHT BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES water 6t sand ETC. TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 f. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Above (STATE ENGINEER), ^ v . musmtmsss 11TTT'r'''TT^di ; ^llOThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAilREIS TROT® OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. Op. TANK OR LINE NET TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Atove Delivered Above CjjKSSSiM illlM mmen .45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.?. 16 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET N 0 'c .■vssnoc? 1 1 .i- %'%''{ Date (Opening Gauges) ■ t 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closi Gauges) .19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. ®F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED »LES A. p . r. AT 60° F. WATER 8t SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP, op */. BARRELS TANK 153 OPEN 'ft frfs CLOSE 8390: vy mei&amp;M O • H91 - 3569J 385 0»( TANK OPEN CLOSE • , | S5S9i WOO 473 TANK OPEN CLOSE • J', iiiikito ij X--.' TANK OPEN 1 , .. CLOSE 1 1 TOTAL OF TANKS rl TOTAL CRUDE ! &amp; W® S3ie?3CB?o©t3.y ajKJBm, as ,001 lasteaS Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT OrS&amp;tsxaX sig&amp;Ad OElgiiiail sl^aed Ijy Bv i By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AR&amp;BIA k crude oil Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges)- Delivered to Refinery the following. Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). barrel TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 'f. NET BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Delivered Above Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), TPfi mmmiiLmmMmmi IT'—nrrr r*OPEN TANK GAUGES FEET INCHES GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES OBSERVED A. P. 1. GRAV. A.P.!. TEMP. 0 F. AT 60° F. WATER «; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS TANK TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18 ARiBIAi' CRHjE OCL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- Isf Ser«t&lt;-C}b&amp;r TANK OR LINE CLOSE TANK OPEN Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT AMERICAN OIL CC®?Ai (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). | ^ ' . ; CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ; sgcii -rriT „ , - ^jfiiinwriitr •-i;... The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AiteAN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges)- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Form B.P. 18 No. 3j ?-t 2nd Sept, 19- -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 45 ^ 3 •v.J 4. . CLOSE • ■$'*. .5 ■/.I.198 3' 1 &gt; 9i T:':2 TANK U3 OPEN 31 0- i/i 89263 •65 108 . CLOSE 29 n-i/i G6123 e3'/ 108 3140 ,2$. 3071 .51 y%j&amp; 3.0' 3068 M 40C: 1 /!;/* TANK OPEN j CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE ■ TOTAL OP TANKS ' 68130 '■St TOTAL CRUDE 6^i 30 .00 mk DeUvered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT aRiiBIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (f &lt;r (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- mt try- i 1 TkThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NHT BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). . ^ Date (Closing Gauges)____ TANK SAMPLES WATER Ot SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE tank temp. 0 f. NET BARRELS at 60 o f, AT 60°F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 'TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMFAHI ■I mmmmmrn thmi KC11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form fJ.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ^ ■ ARABIAN CRUDE OIL . , c . . Date (Opening 2nd September . 40 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel y Date (Closing Gauges)____l__ __19__ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 0 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER fli SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS 1 FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK ^ 133 OPEN 44 X i26V7&lt;&lt; ,01 102 12433'/ CLOSE 19 7-3/3 5592^ '©98 98 54954 .0 a l TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN i i ; CLOSE ' TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 6931/ Wf Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (* # u i-lABlAH AMERICaN' Dili GOalPAKY ^ l ' -R r ,.«■ By -By By ^ , (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). i' T (STATE ENGINEER). ]^iifi WMftm u~ ■ * C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUEE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). No- A-1516 Date 2nd September, , Q Date rinsing ft a n g A g ) Septeffibai , 1ft IS * TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 'LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER » SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 43 12538^ e i2 . 123 5^0 CLOSE 16 1.0-3/^ ,1k ; 0 ■ m*n *79 76^74 sj.O . f : 9-3 Si 76 r 2' .50 99y2 .KM TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS - TOTAL CRUDE 761^ 00 9&gt;; •' . y / W Delivered Above Received Above * By_ ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL C01PAHX ^ (PETFROLEUM ENGINEER). if By_ Bv„ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). BBBBBBBBHB b BBBBHBBBBBBBHHBBBIHBBBBBBHHB msr- .' ^--1 - : mr ^ Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENTForm B.P. 16 The Bahtein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OlL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OK NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE AT 60°F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMFAK (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT),C.11.-45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.— ARABIAN CRUDE Oli Date (Opening o ».n^) 3rd Septembe r,^ ,.S Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel ^ rninH;ri(T ^:c 5^ N&amp;m 1ft (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 1 » ^ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN •BSlf CLOSE / Q ..5 .x; ? .92 V304- 1.-69 7204, 3V.g y .c..04 - .97 '-Mi TANK OPEN CLOSE - 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ' CLOSE [ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 942 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT .. .. ■. ... - f By By By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45, Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.— ARABIAN CRUDE OIL ... Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (CIo8i Gauges) &gt; 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP, op. % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN J'2394' J r 7 i, 125 51? CLOSE 16 If, v&gt; r ? ,0'^St .67 92 j/*2 Ool 76,33 760^ 996( TANK OPEN | ~ CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK ^ ; OPEN CLOSE 1 i TOTAL OF TANKS X TOTAL CRUDE | • -ftirji c00 i .ase Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (* • Oil COHV^X b v By. y— ' ' ' (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 6.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]s^ ii i520 .mmm. crude oil Date (Opening Gauges) ' ' : : 19 ' - Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel , c ., r , , rt •' Date (Closing Gauges) ■' 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK or LINE tank gauges gross barrels tank temp. 0 f. gross barrels at 60 o f. gross tons tank samf observed n-es a, r. i. at 60° f. water si sand etc. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 f. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 124 OPEN 43 io£ _12622 1-63 94 V CLOSE 12 0- 1/5; 33*3 ^ j 44 • 9239 5 ;v 9096: 3715 . Oil 90,9c 908/? : 'U 999 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN j CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE _ TOTAL OF TANKS | 1 1 TOTAL CRUDE - • 9087 100 ,999 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. am3iah american oil gompahy (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). 6 By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. !i (STATE ENGINEER).-) I C11.45. Form B.P. IS The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.-- uKUj .® OiL . c p r -j. Date (Opening Gauges) ± ! 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel I)ate ( Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. I TEMP. A.P.I. 1 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60° F TANK ■m OPEN 43 0-3/J 124055 £3 OB CLOSE 7 ' 1 19r /O o 95 194'-J .95 *J3 6 1 , 102^44 10234.0 .89 13 U J 154 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN . CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE 102241 c00 13^11 el34 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT f A aracf.' on, ooKF.are Bv By, : (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ' «■ (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. AT 60°F AT 60 0 F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No ARABIAN CRUDS OIL Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ,^ i , J Date (Closing Gauges) 19 ; (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ■ By __ By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). v ' fjt (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.___-—— ABAEIAK CRUI® OIL Dat« (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (fin^ina C'uu ,**) 1ft (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. O f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS \ TANK SAMF OBSERVED S LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER Si SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT eo 0 F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. i TEMP. A.P.I. | 0 F. % BARRELS TANK .. . • OPEN K»Jr 3 94 12528: L eS ! 6 CLOSE D 10899; ! TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ' • TANK OPEN 1 1 CLOSE 1 TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - - • 10888' o )*2S8 Delivered Above Received Alovt Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT « * ARABIAN AMERICAN Oil GOMFAin -d * A B y_ By —- -by % (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). x '' ' (STATE ENGINEER).Form &amp;.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN mm OIL Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE NET TONS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOS TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above ARABIA! AMERICAH OIL mX Om-PhViForm B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET - ARABIAN CRUDE Oil Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p «r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. °F. NET BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE vxz^'m TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered Alove ARABIAN ASBRICAM OIL COMPANT (REFiNERY SUPERINTENDENT), ■' 1,1 m— mmm i—C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET tomim crodb on Form B.P. 18 No Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p «r barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Date {Ctesing Gaugea)—i— — -19—1— tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o f. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES water &amp; sand etc. NET BARRELS NET TONS observed a. P. 1. at 60° f. feet inches grav, a.p.i. temp. 0 f. % barrels TANK 332 OPEN 44 ■ 3859C : 30 9 7 8 /093 CLOSE 0 '.Of 131-:.. ■y: 39.? r . - . / --V-j ,30 966' TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TANK OPEN - CLOSE L TANK i, o ■ OPEN CLOSE L TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ' 73633 ^00 1 9 c933 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. ARABIAN ASKKICAF OIL COMPANY (petroleum engineer). By. .4 (refinery superintendent). By_ i r - E state engineer).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET AMSim CRUDE OIL Date (Opening O fl ,n gfta ) ' - :: • l _ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel TWp /nlnqi . n(r , ft (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). V ' * o B ' I TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP, 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 0 F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMf OBSERVED 'LES A. r. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS i FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. °F. % BARRELS TANK US OPEN i. Z j'j 13462 f :.&lt;3 CLOSE 10 2912 149 93 2SbB h73 - 9594 I ; V2 I : m 3? &lt; • : 191 o 8? : B4 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS c . • TOTAL CRUDE 9573« Jo 00 1252 4 0 /9 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT 'u.-• C.;vN c COfiJ-iL*-;: 4 I By By! , By„ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER),C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 6.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRTJIE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No.. A-1529 Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). IQth September^ 48.. : 19 12;th September. 4B 19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. i TEMP. A.P.I. | °F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK H J OPEN 42 7 ■■/: 12281. 9.71 90 121137 .OS CLOSE 11 5 - i pM. 0-49 89 jzvr, •■&gt;44 ^9009 . 64 40 c 95 '37-; Dm L hy XI 6B92G .63 1162i .149 TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN 1 1 CLOSE TANK . OPEN . CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 88921 .00 1162^ .149 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- ARABIAK AMERICAN OIL OGfePAF? (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ &lt;1 (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Jyfo. Form B.P. 18 A ^ ^ ri Date (Opening Gauges) ' 19- Delivered to Refiliety the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel J2- Date (Closinsr Gauges) 19. (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). V ' 6 ' t rV fy-: tank OR line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM! OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. 1. at 60° f. water 8c sand ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o f. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. *&gt;/ /o barrels TANK ;u OPEN A? 11 smi 35913 CLOSE 7 12595 J..'72 9:&gt; 1238^ ^27 -735.2- 719 , »• .* &gt; v-» i, ■ r?.. 7344? ■ ' V TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN -- CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - , TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • 7344 f : 00 960' 3 &lt; &gt; Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By_ ByJ By, (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET 11th Sentenber Date (Opening C4auges). Date (Closing Gauges) 13 tb Septerab TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. AT 60°F, TANK 11099C OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPAKY ■ ■ IL-C11.45. Form 6.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]^ 0 ^1534 ARABIAN OHIte Oil Hth 43- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Clof . ini , r!. ai .n.^) 48 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS | AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. °F. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK 132 OPEN 44 5-1/8 S8?7f U7 CLOSE o 3 1594c 1.32 99 72S3i .'15 7153: 40 C 95 3?. 0 1 '/.US &gt; 7146S ,24 935 I -,621 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ' i CLOSE \ ' TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 00 935: :o621 9 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT -p ambian A merican oil company by_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), By. 0? (STATE ENGINEER).Form &amp;,P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). tank samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. TANK GAUGES net barrels TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE at 60 o f, TANK lU75 t? .03 OPEN CLOSE 95351,93 TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above ARABIAN AIJERIGAN OIL COMPACTC11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE Cil&gt; Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). „ 15th S©D'fcw&amp;bBi% /8, Date (Opening Gauges) 1 19 Date (Closing Gauges) 1 19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED ^LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 6t SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134. OPEN •• 4-5/8 124.7.40 O 10'' 122ll&lt; CLOSE C A'7/e j . - 93 2X2 . &gt; 70 r , 99391 • - y? &lt; 0&lt; ? 99'-9 ■ Oj 13004 4? :&gt; TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN - ' CLOSE TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE i I TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE iOO • :€04 'J'-J Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. ARABIAN AfflBHlGA?' OIL .'CHPANY ' (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. TW (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.— Form B.P. 18. ARABIAN CFUEE OIL , . 15th Sspt -al: • /.f Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel IVfi. 1 ■ 46- Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). v 0 0 ' . TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED ^LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. &lt;6/ /O BARRELS TANK U3 OPEN 42 .11 jx3724 ,01 98 CLOSE v i oS2 9a 9BUZ cl9 .41 - . &gt; 93 37of 0e !. 96 4' 96343 .97 125% .565 TANK OPEN CLOSE * TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE • - - TANK OPEN CLOSE . TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 96344 00 -565 - Delivered Above Received Move Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ■ i AEkBIA3 AMSilv:.. II ccaff' •• K By { 1 By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).Form 6.P. 16 C.11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CHDOS OIL Delivered to Refinery tke following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Ifl TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 6934?- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above fUBahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE GRAV. A.P.I. OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Atove Delivered Above'■ i W. aBQ giimillBMI BH f C11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARA.BIAM CRUDfc OIL Form B.P. 18 No- A 154)0 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) 1_—£— 19 •— Date (Closing Gauges) 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED J LES A. P. 1. AT 60° r. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. %♦ BARRELS TANK m OPEN a -co luoa &gt;,75 1; ■ CLOSE 5 10-3/! ■ ;'&gt;00 HfN | o&lt; I 15 ? ■ .,91 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • 9636 '-■X. .269 Delivered Above By- iMfilAK AMERICAS OIL COKPAMI . (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). Received Above e. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT &lt;~sh 5 (STATE ENGINEER). V'—' . ^ ■ aBWBU BBI WBMBSI! INmm w....... ■ Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CHUDS OIL 18t'n Septembfir t Q 4B 20th Se-teabert o AB Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE 106027 OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE . Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above .3IM-i AM£;{ICAF OIL COMITC11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No— AUBim CRUIE OIL Dale (Opening Gauges)— 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel J Date (Closing Gauges) .19- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE tank gauges gross barrels TANK TEMP. 0 F. gross barrels at 60 o f. gross tons tank samf OBSERVED 'les A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at eo 0 F. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. ®f. % BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN ••617;;; CLOSE 25963 =4.6 5 25561 ,03 ■ 60617 . ■ Tu 5 1 r ' !. TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN • CLOSE | | 1 TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 6j£ 17 7926 7*5-1 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT B y- )isn American Oil Go roan (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REF1NERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).net barrels at 60 o f. TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN | , CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE AMBISN ABS5RICAI-T OIL ^GOMPAJfl (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFiNERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). Form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. ARABT r C-::^ on. Date (Opening Gauges) . Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel Date (dosing Gauges) (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). ., Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Delivered Above RecelVed AboVe net tons WATER &amp; SAND ETC. BARRELS 1272M64 ~v4 r;i l 12512: 27S0 tank samples A. P. I. AT 60° f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. gross tons OBSERVED GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F.Cll.-tS The Bahrein Pettoleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ,./f ' arabian CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NETT TONS). Xo. ' Date (Opening Gauges) : ■ '''— 19— Date (Closing Gauges) LJ -^19-. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM F OBSERVED •LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATJ iR «c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % SARRELS A I bU w h TANK 143 OPEN a g-7 /d 12031 /\77 38 11375; CLOSE •3 2 -1 /2 2303 5.32 39 2272 ! K.1A 9602&lt; : &gt;*50 95 37 .J cv; )5 if y 95978 -.49 12525 TANK OPEN CLOSE I i TANK OPEN i - | • CLOSE TANK ' Q i OPEN &lt; ♦ CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ■ TOTAL CRUDE 9597.1 .,00 12525 : 193 By. Delivered Above ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COKPANI' Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT f t* fc $ h A ' • ' l w (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By \i , JL% 1 \ ' ' (STATE ENGINEER).I® ' ^ / :. ;' , CII.^B. ( The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (0 ' jcmn g Gau g es )- (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Closing Gauges) . . 19 TANK OR LINE TANH GAl JGES GROSS BARRELS j TANK TEMP. I 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM OBSERVED PLES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER A SAND ETC. NET B AT ARRELS 60°F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN 43 ■Bl 1256? Bf'jk CLOSE g ip zufa 1:05 10105 7,2? | 9945 DJ.9 39 .2 25 37* ■ &gt;5 Z.9./73 CK ViO i),Z.6 1 ^Of o TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ i TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS | 1 - TOTAL CRUDE 1 | 99 40 } .00 1300 ? 035 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT i 1 jjy Arabian American Oil Cosnpany (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). ——— {REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER). uForm B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) 2.— —t TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS AT 60 o F*. TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Alove Delivered AboveC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARdEIAF CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No. Date (Opening Gauges J'— ' 122 1 19- /S Date (Closing Gauges)- 25 th Se-ot , -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. ^F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 5 LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 1/-3 OPEN 42 122940 .55 91 121170 .24 CLOSE 55 23761 90 23431 .23 ,01 96 3 7-7 97690 ,14 .£90 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 1 1 - i i TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK . OPEN / CLOSE &lt; - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 97 S9C 0 12755 Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT T. ^ T&gt;_ r By_ By i&gt;y (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Pettoleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARABIA ORUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons p«r barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F, AT 60 o F, TEMP. 'F. GRAV. A.P .I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN i CLOSE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Atovi Delivered Above&gt; L C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Form B.P. 18 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) 19- Date (Closing Gauges). iota -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER A SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV, A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN 8«i3 /2 /. &lt; ■ 12. CLOSE 4l63i 35 r 1 ■ TANK OPEN ' * CLOSE 1 ' 1 TANK OPEN N CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE / TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ' r &gt; 'P _j j oo t,*J ( i JL a By. Deiirtrtd Above car Jomt (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). i By_ Received Alove (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHEEIN GOVERNMENT XO' (STATE ENGINEER). v o.11 C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET FABIAN ORUISS OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No Date (Opening Gauges) :—i—; 19 Date (Closing Gauges) 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 6 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER £c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP, op. % BARRELS AT 60 o r TANK OPEN • . 1 x ;■ , I CLOSE 43^68 71134 ~ y2 , '■ . . TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE '71063 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). k By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ (STATE ENGINEER). ll^TANK SAMPLES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK TEMP. TEMP. 0 F. CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE SSHHHHBHHHHHHI C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET akabian crude oil Form B.K 18. Date (Opening Gauges) —— 19—_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges)^- 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK 133 TANK TANK TANK GAUGES OPEN OPEN GROSS BARRELS 126139 J'. ! 'V 87971 WATER Sc SAND ETC. BARRELS NET BARRELS AT 60°F. Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Arabian Asericen Oil Con? (PETTROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). 1. iiiiiiiiini irmn 11335 CLOSE TANK CLOSE OPEN |CI 1.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No._~^— ARABIAN CRUDE OIL ... . c Date (Opening Gauges) —_— 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (dosing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER ft SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 134 OPEN 43 2-3/J. 124297 .27 12,; 370 -' CLOSE '-3 11-3/i 39459 , / 91 3f:. c 99 .33 -33 39,! ZF 37 -4 0 ,0! J. 74 83429 TANK OPEN i 11 i CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN \ CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE 83430 ,00 1.0912 -.590 Delivered Above Received Atove By- Arabian Anericar Oil Gompany (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). &gt; By— (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT / ; y ^ id'- i|%il ror (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No— - iPABJj lube oil Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). .19— -19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 1 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS | TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP, op. % BARRELS AT 60°F TANK OPEN 'i .&gt;04. CLOSE 07 TANK OPEN t CLOSE ! j TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN • CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE Tt-qe-a?* 00 9S^5 Sv ; :5 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. cian Ab ican Oil 0o 'O8i\y I (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. W ■ v or (STATE ENGINEER). r i3' UryC.11.45- The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ARAB im C^ODE 0X1-- Delivered to Refinery tke following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Form B.P. 18 No Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Date (Closing Gauges)- 19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES | GROSS BARRELS | TANK TEMP. o F . GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. ETC. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op % BARRELS TANK 133 OPEN 41 99 1 j CLOSE 675 ■ 72 90S61- 0077!) TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 i 1 CLOSE 1 1 TOTAL OP TANKS i - TOTAL CRUDE 1 1 90771 Delivered Above Received Atove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- Arabian American Oil Company (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). k (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER),■ &gt; C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18 No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) 7 19 Date (Closing Gauges) 3OH; • jot.., .19 AS. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Ac SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV, A.P.I. TEMP. ®F. % BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK OPEN 1 ■ ;/V CLOSE 362S9 57925 n ■ : ■ TANK OPEN '4/47, . . CLOSE ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN |. CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS . J - - '4 ■'' ', TOTAL CRUDE | By- Delivered Above UBIAr AMEJUJ^ OIL GO Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). t (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). iC11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18 ICfXIifv tsiXulMS* Date (Opening Gauges)_ 19_ Delivered to Refinery tke following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ^ . Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED »LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER Ac SAND ETC. NET BAR AT 60 ! RELS &gt;F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE fgl TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE j i. TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 3322 -1S5 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ARABIAN AMSEICM OIL GOMPAMI C By try - By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)_ Oct- -19 AS .19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM? OBSERVED &gt; LES A. P. I. AT G0 o F. WATER Ac SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN ff Hilrf &lt;£ 3900$, &gt;5^ CLOSE £ 1 /j 61B6 .40 i ✓•it 6e09 6^4,; /o TANK OPEN 1 | CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE \/U .298 Delivered Above Received Alove . Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By oy V By , w. - - - ^ \ / i—^•— f— t v . »— i—« y y . mi— r-^i ^ t-r r'^ ) il-n- 1 \ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED AWALI, B ahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 23rd November, 19A8* FA-685 ' U A 2; 5 IVOk'' jc His Britannic Majesty^ Political iigent, ' ^'7 The Agenc^r, ' r* BAHEEIN. ROYALTY TICKETS - OCTOBER 19^.8 File: #075.1 Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two copies each of the following Royalty Tickets B-684--2 to B-702-1 (inclusive). These tickets represent the total amount of Crude Oil run from Tanks Hos. 131, 152 and 153 to the Refinery, upon which the Royalty for October 194-8 will be computed, I also enclose five extra copies of the Summary of Oil Deliveries. In addition to the above, please find enclosed one copy each of the following tickets, viz;- A-1557-2 to A-1612-1 (inclusive)• These tickets represent the amount of Arabian Crude Oil run from Tanks lies • 132, 133, 13A and 14.3 • Yours very truly. CHIEF LOCAL REPRESEI1TATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM CCMPANY LIMITED Attachments/ Ho.F-32-28/5 Tns Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliment? to:- Tho Foreign Office, London, The Persian Gulf Becidency, i3ahrain, and has the honour to send there the undermentioned document. POLITICAL ASSHCY, BAHRAIH. The 29th November, 1948. Per.cription of ©ncloBure• ITr: re and date. Sub j ec t Sumnjary of Oil Deliveries for October 194B. I V Royalty Tickets.-A No. 5271-28/5 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:~ The Adviser to the Be lira in Government, Bahrai n. and has the honour to send him a cop/ of The undermen 4 :ioned doctiment. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 29th Nov. 1948. SNGLOSURE Summary of Oil Deliveries for October 1948. SUBJECT ROYALTY TICKETS.C11.4S The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). -.19- -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED S LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER «e SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE . TANK OPEN CLOSE t A.0SS * | 29246 ■ TANK OPEN j CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE i TOTAL OF TANKS 1 1 'i ■' C: e ' TOTAL CRUDE h - ■■ Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT „.. By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). Delivered Above Received Above rW' i wnnffiiimm? , C.11.15 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET CRUDE Cir. form B.P. 13 No. B 6S5 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) : - Date (Closing Gauges)-. -19- -19- m:: H TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER ft SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES AT 60 o F. GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP, op. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE Q'• . TANK OPEN CLOSE ! . ■,. ''-5 TANK OPEN CLOSE • . TANK D OPEN | i CLOSE 1 | i TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE ■ 38 By. Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). Bv_ Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT V, t . ' (STATE ENGINEER). — ''' I ' 1 'i 1 ^ BWJMBM —C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET B* '' T T ?' p-Rfj DF C?T t Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No- 3-Ofctt Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). 19_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER ft SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK -■ - OPEN CLOSE f -• •• - 5 ' &gt;.3 • ■ TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE i Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Granges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- -19- _19_ tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE ' 69',So 7' r TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 6 9'61 9286 . 9 ■ Delivered Above By- &lt;petroleum engineer). € By_ Received Above € (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Bj- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). iC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- rsftRMilK CRUDE Oil. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) 19- Date (Closing Gauges) - - -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F, GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.L TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 1 ■ q 28 CLOSE 1 *7 . --- r &gt;3402 ' - -v • 1 K ■ f TANK OPEN i 1 CLOSE - 1 TANK OPEN ! - CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE • TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE mm * 7160 ■ Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT f ' € By By ■ ^7- v —i— t—*^ ^DmKJCTOV &lt;51 ippc?|NTFNJPiENIT 1. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.1M5. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No.-iLi£___ BAHREIN CRUDE O IL Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 1Q (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). N 7 1 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Se SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 152 OPEN t- 9 a/; 126102 \ ..41 90 1^U5C ,47 CLOSE 22 4&gt;St o ; .69 88 6427? .80 60172 06? 35o3 33.2 oa 17 6011] ,.50 TANK OPEN | CLOSE 1 1 I - TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN | I CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS \ TOTAL CRUDE 60111 8062 .079 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT i'V fll % N i By By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).w-r ■ C.11.-4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ■ ■ V : ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET b&amp;hre1k crude oil Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No Date (Opening Gauges)- -19_ Date (Closing Gauges} -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A, P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op % BARRELS TANK 153 OPEN h-A- 1.2/2 127041 125440 9a CLOSE . 26' 7.7/S 76-467 85 A ^ 49 j TANK OPEN - ■ CLOSE i 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 497^9 6701 E ' T. ■ Delivered Aiove By_ (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (i Bv. Received Above SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). wmmam ■ iC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- -19_ -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE , TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK - o v OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delirered Above Received Atove. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By — By — — r-, rr KI K&gt; E-ET CD n WPRY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Na Date (Opening Gauges) 19. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Oln^mr Pnn if) (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED »LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 8k SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 I TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 j 1 | TANK OPEN 1 1 1 CLOSE • TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. (STATE ENGINEER). Delivered Above Received Above € By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT).C.11,45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges), Date (Closing Gauges)- 19_ -19. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED a LES A, P. 1. AT - 60° F. WATER flc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. ^F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ' | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE . TOTAL OF TANKS s • TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. (PETROL.EUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).■—■■■——^—9—^ form B.P. 18 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE GRAV, A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHBEIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (STATE ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). .-v..C.I 1 .45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ^9 Form B.P. 18. S aKREIK CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges)—' : 1 Q Delivered to Refiner V the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges}—..^ ! &gt; Ifl (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 6 6 ' ' TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60° r. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. i. | NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 43 n „V! 1265;A .2.1 1254-0 : | CLOSE 16 ■ 'r-?/.' 47954 c- 83 r • S- «' **93 i ■ 7792 64 . 33c 4 77,93 77849 71 1 ' ■ : .m TANK OPEN ■ . 1 | CLOSE | | TANK OPEN 1 i 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN | CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE | ^6:4 10429 •:/ v. Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT .(C. By By By (PETROI.EUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER)V C, 11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY* TICKET Form B.P. 18. No- Delivered tO Hefinety tile following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). -19- -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMF. 0 f. i GROSS BARRELS 1 at 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. f. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 1 1 ' CLOSE ; ■ .61 — .92 • I p TANK OPEN CLOSE j 1 l ! | TANK OPEN- CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i TOTAL OP TANKS 1 ■ TOTAL CRUDE 7334 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER). /ml v 1 miC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Date (Opening Gauges) — 1 : 19—su Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (dosing Gauges) 10 (WITH COMVERSSON OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. L AT 60° F. ETC. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. C F. % BARRELS AI ou-i- TANK OPEN . 1 • . ..f : , ' CLOSE ^ '■4 ¥ TANK OPEN ■ i CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Reived Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT t « By By By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 19 Date (Closing Gauges). 1 Cil 19 TANK OR LINE FEET INCHES GROSS BARRELS GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). TANK TANK TOTAL CRUDE TANK OPEN TOTAL OF TANKSJ V' C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]^ 0 form B.P. t8. _ - Date (Opening Gauges) Uelivered to Ivetiaery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS), Date (Closing Gauges) 1 .19_; TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAM OBSERVED a LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.f, TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN -- CLOSE 31903. K 7- |3.7 31871 ; o j TANK OPEN F CLOSE ! 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE • TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ^187J 4261; 960 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ' By By By __ &gt; (PCTROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60° F. TANK TEMP. 0 F. NET BARRELS TANK OR LINE A. P. I AT 60° F. AT 60°F TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER).C.1M5. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). —.—_19_ 19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS | TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.f. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN : « / ft#* j | ■&lt; * ■ CLOSE ' ' '3 j ' . TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 ! CLOSE ; v TANK OPEN . | CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ^ i, C-, . Delivered Above Received Above c (( Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. Bv. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- Form B.P. 18. No. _19- (6 o 00 A.Mj TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMF. 0 r. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. f. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F, •V /o BARRELS TANK OPEN - ' - CLOSE -t o $ * ■ TANK OPEN 1 • CLOSE 1 - TANK OPEN ■ | 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE • TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE JC-*. , Delivered Above Received Above 1 C By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By- Bv (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER).C-ll.tS The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WiTH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). -19_ .19. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER ft SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE | TANK OPEN j - CLOSE . TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ^—: ' ' ' . ' 1 - ' ~ / Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT r * 'Rv By I By ^ ('RP-rtNJp-RY SUPERIMTEMDENT). (PETTROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPER1KTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form 8.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Dale {Closing Gauges)- 19_ -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A» P. I. AT 60° F. ETC. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60 W F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 j TANK OPEN 1 1 j CLOSE i i TANK OPEN CLOSE » TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE (js=r ; — Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT r 1 'Rv By — 1 By, — y ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER^.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. • Si: . V^-, JL'ij '? AT Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- _19_ -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. ©F GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 5 LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. &amp;/ /e BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE 1-339 35 &gt; TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN j • CLOSE i | TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS i TOTAL CRUDE - c / Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Bv By _n By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 'I', NET BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE C.1MS. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET gAHRSI?? .. ClgJpIS Cll: Date (Opening Granges)- 19_ Delivered to Refiaery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET SARREUS TO NET TONS). D 0 ' Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By_ ■ ?,:&gt;■ (STATE ENGINEER).vr • ■ ;'. x C.I 1 .45. m The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Form B.P. 18. No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). -19- Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) 2 id TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NF rr BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. f. AT 60° F. 1 FEET INCHES GRAV. A.PJ. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN , 9 \ 86S06 2 8 CLOSE A. i 1 -• %% 7 5 3402 • OQ \ '* ' - £ &gt; ' / f) 5334B 716C TANK OPEN 1 | CLOSE i TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN j CLOSE • • TOTAL OF TANKS - TOTAL CRUDE 533 9 ■ r-c Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT / ^ Bv. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. fot (STATE ENGINEER). •'tWHWWBI ^ • IIC.11.45. The Bahrem Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- CSI Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). _19- J!L TANK OR line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. | GROSS BARRELS | AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS j TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° r. feet INCHES grav. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN y CLOSE 22 g c 650?£ '35 a,3 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN i t CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE | 6C13J 8062 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHBEIN GOVERNMENT By- Bv_ {petroleum engineer). (refinery superintendent). By. (state engineer).C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ffAKR EIK CRUDE OIL Form B.P. 18. No- Delivered to Refinery tile following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges), -19- _19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK 153 OPEN 127041 A/ 89 1 12544.0 02 CLOSE V f/O - 76/£7 nrt f -j ■ • /Q7QQ ♦-i- ^ ■ J J - 32*$ 5 6701 -22 TANK OPEN | CLOSE | \ TANK OPEN CLOSE r I TANK OPEN CLOSE l TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Si-V i%+V 6701 Delivered Above By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (f By. Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) ! 19. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closins Gauges) 19. (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). 0 ' TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F, FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE j TANK OPEN CLOSE i TANK OPEN i CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS 1 TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER) Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT &lt; s By By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C ' 1, ' 45 Til T&gt; 1 • T* 1 . . Form B - F '- 18 ' The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET ]^ 0 Date (Opening Gauges) __19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel . Date rOlosino- OaiK^sl 10 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). LV TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMI OBSERVED =LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. | NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. C F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN '1.2527? 1 CLOSE - TANK OPEN ' CLOSE I r - TAKK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS | - TOTAL CRUDE QQ 9503 ^37: Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- -19_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN • CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN ■ CLOSE m TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT c i By By By c* rr » IC O X/' C I I t»CT3 1 Kl-rC'M rMrKJT\ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18 ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges)- .19_ _19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Oc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A, P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. ®/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TANK OPEN , CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE , TANK OPEN • j 1 CLOSE | | i TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHBEIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ i (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By (STATE ENGINEER).tx n i'' iiWiiirr 'Tn-PV-;-:;^ C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET BAHREIN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). No Date (Opening Gauges)_-_ 19 Date (Closing Gauges) -Li—I __19 L_ TANK OR UINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. C F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN 4 J S 5 ( -s-JsM /I 'r 12 540; J o ?7 CLOSE Xv &gt;-4V - •: t ^ S J - oU 33,.'; - 77&gt;93 71 .4? 6 TANK OPEN 1 1 CLOSE • TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ' r.'29 -4 : '3 Delivered Above Received Above By- (PETROL.EUM ENGrNEER). By- (REF1NERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). ■^-a-c.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form b.p. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No aaH RKIK' CR U1B O IL M Date (Opening Gauges)—1 19—i— Delivered to Refinery the foUowing Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel (Cloging Gauges) i q (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR UNE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60°F TANK '3 «i*5 i J ^ OPEN . O 1.026X2 1 3 v CLOSE ■ ■ - , 33 ,0 ■■ 34 =80 34749 ,12 733- ■ .-v~ ■j *, ' TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN - CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS . TOTAL CRUDE 34749 7334 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET CRUDE' OH Date (Opening Gauges) ——' ' ' '• • —19— Date (Closing Gauges)— ; 19—ijil Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TANK OR LINE TEMP, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above - --tf ■C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B,P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. ■ ■ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- _19_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. 1 NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° P. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS TANK 5 r . OPEN .«w» '• / - • ■ 80 CLOSE ' . r '-~- 3CBS0 i 8 3 8 w • ■ - rv TANK OPEN ' CLOSE I TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE i TANK OPEN - CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 1 1 .'' . G v- v C JC Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT « / ■ ■ By By ——__— _____ By. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TEMP. 0 F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CLOSE CRUDE TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. WATER ae SAND ETC. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET K[ 0 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKE1K GOVERNMENT Hi f $ By .. —— By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER). TANK OPEN I OPEN CLOSE BARRELS s9C NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges), 19_ GROSS BARRELS CLOSE Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS).G.11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET MBREIH CKUDE OXIj Porm B.P. 18. No. _19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) —Ss .,19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60° F. GROSS TONS | TANK SAMP OBSERVED LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 8e SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK V :.3 - OPEN ' ; 1 CLOSE ■0 JM ■ ; ftfl o o t ri-l a/ ft: .... TANK OPEN 1 - CLOSE ' TANK OPEN CLOSE - TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS | TOTAL CRUDE 1 - Delivered Above By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). c By- Beceived Above J, S* /? [ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). - ' 7 — 8 -C.11.4J. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No Date (Opening Gauges). 19.- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel I)ate (Closinrr Gauges) tq (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES water Be sand etc. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS observed a. p. i. at 60° f. feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK i OPEN ■ /, jJtJ) CLOSE 11 o ■■ •ti i''! - - . , £&gt;■25^3 . TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ! 1 CLOSE &lt;}- TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTx\L CRUDE - 1 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT ■ c t &gt; v By By — — j— — - - (refinery superintendent). , (state engineer). (petroleum engineer).T i'' 1 iniWMiiiiK C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET OEUDE OK- Form B.P. 18, No- Delivered tO Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)—— 19 — Date (Closing Gauges) 1=® ' 19— Delivered Above i Received Above A _ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By, (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. • * _ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED | LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK , OPEN 5Q _ ■' ' • | CLOSE 37 1A ' i. 5 5 TANK OPEN - CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS 1 TOTAL CRUDE / r Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). m ■ ; — MMMMMff 58 --'' :T ' ■ ■ - ' '' ■ I .u.11 INH HMWlu. mmmTANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Cjd ROYALTY DELI VEFC 1 TICKET Form B.P. 18 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE GROSS BARRELS GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges). TANK OPEN CLOSE Received Above By By, (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). :T ' ■ - -^ .... m v.aa:'ici Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). Delivered Above TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). CLOSE TANK OPENC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER' TICKET No- Form B .P. 18. i Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- -19- .19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS | AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt;LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN J CLOSE TANK OPEN HimiM 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i TOTAL OF TANKS - TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Bv. Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). - .. A , . --- ^ I llMTITfilWirtllTiiTinilHflti'^Bfn''' ''——C.1MS. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVEffr TICKET Form B.P. 18. No Date (Opening Ganges). 19_ Delivered to Refillerv the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ,^ . ' Date (Closing Gauges). 19_ (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER ee SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.!. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE - 3 TANK OPEN CLOSE | I I TANK OPEN | CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE I TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ■'227( Delivered Above Received Ahove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- JU Bv. (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER).C.I IMS. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P, 18. ROYALTY DELIVER TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery the following Grade Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). _1&lt;L -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o r. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS AT TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ • • • ; ' TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE - TANK OPEN CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By_ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).G.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVEFff' TICKET No- 1561 Delivered to Refinery tlie following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Bate (Opening Gauges)— . Bate (Closing Gauges)—! —_ -19- _19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.f. TEMP. OF. % BARRELS AT 60'F TANK OPEN i ..... ' 119755 76 CLOSE ; : • ■31 ■ 86536 -45 Jf I | ! SO.449 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN * CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUBE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B .P. 18. A~1 ROYALTY DELIVER TICKET No.. ARA 3IAN C 'TT I}E OI L Date (Opening Gauges) 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel I)ate (Closing Q. au geg)__ 19_ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN 43 o6i 'v 7 -.64 99 CLOSE 7 -&gt;41 - -27 91 ■ TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 70918 • 9Z% Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT TW By By J - iKicrrrD. (RFFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ' (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVEF^T TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in buUk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION Or NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS AT 60 0 F. TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE NET TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered AboveC.JM5. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELIVEFtT TICKET No. 3RI' Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSION OF NET QARREUS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges)- _19_ -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS ! TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 3 LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS rEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK J OPEN 122571 CLOSE 37034 1 . ^5537 i 42*77 if I'l ^7^ TANK OPEN 1 1 i CLOSE 1 ! ! TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE ' 11176 Delivered Above ' Received Above Witnessed for BAHHEIN GOVERNMENT By By By v frirrtrik.icca-x^ d l otro l Kl-riTKlr^ETNJ-r'J (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C,11.-45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ROYALTY DELI VEF^I' TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery tile following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)_ Date (Closing Gauges)- -19_ .19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GkOSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER fle SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60 U F TANK OPEN fy ^ / : CLOSE f s Iff TANK OPEN j CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE / | TANK OPEN CLOSE r l TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - Delivered Above Received Above Witnesaed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (petrol-eum engineer). Bv. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.I 1.45. Form 6.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ ROYALTY DELIVERr TICKET ARABIAN CRUD S OIL „ .. . _ I)ate (Opening Gauges)- 19- Llelivered to Ketinery the foUowing Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Closing Gauges) — 19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 86 86299 - . CLOSE 16509 i 1 V* 'AjQ 70389 7 -L 7 A TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ i TANK OPEN ' CLOSE ♦ TANK OPEN | CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • 9197 .059 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By '— By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).iz:. harm B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELlVERIir TICKET Date (Opening Granges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Mexlliery tlie following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE GRAV, A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHBEIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), .. _. .TANK SAMPLES NET BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. AT 60°F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE C.11.45, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. NET TONS TANK OR LINE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL GROSS TONS Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT T&gt;_ r ^ — rPET.OU.UM ENG.NEER)* 7 (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). ' ' (STATE ENG.NE^ ^ ROYALTY DELIVERS TICKET No. TANK GAUGES CRUDE WATER &amp; SAND ETC. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). INCHES BARRELS Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges).TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR UNE AT 60°F, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE C.11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (!f ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No Date (Opening Gauges) 19_ Delivered to Refiner V the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel _ J Date (Closing Gauges) __19- (W1TH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). %- (REFINERY SUPERIN TENOENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER).Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited § ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. AT 60 o F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). h ..... r':The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges), Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPUES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 'F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT tt&amp;m - UC,11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 4 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. No Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinerv the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET QARREUS TO NET TONS). 0 0 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE f|0*r ; a f 91'73 TANK OPEN i CLOSE ' TANK OPEN CLOSE [ TANK OPEN CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE g ■ Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER)._ ( r Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited It ROYALTY DELIVER* TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP, TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above Mm — ■ ------ _- ^...The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERS TICKET Form B.P. 18. No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges}- Date (Closing Gauges)- 19 nVusn. 11 fV /fi 19 TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. 1 FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.!. TEMP. C F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN : 83879 CLOSE • - '* &lt;f f- oOO / TANK OPEN | CLOSE | TANK OPEN - CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE — TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 66* S Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. (ft ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH COMVERSiON OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- -19- -19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt;LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ' CLOSE j TANK OPEN i CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE ' _ TOTAL OF TANKS N TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By / . . r m ■ *— r~ r—t \ f C2 IT - C I KJ C OV C!l I OtT O I KJ TTIT KJ O FT KiT i (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER),IT 1 ' I ZSZZXZZ . '■- - -&gt; a ' ;v ^. . ., ,-r-^^'r^.y--'--- ■'^■r--' C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (4 ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. No. RAF ■ Delivered to Refillefy the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) : ; _19 Date (Closing Gauges)- Octcbe -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. OF. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F, NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK 13.4 OPEN ■' Jr 124G2$ •v. 12S711 CLOSE •S Cj/j ■ 96972 'Vi n Q '■ TV. re TANK OPEN CLOSE I 1 1 TANK OPEN - CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS % TOTAL CRUDE --r S4.3 Delivered Above By„ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. Received Above s sf (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. \ .. Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (* ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET ^O Form B.P. 18. RUDF on Date (Opening Gauges) £ .19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Olosinp- Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 'LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER 8t SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. C F. % BARRELS TANK 113 OPEN - 118719 r- 00 CLOSE •m life 333/1.4 &lt;5 # 9 J 0, 3?/; 0 c ' 30 , - T^lOt ■) ' v &gt; Of?- TANK OPEN CLOSE \ TANK OPEN 1 i CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE i TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE &gt; 79103 -.--..J-: Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- Arp Men (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER).w i I ■ C.11.4S. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (j ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET - ir - v -'- s ^;v.: . . . ^ - Form B.P. 18. No- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). E 19 Date (Closing Gauges) — -19—____ TANK OR UINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60° F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 6c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60'F TANK OPEN 1 • CLOSE a 'C 7M TANK OPEN CLOSE ' 1 TANK OPEN 1 1 1 CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 • CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS &gt; TOTAL CRUDE | 7073' Delivered 'Above Received Above By- (.REFINEHY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). n i ni ^ -- -- — MVC.11.45: Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited « ROYALTY DEL1VERX TICKET No 1MBIAK CRUDE OIL , Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the fojlowing Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges)-. 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. ©F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 1VV : ;V, ? .25 CLOSE 279S6 - 4? - 96*75 ,77 1 j o;; 77? -89 1'-Vr „A20 TANK OPEN | CLOSE TANK OPEN i 1 CLOSE 1 i TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 9 ^'77 &lt; ; :--a Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKEIN GOVERNMENT By By By, J fOFFIKJK'RV &lt;;MPPRINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH COt-iVERSiON OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). — ■I IT—i -Tir .'It. • ii'ii n-■ •.m C.11.-45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f Y ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No. Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- -19. -19- Delivered Above By- Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS ; a TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o r. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE Of &gt;2 ' ■ 10 12579 TANK OPEN j | .. CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE | TOTAL OF TANKS - TOTAL CRUDE (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINEER). -JForm B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f rROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges). Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS TANK OR LINE GRAV. A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above ' '&amp;um atU''C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f lROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET form B.P. 18. No Date (Opening Gauges)- 10_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel {Clo 'r^ Causes) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER 8e SAND ETC. NET BARRELS NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE • TANK OPEN | 1 CLOSE j 1 1 I TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHKE1N GOVERNMENT Bv By By J ' . (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45, 7 a3^ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ■ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARREUS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 - 1 TANK OPEN *{ 1 CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN | CLOSE - TANK OPEN CLOSE ■ TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE I Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER). / (j3 msmz1: wammmm ■ ' ■ ■ ' ; ' C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited C ROYALTY DELlVERi TICKET No- Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U .S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)_ -19- .19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN - CLOSE ac^v^Q TANK OPEN ' CLOSE TANK OPEN I CLOSE - : TANK OPEN 1 CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- (REFINERY SUPERlNrENDENT), By. (STATE ENGINEER). w nirihr'' «'i' 'i-r^ - 'c.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited C ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. No.— Date (Opening Gauges)— 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ^ ^ „ y Date (Closing Gauges) 19- (WITH CONVERSION Or NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Of GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. op % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE 'T i 1 ' . i -l- f TANK OPEN CLOSE ! ■ i TANK OPEN CLOSE V.' -I TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ;■ t ■ TOTAL CRUDE I Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By ______ By. ^ f nrrfr'. Mrrmv ci i Dtr o i kj t-c-vi (petroljeuw engineer). (refinery superintendent). (state engineer).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 0 F. TANK OR LINE A. P. I AT 60° F AT 60 o F. AT 60 o F, GRAV. A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHBK1X GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), -j. mu m rtt-The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ife ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 13. No Date (Opening Gauges) 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19_ (WITH CONVERSION Or NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Sc SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. o/ /o BARRELS TANK OPEN ' CLOSE TANK OPEN . CLOSE TANK OPEN J i CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN ■( [ CLOSE • ' TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • i Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By„ tPETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).I wumm rr « m ■ ■ X CI 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited d ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET form B.P. 13, No- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 0 F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60 o F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE 17 11073 TANK OPEN , CLOSE - TANK OPEN 1 | CLOSE 1 ! 1 i 1 TANK OPEN [ 1 CLOSE « TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 11073, Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. AMBIAK AMERICAN (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By- (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER). ■ ■■ TC ' ■ . a—M MI - ■ ''TOTAL CRUDE By—,— &lt;:N -■ w (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). TANK SAMPLES OBSERVED GRAV. TEMP. A.P.I. 0 F. A. P. I. AT 60° F. TANK TANK TOTAL OP TANKS OPEN CLOSE C.11.-45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ($ ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET ]^ 0 Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) 19. u JLSa/LI\^ ^ V^JJVXi»X±g CV f M. *J Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). V &amp; &amp; TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS AT 60 0 F. GROSS TONS TANK Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERKMENT (STATE ENGINEER). TANK GAUGES FEET INCHES GROSS BARRELS WATER &amp; SAND ETC. OPEN | CLOSE | TANK BARRELS OPEN CLOSE ;OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (PETROUEUW ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT), (STATE ENGINEER). iCP .2, C11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (# ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NETT BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges).. Date (Closing Gauges)- TANK OR LINE TANK TANK GAUGES OPEN j CLOSE GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. Op. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES OBSERVED GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. BARRELS NET BARRELS AT 60°F. NET TONS CLOSE TANK OPEN TANK OPEN | CLOSE J' — -■ V .. | isr - i - ^ : '-y- - • 1 , --The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (I ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- 23rd Ootob TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 'LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN -» J ^ CLOSE 70903 /C:/vcr ».685 TANK OPEN CLOSE '■i l TANK OPEN ' 1 CLOSE • TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS ;' . i TOTAL CRUDE fx:.Ox. f Delivered Above Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). B y- (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT HHBBBMuhbbbhbbibb .1.- ^ 1TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR UINE AT 60 o F. AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE C.11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (($ ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No Date (Opening Gauges) - 1 !&gt; Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Delivered Above Received Alove Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT - Rv By By, ' ' - ... — ( cDcrtr 1 KJC CJV ci rP'KJriP'KiTi (PETROUEUW ENGINEER). ' (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER,'.^ ii Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (^ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET Date (Opening Gauges)— Date (Closing Gauges)—, .. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES NET BARRELS TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OK TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above Delivered Above r ■■ - ' ' • ■ '■'-i-r. ' 'T '• r ■ —'m mm i ' v-.-.r.- ..i.r. - JL . s &lt;*•£ ^ „■' ■w- 1 'WThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. f ^ROYALTY DELIVERYt'TICKET N 0 1E4BT AM OBUBE Q7 .L Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ^ r , ai fl) 10 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). V ' o TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o P. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° P. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. C F • % BARRELS TANK OPEN 34 9713&lt; CLOSE 82 2263' ' 745^ ' V&gt; *•&lt;•'»■ TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 I 1 i | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • tUSi x 9740 Delivered Above By- Arabian American Oi Received Above s/Ssp* A Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT i. uorapa i (PETROL.EUM ENGINEER). By- (REF1NERY SUPERINTENDENT). By.. Fox' (STATE ENGINEER).The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY%*T1CKET Date (Opening Granges) l '- ; Z3TO Date (Closing Gauges)— 19 ..iS Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. °F. TANK OR LINE NET TONS TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Above. Delivered Above Tty Arabian ABierioan 011 0 nn'c.-v.:-.y &gt; (PETROLEUM ENGINEER),TANK SAMPUES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. 'F. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE 74446 TANK TANK TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE GROSS BARRELS 9213- NET TONS Delivered Above Received Above Arabian Amarlo&amp;n Oil Compear■ (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). mrz. 'JWi fll IHilTWTff' gSrifm-irvm-T^'- C.11.45. Form B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited f ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET No Date (Opening Gauges)— —19._ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gaUons per barrel Date ( Closillg Gauges)— If) (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). POT (STATE ENGINEER). Witnessed, for BAiiiiEIN GOVERNMENT GRAV, TEMP. A.P.I. 0 F.fcrm B.P. 18. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ROYALTY DELIVERY ^TICKET iiR&amp;EXAK ORUDB OIX» Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges) Delivered to Refill etv the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK TEMP. TANK OR LINE AT 60 o F TANK OPEN CLOSE OPEN CLOSE CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT Received Abvve Delivered Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (PETROLEUM ENGINEER), - - ' ' T ^ . HaKK - ■ — - kl—i n —- - ^TANK SAMPLES TANK TANK TOTAL OF TANKS C.I 1.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ^ROYALTY DELIVERY ^TICKET No. .•.SkBILiii CRUDE OH, Date (Opening Gauges) 25th ^ 46. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel , r!lriHin , T a a „ Pa ) Octcftrfc--- 2tuk 10 4c (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). NET BARRELS AT 60 o F, NET TONS CLOSE CLOSE Delivered Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). Received Above (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). TANK OR LINE GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. TOTAL CRUDE WATER 8c SAND ETC. TANK OPEN CLOSE 69823 910!- 250 OPEN CLOSE j 1 OPEN OPEN 69825 910; *260 (STATE ENGINEER). TANK GAUGES FEET INCHES BARRELS ^9244 Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENTC.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (^ROYALTY DELIVERY ^TICKET No.-H- Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges).. : 19- Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel /nwino- PS ) io (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS ^ AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER Be SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. I. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN CLOSE S3 ■- . . /-A 61914 .-57 63J '52 50?^ ill TANK OPEN i CLOSE 1 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 61853 3^ 80% ,411 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. :v For (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. ^ J-ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET No CRU DE Oil. , ( ^ 2Sth /r . Date (Opening Gauges) —— 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel . , n 3 ox Date (Closing Gauges) — 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I, TEMP. °F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 89142 TO 68608 a f- JLU CLOSE •J • • 72149 e Ol . t ''C : 2 ifyXO 460 TANK OPEN 1 l : CLOSE 1 | TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN - ' CLOSE - TOTAL OF TANKS • TOTAL CRUDE 9415 460 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By. (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPER IN FEN DENT). (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (tJROYALTY DELIVERY^ TTICKET Form B.P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) : 19_ Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ■ , , Date (Closing Gauges) 10 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). V &amp; &amp; ' TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMf OBSERVED ^LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER 8e SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN - 8270* 1.12 W CLOSE 22291 Lr. f A' ! c92 60.40 6034 &gt;.52 7864 ■ TANK OPEN . • CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN * CLOSE 1 TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • £034'- Vo— 786.4 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By By By (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER)C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Form B.P. 18. (it ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET No.__——— ARABIM CRUDE OIL Date (Opening Gauges) ! 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel „ ^ / ^ l _ ,, J Date (Closing Gauges) •. : 19— (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED 'LES A. P. I. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 3 A. &gt;3/1 97606 CLOSE ic » C'2- rO 61716 .73 | TH t {j 1067C TANK OPEN - CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE • - TANK OPEN CLOSE i TOTAL OF TANKS ' TOTAL CRUDE '81717 10670 Delivered Above By_ Oil C&lt; Received Above (PETROLEUM ENGINEER). By- Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By- i'or (STATE ENGINEER).Mg^Taapaiifcl The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET ARfeBIAN CRUDE OIL Delivered to Refinery tHe following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS), No.., Date (Opening Gauges) —19— Date (Closing Gauges) ^ ^ 19 ' - TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED ^LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER fic SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I, TEMP. 0 F. 0/ /o BARRELS TANK — 'V OPEN 32 92381 of 83 CLOSE 5 ^5/?- 1558( S3 76S0( 0 : 69 7598^ •e60 37.6 oa . S . s , 7591C|'.61 9917 ,721 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN - j CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE • ''591] 991 &gt;721 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT a, •Rv Arabian American Oil Oanpsj^y, gy CPETROUEUM ENGINEER). 7, (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. For (STATE ENGINEER,-. - - ■ &gt; WSL :■ - — ^ ,. 11^C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET AM BUN GB Wm OIL Form B.P. 18. No- A -1605 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WtTH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS), Date (Opening Gauges). Date (Closing Gauges)- 28th Ootobar } ig 48 &lt; _19- TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED &gt;LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER 8c SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A .P .I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK w. OPEN mm 2 24 ' CLOSE 1CW5/ ' C3 7361 So 49 962 3 c 516 TANK OPEN « CLOSE 1 1 - • TANK OPEN • CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 7363 6 ,o| 9&amp; 13.516 DMvered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- 3IAN AMERICAN OIXi COMPAN'J (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENOENT). By- (STATE ENGINEER). i — .— ' | — . . ' — _ gas-:-C.11.45. Form B.P, 13. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (t ROYALTY DELIVERY^ TICKET N 0 . . Date (Opening Gauges) 19—— Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel ,^ (l . .„ Date (Closing Gauges) -19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. - )* GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. ! net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° f. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 f. % BARRELS TANK 132 OPEN 436. CLOSE 6 - 63916c m ro 3T 63 27 63207 0 TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN CLOSE ' TANK OPEN | CLOSE TOTAL OP TANKS TOTAL CRUDE 63208, 00 5267 554 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- ARABIAN AMSRIGAN OIL CCMPAHY (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By_ (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By„ (STATE ENGINEER).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (t ROYALTY DELI VERYfrt TICKET No- Form B.P. 18. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) . Date (Closing Gauges)- -19- -19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60°F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° F. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.F.I. TEMP. op. % BARRELS TANK OPEN 7*2/4, QQ CLOSE i C 9807 TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN \ | CLOSE ' TANK OPEN | j | CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - 753-0 7 &lt; 9807 Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By. {PETROUEUW ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (state engineer).C.11.45. Form B.P. 13. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited O 'ROYALTY DELI VERYl 'TICKET No.—— '' r f :l ' '■••'viA C '' ; . i' 4?' ■ Date (Opening Gauges) 1-_19—.—, Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel . , „ Date (Closing Gauges) 19—__ (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). TANK OR L.1NE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS at 60 o F. GROSS TONS tank samples WATER &amp; SAND ETC. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons OBSERVED A. P. 1. AT 60° f. FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. 0 / ,0 BARRELS TANK OPEN 30 CLOSE - r - c 66 01929 1 37«J2| ..... TANK OPEN ii CLOSE | TANK OPEN CLOSE • - \ TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE - olooSi -00 Delivered Above Received Above By By By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER), (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (STATE ENGINBERj.TANK SAMPLES TANK GAUGES TANK OR LINE TANK TEMP. 0 F. AT 60 o F GRAV. A.P.I. TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). C.11.45 The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ^ROYALTY DELIVERY( TICKET ]S[ 0 Form B,P. 18. Date (Opening Gauges) 19 Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk' of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel Date (Closing Gauges) 19 (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS).C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (( ROYALTY DELIVER^ TICKET Form B.P. 18. No. Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (with conversion of net barrels to net tons). Date (Opening Gauges)- Date (Closing Gauges)- _19_ -19_ tank or line TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS tank temp. 0 f. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMPLES water &amp; sand etc. net barrels at 60 o f. net tons observed a. p. I. at 60° F. feet inches grav. a.p.i. temp. 0 F. % barrels TANK OPEN CLOSE '■ *'•- ; TANK OPEN CLOSE TANK OPEN ■ ; . CLOSE TANK OPEN 1 | i CLOSE ! TOTAL OF TANKS 1 TOTAL CRUDE Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVERNMENT By- (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). By. (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). By. (STATE ENGINEER;. ' (O? —•4C.11.45. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited ( ROYALTY DELIVERY TICKET Forrn B.P, 13. vXw isl Delivered to Refinery the following Crude Oil in bulk of 42 U.S. gallons per barrel (WITH CONVERSION OF NET BARRELS TO NET TONS). Date (Opening Gauges) Date (Closing Gauges) No.. 31ft Ot'.i ; J -19 ' ;&gt;... ..: T _19_ TANK OR LINE TANK GAUGES GROSS BARRELS TANK TEMP. 0 F. GROSS BARRELS AT 60 o F. GROSS TONS TANK SAMF OBSERVED a LES A. P. 1. AT 60° F. WATER &amp; SAND ETC. NET BARRELS AT 60 o F. NET TONS FEET INCHES GRAV. A.P.I. TEMP. 0 F. % BARRELS TANK OPEN ■?; v;v. CLOSE &gt;c * P . - J 1 w; ✓ -. TANK OPEN CLOSE | i - 1 i TANK OPEN CLOSE 1 TANK OPEN i ! : CLOSE TOTAL OF TANKS i | TOTAL CRUDE ^ * - '•r 17S Delivered Above Received Above Witnessed for BAHREIN GOVEHNMENT By By By (PETROUEUM ENGINEER). (REFINERY SUPERINTENDENT). (STATE ENGINEER).THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED FJ: A w a 1 i, { ^ ' Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. PA-755 22nd December, 19^S A ^£A/' ^ His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BAHREIN, ROYALTY TICKETS - NOVEMBER 19£S . File: 075.1 Dear Sir, I enclose herewith two copies each of the following Royalty Tickets: B-702-2 to B-722-1 (inclusive) These tickets represent the total amount of Crude Oil runs from tanksNos. 131, 152 and 153 to the Refinery, upon which the Royalty for November 194^, will be computed. I also enclose five extra copies of the Summary of Oil Deliveries. In addition to the above, please find enclosed one copy each of the following tickets, viz: A-1611-2 to A-1672-1 (inclusive) and A-1672-S, These tickets represent the amount of Arabian Crude Oil runs from tanks Nos. 132, 133, 134 and 14-3. Yours very truly. R. M. BROWN CHIEF LOCAL REPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Attach:</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001ba_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1707</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001ba</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1707</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 28/5 ROYALTY TICKETS.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-30T00:14:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (378 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order.</extent><extent>The foliation sequence starts at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 380; numbering is written in pencil, encircled, and may be found in the top right corner.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file mainly contains copies of Royalty Delivery Tickets showing the amount of oil shipped from July to November 1948, transmitted by Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) representatives to the Political Agent at Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0001ba#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>