<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024a_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-03T11:32:58.265Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">*8 * - NO /// OF I B86 f BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, bushire dated &lt;~july i860. FROM, lieutenant-colonel s*e* miles, OFFG, POLt Tl CAL RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF A H« B* 14 * S CONSUL GENERAL FOR FARS, TO, LIEUTENANT-COLONEL E.MOCKLER, POLITICAL AGENT AND CONSUL, MUSCAT, SI R, I HAVE THE HONOUR TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE RECEIPT OF YOUR LET TER NO Iee,DATED 20 TH JUNE I886,ENCLOSING COPY AND TRANSLATE OF - POSTSCRIPT TO A LETTER FROM SEYYID HAMAD BIN NASIR WALI OF SOHAR TO THE ADDRESS OF HIS HIGHNESS SEYYID TOORKEE AND STATING THAT T H E MINISTER SEYYID SAEED BIN MOHAMMED HAD ASKED ON BEHALF OF TnE oUw- TAN FOR AN EXPRESSION OF MY VIEWS WITH REGARD TO THE PROPOSALS MADE BY SEYYID HAMAD FOR THE ANNEXATION OF THE PORTS OF KHOR FAKAN, KELBA AND DIBBA TO HIS HIGHNESb's DOMINIONS. 'Kl , N RCPLY I BEG TO STATE THAT ANY AGGRESSIVE ENTERPRISES OF THE KIND ON THE PART OF HIS HIGHNESS SEYYID TOORKEE AGAINST HIS NEIGHBOURS THE JOWASIM^WITH WHOM HE IS NOW AT PCACE^ WOULD BE IN -'.Y • OPINION HIGHLY UNADVI SABLE AND WOULD PROBABLY, IF UNDERTAKEN,TERMI- NATE IN RESULTS VERY INJURIOUS TO HIS HIGHNESS 1 INTERESTSF - 3. 1 SHALL be glad to learn from you that his highness t HAS NO SERIOUS INTENTION OF ADOPTING SUCH SCHEMES AS THOSE t PUT FORTH BY THE WALI AND THAT THE LATTER HAS BEEN INSTRUCTED TO ABSTAIN FROM CARRYING ON INTRIGUES WITH THE PL'O F ~E OF IN DEPENDENT CHIEFS IN HIS NEIGHBOURHOOD. ^ - | HAVE ThC HONOUR TO BE, i SI R, YOUR MOST OBEDIENT SERVANT, t DT LIEUT - COLONEL, OFFG, POLI Tl CAL RESIDENT, A | ^ |THC UNDER SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA TO, THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF. FOREIGN DEPTT . 0 ATED,SIMLA,THE 2 ?TH JULY &gt;886, S I R, I AM DIRECTED TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE RECEIPT OF YOUR LETTER and enclosures no 79,dated the 7th july 1886,regaroing a proposal made TO THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT BY THE WALI OF SOHAR TO ANNEX THREE PORTS ON THE OMAN COAST. 2 . IN REPLY I AM TO STATE THAT YOUR ACTION IN THE MATTER IS APPROVED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. I HAVE, &amp;C, SD W.J.CUNNINGHAM,OFFG,UNDER SECY! TO THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, UO/£ZOF 1886, BRITISH RESI DENCY 'AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHI RE DATED ''’AUGUST | 886 , memo: COPY FORWARDED FOR THE INFORMATION OF THE POLITICAL AGENT• LIEUT-CO LONEL,FROM, NO /6% OF Ibb6, BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSUDATS GENERAL,* 7 it BUSHIRE,DATED /? —JUNE Ibb6, LIEUTENAlfT-CODONED S.B.MIDES, OFFG / POLITICAL, RESIDENT PERSIAN GULF &amp; H # B.M'S CONSUL GENERAL FOR PARS, LIEUTENANT-COLONEL E.MOCKLER, H.B.M'S POLITICAL AGENT &amp; CONSUL, MUSCAT. SIR, I HAVE THE HONOUR TO ENCLOSE UNDER FLYING SEAL THE ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THIS RESIDENCY FOR THE PAST YEAR AND SHALL BE OBLIGED BY YOUR ATTACHING YOUR OWN REPORT 'THERETO * AND POSTING IT TO SIMLA BY THE SAME MAIL AS YOU RECEIVE IT BY. v IF YOUR OWN REPORT IS NOT READY PLEASE POST MY REPORT AND SUBMIT YOUR OWN DIRECT TO GOVERNMENT BY THE FOLLOWING MAIL FURNISHING THIS OFFICE WITH A COPY SUBSEQUENTLY FOR RE CORD. I HAVE THE HONOUR TO BE, SIR, YOUR MOST OBEDIENT SERVANT,APPENDIX A TO PART II. NOTES OF A TOUR THROUGH OMAN AND EL-DHAHIREH, By Lieut.-Colonel S. B. Miles. The general tranquillity of the country, and other reasons, at the close of 1885, gave me an opportunity of making a tour through the Provinces of Oman and Dhahireh, which I had not previously been able to explore, and which Lieutenants Wellsted and W hitelock, wh 0 travelled in 1835, 50 years ago, are the only Europeans who are known to have visited. I was also desirous of making the personal acquaintance of the more important Shaikhs in those parts with whom I had not hitherto come in contact during my residence at Muscat. The route I had proposed to take was through Semail and Zikki to Adam, thence across the Nejd El-Dhahireh to Obri and Dhank, and then descending the Wady Howasineh, return by the Batineh Coast to Muscat. This programme was carried out, with this difference, that I returned from Muskin by a shorter road through Rostak. The Sultan was good enough to appoint Sayid Hamood Bin Nasir, the son of the Wall of Muttrah, as leader of the escort, and Nasir Bin Muhammad, Shaikh of the Beni Kelban, as guide and Kcfeer. His Highness’s Secretary, Suliman, and Shaikh Salaam-bin- Hamid, also accompanied the party, which consisted altogether of 23 persons. We left Muscat on the 11 th December, slept at Wateyah the first night and at Fanja on the second, and on the 13th December, after halting at Semail for two hours, reached Seyjeh, a town of the Beni Jabir in the Wady Beni Ruweyheh. The storms and floods of March 1885 did immense damage in the Semail valley, and the people were still lamenting their houses washed down, their date tiees and cattle swept away, and their crops spoilt; the river rose 24 feet, and the marks of its highest point were still visible on the banks. Some of the few surviving members of the last dynastic family, the Yaarebeh, are living in retirement at this town, Seyjeh, whither they have taken refuge from the persecutions of their successors the ALbu-8aidis. December 14th .—I had sent to Nasir bin Muhammad, the head Shaikh of the Beni Ruweyheh, immediately on arriving here, requesting him to accompany me as far as Zikki, and soon after starting this morning we met him on the road with two other Shaikhs. He resides at Obal, a village three miles from Seyjeh, and was anxious we should pay him a visit there, but I declined from press of time. Obal is a picturesque spot; it appears like a white hill surmounted by a tower and skirted by a dense grove of date palms. Away to our left, just opposite Obal, is the Nejd of Wady Akk with its three spurs branching off to the south, forming the valleys of Semed, Andam, and Ibrah. The Wadi Beni Ruweyheh is here very narrow* with high ranges on either side. About half way we reach Mezberriyeh, which is Considered the Nejd or highest point of the valley, and has an altitude of 2,200 feet. From hence the road runs level or slightly descending to Zikki. Passing Wady Meteh and Wady Karoot we reached Zikki at 2 P.M., and I put up in a Sabla outside the fort, which I did not enter this time as I had examined it thoroughly on my former visit ten years before. It was rebuilt in the early years of this century by Muhammad Nasir-el-Jabri, and having since stood several sieges is now in a very dilapidated state, but still strong. The circumstances under which Shaikh Nasir surrendered this fort to His Highness Sayid Turki about a year a o&gt;o were fully reported at the time. The present Wali on behalf of the Sultan is Shaikh Muhammad bin Sinan. The town is inhabited by two rival tribes who occupy separate walled enclosures or Hujrahs, and maintain almost incessant warfare with each other. They are divided by the broad bed of the Wady Halfain, the Nizar dwelling to the south of the stream, while the Yemin Hujrah, as well as the fort, stand on the right bank at the edge of a cliff some'200 feet high. December 15^.—Having obtained fresh baggage camels I proceeded to-day to Manh, which was reached at noon. Descending the steep cliff into the Wady Halfain, we rode along the left bank for a mile until we came opposite to Zikkeyt, a small quadrangular walled villacre of the Beni Riyam, and then crossing the stream traversed a wide and level plain having a gentle declivity towards the south to Manh. The Wady Halfain is here a broad but shallow river, but soon loses itself in the sand, though it is said after heavy rain to reach the sea at Mahot. The bed is a highway for caravans from Oman to the Ghubbet Hashish, and is inhabited by numerous Bedouins, as water is found, everywhere near the surface. The frontier town of Adam is, like Zikki, occupied by two hostile tribes, and hearing here that a collision had lately occurred between them, I determined to leave half my party with the bao-gage at Manh and push on with the escort only, to which I here added six Jenebek2 MH wm » m ' Bedouins. After a halt of two hours we started for Izz, a village in the direction of Adam and about 5 miles from Manh, where we camped for the night. On the following day, the 16th, leaving Izz at 7-80, we rode over a level but gently descending plain, at a good pace, to Adam, which we reached at 1-30 , direction near y ue south, a little east. At half an hour we passed the Wady Kalbuh, a fine stream of watej which rises above Nezwa, and after running almost parallel to Wady Halfain, falls into the Ghubbet Hashish. The plain we are crossing is quite uninhabited, and we met not a single traveller on the road. There is plenty of game, however—houbara, partridge, and sandgrous e rise up on all sides, while gazelles and hares start up occasionally from the dwarf mimosas and bunches of desert grass about. As we approach Adam two low hills rise up in front, one on each hand of the road. The one to our right is Jebel Sulakh and the other Jebel Mushmar 5 they are both perfectly arid, and appear to be about 800 or 1,000 feet in height. As one approaches it the appearance of Adam with the dark lines of its extensive date groves is veiy icfieshing to the eye after the glare and monotonous aspect of the plain we had traversed: it is a true oasis in the desert. I was greeted very civilly here by all parties, and having been invited to visit the town and forts I spent the whole afternoon in seeing what was to he seen. A cousin of our leader Sayid Hamood took us first to the quarter of the Al-bu-Saidis, a walled enclosure named the Jami, inhabited by about 150 families. Ihe chief object of inteiest luie was the house in which the Imam Ahmad, the founder of the present dynasty, was born. He was of low origin, being a camel driver like his father before him ; being a man of energy and courage, however, he rose to be Jemadar of the garrison and then Wali of Sohar. He was subsequently elected Imam by the people in gratitude for his expulsion of the Persians. Taking leave of the Al-bu-Saidis at Jami I went over to the quarters of the town occupied by their enemies, the Mohatik, which are five in number, and over which I was shown successively by their Shaikh, Hamid-bin-Khamis, and by the Temimeh of the Jenebeh^ Saif-bin-Hamud. There are two other quarters occupied by the Shaibani and Beni Wail tribes, making eight in all. As I visited one section after another, I was somewhat surprised and amused at the intense curiosity exhibited by the Arabs here. They not only lined each side of the road in great numbers as I walked through the date grove from one quarter to another and blocked my path to stare at me, but after I had passed them would scamper round another way to get in front again and so gain another gaze at the stranger. They were all perfectly well behaved and did not attempt to offer the slightest rudeness, but 1 never saw the like of their open-mouthed curiosity. There is a large fort here originally built by the Imam Ahmad and repaired by the Imam Azzan in 1869, but it is hardly cared for and weakly garrisoned, for in truth the Adamites are too distant from other tribes to be concerned in the usual intestinal wars of Oman, and reserve their powder and lead for each other. The population as near as I can guess numbers 1,500, composed of five tribes, the Moharik, Al-bu- Saidis, Sheyabina, Majabera, and Beni Wail, of which the most important is the Moharik. The elevation of Adam above the sea is 850 feet, being 500 feet lower than Manh and 1,300, lower than Zikki, which is - 2,150. No other town of Oman lies nearly so far south as this the outlying picket, as it were, towards the great sand desert which stretches away to the Yeman and the Hejaz, and which is known here, as well as to all the Bedouins of Southern Arabia, as the Roba-el-Khali. Looking towards the south and east, neither hill nor habit ation meets the eye, the line of horizon is as unbroken as the sea; while northward in the distance rises the grand pile of Jebel Akhdar which towers up to a height of 10,000 feet. Most of the Bedouin tribes, which inhabit the border of the huge wilderness on the edge of which we are standing, contribute contingents who roam over it with their camels, but the number of these wanderers is necessarily very small, for the only water found is that left in pools in the water-courses after rainfall and some springs of brackish vTater welling up here and there. Animal life is not entirely absent,—the oryx, the wild ass, and two species of gazelle are found everywhere, and the ostrich is met with in the northern and western part of the desert: it does not approach Oman* The soil is said to be everywhere saltish or nitrous. 17th .—I returned to Manh during the day and encamped here in one of the gardens near the fort. Manh is rather a scattered town with a population of some 2,000 souls of mixed tribes. ^ It has been well described by Wellsted, who cannot suppress a cry of admi ration at the extent and luxuriance of the diversified cultivation around. He says :— “ Minna differs from the other towns in having its cultivation in the open fields. As we crossed these, with lofty almond, citron, and orange trees, yielding a delicious fragrance on either hand, exclamations of astonishment and admiration hurst from us. Is this Arabia ? We said, this is the country we have looked on heretofore as a desert ? Verdant fields of grain and sugar-cane stretching along for miles are before us; streams of water flowing in all directions intersect our path, and the happy and contented appearance of the peasants agreeably helps to fill up the smiling picture.” #Manh did not wear quite so fair a dress at the time of my visit, but the district is undoubtedly a well-watered and fertile one. All the springs here, as they are at Adam and Bahilah, and indeed at most places in Oman proper, are hot; the temperature varying from 102 to 1 12 degrees Fahrenheit. There is no Wali here on behalf of the Sultan; the leading man and dispenser of justice is the Metowwa Muhammad-bin-Mesud, who is reputed to be the most learned man in Oman. 18th .—I decided to move on to l^ahilah to-day, because though it would have saved us a day’s journey to visit Nezwa first, as my Arab companions did not fail to represent to me, 1 was desirous of exploring the country between Manh and Bahila. We left at 8 a.m. and at 9 reached Karsha, a small hamlet of seventy houses. At 9-30 we crossed the W. Kalbuh, and at 10-45 halted for coffee at Timsa, a picturesque village under a hill with a large date grove. An hour later we came to Khamaili, a mystic pool of water famed throughout Oman as the source of all magic and sorcery. ^The fable is that a man lies im prisoned by enchantment deep down under the water, which has become red from his blood. Any one venturing to drink it becomes enchanted immediately and falls under the magi cian’s spell. I drank some nevertheless and found it very sweet and good. After a long ride over a stony plain covered with low black hills we came to Fut, a small hamlet to our left, and soon after the singularly situated town of Bahilah comes into sight. The first view presents a long white wall with bastions at intervals enclosing a large extent of cultivated ground with a huge white fort and lofty tower standing on an eminence in the centre, picturesquely overlooking and commanding the town beneath. Its appearance indeed is more striking than that of any other town I have seen in Oman. From the time we had been sighted on the road, the garrison had continued to fire guns at intervals from the walls as we approached, and as we drew nearer the Shaikh with a party of horsemen, and followed by an immense concourse of people, issued from the gate and rode down the bed of the Wady to meet us. We then halted while the Shaikh and his followers exhibited their skill in horsemanship, galloping round in a circle and firing off their matchlocks at full speed, running races with each other, &amp;c. After this was over we formed procession and rode slowly on through the gate into the town, where we were lodged in a pleasant house and garden. After receiving a visit from Shaikh Nasir-bin-Hameyed I occupied the rest of the day i n examining the space within the walls and the town. On the following morning I paid a visit to the Shaikh at his fort, where he received me very courteously. He is a heavy-featured, unprepossessing looking young man of 22, with much decision of character and evidently complete master of the position. He has obtained some notoriety lately by his murder of his two elder brothers, Barghash and Rashid, the circumstances of which have been reported. I learned here that Shaikh Barghash had long suspected Nasir of sinister designs against him and had prohibited his entering the fort. Nasir, however, managed to persuade Rashid to join in a plot for killing Barghash, and having by the help of three slaves concealed himself one night in Barghash’s apartments, he shot the latter dead while asleep. Nasir then proclaimed Rashid Shaikh of the tribe, in place of Barghash; but Rashid wa s incompetent and soon allowed all matters to fall into the hands of Nasir, who, some months later, becoming tired of the situation, quietly shot his brother through the back one day while they were riding out to Yabrin together. No disturbance ensued, and Shaikh Nasir has since re tained possession, but, though undisputed ruler of Bahilah and nominal Wali on behalf of the Sultan, he has not yet been recognised as Temimeh of the Beni Ghafir in place of Barghash. The fort is a vefy large building with two towers, one of which is named the “ Burj-el-Rih,” is very lofty, and commands a splendid view of the whole valley. Our guide, Shaikh Nasir-el- Kelbani, who is the Wazir of Bahilah, told me that the fort was named Hisn Tamah from the Nabhani who built it. I was allowed to photograph the fort from different positions. The upper part, or Alaya, of Bahilah is chiefly .occupied by the Beni Ghafir; the lower town, or S if ala, being inhabited by the Beni Shekeyl, Ibriyeen, Beni Ghafir, and others. The whole town is divided into 20 separate enclosed haras or quarters, and contains a population of 6,000 souls. The outer wall embracing the town and cultivation is an irregular parallelogram cover ing an area of about two square miles. I observed no cultivation outside of this wall, which is traditioned to have been built by a woman named Gheitha 600 years-ago. Inside were fields of wheat, jowari, bai ley, lucerne, sugar-cane and cotton, besides extensive date groves and orchards of other fruit. The manufactures here are brown cotton cloth, loongiea, goats’- hair cloaks, matting, and hulwa. Bahilah is believed to be a very ancient town, and it was the capital of Oman under the Nebhani dynasty in the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries. It is the “ Barler” of Wellsted, who has somewhat misplaced it on his map. The people here have good4 /Stf, w i J houses and seem well off and contented ; they were still lamenting, however, the damage d in the great storm of March 1885, when the river rose many feet and oamrf »« many tonses and date trees. I was much pleased with the general reception I met with here and was glad to have seen so interesting a place. The elevation of Bahilah is l,oo ee . In the afternoon, accompanied hy Shaik Nasir-bin-Hamid, who insisted “P°' every attention in his power, 1 started for Yabrin, which ,s four miles distant, an 1 winch was reached before sunset. The Shaikh and his followers amused themselves by * all “l » ' ' and running races with each other all the way. Yabrin is merely a small fort, gar, .son d y six Arabs, without any dependent township, and there is no settled population heie. y it was of more importance, and in the days of the Imam Belarab bin 8ul an hi Yaareby.who built the fort about the year 1690 A. D., it was the capital of Oman. s ic su revealed in all its glory and distinctness of outline the huge mountain called Jebel-el-Kor, which lies to the westward of Bahilah and forms the geographical boundary between vinces of Oman and Dhahireh. It is quite detached from the Jcbel Akhdar range, an “PF to have a height of 6,000 or 7,000 $eet. The chief road from Bahilah to Dhah.reh runs south of this mountain and is called by some the “ Nejd-el-Makhanm, by ot icis ^ O Dhahireh.” The northern road is steeper and more difficult, and is known as t le i tjo - Barak.” After consulting with the Arabs I resolved after leaving Nezwa to cross over o Dhahireh by the northern pass, and as it turned out it was fortunate I did so. 20t/i .—We despatched a Kossid early to give notice to Shaikh Hilal at Nezwa of our ap proach, and started about Sam.; we passed a hamlet in the Wadi Masalla, reac e aiioo at 2, and at 3-30 came to the outskirts of Nezwa. As we passed the outlying watch towers commanding the various approaches, the men therein fired their matchlocks, and as we came nearer, the fort took up the firing with its big guns. Descending into the bed of the w adi Kalbuh, wp rode through a dense crowd of people until we met Shaikh Hilal-bin-Zahir, w 10 ic. ceived us very civilly and conducted us to asubla near the gate. I was then taken to the lesi- dence allotted to me, and an hour later was visited by Shaikh Hilal, who informed me that the house I was in belonged to a brother of Sayid Nasir-bin-Ali, who was the Governor of Muscat, and was murdered in his house there during the time of Sir B. Frere's visit in 1S73. Shaikh Hilal is a dignified and powerfully built man for an Arab, with a broad, expressive countenance, showing much firmness and intelligence. He is now one of the most prominent men in Oman; his artful diplomacy in turning every move in the intrigue against the late Wali a few years ago to his own advantage and in gaining possession of, first, the fort, and then the government, of Nezwa, drew general attention to him, and he is now looked on as second only to Saleh-bin-Ali himself as a leader. He gave me the idea of being the same sort of man that the Imam Ahmed bin Said was—able, resolute, and capable of any villainy to compass the end he had i^ view. 21st .—Shaikh Hilal paid me an early visit; and we had a long geographical talk, during which he gave me an account of the watersheds of the country. He said very little cotton was o-rown at Nezwa and no cloth made whatever, but that indigo was largely cultivated and used to dye American cloth brought from Muscat. Nezwa was famous for its copper and brass work. After breakfast I took a walk through the town and environs, and was surprised at the prosperity and populousness of the place. Nearly all the tribes of the country seem to he represented here, the predominating ones being the Beni Riyam, who occupy Alaya, and the Beni Hinah, who have been introduced extensively by Shaikh Hilal since he assumed power here. Sifala has six haras, viz., —“Akr,” in which stands the fort and which has a fine gate to its enclosure; “ Saal,” unwalled; “ Khorasin,” walled and contiguous to “ Akr,” “ Khorasitin,” “ Haret-el-wady,” and another. The two Wadies “Kalbuh” and “ Abyad ” divide the town and join near the fort by T,he market. Abyad has a more abundant supply of water than Kalbuh, and consequently supplies nftore felejes. The fort consists of two parts, the “ Kila” and the “ Hisn.” The latter is a quadrangular enclosure, at one corner of which stands the Kila, a huge circular tower 80 feet high, and considered by the Arabs to he by far the strongest fort in Oman. I did not enter it, but Wellsted says that three-fourths of the height, which he gives at 150 feet, are filled up solid with earth and stones, and that the narrow passage inside, leading up from the doorway and forming the only entrance, has seven iron doors to it. Leaving Nezwa at 4-30 I marched to Tanuf, a distance of 8 miles, the same evening, having promised Shaikh Suliman bin Saif bin Suliman-el-Riyami, who had intercepted me on the road the day before, to spend a night in his town. It is a compact and substantial-looking place, fortified with a wall, on which are mounted two guns, and there is a large date grove in the ravine at the back. This ravine is the Wady Hyin, and up it lies the road from Nezwa to Rostak known as the “Tareek-el- Shas” '/iVI 22nd .—Having procured fresh baggage camels we rode to-day in the direction of the Akbat-el-Baralc, by which we intended to cross over to Dhahireh. Our road led over a stony plain crossed by numerous water-courses and very barren. We passed several villages,— Homreh, Ghumriyer, and Belad Sait, &amp;o.,—the inhabitants of which were in a very excited state and usually fired at us on our approach, but they quieted down very easily always when Shaikh Nasir Kelbani had explained who we were. The cause of the panic was that a T;roop of Jenebeh had ridden by in the night; we could see the footprints of their camels; and as they are at feud with the Beni Hiuah, who occupy these villages and are the predominant tribe in these parts, it was expected thClt the Jenebeh were on the war-path, and that their object was to raid the district. We heard to-day also that a band of seventy mounted marauders, coming from Dhahireh to raid the outskirts of Manh, had crossed the Nejd-el- Makharim and camped near Yabrin the day we had left it, and our party congratulated themselves that we had not gone by that road. We now enter the Wady Ghol, which uait^s with the Wady Shams lower down to form the Wady Bahilah, and ascend its broad bed, here tolerably well wooded and inhabited by shepherds, for two hours, until we reach a hamlet called Mithar, near which we halt and bivouac for the night at an elevation of 2,600 feet. 23rd .—The crossing of the pass to-day took us nine hours, and the camels were rather tired when we reached our destination in the Wady Ain at 4 p.m. Continuing to ascend the Wady Ghol, which becomes gradually rougher and steeper, we reach the summit about 11 a.m., and find that the barometer indicates 3,700 feet. From this point we look down a small valley running south, called the Wady Seifam, and then commence to descend the other side of the Akbat-el-Barak, the Jebel-el-Kor here towering 3,000 feet above us. After crossing a small stretch of level ground, the road falls into the Wady Ein, a large and seemingly important valley, with a running stream trending westwards. At 2 p.m. we arrive at Hail, a village of the Beni Hinah, under a jagged, square, perpendicular cliff called Jebel Misht, or Mount Comb. Our approach threw the villagers at El Bin into some trepidation, and they fired a volley at us, one of our camels having his leg grazed by a bullet. They afterwards apologised and explained that they were not accustomed to see so large a party enter their valley. It appears to be the fashion dt the larger towns for the soldiers to salute distinguished strangers with blank cartridge; at the smaller and more defenceless places, they sometimes salute you with bullets, but Arabs are so skilful at missing with their quaint matchlocks, that there is very rarely any harm done. The people here gave me the names of several hamlets existing in the ravines and valleys formed by the spurs of Jebel-el-Kor, viz .,—“ Shedait/” “ ISadan,” “ Sint,” “ Sunt,” &amp;c. Early the next morning we continued our journey down the Wady Bin for some way, and then turned off to the right to Bat, a village of the Beni Kelban, with two towers and four hundred inhabitants, where we halted for an hour; distance about 12 miles. We then proceeded on to Wahaireh, at which place the watchmen maintained a desultory fire on us for some time until we expostulated, and mutual explanations resulted in a treaty of peace • the people then came out in procession to welcome us and insisted on our staying with them for the night, which we agreed to do, and they treated us very hospitably. There is a good stream of water here, and the cultivation around includes wheat, indigo, sugar-cane, jowaree, plantains, mangoes, lucerne, dates, limes, &amp;c., &amp;c. 23th December .—Left Wahaireh early and rode to Dereez, a town 8 miles farther on, where the Shaikh and his people came out in a very friendly way to greet us; those on horseback running races with each other, while the others stood around chanting their war songs. There is a email tumble down fort here with two guns; population about 1,200, all Beni Ghafir. After a short halt 1 left Dereez and rode on to visit the fort of Einein, a famous bone of contention in this country for many years past. It is merely a large house flanked by two towers, and did not appear to me a strong place. There is a large date grove n*ar, watered by three felejes which are commanded by the fort; but there are no inhabitants. After Einein we passed Iraki, a village of the Ibriyeen, and then Ghabbi, formerly a large town, now in ruins, having been destroyed by the Beni Ali in local wars some ten years ago. At 2 p.m. we reached Obri, and soon after one of the camel- men came in and complained of having been looted by robbers on the road. He had lagged behind and had been cut off by two scamps who had taken bis matchlock and dagger and a bundle of clothes belonging to my servant, but had not touched the photo graphic kit and other baggage on the camel. The camelman was a native of this place and had imagined the thieves would not molest him, but they are no respecters of persons. On enquiry it turned out that the two robbers were part of the band of seventy who had gone on a marauding expedition to Oman as mentioned above. They had attempted to plunder a x /( village there, but had been attacked by the people, and in the scuffle two robbers and three villagers had been slain. The band had just returned and were scattering to their homes and the two scamps after overhauling our camel had decamped to a distant village. The Sheikh icie was unable to do anything in the matter, and so I got no redress. Obri has by far the largest and most frequented market in El-Dhahireh, and it is besides the thieves bazar of the province, where all the loot collected in Oman and the Betinah is brought and sold by auction 1 icre- are 62 shops in the bazar displaying all the commodities usually required by Arabs and noticed goldsmiths, blacksmiths, carpenters, and other ^tradesmen in it. The Sheikh Muha- mad-bin-Abdulla-el-Yakeebi was very friendly and agreeable and accompanied me all over the town; he was very particular in showing me the Jami mosque, which the inhabitants are very proud of, as it is one of the largest and best in Oman. He told me Obri was a famous place for fruit, and that limes, mangoes, dates, peaches, apricots, figs, &amp;c., were largely exported. There is a small fort here with a high tower, but I did not go over it. Obri was visited by Wellsted and Whitelock of the Indian Navy in March 1836. They were here two days ap parently, and the spot where their tent was pitched was pointed out to me. Their visit was badly timed, as the Wahabees were then marching through, and the two officers were hissed and stoned out of the town and compelled to return to the coast. There are 16 haras or quarters in the town, and the population is about 3,000, composed of many different tribes. The elevation is 1,180 feet. On the 26th, riding due north for 26 miles, we reached I)hank at 4 p.m. After cross ing the Obri range, which has an average height of 400 feet, we traversed a level plain all the way, with low hills away to the right, stretching up to the high range known as the Hajar. To the left or westwards there are several villages, but no sign of a hill breaks the level line of the horizon. It rained heavily to-day, and the air was bitterly cold, so by the time we reached Mazun, a Belooch town 18 miles from Obri, we were all shivering. The people at Dhank were very civil and well behaved, but not demonstrative; they said they had not seen a European here before. The number of souls here is about 4,000, composed of four tribes—the “ Naeem,” “ Washasha,” “ Azeez, ” and “ Al-boo-shamis.” They make cloth here. The Wady Dhank and the Wady Boo’Karba both join the Wady Safa, a large water-course in the ramool or desert, running to Abuthabi almost parallel with the Wady Ein; the “ Jebel Okdat ” of Wellsted is purely mythical; there is no hill range in that direction whatever, except Hafeet, near El-Beraimi. 27th .—Lucerne grass not being grown at Dhank, our camels had nothing for supper last night but dates and barley. Starting at 8, we wind up the narrow stony bed of the Wady Dhank until we emerge from the gap in the low hills through which it flows, when it rapidly widens out to a breadth of half a mile with a fine stream of water in the middle. The banks are here about 100 feet high, and it is on this expanse that the famous battle of Dhank was fought between Sayid Turki and Sayid Azzan-bin-Kais in 1869, in which Sayid Azzan was completely routed with a loss of 300 killed. His force consisted of 4,000 men and a field- piece, but Sayid Turkics force, though numerically very inferior, was more skilfully handled and sustained but slight loss in the engagement. Sayid Azzan never recovered the prestige h e lost in this contest. After four miles we come to the village of Doot, and seven miles farther is Fida, with a very long though narrow fringe of date-palms along the Wady. Both these places belong to the Beni Zeed. Five miles further is Yenkal, which I was unable to visit, as our road at Fida branched off to the right and led us across a barren plain to Aridh } where we were to halt for the night. This place, like Makiniyat, belongs to our guide, Sheikh Nasir-el-Kelbani, but the people are a mixture from the Beni Shekey 1 , Omar, and Kelbani tribes. There is a small tower here but no fort. 28th .—We left Aridh at 7-30 and reached Muskin at 12, the ground rising gradually Muskin is in the Wady El-Kebeer and belongs to the Beni Kelban. Its elevation is 2,750 feet. The Hajar range, like the Jebel Akhdar, slopes gradually to the desert on the western ”side, but on its seaward or eastern face falls abruptly and presents a precipitous aspect. From noon to dark we continue to descend the eastern face of this range, winding down in a S. E. direction among narrow ravines and steep declivities until we reach Mahbeh, a small hamlet in the Wady Bani Ghafir, where we camp for the night. To-day the high peak of Jebel Shoum was seen by me for the hrst time. _ 29th .—For some hours we descend the Wady Beni Ghafir until we came to Dahas, a walled town with a fort in the centre on an eminence. Farther on we came to the Wady Sahtan of the Beni Ghafir, who have recently wrested possession of it from the Ibriyeen, and at 4 p.m. reach Rostak, where we are hospitably received by Syed Hamad bin-el-Imam in the 5absence of Sayid Ibrahim-bin-Kais, who had gone to Hazam. We sat down at Sayid Hamad’s house to rest ourselves, and while there up came Sayid Saud, the second son of the late Imam Azzan, a bright, intelligent youth of 18, his face beaming with smiles to find so strange a party in his out-of-the-way, quiet old town. They were all surprised to see us here, as Sayid Hamad said they imagined I was still on the other side of Jebel Akhdar. Sayid Saud lives with his *uncle Ibrahim in the fort, a dilapidated mediaeval castle, said to be of pre-Islamitic days and very ancient. Rostak is the second largest town in Oman, Semail being the first; there are 15 villages in fief to Rostak, and the population including these is 14,000. There is a good bazar of eighty shops here. The upper part of the valley in which Rostak is situated is called Wady Auf, the lower part is Wady Far ah. Its elevation is 800 feet. On the 30th we rode down past the towns of Mansur and Jemmeh to Burka, 45 miles and the next day rode in along the coast to Muscat. * ^ f u ■ikS IK, Dated Muskat Political Agency and Consulate,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Political'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1885/1886</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-11-16T22:51:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (64 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 66; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains papers that discuss the possible annexation of Khor Fakhan, Kalba and Dibba by Oman from June-July 1886, as well as administration report and trade returns from 1885-86. The file also contains a discrete report on weights and measures employed in the pearl trade in the Gulf by Lieutenant Colonel Edward Mockler the Political Agent in Muscat, as well as separate reports entitled 'Notes of a tour through Oman and Dhahira' by Lieutenant Colonel Samuel Barrett Miles. Ancillary papers discuss relations between Oman and Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Political affairs</topic></subject><subject><topic>Borders</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00024a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>