<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000092_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T01:49:51.819Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Tele gran Prom GTG Political, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire. No.200 Dated 27th August, 1941. Please telegraph whether mils sent to you by post between 8th and 18th August under my way hills Noss 31, 32, 33 and 34, have been received.Telegram From To No .3/14 Jated 27th August, 1S41. GTC. Britconsul, Bushire. Political, Bs.hrain. Your telegram 27th August 2G0. Last //ay Bill received from you was 30 of July 11thGTC ’ll 7 Telegram From To No.202 Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. Bated 28th August, 1941. ^ 1 $-— Your 3/14. Tails. Grateful if you could possibly let me know whether the mails have been confiscated or will be returned to us. SNo.1682-14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. 31st August, 1941. To The Sub-Postmaster f Bahrain * i/emoran'liui. It has been reported that the registered mail sent by thia oi*fice to the address of Ills ^ajesty^ Consul-General, Bushire, by 3.S. '■^IIYAlfG', 3.3. 'BP.HPETA' and E.3. '’YiRA.I.A”, on 7th, 14Uh and 18th Aupa.t ronpcctively was not landed at BushiT'e. Will you therefore please let raa know v»h.at hardened to other postal mail hags which were sent to Bush ire. by these boata? for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded to Messrs. Cray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. Bahrain#(MMTo Political, l T o .S/43 Dp.ted 31st August Received 1st September, Bahrain. ITy telegram IIo.E/37 August 30th. Mails sent between July 19th to August 18th under your lay Bills 31 to 34 arrived on 'BARPETA' yesterday Saturday.No.1691-14/1 Political Agency f Bahrain. 1st September, 1941. TO The Sub-Postmaster, 0 jjgnor^rdum. • Reference this office memorandum No .1632—14/1 dated the 31st August, 1941. 2 . The mails have now been delivered to is ; i ^est,y 1 3 Consul-General, Buehire, and no action is tiiei^efore necessary on my memorandum under reference.*No*1968-14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. 28th September, 1941. To The Postinaster, Karachi. i Memorandum . Please refer to your letter N0.R2-324 dated 11th Sei^t anber 1941. 2. It is not possible to trace the disposal of a letter from the Postal Registration Number outside the cover. Will you please enquire and let me know the contents of the cover to enable me to trace the letter?. 1 W w for Bbfcitical Agent, Bahrain. k L''No•2020-14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. 6 th October, 1941. To Khan Sahib Yousuf bin Ahnad Kanoo, Bahrain. ■ Dear Sir, According to the rules of the Indian Postal Department the question of the renewal of nail agreements should be examined a year in advance of the date of expiry of curren’u agreements. 2 , I should therefore be grateful if you would let n&lt; have your views on the following points:- (a) Do you propose to execute a further agreement, if so, when? (b) Do you wish an o'' 1 the terms of the existing agreement to be revised before it is renewed or are you satisfied with the existing conditions Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.tl Political Agency, aahrain* 12th October, 1941 ?rom Ibe Political Agent, Bahrain* O' » To The 3 uTierintendent of Post Offices, Lower .Sind &lt;f: Persian Gulf division, Hyderabad* (Sind)* SUBJECT:- Conveyance of nails at Bahrain-Agreement• Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.A-5/72 dated the 26th septarn’oer, 19^1. and to mt m you that Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanc.o, the mail contractor at Bahrain | is prepared to execute a further agreement as soon as necessary. He does not propose to revise any of the terms of the existing agreement. I have the honour to be, sir, Your noet obedient servant, for Political Agent, Bahrain.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; C _ (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N,E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS- GRAY. BUS R E H. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BU N DAR-SHAH POU R BUSH I RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. RAS TANURA. E l_ KHOBAR. The Postmaster BAER UN* ein, 12th October, 1941* Dear Sir, We enclose herewith copy of a letter dated 10th instant, received from the Commander, ss.^Barpeta” We have had similar complaints from other Commanders of mail steamers, ^nd shall be pleased if you will take the necessary steps to make legible all futhre mail bills from your office* Yours faithfully, c.c• Political Agent*Dear Sirs, I have had a complaint from my Mail Officer that the Mail Bills sent off to the ship are illegible. On sending for one i am bound to admit tnat this complaint is justix'ied. I trust that this can be remedied, as in the event of wrong delivery, I do not consider that the Mail Officex* could be held responsible. Yours faithfullyi Sd/- K.G.Mace COMMANDER.No, 2269 &gt; &lt; Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th November 1941 /'V. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, oharjah. Memorandum Reference memorandum No. 460-36/2 dated the 16th June 1941 from t he Residency Agent, Sharjah. 2. I have sent you by the rt Shin Kuang' 26 packages tentage a* in the attached list. Kindly acknowledge receipt. for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 253 ^ -14/1. . ,-iU Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 24th Norvember 1S4I. Prom To The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. Sir, 1 ft yO■ With reference to your letter No.A 5/72 dated the 28th/31st October 1941, I have the honour to return herewith the agreement (in triplicate) for the conveyance of airmails at Bahrain, duly signed and executed. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, Lvf. for Political tfgent, Bahrain ' uk.AGKSSiraT# TJiis cgrcccent tho JJJhi. — day 0 f /V&lt;nt~eys~JK+ p-^rr^ ‘THE C£}V T .TC R G&amp;lrRM, I' 1 C*&lt;T1NCIL ( h*r*in*?t*r ref erred to r? tii* ocvrmor »&gt;neral In Council which *xp**asion phsll incluae hi* iiuecneflcra «na asd^s) cf the ore p^rt ona K^an s®hib jlJsif KKnoo (Kar^aft^r referrca to ae tho cent rector which expression shall include his Personal represents tives one permitted ag^isfisJ 0 ^® t * P®rt* WHBHHAS ti:e contractor h&amp;s agreed to provide a motor v^icle service for transit conveyance and delivery as hert in- sftpr c«r.tioft«d Banruin- Mjhharaq mail aervief of all poatsl artticlea and mail tags aa defined In tto* Indian Post Office act 1898 and Hales thereunder as am«ided for the time being (hereinafter referred to in the Act) end the Governor Genei^l in Council nas agreed to entrust the work to the contrector upon fee terns and conditions hereinafter appearing* -y puling the continuance of this agreement that is to say for *^e priod of one year fr&gt;m the— — days of jt HHn until this agrement shall be determined by such notion as is hereinafter msitionec or otherwise in due course of law ( hereinafter referrec to ss the said contract period) the contractor agrees to take all eir mails from the Bsrain Post office, Kanemah and duly safely and expedioualy deliver them to 'die. station superintendent Imperial Always, or his represent atives at the Aerodrome or seeplsne base I'.uharraJ or at any other place as may be tne recognised depot in Bahrain for the receipt of ’ In ' or ' Cut ' going Imperial Airmails* 2 / m ihf* contractor agrres to be likewise respon- sible for the bringing back of all Air kails to the Bahrain Popt Office from the Aerodrome or the see plane8f*o plfft* bnse* 3/* During such time as the mails are in his actual or constructive possesion tho contractor undertakes to be solely responsible for the safe guarding and comply etp protection of the mails* 4/- should the mails be lost in any way, or any way damaged whilst in the possession of the contractor he agrees to pay at New Delhi the sum of Hs* 5QQ/-» to the Governor General in council* 5/- £iould the contractor fail to deliver the moils at the aerodrome or sea plane base aforesaid in \ time for any service he agrees to pay hs* 200A at New Delhi to the Governor General in Council, ftiis is subject only to the proviso that he has been kept fully informed by Imperial Airways as to Ihe correct times of arrival and departure of (f Imperial Airways planes* 6A *jhs contractor agrees thet st no time will the mails be under the responsibility or in the possess ion of any one other than a person of Bahraini, Indian, or Ne^Sfi nationality* 7/«» When the contractor arrives at the Post office for the conveyance of air mails, the postmaster Guarantees not to detain him for a period longer than fifteen minutes* This is subject only to the proviso that the Postmaster has been kept fully infoxmed by the Imperial Airways as to the correct times of erriv&amp;l and departure of the planes. Should he exceed this period penalty clause No.5 is hullified for that occa sion shold the plane be raissid* 8/~ subject to these conditions, the Governor General in council agrees to pay the sum of Ks* 3/- only to the contractorfbr each return trip performed for the conveyance of mails to and from each and every Imperial Airways ^ail plane which may arrive at Bahrains 9/- Tfcr contractor shall not transfer or sublet thi contract or r&amp;y Part of it or interest in it to any otfc?r person or persons nor attenipt to cio so without the previous consent in writing of the I irector of Posts an&lt;? Telegraphs, Karachi which may be granted or refused in his absolute discretion* lOA Tbo contractor undertakes to receive the mails from the Post Office «nd deliver to the fairways authori ties at the Aerodrome or seadrome* in &amp;ood time before the departure of each service and likewise the contractor ogives to d^livexy of incoming mail and deliver same to th* postal authorities as soon as possible after arrival j jy^ '.‘.hi? contract may be absolutely determined end put an €^*0 to «4y either of contracting parities giving four calancrr mouth;? notice in writing to the other of his intension so ea t.o determine and put «3n end to the same# x%/m \ny notice required to oe given or anything r^uired co be done nereunder by the Governor General in Council* tne Director General* Posts and Telegraphs* or the Politic el Agent! dehrain^ ^ ehjiil be sufficient if signed or done by the political Agent Bahrain^ or the Director General Posts and Telegraphs* kew Delhi or any person authorised by him and service oi any such*delivered or left at the office of the contractor or sent by registered post addressed to the contractor at their last known plec^ of business in Bahrain and any notice required to be given hereunder on the part of the contra ctor shall be sufficiently given if signed by the contra ctor and addressed by registered post to the office of the Director General, Posts an* Telegraphs* uew Delhi, or the Political Agent Bahrain# 13 /-r All disputes and differences arising out of or In anywise touching or concerning this agree®out shall be refferred to the sole arbitration of the Director GeneralDirector of Po^ts sn d Telegraphe and failing him Political BahreinAnd if th« Director General or th? Political Agent aa the caej may be is Ttnrblr or unwilling to act* to the aole arbitration of rome other person appointed by th* Director General or failing him the Political Agent willing to act as such arbitrator. It will ba no objection to any such appoint* r.mt that the arbitrator so appointed is a Government srrviint that h ?&gt; bad to deal with the natters to which this a^frear^nt reiser £nd thrt in ^hf course of his duties ar such Government servant h*&gt; has eJflprassed vifwa on sll or c ny of the matters in dispute or difference# It^c ov-nr^ of the arbitrator so appointed phull he finrl md binding on +he said parties. 14/* ihi:; sgrr.hEcut i-l aDl in ell respect be Latexprefrd in fr eovtma with tt»r lr- v 's of British Indie rvi) be *«ifcrceablc in Indie* In witneb^ &gt;herrr;f for and on brhrJwf of fbe Gov^ nor General of ludi.c in Ccurcil thr Politic ?r A &gt;'*vt Bahrain hath hero* unto set his f ^.c* j?'d th;» r-'id - have hereunto set hi a respective head the day and xne year first hereinafter written. hignad by the said acting / in prpmisps for and behalf of tha Govemor Gene'*l in ^‘ouncil ) in the presence of 7 4 /ft- j &gt; Signed sealed and delivered by the above naafd^ip the presence nm ed ^ ip th c praaenc «• of ) ) ) pelyl .No. C/1204 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 31st December, 1941 To The Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain. I Me morandum - vsr I enclose herewith a letter and a cover in original forwarded to me by Mr. Maulvi Shams-ud-Din, Bahrain, complaining of a delay of 5 months and 5 days in the transmission of this letter from Amritsar post office to Bahrain and I shall be grateful if you \*ill make enquiries and let me have a reply as early as possible• l. Political Agent, Bahrain.- — Ill© ia lopiy jjiea-o quote The Postmaster, Karachi The Politcial Agent, Bahrain, Registered. AV R2-324 dated at Karachi the 8th January 1942 ' 5 ' I have the honour to invite X/ your attention to this office express letter of even No.dated the 10/12/41 and your office letter No^1968-14/1 dated the 28/9/41, and to request you to kindly intimate by return post the disposal of Civil Lines Delhi registered letter No.ISOaddressed to Capt. R.D. Metcalf, Publicity Officer P.G.Bahrain forwarded to your office duly entered in the Regd. list dated 25/6/41 at serial 4 advis ing 5 registered letters.. The registered letter contained only Income Tax notice to the addressee. If delivered, the date of delivery may kindly be intimated and also an attested copy of a’dressee^ ackno../ledg- ment be sent for the satisfaction of the sender. I have the honour to be, Sir. Your most servant for postmaster, Karachi MGIFPAb.—'No.275/14/1 The 22nd February 1942 Dear Metcalfe, The Postmater, Karachi,has enquired whether registered letter No.150 from the Civil Lines Post Office, Ne*-Oelhi,*ms delivered to you in July last year. It con tained n notice from the Income*'Tax neoartment. He has aorarently received an enquiry from the sender and wants this Agency to produce your receipt for the cover, alleging that it was sent here in June 1941. At the time you were,I believe, on leave in Kashmir and the cover would ordinarily have been -orwarde! to you by the Publicity Office with your other letters. Could you please let me know if you got the letter; and,if so, would you mind sending a receipt direct to the Postmaster .Karachi,with reference to his letter No.R 2-324,dated t e 1th December, 1941.addressed to this Agency? Yours sincerely *» Captain R.D.Metcalfe,I.A., Under Secretary t&lt; the Resident,^No^^^/14/l Prom To V - \ Political Agency, hrei n, The 17th February 1942. The Political Agent,Bahrein, The Superintendent, Poet Officers, T/wer Sind &amp; Persian Gulf TVivn. Hydera^d • dubject: -dxoe'jtion of a greenxnt of Bahrein~]?anan a- '~'WoY&amp; rrac; rr, 11 oer^:ire . Sir, vith reference to your letter Mo.A-6/72, dated the bth January 1942,I have the honour to retuni,herewith, tlie enclosed agreement duly authenticated by the Assistant Political Agent. i.!ajor H.G*' V .Alban, the Political Agent, v;hc signed the agreement has been transferred from this Agency. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, M ^ /c For Political Agent,Bahrein. 9u.Q-./t/frl }\-Jl A l\y&lt;-^l uated, Hastings ^ouae, iUipore, Calcutta the ^^Februury, 1942. 'X * ( v 9 \ F ; r’ 3i^ r Please refer to your demi-official letter bo.275/14/1 of tne 22nd February 1942. 1 have no record of such a letter but I do remember receiving some forms from the Income Tax Officer, Central Circle, New Delhi, regarding my pay between 1938 and 1940. There were duly filled in and returned. a, copy of this letter is being sent to tne I'ost Master, Karachi as requested.No. 77-2 -14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. )ated 2nd May, 1942. To Mr. G. J. Khan, InsuecLor, Post (offices, c/o ‘he Jub-Postmaster, 3ahiT &gt; in. Dear Sir, I ?Mn informed that for a considerable period of tine the Bahrain Post Office has been out of stock of post cards and also of sterling postal orders. The reply that a f ’fresh supply is expected shortly' does little to satisiy local complaints• 2 . May I take advantage of your presence in Bahrain to request that this matter may be looked into and rectified as soon as possible? Yours truely, Bahrain-A ' -» Ho. BA/49. MEMORANDUM. \u v l 3 ^ Vb I \ Office of the Naval Officer-in-Charge, H.M. Naval Base, Bahrain. One of my Staff, Petty Officer Telegraphist Kaye, called at the Post Office at 1015 on the morning of 24th April, 1942, to collect mail for H.M. Naval Base, Bahrain. 2.- After knocking for approximately five minutes on the door of the Postmaster^ house, the Postmaster himself opened the door, and in a curt way, asked Petty Officer Telegraphist Kaye what he v/anted. Petty Officer Telegraphist Kaye then stated his business - saying that he had been sent from Jufair to collect mail for the Naval Base - but was informed that as the day*was a Ptiday, the Post Office was closed, and it was added in very uncivil manner:- 'What do you mean disturbing me at this time?'. Petty Officer Telegraphist Kaye again stated that he had been ordered to collect the mail for the Naval Base. The Postmaster then said he would inform the Naval Officer-in-Charge of the matter, and finally stated:- 'Go away' and closed the door. 3.- It is considered that the Postmaster acted in a very unbecoming manner for a Government Servant. An assurance was given this Office some months ago by the Postmaster, that in the event of the Post Office being closed on Fridays, or holidays, it would be in order to call at the Postmaster*s house above the £ost Office, regarding mails for the Naval-Base. 4.- It is requested • • • • •- 2 - 4.- It is requested that a definite assurance may he given that such an 'occurrence v/ill not he^repeated, or a member of the Royal ilavy treated with incivili y n e performance of his duty. Bahrain, P.G. 36th April, 1942. LIEUTENANT COMMANDER, R.N.V.R., NAVAL OPPICER-IN-CHARGE.No.816-14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, 5th May, 1942. To The Naval Offleer- in-Charge, H.M. Naval Base, Jufair. Memorandum . Reference your Memorandum No.BA/49 dated 26th April, 1942. 2. I have given a warning to the Postmaster, Bahrain, in the presence of his senior officer, an Inspector who fortunately happened to be in Bahrain last week. 3 . In future, on days when the Post Office is closed, the Postmaster will telephone to the Naval Base immediately any mail is ready for delivery. If mail for the Naval Base is in a separate bag a telephone message will be sent when such bag is received. If mail for the Naval Base is not in a separate bag, the Naval Base will be informed immediately the mail has been sorted and letters are ready for delivery. The Inspector has undertaken to ensure that there will be no delay in sending intimation of the arrival of mail. This arrangement will, it is hoped, preclude the possibility of further incidents of the nature reported by you. political Sgent, Bahrain.• ■ twl. 1 |S WV (M) L(V Coff.«2S. mm POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT. In reply please quot^ A From m iO No. •38, The Inspector of Post Offices, ‘V, c . Persian Oulf 3ection. / J O »♦. . . y 7 U. / : &gt; - A x T&gt;ate. M , . , n. /*• \ dated at Csj&amp;p Be.hrin ~ l ' e 5th uay 1^44;. The Political Agent, . o JB a h. r Subject, A 3 7 Jir, I thank you for your letter ho:79P-i4/l dated the \ ^nd instt and heg to .'furnish my replj'' as under on both points after looking into the matter thoroughly 2 - (i) POoTAL 0IlPP-i3&gt; cr I hare seen the records of full^one yeai and have seen that the local Post Office had never been without -.ostal orders (British as well as Indian)* As this ^.ost Of i ice «• i *. is allowed to keep only a limited stock viz 2 of eacxi denomin- -V - * 4 . .. • • t ^ -• • - - - v. _ .. ^, C 5 v . :; ation, it sometime happens that tne stock 01 certain denomin ations runs short and it takes a few days to ootain xres.u supply. If during this interval any member of the public asks for thiskparticulat denomination it becomes impossibre -or the •fy t.fr _ost taster to meet the demand. The demand can however oe met if the purchaser agrees to take tv/o postal orders instead of one of a particular denomination. ‘For instance if Britisn Postal order of 2 shillings is not available the purchaser can well/BAAkAwo of one shillings to meet his requirements. Postmaster to see that he However I have instructed the gets his stock replenished as quickly as possible hut lor obvious reasons he will still be handicapped on certain occasions to meet the demands of the public.a 1 an also addressing the higher authorities to increase the present authorised stock of those denominations the sale of which is generally heavy. (2) lOdl CAIilDq. This article of stationery was notno -t av^ilfeole liere since a long time, i’rom the records x na.se ' e~n t'at the xost Cards were indented for by the local -ost Office fox -:ore than a dozen t Use a* this office was^nformed fe • -* the ‘h.rachi head Office that the same were out of stock in the ^p-rachi Teasury. On receipt of your letter 1 wired oo tne postmaster karachi requesting him to supply the same if since available and I cm sbill awaiting his reply. I am also requesting the Director of ^ c* T, ^ind and Baluchistan Ciicxe to take necessary action iff the matter. In the meantime I can suggest to the intending purchasers to use postcards oi prix* private? manufacture and affix.-/-/9 postage stamp thereon. *,s is v;e ii known to you postcards which are used in India cannot be sold or used here. v x snarl be grateful if -you will kindly let me hhiow any other matter which in your opinion requires improvement so that may attend to it before I leave tne. piace. You will find me at -yourscall at any time in case you Iesire to discuss anything with me personally. I have the honour to be» - • r . Ow .. .... ... ,. 3ir.,- Your most obedient seivano^ InspecjwY' of lost Offices, hlam- GuK Geetion. ch- i N) is:-:No *840-14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. 9th May, 1942. To The Inspector of Post Offices Persian Gulf Section, c/o The Pcctmster, Bahrain* Gear Sir, I am much obliged to you for your letter Ho .38 dated 5th T^ay, 1942, which gives a full exp'osition of the situation in regard to the two points which I brought to your notice. 2. I do not think there is any other natter requiring attention at the present moment. I am, with thanks, Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrain.wmm / not rYnilfeule lie re since a long time. From the records i have , ecn that the xost Cards were indented for hy the local -ost office for . ore tiiar a dozen tr ies ^tliis office was A informed n h ; the dZairachi head Office that the same were out ox stock in t'.e Israelii Teasury. On receipt of your letter X wired to the _ os ter a /ail t ^ ^ -i -f* ^ \ —— ; iv'i — •• — u — -No .946-W1 Political Agency, ^ahrain. 27th May, 1942. To The Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter dated 24th May 1942. 2. I have taken action which will ensure that there cannot possibly be a repetition of the incident of which you quite rightly complained to me. Yours truly, Political Agent, Bahrainf POSTAL NOTICE Sending of air mils by Trans Pacific all air route has been suspended for present. Air mils for the U.3.A, Central &amp; South America and ' T est Indies will however he accepted for transmission by air cum. sea route Tr ia Durban, Air fee for the USA by this route will be Rs. 1/6/- per half ounce exclusive of Postage for letters and aimas per postcard inclusive of post-ge. 5th, January, 1942. Bahrein. ©I*!! No. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st June 1942. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. i. The California Arabian Standard Oil Company and the Bahrain Petroleum Company have asked me to represent to the appropriate authority the unsatisfactory position in regard to the carrying of air mail from Bahrain to the U.a.A. 2. Until Christmas 1941 air mail to the U.S.A. was dea- the patched by^trans-Pacific all-air route. iubsequently, however, after the trans-Pacific all-air route was closed to mail traffic, air mail for the U.3.A. has been transmitted by the air-cum-sea route via Cairo and Durban. The American community in Bahrain and Dhahran are well aware that the B.O.A.C. operate from .‘Jahr-iin to Cairo and that Pan-American Airways operate from Cairo to she U.d.A. It has been stated to me that air mail originating in Cairo is carried to the U.S.A. by air but that, in spite of the fact that there is a mail service both between Bahrain anu Cairo and between Cairo and the U.S.A v letters from Bahrain are not accepted for transmission to the U.S.A. by the alb-axr route, fhe Postmaster here states (though I do not know what his authority is; that it is illegal for letters to be despatched by their writers to an agent in Cairo to be re-transmitted by him to the via Pan American Airways. 3. I do not know whether you will think it worthwhile to represent the natter to the Government of India; but if steps can be taken to institute an all-air mail service from the Persian Gulf to the U.S.A. such a facility would be greatly appreciated by the American employees of the Oil Companies. Political^Agent, Bahrain.No. //// -14/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st June 1942, To R.P. Reynolds Esquire, California Arabian Standard Oil Company, Bahrain• Dear Sir, A short time ago Mr* Rodstrom asked me to ascertain whether arrangements could be made to despatch mail from Bahrain to the U.S*A. by the all-air route via Cairo and Lagos* The position at present is that, since the beginning of January 1942, the sending of air mails by the trans-Pacific all-air route has been suspended, and the all-air route via Cairo and Lagos has not yet been opened for mails. At present therefore, there is no all-air route for mails to the TJ*3*A. which are despatched by the air-cum-sea route via Cairo and Durban. 2. I am making representations on the subject to the Political Resident who will, 1 hope, take up the matter with i the Government of India* Yours truly, / Political Agent, Bahrain* Copy to the Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. »i‘ rThe Bahrein i PA-283 M ij l oleum Company Limited A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 13, 1942. &amp; A POSTAL SERVICE His Britannic Majesty’s Political A^ent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No.1117-14/1 dated 21st June 1942, to Mr. R.P. Reynolds, California Arabian Standard Oil Companjr, relative an all-air route for mails to the TJ.3.A. Bor your information, X am in receipt of a commu nication from the American Vice-Consul, Basrah, expressing surprise that Bahrein does not have a direct airmail con nection with the United States, inasmuch as Iraq has had a connection for several months now. I trust that your representations to the Political Resident will result in early establishment of a direct air mail route to the U.S.A. from Bahrein. Yours very truly, W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative The Bahrein Petroleum Co., LtdHo • /2 14/1 • Political Agency, Bahrain, the 15th July 1942, To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Memorandum* Reference ay memorandum No* 1116-14/1 dated 21st June 1942 regarding the carrying of air mail from Bahrain to the U *3*A* 2* The Bahrain Petroleum Company have informed me that they have received a communication from the American Vice-Consul, Basrah, expressing surprise that Bahrain does not have a direct air mail connection with the United States inasmuch as Iraq has had such a connection for several months now* 3. Air mail from Bahrain for the U*S.A* would only con stitute a small addition to the volume of what is already carried from Iraq$ and I hope therefore that it will be found possible to extend to this island the facilities already enjoyed by person; in Iraq who have connections with America* Political Agent, BahrainDear Sir, » We encloae herewith two registered covers delivered to us today. You will observe from the post-marks w ich are confirmed by the letters contained in the covers, that these were despatched by our Karachi Office on the 22nd and 25th June respectively. !Eheir delivery today means that they have taken 29 and 25 days respec tively to be conveyed by air from Karachi. passing between Karachi and Bahrain in 12 hours, there cannot be any justification whatsoever for unwarranted delays of this nature in dealing with first class mail. We request you therefore to take — th.£&gt;r matter up most strenuously with a view to preventing any recurrence. The political Kgen The Public Kelatio _ _ The Eastern Bank, Ltd., Karachi, India. We submit that when aircraft are Copy to. c/ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA; Department, EXPRESS LETTER -® [N , B, —This is an ORIGINAL MNSSAGN, sent by post to sare telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Fbom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf y Camp, Bahrain. To Repeated Foreign, New Delhi. Political, Bahrain. No ‘ TB/4. DataJ 28th July 1942. . I For some months new Americans in Iraq have been able to post letters to America 'via Pan American West Africa' at a charge of 180 fils a unit (of five grammes?). The B.O.A.C. take the letters as far as Khartum and Pan American Airways take them over now. 2. Americans in Bahrain have now asked for similar facilities which I recommend should be granted. Please telegraph what arrangements can be made. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf©. &lt;381 Politico l/.f.ncy Prhrfin, 6th To* Khrn Srhib Yusuf bin /hmed Kmoo Bp.hre in. Defr Sir, /ccor-ing to the rules of the Inlirn Posts1; Depertment the question of renerrl of meii ? nts should be excrained r yerr in rdvence of the dfte of exoiry of current rgreeraent-. I should therefore be greteful if you would let me hfve your views on the folio’ ing points:- (a) do you paflpose to execute r further egreement^ (b) Do you vish eny of the terms of egreement to be revised before it is renewed or ere you satisfied ’ith the existing conditions? if so,vhen? Yours fsithfully ^ J For ioliticrl Agent,^^hrein'ilir (irast ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO t he E ASTERN bank limited. Telegraphic Address: 'EASTERTIDE!' U.0 nkMxmxteS, ngland) 11th Au^iui V- 42* The Postmaator, Bahrain* Dear Sir, We yesterday received an Airgraph letter, bearing Ifo* 754603, from our London Office* 5hia letter was deli vered to ua unfolded and without an envelop or cover of any kind* We are infomed that Airgraphs are supposod to be delivered in covers and we shall be glad to k^ow whether there has bee: any amendment to this procedure* It would appear that delivery of all such documents without covers defeats the entire object of the system and this was not intended by the authorities by whom it was instituted* Please take this matter up Ime- diately and let us know the result thereof* Copy to*- 1* The PoliticallAgent Bahrain. v| Airgraph Section General Post Office Bombay* Manager. 2 *NO 1438/ 14/1 Political Agency, Bahrein; The Islh August 1942. From The Political Agent,Bahrein To The Superintendent of Post Offices Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hudrahadlsind). Subject:-Conveyance of mails at Behrein-Agreement expiring on 27-4-4S. SirA ^ b ^ I have the honour to refer to your letter No-'AV5-72,dated the 5th July 1942, and to inform you that Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo,the mail contractor at Bahrein, is prepared to execute a futt^her agreement jjp soon as^necessary.He does not to revisg^ny of the terms of the existing agreement. I hive the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. For Political Agent,Bahreinvnrr.-' IXDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT.© AIR M Aa. r rapirass L^TT^Ra Prom Foreign New Delhi. To Political Resident, Bahrain. (Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain.) N0*5?5ON/42. Dated the 21' August 1942. Reference your express letter No.TB/4, dated the 28th July 1942. vA 2. A through air mail service from India to United States of America and Canada has since been introduced, and a copy of the Postal Notice, containing the rates of air mail fee and other particulars of the service, is enclosed for information, as Bahrain is an Indian Post Office, air mails for U.S.A. and Canada will be accepted at that office accordingly. THE I331TC OF THF ABOVF HAS AUTHORISED# Addl. Deputy Secretary to the Govt, of India./ POSTAL NOTICE. Introduction of a through air mail service to U &gt; S»A* and Canada * Air mails for U*S«A* and Canada are at present sent by the air -cum -sea route via Durban and the United Kingdom. Arrangements Rave now been made, with effect from the 15th August 1942, to send such mails throughout by air by utilising the Pan-American -x Airways 1 services operating between West Africa and U*S.A* This all-air service will afford considerable gain in the transit time* 2* A blue air mail label should be affixed on the top left-hand corner of all air mail correspondence sent to U* S*A* and Canada* The air mail fee and superscription are given below;- Name of superscrip- letters and packets, card, inclusive 3* The present air-cum-sea route via Durban will also be available for air mails to U*S*A* and Canada at the Air mail fee* Country* tion. of ordinaiy postage* &amp;• a* p* 10 0 U*S* A* India-Lagos-U.S.A. 2- 8-0 Canada India-Lagos- 2-0-0 0 11 0 Canada* existing rates of postage. W.H.Shoobert, Directoi^-General of Posta and Telegraphs* New Delhi 9 The August 1942*V\ ~4. © 4537- /V/ T&gt; THE POLITICAL AQENc/, / $/- ^cei_ / /9^^L To /e ^ 1. The California Arabian Standard Oil Co Bahrein. 2. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Co.Ltd, Bahrein. Dear Sir, t^ryotr ttmtr/4 through air-mail service from India to United States of A^TVnT America has since been introduced,and a copy f of the Postal Notice, containing the rates of air mail fee^and other particulars of the service, is enclosed for /.rw information. As Bahrain is an Indian Post Office, air mails for U.S.A. and Canada will be accepted at that office accordingly. Yours faithfully Vi For Political Agent,Rehrenin. /^7/L/^/ THE POLITICAL AGENCY; / mnummm* j-//' / /?*/£ . To The Superintendent of Post Offices Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Divn: Hydrabad. Sir, In reply to your letter No.A/-5/8S dated the 19th August 1942, I have the honour to inform you that no grain compensation allowance is paid to the staff working in this Agency. I have etc., For Politic!! Agent,Bahrein Z xTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, #PA-395. Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, September 3, 1942. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN . Bear Sir, Thank you for your letter No. 1537-14/1 dated September 1st, 1942 relative the new all-air-mail route from India to the United States of America. 7/e are indeed glad that this mail service has at last been established and much appreciate what you have done to encourage its introduction. W. P. ANDIE SON. Chief Local Representative, TKL EAHRBIN PNTROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The postmester informed on the phone that the p tamps , . . |W heve since prnved and further action to be teken. FileIKIHAar POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS PBFARTMBWT, EXPRBSS LETTER ►. ^'iL 72 - h , ; t j ? ■» p f9 Dated nyd 36 * /v-2-42 19 xhf J^olitic^l ^gent, Bahrain. sir, Su'bjf'cti Conv^yanca of msils nshrain. with rpferencp to the correspondence hiding with your letter no; 1438-- 14/1 dat^d 15-3-42, 1 have tne honour to say that, it has now teen pointed out by the Director of Pos + s fnd lelegrephs, Sind and nsluchi st^n circle P 2^ Karachi that the agreement previously executed in respect of the Above contract does not contain a provision for the conveyance of the Post office forms as e pact of mails. A clause in the following*wordings is therefore required to be inserted in the body of the agreement to be executed at the time of its renewal. It is presumed that thfrr- will be no objection to so doing. This may kindly be confirmed so that the new agreement for the next year may be preparedan d sent to you for execution. i have etc. Superintendent of Tost offices Lower Sind and P. s. Li vision * Pleas« see over leaf. DL werpit-1 (A) ihp c r tntractor shall ca vry as part of mails ■t'ost offics forms and stores despatched ty th^ Postal Stock Depot or the offices wnere such forms and stores are printed wad stored, to the various post offices nail ways and steamer stations and Railways luail service offices named in the Schedules attached to the agreement and /? , such other places as may hr required by the *ooi 5 trr o£iLciiel and shall not claim any extre remuneration on that account ••No. Express Letter /g ^/14/l Politics1 /gency Prhrein, The t^th October 1942 To The Superintendent ofPostOf'ices ^ . . Lov r er Sind and_Persian Gulf Division, Hy dr abed Sind. Subject: -Conveyance of mails rt Pahrein. Sir, f I have the honour to refer to your Express i Letter No.A-6/72,dated the 16th September 1942, and to state that Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo,mail contractor at Bahrein,has no objection to the insertion of the clause referred to in your letter in the new agreement to be executed for^tj^next year. I have etc., For Political Agent,BahreinTelegram From en clair To Political, Bahrain D.P.T*, Karachi. No.218 Dated 17th October 1942. Deference Bahrain Post Office telegram No.X.P.13 October 13th. Serious shortage stamps Bahrain. Please supvly adequate number urgently. !7o.l339~ 14/1 Political Agency,Bahrain. Copy by post (air mail) in confirmation. In addition to stamps, stamped envelopes and at least 10 British Postal Orders of each denomi nation from 5 shillings to 21 shillings may kindly be supplied, to meet the needs of Forces in Bahrain Copy for information to Postmaster General, Karachi. 17th October,1942 * 1 - for^ \1 Agent, Bahrain.Cocr.-41, BY AH % nl' INDIAN POSTSAND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT. (jj) f Une ”*• sl - i 61 t/ 7 Idractoia of jto^ls ana T8ia_rajiis, Sind ana Baiacma tan Circle. t* 'Ihe Political ^cni : xfw&lt;.fe«r «f wriMTirwi panrain kawai t. Karachi # o« li. 15(4P^ Subject; Motor Mail Contract Bahrain-Manewaitfunarra^. ana Kuwait -Zucair. Sir, I have, the honour to say that due to accute shortage ox ^etroi aue to the war emergency, rationing eh erne haf be-n orot.ht into eflect A H UiUIiXi:^, J O-Il^UiO AlcLt UC li Ui UL 0 Ai b i.Ii UU CllCUl lh British Inaia and trie mail motor con tractors in this country arc bein^ ins true tea to e et Froaucer has . plant instal^ea m their vehicles. I shell be obligee by your ninaly intimating to me as early as possible wh ither the supply cf petrol will, oe availabj.e as usuc, 1 for the above motor mail contracts for at xegst ' 5 years from tL date of commencemenL oi the next contract. ‘ii^e favour oi an early reply is requested.'-jQ ' 7?l No.^^/14/1 Political /gency P? hrein, T he /^f^overarer 1..^?. To The Director of Posts and ielegraohs Sin^ and. Baluchistan Circle, Karachi. Subject:- Motor Mail Contract Bahrein-ManaiDa-Muharraa. Sir, In reply to your letter No.FL-161/17,da ted the 4th November 1942, I have the honour to inform you that thej^upply of petrol is likely to be available for the above motor mail contract for at least t years from the date of the ecmirirncement of the next contract. CL, I have etc., s’or Politicfl /gent,PShr?in. CL, cC ■&gt;, tn J ft W» (jj w auneti naoD .32AHHH 3UJSMOO 8 Y3JTli3P 38AflH4 QMOD32 2'Y3JTH3b QHASMOJ .notriuB ht2 D 8 .A OKA *?'•' ' c :lesnaiA i »1 'mA«HAa .ootflbT M - S f 'JMOH^ No. To, /14/1 Pcliticrl /gency Prhrr. in, The November 19 / 2. K.S.Yoosuf bin K?noo,Prhrein. Subject:- M otor Mril Contract PrbiTrin-Yrn^mr- Muhrrrr.g. v?y •Dear Sir, The Director of Posts p.nd Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle,Karachi,has enquired to let him know whether the supply of petrol will be available as usual for the above mail contract for at least o years from the date of commencement of the next contract. will you please let me have your views on this subject? Yours faithfully For Political /gent,Pa hra in.A G H is» Ji m h»‘ W T ♦ ‘1M s «gri»€!fnfnt mad© the /// /Z day of l^nctCL^JY / 7 BB’masN TnK (JUVKiiNoH CiiiWBhAL / * ✓ (X)UNCIL (herrinefter referred to a© the (jovemor umeral in f &gt;uncil which ^xpre&amp;sion shall include his successors end assign©; of the one pert and Khsn yehib Yusif &amp;snoo (hereafter rafarrad to ns the contractor which expression shell include his personal representatives end permitted assigns) of the other part. WHSftftAS the contractor has ©greed to provide © motor vehicle service for transit conveyance ©nd deliveiy as herein-after mentioned oahrain- Man am a-Ku hh a req mail service of all post&amp;l articles end mail bags as defined in the Indian n&gt;st office act 1808 and ^ules thereunder ©s amended for the time being ^hereinafter referred to In the Act^ and the Governor ^€nert*l in uouncil has agreed to entrust the work to the contractor upon the terms and conditions her inafter appearing. 1/- During the continuance of this agreement that is to say for the period of one year from the &lt;k&amp;&amp; of until this agreement shall be determined by such notice as is hereinafter mentioned or otheMLee is due course of l#r (hereinafter referred to as the said (contract period) the contrf ctor egress to take ©11 ©ir rr»ils from the Bahrain tfost offices r Manamsh and duly safely and e^ediously deliver them to th© station SUpe rin ten dent, Imperial Airways, or his representa tives at thi erodrome or seaplane base Muharraq or at any other place as may be the recognised depot in Bahrein for th© receipt of •in* or •out 1 going Imperial Airmails. 1/- A. ih# contractor shall c©^ as ox wgi! r uffice foims and stores despatched by the r 0 stal stock Depot or the offices where such forms and stores are printed and stored to the various post offices nail way and s teaner stations and Kailwey H©il service offices n^ned in the Schedules attached to the xne ^reement and such otherpieces ro^y P# required by th© uir^ctor of njets Telegraphs, &amp;.erechi and shell not claim any extra remuneration on that account. 2/- xhe contractor agrees to he likewise responsible for the bringing back of ®11 *ir wails to the Bahrain f'ost office from the aerodrome or the aea plane base. 3/- juring such time as the mails are in his actual or constructive possession the contractor undertakes to be solely responsible for the safe guarding end complete protection of the mails. 4/- should the mails be lost in any way, or ©ny way dameged whilst in th© possession of the contractor he agrees to pay at «ew nelhi the sum of ns. 5GJ/~ to the uovemor ueneral in council • 5/- should the contractor f^il to deliver the mails at the Aerodrome or sea plane base afbresaid in time fbr ©ny service he agrees to pay «s. 200/- at wew nelhi to the oovemor ucnerei in council. This is subject only to the proviso that h© has been k«|)t fully informed by umperiel Airways as to the correct times of ©rriv&amp;l ©nd departure of imperial Airways planes. A/- The contractor agrees that at no time will the mails be under the responsibility or in the possession of any one other than a person of oahraini, Indian, or h®bi nationality. 7/- when the contractor arrives at the ^ost office for the conveyance of air mails, the postmaster guarantees not to detain him tor a period longer than fifteen minutes. This is subject only to the proviso that the Postmaster has been kept fully informed by the imperial Airways as to the correct times of arrival and departure of th© plaies. should he exceed this period pmslty clause «o • &amp; is nullified for that occasion should the plpne b© missed. 8/- subject to these conditions, the governor ueaeralin Council agrees to pay th* sum of its* 3/- only to tne contractor for each return trip performed fbr the conveyance of mails to and from each and every xm^rial Airv/cysMeil pl*ne which may arrive at Bahrein. 9/- xhe contractor shall not transfer or sublet this contract or any pert of it or interest in it to sro other person or persons nor attempt to do so without the pre vious consent in writing of the jirector of rosts and Telegraphs, ^srachi which may he granted or fused in his absolute discretion. 10/- xhe contractor mdertakes to receive the msii from the J'ost office and deliver to the airways auttorities at the Asm drome or seadromet in good time before the departure of each sergice and likewise the contractor agrees to take delivery of incoming auu fc*’ 4,rtt r same to the postal authorities as soon as possible after arrive* 11/- This contract may be absolutely determined and put fin end to by either of contracting parties giving four calender months notice in writing to the other of his intention so as to determine end put an end to the same. 12/- Any notice required to be given or anything required to be done hereunde r by the i-ovemor general in Council, the nirector taener&amp;l, rosts and Telegraphs or the Political Agent oahrain, shall be sufficient if signed or done by the Political Agmt oahr^in, or the uirpetor ueneral msts and Taiegr&amp;phs* «ew jjelhi or any person authorised by tfe* him and service of any such notice on the contractor shall be sufficient if the same be delivered or left at the office of the contractor or sent by registered post addressed to the contractor their last knovn place of business in oshroin sod any notice required to be given hereunder on the part of the contractor shall be sufficiently given if signed by the contractor gid addressed by registered post to the office of the director General, mats and Telegraphs, aew uelhi, or the PoliticalAgpnt apbrein 13/- All disputes &lt;md differences ©ri sing out o f or in anywise touching or concerning this agreement shall be referred to the sole arbitration of the director ucnerel of Posts «id Telegraphs and failing him the Political Agent, Bahrain gnd if the Director uenaral or the Political Agent as the case may be is mable or unwilling to act, to the sole arbitration of some other person appointed by the Director uenerai or failing him the Political Agent willing to act as such arbitrator. Tt will be no objection to any such appointment that the arbitrator so appointed is a usvemment servant that he had to deal with thematurs to which this agreemmt relate and thst In the course o f hi s duties as such 'Jovrmmmt servant he hi^ views on all or any of the matters in dispute or difference, ihe award of the arbitrator so appointed shall be final end binding on the said parties. 14/- ihis agreesmt shall in all respect be interpreted in accordance with the laws of British indie and be enforceable in oritish India. In WItN£ 33 whereof fbr end on behalf of the uovemor uenrrel of mdia^ in Council the Political Agent Bahrain hsth hereunto set his hand end the said have hereunto set respective hand the day «nd the year first herein aft at written. S'i^ed by the said acting in precises for and behalf of the governor urnersi in council in the presence of J£t Jl. JK 1 **. i0r signed seeled and deliver named in the presmce of- From ^D?DT. OF POST OFFICES, * Wf*' f5 P f » a &lt; •. i - &gt; t •. i . T-q The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject: Execution of an agreement for conveyance of mails at Bahrain, i^our letter No. 1846-14/1 dated the 18-10-1942 refers. Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to this office letter of even number dated the 27-11-42, on the subject noted above and request the favour of an early re turn of the agreement after execution. xyo . A—6/72 Hyderabad Bind 20-1-1943. 23 (v) X CL I have etc.No.-14/1. Political Agency, Of Bahrain, To The February 1943 Th« Sub Postmaster, Bahr? in M emorandum &gt; 6 ' Hofej»enee yoiu^ letter No.993.dated the 3rd January 1943 applying for the appoirt -rnent of night ;?uards at the Post Office and for nature to acconfKp.ny the clerk bringing cash to and fron the Bank. The Bahrain Go^emrwrt are of opinion .; p tf 9 &amp; the Post Off ce is next door to ho Police station, where there is always a Policeman on duty day and night, and in tne aamejp remises as the Telephone Office, where there is an operator on duty day and night,a,special police guard for the Post Office is^unnecessary. They are further of opinion that for cash sent during the day time no esco 2 »t is necessary. If you still consider that a night T essential, it will be for the . ost Office to engage one at its own expense• for Political Agent, Bahrain./ J? ■ / • v • ^ British India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (incorporated in England; TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. No. BI / 17, Bahrein, 14th £pril, i^i3. Political Agent, BAHiiE 3N • Dear Sir, aS. n WO S ANG 11 - hiAILS We have to advise you that the above vessel sailed for India on 13th instant without taking Post Office mails. The enclosed is a copy of a letter received from the Post Master at 6/30 p.m., and, in explanation, we have to advise the following circumstances : At 11.30 a.m. our Mail Clerk advised the Post Master that mails for the SS. n W0 SANG” for Bunder Abbas, Karachi and Bombay were required at 2.00 p.m., this request being followed by our usual Mail Notice, a copy of which you also received. At 2.00 p.m. our Mail Clerk went to the Post Office to collect the mails but found the Post Office closed. An Agency peon with mails was waiting outside the Post Office and informed our Mail Clerk that he had been waiting there about half an hour. At 2.30 p.m. and again at 2.45 p.m. our Mail Clerk called at the Post Office but still the nails were not ready, and at 3.00 p.rn., the launch left the pier as the Commander had ad vised us that he wished to leave at 4.0D : p.m. sharp in order to make Bunder Abbas at daylight to anable^tt discharge his cargo in time to connect with the Convoy. Also, we had a sick passenger to embark and were doubtful about making the ship in such bad weather. At 3.08 p.m. a Post Office clerk called at our Office to say the mails were ready for collection, but was informed that it was by then too late. At about 3.30 p.m. the Post Master him self came to our office and, amongst other things, stated : 1) That the mails were ready at 2.30 p.m. 2) That no one came from our office to collect the mails at that time or afterwards; 3) That the mails could not be closed at 2 p.m. because the Agency mails had not been received. We regret that the mils were not taken, especially as the ship was, in any case, unable,due to the bad weather.to sail at the originally arranged time, but we do feel that had the Post Master closed the mails before going to lunch, they could have been ready in time for us to have taken them by the launch which left at 3.00 p.m. c.c .Post Master, Bahrein.COPY INDIAN POST &amp; TSLSGBAFHS DEPT, URGENT From The Sub-Post Master Bah re in, Banrein 13/4/1943. Sir, To Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.Ltd. Agents, B.I.S.N.Co.Ltd•, Bahrein. The mail for the down boat S3.'WO SANG” was ready at 2/30 p.m. but Mr. Mahmood, Mail Clerk, did not come to take delivery and I myself personally requested Mr. Leared but of no effect. The steamer is still in harbour and God knows when she will sail. Kindly arrange to take delivery of the mail as early as possible. Yours faithfully, sd/- Rajabali, Sub-Postmaster.AM.ADE rylM** Vth A ^ 'M’ tW*. A CONFIDENTIAL. -fr*/ --i w*dt H.L. Jeratih Esquire, B.A.,M.S.P., F.H.E.S. (London) , Dip.Fr. (London) Director of Posts and Telegraphs, . Sind and Baluchistan circle. / A [ » ^he Political Agent, Bahrain . SB-144 dated at . Karachi the ^-4-1943 / FROM: TO: NO: Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to your letter NO: 76-C of 1930, dated the 13-5-1930, to this office,(copy enclosed), and to enquire whether from the political point of view or other local reasons there still exists any objection to employ Hindus, and Sikhs as Sub Postmasters, in the offices in the Persian Gulf ,particularised below. In view of the many changes that have since taken place in the political outlook and general policy and of the great cy.fference in the circumstances prevailing at that time and now, and also ii^vJ^w of the fact that a great number of Hindus and Sikhs are now carry Hag on their business and are the chief mercantile community in several places in the Persian Gulf, it is felt that there need not be any distinction in the employment of officials of any particular community in those places, at present. . '2/- The favour of an early reply is requested. NAMES OF IK THE POST OFFICES. 1. Bahrain 2. Dubai. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant.INDIAN POSTS AND 1'ELEGI^PIiS DEPARTMENT. Pjit.ss Trlicotiax. •kv Copy of a communicatioh NO: 76-C of 1930 dated the 13-5-30 from Capt. C.G. Prior,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Karachi. I have the honour to say that the Bahrain Government have heard with astonishment that a Hindu Mr. Kanv/ersingh, has been appointed permanently to Bahrain vice Mr. Zafar Hussain, who has instructions to report at Hyderabad, on the conclusion of his leave. They have asked me b request that this may be considered as they consider the appointment of a Hindu most undesirable, and request that the present incumbentMr. Zaffer Hussain who knows both Arabic and Persian and is parsona gxzkxwik grate with the Shaikhs and inhabitants may be retained in his appointment. I concur in hs their view, I have nothing against Mr. Kanwersingh who, I have no doubt is an excellent officer, he has, I believe officiafed before wihout any untoward incident occurring but nevertheless his appointment is undesirable for several reasons. You are probably aware that on k this extremely fanatical coast, Hindus are only allowed on sufferance. At Dubai for example they are confined in a single street, the ends of which are locked and which they may not leave after night fall. At Bahrain the situation is not so acute but there are universally despised, and it is only the shadow of the British Agency which makes their trade possible. I feel that unnecessarily to place a Hindu in a position of authority, where he may clash with local interests would be most unwise and harmful to our interests and since the post office is housed in-my building, I have an additional reason for wishing to avoid a potential cause % of trouble. Further since Mr. Kanwer Singh knows no Arabic, he will be very seriously handicapped in discharging his duties, which involves constant contact with the public. A fracas recently occurred at the Telegraph office which would easily have been avoided had the operator been familiar with the vernacular and I am not desirous of seeing it repeated. I trust that you will agree with me that in view of the local (PTO)Coit.-4Q. Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department. From TJ 3.0 of Posts 9.ndi TsIssts-p^is Sind and Baluciiistan Circle To Captain C.G* Prior, I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain* jr of enclosures 9 Dated Karachi , ^ 5th June 19 30 • » a ^ Sir, ^ With reference to your letter No. 76-C of 1930 dated the 13th May 1930, I have the honour to inform you that as Mr. fcafar Hussain has teen for atout 12 years in the Gulf and has got com pletely out of touch with the Indian Post Office it has teen deci ded to transfer him to India. I find that Hindus have several times previously teen employed at Bahrain and there has teen no complaint. This Department has had to incur consideratle charges on account of Travelling and I do not wish to transfer Mr. Kanwar Singh from Bahrain at present. If y however you consider it atsolutely nece ssary I will make arrangements to send a Mahomedan there. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Director* JUUU’Ah.—13i7—MlApp:-0, I'KOM ' -f [\0\ A The iTisj^ctor^sTTo 3 f 'ices, Persian Uul r ou.'-di vi si on fro Tee F o!L i ti c al Agen t, Bahrain, ?\o.,Lj —dateirairr T 19 . TTTh June 4 3. Sir, who js a candidate for liunshi Haffar bin Has8an employment in this office states that he is the son of—jr- T.] a icsident of village Bahrain ss an in the Thana of — District &gt; P ost office FafTrST boh ram I shall be imicli obliged if you will kindly have this verified and also have enquiries made into the character and antecedents of the candidate and communicate the result at your earliest convenience. I have, &amp;c., ?%■ x/^ A^GIVTAk- Inspector of O^ ices, Persian Gulf Sub-div: £ // / at Bahrain. ViiGIFPAh..— 1660 - 3 - 8 -iO— r '**■'** Corr.-60, INDIAN PO'STS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER. / No, % SB- 144 To Kar,ch \^ ^ May , N' ■ •^he political Agent, rour BaliraiJVMuscat Reference ^ Subject: transfer of officials to the Persian Gulf offices. Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to this office letter/endst. of even No. dated the 2-4-1943 on the subject quoted supra, and request the favour of an early reply thereu). ADE ^ ■— , ^4 1 ( 2c. a } k f i-.&amp;T. Circle.DEPARTMENT/OFFICE. r \o?&gt; Letter Draft Memorandum File No. Serial No.BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION TELEGRAMS : ‘FLYING’ BAHRAIN. CODES : BENTLEY’S &amp; I. A. T. A. TELEPHONE i 43M. / ./• NM\v' HBS. 567 . 906 . 3 £■ ■ ^3 BAHRAIN ISLANDS. PERSIAN GUL^. 28th Sept. 1943* The Assistant Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, POST OFFICE MAIL 1 # In accordance with our conversation on the subject of Post Office Mail, which took place yesterday, I shall be grateful if you will instruct the post Master to close all westbound mail on the day previous to it being embarked on one of our Services. The weight should be communicated to us before 12.00 L.T. and should include two separate figures; mail destined for Habbaniyeh and stations west of Habbaniyeh. 2. Mails for Basrah are not affected and may be despatched as in the past. 3 . This arrangement is now necessary in order that we may signal Karachi to reserve the necessary space on our Westbound Services. 4. We shall be glad if this can be introduced as from October 1st, 1943- 0 ''ill Yours faithfully, G.N. DALTON, Station Superintendent. QKC.# • -A ory th« dsy ' which th% mails are* being closed \U‘&gt;' The Sab-Postmasteri Bahrain* Political Bahrain, the Agency, &lt; a a apt, enter 7 4 1943 St*r'X Memorandum I have been asked by the British overseas Airways Corporation to info rm you that, v/ith effect from October 1st, 1943, all vest- bound mails ; ? .oina beyond Basra should be closed on the day previous to that on which they will be embarked on the Company’s services* Separate figures of v#eight should be communicated to the British Overseas Airways Corporations office before 12 noon local time^ in respect of mail destined (a) for Habbaniya and (b) for stations beyond Habbaniya. 2. The object of this arrangement is so that the British over seas Airways Corporation* a office here nay signal to Karachi for the necessary space to be reserved. 3. 'This arrangement does not affect ra^ils for Basra, which may be despatched as in the past* Political Agent, Bahrain. t'V twA *M i 1 COPT a PRESS NOTE (^) /jPI&gt; HEW DELHI- An attractive scheme of national savings has been deviced for small investors as a part of the new ’Save and Lend* campaign. It has been decided by the (rovernment of India to issue from October 1, post-office 12 year defence savings certificates. From the 8ame/f6-y , ears Defence savings certificates will cease to be issued. The national savings certificates will be obtainable at issue prices of Rs. 10/-, Rs. 50/-, *s. 100/., Is. 500/- and Rs. 1000/-. r Ihe total face vaule of the certificates which may be held by any person solely or jointly, is limited to Rs. 5000/-. No income tax will be levied on the yield from the certificates which will also not be taken into account in calulating assessable income and their payment will be made in all cases free of stamp duty. transfers of national savings, certificates by holders as security to private Individuals, banks or other concerns are prohibited; but certificates may b^ transferred to any officer of the Government in his official capacity ti be treated as secutity. he certificates will not be cashed until the end of the third year from the date of issue except in the case of death of the holder, but after three years the holder can surrender it any time before the completion of 12 years. If payment is claimed after three years the holder will get for certificate of Rs. 10/-, Rs. 10 8 - and xt for every succeeding year an addition of Annas 8/-. After twelve complete years the certificate holder will realize Ps, 15/- on a certificate of Rs. 10- new issue, it is hoped, will P roTO * W umm imoaa \JX OXJCIXJL 'HO a IltS XU UJTDan areas to make their contribution to defence loans and thereby help the Government in immobilizing surplus purcasing power• Sd. iirza lohammad For Postmaster, KarachiV V No •C/1417. Political Agency, Bahrain, 25th October 1943. To The Postmaster, Bahrain. MBMURATOUH I understand that according to your regulations you have to send all airgraphs for England from Bahrain via Bombay. This causes, wliat appears to me to be r a very unnecessary delay when it should be possible to arrange for airgraphs to be dealt'with in Iraq. I shall be grateful if you will take this matter up with the Superintendent of Post Office#, Hyderabad (Sind). Political Agent, Bahrain.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. l ' G° i ' 9 i No&gt; PA-310 27th October 1943 r ^' H. B. M*s Political Agent The Agency BAHREIN MAIL SERVICE BAHREIN ISLAND - UNITED KINGDOM Pile: 009.35 Dear Sir: I refer to our conversation on the 19th October during which we discussed the extremely poor mail service to the British Isles. I have received recently some information regard ing an 'Air Mail Letter Card' that is available to the Services. My understanding is that these cards are carried by all air route and make very good time between Bahrein and England. A specimen is attached. If this kind of correspondence could be made available to our British employees and their correspondents in England it would probably do much to remove the existing dissatisfaction in this matter. Whilst fully realising the problem with which the authorities are faced with regard to handling of mail at the present time it seems to me that efforts should be made, from the point of view of morale etc., to maintain a reasonable air mail service for civilians no less than for the Services, and the air card mentioned above might be a simple solution. There may be a number of reasons why this air mail letter card cannot be made available to civilians in Bahrein, and their correspondents at home, of which I am unaware. I shall much appreciate your views in the matter and your opinion as to whether you will be able to pursue it further. Yours very truly, Eor W. P. ANDERSON Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.Ji I) *0 •Ho •C/1472* 31at October 1943. /ty til***- I underetcuid that special facilitioa are granted to members of the Armed Forces serving abroad with units of His Majesty^ Havy, Army and Air Force when communicating by cable with their relatives and friends in the United Kingdom. I believe that the same privilege is granted to the relatives and friends of officers and men serving with Units abroad. 2. in ny opinion f the persona who are employed in under takings which hawe been notified in Kegulation No#2 of IrH*- issued under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order-in- Council 1939 as essential for the prosecution of the war are dust as much on active service as members of the Armed . orces of the Crown stationed in the Persian Gulf area. fhe under takings in question are the iiahrain Petroleum Companyj Messrs# Petroleum Concessions Limited, and Messrs* Petroleum development (Qatar) Limited. The employoeiiof those concerns have many of them been abroad for more than three years, a period certain wireless announcements have told us is members of the Armed Forces to serve outside the United kingdom, and there is little orospect of their being able to to the United Kingdom in the immediate ow.ng to .he essential nature of their operations and the difficulty of obtaining leave reliefs. 3. I should be grateful if you would make representations on my behalf to the appropriate authority with * ™ . , obtaining sanction for the privilege mentioned in paragraph 1 of this letter to be extended to the persons mentioned in paragraph 2 of this letter* &lt;f£ H. L. Penfold, Bsq., Officer- ln-rhnrge t Cable 4 Wir.l.e. Limited, Bahrain. fhC4th Movember 1943. r' Please refer to your letter Ko. PA-310 doted the 27th October 1943. 2. I will do Y;hot I can to w Air Mail better Card’ 1 focilitaes extended to the employees of your Company# 3. I have* taken up the question of special facilities for telegrams with Cable $ ' r irele«s and will let you knov.* the result in due course. Yours sincerely, Ur. TUmaoll )&lt;?• BroYm, Acting Chief Local Hepresentfitive, The Balwain PetroleuLi Co., Ltd., Bahrain.17th Nov«jnbnr 1943. D.O.No.C/1581. Piers* refar to your demi-official . S &gt;/• *• letter No.SFW/16 dated the 15th November 1943. 2. I shall be grateful if the Divisional Manager will forward my representations to your Head Office. * fc'7/r N. L. Penfold, Ksq., Officer in Charge, Cable A Wireless Ltd., nnh-rnie -!&gt; PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED P/A.7/1923 Bahrain, 8 th January, 1944. To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith a letter received through the Post Office addressed to the Chief Customs Officer, Qatar, and shall be grateful if you will kindly confirm if^it will be in order for us to despatch it to him in our mail to Qatar. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PE ■■ 0NS limited Enel: Letter ACM -Vi%. Date of despatch. 2 . List of enclosures. DEPARTMENT/OfHCJCE. Draft Memorandum File No. Serial No. S-5 (Small) B. P. 6&gt;67/A/S-79—25-6-42—50,000 pads.PETROLETl ^ © P/A. 7/1943 Bahrain, 19th Jan Bahrain, 19th January, 1944. To H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith a letter received through the Post Office addressed to the Chief Customs Officer, Qatar, and shall be grateful if you will kindly confirm if it will be in order for us to despatch it to him in our mail to Qatar. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Enel.\ ^ i J' ^ * (^) British India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (incorporated in England; TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. f No BI/S. 84 BAHREIN, 30th JANUARY, ig/44. H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We have to advise you that the s .s . rt Kingyuan rt which vessel arrived and sailed this-morning, bound for India via ports, was unable to accept any passengers, mails or cargo. We have in our Register the following passengers awaiting transport:- GENTS. LADIES MINORS. BOMBAY s 1st Class 2nd Class DECK: 66 13- 4 5 1 KARACHI: 2nd Class 835 DECK-: 79 (The above nutober of deck passengers includss children also.) PASSAGES REQUIRED AFTER 8th FEBRUARY: for India - 122'tut*political Agency, Bnhrain. natcd fth February 1944. From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf division, Hyderabad, Sind. Renewal of contract regarding conveyan ce of mails at Bahrain * Sir, ^//7 I Irave the honour to invite a reference to your letter No. A.-5/72, dated December 22nd 1943. 2 # The contractor is willing to renew the contract irom 28th Anril 1944, but on revised terms. He now wishes to bo paid Rs. 5 for journeys to Moharraq aerodrome and hs. 4 for journeys to the British Overseas Airways Corporation flying-boat station ^ nd gives as hin reasons the increase in local taxi fares. OvJing to the increased services of civil aeroplanes and the irregular tijnihg of their arrival, he points out that most maiSs have to be se ^t in locally hired taxis. I have verified these ’acts and the prices charred by local taxis from the Post Office to Moharraq and the Flying Boat station, and recommend that the contract be renewed at the revised rates. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Agent,Bahrain.'ll No -14/1 Political Agency, Bahra in. Dated /Z February 1944 2 If A From To The Political A^ent, Bahrain. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. A Sir, I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter I have received from Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. 2 . -f/hilc on tour on the Trucial Coast this month I made enquiries from Messrs Gray Mackenzie's Agent at Dubai learnt that ho had a waiting list of 88 persons who were anxious to travel to India. On three separate occasions leading Hindu business men approached me and sought my assistance in obtaining travel facilities. They complained with much justification that the business and the hoal^ of the community were suffering as a result of the serious shortage of passenger accommodation to India 3&gt; j suggest tliat the Ministry of *ar Transport bo requested to make a definite allotment of passages to both Bahrain and the Trucial Coast on all steamers leaving Basra for India and scheduledto call at the two above-mentioned ports. I have the honour to be sir ’ &gt; . ^ Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahra in. a/PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED We enclose herewith a letter 3?eceived through the Post Office addressed to the Chief Customs Officer, Qatar, and shall he grateful if you will kindly confirm if it will be in order for us to despatch it to him in our mail to Qatar. Yours faithfully, For fc on behalf of Enel. ACM-d^-i- it-innl Ardent. Bahra No S^o -14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain. The T T arch 1944. To The ^Wianer, # Petroleum Concessions Lta. ^ahrain. ITemorandum. Reference your letter No P/A/7/ 1985 dated the 2nd March 1944. 2# You may forward the cover which is returned herewith to the Customs Officers Qatar, through your /ail bag.NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Printed in England. JULY 1940. (5.000 pads. 1 CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. I INCORPORA TED IN ENGLAND.) Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. / y QV248/L XT KARACHI 54 11'OL POLITICAL AGENT BAHREIN MAILS B/C 142 AAA REF YOUR NO 395-16/28 FEBRUARY 9 TO SUPERINTENDENT POSTS HYD SIND RE CONTRACT CONVEY ANCE MAILS BAHREIN AAA DIRECTOR-GENERAL P AND T CONSIDERS RUPEES FOUR PER TRIP OF THREE MILES TO SEADROME EXCESSIVE AAA WIRE IF IT CAN BE REDUCED TO RUPEES THREE = DIRECTOR P AND T KARACHI = Dui ^nyieTuaC, MARK YOUR REPLYrSLEGHA-M - EfT CLAIR ^om Political, Bahrain. To Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs, ho. 194 Dated 14th March 1944. Reference your telegram ho.B/C 142 of Llarch nth. Contractor not repeat not prepared to accept Rs. 3 3AF. Political -AIR POSTAL ft 0 T I &lt;3 3 / * 3 Revision of rates of air mail foes v/ith immediate effect the following rates of air mail Postage will be payable on all Air Mail articles posted for transmission from Indie to different Countries. DESIGNATION Superscrip tion Rate per half ounce or part thereof (char- Rate per geable in addi- postcard (in tion to ordinary elusive of postage)on letters ordinary pos- and packets tage. (i) Aden, Canada, Egypt, Rs. A. P. Eire (Ireland) Eritrea,Gold Coast,Gr^eat Britain and Nor y '%rn Ireland, Kenya,Uganda and Tanganyika, Malta, Mau ritius, Newfoundland, Niger ia, Nyas aland,Palestine,Rho No super- desia (Northern and Southern)scription re- 0 14 0 Seychelles, Sierra Leone, quired. Somalia (Southern Somaliland or former Italian Somaliland), Sudan, (Anglo-Egyptian)Trans jordan, Union of South Africa (Including Basutoland and Swaziland) and Zanzibar. Rs. A. P. 0 14 0 \ (ii) Algeria, Bechuanland Protectorate, Belgian Congo, British Somaliland, Cameroons, Dahomey, French Equatorial Africa, French Guinea, Ivory Coast, Libya,Madagascar, Mor- rocco, Portuguese East &amp; West Africa, Reunion, South West Africa and Tunisia. India Africa 1 2 0 0 8 0 (iii) Iran (Persia),Iraq,Saudi Arabia, Syria (including Lebanon) India and Turkey. Iraq 1 0 0 0 8 0 (iv) Ceylon India Cylon 0 (per part 1 0 tola or thereof) 0 1 3 (v) China India China 1 , 7 0 0 10 0 (vi) Cyprus, Gibraltar,Por tugal, Spain, Switzerland and Union of soviet Socialists Re publics. India Africa 1 2 0 0 8 0 (vii) Canada (by all-air route) India-Lagos- Canada 2 0 0 0 11 0 (viii) New Zealand Australia New Zealand. 0 15 0 0 5 0 (ix) Sweden India-U.K. Sweden. 1 8 0 0 10 0Designation b’uperscrip- tion. Rate per half v_V ounce or part thereof(charge Rate per able in addition postcard (in to ordinary pos- elusive or ordi- tage} on letters nary postage, and packets. (x) United States of India-Lagos- America U. 3. A. Rs. A. P 2 0 0 Rs. A. P 10 0 (xi) Argentine, Bolivia,^India-Lagos- Brazil,Chile,Ecuador,Para- Brazil 200 0 13 0 guany Peru and Uruguay. (xii) Colombia,Costa Rica Dutch West Indies (Aruba,Be- naire and Curacoa),E13alvador Guatemala, Guiana (British, Dutch and French),Honduras (British), Honduras (Republic) India- Martinique, Mexico,Nicaragua, Lagosx 200 0 13 0 Panama (0*nal Zone), Panama Trinilayid Republic), Surinam, Trindad Venezuela, Barbados and Wind ward Islands (Grenada, St. Lucia &amp; St. Vincent). (xiii) Bahamas, Bermuda, Cuba, Dominican Republic, Dutch West Indies (Saba, St.Eustatius and St. Martin), Guadeloupe, Haiti, Jamica, Leeward Islands ( India-. (Antigua, Dominica, Montserrat Lagoa Porto 2 0 0 0 13 0 and Nevis), Porto Rico and Virgin Rico. 4. The rate of Rs.l/6/- per half ounce, formerly applicable^to air mails for the U.S.A. sent by the air-cum-sea route via U.K., is not now in force as that route does not ordinarily offer any advantage in •^'ansit time over the all-sea route. islands v r&gt; islands/ 2 . .0 Telegram Prom To No. 290 Dated 23rd Parch 1944 XXX Political Agent, Bahrain Political Resident, Bushire IV Your telegram No.714 Parch 20. None as she is returning to Basra PoliticalNo 14/1 POLITICAI, AGKNCY, Bahrain. The/o/Z: April 1^)44. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf division, Karachi• Memorandum . Reference your memorandum No.A-5/72, dated the 30th March 1944. 2. ; ill you please send me the renewal agreement in quadruplicate in the proper form desired by you. On receipt of the form two copies will bo returned to you duly executed. *}c. for Political Agent, / &lt; 9 ^ Bahrain.gosginigrTMU 2 X X H Li a &amp; LJJLLiUL* •&gt; / Bsitim He *id may k Uonsu late •General Buehir « v the let ^rii 1944• From To i'Olit ioal Resident in the lore lari Gulf, auehire. Tht HopreoentatlYO, Mlnlotry of Wmr Tr»f»aport f B A S R A « Ho* 5C4*»S » TMited the let April 1944* Great dleoomerit it being oaused by eteii&amp;ere arriving at Gulf porta fro® Basra with a full oo®pla®ent of paasengera for India and wl tft no acoouirtodati on for any further passenger a* a« Nearly 360 persons are awaitpaaeagea of all elaaaea at Kuwait, Bush ire, Bahrain, Dubai and yuacat. Moat of the® are business mxi and ther point out with some Justifioa- tlon that this serlcua Portage of passenger acoonnodation is •erioualy affeoting both their business am their health* 3* •Vhile 1 realise that tha shipping position is dlflloult, I would be glad of any steps you oan taka to arrange a definite aliotBcnt of passages for QcIf passengers on all steacers scheduled to oall at any of the Gulf ports* 4* To assist you in making these allotments, 1 suggest that Msssrs* Gray, Kackensle &amp; Company Limited, Basra, bs asked to obtain from their Gulf agsats numbers of passengers awaiting passages at each port* on ths basis of allotments made by you ths local agents oan distribute passages in order of priority of booking* 6* In addition to pas.:cigars most of these ports also have (quantities of oar go await ii*; shipment. 3d# GSOFFR&amp;r PRICE. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* AST8SYSD. / Ed. B.THCUAS. tor Seoretary to the Joilt lo.il afsidoit iii th« i'srtiiur. Silt. j?. V British Residaioy &amp; Consulate-Gener&amp;l, Ko* 305»3 * Bus hire, the 1st April 1944* Copy forwarded, with compliments, to 1« 2. 3* 4* The Secretary to the Government of India in the external Affairs Department, New Delhi* The Political Agent, K uwa it &gt; The Political Agent, BahraTn •%/ The Political Agent, Fuse a FT RHL.Copy of the Postal Notice, dnted the 18th ^pril 1944, from the Sub Post Master, Bahrain, the Political A^ent, Bahrain. !Vl (w) to /ith effect from the 15tlv^pril 1944, the Money Order Service to Bubal 'isresiimed and the commission on the ?'oney Orders to be exchanged between India and Dubai from that date is fixed at 8 annas for every sum of Rs. 10/- or fraction there of. No -14/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The A 4-CtApril 1944. Copy forwarded to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. for Political Agent, Bahrain.PA-245 THE B A HREIN PETROLEUM CQjypANY LILITSD Avali - Bahrein Islarxd , Persian Gulf \ 0 \\ Date April 19, ny 1944. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I refer to your letter D.O.No.C/1504 dated 4th November, 1943, in connection with mail service between Bahrein and United Kingdom, when you mentioned that you were endeavouring to obtain the use of 'Letter Cards’ for civilian personnel in Bahrein. I have not heard from you in this connection and am wondering whether it is possible to develop anything with- regard to the use of 'Airmail Letter Cards'. ni, feTuly, \i. P. aNDIESON, Chief Local Representative, THB BiHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Telegram From To No 1022* ® Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Bahrain* Political Agent, Kuwait* Dated 29th and Received 30th April, 1944* 04 My endorsement No 305-S April 1st* 2. M.W*T* inform me that they have been advised by Gray Mackenzie Basra 'that practically all outstanding passengers and cargo have recently been cleared from ?Gulf ports'* 3. Please confirm if this is correct* It not telegraph number of passengers and quantity of cargo awaiting clearance at Bahrain, Dubai and Kuwait* ^f%uji r7 ' -BRITCOTSDL-fclB 14/1 Telegram • ■fedWiPfllP 11 From political fgent, Behrain. J To political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. No 401 Dated 1st May, 1944. __ ——~?mc Ijff'QRTAKT Please telegraph number of passengers end quantity of cargo awaiting clearance at Dubai and Sharjah for India. -POLITIC/L- ICHTelegram /VK 14/1 (^) From Britagent, Sharjah* To No 737 Political Agent, Bahrain* Dated and Received 2nd May, 1944* IMPORTANT ?Your telegram No 401 May 1st* (a) For Karachi, 4 Second Class, 20 Deck passengers and 715 tons cargo and (b) For Bombay, 15 Deck passengers and 30 tons cargo* -ERITAGENT- ICH I ft 90 IJs //-N 14/1 Telegram From To No 408 Dated 3rd May, 1944* Political fgent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Pushire. hX $ n&gt;l$ Your telegram No 1022 /pril 29th« 2 . situation has been much improved by recent sailing and now only 25 passengers and 20 tons at Bahrain and 39 passengers and 45 tons at Dubai snd Sharjah remain / ✓ to be moved. -POLITICAL- IEHNo / -M r -14/1 POLITIGA.L AOKNCY, BAHHAIN. The 1944 To The Chief Local Representative, Rahrain Petroleum Company, Bahrain. Memorandum . Reference your letter No. PA-245, dated the 19th April 1944. 2. Unsuccessful representations /ere made to ( ' \ ( speed up the air mail service and so far inconclu*- sive representations have been made to obtain a reduction in the cable rates but unfortunately nothing was done about the 'Airmail Letter Cards'. This question will be dealt with at once. Political Agent, Bahrain.INDIAN POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS DEPARTMENT (Post Office) ^opy of Director General’s circular No. dated the 12th October 1942. 1. Air Mail Letter Card Service from India to the United Kingdom. An Air ?feil Letter Card Service from India to the United Kingdom for British Officers and soldiers serving in India will be introduced with effect from the 26th October 1942. The printing and distribution of air mail letter cards to the personnel entitled to use the concession will be arranged by the military authorities. 2. These air mail letter cards wi&amp;l be prepaid with postage at the rare of 4 annas per letter card. 3. The air mail letter cards should be made up by the offices of posting into separate bundles or packets, labelled 'Air Tfeil Letter^ Cards for U.K.» and consigned without any delay, to Karachi Air for onward disposal. 4. These letter cards will be carried by air as far as T 7est Africa and thence to destination by air if the next homeward bound flying boat has sufficient capacity otherwise by sea. Cf.B. 47 (23)/41)No -14/1 M5M POLITICAL AG^CY, BAHRAIN. The I T ay 1944. From To T'lajor T. Hickinbotham, C.I.F, C.B.F.. Political Anent, Bahrain. The Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle, Karachi. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that the Bahrain Petroleum Company has been designated as an undertaking essential for the prosecution of the &lt;var and that their British employees are required by law to remain at their duty. 2. A considerable delay is being experienced in the receipt of air mail letters from Kngland and unfavourable comparisons are being made between the time taken by our air mail services and the much shorter time taken by the United States air mail services carrying letters a much greater distance. The American employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company have the privilege of making use of .American Army postal facilities whereas up till now the British employees of the same concern have not been granted a similiar privilege. 3 . I note from your Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department circular No. 2 of the 12th October 1942 that the air nail letter card service jas introduced from the 26th of October of that year for British officers and soldiers serving in India. Tould it be possible to extend these facilities to the British employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company? I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, BahrainPETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED © P/A.7/2070 Bahrain, 2nd May, 1944. To H.B.MTs Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We enclose herewith a letter received through the Post Office addressed to the Chief Customs Officer, Qatar, and shall he grateful if you will kindly confirm if it will he in order for us to despatch it to him in our mail to Qatar. Enel. Yours faithfully, Eor &amp; on hehalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED\ :i 7 No'3'/ -14/1 (53) / political agtncy , BAHRAIN. The 6 Di May 1944. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., Bahrain. Memorandum . Reference your letter No. P/A.7/2070, dated the 2nd May 1944. 2. It is in order for you to despatch the enclosed cover to Qatar by your office mail bag./ A • &lt;2 3 C&gt;S No. 1025-77/4 i - British Residency and Consulate General Bushire* Dated the 1st. hay, 1944 To The Political Agent, Bahrain. ienorandun A copy is enclosed of letter Mo. J.2. of the 17th. March, 1944 from the Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad (Sind), it is requested that a copy of .the Posts and Telegraphs Guide (1943) may kindly be obtained from the Bahrain Post Office and sent to this office. 2. The sum of annas eight may be debited to this Residency account. Secreta: itical Resident an Gulf VEM.Prom Superintendent of Po^fc Offices, Lower Sind and Persicm^ivision, HyderalDad (Sind) To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Pushire. Dated the 17th. Parch, 1944. No. J.2 Sir, Pith reference to your letter No. 142-77/4 dated the 20th. January, 1944 I have the honour to say that the price of the new edition (1943) of the Posts and Telegraphs Guide has 'been fixed at Rs.l/8/- The balance of Rs.-/8/- may therefore kindly he paid to the Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain and the copy taken from the Bahrain Sub Office. I have etc., v’ UUurtU . Superintendent.V ..'I-have 'the honour to. ackno wledge receliPt of your letter ho. 1^80.-14/1 dated the' o.5.44 and to say that a further communication p / Uj will .folio0 shortly. ZAK/ADPS C-VajJOQ / MGIFPAi.-Copy of letter No. Mails. B/Air/A-165, dated the 31st ay 1944, from the Director of Posts &amp; Telegraphs, Sindlf' Baluchistan Circle, Karachi, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. f ith reference to your letter No. 1280-14/1, dated the 3rd May 1944, I have the honour to say that the use of the Air letter service which is a rationed service controlled by the Military authorities is at present limited to Military Personnel who are on Active Servic e in India . The concession is not even admissible to Military personnel who are in civil emnloy. The British employees of Bahrain Petroleum Company being civilians, it is regretted that the use of the air letter service cannot be extended to them. No. 1661-14/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 6 th June 1944. Copy forwarded to the Chief Local Representa tive, the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Bahrain, for information, with reference to my memorandum No. 1204, dated the 27th April 1944. ell. fbr Political Apent, Bahrain. rPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 5th June 1944. The Superintendent of Post Offices, ^ lower Sind &amp; Persian Gulf Divison, Hyderabad, Sind• Memorandum . Reference your me^randum No. A.5/72, dated the 27th May 1944. 2 . I enclose herewith duly executed 2 copies of the contract for conveyance of mails at Bahrain. for^ olitical An^nt, Bahrain. Copy to-getlier with a copy of the agreement forwarded to Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanoo, C.I•H. Bahrain. 5■OSnMBBRM M hmzmwT . This agreement made the BLTWEKN Thf* GOVKRNOH GKNKRAL IN CuU^CIL day of (hereinafter referred to ae txie ^ovemor'■‘eneril m council which exp re eel on ehall Include hi a succesaore and aaaigno) of the one part and Khan Sahib Yueif Kaaoo (hereafter referred to ae the contractor which expresalon »h©U include hie pereon*! rep re ce nt ft ivee and permittee aeaignB) of the other part* hHKBKAS the contractor h as agreed to p»vide a motor vehicia service for transit conveyance and delivery as hereinafter mantioneo Bahrain* U anana-Muhharaq. mail service of all postal articles and mail bags ©re defined in the Indian Fost office Act 1898 and nulea there under aa amended for the time bsing(hereinafter referred to in the Act) Kid the Governor General in »-ouncil has agreed to entrust the work to the contractor upon the terms and conditions hereinafter appearing* l/- # during the continuance or this agreement that ie to say for the period of one year from the JS&amp; day of 1 this agreement he determined hy aach notice aa la herein after meat ion **d or otherwise in due course or lev»( hereinai t^r referred to as the said contract period)the cant?*ctor agrees to take all air mails from the Bahrain iost office, uenamah end duly safely and expeditiously deliver than to the station superintendent imperial Airways, or his rep recitatives at the Aerodrome or aegplene base Muherraq or at any other pi** as mey ba the recognised depot in ash rain for the receipt of ‘to* or ^ut* going itaperjljel Munaila* 2/-* The contractor agrees to be likewise responsible lor - the bringing back of all Air Mails to the Bahrain i-oet office from the Aerodrome or the sea plena base* 3/- # during such time as the malls are in his actuel or constructive possession the contractor \jnd*rtal*t3 to be solely responsible for the safe guarding and complete protection of the mails*4/. # Should the mails be lost ia en^ or my way damaged whilst in the possession of the contractor he agrees to psy at hew uelhi the sum of hs. 600/- to the Governor ^neral in Council* 5 /« # whould the ecu tractor fails to deli ver the mails at the aerodrome or sea plane base n£xv aforesaid in time for any service he agrees to pgy Rs.2oO/-0t New Delhi to the Governor wieneral in council# Xhis is subject oily to the proviso that he has been kept fully informed by Imperial Mrwflys as to the correct times of arrival and departn ie of imperial Airways planes, S/ m , 9 The contractor agrees that at no time will the mails be under the responsibility or in tbs posssssion of ary one other th&lt;n a person of tfahralnj.| Indian, or Najdi nationality* 7 /_, When the contractor arrives at the Post office for the conveyance of air mallet the postmaster guarantees not to dot sin him fbr a period longer than fifteen minutes* This is subject only to the proviso that the Postmaster has been kq?t fully informed Imperial by the XaBf*xrtte/Miways as to the correct times of arrival and departure of the planes* Shou&amp;d he exceed this period penalty clause No: 6 is nullified for that occasion should the plane be missed* Subject to these conditions, the Governor vj enerol in Council agrees to pay the sum of R8#5/-only to the contractor for journey to Moharaq Aerodrome for the conveyance of mails and ks*^/— for Journey to B*^*A.C* Flying Boat Station which may arrive at Bahrain* The contractor shall not transfer or sublet this contract or any part of it or interest in it to any other person or persons nor attempt to do so wi out the previous consent in writing of the Director Posts and Telegraphs, Aar a chi which miy be grantedmgy be grrmf&amp; o r refu^id in his absolute discretion* 10/-* £he contractor undartakss to receiva th« malls from ths Post office end daiivar to the Airways authorities at the Aerodrome or seadrome, in good time before the departure of each service end likewise the contractor agrees to take delivery of incoming mail and deliver same to the Postal authorities as soon as possible after arrival* 11/-* This contract* mgy be absolutely determined md put an end to by either of contracting parties giving four calender months notice in writing to ths other o^ his intention so as to determine end put sn end to the same* 12/-* Any notice required to be given o r anything required to be done hereunder by the uovexno r general in ibuncll, the Director general, Posts and felegraph* or the Political Agent Bahrain^ shall be sufficient if signed or done ty the Political Agent Bahrain, or the Director.General, Posts and felegraphs, flaw Delhi or any person authorised by him and service of V ouch notice on the contractor shall be sufficient if the sane be delivered or left at the office of the coatmeto r o r sent ty registered post addressed to the contractor at their last knoen place of business in bah rain end any notice required to be given hereunder on the part of the contractor shall be sufficiently given if staled by the contractor and addressed by registered post to the office of the *i rector General, Posts and Telegraphs, i&gt;ew Delhi, or the political *gent u ah rain. 13/-* A 11 disputes end differences arising out of or in anywise touching or concerning this agreement shall be referred to the sole arbitral Ion of the Di rector General of Posts and Telegraphs and failing him the political Agent* bahrsin and if the d i rector v»enere 1 or«nd if t'no Director uenerol or th* political Agent as the case may be la unable or unwilling to actf to the eole arbi tration of aome other person appointed by tne Director general or falling him the kxa Political Agent willing to act ae su di arbltaato r 0 It will be no objection to aiy such appointn ent that the arbitrator sox appointed is a uovexnment servant that he hrf to deftl with the matters to v;hich this agreement rebates and that in tt^e course of his duties as such voveminent servant he has expressed views on sll or any of the matters in dispute or difference, me award of the arbitrator so appointed shall be final and binding on the said parties* interpreted in accordance with the laws of British India and be enforceable in British India* In WXT&amp;h£S whereof for end on behalf of the Governor general of India in council the Politi cal Agent Bahrain hath hereunto set his h&amp;nd and the eaid respective hand the day and the year first hereinafter written* 14/— This agreement shall in aU respect be Signed sealed &amp;d delivered by the above named in the presence | Chaang/-*24*v* *44*&lt;7 - /? • PB^HOLETO? CONCESSIONS UNITED i/A.7/2141 Bahrain, 24th June, 1944. To h.B.h’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Bear Sir, e enclose herewith a letter received through the Post Office addressed to the Chief Customs Officer, atar, and shall be grateful if you will Kindly confirm if it will be in order for us to dispatch it to him in our mail to u atar. .C VJJ. U PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIIIITSD Yours faithfully, For &amp; on b ehaIf of a, Enel.No.2^^ -14/1 IV. Political Agency, Bahrain. The ,23r4 October 1944 To (J|) • The s»ib Postmaster, Bahrain* Memorandum. Reference your letter No. 608, dated the 26th September 1944. 2. I suggest the matter may be referred to the Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluehistan, Karachi, for the required authorization. w Political Agent, Bahrain.•mmm mmmm BnHBHH # No. 3407-14/1. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The /£/£November, 1944* The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind &amp; Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind* Memorandum - &gt;; ■ Reference your memorandum No.A.5/72 dated 14th September, 1944* 2. I enclose herewith duly executed two copies of the contract for conveyance of nails at Bahrain. ^ 34t%- for Political Agent, Bahrain, Copy together with a copy of the agreement forwarded to Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanoo, „ M.B.E., Bahrain.Audit Office, r I : or Journal of Money Orders paid during account ending 19 of money orders issued in !9 the period of f on account Ferial flu. Tint? of fwyiiient. No. of jooisey oiver. AlUOia T«s!ei{ raoiiic immey o:det'. money order. Head or aub olfice of Remarks R R a. »&gt;. Rrou^ld f«rwRr&lt;1• KHCLOSURE TO AGSEKMiUT EXSCUT^O ON THE THIRD DAY OP JAN WHY., 1944 ' BETVEEN THF- GDVEPNOR- GBNSBAL IN COUNCIL Atf D K.S. YU SIP KANOO MAIL CiNW ACTOR IN RESpECT OF BAHRAIN-UANAUA- MUKARAQ MAIL fiT-HPIlS. . • «OoO. . . 1.A/-. The coat^actor &amp;hall ca^ry as part ox* mallo Post Off!o® foxms and fftorea despatched by the ?o t*fcrl Stock Depot or the office© where such form* and ©to i©b axe printed end etc red to the vorloue poet offices itailv^y and V steamer stations and uallwy Mall Service office© naned in the tfehiduies attached to the agreemoit and such other places aa be tequlred by the Director of Poets and Telegraphs f Sind and Baluchistan Cl role 9 Karachi and shall not claim any extra remuneration on thefc account* Sljpi^d by the said acting pramieea for and beihalf o Gbvernor-General in Counc the presence of Signed sealed and deilve] above named In the presec// Of / (of n&amp; British Residency &amp; Consulate-General^ Bushire, the 25th January, 1945 'V J p** The Political Agent, BAHRAIN . So MEMORANDUM NQ.117-S Will you please enquire from the Post Office and let me know all the routes by which Air Mail from Bahrain is carried. It is particularly desired to know whether mail for Aden is routed via Cairo as well as Karachi. 3D/- GEOFFREY PRIOR POLITICAL RESIDENT,PERSIAN GULF ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ?A. * cjUj 4' /lote. r P !EMDj No. 5^1- 14/1.- Political Agency, Bahrain The 30th January, 1945. To The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain. The Sub Postmaster, Bahrain. Memorandum. Will you please let me know for the information of the Hon'ble the Political Resident all the routes by which air mail from Bahrain is carried. It is particularly desired to know whether mail for Aden is routed via Cairo as well as Karachi. Political Agent, BahrainNo * £&gt; c 1£&gt;- i4/i Political Agency, Bahrain The 12th February, 1945. 3. 4. The Secretary to the Hon*516 the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Reference your memorandum No.ll7-S dated the 25th ry, 1945. West Bound. (a) Bahrain - Basra - Baghdad - Lydda or Kallia (from Jerusalem) - Cairo. (b) A branch connects Baghdad with Teheran. Letters for latter place are included in Baghdad bag. (c) A branch connects Cairo with Ankara via Cyprus. Letters for Ankara are included in Cairo bag. (d) Cairo - Khartoum - Kampala - Mombasa - Dar-es-Salaam - Mozambique - Lorenzo - Marques - Durban. (e) Cairo - Khartoum - Nairobi. (f) Cairo to Lagos via El Fasher and Fort Lamy (Chad). (g) Cairo - Jedda - Aden - Karachi. Letters for Jedda are included in Cairo bag. East Bound . Normal route to Karachi - Calcutta. Mail for Aden is routed via Karachi unless other ictions are shown on the Post Office way bill and bag for Political Agent, BahrainNo. go7- 14/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 1st March, 1945. From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Superintendent of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. Subject: Renewal of contract for conveyance of mails at Bahrain. Sir I have the honour to refer to your letter No.A.5/72 dated the 18th January, 1945 and to enclose herewith a copy of letter No.L/8 dated the 22nd February from the present con- following amendments:- Paras 1, 5 and 7. For Imperial Airways read; British Overseas Airways Corporation. 3 # With regard to para (2) of the contractor*s letter, it is suggested that the sentence 'during the latter*s working hours' should be inserted after the expression Bahrain Post Office, Manamah in para (1) and (2) of the v agreement. 4. With regard to para (1) of the same letter the expression 'or other recognised depot' should be inserted at the end of para (2), after 'sea plane base aforesaid' in para 5. and after aerodrome or seadrome in para 10 of the agreement. 5* The contractor has been informed that he is entitled under para 8 of the agreement to a payment of Rs.4/- or 5/- as the case may be for each and every journey performed by him for the conveyance of mails.^ His para 3 refers. 6. If the suggested amendments are acceptable please return the draft agreement for completion. tractor. 2 The draft agreement forwarded by you requires the I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, V Mi- for Political Agent, Bahrain cA^VIQ/1 No. - l/4ir- Political Agency, Bahrain, The 3rd March, 1945. To Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanoo, C.l.E., Bahrain* Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No. 1/8 dated the 22nd of February 1945, I have to inform you that it is not now possible to amend the present agreement. Under clause 8 of the current agreement it appears that you are en titled to Ks.5 or Rs.4/- for every journey you are required to make by the Postal authorities for the conveyance of mails to the B.O.A.C. Yours faithfully, 'V No. 8W. for Political Agent, Bahrain. uM&gt;P- Copy together with copy of the letter under reference forwarded to the Sub Postmaster, Bahrain, for information.\ J IMPt5^^R &amp; EXPORTER. • A sj. _ A.rl iJ~j&gt; Telegraphic Address; (KANOO. BAHRAIN) Telephone No. Wnsuf fin fhrnfd Sanaa. BAHRAIN. Pbksian (Gulp) ated ?th March , 1945 .. / Political Agent, Q*Wa® *A Riih-nu-i n * U ' Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No.821-14/1 of 3rd instant. Before we sign the new agreement, if you see no objection, we would request that our observations be sent to the Postal authorities - The existing contract is up to 28th April, 1943, and even if the reply from Postal authori ties is delayed, we shall carry on the mail work till a decision is arrived at. Yours faithfully, * •1 No. ^J+U- 14/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 11th March, 1945. To The Naval Officer in charge, Bahrain. Please recall our telephone conversation of the 4th of March. 2. The British Overseas Airways Corporation refuse to hand over the mails to anyone other than the recognised army and civil Post offices. They have however referred the question to their Regional Headquarters in Karachi. [L, ^ Political Agent, Bahrain. cx?GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, Receipt EXPRESS LETTER [N, L \—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,} From Political Resident, Bushire, N&lt;k 285-3 bated 24th March, 1945 m JubjectI- Despatch of air mail cover to Aden via E^ypt . dated the Reference your eiemorandurn No. 12 th February, 1245. 593-14/1 2 . I enclose two envelopes addressed to his Excellency the Governor and Commander-in-Chief Aden, despatched by the Political Resident’s tour office from Bahrain in October, 1944. I shall be glad if you will make careful and full enquiries from the Bahrain Post Office and ascertain how these two covers came to be sent via Egypt instead of via Karachi, (c.f. paragraph 4 of letter under reference). 3. Please return the envelopes with your reply. ATTESTED SD/-GEOFFREY PRIOR POLITICAL RESIDENT,PERSIAN GULF. for Secretary to the Political Resident| Persian Gulf. MFP—120G 8&amp;P—(M-l 723)—4-2 36—200,000.1B55 - 14/1. /• To The Sub-postmaster, Bahrain, MiJlD POuITICitij Biiarialh* olst Marcn ld45, V / . | L * A C 1 * Reference your letter Wo. C.856, dated the 31st January ld45. 2* I enclose two envelopes addressed to His Excellency the Governor and Commander-In-Chief, Auen, despatched from hbre in October lu44. Please let me know why these two covers were sent via Egypt instead of via Karachi. 3* please return the covers with your reply. s'*, for POi.XIICiu. Alibi'll, .dau tudLW •1 £ m GOVERNMENT Of INDIA POiaiTICAii AQl.HLX Department. EXPRESS LETTER N. B .—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, &amp;m% by post to stive telegraphic expense and undue use of the wirea, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save taue astd formalities It Is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. 12'Di5» T&gt;~ Datea the 5tll April 194 5,. XdL dQU'BuL iHi, POiiIXICiiii Id Xtih Vhti&amp;ljid GUiiF, BUbHIKfc.. Subjectj- Despatch of air mail cover to Acien via ^ mpt. f Reference your Express better No. 285-S dated the 24th March 1^45. The Sub-Postmaster reports that the two covers for Aden were sent in error via Cairo instead of Via Karachi. 3. The envelopes are returned herewith. KMB for POLITICAL* BAiitlAlN. S. 6. MFP—«27 S&amp;P—6788—(M-1269)—24-11-42—800,000.I No.1517-14/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 12th April, 1945. To The Naval Officer in charge, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference my memorandum No.944 dated the 11th March 1945. 2 . The British Overseas Airways Corporation have now informed the Sub Postmaster that they have been authorised by their Regional Head quarters, Karachi to deliver mails for the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and the Royal Naval Base, Jufair to the Fleet Mail Officer or his representative at their office in Manamah against receipt. f for Political Agent, Bahrain.■INo* 1860-14/1• To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 3rd May, 1945. inn The Superintenden^-of Post Offices, Lower Sind and Persian Gulf Division, Hyderabad, Sind. ,/ Sir', ' I have the honour to refer to your letter ]$r).k.2&gt;/72 dated the 25th April, 1945, and to enclose a copy of letter No. 1/19 dated the 26th April, 1945 from Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo, from which it will be seen that the contractor suggests that a sum of Ps.500/- per mensem may be paid for conveying mails. I consider this amount reasonable if his statement is correct that the monthly average bill at present amounts to Rs.400/- in view of the distance of the British Overseas Airways Corporation's new office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Yo]ju: most obedient servant, for Political Agent, Bahrain.Printed ill England. Sej»t. 1942. (4,100. pad*. J CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED'. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named Prefix Letter* and Number of Message. Office of Origin. Number of Word*, Date, Time handedJn And Official instructions—if any. 7 C ° Clerk’s Time Circuit. _ Name. Received. /3{° - *1 % QV122/0 PORT KR i)uw KL/13 Rahra POLITIC n L r-GELT BAHRAIN &gt;, f • MAILS B-C/142 Am A YOUR 1060-1^-/1 LAY 3 T° SUPDT POST HYD SIND REGARDING SUBSIDY MAIL CONTRnCT BAH,.A IN AnA DIRECTOR GENERnL CONSIDtRS RS 5^0/- PER MONTH EXCESSIVE REQUEST USE, YOUR GOOD OFFICES &gt;71TH COLT..AC = = l'jR TO 'AGREE TO CONSOLIDATED PAYMENT NOT EXCEEDING RS 430/- PER MONTH MARK YOUR REPLY tfta Jm/icSuaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING’THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.No.2873-14/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, Tne 15th July, 1345. To Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanoo, C.I.E.* With reference to your letter No.L/19 dated the 26th April, 1945 suggesting that a sum of Rs.SOO/- per mensem may be paid to you for conve/« in* mails, the Director General, Posts and Tele graphs considers this amount excessive and asks whether you will agree to a consolidated payment of lis.450/- per month. Dear Sir Bahrain Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain..IMPORTER &amp; EX PORTE R. £ % Telegraphic Address; ^fCANOO. BAHRAIN) Telephone No. |ltn Sairwfl. ri&gt; “ A.rl j» BAHRAIN. Persian (Gulp) -g/w^ ^7t h Ju ly, 1945 Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, ^°) i Hu vl i'i&lt;- .Dat©.. f' With reference to your letter No. 2873-14/1 of 13 th instant, considering the^ present excessive prices of Rs.500/-, we think is reasonable, but in view of what you say we are agreeable to accept Rs.450/. Yours faithfully, Yusuf bin Ahmed^Kanoo.'k I k &gt;! Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Director Post Telegraphs, ?Iarachi. 527 19th July, 1945. r aV- Your Mails B-C/142 July 13th. Contractor now agrees to accept ns. 450/- per month. -POLITICAL^ AMO.''X-' ) /vi: f/y^ &lt;-1 '*7' f- *4^t This confirms that the mails sent by us through the post office to Bushire on the 8th, 14th and 18th August have not been delivered by the Iranian postal authorities. There has been no down slow boat from Bushire since the 8 th August,(except the one by which P.R. came and which did not bring any mails from Bushire post office,) or as in the case of Khorramshahr, Abadan, Charbar etc, I think v.e would'have got the mail back from Bushire. The next down boat may, if all is ouiet at Bushire, bring our mails back. v The correspondence which was meant for P.R. or that which can canveniently be dealt with by him here, is being typed out afresh and will be handed over marked as 'duplicate' The undelivered covers contained some passports, bank drafts and correspondence re. handing over taking over of officers, in addition to routine monthly returns etc. The passports and the bank drafts, if not retrieved, may fall into wrong hands. Bushire perhaps could enquire whether the mail has been confiscated or whether it will be returned to us. Replies to our telegraphic correspondence are coming in regularly from Bushire. ts/fA ULo tkA r^&gt;JL ^ C UcAU . &lt;w/o A -f pW ^ rtA' A—^ 4 /^ y// // ~ s 7 ^ ^yfj g , J/uAx. Uj c-v&lt;- ' / a4«^'r A. iV- j */ &gt;./?.*,•/ ^ I? ralM. 0(6. /!.ffs Jx&amp;f ^ ^ o('£ f ^ ~ L*y_ Hef.9, No action appears to h?ve been taken by this of ice or the C.O. The postmaster stated that there is no record of the receipt of the letter referred to having bee given to his office. 'The letter in question came to the /gency direct in the special mail bag. Draft D.O. to Capt.fetcaIfe submitted. Ref, ll. Major /iban is not here to intial the additions in the agreement-perhaps you will do for him pi. Khan Sahib Yusuf Kenoo’s initils will be obtained by the Head Yunshi D.F.Y. submitted. % H 9/2/42. (u.t /*. i&gt;. fy^ ft* /Vv. P&lt;Jy t H * l/W /ft. % 17JT- (#$ n-x-*i- -4(a~ . ^ t7 - 1Un - /&gt; /U' fr*'Ref,25 , Head.Munshi to please send for K.S,Yusuf bin Ahmed Ksnoo and enquire from him if he has any objection to the inclusion of the wording noted on reverse of the p.u.c in the body of the agreement to be executed at the time of its renewal. Ref,25 and page.71. Khan Sahib Yusuf bin Ahmad Kanoo has no objection to the inclusion of the clause in the nev. agreement to be executed for the next year. Draft submitted 3/10/42'X: E.O. 14/1. V ft Telegram 1032 dated 29-4-44 from Political Resident, Bushire Please enquire from G.M. &amp; Co. (Id). T.H. 30-4-44 Mr. Beared cannot give any idea of the passengers or 1 cargo awaiting clearance at Dubai. In Bahrain they have 2 ? passengers on their books awaiting passages for Karachi and Bombay and Mr. Leaned ; thinks there might come another 20 asking for passages as soon as any nev/s of ships does come. (Previously when they had 200 people on their'books only 100 turned up when a ship 1 arrived -— the others had gone by dhows or ’plane). In Bahrain they have only 20 tons cargo awaiting clearance. ' Dubai - May enquire from P.O.T.C.? D.F.A, 1 - 5-44 nit /* //&gt; ^ Issued telegram No.401 dated 1-5-44 to P.O.T.C. Sharjah me ra? • T'h. -VVI cUIbJ. O-S-lt 4 ^ D*F.A. 3-5-44 a* Vy ^ \ s (~o • ^ -s -qi+ Is h*' hwe- /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000092_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1411</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000092</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1411</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 14/1 IV General correspondence regarding postal matters and conveyance of mails at Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-21T10:49:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (224 files)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end of the file, on folios 205-225. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 226; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional mixed foliation/pagination sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-204; these numbers are written in a combination of pencil and blue crayon, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains notes, telegrams, correspondence and notices regarding postal matters: conveyance of mail at Bahrain, dispatch of mail from Bahrain, air mail fees in 1945 (folios 132-133), and postal facilities in the Persian Gulf area.The principal correspondents are: Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo; Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co Ltd; Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO); British India Steam Navigation Company Limited (BISN); British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC); Cable and Wireless Limited; Petroleum Concessions Limited; the Sub-Postmaster at Bahrain; the Postmaster at Karachi; the Eastern Bank Limited; the Naval Officer-in-Charge at Bahrain; the Inspector of Post Offices for the Persian Gulf; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and the Political Agent at Bahrain.The file contains copies of agreements with Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo, operating as contractor for transit and delivery of mail (folios 24-27, 81-84, 164-167 and 175).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Overseas Airways Corporation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Yusuf Bin Ahmed Kanoo</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British India Steam Navigation Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Naval Officer-in-Charge, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Inspector of Post Offices, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Postmaster, Karachi</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sub-Postmaster, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Eastern Bank Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Cable and Wireless Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Postal services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000092#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>