<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00039d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T14:38:17.848Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">File No.3/X7 19 Collection No. I0R:R|;£;-: RD — r\ APPLICATIONS FROM PERSIAN GULF CADRE FOR INDIAN FOREIGN SiSRVICS AND INDIAN ADMIN IST .dA .TiVE SERVICElife / Telegram From To 64/315. Political Fesldent, Dahraln, Political Agent, Fahraln. (By hand). Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat. H.L.Consul, KJ'iorraiLshahr. H.l ? .Consul, Durhire. II.M.Consul, Kerman. No.283. Dated the 4th karch 1947. I have btor: Instructed by Government of India to invite ajpl lest Ions for Cless I appointnents in Indian Foreign Service froir Indians (including An^lo-Indians) not over 4C vho^ I coatldcr suitable. Standard required c. is roughly up to that of a gooc Z.kjS* Applications have to be submitted at once with details of age, domicile, educational and other qualifications, and of service up to date. ?. Question of creating lower grades (ministerial end other) of Indian Foreign Cervlce not yet considered, lio applications for such porta should therefore be invited but you may forv/ard to n?e any applications received from persons you consider suitable with your recommendations. - HAY - 1 &gt;' li IJPO. / /^ A/ o ^ OSAVINGRAM From To No.284. Dated the 4th March 1947. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain. hy immediately preceding telegram.. ^ ^ Only persons in your office who appear to be possible candidates are Hafiz and Rajagopalan. If you consider them up to the required standard please invite Applications from them. If there are other persons you consider suitable please consult me before inviting them to apply. I - HAY - NPG. ConfidsntinK BATTR v r ^.rPT.r 3 . From To K. V. Rajagopalan, U«A» 9 Offgx ouperinteudant, Political AgenGy 9 Bahrain. The Political A^enti Bahrain. Sir, I request that my name be recomiaended■ to the Government of India for enlistment in the proposed Indian Foreign Service. I am a graduate of the .iimamalai University (Madras), holding the Degree of Master of Arts. I took the B.A. Degree in the year 1931, offering Physics arid Chemistry as optional subjects. In English, forming Part I of the iixamination, I secured a second Class standing first among the successful candidates that year, and was the recipient of the Founder 1 s Prize and S.i^. Rung.-Jiadhan 1 s Prize for proficiency in English. Thence I proceeded to take up a course of post graduate studies ia English Language and Literature and came out successful in the examinations held in March 1933. Immediately after leaving the College in 1933 I was employed for sometime as a teacher in the National High School, Negapatam (South India), then in Messrs. Kochouse Sons, Madras, and later in 193$ in the Madras Government, having attained a high rank (second among the candidates from the City) in the Madras Public Services Commission lamination for ministerial Services. I joined the Persian Gulf Residency in October 1936 and ever since have been holding varied and important posts both in the onfidentiai and General Sections. For about six years I was Confidential Stenographer to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and for considerable periods I officiated in the gazetted posts of Assistant Registrar and Superintendent in the British Consulate-General, Bushire* I was placed on special duty on two occasions in Bushire, once for the preparation of a compendium of office orders and instructions and a Manual for the guidance of officers and staff newly appointed to the Persian Gulf; and recently, in connection with the transfer of the Residency from Bushire to Bahrain. I might mention, with pardonable pride, that during all these years I discharged the duties entrusted to me to the complete satisfaction of my superiors. I shall be completing 36 years of age on the 25th March. I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Bahrain, The 6th March 1947. No.C/3C6. Forwarded and Recomiaended political Agency, Bahrain, The 7th of March, 1947. Political Agent, BahrainNo.G/307. To POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 7th of March, 1947. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MFXQRAm)UM . Reference my Endorsement No.C/306, dated the 7th March, 1947. 2. I have a further application to forward from Mr. M.A. Hafiz which is delayed pending receipt of further details from him.Bahrain, 4^ March, 19^ 7. Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Bahrain. I understand that the Governuent of India are recruiting incumbents for the proposed Indian Foreign Service and I request that my name may kindly be forwarded to the Government of India with your recommendations for consideration for appointment in a suitable post. 2. I joined the Persian uulf Residency in the year 1928 and worked in various capacities all along in the Vernacular Section as 2nd liunshi, Bahrain, Head .iunshi, Bahrain and I was holding the responsible post of Dratioman Muscat during the arduous years of the Second Great »i&lt;ar. Since 19th August, 1944 I am holding the ^azelted post of the Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain. During this long period of service,in addition to experience in the purely administrative side of the office, I have acquired comprehensive knowledge of the work of the Consular and Foreign jdissions. I a.i also acquainted thoroughly with the ways of life of the Arabs and the Persians having moved closely and cordially with them. The officers under whom I have had privilege of working will, I am confident, testify to my ability to get on well both in oTfice and outside. 3. I am 44 years of age. 4. I am prepared to serve anywhere,but I feel that by virtue of my long service in the Persian Gulf in the Arabic Section and ray linguistic qualifications, I will be best suited for aaployment in a country where Arabic is spoken. No.c/316. 8th March, 1947. FORWARDED. I have the honour to be., Sir, Tour most obedient servant. ^. political Agent, Bahrain. ^ Jl/^H ilPto the Indian Assistani Bahrain. i^olitical AgentBahrain, The 8th March, 1947. To The Secretary to the Hor^ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Through The political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I request that my name be forwarded to the Govern ment of India for an appointment in the Indian Foreign Service or the Indian Administrative Service. I am a Master of Arts (Economics) of the Calcutta University and graduated with English as my Honours sub ject. In 1940 I joined the Indian Stores Department but resigned after a month to enter the Central Cipher Bureau of the External Affairs Department. In September, 1941, I was posted to Khorranshahr on deputation and subsequently transferred to the Persian Gulf Cadre. I arrived in Khorramshahr immediately after the occupation of Iran by Dritioh and Russian troops and saw it develop into an Aid- to-Russia port. I was conversant with many of the problems thac arose in these connections, and also gained a first hand knowledge of the conditions of the Indian employees of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, Limited, at Abadan. In 1944 I was transferred to Bushire, the then headquarters of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I took leave at the end of that year and on my return in May, 1945, was posted as clerk in charge of the Confidential Section of the Political Agency, Bahrain. I have a working knowledge of Arabic and a smattering /Of Persian. I am 34 years of age, unmarried, and in good health. I beg to remain. Sir, your most obedient servant. J ^r^ m iVo c/3/3»Mk. 1 : No. D.966-FSP/47. The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. The Chief Secretaries to All Provincial Governments and Chief Commissioners. The First Secretary, Embassy of India in China 9 Nanking. The First Secretary, Embassy of India in the United States of America Washington. His Majesty^ Minister, Kabul. The Additional Counsellor, British Embassy, Tehran. His Britannic Majesty^ Consul General for Khorasan, Meshed. The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. His Britannic Majesty^ Consul General in the French Establishments in India, Pondicherry. The Political Officer in Sikkim. His Britannic Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Nepal. The High Commissioner for India, Aldwych House, London. Indian Consul, Bangkok. Indian Vice-Consul, Saigon. Dr. L. C. Jain. Indian Liaison Mission with SCAP, BCOF Sub Area, Tokyo. His Britannic Majesty^ Consul in the Portuguese Possessions in India, Nova Goa. Dated, New Delhi 3, the 5th March, 1947. Subject i Recruitment to the Indian Foreign Service. Sir, I am directed to forward herewith for information a copy of an advertisement issued by the Federal Public Service Commission inviting applications for recruitment to the Indian Foreign Service ....Foreign Service from candidates between 26 and 44 years of age on 1st August 9 1947* For those below the age of 26 years on that datei a competitive examination will be held by the Federal Public Service Commission in July next and an announcement in this connection will be made shortly. 1 have the honour to be f Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. B. K. KAPUR. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. commuw No. 666 - S. PERSIAN GULF KKSIDENCY, BAHRAIN, the 6th April, 1947. Copy, with copy of enclosure, forwarded with compliments to * - 1. His Majesty^ Consul General, Bushire. 2. The Po&amp;itical Agent, Muscat 3. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 4. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 6. His Majesty^ Consul, Kerman. 6. His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr. ? Confidential. BAHB A.TN RECEIPT. Dateytf;..!:7/ ' federal public service commission , Applications are invited from British subjects of Indian domicile or descent pnd subjects of Indian States for vacancies in the new Indian Foreign Service. Recruitment is open to air those-who wi'l have attained thfe ®g9€&gt;f 26 years but will not &gt; have attained the o ^ 45 years on the 1st August 1947. Qualifications . Candidates (i) must Dosses's a first clas 7 3 r 2 of a recognised university, and should preferably (ii) have a wo'kin knowledge of one or more foreign languages, (iii) have some acquaintance with international affairs and (iv) have travelled outside Indi~ 0 na Burma. 2. E.C.Os. who hold or have held Commissions which were granted to hem before the 15th August, 1945, who have not been considered for a war reserved vacancy to the I.C.S., the I.P. or the Central Services under the Government of India and who had not attained the age o: 30 years by 1-1-1947 are also eligible to apply for the Indian Foreign Ser vice. They must possess a degree of a recognised university but canij:^ who have passed the Intermediate Examination in the first or second r ■ division and were prevented from obtaining a degree by joining the \ armed forces will also be eligible. 3. Particulars and application forms can be obtained from the Secretary, Federal Public Service Commission, Siml^. Closing dat or applications 8tti May, 1947, 4. E.C.Os. will not be required to Day any fee. ©ther candic-tes must send with their application form a Treasurv Receipt for ^.25/- (^s.6/4/- in the case of Scheduled Caste candidates). 6. All those who have already submitted apDllcations to the External Affairs Department for appointment tQ the Indian Foreign Service are informed that fresh applications should be forwarded in accordance with the procedure prescribed above. 6. This notice does not aaply to persons in permanent civil employ under the Central or Provincial Governments, apDlications from whom ' n ve been invited separately.'.7. E.C.Os. who.had attained the age of 30 years on 1.1.1947 and who possess the qualifications described in paragraph 1 above are also eligible to apply. 9 8. The basic pav scales for the All India Administrative and Indian Foreign Services will be the same and will shortly bo fix ; 1 ! on the basis of the recommendations made by the Central Pay Commission. In addition officers of the Indian Foreign Service will get cost of living and other allowances when serving in posts overseas. In determining seniority and starting pay, consideration will be given inter alia to the age of the candidate 0.P.Sharma .S. b. GOVEKNMENT OF INDIA, ] )epartment. EXPRESS LETTER | A' Tt —This is an OIUGINAL MESSAGE, sent by foul to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treatea, on receipt, with the name expedition as \f it hcul been telegraphed, io tave time and forinalities it is worded and myned as if it haa been so despatched,] w F rom To POLITICAL, BAUKAIN. RKPGU, BAHRAIN. (3 r*\ -.A t Vo # xi3i - 3/17# Bahrain. the 11th April ^ 47- Reference your endorsement No. 566-S, dated the 5th April 1947* Recruitment to the Indian Foreign Service. 2. Grateful to kno// the procedure prescribed for applications from persons in permanent civil employ, as there are some permanent members of the staff here who wish to be considered for recmiitment to the Indian Foreign Service. a POLITICAL = The issue of the above has been authorised. u Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.*CONFIDENTIA L D.0. No. 682 - S. lr Please refer to your express letter No. 1131 - 3/17, dated the 11th April, 1947, 2, I am desired to say that members of the Persian Gulf Service who were considered suitable for recruitment to Class I appointments in the Indian Foreign Service have already been invited to apply. The suitability of the members of your staff was fully dis cussed between Colonel Hay and your predecessor and as a result only one of them was so invited . 3, if any other members of your staff wish to do so they may apply and their applications, which should contain particulars as in the attached form, should be forwarded to this office with your remarks. Colonel Hay is willing to forward such applications from ^ persons possessing the qualifications described in the enclosure to Government of India letter No. J.966-^oF/47, dated the 5th March, 1947, sent to you under endorsement No. 566 - S, of the 5th April, 1947, but in doing so will be compelled to remark that the applicants were not invited to apply previously because they were not con sidered up to the required standard, viz. that of a good Extra Assistant to the Consul. ■hb? [Za PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, the 22nd April, 1947. J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., I.C.S., Political Agent, BAHRAIN. G .A.M. Coni ^ntiaL bahrain RECEIPT &gt; • Date...*.**»••••r- 1. Name (in Block Capitals). 2. Date of birth and age on next birthday, 3. Nationality, etc, 4. Province or Indian State in which domiciled, 6. Name of service to which the applicant belongs, 6. Scale of pay of parent service and present pay of the appli cant in that service. 7. Present appointment held under the Provincial Government and the pay drawn in that appointment. 8. Educational Qualifications. 9. Particulars of knowledge of foreign languages other than English. 10. Particulars of Foreign travels, experience of work abroad, and of negotiations with foreign countries. 11. History of service under Government up-to-date. 12. Any other particulars which an applicant may wish to mention. fcwcA. t Recommendations of the Provincial Government.&gt;r7 64/316 k 22 U* Telegram G.T.C, From Political Resident, Bahrain. To h.m. Consul-General, Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. (By Hand) H.M.Consul, Khorramshahr. H.M.Consul-General, Meshed. H.M.Consul, Kerman. rA] L F 1 fj ^ P ^ ' ■ •'V No.486. Dated the 22nd.April 1947. Ik PORT ANT Am informed by Government of India that all applicants for Class I appointments in Indian Foreign. Service who are not already permanent gazetted officers and therefore members of the Central Service Class II are not repeat not eligible for appointment in Class 1 appointments of Indian Foreign Service under the^t^rms of Government of India letter No.F.3(l)-F£P/47 February 7th. To Bahrain only . Rajagopalan is accordingly not eligible. 2. All members of Gulf cadre who have applied for such appointments through government channels must, if they / so desire and if possessing qualifications prescribed in enclosures to my endorsement No.5€6-S dated 5th April 1947, apply direct to Secretary Federal Public Service Commission forwarding Treasury receipt for Rs.25/- with application. 3. Have requested Government of India to extend closing date and for provision of prescribed forms or alternatively to waive necessity for these. Meanwhile please telegraph number of applicants. - HAY - NPG. ConfidentiaK BAHRAIN RECEIPT, j Nej-JT? Date« • * ' $ S l y URGENT EXPRESS LETTER From Political Agents Bahrain. To Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain^ No. C/486. Dated the 26th April, 1^47. 8 ^ Reference paragraph three of your telegram No. 486 dated the 22nd April, 1947. 2. Messrs. Ra.jagopalan, Hafiz, Carrau, Joshi, and Nadirshaw from this Agency wish to apply for Class I appointments in Indian Foreign Service. Nadirshaw is not a permanent member of the Persian Gulf Service. 3. Grateful if I could be provided with the necessary application forms. 3d. G.J.PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.BHMnBBBBHPB /lo GOVEENHENT. OP INDIA, D kpaetmkjit. EXPRESS LETTER [N, B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to swe telegraphic eofpense and undue ute of the wires, hut intended to he treuted, on receipt, mlh the same expedition as if it had been tcleyraphM, To sare time and JonnaiUics xt m worded aud signed as ij U lead been so despatched,] F eom Repgu Bahrain. To Political Bahrain. No. 715-S. Dated 25th A 11 S. ' 1 ;S3t47. My telegram No. 486 April 22nd. Indian foreign \ Service. 2. Records here indicate that Hajagopalan and Garrau are eligible to apply to Federal Commisaion and also Joshi if his degree is a first-class one. 2. Please report urgently names of intending applicants so that copies of prescribed forms can be sent for completion and return to me along with Treasury receipts for Ks 25« RSPGU The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. No...••7.^'..^....Date.. 5.?.'.ilo 1 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - THE POLITICAL AGENT, BAHilAIM , and has the honour to transmit to him five copies of the undermentioned document. PERSIAN GULF RESILENCY,. BAHRAIN, dated the 28th April 1947. Reference to previous correspondence; Bahrain Agency express letter 26th April, 1947. .C/48G datedFEDERAL PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION £nstractlons to candidates for appointment by selection 1. persons already In Government service, permanent or temporary, must apply through the proper channel. 2. candidate must deposit a fee of Es.25/- under the Accounts ^ead 'XXXV •• Miscellaneous Departments - Examination Fees - Receipts of the Feden L publie Ser^^ice Corimission' into the neareot Government treasury or In x branch of the Imperial Bank of India or into a State Treasury authorised to transact business with Government, and forward the treasury receipt so obtained to the Secretary, F.P^S.C., with his application. The name of the post and of the treasury in which the fee is deposited should, be clearly stated in the Treasury Receipt. The fee intended to be paiu at Bombay, Calcutta, Madras, or Delhi, should be deposited into the Reserve Bank of India instead of the Imperial Bank of India. The Comml ^ on do not accept payment in cash. THIS FEE WILL NOT IN ANY C IRCWo TANCES BE REFUNDED ONCE AN APPLICATION HAS BEEN CONSIDERED BY THE COMMISSION. APPLICiiTIONS NOT ACCOMPANIED BY A TREASURY RECEIPT WILL NOT B^ CONSIDERED. Candidates in the Forces may send a cheque or money crder or postal order in payment of the application fee, if it is dlffi-'lt for them to obtain a Treasury Receipt. Candidates who submit their a^piLicationB from outside India are not required to pay the appli- catic. :?ee. The Treasury Receipt must be marked prominently at the top right- land corner ' CENTR a L' W1BJ1WG:- The treasury receipt should be on the blue form pertaining to Central Government transactionsiand should be obtained from the trea sury at which the fee is deposited. If the blue form is not available in an T 'creasury the ordinary form hitherto employed may be used. NOT'; i - Cash or postal Orders or cheques will not be accepted by the Feder^ Public Service Commission except from candidates actually in the Forces. 3. a candidate may send copies of testimonials from persons inti- matel' acquainted with his work and character and must also give the names and addresses of three persons in India to whom reference can be made. If he has been in employment he should either give his present or mc t recent -employer or immediate superior as a referee or submit a recent testimonial from him. ^ii) If a candidate desires to name as a referee any person residing outside India he should write direct to that person and ask him to send dirftct to the Secretary of the F.P.S.C., a statement of his opinion con- -^arnl. \ the candidate^ character and suitability for this post. The reply will be treated as confidential, 4. ]v'c recommendations should be forwarded to the Commission except from 'persons who are acquainted with a candidate's work or from persons who g ve certificates of character in accordance with the terms of offi cial jgulations or announcements, jan«assing, in any form, will disqualify a candidate, 5. (i) A candidate must, if required, attend at such place as may be appointed for personal interview. *(The F.P.S.C. soiiq do not defray the trave.'.ling or oth/.r expenses of candidates summoned for interview. They will, however, ccatribute towards those expenses at a rate corresponding to th3 amount of the intermediate railway fare by the shortest route to the p ace of interview from the railway station neaisst to the candidate's norma, place of residence or from which he actually performs the journey, whichever is nearer to the place of interview, and back to the same station. Payment for journeys normally covered by steamer will be made at th same rate. Candidates who live at a place where there is no railway station will, in addition, be paid road mileage at 2 annas a mile for 1 :3 journey to and from the nearest railway or steamer station, or from :ne sub-divisional or Tahsil headquarters to the nearest railway or steam r station and back whichever is less. No such contribution is paid 'o candidates who apply from outside India, *&lt;For civilians only) /(ii)Page 2. (ii) a railway servant will be paid the same contribution as is admissible to other candidates, on producing a certificate from the appropriate railway authority to the effect that he was not provided with free passes to cover the journey. No such contri bution will be paid if he uses a privilege pass for the purpose of coming for interview. If a Privileged Ticket Order is used, the candidate will be paid the amount spent on the Privileged Ticket Order subject to a minima maximum of the. intermediate class rail way fare by the shortest route). 6. The summoning of a candidate for interview merely indicates that the Commission think it possible fcax that he, with others, may be suitable for the post, and convey no assurance whatever th^t he will be selected or recommended. 7, A candidate must be in sound bodily health* He must be pre pared to undergo such medical examination and satisfy such medical authority as Government may require. NOTEi- Cardidates are wqrned that there is no right of appeal from a medical board Js special or standing, appointed to determine their fitness for a particular post. If, hov/ever. Government are satisfied on the evidence produced to them, of the possibility of an error of judgment in the decision of the first Board, it is open to Ggjvernment to ailow an appeal to a second Board. 8» The F.P.S.C. cannot advise candidates as to their eligibility for any particular post and it is for the candidates themselves to see whether they satisfy the prescribed requirements and whether it is irorth their while to apply. 9. Each candidate v/ill be informed of the result of his/her application in due course and any interim enquiries about the result are tficrefore unnecessary and are liable to be ignored.'2* ih EXPRESS LETTER. From - Political, Bahrain. To - Repgu, Bahrain. No .C/523. Dated the 1st of May, 1947. Reference correspondence resting wich your printed Letter No. 745-3, dated the 2Sth April, 1947. ^ ^ ! l, 2, I enclose five application forms which have been completed by Messrs. Rajagopalan, T Taflz, Carrau, joshi, and Nadirshaw respectively together with Treasury Receipts for Rs.25/-. Sd./- C.J. PELLY Political Agent, Bahrain.64/316 G.T.C. Political Resident, Baiirain. Political Agent, Kuv.ait. kUgg»t t / (By hand) H.M.Consul, Khorrarashahp. No•647• Dated the 1st May 1947. IMP OUT A MT Reference 'Instructions to Candidates' forwarded under Residency Wo. 743-S April 28tL. April 26th. 74^^ ApyU ^h. , f / 744-S April 28th. 2. Federal Commission have been asked whether government servants serving outside India are required to pay application fees. Reply may be delayed and applicants must decide this point for themselves. Applications should be forwarded whether payment of fees is made or not. - HAY - NPG. Confidential. bahrain receipt.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, persian gulf residency, D epartmbnt , bahrain, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, iviih the same expedition as {f it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] F rom political resident, persian gulf. To POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. No. 821 - S. Bated the 3rd May, 1947 J93 . Reference your express letter No. C/528, dated the 1st May, 1947. Indian Foreign Service. , ^ ^ 2. Applications of Messrs. Hafiz, Joshi and Nadirshaw are returned herewith as they have not got first class degrees, and are therefore not eligible, vide paragrapl^-1 of advertisement forwarded under Residency endorsement No. 566-3 , dated the 6th April, 1947. In this connection attention is invited to Residency express letter No. 715-S, dated the 25th April, 1947. 3. The applications of Messrs. Rajagopalan and Carrau are acknowledged and are being forwarded. 5 ( Sd. - W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. g.a.m. s. 6. mfp—1407 s&amp;p—(m-2339)—25-5-37—300,000. CorJjiaatial. REC®^'. No...— DateNo. G .T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Afent, Bahrein. • (By hand) Political Agent, Muscat Political Agent, Kuwait. H.M. Consul, Khorramshahr. 669 Dated the 8th Way, 1947. fc'iy telegram No. 547 May 1st. Federal Puolic Service Commtssion has confirmed that candidates outside Indio for recruitment to Indian Foreign Service by selection neel not repeat not pay application fee. For recruitment by competitive examination . full application fee required. - Hay - ML. * ConluaatiaL J3AHRAIN RECEIP^ / no...£^..! date-.^lv^^ 1Mo.iaos-s lw\. 'it y PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY &gt; BAHRAIN , the 17th October, 1947 y ^ / 5) 3 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , The Political Agent, KUWAIT . The Political Agent, MUSCAT . His Majesty's Consul, KHORRAMSHAHR . Subject;- Indian Foreign Service MEMORANDUM The Government of India have been asked to confirm that applications for appointment to the Indian Foreign Service from those members of the Persian Gulf Cadre who have opted for Pakistan have been transferred to that Government for consideration. In the meantime, the Hon f ble the Political Resident considers that those members of your staff who have opted for service under the Government of Pakistan and whose applications have been forwarded to the Government of India would be well advised to send further applications to the Government of Pakistan. 2. Applications should be sent to this Residency in triplicate for onward transmission. For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.^11] 3 64/316 &amp; 1U0. Q«7«C» Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Ater.t, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political A^fnt| iiuscat. H.M.Consul, Khorramshahr. No.1066. Dated the 5^6th October 1947. (By •land). y , 5 IS kA fcy memorandum K0.I8O8 -S October 17th. INDIAIi FOREIGN SERVICE. 2. Government of India have confirmed that applications have not repeat not been transferred to Government of Pakistan. To Muscat only. 3. Memorandum referred to will reach you by next bag. It advised that members of your staff who have opted for Pakistan and who&amp;e applications for the Indian Foreign Service have been forwarded to the Government of India should submit further applications (in triplicate) to Government of Pakistan through this Residency. - HAY - KPG tn /-VM ■7 Confidential. BAHRAIN' RECEIPT. No A ) ;Dibe.. 3 . ii3111 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 4th June, 1949, S.O.No. Dear Chakrabarthy, Mr. K .V, Valdyanathan has been working in this Agency for two years and I am glad to be able to speak highly of his intelli ence, capacity for work and ^ood behaviour. He has dealt with currency questions, exchange control and the like subjects which require the ability to understand often quite complicated instructions. His noting is good and recommendations are reasoned, lie tells me that the Government of India is recruiting clerks for Muscat and Bahrain and has asked me to write this note which I have taken the liberty of doin^. Yours sincerely, Mr, B.N. Chakrabarty, C.I.E., I.C .S., Joint Secretary, Fstablishment Branch,.Ho. D. 3773-TSII/49 MINISTRY OF external af FAIRS NEW DELHI. Dated the 1949, Dear Mr, Pelly, /&gt; Please refer to your demi-official letter No, C/L-195 dated the 4th June 1949 to ^r, B.IT.Chakravorty regarding the appointment of Mr. K r ,'V, Vaidyanathan under the Government of India. 2, The request of Mr, Vaidyanathan for a suitable appoint ment under the 'overnment of India will be considered by the Establishment Selection Committee at its next meeting;. I shall intimate to you its decision in due course. Yours sincerely, «(7 / To C.J.pelly, Esq., Political Agency, Bahrain. TM' 16,6,49 -&gt;S.2.7, Coc&amp;balfeL BATI^AFT E 'OEIPT. ^ a. D at o J2.0.. JilL • .13^.I was informed by the C.C. some time a^o that the Government of India have replied to P .A's D.O. about me, saying that my name would be put uo for consideration in the subsequent r eeting of the Staff Selection Board for posts in Bahrain and Muscat. Since then, we have had f no news from that end. I am naturally anxious about the result. I should, therefore, be grateful if the Ciovernment of India could be reminded about this.♦21 M0.D.9359-EII/49. MINISTRY OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS NEW DELHI Datfid the t /1^ December 1949. Dear Agency, Please refer to your letter No, C/G-445, dated the 11th December 1949 about the appointment of Mr. Vaidhyanathan in the service of the Govern ment of India. 2 # it is regretted that no fresh appointments are at present being made by the Government of India in their missions abroad. Yours ever, Ministry of External Affairs. The Political Bahrain. r.v W7'4em s t 0 • t' &amp; o • mV . For circulation. E.0' Id./- J'• A• 11• C• ^ 10/4. Id./- K.V.R., 10/4. N.M.J. G.H. V.B.S.M. ' . S.D.N. K.M.3. These rules d^ riot apply to permanent members of the scaff. There are some in our office who wish to know the procedure to enable them bo apply. D.F.A. A. P. A. Id./- K.7.R., 10/4/47. Id./-'I. D .H.R- , 10/4. )£-C . Ko. 'S/-3/o • '4 {l*} t-o. ^ p./?. » 'h. v4u s. 10 . Para 2 . I understand Messrs. Hafiz and Rajagopalan 7 were both* invited to apply, cf. s.2-5. Para 3 . This seems to have been drafted before 8 instructions contained in\ para 2 of s.ll, and to be super- v ceded ^by it. s.ll. Para 1 . Mr. Hajagopalan informed. Para 2. Please see N/para 8. There are fotir classes of applicants from this Agency: (a) permanent members of p.G. Service who were invited to apply; (b) permanent members of the P.G. Service who were not invited but applied; (c) permanent members of,the P.G. Service who would now like to apply; (d) would-be applicants who are non-permanent members of the p.G. Service. 9 1( It is presumed that all four classes may now apply direct to the Secretary, Federal public Service Commission,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00039d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/190</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00039d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/190</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Applications from Persian Gulf Cadre for Indian Foreign Service and Indian Administrative Service'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-23T00:09:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (38 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged in approximately chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence begins on the front cover and runs to the back cover; it appears in pencil, uncircled, in the top right corner of the recto of the page. Foliation anomalies: 1A, 12A, 18A, 18B.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bahrain; the Political Agent at Bahrain; K V Rajagoplan, Officiating Superintendent, Political Agency, Bahrain; M A Hafiz, Indian Assistant to the Political Agent, Bahrain; Mr Carrau, clerk in charge of the Confidential Section of the Political Agency, Bahrain; B N Chakrabarty, Joint Secretary, Establishment Branch, Government of India, New Delhi; and the Ministry of External Affairs, New Delhi.The correspondence concerns the recruitment of Indian and Anglo-Indian members of the Persian Gulf Cadre for Class I appointments in the newly developed Indian Foreign Service and Indian Administrative Service in the months prior to the partition and independence of India in 1947. These papers include application letters (ff. 3-6); advertisment issued by Federal Public Service Commission inviting applications for recruitment to the Indian Foreign Service (ff. 10-11); and 'Federal Public Service Commission: Instructions to candidates for appointment by selection' (ff. 17-18A).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00039d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>