<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002d9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T12:11:01.534Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SECURITY GRADING - Upgrade as necessary using appropriate coloured labeis 0 UNCLASSIFIE REFER TO i REFER TO NAME DATE NAME DATE NAME DATE DO NOT RETAIN FILES UNNECESSARILY - RETURN THEM TO REGISTRY FOR B.U. OR P.A. FILE OPENED . CLOSED FILE No. PART SECURITY GRADING - Upgrade as necessary using appropriate coloured labels UNCLASSIFIED T : Hp V/ 5V7042 i JMi/ o LAST FILE: NEXT FILE: «■ RELATED FILES;aaainst unscrupulous traders m First Assistant to the Political Resident in the si- Persian GulfI %r \ C J \ *r\t'.« • y^Af i902. | ' British Residency and Consulate- General , Bushire, 'March 1902. To The Residency Agent , Shargah No report has reached this ^Wtl.CL^r ^Z/ 2 ' 17 ® / rclOT (Jr) •' ^-? z * Ahmed Saleh works the red oxide mines at Bu Inusa; — &gt; ' I have now heard that the ^ y.J same individual is trying to , ^ c0ncesS f 0n from the Chief of Shargah for excavating and exporting red oxide from Sir Bu Neir island. I have therefore tii t ' II I - C ^ written a letter on the subject \ ^ ^ i, 1 i f\ to Sheikh Suggur which I enclose herewith . Please deliver it to him and also explain to him thatI have no desire to interfere, but it would be to his advantage to obtain advice before concluding arrange ments for monopolies or exclusive privileges * Offg: Politiq/al Resident in the Persian Gulf, c? I 'i it&gt;■/ V r* \ a v . i V vV V no of ibb?. british residency ^ consul, ate-gen erab. bush! august t bb 7* to the res i d en c y agent, sharg ah. a. c. i send herewith copies of correspondence about a cor -1/ a t nt rec ei v ed f rom gov e rj^tor of l i ngah to the effect that certain debay people had taken away by force a diver from the boat of one nasm1r, an in habitant of the island of sirrey, at the pearl banks; and request you will hake a strict inquiry into the matter and report result giving your opinion about i t, I -t / ^ *&gt;• ' colon el» political resident, persian gulf./e^lt of i tiblm british residency * comsut^ath- general. bush i re/r^/^ate 'bb 7. to the residency agent, shargah /\a5 W j; w /0&gt; a. c. with reference to your letter no 40,dated 1 fc5th may ibb7» reportino / that a rams buggarah was fired at by a koomzar sambook, vou i % should have taken and forward ed the deposition of the na- *khoda and crew of the rams buggarah with full particulars v ' attested by a kadthi. the information you have furnished is vague and unsatis factory. the previous orders as to no expedition by sea being sanctioned continue in force. colonel, f pol i t t cal res i dij / persian gulf,if ■ -CHH » t BRITISH RSSIDENCY &amp; CONSUI^ATtS GENU B JSRIRE, &gt;2^KOVSMBSR 1887. CONFIDENTIAL, TO RAJ I ABUb KASIM, R^SIDBMCY AG3NT, SHARGAH. Ii. \\ /A.. A. C. IN VIEW TO TRE RECENT INTRIGUES OF PERSIAN A-UTRORI T I aS C&gt; ie- ir, ,HPS cr^P/is^-^r 1 ENT „, R „ IN OMAN, I THINK IT WOULrD BE ESI RASL,S IF YOU OBTAINED FROM SACR TRJClAIv GRIEF A BETTER AfiDRSSSSD TO T!E TO THIS EFFECT. I WISH TO ASSURE. YOU «'• AND BH:r T YOU WILIy INFORM THE RIAL# BRITISH GOVERNMENT THAT I WI L/L» ON NO ACCOUNT ITO NEGOTIATIONS OR AGREEMENTS OF ANY SORT WITH ANY GOVERNMENTS SAVE THE BRITISH, AND THAT I SHAIvL, NOT AGREE WITHOUT CONSENT OF THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT TO ANY AGENT OF ANY GOVERNMENT OTHER THAN TH ;£ BRITISH RESIDING WITHIN MY TERR ITORI iS , CO L/ON S U 1 inRnwp^iuetteks amd messages from other quarters including yourself seek- ' I 1 ng to involve them with matters which are not their concern^ and engage them in negotiations which would not be for their interests and which might co m p. rom i s e th em with the british government^ and inconsistent with their obligations, in response to such seeking of advice t instructed our agent to D esire the several tr U cial chiefs to avoid meddling in matters which do not concern them. so far certa in — l.i the agent has acted under my instructions. as you are aware we have ab stained from any interference in the quarrels and warfare between tou and the beni ias, as it has hot hitherto touched british in terests* i have however closely looked into the history of these quarrels and i am unable to see that the fault is all on shaikh zaeed 's side. this much i will say and no more. so■JP - -liSi % so long as this warfare is between yourselves atstd ueads 'to ho further extension by land and to no warfare by sea t have seen no necessity for brit ish interference, but if others are to step in, and consequence#to become serious, it will behove the british government to guard its interests fll all quarters and you and all may rely on it thii / will be strictly done at what ever cost, ^sd^ e. c. ross, colonel i political resident, persian gulf.A...A</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002d9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/752</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002d9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/752</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Arabic File (1)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1884/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-17T00:08:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (241 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation numbers are circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. They begin on the front cover, on number 1, and end on the inside of the back cover, on number 241. Foliation errors: f. 78 is followed by f. 78A; no f. 211.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The majority of correspondence in the file consists of miscellaneous letters and instructions, with enclosures, in Arabic and English, between 9 February 1884 to 24 February 1914, from the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf at Bushire and ‘Abd al-Qāsim, Khān Bahādur ‘Abd al-Laṭīf bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān and ‘Īsá bin ‘Abd al-Laṭīf, Residency Agents on the Trucial Coast at Sharjah. There are also letters from Messrs A &amp; T J Malcolm &amp; Company (f. 9) and the Residency Agent at Lingah (f. 49). Enclosures typically include copies and originals of letters to and from various Persian Gulf rulers (for example, ff. 69, 70-77) and from British native agents at Bahrain and Lingah (for example, f. 151). Also included within the file are copies of responses from the Residency Agent to the Political Residency (for example, f. 67) and list of claims of various residents of Abu Dhabi (ff. 78-87).The Arabic and Persian text of the letters is handwritten and appears on the left hand of the folio, while the English text occasionally appears typed (for example, ff. 191-192). Some letters have strips of paper attached to them indicating the subject of the letter (for example, ff. 141-144), while on the recto side of some folios the subject of the letter is written in Arabic in pencil or pen (for example, f. 26v). The letters are numbered according to the year, for example, ‘No 389 of 1886’ (f. 107), although some letters appear unnumbered (for example, f. 171).The correspondence within the file deals generally with commercial and consular matters and the relations of the rulers of the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms with one another and the British. Subjects covered within the file include: the islands of Dalmā, Sīrī, Sir Bu Neir [Ṣīr Bū Nu‘ayr] and Abū Mūsá and red oxide mines; the status and claims of British Indian subjects (
                           banyans) in the Persian Gulf; pearl diving matters and cases of absconding divers; relations between Aḥmad bin ‘Abdullāh Āl Mu‘allā, the ruler of Umm al-Qaywayn, and his son Muḥammad; the transport of armed men and munitions by sea, and the preservation of maritime peace; relations between Shaikh Zāyid bin Kahlīfah Āl Nahyān of Abu Dhabi and Shaikh Jāsim bin Muḥammad Āl Thānī of Qatar; attack on an al-Wakrah boat and correspondence from ‘Alī bin Rāshid, the shaikh of al-Wakrah; various slavery cases, including one related to the shaikhs of Abu Dhabi and Qatar; relations between Shaikh Zāyid and al-Qubaysāt, al-Manāṣīr and Banī Hājir tribes; relations between Oman and Persia vis-à-vis the Trucial Coast; and a breach of the maritime peace by the people of al-Ḥamrīyah against ports on the Persian littoral of the Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002d9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>