<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000042_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T16:08:37.192Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">QSXXMBSOTUCXK. Secret V The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. The Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain, presents his and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated... 2?th October 1940. Camp, Bahrain, Reference to previous correspondence : A /) Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident’s tele gram No,T/499 of 29th October 1940. Air Officer Commanding Iraq’s visit to Bahrain.id egram From To Hope a ted io&amp;t copy Inter* Political Resident* at Bahrain* Air Officer Conmanding* agdad• Aeronautic Baerah for Air ^fioer Oi*i»ffianding* to Political Agent* Bahrain, and Air liaison Officer, Bahrain* Ho.T/499* Dated the 29th October 1940* Important * I understand you only propose staying four hours in Bahrain but hope you can extend Yisit as probleas CoywtoliccxkecC . , , - , are Qnnfnnxlwtri , If you can spend night plane could test blackout* Rssidsnt •1 CONFIDENTIAL. No. G /422 of 1940. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Golf presents his compliments to !• The Senior Eaval Officer, Persian Gulf* 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a co]^v of the undermentioned documents (s). v British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Bahrain. V Dated, 2nd November 1940, Reference to previous correspondence ,: \ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Residency telegram No.T/516 dated 1st November 1940.Telegrsun From To Repeated Copy to S Political Resident, at Bahrain. Government of India, External Affairs Depar New Delhi. Secretary of State for India, London. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Political Agent, Bahrain. No.T/516. Dated the 1st November 1940. My telegram No.T/488 of 26th October. Air Officer Commanding arrived 31st October inspected arrangements and discussed Defence problems with Senior Naval Officer Political Agent and myself. Ke returned Basra in the afternoon but hopes pay further visit in a weeks time. He will endeavour supply gun crews and Lae p -- undertaken to provide search lights. he has no listening apparatus available but will arrange system of signals v,/' &lt; to give warning of raids coming via Iraq. Question of -bevy H.C.Os for patrolling is in hand also Aotor transport. A.O.C. expresses view that flight is more isolated act of bravado than first of probable series of raids but I impressed on him effect on American anc local population ii adequate defence measures were not taken. Two planes are being sent here on demonstration flight on ‘ ^W r Id day and one will stay and report on black-out arrangements. RLSIDI5NTr* i 1 mCOCIBffigKIXDML Secret* No. C/217 of 1941* \- ft- / The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (gjix with a request that the necessary arrangements may be made by the Defence Officer* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp,Bahrain. Dated... .&lt;7m$.. 1.9 4 !&gt;. ✓Telegram Prom To Ho. 7939 0. Dated 22nd received 24th June 1941 , 4 ' * Inter Special, Annindia, Simla. Political Eeeldeiit at Reference Annindia 7323/0 of nth June repeated Reaident Buehire regarding vieit of Brigadier Hughes. f ne R.a. officer accompanying reconnai- Lbance party will de^plane Bahrain about June 29th arid re wUn there on dut* untii rejoined by Hughes later. Grateful if acoommodation and transport facilities Bay be made available for him. - AKHINDIa * aVM 24/6*No.C/662. Political Agency f Bahrain, the 25th June 1941. To The Defence Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum The following telegram from the Political Resident has been received:- 'Visit of Brigadier Hughes. One R.E. officer accompanying reconnaisance party will de-plane Bahrain about June 29th and remain there on duty until rejoined by Hughes later. Grate ful if accommodation and transport facilities may be made available for him.' 2. I would be grateful if you could make arrange ments for his accommodation etc. u . Political Agent, Bahraintmuamm Telegram S. From Government of India, Simla. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No. 3107 Dated 24th received 25th June 1941. ,, ‘ /V v /V* Reference Foreign telegram No. 3058 dated June 21st. Funds required to meet expenses in connection with movements of Hughes and his staff will be drawn from you. Please make payments up to Rs. 5000/- and intimate expenditure to Accountant General Central Revenues for action as described in our telegram No. 2860 of June 12th. - FOREIGN - Qec{. S' C «b&gt;.Telegram Prom To Repeated Minister, Tehran* !To*l72 Political Resident, at Bahrain. No.3058 Dated 21st received 22nd June 1941. ? Prior’s telegram No.601 June 8th para 1* 2. Lieut.-Colonel F.E.C. Hughes Indian Army is proceeding to Persian Gulf on reconnaissance duties and and will meet Prior at Basra* He is Commander- Designate of Forces required in that area.—GOVERNMENT OF INDIA; CONFIDENTIAL Depabtmint, '• &lt;Vi &gt; ■ EXPRESS LETTER [^V.B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE^ sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires y but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From The Political Kesident, Camp Bahrain. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. A T o. C/21D of 1941. Dated 25th June 1941 lf% . My Printed Letter No. C/217 dated 24th June 1^41. Brigadier Hughes and party are new travelling by aeroplane leaving Karachi on June 27th and not June 2i&gt;th. Sd/- C. G. Prior, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. s. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.(1346) Wt. 11971/321 1,000,000 5/37 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.112 Form 348 (Medium) SECRET From: — Defence Officer, ?■ To: — H.B.M. *s Political Bahrain. Date: — 26th June, 1941. Ref.: — BEF/AIR/S/10. , ^ \ V' I have to acknowledge receiot of your Secret letter No.C/662 dated 25th June, and to say I will make the arrangements you ask for. A .rAco. Ij _ „ Major, Defence Officer, Persian Gulf,No G/l/17. C/o The Defence Officer BAHREIN. f? 7th July 1941. Cear f We spoke about a possible visit to DHAHRAN in HA.SA. I think it will now have to form part of our reconnaissance. Would you please be so good as to arrange the necessary political formalities. The Officers going will be:- 75 ^ 7o .ouxJ-' boats . IVfy-self Major MURRAY Gp Captain THOMSON Comdr MANSON. We will go over as civilians in one of the Oil Companys Possible date SATURDAY 12 th. With many thanks for your kind offices Major G.R. Alban Political Agent BAHREIN. e&gt;-y , , V r /Telegram S From Political Agent, Bahrain. His Majesty's Minister, Jedda To No.223 Dated the 7th July 1941. Important . Brigadier Hughes, Major Murray, Group Captain Thomson and Commander Manson wish to visit Oil Company at Dhahran for one day. Starting if possible Saturday 12th July. Grateful if permission for visit can be obtained. Ar^' 2. Your telegram No. 007^1 dated 31st May. Instruc tions have been noted and will be followed in present case. PoliticalWt. 30669/2697 1,486,000 2/38 D.P.W. 161-1253 SECHLT From:— To Date Ref: l F 4 Form 348 (Medium) Defence Officer, Persian Gulf, at Bahrain. 's Political Agent, Bahrain, Adviser to The Government of Bahrain, Officer i/c Royal Navy Base. Juffair, General Manager, Bahrein Petroleum Go,, Ltd,, Awali, 8th July, 1941, DEF/AIR/8/10, It is notified that the temporary Headquarters of the Bahrain Reconnaissance is at - H0U8E 14, Awali; TELEPHONE 70, Awali, Defence Officer, Persian Gu Ma^or, /No* 138 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th July 1941 To His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin ’Isa al Khalifah, FCIE, CSI, Ruler of Bahrain* After Compliments. I have the honour to inform Your Highness that some military officers have arrived in Bahrain on a visit for the purpose of examining the defences of the Island and Refinery and of taking necessary steps to improve them. This is what had to be said etc. Usual Ending. Sd/- R.G. Alban Political Agent, Bahrain.✓ California Arabian Standard Oil company Dhahren, Saudi Arabia Major R. G. Alban, 0. B. S. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Manama Bahrein Island Dear Sir: Enclosed is a general map of Eastern Saudi Arabia showing the road system developed by the Comnany. Will you kindly forward it to Brigadier Hughes. July 13, 1941 Yours very truly, FWO: rb yk //-v . - w. L Attach - 1I Confidential No.C/750. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to Brigadier F. E. C. Hughes, I.A., Bahrain andhhas the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Datedthe 14th July 1941. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure Name and Date Subject General Map of Eastern Saudi Arabia I showing the road system developed by I the California Arabian Standard Oil» THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. u 19th July, 1941 \ PA-594 Major R. G. Alhan, His Britannic Majesty*3 Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We enclose copy of a letter dated 19th July which we have to-day received from the Reconnaissance Party in Bahrein. As the work they are asking to he done is of a military nature, we would like to have your approval. In the meantime we propose to go ahead with the work unless you have any objections. Yours very truly M. H. Idpp. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Encs 'Copy to: Defence Officer, Bahrein Reconnaissance Party» Bahrein, July 19, 1941 Chief Local Representative, Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, Awali. Dear Sir, It is possible that an aeroplane landing ground will be required south of Zellaq. We would be very grateful if your Company could oil three small patches in this area so that we can see what is involved in producing a surface suitable for a runway, I have shown Mr. Sommerville what we would like done, and attach a note from the Adviser to the Covernment which shows that there is no objection to the use of the land for this purpose. The cost of the experiment will be met by the Defence Officer. Yours truly, s/ F.E.C. Hughes A/Brig. RECONNAISSANCE PARTYConfidential No. C/772 Politicpl Agencyi Bahrain, the 20th July 1941, To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, BAHRAIN Dear Sir, I have to thank you for your letter No* PA-594 dated the 19th July 1941. 2* As the oiling is only to be done as an experiment, I see no objection to the proposal. Yours faithfully, ,u. Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to Brigadier F.E.C. Hughes with the request that any communications concerning land or other important matters which it is desired to make to the Bahrain Government or to the Bahrain Petroleum Comoany may kindly be made through this office.2 5 &gt; / Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Residency Agent, Sharj ah No. Dated 20th July 1941 Brigadier Hughes and party arriving Shariah by air July -Sand for short stay. Please meet and make any arrangements desired. - PoliticalTelegram 'S n From Political Resident Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/289 Dated and received the 20th July 1941. My telegram No. T/277 July 19th. Following is a repetition of Government of India telegram No. 3668 July 19th begins. Armindia telegram No. 9359/G July 16th. Visa granted on Hughes* passport limits his entry to Khorramshahr c.f. Bullard*s telegram No. 69 of May 2ftt.h. He will therefore have to follow itinerarv suggested hv Minister. Please inform him accordingly. He may prefer to visit Iran before returning to India in which case his passport will be sent to Bahrain by air mail. On receipt of information from him regarding approximate dete nf his arrival at Bandar Abbas ( 5 groups undecypherable) can be arranged. Ends. Please inform Hughes. Prior -From Eushire *■ Sj'f] Telegram inter (13) From Political Resident, Eushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Minister, Tehran. Armindia, Simla No. T/285 Dated 19th; received 20th July 1941 / Following for Hughes. Reference Armindia telegram No. 9ZS9/G dated July 18th. You should of course travel in mufti and your baggage should not contain weapon or uniform or smything which cannot be shown to Customs, please let me know port of entry and proposed date of sailing as early as possible. 2* Demi-o fficial (to Bahrain only) B. I. Ships* Officers are world’s biggest gossips. Verb. sap. 1&lt;a) yt THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i » s^Ba^irein Island, Persian Gulf. lA July 17, 1941. PA-588 His Britannic Jlajesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, We are forwarding the following drawings to Lieut.- Comdr. Manson, for his records: BR-1226 - Location - Bahrein Wharf - Mooring Anchors - dated March 15, 1941. BR-486/1 - Bahrein &amp; Vicinity - dated May 18, 1939. BR-1258 - Outline Sketch of Sitra Loading Wharf. We regret that we are unable to spare the following hydrographic publications, owing to our own depleted stock: No.3788 - Approaches to Ras-at-Tannura No.3790 - Approaches to Bahrein. These charts may be readily obtained at any hydrographic office. BR-473 - Area map - Refinery to Ships Anchorage Bahrein - dated May 29, 1938. BR-510/1 - Map showing locations of Sitra Fish Traps- Original and Existing Barge Channel - also tentative relocation of Barge Channel - dated July 16, 1940. BK-513/2 - Chart No.7 - Hydrography between Bahrein Island and Saudi Arabia - dated September 3, 1940. BR-1232 - Exploratory Route around south end of Bahrein Island - dated April 3, 1941. BR-1257 - Hydrographic Surveys - Zellaq, Bahrein - dated July 19, 1941. Yours very truly Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTDTelegram Inter (13) From Armindia, Simla. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 9612/G Dated and received the 21st July 1941. Immediate Following for Hughes. Cancel my 9585/G of July 21st. Your No. Nil of July 20th. You should consult Resident. Unless you both have urgent reasons for postponement of visit to Iran you should undertake it before returning to India. State reasons if necessary to postpone. X K /'ft M * a /2 f | &gt;•),! f / / / L L f ^ ' c * L&gt;&amp;I °J 0 0 l - \ Dhahran, Saudi Arabia July 22, 19U Major R. G. Alban, 0. B. E. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent Manama Bahrein Dear Sir: Commander Manson has requested through Mr. Rodstrom hydrographic information on the area around the Ras Tanura peninsula. I believe the attached map will give the information that Commander Manson requires. Will you kindly forward it to him. The negative from which this print was made is a poor one and therefore a clearer print could not be obtained. Yours very truly FWO :wj Enel. - 1No. C/790-28/1-V The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— Lieutenant Commander G. W. Manson, C/o The Defence Officer, Bahrain. (3 3 l and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) Ihk Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated ~ 24th -July 194X*- - Reference to previous correspondence: Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter dated July 22nd 1941 from F. W. Ohliger to the Political Agent, Bahrain, Subject. N!ap of Has Tanura peninsula• L. with enclosureA wall July 24 f 1941 Brigadier J.1S.3. Hughes, Keoonnaiaaanue Party, ^ Bahrein. &gt; 6) J i&gt;ear Sir, Please refer to your letter of July 19th requesting us to oil and grade throe small patches of ground in order to test the sur face for a proposed airplane landing field south of Zellao. Please be advised that this test has now been completed and the following results obtained. The area tested in each case was approximately 150* long by 50* wide. ho. 1 ? The surface of the soil was hard and required very little grading, be used 26.02 gross barrels of slop oil to prepare this surface and 3/4 of an hour of grader time. ho. £ : The surface of this area was somewhet sandy and re quired approxirately twice as much time as area Mo. 1 to harden. 38.69 gross barrels of oil were used and 1 hour of grader time. ho. 3 1 The surface of this area was very sandy and when the top surface was broken preparatory to oiling it became quite soft and caused us suioh trouble with our oil truck getting stuck. This surface required 77.3S gross barrels of oil and 2 hours of grader time. Vie will finish, load, haul to site and spread the above slop oil at the rate of Rs.2/-/- per barrel. The rate of grading with our auto patrol, including driver, is Hs.40/-/- for an 8-hour day. For your information, one barrel contains 42 U.S. gallons and there are approximately 6 barrels per long ton. &amp;ajor A. Murray is familiar with the above locations as designated and can probably give you an accurate estimate of the arxrnnt of oil and grading time required to surface the proposed air field, uain^ the above fi pires on which to base his computations. Yours very truly, - '.*Jor iud HUT THS BAHK31M PETHOL&amp;m 90&amp;I&amp;HT LTD. ORIGINAL SIGNED BY By Alban M H, UFP, mmrmmsTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, No. PA-605. July 23, 1941. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, We are attaching two drawings No. A-77535 - Bahrein Refinery ' BR- 1026 - ' « which have been requested by Captain Dyer of the Reconnaisance Party. We shall be pleased if you will have these maps handed to Capt. Dyer, if you consider it in order to do so. Yours very truly, M. H. LIPP. Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.No. C/794-28/1-V The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— Captain Dyer, C/o Defence Officer, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 26 th July 1941 . Reference to previous correspondence: Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.PA-605 dated 23rd July 1941 from C.L.R., Bapco, with enclosures. Maps of Bahrain RefineryTelegram Telegram 'S' From Political Agent, Bahrain. To No. Political Resident, Shiraz Dated 24th July 1941 Important vl . A Your telegram No. T/289 July 20th. 2. Hughes is unaware of nature of Minister’s itinerary and requests details by telegraph. - PoliticalTelegram S# From Political Heeldent f Shiraz* Political Agent, Bahrain. No* T/324 Dated and received the 26th July 1941* r- Your telegram No* 261 July 24th* Minister suggested that Hughes should proceed from Khorramshahr to Tehran thence to Bushire and if desired continue via Kerman to Bandar Abbas* 2* I could ask Falconer to meet Hughes at Shiraz on latter*s way down from Tehran if necessary* Prior.i&amp;) Telegram Inter (13) From Armlndla, Simla* To Political, Bahrain. No. 10014/G. Dated and received 27th July 1941. Important Following for Hughes or his representative. Reference your report dated July 7th. Chief Inspector of Explosives India with wide experience of passive air defence of oil installations probably available for visit to Bahrain and tender advice. Hope also to make Field Artillery officer available. Their visits however must be at invitation of oil Company as latter American concern. Will you secure invitation for both. ArmindiaTelegram From To Inter (13) Armindia Simla. Political Bahrain. No. 9913/G Dated 25th received 26th July 1941. Following for Brigadier Hughes. Your SM 13 of July 24th. K L M passage booked July 30th Bahrain Basrah. Passport should reach Basrah July 30th. Essential you should ______ Iran by August 12th. Following other passages booked. Hughes Thomson Manson, Sharjah Bahrain July 28th by B.O.A.C. Murray Mellsop, Bahrain Karachi August 1st by B.O.A.C. Armindia.Telegram 3. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 257 Dated the 28th July 1941. Urgent . Please transmit following to Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, begins Hughes will proceed by car Khorramshahr to Ahv/az train Ahwaz to Tehran on 31st. Please arrange car and reserve first class berth. Inform train timings departure Bandar Shahpur and Ahwaz arrival Tehran. But would much prefer to go by air same or following day-* Please v/ire arrangements made. Political.Telegram From To Mo. 256 Dated the O • Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Shiraz. 28th July 1941. t Hughes proposed itinerary;Khorramshahr 31st, depart same day Ahwaz for Tehran y *visit Embassy second Isfahan third Shiraz fourth fifth Bushire sixth to ninth Senaveh tenth Ahwaz eleventh exit twelfth. Grateful if you inform Consuls Basrah Khorramshahr and Ahwaz. May Embassy Tehran be informed and requested arran'e motor transport Tehran Bushire. - Political - 8793Telegram From H. M. Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 28 Dated 29th July 1941. Relayed under Bushire telegram No. 750 of 29th July. Bahrain telegram No. 257 dated July 28th. (a) Who is Hughes ? ^ (b) When and how v/ill he arrive Khorramshahr ? (c) Please see my immediately succeeding telegram for train timings. (d) There is no aeroplane other than Anglo-Persian Oil Company aeroplane which will not carry British Government officials. (e) On receipt of reply I will make necessary arrange ments .Telegram 0, From H. M. Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr*. To Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 29 Dated 29th July 1941. Belayed under Bushire telegram No. 751 of 29th July. Immediate Train leaves Bandar Shahpur at 15 hours on Sunday, Tuesday, Thursday and Friday arriving Ahwaz 19 hours same day. Train leaves Ahwaz 1930 hours Monday, Wednesday and Friday arriving Tehran 19 hours following day.- &lt; Telegram 3. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. No. 268 Dated the 30th July 1941. Immediate oui Your telegram No. 28 of July 29th. (a) Brigadier Hughes, head of Persian Gulf Defence but Mission^/travelling in Tran as private individual. (b) Air to Basra, thence Khorramshahr July 31st. (c) Please reserve seat on train from Ahvvaz 1930 Friday August 1st. (d) Vide (a) above. Hughes will speak on his arrival. (e) Please arrange car Khorramshahr to Ahwaz morning August 1st. Political. »ITo: Defence Officer, Persian Gulf, (R)Armindia; y Resident, Persian Gulf,,*^ Bsilirain Please Pass. Air Ministry. Gr. 61. Prom: R.A.P., Iraq. TOO = 1217z/29.7.41. to A«M. A. 362/29th July. Your letter DEF-AIR military Officer S-6 July 17th not As G.in C. India has now taken over responsibility for all land defence measures in the Persian Gulf the disbandment of volunteers should be referred to him by Brigadier Hughes. Inform latter If he is at Bahrain. TOO = 1217z/29.7.41. TOR = 1028z/31..1 &gt; 3. 1320f. NAVAL MESSAGE. Book or Table to be used for Initials of Cypherer or Coder. Time of Receipt in Cypher or Coding Office. Date. Cyphering or Coding. Recyphering or Recoding. (5/374.) \Tt. 30557/D5886. IOOm pads. 10/39. B. &amp; B. Ltd. 51-5092.Telegram Inter, From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Shiraz. No. 27$|^ Dated the 5th August 1941. Following from R.A.F., Basra addressed Defence Officer Persian Gulf, repeated Armindia, Resident Persian Gulf (Bahrain please pass) Air Ministry No. A/362 29th July, begins. Your letter DEF-AIR military Officer S-6 July 17th not to A.M. As Commander in Chief India has now taken over responsibility for all land defence measures in the Persian Gulf the disbandment of volunteers should be referred to him by Brigadier Hughes. Inform latter if he is at Bahrain. Ends. 2. Please inform Hughes. Politico 1.■ i Wt. 36500/2697 1,485,000 2/38 D.P.W. 161-1253 SECRET. , 'TFrom To:- Date: Ref Defence Officer, Persian Gulf, at Bahrain. o S//^ v H.B.M.'s Political Agent, Bahrain. 2nd September, 1941. BAH/DEF/S-10/12S. RECONNAISSANCE OF THE DEFENCE REQUIREMENTS FOR' THE 'UKHSIM 'GULF. I forward for your information a copy of a letter No. 55379/M.0.4 dated, 20th Sent ember, 1941 from The Chief of The General Staff in India. The instructions in oara.3 of the aoovementioned letter have been carried out by me. Form 348 (Medium) L Hi J'i .(■ J-i DEFENCE OFFICER, PERSIAN G'LF, End. 1.BY AIP MAIL SECRET No. 55379/M. 0.4 GENERAL HEADQUARTERS, INDIA General Staff Branch. Simla, the 20th Sent., 1041. To, Defence Officer, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. RECONNAISSANCE OF THE DEFENCE RECUIRKMl-'NTS OF THE PERSIAN GULF n T !? e Tt re 5 ort reconnaissance has been studied at General Headquarters and the conclusions contained therein have been noted for action when the occasion demands. As no action has yet been taken to imolenent the recommendations of the^Reconnaissance Party as regards the defences in Bahrein / ^ ^^ssible that the imoression may gain ground in the Lsiana that the time soent by the reconnaissance Darby and all help given by tne local authorities and commercial interests was to no ouroose. ?• . n .y 0U ^ 7 0U Please take steos to correct any such imoress ion ii it exists. It will easily be understood that the general strategic situation in the Middle East has altered greatiy since the inception.of the.Persian Gulf Reconnaissance, with consequent alteration m tne immediate threat to °aRrein + s a result of tne reconnaissance, however, we are in a oosition to take suitable ana adequate defensive measures at short notice in accordance ith possible future develooments of the situation. In the mean time other cemancls must be accorded oriority in the distribution of our defensive resources. , Further, tne Chief of the General Staff wishes that you should convey to the Civil Authorities of the Island,'to the Management of the Bahrein Petroleum Comoany and to tfie other commercial interests who afforded their assistance, his aoDreciation oftheir whole-hearted co-ooeration and his thanks r 0I V t e manner in which tney did everything in their oower to helo forward the work of the reconnaissance. (Sgd.) G. SIMONS, Maj.-Gen., For CHIEF OF THE GENERAL STAFF. [r~tui Cofaf 1 OCT 2 T. U^ a iA OpJju r pe&lt;A*Ck*&gt; 19411 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• HI a Majesty's Vioe Consul, Ehorractshahr • 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document 3 ^.-Book No. LOCAL PU1 Bill No. INSTRUCTIONS :-l. 2 . 3 . 4. This Form will be completed in triplicate by L.P.O’s. whenever a local purchase The original I.A.F.F.-1035 will be forwarded to the OfTicer-in-Charge, Field Ac receipted vouchers attached, the duplicate I. A.F.F.-1035 being sent at the same The L.P.O. as an ‘Imprest Holder’ will draw cash, as required, from the neare‘ in cash for all supplies purchased. Each L.P.O. will maintain an Imprest account in duplicate on A.F.N.-1531-A in entered as they occur. The original account will be submitted to the Oflicer-i immediately after the close of the month. The second copy of the Imprest A Authorities when it will be destroyed. (For detailed instructions see Field Imp Serial Item No. 1 Artide. 2 Unit of weight, etc. 3 Quant Amount. 4 ity purchased. Amount in words. 5 T Date of purchase. 6 Place of purchase. 7 Name of Supplier and Father’s name. 8 e ! Certified that the above is a correct statement of the description and quantity of sup the following serial item Nos. above are attached. Nos. Place Date M.I.P.—(G.1072)—10-10-41—2,000 Books.LOCAL PUJ Book No. Bill No. _ INSTRUCTIONS :-l. 2 . 4. This Form will be completed in triplicate by L.P.O’s. whenever a local purchase The original I.A.F.F.-1035 will be forwarded to the OfTicer-in-Charge, Field Ac receipted vouchers attached, the duplicate I. A.F.F.-1035 being sent at the same The L.P.O. as an ‘Imprest Holder’ will draw cash, as required, from the nearer in cash for all supplies purchased. Each L.P.O. will maintain an Imprest account in duplicate on A.F.N.-1531-A in entered as they occur. The original account will be submitted to the Officer-i immediately after the close of the month. The second copy of the Imprest A Authorities when it will be destroyed. (For detailed instructions see Field Imj . i i Quantity purchased. 7 i Date of Place of Name of Supplier and Serial Artide. purchase. purchase. Father’s name. Item No. Unit of weight. Amount. Amount in words. etc. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 • - ~A Certified that the above is a correct statement of the description and quantity of sup* the following serial item Nos. above are attached. Nos. ' Place Date M.I.P.—(G.1072)—10-10-41—2,000 Books.Subject: Visit of CIOS HBM f s Political Agent BAHREIN. TOP SECRET 11% Troons BAHREIN' SC/135 BAHRAIN RECEIPT. / Oot 45. Date..*«•••* Confidential* A cony of HQ SOUTH IRAQ Area signals AQ 1 of 19 Oct andAQ 3 of 22 Oct 45 is appended for information. Ui Lt Col OC Troops BAHREIN. PROM: SOUTH IRAQ Area TO: 00 Tps BAHREIN Cony. a Pro AQ 1 (.) TOP SECRET (.) PERSONAL POR OC TROOPS (.) FIRST (. ) CIG-S accompanied by C in C MEF and 000 PAIC arriving by air in C in C s personal plane late afternoon 3 nov 45 from RIYADH after visiting KING IEN SAUD (.) SECOND (.) C in C and GOC will almost certainly stay nimbt and see CIGS depart before returning direct to CAIRO ) GIGS personal plane will fly direct to BAHREIN for onward .journey to INDIA (.) STD dawn nov 4 (.) THIRD (.) accn night 3/4 nov will be required (.) suggest GIGS C in C GOC with political age nt and It cols BONLH and CHARRINGTON (MAs to GIGS) with I-IA to afc&amp;om C and one batman in BOAC resthouse (.) FOURTH (.) GOC desires security measures to be tightened (•) NO ceremonial parades but HQ PAIC are requesting AHQ to arrange RAF guards w you should a contact sta comd (.) PS personnel will be sent from here U) signal if you require further CitP (•) i?Ii?xH {•) area comd flying to'^BAHREIN probably with one staff offr morning 2 nov (-/ arrange accn SNOPG to whom contents this signal should be passed ; OIRd does NOT wish to pay visit to sheihh and suggest you request political agent tactfully NOT to invite sheikh to dinner Copy PROM: SOUTH IRAQ Area TO: OC Tps BAHREIN info G Pro AQ 3 (.) TOPSECRET (.) PERSONAL POR OC TPS (. ) my AQ 1 of 19 oct (.) FIRST (.) confirmed CIGS and C in C will stay night 3/4 nov at BAHREIN (.) GOC will NOT be accompanying w SECOND w liaise with RAP concerning provision of gds on CIGS house night 3/4 an Planes of CIGS and C in C from time of arrival {•) THIRD U; security measures suggested to above are CMP in jeeps front and rear CIGS car (.) letter by air from comd follows</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000042_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/673</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000042</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/673</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/1 V Visits to Bahrain of military officials (Brigadier Hughes &amp; Party)’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-26T21:05:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (66 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 66-67) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 68; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-65; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to visits by senior military officials to Bahrain, principally arrangements for the visit of Brigadier F E C Hughes (ff 6-50), referred to in the file as both Commander-Designate of Forces, and head of Persian Gulf Defence Mission, in late June/early July 1941, for the purposes of carrying out a reconnaissance mission. Correspondence concerning Hughes’s visit includes: arrangements for his arrival and departure, including onward travel to Khorramshahr in Iran; permission/arrangements for Hughes to travel to Zekrit [Zikrīt] (Qatar) and Dhahran [[al-Ẓahrān] (Saudi Arabia); the loaning of maps (none included in the file); assessment of land south of Zellaq in Bahrain for a proposed landing strip.Other correspondence in the file relates to: a visit to Bahrain by the Air Officer Commanding (AOC) Iraq in October 1940 (ff 2-5); various visits in 1942, with details of the officers and visit dates (ff 51-55); correspondence in July 1944 relating to the proposed visit to Bahrain of the General Officer Commanding (GOC) in Charge of Paiforce (Persia and India Force), and the subsequent delay and cancellation of the visit (ff 56-59); correspondence relating to visits by the GOC in Charge of the Persian Gulf (ff 64-65), and the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (CIGS) in October 1945 (f 65).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander-Designate of Forces, Persian Gulf</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Zekrit</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dhahran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000042#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>