<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001b0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T02:59:00.072Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT — PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. V J v 1 ' ' ' L , -S. ' '5 P’-' ^ ♦*! ! } Xk V. a«.v June 3, 1935. Section 2. [E 3438/3438/34] • Mr. Knatchbuli-Eugessen to Sir John Simon.—{Received June 3.) (No. 211.) Sir, Tehran, May 17, 1935. I HAVE the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy in translation of a new Law of Arbitration, consisting of thirty-eight articles, passed by the Majlis in its session of the 28th Bahman, 1313 (17th February, 1935), which replaces the former enactments which formed the subject of Sir Robert Clive's despatch No. 202 of the 11th April, 1929. 2. The new law would appear to be better conceived than its predecessors. It reduces the scale of fees payable to the arbitrators, excludes cases involving suspension of payment, bankruptcy, and personal status, and is not compulsory but can be invoked by mutual consent. 3. In marital disputes, however, the court can impose arbitration upon the demand of either husband or wife. 4. The wording of article 37 is doubtless a natural corollary to article VIII of the Marriage Law of the 23rd Mordad, 1310 (15th August, 1931), which enjoins upon husband and wife to treat each other kindly. 5. In contracts with foreigners Iranian subjects cannot bind themselves to arbitration by any party who is of the same nationality as the other party to a contract. 6. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No. 94), and copies of the law, in translation, to all of His Majesty’s consular representatives in Iran (circular No. 16). I have, &amp;c. H. M. KNATCHBULL-HUGESSEN. Enclosure. Law of Arbitration. (Passed by the Majlis in its Session of the 28th Bahman, 1313 (February 17,1935).) (Translation.) Article 1.—All persons competent to file suits can, by mutual agreement, submit to arbitration by one or more persons any uncertainties or disputes arising between them in respect of rights and properties, regardless of whether they have been raised in the courts or not, and, if so raised, at any stage. A rt. 2.—The parties to a contract can, when making the transaction or by a separate undertaking, agree to settlement by arbitration of any disputes that may eventually arise between them, and can also appoint their arbitrator or arbitrators before any dispute has arisen; but, nevertheless, in respect of any dealings taking place between Iranian and foreign subjects, the Iranian party cannot, prior to any dispute having arisen, bind himself in any way to the settlement of eventual disputes by the arbitration of one or more persons, or an association, if either the person, persons, or the association have the same nationality as the other party to the contract. Any agreement contravening this rule shall be null and void. Art.%. —In the agreement for arbitration, the following points must be included — C (1) Particulars about the parties and the arbitrators, as names, family names, &amp;c., such as would prevent any misunderstanding; (2) The subject of disputes which are to be settled by arbitration. Art. 4.—With regard to article 2, when the parties did not appoint their arbitrator or arbitrators at the time of making the agreement, should a dispute later arise, if one party does not assign his arbitrator, the other party can name his arbitrator and introduce him to the first party by a formal declaration and request him also to appoint and introduce his arbitrator. In such circumstances [440 c—2]this first party is requested to appoint and announce his arbitrator within ten days of the date of the communication to him of the declaration with all due allowance for distance. Should he not take any action before expiration of the term mentioned, the court competent to examine the question in dispute will appoint the arbitrator of this party at the request of the party who has appointed his arbitrator. In case of any dispute between the two parties in respect of the trans action itself or of the agreement to refer to arbitration, the court shall examine that first and, after being satisfied, shall appoint the arbitrator for the unwilling party; but, as long as the arbitrator to be appointed by the court has not been announced to the arbitrator of the other party, the unwilling party can appoint and introduce his arbitrator. The above rules shall be observed also in the following cases :— (1) Where, according to agreement reached between the two parties, any dis puted question is to be submitted for settlement to a single arbitrator and the parties are not willing to, or cannot mutually agree to, the appointment of the said arbitrator. (2) Where the arbitrator of one party dies or resigns from the task and this party does not wish to appoint a successor to him. (3) Where the parties will not, or cannot, mutually agree to the appointment of a third arbitrator. The court competent for appointing an arbitrator is the court competent for examining the dispute itself. A rt. 5.—In case the number of arbitrators is not determined in the agreement for arbitration and the parties cannot agree as to the number of the arbitrators, each of the parties must appoint its own arbitrator and mutually agree to a third arbitrator. Art. 6.—If the duration of the authority of the arbitrators has not been deter mined in the agreement for arbitration, the term shall be two months, beginning from the day when the arbitrators have all in writing accepted their charge of arbitration. Art. 7.—In gmy case where an arbitrator is appointed by the court instead of by both or by one of the parties, it must name at least twice the number of persons required for appointment, and from those persons who fulfil the prescribed conditions pick the necessary arbitrator or arbitrators by lot. A rt. 8.—Persons such as mentioned below cannot under any circumstances be appointed as arbitrators :— (1) Convicted criminals and persons under prosecution on criminal charges. (2) Persons condemned for misdemeanours who have been deprived of the right to act as arbitrators by judgment of a court. A rt. 9.—The following persons shall not be appointed arbitrators by lot:— (1) Persons who are below 30 years of age. (2) Persons who are not residents of the place where the court which assigns arbitrators has jurisdiction. Art. 10.—The following persons cannot be appointed arbitrators by lot, except with the mutual consent of the parties :— (1) Any person interested in the suit. (2) Persons who have relation or connexion with one of the disputing parties to the second degree of the third class. (3) Any person who is executor, deputy, agent of or representative of one of the disputing parties or whose affairs are in the charge of one of the disputing parties. (4) Any person who is heir, or whose wife is heir, to one of the disputing parties. (5) Any person who has formerly been or who still is engaged in an action for crime or misdemeanour with one of the disputing parties or with persons having relation or connexion with one of them to the second degree of the third class. (6) Any person who is himself, or whose wife or one of whose relations or connexions to the second degree of the third class is engaged in a civil action with one of the disputing parties or with his wife or one of his relations or connexions to the second degree of the third class. (7) Judges, officials of the primary court and the Court of Appeal, and Governors and other Government officials in their area of jurisdiction.Art. 11.—After the drawing of lots and the appointment of arbitrator, each of the parties is entitled to refuse the arbitrator appointed within ten days of the date either of the announcement at the meeting in case of his presence there and/or of notification to him in the event of his absence from the meeting; if, however, the causes for refusal arise later, the period shall commence from the day when the cause commenced. The court shall examine the rejection on its being received and, in the event of finding it just, shall appoint another arbitrator in place of the arbitrator rejected. Art. 12.—After the appointment of an arbitrator or arbitrators the parties are not entitled to discharge them except by mutual agreement. Art. 13.—After accepting the charge of arbitration, the arbitrators are not entitled to resign unless they have satisfactory reasons, such as travel, sickness or the like. Any arbitrator resigning without any sufficient reason shall not be appointed arbitrator by lot for a period of five years. Should he be absent from two sittings without good reasons, the arbitrators present at the sittings will report the matter to the competent court, which will appoint another arbitrator in his place, unless the disputing parties agree that the same arbitrator should still act. A rt. 14.—Should the arbitrators fail to issue their finding within the period laid down in the agreement for arbitration or the period prescribed by law, their arbitration shall be considered as null and void unless the parties fix a further period. . . Art. 15.—A third person who has been summoned according to law and who enters the suit either before or after submission of dispute to arbitration can come to an understanding with the original parties in the matter of submission of the question to arbitration and the appointment of the arbitrator or arbitrators selected; in the event of not reaching agreement, this (third party’s) claim shall be independently examined in accordance with regulations. Art. 16.—The parties must deliver their documents and evidence to their arbitrators, and the arbitrators can ask necessary explanations from them. If in the course of proceedings circumstances indicating a crime or misdemeanour are disclosed which affect the finding to be issued by the arbitrators, and if it is impossible to differentiate between the civil and criminal side of the question, and also if the dispute is relative to the matter of marriage, divorce or relation ship, and the settlement of the disputed matter referred to arbitration depends upon prior examination of the marriage, divorce or relationship question the arbitrators must return the suit to the court which referred it to them or submit it to a court competent for examining the original suit. After the issue oi a definite decision in the criminal matter, or the matter of marriage, divorce or relationship, this decision shall be announced to the arbitrators and the legal term for arbitration shall be renewed from the date of the notification. The arbitrators cannot issue findings contradicting the substance or an} judgment issued in connexion with criminal matters or in connexion 'with marriage, divorce or relationship. Claims in the matter of forgery or counterfeit in documents cannot be the basis of prosecutions for crime or misdemeanour if the forger or counterfeiter is not indicated or if there is no possibility of prosecuting the forger or counter feiter for some legal reason. Art. 17.—Arbitration becomes void in the following circumstances:— (1) In case the parties come to a written compromise. (2) In case of death or pilgrimage of one of the parties. Art. 18.—-In their proceedings and issue of opinion the arbitrators are not bound to follow the regulations governing civil procedure, but they must observe the conditions laid down in the agreement for arbitration. The opinion given by the arbitrators must be reasonable and not in contradiction of natural laws (laws justifying rights ?). Art. 19.—The arbitrators can settle the dispute peaceably if they have the authority for so doing. Art. 20.—In case any one of the arbitrators who has been present in time of examination and consultation fails to appear to give his opinion without any satisfactory excuse, or refuses to give his opinion, the opinion issued by the majority shall be binding; the absence of the arbitrator or his refusal to give his opinion or signature must be endorsed in the finding. [440 c—2] b 2Art. 21.—After receiving the finding issued by the arbitrators the registrar shall after informing the head of the court, record it m the relevant file, get the head of the court’s certification and signature to the conformity of the record with the original finding, and send out the original finding for service on the parties^to^th^dmputa ^ condemned party fails t0 comp l y willingly with the finding within ten days after service on him, the court which referred the disputed matter to arbitration or any court competent to examine the original claim is enioined, at the request of the interested party, to issue a warrant of execution in accordance with the finding issued by the arbitrators. Art. 23.—In case the parties to the dispute jointly reject the finding issued by arbitrators, the finding shall be without any effect. A r t 24—The arbitrators are enjoined to give their opinions during the period of arbitration, and should the opinions of arbitrators be issued after the expiration of the arbitration terms, each of the parties can within ten days of the date of service and with the observation of the legal distance, request its cancellation by the court which has referred the suit to arbitration, or any court having competency for examination of the suit , . , ^ Art. 25 .—In case the arbitrators have erred m some calculation which anects their opinion, or have not mentioned in their finding the amount claimed which was subject to their examination, the interested party can, m case the arbitral period has not expired, request correction from the arbitrators themselves, and otherwise, within ten days of notification of arbitrator’s opinion, from the court having referred the case to arbitration or any competent court. Art. 26.—In the following cases the arbitral finding shall be null and void and without any validity ^— (1) In case the finding is in contravention with the law. (2) In case the arbitrators have issued a finding beyond the limit of their authority or in respect of a matter which has not been the subject of arbitration. . , (3) In case they have issued a finding contravening a formal document which has not lost its validity for some legal reason. Art. 27.—Under the circumstances of the preceding article, each of the parties can request cancellation of the arbitral award from the court which referred the suit to arbitration, or from any court having competency for the examination of the original claim. In such circumstances, the court is enjoined to consider the petition and to issue a decree cancelling the arbitral award if it is not justified in accordance with the above article. Any appeal for the rejection of a petition for cancellation of an arbitral award and the decree for its cancellation can only be heard in the Court of Appeal. An appeal can be heard in the Court of Cassation if such decrees have been issued by the Court of Appeal. In respect of this article, in case a warrant of execution has been issued, the court must immediately, and prior to fixing a sitting, attend to the reasons put forward by the petitioner, and, in the event of finding them strong, issue an order for suspension of the warrant of execution. A rt. 28.—In case the suit has been submitted to arbitration when it is under consideration of the Court of Cassation, the request for cancellation must be made from the court which has issued the judgment required by the Court of Cassation^). The rejection of the request for cancellation, or the order of cancellation of the arbitral award issued from this court shall be liable to appeal in the Court of Cassation only. Art. 29.—Petitions of appeal to the Courts of Appeal and Cassation are subject to the regulations governing civil procedure in respect of their cost, period, method of framing, as well as of the procedure of the case. Art. 30.—The arbitral warrant shall be binding only in respect of the parties to the dispute, and those persons who have interfered and participated in the appointment of arbitrators and their successors; it shall not affect other persons outside the case. Art. 31.^—The fee payable to the arbitrator of each of the parties is to be met by the party himself, and the fee payable to the common arbitrator is chargeable to both parties, each having to pay a half. Nevertheless, thear bitra tor s can, when giving their award, provide for the division of the fee in a ditterent proportion, unless the parties have already agreed speciallv with regard to the payment of the fee payable to the arbitrators. A rt 32.—In case no specific arrangement has been made between the arbitrator and one or both parties to the dispute, the fees payable to arbitrators shall be on the following basis :~— 5 per cent, for all arbitrators of the amount of claims up to 100,000 rials. , ^P^cent. for all arbitrators of the amount of claims from 100,001 rials to 200,000 rials. K jp^: cent, for all arbitrators of the amount of claims from 200,001 rials to 500,000 rials. 2 per cent, for all arbitrators of the amount of claims from 500 000 rials upwards. The fees payable to arbitrators according to specific agreement between such arbitrators and the parties to the dispute shall be distributed between the arbitrators on that basis, and, if according to the scale laid down above, the lees collected shall be distributed between them equally. t A Tl' i r T S P eCt i&gt; 0 i P lail ? s wlllc h h ave been submitted to arbitration under the Arbitral Law of Esfand 1306 and its amendments, should the arbitral term have expired m accordance with those laws after the present law has come into torce and the arbitrators not having issued their award, should the disputing parties not agree to the renewal or prolongation of the arbitral term, the terms of this present law shall be applied. A rt 34. In respect of claims which one of the disputing parties has previously requested the court to submit to arbitration, and on which no iudsrment has been issued by the court on the date of approval of this law if all the arbitrators, as provided in the Law of the 29th Esfand, 1306, have not yet been appointed, or if they have not yet been called, the request shall be considered as null, and action shall be taken in accordance with this present law. d.rt. 35 Regarding claims on which the first arbitrators have issued their award in accordance with the Arbitral Law of 1306, and at the request of one of the parties or both the matter has been submitted to arbitrators charged with reviewing the case, if such arbitrators have not yet expressed their view in respect or the case, these arbitrators shall be enjoined to issue and announce their award within a period of two months from the date of approval of this law; otherwise each of the parties can, within ten days from the date of expiration of the said period, submit a petition of appeal to the Court of Appeal against the award issued by the arbitrators. In such circumstances, the arbitral fee payable to the first arbitrators shall be collected and distributed after the issue of judgment by the Court of Appeal in accordance with article 12 of the Arbitral Law of Esfand, 1306. ’ Art. 36.—The following claims cannot be submitted to arbitration :— (1) Claims in respect of suspension of payments and bankruptcy. (2) Claims in respect of marriage, divorce, cancellation of marriage consequent time allowance and lineage. A rt. 37. In respect of a dispute between wife and husband regarding maltreatment, non-submission, sustenance, clothing, dwelling and also the expenses of a child on the charge of the husband but under the protection of the wife, should either of the parties raise a complaint, the courts can, at the request ot either party, submit the case to arbitration and, in' the event of their not agreeing to the selection of arbitrator, appoint at least two men from among the relatives of both parties, or, if they have no relatives at their place of residence, from among persons who have friendship and acquaintance with them. The arbitrators thus appointed are enjoined to try their best to reconcile the husband and the wife and, in the event of failure, to give their opinion to the court, distinguishing the rightful party and indicating the amount of expense of the wife or the child,^ in case the claim refers to expense; the court shall, after receiving the arbitral award, issue its judgment accordingly. In case no concurrence of view is reached between the arbitrators (if votes are even), they can agree to the appointment of a man as the third arbitrator, and if no compromise is reached in this respect they can appoint another by lot, and the majority votes shall be binding. J0 The court must, while selecting the arbitrators, see that they are qualified as '^Ead! of'the f^tieThlvmg any complaint against the award issued by the arbitrators can submit his or\er'complaint to the court within a period of one month from the date of service of the award, and if the court accepts the complaint it shall itself treat the case and issue its judgment. This judgment shall be appealable onlv in the Court of Appeal. The court to be applied to in respect of the above-mentioned claims is the Primary Court In cases where no primary court exists such claims can be submitted to the Justice of the Peace, and in places where no Justice of the Peace exists to officials attending to petty charges! ^ _ Thig law shall come into force after promulgation, and the Arbitral Law of the 29th Esfand, 1306, and the law amending the Arbitral Law, dated the 11th Farvardin, 1308, shall then be repealed ; articles 757 to 779 of the Code of Civil Procedure, which had been repealed by virtue of the Law ot Lstand, 1306, shall so remain. This law, consisting of thirty-eight articles, was passed by the Majlis in its session of the 28th Bahman, 1313. D AI)G A R President of the Majlis.!V 3488/S438/34) r yOREISN OFFICE, S.W.l. 89th June, 1935. &lt;411 ; Sir 9 I am directed by Secretary sir Samuel Hoare to transmit to you, to be laid before the Board of Trade, the aacompaaying copy of a despatch from His Majesty's Minister at Tehran enclosing the text of a neu Persian Law of Arbitration, ^ • I am to enquire wbetUer the Board have any observations to make on the new law from the point of view of whether its provisions are such as to enable Persia to become a party to the Geneva protocol of 1923 on Arbitration Clauses and to the Geneva Convention of 1927 on the execution of Arbitral Awards, 3* Copies of this letter are being sent to the India Office, Colonial Office, cojainions Office and Department of Overseas Trade* I am, etc*, (Signed) o*w, Rendel The Secretary to the Board of Trade,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001b0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/157</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001b0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/157</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 4604/35 'Persian Law of Arbitration'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-27T10:45:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 1, and terminates at f 6, it is the second file in a larger physical volume, each file has its own foliation sequence; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns a new Persian Law of Arbitration passed by the Majlis in its session of 17 February 1935. It consists of correspondence sent to the Board of Trade by George William Rendel, Head of the Eastern Department, Foreign Office, and a despatch from Hughe Montgomery Knatchbull-Hugessen, HM Minister at Tehran, enclosing a translation of the law.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Eastern Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Law</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arbitration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001b0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>