<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000262_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:34:11.427Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">B. 240. This Documod is the property of the Secretary of State for India. SECRET. P. 3501/JC. T1 le Economic Situation in the Persian Gulf and Mesopotamian Markets. From the Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.S.L, K.C.I.E., Chief Political Officer, Indian Expeditionary Force D,' Basra, to the Honourable Mr. A. H. Grant, C.S.I., C.I.E., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. No. 0510. • Chief Political Office, Basra, Sir, • 18th-24th July 1916. In my recent reports to General Ileadquarters, Indian Expeditionary Force 'D,' regarding the working of the Judicial. Revenue, and Mis cellaneous Departments of the Civil Administration of the Occupied Territories, of which copies have reached Foreign Department, it may have been observed that no mention was made of any Commercial Department; and in fact I have at present on my staff at Basra no officer whose experience qualifies him to study and advise upon the important commercial questions which will arise in the very near future. It was primarily with the object of making preliminary enquiries in this direction that I asked for and obtained the temporary loan of the services of Captain G. Lloyd, M.P., 1st Warwick shire Yeomanry, from Egypt, where he had been doing duty under the Director of Military Intelligence ; and I attach an interesting and timely note from him bearing upon the subject of trade conditions here. Captain Lloyd, it will be remembered, was the author of a valuable report on British trade in Mesopotamia in 1908. 2. Whilst our whole energies should be and are for the present devoted to the prosecution of the war, it nevertheless seems to me to be of great importance that we should set to work whilst we may to collect material before the conclusion of the war on which deliberate judgments can be formed in regard to various questions afTecting these territories. This is all the more the case, inasmuch as certain political or diplomatic questions, which are likely to arise for discussion at the close of the present hostilities, depend for their satisfactory solution upon an accurate and up-to-date appreciation of economic needs in Iraq, Central Persia, and the Persian Gulf. Conditions have greatly changed since the commercial (including the agricultural and productive) potentialities of this country were last deliberately considered ; and we now have to look at the question from a point of view which differs widely from that which we adopted before the 'war. 3. The aim of such enquiry would be :— (a) To put His • Majesty's Government within the next few months in possession of a report which would have some claim to be authoritative, so far as our existing knowledge makes this possible, upon certain economical aspects of these territories. (h) To prepare data for the elaboration of a definite commercial policy, to be brought into force, by administrative and legislative means, on the declaration of peace—no action being taken until then which will in any way prejudice our ultimate policy. (c) To examine the information already collected as to the best avenues for railway penetration in the areas in question, and the present possibility of converting this general information into exact knowledge by the undertaking of engineering surveys, .s 327 40—10/16 A4. Amongst the many problems that await consideration and investiga tion I will mention three or four only :— (i) Cnrreuey. —The best method of establishing rupee currency through Southern Persia in order to strengthen Britsh and British-Indian trade which is greatly hampered at present by the chaotic currency conditions prevailing in South West Persia. The best method of establishing currency on a sound basis in Iraq ; and banking facilities at Basra and other ports. (ii) (a) Exports. —The potentialities of Iraq as a grain producing country and the possibility of making it an important contributor to Imperial wheat supplies, in view of our present undue dependence upon extra-Imperial sources. (6) The potentialities of the country, at least in its southern naturally irrigated areas, in regard to the growth of cotton for the supply of Bombay and Manchester. (iii) Imports. —The best means of inducing British merchants to cater adequately for this market, so as to maintain its predominantly British character ; elaboration of legislative and administrative measures .with this object; revision of present 10 per cent. ad valorem tariff. (iv) Shipping. —Question of regular transhipment service ; special rules for certain class of cargoes ; port and light dues ; handling of cargoes; through rates; relations with Continental ports ; possible competition from Far Eastern ports. 5. If these questions are to receive adequate and continuous attention, two appointments are, 1 think, necessary ad hoc:— (I) Temporary, for from three to six months during the cold weather, of aii acknowledged expert in commercial matters with mature practical experience, whose considered views would carry weight both with Government and with the commercial community. He might be designated Director oi; Trade Development. His function would be to start enquiries on the right lines and to give the necessary inspiration to this new development which, particularly as regards the commercial community, must depend in no small degree for its success on the spirit in which it is initiated. (2} Permanent. A junior officer (of the type of Mr. H. G. Chick, C.I.E.) qualified to act as Commercial Adviser in these territories, to be appointed simultaneously with the Director of Trade Development, so as to act as his Assistant and to carry on after his departure. His function then would be to keep in close touch with the commercial community here, in England (through the Board of Trade) and in India (through the Department of Commerce and Industry); to furnish information and statistics; to report the trend of foreign trade ; and to propose measures in advance to promote British trade interests. G. I am somewhat diffident in suggesting to Government the name of any particular individual for the post of Director of Trade Development, but my conception of the requirements of the post leads me to suggest that the Honourable Mr. M. deP. Webb, C.LE., of Karachi be invited to undertake the duty. I feel sure that the enthusiasm and expert knowledge that he would bring to bear on the problems at issue, and his reputation as an expert upon commercial and currency questions, would prove invaluable, and that all parties would be greatly the gainers by his deputation. In any case it would appear to be indispensable that the appointment should only be given to one fully conversant with the complex systems of continental trade shipping and tariff questions, and in consequence a Consular official of the ordinary stamp would be of no use for the work in view. 7. For the post of. Commercial Adviser I should have been glad to have been able to utilise the services of Mr. H. G. Chick, C.I.E., now employed at Bush ire as His Majesty's Vice-Consul and Commercial Adviser to thePolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. His tastes and bent, however, do not lie in this direction, but rather towards Southern Persia, and for the moment it would be inconvenient to spare him from his duties there. 1 am inclined to think that the latter post could be filled by the appoint ment of a suitable junior officer to be nominated by the Board of Trade, who would be well remunerated, say TOOL a year with free house and adequate clerical assistance. 8. 1 am convinced that the expenditure entailed by the above appoint ments is not merely justified but demanded on Imperial grounds. Our position here has suffered most seriously in the past from failure to take timely and specific steps to meet the politico-commercial activities of our commercial rivals, from the adoption of a laissez-faire policy, and from a multiplicity of advisers ; and unless these questions can be considered here and now by an expert whose considered views will carry full weight in the counsels of Government, I greatly fear that peace negotiations or the conclusion of the War will find us as little prepared to face the problems of peace as we were in 1914 to face those of war. In order to facilitate discussion of this question by telegraph I have ventured to send a copy of this despatch with enclosures to the Secretary of State for India. 1 have not had an opportunity of obtaining Army Commander's con currence to the terms of this communication, as he is absent up-river, but a copy has been sent him and I have little doubt that he will be in agreement with the suggestions which 1 have put forward. I have, c'tc., P. Z. Cox, Lieutenant-Colonel, Chief Political Officer, The Honourable A. H. Grant, C.S.I., C.LE. l.E.F. ' D,' Basra.4 Notes on Economic Situation in Gult and Mesopotamian Markets, by Captain George Lloyd, M.P. i. - . * ' k 1. The strategical and naval necessity of maintaining a predominant position in the Persian Gulf as well as in Central Persia is founded on such decisive declarations on the part of His Majesty's Government at various times that it may be taken as axiomatic. It has also been an accepted doctrine that this position must depend mainly upon the retention of a preponderance of British trade in these areas, and that in proportion as Russian or German influence extends into Persia and the Gulf, so will their pretensions to a greater share of territorial and political influence become more firmly established. 2. But this doctrine in recent years has not been supported by a policy active enough to maintain it. It has, it is true, suffered politically as lar as Persia is concerned by its inevitable subordination to more urgent diplomatic needs such as the Anglo-Russian agreement of 1907, but it has also suffered commercially throughout the area by an indecision which neither the unsettled state of Southern Persia nor the struggles with Germany over the Baghdad railway more than partially explain. 3. The temporary elision of Germany from the Gulf, and the certainty that before long new spheres of influence as between Russia and ourselves in Persia must be negotiated, makes the moment one in which, however great our other preoccupations, the economic position of Great Britain in the Gulf and Persia must be resummarised, and such practical and prompt attention paid to it that we shall be ready at the moment of negotiation to pursue a policy in conformity with both our political and economic needy. 4. It is dangerous and may be fatal to continue in partial recognition of the dangers, and in total indecision as to the remedies. 5. Look where you will into the position of British trade in the Persian Gulf and in Central Persia, the evidence points unmistakably to the decay, and the rapid decay, of our trade, and to the serious inroads which have been made in an incredibly short space of time into both our export and import trade, inroads so continuous and severe that nothing but a studied and energetic policy, backed up to the full by the power of the Government, will suffice to check. G. Especially disquieting is it to observe that these inroads have been made and the attacks concentrated latterly, not merely upon the subsidiary trades in which British energies were occupied, but upon those staple industries, shipping, Manchester goods, iron and steel, &amp;c., which were regarded as the impregnable fortresses of our trade position. So long as nine years ago when German competition was but in its infancy in these areas the writer warned the Government, in an official report 1 on trade conditions in the Gulf, that the easy confidence of the British merchant as to the inviolability of these trades was unjustified and pointed out that the subsidiary trades, which the Germans were then engaged in capturing and which were considered as of no importance in view of the strong staple trade position still held by Great Britain, were merely the necessary wedge by virtue of which they would before long split apart the solidarity and monopoly of British trade in its more valuable forms. 7. It must not be thought that it is suggested here that the Home Government have ignored the position or have had no moments of uneasiness in regard thereto; still less that those in charge of British interests in the Gulf have failed to put the position very clearly before them; for locally, at 1 Cf. ' Report upon the Conditions and Prospects of British Trade in Mesopotamia.'— Board of Trade, 1908.all events, everything possible lias been done to record and acquaint the Government of India and the Foreign Office with what was going on. Plain evidences of the Government's uneasiness may be seen, for instance, in the negotiations between the Foreign Office and the Persian Government in regard to the southern trade routes, culminating at one period in a threat to take British measures to safeguard the trade routes themselves; but the fear of committing themselves to new responsibilities in Southern Persia, fears which Russia in the north showed no signs of being incommoded by, seem to have obscured the vision of the Home Government to the greater'danger that confronted them in the loss of their economic position in the Gulf. COMMUNICATIONS. 8. Inasmuch as the primary essential for our trade, vis a vis Russia in Persia, or Germany in the Gulf, is the provision of good land and sea com munications, it is pertinent to examine the position in which British trade finds itself to-day in regard to shipping, railways and roads. 9. Up till 1906 British shipping had a practical monopoly of all trade entering and leaving Gulf ports. 1 10. In 1906. however, the Ham burg-America line started a service of steamers to the Gulf, and in spite of initial losses maintained their services, so that in four years they had increased their import trade by 100 per cent. From that time onwards, working in close co-operation with the German firm of W onckhaus, established at various points in the Gulf, their success has been phenomenal. 11. British shipping lines, who commenced by being scornful, became alarmed when they realised that the German company had come to the Gulf to stay; and British merchants, who at first had seen in the competition of the Hamburg-America a silver lining to the cloud of previous high freights, soon began to realise that the Hamburg-America line had not come there in order to serve the interests of old-established British houses, but rather to carry German goods with which to out-trade the British merchants in all the Gulf markets. 12. In the short space of ten years they have succeeded in wresting practically the whole of the sugar traffic, formerly exclusively in British hands, from the British lines, and in making very serious inroads into much of the general traffic formerly emanating from Great Britain and bow coming from Antwerp or Hamburg. 13. Perhaps the shortest and most convincing evidence as to the hold which the Hamburg-America line had acquired in the first ten years of its competition will be shown in the nature of agreement come to between the conference of British lines (which in itself was formed to oppose the German line) and the Board of the Hamburg-America, recently before the com mencement of the war. The agreement provided two main things (a) an agreement of freight rates from Europe to the Gulf, and (b) an agreement that the British lines should not load at Hamburg or Antwerp, on condition that the German line should not load at English ports. These terms were fatal terms for the British lines to accept, and information goes to shuw that the terms were practically dictated to them as to a beaten enemy. The significance of this fact will only be fully recognised when it is seen that the German line found themselves in a position to dictate terms to a conference of British lines composed of no less important lines than the British India line, holding the largest mercantile tonnage in the world, and of lines under the control of men like Sir John Ellerman and others. 1 -there was, it is true, a Russian line which had a nominal monthly service to the Gulf, but it was in no sense competiti\e as regards liritish trade, and was moreover not very successful in its own trade, in the date season a few non-British ships under special American or other charter called at iiasra ; but apart from this it may be said that all British goods entering or leaving Gulf Ports were carried in British bottoms. S 327 B14. It is important also to recognise the nature of the terms imposed, for at first sight the terms agreed to scarcely seem to warrant their being described as fatal. In any case Lord Inchcape did not fail to grasp the nature of the agreement he was entering into or its serious natuie, for in a letter he wrote to the India Office on 29th December 1913, he stated that— ' It has been an impossibility for British shipowners to compete success fully with the Hamburg-America line, subsidised as that Company is, either directly or indirectly, by the German Government, and the British shipowners have been obliged to come to terms with the Hamburg-America line, and to agree rates of freight, and also to give up directly loading from Hamburg and Antwerp. . . . If the British lines had not come to terms with the Hamburg-America line it would have been impossible for them to maintain a position in the trade. Prior to 190V the shipping trade in the Persian Gulf was practically exclusively in British hands. Sugar export trade to the Gulf was then almost entirely for Marseilles and was served by British lines. The advent of the Hamburg-America brought the German sugar manufacturers into competition with the Irench lelineiies, and the former are gradually monopolising the trade. ' 1 am a little nervous about what may happen when the Baghdad railway is completed. We may find an attempt on the part of the Germans to oust British vessels from the trade from Basra to India, but we have had this well in view, and have been preparing for it by laying out a very large amount of capital in improvement and up-to-date vessels, which, 'l hope, will be able to hold their own against any legitimate German competition ; hut, of course, if the German Govern ment are determined to force their way into the trade with India by means of subsidies, it may go hard with the British lines.' 15. As it may quite confidently be assumed that the Germans both did and do intend to continue their operations against us by means of ' subsidies,' it is clear that Lord Inchcape's anxieties are not confined only to the European-Gulf trade, but that he also fears that they may in the future take a highly dangerous interest in the Indo-Gulf trade. 1G. It is remarkable also that Lord Inchcape's pessimism in regard to the success German methods have had in the Gulf is fully shared by local merchants and traders in Iraq. The traders who nine years ago were full of an unjustified but an easy confidence as to the impregnability of their position in Persian, Turkish, and Gulf markets, are now the first to admit that at the outbreak of war they were something like a beaten body, and in a very short time would have to take second place to the Germans. They still, however, refuse to look the facts squarely in the face, and say that they cannot be expected to fight successfully against German 'subsidies.' Without attempting to define what they mean by ' subsidies,' they merely look upon them as an unfair weapon of economic warfare, something like gas in trench warfare—as a hit below the belt, with which no fighter, however skilled, can be expected to deal. It is, therefore, important to make them realise that it is nothing of the kind, and the mere fact that the Germans have in some areas used their organised system to shroud dishonest methods is no ground for not accepting ' subsidies ' as a perfectly fair and recognised system of modern commercial warfare. 17. It may well be asked what were the powerful methods »by which a single line like the Hamburg-America line were able, after a bare 10 years in the Gulf, to make Lord Inchcape write in this strain. The usual reply of 44 German subsidies' is no sufficient answer, for the French Government have for many years heavily subsidised the Messageries Maritimes line to Australia, and yet British lines have made perfectly successful headway against them. The German line, too, was peculiarly handicapped in the Gulf trade. It was fortified by no large Manchester freight contracts. The British lines had this adantage. It had no share in the large Marseilles7 sugar carrying trade. The British lines had it, all. Tt had no carrying trade between India and the Gulf. The British lines had it all. Its passenger traffic was insignificant. The British passenger traffic was considerable, and included a highly profitable pilgrim traffic. Its mail contract, if it existed at all, was small. That of the British India was substantial. The political and commercial atmosphere of the Gulf was hostile to it, but was entirely favourable to British lines. It had no inland communications to assist its trade penetration, whilst in British hands lay the foreign monopoly not only of the Tigris and Karuu river traffic, but the organisation and virtual control of all trade roads from the Gulf inland. IS. The pressure that a line so adversely situated must have been able to exert to counterbalance all these handicaps, and to dictate any terms at all to so powerful a British group, must have been very considerable, and it was so. 10. That the pressure was exerted by means of 'subsidies'' is in a sense true, but the term is far too loose to indicate the methods employed. The power was derived from State organisation of production and transit working in harmony, and in this particular connection was derived from the employ of what is known as the ' through rate system.' The importance of understanding the system which has been used to forge a way for German products and German shipping all over the world is so great as to warrant its re-statement in ]?rief in this paper. 20. During the early years of the invasion ol' any area a direct subsidy is given by the German Government to the German line sufficient to enable the line to cut rates and underquote its competitors throughout the area. The low rate is designed chiefly to attract traffic away from the competing lines, but also to make possible the rapid and systematic flooding of the invaded markets with cheap German goods. The line works in partnership with a trading house established in the invaded area, who arranges for the distribution and sale of its cargoes, which come out unconsigned, and collects exports under cover of the low rate for return freight. 21. But these early preliminaries are really directed to one object and one object alone, which is to persuade the competing lines to enter into a rate agreement with them. The German system is so framed that, once this is effected, there is every prospect of the Germans becoming masters of the trade position within a short time. 22. As soon, then, as the competing lines have agreed not to carry goods to the area under a fixed figure, the German direct subsidy is replaced by an indirect subsidy system which is of general application to all German export ;&gt; y trade, and which (contrary to the academic views held by some in regard to State subsidies) may, but also may not, involve even any initial loss to the State. This system, known as the 'through rate system,' is designed to enable shipping companies already in rate agreement with their competitors ostensibly to observe their engagements towards the foreigner, but, in practice, to underquote them whenever it may suit them to do so. In the task of capturing a new market, when the formation of a clientele and volume of trade done has temporarily more importance than the earning of large profits, the freedom to underquote and take a smaller profit than their rivals, in order to supplant their trade, is all important. As will bo seen subsequently, the higher the rate agreed to as the minimum the more smoothly does the system operate for the Germans, and the more rapidly is their rival ousted. 23. The system works as follows, and is the outcome of scientific organization of land and sea transit. For the sake of example let us suppose the case of the carriage of goods from an inland town in Germany on the one hand, and from an inland town in England on the other to a common inland port in Turkey.A German line has agreed with its British rivals not to quote less than 406*. per ton from any port in Germany, and the British line has entered into a similar agreement in regard to British ports to Basra. Let ns suppose that a Birmingham manufacturer wishes to send a ton of goods to Baghdad. He is quoted, say, 105. a ton from Birmingham to Manchester or Liverpool, he must pay the agreed rate of 405. for sea freight from Manchester or Liverpool to Basra, and he is quoted IO5. for the carriage of the goods from the port of Basra to Baghdad, giving him a through rate of GOs. plus port and landing charges. The British exporter cannot, however, get a through rate quoted him as from Birmingham to Baghdad, and is dependent upon the fluctuations of the land rate at either end. The German manufacturer at Essen, however, who wishes equally to send a ton of goods to Baghdad will, by applying to the rail authorities at Essen, be quoted an inclusive rate from Essen to Baghdad. The rate quoted him will be sufficiently below the lowest rate available to the British exporter to enable him to undersell his rival in the market of destination, which we will suppose to be 55s. as against the British 60s. The 5.9. loss, if there be a loss, by the interworking of the state railways and the shipping company is apportioned to that part of the transit which can carry it without loss ; or, in the rare case where both the railway and the shipping company are working at too fine a margin to allow of the 5s. to be carried without loss, the loss is divided between the two. In the latter case the shipping company will in effect be carrying the goods for 37^'. 6r7., and under quoting their agreement to that extent. But this fact will never become apparent, for the published rate from Hamburg to Basrah is given as 40s.; or, if suspected, can never be brought home, as it is always open to the company to say that the railway company lowered their rate from Essen to Hamburg by 5s. ; and unless the apportionment in every case of the share of the through rate as between the line, the railway and the transport company between Basrah and Bagdad can be proved, which it cannot be, the British line lays itself open to be underquoted in its agreement without hope of remedy. The main advantages to Germany of which are that— (a) She is enabled at will to underquote her rivals, and therefore capture, the trade without fear of reprisals. (b) Whereas a rate agreement is usually operative for four or live years, and is made irrespective of questions vital to the exporter, viz., fluctuating cost of materials and demand for goods, it is entirely to the advantage of the German exporter (and thus the shipping line also) that his rate should be flexible, while that of his competitor is fixed. (c) If and when the German line can conclude a similar arrangement with the land transport company at the port of discharge, and get them to tie the hands of the competing land transport company by a rate agreement, the loss, if any, over the whole transport can be still further spread. It must be repeated here, however, that, inasmuch as a rate agreement is made with the object of eliminating outside competition, it follows that the parties have a monopoly of traffic within the scope of the agreement. There fore there is every probability that the agreed rate allows for a handsome margin of profit. This enables the Germans, when they underquote in the manner indicated above, not only to do so without any loss at all but at a profit, but also to take the traffic away from those with whom the}^ have agreed rates. 24. The above system explains why the agreement come to between the British lines and the German in the Gulf was described as a ' fatal' one. 25, Not less innocent at first sight would appear to be the agreement come to not to load at Hamburg and Antwerp, in return for a similar agreement on the part of the Germans not to load at British ports. But here again the special circumstances of the case must be taken into con sideration. The German line made no sacrifice in this part of the agreement9 commensurate with the sacrifice mads by the British lines. For the British lines had got contracts of considerable duration for the carriage of the vast majority of the shipments of Manchester goods to the Gulf, contracts which the Hamburg-America could not disturb, and for whose ultimate expiry they probably could not afford to wait. But, on the other hand, the port of Antwerp had provided for a long time a rich source of freights for the British lines, with which the Germans had only recently begun to compete. And the loss of this field was an immense sacrifice for the British lin^s to make. 26. But here again to a small degree the German ' through rate system ' is called into play to circumvent the agreement come to between it and its victim. Where an agreement is come to not to load from a British port on the part of the Hamburg-America, British cargo is obtained from British ports in the following manner. The London merchant is offered through terms from London to Basra by the agent of a line allied to the Hamburg- America, and ships of that line collect cargo in the port of London, transport it to Hamburg or Antwerp for shipment in the Hamburg-America line steamers to Basra. All that happens is that the line carrying the goods between the port of London and Hamburg or Antwerp takes the place in the system of the German State railway. The London merchant will benefit, it is true, by getting the lower rate of freight, but he is really assisting at his own funeral in supporting the system contrived for the replacement of his commodities by those of German origin. 27. It will thus be seen that the 'through rate system,' worked in conjunction with rate agreements, is the chief weapon of the German competitive policy, and it follows that in consequence every effort ought to be concentrated in refusing to make rate agreements with German lines, and in this way to prevent to a certain degree full operation of the ' through rate system against us. But there is some evidence that the Government do not seem to realise the nature of the German system, its danger, or even its existence, for in a Foreign Office memorandum dated 5th July 1913 the whole 'through rate ' principle is at once conceded to Germany as if it were a concession of small, if of any, importance. The memorandum runs as follows :— 'Herr von Kiihlmann called on the 3rd July, to say that he had had a letter from Herr Ballin of the Hamburg-America line to the effect that, though he did not like the idea of a monopoly on the Tigris, he personally would not oppose it in Germany if one of the following alternatives were conceded ' (a) Xo through rates to be quoted by the British India Company or any other company from Europe to Baghdad by water. ' yh) If such rates are quoted Hamburg-America line must have the right to quote on terms as favourable as any other company, British or foreign.'' It will here be observed that the Germans attach the very greatest importance to the power of through rate quotation, and were prepared to make considerable concessions to prevent our imitating their example. In spite of this obvious feature, the memorandum goes on to say :— ' I said that if importance were attached to this, it might be well for the German Government to say so in their reply to us and then they would get a written answer. Herr von Kuhlmann said that he was going to meet Herr Ballin in a day or two on the Emperor's yacht, and as Herr Ballin would be able to say a good deal to influence the Emperor, it was very desirable that Herr von Kuhlmann should be in a position now to state definitely what was proposed. I said the declaration to be made by Turkey did not contain any express stipu lation on this point, but under our draft agreement with Germany, article 7, unfair discrimination on the river was ruled out and I felt sure he might rest easy and that the wishes of Herr Ballin would be met' S 327 r10 28. It will thus ])8 seen that the all-important through rate question is here easily conceded to the Germans in one short interview. It is of course possible that all-compelling circumstances, of which there is no indication in the correspondence, made this concession inevitable ; but the circumstances described in the Memorandum quoted above establish the fact that the Germans attribute the greatest possible importance to the question of through rates. Wvlvn.'a [ b M SAA-' ^VK V L ■ \ qpoT - V ^ &gt;6 &gt;1 '' 11 1^15. H Wjy ' 0 Svux^a^l &lt;ivv4 29. The German line set to work immediately to seize the sugar carrying- trade from the British lines, in whose hands, previous to its intrusion into the Gulf, it had exclusively been, and who were the holders of all the Marseilles sugar freight contracts. 30. The diagrams that follow refer to the Persian ports alone and do not refer to the Basra and Bagdad trade. If figures had been available for the Port of Basra, the most important port in the Gulf, the comparative position of Great Britain and Germany would have been shown far more clearly and unfavourably to British trade as against German. ± H o g. &gt; &amp; \ q io-n »yi i 'u i. -v?i i a o o q I 1 S 0 o t \ O Ci 0 t 0 b 0 ORv^vox. t O G O Ci q b o o It wU be oWwd that the process of seizure worked rapidly, and that whilst m lJ0i5 the British carrying trade (represented by the'imports of India, the United Kingdom, and France) totalled some 2,925 tons, as aeainst the Germau (represented by the imports of Germany and Austria) 1,950 tons, five years later m 1913 the British tonnage had only increased by some 650 tons whilst the German had increased by 4,550 tons. Already in five years the Germaiis were carrying more of this class of sugar to the Gulf than'were the Britifh lines, although five years previously the British lines were canying 1,000 tons more than the Germans. If figures for the previous years were available the results would be shown in an even more indicative manner. 31. In the import of loaf sugar, previously also a monopoly of the British lines, the same story is told, and told even more convincingly.11 L he following diagram deals with the same period and with the same area. Import oj- Loo^f Sugar. Torxs iqo'g-oq ■10 iqio-u iqu-iz ,32. Here the carrying trade of British lines as against the Gf-rnian line is represented as follows : --British by France, the United Kingdom, and India ; German bv Belgium, Austria, and Germany. 1 l . , u N.B.—Belgium is included as German tonnage, lirstly, because it is all shipped from Antwerp, a port denied to British ships under the rate arTeement previously referred to, and secondly, because evidence goes to show that the Raffinerie Tirlemontoise, whence the sugar originates, is m working agreement with, if not actually owned by, Geiman capital. 33. The diagram shows that, whereas in 1908 British ships carried an wuiici *»wxvic. tonnage . - , while the German in the same time increased by LU,4oU tons.12 34. Two things must be reinembsred, firstly, the rapidity with which the Germans captured the trade—in a space oi live years only, and secondly, that the slight recovery of the United Kingdom tonnage during the last two years was solely due to the repeated appeals of His Majesty's Resident in the Gulf, through whose instance pressure was brought to bear upon Messrs. Tate to re-enter this field. Whether the firm in question can be persuaded to persevere in its attempts in face of the situation remains to be seen. 35. As to the serious effects which the loss of the sugar trade must have upon British lines, Mr. Chick (Commercial Adviser in Gulf) has pointed out that, out of a total 75,512 packages carried to Bushire by British lines in 1911, no less than 40,900 were of Marseilles sugar. 36. The sugar trade has been selected as an example of the inroads made upon British sea-borne traffic to the Gulf ports themselves. When, however, the enquirer wishes to examine the conditions of foreign trade in Iraq and Turkish Arabia, and its important Persian transit trade, he is handicapped by the absolute lack of any official information on the subject. Turkish customs statistics are too inaccurate to be of any value, and British Consular reports in Basra are so scanty in their information, and so ill drawn up, that they have no practical value of any kind. Comparative statistics as between Britain and her competitors, which from a State point of view are the most important form of information, are not given at all, and German competition, which has been the one subject of interest and discussion among the local trading community for the last 10 years, has not a dozen lines devoted it throughout the period. We can therefore only fall back upon a general description embodying the unanimous view of all the traders concerned. 37. Such opinion would confirm the existence of an active and successful competition on the part of Germany in Iraq. The Germans became masters of general trade, except Manchester traffic and special Indian imports. In all the various articles of import such as glass, stationery, drugs, hosiery, hardware, t^c., German imports rapidly ousted British trade, in addition to the important sugar trade. Whilst the latter only represents an import value of some 450,000/., as against a Manchester cotton trade of some 1,200,000Z., it is probable that the sugar trade added to the general trade would show a total import trade not greatly inferior to the total British import trade, exclusive of India. This is remarkable enough in view of the s hort time in which German traders have been in this field. 38. But the rapidity with which they have attacked the export trade is far more remarkable. It is a matter of regret that the British Consul here should have neglected to obtain information to demonstrate statistically the well-known occurrences of the last ten years in this matter, for the informa tion was easily to be obtained from year to year. 39. Only in the last report available of 1912 does he show the amounts of grain shipped to London and Hamburg respectively, and their figures show that 80,000 tons of grain were shipped by the Germans to Hamburg and Antwerp, against 90,000 tons to England. This was in 1911, only five years after the beginning of German operations, and British merchants complain bitterly of the loss of this trade to the Germans. They state that the Germans did the trade at a loss, and give the usual reply about ' subsidies '; but there is more evidence to show (and the Commercial Adviser in the Gulf agrees with me on the point) that this was not generally the case, and that the Germans were able to take the trade away from British firms and still make a profit. British firms work on a double margin of profit, leaving a London margin and a local margin, thereby handicapping themselves in quotation to a great degree. 40. In import and export trade then, in Mesopotamia as in the Gulf, the Germans had seized a large share of trade hitherto exclusively British. This was not, however, the limit of their activities, for quite apart from the13 commencement of the Baghdad Railway they were attempting and were succeeding in capturing the river-carrying trade that had been a British monopoly up the Karun River, and which was the link between sea and land on the important caravan road known as the Lynch road into Persia. Briefly, the activities of the Germans in the past few years have had the result of ruining and jeopardising our position not only in the Persian Gulf, but in Mesopotamia and the river waterways that are the centres for British Central Persian trade. 41. We may now turn and examine what was happening to British trade during the same period in Persia itself. Economic Position in Persia. 42. So far the general aspects of British and German competition in the Persian Gulf only have been reviewed, we may now turn to a similar review of the position in southern and central Persia. 43. Just as British trade in Iraq and in Gulf Ports depends upon the maintenance of British sea and river communications, so in southern and central Persia the permanence of our trade depends upon our ability to transport goods from the Gulf ports to the central Persian markets as rapidly and as cheaply as possible. In these markets British merchandise has to meet energetic Russian competition, and British trade has suffered in the last few years severe checks at their hands. This has been due to a series of causes, but notably to the disturbed state of the country, which has reacted with some force in the north, but with far greater severity in the south. 44. But the archives of the India Office and the Foreign Office afford ample testimony of the fact that the need for providing better land com munications for our trade has been a matter of common agreement, and was under review long before the chaos in Persia became acute, and the comparative advantages of one railway over another discussed for the last ten years if not longer. Meanwhile, in the north of Persia, Russia has slowly but steadily progressed in railways and roads, while in the south British merchandise still climbs the rugged passes of the kotals on mule or donkey back over roads ' protected ' only by the local tribesmen. 45. The long-continued official discussions and prospects for railway construction have so far resulted in no action (nor indeed has a single engineering survey been made except a section from Mohammerah toDizful), by virtue of which a decision even as to which of the alternative routes would give the most penetration power to British trade vis-a-vis our main competitor could be come to. 46. British trade recently so active, competing, in spite of geographical difficulties, so successfully with Russia as far north as Kermanshah and Ispahan, has of late years been faced with intolerable handicaps, and received no material assistance from the Government even in an area where, more than in any other, it was to the complete advantage of the Government to afford that assistance. 47. On the Bushire-Ispahan road the trade is believed to be past recovery—transport animals are only available in ever diminishing quantities, and consequently transport rates show a constant and fatal increase. The number of pack animals available, according to official returns in 1912, had diminished by 100 per cent., and in a despatch dated October 1913 forwarded by Sir Percy Cox, the position is summarised in these words :— ' If, compared with seven years ago, imports to the Ispahan Province via the Gulf are being severely restricted, and if under otherwise favourable conditions British trade is unable to check the extension of Russian trade southwards, it is due solely to the dearth of pack animals between Bushire and Ispahan and Ahwaz and Ispahan.' s 327 d14 The despatch dealt with one particular year In which this was no doubt true, but other years would have shown handicaps occasioned by raids, by illegal levies on caravans, and such causes—all going to show that the obsolete methods of transport which are now the only vehicle for British trade into Persia are rapidly killing British commerce. This accomplished, the trade will pass into eager Russian hands ; and the railways, which, if built in time, could have kept alive and doubled our trade, will then have lost their opportunity and their raison d'etre. 48. It is not the purpose of this paper to criticise, bat merely to state once again the facts, and to urge that, unless very early steps are taken to arrest the present palpable decline of our trade, it will fall into other hands from whom it will be difficult to recover it. 49. Even were surveys put in hand at once, it is highly improbable that the railway resulting could be completed before ihe lapse of at least another five or seven years, during which time the decline in British trade, which is already so evident, is likely to have increased ; and should the provision of essential communications be much further delayed the trade may have disappeared altogether. 50. Nor is it the purpose here to discuss anew the rival merits of roads versus railways; material for deciding points of this nature is already at the disposal of the Government; but rather to urge that a decision be come to speedily and action taken. 51. The following tables will be convincing enough as to the adverse trade tendency referred to, and are made up from Persian (Belgian) Customs Statistics. Manchester goods (piece goods and yarns), tea, and metallic goods are the staple imports of Great Britain and India into Persia, and in order to show the share which Russia and Great Britain are comparatively taking of these imports the following diagrams have been drawn up. 52. It would have been very desirable, and the lessons obtainable would have been more pointful, had it been possible to give a comparative review over a 20 year period ; but the fact that up till the establishment of Belgian control of Persian Customs the inaccuracy of the statistics renders them useless, has made this impossible, and figures have onl}' been given for the period since which accurate statistics are available. 50. Xo one conversant, however, with Russo-British trade of the past in Persia will deny tnat it is safe to assume that the farther you go back the greater would the preponderance of British trade over Russian, up to and including Ispahan and Kermanshah, be established ; or in other words that the comparative decline vis -cir -vis Russia of British trade is not a phenomenon of merely six years, but has been going on for a longer period, is therefore more determined, and more indicative of the deep-rooted nature of the disease. 51. The first two diagrams show the position as regards Manchester goods. ' 1:1 '''T- ^^ 0 S • 1 o iq\o.n &gt;Qn-ia. iQia.'. ^15 It will be seen— (1) 1 hat the imports from United Kingdom have steadily declined to a negligible quantity ; while @ ' n P orts starting from nil have steadily increased. [o) lat Manchester yarns have been replaced by Indian yarns. Thus while English imports on the one hand have declined from 800 tons 0 •) tons in six years, Russian imports have increased by 550 tons in the same period ; and further in spite of the steady increase of Indian imports, 1 l + jm P 01 s 0 United Kingdom and India together have only increased by 61KJ tons as against the 550 tons increase of Russia. oo. If we turn to the diagram on imports of piece goods the same tendency is to be observed in an even more marked degree. The figures show— (1) That United Kingdom and Indian imports are steady and each show a small increase. (2) But that Russian imports show a continuous and large expansion. Thus while Manchester imports have increased barely 1,500 tons and Indian by 1,250, Russian imports have increased by 6,000 tons and have actually surpassed the Manchester imports, and are only 1,000 tons less than Indian and Manchester imports combined. 5G. If this has happened in one premier industry, in a field not long ago monopolized by British products, and has, moreover, occurred in the short space of six years, then it is clear that something immediate needs to be done, if the process of decay is to be arrested and our position restored. 57. Be it observed moreover that no random selection of trades has been made, nor a studied selection designed to support a pre-conceived theory, but those trades in which we were strongest have been chosen. If such be the condition of these trades, what is likely to be the condition of those supple mentary trades for which we are not perhaps so well adapted ? 58. We may take as an example of one of the latter trades that large Eastern trade in enamelware, a product which there is no reason why we should not be able to produce as cheaply as our foreign rivals, but which has fallen everywhere largely into other hands.16 'Tans Imbort of 'bnamelooare iqos-o^j (qocj-io iCjio-n ' iq(2-'3 ICjl3' Hi- The diagram tells its own tale convincingly enongb, and it will be seen that our share of the six years' increase has been some 70 tons while that of Russia has been 440 tons. 59. According to the Persian (Belgian) Customs House statistics the imports of British (Indian) teas into Persia have actually declined while those of Russia largely increased. Thus, while Russian exports have expanded from 900 to 2,300 tons, British imports have declined from 2,300 tons to 2,000 tons, that is to say, that Russia has increased her imports by 1,400 tons while Britain has decreased hers by 300 tons. GO. The Indian tea trade, however, has not only been handicapped as against Russian by the worse land transport facilities referred to previously, but by other causes as well. While an adverse tariff checked the trade considerably, yet the smuggling genius of the native traders in Persia did something to counteract this handicap ; but it suffered its worst blow at the hands of the British India line who by its exorbitant freights between Calcutta and the Gulf strangled to a large degree its efforts as may be seen by the diagram below. c crLAt&gt; v VP-A^V-A O-wS tqn-tl. uu 1 - u i 0 Q 0 18 0 0 J ^ Oti J G O O 1*00 1 € o O I ^ 0 o t 1 O o I 0 0 0 . iQ&amp;q.to iQto -M tqn.il 1 Q Q ^ o o H 0 o O 0 i 0 o I o o &lt;^v.dua17 61. The whole question lias been fully dealt with in Captain Birdwood's Despatch, No. 468, of 14th .February 1014, to the Government of India in which he lays stress on the excessive freight rates alluded to. 1 he despatch points out that, according to Calcutta merchants, excessive British Indian freights have much to do with the diversion of trade to Russia and also that m consequence Indian tea now goes into Persia via Russia and is described as Russian tea. 02. Attention is here drawn to this example of the importance of providing better communications for our trade with southern Persia, and to the fact that, partly owing to our misuse of existing sea transit, but still more to the benefits gained by Russia by her development of railways and roads in northern Persia. In support of this I quote from the same despatch page 2, as follows :— 14 The diversion of India, Batavian and China teas from the Persian Gulf to the Black and Caspian Seas has undoubtedly been fostered by the opening of the Batonm-Baku, Batonm-Tabriz and Batoum-AIeshed routes,' after which the converse effect upon Gulf trade is described in the bad land communications from the Gulf. 63. The following table given by the Director-General of Commercial Intelligence in India oi' rates charged by various companies on the alter native routes substantiates the statements made above :— Rates for Tea. Line. Calcutta to Baghdad (for Ispahan, Kermansliah) - . British India, Es. 50s, per ton (50 cubic feet). Calcutta to Hushire - - - British India, Rs. 305. Calcutta to Batoum - - Messageries, Rs. 25. 14 per 20 cwt. Calcutta to Batoum _ _ _ Austrian Lloyd, Rs. 305. per ton (50 cubic feet). J o the first two quotations must be added the land charges. ( 261. 155. per ton. Bushire to Ispahan - - ^ 6/.—10/. per ton - ) 017 ( 151. 105. per ton - j ' ^ ' liates from Batoum to Baku by rail, to Enzeli by sea, and Enzeli to lehran &lt;.110 not known, but said to be much lower than above rates. ^ -n 'i ^ 10 rea30n ^ or ra P^ encroachment of the import via Russia ... till lately supplied almost entirely via the Persian Gulf, notwithstanding the icii gieatei distance to be travelled, is probably to be found in— (rt) high shipping freights from India to the Gulf as compared with freights from India-Batoum ; (^) high rates of transport from Gulf and Kermanshah to Ispahan.' Now the producer of Indian teas may take the view that it is immaterial to him wlucli way his tea enters Persia, provided it reaches the market and demaiul remains. ^ But from the point of view of British trade in general and 1 i itisli mlluence 111 Persia, it matters a great deal. Not only does the import via Russia of an increased tonnage assist in lowering the import cost of all goods coming from Russia, but there is also lost to British traders (a) the proiits on sea carriage, (b) the merchants' profits en route ; and, finally, it has the d^advantage of throwing Persian buyers still further into the hands or the Russian merchant for this and for other purchases as well. 65. No clearer proof could be given of the inadequacy of our trade communications from the Gulf that the fact that tea can reach Ispahan from Calcutta moi e cheaply, in spite of Canal dues and immensely increased mileage, via Suez, Constantinople and Batoum than direct to Ispahan. In the latter journey bulk is broken only twice, or at the most three times whereas via Caspian it must be landed at Batoum, at Baku, at Enzeli at Resht, and again at Tehran. s 327IS 66. The last example may be taken from the figures relating to the imports of iron, iron manufactures, steel wire, &amp;c. , Worbs of Iron, Steel wire .ok / ^ S I o g. Q q I q . t 0 t&lt;\VV-V3. I ^ V X. ^ V-. 0 C' The above shows a British increase of some 800 tons, and shows a Russian increase of some 1,800 tons. The comparative proximity of Russian iron and steel works in South Russia partly explains these ligures, as against which British products have the benefit of sea carriage to Persian ports as against the more costly land transport and bulk breakage of the Russian route. g-HA \ 0 ^ Jnvjxoliii o| ulixxAxu^ci'ciA.vieA J Km. sec o 0 q £ 1 (&gt; &amp; s s U u I 5 1 a j i i In reading the above figures the abnormal and sudden rise of British imports in 1909-10 is due probably to the importation for^ erection of Abadan oil refineries and pipe line, i he normal course oi impoits may more properly be arrived at by a curve from 1908-09 to 1913-14, and the steady decline of British imports, as shown in the diagram, is to that extent artificial or at any rate non-indicative. British imports seem to have risen slightly, but to have been completely overtaken by Russian. 67. The export trade shows almost in exactly the same way the tendencies exhibited by the import trade, and it will suffice if the diagrams are appended without comment. Attention is, however, drawn to the fact that of the main raw mateiials emanating from Persia, viz., wool, gum, hides, rice and cotton, there is scarcely an exception from the adverse tendency displayed in the general trade, and British are importing comparatively less and less year by year, while Russia imports more and more of Persian products.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000262_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B240</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000262</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B240</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'The Economic Situation in the Persian Gulf and Mesopotamian Markets. Lt-Col Sir P Z Cox, A H Grant and Cpt G Lloyd, MP, Aug 1916'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-25T00:07:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (11 folios)</extent><extent>Condition: Loose leaves in a paper folder (the folios show evidence of having previously been bound).Foliation: The file's foliation sequence commences at the first folio and terminates at a melinex sheet containing the remains of the binding; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. This is the sequence which has been used by this catalogue to reference items within the volume.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A report concerning the economic situation in the Persian Gulf and Mesopotamian markets written by Captain G. Lloyd MP. The report was commissioned by Percy Zachariah Cox in his position as Chief Political Officer of Indian Expeditionary Force "D" Basra.The report itself is preceded by an introductory letter from P. Z. Cox to A H Grant, Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. The file contains sixteen graphs related to different aspects of trade in the region.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Economic conditions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000262#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>