<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001f2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T07:22:40.319Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">' \/ INDIA OFFICE, •7HITEHALL, J.W.I. P. Z. 4532/35- 13th August 1935 Sir, With reference to the Government of India's letter of 12th June 1935, copy of which was enclosed in India Office printed letter No.P. Z.4'532/35, dated 3rd July 1935, - on the subject of the marking of the frontier 'between Koweit and iracL on Survey of India maps, I am directed by the Dated 24th Secretary of State for India to forward herewith a copy of a April 1935- I 0 ) similar letter from the Government of India in regard to the 'boundaries laid down by the Koweit-Nejd Boundary Convention of 1922- A '/ 2. It will be remembered that the Koweit-Iraq frontier as described in Memorandum No.5405 of 19th April 1923 from the High Commissioner for Iraq, to the Political Agent at Koweit, to which reference is made in the enclosure to the Government of India's letter of 12th June last, was reaffirmed by the Prime Minister of Ira^ and by the Sheikh of Koweit in 1932 before the expiry of the Iraq, Mandate and the admission of Iraq, to the League of Nations. In this connection reference is invited to the correspondence ending x with the Confidential Despatch of 23rd August 1932 from the High Commissioner for Iraq, to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, a copy of which was received by this Department under cover of Colonial Office printed letter No.98088/32, dated 8th September 1932. ^ 3. Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for/ The Under-S-eoretary of State, Foreagn Office, S. ¥. 1.2. •.i / for Foreign Affairs, the Marquess of Zetland proposes to address the Government of India in the terms of the enclosed draft letter# I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) J CLAUSON''S hks® mm ID JJUAL. , ^ ' i : POLITICAL AG3NCY, . No^C-262. . . , &gt; JrUijXjLi OA.1j iio-xliiMUl 9 i '{' h,. V\ KUV?AIT. The 27th August 1935 0 From Lt.-Colonel H.R.P.Didcson, C.I.S., Political Agent, Kuwait: To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, ft USHlRE r^o-iNCY^ Wo Date : COi'ir'D .N »•'- ^ - Sir , Marking of the frontier between Kuv;ait and Iraq on Purvey of India maps. , I have the honour to refer you to India Office / - r ^ Air Mail Printed Letter No, 4532', dated 16th August 193b, enclosing their letter P.Z.4532/35 T dated 13th August 1934 to the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 2 o From para 3 of this letter, it would appear that the Marquess of Zetland proposed to address the government of India in the terms of the enclosed draft' 1 . 2 # A copy of this 'enclosed draft' has not been sent to me, but it would appear from the context, that tne Survey of India Department have proposed that the frontier line between Kuwait and Iraq should be marked on their maps in future, and that the Marquess of Zetland intends to inform than of the ' Definition of the Iraq-Kuwait frontier' as was reaffirmed by the Iraq Government and H.S. the Shaikh of Kuwait vide my Confidential despatch Wo.129 , dated 12th /&lt;Pt5 ^ Au0istrand previous correspondence so ^hat they (the Survey of India) can work on that document. 4 # As we are now going to 'put something on the Map', I think it behoves us to get the matter done very carefully so as to avoid any chance of future argument or difference of opinion between the two States concerned®. 5 o i n this connection I have been examining the actual wording of the 'Definition of the Iraq-Kuwait frontier' l d-hfpi/. 'CS - 2 - J /I Submitted with Colonial Office Ho.P.Z,2828/32, dated 11th Lay 1932, and find that the wording is somewhat loose, and my mislead the Survey of India Department, and result in their entering on their Maps a line sli^itly differing from what we here recognize as the true frontier line, and which I believe is also understood to be such by the IraQ^ authorities# I refer to the words (a) 'and thence northwards along the Bat in to 'point just south of the latitude of 'Safwan'. (b) T,r j^ince eastwards passing south of Safwan 'wells , Jabal Sanam and Um Q,asr, leaving 'them to Iraq'. Taking 5(a) first: The Batin valley, for His Majesty's Government's information, varies in width frcm 1 to 5 miles throughout its length, and by a survey official living at a distance and not knowing the actual ground, the question might legitimately be asked how is the line 'thence northwards along the Batin' . to be placed on the raap? Does it run on the western edge, dov^n the centre, or along the eastern edge? For your info mi at ion, we here, and the Iraq authorities, I gather, have always worked on the assumption that the boundary line runs up the centre line of the valley, this being the common sense view to take of the wording of the 'Definition'. This also gives both sides an equal share of this fertile grazing valley. I suggest therefore that the Survey of India be told of this commonsense interpretation and ad/ised to draw their line accordingly. 7^ Regarding 5(b) i .Ie here have always understooc. the northern boundary of the frontier to run in a f due slast and West straight line' , from the Batin (centre line) to a point one mile South of Safwan wells (where a large Notice- 3 - b Notice Board exists on the side of the Road which today marks the actual boundary). From there, the boundary continues, also in a straight line, but in a south-easterly direction to the junction of the IQior Zubair with the Khor Abdulla. The whole line thus drawn leaves each of the points known as Jabal bamm t Safwan , and Um ^asr to Iraq, with a space of about a mile to spare. Here again I suggest that the survey of India follow our local inter pretation, when fixing their line on the map. 3, I trust I have not laboured the point overmuch, but in putting forward the above, I am guided solely by our local knowledge and existing practice, and by the fact that there is definitely ^room' for the Survey of India officials to go wrong. Were this to happen, then both Iraq and Kuwait might raise objection, and a 'bone of content ion' always to be avoided, might be opened up. 9 # I trust that my above note will be carefully considered, for it is important, I think. As I have not mentioned the matter to the Shaikh of Kuwait at all, I think, it would be just as well not to draw the Iraq Governments attention to it either. I have the honour to be, Sir , Your most obedient servant, Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.P.Z.6426/35. r\ INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 12th September 1935. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to your letters of the 24th April and the 12th June, Nos.D. 1644-IT/55, and F. 169-1:1/35 , in which it is suggested that the frontiers between Koweit and ITejd and betv/een Koweit and Iraq should be shown as undemarcated boundaries on Survey of India maps. 2. The Secretary of State, who has consulted the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in the matter, is of opinion that it is desirable for these boundaries to be shown. It is, however, important that nothing should be done which could cast any doubt on their alignment or validity. To use the symbol for undemarcated boundaries, with the addition of the word 'approximate', might give the erroneous impression that the boundaries are not clearly defined. His Lordship therefore thinks it preferable that the word 'approximate should not be used and considers that a note should be made on the maps themselves in regard to each frontier stating, in the one case, that the frontier was defined in 1923 and specifically reaffirmed by agreement between Iraq and Koweit in 1932, in the other that the frontier was defined by the Koweit-Uejd Boundary Convention of 1922. 3. I am to request that, if the Government of India see no objection, arrangements should be made accordingly. 4./ The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla.p 2. 4. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and to the Political Agent, Koweit. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, M.J.CLAUSON•Ho* 573. C* ^ British ^tabtMy f — (tyZw.LtP — g 30th October f 1955* Sir, Vitii rorcrence to your despatch Uo« 685 5626/ 127/91) of October 9th, I hare the honour to otter the following observations on the proposals put forward in the II III I 1 '. * despatch froia the Political Agent, Kuwait, No. 0-262 of I ■ ■ . II II IKli II J *•■-' '!■»*»« • ' ' • »*—tv.iH IInm 1)1 , August 27th, to the Politieal resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding the frontier between Kuwait and Iraq. 2* Colonel Mekson points out certain tuibiguities in the description of the frontier line as laid down by oir Percy Cox in his letter to the Political Agent, Kuwait, No. i 5406 of April 19th, 19&amp;5* In order to overco&amp;e the diffic- ulties which they present to the cartographer, he proposes that the line traced on the maps of the ourrey of India should follow the frontier which,he suggests, is recognised in practice in Kuwait. 5. This unilateral method of reiaoTing such uncertain ties as may exist appears to ae to be open to serious objection. I appreciate that no nap published by the Survey of India eould be held to be a binding Interpretation of tiie provisions of Sir Percy Cox's letter or of the notes exchanged between the /iuler of ^uwait kind the Prime Minister of Iraq in 1932* But, as it is proposed that the new maps should indicate that the frontier shown is that defined in 1923 and reaffirmed by m—iiiiih WI rtn.'' 1 .i 1 '' 1 . 1 '^Hi .MUjUouUlllmi the Governments of the two limitrophe countries In 1932, the Iraqi Government might, with good reason, raise objections -• . ... ■ uwew**/-'' • ■ if this frontier line were adjusted solely with regard to the local views of Kuwait. /4. The kight Honourable Sir amuel J. Q. Hoare, Bt. f OCSI. , OBa. , etc. , etc. , etc*16 If - 2 - 4. It is on record in the archives of the High Conciliation that, at the tifae when the Prime Miniater .then Kuri rasxia) wae moved by Sir Franeie Huaphrya to exehange notes with the Hitler of Kinraiit reaffirming the frontier be tween Kuwait and Iraq, he made apecial enquiries regarding He said that this the position of Halaiba in the Batin. watering place had always been regarded as being in Iraq and that police posts had betjn located there on aeveral occasions - notably in 1987. He pointed out that the description of -imr T - ' v ' •' - the frontier which he was advised to reaffirm seemed to leave this zaatter in some doubt, as zsuch would depend on how the line was drawn frws the junction of the ¥adi al Audja with the Batin, northwards to a point just south of the latitude of Safwan* The High Gommissioner reassured Furi r.-,? i-usha by emphasising that the exehange of notes was merely a reaffirmation of the status quo and that no change in the * - - • frontier line was intended or involved- He also showed nn - - »—;.eV : » ,s W» the Prime Minister the map illustrating the text of air Paragr cox's letter of April 1923 to the Political Agent, Kuwait, contained In the compilation of treaties and agree ments between the brltlBh uoverruaent and oertaln Arat rulers (edition of 19S6) published by the uovernaent of India, on which Hulalbe (or Halalba) Is clearly aariced on the lra«l ^ | | iKm 4. « V- . •-«•• Mm-'-' -ff ***' side of the frontier line. 5, I am unable to say Aether these watering holes are correctly placed on this map, but it appears that if Golonel Dickson^ proposals are adopted and the frontier line on the map of the Purvey of India is drawn along the centre of the Bat in, Hulaiba will probably be shown in Kuwait 6. Apart from the queation of Hulaiba f which I cite only as an instance of the diffioulties to which Colonel /Dickson t s• 5 ~ Dickson's proposals might giro x »iss t the position of th« frontier bstwsen Iraq and Kuvait is likely to becoiae a matter —-v,.—^nmiMniiuir II ^,,11 ■ -- . .^s,. : -. ■ t . • of increasing importance» both on account of the lapending mmi miHil'iii'n ii iftifcTW « , - 'hn-i - ■ • exploitation of oil in Kuwait and of the prerentatiye ioeasurcs which, as you are aware, the Iraqi Government are being forced to undertake to suppress aauggling across the border, I consider, therefore, that it is inadrisable that the equit able settlement of such disputes as may arise in the future regarding the alignment of the frontier should be prejudiced by the publication of official maps on which the line shown will have been drawn according to a unilateral interpretation of the international documents In which the frontier is laid down. As you are aware, the line described in Sir J^ercy ruin llllir- .1. n -'--.-v. ,..*■■. ■■■■ r .. -J. - t-,.- ■ .. -w-.-. V .• Co*'# lett«r of April 1983 to the Political Agant, Kuwait, was intended to be identical with the (Jreen line of the .inglo- 'upklah Agpeoaont of July SOth, 1913, and it appears to me desirable that this latter line should be most carefully re produced in all official maps on which the frontier between Iraq and Kuwait is shown# 3. I am informed that the Geographical Goction of the General staff will shortly issue a new map of the country adjacent to the :uwait-Iraq frontier on a scale of li500 f rxK) and I would suggest that the results of this survey might with advantage be studied by the &gt;urvey Department of India before they issue the new maps which they have under con sideration. 9. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Govern ment of India and the Political Kesident in the Persian Oulf. Z have the honour to be with the highest respect, XX* f Your most obedient, humble Servant,I '' 'i GOVEBNMENT OF INDIA. D epahtmest. EXPRESS LETTER .&gt;V. S.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent hij post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, tvith the same expedition as if it had hcen telegraphed. To save time ami formalities it is worded and signed as if it had hcen so despatched.] Z-v ' /r IH-i F rom : Political ^igent , Kuwait, ^ ^ To Political x -iesident, Bushire, BUSh:'RE RE^! n ' NCY TTTTfr. Date .....'Y 'rA' CO.iFiDENliAL REC3~33- iVo. G-351» KUWAIT DatedlZth December 19£&gt;», Kuwait-Iraq Frontier&gt; rceference your confidential printed letter ITo.934-S, dated the 5th December 1935, enclosing despatch No.578 of 30th October from H .M* s embassador, Baghdad to the Ri^it Hon* ble uir 6amuel J.G.Hoare ,Bt* ,G-Ci3l ,GBjLi], etc. , - ■ J 2. 1 l)f I think HJU* s iimbassador, Baghdad, in making his observ ations on the position of Hulaiba wells must have read my despatch No.C-262,dated 27th August 1935 in conjunction with the map of Basra and adjacent territory on scale 1.1,000,000 (international map of the world) as published by the General ataff) t which is admittedly full ibf mistakes as regards the Bat in district and Kuwait generally. 3, If you will examine the map of Kuwait scale 1.500,000 completed two years ago by Major Papworth , (attached Headquarters, Iraq Command) and issued in proof form in March 1934, which survey, I think, we must all admit, is the very latest and most accurate map of Kuwait and the adjacent Iraq territory, you will find that Hulaiba wells fall on the Iraq side of the particular frontier line proposed by me. That is to say if one takes the •take the centre line of the Bat in t o be the frontier, the said wells which lie in the Batin depression itself will be found to be just inside Iraq. * 4 # '&lt;Yhen writing my despatch No.G-262 of 27th August 1935, I confess freely that I had this map before me, which from close personal Imowledge of the Batin valley, I knew to be far more accurate than the old Basra Million sheet, which we have all hitherto worked on. 5 # You will further observe that Major Papworth himself in his map (which I gave you arid which you have in the Bushire _ Office) has placed Hulaiba about one mile inside Iraq. As a matter of fact I am of opinion that Major Papworth has here gone slightly wrong with his frontier line and should have dram it (the frontier line) from bafwan in a due westerly straight line until it struck the centre line of the Batin, after v/hich it should have followed the centre line of the Batin, as he has correctly made it do as far as A1 Auja in the south. In spite of this personal view of mine, however, Hulaiba would still fall just inside Iraq territory by a hundred yards or more. 7 # in view of my above remarks I think that l-T^M*s Ambassador will perhaps appreciate that my suggestion as regards fixing the centre line of th 5 Batin as the frontier was not made lightly, and certainly with no intention to gain something for Kuwait at the expense of Iraq. I knew the a tin district well, perhaps better than any living person today and the frontier line as proposed by me was one iflhich I considered not only the fairest, but one least likely to cause future argument or heart burning. The advantage of such line would, I think, be at once admitted by H.M* s embassador himself if he were himself to see it on the ground, especially-as throughout its entire length there is today a deep and clearly defined motor car track made by the H .a .iT# in 1929-50 ,y /hich as near as possible forms an artificial demarcation line. - - - Lt.-Colonel, Political ^gent, Kuwait.- 3 - ^fter Kot^. It will give me genuine pleasure if on BuM* s iLmbassador*s next visit to Kuwait he will permit me to conduct him to the Bat in valley, and show him part or the whole of that unique natural feature.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.V/,1. P.Z. 249/36. 24th January, 1936. BY AIR MAIL . ill ■■■■ ■ ipKwi 1, Will you please refer to correspondence regarding the alignment of the frontier 'betweeh Iraq and Koweit, and in particular your letter to the Political Resident of the 27th Augustj 1935, No.0.262, and Bagdad Despatch of 30th October, No.578, of which you have presumably received a copy. 2. The question has he en carefully considered here 'by the various departments concerned and the results of the discussion dated / have been embodied in the Foreign Office Despatch to Bagdad, 22nd / &gt;c January/ a copy of which is enclosed, along with a sketch map, showing the relevant parts of the country. 3. The interpretation of the frontier which it is now proposed to adopt involves two slight modifications of the line drawn on the map enclosed. First, between Hulaiba and its intersection with the line running due east and west, the frontier will be drav/n slightly to the northwards of the line shown on the map. Secondly, from the point 1 mile Lieut.-Col. H.E.P.Dickson, C.I.E., south/ Political Agency, Kov/eit.yc f \ south of Safv/an the frontier v/ill 'be drawn in a straight line to the tri-junction of the Khor Zubair, the Khor Shetana and the Khor As SaMya, instead of the alignment shown on the map. The proposed line seems to agree with the local opinion as stated in your letter under reference. It also covers the point ahout Hulaiba, raised hy Sir Archibald Clark-Kerr. 4« I am sending a copy of this letter to Caroe and Fowle with copies of the despatch. You v/ill no doubt forward your concurrence or observations through the Resident as soon as possible. (FU^ J,G. ft AiiDfcit.light of tiile Infornetlon Hie KtoJccty 's Oovernmont are aatlsfieA tliat the frontier if drawn down the centre of tbe Batln» ae in t^ broken line on the enoloaed akatefe -mary, would not leave 2luXaiba in Koweit* 6. Careful ooneideration has alao Dean Jiiren to the queatton of the interpretation to be niaced on the worde M northv7orcl8••••to a noint Juat south of the latitude 'of Safwan; thanee eastwards poaelng south of 6afwan we11a t 'Jehel ftanui •* etc- toa are no doubt aware that the Batln» as . la shown on the enoloaed Bicetch-man, la continued to the north-eaet of Hulalba by a prolongation or delta, called ^ufraah* Hi a llajeaty'a rovera -nent are of opinion that the worda guoted above muat be taKen to tiean that the frontier-line should continue down the centre of j^fraah (not, aa on the eneloaed sketch-mao, down the eastern aide) until It reaciiea the oreaoribed point w ^usi'. south of t.ie latitude of Safwan n ^ The Political Agent, Kotvelt, has atatod that tnere is a signboard marking the frontier at a r ,olnt one mile south of Safwan. In the absence of any indlcntion that the ^oaltion of this signboard is disputed locally, His Ma ^eety's 'toYerniTient regard the point at which the frontier should lenve the Batin distance ^outh of the latitude of aafwan, and tney consider that the frc \tier should thence oroce ^d due eastward©. They note raoi iover, that according to Colonel DleKson, this ie ine intor^re-ititlon locally accented* 6. From (.vafwan to the Persian Gulf, Kls Majesty's 'KMerntaent see no reason to dissent frr^n the frontier line wi.ich tlie Political A^ent at Kowelt hac- indicated as being loyally accented, namely, a straight line from a point one ■ mi leTelegram S ij'rom Political Resident, at Shiraz. To Political Agent, Kuwait* No .1/262 Dated the 13th August 1940. My telegram No.T/261 of todays date. Kuwait Iraq. Boundary• 2. Please ascertain how far ^south of most southerly palm of Safwan* board was formerly situated. This would probably attract least attention if you combined it with trip to Basra and read speedometer.1 Telegram J'roin To Ojo ■ &amp; Political, Kuwait. Political Resident, at Shiran No. 0/404. Hated and received th= 6t5a Septeuber, 1940. /■r* Your telegram T/262 august 13th. During trip to Basra with Dickson 1 ascertained that hoard was formerly situated a^out 1C5C y^rd- -outh most southerly pahn of Safwan, This distance is approximate because road does not run due north and tout . Dista-ce checked by counting telegraph posts and not by speedometer. - Political. W.I. Political Hesident, at Shiraz. Political, Kuwait. Te le^ram From To No. T/37 3. Dated the 9th September, 1940. Your 0/404 September 8th. Oaja you say how former position compared with site of re-erection on 9th June 1940 ? Jid you see any signs of latter position '? - Britcoiisul. jV . L.(360/25/40) 30th August,1940. My dear Baggallay, p I enclooe heroin a copy of a letter from ^J, EdmondB commenting on the enolostire to your letter of May 5th to the India Office (No.B 1758/309/91) about the interpretation to be given to the definition of the Koweit-Iraq frontier laid down by Sir Percy Cox. it may be a pity that he did not reply sooner but it is not surprising as he in common with all of ua has had much too much to do during the surnmer which has n been exceptionally hot. ^ \i* y ' 8. 1 have not studied at all closely the points which he now raises, and I do j»6t propose to delay action on your telegram No.356 of July 31st for the technical examination which may be required. 3. The points of interpretation which will be put forward to the Iraqi Government will be only a basis for discussion anl the Iraqi Government will have ample opportunity to make counter proposals if they wish to do so. In the meanwhile you may care to pass Edmonds 1 letter to the experts so that they may be ready with their views if the Iraqis take up his points. ^ t cfi 4. You will see that iSdmonds still hankers after his palm tree but I agree^flth the Political Resident who strongly deprecates any reversion to this method of defining an important point, and is confident that it will be easy to ascertain the position of the notice board which was improperly removed by the Iraqis in March last year for the second time. It was replaced the first time and obviously can be again. Whereas what is a palm of Safwan, and how is it to be distinguished from a palm of Zubair or a palm of Pao? The whole of Southern Iraq is dotted with palms. I should say therefore that it would be much easier to obliterate any given palm than the position of a unique notice board which was in situ for sixteen years until it was forcibly removed for the second time. 5. I am sending copies of this letter and its enclosure to Bushire and Koweit. Yours ever, Sgd-J Basil Newton. H. L. BAGGALLAY £3Q.of the interior, Iraq. Bagdad, August 20th 1940. P.S-149. $i^r My dear Holt, Please excuae my delay in answering your letter 360/6/40 of 5th June, which we put aside during a rush of urgent work and was then overlooiced. 1 have dxscussed tne matter with you verbally, but I may as well put down my remarks to complete the file. 1. Agreed. 2. As tht: notice board lias been removed for seme years now we should have to say ' Safwan at which a post ana notice board formerly marked th« frontier'. But the exact point is likely to be disputed after so lon^; indeed the ira&lt;ii reports on the Political Agent's recent atlempt to re-establiah it unilaterally state that he placed it well to the north of the original position. A definite distance from a specific palm would therefore have been simpler, but perhaps both parties will be able to find some reputoble map ^hose oath they will accept and so settle the matter. 3. Agreed with corresponding tunendment to (2) i*e. 'for- merl^y stood' , for 'have been erected 5 '., | ^ . 4. See my letter P.S. 846 of 2nd December,1937. I think we should either say 'the trijunction of the taalwug ol the iLhors Zubair, Shetana and Sabiya as shown on the 1:500,000 map of 1936' or add the co-ordinates as read off that map, or better still both. 5. v. ith the maps at our disposal we cannot be quite suie that the straight line would not cut off the tip oi' the north bank where it separates the two Khors or even leave Una ^aor in Iraq, which by the. terms of the original agreement it must; also low-wator boundaries must be unsatibfactox'y. it uould be hardly human for the owner of the bank to respect the ownership of the adjacent water. The 'clarification' I would suggest here would be as follows: 'From the point south of Safwan defined in para 5 the frontier shall run in a straight line to (the point on the high-water line due west of) the junction defined in para 4, provided that if such a line were to cut either bank of the iJiors more than once or were not to leave Um Qasr in Iraq, the line shall be modified by agreement between the two parties in such a way an to prevent e i the r c ont ingency'. If the words in brackets are accepted neither of the contingencies seems likely but it might be wise to leave them in nevertheless. This proposal is intended only to give a good line. It is perhaps unfortunate that it would give a few extra square yards to Ifcaq as against the line straight to- the junoti-onj and so is likely to stampede the Kuwait authorities who seem inclined to haggle over inches; but it would be childish to insert provision for compensation elsewhere by an equivalent area of equally useless mud and sand. Yours sincerely, (signed)- G. J.KDMONDS. Hk (24) Capt.V.Holt C.M.O.&gt;f&amp;) o* U « Brit In h ijttbma»y 9 HmgAMii 0 7th Ootober, I9k0» f*S Your xc«lienoy, X have the honour to inform you that agr Govorm^at oonsidor it dosirfthlo thi t tho f rontior between Iraq and owe it should bo domaroated and I havo received inn true tiona to propose to the Iraqi oovem-iont that arrangoiaonta ahould bo sfiade to do thia at m oarl/ date. 2m with thie end in view 9 Hie .ajeety'a Ovrmrrmmnt auggoat that there should be an exchange of notes providing that the worfc of deoiareating the frontier and erecting pillars should be carried out in a manner siaJULur to that laid down in the notes exchanged for the saoie purpoee between the Iraqi and Baudi Arabian Oovemments in February X93d« In order, however, to avoid diffioultiee which laUcht otherwise arise. Hie Majesty 9 s ooverftcjent think it desirable that the proposed notes should include agreesaent on the Interpretation of certain points in the wording of the definition of the frontier as re affirmed by the Priiae i inis tor in hie letter to the High co^is^ioner Ko* 23UU of July ^Ist, Vjyz* 3* In that letter the definition of the frontieie was re~affimed in the fellowing teme i~ *From the intereection of the adi al u^ja . with the Bet in and t hrnoe northwarda along the fik»tin to a point just south of the latitude of fafvani thence eastwards passing south of tiafwMn wells, Jebel ansia and asr leaving them to Iraq and so on to the Junction of the Khor £.obelr with the hor Abdullah. The islands of ^arbs, Bubien, l asicen (or rfeehjen) Failsitah, Auheh, lubbar vsru end \&gt;m el ^aredin er pertain to Xoweit*' h* Hie ^xcelleaer Al aeiyid ;iurl-al-SaId, G*C*V«0«, etc., eto. , minister for Foreign /iffsirs, a . . .(1) /** m 2 m (2) The 'point ^uat south of the latitude of Safwim' shall be the point on the thalweg of the Bat in due leat of the point a little to the Bouth of Bafwan at whieh the poet and notice-board marking the frontier atood until hlarohf 1939* (3) From the Batin to the nei^hb urhood of rafwaa the frontier ahall be a line along the parallel of latitude on which a tends the aboTeMnentioned point at whioh the post and notice-board forraerly atood* (U) The 'junction of the /hor /ubair with the Khor Abdullah' shall mean the junction of the thalweg of the Khor subair with the thalweg of the north-weaterly arm of the Khor Abdullah fcnown sa the \hor MeUma. (5) From the nei^rhbourhood of f*afwan to the Junction of the Khor Zubair with the Khor Abdullah the frontier shall be the ehorteat line between the point defined in sub-paragraph (2) and the point defined in aub«paragreph (U;. Bat if thia line ahall be found* when followed on the ground to strike the ri^t bank of the Khor ubair before it reaohea the point defined in sub -paragraph (U)# it ehall be modified in such a manner as to follow the low water line on the right banJt of the ^hor 'ubair until a point on the bank imiedlately opvoaite the point defined in aub-parugraph (k) la rer ched, thus leawing the whole of the Khor liubair to Iraq. (6) ifrom the point defined in sub-paragraph (k) to the open sea the boundary ahall follow the thalyer; of the ?Chor Abdul Ish* 4* ?he Iraqi aoremment further propose that the operation of deaaaroation ehall be carried out in the following manuer i~5 f m m (6) in eaee of dlfferciwe® betneeu th# represent a H vcb , they shall aubialt the qaeetlon in dlepute to their Govem^ntfi with a view to a eoluUon being reaehed through the diplomatic channel. (7) The procea Terhaux of the CeMiaeioft shall be prepared in /.rabic and t^llah and, in case of difference, the nglieh text shall prevsil. (8) The date on whioh the Joint Commission shall begin work shall be fixed by si reemsnt between the two UoTentnsatta* (9) The cost of the worfc of triangulation end the ereotion of the frontier pillars shall be defrayed in equal shares by esch of the two aovernwents. xf the above proposals are agreeable to the K0seiti oovernment, the present note and the reply of the eocapeUmt Howe it 1 authority or authorities in identic terns shall be regarded as constituting an agreement between the two tievemi^ents in this matter*/ 53/87 * 63/57. A Telegram 3* From Politioal Agent, Kuwait• To Politioal Resident, Bushire, No•0/5° 7• X)ated 0 3rd received 0 5th 3eptem'ber 1941 # My telegram No.0/515 Septemter 15th. Umm Qasr# I examlaed railway co ns true ti on Comia ay•s survey maj,;. Surveyors are sure th^t Umui Qasr fort is not correctly marked on quarter iiicti map and should he .9 of a mile more to the south. According to their calculations southern 'boundary of port is nearly 3 miles south of Umm Qasr as it is at present shown on map. The fixed point south of Safwaa is in practice 1050 yards south of the village 'but on quarter inch map 'boundary is drawn over one ? aod a half miles of village. I am of opinion that site is ? partly in Kuwait territory and I suggest advantage 'be taken of presence of skilled surveyors with railway construction Oompany operating in the neighhourhood to fix frontier line accurately on the ground and that frontier 'be demar cated without delay, -POLITIOAL.I/ ■^'7 ^ j, O GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. $ V-«f EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL mestage sent by AIR MAIL tohieh provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, viith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Persian viuXX Bushire• N o. 476* To Repeated* Dated W&amp;mi' the list April 1946. Retsxandum, London. irelen, I.eit i-clhl. Prodromes * 1' j PQlitiCRl t f.VX'd. 11 19 Reference y iii? A.IT * 1^1' I* Reference p^ra 5 or Inrtla orflce letter fc»xt* ^3i&gt;y/^L 9 dateci loth Jime la4£ t tp Forelfli Of lice, mnd connected correspondence• g« On a journey toy road from Basra to Kv*; It on 12th /a^ April 1946 I noticed that theishas beeti /oiieiderable emount of agricultural develppment to ti ^e iboutr of vefiian f that a number of addltionel v?elxs had been dug, and ahat appeared to be palm groves laid out. It will be appreciated that 'the most southerly pel* in fcafwan H f may therefore soon have a dlfierent significance. ^ ^g ^ ^ 3. ud It is rep rted ihet a geoloiacal survey party/work- iiu: in pres ^est of Jab el i^nam. If the surve&gt; estab lishes the importance of this area from an oil bearing aspect th* precise definition of the Kueali-Iraq boundary would assume early importance• Sd. GEOFITOX PRIOH. Political Beeidtint, Persian Gulf. cu .''iiii ii*-' i 'r'XLlrtla for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Oulf. HIW. (Sign at\i/re) S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp;P--(M.18705—9-2-39—20,000. {DesigncUiotilift however on the ground is not free frcm aiabiyuity, one of tua points In doubt being the location of thj point through whioii the line x&gt;&amp;nso8 53out i of Saf./an. The only definition itiioh seoim to have .von axything like general acceptance is that the frontier ms mrked by a former notice board which stood about iO^O yards south of 'the laost southerly Thalia of Safwan', and this is the reference in the j olitical xesident* s ez£&gt;rea£ letter of 21st April* , 3« Now that Unm ,^asr has been abark-oneu as a port it no ^ 3 longer provides in itself a reason in favour of the early demroatian of ths frontier. as Sir Gooffrqy ^rior sugf^ots, hoover, the discovery of oil in the area lasy before lone bring the .mostion iqj in a raoie acute fonu, and is not likely to make it aiy easier to rsaoh a &lt; p?oomcait with the IraqjLs. We should be glt'.d to know whether jou have aiy oomacnts to offer l*ro^i this aspect. if* 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Balier at the itoreitfi Office. (sou.) F .A .K. HAHRIBCU(E 5W+/700/91) FOREIGN OFFICE,' S.W.I. 6th July 19U8« * / c/O / COKFIDEHTIAL f / i 3e^. Will you please refer to your letter No: D. 0.21 of the 22nd April about the Iraq - Koweit frontier. In view of the interest of the Basra Port Directorate and the Iraq Petroleum Company of the Sheikh of Koweit^ concern ahout smuggling we are convinced that we should now make a serious attempt to obtain final demarcation of the Koweit - Iraqi Frontier. As you say in your letter D. 0. 2021/S of the 26th November^ I9I4.7 to Donaldson it is necessary to decide on what basis we are to approach the Iraqi Government. Here I must say straight away, with due respect for your views and those put forward by the India Office when they were dealing with Gulf problems, that the only possible basis on which we can go to the Iraqis is the 1911.0 formula. This formula was accepted by Koweit and commi^iicated to Iraq in a manner which makes it in practice 'impossible for His Majesty's Government to claim anything more favourable than this for Koweit now in negotiations with Iraq. It was not communicated to Iraq as a bargain in return for something else; it was communicated to Iraq as being our understanding of how the 1923-32 text should really work out when reasonably and correctly applied. If it were argued on behalf of Koweit that Koweit accepted the 1940 formula only on the basis that it merely sets out correctly what the 1923-32 text meant and that acceptance is not binding if the 19U0 formula departs from the 1923-32 text our views are: ... (a) that we do not for the reasons stated below think that it can be shown to depart from the 1923-32 text and ^ (b) the Sheikh of Koweit cannot base much argument on the 1913 treaty with Turkey because, although Sir Percy Cox told the Political Resident at the time that the 1923 line is the same as the line on the map of 1913&gt; he said that it seemed unnecessary for the Political Resident to mention this to the Sheikh, and it may be presumed that the Political Resident did not do so. The 1923 Agreement defines the frontier as being 'along the Batin to a point just South of the latitude of Safwan; thence Eastwards passing south of Safwan Wells, Jebel, Sanam and Umm Qasr, leaving them to Iraq and so on to the junction of the Khor Zubeir with the Khor Abdullah.' On the 1923 text it is not possible to draw any inference as to how far the line is south of Umm Qasr. All that is certain is that Umm Qasr is north of the line. It is not possible to say that the line must be 100 yards or a mile south of it. It does seem to us, however, that one would draw the inference from the 1923 Agreement that the line should be a straight one from South of Safwan to the junction of the two Khors, always providing that such a straight line left Umm Qasr and Jebel Sanam to the North of it. In fact the 1940 interpretation which provided that this line should be straight was in fact a natural interpretation of the 1923 Agreement.. The 1932 letter uses the same words as the 1923 Agreement. Moreover, leaving aside for the moment the 1940 formula, the one authoritative text is that contained in the 1923 communication and repeated in identica3. terms in 1932. It is obviously the authoritative text for Iraq f s frontier because it was given by His Majesty^ Government to Iraq and to the League of Nations as defining Iraq's frontier when she became a member Sir Rupert Hay, K. C.I.B,, C.S. I., Bahrein. £ i pers ia n gui f rfesidency /VO ,^^5 ^ 0.1 Tf /.?• 7; CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS Of3 '%) of the League in 1932. It was moreover given in 1923 to Koweit as the formal definition of' Koweit f s frontier. It would only 'be possible to go 'back to earlier formulae for the purpose of interpreting the above mentioned text if (and to the extent that) this text may 'be ambiguous. It would not he possible by means of earlier formulae to depart from the 1923-32 text. To resolve ambiguity recourse might be had to Article 7 of the Agreement with Turkey of 1913 on the grounds that there was a probability that the definition of 1923-32 meant the same as Article 7 of 1913 when tracing the line from west to east instead of vice-versa. But the 1923 defini tion does not in fact seem to be ambiguous or stand in need of interpretation. We do not, therefore, think it can be maintained that in presenting the I9I4-O formula to Iraq once again it can be considered that we are 'surrendering' territory which Koweit ought to have. And even if this could be argued we should still feel for the reasons set out above, that the 19^0 formula is the only one which we can reasonably put to the Iraqis. I would add here that we do not think that it would necessarily be a good thing for part of the Umm Qasr development area to be* allotted to the Sheikh of Koweit, since mixed control would lead to friction and might not work properly. Our own inclination therefore would be to seek the consent of the Sheikh of Koweit to a further approach to the Iraqi Government on the basis of the 1940 formula. We appreciate, however, that the approach to the Iraqi Government may not lead to a settlement, that the matter might go to arbitration and that in the course of arbitration the 1913 agreement would probably be brought into the open. In that case, the Sheikh might feel that we have been deceiving him in favour of Iraq* We do not consider that he would be justified in this view, but we realise that it might be somewhat dilficult to convince him. It therefore occurs to us that it might be wiser to explain to him forthwith the position of the Anglo— Turkish agreement of 1913, together with the reasons why we do not consider that it comes into te question of the present demarcation of the frontier and why we do not consider that the 1940 formula in any way involves a 'surrender' by him» The disadvantage of this suggestion is that if, as a result of hearing about the 1913 agreement, the Sheikh refuses to agree to a new approach to the Iraqis on the basis of the 1940 formula, we shall not be to make any progress at all towards obtaining a demarcation of the frontier. Would you kindly let us know what you think of this suggestion? Any comments you may wish to make on the other points raised in this letter will, also, of course, be welcome. The whole problem could then be discussad in the light o „ ur views while you are over here. (L.P.L. Pyman)COHFIDFNTIAL Ho. // c 7 ( 53 /670 PF^sta^ rrtF ^fst^VCY the Slst July 194R &amp; Ple®9© refer to your semi-official letter 544/700/ 91) of the 6th July 194R about the Traq-Kuwalt frontier, 2. I am compelled to accert the decision thet the only possible basis on which we can fo to the Iraqi9 f Is the 1940 formula, but I would surest that In dolnp so we should. If possible, adopt the Interpretation of the forrrmla that Is most favourable to Kuwait. The crux of the whole matter Is the e*act location of the junction of th^ Khor Zubalr with the Khor Abdullah which Is more precisely described as 'the Junction of th^ thalweg of the Khor Zubalr with the thal/.ver of the north-westerly arm o^ the Khor Abdullah known as the Khor Shetana.' 1 There Is no doubt that when the formula was flr^t proposed to the Iraqi Government in 194C f His Majesty^ Government had In mind the line shown on the War Office Basra-Kuwait map of 1.93f. Arguments have, however, been adduced by Wakefield vide paragraphs 17 and 18 of his note forwarded to the India Office with my despatch tT o.lPlr ^of the 20th December 1 0 41 and by myself, vide par^prarhs 5 ar' 1 6 of despatch to the India Office ^o.r/78 of the 10th Vsrch 1 0 4? to show that the junction of the Khor Zubalr with the Khor Abdullah Is Immediately south of TTmr Qa^r. The mention made In the comrrunlcatlon to the Iraq Government of the Khor Shetana may make It difficult to claim this now - this Is a point which merits- further examination - but I consider that In any case our ^irst step should be to Inform th-» Shaikh of Kuwait that we propose, If he approves, to approach the Iraqi Government on the basis of the formula communicated tr him In 1940 and ask him to show us or a map how he regarded the line as running on the basis of this formula, at the time he accepted It. T 'e shall of course Viave to be careful to avoid any Mnd of prompting. If his rerly shows that he considered the boundary defined bv the formula as Identical with that shown on the War Office 19^6 map, we should, T thlrk explain the sltuatlor to him on the lines suppested In the penultimate paragraph of your letter. If, on the other hand It becomes clear that he accepted the formula as describing the more favourable line, I see no reason why we should not in our negotiat ions with the Iraq Government rolnt out that this Is ^he inter pretation put on It bv the Shaikh of Kuwait on whose behal^ we ©re acting.and support his claim to the best of our ability. L.F.L. Pyman, Fsquire, Forelrn Office, Whitehall, ^ONppft, S y W 1 1 ♦ LB*FOREIGN OPPICE, S.W.I. (E 10093/700/91) GOMP IHBI'iT XAL Dear Galloway, 6th Aiig-ust 1948, (/o/ Hay's letter No. 119 of 21st July about the Kuwait Iraqi frontier. We took the opportunity to discuss this question with Hay as he passed through London on his way on leave. ' ' ' \ We still feel,, in'spite of the arguments adduced if^iii^Ain V/akefield's memorandum and Hay*a despatch No, C/78 of 10th March 1942, that the line shown in the War Office Basra Kuwait map of 1936 is the only one on which we could make a fresh approach to the Iraq G-overnment. We are in agreement, hov/ever, that we must now definitely find out from the Sheikh how he himself regarded the line as running, on the basis of the 1940 formula, at the time he accepted it. I should, therefore, be grateful if you would take the matter up with the Sheikh as early as possible. You will have seen from Bagdad Chancery letter o» 367 of 14th July that there is some possibility that the Iraqis will themselves raise the matter quite socn. Yours sincerely. , Cit 1*4 I fj (B.A.B. Burrows) Lieutenant-Colonel A.G. Galloway, &gt; O.B.-Hi. , Bahrein. NO I ' r \ E . ^ CONF!DENT !AL RF ^RDSCOHFIDENIIAL ^T. S.10V Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. the 18th August, 1948. Please refer to Clinton-Thomas letter No. (E 10093/700/91) of the 6th August 1948 about the Kuwait - Iraq frontier. L 2. It is not clear to me ^hat actually is expected from the Shaikh since we already have his written agreement i to a clear and detailed definition of the 1940 formula line (vide enclosures to Residency Printed Letter No. 462-S of the 26th June, 1940, to the late India Office). If I approach the Shaikh as suggested in the letter quoted in paragraph 1 above, he will surely wonder v 'hy he is being asked. I do not know the reason myself, and if he asked me I should have no satisfactory answer to give. Of his own accord he certainly would not be able to give a clearer definition than the one he has already agreed to, and we do not want him to consult, say, the Kuwait Oil Company. His proper reaction to such a question should be to reaffirm his letter of 1940. This would be satisfactory since that definition coincides with the most 'advanced' formula, from Kuwait's point of view, considered equitable to both Kuwait and Iraq. I feel that to ask the Shaikh now how he himself regarded the line as running must raise doubts in his mind as to the correctness of the definition of 1940, or he may infer that he is expected to have an opinion other than the one already expressed in 1940. This might lead him to reply with an 'advanced' claim, or line defined in a vague manner common to Arabs on this coast thus possibly reopening the whole case. 3. I suggest action on the lines indicated in the first sentence of the penultimate paragraph of Pyman's letter of the 6th July would be more appropriate. This would avoid any question of misunderstanding of our attitude towards the 1940 formula, while the Shaikh would be at liberty to make any statement he wished in his reply. 4. I should be grateful to hear from you before I approach the Shaiich. B .A.B. Burrows, Esquire, Foreign Office, Whitehall, Lgnagfli</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001f2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/525</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001f2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/525</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/57 IV Kuwait-Iraq Boundary'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-15T00:03:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (45 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.Serial numbers in red crayon refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Condition: Previously bound with treasury tags, these tags have since been removed and the file's pages are now loose between a front and back cover.Foliation: The file's main foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A second foliation sequence is also present between ff 2-42; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.The file contains the following foliation errors: 13, and 13A; 20, and 20A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials regarding the demarcation of the frontier between Iraq and Kuwait.An unsigned and undated letter (in Arabic) with a list of demands for reform is contained on folio 20a. Seven names (written in English) have been added in pencil to the bottom of the letter.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001f2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>