<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T15:59:52.220Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) * FN.B .—This it an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a meant of communication more expeditions than Use ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb e ie e , on receipt, with the tame expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and o o via ^ formalities it it drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the stgna ure oj responsible officer o f the Department.] No. To ,rX 467 -£ of ISZr&amp;JDate&amp;K i r Simla From New JJelh i xxxxxxx , the W JU! Political Kesident, Buahire* To Becretfery of State for Xnci&amp;, Lom Kepe&amp;t^d Governseiit of Sial&amp;# Keference ^ ... Politic:! jfXXXXXXXXX v4 POLITICAL AGENCY AND olitic&amp;l Agent, Muscat, with copy of the Ir Office Express letter quoted, refei’ence bout CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Date. Ill JL1 PJJG liojr ^ ^ between jChaimh and Muscat frontiers H. B. M'S CONSULATE; MUSCAT bubiect ; Petroleus Conces-slons Liaitec - \ Trucial Coast, Heference y ur Express letter P2*bb6b/£6 dated the 20th May 19o6. 2* X concur that the addition of the Article in &lt;uestion is desirable* 5. With regard to bounda 6haUkhdo«&amp; inter se &gt; alia encuit'y froe the Shaikhs thorny question. tween the Trucial dune without, inter ill be, 1 Imagine, a ay upset them* I thing it woulc be better to wait until Petroleum Concessions Limited have obtained their concessions before taking this matter up. In the meantime I will look up asy archives and *ee #hat (/Signature) (Designation) information / s. 44. DCFP— 1124 S&amp;P—(M- 1314 )— 4 - 8 - 32 “- 12,000informrtian there is in the® be&amp;ring on this cuestion* sd. T*C*Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attestea. for Secretary to the rolltical Resident in the Persian Gulf,it COPY EXPRESS LETTEK (AIR MAIL; From Secretary of State for India, To Political Resident, Persian Gulf, repeated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, and Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 20th May 1936, No. 0.Z, 3363/36. Please see letter dated 14th May from Petroleum Concessions Limited, of which a copy is enclosed, regarding the boundaries inter se of the Trucial Shaikhaoms. 2. I am inclined to agree that addition of Article on these lines is desirable, but should be glad of your views. The issue of the above has been authorised. sd. J.C. Walton.P.Z. 5563/36. PEThOLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED. City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, LONDON.E*C. 2* 14th May 1936, Dear Mr.Walton, In confirmation of our conversation this morning, I am suggesting to Major Holmes the insertion in each of the Trucial Coast Draft Concessions of an Article designed to cover the position which would arise in the case of an inter se dispute between two of the Shaikhs (or possibly between one of the Shaikhs and a semi-independent inlying tribe). There is no doubt that in such an event we might find ourselves quite unable to proceed, and although the suggested solution involves invoking t::e good offices of the Political Resident over what might be far from an easy matter, I cannot think of any other way, and you yourself this morning seemed sympathetic to this suggestion. Would some such formula as the following meet the case? 'The Shaikh agrees that, in the event of a difference of opinion between him and any other ruler or authority as to whether a given place or district is properly to be considered as within his territory or in that of the other ruler or authority, he will accept without reservation the decision ol the Poli tical Resident on this matter, and will, in so far as lies in his power, prevent the existence of the dispute from affecting adversely the operations of the Company in any manner. The Company similarly agrees without reservation to accept such decision.' J.C.Walton Esq.,CB.,MC., If / India office, Whitehall,S.W.1.is If as you suggested, the Political Resident able to progress towards an official definition of the respective areas, this would, ol course, maK.e it much less likely that we should have to have recourse to the suggested Article. Yours, &amp;c., (sgd.) S.H.LONGRIGG.M h/lAs GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. confidential. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). / -7 # (y [N.B •—This it an OltlGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary matt and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended ib be it fated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it it dra fted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.] No. 713-3 of itfsa. ronm.®. ' L - ! 7*$. FT 3i Political He8iaent # Bushin • To - Secretary of state for indiii, lomlorj* Re eat ed 0 over run ent of India, SimlM. POLITICAL Pol it teal Agent, ^hrain. Political Agent, Musomt, j CONFIDENTIAL RECORD UC H. B, M‘S aOH&amp;UiyL. -USC» T . Paragraph 3 colonel j?7wle*s Sxpreee Letter 467-3 June 2nd 19^6. BoyndarieB between the I’rtsial HhaikMoic*, 2, I have received a report fr m Keaidency Agent, Sharjah, atating thet on hearing that Shaiich ::a* id bin Xaktua of 0ibai had granted an oil coaoeat* ton. Shaikh Bhakhbut hin Sultan of Aim ShaM sent a letter and verbal nesaage to him asking wimt territcrj he nad granted. Shaikh shakhbut aeked ti»t the boundaries aijlit he settled before geolc&amp;ists go out, a a he vfould be reepmaible for- prut^ctin^ them within the lisslts of .Abu Dhabi and feared that shaikh sa» id might a end hie armed guard* with the geologist* into Abu Dhabi territory* Shaikh So * id, of Dlbai han nuggeated that he ehoiad go to Abu Dhabi aa Boon as shaikh shakhbut*e uncle, Shaikh Khalifah bin ^id,(without whose advice Shaikh ohakhbut will not do business) returns fron Burfeiuii, Li order ii^at thd&gt; ira-/ settle the boundary question* 3 / (Signature) * ' S. 44. DOFF— 1124 S&amp;T—(M-I 314 )— 4 - 8 - 32 ^ 12 , 000 . (Designation)5 *■ S'* The Hecidency Agent cofanentet- * The Oil question on the TruoiRl Coast has opened the yes of Trucifcl Chiefs and each of them tries to encroach on the boundary of his neighbours and exteM his territory so as to increase his rerenues, Tnere is no doubt that if their (facial Chiefs) boundaries ere not defined before the geologists go out* trouble vould arise bet seen them which might le&amp;d to vnT M . 4* Certain boundaries are mentioned in Lorimer'a Persian Gulf Grsettecr Volume II (Abu Dhabi p*4GSi Dibai p.4b4i Sharjah p. l?56t p,o3i Umm-el-^awaia p. 147dt Has al Khaimah p.lOC4) # but they give only a general idea. In the a course of Tar ious personal enquiries I have always found an overlap, coloured by the allegiance of the person speaking. I sinesrely hope that the Dnalkhe of Abu Dhabi and Pife&amp;l ^riix be able to settle their boundary question for th93m?lYd3, especially &amp;a, if tiioy do so, the other bouiidaries should not be so difficult and a precedent of * self-determina tion* will have been established. * &amp;• In the meantime, shoulo any geologists go out, it will be necessary for them to keep well away from any debatable lend and I should be grateful if the necessity for this could be impressed on the Company. Attested. sd. 0* Loch. Lieut.-Col on el* officiating Political Resident tn the Persian Gulf. ftdr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. XvCONFIDENTIAL. No - No. 3F.0-b of 13c7. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the compliments to 1* Eecret^ry of Etate P* The Foreign Secretary to of Indifi, ^e.v relhi* Persian Gulf presents his f\ i &gt;J A/‘ ' Jf&gt; tor Indii , Lendoh. the Government _ | 2. The Poll tic,'J. Agent, Bc.hri.in. &gt; 4. The Politicftl Agent, Muse-1. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. Reference to previous correspondence: X' 2 ' Political hesidentfe telegram Ko. 154, dated 5th February 1957* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Kuwait D.O. letter No. dated P£nri March 1957.I&lt;y COPY ur-y POLITIC'X AGENCY KU 7 IT. The 2C;nd Mc.rch ^9o7. Ccott, the Oil Superintendent, tells me that the Oil ^outk at r pj-ointin^ hut tin.t he is con tinuing. Pressure in gener? 1, jncpiug b th't behind salt r-ter they have come upon, is good. He rather thinks that they are just on the edge of a field, and I gather he may later stop dri 1 ling t la hr-- nc try sor;e miles est 1 ard. Lecision of course depends upon the London Office. Yours feinc.rely he. G.&gt; . de§auryCONFIDENTIAL. No. C/143 of 1937 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Hajeaty’s Hecretary of State for India, Lend on. 2. The re*Secretary to tne lovemBient of Ini?* in the External Affair® /Department, Sirala. 3. The Political A^ent, Itihrain- / 4. The Political Agent, Muscat. / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents * xxxxxxxacxxxxxx xscxxx&gt;:x^xr. xxx office of the - oliticHl Real dent in the Persian Gulf, damp, Bahrain. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. 1*937 Reference to previous correspondence: esidency Printed letter Ho.320-f&gt; of the 27th March 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter Hg.C-122-a of the 17th April 1937 from the Political Agent, Kuwait. Kuw&amp;it ^ilOopf itiential, D* 0 # Ho.C- 122 -A* PoIltio&amp;X Ag«ncy. KUWAIT. The 17th April» 1937. Dear Colonel Fowle, Will you pleaee refer to de Geury’s d.©.letter HO.C..109, dated the 22nd March 1937. Scott has how infomed me that he has received instruct lone from the London Office to euspend drillingn on Bahra Ho. 1 well and to c ommenoe establishing a cax^ in the vicinity of hill, in the southern part of the State, from which future testing operations will be controlled and serviced. He adds that in all probability a second test well will be drilled in the vicinity of Burgan or l$Rtadaniyat, but the actual site cannot be diosen until the completion, probably about 10th my, of geophysical work (seismic) now in operation in this area. /hen drilling operations were finally suspended the Bahra Ho.l well had reached a depth of 7960 ft. The only aone of oil saturation encountered lay between 6660 ft. and 7016 ft., exhaustive teats, however, failed to obtain production frQna|thi3 source* Tours sincerely, ad. A.O.Btewart. The Hon* tie Lt.-Col.T.C.Fowle,C'E^, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre.CONFIDENTIAL. No. /ttk/z. The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Liu sea t. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). for infonaa tion* POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the Sth mveto. 1938. Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Late. Subject. Telegram to Secretary of State for India, London, Ho.93 dated 2nd Maroh 1938. Oil in Kuwait.c G,T*C, ^row - Political^ Kuwait. Tto - Seoratary of state tvr IruUa, London 'epeeted - By post to Goternnmt of India, Delhi, Buehire, ikihrsin end Muecat. No, 93 , Dated the Bnd &amp;aroh 1998, Arabio News, The KUmiit Oil Oompeny have oom upon oil in Kuwait territory. Definite report* as to the value or quantity have not yet been received. f -Political- rXJOQUXBfflKKKKm S S C R a T The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents bis compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, and Imp the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s), FOR IK FORM ATI OH ONLY. Office of the Political Resident, Persian i».T* 'Rearchus', at sea, 13 ri tish 1 BUSHIRE. Gulf , Dated Reference to previous correspondence: India Office Printed Letter Ho.EXT. 5951/45 dated 17.11.45 to Kuwai t only. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office demi-official letter Ho.SXT.707/46 dated 11th February 19 46 and Jurisdiction over the sub soil beneath the sea immediately adjacent to territorial waters. enclosuresSJaiCRaT EXT. 7 07/46 Dear Weightman* 11th February 1946. You will have received a copy of my letter to Stock of the M.F.P. Ko.Ext. 5951/45 of 17th November 1945, about the Kuwait Oil Company’s enquiry regarding the effect of President Truman’s proclamation extending American jurisdiction over the sub-soil adjacent to the North American coast on the continental shelf. 2. 1 enclose herewi th copies of letters from the From Foreign Office dated 4th J anuary ) Foreign Office and It.F.P. in From M.F.P. dated 7th January ) this connection, together with Letter from Foreign Office dated) the minutes of an inter-depart- 28th January enclosing minutes ) mental meeting at the Foreign and copy of President Truman’s ) Office on 16th January on the proclamation ) general subject raised. I also encloae a copy o f a letter we have sent to the Foreign Office giving the Sec retary of State’s views on the To Foreign Office dated 11th Feb ) conclusions of the meeting. As you will see, we have stipulated that the Government of India should be consulted before any action is taken, but we are not officially seeking the Government of India’s views or those of the Political Resident at the moment, and the papers are therefore forwarded for your information only at this stage. 4. 1 am sending a copy of this letter and enclosures to Prior. fours sincerely, (Sgd) E.P.DONALDSON. R.Weightman i£sq.,C. i.E., External Affairs Department, Government of India, New Delhi* Ext.189/46. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. (W 15433/12/76) 4th January 1946. Dear Donaldson, Would you please refer to your letter Ext.5951/ 1945 to Stock, Ministry of Fuel and Power, dated 17th November, concerning the right of tne Shaikh of Kuwait to grant exclusive or non-exclusive rights over areas lying outside the three-mile limit of territorial waters for oil development purposes. 2. 1 We do not consider that either the recent United States proclamation with regard to the subsoil and sea bed of the continental shelf or the case of the Bahamas have altered tne legal position and,for the present our views are still as stated in paragraphs 3(a) and (b) of Baggallay’s letter to Peel No.E.405/19/91 of 2nd March,1940. 3. The position remains therefore as stated in Peel’s letter to Keu$, No. P.L .2333/40 of 18th May* At the same time, we feel that the question of Kuwait might well be considered in relation to the general question of ITis Majesty’s Government’s future policy in regard to the subsoil under the sea outside territorial waters, with special reference to the united States proclamation of policy* On this general question we are thinking of asking for an interdepartmental meeting early in trie New Year at which we hope, of course, that the India Office would be represented* We shall be writing to you separately about this. Yours sincerely, 3d. N.J.a.CHE THAM (for H.W.A.Freese-Pennefather)&gt;0^1 2 xiixt. 226 / 46 . Dear Donaldson, M1U 1STRY OF FU2L AND POWSR, Petroleum Division, 7, Millbank, 3.W.I. 7th January, 1946. I would refer you to your letter of the 17th November raising the question of tne Kuwait Oil Company’s earlier interest in an oil concession in waters outside the territorial limits of Kuwait in view of recent developments in America and in the Bahamas affecting oil development in extra-territorial waters. i have deferred replying to this until now as Freese-Pennefather agreed that this issue raised matters of general policy in whicn the Foreign Office were airecixy concerned, Doth as regards oil and other activities, and you will now have received his letter of the 4th January. From tile point of view of this Ministry, we are in some difiicuity in replying to your question, since we are not fully aware of H.k.G.’e considered view on the action taken by the United states Government in tneir re cent declaration which concerned not only oil but fisheries and mineral development on taeir continental snelf. 1 Should mention, however, that the u.S.Ci. have nut claimed oil exploitation rights, but rather the right to control oil exploitation in these extra -territorial waters. or til the interdepartmental meeting suggested by Freese-rennefatner has been held, 1 do not think we can be more precise in reply to your queBtion. Apart from the c Larif icalion of our at citude towarriB the American action, there are, of course, also political is 1 uee associated with any extension of oil activities beyond Kuwait's territorial waters. underwater development in the Persian Gulf should be arranged on a basis mutually agreed between the various littoral states, but it seexae likely that Hi is will be difficult to achieve in practice. i am sending copies of this letter to Freeae- Fennefatner and hoscop. fours sincerely, hu • K.L.STOCK* ji.l .DonaicUiOn* Lsq., CJ . 1., irxxia Giiice, S.W*1* (w 1076/391/76) i? Oiui j. Gh OiJ-XCh, LONDON, S.W.l. 2 Bth J anu»ry, 1946. Dear Harrison, 1 ciiClose a copy of the minutes of the meeting recently held at the Foreign Office to discuss President Truman's proclamation regarding jurisdiction over the subsoil beneath the sea immediately adjacent to territorial waters. 2. I am consulting our Secretary of itate regarding the conclusions which we reached and should be grateful if, afc agreed at the meeting, you would inform me in due course of the views of the Secretary of B cate for India. 3. 1 am sending a similar letter to Porter, Dodds and titock* fours sincerely, od • HA.Freese-Pennef ather. F . A .K.Harrison , 5sq*, 'India Office*Copy (W 1075/391/76) &gt; ’-S &gt;&gt; C0 Juriadiotion over the Sub-aoil beneath aea, i m mediately adjacent to territorial waters « A meeting was held on 16th January in Mr.Beckett’s room at which the Following were presents . Vv.K. Beckett G.C.BoJDodds G. W.Lepper K. L.Stook ?• A.K.Harrison L. Porter B.A.Greenhill B • £ • • Gage T.Wikely F•A.Fallat H. W.A.Freese-Fennefather Foreign Office iin Chair) Admiralty Ministry of Fuel and Power M in is t ry of F ue 1 and Po wer • India Office. Colonial Office. £•.2 .Secretariat Foreign Office. Foreign Office. Foreign Office. Foreign off ice. Mr.Beckett opened the meeting by explaining the position under the agreement whica we had contemplated making between ourselves and the United States with regard to tae Bahamas# whereby each of the two parties would refrain from endeavouring to acquire by occupation the sub soil beneath the sea immediately adjacent to the territorial waters of the other leaving the latter free to do so. The Americans had been thinking along the same lines with regard to the suosoil adjacent to United States territorial waters and on 26th September President Truman had issued a Proclam ation i co^y attached ) extending American jurisdiction over the sub-aoil adjacent to the whole length of their coast. The Americans, in fact# he.d done unilaterally wnat we were proposing to do by agreement, and their action had already had repercussions in Mexico and other countries, which regarded the proclamation as a useful precedent and, in the case of Mexico, had already used it as such. A'e should therefore consider what our line should be. Should wes (i) Complain of the American action, putting in reservations etc. (ii) Bo nothing, or (iii) Take positive action ourselves with a view to establishing our position not only in the Bahamas but else where as well, following the American example? As regards (i), we would not be likely to alter what has now become the declared policy of the united States and indeed our policy with regard to the Bahamas was designed to achieve a similar result in the m limited area to which it related. As Kuwait and other countries, for whose interests we were responsible* would require a lead from us as to whether they should use the American action as a precedent, we clearly could not adopt the alternative of doing nothing, whatever other merits, if any, this course might have. it remained, theref ore, to see whether it would not suit our book to follow the American lead ourselves and make some public pronouncement indicating that we approved its general principles in internatianai law. / AA discussion followed on the precise implications of President Truman’s proclamation and Mr. Beckett pointed out that it amounted in effect to a claim by the Americans of nothing less than full sovereignty over the sub-soil in the area in question^ although the word 'sovereignty' did not appear in the document itself. The proclamation referred to the Continental Shelf as being 'an extension of the land mass of a coastal national and thus naturally appertinent to it'. This, and the argumentation of tne proclunation as a whole, indicated quite clearly that it was not intended merely as a claim to ownership of the natural resources of the sub-soil, but that the United States Government regarded themselves as thereby entitled to exercise full sovereign rights* as a result of which they could e.g. issue the licenses for exploitation, make arrangements for policing etc. in whatever way they chose, precisely as on land. While this policy might be simple to carry out in the western hemisphere, where the geographical and political questions were reasonably straight forward, it was evident that if we adopted this policy ourselves there would be areas {notably the Persian Gulf J in which its implementation would be likely to give rise to certain com plications. m the Persian Gulf, for instance, there was no limit to the 'Continental Shelf* at all and the boundaries between the areas over which the various states would exer cise sovereignty of this kind would have to be agreed betweth the states concerned in accordance with 'equitable principles’*, and the present conflict of interests and territorial claims in that area was such that agreement in many cases would be difficult to reach. The American proclamation, however, specifically made provision for such cases being dealt with in this manner {in the penultimate sentence of the document) and we could only hope for the best as regards the success of its application as and when each case came up for con- sideration. iSxcept in the important Persian Gulf area, the line of delimitation should not be difficult to define in most cases, and on balance, we should stand to gain much more than we should lose by expresoing our agreement with the American policy and by adopting its principles ourselves as it might suit us best in each area concerned. The meeting therefore agreed in the following: {!) That it appears that the best policy for His Majesty*s Government to adopt would be publicly to recognise that the principles contained in the United States proclamation with respect to natural resources of the sub-soil and sea bed of the Continental Shelf are sound and of general application. It would be preferable to issue a public statement recognising these principles than for His Majesty's Government immediately to issue a similar proclamation applying these principles legislatively to all 'British* territory since the drafting of such a general proclamation would at once involve questions as to whether it should be extended to protected states and other dependencies whose position is somewhat complicated. {2) That if {!) is approved and acted upon, the Governor of the Bahamas and the Governor of Jamaica might make proclama tions applying these principles to the sea bed adjoining the Bahamas and Jamaica respectively. These two cases seem to be clear since the geographical situation is exactly similar to tbat off the coast of the United States and they are moreover in the same general geographical area. / { 3 }' That an investigation shotila be begun immediately as the application of these principles in other parts of the world. In particular the case of the Pers’ian Gulf seems to demand particularly early and detailed consideration. The Persian Gulf is so shallow that the whole of it might be considered to bea-continental shell within the meaning of the united States proclamationand therefore as an area where the sharing oi* the shelf between the Adjacent states should be determined on equitable principles, in this connection the claims to jurisdiction over the bed of the sea over pearl fisheries might be taken into consideration. 14) Particular attention ie directed to the last sentence of the United States proclamation that the character as high seas of the water above the continental shelf and their right to free and unin^eded navigation are in ro way affected* In this connection possibly suomarine cables YThich merely touch the bottom might be considered rather to oe in the water than on the surface. 15) Supposing that the conclusions above are adopted, it would seem desirable that before any action is taken the Governments of India end the Dominions should be informed or consulted and no doubt the .Foreign Office would also consult the liinbassy at Washington and indeed any other of its missions which it is thought desirable, .burther, it way be argued that since the free and unimpeded right of navigation is recognised and is already in existence, any constructions wade above the sea bed for the purposes of exploitation of minerals below it must be such as not to impede navigation. The application of ' this point in the Persian Gull may a b dnufiihaT^oe important. (6) When the views of the Departments on the above have been obtained, the answer to the application of the Kuwait Oil Company can be considered and agreed. Sxt. 707/46 POLICY OJ? THg UHITSD STaTjSS WITH JtSSfJiCT 10 THi£ SATUTlAL RaS0URC33 OF ■ TH3 3UB30IL aK) S3A BED OK THE COSTiHtiUTAL SHELF..1 f BY THS PaaSiD^T OP 'i’H3 UfclTSD STATES OF AMERICA A PROCLAMATION. WHEREAS the Ciovernmont of the United states of Araerioa aware of the long r?nge world-vude need jofor new eouroea of petroleum am other minerals, nolaa tne view that efforts to discover and make available new supplies of these resources should be encouraged} and WHEREAS ito comi'etent experts are of the opinion that such resources underlie many parts of the continental shelf off the coasts of the United states of America, pnd that with modern technological progress their utilization ia already practicable or/will become so at early date; and 'HEREAS it is the view of the Government of the United States that the exercise of jurisdiction over the natural resources of the subsoil and sea bed of the continental shelf by the contiguous nation is reasonable and just, since the effectiveness cf measures to utilise or conserve these resources wo Id be contingent upon co-operation and protection from the shore, since the continental shelf may be regarded as an ex tension of the land-mass of the coastal nation and thus natural ly appurtenant to it, since these resources irequently i Dsn a seaward extension of a pool or deposit lying within the territory, and since self-protection compels the coastal nation to keep close watch over activities off its shores which are of the/of the nature necessary for utilization of these resources; HOW, TH&amp;REFORii! X, HARRY 3. TRUMaK, President of the United States of America, do hereby proclaim the following policy of the United States of America with respect to the natural resources of the subsoil and sea bed of the continental shelf • Having concern for the urgency of conserving no prudently utilizing its natural resources, the Government of the United States regards the natural resources of the subsoil and sea bed of the continental shelf beneathffthe high seas but contiguous to the coasts of the United States as appertaining to the United States, subject to its jurisdiction and control. In cases v.here the contine ntal shelf extends to the shores of another Swate, or is shared with an adjacent State, the boundary shall be determined by the United States and the State concerned in accordance with equitable princip— les* The character as high seas of the waters above the continental shelf and the right to their free and unimpeded navigation are in no way thus affected. jU ITHES3 WHiiRiX)F , I have hereunto sot my hand and caused the seal of the United States of .America to be affixed. lOUE at the City of Washington this twenty-eighth day of September, in the year of our Lord Nineteen hundred and forty-five and of tne independence of the United States of America the one hundred and ^SSAL) seventieth. HARRY S. TRUMAN By the Presidents DEAN ACKESON Acting Secretary of State.Ext* 707/46 ilth February 1946* Bear Pennelather* Would you please refer to ysur letter iio* W 1075/391/76 of 28th January# forwarding a copy of the minutes of the meeting about jurisdiction over the subsoil beneath the sea immediately adjacent to territorial watere* The Secretary of State for India agrees generally with the conclusions of the meeting but considers that the Grovernment of India =houM be formally constated (and no* merely infon edg be fore any action is takeru 1 ton sending copies of this letter to Porter* Dodds and Stock. Yours sincerely, (iy/^d) E.r. Donaldson* H.'W.A. Preece-Permef ather* Esq Foreign Office.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/436</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/436</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 14/3 Oilfields in the Gulf outside Muscat territory'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-20T10:04:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 27; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to oilfields in the Gulf excluding Muscat territory.The discussion in the file relates to:Negotiations over concessions for oil exploration in the Trucial CoastThe impact of the negotiations on the behaviour of the Trucial Shaikhs and their territorial claims and boundary disputesKuwait oil – the jurisdiction over the subsoil and seabed immediately adjacent to territorial waters (ff 19-26), particularly in the light of a proclamation by the President of the United States of America (Harry S Truman).Included in the file is a copy (folio 17) of a telegram dated 2 March 1938 from the Political Agent, Kuwait, to the Secretary of State for India, London, conveying the news that the Kuwait Oil Company had discovered oil in Kuwait territory.The principal correspondents are: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Trenchard Craven William Fowle); the Political Agent, Kuwait (Gerald Simpson de Gaury); the Secretary of State for India; and the Managing Director, Petroleum Concessions Limited (Stephen Hemsley Longrigg).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>President, United States of America</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oil</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>