<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:01:27.087Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Copy of demi-official letter No C.143A-8/1, dated the 11th March 1948 from Major Stewart Political Agent, Muscat to Sir Rupert Hay Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. i t ( I Please refer to your telegram No 207 dated the 6th March 1948. 2. During a talk I had with the Sultan on March 10th, I told him that we had reason to believe that Nalat State may approach him with a proposal for the sale of Gwadur, and enquired what would be his reactions. He immediately replied that he would not view any such proposal with favour, and that in any case he was bound by treaty not to cede any part of his territories save to the British Government. He went on to say that he realised times were difficult and that it was not impossible that Kalat may even try to seize Gwadur .by force. If so, he said, the world would know that Gwadur had been lost to him by force of arms and he would not greatly mind. Any qssfet question of a sale, however, involved his honour and that it was not compatible with his honour to dispose of the territories which had been handed down to him by his ancestors, in return for money. Although, he added, he^would always be prepared to give consideration to any views expressed by His Majesty’s Government, and should His Majesty’s Government itself wish to take this territory on lease or otherwise, h* would be very ready to listen to any proposals they may have to make. 3. In reply I said that up to the present I had merely been instructed to pass on to him the information which had come to His Majesty’s Government's notice that the Khan may possibly approach him with a ±y view to arranging a sale, tut that His Majesty’s Government had not given me any indication of their views in the matter. Generally speaking 1 got the impression that the Sultan had already some idea that he was likely to be approached by the Khan and that if His Maj esty’s Government urged him to negotiate a sale, he would probably agree, if some formula could be found wher «£y• ' ; » 4 » • . ' lo . iC 1 &gt; *1^ ; • o i s ■ .a. rj . ■ e : r j- ■-: ) c 'J: i &lt; - . O' • ;;r.- ;:oo joji a •• d'j: ^ '.d3 l : iiy&lt; on all bov £■. - I. ..o, ■ . ■ ’ ' . • : a o :: ' r ’ r .+ i. 3 1 e 3 j i I Tix 1 2 1 • ’ . ' 1 ■\i ,■ ■ v v r o. a’ v r. ..'7 c) c' cr'. ? L f a ^ .i .7 •'•’•• &gt; . t. ■ ■ .the transaction would not appear too commercial. 4. Finally I said that I would report the result of our conversation to you and that I felt sure you would }.ike to discuss the matter yourself when you visit Muscat at the beginning of April. In the meantime I stressed the necessity of ensuring that the Wali of Gwadur should not allow himself to be entangled in any political manoevring which may be going on between the Khan and the Nawab Bai Khan Gichki. He said that he would bear my warning in mind but that he felt very unhappy about the position as the acting Y/ali recently sent there was without any experience and he had no other experienced, intelligent person whom he could send to relieve him./*o* INWARD TBLEORAM TO OOiy.MnmvwAT.TTi RELij / i/f^f A ALLOTTED TO X^OLITICAL (3) DEPARTMENT 2o ^ INDEXED ^ M ^Q M U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER EN CL/ilR IL R. Karachi, 15.50 hours, 19th March, 1948. 15.00 hours, 19th March, 1948. IMPORTANT No. 270. Sebfc. My telegramJlo^22 7 March 8th . Kalat. Ministry of Foreign Affairs issued press note last night announcing that States of Kharan, Las Bela and Mekran had applied for accession to Pakistan and that accession of all three had been accepted. 2. Press comment draws attention to the fact that, with the accession of these three feudatories to Pakistan, Kalat State has not only shrunk to less than half its oicvious area of 73&gt;000 square miles, hut has also been left without any outlet to the sea. Copies to Mr. Harrison F. 0. Mr. Tull Political Regy. (12)This Is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate it to persons outside British and United States Government Service.!. Inward Telegram to Comm onwealth Relations ALLOTTED TO POLITICAL (B) DEPARTMENT D. II. CYPHER (TYPEX) FROM: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN RPD.TO: KABUL ( NO,28 ) D. Karachi, 17*30 hours, 20th March, 1948* R. 16,30 hours, 20th March, 1948, IMMEDIATE No, 2?6. • SECRET My telegram 270 March 19th, Kalat, Foreign Minister Kalat has repeated to me his telegrams of 19th March to Pakistan Ministry of Foreign Affairs and to Zafrullah Khan at Lake Success regarding accession of Las Bela, Kharan and Mekran to Pakistan, Texts follow in my two immediately succeeding telegrams in clear, not repeated to Kabul, 2, I was informed by Ministry of Foreign Affairs official this morning that decision to accept offers of accession was taken by Pakistan Cabinet after Jam of Las Bela, Chief of Kharan and Nawab Bai Khan of Mekran had seen Mr, Jinnah on 17th March and told him that if Pakistan was not prepared to accept their offers of accession immediately they would be compelled to take other steps for their protection against Khan of Kalat’s aggressive actions. I understand that they accuse the Khan of (1) attempting to win over Chagai and Mekran Levy Corps (2) inciting people of Kharan against the Chief (3) sending his younger brother to Mekran with instructions to stir up people against Bai Khan (4) attempting to deny railway and road in Bolan pass to traffic by sending tribesmen to fire on trains and cars and /(5) spreading2 - (5) spreading false and malicious propaganda against Mr* Jinnah personally in Kalat and elsewhere in Baluchistan. 3* Pakistan's decision to accept accessions cannot fail to have serious effect on whole structure of Kalat State* Apart from economic consequences of loss to state of third of its area and outlet to sea, recognition hy Pakistan of • independence of three Chiefs who have hitherto acknowledged, however reluctantly, (? sovereignty) of Khan as head of Brahui-Baluch Confederacy strikes at foundation of Confederacy and so at structure of the state. Reactions of the Khan (apart from telegraphic protests) are not yet known, out risk of serious developments are recognised here and Colonel Shah, Joint Secretary in Ministry of Foreign Affairs, is flying to Quetta tomorrow. He will discuss situation there with agent to the Governor General and then proposes to have interview with Khan of Kalat at which he hopes to persuade him that his own accession without further delay is only course which can avert trouble. Copies to: C.R.OA Mr. Harrison F.O. Mr. Tullm inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ALLOTTLL) TO POLITICO DEPARTkENT (B ) D.II v . EN GLAIR : ! PROM: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN P/iKIST/iN. 823 D. TO IMLSDI. 1 TE KliR^CIil, 17.30 hours, 20th March, 1948. 17-.00 hours, 2oth March, 1948. No.277 My ituaeliately preceding telegram. Telegram from Foreign. Minister Kalat dated 19th March to Foreign Karachi repeated U.K. High .Commissioner Karachi. BEGIN S. The attention of the Kalat Government has been drawn to a radio Pakistan announcement that the Pakistan Government have accepted the accession of Kalat’s two feudatories, Las Bela and Kharan, and the district of Mekran. The Kalat Government requests that these reports should be immediately and publicly denied. The action reported by the radio would be contrary to the Standstill agreement (groups corrupt) last July and recently reaffirmed in the United Kingdom House of Commons by Mr. Gordon Walker, Under Secretary for Commonwealth Relations. His Highness received a personal communication on behalf of Quaid - 1 - ^zam Jinnah stating that the relations between Kalat and Pakistan would now be negotiated between the last Governments. Formal approach to the Pakistan Government is under preparation and the Kalat Government would protest strongly against any action in anticipation of receipt of their first formal communication. His highness feels strongly that Pakistan as a Muslim State will disire to take no high-handed or unjust • action against a Muslim neighbour and on these grounds also he is confident that this mischievous report will be denied immediately. E NDS . Copies to C.R.Q. Mr. Harrison. F.O. Mr. Tull. vaninward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office R?S ‘h ALJuOTTED TO POLITICAL (B) DEPARTlvi^N T EN CLAIR - mom U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER in PAKISTAN ). II. I). Karachi, 17,30 hours, 20th March, 1948. 16,30 hours, 20th March, 1948. immediate No.27 8. My immediately preceding telegram. Telegram from Foreign Minister Kalat dated 19th March to Foreign Karachi repeated Ukcom Karachi, Begins. nis highness the Khan of Kalat received on March 9th a communication on cohalf of 7uaid-1-Azam Jinnah stating that Hio Excellency nad decided to cease to deal personally with Kalat S uate negotiations-, and to leave the conduct of the negotiations to decide the future relations of Pakistan and Kalat to the Pakistan Government. as you are aware there nave heen up to the present no formal negotiations to settle this matter, but an informal request for access presented to His Highness personally by Qaaid—i—Azam at Sioi was considered by the Council of Sardars of the State, including Nawab Bai Khan and Nauladad Gichki Meier an Sardars. -lie Sardars unanimously asked His Highness to press for three months time to consider this matter. In accordance with Quaid—I—Azam*s letter and the Sardars* request a formal communication to the Pakistan Government is under preparations. There are no reasons why this negotiation should be spoilt by precipitate unilateral action by either party. The Kalat Government have, however, hoard a radio Pakistan annoancemeno oiint tne x^akistan Government have accepted separate accession of ..uas Bala and Kharan, Kalat State feudatories have (sic) /and Mekran- 2 ~ and Mekran, a District of the Kalat State, The Kalat Government nave asked for this report to he denied. d^e Kalat Government strongly request you to take steps to ensure that no illegal or hostile auction should he taken against Kalat State hy the Foreign Office during your absence and repeat the assurances that Kalat desires to reach a satisfactory accord with Pakistan hy negotiation and that the Government have taken no decision for or against accession, and will take no such decision until you have yourself discussed the matter formally with Kalat representatives. Kis Highness the Khan feels strongly that Pakistan as a Muslim State will desire to take no highhanded or unjust action against a Muslim neighbour, and on these grounds also he is confident that this mischievous report will he denied immediately. Ends. Copies to C.R.O. Mr. Harrison F. 0. Mr. Tull,f&gt; f\ o\/, wLlr owc F : HI ttc CE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR THE UNITED KINGDOM CHAMBER OF COMMERCE BUILDING WOOD STREET KARACHI © So , No. ^ J To 8 th March, 1 47f Your D.O. letter No. Ext.254/48, dated 23rd February, 1948, to Hay about the method of correspondence on Kalat-Gwadur affairs, a copy of -which vras sent to us. 2. The Pakistan Ministry of Foreign Affairs, with whom 1 have discussed this matter, agree to the procedure suggested in para. 3 of your letter, as do we. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Hay in Bahrain. F.A.K. Harrison Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office King Charles Street, LONDON, S.W.l.E This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and ^ J ;&lt; the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate ** to persons outside British and United States Government Services. r i/ ■ItE) V' Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office /.M. 0 Pol,1016/48 CYPHEPl (typex) TO: POLITICO PEPARTMEITT (B) J)lQt ^ / * U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN. / , K ^ (SENT: 20*30 hours? 5th March, 1948.) ^ / 1* ( fj/' ; W N ''ysc • JZ. IMPORTANT. No.454 .Kalat.. Following question is for answer in parliament on llthMarch. Begins . To. ask the Secretary of State wnether his attention has 'been drawn to the refusal of Kalat to join Pakistan; and whether it is intended to offer, without prejudice to Kalat’s relationship to the Dominion, 'a treaty of friendship and/or alliance to the Khan. Ends. &lt;j • -t have no information other than a press report from Daily Telegraph correspondent dated Karachi 2nd March. I propose, subject to your concurrence, to reply on following lines. Begins. My attention has been drawn to a press report that Kalat has refused to 1 .f . accede to Pakistan. I have no reason to believe, however, that negotiations have come to an end. A standstill agreement is understood to be in force. The matter contained in the second part of the question does not therefore arise. Ends . 3. The following might be useful for possible supplementaries• Begins . When power was transferred last year Kalatvas regarded by the Crown not as an independent sovereign entity but as an Indian state. /H.M.G.’s4 \ H. J.i. Lj * r s policy in regard to relations between tbe Doiainions and tbe Indian States applies therefore to Kalat. Ends. Begins. H.M.G. consider it important that a very close understanding should be arrived at between Pakistan, and Kalat or all matters of common concern. Ends. 4. please telegraph reply, and if any later information is received please report it by loth Larch.iMo&amp;k This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate it to persons outside British and United States Government Services. V Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office Allotted to Political (B) Department D, II CYPHER(TYPEX) FROM : U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN D. Karachi, 4 p,m. 8th March, 1948 R 1 *40 p.m. 8th March, 1948 No,227 From Burnett, Your telegram No, 454. Kalat. Pakistan Government received on 4th March official letter from Prime Minister Kalat intimating results of discussions on accession in (A) Lower and (B) Upper Houses of Kalat Assembly, namely (A) preference for Treaty instead of accession and (B) request for further time for consideration. This letter has not yet reached Cabinet to whom it is being submitted, and reply proposed to question is therefore suitable. 2, Secret . I understand that Mr.Jinnah, who has hitherto personally conducted negotiations with Khan, has now sent letter to His Highness regretting that their efforts since last October to reach friendly settlement have not been successful and informing him that future negotiations will be handled at official level by Ministry of Foreign Affairs through A,G,G. Baluchistan. 3* I also understand that the Kalat Prime Minister, Mohammad Aslam who is Pakistan Officer, and report of whose resignation has appeared in press, asked a few days ago for permission to visit Karachi for consultations but has been advised to remain at his post - officials of Ministry of Foreign Affairs had discussions with Fell who left here for Kalat on 6th March, and seem to hope that he will be able to induce the /Khan2 I Khan to implement promise to accodc, which ho apparently gave personally to Mr.Jinnah at Sihi. Copies to: Mr.Tull, Foreign Office Mr.Harrison ? External Dept. IFILE From: The High Commissioner for the United Kingdom in Pakistan. To: Commonwealth Relations Office, London, S,W,1« No.: SAVING. CONFIDENTIAL £-&lt;%. . Folloviing for Donaldson* My Savingr am No.39* 18th February, s', trs^ JfrrCt-- I understand that question of Gwadur was not raised by Khan of Kalat with Governor-General during latter 1 s visit to Baluchistan and that subject was only mentioned casually by one of Khan’s officials to member of Governor-General’s staff. Ministry of Foreign Affairs consider it very unlikely that either the Khan or Nawab Bai Khan Gichki would attempt to seize Gwadur by force, although the Khan would undoubtedly be glad to purchase it from the Sultan in the improbable event of the latter being willing to sell. 2 . I understand that cause of present dispute between the Gichki Nawab and the Khan is the former’s reluctance to continue payment of half the revenues of Mekran to the Khan in return for the latter’s protection against external aggression and internal dissension. The Nawab apparently considers ihat the price paid for the Khan’s protection is too high, particularly in view of * Mekran’s oil producing prospects. He is now in Karachi, but is unlikely to r eceive any encouragement from the Pakistan Government pending Kalat*s decision on accession. Should Kalat Assembly in forthcoming Session decide against acceding to the Dominion, it is conceivable that the Pakistan Government might then accept direct accession of both Las Bela and Reran, and also institute direct relations with the Gichki Nawab, whose territories lie between those States now under the Khan's suzerainty. But although Ministry of Foreign Affairs are cautious in expressing opinion as to result of Kalat Assembly’s deliberations on accession issue, it seems probable that decision will be in favour of acceding to Pakistan. i GRAFFTEY SMITH. REPEAT No. / SAVING, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Ay' fr/^ \ ■ **. ’ // . . ■ 1 .|M| b i S A~ V I N G R A I . U Date : 16«2#2 {j8* No : Jcf Saving. Prom : High Commissioner, Karachi. C*R.O. 8i'&lt;} Repeat to Political Resident, Persian Gulf ^'and Political Agent, Unseat# / _ /W^ /C tVwC^k*-/ TP ■ &lt;■ ^ ‘ } ta v. CONPEDENTIAD# 4 ju/ ^ Following for Donaldson# —•7--/ Bahrain letter 162-S of 19th Januar^r ana subsequent ^ correspondence regarding Gwadur# I will try to ascertain latest position when Governor-General and his advisers return from current visit to Baluchistan# Mr# Jinnah is meeting Khan of Kalat, and decision regarding accession of Kalat to Pakistan may he reached during visit. Press reports that question will he discussed hy Kalat Assembly when it meets on February 21st. Attitudes of tribal leaders of Makran will be more clearly defined when question of Kalat*s accession is decided# GRAFFTET-SMimDRAFT LETTER Lieutenant-Colonel Sir R. Hey, K«C«I«E., C.S.I., Persian Gulf Residency, Ext.322/48 /■j \ } L- L Bahrein, h 1 spare copy) n / A// -iuKj \j' j t . V Would you please refer to your demi- official letter 5 to Donaldson, No.202-3 of 22nd January regarding Gwadur. * Copy to:- r 2. With regard to paragraph ^of your lettei Sir L. Grafftey-Siaith, we agree that the Political. Agent might infona K.B.E/, C.M.G., U.K. High Coiirflissioner in the Sultan on his return to Muscat in March akistan. Chamber of Cormuerce Building, that we have reason to believe that Kalat State Y/ood Street, Karachi. rp/- 'f9(6&gt;4u&amp;. (3 would be to such a proposal. If the may approach him direct with a proposal for the fc* Pfailed sale of Gwadur and; ask him what his L j , . -ft . H&gt; ^X ^.rTJ .ultx h Sultan then asks what the U.K. Government's views are about the sale of Gwadur the Political Agent might reply that if the Sultan desires to consider the proposal seriously the matter will ie feel f / ,/ 5 ,r&lt; o'* &lt;V / be referred to the U.K. Government that an answer on these lines would be /preferable. preferable to telling the Sultan that we are willing to leave it enti^^^^ him to decide^ ^-Ar, ^ ^ ^ wt ljli|JuIa iTia'^ up n ;r min^e- until we know the Sultan’s attitude and until the international position of Kalat is clarified,f 4 ho ^olitioal Agent might explain th.&gt; embigurtT in 3. •fith regard to paragraph 6 of your letter'' * we agree that it would be better to aay nothing to the Sultan at the moment regarding the possibility of ^tribal incursion from Kalat into (iwadur. We certainly do not want to enter into ahy commitment to defend CJwadur against aggression, do not quite see-why the Sultan »« 0 uld e^eeV'auch a guarantee from the U.K. Government. Mr*- 4. 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Grafftey-Smitn anT? Stewart. Q- spare copy for / F - A. K. HARRJSON ill■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■I w KiAFT LSSTm Lieutenant-Colonel Sir R. Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein. Ext.25A/AB o FEB 1946 f * Would you please refer to your demi- official letter to Donaldson No.162-S of l^h January regarding the method of correspondence on.the Kalat-G-wadur affairs. 2. On local disputes ; such as customs Copy to:- Sir L. G-rafftey-i-Smith, K.B.E.7 C.M.G., U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan, Chamber of Qbmmerce Building, Wood Street, Karachi. questions, the U.xC. G-overnment are not of / ii / Qourse directly concerned^and we agree that it . would be best to leave such matters to be settled so far as possible by direct discussion between Gwadur and Kalat officials. 3. As regards matters of a higher level, since you represent Pakistan as well as U.K. interests it seems suitable that so far as Pakistan interests are concerned you should correspond direct with Dundas at Quetta as you propose. Ar$r correspondence should, however, presumably be copied to the G-overnaent ofPakistan and (for the U,K.^Government's own infonnatiory) to the U.K, High Commissioner A in Karachi and Commonwealth Relations Office (/or the foreign Office after 3'Jst Marctyj. 4. Our viev/s on the above point are subject to the concurrence of Grafftey-Smith to whom a copy of this letter is being sent. indicate- Perhaps he would be good enough to knew whether he agrees. A. jit HAKKJSOJV \j■HH Commonwealth Relations A O Office Reference F+ //7/ 9 I'll *Ks&gt; v\ COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE, 4, CENTRAL BUILDINGS, MATTHEW PARKER STREET, LONDON, S.W.I. 1 v ^ r* February, 1943. y /- r. 2C, / /&gt;/i &amp; / ? jm&gt;. fo* Dear Harrison, I think you should see this telegram to the Government of Pakistan because of the reference in paragraph 2 to the retention of the subsidiary R.A.F. post at Jiwani. Gary of x the Air Ministry tells me that he understands by a that the Khan of Ka^t is slightly restive about the matter as he thinks we are asking the Government of Pakistan to agree to the retention of the Jiwani post. This, of course, is not so as all the telegram asks is that the Government of Pakistan should agree to make available certain accoaniodation at Mauripur. 7fe shall, of course, eventually have to obtain the agreement of the Khan to the retention of the post at Jiwani, and I imagine that you will handle this side of the question when the occasion arises. At present I gather that the Air Ministry must have the Mauripur situation cleared up first, as if they cannot retain that post Jiwani is of no use to them. Yours sincerely.This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate it to persons outside British and United States Government Services. Outward Telegram from Commonwealth Relations Office SEk^ICE finance department F.11717 /48 CYPHER (TYPEX) D. II TO: P.iKISTAN (GOVT.) RXPTD : INDIA (GOVT.) No.176 (Sent 5.15 p.m. 26th Jan., 1948) IMPORTANT No.91 Ministry of Finance (Defence) . Please see para 2 of my telegram No.23 to India dated 4th January repeated to you as No.8 and para 4 of India’s telegram No.254 dated 11th January. Please confirm that you also accept liability for units in question. A separate reply is being sent about rest of telegram No.254. 2. After the 31st March 1948 the Royal Air Force will wish to maintain at Mauripur and at the subsidiary post of Jiwani staffs and accommodation on a scale sufficient to deal with the present average of 99 scheduled air services and eight other R.A.F. move ments per month. 3. These requirements are now substantially covered at Mauripur by the staffs required in any case to maintain the Communication Flights. They would not, therefore, in our view, justify any change in the financial arrangements already proposed up to the 31st March. 4. We are at present examining the precis© establishment and accommodation requirements of the R.A.F. at Mauripur after the 31st March to meet the commitments stated in para.2 above. We should be glad if the Government of Pakistan would in consultation with the R.A.F. authorities at Mauripur agree to make available such domestic and technical accommodation as may prove to be necessary for the purpose. /5. This2 f — 5. This would of course be without prejudice to any financial arrangements which may be agreed for the period from 31st March onwards. These are being examined here and we shall be putting forward our proposals separately* Conies to: Sec* C.O.S Treasury M/Defence Air Min. Committee. Mr* Peter. Defence Staff. R. I * A.P.L.O. Er . Mr. Mr. 'r. McSwiug, Hosie. Cary. Smyth*11 r S L CONFIDENTIAL D.0. No.273-S PERSIAN GL -.- 1 -' j KA &gt;? imdexei the 29th Jarfiary EX^ 8 try D f&gt; S' Njy Please refer to my demi-official letter \ *o.202-.3, dated the 22nd January 1948 reg arding Gwadur. 2. I forward herewith a copy of Stewart’s demi-official letter No.C/47-8/1 dated the 17th January with its enclosure and a copy of the paragraph of his intelligence Summary referred to together with a copy of my reply. 3. The aspirations of Aawab Bai Khan Gichki further compli- - cate t..e Gwadur situation and I should not he at all surprised if 1 he were to make an attempt to reassert the independent or semi independent position previously occupied by the Gichki Nawabs vis-a-vis the Khan of Kalat. In any case the Nawab’s attitude makes it even more unlikely that the Khan would be successful in raising the Mekran tribes for an attack on Gwadur. It is however I possible that he might attempt to use the Mekran Levy^Corps which 1 is a well-trained force though as it is locally recruited it is | doubtful where its allegiance would lie if the Nawab was opposed j to the Khan’s plans. /W&gt; /iCi Jai/tfu* l 4. The latest information inclines me even more to suggest /to the Sultan the desirability of stationing a detachment of the Muscat infantry at Gwadur. In the event of any kind of rebellion breaking out against the Khan in Mekran it is obviously desirable that some such force should be present in Gwadur if only to deal with refugees. Personally I consider it more likely that the Nawab will continue to intrigue secretly rather than resort to force, but It is as well to be prepared. 5 if 5. The Sultan is now expected back in Muscat about the middle of March and I am planning to visit him early in April and to go on from there to Gwadur to obtain first-hand impressions of the situation there. I hope I may be able to persuade the Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf to arrange for me to do the tour in one of H.M’s ships. 6. I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to Grafftey-Smith and 'without its enclosures to Stewart.r' Political Agency H. ..f^^-Gonsulate Muscst, the 17th January, 1948. hhCIj^T 9.0.No.C/47-8/1 Dear Sir Rupert, Will you please refer to paragraph 324 of^my iTiteili-gence Summary No.22 of 1947 in whicl. I passed on a report from Gwadur concerning Nawab Bai Khan Gichki. I now forward for your information a copy of a letter dated the 31st December, 1947 I have received from the British Agent, Gwadur. I do not place too great credence in the veracity in this report; nonetheless I feel the Sultan’s position in Gwadur is sufficiently precarious vis-a-vis both Pakistanand the Khan of Kalat without his getting mix ed up in any intrigues of neigh-I bouring tribal leaders. If you agree therefore I feel I should mention to him at the firs opportunity after his return to Muscat I that I have heard reports of dissatisfaction among some of the Mekran tribal leaders, and warn him of the dnagers of allowing anyone in Gwadur to become involved in quarrels, the ultimate result of which could not be other than detrimental to his inter-£ ests, which clearly demand a peaceful frontier. Yours sincerely, 3d/- A.C. Stewart. The Hcn’ble She Rupert Hay, KCIB., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN oOo- (Copy of letter No.432/S dated 31st December, 1947 from the British Agent, Gwadur to the Political Agent, Muscat). Sir, with reference to para. 180 of my Intelligence Summary for the period 12th October 30th November, 1947, I have the honour to state that immediately after Nawab Bai Khan Gichki had left Gwadur for Jiwani en route to Karachi, there was a rumour that he had a secret conversation with Saiyid Badr bin Saud, then Wal: of Gwadur. His younger brother, Mallick Dinar, returned from Karachi in S.S.Barpeta on the 6th December 1947. 1 put him up as a guest and.was able to extract the following information from him:- (1) Nawab Bai Khan Gighki is net friendly terms with the Khan of Kalat. (2) Nawab of Kharan, Jam Sahib of Lasbela and Nawab Bai Khan Gichki are trying to bring pressure to bear upon the Khan of Kalat to join Pakistan. (3) Nawab of Kharan and Jam Sahib of Lasbela have to all intents and purposes disclaimed suzerainty of the Khan of Kalat. (4) Nawab Bai Khan Gichki demands rights to collect reven ue from the Gichki tribe in Mekran himself. (5) Nawab Bai Khan Gichki asked for an assurance from the Wali of Gwadur that his men would not be refused shelter, food stuffs and cloth etc. in Gwadur in case there was open hostility between him and the Khan of Kalat. (6) Nawab Bai Khan Gichki had a private letter sent to the Sultan of Muscat through the Wall of Gwadur. (7/) Nafrab Bai Khan Gichki interviewed Quaid-e-Azam Muhammad Ali Jinnah at Karachi on the 3rd December, 1947. (8) The Khan of Kalat invited Nawab Bai Khan Gichki to a Jirga at Dhadhar - winter H^ of Kalat State- but the latter did not attend it. (9$ Lastly he said that the present Sultan of ...uscat had stopped payment' of their annuity from the Gwadur customs. The [! ii /sum involved...- 2 - The sum involved was only Rs.2/8/0 per annum, .„ta»en of their rights in Gwadur. 2. Nawab Bai Khan Gichki is still at Karachi. He serit a t telegram to .the Wall of Gwadur on the list December 1947 asking if the Sultan had returned to Luscat from Salalah. It is presumed that he is either anxious to ’know the result of his talk with the Kali of Gwadur and eventually communicated to the Sult&lt; n of Muscat in the form of a letter, or he may be desirous // of seeing the Sultan of Muscat personally. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- Hidayathllah. British Agent, Gwadur | ■o0O‘ Kxtract from Muscat intelligence Summary ho.22 for the period 1st - 15th December, 1947. ** ** ** 324. Nawab Bai Khan Gichki, visited Gwadur on the 27th October from Turbat and was accompanied by his son, brother and a large retinue. He is related to the Khan of Kalat and is one of the leading personalities of Mekran. The party stayed at the Rest House for one night and were invited by the Wali to a dinner party and a tea party by the British Agent. The party returned to Jiwani the next day. ** ** ** ** ** ** **\ SECRET D.O. N0.274-S PERSIAM GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN . the 29th January, 1948. v&gt; t Please refer to your demi-official letter No.C/47-8/1 dated the 17th January 1948 regarding Nawab Bai Khan Gickhi. 2. I approve of your discussing the matter with the Sultan on his return to Muscat on the lines proposed. 3. With reference to item 9 in paragraph 1 of the British Agent’s report I have found nothing in ray records about the annual payment by the Sultan of Rs.2/8/- to the Gichki Nawab. Would you kindly let me have any information that is available with you about it and let me know when the payment was stopped. 3d/- V.R. Hay Major A.C• Stewart, O.B.E., Political Agent, MUSCAT ’LB*I■■■■■■■■■ #0 Ej-. B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., foreign Office, London, 3. W. 1 . DRAFT LETTER Ul^A' *7 feb 1948 a. Would you please refer to Donaldson's letter to Hay No.Ext.83/43 of 12th January^ of which a copy was sent to you^ about Gwadur-Kalat affairs. ■flro 2 . I enclose herewith copies oft# letters from Hay No. 202-3 of 22nd January and 162-3 of 19 th // T January^together with dj^ft replies which are, f^hope, self-explanatory. 3. Would you please let me know as soon as possible whether you concur in these drafts. F - A - k marrisonSi«M {W't\&lt;un4a^) Rp&gt;? J GWADUR o * 51 d Please refer to Mr .Donaldson 1 s letter of 12th January and see the .Political Residents letter of 19th January (No.l62-S) and 22nd January below. . , In his letter of 22nd January the P*R. raises the question of -what should be said, to the Sultan of Muscat about the desire of the Khan of Kalat for the cession to him of Gwadur. Prcm the U.K. Government* s point of view there are seme advantages from the strategical aspect in the Sultan of Muscat retaining Gwadur, particularly because we have the right to use Gwadur for military or civil aviation purposes under our Air Agreement with the Sultan. These rights are, however, in the nature of an insurance, and we are not using Gwadur for these purposes at the ^ moment. It is perhaps unlikely that we should be able to retain such rights were Gwadur to be ceded to Kalat (or Pakistan). 3* On the other hand, the Khan of Kalat (through Mr .Pell) has expressed his desire that Gwadur be ceded to Kalat, „ a JLl yjtk U mainly because Gwadur is .used for smuggling into Kalat. • * ^ Mr.Pell has also hinted that failing cession to Kalat, the local tribesmen might occupy Gwadur by force, but the P«R. is not inclined to take this threat seriously. 4# In these circumstances the P.R. (l) proposes that the Political Agent should mention to the Sultan in March that we think Kalat State may approach him proposing the sale of Gwadur, and that we are prepared to let ham decide what action to take. (2) The P.R. does not think that it iSpAgs^rable to warn the Sultan about th^possibility of fogeerelr incursions into Gwadur since he ask us for a guarantee against such aggression. My cwn view is that the P.R.* s. proposal in (2) is apUight. We certainly do not want to enter into any ccmmitment to» defend Gwadur against aggression. As regards (1), it would&gt; % v - 2 - seem better that the P.R. should ask the Sultan in the first plaoe what his attitude would be to such a proposal. If the Sultan then asks the P # R. what H«M.G-.*s views are about the cession of Gwadur, he should reply that if the Sultan desires to consider the proposal seriously the P.R. will refer it to I do not see why we should make up our minds until we know th * ' fir) yt /y Kdkf'b 6* In his letter No, the question of methods of correspondence in connection with disputes between Kalat and Gwadur,^G-wadur is, of course, part of an independent State{ viz* Muscat) and aeemiing that Kalat fn hr aw-indepen^nt State, the U.K* Goveriment are novcon^med,0n loca#icusterns)matters. fhe best .course would be for thistto be iscussed locally between Gwadur and Kalat officials. As regards matters of a higher level, it is to be noted that the PjR* also represents the interests of Pakistan and so far as Pakistan interests are involved^ it seems suitable that the P.R. should correspond direct with Mr. Dun das at Quetta as he proposes. Any correspondence should, however, presumably be copied to the Governnent of Pakistan and (for the U.K. Government* s own information) to the U.K* High Cannissioner in Karachi, and C.R.0.(^«3r Foreign Office/ najoJ Secretary. Political Department. Do you agree generally with the line proposed above? fc Kjl £ C* ^ prv M e o v r%i OK &gt;ViVc tO't ^ PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY /CU&gt; S^ 4 FTRiFTtF 1ECRET D.O. NO.202-S 2o ^ f as 1 (NO EX ED ^ \Ww f j/^u -DA'iD-E - 0CT | PEF f SIAK S’ A ■ R? *■ ') * &gt;U the 22ncr .cji 7 * 9 riLi - ijP-A Ii; January, 1948 •A / % \ ^ \\ l§) Y Please refer to your demi-official letter No.Ext.83/48_ dated the 12th January, 1948, regarding Gwadur. 2. This has crossed my demi-official lette rs Nos.l62-S and 163-S of the 19th January in which I have discussed amongst other things the status of Kalat and the Gwadur-Kalat boundary. 3. Fell's allegation that Gwadur is uded for a 'black market and smuggling trade' are almost certainly true. It was so used throughout the war. Its use as such however is almost certainly to the benefit of the surrounding tribes snd from what I know of them they are most unlikely of their own accord to make an attack , - on Gwadur. Fell 1 s warning therefore can only be interpreted as ^ . thre at b j L the Khan of Kalat to emulate the example the Pakistan l fe 0 ^ f authorities have given him ?n Kashmir the Sultan refuses- to cede it. i.nd occupy Gwadur by force if 4. I think it unlikely in any case that the Khan will endeavour to implement his threat but if he were to do so the Sultan would almost certainly appeal to us for help and would be most resentful if we refused to give it, especially as unless some declaration to the contrary has been made in the meanwhile he cannot fail to £ regard Kalat as being within the British Commonwealth. £il 5. In view of our present and possible future commitments at Gwadur e.g.' the installation of a v/ireless station c.f. my demi- official letter No.2257-S dated the 30th December, 1947, I think &amp; : that as soon as the - Sultan returns to~Ti.uscat we ought Xc* inform him that we have reason to believe that Kalat State may approach him direct with a proposal for the sale of Gwadur and.ask him what his attitude is likely to be in such circumstances. The Sultan will propabTy enquire what our views on the subject are, especially as, under the Agreement of 1891 printed as No.XVII at page 317 of nitchison Vol.XI he cannot cede any part of his territory^ save to the British Government, and although I previously stressed the importance of our retaining some kind of foot-hold in Gwadur, unless we are prepared to give him a guarantee against aggression I think we shall have to reply that the matter is one which we are willing to leave entirely to him to decide and that we have no strong views either way. 6. It is also for consideration whether we ought not to warn the Sultan that we have heard that the Khan is contemplating using force, without disclosing the source of oup information, so as to° give him a chance of making arrangements for its protection e.g. by sending a detachment of the Muscat Infantry there as he has only about 20 armed Arab guards on the spot at present. ' The disadvant age of this is that the Sultan may at once say that he regards us as responsible for preventing any invasion from Kalat, which would plac&lt; - us in an embarrassing position. On the whole I am inclined to say l nothing to him on the subject at present, the more so as I am doubt ful if the threat need be regarded very seriously. 7. I should be grateful for early instructie£s'in ordep that the Political Agent may if necessary approach tijAbSultan on:,.the subject as.soon as he returns from Dhofar at the. end. of Ffebfuary or beginning of March. / E ■ 8. I Stewart. am sending conies of this letter \ I.P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, LONDON, S.W .l LB j Ur-if1th and l' ]/ yv CCNl^IDLNflAlU D.0» No.163-S , k\* 'O fclX '“• ; ■ • PERSIA GULF LI31DEICY L^riRr IP the 19th January, 1948 &lt;g&gt; ^vl / p t 5 ^' v ,: % ; l lA ca^csi^ w ' .^yAjU' Please refer to ry demi-ofletter ' jo. 162 - S dated the 19th January, 1948 regardTng Gwadur^ Kalat ai'^airs. 2. When I was Agent to the Governor-General, Baluchistan I proposed that a certain line should be regarded by political officers as the Gwadur-Kalat boundary for practical purposes without any endeavour being made to obtain the consent of the two Rulers. Prior did not agree'with the proposal but the Government of India eventually approved it in their ZXi. memorandum No.D. 1640-BPG/4G dated the 1st Octobe r. ' 1946 and subsequently forwarded to the Agent to the Governor-General Baluchistan and this Residency , authenticated copies of the map showing the proposed boundary. 3. Did the Government of India forward you a copy of the correspondence and of the map ? If not I will send you the papers now as I think they should be on record with His Majesty’s Government even though with the changes that have taken place in India the'arrange ment made is probably now of little value. E.p. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, LONDON. 3.W.1wm ppp wmmtm / CrQ^r xi/i, . IXaL ^ ii UTJ ii TTvT I forward herewith a copy of sj. telegram the ISth January, 1948. received by the Political Agent, Muscaf, from the ^British Agent at Gwadur, rapcrting alleged interfer ence by a Kalat State official inside the Sultan of iiusc.at's territory. 2 . The incident reported is not of great import ance in itself but it raises the question of the manner in which disputes between Gwadur and Kalat State should be dealt with in future. I am in favour of leaving all such matters to be settled by direct discussion between local officials, whenever possible, but it is almost inevitable that disputes will arise which will have to be dealt with at a higher level. 3. I gather from the Indian newspapers that the Khan of Kalat has not yet decided to accede to Pakis tan and I do not know hoy/ relations with the Kalat State are being conducted so far as His Ma jesty 1 s ( Government are concerned. I would suggest that in any case I might be permitted when necessary to corres* pond direct by demi-official letter with Dundas at ^uetta regarding Kalat-Gwadur affairs, the correspond ence being copied to the U.K. High Commissioner in Pakistan and if it is considered necessary to the Pakistan Ministry of External Affairs and Commonwealth Relations. Would you kindly let me have your views ? 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Grafftey-Smith. E.P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Offic nOKPGh , o.W. 1 t i| - 1 T3T From British Agent, Gwadur. To Political Agent, Muscat. No.424/C Dated 20th received 21st December, 1947. A certain (omission) Mohammadan labour Kalat State official at Gunz employed/inside the Sultan of Muscat 1 s territory to improve the track on the Peshkan frontier. Acting ^ali of Gwadur is arranging for work done to be undone. ’Kb* - BRITAGENTwas were in a position to undertake negotiations with a foreign State. Mr. Fell iruv n' n.mc - ;■ that the position of Kalat was somewhat anomalous^since it was not part of la^istan ^^ hut had been recognised by the Pakistan oh j * rmHy Ay-fc* ui^L-nrruj f j authorit ies^as an independent btate in ireaty relations (before the Indian Independence Act) with the British Crown. and that its exact status 1^ still undetermined. llU&gt;oKj^ ^ -ilr. Fell continued that the Lalat G-overnment ^ . , / f, Ui -j ^ /&gt;^7 Y/ere concerned with the use of Gwadur port/for the purpose of evading Kalat customs regulations. A flouriO^ng black market^traoe was established there, to the prejudice of Kalat revenues,and this was a position which the Kalat authorities could not allow to go on. He hinted that if they did not receive satisfaction, tne local trioesmen would be likely to taxe the law into their own hands and seize the territory for the benefit of Kalat. What would H.M.G-. * s attitude be towards such a development? I said that I did not think / thatthat we would/he bound to help the Sultan to recover his territory or. resist/invaders in such |Qk^CM circumstances, andjjthat as Was not a member of the United hat ions jhe could himself bring the matter before the Security Council. But I should have tnought\that this would be an act of aggression which would bring its own condemnation^and that if the Kalat Government had grounds for complaint againsl the Muscat i^tate authorities, their proper course to take it up with them^ through whatever channels were operand see whether they could not arrive at an accommodation. 2 &lt;ir. Pell enquired whether the British Political Agent at Luscat would intervene with the Sultan on behalf of kalat State. I said that we had undertaken to look after the interests of India and Pakistan in the Gull States and that if, a request were received from the Pakistan Government to make representations to any of the Gulf Rulers on their behalf, the British political authorities would no doubt be /willing-- willing to act for them. But if Kalat was an independent btate, as hr. Bell had claimed, there saeme^/to te no obstacle in the wa^y of direct -tslX- between the two Governments either try correspondence or by the despatch of an authorised representative. H.M.G.»s attitude in this matter / Lit , ^ was that were concerned only with the obligations/v^nch the Sultan had undertaken towards tva .tara and that we had certain strategic requirements u* which we should wish to see safeguarded. Subject to our rights being preserved^we were not concerned with the internal affairs of a part of the Sultan’s Dominions. Mr. Bell had to leave to keep another appointment and our conversation ended inconclusively^ out I gathered that we were likely to hear more of this before very long. I am sending a copy of this letter to the foreign ufiice and to the^d.k. High Consnissioner at Karachi, .gn ufiice and to theyd.ii. High Commissioner e hi. / 6^0^) 9c A /y6&lt;viL cxjry (S;d) E f. DOr’AUtf _ oA s •^r &gt; ^ Not*, t^i %&lt;' h^}J C R-Q , 1 * L U-*' •' ^S' , j - -p - y&gt;ea&gt; s /^ -X iU /tu Co&lt;**tt_^£l CG4&lt;*s&lt;ri&lt;U**^7' T^^rr. &lt;^o /Ua ' U^rviy /- / 0 / ^ ^ ftrlQ'-zi ^ ^CUa^Uau Jy 6^S*&lt;S \XLc'cJ^ y Mctcu^y tin xc.o^-4^' ^ /£ -^wv ft /^cUcJ / 4 : ^ CiJ . '’■B' ^wv, &gt;&lt;/^ ^ ' it ^ ^ (&amp;** ■ AeC^c* '004 6&lt;Ucrz&gt;^^ tj.c^. /y-m** t&amp;G—uJ^C. cj' Jb ^ 4&lt;£rtfcJc* C&lt;-t* '&amp;&lt;»A r «^l' 4 -Vt^Cr oic&amp;~tJ \.oJ cc « '-f* c ^ ( “ y^aZ^T^=^ Sizr, r ftcoA c*. ^ 9ik**CJx \^ Stm^/ol Ur .RuLil/old r\ * VO tV N't e^f itV Sir P.Patrick in his note of 8th January refers to the following points; (a) the possibility of Mr .Pell being required to leave his employment in KaJLat. The position is that Sir L.G- jmith considers'that Mr .Pell is in a slightly invidious position in Kalat, and as tk@ 4 result of this v;e have i infom^d Mr .Pell that he may be required to leave the Khan’s employment if called upon to do so/ (b) Kalat 1 s relations with Pakistan. Latest information we have received is contained in Sir L*G.Smith* s Savingram of 17th Cctober y 7/hich is to the effect that, although no final agreement has been reached, the Khan has assured Mr.Jinnah that he will continue to observe the terms of the Standstill Agreement and that he has no intention of negotiating with India or Afghanistan.The Pakistan Government, it appears, regret their hasty recognition of Kalat’s independence and wish to obtain the Khan* s accession to Pakistan by means of an Instrument similar to that accepted by other States. Sir L.G.Smith believes that the khan* s main anxiety is to avoid signing any document until he has reached an agreement on the Leased areas. (c) Yarning against the unconsidered recognitioncis independent of States such as Hyderabad. I attach the Foreign Office circular*referred to which informed His Majesty’s Representatives abroad that H.M.G. did not intend to recognise any Indian tate as Jt separate international entity on 15th August and that the U.S. Government shared H-M.G.’s desire that Indian States would associate themselves with one or other of the New Dominions.r CXA*r- I - J * K_ -J* ^ w -•&gt; *■ - f “ r^~ (uZl sU tA^ /U —J ‘-- - «- ^ ^ pjz&amp; A/jvv'fc *li Secret ary. P olUt ic al De gt .. Under-Secretary of 3tate« I attach in the form of a draft letter to the Political Resident, a record of an interview I had this morning with Hr. Fell^who claim® to he a representative of the Kalat State G-overrsnentj about relations with Muscat concerning Gwadur. I was speaking from recollection without the papers before me and did not refer in any detail to the correspon dence which took place with the Government of India in July last. The line I took, however, was in conformity with what we said then and I do not think that we are called upon to make any further response to what seems to be clearly a 'fishing enquiry. If Mr. Pell should renew his approach (which I told him I thought was somewhat irregular) I think he should be told that the British authorities in the Persian Gulf could not be expected to intervene between Kalat and Muscat unless they were asked to do so by the Pakistan Government in their role as looking after Pakistan interests in the Gulf States^as we agreed when H.M.G. took over the^Gulf administration. ty\ c 6 . 1 . 48 . ^ v' 0 *' eV &lt;*/* o W, ^tVl Cs \'Vv'*\iV'£j i*' VCcVcA' Sv'c-Vrc. i\ Nn^, CW. Gi CeV^c-tW.^. } €avCc. uT c y ^iV-^vV tVno OCvu.TI-KS DOCUiiENT IS THE PE MAJESTY' 8 GOVEM ENT indexed C-£u ■ fa. / SECRET I. B. (47) 165 12th September, 1947 COPY NO CABINET INDIA AND BURilA CO-^ITTEE ACCESSION OF INDIAN STATES TO THE DOMINIONS OF IN’JJlA Alip 1 ~ : j0l'lY3TAl\!' Mcaorandun by the Minister of State for 1 Commonwealth Relations The India and Burma Committee may like to have the I following summary of information about the progress of negotiations for the association of the Indian States with the Dominions of India or Pakistan. It is derived partly from Lord nountbatten's reports up to 15th August and partly from what the U. K. High Commissioners in India and Pakistan have since reported. A. Dominion of India 2. All salute States (that is to say all but the petty States) within the orbit of the Dominion of India have been invited to accede and s except Hyderabad and . Junagadh, have acceded to the Dominion of India for the three subjects of Defence, External Affairs and Communications. The numerous matters with respect to which the Dominion legislature may consequently make laws for these States are detailed in the-Schedule to the Instrument of Accession (Annexure 1). This Instrument, devised by the Government of India, States Department, closely resembles in form the Instrument proposed by Lord Linlithgow for accession to Federation under the 1935 Act. All the above States, except, we gather, Hyderabad and Junagadh, have also entered into 'Stand-still^ I Agreements with that Dominion whereby, until new agreements have been made between the parties, all agreements and arrangements on matters of common concern existing before 15th August between the Crown and each State remain in force, so far as appropriate, between the Dominion of India and the State. A copy of this Agreement is annexed (Annexure 2). The matters, mainly of an economic character, to which it particularly applies are detailed in the Schedule referred to in the Agreement. The terms and form of the Standstill Agreement were suggested to the Government of India by the Political Department of the Crown Representative before his functions ceased. / 3 ,3 . The Nizara of Hyderabad would have been ready to accede to a* United India; but the division of India on a communal basis has put him in a dilemma. If he accedes to the Dominion of India he will have trouble with the Muslims in his State which, although only Tofc of the population, are regarded as the most forceful element in the State. If he accedes to Pakistan, he v/ould be going counter to the compulsions of geography, the Hindu majority in the State would be stimulated by the Congress Party into rebellion, and the State would probably be subjected to considerable economic pressure from the Dominion of India. The Hyderabad Government therefore wants to enter into a treaty, rather than federate, '■1th the Dominion of India. In particular, it is anxious to be free of any obligation to participate on the side of India in the event of war betv/een India and Pakistan, and claims the right to secede from the Dominion of India in the event of that Dominion leaving the Commonwealth. Hyderabad stands in a separate category J from any other Indian State being larger and more populous than several of the Provinces of the Dominions and probably more wealthy. Negotiations between the State and the Dominion of India ar» in progress and Lord Mountbatten has agreed to continue to represent the Dominion in the negotiations. Hitherto the Dominion of India have declined to consider any settlement short of Hyderabad's accession for Defence, External Affairs and Couiiiiunications. There ar^ press reports that the Nizam declared on 21st August that he had assumed independent sovereign status on 15th August and that he had taken the title of 'King'. 4. Junagadh is a State situated on the sea coast of Kathiawar, with a Muslim Ruler and a population, mostly Hindu, of about 600,000. The Ruler has announced his intention of joining Pakistan. The State can maintain sea communications with Karachi through its ports, but in other respects is economically linked to neighbouring States which have joined India. 5 . There are many petty States in Kathiawar and Gujerat which enjoy very'limited, or no, jurisdictional powers. Four years ago, some 327 of these States were, by our mediation, attached for administrative purposes to large neighbouring States such as Baroda and Nawanagar, with which they have economic and in some cases dynastic associations. The effect of Section 7(1)(b) of the Indian Independence Act was to remove from these small States the limitations on their internal authority imposed by the British authorities and continued by the -attaching' States. It was expected that in practice the 'attaching' States would retain their influence over them. The Dominion of India have however decided to assume the jurisdiction exercised by the Crown Representative in these /petty3 - Pbtty otates pefore.thoxr attactoat, and they claia m tnis to be acting with the general agreement of the tmofs and Talukdars concerned. They have offered to allow these “Rulers” to sign Instruments of Accession, concoamg tnis jurisdiction. ^ The object of the Government oi India m assuming this jurisdiction is said to be mainly to obtain a vantage ground from which to observe the activities of the maritime States of /estern India whose sea borne trade with the interior might escape Indian CUSuOblS GULIGSo ^ e . 0 ^oo^U°Ko High Cohiniissioner in India ha,s also reported inroruation frou coniidential sources indicating that (pertain other States besides the petty attached States m mostbrn India are in the process of accepting the paramiountcy of the Dominion of India* The Maharaja iiOikar 01 Inciore is stated to hcive sought the Government India's, recognition as his heir of the son of his present American wife, which has been refused, but to have •pp?t?ow d -o^?T^ ce r -2* Mis Prime Minister, a retired prieish xOlice Officer, who had not been in favour of Indore s accession to India* Balasinore, a small State moujerat, appealed to the Government of India and neighbour abates about the timie of the transfer of power tof °m acc0L1 Dt of internal troubles. An officer of one Bombay Government with provincial police has restored oraer tnere* A new Dewan has also been appointed on the advice of the Government of India* The present Ruler of ■^ewa has also appealed to the Government of India for help against the intrigues of his father, the late Ruler, who P was excluded from the State some years ago by the Crown Representative under suspicion of grave charges but has iggests that 100 now re-entered Rewa^ these instances go to Sir Terence show that after Shone years and more of parauountcy by the British Crown, some States, for all that they may say about their independence, are by their own actions and the force of past habit straightaway recognising a new paramountcy of the States Department of the Government of India. The High Commissioner further St ates in tiie suggests that if elected representatives of the Constituent ^ssembly decide that the States should extend their accession to the Indian Union to all Central subiects unoer the new Indian Constitution it may be difficult for tae Rulers to resist such pressure. It appears that ' the Congress organisations in the States are now hinting that within 12 months every Ruler v/ill have to give his people self-government. The State of Cochin has lust given a lead in making this concession. ' ~ B. Pakistan 7. Pakistan is moving more slowly tlian the Dominion of India in negotiations with the States in its orbit. Mr e /Jinnah- 4 - Jinnali appears to have made attempts to attract States in the orbit of the Dominion of India away from accession to that Dominion b offering, on behalf of Pakistan^ to accept a ^treaty rather than federal association with them, and it was only under strong personal persuasion from Lord wountbatten that the maharaja of Jodhpur, a State adjoining Pakistan, (whose example it was thought would have been followed by other States of Rajputana) was induced to accede to the Dominion of India and to refuse lire Jinnah's offer. The Pakistan Government have Sot up a Negotiating Committee to deal with each State separately. So far, no States appear to have concluded an arrangement with Pakistan, tout besides Junagadh, Bahawalpur, Khairpur and Chitral, the principal States^adjoining the Dominion, have declared their intention to become associated with it. Bahawalpur has also concluded a standstill agreement with Pakistan. 0. Kashmir lias concluded Standstill Agreements with Doth Pakistan and the -Dominion of India/ The main economic interest of the State is to preserve a treaty right under paramountcy to import goods from abroad free of customs duty. The iiaharaja is a Hindu, while the population is mainly huslim, although there is an influential Brahmin ruling class. The State is dependent on Pakistan for its communications with the outside' w?rld s although it has a common frontier also, though in difficult country, with the Dominion of India, The maharaja has not disclosed his hand but has spoken of holding a Referendum. 9. ^ Pakistan has entered into negotiations with Kalat on the basis of recognising the State's claim to independence and of treating the previous agreements between the Crown and Kalat providing for the lease of „uetta and other areas, which would otherwise lapse under Section 7 (l)(b) oi the Indian Independence Act, as international agreements untouched by the termination of paramonntcy. Tne Khan of Kalat whose territory marches with Persia is of course in no position to undertake the international responsibilities of an independent State, and Lord iiountbatten, who before the transfer of power, was warned of the dangers of such a development doubtless passed on tnis warning to tae Pakistan Government. The United Kingdom High'Commissioner in Pakistan is being informed of the position and asked to do what he can to guide tne Pakistan Government away from making any agreement with Kalat which would involve recognition of the State as a separate international entity. One consequence might well oe that the Pakistan Government would be obliged to concede to Kashmir a similar recognition, although Kashmir has certainly never been independent, having /been$z) @ ANWEXURE 1 INSTRUfCNT OF ACCESSION OF WHEREL'-S the Indian Independence Act, 1947» provides that as from the fifteenth day of August, 1947&gt; there shall be set up an independent Dominion known as INDIA, and that the Government of India Act, 1935’ shall, .with such omissions, additions, adaptations and modification as the Covernor-General may by order specify be applicable to the Dominion of India; AID 7'HEREAS the Government of India Act, 1935» as so adapted by the Governor-General provides that an Indian State may accede to the Dominion of India by an Instrument of Accessic;. executed by the Ruler thereof: KOV7 THEREFORE I Ruler of in the exercis-e of my sovereignty in and over my said State Do hereby execute this my Instrument of Accession and 1. I hereby declare that I accede to the Dominion of India with the intent that the Governor-General of India, the Dominion legislature, the Federal Court and any other Dominion authority established for the purposes of the Dominion shall, by virtue of this my Instrument of Accession, but subject always to the terms thereof, and for the purposes only of the Dominion, exercise in relation to the State of (hereinafter referred to as “this State') such functions as may be vested in them by or under the Government of India Act, 1935* as in force in the Dominion of India on the 15 th day of August 1947 (which Act as so in force is hereinafter referred to as 'the Act'). 2. I hereby assume the obligation of ensuring that due effect is £iven to the provisions of the Act within this Statu so far as they arc applicable therein by virtue of this my Instrument of Accession. 3. I accept the matters specified in the Schedule hereto as the matters with respect to which the Dominion Legislature may make laws for this State. 4. I hereby declare that I accede to the Dominion of Indi. on the assurance that if an agreement is made between the Gov rncr- General and the Ruler of this State whereby any functions in relation to the administration in this State of any lav; of the Dominion Legislature shall be exercised by the Ruler of this State, then any such agreement shall be deemed to form part cl this Instrument and shall be construed and have effect according 1; . 5 . The terms of this my Instrument of Accession shall not be varied by any amendment of the Act or of the Indian Indepcndenc. Act, 1947* unless such amendment is accepted by me by an Instrument supplementary to this Instrument. 6 . Nothing in this Instrument shall empower the Dcminion Legislature to make any Jaw for this State authorising the compulsory acquisition of land for any purpose, but I hereby undertake that should the Dominion f*or the purposes of a Dominion /lawlaw which applies in this State deem it necessary tc acquire any land, I will at their request acquire the land at their expense or if the land belongs to me transfer it to them on such terms as may be agreed, or, in default of agreement, determined by an arbitrator to be appointed by the Chief Justice of India. 7• Nothing in this Instrument shall be deemed to commit me in any way to acceptance of any future constitution of India or to fetter my discretion to enter into arrangements with the Government of India under any such future constitution. o. Nothing in this Instrument affects the continuance of my sovereignty in and over this State, or, save as provided by or under this Instrument, the exercise of any powers, authority and rights now enjoyed by me as Ruler of this State or the validity of any law at present in force in this State. 9* I hereby declare that I execute this Instrument on behalf of this State and that any reference in this Instrument to me or to the Ruler of the State is to be construed as including a reference to my heirs and successors. Given under my hand this day of August, Nineteen hundred and forty seven. I do hereby accept this Instrument of Accession. Dated this day of August, Nineteen hundred and forty seven. (Governor-General of Inda).TTT^Ti v* i SCHEDULE THE OTTERS WITH RESPECT TO WHICH THE' DOI.JHIOK LEGISI^*TURE M/.Y M/JCL r.W3 FOR THIS STx-TE. E.. Defence » 1. The naval, military and air forces of the Dominion and any other armed force raised or maintained by the Dominion; any armed forces, including forces raised or maintained by an Acceding State, which are attached to, or operating -with, any of the armed forces of the Dominion. 2» Naval, military and air force works, administration of cantonment areas. 3 ♦ Arms; fire-arms; ammunition. 4* Explosives. B. External Affairs . 1. External affairs; the implementing of treaties and agree ments with other countries; extradition, including the surrender of criminals and accused persons to parts of His Majesty’s dominions outside India. 2. Ad miss ion into, and emigration and expulsion from, India, including in relation thereto the regulation of the movements in India of persons who ar^ not British subjects domiciled in India or subjects of any acceding A.toto; pilgrimages to places beyond Ind ia. 3. Naturalisation. C. Communications . 1. Posts and telegraphs, including telephones, wireless, broad casting, and other like forms of communication. 2* Federal railways; the regulation of all railways other than minor railways in respect of safety, maximum and minimum rates and fares , station and service terminal charges, interchange of traffic and the responsibility of railway administrations as carriers of goods and passengers; the regulation of minor railways in respect of safety and the responsibility of the administrations of such railways as carriers of goods, and passengers. 3. Maritime shipping and navigation, including shipping and navigation on tidal waters; Admiralty jurisdiction. 4* Port quarantine. b&amp;jor ports, that is to say, the declaration and delimitation of such ports, and the constitution and powers of Port Authorities therein. ^• Aircraft and air navigation; the provision of aerodromes; regulation and organisation of air traffic and of aerodromes. ft-7» Lighthouses, including lightships, beacons and other provisions for the safety of shipping and aircraft. 8. Carriage of passengers and goods by sea or by air. 9. Extension of the powers and jurisdiction of membeis of the police force belonging to any unit to railvyay area outside that unit. D. Ancillary . 1. Elections to the Dominion Legislature, subject to the provisions of the ;_ct and of any Order made thereunder. 2, Offences against laws with respect to any of the aforesaid matters. 3. Enquiries and statistics for the purposes of any of the aforesaid matters. 4* Jurisdiction and pov/ers of all courts with respect to any of the aforesaid matters but, except with the consent of the Ruler of the Acceding State, not so as to confer any jurisdiction or powers upon any courts other than courts ordinarily exercising jurisdiction in or in relation to that State.ANNEXURE 2 bet^en the st.-te cf ;^D THE DOriENION OF IKDi;,. VcHERK'.S it is to the 'benefit and advantage of the Dominion of India as well as of the Indian States that existing agreements and administrative arrangements in the matters of common concern, should continue for the time being, between the Dominion of India or any part thereof and the Ind inn States : Now therefore it is agreed between the State and the Dominion of India that: 1. (1) Until new agreements in this behalf are made, all agreements and administrative arrangements as to matters of common concern now existing between the Crown and any Indian State shall, in so far as may be appropriate, continue as between the Dominion of India or, as the case may be, the part thereof, and the State . (2) In particular, and without derogation from the generality of sub-clahse (1) of this clause the matters referred to above shall include the matters specified ir. the Schedule to this Agreement t 2. Any dispute arising out of this Agreement, or out of the agreements or arrangements hereby continued, shall, unless any provision is made therein for arbitration by an authority other than the Covernor-General or Governor, be settled by arbitration according, as far as may he, to the procedure of the Indian /arbitration Act, 1899♦ 3. Nothing in this Agreement includes the exercise of any paramountcy functions. State . Secretary to the Government of India.I 4k I suggest a somewhat revised draft which I think covers the ground and exposes rather less surface* 2* I agree that we should not let Kalat have any direct contact with the government of a foreign State while paramountcy continues* The position after 15th August is that whereas Kalat is no longer hound to us to have no such relations, we are nevertheless anxious to prevent such relations developing, because it is not our intention to recognise the States as separate international entities but rather to encourage them to associate themselves with one or other of the new Dominions* Contacts between the States and foreign powers would go counter to this policy because it would lead up to the recognition of the States' independence by those foreign powers* On the other hand, the alternative to Kalat discussing the matter with Muscat after 15th August is for the Government of Pakistan to take the matter up with Muscat and, in view of the close relations in the past between Kalat and Muscat and the special circumstances in the present case, the issue does not seem to me to be one on which we would be well advised to make a test case regarding direct contact between the btates ana foreign powers* Consequently as we cannot prevent Kalat taking the matter up with Muscat after 15‘fch August (although the Government of Pakistan may be able to) I think that we need raise no objection. c* 3 * The question whether we should allow the Session to go through is quite another matter* But if we are to prevent it we must do so not by seeking to bring pressure to bear on Kalat or the Government of Pakistan, but by the exercise of our influence and treaty rights over Muscat and I suggest that the Political Resident should be instructed as to what advice he should give to the Sultan in the master*/ • ^rln Q#. Donalds;^: /u Mr, i-_olitical Secretary V Proposed cession of Gwadur “back to Kalat. Please refer at Ext.690^47. to the minutes From the Government of India* s telegram 5289 he low it will he seen tnat halat State have now themselves made this proposal. When v/e consulted the Service Depart', ent 5 before about this,consensus of opinion was definitely against any move, and I should hardly think that subsequent political events have altered the basis of this opinion or made it necessary for us to consult them again. A draft telegram to the Government of India is submitted. ■ciWbto Bxtegnal Peyaytmant ^oBias to?’*' sif-ir^ptss*. ifi* *%■ pslto parly.U8o OS .'for Burma-. *J X “* , ^‘^ aU ° .Vest.US.for Burma. Mr * . , 0 ^2 e Ai» w v j!p.8.V.(4). , BeaWent Clerk. ' nyFfiEP, fo.T.P.) fflovernmant of India, Extern* Affairs * Commonwealth fielationa Cepsrvment Secretary of state fox India political Resident In the Persian &lt;J«lf Haw Delhi, 03.60 hours, 8th July 1347 08o36 hours, 8th July :i * 4? Kalat State hare sought permission to direst with Sultan of Muscat for return of &lt;5wadur 0 A similar proposal for ^.^XSter^ueston usual channels was recent*? . . ba impoaBlhle to w«th Rev on the ground that it would oe impoeoi eSjleS negotiations in the time- remaining Before retroeassiori of parainountcyo, ' views^ From To Hepastad to Data! H«soeivad NOo5289Dated the 30th April 1947. r JI * t- i ?- ■. I D.O.No.P/16. H f(f 4 $ flee^ [/} ^ XS) 19 Please refer to your secret arj&lt;I pereefaWl letter Ext•698/47 of the 15th April about Gwadur* 2. I have now heard from the Government of India that they do not intend to pursue their proposal A/ that the Sultan should be induced to sell Gwadur back to Kalat State. The India Office, London.mmm Please rjefer tS/plxon'js demi ofixcia 1 U-: x O.F.57C2)-:rG/46, da tec the 14 th Jaauc ry ,1947. 2. • The oult^n's i D tent eon o* -/Wcdu'- is somewhat oi an anachronism and from the purely practical point oi view there is much tc he sale in favour oi its retrocession by sale to Kalat. 3. Cn the other hand, a morarch like the ^ultan usually clings to every inch oi his territory, and, with rrior (ci. par graph 2 oi his lemi official letter do.C/464, dated the 26th September, 1939, to daroe), I find, it difficult to believe that he would seriously consider disposing of Gwsdur. However, as he made the suggestion himself in 1939 ostensibly for the purpose of raising funds it should b€ possible to ask him whether he wishes it taken up again now that the war is over, ' 4. I presume tnat if aovornm^nt o± India decide to pursue the matter they will consult his Hajesty ' s Government before asking me to take action. Yours sincerely, -gd)- r.. &lt; /^ightman , squi:? e, C . . . I. , C.I. ., 1 . ^. ., secretary to the Governannt o± India, external affairs ^apartment, New j-I hi. 11/4/47 pvS-m y~ i f- OFFICE OF THE POLITICAL RESIDENT, CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF, aboard H.W.S. '^'ildgoose 11 , D.0&gt;No,C/ll3 At Sea, dated 7th April, £94? r qb 7 ^ indexed 19 I forward herewith a copy of a letter received by the Sultan from one C. Henderson, The Sultan was mildly amused by the letter and is curious to know who Mr. Henderson is. I share his curiosity and should be grateful for any information you can obtain for us. E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., India Office, London. mummm rjHHMMNUNov. 25, 1946 Hill View, Park Close, Fetcham, Surrey, England. Your Excellency, Is there the smallest chance that the enclave of Gwadur could be sold to the Jain community of India? There are 1,500,000 Jains; and the community possess great wealth, and could offer a good price. If this matter could be considered, Mr. S.C. Jain Diwaker, Honorary Secretary, The All- India Jain Political Hights Preservation Committee, Seoni, Central Provinces, would be glad to hear from you. Yours sincerely, (SGD.) C.HENDERSON.Please refer to the noting at X. We have since received the Political Resident*s letter of 10th February, and have consulted the other Departments of H.M.G. concerned. Their replies will he found below* It seems that the^advantages of Gwadur remaining paid: of Ptfsfcat outweigh any possible advantages to H.M.G. in the elimination of a potential cause of friction between Pfcskat and Kalat* A draft letter to the Political Resident is submitted. I think that the position should be sufficiently safeguarded without our addressing the Government of India direct on the subject, . ^ -£l k .mm DRAFT LETTER. SECRET AI'ID PERSONAL. fcL'lb Lt. Col. W. R # Hay, C.S.I*,C. I # E., J Persian Gulf Residency, EXT»69^/4/. , Bahrein. CSfy T ^ J947 I* April, 1947. Hi ' ( /^V ^ Vta—I t Many thanks for your letter of the 10th February about the suggestion that the Sultan of Ifoskat might be induced to sell 1 Gwadur back to Kalat State. 2. The strategic aspect of this question had already occurred to us and 7/e have now consulted the Departments of H.M G. concerned on the subject. In view of the strategic ToHrfK^ advantages/in retaining the right to re-establish the air field „ [r**l * ^ and use the J&amp;eaplane^M? Gwadur both the Air Ministry and the Admiralty are definitely of the vieiw that Gwalior should remain tgt part of the territory of the Sultan at the very least until the political future of India is settled. The position has now, of course, been safeguarded by the fact that the right to use both the seaplane base and landing ground at Gwadur has been secured to H.M.G. by the Civil Air Agreement. 3. The Government of India have not addressed us directly /on(S,&lt;l) E on 'this subject, and we have thought it better, on the wnole, not to write to them about it* \ t v atoierc'i*.'I INDEXED A^v. ^ Dear Harrison, We have no observations to offer on the suggestion that the Sultan of Muscat might be induced to sell Swadur back to Kalat described in your letter Ho. i^xt^2J^4^47 cf the 19th February to Low. I am copying this letter to Dodds, Low and Ratcliffe Cousins. F. A. K. Harrison, Esq., India Office-WHI.9000 Ext. 86 j25' ?§) 0375/47 ADMIRALTY, S.W.l. IIth March, 1947. Secret. My dear Harrison,' Thank you for sending me a copy of your letter Ext. 214/47 of the 19th February about the possible sale of Gwadur to the Kalat State. 2. There are clear strategic advantages in retaining the right to re-establish the airfield and use the seaplane facilities in Gwadur. Assuming that India will not remain within the British Commonwealth N therefore, we should encourage the Sultan of Muscat to retain the Gwadur Enclave; at the very least we should preserve the status quo until the political future of India is settled. Yours sincerely F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., Whitehall, S.W.l. # -c+r/l 'tho* hvsir It* 1 ** fc ft* '76 JTel. No. Abbey 3411. ; MVI/BMK - .—.-I- 4 EXT Ext... C.30350/S.6 AIR MINISTRY, King Charles Street, Whitehall, S.W.l. IMMEDIATE 4th March, 1947 Dear Harrison, Thank you for your letter of 18th February about the suggestion that the Sultan of Muscat should be induced to sell Gwadur back to Kalat State* We agree with the Political Resident that it would be useful to have a pied a terre on the mainland in the event of an independent India becoming unfriendly or in the event of a future war in which India may remain neutral* Moreover, although Gwadur has not been mentioned in connection with recent proposals to investigate an alternative ^ar Fast reinforcement route avoiding India, there is a possibility that it may be before the investigations have been completed* We would therefore much prefer that Gwadur should remain as part of the territory of the Sultan* I have written to you separately on the question of ensuring that our right to use Gwadur in peace-time is covered by the proposed Civil Air Agreement with the Sultan* I am copying this letter to the recipients of yours* Yours sincerely. V V F*A^K* Harrison, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street, S* W. 1*JZMU JW' ^ 7/ ) 214/47 s G H IT Dear bow. The Governrnent of India have recently been considering a suggestion that the ultai of us at should be Induced to cell CJwadur (the Muscat enclave on the Mekr».n coast) back to alat tale, 2, On gene al 'rounds there i ^aich to be aid in fsvour of such an arrangement sine the existence of this enclave of Muscat territory i somewhat of an anomaly and give rise to a certain a.nount of friction between Muscat and Kalat. On the other hand it would appear at fir t si ht oh t it d ht be of considerable advantage to H* ,G. from the point of view of imperial strategy and air coanaunicstions to have (through the good ofiices of the dultan oi Muscat) a pied a tei're on the Metcran coast in vhe event of an independent India at oOiae futu, e da .e becoming unfriendly or lapsing into a st te of chronic disorder* o t will no doubt be av?ai-e ohat G.vadur was a port of c lt on the I perisl irv^ays x-oute until 193 d when the^ ran i erred to Jivmni, but the, till keep emergency moorin facilities there* Theie '• s also I undejc* tand a H*A*F* landinf-; 'round at Gwadur which became surplus to the requirements of the R* A*j; * from April 1 t 1946. e should be glad to knoo what importance if any from the long term planning point of view the ir iAinistry w-uld attach to the continued retention of Gwaaur by the Gultan of iuscat. I hould mention th w „he Sultan is not free to act in thi. mt.er without the a reement of of d*M*G* since in 1&amp;91 he pledged hie elf never to cede. ell/ •:* • I«OW, , Air inis ry. PKitehali, S. /.1.iaortgii,. e 01 oth-ijr^visG occup&amp;t ion a. y of hi dominions or dependencies save to the British Gov eminent 4* I am endin. a copy of thi letter to Dodds the Adirdralty, Ratciifi e Jou^^ns at the i inistiy of Civil viation and Gault at he foreign Uf l ice in case taey have any ob irvations to offer. Tour sincerely. ir. A. K. HARRfSON'C. SECRET PiRSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 1947. (g) / BAHRAIN. V V &gt; I forward herewith a copy of an express letter I have received from the Government of India regarding the Gwadur landing ground. This accords with the instructions I have received from you that the Royal Air Force are interested in no landing grounds other than Salalah and Masirah. 2. I have also recently been addressed demi- officially by the External Affairs Department regarding a proposal that the Saltan should be induced to sell Gwadur back to Kalat State. I sent a guarded reply in which I said amongst other things that I presumed His Majesty's Government would be consulted before I was asked to take any definite action. . 3. On general grounds there is much to be said in favour of handing back Gwadur to Kalat. The Sultan is an interloper there and his retention of an enclave in non- Arab territory will tend to become more and more of an anachronism. On the other hand it would appear that it might be of the greatest advantage to us from the point of view of both imperial strategy and air communications to v £/W M lOjL _ have a pied a terre in the event of India becoming unfriendly A or lapsing into a state of chronic disorder. I expect this has already been taken into consideration and that I .am merely wasting your time by raising the point but I should be grateful if you could kindly confirm this. E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G. India Office, LONDON. G.A.M.To Reptd. Repgu, Bahrain. Political, Muscat. No. D.654-BPG/46, Dated the 29th January, 1947. Subject : Gwadur air field. Correspondence ending Political Muscat No. S.1002, July 19th, 1945. 2. Gwadur landing ground became surplus to requirements of the Royal Air Force from April 1st, 1946. Presumably, by now the Muscat authorities have become aware of the abandonment of the airfield, but, . if you consider it necessary, the Sultan might be informed that the Royal Air Force no longer require the landing ground there. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd. R. E. R. Bird. Under Secretary to the Government of India. \ Copied G.A.MCol. G.S. Please see the note by Mr. Harrison below. There is no need for you to read the connected papers,which deal mainly with the political aspect of this case. The point at issue so far as we are concernea is whether Gwadur is likely to be strategically important to us. As Mr. Harrison states, this Port was previously used as a flying boat base, but after 193&amp; Jiwani was used for this purpose instead. Presumably the air Ministry should be consulted before we can say whether G-wadur is likely to be important to us in future. If, this is liicely to be the case, we must consider whether it would be more of an advantage to us if Gwadur remains part of Muscat, and was not ceded to Kalat. In the latter case if India becomes independent it appears likely from what Nehru has said recently that he will insist on Kalat being part of India, and we might not be able to make use of Gwadur should we desire to do so in future© I Before we give our views on this, I consider that the matter should be referred to the Air Ministry. 1 —*•’ 29.1-47.r / t \« D.O.No.l^-P.1/46,v 1 / ''i, ? &gt; '7JS V | Dear Weigh'Lman, Will O | If vf&lt; ’ 1 : ^ j p I L on-iriwrUL UTA Ziarat. - ^ September 18th f 1946. D$) iii^kinDytham, who knows tint npoblesci fron th&lt; Sultan or Muscat f B angle , han no^w studied it iron th&lt; Kalat noint or view and is return and the examin4tion of docuroBntB etc, ,ar difficulty, to MT ^rt a j^for.g financial surrounded on three sides by Kalat 4 an^l on ^he^Surth oy the sea. I aw unable to fcmtxp Hickinbothatfi*s arguwarits m so far as they aojly to Muscat’s mteresta, though or Itia facie they seera to be oound. I do f however, mpport the case he wakes out in favour of a move tlat to obtain retrocession of this small encli te lines referred to in &gt; Resident A^rsian (lulf ,h June l?k7 to the Foreign foreign h i^oiitical Departnent. an ^ent I will sut f\ilitical Ag^n shall be .grata ^ * r ndia.^ wishes to ;a snail nt ofln may tak e the ^ .at in 1 for an e the matter up officially:- K&amp;lat State requires another port +T. 0 U 0 + 0 offset th&lt;^ rrt 0 increase e damage, earthquake ar.d Owadur, thou^i tidal wave of 'ov.-mb^r 1940. The port ox Uwaaur, to potentially no leas liable to eqrthqiuike than ^aani is better protected ircm + he destructive effects of who are diainclined to rebuild pro tidal waves. Trader , .'VM their warehouses at Paam would willingly to G-^auu;* were j.alut offer them facilities there. disinclined to rfbuiJM in all probability mo tate in a position to of the oicturf picture Hickmbotham ur used to produce a surplus Muscat, this has of recent iminifcheo and in 1940 amounted ag 01 ifurjaes. The disadvantages to Muscat are the remote situation of Gwadur, constant friction between its inhabitants and Kalat State, ificiais, and uncertainty of, the future. These, it is elt, might be willingly exchanged for a substantia of ready money by a Sultanate whose finances Rave ells me revenue . , _ years,been considerabl to little more than oh 0 Muscat are the iption between its 1 ^ ^ ^ ^ orficiaiB, and ungertainty of, tnQ future. These, it ^ felt, might be willingly exchanged for a substantial sum of ready money by a sultanate whose finane been the cause or apprehension for many years. a cause 0 1 constant Ip ca disputes; it would effec £gich ma| welj develop t KM •ciai a ;ate will be in ihe trade of j rt __ in Baluchistan^aS osition to control the as well as a large urn of a seai cajaac; proportion/,mmmm HHH ■■ 'yn D.0.WO. F.67(2)-BPr,/48- •j Paw' Delhi .1. 2 ^ 5 ^ IOT«mber, • £t°vr A ,V ' VJJL^ K^ r I r«JT«P to Pot^lton^ dMii- dcginxil te-refer to Poup.ton's demi-official possibility of considering again the question of the return of Gwsdur to Ralat Stated Before Kay's comments are invited on this proposal, ffe should be glad t&gt; know whether you share Boulton's vie* that It is worth re-opening the subject on the lines suggested by Hickinbothnm. ? » r To The Honourable Lt.Col. Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.S*, Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Comals sinner in Baluchi at Ji . • • • • • 'Kohta' 28/-53CRST GSNT TO THE GOVERNOR GENERA AND GlilEF COMMISSIONER. Baluchistan. *&gt; i/.O.No. 12-P1/47 i ' «£V. Sibi / 4 \ 1947 letter No. ..Jf. F.57(2)-BPG/46, dated the 29th November 1946 regarding the possible return of Gwadur to the Kalat. St t °te? I agree with Poulton and recommend that the subject should be reopened on the lines suggested by Hickinbotham. Yours sincerely, Geoffrey Prior. H * Weigh “tman Bsqr. ,C.o«I»,C.I.H!«, I. C. o. Secretary to the Government of India External Affairs Department, New Delhi.ttt/Ai-X r-v External Affairs Department. ' Hew Delhi 3. ! Ihe / U(L~ January i i , Cs/yyulf | ' « ' ' V J I am deaire^f t&gt; eneltiaii heyAw lth a copy of Derai- offioial letter No* 12-P.1/46,, dated the 18th September 1946. frotu Colonel Pool ton proposing that Gwadur should be returned to Kalat and to say that Sir Geoffrey Prior his successor supports the proposal. 2. It is not the intention that the Sultan should be consulted at this stage, but we should be glad to have your comments. Yours sincerely, Sd/- H.E.R.Bird. *10 The Hon’ble Lt.-CoJ.W.H.Hay. Political torsiV Confidential. D.C.No.C/765. | Dear Beaumont,| Office of the 9 W' Political Resident,Persian Gulf) 'Camp, Bahrain, fflie ^ 6 th August 1946. «OJ A , p AP, your demi-official letter No. D.4S8-BPG/46 dated the 17th July 1946. 2 . I discussed the question of the Kalat-Gwadur ^ boundary with Prior when I took over from him. He expressed 'y// ijjno strong views on the subject and said he was willing fTU SXVr M° leave case to me to deal with. ®8 PsC| 94 f^ I have looked through ail the papers on the ^ subject in this office and adhere to the suggestion I made f - 1/ as A.G.G,Baluchistan that the line referred to in paragraph Jt&gt;- O Mi- H rJ* ^5 of Baluchistan Letter No.]-2^Pl /45 d^t^d— , ■ 1945 should be treated by political officers as t-he boundary for practical purposes. I would deprecate making any communi cation to either of the Rulers concerned on the subject as this would be likely to raise the boundary question in an acute form. I*** A* i ^ 4 # The existence of a presumptive frontier should prove of assistance to political of-i icers m deciding to what extent they are to support representations received from the two States concerned regarding indidents etc.ana in V recommending to higher authority how Such representations should be dealt with. The country concerned^is mostly desert * P(w^l‘ ' and very sparsely inhabited and cases in which i 1 ^ ^ ’ Jb*- necessary to take the presumptive frontier into considera- 7 ( 7 ,i . tion are likely to be comparatively rare. So far as ± Know r\A . the only case of the kind that occurred during my 2 * years tenure of the post of A.G.G.Baluchistan is that relating to two murders described in the latter part of paragraph 2 ^oi ' Baluchistan Lett er No. l2-ol /45 d at^ed_tae 12tn ivxarch 194o. l XL 5 # I regret the delay in replying which is due to an unsuccessful attempt to trace in uhe Bushire office the papers relating to the case referred to in the last ^ paragraph. * ' Yours sincerely, Sd. L.R.Kay. H.C.Beaumont, Esquire,^ Government of India, External Affairs Department, , New Delhi. fyim. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA. foREifiti eecfictAm-s iette*. Ne. IMI* f.iCEIVEO 9 5 1 * Il '1 v \ A K .? ' ■ ' J U kJ SECRET. From The Deputy iRnment of India in the External Affairs Department, To The Hon 1 ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan. Memorandum No.D.1640-BPG/46• Dated New Delhi S, the 1st October 1946. Subject:- T\^:lst - Gwadnr Boundary . o Reference correspondence resting with your memorandum No. 12-P*1/45 dated the 12th October 1945. The Government of India agree with the proposal made in paras 5 and 6 of your p c^uXlette r No.l2-P.l/45 dated the 12 th March 19 45 and direct that the red pencil line referred to should be treated by Political Officers in Baluchistan and in the Persian Gulf for practical purposes as the boundary between Kalat and Muscat States to guide them e.g.in deciding questions of jurisdiction and in considering how far to support particular claims or complaints put forward by one or the other Ruler. An authenticated copy of the map showing the line in question will follow. 2 . This boundary is not to be regarded as the official ly accepted boundary between the two States and is v/ithout prejudice to any legal rights which either side might be able to establish at some future date. 3 , The Government of India further direct that the . existence of this understanding is not to be communicated to the Rulers as it might lead to a revival of boundary disputes i between the two States. 4 # The above has been issued under the authority of the Crown Representative. Sd. M.G.Dixon, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.A &amp;k- From - The Under Secretary to the \ Government of India in {the 46 External Affairs Department, To - The- Kon f ble the A-gent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan., The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Memorandum No.F.57-BPG/46. Dated New Delhi 3, the 22 nd November 1946, Subject:- ffalat- Gwadur Boundary . Reference correspondence resting with memorandum endorsement from the Government of India, External Affairs Department No.D.1640-BpG/46, dated the 1 st October 1946. 2 . Three authenticated copies of the map in question Two are forwarded herewith for record and guidance of local officers Sd. R.E.R.Bird, Under Secretary to the Government of India.© existence of such an ar arigeme.' t and the Sultan of hugest - would certainly .res nt our’naving mad° it vy ionout reference to nim Oft tne otnei hand, to irfoim n n *m of it -&gt; adva ce Vvould probably r- suit in nis pressing for recognition of tne Lluscat claim a-a reviving a gue st * on inich is now, fotunat^ly, dormant. Occasions requiri g the exercise of crimi si jurisdiction in this aiea, wnich is',e yxx^x. spa‘s^ly populat’d, are iiKely to be veryinfrequent. 3. The bultan nas recently apooint d Khan Bahadur r,bdul Hai y el Ha sniin* , ex^ Indian Assist ant at Banrain, ^as Mmini st rat o at G-wadur. fhi s ap ointm nt will, it is hoped, and any at tempts at i. filtration by Muscat, and will vo sult in improve elations between officials on both sid^s. D.O. Copy of t ,e/letter no. F.67-?/45 dat d tne 1st May, 1946 f tne Deputy Secretary to tne Government of India in the External affairs Department, New Deln’, *to tne Hon’ble Lt. Col. B-r G-offrey Prior, KC T E., Political Peg- ■: ent in tn- Persian Gulf. .Subject: - Ks 1 at - Gwadu r h ou id a ry d 4 s pu t e. wifi you please refer to tne correspondence 2 6 sting wittn your memorandum x^o. 29-3 dat a the 7th January, 1946. 2* T am desired to suggest that it would be a good t ,ing to aiscuss this mac ^er with Gol. Hay when he takes over charge from you next montn. The Government of India are of the ooinlon that boundary suggested by Gol. Hay in para 5 of his let er No. 12-P/1/4 5 d tni tne l2nn March, 194o may well be adopted as a guide - without prejudice to any legal rights ^sraoLmich either side might be able ^o establish - by Political Officers on each side in considering now far to support particular claims or complaints put forward by tneir respective rule s. 1Cnur-g- mz.o/o/m•'tL'’*'. k-\LE COPY fa T^ 4 Proa s Th« Hon*bio the A^wt to the “'532 M l .C.r J £“L‘^h i .ti^ tNc'., • ^qg- : The 3 eoreta External 1 Affair Meaorandhu Nosl2~P*l/45 of India. OJL XIiOJ.fi* , Nee Delhi. Dated Hue ta 9 the 12 October 1945* me.i»rm5to 8 Notp^^4h»' A *t0^^i?^^i&gt;tmb«: 1945 to ti;e Hon* hie tne Pol it icnl He aidect in ^e Pereiaa.Quiff copy endorsed to thle Adainietration. 2. I atiould eee no objection to informing His Hichneea the Khan of Wat, preferably veroally, of the arrangement propoeed. He joule think it hie duty to protect, tat I doubt if Ine ■attar would go further than thia. ta far ae I am concerned I aleo ■•• no objection ta Hie Higjtiocst the iultan of Mucoct being inror .ea# dd/* Illegible* Agent to the Governor General in Baluchistan*t Z-' j From • The Undor Secretary to the Gortfmaeryfc of India in the £xtemal Affaire Department, To - The Hon , hIe the Political Resident in the Pereian Gulf • Memorandum Ho.F.67-F/45. Dated Hew Delhi,the { k\ ' botcher 1946. Subject i- Kalat - Gwadur Boundary * diepute* Reference External Affaire Department memorandum Ho •F*67-F/45 # dated the 17th September 1945* 2« A copy of memorandum from the Hon 9 hie the A^ent to the Governor General, Resident end Chief Commis sioner in Baluchiatan. He* 12-P.1/45, dated the 12th October 1945. is forwarded herewith, with a request that /under a reply to the memo ran dus^/ref eren ce may kindly be expedited* Sd/- T. E. Brownsdon* Under Secretary to the Government of India. , — * Jaf rl *flLE COPY., Frcm - The Hon’ble the Agoit to the Governor General, Chief Canmissioner in Baluchistan. ^ W-drph To - The Under Secretary to the Government of India,' /yia &gt; , Affairs D^artamt. (a. Manorandnm No: 12-P1/45. Dated Quetta, tijie 5&amp; September 1945, / //&gt; • Subject:- Gwadur - Kalat boundary, ^.v 5 I 7 8 .u /-•J tted mfi-iu • ■ if# A, 21 et v^ 1 -; the Referenoe your memorandum No: Fe67-f , &gt;6®^ da 1 am unable to see that the adoption for practical puxposeB by the political Officers concerned of the line proposed would lead to difficulties. The m$in purpose of ray proposal was to anggeat a line that midit serve as a guide in considering the lengths to which they should 20 in pressing claims or protests put forward oy the reapfective Rilers. It sews desirable that there should be the minimum conflict of opinion in such cases between the political Officers, irrespective of the views of the States with which they are concerned* The line which I have pro* posed lies between the boundaries claimed by Muscat and Kalat and shows no favour therefore to either. 3. The instance quoted in para 2 of my letter No:12-Pl/45 of 12th March 1945 provides an example of the use which can be made of a •lyoyfr iyig boundary* accepted by the political authorities. In this case the Kalat State nave been advised to treat the murders as having been committed within their territory since there is no dispute as to the exact scene of the murder and it happens to be on the Kalat side of the working line^^ ^ been on the Muscat side i should have adopted a different attitude. , Agent to the .Governor General in ♦ Baluchistan.B.D.P . 4 Frcm:- To*- The Deputy Secretary to the Govemn«it of 6 Inaia in the Sxtemal Affairs Department, The Hon'ble the Political 1?asI3.ant in tte - r Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. P.67-P/45, 5 i 78 Dated New Delhi, the 17th Septenber 1945* - Reference this Department’s meoidlrehdum N&lt; F.67^j/45 dated the 21st Augiet aidresBed to j A^ent to the Grovemor General,Resident and Chief Comnissioner in Baluchistan, of which a copy was endorsed to you* A copy is enclosed herewith of 5* t?, the Grovemor General's reply N0.12-P1/4B, dated the 5th September 1945. f 2. # # The Government of India are of the ajrT*w opinion that the Agent to the Governor General's proposal should adopted as a.working glide for the 011 ®ach side, as he suggests* There might even be advantage in letting the respective Rulers know that this was being done* Althourfi the practise mi^it be regarded technically as being with* Got prejudice to any rights which rnigit exist on either side, the development of a practice of observing a particular line would tend to stabilise the position and so to establish in the end an agrosd boundary. Before, however, deciding whether the respective Rulers should be informed of the adoption of the new practise the &gt; Government of India would be glad of your comments on the desirability of doing so. J a. . x . 30/' C.B.Duke. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Copy to the Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Conmissioner in Baluchistan for favour of ccraments also on ttie further su^estimi made above*'ssa Ho Sa. J&lt; §&gt; _ _ Office of the iiolitical ^«afaert, Pars an Gulf, Canp, ^tiiraz, 26th July, 1945. Prom • Tha Hon*bio the Political Keslcfcntjperslan Gulf* • The see rata ty to the Goveriyrent of ftidia in the —-- A ^ ^ -'W ''WP V C«WB^ To «xtem«i Affairs ueparjtmen -v 'Tew J 2 Sm&gt; Copy to Tho Political Agent, -■SMORAiigat. SwaduiMcalat Boundary 4309 ‘ A ^ Reference &amp; sternal *** tLsia., No.l&gt;.2494-F/45 t d^ted the 2?th^aroh, 1)45. etter 2. in view of the fact that there is a wide difference )6ot opinion between the Muscat andKalat authorities as to the boundary I am not in favour of laying down a 'eertcing' line such as that suggested by the Hon’ble the Agent to the Gove mo ivGene rnl, resident and Chief Oofl*TiieB! oner in B£ uchistan. As mentioned in paragraph 6 of Colonel Hay*© letter, such md line would not be acceptable either to tne sultan of Muscat or to the Khan of ralat, and its adoption by political Officers in the Persian Gulf and in Baluchistan would be likely to lead to diffi culties, particularly as reference to edtther or both State authorities would be unavoidable in any case of importance that ml Jit ariae. , 3. I agree that the question of the fomal demarcation of the frontier should not be revived unless and until such demarcation beoimes unavoidable for very strong reasons, such as tie reaunptlon of oil exploration. Gd. a .C. Gallo way Political He si dent, Persian Gulf. Attested $d.l llegible, for secretary to the Political Resident. Persian Gulf.Mr.Har Secret Politi I ■ Set. 2522/45 ^5 ,^ 0 . 0 . 0 ^ ^ • © '% t7 Department. Gwadur-Kalat Boundary. Please see Ext.132/45 and note flagged 'X M on file below. In October 1944 &gt; the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf raised the question of the possible renewal of oil exploration in Kalat State which would entail the demarcation of the Kalat-Gwadur boundary; he was told by the Government of India that in view of the moratorium, oil exploration could not be started in Kalat until after the war. A copy of the correspondence was sent to the A.G.G. Baluchistan, who has now written pointing out that while there is no necessity for a formal demarcation of the boundary, there is much to be said in favour of an informal understanding between political officers in the Persian Gulf and Baluchistan as to the limit of the Sultan’s jurisdiction. He cites the blocking of a motor road needed by military convoys by the Muscat authorities in 1942 (Ext. 586 7/42) and more recently a murder which both Muscat and Kalat State authorities claim was committed in their territory, as instances of the trouble now caused by the lack of an accepted boundary. Colonel Hay encloses an admirable large-scale map showing the boundaries claimed by both sides and suggests that the line drawn on it in red pencil should be treated as the boundary for practical purposes, and in deciding questions of jurisdiction, etc. Although i£ is unlikely that either the Sultan of Muscat or the Khan of Kalat would agree to this boundary, yet there is a chance that it may in time come to be tacitly accepted by them, and the question of an official demarcation may not arise, especially as there is some doubt whether oil is to be found in this area. A copy of the A.G.G’s letter has been sent to the Political Resident and no action here seems called for until we get his views and those of the Government of India. CO.s mpii ■MB From To O. i\o '*■ s £-C-££ T. Tne Honourable the Agent to the Gfoveirnor General* \ Resident* and Chief Commissioner in (^k * Baluchistan. Tht Secretary to the Gove^nriient of India* External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Dated Camp Sibi* the 12th March 1.945* i^r* \V&gt;j &amp; 0 L d. With reference to the correspondence endi External Affairs Dejwtment memorandum IIq.D. ' dated the # 6 th December 1944 to ^e'l^n t ble Po_ resident in^the Persian Gulf copy endorsed to this Administration I have the honour to state that although there is no necessity to re-open the question of the demarcation of the Gwadur-Kalat boundary for the present, it appears to me desirable that there should be some kind of understanding, at any rate so far as political officers are concerned* where the boundary should be regarded as rumrmg for practical purposes. The Kalat State authorities complain of const ant encroachments by £ )tde Gwadur people and there are probably similar complairi S on the other side* ^ ^ * T 2* In 1942 the Muscat authorities blocked the road in vicinity of Suntsar, vide the cones pond ence ending JJpyth the external Affairs Department endorsement No:6073- l F/42 dated the 10th October 1942 and later in the same year it was reported that the Wall of Gwadur erected aat • _ .riiirr-.iriciT* rv-f* n«»tr 1 1 4- L. * — ir i i Z'V' ; ^^itober of boundary pillars in this area. More recently &gt; 4 * a dispute has arisen over certain murders that have been committed near a place called Chatti yide the enclosed map. In January 1944 the British Agent at Gwadur reported tnat one Hayatun, a subject of Kalat State, had murdered J n - *, two British subjects within the Gwadur boundary and de- fc - &lt;.4 ^nded that ahe should be arrested. The Political Agent' Muscat subsequently asked for extradition proceedings to ^e instituted* The Xalat State authorities did arrest L&amp;yatun, but refused to hand him over firstly because tnere is no extradition agreement between Kalat State &amp; Muscat and secondly because.they claimed that the mr nmtiers had been committed in Kalat territory. So/--—So far as the latter point is concerned, there appears ^ to nie to be good grounds for the State authorities con tent-on and I have advised them to try the npurderer themselaes* J n / J c ~ w ' 3. The question of the dwadur boundary is discussed at length on pages 280 and 281 of the Gazetteer .of ..Lakran and T enclose a map showing the three boundaries described and also the boundary as at present claimed by Kalat State Zhefacts appepr to tree that in 1783 the then Khan of iv ,at allowed Saiyed Sultan to settle in Gwadur as a re fugee and assigned to him the revenues of the place. When Saiyed Sultan returned to Muscat and usurped the SulUan-ale he retained possession of Gwadur and since then he and his successors have bern endeavouring to enlarge their dominion by constant encroachments - a process which is still going on. Tt is difficult for the Kalat State authorities to deal with such encroachments as the country is mostly desSfcand unless^awake they fail to ascertain xx what is go-?ng on # LJfoi HtbexL 'tyuuM 4. My personal view is that although the sovereignty of the Sultan of Muscat over Gwadur cannot #now be disputed we must # resist any encroachments into ^alat territory and limit the Sultan s dominion to that area over which he appears on good evidence to have exercised sway more or less continuously in the past. would accordingly propose that for practical pur- poses(the red pencil line m the enclosed map should be treated as the boundary. This appears to have been the boundary which the writer of the Gazetteer regarded as the generally accepted one at the beginning or the cen- f tury. So far as is kjiown nothing has occured since which establishes the Sultan’s claim to any territory beyond % this line. Sven if demarcation were to take ;jlace it is very unlikely that the Commission appointed for the pur pose would find anything more reliable on which to base their decisions than what is stated in the Gazetteer. 6. 1 would not propose that either the Khan of Kalat or the Sultan of unseat should be asked to accept this boundary as it is certain neither of them would agree to do so. but merely that it should be treated by political officers in the Persian Gulf and Baluchistan as the V)oijryl o-mr^ - V 'boundary for practical purooaes in deciding questions xh of jurisdiction, scich as that which has just arisen, and the like. Tt is possible that if this procedure is adop ted and adhered to for a sufficient length of time, the boundary concerned will in due course be tacitly accepted by the parties. 7. The question of demarcation was first taken up in connection with possible oil exploration. Such explora tion has been postponed for the time being owing to the ' ''ratorium and it is possible that it may not be serious ly resumed as T beliow there is some doubt whether any oil exists in the area. In these circumstances- it may be possible to avoid demarcation - tfhicb.would be an utter wast^of time and money in this desolate country - inde finitely. 1 ^ r . 0 ^ J ! 8. I sm sending a copy of this letter' aM “its enclosure to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and, to save time, to the Political Agents Muscat. ^ I have the' 'honour Sir, Your most obedient servant. 3d/- H±ag£&amp;Le.^' ^ Agent to the Governor General in Baluchistan. (j ly Copy of a letter No*D.2494-F/45.dated tl^e 27th March 1945 from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi to the Hon # ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I *am directed to refer to the letter from the Hobble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident &amp; Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, No. 12-P. 1/45,dated the 12th March 1945, a copy of which has been sent £o you direct,and t o request that the Govt, of India may kindly be favoured with your comments in the matter. MAFRI 17/5/45.ipsipi fa Ml J) 7vy' Mr«Harrison . ZS/t - V/ -v ifyt &amp; i/jyn. P.Z.8&gt;3' ;8 P.Z. 8017/38 Gw&amp;dar was granted by the Khan of Kalat to a destitute relative of the then Sultan of Muskat at the end of the 18th century* When the question of Oil Concessions in Kalat and Gwadar arose, the then- Khan of Kalat claimed rights of speoi«i ub surface revenue in respect of Gwadar, and was told that his claim could not be allowed* The Burma Oil Company and Indian Oil Concessions Limited competed for these concessions, and it became clear that the question of the disputed boundary between the two States would have to be settled, in case the Kalat and Gwadar Concessions should go to rival Companies* In 1938 it was proposed to set up a Boundary Commission for this purpose. However in 1939 Indian Oil Concessions limited obtained a concession in the Makran area adjoining Gwadar and consequently, later in the year the Burma Oil Company broke off negotiations with the Sultan, but it does not appear that Indian Oil Concessions took advantage of the clear field left to them* In November 1939 there were complaints that Indian Oil Concession Geologists prospecting in Southern Makran had crossed the frontier into Gwadar. The same month the Government of India stated 'as it appears unlikely that any attempt will be made to prospect for oil in Gwadar and the adjoining portion of the Kalat State in the near future and owing to the complications introduced by the outbreak of war, it is proposed, subject to your views, not to proceed with the demarkation of Gwadar-Kalat boundary for the present* • • • • • Should however any oil company show signs of ^563/40' -— starting operations in this neighbourhood it will P.Z. 1176/38 P.Z.4285/38 P.Z.1780/39 P.Z.5053/39 on collection 20/24. A r &gt; . ! C b‘ probably/probably be necessary to re-open the question.' • The Acting Political Resident has now written to the Government of India enquiring whether there is any possibility of oil exploration in the Kalat State being renewed in the near future, as if so 'it may be necessary to re-open the question of the demarkation of the Gwad&amp;r-Kalat boundary, to which the Government of India have replied that oil exploration cannot be started in Kalat until after the war.ftKgrnaiTTAi.. 'i'/ * - Jr i &lt;)d prom , cf^ice of tliefpoliti,c^. Hesti«ut in the paesiaa-Slx^/ Camp, Bahrain. The Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The secretary to the Government oi In^ia, iztamal Affairs department. New ^elhi. copy ho The political Agent, 'lisoat, reference correspondence ending w.th Residency prints^ Letter no. 6-8 dated 3rd jan.'40. f T eG,orandum no.c/ 409, dated the 26th October, 1944. To 9 ■' Gi- CUR - SALAT HOtii, ?y Reference correspondence aiding with External Affairs department endorsement no,f.324-n/39 dated the Hth december 1939. — 2. I should, be glad to learn whether there is any possibility of i oil exploration in the Kaiat otate oerng raiewed in the near future as, if so, it may_ be necessary to reopen the question of the dLag^. cation of the G»adur - Kaiat boundary. 3d/- T.Hi cicinbothan. Offg. political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . . 3d/- illegible. for secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. *j*fri*. 12 / 12 .‘ y ^BSBSIx masm. From - Political, Muscat. To - Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ■ ' (Reptd. Government of India.) No. C/1262. S«k7- Dated 8th October 1942. Fpreirpi telegram^No.7909 dated October 6th. 9 ** # Sultan’s representative has sent instructions to Will Gwadur not to obstruct construction of road even should it (group omitted-pass?) through' Muscat territory. SECRET. Telegram No.8016, dated 9th October 1942. From - Foreign, New Delhi, To - Baluchistan, Quetta. .Following is text of telegram from Political Muscat to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.C/1262 8th October. Begins: Foreign telegram No.7909 dated October 6th through Muscat territory. Hinds .T K 4 o SbV hO ^ Hi 35CKFrr« Tele^rag }QC&gt; V From . • . Baluchistan! Quetta. To . » . Foreign, New Dellxi. . • NO.OBS-S. • • . T . &lt;&amp;[' s n Dateci 2nd (Heed 3rd);October 1942* Political Muscat telegraphed to Political A^ent, Kalat on Sept ember -8th that Kalat authesities were reported (to be) making liiotor road through ICALPORaG and KUHTANGl and requested suspensioji of wor^ until sultan^ orders could be t aken on grounds that both 'places are in Gwadur territory. This road aligned by A.P.A. Mekran runs from KUHTANGI Weat of SUNTSAfe Mekran Levy Post and is being constructed urgently for military convoys to JIWANI* ... Political Agent, K.alat therefore declined to discontinue work and h- informed Political Muscat accordingly by letter which may not have reached him. Political.Muscat further wires on September 28th that v he understands work is continuing and that local Gwadur authority intends preventing by force any encroachment on Gwadur territory. 'Demarcation of Gwadur-Kalat boundary has not been proceeded with vide correspondence resting with my expres s 1 et t e i- kq &gt; z-143/38/l. .s - - ■ H7S3-P of pec ember 1st KALPORAG cannot be traced on map but present clalnToTI^usdat seems to be the most-extravagant they have yet made arid appears to include even SU(NTSAR ) Post. Request ins-cx^uctions be urgently (gr.omitted? given) not to obstruct construction of-road which is of military importance* Country through which noad : runs*tis all desert and of ho value to either party* FOr.EiGN SECHi LEi rFR N°. OATP • j p.T.O*7909 Telegram XX No,7909 dated 5th October 1942. * ^ ^ From Foreign, New Delhi. To, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* (repeated Political Agent, Muscat). Following telegram from Baluchistan No.l82-S dated 2nd October Begins :- ! - ’'’Political Muscat telegraphed * * * * * and of no value to either party.” Ends 2, Please instruct Political Agent, Muscat to report Mftscat version, and to take measures to ensure that there is no interference by Muscat officials with construction of this road which is required for strategic purposes. F.BE FS IDS PSV &amp; 0 &amp; IMI.(2) ¥• - !INDEXED X * FILE CO^Yl From To No, F.437 -N/44K r r\ p “ 7 O U u / (% i JU. f.A The Deputy Secretary to the fcoveMitefrt'')o:f India V in the External Affairs Pepwrtmeat|— Tiie Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 2;?2 Dated Simla, the July 1940. Alleged crossing of Gwadur boundary by the Kalat State official®. \o Sir, In continuation of the letter from the Government MX of India xn trie External Affairs Department No* F.437- N/39, dated the 18th November 1939, I am directed to state that the Kalat State authorities have now reported that the Gtoadur Official’s report regarding the corssing of the Gwadur boundary by Kalat State officials in June 1939 is untrue and that no such incident occurred. I have the honour to be. - sir, ENCLOb'j' Your most obedient servant* FOREIGN SECRETARY .-.TIER j No. DATE Ri-CErv'H ] •) 17 -4- 8 1 2-9-1940 i ad /- R. Hay, Deputy 13 ecretaiy to tne Government of India.INDEXED FILE COPY zr. K -To Baluchistan only () To Britconsul Busnire. Express Letter from Foreig n. Mewftelhi. t o Baluchistan, Quetta, Britconsul 39, dated 6th November 1939. ixi 19 ^ n Subiectt - G»ADU3 - KALAT BOUNDSSg— • »- Bu h ,I T o: |D .3 924-3 /j % .563 Reference correspondence ending with the - ^memorandum from the G-overnment of India, Rxternsl Affairs De partment No. J .256~N/3£. dated the l£th January 1939. (fix-press letter from the Political Agent, luscat, No: T-2, dated 26th December 1938) As it appears unlikely that any attempt will be made to prospect for oil in G-wadur and the adjoining portion of Kalat State in the near future and owing to the compli cations introduced by the outbreak of war, it is proposed, subject to your views, not to proceed with the demarcation of . the G-wadur-Kalat boundary for the present. Please state whether you concur. . Should however any oil company show signs of star ting operation in this neighbourhood, it will probably be neces ary to reopen the question. 3. Nor Ba. 1 uchistar . Reference our memorandum No. D.2511- N/39 dated hie 19th July 1939. It may kindly be stated whether action has been taken as indicated in paragraph 3. Further action on paragraph 4 is left to your discretion \ and if you do not consider it desirable to press tne Khan of Kalat further for a statement on the lines proposed, there is no necessity for you to do so. If, however, such a statement is obtained, a copy of it may kindly be forwarded. 4. For.Political Resident Persian Gulf . Reference ourjr memorandum No: B. 2511-N/39 dated tne 19th July 1939. Further action on paragraph 4 is left to your discretion. If, however, any information is obtained from the Julian of Muscat on the lines proposed, it may kindly be com uni- cated to the Government of India. The issue of the above has been authorised.datea December 14^ 1959, from Balm chi star], ;uetta, to Foreign, New Delhi. Dubjeot: G-mdur-Kalat Boundary deference your Express Letter No: S ) .5954~N/39, dated the 6th November 1939« 2. I agree that the demarcation of the Crwadur-Kalat boundary sliould not be proceeded 'with for the present. 3. His Highness the Khan of Kalat was informed on the 2ist August 1939 as indicated in paragraph 3 of External i Affairs Department memorandum No: D.2511-N/39, dated the 19th July 1939. At the same time he was asked to furnish a statement of what in his opinion is the boundary of the G-wadur area under the de facto control of the dultan of t Muscat. His Highnes-: has informed the Political Agent, Kata' that a map of the area has been prepared and that a reply xx will be sent after the new .azir-i-^am has visited the area and submitted his report. I shall continue to press for this statement which will be useful whether the demarcation is proceeded with or not. /N P.Z. . 563 Oopy of Express Letter No: g/7 ctQo4 Q93 9,j doted the 23rd November, 1939, from the Political Resident in the Persismi G-ulf, to the Secretary to the Government of India, Rxterna a Affairs Department, New Delhi. Repeated The Political Agent, lusc&amp;t. for information, with copy of External Affairs Department riemorandum No:D.2511-N/ 39, dated the 19th July 1939, and of Exter nal Affairs Department' Express Letter referred to below. Subject: Gwadur-Kalat Boundary. Reference your Express Letter No: D. 3934/-N/39, dated the 6th November 1939. 2. Your paragraph 1. I concur. 3. Your paragraph 4. As it is undesirable that the Sultan should revert to his proposal for the sale of Gwadur (vide my letter No: C/484, dated the 26th Sep tember 1939), I do not propose to make any enquiry of him at present regarding documents in his possession relating to that territory.mmmm—M ED »4 S' u PILE COW amfelNTIAL- ^ &gt;y t Ls v&gt; ki'L . / 7 A 9-I3.10626-P, dated the i i a * i F i *1 r^i 2nd November 1939, from the Hon’ble the Agent to the t}overnor| General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. L AI/EGiCD CROSSING OF GVvADUR BOUNDARY BY KALAT T STATS OFFICIALS. -. 0 .- Reference correspondence ending v/ith External Affairs Department Express letter No. D.3531-N/39, dated the 29th September 1939, and endorsement No.C/458 dated the 24th September 1939, from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. ^he Kalat State authorities are making enquiries into the various allegations of crossing of Gwadur boundary by the 2 ft state officials, which will take some time involving inevitable delay. The result will be communicated in due course. 3. It is clear, however, that at least the later allegatidjV (if not all of them) from the Muscat authorities (e.f. Con fidential Endorsement No.C/458 dated the 24th September 1939 from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) refer to the I activities of the geologists of the Indian Oil Concessions Ltd. who were prospecting in the southern areas of Mekran and j near the Gwadur boundary. His Highness the Khan of Kalat has now put a stop to all ground prospecting until his agreement with the Company has been finally signed* so for h some moths at least it is unlikely that there will be any recurrence of this difficulty. It is understood that the geologists were operating in what was shown to them and appeared from the map to the Kalat State territory, but is claimed by the Muscat authorities to be Gwadur territory n ENCLOSURE IN INDIA r ,' Foreign secretary's lett%r No. DATE RECEIVCb «'*•# n 1 1 - 1 - 19*0CONFIDENTIAL. Uo.f. From rifm To The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Ihrternal Affairs Department, The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 11 Dated New Delhi, the November 1939. Alleged crossing of Gwadur Boundary by Kalat State Officials. - 0 O 0 - Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your memorandum No .0/458, dated the 24th September 1939, hi* iSxpress letter to the Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor ] I am General, Resident and Chief Comnissioner in Baluchistan, 1 No.D.5001-N/39 dated the 19th August 1939, D.3531-N/39, jj directed dated the 29th September 1939, and D.3593-N/39 dated the 26th October 1939. ; to forward 4. Memorandum from the Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor | herewith, General, Resident and Chief Coninissioner in Baluchistan, I No. 2 ♦ 135/39 - IS .10.626]:. ‘de, t e d the 2nd November .193 ^ i for informa tion, a copy of the correspondence cited in the margin, and to say that a. further communication will be made to you when the result of the enquiries which the Kalat State authorities are making is known. I have the honour to be, Sir, ‘ - Your most obedient servant, Sd/- W.R.Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.30 mD?JTIiLL -No. C/458. 45P VS G-ulf presents his corapliments to 1. The Secretary to the Grovernraent of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. 2. The Hon'ble the .Agent to the Dover nor-Greneral, Resident and Chief Commissioner ±n Baluchistan, puetta. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned documents. Camp Bahrain. Dated 24th September 1939. Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter iCo.C/438 of 20/9/39. Description of enclosure. Name and Date Subject Muscat letter No.0/252 of 28th Alleged crossing of August 1939, with enclosure. Dwadur boundary by Kalat State officials.CC'-FIDgw'-TIAL No.C/252. Political .tiency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat, the 28th August 1939. From Captain T. Hickinbotham, 0*B.E.,l Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Gel ,,2,522 To Muscat. f The Hon r ble the political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire• Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with your express letter l T o«d/28j. dated the 21.st July 1939 and to enclose a copy of a report dated the 17th August 1939 l!o.10/839 from the British Agent, Iwadur. 2. 1 showed the British Agent f s letter to His Highness who stated that he had not recei/ed any report from his Tali but that he would oe giatefui £x if measures could be taken to ensure that there was no recurrence of such incidents* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/ -T. Hi ckx nbo th&amp;qp Captain, I.A. Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.Copy of letter No. 10/839 dated the 17th Au^st 1939 from tiie British igent, Nwadur to the Political Agent &amp; K.B.IFaj Consul, Muscat. I have the honour to quote below the ' 7 ali ? s report for favour of suitable action in the matter. 'Four Christians who are Engineers entered Owadur terri tory, through Sunt Bar, with cars, visited Saiji, Fishan, Fieri and Cung and r ; turned. They came again via Karmt where the track was not passable by cars. They therefore prepared the track and entered this territory, came upto Darbla and C-urandani, and returned. This is irregular. If they want to enter this territory and make any investigation, they should take permission from the Sultan otherwise I will not allow them to enter this territory. Kindly take up the matter with Kalat State and have them forbidden from entering this territory.' 2. I understand that the four men in question are some American Eeologists, they came by two cars, entered this territory, prepared the track where ever they found it impassable went up the hills, looked round and returned. I also understand that they are stationed at Pasni. 3. The 7ali objects especially to these peoples* making investigations and tempering with the soil/ of this territory for making motor t^ack without permission.EN Government of India, Eiternal Affairs Department^ fm. £ T r 1 5 3 3 L 5 T T 7522 L 1939 Erom FOREIGN, NS? IELHI, ^ I W I To BALUCHI STM, QUETTA. s' ij 0 . D.3593-N/39. Dated. £&lt;£//, October ^&gt;9 SUBJECT:- AlleKed crossing of the Gwadur Boundary by Kalat State Official. Reference express letter from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department No.D.3531-N/39, dated the 29th September 1939, and memorandum from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.C/458, dated the 24th September 1939, a copy of which was sent to you direct. 2. tie result of the enquiry made regarding the incidents in question may kindly be reported as soon as possible. 3. This coumunication is issued under the authority of the Crown Representative. Hie issue of the above has been authorised. 3d/- t 7.R. HAY, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. ' .1-1(Received under Muacat Printed letter No .C/oil dated the 12tli Sejjtaiiiber, 1939.) Telegram G.T.C. From British Agent, Gvjadur. To Political Agent, Muscat. v A / u m No. 918. Dated 11th received 12th September, IQ . j In continuation of my despatch No.10/839 of August 17th. ifeli reports 'Engineers came x again via Kanmt in Gmdur territory up to Darbla. Muscat subjects checked them from proceeding further. They returned but sent a Babu with labourers who prepared the track for psgfai vehicles. The Babu only halted when my sepoys went and prevented him from doing work. I am afraid that they will come again. I will not allow encroachments. Please arrange to stop them otherwise there shall be trouble'.I — Confidential ■ GOViSRNMiSNT OF INDIA, iirternal Affairs Department EXPRESS LSTTER r 70 VI 1 1939 From Foreign, Simla. To Baluciii stan, No. D.3531-11/^9 Dated The Sept. 1939. Alleged crossing of trwadur Boundary by Kalat State Officials. Reference express letter from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, ho.D.5001-M/59, datea the 19th August 1939, and memorandum from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.0/458 of 1939, dated the 20th September 1939, a copy of which was sent to you direct. 2. The result of the enquiries made regarding the incidents reported may kindly be communicated at an early date. 3. This communication is issued under the autnority of the Crown Representative• The issue of the above has been authorised. Sti/- W.R.Jky Deputy Secretary to the Government ofcom mm. file copy '■ lo 16 UL 1 ^ »■ Exnreas let &amp;2(D»&gt; Mail)&gt; h- No. C/281 of 1939. OfiiceifafOtibe Political Resident Persian Gulf, Gamp Shiraz. Dated 31st July, 1939. (6 From - Political Resident, Bushire, at Shiraz. To - Ihe Secretary to the tiovernment of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Repeated The Hon t ble the Agent to the Governor-General, Resident and Chief Goamissi oner in Baluchistan, Quetta. The Political Agent, Muscat. 'M Subject:- Alleged crossing of Gwadur Boundary by Kalat State Officials. I enclose herewith a copy of a letter No. c ll.76, dated the 17th July, 1939, from the Political Agent, Muscat, and of its enclosures. 2. If the allegations, after enquiry, are subs tantiated, I would be graceful if necessary action to prevent recurrence of such encroachments could be taken. Sd/- T.C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. Sd/- J.Croning. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Sun Persian Gulf. } ENCLOSURE JN I ^ FOREIGN SEGRETARra l T , R No. DATE ii j 1 56 2 1-8 1 i ' 1' r 9 |Confidential. No.C/176. I' Political ti&amp;ancy &amp; H* Muscat, July 17th, From Captain T # Hickinbotham, CBS Political Agent and H Muscat. f s Consul, To The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Crossing of boundary by the Kalat State Officials. Sir, I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter dated the 5th July, 1939, No. 223, from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman together with a copy of a report from the British Agent at Uwadur dated the 1st July 1939. 2. His Highness mentioned this subject to me at am interview which 1 had with him on the 29th June,1939. On receipt of his letter of the 5th July I telegraphed to the British Agent for a report. The British Agent had already been in touch with the Wadi and had forwarded a report. 3. I suggest that the Baluchistan authorities be asked to investigate and in the event of it being found that the allegations are true to take such measures as may be necessary to prevent a recurrence. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- T.Hickinbotham. Political Agent and H.M.fs Consul, Muscat.Translation of letter No. 223 dated the 5th July 1939 from His Highness Saiyid Said bin Tairaur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, to Captain T.HicKinbotham, OBE., H.B.M. f s Consul, Muscat. After compliments. Q I have received information from Crwaduy.^o the effect that the officials of Kalat Grovernment, who are on the frontier between Gwadur and Government of Kalat at a place named Sunt Sar, always cross the valley separating the two countries, and inspect the caravans there. As this action is against the regulations followed, I have to bring it to your notice for conmunication to our friend the Government of India with a view to stop it, so that there should not be any trouble between the officials of our Government at Gwadur and those of Kalat Government mentioned above. , I am sure that the Government of India do not agree to the action the officials of Kalat Government are taking at Sunt Sar. Usual ending. Copy of letter No. 8/701, dated the 1st July,1939, from British Agent, Gwadur, to the Political ^gent and H.B.M. f s Consul, Muscat. I have the honour to report that the Wali wrote to me on 27-6-39 that some Dafadar of Kalat State had pestered the camelmen in Gwadur about four days previously and that I should write to the State Authorities to order their officials coming to Gwadur to refrain from interfering with the public here. I wrote back the same day and enquired the name of the Dafadar and also what the Dafadar had actually done. No reply having been received from the Wali, I went to see him on 30-6-39 and enquired from him personally. He stated that the Dafadar had not come to the town of Gwadur but that at a distance of about 20 miles from the town the Dafadar had interfered with the liberty of some caravan, ihe Wali also added that he had sent out his men to find out the name of the Dafadar and that as soon as he had received further particulars about the incident he would inform me. 2. Now the....2 . n ^ Now the Wall reports that Dafadar Qaeam of Suntsar and Munshi Ghaus tiakhsh of Gabd stppp^., near Fieri in Gwadur territory, a caravan coming from Mekran and 'received from them Ns. 6/- in the name of customs duty. Similarly Jamadar Npk Bakhsh who is in charge of motor road in Kalat State recovered, at Fieri in Gwadur territory, Rs. 5/- from a caravan coming from Mekran. I doubt very much that anybody can prove the above- 3* mentioned outrages alleged to have been conrnitted recently by the *alat State Officials in Gwadur territory, but as the Kalat State Officials have behaved similarly on several occa sions in the past, I do not consider the outrages now alleged, j improbable. 4. In the circiznstances, I would request you kindly to take what action you consider necessary in the matter. In ray humble opinion if the Political Agent, ^lat, could be re quested to have the customs officials in Mekran to refrain from extending their activities into Gwadur terri tory, it shall meet the situation.;.sm UL r ... wnmmr of India. eternal Affairs Dspartiaent.; r rr y i | k- From To Foreign Simla. Baluchi stan f Ziarat. (Repeated Political Resident in the Persian Qulf). No. D.3001-N/39. Dated Simla* the 19th Auguat f 1939. SUBJECTUlsged cresting of Owadur Bounaary 'ey Xalat State Officials. —— Reference express letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. C/2S1 of 1939, dated the 31st July,1939 &gt; \diich was repeated to you. 2. It is requested that enquiries may kindly be made and the result reported m soon as possible. 3. This communication is issued under the authority of the Crown Representative. The issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- W.R.Hay. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.n \ •r - ■ Copy of Memoana No» 2*143/38 IS-668 /P*Z« dated Ziarat, the 4th July 1939, from the Hon’ble the Agent to the Covernor-^aneral, Resident and Chief Commissioner in BalucMstant to the Secretary to the Groyernment of India External Affairs Department, Simla* ( ^ \ / 4811 Kalat Ghsadur Boundary I959 i Reference correspondence ending with External Affairs Department memorandum No; F# 256*N/38, dated the 2nd December 1938. 2. The decision of the Government of India ms communicated to His Highness the Khan, and I forward for the orders of Government a copy of a memorandum No* 1141, dated / v the 12th June 1939 from the Wazir-i-Azam Kalat State. The course proposed in para 5 of that memorandum is obviously impracticable and I recommend its rejection. The attitude of His Highness will however make the settlement of any boundary by consent almost impossible. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S LETTER No. DATE RECEIVED 131 20 -.7 8-.8-1939 \ V-. I Copy of ffletnorandufn No; 1141, dated th© 12th June 1939 from the •vazir-i-Azam, Kalat dtate, to the Political Agent in Kalat, Mastung. I • - - | Claim of the Jialat dtate in respect of Gwadur. Kindly refer to your confidential memorandum ho* 9, dated ' the 3rd December 1938, in w dch it is stated that ^.he Govern ment of India are not willing to support the claim of Kalat Dtate to exercise the rights of 3overei£hty over the Gwadur are I and that tnese rights as well t ose of oweuership hove both lapsed by adverse excerciae of them by the iultan of Muscat* 2* I must sa r that Hi a Highnaas the Khan of Kalat is very much disappointed at the raply of ti^e Government of India and &lt; its reluctance in recognising tha rights of owenership and Sovereignty of the Kalat itate over Gwadur area* 3* The single fact that the dultan of Muscat has been exercising his powers over Giadur area for a long time in the I past does not in any way mean that Kalat State has waived its rights of ownership and Sovereignty over the said area. In th;! particular case the position of tha Sultan of Muscat is simila 0 to tixe postion of those many persons who hold similar grants # but have nd Ht^tle to the rights of ownership or Sovereignty. 4. Gwadur is a port, of Mekran and it is quite evident that Khan Mir Nasir Khan Azam had, by an act of grace, grant© , as Inam, the revenues of Gwadur area to the bjcf^iher of the }ult* of Muscat who was then a homeless exile. It ia totally again H the practice of the State that the rights of Ownership or of Sovereignty should, by lapse of time or otherwise, pass over j to the holder of the Inam land. I am directed to make it clear to the Government of Ind || that Kalat itate is not at all prepared to waive its rights owner-ship or sovereignty over tha s^id area. 5* On the basis of friendly and mutual relations tliat exist between Kalat itate and the Government of India, Kis Higjiess would therefore suggest that the Government of Indi.’ advise the dultan of Muscat to send his representative to2 n yf o i i Darbar-i-Kalat for the settleinent of this issue* a course would foster the mutaal and f^endly relat^ions ^ s v_y O ^ / between the Government of Kalat and Muscat* It is only after this issue has been finally settled that the question of the settlement of boundaries between Kalat dtae and the dultan of Muscat can be taken up.From - The Deputy secretary x&gt;o uie CJoTornmaat of India ^ in the Sziernai Affairs Department, To - The Hon’bie the Political Resident in the Persian GULP. Memorandum Mo. D. 2511-N/39. Dated iimla, the July 1959. Kalat-Owadur boundary. Reference correspondence ending with Express letter from the Political A^ent, Muscat No. C/2 f dated 6tl; January 1959 • 2. A copy of memorandua No. 2-143/58-11-66^ .2., dated the 4tn July 1939 from the Hon’ble the ngont to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, is forvNurded herewith for favour of such comments as you ijay wish to make. The Government of India a^ree wiUi the iiesiaent in B&amp;lucnistan that the course recommended in parr^raph 5 must be rejected. 3. If Indian Oil Concessions Limited who iiave already obtained the oil coficession in the Pekran area also secure the concession for Gwadur, there would appear to be no immediate necessity for the demarcation of the Gwaaur-Kalat bounuary. If, however, oil is subsequently found in the vicinity of the supposed boundary or if same other Company obtains the Gwadur concession, it will be necessary to carry out the demarcation regardless of the attitude of the Khan of Kalat. 4. It would be convenient if you could obtain from the huitan of Mhsc&amp;t particulars of any documents relating V i tO . . « a •to Owadur which may be in nia poaaesaion (Of. Lemonindum No. 2327 dated the 18th October 1938 from the VMzir-i-Azam, Kalat State to tiic Political A&amp;ent in Kalat, a copy of which is enclosed) together with a statement of the boundary claimed by him. A suggestion ms previously made by you to this effectt vide your 3.J. No. G/377 dated the 27th June 1938, but it does not appear that any reply has boen sent to you. It may be difficult to obtain any similar statement from the Khan of Kalat in view of the attitude he has taken up» but the Resident in Baluchistan will be a«kod to approach him on tho subject. 5. A copy of tliis memomndum is being sent to Baluchistan. :W- ^ .H. Iky, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.From - The Deputy Secretary to the Government oi India in the internal Affairs Department, To - The Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor,General, Resident and Chief Commissioner m Balucnists.n. | Memorandum No. D. 2511-N/39. Dated Simla, the A? ' July 1939. Kalat-Gw&amp;dar Boundary. Reference your memorandum No. Z-143/38-IS-66Q/P.Z., dated the 4th July 1939. 2. A copy of a memorandum addressed to the Hon’ble the , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf No.D. 25U-N/39, dated the x y July 1939 is enclosed. 3. Your recommendation that the course proposed by tne azir-i-Azam r\nr*cs.;mrih n of hia f‘iaffloran‘“ dura dated the 12th June 1939 be rejected ia approved and Hie Hitihneaa the Khan may kindly be informed accordingly. 4. It is also requested that, if you see no objection. an endeavour may be made to obtain from the Khan the statement of vdaat he regards as the boundary of the Muscat. 5. This memorandum is issued under the authority of the Crovm Representative. Dei/- w.R.Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Governnwnt of India.mpi @) ) India Office Whitehall, Of,7.1. P.Z.3745/39 19th 1959 Dear Mr. Gray Please refer to your letter of the 15th June about Gv/adur. Go far as Kalat clainis enter into the matter we see no reason why your Company should hesitate to sign an agreement with the Sultan. The right of the Sultan to dispose of mineral rights in Gwadur was in fact disputed by the Kalat State last year in a claim to suzerainty over the territory. The claim was rejected by the Government of It was also stated by the local authorities in this connexion that the Gitchkis cannot have any claim apart from that of the Kalat State. The Government of India's decision is not necessarily the last word since the Khan has the right to appeal to the Secretary of State. But we have received no indication bhat the State intends to exercise the right* nor is it at all likely that if they did the Government of India’s decision would not be upheld. Yours sincerely W.A. Gray Bsq., Burmah Oil Co.* Britannic House* Finsbury Circus* E.C.2.■&gt; 0} P'.Z. 3745/39 ^J/WAG BRITAJtIC HOUSE ? PI US BURY CIRCUS, LOUD01R E.C.2. 15th June, 1939 Dear Mr. Gibson GWADAR I understand that the origin of the connection between Muscat and Gwadar was that a former Khan of Kalat permitted an ancestor of the present Sultan, who was fugitive from Muscat, to reside at Gwadar and enjoy its revenues, but I am unable to discover whether this arrangement was ever formally regularized. In any case, at the time when it originated there was presumably no question of any revenue from minerals. It seems, therefore, that there may be a possibility that the Sultan's right to dispose of the petroleum rights and to receive the royalties thereon might be disputed by uhe Khan of Kalat, — or by the Gichhis, who, I believe, are entitled to a share in the revenues of parts of Mekran. Before we sign any agreement with the Sultan, we shall need to be assured that the mineral rights have been definitely ceded to him or that they will be so ceded when the settlement of the boundary is made. Can you reassure me on this point ? Meantime we are awaiting the Sultan's reaction to our latest proposals, and it is not yet certain whether we shall come to terms with him. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) W.A. Grayu n 00?^ 3 % | 8539 Confidential. Copy of memoramum — llQ^Sb/db-I3-11367-P., dated the 18th| November 1938, from the Hon’ble the Agent to the G-ovemor General, Eesident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. . Kalat - Gwadur boundary. • • • • • Reference correspondence ending with External Affairs Department Express Letter NO.F.&amp;56-N/38., dated the 6th September 1938. 2. I forward for the orders of the Government of India a copy of a memorandum No.2327., dated the 18th October 1938, from the Wazir-i-Azam, Kalat State. 3. The claim of the State to rights of sovereignty over Gwadur appears to me as untenable as that to those of ownership, both having lapsed by adverse exercise of them. 4. The orders of 1863, reaffirmed in 1928, though specifically dealing only with ownership and the right to a share of revenue, may be held to have disposed of the claim to sovereignty as well. The Gitchkis at any rate cannot have any claim apart from that of the Kalat State. 5. I recommend that His Highness should be informed that the Government of India are not willing to support his claim. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S LETTER No. DATE RECEIVED ^ 19 8 - - 12 2 8 ~12\ 1938 11 .... ./■■■ ■ , ^ G^Py °f a memorandum No.2327, dated the 18th October 1938. from ¥azir-i-Azam, Kalat State, to the Political Agent in Kalat. Subject:- G-wadur boundary. Reference correspondence ending with my memorandum No.2268, dated the 10th instant. 2. Your Express letter No.4888 dated the 26th September 1938 sho?/s that the position at Gwadur is at present in a state of such confusion as to require clarifying to enable a correct conclusion to be arrived at. The actual facts as can be gleaned from the different versions and correspondence, printed and otherwise, lead one to believe that Gwadur port and its hinterland formed part of the territory which was undeniably included in the borders of the Kalat State and that the income of the port of Gwadur was allowed by the then Khan of Kalat to be enjoyed hy for his maintenance by a relative of the then Sultan of Muscat, who had left Muscat and come to the court of Kalat as a refugee about the end of the eighteenth century. The practice of the Khans of Kalat has been, and still is, to grant a sanad to the person on whom they bestowed grants of land or jagir showing pretty well a the area thus bestowed with a clear indication of the boundaries of such area. This being the case, the Sanad of the then Khan of Kalat conferrirg the enjoyment of the income of Gwadur to the refugee relative of the Sultan of Muscat must be in possession of the present Sultan and can no doubt be produced by him. This Sanad will not only show the extent of the Kalat territory given as a jagir to the Muscat refugee for his subsistence, but will also show that the concession was given in the same manner as such concessions were granted, and are even now granted, by the rulers of Kalat to their subordinate Sardars and other personages. The grant of such concessions did not, and does not, mean that the Khans relinquished their suzerain powers anf and rights over the areas, but that on the other hand it always meant that the Khan retained, as they do even now, their suzerainty over them and thus possessed the powers of either allowing, at their discretion, the continuance or discontinuance of the concession. This will show tint Gwadur is a-jagir granted by the Khan of Kalat to a refugee of standing ... I- 2 - (§) standing from Muscat and is held by Muscat in the same manner as the other jagirs are held by the Kalat Sardars etc. This fact leads to the corollary that at present the question * regarding G-wadur is not one between an independent foreign power and the Kalat State, but that it is, without any doubt, one between a principal and his concessionaire, and is a purely dometfstic affile between the Khan and his jagirdars, be he a Kalat Sardar or any other personage from outside the State. As such, it should as a rule be dealt with by the w two parties chiefly concerned and the |i question of the intervention of the British G-overnment or the G-overnment of India in the case of a dispute does not arise. The question at present under consideration merely relates to the demarca tion of the boundary of the concession granted by the Khan of Kalat to the Muscat refugee as a Jagir and does not at all concern either the proprietary rights or the suzerainty of the Kalat State over G-wadur. The Muscat refugee was, as already stated above, allowed to enjoy the e income of Gwadur, which was a small place at that time, and the produce of the sura^ee of the land which was attached to the Port. Kalat being the suzerain power in respect of Gwadur, was and is, like other suzerain powers, fully entitled to the proprietorship, possession and disposal of all mines, rivers, hills and forests in the concession and has every right to exercise this prerogative in any manner and at any time they like. It would thus appear that Muscat has no right whatever to enter into negotiations with any body for the exploitation of oil or other minerals in the Gwadur area without the knowledge and express permission of the Khan, who still holds absolute and complete suzerainty over the place, which for purposes of Civil and revenue administration is a part of the territory of the Khan, although administered by a J&amp;girdar. His Highness the Khan feels e very keenly on this question and entertains strong hopes that this aspect of the matter will be brought to the notice of the Government of India and the British Government and that it will receive their full and sympathetic consideration. 5. It may also be mentioned that, as you are aware, the present question of the fixation of boundary is not one affecting the Kalat Durbar only as the Gitchkis of the Kech Valley ..- 3 - @ Valley, which is coterminous with the G-wadur concession, hold revenue interests in the area outside the concession, any alteration or amendment of the G-wadur boundaries as laid down in the Sanad granted by the Khan of Kalat, which are still very well known to most of the local inhabitants of Kech, will naturally affect the G-itchkis as well and are likely to createtroublesome complications. TrueVjW, SaK-\ll legible. Baluehist tendent, cretariat.Conf idential. ■i ■■■■■■■■■■■■ ) 8539 i i 1938 ; From - The Deputy Secretary to the G-overnment of India in the eternal Affairs Department, To - The Hon’ble the Agent to the G-overnor (General Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan v i emorandum No,F.256-N/38. Dated New Delhi, ihe3 ^December 1938, Xalat-Gwadur boundary. Reference your memorandum No.Z-143/38-IS-11367-P, dated the 18th November 1938. 2. The Grovemment of India accept the recommendation made in paragraph 5; and it is requested that action may be taken accordingly. This memorandum is issued under the authority of the Crown Representative. 3d/- W.R.Hay, Deputy Secretary to the (Government of India.THE GOVERNOR GENERAL, /f./jy 5 r ^/ AGENT TO THE GOVERNOR GENERAL, RESIDENT AND CHIEF COMMISSIONER IN BALUCHISTAN. Ziarat, 24th October 1938. - KaCcU' /itTZAAx^OAAj My dear Metcalfe, Please refer to the correspondence ending with Foreign express letter No. F. 256-N/38, dated the 6th September 1938. 2. I enclose a copy of demi-official letter No. 5194, dated the 15th October 1938, from Edwards for the information of the Government of India. A reference is invited to Foreign and Political Department letter No. F. 467-N of 18th in which it was decided that the claim of the Khan _ m which it was dec idea that the claim oi the Kha ^ • / of Kalat to Gwadur was untenable. I shall await an official answer from the State, but it looks as if His Highness will have to be told pretty definitely that the matter must be regarded as settled. C&amp;j Yours sincerely, So/- A.E.B. Parsons. To Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., M.V.O., Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi.CONFIDENTIAL, D.O. No. 5194. Kal&amp;t - Cwadur Bounday. The 15th October 1936. My dear Bedi, Please refer to the correspondence resting with your Express letter No. Z-143/38-IS-1994-P.Z., dated the 14th September 1938. 2. I had a long talk with the \7azir-i-Azam a few days ago about the Kalat-Gwadur boundary question. He gave me to under stand that while the Ealat State recognise that the Sultan of Muscat has established his right of occupation in Owadur and cannot now be turned out, they are still determined to deny that he has any sovereign rights there. They hold that his authority at Gwadur extends only to surface administration and the right of collecting revenue, end that he has no sovereign rights over the territory. From this it follows, in their view, (1) that the demarcation of the boundary is not in fact an inteifi national question of an agreement between Kalat and a foreign State, but is more in the nature of a domestic affair of the Kalat State for the demarcation of a particular area of State territory which has been granted by His Highness the Khan to the bultan of Muscat for enjoyment of the surface revenue - and (2) that all sovereign rights and rights of sub-surface revenues in Gwadur still vest in the Khan of Kalat, and that the Sultan of Muscat has therefore no right or authority to grant any concession for prospecting or mining for oil in Gwadur. 3. The Wazir-i-Azam made it clear that the State are determin ed to go to great lengths in order to establish and maintain this position; and I did not therefore think it right to try to dissuade him. I shall doubtless hear from hia officially in due course; but I scarcely expect to do so before the beginning of December, as MgK His Highness the Khan is absent onV w . - - 2 - 8017 I958 , on a protracted tour of Jhalawan and Mekran and is unlikely to give his approval to any cormmication before he returns. Tours sincerely, Sd/- C.Gr.N. Edwards. To Captain B.D.S. Bedi, Secretary to the Resident and Agent to the Covernor General in Baluchistan, Ziarat.b) ' !? ® S g 1 $ Copy of confidential Expreas letter (Air Mail) No,505-3 ui 1938, dated the 26th Octooer 1938, from Political Resident, Bushire, to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. (Repeated Political Agent, Muscat.) , '* \ of Gwadur-Kalat Boundary. 8017 l I938 Reference correspondence ending with your Express letter No.F.256-N/38, dated the 1st August 1938, I enclose herewith copy of Express letter No.C/140, dated the 12th October 1938, from the Political Agent, Muscat. 2. With regardi to His Highness’s query as to the amount which he would have to pay (vide paragraph 2 of enclosure). (a) As I understand it the two States concerned would share the travelling allowance and transport charges of the Government of India officers employed though their salaries would be met by Government. I presume that Government will provide tentage for these officers ? (b) There will also be the cost of the actual marking of the £hx frontier e.g. boundary pillars. (c) Other miscellaneous items of expenditure. 3. Perhaps the Government of India with their experience of boundary commissions can give me some rough idea of the total expenses, half of which the Sultan would have to meet, which I can pass on to him ?dopy of confidential Express Letter (Air Mail) No.C/140, dated the 12th October 1938, from the Politiaal Agent &amp; His Britannic !fe.jesty f s Consul, Muscat, to the Politicali^e’si{ient, Bushire. Kalat Owadur Boundary. Reference correspondence ending with my express lettdr No.C/131 dated the 3rd October 1938. 2. I have now had an opportunity of seeing the Sultan and took up with him the question of his sharing equally in the expenses of the proposed Boundary Commission. A look of alarm at once appeared on the Sultan 1 s face when he heard that it was suggested that some contribution should be made by him for this purpose and he asked how much his share would amount to. I replied that I had no information on this point but that I felt sure it would not be a great sum and mentioned that the salaries 1 of any Political Officers employed with the Commission would not be included vide Government of India express letter F.256-N/ 38 of 27th July 1938, enclosure to your express letter No.C/544 dated 14th August 1938. 3. His Highness said he wanted to think over the matter and in the last inter vie?/ I had with him which was on 11th October he informed me that he was quite willing to pay all the expenses of his own representatives on the Commission but that as regards any further contributions he would like to be informed that exactly they would be for and as far as possible, the amount involved.. GOIfFIDENiIAL . GOVERNfilENT OF INDIA. (£?) JiXTKlil^AL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT, EXPRESS LETTER* From Foreign t New Delhi To Baluchistan, ^uetta, No*F. 256-N/38 miECT:- u - Dated / 7 November 1938, Owadur-I'alat boundary. Reference correspondence ending with your demi official letter Ho. 2-145/38-IS-2417-, .2., dated the 24th October 1938. 2. A copy of an express letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. 505-S, dated 26th October 1938 (without enclosure) is enclosed. Pending receipt of a definite^reply from the Kalat State the Government of India will be glad to know:- (1) whether the Baluchistan Administration will be able to supply tentage for the proposed coiniaission which will consist of about \tyiree Government officers and staff and two representatives from the States concerned; (2) what sort of transport is likely to be available for the Boundary Lommiasion at Gwadur and what are the rates of hire per day ? The issue of the above lias been authorised SdA V Secretary to Tnaent ofCrUV^i^jakiNT 0 / lit &lt;5&gt; / 6 \ .a K CS) ^7 4' s, ^ liSctemal Affairs pi , T JCwLfT* *” g*jy &lt;?io i %£?** &amp; IMG From To Foreign, uimla, Baluchiatan f /Uarat 1938 . / . Dated the ^ September 1938. aw^Un&gt;KAUT BuUHkaiY, Gontinuation of para. 4 of impress letter from the Government of India in th© External Affaire Depart ment No. F. 256-N/38, dated 27th July 1938. 2. Th© question of the final arbitral authority is linked with that of the authority competent to sign an agreement arrived at between Kalat and Muscat for the settlement of the boundary between these two States. In this connection it has been decided that the Government of Ixidia will sign on behalf of the Kalat State and that although tnero is no objection to their also acting as the final arbitral authority in case of dispute f it would be preferable if His Majesty’s SiiMHMMl ware deaigtt&amp;teu for this purpose. 3. This communication has been ianued under the authority of the Crown Representative. The issue of the above has been authorised. C * a •G ♦ oav idge § Under Secrotfiry to the Govemaent of India&lt; f I \'r «KJ IA FC - , - ' /r ST ARY* 8 Utter f 1 G :*$ S DetwJ 6 SEf Peoehwl 1 - St h V -*t- ''juaMamanr *-3. Ab regards expenditure in connection with Coraniasion raid any preliminary survey which may be necessary the usual custom in these cases is to divide cost equally between parties. Salaries of Government officers employed on Comaisaion would of course be excluded. It is considered that consent of Khan to this procedure should if possible be obtained. Political Resident is being requested to secure consent of Multan on this point, 4. A further communication will follow re^ardin^ the proposal that the Government of India should act as the final arbitral authority in case of dispute. This communication has been issued under the authority of the Grown Representative. 3d/-* mgSEzr* Deputy secretary to the Government of India.Af 5~ooP FI LE GOBY U/rv ^t ^7^. VW0u/^ £ f*S I938&gt; My dear Hay, Gould you please refer to my Express Letter Ho. 222-S of 9th May 1 9j38 on the subject of the Gwadur-Kalat boundary. 2- I discussed the matter further with the Sultan on 25th June without going into details. He made the tentative sugges tion that before the d^emarcation was undertaken the Khan of Kalat should send to the Government of India a map in which i Y/as marked the Kalat - Gwadur boundary according to Kalat ideas. This seems a sensible suggestion in itself, but I imagine that if the proposal is passed on to the Khan, the latter will reply that the Sultan should do likewise. The Sultan could do this and the Government of India will then be in a position to I see how far the xtwo claims differed. 3. If the Government of India agree i will approach the ^Office of the Political Resident in Persian Gulf. ] Karachi, the 2r7th June 1938. Sultan accordingly, * I am sending a copy of this letter to Tatts. Yours sincerely, Sd. T.G.Powle. Ma 4 or ff *h.H ay, C. 1 ,JS», Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. * sent under P.L. Ho.C/378 of 27/6/38.*v Jl 1 ft ip • z: LA S O O ^ . \ ^ 5057 1 938 •■ * j&gt; c * k %, . .. •. l'-i3. *) Telegram K.No„1033 dated 25th June 1938. From Foreign, Simla. r-. ■|' 0 pol- :.ioal Resident Persian Gulf at i^.rachil^^j r- ^ ^ IS) Demi-official from Hay. Gviiadur .v-dat Bouidaiy. 2. Parsons is against definition of boundary but recognises that it mil be necessary if Sultan grants oil concession for Gwadur. According to papers received from India Office Sultan informed you in London that because of obstacle of necessity for approval of Government he had decided not to proceed with negotiations with Burma Oil Company and Indian Oil Concessions. Je learn on oohei hand that representative of former Company has been discussing Gwadur Concession with Sultan at Bombay and it is seated that Sultan has suggested that Company should send representative to 'uscat in October to conclude agreement. Could you ascertain from Sultan what his intentions in the matter are so that we may know whether we ought to proceed with demarcation proposals. fc: F .3. D.S.F. U.3.F .mvin*4? AT riLt oapv nr / . GOVERNMENT OF INpi £008 H T S S 4 u A t 5 ; Y'&lt;S. hy?r c-x fia. Department, j 9 3 3 Confidential EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). /H4 m 3 ) Ivr f J V— [N.B.— rAt* is aw ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, Mb TP.CP.t Titm. h. t})P Stamp. ~r Yinrl'l.h i /\Yi ft C V/* 1 / h n rl ho oca tol o n m* sin Ji ari Wa otttnm intnto n so A t vine. vi**utu,/y 7/HJ I/O VkflU, 19 tlnCfJLJJCI LfbUTl VlwC l/rl.r^r Av 79 ITbvc nA» CIA v\J t/c. iwcu/vnu. 9 on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the farm of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No* &amp; 0/ 457 Worn ?o Hepeated Reference Dated Si'^a ,7 m&amp;mhi' the XS.XXKXX Office of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Karachi. 9th July 1950 7 %8 ’ political Resident, Bushire, at Karaohi. GorernBient of India, External Affairs Department, ^iaila* H#M* georetfiry of State for India, London. politioal Agent, Muscat. Subject i Gwadur Kalat Boundary* I enclose herewith a c opy of any letter l'io.c/457 of 7th July 1938 to the Sultan of Hu scat and a translation of his reply. 2. I agree with Hi a Highness that now that an oil concession Is about to be granted, the demarcation of the frontier is necessary. It is satisfactory that His Highness agrees t o the Government of India bein&amp; the f in&amp;l arbitral authority. 3d.T.&lt;3.JOWL'S . political Resident in the Peraion Gulf. ATTESTS!) M for secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ! 15 JUL 1938 INDIA OFFICH i ■ ' I' S. 44. MFP—985 S&amp;P-&lt;M-1597)—27 11-36—10,000. {Signature) {Designatim)» /j I (l. i 5003 ® ho. a /437 Jr i4S63S'_..j Office of the ?olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Karachi. 7th July 1938. His Highness 3aiyid ;.Jaid bin Taimur, Oultan of Uuacat and Oman. Iftr honoured and Valued friend f With reference to the conversation which I had with Your Highness yesterday on the subject of the demarcation of the Owadur - Kalat frontier Your Highness stated that in view of the possible grant of an oil concession oy you, i or vhich negotiations v/ere slready pro ceeding betv/een Your Highness and two certain Companies, the frontier would now have to be demarcated. 2. Your Highness likewise agreed that the final arbitral authority in regard to the frontier in case of dispute would be the Government of India. 3. I also informed Your Highness that His Majesty's Government would like to know how negotiations for the Oil Concession were pro ceeding between the Burma Oil Company and Indian Oil Concessions Limited and yourself. Your Highness informed me that you did not intend to give either Company a definite reply until you had returned to Muscat, after which you/you would again communicate with them* Your Highness added that you would stipulate that no operations und'er the concession should commence in Gw&amp;dur until the fi* on tier had been demarcated. 4. I would be grateful if Your Highness v/ould confirm the acove in a letter, .then I will inform His Majesty^ Government accordingly. I desire to express the high consideration which I entertain for Your Highness, and to * I subscribe myself. Your Highness* sincere friend, Sd.T.S.mOHS political Resident in the Persian Gulf. tf n i *, ♦&gt; c y w/ * i Translation Dated KaraeM 1 4' &amp;1 ^vwal 1357. 9th July 1938. yroift - H.H. the ;$uitai? of ^uecat and Ctaan. To - Lt.-Col. Trenohard yo«le f Political Peaident in the Persian Gulf. After OompliraentB. I hare received your letter 5o.1/437 dated 7th July 1938 which I read and understood to the end what you mentioned therein. I eonfina the contents of the oaid letter end request you to in form His Majeity f e Government accordingly. I would be glad t o hear from you in due oourae when the doanrcation between i*ty territory, Gwadur, and the fltate of Xalat will commence and wti&amp;t arrange ment u will be made for it. nd. Znld bin TaiaurCopy of a confidential expr^eii letter:No«429-S/3-N,S./37, dated 4th June 1938 f from Baluchistan, Zierat, to Foreign, Simla. 'Gwadur-Kalat Boundary'’. Reference your Sxpresa Letter No.D.1941-N/38 dated the 31st May 1938. (1) Agree that on Kalat side negotiations would hare to be rm&amp;e by Ck&gt;Yt. of India. Presumably Kaiat adviser would be attached to Indian Cooinisaioner. (2) Believe that it has been decided that Central Grovt. bears expenses of demarcation of external frontier of India. (3) As Kalat has gained one of its main objects in establishment of Jiunri and has many other possible oil bearing areas do not consider Khan will be anxious for demarcation.See my telegram 72 of 12th u4ay 1938. (4) Similarly Muscat has apparently abandoned, idaa of oil concession (see papers sent with your endorsement F. 206-N/38, dated the 25th May 1938) and presumably Sultan will not press for demarcation either. (5) Ihere will be no use in having accurate map prepared until agreement of both parties is obtained to 0onmission. ENCLOSUrtE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S Letter No. 10 7 Dated 23 JUN Received 11 Jw 18u8Copy of a confidential demi-official letter No.284-S f dated 25tn May 1938, from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Deputy Secretary to the Govt, of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. Could you please refer to your demi-official letter No.D.1724-N/38, dated 11th May 1938 with enclosures on the subject of the settlement of outstanding questions between Muscat and Kalat. 2. The most important question is that of the frontier demarcation, which is already under consideration, ± vide correspondence ending with India Office telegram No.958, dated 19th May 1938. 3. The other questions centre round the matter of customs dues. On the one hand the Kalat State complain that goods passing through Gwadur into Kalat have to pay Gwadur dues as well as those of Kalat, and on the other, the Sultan a complains of^Kalat blockade. 4. The Sultan was approached on the former question and adopted an uncompromising attitude, vide my Express Letter No. 1494/56/2 of 3rd August 1937. 5. With regard to the latter, as Parsons explains - paragraph 3 of his letter of 29th April - there is no blockade of Gwadur but only a perfectly legitimate customs cordon. I will explain this to the Sultan. 6. With regard to discussions between the two States I agree with Parsons that now that it has been decided to transfer the flying boat base to Jiunri the cards sire more or less in the Khan’s hands. However this may be, I think we should now concentrate solely on the frontier question and leave the others lie quiet for the present, unless again strongly raised by one party or the other. I am sending a copy of this letter to Watts.* *Copy sent under Printed Letter No.285-S, dated the 25th May 1938.[N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. To 222 - Dated xxxxxxx 9th £2ay 19 38 From To lie pea ted your Jolitical Kesldent, huahlre. The Secretary to the Government of India# External Affaire department# Simla* * The A^ent to the Governor General# Resident and Ghief Commissioner in Baluchistan* Political Agent, Muscat. Subject * Gv/adur » Kalat Boundary* My telegram -b*l76 of 9th May 1938* enclosure )N INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter No. 8 9 Dtttd l JUN Reoelved ?0 JUM 1S58 2* Ihe Government of India have conaiderably more experience of demarcating boundaries than 1 have# but they # may find the following suggestions of use. (a) Some sort of small boundary commission will pre» sumably be necessary* ihis commission might consist of the Political Agents Muscat and &amp;al&amp;t# and representatives of the Huscat and Kalat States* tb) In drawing up the terms of the commission a final Arbitral authority will have to be Included# to whose decision both States will submit# In case of dispute between the two States as to any section of the boundary which cannot be decided on the spot by the commission* Such disputes may well arise since, in the event of oil being found any where near the frontier, it may make considerable {Signature) difference/ S. 14. MFP -367 S&amp;F—(M-508)—16-7-35—10,0C0. {Designation)— 1dlfftrei*)* to th« states oorioornod where the frontier line actually rune* arbitral *uithority wi^t be the ^oyeriiaent of India* (4l)oI have little idea how Ion# the oossmieeion will take over ite laboure* Die frontier to be demarcated la not extensive# but there may be dispute# to be settled* (d) It would 1 think save much time if before the qoiaaieeion actually met# the Survey Officer, referred to above# made an accurate may of the area throu^ which the frontier would run# He could be accompanied the 3tats representatives who would later be member# of the oommission# y©r this purpose the -Survey officer could start this preliminary work at Owadur on the l#t October# or whatever was considered a suitable date# (e) Be the expenses of the commission# 1 do not know what the ordinary procedure is# but ae in this oase the boundary is bein^ demarcated for the benefit of the two states concerned# in order that they may con** elude oil concessions# 1 suggest that they - the states • should bear in equal proportions at least some of the expense# of the commission as well as that of the i 1 preliminary survey# ihis mi^t take the form of sharing all expenses except the salaries of the B Soverisaent of India Officers employed# ihis will at least ensure that both states have a motive for expediting proceedings# I 3* It may be worth while mentioning that when I broached/broached to the Sultan the subject of settling the frontier he was very firm on the point that he oould have no direct relatione with : alat&gt; but could only negotiate through His Majesty f s Government* hie 1 of course t ^ulte correct, and for the present purpose as Kal&amp;t is undsr the Government of India, it Is through the latter that negotiations must take place* Gd • T* G • FO lolltioal dissident in the iersiaui Gulf* Sd.J.GRONING for Secretary to the lolltlaal liealdent In the 1 era!an Gulf*COffFIDjMTI/L. Government of India. External Aff- ire Department. EXPRESS LETTRR. A O O k +Zco&gt; ; ' 9 i o j Prom Foreign, Simla. To The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan Ifo. D.1941-N/38. Dated 31st May 193 8 . G AD UR-K/iLAT BOUNDARY. Reference Bushire express letter Ko.222-S., dated the 9th May 1938. 2. 'lease furnish your comments on the suggestions made at a ve^y early date together with any recommendations you may wish to make • 3. This letter is issued under the authority of the Crown Representative. The issue of the above has been authorised. enclosure in INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter No. 8 9 Dated - j U Received 1958 3d * ¥.R. Hay, to the Government of India &lt;T-TTT r i U sat* Confidantlal. w / -v I U i i _ i «»*&gt;*• »ss&gt; i 5 i fu ^ I Vo ^ ? dr«&gt;-j; /vf d 4c.iiCo*ca&lt;c/ kvU H* CA*e&lt;Zk^j ^ !h{ Cm c t r» u&gt;^&gt; ^ 4iA ■a n /?»M, i D«ni -Official No. 2 » 95 / 36 -I 3 » 5107 -P^r y/J /6 | QUiSTTA. ° 29th April 1938. , ^ folj 4_l 6 My dear Hay, Please refer to your demi-official letter No.P.564-N/37, dated the 22nd December 1937. 2. Discussions vith the Kalat State have taken some little time, but I now enclose &amp; copy of a letter from inwards with enclosure, from which it will be seen that His Highness the Khan would not refuse to enter into discussions with the Sultan of Muscat on these matters. 3. There is no 'blockade* of Dwadur from the land side but only a perfectly legitimate guatoms Gordon. 4. The suggested compromise to which Kdwards refers in his letter was to the effect that a joint duty on goods imported into Gwadur for consumption in the Kalat hinterland might be shared between the two Stated in an agreed proportion. 5. I do not myself however think that anything would come out of discussions between the two States, particularly now that it has been decided to transfer the flying boat base to Jiunri. The cards will now be likely to be all in the Khan's hands and he will see no reason to negotiate. Yours sincerely, Sd. A. ii. 3.Parsons . ENCLOSURE IN 'CIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S letter No. *7 1 Dated ]2W Received o AY To . Ttram ( P. Z, 1 M a a t u n rhe 26th April 1936. BABik—Al—£ Uy dear Pinhey, Please refer to Graatrell^ D.O.No.D9-Con. (XLI-13/37 of the 4th April 1938. 2. I enclose a copy of memorandum No.l7-S. f dated the 6th April 1933, from the Wazir-i-Azam, Kalat State. Having so recently taken charge of this Agency I find it difficult as yet to offer any useful opinion on the questions at issu but as His Highness is clearly prepared to enter inot dis cussions on the subject, I am inclined to think that the compromise outlined in paragraph 2 of your D.O. letter No. 431/P*t of the 13th January 1938 might fom a very suitable basis for discussion. The main difficulties in the way of a final solution appear to be the uncompromising attitude of the Sultan of Muscat on the one hand and on the other j the fact that the Kalat State, in their anxiety to attract trade to thiir own posts of Pasni and Jiunri, have little desire to give facilities which might encourage further trade through Gwadar. 3. On the information at present at ray disposal f it does not appear to be true that the Kalat State authori ties have established any '•blockade' on t he Gwadar frontier Possibly the Jultan of Muscat was referring to the Kalat State customs cordon described in Gastrell's D.O.No.368- 4. As to the encroachments referred to in paras 6 and 7 of the Wazir-i-Azam*8 memorandum, I do not suggest that any representation need be made at present. 1 am not yet in- 2 - in a position to estimate to what extent his allegations are justified; and on prima facie grounds it seems that the existence of the Kalat State oustoms cordon should in itself afford a sufficient safeguard against any manifest encroachment. In any cas6 9 if a general discussion is initiated on the compromise basis, the Kalat State author!* ties would doubtless find an opportunity then to ensure that any final agreement contains an adequate safeguard against encor&amp;chment by the Sultan of liuscat beyond Gwadar limits. Yours sincerely, od/~ C.Gr.N • Edwards • To Captain L.A.Gr.Pinhey, I.A., Secretary to the Agent to the Goremor- General in Baluchistan, Quetta. True Copy, Sd/- Illegible Superintendent, Baluchistan Secretariate. Copy of memorandum No.17-3., dated the 6th April 1938 from the Wazir-i-Asam, Kalat State, Kalat, to the Political Agent, Kalat, Mastung. Subject:- Gwadur trade. Reference your telegram No.192 dated the 3rd April 1938 and our discussion dated the 4th instant on the above subj ect. 2. The situation regarding Gwadur affairs is undoubted ly very peculiar of its kind. Originally Gwadur was a part of Mekran territory in the Kalat State. In the Idth century i of Gwadur port was bestowed upon one of the ancestors of the present Sultan of Maskat for his maintenance by the then Khan of Kalat. The remaining t share had neverA leen gifted by the Grichkis of Mekran who still possess such gift Sanads in which the then Khan of Kalat wrote to the aiohkis (ancestors of Nawab Uai Khan) that he had gifted i of his share of Gwadur port to so and so for their maintenance* It is an admitted fact that Gwadur is a gifted property from the ancestors of the present Khan of Kalat and the gift is strictly confined to the Fort area of Gwadur* 3. As regards the complaint made on his part regarding land customs that the Kalat State authorities are not allowing the traders to pass to Gwadur is deroid of facts* 4* The Kalat State has got at present two main Sea PortsFasni and Jiunri along the Mekran Coast* These ports are visited by traders from the following localities;* (1). From Kech Side-pay customs at Karwat and Talan£* (2). Iranian traders coming via Mand and Tump* lay customs at Suntsar* (3) Iranians border traders coming i ay customs at T) _ i J ^ &gt; * .... from Bahu side* kalatak, Kuldan and Chatan* It is in the interest of the traders from the above centres proceeding to Jiunri and Pasni that they are not charged any customs at the above mentioned posts, but when they proceed towards Gwadur a fair rate of customs is charged according to the old established rights* The majority of the traders in their own'financial interest would naturally hesitate to proceed towards Gwadur where they have also to pay another eustoms to the Wali of Gwadur besides the Kalat State dues; and therefore they prefer to go to Jiunri and Pasni rather than to Gwadur and return to their country by the same route. It is this clear that the rights enjoyed by the Kalat State to levy land customs in her own territory are justified in every way and such right could not be waived in favour of the Mli at Gwadur as a gifted property* r:mm A A 6, I think personally the complaint made by the Wall againat the Kalat State customs policy is only meant to conceal his activities which he is raakin ; in connection with the encroachment in the State territory* It is re ported to me by the Naib Wazir Mekran that the Wali is extending his influence along the Mekran coast and he has actually gone as far as 3ur about 12 miles north east of Gwadur and then to Ban and Darbela along the coast while towards Kulanch about 30 miles in the interior of Kalat State and again towards our customs post at ftuntsar about a distance of 3-4 miles from the post* He has started an encroachment gradually upon the State territory which will come to light very soon* In the light of circumstances, the ftali is an aggressor and the Kalat State is an aggrieved party, who cannot tolerate to see his encroachment in the State area likewise* In spite of all this if he is anxious to discuss on the subject, the Kalat State is prepared to receive him or his representative. 7* As regards his encroachment, it is requested that the Wali of Gwadur may kindly be asked to confine his activities to Gwadur Port only, otherwise there is every likelihood of a trouble between his men ana the State people on the border, and which we never desire.Telegram R Nc. 776 Dated 7th May 1938 From Foreign, Simla. To Baluchistan. : 776 (Repeated Political Resident Bushire.J , 'b 0 . ' t ^ A '' tan only. lu / Reference Secretary of State's telegram No. 872, dated the 4th May 1938 /~forwarded with our endorsement No*F.206-N/38 dated the 5th May 1938 y Kalat-Gwadur boundary. 2. Grovernment of India are of opinion that settlement of boundary should be taken up in contemplated discussions between Kalat and Muscat over Grwadur questions and that these discussions should be initiated as soon as possible after Sultan's return to Muscat. 3. In these circumstances they v/ould propose to concur in permission being granted to Companies to conclude conditional agreement with Sultan as proposed by Secretary of State provided they are clearly warned that approval of His Majesty's Government Y/ould not be given until boundary question has been seotled and that this may take a long time. 4. Please telegraph if you concur. 5. Will Political Resident Bushire also telegraph his views. tan only. lu If, fclv-tw'*- (N. FI 959. Telegram R., No. 176, dabed (&amp; rood.) 9T,h May 19:58 From ...... donsul-General, Bushire, Risher. To . Foreign, Simla. (Copy by pest to the A.G-.G-.. Baluchistan) B1PR1SS Your telegram No. 776, May 7th t Kalat-G-'wadur Boundary c 2. I concur in Government of India r s views. va d 4 . Having regard to climatic conditions at G^adur during tne hot weather I. suggest actual denarcation of ooundary sncuJ.o. not commence until say the end of October* Letter follows giving suggestions as to composition of Boundary Commission, etc*P*. Z. 3 Gyphe 'her telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, External Affairs Department, repeated olitical Resident at Bahrein and Political Agent, Lius cat, dated 4th May, 1933, number of v/ords 231? 234 and 234. Important. 872 . Addressed Government of India; repeated Political Resident, Bahrein, and Political Agent, Muscat. Reference your telegram of the 13th January, 60, and (connected correspondence. Gv/adur oil concession. 2. Original intention that Companies should be required to pursue negotiations in Muscat has been frustrated by Sultan's approach in London to Indian Oil Concessions, Ltd., presumably in consecpuence of contact made by him with Standard Oil Company in nmerica. It was considered impossible to prevent Company discussing matter with Sultan and consequently Burmah Oil Company were informed that they also were free to approach Sultan in London. Both companies were reminded of position explained to them in letters of 31st January, viz., that Sultan was under obligation not to grant concession without approval of Government, and that in considering whether permission could be given H.M.G. would have to tame into consideration the boundary difficulties between Gwadur and Kalat. Companies have been allowed to make offers to Sultan, and Indian Oil Concessions have sought permission to conclude an agreement which would contain a clause indicating that the agreement or concession takes effect only when approval has been given by H.M.G. 3. Sultan left this country on 1st May on conclusion of his second unofficial visit. Matters may therefore remain as at present till he returns to Muscat, though there is a possibility that companies may in the meantime wish to continue discussions with him direct or through a representat- Both companies have been asked to refrain from concluding/ ive.2 . concluding any agreement or concession until terms have been approved by Government. 4 . I should be grateful if you could let me have your views very urgently on attitude to be adopted in regard to further progress of negotiations? and with particular reference to boundary question. V/hat is present position in regard to the latter ? I may add that, I understand that both companies are applying for a concession in respect of the Sultan’s territories in Gvadur without any more detailed specification of the area covered. Also Sultan has recognised orally that if a concession is granted, it will then be necessary to proceed to demarcation of frontier. In these circumstances I should be glad to know 'whether you consider that difficulties connected with boundary justify us in continuing to refuse permission to even a conditional agreement with Sultan as described at end of paragraph 2 above.rlLE C y ^ Confidential, D-0.No .0/106. « 71 Office of the ioliticcl fU Qt* Kieidont in the Persian Gulf, H.M.3. Bideford, At Sea* Dated the 23rd February 1938, s Application by the Burraah Oil Company Limited for a prospecting license in Gwadur. H” I'J . -^5 / Hi l^y dear Hay, Would you please refer to your demi-official letter No.F*621-H/37 dated the 28th January 1938* 2* I agree that an attempt on the lines you suggest might be made to settle the outstanding differences between Kalat and Muscat* Nothing in this direction, however, can be done in the absence of the Sultan from his State, and it is tho sort of proposition which in the first instance could best be discussed with him personally* If I get home (see correspondence ending with ray telegram No*T/38 of 20th February ) I could mention the subject to him informally and see how he reacted* 3* I am giving a copy of this letter and of yours to Watts. Yours sincerely, Sd/-. T.C. Fowl©* Major W*H*Hay* CIS*, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, iilxtermil Affairs Department, New Delhi. * under Printed letter No*CA07 of the 23rd February 1938. ENCLOSURE IN ! ’ F0r&lt;E,GN SECRETARY’ S S I liter No. 2 Q 1 jated 1 0 M/ 1 ! h:jcived 2'j Ga.: A &lt; I i 4NFJDENTIAI Office of the igent to hie Govemo General and Chief Commissioner, No.99-3/3-N.S./37. P. Z. 1 Baluchistan. iuetta. Baluchistan. ^ ;;3rd February 1938. Dear Hay, Will you please refer to your demi-official' letter ITo # F.621-N/37, of the 28th January 1938. Owing to his absence from the State I am unable to consult the Khan personally, but judging from a conver sation I had with him just before he left I should say that he would be glad to .^ree to a meeting with the Sultan, and to the inclusion of the Political igent in such a conference. From his side there could be no loss of dignity, as Kalat has 19 guns against MuscaVs 21, while i us cat is an independent Principally. I would suggest however that (a) the Wazirs of each State should be included, (b) the meeting should be on neutral ground, e.g. at Karachi, and (c) a very careful agenda should be drawn up with the idea of arriving at some definite £o inclusions. Finally I rather doubt whether any conclusions will emerge unless a sails appointed by the Government of India can preside at the meeting. Yours sincerely, 3d/- O.K.Caroe. To I la j or W.R. Hay C.I.3., I.A., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, enclosure in ,MDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S letter No. 1 5 Dated lOFE* Received 2 b FEB New Delhi./ »» t/vv. To IMVA 2SlJfr S ® Copy of a confidential letter No* 32-S of 1938 dated Bushire, the 7th January, 1938, from the Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Secretary to t^e Governre-ent of -A- It * ■xy &gt;'} n *7?: 1 India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. * rt x * Subject:- Attitude of Kalat State towards Gwa U- M 1L+Ic% 00 &gt;■ cc r? SC LU ~~ CC rH m £ s 6 LU oc u. z CO sc T—- o C3 rr* lu Lu z o= UJ £ «&lt; ft. o ■4-* ro ■o •o &gt; 'qj o ft&gt; «* 2 sr —J O CC ( I have the honour to refer to your letter No.P.364-N/37, dated the 22nd December 1937, asking for my comments on the application by the Burmah Oil Company for a prospecting license in Gvfadur* 2* The situation appears to be that there are two oil Companies in the field for the Gwadur concession i*e* the Indian Oil Concessions Ltd. representing 50^ American and 50^ British Indian interests (vide paragraph 2 of India, Office telegram No.2809 of the 26th November 193£), and the Burmah Oil Company Ltd., which is of course a British concern. It is presumably preferable from our point of view that the latter should be given at least an equal chance of obtaining the concession. 3. I appreciate Mr. Caroe*s general arguments that previous to the giving of a concession it would be better for the two States of Kalat and Muscat to come to a reasonable compromise over their trade differences and also to demarcate their frontier. The following, however, hhs to be borne in mind. Though the Sultan cannot actually give an oil concession to any Company without the approval of the Government of India (see Undertaking by the Sultan of Muscat regarding oil 1923 at page 319 of Aitcheson*s Treaties Volume XI) there is nothing to prevent the Company starting egotiations with His Highness. If, therefore, we v/ere to try and 4*■ (w) On the balance of advantages, therefore, I arc in favour of allowing feifc both Companies to negotiate with the Sultan forthwith, and I suggest that they should be informed accordingly, 5. 9 ^ am sending a copy of this letter to the Political Agent, Muscat,D.0.Ko.F.62i*N/37. External Affairs Department. ^ New Delhi f The January 1930 • Gwadur. Application by the Burmah Gil Company Limited for a prospecting license in Zi 7 o^S Please refer to our official letter to you No#F.564-V 37, dated the 22nd December 1937. 2* It seems desirable to make some attempt to settle the outstanding differences between Lalat and nscat not only on account of the applications which hare been received for oil concessions in the Jubal-i-Uehdi area, but also on the general grounds. It has been su*/gested that a meeting might be arranged between representatives of the two otates in ' the presence of the Political officers concerned for the purpose of reaching an amicable settlement. I am desired to enquire whether you consider this practicable. 3. One of the difficulties is the difference of status between Muscat and Kalat. V«e have a precedent, however, in the discussions that have recently taken place at Kabul between / nvjWLi.—nbetween representativea of Affc^ianisian and Chitr;d o?er tiie transit of Chitral timber throu^x Afghani a tan* The Oriental ^ecretjury of the Legation was present and took part in H these uiacusHions, and a unanimous report was submitted which is at present under consideration* 4* de are addressing a similar letter to Garoe* Yours sincerely, 3d/-. vV.R. Hay, The Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel 3ir Trench ird Fowle, CBri., Political (esident in tiie Persian Gull*—i—■ D.0*no.F.621-H/37 External Affairs Department. £ Hew Delhiri The January 193 s . Application by the Burmh Oil Company Limited for a proepecting license in Gwadur* Please refer to your letter No.7335, dated 13th December 1937. 2* It seems desirable to make some attempt to settle the outstanding differences between Kalat and &amp;£uacat not only on necount of the applications which hate been received for oil concessions in the Jabal Mehdi area, but also on general grounds* It has been suggested that a meeting might be arranged between representatives of the two States and the Political officers concerned for the purpose of reacning an amicable settlement* I am desired to enquire whether you consider this practicable* 3* One possible difficulty is the difference of status between Muscat and Kalat* 1* have a precedent, however, in the discussions that have recently taken place at Kabul between /between ropreaentatives of Af^uuiistan and Jhitral over the t oi Chitral timber through Afghanistan* The Oriental oeoretary of the Kabul Legation was present and took part in these discussions* and a unanimous report ^ae submitted which is at present under consideration* 4* Vie are addressing a similar letter to Kowle* Yours sincerely, 3d/-. W.R. Hay, The Hon'ble Mr* O.K* Caroe, CB*. Agent to the Governor General. Resident and Chief Conaaissioner in Baluchistan.tN ■ MP4 nvA Att^tudn of Kalat State toward G-y^d u^. V\ We have some papers (Coll. 30/27) giving the Kalat versibn of the story in which they complain that goods entering Kalat through Owadur, though only in transit, have to pay a double iuty, first to the Muscat State and then to Kalat. The solution proposed by the Kalot State was to open a port of their own at Jiuni but this had to be dropped owing to the refusal of the B.I. Steam Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to call at that place. In order to ease the situation the Political Resident suggested, and the Government of India agreed, that the Sultan should be asked to reduce the duties on Gwadur transit trade; but v/hen the suggestion was put to him (about last May) he stated that he was unwilling to make any reduction in the Gwadur customs dues. In such circumstances the Kalat Authorities can hardly be blamed for their blockade tactics and it looks as though the ; ultan must give way in some measure before any compromise can be reached. Here again nothing can be done until we receive the views of the Government of India and the local ’olitical Authorities concerned.IMIKMp P.Z. 195/33. CONFIDENTIAL. No. 7335. From The Hon 1 hie the Agent to the Governor-General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Qaln. To The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi . Dated Quetta, the 13th December 1937. Subject: Application by the Burmah Oil Company Limited for a prospecting license in Gwadur. Sir, In reply to Major Hay’s letter No.F.564-N/37, dated the 30th November 1937 I have the honour to say that Colonel Parsons left no record from which it is possible to conclude what were his exact reasons for holding that it is undesirable to raise at present time the question of the undemarcated boundary between Gwadur and Kaiat. I learn moreover that he did not think it necessary to explain his objections in the course of his meeting with the representatives of the Burmah Oil Company. 2. It occurs to me, however, that his attitude may have been influenced by the fact that there is at the present time considerable friction between the Kaiat and Muscat States, due to a divergence of interest in the matter of control of the trade which uses Gwadur as a base to serve the hinterland of Mekran and adjacent parts of Tr»an. It is believed that His Highness the Sultan of Muscat in the course of his recent visit to Delhi raised objection to the duties which the Kaiat State authorities impose on goods imported via Gwadur, on the ground that such goods are subjected to a double duty, namely a Gwadur transit tax/whip —Hi 1 mmmt tax and a Kalat import duty. On the other hand, as the Government of India are aware, the Kalat State in their turn wish to develop their own port at Jiunri as a rival to Gwadur, and have approached the British India Steamship Company with a request that the Company’s steamers may call at that port, the object being to avoid the transit duty imposed by the Muscat State at Gwadur. Col.Parsons may, perhaps, have thought that any development scheme or concession i-aising the question of demarcation of the Kalat-Gwadur border would be inopportune in view of the trade disputes which have arisen between the two States. Prom such knowledge as I possess of this matter I am inclined to agree with this view and in particular to doubt whether an oil concession, part of which would be in Muscat territory and part in adjacent Kalat territory, could be easily worked, until the authorities of the two States have arrived at a reasonable compromise regarding other matters in disrjute along the Mekran Coast. 3. The matter is one on which the Government of India will no doubt wish further to consult the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, of whose views I should be glad to be informed. I have, etc., Sgd. 0. K. Caroe. Agent to the Governor General in Baluchistan.Confidential. Prom To No.P. 564-N/37. The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated New Delhi, the 22nd December 1937. Attitude of Kalat State towards Gwadur. Sir, In continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, No.P.564-N/37 dated the 30th November 1937, I am directed to forv/ard a copy of letter fr'om the Hon f ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, No.7335 (without date) and to say that the Government of India would be grateful for your comments. I have, etc., Sgd. W. R. Hay, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.\V ,0 &amp; &amp; P ry *-.i a 1 r 'i ton h,eld on 17.11.37. Extract from Note of di. , between Sir Aubrey MetcaTfeT^sicre^ary, External Affairs Department, and His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, at which the Political Agent, Muscat, was also present. (12) Attitude of Kalat State towards Gwadur . The Sultan brought up the question, which he had referred to in his interview with H.E., of what he declared was the blockade of Gwadur by the Kalat State authorities. He asserted that both travellers and caravans with goods from the interior especially from Persian Baluchistan were being prevented from entering Gwadur. Since it was such caravans who used also to take back goods purchased in Gwadur into the interior, a considerable loss in revenue from customs duty was being suffered by his State. Secretary said that he had no information on this matter but that the action alleged tobeing carried out by the Kalat State was certainly not being done under instructions from the Government of India. He would however have inquiries made in the case.■HnmM p r /' • Jc .. ' (w&gt;) Extract from Note of an interview lietwejQjj'^ps Excellency the Viceroy, and His HiSulian of Muscat, at which Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, Secretary, External Affairs Department, was also present. After His Excellency had explained to His Highness that he would like to listen to any matters which His Highness wished to raise, the Sultan opened proceedings by explaining his grievances regarding Gwadur. He said in effect that the Kalat State, by using their geographical position, place what amounted to a blockade upon Gwadur. This place is a small tract of land on the coast of Baluchistan with only a few square miles of territory, but an immense hinterland formed partly of the Kalat State and partly Persian Baluchistan. It has been the practice hitherto for the Sultan to make large income from import duties on goods which come in by sea to Gwadur and are then taken by caravan either into Kalat or into Persian Baluchistan. It is probable, so Major Watts tells me, that the greater portion of the imports into Baluchistan is smuggled without payment of Persian customs duty which makes of course this route a popular one for traders. Goods intended for Kalat have to paynot only the Gwadur import tax but also Kalat import duty which the Kalat Government not unnaturally regard as oppressive. The Kalat State are therefore anxious to develop their own port at Jiuni which is 40 or 50 miles west on the same coast. Their difficulty in doing so lies mainly in the fact that no ocean going steamers call at Jiuni whereas the B.I. Coastal Ships call at Gwadur. The Kalat Government therefore approached the A.G.G. some little time ago asking that pressure might be brought either on the B.I. Steamship Company to call at Jiuni or on the Sultan of Muscat to reduce his import tax for goods intended for ■ consumption/-* 2 . mmid consumption in Kalat and the substitution of a transit duty. The first alternative was impracticable, since the 3.1. Steamship Company are not amenable to control by the Government of India and the Sultan when approached on the subject flatly declined to reduce his import tax for the benefit of Kalat. Major Watts tells me that he made enquiries a few days ago on his way from Muscat to Karachi and found that the •‘■'•alat State were in fact preventing caravans from coming from Persian Baluchistan through Kalat | to Gwadur and were diverting them further north to Pasni. There is, therefore, certainly some truth in the facts whichB the Sultan stated to His Excellency; but his idea that the : Kalat State are acting at the instigation of the British Government is entirely incorrect. They appear to be acting solely in their own interests and it is difficult to |jf see what can be done to help the Sultan in this matter. I will, however, have up the papers and if His Excellency wishes will address the A.G.G. in Baluchistan on the subjec in case some compromise can be effected. But it must be realized that the Sultan himself must give way in some measure before any compromise can be reached.Co»fIdgftiial* Ftok 2fo.F.564-V37. to 3ir The Deputy Secretary to the GoT^rncerit of India in the External Affaire Depertm&lt;»nt» Xh« Hon’blQ the A*, eat to the OoTemor General Resident and Chief Coralsaloner in Baluchistan* Bated Sew Delhi» the J-z? Sov - -i'd&lt; r 1937* Application by the Borsah Oil Company Limited for a prospecting license in Gwadur. I am directed to forward for information a copy 1* Express letter fro&amp; Brltooasul, Buehirc Bo*738-3/37 ? 5 cf the dated the 6th Bovember 1937 and encloeures ) with map/* 2* Letter froja Colofiel V*i2* Abraham , dated the 22nd , ■ .^} Boveober 19f7 with encloaure* ° | aot ) corr^epondence in the 3* Memorendu* fron, the Kon*ble the Political Resident in the i&amp;xzl&amp;n Gulf So#bl2-3# dated the 16th ) o^rgin and to Bovemb^r 1)37 and enclosures^ } 4.Ib!CenaE fro* the Gecretary of State for India Ro.2809* j »%y that if the dated the 26th Bo^^ber 1937, ) 5. Telegrao* to —ditto— Bo*£326# d?ited the 27th Bo^ember 1937. 6. Telegr&amp;fO from --ditto-** &amp;o.282S&gt; dat»?d the 27th } attributed to Be? ember 1937* ) \ J Colossi Parsons -77:2 &amp; j statement in the first sentence of paragraph 3 of th second enclosure has been rorreo'Cly reported the Covertiiaent of India would be glad to know, more fully why he considered it undesirable that the quertion of the und^narea ted boundary between Muse* t cu.d Knlat should be raised at the present ) in *w. I have the honour to be* 3ir* Your most obedient servant* Sd/- W.R. Hay* Dsputy Secretary to the GoTernment of Indie*aiAMIL. We hfi?e applied for a prospecting licence over the Jebel Mehdi area, of which the Western part is in Muscat territory and the eastern part in Baluchistan territory, the dividing line between the western and eastern parts being uncertain as the boundary has not been demarcated. 2* Watts told me yesterday (a) that Sir Aubery Metcalfe had said on 20-11-37 that he could see no obj ection to Watt's raenti ning the matter to the Sultan (b) that since the Sultan was leaving on a world tour on 30-11-37 it might be wise to arrange something before that but (o) that before we eoul^ actually negotiate wi tl the Sultan he (Watts) would require the sanc tion of the India Office, and he therefore | suggested (d) that I should today cable my London Office asking them to get in touch with the India Office and request the latter to cable the necessary sanction to Watts. 3. I should not be worried about any of this were it not!, that last week, in Quetta, Colonel Farsons said definitely that applications for the eastern part of the same area could not now be considered, as consideration of any such application would automatically raise the question of the undemarcated boundary between Muscat and British territory and he *tar»f*xax thought it most undesirable that this question should be raised at the present time. The quest ioiv'-question of the boundary would presumably be raised just' as much by an application to the Sultan for the Western portion as by an application to Baluchistan for the east ern portion, and before taking any action on the lines of paragraph 2(d) above I should like to be assured that such action would not meet with the disapproval of the Govern ment of India# 4* I ought to add that Ta.tts ie under the impression that I am today cabling London on the lines iug- ested by him. It was only after further consideration of the implications and possible consequences of this action that 1 decided that I ought first to put the matter before your Department. I tried to get Watts on the telephone this morning to let him know that I was doing this, but failed. 5. I attach a copy of a letter received a few days ago from the Resident, Persian Gulf, indicatin that the correct procedure now is an approach to the India Office in Jondon. If I do not now cable, such an approach will presumably be made by our London Office in a week or two « but by that time the Sultan will have left Bombay. Yours sincerely R 3d/- W.Abrahamy of Express letter No.1494/56/2. dated the 3rd August 7 f from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Secretary to the Government of India m the External Affairs Department. Cop 193 Request by the Kalat State for compelling British India Steam Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to make fort nightly calls at Jiuni port. Reference correspondence resting with Deputy Secretary’s memorandum No.F.18-F/36, dated the 28th May 1937. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat, reports that he approached the Sultan on the subject. The latter pointed out that, under the 1891 Treaty, British subjects already enjoyed a favoured position and he added that he was unwilling to make any reduction in the Gwadur customs dues. 3. The Sultan’s attitude was most firm and unc ompr omi s ing. WD1A FOOLM utte, u £ 4 » Daiad 9 . i : ' •’Oalved . .1 .j37 • v 'W'', 1 _11»&gt; B From — The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department # To — The Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Conmissioner in Baluchistan*I Memorandum No.F.18-F/36. Dated Simla, the / ? A August 1937. £e&lt;juest by the Kalat State for cornpellim? British India^ Steam Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to make fortnightly calls at Jiuni port. Beferenee correspondence ending with Government of India, foreign and Political Department, endorsement No.F.18-F/36, dated the 9th December 1936. 2. From the enclosed copy of Express letter from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire, No # 1494/56/2, dated the 3rd August 1937, it will be seen that the Sultan of lluscat is unwilling to make any reduction in the Cwadur customs duties. It is regretted, therefore, that no further action can be taken. 3. This consmmication is issued under the authority of the Crown ^representative# ux urown representative# Sd/- W.R. Hay, \ Deputy Secretary to the GoTeraman t of India nm Fv better ;PILE COFte c - rf, &amp; ^■J' i h (m d Copy*of memorandum No* 2346/56/2 dated Bushire, the 18th November 1936 from the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to‘ the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. ! 9 1 3 7 L. 1936 Request by the Kalat State for compelling British India Steam Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to make fortni^Jitly calls at Jiuni Port. 2r , v lurn No. 4. ces, I do have ; Reference correspondence ending with your memoranda F.18-F/36 of 29th October 1936 with enclosure. 2. Since the Government of India, vide their Express Letter No. F. 18-F/36 of 28th August, are not in a position to compel the British India Steam Navigation Company’s steamers to call at Jiuni, presumably these steamers will not call there. This being so the Indian merchants of Gwaaur (see paj22graph 5 of my Express Letter No. 1518/56/2 of 20th July) will stay where they are. The position, therefore, from the view of the Muscat State is not so serio u s . 3. At the same time I recognize, as I said in paragraph 5 of my Express Letter quoted above, that there is force in the complaint of the Kalat State as to gpods entering that State through Gwadur having to pay double duty. I shall be visiting Muscat in the course of the next month or so, and propose dis cussing with the Political Agent and the Muscat authorities the solution put forward in paragraph 6 of the same letter. The Sultan is still absent at Dhofar and in the circumstan- EKGLOCURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Utter No. 23M: M. i o dlo. i 2 3 DEC 1936QOMrag-^i From - The Deputy Secretary to the Goreminent of India in the Forai t n and Political Department* To - The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Memorandum No* F* 18-F/56* Dated New Delhi, the } December 1936* f Request by the Kalat State for conr.)ellin^; British India Steam Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to make fort- ni^itly calls at Jiuni Port. Reference your memorandum No* 234£/56*2, dated the 16th November 1956, 2* The Government of Imia have no objection to the proposed communication to the Sultan of Muscat being i deferred until you have visited Muscat* 3d. ».H. Hay Deputy Secretary to the Goverm® nt of India.-yiH '&gt; 4 05;^ j Copy of a memorandum No. 1466-P.Z. dated the 22nd September 1956, from the Agent to the G-ovemor General and Chief Conmissioner in Baluchistan, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. v 'n/ 1 / Request by the Kalat State for Compelling British India Steam Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to make fortnightly calls at Jium Port. Reference Foreign and Political Department impress letter No.F. 18-F/36, dated the 28th August 1936. 2. The reduction of the Gwadur duties might afford some minor relief to Kalat traders generally but would not meet the main object which the Kalat State authorities have in view, namely to establish a port of their own in the western section of the Mekran coast and thereby to develop their own trade and ensure that the State receives the revenues from its own comnercec If however the Government of India is unable to bring any influence to bear on the British India Steam Navigation Company, there is nothing more to be done. 0 0.00From - The Addl: Deputy iiouy* to the Gofemaent of India in the Forei^x and Political Department, To - Tl&gt;e Hon'bie the Political ^eaident in tho ^«oranclU 0 i No*F.ll3-F/36 # dated New jelhi, thz October 1 &gt;b6. .vcaueat by the Kelat State for compelling bn tiali India Steam Kavaction Company to nrnoi^e for tlieir to nake fortnightly calls at Jxuni port. * • • ♦ • Roferoiice correspondence ending with tiie endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, i!o.F.18-F/3C, dated the 26th ruguet 1936. 2. A copy of mamorant&amp;ia from the Hon’ble the feent to Ulq Governor General and Chief Coaoiseioner in haluoliistan, Ko.l4S6~P*Z, datoci the 22nd September 19v ? 6, is ©nolosed, for inforaationi Tiie Government of India consider that some relief should, if possible, be afforded to the Kalat traders and for this pirpose they agree to a corsaunioation being sent to the Sultan of iiuscat on tiie lines of paru- gniph 1 of Uie dnd% enclosed with your Express letter N0.151Q/&amp;6-2, dated the 20th July 1936. In view of the time that has ©lapsed the remaining paragraphs of the draft appear no longer applicable and the Government of India leave it to your discretion to re-write them in such form as may appear to you appropriate. 3d/-. K.P.S. Menon, Additional De^ty Secretary to the Govemmeiit of India.Prom To FILE CO^YB78R I v. K\&lt; '«*&gt;. 1 trv*&lt; Vr .1 ’956 j ; 0 iit to tiie and Chief COKB..isaiont;r in Baiudiistan c I ( The Hon’ble the Agent to liie Governor-General The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign arid Political Detriment, New 7 )elhi. H enio random No. 742-P. 3 • hnted Camp Sibi, the 22nd January 1936. V lubject R 1 po9t.b^ th nti o ar ortn Inai^ e for their .. . lv calls at Jiuni ort. I enclose a copy of the marginally cited memorandum from the Political Agent in Kalat and Political Agent incharge of the Bolan Pass and of Chag&amp;i District and request the Government of India to use their good offices in the matter if they have the power. J-&gt; sd/- for Agent to the Governor- Gone ral in Balucnistan.Copy of a latter No. 266 dated the 13th January 1936 from the Political Agent in Kalat and Chftgfci to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Agent tc tiie Governor- General in Baluchistan, 3ibi. I have the honour to report that I have recently received a request from the asir-i-Azam, Kalat State, for the assistance cf the Government of India in compelling the British India Steau Navigation Company to arrange for their steamers to fortnightly calls at Jiuni port. 2. Jiuni is situated to the east cf Gwattar Bay and is admirably located as a port for the valley of the Dasht river. It is also well placed as an export base for the Wishing industry of the western section of the .Vekran cop^t, and for trade with south east Persian Mekran. At the present moment the whole of this trade passes throu^i Gwadur, which is a luacat possession, and which has for many years, by reason of its favourable position, drawn considerable revenues from trade passing to, from and through Kalat territory. For reasons into which it is unnecessary to enter, the majority cf the Indian traders in Gwadur are anxious to move tc Jiuni 3 but it is obviously impossible for them to carxy on business in Jiuni unless and until arrangements have been made for regular steamer service to that port. 3. On various occasions efforts have been made to xxx± induce the British India Steam Navigation Company to arrange calls at Jiuni, but hitherto that company has declined to consider the proposal on the ground that 'No advantage would accrue to them by making &amp; regular call at that port'. 1 hile it may be freely admitted that the establishment of Jiuni as a port cf call for steamers would not appreciably increase the total volume of trade on this coast and would, in fact, do little more than divert a considerable proportion of the Gwadur trade to Jiuni, it remains a fact tnat the British India Steam /Navigation'avigation company iiave used Uieir monopoly ol tifie carryin^r trado along the ieKran coast and tho P ersian Gulf to tne detriment of an Indian i tate under tne protection of tho Government of India, and tc the equal disadvantage botii of tiie traders and of the fishermen and other producers living in Kaiat State, whose goods taey carry and whose merchandise must now perforce pay both J uscat and r&amp;lat dues. The State authorities iiave therefore explored the possibility of compelling the company to waKe a call at Jiuni and tiiey report that according to tiieir inionnation the Government of India are in a position tc compel Uie British Indian Steam Navigation Company to call at any port for tiie purpose of delivering and collecting tails. If this information is correct and if the Government of India are prepared to use this power the State authorities on their part are ro n iy immediately to guaranuou the roots and Telegraphs Department ugainst any loss on their establishing a combined office at Jiuni ana they have in fact already made this offer to the Director of Posts and Telegraphs at Karachi. They are at the sa.xe time prepared to expend funds on the improvement of Jiuni as a port. They therefore request that the Government of India be moved to intervene on their behalf, and in exercise of the autnority residing witei thorn to direct the British India Steam Navigation Company to make fortnightly calls at Jiuni on both the inward and outward voyages. This request 1 most strongly support since it seems clear that a State under the protection of the Government of India is entitled to claim their sympathy in the development of its own trade, the revenues from much of which have in the past been diverted to an alien State solely owing to trie obstructive attitude of a mono poly-owning Company. 4 # i should add that it is only with reluctance that the State authorities have decided to solicit the aid of tiie Government of India, and they have in fact explored various other means of compelling the company in their own interests to call there, botore tailing back /on,on this final expedient, efforts have, for instance, \been made to interest Imperial Airways in Jiuni as an alter native aerodrome to Gw&amp;dur and indeed such are its advanta^*es that these effcrte would probably have succeeded but for the decision to exchange from land-planes to sea-planes in the near future. Unfortunately for ;alat State x the T-shaped headland at uwadur provides a sea- % plane harbour with which neither Jiuni nor any other port on tliis coast can compete in safety or all-weather utility.mmm EXPRESS LETTER. Prom Resident, Bushire. Foreign, Simla. Repeated to Political Agent, Muscat. No. ^518 Dated 20th July 1936. Reference your memorandum No. F.18-F/36 dated the 20th February 1936 and my memorandum No. 1011 dated the 16th May explaining that the matter was under correspondence with the Political Agent, Muscat, and that a report will be submitted as soon as the latter had given the details. These details have now been received and I am in a position to reply as follows :~ 2. In paragraph 3 of Political Agent, Kalat’s letter No. 266 dated the 13th January, it is stated that in the opinion of the Kalat State tae Government of India are in a position to compel the British India Steam Navigation Com pany to call at any port for the purpose of delivering and collecting mails. I shall be glad to know if this assumption, which is an important factor in the question under review, is correct or not. Assuming it to be correct then if a Post Office is opened at Jiuni (marked Jiunri on some maps) the Government of India can compel the British India Steam Navigation Company to call there. If the assumption is not correct then the British India Steam Navigation Company will presumably make their decision as to whether call at Jiuni or not on purely commercial grounds. 3. Even if the assumption of the Kalat State is correct, I venture to think that the Government of India, in making their decision, will, doubtless, consider /the....the interest of the Muscat 3tate as £iuch as that of :alat. It is true that technically •peaking the Sultan of Muscat is an independent sovereign, and that Kalat is a state under the Government of India, but at the aaiae time to itAny intents and purposes the Muscat Jtate is also under the protection of the (jtoverrment of India, who have in the past come to its assistance on many occasions in various ways - financial and otherwise* 4# Major ?iatts is cf the opinion that il’ tho British Indian coramunity in Gwadur were to migrate to Jiuni (Yids. Paragraph 2 of Political Agent, KalaVs letter referred to;, and if that port were rrade a call for British India steamers, there will be a heavy fall in the import trade and therefore of the customs revenues of Gwadur, and con sequently of the Muscat State. (The proportion of the trade of Gwadur to the total of the Muscat trade is approximately 20,4 and that of the transit trade of Gwadur to the total trade of Gwadur is 80/i). I quite concur in Major Watts’ opinion, and in this connection the Government of India will remember that only recently the ! uscat State, after many years of semi-bankruptcy, has at last become solvent. It is hardly necessary for me to point out that it would be most unfortunate if by reason of its loss in Gwadur revenue the state were once more plunged in financial difficulties. 5. I recogdse nevertheless that there is force in trie complaint of the Kalat State that goods entering that State through Gwadur though only in transit have to pay a double duty, first to the Muscat State and men to Kaiat. Major \vatts points out that until recently when the duty in both states was low (the actual duty in each case being 3&amp;) the double duty was not of &amp;mt conse quence. In 1934, however, when the Muscat government (with the pennission of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India) raised its duties on numerous arti cles to 10* the situation was altered, and at the present moment the merchants of Gwadur are complaining that their export trade with the hinterland lias fallen off considerably. Major Matts further confirm* the statement of the K&amp;lat State (referred to in paragraph 4 above) / tnat. 'IT 1 T'*’ 1 ,'th&amp;t tha more enterprising Britisn Indian mordunits of Grwadur, in whose hands practically the whole trade of Gwadur lies, declare their readiness to move to Jiuni directly arrangements have been made for steamers to call at that port. 6. The beat solution of the problem seet.B to me for the li uscat State to reduce their duties on Gwadur transit trade* This reduction cannot, however, be c^de without the personal sanction of, and discussion with, the Sultan who is, as the Government of India are aware, absent in Dhofar and from which place he cannot re torn, now that the monsoon has set in, until October* I propose, therefore, subject to the sanction of the Government of India, which I will be glad to receive as early as possible, to send him through the Political igent, iiusoat, tdi© communication attached* In this connection please see ray letter No. 133-3 of 17th February 1936* Resident The Issue cf the above has been authorised* SdA I Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.'rom Th&amp; Hon*bio the Political Heeident in the Persian Griilf. To His Ht'hnoas the Sultaii of Muscat. After compliments: 1 have the honour to inform your Hiciness of the following situation which has arisen. The ialat State have approached the Government of India with a request that a postal and telegraphic office should be opened at Jiuni (Jiunri) in their territory and that arrangements should be made for steamers to call there. The reason for this request is that goods in transit for Kalat via Gwadur have to pay &amp; double duty f that cf your Government and that of the Kaiab 3 tat* These duties have recently been raised by Your Highness from 5 to 10/J. The Kalat State affirms, and Major iiatts confirms this, that British Indian merchants in Gwadur, in whose hands, as Your Highness is aware, most of the trade lies, are prepared, if B,I« steamers call at Jiuni, to leave Gwadur and proceed there. If this were to occur, lajor Watts is of opinion that the Gwadur customs revenues of your State would suffer severely, 1 agree in this opinion, 2, The Government of India are, as Your Hi^mess is aware, always ready to protect your interests, but in the present instance they find it extremely difficult to do so owir^$ to your absence in Dhofar, They are of the opinion that this matter can only be satisfactorily settled by personal discussion between the Political Agent, myself and Your Highness, They are willing to postpone any action in the matter until next October, but if Your Highness by that time has not returned to l uscat they will be compelled to take such action as they see fit, in your absence.■m 3# I have nn various occasions (please see my letter, for instance, of 4th Parch 1933) explained to Your Hi^inesa that should arythin^ untoward in the 3tate happen by reason of Your Hi^meBs* absence, it would im of course be Your Highness 1 responsibility and in no way mine or my Government’s, I GAist anain repeat this warning in connection with this natter• I hope, however, that I shall have the pleasure of seeing Your Highness in Muscat next October and that in the meantime Your Highness is enjoying good health. Usual Ending* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,gQrtl^ilBfTIAL . foreign and Political laperteient. EXPRESS LETTER. from •’oraifTi, Ski la. To Baluchistan, Ziarat. Mo. .16-/36 Dated &lt; ur i 3 6. Request by the Kalmt SUte for ooiapolii^: British India Steam r vi ation rompany to arri4^,e for tiieir al fortiiirhtiy calls at Jiuni port# to cake leiorenoe your t^aoranduia Ho. 742-P. ;., dated the 21nd January 1936. 2. Under the tew a of the Agreement with the Britieh India ! team Haviention Company the OoTomaent of India are not in a poeition to ooapel the Compehjr'a atow era to call at Jiuni port for the purpose of delivering; and oollecting mail*. The aovemmant of India would, however, be glad to be fumiahed with your viewa on tie au geation Bade in para. 6 of the express letter from the Resident, Bashirs, Ho. dated the 20th July 1936, a copy of which ia enclosed. laaue of the above hea been authorised. jd/- K.P.J. 1 anon. Addl. Deputy Jeeretaxy te the aeten—rt ef India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2985</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2985</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/25 'Muscat: Kalat-Gwadar Relations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-14T22:08:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (201 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 203; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-203; these numbers are also written in pencil and circle.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, notes, and memoranda relating to relations between Kalat State and Gwadur [Gwadar], the latter being part of the Sultan of Muscat's territory.the Kalat State's request for postal and telegraphic offices to be established at Jiuni [Jīwanī] and for British India Steam Navigation Company steamers to make fortnightly calls therethe Burmah Oil Company Limited's application for an oil prospecting licence in the Gwadur areathe demarcation of the boundary between the two territories, necessitated largely by oil explorationthe Sultan's complaints about a blockade of Gwadur by the Kalat State and encroachments over the border by Kalat State officials and American geologistsarrangements for a meeting between the Sultan of Muscat and the Khan of Kalat (which never took place)the Royal Air Force's use of facilities in Gwadur and Jiwanithe question of the strategic importance of Gwadur to the British and whether to induce the Sultan to sell the enclave back to the Kalat Statethe status of Kalat following India's independence and the creation of the Dominion of Pakistan, including a memorandum by the Minister of State for Commonwealth Relations, dated 12 September 1947, that deals with the legislative and political relations between certain 'Princely States' and the Dominion of India (folios 42-51).The principal correspondents include the Government of India (External Affairs Department), Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Political Agent at Kalat and Chagai, Agent to the Governor-General in Baluchistan, Political Agent at Muscat, Admiralty, Air Ministry, British Agent at Gwadur, Commonwealth Relations Office, and the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom in Pakistan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner to Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kalat and Bolan Pass</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Agent to the Governor-General, Resident and Chief Commissioner, Baluchistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Air Ministry</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Gwadur</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kalat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000211#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>