<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00033f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T19:08:36.424Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ INDEXED - From To (Copy) FSLE GORY The Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, Grovernment of India, Quetta. ^ 27 OCT 194W^ Xttf- The DIRECTOR, XS'J^. ' Intelligence Bureau (Home Department), 5overnment of Ind A Simla. Memorandum No. 3P/12/17/2097. Dated Quetta, the 13th May, 1940. c i ^jr A I— r / - 'v 53bO 1940 Copies of preliminary statements of the four Poles and one Russian arrested at Juzzak on the 6th G:ay, recorded during an interrogation conducted by Mr.N. 7. Dorofeeff, Garrison Engineer, Reconstruction, are attached for information. The following passage in the statement of Adam Backer requires elucidation and this will probably be forthcoming. It would appear that he and Stolyhwo proceeded from Krasnovodsk to Charioi and Merv before returning and crossing the Persian frontier. 'From Krasnovodsk after consideraole journey we reached the Persian frontier beyond Charjoi and Merv. We obtained railway tickets help of a Russian woman who Odessa.* from Krasnovodsk with the travelled with us from There are a few other minor discrepancies which are of little importance. The impression gained by Mr. Dorofeeff is that all five are genuine refugees, but that Bekerman is hiding something~of his life^oefore he joined the polish army. All the four Poles wish to be sent to join the Polish army in France. The five refugees will be interrogated further and the documents in their possession examined. Anything of interest that_comes to light will be reported. £NGGO \N \NO' F 0RE' qH 0 mX ' 5 ; W - 1940 so. a . 8 A A8 - U 3d/- C. Jojfce o Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, Government of India, Quetta. No. BP/12/209,8-3._ Dated Quetta, the 13th May, 1940. Copy to:- The Secretary, External Affairs Department, Simla. The Secretary to the Agent to the iGovernor-General in Baluchistan, Ziarat. The G.O.C., Western (Ind.) District, Quetta. The Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters (India), Simla. The Political Agent, Quetta. The Senior Superintendent of Police in Baluchistan, Quet4a. Sd/- C. Joyie, Senior Assistant Director, 7 JU- 2 - v O- Name; Bekerman. Father: Folish. mother: Jewish. Age: 21 years. 1940 j In 1936 father and mother separated. I was then living with my mother, whose home address was Yagelonska Street, Warsaw. In 1936 my mother left Warsaw ior Lodz and lived at Nova-Zafevska, No.9, appartment ID. By profession I am a lathe operator. I joined the Polish army as I had nothing to eat. I was employed as a cleaner on a motor car. After the German attack at Boyden I and 16 others escaped from the iront. All ol us succeeded in reaching Keltz. From there I ana two of my friends walked across the Iron tier ana reached Vladimir Volinsk where I changed my military uniform lor the suit I am wearing. I was then ordered by the Russians to proceed to Don Bazen and worK in the coal mines. I worked in the mines for about two months. Tne conditions were terriole and it appeared to me that the only chance of surviving would oe to get ba.ck to my own country. I accordingly escaped and arrived at Lwow. Very soon information reached Lwow that all tnose who na been sent to the mines had escaped. Our documents were checked and when it was found that I was oi^e Ox those w had escaped from the mines I was arrested and sent uacK. I was told that I would have to work as a prisoner a or three years and after that, suoject to good oehaviour, I would be driven a Russian passport. I worked at tne mines for aoout another two months and during this time met Bogussewier. Owing to the appalling conaitions in the mines we decided to make an attempt to escape, .by selling my watch, two shirts and the boots oi my inena we realized 1,200 Rubles. We oought a map. i rie maps available were those used in schools. We cut out .i r . _ v x* xt— i v* nA o H ^aa+.rrkVPri t.nfl rest.I have a sister in Belgium. She is Mrs. H.Vogler, Vonderlleo, Bue d’ Abbe, No. 6, Brussels. I wish to be sent to France to fight with the Polish army. I would also be grateful if you would inform ray mother and sister that I am alive. Name: Bronistaw Bogussewier. Nationality: Polish. Father: Polish (deceased). 533 ^3 My am I was born in Lithuania home address is Kedainiai, and am Do tnovo a mechanic of internal combustion yearg-'Of age. By profession engines I joined the military school in Lithuania shortly before war broke out. Before the war I crossed the frontier from Lithuania into Poland with confidential information for the Polish Grovernment. I was ordered to return to Lithuania for more information and complied with the orders. I worked for the Polish Grovernment because I am a Pole and tne Litnuanians did not like the Polish residents living in their country. I was definitely employed oy the Polish Government for the collection of information. 7/ar broke out when I was in Vilna. I immediately joined the Polish army and worked as an instructor on motor vehicles. It is likely that my worK for the Polish Government came to the knowledge of the Lithuanian Government, as ray family, including my sister and mother, were arrested and badly treated. I fought with others against the Bolsheviks and was eventually made prisoner near Vilna. I was a prisoner of war for about two weeks before escaping and proceeding towards Warsaw where I heard fighting was going on. I^could not reach Warsaw, but got as far as Breslitvosk where I was again arrested, tnis time by the Bolsheviks, and sent to the coal mines at Don Bazen. Conditions of work there were terrible. We were made to work like slaves. Our pay was negligible and food was very expensive. The amount we received daily was not enough for food. Our camp was surrounded by baroed wire and it was difficult to escape. I made suggestions to several Poles, but everyone hoped to be released. I eventually met Bekerman and one night we jumped over the barbed wire and reached Voroshilov Grad. The remainder of my statement is the same as that of Bekerman. I wish to oe sent to France to join the Polish army. Name: Adam BacKer. Father’s name: Yooan. Nationality: Polish. Age; 26 years. Home address: Zakopane. Profession: Civil marine. Education: Public School and Civil Marine School. Father’s profession: A junior police officer. Languages best known: Polish, German, Russian and a i-'little English. I left Poland on the 1st October. I ran away from the German concentration camp, eight miles from Gostynin, where I was a prisoner for tnree days. 7/hen I escaped from the concentration camp I was in possession of Polishmoney to the value of one English pound. I proceeded from the concentration camp to ZaKopane where I saw my father and mother and obtained £ 2, from them. I then went to Grakow, returned to Zakopane, then proceeded to Lwow, thence to Tarnojol and on to Zoaraz. At Zoaraz I met a friend of my father, who was worKing as a sweeper on the streets. I then went oack to Tarnopol and from there to Proscourov where I worked for a month as a fireman in a sugar factory. While at Proscourov I changed my polish passport for a Russian one which was valid for three months. I then went to Odessa where I worked on the steamer 'Grrussia' for three months. The steamer plied between Odessa and Batum. After full consideration of all the conditions I came to the conclusion that it was impossibl to escape to Rumania from Odessa and we decided to try to get to Japan. When I say we, In mean myself and Olgierd Stolvhwo. Both of us escaped from Poland together. We came to the conclusion that it would be better to try to get to Japan. We could not, however, proceed beyond Krasnovodsk. There I was offered wages of 4 Ruoles per day in a paper mill. The cost of one plate of soup alone was 4 Ruoles. The price of bread was beyond our means. Polish refugees who arrived there early were also working in the paper mill. From Krasnovodsk, after considerable journey, we reached the Persian frontier beyond Charjoi and Merv. We ootained railway tickets from Krasnovodsk with the help of a Russian woman who travelled with us from Odessa. The whole journey from Odessa, via Kiev, Moscow, Krasnovodsk, and the walk from Tejend to the Persian frontier took about three weeks. The first post we reached in Persia was Karachikan, where we were arrested and taken to Sarakhs from where we were orought to Meshed by car. In Meshed we demanded to see the Bn tish-consul and asked if there was a Polish representative in Persia. The only people we saw, however, were the Persian police. After twelve'days in Meshed we were taken oy motor car to Birjand. From Birjand we were taken towards tne Indian frontier and between Birjand and the Indian frontier, at a place, the name of which I do not remember, we met three other young men who were not very willing to talk with us openly, or to tell us who they were or from where they came. My object in leaving Poland was to enter the French or British Empire and eventually join up with Polish forces to fight against the Germans. In Zahidan, we were told that we would be directed towards the Indian frontier. I have known Olgierd Stolyhwo, Pole, since 1934. Except while in Odessa, wnere we worked on different steamers, we have always been together since our escape. We both planned our escape together and left Odessa at the same time with a woman friend. Name: Olgierd_Stolyhwo. Nationality: Polisn. Age: 24 years. Home address: Krow Gfrodzka Burgstrasse o3. Ran away from school and joined tne merchant service. Served on s.s. nellioin of Cardiff. I joined the ship at Marseilles and was discharged from the same port. I joined the army on 1.6.39. ana remained in tne army until 18.10.39 when I was taken prisoner by the Germans. I was a prisoner for three days and after that succeeded in escaping to Russia My father, Kazimir Stolyhwo, who was a professor ofAnthropology in the University of Crakow, had received the Legion of Honour ana is knowi to Admiral Qoodener(?) of the British Navy. I wish to rejoin the Polish army. The rest of his statement given by Adam Backer. Name: Bazileffsk. Father: Polish by adoption. Mother; Ukrainian. Home address: Village AngonouKa is exactly the same as that r y * y near KiWt 5383 940 My home was destroyed in 1930 as a result of a change in the Soviet policy regarding peasants. No one was allowed to retain possession of his own fielas and all haa to work in collective farms. My father and mother are dead and my only brother was deported from our home to Siberia - town KsnayGrsk - following a revolt against the Bolsheviks in 1930 in which I took part. I am a religious man and as it was impossible for me to attend church and all moral life had been destroyed by the Bolsheviks I hated them. Even before this, viz. in' 1929 I ran away to Poland and after staying there for some time was sent back as I could not produce any documents. In 1934 I made another attempt to reach Poland but was arrested on the frontier, sent oack and put in prison. I was released in 1936. On release from prison I obtained service in one of the 'colhos* 1 ^in order to keep myself alive. I was given 0 Ruules per day, but the cost of satisfactory food was not less than 10 Rubles. On the 14th May, 1938, the Bolsheviks checked all documents and discovered that I was attempting to escape to Poland. I was again arrested. They refused to allpw me tp return to my home country and sent me to Samarkand, in Turkistan. Tne procedure of checking docurnentsts done periodically and is called 'cleaning”. In Samarkand i was allowed to work as a watchman on a piggery and I stayed there till March, 1940. On the advice of a Russian gentleman who was deported from Persia by the Iranian G-overnment I made up my mind to escape to Persia. I had heard that the Iranian Government did not 1 ike Russians in their country and deported Soviet subjects whenever they could find them. I was sufiering a great deal from the tyranny of the Bolshevik Government and could not remain in the country any longer. I left Samarkand on foot with 120 Rubles in my possession. This sum I spent on food in a very short time. I then took to begging and fortunately the Turkomans I met were very kind and helped me with food and lodging. In Chaikhana I studied maps to guide me on my way to Persia. I do not remember the place in Russia from which I crossed into Iran. On the Persian frontier I met a Bulgarian who had run away from Russia and two others of the party now in Quetta, namely Bronistaw Bogussewier and Yosef Bekerman. The Bulgarian, I believe, was sent to Afghanistan. As I was in possession of a Russian passport it was with consideraole difficulty that I persuaded the Persian officials not to send me oack to Russia. I told them I was prepared to stay in Persia out they sent me with the other two to India. I first met my two companions mentioned above a£ Lutfacad. I crossed the frontier into Persia alone at night. I heard noises of horses cantering. I hid myself until they passed. My shoes were worn out oy the time I reached the Persian frontier and I finished ray journey bare-footed. The officer commanding the Persian post gave me the shoes I am wearing and a little money.2077 Telegram R No. 98 dated 29th(recd 30th)Mpy 1940. From Minister, Tehran. To Governor G-enerpl(E.-A•Deportment) Simla. EXPRESS Your telegram No. 60. Iranian Government state that these people were not deported or even pressed to leave. I am asking them not to grant exit visa by any route leading to British territory to any person not already holding British visa for that territory and am reserving right of Government of India to return men to Iran,(Copy) From The Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, Government of India, Qu e t ta. To The (Government of India, Simla. Iil emo r an dum No. fig/1 2/ 17/g284. Dated Quetta, the 24th May, 1940. Please refer to this office Memorandum No. BP/12/17/2097, dated the 13th May, 1940, forwarding copies of preliminary statements of the four Poles and one Russian. An examination of tne documents in their possession has been carried out and such information as can be obtained from them confirms the statements made oy the men. Lists of such property are attached. The Statements now made clear up discrepancies mentioned in the above quoted Memorandum. Although fully questioned the Poles were unable to give any opinion of conditions in either Soviet Turkistan or in Iran'. In the former country their whole efforts were directed at avoiding detection and in Iran they were in The four Poles reiterate their desire to be sent to join the Polish army in France. The Russian, Bazileffsk, is of peasant origin and of limited intelligence. In his former statement he said that he had studied a map, of the route to Iran, in Chaikhana. He was referring to a tea-shop in Samarkand, not to a place. According to his statement, he and his family have suffered much at the hands of Bolsheviks and his description of conditions in Russia is influenced by tnis. He considers a rising on a large scale unlikely as Soviet agents are everywhere and everyone is suspect. He appears, however, to have little knowledge of places or events outside the towns or villages he has lived in. He requests that he may be permitted to remain in India to earn his living. No. 3P/12/17/2285-90, Dated Quetta, the 24th May, 1940. Copy to;- 1. The Secretary, External Affairs Department, Simla. 2. The Secretary to the Agent to the (Sovernor-Jeneral in Baluchistan, Ziarat. 3. The (S.O.C., Western (Ind.() District, Quetta. 4 . The Chief oi the General Staff, Army Headquarters, India,Siml the police. 3d/- T.f. Boyce. Major, Intelligence for Senior Assistant Director, ligence, government of India, Quetta.b. The Political Agent, Quetta. 6. The Senior Supenntendent of police in Baluchistan, Quetta. The documents belonging to these foreigners are enclosed herewith. Sd/- T. W. Boyce. llajor, for Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, government of India, Quetta. Name: Olgierd Stolyhwo. Nationality; Polish. Born in Warsaw. Age: 24 years. Father's name. Kazimir Stolyhwo. Father's address. Krow Orodzka, Burgstrassee (This'corresponds with^addr Card sent by his motner). Education. Attended many schools but either ran away or was dismissed from most. 'Mb permitted to take examination at Technical School at Cracow when aged 19. Languages. Polish, German, Russian and a little English. Is in possession of certificates of discharge from 3.S. Kellwyn, Cardiff. 1 &gt; L. 5383 1940 I ■. . i. r* ess on Post In my original statement I said that I had joined the army on the 1st June, 1939. Before this, in Septemoer,1938, I had been permitted to join the Officers’ Artillery Schoo^l at Zambruf as a Cadet. I remained there until June,1939, when I wasappointed under suo.Lieut. (N. Pod Horunjie) in the 16tri Division. After being captured I met Adam Backer, whom I had known for some years, and we maae our escape together. I met a lady named Tatiana Chinova in Odessa and she agreed to accompany me. We travelled by train to Moscow where we remained on the station for oHe night. Our passports were checked but we were not questioned. We then left for Krasnoyarsk, in Southern Siberia. At this place I saw a few soldiers but do not know tne strength of the garrison there. From Krasnoyarsk we went to Tashkent, via Almata, and after a brief stay travelled oy train to Charjui, where we stayed for two days, thence to poltorask ( AsKhabad) and back to Te j end. The following are the only troops were seen:- Krasnoyarsk. Infantry. Almata. Artillery. Tashkent. Infantry. Poltorask(Askhaoad) Infantry. places in Russia at which strength unknown. -do- -do- -do - At Tashkent I saw some aeroplanes flying and at Charjui there were a few airmen but no aircraft were no tic ed. The organization on Russian railways is very bad and trains run at anything from 5 to 8 hours late. The rolling- stock is poor but the permanent way appears to be well maintained. The speed of the passenger train I travelled in was about 40 Kilometres per hour.Between Moscow and Krasnoyarsk I got into conversation with an individual who claimed to be a chemist. He told me that he had been present at a demonstration where gas was sprayed from a tank. When this gas rose into trees the leaves withered and dropped off inside a period of about half an hour. He also said that he nad oeen present when a bridging display was given by tanks. The first vehicle laid a light pontoon ondge which was capable of taking a column of medium tanks. The bridge was than taken up by the rear tank. When we arrived in Meshed the woman, Tatiana Chinova, was separated from us and I did not see her again. I heard that she was living with an Iranian official. Name. Adam Backer. Father’s name. Yooaji. Nationality. Polish. Age. 26 years. Place of birth. Kalwaya, Zabsidowlka. Home address. Zakopane. Placeleducated. ZaRopane. My papers were taken from me in the prison hospital, Meshed. I would be grateful if they could be obtained for me as they contain articles of sentimental value. They are (1) Polisn Permit (2) Russian Employment Register (3) Three photographs (one family group). When Germany invaded Poland I was in the reserve and was at sea. I was calledAip a few days after the war started and joined the o9zh Regiment. I was captured at How. The lady Tatiana Chinova came aboard my ship, the •Grussia', in Odessa looKing for Stolyhwo. Wa laler met and decided to go to Japan. We spent one night in Moscow and then left for Krasnoyarsk. I noticed no troops on my journey through Russia andonly saw aeroplanes flying in Siberia. In either Tashkent or Askhabad ( I do not remember which) I met a Pole who has lived there for some years. He is employed as a cook on 40 Roubles ber mensem, which he described as insufficient to keep boay and soul together. He said that it was useless to attempt to escape as many had done so and had been re-captured. At one point, probaoly Charjui, I met a Russian engineer who was so poorly paid that, he stated, he could not afford shoes. He told me that the inhabitants of Turkistan were better treated than the Russians themselves. Apart from this I am unable to give any opinion of Condi; tions in Soviet Turkistan or in Iran. The Iranian officials gave us a good reception but guarded us very closely until we left their custody. Polish railways are much superior to those in Russia where organization is bad and roiling stock and the permanent way are poor. In Odessa, the inhabitants are treated like slaves un less they belong to the local Soviets. Non-members are compelled to pay four and five times higher prices than members.( -4- iL . 5383 1940 ) Name. Bronistaw Bogusaewier. Father^ name. Nicolai. Nationality. Polish. Ape. 22 years. Place of Birth. Lithuania - Place not known. Present Home Address. Kedainiai, Dotnovo. Education. At a Primary School, Kadau, and a Technical School, Kovno. Aece when completed? 19 years. Education. On the outereak of war I joined the 2nd Polish Regiment of Technicians. Our lourney from Krasnovodsk to Stalinabad was done by rail but I do not know the names of stations through which we passed. We did not leave the train at any point, to avoid questioning, and left Stalinabad for Poltorask (Askhaoad; on the day we arrived. We changed at a station called Kagan. I saw no troops or aircraft at any place. The organization of the railway between Krasnovodsk and Stalinabad is poor and the train was running between 6- 8 hours late. I did not notice the rolling stock but the permanent way appeared to be bad in comparison with polish railways. During the period of our travels I talked with very few people and am unable to say what conditions are. I do know that labourers in the coal mines where I worked are bitterly anti-Soviet but are kept under through fear. (His account of their Adventures in Iran agrees with that of Bekerman). Name. Josef Bekerman. Father 1 s name. Bronig. Nationality. Pole. I Mother Jew). Place of birth. Don Brovitsa, 70 Kilometre from Ifeirsaw. Present address. No. 9, Nova Zafevska, Lodz. Education. General, Warsaw. Languages. Polish and German. I joined the 28th Regiment as a volunteer in August, 1939. Wnen the Germans attacked at Katowitz a number of us deserted in cars and esesped to Russia. We heard that the Germans were advancing everywhere and that the Polish army was in full retreat. 7,hen in Voroshilorgrad I heard that troops were being sent to the Caucasus and7 when near Baku, I saw a troop train proceeding towards the latter plade. Another train was also seen conveying tanks to Baku. I also saw troops at Askhaoad ana Ka^ran, out I could not say how many there were. We stayed in Stalinaoad about 11 hours and then left for Askhabad. We were not questioned on our journey and we did not leave the train at stations. The Russian railways are badly organized and do not compare with those in Poland. Our train was usually about 5-8 hours late. The rolling stock and the permanent way are poor.In the Don Basin, conditions are appalling. The police are corrupt and one can obtain concessions by bribery. I saw little of conditions ih Soviet Turkistan as we kept to the train, out I noticed children’s shoes for sale on some railway stations. I bought a pair of shoes for 247 Roubles. In Iran, I got the impression that the officials were afraid of the Russians. In Meshed we were confined in jail and were taken from there to Zahidan in a crowded public bus. We stayed five days in Zahidan and were then taken to Zabulistan where we were detained for ei-zht days. Here we were told that we would be despatched lo Tehran but were taken back to Zahidan. Before arriving at the latter place we stopped at a tea-house where we were informed two Poles would join us. The five of us were then despatcned up to a railway line in the lorry and then guided across the frontier as already stated. We were warned that if we saw British troops to lie down. Name. Bazileffsk. Father’s Name. Josef Bazileffsk. Nationality. Father Polish. Mother Ukrainian. Place of birth. 0 Village Angonouka, Present Home address. ) ne^ar Kiev. Any Education. At the Village School. Languages. Russian and a little Polish. My mother died of starvation in 1932 and my brother is still in Siberia. Although poorly armed, in 1930, we decided to make an attempt to overthrow the Bolsheviks and we failed. I believe there are still a few arms i n possession of Ukrainians but they are kej&gt;t concealed as strict searches were carried out after the 1930 revolt and many were seized. While in Samarkand, at first I had to report to the police weekly, then fortnightly and finally every month. Because I was (and am) religious I suffered more at the hanas of officians than aid others. I think that the Soviet Government were aware that I had tried to enter a monastery in Poland. It is difficult to form any opinion of internal condi tions in Soviet Turkistan as peopleware afraid to express their thoughts. From conversations I had, however, I gathered that all the tribes hate the Bolsheviks but£re unable to do anything. Russian troops occupy all cAtres of importance and secret agents are everywhere to ensure that the inhabitants are kept in subjection. I do not know if the tribes have any arms. Food is very scarce and this and commodities are very expensive. We had to form queues for everywthing we required. Officials and soldiers receive preferential treatment. When I left Samarkand for Iran I walked except for two nights when I stole a ride on a goods train. The only places I remember having passed through are Bokhara and atom at a river where I crossed by a wooden oridge. I do not know the name of this town. The troops in Samarkand are Russian but I do not 21 know their strength. There are Koreans living i n Samarkand and local opinion was that they were probably Japanese spies removed from the Far iast. * About November, troops from Samarkand were sent away it was said, to Finland. They were not, to my knowledge, replaced. I saw no other troop movements during the past few months. On the way to Iran I avoided all towns as far as was po ssi ol e. There are a few aeroplanes in Samarkand but I do not know how many. I know nothing of conditions in Iran as I was kept in close custody there. I have some knowledge of leather work and I would like to be employed in a factory in India if possible. I do not want to travel any more. I can also work as tractor. Description of property taken from i^J£E-M£jSaMAiUEole. Focket Wallet containing Russian money to the value of, in Russian, one 1 Rouble note, two 3 Rouble notes, twelve 30 Rouble notes, and one 50 Rouble note. Total in notes 417 Roubles. In coin, one 20 Kopesas, one 15 Kopekas, one 3 Kopekas (Russian), and 5 small Iranian coins. ( one coin of 5 dinars, three coins of 10 dinars ana one coin of 50 dinars (half-rial). One piece of paper and one card with Polish writing. One used Iranian postage stamp of 5 dinars. 18 snapshot photos, ( one of these photos is a photo of Bronislaw Bogussewier), and one certificate (? ?) jjegcription of property taken from BBOlilSLAI-SQSIISiiilUB &gt; (Po 1 e). PocKet Tfcllet containing an identity certificate (?? 3 postcard photographs, 7 snapshot photos (one of the photos *s a photo of Bekerman), one used Iranian postage stamp of 10 dinars, one piece of paper.-7- 5383 Deacr ift tion of property ta ke n fr &lt;;m pocket llallet, containing, 4 notes, poliLu, f ) 2 units (?) each, 2 Russian Lottery notes* which are^a Grovernraent loan worth 25 Roubles each in 20 years time. One Russian work certificate. One note-book containing Polish and Persian writing. A Certificate Card (?) Two seaman's discharge certificates, in English. 6 pieces of paper with Polish'writing. One paper with Russian verses. One postcard in Russian. One handwritten certificate in Norwegian. 4 snapshot pictures, one piece blanK photo paper (?) Two olack silIhouettes. Ileacr ipt i on_ o f prope r tv taken fr om BA2ILi£EaK&gt;iEQLI5ILbiL-ado £ti onl. One Russian work certificate and one Russian passport. ADA M 3ACjtlb R*a pole, had no papers in his possession. He states that his papers were teken from him by the Iranian police in Meshed ana, as he thought he would be able to obtain them when he saw a a British Consul* he did not worry further. He now requests that the Iranian authorities may be asked for the papers as they contain articles of sentimental value.(S) From The Senior Assietar Intelligence, G-o 1 * - * • Quetta. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the agen the Ooverno r-G-eneral in Baluchi a ta; Ziarat. No. BE/IZZS^B^ Bat Ad Quetta, the 29th May,1940. Subject. Folign ana Buasia_n .Beiu ge eg. Memo random Please refer to this office No.BP/12/17/ 2284, dated the 24th May, 1940, on the aoove subject. Josef Bekerman has asked to be separated from the other Poles and the Russians as, he alleges, they have abused and assaulted him on account of his beinga Jew. has written a letter, in Hebraic, to the Jewish Relief Association, Bombay, asking for assistance. He apparently ootained the address of this body from Dr. Hoff, the Hungarian dentist in Quetta. 3d/- T.W. Boyce. Major, for Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, (Government of India, Quetta. Go py to t - 1. The Director, Intelligence Bureau, Home Department, (Government of India, Simla. 2. The Secretary, External Affairs Deptt.,Simla. 3. The (G. 0. G., Western (Ind) District, Quetta. 4. The Chief of the General Staff, Army Head quarters, India, Simla. 5. The Political Agent, Quetta-Pishin, Quetta. 6. The Senior Superintendent of Police in This individual also states that he No. BE/17/2383- .Dated Quetta,'Karwa Castle 11 , 77, Walkeshwar Road, Bombay the 11th June 1940. No. 422 z aZl/27 The Secretary in to V ^ • I __ the Gpjemment of India the Ext erngl^A^^r s| Department, Sir, 1940 J A month ago thhpfi Quetta four ‘Polish citizens as war refugees after escaping from G-erman and Russian camps for prisoners of war. I very much regret to note that the authorities in Quetta who kept them under Sur veillance did not inform them that there is the Polish Consulate G-eneral in India at Bomuay which carries on normal consular work and with which they might establish contact. They came to know of the existance of this Consulate General from an English lady in Quetta who in her letter to this Consulate” Ceneral states:- M They had not been informed of your existence here in Bombay oy the Intelligence. ” As it appears that the authorities in different places in India do not seem to be aware that there is a Polish Consulate jeneral of Poland in India at Bombay, I have tne honour to request you to issue a proper notification to all the provincial authorities in this country and especially to those in various frontier towns and outposts giving full details as under :- ^Con sulat e Ceneral o f t he R epublic of Po lan d m InJia.~ Consur’Seneral: Dr. Eugene Banasinski, Address: M Karwa Road, Tel. Add: POL Castle ^,77, BOMBAY. CONSUL, Ph.D. Jalkeshwar BOMBAY.(Copy) From To The Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, iiovernment of Indta, Quet ta. The Director, Intelligence Bureau, (Home Depar Grovernment Of India, Simla. Lmen't9p' i'ernorandom No. BP/12/17/26o7. Dated Quetta, the 13th June, 1940. Please refer to tnis office Memorandum No. BP/12/ 17/2264, dated the 24tn May, 1940, forwarding statements of the four Poles and one Russian who were arrested at Juzzak on the 6th May, 1940. Tatiana Ghinnova, who claims to be the lady mentioned by Olgierd Stolyhwo in his statement, arrived at Kila Sufaid from Mirjawa on the 3rd June, 1940, and asked if it was a Turosh post. She was informed tfcat it was a British post and, on the following day, she returned to Mirjawa. Iranian officials, however, sent her back to Kila Sufaid. She was then sent to Quetta where she arrived on the 9th June. Her passport, she states, was taKen from her in Meshed and was not returned. She has no money and her few documents contain nothing of importance. On the day of her arrival in Quetta she visited the Iranian Consul who ^ave her a small sum of money. Her statement is attached for information. Tnis was recorded during an interrogation conducted by Mr. Dorofeeff. While this was going on she kept referr ing to a paper and, when asked the reason for this, she stated that her memory was bad and that she had only noted down some dates and names of places. She said that her failure to remember these details had caused her much troublein Meshed. Mr. Dorofeeff checked tne paper and i s o f opinion that she was speaking the truth. Mrs. Thomas/the manageress of the Dak Bungalow where Tatiana and the Poles are staying, states that on arrival ihe girl appeared surprised and pleased to find Stolyhwo and BacKer there, and that she mentioned their names at aiae. She requests to be sent back to Iran or, if this is not permitted, to be allowed to go to Australia to look for an uncle who, she states, is living there,* Restatement contains full details. Name. Tatiana Ghinnova. Nationality. Russian. Age. 28 years. Place of Birth. Moscow. Fathers name. Ivan. Mother's name. Anastasia. Mother's address. Appartment lb, No. 5/lo St Corny, Trehproudni, Pereulok, Mosco w. Where educated. Kazan and Moscow. Languages. Russian, local Kazan dialect and a little Persian learned in Meshed. When I was about two years of age my parents separated and I was taken by my maternal grandmother to live inR Kazan. She told me that my grandfather was a Muslim, that he insisted on my being brought up in that faith and that my Muslim name was Mariam. I have not seen or heard of my father for about 9 years. In 1928, I returned to my mother in Moscow and attended schools of physical culture and type-wri ting. When I was about 17 or 18 I married a Georgian named Ghetashevili. In aoout 1982, we were Doth arrested for his collecting money under false pretences. My husoand was sent to a House of Correction and I was ordered to leave Moscow. I did not do so and was again arrested ana sent to a Camp of Correction near Haoarvosk, and from there to a similar camp in Gulubechnia in Taigi , in Siberia. At this place I worked in the camp oifice as a typist and was also made to dance for the other detenus. I received 40 roubles a month. this time I married an Armenian actor named an infant Doy was Dorn. In march, 1936, we and I returned to Kazan with my husband husband got employment on the stage and I my child. We remained here for ll^months £ During Samveloff anct were released and baby. My looked after and then went 'to Baicu where we stayed until aoout June, 1938. In this place I worKed as a typist but ray husoand was only able to obtain casual temporariy employiient. The child died in this year and we' then went to Kriv^n in Armenia. After about two months in this place I separated from my husband. I remained there until June 1939, and then went to Batum. I could get no employment in the town but eventually obtained a post as childrens’ stewardess on a steamer, the ’’Armania” ? plying between Batum and Odessa. I worked on this ship, ana sometimes on the *Crruzzia w , until March, 1940. During this time - about October or November, 1939 - I met two polish officers, One of them, Stolyhwo, was working on the ”Armania H and the other, Adam Backer, was cn the 'Gruzzia'. Stolyhwo told me on several occasions that he and Backer wished to go out Kast where he had heard tnere were better opportunities for employment. I decided to accompany them. I obtained tneir railway tickets for them and we eventually left Odessa for Moscow. On arrival there I called on my mother and found she hadicmKr married again and was called Idorova. Her second husband, a well-known actor, had died recently and she was in receipt of a pension. We ki left Moscow for Krasnoyarsk and, on arrival there, my friends found that there was no suitable employment available. They then decided to make for Askhabad and cross into Iran. Again I purchased the tickets and we set out for the latter place. I do not remember all the places we passed through but we had long halts at Almata, Tashkent, Chariui and Askhabad. We crossed the frontier into Iran ana were taken to Sarakhs. At this place we remained for about ten days and I fell in love with a young Iranian officer named Asmatullah. I lived with this individual until the day we were removed to Meshed. In the latter town I was separated from the others and was confined in a female prison. I did not see the Poles again until my arrival here in Quetta. In Meshed, a Georgian woman was in custody but I was not allowed to converse with her. My passport was taken from me and has not been returned. I was in this prison for about a m onth and was then taken ink bus, with an escort of two men, to Zahidan, passing about tnreedaysori the way. I was kept in Zahidan for four days and was permitted to sleep in the prison garden. I was told that I would be putiaiacross the frontier into Turkey and was advised to tell Turkish officials that I had travelled alone and h ad n ot been in the hands of the Iranian Government. I left a letter,addressed to my Iranian friend in Sarakhs, with one of the prison staff who promised to despatch it by post. I pretended to the Iranians that I had left some iewelry in Sarakhs and wished to return there for it but they said that I must go to Turkey. On being put across the frontier I found that I was on British territory and was refused admission. I did not want to come to India and my one desire was to return to Saraiths. However, the Iranians sent me back across the frontier. At the frontier, and In Kundi, (Nok Kundi) I found it very difficult to understand what was said to me and I could not explain what I wanted. The only Europeans I saw in Iran were two men, in green unifonns, travelling in the bus from Meshed to Zahidan. Themen were eating food with Iranian families and one of the guards tolcpi e they were English. One was blond and tHe other dark. I do not wish to return to Russia. In the. various places I have lived there food ana clothing arefcScarce and prices are very high. One can never get sufficient ma money to live on. When in employment and i n receipt of pa pay a large portion of it must be paid back to the Soviet, m the form of subscriptions. One of my uncles in Kas&amp;n, a lawyer, was shot for suspected activities against the Bolosnevika and other relations nave been arrested without cause. If I returned to Russia I, too, would certainly be arrested andrry relatives would also suffer on my ac co unt. I wish to return to Tran where I can join my friend in A Sarakhs. He askedfiWto return to him and we have arranged to sret marriea. If this is not permitted then I would like to go to Australia. My relations often spoke of wy uncle who has lived in that country for some 2o-30 years. I do not know his address out his name is Pavil Ivanovitch and he is a composer. 1 2 3 4 1. A Lux advertisement on the back of which a series of dots and dashes are written. She states that it is a Russian game of seeing what the future holds and that she wrote it in iail in Meshed tosee^if she would escape from her troubles. 2. A poem, in Russian, written on similar paper for her Iranian lovcer, Asmatullah. 3. Part of an envelope wnich haa contained outtons sent by a friend from Hrivan to Batum. 4. A letter, written in Nok Kundi, addressed to Asma tullah, officer of Sarakhs post. A translation of this r Qac t3 ^'Greetings from England. I thank you for your atten tion and long to return to you, and I am^ trying to do this. I have done many silly things which micx may be harmful to me. I beg of you to. make arrangements for me to live in Iran or if you can come here I would be Lappy. Relieve me, these lines are written from a pure heart which I left in Sarakhs during my stay with you. I could not say this at parting as the Poles were present and I was taken to Meshed the same day. I still hoped to see you in meshed and I want to see you now. M(Gopy) From The Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, Government of Iidia Qu e t ta. a, To The Director, Intelligence Bureau, (Home Department) Government of India, Simla. Memorandum No. BP/12/17/2694. Dated Quetta, the loth June, 1940. Please refer to this office No. BP/12/17/2284, dated the 24th May, 1940, regarding the four poles now in Quetta. It has just been discovered that the polish Consul General, Bombay, has been in Correspondence with Mrs. /ernon Smith, wife of Major V.T. Smith, 3rd Bn. 7th Rajput Regiment, regarding these Poles. In his last 1 etter the Consul General stated that he had remitted Rs. 200/- to Mrs. Vernon Smith for their expenses to Bombay, and also that he had approached the Bombay Government on the subject. Mrs. Vernon Smith, who is an American by oirth, was employed by the American International Red Cross as a transport driver in Poland from the outbreak of war until'the 29th March, 1940. She claims to have a good understanding of polish. Recently, she adds, she re ceived letters from Poland and, as she was unable to translate certain portions, she enquired about assis tance and discovered that these poles were living in the Dax Bungalow! n Quetta. She visited them ana, on hearing their account of their experiences, referred the matter to the Polish Consul General. Mrs. Vernon Smith has given the following^informa tion about her conversations with the Poles and, as this conflicts in some ways with their former statements, or was not mentioned by them, and also with the statement of Tatiana Chinnova, it is given belov/:- been attached to the diplomatic service and had served in the Embassies in Pans and in Berlin. He failed to qualify in the final examination. He also stated that he bad been a cadet in the Polish navy. AD AM BA-uH^d * Mrs. Vernon Smith states that, when m ZaKopane, Poland, in October, 1939, she -rememoers seeing the papers of one Jan Backer of Za&amp;opane but did not hear of Adam Backer. In his statement BacKer mentioned that ne 1 eft Poland on the 1st October, 1939, travelled for what would probably total about 15 days, worked in Tarnopol for a month (up to the loth November, 1939), and was on the 'Gruzzia* for three months. This would oring the date to approximately the loth February, 1940. According to Mrs. Vernon Smith the 'Gruzzia' was in Chatham in January, 1940, as an armed merchant cruiser. In a general conversation in Polish wjrs. Vernon Smith states tnat she heard tnis individual say H I am as much a Pole as any of you'. Vernon Smith that he hadJ U biLr . . iilrsTyernon Smith states that this indivi dual at first told her that he only Knew a few words of G-erman but that later she heard him speak a sentence fluently in this language. She aads that his Polish is oad and that he might well be a G-erman Jew. TATIi^ AGHim iA- • ' t , This individual stated that she served on the H Armania* and the ’♦Grruzzia” up to March,1940. According to Mrs. Vernon Smith the latter vessel was in Chatham in January, 1940. GaLaBAL* In a conversation in Polish Mrs. Vernon Smith states that she heard pne of the Poles say ’•Whatever happens we must stick to the same stor} 2. On the wnole Mrs. Vernon Smith appeared to harbour some suspicion about the party, parti cularly about Bekerman. Sne suggested, and this is passecubn without comment, that the Poles, including the Jew, Bekerman, should be sent to the Polish Consul General who would be able to test their credentials. Mrs. Vernon Smith mentioned that she would ask the Polish Consul General by telegram to approach the Government of India on the subject. Sd/- T.W. Boyce, Major, for Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, Government of India, Quetta.22. No. (Copy) ( 24 . 'Karwa Castle', 77, Walkeshw r iload, Bombay the loth June 1940. 549 / 1 /Iq. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaris Department, jlOrLik*- Sir, In the beginning of the last month there came to Quetta four Polish citizens - prisoners o f war who had succeeding in escaping from German and Russian prison camps. A week ago, I received letters from them stating their status, their present position, etc and requesting this Consulate General to give them a chance ''to proceed to France to join the Polish Army. This Consulate General, therefore, forwarded to them the money for the railway fare to enable them^ to come to Bombay with the intention of arranging their passage with the assistance of the Army Transport authorities in Bomoay. To-day, I received information from Quetta that the authorities there will allow them to proceed to Bomoay only upon receipt of instructions from the Government of India permitting them to ao so. In view of this, I have the honour to request you 1 . to issue instructions to the authorities in Quetta to permit the Polish citizens mentioned above to proceed to Bomoay in order to place themselves at the disposal of this Consulate General. 2 . that on account of thepurtailed budget of this Consulate General owing to the war situation which makes it impossiole to pay for their passage to France, to instruct the Army Transport authorities in Bomoay to give them the chance to proceedto France by the first available troopship. I do hope that tne Government of India in this critical times, when the services of every available soldier should be taken advantage of, will do their best to enable these polish citizens to fight for the Allied cause. They are trained soldiers with experiencebf the present war. Out of these four one was a'cadet in the Polish Naval School in Gdynia and another a professional seaman, before they were called to the colours on the outbreak of war m Poland in September last. I nave the honour to be, dir, Your most ooedient servant, Sd/- E. Banasinski, Consul General for Poland.• mmmmm &amp; 23 r -»■&gt; f ' 1 1 - ,'Li » 5383 1940 j E530o Telegram H *3 dated (and reed,) 19th June 1940&lt;&gt; Promo * o ^ .Intel.ligence Quetta. To.,....«Foreign, Simla® ESPHIfiS, Reference my Mo-,B 0 Fo/l2/l7/2694^700 of June 15th 3 Mrs, Vernon Smith state's^ that ; 3 aker.man has admitted to her that he is a German Jew a &gt; escaped from Germany to Poland and ran away to Russia during invasion of Poland® PI ease repeat to Into.lligence Bureau and C*GeSe Sirmla^ Copies by post to Baluchistan Ylest District; Political and Police Quetta* (M c FeSr D^S-P. A.DeS* U,S,P. Home Department D.I.B^ &amp; G^SiBr- ) GLR,2 i+ £543. Telegram R No. 46~S dated 19th (reed. £Oth) June 1940. From.••,.Baluchistanj Ziarat. To.......Noreign, Simla# Reference my telegram No. 40-S of 10th June and previous correspondence. There is now good reason to suspect that Joseph Bekerman who claimed to be Polish Jew is in fact German Jew who did not serve in Polish army but escaped from Poland after Russian occupation. It is I think dangerous to allow him to remain at large in Quetta even under surveillance and I have arrested him under Rule No.129 1(a) Defence of India Rules and lodged him in Quetta jail pending further orders# ...........t) (No P.S. D.S.P. A.D.S. U.S.P. Home Department &amp; D.I«B.) GIR.L\ £ (Copy) w Karwa GastlLe Bom 5383 Da S(_ th / 2 tV yalkfshwacr Road Jji /0 1940. I\ o. Sir, 682/1/93. UHO^M T k G 0 NFID^ r TJAir The Secretary to the Grovernment Of India in the External Affairs Department, A . \ Following this Consulate G-eneral^ letter No. 349/7//15 dated the 15th June 1940, I give oelow the contentsof a Press Note which appeared in the Morning Standard, Bombay, dated the 22nd June 1940 POLISH bafuceb arrested Quetta, FnJay. Joseph Bakermann, polish refugee who had arrived some time as:o, has been arrested under section 129/l/A of tne Defence of India Rules. -A.P. In view of the fact that the escaped Polish prisoners of war, including Mr. Joseph Bakermann, referred to in my aoove mentioned letter, are already in communication with this Consulate G-eneral and as it appears to me that their arrival in India is not motivated by any ill intention towards this country or the Allies but only to find temporary refuge, I have the honour to request you to com unicate to me for what contravention of the Defence of India Rules 7 r. Bakermann has been arrested and to let me know his present whereabouts. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most ooedient servant, 3d/ — A. Banasinsici, Consul G-eneral for Poland.2904. Telegram R No..58~S dated ( and reed) 6 th July 1940. From. Baluchistan, Ziarat- Foreign, Simla. Reference your Express Letter D..3217-N/4Q. Poles are becoming increasing embarrassment and recently su?ged short hunger strike cas protest against being detained in idleness here when they wished to join Polish urmy. Polish Consul General Bombay has sent P* 200 through an American he re lady/with knowledge of Poland but in absence of Government of India's orders I am unable to allow them to leave. Grateful for very early decision. Even a move to Bombay would encourage them that they wore on their way. • *###•••••••••••• N,, P.S., D.S.F., A.D.3., U.S.F., G.S.Branch, Home Department and D.I.B.Copy of telegram dated 3i/ni'art h ^ 1 y, 1940, irom the Polish Goasul JGrene£al ^qmbay', to Secretary External Affairs Department, aovprn- merit of India, Simla. 1940 I Referring my letter 54dtn Jun-e to Political Department Bombay and 349/\VlD 15th Jane to you Please settle immediately release Polish escaped war prisoners at Quetta. If matter not settled before 12th July I shall intervene direct with His Excellency Governor- Gen eral.Copy of a 1etter No. ^ Simla the 9th July i960 £. A. Department, ■general for Poland attiom bay, 77, '^Ikeahwar Road, Bombay D^ 21 i.-N/AQ^ aXTT tne ^ I he s ul ^wa-aCas :1 e*, Subject: Arrest of Mr. Joseph With reference to your letter No. 682/ #/93, d/- the 24.6.40, I am directed to state that when Mr. Bekerman first arrived in Quetta he stated that he was a Polish citizen and that he had served in the Polish army in thew^r against G-ermany. Subsequently 5 © admitted that he was a (German Jew who had f 1 gq to Poland i rom Grer.jany whence he escaped to Russia and eventually made his way yja Iran to India in company with three Poles. In view of this and other suspicious circumstances the Baluchistan Administration arrested him under the Defence of India Rules and he is at present detained in the Quetta jail pending further investigation into his case. 2. You will be informed in due course of the decision reached.(Copy) I No. 78 (570/7/40) To the Secretary to the Government of India in the oixternal Affairs Department, With the compliments of His Majesty’s Representative. Note No. 277 dated 18th June 1940 to the Iranian Minister for Foreign Affairs. Reference (Govt, of India telegram No. 75 o f 8 th June 1940. BRITISH LEGATION, TEHRAN. 18th June 1940. 18th June 1940. No. 277 . Monsieur le Ministre, In my note No. 240 of May 29th last ( 8 th Khordad) I had the honour to request Your Excellency that instructions should be issued to the competent Iranian authorities not to grant an exit visa oy ai route leading to British territory to any person who does not already possess a valid Britisn visa authorizing him to go to that territory. 2. I now have the honour to inform Your excellency that on June 4th (14th Khordad) an Armenian^ woman named Tatiana entered British territory at Kila Sufaid from Iran, having travelled via Meshed and Mirjawa. Being unwilling to enter British territory she returned to Miriawa out was again evicted by the Iranian frontier authorities. 3. In view of the short time which elapsed between the date of my note of May 29th and that of the incident in question^ I do not wish to make a formal protest against this action of the Iranian authorities; but I must request His Excellency Monsieur Mozaffar A’lam, ‘.Minister for Foreign Affairs, TEHRAN. Your Excellency to cause the necessary instructions to be sent immediately to the frontier authorities in the sense of paragra h 1 of this note in order that there may be no repetition of such incidents. In this parti cular case the Government of India reserve the right to send the woman, Tatiana back to Iran. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew.to Your Excellency the assurance of ay highest consideration* ( Sgd) R. W. Bullard.(Copy) do From - The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident &amp; Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan To - The Secretary to the Government of External Affairs Department, Memorandum No: 41C-S/Z-o/40. Ziarat, dated the 29th June 1940. Arrest and detention of enemy fo Rule 129 of the Defence of India Reference my telegram No :46-S dated the 19th June_ 1940.* A copy of the Order of arrest and detention a. amst Josef Bekerman is enclosed together with an Order^unaer Rule 129(2) for his temporary custody for a period of two months. It is requested that the Csntral Government will intimate what further orders should be passed under Rule lt9'4) of the Defence of India Rules on expiry ot two months. The presence of such foreigners in Baluchistan is most undesirable and it is requested that orders may be passed as soon as possible for the removal of Josef Bekerman. 3 d/- H.A.F. Metcalfe, Agent to the Governor General in Baluchistan. ORD^R BY THA SANEJR SUPARINTANDANT CF PGLICA, BALUCHISTAN. — mm I* .1* Dated Quetta, the 19th June 194C No: 212 7/S.B . Having reasonable grounds to suspect tEaT JoserBekerman, a reputed German Jewish subject, has acted in a manner prejudicial to the public salety, I hereby direct that he snail be arrested forthwith m virtue of the powers conferred by Rule lB9(l)(a) oi the Defence of India Rules, 1939. . . x , „ . In accordance witn the provisions of n^le 129(2) of tne Defence of India Rules, 1939 read with Secretary to the Agent to the Governor General m Baluchistan’s Order No :A“4/39-Yifcr-10 27l-p dated the 26th October 1939, I direct that the said Josef Bekerman be committed to jail custody penaing the further orders of the provincial Government. g ^ . r o Hi 11 SAN I OR SUPERINTEND ANT 0-F POLICE, Balucnistan. 5, Luck Road, I nereoy certify that in conversation with me Josef Bekerman made the statement tnat he was German Jew from Germany who escaped into Poland prior to tne invasion. . , I have made this report because I nave seen him wandering about the Cantonment, displaying unnecessary amount oi curiosity. . w . . _ o True copy. Sd/- (Mrs) Marjorie Vernon Smith Sd: R. A. C. Hill. Senior Superintendent of Police, Baluchistan.-2 '• HON’BLS THE AND CHIEF C ADENT TO THE GOVERNOR G OMI SSI ONER IN BRITISH i^OAUilikSI I AIUC^ISTAN asniB. Ziarat, dated 5383 the.^ttfWunei' No; 409-3. In persuance of the power con ferred on him by suo-rule (2) of Rule 129 of the Defence of India Rules the Agent to the 'Jrovernor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in British Baluchistan is pleased to direct that Josef Bekerman, a reputed German Jewish subject, who was arrested by the Senior Superintendent of Police in Baluchistan on the 19th June 1940 in pursuance of sub-rule (1) of Rule 129 of the Defence of India Rules for having acted in a manner prejudicial to the public safety shall be committed uo custody for a period of two months from the date of his arrest. By Order 3d/- L.A.G. Pinhey, Secretary to the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan. Copy forwarded to the Senior Superintendent of police in Baluchistan for information.From - Foreign Simla. To - Polish Consul general, BombAy (Copy) ' '^ 2 ' Express Telegram dated the 11 th July T34T)'. m .5383 139-N/Camp Your telegram of hth (Jgi^ q escaped Polish Prisoners of Ifar Delay in reply***' much regretted 2 Government of India have some reason for suspecting bona fides of these persons especially as Bekerman has confessed to being a German Jew They propose to transfer them all to Bombay and will be grateful for your help in interrogating them in order to establish genuineness or other wise of their claims to be Polish subjects Letter follows(Copy) 'Karwa Castle', 77, Walkeshwar xRoaci Bombay the 8 th July 1940.&gt; The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, 1940 \ Sir, Yesterday, I have oeen informed that the three Polish young men who had escaped from German prison camps and arrived at Quetta went on hunger strike on the first of this month. Thanks to the persuasion of an iCnglish lady who out of sheer sympathy took interest in their fate they have given up the strike. Being far from Quetta it is difficult for me to judge impartially the attitude which has been taken up by the authorities in Quetta towards them. Yet judging from the fact that they took decision to go even on hunger strike as well as from some remarks in their letter which I received from them on the 6 th July 1940, I consider that I cannot leave long the matter as it stands. I quote below the remarks in translation •ifendering from one place to another, sick with fatigue, sometimes even without a drop of water through the mountainous desert of Cralter-Dag on the Russian and Iranian frontier, our strength helped us to make up our mind that if we at all go'somewhere, we snail go to our friends - our comrades in arms for fight for the independence of nations - and therefore we directed our steps to India. 'Nobody asked you to come here' somebody darea to tell us. 'As a matter of fact, in the German prison camp we got onlyafter three days some sort of soup. But all the same our position there was clear and required no comments. The Germans although they placed machine guns around us showed us some courtesy as from a soldier to a soldier. Under our window at Quetta there walks a detec tive, so insolent, that he comes to harass us even in the night. But we have good food and we stay in the Dak Bungalow.’ We are still young, naive and inexperienced. ^ We are yet not accustomed to cynicism. “ I have, therefore, decided to proceed to Simla to seek audience with His Excellency the Viceroy, tp present the case before His Excellency and to acquaint him with the treatment which has been accored by the authorities^ Quetta to the soldiers of an Allied country - comrades in arms with the British fighting for the common cause - soldiers who have fulfilled their duty for the Allied cause and who are ready to fight once again. Along with this case, I desire to acquaint His Excellency with all other cases in which the;ap—***♦ *c§ authorities in this country have taken decisions wfiich I consider as detrimental to the fulfillment of my duties as Consul General of a foreign country and especially as representative of an Allied country which has carried out and continues to carry out all the obligations arising out of the alliance with His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom. I have, therefore, the honour to request youto arrange audience forme with His excellency N the Viceroy not later than the 22nd of this month as I understand from Press reports that His Excellency is proceeding on a tour on the 25th of this month. I shall be much obliged ^ for a reply before the 15th by telegram fixing the date of the audience in order to enable me to proceed to Simla in time. Notwithstanding the aoove, I repeat my request to release as soon as possible the three yo ung polish soldiers so ti.at they may proceed to Bombay in order tofclace themselves at my disposal. ^ I have the honour to oe, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d/- E. Banasinski, Consul G-eneral for Poland.1940 J To No* U. 3977-N/40. ?ho Additional ooputy ;jeoret^ry to ti*e Uoyemment of India in the xtomal j ffalro Tko Conool Qonor&amp;l for Poland, Kama Castlo, 77 , WaUceouwar HoaA, do^oay. l^itod -virala, tho 13th July 1340• Bir, %ith reference to the oorroapondenco ending with your letter No* 6#2/v;/100 t dated the 3th July 1340, I am directed to state that the Government of India very touch regret tire delay which has taken place in cootnun^c* ting with you on the subject of the four persona who entered Baluchistan from Iran and declared themselves to be i olish subjects and they appreciate your solicitude for the interests of ths nationals of your country as an Allied Power. This delay is due to the fact that a succession of reports was received from -uetta about the so persons and that each report turew iore and .lore uoubt on their bon&amp;fidea* As stated in w letter No* D. 3313* N/40, dated toe 3tn duly 1^40, ur* Joseph hekeneany after having claimed that he was a Polish suoject and had served in the i olish aruy, subsequently admitted to being a Ger^oi Jew* In view of this and other suspicious circumstances he was arrested* This, together with certain other facts, threw considerable doubt on the bonafldee of the other three .^«n who are living at the Uak hung-low in uetta, and it was necessuxy to investigate tiie matter further* 2* According to the statement made by these men &amp;tnd papers in Uieir possession, their names and utuer particulars are as followsi«- (a) (ij Name and agsc Igierd btolynwo, 34 years. (11) PJbaae of birthi Warsaw. (ill) Father's name, address) tasimir wtolyhwo, ^ row Grodaka, etc* ) BurgAStrassee 53. vsas a feasor of /.nthro*pology in Ui% University of Crakow and received ths legion of Honour* (iv) Other particulars - served in &gt;*-• ^kelleya', Oaruiff and is in possession of certifica tes of dlscittarge from that ship* In Jeptfeober 1933, Joined the Officers* Artillery school at Hfeobruf as a Cadet* In June 1033 was appointed under sub-lieutenant (N. -od liorunjie) in ths 10th division ana served until 13th October 1939 when he was taken prisoner by the (ieraians* /.nows Us following languages - Polish, Gsrokin, Ausulan and a little t rv lish. is known to (b)* (b) (1) Name and age • Adam Backer, 26 years* (11) Place of birUi • Kalwaya, Zabsidowlka* (ill) f'aUHer's name and profession • fooan, a Junior police officer*(iv) U&gt; Horae address - ^a*o;&gt;&amp;ne« Other particulars • Joined the 5Jth a^;i^ent a fee days After the outbreak of war with Germany end was captured at I low. According to his statement) hie papers were Uuien from him by the Iranian police in liesned* Knows the following languages - Polieh t German, Russian and a little ri.iish* (e) (1) Ht\rae and age • Hronlstaw dogussewier, 22 years. (ii) Place of birth - Lithuania, (place not Known)* (ill) Father's name • ificolai (deceased)* (iv) name address - Kedainiai Lotnovo* (v) Otiker particulars • Before tile war was employed by the Polish Government for the collection of information* On the outbreak of war, Joined the gnd Polish Regiment of Technicians ana worked as an instructor on o»otor vehicles* nought against the Russians and was made a prisoner near Viina. (d) (!) Hume and age - Joseph Bette man, 2 l years* (ii) i'laoe of birth - bon Jirovitaa 70 Kilometres from Warsaw, (iii) Father's name - bronig* (iv) vddress of jsaother • Ho* 9, H 0 v* afevsKa, bods* (v) OUter particulars - Joined the JBth ilsgiment as a volunteer in Avgust 1S39. was empioysd as a cls&amp;ner on a motor car* whsn ths Germans attacked Katowlts, deserted along with outers and escaped to Russia* Knows Polish and Oerrsan languages* 3* On their arrival all four stated that they had been evicted from Iran into British territory by the Iranian authorities* bnquiries were raade from Tehran and the Iranian Government have CctogoriColly denied having elUier deliberately sent Utem into India or orderevi them to leave Iran* It also appears that br* ^tolyhwo mentioned in the oourse of a conversation in v ustta that he had been attached to Ute diplomatic &gt;ex*vice and had served in the Polish ^abasoies in Juris and lieriin. Ue also said ttuxt he had been a Cadet in the Polish Navy* inese facts, however, were not mentioned in the state^uant previously (aode by him* br* A* iiacker said in his statement that after his escape ike worked on ste^aer 'Grussia' at &lt;xiessa ior 3 isonth* from the IbUi November 1B39* It is, however, understood that this ship was in Chatham in Junu&amp;ry IdSO as an araed merchant cruiser* Mr* B* Bogussewier was also heard to say in Polish 'I am as much a Pole as any of you** One of them was also heard to remark in Uie course of a conversation waver happens ws raust stick to ths sajis atoxy M * 4* You will no doubt appreciate the possibility that German agents my be introduced into India in* the guise of refugees «*nd that it is necessary to ta** the greatest possible care to see that this does not occur* The Government of India do not feel that the three persons now in the bek Bungalow at uetta have valid grounds for complaining of their treatment* In ••••••37 . 3 In your letter No* 6J2/../100, Oatea 8th July 1940 1 you have quoted certain remark* made by thea and it appears that they complain of the fact that a detective walks about outside the Bungalow and is insolent* They go on to ndUit| as is indeea the fact f that they have good food and they are living in the ha* Bungalow* The Government of India appreciate that) if these three uum are in fact f'oles 9 they are naturally resentful at being kept In ; uetta inatead of being free to proceed as soon as possible to burope* At the same time they fssl sure that you will appreciate the need for caution in ex?*mining the case* 5* as a result of careful examination of the evidence before them 9 the Government of India remain in some doubt whether these three mn are in fact Polish subjects* they are therefore anxious to establish these men*s rides beyond dispute y and would be most grateful for your cooperation in interrogating them and stating your conclusi&lt; ns* Arrange .tents ere being made to send the;rt down to Bombay t ith this object without delay* 6* In order to max* the interrogation complete it is also proposed to send Ur* B**era&amp;n with them to jomoay as well us two self styled nuseituis and f IIaNA CHlrfUUVA who have been aa^ociAted with them in Uieir travels and whose interrogation ;aipht assist to clear up the bona rides of the thre* ^oies* ?• In view of the situation as now ex li-ined the Government of India will be i lad to be informe*! wneUier you still desire an audience with His excellency the /iceroy «and y it so t they would ask to be informed in general teres what other subjects it is desired to raise with fits I xcelloncy* As you are aware t i ia .xcelle»jcy Mis shortly proceeding on tour and I am to s^y that owing to preoccupations it is likely to be difficult to arrange interviev/ before his departure* X have the honour to be f Uir f Your moat obedient sei'vant) Sd/- fi.W. Fletcher f Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India*(a J 38, Copy of telegram dated Simla the llth July 1940, from the Polish Consul General, Bomoay, to Foreign Simla. Yours dle^enth received ready to co operate utmost establish bonafides Poles at Quetta upon their arrival Bombay. Regards Bekeyear also ready help local find out his identity 4°j 5566 1940(Copy) Copy of an Express Letter No, D.4034-N/40 dated Simla the 18th July 1940, from th e Addi tipaal Powfry— Secretary to the Government of India, j£• A.Eeparraient^ to the Chief Secretary to the Govt. Of Bombay, * es at Political and Services Department. of Polish and Russian ref Subject: Arrival Quetta. [ge 940 Reference Govt, of India letter No. D.3977-N/40, dated the 13th July 1940, to the Consul-General for Poland, Bombay, a copy of which is enclosed. The polish Consul-General has now agreed to assist in interrogating the three self-styled Poles, two Russians and one German Jew referred to in the aoove mentioned letter. 2. It is proposed to arrest the three Poles now at liberty and the two Russians under Rule 129(1)(a) of the Defence of India Rules, and send them to Bombay under escort where they can be interrogated by the Polish Consul-General as soon as possible after arrival. Please telegraph whether you agree to receive these men. , 3. The Polish Consul-General has expressed great concern over the fate of the three self-stylea Poles named Stolyhwo, Backer and Bogussewier, who up to now have merely been kept in the Dak Bungalow in Quetta under surveillance. If it impossible to arrange for their accommodation in some building under surveillance, it would be desirable to do so as if they are put into jail, representations may be made by the Polish Consul-General. 4. The Baluchistan Administration are being sent a copy of this letter and are being aSked to arrange direct with you regarding the transfer of these Poles and inform the Govt, of India of the date of their departure from Quetta and their arrival in Bombay so that the Polish Consul-General can be informed accordingly. IWrensri GOVBRNMiiiNT OF INDIA, External Affairs Department. ISEBiSSS-LmaB- From - Foreign, Simla. To - Baluchistan, Ziarat. No. D. 4034-N/40. Dated/,he 18th July 1940. Arrival of Polish and Russian refugees at Qu e t ta. Reference correspondence noted in the margin 1 (copy enclosed). The Government of India wile be grateful if arrange ments can be made direct with the Bombay Govern- 2. Letter No. D.4034-N/40, dated the t&amp; ,k Joient to send Bekerman, July 1940, from the Govt, of India, to {the three so-called the Chief Secretary to the Govt, of jtPoles and the two Bombay. {Russians to Bomuay unaev escort as soon as possible. For this purpose it will be necessary to arresu the three Poles and two Russians under Rule 129(1) (a) of the Defence of India Rules. It is suggested that the actual arrest should be deterred until^the actual time of departure. Please telegraph- 2 - luz when the party is despatched and the date and time of arrival at Bomoay so that the polish Consul-G-eneral can be informed. The issue of the above is authorised. 3d/- E.W. Fletcher, Additional Deputy Secretary to the Grovernment of India.From To (Ooj^y) No. D.4034-N/40. The Additional Deputy 3 Grovemment of India in Affairs Department, fee r e tar the ixt ernal The Consul-den eral for Poland, Karwa Castle, 77, Vfelkeshwar Road, Bom oay. Dated Simla, the 18th July 1940. Sir, I am directed to refer to the corres pondence ending with your telegram dated the 13th July 1940, and to say that the Government of India are extremely grateful t o you for agreeing to assist them in estaolishing the bona fides of these persons. Bekerman, Stolyhwo, Backer and Bogussewier, together with the two Russians named Bazileffsk and Tatiana Chinova, will be sent from Quetta to Bombay under escort and the Bomvay Government^ are being asked to make arrangements for their reception. In view of the suspicious circumstances attaching to these people, it is regretted tnat, in order to enable tne Govern ment of India to have them suitably guarded en-route to Bombay, and during their stay there, it will be necessary to arrest Stolyhwo, Backer, Bogussewier under the Defence &lt;?f India Rules. The two Russians will also similarly be arrested. You will be informed by telegram of the time o f their arrival. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d/- E.W. Fletcher, Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.(Copy) 'Karwa Castle”, 77, .felkdc Bombay the 17th July f shwar No. 68 2/f /lQ6. jof The Additional Deputy Secretary to the . India in the External Affairs Department, £_IJLL_A. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. D. 3977-N/4C dated the'l3th July 1940 ana I thank you for the details given therein regard ing the four persons at Quetta wno have declared them selves to be Polish nationals as well as for the explanation given by you as to why the matter has been del eyed so long. .1 fully understand the caution of the authori ties concerned during present times in their dealings with the entry or sLay of foreigners in this country and I may assure you that I shall be ready to do my best to help the Government of India in tneir en deavours to eliminate danger to the cause of public safety which may come from Polish citizens living in this country or from those who by the vicissitudes of war are forced to seek temporary shelter i n this country. At the same time, I should like to make clear that my solicitude for the interests of the nationals of my country is not motivated merely by the reason of their Polish citizenship but by the desire to protect their interests against possible misconclusions which may easily happen at present times. Further, I regret that I cannot conniva^t the altitude of the authorities concerned in taking steps against Polish citizens, who are entitled to the protection of this Consulate General, without informing me as in the aase of the arrest of Mr. J. Kichler or the detention of the Poles at Quetta andn ot giving me clear reasons for the same upon my requests The particulars regarding the three Poles which I have in my hand correspond more or less with those stated in your letter. The fact that their subsequent statements were not completely in accord xk with their first statement may be explained, in my opinion, by their scanty knowledge of the English language and may partially oe attributed to the fact that the authorities in Quetta treated them as enemy suspects while they had expected that they would be received as friends in arms. I very much doubt tnat these Poles have come to India in tne guise of refugees to act as 'German agents”. As soon as they entered Indian territory, their first move was to approach the Polish Ambassador in London to help them to leave India to join the Polish Army, then in France. They have directed to me the same appeal in their letter dated the 31st May 1940 as soon as they came to know of the existence df this Consulate General. This leads me to believe that if they have come to India n as German agents 11 they would try to find out some pretext to stay in this country instead of expressing their desire to leave it at the first opportunity. As these Poles are being sent to Bombay I shall be glad to co-operate with the authorities to establish their bona fides and to state my conclusions.- 2 - As my intention to come to $imla was not only to seek an audience with His Excellency theViceroy but also to elucidate by personal discussion with the -n External Affairs Department the attitude . V of the Government of India regarding some matters and also my position as Consul General of an Allied country, I shall come to Simla for the latter purpose. As soon as I carry out the investi- f ation regarding the Poles at Quetta upon heir arrival in Bombay as per your request in paragraph 6 of your letter, I shall let you know the date of my arrival at Simla by telegram. I I have tne honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- E. Banasinski, Consul General for Poland.Copy of a latter No. D.4254-N/40 dated Simla the &lt; 4.7 23rd July 1940 from the Additional Deputy Secretary to the government of India in the External Affair/srir - —^ Department to the Consul Greneral for Poland at 'Karwa Castle”, 77 ^ilkeshwar Road, Bombay. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt 01 your letter No. 682/^106, d/- ^he 17.7.40,landj thank you again for your i offer to co-operaW-wa— establishing the bona fid eg of the Polish refugees now in Quetta. The Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, i_LJLL-4. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. D. 40 34-N/40 dated the 18th July 1940 and note that the three Poles are being sent from Quetta to Bombay under escort and that the Government of Bombay are being asked to make arrangements for their reception. . I shall do my best to clear up the bona fides of these Poles as well as to assist tne local authorities in their investigations to establish the identity of other persons. I from Restis, Poona, ter Foreign Simla. Your express letter No. D 4034-N/40 July 18th Provincial Government agrees receive three Poles &amp; two Russians it proposes Keep Poles in Hotel under suryeillance at cost Rupees r ive each per day &amp; send Russians to jail presumed Central Government bear necessary charges kindly telegraph how Baxerman should be treated w Karwa Castle”, 77, Walkeshwar Road, Bombay th e 22nd July 1940. Sir I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most ooedienb servant, 3d/- E. Banasinski, Consul General for Poland. AL o/rfu- Kl- V. Copy of telesrain/dated Simla the 27th July 1940, AL •-ram /r\n +.Af ■m/dAr Copy of telegram dated from POL CONSUL Bombay to the Secretary C/o Foreign Simla. Simla the 29th^Jul3|'2-^40 e Additional Dsput^* Referring Telephonogram this morining &amp; voip re stating Poles will be sent Bombay pro oably l^ext^ days gives me impression nothing definitely IT^cTded stop If my interpretation correct Doctor Lisiecki proceed Quetta in spite burden of expenses on Consulate budget as'I wish solve deadlock without further delay Please wire reply when Poles definitely leaving Quetta for Bombay. Copy of telegram Mo. 1 99-11 Dated 30th July 1940 Camp from Foreign, Simla, to Polish Consul Ceneral, Bombay. Your telegram of 29th July. Telegraphic instructions are being issued today to Quetta authori ties to despatch poles at earliest oossiole moment • Bombay Covt. have agreed to lodge them in hotel 'under surveillance. 'Covt. of India prefer that interroga tion shoulfid’ be carried out witl^our co-operation in Bombay and request y 6 u not to send Dr. LISIECKI to Quetta. Ls.Ii.S- Telegram No. 202-N Camp. Dated the 30th July 1940. From- Foreign, Simla. To Baluchistan, Ziarat. (Repeated to Bombay Government, reference their telegram 0/Misc .W. ?. of 27th July). Express letter 19^0, polish and Reference Government of India NO.B1034-N/40, dated the 18th July Russian refugees, 2. Bombay Government agree to receive 3 Poles, 2 Russians and 1 German Jew. Poles will be kept in hotel in Bombay under surveillance, remainder will be lodged in jail. Cost of this and of journey to Bomoay will ultimately he borne by Government of India, Please despatch party with suitable escort at earliest possible moment as Polish Consul General is making urgent representations. Please tele-' graph Bombay Government date of despatch and date of arrival in Bomoay, repeating here. 3. Bekerman should oe lodged in jail and treated like Russians. One Russian is a woman. 4. Polish Consul General has been informed that Quetta authorities are being asked to despatch party immediately. Request that you will get into touch with him as soon as possible informing him of date ' interrogation. July'. fate 'v e r i mi eflm o fhin&amp;KC? tmeiii/, u 1940. —FILE COPY i —TP' — JL • m '• • -V A . ■V-' ^ W 'k' ' ' ►w' V% w • Wb - !.. • . « i W ^ . .. •^'-V » v V Pi^om Govt.of India, External Affairs Dept., to His Majesty 9 s Representative, Tehran, and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India* Dated Simla, 19.25 hours, 8th June, 1940. 1948 . Addressed to His Majesty 9 s Representative, Tehran, telegram No. 76, repeated to Secretary of State for India, His Majesty's Consul-General, Meshed, and His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Zahidan. Reference your telegram No. 98 of 29th May. Report received from Baluchistan that Batina, Armenian actress, entered British territory at Kila Sufald from Iran on 4th June, having travelled via Meshed and Mirjawa. Being unwilling to enter British territory, she returned to Mirjawa, but was again evicted by Iranian authorities on border. 2. If you see no objection, kindly make representation to Iranian Government against this further deportation without consent of Government of India, and inform them that Government of India reserve their right to send the woman back to Iran. MCo. POL. DEPt. 10 JUN 940 INDIA OFFICE P. T. 0.tNDEXED HLEJX)* * (1213 groups) Allotted to political Department , Copies 'Circulated , P. Z. 2 ( d65 1940 j Prom Dated Received 60 a DIlC YPHI^R QP Tv3 L E G- R A M, Government of India, External Affairs Department, to Tehran and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India* HC (. /* •* Simla, !30*36 hours, 21 st May, 1940* ' / /». a 20*00 hours, 21st May, 1940* € Jj Addressed to Tehran, repeated to Secretary of State for India No.1621. Pour Poles and one Russian arrived in British territory from Iran on May 6 th. Prom their statements, it appears they entered Iran from Soviet territory and that they have been deliberately deported to India* 2* The Government of India would be grateful if enquiries could be made from Iranian Government with a view to making protest regarding these deportations, if facts are as stated, and if Iranian Government could be asked to obtain the consent of the Government of India before any further such deportations are made*. Three more Poles are reported to be in custody in &amp;ahidan and it is presumed that it is the intention of the Iranian Government similarly to deport them. The Iranian Government may also kindly be infermed that Government of India reserve the right be deport back to Iranian territory any foreigners evicted to India without their consent. 3&lt;, For your personal information. Government of India are considering the possibility of sending the Poles to France but may decide to return the Hussian to Iran. REOo. POL. DERn 22MAY'&lt;W0 INDIA OFFICEP/Z. 1 2?^ yW ® 2874 1 940 No. 160~i^ dated (and xi«cd.) 8th May I&amp;4G. From - Baluchistan, Quetta. To - Foreign, Simla* Russian Chinese Turkistan entered Iran and met two other * olee at Ztdiidan* They aloiv, with one Rijssian were evicted into British territory on 6tlx Hoy. They are being sent to Quetta list and full details will be forwarded on their arrival. s olchagal rerorts two Polish Uilitaxy officers viho are said to have esca-ed tnia crossed L ino. d 83 14 ENCLOSURE IN IN 01 /, FOREIGN SECRETARY'S u T No. DATE R/.J. v. ') 83 14 - 5 2 1 - 5-1940</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00033f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/380A</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00033f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/380A</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 287/40 'Deportation from Persia into British Indian territory'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-26T23:00:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-49; these numbers are also written in pencil, and are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the deportation of three Polish men (Oligierd Stolyho, Adam Backer and Josef Bekerman), one Lithuanian man (Bronistew Bogussewier), one Ukrainian man (Iwan Basileffsk) and one Russian woman (Tatiana Chinnova) from the Persian Border to British Indian territory at the beginning of the Second World War.The main correspondence is between:• the Government of India, External Affairs Department to Tehran• the Secretary of State for India• the Senior Assistant Director, Intelligence, Government of India, Quetta• the Director, Intelligence Bureau (Home Department), Government of India, Simla• the Secretary to the Agent to the Governor-General in Baluchistan, Ziarat• the Polish Consulate General in India• the Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs DepartmentDetailed are the British Indian Government’s concerns regarding national security leading to the arrest and detention of the group. Attributed to this is a belief that Bekerman is German and Jewish, and conflicting reports from Vernon Smith, an American woman who came in contact with the refugees. Also detailed is the Polish Consulate General in India’s wish to facilitate their release, and his assessment of their legitimacy once they had arrived in Bombay, India.Included are statements from the five men; preliminary (folios 3 to 7) and revised (folios 9 to 15) following alleged inconsistencies in the former, and a statement from Chinnova (folios 19 to 21). These contain personal information and include the motivations and circumstances which led to their arrival at the Persian border, and a description of items in their possession.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Poland</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bombay</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Soviet Union</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imprisonment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Refugees</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00033f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>