<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000022_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:43:36.073Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">w DRAFT L3TTSR A Capt. M»P. 0*0 Tandy, Bsq 0 , x Whitehall Court, ^ S#W*lo ''2 t Ext. sj * ! Qr'd 2 3 JUN 1944 Mr» Pet afford is still head of the Passport Office. U 0 . 0 . r pi V Dear Tandy, j f- j I have made enquiries^from the Passport 70*~r Office about the chances of -being allowed to visit Southern Ireland. I understand from them that no-one is allowed to visit Eire unless they can prove that their parents, wife or children reside there permanently. It looks from this as if Pelly will be able to go, but it seems doubtful if you would be given permission. I believe, however, that there is some chance that the ban may be relaxed fairly soon and it might be worth while for you to to the Passport Office nearer the end of your leave. s^° ^ a —C tv*—6*- I crJu cl‘ u Lt^-c 1‘^—trJ 'A \ ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000022_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/926</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000022</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/926</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 2751/44 'Facilities for Capt Tandy and Mr Pelly to visit Southern Ireland'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-28T22:37:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to the travel plans of Captain Maurice Patrick O’Connor and Cornelius James Pelly (Political Agent and Consul, Muscat) to visit Southern Ireland and the potential restrictions involved. The papers include a draft telegram from Sergeant Roland Tennyson Peel regarding Tandy’s request to visit Ireland and letters from Pelly relating to his own travel arrangements addressed to Sir Geoffrey Prior (Political Resident, Persian Gulf).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Southern Ireland</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Travel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000022#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>