<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00026d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T09:56:07.899Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEGB BUSHjRS Date... .. ................J Q«PY S^NT TO. CS^HDZ^TIAL P£ZM 2911/37, VI fat &gt;s&lt;May, 1937, Sir, / /O V ^ *?/\ In reply to your letter of the 19th April I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that the Company s proposal to employ Mr. .Thomas ^ Patrick, an American citizen, in ihiaiiH has 'been considered by His Majesty's Government. They understand that the post of Drilling Superintendent is a responsible one, and that at the present time it does not appear to be easy to secure British subjects with the qualifications and experience necessary for a post of this kind. In these circumstances, and in view of the Company's assurance that the employment of Mr. Patrick is in their opinion desirable for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking, His Majesty's Government are prepared to give the necessary permission under Article 3 of the V?' 1 * V Agreement dated 5th March, 1934, I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Bd.) M. J. OLAUSUW. he Secretary, The Kuwait Oil Company, Britannic House, Pinsbury Circus, E.C.2.'M jfiij Copy of a letter Ho,579c of tie 2 5th 19L7, from the xluy-ait Oil Company, Ltd., to the Political A-ent, Kuwait. ■, iS-iUSl'vi*# liliHj* 7e liave the honour to forward 'or your infornation copies o^ correspondence that has taken place between, the Basrah Port -authority anc ourselves regarding the . ^ , , fitfiWJ- ■ rtum ■ iWMiKWjig'mMftiioWi'iiMti ter mina tion of the Buoying arran^anent at the Kadhauah anchora -e. Copy of a letter Ho. 5636, dated 11th May, 19^7, from the Iluvmit Oil Company, Ltd., Lx ait to the Port Director and Bi recto r lenera 1 of Ila vi jati on, Basra , i 7e '■/rite to advise you that v/e si: all not require the Buoys installed at lladhaix h ^nd ora je a'^ter the end o' this month. They should, therefore, be roi.oved at the expiry of the present perioc of three months which cones to an end on 9th June next. J q should like to take this opportunity of thanking you 'or the assistance you have given us in this matter. Copy of a letter IIo.l/PE3/2, dated the 2 Ot h May, 19L7 , from Port director /and Director General Qf navigation, Basra to the Kuwait Oil Company, Ltd,, Kuwait, In reply to your letter 5636, dated 11th May the Buoys installed at Kadhamah anchorage will be removed as requested when opportunity offers after June 9th. ^ ■ V ^ ^ ^ ^ • ^' } i- Vw -V CONFIDENTIAL. No.C - 8^ [EUSMIR^ P iSIDENCY ffe - 16-7-S7 i p' n ~! ri . - j ~ i i«—■ ■ ■• i-w # - ....''.-i' The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments tq The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* V and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the ?P * ^-17 1? 37 Keference to previous correspondence DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Translation of an article which appeared in the Iraqi newspaper 'AS SIJIL' of the oth July 1957 # Kuwait Oil Company, --- ,.^Tc 'v , .(Heoeived und.6P ICiiwQ.i't Oil Coin .p&amp;iiy's oovGrinp* Letter No.6028 of the 12th July 1957). ARTICLE IN I^WSPAESR 'aX SUIL^ DATISD 6,7.57, Has the Kuwait Oil Company failed at Kuwait: Is this failure becoming a danger (at the finish). The K.O.C. drilling on the North side (of the bay) has ended in nothing. The Company has encountered failure there, not having found oil after having spent octisiderable sums of money and working for a whole year on the site recommended by the Geologists. The equipment has now been taken away and no one is left there. Therefore the Kuwaitis have lost their hopes of oil or black gold as it is called these days. People n^io have come from Kuwait say that tiie Company is doing its best in a survey of the south but the slowness of results show that they are uncertain of success - they be lieve that the only place in Kuwait territory that has deep oil is Subahiyah. This place the Saudi Government claims as it is part of the land in which Saudi Arabia and Kuwait are partners, in accordance with the agreement made at Ojair in 1922. The Kuwaitis who are reasonable men are asking!?) is there any reason for this failure and is it a bona fide failure? The Kuwaitis think that after the failure in the North the K.O.C. are surveying the south (though they know the only plentiful supply of oil is at Subahiyah) in order to alter the agreement between themselves and the Shaikh of Kuwait, as they are relying on the following:- 1# The K.O.C. did not commence work in the north until the Geological Party had finished surveyii^; the ground with a view to finding the likeliest place to drill for oil. A Qhief Geologist came to Kuwait to give his opinion of the survey of the Geological Party and agreedBfl Ycf on lod }9 &lt; i lo5 m :io SI w J o - 2 - agreed their report. How then have they failed after all this accurate survey and is it true that the K.O.C. spent the amount of money they are reputed to have spent on 500 labourers in one year unless they knew there was oil there? 2. When the Company commenced operations , Subahiyah was never mentioned but when a dispute arose between the Saudi Government and Kuwait the Company began to discuss the possibilities of Subahiyah and to say that there was oil there, These two reasons made the Kuwaitis think badly of the Kuwait Oil Company and try to clear them iout?) in the near future. It is believed that the Company anted the opportunity of working on this ground jointly owned by the Saudi Government and Kuwait in order to alter the agreeiaent between themselves and Shaikh Sir .ahmad al Jabar as isubatu ie do not want to leave this subject without drawing attention to one bad fact, and that is the K.0.G, would not play this game unless they knew that the dis- cussions betv/een the Shaikh and themselves were secret and that the substance of the agreement remained unknwon to the Kuwaitis - for no Kuwaiti knew anything about it. It is not necessaiy for us to say that the Shaikh would benefit a great deal by consulting his people before making a final decision in this important matter and ^iculd publish the substance of the agreement for his people to study after which they will expound to him their enlightened opinion so as to protect the country's interests. But so far nothing has been done* Although the Company has begun to play its dangerous game His Highness should not help them in the slightest degree. Physically, Kuwait has no great value except for oil and His Highness should fear God and think of histhink of his people and not help the Company in any way to this only wealth of Kuwait. We see no disgrace in His Kighness's having a consultation over so important a matter. All leading nations discuss important matters with their people and it is hoped that the Shaikh will follow in their steps. As to the game the K.O.G, has begun to play - we trust it will not succeed. In*s*alia. One of them.s. BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. I'o. ■; CONFIDENTIAL. ?-8.37. . No. C - ' ^ ' c■):ifi■.t5l records r The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The General Manager, Messrs: Thefc Anglo- Iranian Oil Gonipaiiy,Ltd. , A B A D A H . ■fx w in duplicate and has the honour to transmit to hin/a~cop'or'the undermentioned dooument(s). It will be seen that the authorization has been rasde valid up to the 51st December 1957 only, so as to bring it in line with the one held by you in respect of your aircraft marked G-ASI4M (D,H.89 Dragon Hapide), so that, if necessary, at the expiry of the above period, the two can be assimilated into a single authorization covering all the three aircraft. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 24 th July 1937 Eeference to previous correspondence: A.1,0.0. ? s letter No.545/7 of the 24th May 1957. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Special Authorization granted by Kuwait in respect of two aircraft Hapide(2) - a~AC£Hl,G-AGZF), and v^lid up to the 51st December 1957. lis Highness the Ruler of of the a . I .0.G.(D .H. Dragon Copy (without enclosure), with co the Political Resident in the Per with a copy of the A.I.O.G. lette oapliments, to the Hon'ble sian Gulf, Bushire, together r quoted above.COPY. ANGLO I HAITIAN OIL COMPANY, Ltd ABADAK , SOUTH IRAN No.345/7 E4th Hay 1937 The Political Agent Kuwait Sir We have the e bdiioui- to refer you to your confidential memorandum No.C-260, dated the 3rd August 1936 forwarding a special authorization granted by His Excellency the ituler of Kuwait in respect of our two aircraft (DH.Dragon Rapide - G-ACZS and G-ACZF) to land at Kuwait. This permit is valid for a period of one year from 1st -ugust 1936 to 31st July 1937 • 19 37, we will be grateful if His Excellency would kindly agree to renew this permit for a further period of one year for these two aeroplanes. As this permit expires on the 31st July We have the honour to be , Sir Your obedient servants Sd Illegible. DY. GENERAL MANAGERy ) 86/1 Telegram Fro^n To Repeated Q Secretary of State for India, London, Political Resident at Shiraz, Political Agent, Kuwait# Copy by air mail to Government of India, External Affair Department, Simla* No»8314. Bated 21st received 22nd September 1937. Kuwait Oil Company wish to employ SAMTTSL CARL MeMACK IN unmarried American citizen as geologist in place of RHOADES who is not returning. Number of Americans will thus remain at two. Company have given V &gt;&lt;. assurance under Article 3 of Political Agreement and Petroleum Department are satisfied. Do you see any objection ? 1 hbtaxandttm c.v.a.By Air Maii. P-Z- . j I a ii rushir e residency. | COiiraEiJTIAL RECORDS INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, ■ s Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to J, '•— \ by Mail. wtluuiulmj) Qui. UiiHU mt of Inrlin, The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36P.Z.6115/37 /1?&gt; KimiT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED Britannic House, Finabury Circus, London, E .G.2. 14th September, IQSY. The Under 'Secretary of State for India India Office, Whitehall, S .W .I. Sir, It will 'be recalled that permission was given 'by His Majesty's Government for the employment of / Mr. R.O. Rhoades in Kuwait in the Under Secretary of / State's letter of 12th December, 1935, reference P.Z.8848/35. Mr. Rhoades left Kuwait on leave in June last and we are now informed by Gulf Exploration Company that he is required for duty elsewhere and will not return to Kuwait. The Kuwait Oil Company is desirous of employing, as Mr. Rhoades 1 successor, Mr. Samuel Carl McMackin, single, an American citizen of American parents born on 17th September, 1904, at Champaign, Illinois, Mr. McMackin has recently become employed by Gulf Exploration Company after careful investigation, and is considered to be a suitable successor to Mr. Rhoades. It is, as you may be aware, very difficult to secure the services of competent British geologists and this Company is of opinion that the employment of Mr. McMackin is desirable for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking. The appointment of Mr. McMackin will raise the number of American employees in Kuwait to two. We beg, therefore, to request that His Majesty's Government will consent to his employment in Kuwait. I am etc. Por Kuwait Oil Company Limited (Sd.)H. KEMP. Secretary.V V INDIA OFFIC / / WHITEHALL, S.¥.l. P # 2.6115/37 16th September, 1937 Dear Gunn, I enclose a copy of a letter from the Kuwait Oil Company who wish to employ an American, Samuel Carl McMackin, as geologist vice Rhoades, who is required for duty elsewhere. You will ohserve that the Company give the necessary assurance under Article 3 of the Political Agreement and that the total number of Americans employed ^two) will not 'be increased. Do you see any objection to Mr. McMackin's employment? I am sending a copy of this letter to Brenan and Seal. (Sgd.) W. J. CLAUSON P.S. I gather that as usual the Company is^in a hurry, and that the man is sailing from the U.S.A. for this country on the 23rd September. H.G. Gunn, Esq., Petroleum Department, Mines Department, Dean Stanley Street, S. y. 1.By Air M ail. P.Z. 1951 J-* BUSH1RE RESIDENCY, I Date 7r.*l.... CONFIDENTlUliECOnDj INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, « J ■ 5-; /£ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to z &gt; by Mail. J Sea **f]i i 1 , FuiuijU'ii S lluj L u.v , Q^verniriCAi t of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36 /sc.V tfr j I I BUSH'RE RESIDENCY'] rc , | I COM F^DE Nil A l T RECORDS I 'n *zaaB£*.*i uw* i INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, _ kwo.n Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. By Air Mail. P.Z. ' 10 jp, I 10 A copy lias been sent to b r MaiL I -^i^- The Foro iin-n iSoorotaryr^r^^Bm^-oLTi-irlia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36P.Z. 6316/37. 4th October, 1937. k.t^ Sir s x In reply to your letter of the 14th September I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that, in the circumstances explained no objection will be raised under Article 3 of the Agreement of the 5th Marchj 1934, to the employtnen of Mr, Samuel Carl McMaclcin as geologist in the place of Mr. R.O.Rhoades. I am y Sir, Your obedient Servant, r : f ri,- - - Secretary, Kuwait Oil Company, Britannic House, Finsbury Circus, E.G. 2,/y rs BUS M, RE RESIDENCY ; puoninc. n^c Poiitioal Agenoy, 4 / / ^ \ I Hn,, . /tejrv Confidential ^ 7//1/37 ^ Kuwait, D.O.No.C- ' '■ ''eoNFiPEWTitL '.EC'K s 30tll H «remb«r, 1937. -^Ci -^yS &lt;r^ L C ^A. &lt;2 !u^c. I hear rrom Mr.Scotlii th© G-enor&amp;l buperintencieiit of the Kowait Oil Company, who has just been to Iraq, that there is news there that one of the big American Supply Houses of machinery for oil fields will shortly establish a depot somewhere in this area, probably at Basra. Such firms I gather keep a very large stock of machinery and tools at their depots, so that Oil Companies can readily obtain them, instead of sending for them to the various factories ol orUtin. I understand that it is an institution which only comes when there is a large demand from several fields, such as those developing now in the Middle Hast and the Gulf• It occurs to me that you might wish to know of this, if you have not already heard about it. 2^ 1 gather no decision has been made yet, out that one of the big American firms, the National oupply Company, has been making tentative enquiry. Superior employees of the Oil Companies think that Basra in spite of irksome Customs Rules and duties, is the most likely site for a depot because of the landing facilities and that Bahrain, while conveniently situated is rather an unlikely choice, owing to difficult landing arrangements. The Hobble Lt-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.S., Political Resident in Persian Gulf B U S H I R E.7^ There are presumably advantages to the Navy, and the Air force, in having such important reserve stocks of material close at hand to oil fields in time of war when oil production might have to be speeded up for them, and when mercantile shipping is delayed, Y ou may be informed about this already. In any case my information is second hand, and I only write in case you had not heard, or you thought it of the Interest which it seemed to me to be.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. oonfidentiai. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent bv A.IS, MAIL which provides a means of commuuieation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it h &lt;$d been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department,] Ty No 4 840- S of 1937. Bushire, Bated the 17th December, 7957.. x6p From « political Resident, Bushire. To • Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, JSew Delhi. His Majesty^ Ambassador, Bagdad. The Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Iraq, Hinaidi, The Senior ilaval Officer, Persian malf. The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat. Subject: American Supply Depot for macninery for Oil Fields. ~i ' KV ir * I enclose herewith a copy of a letter, ^o.C-279, dated the 30th November 1937, from the Political Agent, Kuwait . 2. Prima facie I should have imagined that Captain de uaury's remarks in his paragraph 3 have considerable weight. sd. T.G.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. ni-y 7 for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. f) [Signature) (Designation) •mmtiumtaaaimiamm86/1 ✓ Telegram (i.T.C. From iPolitical Agent, Kuwait« To Politica.1 Resident on H.M.S. 3idef ord* Oo90o Dated and received 27tJi February 19 38o I i Kuwait Oil Company Joave struck oiX at 3700 feet ? 1 H at BURGANi Quantity will not be known Tor some weeks but quality is about the same as at Bahrain. #/ell has been a difficult one to drill# Political Agent C.V.A. i-v6 86/|f Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident on h . M . S .Bideford, At Dibai # To Political Agent, Kuwait. jmo, T/52, Dated the 28tli February 1938 # f. 5&gt; Your telegram ^o«90 of February 27tn. Best congratulations to Company and Snaiicn. I am informing India Office and Oovermient of India. - Resident. 7.L #CONFIDENTIAL , /XDC/2# BUS! A/0 Date.-- iJi'p' Pv^fJOENCY I4-V WnfIDE NTUL RcOO^PS The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U 3 H I R S. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dooumentfe) for information# POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 5th Mar ch 1938 ♦ Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Telegram to Secretary of State for India, London, No»93 dated 2nd March 1938o Oil in Kuwait,Tele gram G,T # C. From - Political, Kuwait. To - Secretary of State for India, London Repeated - By post to Government of India, Delhi, Bushire, Bahrain and Muscat. No • 93• Dated the End March 193S. Arabic News. The Kuwait Oil Company have come upon oil in Kuwait territory. Definite reports as to the value or quantity have not yet been received. •Political-and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dooument(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 8th March 1938. ^6 / 1 - &lt;a&lt;M&gt;iiapg.Ma!iil*f—F&gt;USHIR^ ns^T^NC} No. fa /3«f j CeNFiOGNTiAL RECORDS | The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon'lDle the Political Hesident, in the Persian Quit. BUSHIKE, Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Subject Name and Date Translation of a letter No. B/5/ 829 of 1st Muharram 1357(3.3.38) from H,H. the Buler of Kuwait. Burgan well.Translation of letter No. H/5/829 of 1st Muharram 1357 (3.3.38) from H.H. the Euler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait &gt; After compliments, With pleasure I have received your letter No. 158 of 28.2.38 (28.12.56) informing me alDout the telegram which was received hy you from the Hon'Me the Political Besident, and which contains his congratulations ahout the good news of the Burgan well. Therefore, I would request you to kindly forward , to the Hon'hle the Political Resident, my most sincere thanks for his kind congratulations which I appreciate. Usual ending.V r-b I $ No.of i*db iUSH ! P~ RESIDENCY No 3*1' J Date •ONFIDGNTIAL RECORDS The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the March 1958. Reference to previous correspondence: DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE, rsame and Date. Subject. The Hon T bie the Political He si cent in the Persian Gulf, f I V/ Bushire and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). ISxtract froia letter No♦5211 dated 5th liar da 1956, from the General Superintendent, Kuwait Oil Co., Ltd., Kuv/ait. Oil in Kuwait.P.2.11-225/1938. KU7AI2 OIL GO?J?Amr, LIMITED, BRITaNNIG HOUSE ? FINSBURY CIRCUS, LONDON, E.G.2. 17th June, 1938. The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, WMtenalj., o • 'J. 1 • / Sir, As you are aware, Mr. 0. G. _ McMackin, an American citizen, is at present employed by this Company in Kuwait in the capacity of geologist. It is proposed to replace Mr. McMackin by Mr. L. C. Sass, also an American citizen, who was born of American parentage on 18th December 1910 at Chicago. Mr. Sass is unmarried. Tie has * been employed by Gulf Exploration Company since September, i';33: and is recommended by them as a suitable person fcr em pi cyxr.ent V Kuwait. The Company is of opinion that the employment of Mr. c k;ss is desirable for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking m view, particularly, of the fact that competent British geoj ogi»rc are still very difficult to obtain. ■ : ' r e beg, therefore, to request that H.M. G-. will consent to the employment of Mr, Sass in Kuwait. lie are, Sir, Your obedient Servants, For KIimiT OIL GOi^PANY LIMITED, ( Sgd. ) H. T. Kemp Secretary.V 34 &gt;,5/1958. KUWAIT OIL COMPANY LIMITED, BRITANNIC HOUSE, FINSBURY CIRCUS, LONDON, E,C. 2. 17th June, 1938. Symon, Esq. , India Office, S .W .I. Dear Symon, ^ ' I enclose herewith the customary official letter asking for permission to employ a non-British individual in Kuwait and shall he much obliged if you will give us your help in getting it through. If H.M.G. approve the employment of Mr. Sass in Kuwait, would you be so kind as to communicate that fact to the British Consul in New York in order that a Kuwait visa may be issued. There is a little less urgency than usual so a letter to the Consul would 'be quick enough. Yours &amp;c., (Sd) H.T.KEMP.**1 P. Z. 4325/38, 7) INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S .W.I. SOth June, 1938. Dear Starling, Would you please refer to XMifm's o a letter of the 17th September, 1937, (No.P.D. 98/2) regarding the employment by the Kowait Oil Company of Mr. S.C.McMackin, an American subject, as geologist in placjs of Mr. R. 0. Rhoades? W ^ r ^ ^ T now enclose a copy from the Kowait Oil d 17th June, 1938, ) Company in which they seek consent to the employment of another American, Mr 0 L.C.Bass, in place of Mr. iic,Mackin and should be glad to learn, as soon as possible, whether you see any objection. You will observe that the Company give the necessary assurance under Article 3 of the Political Agreement. I am sending a copy of this letter (and enclosure) to Seal and Brenan. Yours &amp;c., (Sd) R.PEEL. • C.Starling, Esq., Petroleum Department, (Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street, S.W.I.By Air Mail. p.z. Sm i92S I: K ( r/ v /. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. Tlie F^oi^n Seergtaryr Q uy^vnme^-of .1 iirli ii The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36•s. By Air Mail. F.Z. Uy 1/ 1836 - LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by ^ Mail. 4963 2000 7.36 BetrretaTy, frDTeTntrT^tit of fndtg^ The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. r/, ' 1 c /196/38 | ; (Appru x47 i06/38) Passport Office, 1, ueen Anne's Gate B ildings, Dartmouth 3treet, Westminster, London, S # .. 1. 3Jth August,1938. dhrn' Dear Symon, As mentioned over the telephone we have granted a new passport to Lieutenant Colonel H.R. . Dickson who is again proceeding to Koweit on the lousiness of the .oweit Oil Co. and I enelofie herewith a copy of a letter from the Company. A visa for Koweit was a fixed to the new passport 'but as arranged Sharjah was omitted. The Company were informed verbally that should Lieutenant Oolonel Dickson wish to proceed to Sharjah he shoulc; apply for facilities at Koweit. Yours sincerely* (Sd) Lambert. 81311 ?/: .13.Symon, K sq.» India Office, O • • j. *uM KUWAIT OIL COMPANY, iJMITSD, Britannic House, Finsbury Cireus, London, 26th August, 1938. ' jl O v^uOi\i i.'J. it. . i U . il ^C... • This is to certify that Lt .Gol. H*H.P .Dickson is proceeding to Kuwait on the business of this Company, 'by train across Europe, thence via Turkey&gt; Syria and Iraq.. He may also require to visit the following countries, either on the 'business of this Company or in transit on his return to this country;- 3 audi Arabia, 3 ha r J ah » II ran s Jordan, Palestine i ii in i.^tKWinnntnwiiii and Sgypt. l-'OK KUWAIT OIL COMPANY LTD. (Sd) 1 Asst. Secretary.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D bpaktmbnt, EXPRESS LETTER [N. —This is an ORIGINAL MJESSAGJE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] F bom Political Agent, Kuwait, [3! J'&amp;M'rKC ppo|Q|rrsj/^v I fxX\ uJ WI vl I Da. / f 0 . i. 'o' • v i % tJ . J To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Gamp Kuwait. No. C- 3 i f Bated 15th October 193 a Subjest:- Kuwait Oil Company. , h' ^ 1 Kuwait Oil Company report that oil similar to that found in No.l well at Burgan (thirty five miles south of Kuwait town) was struck in No.2 Well, in the same neighbourhood, on the 15th. Captain, Political Agent, Kuwait. 4 £/&lt;2 S. 6.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. nonfidential &gt; EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). STB. This is an O BIG IN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] office of the Political Resident r ^ in the Persian (Julf, IO'C/794 of 1938,^ ^ Kuwait. Dated $XSui&amp;k' the 17th October, ^381 I | I I r (an Political Resident , at Kuwait* If 11 Jr ^ I j a ^Reference Residency telegram Uo.T/53, dated the 28th ^e Secretary, to the Government of India,)February 1938. asternal Affairs Department, Mew Delhi, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London* The Air Officer Coramaoding, British Forces in Iraq, Hab baniya. The Senior Uaval Officer, Persian Gulf* Reference A^J Residency Printed letter No.G/X28, dated the 28th ) February 1938, The Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to his ISxpress letter lJo*C~331, dated the 15th October 193 ci, Subj ect : KUWAIT OIL. Hnwait Oil Company report that oil similar to that found in tlo, 1 well at Burgan (thirty five miles south of Kuwait town) was struck in No*2 well, in the same neighbourhood, on the 13th October. attested* sd. T.C.Fowle; Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (C ' .for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* {Signature) (Designation)By Air Mail. P.Z. (fflSif 19 5^ /oik INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, l^'(DcJh l^iSb Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by i£. MaiL Tho Foreign Sooi'Qtary, Grovofimnpnti nf Inrliau ^ The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36KUWAIT OIL COMPAI1Y LIlilTED, BRITAI'ITIC HOUSE 9 FIHSBUHY CIHCU3, f*) LOiTDOIT? S.C.2. 10th October, 1938 The Under Secretary of State for India ? India Office? Whitehall ? S.W.I. AT TE ITT I ON : MR. J&gt;?. GIBS PIT Sir s We l^eg to inform you that Ha3or Harry G. Davis ? a Director of this Company5 proposes to visit Kuwait ? leaving London towards the end of this week. We should he greatly obliged if you would give the necessary instructions to the Passport Office for a Kuwait visa to he issued to Major Davis. We are ? Sir* Your obedient Servants? For KUWAIT OIL COMPAHY LIMITED ? Sd. H. Kemp Secretary.v. / p 86/1 ^ Telegram 4 ^rom Political Agent, Kuv;ait« To Political Resident, -Bushire. I 0.403. Bated and received 17th December 1938. Dickson wishes to visit ibn oaud for pleasure at Christmas and has obtained King's assent. Kuwait Oil Company have no objection. 2. Have you any objection V Political Agent. -j • 'J % j\. *85/i Wn Telegram Q, ^om Political ivesident, iJushire. To lolitical ^gent, Kuwait. ^0.432 Dated the 18th December 1958. ♦ Your telegram ivo.407 of 17th -December. Mo objection. ^ ^ h' f0 2. See corre sjciondence ending m th my letter to India Office i\'o.67 3-3. I lease ask -Jickson verbally L and confidentally from me (a) If he is going to talk oil at Hiyadh with Ibn Saud (b) If so I v/ould be grateful if he could let me know for my confidential information and that of His Majesty's Goveriiment what will be the purport of his conversation. .Bri tconsulI / S6/l and 06/13 i Telegram From To -0.2161 Dated 19th December received 20th Jeoember 1938. Secretary of State for India, London, political xiesident, Bushire. I ersoxial. -'ollowing for Fowle froro Walton. Kuwait • il Jompany have informed us that Dickson has applied for fortnight's leave from December 23rd for a private visit to ibn Saud at latter's invitation. Jompany proposed to grant the application if we saw no objection and after consulting Foreign Office we have informed them that we see none. Secretary of State for India/ 86/1 &amp; 86/13 Tele gram ^ From lolitical -agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. ITo #416. Bated and received the 21st December 1938. IMPORTAKT. Dickson's visit to Saudi king. 'Shaikh today used very strong language about visit which he said was for selfish motives and regardless of embarrassment to him or king. He left it to me to stop it if ? possible. 2. Do you wish me to inform Dickson and Company Shaikh is against visit and leave it to them to decide. POLITICAL./ 86/1 and 86 /i3 Tele gram l^roia jolitical resident, Bushlre. Political Agent, Kuwait. To -v 0.44 5 Jated the 21st December 1938. Important our telegram -o.416 of 21st i)eGeinber You do not say iaj v/hat the Shaikh's reasons are for objecting to visit or (b) whether you asked him and he preferred not to inform 3 /0u or ic) in this case Y ;hether you have any inkling what these reasons are or id) whether you have approached Dickson on ray telegram Bo.432. jxease reply to these points urgently. Company verbally that Shaikh objects strongly to visit and has asked us to stop it if possible. ^ou should also inform Company that pending further reference by you to me 1 would be obliged if Dickson postponed hi departure. You should further explain to the Jompany that the last thing we want to do, in their interests as well as ours, at the present juncture (recent crisis re Council} is to irritate the Shaikh. 2 In the meantime please inform the i3ri tconsulTelegram ^ From Political Agent, Kuwait. P 0 1itical Resident, Bushire. Ho.422 Dated and received 22nd December 1938. importaitt \&gt; Your telegram No.445 of December 21st. (a) and (b) Shaikh only gave reasGn (s) b 6 1&gt; mentioned.' / (c) Ho. He only said Dickson talked too much and indiscreetly, and had already first mentioned matter to him in full public audience, also that there was no reason except personal profit for it so why sanction it. (d) Ho. Political'6&gt; 86/1 Telegram i. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No«448 Dated 22nd December 1938. Important* 1 Your telegram io. 422 of 22nd December. 2, Please take action on (d) immediately and telegraph Dickson's reaction and why you have delay- -ed taking action. Please also telegraph CSompany s reaction on messade in paragraph 2 of my telegram Ho. 445. Britconsul66/1 and 86/13 3 olitical -igent, Kuv/ait. iolitiGal xtesiaeiit, iiushire. Tele ^rarn ]?rorf} To -■ o • 4 23 .Dated and received 23rd December 1938. Immediate Your telegram 1^0.446 of December 22nd. Dickson can give no reason for Shaikhs attitude. I took action absolutely immediately on receipt of your views. 2. Jompany has decided best to cancel journey and has told Dickson ^dates had not been fixed vdth King owin^ to latter 1 s desert tour). t oli tical86/1 -jelegraia S# j^ om political Resident, Bushire. rj* 0 Secretary of state for India, I/^ndon. j[o. 450« Dated tJie 24th December 19S3, pers onal• j 5*owle to Walt on• Your telegram lTo.2161 of 19th December. 9. previous to the receipt of your telegram Political Agent Kuwait had already wired me re; Dickson's visit. I replied no objection, political Agent then however telegraphed that Shaikh objected very strongly to visit on grounds .vhicn Shaikh would not make clear and had asked us to stop it if possible. i 5. I wired Political Agent to inform Kuwait Oil Company of shaikh's attitude and to explain that the present juncture (crisis re: Council) was a bad time, in their interests as well as ours, to irritate the Shaikh. I also instructed policical Agent to inform Company that pending further reierence by him to me I would be obliged by Dickson postponing his departure. 4 # political Agent has now wired that rt Company has decided best to cancel journey and has told Dickson (dates had not been fixed with King owing to latter*s desert tour].* 5 a xt is possible that Company were attempting to double cross the Shaikh by sending Dickson to talk oil with If- p 1 * ^ ^ Ibn Saud (see my le'tter 6*73 of 6th December ) and that it was to this that the Shaikh not unnaturally objected. — -Britconsula ¥.L.ii ^ / / GQ^IFIDEM'IAL , Political Agency, Kuwait, D#0. No. 0- 42. 8th February, 1939. p ; ! nES-DENCY. \ i kj Q CK ^ : 1 /S^/xJiq . ...I / His Highness recently informed me tiiat he had written to the Kuwait Oil Company, at Colonel Dickson's urgent request, alDout an extension of his contract as Chief Local Representative. His Highness said 'I was careful not to recommend it. I said if the Company have need of his services further I have no ohjection'. 2 # Mr. Scott then informed me that he had recommended that Colonel Dickson should 'be kept on until he reached 60. I now hear that Colonel Dickson has received an extension of three years, presumably until FelDruary, 1941. Having in view paragraphs 4 and 5 of the Political Agreement 'between His Majesty^ G-ovemment and the Kuwait Oil Company, it would, I think, have 'been more correct if the Kuwait Oil Company had asked you before renewing Colonel Dickson's contract although the paragraphs do not appear to make it obligatory for the Company to do so. Hon'ble Sir Trenchard Fowle, KCIE., CBS., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bahrain.Slji, Confidential Off lot of the '' oli tical Hcsident iii the i-ergian Mli\ -aiap Bahrain i).0&gt; io* V4l 16th February 1939* I enclose a copy of de ^aury * &amp; letter • 0*42 dated the 8th ebruary 19.39, on the subj ect of the exteneion of Jicksoa*a contract uith the Huwmit til Company until he reaches the a^e of 60 • It mi Jit have been mor® correct, as de '-aury f oints out, if the Jorapany had iiiformed ua of their intention, but under ^aticle 4 of the Kuwait «''il Joaceegion they ax e not obliged to do so, and 1 do not think that any action is called for* I nm Bending a copy of this letter with a copy of ae 'aury* gs letter to retcalfe, and without to de Oaury. • i eel, ^uire, ii• J. The India Office, London* * sent under i-#L# ;/42 of5(1* iu D.O. No. C/2S4 iii e 4' BUSHtP*- RESIPEN GY . Political Agency, Kuwait, 19th May, 1939. Ho... Date. ^C0^FS0£MTiAL RECORDS /U ~i I enclose a copy of a self explanatory letter from Scott to me on the subject of the eraployment in Kuwait Dy the Kuwait Oil Company of a non-British subject n amed de Trairup. De Trairup appears to 'be without nationality, 2- T have discussed the arrival of de Trairup in Kuwait with Scott who fully realises that the necessary preliminaries were overlooked. He expresses willingness to send de Trairup back to Abadan, but states that to do so would hold up the Company's work, already held up for many months through the inaoility, Scott states, of his principals at Abadan to supply a much needed man, 3* In the circumstances I wish to recommend that de Trairup be allowed to remain in Kuwait and be permitted to begin his duties (G-arage Superintendent) at 0n0 J' 1:)e;f,ore ^ consent, if you decide to apply for it, oi His Majesty's Government (vide paragraph 3 of the Political Agreement) is obtained. While conveying your provisional consent I could ask Scott to obtain confirmation of de Trairup's character. 4. Napier might, I suggest, be reminded that he should not give visas for Kuwait to non-British subjects without prior reference to me. The present No T- Zin/SfS/W ^ ''filb') £ St/e* ■ i ' i Hon'tie Sir Trenchard ?owle, KCIE., CBE., Political Resident in the Persian Gul'f,V &gt;2- $ i situation is iDrougiit upon us, not only 'by the Oil Company 's non-observance of preliminaries, 'but also through an oversight of one of our own officials. V k 1 1Copy of letter No. 5570, date! the 14th May, 1939, from the Kuwait Oil Company, Limited, to H.B.M's Politieal Agent, Kir/ait. w ¥e have the honour to report that a Mr.E.L. De Trairuj arrived in Kuwait yesterday per slow mail steamer s.s, Barala ex: Khorramshahi\ 1 i| 1. This gentleman is a member of* the staff of the Anglo- Iranian Oil Co. Ltd and has l^een sent to Kuwait to fill an outstanding indent on that Company for a Transport Officer for service with the Kuwait Oil Company Limited, Unfortunately we were not notified of Mr. de Trairup*£ impending arrival until the time of arrival of the mail steamer, when a telegram advising us of his departure was received via 'Basra. ^len Mr. de Trairup was met 'by our staff Eepresentar tive it transpired that he is not a British subject and that he is travelling under the authority of a Certificate of Identity issued 'by the Home Office and a Travel Permit to Kuwait signed 'by H.B/.T's Consul, Khorramshahr, &gt; / 2. Under article 3 of the Company Government Agreement Y it is laid down that the consent of His Majesty's Government must 'be obtained for the employment of staff who are not either British subjects or subjects of the Shaikh. 3. Owing to the unfortunate circumstances detailed in para 1 a'bove, we have not hitherto had an opportunity of complying with the ahove quoted article and we now wish to make formal application for the consent of His Majesty's G-overnment to the employment of Mr, de Trairup in the capa city of Transport Officer. After 4 years experience in this capacity in the .Anglo-Iranian Oil Co. Ltd, he should 'be excellently suited to our requirements in this respect, 4, We understand that Mr, de Trairup had an English mother, and Danish father, that he was 'born in Berlin on 14-4-1911, and the family moved to England in 1912, subsequer tly he has resided in England continuously until tios he joined the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co, Ltd in 1935, when he was sent for service in Iran. He is now negotiating for naturalization as a British subject and we attach hereto detailed particulars that he has given to us, in respect of his parentage and his appli cation for naturalization, 81Binar Leonard de Trairup. Born In 14/4/1!• Berlin Father Nationality Mother Nationality Baron Martin Krister sin de '^rairup Danish Smmeline Faulkner Brown Br iti s h Present address of parents: 19, Grosvenor Place, London, Home address of E .L. de Trairup: 416, Cannock Hoad, Fallings Park, WoIve rhamp ton * Oc cupa ti on Ihgine er• E # L» de Trairup came to England in 1912 with his parents and remained there till 1935 when he went to Iran as an employee of ^he A.I.O .C, -after being educated at St. John's, Dulwich and South Stafford Technical Colitege he was employed by Guys Motors Ltd. Wolverhampton for about 7 years during which pericud he was in receipt of a salary# He has been employed by A. I»0»C a| Iran sine© 1935 on agreemeait. for British Naturalization in October/No venfcer 1938 when ojj leave from Hie A»I»0»C» Iran and completed and sisned naturalization papers sponsored by the following:** (l) Brig. General Sir Edward Bellinghan, D.S.O., G .M .G^, Lord Lieutenant of lough Castle Bellingham lough and at 22 Grosvenor Square, London. (z) Major J.Westwood-Henderson 2, Landsdown Crescent London (3) L «R* Perkins, Esqr., Chief Engineer of Lucas Ltd., Birmingham. (4) Various Wolverhampton friends. No, reaction to the signing of the papers has yet been received. He applied to the following firm of london Soli ci tor s:-* Merriman White &amp; Co., 3 Kings Bench Walk, Inner Temple, London.'6 ilT»» , He was told that British Naturalization would be applied 6 months after application without difficulty# Solicitors have been written to today to advise developments as the period has almost elapsed, E.L, de 'Creirup held a Danish passport till 1935 when as a result of acceptance of employment abroad with the AoI.O.C# it was cancelled by the Danish authorities in London whilst applying for its renewal to travel* Reason given was that having been resident in Great Britain since 1912 he was aje* no longer a subject of Denmark# He then applied to the Home Office and wes granted a Certificate of Identity (valid for one year) to allow him to travel abroad^ This was renewed for one year in 1938 for his return journey to Iran* The foregoing particulars were given verbally to A.R.G» Harvey, Kuwait Oil Company, by de Trairup on 14th May 1939. flOtfSt: fins air 'IiXi (I'miol, 5e\ r 0iq® 3:' • SflM &amp;. (pis nse'f qe «H km j gofl 9V2J1 • noijflsi: »o Ml* 'f- 1 f\ 0 no^ 5 ''cL| QUI Confidential GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). This is an OSIQINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communitaiion more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to ie treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to ohviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It i» authenticeded hy the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department,] Office af the Political Resident No. 3/201 To . -•ep «at9d Dated in the Persian Gulf. _ the i'&lt; 22nd May 39* Hia Majeaty'a Secretary of State for India, London* The -teeretary to the GoTernraent of India in the External Affaire department, Simla* Political Agent, Kuwait* Reference Subject : Employment of Mr* de Trairup by the Kuwait Oil Company* I encloae herewith copy of letter Mo*C/234 of 19th Uay 1939 with enclosure from Political Agent, Kuwait* 2. With reference to paragraph 3 of Political Agent'* letter, 1 hare concurred in hia proposal pending final decision of His Majesty's Government* 3* In the circumatancea I recommend that ^lr* de Irairup be permitted to continue in the employment of the Kuwait Oil Company In Kuwait* ^d• r.a* -Po ..L'.ii Political Heaident in the Persian Ooif. Attested for secretary to the Political esident in the Persian $ulf* l&gt;/ S. 44. mfp—985 s&amp;p—(m-1597)—27 11-36—10.000. (Signature) (Pesignaiim)■ ICONFIDENTIAL. No. 334 b' reoid~ncy' Date... 'a-K|^ ^c oanoea bal records The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon ? ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the underjnentionCd d0Cfttment(4. for info me ti on. ■ il, I POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 5 th. June, 1939 Reference to previous correspondence: Kuwait D.O. letter No.C/254 of 19th May, 1939» DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-offioial letter dated 24th May, f 2 from Mr. L. D. Scott, General Supnerin- tendent Kuwait Oil Company, Limited, Kuwait, to Major A. C. Galloway, Political Agent, Kuwait. / 9 Employment of Mr. de Trairup by the Kuwait On Company«KUWAIT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. Kuwait♦ Reference No. D/0. S4th A'iay, 1939, My dear Major Gallov/ay, Thank you for your D.O. letter No,238 of 23rd May, 1939, in this connection I wish to assure you of Mp# de Trairup^ good character througout his four years service in Iran, 3s shown by his record of service with Messrs* Anglo Iranian Oil Company Ltd., His application papers for employment with Messrs, Anglo Iranian Oil Co. Ltd., also attest to his good character prior to his emplojTnent by that Company® Yours sincerely, (Sgd) # L. D. Scott* 0. Galloway, M's Political Agent, igmir./ » W i aonfidential The Residenoy, Buahire, the 19th June 1959 A non British subject named de Trairup recently arrived at Kuwait tov employment under the Kuwait Oil Company holding a visa for Kuwait from you given without prevloue reference to the PoXltloaX -^ent, Kuwait. Under tlie paeeport regulations however# Oonssuie, before giving viaae to foreigners i*e« non British aubjects, for any of the Arab States of the Persian Gulf ehould make previous reference to the Political Agent concerned. Xn the present instance no particular harm resulted as X have allowed de Trairup to stay on in Kuwait* but please mice previous reference in such oases in future* * I am sending a copy of this letter to Galloway, r/c- Tt isotf- 3 '' - tain A. Kapler t X.A* His lla4esty f s fice-Consul, Khorraiashahr * * sent under P,I».Ko«b8i- &gt; of 19/6/39 (j)' } v7471 Wt 23481/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, Political DEPi u EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). BUSHSP.E RESI DENCY. m 7 ^ COwrJDtMTlAL RECORDS CN.B. J his is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Political Agent, Koweit. Dated -7th June, 19 39, No. P.Z. 3523/39 Reference your express letter of the 22nd May, - It.-jo No. C/201 # de Trairup. Please send copy of enclosure to political Agent's letter of the 19th May, D .O. No» C/254, which has not 'been received here. jS • I^Ur The issue of the ahove has 'been authorised.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 5o4_S qifi , rrs &lt;, ! \ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to * 1, His lifiajesty's Secretary of State for India, India Office, London, 2. The Secretary to the Government of India, JEocternal Affairs kepartmeut, Simla, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). 2. The omission is resetted • e /&lt; c JojV' British Oonsulate-General 5 BTJSHIRE. Dated .21s t • June. . Reference to previous correspondence : ^ ^ To 1 only # India Of lice .express ^etter $o#F.Z.3523/3ky datM the 7th June Description of Enclosure. Name and Date 14 Enclosure /to Political Agent, iUiwait^ letter Ko. C/234 of l^th May 193^, referred to in Residency express Letter l»o#0/201 dated the 22nd alay 1^39, Subject. iijirployment of ^dr.de Trairup by the Kuwait Oil Oou^aiy, If '471 Wt 23481/P 215 £000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, Depautm ent. i 'O EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B. This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to bo tieated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State, To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Repeated to Political Agent, Koweit, Government of India, External Affairs Dept- 15th June, 1939 P.Z.3631/39 BUSH1RE RESIDENCY. h'o f./.f. Date.-lMHW CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS Please see enclosed copy of correspondence with Kuwait Oil Company regarding provisional arrangements for medical facilities for Company's non-Asiatic staff in Koweit• Please let me know as soon as possible whether you see any o'bjection to recruitment of American nurse for service in Koweit as proposed 'by the Company• I Issue of the ahove message has 'been duly authorised^ i ^11 .z.3531/39. 3&gt; KUWAIT OIL COKPAHY, LIMITSD J.P. GilDSon, Esq. , India Offices \/hitehall, S .W .I. Britannic House ? Pinsloury Circus? London, S-C.2. 9th June, 1939 Dear Giloson, The question of medical and hosx^ital facilities for European and American Staff of the Company in Kuwait has lately 'been under consideration. we rely? at present? upon the American Mission 'but their o'tajects do not, of course? comprise the supply of such facilities as we shall presumably need in the near future, if the numbers of staff in Kuwait continue to increase. It is probable, therefore? that in about two years' time we shall have to construct our own hospital together with docotor's and nurses' quarters at some suitable place near Kuwait town. At present? ho ..ever, the minimum which could be done in this way would be considerably in excess of our needs, so that the medical staff whom we would have to engage would? to a large extent, be unoccupied. Our general superintendent in Kuwait has discussed the matter with Dr. Mylrea of the American Mission and it has been suggested that vjo should temporarily convert a convenient house, which we already renti into a hospital - ^'I*iw»V^K/v'yxnivvowjpixrI'V»Wfc* 3 * nnriMwuij.n^mr r-- - for our employees. The Mission would continue to provide medical services and? in order to handle the extra work, it is proposed that another nurse should be engaged in the United Stated for service in Kuwait. The nurse would give/IS 2 6 give us whole-time duty whenever required but would otherwise be available for work in the Mission's women's Hospital. We hope to proceed on these linos and to arrange for the nurse to arrive in Kuwait at the end of September. I find it difficult to decide whether she will be an employee of the Mission or of the Company. In either case, the Company will no doubt approach H.M.Government for permission, for the nurse to go to Kuwait and for a passport visa. Would you kindly let me know if, in the circumstances, the India Office would facilitate our obtaining-these in either of the possible conditions of employment. Yours sincerely, (Sd) H. Kemp m3531/39 INDIA OPPICBj ..HIT.EI1ALL, 3 .V /.1. 15th June, 1939 Dear Kemp, Thank you for your letter of the 9th June ah out your plans for the provision of medical facilities in Kov/eit for the non-Asiatic staff of your Company. Prima facie we see no oojection to the interim proposal for the engagement of another American nurse? hut ue should wish to consult the local authorities before giving you a definite reply* We are writing at once to the Gulf and I hope to let you have a firm answer shortly. Yours sincerely, (SltdA J ' CII»SOW j?, Esq., 'ait Oil Company ,Limited, Britannic House, Pinsbury Circus, E.C.2.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. . - ' &lt;1 Department. Confidential EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form, of a telegram. It »« authenticated hy the signature of a responsible officer of the Department^ No, 612 -3 Bushire, Bated 7th July i9 39 To Repeated His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. The Secretary to the Government of India in the i&amp;ternal Affairs Department, Simla* Political Agent, Kuwait* \ Reference my Subject : Provisional arrangements for medical facilities for the non-Asiatic staff of the Kuwait Oil Company in Kuwait. Reference India Office Kxpress Letter JSOtP^Z.3631/39 dated the 15th June 1939, with enclosures- 2» I see no objection to the recruitment of an American nurse as proposed by the Company# Sd. T.C.FOlLa Political Resident,in the Persian Gulf, Attested for Secretiafcy to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* }) (Signature) , (Designation) S. 44. o».p _#1Ur oalas sit * isBy Air Mail rz. mx Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.?&gt; 882/39 KU\/AIT Oil, CCKPASY LIMITED, Britannic House? P i n s T j ury G i r cus ? London, E.G.20 21st June s 1939 J.C.Walton5 Sscj.., India Office, 'Whitehall ? 3 « l' i O 1 a Dear Melton, Ihe Shaikh of Kuwait has addressed an enquiry to Directors through Major Holmes as to the Company's intentions regarding a declaration that petroleum has been found in commercial quantities and I enclose for your confidential perusal a copy of a letter which it is proposed to send to Holmes on the matter. As you doubtless know, our relations with the Shaikh have always been extremely cordial and the Board are anxious to do everything they can to maintain that happy sbaoe Oi. affairs. They would like, therefore, to satisfy the Sheikh by making the declaration as soon as, and if5 ijt i s justified by the results of Burgan, No. 3 well. They have, however, to consider the incidence of Clause 10 of the agreement between H.M.Government and the Company which requires the latter, when it is satisfied that commercial production is assured, to examine with H.L.G* the qaeotion of establishing a refinery in Kuwait. The establishment of a refinery, as you know, involves very large capital expenditure which coulo. only be made if the Company were assured that oil could be produced in Kuwait in large quantities over a long period of years. The two present wells and the third which is being drilled and which it is hoped to bring in shortly could/5 2. could not 'by any means provide such assurance. Moreover, the erection of a refinery in Kuwait has of course to be justified by corameidal conditions quite separate from the volume of production in Kuwait and the anticipated longevity of the field. In the Board's view, the 'commercial quantities 5 ' of the Concession agreement and the 'commercial production' and 'commercial conditions' of the Company/Government agreement ought to be considered independently. If, therefore, they were shortly to make a declaration under the Concession, they would not expect any question under Clause 10 of the Company/ Government agreement to he raised by H.M» Government. iifter you have had an opportunity of refreshing your memory on the various points raised by this letter, I should be glad to hear from you. Y our s sincerely, (Sgd, ) H. KEMP.a* . W4 COPY OF DRAFT LEi'J TI-l vQ IL^d OIMjQLLgS. Major P. Holmes, Mill Hill, Sandon, Chelmsford, ESSEX. V Dear Major Holmes, / '/ith reference to His Highness' letter to you dated 24th May, I am instructed by Directors to request you to transmit the following observations to His Highness. At all times since the discovery of oil in Kuwait at Burgan No. 1 well, Directors have been mindful of the provisions of the Concession agreement relating to the declaration that oil has been found in commercial quantities and were anxious to make this declaration as soon as it was justified by the information obtained from drilling. As you are aware, Burgan No. 1 well was regarded as complete when it had penetrated only 18 feet into the oil reservoir. This action was taken on the sound principle of not jeopardising a discovery well by further deepening at a time when reservoir conditions are virtually unknown. Burgan No. 2 veil was then drilled and, having struck oil, was carried to a considerably greater depth than No.l. In order to obtain information on reservoir conditions, a petroleum engineering examination was made promptly after the discovery of oil in No. 2. Unfortunately, the examination did not provide the data which it had been hoped to obtain 'because the shales above the oil horizon in No. 2 well caved in and prevented tests being made in that well. In many respects, the information provided by the examination of No. 1 well was satisfactory but it was found that, after the well had been flowed and then closed in, recovering in bottom hole pressure was very slow. This fact/Q fact v/ ill pro'bal3ly have a considerable influence on methods of production from the Burgan reservoir and if it is confirmed 'by ooservation at other wells it may 'be necessarv to drill a much greater number of v/ells than are necessarv in regions which are not characterised 'by slow recovery of pressure. Witn these 1 actors in mind^ 'but realising that His Highness would doubtless wish a declaration to 'be made as soon as possible? Directors had agreed to reconsider the question immediately information from No. 3 well 'became available. This well is now drilling in the cap rock. 11 inch casing will shortly 'be set and the well will then be crilled into and through the reservoir. If oil is found in this well also, casing will be set throughout the oil sands which will be tested from the bottom upwards by gun perforation. Directors are satisfied that this procedure is the best that can be adopted for the development of the oil resources of His Highness' territory. Directors wish me to stress that the procedure for ■ irm ■ ■ No. 3 well outlined above will be carried out with all expedition. It is their great hope that the results of the drilling and examination of the well, taken in conjunction withjnfformation already obtained, will enable them to make a declaration that oil has been found in commercial quantities in the near future. Yours sincerely,SCjl Confidential The Raaidmwy, j m v.8o*6$6~di Buahire, the lath July 19^. '^0 Could you pleaae refer to the enoloauree to India Office Printed setter Mo.P.i;, 3882» da tea the 27th June 1959# on the subject of the Kuwait Uil Uo^uny making a declaration that petroleum has been found in comaercial quantities* 2* In this connection please see paragraph 2 of my ^ SGjxi t h.nu letter ^o«&amp;9d«*^»f dated the 4rd July 1959§ (not sent to Kuwait)* The Jhaikh of Kuwait has evidently been getting rather impatient and, personally, I am not very much surprised. It is obvious that if itie Majesty # s Government press the question of a refinery this will further induce the Company to delay declaring production in oomaeroially exploitable quantities* # X am sending copies of this letter to Metcalfe and Galloway* , '■ -A. «el, iaq., C.B.4., M.C. tb* India Office, tiffiaaSB- * sent under P.L.Ho.637-3 of 12/7/39 vv;(c \ \ U GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR, MAIL). Ldential . This is an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communicalion more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, m receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime arid to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department!] Polltieal Agency, Kuwait• 0/288 No. To Dated S 'lVlltT New-Ddhi the 27th July, Politioal Hesilent in the Persian Gulf, Eushire. Subject : - Bandar Shuwaikh site. &gt; if-' I yv Reference memorandum No. 123-S, dated the 23rd January, 1937. 2. I enclose a copy of a letter I have received from Scott from which you will see that the Kuwait Oil Company, Limited, are now going to start 'building the proposed jetty, actually a i ^ in a'bout a fortnight's time. 4 p- L' 1 ' ^ 3. Basing my remark on India Office telegram No. 221 of 22nd January, 1937, I said that there seemed no impediment from our point of view to the work 'being taken in hand. // r 2_ Political Agent, Kuwait. [Signature) s. 44. MFP—1534 S&amp; P—(M.2835 )_24-o-38— 10,000. (Designation)••to- 3 * Hi ! . ,H*.; WRi^ - iBOWil KUWAIT OIL COIvIPANY, LU^ITBD. No, 5958 i.tkv ; H.M's Political Agent, Kuwait. KUWAIT ARABIA. 27tii July, 1939. ■ linoKfi 'Si ) 6 98010081 i III? UOV , lfi&lt;t8 Oit %sl.. r ,^1 ? v- ot welv !o i Sir, We have the honour to confirm the conversation 'between yourself and the undersigned on 27.7.39 in which the writer informed you that the Kuwait Oil Co. Ltd proposed to erect a jetty on the foreshore at Shuwaikh on the sea frontage granted to the Kuwait Oil Co. Ltd 'by His Highness the Shaikh. The site chosen for this jetty is at a point on the shore line 850 ft. N.E of the building known as the Shaikh's coal shed, marked on the Admiralty Chart, 1213, Persian Gulf, Port of Kuwait. The proposed jetty will 'be 540* long in all, 16 ft. wide, with an L head 40 ft long. The seaward end- of the jetty will 'be situated approximately 100* 'beyond low water spring tide mark. The shore end of the jetty for a length of ^00* will 'be constructed of concrete and the remainder will 'be of steel pile construction. At various times the site has 'been indicated on the ground to 'both yourself and the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. We now wish to commence work on this j etty in the immediate future and advise you of the fact in connection with Article 8 of the Company/Government Agreement. / i ^ ■ '' / £ fm f. u ■&gt; We have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your obedient servants, Sd. L.D. Scott, for Kuwait Oil Company Ltd. 9'3/ B y Air Mail. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, (/ 3V Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to bv^-- Mail. 3681 Tilt) Fuiu^n CiiM'ntnrFj ( JnrprnTnnnt nt mrln The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.p.Z,4424/59 . •p ^ qo/tr Petroleum Department, P.D.9e./j. (Mines Department) Dean Stanley street ^ Millbankj London; S.W.I. 17th July 5 1939. ^ n 0 * Your leuuer, P,Z.6882/39j of 29th June about the Dear Peel^ iA - Koweit Oil Company and the question of the commercial -A production of oil. ^ ^t- yho 1 I noce from your letter and the enclosure to printed letter P.Z.4061/39 of 3rd July that the Company have decided to make a declaration to the Sheikh at an earlv ^ b t ' dace in connection v/ith Article 3(b) of the Commercial Agreement that 'petroleum has been found in commercial quantities'. I do not think that we can possibly maintain that the making of this declaration involves the raising of the question of the erection of a refinery which is dealt v/ith m Article 10 of the Political Agreement. It is true that under that Agreement the Company agree to examine with H.M.G. the question of establishing a refinery if and when they are 'satisfied that commercial production is assured'. But under the Article the Company only declare their intention to erect a refinery 'should they consider that commercial conditions justify it'. The drilling of three wells 5 which is all that has taken place so far, represents in effect only a very early stage of the development of the field and it may be some time before the refinery question becomes a live issue. I think it is arguable that the Company's declaration under the Commercial Agreement is a trifle premature but I do not feel that justifies us in raising the refinery question. 4. In the circumstances I suggest that you might inform Mr. Kemp that we do not propose to raise the refinery question ^t this stage although we attach considerable importance to it Esq, 5 'C.B.I., M.C. , India Office, King Charles Street, S^.7.1. ' and/By Air Mail. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, /m ::j i '' js | Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been seat to 1 b y^ Mail - Tlie -F^oign Soorotary, GovcynnimL ul ludift. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf- 3681 'V,INDIA OPFICiil, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. P*Z. 4118/39 iSir ? 6th July, 19R9. AO Wi ch erence to the enclosed copy of correspondence xrorn tlie Political Resident in tlie Persian Gulf regarding the employment of Mr. E.L. de Trairup in Koweit ? I am directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to enquire whether the statement tha Ivir. de Trairup has applied for naturalisation on the 'basis of the particulars given in the correspondence can he confirmed. I am, Sir ? Your obedient Servant ? (Sd) J.P. Gibson. nder Secretary of State .ome Office, S.W.I.T. 1489/2. . 4504/39 HOME QFPICiS, vi/HI T^ilALL 5 80th July, 1939. / / o * Sir 3 With reference to India Office letter (P.Z. 4118/39) of the 6th instant covering a c .g a copy of correspondence irom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf regarding Mr. Einar Leonard de Trairupj I am directed by Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to say, for the information of the Marquess of Zetland that Mr. de Trairup applied for naturalization on the 7th November, 1938 ? and that consideration of the application is postponed until he returns to this country. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd) J.I. Wall. Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office.\ )4/39 INDIA OFFICE, UHITEIL \LL, S.W.I. 27th July 1939 / Dear Eyres, with rp^rence to correspondence resting with my letter to the Homo Office y P.Z4 4118/39 dated 6th July 1939, (copy sent to you on the 7th July) regarding the employment of Mr. E.L. de Trairup hy the Koweit Oil Company, I enclose a copy of the Home Office reply which states that do Trairup has applied for naturalization hut that his application will not 'be considered until his return to this country. Do Trairup thoreforo seems still to 'be without nationality and it is necessary to consider his position with relation to paragraph 3 of the Koweit Political Agreement In-all the circumstances, and as he appears to he essential to the efficient working of the company^ '^0 (vide enclosure to the Political Resident's Express Letter dated 22nd May, copy circulated with India Office letter of the 9th June, No. P.Z.3523/39) it is felt that no ohjection need he raised to his continued employment 'by 3, Esq.. , gn Office, the/ S.W.I.2. tho Kowcit Oil Company in Koweit. \yould you please lot me know if you agree? I am writing similarly to Giffard at the Petroleum Department. Yours sincerely, ,3 4d.) a. K ai* 1 ■ cty * ifftj S' GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. sBCtasT. Department. ^ /'-m, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). rjj 3, Thin is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communieation more expeditious than the ordinary moil and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] of the Political KeBident ill No. To the Persian viuif, Oarflp, Shiraz. 0/336 of ihp 19 12th August, i?y 39: His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London* Repeated - f i n he Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. The Air Officer Commanding, British forces in Iraq, Habbaniya. - - - ■ - - - • ' ^ your The Jolitioal Agent, Kuwait. 'my Subject a Bandar Shuwaikh site. I enclose herewith oopy of a letter iio.C/288, dated the z&lt; -h July 1939, and of its enclosure, from the Political Kuwait. 2. Far from their being any ohjection from our point of view to the construction of the jetty, it will he of considerable advantat? for Defence purposes as it will enable the speedy disembarlcation of mechanieed forces in case of emergency (see paragraph (e) of Aote / the Chief of the General Staff in India, enclosed with External Affairs Department Express Letter 0^.2016-^/39, dated the lit! July 1939}• jtter ;o oD»2016-iy 39, s wW'' r sd• T• G« Attested. iFowle • Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. d{c 12 -S -3 ? for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* {Signature) (Designation)By Air Mail. px^ieVi uiJlj emj; No. , 0 r- pr Mi^V 77tx . J..~o J INDIA LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political (..vty.- ■ &lt;- V Department, India Office. A copy has been seat to JL-jLL*. i by Mail. 3681 v. \ St ThTT-F rrrm^'ii Oeei'efoiry; Indian The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Major F. Holmes 9 Millhillj Sandon 9 Essex. Dear Major Holies, You will remember that on 25th April you asked me to consult Directors on the question of the acquisition 'by the Company from H.H. the Shaikh of Kuwait of rights over an area covered 'by the sea which you had indicated on a copy of chart No. 2837B. As you are aware ? the Company's Concession agreement gives it the exclusive right to explore, search, drill for, produce and will petroleum within the State of Kuwait, including all islands and territorial waters appertaining thereto. The phrase 'territorial waters' was deemed to include all submarine areas over which His Highness has authority in any form, and, therefore, all areas over which His Highness could grant rights to any party. The intention, therefore, of the concessionary provision - in the opinion of Directors and doubtless also in that of His Highness - was to give the Company the above exclusive right over all areas which lay within the gift of His Highness. Directors v/ould be glad if you would convey this expression of views to His Highness, and would be pleased to learn His Highness's further opinions on the matters concerned. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) H.T. Kemp. 6th July, 1939.rilLLHiLL; SANDOiT ? GHELLISPORD. 10th July 3 1939. I.T. Kemp s Esq. s imia.it Oil Go. Ltd. j, Britannic House, E.G.2. A i I Dear Mr. Kemp: I have to thank you for your letter dated 6th July, 1939, It appears to me that some confusion has arisen in respect of the status of the area which I indicated to you on the copv of the Chart No. 2837.B. Before commenting on your letter, I would like to make it clear that His Highness has always been most anxious that the terms and rights granted in the Kuwait Oil Concession be honoured meticulously both in letter and spirit and has impressed upon me that nothing should occur to disturb the pleasant relations that have always existed between His Highness and the Company. The Area which I pointed out on the Chart mentioned above does not include any portion of the 'Territorial Waters' of either the Mainland or the Islands belonging to the State of Kuwait, The whole of this area is situated outside the limit of 3.45 statute miles (3 nautical miles) from high water mark which distance (3,45 miles) is the Internationally recognised limit of 'Territorial waters'. In other words the area under discussion is 'International Waters' and His Highness is fully aware that such is the Status of the Area. His Highness has made no move, either officially or otherwise in respect of the area in question, except to make a private enquiry, through me, from your Company as to whether your Board would be interested in such an area. The position in respect of 'International '7aters' situated opposite to Territory adjacent to the Arabian Coast,^ - but excluding that opposite to Kuwait - has changed considerably of recent months, I understand that a large area, the greater portion of which is International Waters, has been offered to an American Oil Company by His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrein. This action in respect of 'International Waters' may draw the attention of other Rulers along the Arabian Coast and naturally they may wish to protect, as far as possible, oil rights over International Waters lying adjacent to their respective Territories and may possibly do so on the same lines as Bahrein. I am sending a copy of this letter to His Highness by the same mail that takes to him your letter of the 6th July. Yours sincerely. (Sgd,) PRANK HOLMES.P.Z.4603/39. J. P. Gibsorij Esq., India Office 9 Whitehall, s.w.i. WAIT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED Britannic House, Pinsbury Circus, London, E.G.2. 25th July, 1939. Dear Gihson, With reference to our conversation on 19th July, the following is the resume of the subject which Walton asked me to send for consideration. On 25th April, 1939, Major Prank Holmes, the London Representative of H.H. the Shaikh of Kuwait with the Kuwait Oil Company, called on me and proposed that the Company should acquire from H.H. an oil concession covering an area lying beyond the territorial v/aters of lit — Kuwait and bounded by a line which he indicated on a chart. I am forwarding under separate cover two copies of a photostat showing the area concerned. Major Holmes'.proposal was considered by Directors, ^ $tx ?? and I wrote to him on 6th July and received a further letter from him dated 10th July. Copies of these letters are enclosed. We should be obliged if His Majesty's Government would give us a ruling on the following points (a) what exclusive and non-exclusive rights has H.H. the power to grant in the form of an oil concession over the area indicated. (b) if such rights can be granted, would H.M. Government have any objection to negotiations for, and conclusion of, a Concession agreement between H.H. and the Company. Yours,, etc. (Sd. ) H.T.Kemp.id v 1503/39. Kuwait Oil Company, Limited; J.P.Gibson ? E sq., India Office P Whitehall s S.W.1, Britannic House, Finsbury Circus, London, E.G.2. 85th July, 1939. jof Dear Gilo son. Farther to rny letter of today's date, I think it might oe useful if, in the course of the present inquiry, you could give us a ruling on the extent of Kuwait territorial waters. I presume that for the most part the limit of territorial waters lies three nautical miles from low water mark around the mainland and around all islands appertaining to Kuwait. With regard to Kuwait Bay, as this is virtually a land-locked harbour, having all its shores within Kuwait territory, I imagine that the limit of territorial waters in this region would not lie closer inshore than three nautical miles beyind a line joining the two headlands at the entrance to the Bay. I can, however, find no clear ruling on this issue in the available text books. Yours &amp;c. (Sd.) H.T.Kemp.P.Z.4603/39. INDIA OFFICE; WHITEHALLj S.W.I. 2nd August 9 193 Dear Baggallay th h I enclose a copy of two letters from Kemp ; of the e. Kuwait Oil Go. 3 arising out of a proposal that the Company should acquire a concession from the Sheikh of Koweit covering an area lying outside Koweit territorial waters., as indicated in the enclosed chart. We should he glad to have your comments on the three questions that are put to us, viz. (a) what exclusive and non-exclusive rights has the Sheikh the power to grant in the form of an oil concession.. over the area indicated? (h) if such rights can he granted, would His Majesty' Government have any ohjection to negotiations for and conclusion of a concession agreement between His Highness and the Company? (c) what is the extent of Koweit territorial waters? 2./ ggallay, Esq. 9 reign Office.2. The problem raised in Question (a) seems similar to those which appealed, in last year's correspondence regarding the definition of the limits of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company's concessional area in Persia (sep in particular - r'ljzty, -'cr.'-y ■ Baxter's demi-official letter to the Company dated the 29th November 1938 5 No.^.7158/201 /34) . According to that correspondence the generally recognised view with regard to areas outside territorial waters is that the sea-bed and the sub-soil beneath it is res nullius , but that it is capable of acquisition by effective occupation in the same manner as any unoccupied territory above the level of the sea. On this basis the Sheikh could presumably be regarded as having only potential rights in such areas and could expect no support from His Majesty's Government in respect of them un U. they had been made actual as the result of effective occupation, and the Company could only negotiate for a concession in respect of such rights as the Sheikh may hereafter acquire in the area which is marked in the chart and is not already covered by the existing concession. But we should be glad of your views as to the reply it would be desirable to send to Kemp on questions (a) and (b). 3. It may be that there is no answer to question (c) that would be universally accepted? but prima facie ; and/[0^ and subject to any information bearing on the point which we may receive from the authorities in the Persian Gulfj it woul. seem reasonable to regard Koweit bay as a territorial inlet. 4. I am sending a similar letter to Jarrett and Starling. Yours sincerely 9British Vice Consulate, Kiiorramshahr Iran, August 10th 1939. . I f*— tL^&gt;~ Jl _ 1 I apologise for the delay in, replying to your _ h - '{■*■ confidential demi-official letter 1^.680-3 dated the 19th June 1939, due to my being away on recess and not having the relevant files with me. As regards giving visas for the Arab States in the Gulf, the practice in the past has been to grant these, without prior reference, to employees of the Anglo Iranian Oil Company Limited. I enclose a ^p copy of the original request of the Anglo Iranian Oil Company Limited dated 10th May, for a visa for Mr. de Trairup. From this I presumed that he was one of their employees and this was confirmed by them in their |0 | letter dated 28th June (copy enclosed). If Mr. de Trairup actually went to Kuwait to obtain employment in the Kuwait Oil Company, Durable ► Col. Sir Trenchard Fowle, K*C*I.£., C•©.E., uical Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.■ ill I [■■■WlllllM 0 1 2. | i I will take up the matter with the Anglo Iranian Oil Company Limited, but I shall be grateful if you will kindly confirm this before I do so. I am sending a copy of this with enclosures to Galloway,Copy of letter dated ICth May 1939, from Messrs the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co., Ltd, Khorramshahr, to His Majesty^ Vice- Consul, Khorramshahr. VERY URGE NT. We have the honour to forward herewith the following passport and shall be obliged if you will kindly do the necessary as stated against each* P.P.Kumber^ Name Visa required Fee Certificate M e .E.L # de Trairup Kuwait No.T1489 permitCopy of letter ^0.610/13/13 dated the 28th June 1939, from Messrs the A.I .0,C»Ltd. ,Khorraii]Shanr to the British Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr• We have the honour to refer to our letter dated the 10th May 1939 applying for a visa for Kuwait for Mr. E.L.De Trairup and to inform you that the said person is an employee of Messrs the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co. Ltd., Abadan and had been sent to Kuwait on duty. CConfidential irk/' I D.O.No.0/387. Office of the Political Resident in the Pereian Gulf, Camp, ShjUiA&amp;. bated the 18th August ' 3 3{, : ^ sm 9 | . ■ a . 35 ^ - &gt;:&gt;. ; ■ ' f'fU'fi' : . . H. Could you please refer to your letter ^o.52B-2/10 dated the 10th August lfc&gt;3b&gt; f on the subject of a certain de Trairup# • .■ : : ■ r ' S. The practice you refer to in your paragraph 2 is contrary to the Passport riegulationa, and should cease. No inconvenience is involved in foreign employees of the Anglo Iranian Oil Company applying to you for visas, and in case of urgency you can always telegraph at their expense. fce insist on prior reference being made to us from home beiore foreign employees of the oil companies operating on the Arab Coast are given visas, and I think it as well to keep up this principle with regard to the Anglo Iranian Oil Gompany also. 3. In view of the above instructions it is immaterial what oil company a foreign applicant may belong to; if he wishes to go to the Arab Coast from your area prior reference to the Political Agent concerned, with a copy of your communication to me, should be made. &lt; ; , ; ■ ' 1 H • I am sending a copy of this letter to Galloway. aptaln A. Napier, I.A., His Majesty's Vice-consul, Khorramshahr. ..i • Y- » sent under' P.i ^.ho.C/368 of le.s.'aa.'llfl u.fr- ^ 'A/ nl ^ r INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to byAHMaU. TjCTW 3681 Tlii^ Fwoi^n Ouu^lavy, The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 'V, rP.Z. 4742/39 P.D. 98/4. PETROLEUM DSPAKiMENT (MINES DEPART CUNT), DIHAK' STAxTLZII STREET ? MILLBANK5 LONDONj S.W.I. 2nd Angust ? 1939. ! S Dear CxilDsonj In reply to your letter of 27th July No. P.Z. 4504/39 regarding the employment of Mr. de Trairup by the Kuwait Oil Co. 9 I write to say that in view of the particulars given in the enclosure to your letter to the Home Office of 6th July No. P.Z. 4118/39s we consider that, notwithstanding the technical difficulty arising out of the wording of paragraph 3 of the Koweit Political Agreement; no objection need be raised to his continued employment by the Kuwait Oil Co. 9 in Koweit, Yours sincerelys, (Sd.) K.P.¥. Gifford. J. P. Gibs on, Esq. ? India Office 9 Whitehall 9 S.W.I. P.S. I an sending a copy of this letter toS requested that in any further cornmuni- , on this subject the under-mentioned letter number may he quoted, and the reply Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, s.tv. 1. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. 12th August, 1959. z. 4846/39. /1/i Xo - £• ^ ) Sir 3 I am directed 'by the Secretary of S&gt;£te for India to refer to your Express Letter No. C/201, of 22nd May, regarding the case of Mr. de Trairup, and to say that in the circumstances His Majesty's Government have no objection to his employment hy the Kuwait Oil Company. It is assumed that he will make every effort to obtain the consideration of his application for naturalisation at as early a date as possible. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, icopjf sent to P.A«KuY/ait under X'.L. 23/8/39)• The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. LCONFIDENTIAL. m \ No. C/395 of 1939. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, at Karachi, if\o and has the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned documents (s). xxxx with the reqL ues t that he may infoim the Kuwait Oil Company of the oonteuts of the India Offioe letter. a $■ British Cor ^ulate-General, BUS HIRE, Dated, 2 3rd Aii gust V 1^9 • IC; &amp; % Gamp, Shi raz• §kfp:. W' \ f tS 1i Reference to previous correspondence: Political Residents Bxpresa Letter No#0/201 of 22nd May 1939* Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject, India Office letter iro*P*2. 4846/39 of the 12th August 1939 • Mr. de Trairup.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. [bushire RESIDENCY. 1 I 1 ! Dm. | CONFIDENTIAL r.SCofes' { EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail nnd is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature tf a responsible officer of the Department,] Political Agsncy, Kuwait, Ttihe iSth September, i&lt;?39. No. ; Bated To The Political Eesident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire at Bahrain. Subject; - Bandar Shuwaikh site. it ^ iU- 1 m • * x / Reference 3 ^ Bushire Express Letter No. C/336 of 12th August, 1939. I was recently talking to Scott on the subject of the new Jetty. It will 'be of interest to know that the jetty is ejected to 'be finished in the spring of next year, provided the arrival of the necessary steel is not unduly delayed. Should the steel 'be held up the stone Quay alone, in extension of which a steel pier is to 'be iDuilt over the sea, will consi' derahly improve landing conditions here. political Agent, Kuwait. (Cop* sent to India Office, Govt.of i. and A.O.C.Iraq under j P.L.H o. C/446 of 21/9/39). ir (Signature) (Designation).... ee/r Telegrais Q,« From Secretary of State for india, London. To Political Resident, at Bahrain. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait# Copy to Government of mdia, by mail. No•2028• Dated and received the 23rd September, 1939# 1. Kuwait Oil Company Limited wish their drilling Superintendent Mr* Thomas JPatrick a U .S.A.citizen to return to Kuwait from the united States ot America on expirty of his leave in the middle of uctober. 2. Bo you see any ohjection to grant of a visa for Kuwait ^ -Secretary of State for india. r .I^Telegram q From Political Resident, at Bahrain. To Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by post Government of India, Simla. Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho.T/267 Dated 't he 24tii September 1939. Your telegram No. 2028 September 23rd. Patrick. ITo objection. Resident G.T. Copy sent under P.L.No.C/461 of 24/9/39 to Govt* of I and Kuwait#IX®IA OFFICE, WjIIT K::Q/ , P.Z.5999/39. 3, ■7.1. 291 n 3 e pt enilo er, 19 39. Dear Kemp. Would you Please refer to your letters of the Si st June and the 30th June on f'-P m■o^ o . 1 ^u.xe Oxt ^..e uuesoion of the production of 011 ln Kowelt ln commercial quantities. it is noted that Major Holmes has been authorised to intimate to the Sheikh the Company's hope that they will he enabled in the near future to make a declaration that oil has been found in commercial quantities. I am desired to say that His Majesty's G-overnment do not propose to raise the refinery question at this stage although they attach considerable importance to it and will, of course5 raise it if and when the oil field develops. i r ours sincere 1 y ? ? Esq.^ Oil Company 3 Box 1 5 •ertsey Road. Sunbury-on-Thames.Telegram Q From Political Resident, at Kuwait. To H.M. Secretary of state for India. London. Copy by post to Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Copy to Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho.T/406, Sated the 23rd October 1939, o Reference Gibson's P.Z.5999/39 of 29th September to Kemp. Shaikh asked me two days ago to press Company to make this declaration as early as possible. Presume I may inform him of contents of above letter ? RESIDSOT. (Copy sent to Govt. of India and P.A.Kuwait under I.L.No.C/623 dated 23.il..7 39.) ill : ih, i » I I t' . L •I ■. / Telegram From To 0 / 1 3 / ' Secretary of State for India, Lond on Political Resident, Externa 1 Affairs Department, New Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. Repeated Uo.2574 Dated and received 26th October 1939. % Your telegram No.T/406 October 23rd* Company have just reported they are informing Shaikh through Holmes and Scott that though unable in present conditions to satisfy themselves that they would be justified in making desired declar ation, they propose nevertheless on December 23rd and annually thereafter to offer Shaikh the sum specified ' 1 in Article (c) of Concession viz. Rs •250,000. :::! 0- 3 ' Secretary of State for India G.T. mConfident! aX» »o«a/67l of 19391 Office of the Political Heeident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuwait• Dated the 7th November, 1939# From - The Hon f ble the Political lieeident in the Persian Gulf To Middle blast Intelligence Centre C airo. Memorandum» The Kuwait Oil Company, who have drilled three welle in Kuwait* are informing the Shaikh of Kuwait that though they are unable in present conditions to satisfy themselves that they would be justified in making the declaration that oil has been found in commercial quantities, they propose nevertheless to pey him from 23rd December (the anniversary of the signature of the concession) and annually thereafter the minimum sum (H8*250t 000/* ) payable under the terms of the concession on the making of such declaration# This action on the part of the Company indicates their confidence in the future of the oil field# sd* G»G # jPrior* Political Hesident in the Pereian Gulf# Attested# for SeOefretary to the Political resident in the Psrsiaa Gulf#Telegram Q, From Politica1 Resident, at Kuwait. To Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by air mail to Government of India, lew Delhi. Copy to Politlca 1 Agent, Kuwait. No.T/485 Dated the 16th November 1939. f.i^ Your telegram No.2674 October 26th. Shaikh has showed me stiff letter he is addressing^oil company in which he objects to their action in delaying declaration and demands minimum payment of four lakhs not provided for ia the agreement. 2. He told me that the American companies were pressing on with drilling whereas Kuwait Oil Company only had one rig working. 3. Action of Kuwait Oil Company will only tend to confirm general opinion in Gulf that American companies are only ones who genuinely desire to exploit their concessions. Since any addition to British controlled supplies of oil is valuable could company be pressed to reconsider decision ? 4. Company can of course obtain ample supplie through their American connections so cannot plead shortage of necessary material. Resident G.T. (Copy sent to Govt •of India. a.nd Kuwait under JP .L.IIo.C/761 of iV/ll/^ 9 )*f GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D epartment. f.jQ . . /CU /)::/ ■h C. i(c* U~ J f, CQW*D2\iTu\\. R£C0^D3 EXPRESS LETTER [N. B .—This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegrophic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be Ireatel on veceipt, with the same expedition as if it had heen telegraphed To save time and formalities it is worded and siyned as if it had been so despatched,] ionfidential. F rom Political Agent, Kuwait. t0 Political Hesident in the Persian G-ulf at Kuwait. S ubj ect: - Kuwait Oil. kl H c/jf7 Duiei letii Noverdter, iM 9. Eeference India Office telegram No. 2574, dated the 26th October, 1939, on the subject of the payment to the Shaikh of Rs, 250,000 in December. 2, Scott informed me yesterday that he had received instruc tions to put up to his Directors schemes for the closing down of Kuwait Oil Company's activities except for the drilling of No, 4 well, and water-drilling this winter, Scott thinks that work will go on normally here until January of next year when, as present supplies of material will then 'be finished, he will fte forced to pay off some of the present staff. s. 6. Political Agent, KuwaitBy Mail. P.Z. ^ i 19 i c 1 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to o b y £ Mail -INDIA OiPICi;, vjHIi'jJHALL, 3. V/. 1. 5951/39 27th Septemloer 3 1939. i'' s Dear Court! I understand that you hsve already loeen jn'formed / 'by telephone that this Office and the Gulf authorities have no objection to the grant of a Kuwait visa to Mr. Thomas E. Patrick, a United otates citizen in the employment of the Kuwait Oil Company? and I write to confirm this. Mr. Patrick is the Kuwait Oil Company t Drilling Guperintendent. He is at present on leave in the U.S.A. and when his leave expires in mid-Octoher the Company wish him to return to Kuwait which he will probably do via the Pacific. Perhaps you would 'be good enough to let the British passport authorities in New York know that there is no objection in this case to tne grant of a visa for Kuwait? Yours sincerely? &gt;urti ce , ^sq.^ M.B.T j. , 'assport Office, ly Queen Anne's Gate Buildings, 3.V/.1.7051/39. No. P.D. 98/2. Part DENTIAL. Dear Peel, petroleum department, (i- ine3 department j , dean stanley street, millbank, s.w.i. 8th November', 1939, Your letter of 26tn Octo'hpr» letter from Kemp regarding the temporary clssatton 8 operations by the Kuwait Oil Company in Koweit. While the cessation of nn-M ir-j it, appear to be unfortunate, it is the'case 0 ??-^ f® 06 0f present there is a surpl-is ni i f? that at of the world, and difficulties over tanke 's^rp tnat . paPt us to restrict purchases for the time being. Ihe^arf so many other directions in which the technical staf?! of tne oil companies can 'be more usefullv ernolovp i that t do not think we have any .round for contesUng t^e ' decision of tne Company, z.ie We will not fail to let you know if circurrwtaaopc? theiTdecieion. COmPany 0U8ht t0 be aSl&lt;:eCl to reo °nsider Eyres. I am sending a copy of this letter to Jarrett and 9 Yours sincerely, F. C. Starling, sel, Esq. , C.B.E. , M.C. , India Office, King Charles Street, s.w. 1,9^/^- Telegram Q,. From Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, at Kuwait. Bopy by mail to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Ne?/ Delhi. Ho.34l9. Dated 16tfe received 17th December 1939. Please give copy to Political Agent. Your telegram No.T/485 November 17th. Kuwait Oil Company. ^ • 2. Kuwait Oil Company propose to send Major Holmes to Kuwait shortly after Christmas in order to explain matters to Shaikh. Please telegraph as soon as possible whether you see any objection. 3. As regards your paragraph 3 please see Petroleum Department's letter of November 8th copy by air mail of November 21st. r : /-f -Secretary of State for India. W .L. Copy given to Political ivgent, Kuwai t.Te leg rem rrcffi Political Resident, st Kuwait. T0 Secretary cf State for Indie. London. Copy by air Bail Government of India, New Delhi. Copy given to Political Agent, Kuwait. Ifo.T/598 Dated the 16th December 1939. HOIiCES. Your telegram i[o.34l9 December 16th» No objection. G.T.KUWAIT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. Chertsey Road P.Z. 6714/39. Surroupy -on-Thame s. 23rd Octo'ber 5 1939. Dear Gibson, In march last, Mr. L.D. Scott attended a conference with the Hohble. the Political Resident and other representatives of H.M. Government at which were discussed the steps to he taken in Kuwait in the event of war. The Political Resident was anxious that our wells should he adequately safeguarded against enemy action, and that we should take particular care against such types of action as those which took place in the region of Bushire during the last war. The Board decided, therefore, that in the event of war any live wells should he mudded off. This procedure is quite usual in oil field practice and is not harmful to the wells, which can he Drought hack to their original condition 'by de-mudding. On the outbreak of war, Wells Nos. 1 and 2 were forthwith mudded off. With regard to Well No.3, the position is that this well has only recently 'been completed and casing has 'been set with its foot in hotuom water. It was the Board's intention, in the ordinary course, oo nave this well tested 'by gun -perforating the casing from the 'bottom upwards. In the present circumstances, however, they feel that it would he inadvisable to do so and that the well itself and the oil resources of Kuwait would he oet^er protected if the v/ell were mudded off and the test postponed. As you are aware, however, it was also the Board s intention to consider making a declaration that oil had 'bee found in commercial quantities when Burgan No. 5 Jell ha he en/ S.W.Il^een tested and if satisfactory results had 'been obtained The Board feel tiiat without this information they will not De in a position co make the declaration. On the other hand ? they are anxious to do everything they reasonably can to prevent H.H. the Shaikh from suffering loss as a result of action necessitated by war. Although they do not regard themselves as justified in prejudging the results of Burgan No. 3 Well 5 they intend on 23rd December next and annually thereafter to offer His Highness the amount to which he would be entitled had tne declaration been madej i.e.&lt;, Royalty of Rupees 250 ? 000 per annum. The Board have also had under consideration the policy to De adopted for the Company's operations in Kuwait in the changed circumstances arising out of the war. Having regard to tne general financial 5 economic and industrial conditions which must prevail during wartime? the Board find it necessary to restrict the Company's activities in Kuwait to the present one-rig programme instead of the two rigs which they had hoped to adopt early in 1940. The Board still intend? however? to proceed with the search for fresh water in Kuwait which they had decided upon before the outbreak of war 5 and will endeavour to supply the equipment? etc. needed for this investigation with the least possible delay. The information contained in this letter has been communicated to Major Holmes and Mr. Scott for submission to Kis Highness. Yours sinc erely ? (Sgd.) H.T.Kemp. 1 ?■ ■ I p.Z, 6714/39. INDIA OPPICE, whitehall ? s.w.i. 26th October5 1939. Dear Starlings I enclose a copy of a letter from Kemp from which you will see that tne Kuwait Oil Company 9 while acting with reasonable generosity to the Sheikh 9 propose to curtail their programme of operations in Koweit. We assume that you will let us know if at any time His Majesty's Government should decide that ? with a view to augmenting the oil resources available to them ? the Company should be pressed to reverse this policy and to accelerate and expand their operations in Koweit. I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Jarrett and Eyres. Yours sincerely ? 3 ! 3 ! I vw ' Starling Esq. 9 C.b.E. troleum Department ? Mines Department, Lean Stanley Street^ M i 1 Ibank &lt;, S.W.I. *N- T. Confidential# / ' .. ■ .0 The Residency, iuehire, the 23rd December, 1939 # l Dear i -eel, o| fi^ ould you pleaee reftr to Starling's letter Ho. t.n. 98/2. . art 2, dated the 8th November 1939, which wae forward ed to us with your air mail Printed Letter Ifo.JP.2,7051/39, dated the 20th November 1939 1 j• ' 1 2# When I was in Bahrain, Weightroan ahowed me the programnj* of deliveries of the Bahrain Oil Company for the next month or two, and drew my attention to the fact that the yast majority of the consignments were sent to Smpire destinations such as India, Burma, Australia, Kew Zealand and South Africa* It appears to Joe, however, from what I have heard of the activities of the ^nglo-Iranian Oil Company, that these are markets which they normally cover themseives and that whatever the value of the Bahrain oil may be to us on a long term view, every ton of oil now sent by them to an iSmpire destination probably means the sale of a ton less by the entirely British Coiapany from Abadan» Could you very kindly ask the Petroleum Department whether this view is correct V As you are aware neither the Bahrain Petroleum Company nor the California Arabian Standard Oil Company have in any wa^ restricted either their output or their development programme * i H.T •l^eel Esquire, M.C., The India Office, London* Yours sincerely, &amp; (X i' kM ,vRUSHiRH RSSlOEWtVri Ko...r^^^ r I/O • D:iP. Xo ■ f- ..&gt;.;/.D€KT^L RHCOr33 1^6 P.Z.7257/39. &gt; Dear Jarrett, CT yl INDIA OFPICE; WHITErlALL, S.W.I. 6th December 5 1939. Yon will have seen the correspondence of a month or so £!% ^ cigO; including otarling's letter of the 8th November (P.D.9S/2 Part 2) regardinr- the slowing down of operations 'by the Koweit Oil Gompany in Koweit. ■ 0 . I v ■ 2. It appears from the enclosed copy of a telegram from __^ he __^ itical Resident (copies of which have already 'been 3d 17th November, 1939.) circulated) that the Sheikh is far from satisfied with the Company's decision, and the Resident invites us to press the Company to reconsider it. For our part we triink that on the financial side the Company have dealt quite fairly with the Sheikh, all things considered, and we had in mind to tell the Hesident that in the light of what Starling said in the above-quoted letter we did not at present see sufficient ground for intervening. Before doing so, however, we should wish to learn whether the Admiralty agree with the Petroleum Department letter, and I should be grateful if you could inform me on this point at a very early date. The Admiralty attitude would seem to depend on (a) The suitability of Koweit oil for naval requirements and ('b), if the oil is suitable, the degree of importance attached by the Admiralty to developing a reserve source of supply at Koweit. I gather that for the determination of (a) it has been suggested that you should obtain a sample of Koweit oil from the Company and have it tested. It would/ G-Jarrett, Esq., Admiralty, S.W.I. COPY SENT TO— islwould seem well worth while to have this done as soon a possible. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Starling and to Eyres. Yours sincerely ? (Sgd.) R. 'HHHHHI P. Z. 3035/39, pi » fo TcT^Z Dire.... ■E RESIDENCY. CO'iFiDCNTJAL RECORtS n /Vwv INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHi\LL, S .W.I. 1st January, 1940, // I enclose a copy of correspondence with the Kuwait Oil L/Oflipariy al^out the proposed visit of Mr. R. 0. Rhoades to Koweit. In view of the responsible position held 'by Rhoades in the Kuwait Oil Company and since we have been unable to find anything in our papers to suggest that Rhoades is in any way an undesirable person, we have, as you will see, assumed that you would concur and have told the Passport Office that there is no objection to the grant of a visa. tie Hon 1 ble Lieut. Col. G.G.Prior, G.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (copy sent to P .A.Kuwait under F .L.No»G/6 of 23/1/40) - L- Q i I IIHTele gram from To No. Dated the Expect arrive Kuwait about 5-30 P,M # Tuesday, -HOLMES- Enclair. - Holmes, Basrah. - Political Agent, Kuwait. - Nil. 21st and received the 2 3rd January, 1940.Confidential. D.O. No. C /114 .1' Political Agency, Kuwait, 18th March, 1940. Will you please refer to your telegram No.T/598 of the 18th December, 1939? 2* I enclose copies of letters and telegrams which have passed 'between His Highness ShaiKh Ahmad and Major Holmes, his London Representative, and also copies of telegrams which have passed between the Kuwait Oil Company Directors in London and the United States, and the two Directors now in Kuwait, Messrs. Jameson and Hhoades. I have copies of these telegrams as I agreed that the means of communication might be between the India Office and myself, since the use of codes is not allowed on Iraqi wires during tte war-time. i 3. The proposal now before the Shaikh is clearly set out in enclosure D, and the Shaikh has informed me that he proposes, on Holmes* advice, to try to establish the figure of Rs. 500,000 and not 8s. 450,000 as the figure over which the Company may deduct instalments of the royalty advance. I understand that the figure is worked out on the basis of a 'unit of production H but regret that I must be vague on the matter as I am not a technical oil-man. 4. His Highness has explained to me that the matter is between him and the Company, but has asked my advice sHon'tle Lleut-Oolonel C.G.Prior, CIE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Kuwait.all along. In fact he has refused to act at all without my advice, which, while 'being somewhat einbarras 1 sing, shows that he is turning to the Political autho rities again with trust, I have given what little advice I had to give as sparingly as possible. ^74 con;. gy dear Major Holmes. Kuwait ^Snd, February 1940, After consideration and consultation with the Political Agent, I have come to the conclusion that in order to avoid any danger of the Concession Agreement terms being brought into auastinr I hare decided to withdraw my request that the Company should increase the amount of the Royalty minimum payment from Rs. 250,000 per annum to Rs.400,000 per annum, ' ouuum if 4. ^ i now w^kdraw that suggestion and replace it with the request that the Company should make me an advance against future Royalty. In making this proposal, I feel that you will agree with me that I am within rights in requesting additional financial help-from the Company- seeing that I had been led to hope that a declaration of the discovery of oil in commercial quantities would be made during the late months of 1939 • If such declaration had been made the increased development activities which-in the ordinary course- the* Company would have undertaken, thereby giving my work-people the opportunity of work and hastening the day that regular production of oil would eventuate. I request that I may ask for an extension- to be agreed upon between the Company and myself,-after the expiry of the period of the first five years, if the production of oil-at that time- has not reached the stage where the yearly revenue in the form of Royalty does not equal the minimum Royalty of Rs^SO^OOO plus the yearly advance against Royalty of Rs»200,000 mentioned below, making a total of Rso450 f 000. And such an extension -if any be made- shall be upon the same terms and conditions-except as to the period of extension -as mentioned in the following suggestion. SUGGESTION . (a) The Kuwait Oil Company shall make to me an advance against Royalty by yearly instalments of the sum of Rs.200,000. each, for a period of five (5) years# The first instalment -of such advance against Royalty- shall be made to me by the Company on March 1st, 1940. The remaining instalments of Rs.200,000.each, shall be made on each anniversary of the date on which the first payment is made f The final payment being made on March 1st, 1944. This advance shall be free of interest. (b) The Company at any time subsequent to March 1st, 1944, may deduct each year 10^ from all Royalty which may become due to me, in excess of the sum of Rs.450,p00. per annum until the whole sum of Rs. 1,000,000. has been recovered by the Company. (c) It must be clearly understood that this advance made by the Company is an advance against Royalty, and not in any manner a loan. The advance made is not recoverable by the Company, except from Royalties that may become due to me on the oil produced. I trust that the Board of the Kuwait Oil Company Limited, will decide regarding the above request with as little delay a s possible. Please convey my compliments to the Board. #■ With good wishes. Tours sincerely, Major Frank Holmes. London Repcesentative, £ u W A I T. sd/- Ahmad Al-Jabir Al-Subah.3 i v J Kuwait, 2nd March, 1940, &lt; ■ .. ■ ..f. PfSj ;■ '0 h t . I -it ic ■ IQOifV?-, # ?7i!£ fO ]#A» C . . [® risi lor}] . . 1 &gt;1111 e.,; t &amp;■:■ Mi r: idif VST. ir^; ■. giw nl r.^:. [I ifr A ' f ff : 8^ ' Sftt 3i ;■ :ce3 &gt;, Mi ' His Highness Shaikh Sir Ahmad al-JaMr As-Su'bah, KCIS., CSI., Kuwaiti Your Highness, Hef: Your Highness's letter to me dated 22nd i 'ehruary, 1940, suggesting for the Kuwait Oil Go, Ltd to make yearly advance against future royalties of Rs. 200,000 each free of interest for a period of five years. G-reetings: I have the honour to inform Your Highness that the following are the terms for recovering the amount of the advance against royalty that the Company have proposed: - (i) No deductions are to he made 'by the Company from royalty until it exceeds in any year Rs,500,000. (ii) The Company may deduct 20$ in any year when royalty exceeds Rs. 500,000 hut is less than Rs. 900,000. (iii) fhen the royalty exceeds Rs. 900,000 in any year then 20^ of the difference 'between Rs.500,000 and Rs. 900,000 plus 100 per cent of the excess over Rs. 900,000 shall he deducted hy the Company until the whole of the advance of Rs. 1,000,000 has 'been recovered 'by the Company. The ahove manner and rate of recovery of the advance 'by the Company appears to me to 'be satisfactory for 'both parties, 'but it is subject of course to the approval of Your Highness and the Board of the Company in London. I remain. Yours sincere friend and obedient s ervant, Sd. ?rank Holmes. iff i fgl* 4 f ITelega® 211 ® From, fo# / No« C/73o Dated the 26th February, 1940 C 'S'. Political Agent, Kuwait, Secretary of State for India, London. '0 We have had meeting at Basrah with Holmes and Scott to^onsider P following communication from Shaikh of Kuwait to Holmes begins^ After consideration and consultation with the Political t come to the conclusion that in order to avoid a^y daSr^ft^ 1 76 Concession Agreement terms being brought into Question. Ihavert« n iri.^ to withdraw my request that the Company should inc^e'the ^t of the Royalty minimum payment from Rupees two hundred and fif^ thousand per annum to Rupees four hundred thousand per annum. I new withdraw that suggestion and replace it with the request t^t the coSanf should Proposll^u^lst?! aeainSt fUtUre Royaltie£ . ^ ^ ^ alternative lastly the Kuwait Oil Company shall make to me an advance against Royalty by yearly instalments of the sum of Rupms two hundred thousand each, for a period of five years. The first instalment of such advance against Royalty shall be made to me hv t-ho Company on March 1st 1940. The remaining instalments of rupees two each, shall be made on each anniversary of the date on which the first payment is made# The final payment beine made on March 1st 1944© This advance shall be free of interest* iqaa a n ^ econ&lt; *ly the Company at any time subsequent to March 1st 1944, may deduct each year ten per cent from all Royalty which mav Decome due to me, in excess of the sum of four hundred and fifty ^°'^ d , p ® r until the whole sum of rupees one million has been recovered by the Company o » , ^ „ Thirdly it must be clearly understood that this advance made by the Ccmpany is an advance against Royalty and not in any manner a loan. The advance made is not recoverable by the Company, except from royalties that may become due to me on the oil produoed # Rhoadea and Jameson recommend this for favourable consideration but suggest the recovery be made as under; Nil until Royalty exceeds five hundred thousand rupees# iwenty per cent of excess in any year when Royalty exceeds five hundred thousand rupees but is less than nine hundred thousand rupees# wnen Royalty exceeds nine hundred thousand rupees repayment to be made up of twenty per cent of difference between five hundred thousand rupees ana nine hundred thousand rupees plus in addition one hundred per cent oi excess over nine hundred thousand rupees# In view of local position we request that the matter be dealt with expeditiously#1&gt; ^ 4: I itim. I I ! W i* I ite I , i .1)110-:. I l!I, . I 4 „ ,:;:.v ■ I s sorii' - &amp; )i i m i: ' y ■ v •■ I If: ••* ' A ' f V Telegram - S From - H.M's Secretary of State for India, To - Political Agent, Kuwait. No. - 1126 Dated the 7th and received the 8th March, 1940. Following from Kuwait Oil Company to Jameson Rhoades 'begins: 'Referring to your telegram of the 26th J^elDruary we are prepared to advance Shaikh Rs. 1,000,000 in five annual instalments of Rs. 200,000 free of interest. With regard to repayments we prefer a straight scale 'based on percentage of excess of royalty over Rs.450,000 in any year and hope you will he ahle to arrange for Shaikh to repay 25 per cent of such excess. Original of Shaikh's letter of February 22nd to Holmes now received and includes request regarding extension of advances after five years. We feel neither party can commit themselves now to arrangements to take effect in five years time. This matter should 'be left for later discussion in the light of existing circumstances, For Ehoades: Following caole received Iffy G-aley from G-ulf: Agree with associates we should limit advance to Rs. 1,000,000 without commitment for exten sion. We are also willing to go along with any repay ment plan approved 'by Rhoades which is satisfactory to them. Ends. - SSGRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA - .'i --&lt;111 , * __ J Ma H m'1 GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. confidential . Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [S3—This is an ORlOlNAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expedittous than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalittes it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] 87~S of 1940 No* To Repeated xxxxxxx 26th March, M 40. His HajeBty»s Secretary of State for India, London. The Secretary to the Govemnjent of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. The Political Agent, Kuwait. Reference your xxxxxxx^&amp;c Subject : Advance of royalty to Shiikh of Kuwait by the Kuwait Oil Coiajiiany • ?\v^ Reference correspondence ending with India Office Printed Letter No.P.Z.7865/39, dated the 15th December 1939, I enclose copy of a letter No.G/ll4, dated the 18th March 1940, from Political Agent, Kuwait, and of its enclosures. The negotiations had not concluded when I left Kuwait for Bushire on 22nd March, and I shall report further on their conclusion. 2. The Shaikh's action in spontaneously seeking the advice of the xolitical Agent is satisfactory. 3. Residency telegram Ko.T /598, dated the 18th December 1959 (addressed to the India Office with copy to the Government of India under Residency Printed Letter Ho.G /910, dated the 18th December 1939), merely intimated that there was no objection to Fajor HoL es 1 visit to Kuwait. sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. S 'I44. MFP-.985 S&amp;P—{M-1597)—27-11-36—10,000, {Signature) [Desigjiation)Confidential . ^ Political Agency, No. C/136 hr'^ ! '~iJ2§§!DENCYlKuwait, jttifc.... 1940. L KX' F,D5 2&lt;L HSCO^^ I 'i' | ' Till you please refer to your telegram . T o, 102 of March 26th, 1940? 2. The letter of settlement has not yet teen signed, I understand from Holmes, who heard In a round-about way, that His Highness Is now contemplating asking for an advance of Rs. 250,000 a year, T h. leHon'hle Lleut-Col. C.G. Prior, cie., irolltical Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. : i^ / it\ ^ INDIA OH'ICE WHITEHALL @ LONDON, S.W.I. -Qbh January ? 1940. Dear Jarrett ? //ould you please refer to your letter of the 9th - h iSf January, No. M.077Y3/39, regarding the suggested acquisition bj- tiie Kuwait Oil Company of a concession covering an area lying outside Koweit territorial waters. ^• ■ L 1 aj.raid we should find it difficult to accept the suggestion that His Majesty's Government should take the responsibility of deciding 5 and informing the Sheikh, that the whole matter should be left over until after the war. That the Company should be reluctant to take up and still more to operate, such a concession in present conditions is understandable, having regard to commercial considerations only. But it is hard to see with what justification, or even with what right. His Majesty's Government should 'decide'that the question should be postponed until after the war. I imagine the only reason that Plis Majesty's Government could give would be that their preoccupation with the conduct of the war did not leave them sufficient time to give the Company the advice it desired on certain points to enable it to ansv/er the Sheikh's advances. I am afraid this sound to us more impressive than convincing. '$♦ Jarrett, Admiralty, S.W.I. eOfY S£NT3. As you know, the oheikh's relations with the Company are somewhat strained at present. He has had a grov/ing ieeling tnat their activities compare unfavourably with the energy displayed by the Standard Oil Go. in Bahrein and Ilasa ? and the feeling has been accentuated by the Company s recenu decision to slow down operations on accounu o.t 1110 v/c.ir, me ohsihh will scarcely welcome a decision to postpone consideration of the 'deep-sea' concession, and naturally the Company are reluctant to announce it as theirs 5 but that seems insufficient reason for His Majesty's Government to incur the odium of communicating it to the Sheikh. 4. We should therefore much prefer to return some answerj not necessarily an elaborate one 5 to the specific queries raised by the Company ? and we should be grateful if, on reconsideration^ you could find it possible to assist us with a brief statement of the Admiralty views. 5. We are still awaiting the views of the Foreign Office and Petroleum Department also, and I am sending to Eyres and Eavenshear a copy of your letter and of this reply. Yours sincerely,1*1 ?. Z. 172/40. Military Branch, Admiralty, S.W.I, M. 07772/39. SECRET. 9th January, 1940,. Dear Peel v/e are now in a po8 .1 tic to your letter of the 2: (I Vr ion to give you an answer Viigust last P.Z. 4603/39 acquire a concession from the Gheikh of Kuwait covering an area lying outsicie Kuwait territorial waters. Ov /iixg to outbreak of war 5 and as the questions raised involved, the delimitation of the northern limits of Kuwait waters 3 and arbitrary sea boundaries to the area fixed upon, it was thought better to arrange if possible for the matter to be left over until after the war, when proper detailed consideration could be given to it. An opportunity was therefore taken to obtain the informal views of the Company on postponement, and it is now understood that they would welcome a decision to leave the whole matter over until after the war, but as the question was originally raised by Kuwait, it would assist them in their relations with the Sheikh if the decision to postpone were communicated to him as coming from His Majesty's Government, When eventually the question does come up for discussion, I gather that there would be no objection on the Company's part to the definition of an area in rather general terms and a working arrangement made v/ith the Company to confine their operations to an area with regard to which a dispute with either Saudi Arabia or Iraq would not be likely to arise, I am presuming that the above will meet your views and will render unnecessary at the present time^any detailed remarks on the questions of the acquisition of the sea-bed, whether Kuwait Bay is or is^not a territorial inlet, and where the northern limit of Kuwait territory actually runs. In any case, it is understood that the boundary of the concession area suggested by Major liolmes is merely tentative and has no particular geological significance. -Yours sincerely. (Sd. ) C. G-. JARRETT. T.Peel, Esq. , M. 0. , India Office, S.W. 1.I &amp; 1 1 IKDIA OPPICE, I E ! '^''RE RESIDENCY. 1 WHITEfIA LL, P.Z.1647/40. | ;V ' S.iV.l. Confidential. 15(31,(1 '■ a - or -» 1940. It b c \v k i I ILc M ! Dear Prior, I enclose for your information a copy of a letter from the Petroleum Department giving the views ed 19th March ) of the authorities here on the point raised in your letter of the 23rd December (No.750-3) ahout the desirability of ensuring that supplies of oil to British territories are made as far as possible 'by British-owned companies. Yours sincerely. ■ ■ ^4 The Hon'ble Lt• Col.G.G-,prior, C.I.E.,PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT (MINES DEPARTMENT), DEAN STANLEY STREET, MILLBANK, ?.!&lt; • 1647/40* S.W,1» 19th March, 1940. Dear Gibson, ' Your leoter P«Z#147/40, of the 11th January, enclosing copy of a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ahout the sales in British territories of the products of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and of those of the Bahrein and Hasa fields. I am sorry I have 'been so long in replying» 'but I have 'been awaiting the outcome of a reviev/ we have 'been making for the Oil Control Board of sources of supply of petroleum products with a view to making the 'best possible use of the tanker tonnage available. This, as you will appreciate, is a complex problem, and we have not yet been able to secure decisions on some points. We agree that so far as practicable it is desir able that Empire countries, such as India, Burma, Australia, b « New/ P.Gibson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I.iko 2. New Zealand and South Africa should be supplied to the fullest possiole extent by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, At the moment, however, in view of tanker difficulties, we cannot neglect any opportunity of having these countries supplied by tankers which might not otherwise be available to us, and this I believe is the case with most of the tankers used by Caltex. in these circumst ances, any action on the lines suggested in Priori letter must stand over for the present. Yours sincerely, (Sgd*) F.A.Starling. -V. * * A ii CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/152. B eutnp nrrr ir-sri vJOl ic. iL. i 1 . | h'o 3XU. I - (4- i4o • CO^FlDENTiAL RECORDS tl The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to i 0? vA v The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 8th April, 1940 • Eeference to previous correspondence : t bis U/Kr*' U. UK ^ Cft3 6 • 2.P DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. A. Name and Date. Subject. Letter dated the 18th March, 1940 $ ss from Mr, J.Jameson, Director, Kuwait Oil Company, to His Highnes the Ruler of Kuwait, and His Higlmess , reply dated 19th March, 1940. Kuwait Oil Company,Ib&gt; iSth March, 1940. His Highness Shaikh Sir Aixmad al as Subah HULISIi OF KUWAIT . ' Your Highness # h ^ ^' Greetings. With reCerenoe^tb Your Highness # s letter of the 32nd February, 1940 to Major Holmes, Your London Bepresentative, which was passed to us, and the interview Messrs, Jameson and Ihoedes had with Your Highness on the 18th Inst# at Dasman Palace # we beg to oonTirm the agreement reached, namely:- (a) The Company will advance to Your Highness five annual sums of Rs.200,000 (Rupees two hundred thousand only), the first advance to be made as soon as possilile after receipt of Your Highness*s acceptance of the terms of this fatter, and the remaining four advances to be ipade on 1st March in each of the years 1941 to 1944 inclusive* (b) No interest shall be payable on these ad?anoea* (c) Repayment of these advances shall be nale as follows:- Whenever, subsequent to 1st Hareh 1944, the Company is under obligation in accordance with the terms of Article 3 of the Concession Agreement dated 23rd December 1934, to pay to Your Highness ® lua by way of Royalty in excess of Hs•500,000 ( upees five hundred thousand only), Your Highness authorises and Requests the Company to deduct frcci such payment of Royalty a sum •quivalent to 25 per cent of the amount by which the Royalty exceeds Hs•500,000 (Rupees fl?e hundred thousand only), and only the balance shall be payable to Tour Highness under Artiele 3 of th^ Concession Agreement. d) Such deductions shall continue until ih© total of the advances made to Your Highness has been repaid to the Company. Tours faithfully, FOR KUWAIT OIL COMPjiHY UMITSD. oOD. JAS. JAMSSON, DlilSCTOH.The Kuwait Oil Co. y Ltd. 9 Siffalt , I Dear Sirs, I am ia receipt of Your letter of 18th March, 1940, on the subject of advances to be aade to me against, and repayments Itt J. -;i. to be deducted from, futu^o Royalty payable under the prorislona of irtiole 3 of the Agieemeiit between ourselves, dated 23rd Deo ember, 1954. The terms of your letter are acceptable : ■ 1 to me. A*m: m j Tour© sincerely, /Lb 19th March,1940, % 1 . : ■! Sd/ Ahmad al-Jabir as subah.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. Confidential. EXPRESS LETTRP (AIR MAiU. T a5 &lt;J [ it had been ^graphed. To save time and to obviate ' ' eUgram - 11 'y ***'»' of a uj u tetegram. it t8t auther ^ 0# 193 —3 of iQ&amp;Qidnipfi ^^Sl. re, /i I To Hie Majesty 's Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated The Secretary to the Government of Indit, External Affairs Department, Simla* The Political Agent f Kuwait • Beference xxxxxxxxiBbc Subjaoti AdTanoe of royalty to Shaikh of Kuwait by the Kuwait Oil Oompany. /O In continuation of my Express Letter Ho.87-S, dated the 26th March 1940, I enclose copies of letters dated 18th and 19th March 1940 respectively, exchanged between the Kuwait Oil Company and the Shaikh O j . Kuwait recording the agreement reached for advances to be paid by the Company to the Shaikh against future royalty. sd. O.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Attested. Lfo ' for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Signature)- 1 ■ ($1 &gt; Confidential , D.O. No. 0/179 ri/ SH'-R£ n&amp;' VO iNCY RSC0M8 Political Agency, Kuwait, 18th April, 1940. Holmes has sent me a copy of a letter of which I enclose a copy, it concerns the payment 'by the Kuwait Oil Oompany of a petrol allowance to His Highness. I can find no records, and I am only forwarding this for your information Holmes explains that the matter is outside the Agreement, and was fixed up 'by an exchange of letters. aue-*- ^eEon'TDle Lieut-Oolonel O.G. Prior, CIE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.4th April, 1940 His Highness Shaikh Sir /Uimad al JaMr as Satah, KOIE. , OSI. , Ruler of Kuwait, Your Highness, With reference to Your Highness * request through youi London Representative Major Holmes that payment in lieu of supplying Petrol or other Petroleum iDe increased from Rs. 5000 to Rs. 10,000 per annum we would refer Your Highness to our letter of the 19th Oetoher, 1939, to Major Holmes, and for the same reasons as stated therein we agree to pay, in addi tion to the Rupees 250,000, Rs. 10,000 in lieu of supplying Petrol or other Petroleum. Yours faithfully, 7 OR KUWAIT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. Sgd. JA3. JAMESON. DIRECTOR.P.Z.1174/40 K.01956/40 SFCIET . Dear Peel, i'ilitary Branch, Admiralty, S.?/.l # 23rd February, 1940. In r ©Ply to your letter of the 26th January, ivo» I .172/40, concerning the suggested acquisition by the Kuwait Oil Company of a concession covering an area lying outside xvuwait territorial waters, I write to say that our main reason for suggesting that consideration of the matter should be postponed until after the war was that the limits of the concession suggested by the Oil Company raised difficult and awkward questions regarding the boundaries between Kuwait end Iraq. The position of the frontier was the subject of consideration recently in connection with a suggested Iraqi port in the Khor Abdullah (see Foreign Office letter £.5116/ , 58/92 of the 5th August) and it is clear that the whole question even of the land frontier is extremely obscure. To fix a boundary running out to sea within which' oil concessions can be granted by Kuwait is even more difficult, and to attempt to do so may well give rise to trouble with Iraq, to say nothing of possible Iranian reactions, even if no question with Saudi-Arabia arises as regards the South-eastern boundary. Apart from any views held 'by the Oil Company, we should find it very difficult in present circLimstances to give adequate consideration to the problem* and we should imagine that the same applies to the Foreign Office# who ai^e still more concerned in that they have to take into account the effect of any action on our relations with Kuwait's nei^ibours. It will* also, we think be very difficult for the Oil Company, under war conditions* to take up actively the examination and development of an additional area, and we feel that* from their point of view* it is quite reasonable to ask for a postpone ment. We obviously, however* cannot push these objections too far* and if both you and the Foreign Office are agreed that it is necessar * for political reasons, to go on with the matter now, we can only suggest that the boundaries of the concession should be defined in such general terms as not to raise any vexed questions of the extent of the Sheikh's jurisdiction- ^/hat we have in mind is that instead of showing the seaward boundaries on a chart* we should define them in some such general way as 'bounded on the 3outhr-East by a straight line drawn from th® point at which the territorial waters of Kov /eit and the neutra~ zone meet* in a direction at right angles to the coast or the general trend of the coast* if this is thought preferable; and on the North tiast by a straight line drawn from the point xartaesu to seaward at which the territorial waters of Kuwait and Iraq meet, in a direction following the trend of the boundary between Kuwaiti and Iraqi waters to the point oi intersection wich uhe first line' • This is, of course* only a rough idea and we should have to examine the exact terms more closely oofore .g i^na. 1/ decided upon them* As we stated in our letter ohe ■ j - Januarv, we understand that the Company will be quite williiig^to agree to some working arrangement* under which they would comine their operations to an area v/ith regard to which a dispute with either Saudi/or Iraq would not be likely to arise- Arabia _ . We are not sure whether, in uhe circiir :iS ucui^es, iu necessary to define the extent of Kuwait territorial waters, but our views are that the configuration of Koweit Bay would Justxi, its he?ng regarded as a territorial inlet with a closing line from Ras al Ardh to the South-west extreme corner of Falakah Island, a distance of ahout 9i miles, provided that there xs Ssq*, M• C* a \0^1 , i 2. evidence of a long exercise of o^jLsdiction over the area in question# The ciues tion of the 'boundary TDetY/een Kuwait and Iraq, is# as we have already indicated, extremely olDScure* We agree with your remarks regarding the powers which can 'be exercised 'by the Sheikh outside his territorial waters, subject to the proviso that nothing must 'be done to affect rights of navigation, or any prescriptive rights, such as fishing. I am sending a copy of this letter to Eyre and Ravenshear. Yours sincerely, (Sd) &lt;11• no afkfuo I INDIA OPFICS, is. ci I TEL J\LL, 3 • \l% i • r 33/ ' 40 , ieth Mr.y,l94 \-\ 0 Dear Kemp, . w. 11 i„ anl \?. sked t ® express regret for the long delav in r^alv 0 ^ 1 ^ of f asked that your Company should acquire^'r® 0 the'Iheikh ofloweit ®' t °^ ooncebsion covering an area lying outside territorial a era. iue --g 1 ay has oeen due to the pre-occupation of the o^ r departments whom v /e had to consult v/ith more urgent worh. connected v /i'bh. the wsr» 2* ue do not know v/hether in the altered circumstances of war- time your Company will wish to pursue discussion of this proposal with the Sheikh, 'but in case you should, the following answers to your questions may assist you* Thev are necesscirily provisional in respect of 'boundary lines, and the interested Departments would wish to give them further consideration in consultation with the authorities in one Persian Gulf before the discussions 'between your Company and the oheikh crystallise into a definite agreement. ( a ) asked 11 what exclusive and non-exclusive rights has H.H. the power to grant in the form of an oil concession over the area indicated in Major Holmes's map'. I should say at the outset that this area could not 'be accepted as it stands, since it raises 'boundary questions which, partly 'because the 1'owe it-Iraq frontier has not yet 'been delimited, it would 'be impossible to settle at the present time. It would 'be preferable, instead of showing the seaward boundaries of the area on a chart, to describe the area in more general terms and in a way that would avoid the possibility of boundary disputes with neighbouring countries. If you wish to pursue the matter we are prepared to consider whether we can suggest a provisional formula for the purpose. I should at the same time make it clear that any definition of the extent of Koweit territory which may be agreed to for the purposes of the proposed concession should not be regarded as precluding H.fc .G. from giving the Sheikh such advice as they may see fit to give him at any time in the future with regard to the disposition of his territory. In reply to your specific enquiry, the Sheikh cannot grant any exclusive or non-exclusive rights over any area lying outside his territorial waters. But if the phrase 'submerged land belonging to the Sheikh' v/ere used in the concession, the effect would be that your Company would have the right to exploit submerged land outside the three mile limit as soon as they had appropriated it by sinking shafts. The appropriation would have the effect of vesting the land in the Sheikh from the point of view of sovereignty, since £ emp, Esq., COPY SENT BY AIR MAIL Nit Oil Co., ic f,- of Jl - f Ae .Ua . stannic House, Finsbury Square, S,C.2. COPY SENT BY MAIL COPY SENT BY AIR MAIL frf il. k* r&gt;f pkf the Company would be Sheikh.' This would not^deprive 6 anv fr0m the right «,« starts in adjacent ^ waters if thejr wished to do so. uu^iae territorial concession agreement with the Sheikhf T tn o S '- that in principle H.M.O. would hive no oiection provided ^ that the area of the concession is so defined as to countrief anrLbiecrto 16 ^ disputes with neighbouring coununes and suoject to other comments in this letter nnd tn approval of^tae actual terms of the concession agreement* H.L.G. woulo. 01 course require the Company to enter into a pre-emp-cion agreement with them* ' ^^oer mxo a + aSt1 ?' ^ raised question of the extent of Ko\/eit s ternconal waters# This raises# or mav ralsp ?^nf lfflCUlt prol3lerns and a definite reply cannot he given to you ac present We understand that the configuration of I 701 ? 1 ?, its being claimed as a territorial of longstanding exercise this proviso were political authorities as national territory inlet provided that there is evidence if jurisdiction over its waters# If satisfied (a point on which the local would have to be consulted Koweit Bay ■ a ? u ^ t | 30 re g a ^d;ed as bounded by a line joining Ras al Ardh wich une northern headland of the bay, or possibly by lines eonnecting (a) the S # V/*corner of Failakah Island with Ras ai Apdh^and (b; the K»W* corner of the Island with the nearest point oi the mainland on the north side of the Bay* Territor ial waters would extend three miles seawards of these lines. 4# I hope the foregoing will be found a sufficient reply co your letter for your present purposes* Yours sincerely,n% In reply please quote- p .Z. 3279/40 Dear Prior, HIRE KtSlDENC • • $!. ^ Date. 'Ilfa, CO«riOZ^T;AL'?£CORD3' !?if TICAL D epartment, I ndia O ffice, L ondon , S.W. 1 13th June,1940. I You will have seen our correspondence with the Kuwait Oil Company, resting with my letterof the 18th May, I aDout the proposal that the Company should acquS; Shei h an oil concession covering an area outside territorial waters. earlier m the year the Admiralty, after private d'scussion with the Company, had suggested that the prohllms raised by the concession could receive more adequate consideratior of their^Tp- t ^ e 1 3heikh shonld be informed by H.M.G. of their view that the whole matter should be postponed till u • ? 0wTl was that there seemed no reason why H.M.G# should intervene in the preliminary stage of a commercial transaction between the Company and the Sheikh in order to relieve the Company, at least for the duration of the war, of ^ 6i fu? rnDarrassment re P 1 y in g to the proposals made on the Sheikh s behali by Holmes* OonseQuently we took steps resulting in our reply to the Company of the 18th May. ^ h • Ho ' we gather now that the receipt of this letter has been very un./elcome to the Company, who can no longer attribute to us the delay in their reply to the Sheikh,, and they have conseQuently appealed privately for our help. We do not particularly wish to make ourselves a shelter for the Company in their commercial dealings with the Sheikh* but we appreciate their difficulties, particularly in war-time, in attempting to obtain and operate such a concession. We should not think it necessary to encouraKe the Company to do so, as you will 'understand from our acquiescence in their war-time policy in Koweit. The Company might argue moreover that Government is responsible for adding to their difficulties in prosecuting operations in war time as a result of its control of steel and dollar exchange# There is therefore something to be said for giving the Company any reasonable assistance in this matter, especially as they have dealt not unreasonably with the Sheikh in the increased payments which they have undertaken. We should be glad if you v/ould consider the question in the light of the above considerations and would let us know whether in all the circumstances you would think it possible and desirable for the Political Agent to mention the subject to the Sheikh, explaining that H.M.G. had been consulted and had Hon'ble Lt.Col. C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Bushire. found/found some difficulty in present conditions in giving final answers -to certain problems that arose, while the Company themselves are faced with substantial difficulties in attempting to obtain and operate the proposed concession in war-time conditions; and suggesting that the matter might be left in suspense until after the war. If you are not in favour of this course from the point of view of our own relations with the Sheikh, there seems nothing for it but to tell the Company that they must make their own explanations to the Sheikh# I am sending a copy of this letter to Galloway and Caroe. Yours sincerely. ( v!•*? '83 in ' Mcessiojj, «ter u 1 316 DOtij OUT o® to it but m ex Pla]iaii^ 'WaMCafoj, INDIA OFilCL, WHITEHALL, S.W.I• 1^th June, 194C. P.2.3362/40. Dear Prior, Would you please refer to my letter of the 13th June, No. P.Z.3279/40, on the raavter of the suggested oil concession over an area outside Koweit territorial waters. I enclose a dated 12th June without enclosure) copy of an AdmLralty letter, received just after my letter had issued, which, as you will see, supports the case for our intervening in this matter on the lines suggesxed in paragraph 3 of jzy letter. 1 an sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Caroe and Galloway. Yours sincerely. The Hon T ble Lt. Col. C.G-. Irior, C.I..C-COPY P2. 2562/40. M. 05357/40. Sir, adibihai/ty. r.-w 1 O' r 12th June 1940. 'W- . i _ / f ^ com ^ a nded by My Lords Goimnissi oners of thp Admiralty to forward herewith for the information df thpl Secretary of State for India the followin ^bse^attono 1 t Office semi-official letter PZ.1313/40 of 0 the lA .t? ^ + -d/oretgn Office semi-official letter E.1229/19/91 of the 19th April concerning the various considerations arisins- out^n-F certain proposals for the Kuwait Oil Company to acquire a concession from the SheiKh of Kuwait covering an area Ivine outside .Kuwait territorial waters. ^ a ^ords understand that the actual position of the + 0 o P ?'h i pivk ^ e /{ Pre f e ? t t ime is ^ ha ' b has, 'by agreement with the oheikh, reduceo. land operations to a minimum. * 'The prohahility is therefore that the Company has no intention, so v S 31 ?^ 8,8 -! 1 war - i - as ^ s &gt; &gt; 01 doing anything to examine the bed 01 the large extent of territorial waters included in its concession, since to do this would involve the provision of heavy equipment purchased in dollars and freighted from America. ^till less could it possibly consider work on the bed of'extra-territorial waters. 9 31 h , In the circumstances, as they exist to-day, I.iy Lords feel sure that the Secretary of i)tate for India would be averse from advocating a policy involving large expenditure which cannot possibly serve any useful war purpose, and might there fore now be disposed to support the Company in the matter of postponement of operations, as suggested in Admiralty semi- 4 official letter M. 01956/40 nf the 23rd Pebruaiy last. - p fhS h-As regards the other matters referred to in the last mentioned Admiralty letter, the claim to regard Koweit Bay as a territorial inlet would rest not only on configuration, but also on the grounds that territorial rights are necessary for defence and neutrality, and that the Bay is secluded from normal traffic routes. In Iv^r Lords opinion such a claim would be unlikely to be challenged in an international court firstly because the configuration appears to be of a satisfactory nature and secondly because the prescriptive .00 rights/2. rights are no doubt strong enough to make it possible to establish long standing jurisdiction over the Bay. In the further matter of the base line passing % across the Bay, My Lords desire to amend their originals' view, first expressed in Admiralty letter M.01615/28 of the 28th June 1928, that an appropriate closing line would run from Ras al Ardh to the south west extreme corner of Failakah Island. On reconsideration they now consider that the proper base line should be drawn from low water mark at Ras al Ardh to a position at low water mark on the opposite coast in latitude 29° 27 1 10' N longitude 48° 14 1 00' E. (See attached copy of Chart where closing line XT has been drawn from 'Headland to Headland at high water, and the Base Line Y2 from the low-water mark appropriate to each Headland, the limit of territorial waters P .O.. being drawn 3 nautical miles to the seaward and parallel 'to the Base Line YZ.) . r ~ 1 -l 1 U -■Jy 0 ICj £»A further matter which it would be convenient to mention at this stage is the erroneous impression in paragraph 12 of Foreign Office (Mr. Baggallay) Memorandum (E.1020/10/34j dated the 2nd April 1936 in connection with the international frontier dividing territorial waters. Three such methods are mentioiied in the Memorandum and of these, it is stated that it is assumed that the Hydrographer of the' Navy is in favour of method 2 whereas this method is not specially favoured. In fact method 1 whereby the ..frontier is a line all points on which lie at an equal distance from the nearest points on the coasts of the states whose frontier is being determined is preferred and is no more than a special application of ? the Median Line. There may, however, be occasions possibly in the Estuaries of rivers where there are large low water mark areas, where the bisection of the angle forming the general line of the coasts (Method 3/ would be preferable. There are no practical difficulties to be met, either in navigation or in drawing a frontier by using Method 1. trvvm v*- 3 % XX'tTol C/Ji sn ' . ; ■ '\i .1.i&gt;i ' 0 Lft p p\ , , lvHaving gone into this matter In some detail. My Lords would deprecate any further inter-departmental correspondence on the subject during the rest of the war period and would urge that the Political Agent in Kuwait should/^/28 of s ^ ^ouii corner/ ^ cons% l w water mark on ^gitude feere id at . mark 'itorial venient to on in J ? Memorandi ectionifiti ' waters, dim and of is reby the i equal 5f tlie stat and is no ^ne, Iliei tries of is, where ine of Te no gation or should be instructed to inform the Sheikh that nothin- can be done to define extra-territorial limits during the war period, as the question is highly involyed, hut that the matter could be taken up when the war is over. In Var Lord 1 - opinion, the Political Agent might inform the Sheikh in the same informal manner as the question was originallv ri ° ;L ° 1 ? s i n „^ he oommunication dated 10th July 1939 included in India Office letter P.2,4603/39 of the 2nd August 1939, ouch a communication would assist the Company in its relations with the Sheikh. A copy of this letter has been sent to the Foreicm Office and the Petroleum Department. -oxeign I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) RICHMOND WALTON.Si j I Confiientii.l. B.O. Ho. 0/344 Political Agency, Kuwait, 20th July, 1940. ^ P.';2^?X: I'fj'Z z ^/l/^C' / ou please refer to your telegram No,534 of the 15th July, 1940 9 2. 'y first inclination is to say, since I do not 'believe that the issue is now a live one with His Highness, that we need not raise the matter unless he does. But it is possiole that Holmes might on the Shaikh's 'behalf and this should 'be forestalled, I agree, therefore, with the views expressed in the ^ 4 ., rn last paragraph of Admiralty letter Mo. 05357/40 of the 12th June, 1940. An informal mention of the matter 'by me will, I think, he well received, as my experience is that 'is Highness fights shy of questions connected with the rights of neighbouring States. Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel G.G-.Prior plitical Resident in the rs Trn j O— • 9 3 ersi*n Gulf, Bush ire.86/1 Telegram FroM Political itesident, Bushire, India Office, London# Copy by poet to Government of India, Simla. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 578 Bated 25th July 1940. tael'e deml offlcisl letter r.z.zztz/ic Jalrjr June 15th. 2. Political Agent does not think matter is now a live issue with ahaikh, but to forestall any possible action by Holmes I am instructing Political Agent to appe. roach the shaikh informally on the lines mentioned in last nl paragraph of Admiralty letter of June l2th» - BRITCOKSUL • uro_86/1 IB! Telegram *§* irom Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait., llo^ 579 Dated 25th July 1940• A'* Your demi official letter C/344, July 20th. Please inform Shaikh accordingly. - BRITCONSUL -- V 1 \\0 Confidential, The Agency, !S&gt; Ku.vait, 30th July, *40. D.0,!To. C/362. Will you please refer to . p (S } your telegram No, 579 of the 25th July, 1940, on the subject of a concession to cover Ku.vait terri torial waters? 2. His Highness states that he is perfectly willing to let the matter lie dormant, and would only raise it at a time convenient to His ITajesty's G -overnment, Hon'hle Tdeut-Golonel C.Or.Prior, O'TE. , Bushire•Political Resident^ Bushire at Shiraz^ Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by poat to Government of India, Simla» Political Agent, Kuwaiti Io»T/281# Dated the IStii August 1940• /t - - My telegram Ho*573 25th. July* Shaikii agrees not to raise matter until convenient to His Majesty , 3 Government* BRITGONSUL# sScmI- U- ^86/1 a m Telegram 3. From Political Agent, Kuv/ait. To Political Resident, at Muscat. No•0/550. Dated and received 22nd ITovember 1940. 1&lt;T I' jih In continuation of my telegram lTo.546 November 20th. Holmes informs Kuv/ait Oil Company in London that he thinks someone in Shaikh T s entourage is attempting to stir trouble between Shaikh and Company, xibove is for your information and in the meantime I have asked Kuv/ait Oil Company for details• - Political. '.L.Telegram 'q* From Political Agent, Kuwait. - 0 Political Resident, Bushire. No. G/274. Dated (and received ) 21at May 1941. m'ORTANT . Sass Geologist 'wishes to visit Dhaharan by overland route discuss certain matters with Manager of G.A.S.O.G, He proposes asking- Manager to arrange permit with Saudi authorities and send car take him from Kuwait frontier and return him same 'way. Shaikh agrees if you have no ohjection. Political. DJ3.86/1 Telegram S To Ropeatea No. 925b gnj Secretary of State for Inaia, Lonaon Political Resident, at Shiraz. Political 'gent, Kuwaito Dated 5th received 6th August l?4i 0 iTQinedlate Kuwait Oil Cmnpany wish to replace drilling superintendents Patrick and Sass by Fuss and ?Ker ens also Americans. Latter previously been emxjlcyed by C.A o S e 0pC. in Bahj-^ln e Have you any objection ? visas wanted by anthortties. Ple%fle reply immediately. «Secretary of State lor India. l.X86/1 Telegram s From To Hepeated Ho.10094 Dated 23rd received 24th August 1941. Secretary of State for India, London. Political xiesident, at Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Your telegram lTo.T/405 of August 6th, Kuwait Oil Company now wish to send Guntz, also American, in place of Hurry. if i do not hear from you by 29th August 1 shall take it you have no objection. Secretary of State86/1 ip Telegram »s' From To Repeated No. T/495. Dated 24th August 1941. Political Resident at Bahrain, H.M's Secretary of State for India, London. Political Agent, Kuwait. Guntz, Your telegram No. 10094 August 23rd No objection. - RESIDENT - AVM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00026d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/647</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00026d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/647</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'D.158. 86/1 - xi KUWAIT OIL'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-03T14:02:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (209 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence in the volume has been arranged chronologically based on the date of its receipt at the Bushire Residency.Folios 191-204 contain file notes relating to the items in the volume. The notes include details of correspondents and dates of receipt and also include notes written for the information of the Secretary to the Political Resident in regards to the responses and instructions required by the Political Resident to the correspondence in question. Also included with the notes are pencil numbers, written in the margins, which refer to the pencil foliation numbers and enable the notes to be used as an index.A topic based index is located on folio 1A .</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation has been written in pencil and can be found in the top right hand corner of the recto side of each folio. The sequence begins with the first item of correspondence and ends on the inside back cover.Foliations anomalies: 1, 1A and 1B. Foliation errors: 173 and 176 have been omitted.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file primarily focuses on the progress being made by the Kuwait Oil Company (KOC) in drilling for oil in Kuwait, including establishing drills at new sites and the discovery of oil at the Burgan site in February 1938. Later correspondence relates to various topics, as follows: the work and tests required on the oil before announcements relating to the discovery of oil in commercial quantities can be made; discussions with the India Office over the difference between 'commercial quantities' of oil and 'commercial conditions' for oil, the latter requiring the company to discuss the establishment of a refinery with the British Government; the decision by the KOC to cease their activities in Kuwait, other than drilling for water, owing to the outbreak of war, along with their actions in safeguarding the wells against potential enemy action; the negotiations with the Shaikh of Kuwait regarding the payment of royalties for the discovery of oil and advances on those royalties. The primary correspondents are the Kuwait Oil Company; Shaikh of Kuwait (Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ); the Political Agent at Kuwait (Gerald Simpson de Gaury, Andrew Charles Stewart); the Political Resident at Bushire (Trenchard Craven Fowle, Charles Geoffrey Prior); the Secretary of State for India (Lawrence Dundas, the 2nd Marquess of Zetland) and India Office staff (J P Gibson, Alexander Symon, Roland Tennyson Peel)Also discussed in the file is the question of a concession for an area outside of the territorial waters of Kuwait and numerous correspondence between the Kuwait Oil Company, India Office, Admiralty (Clifford George Jarrett) and Petroleum Department (Frederick Charles Starling) that debate what the jurisdictions might be in such an area, the exact nature of the territorial waters surrounding Kuwait, and potential boundary and frontier issues that might arise from such a concesssion. The correspondence is cut short owing to the outbreak of World War II as the various departments no longer have the time to discuss such matters and an agreement is reached with the Company and the Shaikh of Kuwait to suspend the matter until the war is over.Other matters discussed in the volume include:An article which appeared in
                              Al Sijilmagazine which criticises the Kuwait Oil Company for failing to find oil in Kuwait and the Shaikh of Kuwait for keeping the concession negotiations and signed agreement secret from his own people. A translated copy of the article is included at folios 8-9;The commencement by the Kuwait Oil Company of the construction of a jetty at Bandar Shuwaikh, and the potential defensive benefits such a jetty could have in war-time;A proposed visit by Colonel Harold Dickson, Chief Local Representative of the Kuwait Oil Company, to Ibn Sa'ud over Christmas 1938 that was eventually cancelled due to objections from the Shaikh of Kuwait;Arrangements with the American Mission in Kuwait for the provision of medical and hospital facilities for Company employees and the decision to employ another American nurse who would attend to the hospital needs of the company but would also assist with the work of the Mission's Women's hospital (folios 76-80);Correspondence between the Kuwait Oil Company, Secretary of State for India and the India Office regarding the appointment of American personnel in Kuwait and obtaining the British Government's permission for their appointments;Correspondence between the Political Agent at Kuwait, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and His Majesty's Vice-Consul at Khorramshar (Albert Napier) regarding a Kuwait Oil Company employee of non-British or Kuwaiti status who was granted a visa to travel to Kuwait for work without permission from the British Government and discussing the correct passport and visa procedures for non-British subjects travelling throughout the region.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian Development Syndicate Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Division</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Shuwaikh </geographic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial waters</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Kuwait</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00026d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>