<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00017a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T21:28:21.968Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROMi Utt^ f,— 30 D *“' I i VKi' mi “ Rec. j 1 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State..... Copy to * Ml* ) (o I /v5'. FOR INFORMATION,'V 3 [T hia Doomnent la the Property of 11s Britannic Majesty's CtoTemment, and should be returned to the foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] 1 0 ', u K 1 ■« V 'EH SI A POLI TIC AL Decypher of telegram from Mr, Marling (Tehran), July 12th. 1915, (d. 12.15 p.m. r, 6.45 p.m. July 12th), No. 242.- fy**) My telegram No,240. Democrats are finding great difficulty in forming a Cabinet and the Shah is giving support to Ain-ed- Dowleh and Farma Farman so that there is some prospect of the Cabinet resuming office. Russian Minister has telegraphed to his Government recommending that the force at Enzeli should be strengthened and Ain-ed- Dowleh has intimated to us that the arrival of 1,000 more men or a few more guns would have an excellent effect. I hope that this can be done. Russian Minister has also urged the despatch of force from Trahscaspia into Khorassan. Addressed to Foreign Office and Petrograd.¥ [This Docnment is the Property of His Britenalc Majesty’s Qovenunent, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] RUSSIA , _ ° b POLITICAL . Cypher telegram to Sir G-. Buchanan (Petrograd.). Porejgn Office, July 14th 1915 ? 7 p-rm No. 1456. R.. Mr. Marling 1 s telegram No. 242 (of 12th July, Troops for Persia). Your Excellency is authorized to support the view of the two Representatives at Teheran. Repeated to Teheran No. 184.s Register No. vvith Minute Paper. 2 Sc\u- 's'' Secret Department. 't * €4.1^ 3 0 Dated Bee. _ /t 191 s. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State Pc eopyto fj' ^ /}M- FOR INFORMATION.[This Document Is the Property ot Hie Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should be retnmed to the Foreign Office when nnless required for official use.] O -f # PMSIA. MILITARY. Decypher, Mr. Marling (Teheran) July 14th 1915. (d. 8.30 p.m. f. 11.10 a„m. July 14th). No. 244. Following from Senior Naval Officer dated July 12th: R. 'A report was received to-day that a party of insur gent tribesmen were coming over to lie in wait in Nullah c/L delelates country residency. It seemed possible that this was probably one of the usual unfounded or false reports but Major Oliphant 96th Regiment and Captain Ranking went with a party of Sowars and infantry to reconnoitre. Un fortunately they apparently came suddenly on a large well- concealed party of the enemy who immediately opened fire at close range. Regret to say that both officers and four sepoys are reported killed. Enemy then advanced to attack southern outpost line. Heavy firing took place at sunset and soon after but has been only desultory since so attack has been apparently repulsed. (3 groups undecypherable) Sent to India.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should he returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] r n PERSIA. PQLJTiCiiL. Decypher, Mr. Marling (Teheran). IA 8,20 p fl ni. , A. 11.50 p.m,, He.. 245. Urgent. July 13 tli 1S15 Iv^ telegram Pc. 244.. At tank on Residency at Bushire appears to me to justify despatch cf any force tnat may he cc ns leered requisite tc prevent Gernean missions from reaching Afghanistan, and I submit new tnat German intrigues have resulted in the death cf two British officers, we are entirely justified in adopting similar means ourselves, and employ steady tribesmen to attack their emissaries. Bent tc Foreign Office; repeated to India, Bushire, and Basrah., and Birjand.[This Document la the Property of HU Britannic Majesty’s government, should be retnmed to the foreign Oftlce when d ona with unless required lor official use.] -N O A ' ■ v &lt;y i J '-L)I'CbXA t» MILITARY r Decypher■ i.t r Llarling (Teheran) July 15thr 1915, D « le r Pr r He ICrlOrPri'ir NOr 248 r (H)r July 15th, 1915e Wlo i ‘'/ing tron Bus hir e June (?July) 13 th, ay telegram MOr 299 C» The party of tribesmen are reported to have come from Dilwar and a. few from Dasti, Regiment worked down island this morning and found none left,. Simul taneous attack was to have been made last night by this party and another coming straight across masilleh near main caravan. Latter however appears to have thought better of it. Bodies of Oliphant and Ranking brought back this morning - only revolvers and ammunition had been re moved, nothing else, not even watches. One wepog s body also found. It appears that one was killed and. two wounded and not four killed as previously repor ’cecn Am. trying to ascertain whether second par eg pro poses to attack to-night. Governor thinks not. If we had had some cavalry to reconnoitre^ I do no think we should have lost the two officers. Addressed to Sir P, Cox, Repeated to Legation and to Foreign,\o [This Document lg the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] Pi^KBlA r UILITAXYr Decypherr Mr r I iarling (Teheran) 2 5 9 4 o Fuly loth- 1915 Dr DcSSrPrilir Rr 7c55rpcni.r NOr 249r July 1 5th r 1915c Following from Bushire No r 3C4 of June (?July) 14th r My telegram. Nor 301 r Or In last sentence I intended to put in after the word 'reconnoitre' words 'or sufficient infantry to hold Mogam Haleleh line'r Please insert therm From, an independent source it was confirmed that Raisali and his party left the neighbourhood of Chagadeck in the forenoon of 12thc while Sheik massemi (?in conjunction with) Sain Khadar left about Sunday 11thr Neither party returned there and Governor thinks that they must have decamped to Chatal Dilwarc Our discovery of the first party upset their arrange ments for concerted attache Addressed to Sir Pr Core Sent to Teheran,. Sent to India* i\ K, /it™[This Document is the Property of Hie Britannic Majesty s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] r p .JL O K c t ■ &gt;-,J V. 2.&amp; PE i. v... POLIIICaL Decypher. Ivir. Marling (Teheran). D 0 8 * DO p,ra He 11.50 p.m., No. 245. Urgent. Duly loth 1915. f telegram in. 244. Attack cn hesidency at Bushire appears tc me to justify despatch cf any force txiat nay he considered requisite tc prevent German missions from reaching Afghanistan, and I submit now tnat German intrigues have resulted in the death cf two British officers, we are entirely justified in adopting similar means ourselves, and employ steady tricesmen to attack their emissaries. Gent tc Foreign Office; repeated tc India, Bushire and Basrah, and Birjand. rj. [This Document la the Property ol H1 b Britannic Majesty’s Government, and ahonld be retnmed to the Foreign Office when done with nnlea» required for official uae.] MILITARY. Decypher, Mir. Marling (Teheran) July 14th 1915. (d. 8.30 p.m. t. 11.10 a.ra. July 14th). No. 244. 1 R. Following from Senior Naval Officer dated July 12th: 'A report was received to-day that a party of insur gent tribesmen were coming over to lie in wait in Nullah ck)loga4e-s' country residency. It seemed possible that this was probably one of the usual unfounded or false reports but Major Oliphant 96th Regiment and Captain Ranking went with a party of Sowars and infantry to reconnoitre. Un fortunately they apparently came suddenly on a large well- concealed party of the enemy who immediately opened fire at close range. Regret to say that both officers and four sepoys are reported killed. Enemy then advanced to attack southern outpost line. Heavy firing took place at sunset and soon after but has been only desultory since so attack has been apparently repulsed. (3 groups undecypherable) Sent to India. ii*&gt;PERSIA Decypher of telegram from Mr„ Marling (Tehran), July 14th, 1915. (d. 12.10 p.rn. July 14th. r. 3,50 p.rn, July 14th). Mo.246. f*&gt; Your telegram Mo.180• p Following sent to Government of India No.67. ''For obvious reasons I must leave it to you to make necessary preparations and decide on best measures to adopt for intercepting Germans. I will send you all information that I can obtain as to movement of Germans, as to possible Russian action and as to changes in political situation here more or less affecting our action.'V , t I L PThla Doonment la the Property of H1 b Britannic Majesty's Qovernment. ahonld he retnmsil to the foreign Office when done with nninna re quired lor ottlclal nae.] POLITIOAl,. (94462/15). PERSIA. Cypher telegram tc Mr. Marling (Teheran). Foreign Office, July loth 1915, 11.30 a.m No. 189 . Urgent . /cur telegram No* 245 (of July loth. Gorman activity). I approve entirely and you are authorised to take necessary action in concert with Government of India.—j FOREIGN OFFICE, July 15th. 1915 (95101/15). r ] I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you, herewith, to he laid before Mr. Secretary Chamberlain a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at Teheran reporting on the serious situation which has arisen in Persia. In view of the facts stated by Mr. Marling, Sir S. Grey considers that from the point of view of foreign policy His Majesty’s Government would not only gain nothing but would render their position increasingly difficult if they further postponed armed intervention in Southern Persia as it appears that such action has now become inevitable sooner or later. I am, therefore, to urge that, unless there are in surmountable objections from the military point of view, measures should be taken with the utmost practicable despatch for giving effect to the plan suggested by Mr. Marling. \ copy of this letter has been sent to the Admiralty. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant ^he Under Secretary of State India office.Jr rrhis Document ia the Properly of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PEHSIa . PQui T ICAL . Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran). July 14th 1915 D. 8.30 p.m.j July 14nn 1915, R. 1 a.m., July 15th 1S15. Nc; 247. Urgent. Vi My telegram Mo. 242. Cabinet crisis still continues and although it seems certain that Ai n - e d - Do w 1 oh will ret-ain cilice, he is already talking of doing without Parman-Farma at Ministry of the Interior. Should this final concession be made to pro-German party, Ain-ed-Dcwleh will be sc dependent on them that it will be hopeless to expect that anything will be done to check German action, as it is,small (sic) begin ning to fulfil explicit promises made to me to hold up German emissaries has been arrested by resignation of Ministers. Pact is that there is a very general belief which is carefully festered by Germans and Turks and from which Ain-ed-Dcwleh is (?thought) exempt that we and cur allies are in desperate position; contrast is being drawn between mild action taken by Russia tor murder of her Vice-Consul at Ispahan and vigour with which she would have displayed her displeasure at such an occurrence in the past aim conclusion is drawn that Russia is really powerless to help herself even in Persia. Ain-ed-Dcwleh may know better but he prefers not to risk, his popularity with noisy demo cratic minority in Majlis by taking energetic measures to step constant and flagrant violation of Persian neutrality by Germans and allies of that party and he thinks that, aswe do not show ourselves capable cf protecting cur own interests he re, he can satisfy us with promises and half-measures * As for the future he reflects that if friction between the two legations was possible before the war, when their Governments were allies, disagree ments bet we exi them in tuture may make it possible for Persia to play one Power off against the ether, as before the 1007 agreement. kith this state cf thinjgs at the capital, we are confronted with an attack on the Bushire Residency, an attack beyond question directly due to German intrigue and of which Persian Government had every knowledge and warning. I submit that, coming as it does after the out rage at Ispahan, i^^g,^solutely imperative that we and PiUssia should take decisive action at on ce and I urge for consideration cf two Governments that Russian force at Kasvin and Resht should be raised to 5000 with a pro per proportion of cavalry and guns (which Ain-ed-Dcwleh new agrees is accessary) and that we seize Bushire, ' ,N 11 ' 'w.***.-*-****-**^^ Bunder Abbas, Lingah and Mchamraerah and occupy Hormuz and — ^ ^ that having done this we inform Persia that we shall re tain possession until reparation Is made for attack at Bushire and until German intrigues are put a stop to by arrest cf various German (?agents) now at work in Persia. It Ain-ed-Dcwleh should not retain office, such ac tion is T a fortiori’ more necessary. Failing it we must be prepared to be exposed to the possibility of further outrage and to see Germans tree to do what they like except where we are able to use cur own resources. Russian Minister entirely agrees in this view and is telegraphing to Petrcgrad in this sense. Addressed to Foreign Office, No. 247. Repeated tc Petrograd, Government of India, Basrah Bushire.(1 &gt;1 0 i [vwA 1 From Sir P. Cox, Basra, \ 5th July, 1915. (Addressed Foreign, repeated to Tehran and Bush ire for repetition to Shiraz.) Following is my No. 1398 B. of 4th to Simla and Tehran. This recent attack on us at Bushire, winch has been long expected and planned and of which Persian Government has had lull warning from time of Listeman’s arrest, is indistinguishable from an act of war ; but I am aware that it is not policy of Mis Majesty’s Government to treat it as such. 1 venture, however, as Resident [? Persian] Gulf, to urge that we should make prompt use of incident both obUgatww-M** Persian Government -mcn^ver abandoned their present attitude of veiled hostility and adopted- a really neutral demeanour, and also to take active measures ourselves for preserva tion of those interests in Pars and elsewhere which Persian Government is unable or unwilling to protect. In former direction I would urge that we present ultimatum on following lines :— (1.) That present Governor-General of Pars should be immediately recalled and his recall publicly announced. (T.) That gendarmes in Pars should be recalled forthwith to their duties on road and that they should be withdrawn altogether from Bushire-Borasjun section, which should be delivered charge of Governor, Bushire, who will maintain guard from funds to be supplied from Bushire Customs, under our supervision. (3.) Arrest or recall of all [(lermans ?] from Pars. (4.) Deposition and proclamation as outlaws of following local Khans : Rais Ali Dilwari, Zair Takly of Tangistan, Sheikh [?J of Ohahkutah and his son Mahomet who have been concerned in recent attack, and removal of Ghazanfar-us-Sultaneh from Borasjun and replacement by nominee agreeable to us; and expulsion from Pars of Seyyid Murteza,4ie*44»ge disturbers of 1909 now concerned with above. Failing acceptance of these terms within 48 hours, and failing execution within 10 days, we should assume control over Customs house, Bushire, hold revenue, and dis [ ? ] despatch of merchandise* inland pending compliance with above ultimatum. As Resident 1 would further recommend, if military resources admit of it, that we should send an armed recon imlssa nce to ra ze to wersof K han &lt;d Chahkutah at AhmadiyGvhanBf Borasjun at Borasjun. We should also bombard Dilwar from seawards as we have done before. I am confident if we were to control this action, and were to warn friendly Khans of our intentions, latter would co-operate themselves in interests of law and order, and settle affairs in Bushire hinterland in a way conducive to our future interests. I’hey have, in fact, repeatedly offered to do so. For occupation of Bushire Custom house and action above recommended it does not seem to me, as a layman, that garrison would need to be increased temporarily by more than two regiments, one mountain battery, and two squadrons of cavalry. Continued presence of man-of-war would be necessary. . As regards Germans, experience shows all rascally element m Bushire hinterland*Zon side of German faction, and iiicapalih-'-;—i+o- bribes, how ever great, has produced no results. It is possible, how r eyer, that failure of attack on Bushire may alter situation, and that some of their recent friends may now be ready to turn on Germans, as happened on ligris.Of, - '; v .v Immediate and Confidential. r 'CjblOl [ 15 a ] 9 r o ^ £ '* %*' ^ - V ...... The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of telegram, as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, , I 9 I 5- (a - w ^ L... at.^ 'Vc ^ ^ a itTMa Document la the Property of Hla Britannic Majesty's OoTernment, and should be returned to the Foreign Offlee when done with unle ss required for official use.] PEBS1A . POLITIOAI i . Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran). Mt-h - &gt; D. 8.50 p.m., July 14th 1915. H. 1 a.ra., July 15th 1915. Nc; 247. Urgent. 9 Q •X m V far) My telegram No, 242 Cabinet crisis still continues and. although it seems certain that Ain-ed-Dowleh will retain oifice, he is already tailing of doing without Farm an -i&lt;arma a &amp; iuii.xij.str y of the Interior. Should this final concession he made to pro-German party, Ain-ed-Dcwleh will he sc dependent on them that it will he hopeless to expect that anything w:,ll he done to check German action, as it is, small (sic) hegi ning to fulfil explicit promises made to me to hold up German emissaries has been arrested by resignation of Ministers. Fact is that there is a very general belief which is carefully festered by Germans and lurks and from which Ain-ed-Dcwleh is (?thought) exempt that we and cur allies are in desperate position; contrast is being drawn between mild action taken by Russia for murder of her Vice-Consul at Ispahan and vigour with which she would have displayed her displeasure at such an occurrence in the past and conclusion is drawn that Russia is really powerless to help herself even in Persia. Ain-ed-Dcwleh may know bette but he prefers not to risk, his popularity with noisy demo cratic minority in M&amp;jlis by taking energetic measures to step constant and flagrant violation of Persian neutrality by Germans and allies of that party and he thinks tnat, as weJL &gt; we dc not show ourselves capable of protecting cur own interests here, ne can satisfy us with promises and half-measures. as for the future he reflects that if friction between the two legations was possible before one wax , when their Governments were allies, disagree ments between them in future may make it possible for Persia to play one Power off against the other, as before the 1907 agreement. With this state of things at the capital, we are* confronted with an attack on the Bus hi re Residency, an attack beyond question directly due to German intrigue and of which Persian Government had every knowledge and warning. • I submit that, coming as it does after the out rage at Ispahan, it is absolutely imperative that we and Piussia should take decisive action at once and I urge for consideration of two Governments that Russian force at Kasvin and Resht should be raised to 5000 with a pro per proportion of cavalry and guns (which Ain-ed-Dowleh now agrees is rjgcessary) and that we seize Bushire, Bunder Abbas, Lingah and Mo hammerah and occupy Hormuz and that having done this we inform Persia that we shall re-' tain possession until reparation is made for attack at Bushire and until German intrigues are put a stop to by arrest of various German (?agents) now at work in Persia. It Ain-ed-Dcwleh should not retain office, such ac tion is 1 a fortiori’ more necessary. Failing it we must be prepared to be exposed to the possibility of further outrage and to see Germans tree to dc what they like except where we are able to use cur own resources. Russian Minister entirely agrees in this view ana is telegraphing to Petrcgrad in this sense. Addressed to Foreign office, No. 247. Repeated to Petrograd, Government of India, Basrah Bushire,. iA. 1 r r '“7 Id 6 o c / From Viceroy, \Aih July 1915. Foreign Secret. [R.] Bushire. My telegram 13th from Trevor, 301 C., 13th July “ Ihe party of tribesmen are reported to have come from Dilwar and few from Dasti. Regiment worked down island this morning and found none left. Simultaneous attack was to have been made last night by this party and another coming straight across to Masilleh, near mail caravan. Latter, however, appears to have thought better of it. % Bodies of Oliphant and Ranking brought hack this morning; only revolvers and ammunition had been removed, nothing else, not even watches. One Sepoy’s body also found. It appears one was killed and two wounded, and not four killed as previously reported. Am trying to ascertain whether second party proposes to attack to-night. Governor thinks not.” CL-''’ ' Aj y#- V y July. Following y / F-’:f 1 ;ji. :? h 4 o 14-7-IS' • l 4- 1 / Foreign Secret. From Viceroy, 1 3th July 1915. Hu shire. Major Hevor telegraphed on 12th July, No. 4, »7 . 7 L . (R.) A lepoit was received to-day that a party of tribesmen were coining to lie in wait in nullah south of German Residency. It seemed possible that this was probably one of the usual false reports ; but Major Oliphant, 96th Regiment, and Captain Ranging went with a party of sowars and infantry to reconnoitre. Unfortunately they apparently came suddenly on a large, well ■ concealed party of the enemy, who immediately opened tire at close range. Regret to say that both officers and four sepoys are reported killed. Enemy then advanced to attack southern outpost lines. Heavy firing took place at sunset and soon after, but has been only desultory since. “Attack has been apparently repulsed. “ Addressed to Cox, sent to Teheran, India.IThlB Document la the Property of Hla Britannic Majesty ’s OoTernment, and ahonld he retamed to the foreign Office wh en done with nn|o B8 required for oftiolal use.] My telegram Democrats are finding great difficulty in forming a Cabinet and the Shah is giving support to Ain-ed- Dowleh and Parma Parman so that there is some prospect of the Cabinet resuming office, Russian Minister has telegraphed to his Government recommending that the force at Snzeli should be strengthened and Aiin-ed- Dowleh has intimated to us that the arrival of 1,000 more men or a few more guns would have an excellent effect. I hope that this can be done. Russian Minister has also urged the despatch of force from Transcaspia into Khorassan. Addressed to Foreign Office and Petrograd. ’• r; W 1 ' PERSIA 1^ J POLI TI CAL Eecypher of telegram from Mr. Marling ('leliran). CP J. y 1C oil , 19 IP (d. 12.15 p.m. r. 6,45 p.m, July 12th). No.242.A [This Docnment la the Property at Hla Britannic Majesty's flovernmen t, alionld be returned So Ilia foreign Office when done with nninaa required tor official use.] ♦ ^ PERSIA (90995/15). Cyphertelegrara to Mr. Marling (Tehran). Foreign Office. July 9th 1915. 6 p.m. No.172. f Your telegram No.229 (of 7th July. Farman Farm). Action approved. Your telegram No.226 not yet received.• Repeated to Sir G.Buchanan No.1395. uiy, r o z O fr * ^ ^ , £ -.y Ob'* ^2 S POLITIOAT..[This Document la the Propertj of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to tha Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] r~ % 9522 Ci ■ fcru wri PERSIA 1 1 O ?! CX x ‘''AlXl POLITiOAT, Decypher of telegram from l,:r. Mrli llg (Tehran). July 10th 1915. (d. 4.40 p.m. r. 6.10 p.m. July 10th). No.239. (H). Following is repetition of my telegram No.226. Begins:- 'Cabinet resigned July 3rd but seems likely to iesume office with little alteration.' |A. -iC tTHis Docnmenl Is the Property of His Britannic Majestrs Governmen t, and slioiild be returned to the Foreign Office w hen done with required for official use.] P'’ PERSIA. Decypher r Dr 4: r Q r p p ID. r PQLITICAT, , I'/ir r Iviar 1 iny (T eher an) I 9^2 i tkm £sc* fa** ( t July lotli*' 1915 8r5 r p r na, July loth, 1915 No O 40 r an 4&gt; ^ j * Urgent 7-&amp;° H t Is ! W telegram N 0r 232 r At an auaience wnich Russian Iviimster and t had of the Shah to-day we pointed out to His Majesty the danger towards which the country is drifting and told him that our Governments would view resignation of the Cabinet at the bidding of a minority in Medjliss as a sign that Persia was under the influence of enemy and that as in those circumstances there could be no prospect of Persia observing a real neutrality by putting end to German in trigues and preventing their endeavours to create troubles in Afghanistan etCr we had no course but to suggest to our Governments that they should consider what measures they should take to protect their own interests^ And we urged the Shah to use his influence to maintain present Government P From the Shah’s reply it seems that the Cabinet has at length definitely resigned and that although he would like to maintain it he doubts his power to do so. Crisis is therefore likely to continue and so long as it lasts no action can be taken to hold up emissary from going to Afghanistan* In view of the situation as re gards that country now disclosed by Government of India’s Addressed to F P C* sent to India and Petrograd[12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. mil / I 9 I 5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Iiyclia. “Uf-trLf- uolhT The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the nnder-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, yf (o , 1915 . (f d Reference to previous correspondence Letter Foreiqn Office: from J ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /k-C. f 12JUU315D (StmilnT^ tedler^seLtt toCopy. VMP/CON ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY LIMITED, Qiumm hou Confidential (88622) 2nd July 19 sir: I beg to enclose copy of a telegram received froL, our Agents advising tiuit a drilling party wLicli we have now working on ti e Island of Kioto has been attacked, by armed natives with the object of murdering our English employees, probably as the result of the usual political (German) intrigues. In this connection I have considered it advisable to enclose a ; ernorandum of a conversation I had recently with His Highness asr-el-Mulk on the subject of these intrigues At first I had not Intended troubling His Majesty’s Government with an account of this conversation .because they have, doubtless, already been made fully acquainted with these views, either by His Highness himself or by the Persian Minister, but in view of this further indica tion of the activities of the Germans in Persia i have on re-consideration thought it better to submit the enclosed l ernorandum. We are to-day in receipt of a telegram from ! ohammerah reporting that it is in contemplation to withdraw the British troops now stationed at Ahwass. In view.however. of the continued activities of the Germans.and of the proximity to our Oilfields of their present headquarters (Isfahan) 1 venture to point out that the withdrawal of the The Under Secretary of State Foreign Office.the troopo from Uie Ahwoz diGtrict would place the lives of our employees, and the properties of the Company, in great Jeopardy. 1 have etc. t (Signed) C. Greenway. Ghairrnan.iiiSl B CONFI Ifl/tAT ION OF TELEGRAM TO essrs ot-rlck Scott and Joicpany limited, Mohansneran ; essrs Anglo-l'aralan Oil Company ikilted, London. Uatad 24th Juno 1915. Secret Cypher Kishm camp attacked by araed natives 11th June apparently cole object murder Europeans probably result of usual political intrigues all staff safe Kenjam effective action in progress.MSMORttTOM OP AN INTSRVI3W with iiis Highness Nacr-el-! ulk, late decent Persia, on the 18th June,1915. of I was recently invited by the Persian Minister to iXiBdu his Highness Nasr^ei^Kmik at dinner *to discuss the present political situation in Persia% I found that the principal object of the meeting was to give His Highness an opportunity of representing his views on the situation t and as to the steps which, in his opinion! the British and Russian Governments should take to deal with It* in the expectation time , ht be dis posed to pass these on to His Majesty 4 s Government as an expression of my own views (i ) ' He begOT by explaining %iie serious dileoma in which the Persian Government have been placed by the recent German intrigues, and their total inability in the present state of their finances to check tnese intrigues and other wise fulfil their duties as a Neutral i ower* The anti-British and ;Russian propaganda was, he said, being carried on to such an alarming extent all over Persia, that, unless speedily checked, it would be extremely difficult, if not impossible, to overcome its effect upon i ahomrnedan fooling. it was, he said, needless for him to point out the great danger of this to British interests in the diet generally, and more particularly in India,and therefore he considered it essential that hue British Govern rnent sliould take immediate and strong steps to deal with the situation* i asked him v/hat wore the stops he v/ould reconimenu* Ho replied that the Persian Government should be called uponupon at once by the British and Russian Governments to carry out their duties as a Neutral Power, and bo asked to fl) immediately remove from the Country or arrest all the 'agents provocateur' ?*ho are now engaged in spreading this propaganda, and in supplying disaffected tribesmen with arms and money, (2) obtain from toe German and Austrian I inisters at Teheran satisfactory ascur&amp;nc e § r c 3y « 0r indirectly any further breaches of neutrality ttvit h..y v/ill not coim^it^otneniise to call upon them to'' lenve toe Country, (3) demand toe immediate departure of the Turkish Minister in view of the act of mt committed by his Government in invading Persia, (4) take toe necessary measures for driving out toe Turk!to troops now occupying Persian territory* he went on to explain that these steps could not be taken by the I ersian Government without a strong Military force, and. that to raise and maintain this force a large cum of money was essential. This money - and this was no doubt the main objective of the 'discussion' - must, he said, be supplied by the Governments whose interests were at stake, to counteract the potent influence of the German money now being scattered about in ]ersia. I expressed doubt as to any ! Hilary force which it would be practicable for the Persian Government to raise being able to deal with toe present situation inasmuch as a considerable time must necessarily elapse before such a force could be trained, equipped, and distributed over the affected districts of Persia, and suggested that perhaps toe better course would be for his Government to apply to toe British - and Russian Governments for the necessary ilitary assistance* To this he replied that the British Government had alreadyalready given this assistance in the South without being asked (i) I said 'Precisely, they had to do tuis because British lives and property were being attacked by urks and by Persian tribesmen and your Government had ndt the troops necessary to give them protection. The position is very much the sarne in the North. ,vhy not ask the iussian uovernment to give you similar assistance there** # he replied that to deal with the situation in the North the Russians would require a very large force (which it is doubtful if they could spare at the present time) inammch as the Jhissians were so unpopular there that not only would they have the Turks to contend wish, but practically all the iersian tribesmen, bhereas, if Persian troops were employed a very small force would suffice, as they would be fighting in their own Country, and secure the co-operation of every Persian. (1 did not think it worth while to pucntion the latb 1 ,ement # experience hae shown that many of the Persian but past tribes now co-operating with the Turks are extremely hostile to their own Government) At the end of the discussion I asked His Highness if he desired me to put what m had said before His Majesty’s Government ae an expression of his views - to which he replied 'No - please don’t do that - as since 1 r,signed the vegency 1 have retired entirely from political life* but the matter is such an important one for Your Country* with whom * as you know, I have always been in great sympathy, that 1 have thought it well to give you my views in case you may consider it advisable to press your Government to take some action. At present, so far as X can judge, they appear to have no pol icy and to be taking no steps whatever to check the German intrigues* This*I m.y .A &amp;m sure # will lead to terrible consequences for Great Britain unless speedy and strong action is taken'. (Signed) C. Greenway.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ government, and , shonld be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless * required for official use.] i I ''1 PERSIA. (89685/15). POLITICAL. Cypher telegram to Mr. Marling(Tehran) Foreign Office. July 6th, 1915. 1.55 p.m, No. 166. (i b Russian Government agree to payment of subsidy of £1000 to Farman Farma for one month as experiment off His Majesty'3s Government concur. They have no desire that His Highness should employ this subsidy to overthrow Aim ed Dowleh but merely expect him in accordance with his promise to check agita tion and to ; v win over public opinion should present Cabinet fall and new one be made under Farman Farma the subsidy might be continued so long as he remains true. Your Russian Colleague is authorised to promise subsidy if you are similarly instructed. Before sending you instructions I should like to have you views as to the proposal.rriilB Docnment Is the Properly of H1 b Brttaimtc Majesty s Oovenunent. and shonld be retnrned to the foreign Office when done with nniB B H reqnlred for official use.] —\ L ?. &gt; V J POLITICaI, P JLliblA J Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran) July 7th. D. 10.50.^m. R. 3.15.p.m. Nc. 229. n ^ July 7th, 1915. ^ bM iq'' 11 S^\lO ■ My telegram Nc. 226. Russian Minister informs me that ycu are being consulted hy Russian Government as to support to be given to Parma Parma and I therefore explain position. Crisis which brought about resignation of Cabinet was due to attack engineered at German instigation by democrats against Parma Parma whose energy in dealing with German emissaries has made him faery obnoxious to them. Although attack failed and Government might have had a majority in Medjdiss Prime Minister seemed ready to sacrifice Parma Parma and we informed him that if he did sc we should consider he had given way to German pressure and that he must not count upon same support as hitherto. We have reason to suppose that Parma Parma with cur assistance can form body of supporters in Medjliss which will make him indispensable to cabinet and prolong its existence. We prefer to see both Ain-ed-Dcwleh and Parma Parma in cabinet but latter is more resolute in dealing with German intrigues and if Ain-ed-Dowleh whose conduct has been very ambiguous of late should resign we could fall back on Parma Parma to take his place. I have been giving Parma Parma assistance of the nature he requires and I hope Russian Government will agree to (? group omitted 'instruct') Russian Minister to -do same. N Repeated to Petrcgrad.[This Document Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] 1 r *5 PERSIA POLITICAL t Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran) July 8th ? 1.915, Do 3,55 p 0 m* July 8th, R, 9 a,m t , July Sth 0 No . 23 S. Following sent to-day to Foreign Office No. 232: / My telegram No, 229. Information having reached me privately that Shah’s mind has been influenced against Parma Parma by democrats and Germans by reviving an old story that 1 arma Parma is plotting to dethrone him and that Shah had consequently intimated to Ain^ed'-Dowleh that Parma Parma should not remain in Cabinet, I called on Minister for Foreign Af fairs this morning and told him in name o . two Lega jio--u that we regarded present struggle as a test case wh mh ca qhrw whether or not Cabinet was going to continue to truckle lo af ScrSs U Gerrans ^d that if Government f ave way we should warn cur Governments Aiat we could no ^ no lo g (sic'' hold out any hope that Russian Government would maintain (? real) neutrality by putting end ■noGerman^n-r trigues agaiist us and that we should advise cur Gcverments (? to) consider wfeat other measures could he taken to proueoj our lnt ,®yg^ red Hls Excellency to inform Shah of foregoing already sent a (? message omitted ...n very raucn mnc sense ^directly to Shah^^ fQr Fcreign Affa irs that while I understood that Government of India had no uneasiness on the subject of Afghanistan I was quite ^ntident considering vastness of struggle “ S aL' iLpersian Gov ernment was in no mood to run any^isks would ernmen't would do iiot;hj.ng oo su ■ see what they could do themselves. Sent to Petrcgrad. h K' 5-'''K 4 v Telegram, No. 1118 B., dated (and received) the l^Sth May From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz :— Begins. Wassmuss is now flying German flag. Telegram P., No. 50, dated the 16th (received 17th) May 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please see my telegram, 183. There has been a very marked improvement in situation during last week and Russian Minister and I think that Persian Government will check any further Turco-German activities and succeed in maintaining their neutrality if we can give them reasonable support. On 13th May we saw the Prime Minister and told him that we desired to discuss the situation with him and especially the best manner of co-operation. We knew that the Persian Government required money but it would be useless for them to expect (that) (the) two Governments would discuss large measures of financial reorganisation at this moment, and we could hold out hopes of nothing more than moderate advances from time to time to tide over period (of) war. We also mentioned that we must have something definite to submit (to) our Governments and we should like (to) have a statement in writing as a guide showing what would be required per mensem. His Highness replied that he quite understood. By his own methods he had already done enough to prove that he wished to work with us. He now hoped that a small sum which was required for urgent expenses could be found, and with Russian Minister’s concurrence I said that Imperial Bank of Persia was willing to find (—?) tomans desired. In continuation His Highness said that he desired to work on those lines and that opportunity should be granted to him to work his own w^ay and that we should continue to give support if w^e were satisfied with results. A system in fact of payment by results as it were. His Highness appears to be very confident of being able to master the situation and he has some hope of inducing mejlis either to adjourn for a long holiday or grant him full power. I fear it will not be possible to re-establish general control over the Persian Finance. B:ltta!i0U8 (that ?) was abolished when law of Jauza was repealed. At all events itTs'pretty certain new law which the mejlis are now discussing will not provide any real safeguards. But I consider that control over the expend iture of any advances two Governments may agree to make can be kept by us, and we can make sure that they are applied to the object which we have m view viz., maintenance of neutrality of Persia. The statement mentioned m paragraph 2 above has not yet been furnished by the Government of Persia. Addressed Foreign Office, London; repeated Basrah and Petrograd. A Telegram R., No. 1129 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) May 1915. From ■The Hon’blr Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I, Political Resident in tiie Persian Gulf, Basrah, T 0 Thu Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegram No. 1109 B., 14-th May. Following from Shiraz, dated May 14th:— Begins. I fear that unless Persian Government consent to send instruc tions to Kawam, making him responsible (or jointly responsible with merie) for good order in towm of Shiraz, we shall soon have serious tr' India. Forf; h il •_ h L i A i\ , dated 10 JUN 1915 No2 A certain Saiyid has been openly preaching jehad, expulsion of foreigners, &amp;c., to large crowds, for the last, three evenings, in road between Consulate and city, and in spite of ray official remonstrances, Governor-General has done nothing to stop him. Our employes are being threatened and terrorised and general situation is becoming very strained. Kawam is fully prepared to take steps to maintain order, on receipt of formal instructions from Tehran, and I venture to hope that Your Excellency will be able to arrange this. French and Russian Consular Agents and Armenian community keep urging me to impress on Your Excellency urgent necessity for this measure. Addressed to Tehran; repeated to Basrah and Bushire. Telegram P., No. 51, dated the 17th (received 18th) May 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please refer to Cox’s telegrams, 1081 to 1086 B. and your telegram, No. 118. I do not think that I could offer any useful observations on Cox’s in dividual suggestions, as he is so much more intimately acquainted with affairs (of) districts in question, but I would like it to be understood that I fully concur (in) views expressed by Government of India in their telegram No. 493 , dated 15th May, that as a general line of conduct it will (be) more prudent to bind ourselves by promises and assurances for future as little (as) possible and to rely on subsidiary secret service funds in case (of) need. Telegram, No. 1131 B., dated (and received) the 18th May 1915. From—The Hon’blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Peecy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz, dated 16th:— Begins. Signaller, Kazerun, reported yesterday that Hussain Beg of Konar Takhteh had arrived at Kamarij with 200 tufangehis and that fighting was going on between him and Kalantur of Kamarij. Ends. Second telegram, dated 17th :— Begins. Fighting still continues ; several Konar Takhteh men have been killed. Affair does not seem very serious at present, but road is temporarily rendered unsafe. Captain Oertengren is on his way hack to Shiraz with gendarmerie ex pedition, Ends, Telegram P., No. S. 500, dated the 19th May 1915. From—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla, To—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London (repeated to Tehran, and Basrah). Persian situation. .Please see my telegram, dated 15th May, and Sir Percy Cox’s telegram, No. 1084 B., dated 12th May. Government of India are of opinion that any negotiations with Mekran Chiefs in view of improved position at Tehran would for the present be premature. In any case, they do not want to pledge themselves to such persons as Mir Barkat or Sardar Saiyid Khan, except in case of absolute necessity. In event of rupture with Persia, the Chiefs of Mekran should be advised generally that those Chiefs will be duly rewarded who stand by us in maintaining peace and order but it should be left to Chiefs themselves, so far as possible, to make definite overtures. With reference to telegram No. 1085 B. of 12th May from Sir P. Cox, it would be a mistake for His Majesty’s Government to commit themselves to the Vali of Pusht-i-Kuh at present, as he has shown himself quite unreliable. $„-n,?T US \ t r' i ‘ K !' h :T n0t dalnase l i s seriously so long as the Batttiaris stand in wdh His Majesty s Governraent. It, on theother hand, Bakhtiaris are inimical to us, 1 usht- 1 -Kuh s attitude will not greatly affect situation. Government of India are, theretore, ot opinion that any negotiations with Pusht-i-Kuh on lines proposed arc to be deprecated. - &gt; Government of India will address Your Lordship shortly re^ardin^ Cox’s other telegrams relating to Buskire and Gulf ports which are at present under consideration. • 1 r . r r r • Telegram P., dated the 18th (received 19th) May 1915. From His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla. . , The d r s P ( at ^ h . . of Russian tro ops to Ilesbt and Enzeli and simultaneous re- mforeement ot British detachment in Bushire is suggested by His Majesty's Minister at Tehran in order to deter pro-German elements in Persia and strengthen hands of new Persian Government, tion with the Prussian Government. Could forcement, even as a temporary measure, should occasion demand it ? Foreign Office is in consulta* arrangements be made for rein- Telegram R., No. 183 C., dated (and received) the 19th May 1915, From—The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Your telegram No 162. Tuo hundred and fifty men, being remainder of regiment less fifty men, who uere landed temporarily at Charbar, landed yesterday without any hitch. Addressed to Tehran; repeated to Foreign and Basrah. , Telegram P., No. 52, dated the 19th (received 20th) May 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. The following has been addressed to the London Foreign Office and repeated to Sir P. Cox, Basrah, and Pelrograd :— Begins : Yesterday, about midnight, the Manager of the Bussian Bank at Ispahan was murdered hy men who afterwards disappeared into the German Consulate close to whicli the murder was committed. The Manager was also Russian Vice-Consul at liumisheh. Slight wounds were inflicted on the Belgian financial agent who was with Manager at the time. The Russian Vice-Consul and His Majesty's Consul-General are convinced that the murderers are connected with a band of ruffians whom the German Consul had recruited for the purpose. As the Governor-General professes, in spite of strictest orders from Tehran, not to be able to take requisite measures as long as the gendar merie is entirely on the Germans’ side, they consider the position of the British and Russian communities to be somewhat dangerous. Of course, I shall give the Russian Minister every possible support to obtain satisfaction, but I feel that it will be imperative for us to show we are ready to give them material support by landing troops at Fuizeli, if the Persian Government is not strong enough to afford it. /&amp; Telegram P., No. 53, dated (and received) the 20th May 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India ialhe Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please refer to Tehran telegram No. 188. 5; Ar/t %&gt;) jwf .4 p&lt; V i,4 Prime Minister tendered his resignation yesterday but consented to remain in office at the request of the Shah. The position of the Prime Minister, however, is not a secure one, as MejliS) which is coming more and moie under Turkish and German influence, displays increasing mistrust of him and is openly hostile to Persian Minister and Minister of the Provinces. A short while back the appearance at Enzeli of two or three thousand men might have proved sufficient, but at the present juncture a larger force, say about six thousand men at the least, is necessary and situation at Ispahan seems to offer a plausible excuse for their despatch. I have no confidence in the ability of Ain-ed-Dowleh to keep things standing in Tehran for more than few days and unless (rest of sentence mutilated). Should Ain-ed.Dowleh fall, the next Persian Cabinet that is formed will owe its existence to influences of German agitators. Addressed to Poreign Office; repeated to India, Pasrah and Petrograd. Telegram P., No. 189 C., dated (and received) the 20th May 1915. From—The First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart - ment, Simla. The Officer Commanding Troops here received a telegram yesterday from the Chief of General Staff, Simla, in which lie was requested to furnish a report on the situation at Bushire, with reference to possibility of hostilities breaking out with Persia. The Officer Commanding consulted me before he despatched his reply and showed me a copy of his report after it had been despatched. His reply was to the following effect“ In my opinion the first thing to he done on the outbreak of hostilities would be for troops to occupy the town, residency and custom-house with one hundred and fifty men, depose the present Governor of Bushire and instal a Military Governor in his stead, and overawe, if possible, the town and neighbouring villages which shelter about I five hundred armed men. I should have to be on my guard against attack by gendarmerie and tribesmen from mainland, composed of about one thousand gendarmerie and three thousand tribesmen, whose object presumably would be to crush force at my disposal and interrupt wireless telegraphy and telegraph communication between Basrah and India”. The Officer Commanding’s report went on to furnish details of^ bis posi tion, &amp;c., and finally stated that in his present position the force at his disposal, viz l seven hundred and fifty men belonging to his owm regiment and His Majesty’s ship “Lawrence” would be insufficient. He added that to be certain of matter he would require in addition one battery Mountain Artillery, one squadron Cavalry and one regiment of Infantry. I report the above for information and beg to say that I agree in a general * wav with Officer Commanding and think that the additional troops he asks for would be necesssary. If war becomes imminent, perhaps the troops could be brought up the Gulf and stationed at Lao or some other handy place, as in order 5 to he effective, prompt action would be necessary. A cruiser would he a verv desirable addition. If one was brought up a landing party from here could' occupy town, Eesidency (and ?) custom-house—wete your telegram No. 1806 B. Addressed Sir P. Cox; repeated to Poreign. ————— Telegram R., No. 1156 B., dated (and received) the 22nd May 1915. From The Hon’blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegram No. 1029 B.S A Following from Shiraz, No. 156 :-™- 5 Begins. Kawam and Soulet have had meeting and have agreed to do all in their power to maintain neutrality as long as this is policy of Persian Gov ernment. They also agree that present Governor-General is chiefly responsible for unrest in Pars and that his removal is desirable in public interest. They ^ have cemented good relations existing between themselves. Ghulam Ali Khan Nawab has also had interview with Soulet on my be half and has obtained from him satisfactory assurances regarding preservation of neutrality amongst his tribes. Wassmuss tried to bribe Soulet with offer of five thousand pounds but Soulet refused to have anything to do with him. Addressed Tehran ; repeated to Basrah and Bushire. % Telegram P., No. T.-13, dated the 22nd (received 23rd) May 1915. From—The Hon’ble Ltetjtenant-Colonel Sib Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I. , Political Resident in the Persian, Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to Bushire, Tehran and India Office). Kindly refer to comments of His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, and the Government of India on the series of telegrams beginning with my No. 1081. Doubtless they are in a position to appraise situation from a more detach ed and longer standpoint than I can, but I respectfully submit further observa tions as follows. In the autumn of 1914, when a rupture with Turkey was expected and when the opinion was expressed by the military authorities in India that our resources were fully occupied and that troops for the Persian Gulf could not be spared, we did not hesitate to discount the fact by making reassur ing announcements to many Persian Gulf potentates and by offering induce ments to Basrab, Mohammerah and Kuwait notables in order to make sure of their benevolent neutrality or co-operation. To me the position at the present moment appears to be much the same with regard to Persia. Brimd facie, we have no troops to spare with which we can protect our interests or support our friends. Therefore, I submit that, in order to ensure their benevolent neutrality and to obtain, if possible, their co-operation and thus discount host (s) of doubtful elements, the natural alternative is to offer practical inducements to those elements which are now friendly with us. I am afraid that disburse ment (of) periodical secret service doles and other alternatives which have been proposed by the Government of India will not be either sufficient or practicable for the propose. Provided that our friends receive sufficient inducements to repay them for risk(s) and odium entailed, they can look after themselves and prevent the spreading of hostilities. We must face the possibility of these friendly elements leaving us and consequently creating much more serious situation which will necessitate military dispositions on a proportionately larger scale than those the Government of India contemplate, if we take no action on t e lines suggested. / /-f^ , Telegram P., No. T.-14, dated the 22nd (received 23rd) May 1915. From— The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.LE., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to Secretary of State for India and His Britannic Majesty's Minister at Tehran). Exclusion of Arabistan from sphere of disturbances will in the event o£ outbreak of war with Persia be a matter of great (?) consequence. Ihe position at present is that Beni Turuf and Haweizeh and Bawi tribes have submitted and only Chaab remain “out”. It is hoped that latter will also submit within a few days. 1 am of opinion that we should on the outbreak of uar6 immediately offer the Sheikhs of those tribes substantial bribes to induce them to stand with the Sheikh of Mohammerah and with us. If we did this and at the same time £*ave them an undertaking that we will in future take a benevolent interest in their fair treatment and welfare as well as in that of the Sheikh of Mohammerah, my opinion is that we should have them on our side and that Arabistan would, if not actually attacked by Bakhtiari or other elements hostile to us, remain undisturbed. I am about to interview Bakhtiari Khans with regard to Bakhtiari interests and will, as soon as possible, report the result. It is also my opinion that steps should also be taken to secure the neu trality of the Kuhgelu tribes in the event of war. Telegram P., No. 55, dated the 23rd (received 24th) May 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. I have received information that late in the month of March last Herr Pugin ordered two Germans to proceed to India in disguise, on the pretext of trading interests. These men were to get in touch with Chinese (?) Committee who had also been sent by Germans. In the beginning of this month Pugin wrote to the German Legation at Tehran to say that emissaries had arrived and that operations had commenced.67 /(p- Telegram P., dated the 25th May 1915. From—H is Excellency the Viceroy, Simla, To—His Majesty^s Secretary of State for India, London. * Serial No. 120 . . ^^ ease re ^ e r to your telegram,* 18th instant. Persia. We have anticipated your request so far as to despatch the remaining four companies of 96th Infantry on the 18th instant to Bushire making a total tlim’e of one battalion which, unless war takes place with Persia, seems to us sufficient infantry. We can despatch in addition four mountain guns and one squadron cavalry as a temporary measure if this is really necessary as a precaution against war. Force “ D ” must furnish any further infantry which may be required. J ; 7- Telegram R., dated (and received) the 23rd May 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran. ’ f To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- r*- F ment, Simla. ° ; It appears that Agent of German Consul, Ispahan, set up wireless tele graphy apparatus about two miles from that town and messages were sent here by it. Otherwise I can say nothing more as to its range. Particulars (coming to notice ?) of Persian Government, German Consul sent (for and ?) instructed stoppage of working it. Addressed to Foreign Office; sent to India, Basrah. /P. Telegram P., dated the 25th (received 26th) May 1915. From—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla. On the 23rd instant, His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran reports by telegram the arrival at Enzeli from Envekera, on the 21st instant, of two Sotnias of Cossacks under a Lieutenant-General. Telegram P., dated the 25th (received 26th) May 1915. From—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla. Serial No. 107. On the 21st instant following Minister at Tehran :— Persian situation. Please refer to your telegram of the 15th instant. instructions were sent to His Majesty’s “ The views expressed by the Government of India with regard to Ears and Bushire Hinterland are approved generally by His Majesty’s Government— vide the telegram of the 15th instant from His Excellency the Viceroy. In con nection with the Bakhtiaris, it is preferable to make rewards now by cash payments than to make promises of Governorships or other political privileges in the future. There are also weighty objections to Bakhtiari Khan being encouraged in projects which give him access to Persian Gulf littoral.68 “From your tele-ram o£ the 17th instant I understand that you are of the Jirom your ieie 0 i game opinion. In the circumstances, and Serial No. 117 . and wIigh you consider the situation requires it, you may authorise Sir P. Cox to negotiate, ^jeot t 0 the above limitations, according to the In’tant ‘from His Serial No. 107. T\-r&gt;f.] Ipnev the Viceroy.” a. r 20. Telegram R., No. 199 C., dated the 27th (received 28th) May 1916. _ From—M «job A. P. Tkvoe, C.I.E., Officer on Special duty in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. , To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- ment, Simla. Poliowing is repetition of telegram from Shiraz, No. 161:— “ Wassmuss has been absent from Shiraz for some days and it was reported that he was with Kashgai. . « . . v. « Signaller at Borasjun now reports however that he has arrived at Ahram in Tangistan.” , £(. Telegram R., No. 198 C., dated (and received) the 27th May 1915. From—M ajor A. P. Trevor, C.I.'E., Officer on Special duty in the Persian Gulf, To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. * serial No. 135 . Urgent. Shiraz telegram,* No. 161. Wassmuss arrived at Borasjun this morning. I think it is improbable that he will come into Bushire, but will content himself with working up hostile Khans to attack Bustnre or Haider Possibly he might try and force an issue by coming m with a large escort ° £ ^Can^Your Excellency get Persian Government to take steps to obtain his immediate recall, as he in only be where he is to create trouble. In this case should any on hnes^of my telegram Vide Serial No. 69. ... v Perhaps Officer Commanding Gendarmerie would issue orders prohibiting gendarmes from accompanying Wassmuss on his filibustering trips. Addressed Tehran; repeated Shiraz, Basrah and Foreign. Telegram P., No. S. 519, dated the 29th May 1915. From—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla, , To H is Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London (repeated to His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran ; Sir Percy Cox, Basrah). Please refer to telegramsf Nos. T.-13 f Serial Nos. 128 and 129 . an( j rp .X4 of 22nd instant from Sir P. Cox. Our reassuring announcements made in autumn 1914 to the Persian Gulf tentates were addressed to semi-independent or independent Arab Chiefs, for ?k° most nart in Treaty relations wilh us, and except m case of Bin Sand, Koweit and Mohammerah, in no way committed us,_ the definite co-operation of these Chiefs being essential as regards the occupation of Basrah. We think that in the event of war with Persia the following policy should be definitely accepted , , , (a) We should leave Persia as a whole severely alone and take what steps are possible to extricate our Consuls and Minister, and i Tfnooi’n to take such action in North Persia as she chooses.f- -L 69 (b) An endeavour should, however, he made by us to safeguard the Angio-Persian Oil Company’s pipe line and property and Mohammerah. (&lt;?) We should, if possible, continue to hold Bushire and the telegraph stations at Jask and Charbar. Por purposes of (&amp;) we further recommend, as proposed in Sir P. Cox’s telegram* T.-14, an offer of substantial sums to Chaab, Benituruf and other Arab tribes in addition to arrangements with Bakhtiaris sanctioned in your tele- gramf of 25th instant. In regard to the . Kuhgelu tribes, Sir P. Cox may similarly be given a free hand. In our telegram4 dated 25th instant, we have already, as regards (c), stated what military reinforcements are possible at Bushire. It is essential, however, that these troops should be supported by ships of war, which should also effectively blockade the ports of the Persian Gulf. We see no reason to hold Lingah from which the Vice-Consulate could be withdrawn. With regard to the other garrisons our action will depend on developments. •jf Serial No. 134. J Serial No. 131. Telegram P., No. 20 T., dated the 27th (received 28th) May 1915. p rom The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to His Majesty's Secretary of State and His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran). In continuation of my telegram§ No. § Serial No. 129. rj\ ^ 0 f 22nd instant. On the 23rd and 24th instant I met Bakhtiari Khans Sirdar Bahadur and Jang and discussed matters fully with them. That Persia would enter into war against us. they professed to find it impossible to believe, but expressed their comnfete inability to give either verbally or in writing any undertaking as to Stitude of the tribes in the event of the Persian Government being drawn into war They argued that the tribes would risk having the whole ot Persia against t'hem UMthey openly refused to support the policy of the Government and that thev would -jeopardize the lives of their relations m Tehran Persia would, to their mind, make a grievous mistake by entering into the war but if she did, the 15,000 loyal Bakhtian subjects might nominaTlv have to take up arms but means could be found for not doing so seriously. The negotiations terminated in these two Khans giving ™ e lira. TMJ themselves uMe.t.ke m the ™t F ”‘ '“““K to protect the property and employes of the Company ^ be an of their power maintain order along the Bakhtiau boraei. , , fctsr e. 01, Company’s British community during those 20 days. In consideration of above representations and °f fact ^ have, in order to “ “ al ln “given them each £1,000. I am LTncl evTnt of war heTng declared so far as these two Khans70 are concerned, it is their bond fide intention to do their best to secure that the Oil Company does not suffer harm in their territory ; hut some of ^ the junior Khans hold pro-German views and have been aiming at infringment of irresponsibility and the fact that these two Khans felt their inability to ansvt er ^ for any of the senior Khans or for the tribe warns us of the suspicion that the German Agents have succeeded in squaring some of them. 1 incidentally visited the oil fields and travelled down the pipe line and am submitting to the Army Commander my views regarding their requirements. Ja. Telegram R., No. 200 C., dated the 28th (received 29th) May 1915. From—M ajor A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special duty in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Poliowing from Shiraz, No. 163, dated 28th May: Begins. I had long interview with Governor-General and Ponsette yesterday regarding Wassmuss and German intrigues. Both emphatically disavowed any intention of supporting Wassmuss in any way and promised to telegraph at once to Borasjun ordering gendarmerie and Khans not to assist him. Ends. Telegram R., dated (and received) the 9th May 1915. From— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special duty in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegram No. 198.* I hear Wassmuss has sent a telegram to his 0 Legation stating that English have erect- « senai No. 136. e( j man y fortifications round Bushire and are instigating the Khans of Dashtistan to fight and have sent a gun to Haider Khan, the robber of his caravan. As regards fortifications as mentioned my telegram No. 420,+ village of Tengak was occupied after Haji Ali was t Senai No. 85. expelled and post was established on isthmus and two pickets south of Residency to prevent any attempt by tribesmen to rescue Haji Ali or to raid Residency or telegraph station end of island. Statement re instigation of Khans to fight is totally false and is amusing coming from such a quarter. Recently quarrels at (?) bankara(?) had just been settled without fighting before Wassmuss came on scene. It remains to be (seen) what effect of his coming will be. No gun has been sent to Haider Khan. I have telegraphed above in case the Persian Government makes any representations. There is little doubt that Wassmuss’s object in coming to Borasjun is to • try and get up a combination of Khans to attack Haider Khan. Addressed to Tehran ; repeated Shiraz, Basrah, Foreign.71 T! Telegram P., dated the 30th May 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah. On the 25th instant His Majesty’s Secretary of State telegraphed as follows :—“ Persian situation * * * * * * Viceroy. ” Serial No. 134. _ '4% Telegram P., dated the 29th (received 30th) May 1915. From—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla. • semi No 133 Reference my telegram,* dated the 25th instant. On the 27th instant His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran repeated the following telegram from the British Consul at Resht :— “ I understand that the troops landed are as follows: 200 artillery, 6 quick.fires, 4s guns, 1,200 Cossacks under the command of two Colonels, not Lieutenant-Generals as was reported in previous telegram. ” Telegram R., No. 1180 B., dated (and received) the 30th May 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Serial No. 118 . My telegram No. 1131. followin g from Shiraz, 7 C., dated 28th I have had several long con versations with Ponsette regarding situation in general and Gendarmerie in particular. I believe Ponsette to be actuated by best motives and to be sincerely anxious to maintain strict neutrality and to discourage political intrigues. He has already spoken to officers in strong terms in this sense. Unfortunately, however, like all Swedes, he is too much in hands of his Persian officers who are already making fool of him. He consulted me regarding finances which are desperate. If I were convinced Gendarmerie were genuinely neutral, I would he prepared to submit question of fresh advance for favourable consideration of Your Excel lency. But that as long as we believed Gendarmerie to be hostile to our interests, it would of course be impossible to consider question of affording them further support. We shall soon see whether Ponsette is capable of controlling situation and of stopping intrigues of Persian officers, but per so nally I doubt it. Addressed Tehran ; repeated Basrah, Bushire. Telegram, No. 1183 B., dateU the 30th (received 31st) May 1915. p rom — The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., G.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. f Serial No. 143. My telegramf 1180 B.72 Poliowing received from Trevor, 528:— Begins. Shiraz No. 163.* Borasjun reports that Wassmuss is living in the gendarmerie barracks and that strict • serial No. 139 . orders have been issued that no one is to enter without permission of the officer. It appears that Governor-General has wired saying he cannot be responsible for Wassmuss should he leave the main road. Ghazanfar and gendarmerie officer Abu Talib are having secret meetings with Wassmuss. It thus appears, as was to he expected, orders of Governor-General and Ponsette are disregarded. Ends. f A?. No. Cf. 207, dated Bushire, the 19th (received 31st) May 1915 (Confidential). From— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special duty (in the absence of the Resident), To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I have the honour to forward, for the information of Government of India, a copy of the marginally-cited despatch, with its enclosures, received from His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan. No. 39, dated the 20th April 1915. No. 39, dated Ispahan, the 20th April 1915. From — G. Graham, Esq., His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General, Ispahan, To— Charles M. Marling, Esq, C.B., C.M.G., His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. In amplification of my telegram No. 43 of to-day’s date, I have the honour to transmit herewith enclosed a translation of a broadsheet, which Dr. Pugin has caused to be printed and disseminated here since the 17th instant, on or about which date reports began to circulate in the bazars that Kermanshah had been invaded by a Turkish force. I further transmit an extract from a letter of yesterday’s date now received by me from a Persian friend on whose veracity I can thoroughly rely. If language such as that therein reported is held by the Deputy Governor of the Province, what is the talk in the tea shops of Ispahan likely to be ? It is conceivable—though not, in my opinion, probable—that to mark the arrival here of Herr Zugmeyer and Captain (?) Greisinger some noisy anti- Russian and anti-British demonstration might take place. Such barking would of course break no bones but exaggerated report of such a demonstra tion spreading to other parts of Persia might serve to promote similar demons trations there to the momentary detriment of our prestige. {Translation.) 3rd Jamad II, 1333 (16th April 1915). Important news from Kermanshah. According to telegraphic information. At the time of the arrival in Kermanshah of the German and Austrian Ministers, the British and Russian Consuls fled by another gate of the town, and the night before this incident also the Persian Cossacks on garrison duty there had fled and fifteen of them took refuge in the Imperial German Consulate and implored that a telegram be sent to the Persian Government that we, Moslem Cossacks, are no longer ready to be commanded by Russian Officers, and the same night also the Indian Guards of the British Consulate came in af I I ^ 1 ■W'*-' 73 fl &gt; 7 ; t0 7 ^ ie ( ^ tto ! nai1 ^ 0ns ^ ate &gt; took refuge there and stated that at this time ot Jihad we Indians cannot obey orders of the British, and thus the British Consul was obliged to fly sole and single. Note. A similar notice was posted here on 21st April 1915, which shows ,at pro-German party have a good system for disseminating news. A. P. T.,—18-5-15. ( Extract.) CONFIDENTIAL. Ispahan, Monday, 19th April 1915. I happened to meet Sardar Fateh yesterday and in the course of talking I said to him that there was a rumour that 4,000 Turkish troops had already arrived in Kermanshah and asked him what he thought was the object of the Turks in sending troops there. He said that he had reasons to believe that the Turks are planning to stir up the Persians and send a united campaign through Persia to attack India : that the number of Persian Mojaheds who have already joined the Turkish army around Ahwaz is more than a hundred thousand : that he has had fresh letters from Sardar-i-Jang saying that the English Commander of army at Ahwaz had appealed to him for help and that he had refused. There were some others present when Sardar Fateh was giving all these news. 5 //, No. Cf, 212, dated Bushire, the 23rd May 1915 (Confidential). From— Major A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Officer on Special duty (in the absence of the Resident), To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I have the honour to submit, for the information of the Government of No. 43 , dated 4th May 1915 . India, a copy of an interesting despatch trom Mr. Grahame, His Britannic Maj esty’s Consul-General, Ispahan, to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, regarding the situation at Ispahan. No. 43, dated Ispahan, the 4th May 1915 (Confidential). From—G. Grahame, Esq., His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan, To — His Excellency C. Marling, K.C.M.G., C.B., His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. With reference to my reports passim on the situation at Ispahan and more particularly to my telegram No. 51 of the 1st instant regarding Sharif- ul-Vaezin, I have now the honour to transmit herewith enclosed a copy of the draft (in French) of the identical note addressed by my Bussian Colleague and myself on the 29th ultimo to the Sardar-i-Muhtasham, Governor-General of Ispahan, and a translation of His Excellency’s reply of the 1st May. I am informed by Monsieur Hildebrandt that he received a brief reply to the effect that before receipt of bis Note, reports on this subject had already reached the Governor-General who would take the necessary action. I avail myself of this opportunity to invite your consideration of the situation here, so far as it is known to me from the reports which I receive and from the conversation of my Persian friends and acquaintances. Dr. Pugin and the agents in his pay have for some time past been play ing on the nerves of the native population with a view to drawing out as many \discordant notes as possible and creating a high tension. It is, therefore, not surprising that the reports which reach me should he pitched in a very high key, sounding a note of alarm which appears to me greatly exaggerated. Prom more sources than one I am assured that, both before and since the arrival on the 24th ultimo of MM. Zugmeyer and Greisinger, Pugin has been enlisting from among the baser sort followers now numbering over sixty to whom pay at a high rate and arms are given. Independently of these outsiders are receiving arms. The total number of fire-arms distributed is variously reported from 100 to 200. It is represented to me that all the Persian officers of the Gendarmerie are in close touch and full sympathy with Pugin and his creatures and that the control which Captain Gleerup, the Swedish officer in command locally, might attempt to exercise over his officers and men is a quantile negligeable. ° Shukrullah Khan Lumhani and his blatant band of Democrats, which has lately been increasingly in evidence, is designated as another possible element of danger. The attitude of the Bakhtiari Khans themselves in the event of trouble is represented as questionable. Zargham-us-Sultaneh figures largely in the popular mind and in my reports as the protagonist in an imaginary drama reminiscent of those early days of 1909 when he rode into Ispahan with a hand ful of followers. Several of the fledgling Khans, already adversely known to us as mischief-makers, more particularly Salar-i-Ashraf, Muntazzim-ud-Dowleh and Salar-i-Masoud (this last practically crazy) are said to be boasting openly of the prowess they will show in massacring Armenians and looting the British and Russian Banks. The attitude of Sardar-i-Muhtasham towards would-be agitators, clerical or others, is severely criticised by many of my r'eisian friends one of whom onlv yesterday cited to me a remark recently made in public by His Excellency‘to the effect that, perhaps it trouble did arise, the Central Government would at last cause him to be paid his dues. The same person, who is in touch with the clerical faction, remarked that the clergy has only now come to recognise that they have kindled a fire which they cannot quench, the flames of which must inevitably scorch the hem of their own robes. Thus far the local situation as pictured by the soothsayers of Ispahan. To come down to sober facts. I am unable to find that so far British interests or British subjects have suffered from all this pother. A certain number of small boys have been intimidated from attending the Missionary School. Since yesterday a run on the Bank, as yet of a very feeble nature has been engineered. A large number of false reports re our position at Basrah and elsewhere have been circulated with the connivance—as I have reason to believe—of the higner authorities, and every effort has been made to prevent the dissemination by me of correct reports of our operations at Basrah, Ahwaz, the Dardanelles, &amp;c., or to discredit such lying reports. That I think is the sum total to date of the actual facts of the local situ ation. It is not of an alarming nature. I do not, however, shut my eyes to the off chance of possible troubles. Given a large town with an idle and highly imaginative population, some elements in which might furnish facile instruments in the hands of unscrupu lous persons and it will be obvious that there is fine scope for the enemy. While drafting this despatch, I have received a visit from the Deputy Governor (Sardar-i-Eatheh), who represented that he came both on behalf of Sardar-i-Muhtasham and himself to ask my advice in regard to the present attitude of the clergy. I demurred to give this on the ground that the Governor-General must know his own business and his own countrymen muen better than I do. Pressed farther, I enquired if it would not be possible for Ain-ud-Dowleh to invite the leading Mollas of Ispahan (and other large towns) to Tehran, to confer with him on the situation. Sardar-i-Eatheh said that that was exactly his own idea. Bailing such action on Ain-ud-Dowleh’s paitthe Governor-General and he himself, who bothclearly recognise their responsibility for the safety of Ispahan, must have clear orders from the Central Government to deal with the Clergy. He again requested me to solicit your good offices to obtain despatch of these by tele gram. Sardar-i-Fatheh dwelt on the extensive preparations made by the Germans asserting that they had enrolled and armed about 120 men (my recent reports put the number at 6t) and were continuing such enrolment. The number of the Governor-General’s own Bakhtiaris, which could in an emergency be mustered at Ispahan with ample previous notice, he put at 800, the number actually available here now at 200 (I believe about 100 would be nearer the mark) and that of the local Gendarmerie available (without previous notice) at about the same. Asked if he thought the Governor-General could count on the support of the latter, the Sardar-i-Fatheh said only if the Swedish Officer Commanding had ample previous warning, not in a sudden emergency. My Russian Colleague, who was present at the latter part of this inter view and to whom I related what had passed at the former part, consented, as did I, to accede to the Governor-General’s request that we would again telegraph to our respective Legations in the sense above indicated. I am clearly of opinion that, until the local Clergy are severely put in their own place, they will continue to represent a constant potential source of trouble, possibly of danger, and I regret that Sardar-i-Muhtasham apparently cannot rise to a higher role than that of “ the cat i’ the adage, letting I dare not wait upon I would *\ (Enclosure No. 1 in Ispahan despatch No. 43 of 4th May 1915 to Sir C. Marling.) No. 12, dated Ispahan, the 29th April 1915. From—His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan, To—The Governor-General, Ispahan. J’ai Fhonneur de prevenir V. E. que d’apr&amp;s des informations qui viennent de mo parvenir uncertain Sharif ul Vaezin—a ce qui parait un Rozekhan—qui provenant de Teheran tient depuis 15 jours des reunions secretes a Kachan dans le hut d’exciter i.es sentiments des habitants contre les etrangers, a quitte Kachan ce matin pour Ispahan. Comme il est probable que cette personne cherchera a poursuivre ici une propagande pareille j’ai cm de mon devoir d’avertir V. E. d’avance, afin qu’Elle puisse prendre les mesures necessaires pour empecher soit Sharif ul Vaezin, soit d’autres agitateurs du m6me genre, de compromettre directment ou indirectment la neutralite du Gouvernement Fcrsan. (Enclosure No. 2 in the same.) (Translation.) No. 280, dated Isphan, the 4th May 1915. From—The Governor-General, Ispahan, To—His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ispahan. I am iu receipt of your Note, No. 12. According to reports it is possible to take action. It is also necessary that you inform Tehran that an order for stopping these persons be sent to the Governor-General of Ispahan, by telegraph. P. &amp; P. Dept. Prisi—Xo. 1013—3-C-15—43,•4f [TMb Docmnent Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the foreign Office when done with nnless required for official use.] ;2430 ■ P SR 81A i (86730A5 )- POLITT H.-U Cypner telegram to Mr. Marling (Tehran). Foreign Office. June 30th, 1915. 7.30 p.ra. No.154. Your oelegiam No.220 (of 28th June. Russian troops). I concur in view that Russian troops should remain for the present. Repeated to Sir G.Buchanan, No. 1314 .±, 1 K lu any farther communica tion on this subject, please quote M. 04848 . and address letter to— The Secretary, Admiralty, Whitehall, London, S.W. :v ' 2404 _!9 rr&gt; ( n ?) 29th June, 191 5 . • Confidential Sir, With reference to the prints enclosed in your letter of the 22nd instant, No. 2273, relating to the Political Situation in S.W. Persia, and in continuation of the notes enclosed in Admiralty Letter of the same daue, I am commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith a copy of some further notes by Vice Admiral Sir Edmond Slade. I am, , The Under Secretary of State, India Office. Sir, Your obedient Servant, lfl/\ kL for Secretary* } ''x ^ '• ^ ,1 *r W # T c- COiY OF A MITOl-BY 1 VICE-ADJ/IIRAL SIR EDMOND SLADE, relative to the political situation IK PERSIA. Thes© papers bring our knowledge of the situation in Persia up to the middle of May and from them it is quite evident that active intrigues are being run by the Germans from the Legation at Tehran and the so-called Consul at Shiraz, Herr Wassmuss. It is also clear that the Swedish gendarmerie have been actively enlisted on the German side and the whole of their influence - such as it is - is being used against us. It is said that for the moment the situation is less serious and the Persian Government are inclined to try and take the action that they ought to take as a Sovereign Neutral Government. It is futile to say that the Germans should not use neutral territory as a base of operations against us. They are doing so in every way they can and it is for us to prevent it if we can. The Persian Government is to all intents and purposes impotent. The Germans have enlisted against us every Khan or Sheik with whom we have had differences of opinion over the arms traffic and general lawlessness in the Gulf for the last 8 years. I notice that the man who was responsible for the attack on the Central India Horse is actively employed in trying to arouse the tribes against us around Bushire. He is endeavouring to raise Tangistanis to attack us, and Saiyid Murtaza who was responsible for the trouble in Bushire in 1909 is again to the front. These people thoroughly understand the importance of the Bushire position and apparently they are attempting to establish themselves on the isthmus so as to&gt; -n /jM to command the approaches to the town. It, therefore, becomes all the more necessary to supply the Bushire garrison with machine guns at least and in my opinion they ought also to have two mountain guns, in order to prevent this vital point from being held against us. From my experience of the people and the situation out there, I would certainly advocate the immediate strengther mg of this garrison by the addition of two mountain guns and four or six machine gms. The effect of this will probably be to produce a rapid cooling off of the warlike attitude of these people. A sentiment attributed to the Persians by a member of the British Legation in Teheran in the early part of the 19th century who knbw the real Persian and his character intimately was 'what good fighters we 'Persians would be if there was no killing- - is as true to _ day as it was then. Any increase to the force employed would be evidence that we are in earnest and intend to make our words good and such action has invariably resulted in all o q ; e ; ti0n ° f attaCk dyi ^ 0Ut * ^ast, that is my experience of 3 years' dealing with them. But if we take things supinely and do not secure the main position there may be endless trouble. With regard to the situation in Kerman, Mekran and ersian Baluchistan, the proposals of Sir Percy Cox seem to *eet the point. Mir Barkat is the strongest man in those regions. He has had one or two severe lessons from us and it is probable that if we show that we intend to keep order there that he will act straightforwardly with us, but any sign.'•C' sign of vacillation or weakness will turn him against us. He is quite unscrupulous and is connected by marriage with all the principal people around and, therefore, has consider- able influence. Sirdar Saiyid Khan is not to be trusted. He is an opium eater amd i s often for long s p e i ls urter the ’nfluence of the drug. His daughter is married to Mir Barkat and probably the latter if supported by us can manage him quite satisfactorily. The arming of this part of Persia takes place from Muscat, and although we have nominally stopped the supply of arms ohere are still considerable quantities on the Batineh and Pirate Coasts. The situation in Muscat is still I believe somewhat disturbed, but if Persia declares war and there is serious troublo m the Gulf, it may be necessary to include Muscat in the sphere of operations. It should be soon practicable to detail a number ^~ ships which, with the river cmrTnpoo+n. .,, ’ 9 river gunboats, will be quite sufficieS for tme punpon, of tle serTioe ^ it ls pmable ttat with resolute action on our part nothing serious .111 take place* (sgd.) Edmond J. W. Slade Vice-Admiral. 25 June,1915. Since writing the above I have received a wire to say that armed natives attacked the A.P.O.C. camp at Kishm on 11th June - unsuccessfully. (itd) E.J.W.S.* Mi rPERSIA .POLITICAL. Decypher, Mr. Marling (Teheran) June 28th, 1915 L. 8.eO p,m. H. June 29th.,' 9,40 a.ni. No. 220. Your telegram'No, 49(sic ? 149) and my telegram No * 213. It is possible that the presence ot Russian troops at Odessa aggravated local situation at Ispahan by causing centre of German activities to be transferred thither from Tehran but otherwise their presence has been most beneficial and it would be difficult to imagine surer way of enhancing German influence and prestige than by giving way to Ain-ed- Dowleh’s request as concession would be represented and rightly so by Turkish and German owned press as a conces sion extorted by German pressure. Government have just shown signs of dealing with quite unwonted energy with German agitators having actually disarmed followers of German agent who was proceeding to Meshed, agent himself being sent back to- Teheran,while they have induced German Minister to recall Wassmuss. This is result of presence of Russian'troops. Russian Minister has already given assurances of with drawal as scon as situation permits and has premised to settle various Persian grievances $UiOh aq ■collection of Maliat by Russian Consuls, His attitude is perfectly con- Q5i4iatory and taken uogether with contemplated measure of financial support which we have informed Persian Gov ernment is being favourably considered by the two Govern ments should be ample to convince all but most rabid anti- Russian democrats of our good intentions. Presence of Russian troops has been interpreted as sign that we cannot be tolerant any longer and demand for their with drawal is only put forward by nin-ed-Dowleh as a sop to democrats-[TMs Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PERSIA . POLITICAL . (83699/15) c Cypher Telegram to-Mr, Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, June 26th, 1915, 5,35cp r m c No, 149, Persian Minister has expressed earnest hope of Ain ed Dowleh that his request for withdrawal of Russian troops may he granted on ground that their presence at Enzeli, Kasvin and in Khorassan plays into enemies’ hand whereas their withdrawal would enable Kis Highmss to turn public opinion unanimously against Germans and agitators, Persian Minister added that troops in Azerbaijan were expressly excluded from this request, I now see from your telegram No, 213 (of 24th, June) since received that presence of Russian troops has somewhat aggravated situation, I should be glad to have your views after consulta tion with your Russian colleague as to whether it would in the circumstances be of advantage, or otherwise, to meet the Persian Prime Minister’s wishes in this matter. Repeated to Sir G, Buchanan (No, 1277),V [Tills Document is the Property of Hla Britannic Majesty’s Government, should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PERSIA 1 ' HV POTTTTfflAT, Decypher of telegram- from Mr. Marling(Teheran) D, June 24th, 9.15 p.fa. R. June 25th, 8.40 a.nr. NOe 213c Ispahan situation. Your telegram No, 140 There are certainly disquieting elements since ar rival of Russian troops (? at all events) centre of German activities has been transferred from Tehran to Ispahan and there are now at the latter place fpur or five German agents with perhaps 30 Austrian soldier prisoners escaped from Trans-Caspia via Meshed and as many as 200 armed re tainers recruited locally and from Nib Hussein’s brigands-. It is possible German plan is to attack Russian and British Consulate -esc,,, in hope that Russia will send troops to Ispahan and that Persia will eventually get embroiled in the war, Persian Government have at present about 400 gendar merie in Ispahan and more are to be sent from. Pars while new Governor General Sirdar I. Ashja, whom Russian Legation believe can be trusted, has a considerable force of Bakh- tiari Sowars, Government has sent orders that German re tainers are to be disarmed and if Swedish officers have their men in hand and are supported by the Governor General there should be no danger. Rank and file and particularly native officers of gendarmerie however are reportedto be very pro-German while attitude of Bakhtiaris generally was decidedly defiant at time of_Russian demand for dismissal of Sirdar Mohtashem and so far 1 can see (? Russia’s) hold on new Governor General consists mainly in his personal rela tions with Evreinoff and it was mainly on Phat account that Russian Legation agreed to. his appointment in succession to Mohtashem, Personally I deprecate withdrawal of Consuls., it would be sign of weakness and presumably with them Colonies and telegraph staff would also have to leave,I think that Evreinoff should be sent to Ispahan with a good supply of money with which to (group undecypherable) Governor General’s friendship, Zi-L-Es-Sultan’s appointment to Ears was suggested by Persian Government about five weeks ago and at the time in their (group omitted ? opinion) seemed unobjectionable but proposal has not been revived, I have heard nothing of His Highness’ request for a guarantee. Addressed to Foreign Office, repeated to Petrograd and Basrah. ofCONFIDENTIAL. 1 ■j i?i Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received June 25, 11*5 p.m.) (N 0 .216.) R. ({June 25, 1915, 2*10 m”) MY telegram No. 208 of 21st June. There appears to have been a sharp action at Kerind, in which Turks were roughly handled by tribesmen, losing about 100 killed, while Persian losses were about 65. Subsequently German consul and Swedish officer arranged a meeting of Turkish and Persian leaders, as a result of which Turks retired at Kasr-i-shirin.[Tills Document Is the Property of Hie Brlt&amp;nnic Majesty^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required lor official use.] Your telegram No* 14C V . There are certainly disquieting elements since ar rival of Russian troops (? at all events)- centre of German activities has been transferred from Tehran to Ispahan and there are now at the latter place fpur or five German /'-y* v* -4- r a r -4- ^ ^ rr f \ \. _ j- J! ^ ^ i * * ? -i It is possihld German plan is to attack Russian and British Consulate Re*, in hope that Russia will send troops' to Ispahan and that Persia will eventually get embroiled in the war* Persian Government have at present about 400 gendar merie in Ispahan and more are to be sent from Pars while new Governor General Sirdar I. Ashia, whom Russian Legation believe can be trusted, has a considerable force of Bakh- tiari Sowars* Government has sent orders that German re tainers are to be disarmed and if Swedish officers have their men in hand and are supported by the Governor General there should be no danger* Rank and file and particularly native officers of gendarmerie however are reportedto be very pro-German while attitude of Bakhtiaris generally was decidedly defiant at time of_Russian demand for dismissal^of Sirdar Mohtashem and so far i can see (? Russia’s) hold on new Governor General consists mainly in his personal rela tions with Evreinoff and it was mainly on that account that Russian Legation agreed to, his appointment in succession to Mohtashem* Personally I deprecate withdrawal of Consuls* it would be sign of weakness and presumably with them Colonies and telegraph staff would also have to leave*I think that Bvreinoff should bo sent to Ispahan with a good supply of money with which to (group undecypherable) Governor General’s friendship* Zi-L-Es-Sultan’s appointment to Pars was suggested by Persian Government about five weeks ago and at the time in their (group omitted ? opinion) seemed unobjectionable but proposal has not been revived* I have heard nothing of His Highness’ request for a guarantee* Addressed to Foreign Office, repeated to Petrograd and Basrah* PERSIA Ispahan situation agents with perhaps 30 Austrian soMie from Trans-Caspia via Meshed and as ma tainers recruited locally and from Nib with perhaps 30 Austrian soldier prisonet ans-Caspia via Meshed and as many as 200 - recruited locally and from Nib Hussein’s 03iets escaped 200 armed re in’s brigands*^ [Ting Document Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with nnip ^ required for official usej ' ‘ — PERSIA . 9 t? 'X 2 ; r a Political;• Cypher Telegram to Mr. Marling (Teheran). Foreign Office, May 6th, 1915. 6.15 p.m. No. 110. Your telegram No. 1Y4 (of April 30th: Zil-es- Sultan). In view of considerations advanced hy you, we would raise no objections to appointment of Zil-es- bultan if desired by Persian Government.-V Minute Paper. Register No. ^ % Secret Department. Put away with.....' &lt;!o. Dated Rec. iL^ ^ igiS' Date. Initials. Under Secretary -fXM \ Secretary of State l, Lj* Id Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State..... SUBJECT. J^rSv Previous Papers :- /y(~ Copy to*. 2l i FOR INFORMATION. 18698. I. 483. 2000,—4/1915. [1000/14.] -rJ[This D ocument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Qoverninent t and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] i / 7325 PERSIA ! *_■' POLITICAL Cypher telegram to Mr, Marling (Tehran). Foreign Office, June 25rd 1915. 7 p.m. No.140, (R). Russian Embassy state that your Russian colleague has been instructed to discuss with you desirability of withdrawing Russian colony from Ispahan where situation is reported as intolerable. Do you consider British Consulate General and Colony in danger? Russian Embassy also allege that you and your Russian colleague have invited Zil-es-Sultan to return as Governor General at Fars and that he lias requested guarantee of two Governments for himself and his family. Please telegraph your observations. Repeated to Petrograd No.1246.,,_x TO 3E RETURNED TO THE EQREIGN OPPICE OFFICIAL USE. ^SS UIRED POR PERSIA, POLITICAL. Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran) June 21st. 1915 3r 9*o„p r m* x\ ® 10 f) O Q r P e /Ti e -i-'iO r 208 o (p ) r June 21str 1915 Raouf Bey, who was threatening Kermanshah about a month ago with a small force of Turkish troops, has sin been hanging about neighbourhood of Kerind endeavouring oo seduce tribes. He has now got involved in a quarre: wion onern and has shot three Kerindis. Tribes are preparing to resist him. Incident is calculated to inflame Persians against Turks and their Allies. Addressed to Foreign Office. Repeated to Basrah. 71-V. In nny further communica tion on this subject, please quote K. 045OS and address letter to— The Secretary. Admiralty, Whitehall, London, S.W. % Sir, SECRET:- ith reference to your letter of the 10th instant, P. 1981, relative to the action which will be required in the event of war breaki^ out with Persia, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to forward herewith, for the information of the Secretary of state for India in Council, copy of a telegram which has been sent to the Commander in Chief, East Indies, on the subject. My Lords consider it desirable that the Naval and Military responsibility for any Operations should be defined beforehand, and, as shewn in the telegram, they have instructed the Commander in Chief that the Navy may have to assist and cover the landing of troops, patrol of the Gulf and the blockade of ports. All occupations of Persian territory, including Bushire, would be a Military responsibility/. A further communication will be made on receipt of a reply from the Commander in Chief. It must, however, be borne in mind that our present Naval resources in the Gulf are limited, owing to the combined Operations in the Shatt-el-Arab, and the'necessity of assisting in the defence of the Suez Canal. I am further to enclose some notes by Vice-Admiral Sir Edmond Slade which may be of use to the Secretary of State in cojoaide-ring the situation. \ I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, 23JUNJ915J &gt;/ The Under Secretary of State, India Office. L.P.—No. 8. 1 I I4 A. i # ap y , . , Unless the Gormans have been able to Supply Persia with artillery, the seizing and holding of the coast ports is a very simple matter. Bushire is practically an island and if the approach through the shallow water is held along the line of the telegraph posts by properly prepared defensive works, quite a small force should be able to hold it if provided with machine guns. Lingah can be held with a force of about 500 men without difficulty against any army the Persians are likely to be able to put in the field in this region. A few field guns or machine guns will be all that is necessary to make them quite self—supporting. Bundas Abbas similarly can be easily protected. The Consulate is already a defensible position and with very little further expenditure of money it would completely command the approaches to the east of the town. On the west and north it would probably be necessary to undertake further works, but having in view the poor quality of the local tribes who are likely to attack them, they need not be of very considerable magnitude. For the protection of Lingah and Bunder Abbas a very good base exists in the Island of Kishm. If the Persians attack one of these places in force they cannot attack the other, and if they are held by a sufficient garrison to keep the townspeople in order a reserve can be stationed in Kishm which can be thrown into either place in 24 hours if required. We should have at least a week’s warning of any movement against either of them. It is therefore estimated that a force of 2,000 to 3,000 men with a liberal allowance of machine guns would be quite sufficient for seizing and holding the coast ports and islands with such naval support mmm-I— | -p support as can be given bjr the Fleet. It is probable that experience would shew that this force could be safely reduced after the effects of the action taken began to be felt by the Persians. Jask is already defended and would onljr require a ga,.risen to be made up to about 150 men with machine guns. The barbed wire entanglements require exterition and repair. The same applies to Charbar. Mohammera and Ahwaz must stand or fall with the general position on the Shatt—el—Arab and Tigris^ but it wii. be absolutely essential to come to a definite agreement wr&amp;h the Sheikh of Mohammera as to his future position in Arabistan if we intend to get him to act on our side. Too much reliance must not be placed on the action of His Majesty's Ships except to prevent the passage of arms into the south of Persia. In nearly all cases the ships have to lie a long way off the shore and they cannot under circumstances co-operate effectively with any shore detachments. They can command the approaches to Jask and Lingah along the beach and to Bunder Abbas in fine weather, but if there is any wind the dust very soon rises and all view of the shore is cut off. At Bushire ships lie 5 to 7 miles off the shore and very often dust hides the town entirely from the anchorage. It would be necessary in the case of this place to provide launches for inshore work to see that no communication takes place between the island and the mainland and in order to secure this all dhows and boats should be seized immediately. If these precautions are taken as soon as there is any sign of trouble, I do not think that there will be any difficulty in holding these places. TheA i.he effectiveness of the Persian aggression will depend entirely upon what the Germans can do to assist M.Lh either men, officers or munitions. If none of these are forthdoming the question will remain a very simple one and resolute measures taken in advance would, in opinion, entirely prevent anything from happening. The amount of arms and ammunition which at present exists in Southern Persia - unless they have been increased in a way of which I have no knowledge - are not enough to constitute a serious menace to purpposition, provided we take steps to prepare and occupy defensible positions at the start. (Signed) Edmond J. W. Slade, Vice Admiral, 14th June 1915.DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE ' AS TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) Foreign Secret. Your telegram 29th May..Measures in event of war with Persia. H.M.G..accept your policy and also approve measures proposed in Cox’s 1086-B of the 12th May to be taken at Hohammera on outbreak of ware Precise action practi cable at Bushire must presum- ably depend on naval and mili tary forces available as indi- | cated in your telegram of 25th May® Admiralty have been address-tfoc.) In any Inrlhcr communication on the subject, please quote No. 79009/15. I and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Foreign Office 1 iV London. Sir:- cL o D i o ■; •;, 1 / a in reply to your letter of the 10th instant, P.1981-2, relative to the measures to be taken in the event of war with Persia, i am directed by Secretary bir Edward Grey to state that he concurs in the proposal of Mr. Secretary Chamberlain to approve the policy outlined by the Government of India, while at tne same time adhering to sir p. Cox's proposals ^ ' regarding such action as it is desirable to take at Moharrimerah. In this connexion, i am to transmit to you, herewith, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran expressing his concurrence in the views of the Government of India and calling atten tion to the necessity of arranging, in the event of war, for the removal from Persia of all British subjects, including the telegraph staffs of the Indo- European ’he Under Secretary of state, India Office.(79009/15) European Telegraph Department and Company. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,i [This Document la the Property of Hla Britannic Majesty’s Oovernment, should be retnrned lo the Foreign Office when done with unless sM required for official use.] V A KSH SI A. nr. gLITIRAr,. Decypher. Mr. Marling (Teheran) .U* 5.lo.p.m. fi. lO.lO.p.m. JUn8 16 ^ 1915 - No. 201. Your telegram'No. 133 . u.ll„ concur in Viceroy's views and would only note that withdrawal of this Mission and of Consuls mght have to include also that of all British subjects an 01 telegrapnic staffs throughout the country. Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India.[This Document is the Property of His Brltoufc Majesty’s Ctovernment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] POLITICAL. Cypher telegram to Mr. Marling (Teheran). Foreign Office, June 13th 1915, .3.5 p.m. No. 133. Viceroy’s telegram of 29th May regarding possible outbreak of war with Persia. India Office state that in above mentioned eventuality situation on frontier of India would fully tax remaining military resources of Government of India and that military operations on large scale in Southern Persia would there fore be out of question. India Office therefore propose to approve policy out lined by Government of India which need not preclude action at Mohamerah proposed in third paragraph of Sir P.. Cox’s telegram No. 1086B of 12th May. Before concurring in proposal of India Office I should be glad to receive your observations. It i&amp; quite possible that hostilities will not ensue between this country and Persia but it is as well to pre pare for any eventuality..COPY OF TELEGPAM. Sir P. Cox, f P Dated Basra, 19th June, 1915. Received at London Office 1262 B. Your telegram dated 27th April and reminder re Ahwaz Telegraph Office. Question was discussed with Telegraph Autnorities at the time and Ahwaz office was forthwith reopened under British auspices and connecoion with Bushire restored. This appears to be all that Director General wants. I regret tnat no intimation of fact was sent. Military authorities however object to any Persian employe handling instruments. They use him lor translating; messages into Roman character which are then signalled by British signaller and they desire to maintain arrangement as long as British garrison remains.Tehran (R.) our oner conduct] reply to Folk “ To reply so Tot a so from A attempt! on Grei Turkish obliged to the 0 any step which tl also for cireums tempted ternton safety Govemi% 1257. Tehran (R.) From General Nixon, Basra, 17th June 1915. (Repeated to India, and Secretary State for India by Army Commander.) Following received by (Jox from His Majesty’s Minister at T lla . ve £ ece ! ve &lt;l note from Persian Government protesting against our operations m Persian territory. It is only p- 0 forma document and could easily be left unanswered, but if as seems possible we are no longer conducting operations on this side of the frontier, I should be able to give a reply to this eftect. * Following reply sent by Cox, No. 1256 B, dated 17th June : - Y our telegram No. 197. Army Commander desires me to suggest reply somewhat on the following lines m so far as you deem expedient, fot a ^Uiier was landed by us m Persian territory until Turkish troops loni Amara invaded Arabistan unopposed with avowed purpose of attempting attack on British forces at Basra in flank, and of inflicting ini'urv on Creat Britain by wrecking the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s pipe line. ersian Government were either unwilling or unable to take any measures whatever to repel this invasion of their territory, and it was only after 1 urkish troops had been m Persian territory fortnight, and British pipe line had been wrecked and Nasm itself threatened, that Great Britain was obliged to send troops to (repel ?) enemies of Persia and save further damage to the Oil Company s property. As it is Turkish invasion brought about the destruction of the pipe line which the Persian Government failed to take any steps to prevent and oil industry has been consequently suspended for four months involving loss of many thousand sterling to the Oil Company for which the bill will be presented to the Persian Government in due course, as also for the cost of maintenance of British troops in Persia for protection of British lives and property and expulsion of Turks. These being the circumstances, it is astonishing that the Persian Government should be tempted to protest at the operations of British troops in their interests. As a matter of fact, Turks having been just expelled beyond her frontiers, a portion of the British force has been already withdrawn from Persian territory and only such troops will now remain as may be necessarv for the safety of British lives and property in Arabistan until the Persian Government has shown herself capable of assuring it herself.”-V In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No - I ^ 8 2 . /W and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. The Undersecretary of State \for_,Edreig4-y4-finrs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for elect ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop K , of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Xx'-'VoT. 0 Y ■ 7 ? 7 5 Reference to previous correspondence to Letter j rom Foreign Office Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. (ft- Ik / K. Kl - u&gt; oLsiyj^^if Cut 1 j v (• &gt;! A ( ’X XX- x /. 1 It y A Ke. 35 , zq 1 (Cf 10 L 8 JUNI 915 J £ l 12 ]1 Teloran o. 33 Sir April 29tn 71882 , 4 I9i5 mth reference to my telegram No. 165 of tlie 22nd insin nt and to previous reports on the subject , c honour to transmit to you herwith copies of A I have the despatches from Mp vC^ffisul i acdouall reporting the cir— cumstsnces 'crdnnected with his withdrawal from Kirmansihh together with a copy of Sir Walter Townley 1 s telegram, to Kinranshah No.25 the 8th instant . At the same time I enclose copy &lt;jj£ a letter on the subject which has been communicated to me from another source and which gives a more detailed account of the situation immediately prior to the departure of the Allied colonies • You will observe from Sir Walter Townley’s telegram above referred to , that Mr Lacdouall was auth orised at ,onco to withdraw to Hamadan if he considered the situation critical and if he was unable to secure a guarantee from the Governor General for his safety , very tort although the situation was undoubtedly serious , it would seem to me that in the circumstances Mr hac- douall would have been better advised to have sent awey the British community and to have himself remained at Rirmanshah , at any rate until the menace of Turkish occupation became a more tangible one • From all accounts it would appear that the Turkish troops did not advance any further than Kerind , some forty or fifty miles by road from Kirmanshah ,an&amp; , though I have no doubt that tno town was full of the reports , Lr hacdouall*s long experien e most alarniHvg Rl3bt Honourable Sir S.Qrey Bart. :c.G.L.P. ot etc etc—w\ % O- Pei'sia ousiit to have taught hixs that they con be largely dlsoouhted . I ahould not lll £ « sltlwut a ttUCh bStt ° r 3mo ' rlo ^° ^ the clrcuEetanoes to go ,o far as to eay that ttr hacdouall-, doclelon to leave wae the actual cause of the desertion of his escort , i cannot help thinking tl.at . if he had sho TO a bolder front . it is „ 0 t impossible tlmt they .ould have remained staunch to him . On the other hand it rust be adrifed that the departure of citato hatronoT and^the Cossack force was most demoralise . ^ Kacdou _ all a withdrawal has caused much disagreeable comront here and must iiavs produced a deplorablo Impression locally . Indeed the German agitators ..av&gt; seized upon it and upon the story of the desertion of the Consulatr escort as further capital tor thoir anti-Eritiah pro- t paga^ida . I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir , X r our ro3t obedient , humble Servant ,3rit»i sli Go isulat&gt;© of 'KcWit* i— Imo.I ^aiup Ka' igaw ?;r .■ April 17 19: [t. 71882 Sir JUN 4 19i5] I have t/he loiour to report that, em reported 1-y telegra.'oh, u leit Kermanshs,!! for Hezaaia/i op the X4th sb reported of April apd hope to reach that tori op the 20th. Tl'e party coisiets of the British, Ruseiap and Gelsjlap coloiy aid the detachment of Persiai Cossacks who were ii Kermaishah, aL.© circumstaices that led to our departure were as follows:- The xar ±16 mder fuse ip H.a,ouf 3e^, a p^val / cap tai l, came to IIasr-i~3hirii a id are repor ted to have l occupied it. It had beep arranged that the Governor Gen eral should meet the Turkish repr ese itative to arrange peace between the Siujabis and a tribe oi the Turkish side of th© border lamed Dllloo. Mukhbar*es-Sultaneh, 0 commandant of the forces, had gone to Kaer-i-Shirin % oi behalf of the Governor Geieral. It was at first sup posed that the Turks had come to Kasr for this purpose, but it appears that th ey have actually occ ;pted the town with a force of from two to four thousand men. T had enquired from the Governor General if he could guarantee our safety, but could get no reply. The Karguzar and Deputy Governor deprecated our leaving, saying we had no definite news and could leave if the Turks really advanced Durie , the manager of the Imperial Bank of Persia, was war ned that his house would be attacked that evening. He warned Major de Mare, who came himself with a force of Ge idarmes and during the night shots were exchanged between them and a party of Sowars. After this it seemed On the I3th the Hussian Consul left and Mr usclepc The Briti'h Minister Teheran.hs4 I useless to renali, especially PB the Coseacie were leev- iig. On the fflonlng of the I4th; I eeot for the Kerruzar aid told him I haided over the Coisulete to him end he must Place a ?uerd In it to protect the goods there, lagi Hustaci 3e«i, a local lando- ier, who had at one tine been in best in the Consulate, offered to guarantee ay safety and bring one hundred sowars or more to guard the coisula.te. As he had no official ■nosltion, I did not accept,. i fliQ iufladax had bee i bold bbab we would leave a vl Had received ai admaiee of five hu idred kr&amp;ne for bne exoe ises of bhe road. O'! my enquiry How ma/iy mules He required, he said he had already engaged them, T le was bold bo 1)0 ready at* 3 t)iQ. Ab bla'b hour* 1 b was reported bhab Duff ad ar Malik GMulam Ahmed with five sowars, bheir horses aid ©rmes, aid b^o cases of pmmuiibioi bad gone uo the Turkish Coisulebe, also an India i f err ash, an ex— -soldier, lamed Khudeyar Khan. One man of the escorb, Duffadar Nur Mohammed Khan, remained faithful and is with me. After my departure I am informed that some Turkish soldiers wi th the son of o le H&amp;Ji Safer, alias Mae.4el, a Persian subject, came to the escorb quarters aid boo**, the baggage of the escort including that of the man with me. Tliey also broke down the flagstaff. Gendarmes were guard!ig bh© Consulate itself, where most of my oersoaal effects and the ordinary archives are locked up. Tlie more confidential ones are with me. It war i impossible to bri ip away much as there was y difficulty in obtaining mules. A few necessaries which I had ordered to follow me have arrived; but only got away after ap pealing to th© XTarguzar aid Deputy Governor ^ho appear to have done what was lecessarv. The latest news is that the Governor Generalix&amp;s retired to Keri ig, that is, has left the plai is and that the Turks are advancing, it is also reported that an advance guard of gendarme© who had arrived at Bisaitm iiad been hurriedly recalled to Kermaishah. 1 have, etc. Sd/ w Me^Douall.Copy oX Mr Mac&amp;ouall'e deBpat»ch $o # S O&amp;mp of* , 2ist 1915 report.! pg deseroioi or six raer or 'the Sowar e &gt;1,882 Sir , ’ JUN 4 !Sib j I have the honour to report that the following men oT the Indian Consular escort , deserted a/nd went to the Turkish Consul instead or accornn©.nyina’ me to la^adsn ! — No,SB61 DiiTradar Malik Ghulam Ahmad Khan No.2886 Lance DufTadar Fasal Dad Khan No.2773 Sowar Surkhru Khan No.2849 ,g Said Muhammad Shah No.2649 ,, Habile Shah No.2649 ,, Aklibar Khan Corps 9th Hodaon’s Horse . I have their sheet rolls with me • They took with them their horses , riries , lances , and swords ; 2 cases or ammunition , 2000 rounds , and it is reported that they have since taken the balance or the ammunition , 2000 rounds , and the balance of a case or old ammunition , all .303 cordite ; also all the belongings or the man who remained r&amp;ithru! , Including his drees unirorm , bedding end clothing which was packed up and was to liav© been brought by my servants who rollowed next day. DufTadar Nur Muhemxaad who is here with his khaki Uniform , horse and arms . the six men are reported to have mounted and left , Sirdar who lives near , but they went straight to the Turkish Consulate ♦ They sent a message to DuTfadar Nur Muhammad to follow them which he reported to me . He tells me that Ithudayar Khan , an ex-sowar of the I7th Lancers , who has been employed for some years at the Trie one faithful member of the escort is No.2623 At the hour origi lally fixed for my departure , &amp; saying that they were going to say good-bye to the Afghan ConsulateI Consulate as a ferrash , ca^e to him and tried to oer- suade him to remain and Join the others , eayinf that as an old ifriend h© did not like to see him go inf to his death and men hod been sent to the bridge four miles from Kiraan- shah to attack the oarty (this story had also been heard by the commander of the Cos sacks acid he took orecaaitioos against attack , but lone was made) . Nur Muhammad says t ' ha “ h6 replied Oiat his life fcelopged to the Govermnent which he i»»d served for sixteen yeexs and that Government would take care of his relations . There is reason to suppose that Khudayar Khan seduced the sowars . I had a slight suspicion as to his x aithfulness 9 hut had no evidence to warrant taking any action . In addition to the Government property token the Duff ad ar Malik Ghulam Ahmed owes the following sums P n . Advace for road expenses Krans 500 Advance for sto.ble exoenses . ,, 250 1st March personal advance ,, 119.45 869.46 The above ©re government monies . He also owes me persoially Frans 200 and to my c^erk * * 200 - \ \ { i To Manager of the Imperial Bank 200 (borrowed 1 1 my absence at Baulatabad) * \ 600 or in all Krans T469. Akhbar Khan has received an advance of Frans 90 ; Fazal Dad owes Nur Muhammad Khan fCrans 320 ; Malik Ghulam Ahmad is said to belong to a wealthy family.W.Macdouall It, is necessejry t,o su-o-nly DufTadex Nur Muhemmad Khan ^'ith some clothing and bedding , which I suppose will be sanctioned . I em of the opinion that he deserves grea;t credit, for the way in which he has acted and would suggest that some notice be taken of this . He was only promoted to Duffad&amp;r on the 1st of November 1313 . H© would like to join his regiment in France , but knowing no European is. iguage believes it? would be impossible . He says thxat 400 me \ are ii Fro/ice and 100 in India • He knows very little Fersian , otherwise I would suggest that on returning to Kirmanchah a few local men should be en gaged under him until other arrangements can be made , ad and even as it is such a plan might be taken into con sideration . I have written to the Karguzar that the late escort have stolen the above articles , and he should obtain aid hold the same and the men oendiig orders * I now hear from Captain Maixaonow that the Cossacks will return to Kirmanshah in a few days , and he might take the necessary action . Come sixteen Persian Cossacks also deserted . I have etc ,W.Macdouall Copy of Mr Macdouall*s despatch Ko .3 Cano of 5 . Cir , '71882 ,JUN 4 1915! I have the honour to inform you that according to reports brought by my servants , who left Kirmaoehah the morning after I did , the man who came to the Consulate aid broke down the flagstaff was Mahmud Funachi t son of TTaJi Safar who has the title of 'Taji Tfuadel 5 he is also reported to have carried off the surgical instruments and disoenssry belongings which were stored in the escort building , as well as other such things as tents . He is also reported to have tried to interfere with our party when leaving but I have no direct evidence of this . He is said to be a Turkish subject , but this father is a Persian subject and is now in Tehran • Perhaps some action could be taken against him there # Haji Safar is husband of one of the widows of the late Wkil-ud-Dowleh of Kirmanshah and guardian of the two sons ♦ I have the honour to be etc ,Gopy ot Sir -ialuer TowiXey*® on Ho*88 to ElrroapeXiefc daut-i 6til April I 315 . xour Ho .40. I caiaot Be© ttot there ^ould be any e,&lt;Jvantage io ap^ejgin^ sowar© . Y m could lot resist the advance or what would appear to be a much superior force , and you would merely precipitate a crisis and pl&amp;y into the bands of the Germans . If you consider tht- situation critical and the Cov er lor General cannot guarantee your safety 9 you had better leave at snee for Hamadan tailing your cyphers with you , or destroying the secret ones if y nfc consider -the road unsafe . d*here can be to question of sending Russian troops as there ex-'© no t© available « I doubt Salar being at Hhaniqln . I have 1 nformsd the Persian Government of the situation . TI;e Minister for Foreign affire asserts that the Ambassador has telegraphed to the TuvhiBh military authorities that they should not enter Persian territory.Codj British Co isule.te for Kovmz'. irhei:, Haniadan, Aoril 54 1916. A0.4 Carip. Sir, 71882 I have the hoiour , ii co itipuatioo Jf my ies- patch No.I Cano to inform you that it appears th^y^ r^as in some danger. T Te was strongly advised hy Major de Mare to leave. As manager of the Bank he was able to pee people who were afraid to go to the Consulate ail has been very active in trying to obtain news and this, it appears, iiad come to the ears of the Germans and the Turks. Some other people were also suspected by them and one of the Afghan exiles, a cousin of Serdar T Iaidar Quli rlhai, but lot himself a pe is loner, was warned by a fxieid that the Turks would seize him if they could, so he. accompa lied our party to Hsmada i with his family. Tie had lot aiything to do with obtaining; outside news but had given me lews about the town. That some people im TTermanshah were in favour of the Turks appears from an incident which occurred at one of the mosques a few days before we left. A stranger, a. pilgrim returning from Verbal a , was preaching and said thfeb if people supposed that 3eyid Kasem had sanctioned so holy war they were entirely mistaken; that Alem had simply said a prayer for Mohammedans end the accursed Sheikh Maesen had shouted out that tdiie authorized an holy war, and had since published it. ( This Sheikh Mcssan is one of the Turkish emissaries who recently visited irermaneheh) . At ohis some of those present threatened the preacher, but they are said to have been some of the bad characters of the town. It is asserted that Serdar Ijlal has joined the ProTurks, but I have no direct evidence of this. Me owes a large sum to the Russian Bank to which his estates ere mortgaged Mis Majesty’s Minister, Teheran. ! 3mortgage 1 * The Ulema or Ferma'iehah, bel'ig , through t&gt;11 - grslms, io touch with the leadi ig Ulema at Uejef*, ere oot i iflue ice l py the Ttatices circulated in their names, nor in those of the other Ulema rho have been bribed by the Turks. Some sixteen men of the Persian Cos recks de serted to the Germans before we left which shows* they had been tampered with. That is^a foreign consul had been tam pering with the troops of the country in which he was con sul . I expect to be Joined by my munehi in a few days when I will be able to report further* I have, etc. ¥ MacBouall71882 Cow ol' a letter from tdie Manager of Imperial Je/ik of Persia at Kirmaisii&amp;h to the Manager at Tehran , rea^riing tie evaluation of Firr.pnsliel hy British end Russians . Dear Mr Wood , Xn previous letters I have givei you some idea of the situation at Kirmanshah but it ?jill do 10 hams to repeat nxyeelf here and give you an outline of the oirout}stances rhich led up to our evacuation of that place . Since the outbreak of the war with Turkey the Turkish officials in Kir.naishah have been active ii working against the British and Russians by all and every means in their rower . About the be-yi mini? of February the first of the German agents arrived in the town - Messrs Schunemam and Pascben - and immediately launched ^out on the most dangerous intrigue . Tliey be ran to gather around them all the worst characters of the town and district , well- known robbers abd murderers , several of whom were wanted by the Persian Government , and they have today e/t least 150 men of this type in their ser vice , fully aniifed and equipped # Ttitey have made practically house to house 5 visiujfc among the Muhammadan population with the object of stirring up a Jihad and spreading false reports of German and Turkish victories , aid stories of maltreatment of Mussulman® by the dritish and Russian forces # Among the better class of people w e io not think that they have made much effect but among the poorer class they heve certainly found ready sympathiserssymtsatjhisers 8,s tih.ese laht»er are ever anxious for an excuse to loot . It was several times whieperd that the ± eae ur i e s o± the 3r i ti ©li and JEcuseia. n Sanhs would soon be divided aiuo w these ruffle is . y&lt;o l» oily ai&amp;otig the townspeople was this propaganda csui'ried on but 8-1 so anon? the tribesmen# especially eaeong idle KalkLurs who ere the most numerous and disreputable of all the clans of the neig'hbourho od . At no time is this tribe much under Persian Government authority # at the oresent , so far as we can learn , it is in rebellion avalist the local Government who had sent the Governor General Amir Mufakhitham to collect past due taxation . IProin. news tha &gt; reached Itirmaishah a few days before our departure the Amir h&amp; 1 imprisoned one oi the Kalkhur chiefs — Suleiman Khan — end his followers had fired upon the Amir’s camp and decamped with some 300 Government mules into Turkish territory * A few days later Turkish soldiers anoeared in Ralkhur country and it was said that the Turks had demanded the release of the Suleiman Khan by th e Amir , otherwise they would attack him , from Khpniqin . A meeting war arranged between the Persian and Turkish authorities to discuss this question and frontier questions but we do not know jjif this ever took olace . The 'Turks without warning advanced to Easr-i-Shirin and the Sinjabi tribe who are really perhaps the only one^loyal to the Government , fell fcac-x and Joined the Aiiiir’s ceffip at Sar-i-Ful . v ■ v From S !ji'■ A . ... -t.—-1 _ L Prom there ee Tar as can lean the com bined force retired before the Turks to Period and later to Kirm&amp;nshah , probably by order of the Gen- tr&amp;l Qovernraent , *t:o appear to have given explicit &gt;rders to avoid any conflict * So far ae we cai learn there is a Turkieh force of ab mb 600 regulars and 1,600 tribesmen at Xerind today , when we left fClrtsmnehah it t&amp;.b reportel afe Sar-i-Iul * This latter news res.c.nad us in Plrmanebeh on the 12th of April , pid it was agreed by the Turorean colony that shoul1 it advance further , it would be necersarw for Allied subjects to leave for tlamadan • On the 13th of April the German and Austrian Ministers arrived from Baghdad with some fourteen *^1 u iiiiiuiinnn mnTiT&gt;mii ir German aid Austrian subjects and many retainers , aid it becetie evident that unless we took the road before them , we would be unable to procure the leceseary transport , especially as oil the available mules were being gathered up by fore© to replace those stolen from the Amir by the Talkhurs • It was the ref or© decided that all the Sr3&amp; tish ani Russian subjects should leeve the follow- iny day with their Consuls and accompany the Persian Cossacks who had received orders to leave immediately any Turkish force should threaten an advance on ftirnansheh • were all loath to le-vc before things became more critical , but we had every reason to believe that to remain af/ter the departure of the Cossacks would be a temptation of Prfrviienc© esp ecially as we had received repeated warnings that we already ran considerable danger of being arrested if! ^ On the evening? of the I3th the writer received a warning that on no account must he sleep in the Bank house that night as an attempt was to be made to arrest him . Tills was in all probably an atfcemnt to make him endeavour to leave during the night as the following morning it transpired that men had been sent out from ■ the Turkish Ooisulate after sundown ii the direction ox the bridge which has to be crossed by travellers en route for Hamadaa . We informed Major Hyetrom of the Oendarmes of this warning aid asked dim to take any sters he consid ered necemary to nrovide for our safety . Me immediate* !y sent over a guard of thirty gendarmes commanded by Major d@ Mare who spent the night with us . from this officer and from Major Uyetrom we learned tliat there was very real danger for us and e g&amp;bherd that the reason of our enemies desire to arrest A some of ub was to be i i retaliation for the arrest of the Gerxian Co naul at Bush ire . Both these Swedish officers strongly advised us to leave hirae.nsbah without further delay • Although these Swedish officers admitted strong . -a—n«iii*?fi ti ,i 1 T i r pro-Oeri’^an sympathies they were ready to guarantee our eefety as long as they remained in the town but air they had come with the @&gt;mrers purpose of escorting the German and Austrian Ministers to Tehran they ejected to continue their journey at any moment • They actually left , we believe, on the irorning following our departure . The mules we had engaged to remove the balance of our cash ii the Treasury were lot forth.comi on the 1514th and we were obliged to make the followingsrr&amp;.Tgeme it with tile Swedish Qeidexmerie ofricere # We bought their Sld/et bill 01 Tehran Tor Toxnane 4 9 cou for which we paid them cash , and thez?' engaged to transport Tor us the balance of our cash Tomans 9,000 iree of charge , do XjLe first office of the Bank thef should touch oa their way do Tehran • With this remittance we sent our' own cashier ii charge * All iotas , bills etc , and the most importsnt books we brought with us , and some Bank an.1 orivete rrooerty . The remainder we either left at the Bank B. s ii Quarters or han-.iei over to Persian frie nde w© wrote officially to the Perrucar requesting hir to tak^» charge of the property remaining and asking him to seal all doors and locks , but beyond Placing local policemen in charge we do not k low what stens he actually took . until proper arrangements had been made we requested ohe Gendarmerie to mainbain the guaris they hud px'ovisio lal ly placed at the Bank and houses • Our Mlrza was to sec that proper precautions ha^ bee i taken but he i#11 obliged to leave almost immediately and w© do not knot’s' how far he was satisfied The other clerks were also 'told what was expected and woul 1 do their best , but w© heve so far no communica tion from eny of them * So long as the German Shuneman Is permitted to retail hie gang of ruffians there can be small sec urity for any ally subject in Kiraanohah . The Government force cannot be trusted even if the Amir has returned to town o- since before lloroos ho has been away and the only force consisted of the CosBacks , lb0 men and some useless local nolle® # The local authorities could or woulI lot takeIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. /I9I5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, d ityr- V ' .--s London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for f by direction of the Secretary of Stale, transmits herewit h cop Lf of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, d ^ y 1 9 I 5 Reference to previous correspondence Letter ° rQm Foreign Office: 1 \In any further communication on the subject, please quote No, i. 68235/15. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 9c4J Foreign Office June 1st, 1915. Sir;- I am directed by Secretary sir Edward Grey to refer to your letter of the 28th ultimo, P.1936/15, and to state, for the infomation of Mr. secretary Chamberlain, that he concurs In the view of the Government of India that the British detachment at Bushire is adequate In present circumstances. I am, ,q l{ Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of state India Office. 'Sir Edward Grey to Mr. Marling (Tehran). PERSIA (N°. 125.) ; J ) Foreign Office, May 28, 1915, 7 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 189 of 20tli May : Murders at Ispahan. Russian Government inform me that your Russian colleague has been instructed to insist (1) on despatch of special commissioner to Ispahan to institute enquiry ; (2) dismissal of Governor, Vice-Governor, and Karguzar of Ispahan; (3) recall of Swedish officers Gleioup and Fosselius; (4) appointment of new Governor as approved by Russian Mimstei , and they ask that you should support your Russian colleague in making these demands. I should like to have your observations on proposed procedure before I reply. (Repeated to Petrograd, No. 1024.) !TO BE RETURNED TO THE^OREMlCE UNLESS REQUIRED POE PERSIA. (68964/15). POLITIOAT,. Cypher Telegram to Mr. Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, June 1st, 1915. e.io.p.m. No. 126. (R). Your telegram. No. 195 (of 30th, May. Ispahan). You may if consulted by Persian Government reconi-, mend acceptance of Russian demands - but I am doubtful if immediately after Sir P. Cox' arrangements with two of the Khans we should be too prominent in supporting a demand which would possibly alienate them.t DRAFT . U. S. of S. Foreign Office. From Sir P. Cox, 12th May. From G-.. of I., 29th May. t Sir, With reference to previous correspondence regarding measures to he adopted in Persia in antici pation of a rupture with that country, I am directed by the S. of 5. for India to forward for the information of the S. of S. for F.A., copy of further telegrams in which a policy to be pursued in the event of rupture is proposed for definite acceptance. Mr. Chamberlain recognises that, in the absence of the tribal and other arrangements proposed by Sir P. Cox but negatived by H.M.G. , the policy of withdrawal recommended by the G. of I. amounts in effect to the complete abandonment of southern Persia east of Arabistan for the duration of the war. But military operations on a large scale in this region would clearly be out of the question, if only because in the event of war with Persia iV oeomo a situation be created on the frontier of India which wrH^tax the remaining mili tary resources of the C. of I. -W. In these circumstances he pro poses, with Sir E. Grey’s concur rence to approve the more cautious policy outlined by the Government ofof India, but he sees no reason why the programme at Mohammera proposed by Sir P. Cox in the third paragraph of his telegram of 12th May should not be carried out on the outbreak of war. The Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty are being addressed with reference to the use of H. M. ships.i . mm*.. The Secretary, Admiralty. [(^j( £ From Sir P.Cox,12 May. ' Govt, of India, 29th May. Sir, I am directed by the S. of S. for India to forward for the information of the L.C. of the Admiralty copy of the telegrams noted in the margin regarding the naval and military action that will be required in the Persian Gulf in the event of war with Persia. The present garrison of Bushire consists of one battalion of native infantry. A -reghment- of Imperial Service Cavalry is on its way; but no further troops . &lt; can be spared from India. In these circumstances Mr. Chamberlain proposes to approve the more cautious policy recommended by the Government of India, with the exception that he would authorise Sir P. Cox to carry out, on the outbreak of war, the programme at Mohammera suggested in the third paragraph of his telegram. I am to express the hope that the C-in-C. East Indies station willFrom Secretary of Stale to Viceroy, Foreign. Department 18th May 1915. Foreign Secret H.s Majesty's Minister, Tehran, suggests desmteh of Russian troops to Enzeh and Resilt, and simultaneous re nforcemlnt of British detachment, Bush,re, in order to strengthen hands of new Persian (government and deter pro-German elements in Persia. Russian Government ven'emporarUyf- If lle ° eSSlty an3eS ’ C0 ' ld rei ' lfo ~'t be arranged r U/A From Viceroy, 25th May 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 18th May. Persia. We have so far anticipated your request as to despatch the remaining four companies of the 96th infantry, who reinforced Bushire on 18th, making one battalion there which seems to us sufficient infantry unless war takes place with Persia. In addition we can despatch one squadron cavalry and four mountain guns as a temporary measure if really necessary as a precaution against war. Any further infantry which may be required must come from Fore* “ H ” J v1 I) If 0 ) )r Forebn Secret. From Viceroy, 2Mi May 1915. (Repeated to Tehran and Basra.) r Reference to Cox’s telegrams, T. 13 and .. -^iid ; \i;y. Our reassuring annonncements to Persian (dull potentates in’lhe autumnbf 1914 were addressed to independent or semi-independent Arab cneis, ij&gt;r the most part in treaty relations with us, and m no way committed as except in the case of Pin Sand, Mohammera and Koweit, whose definite co-opergjtion was essential as regards occupation of Basra. 2. In the event of war with Persia we think the following policy should be dehnitely accepted : Q) We should leave Persia as a whole severely alone, taking what steps are possible to extricate Minister and Consuls and .leaving Russia to take such action as she chooses in North Persia ; (2) we should, however, endeavour to safeguard Mohammera and the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s pipe line and property ; (3) wie should continue to hold Bushire and if possible telegraph stations at Jask and Charbar. 3. For the purposes of (2), in addition to arrangement with Bakhtiaris sanctioned in your telegram of 25th May, to further recommend offer of substantial sums to Beni Turuf, Chaab and other Arab tribes as proposed by Cox in his telegram T. 14. lie might similarly be given v free ?) hand in regard to Kuhgelu tribes. regards (3), we have already in our telegram dated 25th May stated what military reinforcements are possible at Bushire. It is essential, however, that these should be supported by ships of war, which should also effectively blockade the Persian Gulf ports. We see no reason to hold Lingah Irom which the \ ice-Consulate could be withdrawn ; our action with regard to other garrisons will depend on developments.From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 'Bah May 1915. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Tehran and Secretary of State for India.) (M.) T. 20. In continuation of my telegram No. T. 1 4. I met the Baklitiari Klians, feirdar Jang and Bahadur and had full discussion with them on 23rd and 24th May. They professed to find it impossible to believe that Persia, would enter into the war against as, but expressed complete inability to give any undertaking, written or verbal, as to the attitude the tribes would adopt in the event of the central Government being drawn into war. Their argument was, if the tribes openly refused to support the policy of the Shah’s Government, they would risk having the whole of Persia against them, and that the lives of their relations in Tehran would be jeopardised. They expressed the personal view that Persia would make grievous mistake if she entered into the war, but that if she did, Bakhtiaris as loyal subjects miuht nominally have to take up arms, but that they would be able to devise means for not doing so seriously. Negotiations following effect: They can beliey g ^f that Persia will 1)£ drawn into war In any case they will express their painful convictions to the ruling Ministers, and will do their utmost to dissuade them. If, however, Persia should join our enemies they themselves under take to protect the employes and the property of the Company and to maintain order along the Bakhtiari borders to the utmost of their power. Should affairs develop so unfavourably as to make them doubt whether they can afford effective protection any longer they will give 20 days’ warning in order to enable the Company to consider and arrange other measures. During those 20 days they will continue to be personally responsible for the safety of the Oil Company’s British community.” In consideration of the above and of the fact that they have remained down in [group missing ?] a month longer than usual and assist in main taining normal conditions at the oil-fields I have given them 1.000/. each. As far as these two Khans are concerned 1 am convinced that in the event of war it is their hand fide intention to do their best to secure that the Oil Company does not suffer harm in their territory ; but some of the junior Khans have been admitting (?) irresponsible and pro-German views, and the fact that these two Khans are quite unable to answer for the tribes or any of the senior Khans warrants the suspicion that some of them have been squared by German agents. Incidentally 1 visited the oil-fields and travelled down the pipe-line, and am Submitting views to the Army Commander regarding their requirements. ended in the two Khans above-mentioned giving me a writ to the1 In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 6ut(bf /I9I5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. . \a . v\ r v&gt; 1 ^ If ; o : u The Undersecretary of Stair for- {fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for / and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, /JnezUp 24 ? , 1915 Copv to India 28 MAY 1915 Reference to previous correspondence: to Letter j rom Foreign Office: Description of Jnclosure. Name and Date. Subject. y^Rist fat £ 4 , 0 ^ /^ m&gt; \ L 27MAY1915 ; (Similar letter sent toWith reference to iry despatch No.56 of the 31 st ultiiro, I have the honour to trail sir. it to you herewith a copy of a ireiroraduir addressed to the Persian hintster for Foreign Affairs under date of March 16tn last relative to sore pazrphlets of an inMarcat^ory nature which were found among; the effects of dorr Wass- rruss. The reply of the Persian Government to the above- mentioned memorandum ia also enclosed harwith. the honour to be, with the highest respect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Right Honourable Sir Fdward Grey, Bart, M.G., H.P., etc, etc.Copy of* aide-ramoire addressed to tne L ini star Cor Foreign AfTairs, dated Larch 16 1915, lis 3ritannic Lajesty* s kini 3 ter learns fror Jts Majesty* s Consul General at Bus hire tnat aE'iong the efCects of* Herr Was situs s racontly seised was a box contain.' ing 1000 pamphlets of a moat inflammatory nature printed - in the Silfh, Durdu, Punjabi, Hindi and English languages. These pamphlets were addressed to the native soldiers of th© Indian Army calling upon them to tahe the opportunity to rise, throw off th© hated English yoke and kill their officers, Among th© papers is also a long appeal to the Mohammedan soldiers in India to rise and join the Jihad. Sir Walter Townley feels convinced that His Excellency Koaven ed Bowleh will readily recognise that a man employed upon such an errand is as much a belligerent in a neutral country as is a soldier with a weapon in his hand. When such proceedings are brought to light, thePersian Government can surely no longer credit the assur ances of the German Legation that such men as Dr Pugin, Harr ochoenemann, who carries his perfidy. Sir Walter Tovmley learns, to such a, pitch as to cadi himself a Mussulman, and Herr Was emu ss are not acting in a manner contrary to the declared neutrality of Persia. It is hardly conceivable, as has been asserted , that the Persian Government can meditate such an unfriendly act towards the allied powers as the recognition of these violators of Persia’s neutrality as German consuls. ICopy of reffioranduir trow tlie Persian April 1st 1915. Tne Imperial Persian Foreign Office has re ceived tiie rremorandum of His Oritannic i ajesty* s Legation dated March I6tli last, containing 3ir W tJorniley* s inform ation respecting Herr Wassmuss. Translation of the tele graphic reports from the British Consul at Shiraz have alsn 'been redeived by the Foreign Office. The Minister for Foreign Affairs is much sur prised at the charges brought against the Governor General of Pars and the Gendarmerie officers based on illus toragy reports from the south. Immediate enquiries were made. The authentic reports recently received by the Foreign Office are to the effect that when Herr Was emus s was attached, and his companions arrested and taken on board ship, he escaped to Borasjun, whither he was followed by a Captain, apparently called Fool, from Bender Rig. In conform ity with their duty, the Gendarmerie, with whom I err Wassruss, who was in danger, had taken refuge, es corted him to Hazerun and thence to Shiraz and naturally took hiir to their own office in that city. This measure, in default of which the gendarme would have been responsible from the point of view of local security, should not cause any suspicion nor should any evil intention be attributed to it. Out of courtesy the Governor General then send* a messenger to enquire after Herr Wassmuss* health* The ran drives there in a hired carriage. HBrr Wassmuss ex presses a wish to see the Governor General and drives in the same carriage to the Government house end demandsI —' V . ? J hi' 5 ! plundered property * The Governor General replies tdiat t»ne matter concerns Tenran • Herr Wasssiuss wialies to r^ca n in the Gendarmerie , but Major Fravita does not accept tnir &amp; the ronner goes to the house which he had .fonrerly lived ) in . « . The Governor General is perfectly sure that the report about the intention of arresting the rltish Consul which has reached the Legation , is untirely unfounded , d that tno run our has been circulated by interested persons • Contrary to this Herr Was -'muse is much alarmed tor want of security * The Governor General of Pars , whose good intenfcioiB &amp; partiality are known to the Persian Govermrentb, who are sure that ho will not take any measures against the intere to of the country , is of opinion , &amp; has expressed the sane f o the Consul , that while he does not think that the local officials will take any measures against the English , he cannot conceal the fact that the incidents at Bus hire &amp; Bonder Big which were violations of Persian neutrality have made a serious impression on the public,&amp; that the let ter feel themsalves agrloved * The idea of the Governor General, which tallies v«L t that of the Persian Government , is that there is no probch~ ility of any untoward incident in Pars for the present , but any measure,such as the landing of troops, on the part of the British Bovermrent , which is calculated to ha an infringement of Persian neutrality , may cause such excite ment 4 lead to such religious revolt in the South , as the Persian authorities may be unable to cope with • The Governor General , in reply to the Persian Government 1 s demand for explanations , expresses his suprfe e &amp; says that it is possible that h© should give up the into — adopt a policy , the ests of the Government &amp; the nationevil consequence*? ot which mould invoke the north 3.3 mil a® t Ir* South of Persia. « Hie Ixc allencf further points out that the pressure brought to bear on the Persian Sovennneit- ? IfXeuto by that of Great Britain is the autocue of based reports 6 • British officials # &amp; will cause snore difficulties &lt;1 agitd - ion rather than lessen th@&amp; • If hie Excellency Sir Walter Gownlay cor-plaixis of certain mysterious pamphlets in the possession of foreigner &amp; considers them contrary to our attitude of neutrality , yet surely the persecution of foreign subjects by British t officials in Persia &amp; the landing of troops are a clearer v 1 ™.« —v..™—~~ excitcront among the populace • The Governor General in his reports about the tel eg. - aphist at Ilasaroun says thaB he is a notorious intriguer % « ainat whom the Governor &amp; the Gendarmes continually , &amp; th Haslr Diwen recently , have complained * Ho reliance whale/ er can be placed on his reports * His removal has been rep eatedly asked for « Having full confidence in the assurances given by the Governor Gen or c 1 of Pars , the Minister for Foreign Affairs does not think that Major Pravitz &amp; the other Gendarmerie Officers would interfere with politic®, nor does he think that there is any likelihood of untoward inc: - dents occurring for the present • Captain Oertongren reports from Eazeroun tljat he was travelling over that road for the first time for purin *• see of inspection , &amp; was therefore obliged to talk to the chiefs of the villages • He always conversed with them in tie presence of throe other officers » that no never discussed politics its warned his subordinates not to do so « Tne Captdtn demands urgently fur an. enquiry to be made into these charps so tiltt rallacious cliarac er iray 'be recognised &amp; reparation made • Under tiiese circumatance® the Minister for Foreign Affairs is obliged to demand the removal of the telegraphist at Kazeroun , who has given all this trouble to the Per sin Government &amp; the British Legation . ,In vie^ of the friend ship wjioh has always existed between the two Governments&gt; A which some biased British officials in the South are now endeavouring to jeopardisise , the British Minister whoso sense of Justice &amp; Bquity is so well known , is Government the favdtur of instructing British officials to change their attitude &amp; desist from all action prejudicial to the honour of the Gendarmerie , the efficiency of which is so important for British trade . mmBmFrom Viceroy, 25th May 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 18th May. Persia. We have so far anticipated your request as to despatch the remaining four companies of the 96th infantry' who reinforced Bushire on 18th making one battalion there which seems to us sufficient infantry unless war takes place with Persia. In addition we can despatch one squadron cavalry and four mountain guns as a temporary measure if really necessary as a precaution against war. Any further infantry which may be required must come from Force “ D.”‘ x [TMa Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and sfaouid be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] ! f '*?) I'i o e 963 2 EQLW-hL . MSSIA (63625/15) r Cipiioi telegram to Sir Gr.Buchanan (Petrograd) r Foreign Office e May 21st 1915 r 4 C 15 p*n r Ivlr * Mar ling’s telegram No *189 (of 20th Ma,y * Situation in Persia)* m view of critical situation and of grave danger which would inevitably arise were Germans to establish Cabinet at Teheran, it appears undesirable to defer any longer despatch of troops to Enseli* Your Excellency should accordingly express to Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs my earnest hope that the views and recommendations submitted by Mr* Plarling will receive early and favourable considera tion* '••• Repeated to Mr* Marling No.120*i t CONFIDENTIAL, Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received May 20, 5‘5 p.m.) PERSIA Tehran, May 20, 1915. ( No - 189 -) (May 20, 2S5 p.m.) MY telegram No. 188 of 19th May. Yesterday Prime Minister tendered his resignation, but at the request of the Shah consented to remain in office. His position, however, is insecure, as Medjliss, which is falling more and more under Gferman and Turkish influence, is showing increasing mistrust of him and open hostility [group undecypherable] Minister of the Provinces. Short time ago appearance of 2,000 or 3,000 men at Enzeli might have been sufficient, but at present a larger, say 6,000 at least, is necessary, and murder at Ispahan seems to offer plausible excuse for their despatch. I have no confidence that Ain-ed-Dowleh will be able to keep things standing in Tehran for more than a few days, so there is no time to lose. If Ain-ed-Dowleh falls, next Cabinet will owe its existence to German influences. (Sent to India, Petrograd, and Basra.)FThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Qovernmen t and should be returned to the Foreign Office when dona with required for official use.] I RUSSIA . POLITICAT, . Decypher. Sir g. Buchanan (Petrograd). D. 9.30 p.ra. May 21st 1915. R. 9.15 a,ra. May 22nd 1915. No. 729. I Your telegram No. 929. ^ Ho^ I have spo-ken several times to Minister for Foreign Affairs respecting situation in Persia dnd Question of despatch of troops hut he has been able so far to take no decision owing to there being no troops to spare for the purpo se. He told me this morning that it might be possible to despatch a small force but that if so it would be sent to Kasvin and not to Enzeli as latter place was unhealthy.-I mnHupR Jt v._ :J 5 o i PERSIA P QLIIISATi , Decypher of telegram from Mr. Marling (Tehran), (dr 5.30 p.m. r. 9.5 p.m. May 23rd 1915). No.192. (H). It appears incontestable that the German Consul at Ispahan set up wireless telegraphy apparatus about two miles from that town and messages were sent here by it. Otherwise I can say nothing more as to its range At the request of Persian Government German Consul has been instructed to stop working it. Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to Basrah.&amp;nx5lch&gt;\XM yr\ '7 Cl Dated 2J OjJi. o 1915 . Pec. 25 . Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committe Under Secretary. Secretary of State efsicb 7 ft. (i/\* * Copy to ?nS/ FOR INFORMATION. Previous Papers An«i) ^ 74 . Uotes on pr incipal Tiersonages mentioned in the correspondence. L ?l 1°0 ^ Dr.»Li.s.temann: Late German Consul at Bushire; arrested by British authorities at Bushire in larch 1915 and deported to India,where he is now interned. Herr Wassrnuss : see attached copy of Press communique regarding German intrigues. Major Pravitz t Swedish gendarmerie officers. Capt.Oertenrxe n Hyder IHian : chief of Hayat Baud, a coastal district (Persian territory) north of Bushire, of which Bunder Rig is the port and chief town. Hyder Khan is firmly attached to the British interest. ' Soulet-ud-Dowleh : chief ('Ilkhani') of the Kashgais, who are the predominant tribe of the Persian province of Pars. The Kashgais are said to be of Turkoman origin, and consist of some 66 branches, comprising 25,000 families. Kawam-ul-Mulk (called 'Kawam' in the correspondence) is a leading representative of the Hashimiah family of Shiraz (capital of Pars), which is possessed of extensive landedlanded property and much influence in the province. He and his adherents are at feud with the Kashgais. Sardar-i-Janf: . Chief of the 'Haji Ilkham” branch of the Bakhtiari tribe (the tribe is divided into 2 main branches, known as the 'Ilkhani” and the 'Haji Ilkhani'). The Bakhtiaris are the Highlanders of Persia, and from very remote times have occupied the mountain tract lying between the province of Arabistan and that of Ispahan. Of recent years the 'Khans' or leading men of the tribe have exercised great influence over the central Govern ment at Tehran, where some of them care in more or less permanent residence; they also hold a certain number of /VUTY v* , ' * governorships, including that of Ispahan. The Bakhtiari country is outside the British 'Sphere' as defined by the Anglo-Russian Agreement of 1907; but their relations with the British Government have been intimate for many years past, and the retention of their goodwill is important to us because we look to them to protect (1) the trade route (known as the 'Lynch road') from Ahwaz to Ispahan; and (2) the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s property and oil-fields, in which H.M.Govt. have - ■ '4 l ' tyyi'U. -$-■ '■ ' ,: 'f''’ $L\y\- f ^ '-.J-^} The Secretary of State for India communicates the following :— Documentary evidence has reached His Majesty’s Government provin conclusively that German consular officers in Persia and the agents of the German firm of Wonckhaus have been engaged in intrigues with the object of facilitating the Turkish invasion of Persia and of raising the tribes against Great Britain, thus flagrantly violating Persian neutrality. For example, not only were the agents of Messrs, Wonckhaus at Ahwaz and Mohammerah found to be in direct communication with the Turkish troops, but an elaborate plot has been discovered of which Afghanistan, the frontier, and the Indian Army are the objective. Herr Wassmuss , who was formerly German Consul at Bushire, and has recently been appointed German Consul at Shiraz (where Germany lias no commercial interests and has not hitherto had a consul), was the prime mover in this. It is now known that he was at Cairo shortly before the war, and in Constantinople when war broke out. Accompanied by four other Germans and four Indians who were sent from Berlin to join him at Constantinople, he made his way to the Persian frontier, and thence to Shiraz. Among his effects was a box containing several thousand violently inflammatory pamphlets in the English, Urdu, Hindu, Punjabi, and Sikh languages, addressed to the Indian Army, calling on them to take the opportunity to throw off the hated yoke and rise and kill their officers. A long appeal to Mussulman soldiers in India was also found, urging them to join in jehad. This person is now at Shiraz awaiting instructions frpm the German Legation at Tehran. Not less discreditable is a correspondence which has come into our possession between the German Legation and the Consul at Bushire? Some time ago a large consignment of arms and ammunition arrived at that port, and was hurriedly and secretly conveyed up-country by the Swedish officers of gendarmerie. The following telegrams were exchanged From German Legation to German Consul, Bushire. “ Thanks, for news regarding arms. Please henceforth do not manifest any further interest. \\ eapons will be fetched away for our secret object. From German Consul to German Legation. “ Weapons were fetched away some days ago by Swedish officer. My promotion of this affair has remained inconspicuous throughout. Light is thrown upon the “secret object by the following facts. Ihe German Consul had been in communication with the Persian bheikh Rais Ali of Dilwar, a coast town some miles to the south of Bushire, regarding a proposed attack on the latter place which Rais Ali w^as apparently anxious to begin at once. The German Legation telegraphed as follows on the 19th February :— “Reference telegram No. 25, dated lehran, 1st instant, regarding undesirability of immediate action by Rais Ali, and the absolute futility of independent action. Please hold him well in hand and assure im confidently of a movement in the spring. If you really think him ic lab e and consider that circumstances are ripe for action there, wouic R e a good thing to make out a plan secretly with him which would be combined with an already arranged secret action led from here and would at the same time win over all Persia ? As soon as possible wil et you mow secretly further on this matter.’% Telegram, No. 702 B., dated the 1st April 1915. From The Hon'blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C I E CST Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ’ * *’ * ,1 *» T ° The ^orelaryto th e Government ot India in the Foreign and Political Depart- Letter from Persian gendarmerie officer employed speaking foolishly and offensively of the British having been found among Listemann’s papers! copv was handed by First Assistant Bushire, to Captain Oertengren at his recent meeting with protest, bwedish Commandant, Shiraz, having now seen letter telegraphs as follows :— ’ Begins. Informed of letter from Abu Turab to German Consul and have given orders to arrest him. Thankful if you will inform me about such incidents regarding gendarmerie who violate neutrality that I am commanded to protect. Ends. Addressed to His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran; and repeated to Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and Secretary of State for India. -5, Telegram R., No. 706 B., dated the 1st (received 2nd) April 1915. From— The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Beliable reports received from Dizful indicate that general attitude of inhabitants is satisfactory and they are not inclined to respond to religious appeal. Reports also state that Sardar Jang specifically asked Minister of the Interior for instructions as to what line he should take in connection with present situation in Arabistan and incursion of Turks and religious volunteer(s) hut cannot get reply. It would help matters good deal if Minister of the Interior could he only induced to telegraph unequivocal instructions to Bakhtiari Khans and Vali to do their best to discourage and disassociate themselves from incursion and holy war cry. If telegram is sent, I trust Your Excellency will he able to telegraph to me a copy. Addressed to Minister; repeated to Foreign. Telegram R., No. 709 B., dated the 1st (received 2nd) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz, No. 70, dated 1st April:— Begins. Major Pravitz is much perturbed by accusations brought against Swedish officers and has telegraphed to Tehran that he wishes to resign his present post. There is no saying whether he is definitely associated with German plans or not, but Captain Oertengren and some of the other Swedes certainly are and practically all Persian Officers of the Fars regiment of gendarmerie are openly pro-German and anti-British. In spite of Pravitz’s orders to the contrary, they continue to take prominent part in campaign against us. If any arrangement can be made for replacing the Swedes, it would seem favourable opportunity for accepting Pravitz’s resignation and effecting^ entire change of gendarmerie svstem in Southern Persia. Addressed to lehranj repeated to Basrah, Bushire. Ends. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to India Office.Telegram R., No. 703 B., dated (and received) the 2nd April 1915. From—The Hon'blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Information was recently received from Amara to the effect that the Commandant of Turkish force (War ?) Ahwaz, had telegraphed to Constanti nople, via Amara, saying that he was not strong enough to attack the British position. He has since received reinforcements, hut his want of confidence is further shown by desperate but apparently abortive efforts on his part, and that of the Alujtahid, who accompanies him, to corrupt the Arab troops and populace of Ahwaz, and revive holy war cry. Incidentally, Mujtahid declares tribesmen and volunteers are acting with cognizance of Persian Government, who is not neutral, and that even if she is, then Islam is not. General Officer Commanding is now increasing force at Ahwaz by another British regiment. If, when they arrive, military authorities consiaer them selves strong enough to deal an effective blow at the Turco-Arab force, I am convinced that it will do a great deal to settle the general situation in Arabistan, and enable pipe lines to be repaired, and measures to be taken for its future security. Examination of the last Persian mail bags from Ahwaz and MohammeraU shows that the attitude of literary section of Arabistan public is very satis factory. There is no mention oi jehad \ military position is commented on quite intelligently, and if our casualties are exaggerated, so also are our strength and resources, and there is no sign of nervousness as to our position generally. As regards Southern Arabistan, fanatical and disaffected elements have defeated Sheikhas representatives and adherents in Jarahi, Hindia, Dehmulla and Mashur, and those districts may be regarded as lost to Sheikh, until he can recover them after the war. Movement seems to be marking time for the moment, but any stimulating cause would no doubt extend it further through the hinterland towards Bushire. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to Minister and India Office. Telegram R., No. 710 B., dated (and received) the 2nd April 1915. From— The Hon'ble Lieutinant-Colonbl Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz, 1st April:— Begins. I venture to impress on Your Excellency desire to get rid of present Governor-General as soon as possible. There is authentic evidence he is centre of influences hostile to British interests in these parts. So called democratic party are leaders of the anti-British campaign and Governor- General has latterly allied himself openly with this movement. Leaders are all associates and intimates of the Governor-General and are evidently acting under his instigation. Fortunately there is a strong party against Governor-General, but he and German Agent in any case are leaving no stone unturned to win over or vanquish these persons. With removal of Governor-General we should, I believe, see immediate improvement in situation in Southern Persia. Addressed to Minister ; repeated to Basrah. Ends. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to India Office. .....■ xr(3 * fo- Telegram R., No. 711 B., dated (and received) the 2nd April 1915. From-The Hon'bl* LiEUTaNaHT-CoLOKeL Sie Pekct Coi, K.C.I.E. C.S I Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, , * ’ ** T0_,rhe ments7mla. the G0TernmeDt o{ India in and Political Depart- My telegram, No. 703 B., 1st April. As situation at Ahwaz is still reported quiet and as new Force Commander is expected to reach Basrah on 5th or 6th, General Officer Commanding does not wish to make any considerable movements (of) troops in the meantime. Extra battalion for Ahwaz alluded to in paragraph 3 of above-mentioned telegram will not be consequently despatched. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to Tehran and India Office. % Telegram R., No. 712 B., dated (and received the 2nd April 1915. From—The Hon'blb Lieutbnant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, KCIE CSI Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ’ '* ‘ To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla; v Owing to expeditionary force having gradually increased to strength of two divisions and oyer, Sir John Nixon, Commander, Northern Army in India, is on the way to assume Command of force. He left Bombay on 1st April in “ Pentakotta ”, and will touch at Bushire, about oth April, where ship will land detachment of 96th Infantry, forming usual annual relief of Bushire detachment. Firstly, please make necessary intimation to Governor when you think time^ has arrived, and, secondly, proceed on board “ Pentakotta ” to visit General Nixon, with maps of the island, and explain situation with reference to position and attitude of several Khans of the hinterland and gendarmerie. Addressed Bushire; repeated Shiraz, Tehran, Government of India. Telegram, No. 721 B., dated the 3rd April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lirutrnant-Colonbl Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Situation Bushire hinterland. Please see last paragraph of my telegram 498, paragraph 2, my telegram 534, and paragraph 2, Foreign Department telegram 322 D.-S. On 25th March, Bushire telegraphed that there were persistent rumours that gendarmerie under orders from Tehran were contemplating very early attack on Hyder Khan in conjunction with Khans of Borasiun, Shahbancara, Chahcuta and Tangistan. On 26th March, under my No. 647, I urged upon British Minister, Tehran, that/simply^, owning to their staunchness and co-operation with us, Sheikh of Mbhammerah and Hyder Khan were become objects of active hostility of our enemies and of jehad element; that Hyder Khan had in the past rendered most valuable and courageous service to His Majesty’s Government by personal participation in arrest of Arab pirates and by unfailingly assisting British trade and British interests and now in con nection with arrest of German and that it was incumbent on us to give him all the backing w'e possibly could. On 27th March, British Minister, Tehran, agreed and telegraphed that energetic representation had been made to Persian Government.^ On 1st April, I enquired wffiat had been response. On 2nd April, British Minister, Tehran, informed me that he had then been given assurance that necessary steps would he taken, but that he w ould press matter again. a4 In the meantime, although my protests in Tehran and elsewhere will probably deter Swedes and gendarmerie from actual participation in attack, there seems to be no doubt that hostile Khans are receiving secret encourage ment from Governor-General and Persian gendarmerie officers while to-day Bushire reports that Governor of Bushire has received telegram from Mini ster of Interior informing him that Minister for Foreign Affairs is attacking Governor bitterly in Tehran for failing to make any remonstrance against Hyder Khan in connection with attempted arrest of Wassmuss. It is clear from above that any one who co-operates with us becomes object of hostility on the part of Government officials, and that, when above is attitude of Foreign Minister, no mere assurances of Persian Government can be relied upon. I have telegraphed above resume as it may be necessary to decide urgently what amount and form of support we intend to give Hyder Khan. Telegram R., No. 729 B., dated (and received) the 4th April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutrnant-Colqnbl Sie Percy Cox, K.C.I.E, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Tour telegram No. 126, April 2nd. In view of facts reported in Bushire telegram No. 112 C., indicating per sonal attitude of Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs, it would not appear that reliance can be placed on assurances given Your Excellency and further action seems urgent if attack on Hyder Khan is to be averted. He is threatened by hostile Khans on Bushire side and by fanatical rebels via Lirawi on the west encouraged so far as we can judge by Bakhtiari element at Behbehan. (Persistent ?) withdrawal of gendarmerie will, of course, help greatly. Is there any further deterrent action you can take in Tehran ? I have asked Bushire if there are any particular steps they can suggest which would support Hyder Khan directly or indirectly. Meanwhile H. M. S. “ Clio ” is at Bushire and Residency has authority to ask her to proceed to Bunderrig, if necessary. Addressed to Minister; repeated to Bushire, Government of India. /0 Telegram R., No. 742 B., dated the 3rd (received 4th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Pebct Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Minister, April 3rd :— Begins. Your telegram No. 38—269. I spoke emphatically to Prime Minister yesterday on the subject of threatened attack on Hyder Khan which I said was largely engineered by Ali Kuli Khan of the gendarmerie who ought to be dismissed. I warned His Highness that, if local Khans attacked Hyder Khan, it was more than probable that they would find themselves face to face with British troops as we should defend him. I added that Persian Govern ment would be held solely responsible if such a deplorable incident occurred, as they had done nothing to oblige local authorities to keep peace. Addressed Bushire ; repeated to Basrah, Shiraz, Ends. Addressed Government of India ; repeated to India Office.5 // Telegram P., No. 71-5 B., dated the 4th (received 5th) April 1915. From—The Hon’blb Lieutenant-Colonbl Sir Percy Cox. K C.I.E C S T Pnli. tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, ’ •&gt;•••&gt; To The Secreta^tothe Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- Please see Minister s telegram of April 3rd re Hyder Khan. Merely because he is a staunch friend of ours, he is threatened simultaneously by an exten sion of Arabistan moyement from west, and by an attack from the Borasiun confederacy on east. Were he to be attacked and defeated for want of backing from us, our good name would suffer lasting harm ; hostile movements in hinterland would receive great stimulus, and attack on Bushire would nro- bably follow. ^ General Nixon reaches Bushire by transport on April 5th or April 6th. I trust he will be authorised to discuss local situation with Colonel Knox] whom I have instructed to call on him with necessary papers. I should say that the despatch to Banderrig of a gunboat and transport with battalion and gun on board, to be landed in case of imminent attack would be quite sufficient to avert trouble. Addressed Government of India; repeated to Tehran and Bushire for information of General Nixon. r /x Telegram P., dated the 3rd (received 4th) April 1915. From—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla. Swedish gendarmerie. Beference Sir P. Cox’s telegram, No. 709 B, dated the 1st instant. The charges made by the Consul at Shiraz are vague and general. What definite evidence is there in support of them? Effective action by His Majesty’s Government for the removal of Swedish officers is difficult in absence of such evidence. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to Sir P. Cox. /S Telegram R., dated the 4th (received 5th) April 1915. From—The Hon’blb Lieutenant-Golonrl Sir Percy Cox, K C J.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla, Pollowing from Minister, April 3rd :— Begins, “ His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz reports that Governor-General still continues to associate himself openly with Wassmuss and German party. “ I caused representations to be made to Minister for Eoreign Affairs yesterday and myself personally saw Prime Minister. His Highness asserted that he had sent categorical instructions to Governor-General, Ears. “ I replied that this was further proof that his recall is imperative, as from latest information in my possession it was clear that His Excellency pays no attention to his instructions. t “ Prime Minister replied that he was ready to recall Governor-General but that it was difficult for him to do so unless he had something by way of com pensation as a quid pro quo to offer public opinion. In a conversation in which very plain speaking was indulged in, I pointed out in answer to His Highness’s assurances that Cabinet was imbued with most friendly sentiments to Great Britain, that coincidences are unfortunately against Persia and that they may combine to shake faith of Persia’s English friends in her sincerityNo one, I said, would realize better than His Highness what the loss of British sympathy might mean, to Persia. « As coincidences I cited that whereas all that is possible appears to be done for Germans, Persian officials in whom we have confidence, such as Sheikh of Mohammerah, Hyder Khan of Bunderrig, Governor (of) Bushire and Deputy Governor (of) Bunder Abbas, are not only not supported but are harassed and bullied. Also Swedes who were formerly roundly abused, because of their insubordination to Minister of the Interior are now darlings of the Cabinet because they are openly pro-German, whereas Belgians who are our allies are publicly attacked in (public talk) and press and are being hounded out of the country by systematic hostility of Government. “ Prime Minister endeavoured to defend himself but, I think, realized that such unfortunate (coincidences) made his excuse a poor one. His one remedy for all misunderstandings is evidently recall of Russian troops. “ I replied that this could not be done now and^ added I was inclined to think that if carried out it would be accepted as a sign of weakness and would make bad worse. Repeated to Petrograd and Basrah. ” Repetition ends. Addressed Government of India; repeated to Bushire. No. Cf. 115, dated Bushire, the 27th March (received 5th April) 1915 (Confidential). p r0 m Captain W. G. Neale, First Assistant Resident, (in the absence of the Resident), To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. In connection with present attitude of Swedish officers of gendarmerie in South Persia, I have the honour to submit under instructions from Lieuten ant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.LE., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, copies of the two telegrams noted on the margin. From Signaller, Borasjun, to Resident, Bushire, dated 20th March 1915. From Signaller, Borasjun, to Resident, Bushire, dated 20th March 19i5. I also submit a copy of report from a secret agent employed by this Residency and Cosulate-General, which corroborates the information given in the above reports relative to the attitude of Captain Oertengren. A copy of this letter and its enclosures is being forwarded to the India Office. No. Cf. 115, dated Bushire, the 27th March 1915. From— Captain W. G. Neale, First Assistant Resident (in the absence of the Resident and His Majesty J s Consul-General for Fars, &amp;c.), To—The Political Secretary, India Office, London, S.-W. In connection with present attitude of Swedish officers of gendarmerie in South Persia, I have the honour to submit, under instructions from Lieutenant- „ ^ . Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.LE, C.S.I., d»SoXKr iu “' to KeS ‘ deat ’ E ” h,,e ' Political Resident in the Pereian Gulf, From Signaller, Borasjun, to Resident, Bushire, copies of the two telegrams noted 0U the dated 20th March 1915. margin. I also submit a copy of report from a secret agent employed by this Residency and Consulate-General, wTiich corroborates the information given in the above reports relative to the attitude of Captain Oertengren. A copy of this letter and its enclosures is being forwarded to the Govern ment of India.Telegram, dated the 2Cth March 1915. From—The Signaller, Borasjun, To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ,, ^ ( ' ir( -' ular written and sent apparently from Bushire to Haji Ismail of the Sefa Company reporting that the British forces at Ahwaz had been f a i ? 9 n y n viT U / a ? d n d o rl T 0ut ? f Ahwaz - aa d that the British lost about 1,200 killed an d 12 offlecrs and 160 men taken prisoners, and 12 guns and quantity of ammunition, &amp;e captured. This circular was put in a coyer addressed to Ghazanfar Saltaneh and handed to a dumb hoy to deliver. A certain party here seeing the cover in the boy’s possession took him to' his house, opened the cover and read the contents. He closed it up a&lt;rain and returned it to the boy, who eventually delivered it to Ghazanfar ° Telegram, dated the 20th March 1915. From—The Signaller, Borasjun, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Captain Oertengren returned to Borasjun this morning. Information that I have been able to gather is that he went to Sadabad and interviewed Ismail Khan. He expounded the urgent necessity of his making peace with Ghazanfar and then went on to say that as tiie British were not^observino* the neutrality of Persia all the Khans should join hands and get ready to protect interests of Persia in the South, and that, should it be necessary, help could be obtained from the North. He said that we all know that the Persian Govern ment has no standing army to protect her rights, hence the necessity of imme diate co-operation of all the Khans in upholding the rights and safety of Persia. Ismail Khan replied (apparently ironically) that Ghazanfar was chief and leader of the Khans in the South, and that, if necessity arose, he should lead the cause and we would follow him. Special messenger has been despatched to-day, and on his return I will wire his version if his report does not corroborate this. Report of Agha Mohsin's (Consular Dragoman) wool buyer, sent as secret agent to Shahbancara, dated the 24th March 1915. On Saturday last (20th March) the agent met the gendarmerie party near Khushab, numbering 25 gendarmes, one Swedish officer, and three Persian Officers; they were coming to Bushire after calling Sa’adabad. On Sunday, when the agent arrived at Sa’adabad he obtained information from Kerblai Ismail, the servant of Ismail Khan of Shahbancara, that the officer of the gendarmerie during an interview with Ismail Khan on the previous day had obtained from the latter (Ismail Khan) a written promise binding himself to be obedient and act in whatever way the gendarmerie officers ordered him to do. The agent also heard at Sa’adabad that the gendarmerie intend to make an attack on Bundar Rig with the help of Ismail Khan, Ghazanfar-us-Saltaneh (Borasjun), Zair Khadar of Tangistan, Sheikh Husain of Chahkutah, Rais Ali of Dilwar and a certain number of men from Dashti. The agent heard at Ahmedi that there is an appointment for Ghazanfar, Zair Khadar, Sheikh Husain Khan and a representative of Ismail Khan, all to proceed and meet each ether at Chahkutah and consult with each other how to go to Bundar Rig and further to take an oath that they will always remain friends and in good terms.Telegram P., No. 338 S., dated the 6th April 1915. From—The Secretary to the Goyernment of India in the Foreign and Political Dapartment, Simla, rj! 0 __jpij e Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political ^ Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah. [Repeated to (1) His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran. (2) Lieutenant- Colonel S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Bushire.J Please refer to correspondence ending with your telegram, 4th instant, No. 745 B., Hyder Khan. Instructions to following effect have issued to General Nixon : “Whilst His Excellency the Gommander-in-Chief desires you to discuss the question thoroughly with Colonel Knox, the following objections to getting entangled on the mainland must be kept in mind. To fight the battles of local chiefs or to interfere in tribal quarrels is not our policy. Any rupture with lersia or breach of her neutrality likely to result in a rupture is to be carefully avoided, and it is necessary to prevent being drawn into a diversion except as ma y be necessary for the protection of British property and life at Bushire. With the exception of 96th Infantry no troops without reference to me should be landed. ,, /£. Telegram P., dated the 6th April 1915. From—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla, To—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. Hyder Khan. Please refer to Sir P. Cox’s telegram of 3rd instant, No. 742 B. Sir P. Cox on the 4th instant telegraphed that Hyder Khan of Hiaut Hand was, because of his services to us, threatened both by Borasjun confederacy in East and from Arabistan on West, and he urged that General Nixon, who is expected to arrive at Bushire on the 5th or 6th instant, should, after discussing the matter with Colonel Knox, take necessary action in support of Hyder Khan. Instructions have, after full consideration, been issued to General Nixon to discuss situation with Colonel Knox but not to land any troops without making a reference to Government of India. It has been explained to him that it is not our policy to fight battles of local chiefs or interfere in tribal quarrels, that we must endeavour to avoid any breach of neutrality likely to lead to rupture with Persia and that we must not be drawn into diversion unless forced to do so for protection at Bushire of British property and life. Telegram P., dated the 6th April 1915. From—His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla, To—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. Reports from Basrah indicate that the concentration of Turkish forces against Basrah is nearly completed and that within ten days an attack is expected. Fifteen Germans, of whom five are officers and ten artillery sergeants, are said to be with the enemy. New Turkish Commander is said to have arrived at the Turkish camp above Kurnah ; also one aeroplane. Telegram R., No. 748 B., dated (and received) the 5th April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please see reference in Reuter (telegram) of 3rd April, regarding attitude of Italian Government in regard to German mission to Abyssinia.I YCDture to suggest to Your Excellency that it would form valuable precedent to adhere to in support of a demand that Wassmuss should be required to leave Shiraz and proceed to say Tehran and that Germans now iu Ispahan and elsewhere should not be allowed to proceed further east or to leave towns in which they are now residing unless to return to Turkey. Addressed Minister ; repeated to Government of India. Telegram R., No. 750 B., dated (and received) the 5th April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Eollowing from Bushire, April 4th :— Begins. This evening Governor informed me that he has received a tele gram from Minister of the Interior approving His Excellency’s action as shown in recent telegrams. I trust this is outcome of our representations pressing for support and means that they are taking juster view of situation here. Addressed Cox; repeated to Tehran. Ends. 2.0. Telegram R., No. 759 B., dated the 6th (received 7th) April 1915. ir r o m —The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Eollowung from Shiraz, 77, April 6th :— Begins. Reference Bushire, 43—288. I have frequently spoken both ^ to Governor-General and Pravitz regarding attitude and proceedings of Persian gendarmerie officers and although both have assured me their political activities would be checked and although formal orders to this effect have been issued to Pravitz, no other measures of any kind seem to have been taken and these officers continue to conduct active campaign against our interests iu co-operat ing with Wassmuss and democratic party here. I regret to say I have lost any belief I originally had in Pravitz s profes sions of neutrality. If these were sincere, he could by now have taken effective steps to enforce attention to these orders and to punish disobedience. Tsot onlv has he not done (so) but his own attitude is most ambiguous and unsatis factory and he himself spreads absurd reports regarding defeats of the allies, German victories, &amp;c. There can. I think, he no doubt whatever that he, as well as other Swedes, is cognizant of German plans and is working hand in glove with them to destroy our influence in South and to embarrass us in every possible wa y* receive daily many proofs of this. Their early removal is, m my opinion, imperative for preservation of our interests in Southern Persia. Adc resse Tehran ; repeated to Basrah, Bushire. Ends. Addressed Government of India; repeated to India Office. 42/ Telegram R., No. 763 B., dated (and received) the 7th April 1915. From—The Hobble Liutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and o itica epar ment, Simla. Your telegram No. 388 S. Hyder Khan.Tehran telegram No. 130, dated April 4th, repeated to you from Bushire, engenders hope that attitude of Persian Government is improving under pressure] and this improvement will probably be refleuted in behaviour of hostile Khans. But the message of His Excellency the Commander-in-Chief to General Nixon, makes it evident that there is considerable misapprehension, which, I trust, Foreign Department will remove. This is not a case of a tribal quarrel, or of our fighting the battles of a local Khan, nor would the deterrent presence of a gunboat, and a vessel conveying a detachment of troops to be landed in emergency, in sight of ships, involve any entanglement on mainland, any more than many other such landings on Persian coast during the past few years. What we are dealing with now is a conspiracy of hostile Khans, engineered by German agents and gendarmerie, with the object of injuring us indirectly by attacking the only Khan, who has openly stood in with us. But for Hyder Khan’s co-operation, the German scheme would never have been revealed in time, and had it materialised, we should have been confronted with a very much more serious situation. It is rather a case of his fighting our battle than we his. As regards action on mainland, please see my telegram No. 494 B., dated 13th March, paragraph 2. Addressed to Foreign; repeated to Minister and Bushire. Telegram R., No. 765 B., dated (and received) the 7th April 1915. From— The Hon'ble Lieutbnant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I.. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegrams Nos. 61 B., dated 14th January and 382 B., dated 3rd March. I have received further letter from Araibi Pasha, a most important Sheikh of Albu Aduhammad, in neighbourhood of Amara, saying that religious volunteer force is weakened by dissensions, and incapable of attack or defence, and that Havize tribe is in a state of expectant fear of our reprisals, whilst Amara tribes only wonder at our delay in coming. Corroboration of above is found in arrival of a messenger at Ahwaz from above-mentioned Sheikh and others hitherto sitting on the fence, but now offering to help Sheikh of Mohammerah by attacking Havize or Bani Turuf in his interests. Message ends. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to India OflQ.ce and Tehran. £3. Telegram P., No. 770 B., dated the 8th (received 9th) April 1915. From —The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. The following telegram has been received from His Maiesty’s Minister at Tehran, 113, dated 8th April:— Begins. Please refer to my telegram No. 114 (?). Latest reports which have been received from Kermanshah are of an alarming nature. Ten thousand Turkish troops are stated to be threatening the frontier, whilst loyalty of Kalkhan and Kalhor is doubtful. In addition, the fact that German agents have enrolled about one hundred ruffians as guards, gives rise to great uneasiness. it is feared that situation may pass beyond Governor-General’s power of control. His Majesty’s Consul has requested permission to enrol sowars. I have informed him in reply that there would be no object in adopting such a course, which3 it&amp;ysxs « f , 1 have informed Minister for Foreign Affairs of situation. His Excel- lency asserts that a telegram has been sent bv the Turkish Ambnl^ln^ frontier milltary aU ° riUeS to the effeot that t ’ roo P* should no^ cross the Repeated to Sir Percy Cox and Petrograd. End of menage. 24-. Telegram R., No. 39, dated the 9th (received 10th) April 1915, From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. ^ Cox’s telegram, No. 765 B., to Government of India. There appear to be signs here that pro-Turldsh movement is losing ground. Arrival of very influential and important member of clergy from” Kerbala has resulted in confirmation of rumours, previously received, of Turkish exac tions, at the expense of Shiah community in Mesopotamia. People are also beginning to learn extent of Turkish exactions at Tabriz. Movement on Kermansnah frontier is likely further to check enthusiasm for Turkish- German cause. It was probably really this, that caused the Ambassador to telegraph, that Turkish troops should not cross the frontier. Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; repeated to India and Basrah. al 'MUX i 26' Telegram R., No. 775 B., dated the 9th (received 10th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sib, Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. On 17th March I addressed a friendly communication to Sowlet-et-Dowleh, among others, explaining position and intrigues of Germans, and urging on him the importance of keeping his tribesmen quiet and neutral and not making difficulties for his own Government by listening to advice of intriguers whose purpose it was to make strife. I have now received a satisfactory telegram from him via Shiraz. Addressed to Minister; repeated to Government of India. : Telegram R., No. 126 C., dated (and received) the 10th April 1915. From— Captain W. G. Neale, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz, No. 75 :— Begins. Edwal has telegraphed to Pravitz substance of a letter received from the Minister of the Interior to the effect that the Persian Government are well satisfied with good services rendered by Pravitz and that they propose to reward him suitably. This is evidently the Persian Government’s reply to Pravitz’s resignation, and our representations regarding attitude of Swedish officers. Addressed to Tehran; repeated to Basrah and Bushire. Ends.Telegram R., No. 791 B., dated the 10th (received 11th) April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Libutin ant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- $ ment, Simla. Case of Uyder Khan. According to Mohammerah reports, the Atabistan rebels, who were threatening Lirawi, have turned back and joined Chaab in their movement towards Ahwaz. According to Bushire reports, it is thought that efforts are being made to collect supplies, and Khans are being encouraged by Wassmuss to hope that orders will be received from Central Government to proceed with attack on Hvder Khan. They lack cohesion and ammunition, and attack is unlikely to materialise, unless they receive fresh incentive and support from gendarmerie and Governor-General. It is clear therefore that our best course for the present is to continue pressing for the withdrawal of gendarmerie and recall of Governor-General. Addressed to India; repeated to Tehran. Telegram P., No. 125 C., dated the 10th (received 11th) April 1915. From— Captain W. G. Neale, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at Tehran telegraphs as follows :— “No. 130. Yesterday I met, at Alaes-Sultaneh’s house, the Prime Mini ster. His Highness had, it appeared evident, been much impressed by the warning I had given to him two days previously (as reported in my telegram No. 142) of the danger that Persia is running by alienating sympathy of her friends in Great Britain by the pursuit of her present Unsatisfactory policy. He enquired from me what he could do to improve matters. “ He should, I replied, send a telegram to the Governor of Bushire approv ing his conduct, should arrange for the removal from Borasjun of Ali Kali Khan, and in the first instance should take steps to put a stop to the movement against Hyder Khan of Bunderrig. He made a promise that he would do this at once. His promise respecting the Governor of that part has been carried out as a telegram has been received from Bushire showing this. “ This afternoon I received a call from His Highness and he begged me to represent to you that he is sincerely desirous of retaining the goodwill of His Majesty’s Government and doing all in his power not to forfeit it. In accordance with his promise he had sent telegrams to the above-mentioned persons. He also had had a private telegram sent by bis nephew, Minister of Posts and Telegraphs, to the town (of) Pars to which he has received a satisfactory reply. He also promised to send Sardar Jang a telegram request ing him not for the present to come north, but did not appear to he very confident of his influence over Bakhtiari. (I have urged this on Khans here! (?) His Highness had also impressed (on) a convocation (of) Members meeting that the true interests of Persia demanded close friendship with Great Britain. His words had met a most satisfactory echo. He would see clergy and also editors of (the) chief papers and speak in same strain, tbough the leading Mulla(s) of Tehran had, he could assure me, remained 1 loyal to the cause (of) Great Britain. He had great hopes of bringing about a complete change (of) (in ?) public opinion but he longed for the downfall (of) Constantinople by which he said his task would he largely facilitated.13 “About the recall (of) Eussian troops or ratifications His Highness said that he would say no more. All he asked for was the goodwill and support (of) His Majesty’s Government. He would (be) deeply grateful if it were possible (to) help Persia by suspending service (of) foreign loans for two ^ years dating from 1st August last. “ Prime Minister is a (straight ?) man. Sincerity of his accent carried conviction. Our conversation might, His Highness begged, be considered as strictly confidential. “Repeated Shiraz and Petrograd, Busbire and Basrah.” Telegram R., No. 800 B., dated the 11th (received 12th) April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please see my telegram No. 748 B., dated April 5th. Kindly let me know what the present position is as regards Wassmuss. His there been any definite result from pressure of two Legations, and is any thing definite pending ? Addressed to Tehran; repeated to Government of India. 30- Telegram R., No. 804 B., dated the 11th (received 12th) April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz, 12th(?) April:— “Your telegram No. 49. “ I gather from Governor-General’s attitude during last two or three days that Your Excellency’s conversations with Prime Minister have produced good effect. Governor-General has both spoken and written me in satisfactory terms. He has assured me he is doing every thing in his power to repress anti-British agitation and that he has even counselled Wassmuss to stop his intrigues. “Wassmuss, who dresses as Persian and poses as Mussulman, is busy carrying on his campaign by all means in his power. His chief supporters arc democratic party, Persian gendarmerie officers and riff raff. “ No instructions would appear to have been issued for recall (of) Ali Kuli Khan from Borasjun. “Addressed Tehran; repeated to Basrah, Bushire.* Ends. 3/ Telegram R., No. 798 B., dated the 11th (received 12th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Reference India Office telegram, April 3rd. Evidence against gendar- merie.14 Swedes themselves of course careful not to put anything in writing, and nothing of a tangible nature has so far come to hand beyond what had already been telegraphed. Please see my telegrams 532, 541, 56S, 650 and 675. I submit that following items collectively constitute strong case jirst .—Sudden removal by Swedes under most secret arrangements of a large quantity of arms and ammunition which German Consul’s correspondence proves to have been intended for secret purposes of the German Legation. If they were intended for gendarmerie, then there was absolutely no reason for secrecv or for German Consul or Legation to have any connection with matter. As it was, Lundberg, who came to fetch them, observed utmost secrecy and though be had many friends in Bushire saw no one except the German Consul with whom he stayed. Secondly .—On 13 th, 17 th and 21st February, German Legation telegraphed to German Consul to collect all money possible and remit to Tehran for official purposes through Swedish officers, mentioning Lundberg and Prayitz by name. Thirdly-—On 11th March, Pravitz telegraphed peremptory messaore to Resident demanding release of German Consul, a matter which did not properly concern him at all. Fourthly.—Shvcw reported on the 17th March that Pravitz had sent a telegram to the gendarmerie at Borasjun by Persian line ordering them to prevent landing at Bushire of British troops. Fifthly .—Two visits were paid by Oertengren to Khan Shahbancara, though place is off the road and it is no part of his duties to go there. After him two more visits were paid by his Lieutenant AH Kuli Khan, all with object of getting the Khan to make peace with Borasjun with whom he is on bad terms in order to join in attack on Hyder Khan or Bushire. Oertengren was unable to give any satisfactory explanation of these visits when taxed by First Assistant at interview on 25th March. Sixthly .—Report of Mr. Stas, the Belgian, on his passage down to Bushire, vide my telegram 675 B. Seventhly. —Discovery in German Consul’s papers of letter from the Persian gendarmerie officer (Abu Turab) making hostile references to the British. Eighthly .—Residency messengers taking pacifying letters to the Khans of the hinterland urging on them the importance of remaining quiet in the interests of their Government were stopped and ill-treated as such by gendar merie posts. We have had constant reports by telegraph signallers on Shiraz (line), but it would put them in danger to quote them by name. Addressed to Government of India and repeated to India Offic e. 32.. Telegram R., No. 824 B., dated the 12th (received 13th) April 1915. Prom—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Minister, April 12th :—- “ My telegram No. 152. “ Government has received information that four thousand Turks with guns have occupied Kasrshirin. “ Addressed Foreign Office, No. 156.” Ends.15 33 , Telegram, No. 806 B., dated the 12th (received 14th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sie Percy Cox Km? Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ’ ‘ ‘ ‘ ^ To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political ment, Simla. My telegram, dated 2nd April, 702 B. C.S.L, Depart- v Ab f u Tu f t b has been recalled to Shiraz from outpost duty and his case has been referred to 1 enran by Pravitz for instructions. Addressed Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and reneated to India Office. 1 3^ Telegram R., No. 814 B., dated (and received) the 13th April 1915. From— The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox K C I E C S I Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Busrah, ’ • • • -, . .i., To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Denart- ment, Simla. ^ My telegram No. 689. Yali’s emissary referred to was arrested by Turks on his way back to Yali. This indicates that Turks no longer hope for assist ance (of) Yali who is likely to be conveniently annoyed at their action. Addressed Foreign ; repeated to Minister. 3jr Telegram R., No. 825 B., dated (and received) the 13th April 1915. From—The Hon’blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E, C.S.I. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Shiraz, April 12th :— “Your telegram No. 792 B. “ As you know, definite proofs are difficult to produce in such cases. I will try to formulate situation briefly. “ I know as a fact all Swedish officers who have been and who are at present in Fars are pro-German and that they have openly expounded their views accordingly to Persians and Europeans. Captain Killandar, for instance, told me himself that he regarded all Beuter telegrams news as false and all German news as absolutely accurate and that he had so informed his Persian officers and others. Major Pravitz has recently given out that England is blockaded, Amir of Afghanistan assassinated, and many other absurd rumours all calculated to do us injury. And I could quote many similar instances. “ With regard to Captain Oertengren I have received information from four different sources regarding his anti-British propaganda at Kazerun. I have seen letter written by financial agent there to Acting Controller, Shiraz, an Armenian, giving detailed account of Oertengren’s interview with Nasred Diva. This letter which was written by Persian subordinate to his chief entirely corroborates information received from our telegraph signaller and from Stas. I also tackled Governor, Kazerun, who was present at interview in question and who is now on visit to Shiraz, on the subject a few days ago and he admitted substantial accuracy of accusations. “ There is also suspicious affair of arms and ammunition referred to in Bushire telegram 90 C., which has not yet been explained as far as I know. “ Then whole Persian gendarmerie officers are rabidly pro-German and anti-British. They openly associate with YFassmuss and have committed them selves in many other ways. I have ample proof of this and it cannot be denied even by Swedes themselves.“ So eyen if we give Swedish officers credit for wishing to restrain their Persian officers we must at the same time admit that they are incapable of doing so. Major Pravitz in conversation with me this morning told me some eight hundred men of Pars regiment of gendarmerie are of Turkish origin, and that if there were rising in South or if Turks advanced beyond Ahwaz nothing f could prevent them from rising also. “ If then we supppose Swedes are not purposely conducing to campaign against us in German interests, actual consequences of their pro*German attitude are same as far as we are concerned as if they were doing so; and gendarmerie under these officers constitutes a very serious menace to our interests in Southern Persia and to neutrality of country in general. “ Addressed Cox; repeated to Tehran.” Ends. Addressed Government of India; repeated to India Office. 1,1— -! I 11,1, - Telegram R., No. 832 B., dated the 13th (received 14th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colokel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- meut, Simla. Following from Shiraz, 81, April 13th :— Begins. Pravitz informed me yesterday that a force of about 200 gendarmes is about to start for Kazerun to relieve troops there. I have now- learnt this is false and that expedition is being sent to attack present Chief of Kamarij and to replace him by another person. Present ruler has always been friendly to gendarmerie, but is not on good terms with Khans of Daliki and Borasjun and object of expedition is to remove sole obstacle combined rising of all Khans from Kazerun to Bushire when right moment arrives and also to give Khans support and encouragement which will be afforded by arrival of fresh gendarmerie force. But whatever real object expedition may he its despatch at this moment will produce bad impression and wdll revive unrest on road. I venture to suggest on these grounds Your Excellency should -protest to Persian Govern ment against despatch of expedition which is quite uncalled for. Column will be starting immediately and protest should be made to-day if possible. Addressed Tehran; repeated Basrah, Bushire. Ends. 3/- Telegram P., No. 829 B., dated (and received) the 14th April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. I have received the following from His Majesty’s Representative at Tehran, No. 138, dated 12th April: — “ Please refer to your telegram, No. 800 B. “ I was awaiting an expression of opinion from the Indian Government. Under present circumstances the Persian Government would not agree to take step suggested, but any attempt to proceed in direction of Afghanistan on the part of Wassmuss or others could probably be stopped, as we have more control (over) the local authorities at Khurasan, Sistan and Kerman than over those | of the western and centre provinces. To me German propaganda seems to be losing ground, and I think that it is more likely if left alone to die a natural death than if public opinion is excited by bringing constant pressure to bear upon Government.”17 I dg'. Telegram R., No. 857 B., dated the 15th (received 16th) April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lihitenjst-Coloskl Sir Percy Pnv ir n t u „ r , , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah ’ ^ C.S.I., T0_The meTsLt 4116 G0VerD “ ent of foreign aod Political Depart- following from Tehran :— . , H , is Ma j est y’ 8 Consul, Kermanshah, left for Hamadan vesterdav mth British colony on account of occupation of Kasr-i-Shirin bv^ Turkish Troops, finds. ■ * Telegram R., dated (and received) the 15th April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox K C I E Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ’ •• • -, To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political ment, Simla. C.S.I., Depart- Following from Shiraz, No. 85, dated 15th April Begins. “ My telegram, 81. I called on Governor-General this morn ing and protested against the despatch of expedition. Governor-General pro fessed entire ignorance of any intention to send expedition, or of its object. “I have best reasons for believing this to be untrue, and that he is perfectly well acquainted with whole circumstances of the case. “ On enquiring from Pravitz whence funds for expedition would be forth coming, he replied that they would be despatched from Tehran. In view of fact that gendarmes have not been paid for several months, it seems prepos terous to expend money on expensive and uncalled for movement of troops, instead of paying men’s salaries. r 5 “I regard whole matter as most suspicious and as undoubtedly coverino* some hidden design. ° “ I venture to think the time is approaching when His Majesty’s Govern ment must give definite ultimatum to Persian Government, regarding the situation in Pars. As already stated, I believe immediate recall of present Governor-General, and of Swedes, would oe best means to check materialising- plans of pro-German party. New Governor-General, with Merill, should start as soon as possible, and we should have to find funds to carry on gendar merie, until matters straighten out again. Addressed to Tehran; repeated to Basrah, B^shire.’ , finds. Telegram R, No. H62 B., dated the 15th (received 16th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To —The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Pollowing from Bushire, No. 139 C., dated 15th April:— Begins. “ Shiraz telegram, 81. Expedition of gendarme. “ Venture (to) support Consul’s representations. Present Khan of Kamarij is believed well disposed towards us and his removal would be gain to hostile Khans ; moreover, movements of this sort will revive idea that gendarme are moving in a bodv to attack Hyder Khan or Bushire Khans and with approval (of) Tehran. “Have just been informed by Tfinance Department, Bushire, that they have no more money to pay for gendarme fodder and provisions from Bushire to Kazerun which was met from revenue (of) Dashti and Dashtistan,This might be used as an argument against an expensive movement of gendarmerie. Financial Department state that chest is now empty and will remain so till next autumn, and there will not be even money with which to pay Governor’s salary next month. “ Addressed Tehran ; repeated Shiraz and Basrah.” Ends. Telegram R., No. 872 B., dated the 16th (received 17th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C S.L, Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Following from Shiraz, 16th April:— “ I yesterday visited Kawam who has recently returned from Lar and had long conversation with him. He assured me that he entirely disapproved of pro-German agitation and would do his utmost to discourage it. He said he fully realised what he himself and Fersia generally owe Great Britain support and friendship and that interruptions (of) friendly relations with us must be disastrous to Persia. “ Kawam of course realizes that disturbance in Southern Persia must involve heavy losses and possibly ruin to himself, and for this reason, if for no other, I believe his assurances to be sincere. “ I have also received letter from Soulet containing satisfactory assurances (of) neutrality and friendship. “ Addressed Tehran; repeated to Basrah, Bushire. ” Telegram R., No. 871 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Likutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegram, No. 660 B. jEiich Zug mayer accompanied by Captain Greisinger were reported by Consul-General, Ispahan, 5th April, to be on their way to Ispahan, which they should have reached by now. Bahrein informs me that Zugmayer is an officer of Bavarian .Reserve, and a Professor of Natural History, who spent some four months in British Mekran four years ago, where he lived some time with Dawkes, and travelled a good deal in Kej, with escort of Mekran Levy Corps. He was well informed about the country, and well fitted to cause trouble in Persian Mekran, which is not improbably his objective. Addressed Foreign; repeated Tehran, Bushire, Ispahan, Shiraz and Kerman. Telegram R., No. 880 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April 1915. From—The Bon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Tehran, 17th April:— “Your telegram, 85. Minister of the Interior stated that he had no knowledge of proposed expedition against Kamarij and promised to send tele graphic instructions (to) stop it. “Repeated Basrah and Bushire,”19 Telegram R., No. 882 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E CSI Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, * • • • ., . . ., To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- ment, Simla. ^ following from Bushire, 143 :— Begins. “ I have an intercepted letter from Wassmuss to Rais Ali, dated 3rd April, encouraging latter in ideas of revenge against the English and Ryder Khan. If Wassmuss remains ignorant of seizure of letter, I might get hold of some more. Meanwhile I think you are best judge of what use should he made of it and of any other similar letters that may come into our hands. An anti-English pamphlet formed enclosure to letter. ‘Copies of this had been already distributed in Bushire and it is said to be work (of) (Said ?) Hassan who, I am informed, is Wassmuss’s right hand in these intrigues. “Addressed Shiraz ; repeated to Basrah.” Ends. Addressed Tehran ; repeated to Government of India, India Office. 4-6' Telegram R., No. 883 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April J915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E, C.S.I. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Reference Bushire telegram, No. 143, 17th April. My personal view is that we should make the utmost use of material of this kind and that this letter should be photographed and posted in Bushire and neighbourhood, and should become subject of renewed protest to Persian Government on part of the two legations. Addressed Minister; repeated to Foreign and Secretary of State, Bushire, Shiraz. Telegram R., No. 888 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April 1915. From—The HojPble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Following from Bushire, 142 :— Begins. “ Persistent reports are being received from Behbeha regarding intentions (of) Bakhtiari Khans to seize opportunity to invade Lirawe. “ Khan, our friend, telegraphed (to) Minister of the Interior weeks ago asking to be relieved of anxiety by repetition (of) orders of 12th October from previous Cabinet to the Bakhtiaris. “Only reply he received was instruction (to) release his brother from detention and restore to him his inheritance on all fours (with) friend (ship) (of) Khans. Understand matters are being purposely misrepresented to Minister and Behbeha'Deputy in Mediiiss in order (to) give Bakhtiaris opening for (aggression ?). “ Your Excellency is aware from correspondence in September-October 1914, brother referred (to), who was disinherited by late Khan his father for constant sedition, has only been detained in order to prevent disorders in district. “ Internal trouble there now would be fatal to our interests and would moreover jeopardize collection (of) revenue due (to) Bank.20 «it W ould (be) helpful to me if Your Excellency could urge Minister of the Interior to keep to policy of his predecessors and warning Governor (ol) Behbeha and Jang similarly, and inform me when this has been done. According to rumour Jang has received instructions in this sense, but Samsam- us-Sultaneh had secretly urged former to gain a footing in district. “ Addressed Tehran ; repeated Basrah.” Jftnds. Telegram R., No. 889 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April 1915. From—The Hon’blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sib Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, rp 0 The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- men, Simla. My telegram, 792 B., 11th April. Bushire telegram, 142 C., 17th April. I trust that pressure will not be relaxed and that renewed representations will be made both to Khans in Tehran personally and to Persian Government to discourage any sort of interference with or annoyance of Hyder Khan. I will make similar representations here to confidential agent Sardars Jang and Bahadur, who has just arrived at Mohammerah (with ?) letters for Sheikh of Mohammerah and for me. ±mds. Addressed Tehran; repeated Government of India, Bushire. Telegram R , No. 890 B., dated the 17th (received l»th) April 1915. From— The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Eollowing from Shiraz, 86, 17th April:— Begins. “My telegram, 86. Kawam has sent me message through confidential agent to the effect that he considers situation at Shiraz very critical. Some 40 or 50 meetings are held nightly at which pro-German agents endeavour (to) excite populace feeling against British. Kawam says he will do his best (to) avert trouble, but in the event of any populace outbreak be guarantees to protect Consulate with his own men. He has warned me (that) no reliance can be placed in gendarmerie who are openly hostile. “ Kawam himself is in difficult position, as he cannot openly oppose Governor-General with whom he has always been on good terms, but he admits that Governor-General is to blame for not checking agitation and that most of dangerous clique is composed chiefly of Governor-General’s intimates. “ If Governor-General were removed and Kawam appointed acting tempo rarily as Governor-General, he would then be in a position to take necessary steps to keep town quiet. “ Addressed Tehran ; repeated Basrah, Bushire.” Ends. Telegram R., No. 891 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegram, 880 B. Kamarij expedition.-V 21 Poliowing from Shiraz, 88 :— Begins. “Your telegram, 52. Pxpedition started this morning 17th April. It is very desirable (that) it should stop. Please (?) order return which can easily be done if telegraphic orders are despatched at once. “ Addressed Tehran; repeated Basrah, Bushire. ” Ends, Addressed Government of India; repeated India Office. Ul sforSiti k ^ ttoi ys le fil itlreal If Telegram R., No. 893 B., dated the 18th (received 19th) April 1915. From—The Hon'bjl.b Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox K.C J.E. C S.l Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, * '* * To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please (see ?) my telegrams, No. 890 and 891 B. So long as vigorous pressure was being applied in Tehran, there was a palpable lull in activity of the hostile element in Ears. That pressure having been apparently relaxed during past fortnight, owing probably to Townley’s pending departure, the said element have become bolder again and it is clear from recent Shiraz telegrams that possibility of serious developments has by no means disappeared. I feel sure that both Kawam and Soulet personally would be most unwilling to become involved in any anti-British movement, but they would be unable to go against the tide in the event of a semi-religious and quasi national rising being engineered against us. I am confident, however, that Central Government can, if they wish, prevent situation passing out of control, and that if there is no relaxation of pressure on the part of two legations they will do the necessary. On the other hand in absence of such pressure and of strong and bond fide measures on the part of Persian Government, I do not consider danger of serious trouble is past. Steps needed are the recall of Governor-General, recall of punitive expedi tion against Kamarij, withdrawal of Swedish officers, expression of disapproval and disavowal of proceedings of German agitators, and support to be given Government of Bushire in deportation of agitators at Bushire. I venture to think recent defeat of Turks here offers an opening to two legations for renewal of grave warning to Persian Government, and discovery of Wassmuss’s letter to Khan of Dilwara an opportunity for fresh remons trance to them. Addressed Minister; repeated Government of India, India Office. 'Si, ^ Telegram R., No. 90S B., dated the 19th (received 21st) April 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Pollowing from Shiraz, 18th April:— “My telegram, 88. Signaller, Kazerun, reports Khan (of) Kamarij has sent away women and children and is preparing to resist gendarmerie. It is said that some of Kashgai t ^ e e&gt;me — will assist him. There is in fact makings of serious disturbance which once begun will spread rapidly and may involve all Pars. “If Persian Government really wish to avert such consequences, they should seud urgent instructions for recall (of) expedition. “ Addressed Tehran ; repeated to Basrah, Bushire. ” Addressed Government of India; repeated to India Office. I2* $2. Telegram R., No. 909 B., dated the 20th (received 21st) April 1915. P'j.qjjj The Hon'blb Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- ment, Simla. following from Shiraz, 17th April. ~Rpnin&amp; “ Zugmayer has telegraphed from Sultanabad to the Com- rnnndant of the gendarmerie here, requesting him to transmit message to Wassmuss to the g effect that Zugmayer and Gnesmger were leaving for IsnahTn on 17th April, and expected to arrive there on 25th April, and asking that Wassmuss should communicate to them at Ispahan. “ They seem to take it for granted that Swedish officers are safe medium for transmission of their communications to one another. Addressed to Tehran; repeated to Basrah and Bushire. ” Ends. Addressed to Government of India; repeated to India Office. $5. Telegram R., No. 919 B., dated the 20th (received 21st) April 1915. p ronl The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. following from Shiraz, No. 92, dated 20th April: Hearns “The pestilential Wassmuss has written an encouraging letter to Mulla at* Bushire, and is doing his best to stir up Bushire, as well as Shiraz. He signs himself as Consul. “ He has also issued notice, in last number of local paper here, signed German Consul. “ I venture to suggest tliat protest should be made to Persian Government against Wassmuss styling himself German Consul, when he has not been accepted as such by the Persian Government. Addressed to Tehran. Ends. Addressed to Poreign j repeated to India Office. Telegram R., No. 924&lt; B., dated (and received) the 22nd April 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Pollowing from Shiraz, No. 93, dated 20th April:—• Begins. “ Please see Cox’s telegram, No. 893 B. “ I believe that both Kawam and Soulet could he relied upon not to oppose British interests, if present Governor-General were removed. Kawam hesi a es to oppose him, although he regards him as mainly responsible for presen unsatisfactory situation. “ Soulet’s position among his tribe has been much weakned by Governor- General’s intrigues against him. Latter’s removal^ would relieve him o constant source of anxiety and would tend to restore his prestige and mnuenc . “Pending any more decisive measures, telegrams from Minister of the Interior direct to Kawam and Soulet, instructing them to preserve neutrality and good order, would strengthen their hands and have good effect. “ Addressed Tehran; repeated Basrah, Bushire.” Ends. I. &amp; P. Dept. Prow.—769—27-4-15—42.'1 In continuation ol n^ r leit-er of th© ISfli April 1915, I am desired to forward a copy of the telegram of the 18th April 1915 received by the Consul-General for Persia at Calcutta, Simla, from the Persian Minister. The substance of this telegram and the text of the reply sent thereto by His Excellency the Viceroy were reported in our telegram of the 22nd April 1915. Telegram from the Persian Foreign Minister, Tehran, to the Persian Minister, Pome, No. 386, dated the 14th April 1915. Telegram from the Persian Minister, London, to the Persian Foreign Minister, Tehran, No. 29, dated the 16th April 1915. grams which have been intercepted. I am also to enclose a copy of the marginally noted tele- /A.■ 4 ; ril iPlo from the Persian Foreign Minister to tne Persian Consul-General at Simla. In continuation of No. 364. m accordance with your telegram His Excellency the Governor- General of India in view of his acquaintance vitl . ~F 'f*. •• i v&gt; c • r' i • v» ot , c.j-j-c.arb c ui Iuk ills O U!--, i -lG. .er. .• G.V1SGB '0 the Persian Government should not allow themselves to oe influenced by others. if the British uov erment is a v eil wisher of Persia and resl 1 v thinks tlis,! i*t is aovisaole for Persia fo remsin neutral, as the upsetting of that neutrality will have dangers for the British Government also, then they must a os tain from taking steps which are hound to destroy that neutrality and cause cala- niaties to befall Persia. But, on the contrary, it is noticed that the steps that are being taken by them are opposed to this object. For instance they are closing the Telegraph Offices in Arabistan resulting in great loss daily to the (Persian) G vernment, and are arresting German officials notwithstanding the fact that these measures, as they must be observing themselves, are disturbing the minds of the people and making them favourable to the Ottomans and the Germans. Recently five hundred men were brought to Bushire and three hundfed men to a place five farsakhs from that place. The boatmen declined to land them and the Governor of the ports in spite of the instance of the officer in charge of the (British)Consulate- General took no action to avoid a public disturbance The (British) Legation write to say that these troops have been sent to relieve the former troops.4 But the Persian Government really object to the stay of foreign troops in Persian territory and earnestly demand their removal. Should the British Government wish to save Persia from the fire should also remove their troops in garrison. Thev should also ask the Russians to vacate Persia, and Idave her to her own resources. Then the Persian Government will organize an army of sufficient strength under Persian officers and safeguard, their neutrality. If there is no other object in view, the morat orium should be accepted and the Persian Government assisted in this way the chief advantage of which will accrue to the British Government. But if difficulties should continue to be created as before, I am sorry to say that power will go out of the hands of the (Persian) Government and various disturbances and disorders (lit. fights) will occur in Persia, in consequence of which peace will depart from British possessions also for which no responsibility will on the Persian Government. Please discuss the matter in this strain and request them to recall them their troops and not to land any more so that the Persian Government may get an opportunity to communicate with the Ottomans, ask them to remove their troops and thus protect Persia from dangers* of war, they should not land a single soldier and (Sd) Muavin (Attache) Foreign Ministry.a force collected and violated our territory at Kazvin. Sainsarn-ul-Huiralik --- — evacuated that town. The Turks cut the telegraph wire and killed Hamid Khan, the brother of the Chief of Bajldn and 7 other persons. The Turkish Ambassador telegraphed to the Turkish General at Qasr that he did no wish communications to be interrupted; in spite of this my telegram to Your Excellency has been delayed for three days. At length communication has been restored. News has just arrived that that Turkish force has violated our territory at Sar-i-Pul and has cut the telegraph line there also. Point out a.t once to the Porte the-dangers, which arise for Persia from this violation, that these violations are in our territory, that the Russians are in Hamdan and in other districts and that great loss is occasioned to Persia thereby. Our hands are forced in this manner and the cause of Islam suffers. Demand the immediate recall of Turkish troops from the nrovince of Kirmanshahan and ask that they be I -i IffFrom The Persian Minister, London. To The Foreign Minister, Teheran. No, 29, dated 16-4-15, I gather from the situation that the Britisi: see that the behaviour of the Russians is such, that if it is not stopped, it will be harmful and dangerous to the success of the Allies. in the question of the attack on the Dardanhelles, the Russians made shores of the it clear that Constantinople and the Adriatic the inhabitants of which are Slavs must, when occupied, be handed over to Russia. For this reason Italy, Bulgaria and Greece have become afraid of the Allies; even Roumania, whom the Allies looked on as a partisan and whom they thought engaged in preparations for war havecried out at the idea of Russian autrotratic rule in these parts. Owing, to these considerations, whilst preserving perfect harmony, they are doing their best to get Russia to change her policy. If they succeed, it will probably also affect Persia. In any case it is an advantage for our discussions. I expect a Russian Ambassador, ,, who is an easy-going man and comes with instructions to be yielding. Well informed, people think that in a month it wall be known to some extent what shape the war will assume and what some of the neutral powers will do. Both sides are confident th*t they will, with their forces and wplth, be able to fight to the end. The neutral countries generally hold the view, that in spite of all sorts of promiser which both sides hold out to attract them to their side, it is better to play a waiting game.. _ ;v », , w u *m *! • ! ' ] j S U IT0(, p I ' Hf In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote f I 1 *'* r&gt; No. | and address The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign! Office, London. 1 1 ^ i r O The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for f and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, isLc' , iqi 5 . Reference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreign Office from * ^ Description of I ncto sure. Name and Date. Subject.1 Copy* (62728) I i&lt;?7 BRITISH CONSULATE FOR KER^'IANSHAH, HALADAK, April 24th, 1915. sir:- I have the honour to report that affaire at Kerrnanshah have been gradually becoming critical. The Lohammadan clergy did their best to prevent any propaganda by religious emissaries in the name of religion against Great Britain and Russia; but the authorities did nothing to prevent this being done by laymen. , r.dchunemann German Consul for Iraq (Bultanabad) has been for some months in Kermanshah and has engaged more than a hundred men as guards, many of them being notorious criminals. The Governor-General was in the districts on tour dealing with tribal matters, and I could not get into touch with him. A force of Turks invaded Persia and occupied the border town of Kasr-i-Shirin. Apparently the Governor- General had orders not to resist them and they are said to be acting contrary to the orders of the Turkish Govern ment. His Majesty’s Legation instructed me that if the situation ware critical and the Governor-General could not guarantee my safety 1 had better leave for Hamad an • 1 did not at first consider it necessary to leave, but on the 13th my Russian colleague left and that night shots were exchanged between a guard of gendarmes at the house of the manager of the Imperial Bank of Persia amd a party of armed men. After His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State.After this and as the Persian cossucks under a Russian officer were leaving, I sent fox* the agent of the Persian foreign office and told hini tlxat 1 would leave and that he was in charge of everything left in tne Consulate. 1 only brought away the more confidential Archives and some necessaries there being a difficulty in detaining transport. The party consisted of the British, Russian and Belgian Colonies, eleven persons, and an Afghan exile who had been warned that tne Turks suspected him of supplying information. At the time of leaving six out of seven sowars of bA&amp;bgi *® Hors* 'mil n e cort to the Consulate deserted, and ’went to the Turkish Consulate, and {some fourteen Persian CossacKh v/ent to the Germans. we left Kerrnanehan on tne afternoon of the 14th and arrived at Hamadan on tne 2utn. i nave etc, (Signed) w. c Douall.4 * [Tliis D ocument is ehe Progeny ai flis B ritanalc Majesty's Government, ahould be returned to the F oreign Office when «in na 1,-^ Manager Hussian Bank at Ispahan who is.also Russian Vice Consul at Kumisheh was assassinated about midnight yesterday close to German Consulate by men who afterwards disappeared into that Consulate. Belgian Financial Agent who was with Manager was Russian Vice Consul are convinced assassins belong to band of ruffians recruited by German Consul. They con sider position of Hussian and British communities to be somewhat dangerous as Governor General in spite of strictest orders from Teheran professes himself unable to take requisite measures! while gendarmerie is entirely on the side of Germans. I shall of course support Hussian Minister by all means in my power to obtain satisfaction but if Persian Government is not strong enough to afford it I feel it will be imperative for us to show we are ready to give them material support by landing troops at Enzeli.- Addressed to Foreign Office, repeated to Petrograd, Simla and Sir P. Cox. required for official use.] E2LITICM!, Decypher, Mr. Marling, (Teheran) May 19th, 1915, slightly wounded VWXXU YVCXkJ VV _L U1J. J.VJ.CU. 1 Cl £5 O VVO-D His Majesty’s Consul General and M lvM ,V I $h-l J /!r [This Pocmaent is the Property ot Hla Britannic Majesty’s Bovemmenl and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with anl esa required for official use!] ~ ' ' ^ hL 1 MJtjblAt POLITICAL. (61498/15). T,\ Cypher Telegram to Sir G. Buchanan (petrograd) Foreign Oi!ice. May 18th c 191o. ( BrlOmpriu No. 929. Secret. Mr. Marline’s telegrams Nos. 185 and 186 (oi 16th. May. Situation in Persia). X share.entirely view of Mr. Marling and his Mus- sian colleague that despatch of t v,r o div is ions oi -- '•u s s i an troops would go so far beyond the needs of the situa tion as to create fresh dangers * optli tiie.ii numboi s and their mission would re-act unfavourzbly on Persian opinion. ' On the other hand if Russian Government can keep two or‘three thousand men in readiness at Baku i-or short time, it might serve useful purpose. I am quite ready to give all possible financial support to present Persian Cabinet on receipt of Pi ime Minister’s statement: and I am also prepared as non- si-eur Sa&amp;onov suggests to pla.ee His Laiesty's sinister in a position to counteract German activity by judicious outlay, if Russian Government concur. You should inform Russian Minister for-.Foreign Ai- fairs accordingly* f \ Re '0 eated to Ivir. Mar 1 1 ng , no. 9l9 h sdtYI J1S ' -r \[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty 8 s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done wi th unless required for official use.] a O 42 ; 9 Lb PERSIA. POLITICAL Decypher, Mr, Marling, (Teheran} May 16th,1915 D, 6 pjno K. May 17th ? il aom. No, 185, % i- My telegram No, 183, During the last week there has heen a very marKed improvement in the situati’an and Russian Minister and I think that, provided we can give reasonable support to the Government they will succeed in maintaining their neutrality and independence ? in spite of Turco German activities. We saw Prime Minister on May 13th and said tnau we wished to discuss the situation with him and especi ally the best manner of co-operation, we knew that the Persian Government required money but it would be useless for Persian Government at this moment to expect that the two Governments would discuss large measures of financial reo-ganization and we could not hold out hopes of anything more than moderate advances from time to time to tide over period of war- But we must have some thing definite to submit to our Governments and we shoul like to have as a guide a statement in writing showing what would be required a month. His Highness said he quite understood; he had al Leady done by his methods enough to prove dost he ^Wished to work with us. He new hoped Miau a smc.li ^coaid be 4 .ouiid which was required for urgenb expanses and I said wiuh Russian Minister 1 s concurrence fhal Imperial hank of Persia was willing fo find sinly(sic) tomans desired. His Highness continued that he wished to work on those lines and that he should be allowed to work his own way and if we were satisfied with results we should continue to give support, a system in fact of payment by results so to speak. His, High- Highness seems to be very confident of being able to master situation and he has some hope of inducing Mejlis to grant him full powers or possibly to adjourn for a long holiday. It will not I gear, be possible to re-establish general control over Persian finances.that was done away with when law of Jou^was repealed; at all events it is pretty certain that new finance law now being discussed by the Mejlis will not provide for any real safeguard. But I think that we can keep a control over expenditure 6 f any,advances which the two Govern ments may agree to make and ensure that they are ap plied to the object we have in view viz. the mainten ance of Persian neutrality. Persian Government have not yet furnished statement mentioned in paragraph 2 of above. Address to Foreign Office, sent to India.Petro- grad and Basra.1 : [Thia Document is toe Property of Hia Britoanlc Majesty’s Government, and should be retnrned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required (or official use.] r 3 42 PERSIA Decypher of telegram from Mr (dr 9ro 0 pmHc May 16th 1915, No-186r (K)r ivi POLIT ICAL o iarling,(Tehran)r m- 12 noon May 1.7th) * Secret - Russian Minister has communicated to me and French Minister for joint discussion secret telegram from his Government informing him of a proposal emanating from Russian Military authorities for the despatch of two divisions of troops to Persia with the object of seizing persons of enemy missions in Tehran, troops retiring after a short stay- rt.FA. Russian (0 ) however expressed himself averse to so heroic a measure and asked whether German activity here, which depends in large measure on lavish expenditure could not be counteracted by employing the similar means- We are unanimously agreed that situamion does not de mand despatch of so great a. force- In first place it would probably fail in its object, as the quarry would fly and in second Russian Minister and I xeel convinced that a much smaller demonstration of military power would cause German adherence to fall away at -east in capital- French Minister thinks it might drive Germans to attempt desperate coup here but my Russian colleague ana I do not f 5 ^Ci?Hhink there is much to fear on that •' ocount Russian H i s \* Russian Minister and I Relieve that our test policy is that outlined in my immediately preceding tele gram provided that snail force is kept in readiness at Enseli (Russian Minister even suggests Baku) in :ase occasion arises wnH-Ch renders their preseiice nei e necess* ary. Knowledge that they are h ndy would do a great, deal to steady hot-headed pro-Gernan (? fanatics) r-nd would lend great strength to deternine Government. An import ant and undeniable success in Europe or such an event as Italy Joining us would greatly modify situation mere. Repeated to Petrograd.-V In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. 59094/15. i A ■** and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. I o i i Foreign Office May 16th, 1915. ^mediate. Sir; - With reference to my letter of the 11th instant regarding the situation in Persia^I am directed by Secre tary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith^ to be laid before the Marquess of Crewe, a copy of a telegram ^ f rom His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran suggesting that the despatch of Russian troops to Enzeli and Resht, and the simultaneous reinforcement of the British detachment at Bushire would serve to strengthen the present Ministry and furnish a warning to the pro-German elements in Persia Sir E. Grey is consulting the Russian Government as to Mr. Marling’s proposal and would meanwhile be glad to receive Lord Crewe’s observations on the suggested rein-PERSIA Mr. Marling to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received May 12, 5’25 p.m.) Tehran. (No. 184.) (May 12, 1915, 10-45 a.m.) YOUR telegram No. 112 of 10th May. I do not consider that we are in any personal danger, but, considering what German methods are, there is always possibility of an attempt at violence. There was some little danger a week or so ago owing to intense nervousness in the town, but things are now calmer. Our object in requesting despatch of troops to Enzeli and Resht is as follows : We have succeeded in bringing into office Minister who, with our support, is probably capable of dealing with the situation, that is to say, of maintaining Persian neutrality and frustrating German and Turkish efforts to push her into abandoning it, but Ministry has no strength of its own and we have to find it for them. It must be remembered that, except for arrest of German consul, we have taken no steps in reply to German activities all over the country, and appearance of Russian troops js intended to show that our patience has its limits, that we have means to support Ministry who will act firmly in interests of neutrality, and they can count upon our support. Troops need not come to Tehran; 2,000 or 3,000 should he landed at Enzeli, and Kazvin could be slightly reinforced thence. I am convinced that appearance of troops will not provoke Persian Government to abandon its neutrality. No Persian wishes that event, but Persia might be jockeyed into it unless we show unmistakably that we are in earnest. Simultaneous reinforcements of our detachment at Bushire advocated by Major Trevor would contribute to produce that good effect.Cypher telegram to Sir G„ Buchanan (Petrograd) Foreign Office, May 14th, 1915. 11 p, m . No. 899. Mr. Marling's telegram No. 184 (of 12th May. Troops for Persia). Ufrilo I realize difficulty of dispatching any con- siderahle hussian force to Persia at present time, I should he glad to receive views of Kussian Minister for Foreign Affairs on proposal to give backing to present Persian Cabinet and to furnish warning to Germans by dispatching 2 or 3,000 troops to Enzeli. I am meanwhile consulting India Office regarding Pushire. &lt;! I ' i -Sir, i0 j With reference to previous correspondence relating to the situation in Persia, I am di rected by the S.of S. for I. to enclose, to be laid before the S.of S. for F.A., copy of a telegram from the G.of I. dis cussing the various recom mendations submitted by Sir P. Cox in his telegrams Nos.lOSIB 1082-B, and 1083-B, of the 10th and 11th May 1915, copies of which have already been com municated to you. The Marquess of Crewe con curs generally in the views expressed by the G.of I. on the subject of Pars and the Bushire hinterland. With regard to the Bakhtiaris, it is very desirable, in His Lordship’s opinion, that Sir P. Cox should make no promises the fulfilment of which may be held to be inconsistent with the rights of the Russian Govern ment in the Russian sphere; and, speaking generally, it seems preferable to reward the Khans by cash payments in the present rather than by promises of governorships or other poli ticale tical privileges in the future^ Lord Crewe further doubts the advisability of encouraging the Bakhtiaria in projects for obtaining access to the Persian Gulf littoral. Subject to these reimrks His Lordship sees no objection to Sir P. Cox being authorised to negotiate on the lines proposed in the last para- graph of the G.of I r s telegram. * ’• ff.aitojess. r r-V r** mmmm XIX 2n r Viceroy, 15th May 1915. (Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Tehran and, Cox.) Foreign Secret. Reference to Cox’s cyphers 1081 B, 1082 B, aid 1083 B, of 10th May. Persian situation. Until a rupture actually occurs our policy should be to endeavour jby friendly representations to induce Khans to prevent isolated attacks on our officers and consulates and generally to protect our interests. This attitude- can be encouraged by disbursement of secret service money which we have already authorised. It unfortunately war with Persia should break out my view is that we should leave bars ana Bushire Hinterland severely alone, and merely if we have troops available hold Bushire peninsula itself. It seems useless to commit ourselves either to Kawam or Soulet in Pars, or to entangle ourselves in a mesh of inter-tribal intrigue in the Bushire Hinterland. Should occasion arise, Soulet and Kawam might be given a liberal sum for services rendered in the event of their extricating our Consul and his Staff from Shiraz and be promised generally rewards and recognition proportionately to their servi ces hereafter. But suc h promise should only be made in the event of Peak of war. ()n war we shall want to deal with de facto rulers, and not merely with chiefs with whom we have committed ourselves. As regards Haidar Khan, it is out of the question to defend Bander Port T^against attack, if it is seriously threatened we should offer to 1 826 remove him and his family to an asylum in India or Basra for time being. As regards Mohammerah and the Bakhtiaris, though there seems little hope of the hitter cordially co-operating with us, I support proposals put forward in Cox ’s telegram. 1(&gt;S2 B. and recommend that he be authorised to negotiate on these lines as to steps to be taken in event of outbreak of war but that he should be careful not to commit us too deeply should situation improve and war be avoided.[this Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should be retunxed to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use,] j TJ' 1 Decypher r Lir. I .arlinp (Teheran) Dr 10*4:5 a*it* May 12th 191b r 0.1* b r&gt; , ' J a p riJ. r HOr 134 r Your tele; ran hOr 112r . I do not consider that we are in any personal danger, but considering what German methods are tnere is always possibility ox an atterapt at violence r There was some little danger a week or so ago owing to intense nervousness in the Town, ouu uniago are nO' J calmer r Our object in requesting despateu ox troops to Dnzeli and Me slit is as follows: we have succeeded in bringing into office minister who with our support is probably capable of dealing with the situation, that is to say of maintaining Persian neuoraliu * ana frustrating German and Turkish efforts to push her into abandoning it. But Mi retry has no soreng on of its own and we have to find it for them. It nuso be remembered that except for arrest of German Consul we have taken no steps in reply to German activities all over the country rad appearance of Kussian troops is intended to show that our patience has its Hants, that have means to support Ministry who will act firmly in interests of neutral it,/ and. tney c--^ couuo upon our support. Troops-V, . j . Troops need not come to Teheranr Two or three thousand ot r:&amp; landed at Enzeli and Kasvin could he slightly reinforced thence r I ar# convinced that appearance of troops will not provoke Persian Government to abandon its neu trality, No Persian wishes that event, but Persia might be jockeyed into it unless we show unmistakably that we are in earnestv Simultaneous reinforcements of our detachment at Bushire advocated by Major Trevor would contribute to produce that good effect.I From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department 2bth May J915. Foreign Secret. Yonr telegram of 15th May. Persian situation I oil owing instructions sent to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, 21st May •- ’ r ;;His Majesty’S (lovernment approve generally view of Government of 15 t p a M 1 ^ ar( ing ' ai ’ S and liusllire hinterland (see Viceroy’s telegram of “ As regards Bakhtiari, rewards by cash payments now are preferable to pi onuses of governorships or other political privileges in the future and there are weighty objections to encouraging Bakhtiari Khans in projects for obtaining access to Persian Gulf littoral. J “ ^ ather fror p y° ur telegram of 17th May that you hold similar view i ou may, therefore, authorise Sir P. Cox, if and when you think situation requires it to negotiate on lines proposed in last paragraph of \ iceroy s telegram of loth Ma y^suliject to the above limitations.” ..(C°h) 0 From Sir Percy Cox, Basra, 22nd May 1915. (Addressed Foreign, repeated Minister, Secretary of State for India.) (M.) T. 14. In the event of outbreak of war with Persia exclusion of Arabistan from sphere of disturbance will be matter of much importance. Present position is that Bawi and Beni Puruf and Ilaweiyeh tribes have submitted and only Ohaab remain “ out ” ; it is hoped that they also will submit within a few days. On outbreak of war I am of opinion we should at once offer Sheikhs of these tribes substantial bribes to induce them to stand m with us and Sheikli of IVlohammerah. It we did this and ^ave them undi itaking at the same time that in future we will take a benevolent interest in their welfare and fair treatment as well as in that of the Sheikh of Mohammerah, \ am of opinion we should then have them with us and that Arabistan would remain undisturbed if not actually attacked by Bakhtiari or other elements hostile to us. As regards Bakhtiari I am about to interview Khans and will report the result as soon as possible. In the event of war, I am also of opinion we should also take steps to secure neutrality of Kuhgelu tribe. From Sir Percy Cox, 22nd May 1915. (Addressed Foreign, repeated to India Office, Minister and Bushire.) (M.) T. 13. Please see series of telegrams beginning with my No. 1081, and comments of the^ Government of India and His Majesty’s Minister at lehran thereupon, ihey are doubtless in a position to appraise situation from a longer and more detached standpoint than 1 can, but 1 respectfully submit following further observations. Last autumn when we were expecting war with Turkey, and when military authorities in India expressed opinion that our resources were fully occupied and that troops could not be spared for Persian Gulf, we did not hesitate to discount facts by making reassuring announcements to Arab potentates of the Gulf, and by offering inducements to Koweit, Mohammerah, and Basra notables in order to make sure of their co-operation or benevolent neutrality. Position seems to me to be much the same now in case of Persia. Primd facie we have no troops to spare where with to support our friends or protect our interests. I submit, therefore, that natural alternative is to offer practical inducements to elements which are now friendly in order to ensure their benevolent neutrality, and if possible obtain their co-operation, and thus discount hostility of doubtful elements. Disbursement of periodical secret service doles and other alter native propositions by Government of India will not, I fear, be either practicable or sufficient for the purpose. Our friends can look after themselves and prevent spread of hostilities provided they receive sufficient inducement to repay them for risk and odium entailed. If we take no action on lines suggested, we must face possibility of these friendly elements leaving us, and consequently create much more serious situation, necessitating military dispositions on a proportionately larger scale than those contemplated by Government of India. : ii \ i ——: ICo|h From Viceroy, 20th May 1915 (AMressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Teheran and Basra.) Foreign Secret. Reference to my teleeram nf i mi vf n situation. Please see Cox’s telegram 1084 ! „f ? 2 th Mo t ' / “ •' f rSmn proved position at Teheran I thinV fPof • lVa ^'. ^ 11 view lni ~ would 1)6 premature for the present wlth iMekran Chiefs ourselves except in case of absolute necessiti to 86 ’ ^ d ° DOt Wai \ t f to P led ^ e or Sirdar Saiyid Khan In event of mmn ^ 1 persons as ^ ]r I,ai ' kat Chiefs of Mekran know generallv that thr p we . sll0uld let the peace and order will be duly rewarded hm W ° '’i' 111 * US 111 inainta i nnl g As regards Cox s telegram, No 1085 B of \/To^ \ 7 r,r r o u o i has shown himself quite'imreliable 1 mul it woui^“ft ourselves to him at present. If the Bakhtiaris stand in with us PushtTkuh ofTushtikuh^wilT n 8 ot nOU8ly t | ’V'f BakhtiaI ' is a 8' ain8t the attitude UpS^StOXS^ tS proposed ' *— *»— -» From Viceroy, 15th May 1915. (Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Tehran and Cox.) Foreign Seoret. Reference to Cox’s cyphers 1081 B, 1082 B, 1083 B, of 10th May. Persian situation. Until a rupture actually occurs our policy should be to endeavour by iieudly representations to induce Khans to prevent isolated attacks on our orficers and consulates and generally to protect our interests. This attitude can be encouraged by disbursement of secret service money which we have already authorised. If unfortunately war with Persia should break out my view is that we should leave bars and Bushire Hinterland severely alone, and merely if we have troops available.hold Bushire peninsula itself. It seems useless to commit ourselves either to Kawam or Soulet in Fars, or to entangle ourselves m a mesh of inter-tribal intrigue in the Bushire Hinterland. Should occasion anse, Soulet and Kawam might be given a liberal sum for services rendered in the event of their extricating our Consul and his Staff from Shiraz and be promised generally rewards and recognition proportionately to their services hereafter. But such promise should only be made in the. event of outbreak of war. On conclusion of war we shall want to deal with de facto riders, and not merely with chiefs with whom we have committed ourselves. As regards Haidar Khan, it is out of the question to defend Bandei l oit against attack. II it is seriously threatened we should offer to remove him and his family to an asylum in India or Basra for time being. As regards Mohammerah and the Bakhtiaris, though there seems Tittle hope of the latter cordially co-operating with us, I support proposals put forward in Cox’s telegram, 1082 B, and recommend that he be authorised to negotiate on these lines as to steps to be taken in event of outbreak of war, but that he should be careful not to commit us too deeply should the situation improve and war be avoided.} From, Sir P. Cox, Basra, 1 2th May 1915. {Addressed to Foreign / repeated to Tehran, Hash ire, and Secretary of State.) 1086b. Reference to Minister’s telegram No. 161, dated 8th U rgent May. / I submit action to be taken on outbreak of war in ersian ports requires l- First and foremost, urgent desideratum is that as many [? as possible] of His Majesty’s ships from the East Indies squadron should be made available. At Mohammera all we have to do is to make prize of “ Persepolis,” and take over Customs at Ahwaz and Mohammera. I think it would be politic, and have excellent effect, to allow Sheikh of Mohammera to put in guards, and allow Belgians to carry out as usual Treasury import duties we merely keeping account of receipts, and allowing the Sheikh of Mohammera to take them for the present. &lt;4. At Bushire we should at once land Naval brigade as in 1909 to seize and occupy Custom-house and place cordon round the town in concert with the military as was done in 1909. Duties can be handed over to the military in due course, but occupation of town and Custom-house can be most effectively carried out by landing parties from ships in the harbour, preceded by armed boats. S'. I am aware the number of troops available will depend on conditions prevailing in India, but 1 do not think' that in the event of war situation at Bushire would be satisfactory with less than two battalions and four guns, and presence of cruiser with large white crew such as H.M.S. “ Fox.’’ tu As regards Lingah and Bunder Abbas, immediately war broke out we should control the telegraph and postal communication with those ports, and 1 am of opinion that when they kuev Bushire was occupied Bunder Abbas and Lingah would give little trouble. 7* There is one remaining young German at Lingah, but he is not of sufficient importance to make it worth while causing a disturbance in order to capture him. Supposing that we cannot, to begin with, spare enough troops to garrison Lingah and Bunder Abbas, action to be taken depends on local developments, whence patrol by His Majesty’s ships prime necessity for maintenance of wireless telegraph and protection of: British lives and property. As regards Jask and Charbar, garrisons are possibly strengthened or being strengthened in view of Khalifa’s rising, and 1 doubt if anything further is necessary. From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 12th May 1915. ( Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Tehran, Ihishire, and Secretary of State.) Urgent No. 1085 B. Reference to Minister’s telegram No. Ibl to forthwith to resume former negotiations 01 &lt; | ' , . , j n retum f or l,i s Pushtikuh, and that we also offer him compact mu ei w Sheikh of standing out of the war and co-operating ^h^ aiK^.^bhei ^ Mohammera, we should guarantee to keep ■ - ' H .' J- | p 0ss iblv give him to manage his tribes in his own mMLrdip of him other inducements m the event i , . f ti ,. Incidentally we Luristan or grant of some territory on nWi ^ ^ ^ should assure him that we weie , wi|1 coinmnn i ( . a te further that he had nothing to feai from th, Dr ineiple to commencement in the above connection but request approval in pnmqm of negotiations at the proper moment.L From Sir F. Cox, Basra, \2th May 1915. {Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Tehran, I’mslure, and Secretary of Stale.) No. 1084b. Minister’s telegram No. 161, dated 8th May. Question of Mekran. In the event of declaration of war, I think we should issue suitable proclamation to Khans on the lines of our assurances to Arab population of Mesopotamia. In consideration of their suppressing fanaticism and maintaining order m them territories and security of telegraph lines, we might offer to make iVlir barkat, Governor of tract from Eastern boundary of Jask district to Minab. To Sirdar Saiyid Khan we might agree to make him Governor of Baluchistan, with suitable subsidy and subject to acceptance of British Agent To other less important but friendly Khans we might offer pecuniary rewards for co-operation in maintenance of security and order. Othei possible inducements may suggest themselves when we open negotiations. 1 From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 11th May 1915. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Tehran, Bushire, and Secretary of State.) No. 1083 B. Minister’s telegram 161, dated 8th May, to Foreign Office. 1 make following suggestions for Bushire hinterland : We have Khans of Kirawi, Hayat Baud, Rudhilleh, and probably Shabancara in our favour, while Ahmedi, Tangistan and Borasjun, and probably Daliki are hostile. Agent of X i z a m-u s-S u 1 tan eh, at Mohammera, has been doing his best to persuade Ikdiki r,o stand out, but Borasjun is likely to succeed in getting him to join. If Kawam and Soulet stand in with us Khans in the low country will be more or less cut off from telegraphic incitement from Tehran and thus effective combine for attack on Bushire will lie difficult, but in that case they maybe expected to turn their attention to our friend Haidar Khan who assisted us in arresting Germans. In order to keep members of friendly elements together and secure their active co-operation in suppressing any fanatic movement and in opposing hostile confederation if rising takes shape we should offer the following inducements in anticipation of successful issue to the war. We should undertake to detach Lirawi from Behbehan and associate it with Ilayat Baud under Bushire, and should assist Khans to buy out Said-us-Sultaneh interest in district. We should agree to maintain Khans of Hayat Baud and Rudhilleh in the enjoyment.of their existing privileges as regards taxation. W r e should undertake to eject present hostile Khan from Borasjun and put in relative and nominee ol Khan of Shabancara. Similarly we should eject present Khan from Ahmedi and hand it over to Khan of Angeli who has support of Haidar Khan. With common interests thus secured and consolidated, friendly Khans would, I believe, be able to hold their own against hostile confederation, but we should need to give them some ammunition and probably aims, and m the event of attack being imminent on Port Bander itself, i am strongly ol opinion that we must support Haidar Khan to protect the port. If situation in Arabistan is satisfactory Sheikh of Mohammera might be able to assist Haidar Khan by despatching to Bander proportion of force which he has now mobilised. I request authority to act on the lines above indicated when the moment arrives. 1 1 tiSecret Department. FOREIGN SECRET TELEGRAMS From Sir P. Cox, May 1915. (Addressed Foreign, repeated Tehran, Bushire, Ispahan, and India Office.) ■ 1 ?i 82 i! 3 ' Terence to Minister, Tehran, 161 to Foreign Office Following is, outlook as regards Bakhtians. Sirdar Jang and Bahadur are at I)i/fhl &amp; and WsTntXflnat'ren 17 '''J theni ^.ling ArabRtan affairs a.'riecfef^ 1 ’-’ and ’ n « ith « r Shdlio/M^LZkh nor IfeHbrtoTsottss meet them at llXf^ry “ W ' th h ' m - 1 ^‘“8 &lt;*pporUmity to Sirdar .Fang’s attitude, however, in regard to incursion of Turkish troops Wl !C f a ' S T IU ShuSt6r ’ 8;lfe couduct of Wassmuss, and rising in . abistan nas been most equivocal, and even Ills staunch adherent, Dr. Young wired ^ on 27th April that Sirdar’s present attitude excited his grave suspicion. to Sheikh of Mohammerah reminds me Bakhtiaris are not a one great body but a many-headed monster ; that their interests are now no longer limited to Bakhtiari country, but that they have stretched their tentacles all over rersia, and though he thinks from self-interest they will not enter seriously into war, he is not confident of their being ready to enter into any compact with him and us. . As b8fore stated, however, lie is prepared in our joint interests to enter into matiimoniai project if it proves likely to promote an agreement. In view of Sirdar Jangs recent attitude it is possible he may seek to avoid open meeting with me or my representative ; in that ease l would propose to send Haji Rais to represent me as well as Sheikh of Mohammerah. W e could hardly have a better emissiary for the purpose in view. After pointing out what Bakhtiaris stand to lose by joining in hostilities against us, and what they may gain by peaceful co-operation with Sheikh and us, we should state following requirements. They must refuse to take up arms against us, and must do their utmost to discourage jihad^ generally, and vigorous suppression of it within their tribal territory. 1 hey must maintain internal order and secure escort in sphere of oil company, also on Ahwaz-Ispahan road and at Ispahan itself, where their representative^ must protect all subjects of Great Britain and her Allies and must maintain security of road and telegraph lines up to Kars boundary. They must come to a permanent friendly understanding with Sheikh of Mohammerah and give him all necessary co-operation in Arabistan by refusing to harbour refugees from his territory and by maintaining peace on border. Their representative at Behbehan must likewise suppress fanaticism and maintain order there and refrain from all interference with Lirawi or with Sheikh of Mohammerah’s tribes in that vicinity. Any Bakhtiari being a provincial Governor in Southern Persia at time of outbreak of war must do his best to protect British subjects and interests, suppress fanaticism and keep [? Bakhtiari] quiet and neutral. In return for this we should undertake on conclusion of war to preserve Bakhtiari country with its present limits for tribe and give Khans local autonomy to deal with their own tribesmen in their own, way under our aegis. We should agree to keep Bakhtiari Governor at Ispahan under our guidance and be prepared to consider Bakhtiari candidates among others for other governorships in sphere controlled by us. We should be prepared later on to consider sympathetically any workable proposal they might put for obtaining access to ports on Persian Gulf. On receiving undertaking to the effect required from recognised repre sentatives of two families we would pay each branch 5,OOOL each now, and 10,000k each at end of war if they carry out their part of the bargain effectively.— From. Sir P. Cox, Basra, 12th May 1915. [Addressed to Foreign ; repealed Tehran, and Secretary of State.) May. yr ' ,e ' !/ ' 1O80B - Reference t0 Mi telegram No. 101, dated 8th. • f al ! b ' nit act| oi) to be taken on outbreak of war in Persian ports reauires immediate consideration and decision. ^ tt* a , 11( ? £( 1 )r . emc f t ’ lir f eilt desideratum is thai as many [? as possible] of is Majesty s ships from the East Indies squadron should be' made available ove^Ou^ ,amm t Tl' 1 wella 1 ve£o 1 (1 ° ^ to make prize of “ Persepolis,” and take i ustoms at Aliwaz and Mohammera. I think it would be politic, and have excellent effect, to allow Sheikh of Mol,ammera to put in guards, and a ow &gt;e Aians to carry out as usual Treasury import duties we merely keeping account of receipts, and allowing the Sheikh of Mohammera to take them for the present. At Bushire we should at once land Naval brigade as in 1909 to seize and occupy Eustom-house and place cordon round the town in concert with the military as was done in 1909. Duties can be banded over to the military in due course, but occupation ol town and ( 1 ustom-house can be most effectively carried out by landing parties from ships in the harbour, preceded by armed boats. J 1 am aware the number of troops available will depend on conditions prevailing in India, but 1 do not think that in the event of war situation at Hush ire would be satisfactory with less than two battalions and four guns, and presence of cruiser with large white crew such as HALS. “ Fox.” As regards Emgah and Bunder Abbas, immediately war broke out we should control the telegraph and postal communication with those ports, and 1 am of opinion that when they knew Bush ire was occupied Bunder Abbas and 1 ingali would give little trouble. 'There is one remaining young German at Lingah, but he is not of sufficient importance to make it worth while causing a disturbance in order to capture him. Supposing that we cannot, to begin with, spare enough troops to garrison lingah and Bunder Abbas, action to be taken depends on local developments, whence patrol by His Majesty’s ships prime necessity for maintenance of wireless telegraph and protection of British lives and property. As regards Jask and Char bar, garrisons are possibly strengthened or being strengthened in view of Khalifa’s rising, and 1 doubt if anything further is necessary.From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 12th May 1915. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Tehran, Bushire, and Secretary of State.) No. 1084b. Minister’s telegram No. 161, dated 8th May. Question ft Mekran. * r In the event of declaration of war, I think we should issue suitab proclamation to Khans on the lines of our assurances to Arab population Mesopotamia. In consideration of their suppressing fanaticism and maintaining ord u in their territories and security of telegraph lines, we might offer to mane MTr Barkat jd azk district to Minab. To Sirdar Saiyid Khan we might agree to make him Governor of Baluchistan, with suitable subsidy and subject to acceptance of British Agent. To other less important but friendly Khans we might offer pecuniary rewards for co-operation in maintenance of security and order. Other possible inducements may suggest themselves when we open negotiations.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00017a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/483</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00017a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/483</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3516/1914 Pt 6 'German War: Persia; general situation May-July 1915'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-21T22:33:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (237 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 239; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-237; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns events that happened in Persia and Balochistan, during the First World War. The main focus is measures to be taken in the event of Persia entering the War against Great Britain.The volume covers:Advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on measures to be taken in Balochistan, in order to form alliances with the rulers (Khans) and maintain a British Protectorate after the war.Recommendations of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on reinforcing British troops at Bushire.Situation in Tehran, and the arrest at Bushire of the German Consul, Listemann.Offering of so-called 'bribes' to the Bakhtiari tribe and to other tribes in Arabistan, to convince them to support the British.Despatch of Russian troops in northern Persia, at Enzeli [Bandar Anzali, Iran], and Resht [Rasht, Iran].Assassination of Alexandre Kaver, Russian Vice-Consul and Manager of the Russian Bank at Isfahan.Situation at Kermanshah; withdrawal of the British Consul for Hamadan and evacuation by British and Russians.Translations of telegrams from the Persian Foreign Ministry regarding the War.German plot in Persia, led by the German Consul at Shiraz, Herr Wassmuss, with support of the Swedish gendarmerie.Protest of Persian Government against British military operations in Arabistan.Naval measures for the defence of Persian Gulf ports.Arrival of Russian troops in Isfahan, centre of German activities in Persia.Notes on the political situation in Persia by Vice-Admiral Edmond Slade.Attack on Anglo-Persian Oil Company's British employees drilling on the Island of Kishm [Qeshm, Iran].Resignation of Persian Cabinet on 3 July 1915; difficulties in the formation of a new cabinet.The volume’s principal correspondents are: Charles Hardinge, Viceroy of India; Thomas William Holderness and Arthur Hirtzel, India Office; Percy Cox, Political Resident in Persian Gulf; Walter Gordon Neale, Assistant Resident in the Persian Gulf; Walter Beaupre Townley and Charles Marling, British Ministers at Tehran; W MacDouall, British Consul for Kermanshah; G Grahame, British Consul-General at Isfahan, Eyre Alexander Barby Wichart Crowe, Foreign Office; Edward Grey, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; John Nixon, General Officer Commanding, Force 'D', Basrah; the Admiralty; Imperial Bank of Persia; Anglo-Persian Oil Company; Strick, Scott and Co.There is a newspaper cutting, from
                           The Times.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>German Consul</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>German Consul</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Enzeli</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Resht</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Balochistan</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul General, Isfahan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Bank of Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>The Times, British newspaper</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Frank C Strick and Company Limited, shipping company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander of the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gendarmerie</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Arabistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kishm</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oilfields</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00017a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>