<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002e4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:01:45.077Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">BRITISH DESIDERATA IN REGARD TO THE BAGHDAD RAILWAY. IT is not easy to fix upon a definite policy in regard to the Baghdad Railway, for it seems that the solution of this question must necessarily be subsequent to and in some measure dependent upon the disposal of the territory through which it passes, and the territorial settlement is still entirely en Vair. It may, however, be assumed that the Sykes-Pioot and Italian Agreements will be revised, that an attempt is to be made to divert France from Syria by offers in Armenia, and that our general policy is to plump for self-determination in the sure hope that the Arabs, or rather the Arab-speaking races, will opt for us. While there might be some reason for not banking too heavily on this hope in Syria, we are not likely to be disappointed in Mesopotamia. Even on this assumption there is difficulty in precision prior to the meeting with our Allies. We can, however, indicate the various courses that might be followed, and endeavour to select the policy most desirable in the view of the depart ments most concerned—that is, of the India Office and Board of Trade. We should then have to stand out for as much of this policy as we can get. The following variants may be considered:— 1. It has been proposed by the Chief Political Officer at Baghdad that the Bagh dad Railway should be regarded not as a private company, but as a Turkish State railway, and that all its assets in Mesopotamia should therefore be transferred to the Iraq State pending transfer to an Allied Railway Company to be formed hereafter if desired. The difficulty here would be to show ground on which the Railway could be made to appear a State as opposed to a private undertaking. Legally, the theory could not be demonstrated. In practice We should be reduced to the history of the enterprise, and in particular to the kilometric guarantees (which were held to be unfavourable both to the Government and the Company, as offering no inducements to the latter to develop traffic, and as hastening the former towards insolvency) to show that it was contemplated by the Turkish Government, and probably by the Germans, as a strategic and political and not as a commercial line. Out of this we could construct some kind of a case. It could be urged that, at considerable present and future cost, Turkish policy had been generally directed to the construction of uncommercial lines by the aid of heavy Government guarantees—that is, by the misuse of Turkish revenue. These lines were planned irrespective of traffic develop ment (c/. the refusal about 1893 to allow the extension of the Smyrna lines to Konia), and partly through sparsely populated country. They therefore were unlikely at first to be a paying proposition. Figures are, in fact, there to prove this view from the receipts, while, owing to the size of the kilometric guarantees, a profit of some £5.000,000 was expected to be realised by the promoters on the construction of the Baghdad Railway. As to the German view, it has been sufficiently demon strated during the war by open advocacy of this line as the means to split the British Empire, to destroy the British position on the Persian Gulf, and to under mine British sea power. j • 11 v With all this, however, we shall still be on weak ground, and, desirable though it undoubtedly is to secure sole management of the whole length of the line in our sphere, it may be doubted whether this is the right way to set about it. 2, A second solution proposed is that of internationalisation, that is, pre sumably, point control by Great Britain, France, and Italy. 1 he plan is in any case to be deprecated, but if it were adopted it might be well for us to add the I nited States. Their inclusion was proposed by Lord Lansdowne in his suggestion; tor internationalisation in 1905. There can be no question of admitting Germany. Turkish management or mismanagement would also be barred, even if a portion of the line ran through territory still remaining to her, [1057] B2 It may be however, that this plan has been suggested rathei with a view to meeting President Wilson than because it is practical. Of all bad systems tor working purposes internationalism is the worst, and there is reason to neue'vC taat the idea would be opposed on practical grounds by both the most mte^csLed depart ments, the India Office and the Board of Trade. The latter certainly are entirely and emphatically opposed to it. i he^ hold thai t-rc luikish aiid Gciihan interests should be expropriated, their value to form pari of the indemnity due to the Allies but that the Railway itself should be definitely partitioned among the various new States which it traverses, and that no other country or combination of countries should be entitled to have a say in the management and working of the line in our sphere. This they consider vital, and it seems impossible to dissent from this view. Apart from the unwisdom of allowing such a measure of foreign inter vention and eventual intrigue in our sphere, it would suffice to point to the example of Serbia and Bulgaria, who both before the war lound it intolerable that the main or sole great artery of their system should not be under their own control. In the case at Teast of Serbia internationalisation was at first contemplated and then aban doned. Moreover, with the deplorable record of the French and Italian business communities before us, we might well not be long in finding these elements acting as cat's-paws or cover for German interests—the very thing we wish to avoid. It has been suggested that such a contingency and other malpractices might be guarded against by the establishment of a Federal Commission, as mandatory of the League of Nations, with wide powers of veto, control, and regulation in regard to railway lines and their prospective free ports. This, however, in itself seems at least equally undesirable. * The solution of internationalisation should, in fact, only be considered, inas much as we may conceivably be driven back upon it in the last resort. The proposal would run somewhat on the following lines; We desire generally to maintain that concessions are not cancelled by the war; therefore, the Baghdad Railway Concession is still valid, but we should insist that it be handed over— together, of course, with the Anatolian Railway—as part of the indemnity to the Allies. The French contemplate such a demand in regard to all German concessions. The first question arising is, who is to make the cession? The (Convention of 1903 was concluded between the Turkish Government and the Anatolian Railway .Companv, represented by Herrn Gwinner, Zander, and Huguenin, acting for the Imperial Ottoman Company, in formation, of the Baghdad Railway. The concession- naire, i.e., the Anatolian Railway Company, was to form a limited Turkish company —stress is repeatedly laid on its Turkish character—w T ith the above title. The Anatolian Railway Company brought to the new company the concession granted by the Turkish Government—that is, the new line from Konia to the Persian Gulf and its branches—' with all the rights, privileges, and advantages, attached to or flowing from it.' The new company became the proprietor of the concession ' and takes over all the rights and obligations of the concessionnaire. Nevertheless, the Anatolian Railway Company keeps for its exclusive account the rights and obliga tions concerning only the old lines, i.e., the Anatolian Railway. The Turkish eminent, like the Anatolian Railway Company, retained 10 per cent, of the share capital (15,000,000 francs), and the new company was only to be definitely consti tuted w T hen one-tenth of the share capital had been paid up. Some space has been allowed to this point, because doubt has been expressed on the exact character and oomposition of the Company, with a view to deciding on the form of the cession. In view of the above pafagraph it is suggested that the cession should be made by both the Turkish and German Governments, witK whom we made the 1914 agreements. Ft would then be for those Governments to indemnify any of their subjects whose interests might be affected. It was believed that the subscribed capital was not considerable, but, according to the Baghdad Railway Company's Import for 1904, £300,000 had been paid. (The Germans, how ever, have themselves admitted that the Company's balance sheets were neither intended to be accurate nor intelligible.) The same principle would apply to the subjects of France, or any other country in a similar position. We should be justified in adopting this attitude towards French private interests, as their partici pation was originally concealed from us, and the original agreement providing for it was only discovered in 1902 through the French Ambassador in Constantinople. In 1905 the French Ambassador in London assured Lord Lansdowne that France was absolutely unconnected with the Railway. The attitude of the French Govern ment was officially that they refused, pending an agreement equitable to the interestsof all the Powers, to allow quotation on the Paris Bourse of any issue relating to the Baghdad Kailway. As such an agreement had not been reached at the time of any French participation, we should have ground lor arguing that French private interests had gone behind the back of-their own Government. Such interests must, therefore, look to the concessionnaires lor indemnification-—with the assistance of their own Government, if it deemed them worthy. The part played by French iinanciers and politicians in this business is dealt with at some length in M. Cheradame's book on the Baghdad Railway. He is especially severe on M. Constans and M. Kouvier, the latter of whom he describes as an agent of the Deutsche Bank. M, Delcass^ is equally criticised, and the whole review is most unfavourable. 1 he exact degree of French participation cannot be definitely given, but it may here be convenient to indicate the stated composition of the £300,000, to which reference has been made above. Ten per cent, was said to have been subscribed by the Anatolian Kail way Company, 10 per cent, by the Turkish Government, and 80 per cent, by the Deutsche Bank group of financiers. It is doubtful whether the subscription of the Anatolian Railway Company was more than nominal. Of the 80 per cent, subscribed by the Deutsche Bank group, 70 per cent, was believed to have been subscribed in nearly equal proportions by French and German groups, and 10 per cent, by groups of Swiss and other nationalities. Considering these figures with the composition of the Administrative Council of the Company, it was held clear that effective control of its affairs was in the hands of the Deutsche Bank group. It may be added that in 1905 an Austrian, a Swiss, and a Belgian bank were each represented on the Board of the Company by a director, and there was also an Italian member, representing an Italian electrical company at Milan. There were also five directors, who were Frrtich officials of the Imperial Ottoman Bank, and a number of other prominent Frenchmen as well. There had already been an interchange ot directors between the French Smyrna-Cassaba Railway and the Anatolian Railway. Our information was briefly that there was close connection between the French and German groups, that the interest of the former in the line was considerable, and that the French holding of shares in the Company was probably between 30 per cent, and 40 per cent, of the whole. It is obvious that this is irreconcilable with M. Cambon's assurances to Lord Lansdowne, or with the statement of the Com mercial Controller of the French Foreign Office to Sir F. Bertie, that no negotiation between French and German groups could take place without the knowledge of the French Government, who would not give their concurrence without previous com munication with the British Government. To revert to the present suggestions for internationalisation. The concession being surrendered to the Allies collectively, it is suggested that the administration of the Railway should be placed in the hands of some body analogous to the Danube Commission. Incidentally it has also been proposed that this body might create revenue—replacing the kilometric guarantees—by selling the mineral rights, provided for by the concession, to the national authorities of the territory through which the line passes. (By article 22 of the 1903 concession permission was granted to work minerals, which might be found within 20 kilom. on either side of the line, but this was expressly qualified by the reservation that ' no privilege or monopoly is thereby constituted.') If the working of different sections were handed over to different managements, the receipts of the entire system would presumably be pooled and distributed by a clearing-house managed by a committee from the several Boards. It should not be forgotten that the commercial values of the various sections will be most unequal, o -,1 tW, the southernmost section may be the most valuable, especially with the Khanikin branch. It was originally estimated that the Baghdad-Gulf section ot the line would alone pay at once as a commercial undertaking without kilometric guarantees, partly owing to the pilgrim traffic to Kerbela and Nejaf. Apart from the political evils of internationalisation, there are serious disad vantages from the railway point of view. For example, the construction of branch lines and extensions would be a constant source of trouble. The controlling authority might maintain that it was internationally more important to provide money for extensions in the French sphere than in ours, and great difficulties might be put in the wav of development in the British section. Branches not likely to be immediately profitable would be eschewed, and the opening up of the poorer and more backward sections would thus be arrested. The same considerations apply to the improvement of existing lines, and under international control there would always be a tendency [1057] B 24 to cuitail unduly the working expenses on the sections wiiicli cuntributed least revenues to tlie common pool. . Moreover, the French will also probably not welcome the plan io begin witli, they are quits likely to take the pretext of the Trench private interests already involved in order to aim at a preponderance incompatible with real internationalisa- tion. That tlie French Government was not really indillerent to the operations ot French financiers is indicated in the report oi an interdepartmental committee, in March 1907, that the French ' k interest in the enterprise is apparently above all financial.' Further, the plan would certainlv involve the creation o( some such body as the above-mentioned Federal Commission; but this might entail the constitu tion of Alexandretta, and probably some of tke Syrian harbours as tree ports. Indeed the creation of a free port at Alexandretta would be the sole really tangible advantage that this country would derive Irom internationalisatioii, and even this is now somewhat discounted. There seems to have been considerable consensus in the past on the necessity in our interests that Alexandretta should not be controlled bv France or any other Great Power. This view would have seemed likely to be accentuated as the development of oil increasingly provides cheap haulage to Alexan dretta, which should be geographically the westward outlet lor oui leisian and Mesopotamian trade, as opposed to the alternative circuitous route by the kMiez Canal. This view, however, is not upheld by the Board of 1 rade opinion quoted France, moreover, will probably oppose a project which would weaken hei grasp on coveted points like Alexandretta. Her opposition may also not be much dimin ished by the regulation of details like the nationality of the employes in the various sections, or even by some modification in the sense that the federal ( ommission, oi similar body, while taking over the trunk lines, should entrust their management to local administrations working under a joint traffic agreement. Her appetite will not easily fall in with internationalism in any veiled form at Alexandretta or in Syria, nor can we count upon success in switching her attentions Irom those regions by baits in Armenia. As regards internationalisation, the position therefore is— 1. It is an inherently cumbrous and in many respects vicious method, especially in this particular instance. Those who have recommended intern a tional- isation or partial internationalisation in the past— e.g., Sir G. Clarke, in 1907—have only done so as a yis aller. The Interdepartmental Com mittee of March 1907 reported that British control from Mosul, or failing that Baghdad, southward was essential to British interests, and such control could not, in their opinion, be obtained ' under any system of internationalisation.' Incidentally, it has always been held that nothing less than Mosul would really serve. - 2. Whatever the views of this department may be, internationalisation will not command unanimity, even in our own ranks. 3. It is unlikely of acceptance by Fnance, with whom, at the end of the chapter, we must probably deal, and deal tete-a-tete as we have done in the past, whether we will or not. On the credit side its recommendation is that it may get a blessing from Mr. Wilson. Presumably, however, we do not mean to base our policy on this hypothesis alone. The following solution would seem on all grounds preferable: Whether by ' self- determination,' or by any other process, we shall obtain practical control in Meso potamia. Our position vis-a-vis of our Allies will be the stronger if we are spon taneously selected. Even President Wilson could hardly fall foul of our railway policy in such an event. We should then take a firm stand against internationalisia- tion, and we might strengthen the argument for national control by the examples of Serbia and Bulgaria above mentioned. (The latter bought out the Orient Railway Company for 42,000,000 francs in 1909.) As regards French financial interests, the line to be taken is indicated in the body of this memorandum. We should have fairly good ground for such an attitude. As regards French political opposition, our course must depend somewhat on the territorial settlement which is still in the melting-pot. Our success will, however, in any case depend entirely on the firmness of our attitude, and we should leave no doubt that this will not be modified even if the French refuse the Armenian offer.e can enueavour to tone down our insistence on strict national control {i.e., control by us, selected as representatives of the self-determined Mesopotamian Htate) by allowing a representative of each section of the line to sit on the railway board of the others. For this plan would involve dividing the line into several sections worked by separate managements under a joint traffic agreement, providing explicitly for equalisation of rates and conditions over the railway as a whole, or such stipulations for equitable transit (especially for the unrestricted interchange of all through traffic), and against any discrimination, direct or indirect, as we may deem desirable. Provisions of this kind have, in fact, figured in all the pro jects of territorial division in Asia Minor hitherto discussed with our Allies. Given national control, the question of through traffic would become a pure ques tion of a railway agreement between the owners of the line on the two sides of the frontier—an agreement, in fact, similar to that which regulates through traffic on the Gothard Railway. It seems essential in our interest that our section of the line should run at least as far as Mosul. This will not be obtained without great resolution on our part. It has also been held to be essential, as above indicated, that Alexandretta should be a free port. The Board of Trade view, however, is that, while this would no doubt have certain advantages for the purpose of working the line, they do not regard it as essential. If ^o, our policy should be to try for this without making it a sine qua non, as there might be objection to making a free port of Basra, which would be the logical counterpart of our demand for a free port at Alexandretta. (Our historic position and record in the Persian Gulf might give us some ground for resisting the application to the Gulf terminus of the control which we should try for at Alexandretta; but this line of argument would hardly be held valid by foreign Powers.) It might, however, be wise to provide in the settlement that no undue preference shall be shown by the French to railway traffic using the port. If we obtain these desiderata we should not need to trouble ourselves too greatly about the management of the other sections, as practically all our trade would go either by the Gulf or by Alexandretta. We need not, therefore, object if the French obtain in .the northern sectors—this they would have to settle with the Italians—a mandate similar to that which we shall obtain in the southern. We could make this declaration of desinteressemeM with a lighter heart, as the French would probably be unable in practice to obtain such a mandate. Such an attitude on our part would, however, give us material for dealing with them, even if they refuse to be lured into Armenia; and we shall probably, after much bargaining, be able to offer them a sufficient inducement to leave us in control of the line as far north as Mosul, provided we are quite clear in our own minds before we meet them that no other solution will be satisfactory to us. The formula of self -determination should cover us from Presidejnt Wilson. The French are the real people with whom we have to settle. As already indicated, their interests in the line have hitherto been mainly financial; they cannot pretend to political interest in the Gulf end/ If necessary, we can transiger on the financial aspect, though it may be better to keep this suggestion m reserve. The Board ot Trade point out that any French or other friendly interests entitled at present to a share in the concession must be properly compensated for expropriation. This is. of course incontestable. The debatable point is whether the French financiers arc to look for compensation from us or to the Germans whose interests they subserved. If. then, national control is our proper aim, it is suggested that the toilowing method 1 might conciliate all parties in the attainment of it:— 1. Turkey to expropriate all the shareholdings in private hands. 2. Germany to find the money for this operation. . 3. Turkey then to cede, with Germany's assent, the whole concession to the Inter-Allied Pool. # i cu i. v 4 The Inter-Allied Pool then to sell to the Government of each State through which the line passes so much of the line as lies withm the boundaries ot that State. The advantages of this method would be as follows:— 1. The countries ravaged by the war would get some benefit In the transtei of the concession, as they would share the price obtained b\ the oo . an would 1 not depend on getting the territory m Asia Minor in order to benefit by the cession of the railway. This would help Belgium, 10 is not wholly disinterested. The Baghdad Railway Company had anagreement with the Society de Transports fiuviaux en Orient, of Brussels, for the carriage of railway material. 2. We should be guarded against a possible charge of grabbing. _ 3. The French financiers would thus be got rid of at the beginning. It would be for them to get the best price they could out of the German Treasury; but they would not come into conflict with us. 4. There would seem no ostensible reason why Mesopotamia, &amp;c., should get the railway as a free gift. If they bought their sections from the Allied Pool, the above-quoted justification by analogy with Bulgaria and the Orient Railway would be complete. R. V.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002e4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B304</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002e4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B304</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'British Desiderata in Regard to the Baghdad Railway'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-09T00:12:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 153, and terminates at folio 155, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 11-158; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This confidential memorandum, signed R V, concerns Britain's policy with regards to the Baghdad Railway following the occupation of the Mesopotamia. The memorandum details two variant policies: (1) regarding the Railway not as private property, but as a Turkish State railway, and that all its assets in Mesopotamia should therefore be transferred to the Iraq State pending transfer to an Allied Railway Company; and (2) a proposal for the internationalisation of the Railway to be controlled by Great Britain, France and Italy, and perhaps the United States of America. The advantages and disadvantages vis-a-vis British interests are then further discussed throughout the report.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Baghdad Railway</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002e4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>