<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:28:46.823Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i t 0 * 0 ° ' * .£• 81/28 Telegram En Clair. From Political Resident, at Bahrain To H.M.Ambassador, Cairo. No. T/464. Dated 4th August 1946. IMPORTANT . Your telegram No. CIVATT 273 August 3rd. No objection will be raised to landing by Dyer in private aircraft at Bahrain and Sharjah as a special case. It is however contrary to present policy and agreements with Shaikhs. - HAY - y Office of the iiQa..£/&amp;§£• ‘Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, Copy, with copy of tdiegram referred to, forwarded, with compliments, to the 4th August 1946 The Political Agent BAHRAIN . RHL.81/28 Telegram From To Repeated No. En clair Ambassador, Cairo. H.M's. Ambassador, Tehran. H.M*s. Ambassador, Baghdad. . Political Resident, at Bahrain, CIVATT 273 Dated 2nd received 3rd August, 1946 Proctor Gahtn pilot John Dyer has arrived Almaza en route to Australia. Pilot carries letter from Ministry of Civil Aviation stating that they have requested permission from Baghdad and Tehran for aircraft to land at H 3 Baghdad West Basra Bahrain Sharjah and Jask. Passengers include two women. No radio. Please advise urgently by telegram whether it is in order for this aircraft to proceed. CAMPBELL -H OVERSEAS 13/vi ® 3 AIRWAYS CORPORATION Bahrein, 5th Aug.,1946. XSM.2291.0535* Bahrein. Sir MR. AKD LiRS. OGDEIT I have the honour to advise that the above-mentioned, together 'with their small daughter aged approximately 6 years, stayed at the B.O.A.C. Resthouse, Manama from 1300 hours on 30/7/46 to 0700 on 1/8/46. 2. They were flying to Australia from the United Kingdom in a privately owned Procter aircraft and were accommodated at the request of the Officer Commanding R.A.P. Station, Bahrein. Station Supdt. GF.7P:VKK® 4 - . CONFIDENTIAL. r u. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No. C/Z'SI. • Dated the j jl)^ . The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: Description of Enclosure . NAME &amp; DATE. SUBJECT. Letter No. XSM. 2291.0535 | Dated the 5th August, 1946 fas and Mrs. Ogden. From B.O.A.C., Bahrain. NS.-.'As •sjy v— The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 8th August,1946, The Afiviser to the Government of Bahrain Bahrain. 0 ., 3 - MEMORAMDTIM Reference th^tittached copy of B 0 A C letter No. XSM 2291.0535 dated the 5th August, 1946. 2. I understand that no customs or passport examination was made of the occupants of the aircraft in question. 3. Please confirm. Sd. H.D.H.Ranee. Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. A. &lt;T. o« y■From &gt;'/3 Officer Commanding, A. Station, To s Political Copy to : A H.BJ.I* s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain. Copy to : A.S.L.O. Date 7 th August, 1946 . Ref. BAH/6/AIR. CIVILIAL'! AIRCRAPT - LOCUu IGGITi^ulIQIIL. Attached is a copy of a report by the Officer i/c Passenger and Freight Section giving all available particulars of the passengers and crew of the Proctor aircraft, CA-HPa, which landed at Bahrein on the 30th July, 1946. left the aerodrome boundaries was domestic, and made possible by private arrangement between the R.A.F. and B.O.A.C, 3. It is regretted that passports and visas were not inspected, but it has not been the practice of the R.A.F. , Bhhrein, to demand these. 4 . In view of this fact, and the ignorance at R.A.F. , Bahrein, as regards local regulations in such matters, it would be appreciated if a ruling could be given by H.B.M* s Political Agent, for onward transmission to higher R.A.P. authority. 5. It is known that several other Civil aircraft are intending to land and refuel at R.A.P., Bahrein, in the near future. 2 . It is pointed out that the only reason for the persons stated having ~\~ (V.P. KEX) O.B.R., Squadron Leader, Commanding R.A.P. Station. BAHRBIK. nzi *PROM: AIR TRAFFIC OFFICER RAF STATION, BAHREIN TO: OFFICER COMMANDING RAF STATION, BAHREIN DATE: 6.8 .46 REF: P. &amp; F. 100 CIVILIAN - (m£) HtOCTCR. REGISTRATICS^ G A H F X The following is the information available on the aircraft indicated above 5 - &lt; 1* Arrived at Bahrein on 30th July 1946, at 0813z hrs., having flown from RAP Station, Shaibah. 2* Departed Bahrein for RAP Station Sharjah, on 1st August at 0535z hrs, 3 The aircraft was flown by Mr Ogden, and he was accoinpanied by his wife and small child, (Girl, about six years). Owing to the lack of toilet facilities for female passengers, due to the temporary structural alterations to the VIP block, arrangements were made for them to be accomadated at BOAC Rest House, ilanama. They returned to Lluharraq aerodrome approximately one hour before take-off, and after being cleared from the Plying Control section, left for RAF Station, Sharjah. It is understood that their original departure point was Croydon, U.K., and their ultimate destination, Australia. M. S. Scotney, P/Lt. AIR TRAFFIC OFFICER.No. of 1365 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Ramadhan 13, 1365 August 10, 1946. 9 H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. C ^ ' Memorandum : Reference your memorandum No.C/884 dated 8th August, 1946. As the Bahrain Government has no intimation of the arrival of this aircraft neither customs or passport Officials were present and no exami nation was made. YG. Adviser to the Government. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.CONFIDENTIAL. EXPRESS LETTER From Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Persian Gulf To No. C/HW at Bahrain Reference my printed Letter No. c/881 dated the 7th August, 1946. I enclose copies of Memorandum No. BAH/6/AIR dated the 7th August, 1946, and its enclosure, from the Officer Commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain. The Bahrain Government have since confirmed that they had no intimation of the arrival of this aircraft and that in consequence no customs or passport examination was made. Neither do any landing or housing fees appear to have been paid. - i 01 a to private aviators has been that they should not be permitted to fly along the Arab Air Route. Please see in this connection correspondence resting with enclosures to Residency Printed Letter Nd. 594-S dated the 15th November, 1938, and India Office Complimentary Slip No. P.Z.569 dated the 28th January, 1939. I have not approached His Highness, but the Adviser has informed me verbally that, in his opinion, the present Ruler has no objection to private aviators landing in Bahrain. If you wish I will ask the Adviser to confirm this point in writing. uua chey were before the War and have a longer radius of action. It would therefore appear likely that the pre-war policy referred to in paragraph three above will now have to be altered, but whatever changes may now be made ixi regard to private aircraft previous notice will still be required of their E.T.A. in Bahrain, and should it become necessary for any of the occupants of the aircraft to leave the aerodrome the necessary passport and customs formalities will have to be carried out. Even when these are not necessary the Quarantine Medical Officer will have in every case to carry out the usual quarantine examination, if you have no objection therefore I propose to ask the Officer Commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain, to ensure that the Quarantine Medical Officer, the Bahrain Government Passport and Customs Authorities, and this Agency are informed immediately he receives any information regarding the arrival of a private aircraft in Muharraq. 4 Light aircraft are now far more reliable Sd. H.D.H. RANGE political Agent, Bahrain Attested &lt;37o for Assistant Political Agent, BahrainFrom*- Tot- Date*- Reft- Offleer Commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain. Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain. 7th August, 1946. BAH/6/AIR. ^o g .Ati W WL MIOJ® Attftfihed is a copy of a report by the Officer i/c Passenger and Freight Section giving all available particulars of the passengers and crew of the Proctor aircraft, GA-HFX, which landed at Bahrain on the 30th July, 1946. 2« It is pointed out that the only reason for the persons stated having left the aerodrome boundaries was domestic, and made possible by private arrangement between the R.A.F. and B.O.A.C. 3* It is regretted that passports and visas were not inspected, but it has not been the practice of the R.A.F., Bahrein, to demand these* 4. In view of this fact, and the ignorance of R.A.F., Bahrein, as regards local regulations in such matters, it would ^ be appreciated if a ruling could be given by B.B.M’s Political Agent, for onward transmission to higher R.A.F. authority. 4. It is known that several other ft Civil aircraft are intending to land and refuel at R.A.F., Bahrein, in the near future. Sd/- (V.P. KEY) O.B.B., Squadron Leader, Commanding R.A.F., Station, Bahrein* From* Air traffic Officer, RAF Station, Bahrein. HI O • Officer Commanding, R*iF Station, Bahrein. Date* 6/3/46, Rw#*- P. A F. 100 GlYILIAIfQWNRD PROCTOR. REGISTRATION GAHFX i The follotdng is the information available on the aircraft indicated above*- 1* Arrived at Bahrain on 30th July, 1946, at 0813z hrs,, having flown from R.A.F. Station, Shaibah. 2. Depa r ted Bahrein for R.A.F. Station, Sharjah, on 1st August at 0635z hrs. 3. The aircraft was flown by Mr. Ogrdan, and he was accompanied by his wife and small child. iGirl, about six years). Owing to lack of toilet facilities for female passengers, due to the temporary structural alterations to the VIP block, arrangements were made for them to be accommodated at BOAC Rest House, Manama* They returned to Muharraq aerodrome approximately one hour before take-off, and after being cleared from the Flying Control section, left for R.A.F. Station, Sharjah. It is understood that their original departure point was Croydon, U.K., and their ultimate destination Australia. Sd/- M*S. SCOTNRY, F/Lt. Air Traffic Officer* L.R,81/L8. Telegram From To ^Wipeated No. a Political Resident a t Bahrain. India Office London. Government of India, Rev Delhi. T/491. Dated 13th August 1946. On July 30th Ogden with wife and daughter landed without prior notice at Bahrain in private Proctor aeroplane en route from United Kingdom to Australia and stayed for two days. 2. On August 3rd I received a telegram from H.M's Ambassador Cairo that John Dyer had landed at Almaza en route to Australia In Proctor plane and that he carried letter from Ministry of Civil Aviation that they had requested permission from Baghdad and Tehran for Aircraft to land at Bahrain and Sharjah am ngst other places. I replied that landings would be permitted as a special case but have heard nothing further of the aeroplane. 3. Regarding flights of private aircraft over Gulf Sheikhdoms please se^ this Residency Express Letter 920-S of the 27th July 1938 repeat 1933 and Foreign Office despatch to Cairo 1232 of the 28th heotember be persuaded to a^ree to flights over and landings by private aircraft in tneir territories and I see no strong objection myself provided prior notice of landings is given and if It is proposed to break journey all crew and passengers are in possession of passports properly endorsed and visaed for ^halkhdom concerned. b. Grateful for instructions. «.0‘»0*0«»0' , *0«»0«»0'*0«»0 a »0 aa&gt; 0~0~0'&gt;0~0~0'»0~0 a »0~0«»0-»0 a '»0*(&gt;'-0~0~0-0«”0~ Hay Kg.» Office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, « w* EIJlGUA VXUJL4 | Camp Bahrain, the*14th August 1946• Copy forwarded with compliments toa- i/ifhe Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. The Political Agent, Muscat. i/the Political The Political The Political Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ICeJs2:&gt;' 0 ..Date... (I't o« G/ 668 office of the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Camp, Jbahrain, the 14th August 19 46. To The Political Agent, Reference your express letter lio. C/892 dated the 12th August 1946 regarding the landing of private aviators at Bahrain* / / 2. Please take the action proposed m the last sentence of paragraph 4. od. W.R.HAf. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested* / i/\ for oecretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf • RHL. ConMential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. No... ,No. C/912. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 18th August, 1946. To. The Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force Station, Bahrain. © 2. I should be grateful if you would ensure in future that the Quarantine Medical Officer, the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, and this Agency are informed immediately you receive any information regarding the arrival of a private aircraft at MUharraq. Sd. H.D.H.Ranee. Political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 18th August, 1946. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, No. c/i The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. No. c/^jFran t To Date Ref. - R.a.F. station, BAHRED'i, British Forces in Iraq. - H.B.M*s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. - 21st August, 1946. - BAH/6/AIR. / / i V ; CIVILIAN -OWl'ffiD PROCTOR AIRCRAFT RSC: Gr-AHTN. As requested by telephone on 20th August, herewith is a report onPiOCTQR G-AHTN. 2. If particulars cf civil aircraft are to be required on future occasion it would be appreciated if you could furnish this Unit with a draft copy of the. exact particulars required, so that a proforma may be utilised. (V.P. KEI) O.B.E., Squadrpn Leader, Commanding R».ti.F. Station . ' Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. No.1.11?.Prom: Air Traffic Officer, R.A.P.Station, Bahrein* To: Officer Gcmnanding, R.A*P.Station,Bahrein* Date: 20th. August, J \9)+b. The follov/ing are the particular’s regarding the above-mentioned aircraft:- 1. Actual time of arrival from R.A*P. Station Shaibah, O^IOhrs.Z, on Thursday^5th. August, 1 946 . 2. Actual time of depai’ture for R.A.F. Station Sharjah, 0255hrs.Z, on Sunday, 1 81h. Augus t, 1 • 3. The aircraft was flown by Mr.John Dyer, accompanied by one passenger, Mrs. I.Pollard. A. Mr. John Dyer and his passenger were accomodated on this station, and both were in possession of British Passports. The latter were examined on two separate occasions by Bahrein Customs Officials. 5. The ultimate * destination of Hr. John Iyer and passenger was Australia and his original departure point England. CP/IL0V.1IED PROCTOR.REG-. OAIITN. (M. S.Sco tney.p/Lt.) Air Traffic Officer BAHREIN.CONFIDENTIAL EXPRESS LETTER From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain No. C/936 Dated the 22nd August, 1946. your telegram Nsx' T/491 dated the 13th August, 1946 Officer Commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain, giving particulars of .the arrival in Bahrain in a Proctor aircraft of Mr. John Dyer and Mrs. I* pollard. They arrived in Bahrain on the 15th and left on the 18th August, 1946. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. 2 I enclose a report from the Sd. H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain Attested JANC.e No. C/943 . The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 25th August, 1946. To. The Officer Commanding, R.A.F. Station, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. £• n I thank you for the report on the proctor aircraft G-AHTN sent under your^morandum No. BAIl/^AIR dated the 21st August, 1946^ 2. I attach a draft pro-forma giving the particulars required in future in respect of any private aircraft landing at Muharraq. Sd. H.D.H.Ranee. Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED for Assistant Political Agent, BAHRAIN. A.J.SMake and Registration marks of aircraft• Number of occupants. Full names and nationality of occupants and numbers of their passports. Times and dates of arrival and departure of aircfaft. Original departure point. Next stop. Ultimate destination. Where accommodated while staying in Balirain. Whether seen by:- (a) Passport Officer. (1?) Quarantine Medical Officer.No. -29/10. To:~ i \ ^ Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated August, 194-6. The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B_A._H_R_A_.I_N. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that Mr. D.N. Dalton, Miss A.M. Bartlett and Miss I.M. Ogden, all British subjects, landed on !£uharraq aerodrome in a Proctor plane at noon on the 27th August, 1946. Their passports were neither endorsed nor visaed for Bahrain. They came from England and left for Australia the next morning. I have the honour to be, , Sir, Your most obed5.ent servant, i/ Political Agent, Bahrain.iHs &amp; No. C/993. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 4th September, 1946. To The Officer commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain . Memorandum. c Reference correspondence ending with my memorandum No.C/943 dated the 25tt , i Auguso, 1946 ^' 2. I should be grateful to receive a report on the proctor aircraft piloted by Mr. D.N. Dalton which landed at Muharraq aerodrome on the 27th and left on the 28th August, 1946. Sd./- J.S.H. HUDSON In the absence of the Political Agent. ATTESTED. I AC+S?' for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA- Department. confidential. EXPRESS LETTER frttlfocMsMfefr [N.B .—This \* an ORIGINAL message tent by AIR MAIL which provide* a meant of communication more » •. • mi At . !• ^1. ^ ~ ~* **. si. S L * 4 s,1 sintrrt &gt;rxh It • a i n fo'n/hj/j tn h P frenff'd- expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No.699~S» Dated Xxjtxx Persian Gulf Residency, , Bahrain, =£,the 6th September 1946# 19 To Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference my endorsement No.C/659 dated the!4th August 1946 copy is enclosed of India Office telegram No. 16005 dated the 1st September 1946. In 1933 the Shaikh of Bahrain specifically No. C/292-21/20 dated the 24th July 1933. x If you see no objection would you kindly endeavour now to obtain his agreement to private aircraft flying over and landing in Bahrain territory on the condition that normal passport and visa requirements are maintained. If you consider it necessary it may be pointed out to him that in view of the reliability and range of modem light aircraft it is no longer considered necessary to forbid the use of the Arab air route by private aircraft. 2. So far as the Trucial Shaikhdoms are concerned they have already authorised H.U.G. to accord rights to foreign aircraft, vide enclosures to your Printed Letters Nos.C/365 and C/406 dated the 6th and 17th April 1946 re think it may be taken for gran similar rights being accorded or foreigp. I should however objected to private aircraft landing at Bahrain vide your letter Political Keaiaent, Persian uuiz Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL Confidential. Uol.U.J. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. (Signature) 7 ?. 2b, S. 44 MFP—1450 SAP—(M-2386)—28-3-40—15,000. (Designation)\ r o, - 81/28 T«ltgram From To Repeated No* India 01 floe 9 London. Political R«aldent 9 Bahrain. Government of India, E.A.P., New Delhi. 16005 Dated 1st received 2nd September, 1946 .6 Your telegram No. T/491 of April 13th. Flight# of Private Aircraft over Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. 2. Ms Majesty’s Government favour suggestion in your paragraph 4. Shaikhs may be approached accordingly. 3. Lorm&amp;l passport/ and visa requirements will be maintained.IWill you please refer to correspondence ending your demi-official letter No.379-30 dated the 23rd July, 1933* 2. I understand that you Informed Ranee that the present Ruler had no objection to private aviators flying over or landing in Bahrain on the condition that normal passport and visa requirements are main tained. If I am correct in saying this I should be grateful if you would obtain from His Highness a letter of agreement to this effect. 3. If you consider it necessary it may be pointed out to him that in view of the reliability and range of modern light aircraft it is no longer considered neces- - sary to forbid the use of the air route along the Arabian side of the Gulf by private aircraft. Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Esq. f C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government^ . Bahrain .\ OA POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, No. C/1029. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his comp 12th September, 1 ,ts to; The Hobble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents REFERBUGS TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: r.) h Agency letter No•2823*29/10 dated the 30th August, 1946. Description of Enclsoure . NAME &amp; DATE. SUBJECT. Memorandum No.Bah/3/Air dated 10.9.*46 from the Commanding Officer, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain, to the political Agent, Bahrain. 2 * . CIVIL IAN - OWNED PROCTOR AIRCRAFT. 0 I ca. 4 ' Telegram En Clair. From Britain, Bushire. To Resident, Muscat. Repeated to Repgu, Bahrain. political, Bahrain. No.x/20. Dated 14th Received 15th September, 1946. IMMEDIATE. Following telegram dated September eleventh received from M.C.A. London. Begins: 'X /V 'Swedish Legation, London, report desire of Swedish Missionary Board to send Douglas DC3 aircraft SEAPGON on flight to Calcutta and return via Sharjah as follows: Arrive Sharjah from Baghdad twenty-third September P.M. Depart Sharjah twenty-fourth September A.M. Return flight arrive Sharjah from Karachi and depart twenty-ninth September A.M*' Ends I.R.294. 15.9.*46. =BRITAIN= NS*En Clair. Political Resident, Muscat. Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram From To No.T/594. Dated and Received 15th September, 1946. IMMEDIATE. ^7 S Bushire telegram x 20 September fourteenth. Landings of Douglas at Sharjah. 2. If you see no objection to landings please ask my office at Bahrein to reply to M.C.A. accordingly. Also inform B.O.A.C. at Sharjah. =HAY= I.R. 296. 15.9.»46.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dbpabtmbnt. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B ,—This is art ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and formalilies d is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,} POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN From political Agent, Bahrain* To under Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain * No, C/1038. Dated 16th September,46. Reference Bushire telegram No.X/20 dated 14th September, 1946. 2. I enclose copy of telegram No*T/ 594 dated the 15th September, 1946, from the Political Resident at Muscat, please inform M.C.A. that there is no objection to landings at Sharjah. Sd./- J.E.H. HUDSON In the absence of the political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS. S. 6. MFP— 601 S&amp;P-(M-820)—23-7-36—300,000.From Telegram To G.T.C. political Agent, Bahrain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. No.239. Dated the 16th of September, 1946. TL-PORTART. Swedish Legation, London, have asked per- Kissionary Board to land at Sharjah on flight to Calcutta and return as follows: Arrive Sharjah from Baghdad 23rd. September P.M Depart Sharjah 24th September A.M. Return flight arrive Sharjah from Karachi and depart 29th September A.LI. I have replied there is no objection to mis ission for Douglas DCS aircraft SSAPGON owned by Swedish landings. 3. please inform station Manager, British Overseas Airways corporation, Sharjah. =POLITICAL=81/28 From Telegrj RIPOUt Bahrain. an clair To India office, London. TTo. 1007 ^atod the 13th Septer/ber, 1946. XMKKDIATl Following for Ministry of CiTil Aviation begins '♦Tour telegram September ilth to Bushire. Swedish aircraft S1AFGON. Copy forwarded with coroplimenta to The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his -Express Letter Bo. C/1038, dated 16th September, 1946 . Bo objection 4 ends R1PGU Ho. 764-S Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, The 17th September, 194 6 (|&gt; ill'll'' Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.irio j»_ From The Palace, Manama. September 26 *46 Salman bin Hamad Alkhalifah Ua^JUJ^jJI &lt; j To I L^jJ^y-eJ 4 1 ^ ^v 5 ^ 1 l -^&gt;‘ J 1 • 4-^iJI J^&gt; N JI '-f **-^ J -l ^Jl Ijl JX ^ aJ^» LlCvi Ui^ l*XA I p ^ c6 H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, We have to refer you to the subject of private aviators flying over or landing in Bahrain. We have no objection to private aviators flying over or landing in Bahrain provided they carry proper passports and possess visas. This is what was to have been said and Salaams. &lt;dul»J I JU^&gt; (Jy. {j Salman bin Hamad Al-Khalifah. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. ^EXPRESS LETTER . From - political Agent, Bahrain, To - Political Resident, Bahrain No.c/1136. Dated the 8th of October, 1946. 9 Reference your Express Letter No.699-S dated the 6th September, 1946. objection to private aviators flying over or landing in Bahrain provided they carry proper passports and visas. rised His Majesty's Government to accord rights to all foreign aircraft, whether State, Commercial, or private, and I consider they could have no objection to according the same facilities to British private aircraft as are already accorded to Royal Air Force and British commercial aircraft. 4. I presume that the only Trucial Shaiichdom where private aircraft will make landings is Sharjah. The Royal Air Force are now in control of the aerodrome there and will, I think, have to be asked to undertake the exami nation of passports and visas and to collect landing fees. In this connection it is pointed out that the provision regarding landing fees in the Sharjah Air Agreement relates only to commercial aircraft. 2 His Highness has informed me that he has no 3 Trucial Shaikhdoms would seem to have autho- Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain ATTESTED for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.Eyt.£14C/46. FOREIGN OFFICE, : ' 1 (',7 6593/5609/802) 7th Eeptenber 1946 V.ould you please refer to your letter to Ratcliff e-Cousins at .the Kinistry of Civil Aviation No.Ext.6568/46 of 15th August, concerning flights by private aircraft over the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms. 2. Vvhen the Chicago Convention comes into force, as I gather it is expected to do next 1.1 arch, such flights will be permissible without the necessity of obtaining prior authority (Article 5 of the Convention). In the meantime there appears to us every advantage in agreeing to permit flights now, subject to prior notification, as this would provide a useful transition stage. Copy of this letter is being sent to Hatcliffe- Cousins (Ini.C.A.) and ^arran (A.L .) F. A. K. Harrison, Esc., India Office. Yours sincerely (SGD.) A.J.2LDEN. Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain, the 1st October 1946. Copy forwarded with compliments to - The Political Agent, BA 111 AIM. NPG. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date...?, ' * -CONFIDENTIAL. No. 827-S. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, BAHliAIN , and lias tlie lionour to transmit to liim a copy of the undermentioned document (/£). with the request that, with reference to the last sentence of paragraph 3 of the last enclosure, he will please inform this office as to what visa and passport requirements he considers should be insisted on at both Bahrain and Sharjah. XMMmxz&amp;xE&amp;ai ymiSEim: Persian Gulf Residency, BAHRAIN. Dated... A.'!' ..?r;. t .?.V. ( ;r. 1246 Reference to previous correspondence: Residency endorsement No.826-S dated the 1st October 1946. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office demi-official letter No.Ext.5938/46, dated the 10th September 1946, and its enclosures. NPG. FLIGHTS OF PRIVATE AIRCRAFT OVER THE GULF SHAIKHDOES. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date ..3- -Ext.593E/46. \ INDIA OFFICE, T/HITE HALL, s.... 1. 10th September 1046. Lear Hay, n continuation of'our telegram Ho.16005 'of the 1st September, I enclose copies of the demi-official correspondence which has passed between the India Office and the Linistry of Civil Aviation on the subject of flights of private aircraft over the Gulf Sheikhdoms. Yours sincerely, ( SGE .) 0 The Ilon'ble Lieut. Col. ’H.H. Hay, CGI., OIL., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. NPG. /fcxt♦b56S/46» Dear Ratcliffe Cousins, I enclose a copy of a telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding flights of private aircraft over the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms, 2. With regard to paragraph 3 of the telegram, I should explain that in 1933 a decision was taken that private flyers, whether British or foreign, should be excluded from the Arab coast air route generally, and the Sheikhs of Bahrain-and Koweit were prevailed upon to address to the Political Agents letters saying that they did not wish any private aircraft to fly^ over or land in their territories. Conditions have, however, now changed somewhat, owing to the improvement in aircraft and in conditions on the Arab coast generally, and you will see that, the Political Resident now sees no strong objection to these flights being permitted. 3. We should accordingly be glad to have your vievs on the reply to be sent to the Political Resident. If it is decided to permit flights in future it will be necessary to arrange for intending flyers to be informed of the passport and visa requirements. Incidentally, with regard to paragraph 2 of the Political Resident's telegram, I am not clear how Baghdad and Tehran come in on the question of granting permission for aircraft to land at Bahrain and Sharjah. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Cheetham at the Foreign Office, and to Warran at the Air Ministry. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) F.A.K.Karrison. E. Ratcliffe Cousins, Esq Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, W.C.2.MINISTRY OF CIVIL AVIATION ARIEL HOUSE, STRAND, LONDON, V.C.2. Ext.5938/4C. 29th August, 1946 Dear Harrison c dx iicix x x. o A/i J. ^ ^ 37 ^Flease refer to your letter Ext.55^8/46 of the 15th August, v/ith which you enclose a copy of a telegram^from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject of flights by private aircraft over the Trueial Sheikhdoms. Private 'flights are increasing in numbers and are likely to increase even more in the future. We are trying to free the private flier from unnecessary restrictions and to establish freedom of innocent passage subject only to prior notification v/here this is required. written by the Sheikhs at our request there would probably be no difficulty in getting them to withdraw them, and in our view this would be desirable. We are entirely in favour of the suggestion in paragraph 4 of the Political Resident’s telegram which fits in with the system we are trying to establish. We already notify our Civil Attache in Cairo of these flights and he has arrangements for notifying the Governments to which he is accredited. If you wish, we could arrange that in respect of future flights a simultaneous notification containing all relevant particulars is sent telegraphically to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. If we could be notified of any requirements in the shape of visas and passports, v/e will arrange that these are brought to the notice of intending fliers, and that they are armed with the necessary documents before they start. I have not been able to trace-the papers regarding Ogden, but in regard to John Dyer, it seems that notification was sent to.our Civil Air Attache, Cairo, and the Govern ment of India, and since Jask was included in the itinerary, a notification was also sent to the Air attache, Teheran. This was a mistake and it has now been agreed that our Civil Air Attache in Cairo will be responsible for notifying all the Governments to which he is accredited. I am sending copies of this letter to Balkwill of the Foreign Office and Warren at the Air Ministry. As you say, conditions have changed since 1933 Since the letters of 1933 were apparently As regards the particular cases you mention Yours sincerely, (SGD.) E. RATCLIFFS COUSINS F.A.K.Harrison, Esq , uoq., India Office, King Charles Street London , S.W.l. NPGEXPRESS LETTER . From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/1148. Dated the 13th October, 1946 Reference your Endorsement No.826-S dated the 1st October, 1946. 2. in this Agency air facilities for land aircraft are available only in Bahrain and Sharjah. It is therefore suggested that, before the Chicago Convention comes into force, His Majesty’s Govern ment should lay down the specific route to be fol lowed in this Agency, designating Bahrain and Sharjah as the only landing places. Section 9 of Article VIII of the Interim Agreement now in force does not appear to apply to private aircraft. ATTESTED . Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE Political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS. &lt;n icEXPRESS LSTTER . prom - political Agent, Bahrain. . To - political Resident, Bahrain. No. C/1149. Dated the 13th October, 1946. o* Reference your printed Letter NO.B27-S dated the 1st October, 1946. 2. I recommend that all occupants of private air craft liable to land at Bahrain and/or Sharjah be com pelled to obtain visas for Bahrain and the rrucial Coast before they are allowed to start their journey, and that they be warned that if they fail to do this, and land without the requisite visas at either of these places they will not be permitted to proceed. The passengers and crews of commercial aircraft have already to be in possession of such visas and if the regulations are relaxed in the case of private aircraft it will be impossible to exercise any control over the movements of the aircraft and their occupants. 3. At the present time the Royal Air Force are in charge of the aerodromes at MUharraq and Sharjah, and I suggest that instructions should be issued through the Air Ministry to the Commanding Officers at each of these places, to ensure that the necessary visa and passport p requirements are fulfilled. The present system in Bahrain, vide enclosure to my printed Letter No.C/1029 dated the 12th September, 1946, is that the Royal Air Force notify the Agency, the Quarantine Medical Officer and the passport Officer whenever a private aircraft lands at Muharraq. This arrangement will suffice so long as there is only a small number of private aircraft passing through Bahrain, but when such traffic increases, as it inevitably will, it will become necessary for the Bahrain Government to appoint a separate passport officer for permanent duty at Muharraq. Sd./- H.D.H. RANGE political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . _L^' *\t for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 2^ CeJ' (hG / Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, External Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to — il ..by ^^--Mail ^ Sea Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date... The E. A. Dept., Government of India. — ■ ■■— ^— The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (22554) Wt.30365/P.153 2,000 10/42 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685-*t. 6957 / 46 . HID IA ODPICE, ' Y/HITEIIAIxL, S.D.l. October, 1946. In your letter No., 0H.850 of 29th August, you asked for information regarding passport and visa requirements for private flyers intending to proceed to the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms, 2, Bahrein, Koweit, Qatar and the Trucial Sheikhdoms (Sharjah, Debai, Has al Khairnh,- U)u Dhabi, Kalba, Umm &amp;1 Qaiv/ain and Ajman) are independent i\rab States in special treaty relations with under which the conduct of their foreign relations is entrusted to British subjects proceeding to any of these protected States must be in possession of a valid passport specially endorsed for the territory concerned, and a visa, A foe of 2s, is chargeable for the endorsement, but for the grant of a visa to a British subject no charge is made,- The visa is usually granted to male British subjects without prior reference to the authorities in the territory concerned,- 3, Foreigners other than British subjects proceeding to any of these territories must be in possession of similar travel documents, but in their case visas are granted only after reference to the local British authorities. Visa fees for foreigners vary accordingly to the nationality of the claimant concerned, // 4, ' Applications for British passport endorsements and visas are dealt with by the Passport Office, Queen Anne’s Gate Buildings, Dartmouth Street, London, 0,Y/,1. Questions connected v/ith the grant of British visas to foreign nationals resident in the U.K. are to be dealt with by the Passport Office, Foreign Nationals Department, 28, Princes Gate, London, S,d,7. E. Ratcliffe-Cousins, Esq., Ministry of Civil Aviation, Ariel House, Strand, W 0,2,.iduriifa r - . -V. - V * X k c DO *1 ' 3 - *• 5* We should be grateful if arrangements could be made as soon as possible to ensure that the notice of all intending flyers who may wish to land at aerodromes in the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms is drawn to the above regulations. It will presumably also be desirable that the aerodrome authorities at places en route should be given prior notice of such intention. Unless we insist on endorsement and visa formalities we may have someone like the Mufti of Jerusalem ! ' suddenly arriving out of the blue at Bahrein. .. taura ainoe**'*-D.O. No.C/1284. The 18th of November, 1946. Dear Belgrave, Will you please refer to my Memorandum No. c/912 dated the 18th August, 1946, to the Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force Station, Muharrai*, a copy of which was sent to you under my endorsement No. c/914 of the same date. 2. In actual fact the Royal Air Force authorities have made a practice of informing this Agency only instead of also telephoning the Quarantine Medical Officer and'the Passport Officer direct. This proce dure has proved unsatisfactory as, for obvious reasons, it is not possible for us to maintain a clerK on duty for 24 hours a day merely to record occasional tele phone messages from Muharraq. Before, however, the matter is taken up afresh with the Royal Air Force • I should be grateful if you would let me know what arrangements are at present made by Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and company, Limited, to inform the passport Officer when a ship arrives at Sitra without prior notice. I should also be grateful for similar information as to the proce dure adopted by the British Overseas Airways Corporation for informing the Passport Officer of unexpected departures from normal aircraft schedules. 3. would it be possible for your present passport establishment to maintain a 24 hour watch for telephone calls of this nature? It would not, of course, be necessary for the person concerned to keep awake provided that he remained close enough to the telephone to be awakened by the bell should it ring. vours sincerely. C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. NS.camPhaiiAL Persian Gulf Rtsidency t Bahrain* the 11th Novacber 1946. Please refer to the correspondence resting with Jones* deal-official letter fio.Lxt.6938/46 dated the 10th Septeaber 1946 to Kay regarding flights of private aircraft over the Gulf Ghaikhdoas* £• Kance 9 now acting as Political Agent Bahraln f suggests that It Is desirable thet the specific rouiti to be followed by private aircraft along the Arab Coast of the Gulf should be designated* Personally (apart from forced landings) 1 cannot Imagine anyone, other than perhaps a more than usually avid concession or notoriety hunter, wanting to land In the desert. 3. As for Bahrain, Its only landing ground Is at Uuharraq and Article 4 of the w Alr Navliatlon Regulations for Civil Aircraft” lays down that no aircraft shall use as ’’a place of landing or departure 11 any place other than the land aerodrome at Huharraq or the water aerodrome at ifanamahj this might be brought to the notice of filers on the route* 4. As you know, the only other serviceable aerodromes on the coast are at Sharjah (for M lanri M planes) and bubal (for ^ea” planes), and pending a decision as to whether these landing places are to be maintained In the future or not. It Is advisable, In my opinion, to refrain from designating them the air ports which may be used on the Trucial Coast. (SGD.) A.C.GALLONAY. E. P. bonaldson, Esquire, 0$., The India Office, JLdUBtfflfltks Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, No.974-S , the 11th November 1S46. Copy forwarded with compliments to - POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAINI [' “Yt &amp; \ o v '/n'&gt; .BAH 7 ? . / « (9%. NPG.Colonel Hay desires me to refer you to the correspondence ending with our endorsement No. 974 - S, dated the 11th November, 1946, and to inquire whether you agree that in the case of private aircraft we should insist that all passengers and members of crews have endorsements and visas for Bahrain even in the case of machines only landing for a short time here, e.g. to re-fuel. ^'Lieutenant Colonel A. C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. G.A.M. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.D« 0- No.C/1379. POLiriCAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 1946. The 14th December My dear Pelly QJU '.Vill you please refer to your demi-official letter No.1113-S dated the 4th December, 1946? 2. I do not thinic it is practicable to distinguish between private and commercial aircraft, and in any case all travellers should, I think, be governed by the terms of Article 12 of the Bahrain Air Navigation Regulations. 3. in the event of a traveller's not being in possession of the required visa he could obtain one on landing. Yours sincerely Pelly, Esq., O.B.E., I.C.3., Secretary to the •» Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain NS.© D.O .No Advisorato, Decombor 10, 1946. Reforenco your D.O.No .C/1284 dated 18th Novombor 1946, when a boat arrives at Sitra Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., inform the Director of Customs by telephone or they inform the customs and passport officials who are on duty on the pier. BOAC communicates with the Director of Customs who sends information to the clerks who are concerned. I have now arranged for a telephone to be installed in the gate office of the pier clerk close to the passport office, at the customs entrance, where there is always a watchmen on duty. Ee can get into touch with the passport and customs cl'*' 1 '” Confidential Liout. Colonel A.C. Galloway, 0.B.I5 H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.Ko. C/1400. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 17th December, 1346. To The Officer Commanding, H.A.K. Station, Bahrain. Heference my memoranduia No. C/912 dated the 18th August, 1946 to The Officer Corar^anding, K.A.F. Station, Bahrain. 2. In future to avoid unnecessary delay will you kindly arrange to inform the Passport and Customs authorities direct, by ringing up Manama No 64. 3. Arrangements have been made by the Bahrain Govern ment for a 24 hour watch to be kept by this telephone. The Clerk on duty there will inform the other authorities concerned on receipt of your message, and in future it will therefore no longer be necessary for you to telephone either the Agency or the Quarantine Medical Officer direct. (SGD) A.C.OALLOfAX. Political Agent, Bahrain. ti. V . M. k/'- — Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to «• The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, for information, The Quarantine Medical Officer ft I for necessary action, A.J.SNo. //‘f-1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Muharram 27, 1366 December 21, 1946. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - Reference your memorandum No. C/1400 dated 17th December 1946, para 2, addressed to the Officer Commanding, R.A.F. Station, Bahrain. The Number of the telephone is 120 M and not 64. Adviser to the Government. S.Z CoTifirbzitial. BAH r ' R-’OEIPT.URGENT , POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. The 24th December, 1946. The Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force Station, Bahrain. No. c/1424. Memorandum. Reference my Memorandum No.c/1400 dated the 17th December, 1946, paragraph two. 2. The number of the telephone is Manama 120 and not repeat not 64. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . Ufi' for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain with reference to his Memo. No.189-31/15 dated 21.12. »46. The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. The passport Officer, Bahrain.( 2 ) l5 ^' cCt' ~x6. ^t. L Please see X*L. from P.R. at s*l6. We have never asked Tmcial Shaikhs or Shaikh of Qatar if they had any objection to private aviators. They have accorded certain rights to foreign aircraft and they would seem to hold good for all foreign air craft, State, passenger, and private. Position in regard to British aircraft is nebulous. Dubai Air Agreement is for air craft of Imperial Airways (now B.O.A.G.). Sharjah Agreement was also made for I.A# but speaks in its preamble of desire to have an air station at Sharjah 'at which British aeroplanes can land'. There were .also a number of air agreements made with other Trucial Shaikhs to provide air facilities for the R.A.F., e.g. the Kalba Air Agreement at page 24 of 7/2-V. This provides air facilities for (undesignated; aircraft at Kalba. In so far as British civilian aircraft other than B.O.A.G. craft can make use of air facilities provided under these agreements then British private aviators can make use of them. There would seem however to be no means of controlling the flights and landings of private aircraft except at Bahrain where they are bound by air navigation regulations. P.R# is of opinion that conformity with visa and passport regulations would be sufficient check for flights along Arab coast. In practice, with R.A.F. in charge at Sharjah (and Muharraq) it is uncertain whether passports and visas are examined or even whether landing fees are .collected. In fact, according to Sharjah Air Agreement landing fees are only to be collected from 'commercial aircraft'. In this connection it is pointed out that owing to the use of the various terms 'aircraft', 'airktae'| Hair service', etc in the Chicago Air Agreements (see Definitions at page 28 of pamphlet) some of the sections would not seem to apfily to private aircraft, e.g. section 4 of Art. VIII of the Interim Agreement seems to apply and section 9 ibid not# P.A. . t~ A - 2/10/46. pA sdu&gt; \° *2 hrL r; if ^ % rro-u(, ^ rie-i. Pp’ $ /. [c C[( P- /?., s.27 . It is suggested that lack of air facilitips (and political considerations) make it advisable that all aircraft, including private aircraft, flying over territory in this Agency should follow specific route, vide Art. 5 of Convention, and that they should land only at, Bahrain and Sharjah aerodromes, which are the only places where jhasspBrts and visas could be examined (cf. Art. 10 of Convention). P.T.O./ 13/21. s.28. May recommend that all occupants of a private aircraft which lands at Bahrain or Sharjah must be in possession of visas for Bahrain or the Trucial Coast before they will be permitted to leave the aerodrome at these two places, as is required of passengers and crew in commercial aircraft. May also recommend that in view of difficulty experineced in getting H.A.F. at Sharjah and Iwuharraq to undertake examination and control of civil aircraft we should take up question of passport and visa arrangements with them at higher level than Os.C., B.A.F., Bahrain and Sharjah. In this connection please n/para 14 and correspondence ending with s.18 of F.13/2. : * ' ‘ * — . . It is understood that from December of this year B.O.A.C. are taking off 'C' class flying boats from their air services and replacing them with Tudor land planes, which will alight at Muharraq. In that event they will become responsible for all civilian aircraft using the aerodrome, and may be asked to adopt same procedure with regard to private aircraft landing at Muharraq as was specified in our letter to O.C., R.A.F. at s.13 - a copy of which may be sent to Station- Manager when B.O.A.C. move to Muharraq. fLtl« . 10/10/46. 6u SKA -n £ f lAA ^ dauL • ^ eJb I fcr k’ ' - 1 ti (Jr *JLa K*\ c ' fyk/</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/525</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/525</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 13/21 Flights by private aircraft in Persian Gulf’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-14T00:02:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (54 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 51-55) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-50; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to the use by private aircraft of aerodromes along the Arab coast of the Gulf, chiefly of the RAF aerodrome at Muhurraq, Bahrain, but also the RAF base at Sharjah. The principal correspondents in the file are the Acting Political Agent in Bahrain, Captain Huge Dunstan Rance, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Lieutenant-Colonel Arnold Crawshaw Galloway, the Air Traffic Officer at RAF Bahrain, Flight-Lieutenant M S Scotney, and officials from the India Office and Foreign Office.The correspondence is in response to the arrival of an increasing number of private aircraft at Bahrain, most travelling from England to Australia, raising questions of: how best to ensure that the visas and passports for passengers and pilots are being adequately checked; whether private flights arriving at Bahrain are covered by the existing Air Navigation Regulations for Bahrain; and whether additional approval for private flights should be sought from the ruler of Bahrain. Included in the file is a letter from Rance to the RAF Commanding Officer (ff 18-19), with a list of the particulars of private flights required by the Political Agency, Bahrain Government and Quarantine Medical Officer, and a letter from Sheikh Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah, ruler of Bahrain (f 32), stating that he has no objection to private aviators landing at Bahrain, provided they possess the proper passports and visas. Later correspondence in the file concerns the means by which RAF officials communicate to the Agency, Government and Quarantine Officer on the arrival of private aircraft at Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>RAF Muharraq, Air Traffic Control Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Muharraq Aerodrome</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Visas</topic></subject><subject><topic>Passports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Quarantine</topic></subject><subject><topic>Private planes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00033c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>