<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00030f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T12:56:13.999Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Bri-tish. Residency and C^nsulate-aeneral, Bush ire, i'e\ (3 'ebruaxy IP'll, / Please see your diary for the week ending January 27,1911, last, part, of paragraph No,30, It is not quite clear what the object is or what the effect will be of the certificate from the Ruler of Bahrein mentioned in that paragraph. Colonel Cox asks me to say that if the report is confirmed he will be glad to have full details on the subject especially as to ivhether the cer-blficate in question Is Intended to exempt the Dearer from paying any duty or whether he will pay more or less than the usual IKS,' also how the duty levied will compare with that on goods arriving from Busreh or other Turkish ports. MM /V Major S.G. Knox, C.I.S., Political Agent, B a h r e in. V l / i -1Political A'^oncy IpJiraln, 36t/h. lay 1911. x Beler-moo co^espondonco ondin^ \;ith Major Knox's D # 0 # dated 13th February 1911 to you regarding the i3sue of s pecial Ebcpoirt Oertifioates by the BahrajLv- Customs authorities for ^^ods shipped irom here to Oatif and Oqair# llajor Knox talked to Sheikh Isa bin Ali on the subject in the end of ilarch and also addressed him a letter inviting him to nake enquiries and lumish precise inlomation. I have only now received the Sheikh 1 s an^er ol I enclose a copy. You vd.ll see that he excuses hinself fron supplying lAlomation and merely states that he has discontinued the issue ol these certificates. I presume this nay be taken as laying the question to rest; unless it should appear that they rare bein^ issued again. Captain L.Birdwood^I.A. # First Assistant resident, }\is}iire.Trasnalation of a letter dated the 3th Janadl al A./wal 13^9 (8th 'lay 1911) from Sheikh Isa bin Ali Al Khali fa Chief of .Bahrain to Captain T),L.R.Loromer # Political A^ent, Bahrain# After Compliments, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Ma^or Knox's letter No:4b6 dated the 7th Rabi ath ^ ' ;T hani 1339 (8th April 1911) stating therein that Colonel Cok Political Resident and Consul General in the Persian 'Mxlf aiid Major Knox are interested in the mat er of the Certificates issued by my Customs olficials to people vfho export floods from Bahrain to Qatif and Oqair. I should be ^lad to ^ive them information on the subject but doubt has cropped up in ny mind in regard to this matter, ^hoiirr* I had '?iven orders lor the Cert.il icates to be issued so that the Customs officials of those places miqht also issue cert..iiicates for ^oods exported to Bahrain and had no in tention in doinq so except to regularize the Customs. Hit as this procedure is open to misunderstanding I have aban doned the expedient in order to avoid suspicion. True Translation. / *7 Captain, Poli-tical A^ent^ataram./3 - July 1911. Please see your demi-official letter of 26th Llay to Birdwood, regarding the special export certificates issued by the Customs at Bahrein at the request of the ivatif Authorities, for goods shipped to Katif and Ojair. Wo exception was taken to the issue of the certi- ficates^ what was needed was information as to what the object and bearing of them was; and the fact that they have ceased to issue does not supply this. Please explain to Shoikh Ssa if you nave an op portunity, that the certificates may possibly be quite innocuous and useful for all 1 know, but until we un derstand ohat the bearing of them is or was we can ex press no opinion. Your Captain D.L.R.Lorimer, Political Agent, Bahrein. / 1 L^\ — ^ ' ' ^ ^ V; •?Your Diary entry for the week ending 27th January 1911, said 'SVith regard to importo from Bahrein the consignees will be required to produce a certificate from the Ruler of Bahrein to enable the Customs Of- ticials to distinguish them from the imports from Basra and other places'. What was the result of their being so 'dis tinguished' ? It may be that Bahrein is being treated as xurkish territory and no duty charged; ' or it may be that orders in that sense have been issued by the Porte but that the local authorities though showing the goods as exempt on their accounts really levy the duty and pocket it. As at present advised I am disinclined to believe in any case that 22% is charged to any body. It is noted too that the certificate issued by Laaharaj does not specify whether the goods are the produce of Bahrein or elsewhere. ^ith the regular inter-communica tion which goes on between Katif and Bahrein there should be no great difficulty, I think, in getting tof n (/x v &lt;AeJz~ I be^ a^ain to address yon on the subject ol the issue of op.r^o certilicates to boats proceeding to Turkish ports on the mini and, vide 3 r our 0.0. dated 13th July 1911. Further enquiries Irrn people of Oqair tend to show that in no case is 32# Custom Outy charged by the Hustons Authorities there. Ifo dn^j at all is c xarged on specific products of Bahrain,\Yhich are allowed in duty free as in the case of ^oods cordng from 'Turkish ports. Such pro ducts are fetr and unniportant e.g. shrimps, lucerne sond^ etc.. On ^oods of noa-Bahrain origin 11 % duty is charged. vta n any boat readies Oqair or Qatif it has to report 1 irst to the Anir ral Balir, \/ho exacts a fee of Fs.l per boat, after which he allovrs the oar'^o to be landed. At the sane tine he enters in his books details o^ the cargo. V /hen the Ilakhuda can present him with a car^o certificate from the port from which he comes this is accepted and time and trouble are sa^ed. Otier\/ise the Atoir al '-air has the cargo sorted out, in order to obtain the necessary inicreation, before he releases it. Colonel P.^.Cox, C.^.I., C.I.&gt;1., Political Resident in the Persian r ulf, Bushire. It ^ /vl -(3 1% is st/at,ocl that, boats brin^ sncn, cortifi- cates Iron all other ports, Basra, Bus hi re etc. As Bahrain products - o ^e very few there is little actual rli ■ f ioult3 r in distin^iishlng them from ^oocls of lorei^n ori gin, onc^ the - ar^o is 3ho\m up, I have had a conversation with MaharaJ the lied of 1 he Hustons, 'lose information confix^is the r above account. lie said,howwer,that no complaints of illtreatment had reached lin fron masters of ships ?inco tJie issue of the certificates was stopped sone 3 months a^o. In those circumstances I expressed tlie opinion that it wo\ild be best to - let things remain in statu quo, but I asicod him S to inlorm me immediately should any comprint reach A .him. As regards what yon remark that tahara^j 1 s cor- tilicates did not show the country of o^i^in, laharaj explains that Bahrain products are so lew and so well kno .Ti, that the mere list oi i he car^o » furnished by him rras sufficient and no disputes a^ose as to .:hich vrore nnd /hich were not• Baixrain products. 'Hiis seems probable. « I hpxl spoken to ^iieikh Isa once or twice recoil ly on. the subject, and he promised as be!ore to m-ke enquiries,but up to the present I have heard nothing from him.NO. lUfof 1911. British Residency and Consulate-General. Butihire, October 1911. To The Political A b ent, Bahrein. Sir, With reference to item 30 ox* your Diary for the week ending 27tli January 1911 and subsequent cor'-'. spon .ence, I have the honour to forward, for your information, a copy of dressed to the Government of India, drawing attention lo uhe fact that the Turkish Authorities are treating Bahrein Gus- toms matters as if it were Ottoman territory. You mi^ht take an opportunity of explaining to Sheikh Ssa that investigation has placed this fact beyond .loubt, anu that he will no doubt concur as to the inexpediency of playing into their hands in any way. ] } a letter which I have ad- I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Liout-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.I I Ho of 1911. From liritish Jief?l enoy and Consulate-» iiuahire, /4 October 1911 • Liout-uolonel P. Z. 'Jox, C,h.I., C.i.a.., Political Heaident in the Persian Gulf. •I'he Hon 'tola Lieut-Oolonsl Sir Henry iioiiahon, i&gt;. 0. I. S., 0. S. I., Seoretftry to tha i..ovsrnE!ant of India In the Foreign Ijepartnant, Simla. I have tlie honour to lay the following before the Uo- vernmant of India for euoh action aa nay aeera called for. 2. In the nonthly Diary of this ..-eaidency for January 1)11, it was reported in paragraph iy(a}, (b) and (o) that the Ouatoiaa Offioiala newly appointed by the L'uriilah uovarn- ment at Ojalr and -.atif had required the oonsigneaB of goods from Bahrein to produce a Oartlfioata from the xiuler of Bah rain to the eifect that they had been ao exported from Bah- rein. Th.^ Issue ox such a oertificite being regarded v/ith ous- piCion, the Political Agett was directed to furnish further details, ne made enquiries fron Sheiiih dlsa who evidently aid not understand the purpose or effect of the Certificates but replied that thinking that it was an ordinary Customs foriuality he Had authorised his Customs Superintendent to give tiie Certificate asiied for by the ^atif Customs, but that ac our interest in the matter sho/zed that the practice was of doubtful expediency he had discontinued it. 3. Further enquiries by the Political Agent elicited the fact ■fact that no duty at all wau baln^ charged on products of Laiirsin origin, such as lucorna ato., .li-ich ./are allowed free 'as in the case of goods coming from Jur^ish ports', but that on goods of non-Bahrein origin 11;,o duty .yas balng levied. - -aiquiries .vere then aiade from iiis majesty's Consul Busreh as to v/hether local produco, such as lucerne, prawns, etc., cf foreign origin -vsre adsittad into iiuoreh -md other Tur- iLibh ports duty free, he no* r jpliaa that 'on lucerne, shrimps '(prawns) and such produce of rorui^n origin a 'Justoms duty of Busreh Uonsulata ^0.^4, dcttod} tt 4 . ^ ^ btliOctober 1911. I 11/o ia if such pro- 'duce is accompanied by a certificite of origin, in the ab- 'aonce of a certificate or origin, an additional charge of '2o;4 is levied by the Public i^ebt Adiainistration'. I may mention tha A , according to Information received from otiier aou-^aa®, i . id not au additional ob irge of 26^ that is levied but a duty of instead of 11 /c. That how ever is u aatail with which we are not at present concerned. 4. uij up^iot of tiie foregoiiig is that Turkish Author ities in the levy of Oustoms duty are treating oahrein as TruK-ish territory, and that the Juitoms either from ignorance or oomplaoency have been playing into their hands by accepting favoured treatment .i&gt;; a j . -r^ish port. 5. The position, novr th^.t it is fully understood, Till be explained to ShoiKh isa, and he ^ill, no doubt, confirm his instructions for the abandonment of the practice of issuing certif.1 oates, but I think it advisable to draw the attention of Government to the proceedcf tha Jvatif Customs as af fording fresh evidence of the persintent prrterfelona of the ^orte in regard to the Bahrein Islands. I hrtva the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. (sd) P. Z. Cox Lieut-Colonel,^ Political iiesiaent in the Persian Gulf.Np. 7/^ ot laU. Political Agonoy, Baarain, Octooer 26Uu From Captain D« L« R. Lorlmar, I .A. r&gt; olltlcal Agent f Bahrain. To Colonel YJ » Cox, C«S*1« 9 C#!®^* Political Ptalaent ana Conaul General, Persian Gulf, B T J S H I P. $ • Sir, In repyl to your letter No. 2668, aated tne 14un. Ootooer, Xyll # reierring to tne la^ue py tne Baxxraln Customs or oertlrlcates lor presentation to tiie Customs Authorities etc., I ha/e the honour to say that I have ♦jpoicen to Shexh Isa In the sense or the concluding sentence or your letter. He replleu that he qalte unaerotooa the situation ana tnat cw haa someiliao ago Issued orders prohibiting the issue or such certllicates, ana that this oreer was, ana vould remain, in roroe. Tnat the order is actually in icrco, is supported a statement made to me recently by the Heaa or the Customs. I have ihe honour to oe f Sir, Your most obealent servant. I Captain I.A. Political Agent, Bahrain.Britisj. Residency and Consul ate-General', Buslilre, 23oli September 1911. Cbe&amp;yr / Please see your diary entry Ko• 168, dated otii Septem ber 1911, regarding the Katar Customs. colonel Cox would be glad IT you would report at once If you should hear anything more of the matter. p- //• l( ro Ln^u. r/ A^yoW Captaln D.L.R. Lorimer, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrein. i y ^ /cr^ &amp; — 7&gt;fA &lt;)t 3a m. i3.FEB.1912 } [ * &lt; v« ^J.V No. 2667, dated Busliire, the 14tli (received 2.3rd) October 1911 (Confidential). From —L ieutenant -C olonel P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Reiident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to lay the following before the Government of India • for such action as may seem called for. 2. In the monthly diary of this Residency for January 1911, it was reported in paragraph 19(a), {b) and {c) that the Customs officials newly appointed by the Turkish Government at Ojair and Katif had required the consignees of goods from Bahrein to produce a certificate from the Ruler of ^ Bahrein to the effect that ikej had been so exported from Bahrein. The issue of such a certificate being regarded with suspicion, the Political Agent was directed to furnish further details. He made enquiries from Sheikh Esa who evidently did not understand the purpose or effect of the certificates, but replied that thinking that it was an ordinary Customs formality he had authorised his Customs Superintendent to give the Certificate asked for by the Katif Customs, but that as our interest in the matter showed that the practice was of doubtful expediency he had discontinued it. 3. Purther enquiries by the Political Agent elicited the fact that no duty at all was being charged on products of Bahrein origin, such as lucerne, etc., which were allowed free ' as in the case of goods coming from Turkish ports,' but that on goods of non-Bahrein origin 11 per cent, duty was being levied. Enquiries were then made from His Majesty's Consul, Basrah, as to whether local produce, such as lucerne, prawns, etc., of foreign origin were admitted into Basrah and other Turkish ports duty free. He now replies that ' on lucerne, shrimps (prawns)and such produce of foreign a Customs duty Basrah Consulate No. 24, dated the 5th October of 11 per CCnt. is levied, if SUcll produce 19lL is accompanied by a certificate of origin. In the absence of a certificate of origin, an additional charge of 25 per cent, is levied by the Public Debt Administration.' I may mention that according to information received from other sources, it is not an additional charge of 25 per cent, that is levied but a duty of 22 per cent, instead of 11 per cent. That however is a detail with which we are not at present concerned. 4. The upshot of the foregoing is that the Turkish authorities in the levy of Customs duty are treating Bahrein as Turkish territory, and that the Sheikh's Customs either from ignorance or complacency have been playing into their hands by accepting favoured treatment as a Turkish port. 5. The position, now that it is fully understood, will be explained to Sheikh Esa, and he will, no doubt, confirm his instructions for the abandonment of the practice of issuing certificates, but I think it advisable to draw the attention of Government to the proceedings of the Katif Customs as affording fresh evidence of the persistent pretensions of the Porte in regard to the Bahrein Islands. ?554 F. D.—S E—429-431—Deci</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00030f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/48</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00030f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/48</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File H/14 Vol I Turkish Customs on Mainland'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1911/1912</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-21T00:00:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: Foliation starts on file cover and terminates on the final folio before the back cover. Foliation is in pencil in circled numbers in top right of recto.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between Stuart George Knox and David Lockhart Robertson Lorimer, British Political Agents at Bahrain, and Percy Zachariah Cox and Richard Lockington Birdwood of the British Political Residency in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, as well as with Sheikh ‘Īsā bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah, ruler of Bahrain. In addition, included within the file are office notes of various conversations between the Political Agent with the ruler of Bahrain and Seth Rao Sahib Tirathdas Maharaj, Director of Customs at Bahrain.The correspondence and notes concern Turkish customs regulations at the Eastern Arabian ports of al-Qaṭīf and al-‘Uqayr pertaining to the landing and levying of duty on Bahraini and non-Bahraini goods, and the system of issuing cargo certificates. Included in this file are two examples of stamped cargo certificates in Arabic (f. 6 and f. 7).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Al-Qatif</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Al-ʻUqayr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00030f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>