<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00015b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T14:16:56.450Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/t J P.Z.994/35. INDIA OFFICS. Conllderitial. NOTE OF CONVIrt■14.1 ION '.VIiK IAJOP ??Ai\K HOL^S. Mijor Holmes came to see me on Wednesday, 6th February and explained that he had done so because he had now had a private lette~ from the Sheikh of Koweit in which the Sheikh intimated that he was desirous of appointing him (M*jor Holmes) as his representative in London under the terms of the Kuwait Oil Concession. Major Holmes said that he thought it desirable to let us know at once. The sheikh’s action was somewhat of a surprise to him as never at any stage had any conversation taken place between him and the sheikh as to the filling of this post. He trusted that H#M # G. would see no objection to his appointment to it. I said that the sheikh would no doubt notify the Company in due course and that we should hear from them officially of the name which he wished to put fonward for this post. I did not think that Major Holmes need anticipate difficulty with H.M,G. if his name was put forward. /The agreement, in fact, gives us no control over the filling of the post/. 3* M&amp;jor Holmes, in the course of somewhat discursive conversation, made the following points;- (a) Koweit Neutral Zone . He thought this was dehnitely a valuable area from the oil standpoint and ; while no-hcd now no share or part-in any negotiations which might be goin 6 on about, the Neutral Zone aha had declined to involve himself in them, he -t/buld much welcome a chance of securing a concession for British interests himself. He had had sane discussion since his return from Koweit with the Afubian LMvelopment syndicate. Mr. Ydlibi was in his view a * mo st/( 2 ) . 2 - most unsatisfactory person to work witti and he did not think that the syndicate need take him too seriously. He had in fact, in the course of discussions with them since his return, advised them to cut their losses and abandon their efforts to secure the concession. (b) Despite the unfavourable opinions which had been expressed in the past, he definitely considered that there was a good prospect of valuable oil in Koweit itself, as regards both Koweit and the Neutral zone we had probably noticed that the Rasa Oil Company’s employees were working very near to the borders. (c) The oil in Bahrein was of the highest quality and the field a very valuable one. (d) Water in Koweit . Major Holmes having made some reference to his boring of wells in Koweit, I asked him what the position was as regards water. /The point is, of course, one of much importance, since at present the Koweit water appears to a large extent to be drawn from Iraq - a fact which places a valuable weapon in the hands of the Ir&amp;q Government should they wish to bring pressure to bear on Koweit/. Major Holmes said that it was a point in which he had been closely interested. He thought that there was almost certainly water down on the border of Koweit and the Neutral zone and that it was very probable that there was water on or close to Failakia Island. He had noticed a fresh water ooze in the sea and had actually tested it. When, however, he had suggested to the sheikh that he (Major Holmes) might put down a bore hole, the sheikh, who could be extremely obstinate and tended to react negatively to any proposition put to him, had not pursued the matter. J*G» LAITHWAITE. 11th February 1935.— * ~ ■ ■ Iv Ojh+d &gt; flo i ' OoiLpiciints against Fersia in repeat oX •DHow Incidunts* In Persian Gulf. Dhow belonging to Koweiti subject of Persian extraction with cargo of sugar and groceries properly manifested for P&amp;o seized in uhatt-el*Arab (almost cer tainly in Iraq waters) by Persian Customs on 6th December 1932 f on suspicion of smuggling; crew of 4 detained for 9 days without food except their own cargo; Captain, a Koweltl Arab, kept for trial; stated by Persian minister for Foreign Affairs on £lst December 193D to nave confessed himself guilty of smuggling ana to have been condemned to a month 1 ** Imprisonment and payment of &amp; fine; later stated by Persian M*P*A* on 31st lay 1934 to have appealed against this judgment; ahow still detained in spite of repeated representations by H*M« Legation, the last of which was on dth June 1934 (P.S.4479/34). Koweiti bum arrested early in April 1933 by Persian warship * about 4 miles «tff hen Jam, for m icbsh« was making In naavy aaa to mana ner sails, ana taken forcibly to BandfU* Abbas before being released; Oiiffiage cone to bum variously estimated from He. 400 to its. 400; very unsatisfactory answer received from Persians last October In reply to representations of His loajesty's Charge d*Affaires, Tehran (F.Z.8156/33); no further action subsequently taken. Large Koweltl ahow forcibly inspected on 41st kay 1933, by Persian gunboat off Busnlre (probably not In Persian waters) on pretext of searching for opium; •.aster of -now tisultsd; very unsatisfactory ruU rectivi last October from Persians in reply to our protest at Tehran (p.z.7748/33) and no action subsequently taken. -(5) v jr** r fO r j / a f' .. • ^ ctV A ^ / ^ fxiX^^ 'iji.C,’-* ♦ f ( fi ) ^/V Persian araea launcii ancliorea wito captured (Persian) utoow on iiitn June 1953 t in Muscat terriLor^ai waters, near Kh&amp;sab, ana is su^ected oi navin^ used j^^usctit waters as a base for its activities* Persian reply (October 19o3) to protest frade bt Tenran jn Pedal; ol ivuscat aenied tdat any xersian wared ip or Guatoius ic&lt;,uncn was near Kiiaeab on tde date caentioned; no reply yet received to subsequent note oi olst &amp;arch 1934 irorn H # M« minister to Persiazi M#P.A. questioninc; statement oi latter that the suspected launch was at Bandar Abbas on the date oi the incident* Kowelt water dhow held up near Gusb&amp;h in BhaV el-A1?ub by Persian river police patrol on or about 23rd I August, 1933; crew beaten and robbea; Persian itaiz-!• wiich took prompt proceedings against two of culprits; Tehran negation was therefore authorised m Noveiiher 1933 to ask for punishment of guilty anu return of stolen goods but not to demana compensation (P.'’.7883/3: y. no lurtfier record of action tasen. Jollyboat belonging to Trucial Oman boarded on 10th September 1933* ana subjected to searcn lasting fo hull an hour by Persian warship 'BA3H* which steamed of on approach of H.M.S* ; no reply has ever apparently been received to the protest made on 13th October 1933 by H.k. Charge d'Affaires to the Persian Government (P.Z.7289/33).ii j&gt;ia omajs. il i -HALL, S.V.I. 18th Au u t, 19 54* &amp;,y d«ar WarR«r f of 17th Wot ©nib er last and com acted correspondence (Foreign Office reference ti.tilfyt/lhZA/Stl) about rn maeeult by Feraian rirer police on e Kuwaiti enter dhow in the 3hatt-el~Arab. we do rot appear to hare hc*rd the result of the representations made by Xallett te the Persian uuthoritlee* If you see r.e objection, we should be grateful if you could, at your convenience, as* Tehran how the matter ets&amp;de and whether it hsa been S'tisffcctorily disposed of* Yours ever, GILBERT LAITHWAITE, C* ?• A* Warner, Esq* , Foreign Office* 3.W.I.- - ■ — ■ —© P.z.7022/33. V Draft Paper. political Department. '-'s The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. Was. Tel India, dated 26th October 1933. Telegram from Political Resident, dated 28th October 1933. Telegram from Government of India, dated 31st October 1933. / / Sir, In reply to Foreign Office letter No.E. 6106/1524/91 of 18th October 1933 on the subject of the assault a Koweiti water boat by a Persian river patrol-vessel in the Shatt-el-Arab, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the telegraphic correspondence noted in the margin with the Government of India and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, copies of which were sent to the Foreign Office under cover of India Office printed letters Nos.P.Z. 6704/33, 6916/33 and 7022/33, dated respectively 28th October, 30th October and 31st October /v. r. 1933. ^ Taking -int o considerati on ■ the- 4* view r* ix f prcoWd -by r -f* ■by tho ' G overnmont -ef- 1925 5000 G.33 i* (XL X U* (*+~*~*s *-*—3 (a{ Ha. India and the Political Resident, Sir Samuel Hoare agrees that it might be inexpedient to demand compensation from the Persian Government and he accordingly concurs in the proposal of Sir John Simon in paragraph 2 of your letter under reference. ^ In connection with this incident X am to refer to para.9 of the letter from the Political Agent at Koweit dated 6th September/ a copy of which was forwarded with Ind'ta Office printed .letter N o. P. Z. 6345/33\f 6th October 1933 and to say that, while recognising thatI the matter islprimarily one for the consideration \of the Iraqi Government itself, the Secretary of State would be interested to receive the views of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs as to the right of the Persian Government to maiptain armed police in the Iraqi waters \of the Shatt-el-Arab , and to be advised Whether, in Sir John \ Simon’s view, the Iraqi Government would be justified in making a protest to the Persian Government against an incident such as the present, as constituting a violation of Iraqi sovereignty. 3 A copy of this letter is being sent to the Admiralty. &lt;*U J. C. WALTON.'A\r&gt; U (C 7022 1933 /)v-^ /v CWP/EM (14 groups) 5830 ,L, ]j„ a p^j From Government of India. Foreign (COPIES and Political Department, to CIRCULATED) Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 31st October, 1933. Received 31st October, 1933, 11.30 a.m. . X 2576. Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Bushire. Bushire telegram of 28th October, 969. Assault on Kuwaiti water dhow. We agree with the Political Resident. w ■■■Notes. Register No. P. z. Minute Paper. 6345/33 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee • « Robbery of a Koweit Water Dhow in the Shattrel-Arab by Persian River Police and maltreatment Under Secretary of Nakhodjf and crew. Secretary of State... Copy of to FOR INFORMATION This is the incident reported in Political Residents telegraija of 14th September (P.Z.5805/33) and it is the fourth case within eight months of inter- ference by Persian Customs Officials^rith Koweiti Dhows. This particular incident, however, presents somewhat special features since it appears to have been a pure case of piracy by irresponsible petty officials. It is at least satisfactory that the Persian Rais-i-Amnieh at Gusbah took inmediate steps to arrest and deal with one of the Previous Papers - culprits when he was informed of the incident and it appears that the stolen goods are being returned to their owners. 4407 r 1000 3.30 1 Nevertheless/Nevertheless the Political Agent considers that a demand for compensation should be made of the Persian Governnent in view of the moral and physical hurt suffered by the innocent crew of — the Koweiti Dhow* /Colonel Dickson also suggests that the Political Resident should write to H.M* Ambassador at Baghdad and lodge a complaint regarding the s^irEreatment accorded to the fleaBeywwwi ofl m Koweitis by the Iraqi Police Inspector at Fao when the former called * upon him to report the incident* Colonel Dickson points out that this official is the person upon whom the Sheikh of Koweit is relying to support his land agent and strengthen his authority among Nt/— his recalcitrant Fao fellaheen. /With regard to the point raised in para. 9 of the Political Agent 1 s letter regarding the maintenance by the Persian Government of River Police in the Iraqi Waters of the Shatt-el-Arab, the Persians would no doubt contend that these are necessary for the prevention of smuggling into Persia, but it certainly seems desirable that their right to maintain armed forces in the territorial water of another state should be carefully considered. This is of course a matter primarily for the Iraqi Government itself. / The Political Resident states in his telegram of 14th September that he is making enquiries regarding the incident, but we have not yet had his report. Meanwhile no action seems necessary at this end.A In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. E 6106/1524/91. and address— not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secrctary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. i ^ o 3 Sir, With reference to India Office letter No. P.Z. 6345/33 of the 6th October, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you, to be laid before Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare, the accompanying copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Charg£ d T Affaires at Tehran on the subject of the reported assault, by a Persian river patrol-vessel, on a Koweiti water-boat in the Shatt- el-Arab, and the theft of certain property, food etc. from the nakhuda and the crew. 2. Sir John Simon shares Mr* Mallet's views regarding the inexpediency of demanding compensation, and he proposes, subject to the concurrence of Sir Samuel Hoare, to authorise Mr. Mallet by telegram to address the Persian Government in the manner which he has suggested and to restrict his representations to asking for the punishment of the culprits and the return- of the stolen property (or its equivalent - since part of it seems to have been food)• 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Admiralty* I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office(3 JL\ » P7Q4 1 NO DISTRIBUTION. Decode, hr. Mallet 1933 . D, 3.50 p.m. 12th October, 1933. R. 9.00 p.m. 12th October, 1933. No. 260. (R). Bushire despatch U/69 of 16th September to India Office. | As chief of gendarmerie seems to have behaved well H I deprecate asking for compensation which would never he paid unless we exerted extreme pressure. I suggest I should ask for punishment of the culprits mid return of the goods said to have been taken to Mohanmerah (see last enclosure in Eushire despatch C.89 to India Office). Addressed to Foreign Office No. 260, repeated to Government of India No. 98, Bushire No. HC.CONFIDENTIAL. J ' No.C/89 of 1933. to 'ij . 1. His Majesty's Secretary of S^ite for India. London, The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to —• for India, London 2* The Foreign Secretary to the Grovernment of India, Simla. 3. His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires/Tehran. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, H.M.S.Shoreham, Henjam. TfOFWILR®, 1 &lt;*\ Dated A^iU..i3SBJigWt).9X...l.?3S., 5.1 . /CW Reference to previous correspondence : ^/Political Resident’s telegram No.T/43 dated the 14th September 1933. Description of Enclosure. * Name and Date. Letter No.208 dated the 6th September 1933 from the lolitical Agent, Kuwait. Subject. Hold up of a Kuwait water dhow in the Shatt al Arab by a Persian River Police Patrol,and the mal treatment of the Nafehuda and crew.from what the halkh tolls a* f it was a sass of oannoa plrsegr tm th® part of two regular i’arslsn Hiwor foil so offloials 9 assisted by two of their men and two boatmen (ballamhls) obYloualy in league with them* 4. hat robbery pure and stetple, was the intention* may* 1 think* be assumed from the ivoatents of 1(e) shore* which* if true* shows that the ^ais«»i^ anleb at Gusbah took imcdiate steps to arrest and deal with one of the culprits cm the representation of ohnaed al aciar of a friend of Ihe Kuwait owner «*f the dhow* 5» That an incident of this nature could happen cm the much frequented part of the hatt al mb, close to FAG* idiere hundreds of river craft ply daily* and in broad daylight, reflects a serious state of affairs* and shews that all o&amp;mot be well with the f Iraq aiver Police, who are supposed to be entirely responsible for las and order and the safety of the ubllc, on this greet Inland waterway* d# The 111 nannered and insulting treatment accorded to the unfortunate nakhuda and crew of the Kuwait dhow, by the oliee Inspector at ifoe seems to oonflra the faet that the latter felt hie department had been guilty of ncgleet of duty soanwhere, and in ahe«-r annoyance vented hie spleen on the dhows crew whose only fault apparently lay in report ing that they had been set upon and assaulted by £ erslen 'Official** plratea, acting much in the same way aa Chinese river bandits would* F* hile freo the errldeaee to band it eeen fairly clear that the ! sreian uila»i~ anleh at Cuabah did his best to brin#: the culprits to book* aa soon as ho heard of tho in aidant, the morel and physical hurt suf farad by the inno cent craw of the Kuwait Ihow* should not, X consider, bo allowed to pees without a demand for some form of oosapeaca tion from the i ersian Government* Aa regards this latter*I think it Would not ho mrmnonoblo to ask for M»,&amp;40/~ or £4Q/~ 9 wftleh sun to bo dlrldod botwoon tho cnklmda and his orow In tho proportion of 2 shares to tho nakhuda and 1 share to oaoh member of the orow* B« At tho cams tins, and If yon urn no objection to suoh course f 1 would suggest that a very strong protest be otioe again nada to the Central Persian ^orenuasnt at tills fourth highhanded f&lt; hold-up 4 ' t within S &amp;anths 9 of la- nooent Kuwaitis craft engaged In their ordiimry Isgitlnate buslneesi by Persian Uver olio®, or lerslan sloops f wide ny Po»07O t dated ZSm Peoeaber 193£ i my Confidential So«6S dated the 34th April 1953, and ny tcnfldmtial Ho* 116 1 dated the 4th Juno 1933* respectively# 9* It i So«s not fall within sy province, to ask why or under what ercuee the r err.lans are nealnte inlng lv«r lollee on tho hatt si i ^ab, ehlch 1 always understand to be entirely sn f Irae rlrer, but it doer strike me that if the 9 Iraq Oewensnent do not take action in the matter so cm they will find it difficult to eject Persian olios from the river, ihea eventually they wish to do so# 10# In conclusion mi#t I ask that a copy of this letter, or possibly a separate complaint from you to Itls Majesty 9 s .hahassndor at Baghdad be sent drawing attention to the wholly unnseesaary rough treatment accorded to Kuwait natlansla by the Inspector of Police at /ao# In the present oaee the biased actions of thi s^n person cm whem the i haikh of Kinwlt is relying to support his land ngemt and strengthen hie authority among his recalcitrant ?ao fellaheen, are not such as to Inspire one with eon- fid once* I have the honour to be, air. Tour most obedient servant. Sd. H.R.P.Dickson, Pollttoal It #-0010X101, .gent, Kuwait#Translation of lotto? data* the 3rd JmmA ryxm Bmfmd bdul lattf «1 CttNurmbaily, m to Bla xo^Uimoy th* hailth of K.milt* kml 1362 (24*8.33.) of tho Bub 4ft«r r&gt;om&lt; Iteontfi* Th« roaoon of thlo l^ttor la that X t a/od . bdul Latlf al iharahelly, Uakhuda of a aw oimod by *yed r ollk al^ayad , uluB^d^aJU^^harafeally, Ml lad m ihuroday (21st Au^dt) fbr tha hatt al junb to transport wit tar to Kuwait* whan wo got thera I was tasking Inslda tha ihatt to suit tha dlraotIon of the wind* -rhaa soBaono in a ^fellan' (a aaoll rlrar boat)* near the oaatara bank atartad shouting at us* ^a wars in tha centre of tha river at tha time* and wa wars steering towards the i*ao bcink. rha man shoutsd ^Ta abu Fnliw f, i (you owner of the ballsy) iieave te*« X shouted back, 'Thin J is a water Bum' # but ha repeated his shouting, naylng* M You era as and ao 9 lower your aail^* ^ur nail at tha tlma was •at full, sad wa kept it holstad until wa arrived at tha £eo aide of tha rirar, we than lowered our sail and anchored* Ihe henna, with thoaa in it, followed us, boarded our craft end ordered us t© sat call for the other aida(of the river)* 3e asked the reason why they wanted us to invert our eouree, ana th*y ct nee began to strike us savagely with tha but m&amp;a of their rifles, mm with their fists* They foread our sailors to raise tha anchor, and they beat us until wa ware ©expelled to hoist the sail, ana they continued to strike end ill treat us, until wa reached a point opposite 'Tfahr-sW r iehri at i&gt;usbah and than made us lower our sail awd anchor# 1 Haort /They pretended to inspect the boat, and carried out a sham examination, but as wa had nothing on hoard (except water tanks) they naturally wars unsuocos-ful in their search# They, howaver, seized our provisions for tha Toy ago ^4akla* which consisted of two ianiyahs (8 lbs#) of sugar, a quarter of a aqiyah tea {$_ Ibd), tha tobacco of the sailors; Hn.10/- end a watch from myself, end soma old garments belonging tom £ m sellers, B«1 their in t oat Ion ms robbery wo refused to let then rooore the abate articles from the dhov. There upon they accused nr, of ha-rlae with us two , erslan sailors* e replied thet we had no . erslan sailors, exeept two whose origin was i are inn but were now uwaltle her la,: resided there many years. Ihey then said, 'ilther you giro us your belongings, or you Bust all disembark and go to the courts o with us, together with your thinge**. so, determined to aee the natter out, I took the nanlfost with no and went with then, as on the manifest was notsd everything which had been with us* han we landed with them they proceeded to taka us to a distant and lonely place, end when they new that wo had no intention of lattln: them out of our eight, they began to frighten my as Hart) by saying, -if you get aa far as the courts with us, they will conscript you as soldlsra, and will give you no end of trouble'. My man became thoroughly frightened at this trick, and began anxiously and with taara to Implore mi to return, I told them net to be afraid, but they aald that they did not want to go further, and If I wished to go alone, I could, ^s night woe JhiUng, end in view of their further threats, I feared 1 would be further beaten or even worse would befall aa, eo 1 decided t® return with ay son to our dhow, 'they (the Hirer patrol) accordingly took everythin* from us enumerated above. ; eachlng the dhow we set our sell, filled up our tanks with water, and proceeded to the Kao Customs House, where wo reported the whole matter to the Jlractor of (histoms. lha latter directed us to ths 'Mir ;*abfir', (Port Officer), who In turn sent ue to the 'dice. Before we left the Ireotor of Customs we told him that we feared to be delayed as we had no longer any provisions 'i.akla”, and also our money had been taken from us, but he told us to go to theto tko Imlpector of ^olloo oaa oxpX&amp;ln th« amttor to hlm t th# l«ittor would not koep ue waiting long. l&gt;o w* went to tlw Inji)&gt;ootor and told hin our atory fully, and ha rapliod, w Tou ara subjaota of a foroini ooparn&amp;mt, «ad I oan hava &amp;o1fcl&amp;g to do with you”* ir# told him that wo wars adviood to report to hlat by tho Dir act or of Quataaa, she had said that it waa noowoaary to otato our eaus to hla« At this the Inapaotor mnt ua to tho T&gt;ootor to hare mvat hurts ^cauinad* Do wo wore i&amp;» apootod by tho Doctor, who stated in writing that wo had reeoiyad a r^ry to/are boa tin Uia report wo brought bask to tbs Inapootor. 1tion ho bo tm to inquire into tho aattor. Urn abused uo and our parents at alaoot »rory oentanoe, and uaed other worde highly iaaultlag to our fanily honour, but * ho saw that I roa vary upoat at hie goin^a on, ha i aoaiod to taka moi' , o trouble with Ilia enquiry, but oontinned to oall no by bad mm* t betwooa hio writin/ down of our oviti nee* At last ho lot w ^ and told ae to uosia the next day, but when wo returned to our boat, wa found that the two of the prow loft in olmrg» had dia^j^arod, and tho root had becono 00 alamed that X deoated it wise to nail away, lest they elao daaart# eo rdiag to ehat i heard frcai sosae Ousbah people who had aaasi the oapture of our boat, tho ntssea of tha Hiver r'atrol Police, who took no, were as follows: One wee naned * uham^d, and the ether ha’abon* These were the officers. The other two they did not know, ihe crew of the balam oon-&gt; aisted ef tee sen, one was called Kairoor and the ether wae a baldheaded parson, whom they could not identify. The total number in the balla^i was 8 officers end two men, also the bailftne erew of two «i&lt;m«INDEXED LJS/iiM file: copy (26 groups) % My . 15) 4956 DECYPHER OF TELEG R.A .M • From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to (COPIES Secretary of State for India, repeating CIRCULATED) telegram addressed to Tehran. Dated Hen jam, 14th September, 1933. Received 14th September, 1933, 7 p.m. X T/43 . Addressed to Tehran, repeated to Secretary of State for India and Government of India. Copy handed to Senior Naval Officer. Political Agent, Koweit, has forwarded protest from Sheikh against assault on and robbery from crew of Koweit water- boat by Persian river police patrol in Shat-el-Arab near Gusbeh on or about August 23rd. I am making enquiries. 1 J t-vwV 4U/ A</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00015b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3780</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00015b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3780</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/63 'Persian Gulf. Assault on Koweiti dhow by Persian River Police in the Shatt el-Arab'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-11T22:20:08</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (31 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 33; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British diplomatic and naval officials regarding an incident in which a Kuwaiti dhow was held up and robbed on the Shatt al-Arab by a patrol boat of the Persian Police. An account of the incident as reported by the Political Agent in Kuwait, Harold Dickson, in correspondence with the Political Residency is contained on folios 24-26.In addition to correspondence, the file contains the following:'Note on Conversation with Major Frank Holmes' (folios 2-3)'Complaints against Persia in respect of "Dhow Incidents" in Persian Gulf' (folios 4-5)'Cases of interference with vessels or violation of territory belonging to the Arab protégés of His Majesty's Government in the Persian Gulf by Persian Warships or Customs Authorities' (folios 7-9)An account of the incident by the Dhow's captain, Seyed Abdul Latif al Gharabally (folios 28-30).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Shatt al-Arab</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00015b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>