<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:31:00.278Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">2 ) d.o. \\o.YS9- * ‘ Adviserate, DeceralDer 23&gt; 1946. Referring to your D,O.No*C/L130 dated 28th August 1948, and the note on our meeting, para 3* Brammer recommends the employment of a Mr© J*Hudson, at present working for Holloway in Qatar, I have interviewed him and I think he would he suitable, I enclose, for your information and return the details of his previous service etc# 2# It is proposed that his basic pay shall be Rs. 623/- per month v/ith cost and living allowance of RS. 3 O 70 of basic pay, free quarters, l%ve on the same scale as other European employees, term of service, 4 years and Provident Fund Rs# 50 per month. If you approve of his being employed I will prepare a draft agreement. 3. He has been informed by his Company that his services will not be required in Qatar as the Company’s work there is closing down. He is recommended by Skinner, Holloway 1 s head man in Qatar and is well reported on by Peter Holloway. He is unmarried but has matrimonial intentions and asked that should he marry he might be given married quarters after 18 months service. At present the question of accommodation is extremely difficult but in a year and a half we shall, I hope, have more quarters available. C. J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E., H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. RECEIPT.&lt;3 ^ No.C/R-12. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 10th January, 1949. Dear Residency, The Bahrain Government agreed at the time of Mr. Brammer, the State Engineer's appointment to give him a European Assistant. They have now found a Mr. J. Hudson, who is employed hy Messrs. Holloway Bros, in Qatar but who has been told by his firm that his services will not be required in Qatar as their work there is closing down. He has been recommended by Mr. Brammer, and by Mr. Skinner of Messrs. Holloway Bros, and has teen well reported on by Mr. Peter Holloway. 2. The Bahrain Government propose to pay him a basic salary of Rs.625/- per mensem with a cost of living allowance of Rs.30$ of basic pay and a provident fund of Rs.60/- per mensem, and to provide him with free quarters and leave on the same scale as other Bahrain Government European employees. His term of service will be for four years. 3. We should te grateful to know whether you have any objection. Yours ever, AtfENCY. The Political Residency, Jufair.r\ © URGENT. ( 3 a S A V I N G R A M J POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. From POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. T o PRODROME, BAHRAIN. No.C/R-20. Dated 16th January, 1949. Reference Agency Chancery Letter No.C/R-12, dated the 10th January, 1949. 2. Hudson has gone to United Kingdom and Brammer, State Engineer, is afraid he will change his mind if he is not offered the appointment without further delay. Grateful for sanction to his ap pointment. = POLITICAL = t — TS.O.No.C/L-31. Dear Belgrave, Reference your D.0.No.469-El, dated the 23rd December, 1948. There Is no objection to the employment of Mr. J. Hudson. I return the details of his previous service etc. herewith Yours sincerely, A- POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 20th January, 1949. C.D. Belgrave, Esquire, CBE, Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN.PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN. 13th January, 19^9. (106/2/49) Dear Agency, Will you please refer to your letter No.C/R 12 of the 10th January about the employ ment of an European assistant to the State Engineer. 2. We have no objection to the employ ment of Mr. J. Hudson in this post.I * ^ 2 - (£) mo.; sss -of 1368 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 29th J/Thani 1368 April 28, 1949. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum I forward herewith two copies of an agreement between the Bahrain Government and Mr. J. Hudson, who was engaged recently as Assistant State Engineer. Adviser to the Government. AY. ». ^ ^ ' 'SIPT. Dzt e ...l/A Ar MEMORANDUM OP AORSEMZNT rtade thift the fifteenth day of J/TCuami* One thousand three hundred and «ixtyelght 9 A.H., correaponding with the fourteenth day of April, One thousand, nine hundred and fortynlne, A.D., BETWEEN HiB Highness Shaikh Sir Sulican bin Haxaad AlKhalifah, K*O.I # S #f Ruler of Bahrain, on behalf of the Sovarnnient of Bahi*ain of the ono part, and Mr, J, Hudson, of the other part, WITNESSETH that it is ;mitually agreed that the said Government of Bahrain will empioy the said Mr, J, Hudson and the said Mr, J• Hudson will serve the eaid Government of Bahrain for a period of POUK years commencing from the nincih day of J/Yh&amp;ni, One thousand, three hundred and sixtycight A.H., corresponding with the eighth day of April, One thousand, nine hundred and fortynlne A.D., on the terms specified on the Schedule of Terms attached, IN WITNESS WHEREOF the parties hereto have hereunto signed their names. HI - i . Seel of ffle Highness Shaikh Sir bulman bin Hamad AlKhaliffih, X.3.I.K., '.viler of Balirain.2 / 1 . Terms and. Nature of Contract. V 2 . 3. k. Mr. J. Hudson shall faithfully serve the Government of Bahrain as Assistant State Engineer for the term of this contract which is for four years f the first six months of which will be on probation. The contract may be terminated by three months notice on either side and may be renewed after its expiry, by mutual consent. Pay. The rate of pay shall be Re.625/- (Six hundred and twenty five rupees) per mensem. Allowances. Cost of living allowance will be paid according to the rates in force for Bahrain Government employees. A sum of Rs.100/— (One hundred rupees) per mensem or its equivalent in sterling will be paid monthly into an account with the Eastern Bank Limited, London, being the Assistant State Engineer*s Provident Fund. This sum will be invested periodically in War Loan Bonds and the total amount will be handed over to the Assistant State Engineer on termination of his contract with the Bahrain Government. Accommodation. Free accommodation, with furniture, but not including plate, linen, utensils etc., will be provided by the Government or an allowance of Rs.200/- per month in lieu of same.3 / 2 Furlough. (a) Furlough will bo earned on the bails of one and a half months per year’s completed and approwed active service. Furlough will not count as active service for the purpose of assessing subsequent service or annual leave* (b) Annual leave, for one month, in addition to furlough, will be granted after each yeart’s completed and approved service; it will be counted as active service for the purpose of assessing furlough due and It may be accumulated up to two months in all. (o) Full average pay will be drawn in respect of normal furlough and annual leave. (d) Leave may be granted in special circumstances and when no leave is due, without pay; this leave will not be reckoned as active service under the contract. 7. Med^caL,, Medical attendance will be provided for Mr. J. Hudson at the expense of the Government of Bahrain, in accordance with Bahrain Government regulations, contained in circular Ho. 9/10 dated 28th January 1941, which is as follows:- 'All officials in the service of the Bahrain Government are afforded, according to their agreement free medical attention and their wives and families are entitled to similar medical privileges. This entitles them to the service of the Bahrain Government medical staff and to such facilities as the Government Medical Department has available. It does not however entitle the officials and their families to free tre tment at any of the other medical institutions in Bahrain such as the Awali hospital or the Arabian Mission Hospital. The wives of officials are not entitled to free medical attention at confinements. 198, Transports A car will be placed at the disposal of the Assistant State Engineer while on duty, 9* Passages, Mr, J, Hudson will be entitled to the following Passages during his four years* agreement, 1. A first class sea passage for himself and for his wife from United Kingdom to Bahrain and a return passage from Bahrain to United Kingdom for himself and for his wife on completion of his four years 1 eerrice or on final termination of his contract with the Bahrein Government* 2, A first class return passage, Bahr a in-Karachi, after each year f B completed service except during the year in which he receives a passage from Bahrain to United Kingdom, In the event of Mr. J. Hudson not availing himself of the annual leave to Pakistan, admissible under clause 6(b) he will be permitted to utilise the value of such passage or passages towards the cost of any passage to Europe on furlough which, under the terms of this agreement the Government of Bahrain is not under obligation to pay. The first class passage referred to above shall be P A 0,, 1st class 'C' from Bombay to England, and first class B.I. with food, from Bahrain to Bomaby or the equivalent sura if it is desired to t ravel by other routes or means. 10. Rastrlctlon of Tr»4e. As long as Mr. J. Hudson remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain he shall not carry on any 4/ —trade or bueineeB on hie own or anyone elee'e behalf 9 or receive any remuneration for any service rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Government of Bahrain which must be obtained in 1 writing. For the purpose of this agreement all dates and periods shall be those of the Arabic calendar which is the offloial calendar used by the State of Bahrain. Arbitration. If any question arises under the contract, whether as regards the meaning or in other respects, the question shall be referred to the arbitration of His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain, and his decision shall be final.CON? IDE NT T AT. Mi,C/R-187-42/4 sents his compliments co ’ His Excellency the Pelltlcal Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) with reference to his letter Re.108/2/49, dated the 13th January . ^ 1949. { 7 ! H.B.M'S POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. v ^ Dated 5th May 1949, Reference to previous correspondence Description of enclosure Agreement between the Bahrain Govern ment and Mr. J. Hudson. SUBJECT.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/902</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/902</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 42/4 Assistant State Engineer, Bahrain Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-12T21:07:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 15; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-5; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding the appointment of J Hudson (previously of Messrs. Holloway Bros in Qatar) as Assistant State Engineer for the Government of Bahrain in 1949.The correspondence is primarily between Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, and the Political Agency in Bahrain.The file contains a copy of Hudson's contract on folios 8-12.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00016d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>