<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000293_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:17:51.833Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">II &amp; . In any further comnmnication on this subject, please quote No, id address —not to any person by/name, but The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. «.&lt;L- » r f i l /; . f- o r* | * ‘ j SO 92 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* preser ts his » s». -v. ' S I Gh compliments to ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, jCty , 193^'.wmam COPY (E 43^8/4328/25) No.186. (1571/135/18) r r, o £ r, / . V &gt; Vv' 0 lh 5 i ^ n. )3 ?\ ^ 5 fs Jedda. 24th June 1935. % Sir, I have tne honour to transmit to you herewith , with reference to your despatch No.463 (E.7443/6362/25) of the 26th Decemher last, the translation of a note verbale of the 20th June, from the Saudi Minister for Foreign Affairs, relative to the regulation of coastwise shipping. It will he observed that this communication relates to sailing craft only and is restricted to the Red Sea ports of Saudi Arabia. 2. Whilst this appears to be a measure excellently conceived, it may he expected to be rather difficult of practical application in respect of some of the remoter ports and the intervening stretches of coast, where Saudi administrative control is at best a shadowy thing. Never theless, any effort to develop the coastal preventive organisation of the country is, I consider, to be welcomed, not only on general grounds but also, in respect of the Southern Red Sea shores of Saudi Arabia, as a help in combating the illegal dhow traffic from Massawa. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch and enclosure to the Department of Overseas Trade, Trans-Jordan, Khartoum, Aden and the Senior Naval Officer, Red Sea Sloops. I have, etc., (Sgd) A.S. CALVERT. The Right Honourable Sir Samuel Hoare, G.C.S.I., G.B.E., etc. , etc., etc. /1 ' . r ’ ~' f 'VT v” ■■■'- r o^r; • ! ^•' / . V.; ; s ( I ,y. ;. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Taif. 18th Rahi* ul Awwal 1354. 20th June 1935. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Saudi Arab Kingdom has the honour to enclose herewith with respect, copy of the official communique lfo.29 dated 18th Rat&gt;i f ul-Awwal 1354 (20th June 1935) regarding the territorial ports of this country, at which sailing ships and boats are allowed to call and ship cargo. The Government of H.M. the King have published the said communique in the Umm al Qura newspaper for the information of the authorities concerned in your Government. The British Legation, COPY 55/1/12. JeddaOfficial Communique No. 29 dated 18th 1354 (20th June 1935). Rahx^ul -Awwj In view of the f act that dhows (sailing boats) on which there are no officials of the Government of the Saudi Arab Kingdom are not allowed to call at territorial ports belonging to this country in accordance with the Coast Guards f regulation, the Government of H.M. the King indicate hereunder the names of the ports at which sailing boats and ships are allowed to call for discharging and taking cargo Any sailing boat which calls at ports other than those mentioned above, will be considered as smuggling, and will be liable to the application of the special provisione indicated in the Coast Guards* regulations. Northern ports Southern T3orts Jedda Lith Tuwal Qunfidha A1 Qadhlma A1 Birk Rfibegh A1 Qahma Yanbu* Jl z§n Umm Lejj ParsSn We jh DhabS1 'ED In any further communication on this subject, please quote and address —not to any person by name, but to— -4 “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1.' | a THE Under-Secretary of Sfcat^ for Foreign Ai a i rs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop \Su&gt; of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193^ . ? Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ’XWVv, Similar letter sent to 'O 14—6130 10292 ( 2 )MW—&lt;i2291. Wt. 16213/7530. 3000. 8/33. Wy.P.C. 613 . Great George Street; Westminster, S.W.l. |V ° 1 0$ 17th December, 1934. The Board of Trade present their compliments to The Secretary of State for India in Council and beg to transmit herewith for information copy of a letter 26th November . ot to«day-s-4ate which they have caused to be addressed to The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l.Am COPY. M.13697/54. •A Sir, ... Mercantile Marine Department, /To p t A 06 U I 7760 i 4 4()() L.. / :./l. ii \ _'.Y.rL., Board of Trade, Great George Street, Westminster,S.W.1. 26th November, 1934. With reference to your letter No.E.6362/6362/26, of the l4th November, 1934, enclosing a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Representative at Jedda and a translation of regulations concerning the Coastguard Administration in Sa f udi-Arabia, I am directed by the Board of Trade to state, for the information of Secretary Sir John Simon, that, as His Majesty’s Representative has already informed the Sa’udi Government that His Majesty’s Government reserve all their rights in International Law in respect of waters outside the three-mile limit, they have no observations to offer on the regulations. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) N.A. GUTTERY. The Under Secretary of State, FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l.It. 6404/34 4 13th Deceaber, Sir, With re fere ace to your letter Ho*E 6362/6362/ 26 of tiie 14th WoTember, X am coiaaaadied by My horde QomiiileeioaerB of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the secretary of btaW for Foreign Affaire, that Tney ao not de&amp;ire to offer any obaexTationa on the herniations relative to the Saudi goaatguards /.uminiatra- tion, a translation of which was included in the enclosures to your letter# Their hordehips observe that Article 4? of the hegulatlone contains a reiteration of the Saudi elslm to a marine territorial belt four miles in width; but as the views of his Majesty* s Government on this subject were before tm Saudi Government as recently as July, 1933 (Sir Andrew kyan'a letter Ko#97 of the 16th July enclosed with your letter Mo#K 4311/4311/26 of the 18th August 1933) They do not consider that any further protest is necessary in the present circumstances# Their Lordships assume that the Board of Trade will take note of Articles 12 and 49(g) and any others which might give rise to unwarranted interference with British merchant shipping# Copies of this letter have been addressed to the mala Office and hoard of Trade. 1 am, dir, four obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of htate, FOfcUGH OFFICE, 3# V. 1#1334 Lf 4 V .... 1 In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. (J rv- &lt; THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his PA- compliments to V 1 * and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ’sa^o of the under-mentioned paper. - ^ ^ Foreign Office, 6 Name and Date. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. VK.V\, Subject. ~4At« ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER ro. 4 7 22 NOV 1934 ;. ;c I ^ .jniTARY, POLITICAL AND S.ORLT DEPT. INDIA OFFICE 15 N 0 V 193 1 • w~ ^ &gt;\ Q n 4ob(/ 4 -) COPY (K 6562/6362/25) British Legation, No&gt; 292,E Jedda (264^/2598/8) 24th September, 1934 Sir I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy in translation of Regulations relative to the Saudi Coastguard Administration, which have appeared in successive issues of the Umm-al-Qura during the past two months. improve the control of shipping, both sailing and other, and to create an organisation for the prevention of smuggling. As far as I am able to judge, no exception can be taken, generally, to the provisions of these rules, many of which are in accordance with present practice, i would invite your attention, however, to the following Articles:- Article 15 . From the reference to 'sheli-f ishing*', it may be presumed that this organisation will control the pearl- fisheries of the Saudi coasts. Article 22. The upkeep of the buoys, beacons and sea-marks at Jedda leaves much to be desired. Representations over a number of years by various interests involved have failed to stir the Port autnoiitifco into activity. It is to be hoped that the Coastguards Administration will take this matter in hand. 25. Importance is attributed to this Aiticle by the Manager of Messrs. Gellatly, Hankey &amp; Co. (Sudan), Ltd., who informs me that owing to heavy claims paid here by Insurance 2 These Regulations appear to be designed chiefly to Companies,/ The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.Ii, K.C.V.O. , • 9 • 9 etc etc etc.Companies, underwriters frequently ask for reports on the method of lighterage, at present regarded as unsatisfactory. Article 47 . ”territorial waters to a distance of ‘•four miles 11 is, in effect, a re-assertion of the Saudi claim to territorial waters up to four miles, in respect of which His Majesty’s Government maintain reservations, vide my despatch No.216 (2033/161/10) of the 16th July, 1933. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch and enclosure to the principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Department of Overseas Trade, Senior Naval Officer, Fed Sea Sloops and the Honourable the Political Fesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have etc., (Signed) A. S. CALVERTTRANSLATION Extracts from the Mecca Umm-al-Qura Nos.501, 502 503, 505 and 506 of 8th Rabi ath-Thani 1353 (20.7.34), 15th Rabi ath-Thani (27.7.34), 22nd Rabi ath-Thani (3.8.34) , 6th Jumad Awal (17.8.34) and 13th Jumad Awal (24.8.34) , respectively. Regulations Concerning the Coastguards Administration . High order has been issued sanctioning the following Regulations concerning the Coastguards: Article 1 : These Regulations shall be entitled M Regulations concerning the Coastguards Administration and its branches.” Article 2 : The Authority to which the Coastguards Administration refers is the Ministry of interior. Article 3 : The Coastguards Administration is the Department charged with the protection of coasts and the arrest of smuggled (goods) by sea or overland and within the harbours or through the land ar sea patrols and the marine detachment, and the permanent stations (? ports) in harbours. Article 4: The Coastguards Administration should organise maritime affairs concerning it and relating to the work of ports and decisions and cases pertaining to marine affairs in accordance with these Regulations. 'This is to be effected through the stations attached to it. Article 5 ;/of the Sheykh of the quay and four leading dhowmen under the presidency of the office of the Coastguards Administration and to he selected hy their parties and to he renewed annually. Their duty is to look into cases of individual working on the sea and such people connected with the ports Department and to settle them in accordance with their custom and rules in practice. As regards any such cases wnich cannot he settled in the above manner, a decision should he drawn up about them and should he forwarded to the Government through the authorities concerned for necessary action. Article 11 : The Coastguards Administration must arrange for tours of inspection to he made at night within the port of Jedda at the gates of the Marine Detachment to ensure that the duties imposed hy the Regulations are being carried out. Article 12 : The Coastguards Administration should appoint soldiers of its Marine Detachment to go on hoard ships when they arrive in order to keep order thereon and to observe the discharge of goods from ships and to prevent smuggling and the landing of prohibited articles from ships. Article 13 : The Coastguards Administration should inspect the port dhows used specially in the carrying of goods discharged from ships, through the soldiers of the Marine Detachment, together with the guards of the customs on suspicion arising of smuggling and so on. Article 14 : The Coastguards Administration should prevent dhows/dhows and boats used specially lor carrying goods discharged from ships from communicating with ships before permission is given by Quarantine, through the Marine Detachmenx. Article 15 : The Coastguards Administration will control boats engaged in shell-fishing and apply the regulations concerning shell-fishing and fishing generally through the sea patrol. Article 16 : The Coastguards Administration should control sailing boats when they are in harbour and when sailing and should inspect their papers and cargo when sailing. Article 17 : The Coastguards Administration should arrange for a special record (to be kept) of everything seized of smuggled goods and articles handed over to customs and Finance authorities. Article 18 ; The Coastguards Administration should forward the necessary reports and enquiry papers to higher authorities in respect of everything seized of smuggled goods and the places where they have been deposited. They should also inform the Ministry of Finance accordingly so that necessary action may be taken in accordance with the Regulations, and should collect the rewards for those who have seized the goods or informed about them, and hand the same to them against receipt snowing the smuggled articles seized. Article 19 : Tde Coastguards Administration should forward with its remarks to higher authority the reports it receives/receives from the sea and land patrols and from the iiarine Detachment in respect of their work of patrolling and inspection* Article 20 ; The Coastguards Administration has the right to communicate with the concerned Departments regarding its work and branches. Article 21 : The Coastguards Administration should check the accounts of the ports and forward the general accounts monthly to the Ministry of Finance* Article 22 ; The Coastguards Administration should look after the sea-marks insid.e or outside the harbours and should have them repaired at once if any of them is damaged. PART II Harbour Duties . Article £5 : Harbour Departments are charged v^ith the control of ships when they arrive and when they sail and with enforcing the regulations, relating to them. They should also collect the fees laid down for them in accordance with their tariff. Article 24 ; Harbour Departments should keep a record and a register of all dhows belonging to the port and which make voyages. They should give them special serial numbers, like those marked on the dhows themselves. Names of owners and their nationalities must also be shown (in the register ). Article 25 : Harbour Departments should survey all boats with a view to establishing their tonnage which should be shown on the boat together with its number. They also must havemammmmm msmmmmm •■a ® j / a special mark made at the side of the boat to indicate that such mark is the extreme limit for the L boat to be immersed in water after it is loaded. Article 26 ; Harbour Departments must keep a record to register all sailors who v/ork in sailing-boats for travelling or those which work within the harbours. They must also register people who practise diving and fishing in accordance with the special regulations. Article 27 ; in the event of owners or agents of sailing boats approaching Harbour Departments with a view to obtaining permission to sail to a local or foreign destination and having cargo with them, their boats must first be inspected and if they were found seaworthy they could be allowed to take cargo. Uhen they are about to sail they should be given the 'Kushan' (permit) and the manifest and caused to pay the prescribed fees in accordance with the- tariff taking into consideration the quantity of cargo to be loaded and comparing it with the tonnage of the boat. if they intend to sail without cargo they may be allowed (to go) after obtaining the rt Kushan' (permit ) and paying its fees in accordance with the tariff. Article 28 ; A 'Kushan' given by Harbour Departments is valid for one or more ports on condition that sailing boats should not take extra cargo or carry passengers from ports at which they call. In this case it will be sufficient to make a note on the 'Kushan' regarding arrival only, but if the boat communicates, it will be necessary to have the 'icushan' renewed for it and the fees collected in accordance with the tariff. Article £9 ;/Article 29 ; permit to enter a port or ports is considered valid for use in ports mentioned in the 'ICushan' as allowed for the boat to call at. Any boat entering a port not permitted in the 'icushan' must take another 'icushan' unless its entry was due to force majeure and not to the taking or landing of cargo or passengers. Article 2Q ; A special manifest should be made for each port separately and fees for it should be paid in accordance with the tariff. Article gl ; when sailing boats arrive in harbour and owners or agents of such boats approach Harbour Departments to show their papers and take the necessary steps, the following should be effected;- (1) Buoy fees, in case there is any in the harbour, should be collected at once, (2) in case the boat is loaded from a foreign port, the necessary manifest showing quantity of cargo should be made by the Harbour Department in accordance with the foreign manifest and the prescribed fees should be collected in accordance with the tariff. (2) phe 'Nakhuda' (Captain) of the boat should be asked whether he had any cargo in his boat not entered in the manifest, so that in case there was any cargo of this sort in the boat, it will be entered in the manifest with a note to indicate that it was not in the manifest. necessary explanations as to the reasons for carrying it in this way must be given. (4) in case the boat is coming with cargo from a foreign port without a manifest, one should be made for it and its Captain must be asked why there was no manifest. Explanations to this effect must be written on/on the manifest Article 22; All boats that enter by force majeure ports not allowed in the r, K&amp;shan ,T , in case they have the flag of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, should pay the buoy fees in ports where there are buoys, and, in case they are foreigners, they should pay buoy and anchor fees in accordance with the prescribed- tariff whether they communicate or not. of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia must be in possession of a maritime document showing name of the boat, its owner, serial number, tonnage and how it has been possessed. The prescribed fees in accordance with the tariff should be collected unless the owner of the boat is in possession of such maritime document. owner to another by selling or granting or any disposal of the same sort, the necessary note must be made on its special register indicating the conveyance. A maritime document should be made for its new owner and the due fees should be collected in accordance with the tariff. to increasing its capacity, must be registered in the Harbour Departments after it has been surveyed and the necessary document has been made for its owner and the imposed fees for the document and the survey have been collected in accordance with the tar in laid down. The necessary number must also be put on it. Article 32: :very sailing boat belonging to a sueject Article 34*. In the event of conveyance effected by one Article 35; Every boat newly made or enlarged with a view Drticle 36*. Harbour Departments should collect the fees for permits granted to sailors, divers, coolies and fishermen in accordance with the tariff. They should als o /also see that such permits are renewed at the expiry of the legal period' and make a note of this in the register* Article S7 ; Any boat having a number of crew up to four, v/hich is the exempted limit, should pay fees of fifty piastres Miri, and the permit should be given to its captain in accordance with Article 16 (? Article 15) of the Regulations, concerning shell fishing and fishery. Article 58 ; All foreigh war ships are exempted from all fees concerning the harbour. Article 59 : Dhows of fishermen of which the capacity is less than five tons are exempted from buoy fees. Article 40 ; Minors who sail by sailing boats for the purpose of learning (to become sailors) are exempted from the fees of sailors* tickets on condition that ♦ they are not more than nine years old. Article 41 : launches belonging to Ministers and representatives of Foreign powers are exempted from all fees. Article 4S ; Harbour Departments should organise the records with a view to checking revenues and registering all actions taken in respect of imports and exports. Article 42 : Harbour Departments should hand over the revenues they collect to the Finance Departments. Districts where there are no Finance Departments should send their revenues to the office at jedda. Article 44 ; Harbour Departments should forward detailed monthly accounts showing the revenues in their different kinds to the Finance and a copy of v/hich toArticle Article their higher authority. _45: Harbour Departments should collect fees in accordance with the tariff laid down. 46 ; Harbour Departments should carefully and attentively observe the application of the tariff in collecting fees. PART III Marine Patrol 47 : The Karine Patrol is the Department charged with the control of the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, the protection of territorial waters to a distance of four miles and along the shore to a distance of ten Kilometres and the seizure of smuggled and prohibited goods. 48; The Marine Patrol is divided up into three sections:- First : Central Office at Jedda and its duties are to appoint and change troops for the posts and ships and to forward to the Directorate any reports it receives from the stations under it, as well as seized smuggled and prohibited goods. Second : Boats charged with wandering about on the sea, along the coasts and at anchorages. Third : Tixed posts in anchorages and harbours. Their duty is to control the coast and to do in harbours the work done by the Marine Detachment in the Directorate. Article 49 : The duties of the Marine Patrol in ships and at fixed posts are as follows:- (a) To protect the Customs line within territorial waters and the coasts, to patrox north and south up to the frontiers of neighbouring countries in a manner to prevent smuggling or committing jcommitting a breach of these Regulations, (b) to inspect and seize smuggled and prohibited goods within the Customs area. It is entitled to go beyond the Customs line within the boundaries of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia with a view to pui*suing boats and smugglers should suspicion attach to them, (c) To forward any seized smuggled or prohibited goods to the nearest Customs Administration with a report of the incident and to inform the Central Office accordingly, (d) To seize any luggage, goods, things and (detain) passengers entering or leaving places where there are no Customs Department, and to forward the same to the nearest customs Department with a report about the incident and to inform the central office accordingly, (e) to seize all articles and luggage v/hich may be loaded or discharged or insisted upon to be loaded or discharged in an improper manner, and to forward the same with a report about the incident to the nearest Customs Department and to inform the central office accordingly, (f) To seize all prohibited articles if they are shipped or discharged or if it is insisted that they should be shipped and not entered on the manifest and to forward the same with a report about the incident to the nearest Customs Department and to inform the central office accordingly, (g) To go aboard boats vhiich come near the coasts and which may be carrying cargo, and to ask for the manifest which-should be checked with the cargo they carry. should there be in the boat a small quantity/quantity of cargo other than tobacco not included in the manifest, a note must be made in the manifest indicating the extra quantity of cargo so that it may be noticed at destination. As to I tobacco it should be seised and taken into the patrol boat to be forwarded to the central office together with a report regarding the occurrence, in case the boat is going to a Hejazi port and not carrying a manifest and refuses to produce its papers or appears to be smuggling, the patro^. will take her to the nearest Customs Administration suitable for the boat to approach. Then a report should be made regarding the occurrence and the boat should be provided with an adequate guard until she arrives at the destination named by the captain or it should be accompanied by a patrol boat, (h) in the event of the patrol pursuing a boat of which the captain refuses to come near, the patrol should lower the flag of the boat and warn it to stop; and, if it refuses they should pursue it; and if the smuggling boat should venture to use arms, it should be met with the same and continually pursued. The patrol has the right to arrest it outside the Customs Line within the frontiers of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in case it tries to escape, (i) It has to control diving and fishing boats and to apply the Regulations concerning fishery and shell fishing Article 50; Any boat, flying a foreign flag, found by the /the patrol loading or discharging goods or anything else, or insisting on loading or discharging anything in a manner contradictory to the rules and principles in practice, and vvhich refuses to go with the patrol to the nearest Customs Administration, should be detained with its cargo under the control of the patrol which should make a report of the occurrence at once to the central office. Article 51: investigations by the patrol in foreign boats should be in accordance with recognised principles and rules. Article 52; The patrol is not allowed to enter the smallest or largest war ship. PABT IV Land patrol . Article 55: Land patrol is the Department char red with inspection on land within the customs line in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, and arrest of smuggled and prohibited matter. Article 54: Land patrol is divided into two parts:- yirst : principal one at jedda, whose duties are to appoint the camel corps to patrol on land, to change them and to forward the reports they receive from the Land patrol to the Directorate together with the seized smuggled or prohioited goods. Second : Land patrol whose duty is to tour about on land and along the coasts. Article 55: The functions of the patrol are as follows :/follows : (a) to protect the shores within the Customs line, specially at places where it is suspected that smuggling is likely to occur, in order to prevent smuggling and breach of the rules, (b) to inspect and seize smuggled goods on all shores on which they patrol v/ithin the Customs line, (c) to forward all smuggled and prohibited goods seized to the principal office with a report on the occurrence, (d) to seize all goods, cargo and articles and (detain) passengers entering or leaving points on the coast where there may be no Customs Department and to forward the same to the nearest Customs Department with a report on the occurrence and to inform the principal office, (e ) to pursue whosoever dares to smuggle, should he refuse to stop, and to meet v/hosoever dares to use (fire) arms in a like manner and to continue pursuing him within the limits of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, (f) to carefully inspect every thing the patrol meets in its way and to ask for official papers which prove that the goods loaded on camels or other means have been duly passed by Customs Department, in the event of non-existence of such official papers with the people concerned to prove this, and the patrol has ascertained that all the goods were corning from a city where there was a Customs Department or a Government office or that they passed through them, such goods shall be considered/— • - considered as smuggled and should be sent with a report to the nearest Customs Department and the principal office should be informed accordingly. If the patrol is satisfied that the goods are from a place where there is no Customs Department or that there is none on the way and the patrol know the destination of the goods, it should send with it one soldier to accompany them as far as the Customs Department at the place of destination, (g) Every thing transported on camels or other means and found on a way (track) other than the usual one vail be considered as smuggled and should be seised as well as the camelman and the transporters. it should then be sent with a report on the occurrence to the nearest Customs Department and the principal office should be informed accordingly. PAH? V. Article 56: General rules . Wandering about at night in and out the harbour is prohibited except for authorised fishermen and those who have permission from the Government. .-xTticle 57 : Loading and discharging of cargo at night is prohibited except for those who have permission from the Government. .art.-.cle 6 : Loading and discharging of cargo and | landing of passengers during times of atmospheric disturbance, storms and rains is prohibited. Articfe 59 : Sailing of sailing boats during times ( oi atmospheric disturbance, storms and raiss % is prohibited. Article 6o : /Article 60: Any sailing boat that leaves its specified place and goes to a coast void of Government Departments within Saudi Arabian territorial waters and there lands its cargo without good reason, will be considered to be smuggling and its cargo shall be confiscated. Article 61 : Boats which enter the harbour carrying inflammable material should anchor far away from the anchorage of commercial boats and ships. Article 62; Agents of shipping companies are compelled to warn the Administration in writing of the times at which their ships arrive in the harbour twenty-four hours before their arrival. They should likewise give the names of the places from which they are coming and also those to which they will go as well as the number of passengers and cargo they carry, whether the ships have pilots or otherwise. Article 63: Shipping agents are compelled to notify the Administration of ships that may require pilots from the country to bring’ them in the harbour and must nominate the pilot so that he may be given permission. Article 64 : In the event of fire breaking out or collision ocurring to any ship within the harbour, the company to which the ship sustaining the damage belongs must draw it away from the route of other ships in the course of fifteen days. should the company fail to comply with this, the Government will arrange for the ship■H to be towed and the expenses incurred on towing ano protection for a period of not exceeding one year nrast be paid by the company. After the elapse of one year the ship shall be considered as the property of the Government and the company shall have to pay for the damage. Article 65 ; Any boat, big or small, foreign or otherwise, loaded or unloaded, sailing without formal papers of sailing will be liable to double fees. Article 66 ; Captains of boats must report to the Administration twenty-four hours before loading their boats in order that their boats may be inspected (? surveyed). Article 67 ; All sailing boats are not allowed to sail, loaded or unloaded, to any direction, before tailing their official papers when sailing, and also when they arrive loaded or unloaded, their captains must report to the authorities concerned with whom they have dealings. Article 68 ; sailing boats are not allowed to sail from the harbour after sun set. In the case of a boat disobeying this order, its captain will be responsible for compensation for any loss or damage and will be liable to punishment by a disciplinary board. Article 69 : Owners of boats when desiring to make contracts with crew for service, should report to the harbours (? authorities), so that service contracts, permission to crew and tickets for them may be made through them. Article 7Q ; /Ar ti cle 70: Captains of boats generally should see that liquid, breakable and perishable materials are not mixed with other goods. Article 71 : Captains of boats axe not allowed to employ crev/s without permission from harbours (? authorities), and no crew is allowed to work on another crew f s ticket. Ax tide 72 ; Captains of boats which have no agents in Arab ports must pay the dues payable by them. Article 73 ; In case owners of boats in the harbour wishing to effect repairs to their boats secure the work by taking the number of some other boat, their boats will not be considered damaged and the monthly fees should be levied thereon. Article 74 ; All damaged boats which require repair and seized ones as well, shall be brought ashore in the place specified by the Harbour Directorate. Article 75 : Anything found floating on the surface of the water, sailors should give the necessary information thereof and to bring it to the harbour. if its owner is known, its value should be estimated and the sailors given one quarter of the same as a reward. patrol troops will also be given twenty per cent of the price as a reward for protection. The remainder will be given to the owner. Handing over of such material will be effected through the Customs//■N y mmam Customs in order that the necessary customs dues may be collected* If the owner oe unhnO'./n, they will be sold and the sailors and the patrol troops given their rewards out of that. fhe customs dues will also be paid and the remainder will be deposited in the deposit chest in the Finance (Department). Article 76: Anything found sunk in the sea, divers will give the necessary information about it and bring it to the harbour. if its owner is known, its value will be estimated, the diver given one third and the patrol troops fifteen per cent of the estimated value as rev/ard for them. fhe remainder will be given to the owner who will receive the objects through the customs in order to pay the necessary customs dues. If the owner is not known the things will be sold, the divers and the patrol troops given their reward out of that and the customs dues paid to the Customs. The remainder will be deposited in the deposit chest in the Finance (Department). i L' ; - Article 77; Sheykh of the auay is attached to the harbour department of the same place, in connection with the affairs Oj. the port and its boats. Article 78 ; Any quarrel or dispute arising amongst seamen should be reported by the Sheykh of the cmay to the harbour department for necessary investigation by the committee indicated/indicated in Article 9 of these .regulations and then submitted to the Government. In case of any criminal action resulting from quarrels, riots or disturbances of peace, the Sheykh of the quay should inform the harbour department. He must also report Jjfte matter to the Government for necessary action. Article 79 ; Sheykhs of ouays should not accept the work of any boats unregistered and having no number from the Harbour Department. They should also report on boats which have no numbe r s. Article 8Q ; sheykhs of sea-carpenters should control the work of the carpenters and must not allow any one of them to work without permission from the Harbour Departments. They must also make no new boat or purchase one except with permission from the Harbour Departments. Article 81 ; sheykhs of fishermen should not ; allow anyone to practise fishing without permission from the Harbour Departments. Article 62 : Any one committing a breach of these Regulations is liable to measures prescribed by the said Regulations. Article 83 ; The Ministry of interior and the Coastguards Administration should see that the provisions of these Regulations are strictly carried out.■M 3^ APPENjIX to the Regulations in respect of coastguards Administration. (1) 'Kushan' ( Government toll) fees. fees per ton on every boat sailing under the flag of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, sailing - loaded or unloaded - to a Saudi port. on every boat belonging to Saudi Arabia, sailing - loaded or unloaded - to Saudi ports, fees per ton on every boat flying a foreign flag sailing - loaded or unloaded - to Saudi ports, fees per ton on every boat flying a foreign flag sailing - loaded or unloaded - to fore.ign ports. f 2 ) ,f i:anifest fees' . fees on every boat of which the tonnage is from one ton to fifteen tons. fees on every boat loaded from sixteen tons up to twenty-five tons. fees on every boat loaded from ty;enty-six tons up to fifty-nine tons. fees on every boat loaded from sixty tons upwards. Boats coming from foreign ports with shipment, whether they may be in possession of a manifest or not will have one made at the port showing the quantity of shipment, which should be referred, together with the foreign manifest, to the fees department. m/( 2 ) 'llaritime document fees' The value of the Maritime document to be made at the ports Departments is as a title-deed for the ownership of the boat. yhen this document is being made, two and a half per cent of the estimated price of the boat is to be collected as fees. (4) 'Maritime ticket fees ' . Fees (are collected) for the Maritime ticket given as a license to every sailor of sailing boats. The period of its validity is one year, after which it should be renewed at the same cost, taking into consideration the exemption of those entitled to exemption of fees in accordance with the Regulations.rojH | Vi 5* survey fees pt.Miri On every newly-built boat o! a capacity from 2 to 10 tons. On every newly-built boat of a capacity from 11 to 18 tons. On every newly-built boat of a capacity from 19 to 28 tons. On every newly-built boat of a capacity from 29 to 38 tons. from 39 to 48 tons. On every newly-built boat of a capacity from 49 to 58 tons. from 59 tons upwards. 6. Anchorage fees . On every boat that anchors in the harbour on arrival. in the harbour on arrival. 7. pilot fees . On every boat entering the harbour whether with or without a pilot from the town except in the case of warships which are exempted from such fees. 8. Buoy fees . On every boat anchoring in a harbour having a buoy whether the boat moors to the buoy or ndt. On every newly-built boat of a capacity Tt On every newly-built boat of a capacity i. On every foreign sailing boat that anchors On/On every sailing boat anchoring in a harbour having a buoy whether it moors or not to the buoy, with deductions in certain cases. 9. Boatmen’s fees . Payable for license for every boatman in the harbour who works in boats which carry goods and passengers from steamships to sailing boats. Period of the said license is one year to be renewed on payment of the same fee. 10. Stevedores’ fees . Payable for license for every stevedore, period of license is one year to be renewed on payment of the same fee. 11. Fishermen’s license fees . 'Payable for license for every fisherman who work in the harbours. period of license is one year to be renewed on payment of the same fee. IS. D iving license fees . These fees are to be collected together with fishery fees in accordance with the regulations concerning fishery and shell- fishing. 12. Monthly fees. Payable/Payable monthly on every dhow which works in the harbour for the transport of cargo and passengers from steamships and sailing boats to the quay. Payable monthly on every launch which works in the harbour, launches of Representatives of Foreign Powers being exempt • Payable on every boat which works in the harbour for the transport of passengers and their luggage. 14. La unch Drivers T fees. Half a pound is payable yearly as fee for the license of drivers of launches which work in the harbour. The license is to be renewed every year on payment of the same fee. 15. Shipwrights 1 license . Payable yearly by every shipwright. The license is to be renewed every year on payment of the same fee. 16. stamp fees . Stamp fees on Kushans (Government tolls) and licenses issued in the ports are to be collected in accordance with the stamp regulations.1 4/r A Pilot Zees . High Decree has been issued to the effect that the pilot fees mentioned in Article 7 (? item 7) of the fees payable to coastguards Administration viz - two English pounds should be collected on ships that enter the harbour by pilot from the city, but ships that enter the harbour without pilot should not pay anything. Warships are likewise not to pay / anything.copy (E 4311/4311/25) 5 C; British Legation, Jedda. 16th July 1933 Sir ¥ith reference to Mr. Hope dill’s printed despatch Koa 460(3330/392/10) of November 25 last, I have the honour to forward herewith translations of a note and enclosure from the Sa 8 udi Minister for Foreign A-ffairs relative to the right claimed by his Government to fix at their discretion the limits of their territorial waters. I enclose also a copy of Sir Andrew Ryan’s reply, worded in such a way as to obviate the necessity for further correspondence unless you should wish to oursue the matte * 2* The enclosure to the note has received a carefu translation but the final sentence, faithfully rendered from the Arabic text, remains unsatisfactory although the meaning is generally clear 0 3» I am sending copies of this despatch and enclos sres to The Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Department of Overseas Trade), to the Governor-Cieneral c ? the Sudan, Khartoum and to the Commissioner, Port Sudan® I have, etc®, (Signed) A.S. CALVERT The Right Honourable, Sir John Simon, G*C«S.I., K.C.V.O., etc o, etc®M3M0RAMUM £r) The delImitation of the territorial waters of each country has not heen agreed upon definitely between Governments and no definite rule to to followed in this respect 1ms 'been drawn up in all general international laws. i&amp;ch country has to define the extent of the delimitation of its territorial waters,, Different views may he put forward to aocord with the interests of their sponsors. Some reserve the right to territorial mters up to four miles and some reserve to three miles and others delimit them to the further point to which their projectiles would reach, tut the Government of His Majesty the ling have adopted the first pi^posal i.e., they have delimited their territorial waters up to four mllos distance from the shore, with the exception of gulfs and hays. If our delimitation does not accord with the international legal rule, therefore there are no International rules to prevent us £x*om fixing territorial waters up to more than three mile Sc written on 16th SalI-uXAwwai 1352, ( 9th July 1933)m rnsmm COPY NOo 97. TmSSTiETTz) /\ ‘ P.Z. £ 12 '; ! I9 T British Legation, Jedda * 15th July 1933 6 Your Royal Highness, Aft e r 0 OEip X i men t s , I ha^e the honour to aolmowledge the receipt of Your Royal Highness 0 note NOo 2/6/2 of the 20th Rabi-ul-Awwal 1352 (July 13) and to thanic you for the statement in the annexed memorandum of the views of the Government of Sa*fidi Arabia on the principles of intemati* aal law governing territorial waters* I shall not fail to communicate the views of the Sa’udi Government to His Majesty* 8 T Government in the United Kingdom t/ut I must maintain the reservation made under their instructions in Mr. Hope Gill *3 note No. 166 of November 25 last regarding their rights in respect of waters outside the three-mile limit. With highest respects ? (Signed) ANDREW RYAN. Hie Royal Highness, The Minister for Foreign Affairs.( P.Z. Mo. BIO. 4811/4811/26; Bir X have received your cieeoateh ilo. V216 cl the 16th July, enclosing cooiea of correaoonuenee with the Saudi Arabian Qorenment regarding the liMte of Saudi Arabian territorial waterso I approve the tersia of your note of the 15th wo the Saudi Arabian Minister for Foreign Affaire* You need take no further action in this isatter at the oresent stage* I am, with great truth, Sir, four obedient, Servant, (in the absence of the Secretary of State) A»S• Calvert, Ksq*, etc» 5 J'edua • 9 etc. ? etc1TV' cvt^O In any furtlier communication on this subject, please quote J* \c Smv \smv\\5’ P.i. Lit)? r, o. /243 * and address —not to any person by name, but to- “ J'he Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. IC &gt;32 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents Ins ipliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith coptfc* of the under-mentioned paper. comi Foreign Office, \ ^ CJz. , 1931 . 5 Reference to previous correspondence Similar letter -sent to H- 613 O 744 I ( 2 ) / V\&lt;$P . C-o .J&amp;DM. September 26th, 193 Sir, I hare tho honour to report that the 'U«*-al- Cuxa , ♦ has recently completed the publication of a lengthy 'Regulation controlling Pishing and Shell fishing on the Red Sea Coasts'• 2. It appears to be a comprehensive enactment dealing with every aspect of the licensing and control of the coastal fishing industry, its peiscnnel and boats. 'Hie only point which seems to be worthy of special mention is that Hejas-Hejd territorial waters are defined as extending four miles from shore, excluding gulfs and bights (i*e. presumably including them entirely) but including 'the other localities outside this area where the Hejasi government are accustomed to permit fishing'# Unless you wish me to do so, I do not propose to enquire what these localitiefe are# a. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade, the Acting 3overnor- Ceneral of the Sudan and the Acting Commissioner at Sort Sudan# I have the honour, etc#, (sgd.) c.a. Hope am. ' (E 6271/6271/25) Ho.40a• (2836/392/3). M Hie Majesty's X^inolpal Secretary of state for ?oreign Afffcirs.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000293_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2121</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000293</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2121</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/54 'Saudi-Arabia: Limits of Saudi Arabian territorial waters.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-05T11:26:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the delimitation of Saudi Arabia's territorial waters. It documents reservations held by the British regarding the Saudi Government's claim that its territorial waters extend as far as four miles from the shore (as opposed to the three-mile limit favoured by the British). The file largely consists of correspondence regarding this issue, and features the following principal correspondents: His Majesty's Chargé d'Affaires to Jedda (Cecil Gervase Hope Gill, succeeded by Albert Spencer Calvert); His Majesty's Minister at Jedda (Sir Andrew Ryan); the Saudi Ministry of Foreign Affairs; the Saudi Minister for Foreign Affairs [Fayṣal bin ‘Abd al-‘Azīz Āl Sa‘ūd]; officials of the Foreign Office, the Admiralty, and the Board of Trade's Mercantile Marine Department.Also discussed are Saudi Government regulations on coastguard administration, which concern fishing and shipping rights, measures taken to prevent smuggling, harbour duties, marine patrol, and land patrol. A copy of a translation of these regulations is included in the file (folios 16-41).The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>National regulations</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade, Mercantile Marine Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Admiralty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Saudi Arabia, Āl Sa'ūd dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Territorial waters</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping regulations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000293#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>