<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:03:26.514Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">II rt'' 8 ■ No. «• 1 /33 Politicel Agency, Bahrain, the 10th September 1937 To The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. nemorandum i ^ /V Reference this office Endorsement No#898/1/33 dated the 17th April 1937* 2. Item 2 &gt; As at present there does not appear to be any chance of confirmation of Mr* Hidayatullah,4th ^lerk Bahrain, in the cadre, he has therefore abandoned the idea of proceeding on leave during December 1937* for Political Agent, Bahrain.8 Please state for purposes of the half yearly report to Bushire whether you contemplate taking leave during the 2nd half of 1938. If so, please give details of the nature of leave, date of availing and extent of leave. C-0- ** Sf.o. Hod- '(w f i ifI Political Agency, Bahrain, the 11th October 1939, 0 The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum In forwarding the half yearly return for leave requirements of the clerical staff, I enquire whether, if war continues, applications for leave will be given consideration. for Political Agent, Bahrain. *V&gt;' / gsNo. 'ik'l -64/238 Dated the 19th October, 1939. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum f(. Reference your memorandum No.1773-1/53, dated the 11th October, 1939. 2. So far as can be foreseen at present, applications for leave will be given consideration. order. 'v y Secretary to tne Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No.l^^ -64/238, Dated the 6th October 1940. To The Political Agent, Musi The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait His Majesty^ Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr. MEMORANDUM tfill you please let me kno^f if any members of your clerical establishment want to proceed on leave this winter. If so, kindly iiform me of the probable date and nature oi the leave to be taken. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,No.'^3 -64/238. Dated the November 1940 15th October 1940. 2, It is presumed that you will forward formal applications for leave from Mr, Ras Masaud and Mr, Abdulla Jassim Boodai. 3, Mr, Ras Masaud may have his leave on the return from leave in about April 1941 of Mr, Thomas, 4, Proposals have been submitted to the Secretary of State for India for sanction to the provision of one extra leave reserve for the Vernacular cadre. If these proposals are accepted this leave reserve can take the place of Mr, Boodai whe^i he proceeds on leave in May next.^ Otherwise there will be no one available; and it will be necessary to make local arrangements. By order, Secretaryxto the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.I Telegram ^.T.C, Political Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. 1 2nd January 1941 After richolas returns Pajagopalan anxi6us proceed, on short earned leave not exceeding one month including Joining time on private affairs. I strongly recomraend he be allowed to go. T r o relief Is required. Please telegraph sanction. - Political (§&gt; pJ Telegram G.T.C. —7- ;—Zrf //'/- From Britconsul, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. A 11 Dated 8th January 1941 Your telegram No. 1 January 3rd. Hajagopalan. Leave sanctioned.21^ Telegram GTC. From Britconsul, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No.A/130 D a ted 16th April, 1941. © Reference my memorandum No.1457 November 26th 1940. I propose to send Bhasin to Bahrain by the next boat to relieve Has Masud v*ho can then proceed on leave.&amp;&gt; No. ^-64/238, To British Consulate-Creneral, Bushire. Dated the //i* May, 1941. ^r/ The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM. f&gt; ' J- y Reference your endorsement No.610-1/33, dated the 3rd April, 1941. 2. Leave applied for by Messrs. Nasir-ul-Kaq and Grhulam Rabbani is sanctioned. Suitable reliefs will be sent in due course. By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.ri To British Consulate General, Bughire. D?ted the^ t Sept emte r 1941. The political Agent, B&amp;hrain. LJLMORAITDUM Reference your memorandum No.1609-1/33, dated the 16th August 1941. 2, It is regretted that owing to unforeseen circumstances it will not be possible to send a relief for Mr. Ghtilam .^attani before the end of December 1941. By order, s ident in the J^rs-iaiT'Gulf. xSkir -Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Britconsul, Bashire No 227 ^ated the 15th September, 1941. Acting on sanction received in your 602 Rabbani sent his wife to India in June. Unless he proceeds before December 3rd he will not follow her within 6 months and will forfiet Travelling allowance for her through no fault of his own, Please telegraph if relief can be arranged earlier#Telegram. G.T.C. Prom. To No. dated. Political Agent, Bahrain Britconsul, Bushire. 292. 11-11-41 Your telegram A/309 23rd September 1941. Owing shipping difficulties Habbani will / y unless you liave any objection book passage now / to leave here early next month.Code. G.T.C. From. Britconsul, 'Rushire. To. Political Agent, No. 724 /n Dated. 16-11-41. ( Your telegram No.292. Relief for Habbani will be sent end of November.KO.J34J -1/33. Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 26th November 1941. To Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I shall be grateful if you will book two second class passages without food for Messrs Nasirul Ilaq and Ghulam Habbani, Government servants and members of the staff of this Agency, from Bahrain to Karachi by the next down boat. The cost will be paid by this office on receipt of your bill. Yours faithfully, IM' for Political Agent, Bahrain. ^7 xC 0 i&gt; Y fl fel li.T.C. ^'roHi ^olitieal, Bahrain. To Briteonsul, Bushire• Mo. 239 Dated 5 # 7 # 43 Reference your telegram No.A/841 June 26th. 2. I will send Seth on Resale's first trip in August. wames of rest will be sent on RccidenVc return from IXidia* Seth will probably be followed by another bachelor on RQaang'a raid-August trip. POLITICAL iMO. 1435 Copy forwarded by post in confirmation, Mr* Seth, who was taken on by this Agency last January from P.C.L., has not been to India since 1st December 1940 and proposes to apply for leave next year. It is assumed that his application i-or leave will not in any way be prejudiced by hi» visit to Shiraz this summer. ltd. for Political Agent, Bahrain. COPY ■uO. 1187-^8/37 British Residency cc Consulate-General, Bushire, 14-7-43 , TO ihe P olitical Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your endorsement No. 1435 dated 5th July, 1943. 2. xour assumption is confirmed. Sd/ R.G. Daubeny secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.■I / M DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. __ Letter L&gt;ratr Memoranduni Telegram I INLAND: Immediate Class for 'telegrams important Express Ordinary &lt; To be issued oa 1st Reminder 2n(l Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures Dated (Code word for telegrams.) MGIPC—So—1768 (S&amp;P)MFP—&lt;l-9-39 SO,000 Pads. File Ko. Serial No, 19 £• 'i * v-u J?' •A • My child has a^ain taken sorioaaly ill and it lias becomG essont- ial tliat j. take my ramily to mdia as early as possible, i had applied for o lenve from the be^inning of ^avember, i .vould be graxeful if you could kindly let me knov^ when i may be able to proceed on leave.No.A7^- V' ME^OItANDUM Cff Political Agency, Bahrain, 1st October 1944, To The Secretary to the Hen'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Clerks* leave Reference my telegram No.593 dated September 11th* 2, I shall be grateful for a telegraphic reply to the points raised in my telegram under reference. Political Agent, Bahrain. __y TO WliC. IT MY CONCERN This Is to certify that Mr. M.A.Khlre ,a clerk of the Persian Gulf Residency Is proceeding to India on 3 months' leave . % It Is requested that he may be granted all travel facilities for his return journey to the Gvlf with his wife. 52 1 ■c Political Agent,Bahrain, Bahraln Dated the 4th November ,1944.Sir, I understand thai: at present there is a vacancy in Kerman. As tnore is a great likelihood that I shall be transferred on my return from leave, I would very much wish for a transfer to kcrman for the following reasons:- My wife does not maintain good health in the Gulf, as she was nrought up in Kerman, a cold place. In addition, she owns moveable and immoveable property in Kerman, which after her cibsence of 6 years from there will require her attention. I myself will be completing three years in the ^ulf by middle of Cctober and a change to a colder and drier jsiscKE climate will greatly help towards neutralizing the bad effects on health of the Gulf climate. I shall be most grateful if F.A. very kindly approaches the Secretary, Bushii^?, to grant me this favour, if the time of my leave, i.e. October, is not compatible with the postings in hand no®, I shall adjust my leave accordingly. 18.6.46.Political Agency, Bahrtlrif The 19 tii June, 19^6* iH v5h*'- Will you kinoly refer to my endoraoment No#1389-1/33 of the 8th April, 1945, in which Mohamad Asm Quxosiil, my passport clerk has asked for leave from 1st October, 1946? 2. He has put in a petition to me a cooy of which I am enclosing herewith for anything you Ccji do to most his request. Yours sincerely, ^ ' £ B.G. Danbeny, Ssq., O.B.ii., ^ • Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* ' mNo.2545-64/238. mmmmrr- - BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. Dated the 21st June X945. Paljta'n The Political BAH R_A I\N • &amp; p Mftmorandvun, / Reference your endorsement No. 1389-1/33 dated the 8th April, 1945• 2, On relief by Mr. Nedungadi, Mr. Joshl may proceed on earned leave for thre ® ®° nth ? with effect from the 1st September, 1945. relief for Mr. Nedungadi will be sent in due course. 3 Mr. M.A. Kureshi has been sanctioned 90 days earned leave with effect from the 1st October, 1945. A suitable relief will be sent in due course. 4 Mr. Ringrow is sanctioned earned leave for thirty days with effect from 1st December, 1945. A relief will be sent in due course. Secretary to x the Pol^ tical ResidentD.O .No. 2667-64/238 BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, Bushire, Dated the 3rd July 1945. BaSrafn Receipt Al v C L slAa. f Please refer to your demi-official letter No. 2548-1/33 dated the 19th June 1945. 2. Mohamad Azam Qureshi's request for a transfer to Kerman on the expiry of his leave will be borne in mind when postings are made in November 1945.• &lt;S) 7^- 1/33 Circular E»0. , C . 0. , and V,0. Will you please state for purposes of the half- yearly report to Bushire, whether you contemplate taking leave during the 2nd half of 1937, if so, please give details of the nature of the leave, date of availing and extent of leave. '-4-37. IVo j k jd fHo [l ■ iij'i- I intend to take combined leave for sixteen months (four months on average pay and twelve months on half average pay) with effect from 1st November 1937 or date of availing^ ^2^ ^ t/ii, Ctw &lt;A/ 3 lA^i LA/&lt;a - ^ 0k ^ J \ LL ^ ^ ^ ^ ^-JL &lt;ry*. n 3 7. Issued endorsement No. 898 dated 17-4-37 to Secretary.&lt;2. prepage) P.U»C y 2, Only Mr.- Nicholas intends proceeding on leave this winter. H© being a temporary hand is due only 15 days earned leave, but since he intends to nroceed in December he could take advantage of Xmas holidays. If he is permitted to nroceed on leave the total period of his absence will be as below:-* joining time 18 days from 27.11.40 to 8.12.40 Leave 15 days from 9.12.40 to 25.12.40 Xmas &amp; New Year holidays 9 days from 24.12.40 to 1.1.41 joining time 12 days from 2.1.41 to 13.1.41. Due to rejoin duty at Bahrain 14.1.41. (this mostly depends ±t on the boats leaving from and returning to Bahrain.) iLL^ I iy.L t U~p Submitted for orders. If you approve the request may be forwarded to Bushire. The reason M^' « -i • attend tq some urgent private affairs at home and Nicholas applies for leave is/g^ wants to undergo a minor operation (tonsils) at Bangalore. half -yearly leave return of clerical establishment Our half-yearly leave return is also due now. The following intend to proceed on leave. Abdullah Boodai tms. on 120 days earned leave on 1.5.41. He has 120 days leave to his credit. He took no leave since he joined service in 1937. Srsmfis. Lr. Ras Masaud . I beg to apply for 8 months leave from 1.4.41., iECTE 4 months on average pay and four months on half average, I am due 4 months on average pay and 10 months on half average. Taken no leave since 1937. I apnlied for lea^re on medical certificate last year but even on M . c . it could not be granted as no relief was available. May prenare the leave-return accordingly? i /U IU- u■ Jl 'Li P.A. T request that I may kindly be granted a few days' leave, just sufficient to enable me to proceed to Bombay and bring my wife and child by the next boat. The total period of my absence f rom Bahrain will not exceed four weeks - it will be much shorter if there is a fast mail service then, Mr. Nicholas is due back about the 14th January and I would like to leave here early in February. Mr, Nicholas will be able to carry on during my absence, which will be only for about three or four weeks. /(OA »' \ s 1 29/12/1940 ■ -x-ji /-x. 4 ^ ■Ih. /? ( / A JCr- 7 2 t, /£ tCc. / ' - ^ S c St,.' : ^ ^ 7^ ^-7 ^ 6- /% 6 v' / y , ^ , ' 7) /3 ^*3 ^ y // /~ / * jC ^ luC- ^ ^ ^ ^ •? /• ' ' r/. J I I a &gt; IJ /v ^ : / 4? /^. A-'fr', I have postponed my leave till August and v»e have already wrl'tt.€n 'to Bushire abou't 'this -page 22• Since was sent via Basra it this letter/will not reach them earlier than May. Draft reply for approval# Mr* Boodai has aiss cancelled his leave and I havc,therefore,added his name also as they may send a relief for him .ac n!n A I'/. H I r</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1025</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1025</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/33 Six-Monthly Returns of Contemplated Leave by the Clerical Establishment'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-03-28T00:06:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (80 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 80 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. There are also two incomplete foliation sequences written in pencil (uncircled) and appearing in the same portion of most of the folios.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file includes half-yearly statements (returns) showing the leave contemplated by the Clerical Establishment of the Political Agency, Bahrain, 1935 to 1945 inclusive; correspondence between the Political Agent and the office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf relating to the returns, leave of individuals, appointment of reliefs, and effect of war on applications for leave; correspondence from individual members of the Clerical Establishment requesting leave; and papers relating to travel arrangements.The last item of correspondence in this file is dated 3 July 1945. The overall date range is supplied by an entry in the notes at the end of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Clerical Establishment</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000248#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>