<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100029145977.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T12:40:50.002Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(COPY). No. 2 0, g„.£c_EBt.A. 3(5 hr ^ /i i'll)t From V —: ?, . To Sir, The Deputy Secretary to the Government ot India in the Foreign Department, The Officer-in-Charge, Hie Britannic Majesty'* Consulate at Jeddah. Simla, the 4th December 1913. India, Foreign Secretary’s No 49 .Vl, dated 4 UiG 1913 With reference to Mr. Shipley'e letter No.12 Consular, dated the 4th June 1913, to the address of Hie Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, I am directed to acquaint you that, with the concurrence of His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, the Government of India are pleased to sanction the grant, with effect from the 1st April 1913, of thlrteen-and-a-half months' pay for twelve months' service to the Indian cavass attached to His Majesty's Vice-Consulate at Jeddah. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- H. Chenevix Trench. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. iI. 821 * India Office, London, 10th October 1913. &gt; Political, No. 101. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, I forward herewith a copy of Turkish Arabia. Proposed gratuity of one-and-a,-half months' pay to the Indian Gavass at the Jeddah Consulate. be granted a gratuity of one-and-a- * From Foreign Office, dated 27th June 1913 (and enclosure). From ditto, dated 14th July 1913. To ditto, dated 5th August 1913. From ditto, dated 12th September 1913. correspondence'' that has passed with the Foreign Office respecting a proposal made by His Majesty’s Consul at Jeddah that the cavass employed at that consulate in connection with Indian pilgrims should ■half months’ pay, as was recently done in the case of the Malay cavass attached to the post. 2. I understand that the salary of the cavass in question is borne entirely by Indian funds as part of the establishment of the Vice-Consulate at Jeddah, and that the proposed gratuity does not in any way affect the question of India’s fixed annual contribution to the upkeep of the Consulate there. In these circumstances I have expressed my willingness to consent to the proposal, and request that if Your Fxcellency s Govei nment sees no objection, thirteen-and-a-half months’ pay may be issued to the cavass for twelve months’ service, the concession to take effect from 1st Aprd ID 13. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Crewe.I ENCLOSURES. ENCLOSURE No. 1:— Foreign Ofjice to India Office. No. 28,681. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents bis compli ments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of a letter from His Majesty’s Consul at Jeddah, No. 12, dated 4th June 1913. Foreign Office, 27th June 1913. Annex :— Mr. Shipley to Sir E. Grey. No. 12. Consular. Jeddah, 4th June 1913. With reference to despatch from the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, No. 9 (50,966/12), of 5th December 1912, in which I was informed that the Governor of the Straits Settlements saw- no objection to the payment out of. public funds oi thirteen and a half months’ salary for one year’s service to the Malay oavass attached to this Consulate, I have the honour to enquire whether the same grant will be sanctioned by the Secretary of State for India in respect to the cavass employed on business connected with the Indian pilgrims. Abdul Samad, the cavass in question, has been in the service of this Consulate for over ten years and is invaluable where British Indian subjects, whether pilgrims or residents, are concerned, and a yearly gratuity such as that proposed would mark the Government of India’s appreciation of his services and abolish the difference which now exists between him and the other cavasses, who receive the gratuity, the one from the Colonial Office, the other from His Majesty’s Consul. If the grant is sanctioned, I venture to request that it be made as from 1st April 1913. I have, &amp;c., The Secretary of State, Avalon Shipley. Foreign Office. Foreign Office, 14th July 1913. 9th of September cavasses and other ENCLOSURE No. 2 :— Foreign Office to India Office. No. 28,681. Sir, With reference to the letter from this Office of the 1912 (No. 36981/12), on the subject of certain payments to employees of His Majesty’s Consulate at Jeddah, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to state, for the information of the Marquess of Crewe,^ that a grant of thirteen and a half months’ pay for twelve months’ service w T as sanctioned by the Colonial Office in respect of the Malay cavass.^ Sir E. Grey would therefore suggest that, in accordance with the request contained in Mr. Shipley’s despatch of the 4th ultimo, a copy of which was forwarded to the India Office on the 27th ultimo, a similar concession should be made by the Marquess of Crewe in respect of the Indian cavass employed at Jeddah, to take effect as from the 1st of April last. I have, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State A. Law, for India. ENCLOSURE No. 3 :— India Office to Foreign Office. India Office, gi r? 5th August 1913. I am directed by the Secretary of State for India in Council to acknow ledge the receipt of your letters of 27th June and 14th July regarding a proposal made by His Majesty’s Consul at Jeddah that the cavass employed at 821 *.in Hi an Dilffrims should be granted an annual that post m connection with ind J&gt; g April last. The Marquess gratuity of one and a half mon is pay ogal on t p e understanding that no of Crewe is prepared to c o ns ® nt , Z e( { annU al contribution from Indian increase is thereby involved t Jeddah In this connection a reference Revenues in respect of the Consulate ^% c ^Xttev of 1st March 1911, is invited to the third paragraph of Sn of t i ie cos t of that and to previous correspondence, regarding the incidence Consulate. X Pave, &amp;c., ^ , T. W. Holderness. The Under Secretary 01 btate, Foreign Office. ENCLOSURE No. 4 Foreign Office to India Office. _ at qcooi Foreign Office, No. 36,331. ^gth September 1913. Slr ’ With reference to your letter P. 2825, of the 5th ultimo, respecting the proposed Gratuity to the Indian cavass at Jeddah, I am directed by Secretary C F Grl’v to observe that, as the cavass is paid direct from Indian funds ft wmild seem that any increase in his wages would also be paid dnect, and would not, therefore, affect the fixed annual contribution. l am, cxc., The Under Secretary of State Ralph Paget. for India.In any further communication on tWS' subject, please quote no.36331/13 . zT Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign (Idee, '-v London. September /2 1913 Sir With reference to your letter P. 2825 of the 5th ultimo respecting the proposed gratuity to the Indian Cavass at Jeddah, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. G-rey to observe that, as the cavass is paid direct from Indian funds it would seem that any increase in his wages would also be paid direct and would not, therefore, affect the fixed annual contribution. I am Sir Your most obedient humble Servant re Under Secretary of State, India Office.■ h&gt; , Foreign Office July /Lf' 1913 0N iC With reference to the letter from this Office of the 29th. of September 1912 (No.36981/12) on the subject of certain payments to cavasses and other employees of His Majesty’s Consulate at Jeddah, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward G-rey to state for the information of the Marquess of Crewe, that a grant of thirteen and. a half months pay for twelve months service was sanctioned by the Colonial Office in respect of the Malay Cavass. Sir E. Grey would therefore suggest that, in accordance w r ith the request contained in Mr. Shipley s despatch of the 4th. ultimo, a copy of vhich was for warded to the India Office on the 27th. ultimo, a similar’ concession should be made by the Marquess of Crewe in respect of the Indian Cavass employed at Jeddah ie Under Secretary of State India Office. eiennr 917 (28681/13) Jeddah, to take effect as from the let. of April laBt. ) 0 ) I am. *&gt; Sir, Your most oled-ient. humble Servant,In ahy further comii/uiiica- tion on mis subject, please quote no. 8'^//3 and address— The Undersecretary of State, Foreign Office London. I f) -S... 7^C?v ;7^v 9 T/ie Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents (L his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^ — — and, by direction of the Secretary of of the tmder-mentioned paper. State, transmits herewith cop o If Cf t A &gt; V' 2. ^ / / Foreign Office, SL C c*- C 9 r i Description of Inclosnre. Name and Date. Subject. 4 ./s fV * 30 JUm3D ; Jvi ' - * ’ 5 &gt; r i . k A s ' V JT^OC v «- , \ ^ .• ^ i ^ s 2P681 h±J ,4 ^ 2 ■-„./ i JUN2519^ : : JEDDAH, Jus.@ 4,1913. Sir, With reference to despatch from the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs No. 9 (50966/12) of December 5,1912, in which I was informed that the Governor of the Straits Settlements saw no objection to the payment out of public funds of thirteen and &amp; half months salary for one year’s service to the Malay Cavass attached to this Consulate, I have the honour to enquire whether the same grant will be sanctioned by the Secretary of State lor India in respect to the Cavass employed on ousiness connected with the Indian pilori s. Abdul Samad, the cavass in question, has been in the service of this Consulate for over ten years and is invaluable where British Indian Subjects, whether pilgrims ?he Right Honourable Sir E.Grey K.G. Bart. His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsT @ pilgrims or residents, are concerned and a yearly gratuity such as that proposed would mar* the aovernment of India’s appreciation of his services and abolish the difference which now exists between him and the other oavasses, who receive the gratuity, the one fr^m the Colonial Office, the other from His Majesty’s Consul. If the grant is sanctioned, I venture to reauest that it be made as from April 1,1013. I have the honour to be, With the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant^ (iy Chral O-IA.'T-'-’t--- • fN In Vny fiu^Mr coinii\unicali»H. on this subject, please quote no. 36983/1^ • and address— The Ultder-Seeretary of State, Foreign Oflice, London. J \ Foreign Office September ij , 1912• Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s £ 1 . Consul at that place to charge in his account with the Government of India a sum not exceeding One pound a month for the hire of a punkah-wallah during those months when a punkah is indispensable, the arrangement to have effect as from June 1st last* I am to enquire whether the Marquis of Crewe is willing to grant Mr. Shipley’s request. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, RkCHSVFQ | j 10 SEP 1912 j i ! i 1 ri U »* Of- t’iU Zz.jj The Under Secretary of State, India Office.-TV &gt;py. i. 11. tX W' 4 i W BRITISH CONSUUTH, JEDDAH. August 19, 1912. Sir: - J Q | i ^' fi &lt;&amp;*+ I have the honour to request, that T may be authorised to charge in the Quarterly account with the Foreign Office the customary gratuity of one months pay at Balram and one half months pay on the King's Birthday to the Cavass employed on behalf of the Malay pilgrims. These two gratuities are obligatory and no cavass could be obtained at the wages paid at present by the Consulate excepting on the understanding that he receive thirteen and a half months' pay in the year; and that the Vice Consul be authoriz-ed to charge in his account with the Government of India a sum not exceeding one pound per month for the hire of a punkah- olah during those months when it is indispensable that a punkah should be used - the authorization to take ef fect as from the first of June 1912. Neither of these charges are incurred in the course of the ordinary business of this Consulate ana they should, I venture to think, not be made to rank with The Fight Honourable Sir Edward Gray, Bart., K.Q. &lt;&amp;i0 • f «j •with those covered by the Office Allowance, which is barely sufficient to cover the actual faxpanses of the Consular Office apart from the Indian and Malay work. I have &amp;c., *% ^ . (Signed) Avalon Shipley.\■■ No. 82 of 1912. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. ESTABLISHMENT. To The Most Hon’ble the MARQUIS of CREWE, K.G., His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India. My Lord Marquis, With reference to Your Lordship’s Political despatch No. 47, dated the 10th May 1912, we have the honour to forward, for your information, a copy of the orders which we have passed on Mr. Consul Monahan’s recom mendation for the grant of a personal allowance of Rs. 50 a month to Assistant Surgeon Abdur Rahman, His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Jeddah. Simla, the 11th July 1912. We have the honour to he, My Lord Marquis, Ydur Lordship’s most obedient, humble servants, (ji^ t -UMi\ X ' No. 2074-Est. (A). Feom The DEPUTY SECEETAEY to the GOVERNMENT op INDIA in the Foreign Department, To J. H. MONAHAN, Esq., HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSUL, JEDDAH. Dated Simla, the 5th July 1912. Sir ’ T nm directed to refer to your letter, dated the 16th March 1912 recom- s-g*,.AM.. 4bd „ Wd. - 2 . 1 am t0 ex P lai nfp of an d has not reached the maximum appointment on a progressi rovernm ^ , of India are not prepared to sanction pay of his appointment, ^ U i n view however, of the special cireums- r srxc t a «t» ?m i b, »..»»....« June 1913. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, W. H. J. WILKINSON, Tirrmtu Secretary to the Government of India.1912. SIMLA. foreign department establishment. No. 82, BATED THE llTH JtTLY 1912. Letter to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India Grant of a personal allowance to His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul, JeAUh. roreign Office Press— No. 636 —6-7-12-2 i.t- c'^* In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address- (oiT- The Under-Secretafy of State, Foreign Office, London; ^ . Vh W ' The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secret ary of State for | and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop \ Co of the under-mentioned paper, Foreign Office, fl4 Cc4tuL ~ , Igi2. --UV(z£ w- ).33. BBITISH EMBASSY, jupu'i ar . CONSTANTINOPLE. 5587 ) April 4t2i, 191E . Sir I have the honour to forward herewith a despatch, as marked in the margin, for transmission to the Government of India, forwarding an application for personal allowance Jeddah. from the A-eting Di Hish CuiHUl at “T' I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Gerard Lowther. His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.’ tao.-JTv 1 yK i- ■ BBITIBH CONSULATE, ^ JEDDAH. March 16th, 1912 Sir:- In continuation of ray Despatch No.35 of 8th. March 1912, I have the honour to transmit herev/ith an appli cation from Vice Consul Dr. Abdur Rahman for a personal allowance of 50 rupees a month. I would give his application my strongest possible support. The statements he makes of the excessive and increasing dearness of living and as ‘to the high pay always given to commercial clerks are accurate. His predecessor was granted such allowance on account of dearness when living was much cheaper than now. The manner in which Dr. Abdur Rahman has performed his duties when under my orders and when for practi cally no extra remuneration he has been acting for me. entitles him, so far as such performance could entitle any public servant, to such emoluments as will free him from all money difficulties which his present emoluments lie Secretary to the Govera men t of jndla in the Foreign Department, i i -- mtirnwmmmmm Simla.emoluments certainly cannot do, and his long services before coming to Jeddah are well known to Government. As to his private medical practice he has little or no time for any for half the year when the pilgrims are numerous here, and considering the email and penurious population, it can at any time bring in but little. I would earnestly recomend his application to the favourable consideration of the Government of India. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) J. H. Monahan. His Britannic Majesty's Consul.n ' BRITISH CONSULATE, JEDDAH. March 15th, 1912. Sir:- I have the honour to puhrait thlB application for BUhmiBBion to the Government of India with your favour able remarks. (1) That there being no means of educating my children in this country I am obliged to bear the cost of keeping them in the M.A.0.Collegiate School Aligarh and have to bear an expense of 100 Rupees per month, a substantial amount of my pay, and on account of extremely expensive living of this place my pay is quite rj inadequate to enable me to live up to the requirements of ray position. (2) The complaint of the expensive living of this place was brought to the notice of the Government of India by my predecessor vide No.15 of 23rd. April 1904 and his predecessor vide letter No.61 of 8th December on/i +&gt;no rm-inoe hft va riflri v been going ud since \ then J. H. Monahan, Esq., His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Jeddah.then, and they have now reached almost famine limits compared with those obtaining in India. (3) Notwithstanding all the disadvantages of living in a place like this, away from my own people, I have faithfully stuck to my post for the last three years, and I venture to hope that the Government of India may he graciously pleased to give me at least what was given to my predecessor, that is, a personal allowance of 50 Rupees per month as the reasons for which this personal allowance was given to him apply in my case with greater force, the conditions of life having grown worse in every way. (4) I have a service of 15 years out of which for 7 years I have served the Government in foreign countries first as medical officer in the Persian Gulf for 4 years and now as Vice Consul here for the last three years. In India I held important posts as Assistant Burgeon, among others as officiating lecturer of surgery in the Agra Medical School, and Assistant Surgeon in charge of Colvin hospital Allahahad and lastly Balrampur Hospital Lucknow. I may mention that in Lucknow in addition to my private practice my post carriedcarried an allowance of 125 Fupees per month and only my deeire to serve the Government out of India and a hope that the Government vri.ll he pleased to give me all the privileges enjoyed hy my predecessor made me accept this post. ( 5 ) During my stay here I venture to submit that I carried my duties diligently and conscientiously all these years and for a period of seven months I carried out the combined duties of Consul and Vice Consul I have to add that twice my name has been mention ed in the despatches of His Lajesty's Secretary of State j| approving my Haj Reports. (6) I would venture to point out that His Majesty’s Vice Consul at Hodeidah, a place comparative ly much cheaper receives a summer allowance and an entertainment allowance, and an Imperial contribution of £350 per annum is also allotted to that Vice Consulate in addition to what he receives as his pay from the Government of India. Clerks of commercial houses in Jeddah draw from 250 Rupees to 300 Rupees a during the absence of Consul on leave. month. Onn On the ground of the dearnepp of this place Hip Majesty's Foreign Office have Increased the allowance of this Conpulate from £300 to £400 per annum. The pay of the Vice Consular staff wap also raised by the Government of India, with the exception of that of Vice Consul who was at that time getting maximum pay of the post and a personal allowance of 50 Rupees per , 'A (AJ month vide Government of India Foreign Department No.2182 E.A. of 2nd. July, 1909. I have, &amp;c.. (Signed) A. Abdurrahman British Vice Consul- W, '[ 12; r &gt; . In any further ccmmumca- tion on this subject, please quote Ko - iao^ iqn ind address— ' The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. k 18JAN1911 @ ^h/fo X r rr '' The Under-Secretayy of State for Foreign Affairs presents I I I his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for &gt; ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copcJi of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, I O , IQl\ r ) 18 Reference to previous letter: 1-0. I? Description of Inclosure. 'll Name and Date. u^j Subject. (Similar letter sent ter ):opy. TREASURY CHAMBERS, loth January 1911. 10 . 1202 ) Sir:- I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of His kajesty's Treasury Mr. Langley's letter of the 28th November i)\ i lest (42131/10) and its enclosures, respecting the incidence of the cost of His Majesty's Consulate at Jeddah. In reply I am to state, that, es Secretary Sir i.Grey is aware, India's contribution in respect of the expenses of this Consulate is included in the annual payment of £6,000 (since reduced to £4,087.10. 0.) which she undertook to pay this country under the agreement of September 1900 as an equitable settlement of mutual claims under the awaruoi the Roval Commission on Indian expenditure. Except for the reduction in respect of the Consulate et Kerman, in consequence of the transfer oi that post to Indian Administration, no modification has been made in the amount of this annual contribution, and My Lords would remind The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.r * remind Sir E. Grey that in 1904 They declined to press a claim for £200 per annum extra against the Government of Indie in respect of Basrah Consulate on the ground that it was undesirable to reopen the general settlement of 1900, A. :t y (Vide Treasury reply of 5th August 1904 to Foreign Office I Letter of 29th June 1904) s view which was recently repeated in Their Lordships' letter to your Department of the 2nd ^' November last (17037/10). ky Lords see no reason to reconsider Their decision and They therefore feel unable to assent to any alteration such as that proposed by the India Office in the existing financial arrangements with regard to Jeddah. I am &amp;c., (Signed) T.L. Heath.Sir, iqio ^pprowd Pol Coi'®6-- 15 MOV 1910 finance committee make no observation 16 NOV. 1910 I am directed to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter of the 14th .October,No .36301/10, regarding expenditure in connec tion with His Majesty's Consulate at Jeddah. In reply I cun again to point out that, when a sum of &lt;£790 per annum was decided up on- in 1899 as the moiety of the cost of the Jeddah Consulate payable from Indian revenues,it was cal culated with reference to the whole charges jand not to the so- called 'fixed' charges alone. The distinction between 'fixed' and other charges,although it may be useful for certain purposes of account t is irrelevant to the present issue} and as it has been shown that India is now paying considerably more them half of the total charges of the Consulate, the Secretary of State for India in Council is aware of no reason why she should not be relieved of the excess. I cim accordingly that the correspondence may now be laid before the Treasury with a view to the adoption of the proposal made in this Office letter of 51 h .May 1909. Jhfo &amp; * ^ ^$3 ss) 'This is the third attempt of the Foreign Office to shuffle out of an embarrassing situation which they have created for themselves. In December 1908 they askea us to increase our annual contribution in respect oj the Jeddah Consulate (viz—U/90 a year) by £75 a year, on the ground that the pay ana allowances of the Consul had been increased by £150, On our eliciting from them that this increase voas more than counterbalanced by decreases in other expenditure of the Consulate they naively said that they would not n press” their proposal (F,0, letter oj' 25th February 1909). We then pointed out that according to the information which we had elicited from tnem we are paying considerably more than half the charges of tne Consulate and suggested that as an equitable arrangement our contribution should oe reduced by £190 a year for 5 years. The reply was that as the ”fixed charges” remained the 'seme” (which was not the case, as they had increased}, the Foreign Ofj ice aid not consider that there was any sufficient reason for revising the contribution. They presumed that thethe India Office haa no intention of re-assessing the various items which entered into the general Agreement of 1900. We replied that when the Jeddah contribution is revised all the charges (and not merely the officer's pay and allowances) must he taken into account, and that it was the Foreign Office themselves who first suggested a revision. Their present reply is very lame ana will not stand analysis. The question now to be considered is whether the proposal made by this Office for a reduction of the contribution should be pressed, or the matter be dropped pending a revision o.f the Agresmsnt, if, ana when,such a revision takes place. In a nooe by this Deparov^no on Pol,3337/10, the financial position which has resulted from the Agreement is stated as follows (1) In respect of Persia and Turkish Arabia we spend, after taking account of all j inane lal adjustments, about &lt;£9,000 a year more than the Foreign Office. (2) Ws bear the whole cost of Mu skat, amounting to about &lt;£9,000 a year but on the other hand. (3) The Foreign Office expenditure China has risen from 72,200 (approximately) in 1900-01 to 6839,500 (approximately) (estimate for 1910-11) while our contribution a year has remained stationary. Iso of Bahrein 3,700 in 08-9) ana Kashgar ounting probably as much, per- ps more).If, therefore, a revision of the Agreement were to take place the balance of advantage would probably be on our side, and we have, therefore, I think, nothing to fear from a revision, but it is another question whether we ought to press for trie revision of a small item in our payments which has been regarded as fixed since 1900-01 m We have also to consiaer whether pressure on the Foreign Office in this small matter would adversely affect the success of our claims in -respect of:- (1) the discontinuance of the advance payment of &lt;M,087. 10 made annually in our financial adjustment with the Foreign Office. (2) the Military Attache at Meshed. (3) the expenditure at Koweit. On the whole I am inclined to think that in view of the clearness of our case we ought to press the claim. A draft letter is attached:- JMorley, that variations of incidental expenditure can he taken into account, when a general revision of the fixed contribution to Indian funds is made There is however, no question of revising the amoun of that contribution at present. Sir E. Grey considers that it is unnecessary in the meantime to deal with anything except changes in the fixed DECEIVED j 10 SUE. 15 OCT 1910 OFrJCE. charges, and I am to point out with reference to th * c letter from this Department of the 29th of Feoruary 19.09 that no claim has been put forward in respect &lt; the The Under Secretary of State, India Office. 36301/10). I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to ac knowledge the receipt of your letter of the 6th instant, respecting the incidence of the cost of His Majesty's consulate at Jeddah. I am to state, for the information of Viscount .15 OCT FOREIGN OFFICE, October i ’ 1910.the fixed charges at Jeddah I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant,In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 17153/09. and address — Foreign Office The Under-Secretary of State, /V ' 1 \ / * / ■ . \ I yj May ‘nr* ' j May , 1909. — Foreign Office, ) London. \Om ” ; ; Sir:- I &amp; r n directed by Secretary Sir E.Grey to acknow ledge the receipt of your letter of the 5th instant respecting the expenditure in connection with his ha- jesty's Consulate at Jeddah. I am to state for the information of Viscount Morley that any reduction which may have occurred in the expenditure on this post during the three years ending March 31st, 1908 can merely have arisen from a falling off in the incidental charges such as tra- veiling expenses and telegrams. The fixed charges remain the same and Sir E.Grey does not therefore con sider that there is any sufficient reason fox’ levising ih^he contribution from Indian Revenues. The existing arrangement forms part of the gener al adjustment made in 1901 and it is presumed that there is no intention of re-assessing the various items The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(17153/09) items of that adjustment at the present time. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Reference Paper. 3o52 Political and Secret) Department.) Letter No. Rec. 190 . 2/ V • 5U -^*25. „, Referred to Vb. Sc t^r-v^'A^^co — M day of 1904. 1 ^ a^j \ &gt; \ ^ 'fv hi’ \ ‘908 | ■^4. Uv ! Ci o H ■ if-— y V'- TTjs repiy s??ews that daring the years for which the figures are given, viz. 1905-6, 1906-7, and 1907-8, the annual contribution of *£790 a year from Indian revenues, instead of being less, was considerably wrethan half the expenditure from Imperial funds. It would not be reasonable, I think, to ask for any refund from the Foreign Office in respect of these years, but there appears to be food ground for asking for some redaction of our contribution with \ effect from the present financial year. In estimating the amount, of the reduction.however, it would not be fair k, take the average expenditure in 1905-6, 1906-7, and 1907-8 as a basis, since the total payments on account of Salary. Local Allowance, and Office Allowance were abnormally low in 1906-7 and 1907-8 owing to the post being vacant during part of those years. Had these payment? been on the same scale as is now contemplated, viz. a year, CAj the average total expenditure by the Foreign Office in the three years ’would have been *£713. 16. 0,It is possible, of course «£’. s • d • Salary Local Alice. &amp; Office Alice. ■ 345 O (3 x 1150) Other charges 181. 14. 3. (J905-6 i 344 . 16 . 2 . [1906-7j 306. 5. (2907-8/ 314282. f-ip' ~ jggV 12, %-* 713 . ILL A A A A A A A A A A A A _y 2778. I. 447. 1000.—3/1908. dffUi ZA lift */c ~\ that similar causes may operate in the future to reduce the amount of Sal ary t Local Allowance, and Office Allowance, and for this reason it would seem fai^ to suggest to \y v-v i . * A* V 1 ^to the Foreign Office that the Indian contribntion should be fixed at •£700 a year for 0 years, subject to reconsideration at the end of that time. The most convenient method of adjustment would, seem to be an annual payrr&amp;n t of ^90 a year to this Office by the Foreign Office. S', a. r i v &amp; 856 l 1909. d SA fa ■ fl V I/)In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 6664/09. and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. February , 1909. Foreign Office Sir:- With reference to your letter of the 16th instant re specting the increase in the expenditure in connection with His Majesty’s Consulate at Jeddah, I am directed by Secre- ation of the Secretary of State for India, the accompanying statement of the total cost of the post during the last three years. In view of the amount of the average expenditure Sir E. G-rey does not desire to press the claim for an additional contribution from Indian Revenues in respect of Office expenses. tary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith,,for the inform- V 1 I am, Your most obedient, Sir, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.// ^ / would suggest that in the first instance the Foreign Office be asked to state what the total expenditure from Imperial funds in connection with the Consulate has been during the past 3 years. It may be, as Sir T. Holdemess suggests, that these figures will shew a greater increase over £1,580 than the £110 which has taken place in the two items of salary and office allowance, but whether this be so or not the information seems necessary for a satisfactory treatment of the case. It has, however, been privately ascertained from the Foreign Office that the expenditure on telegrams during the past 3 years has been about £300 a year less than during the years on the result of which the contribution of £790 a year was based, and it is quite possible that the total expenditure has fallen. The Foreign Office officials did not take out the figures for telegrams and other contingencies before writing to us.Q- 'L-j / In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 44454/08. T /l Zlotys' .. . , (%0 ; 4 ^ ' —— i r ''.ih and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. !r . u-&lt;7 r ' ' J (£790) £700. £300. £ 1 , 000 . Foreign Office December ,1908. Sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E.Grey to request that you will submit to the Secretary of State for In dia the following facts in connection with the contri bution made by the Indian Government towards the ex penses of His Majesty's Consulate at Jeddah. ^ j 9^ In the arrangement which was arrived at in 1900 between the India Office and this Office, respecting the payment of the expenses of this and other Consu lar posts, the fixed contribution (Seven hundred and ninety pounds) made by the Indian Government was taken into account. At that time the salary assigned to the post was Seven hundred pounds, with an Office Al lowance of Three hundred pounds, the total being thus One thousand pounds. The emoluments now attached to the post are * salary The Under Secretary of State, RECEIVED to a.rn. 2 JAN. 1909 INDIA OFFICBo India Office.Mi L? £600. £150. £V0. r £ 1 , 110 . £40. £1,150. £75. (44454/08) salary Six hundred pounds. Local Allowance One hundred and fifty pounds, and Office Allowance Three hundred and sixty pounds, a total of One thousand one hundred and ten pounds, while it is proposed to increase the Office Allowance Ly Forty pounds, from April 1st next which will raise the total annual cost of the post to One thousand one hundred and fifty pounds. In addi tion to this there are contingent expenses such as travelling, postage, telegrams,pensions etc. I am to point out that the necessity for increas ed expenditure at Jeddah is largely due to the in crease in the number of British Indian Pilgrims, who cause a large amount of work to fall on the Consular Staff. In view of this consideration Sir E. Grey would propose, subject to the concurrence of Viscount Morley, that half of the additional expenditure since 1900,or Seventy-five pounds, should be defrayed from the re venues of the Indian Government. Sir E.Grey does not wish to make any claim in respect of the extra ex penditure incurred between 1900 and the end of the pre sent 15689. I. 505. 2000—3/1905.? I Q (44454/08) present, financial year, but is of opinion that a con tribution of the above amount might justly be made from the 1st April 1909. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,mm.u 0 i ■ % 2 . j^^cf&lt;f&lt;r w No. 107 of 1905. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA* FINANCE DEPARTMENT. SALARIES, ES TAB LISHMENTS, etc. Personal Allowanced r F O 7 4- ^ 04 i 9 0 E ) k To Tue Right Eon’ble St. JOHN BRORRICK, Bis Majesty's Secretary of State for India, k % Sir, Calcutta, the 23rd March 1905. We have the honour to transmit to you a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Consul at Jeddah, recommending the grant of some special concessions to Hr. S. Muhammad Hussain, His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Jeddah. In our Poreign Department letter No. 4369-E. B., dated the 24th December 1904 (copy enclosed), we have passed orders on all the proposals contained in the despatch, except that relating to an increase in Dr. Hussain’s pay, and the present despatch deals with this latter proposal. 2 . Dr. Hussain’s predecessor, Dr. Abdur Razzak, applied, as far back as 1885, for an increase of salary, but his application was refused on the ground that his pay was already high for an officer of Vice-Consular rank. In the 3 ear 1895, Dr. Bazzak applied for the grant of a personal allowance of R100 a month, and this was recommended to the Bight Hon’ble H. H. Fowler, then Her Majesty’s Secretary of State, in a despatch No. 125 (Finance and Commerce), dated the 21st May 1895. The necessity for the grant of the allowance, however, was removed, as very soon afterwards Dr. Bazzak met his death in the course of an attack made on certain British Consular Officers near Jeddah. 3. Dr. Hussain was first appointed to the post in 1896 on a pay of R300 25—400, and has been drawing the maximum pay of the appointment, viz., B400 a month, since the 1st of May 1900. We are not satisfied that there is sufficient reason for increasing the pay of the post, but in view of Dr. Hussain’s meritorious services at Jeddah and of the long period that has elapsed since he obtained his last increment of pay, we consider that his case c sr ;2 deserves exceptional treatment, and we therefore recommend the grant to him of a personal allowance of R50 a month with effect from the 1st of April next. We have the honour to be,. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servants, (Signed) CURZON. „ KITCHENER. E. R. ELLES. A. T. ARUNDEL. DENZ1IL IBBETSON. H. E. RICHARDS. J. P. HEWETT. E. N. BAKER. 1 r /UM305 ^' 4 4 KGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Enclosures of Despatch No. 107 of 1905 . Enclosure No. 1.] Dated 23rd April 1904*. From—G. P. Devet, Esq., His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Jeddah, To —The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honour to forward herewith an application from Vice-Consul Dr. Muhammad Husain asking for exemption from septennial examination and for other privileges. I trust that it will he found possible to place Dr. Muhammad Husain on the same footing as Consular officers employed under the regulations of the British Foreign Office, and consider that he is qualified in every respect for the charge of an independent post. Besides the unhealthiness of the climate of this place, which is very trying even to the natives of British India, Con sular officers cannot enjoy free exercise and liberty except under restrictions of excessive precautions. In addition to the above inconveniences I should mention that the pres sure of work, which during the height of the pilgrimage, is very considerable, appears to be growing yearly more heavy, but I trust to the advantage of both pilgrims and of the resident British Indians: but little time is left for private repose and recreation. For these reasons and those advanced by Dr. Muham mad Husain I venture to hope that exceptional treatment may be accorded to him. It is with much pleasure that I take this opportunity, when on the point of leaving Jeddah, of stating that I have observed with much satisfaction the devotion of Dr. Muhammad Husain to his duties and his anxiety and care to find ever new means for assisting and protecting the British subjects residing in or resorting to the Hedjaz. His reputation for surgical skill has been established leven in the interior of the country, and he is untiring in his attention to the sick and needy of all nationalities. Dated 21st April 1904. From— Dr. S. Muhammad, Husain, Br itish Vice-Consul, Jeddah, To—G. P. Devby, Esq., His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Jeddah. I have the honour to request the favour of your forwarding this my application for the favourable consideration of the Government of India, with any remarks that you may be kindly inclined to offer. 2. Before leaving India, while I was in medical charge of the Barh Sub- Division and the Dispensary, I was pro- Proceedings No. 29 in External A, August 1896i mised the post of a teachersMp LU One of No8 - 26to46 ' the Medical Schools of Bengal, which usually carries a pay of R350 per month (copy of the letter of the Inspector General of Civil Hospitals, Bengal, inclosed), but my desire to serve the Gov ernment beyond the limits of India prompted me to come to this country. 3. Since my appointment to this present post in February 1896, I have always tried to discharge my duties Proceedings No. 40, idem. faithfully and to give satisfaction to my superiors, and gain the confidence of the official and non-official public with vffiom I had to deal with as a Vice-Consul or a medical man, and I believe I have been successful in my endeavours. Thrice I have been placed in charge of this Consulate for a total period of more than 16 months, and my services have received the approval of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and His Majesty’s Ambassador at the Sublime Porte.^ 4 . There being no means of educating my children in this country, I have to keep my family in India, and consequently have to bear the cost of keeping2 mKtKKmmmmmmmmmrnm R1 to ftl-4. R1 to Rv. Rl to RI-8. R2. Rl to Rl-4. R2-8. R30 to R40. R15 to R20. two houses; and on account of the extremely expensive living of this place my present pay is quite inadequate to enable me to live up to the requirements of my position without creating pecuniary embarrassment. The complaint of the expensive living of this place was brought to the notice of the Govern ment of India by my predecessor, the late Dr. Abdur Razzack, a short time before his death letter No. 61,* dated ^•P^ng.No. i°9 in Extend A , 8th December 1894, addressed by 9 ’ ° 9 ' 0 ‘ Mr. Consul Richards to the Government of India), and the prices have decidedly been going up since then, and they have now reached almost the famine limits compared to those obtaining in India. A fair idea can be made from some of the usual prices given below (a) Four skinfuls of water of bad quality . (5) One seer of mutton .... (c) One fowl . . • • • (d) One seer of ghee . . • • • (g) One seer of vegetable . . • • (f) W ashing of clothes per dozen . . \g) Wages of a cook per month . . . (h) Wages of a table boy .... 5. In India as an Assistant Surgeon I was always provided with free quarters, and although I was getting there much less than my present pay, my private practice, of which I have practically none here, used to contribute a good deal to my income, which combined with the cheapness of the necessities of life in India provided me with a decent living. Notwithstanding all the disadvantages of living in this place, I have faithfully stuck to my post for more than eight years without unduly pressing my case upon the notice of the Government of India, but I am afraid continuation of this state of things is sure to involve me in greater pecuniary difficulties ; therefore most respectfully I venture to hope that the Government of India may be graciously pleased to give my following requests a favourable consideration :— ( 1 ) To exempt me from the second professional septennial examination, and to promote me to the grade of Civil Medical Officers, so that in the event of my returning to India I may be given charge of a district. (2) To count my one year’s service in this place as one year and half towards calculating for pension, as allowed by the London Foreign Office to the Consular Officers serving in this place, on account of the unhealthiness of the climate, which, due to the restrictions placed by the Turkish authorities on the movements of the Consular officers, specially from the time of outrage on the Consuls in 1895, effects more or less equally all the Consular officers, European or non-European. ( 8 ) To grant me house allowance of R33 per month which I am paying , _ at present from my own pocket, and which has already been granted t to the Vice-Consul of Hodeida. (4) To raise my pay at least by one hundred rupees per month and make it R500. 6 . Even in the case of my returning to India my services will always be at the disposal of the Government to be utilised in the Political Depart ment in any of the Native States or on the frontiers for which work my long experience of this place, where one has the opportunity of mixing with people from all parts of the world and gaining wide and varied experience, and my thorough knowledge of Persian, Arabic and Indian languages, I venture to hope, qualify me. In conclusion I beg to state that the loyal and faithful services of my late father who had served the Government in the Military Medicnl Department with the forces under Colonel O’Neill and Sir Henry Havelock at Benares, Allahabad, Cawnpore, Futtehpore and other places during the most trying time of the Mutiny of 1857, might weigh in my favour when taking into consideration the question of my future prospects.3 Enclosure No. 2 .] No. 4369 E, B., dated 24th December 1904. From—C. Somers Cocks, Esq., C.M.G., Assistant Secy, to the Govt, of India, Foreign Department, To G. P. Devet, Esq., His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Jeddah. In reply to your letter, dated the 23rd April 1904, forwarding an applica tion from Vice-Consul Dr. S. Muhammad Husain for exemption from the second septennial examination, for promotion to the grade of Civil Medical Officers, and for certain other privileges, I am directed to communicate the following remarks and orders:— ( 1 ) Dr. Husain is exempted from passing his promotion examination while he remains at Jeddah, but when he returns to employment in India, the examination must be passed within one year of his taking up an appointment in India, otherwise he will revert to second class. (2) By asking to be promoted to the grade of “ Civil Medical Officer,” Assistant Surgeon Muhammad Husain apparently means, that on his return to India, he may be appointed to a Civil Surgeoncy reserved for medical subordinates of his class, under the terms of Home Department Resolution No. 1141-50 (Medical), dated the 22nd August 1898. No promise in this sense can be made to him; but he may be told that on the occurrence of a vacancy after his return to India in the list of Civil Surgeoncies reserved in Bengal for Civil Assistant Surgeons, his claims will be taken into consideration with those of other Assistant Surgeons belong ing to the Bengal Provincial Establishment. (3) The proposal that the Vice-Consul should be permitted to reckon service for pension, on the basis of one year’s service counting as one year and a half, is open to strong objection, and cannot be agreed to. In making reference to the fact that a concession of this kind is allowed to officers who are subject to the British Consular Regulations, it appears to have been overlooked that the Indian pension rules are framed for officers who have to serve in tropical and unhealthy climates, and are more liberal in their provisions than the English Superannuation Act. (4) A house-rent allowance of R33 a month for Dr. Muhammad Husain is sanctioned. 2 . The question of an increase in Dr. Husain’s pay is under further consideration, and orders will issue on this in due course.Schedule of Papers. No. 1. Despatch from His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Jeddah, dated the 23rd April 1904, and enclosure, viz ,:— Letter from the British Vice-Consul, Jeddah, dated tho 21st April 1904. No. 2. Letter to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Jeddah, No. 4369-E, B,, dated the 24th December 1904. v sCopy. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. SAL AR IES, ESTAB LISHMENTS, etc. Personal Allowances. r PitOM The GOVERNMENT of INDIA, The SECY, of STATE foe INDIA. ' No. 107. Dated Calcutta, the 23rd March 1905. Deceived Proposed grant of a personal allowance to Dr. S. Mu* hammad Hussain, His Britannic Majesty’s Vice* Consul at Jeddah.— ■ 'IJJH 1 ITS, etc, ttli, &gt; India Office, London, 18th October ] 900. Financial, No. 178. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Loud, In continuation of my Despatch, dated the 19th of July Royal Commission on Indian Rxpendi- FTo. 120, legal ding' the recom- ture - mendations of the Loval Com- mission on Indian Expenditure respecting the apportionment of the Home Charges, I transmit, for the information of your Government, a # Letter to Treasury, dated 17th July 1900. Letter from ditto, dated 26th July 1900. Letter to ditto, dated 2nd August 1900. Letter from ditto, dated 10th August 1900. Letter from ditto, dated 11th September 1900 (with enclosure). Letter to ditto, dated 11th October 1900. copy of the correspondence* that has taken place on the subject. 2. Your Excellency will observe that those recommendations, after the necessary correction, would have resulted in the relief of Indian revenues by 257,000/. a year ; and that although it has been thought convenient to simplify the Accounts by an alteration of the mode of giving that relief, the Imperial Govern ment have consented to arrangements which will amount approximately to the same annual sum. 11 toDr.S' 1 ’ ijesty I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Geoiige Hamilton.ENCLOSURES. No. 1 . Sir E. 3418. India Offi ce, r i • j -i i July 1900. I am directed by the Secretary of State for India in Council to draw tiie attention of the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury to the proposals of the Royal Commission on Indian Expenditure regarding the apportionment of charge between the Governments of the United Kingdom and of India for purposes in which both interested. According to paragraph 364 of the Report of the Commission the total amount of the annual charges to be transferred from the Revenues of India to those of the United Kingdom would be approximately 293,000/.; but this includes a sum of 108,000 pounds sterling as one half of the military charges for Aden which should have been stated as 108,000 tens of rupees, so that a deduction of 36,000/. must be made. The total amount of the relief which India would receive, if all the recommendations of the Commission were adopted, would therefore be not 293,000/. but 257,000/. a year. I am desired to express Lord George Hamilton’s confident hope that the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury will accept the unanimous opinion of the Commission, in so far as it is in favour of relieving the revenues of India to that extent. As regards the heads under which the relief should be given, I am directed to make the following suggestions. It appears to Lord George Hamilton that this opportunity might with advantage be taken to put an end to certain minor payments that are now made by India, and thus to simplify the accounts between the two Governments. At present the Secretary of State in Council pays 7,000/. a year on account of the Mission to the Court of Persia, 12,500/. a year for Her Majesty’s Establishments in China, and 1 , 787 /. as contributions towards the expenses of the Jeddah, Momein, and Busreh Consulates, making a total of 21,287/. for political charges. He also pays a subsidy of 10 , 000 /. a year to the Eastern Telegraph Company on account of the Zanzibar-Mauritius cable. I am to suggest that for the future all these contributions might be foregone by the Imperial Government. His Lordship assumes that 130,000/. will be allowed as half the cost of the transport of troops to and from India, and will be defrayed by the Imperial Government in accordance with the proposals of the Commission. With respect to the Military Charges for Aden, Lord George Hamilton desires me to suggest that the sum to be granted from Imperial revenues might equitably he fixed at 100,000/. a year, being slightly in excess of the share which the Commissioners considered that the Imperial Government should bear, but, on the other hand, somewhat less than the sum (108,000/.) by which they apparently intended that India should benefit under this head. 10623. BIf these suggestions are accepted by the Ijords Commissioners, the total amount of relief to be received by India will be 261,287^.,* a year, and Lord George Hamilton is * Political charges Telegraph subsidy Transport moiety - Share of Aden expenses Total £ 21,287 10,000 130,(00 100,000 - £261,287 to the Royal Commission. The Secretary of the Treasury. prepared to accept that; sum as satisfying the equitable claims of India under existing circumstances in respect of the subjects referred I have, &amp;c., A. Godley No. 2. No. 12,560. Treasury Chambers, Sir, 26th July 1900. I am directed by the Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury to acknowledge the receipt of your lettor (E. 3418) of the 17th instant, on the subject of the recommendations of the Royal Commission on the Administration of the Expenditure of India with regard to the financial relations between Her Majesty’s Government and the Government of India. As the proposals of the Secretary of State for India in Council affect not only the Treasury but also the Eoreign Office and War Office, it is necessary that my Lords should consult these Departments ; and this has been done by their Lordships, who, on receipt of replies, will communicate their decision to you forthwith. Meantime it would be convenient to their Lordships to be informed, as soon as possible, whether they are correct in assuming that Lord George Hamilton proposes that the new financial arrangements should come into force on 1 st April 1901. I am, Ac.,No. 13,585. Sir, I am directed by the Lords Commissioners of Her Maiesty’s n ' ea ^ t0 L C . kn 0 W i? d ' e tlie receipt of your letter of the 2 nd instant (h. d730j, stating that the Secretary of State for India in Council concurs m the view that the financial arrano'empni* wtnVL Tvm,r no The Lords Commissioners of Her Majesty’s Treasury have carefully considered, in communication with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Secretary of State for War, your letter of the 17th July 1900 relative to the recommendations of the Royal Commission on Indian Expenditure in favour of the transfer of certain annual charges from the revenues of India to those of the United Kingdom; and I am directed to request that you will submit to the Secrefary of State for India in Council the following reply. ^ After the necessary correction of the figure given by the Royal Commission for half the military charges^ for Aden, their recom mendations are that the following grants he made by the Imperial Crovernment to India :— r • £ In aid of the charge for the India Office - - 50,000 Half the military charges for Aden - - 72,000 Increased contribution to the charge of the Persian Mission - .... 5,000 Half the cost of the transport of troops to and from The modification of these proposals suggested in your letter under reply consists in the substitution, for the direct contribution in aid of the charge for the India Office and for the 5,000/. increase of contribution to the Persian-Mission, of the following :— Additional grant in respect of the military £ £ charges for Aden (making the total 100 , 000 /.) - ... 28,000 The waiver by the Imperial Government of certain minor payments now made annually by India:— 1. Subsidy to the Eastern Telegraph Company 4. Consulates at Jeddah, Momein and Basra 1,787 31,287 I am, &amp;c., for India. No. 5. No. 14,137. Treasury Chambers, 11 th September 1900. Sir, India 130,000 Total 257,000 on account of the Zanzibar-Mauritius Cable - 10,000 7,000 12,500 2 . Persian Mission 3. Establishments in China 59,287 A. TotalThis sum, together with 7^»000/. representing half the military charges for Aden and 130.000L representing half the cost of transport of troops, makes up a total of 261,287/., as compared with the 257,000/. recom mended hy the Royal Commission, heyond winch my Lords are not prepared to increase materially the contribution irom Imperial Lunds. ■ With reference to the aoove proposals, the Secretary of State foi Whr informs my Lords that he is prepared to make an annual contribution from 4rmy Funds, towards the cost of the transport of troops and towards the military charges for Aden, of 230,000/., to commence as from 1st April 1901. His Lordship, however, points out that the Royal Commission recommended that the capitation rate, which forms the basis of the contribution paid by India for Home Effective Charges, should be revised in live or six years, and he proposes therefore that the contribution of 230,000/. should remain in force for a similar period. Mv Lords concur in this proposal. # There remains to be considered the suggestion that the Imperial Government should forego the payments now made by India to the extent of 31,287/. per annum, as set out above. . My Lords fullv share the opinion of the Secretary of State in Council that it is desirable to take the opportunity of putting an end^ to these pavments, so far as circumstances justify, with a view to simplifying to that extent the accounts between the two Governments ; and, lor their part, they readily agree to give up the Indian contribution of 10,000/. per annum towards the subsidy for the Zanzibar-Mauritius cable. As regards the other payments by India which are now appropriated in aid of the Diplomatic and Consular Vote, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has expressed his views in a letter dated the 11th ultimo, of which I am to enclose a copy. It will be seen that the Marquess of Salisbury is prepared to forego the following sums :— ° £ For establishments in China - - 12,500 For the Persian Mission (the sum recom mended by the Royal Commission) - 5,000 17,500 2,000/. per annum would thus continue to be payable by India in respect of the Persian Mission. The Foreign Office letter points out that 1,787/. does not correctly represent the existing contributions for Jeddah, Momein, and Basra Consulates, which should be 2,664/. per annum, and suggests that India should continue to pay a lump sum of 6 , 000 /. (to include the remaining 2,000/. in respect of the Persian Mission, and the present contributions (a) for the Consulates at Jeddah, Momein, and Basra, and (b) for the Consulates at Kerman and Chiengmai). My Lords .concur in this suggestion, which would have the result of making the total concession to India about 500/. more than the 257,000/. per annum recommended by the Royal Commission. My Lords trust that the Secretary of State in Council will be able to accept the above proposals as satisfying the equitable claims of India* under existing circumstances, in respect of the subjects referred to the Royal Commission. I am, &amp;c., E. W. Hamilton. The Under Secretary of State for India.' Enclosure in No. 5 . Sir* Eoreign Office, • j • • . 1 n , ^ ^ 1 iX\J IJv^cAl cto cili &lt;X [J U i V J' puation-in-aid of the Diplomatic and Consular Vote, and that the 7,000^. now tarnished by India towards Imperial expenditure m Persia should be reduced by 5 , 000 /. With regard to the payments for the maintenance of Her Mniestv’s Consulates at Jeddah, Momein, and Basra, I am to observe that the sum of 1,787/. does not correctly represent the amounts supplied bv India for that purpose. The figures appear to have been taken from the Appropriation Account for 1898-99, which, amongst other things, only included a half-year’s contribution in the case of Basra. The items now stand as follows :— I am also to point out tnat contributions have hitherto been received fiom India towards the expenses of two other consulates, viz. :— that it is very desirable to put an end to the minor payments which are now made by India, and thus to simplify the accounts between the two Governments, and he gathers from the expressions contained in your letter that the Lords of the Treasury are of the same opinion. The periodical revision of these assessments gives rise to some incon venience, and to much lengthy correspondence. If the Secretary of State is asked to forego so large a sum as 17,500/. for the benefit of the Indian Exchequer, there seems to be no sufficient reason for disputing the exact figures at which the half share to be borne by India on account of each individual consulate should from time to time be fixed. Moreover, these special payments are apt to attract attention, and to give rise to adverse comment and criticism, relating as they do to places affected by so many diverse political considerations, and situated so far apart on the Red Sea and the Shatt-el-Arab and in remote provinces of Persia, China, and Siam. It appears to his Lordship that the desired simplification of accounts can best be effected by merging the smaller payments in one general contribution, which, however much reduced, might still be regarded as a share of the Imperial expenditure in China, Persia, and Siamr 10023. C For Jeddah - „ Momein - ,, Basra £ 790 474 (maximum) 1,400 £ For Kerman Chiangmai 1,000 400 (maximum) 1,400 Lord Salisbury entirely concurs in Lord George Hamilton’s s vjew1 am therefore to suggest, for their Lordships’ consideration, that the Government of India should for the future contribute 6,000/. per annum to the Diplomatic and Consular Vote, this sum being arrived at approximately as follows :— £ Ilemnant of general contribution for Persia 2,000 Existing contributions for Jeddah £ 790 ,, ,, „ Momein 474 ,, ,, ,, Basra 1,400 2,664 „ ,, „ Kerman 400 ,5 „ Chiengmai 1,000 — 1,400 &gt; . 6,064 i'he total amount at present paid from Indian revenues is 23,564/., and the saving to India by reducing this sum to 6,000/. is 17,564/., as compared with 17,500/., the figure mentioned in your letter. The Secretary to the Treasury. I am, &amp;e., T. H. Sandeuson. n No. 6 . *•4^. India Office, ^ r &gt; . 11 th October 1900. In acknowledging the receipt of your letter of the 11th of September No. 14,137, respecting the apportionment of the Indian Home Charges, I am directed to express the concurrence of the Secretary of State in Council in the proposal that the contribution by the Government ot India towards the expenses of the Persian Mission and the Miner Consulates shall be fixed at 6,000/. a year, or less by about 5,000/. than the amount for which they are at present liable. With this modification of the suggestions made in Sir Arthur Godley’s letter, dated the 17th of July, the reliefxlndian revenues in the apportionment of the Home Charges will be approximatelv as follows J ' S £ Transport of troops - - „ _ 130,000 Aden - - - . Iqo’oOO Zanzibar-Mauritius cable - _ ~ 10,000 China Establishments - - _ 12,500 Persian Mission, &amp;c. - - . 5,000 257,500 This arrangement will take effect on the 1st of April 1901, up to which date the payments by India will remain unaltered. The contribution of 230,000/. a year for the first two entries in the list will be subject to revision if and when any alteration is made in the capitation rate for the Army Effective Charges. I am, &amp;c., Hon ace Walpole. The Secretary of the Treasury.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100029145977.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/86/1</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100029145977.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/86/1</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 2776/1905 Pt 1 ‘Arabia:- Hodeidah Consulate. Expenditure etc’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1903/1910</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-07T18:35:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>180 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The first part of the volume (folios 95 to 275) contains correspondence and notes about British government expenditure on the consular establishment at the Red Sea port city of Hodeidah in Yemen. The correspondents are senior officials at the Foreign Office, the India Office and the Treasury in London and at the Foreign Department of the Government of India in Calcutta and Simla [Shimla], the Consul and Vice-Consul at Hodeidah, and the British Ambassador to the Court of the Sublime Porte of the Ottoman Empire at Constantinople. They discuss the pay and allowances of Dr G A Richardson the Vice-Consul at Hodeidah, and a proposal to increase his office allowance allocation, so that he might engage extra office assistance, in particular a competent dragoman (an official interpreter and translator) by offering a higher rate of personal allowance. There is also extensive correspondence about how the increased costs of the Hodeidah Vice-Consulate are to be divided between the Imperial Government in London and the Government of India. Included in the correspondence are representations made by the British Ambassador to Constantinople in 1907 about the importance of adequately funding the vital work of the Vice -Consulate in supporting trade and commerce; a statistical table showing the total annual costs of maintaining the Hodeidah Vice-Consulate in the years from 1887 to 1905; and an account of the settlement of a compensation claim in 1905 by the Vice-Consul, arising out of a piracy case.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100029145977.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>