<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000288_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:47:45.342Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Form D. It is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. VF. 1. No'\z. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. /'“S With reference to Foreign Office letter of No. , I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India regarding the appointment of as for and to say that the Secretary of State sees no objection to the issue of His Majesty’s Exequatur. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. 3771b 300 5.35Ljt. Harrison: I have spoken to the Ivlinistry of Health on the subject of procurement of indents for other branches of H.l .G.» and the situation is roughly as follov/s:- The Idnistry of Health have recently taken over the medical directorate of the Innistry of Supply together v/ith the latter's commitruants, and although they would be willing to purchase for other departments, if requested, they point out that they have no shij. ping facilities, which would have to be arranged by the department concerned. The main function of the Supplies Directorate of the llinistry of Health will, I gather, be procurement for home hospitals under the new Act. It is true that we do not icnow the size of the Political ■Resident's indent but therek I thin}:, only about five small hospitals and s fev/ dispensaries in the whole e, :ency and effecting procurement through the Ministry of Health would seem to savour rather of shooting snipe with a 15 inch gun. Although we have at the moment a Supply Section of our own, this will cease to function on the 3lst March so far as Indin is concerned, and though we may possibly be doing a little agency work for Pakistan after that date, the staff concerned will be under the payment of Paid.stan, and the duration of the arrangement is uncertain. It would, therefore, hardly seen worthwhile approaching Pakistan about the handling of the Persian Cr u df indent by us in such tm impermanent circumstances; and the best solution I think, would be for the Residency Surgeon to place his indents on approved wholesale firms of whom there are several, who would be responsible for the procurement and despatch of the goods required • such firms are Burgoyne, Burbidges; Boots pure Drug Company} Allen 1 Han bury sImperial Chemical Industries &gt;' and John sell &amp; Croyden, etc., etc., while surgical instruments could be handled by Messrs. Down Bros., Messrs. Allen &amp; Hanburys and Messrs. Weiss. I would suggest as Icing all the firms in the former (chemical category) to send to the Residency surgeon their indent forms; if supply is urgent he would have, in the first instance, to select one firm and order through them, but would be able to put his subsequent indents out to tender thereby assuring buying in the cheapest market. If you agree, this suggestion might be put to the Political Resident in response to his cable- I do not think that procurement through the Ministry of Health would be satisfactory in that - 'a) the indent is, comparatively, very small and (b) it would have to take its place in the routine work of the Directorate, which is voluminous, and the delay involved would probably be considerable. Jbn*’ u *’ / it /J. 10.3.1948mam 'Till you please accept transfer of the attached lettei* (ref. FDG/EDC dated the ?th Lay, 194^) from DakLn Brothers Ltd., together with the drug and chemical price lists covered by it. Messrs. Burgoyne Burbidges have not so far replied but it is understood their catalogues and forms are in the process of being printed. Sncs.wum Hartlcal Section ^ .&gt;0t3i April. 194^. Dear Sirs, •Ws Hei -whence tliis Office teloplioiie enquiries last month and this afternoon - The Residency Sur^;ec3n, lia^irain, Persia^ Gulf, is {tfixious to receive fron you indenting forms, price lists and cntaio^ies to enable him to older direct, supplies of medical stores urjently required. On these lists, etc. bocoirdiui available froiri your printers, despatch to tlie officer nettled ulove vdll be an*tu^;ed by this Office if you will kindly forward them to the above address. Yours faithfully# 3d/- M. LijJGH-JCilES for Medical Adviser. rOr the attention of the 'ixiort . .ana^r# rirfpyne* isurhid^es &amp; Go, Ltd.# ilfg. (Jierists, Dindi ists, High 3 treat, 3-OIIDOII, E. 6. \KHT/3B I4odical Sect cm ^Otli 194 ^ Dear si. *, I ackncKfltxli^e with thanks receipt of your letter reference KHT/38 dated the 28th -April, 1948. and «t: obliged to you for the fiction taken by your representative in furnishing the Residency surgeon, Bahrain, with a copy of your catalogue Yours faithfully, s'? JJLmiti MJeneral 1 •K.*S» (R)• • Iledical Adviser Allen &amp; Hanburys Limited, T^reo Colts Lane, Betimal Green, LQNDOI , s. 2.TELEPHONES BISHOPSGATE 32 O I (12 LI N E S) TELEGRAMS ‘GREENBURYS,BETH,LONDON ALLEN &amp;. HANBClRYS LTD SURGICAL DIVISION BETHNAL GREEN ♦ LONDON* E -2 kht/bb. 28th* April, 1948* Cpiomeroiel Relations Office, Mv ~ical Section, Clarence House, Matthew Parker Street, Westminster, S*W.l* Dear Sirs, With reference to your recent telephone request., we would inform you that the Resident Surgeon at the Government Hospital, Bahrain, now possesses a copy of our catalogue which was left hy our representative during his recent visit* Yours faithfully, 2 b rpr mExt,819/48 Dear Fisher, v^izU y^pc 21st April, 1948. With reference to the X^olitical Resident's telegram No.A/2C3 oi' 22nd Kerch of which a copy is enclosed, X forward herewith for transmission by you to 'Bahrein literature received from Kessrs. heiss and Son^ and ossrs. B ots. The latter say that that the export prices which applicable are those included in the radical Specialities ?rice List. They are unable to supply indenting- forms. Down Brothers say timt they have no catalogues etc. in stock but say that these will be available either at the American lission Hospital at Bahrein or at the Bahrein Government Hospital. No reply has yet been received from Messrs. Burgoyne, Burbidges, Allen &amp; iianburys or Dakin Brothers, ijeanwhile you will probably wish to despatch the available literature to Bahrein. Tours sincerely. w *KRfSON J.j • Fisher, Esq., Foreign Office, London, B. &gt;&lt;. 1.Dear s£ro. Me licjetton ^ fh 19 ih /jui-i * 19 ^ I acknowledge with thenl® receipt of your letter ref# JTC^IAB dated the 2nd April 1948, enclosing your Price Idsts for Phanaa- ceuticnl 3peeialltiea and booidLota ^ Boots products in Jlodem Therapy* and “Penicillin therapy* with suppler:gate . It is noted that prices in these booklets should be disregarded, end that export prices arc included in the Medical SPeei Cities Price List. This liter at ure is being despatched to 34ihr;dn. Yours faithfully* Lieut.-Ckjneral I#ILS*(R)* Medical Adviser Loots Drug Conpany United, NOTfDJ'JHM.Dear Sirs, iakdical section to 19«-. April, 19&lt;j8. I acknowledge ?/ith tliaxka i'eceipt of your letter of the ^Ist liarch, 194 ^* covering a copy of your Ophthalmic Instrunanta and Appliances catalogue 194&lt;^ which is being forwarded to Bahrain. Yourr, faithfully* Lieut. -G^iaral Hedical Adriser Jorm eiso &amp; Son* Ltd** 237# Oxford street, LO^JDai, W. 1.Dear sir« # Medical Section l?th APrii* 194^ Thauiic you for your lettea* ref. C.a* 3 dated the j&gt;lst March* 194^* Your kind su^^estion that, ia the absence of e supply of your catadoijues, tlie Besideney Sur^eoii, Bahrain td^t refer to copies of your publications ^tilable with the American Mssion and Goverx^ieut Hospitals, Bahrain, is noted with appreciation. Youi’s fed tlifplly. Lieut.-General Medical Adviser Bovjx Bros, end Meyer 6 iixelpc Ltd., 2p, iiill Rise, GROYDCN, Surrey.BOOTS PURE DREG COMPANY LIMITED Telephone: NOTTINGHAM 45501 Cablegrams: DRUG, NOTTINGHAM ENGLAND Codes: A.B.C. 5th and 6th BENTLEYS MARCONI MANUFACTURING CHEMISTS &amp; MAKERS OF FINE CHEMICALS NOTTINGHAM ENGLAND AFP/MF. Uear Sirs, &amp; AU communications to be addressed to WHOLESALE AND EXPORT DEPARTMENT BOOTS PURE DRUG CO. LIMITED STATION STREET NOTTINGHAM, ENGLAND -(^pril 1948 (Jolden Bye Ointment - large size tube We have pleasure in advising you that the above additional size of Golden Bye Ointment is now available, the price being 4/9d. per dozen tubes, F.O.B. BRITISH PORT. Perhaps you will be good enough to arrange for this addition to be noted in your copy of our Export Price List of Pharmaoeutioal Specialities. BOOTS PURE DRUG 00.LTD.,BOOTS PURE DREG COMP Am 1 1IUI III! Telephone: NOTTINGHAM 46501 Cabli'srraniB: DEUG, NOTTINGHAM ENGLAND Codes: A.B.C. 5th and 6th BENTLEYS MAKCONI MANUFACTURING CHEMISTS &amp; MAKERS OF FINE CHEMICALS NOTTINGHAM ENGLAND 2RH/MAJB All communications to be addressed to WHOLESALE AND EXPORT DEPARTMENT BOOTS PURE DRUG CO. LIMITED STATION STREET NOTTINGHAM, ENGLAND 2nd April, 1948. The Medical Section, Commonwealth Relations Office, 4, Ce^ral Buildings, Matthew Parker Street, London S.W.l. Dear Sirs, Thank you for your letter of 25th Murch. have noted that the Residency Surgeon, Bahrain /£o is interested in receiving from us details of our preparations. We are sorry that we are unable to supply indenting forms. However, we are enclosing herewith our Price Lists for Pharmaceutical Specialities and Medical Specialities and our booklets Boots Products in Modern Therapy and Penicillin Therapy with Supplements We would ask you please to disregard the prices in the booklets as these apply to doctors in this country only. Export prices for these items you will find are included in the Medical Specialities Price List. Assuring of our best attention at all times. We are, Yours fait BOOTS PUREDl RECTORS H. E. NOTCH Kl N, F. i.B-S.T. F.T. BA R N ES. F. R. PAI N E. A. T. COX, F.I.B.S.T. Established 1787, Telephone MAYfair 8343 (slines) Telegraphic Address, Lithotrite' P hon e, Lond on. a, d •. caicions. ^ Ji A fp|si § § &gt; 287 , Oxford Street Vo 'V Vs V T0 Ma kers of Surgical Instruments, Aseptic Metal Furniture, Cutlery, Razors,&amp;c. Contractors to h.m.Government, Indian &amp; Egyptian Governments, &amp; THE PRINCIPAL BRITISH, Colonial* Foreign Hospitals. 51st March, The Commonwalth Relations Office, Medical Section, Clarence House, if. Central Buildings, Matthew Parker Street, Westminster, S.W.1. Dear Sirs, As requested in your letter of the 25 th instant, reference AJP we have pleasure in sending you herewith a copy of our Ophthalmic instruments catalogue, for you to forward to the Residency Surgeon, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Yours faithfully, JOHET WEISS &amp; SON, LTD. Director.Hasimfsc*. w''- ^ irr iLc UU ALLOTTED TO EXTERNDEPARTMENT (B) EN GLAIR. POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULP. PROM: D. R. ■mi—-» t — INWARD TELEGRAJ&lt;1 TO COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS OFFICE /* r \ BAHRAIN, 14.15 hours, 29th February, 1948 13.20 hours, 29th February, 1948* NO.a/155. Difficulty in bbtaining medical stores from India, Can you arrange supply our annual indent. No distribution. ^ *jChV It-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000288_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1302</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000288</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1302</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 607/48 'Medical stores for the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-23T23:12:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (25 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 27; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains requests sent by the Persian Gulf Resident to various British manufacturers and suppliers' for medical supplies to be shipped to the Gulf. The letters are mostly requests for indent forms or suppliers product lists, and responses from manufacturers in Britain. Few of the papers mention particular medical products.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>American Mission Hospital, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Business records</topic></subject><subject><topic>Medical supplies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000288#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>