<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T08:59:56.060Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">TRANSLATION . * ' ' W ^ ^32. In the Same of Allah, the Beneficent, the Merciful. KINGDOM OF HEJAZ, AND NEJD, And its Independencies. His Majesty the King's Office. Special Secretary. AL HASA, the 30th Ramadhan 1350 - 2fth January 1932. My dear Colonel Biscoe, With reference to the verbal conversations which took place between us on the occasion of Your Excellency's visit to His Majesty the King, the great, at Hasa, I have the honour to confirm here below the conversations that took place about certain matters. 1. That no visa fees should be charged in the case of Nejd subjects travelling from Nejd Ports to Kuwait and Bahrain or between Kuwait and Bahrain, either at their entry or at their exit. Similarly Bahrain and Kuwait subjects should enter our Ports in the Gulf, without paying any fee for visas on their passports other than half Qursh Amiri^one anna) at the entry and half Qursh Amiri at the exit, it being value of the stamp affixed on the visa. That our subjects who travel to India from Nejd, will not be charged more than a rupee at their ^ .. j*. regards the Indian subjects, Bunniahs will be permitted to enter Q^atif temporarily, not for permanent .. • Hj &lt;* ' ^ i. ^ t j{ypermanent residence for a period not exceeding two months on each occasion, method of granting permission to be the same as formerlyT] A.nd Moslem Indians are permitted to enter our ports in the Gulf for the purpose of trade only, and one rupee will be recovered from each, i- If any of the parties wish a modification in this, he should inform the other party about his desire, so lhat agreement may be arrived at # 1 request that those of our subjects in Bahrain, who do not possess passports, but who wish to travel to India, or to foreign countries, should not be supplied travel permits at Bahrain, but should be called upon to obtain passports from their country of origin and we shall make special arrangements to expedite the completion of their passp orts. I request Your Excellency to recommend that our subjects in Bahrain should be well treated, and t their rights guarded. I request that you will undertake the necessary negotiations to open wireless communications with Bahrain, and to fix moderate rates so as to encourage the expansion of trade and improve the relations between the two countries, I await the proposals which you will make regarding an agreement for the surrender of criminals between Bahrain and Hejd, I request you to make arrar^ments for exchange of mails between Nejd and Bahrain and for their despatch from Bahrain io'fhefcr destinations.I request that efforts be made to arrange that commercial boats plying between our coasts in the Gulf and the Bahrain coast, should carry manifests for the cargo on board. I request that efforts be made to arrange for exchange of Judicial summonses between Bahrain and Nejd through the Amirs of places in our iaatnat lands and through the Shaikhs of Bahrain in Bahrain. As regards the discussions that took place about permitting our subjects to trade at Kuwait, we see no objection to a meeting of representatives of our Government and representatives of the Kuwait Government, at Kuwait, Bahrain or Hasa to discuss this matter to consider how interests of both parties may be protected. {sd) YUSUP.Hofuf, the 23th.January 1932, Dear Mr.Yusuf Yasin, {2S.l.7&gt; o) I have received your letter of the ^Ct amnz^n/_ and thank you for your resume of the subjects discussed between us. On my return to Bushire I will take up these questions with the authorities concerned, and trust I shall be able to arrange them in accordance with the conclusions which we arrived at during our discussions. sd/- H.V.Biscoe•</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/597</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/597</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 61/18 [II] (D 125) Bin Saud'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-02T11:55:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The two items that comprise the file are arranged with the Arabic original first, followed by an English translation. There is no chronological arrangement as both items bear the same date.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file is foliated from the front cover to the last item in the file, with small numbers in the top-right corner of each recto . There is an earlier pagination system that runs from 79 (verso of folio 1a) to 84 (folio 7). Foliation anomaly: 1a.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the development of formal communications between Najd and Bahrain, and the wider Gulf and Indian region. The first of two items in the file is a letter (dated 28 January 1932) from the Special Secretary to ‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd (Ibn Sa‘ūd) King of Hejaz and Najd, to Lieutenant-Colonel Hugh Biscoe, then Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (folios 1A-5). The letter summarises a number of points arising from a meeting that took place between Biscoe and Ibn Sa‘ūd.All of the points concern the development of formal relations between Najd and Bahrain, and other British protectorates and colonies, including India. Points covered include the instigation of formal procedures for issuing passports and visas for travellers between Najd and Bahrain, Kuwait and India, the set-up of wireless communications between Najd and Bahrain, the extradition of Najdi criminals from Bahrain, exchange of mail, and papers for commercial vessels. The English translation of the letter (folios 3-5) has been annotated, with parts relating to visas for Indian subjects highlighted.In Tuson,
                           The records of the British Residency and agencies in the PersianGulf(London: India Office Library and Records, 1979) the file is listed with the title 'Visa and passports for travel between Najd, Kuwait and Bahrain.' The date range on the cover of the file (1 April 1931-30 September 1936) is incorrect.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia 'Abd al-'Azīz bin 'Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00023a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>