<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100030782395.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:47:55.673Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">1. Transfer of diplomatic rela tions to the Foreign Office. Zanzibar, Arabia, and the Persian Gulf. There are so many questions raised in the papers we have before us, connected with these localities, that it will be necessary to separate them and take up each in succession, in order to give any opinion that will be worth reading. the management of our relation with the Chiefs and Governments of these territories ^° f ? ny of them &gt; be transferred to the Foreign Office ? ° There is no doubt that in the management of the existing relations we come frequently in collision with Turkey, with Egypt, and with Persia, all of which are within the circle of European diplomacy, and there are Ambassadors, Consuls General or other agents appointed by the Foreign Office, and exclusively under their control, for the management of the interests and relations of these powers with the British Empire. The Courts and Governments of these territories are becoming more or less Euro peanized in their opinions and in the principles of their administration. It would seem at first sight natural that our Imperial diplomacy should extend as tar as the relations of either of these Govern ments should carry it, and that when thev come into collision with the acts or interests of India now that India is a dependency of the Crown the decision and settlement of the questions that arise should be dealt with as a matter of Imperial diplomacy, to be settled in the Foreign Office. The obligation, moreover, undertaken by England to suppress slave dealing in all parts of the world is a new feature introduced into the diplomacy of these Indian seas, and the management of this is entirely a matter of Imperial diplomacy attaching to that Office. But, notwithstanding that on these broad grounds there would be an apparent con- gruity, in transferring to the Foreign Office the future management of relations with the Chiefs and Governments of these parts, and it would be a great relief to the Governments of India to be saved from the trouble and inconvenience of interfering to settle the many questions that arise requiring such inter vention to prevent the public tranquillity from being disturbed, still the transfer seems to me an impossibility unless the Foreign Office is prepared to remodel all existing arrangements, so as to bring Vn m &gt;vbb * n . ^ be SC0 P e of their official supervision. All our existing relations with Muscat, with Zan zibar, and with petty Chiefs and places of the 1 ci sian Gulf, have been settled by treaties, engage ments, or mere agreements, concluded by British Officers m the name and on behalf of the Govern- ments of India or Bombay. In some, as more par- 9638 d. a 1 1 u iticularly in the engagement by which Syud Mujeed was established as Sultan at Zanzibar, while his brother, Syud Thuwenee, was secured in the peace ful sovereignty of Muscat, it was settled that an annual sum should be paid by the former to his elder brother, and the Government of India gua ranteed this payment. Will Her Majesty’s Go vernment accept this guarantee as one to be en forced, and eventually met from Imperial resources? On the other hand, could the Government of India be called upon to make good a payment resulting from a failure in the Sultan of Zanzibar to fulfil his engagement, without the Government of India having had a word to say in the negotiations and other measures which culminated in the default. The existing relations with Southern Arabia, and with the Persian Gulf, had their origin in the ne cessity the Indian Government felt to suppress piracy in the Indian seas. * We found a useful ally in this work in Syud Suyeel, the father of Thu wenee and Mujeed, who for upwards of 40 years governed Oman with great vigour, and who was himself a merchant as well as a ruler, and had ships which he annually sent with cargoes to Calcutta as well as to ports of Western India. The trade rela tions of Arabia and the Gulf are entirely with India, and it would be hard to compel those who have complaints to make, or interests at stake arising out of this trade, to look only to the Foreign Office for redress, or for their settlement. On this acconnt, as well as because the existing treaties are all made with India, it seems to me necessary that the management of our relations with these countries should be committed to Officers appointed by, and corresponding with India. The slave trade suppression duty has super vened, having been assigned to the Indian Officers, because they were officials on the spot. If the Foreign Office does not think they perform this duty well, it might be committed to separate Officers appointed for the purpose, or left, as it in a great measure is at present, to the navy captains, who have Acts of Parliament and instructions from the Admiralty to guide them, and who now act very independently of the Indian Governments and their Officers. The question I propose next to consider, because it is in some way connected with the first, is second, whether it is advisable to send a diplomatic Agent or Commissioner of high position and character, to inquire into all existing arrangements, and to put them on an improved footing. Undoubtedly, matters in Southern Arabia, Zan zibar, and the Gulf are at present in much con fusion. The causes of this and the remedies I shall hereafter refer to. I do not think any person sent from this country would do any good, so long as the relations with the Chiefs and Governments remain on their present footing. Such an appointment would weaken the influence and authority of the existing diplomatic Agents and would not be favour- 2. Appointment a special Agent Commissioner.3 3. Claim of the Sultan of Zanzibar to be exempt from the obligation to pay subsidy. ably viewed by the Indian Governments which now conduct these affairs. If, notwithstanding the ob jections stated, it should be resolved to transfer the management of these affairs wholly or extensively to the Foreign Office, there can be no doubt, that in that case, as a preliminary and means of carrying out such an arrangement, an appointment of the kind proposed would be indispensable. Otherwise, all that we can do with propriety would be to suggest to the Government of India the expediency of appointing such an Officer, leaving the decision and the selection of the person to that authority. I cannot bring myself to believe that the Govern ment of India would decide this question in the affirmative. If it should do so, the Officer deputed should be supplied by the Admiral with a vessel of war beyond the usual strength, besides having Government steamers as yachts, or partly armed, to give to his mission due prestige and authority. .A third question has been mooted, and we have the opinion of the Government of India upon it; and that is, whether Syud Mujeed, the present ruler of Zanzibar, has any claim to be relieved, or, on the grounds of policy should be relieved, from the obli gation to pay an annual amount to the Ruler of Muscat, as settled and agreed to by him, and guaranteed by us, in the arrangement made be tween him and his brother Thuwenee ? Syud Mujeed pleads that his brother having been assas sinated by his son, the present Ruler of Muscat, that act frees him from any obligation to make any payment to the assassin. Nay, he might further plead that that atrocious deed imposed on him the obligation to avenge his brother’s death, and, according to all Asiatic ideas, gave him full right to assert a claim to the succession, as next brother in age to the deceased, and as was done by Syud Toorkee, the third son of Syud Suyeed, but not successfully. In fact, according to all Asiatic notions, the death of Syud Thuwenee in the manner it occurred, would be considered by any one in the position of his brother, Syud Mujeed, as freeing him from the obligation of making any further payments, so that that question would stand as between him and his nephew, the assassin, upon the simple ground whether he was in a con dition to resist the payment by a resort to arms. Here, however, our Government comes in and says, “ We forbid a resort to arms. It was to prevent “ this that we mediated the arrangement between “ you and Thuwenee. We insist on that being “ carried out to the letter, in favour of the suc- “ cessor of Syud Thuwenee, whosoever he may “ be.” I am sorry to see in the letter of the Government of India a doubt expressed upon the fact that Syud Salim did assassinate his father. The deed was perpetrated in open durbar. He shot him in the presence of hundreds, and the convulsions and troubles that followed were evidence conclusive of the crime. For some time our Government hesi tated whether to acknowledge the assassin. We took4 measures to remove our agent of the Indian rr [ e &gt; r ‘ chants, whose safety was likely to be compromised in the disturbances, from the scene of this act of violence; and it was only after the parricide son had succeeded in establishing himself that the Indian Government, from motives of policy, recognized him as the dt facto ruler. We cannot now ignore the circum stances under which this sovereignty was obtained. But we have lost our opportunity for rectifying and improving the relations between him and his uncles. He had evidently, nay, he has now, no means whatsoever of acting offensively against Zanzibar. He relies upon us entirely to enforce his claim to the subsidy agreed upon. He relies upon us lor a great deal more. There is the farm of Bunder Abbas, which the Persians have given him notice to close. He looks also to our assistance with arms, if not with money, to enable him to resist further aggressions from the Wahabees of Nejd. He has from the first of his usurpation been in a position to accept from us any terms as the condition of obtaining thu moral support of our recognition, and the further support of our good offices and eventual assistance in his other difficulties. What would have been more easy than to have suggested as one of his conditions, and as a means ot securing our intervention to prevent troubles from the assertion of the claims of his uncle of Zanzibar, that the money payment engaged to be paid to his lather should be permanently remitted } Until lately we had only a Native Agent at Muscat, and the present appointment of Captain G. Atkinson is not a permanent one. We have had, therefore, very imperfect information as to the policy, disposition, and fitness of Syud kalim. We know nothing of the relations subsisting between him and the Wahabees. It has been our aim hitherto to use our influence to prevent the exten sion of Wahabee dominion, because it is cruel and fanatical in the extreme, and we see in it an ob struction to our endeavours to suppress piracy and promote beneficial commerce. We do not know whether Salim is pursuing a course likely to assist or obstruct our views in this respect. And yet the Government is drifting into a course or measures which have the effect of upholding this Chief as our especial protegt. Whether this con duces to give us popularity, or to make us odious to those whom we desire to conciliate, we have had no means of judging. If we are to do so much for Muscat, we ought at least to have a permanent resi dent British Officer to manage our relations, and to keep us well informed of all that passes. 4. Amongst the troubles brought upon us by our relations with Muscat, is the farm tenure, by which that Government has hitherto held Bunder Abbas from Persia. Syud Salim has failed in the pay ment of the rent or tribute settled as a condition of his tenure. His people further are alleged to have been guilty of acts of violence, even of piracy, which gives Persia another plea upon which to forfeit the lease. Persia evidently desires to extend 4. Notice by Persia of the for feiture of the lease of Bunder Abbas to Muscat, and of the intention to resume.ho r direct dominion over the territory bordering on ^ consistent with our policy to permit this. It not, what right have we to prevent, what means to counteract it ? Under the doubt I feel respecting the character and policy of Syud Salim I am not sure that it signifies much to us whether Bunder Abbas is in his hands or in that of the Persian Government. In the time of Syud Suveed we had much more confidence in him than in the Shah of Persia, who was a weather-cock not to be depended upon, seeking money wherever he could get it, and caring for little else. But the Govern ment of Persia is much more steady now than it was in the times of Futeh-Ali-Shah, and I have little doubt that the influence of the British Minister at Teheran would be able to secure that any Per sian Governor sent to Bunder Abbas would manage it just as well as an agent from Muscat. But Syud Salim has this to say,—It is because I have not received the subsidy I was entitled to from Zanzibar, which the British Government guaranteed to be paid to my father, that I have been unable to pay the rent due to Persia for Bunder Abbas. I have incurred the forfeiture, therefore, through your default. The money payment from Zanzibar will, before this { have been realized by the Muscat Go vernment, the amount having been paid under pro test by Syud Mujeed to the Bombay Government. Is any further action on our part necessary to save the farm of Bunder Abbas from forfeiture and con fiscation by Persia? I cannot think that it is, nor have 1 so favourable an opinion of the Government of Syud Salim as to wish to extend or perpetuate his dominion, but I acknowledge, as I said before, that our information respecting his policy, qualifica tions, and character, is very defective. 5. Proposal of the Persian Govern ment to establish a fleet of war steamers in the Persian Gulf under British officers. 5. As part of the same policy which has sug gested to the Persian Government the resumption of Bunder Abbas, the durbar has proposed to our Ambassador to establish a fleet of war steamers under British Officers, and the proposition has been made, as if it was a favour to give a preference to our nation instead of making the same offer to the French or Americans. It is to be observed, that the vessels are to be built and provided at our expense, under promise of repayment hereafter. This part of the proposal is conclusive against its being likely to be accepted by any power that has not views of its own to be promoted thereby. The vessels are to be commanded by British Officers. Ol the crews nothing is stated, nor has anything been said respecting the position of these Officers, or respecting the authority from which or through which they are to receive their orders. A similar proposition from the Chinese Government, which was carried so far that five steamers were provided by the British Government, and sent out under Sherard Osborn as Commandant, broke down alto gether, and the project was given up, because the6 British Officers could not consent to receive their orders, and to be under the capricious authority, of any mandarin who might be sent to hold local command. We must not fall into the same error again. Before, therefore, at all entertaining the proposition, we must know exactly the footing on which the steam fleet is to be entertained. If it be placed on a footing corresponding with that of the contingent troops entertained at the expense of the Native Princes of India who have subsidiary rela tions with us, then he might readily entertain the proposition. In that case, however, the wishes of the Shah’s durbar would have to be communicated to the Ambassador, under whose discretion all orders would be issued, and the diplomatic agents in the Gulf, acting in communication with the Ambassador, would find this steamer force a most useful auxiliary in carrying out the views of the Government for the suppression of piracy and the preservation of tranquillity in the adjacent seas. But even on this footing, it may be questioned whether it is worth our while to go to the first expense of providing the vessels, and to trust to Persia for the regular payments necessary to main tain them in efficiency. The credit of Persia, and her reputation for probity and punctuality in her dealings, is scarcely high enough to warrant our entering into such engagements. There is too much likelihood that the entire expense both of providing and of maintaining this war-fleet would be thrown on the British Government. Under the probability of this, would it not be preferable if we deem it desirable that there should be an establish ment of war steamers in the Gulf, that we should provide and maintain them for ourselves, and so be able to employ them according to our views of expediency, unembarrassed by any interference from the Persian or from any other Native Court ? b. 1 look upon it as quite premature to enterta the proposition to send Commodore Crittenden, &lt; any Officer possessing similar experience of tl naval duties in the Persian Gulf, to assist tl Ambassador at Teheran in negotiating the co: templated arrangement for the establishment of Persian steam fleet in that quarter. We have fir to determine whether to entertain the propositic at all, and this, even if we are not disposed I negative it absolutely on broad grounds of gener policy, still, without further information, as befoi pointed out, regarding the footing on which tl Officers are to stand towards the Persian Goven ment, and other details, which the Ambassad. would!° en ? ble him t0 ascertain, would, I think, be extremely unwise to send a nav man to settle details. It would show an eagerne' on our part to jump at the first proposition whk would give the Persians great advantage in tf subsequent negotiations. We should be fommitte to an acceptance of it on the present vague an 6. The proposition to send an ex perienced naval Officer to assist the ambassador at Teheran in settling the details of such an arrangement.4 » 7. The existing difficulties and troubles in the Persiau Gulf. Revival oy piracy. uncertain basis, and, in my opinion, the offer as now made would be best answered by a declaration that the naval police of the Gulf has hitherto been undertaken and maintained by the British Govern ment, and that we have no intention to withdraw from the obligations and duties incident to this undertaking. 7. There can be no doubt that things are not now managed in the Gulf of Persia with the same promptitude and efficiency that they used to be. So long as the Indian Navy was in existence, it was the especial duty of that navy to have one or more vessels always cruising there; and the Officers, who were accustomed to the duty, and well experienced in dealings with Native Chiefs, and quite competent to settle, according to their own judgment and dis cretion, petty claims and quarrels, were most useful assistants of our diplomatic agents, giving them a ready means of acting wherever there was an appearance of trouble of any kind arising. At present, the duties performed by the Indian Navy have been undertaken by Her Majesty’s Navy, but there is no roster of vessels told off for continual service. For six months of the year the climate is so unfavourable to Europeans that, except under pressing necessity, no vessel is ever sent there. The vessels that go have no Native crews, for boat service under the tropical sun of the Gulf. The Commanders and all their Officers are totally igno rant of the languages spoken. They obtain from the diplomatic agents interpreters or assistants, through whom all their communications are neces sarily made, and by whose advice they are, of course, guided; but they are impatient to have their cruise completed, and never can be zealous agents for the maintenance of a maritime police. The remedy for this,—and it is a remedy that must be adopted, sooner or later,—is, to revert to the old scheme of maintaining vessels of our own, adapted to the service, and commanded by Officers, a large * proportion of whose lives has been spent in per forming the duty. There must be a regular routine of service to be rendered by Officers of this de scription, in order to make the maritime police of the Gulf efficient. The suppression of piracy and of slave dealing are duties repugnant to the feelings and habits of the population, whose laws and whose ideas countenance both. Unless, therefore, we show ourselves continually in sufficient strength to repress the disposition to resume the habits of their fathers and grandfathers, we must expect to see everything fall again into the same anarchy, and life by violence, that prevailed when we commenced our measures of repression at the beginning of the present century. There is no nation but ourselves that has any direct interest in maintaining the tran quillity of the Indian seas. The duty falls upon us, as the de facto sovereigns of India. We have no rivalry or collision to fear from any European8 or American power. But while we hold India we owe it to our subjects there to keep the Indian seas free and open for their commerce, and it would be a very unworthy policy to lay it down that, because European vessels are generally too powerful to be molested by Native pirates, therefore we need not trouble ourselves about the accidents and disasters that befall the Native craft. H. T. Prinsep. India Office, 15th July 1868.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100030782395.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B2/5</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100030782395.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B2/5</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Zanzibar, Arabia, and the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1868/1868</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-06T09:20:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent><extent>Foliation: ff 42-45.Pagination: there is an original, printed pagination system, from 1 to 8.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A printed memorandum written by Henry Thoby Prinsep, member of the Council of India, 15 July 1868. The document addresses seven matters pertaining to Britain's relations with Muscat, Zanzibar, and Persia, as follows:1. The transfer of diplomatic relations to the Foreign Office; 2. The appointment of a special Agent or Commissioner to inquire into existing arrangements; 3. The claim of the Sultan of Zanzibar to be exempt from the obligation to pay the subsidy to Muscat; 4. The notice by Persia of the forfeiture of the lease of Bunder Abbas [Bandar Abbas] to Muscat, and of the intention to resume; 5. The proposal of the Persian Government to establish a fleet of war steamers in the Persian Gulf under British officers; 6. The proposition to send an experienced naval officer to assist the ambassador at Teheran [Tehran] in settling the details of such an arrangement; 7. The existing difficulties and troubles in the Persian Gulf, the revival of piracy.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Henry Thoby Prinsep</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bandar Abbas</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Piracy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Naval affairs</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100030782395.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>