<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00039d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T14:55:10.115Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">£ Af f fXiofli 1 &amp; CONFIDENTIAL. Little Campden Houst,, Kensington, December Ist, 1838. T he R ight honorable THE LORD VISCOUNT PALMERS TON, M y L ord, Having passed twenty-three years of my life in Persia, and having superin tended the relations of Great Britain with that Court during eleven years of that period, I have viewed with the deepest regret recent events in that country, and the threatened annihi lation of an alliance not only purchased at a great price, but preserved by the exercise of the greatest discretion from the dangers which from time to time have assailed it. It must not be argued, because Persia undertook with earnestness the reduction of Herat, that she is disposed warmly to adopt Russian interests, and to be neglectful in the preservation of the British Alliance. For the last thirty years, it has been the ambition of the Kings of Persia to elFcct the concjuest of the Province of Hentt, which they regard as an integral part of the Persian Empire. Whenever the Governors of Herat have neglected to acknowledge bv annual tribute, the supremacy of Persia, or whenever a cessation of hostilities with Russia permitted the Shah to turn his attention to the Eastern Frontier, expeditions have been sent towards Herat, and on one occasion within my recollection coin was struck at Herat in the name of Fatteh Ali Shah. No objection was offered on the part of the British Government to prevent the annexa tion of Herat to the Persian Empire, and the attacks having been so long tacitly sanctioned, we cannot be surprized that a young Sovereign, anxious to establish a military reputation, should have resisted the remonstrances of the British Government to deter him from so cherished a project. Had His Persian Majesty been told, before he undertook the expedition, that the prosecu tion of it would entail the loss of the British alliance, I think he would not have hesitated as to the alternative, and would have adhered to a Power, which he has been accustomed to consider from his childhood as the legitimate protector of his country. However the latter opinion is speculative, and is not important in the present position of affairs. The Shah, if past and present reports are to be credited, has been defeated in all attempts to reduce Herat, and every resource which afforded the prospect of a happy termination to his enterprize having been exhausted, is now returning to his Capital. It is now to be considered what line of policy may hereafter be applicable to Persia^ and how her confidence is to be regained—I say regained, because it must have been weakened by the recent occupation of Karrack, which I cannot but consider as an unjustifiable and highly impolitic proceeding. This measure could only have in view two objects: First, to induce the belief that the invasion of the Shah's country was meditated bv the subsequent mission of larger forces, for it was not to be supposed that the occupation of a barren rock by one thousand Indian soldiers was to occasion the immediate retreat of the Shah from Herat. Sufficient time elapsed to show that His Persian Majesty was not to be intimidated by such an insignificant demonstration. In effect he disregarded it, and continued the siege.( 2 ) Secondly, it may have had in view to weaken the authority of the Shah, by raising an insurrection in the South of Persia, and the first consequence of the Shah's diminished strength would have been to throw him more completely into the power of Russia; for if he had not felt himself competent to subdue the rebellion, he must have called in the aid of Russian troops. To regain the confidence of Persia, I conceive, must be our first step, and to effect this we must make an unconditional retreat from the barren island;—for the occupation of Karrack has altered the whole character of our policy towards Persia. We have for the last thirty years professed to be her protector; we have loudly deprecated the ambitious projects of Russia in the East, and we have now become aggressors upon a more slight pretext than ever Russian encroachment was founded on. We have seen in the events of the last year, how dangerously exciting to our Indian Empire is the appearance of any armament from Persia on the frontier of Afghanistan, which bears the character of being countenanced and encouraged by Russia, and we have learnt the necessity of checking as much as possible the encreasing influence of Russia in those countries. This it must be confessed is most difficult to counteract, because Russia has assumed a position in the East which must be progressive, until some check at home, or the struggles of the Caucasian nations to recover their independence shall impede her overt and covert attempts to extend her connexion towards India. To this she has legitimate pretension, with a view to the development of her commerce with Central Asia. Communications arise with independent Princes for the protection of Russian subjects engaged in this pursuit, and such relations are so immediately available for the extension of political interests, that the most sedulous attention cannot prescribe the admissible limits of such plausible and insidious approaches. Much more will always be attributed to Russia than she really designs, and to this she has no objection, so long as her direct agency cannot be discovered; and when it is laid open, she has no hesitation in sacrificing her maladroit agents. In the year 1820, 1 obtained a letter written by M. Mazarowich, the Russian Charge d'Affaires at Tehran, urging the Persian Ministry in the most undisguised language to make war against Turkey. This letter was sent by Her Majesty's Government to St. Petersburgh, and M. Mazarowich, an excellent public servant, was recalled, and has never since been employed; and the same fate perhaps awaits Count Semanitch. A war of rumour is the most powerful weapon Russia can wield; by its skilful manage ment, she will keep our frontier in a continued state of excitement. Armaments must be ready to check the increasing restlessness of the Indian powers, a decay of revenue is the next necessary consequence of such an unsettled feeling, and in process of time increasing expences must produce inextricable financial embarrassment. This is the point at which I have no doubt Russia aims. She never can hope to raise an Empire in the East on our ruin, but without the aid of armies, she may render India to us a burthensome possession. How is the evil to be protracted ? I should say by keeping the Russians and their influ ence as far from us as possible, and this 1 conceive is best to be effected by the continued cultivation of the alliance with Persia. I do not pretend to say that Great Britain may exercise a preponderating influence at the Court of Tehran, the attempt must be unavailing and productive of dangerous collision. So long as 10,000 Russian bayonets may, at a short notice, be transferred from the Georgian and Armenian Provinces to the Persian territory, so long will the weight of Russia be felt( 3 ) and dreaded at Tehrai^, and Russia mi&lt;^ht as well attempt to maintain a paramount influence at Delhi in opposition to our Councils, as England to suppress the power which peculiar position gives to Russia at Tehran. Still we are well armed, and may maintain a respectable footing at the Shah's Court. The feeling of the nation is with us, the reigning Sovereign has been brought up in attach- ment to England and her interests. Moreover he was placed on the Throne by the aid and encouragement of the British Government. England has been considered as the protector of the Persian Empire, and will continue to be so regarded if due attention is shown to the espousal of her interests. The present juncture is favorable for the renewal of strict amity. Russian views and movements have been thrown back for the moment, and Persia has learnt that Russia is not prepared to set England at defiance; if she had been, she might in the course of six weeks have conveyed to Herat the seat of warfare, a few thousand troops from the mouths of the Volga, by her steam-boats on the Caspian to Asterabad, from whence the land journey to Herat, not exceeding 500 miles, might without difficulty have been completed, the army being provisioned by the Persians. The resistance of the Circassians, and the disturbances in Daghestan, will also show to Persia that a joint effort may be made, when the opportunity becomes favorable, of shaking off the Russian yoke, and this feeling will induce the Shah to be more alive to the advanta-e of the British Alliance. Our attention must be more than ever turned to check the progress of Russia, because she has additional motive for such advance, in having observed that the presence of her Envoy and a few of her engineers with the Persian army at Herat, has not only aroused the Nepaulese, the Burmese, and other tribes, and chiefs to thoughts of regaining their place amongst Nations; but that even the adherence of Runjeet Sing to our alliance may have been shaken and rendered questionable, that the movement has extended to the Councils of Calcutta, and that something like a panic has occasioned the whole of the disposable force of India to be placed in motion, for the purpose of effecting projects, of which the expense is incalculable, the policy questionable, and the result at best uncertain. She has also learnt the mode of embarrassing our finances without putting a single battalion into motion. It is therefore to be expected that Russia will more sedulously, though perhaps more warily, pursue her onward progress; and that she will renew her endeavours to obtain a footing on the Eastern Coast of the Caspian * It is in concurrence with Persia that we can best thwart such a design, and the Shah is equally interested with us in opposing such a settlement. Under all circumstances, I think it preferable to spend a little money in Persia, and thereby to keep the Shah in the right course, than to enter on schemes for the establishment of an independent monarchy in Afghanistan, which, if successful, would have the effect of annulling the alliance with Persia, and of rendering her Monarch and the Ruler of Herat disposed to coalesce with Russia; and I think that the sum of 50,000 Tomans annually spent in maintaining a small but efficient force of Persian troops exclusively under the authority of British Officers, would show beyond question a determination to preserve the independence of Persia, and would induce the Shah steadily to adhere to his true friends. In enumerating the advantages of preserving strict relations of amity with the Shah, I must not forget the policy of fostering the branch of valuable commerce we carry on with • This has since been effected, for the Russians have forcibly occupied Asher Asda, an island beloneine to P e r a i« iu the Buy of Asterabad,that country by the Black Sea, which has not yet attained its full development. The British manufactures imported at Trebezond and Constantinople for the consumption of Persia are said already to amount to one million* in value annually. In justice to the Shah, and in proof of his disposition to England, I must state that he has given her all the advantages in trade which were formerly conceded to Russia. The fear of giving offence to Russia prevented his sanctioning a formal Treaty of Commerce—but he granted by Firman the required pri vileges, and the wisdom of the Right Hon'ble Henry Ellis, acting under your Lordship's superintendence, induced him in obtaining the essentials to hold light the formalities, and I cannot but consider the advantages gained by him to be as well confirmed as if stamped by a more orthodox engagement. In alluding to the extension of this branch of commerce by the Black Sea, I will not omit to mention that I labored for years in endeavouring to change the channel of commercial intercourse between the two countries from the more circuitous route of India, both in inducing merchants to make experimental speculations ; and in endeavouring to persuade Her Majesty's Government to appoint a Consul at Trebezond, in order to attract the attention of the com mercial world to that quarter. For a long time my efforts were ineffectual, as I was informed it was not the practice of Government to make such appointments before receiving evidence of the existence of sufficient trade to require protection. The enterprize of our merchants created the required necessity ; the Consulship was happily assigned to a very able man, Mr. Brant, and the trade has been annually on the increase. Again we must hold in mind that in concert with Persia, and with the Nations border ing the Eastern Coast of the Black Sea, we have the power of disturbing the tranquillity of the Russian possessions South of the Caucasus, and Russia has taught us how much may be done by encouraging disaffection, and by the most trifling demonstration. We have every facility to play the part in Cireassia and Daghestan which she has successfully practised on the borders cf our Indian Empire. The slightest indication on our part to encourage a disposition to revolt,, would be responded to by a general rising of the Caucasian Nations ; Circassians, Immeretians, Georgians, and Lesghis, are equally impatient of the Russian yoke, and when the period for the exercise of such steps may arrive, it is unnecessary to point out how much may be effected by the co-operation of Persia. These views naturally lead me to a consideration of the plan for raising an independent Sovereignty m Afghanistan, and for forming a new barrier against the encroachments of Russia. Hie supposed occasion for this extreme measure having ceased in the retreat of the Shah from Herat, it is to be hoped that the Governor General will have suspended an operation so pregnant with danger. If there is one principle of action for the preservation of our dominions in India more imperative than another, it is to avoid the unsettling of the public mind by the all-stirring excitement of war ; but in this instance we not only create a war, but lay the foundation o'f future disturbances. As far as I can learn from Newspaper report, the object of the British Government in India is to remove from authority Doost Mahomed Khan, the present Ruler of Cabul, (a Chief whom Colonel Sir J. Burnes formerly characterized as able and sound judging), who has sought by connecting himself with the Persians to defend himself against the encroachments of Runjeet Sing, and to substitute Shah Shuja a superannuated Puppet, who judging from his fallen fortunes, has not adherents to give strength to his cause. An army of 10,000 men is to be raised in his name in the Northern Provinces of India at our expense, (who may form 1856. These Imports have now even increased to two millions sterling.( 5 ) a nucleus for renewed Pindaree wars, when their services are hereafter dispensed with,) and we declare war Against the Afghans, the most hardy and bold race in Asia, on whose soldiery Nadir Shah placed more reliance than on his native Persian troops. It seems uncertain whether Runjeet Sing will permit the passage of our troops through his territory, in which case our march is through a difficult country to the South, and a distance of 6 or 700 miles is to be accomplished before we reach Cabul, the scene of action, We have then to contend not only against brave men, but against the elements. No person can have a higher opinion than myself of the bravery of our Native Indian Troops, and when I say that their moral courage far exceeds their physical force, I pay the greatest possible compliment to their mental energies ; but they cannot withstand cold, and an ordinary frost of Cabul would at once paralyze their powers. On this point I speak from experience. At the commencement of my career in Persia, I commanded the escort of Sir Harford Jones, consisting of fifty troopers of Madras Native Cavalrv I considered it my duty, when in winter quarters at Tabriz, to exercise them twice a week during the warmest part of the day. The severity of the cold did not subdue their spirit but I found the sick list gradually increase, until there was scarcely a man efficient. I was compelled to relieve them from all duty, excepting that of cleaning their horses in warm stables. I covered them with flannels and sheepskins, and shut them up in heated rooms until the return of spring. Thus I am led to the conclusion that British Troops alone are efficient for the service of Cabul. The next point of &lt;louht and diffienlty is, whether the eo -ope.'ation or neutrality of Rnnieet Sin- is more desirable. This Prince has views and interests which are direct y opposed to the feelings of the Afghans as a nation. He wishes to be guaranteed ... t .e po.- ses«ion of Peshawnr, perhaps also for an extension of his anthonty The Afghans have deep-rooted detestation of the religion of the Seiks, and I am told that the P -t.c.pat.on in our design by a single soldier of Ennjeet, wonld at once enlist every sonl of the Maho- medan population of Afghanistan in opposition to it. But to take the most favorable view of the result, I will suppose that Shah Shuja is seated at Cabul, that Runjeet Singh has been faithful; that the Burmese, Nepaulesc. and other powers have not been restless, and that every thing has been thus far arranged, as the autho the enterprize could desire,-will Shah Shuja be able to ma.nta.n his mdependenee on the resources of the country ? How is Shahzadeh Kamran to be disposed of ? and is he w o in Takiu, so Pliant a defence of Herat, has fought the battle of England, to be neg ected and 'own' off'? and if he is so treated, will he not be disposed to ally h.mselt w.tb the powers with whom he has recently been in conflict ? We have established Shah Shuja in power, and what security have we that he w.U not become in time a convert to Russian movements ? and that the arms we .ave p ace hands may not be turned against ourselves. In the course of our own times, we have seen Afghanistan powerful under one sovereign, and we have found less inconven.ence in her distracted state; for we most not forget that the occasion of Captain Malcolm's Mission to Persia in 1799, was to induce the Shah to make a demonstration on his Eastern frontier to avert the threatened invasion oi India bj ... . Zuman. I cannot help looking «ith the greatest anxiety on the departure from our frontier ol our bet disposable troops, and on the threatened points bordering on Nepaul and Ava being comparatively unprotected; neither can I reflect without the deepest concern on the necessary( 6 ) embarrassment to our finances, which the great addition to onr Army, and the -eneral move ment of all the forces of India must occasion ; and I cannot but think that there'' is comnara t.ve safety m adherence to the alliance of Persia, and in a moderate annual outlay in that country, whereby the ruinous expenditure attendins; occasional panic, as in the recent instance of the attack of Herat, may be obviated. I have the honor to be, M ith, &amp;c. See. &amp;c., (Signed) HENRY willock. Ijittle Campden* House, Lord Kensington, February 1839. I fear I may be considered intrusive, but I hope that the renewed expression of my opinions may bo viewed in the spirit they are offered, for I am deeply impressLl with he critical state of affairs in Asia, and I have no motive in addressing your L d L b t the promotion of the public service. P I have the honor to be, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c., m „ TT , (Signed) HENRY WILLOCK The Right Hon'ble VISCOUNT PALMERSTON, Secretary of State, Foreign Department. Memorandum. Bv newspaper report I learn that the British Mission is about to leave the Court f crsia. Having no knowledge of the occurrences which have led to this rupture at a m \ when reconciliation was hoped for, I offer no opinions except on the effects whi h Z Z anticipated by such an event. be The British Government having already made a demonstration against Persia bv t-K military possession of Karrack, I conclude that the retreat of the Mission is ' lead to further hostility. Occupied as we arc in the projected invasion of AfghanHa',r'l d' not see the practicability of such a proceeding; and inaction after the .xecul f i repeated feint will be ascribed to the inability of acting on the offensive. ' I seek in vain for any one advantage to be derived from the retreat of the Afi • r Persia, and I think it can only be justified by the prohibition of he S L r'' T continued residence at his Court. against its The disadvantages of retreat are manifold ly.—The field is left open in full and undisturbed occupation to fho P • when the Shah, galled by the opposition of Great Britain to his favo r' 5 '! ^ mortified by the loss of character which the unsuccessful result of his at! i t 1^' and entailed, is ready to lend himself to any measure by which he may at once embarL EnW T and recover his military reputation, and if he is allowed to brood over hi a ' ! g d ' grievances, and is not speedily conciliated, 1 shall be very much surnris r' l! SU| ' P0Sed more before the walls of Herat in the course of the ensuic 'sommer ^ n0tr 7 ) Indly. —The commercial relations between the two countries, which from their mngnitude are very important, will be entirely deranged. The Persians deprived of their usual supplies from England will once more return to the manufactured goods of Russia ; and our own merchants, alarmed by such repeated interruptions to the trade, will be weary of speculating at a market which is found subject to so many contingencies. Zrdly. —Persia will very soon discover that we have not the power to injure her; and so long as she is coaxed and cherished by Russia, she has no immediate occasion for our alliance. We shall therefore be more anxious to rtsume our lost footing at Tehran, than the Shah will be to invite our return. If force is to supply the place of conciliation, I should next wish to consider in what manner England has the power of compelling Persia to more social feelings. I have elsewhere observed that compulsion cannot with safety be resorted to; because the first consequence of weakening the Shah is more completely to render him a tool of Russia—if this view is sound, further enquiry is unnecessary, but as it may not generally be conceded, I will touch on the two points by which Persia may be supposed to be accessible and vulnerable. Is it by invasion ? All who have been in the country know the impracticability of the passes which separate Dashtestan from the interior Provinces; and if these difficulties did not exist, the poverty of the country, and the paucity of supply, for an invading army, would discourage such an enterprise. Is it by the unprofitable policy of setting up another Prince?—of creating a revolution? —of disturbing a Government which is not oppressive, and which is not more unpopular than would be any other we could raise in its place? Such projects might possibly be hazarded if Persia were unprotected—backed as she is by Russia, they cannot for a moment be entertained. Situated as we are at the present moment in Asia, encompassed by so many dangers, warnings, and threatenings, it is impossible to act on all points with vigor, nor is it politic to threaten where we have not the power of execution. With the Shah of Persia it may be expedient to temporize. He has been mortified,—-he has also strong ground for irritation in the occupation of Karrack,—that he has displayed energy no person can question; that his obstinacy and pertinacity of purpose have disturbed the peace of Asia, and involved us in great embarrassment, is undeniable. But circumstances have developed in his character qualities which may render him formidable as an enemy, useful as an ally, and he has redeeming virtues which, if properly directed, may lead him to the steadfast upholding of the independence of the Persian Empire; and such an instrument, at such an epoch, should be handled and moulded to our purpose. We shall not lose in dignity by now conciliating Mahomed Shah, nor is it desirable to try him too much by demanding that which his pride may have difficulty in conceding, nor in resisting any concession which he may have a right to demand. We cannot injure the Shah of Persia ; he may do us incalculable mischief by disturbing our contemplated operations in Afghanistan, which I pray may still be cancelled, for I confess that I cannot contemplate without awe and dread the labyrinth of political intricacies, and military difficulties into which we are immersing; the calling into action the hostile feelings of myriads of brave warriors west of the Indus; whilst we leave in India elements of disor ganization which are strongly developing, even before the departure of our Army, which is our only safeguard; and I do not regard as the least evil of the growing system, the annihilation in the breast of the Shah of Persia of all expectation in the alliance of Great Britain. (Signed) HENRY WILLOCK. 'S( 8 ) Little Campden House, Kensington, September 4, 1841. M y L ord, As an old servant of the Crown, T have from time to time submitted to the Secretary ot State for Foreign Affairs such remarks on passing events in Persia and Central Asia as my experience in that quarter of the globe may have suggested. In pursuance of the same course T now solicit Your Lordship's attention to the accom panying Memorandum. I have the honor to be, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c., (Signed) HENRY W1LLOCK. The Right Hon'ble THE EAUL OF ABERDEEN, The Secretary op State, Foreign Department. Memorandum. The present state of the British Empire in India, the false position we are placed in on the 'West of the Indus, and the financial embarrassment which has resulted from the expedi tion to Afghanistan, are matters of so important and pressing a nature, as to force themselves on the immediate consideration of Her Majesty's Government. In order that it may not be supposed that the opinions here put forth have been formed since the aspect of affairs to the North West of India has become gloomy, I append a letter addressed by me to \ iscount Palmerston of the 1st December, 1838, which recommended the maintenance of the Persian alliance and the abandonment of the projected subjection of Afghanistan, a measure at that moment no longer called for, which might with honor and advantage have been relinquished, for the Persian Army had retreated from Herat; the Emperor of Russia had disavowed the offensive acts of his Agents, and Afghanistan was left in the best possible position as regarded our interests, in a disunited state ; but still the hand of authority preserved the maintenance of tranquillity under the several Chieftains presiding at Cabul, Ghizni, Candahar, and Herat, each exercising almost independent sway. The retreat of the British Envoy from the Court of Tehran induced me again to address Viscount Palrnerston on the ^th of February, 1839, and I have since continuously committed my remarks on the passing events, and on our future prospects in Central Asia, in private communication to the Right Hon'ble Henry Ellis, a gentleman of acknowledged ability, whose experience in Asia, and whose sound and enlightened views, render his opinions on these matters of the greatest weight. In entering on a review of the project of placing Shah Shuja on the throne of Cabul, I necessarily place myself in opposition to the opinions of Lord Auckland, which is a matter of regret to me, respecting as I do the exalted bearing of His Lordship in the performance of the highly important duties committed to his charge; yet as this expedition forms the leading feature of His Lordship's administration ; and as His Lordship has declared to the world that the projeet was of his own creation, he has taken upon himself the responsibility of the measure, whether of good or evil result. I must here remark that so high a sense was entertained of His Lordship's assiduity, impartiality, an i soundness of judgment in the internal administration of the affairs of India by the Directors of the Last India Company, that even those Members of it, who disapproved( o ) of the trans-Indus expedition, united in re^ussting His Lordship to give to the public service the advantage of his continued presidence. It will hardly be credited that a measure calculated in so great a degree to influence the deepest interests of the British Empire in India, as the erection of a new Dynasty in Afghan istan, should have been undertaken without the concurrence of the Court of Directors ; and that not an individual of thoir body with the exception of the gentlemen who formed the Secret Committee was in any way consulted thereon. I will now enquire what were the advantages expected from the design, what were the implements employed in its execution, and how far the expectations formed have been realized. Persia was supposed to have lent herself unreservedly and irremediably to the views of llussia; it was therefore proposed to form a barrier nearer India by placing Shah Shuja on the throne of Cabul. This Prince was represented to Lord Auckland as f&lt; Le Desire' of the Afghans; a superannuated exile who had not even a title to legitimate succession; Shah Kamran, the ruler of Herat, being the son of his elder brother. It appeared to me that the design was fundamentally wrong; that our position in Persia was still tenable; that the true system of precaution against the approach of Russia was to keep ourselves as far as practicable from collision, and that a measure, such as that proposed, which encouraged propinquity, exposed us to the danger which it was our policy to avoid. I should always be disposed to regard with distrust, aud to adopt with great caution any recommendation connected with the alfairs of Asia emanating from the wily Court of St. Petersburgh; yet the wisdom of the suggestion thrown out by Count Nesselrode, to regard Afghanistan as neutral ground, and to permit hwr to remain independent, was manifest and convincing to my mind, and I have always regretted that Lord Palmerston did not accede to it. I Certainly did anticipate difficulty in the execution of the design against Afghanistan, but I felt that our more serious embarrassment would commence on its successful attainment. It was very evident to those who had a knowledge of the independent and turbulent character of the Afghan, that he would not readily brook the supremacy of a prince whom he had twice hurled from the throne, when imposed upon him for a third time by the hand of a foreign Power. I anticipated that Shah Shuja would not be able to maintain an independ ent position; that he must still be supported by our troops and our treasure; and though we were precipitating ourselves into an entanglement of political and financial embarrassment, which might almost render India to us an unprofitable and burthensome possession, and from which we should have the greatest difficulty in extricating ourselves. I was alive also to the inconvenience of maintaining a military position in a mountainous country, accessible only by passes inhabited by a lawless and hardy race, separated from our own territorv by a nation (the Seikhs) hostile in their feeling towards us. Our most favourable anticipations have been realized—we have fought, we have conquered, but our troubles have not terminated—glory and military fame have been acquired at a vast price, countless treasure has been expended; but the object of the enterprize has not been gained, for where is the projected barrier? Our position in Afghanistan is precisely that of the French in Algeria as described by Viscount Palmerston at Tiverton. We have authority immediately on the ground occupied by our troops, but the safety of individuals is compromised whenever they venture beyond the reach of British bayonets, and beyond the precincts of the Camp. Every man in the country is at enmity with us, the public roads are infested with robbers, and communication with distant parts is only practicable for large detachments. Before we appeared in the character( 10 ) of invaders, the Afghans had no strong predilection against us, on the contrary they wete kindly disposed, and shewed hospitality to such English travellers as occasionally visited them Now the case is altered. We have the helpless Shah Shuja in our favour, whose sole hold on the country is our army, whilst the population of Afghanistan is hostile to (he British nation ; and should Russians or Persians appear on the arena, every sword and spear in the country would he raised in assisting to drive back the foreigners who have imposed upon them a ruler whom they both hate and despise. It results that we could fight a better battle in defence of India on the East of the Indus than on ground far removed from our resources, from whence retreat is difficult and w ere we should have at once to keep down a hostile population, and to resist an invading Army. 0 The enmity of the Natives is unhappily on the increase. It is necessarily the aim of the ntish local authorities in Afghanistan to raise as much revenue as possible, because all deficiency of supply must be met by our Treasure chest, and to our forces is assigned the unpopular duty of exacting tribute. This practice was pursued for a long time in c 'ollectinL' the revenue of the Nabob of Oude, whenever the ordinary means of the Kative Government failed; but we wisely relinquished it, as it rendered us detested by the body of the people. he Khiljies and other Mountain Tribes have always preserved a degree of independence which has rendered them slow in payment; and Military service has perhaps been more exacted from them than money. Shah Shuja, armed with our authoritv, calls them to strict account, thence follows the still recurring warfare; for the defence of the many hill forts which we hear of being stormed, which generally fall, but in some cases have made suceessful resistance, is occasioned by an unwillingness to discharge demanded tribute: such wa* th, origin of the attack on Kudjuck. ' »as tne The Native assessments of Asia as recorded in official documents, are always larger than what is usually levied, and in many of our own conquests we have fallen into the error of strictlv exacting what we erroneously supposed to he the real assessments, and our levies have consequently been too onerous. This may be the case in Afghanistan. The late Governor of Cabul, Doost Mahomed Khan, was a man of simple habits, and did not affect the pan-eantrv of a Court. We may conclude, as we know him to have been popular, that he was not harsh in his exactions, Shah Shuja has greater exigencies. What is to be the termination of the one great error in crossing the Indus? We are virtually guaranteed in the preservation of the independence of Kamran against Russia and Persia, and being compelled to the defence of Herat we are carried to within oOO miles of the Caspian, and have subjected ourselves by propinquity to unavoidable and perpetual collision with Russia. I quite shudder at the onward movement, and at a moment when the independent state of lunjab separates Afghanistan from our own Territories, the popular cry now is 'We ' must man the walls of Herat. We must depose Kamran.' The Indian Press holds this language and I am sorry to say that men of influence in India arc adopting the same tone etake Herat— our next neighbour becomes offensive—we dispose of him—a restless spirit is now perceived at the succeeding frontier position of importance, Meshid,—our jealous dis- position cannot brook it, we there become masters, and it will then be argued that if we do not take possession of Asterabad, (the Persian port at the South East extremity of the Caspian Sea) the Russians will do so. ' Now it must always be recollected that Russia like ourselves is propelled by the supposed necessity of onward movement in Asia, and if we both yield to the pressnrc. our bayonets( 11 ) must inevitably cross. She has had a wholesome check to offensive enterprize in the difficulty of raising funds, a point to which we are fast approaching, and perhaps with advantage, for had there been a paucity of pecuniary supply the ruinous wars in Burma and Afghanistan might never have been undertaken. We however take no pains to check our onward progress, but al.nitting the necessity, (which forms the apology of our aggressions) blindly rush forward in a system of extension, which must hasten the annihilation of our Empire in India. The late President of the Board of Commissioners for the Affairs of India,* at the dinner given by the East India Company to Lord Keane, expatiated on the advantages of forward movement, and declared that any secession from our recently acquired prominent position in Central Asia would be fatal to the interests of the British Empire in India. I think this notion should be resisted in every possible way, and that in the present unhappy state of the business we should seek with eagerness the earliest possible opportunity of retreat. We have never ple lged ourselves to maintain a permanent footing in Afghanistan ; on the contrary, we have professed the intention of rendering the Afghans an independent nation, and therefore when opportunity offers we may leave them to their own machinations, without incurring the imputation of being thrown back. I have had a great deal of conversation with that eminent statesman Mr. Elphinstone on this subject, and he quite inclines to the notion of safety in retreat; and he says there is a certain strength in our Indian Empire, which so much counterbalances our supposed weakness in disparity of numbers, that it will be found to sustain many more shocks than it is supposed to be capable of, and he thinks that secession should not be regarded as an evil of that magnitude generally represented. The extent of our financial difficulties seems suddenly to have forced itself on the notice of the Supreme Government of India; it was anticipated nearly two years ago by my honoured Colleague Mr. Tucker, who foreseeing that neither the treasure in hand, nor the current revenue, would meet the extraordinary expences of the war in Afghanistan, which has occasioned a Million and a half annual expenditure in excess of the revenue, recommended that a loan should be opened before our Treasury became too low, and before the Public were apprized of the pressing exigencies of the State. Unhappily this was not attended to. Money was plentiful at that period; it has since been embarked in different channels, and the recent attempt at Calcutta to raise a loan at 5 per cent, interest has failed. The pressure for money is two fold. The one arises from the temporary inconvenience of the Company acting as Bankers to Her Majesty's Government to meet the charges of the war in China; the other is a still recurring evil, and has no remedy except our withdrawal from Afghanistan. I find many who will not open their eyes to the depth of our embarrassments. They say ' the difficulties are not unprecedented, we have had as expensive wars, and have recovered ' from them.' But they lose sight of the altered circumstances, former wars have terminated in accession of territory, which afforded the prospect of repayment of the sums we had disbursed. In crossing the Indus we have left fertile plains, and rich products, such as sugar, silk, indigo, opium, cotton, spices, drugs, &amp;c. In Afghanistan we act as Auxiliaries, and what little revenue can be raised in the hilly and thinly populated country which produces wheat, barley, rye, millet, and smaller grains, is taken up to defray in part the expences of Shah Shuja, the residue being furnished from our Treasury. But the whole of the revenue of Afghanistan would not cover a fiftieth part of our current disbursements in that country. • Sir John Hobhouse—his words were to this effect: ' We have itill great destiniei to fulfil in Central Asia. Our ' motto tauit be ' Forward*—collapse is death.'( 12 ) The expences of the war in A fg-hanistan are only known to the Secret Committee, but the extent of increased outlay may in some measure be judged of by the following notice from the Secretary of the North-West Provinces to the Secretary of the Financial Department at Fort William. ' The expences under Bengal, which include all our Military charges, and the bills drawn ' by the Paymasters in Afghanistan, and the Agents in that Country, have much encreased ' our charges during the last two years; I may say from 15 and 16 to '26 and il Lacs a ' monthand this it may be observed shews the increase of disbursements on one part of the frontier only, whereas the equipment of a great part of the armament, with all the freightage for the transport of Troops, and shipping charges, are defrayed at Bombay. But the great evil in the drainage of India to cover trans-Indus expences is, that all our plans for the improvement of the Empire are in abeyance. The formation of grand lines of communication through different parts of India, the building of bridges, clearing of lands, opening canals for the purposes of irrigation and navigation, were not only in contem plation, but in operation; and it is melancholy to think that such great and good works should be suspended; and the resources destined for their completion sunk in the support of a fruitless enterprize. It is true the Court of Directors have very recently authorized the construction of a canal at the estimated expeace of £30 ; J,00i), to carry the waters of the Ganges from Hurdwar through the Dooab to the conjunction of the Jumna and the Ganges at Allahabad ; and the means thus to be supplied of irrigating so extensive a tract it is hoped may prevent the recurrence of famine which recently devastated that country. This looks well on paper, but the order is issued under a knowledge that its execution must be suspended until more prosperous circumstances will admit of the appropriation of so large a sum to so beneficial a purpose. Every branch and department of the service is to be hampered, and indeed not temporari ly but for an indefinite period, and Lord Auckland recently being alive to the full extent of the evil, says—' It will be sufficient for the present to state that we shall enforce in every ' department of the Government the utmost practicable limitation of expenditure; and we (&lt; would submit to your Honorable Court the propriety of your adopting a similar course in ' England.' Mr. Bird, a member of the Supreme Council, even goes further, and he actually contem plates the possibility of a suspension of payments at the Treasury of Fort William in this month of September. With regard to curtailment of disbursement he observes :— ' I would suggest that the several Local Governments be enjoined to reduce their expen- ' diture to the lowest possible scale, to suspend all works involving considerable outlay, the ' immediate prosecution of which is not indispensably necessary; and to abstain for the ' present from incurring any now pecuniary obligations not imperatively required by the ' exigencies of the public service.' All resolutions to diminish expenditure are sound and wholesome, but extremely difficult of attainment when reduced to practice. The advantages of the service, as respects salaries, have been clipped to the lowest possible grade, and Lord Auckland, whose time is always devoted to useful purpose, recently endeavoured to curtail the charges of the Eastern Settle ments of Malacca, Penang, and Singapore, which are at present a burthen on the finances of India to the amount of £70,000 annually; indeed the pay of the Military employed there exceeds the annual revenue of the joint settlements by 270,000 Rupees. The result of this attempt has been very unsatisfactory, and serves to show how little is to be hoped for by reduction; and that we must ground our hope of amelioration, and release from financial( 13 ) embarrassment, by striking at the root of the evil, in disconnecting ourselves from the affairs of Afghanistan. Our Establishments in all branches have necessarily of late been much encreased. The Surgical and Ecclesiastical departments have been strengthened; the Marine has been much enlarged, and in the most expensive branch of that armament in steam vessels; we have encreased the numerical strength of the Officers of our Artillery; and our Native Army has received additions, and still is not efficient to the extent designed, from so many of its European Officers being employed on civil duties. I know no points on which any great diminution of expenditure may be looked for, except in the evacuation of the Island of Karrack, which is a necessary consequence of a renewal of friendly relations with the Court of Persia; and I cannot pass by tins subject without remarking how much our credit has sudered by taking possession of it, and ho\\ great the sacrifice of life and treasure has been in retaining it. There is one other place, obtained by united fraud and violence, I make use of these strong expressions advisedly, which it would be extremely desirable to givo up, I allude to Aden. This port in the Red Sea is garrisoned by a battalion of European Infantry, by a battalion of Native Infantry, a proportion of Artillery, who are always kept on the alert by the interminable restlessness of the Arabs to recover their country from the hands of foreigners; and the Garrison are provisioned and supplied with fruit and vegetables, and the cattle with provender from Bombay. This place is only useful as a coal depot, and the Arab Governor was ready to permit of our making use of his Port for that purpose, which arrangement may still be resorted to with honor and credit. The correspondence regard- inf* the capture of this place was published by parliament. The subject attracted the attention of Lord Lyndhurst, who, at the close of a session, asked Lord Melbourne for the treaty by which it was ceded to us. The Noble Lord replied, that there could be no objection to laying the treaty before the House, and the matter was not again mooted. The real fact is, that no treaty was ever contracted. This place is at present maintained at an expence not far short of £100,000 per annum, under the stigma of violated rights, calling on us the imprecations of the united population of Arabia, whereas it may be used as a coal depot under the sanction of the Arab Government at a very small cost. There are two protests on record at the Board of Control by Members of the Court of East India Directors against the violent usurpation of Aden;—one is a most able and dispas sionate examination of the case, by that great sage on questions of Oriental policy, that highly respected gentleman lately deceased, Mr. Ldmonstone ; the other is by myself, a plain exposi tion of facts, which has not however the merit of being unimpassioned because I felt strongly indignant at the injury inflicted on British honour, but I will venture to say that it does not contain a single circumstance in any way exaggerated, nor a single strained conclusion : I may also state that my report was first drawn up, and was not perused by Mr. Edmonstone until he had formed his own conclusions; for he determined to examine the case without being influenced by my opinions. I have entered on practicable points of diminished expenditure, in order to shew their insufficiency in releasing us from financial embarrassment which unquestionably arises from our trans-Indus operations. That sudden retreat from Afghanistan is impracticable I am free to admit; but if it is acknowledged that the welfare of the British Empire in India demands the restriction of our boundary to the East of the Indus, an J if this principle is recognized and laid down for the direction of future proceedings, I confidently believe that we may gradually work our way back without compromising national dignity, and to the eventual restoration of our former prosperity. ti^xtdv wtt t a HENR\ WILLOCK. [ *** This Memorandum was sent to Lord Aberdeen nearly four months before the general outbreak in Afghanistan. ]</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00039d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Mss Eur F126/18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00039d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Mss Eur F126/18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Printed copies of letters from Sir Henry Willock to successive British Foreign Secretaries discussing the situation in Persia.</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1838/1841</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-06-04T11:41:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The copies of letters have been printed in the booklet in date order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file has been foliated in the front top right hand corner of each folio with a pencil number enclosed with a circle.The file also contains original pagination 2-13 which starts on the verso of the first folio and concludes on the recto of the final folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The printed copies of the letters have been brought together as a booklet giving Sir Henry Willock's thoughts on the situation in Persia from December 1838 to September 1841. Sir Henry Willock had spent 23 years in Persia, 11 of which had been spent superintending British relations with the Court of Persia. The letters that comprise the booklet are as follows:Letter to The Right Honorable The Lord Viscount Palmerston, 01 December 1838, outlining the background politics in Persia and in particular with regards to the Kings Of Persias ambitions over the last 30 years to conquer Herat, the view the British Government had taken to such attempts and amibitions in the past and the views of the Sovereign who had mostly recently attempted to annex it. The letter goes on to discuss the line of policy which should now be applied to Persia, particularly in light of the British Government's occupation of the island of Karrack, and Sir Henry Willock's belief that the British now needed to regain the confidence of Persia and should unconditionally retreat from the island. The letter also discusses Russia current aims and intentions with regards to Afghanistan, its own empire, trade with India and the need for the British to check its progress. There is also speculation by Sir Henry as to the British Government's intentions of removing Dost Mohammad Khan from power owing to his decision to ally with the Persians in order to remove a rival from power; thoughts on the difficulties of marching Indian troops through Afghanistan and his opinions on the Shah's rival Runjeet Singh and his conclusions that the safest move for Great Britain is to adhere to its alliance with Persia.Memorandum to The Right Honourable Viscount Palmerston, Secretary of State, 4 Feburary 1839 offering his opinions on the effects that the British Mission leaving the Court of Persia would have. The memorandum focuses on the disadvantages of this action including leaving Persia open to occupation by Russia; enabling the Shah to occupy Herat; damaging commercial relations between the two countries; the likelihood of Persia discovering Britain does not have the means to cause injury and cautioning that invasion of Persia would be impractical owing to the difficulty in traversing the passes into the country.Memorandum to The Right Honourable The Earl of Aberdeen, Secretary of State, 04 September 1841 regarding his recommendations from 1838 to Viscount Palmerston of maintaining the Persian alliance and abandoning the subjection of Aghanistan and his letter of 1839 following the withdrawal of the British Mission from the Court of Persia and other private remarks since which he has made to the Right Honorable Henry Ellis. The memorandum outlines Willock's opposition to the opinions of Lord Auckland and the intention to place Shah Shuja on the throne at Cabul; his dislike of the news that a secret committee had taken this decision without consulting the East India Company Board of Directors and his belief that the British's best approach in Persia is to avoid collision and to avoid recommendations eminating from the Court of St. Petersburgh. Willock goes on to consider the benefits of a neutral Afghanistan permitted to remain independent which he views as having been the best solution that the British Government threw out; comparing the British position in Afghanistan to the French position in Algeria; considering the potential threats to Punjab of viewing Herat as an enemy; the risk of war with Russia; the need to ensure secession is not regarded as an evil of great magnitude; financial difficulties in India; the cost of war in Afghanistan and the need to retreat from the island of Karrack if friendly relations with Persia are to be restored. Towards the end of the memorandum Willock diverges from Persia to discuss the port of Aden which he believes is only useful as a coal depot and that it should be given up as a way of saving money.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000001524.0x00039d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>