<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00031b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-23T12:05:08.385Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">COPY. CONPIDENTIAL. ien/C. 5 539/0 RG. Headquar ter s, Bri ti sh Force s, Aden. 8 th August 1947. MUSCAT AIR AGREEMENT. With reference to paragraph 21 of the Muscat Air Agreement, the Dfficer Commanding R.A.F. Units, Salalah and Masirah were instructed to choose a site for a cemetery. Copies of plans showing the sites selected are attached hereto. 2 * It is requested that you will obtain the approval of these sites from His Highness. 3* It will appear that the site selected at Masirah has already been used as a cemetery, as reference is made by the Officer Commanding,R. a.F. Unit, Masirah to the removal in 1946 by the War Graves Commission of the remains of British personnel Signed. (R.E. KIRKBY) Sqn.Ldr. for Air Vice Marshal, Air Officer Commanding, British Forces. Aden. The political Agent, Muscat.4/2/40/50. (D Tho British Consulate. MUSCAT . 28th January,1950. Sh wa mlva ' r £3 eld. dear V/oods-Ballard, The R.A.B. flying over the old airfield of 'huwaniya en route to Masirah have noticed what appear to be marks made by aircraft wheels, and tl at the loose sand has been cleared in the vicinity. I pass this on for the information of the hiscat Government. The .A.P. would, however, be grateful to know, if there is no objection^whether tho tnscat Government are already aware of this and, if it has Iren in recent use by aircraft , v/hat the condition of the a’rfield is for possible use in emergency. The Political Resident has also suggested that if one of Pis '7ajesty*s ships is likely to pay a visit to Salalah during tho next few months, they could if possible try to send a party ashore to obtain further particulars. Yours sincerely, (Sd). i'.C.L. Chauncy. P. Vfoods-Ballard Pan, C.T.P.,' Minister for Foreign Affairs. ' 'us cat. Copy to x- His Excellency The Political Resident. Bahrain. 0C Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf, for information.(G A 15/3) copy fOftjaGh OI FI CK | S.w.l. 21st February, 1950. Z in Dear Sir Kupert, I am sorry it has not been possible to reply sooner to your letter tto.26/123/49 of the 9th July 1949 to Burrows, regarding the control of the Persian Gulf airfields; but the question is a complicated one owing to the unique position of the Jhaikhdoma anc has required lengthy consideration in this oix'ice anc in the Ministry of Civil Aviation. 2. The Ministry have in hand the preparation of iiOTAMS of Inioritawion Circulars dealing with the Gulf aerodromes, but they are not yet in a position to publish them; and they have suggest ed that for the present an Information Circular on the lines of the draft enclosed should be issued. You will see that it covers adequately the most important problem with which we are concerned -the procedure for clearing flights - and provides that in future all applications with the possible exception of the cases referred to in paragraph 3 below will be cleared through oiie central Channel - the Ministry of Civil Aviation - and that apart from those exceptions you will no longer be calleu upon to deal with applications yourself. I shall be very glad if you will leu .tnoiu whewiier the proposal meets with your approval; anc whether you think the bhaikh of Kuwait would a^ree to a suitable amendment being mane to article 6 of the Civil Air Agreement , and the other Rulers concerned to similar amendments tc our agreements with them. 3- xha Ministry oi Civil Aviation suggest however, that if y° u dgree, the instructions in this Information Circular might ’*1 oh advantage bo modified ^n '-vyo respects «- (a) that you she die be autheisod to gr ant permission in the Cose of single flights from adjoining territory. (b) that prxor permission should net bo required in the case oi non stop ili^hts over the chaikhdems, and m the case of flights for non-traffic purposes. 1 . SiiCulu be txad I- you wouru let me have your views on taese proposed exceptions to the general rule that permission ivj. au .1 A.i4.^nts should be made through tne diplomatic channel, ^e are m iavour of them; In tne case of (a; because it will ^&amp;vq a ro « oi uni.ocessar^ t-Lme and srcuble over minor flights; anu/J^he case o - (b) because wo doubt whether Caere is sul fie 1 erir, justification merely on safety grounas, for ^ e tain mg tno requirement. Iho iliristry are considering xhethoi, as ar alternative precaution aircraft flyint, through the Persian Gull area should be a-vised to fellow ¥. r ell defined routes. 4. The Ministry of Civil Aviation have examined your suggestion that a penalty shoula ue imposed, witnout legal process, on aircruxt landing without proper authorisation, /but Li eutenant-Colonel Sir Kup«rt Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Bahrain.2 but they considei-, arid are inclined to a^ree, that although the proposal has the attraction of simplicity and expedition, there is &amp; danger that unless the fines A’ere fixed at an exorbitant figures, operators in some circumstances would rather pay the fine than obtain, or attempt to obtain, prior permission. We also feel that the absence of legal proceeding might make operators feel that they had been dealt with aroit- rarily and unjustly; and it might very well lead to the institution of retaliatory measures by foreign governments, whose airfield officials are not as impartial as our own. 5* We realise however, the difficulty of dealing th these people by instituting legal proceedings against then, under the regulations as they are drawn up at present; and the Ministry of Civil Aviation, suggest taut t ra best solution would be to add two additional &lt;.egulatiers to ~ue .^ir ftavigetlon regulations of Bahrain and huv ai t, am eventually in the Air Navigation hegulations of bhtrjah m&lt;± ^©tar, on the lines of Article 46 ©do 59 of the United kingdom xir havigation Order, in ordex* tc establish urieqilv ;cabiy that landing or picking up or setting down traffic at Loose airfields without permission is a contravention oi the Regulations; and to provide powers under . :oh of ending aircraft would be detained. * The ministry or Civil Aviation have found that these two Regulations enable them to u«ai adequately with any aircraft which land in this country without authority. 6. We suggest therefore that provisions tc bo bcism on Articles 46 and 59 of the United Kingdom Order should be inserted in the kuwait Regulations as follows «nd that similar provisions should also be included in the Air Navigation Regulations applicable in the other tejeritories concerned add the following, paragraph to Article 1. “Ail aircraft engaged in the carriage of passengers or goous for hire or reward, shall not take*cn board or discharge passengers or goods at any place within the territories of Kuwait except in fccordance with the terms ci any agreement for the time being in force between His Majesty’s Government in tne United Kingdom (acting in this regard on behalf of his Highness the ShaikhJ and the Government of the country in which the aircraft is registered or in accordance with the special permission of the Minister of Civil aviation in the United Kingdom ^ranted on behalf of His Highness the ohaixh ana subject to any conditions or limitations which the Minister may specify. Insert the following new Article after article 14s- “(i&gt; ii it appears to an authorised person appointed for the purpose by His Highness the Bhaikh with the agreement of His Majesty’s uovernment that any aircraft is intended or likely to be flown - (a) in suen circumstances that the flight would be in contravention of the provision or any provision, ox these regulations, or of the conditions governing the use ci the aerodrome or aerodromes at Kuwait, set out in Annex 2 to the Heads of Agreement between His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom and his Highness the Shaikh of Kuwait dated the c:lst June 1949* or /(b)/-N /your views (b) while in a condition unlit fc.* flight whether tne xlight would other wise be in contravention oi any provision of these regulations or of the conditions set out in Anne.x. 2. aforesaid or not£ such authorised person may give such instructions and tfaice such steps by way of detention oi* the aircraft or otherwise as appear to him necessary in order to prevent the flignt. (ii) ii any person contravenes any instructions given under this nrticle, he shall be deemed to have contra- veneu these heguiations and, if an aircraft flies in contravention of any such instructions, or notwith standing any steps tt.ken by way of detention or -fcary otherwise in order to prevent the flight, it shall be deemed to have iailed to comply with tnese regulations. ' 7» x sag old be very glad ii you would lot me kn ow whether c£ U cojaction to this plan; and whether you think the Shaikhs concerned are likely tc agree to the proposed amendments. depends on tne reliability of the authorised pex^son xnc it is ersential therefore that Is la^esty’s CoverxuBcat control over his appointment. if ^ny of the chaikhs object to the Reference to His Majesty’s Government in „ne regulations themselves the point mi 6 ht be covered by an appropriate exchange of letters. ^ J 8. Subject to the above on which we should not like to have / we agree generally with the measures suggested in paraaraph 8 of youc* retter. In the meentime the Ministry of Civil aviation have appointed a representative to serve at Kuwait, wno will it is hoped arrive early in March. He should be able, unaer your authority, with the additional powers conferred by implementation ol the proposals referred to above, to deal promptly and effectively with most of the /.uwalt aero drome problems, particularly the unauthorised landings. Yours ever, (k£d.) W.H. Montagu-Pollock.DMEX IUkQi^L&amp; TKERlTOKti^S IN TH£ VLHulaH GULF VHD&amp;i TH&amp; PHOTltCT- m.aOLM*.S« - R ON - SCHjb'DU Li-D Ai^D P.-IVATii. &gt;LIGHIi&gt; mi /.ll operators oi aircraft registered in elates other than the -nitad iLln^doBi are randnded that prior’ permission mast be obtained from His Halvsty's Government in the United ILingdom fCi. non-scheduled or private flights over or to any point in the Persian Gulf sheikhdoms under the protection of His majesty’s Government. application for such permission should be made to the Ministry oi Civil *.viation (A3C1) by the Government of the country in vhiich the aircraft concerned is registered| through their iuiibassy or legation in ^ondon. 4 Tne aerouromes at Bahrein, oharjan, Kuwait a:;u ^atar are situated in territories in the Persian Gulf uiider the protection of E.«Lo• iii the U.iC.CONFI PI ENT IAL. Aden/5520/Or g. Headquar ter s, British Forces, Aden. 21 st June 19 50 . /&gt; I MUSCAT AIR AGREMEl?r&gt; It is desired to refer to the Muscat Air / Agreement, in particular this Headquar ter s letter Aden/ 5539 /or g. dated 8 th Aug. 1947, a copy of which is attached, in which it was requested that you obtained the approval of His Highness The Sultan for sites at Masirah and Salalah for use as cemeteries* No record is held at this Headquarters of an answer having been given to this request. Furthermore, a copy of the Muscat Civil Air Agreement of 1947 held at this Headquar ter s, lists only paras* 1 to 1 7 in the agreement, and paras 1 to 8 in the General Conditions laid down by the Sultan to govern the use of aerodromes within his territory. Although paras 5 and 6 of the General Conditions states that no new building or other obstruction shall be erected on an aerodrome without the autho rity of the Sultan, no mention is made of objections to a cemetery site* in this connection it is desired to point out that in the agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Sultan of Makulla, the sultan of Makulla raised no objection to the provision of a small cemetery at Riyan airfield, inside the airfield boundary. 3. It would therefore be greatly appreciated if you could obtain the permission of the Sultan for a site for cemeteries within the airfield boundaries at Masirah and Salalah, and if at the same time an up-to-date copy of the Muscat Air Agreement could be forwarded to thi s Headquar ter s for check and confirmation. PtjZ Ojul, Flit T/v* Vo t- , i.H&lt;f' Us&lt;~ A~- fm.Jk: fact,, V-? . &lt;p l| Q SjuU S~/3/ ■— oiUF jMo+m 5* {L 44 Cuiio**, /fa* . ( G.H. GATHERAL) ’Yng.Cmdr. i-m - &amp;uTc» 4 A J 0 ^Air Vice Marshal, ^ ^ j, 1 ^ Air Officer Commanding, British Forces, Aden. $~lu* / O- ^ ^ U~i U~% \j 1 The Political Agent, Muscat. (frJr ftZm / £jeu ccX+v &amp;&lt;-*-&lt;» ^UjcjuJF aAJLcifa*A&lt;4+4jt vsOru/’ +4' - 1/iFJf 7 / c. nx , (xjtsfr +*$ fiu Enel. F- 1 2 / 'ff)7■sasRar Headquarters, British Forces, Aden* 23rd June 195^* SAF^ULUQIHG OF AlRFIiJ^ ARPROAGHiSS. i Since the signing of the Muscat Civil Air Agreement between the heads of His Majesty's Government and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, the development of the modern aircraft has necessitated the review of certain clauses in the agreement, in order that the approaches to the airfields may be safeguarded. Para* 5 of the agreement states that all transactions and correspondence of technical matters concerning the arrangements of the aerodrome shall be conducted by the relevant British authorities. This Pie ad quarters, which is Responsible for main taining the airfields on behalf of the R.A.F. has been asked by higher authority to see that safeguarding plans are prepared for Salalah and Masirah, on the basis of any future extensions to the flight-ways(run way) &gt; that may be envisaged in the future, and that as far as possible building limitations should be made within the funnel approaches defined as 1 in 50 from the end of the runway, unless a natural obstruction presents a greater slope* 2* Attached are one copy each of the stripping plans for Masirah and Salalah, detailing the present runway# directions, in which extensions might be possible, should the need occur in the future, together with funnel approaches to each of the runways. It is requested that this plan will be reviewed with a representative from the Sultan, and further agreement obtained, to ensure that no buildings that would infringe these safeguarding limits are allowed* 3* For your information there are no buildings at the present moment which infringe these safeguarding^limits at either airfield* (P for Air Vice Marshal, Air Off icer Quakaoding, Britis h F orces, Aden* luGrUr' I 1 Jr u/p g -rfl 1 {fr. 2 - 2 / 7 /;-?® f. 'fim British Consulate. WSGtS. 22t»d July, 19 ^ 0 . ■^ngiiSinraing of Airfield /gaores^e^ Sir* ^ feavo the honour to re?*r to jour letter :?o* rc dated bha 23 rd June 1930* a d to saj that i t will se t be possible to revUnr the plan with the Muscat Coveranen** «itil the Sultan returns la otober, but I m aware that no building is at present conteaplated upon ^ ^ event of eoergenqy occur lag before Oc.ooor* I an certain no diffioaltj would be experienced in obtaining sgreenent froa the oultan ter cabU to aqt •afagaarde dictated tgr the ailitarj situation; action required in paras 2 of jour letter will be taken as soon as possible after the Multan*s return. 3. I as sending a nop/ of this letter and of jours under reply to His kcelieoqy the Political Resident in the Persian :ulf for Information. 4* In the meantiae two more oopiea of each of the oL oa would be helpful If readilj available* I base the honour to be Sir* ^ four obedient servant* n rr . _ , „ HU -'-(Oosty’s Cotmui, 'T- Alt' Of floor CoaciandUg. 4 H—diyartw, BrttUh foroes, . Copy to His Excellency the Political Kesident in the era Ian Gulf, BAHRAIN. - for information.2j/3/W/» ?he British Consulate, MUSCAT. 23rd JuX^r, 1930. (!}) Mugoat Air Agreement - Ceoetriea. Sir, I have the honour to refer to /our letter '?o. Aden/3320/0rg dat#a the 21st June 1930, ^nd to foitrard a copy of this A ency letter No* 061-2/40 dated the 8th December 1947 a Q&lt;i its enclosure; which seems to have gone astray. 2. It will be se n that the Mas!rah site was agreed to, a nd the .Dhofar one was to be at Has Result, As the Sultan is at Salalah until October, I suggest that the 0 i/e R.A .F. there should get the site fixed up finally by direct approach: since the Sultan has al eady agreed in principle to a c«netry being situated in the vicinity. ^ 3* Please inform this Agency of the final result* I hgVe the honour to be Sir, lour obedient servant. His ^jesty’s Consul, Muscat* Air Officer Coamanding, British Forces,COPY. OQIfPIDBNTIAL. No. C # 610 » 2/LO Politio 0 X Agency, Muscat. 8th December, 1947 To Air Officer Commanding British Forces, Aden. . .e.aoran.diji. Reference your memorandum AIKN/C.5539/ORG dated the 8th August 1947 . 2 * 1 enclose for your info ram tion a copy of a letter d a ted 29 th October 1947 which I have received from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman* Perhaps it would be possible for the Officer Commanding at S a lalah to call on his Highness a nd discuss further with him the proposals for the Christian cemetry at Dhofar. Sd/- A.C. Stewart, Political Agent, Muscat C OPT, AU HUSN Salalah ~ Mhofar. The 29th October 1947, My dear Friend, Please refer to your letter No. C./502-2/40 dated the 16th September 1947* »¥e approve the site for the Christian ^emetries at Masirah according to the plan. As regards the site for the sa e purpose at Dhofar we had m nind that the site should be somewhere in the vicinity of Has Rasuit therefore a site will be chosen for that purpose. Major A.C* Stewart, His Britannic Majesty* s Consul, Your sincere friend, SIXD BIN 7AIMUR.SECRET He adquar ter s, Br itish Forces, Aden. Ref:- Aden/201 2/Crg. 18 th August, 1950* Sir, safeguarding of airfield app roaches I have the honour to refer to your le tter 24 / 2 / 40/50 dated 22nd July, 1950, and to thank you for your information concerning the safeguarding 01 stripping plans at Salalah and Masirah. 2 Two more copies of the stripping plans are being prepared and will be forwarded to you as soon as possible. I have the honour to be, Sir , Your obedient Servant, (P.M. PROCfER) Sqn/Ldr. for Air Vice-Marshal, Air off ic er Commanding, BRIT1SH FCRCS3. ADEN. His Majesty*s Consul, British Consulate, Muse at.Headquarters* British Forces, Aden* Ref:- Aden/5520/Org, 29th August 195°' MUSCAT AIR AG-RdSvtSNT* Further to our letter of even reference dated 21st June 195°, Sqn*Ldr. Procter, 0rg*1 of this Headquarters visited Salalah on the 24ti/25th August this year and was granted an interview by the Sultan of Muscat* 2 The question of the safeguarding of the airfield approaches at Salalah and Masirah was discussed, and His lOllnnor the Sultan stated that he was in full agreement that the approaches to the run-ways at both these airfields, should be safeguarded in the interests of the safety of the aircraft and the passengers using them* The Sultan that he would approve suitable axnenaments to the Muscat Civil Air Agreement of 19V7* Appended below are suggested amendments to the general conditions laid down by the Sultan to cover the use of the aerodromes within his territory:- , _ new sub paragraph to Para* 9 of Section 3 General Conditions. Add M viii* No buildings or other obstructions shall be erected in the funnel approaches to the runways without the conjoint authority of the Sultan of Muscat and the R.A.F.,' whilst the R.A.F. is managing the aerodrome on behal of the Sultan*” The Political Agent, MUSCAT* (P*M*fHOCTSR) Sqn.Ldr., for Air Vice Marshal, Air Officer Cotananding, HRTTTSH FORCES. ADMN. nonv to Suner in tending Engineer. * tt/t*Headquarters, British Forces, Aden* Aden/2012/0rg. 12 th Sept ember, 1 950* Sir, ^ Safeguarding of Airfield Approaches. I have the honour to refer to your letter 24 / 2 / 40/50 dated 22nd July, 1950, and to forwarded herewith two more copies of the arfield stripping plans for Kasirah and Salalah, as requested* 2. • An interview was held wi th the Sultan of 1'uscat at Salalah on the 23rd August and he has agreed that the funnel approaches to the runways shall be safeguarded both at Masirah and Salalah* 3 . When, therefore, copies of the Muscat Air Agreement are being forwarded it would be appreciated if an amendment safeguarding the airfield stripping plans be incorporated within the structure of the agreement. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (p.if. PROCTER) Sqn/Ldr. for Air Vice-Marshal, Air Officer Commanding, 3RITISH FOROaS t ADM. His Brittanic Majesty's Consul, British Consulate, Muscat*29/2 W50. H.B.M’s Consulate and 'Olitical /genoy, :USCA^» 1i&gt;th October # 1950# % © Muscat Air /y reenent« *r, y' 1 - ^ / I have the t.onour to refer to your eraorandun I To# derv / 5520/Cx &lt; £ dated the 29 th August 1950. 2* Free the copy of the Air Agrecnent of 1947 in ny possession it iMiim that the riendibent you require to mate is governed by /article 6 of the j grecraent# and ttIII be raade in Schedule 111 para: 6 . 3# This para: 6 already has eleven sub -paragraphs, (i) to (ri) in it, nnd I am therefore not dear how you:'' proposed or:endnont is to be incorporated. ’X 4 « It vrauld seem convenient to include in the eri ting sub^ paragr^h (vi) shich precludes building on the aerodrome itself, i.e. ”##. 'or shall buildings or other obstructions be erected in the funnel ^yroaches #••#• Sultan'* Or, alternatively to add it as a new sub para rcr h (xii). 5 # Tlie documents in ®y possession are only typewritten and ursignecl copies. The amendment can presunubly be effected by e^cha ge of letters without any need for initialling the original docurents by the signatories, i.o# the Sultan and I!is uucellency the olitical esident, and .hen the Sultan has accorded formal consent, it will merely be necessary to infoxm all concerned to nakr the amendment it: their cory of the Schedule to the /greenent accord ngly# This seems to have been the intention of Article 6 of the Agreement. t 6 . I shall be rateful^4^ your views or this point :nd your decision regcxrding the anendnent itself. I have the honour to be Sir, -n Your obedient servant, rV^ - IHs Britannic ! ajesty f s Consul A iblitical Ag«it, ' nscLit. tfjc ■ Air Officer Ccnnanding, Headquarters, British Forces, ADELHeadquarters, British Forces, Aden. fief:- Aden/552O/Org. Noveraber, 1950* Sir, Muscat Air Agreement ^ ^ I have the honour to refer to your letter 29 / 2 / 40/50 dated 14th October, 1950, and in particular to paras. 3 and 4 . 2 . It is agreed that a suitable amendment tothe Muscat Civil Air Agreenent 1947 which gives full protection to the funnel approaches of runways at Salalah and Masirah could be amply covered by the under-mentioned amendment. Section III. G-eneral Conditions laid down by the Sultan to govern the use of aerodromes within his territory. Add to para. 6 (vi) “nor shall buildings or other obstructions be erected in the funnel approaches to the runways without the conjoint authority of the Sultan of Muscat and the Royal Air Force, whilst the Royal Air Force is managing the aerodrome on behalf of the Sultan’*. 3 . It is also confirmed that the documents concerning the Muscat Air Agreement held by this Headquarters are only typewritten and unsigned copies. Under these circumstances it is suggested that the above mentioned amendment can be effected without the need for initialling of the original documents by the signatories. It is, however, desired to confirm that the copy held by you does in fact agree with the copy held at this Headquarters, and for this reason the copy of the agreement held at this Headquarters is forwarded for your perusal and check. The above mentioned amendment has been incorporated in Section III. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (G-.H. gathsral) Wing Commander, for Air Vice-Marshal, Air Officer Commanding, BRITISH FOfiGSS, ADSN. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul and Political Agent, MUSCAT. W/L-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00031b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/115</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00031b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/115</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/40 IV. AIR FACILITIES. (Air Agreement)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:02:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence between ff 4-20, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of telegrams and letters that are related to the following: the use and control of the airfields in the Persian Gulf; the Royal Air Force (RAF) obtaining permission from the Sultan of Muscat and Oman for the use of certain areas in Salalah, Dhofar and Masirah as cemetery sites; and the amendment to the Muscat Civil Air Agreement of 1947 in regard to the safeguarding of airfields approaches at Salalah and Masirah.The main correspondents in the file are: the Foreign Office, London; the Political Agent, Muscat; the Political Resident, Bahrain; and the RAF Headquarters, British Forces, Aden.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Muscat Civil Air Agreement (1947)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Muscat Civil Air Agreement (1934)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Air Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Air services agreements</topic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00031b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>