<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:11:46.694Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Reference E.L.221005. The Secretary to the Board of Trade presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India and transmits herewith, by direction of the Board, a copy of an application for a licence under the Arms Export Prohibition Order, 1931, to export certain articles to the destination stated. The Board will be glad to learn whether the Secretary of State sees any objection to the issue of a licence on this application. 1st July. 1938. Board of Trade, S.W.l.Application Form A. Numbei and description of Enclosure forwarded with A this application. 2 2 1 0 0 5 APPLICATION FOR EXPORT LICENCE. Attention is drawn to the Instructions appearing on the back of this form. Delay may be caused if these instructions are not followed, if any of the questions below are not answered, or if the declaration is not signed. (See Instruction 8.) It is requested that the form be filled in legibly, preferably typewritten. This column is for Official use only. Licence Cheeked by Applicant’s Reference No. ^^21 (See Instruction 3.) Date * (a) Full name and address of CONSIGNOR (See Instruction 8.) VV.J. RAIL?0N, 11 # Queen Victoria Street, London, E.C.4. (6) If a registered dealer under the Firearme Act, 1937, give date and number of current certificate ; and name of issuing authority. (c) Name and address of person or company to whom the licence is to be sent. (d) [1] Proposed date of despatch of goods. [2] If the goods are to be despatched by Parcel Post state Post Office of despatch. (See Instruction 6.) (e) Prospective port, and country in which situated, to which the goods are to be exported. 3 equal monthly lots. [2] By Parcel Post from Post Marmagoa, Portuguese India. First 5/7/37. Office. (/) FULL NAME and POSTAL ADDRESS of CONSIGNEE ABROAD. Lourenco Goncalves, Nova-Goa, Portuguese India. The Instructions in paragraph 4 on the back of this form should be carefully observed when completing this table. (?) Quantity. (See Instruction No. 4[&lt;g). Full Description of the Goods (including calibre, &lt;fcc.) Total F.O.B. Value. If more than one commodity, state values separately. £ 1,5,0 ,000 No.26 Joyce F.3. Percus sion Caps 243“. 15. Od. Total Total I hereby declare that to the beet oj my knowledge and belief dll the particulars in this application are correctly stated, and I undertake that if this licence is granted to me, it shall be used solely for the export of goods being my own property or the property of a person, firm or company for whom I am authorised to act in this transaction as the sole responsible representative. I am aware that any licence granted to me is issued on the condition that the Owner or Shipper of the exported goods, if so required by the Commissioners of His Majesty's Customs and Excise, shall produce to them, within such time as they may (Mow, proof to their satisfaction that the said goods were duly delivered to the consignee at the destination named in the licence. I undertake if this licence is granted to me, to comply urith this condition. Signed 7 : N.B.—This Form must be signed in accordance with Instruction 8. If the signatory has been specially approved to sign applications on behalf of his firm, quote here Official No. of the letter approving him for the purpose. [OVER]INSTRUCTIONS FOR FILLING UP THIS FORM. NON-COMPLIANCE WITH THESE INSTRUCTIONS MAY INVOLVE DELAY. 1. Applicants for export licences are requested in their own interests to fill up the form fully g,nd correctly, and to give as long a notice as possible of their desire to export. In particular, they are advised not to put in hand the production of goods which will need to be specially manufactured for a particular order unless and until the export licence has been granted. In other cases, however, applications should be made more than two months before the proposed date of shipment. 2. All the requisite particulars as to the goods to which the application relates should be given on the form itself except as provided for at 4 (b), and not on a separate sheet or covering letter, and separate applications should be made for specific licences to export different classes of goods. _ . -grtau •' . 3. REFERENCE NUMBERS.—For convenience of reference, applicants are recommended to date and number their applications on the lines provided on page 1, and to quote this date and number in any further communication (as well as the Official reference number, if known). Further communications can be dealt with more expeditiously if they relate to one application only. 4. RULES TO BE OBSERVED AS REGARDS PARAGRAPH (g) Page 1.—In order to avoid delay the following rules should be carefully observed : (а) Not more than one item should appear on each line provided in the table. (б) Where the number of items exceeds twelve lines three copies of a schedule giving the requisite particulars should be furnished instead of including them in the table. (c) The information required under each heading should be given as accurately as possible. (d) Quantities and values must be given in British denominations. It is not enough to indicate quantities by vague terms such as “ cases,” “ barrels,” “ bags,” etc. 5. GOODS IN PROHIBITED LIST. Board of Trade Journal. -A list of export prohibited goods is published quarterly in the 6. PARCEL POST. —Goods which are to be despatched by parcel post must be posted at the Head or Branch Post Office nearest to the exporter’s place Qf.business. —(Head Offices are printed in the Post Office Guide in capital letters and Branch Offices are indicated by the letters B.O.). Exporters are warned that under the Post Office Regulations the export of explosives, including cartridges, by parcel post is prohibited. 7. RESPONSIBILITY OF EXPORTER. —Attention is called to the fact that where a licence is granted for the export of prohibited or restricted goods the licence does not relieve the owner of the goods or the consignor or other person to whom the licence is granted from any responsibility to which he may be subject for any breach of law or regulations. 8. SIGNATURE OF FORM.—The declaration on page 1 must be signed by a person domiciled in the United Kingdom, otherwise the application cannot be accepted. Subject as hereinafter mentioned, applications will not be considered unless they bear the signature of the applicant, or, in the case of a firm, the signature of the partner, or, in the case of a company, the signature of a director or the secretary ; the status of the signatory should be indicated. In exceptional circumstances applications may be otherwise signed if reasons which are regarded as adequate are submitted, in writing, to the Imports and Exports Licensing Section, and full responsibility is accepted for the person whose signature is allowed. In such cases the Imports and Exports Licensing Section number of the approval must be quoted in the space provided on page 1. Applications must always be made by the merchant, manufacturer, or other person who is directly interested as consignor in the export and not by a forwarding agent or other person on behalf of the actual exporter. For this purpose the consignor is the person or firm who accepts an order from abroad, although he may not be the actual manufacturer or supplier of the goods. All applications should be addressed to :— The Director, Imports and Exports Licensing Section, Board of Trade, Great George Street, London, S.W.l.COPY W.J. RAILTON. 11, Queen Victoria Street London, K.C.4. The Director, Import &amp; Export Licensing Section, Board of Trade, Great George Street, LONDON . S.W.l. 30th June, 1938* Dear Sir, Your Ref: 221006. E.L. My Ref: 1621. I thank you for your letter of the 29th and I return herewith the application form duly completed. In case you should require the Importers Licence I also enclose this for your perusal and should be obliged if you would kindly return this. The first shipment is ready for shipment by a steamer closing bth July and as there is only one steamer per month I trust under the circumstances you can let me have the necessary licence by return so that I can catch this steamer. Thanking you in anticipation, Yours faithfully, (Signed) W.J. Railton.■should quote the following reference Teleynon.e No. Whitehall, 5140. Any reply to this communication C.E.T. 688/34. BOARD 01-' TRADE, Great George Street, p Westminster 24 th ’y, 1934 London, S.W.l. '9?4 Dear Walton As Sturton is now employed on other work, I am replying to your letter (PZ. 430/34) of the 12th February, regarding the revised arrangements for licensing the The objects of the new licensing system (which is limited to armament manufacturers approved by the Service Departments as being of national importance) are:- (1) to define clearly on the licence the conditions under which alone it may be cancelled (viz. in the interests of Imperial security or in consequence of any international agreement to which His Majesty’s Government are or may become a party) and so to remove the former provision that the licence ’’may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade without reason given”; ( 2 ) to speed up the issue of licences; ( 3 ) to remove the necessity for the renewal of licences every three months. A copy of the new form of licence is enclosed. With regard to (2) of the preceding paragraph, it was arranged, in accordance with the Cabinet decision of export of war material to foreign governments J.C. Walton, Esq.i 20 th December last, that applications received from selected firms for licences to export war material to foreign governments should be referred only to the Foreign Office and that on receipt of their approval of the applications the Board of Trade should issue the necessary licences and forward copies of them to the Service Departments concerned. The foregoing represents a general statement of the procedure but it is assumed that in practice any application for the export of war material to Afghanistan or Nepal would not be approved by the Foreign Office before consultation with the India Office. It is recognised, however, that special considerations apply to the exportation of war material to the Governments of Afghanistan and Nepal, and the Foreign Office, with whom I have discussed the matter, agree that as regards these two countries the old arrangements should continue in force, viz. that applications received from the selected firms for the export of war material to Afghanistan will be referred both to the Foreign Office and the India Office /andand those relating to Nepal to the India Office only. A copy of the list of firms to which the special form of export licence may be issued is attached for your information. When an application from one of these firms relating to the export of war material is referred to the India Office the accompanying communication will be stamped 'Special Licence' to denote thflt it refers to a case in which the issue of the special form of licence arises and to serve as an indication that the examination of the application should be made with the minimum of delay. I have sent a copy of this letter to Ashley Clarke of the Foreign Office. Yours sincerelyCOPY. EXPORT LICENCE. v v&gt; a *ii£* In pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by the several Proclamations and Orders prohibiting the Exportation of certain articles from the l nited Kingdom, the Board of Trade do hereby authorise and permit to export from any port in the United Kingdom to consigned to (hereinafter referred to as the consignee) the following goods, namely, upon the following conditions :— (1) That the said goods are delivered to the consignee at the destination named in this Licence, and that the Owner or Shipper of the said goods, if so required by the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and Excise shall produce to them, within such time as they may allow, proof to their satisfaction that the said goods were so delivered. (2) That this Licence shall be deemed void and of no effect in the event of non-compliance with condition (1) as set out above and as accepted by the applicant in his application for this Licence. (3) That this Licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade if they deem it necessary to do so (a) in the interests of Imperial security ; or (b) in consequence of any international agreement to which His Majesty’s Government are or may become a party. Dated the day of 19 NOTE.—The Board of Customs and Excise require pre-entry (i.e. entry and clearance before shipment) of all export prohibited goods. An Assistant Secretary to the Board of Trade. Note. —If any alteration is desired in this Licence it must be returned with a request for amendment. Net unauthorised alteration is permissible. \Yt. 28347iSH)4. 3500. 2/34. W\ .P C. 613.List of selected firms and Service Departments which will acquaint them of the new procedure . Barr &amp; Stroud, Ltd, (Admiralty) Anniesland, Glasgow. B.S.A. Guns, Ltd, (War Office) Small Heath, Birmingham. W. Beardmore &amp; Co., Ltd. (Admiralty) Parkhead Works, Glasgow. T. Firth &amp; J. Brown, Ltd. (Admiralty) Sheffield. Greer^ood &amp; Batley, Ltd. (War Office) Leeds. Hadfields, Ltd. (Admiralty) East Hecla Works, Sheffield. I.C.I. Metals, Ltd. (War Office) Millbank, S.W.l, and various works. Imperial Chemical Industries, Ltd. (War Office) Millbank, S.W.l, and various works. J.I. Thornycroft &amp; Co., Ltd. (Admiralty) Smith Square, Westminster,S.W.l and various works. Vickers-Armstrongs, Ltd. (War Office) Vickers House, Broadway, Westminster, S.W. 1, and various works. Whitehead Torpedo Works (Admiralty) Weymouth. Aircraft manufacturers: (Air Ministry) Sir W.G. Armstrong Whitworth Aircraft Ltd. Parkside, Coventry. Boulton &amp; Paul, Ltd. Aircraft Works, Norwich. The Bristol Aeroplane Co. Ltd. Filton House, Bristol. The Blackburn Aeroplane &amp; Motor Co.Ltd. Brough, East Yorks. The De Havilland Aircraft Co. Ltd. Stag Lane Aerodrome, Edgware, Middlesex. The Fairey Aviation Co. Ltd. Hayes, Middlesex. The Gloster Aircraft Co. Ltd. Gloster Works &amp; Aerodrome, Hucclecote, Glos. Handley Page, Ltd. Claremont Road, Cricklewood, N.W. Hawker Aircraft, Ltd. Canbury Park Road, Kingston-on-Thames. George Pamall &amp; Co. The Aerodrome, Yate, Bristol. A.V. Roe &amp; Co. Ltd. Newton Heath, Manchester. The Supermarine Aviation Works, (Vickers) Ltd. Short Bros. (Rochester &amp; Bedford) Ltd. Woolston, Southampton. Seaplane Works, Rochester, Kent. Saunders, Roe, Ltd. Bush House, Aldwych, W.C. 2. Vickers Aviation Limited. Weybridge, Surrey. Westland Aircraft Works Yeovil, Somerset.* DRAFT LETTER 1 2 FEB 1954 SECRET. (Tj HTTh.C arr, Esq., C.B.E., Foreign Office. (2) F.Sturton, Esq., O.B.E., Licensing Section, Board of Trade. We have received demi-officially from the Board of Trade a copy of the record of the meeting held on the 29th December to decide on a revised procedure for the export of war material to foreign Governments in accordance with the Cabinet decision of 20th December (Cabinet 70(33) Conclusion 22). We note from Ah is /that under the V*. [O' new procedure the F.O. , but not the Defence Departments, will be consulted before the issue of a licence to an approved firm and we should like, in this connection, to draw attention to our special interest in war material ordered by the Governments of Afghanistan and Nepal, the import of which through Indian ports is governed by specific ^ treaty provisions. ^ ^ £*0+4* 4cS c* ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ /TW, * 4 * t+m // tiOlXU* $ ^ 2-0 ^ The point is explained in the etter to Hind, of which I enclose a copy; in reply we were told at the time that we should look to the Defence Departments for the information we required. Now that a change has been V- made,we should be glad fre know whc-tfror ^-wr'r» C» (to* thoro would bo any objection isu Lliln Aft \rrtJL 9kf Ifi* bo (**- a 7v4 2262 5000 11.33 0^ rftrr Office/beift^ consulted by the Board of Trade in the same way as has been done hitherto/EgAm Of TRADE :r. s.w.i i^u^i 17th January, 1934, Dear Anderson, I gather that your Department will he interested in the conclusions reached at an inter departmental meeting held here on the 29th December last to discuss the revised form of export of arms licensing procedure. I enclose a copy herewith. fours sincerely,It • i Note of a meeting at the boa] the 139th December, 1935, at P. z. 430 1934 T-rrfmr •erf o c 15 7m Friday, p « dir Horace Hamilton (in the Chair) Sir Henry fountain \ ) \ ! r. T. St. a. Hill ( ) \ Hr® Sturton i Board of Trade hr, iCemn ) hr. Stacy i Hr* Carr Foreign tiff ice Hr* Newsam Home ^Office Hr 0 Jenkins Director of Contracts, Admiralty Hr. V.hitham A.D.O.F. \.ar Office Hr. Bovenschen Director of Contracts, War Office Hr. Oaipin Air Ministry Col® Hind C.I.D. Hr. Helton Do O.T. Hr. Jfc,(enzxe Customs l e The Conference had before them a revised form of licence for the export of arms, drawn up In accordance with the decision of the Cabinet of 2nth Deceraber 0 The Chairman drew attention to the T'ote circulated by the Cabinet Secretariat in this connexion and to the specific points raised therein which required the attention of the Conferenc ? 0 list of approved firms . 2. It was agreed that the Defence Cervices panel of the Contracts Co-ordinating Committee should be invited to be reononBible for the drawing un of a list of approved firms2 - of* nGtioncl importance and for its amendment from time to time, if necessary, as circumstances might require,# Questions arising in this connexion would also he referred to the Committee. The members of the Committee would report to their respective departments. list of firms would be circulated to the foreign Office, Home Office, Board of Trade, department of Overseas Trade, the Service departments and the Customs. hethod of informing approved firms of the new procedure . o. It was agreed that, in accordance with the Cabinet decision, the approved firms should be told of the new arrangements as informally as possible. The Gervice Departments were in favour of the Board of Trade, as the licence issuing authority, acting as the channel of communicationa The Chairman pointed out that the Cervice Departments could much more conveniently arrange for infoir* 1 communication with armament firms than the Board of Trade* It was agreed that the Cervice Departments should divide th 2 approved firms among themselves and arrange for the oral and informal communication in question, a Board of Trade representative being present, where possible. 4* ?&gt;r. Carr (Foreign Office) expressed the hope that as little should be said as possible of the existence of an approved list. He anticipated embarrassing questions being asked of H.H. Reoresentatives abroad as to whether, for example, it was the fact that armament orders placed with firm A were likely to be more certainly carried out thffi orders placed v/ith firm B. Hr. B o v^nsch^n (V&lt;&gt;0. ) also foresaw difficulties arising from the fact that fims not on the approved list ('borderline cases') would ask tThe panel has since met (on 9th January) and a Report is being made to the Board of Trade,,-3 why they were excluded* The Chairman suggested that orders were not likely, in any case, to be given by foreign Governments to firms not on the approved list„ It was agreed that the existence of such a list should not be referred to* The procedure ivould be to inform a particular approved firm that they need not anticipate difficulties about export licences for orders from foreign Governments and that the latter would be in a form that would facilitate their securing orders*, It would be made clear that other firms were being similarly treated 0 It was further agreed that firms which discovered that they ware not being accorded the advantages of the new procedure and made representations on the subject would be required to substantiate their claim for similar treatment,. Applications for licences . 5o Th 0 Chairman explained that, in accordance with the Cabinet decision, the Service Departments would not be consulted before the issue of a licence, although they would be informed as soon as a licence was issued. The Foreign Office v/ould still have to be consulted before the issue of the licence 0 It was agreed that the existing fom of communication from the Board of Trade to the ForoLrn Office should be retained but that it should be sent seml-officiall? direct to the Department of ths Foreign Office concerned and that it should bear some distinctive sign to show that it related to a licence under the new procedure. ‘I hQ Chairman explained that the safeguards which the Sub-Committee on Licensing had contemplated in their scheme, viz. pre-entry with the Customs at least seven days before export and the obligation on the part of manufacturers to keep the Service Departments infonned of armament orders, were no part of the present proposal. M r, Palpin (Air Ministry ) expressed apprehension in this connexion but the representatives of the far Office and Admiralty doubtedwhether any difficulty would arise in practice* The Chairman explained that the Board of Trade would have power to revoke a licence r 'in the Interests of Imperial security”» iloreover, specific licences and not open licences were still to be required, &amp;ew form of licence o Chairman explained that the existing unlimited provision as to revocation would be deleted from the new licences * Mr, Carr (Foreign Office ) said he thought that the Mote on the licence form as to the Governments to which wax- material might he exported was superfluous and nossihiy* misleading. The Chairman explained that this note *was necessary because of the Cabinet decision that the new licence should be in a form which* If published p might permit of easy comparison with the old licence and that it should therefore be self-explanatory. It was agreed that the ex-enemy countries need not be specified by name. The Chairman also explained* with regard to condition 3 of the licence* that the insertion of the words ”If they deem it necessary 1 ’ and the substitution of the v/ords 'in consequence of any International agreement' for the words 'in pursuance of any international agreement” were necessary to meet legal points raised by the Solicitor to the Board of Trade. A copy of the draft form of licence as agreed upon by the Conference is attached. Question of informing foreign Governments » 8 0 IAro Carr (Foreign Office ) said that his Department were disposed to do nothing at present on this point. They would be guided by the progress of the Disarmament discussions. T he Chairman pointed out* with reference to the Cabinet Secretariat Mote referred to in para. 1 that It would not be wise to speak In conversation with representatives of foreignGovermiants of rf restrict Ions v/hlch operate In this country alone', since certain foreign Governments might retort that ^ they already had a licensing system (even if the system were in fact, not adequately enforced ) 0 Date of operation , it wa s agreed that February 1st, 1934, should be fixed as the date on which the scheme should come into operation, the date to be postponed If necessary*Vc^ CABINET 7 0 ( 33 ) 20th December 1933* IMPERIAL DEFENCE. Position of Private Arma ments Industry in. (Previous Reference: Cabinet 69 (33) Con- elusion 6.) 22. The President of the Board of Trade informed the Cabinet that following a meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence on Monday, December iSth, the Prime Minister had discussed with those of his colleagues principally concerned the outstanding point of the ♦ decisions reached on the subject of the Private Armaments Industry at the meeting referred to in the margin, namely, as to when this policy ought to be announced. As the result of this discussion certain fresh proposals had been made and had been remitted for discussion between himself and the Ministers at the head of the Defence Departments. That discussion had taken place that very morning before the meeting of the Cabinet and as a result he submitted a fresh proposal, copies of which he handed round to the Cabinet (Appendix III). On being informed that the new proposal commended itself to the President of the Board of Trade and the Ministers of theDefence Departments and was based on suggestions made by the Prime Minister, the Cabinet agreed: To cancel their decision in Cabinet 69(33) Conclusion 6 (a) headed ' Modification of the ^]^^nt_^£tejTL_nf_.li c^n^ing exp orts of arms an d^arnmumtion ' and to substitute therefor the scheme in Appendix III.APPENDIX III. PRIVATE ARDALSNTS INDUSTRY . On the assumption that it is decided to reconsider the decision reached on December 13th, to issue to approved firms open licences for the export of war material (Cabinet 69 (33) Conclusion 6) the Ministers mainly concerned have agreed to submit to the Cabinet the following alternative proposals v/hich represent in their view the bare minimum which will be of any value in allaying the uncertainty at present existing in the minds of prospective customers of the British Armament Industry. The new proposal, if approved by the Cabinet, should be given a three months’ trial; if at the end of that period the arrangements are found not to have worked satisfactorily the Question of adopting the ’open licence’ system should be again considered. P rocedure . When an approved firm receives information that a foreign Government is in the market for a specific transaction the firm will be granted a licence by the Board of Trade and an assurance will be given that the licence will not be revoked g^e J.n^^^xQm) tl ^ri a l,. cir cums tances. In order that there may be no loss of time in the granting of the licence (a) special arrangements will be made by the Foreign Office which will ensure that in ordinary circumstances there will be no delay in communicating the consent of that Department to the Board'“of Trade. (b) it will not be necessary (as at present) for the Board of Trade to consult the Service Department concerned before the licence is granted, but that Department will always be notified at the time the licence is actually granted. InIn order to give effect to the proposed arrangements ^ the following alterations will be made in the Form of li cence lQZ_. &amp;nm:QiL Qd__lirm2 : - Dele te the proviso that the licence is valid only for three months. D elete the proviso tfa t the Board of Trade may revoke or modify the licence at any time. Insert : The conditions under which this licence is granted are set forth below (viz -) 'This licence is granted only for the export of war material to such'foreign Governments (or their accredited aPBnts) as are recognised by H.K. Government with the exception of the Govern ments of Abyssinia, Germany, Austria, Hungary and Bulgaria to which countries the supply of'war material is precluded by Treaty. Tn.e licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade (a) if the foregoing condition is not fulfilled; (b) in the interests of Imperial security; or (c) in pursuance of an international agreement to which His Majesty's Government are or may become a party'. l^il 2 IL.toJ 1 nfprm^r^£^d^Iirr:^. It will be necessary that the approved firms (after they have been selected) should be given an assurance in advance that licences on the above terms will be granted to them and th t they should be allowed to ecrueint their prospective customers (either direct or through their accredited agents). The Departments concerned might explain to firms verbally the more elastic procedure to be adopted in future in their case, reminding them that as there is only a limited number of firms to whom this privilege is granted they should use discretion as regards the method of imparting the information to their prospective customers. A^iQn_lf_ijr^C£d ur£_i£...4 U£ ^Mioned . In due course the new arrangements may be expected to become public and enauiries must be answered. The answer might, it is thought, take the form that H.M. Government have decided to define more closely the manner in which they intend to exercise control over the export of armaments in future. The3 . &gt; The new and old forms of licence should be Quoted in extenso. The new form of licence applies at present only to selected firms. The policy of H.M. Government remains unaltered so far as Geneva is concerned, viz; to seek international agreement to reach a position in which the export of arms from all countries will be regulated by identical measures. If it is thought desirable for political reasons that Foreign Governments should be notified of the proposed change it is suggested that it be done informally and unobtrusively, and in such a v/ay as to minimise the importance attached to the matter. H.M. Representatives abroad should be instructed to take some opportunity when they are discussing some other topic with the Foreign Ministers concerned to point out that the policy which H.M. Government have consistently advocated regarding the adoption of national systems for licensing the export of arms and ammunition has failed to produce any response and to draw attention to certain results of this failure including the fact that the restrictions which operate in this country alone not only do not check the total volume of the traffic in arms but allow the foreign competitors of our armaments industry to increase and profit at the expense of employment in this country. H.M. Representatives will make their oral communications in such a form as will not call for any reply but at the same time will give us a good answer to any foreign critic who may accuse us of changing our arrangements without notice.-t P •Z.71 55/35. A. . - i 1 Mr.Laith^4ite, I spoke to Mr.Hoskin on the telephone about this and understood from him that there would probably be little objection on the part of the Service^ Departmentsto the information we require being given us direct by the approved armament firms but that the attitude taken up by the Sub-Committee was due to their being unaware of the fact that the armament firms concerned do / in practice / constantly communicate with this Office either direct or through the Department of Overseas Trade in connection with consignments of arms ordered by jthe Governments W Afghanistan and Nepal/. I said that the India Office would probably not wish to press the point if there were any substantial objection on the part of the Service^ Departments, but that we felt that as the firms concerned had in the past been willing to communicate direct with us they should continue to do so^and that our position was in fact somewhat different from that of the Foreign Office, in view of the close relations between India and the two countries concerned for which we wei sible in this/c .«• this country. Perhaps we might await any observations which the War Office may have to offer on the letter to Colonel Hind of 28th, nde^ d n • r/ r r r T r&gt; ' ', ' r ^ - . -/z. -'. Z Z J v S.W.H. , ( p 7 ^ Y,, U rr (7 L - it Ib5 . /fciH-' M-('([ss Dear Laithwaite, ''^h/ ' ^ ' V ^ I have received a copy of your letter to Hind of the 28th October (P.Z. 6848/33) in which you suggest that firms receiving open licences to export arms to foreign Gfovernments should report direct to the India Office, as well as to Defence Departments, any orders for war material received from the Governments of Afghanistan and Nepal. As it will presumably fall to the Board of Trade to make any necessary arrangements with the firms concerned, we have noted this suggestion for consideration if, and when, the occasion arises. I may mention, however, that the sub-committee were definitely of the opinion that reports of orders should be made to the Defence Departments only, and that those Departments should be responsible for notifying any otner Department that might be interested. The Foreign Office representative on the sub-committee was quite satisfied with this arrangement. J.G.Laithwaite, Esq.,qaestion of the report of the Sab-Committee on the system of licensing exports of arms and ammunition. Z* The procedure proposed in the report, together with the arrangement you referred to, would substantially Ar« Lj***t* *+. — meet our noint* did be Departments, any orders for war material received from the Governments of Afghanistan and Nepal (in the case of the former country the Foreign Office should be informed as well). 3 « I am not sure whether there would be any difficulty m arranging this, Board of Trade, in case they may care to offer suggestions before the report is finally approved. SECRET. £ 8 %) 1955 My dear Hind, Lieut.-Colonel N.G. Hind, M.C., 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1. Many thanks for your* letter of 2ord October, I.D./G/137, on the Copy to Col. Hill, war Office. r r. A.8/ Hoskin, Bd. of Trade. preferable if it could be arranged It hat the approved firms should report to us direct, as well as to the Defence but I am sending copies of this letter to Hill of the War Office and Hoskin, j. G gAITHWAlTE.&gt; X IH' -AliO ID/Q/137 23rd October, SECRET My dear Laithwaite, In reply to your letter. No. P.Z.5250/33 of the 20th October, on the question of the Report of the Sub-Committee on the System of Licensing Exports of Arms and Ammunition. The Sub-Committee fully realise that the India Office would require all information regarding exports of arms to Afghanistan that might be des patched from the United Kingdom. They consider that this information would be forthcoming under the proposed arrangements. In granting open licences to approved firms these firms would be v/arned that they must report to the Defence Departments any orders for war material received from the Government of any country. This would, of course, include Afghanistan and Nepal. All shipments by other firms or private individuals would continue to be sub ject to licence, and in the event of any orders from those countries information would be received under the existing system. I am sending a copy of your letter and my reply to Colonel Hill of the War Office, who has succeeded Mackesy in M.I.la. Reports from firms regarding war material would, in the case of Afghanistan and Nepal, be sent to the War Office, who would be expected to inform the India Office. I am also sending a copy to Hoskin of the Board of Trade, who is already aware of your requirements. The present situation is that this Report is to be considered at a meeting of the Cabinet Committee, under the Chairmanship of Mr. Runciman, at some dateearly in November. Directly it is approved, or otherwise, I will let you know, so that you may remind the War Office and the Board of Trade to hear this point in mind when issuing any Instruc tions or open licences to approved firms. J.G.Laithwaite, Esq. , India Office.5250/33. rs IHiilA 'JmCE, 3 U-tJ I ^ ***%£ L IBITHiA. • . y_’ 10th October, 1933. (P Ij deer Hinu, Ion kindly sent in your letter of 3 th June &amp; copy of the Report of the «^ub—CoissitLer on the ystes of Uc«iBing xports of xsp ana OTinitions. 1 'smj perhaps mention, with reference to paragraph 26(f)-ii' of the report that attention has been drawn here to the ▼slue of the Xpert Licencing Syaten in providing a check on imports by the ^fghan iofei*naent who freinently fail to notiiy ills Majesty’s inister at abnl of their intention to buy eras froa the inited ingdoA* l 9 As repirds the grant of open licence , while we recognise that it is possible to exercise u control of imports at British Indian ports, we think it very desirable that the India Office, as well as the errice departments fcf« paragraph 4' ot the report) shou^a be kept infons^d by the j rmaaecte finis to whom open licensfm are issued, of orders for war material destined for/ it •Col* H*)- Hina, !.?•. Qommi t tec o f iaDerial i once 2 9 hitehall hardens, ofor Afghanistan (ana also for Hepal)* As you will appreciate the question is one of eo»e importance. 3. Xhe check to which i hare referred in paragraph 1 chore is, of course, not merely useful to us, but is also definitely in the interests of British manufacturers, who might otherwise consign goods to Afghanistan, fail to get an import license at 'areehi, and hare to pay freight charges both ways for nothing. 4. '&amp;e should be glad if the points referred to ebore could be brought to the notice of the interested departments. Could you, in this connection, let *e know what the present position is as regards approring and implementing the proposals of the l ub-Comuittee? lourf sincerely, J. G. LA1THWAITE.Committee on the System of Licensing Exports of Arms and Ammunition. It has 'been duly approved and signed by all members. You will see from paragraph 41 that the proposals made in the Report are considered to be consistent with the provisions of the Arms Traffic Convention 1925. In view of this, the proposals given in paragraph 46 are hardly likely to conflict in any way with your views. The Report will now be laid before the Principal Supply Officers Committee, and subsequently before the Cabinet Sub-Committee on the State of the Private Armaments Industry. J.G.Laithwaite, Esq. , India Office.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence. June 1933. SECRET. Copy No. 22 Q P.S.O. (E.A.) 33. (Also Paper No. P.S.O. 374.) COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE Principal Supply Officers Committee. Sub-Committee on System of Licensing Exports of Arms and Ammunition. REPORT. * i JVt 1 ? 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.1F. 1, June 23, 1933. ( 8664 )INDEX. Paragraphs I. —Introduction ... ... ... ... ... ... 1-3 II. —Powers ... ... ... ... ... ... 4-9 III. —History of Control of Arms Traffic ... ... ... 10-13 IV. —Description of existing Export Licensing System ... ... 14-25 V.—Uses of the Licensing System ... ... ... ... 26 VI.—Effects of the present System upon the Competitive Position of United Kingdom Manufacturers ... ... ... 27-31 VII.—Limitations of existing Legislation ... ... ... 32-34 VIII.—Proposals ... ... ... ... ... ... 35-45 IX.—Kecommendations ... ... ... ... ... 46 Appendices. Page Appendix (A).—Text of Legislative Powers ... ... ... 13 Appendix (B).—Historical Note on Control of Arms Traffic ... ... 14 Appendix (C).—Text of the Arms Export Prohibition Order and Open General Export Licences ... ... ... 17 Appendix (D).— Form of Export Licence ... ... ... ... 22 Appendix (E).—List of Export Licences revoked and Renewals refused. 1924-32 ... ... ... ... 23 Appendix (F).—Examples refusal of Licences ... ... 24REPORT. I.—Introduction. Terms of Reference. 1. WE were appointed by the Principal Supply Officers Committee at its 54th Meeting on the 15th March, 1933, as a Sub-Committee, with the following terms of reference :— “ To consider the present system of licensing exports of arms, ammunition and other materials to which the Arms Export Prohibition Order, 1931, applies and to report what modifications, if any, are, in their view, desirable, having regard to— (a) the interests of the Fighting Services; and (b) the competitive position of the United Kingdom firms in obtaining orders from foreign countries.” Constitution. 2. The Sub-Committee as constituted consisted of representatives of the Foreign Office, Home Office, Admiralty, War Office, Air Ministry, Board of Trade and Department of Overseas Trade. 3. In considering our terms of reference we have noted the conclusion of the Principal Supply Officers Committee in their Report on the position of the private armaments industry in Imperial Defence (P.S.O. 366) that a steady supplv of foreign orders is necessary if the armament firms in the United Kingdom are to have an adequate potential capacity for production in war. That Committee also express the opinion in the same Report that the existence of an effective control over the export of arms and the fear that an embargo on export may be imposed by His Majesty’s Government at a time when arms are most required, has led foreign Governments to place their orders elsewhere. Origin. II.— Powers. 4. The present powers to regulate the export of arms from the United Kingdom are derived from Section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, as amended and extended by Section 1 of the Exportation of Arms Act, 1900, and Section 17 of the Finance Act, 1921. This legislation repeated and expanded much older legislation. The text of the more important provisions is given in Appendix (A). Effect and Scope. 5. The combined effect of the provisions of 1879 and 1921 is to give power to prohibit by Proclamation or Order-in-Council the export or coastwise shipment of weapons and munitions of war of every description, and also of firearms not being weapons of war and ammunition for such firearms. 6. The legislation of 1900 gives power to prohibit by Proclamation the exportation of arms to any specified country or place “ in order to prevent such arms, ammunition, military or naval stores being used against Her Majesty’s subjects or forces or against any forces engaged or which may be engaged in military or naval operations in co-operation with Her Majesty’s forces.”* Thus power to prohibit export to a specified country can be used only when hostilities involving this country are in existence or are threatened; at other times any prohibition must be general in its scope, and exports to a particular destination can be controlled only by means of a licensing system. Warships. 7. There is now special legislation dealing with warships. Bv Section 1 of the Treaties of Washington Act, 1922, it is prohibited to buila, equip, or despatch any vessel of war without a licence from the Admiralty, but there is a * These powers were intended primarily to prevent the export of arms and ammunition to the Boxer insurgents in China. Immediately after the Act came into force, however, the Boxer rising was suppressed; and apparently no proclamation prohibiting the export of arms to China was actually issued. [8664] B 24 proviso that a licence shall not be refused unless it appears to the Admiralty necessary to do so for the purpose of securing the observance of obligations imposed by the Washington Treaty for the limitation of naval armaments. 8. It should be noted that warships are not covered by the general legislation dealing with export of arms and that the export of naval craft and their armament on foreign order is subject only to the Washington legislation although naval armaments exported separately require a licence issued in pursuance of the general legislation. Special attention is called to the fact that licences under the Washington Act cannot be refused except for the purpose of securing the observance of international obligations. A ircra jt. 9. Unarmed aircraft and aircraft engines would not fall within the scope of the system of export licences if it were not for the Ethiopian Arms Traffic Treat} of 1930 (see paragraph 12), which requires every consignment of aircraft and aircraft engines to Abyssinia to be specifically licensed. After that Treaty came into force, the position of aircraft manufacturers was safeguarded by the issue of what is known as an “open general licence” in respect of aircraft and aircraft engines under which manufacturers are allowed to export freely except to Abyssinia. In fact the Air Ministry have had for many years a working arrangement with the manufacturers under which the consent of the Ministry is obtained before aircraft are exported, and that Department consults the Foreign Office where considerations of policy appear to be involved. It is, of course, in the interest of the manufacturers to comply with the wishes of the Air Ministry, who are fully satisfied with the working of this arrangement. III.— History of Control of Arms Traffic. Prior to 1914. 10. A note on the history of the control of the arms traffic is attached as Appendix (B). Attention is drawn to the fact that prior to 1914 there was no prohibition on the exportation of arms from this country and therefore no licensing system. The present system is to a great extent a legacy of the general system enforced during the late war for the control of exports. Only arms, ammunition, &amp;c., now remain subject to licence on exportation. International Conventions, 1919 and 1925. 11. As regards the international aspect, prior to 1914, the problem of control was related mainly to the slave trade. The measures taken to cope with the traffic were local in character and no system of export licensing existed. Since the close of the war two international Conventions dealing with the arms traffic have been signed in 1919 and 1925, the latter superseding the former. Under these a system of export prohibition and licence was to be set up by contracting countries. The 1925 Convention was ratified by His Majesty’s Government in 1930 with the reservation that ratification would not become effective until ratifications by the other principal arms-producing States had also become effective. This condition has not been fulfilled and the convention has remained inoperative. FAhiopian Treaty. 12. The only international obligation which binds His Majesty’s Govern ment and involves the control of the export of arms from this country is the Ethiopian Arms Traffic Treaty. 1930, to which France, Italy, Ethiopia and the United Kingdom are parties. This applies the provisions of the Arms Traffic Convention of 1925 to Abyssinia. Accordingly His Majesty’s Government are bound not to permit the export of arms of any kind (or of aircraft and aircraft engines) to Abyssinia except under specific export licence. Disarmament Conference. 13. The control of the arms traffic has also been among the subjects considered at the present Disarmament Conference. The discussions have beenbased on the assumption that some kind of control is necessary, but there has been a difference of opinion as to the form which it should take. His Majesty’s Government have instructed the United Kingdom delegates to the effect that they should insist that any convention should provide for an export licensing system for arms and ammunition, such as is already in force in this country. IV. —Description of Existing Export Licensing System. A rms Export Prohibition Order, 1931. 14. The present system has been in force without substantial alteration since 1921 and is now based on an Arms Export Prohibition Order-in-Council which came into force on the 1st June, 1931. This specifies twenty classes of material, the export of which from the United Kingdom is prohibited save under licence. The issue of the Order was accompanied by open general licences permitting unrestricted export in certain cases. The general effect is that the export of war material and rifled weapons of every description is subject to licence whatever the destination; the export of aircraft and aircraft engines and of bayonets, swords and lances is subject to licence only when the destination is Abyssinia; and the export of shot guns and ammunition and of certain types of gunpowder and industrial explosives is subject to licence only when the destination is in one of certain special zones in Asia and Africa (see paragraph 26 (/)). The text of the Order and of the open general licences is given in Appendix (C). 15. The administration of the Order is carried out by the Imports and Exports Licensing Section of the Board of Trade which acts upon the advice of other Departments, mainly the Foreign Office, Home Office and the Service Departments. Period of Investigation. 16. The time which elapses between the receipt of an application for a licence and its issue is usually between two and seven days, according to the time taken by the Departments in making the necessary investigations. In urgent cases, as where an armament firm is asked at very short notice to submit samples for adjudication in a foreign country, special steps are taken to expedite the necessary enquiries and the licence may be issued within 48 hours of the receipt of the application. Period of Licence. 17. Licences are normally valid for a period of three months from the date of issue and may be renewed at the expiration of that period. If a request is made for a licence to be valid for a period exceeding three months the Department, in accordance with a Cabinet decision of 1925, is required to seek the approval of the Cabinet. This is known as a “firm” licence. No request of this kind has been received since 1928, firms relying where necessary on the renewal of the ordinary licence of three months. Conditions of Licence. 18. A copy of the form of export licence (Appendix (D)) is attached and particular attention is directed to the conditions printed on the licence itself. These conditions are’ very relevant to the present inquiry as foreign customers of United Kingdom firms will be familiar with the form of licence issued. 19. The most important condition is that the Board of Trade may modify or revoke the licence at any time without reason given. This is the common form on all Board of Trade licences and is inserted in order to make it clear that the licensee would have no right to compensation if the action indicated is taken. A list of all cases in which licences have been revoked or renewal refused is given in Appendix (E).20. Arising out of certain cases* in which licences were revoked or renewal was refused, the Cabinet in 1925 issued an instruction that a warning notice should be attached to every war material licence at the time of issue. The terms of this notice are as follows :— “ Attention is called to the fact that licences for the export of Arms and Ammunition are granted for a period of three months only and that no guarantee can be given, or has ever been implied, that they will be renewed after the expiration of that period (the period being limited in order that His Majesty’s Government may have an opportunity to reconsider the matter, if necessary). All firms accepting foreign orders which require more than three months to complete must understand that they do so at their own risk. It should, of course, be understood that this notice does not modify the condition under which all licences are issued, viz., that in exceptional circumstances, they may be cancelled or withdrawn at any time, even before the expiry of the three months without reason given, the risk of which is, of course, taken by the licensee.” 21. Subsequently, in 1925, when the Cabinet considered the question of the grant of licences for a period of more than three months, it was decided that, where such licences were issued (after approval in each case by the Cabinet: see paragraph 17 above) the form of licence should omit the condition relating to the power of the Board of Trade to revoke or modify a licence at any time. In its place the licence is accompanied by a letter stating that the licence will not be withdrawn ‘ ‘ save in the event of circumstances of an altogether exceptional character arising which the Board of Trade are at present quite unable to foresee.” Categories of Licences. 22. Applicationst for export licences may be divided broadlv into three categories :— (a) Applications relating to war material. This category can be sub-divided under the following heads :— (i) Applications by manufacturers. (ii) Applications by arms dealers and others which relate to sales of Government surplus stores. (iii) Applications by representatives of the Dominion Governments, the Government of India or the Crown Agents for the Colonies for licences to export material to the Government concerned. (5) Applications for licences to export arms other than war material. e.g., sporting rifles, shot guns, revolvers, pistols, ammunition and industrial explosives. (c) Applications by persons who do not possess a certificate issued under the Firearms Act, 1920, entitling them to hold firearms in this country, but who wish to purchase firearms to take with them on going abroad. Number of Licences Issued. 23. The total number of export licences issued in 1932 was 10,897, of which by far the greatest number is represented by category {b). The available statistics show that the number of licences issued to manufacturers and arms dealers for the issue of war material was 410, representing only between 3 per cent, and 4 per cent, of the total number issued, although they cover by far the greater part of the value of the goods exported. Of the 410 licences, 357 were issued to arms manufacturers. * After the war it was forbidden to send arms to Soviet -Russia. This embargo was removed by the Labour Government in 1924. The B.S.A. Company and Vickers, Limited, obtained licences in that year for the export of certain machine guns and parts to the Soviet Government. When the Conservative Government came into power in December 1924 the embargo on arms for Russia was again imposed (It was removed by the Labour Government in 1929 and is no longer in force.) By this time some, but not all, of the material had been shipped. The reversal of the Government policy involved revocation of one licence and refusal to renew three others (for details, see Appendix (E)). The B.S.A. Company and Vickers, Limited, were accordingly prevented from completing their contracts and made claims for compensation, which were refused. f No licences are, of course, required for export of war material by the Service Departments, who, in lieu of a licence, supply the Customs with a certificate.7 Refusals to Grant Licences. 25. Apart from cases arising out of general embargoes, refusals to issue licences for which specific applications have been submitted are comparatively rare. It is, however, the case that a manufacturer or dealer does not usually accept an order for war material without first ascertaining by preliminary enquiry whether an application is likely to succeed. The refusal of licences may be due to reasons of policy or to such reasons as the failure of the applicant to disclose the ultimate consignee or non-compliance with the Firearms Act, 1920. Examples of cases in which licences have been refused to arms manufacturers are given in Appendix (F). V.— Uses of the Licensing System. 26. The primary objects of pre-war legislation were presumably to conserve national resources and to prevent in time of actual or threatened war the export of arms for use against this country and its allies. The Great War brought with it both prohibition of exports and a licensing system which survived after the war. Since then they have been adapted in peace time to other purposes, both national and international, e.cj., restricting the world traffic in arms. The various uses to which the licensing system has been, or can be, put are discussed below. (a) Conservation of United Kingdom Resources in Times of Emergency. If war were imminent it would no doubt be necessary to impose forthwith export restrictions covering a list of goods which would go far beyond the list contained in the present Arms Export Prohibition Order; but the maintenance of a system of prohibition and licensing in peace-time is not a necessary condition in order to enable such emergency action to be taken. (b) Prevention of Arms and Ammunition from reaching Actual or Potential Enemies. Here, again, if war were imminent, the necessary action could be taken to prevent the export of war material to particular destinations. In other times no useful purpose would be served by preventing the sale of war material to a potential enemy, as a country with money to spend on munitions will get its supplies elsewhere if not from us. Moreover, it has been pointed out that there are, in fact, certain advantages in supplying munitions to foreign countries who are possible enemies, because in the event of war or emergency it is possible to cut off supplies, not only of the munitions themselves, but also of spare parts and ammunition for those already supplied. (c) Imposition of Embargoes in pursuance of International Obligations. An instance in the past was the agreement entered into by the representatives of the Powers in Peking in 1919 known as the China Arms Embargo Agreement, under which the parties agreed to restrain their subjects from exporting arms to China. The agreement was strictly observed by this country and the Dominions, and to a certain extent by the United States, but was evaded by other countries, especially France and Italy The only definite obligation of this kind at present in force is that imposed by the Ethiopian Arms Traffic Treaty of 1930, to which France, Italy, Ethiopia and the United Kingdom are parties (see paragraph 12). Under existing legislation obligations under this Treaty cannot be implemented except through a general licensing system. Similar considerations apply to any undertaking which His Majesty’s Government might enter into in agreement with other Governments to put an embargo on the export of arms to countries which are at war. A case in point is the proposed embargo on export to Bolivia and Paraguay which His Majesty’s Government have agreed to impose if certain other specified countries (21 in all) will take similar action. (d) Imposition of Embargoes not in pursuance of International Obligations. The most recent example is the embargo imposed by His Majesty’s Govern ment this year upon the export of arms to China and Japan. Since the war there has, from time to time, been a similar embargo on the export of war material to Russia. The effect of action of this kind upon the ability of armament manufacturers to obtain foreign orders is discussed in paragraph 30.(e) Prevention of Arms or Ammunition of Secret Design from leaving the Country. We understand that the Service Departments are satisfied that the licensing system is of little value in this connection, and that the desired result can equally well be attained through their close working arrangements with the armament manufacturers. (f) Prevention of Arms from reaching certain Territories in A frica and Asia. (i) Under present arrangements the exports of arms to certain zones in Africa and Asia, which were scheduled for special treatment under the inoperative Geneva Arms Traffic Convention of 1925, are all subject to licence; exports to these destinations constitute an exception to the open general licence issued in respect of shot guns and certain kinds of gunpowder and explosives. Enquiries which we have made from the Departments concerned do not convince \us that the licensing system in this country plays an effective part in the prevention of the traffic. We would point out, firstly, that the measures taken I to prevent uncontrolled traffic in arms in these places must be essentially local in character, and, secondly, that the traffic is international and the licensing system in this country has no significance so far as the arms come from other countries. (ii) Under the Anglo-Afghan Treaty of 1921 and letters exchanged in connection with it the Afghan Government is under an obligation to inform the British Minister at Kabul whenever an order for war material is placed abroad for delivery through British ports. Consequently, all applications for a licence to export arms from this country to Afghanistan are referred to the India Office for advice. The arrangements, however, relate onlv to the import of war material through India, and any necessary control of sucli import could presumably be exercised at Indian ports. In any case, the licensing system here can be of no use in the case of any arms ordered from countries other than the United Kingdom. (iii) The Government of India keep a stringent watch on the import of firearms at Indian ports in order to prevent them from passing into the possession of revolutionaries and terrorists. The India Office are disposed to attach some importance to the licensing system in this country as a check upon this traffic. They point out that the traffic originates mainly in certain continental ports, and they are seeking the co-operation of the appropriate foreign Governments in restrictive measures. They hope, therefore, that meantime the present licensing system will not be relaxed. In this connection we would observe that the traffic in which the Government of India are primarily interested is that of the import into India of firearms, such as revolvers, and does not concern our armament manufacturers to any extent. Moreover, prospective smugglers of such weapons do not apply for export licences. (g) Assisting Foreign Governments in regulating Arms Imports. His Majesty’s Government have agreed with certain foreign countries— Spain, Portugal, China and Mexico—that no licences shall be issued for the export of arms to those countries except with the permission of the Government concerned. This may be some convenience to the foreign Governments in question, but it confers no benefit on the United Kingdom, and should presumably not be allowed to impede any relaxation that it may be desired to make in favour of United Kingdom manufacturers. (h) Facilitating Purchase in the United Kingdom of Personal Arms by Persons going Abroad. There is another use, relatively unimportant, to which the system is put. A person who does not possess a firearm certificate, but wishes to purchase firearms in this country to take abroad with him, can do so on obtaining an export licence, the arms being sent direct to the ship. In the absence of a licensing system, provision could be made for the necessary authority in these cases to be given by the police, but the administration, not being centralised, would lack uniformity, and applicants would probably experience difficulty and delay in obtaining the required permission. Consequently some firearms would be bought abroad which are now bought here.y Effects of the Present System upon the Competitive Position of United Kingdom Manufacturers. 27. We are assured that armament firms in this country are severely handicapped in obtaining foreign orders by their inability to clinch a deal immediately, owing to the necessity of obtaining an export licence, and also by the uncertainty arising from the possibility that such licence may subsequently be revoked or may not be renewed at the end of the period of three months for which it is valid (see paragraph 20). 28. The obligation to obtain a licence for the export of individual consign ments must obviously constitute a serious obstacle to manufacturers in dealing with possible orders from foreign customers who insist upon an immediate reply. This consideration must, however, be distinguished from the question of possible delay in dealing with an application for a licence. In this respect we are satisfied that there is no ground for complaint. The administration of any system must necessarily occupy a certain time, but the information before us shows that the time taken in dealing with applications for licences is reduced to a minimum, and it would not seem that in this respect the system imposes an appreciable handicap upon the firms concerned (see paragraph 16). 29. The complaint as to uncertainty, however, is much more serious. As explained in paragraph 19, the licence itself contains a statement that it may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade without reason given, and where it relates to war material, steps are taken to emphasise this possibility by attaching a special notice to each licence at the time of issue (paragraph 20). 30. The feeling of uncertainty attributable to these conditions has recently been increased by the embargo which in February last was placed by His Majesty’s Government, and by no other Government, on exports of war material from the United Kingdom to China and Japan. Armament manufacturers realise that the Government must have complete power to stop at any time the export of arms for reasons of Imperial security, and they would have no legitimate objection to restrictions on export which arose out of an international agreement which was actually in force in the principal arms-producing countries. But they claim to be freed from uncertainties to which their foreign competitors are not subject, and, in particular, the possibility of His Majesty’s Government enforcing prohibitions or withholding licences in pursuance of international aims in regard to which there is no agreement for international action. 31. The effects of this feeling of uncertainty are not confined to armament manufacturers. There is evidence that United Kingdom producers of steel and other raw material for armaments lost orders at the time of the recent embargo by reason of the fear of foreign Governments that His Majesty’s Government might at any time place an embargo on these materials also. VII.— Limitations of Existing Legislation. 32. Before we discuss the measures that might be taken to improve the competitive position of the armament firms, it is desirable to call attention to certain features of existing legislation. As already explained (see paragraph 6), prohibitions relating to the export of arms in peace-time must be general in character; unless hostilities are in existence or imminent, the law does not permit the prohibition of arms exports to particular destinations. Hence, if in fact it is desired to control the export of arms to a particular place, it is necessary to issue a general prohibition accompanied by an open general licence in favour of all destinations except those to which it is desired to prevent export save under specific licence. Accordingly, so long as the law remains in its present form, and this country is bound by the terms of the Ethiopian Treaty, a general prohibition of the export of all arms must be in force, and there can be no question of revoking the Arms Export Prohibition Order of 1931; anv mitigation of the system of specific licensing must be effected by an extension of the present [8664] ^ * cj 0 system of open general licences which, for example, is now applied in the case of unarmed aircraft. 33. It would doubtless be more convenient if the law enabled His Majesty’s Government to prohibit in peace-time, as well as in times of emergency, the export of arms to a particular destination. It is suggested that if at any time amending arms legislation became necessary, this point should be considered. Such an occasion would arise if legislation had to be passed as the result of the present discussions at Geneva relating to the control of arms traffic and manufacture. 34. Meantime, we desire to make certain proposals within the framework of the existing law which, we think, should be of material assistance to armament manufacturers in obtaining foreign orders, while maintaining effective Govern ment control over the export of arms from this country. VIII .—Proposals . 35. The object of the two proposals which we submit is to deal respectively with the two main difficulties arising out of the licensing system with which our armament manufacturers are confronted. As shown in paragraph 27, these are :— (а) The inability of manufacturers to clinch an immediate bargain, and (б) The liability of licences to be revoked or modified at any time. Both proposals follow the lines of arrangements already in existence. Issue of Open Licences to Approved Armament Manufacturers. 36. In making this proposal we have had prominently in mind the present arrangements under which an open general licence is in force in respect of aircraft and aircraft engines (see Appendix C), and the manufacturers concerned are therefore able to export without obtaining specific licences. As already pointed out, this arrangement has worked to the entire satisfaction of the Air Ministry. 37. Our proposal is that open licences should be granted to armament manufacturers, who are approved by the Service Departments as being of national importance, for the export of war material to such foreign Governments (or their accredited agents) as are recognised by His Majesty’s Government. Exceptions would have to be made for Abyssinia, which has a treaty with His Majesty’s Government prohibiting the export of war material except under specific licence, and also for the Governments of Germany, Austria, Hungary and Bulgaria, which have treaty obligations not to import war material. It may be noted that such open licences would not have covered export in any cases of the kinds enumerated in Appendix (F), in which specific licences were refused. 38. We observe that, since this proposal concerns only export to Govern ments or their accredited agents, its adoption would not appear to run counter to the control of exports to the various zones and countries enumerated in paragraph 26 (/). 39. A list of approved firms could readily be prepared by the Service Departments, and we understand that it would be of comparatively small dimensions, consisting of some ten or twelve armament firms and sixteen aircraft manufacturers (in respect of aircraft armament). These manufacturers produce the bulk of the war material exported from this country under Board of Trade licence. 40. These open licences would cover all the kinds of material enumerated in the Arms Export Prohibition Order, except in so far as export is already allowed under existing open general licences. They would be made subject to a special condition that the manufacturers to whom they were issued should supply the Service Departments with information regarding orders for war material for foreign Governments in such manner and at such times as the Departments may require. If a manufacturer failed to comply with this condition, the sanction would be the withdrawal of his open licence.11 ! ^Si 41. While we confidently expect that full information regarding the export of war material will be supplied by approved manufacturers, it is desirable to have some independent record which will detect attempted abuse of the arrange ments by unauthorised firms and provide a check on the transactions of those on the selected list. We recommend therefore that every firm exporting arms under an open licence should be required to furnish to the Customs the following information in respect of each shipment:— (a) A description sufficient for the identification of the articles to which it relates, and their number or weight. (&amp;) The name and address of the exporter. (c) The name of the purchasing Government. (d) The name of the consignee, if not identical with (c). This requirement would be linked to the existing rule that all shipments of war material are subject to “pre-entry' with the Customs, t.e., exporters have to give notice of their intention to export. At present the period that must elapse between “pre-entry' and shipment is not specified. It is suggested that in the cases covered by our proposal a period of seven days should be prescribed in the licence. This would allow time for the Customs to let the Defence Departments have particulars of the intended exportation, and for these Departments to consult the Foreign Office in any case of doubt. Unless the Customs received an intimation that the shipment should be delayed, the arms would be allowed to leave the country in the ordinary course. 42. The above plan, by relieving approved manufacturers from the necessity for applying for a separate licence in respect of each consignment, would enable them to conclude an immediate deal, and foreign customers would know that these manufacturers could accept .foreign orders forthwith without obtaining formal permission from His Majesty’s Government. We understand that the representatives of His Majesty’s Government at the Disarmament Conference have, in accordance with their instructions, urged the adoption of the precise system of licensing at present in force in the United Kingdom. In fact, the Arms Traffic Convention, 1925, has been taken as the basis of discussion at Geneva, and we are advised that the proposal we are submitting would be consistent with its provisions, since the obligation to furnish the particulars specified to the Customs will constitute an export declaration within the meaning of Articles 4 and 14 of that Convention. 43. If our proposal were adopted, the most important cases in which individual licences would still be required would be as follows:— (a) Export by an approved firm to a Government not covered by the open licence, or to a private person or corporation. (b) Export of war material by an arms dealer. (c) Export of rifled arms and ammunition therefor by any person or firm not holding an open licence. (d) Export of firearms as personal luggage by any person not possessing a firearm certificate. Position of Dominions, India and Crown Agents. 44. The India Store Department has written to the Committee urging that the Government of India should be exempted from the requirements of the licensing system in regard to their exports of arms to India. If the above plan for granting open licences is approved, the question of treating Dominion, Indian and Colonial exports on similar lines obviously arises. In fact licences in these cases are now granted automatically, and it is doubtful whether alternative arrangements would be of any advantage. We suggest that if our proposal for open licences is approved, the question of alternative arrangements could be discussed with the High Commissioners and the Crown Agents. Modification of the Condition attached to Licences giving His Majesty's Government fower to revoke or modify Licences. 45. The present position in regard to this condition is described in para graphs 18 to 21, and the uncertainties to which it gives rise are indicated in [8664] c 212 paragraphs 27 to 31. We are of opinion that His Majesty’s Government must retain the power to revoke or modify a licence at any time, but we suggest that the circumstances in which such action would be taken might be made the subject of a statement of Government intention, so far as open licences to manufacturers are concerned. We are advised that the condition empowering the Board of Trade to revoke or modify the licence at any time might, without impairing the complete discretion of the Government, be supplemented by a statement that His Majesty’s Govern ment have no intention of exercising that power except in cases in which manu facturers in receipt of open licences have broken the conditions on which the licences were granted, or in the interests of Imperial security, or in pursuance of an international agreement to which His Majesty’s Government are or may become a party. In cases where this statement is made the present notice used in certain cases (see paragraph 20) would no longer be issued. In making this proposal we have had in mind the provisions of the Washington Act of 1922. under which the Admiralty cannot refuse a licence for the building equipment or despatch of a warship, except for the purpose of observing the obligations imposed by the Treaty. It will be observed that a definite reservation is made in regard to any international obligations undertaken by His Majesty’s Government. The proposed statement would not therefore affect the position of the United Kingdom Delegation at the Disarmament Conference in regard to the Traffic in Arms. IX.— Recommendations. 46. We therefore submit the following recommendations :— (1) That provision be made for the issue to armament manufacturers, who are approved by the Service Departments as being of national importance, of open licences covering the export of all war material to such foreign Governments (or their accredited agents), as are recognised by His Majesty’s Government with the exception of the Governments of Abyssinia, Germany, Austria, Hungary and Bulgaria (paragraph 36). Every such licence should be subject to conditions framed so as to ensure— (a) that the manufacturers to whom the open licences are issued should supply the Service Departments with information regarding orders for war material for foreign Governments, in such manner and at such times as the Departments may require (paragraph 39); and (b) that all material exported under the open licences should be pre entered with the Customs seven days before shipment, and that at time of pre-entry the information specified in paragraph 41 should be furnished to the Customs. (2) That, if recommendation (1) is approved, the High Commissioners for the Dominions and India and the Crown Ag-ents for the Colonies should be consulted on the subsidiary question of modifying the present system in regard to the Dominions, India and the Colonies (paragraph 44). (3) That the condition attached to the issue of every export licence for war material, empowering the Board of Trade to revoke or modify the licence at any time, should, in the case of open licences granted to manufacturers, be qualified by a statement that His Majesty’s Government have no intention of exercising that power except in cases where manufacturers in receipt of open licences have broken the conditions on which the licences were granted, or in the interests of Imperial security, or in pursuance of an international agreement to which His Majesty’s Government are or may become a party (paragraph 45).* Section 8. Section 1. Section 2. Section 17. Restriction on building, &lt;fec., vessels of war. 14 APPENDIX (A). Extracts from Acts of Parliament. Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879. THE following goods may by proclamation or Order in Council be prohibited either to be exported or carried coastwise : Arms, ammunition and gunpowder, military and naval stores, and any articles which Her Majesty shall judge capable of being converted into or made useful in increasing the quantity of military or naval stores, provisions, or any sort of victual which may be used as food for man; and if any goods so prohibited shall be exported or brought to any quay or other place to be shipped for exportation from the United Kingdom or carried coastwise, or be waterborne to be so exported or carried, they shall be forfeited, and the exporter or his agent or the shipper of any such goods shall be liable to the penalty of one hundred pounds. Exportation of Arms Act, 1900. It shall be lawful for Her Majesty by proclamation to prohibit the exportation of all or any of the following articles, namely : Arms, ammunition, military and naval stores, and any article which Her Majesty shall judge capable of being converted into or made useful in increasing the quantity of arms, ammunition, or military or naval stores, to any country or place therein named, whenever Her Majesty shall judge such prohibition to be expedient, in order to prevent such arms, ammunition, military or naval stores being used against Her Majesty’s subjects or forces, or against any forces engaged or which may be engaged in military or naval operations in co-operation with Her Majesty’s forces. This Act shall be read as one with the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, and all the provisions of that Act, so far as they are applicable to the exportation of prohibited goods, shall apply as if they were embodied in this Act, and as if section 1 of this Act were part of section 8 of that Act. Finance Act, 1921. (1) Section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879 (which gives power to prohibit the exportation and carriage coastwise of certain goods), shall extend to weapons and munitions of war of every description and firearms not being weapons of war, and ammunition for such firearms, as it applies to the goods therein mentioned. (2) The said section, as amended by this section, shall extend so as to give power to prohibit the shipment as ship’s stores, whether on vessels proceeding to foreign ports or on coastwise voyages, of any of the goods to which the said section applies, and the provision in the said section relating to a penalty shall have effect accordingly subject to the necessary modifications. Treaties of Washington Act, 1922. 1.—(1) No person shall, without a licence from the Admiralty— (a) within any part of His Majesty’s Dominions to which this Act applies, build any vessel of war, or alter, arm or equip any ship so as to adapt her for use as a vessel of war; or (b) despatch or deliver, or allow to be despatched or delivered, from any place within any part of His Majesty’s Dominions to which this Act applies, any ship which has been so built, altered, armed or equipped as aforesaid, either entirely or partly, within His Majesty’s Dominions. Provided that a licence for any such purpose shall not be refused by the Admiralty unless it appears to the Admiralty necessary to do so for the purpose15 of securing the observance of the obligations imposed by the first-mentioned Treaty,* and where a licence is granted subject to conditions, the conditions shall be such only as may appear necessary to the Admiralty for the purpose aforesaid. (2) An application for a licence under this section shall be accompanied by such designs and particulars as the Admiralty may require. (3) 1 he Admiralty may, by warrant, empower any person to enter any dockyard, shipyard, or other place, and to make inquiries respecting any ship being built, altered, armed, or equipped therein, with a view to ascertaining whether any ship is being built, altered, armed or equipped contrary to this Act, and to search any such ship. (4) If any question arises as to whether a ship is a vessel of war, or whether any alteration, arming or equipment of a ship is such as to adapt her for use as a vessel of war, the question shall be referred to and determined by the Admiralty, whose decision shall be final. APPENDIX (B). History of the Control of Arms Traffic. Legislation. 1. Legislation empowering the prohibition of export of Arms and 1846- Ammunition is traceable as far back as the Tonnages and Poundages Act (12 Charles II, Cap. 4), and these powers are perpetuated in several later Acts, e.g., 1755, 1825, 1833 and 1845. In Section 112 of the last-quoted Act (Customs Act, 1845) there is set out a Table of Prohibitions and Restrictions Outwards, the following list of goods which may be prohibited to be exported by Proclamation or Order in Council:— Arms, Ammunition and Gunpowder. Military Stores, Naval Stores and any Articles (except Copper), which Her Majesty shall judge capable of being converted into or made useful in increasing the Quantity of Military or Naval Stores. Provisions or any Sort of Victual which may be used as Food by Man. The penalty for contravention of an export prohibition was forfeiture of the goods. 2. With the addition of a clause to cover goods “carried coastwise,” this 1853. provision was embodied in section 150 of the Customs Consolidation Act of 1853, which, in turn, was re-enacted without amendment in Section 138 of the Customs Consolidation Act, 1876, and was repeated in Section 8 of the Customs and Inland 1876. Revenue Act, 1879, in similar words with the provision, in addition, of a fine for 1879. contravention of a prohibition, where previously the only penalty had been forfeiture. This last section is still in force. 3. So far, an Order or Proclamation prohibiting the export of arms could only be general, that is to say, any prohibition had to cover export to all destinations. By Section 1 of the Exportation of Arms Act, 1900, however, power was given to prohibit by Proclamation the exportation of arms to any specified country or place “whenever Her Majesty shall judge such prohibition to be expedient in order to prevent such arms, ammunition, military or naval stores being used against Her Majesty’s subjects or forces or against any forces engaged in military or naval operations in co-operation with Her Majesty’s forces.” The new powers were intended primarily to prevent the export of arms and ammuni tion to the Boxer insurgents in China. Immediately after the Act came into force, however, the Boxer rising was suppressed; and apparently no proclamation prohibiting the export of arms to China was actually issued. 4. After the outbreak of the European War the power to make Proclamations prohibiting export was extended by the Customs (Exportation Restriction) Acts, 1914, to cover the export of all articles of any description; and by the Customs * The Washington Treaty for the Limitation of Naval Armament, 1922.16 T (Exportation Restriction) Act, 1915, power was given to secure that any article to which a prohibition applied was delivered to an authorised consignee. These extended powers were valid only in time of war; but they had an important bearing on the development of the export licensing system. 5. The powers to prohibit the export of articles other than arms, ammuni- ^ tion, &amp;c., lapsed after the War; but Section 17 of the Finance Act, 1921, extended Section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, to cover weapons and munitions of war of every description, and also firearms not being weapons of war and ammunition for such firearms. It also gave power to prohibit shipment as ship’s stores. 6. The text of those sections quoted above, which are still in force, is given in Appendix (A). The War Period. 7. Export Prohibition .—Until the outbreak of the European War, although the necessary powers existed, there was apparently no actual prohibition of the exportation of arms from this country. Commencing in 1890, however, a daily return of all arms exported was sent by the Customs to the Admiralty. 8. In 1914, immediately on the outbreak of war, a Proclamation was issued under Section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, prohibiting the exportation of certain articles, including arms and ammunition, to all destina tions. The Proclamation was absolute in its terms, i.e., it made no mention of exports under licence, but a rough and ready export licensing system was devised almost immediately. At the outset applications for licences were submitted to the Customs, who forwarded them to the various Departments interested in the goods. In cases of doubt applications were submitted to the Committee on Trade with the Enemy—a body which had been established at the beginning of the war to deal with questions relating to the law on trading with the enemy. As the list of prohibited articles continued to expand it was found impossible for the Committee to deal with the great amount of work involved, and the War Trade Department was accordingly created by Treasury Minute, dated the 17th February, 1915, in order to control inter alia the issue of export licences. In addition the War Trade Department dealt with questions relating to the Black Lists, to embargoes, to agreements with trading bodies in neutral countries and to trading relations with Allies. 9. The prohibition of the exportation of war material continued without interruption until the end of the war, by which time almost everything which was capable of being of use to the enemy was on the prohibited list. With the cessation of hostilities, however, the export restrictions began to be relaxed, until the time came when only arms, ammunition, &amp;c., remained subject to licence on exportation. The War Trade Department was wound up, in common with other war-time Departments, and the Imports and Exports Licensing Section became a unit of the Board of Trade. 10. International Control .—As the Great War progressed the prospect of an immense surplus of arms all over the world when peace came led to the appointment in 1917 of a Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence with Lord Islington as Chairman “ to consider the general question of the traffic in arms after the war with special reference to native races.” The Sub- Committee recommended that immediatly after the War an effort should be made to obtain international agreement (1) to control the arms traffic, with particular reference to special zones in Asia and Africa, in which it was regarded as specially desirable to prevent arms from reaching the native races; (2) to prohibit the export of automatic pistols and ammunition of every kind to any destination except under Government licence. The Committee on the Control of Firearms, which reported in 1918 to the Minister of Reconstruction, concurred in both these recommendations, and, in regard to the second, went further in recommending a General Export prohibi tion covering all firearms, such prohibition to be modified at discretion by issuing licences freely for sporting guns and parts of firearms to approved destinations.17 Post-War Development. 11. Export Prohibition. —In 1919 the Board of Trade issued an open general licence authorising exportation without specific licence of cartridges, charges, &amp;c., industrial explosives, double-barrelled guns and sporting rifles to certain destinations. 1 his was subsequently modified, at the instance of the Foreign ^ ^ v ^ ew provisions of the Arms Traffic Convention of the 10th September, 1919 ; and the revised open general licence excepted consignments to destinations within the prohibited areas specified in that Convention (see paragraph 13 below). 12. On the 24th March, 1921, the residue of the war-time Orders prohibiting the export of war material was replaced by a new Order defining, more closely than was done in the Acts of Parliament, the kinds of material whose export was prohibited, and making, for the first time, specific provision for licences.* The dehnition included fifteen classes of war material, which, although not quite so comprehensive, were substantially the same as classes (i) to (xv) of the list in the existing Order (see Appendix (C)), and by a further Order made on the 13th December, 1921, the prohibition was extended to shipment as ship’s stores. Ihis last Order remained in force until 1931, when the ratification of the Ethiopian Arms Tralhc Treaty, 1930, made it necessary to prohibit the export to Abyssinia of arms, including bayonets, swords and lances, and of aircraft (see paragraph 17 below). As the power to prohibit export to a specified country applied only where there were actual or threatened hostilities, a special Order prohibiting the export to Abyssinia could not be made. A new general Order was, therefore, made on the 19th May, 1931, extending the export prohibition to cover aircraft and bayonets, swords and lances, and at the same time an open general licence was issued permitting the export of those articles to all destinations except Abyssinia. The opportunity was taken to include separately in the prohibition certain classes of war material which had previously been regarded as falling within the classes specified in the 1921 Order {e.g., a tank had been regarded as a gun mounting). The text of the Order, whicn remains in force to-day, is given in Appendix (C). 13. Ships of war and their armament are not covered by the export licensing system administered by the Board of Trade, but the licence of the Admiralty is required for their building and for their despatch, in accordance with the Treaties of Washington Act, 1922. The Arms Traffic Conventions. 14. The 1919 Arms Traffic Convention {Cmd. 414), signed at St.-Germain- en-Laye. Under Article 1 of this Convention, the High Contracting Parties undertook to prohibit the exportation of a short list of “ arms of war,” except undei licence. I nder Article 2, they undertook also to prohibit the export of firearms and ammunition other than arms and munitions of war, to certain specified zones. These included the zones covered by the Brussels Act of 1890 relating to the slave trade. The Convention also provided for the annual publication of certain statistics of licences issued. The export from the United Kingdom of the arms to which the Convention related was already prohibited, so that, if the Convention had been ratified, no further action on this score would have been necessary so far as this country was concerned. The Convention was. in fact, never ratified; but His Majesty’s Plenipotentiaries had signed the Protocol, which reads as follows :— “ At the moment of signing the Convention of even date relating to the trade in arms and ammunition, the undersigned Plenipotentiaries declare in the name of their respective Governments that thev would regard it as contrary to the intention of the High Contracting Parties, and to the spirit of this Convention that, pending the coming into force of the Convention, a Contracting Party should adopt any measure which is contrary to its provisions.” It was in accordance with the obligations which His Majesty’s Government had assumed under this Protocol that export of non-military firearms and ammunition to the areas specified in the Convention was excepted' from the Onen General Licence of 1919. ^ * The Acts of Parliament make no provision for licences; but power to prohibit export clearly includes power to except from the prohibition goods specified in an export licence [8664] D ’15. The 1925 Arms Traffic Convention {Cmd. 3448), signed at Geneva .— This Convention is very much wider in scope than that of 1919 as regards the classes of goods it covers, and in many other respects. The special zones in respect of which exceptional control has to be exercised, are, however, smaller in extent than the prohibited areas defined in the 1919 Convention. The goods to which the 1925 Convention relates are classified into five categories : Category I includes arms, ammunition and implements of war, exclusively designed and intended for land, sea or aerial warfare; Category II, arms and ammunition capable of use for both military and other purposes; Category III, vessels of war and their armaments; Category IV, aircraft and aircraft engines; and Category V, gunpowder and explosives, and arms and ammunition of a definitely non-military nature. 16. The Convention stipulates that the export of articles falling within Categories I and II shall be permitted only under licence issued by the competent authorities of the exporting countries. As regards Category III, the Convention requires each Government to publish quarterly a return giving certain particulars of each vessel of war constructed for, or transferred to, the Government of another State. The Convention places no restriction on the exportation of articles in ( ategories I\ and V, except when the articles are being sent to the special zones, in which case an export licence is required. In addition to the provisions relating to export licences, there are clauses in the Convention under which comprehensive import and export statistics have to be published at stated intervals. The form the statistics should take is indicated in annexes to the Convention itself. 17. This Convention was ratified by His Majesty’s Government in 1930, with the reservation that ratification would not become effective until ratification by the other principal arms-producing States (Austria, Belgium. Czechoslovakia, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Spain, Sweden and U.S.A.) had also become effective in accordance with article 41 of the Convention. Of these States, France, Spain and Sweden have ratified conditionally; the remaining States have not yet ratified. 18. The Ethiopian A rms Traffic Treaty, 1930 (Cmd. 3707).—This Treaty, between the United Kingdom, France, Italy and Ethiopia, which was signed m Paris on the 21st August, 1930, applies the provisions of the 1925 Arms Traffic Convention to Abyssinia. It has been ratified by all four countries, and His Majesty’s Government are, therefore, bound by its provisions so far as the export of arms from this country is concerned. Broadly speaking, the effect of the Treaty is that none of the articles covered by “ The Arms Export Prohibition Order, 1931,” may be exported to Abyssinia except under the authority of specific export licences, and licences are not issued for articles falling within Categories I, II and IV, unless the application is supported by an import permit issued bv the Ethiopian Government. Statistics have to be published by the Governments of the limitrophe territories at stated intervals, showing the imports into and exports from those territories of arms, &amp;c., but no such statistics are required to be published by the Metropolitan countries. APPENDIX (C). Exportation of Arms, &amp;c. Text of Order-in-Council, 1931, and Open General Export Licences At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 19th day of May, 1931. Present: The King’s Most Excellent Majesty in Council. Whereas by Section 8 of “The Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879,” (a) it is provided that the following goods may, by Proclamation or Order in Council, be prohibited either to be exported or carried coastwise: Arms,19 ammunition and gunpowder, military and naval stores, and any articles which IIis Majesty shall judge capable of being converted into or made useful in increasing the quantity of military or naval stores, provisions, or any sort of victual which may be used as food for man: And whereas by Section 17 of the Finance Act, 1921, (b) it is enacted that ^ Section 8 of “ The Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879,” shall extend to ^ weapons and munitions of war of every description and firearms not being weapons of war, and ammunition for such hrearms, as it applies to the goods therein mentioned, and that the said section, as so amended by this section, shall extend so as to give power to prohibit the shipment as ship’s stores, whether on vessels proceeding to foreign ports or on coastwise voyages, of any of the goods to which the said section applies : And whereas by an Order in Council dated the 13th December, 1921, (c) made in pursuance of Section 8 of “ The Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, the exportation from the United Kingdom of certain articles was prohibited : And whereas it is expedient that the said Order in Council should be revoked : And whereas it is expedient to prohibit the exportation or shipment as ship’s stores on vessels proceeding to foreign ports of the articles hereinafter enumerated : Now, therefore, His Majesty is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows :— (1) As from the 1st June, 1931, the following articles shall be, and the same are hereby prohibited to be exported from the United Kingdom, or to be shipped as ship’s stores on vessels proceeding to foreign ports, that is to say :— (i) Cannon and other ordnance and component parts thereof; (ii) Carriages and mountings and accessories for mountings for cannon and other ordnance and component parts thereof, (iii) Cartridges, charges of all kinds, and component parts thereof; (iv) Explosives of every description; (v) Firearms of every description and component parts thereof; (vi) Grenades and component parts thereof; (vii) Machine guns, interrupter gears, mountings for machine guns and component parts thereof; (viii) Projectiles of all kinds (except air-gun pellets) and component parts thereof; (ix) Mines, land or sea, and component parts thereof; (x) Depth charges, apparatus for the discharge of depth charges, and component parts thereof; (xi) Bombs, bombing apparatus, and component parts thereof; (xii) Flame-throwers and component parts thereof; (xiii) Fuses and component parts thereof; (xiv) Torpedoes and component parts thereof: (xv) Torpedo tubes, or other apparatus for discharging torpedoes; (xvi) Fire-control and gun-sighting apparatus and component parts thereof; (xvii) Appliances for use with arms and apparatus exclusively designed and intended for land, sea or aerial warfare; (xviii) Bayonets, swords and lances, and component parts thereof; (xix) Tanks and armoured cars and component parts thereof; (xx) Aircraft assembled or dismantled, and aircraft engines. Provided always, and it is hereby declared, that this Order shall not apply to any exportation or shipment as ship’s stores which shall be expressly permitted by a licence given by the Board of Trade, and in accordance with the conditions (if any) of such licence. (2) The said Order in Council, dated the 13th December, 1921, is hereby revoked. (3) This Order may be cited as “ The Arms Export Prohibition Order, 1931 ” [8664] ‘ D 220 Open General Export Licence, No. G.L. 110. In pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by “ The Arms Export I rohibition Order, 1931, the Board of Trade do hereby authorise and permit the exportation from any port in Great Britain or Northern Ireland to all destina tions other than Abyssinia of the following goods, namely :— Aircraft, assembled or dismantled, and aircraft engines; Bayonets, swords and lances, and component parts thereof, upon the following conditions :— (1) That the Owner or Shipper of the said goods, if so required by the Commissioners of His Majesty s Customs and Excise, shall produce to them, within such time as they may allow, proof to their satisfac tion that the said goods were duly delivered at a destination to which this Licence applies. (2) That this Licence shall be deemed void and of no effect in the event of non-compliance with condition (1) as set out above. (3) That this Licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade without reason given. (4) That nothing in this Licence contained shall affect the powers of the Commissioners of His Majesty s Customs and Excise under any Act relating to the Customs or to the export of prohibited goods. Dated the 1st day of June, 1931. Open General Export Licence, No. G.Ij. 111. In pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by “ The Arms Export i rohibition Order, 1931,” the Board of Trade do hereby authorise and permit the exportation from any port in Great Britain or Northern Ireland to all destina- tions other than the destinations included in the special zones set out in the schedule hereto, of the following goods, namely :— {a) Smooth-bore shot-guns and ammunition for use therewith; ib) The following brands of smokeless gunpowder used in the manufacture of shot-gun cartridges, namely :— Amberite; E.C. No. 3; Empire; Ideal; K.S.G.; Nobel No. 48; Schultze; Shot-gun Neonite; Smokeless Diamond; \c) The following explosives, namely: Amazonite; Amorces; Barwick; Blasting gelatine; Bonbons; Brocalite gelatine; Detonators; Dynamite; Dynobel; Electric detonators; Fireworks; Fog signals; Forcite; Gelatine dynamite; Gelignite; Glycerita; Hertford; L.G. gelatine; Monobel; ?sobel gelatine; Rex powder; Rockite; Sabulite, No. 1; Safety fuses; Samsonite; Stonobel; Super-Cliffite, No. 1; Super-CJiffite, No. 2; Super-Cliffite, No. 3; Super-Rippite; Super-Sabulite; Thames powder; Tonite or cotton powder, No. 1; Viking powder;21 upon the following conditions: — (1) lhat the Owner or Shipper of the said goods, if so required by the Commissioners ot His Majesty’s Customs and Excise, shall produce to them, within such time as they may allow, proof to their satisfac tion that the said goods were duly delivered at a destination to which this Licence applies. (2) lhat this Licence shall be deemed void and of no effect in the event of non-compliance with condition (1) as set out above. (3) 1 hat this Licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade without reason given. (4) I hat nothing in this Licence contained shall affect the powers of the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and Excise under any Act relating to the Customs or to the export of prohibited goods. Dated the 1st day of June, 1931. Schedule to G.L. 111. 1. Land Zone. (а) ihe whole of the Continent of Africa, with the exception of Egypt, Lybia, lunisia, Algeria, the Spanish Possessions in North Africa other than Ifni, and of the Union of bouth Africa, together with the territory under its mandate, and of Southern Rhodesia. 1 his zone also includes the adjacent islands which are situated within 100 nautical miles from the coast thereof, and also Prince’s Island (Principe) in the Bight of Biafra, St. Thomas (San Thome), Annobon and Socotra, but does not include the Spanish islands situated to the north of the parallel of 26° North latitude. (б) The Arabian Peninsula, Gwadar, Syria and Lebanon, Palestine and Transjordan, and Iraq. 2. Maritime Zone. A maritime zone, which includes the Red Sea, the Gulf of Aden, the Persian Gulf and the Gulf of Oman, and is bounded by a line drawn from and following the latitude of Cape Guardafui to the point of intersection with longitude 57° East of Greenwich, and proceeding thence direct to the point at which the eastern frontier of Gwadar meets the sea. Open General Export Licence, No. G.L. 112. In pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by “ The Arms Export Prohibition Order, 1931,” the Board of Trade do hereby authorise and permit the exportation from any port in Great Britain or Northern Ireland to all destina tions by the holder of a valid firearm certificate issued under Section 1 (1) of the Firearms Act, 1920, of the following goods, namely : The firearms and ammuni tion which are authorised by the said firearm certificate to be held in Great Britain or Northern Ireland, upon the following conditions :— (1) That the firearm certificate shall be produced by the holder with the firearms and ammunition to the Customs Authorities at the port of departure at the time of exportation. (2) That this Licence shall be deemed void and of no effect in the event of non-compliance with condition (1) as set out above. (3) That this Licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade without reason given. (4) That nothing in this Licence contained shall affect the powers of the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and Excise under any Act relating to the Customs or to the export of prohibited goods. Dated the 1st day of June, 1931.* 22 Copy. APPENDIX (D). (Crest.) Export Licence. No, In pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by the several Proclamations and Orders prohibiting the Exportation of certain articles from the United Kingdom, the Board of Trade do hereby authorise and permit to export from any port in the United Kingdom within a period of three months from the date of this Licence, to consigned to the following goods, namely, OQ a o • r-4 -M o 00 © U © u a © Ph © +3 &lt;3 © &gt; © •pH r-H © Pi •M O a 00 © O 'C © o a © © 00 O •pH be © Pi © A o3 * © Pi c$ 00 Pi © +3 Pi O ft X e3 +3 Pi © © o d o c3 +3 Pi O ft a •pH © +3 0 O Pi o ft X W be 0 •pH j—H ft a o © a o .p-l d o •i-i 43 o3 d • p-H 4-3 00 © o t&gt;&gt; Pi 43 d d o © © .ft % 0 ' no •&gt;1 © 43 d o3 oo d o © © rd &gt;&gt; 0 o3 upon the following conditions:— (1) That the Owner or Shipper of the said goods, if so required by the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and Excise, shall produce to them, within such time as they may allow, proof to their satisfaction that the said goods were duly delivered at the destination named in this Licence. (2) That this Licence shall be deemed void and of no effect in the event of non-compliance with condition (1) as set out above and as accepted by the applicant in his application for this Licence. (3) That this Licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade wdthout reason given. Dated the day of 19 4 . &gt; l « ? NOTE.—The Board of Customs and Excise require pre-entry (i.e., entry and clearance A?i Assistant Secretary to the before shipment) of all export prohibited Board of Trade. Note —If No unauthorised any alteration is desired in this Licence it must be returned with alteration is permissible. a request for amendment.APPENDIX (F). Cases where Manufacturers have been refused Export Licences. E.L.No. Applicants. Material. Value. Destination. Date Licence Uefused. Reason for Refusal. 78054 B.S.A. Guns, 5.000 ‘303 rifles £ 12,500 Nicaraguan Govern- 20.9.26 Existing Govern- Ltd. ment ment of Nica ragua not re cognised by H.M. Govern- ment. 83564 Nobel’s 17,600 lbs. nitrocellu- 3,500 Bulgarian Govern- 25.1.27 Ex-enemy coun- lose powder for manu facture of rifle ammu- ment try. nition 103046 B.S.A. Guns, 150 ■303 i ifles 1,232 An arms dealer in 11.9.28 Arms not ordered Ltd. 10,000 GlOO cartridges Afghanistan by Afghan Government. 118025 Vickers 12 machine-gun barrels 36 An arms firm in 5.9.29 Ex-enemy coun- Germany try. 127231 Vickers 1 • 455 revolver 4 A private individual 13.5.30 Ex-enemy coun- in Austria try. . 130274 I.C.I. 100,000 lbs. T.N.T. . 5,313 Canton Provincial 12.6.31 Canton in re- Government bellion against Chinese Go- vernment. 154640 I.C.I. 20,000 20 mm. machine- 13,000 State of Sao Paulo, 10.10.32 Revolution in gun cartridges 1,000,000 7 mm. rifle Brazil Sao Paulo. cartridgesIN31A OFFICE, iSHimAU., 3.». i 5 th ...-jJ 1933 3Jf dear Hind, feny thanks for your note of the discussion yesterday. I am sorry to have been so lon^ In replying, but owin^ to u-eetlnfeB with Fowls before he leaves toa&gt;orrow i have not nad a Uioment to do so. I ^ioulu Pither like to amenu the statecient of cy r&amp;mrka as follows:. j.'dii? ik« af»thanlsta,n. * Article VI of the An^lo-Afghan ireaty of hovember 19^1 and Letter No.II appenued to taat ire:-ty lala aown a specific procedure to govern the licport of arms into Afghanistan through the ports of the British jsles and British India, whether tne material in question was purchased from British or from foreign sources. It seemed aoubtfui to the India Office to !»hat extent this arrangement was of very active Interest to the export Licensing sub aommlttee, since It was definitely bused on treaty provisions which could be amended only by consent of ooth parties, the maintenance of wiiich r,ua on general political grounos of great importt^nce to H.L.G. and the . 0 . Hind, M.C., Government/ Ittee of Imperial Defence, all Guruens,Government of India* The maintenance of an export licence aystem #as related to tnie procedure only, in the liret place, bee uae it provided tne necessary ©acninery at tdis end, and, in the secona, because it uffordea a second check on anas exported to an -fghan destination from this country, ihe consignments of arms to Afghanistan from foreign countries, while prior notification to under the procedure iaia do«n in the ireaty, would in all cases be necessary, could, of c )Uree f ke checked only at tne port of entry into India. tdiTfrififl Hie position here was rather different. The effect of the present export licence system was to keep the Departments of H«M*G., including India Office, concerned with the affairs of the ivlddle £hst and the Persian Gulf fully informed in regard oo any shipments of arms to the Trucial Sheikhs or other of the Arab rulers in this area, fchile the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf was at the moment at negligible importance, u &amp;ud m the pu 6 t been a source great trouble and expense to the Government of India cJia , and taere was always the risk tixit it might revive/revive at &amp;&gt;m iater *xsriocl f whan the market on the North «vest Frontier ana in Arabia, both jl Ahich appeared at present to be satur^tea, revivea. ine control aironied by the export licence system man a real one ana cases n-c Dccurrea oi the rolUiKil of licences in xtispect of particular consignments. 3ir Homce haaiiiton Eantionea that the Admiralty representative on the Committee h^a expressed the opinion th^t it al^iit be possible to exorcise uii.active control in this even if the export licence f&amp;otmu were abandoned, by u.e^ns of the daily customs entry, ir. Laithwait© said that the Admiralty Wei's principally concerneu with tiie suppression of tie traffic in ante in the Juif one tl&amp;rt if tney were satisfied that a method least as effective as the present, which would adequately meet the case, could be devised, he thought ihe India Office would be guided ^y toeis. He admitteu tnat the export licence procedure provided no check on consignments of ants purchased in foreign countries and in so far as these were concerned we should have to trust to the vigilance of the Navy (which)(*nich iiuu t however, only lour sloops to p&amp;trol this very large and difficult areu) ^ 0^1 to a strict onlorce^ent of our engagements with the Arab rulers,' ■? ln 11M...S lacSweeney • s remarks, for 'India' read 'Colonial'. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAE IS. JTREATY SERIES No. 19 (1922). ^ TREATY BETWEEN THE BRITISH AND AFGHAN GOVERNMENTS. Signed at Kabul, November 22, 1921. [Ratifications exchanged at Kabul, February 0, 1922.j Presented to Parliament by Command of His Majesty. LONDON: PRINTED &amp; PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE Po be purchased through any Bookseller or directly from H.M. STATIONERY - OFFICE at the following addresses : Imperial House. Kingsway, London. W.C.2, and 2S Abingdon Street, London, S.W. 1 ; 37 Peter Street, Manchester: 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent. Cardiff: or 23 Forth Street, Edinburgh. 1922 Cmd. 1786. Price 3d. net.Treaty between the British and Afghan Governments. Signed ai Kabul, November 22, 1921. (Ratijications exchanged at Kabul, February (}, 1922.) Preamble. The British Government and the Government of Afghanistan with a view to the establishment of neighbourly relations between them have agreed to the Articles written hereunder whereto the undersigned duly authorised to that effect have set their seals :— Article 1. The British Government and the Government of Afghanistan mutually certify and respect each with regard to the other all rights cl internal and external independence. Article 2. The two High Contracting Parties mutually accept the Indo- Afghan Frontier as accepted by the Afghan Government under Article 5 of the treaty concluded at Rawalpindi on the 8th August. 1919, corresponding to the 11th Ziqada, 1887 Hijra, and also the boundary west of the Khyber laid down by the British Commission in the months of August and September 1919, pursuant to the said Article, and shown on the map* attached to this treaty by a black chain line; subject only to the realignment set forth in Schedule T annexed, which has been agreed upon in order to include within the boundaries of Afghanistan the place known as Tor Kham, and the whole bed of the Kabul River between Shilman Khwala Banda and Palosai and which is shown on the said map by a red chain line. The British Government agrees that the Afghan authorities shall be permitted to draw water in reasonable quantities through a pipe which shall be provided by the British Government from Handi Khana for the use of Afghan subjects at Tor Kham, and the Government of Afghanistan agrees that British officers and tribesmen living on the British side of the boundary shall be permitted without let or hindrance to use the aforesaid portion of the Kabul River for purposes of navigation and that all existing rights of irrigation from the aforesaid portion of the river shall be continued to British subjects. * Not reproduced.5^ 3 Article 3. L’lio British Government agrees that a Minister from His Majesty the Amir of Afghanistan shall be received at the Royal C'ourt of London like the Envoys of all other Powers, and to permit the establishment of an Afghan Legation in London, and the Government of Afghanistan likewise agrees to receive in Kabul a Minister from liis Britannic Majesty the Emperor of India and ^permit the establishment of a British Legation at Kabul. Each party shall have the right of appointing a Military Attache to its Legation. Article 4. The Government of Afghanistan agrees to the establishment of British Consulates at Kandahar and Jalalabad, and the British Government agrees to the establishment of an Afghan Consul- General at the headquarters of the Government of India and three Afghan Consulates at Calcutta. Karachi and Bombay. In the event of the Afghan Government desiring at any time to appoint Consular i ffieers in any British territories other than India a separate agree ment shall be drawn up to provide for such appointments if they are approved by the British Government. Article 5. The two High Contracting Parties mutually guarantee the | crsonal safety and honourable treatment each of the representa tives of the other, whether Minister, Consul-General or Consuls, within their own boundaries, and they agree that the said repre sentatives shall be subject in the discharge of their duties to the provisions set forth in the second schedule annexed to this treaty. The British Government further agrees that the Minister, Consul- General and Consuls of Afghanistan shall, within the territorial liniits within which they are permitted to reside or to exercise their functions, notwithstanding the provisions of the said schedule, receive and enjoy any rights or privileges which are or may hereafter be granted to or enjoyed by the Minister, Consul-General or Consuls of any other Government in the countries in which the places of residence of the said Minister, Consul-General and Consuls of Afghanistan are fixed; and the Government of Afghanistan likewise agrees that the Minister and Consuls of Great Britain shall within the territorial limits within which they are permitted to reside or to exercise their functions, notwithstanding the provisions of the said schedule, receive and enjoy any rights or privileges which are or may hereafter be granted to or enjoyed by the Minister or Consuls of any ether Government in the countries in which the places of residence of the said Minister and Consuls of Great Britain are fixed. Article (&gt;. As it is for the benefit of the British Government and the Government of Afghanistan that the Government of Afghanistan shall be strong and prosperous, the British Government agrees 1145 Wt. 1500 12/22 F.O.P [9036]that whatever quantity of material is required for the strength and welfare of Afghanistan, such as all kinds of factory machinery, engines and materials and instruments for telegraph, telephones, Ac., which Afghanistan may be able to buy from Britain or the British dominions or from other countries of the world, shall ordinarily be imported without let or hindrance by Afghanistan into its own territories from the ports of the British Isles and British India. Similarly the Government of Afghanistan agrees that ev^g^ kind of goods, the export of which is not against the internal of the Government of Afghanistan and which may in the judgment of the Government of Afghanistan be in excess of the internal needs and requirements of Afghanistan and is required by the British Government, can be purchased and exported to India with the permission of the Government of Afghanistan. With regard to arms and munitions, the British Government agrees that as long as it is assured that the intentions of the Government of Afghanistan are friendly and that there is no immediate danger to India from such importation in Afghanistan, permission shall be given without let or hindrance for such importation. If, however, the Arms Traffic Convention is hereafter ratified by the Great Powers of the world and comes into force, the right of importation of arms and munitions by the Afghan Government shall be subject to the proviso that the Afghan Government shall first have signed the Arms Traffic Convention, and that such importation shall only be made in accordance with the provisions of that Convention. Should the Arms Traffic Convention not be ratified or lapse, the Government of Afghanistan, subject to the foregoing assurance, can from time to time import into its own territory the arms and munitions mentioned above through the ports of the British Isies and British India. Article 7. No Customs duties shall be levied at British Indian ports on goods imported under the provisions of Article G on behalf of the Government of Afghanistan, for immediate transport ro Afghanistan, provided that a certificate signed by such Afghan authority or representative as may from time to time be determined by the two Governments shall be presented at the time of importa tion to the Chief Customs Officer at the port of import setting forth that the goods in question are the property of the Government o-' Afghanistan and are being sent under its orders to Afghanistan, and showing the description, number and value of the goods in respect of which exemption is claimed; provided, secondly, that the goods are required for the public services of Afghanistan and not for the purposes of any State monopoly or State trade; and provided, thirdly, that the goods are. unless of a clearly dis tinguishable nature, transported through India in sealed packages, which shall not be opened or subdivided before their export from India. And also the British Government agrees to the grant in respect of all trade goods imported into India at British ports for re-export5 to Afghanistan and exported to Afghanistan by routes to be agreed upon between the two Governments of a rebate at the time and place of export of the full amount of Customs duty levied upon such goods, pio\ided that such goods shall be transported through India m sealed packages which shall not be opened or subdivided before their export from India. ^\nd also the British Government declares that it has no present JtW. ition of levying Customs duty on goods or livestock of Afghan origin or manufacture, imported by land or by river into India or exported from Afghanistan to other countries of the world through India and the import of which into India is not prohibited by law. in the event, however, of the British Government deciding in the future to levy Customs duties on goods and livestock imported into India by land or by river from neighbouring States, it will, if necessary, levy such duties on imports from Afghanistan; but in that event it agrees that it will not levy higher duties on imports fi om Afghanistan than those levied on imports from such neigh bouring States. Nothing in this Article shall prevent the levy on imports from Afghanistan of the present Khyber tolls and of octroi in any town of India in which octroi is or may be hereafter levied, provided that there shall be no enhancement over the present rate of the Khyber tolls. Article 8. The British Government agrees to the establishment of trade agents by the Afghan Government at Peshawar, Quetta and 1 arachmar, provided that the personnel and the property of the said agencies shall be subject to the operations of all British laws and orders and to the jurisdiction of British Courts; and that thev shall not be recognised by the British authorities as having a nv official or special privileged position. Article 1). The trade goods coming to (imported to) Afghanistan under the provisions of Article 7 from Europe, &amp;c., can be opened at the railway terminuses at Jamrud, in the Kurram and at Chaman for packmg and arranging to suit the capacity of baggage animals without this being the cause of reimposition of Customs duties; and the carrying out of this will be arranged by the trade representatives mentioned in Article 12. Article 10. The two High Contracting Parties agree to afford facilities of every description for the exchange of postal matter between their two countries, provided that neither shall be authorised to establish Post Offices within the territory of the other. In order to give effect to this Article, a separate Postal Convention shall be concluded for the preparation of which such number of special officers as the Afghan Government may appoint shall meet the officers of the British Government and consult with them. [9036] R 2tsJhtJs | Article 11. The two High Contracting Parties having mutually satisfied themselves each regarding the goodwill of the other, and especially regarding their benevolent intentions towards the tribes residing close to their respective boundaries, hereby undertake each to inform the other in future of any military operations of major importance which may appear necessary for the maintenanc^ol order among the frontier tribes residing within their respe^rAe spheres, before the commencement of such operations. Article 12. The two High Contracting Parties agree that representatives of the Government of Afghanistan and of the British Go\ eminent shall be appointed to discuss the conclusion of a 1 rade Convention and the convention shall in the first place he regarding the measures (necessary) for carrying out the purposes mentioned in Article 9 of this treaty. Secondly. (They) shall arrange regarding commercial matters not now mentioned in this treaty which may appear desirable for the benefit of the two Governments. The trade relations between the two Governments shall continue until the Trade Convention mentioned above comes into force. Article 18. The two High Contracting Parties agree that the first and second schedules attached to this treaty shall have the same binding force as the Articles contained in this treaty. Article 14. The provisions of this treaty shall come into force from the date of its signature, and shall remain in force for three years from that date. In case neither of the High Contracting Parties should have notified twelve months before the expiration of the said three years the intention to terminate it, it shall remain binding until the expiration of one year from the day on which either of the High Contracting Parties shall have denounced it. This treaty shall come into force after the signatures of the Missions of the two Parties and the two ratified copies of this shall be exchanged in Kabul within 2i months after the signatures. (Sd.) MAHMUD TAEZI, Chief of the Delegation of the Afghan Government for the conclusion of the Treaty. Tuesday ,30th A grab 1800 Hijra Shamsi (corresponding to 22nd November, 1921). (Sd.) HENRY R. C. DOBBS, Envoy Extraordinary and Chief of the British Mission to Kabul. This twenty-second day of November one thousand nine hundred and twenty-one.7 Schedule 1. (Keferred to in Article 2.) In the nulla bed running from Landi Khana to I’ainda Kliak Tost, the Afghan frontier has been advanced approximately 700 yards, and the Tor Kkam Ridge, including Shamsa Kandao and Shamsa Kandao Sar, is comprised in Afghan territory. t rther, the Afghan frontier has been advanced between the point ere the present boundary joins the Kabul River and Palosai from the centre of the river to the right bank. Schedule 11. Legations and Consulates. (a.) The Legations, Consulate-General and Consulates of the two High Contracting Parties shall at no time be used as places of refuge for political or ordinary offenders or as places of assembly for the furtherance of seditious or criminal movements or as magazines of arms. (6.) The Minister of His Britannic Majesty at the Court of Kabul shall, together with his family, Secretaries, Assistants, Attaches and any of his menial or domestic servants or his couriers who are British subjects, be exempt from the civil jurisdiction of the Afghan Government, provided that he shall furnish from time to time to the Afghan Government a list of persons in respect of whom such exemption is claimed, and, under a like proviso, the Minister of the Amir to the Royal Court of London to which all the Ambassadors of States are accredited shall, together with his family, Secretaries, Assistants, Attaches and any of his menial or domestic servants or his couriers who are Afghan subjects, be exempt from the civil jurisdiction of Great Britain. If an offence or crime is committed by an Afghan subject against the British Minister or the persons above mentioned who are attached to the British Legation, the case shall be tried according to the local law by the Courts of Afghanistan within whose jurisdiction the offence is committed, and the same procedure shall be observed vice versa with regard to offences committed in England by British subjects against the Afghan Minister or other persons above mentioned attached to the Afghan Legation. (c.) (i.) A Consul-General, Consuls and members of their staffs and households, who are subjects of the State in which they are employed, shall remain subject in all respects to the jurisdiction, laws and regulations of such State. (ii.) A Consul-General, Consuls and members of their staffs and households, other than subjects of the State in which they are employed, shall be subject to the jurisdiction of the Courts of such State, in respect of any criminal offence committed against the Government or subjects of such State, provided that no Consul- General, Consul or member of their staff or Household shall sufferrr any punishinent other than fine; provided also that both Govern ments retain always the right to demand recall from their dominions of any Consul-General, Consul or member of their staff or household. (hi.) A Consul-General, Consuls and members of their staffs and households, other than subjects of the State in which they are employed, shall be subject to the jurisdiction of the Courts of the said State in respect of any civil cause of action arising in the territory of the said State, provided that they shall enjoy customary facilities for the performance of their duties. (iv.) The Consul-General of Afghanistan and Consuls shall have a right to defend the interests of themselves or any members of their staffs and households who are subjects of their own Govern ments in any Court through pleaders or by the presence of one of the consulate officials, with due regard to local procedure and laws. (&lt;/.) The Ministers, Consul-General and Consuls of the two High Contracting Parties and the members of their staffs and house holds shall not take any steps or commit any acts injurious to the interests of the Government of the country to which they are accredited. (e.) The Ministers, Consul-General and Consuls of the two Governments in either country shall be permitted to purchase or hire on behalf of their Governments residences for themselves and their staff and servants, or sites sufficient and suitable for the erection of such residence and grounds of a convenient size attached, and the respective Governments shall give all possible assistance towards such purchase or hire: provided that the Government of the country to which the Ministers or Consuls are accredited shall, in the event of an Embassy or Consulate being permanently withdrawn, have the right to acquire such residences or lands at a price to be mutually agreed on; and provided that the site purchased or hired shall not exceed ‘20 jaribs in area. .Vote.—Each jarib = 60 x 60 yards, English = 8,600 square yards. (/.) The Ministers, Consul-General and Consuls of the two Governments shall not acquire any immovable property in the country to which they are accredited without the permission of the Government of the said country. (&lt;/.) Neither of the two High Contracting Parties shall found a mosque, church or temple for the use of the public inside any of its Legations or Consulates, nor shall the Ministers. Consul-General or Consuls of either Government or their Secretaries or members of their staffs and households engage in any political agitation or movement within the country to which they are accredited or in which they are residing. (//.) The Ministers. Consul-General and Consuls of the two High Contracting Parties shall not grant naturalisation or passports or certificates of nationality or other documents of identity to the subjects of the country in which they are employed in such capacity. (i.) The Ministers of the two High Contracting Parties, besides9 their own wives and children, may have with them not more than thirty-five persons, and a Consul-General and Consuls, besides their own wives and children, not more than twenty persons. If it becomes necessary to employ in addition subjects of the Govern ment of the country to which they are accredited. Ministers can employ not more than ten persons and Consul-General and Consuls not more than five persons. (j.) The Ministers, Consul-General and Consuls of the two High Contracting Parties shall be at liberty to communicate freely with their own Governim nt and with other official representatives of their Government in other countries by post, by telegraph and by wireless telegraphy in cypher or en cAair, and to receive and despatch sealed bags by courier or post, subject to a limitation in the case of Ministers of fi lb. per week, and in the case of a Consul- General and Consuls of 1 lb. per week, which shall be exempt from postal charges and examination, and the safe transmission of which shall, in the case of bags sent by post, be guaranteed by the Postal Departments of the two Governments. (k.) Each of the two Governments shall exempt from the payment of Customs or other duties all articles imported within its boundaries in reasonable quantities for the personal use of the Minister of the other Government or of his family, provided that a certificate is furnished by the Minister at the time of importation that the articles are intended for such personal use. Appendix. T. —Letter from British Representative to Sardar-i-Ala, the Afyhan Foreign Minister. f After compliments.) With reference to the provisions contained in Article f&gt; of the treaty concluded between the Government of Afghanistan and the British Government regarding the importation of arms and munitions into Afghanistan through India, I have the honour to inform and assure you that, although the British Government has in that article reserved to itself the right exercised by every nation to stop the transportation to a neighbouring country of arms and munitions, in the event of its not being assured of the friendly intentions of that country, the British Government has no desire to make trifling inci dents an excuse for the stoppage of such arms and munitions. It would only be in the event of the Government of Afghanistan showing plainly by its attitude that it had determined on an unfriendly and provocative course of policy towards Great Britain contrary to the neighbourly treaty above mentioned that the latter State would exercise the right of stoppage. There is every ground for hope- that such a contingency will never arise, in view of the friendly relations which are expected to spring from the treaty which has now been concluded. (Usual ending.)II.— Letter, No. 112, from Sardar-i-Ala, the Afghan Foreign Minister, to the Britisii Representative at Kabul. (After compliments.) Regarding the purchase of arms and munitions which the Govern ment of Afghanistan buys for the protection of its rights and welfare, from the Governments of the world (and) imports to its own territory from the ports of Great Britain and British India, in accordance with Article 6 of the treaty between the two great Governments, I, in or^ to show the sincere friendship which my Government has with your Government, promise that Afghanistan shall, from time to time before the importation of the arms and munitions at British ports, furnish detailed list of those to the British Minister accredited to the Court of my sacred and great Government, so that the British Govern ment having known and acquainted itself with the list and the number of imported articles should, in accordance with Article 6 of the treaty between the two Governments, afford the necessary facilities.' (Usual ending.) Dated, 291 h A grab A .II. 1800. IU.—Letter, No. Ill, from Sardar-i-Ala, the Afghan Foreign Minister, to the British Representative at Kabul. (After compliments.) As in Article 7 of the treaty (between) the two great Governments of Britain and Afghanistan, your Government lias with great sincerity granted a discriminating exemption from Customs duties on the goods required by my Government and on the trade goods transported to Afghanistan through the ports of Great Britain and British India and has not imposed Customs on goods produced and manufactured in Afghanistan, 1 therefore also, in consideration of the friendship (between) the two Governments, write that my Government will not give the opportunity of establishing a Consul- General or Consul or representatives of the Russian Government at the positions and territories of Jalalabad, Ghazni and Kandahar, which are contiguous to the frontiers of India. If the Consulates or representatives of the Government of Russia are allowed in the parts mentioned, the Government of Afghanistan shall not have the above- mentioned right of exemption. Of course, the temporary association of the Russian Minister with His Majesty’s move to Jalalabad in winter will be an exception. (Usual ending.) Dated, 80/h A grab. A ll. 1800. IV .—L etter from British Representative to Sardar-i-Ala, the Afghan Foreign Minister. (After compliments.) As the conditions of the frontier tribes of the two Governments are of interest to the Government of Afghanistan, I inform you that the British Government entertains feelings of goodwill towards all the frontier tribes and has every intention of treating them generously, provided they abstain from outrages against the inhabit ants of India. I hope that this letter will cause you satisfaction. (Usual ending.)You should see these papers about the Export Licences Sub Comnittee of the C.I.D. Hie question generally is, I unaerstana, under consiuerution and no date has yet been fixed for the next meeting of the Committee. You will remember that it was proposed that representatives of inaiviaual aepartments interestea should aiscuss the natter personally with Sir Horace Hamilton, but this also has been put off. 7/e shall no doubt hear more of the question in the near future.&gt;%/ i . ,2296/33. INDIA OmCE, iill ilAi-L, 3. , 1. 21 st (ff/U 1933. fcy a#ar Hind, hta# tu&amp;nk&amp; lor your letter *X the i±Ui April enclosing Uie minute# oX the Xirst ana draft minutes of the secona meeting of the apart Licences ^uh»OosKlttee« L* as I unaerstsna the position, the Con&amp;ittee in the first place would he glud if possible to do anything to help British nationals to get a larger share in intern-tionai eras orders by some relaxation of existing export restrictions, if this can be done consistently with our international engagements ana with our special responsibilities in certain are^s, ieconaly, the existence of an export licence system Men a# is at present in force might on occasion give ri&amp;e to poiillcui aifilenities for the reasons set out In Howard-Jttdth # s remarxs on page 4 of the minutes of the first meeting. fs jor ina, k,c. 9 Oosmlttae a Imperial Defence, ^hitohiili Gardeiis, # • JL.4. a» rdfcurtu ftrait* aca tne rarai&amp;H OaUT, It is toquhlly ot isiportaaes to us to exerciss so&amp;e itiriy eirsctivs cnock over srupaaots of sms. irse prefect «ystsfc’. Dorics very satisfactorily. 1 ao not think that we ahouia ht ve any objection to a moo ificution in proceaur* if tu&amp;t is all that is involveu. But any biouif icutiou of substance souia, i think, be unsatisfactory frou our point of vies and that of the Qovero&amp;ant of India, whoB as anoulo probably wish to consult if any such change was conte&amp;piateu. 5. As re^firde in enai security in India itself, the abolition or substantial aodifleation of the export licencing ay b tea. in this country as rsgaras ssbII ams would in our opinion bs a retrograde ana dangerous step, se are not sued concerned in this connection with uhlpiusntis of anas in bulk, but we are deeply concerned with the prevention of snuggling of revolvers etc. Into India, for use by terrorists and revolutionaries, a traffic which in spits of constant vigll*&lt;nce Is still carried on sporadically ey iascurs ana sailors in shipsfrost buropoMA ports* At pre»«at tbs traffic orieia tea fe-iniy in certain continental parts, «4»u various proposals lor intsaeifylug Mitsurec to aeal sitb it, incluains s proposal to sseic tbe cooperation of the appropriate foreign govermenta in restrictive taeasuree, are at present under consideration. bolitim of our own export control ays tea, would not only tend to encourage illicit export frost, tnis country but soul* preausiaPly iut&gt;km it ver^ difficult to seek use cooperation of foreign autnorltles in tlgtitening up tneir systems of control* 6. »e asstHEe tnnt the oign sosKiesioner*s office will already bave coaaunic&amp;ted direct witt, you on tne points that are of interest to tae&amp;, • 2 note tftfct iihniels bus been in correspondence eltn your Obairoan 7. I nope tbe above sill sMce our posiUon clear ts inixtk on the absle, however, that it night be well if ee sere represen ed at tne next ncating, and, if you agree, Ciauaon end 1 sill utteoa it. 6 /Draft Paper. p.z. l 2295 ’ poi in cal Department. I w O J vi DRAFT LETTER . fejor N.G. Hind, M.C., Committee oT Imperial Dp-fpin p p 2-, 'ifl/hitehull Gttrciens, S.W. 1. S'* t T2f- i r, 'L- Mi My dear Hind, Many thanks for your letter of the 12th April enclosing the minutes of the first ana araft minutes of the secona meeting of the Export Licences Sub-Committee. 2. As I understand the position^the Committee in the first place would he glad if possible to do anything to help British nationals to get semeT share in international arms orders cnnsequent oib some relaxation of A existing export restrictions^this can he done consistently with^our international engagements and with our special responsibilities in certain areas. Secondly, the existence of an export licence system I such as is at present in force might on occasion give rise to political difficulties lor the reasons set out in Howard-Smith’s remarks on page 4 of the minutes of the first meeting. 3. Save as regards India itself, with which I deal helow r , we are concerned principally with two areas - Afghanistan and the Persian Gulf. (I assume that the Colonial Office will deal with the position of Aden). As regards Afghanistan there are Treaty 1401 5000 11.32 provisions/provisions (Article 6 and Letter II attached to the Anglo-Afghan Treaty of 2nd November 1921 of which I attach a copy) which give us the right (apart from any right which we may be in a position to exercise in the ordinary way) to exercise a definite control over the import of arms into that country through British or Indian ports. I am not sure that these provisions^actually wme-witj»in the ^ aeope -e-f tho poiftto which you are at present considering^ for W no queETtiarr mogi’ify^ t)he., Tronty tina in un.y rasa, as you will see,'the restrictions concerned['apply to arms purchased from any government and not merely from British sources. But it /mo may be well to put the piitut on record, r t* u. a=t^ u_ ^ ^ ^ 4. as regards Persia and the Persian Gulf, it is equally of V&amp;SQ&amp; importance to us to exercise some fairly effective check over shipments of arms. The present system works very satisfactorily. I do not think that w should have any objection to a modification ih procedure if that is all that is involved. But any modification of substance would, I think, be unsatisfactory from our point of view ana that of the Government of India } whom we should probably wish to consult if any such change was contemplated. wV*- CU 4. Im^r^ x (t ^ ^ dJts.: Ljil : ^ fa.12th April, 1933 /V My dear Laithwaite, I understand that you deal with the question^ of the Arms Traffic. I am sending you copies of the Minutes of the first meeting and draft minutes of the second meeting of the oub-Committee which is considering the present system of export licences. You will note on page 10 of the draft minutes of the second meeting that Sir Horace Hamilton, Chairman, has suggested the Colonial Office and India Office should be asked if they wish to raise any points. If you think that your Department is interested on this question, could you either let me have a note or, if you prefer it, would you attend our next meeting which will probably be on Monday, 24th April. Yours sincerely, a/ N t&gt; J. G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office(THIS DOCUMENT I&amp; THE PROPERTY Or HIS BRITA : iNU 8 GO^/ERITMiJNT ^*, SECRET. PoS.CyE.A.) 1 st Mtg. (FINAL COPY) . COPY NO. JO COMMITTEE OF IMPERI/Hi DEFENCE, PRINCIPAL SUPPLY OFFICERS COMMIT TEE SUB-COM] TITTLE ON SYSTEM OF LICE NSING EXPORTS OF ARMS AND AIETUNITION. MINUTES of the First Meeting 3 held at Whitehall Gardens s S. W. 1 • 5 , on Wednesday ? April 5th ^ 1955 j, at 3 p. m« P P E S E N T:- Sir Horace Hamilton&lt;&gt; K.C.B* ^ Permanent Secretary 9 Board of Trade. (Chairman). Mr. J.C.MacIver* Principal 5 Home Office. Mr. W. St.D. Jenkins 9 C.B. C.B.E. ? Director of Contracts 3 Admiralty. The Hon. C.C.Farrer s O.B.E. 5 Assistant Director 5 Department of Overseas Trade. Mr. C. Kov/ard Smith* C.M.G. «&gt; Counsellor* Foreign Office. Colonel P.J.Mackesy* D.S.O. * M.C. * Directorate of Military Operations and Intelligence* War Office. Mr. C.J.Galpin, D.S.O. * Principal* Air Ministry. THE FOLLOUING '.'vE RE /lLSQ PRESENT Mr. F. Starton* Board of Trade. Mr. A.S.Hiskin* principal, Board of Trade .......... ) Joint Secretaries . ^ x ^ , ( to the Major N.G.Hind* M.C. * Assistant secretary* ) Committee of Imperial Defence ) Siib-Committee.1. THE COMMITTEE had before them the following papers: Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 1 - Terms of Reference and Composition. Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A. ) E - Note by Joint Secretaries covering a Report by the Sub-Committee on Industrial Intelligence in Foreign Countries. Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 3 - Memorandum by the Board of Trade outlining the history of the export licensing system. Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 4 - Memorandum by the Board of Trade on the administra tion of the Export Licensing System. THE CHAIRMAN, in opening the meeting, outlined the previous discussions by the Defence Organisations v/hich had led to the institution of this Sub-Committee. These were given in the second paper under discussion (Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 2) which was the basis of a Report on the situation of the Armaments Industry now under consideration by the Committee of Imperial Defence. The main feature of this Report was the fact that our armaments industry cannot be expected to be in a stable and satisfactory condition without a steady supply of foreign orders. It also showed that this country had failed to compete in this respect with foreign Powers, and attributed certain reasons for the falling off of foreign orders. The Sub-Committee had accordingly been set up to report v/hat modifications were possible in the existing export licensing regulations, having regard to the interests of the Fighting Services and the competitive position of United Kingdom firms in obtaining foreign orders. Information had been prepared by the Board of Trade on the subject of export licences, v/hich was circulated as Papers Nos. P.S.O.(E.A.) 3, which gave the history of these Regulations, and P.b.O.(E.A.) 4,Preliminary O bservations . Paper No. P.S.Oc ( 3. A. ) 2 - Report by Sub committee on Indust rial Intelligence in Foreign Countries . which described the administration of the system. He azgg^sted that these papers should form a basis for discussion end that it would be useful if some information on the Regulations in force* in foreign countries could be produced. He then invited observations of a generalmture from members s prior to detailed discussion,, MR. HOWARD SMITH stated that the United Kingdom Delegation at the Disarmament Conference had received definite instructions based on a Cabinet decision of February 8 th ? to insist on the inclusion in the Disarmament Convention of a system of export licences which could be really effective* such as is already in force in the United Kingdom. The United Kingdom Delegation had already proposed this and it would thus be very difficult to rescind the existing regulations or to make any appreciable change in their form* unless we completely changed our policy at Geneva which had been adopted because the Service Departments objected to licences for manufacture and considered that the only effective way to control arms traffic was by our system of export licences® THD CHAIRMAN pointed out that the Sub-Committee had been asked to suggest modifications of the present Regulations* and that a modification of the system might not be inconsistent with tho instructions given to the United Kingdom Delegation at Geneva© THE SUB-COMMITTEE then proceeded to discuss the document mentioned in the margin® THE CHAIRMAN first referred to paragraph 4* where it was pointed out that u thare is no doubt that the existence of an effective control over the expert of arms and the fear that an embargo on export may be placed by His Majesty*s Government at a time when they are most required has led foreign Governments to place their orders elsewhere”« He also drew attention to the statements given on page 11 of this paper outlining the reasons for the decline of foreign orders. 2 6COLONEL MACKESY said that the present system of export licensing was of little value to the Defence Departments as a means of preventing articles of a secret pattern from leaving the country. It was a point cf very miner importance compared with the damage done to our armaments trade owing to lack of foreign orders. MR. JENKINS said that the Admiralty took a similar view. They had their own system of preventing secret information from leaving the country, based on the co-operation of contracting firms. THE CHAIRMAN asked whether the Services had similar powers of control over the arms dealers as opposed to the manufacturers. MR, JENKINS stated that dealers traffic usually only in second-hand arms and surplus stocks. In the event of their desiring to export new arms these would have to he purchased through a manufacturer, v/ho would pass on the information to the Defence Departments. MR. PARRER said that whenever a case of a proposal to export arms came to the notice of the Department of Overseas Trade the «ar Office (M.I.l.b.) v/as alv/ays con sulted. They usually obtained information either from the purchaser or direct from the salesman, and occasionally from secret sources, as to the destination of any consign ment. Difficulties arose when a false destination was givei MR. GALPIN said that the Air Ministry had their own system and arrangements with manufacturers to prevent secret inventions from going out of the country. They, however, thought that the present system of export licensing was useful in preventing the shipment of armsto undesirable quarters. Le quoted the recent canceU.a'tlor^ of licences for the export of bombs to Persia. MR. MacIVER said that the Home Office were concerned rather in the internal traffic and sale of arms, i.e. , from the point of view of the Firearms Act, but all cases of export were referred to the Home Office, who sometimes had information from secret police sources which had some bearing on the application for licences. MR. JENKINS explained that the present system had grown up as a result of the war, and in order to deal with the large accumulation of surplus munitions in the country. A Report on the disposal of surplus war stocks, which had been issued in 1917, had corns to his notice. The powers of prohibition of the exportation of arms which were intended to conserve the re sources of the country and to prevent arms reaching an actual or potential enemy in war time had been utilised to control the traffic in arms to undesirable destinations in peace time. (This Report is circulated to the Committee as Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 5). MR. HOWARD SMITH said that one great political objection to the present system is that, if at any time there is a demand for an embargo on the export of arms to any country, the existence of our system which enables us to impose an immediate embargo without any fresh legislation makes it very difficult for us to refuse, and practically forces us to take the lead in such matters when we have no desire to do so. COLONEL MACKESY pointed out that even if other countries had power to control exports of arms, it was quite possible that they would not exercise it. He instanced the case of the embargo on arms to China in 1919-29, which was openly evaded by most other countries. MR. STURTON said that the manufacturers in this country could have little grounds to complain of the administration of the licensing system. Licences were granted expeditiously and were seldom refused, to delay in the The loss of orders could not well be attributed issue of licences. -4-MR. PAPuRiiR said that the fact that the power to cancel licences exists, and can 'be enforced at a moment’s notice, was what mainly deters foreign 'buyers. THE CHAIRMAN suggested that foreign countries might have some system of open licences which they grant to recog nised armament firms, while keeping a tight hold over dealers and other dubious firms. THE CHAIRMAN explained that our present powers to Paper No. P.S.C. (E. A, ) 3 - Memorandum 'by Trade° outlining CCntro1 the ex P° rts of arms were derived from Section 8 of Export^Licens 6 Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, as amended and System. extended by Section 1 of the Prohibition cf Export of Arms Act, 1900, and Section 17 of the Finance Act, 1921. In addition, power to control the export of vessels of war and their armament is exercised by the Admiralty under the Treaties of Washington Act, 1922. He observed that the power to prohibit export to specified countries, which was given by the Act of 1900, was limited to cases where hostilities were in existence or threatened, so that, speaking broadly, any export prohibition made in time of peace must be of general application. MR. HOWARD SMITH pointed out that it is impossible to interfere with cargoes of arms v/hich pass through British Ports in transit. MR. JENKINS stated that the Customs authorities no longer submitted to the Admiralty and War Office daily lists of arms exported. MR* STURTON said this practice had now become unnecessary, as all war material licences are now forwarded by the Customs to the Board of Trade after each shipment, duly endorsed with particulars of the arms shipped. MR. GALPIN stated that the Air Ministry received such reports and these include aircraft which are not subject to the rest of the licensing procedure. -5- 1THE CHAIRI.iAH said that should further information on this point he required later 9 representatives of the Departments of Customs and Excise should he callod in 0 He asked whether the Service Departments attached much importance to knowing what arms left the country* MR. GALPIN said that the Air Ministry definitely need this information hy whatever means it is obtained. COLONEL 1IACKESY said that the 'Jar Office would like this information. They thought 5 however s that it could well he obtained direct from firms. As such dealers as there are in this country buy Government surplus stocks ? the War Office would he acquainted with such transactions* When, however, such dealers purchased stocks in Belgium or another foreign country, we have no means of control over them whatever regulations may exist* THE CHAIRMAN noted that the Ethiopian Arms Treaty 1950, to which France had subscribed, necessitated some form of export licences. COLONEL MA0IC3SY produced a copy of the law passed by the French to implement their obligations under that Treaty* MR. STURTON remarked that there were certain countries, such as China, Spain and Portugal, who required the British exporter of arms to obtain permission from their Legation in London prior to shipment. As regards shipment of arms to Afghanistan, there is a special Treaty, under which it is ^ £C» necessary to obtain permission from H«Mo Minister at Kabul* AAa-' V*~ &gt;2&gt; lAzw'-I'V'v'l 'VVV 'i THE CHAIRMAN then asked whether members of the Committee thought it desirable to examine witnesses 6from the trade. prima facie it was inadvisable to go outside Government Departments; should the attendance of any representatives of armament firms he required 9 Ministerial consent to call them would he necessary* It was agreed that 9 unless any special point comes up* it would he undesirable to call civil witnesses. Paper No. P.S.O. (E.A.)4 - Memorandum by the Board of Trade on administration of export licensing system. THE CHAIRMAN said that the first point which struck him about this paper was that an export licence was only valid for three months. asked to what extent this limitation militated against the interest of armament firms* if at all. MR. STURTON stated that very few applications for 'firm licences'' had been received. The issue of such licences had not been discouraged by the Board of Trade. The ordinary licences, i.e. for three months, were renewable, and cases had occurred of their being extended as long as three years. THE CHAIRMAN said that the notice which is attached to every licence form, as referred to in Para. 2 of the Paper, might be expected to frighten firms. He understood that it was attached as a precautionary measure. He asked whether the wording of the first sub- paragraph of the licence form had any special significance; this was to the effect M that the owner or shipper of the said goods, if so required by the Commissioners of H.M. Customs and Excise, shall produce to them, within such time as they may allow, proof to their satisfaction that the said goods were duly delivered 7.8 . p.t the destination named in this licence'. MR. STURTON stated that within his experience proof of delivery at the destination named had never been required. But the requirement was occasionally useful in the prevention of smuggling of arms from this country to undesirable destinations* such as South America* Central America* and Belgium, which is used by arms dealers as an entrepot. The general principle followed by the Board of Trade was that no licence was granted to export a large consignment of arms to any individual, but only to Governments. In view of the existence of a Government licensing system, any consignment of arms to revolutionaries or other irregular persons might have grave international complications. MR. HOWARD SMITH remarked that the issue of an export licence entailed a certain amount of Government responsibility that shipments are only made to authoritative individuals. COLONEL MACKESY agreed, and stated that the existence of such a licensing system might, should the arms be put to wrong purposes* lead to incidents with toreign powers such as the 'Alabama' cas©. THE CHAIRMAN realised the danger involved* especially if any discrimination is made to foreign countries. MR. STURTON stated that the Board of Trade were often approached by members of mercantile firms with a view to the issue of a licence to ship arms to undisclosed consignees. The Board of Trade had then produced the regulations, and pointed out - (a) that applications could only be maintaineo. from registered firearms dealers; and (b) the penalties attaching to non-delivery to the consignee named in the licence.HR. JBl'iKIJSS said that a further important factor which caused foreign orders to be placed elsewhere was the fear that the purchaser would be unable to obtain spare parts and replacements. PJa, FiduiiiK suggested that the gun running business and the traffic in surplus arms ought to be kept distinct from the traffic in major armaments: as they formed an insignificant proportion of the value of the armaments export trade. THE CHAIiU'udl then referred to Note (3) on the licence form to the effect that 'this licence may be modified or revoked at any time by the Board of Trade without reason being given'. hh. BTURTON said that this power had only been exercised once, when in 1924 a licence to export a consignment of anus to Russia was revoked. COLOR EL ish'XKEoY said that though there might be a few cases where this power was useful, he could not imagine anything that would do more to frighten away a foreign buyer. P.i. EaRRER suggested that this sentence should be omitted from tne export licence form and a tacit understanding arrived at with reputable firms, that as long as they play the game, they are unlikely to be interfered with. lie considered that armaments firms ar.d dealers can usually be relied upon to give full information, provided they are taken into confidence. l,lR. JENKINSotated that the Admiralty could fully rely on the co-operation of those firms with which they were concerned.TflE CHAIRMAN said that this suggestion indicated a system of open licences to certain responsible firms. He observed that most of the work of the Licensing Department of the Board of Trade was concerned in applications for individual weapons, which was no great concern of the Committee. He understood that the applications from armament firms formed only some 5% of the quantity dealt with, but more than 90$ of the value. It was such applications that the Committee were primarily concerned with. CONCLUSION. The Committee agreed to adjourn the discussion to the next meeting, to be held at 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l, at 3 p.m. on Monday, April 10th. 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l, 6 th April, 1933. 10r s CTHIS DOCUIvENT IS THE PT'OPKRTY OE HIS BRIl'ANNIG MAJESTY^ SQVERmiEN_Tl SECRET. P. S. 0. (E. A. ) /2nd Mtg. C0PY N0 * # COIvgvlITTEE OF B1PERIAL DEPENCE. PRINCIPAL SUPPLY OFFICERS COMMITTEE. SUB-COMMITTEE ON SYSTEM OP LICENSING EXPORTS OF ARMS AND AMMUNITION. DRAPT MINUTES of Second Meeting, held at S ' Gardens s S.W.l*, on April 10th, 1933, at , Whitehall 3.0 p.m. P RESENT; - Sir Horace Hamilton, K.C.B. , Permanent Secretary , Board ol Trade. (Chairman;* Mr. J.C.MacIver, principal, Home Office. Mr. W. St.D. Jenkins, C.B. , C.B.E., Director of Contracts, Admiralty. The Hon. C.C.Farrer, O.B.E. , Assistant Director, Department of Overseas Trade. Mr. C. Howard Smith, C.M.CJ. , Counsellor, Foreign Office. Colonel P. J.Mackesy , D.S.O., M.C. , Directorate of Military Operations and Intelligence, War Office. Mr. C. J.Galpin, D.S.O. , Principal, Air Ministry. THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT! Mr. F. Sturton, Board of Trade. Major N.0.Hind, M.C., Assistant Secretary, Committee of Imperial Defence ) joint Secretary to ) the Sub-Committee.1 . THE CHAIRMAN suggested that those papers which had been circulated since the last meeting should first be considered. These were:- Paper No. P.S.O, (E.A.) 5 - Note by Joint Secretaries, covering a copy of the Report (C.I.D. Paper No. S33-B). Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 6 - Note by Joint Secretaries, covering information regarding permits for the manufacture of, and trade in Arms in foreign countries. Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 7 - Letter received by Mr. Howard Smith from the British Embassy, Paris. Paper No . P .S.O,(E.A.) 5 - Note by joint Secretaries, covering a copy of the Report by the Sub-Committee on Arms Traffic, March, 1917. THE CHAIRMAN observed that this Report, which was issued in 1917, dealt v/ith the large quantities of surplus arms that it was expected v/ould be available at the end of the war. It covered two aspects of the problem. First, the external traffic, i.e., the denial of arms to tribesmen, etc; and, secondly, the internal aspect, which concerned the Home Office. MR. JENKINS stated that he had referred to this paper as it shov/ed that the original purpose of Section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, was to prevent arms reaching a possible enemy; this had been diverted rather to the control of surplus war stocks. He noted that this Report had been followed in 1918 by a Report to the Ministry of Reconstruction on the control of firearms. MR. MacIVER stated that the latter Report showed that importance was attached to the export licensing system, from the point of view of preventing the export of arms to undesirable quarters.2. * * Ke suggested that the views of the Colonial Office on this question might he obtained. MR. HOWARD SMITH, in reply to a question, stated that the zones referred to in the Arms Export prohibition Order, 1931, corresponded with those given in the Draft Arms Traffic Convention of 19^5, from which he read the following extract:- Article a. ’‘The High Contracting Parties undertake not to export or permit the export of articles covered by Category I, except in accordance v/ith the following conditions:*” 1. The export shall be for a direct supply to the Government of the importing State or, v/ith the consent of such Government, to a public authority subcrdinate to it; 2. An order in writing, which shall be signed or en dorsed by a representative of tne importing Govern ment duly authorised so to act, shall have been presented to the competent authorities of the exporting country. This order shall state that the articles to be exported are required for delivery to the importing Government or public authority as provided in paragraph 1 '. MR. STURTON said that His Majesty’s Government had signed the Protocol to the 1919 Convention, so that it would be difficult to go against it even if other powers have not complied. There was, however, no similar Protocol to the 1925 Convention. He produced a document from the Foreign Office showing' that in 1925 that department authorised the issue of a licence to export war material in any quantity only to a governmental, as opposed to an individual, consignee. MR. HOWARD SMITH stated that our ratification of the 1925 Convention would not become effective until it had also been ratified by the Governments of the other principal arms producing countries. An embargo had been proposed in connection with the recent dispute between Paraguay and Bolivia, but this was still the subject of international discussion at Geneva. Aircraft, hov/ever, v/ere not included in the recent British embargo on export of arms to China3 . and Japan. If there v/as no Arms Export prohibition Order oar position would t&gt;e much the same as it v/as before the war 5 i. e. the Government would have no pov/er to regulate the export oi arms to undesirable destinations. THE CHAIRMAN pointed out that the present Regulations had no doubt been useful in dealing v/ith the abnormal con~ ditions existing after the war* when there were heavy surplus stocks, and when it was desirable to prevent their export to semi-civilised or other undesirable quarters. MR. GALPIN said that the disposal of surplus stocks v/as of no direct benefit to the armaments industry. He under stood that the stimulation of manufacture was the main object of the Sub-Committee. THE CHAIRMAN said that the disposal of surplus stocks was of indirect benefit to manufacturers as when they were exhausted or v/ere no longer of large dimensions, manufacturers would tend to get larger orders. Paper No. P.S.0.(E.A.) 6 - Control of arms manufacture and trade by foreign governments. THE CHAIRMAN stated that the next item (Paper No. P. S. 0. (E. A.) 6 ) dealt mainly v/ith manufacture and only gave a limited amouht of information about exports. COLONEL MACKESY drew attention to the fact that the Sv/edish Government at present enforced a system of licensing for exports. Papers Nos. P.S.O. (E. A.) 7 and 8 . Letter from British Embassy, Paris, on Arms export Regulations in Prance. (P.S.0.(E.A.) 7). Note by the War Office on Regulations in Foreign Countries, as notified to the League of Nations. (P.S.O. (E.A. ) 8 ). COLONEL MACKESY stated that the information given in Mr* Hardy’s letter did not tally v/ith the imormationr~ 4 | furnished hy the F’rench in their memorandum to the Disar mament Conference, which had been circulated as Item 5 % (Paper No. P.S.O. (E. A.) 8 ). THE CHAIRMAN thou^it that it was possible that the French, while having stringent regulations for the control of arms of a Government pattern, might have no regulations for the control of other kinds. He asked Mr. Howard Smith to try and reconcile these conflicting statements. MR. HOWARD SMITH undertook to make further enquiries. THE ClLilRHAN then asked the Committee to refer to the Board of Trade memorandum on the administration of the export licensing system (Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 4) , the examination of which had not been completed at the first meeting. He stated that since the last meeting he had ascer tained from Sir Henry Fountain that condition (3) of the export licence form had originally been inserted in order to cover the Board of Trade against action for breach of contract should it be necessary to revoke the licence summarily. He pointed out that the arms in respect of which licences v/ere granted v/ere dealt with in the memorandum under five heads and he thought that it would be useful if a statement could be drav/n up showing the number and value of the applications in each category. It v/ould thus be possible to ascertain v/hat proportion of the amount, and the value of the total arms exported, v/as manufactured by armament firms. He suggested that this statement should cover the years 19&lt;!8-32 inclusive. MR. STURTON stated that some IE,000 applications v/ere received per annum for the export of arms. Of these some 400 v/ere for v/ar material, information as to the value of v/hich v/as available. It was impossible to l: lZztz ' r. , _make a rapid analysis of all applications over the five yea period 19d8-3d. He suggested that an analysis should he made of all applications for the export of v/ar material, which should he divided into the following categories:- (a) Applications hy manufacturers; (h) Applications hy known armament dealers; (c) Applications hy others. He warned the Committee that the licences granted had not, until 1st January, 1933, shown the actual exports. It would therefore he difficult to give exact information. THE CHAIRMAN considered that sufficient information could he drawn from the licences granted for the export of war material between the 1st January, 19d8, and the 31st December, 193^, and accordingly asked Mr. Sturton to prepare this analysis. He hoped that this would disclose the approximate percentage of surplus stocks in the total of war material exported. He asked the Services whether the surplus stocks now in their possession were still abnormal. COLONEL MACKESY stated that the War Office still have appreciable quantities of surplus and obsolete stocks, left over from the late v/ar, in hand for disposal. The main items were 750,000 rifles, 30,000 Hotchkiss guns, and 50,000,000 rounds *303 rifle ammunition. MR. JENKINS said that the Admiralty had practically no abnormal stocks. Surplus Admiralty war material was generally sold for breaking up. A few naval guns and gun mountings had been sold for export, as higher prices were thus obtainable. MR. GALPIN stated that the Air Ministry only have a small surplus of machine gun cartridges and obsolete bombs, which they were willing to dispose of to a foreign buyer.MR. MacIVER said that the Government of Northern Ireland had accumulated at various times a considerable quantity of arms and ammunition. He undertook to enquire hov/ far these stocks had been disposed of and the quantities still remaining. He also added that cases of gun-running to the Irish Free State had come to the notice of the Home Office. MR. HOWARD SMITH stated that when the Foreign Office considered that there might be a political objec tion to the proposed export of arms, a reference v/as made by them to the British Embassy or Legation in the foreign country concerned, in order to see that the order was f bona fide 1 . MR. STURTON, in support of this, quoted an instance a large of a licence issued in 1927 for the export to Nicaragua of/ consignment of Lewis guns on an order represented to be on behalf of that Government. It was found, on enquiry, that the Nicaraguan Government were entirely ignorant of the order, the ultimate destination of v/hich was probably China. In this case the licence v/as immediately revoked. COLONEL MACKESY stated that,while the War Office carefully considered each application for the export of arms that v/as referred to them, they attached little importance to the possibility of these arms being used against British troops at some future date. This was rather a matter of sentiment, as it was obviously better that a potential enemy should be armed with British-made v/eapons, for v/hich, in the event of hostilities against us, he v/ould be unable to obtain spare parts and ammunition rather than with arms of foreign manufacture.MR. GALPIN stated that the 'basis of the present R.A.F. system was that firms 5 in return lor being given a free hand, disclose all information regarding exports. MR. FARRER thought that if certain known armament firms were given a free hand to export arms it would help them to a great extent in obtaining foreign orders. COLOIIEL MACKESY considered that as long as firms were liable to arbitrary stoppage of export, other than a national emergency, they were unlikely to regain the confidence of foreign customers and obtain orders. THE CHAIRMAN observed that the action taken in this country to regulate the export of arms had oeen entirely unilateral, with the effect that British firms suffered from handicaps to which their foreign competitors were not exposed. A solution might possibly be found if the present licensing system were to be abrogated in the case of selected armament firms, who would then export know definitely that their/trade would only be interfered with in the event of circumstances of an exceptional character. MR. HOWARD SMITH observed that if an export licensing system had not existed in this country unilateral action could not have been taken. MR. JENKINS said that were selected firms given a free hand accusations might be made in Parliament and elsewhere that the Government were discriminating between firms. He thought that a solution could be found were some v/ording adopted similar to that given in the Washington Treaty 1921-22 for the construction and sale of warships, i.e., to the effect that no licence lor 7.the export of arms v/ill be withheld unless contrary to any international agreement on the subject. MR. PARKER thought that a charge of discrimination could easily be refuted if the 'white list' solely comprised selected armament firms of known integrity, whose maintenance was important from the point of view of national defence. MR. JENKIIJS stated that the Admiralty have an understanding with contracting firms to maintain secrecy and to disclose sales to foreign countries. These contractors would understand and accept any prohibition imposed on them in the interests of national safety. They would v/illingly conform to any international conven tion that might be agreed to, provided other countries not only adopted,but enforced its provisions. MR. PARKER said that British armament firms com plained that they were the victims of the unilateral action of His Majesty’s Government, as firms in foreign countries were not exposed to similar handicaps. They felt that prohibition had been placed on exports of arms v/hen the national interests were not directly concerned, with the consequence that the order was placed abroad, and the con fidence of the foreign customer was irretrievably forfeited. MR. JENKINS pointed out the anomaly v/hich exists, whereby under existing legislation the Admiralty can export a v/arship completely equipped providing it complies with the Treaty of Washington. Under this Treaty the Admiralty cannot refuse a licence to build, deliver and despatch a warship that conforms with its terms. Embargoes on arms do not, therefore, affect warships, though they do cover any renewals of ammunition and guns for the same. MR. MacIVER noted that small trade applications for sporting guns, revolvers, etc., i.e. , not relating to war material, comprise the bulk of the applicationsreceived. The Home Office v/ould like to retain a system which v/ould prevent any possihility of leakage within the United Kingdom and thus of criminals and undesirables acquiring firearms. The Home Office v/ished to he satisfied that all arms sold under export licence actually left the country. COLONKL MACKESY noted that in paragraph 5* the Spanish and Portuguese Governments were stated to he consulted whenever an export licence for arms to either of those oouitries is under consideration. He thought that this was a case of foreign countries making use of our system. MR. HOWARD SMITH undertook to furnish further particulars on this point. THE CHAIRMAN then stated that the High Commissioners for the Dominions and India receive licences for the export of consignments of arms from the Board of Trade on application. automatically/ Licences are necessary for Customs purposes. It was therefore not possible to exempt them y and it is quicker for them to use the ordinary licensing machinery when mailing shipments. He had recently received a letter from Mr. Daniels of the India Store Department asking that licences for that Department might he dispensed with and an export certificate issued, as in the case of arms sent out of the country by the Defence Departments. (A copy of Mr. Daniels’ letter is circulated to the Sub-Committee as Paper No. P.S.O.(E.A.) 10). THE CHAIRMAN asked if there was a possibility of sub-contractors obtaining sufficient knowledge to construct a complete article of secret pattern which might'be exioorted. He noted that s as shewn in paragraph 12 of this paper 5 a case had occurred when Messrs. Brov/n Bros. , had applied for a licence to export an aircraft bomb that was found to be of a confidential design* MR. GALPIN said that the case in point was of an exceptional nature. Messrs. Brov/n Bros. 5 v/ere certainly sub-contractors and had obtained 5 probably quite unwittingly , certain specifications of an article which happened to be on the secret list. The projected exportation of the bomb in question v/ould not have come to light if there had been no export licensing system. MR. JENKINS said that the Admiralty were confident that they could fully control their contractors, who only relied on sub-contractors for component parts. COLONEL MACKESY stated that War Office contractors were not allowed to sub-contract completed articles of a secret pattern. THE CHAIRMAN invited the views of the meeting as to v/hether other Departments, such as the Colonial Office and the India Office, should be called upon to express an opinion. He suggested that the Joint Secretaries should inform these Departments of the proceedings of this cub-Committee, and ask them to put forward, in writing or otherwise, any views they may hold. He observed that special importance had formerly been attached to certain zones, i.e., the Persian Gulf. He asked Mr. Jenkins to ascertain if the Admiralty still Held any decided viev/s on this and v/hether they considered a licensing system was of any value in controlling the arms tralfic in such regions.I ^ it 11 . It v/as protiable that the Report of this Interdepart mental suh-committee would he required by Ministers at an early date. It would therefore be as v/ell to prepare forth with an outline of the Report- He suggested that the Joint Secretaries should draft a Report for consideration at the next meeting, showing the advantages and disadvantages of the present system and the headings on v/hich discussion can be concentrated. He suggested that Monday^ April 24th, v/ould be a suitable date for the next meeting. If, however, the Ministerial Committee desired an urgent Report, an earlier meeting might be necessary. CONCLUSION. THE SUB-COMMITTEE agreed:- That the Joint Secretaries should prepare and circulate the outline of a draft Report, with a view to its discussion at the next meeting, to be held on Monday, April 24th, 1932. 2, Whitehall Gardens, S»W.l., 10th April, 1933.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2188</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002d7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2188</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/20 'System of licensing exports of arms and ammunition'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:52:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">por</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (97 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 97; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains minutes, correspondence and reports regarding changes made by the British Government to the system for licensing the export of arms and ammunition to foreign countries. The India Office participated in the process to ensure that requests from the Governments of Afghanistan and Nepal would be referred via the India Office before approval.The file consists of correspondence between the India Office Political Department, Major Neville Godfray Hind of the Committee of Imperial Defence, the Foreign Office, and the Board of Trade Import and Export Licensing Section. The potential advantages and disadvantages of the proposed open licence system are discussed, as are India Office concerns that a change to an open system would make it difficult to regulate the purchase of arms by Afghanistan and Nepal, and could pose a threat to the security of India.The file also contains the following minutes and reports:minutes of the first and second meetings of the Committee of Imperial Defence Principal Supply Officers Committee, Sub-Committee on System of Licensing Exports of Arms and Ammunition, ff 74-96;the final report of the above Sub-Committee, ff 40-51;a copy of the Anglo-Afghan Treaty (1921), ff 56-60;a copy of the Cabinet Minutes 70(33), 20 December 1933, ff 24-27;notes on a meeting held at the Board of Trade on 29 December 1933, ff 17-22;and a 'List of selected firms and Service Departments which will acquaint them of the new procedure', f 12.The file also contains a small amount of correspondence dated 1938, regarding a request from the Government of Portuguese India for ammunition to be supplied by a British firm.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade, Commercial Relations and Treaties Department, Imports and Exports Licensing Section</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Committee of Imperial Defence, Principal Supply Officers Committee, Sub-Committee on System of Licensing Exports of Arms and Ammunition</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Export controls</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002d7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>