<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:12:03.215Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Translation of letter No.124, dated 27-1-45 from Sharjah to the P.A., Bahrain. 6-1-45. I have received the sun of Rs.940/- sent for the Ruler of Dubai which has been paid to him. Copy of the receipt is enclosed .and the original has been sent to the Secry to P.R. Copy with the original receipt is forwarded to the Secry to P.R. I have received from the R.A. the sun of Rs.940/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at Dubai Bay for the 78th month after agreement for the period from 22-12-44 to 22-1-45.. (x) — \VV Reference yQur letter No.40-4/26, dated © U.E. Dated 23-1-45. Seal of Said bin Maktoom. Bahrain ReceiptA HO. - 4/26 To The Residency Agent t POLITICAL AGiiRCY, 7 BAHRAIN, p//L Fehn ‘uyy, 1945* Memorandum :» I am forwarding you a sum of Rs« 940/-(Rupees nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said bin Maktam, O.B.L., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil air agreement for the 79th month after, the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2* Please forward the Shaikh 1 receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me* for Political A^ent, Bahrain* Copy, with compliments to the Secretary to the Rouble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 , dated the 28th June, 1938*Translation of- letter Mo.236, dated 27-2-45 fron the R.a. , Sharjah' to the Political Agent, Bal rain. Reference your letter ho.476-4/26, dated 6-2-r-to. I have received the sun .of Rs.940/- sent for payment to the Ruler of Dubai, which has been paid to him. A copy of the receipt is enclosed and the origina. has been sent to the Decry to P.R. Received fror the R.a. Rs.940/- being rent of the civil Seaplane Base at Khor Dubai for the 79th month t /-» i i • j ^ '1 AT. ~ O 'I Copy forwarded v»ith the original receipt to the S.ecr to P.R. after agreement for the period from 22-1-45 to 22-2 23-2-45.No. StS.' 4/26 POLITICAL iili^WCY, BAHRAIN. ^/&lt;iiarch, 1945. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Ueaoranduu. I am forwarding you a sum of Rs.940/- (Rupees nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said bin Maktoom, O.B.S., Ruler of Dubai on account . of Dubai Civil air agreement for the 80th month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter for Political Agent, Bahrain. Wv^tr Copy, with compliments to the Secretary to the lion 1 Die Ihe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187, dated the 28th June, 1938. to meN-&gt;- POLITICAL AlihNCY A. BAHRAI I., c ,n-'April, I'XS-. To Tiie Rasidency ii # ;ent dilc. I' .‘t tiU wiOuiOX‘c ; J Ivu l-U u I • ± iun forN.uxTiing you a of 94.0/-(nine hui.ured and forty)only in a sealed bag for ^ayient to uiiaxl.ii bald bin iuaittoojJij u*jLi»u* y iwiilei' of -u nti cn account of bubal Civil air agreement for the 31st month after the agreement date! the Cth Junej 193B* 2. Please forward the ohaikh's receipt direct to the becretary to the Uon’ble -he* Political Resident In the Persian duif, bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me* Copy, with compliments to the becretary to the uon*!).© the Political Resident in the Persian 'juif, nushire, with reference to India OTfice teieoram ho*1187, dated the 28th June* 1938* \A^ J~ uA^' - for Political Agent, bahraln4/26 POLITICAL AGENCY, U .V fit! A Tff v5 To 1 aiu forvardirifc you a ouui of Iw* 940/-(nine hundred and forty)only In a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said bin **iuktoou* Kiiler of bubai on account of Dubai Civil air agrcOiaent for the S2nu aonth afuer the a^reOiiieiit dated tne otn ^• Please forward ll«_ Slti -kh*s receipt direct to the Secretary to the ^on*ble the Political Kosident in the Copy, with complixacnts to the Secretary to the }ion f ble the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No. 1187. dated the 28th June, 1938. Persian Saif, Bushire, and a copy of the f to me. brwaruing letter for Political Agent,© Translation of letter Ko;556, dated 1 7-5-45 from P.O.T.C,, Sharjah to the P‘. A. , Bahrain. I have received the sum of its.940/- for the Ruler of Dubai ,/hich has been raid to him. A copy, of the receipt is enclosed and the original has been sent to the Secry. to P.R. Copy forwarded, with the original receipt, to the Secry to P.R. Received from R.A., Sharjah the sum of As.940/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at Khor of Dubai for the Slst month after agreement for the period from- 22-3-45 to 22-4-45. Reference your letter ITo.l- . y ited 9-4-45 2G-4-45 Said bin Laktoom.Translation of letter Iio.597, dated P.G.T.C., Sharjah to the Political a( r ent, 28-5-45 iron Bahrain. A» C, Reference your letter No I have received Rs.940/- which has been .aid to him. is enclosed anti the original to P.R. xo'qIa 1838-4/2G, dated 6-5-45. for the Ruler of Jubai A copy of the receipt has been sent to Secry. U. ‘Copy forwarded, with original, receipt to the decry to P.R. Received from the R.a., Sharjah Rs.240/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at Jubai Bay for the 82nd month after agreement for the period from 22-4-45 to 22-5-45. 22-5-45. Seal. r* No^SJZ hate &gt;$. ^To The Political Officer f Xrucial Coasts Shftr'ftli' i I am forwarding you a su.i of .ks# 940/-(nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed tag for payment to shaikh bald bin Maktooia* O.B.b. jRuier of Jubai on account of Dubai Civil Air agreement for the 84th month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938* 2* Please forward the bftaiki^s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Jushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me* °fo J for Political Agent, $ Bahrain* Copy vdth compliments to the becretary to the Hen 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, *rith reference to India office telegram No*1187, dated the 23th June, 1938* V 1 * '*•/ ^/• ^. /r? 7 o Translation of letter No.720, dated 3C-7-45 from R.a., d.arha to the P.A., Bahrain. /i . ^ Reference your letter ho.2342-4/26, dated 7-6-46 I have received tjie sum of Rs.940/- for the Ruler of Jubai which has been paid to him. xi cony of the receipt is enclosed and the original has been sent to the decry, to P.R. U. 3. Copy forwarded, with the original receipt to the decry, to P.R. Dabr&amp;ia Receipt No. k&gt;£h. .Date...NO . &lt;3 I'to ' 4/26 To Xhe Residency Agent, ivH» M-&amp;MQRANDUM s - I am forwarding you a sum of Ss« 940/-(nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for payment to bhaikh baid bin iwaktoom, O.B.b., Ruler of Uubai on account of Dubai Civil air agreement for tne 85tii month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2* Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Uon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian 0ulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter me* (/ „ for Political Agent, J' Bahrain# Copy with compliments to the Secretary to'the Kon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian uulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegr.-da No# 1187, dated the 28th June, 1938#i ■ % y _ //, /? •7. ( / S' Translation of letter No.872, dated 12-8-45 from R.A., Sharjah to the P.A., Bahrain. A.C. ''&gt;P 3 V Reference your letter No.2780-4/26, dated 8-7-45. I have received the sum of Rs.940/- for the Ruler of Dubai which has been paid to him. A copy of the receipt is enclosed and the original has been sent to the Secry. to P.R. U.E. Copy with the original receipt to the Secry to P.R. Received from the R.A., Sharjah the sum of Rs.940/- being rent of the Seaplane Base at Khor of Dubai for the 84th month after agreement for the period from 22-6-45 to 22-7-45. 23-7-45. Said bin Maktoom. tfo- fiakain .Date- «• jiK0.3i&gt;^o- V86 i‘o The Residency Agent* POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHIUUiy Gep teiiil&gt;cX'* a. ‘.../i-O • I am forwarding you a sum of Ss»940/e Cnine hunared and forty) only In a soaled &amp;ag fur payuent to bnaiKh Bald bin Uaktoom* 0«d«B* 9 Euler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air agreement for the 86th month after the agreement dated the 6tii Ju e* 1938. 2. Please forr^ird the SUajlch^ receipt dire6i to the secretary to the hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bushire* and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Y l l for Political Agent* ^ r T Bahrain. Copy with coapliments to the Secretary to the Uon'ble the Political Rcsiaent in the Persian uulf* bushire* with reference to India Office telegram No.ll&amp;7* dated the 28th June* 1928.&lt;§)^ ? 7~ 7 ? rr ¥jr~ Translation of letter No.973, dated 23-9-45 from R.A., Sharjah to the P.A., Bahrain. . „ {p)}W A.C. Reference your letter No.973, dated 23-9-45*) I have received the sum of Rs.940/- for the Ruler od Dubai which has been paid to him. A copy of the receipt is enclosed and the original has been sent to the Secry. to P.R. U.E. Copy with the original receipt is forwarded to the Secry. to i.R. Bahrain Receipt No„.«r?.^i/D at e Receipt . Received from the R.A., Sharjah the sum of Rs.940/- being rent of the Seaplane Base at Dubai Bay for the 85th month after agreement for the period from 22-7-45 to 22-8-45. Dated 23-8-45. Said bin Maktoom.NO. i4A&lt;3jj- 4/26 POLITICAL AUii^CY, BAHRAINf October, 1945. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. MtittORAKpTIfl t.. I uiu forwarding you a suia of ^940/-(nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for payment to ahaikh Said bin maktoom, O.S.n. , Ruler of uuoai on account of inibai Civil Air agreement for the 87th month after the agreement dated the 6th Juno, 1933. 2. Please forward the shaikh^ receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf, iiushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy with compliments to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, A&gt;ushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187, dated the 28th June 1938. for Political Agent, ^ Bahrain.Translation of letter No.1048, dated 10-10-45 from R.A., Sharjah to the P.A., Bahrain. a.c. i ' Reference your letter No.3620-4/26, dated 5-9-45. I have received Rs.940/- for the Ruler of Dubai which has been paid to him. A copy of the receipt is enclosed and the original has been sent to the Secry to P.R. U.E. % Copy forwarded, with the original receipt, to the Secry. to P.R. Received from the R.A., Rs.940/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at Dubai Bay for the 86th month after agreement for the period from 22-8-45 to 22-9-45. 23-9-45. Said bin Maktoom. No Bahrain ^ 'NO. 4/26 To MKMOliAMDUM : - I am forwarding you a sum of Es. 940/- (nine Hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said bln Maktoom, O.h.iii., Huler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air agreement for the 88th month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. Please forward the Shaikhs receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon* ole the Political liesident in the Persian &lt;iulf, hushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. The Residency Agent, Snarjah. A Vi P0i»l TIC Ah AGMCX, BAHRA1; , November, 1945. ue&gt; Political Agent, Jiahrain. Copy with compliments to the Secretary to the non*bl6 the Political Resident in thd Persian dulf, Bus^iire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187* dated the 28th June, 1938.UO Translation of letter Ko. 11(34, dated 14-11-45 from R.A., Sharjah to the P.a*, Bahrain. 7-1C-45. I have received Rs.940/- for the Ruler of Dubai which has been paid to him. A copy of the Copy forwardddtj with the original receipt, to the Secry to the P.R. .V Received from Jasim bin Mohammed, R.a., Sharjah Rs.940/- being rent of the Seaplane Base at Dubai Day for the 87th month after agreement for the period from 29-9-45 to 22-10-45. Reference your letter No.4226-4/26, dated S&gt; - receipt is enclosed and the original one has been sent to the Secry to P.R. 23-10-45. Seal of Said bin Maktoom.&lt;5' 4/26 POLITICAL AGiSNCX, BAHRAIN, Deceiaber, 194 5. ^iC ■ The Political Officer, Trueial Coast, JHHw s \ ■li-...10RANDUll 8 - I am forwarding you a sun of Ks. 940/-(nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for P^^nt to tihaikh Laid Bin Uaktoon, O.B.^., riuler of Lub^l accaait of Dubai Civil Air agreement for the 89th month after the agreement dated the 6th June^ 1938* 2 # Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in ^ e Persian uaLf* Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me* A- Political Agent, Bahrain* Copy with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian dulf, bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187, dated the 28th June, 1938*Translation of letter'- No. 1234, dated 5-12-45 I have received Rs.940/- for the Ruler of Dubai which has been paid to him. A copy ol the receipt is enclosed and the original has beer sent to the 3ecry. to the P.R. Copy, with the original receipt, forwarded to the Secry. to P.R. nECtuIPT . Received from R.A., Sharjah the sum of Rs.940/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at Dubai for the 88th month after agreement for the period from 22-10-45 to 22-11-45. from R.A., Sharjah to the political Agent ,Bahi ain A. C Reference your letter No.4632-4/26, dated 7-11-45. . 23-11-45. Seal of Said bin A; ale turn.Translation of letter No.1300, dated 30-12-45 from R.a.. Shariah to the P.a., Bahrain. 9-12-45. I have received the sum of Rs.940/- for the Shaikh of dubai which has been paid to him and a copy of the receipt is enclosed. The original receipt has been sent to the Secry. to the P.R. Copy forwarded with the original receipt to the Secry. to P.xH. Received from the R.A. the sum of Rs.940/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at Dubai Bay for the 89th month after agreement for the period from 22-11-45 to 22-12-45. 22-12-45 Seal of Said bin Maktum) T7 NO. 7^- To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, January, 1946. Tho Political Officer, Trucinl Coast, SHARJAH. MEMORANDUM: - ' «&gt; **** I am forwarding you a sum of h. •940/-(nine hundred and forty) only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Uaktoom, O.B.E. , Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air agreement for the 90th month after tho agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh’s receipt direct to tho Secretary to the Hon'bio the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. 0 ^. for Political Agent, I Bahrain. Copy with compliments to the C &gt;ecrotary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire with reference to India Office telegram No.1187, dated the 28th June, 1938.(g) S' Translation of letter To.117, d; ted 30-1-46 from 3.a., Sharjah to the P*A., Bahrain, ^ A.C, ' deference your letter No.75-4/26, dated 8-1-46. I have received the sum of ds.940/- for the duler of Dubai which has been paid to him. /icopy of the receipt is enclosed and the original has been sent to the Secry. to i\A. U. . Copy for arced, with the original receipt, to the Secry to P.R. Received from the Rs.940/- being rent of the Civil Seaplane Base at hhor Dubai for the 90th month after agreement for the period from 22-12-45 to 22-1-46. Said bin Kaktura.Political Agency, Bahrain, The 13th . ltrch f 194 6 To The Political Officer, Tracial Coast, Shar.iah. Me morandom. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed hag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the 92 nc i month after the agreement dated the 6;h June, 1938. 2„ Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. for Political Agent, Bahrain.£ ©si j\lo.3o8*o4ol British Agency, ibharjah. Bated 19th j^arch 19^6. TO, The- political ii&amp;ent, baiirain* Memorandum. Bahrain Receipt Ket'erence your memorandum j\o •479-4/26 oated the 11th of February 19&lt;t6 forwarding a sum of jis.940/- for payment to the Kuier of Bubai on account of Bubai uivil Air Agreement. 2. The amount has been paid to the shaikh and a copy of his receipt is enclosea together with a copy of its translation. The original with translation is being forwaraea to the secretary to '9? the hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, sushire. Political Officer, Trucicil coast, sharjah. copy with enclosures is lorwardea with compliments to the secretary to the Hon 1 ole the political .Resident in &gt;the Persian Gulf, cushire.1 m * y &gt; 1 ® Political Agency, Bahrain, The 3rd April, 1946 The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. M emorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the 93 Y.H month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2 . Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. 4 &lt;7 IT' /4 for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.isjo.a^y.CAOl British Ag, on cy, ^h arj a h L»£:ted both March TO, The political &gt;^ent bal.rain ;nt, /m) &lt;in. lo- i' emorenoum. No, lb if / fa ^ r p.!fV Ketei*ence your meQioraiiauni i\c•b^b-4/kb c^teci the loth of ^arch 104b forvarcing a sum ol as.9^o/- for payment to the buler of oubai on account of j^ubai civil win Agreement. 2. The amount has been paid to the shaikh ana e coj^y of his receipt is encloeea together vith a copy of its translation. The original uith translation is bein &amp; torwaroed to the secretary to the Hon»ble the political resident in the Persian oulf, bushire. boast, oharjah copy v^ith enclosures is forv-arded v,ith compliments to the aeci'etary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, bushire.Nc -W To -4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, The rj ., . 194- 7 tn j&amp;y, 6 The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandum, I am sending herev/ith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the month after the agreement dated the 6 oh June, 1938. 2 . Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. € &lt;4 % for Political Agent, Bahrain. !opy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.Political Agency, Bahrain, The 194 6th June, 6 To TYWrJr-CW^rrr 'Shar.i ah. Memorandum. Vly I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the month after the agreement dated the 6 th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh’s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, _th reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th ime, 1938. Agent, BahrainNO. i'?? .0401 British A*e n cy&gt; S^^rjeh* Datea 4th June, 1946. No. To, The political Agent,, Bahrain# fy.emorandxm . Reference your memorandum ho*1426-4/2&lt; dated the, 7th of May, 1946, forwarding a sum of as»94o/~ for payment to the Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement. 2* The amount has been paid to the Bhaiic and a copy of his receipt is enclosed together with a copy of its translation# T^e original with translation is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hobble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Copy with enclosures is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hobble ^ie political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire#Receiveo from Bar* biii Resiaency A^ent, Sharjah, the sum of &lt;fc.94o/-, beir^ tiie rent of the Civil Biarine Base at Dubai creek for the ninty-forth month after ^ the Agreement i.e. from the 22na of A^ril, 1^6 to the 22iid of May, Dated/ 22na iiay 1^6, 4 Sealeo Said bin kektum, Kuler of Dubai.No. 677 &lt;*0^01 Agency 9 Bated 29th June Sharj&amp;h# 1946. •~r i To, The political A 4 »e n t, Bahr&amp;ira. v i ^ emoranduiR . Reference your meoiorandum No .1801*^/26 dated the 6th of June 1946, forwarding a suil of ife.94o/* for payment to the Ruler oi Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement. 2. The amount hae been paid to the Shaikh and a copy of hie receipt ia enclosed together with a copy of ite trexislation. The original with translation is being forwardeo to the Secretary to the Hon , ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Copy with enclosures is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Bahrain ReceiptNc Political Ag( The Bahrain, 194 k ^ To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Me morandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed lag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the it'* month after the agreement dated the 6th 'June, 1938. 2 Please forward the Shaikh’s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political-Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.no. ^|, 6 y ^ ly J Political Agency, Bahrain, The ||^ CKiAjy^s 194 1 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Me morandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed tag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Moktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. ' 2, Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded wit the Hon 'ble the Political Resident'in the Pe/tsian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram‘No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.No. J4/44 . Political Agency, Bahrain The September, 194 6. To ' The Political Ofileer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandum^ I am sending herev/ith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the oath mon th after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2, Please forward the Shaikh’s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Eon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. , f orpfkft-iticab w So, fV s' Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th une, 1938.■&gt;} to? • 9^41 • 0401 To^ British Agency, Sharjah. Dated the 10th Sept.* 1^46, (9 The polidic&amp;l AB en t&gt; Bahrain. iieniorarictm^ \ n5 Heference ycur memorandum Ko.2607-4/26 dated the 11th of August, 1246, for^ardir% a sum of &amp;.240/- for payment to the Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement. 2. The amount Las been paid to the Shaikh anu a copy of his receipt is enclosed together w ith a copy of its tx*anslation. ii»e oi'i^i^-^al v^ith translation is being forwarded to the secretary to the Ron’ble tiie Political Resioeno in tlie Persian Gulf, Bushire. c? 3 &lt; S/h? rteSAdency Agent, Sharjah Copy vith enclosures is forv.ai’ded with complimenus to Uie Secretary to the Ron*ole the Political Resideriu in the Persian dull, Bushire.Received 1 rom j^uhainuaG, Resiaency Agent, Sharjah, the sum of As*940/-, bein^ the rent of the Civil marine Base at Lwbai creek for the ninty-seventh month after the Agreement, i.e. from the 22na of July 1946 to the 22nd of August 1946. Detea, 22nd August 1946. Sealed Sa'ia bin kaktum Ruler of Dubai*No. 330' - 4/26 p ^f4^c«p° y ’ Ba ^fg’ To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruc^^of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2, Please forward the Shaikh’s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Busirtra, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain '{‘V Captain. ; for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident ill the Persian Gulf , Bushirs^ Bahrain with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.(?*■) r /2j ^o*1015•0401 Britieh Agency, Sbaijah. Dated 3otH September 1946# To, The political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandum * Reference your memorandum no *2912-^/26 dated the 7th of September 1946, enclosing a sum of &amp;*940/- for payment to the Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil/Agreement* 2. The amount has been paid to the Shaikh and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt, together with a copy of its translation* The original with translation is being forwaided to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Copy with enclosures is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire*No. -4/2C Political Agency, Bahrain, The^/2^ ovenber 194 6 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the l°0th month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh’s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain, / for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu^hire,^hr^ir. with reference to India Office telegram No#1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.NO,1139.0401 British Ac^cy, sharj&amp;h. Dated 14tn November 1946. No To, The political At&gt;ent, Baiirain. ^ ^ t v kemoranaum . Reference your memoranauni No.3301-4/26 dated the bth of October 1946, enclosing the sum of Hs.940/- for payment to the Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement. 2. The amount has been paid to the Shaikh ana I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt together with a copy of its translation. The ori^ical with translation is bein&amp; forvaraea to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Copy with enclosures is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Bon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.Received from Mr* jasim bin luhammaa, Residency Agent, sherjeh, the sum of tfc*940/-, being the rent of the civil Marine Base at Dubai creek for the 99th month after the Agreement i*e* from the kknd of pacefa.ber lt46 to the 22nd of Octobei* 1946. Datea 22na October 1946* bealeu s&amp;’iQ bin Maktum, Ruler of Dubei*f\ No. 4-o ~ 4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain The S . jr 194 The 9 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.lah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the lOlst month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. P13&amp;S3 f^prard the Shaikh’s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Qulf, &amp;usbri*e 5 and, a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain, Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, .^hrair,, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. S' fjjr0 No.l2fc2#O^Cl British Agency, Sharjah* I/&amp;^ea 27U. Lee ember To The political A^ent, Bahrain. ^emo I'aiicuiii. .nduc Reference your memoranduia ho*3649-4/26 dated the 9th of November 1946, forv/aroin^ the sum of Hs*940/- for payment to the Ruler of Lubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement. 2. The amount has been paid to the Shaikh and a copy of his receipt is enclosea together with a copy of its translation# The original with translation is being forwarded tto the Secretary to the hobble the Political Resident 1a u~t Persian Gulf, Bahrain# Copy with enclosures is forwardec vith compliments to the lecretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain#No - /OO -4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, The // it jami*ry f 194 7 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the i02i d month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh'-s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Dahraln 9 for ^Po^Litical Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bjagfefeee* &gt;.ihr~:n, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th' June, 1938.mm** K 0 . 2 fc• 04.01 Britifch Agency, S^erjeh* De^ea &amp;th jenuery 1947 * The polruieal baiii^ln* -^s keaxoraiiQum* y VH Reierence your meniorAficufli Ko* 4000 -^/L 6 datea Uie bth oi oeceniber 1946 , forwarcii% the sum oT i-b® 940 /- tor payment to the Ruler of i»ubai on account of Dubai civil Air Agreement* 2 . The ©mount has been paid to the shaikh and a copy df his receipt is enclosed together with a copy of its translation. The original with translation ia beiiie forwarded to the secretary to the hon'ble the political Refciknt, in tl^e Persian Gulf, B&amp;hrsin* Receipt Copy with enclosures is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the hobble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain*No. Political Agency, Bahrain, The February 194 ? ^. 3 ^- To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Me morandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air v Agreement for the . month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2, Please forward the Shaikh'-s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Brasttidprc, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. tfahrciin , for Political Agent, Bahrain. MlT C^- Ccpy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, &gt;, r with reference to India Office telegram No* 1187 dated the^’Sth June, 1938.MO.129.0401 britieh agency, blerjeh. oeted 6th *eDruery, 1947. TO The Political *^ent, bahrain. ^emorangum . Keterence your memorandum mo. 100-4/26 dated the n 11th January, 1947, ioi^arding a sum of Hs.940/- for payment to the buler of uubai on account of uubei v*ivil air agreement. The amount has been paid to the bhaikh and a of his receipt is enclosed together with a copy of its translation. The original with translation ie being forwarded to the secretary to the non* ole the Political Hesident in the Persian uulf, baiirain. copy with enclosures is forwarded with complimenti to the secretary to the non* ole the political nesioent in the Persian uulf, bahrain* Political Officer, Trucial coast, bharjah*l / No. To yy/f. -4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 194 i&amp;rch, 7 The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Meniorandimi. I am sending herewith a sum of Is. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. i04th 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushin, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. L -Pm am / for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No. 1187 June, 1938.Translation or letter No.255 dated the 4th March&gt;~' 1947, from the P.O.T.C., Sharjah to the Political Reference your letter No.434-4/26 dated the 8th February, 1947. I have received the sum of Rs.940/- sent by you for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. The amount has been paid to the said, and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Copy with the original receipt is forwarded te the Secretary to the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Agent, Bahrain After Compliments0 Received from Mr, Jasim bin Muhammad, Residency Agent, Sharon, the sum of Rs.940/-, being the rent of the Civil Air Base at Dubai creek for the 103rd month after the Agreement. I received the said amount for the period from the 22nd January, 1947 to the 22nd Ferbaury, 1947. Dated, 23rd February, 1947. Sid. Sa 1 id bin Maktun, (Ruler of Dubai).No. To -4/26 Political Agency, la IK. April 9 The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Bahrain, 194 7 M emorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 106th 2. Please fQjward the Shaikh^ receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B^strirre, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. ** QEBJPwSwflt Bahrain, Ofu \l/i \ J for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No. 1187 date^ June, 1938.Translation of letter No.485 dated the 1st of May, 1947, from the 1 .O.T.C., Sharjah to the Political agent, Bahrain. deference your letter No.1139-4/26 dated the 12th April, 1947. I have received the sum of Fa.940/- sent by you for payment to the duler of Jubai. I have paid the amount and I enclose herewith a copy of the receipt. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Copy with original receipt is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gflilf, Bahrain. After Compliments,N°. - 4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 194 7 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.jah. Me morandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Is. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the i06vbmonth after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 7 N 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain C/Cs h* Z^^^ f ^i Political Agent ’ Bahrain * Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BxsiiirBapcBahrair with reference to India Office telegram No.ll87 dated the 28th June, 1938.No - n^7 -4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, Junet 194 7 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the -iryyfh mon th after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. B&amp;hraln 9 Copy forwarded with compliments to tne secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, OoabdXDe^jc Bahrain, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.Translation of letter No.604 dated the 14th June, 1947, from the R.=A., Sharjah, to the P.A., Bahrain. by you, which is for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 12th May, 1947. I have received the sum of Rs.940/- sent Usual Ending. Copy with the original receipt is forwardedPOLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No. -4/26 The 23rd June, 1947. To / The Residency Agent, / - ) i Sharjah. Sub» Payment of Rs. 940/- per month to the Shaikh of Dubai for Civil Air Agreement lA^MORANDUH , ^ * &lt;^1 Reference your letter No. 14th June, 1947. 604 dated, f 2. The amount of Rs. 940/- foprarded under cover of Agency memorandum No.1614-4/26 dated 12th May 1947, was sent for the 106th month after the Agreement and was paid for the period from 22nd April to 22nd May, 1947. The receipt signed by the Shaikh of Dubai shows the amount to have been received for the 105th month i.e. for the period from 22nd March to 22nd April 1947. Will you plsaxH therefore please obtain a fresh receipt from the Shaikh for the correct period, and forward it in original to the Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with a copy to me. Sd. C. J. FELLY Political Agent, Bahrain. attested, Superintendent, Political Agency, Bahrain. Copy, with compliments ; to the Secret* ry to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information.No. ^ ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, The July, 194 7 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Me morandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the lOSthmonth after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2, Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus-h&amp;ra, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, , ; &gt; with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. Bahrain, ^^^for Political Agent, Bahrain. j .for Political Agent, Bahrain.Translation of letter No.668 dated the 5th July, 1947, from the R.A., Sharjah, to the Reference your letter Up.1947-4/26 dated the 8th June, 1947. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy with the original receipt is forwarded with compliments to the secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, / 7- y ;&gt; I have received the sun of Rs.940. 0.0 sent by you for payment to the Ruler of Oubai T hnvp nnid the amount to him and I enclose Usual Ending4 / * *411 iV S' Translation of letter No.671 dated the 5th July, 1947, from the R.A. V Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. S /, \ — ——■ After Compliments, / 2 ^ - ? - Reference your letter No.2100-4/26 dated the 23rd June, 1947. I enclose herewith a copy of a receipt from the Ruler of Dubai for the 106th month after the Agreement. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Copy with original receipt is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.No ^i Political Agency, Bahrain, The ^ August y 194 7. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.jah. Mem orandum* I am sending herewith a sum of Is. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the m °nth after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian anc * a C0 Py 'the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain ^for^Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with reference to India Office telegram No. 1187 datJ^^he June, 1938.'fc. \H &lt;S Translation of letter fto.743 dated the 26th July, 1947, from the R. A, Sharjah, to the P.A., Bahrain 0 After Compliments, Reference your letter No.2261 dated the Pth July, 1947. I h^ve received the sum of Rs.940/« sent by.you for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Copy, with the original receipt, is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'Ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No. 2.g ^ -4/26. Political Agency, Bahrain, The ^ -August, 1947. To y ^ The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Me morandum. ^ I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the 110th month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Sdx&amp;x&amp;de, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. Bahrain for Politi gent, Bahrain.Translation of le f 'or Mo # P30 dated the 31st August, 1947 from the R.A., Sharjah, to the Political Arent, Bahrain. After Compliments, j '■ ’ 3 Reference Your letter No.2621-4/26 dated the 13th A 1 ust, 1947. T have received the sum of P'.°4C/- sent by Your Excellency for payment to the Ruler of Jubai. T have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being sent to the Secretary to the Hon'bie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. with compliments to the Secretary to the Ilon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Copy with the original receipt is forwardedNo - 32Jf_4 A6# To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 6 'October, 194?. The Political Officer, Tracial Coast, Shar.iah. i Memorandum. 1 am sending herewith a sum of Es.(940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin M ktoora, O.B.h., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air ^ g the 111th month after the agreement dated the ?• , forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the r^ C c et p ry vJ° the ? on,ble the Pol itical Resident in the Persian and a co Py of the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain, \ Political Agent, Bahrain. t, .v, C 3 py £ orwar 4ed with compliments to the Secretary to the H ?l l h ble f . the Polit ioal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 datedthe28th j litig jTranslation of letter No. 915 dated the 27th September, 1947, from the R.4., Sharjah, to the Reference your letter No. 2832-4/26 dated the 7th September, 1947. I have received the sum of Rs.940/- sent hy you for payment' to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is bfcing sent to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Copy with the original receipt is forward ed with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. P.A., Bahrain.No. political Agency, Bahrain, n Ik I. 194 To -4/26 The Political Officer, November 194 7 Trucial Coast, Sharjah. M emorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Es. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the 112th month after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forwaj^^the Shaikh r s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon^nxe the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, , and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon : ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bughwr-e, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. Bahrain - Vl T&gt;: ■ i Tl for Political Agent, BahrainTranslation of letter No.1058 dated the 2nd November, 1947, from the R.A., Sharjah, to the , Bahrain. After Compliments, Reference your letter No.3219-4/26 dated the 6th October, 1947. I have received the sun of Rs.940. 0.0, sent by you for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being sent to the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. Political Agent O /o Copy with the original receipt is Betwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.4r * *No. 3?C^O - 4/26 Political Agency, Bahrain, To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Memo rand lain. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the 113 th ^onth after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh f s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, , and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. Bahrain for Political Agent, Bahrain.Translation of le^er Nol200 dated the 9th December, 1947, from the POTC., Sharjah, to the P.A., Bahrain. Reference your'letter No.3542-4/26, dated the Pth November, 1947. 4 by you for payment to the Ruler of Dij^ai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being sent to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Cory with the original receipt is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No - &amp;Z -4/^r Political Agency, Bahrain, The f j k.- y 194 To The Political Officer vJ-L jL U X d-L VX i. X U 1 ^ Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only in a sealed bag for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the HAV month after the agreement dated the 6 th June, 1938. 2 . Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Translation of letter No.79, da + ed the 19th January, 1948, from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Reference your letter No.3844-4/26, dated the 10th December, 1947. I have received the sum of fc.940/- sent by you for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf After Compliments, Usual Ending. Copy, with the original receipt, is forwardedNo - 17 $ . 4 / 26 . Political Agency, Bahrain, The -jlz February t 194 8. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Memorandum. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only far pi aeal&amp;d -hag- for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the 115 th ^onth after the agreement dated the 6th June, 1938. 2. Please forward the Shaikh's receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian a C0 P7 ^he forwarding letter to me. Bahrain for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 1 a with reference to India Office telegram No^. 1187 dated tne Ssrn ’ June, 1938.► * I NC.S3/-4/26. ■f Political Agency, Bahrain, The ?iarch f 1948 0 I To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Shar.iah. Memorandnin. I am sending herewith a sum of Rs. (940) nine hundred and forty only for payment to Shaikh Said Bin Maktoom, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai on account of Dubai Civil Air Agreement for the ilfcth month after the agreement dated the 6 th June, 1938. i 2 . Please forward the Shaikh f s receipt direct to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and a copy of the forwarding letter to me. Bahrain, t foj^Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, j.^hrain, with reference to India Office telegram No.1187 dated the 28th June, 1938.* t Translation of letter No.184, dated the 4th M^rch, 1948, from the Political Officer, Truclal Coast, Sharjah, to the Political A^ent, Bahrain. After Compliments, Reference vour letter No.375—4/86, dated the 7th February, 1948. I have received the sum of Rs.Q40/- sent by you for the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herev/ith a copy of his receipt. The original is being sent with to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Nsual Ending. Copy y with the original receipt^is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.4 / Translation of letter No.193, dated the 4th March, 1948, from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, to the Political Apent, Bahrain. After Compliments, Reference your letter No.62-4/26, dated the 10th January, 1948. I have received the sum of Rs.940/- sent by you for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being sent to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Usual Ending. # Copy with the original receipt is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.*i * ^ 4t ^ I I ^j£■ ^ J (_&gt;&gt; **J L-^l) I I Residency A^ent, Sharjah, the sum of fc. Q 40/- being the rent of the Civil Marine Base at Dubai creek for the 114th month after the Agreement. I received the amount for the period from 22nd December, 1947, to the 22nd January, 194ft. Received from Mr. Jasim bin Muhammad, &gt; 0 ^ ^ Si'id bin Maktum, ( Seal )Translation of letter No.284, dated the 25th March, 1948, from the POTC., Sharjah, to the P.A., Bahrain. after Compliments, Reference your letter No.831-4/26, dated the 14th March, 1948. I have received the sum of .940/- sent by you for payment to the Ruler of Dubai. I have paid the amount to him and I enclose herewith a copy of his receipt. The original is being sent to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Usual Ending. Copy with the original receipt is forwarded with compliments to the Secretary to the Hon’ble the y Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1144</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1144</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/26 II Payments of Rs 940/- on a/c of Dubai civil air agreement.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T11:50:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (165 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes, folios 161-166. Circled serial numbers in ink (red for incoming, blue/black for outgoing correspondence) refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 167; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 1-166; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains records of payments by the Political Agent, Bahrain to Shaikh Said bin Maktoom [Saʻīd bin Maktūm Āl Maktūm], Ruler of Dubai, under the terms of the Dubai Commercial Air Agreement, 1938. Under the terms of the agreement, the Ruler of Dubai was to receive 940 rupees per month for 'rent of Civil Seaplane Base'. The records cover payments for the period November 1944 - March 1948 inclusive. Payments were made through the Residency Agent, Sharjah, and the Political Officer, Trucial Coast (POTC), Sharjah; original receipts were to be forwarded to the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.The papers include: covering letters for the payments, sent by the office of the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, and the Political Officer, Trucial Coast; letters in Arabic (with English translations) from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, and letters from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, confirming payment to the Ruler of Dubai; and copies of receipts in Arabic (with English translations) issued by the Ruler of Dubai.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Airfields</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>