<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:30:38.628Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FILE NO: 16 V.Q. IMPERIAL AIRWAYS REST HOUSE AT SHARJAH. £ File No. 16'. V.O!4 ihx h y s- T : if i i^Jb^Aj^ \ l-jL^ij^U ix o^Jn Ul. vi y'J V^«J l*a._3 iCL^_j (j-j V^V^a^ (X^t i-V' '‘bOi^^- iv^u is ! , I ) Translation of letter No.386 dated tne 10th Dhul Hijjah 1353 (i.e. 15.3.1935) from Shaikh Sultan bin Sa^r, Ruler of Sbarjah to Colonel Loch, Political Agent,Bahrain. After Compliments, On the occasion of our f Id I send you my best congratulations ana hope that we all may enjoy happy returns every year. Our friend T Abdullah bin Paris, is going to see you and he will inform you verbally of whatever I have to say. Usual Ending. liIMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD HELIOPOLIS AERODROME, HELIOPOLIS EGYPT Telephone: 62293/4/5 Telegrams . AIRWAYS, CAIRO Codes. BENTLEY’S &amp; LATA. /^/1130 Sharjah 3rd April:i937 Dear Col. Loch, I am sorry to have to inform you of an unfortunate incident which took place here on the ni£ht of 31st 'larch and which in a sense is partly the fault of our Wireless Officer being somewhat careless with the custody of cash. On the night in question we had three aircraft on the ground and everybody was extremely busy. The Wireless Operator left his office at 7 p.m# after the last machine had landed and definitely remembers seeing his cash box in his desk at that hour. When he returned to duty at 4 a.m* the next morning he noticed that it had gone. After completing his work he came and reported the matter to me. The cash box contained the exact sum of Rs.680 and as it happened the bulk of this amount was made up of Rs.536 received in settlement of a telegram despatched by Major Holmes and paid for that day. immediate access to the 'ireless Office, as they were in the habit of taking in early tea etc.etc. to the Operators I immediately closed the Fort and with the aid of six guards had a thorough search made of all servant’s quarters having described my loss to the guards as a small black metal box. This search having proved fruitless I immediately comiTunicated with the Residency Agent here as it was evident that with the Fort open that night various other people employed in refuelling etc. were coming and going within the premises. The Residency Agent immediately came up on receipt of my advice and I put the entire matter before him and told him of the action I had already taken. I told him that in my opinion I held as first suspects a man Abdul Rahman who acted as telegraph peon but who was not in the direct pay of the Company, another servant Abbas Kanar who belongs to Sharjah and who I knew to be in debt and a further servant whom I thought might know where the cash was kept. All these three suspects had more or less acknowledged access to In view of the fact that certain servants hadIMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD HELIOPOLIS AERODROME, HELIOPOLIS EGYPT Telephone: 62293/4/5 Telegrams: AIRWAYS, CAIRO Codes: B ENTLEY’S &amp; I A.TA. (ID to the Wireless Office. I strongly suspected Abdul Rahman as he was continually in and out of the Office with telegrams and furthermore actually saw the cash paid by Major Holmes and which was all in silver, being checked. When the Residency Agent arrived and I told him of my thoughts in the matter he immediately asked me where the A.I.0.0. Petrol Tally Clerk was that night and I told him that he had been at the Port and had been engaged in refuelling until about 9 p.m. He then told me that this man and also Abdul Rahman were bad characters and asked me the position with regard to the liberty the former enjoyed up here. I of course immediately realised that this tally clerk was also a very definite suspect as he had free access to the Office for despatch of A.T.O.C. telegrams and other minor enquiries in connection with aircraft arrivals, and was bound to have seen telegrams and cash being received. Furthermore when the Residency Agent informed me that both these men were relations and incidentally were also related to Hosein, the A.I.O.C. Agent, my suspicions were further aroused. The Tally Clerk always carried a small attache case in which he carried his petrol receipt books and which, often as not on busy nights he left in my office to allow the Engineer to sign in the morning when aircraft work v/as finished. On the night in question he took this case with him and it was evident to me that the cash box could have been taken out in this case without being noticed, whereas its weight would have prevented anyone carrying it easily under their arm without possible detection by the guards. When we had discussed the question fully the Residency Agent left for Sharjah to investigate the matter and returned in about three hours with Rs. 652 in silver v/hich he told me he had found in of the tally clerk, the former h from the aerodrome on Wednesday The Sheikh also was with the Res when the discovery was made. On evident to me that, as this petro know something of the manner in out their work as he was in the the house of the mother aving stated that it was brought night for payment to Hose in. idency Agent and was present the face of things it seems 1 clerk was almost bound to which our Operators carried Fort till a late hour, as he'mm. © Cf IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD HELIOPOLIS AERODROME, HELIOPOLIS EGYPT Telephone: (&gt;129Z/4?l5 Telegrams: AIRWAYS, CAIRO Codes: BENTLEY’S &amp; LATA. ((HI) took away his attache case and as he was known to have gone round somewhat exitedly asking for the Station Engineer to sign his papers so that he might leave, he definitely was a man who could easily have committed the theft without detection and one whose exit and entry to the Port would not be specially noted by the guards. Also these latter inform me that this clerk went round the East side of the Port that night instead of by the shorter way through the compound. Now that practically all the money has been found in this clerks possession there would seem to be little doubt as to who the actual thief was, but as the Residency Agent has taken up the matter in a very capable way and has given me every confidence that the matter is being properly investigated I have left the question entirely in his hands and advise you of the incident from what I know of circumstances on the night when the cash was stolen. I feel very much indebted to. Khan Sahib Abdul Razaq for the prompt assistance he has given me and trust that a satisfactory outcome will be forthcoming. Unfortunately I am not always aware of the characters of some of the men who come into this Port and can assure you that had I known as much of the petrol Agents as I do now no member of that staff would have been allowed the liberties which we all extended to them here. I am extremely sorry to have to trouble you over this matter but feel it is best to put the whole question before you as it is of a very serious natureand quite beyond my control. With kind regards to Mr; .Loch and yourself. Lt. Col. G. Loch, Political Agent, Bahrein. Yours SincerelyBritish Agency, Sharj ah, 3rd April 1937. \ I The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. I beg to report that on Friday the 2nd April 1937 at 3 p.m. the station Superintendent, Imperial Airways Limited, oharjah, reported to me that late on Wednesday night some one got into the Wireless Office and removed a black cash tin box from tfeere. The box had Rs.680/-. The Superintendent searched every one in the forst but was not able to trace the money. The Station superintendent suspected that the theft was committed by two of the Rest House servants, 'Abbas and Muhammad. He also had a strong suspcion against 'Abdur Rahman(cousin of K.S.HusainJ Wireless peo^n, who is not paid by the Imperial Airways but has been kept, as a matter of courtesy to Khan ^ahib Husain and a fee of As.l/- has been fixed for him which he gets on each telegram he takes to Dubai. 2. On getting the Superintendent's report, I immediately went to the A e st House. From inquiries made by me from the Superintendent and also of seeing myself, Muhammad Ka/jjih(cousin of Husain; the Clerk-in-Charge of refuelling used to enter freely into their offices even when no one used to be there. Muhammad Hajjih was wprking in Lingah for the Persian Government and was sentenced for one year's imprisonment and then sent away from Lingah^and^ came to Sharjah five years ago where he has been working for Khan Sahib Husain in the refuelling. Muhammad Hajjih is- 2 - a loose character person, opium smoker and drunker* Muhammad Hajjih is also heavily indebted in the market to various people* Xs 'Abdur Rahman bin *Ali , the telegraph peo^n is also a |relative of Muhammad Haijjih, I had strong suspicion against both of them and also 'Abbas who is a very intimate friend of Muhammad hajjih. 'Abbas was detained in the Rest House but 'Abdur Rahman was away at Dubai and also i^uhammad Rajjih, the first took telegrams and the second *ent to Dubai for enjoyment* I therefore, went to the bhaikh and requested him to search the houses of these three persons in my presence* Muhammad Hajjih had two houses, one in which he lives with his prostitudfe and the other in which his mother lives* Before search was made, a man was kept at the door of each house sofas to prevent anything being taken out. we searched the first three house but nothing was found. We then searched the house in which Muhammad Hajjih lives with his mother and found one of the huts locked, we asked his mother about the keys and she# said they were with her son at Dubai. The door was forced in and the search was acrried in the presence of the Shaikh and myself* A suit kxxs box was also locked and the mother^that the keys were with her son. The locg; was broken and a sum of Ks.400/- in cash was found in^piece of cloth* As soon as the money was taken out, the mother, who was standing with us, said of her own accord ' He(Muhkmmad Hajjih; brought this money last night from the aerodrome, ^^Lng the cost of petrol and oil, and had no time to give it Hajji Ya'qubCcousin of Husain 'Amadiand his Clerk; '. Another small wooden cash box was also found in the hut below the bedstead, in which a sum of ns.252/- was also found. The mother again remarked* this was part of Muhammad Hajjih's pay* To give no chance to Khan Sahin Husain or Hajji Ya’qub to make /- 3 - ® 7 make false entries in their accounts about the money found I went to Khan Sahib Husain and aksed him to show me his daily cash account. Befor examining the book , 1 asked him whether Muhammad Hajjih was authorised to sel^ petrol or oil on his behalf or receive money on that account to which Husain replied 'No* I then asked him if had sent Muhammad Hajjih to recover any money for him and he replied * No 1 . I then asked him about Muhammad Hajjih's pay and he said •Rs-BO/- 1 I asked • him a&amp;so if Muhammad Hajjih did take any advance against his pay and if A how much. He said that on 1st April in the morning he took ds •3/-. I last asked him if he had sent any money with Muhammad Hajjih to pay to anyone.and he replied no. 3 * I then took the money to the Station Superintendent and asked him to keep it in deposit with him until further orders from you^ 1 a&amp;so asked the Shaikh of Sharjah to detain both ‘Abdur Rahman and Muhammad Hajjih as soon as found. As Muhammad tiajjih was away at JJubai, I immediately went there and asked the Shaikh to arrest him and send him to Sharjah He was arrested at about 12 p.m. and in the morning ofi Saturday was sent to Sharjah. HlAbdur Rahman was detained at the aerdrome with the guards when he came back from Dubai in the evening and was taken to Shaikh^s prison in the morning. Both Muhammad Hajjih and ’Abdur Rahman are now detained in the Shaikh's prison. There is nothing to prove against 'Abdur Rahman except the suspcion that he is cousin of Muhammad -ttajjih and from his statement he appears to be innocent. 'Abdur Rahman stated that Muhammad Hajjih went to his house when he was awav on Tuesday night at Dubai with telegrams/and asked his(Abdur Rahman's; wife to lend him one rupee and she could not do so as she had no money© Muhammad Hajjih admits this and also that he took an advance of As •3/- against his pay from Khan Sahib Husain. Raving realized that he was arrested on account of a theft at the aet drome he said that he had about Rs.400/— in his mother's house /-4- ivC house which saved from his pay* Khan Sahib Husain ’Amad A told me that Muhammad Hajjih was heavily indebted to many people in the market and that he has been deducting part of his pay for payment to the creditors of Muhammad Hajjih* Muhammad Hajjih also admitted that he hagf.no money and that he was indebted and could not afford to p&amp;y and that Husain was paying on his beh&amp;Lf* 4 , Taking into account his past history and the fact that he has been indulging in vice and indebted to several people, it was not possible to believe his an after thought statement that he saved Rs.400/- while he admitted that he could not afford to pay his debts. Muhammad Hajjih who v/as ignorant about the search and the money found in his house, told me in his first statement that he did not have a single pie. He also did not give any explanation about the ^8.250/- found in the same hut. 5. Taking the above into consideration and the|fact that his mother had admitted before the Shaikh and myself that her son brought the money on the night the theft was committed and said that it was for n ajji Ya^ub, which statement was not corerect, establishes beyond doubt that the theft was actually committed by him and that he has failed to give a satisfactory explanation as to how he got the money. Both the Shaikh and myself, are satisfied that the money was stolen by Muhammad Hajjih© 6. I therefore beg to suggest that a deterent action is necessary in such case, and subject to your approval, the Shaikh may be asked to (a) give him 30 lashes publiclyCb) imprison him for one year and(c) deport him to Iran after completion of the sentence. Also tha su^pf Rs.28/- which have been spent by him from the amount^may be recovered by sale of his effects© 5 LjrUtA 7 I should be grateful to know of your orders about kxmx these two persons, f Abdur Rahman and Muhammad. RtsuftSCY AGENT' SHARGAH'© ^ TELEGRAM - G.T.Code. From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Residency iigent, Sharjah. No. - lt&gt;8. Dated - Ibth April 1937. lour memorandum of 3rd April No.0/283. Punishment in paragraph 6 approved but you should not specify number of strokes. -POLITICAL- i r10 V No.132-B/lo. To, The Itesiaency Agent, Sih,RJAH. V- Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th April 1^37. Kiemoranaum * in continuation oi my telegram No.lbB uated the 16th iipril 1937, I liave eiio./n your memorandum Uo.G/363- 10/1 dated the 3rd April 1937 about the theft at the Airways Station to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gull. 2. The punishment recommenced in paragraph 6 is approvec, but you should not specify the number of strokes to be inflicted. 3. Both tne Honourable the Political Resident and i much appreciate your quick and successful action. 4. 1 am informing tne station Superintendent about the punishment of the thief, b. No action should be taken against f Abdur Rahman except that i am recommencing the ht&amp;tion Superintendent to employ another man as telegraph peon and enclose a copy of my letter to him No.l33-B/16 dated 16th April 1937. . // / C. Lieut-Uolonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.£ for Political Agent, Bahrain. No. C/154-B/16 Political Agency, Bahrain, the £4th April 1937. To The Residency Agent, 3 i l h. R J A H • Memorandum: 0 Vl,v - / w -‘ Reference correspondence ending v.ith my morandum No. 132-B/16 dated tne 16tn april 1937. Please report exactly v,hat relation the convict Muhammad Hajjih is to Khan Sahib Husain bin Hassan Amad and whether the case a£facts the suitability of the latter to be agent for the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company.Confidential .jr N 06 &amp; 73 - 10 / 1 . British Agency, Sharjah, 28th April 1937. To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. RECEIPT l^s . • 1 L &gt; Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.C/154-B/16 dated the 24th April 1937. 2. According to Khan Sahib Husain bin Hasan , Amad, Hajjih, the father of the convict Muhammad Hajjih, is the son of the paternal aunt of Khan Sahib Husain ‘Arnad. 3. On 25th April 1937 another offence was committed by the same family at the aerodrome. At about 10.00 hours on 25th April 1937, the Station Superintendent, reported to me that someone went behind the aerdrome and slip in the cash box,yhich was rolled in a shirt and in which the money was kept when the previous theft took place, between the matting of the wall of the hut of the cook of the aerodrome. I went there at once and saw the place. Having realized that the object was to throw the blame on the employees of the Rest House, I asked the Station Superintendent to keep the matter quiet , so that 1 may be able to disover who was responsible for the action. Yesterday evening everything came to light and I was able to discover that nine persons either directly or indirectly were connected in this offence, including Khan Sahib Husain and his cosuin Hasir bin 'Abdul Latif. It was proved by the evidence of his mother, wife(prostitute) and other friends whom he asked to take the box to the aerodrome that it was done by Muhammad -^-ajjih in order to show to the people that it was discovered in the aerodrome and that he was innocent of the theft committed at Rest House. A letter was also found on Muhammad Shafi^who hired a Baluchi from Hira village, instructing him what to do, from Muhammad n ajjih with his own hand writing in which he says that as soon as2 - the action of throwing the box at the aerdrome taken, he will be released. The person who actually stuck the cash box between the matting of the hut is hiding and could not be traced y and his arrest has not yet been effected. The mother of Muhammad Hajjih has been detained in the Shaikh's house while Muhammad Shafi, the person who went to Hira and arranged ^ with a Baluch,'Abdullah Husain, to take the box to the aerdrome is detained in Shaikh's prison. I am sending a full report about this by the next mail. Residency Agent,Sharjah k t*fot/?. No.480-10/1* British Agency, Sharjah, 15th May ly37o Memorandum# To The Political Agent, Bahrain# In continuation of my letter No#373-10/1 dated the 28th April 1937, I beg to report as follows After the sentence approved by you in your letter N0.132-B/16 dated the 16th April 1937, Khan Sahib Husain and the rest of his family members began to circulate rumoures that Muhammad Hajjih was innocent of the crime and that an injustice was done to him# 2# At 9.30 a.ra. on 25th April 1937, fche Station Superintendent reported to me that Rasul, the cook of the Rest House, went to him with the cash box,^.n which the money was stolen from the Wireless Office, and stated that his (coo^s) son, a child, found it stuck in the matting of his hut situated behind the Rest House# I immediately went to the place and saw it. Having realized that it was done with the intent (a) to throw the blame on Rasul and (,b) that the discovery of the box so placed night be used in evidence in a protest against the sentence passed against Muhammad Hajjih, I asked the Station Superintendent, in order that I may disover the person responsible,thhat he should keep the matter quiet and show no interest in it# I did not also inform the Shaikh lest the information may leak out and the offenders take their precautions. On 27th April 1937, I got information that Nasir bin 1 Abdul Latif went to the Majlis of Shaikh Saif bin kadfa', the Qadhi, on 26th and 27th April# He did not say anything on 26th but on 27th he said that the cash box was found in the house of Rasul, the cook of the Rest House and that Muhammad Hajjih /Hajjih was gping to be released being innocent of the offence of theft which was discovered at the Rest House. I at once informed the Shaikh of Sharjah and showed him the place. We then came to the Agency and called two respectable persons, Shaikh Ghulam Abbas Lari and Hajji kukhtar Jusbani, and in their presence called JMasir bin 1 Abdul Latif, who claims to be a subject of Sharjah, and recorded his statement. He said that he heard from Khan sahib Husain , Amad when they were dining veMt f Abdur Rahman bin Husain's house on 26th. Khan Sahib Husain was then asked as to how he got information about the box and he said that he heard it from the head cooly working for him in the refuelling who happened to be at the aerdrome when the box was found. Further inquiries led us to believe that the offence was committed by the same family. The wife of Muhammad Hajjih was then called and she stated that Fatimah, the mother of the convict, went to her and asked her, for the sake of Muhammad Hajjih, to take t the box to'the aerdrome and place it somewhere near the huts. Mas'udah, the wife of Muhammad Hajjih refused to do this unless if she was accompanied by Fatimah. Fatimah told Mas'uddh that she could not go with her as the people knew her, but that as kas'udah was a slave woman she could go^ dressed in ragged clothes, to the Falaj(water-hole) as if she would bring firewood and remain there until it wads dark. That when it wad dark, she could take the box and place it near the huts without being suspected by anyone. Mas'udah declined to do so uhless she was acc^ipanied by her. Fatimah was then called and asked about the statement made by kas'udah and she admitted that she asked kas'udah. Fatimah also admitted that skn Muhammad Sa'idCone of the refuelling coolies and cousinx of Muhammad Sharif from whom Khan Sahib Husain stated that he heard the news) few days after the sentence was passed against her son Muhammad ^ajjih, ax^xaxkadxkiia went to her and asked her to give him the ' Article' v/ithout specif lyingit so that he throw it at the aerodrome* She stated that A as she was not confident of his statement she told him to go back to Muhammad fiajjih and ask him what it was. Muhammad Sa’id then went to her A asked her to give him the box and she told him that she was going to send it with one ^bdul *Aziz walad Jan^adar, a servant of the Shaikh of Sharjah* Muhammad Hajjih then sent 1 Abdul *Aziz walad Jamadar to his mother Fatimah. 'Abdul 'Aziz asked Fatimah to have the box ready so that he could take it , but that he went away and did not go to her again. Fatimah then went to 'Abbas Ghulam, who was employed in the Best House, and asked him to take the box and place it at the aerodrome, but he refused to do so* Fatimah then went to Muhammad Shafi and told him that her son Muhammad hajjih wanted him and that he could do so when he is taken out of the fort for abihution. Muhammad Shafi then went to Muhammad Hajjih and undertook to him to arrange for i£&lt; the box to be placed at the Rest House in a prominent place* On 24th exEHxxg Muhammad Shafi went to Hira village and arranged with a Baluchi begger, by name 'Abdullah Husain, to place the box as required and that he was going to pay him Rs.2/- for the work* After sun set, Muhammad Shafi went to -^atimah and took the box which was dug out from the same hut in which the money were found* 'Abdullah Husain slept the night in the house of Muhammad Shafi who L ave him ihe box to take to the aerdrome early on the morning of 25th ^pril 1937* 'Abdullah Husain then took the box and placed it as instructed. 'Hbdullah Husain then returned to Muhammad Shafi and informed him of his action and after taking break fast returned to Hira*. 3* Muhammad ^a'id denied that he had any connection. 'Abdul 'Aziz Jamadar denied any knowledge. Mas'udah W/0 convict .admitted that she was asked but refused to do it unless she was accompanied by Fatimah. ' Abbas Ghulam admitted that he was asked but that refused to do so.V 4- /P Muhammad Sfaafi admitted and produced a note written by Muhammad ^ajjih the convict telling how to act and asking him to do the work for him so that he may be released* He also stated that he went to Hira and araanged with.Jilbdullah Husain, to take the box and place^at the hut and that although he promised to give him Hs«2/- he gave him six annas only* At*time of the inquiries Muhammad Shafi disappeared and although the Shaikh said that his men searched for him and could not find him even at Ajman, was arrested by one of the Agency guards at day break when he was running away from Sharjah to Hira* f Abdullah Husain has not yet been arrested as he could not be found* The case is a clear one of trying to screen the offender and to mislead the people to believe that the theft was committed by the people of the aerdrome* xhe principal offenders are s- 1* Muhammad Hajjih, the convict* 2* i^atimah, mother of the convict* 3* Muhammad Shafi 1 and 4. * Abdullah Husain* 5* As Muhammad Hajjih is already undergoing a sentence of one year's imprisonment and deportation on completion of the sentence, I do not think we need to take further action against him. Fatimah being the ^ther of the convict, she has acted jointly with them in order to help her son and as she is old I suggest that she be released with a warning* Muhammad Shafi, however, may subject to your approval be kept in prison for three months and then sent away to Iran He has no house or family here* 'Abdullah Husain may be giver similar sentence to that inflicted on ths Muhammad Shafi whenever he is arrested* Residency Agent,Sharjah.r No.T/lV.B/ 16 . Of lice of tne Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp, Sharjah. Dated, tne 29th May 1907. To, The Residency Agent, Sharjcn. Memorandum. Reference your memorandum No.480-10/1 dated th 15th May 1937• 2, Five rnontns 1 imprisonment approved for Muhammat Shali T and one year lor ! Abdullan Husain waen arrested. Cap tain, Political Agent, Bahrain,No.548-6/1 British -agency, Shar j ali, 27th August 1939. To, The Politicsl agent, Bahrain. Memorandum I beg to enclose herewith copies of the following correspondence, for your information:- 1. Letter No.SHA* 1/1988 dated 17th August 1939 from the Station Superintendent,Sharjah. 2&lt;&gt; Letter (with translation) No .528 dated the 19th August 1939 equivalent to the 2nd xiajab 1358 from the Residency Agent, to the Shaikh of Sharjah. 3. Leocer .uOo*5 105 dated the 8th Rajab x358(i.e. 24th August 1939) from the Shaikh of Sharjah to the Residency Agent,Sharjah. 4Copy of letter Uo.SHA* 1/1988 dated the 17th robust 1939 from the Station Superintendent, Imperial Airvays Limited,Sharjah to the Residency Agent,Sharjah. Dear Sir, For about a year now we have had a red fabric covered canoe on the bank of the creek by the ruined tower, but in the last week or so the canoe has disappeared. It, was always kept well above high tide level, and I do not consider it could possibly have been washed away. Vould you please ask the Shaikh of Sharjah to see that it is retiirned? Yours faithfuuly, • Sd: Stephen Broad, For Imperial Airways Limited*Translation of letter No.106 dated the 8th Ragab 1358(i*e. 24th ^'August 1939) from Shaikh sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah to the Residency A^ent,Sharjah. Afuer Comp1iments, I received your kind!:, letter No.528 dated the 2nd Rajab II 1358 equivalent to the 19th August 1939 and noted its contents . regarding the canoe. I made thorough enquiries and found it across the bank opposite the place in which it was kept being washed away by the wsuer and left, for the children io play with it as no one was looking after it. I request you to inform the Station Superintendent,Sharjah, that he should not neglect their belongings at a place which is far away from the town and not frequented by the people. I shall not be responsible for such things which are not necessary for the Company's operations©For your information© Usual Endingi No.644-8/1. TO, ■ &amp; British Agency, Sharjah, 26th August 1939 • \ The Bt^tion Superintendent, Imperial Airways Limited, Sharjah# &gt; „ Dear Sir, Reference your letter No#SHA#Vi988 dated the 17th August 1939# 2# The Shaikh of Sharjah informs me uhai he found your canoe across the bank of the creek oppoiste xhe place in which had kept it it being washed away by the water* He S£ys that the Ccnoe was kept at a place far away from the town which is not frequented by thepeople without a care taker* The Shaikh asks that you /mw should be more careful about your belongings in the future for he would nfct be responsible for such things which are not necessary for the Company’s operations* Yours faithfully, Sdi A.Razzaq Residency Agent,Sharjah* (i \ \ Uo.482-10/3. British agency, yharjah, 19th August 1940 To, Memorandum The Political Agent, Bahrain. I beg to enclose herewith copies of the marginally Letter No.126 dated 10th Rajah 1359 (i#e. 15.8.40) from the Shaikh of Sharjah Letter No.475-10/3 dated 16.8.40 from the Residency agent to the station Superintendent, BO.A.C.Sharjah. Letter ho.SHA/i/C-6/1064 dated 16.8.40 from the Station 5uperintendent,Sharjah. Letter No.127 dated 13th Rajah 1359 (i.e.18.8.40) from the Shaikh of Sharjah. Letter No.480-10/3 dated 18.8.40 from the Residency Agent to the Station SuperintendentJ Sharjah. | I Letter No.SHA/i/C-6/1073 dated 19.8.40 | from the station Superintendent,Sharjah JL was his brother f lsa. cited correspond ence for your information. 2. Ibrahim bin Muhammad al Madfa* is the clerk of the Shaikh of Sharjah. The person with him when he wanted to send the parcel Residency Agent,Sharjah,o Translation of letter No.126 dated the 10th Rajah 1359U.e.15th August 1940) from Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr,Ruler of Sharjah, to the Residency Agent,Sharjah. After Compliments f I beg to inform you that today before noon, Ibrahim bin Muhammad al Madfa* went to the Rest House with 4W tin# of pearls X, , containing^parcels/for despatch by air. The clerk asked him to open the said parcels so that he may examine them. One of the clerks went out of the Office and the other remained in Office to examine the paxMiHxxhxgfrxg pearls. After examining the two parcels he opened the third parcel# which contained Na'mah big (seed pearls) and two/Danas (big) of pearls. V/hen he opened the parcel, the clerk put his hand inside it and suddenly removed it and went outside the Office as though to answer a call from his companion who went out. The owner of the pearls looked for the two pearls but could not find except one. The clerks then came back from optside and asked him( Ibrahim) whether he intend ed to send the goods. He replied that one pa&amp;rl had been stolen from it. They denied the allegation whereupon he left them and came to report the matter to me. The pearl in question weighs three and a half rattis and one anna m seven and a quarter chaus and two dokras. Its purchase price being Rs.600/-. I request you to do what you consider fit so as to recover the pearl in question from the said clerk for which act I shall remain very grateful. Usual Endings.Copy of letter No.SHk/I/c- 6/1064 dated 16th August 1940 from the Station superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation,Sharjah to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Dear Sir, Thank you for your letter of the 16th instant, reference JMo•475—10/3 and for the translation of the shaikh's letter upon the above subject, which it covered. I have carefully enquired into this matter, which formed the subject of a discussion between ourselves on the evening of the 15th instant, and I enclose herewith a signed statement made by -the two clerks directly concerned in the matter. Yours faithfully, Sd: B.L.Nelson Statement by B.O.A.C.Cleik upon the incident in connection with an alleged missing pearl. On the morning of the 15th instant, two persons came into the office with an unsealed tin of pearls which they wished to dKKgsafcx despatch by air to Bombay. I asked them to open the tin for inspect ion according to the usual custom. Inside were three bundles, one of fairly large pearls, another of medium sized ones and the third of ver very small ones. After I had finished my inspection in their presence by stirring the contents of the bundles with my finger, and had satisfied myself that there was nothing other than pearls contained therein, I asked them to seal the tin. Mr.D'Sylva, who had gone dut of the office to the Wireless Room to confirm the Aircraft's Load Message, called me whilst passing the door on his way to the Station Superintendent's Office, and told me to accept the consignment, but to keep it apart, as no load was available on that day's machine. Within ten seconds I returned to the room having been a bare six paces from the door, to inform the Consignors that the parcel could not be sent that day, but I found that the Consignor and his companion were in the idst of a heated argument, upon the conclusion of which, they told me that a big pearl was missing which they said was contained in the bundle of the very small pearls. I taidx did not see any large pearls among the small ones, each bundle was definitely of separate grades. When Mr.D'Sylva returned fxjaaa to the Office some three minutes later, 1 told him of this statement, and he asked them tomake sure of it, whereupon they opened all their bundles and searcl -ed them, their pockets, and their belongings, they also went throi through the letters of advice which are always enclosed with rbx consignments of pearls, after which they left the office with the parcel without any further comments to us, though still arguing between themselves• The Station Superintendent had Already left for Dubai by this time, so the incident could not be reported to him until he returned from the Srvice, though in his absence Abdulla Bin Fares called to see him in connection jf(?th the matter, accompanied by the Consignor who is also his Agent* The whole matter was duly reported to the Station Super intendent upon his return from Dubai* Witness: •. D'Sylva Local Traffic Assistant. Sd. G.C.Sen Gupta Cashier and Accounts Clerk Sharjah, Dated: 17th August 1940*No. 480 -10/3. British Agency, Sharjah, 18th August 1040 To, The Station Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Sharjah. \ Dear Sir, f Beference corresp«3ndence resting with your letter No.SHA/1/C'•6/1064 dated the 16th August 1940, I enclose herewith copyCin translation) of letter Nc.lL&gt;7 dated the 13th Rajah 1369 (i.e. 18th August 1940) which X have just received. Sds A.Razzaq Residency Agent,Sharjah.Translation of letter Ho.l&amp;7 dated the 13th Rajab 1369Ci.e.l8th August 1940) fTon Sheikh sultan bin Saqr,Ruler of Sliarjah to tl»e Residency A^ent,Sharjah. After Compli/nente | With reference to my letter ho.126 Xxfesg dated the 13th Hfijab 1369(1.e. 16th August 1940&gt; on the subject of the pecs*! stolen by the cleric of the Rest House. Certain evidences heve come out which proves thr&lt;t the complaint made by Ibrahim bln Muhammad al Madfa’ is true. This clerk had done similar acts several times before and th»re are witnesses. Besides,the said clerk had no right to inspect the pearls with his own hand nor v to leave the Office at that time. You should, therefore, arrest him, have him tried criminally end all his belongings searched. Ibrahim also accuses the other clerk,D*sylva, who v/as with him outside the Office as being hia partner in this embeMleraent and that he should be searched as well. I am confident that you will do this and take out the pearl from the said person. Usual Endings.(° r\ Copy of letter No.SHA/l/C-6/1073 dated the 19th August 1940 from the station .Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation to the Residency Agent,Sharjah. dear Sir, Thank you for your letter ho.480-10/3 of the 18th instant, which ± received at 9.30 p.m. last night, together with the enclosure, a translation of the Shaikh's letter Wo.127. your letter, I called upon you and suggested we should invite the Shaikh and his Minister,Abdulla Bin Bares to accompany us to the Fort for one purpose of making a surprise search of the belongings of the two clerks, against whom the charges have be preferred. in our joint presence Abdulla Bin Fares carried out a thorough search of all Jhe belongings of both Clerks, which failed to produce any evidence whatsoever in connection with the charges. I wr'ite to confirm that immediately upon receipt of The Shaikh and his Minsiter duly accompanied us, and Yours faithfully, Sds B.L.Nelson111 uiuyjfw © ii No#1747 Political Agency, Bahra in, 16 th Sep tember. 1940• To The Residency Agent, Sharjah * Memorandum* Reference your ?’emorandum ^0.482-10/3 dated the 39th August 1940. 2. Would you please obtain from the Station Superintendent his copy of the advice notes for the parcels of pearls, and send them to nc: for my inspection. for Political Agent, -ahrain.(§) 1 ^- No.538-10/3 British Agency, Sharjah, 20th September 1940® To, The Political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandum Reference your memorandum No.1747 dated the 16th September 1940. 2. No advice notes were issued for the parcels of pearls in question which were immediately taken back by the consignor after alleging that one pearl was Blissing® Residency Agent,Sharjah.No.l882«ie/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. 6th October, 1940* To The Station Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation, ahar.lah. Dear t&gt;ir, Please refer to the correspondence resting with your letter No.SHA/l/C-6/1073 dated 19th August 1940 to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, concerning a complaint by one and Mr# D'Sylva two of your employees# 2* From the information before me I am forced to regard the case as most suspicious# Such complaints are not made without cause and pearl merchants do not make mistakes. Obviously however no proof can be obtained, the search having failed as it was bound to do# 3. The only course therefore is to take steps to ensure that the opportunity for such a complaint does not occur again# I should be grateful therefore if you would do this and let me know the action you have taken# Ibrahin bin MUhammad al Tfodfa* against Mr# G.C. Sen Gupta Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain# Copy to i- The Residency Agent, Sharjah, for information#BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS ( INVORfORATED IN GREAT RllITAIN ) AIRWAYS HOUSE KING GHAZI STREET BAGDAD Telegrams: Flying BagilaJ Codes i Bent I ey s 2nd Plirnse &amp; T A.T.A. Our Station Super in —has forwarded to me a copy of your letter No. 1822-10/3 of the 6th October, in the above connexion. I am extremely sorry to see that in your mind there still exists a certain amount of doubt as to culpability. Your letter gives me the impression that you regard our staff at Sharjah as not entirely free from guilt, and natur ally we are anxious to do all we can to dispel this impression. The object of this letter, therefore, is to assure you that our Sharjah staff involved in this incident will be made available for personal cross-examination by you, if you desire it. Would you please let us know whether there is any assistance which we can give you towards clearing this matter satisfactorily. IPG. 1/R. 9/4094 16th October, 1940 The Political Agent Bahrein. t ALLEGED PEARL THEFT Dear SirNo. 287 -A.0 Political Agency, Bahrain, 24th October 1940 To The Regional Director, British Overseas Airways, Baghdad. Subject: Allered Pearl theft at Shariah . Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. IPG.1/R.9/4094. dated 16th October 1940 on the above subject. There is no object in pursuing further enquiries so long after the event and,as I am sure you will agree,the obvious course is to take steps to ensure that oppotunity for such complaints does not occur. for Political Agent, Bahrain.DEPT. BRANCH. Section. Heading. Pros. NOTES. 19 ; Nos. Subject. Imperial Airways Rest House at Siiarjaii. : Notes and Orders. S.L MGIPC—81-1027 (CPS)MFP—(M.753)—24-8-34—6,00,000. FileNoB/l6. Serial No.% ' ‘ ; Letter N 9.386 aatea lotu Lhul Hijjah 1353(15.3.35) from Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr,Ruler of Sharjah. D P.A. You wanted this letter to be put up to you after the P.R. has left as-you may like to see f Abdullah bin F$ris, who is still in Bharain, For orders,please 0 ^ 21.3.35 P.A. T Abdullah bin Faris has been informed accordingly He will be coming today at the time fixed,please. 23.3.35 t h &lt;Hlf m On the 23rd March 1935 f Abdullah bln Faris came to see me. He brought messages from the Shaikh of Sharjah about three matters. 1. Emigrants from Sharjah to Ras al Rhaimah. He said that considerable numbers of people, about 500 In all, had left Sharjah and gone to Ras al Khaimah because they disliked having the/ImihattaCat Sharjah and the Shaikh was anxious lest the Government should blame him. He emphasised that the Shaikh was friendly to us and that he had a good deal of trouble ov/ing to the mahatta. I said that he had also made a great deal of profit from the^fekhattaC ’Abdullah bin Faris said that he had to make large payments to the bedouin to keep them quiet. We have a separate report that 80 people have gone to Ras al Khaimah and enquiries should be made on the next Trucial Coast, tour. 2. He said that the Shaikh would like the Post Office put in as soon as possible and that the question of rent for the house was left in my hands. I rather gather that they might give it free of rent.3. ssue draft. (£P. jOU Re: Barbed wire, (see C.O file 13/2) Diet 26-3-1935. Letter No.AT/5/1130 oated 3rci ,.april 1937 from Mr.A. ihomson, Station Superintenaent, I.A.Rest House,Snarjail. A.P.A. -Its seems that the Be sidency Agent, Sharjah, has taAen the necessary action in the natter. May keep penning receipt of a report from the R.A.-Sharjah pi- '.? c 5/rr ^ i ^ 5. Confidential Memorandum No.C/28S-10/l dated 3rd April 1937 from the Residency iigent, Sharjah.INDIA OFFICE Records</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1883</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1883</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File B/16 IMPERIAL AIRWAYS REST HOUSE AT SHARJAH’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-18T01:26:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (52 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 54; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Three additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 4-23, ff 24-30, and ff 31-43; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to three reported incidents at Sharjah Aerodrome, involving the servants, staff and property of Imperial Airways and its successor British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC). The three cases are: the investigation and conviction of refuelling clerk Muhammad Hajiih for the theft of cash from the Wireless Office in 1937; the search and recovery of a missing canoe belonging to Imperial Airways in 1939; the investigation of a complaint made in 1940 by Ibrahim bin Muhammad al Madfa’ the clerk of the Ruler of Sharjah and his brother Isa, a pearl merchant, against two clerks employed by BOAC, concerning the embezzlement of pearls entrusted to them for dispatch by air freight. The main correspondents are the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Residency Agent at Sharjah, Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr [Shaikh Sultan II bin Saqr Al Qasimi] the Ruler of Sharjah, and the airline’s Station Superintendent at Sharjah. Included in the correspondence is a witness statement made in 1940 by Mr G C Sen Gupta the BOAC Cashier and Accounts Clerk. There are both Arabic and English copies of the letters exchanged between the Ruler of Sharjah and the Residency Agent, Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Airways, Station Superintendent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Overseas Airways Corporation, Station Superintendent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Theft</topic></subject><subject><topic>Criminal investigation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>