<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000336_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:04:56.829Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">File copy Copies Circulated and copy to E. &amp; 0, SECRET DKCYPHEK OF TELBGRAM . Frora Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India* Dated Risher, 16.40 hours, 16th April, 1910„ XXX Received 17,10 hours, 16th April, 1940. 169* Following is repetition of Political Agent, Bahrain c s telegram No*104, April 14th. Begins * Following general instructions from Admiralty and Commander-in- Chief, East Indies^f^enior Naval Officer has arranged that Bahrain is to be main collecting and temporary detention (v port) for Danish and (’? Norwegian) ships in the Gulf, 8* Coramandei*-in-Chief, East Indies, apparently thinks civil authorities are responsible for detention and that they will have received instructions from His Majesty’s Government. 3° (? I have had) (V no such) instructions but have made arrangements in consultation with Senior Naval Officer in Persian Gulf and Bahrain Government. EndS o Presume orders 7/111 be issued in due course. RECd. POL. DEPr. 1 7 APR i940 INDIA OFFICE—</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000336_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/371</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000336</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/371</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 2216/40 'Bahrain to be main collecting and temporary detention port in the Persian Gulf: question of responsibility'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-09T12:47:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>The two letters are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 4; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a letter sent to the Secretary of State for India by Lieutenant-Colonel Charles Geoffrey Prior, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, on behalf of the Political Agent in Bahrain, and a draft reply. The subject of the correspondence is a question of whether or not Bahrain is to become the main collecting and temporary detention port in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Detention</topic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000336#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>