<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00026a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T06:43:11.162Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(V, 125f«l/3397/94) (TkAHSliATION). Ko, 428b/fl.l2. ITALIAN KiiBASay, U.NCON J 10th November, 1932. Sir, ith reference to my Note No*1179/B 20 of the 16th March last, I have the honour to communicate to Your Excellency the follov/ing:- 1. By a note-verbale of September 8, 1932 addressed to the Italian legation at Jedda, the Government of H,Mo to the International Institute of Hygiene of Baris requested to be admitted to participation in the expenses of administration of the Bureau of the Institute in category 5a instead of category 6a. 2. In accordance with Article 6 of the said Convention the Italian Government instruct me to notify the foregoing to His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom., and through them to His Majesty's Governments in Canada, the Commonwealth of Australia, the Union of South Africa, the Irish Free State, the Government of India and the Governments of the Sudan, Ceylon, Federated Malay States, the Gold Coast, Hong Kong, Kenya, Nigeria, Palestine, Sierra Leone, Straits Settlements, Tanganyika Territory, Uganda, Zanzibar and Trinidad. I shall be grateful if Your Excellency will be so good as to acknowledge the receipt of this communication the King of the Hejaz, Nejd and Dependencies, in part modification of their previous notification of accession in due course. I have, etc., (Signed) G. A1AMKLI The kight honourable oxr eTohn Sxmon, Cr.C.S.I. , l-.C.V.O. , M.B. , etc., etc. , etc.J • Ho. V 12568/3397/94 i ’. A. \ ■ FOREIGN OFFICE, S* 7.1. i g l8 t November, 193*.U-^ I 103 2 Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note No. 4285/B.12 of the 10th November in which you were so good ac to &amp;zaform me that the Government of His Majesty the Ring of the Hejaz* Nejd and Dependencies 0 in part modification of their previous notification of accession to the International Sanitary Convention of 1907, have now requested to be admitted to participation in the administrative expenses of the International Bureau of Public Health in category 5 a, instead of in category 6 a Q 2 0 This information will, as you request, be communicated without delay to the governments enumerated in Paragraph 2 of your note, with the exception of His Majesty 9 s Government in the Union of South Africa, with whom it is suggested that your govenimont should communicate direct through the Italian Minister in Pretoria or the Union Minister in Rome. I have the honour to be with high consideration. Sir 9 Your obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) Monsieur F 0 G* Marneli.■VPMHPHI r^s 930 (W 12368/3397/94) . -v -V.' V. -t i ^ORIilGN Ol^FlCK, 932 21st November. S^Walo 1932. Sir p With reference to my despatch No. 291 of the 15th April, regarding the accession of the Government of the He3az ? Ne,jd and Dependencies to the International Sanitary Convention of 190?^ I request that you will inform the Sudan Government that the Italian Government has notified His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom that the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd have now modified vheir notification of accession and. have requested to be placed in Claae £ a, instead of in Glass 6 a, for the purposes of contributing to the expenditure of the International Office of Public Health, under Article 11 of the Regulations annexed to the Convention Q 1 am 5 with great truth and regard,, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) Sir Percy Loraine, Bart,, K a C.M.Go» etc,, etc,, etc* 0 Cairo*Copy. (E 2356/103/i35) I j Q T o British. Embassy, ! Paris. 11th May, 1932. My dear Rendel, So far as I can ascertain the only subject discussed with the Hejaz Mission whicu might be of interest to us related to the Alexandria Quarantine Board. The Hejazis are chafing under the fact that the Board concerns itself with the pilgrimages and apparently wish, for reasons of amour-propre to have this put a stop to. The Prencn remained firm and maintained that it was in the interests of the Hejaz itself that the Board snould continue to occupy itself with the pilgrimages, since if it did not do so no one would have any faith in a Hejazi declaration. On one occasion moreover, the Board had to declare the pilgrimage clean after doubts had been raised in other quarters. 2. I do not know if this is of any interest to you, but I send it for what it is worth. Yours ever, (Signed) R. H. CAMPBELL. G. W* Rendel, Esq.., Foreign Office.(Tii^StATlUSk) N«.UTi/S.80. ftlr. / t ITUlAW hMBAiktf, \ UMIXJM. 2 4 44 il6th knroh, 1938. ' . In iulfllmeat oX Instructlone trm say Oavemrient 1 have tho honour to oofauunlcate to Your tixcellency the Xollowlaac 1. In a not* verbal* dated January 21st,1938.addreaeed to the Italian coniml at Jeddah,the Government of il» majesty the King of th* HeJaa.IieJd and dependenclea faade appllcntion to accede to the International danltary con vention signed at jiao* on aeceuber 9th,1907, tor the eetabllehment at Farls of an International durean of rtibllc Health, f ynd to contribute to the expenditure of thlt of Ice (category 6) uiu.er Article 11 of the Hegulatlone asme .ed to th* said Convention. 2. In accordance with Article 6 of the Convention in question.the Italian Government instruct me to notify the above-mentioned accession to Hie Britannic Majesty's Govemsent In the United Kingdom and,through them,to the Governments of Australia.Canada,the Union of Bouth Africa, the Irish Free Btate.lndia.uudon,Ceylon,the Federated Malay at*tes,th* Gold Coast,Hong Kong.Kenya,Nigeria, Palestljje.ulerra Leone,the Straits Battlements.Tanganyika Territory,Uganda, Bansibor and Trinidad. 3. I shall be grateful if Your Excellency sill kindly acknowledge th* present oonrunlcatlon In due course. Thanking you in anticipation for your courteous attention to the matter, 1 have, etc., The Bight Honourable (Signed) A.C.JkXiGuMAKO. Sir John Sitaon.G.C.n.l, .K.c.V.u.,Ho. \y 2397/8397/94. £3- &lt;'*' /' C. ”• T o POHFIOH OFFICK, 8.V*1. iBtb April, 195S. tour JSxoclleaoy, 1 hoTo the honour to eokrowletige the receipt of your note Ho. 1179/B* 80 of the 16th 25aroh lart In thloh Your Kyoellenoy v.ap eo good ae to Inforu rac that the Ooverxmcnt of Hie Hajecty the King of the Hole* ond Hejd and Ite Dependenoiee had cade application to accede to the International Sanitary Convention, rlgned at Rone on the 9th December, 1907 for the establlehment of on International Bureau of Public Health, and to be placed in Clef?e 6 ae regarde contribution* to the expenditure of thie office under Article 11 of the regulation* annexed to the Convention* 8. Further, I hove the honour to inform you that youi notification *111 be communicated in due course to the government* enumerated in paragraph 8 of your note under reference, with the exception of H1 b Majesty's Government in the Union of South Africa, vlth vhom it ie pugfsseted that your government ehould communicate direct through the Italian HlnUter at Pretoria, or the Onion Minirter at Rome, I have the honour to be, vlth the highest conrIderatlon, Your Kxcellenoy'e obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) Hie Excellency JsSon^ieur Antonio Bordonaro, G.B*v.,Ho* &lt;W 5397/5397/94) fow^ioh omcr. a.7.1, 15th April, 1952« Sir X request that you will Infora the Budan Government that the Italian Oovemaent haa notified His Haieety's Government in the United Kingdom that the Government of Hia i'&amp;i^ety the King of the Hejac and and its Dependenclee has made application to accede to the International Sanitary Convention, signed nt Koa© on the 9th December, 1907 for the estahli eh merit of an International Bureau of Public Health, end to he placed in Claes 6 as regards contributions to the expenditure of this office, under Article 11 of the Regulations amexed to the Convention. I am, vith great truth and regard, Sir Your obedient servant, (For the Secretary of State) Sir Percy Lorsine, Bart,, K.C.M.G., etc,, etc. , etc., Cairo,GopyT (K 4168/100/26). No.281. C Q 4 O O O ! C. BRITISH LEGATION, 19 31 j JED DA, July 13th, 1931. Sir f \Hith reference to your despatch No. 166 (E 1^17/ 100/25) of April 16th, I have the honour to state that Fuad Bey hamza, who has 'been very little in Jedda since his return to the Hejaz, did not revert to the question of the position of this country in regard to international sanitary arrange ments until July 8th, when he enquired in conversation whether I could tell him anything further, with special reference to the question of ratification with reservations of the International Convention of 1926. I told him that I would look up the papers and see whether there was anything I could put in writing, as Fuad Bey was on the point of returning to Mecca and was doubtful whether he could revisit Jedda before my departure on leave. 2. I should have preferred to deal with this matter orally, but as Fuad Bey was clearly anxious to get a written answer of some kind and telephoned a further enquiry to me on July 12th, I have sent him a oersonal letter, a copy of which I enclose. I have confined myself to a bare statement on each of the three ^nain questions raised in earlier conversations and correspondence. Should I see him before I leave, I will add any necessary further explanations, bearing in mind the caution in the last sentence of your despatch under reference. I have, etc. (Bgd.) Andrew Ryan. His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.My dear Fuad Bey, I have refreshed my memory of the correspondence arising out of our personal conversations etc., last year on the position of the Fejss in regard to the international Sanitary system. There is a certain amount of matter in it which I could explain to you hect in a further conversation hut in case you should he unahle to come to Jedcia before emerge are these (a) If your Government wish to attach reservations to their ratification of the International sanitary Convention of 1926, they could only do so with the previous consent of all htates which have signed or acceded to the Convention. For this purpose it would he necessary for them to communicate the proposed reservations to the French Government for transmis to those States. Quarantine Board, to which you referred last year, is one the decision of which rests with the Egyptian Government. (c) For the reasons which I explained privately to BheiJsh Yussuf Yasin on February 6th, the Hejazi Government might, in the opinion of my Government, find it advantageous to accede to the Rome Convention of 1907 and thereby acquire the right to representation on the Committee of the International Office of Public Health at Paris. This opinion is expressed informally by way of friendly suggestion. The official action necessary would be to notify the Italian Government in accordance with Article 6 of the Convention of 1907. I leave I may say that the three definite points which (b) The question of obtaining a seat on the Alexandria / His Excellency Fuad Bey HamzaOopyv (E 4176/100/25). No.290. 1 *5 9 \J K.J ! 1 9 / i JL W O i viir, BRITIoH LEGATION, JEDDA , July 16th, 1931. &amp; {% ¥ith reference to my despatch No.281 of July 13th, I have the honour to state that, when Fuad Bey hamza paid his flying visit to Jedda on July 15th, we had a short further conversation regarding the position of the Hejaz in regard to the international sanitary system. Fuad Bey said that, hefore receiving my letter of July 13th, he had himself arrived at the ooiii*.i.ai&gt;ion that the heet course for hie Government would he to acceue in the first instance to the Rome Convention of 1907. he did not expressly say that he thought it would he better to abandon any idea of ratifying the International danitary Convention of 1926 hut I gathered that his idea was that this country, having established its position in the Paris health Office, should await the next revision of the Paris Convention, he spoke of getting on with sanitary organization in this country in the meantime. 2. I onee more warmly encouraged Fuad Bey to work for accession to the Rome Convention. I also said, speaking not officially hut as a friend, that it was really most desirable to work up a good sanitary administration. At the same time, having in mind the warning in the last sentence your despatch No.156 (E 1817/100/25), I reminded Fuad Bey that other countries would continue to protect themselves, . within the limits of international arrangements, against the special dangers arising from the dispersal of the large numbers of possible disease carriers brought together by the pilgrimage. 3, His Majesty's Principal Secretary of otate for Foreign Affairs.3. I am afraid that the prospecte of any serious improvement of the Hejazi sanitary administration in the near future are poor. The Government have neither the money nor the men. They are alow at the best to realize that to get good men they must pay good money, liven the existing doctors, not a brilliant collection, have of late been restive. Dr. bdyuti, who has for some time been in charge of the quarantine arrangements at JedGa, has just left the country for good. He was not a man of the first quality any more than the others, but he did know something about his job. I have, etc. (ogd.) Andrew Ryan.Copy. No. 156. (E 1817/100/25) Sir, Foreign OFFICE, S.W. 1. 16th April, 1931. 0^ ffrflji With reference to your despatch No. 48 of the 6th / February last, relative to the position of the Hejaz-Nejd in regard to international sanitary arrangements, I approve the language which, as reported in that despatch, you held to Sheikh Yussuf Yasin in your conversation of February 5th. 2. As regards the possible accession of the Hejazi Government to the Rome Convention of 1907, I have to inform you, with reference to paragraphs 6 and 11 of your despatch, that the He^azi Government could accede to that Convention by notification to the Italian Government under Article 6, and would thus become entitled to representation on the Committee of the International Office of Public Health, without ratifying the International Sanitary Convention of 1926. 3. Should the Hejazi Government, as indicated in paragraph 9 of your despatch No. 48, seek to attach reservations to their ratification of the Convention of 1926, they would only be entitled to do so with the prior consent of all States which have signed or acceded to the Convention. For this purpose it would be necessary for them to communicate the desired reservations to the French Government for transmission to the Governments of those States. 4 . Sir Andrew Ryan, K.B.E., C.M.G., etc., etc., etc., J edda.f L.. 4. As regards the general line which you should follow in any future conversation or correspondence with the Hejazi authorities on the subject of international health matters, I request that you will he generally guided by the semi-official correspondence enclosed in my despatch No. 125 of the 26th March and, in particular, that you will, if you consider it desirable, convey to the Hejazi Government the information contained in paragraphs 2 and 3 of the present despatch. At the same time you should be careful not to commit either His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom or yourself regarding the desire of the Hejazi Government to secure a modification of th4 special position of the Hejaz under existing international sanitary arrangements. I am, with great truth and regard Sir Your obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State)■ MgBP K 1063/100/26. blr t with reference to eeml-official correapondence ending with Mr.Rendel'a letter Ho. It 966/100/26 of the 13th March to Sir George Buehenan, I am directed tos Mr. secretary Hendereon to tranealt to you, for anj oheerwetions which t: t Minieter of Health may wish to make, the accompanying copy of a deepatoh from Hla Majesty’s Minister at Jedda, reporting a private and unofficial conversation with heikh ’tusuf ^ain, the acting Hejazi Minister for Foreign Affairs, regarding the position of the hejaz in regard to international sanl u«ry arrangements. g. Mr.Henderson proiioses, subject to * 1 *.Greenwood a concurrence, to approve the language held hy oir A. r.yan in this conversation end to Inform him, with reference to paragraphs 6 and 11 of his deapatch, that the hejazl Government oould accede to the Home Convention of 1907 hy notification to the Italian Government under Article 6, and thus become entitled to representation on the Committee of the International Office of iublio Health, without ratifying the International anitary Convention of 1926. Mr. Henderson is advised that the Hejazi ^ovarnment would not be entitled to make reservations in ratifying the Convention of 1926 without securing the prior consent of all tates which have signed or acceded to the onvention. For /this The Secretary, Ministry of Health.I [931 I \ thie purpoae it would *be necessary for the Hejazi Gorernment to communicate the desired reservations to the trench Government for transmission to the Governments of those states* 4« Mr.Henderson proposes to inform Sir A.Ryan accordingly. He would be glad, however, to learn Mr.Greenwood’e views as to the general line which ^ir A.Ryan should follow in any future conversation or correspondence with the Hejazi authoritiee on the subject of international health matters generally, and more particularly in regard to the possible ratification of the anitary Convention of 1926 by King Ibn oaud. Kr.henderson is, for his part, disposed to think that Sir A.Ryan should be instructed merely to convey to the Hejazi Government the information contained in paragraph 3 above, should he consider it desirable, and not to commit His Majesty’s Government or himself in regard to the desire of the Hejazi Government to secure a modification of the special position of the Hejaz under existing international sanitary arrangements. 5. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Colonial Office and India Office. I am, &amp;lr, Your obedient Servant, ($d.) Q. W. RENDCL.(S) Copy No,48. (S 1063/100/86) i.2.0AT|ull ji. baJ |93| February 6th, 1831 ^lr With reference to ny deepatoh No. 191 of July 26th last, I h^ve the honour to report a dltcuseion which I ca * * vkj «»»*%* w# 4a.W4 4 e» a w **#«■&gt;«» w a**q w ^ waawwa ve 2. On my return from letive Mr.hope 0111 passed to me Mr.Rendel’s official letter (i. 6864/64/91) of Pecemher dru laat suggesting that a suitable opportunity should be taken of pointing out privately and informally to Fuad Bey Hamsa the advantage which the Hejaa-Ne^d Government would derive from adhering to the Home Convention of 1907 and thus securing the right to be represented at the meetings of the Office International d’Hygiene publique. Fuad iiey having vacated hi a post temporarily I included this in a note of subjects for discussion with the Minister for Foreign Affaire, marking it aa a matter with which I wished to deal unofficially. heikh Yuaauf Yaain caught on to this with alacrity, thinking, I fancy, that it had to do wit: the In ternational anltary Convention. 3. You will remember that when at home in the autumn, I submitted a short extraot from a personal letter a dare a sed to me by Fuad bey liamaa regarding hejaz Hejd par ticipation in international oanitary aeaaurea, with a minute of ay own suggesting certain points for your conaideration. I have not y^t received your vlewa but I did not think I could do any harm by exploring the aituation generally in /conversation His kajeaty's Principal Secretary of .tata for Foreign Affairs./6 convaraation with shaikh Yuabtif Yaaln* 4. At the outset X eeked the helkh to rigalt Qa&amp; l ^ converBation aa private» hoth heoauae the aut ject wae not one on which I was very fully inforaed and because it waa an inter national matter concerning other powera# I said that there were three cardinal factors in the international arrangements, via* the Paris Office International, the Health Organisation of the League of Nations, and the Unitary Convention of 1986. I made no further mention of the League of Nations, as it seemed doubtful fro® my conversations at home on the general question of the position of Hejea-Nejd in regard to the League, whether it would be prudent to stimulate the interest of Ibn aud in the possibility of becoming a member. 6. I outlined the nature of the Home Convention and the soope of the arrangements made under it. I said thfc*t any power oould adhere to the Convention, subject to one condition only, namely that it should contribute to the expenditure, which I understood was moderate. I explained that the action of the Hejasl Government last year in approaching the French Government regarding its grievance over the attitude of certain countries to returning pilgrims, which grievance had been referred to the Office, had drawn attention to the advantage of having a Hejaxl representation in the Office. Ae a proof of the general advan tages it offered, I observed that while only twelve states had signed the Convention originally, there were in 1989 no less than 49 members, including British and French dependencies. I mentioned the role of the Office in regard to the International v aniury Convention. As regards the latter, I referred to my conversations with Fuad Bey last July and his aubaequent letter. I reminded the Sheikh that a Hejazi representative had signed the Convention and, unlike many, without making reservations in the Protocol of signature.6 . sheikh Yuesuf Yasln sold th: t hie Ooverr.i jnt were i93 i anxloua to ratify the anitary Convention, fouh^ect to ***%-**+ necetioary to protect their own intereate} and they de8iz*ed the help of Great Britain. Ihn ^•ud had sent a repreeentative to Paris in 1926 but he had not ratified the Convention because in technical respects it affected hi a interesta. He had now been studying the matter with a view to ratification with reservations. Heferring to the action taken last year to lay the Hejaai grievance before the French Government, the oheikh seemed to think that that action was pertly directed towards admission to membership of the Office but said that no reply had been received up to date. He now understood, he said, that membership of the Office would depend on adherence to the Rome Convention and ratification of the Convention of 1926. X corrected him on this point, saying that, as I under stood it, the Hejas Government were free to adhere to the Rome Convention and so become one of the states entitled to reprt a- ent&amp;tlon on the Committee of the Office, whether they ratified the 1926 Convention or not. 7. The theikh then brought out the real question which worries the He^aa Government. How, he asked, could they ratify a Convention which treats the hejaz as a country of epidemica? I aaid I would answer him frankly. In the firat place the Hejaz was in fact a country productive of danger to others because of the pilgrimage, which brought here masses of people, many of them ignorant in their own countries of hygiene and dispersed them In conditions likely to lead to the dissemination of disease. Serious epidemics had resulted in the peat. It was recognised th£.t there had been an improvement in recent years and much of the credit was gladly /givengiven to the King. But* and this was the second pert of^a^jr answer* I was told truly thut he had not had long enough solve many important problems. The problem of organising an efficient sanitary service was peculiarly difficult. Ita solution must take years and required expert staff* laboratories and* in the conditions of this country* control at places other than the great centres of population. T had myself studied the question whleh had artosn sfter last year's pilgrimage. I was satisfied that no cholera had been detected in the Hejas but it was certain that it had appeared among returning pilgrims st Maesowsh end that caeea of grave suspicion had been discovered at Tor. 8. T urged the Sheikh not to think thbt there was any desire to brand the Hejaz as an inferior country. The more she did to organise her sanitary service* the lees would be the burden of precaution Imposed on other countries* although every country would always take its own measures of precaution within the limits of International agreements. I mentioned that not many years ago* when there wae small pox in England, France had taken special measures against English travellers. 9. ohelkh Yussuf Yasln said that real attention was being given to the improvement of the sanitary equipment of the Hejax and that increased financial provision was made each year. He intimated definitely that it was Ibn ta'ud’s intention to ratify the 1926 Convention* provided he could make his reservations. He asked whether the King could do this. I said I was not clear as to how far reservations could be made in an instrument of ratification but would enquire. I pointed out that in any ease the value of participation in the Convention /wouldwould be In Inverse proportion to the number 5T reservetlone made. I did not press him ee to the scope of the proposed renervations as I thought it better to confine myself 10 # In a final summery the .heikh repeated what he had said about the increased annual expenditure on sanitary organization and said th&amp;t the King would both adhere to the Rome Convention and ratify that of 1926 9 subject to hia reserva tions. I again pointed out that the two things were independent 11. I should explain that Sheikh Yuasuf Yaein did not appear to be conversant with the whole subject and knew only that part of it relating to the 1926 Convention, which the Kejazl Oovemment have been considering more I fear, from the point of view of escaping its restrictions than from any genuine desire to co-operate in efforts to protect the health of the world. Much of what I told him (I hope fairly accur ately, though I have myself no expert knowledge) about the 1907 Convention and the Office International seemed to be new to him. I gave him a copy of that Convention. I presume that any notice of adherence to it should still be given to the Italian Government but I should be grateful for definite Information on this point. 12. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Government of India, Foreign and Political 1 apartment and to Hie Majesty's High Commissioner at Cairo. to generalities until I should have received your views. I have, etc., (fcgd) ,vHI&gt;Rk KYAK.17619. I. 1349. 2000.—9/1914. Register No. Minute Paper. Political Department. letter from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 191 To Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State Council rm?,: • * Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Copy to Previous Papers . 4</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00026a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2080</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00026a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2080</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/14 'Hejaz-Nejd: International Sanitary Arrangements.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-04T22:13:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (37 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 39; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-39; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns international sanitary arrangements in relation to the Kingdom of the Hejaz and Nejd (later Saudi Arabia). The file consists almost entirely of copies of Foreign Office correspondence, which have been forwarded by the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to the Under-Secretary of State for India. Most of the correspondence is between the British Minister at Jedda (Sir Andrew Ryan) and various Foreign Office officials. Other correspondents include the Italian Ambassador and the Italian Chargé d’Affaires in London.The correspondence principally discusses the following:Reports of objections from the Hejazi Ministry of Foreign Affairs to quarantine measures taken by the Egyptian and Italian sanitary authorities, following suspected cases of cholera among pilgrims at Tor [El-Tor] and Massowa [Massawa, Eritrea].British efforts to persuade the Hejaz-Nejd Government to adhere to the Rome Convention of 1907, in order to secure the right to be represented at the meetings of the Office International d'Hygiène Publique (International Office of Public Hygiene).The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Italian Chargé d’Affaires to London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Office International d'Hygiène Publique</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Italian Ambassador to the United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kingdom of Nejd and Hejaz</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Sanitation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00026a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>