<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000281_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T10:30:45.037Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram (Code) J * T0IL Resident on ''Patrick Stewart', ^ 0 i t ical ,'Mu£cat, Pated 20/12/29 (reed 21/12/29) 2 v t o.T/ 75 . 'Ormonde' leaves Aden 26th December to carry out survey in the trulf and has inquired whether ( \ i or survey permitted on Oman peninsula and on ia c«KSfy&gt;^wigv ^ yjj thusandum (Musandum ? peninsula* Commanding officer has been instructed to call at Muscat and obtain your concurrence* please expedite report on outcome of discussion in due course I suggest that State should send someone with Ship whilest working on Oman Coast* Kesident. s- rj 1140 . ot‘ 1929. . olltiofil Agency &amp; H.B.F’b Conuulrte. 'UBcat, 2lBt December 1929. To ''’he Council of Minietere to His Highness the Cult an of i.uscnt and Oman, Huscat. if ter Compliments. I am informed by telegram from the Political Resident that K.M.Survey ship H Ormonde’* leaves Aden 26th December to carry out survey in the Oulf ana has enquired whether lanaings for survey may be permitted on the Oman peninsula anc. on : in; and am peninsula. The Capti in has been asked to call at i uscat and obtain .concurrence. Tculd you please let me know vfhether the Council of i misters are agreeable to this. The Resident suggests that someone may be sent on the ship on behalf of the iusent Rtate v nilst she j if working on the f'mt n Coast. This is what had to be sria and sal a? ns • ms i or, Political ivgent 8: U.I .K's Consul,] uses!Letter rto.94 dated 22nd Lecenter 1929 from the Council of Ministers to h.H.the Multan of .Muscat Oman, to Major G.P.Murphy, I.A., Political A^ent &amp; F.P.I^e Consul,Muscat• A.C. ^ Reference your letter lio.154, dated the 21st .December 1929, intimating that you have received a telegram from the Political resident saying that H.11.Survey snip 'Ormonde' leaves ^den on the 26th December 192S to carry out suvery in the Gulf and on tne Oman and musandam Peninsulas* • # Ve have the honour to state in reply that v/e agree to this and concur with the Political Resident’s auggestion, and on arriv c ':l of the ship we will send a man to accompany tl the Captain as desired Ly you* ■ im u. p* * , •. F Im . ^ &lt;» ■ ’ i: l aT K h i&amp; (i H A M (Code ivZZ} jj‘rom To I'l o. n. M. ti • '* ORiiU^DE ** Henj am readi o. rOL i ti CM ,, MUSCAT. nil Dated the 2nd January 1930. (received 2nd January;. H.M.S' Ormonde’ 1 expects to arrive at muscat approximately 1400 hours tomorrow Friday, nenuest | nassib be instructed to provide bakers on arrival, farther requested that Interpreter qualified in Persian Arabic may be provided. It is hoped it will be convenient' for Commanding Officer to discuss certain matters with you. it is proposed to sail same day.* note ’‘Ormonde* 1 is 1 not a saluting ship. J •oOo- Supdt . Please inform nassib as soon as possible so that he could maice arrangements tomorrow morning. u. r.M. P. A, i have informed nassib. m • A, I # 2-1-30- ! / : l'TELEGRAM CODE Prom h.L.S.'Ormonde' Henjam To x^ol^ticai, Muscat. No. 1653 Dated ^7th. January 1G3J( received i38tL January 1950. Serixor llaval Officer, Persian Gulf inforr^me / there is a suitable a^dica^t at Muscat for the post of Interpreter 3rd class for H.M.S.'Ormonde' It is requested to engage him and send hxm to join at Henjam as soon as possihie. His name and address is Abdulla An Mohamiad C/o Director of Customs. .* ■ • a • This is the same man whom you saw, he does not know- Persian but knows. Arabic and English. If Persian is not required hfc is al-0 TELKURAil CODE Prom h.m.S.'Ormo nde' henj am To rolitical, Muscat. ho. 1015 Eated and received 5th February 1930. Please communicate following to Council of Ministers of Muscat from Sheikh Ibrahim Hahommad H.M.S.'Ormonde”. Place wanted belongs to Bokha but Shaikh will not allow H.M.S. 'Ormonde' to observe there. I report matter for your dicision. Awaiting reply. iiunshi Please show this to trie uouncii of ministers. Id/- O.P.M.at Henjan* Persian Gulf 8th February, 1930• H*U» 8* ^ 0RM0HDB •• . H Dear Major Murphy Sheikh Ibrahim Mahoamed is returning to Muscat today in H*M»S» *CR0CUS' and I should like to say that he has been of the greatest assistance to *0RM0NDB' and most ready to do everything that he could to further our interests; it is in no way due to him that we have so far failed to obtain the cooperation of the Sheikh of Bokha and the Tribes on Musandaa, about which Sheikh Ibraham will make a full Tours sincerely Major G&lt; G»P. Murphy, Political Ageftt, British Consulate, MUSCA*. Arabia.Political Agency and H.Ii.Jd'e Conaulatfe, Muscat jjth February 1930* To The Commander* II *M a %Ja Ormonde”* attack • Hen.iagu Memorand um ♦ The undernoted siime ^etre due to this office 1. Paid to Sheilch Ibrahim bin Muhammad on account passage and other expenses Ks*50/« 2. Cost of passage provided to Interpreter Abdullah All Re.30/- Total* »•••••••• •Rb*80/ •• I request that this sum may be remitted to this office* Major* y Political Agent and Consul*Mubcat* h mTTThe Commander, H.M. S*'Ormonde*, Memo randmu. Reference your iiemo.jNo.37 dated 24th jH'ebru^xy 1930 regarding the sum of Rs.50/-advanced by thio office to Sheikh Ibrahim Of the above amount iiheiich Ibrahiru spent Ks.7/8/- on^for boat hires and food as detailed below and refunded to this office the balance Rs.42/8/-i- jboat hire at muscat and henjam... .Ks. 2-0-0 Food..Ks.5-8-0 . Total. «Ks. /—8—0 I request the balance &lt;tue to this office namely Ks.37-8-0 may please be remitted at an early date. J s Maj or. Political Agent and K.B.k's Consul,Muscat. ;; / m 1 :FROM DATE TO The Commanding Officer, H-M*S. ” ORMONDE ' . 24th February, 1950. Ref. No. 37. The Political Agent A His Britannic Majesty*s Consul, Political Agency &amp; His Britannic Majesty*s Consulate, MUSCAT. With reference to your communication No. 137 dated 12th February, 1930 respecting an amount of^30 Rupees owing to you on account of passage money, etc., for Sheikh Ibrahim bin Muhammad, and for Interpreter Abdullah Ali, it is observed that the sun of 50 Rupees was incurred by Sheikh Ibraham for “passage and other purposes”. As return passage was provided by one of H.M. Ships it is not understood howa any expenses in this respect can have been incurred. In order to fully explain matters in the Cash Account of H.M.S. ORMONDE”, I should be obliged if more ’ parcioulars could be provided for the expenditure of the 50 Rupees in question. 1 COMUA NDBR- in-COM MAND. 0/ V h .w 5-3 • ? ^ ^ /0 - c t/ ^ * mA '■ &lt;7/ O C &lt;rXUc &gt;PROM TO DATR The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. 'Triad The Political Agent, H*M* Consulate, Muscat 9th February, 1930% 32*F/36/2. The Coarianding Officer, 'Ormonde' has requested that an expression of his appreciation of the valuable services rendered to H.M.S. 'Ormonde' in her survey work by Sheikh 1 Ibrahim Mahomed may be conveyed to His Highness The Sultan and the Council of Ministers of the Muscat State. It gives the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division great pleasure to communicate this request to you. U*V&lt;?U y yO 2— CAPTAIN SBNIOR NAVAI OFFICER PERSIAN GUI F.i/rai't i'ur approval Ht.iL i-C/h fio To The Council of ii-inistere to K.H.the ftultfin oi‘ hub cat and ur.ian, hub cat. I have the honour to inform you that 1 am desired by the Senior naval Officer, -Persian Gulf, to xrvite this letter and to express to the Council of ninistere the Commanding Officer, H.M.S.'Ormonde*8 appreciation oi the valuable services rendered.to II.M.S.'Ormonde* in lier survey work by cheikh Ibrahim bin iiuhamad* A • C. hajor, PiA. &amp;: H.M r s Consul,i:u8cat «Tifi-LiJilrKAMi Code 1922; jj’rom xi.M.b. ••l,upin‘‘. To i^uLITICAJLi MUSCAT, i\o. 1304 dated tlie 7th. march 1930, Sultan of Muscat’s wall at hhasab reports that She lien of Aha sab has attempted to confine him to his fort will not allow him to buy food in bazaar and has disarmed and beaten 2 of ms guards, wall requests instructions from Muscat*, nave informed wall I will pass his message to Muscat and commnnicate reply to him. Cause of troubje is believed to be sheihh's refusal to recognise authority of Muscat uovemment and suspicion of wall enlisting help of n M,s ships to enforce it. Addressed to r.A. Muscat, repaeted to resident, susnire V n.M.s, Ormonde and s.n.O. from n.M.S M jL,upin M .- ■ T JU ii; Cr K A m ( Code 1V22j Jj'rom resident, uushire. To Political, Muscat, jno. 231 Dated tfte ctn karcn 1^30, li V 'Ormonde- ?rx.ch , Jj’oljioiwing fromM.M.S.** Lupin” Degms. principle opposition to landing of H.M. M Ormonde' party at Boicna now appearing to come from Sheikh of Ahasab whose territories it is understood have to be crossed in order to reach observation station. Opposition is believed to be due to suspicion h.M.a.'Ormonde' opersations are connected with enforcement authority of Muscat Government Suspicion is increased by fact that Sheikh Ebhrahim was brought from Muscat in H.M.S.'Ormonde'; anxious regarding Sultan's Wall return to Kina sab in her. Meeting of Residency Agent and Sheikhs of Bkoha and Khasab is now taking place at Khasab and it is hoped arrangement will be arrived, reference ray 1304 7th March it is not proposed to discuss with aheikh question of. author!ty of Muscat Government. 1303 - 7th M a rch . Addressed to Political Resident, uushire repeated tc B.jn.O. rersian uulf, n.M.B. RhOlBBt'! T 231. oOo-x HI IMPORTAKT. y'lrrXr, 2.3/ S facm. As action being talcen would appear to under- —nine whatever influence the iiuscat otate possesses request that V/ali should not be excluded fron conference. Sultan is sending letters to Sheikh and I T ?ali by accredited representative to whom flying jioet is giving passage to Has ®1 Khaiiija. Bequest Pavj 1 be asked to show this representative every consider- -ation. ■ Political. -TK 1&gt;E (iK AM ( Code 1922) yrom M Lupin M To j^olitioal, Muscat My 1303 Attempts to arrive at an agreement by which, bheildris of isokieaii and Khasab were to provide a joint escort for ri.M.S.'Ormonde's observation party resulted in a dispute between Oheilda concerning boundary between their territories, tiheiich of Bokicah eventually agreed not to interfere and thus allow the Sheikh of Ahasab to provide escort. On arrival of n.M.S. 'Ormonde 1 s party at Ahasab escort at Aidah Cove tins morning, landing was opposed by armed men who said that they recognise neither Sheikh of iUiasab nor hokicah, but ready to negotiate with n.M.S. Ormonde *.k party. Propose H.M.S W Ormonde's party should take observation from Jabal Sham near islphinstone inlet returning to ship each quarter night. Observation party for bombardment practice by u.kl.s. ships here frequently landed in vicinity and it is not considered permission to land or escort will be required* Also propose inform sheikh of Ahasab and Bokkah but it is no longer desired to land there. Bequest approval. Addressed to r.K. Repeated to S..N.0. n.M.S Ormonde from n.M.S 'Lupin' no. 1141 dated 9th March 1930. Addressed n.M.S. 'LupirP* repeated Muscat Your 1141 9th March X approve. owing to their inability of governing their own territories I -- 0 O 0 TELEGRAM( 1922 Code; Erom RESIDENT, BUSmiUfi i To n.M.S. 'Lupin'. 234 Jiated the 10th march 1930 Residenton shore to-day Friday and handed him the letter from hha sab ra Muscat Government, SheiJch of;x£iii£iich stated that he had no ■ i reply to make to the letter and that he would confer no one but sultan himself or his waair, sheikh Saif wishes to return to Muscat to report and will be placed on board s.s.“harjora* due at Muscat on the 16th march. It is considered if xi*M,Ship leaves vicinity of Khasab jejsxiat wall would be in some danger and h.-lunS, 'Lupin” will therefore remain until further instructions are received J but from Political Resident it is requested she may not be | m delayed longer than is essentia. I Addressed Political A, Resident, repaeted to political Agent muscat from L n.m.S.'Lupin' 1^35 14th March, L U r In,•'■e leg ram ^Gode/ From Kesiderit^uusiiire, 1*0 , •loliticaliMuscat, xiQ.ZSZ dated 16/3/30• feu will xax&amp; presumably have heard from SheiJOi 6aif what has happened at ilhas&amp;b. Have proposed to Govt of India that Sultan should be invited to proceed there m person or to send vtazir to impose fine and that sloop should accompany with authoritative enforcement deraand.— T i*j x. in Xr K A M ( Code 1U22) From rCIjlTlCALj Xiusctit, To iCiolDXli'. T , iju sill re. i'io, 262 ■^ated the 13th narch 1930. / I neference your telegram no.262 dated the 16th march Sultan and Council would be grateful for action proposed. Sultan is proceeding tc India by next-mail but saiyid Said and wazir are available, sultan would object to I Saiyid Said proceeding there by Air as he considers an escor' of 20 askaris essential. XDLlTiCAh.Tele^raiu (Code; 3^ l^r oi! • # • • Resident,iiuehire, To Politicaljtiuscat ±'io.2B2 dated 21st iiiarch 1930* l*. ^ s • Your telegram 262 Govt.or India while! appreciating necessity of enforcing bultan's authority to pay (fine) consider he should first endeavour to restore statu quo by his own efforts* I suggest that Y/azir and if you think it desirable ^aiyid 3aid should proceed to Khasab in 'A1 Said* Y/ith adequate force to deal with Sheikh* Would it not&gt;£ be better to send detachment of Levy Corps rather than Askaris* As Wali threatened to leave if the ship left I have told ship to remain at Khasab for the present* It is therefore essential Wazir should xjroceed xb v/ithout delciy. flease notify h*ll*b* H Lupin 1 * v/hen he leaves* Resident*1 to. ....... .BeBicent* rushiro, i'T PoiiticGl,i-UBcat* Uo*40-Ci dated 2£nd lierch 1950* ’k'ls' Your teiegran X'&lt;o*282 dated 2iet karch 1950* Council conaider ttie i'oixo?/ing I* That the landing of inadequate force available unleae baclced by active Baval supx&gt;ort would provoke opposition from oheikh and possible bloodshed ana would be unable to maintain their position when sloop leaves* II* In event Saiyid 8aid proceeding in A1 Said Sheikh regaining incalcitrant and no action following measure calculated to react on hip personal prestige throughout Sultanate* III* v/azir Thomas accompanied by sheikh Zubair bhoulc proceed upioadl and be ta^cen off at liusandum by sloop to investigate thaughx thorougnly and report situation before action taken* P/* Post necessary British hgent Isa bin Abaul Latif should meet them there* Political* — ■ —- .•TEJL&amp;GKAiM Code IVZZ) Fr om 3)1 S]nT. BUSHIHli) • To POLITICAL, MUSCAT. jno, 285 I»ated the 22nd March iy30. IMMEDIATE. Tour 40-c: Sheiim of Ahasab has left for LIMAH with 15 men one of his wives comes from LIMAH. Headman KUirfiZAn has offered assistance to v/aii against Ahasab. Government of India appreciate necessity of enforcing authority of Muscat State in the last resort. Council's apprehensions are therefore largely baseless. I suggest ' Thomas proceed to LIMAH in ’'Al Said* 4 to investigate and thence to hhasab and report to me through n.r.S. H Lupin'. I consider SheiJch of Khasab merits heavy fine. RESIDENT 285.Am sending you two code messages winch should be communicated to Thomas before he leaves.*TKjLiS&lt;iKAisc.( code 1922; 3 i Frora M Lupin M To P.H. ±5usiiire repeated to S.JN.O. r.u- x\o. 1603 ^atedtde 23rd march 1930 x Immediate Following from H. ^upm 41 . reference my 1911 of 22nd March, messenger from hiimzar reports that on his way baclc to Kuazar to-day Sunday he intercepted man with messages from Sheiich of xthasab and Sheikh Saleh to headman iCumzar saying that they owe re going to A1 i*ujaira to enlist help of Sheikh there and asking whether the Kumzar would join them or not. weply of headman is not known but I would not p/resume^ he refused. Addressed political Resident repeated to s.n.O. m.Ci. from n.jv .s. 'Lupin'* 1603 dated 23rd march . RESIDENT. 291Telegram( Code 1922; ij’rom n.K.b, M j J u Jr m M resident, ±5usiiire and repeated to s.jn.O. r.ix IN 0 , 1911 dated tne 22nd Marcix 1930 IMMEDIATE . Following from M.M. t&gt;, “JLupin M 'begins Keference my 1213 dated 22nd March* messenger from hu^zar Aho is cousin of headman reports that when u Griaaode M first arrived' and landed surveying party Sheiich of Aha sab and dheihh baleh of Dibah made secret agreement to join force to defend their country against nritish^to eject wall of hhasab and proclaim themselves independent of Muscat, neadman of Kumzar was ashed by ilheihh oaieh to join m agreement but he refused* when n.M.bhip returned to hhasab in i.iarch bheiich of hhasab v/robe to inform bheihn baleh that he expected some action v/as going to talce against him and sheiien baleh, ashed bheihh of hnasab to mee't him at himah to discuss what steps they should taxe* neadman mg and was in danger so had sent messenger to offer his assistance. Messenger has been instructed to tell headman to tahe no action as n.M.bhip is at ivnasao and wail is not in danger but that ms offers for assistance will be reported to Sultan. 1911 dated 22nd Marcm Addressed to political resident repeated to bJh/O. jt.u-. from n.M.b. “.Lupin“. that wall of ithasab v/as no longer officiat- ithSIDEhT 290 ouo- o' Telegram Code Prom Political Kesident, duanire To Goverruneiit of India, -New Delhi No. 26x Dated iotn March i930. IMPORTAN T. Trouble has occurred on Musandam peninsula in connection with survey of H.M.S.'Ormonde M (vide n*y telegram of 11th .November, 1139). Early in February H.M.S. 'Ormonde' wished to land party olll^ine ^eak to taice observations but Sheikh of Bokha objected. Fixially with concurrence of Muscat b placed hesidency Agent at disposal of Beni or Naval Officer and latter reported that satisfactory settlement had been arrived at and survey would proceed after Ramazan, un 7th March H.M.S. 'Lupin' reported Sheikh of ilhasab was op posing landing of survey party gs his territory had to be crossed to reach ooservation post. Opposition was said to be due to suspifiion that H.M.S. ''Ormonde*s' operations were connected with enforcement of authority of ^ultan of Muscat, as Sultan* s w ali had returned to Khasao in her. Later H.M.S. 'Lupin' reported that Sheikh of ithasab had attempted to confine wali to his fort and disarmed and o beaten two of his guards, on receipt of this news sultan sent representative Baif by flying boat which happened to be going from Muscat to Has al Khaimah. Finally arrangement was made by wnich Bo&amp;ha and Khasab would provide joint escort for survey party, but on landing party were opposed by armed men who said tney recognised neither M heikh but were ready to negotiate themselves. Party therefore with- diew axid H.M.S. 'Lupin' proposed that observations should bea. 'lupin H reported that V'ali of Khasao requested refuge on board on ground that his life was in danger, but this was refused as officer '-'ommanding did not consider he ?/as in danger while H*M.S.'Lupin' remained there* As difficulty regarding survey had been surmounted I requested officer Commanding to try and compose differences between Sheikh and tfali on basis of maintenance of previous status quo and he therefore invited both to conference on board* aheikh refused to attend statirig he would not negotiate through British but only with Muscat representative direct, ne also said that Jebel *ham was in his territory and he would not be responsible for sal&amp;ty of survey party* At that moment baif arrived and endeavoured to effect settlement, but ohei^h ^»aid he would only negotiate with Sultan or his Wazir, and Saif has returned to Muscat. H.M.S.'Lupin* reports that no escort is necessary for Jebel sham and ^heikh’s attitude can be disre|arded and observations will^ be carried out in few hours on first clear day* #e considers Wali is still in some danger and is remaining at fQiasab for the present, but cannot stay much longer* i consider it necessary tnat prompt steps should * be ta*en to re-assert Muscat authority and punish -heikh of hhasab and recommend that “ultan snould be invited to proceed tnere nimseif or sen* Wasir to impose reasonable fine axid tuat demand should be supported oy presence of sloop which should oe authorised in last resort, to enforce demand by uestruction of fort after cue notice, it is improbable tnat it would oe necessary to resort to sucn measures, but presence of sloop witnout autnority to enforce demand, or only after delay necessitated by further reference, would be exnihition of futility. On the other hand if Sheikh is allowed to flout 5uUan's authority with impunity effecteffect will spread, and settleraent at •-•ur will become more difficult, ana authority of State will be further undermined, if this proposal approved 1 would proceed in sloop myself but would leave actual negotiations to Muscat* RESIDENT *** Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent Muscat By oraer Capt., for Secretary to the Political Resident in the' Persian Gulf. Bushire 17th March 193044/7. Telegr.-iin Code Jdl fY^' From -*• ^• '’lupin' Henjamra&amp;io. Political Besidant, Bushire. Senior Naval Officer 'Triad' Bjom'oay T T. . S 'Oroionde' Henjamradio. To Hopeated No 1434. Dated loth reed 17th March 1930. ourvey party landed at Jahalsham ttus Sunday aiorning and have now Been re embarked. Essential work has been oompleted and it is not expected that they will be required to land again. it is reported leit xihasao and has stated that in that event he wooid not remain. it is now considered improbable he would he attacked but he would probably have difficult,/ in obtaining provisions and it is unlikely that Sheikh will come to terms with him. that iiheikh of fiassa has heen arrested oy Sheikh of Khasao for allowing party to land last week.- y a li considers he would be in danger if His Jiaflesty's Ship Lupin rcct copy -ivor^V/ar'clcd to tilt j^ulitical A^ent at Muscat for information. ±}y Order, Cap tain, for Secretary to the Political Kesioent in the Persian Gulf. b Buc hire, IRth March 1930.From ivAZIR THOMAS, LUPIN H . To PULITiGAL, lUSGaT. Iho. 13Q1 Dated the 7th April 1930. Following for baiyid Said from Y/azir Thomas begins Kindly arrange to send by next up nail to M A1 Salve’' waiting at Henjam .303 ammunition 2 boxes . Henry Martine 1500 m 7 miliiietres 3500. Rupees 1000/-' Dollars 500/- Rice 15 bags Sheiich Hasan is at Khasab. Hut still recalcitrant u.nd we are waiting for w-overnment to authorize action. If this decided I have requested that the rolitical resident to inform you immediately so that you may come here. On receipt of telegram can arrange u Ai Said' meet you ^enjam. WAZIR TK0MA3. oOO' A-^l' ^ 0^C LJ-£-o RLu-m. ~6***IC*Q u+-*~ ^ Ca? lZcxl &lt;t : -4?44/7 Telegram Code From Political Resident, Bushire To Government of India, hew Delhi So. 294 Dated the 24th March i950. IMMEDIATE. My telegram ho.2B8 of 25rd March • Officer Commanding M Lupin M reporta tnat relative of 3heiKh of Kuinzar arrived at Idiaaab atateo that when H.M.S. ,, OrInonde ,, first landed survey party in February Sheikhs of Khasao arid Dibba]^ made agreement to combine to resist survey eject Wall of Khasab and proclaim themselves independent of Muscat. Kumzar was asked to join out refused, when H.M.S.'Ormonde' returned in March with sloop Khassab informed DiDoa&amp; that he thought action was going to be i a4.en against him and Dibbah asked Kliasab to meet nim at Limah to concert measures. KUma&amp;r hau seh messenger offering Wali assistance. On nis wag tack re lative of bneikn of Kumzar iiiterceptea messeii ^.er from Sheikh of Khasab and Diboa^ saying tnat they v/ere ^oixi^ to Al Fujairah to enlist his support. JLatter has frequently proved troublesome vide Busnire letter ho. 754 of 2nd Haj 1935. Thomas is proceeding up coast in Muscat yacht. In view of fact that Khasab * s action is not isolated but is concerted action by number of petty Sheikhs to resist authority of Muscat and also to flout British authorities 1 recommend that sloop should proceed to Fujaira to meet Thomas arid reinforce is authority ana enable him to report as Muscat Yacht * ias wireless. - RESIDENT -Code Telegram From Government of India, New lielhi. To Political ReM.aeot, Bub hire. No. 543-N. Bated and received P.dth March 19^0. L-*' IMMEDIATE. f Your telegram No. P94, P?rd March. Secretary of State*e approval 1 b heing ta^en to action euggeeted in your telegram No. ?6l of 16th March. You are authorised to make any pi e- -liminary arrengemente necepeary in anticipation of sanction, which will he telegraphed to you as soon as received. FOREIGN. Telegram Code. Fr ora Political Kesident, Bushire. v 0 H.M.R. '711° IN M , Henj amradi o. No. PQ?. Bated Phth March 19?0. Should be glad if yon. could proceed at once to Fuiaira to meet ^homae in ”A1 Said” end report on Pit** -uation, hut further action should not be taken till sanction of H. M’r. Government, to v^hom reference iP being xiiade, is received. PFSIBKNT.44/7 584-27/3/30 Telegram uode Prom 'Lupin' hen jam TO Time 2259 Political Resident, hushire. Dated and received the 27th March 1930, IMMEDIATE, xour telegram no.297. Poliowing has been received from the Political Agent, Muscat begins, M Al ^aid rt due Dibah 26th March, Limah 27th March, Khassab 29th x^arch. iii .ds. if you approve propose to asK the oheiich of ilalba if he has arty information tomorrow Thursday and also proceed to Dibah, 'Lupin' **#* Telegram p*n clair From Po itical hesident, hushire. To ho.302 h.M.S.'Lupin' henjam nadio Dated the 27th i&amp;arfih 1930, ¥our 2259, i approve but please get in touch with Thomas, and act in consultation with him. *#* ~ Ri’JSIDElfTrv 44/7 596-28/3/30 Telegram Code From H.M.S. “Lupin H u e ujam Political Keeident, Jjushire Time 1801 Dated 27th (received 28thj March 1950 My 2fra&gt;teof 26th March. H.M.a.“Lupin“ joined “Al 3aid M this after noon, Thursday, Thomas is not yet in a position to report on tne situation out hopes to do so in a^out 3 days He interviewed Sheikh Saleh on board “Al Said” yesterday and Saleh said that sheikh of Khasab was at Dibah but was leaving immediately for Khasab and Thomas did not see him. ”Al Said” is proceeding to itumzar and tnonee to Khasab and H.M.S.“Lupin” is returning to Khasab to await her arrival. Thomas also wishes to see the Residency Agent and if you approve propose H.M.S.“Lupin” should take him to Sharjah, ”Al Said” remaining at Khasab until H.M.S.“Lupin” returns. Government does not aeem to intend taking any action at present. Reference your ho.285 of 21at March “Al Said” has no levies on board and Muscat - H.M.S.”Lu in” ***44/7 5 d i Telegram Code From Foiltical Hesideut* dushire. To fovermuent of India, Hew Delhi* no. 31 • Dated the 28th *arch 1930. jr I My telegram Ho.298 of 26th March. Thomas interviewed She!nil of Dibba on hoard 'Al Said” yesterday and was told aheinh of Khassab was leaving iiijmediately for Khassao so did not see him. M Al Said' is proceeding to Xhassab and H.M.S. 'Lupin' who had gone to meet Thomas has returned the re • Thomas expects to be able to report on situation in about 3 days.- - RhSlDEHT - * * *Telegram Code To Political Resident, iJushire H, M, S. '’Lupin' Henjam Kadi o Ho.5il Dated the 28th March 1930 IMMEDIATE. Your 1801. f Ho objection to your taking Thomas to Sharjah or fetching Residency Agent from there, to asoist Thomas if ne prefers. 1111 sanction oi His Majesty’s Government is received to action by H.M.S.’•Lupin” in support of Muscat authority Thomas had setter not commit himself, nut when this is received 1 hope Kbassab will be suitably dealt with in view of facta reported in your 2019. I entirely share views of the Residency Agent. Please inform Residency Agent that fl lag boat is due to arrive Haa al iOiaimah March 30th en route for Karachi. ***44/7 511-1-4-SO. Tele^rafti From To Ho U17. Code* H* M* 3. ’•Lupin** Kenjamradio polltloal lesident, Buahire* Dated and reed 3ist arch, 1930. * Uy 1801 of l ax-oh* Thoiuaa * a report is Being forwarded per fast mail 'Varsova** due Bus dire r; ednesday 2nu Apixl* Letter has Deen sent by Muscat autnorities on board *1 3ai&amp; to the Shaikh of Khasah requesting his re urn to Khasab to meet Thomas but his whereabouts are uncertain and x-eply is not expea ted till about Wednesday* Thomas will remain at Khasab in A1 Bald for tne present* .upin 1Telegram Fr om Code. H.M.S. ’’JjTTPTN 1 * . To Political Pepir.ent, 3i\fihlre. Repeated Senior Officer, Bombay. No. .to08. Dated 2nd received $rd April Reference section 6 of Thomas’ report. In ' r ie ,A / of the fact that Khftso.o con? d ootain sunn?.ies overland if is submitted that if wmOh be necessary to be prepared to take some more immediately effective action in the event of threat of blockade fo.il- - i.ng to bring Shaikh to terms. 'LtTP .K'. Telegram Code. From Political Hesident, Bushire. To H. M. 3. ’’Lupin” Henjamradio. No 331. Dated 3rd April 1930. Important. r • Your 1308 of 2nd April. I agree with your views and should prefer to take action more immediately effective, lias Sheikh of Khasab returned yet ? If he has and still adopts recalcitrant attitude please let me know what action you consider can be taken against him to bring about his submission to Muscat authority. Is bombardment likely to be effective ? If so against what particular point would it be directed. Resident.! * k /-2-7 —y ~ 3° Telegram From To No 1101. Dated 3rd reed 4th April 1930. Code. Senior Naval Officer 'Triad' Bomhay, Political Resident, Bushire. I Senior Naval Officer ttfoughly conouit in opinion of commanding officer of 'Lupin*'in his telegram to you No. 1308 of 2nd April. Our knowledge of the interior is small hut there is reason to believe that Khasab could withstand a blockade by getting supplies overland. For blockade to be effective it might prove necessary to include other coast villages and such action might bring Trucial Sheikhs into active sympathy for Khasab. Senior Naval Officer.44/7 L Irf V ' ^ Telegram From To No 2113. Dated 3rd reed 4th April 1930. Code. H. M. 3. M Lupin' Henjamradio Political Besident, Bushire. Your telegram No. 331 of 3rd April. Following has been made out iin conjunction with Thomas. Sheikh returned Khasah on Tuesday and his attitude remains recalcitrant. In view of fact that he can retire to mountains and presumably has support of Li bah his early submission is not likely. Subject to approval of Commander-int Chief following action is proposed with object of bringing maximum pressure to bear on him. Bombardment ( to be repeated if necessary) of Sheikh Hasan’s quarter of Khasab and neighbourM^ Beni Hadiya village including destruction of local craft. Blockade of Khasab area including prohibition of local fishing. Suggest this action should not be taken until 43 hours after the delivery of ultimatum. In connection with blockade suggest you should issue letter to Trucial Chiefs to co-operate. It is considered that Wali should not evacuate fort provided Kumazara agree to garrison it. Steps will be taken to this end if found practicable and if you approve. This message is being repeated to Command err -in-Chief and Senijr Naval Officer. Lupin. VMy telegram 312 of 28tti March. Situation at Khasah. I have received long report Irom Thomas. Gist is as follows:- (1) Trouble originated through apprehensions of Shihuh trihe at survey and they tried to revenge themselve on Muscat Government who had helped survey. (2) They were emboldened to oppose British oy impunity with which Trucial Sheikhs have opposed air route. ^ 3 ^ was close pact between Khasab ana. Liba and some of Kumazara Sheikhs but leading Sheikh of Kumzar has remained loyal. (4) Landing at Khasab in face of opposition would be matter of much difficulty and Shihuh possess rifle strength of 1500. It is not feasible therefore to use Muscat Infantry. (5) Sheikh has returned to Khasab but maintains entirely recalcitrant attitude. (6) If action not taken against him la) repercussions of Shihuh insurgence will be felt throughout Oman and Trucial Coast (b) landing of any British personnel in Shihuh country about which there has beon no difficulty hitherto will in future be attended by grave risk. ; 'c. X-l f.- 2 - I entirely agree with (o) see my 298 of 2jth yaroh. Moreover normal route for flying boats proceeding to Muscat is from Ras-el-Khaimah to Dihha. I should hesitate to permit this in future unless our authority was established on peninsula, and considerable aetour would be necessary. Officer Commanding H. M, S. 'Lupin* recommends subject to approval of Commander-in-Chief bombardment (to be repeated, if necessary) of quater of Khasab occupied by Sheikh and neighbouring Beni Hadijah village and destruction of local craft. Action to be taken 48 hours after delivery of ultimatum. I**event of wJheikh retiring to mountains this would be followed by blockade of Khasab area (in which Trucial Sheikhs would be inviteu to co-operate) including prohibition of local fishing, not Wali would/evacuate fort provided arrangements could be maae for Kumaz&amp;ra to garrison it. I strongly support recommendation regarding bombardment and consider it essential that Sheikh should be subdued. 24 hours notice would however suffice. Cnl^ £ hours were given when Fujaira was bombaraea vide para 13 Bushire letter 731 of 2nd Kay 1925. As regards suoseqh 61 ^ blockade I would prefer to reserve opinion until further consultation with Senior Naval Officer who is now at Bombay and review of position after bombardment. I request therefore that 'Lupin* may be authorised to enforce by action recominehded above ultimatum to be issued by Thomas and would solicit early instructions. Resident. J * i44/7. Telegram Code. From Political Resident, Bushire. To H. M. S. 'Lupin' Henjamradio. Repeated Senior Naval Officer 'Triad' Bombay. No 333. Dated 4th April 1930. I have recommended to Government of India that you should he authorised to carry out homhardment suggested if ultimatum to he issued hy Thomas is rejectee As regards subsequent blockade I have sale I would reserve opinion till further consultation with Senior Naval Officer and review of situation. Resident.Telegram From To Repeated Code. {. M. S. M X&lt;TTP IN * , He nj amr aa i o^. Political Keelaent, BuePlie. H.N.o. P.C., H.M.S. 'T’RIAP 1 ', Bomba; 1 -. No. 1031. Dated 5th received 6th Apr ID 1930. Following from ^homaa, beglne ;- Ohleote that p^e hoped for from local blockade (l) It prove? a deterrent Dlbbah from aiding HASAN, (?,) i + - cauper sufficient local discomfort to affect Hasan's cretin. Hasan is in strong position. It v-oulo appear probaWe that his plan after bombardment would be to retire to the mountains, refusing to treat for terms ana hop. -ing to emerge after operations with enhanced prestige amongst SH.IHTJH. It is desirable that no steps be left untaken to the end that his own people bring pressure upon him to the accentuation of an intermediary and terms while operations ore inprogress. It is considered‘that local blockade would be some contribution towards influencing tribal minds. As regards Senior Neval Officer's views on Trucial Coast reaction. I took the liberty of tentatively sounding Resia- -ency Agent on the advisability of warning the 'rvcial Chiecr in the event of blockade and he concurred. It. is cesjr- _able that the SHIHUH find their normal facility for purohas- -ing arms and supplies, from Tructhl villages interfered with. The limit of '’rucinl co-operation desired is non-cooperation. 'TJTF IN”44/7 node. H.M.S. '.VreTfl*, Hen;•&gt;'o. Political Repid.ent, BuPhire. Telegram From To No. 1731. Bated 5th received fith April 1930. Your 335. Thomep and hie Council colleague pieeent Ctry^ consider that terns of ultimatum should be unditional eurr- -ender only. In the e^ent of his aurrender an Imredipte Is. 5,000/- fine on Khasab and Rha.iFh’p impr.lponnent for terra of one year in Muscat and on his release to give a surety of i$s- 10,000/- to be of good behaviour. Thomas suggests that, if you approve, these conditions be referred to Muscat and that if action is anticipated dur'lng the next week, Baiyid Said be reonested to proceed in next up mail when he kkx can be met at Herman by M /M. ^AXB' in older that he may be present. ’•LUPIN'.44/7. Telegram From To No 339. Dated 7th April 1930. Code. political Besident, Bushire. Government of India, XajtxiS® Simla. I'k Imp ort ant . My telegram No. 332 of 4th April. Khasah. Muscat Council consider that ultimatum to Sheikh should demand unconditional surrender. In event of surrender fine and short term of imprisonment would he imposed and Sheikh would he released on furnishing security for good behaviour. I consider this suitable. It is possible that Sheikh may retire to mountains hoping to emerge after bombardment with enhanced prestige among tribes. In this event pressure could be brought to bear on him by causing discomfort to tribe either by repeated bombardment at uncertain intervals or by local blockade as seemed desirable. De mi-Official I hope His Majesty’s Government will grant very early authority for sloop to take action. Thing I really fear is repercussion on Trucial Coast where as you know I am being urged to arrange facilities for B. A. F. Failure to clear up situation at Khasab will make matters much more difficult whereas surrender of this petty Sheikh would have salutary effect. Delay however is creating unfortunate impression on Arab mind. * oca i ri on t. -Telegram From To No 1236. Da tea 7tli reed 6 th April 1930. Code. H. 1'. S. 'Lupin', Henjamradio. Political .Resident, Bushire. % * '7 Following from Thomas. The probable situation aris^ing after a ■bombardment and nature ol contingent action on our part requires consideration# Two ends are desiied. (1; A Shihuh situation that will ensure continuance ol bulianate Wali in Khasab. (2) The surrender or aouication of Sheikh Hasan. As regards (1) the first step aesirable is dissociation on Dibba’s part of any further alliance with Hasan. This may be hoped from moral effects of punitive action against Khasab especially exem|)lary effects of our employment/of blockade measures. Disavowal on Dioba's part should be followea up by his being informed of requirements of Muscat State's authority, namely a Walls continued /Residence at Khasab, and Dibbals own responsibility in the event of future retaliatory measures against Wali on the part of whomsoever. As regards l2) it would be unwise to reckon on change in Hasan's defiant and uncompromising attitude, punitive action being taken calculated to discredit him but there is no reason why he should voluntarily aoaicate Shaikhshlp unless through tribal pressure or by disinterested advice, The only apparent candidate for Khasab, if such is desired, is one of Bakna's nephews who may on the point of honour be expected to decline if dictated by British or Muscat Authorities. Pny durable solution would have to be based on tribal consent. It would appear that an independent intermediary may be best means for ffapprochement, one who is personally acceptable P miII acceptable to trioes. The man whose envoy most ^likely to he listened to is 3aid Kaqtum Sheikh of Dihai. The Shihdh-Bani-Yas- Hinawi partisanship and Sheikh Said* independence, apart from personal prestige, should disarm suspicion. Borne vol^untary movement on Liha^s part offering Shihuh to approach authorities on uheir hehalf would, if made in good faith soon after operations commencoa, seem to me to be of service to doth sides, 'Lupin*44/7 Telegram 11. / iTOin Senior Naval Cifleer ,, Triaa H Bomoa^, To Coin ander-ln-Suiei', Saat Indies. No 666. Bepeated Politloal .Resident, Busuire. No. 6c36« Dated dtd reed 9tb April 19SO. Delay of Bis Aajaaty’s Government in giving a decision as to action to be taken ao Ktxasab is having grave effect. Matters have boon serious there lor eonsiaex'able time and it is Quite clear a conspiracy exists in several districts to combine to flout British authority. 3very day's delay further encourages rebellious attitude and consequent severity of punishment measures which will ultimately have to be taken, Arab views oi good government differ largely from Western ideas and centre in respect for strong right arm. During the past two years Senior Naval oificer has icaratxxxx noticed very clear indications of lessening respect xor authority of Great Britain on both coasts of Oman and has heard Sheikhs frankly state that they regard Great Britain as a decaaent Power. Unless Ktiasab is now reduced to complete suomission British authority in the orsian Gulf will receive a most damaging blow. This will have an especially advers*^^ effect on respect for His Majesty’s Navy, which is recognised as instrument for enforcing British control. Senior Naval Officer respeetfu ly submits that tnese views may be placed before Admiralty as a department of His lajesty's Government materially involved. senior Naval officer supports proposals in 'Lupin's* 2114' of April Bra. ( ^ 1 1 ^ 7 P* ~y ' Senior Naval Officer.wOCl 6 • Political Bssidant, Bushire. Senior ITaval Officer ”Triad w Bom'bay. Wall received letter this evening Tuesday from Oheikh of Khasah ordering him to leave the town. It is considered doubtful, if he could resist a determined attack, and a very early decision as to action against Shaikh is requested. •‘Lupin’*. Code. Government of India, Simla, political Resident, Bushire. Telegram To Prom Ho 346. Dated 9th April 1930 Important. My telegram of 7th April ho. 339. following from •Lupin* begins;- Wali received Shaikh is requested. Ends. Ilesident. ft; mj t48 hours ultimatum issued to Sheikh Ha^san at 1000 today&lt;1 A1 Sa'idi' I Khasa'b. * \ri / j / / / 1 U ( T ^c_) &gt;1^1; NS l^th^ April _ 1930 . ^1^1! *■ % Dear TKo^jr^ This is to give you the news from here. A1 Sa 1 !^ put in at Diha and Kumzar on our way north. At Diha Shaikh Salih came off to see us hut the feeling there was not such that we cared to go ashore and on arriving /here I later heard that Shaikh Hasan of Khasah was at Diha all the time. A.t Kumzar two of the local shaikhs' came off to see us and I went ashore. Shaikh Hasan returned to Khasah 3 days after we arrived hut his attitude has remained uncompromising. The Wali is still in his fort hut is not alio ed to go into the hazar nor are his servants. Three nights ago he received a letter from the Shaikh inviting him to leave •Shaikh Hasan*s town of Khasah*. H.M.S.Lupin has heen here throughout i.e.for the past five weeks and are getting tired of it as of course no one daie land. I wrote an appreciation of the situation 2 days after my arrival which H.L.S.Lupin sent to P.B. hy fast mail and as the slow down mail does not call here I sent a wireless message to Secretary Bushire asking him uo send a copy to you also of telegrams to keep you au ^.t with the•situation. Two days ago H.M.S. Lupin received a message from P.B.. saying the shaikh’s house may oe demo wished if C - in - C concurred. Shaikh Zuhair,Saiyid Malak and I considered that this action alone would not achieve the results2 results desired and we asked that the scope of operations may he extended. There is no reply yet hut we anticipate one shortly. The shaikh is in a very strong position of course and unless adequately chastened will never agree to a Sultanate Wali remaining in Khasah. Are you coming up here ? and is Saiyid Sa'id ? I hope you think he should. I anticipate that operations will last for some weeks if a satisfactory and permanent settlement is looked for. I hope you are fit again. I am very sorry to miss Mrs.Murphy and Pat hut I wish them both hon voyage.following from Thomas, Reference your telegram Ho.368 sent message as follows dated seventh to Secretary to Political Resident Bushire. Shall he grateful if you will send copy of my report to Political Iluscat and copy of all my telegrams ends. Terms ultimatum unconditionally surrender bombardment take place tomorrow Sunday 1000, Will keep you informed any development 1935 19th April H.IRS,'Lupin' • • ft -/* / i Telegram (Code; Tom To P. A.L'uscat, l Reference your374 dated 16th April and my 1244 iStii April 'bombardment of yiieilcii Hassan'a quarter of Kiiasab and neighbour -Deni nadiyah village and local craft and ’‘An oaid' to«day 20th april. Sheikh iiassan’s house nas hit by shells . After 'bombardment a verbal ■2T dL^,‘j ^urpor Lmg com4Jig r I 1 * 01 - Sheikh was received ashore to see him* This request nas refused* It is rep or ted Lhat h.c She inh has gone* Lo the m.un ,• .ins and it is doubtful whether message came from. him. It is novi proposed to carry out bloackade of area South mi hast of line joining Has Sheikh M&amp;sud and western points of entrance to Hor Cfhokub Ali* Addressed to R. repeated to Commander-in-Chief hast Indies,S .jn . 0. there 'tfas carried by h*M«S* * Lupin* h.h.S.’'Cyclamen 1 A requesting S.n.O.x'ersian (iUj-f’s interpreter be sentHo. 136-3. of 1930. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bus hire, the 28 th March 1930. The under^mentioned paper is forwarded in original to the Political Agent at Muscat for disposal. By Order, Mia Captain, for Secretary to the political Kesident in the Be r s i an Gulf. Subject :.?1 our supplied by t; e ’’ORMOHDii'• to the Wall of Khasab on 10th Marcii 1930. Letter Ho. S10/20/A, dated 17th March 1930, from the Commander, H.M.3. '^unu'' at lihasab, with en closure. 7 V&gt; 3 —»To The Hor^ble, The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to forward the attached claim for Rupees four, Annas fourteen, from the Commanding Officer, H.M.S. 'Ormonde,' on account of the supply of 50 Lbs. of flour to the Wali of Khasab. It is requested that the amount may be remitted direct to H.M.S. 'Ormonde.' 2. The issue of provisions from H.M.S.'Ormonde' was rendered necessary in consequen.ce of the action of the Sheikh of Khasab in prohibiting supplies from the bazaar to the Wali as reported to you in my signal 1304 of 7th March, 1930. I have the honoir to be, Sir, Your obedient servantPROM .. The CoamiaaiUng; Officer, ' ORMONDE ' . DATS 12th March, 1930, Ref. No. 14. TO .. The Senior Naval Officer, PERSIAN GULP. (Through - The Commanding Officer, H.M.S. •LUPIN'] Subject. - FLOUR SUPPLIED TO WALI OP KHASAB. Submitted, On 10th March the Wali of Khasab reported to R*M*S. 'ORMONDE* that the Sheikh of Khasab had cut off his supplies and that he was without food. He was accordingly supplied with 50 lbs. of flour from ship , s stores. 2. - It is requested that arrangements may be made for the cost of these provisions i.e., 7s/3|d (Rs. 4, As. 14) to be recovered through the Political Agent, Muscat.Preliminary note on Shihuh politico* I A brief note »ould appear to be neceesary to giro recent ements a background* The g hilwdl are the ;ude» suspicious and wild inh&amp;blimits of Ktl f US Ah JX&amp;AU Pos»ibly in part aborigi- nal ( their alleged descent from the Asdite inv ader of the 2nd Century A*£. salilc bin yaham ie iiaprobable) they are tiore ignorant and uncouth than their neighbours either of fruoial Oman or of the Guianante*Kthnologi- o&amp;xly they are not one. the Kumsara of the Tillages of KUms&amp;r exclusively and of Khasb and Llosh partly are Iranian elements*racially and linguist!col y peculiar, and it is they who have established &amp; shailchly asoendanoy over the southern half of the ahlhah, by ^hloh tribe in and politics they have been absorbed* this out-hem confederation by rume hani Shatair and a norli.cm one nan! Had!yah together compose 'the Sihhuh txkm tribe* the 0 scats of their Shaikhs are Dibah and Xh&amp;sb reapeotively* These towns are the foci of shihuh politics* T**# X&amp;c Sheikhs ars generally regarded as equal and rival* Their respective confederations the n&amp;ni Had!yah and the hani shatair { with which is associated the duioasssa) are traditional eneiuies ^oid are normally divided by old blood feuds* Historically, the ice oping of the tribal peace between thsae two elements has been the ’raison d’etre* of the Sulatanate wall at Xhltfifth* The Shihuh, when free from external cares are thus a house divided a^anist b^self, but they ^ntite in the face of the oomson enemy -traditionally the neighbour ing dA?ASi* tribe. The sliihuh belong to tiie Hinawl fact! the qAWASiM to the OiiAfARI faction* The menace which the qAWASIJt cenatituted for die inhabitants of rtusandam. Iifege -* 2 i- % t Musandam aocounte for 12 &gt;e merging of the Oxmazara arid Interior Shihuh eieiaentaf it also explains the adhesion of the shihnh tribe as a whole to the muscat State* The Shihuh looked to the Imam Saiyid Sa*id bln Sultan for protection from the awaeim .hen he his wars against trie ooi- on enony in toe early years ol the last century* Prom the time of uaiyid sa’ld son saiyid Thuv.aini onwards a -mli an oint ed fro^ jaueoat has throughout* it is believed* resided at iQms&amp;b fort* The presence of this *ali was deairabls to the Shihuh standing as it did for the moral sup. ort of sueoat* Tie a ns the ^awaglsu ind the «?ali functioned ride Miles Vol* 3 pp* 446 In the maimer 1 hare indicated* The last siilhuh - vA^A3IM trouble occurred in 1922 ostensibly orer a, territorial question connected «ith RAMS and SHA'AM a local Alsace -Lorraine* One of H*&amp;* Ship was employed for the conference# The issue favoured the qA^ASlX* Several rhihuh Sheikhs of whom one was Sheikh Hasan the present Malcontent were taken off to Huscat and Imprisoned there* To the unwillingness or inability of ssusoat to maintain its traditional sup ort of iihihuh versus qA^ASln in the day of troubls 9 may be ascribed a certain cooling of their loyalty* Cause at any rate is not to be found in any excess of interference ratner tiie reverse* for the wali's authority for so;ie ye^xrs past has been shadoyt Rsvenuo taken from the hiihuia is of t^'.e lightest kind* none in fsc t out aide the t.on of Omaab whore a nomxnal * aakat* in kind on dates* onions and &amp;he«p provides about 600 rupees annually - a bagatelle* and not sufficient to maintain the all and his askaries* Customs imposts are nowhere imposed on the shihuh as tiiey are elsewhere along the tfulAdnate mmxm coasts** 1 H. ' h * : -r : g * jrtige -i 3 «• traditionally* the ahihuh, of all tribes » are said to haye been boastful of their loyalty to the sons of S&amp;'id bin sultan i.c. the Albu Sa'id X/ynaaty, and in the oxann Cibil bar eoiae 16 years a^o towards the end of aultan y&amp;isal's reign* ^nihuh elements fought at bidbid under the liusoat baiiner* Of late years however the j&amp;uaeat ties would seen to have been veaitening* three factors have contributed to this* (l) the passing of the old native fora of uovern&amp;ent regiise in Muscat itself • the patriarchal fora that preceded the rounoil of btate - hen tribal hheikhs periodically visited the xtuler* a personal roller* and came away aith ’bahta 1 ( preirndt of rice &amp; coffee 4b money» perhaps of amrimition if the Mheikh had a war in hand at the tim)« (il) a changing 'abasia aituatlon v JU aii has strucJc at the roots of the nutual Identity of interests* (ill) a realigning of bhlhuh acntiiannt towards the frucial aide; for the resen tram t to foreign octivltlee* a natural condition of -ind in the rude i&amp;ilhuh* find the frucral spirit* recently exanpllfied m the unaccossscdatlng altitude towards tt*A«jr* activities* more xn ac ord with its Own*ifege -s 2 i- ^ ^ tihciiZh isunamimd is ixnoae j tioncwl za&amp;ster of isaicha though threa nephew* of ^Aporu&lt;.uo« li.v* with hJL«t Ahioad» Abdul ah and aulaiman all aulaa ^uhaiw.ad* un* oi these would be a probable candidate for ^aaab if it were van ant a* Sheikh haean i* only surriTor of Sheijchly house of :&amp;a«;.b* one of thee* nephew* Ahaad bin jaihauiiiad x* xn close personal touch with bheik ^asan of Ahasab* He waa reported to be intriguing last year to reiaove hxe uncle sheikh ^iLa/iu ad of naKba In order to auoce^d him* sheikh -iuhn. ad and sheikh Hasan of Aha sab are not believed to be in friendly term* though they belong to the Hani Hadiyah c enfederatiun* ^ Village Confederation sheikh local atrencth* KHASAB BAH I f SHEIKH 1i\SA.F bin 1200 rifles* inm?i*AT&gt; See footnote. \UB2AR jCIHAZAKA { tlie Hhcikhly house of Bani SHATAIK) (a) Sheikh muhar.^ ad 50C rifles. HsbAi. (b) Sheikh Abdullah bin sultan. (o) Huhaui ad bin Eilal. (d) Zaid bln Yaslr. JULHAR dibah Mt&amp;i. • Jbur sheikhs of KUmsara - a poor spiritless people who own perhaps one third of the date gardens of Khaeab .here they come in the sur&amp;mer • possess a fort on the seat side of Khaeab s ar the hereditary emmalmo of the bani nadiyah of the/ to n whom they fear, bheikfe Muhamxisd Bahdi ( 60) with the strongest following ( nearly one half of the tribe) ie loyal to the Muscat connection. Abdullah bln Sultan (60) in does toioh with Sheikh bal&amp;h of Blbah. is hi* rival m the tribe. Mahmaim4L bin Hilal (40) is the most enlightened of a poor lot and a frequent visitor to the fracial Ooa&amp;t. He is however not trunted. 2 ^.id bin Yaeir (24) a Sheik in name but is young and without much influence* i Ban! Hadiyah Alarur bin All ( deceased) KUBAZAHA aul^aisaad bin naraisu 50 rifles. f jfl 70 Banl bhatair Salah bin I^uhaisrad 2000 M See footnote. ^ootno te. the outstanding personalities of ohihuh are (a) idu ikh iiaaan b i n h^iha^w ad, the paramount aheikh of the •oaui '3adiya)i confederaiion who lives at Aahasi.b. (b) Sheikh balah bin ^uhamg^d ( a Kumasari) th^ paraaount Sheikh of the Ban! Shatair confederation who ixves at Bibah.-* 3 i- Both are men of atreotsth and otanding in their tribe* uoth. are limited in outlooic fanatical* Jbotb are auibitioua* ^heilch iifc. en bill Muha iu ad of ia a mvi of about 32 he vily built - rVuther bo^oriah stupid in comreraation but resolute in action* he succeeded hxm wiser uncle ha*id bln tfulaiiaan aoim to it years a£© and from the firnt ahowed himself vain arid independent* ;li.de a practice of not sailing on H*.'i* ships and when tiie hultun &gt;yp.id p. virji t to Kfcaaab two years ago did not come off to Uie ship and titen delayed an hour before coming to amke his ©all at the fort* 7 b.cn aoiyld be* id the present ^resident of tne Council came on visit in the early part of this year the Sheikh did not bother to coxae and pay hxs respects to all* sheikh Hasan is traditionally the enemy of Sheikh S&amp;lah but inters i into agreement *Xti. him for presenting a solid front to protect their supposed raatual interests in the orwmde incident. He is traditionally in alliance with Bakbfv »id eppoeed to •Cumsar* Me married a dau&amp;hte; of Um late Sheikh of Limah by \d 103 e recent death iie is said to have inherited considerable property at himah* He is weil off and trader himself' at 'O&amp;msh v here he has at least one small dhow. Sheikh aaiih bin ad of Plbah about 40 years old the elected Sheilch of the ban! nhat&amp;ir but in origin a poor i^juazari* A pale insignificant individual with rather an inflaimsable terser* Is crafty» clever and concerted - is the most important personality in the bhihuh and api^ears to be able to muse Khasab his butt* is on closest terms with bheikh Hamad of fujairah the alliance believed to be defensive and offensive* The town of Dibah he chares rather unequally with the Aav&amp;sim tsheiich aashid bio Abzeed* The latter a loyal supporter of authority having only about 200 men and apimars to live on eufference* 01 ah follows bheihh oaiah as also the uhlhuh elements of bha'am near Kan t.l Khaim* he has recently built a baanar of eo^e 14 uhops on the seashore at Dibsh .here he himself trades* He possesses a dhow* ^aiyid Kasir bin Kjri alftm * age 42 the all of Khasab has been in that fort for nearly four years* A Sultan 1 s nominee he is a pure Arab and of good family* iimd experience before as wali of JKurbat in South Arabia* He has been a cypher in the affairs of Kh&amp;sab where Shoikh Hasan has b$en ths *de facto* Uovernor in nature of the situation he has not attempted to inter fere except the exceptional caces e*g* ( 1 ) slavery (il) murder and has usually been resisted in both* juast year a murder took place in Khasab bazaar of an itinerant JHoroccan or Egyptian doctor* a Baiyid* Theft ms the motive* The wall appealed in vain to the Hhei kh to hand the taurderera over and they presumably escaped justice* During the Mali’s term of office this is the first v^ord of complaint from the bhlhuh against him. His is a pleasant but not strong character and during the recent troubles he/£ made several appeals to h**i* ships to hi«i an tiui &lt;icor*; of fear.DIAKY OJf XVKMIB 4th January • Uth jtaroht 1930* 4th January* 5th January r\ 32nd January 23rd Jenuary 24 th January 25th January 27th - 23th January 22 th January* 29 th January 50th January - 3rd February February* 5 th Jabruary* * Ormondft“ pi*oce dcd fvcn t to Khaeab oai rying waXr» thaaab ( returning from leave) and me a ganger ( Interpreter ) of Counoll of state with 3 letters to Sailiuh Ghelich to af ford faollltlse to eurvey ship* letters A tc 3hel£h Khasah} B to ftheiih hiba$ C to ttiiQt kh ihUdia* ,t OmoIide ,, arrived i£hasab 9 vail landed and was well received by sheilch* * 0 rmoiide* left with Interpreter* Ho letters .m yet preeonted* •Ornonde* returned to Ihr.o&amp;b and letter A presented* Sheikh asked for time to consider and after entertain ing ship’s Officers nnd toll granted permission for ascent of hill required by officere next day* Hill ascended* But In evening Shaikh forbade reaaoent on merrew or. score of B&amp;xm'a opposition* ho one a i low ad to ascend* hut In evening sheikh again agreed to ascent for fallowing day* Hill ascended, hut In evening shaikh forbade ascent for the future* Purvey Officers camped on beach but hill ascent not allowed* sheikh of Bakha arrived vhesab* Council's letter C presented* *onaonde* left on understaruling it would return after six days to obtain Khasub Bakha's pomi&amp;aiont as the Bheikha were not clear as to which of them owned hill* iheikh Sakha left ihasab for Bakha* 2hoikh Biba arrived Kh^sab and was presented with Council's letter B* Hheikh Diba remained fOmsab 4 days* A pact was aworn on oath between Sheikh Diba» Sheikh Khaeub» and 3 Sheikhs of J&amp;imzar for - ( I ) Resistance to any ascents of aheikh hills by ths has&amp;ra ( Cliristians )* (II) To expel bultanate all* Sheikh dibit left Khasab for Bibs* * ormonde' arrived j^hasab* Shekih Aha sab in refusing help stated that hill belonged to Sheikh bakha* 'urnonde 0 with all on board then proceeded to Hakha where libelkh said lie*could not co-operate as all the Badus were opposed to it* 'urmor^de (I) 11 left and landed .all at khasab*JUST IKK A. 0 gib^ Prom bin MtihungtHtd Utoeikh of Khaoab* To aal/Xd Itasir bin ^balfan »aii of fChaoab and bbeikh Inrahim bin /dibcuifiiad bin jus * 9 aossongor of C uncil of Ministors* thm tribe in general and particular bare been inforaod that you are desirous of placing a flag in the Ku f us al Jabal* This is absolute,y inpoesible and never obtainable from them neither as a favour nor with a price* Bo not trouble us with a thing that we cannot endure* «e apologize to you* Bo not expect the friends to acco&gt; pany you tomorroe morning to the places you require* we earn you against it* Be it knovn to you* it is our desire to assist you to procure what is required so that you may be advanced by your good asrixs service with the government and officials ’but muchness of water mil spoil the flour* • rarden us* If you can wait so that *e can consult them as It has always been the custom* date 1548 received end of January. *Your honoured letter has reached us and the contents hare been understood* rarticularly with regard to the arrival of the man-of-war at Shabus and Khasab* he informed my brother that we will not sire our places to any body absolutely 9 neither to the wealc nor to any body else* As for you t you are not a Alng over us so that you might discover our conditions and we wish you to postpone the interference. And if the King ttaiyld Taunur arrived in the land of :msoat we will follow on his tracks to see what the ministers are doing in this matter* This ie what had to be said and saluams. j ■ - ■ ilatter C* ifrom ilaaan bln iftthanraad bln Sultan Sheikh of Kh&amp;eab* To the Lored the honoured Sahib of 'Cyclaaen* the reepocted* After Salftetae and CotapllmmtB and hospitality your letter arrived* You wish us to oo&amp;ie off to your ship for settlestent of the natter between ue and sheikh jssUmul ad bin Ahmad Sheikh of hakim* be it known that X am a little sick and 1 apologise to you for that because your previous x&amp;sss&lt;mger(s) Shan Sahib Sheikh Isa has regarded that v.hich he has regarded* Should your honour desire the hobble (writer) awaits your arrival* Be it known to you and salaams* written on the 3th nhaww&amp;i 1348* Mletter D* In naa» ef God the Highest, ifrom all the eeiraasmlty of Ban! Had 1 yah ( tribe) To the honoured the lored Captain of il«£Ua«*Cyclaae&amp;' the respected. Hay God the highest aaro hlau reaoe be u&lt; on you and the mercy of God and his hies singe always. That which Inform you Is that a letter reached Sheikh Hasan you want from him to emharlc on the ship for settlement of the matter. Than be it known to you that he has no choice In this and If you have any answer come ashore and will answer you# as for the sheikh *e hare forbidden him to come off. This is for you to be informed, Bated 5th Shawwal. 3 —3—30.(From all the Mhlhuh ooisimuiity of Idah to tthlekh lea bin Abdul Xatlft Agent). All Hadue of Kxdah* To the high* glorious* honoured and Stately Shei ih lea bln Abdul latlf* the reelected* Say the uod Highest save him. rease be upon you and aod^ jaerey and bleealngs always* and after be It known to you that tiie incident ^hleh haa hap,one ed in connection with the Kn&amp;liah cuid mbjecta of Sheikh Hasan and of sheikh 3uha :ad bin /duoad wo have heard about it and now we infona you to bo ca.roAil you und Uie j&amp;ngj.iaL. And Sheikh Hasan and all his subjects we have nothing to do with you and do not be interferors in our proecincto and properties und the place in which your desire lias is our property and preeiuot and whoever of you trespasses in that quarter not one of you will return by Cod by Uod by uod and by the nerds glory and by the right of ths Proud* -e desire *Jahad' (religious war) and kill whosoever arrives in our quarter and will spare no one of them to return* There ie no Uovernor to tiovem ue and we are Independent by ourselves and Y&gt;e do not regognis* aheikh nor Governor nor Huitan and now we warn you with every warning and be cautious to arrive at this place* And you O Sheikh Isa pardon from your honour be helpful to defend off the enexay with jseans that will succeed and this ie what le required of you* This is the police of the infidels and do not bring upon yourself blame* And a hint will suffice the wise* This Is what we have told you* *e drink the blood and do not care* It ie requested from you to fend off this matter and do not inter* fere a in our precincts and property* four despotism be upon yourselves and your danger be upon yourselves* Po not hadbc blame ue and salaams* jd*hairaaad bin Sulaiman, Sheikh al Badu in iCidah* r :XX. A natural impulse of this fanatical tribe jealous to preserve its aoil sals unmolested by infidels was a revenge itself on the ru&amp;c&amp;t Government that had dared to aid and abet. ill. Ifp to this time the Muscat connection was obviously not irxsoDe. By it the Sin huh profiled nothing, suffered nothing, feared no timing. In f.ct they claimed to cherish a sentinent for susoat. Kev&gt;ilnion of feeling la the outcome of tiie iztaglnod disservice of M^iscat to Bhih’ih Interests. XV. Tiie nhihuh# cIob© neighbours of Has al Khaim and eye . it no sacs of the latter^ attitude to^aurds H.A.jf. • a position not improbably magnified in the tribal mind to defianoe of British internets with impunity, have been emboldened to emulate example. V. Sheikh Hasean of Khasab could not have taken up the uncompromising 11ns he did without ass ranee of the sworn backing of his rival Sheikh Salah ef I&gt;iba and his Kumsari ailiss. Vi. ahslkh Hasan*s acquiescence to Survey party’s design In the first place would set n to havs a blind, followed as It was by an immediate volte face. The equivocation that followed was ap^rently designed to gain time in order to canvass support for a united resistance. VXX. There was a close pact ( mads between 30th January and JL 3rd February) thro*ightout between the sheikhs of Khasab and Diba and 3 of Vie 4 sheikhs of Kumzara. The one Kumzari b ei h who appears to havs remained loyal to authority was Muhasirad bin All al Mahdi. This presumption needs testing by reference to the signatories of their letter addressed f|| || ai the Sheikh of Ba^ha ( it is iinderstood that a -copy waswas forwarded to political Hoaldent by the Britieh Agent)* YIXX. the Sheikh of Bakha f 8 particpation or otherwise in the pacrt is not clear from present evidence. A strong suspicion attaches to hie nephew Ahmad bln ifiuharjmad of Sakha, the apparent misunderstanding which arose over the Shiekh's personal dispute with the Sheikh of iQiasab the unwillingness of each to meet the other and the unsatis factory incident of the ownership of the hill look as though these delaying incidents were part of a concerted plan. Aganlst this and in the dheikh 9 * favour is the tremendously important step he took of showing the British Agent a secret letter Incriminating all but one of the other dheikhe of ahihuh.i thm present situation. Slielkh Hasan of Khasab is on &amp; visit to Llreah and Diba. The rumour that has gone there and to Fujairah to enlist the support of thr tribes in the event of punitive action being taicen against mat ( as indioated in P.H f s telegraia He* 29X) so far lacks oonflrmtion but It is not lic, rebac le. He s&amp;s reported to be nt al ihrsha near JDiba on 27th the da/ i left Dlba. X have written to hla to cone at Khasab to see me* the stall is still living in his fort at /Q»a*ab but without Influence and indeed Is unable to go in sr-feijr to the village where the sheikh’s ordflr for* bidding tiie bazaar to sell him f od etill bolds, h* is therefore still being sustained from one or other of X landed at Kura&amp;zar on 27th where situation Is normal. 3k. wuhaganad bin All al kahdlh Bh.^iha: ad bin Hilal are with me In Al Sa’id. The other two Shieidis Abdullah bin Sultan and Zaid bin fa sir are in iiiba. the ships in harbour • at present Al sa*id. The Sheikh has left a retainer one Htlal bln All / in his place. This man has not called on me In Al Sa’ii but ia response to tsj letter inviting him to do so has expressed his willing ness to receive me ashore. As this has no full powers to treat for ahiekh Hasan or the Shihuh X have not considered such a meeting with him necessary. At Siba . hen X arrived on 26 th aheikh Sah to see me. He wbs clearly frightened* X did not bi« with his letter B by which he had incriminated himself at the outact, as it may later prove to be 1 politic to localise the ares of punitive measurea. Conditions in the Hhihuh country render the nature,! and scope of punitive measures a matter requiring much careful consideration* Kh&amp;sab is a cove flanked by steep cliffs where concealed tribesmen could make landing a matter of s difficulty.Jftg* -I 2 i- The bO iCh itoexT ie a g;cnti/ shelving one InvolTlog Xor«g stxetobee of dangerous ^-3uUr»g ee^dciaily *oam stages of the tlde^ It xa teemed b/ &amp; data grove which would afford coniiXder&amp;bio oovor to dv;fangora* the old ^ortuguase fort is in a &amp;tate of rum and would h£ive to bo built u*&gt; ia iuO^oved wa/ froaa inside by Lifiy force that iandod to oo^u^jT it* Vi*o6»e coua^daratAons pius hoeUie r^fdo etxeiigth of i5d0 «nd bviu^id it aii a funaUoai i iny i unyieidiAig spirit are c -♦* 4 *dex*.:itlone ^Aicii in Jud^nont iwreculda Wo ^oe WiXity of aoi*ig the ^saaat luf&amp;ntrjr %*th any hope of amasariis suocoua* 'i!Ue Ghdhuit dorive a good doai of thoir livolihood from fiohxng oca trading tn*d pearl listing* are therefore vulnerable to osa powers and could bo mad© to oufier by a Meetede* rrosouxo also cculd b© a pi lied bp* the sequestration of certain date gardens o&amp;ned by them in tho ii&amp;tin&amp;hn fnie measure in itself ho-over &lt;*ouid be iniiuf ^icinet to induce a spirit of as.y**sa^ig.v surrender* ( ^i eh asasuroa oouXd pexh&amp;^a be considered as threat* to be carried out in the event of bhe *h hasan not c^reerng to a fine payment or peroonai surr^ssider to b© ioilowed by hie iiuprieomaent in muscat* fou may deem the envisaging of such oontii^goncies premature at the moment as the uhexkh has not ytt returned to ti hh mkk and it is not considered possible fox him to return before ^©dnesd&amp;y 2nd at the earliest* Indeed in view of (i; seriousness of hi© later actions# witness letter h to Sheikh Isa purporting: to cotie fro® oo 2 .*e nonentity but obviously inspired by the Sheikh (ii) the excellent sanctuary his inacoessibls mountains provids# he may not be prepared at this stage and without ©ome pressure to come in of his e«n free will and treat for terms*FROM DATE No. Tho Soaior Haval Offioor, ? oral on O-alf Division, H.M.S, •TRIAD* at Bombay. 1 The Ilonourahlo the Roiitxcal Roaidont la tho Poraiaa Quohlr©. (Copy to tho Political Acont, Kuooat) B4th March, 3.030. 3C/J t 7b j // . The follovd.nc extract from a report tho Senior Navul Officer from the ComLiaaciiag Of floor. H.M. S* *LUPIK* la ooiDmmioated for tho infomnatioa of tho Honourablo the Politio-al Realcicsat in tho Persian Gulf (Copy to Political Afient fit Muscat). •Date 13th March, 1930. 'Gaxabuh 'Tufa 1 an* No. 3449 C, owner Suleiman •bin Jafur of Suvalk, Rakhoda Moh^nmod bin Saloa, •oarry±ii£i ricoj Hour, coffee, ougar and dates from •Dobai to Dlbah, boarded by H.M.S. •LUPXII* at Khasab •where she was sheltering from a Shumal. •Tho Udkhoda reported that soon after hor arrival •at Khaoab a man hailod hor fro^ the rocks and asked •the Kdkhoda to come ashore. VJhon tho Kakhoda had •landed he was informed that ho would not be permitted •to return to his Sambuk until he had paid the Sheikh of Khasab Ro.20. Tho Hakhoda complained but was •compelled to pay this su#, which ho did with Rs.7 •and a bag of rice worth Re. is. The Nukhoda stated •that he was going to inform the Wall of Suvaik on •arrival ? One Persian and one Hindu Merchant, both of •Dibah were onboard as passengers. It appeared that •they were in the habit of buying stores on the •Truoial Coast, usually Debui, and importing them to •the Batinoh, usually Khor Fokan, Dibah and Kalba. * 2. Tho action of the Sheikhof Khasab appears to the Senior Haval Officer to be high-handed and Harbour Dues of Rs.20 for a small ship taking shelter at a natural port like Khaaab seem excessive. The Senior Naval Officer requests he may be informed whether it is correct for tho Sheikh to collect dues at Khasab and not tho Wall of His Highness the Sultan. \V *7^ tJUA 4v/ ^ C A P T A I N SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF ' v ‘ K v-'r^ \ V ^ tDEPARTMENT- BRANCH, Latter File No. SerUl No. Draft Memorandom Taltfriun Class for telegrams Ordinary Exprea* Urgent* Priority CWr Ljoe-*- •Only for Foreign Telegram*. fNot for Foreign Telegram*. To bo ieonod on 1st Reminder tnd Reminder Srd Reminder Hawiing; : Cnte ©t Diary No.- leeaed ** No. . 5j_ 7^ 193 c J To If pest eopy of telegram required- Date of despatch, of above List of enclosures !l/ U) \ . ^ &lt;v S. 5. The Council of iiinisterb to K.li the Sultan of Muscat L Otian, LiUSC c!.t • A.C • I have the honour to inlorm you unat I nave recexved a letter iron ane c-U.C., ^crsiau eull, stating that tne She itch oi Xhasah is m the haoit of taning harbour dues of xxs.St'/- irom boats eaixing at hha£?ab- The action ox the Sheikh ol Khasab appears to be irregular and I shall be hignly obliged if you will let Lie know whether the Sheikh is allowed to recover such taxes or it is for the Tali or H.H.the Sultan to do so. U. E. wm K' na.: j t 1 ft °r &gt; P.A.and H.M’s consul, Muscat* ^ (j.After ooraplinento, V»e heve tii© honour to Hcknowlea^e the receipt of your letter tfo.51, dated the 7th hpril 19o0 # intimuting Uiat you liave received a letter from the henior Naval On icer,Perfcifin dulf, to the effect that the oheikh of Khauab le in the habit of taxing harbour feeu of Hu.20/- froto boe-tu calling at Khaeab. In reply we atate tiuit the action of the bheikh is irregular and he has no right to take harbour, feee or any tort of tax on goods imported into iOiaiiab and he is not autiioribeu by us to do so. Tills action is one of his irregular actions which he is taking now against the Government. It is for the Government to fix, whenever they like, taxes such as harbour fees on boats and taxes on goods which are imported into Khnsab, and to appoint any person they like to collect them there. U.H. F- i No. 333 / of 1950. Political agency ic H.li.k v e Consulate, Muscat, the ilth april 1950. The xoregoxng copy forvmruea to the becretary to the Hon’ble the Political Hesiuent in tlie Persian Gulf, buehire,und to tiie Senior Naval Oifioer, Persian Gulf Division, with reference to his No. 350/75/4 dated the 24th March 1930, for information. Major,’ \dl Ko * 3 of 1930. political Agency and Consulate, Muscat 21st April 1930. To The Commander, H.M.S, M Ormonde M , Hen jam. 0 Memorandum . Reference your letter Ho.810/20/A dated 17th March 19; to the address of the Hon'ble the political Resident in the lersiai Gulf,Bushire, I have recovered the cost of 50 lbs.of flour suppliec to the ^ali of Khasab from the Muscat State which amount viz. Rs.4//y: is herewith enclosed in postage stamps. jt-lease acJmowledge receipt. Major, Political Agent and H.B.k’s Consul,Muscat.Telegram Code, From Political Resident, Bushire, To R. M. 8. 'Lupin*, Henjamradio. Repeated Senior Naval Officer 'Triad', Boiabay. No. 348* Dated 10th April 1930. Immediate . His Majesty's Government have approved uestruetion of Sheikh's fort if terms not accepted. Ultimatum should he delivered as soon as you receive requisite authority from Commander-in-Chief to take action. Twenty four hours notice woula seem sufficient hut I leave mattex* to your discretion. Resident.Your tela&amp;ram No* 343. Fort at Khaaa'b is occupied ‘by Wali and Bhalkh Hasan resides in house at hack ox' town surrounded hy other buildings and date palms by which it is obscured from the sea. It would therefore be necessary for bombardment to include quarter of the town. Thomas considers this degree of support insufficient to justify his issuing of ultimatum and message i*rom him follows. Keguest instructions. “Lupin** • ■ /-'• * w »44/7. Code* II. M. 3. •‘Lupin’*, Henjamradio* Political liesident, Bushiro. Telegram From To No. 1513. Dated and reed 10th April 1930. Immediate. Following from Thomas:- An isolated bomDardment of Khasab will not restore Muscat's authority there. Unless operations are of sufficient scope to result in discrediting Sheikh - Hasan in tribal eyes, he is certain to remain Sheikh ol Khasab. In that event it would he injudicious for Muscat to issue a strong ultimatum. In any case he is not likely to tolerate Sultanate Wall remaining after E. M Ship# withdraws if action taken against him is inadequate. It is submitted that measures set forth in Lupin'a telegram 2113 of 3rd April are those demandeu hy the local situation. I am therefore not issuing / ultimatum pending your furtfLar instructions. Lupin#44/7 • Telegram Code. From Political resident, Bushire To Government of India, Simla. Repeated Senior Naval Officer -Triad No. 352. Dated 10th April 1930. Immediate. Boinba^ • Reference telegram No. 1204 from Secretary of State to you. Ktiasa'b. In my telegram No. 261 of 16th farcti I recommended destruction of fort. This v,as however nearly 4 weeks ago. Owing to delay opposition has considerably stiffened and measures which il taken promptly might have been adequate will probably not now suffice. Commander of Lupin and Thomas have therefore represented that they do not consider isolated bombardment will have desired effect, and that measures outlined in my telegram No. 332 dated 4th April are minimum necessary to secure compliance with ultimatum, and that it is undesirable to present it unless it will be enforced. I agree and would request therelore that Naval Commander on spot may be accordea reasonable latitude on lines Indicated aDova to enforce compliance with ultimatum. Resident.44/7. Telegram Oode. From Political Resident, Bushire. To li. 3. '1^1^ Henjamradio. No 360. Dated 12th April 1930. I have informed Government of India that owing to delay that has occurred measures which might have proved adequate if taken promptly are no longer so and have asked that you should he given reasonable latitude in enforcing ultimatum. As no reply received n-piuwiT further reference is probably being made to Secretary of State. Resident.Teleg^ara Code. From Political Resident, on fi.R. M VASNA H . To H.J4.R. HenJamradlo. Repeated Senior Naral Officer, Bombay. No. T-64. Dated 16th April 19?j0. ■tj telegram No. 374. H. ^*b. Oovernment have now modi!lea instruct- I -ionB an fo!3ow8. For r/ords 'Bubject to distinct under stand ing that action should entail no loss of humal life” the following should be substituted begins 'on the understanding f that every precaution will be taken against 3 obs of humaii life RESIDENT. Post copy to the Political Agent, Muscat. By order, Capt., for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian ftulf. MohammerahTelegrara From $8peated No. 3?V.&amp;^.v e SofiS££: 0/0 of . ^ MonajrtnerRn. tu lb Datea and received 17th 1930. Your telegram 374 and my ?H3 of 3rd April. It If hoped to reinforce ga.rr If on in Wal i * p fort tomorrow ni^ht Thurnday and to iFRue ultimatum on Friday morning* 'LUPIN”. Code. M Jj ttx&gt; IN”| HenJamrarHo. repeated No. *-65. Dated 17th April 1930. Code. Political Pep} dent, Bnahire. Government of India, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. KhaFab. Following telegram dated 17th April from H..4.S. H LU T:) TN M i begone It in hoped morning. Fnd”*. RKRIDFNT. Pop t copy to the PoMtical Agent, Mu p cat Ik/l^L By order, Capt., for Secretary to the Political resident in the Persian Gulf. aTelegram From To Pepeated No. 1244. Dated and Code. H.M.S. 'TJTPTN', Henjamradio. Political. P.eBident, at Mo hammer ah. Senior Naval Officer, P.G., Bombay. Commander in Chief* Sant Tnolea Station. received 3Bth April 1930. My 2148 of 16th April. TTltimatum wan delivered to Shaikh thin uornin Friday 18th April and expiree at 1000 hoi»ra 20th April. •*litpin h Post copy to the Political Agent, cat .Hy order, Capt., for Secretary to the Political Pea ident in the Pers ”»an OlO f. Mo hammerah, 18th 1 ,44/7 a) Telegram From To Hepeated No. 374. Dated 16th April 1930. IMMEDIATE. H.M's. OfOvernment have approved ueraand for unconditional surrender, and punitive xaxaLBxx action to enforce it within limits recommended in your 2113 of 3rd April but subject to distinct understanding that action should entail no loss of human life. While leaving details to your discretion I consider that ultimatum should he issued accompanied by notification that bombardment will take place at the end of 43 hours and explicitly definingthe area within which there will be risk of shells falling, which inhabitants should be called upon to evacuate. Similarly if bombardment is repeated three hours notice should be given. If bombardment and destruction of local craft prove ineffective I agree to blockade and will call on Trucial Shaikhs to cooperate. If you consider that Isa’s presence would be useful please send for him. Code. Political Resident, Bushire. H.M.3. 'LUPIN*, Benjamradio. Senior Naval Uff*i G er, Bombay. Government of India, idix Simla. RESIDENT Post copy to the Political Agent, Puscat. By order, less* Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, loth April 1930.jj r oiiu »*»»»••■ .* o• it* t To Iroliticai,muscat • jio#1414 dated 26th .vpril i930* M O Please pass to 6ai^ id 6aid uy 1601,20th .wpril* Short bombardment of IQiasiah v/as carried out on 22nd April ana ol Kliasab and neighbouring village to-day 26th April* io vesseie have been allowed to enter or leave and no fishing has been permitted in area mentioned in my 1601 20th April* Khasab and village appear to have been evacuated and there is good reason believing local inhabitants are forsaking Sheikh Hasan who however has support of mountain Badus* iiuscat autho- -rities received letter from Sheikh Saleh of bibah expressing adherence to Luscat Government and condemning Sheixh Hasan's attitude* Addressed to Political Resident,iiushire,repeated to Senior -iaval Offleer,Persian Gulf,Commander-in-ChieC*Hast indies political .^gent,muscat, 1414, 26th April* ti*m. 6* 'Lupin' • ** ^ -s U Copy to Saiyid Said* 27/4/30«» ; -J » -? r~ n *» ■ cl. ±u-JL cl T r hac ; o’h Jlii e&gt; v 5 / / n / \ri ^ — 4 27th April 19'0. n NN This is to give you our news. The situation is very much what one expected it would he. Shaikh Hasan is supported hy the mountain Badus //ho take refuge in the hills during homhardments and emerge during the lulls, The town’s people and neighbouring villages are getting fed up with'him and seceding from allegiance hut it will take more pressure yet to induce general frame of mind from which settlement car: he hopeo for. h T e have since the original big bombardment carried out 2 small ones each of a few minutes duration to make the town untenable and shov/ the locals that we •e in earnest. It has been a rather trying month and I shall not be sorry when it is over. I hope you have received copies of the telegrams from Bushire but in case you have not I enclose a copy from the ship’s log. You will see in No.l 751 I requested that Saiyid 2 a’id should come here. I thought you will come along too but it is bad luck being ill. I sincerely hope you are well again. \w 3 t'*’'**1 ^ ' M Bpi .. i r-ii BassssaiisaSi WSa From Lupin To P.H.BusLire. p/51/3/30. ! / Thomas’report is Being forv;arded per S/S Varsova due BusLire TTednesday April 2nd. Letters have Been sent By Muscat Authorities on Board A1 Sa’id to Sheilh KhasaB hlz requesting his return to EhasaB to meet Thomas But his whereaBouts are uncertain and reply is not expected till aBout Wednesday. Thomas will remajn at KhasaB in A1 Said for the present. I.- 1 M Prom Lupin To P.B.Bushire. B/2/4/30 Beference section 6 of Thomas * report in view of the fact that KhasaB could obtain supplies overland it is submitted that it would Be necessary to Be prepared to take some more immediately effective event of the threat of Blockade failing Sheikh to terms. action in the to Bring the Prom P.B.Bushire To E.K.S.Lupin. D/2/4/30. Important. I agree with your view and should much prefer action more immediately effective. Has Sheikh KhasaB returned yet. If he has and still adopting recalcitrant attitude please let me know what action you consider can Be taken against him to Bring about his submission to Muscat Authority. Is Bombardment likely to T-e effective. If so against what particular point would it Be directed. Prom H.K.S.Lupin. To P.B.Bushire. P/4/4/30. Immediate. Your 3310.Following has Been made out in conjunc tion with Thomas. Sheikh returned KhasaB on Tuesday and his attitude remains recalcitrant. In view of the fact that he can retire to mountains and presumably has support of LiBah his earl^ submission is not likely. Subject to app roval of C-in-C.E.l following action is proposed with object of Bringing maximum pressure to Bear on him. BomBaid ment (to Be repeated if necessary) of Sheikh Hasan quarter of KhasaB and neighbouring Beni Hadiyah villages including destruction of local craft. Blockade of KhasaB area includ ing prohibition of local fishing, suggest this action should not B-e taken until 48 hours after delivery of ultim atum. In connection with Blockade suggest you shoujd issue letters to Trucial Sheikhs to co-operate. It Is considered that Kali should not evacuate fort provided Kumazari2 faJ- a.grse 'to gapi'ison it. Steps will 'be taken to bhis end if found practioalDle and if you approve. This message is 'being to C-in C.E.I. and S.N.O.P.C. Prom P.B.Bushire. 333 To H.L.C.Lupin (B) S.N.O.P.G. D/4/4/30 I have recommend to Govt, of India that you should he authorised to carry out homhardment suggested if ultim atum to he issued hy Thomas is rejected. As regards sub sequent blockade I have said I would reverse opinion till further consultation with S.N.O.P.G. and review of situatior From I.B. Bushire 3 3 5. To T.L.S.Lupin. D/5/4/30 I should like to know what terms Thomas, considers should he imposed on Sheikh of Khasab in ultimatum From F.I'.S.Lupin 1031 To P.B.Bushire D/5/4/30. Following from Thomas begins. Two objects are hoped for from local blockade (l) It prove a deterrant to Diba from aiding Hasan (2) It cause sufficient local discomfort to effect Hasan*s credit. Hasan is in strong posirion. It would appear prob able his plan after bombardment would be to retire moun tains refuse to treat for terms and hope to emerge after operations with entranced prestige amongst Shihuh. It is . desirable that no step be left untaken to the end that hi s own people bring pressure upon him to accept an intermed' iary and terms while operations are in progress. It is considered that local blockade would be some contribution towards influencing tribal mind. As regards S.N.O’s view r s on Trucial Coast reactions I took the liberty of tentativel; sounding Besidency Agent on advisability of warning Trucial Chiefs in event of blockade and he concurred. It is desir able that the Shihuh find their normal facilities for pur chasing arms and supplies from Trucial villages interfered with. The limit of Trucial co-operation desired is non co-operation. From H.H.S.Lupin 1731 To P.B.Bushire. D/5/4/30 Thomas and his council collegues present considerconsider terras of ultimatum should he unconditional surren der only. In event of his surrender an immediate i.5000 fine on Khasah and Sheikh’s imprisonment for term of one one year in Muscat and on his release to give a surety of L.10000 to he of good behaviour. Thomas suggest that if you approve these conditions he referred to Muscat and that if action is anticipated during the next week Saiyid Sa’id he requested to proceed in next up mail where he can he met at Henjam hy A1 Sa'id in order that he may he present. From H.M.S.Lupin 1236 To P.B.Bushire. D/7/ 4/30. Following from Thomas. The probable situation arising after a bombardment and the nature of contingent action on our part require consideration. Two ends are desired, (l') A Shihuh situation that will ensure contin uance of the Sultanate wall in Khasah. (2) The surrender or abdication of Sheikh Hasan. As regards (l) the first step desirable is the dissociation on Fiba’s part of any further alliance with Hasan. This may be hoped from moral effect of punitive action against Khasab espictally exem plary xxixi&amp;x effect of our employment of blockade measures. Disavowal on Diba’s part should be followed up by his hxg being informed of the requirement of Muscat State Authority namely a Dali’s continued residence atpiAs&amp;Tjand Diba’s own responsibility in the event of future retaliatory measures against Dali on part of whomsoever. As regards (2) it would he unwise to reckon on change in Hasan’s defiant and uncom promising attitude, punitive action is calculated to dis credit him hut there is no reason why he should volun tarily abdicate except through tribal pressure or by dis interested advice. The only apparent candidate for Khasab, if such is desired,is one of Hakha's nephews who may on point of honour be expected to decline if dictated by British or Muscat Authorities, Any durable solution v/ould have to he based on tribal consent. It would appear that an independent intermediary may he best maens for rapproa- ehment and who is personally acceptable to tribe, ''he man whose envoy most likely to be listened to is Sa'id Maq.tum Sheikh of Dabai. The Shihuh- Beni Yas Hinawi partsanship and Sheikh Sa'id’s independence apart from personal pres tige should disarm suspicion. Some volimtay movement on Dibai’s part offering the Shihuh to approach the author ities on their behalf would if made in good faith soon after operations commenced seemed, to me to he of service to both sides. From Mr.Thomas 1238. To P.B.Bushire. D7/4/30. Shall be grateful if you will send a copy of my report to Political Muscat and copies of all telegrams.Fron H.F.u.Lupin,'' 331. To P.E.Bushire. D/8/4/30. Dali received a letter this Tuesday evening from Sheikh // of Khasah ordering him to leave the town. It is considered doubtful whether he could resist a det ermined attack and a xsry very early decision as to action against Sheikh is reguested. From F.B.Bushire 348. Immediate. To F.h.o.Lupin (F) H.I .3.Triad. D10/4/30 H.I .Govt.have approved destruction of Sheikh’s fort if terms not accepted. Ultimatum should he delivered as soon as you receive reguisite authority from C-ln-C. to take action. 24 hours notice would seem sufficient hut I leave matter to your discretion. From E.L.S.Lupin 1513. To P.B.Bushire. D/10/4/30. Following from Thomas. An isolated bombardment of Khasab will not restore Muscat authority there. Unless operations are of sufficient scope to result in discred iting Sheikh Hasan in tribal eyes he is certain to remain Sheikh of Khasab. In that event it would be injudicious for Muscat to issue a strong ultimatum. In any case he is not likely to tolerate Sultanate Mali remaining after H.Mship withdraws if action taken against him is inadeg- uate. It is submitted that the measures set forth in Lupin’s telegram 2113 of 3rd April are those demanded by the local situation. I am therefore not issuing ultimatum pending your further instructions. From H.M.S.Lupin 1445. To P.F.Bushire (B) S.N.O.P.G. D/10/4/30. Fort at Khasab is occupied by Mali and Sheikh Hasan resides in house at back of fort surrounded by other buildings and date palms by which it is obscured from the sea. It would therefore be necessary for bombardment to include Sheikh Hasan’s guarter of the town. Thomas con siders this degree of support, insufficient to justify his, issuing of ultimatum and message from follows. Heguest instructions. From F.F.Bushire 360. To F.M.S.Lupin D/12/4/30. I have informed Govt.of India that owing to delay that has occurred measures which might have proved adeguate if taken promptly are no longer so and.I have asked that you should be given feasonaMeh atitude inState. From P.B.BusMre 368. Lupin. in enforcing ultimatum As no reply received yfct?(they are)? further reference is probably being made to Secretary oi Govt, of India lave represented to IT.M.Govt.that situation has deteriorated owing to delay and have asked th; that you should be authorised to carry out measures rec ommended in your 2113 3rd April It is hoped order will be received in a day or two. From P.L. Bushire 374. To H.L.S.Lupin,H.M.S.Triad Govt.of India. D/16/4/30. H.M.Govt.have approved demand for unconditional surrender and punitive action to enforce it within^the limit recommended in your telegram 2113 3rd April but subject to distinct understanding action should entail no loss human life. Thilst leaving details to your *discretio;i I consider ultimatum'should be issued accompanied by noti fication that bombardment will take place at end of 48 hours and explicitly define area within which there will be risk of shells falling which inhabitants should be j _ called on to evacuate. Similarly if bombardment is repeatec 3 hours notice should be given. If bombardment and desiruc- tion of local craft prove ineffective* I agree to blockade and will call on Trucial Sheikhs t?co-operative. If you consider that Isa*a presence would be useful please send for him. From H.IT.S.Lupin 2i48_« To P.k.Bushire. D/16/4/30. It is hoped to reinforce garrison of Tail’s fort tomorrow Thursday night and to issue ultimatum Friday morning. From P.P.Bushire 1/64, To H.L.3.Lupin (B)S.N.C.P.G. D/17/4/30. IT. IT. Govt .have now modified instructions as followp For words 'subject to distinct understanding action should entail no loss of human life'the following should be sub stituted begins ' On the understanding?every precaution will be taken against loss of human life' From H.M.S.Lupin 1241^ f o P.:.. Bus hire (B)o.N.G.P.G. D/18/4/30. Ultimatum was delivered to Sheikh this morningmorning April 18th and expires 1000 April 20th. Prom HJff.S,Lupin 16 T o P. P . Bn sh ire, (B 7 TT B/20/4/30. -m-u E I and l.N.O.P.G. Keference your 374/16 and 1224/1r. Bomhardment# of Sheikh Hasan f s gLuarter/of Khasah ana Leighhouring Beni Hadiyah villages and local cfaft there was carried out hj/ Lupin, Oylc amen and A1 Sa’idi to-day April 20th Sheikh Hasan*a house was hit hy shell Afeter homhardment a verbal message purporting to come from Sheikh was received rec^uesuing S.N.C’s interpreter he sent ashore to see him. This request v. Is refused. It is reported Sleikh has gone to the mountains' and it is doubtful whether the message came from I him 1 It is now pronosed to carry out blockade of area south east of line joining Has Sheik Masud and western point of entrance to Hor G-hubb Ali. from P.B.Bushire T/70 To H.P.S.Lupin P/21/4/30. Please arrange with Pesidency Agent to notify Trucial Sheikhs and invite their co-operation. Prom TT .H.S .Lupin 1726 To P.B.Bushire P/25/4/30 Besidency Agent was visited at Pabai today Wednesday | and arrangements were made for warning Trucial Sheikhs of blockade of Khasab,44/7 Telegram Code, ^rom Political Peaident, Bushire* To H* M. S. 'Lupin' 1 , Henjamradio. No. 3o3. Dated 14th April 1930. Government of India have represented to IIis Majesty’s Government that situation has deteriorated owing to delay and have asked that you should be authorised to carry out measures recommended in your It is hoped that orders will he day or uwo. .Resident. I I - -f44/7 Telegram From To Bepeated Dated 15th B. Secretary of State for India, Lonaon. Sovernnant of India, Simla Ko. 1280. Politioal Besident, Boshire. Ho. 1281. reed 16th April 1930. Import ant. Foreign Department. Your telegram of April I2th No. 1091-8. Kh^sab . Your proposal in regard to ultimatum is approved. His Majesty’s Government also approves punitive action to enforce it within limits of recommendations made in Political Resident's telegram of April 4th No. 332 and suttfeet to distinct understanding that action shauld entail no loss of human life. Secretary of State for India,R. 44/7 Telegram From To No. 1.14 R-S. Datea and received 16th April 1930. Government of India, Simla. Pol if leal Reeident, BuPhira. (Repeated under BuPhire 379 of 16/4) Secretary of State’s telegram No. 1281 of Ibth April, repeated to you. Ultimatum referred to is that proposed in your telegram No. 339 of April 7th, Please repeat your telegrams reporting developments to Secretary of State. Wo 2 FOPK TGN. Telegram Fr om To Repeated R. Secretary of State for Tnd^a, London. Government of India, Simla, No. 1289. Political Resident, Bushire, No. 12,90. Dated and received 16t,h April 1930. i oG My telegram No. 1280. (Repeated, under Pushire 381 of 16/4). Khasab. In place of rforde M pubjpct to distinct understanding that action should entail no 3 .ops of human life' the following should be substituted, begAns ' on the understanding that every precaution will be taken against loss of human life' ends. SRCRKTARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.44/7 Telegram : Code. From : H.M.S.Lupin,Henjamradio. To: Political Resident f Bushire No. 2234 Dated 27th (Deceived 28th)April,1930. Oommander-in-Chief has received the following from Admirality begins It would not be permissible to declare a formal blockade and the word blockade should not be used. It is presumed that operations would be limited to intercepting of local craft and goods in local craft. Foreign vessels should not be stop ed or interferred with. Any such measures are, of course f subject to concurrence of the Political Resident ends. • I have received orders from Commander- in-Chief that Persian vessels must not be interfered with. 'LUPIN*44/7 Telegrams- Code. Trom: * H. . S. Lupin, Sen J amradi o • Tos Command er-in-Chief. Bepeated: Senior Naval Officer Political Besident,Bushire. No: 0852 Dated: 27th April,1930.Received 28th April lours 1235 Submit that I may he authorised to warn orews of Persian Dhov.s that owing to punitive measures Kasah and villages have heen evacuated and that it is unsafe to land. Lupin.44/8 Telegram Coce. From M.M.8. Lupin, henjaiaradlo. To Political Keuitient, jsuBlaire. Mo. 2307. Dated 27th (received 28th ) April 1930. Following from Thonas j- Reference Lupin *b 2234. Tiie only vessele using Khasah harbour are Arab and Persian country-craft. Diocriiainating treatment in favour of latter creates unfortunate impression along Arab side of the Gulf. There are neighbour ing ports hAKHA and hUMZAH almost within sight of Khasab which all craft are permitted to use and remove slightest chance of hardships on ( y) outside trader. It woild seem that fear entertained of offending foreign traders may be met if Muscat patrolling ship in own territorial waters advises them to proceed to one of these ports as Khasab is dangerous area. lUpIM.A&gt;47 xiC. ci ly^u ^ritisn xvesiaency u. ocnsuiate-&gt;-eneral, ^-usnire, uie May 1930. -usmre, uie x 1 A ocpy cf the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat, for information and with the request that the sum cf Es. 61.8.0 on account cf cost cf provisions supplied to the ■Tali cf Khasah may he recovered from the Muscat State and remitted to H.M.S.'I/upin*. Letter No.810/20/A dated the 4th April 1930 from the Commander in Ccmriand, H.M.S .‘•Lupin - . Copy forwarded tiftth compliments to the Commander, H.M.S.*Lupin H for information. By order, . L ' Major Secretary to the Pclit ical Resident in the Persian G-uj.f. •L.PH.M.S. ‘•Lupin', at Khasab, 4th April 1930. No.810/20/A Tc The Hcn’hle the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. Sir, H is requested that the sum of Rs.61 - annas 8. may he remitted tc the Command ing Officer, H.M.S .’•Lupin' on account of the issue of the 'following previsions tc the Wali of Khasah during the month of March 1930:- £ • S. B. Rice 318 Lbs * 3 19 6 Sugar 21 m 0 3 ni Bread 24 * 0 3 0 PI cur 40 m 0 5 10 Total £.4 - 12 - H (Rs. 61 - Annas 8 ) 2. The Issue of provisions from H.M.S.'Lupin' was rendered necessary in consequence of the action of the Sheikh of Khasah in prohibiting supplies from the Bazaar tc the Wali as reported tc you in Lupin’s signal 1304 of 7th March, 1930. I have the honour tc he, Sir, Y c ur asask obedient servant, (Signed) I.M. ALLEYNE, 0OMMAITLSER IN COMMANDsetter ^o.31 dated 17th May 1*30 from the Council of Ministers to H.H. the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman to Major C-.P Murphy, i.A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat A.C. We have received your letter no.64 dated the 14th may 1930 and noted its contents with regard to the sum of Ks.61/8 on account of supply of provisions by H.M.S. 'Lupin* to the &amp;'ali of Ahasab. The amount is forwarded herewith, please acknowledge receipt. U. E.o \ / Mo. Lf-y. Of 1930# Iditlcta A&amp;ency and H.jb.k^e Coneulate, kUBo&amp;t 20th isott kay 1930. To The Commander, H.M.B. •Lupin 1 *, Cir, ?yith reference to your letter Ho.810/20/A dated 4th April 1930 to the addrese of the Hon f TDle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire,I have the honour to state that the sum of Rs.61/8/»(sixty one and annas eight only)has Been recovered fro* the Muscat State on account of the cost of ration® supplied to the VTali of Khasato during the month of March 1930 and paid to Masib blr Mahomed &amp; Bon,Muscat,Maval Contractorswhich amount please adjust from the amount due to them* I enolooe their receipt in duplicate for the amount* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Msg or. Political /gent and K.B.tf’e Consul,Muscat* /* \ HO. 173-b. or 1951. British nesidency ana Consulate-aenerai, jjushire, the iiBth March 1951. irrom - The aecretary to the non’ble the jrolitical nesident in the Persian u-uir, to - The Political Agent, Muscat. Sir, 1 am directed to forward herewith for your informa- ft.M.S. “Penzance M , I’egarding the liiiaikh oi iihassac. understand 'when he v;as last at Muscat that it was tne intention of the Council to release the Shaikh at an early date, but to keep him under detention at Muscat. i- so, it will presumably be possible for him to have his family with him. in any case, however. Colonel Miscoe considers that some arrangement should be made for the subsistence of the famioy so that they will not be reduced to begging farom other Arab Shaikhs. lie would be glad to be iniormed in due course what arrangements have been made for them. Report. tion a copy of a report received from the officer Commanding, 2 The Hon'ble the political nesiuent was given to i have the honour to be, sir, lour most obedient servant Captain, for secretary to the political resident in the Persian oulf.\ 2- 7 'PENZANCE' At 'DABiOl' 15th March 1031. Visit of 'Penaanoe' to tlie Tnicirl Coast. N° 17/1^1/S . Sir. I liave the honour to forward the following report after ay visit to the Truoial Coast on the 14/l5th March 1931. 2. The Sheifch of DABAI and the Residency Advent called on ae on the 15th March and the former requests your help in obtaining the early release of the SheiKh of KHASAB now imprisoned in MUSCA2. 3. Ke has received information that the confinement of the last 12 months has affected his brain and furthermore his family are continually begging from SheiKh Sa'id owing to their impoverished state. 4. As the latter helped to obtain SheiKh Hasseh for imprisonment he would like to be instrumental in affecting his release, and requests that this matter may receive your favourable consideration. I have the honour to be Sir Your Obedient Servant. To The honourable Commander in Command. The Political Resident. Bushire, Copy To Senior Naval Officer Persain Gulf Division.—1 1 % no. of 1931. From To / ‘f /f of 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.JfcJ.M’s Consulate, Muscat, Recess Office, Karachi, the 1st May 1931. - The Political Agent, Muscat, Karachi. • The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sir, y I have the honour to refer to your no.l73-S of 28th J&amp;arch 1931. 2. I discussed the matter of the Shaikh of Khasab with the Council of Ministers. They informed me that, as his sentence was 18 months imprisonment beginning from May 1930, he will not be released until next .November, when it is the intention of the Council to keep him in Muscat for sometime at any rate. If he likes he can then have his family to 4 live with him. The Council informed me that the Shaikh is quite reasonably well off, owning property at Khasab, and that therefore there is no need for his family to beg from anybody, Shaikhs or otherwise. Presumably the family ect represent4*g their condition as impoverished as a leaver to get the Shaikh released. The Council also informed me that the confinement of the last 12 months has in no way affected the Shaikh f 8 brain: considering the short period of his confinement up to date, there seems no reason why it should have. I have the honour to be, Sir, your most obedient servant, 'll — Major, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.I Ho of 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’b K ecees Office, Karachi, the 1st May Consulate, 1931. Muscat, To The Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian tfulf. Memorandum . y Please refer to my letter ho.^A* of 1st May 1931. The suggestion that the Shaikh’s mind has been affected by his imprisonment, though not substantiated, raises the question of the wellbeing of the State prisoner at Muscat. Primarily the health of the prisoners is a question for which the State is responsible. Un the other hand considering the peculiar and close relations which we have with Muscat, any scandal arising from bad housing or feeding of the prisoners by the state would probably react on us to some extent. I have suggested informally to Saiyid Said that Captain Mackay, in his capacity of Quarantine Officer of the state, might visit the prisoners twice a month, and see that reasonably healthy conditions were being observed. Saiyid Said concurred, and if the Hon’ble the Political Resident approves, I will write to Captain Mackay accordingly. During the absence of Captain Mackay on recess the Sub Assistant Surgeon could carry out his duties. 2. I may add that Captain M a ckay informed me that about two years ago a case of Scurvy occurred amongst the prisoners, which of course should have not happened. ^ Major, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.I No,245-S of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, From The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To The Political Agent, Muscat at Karachi. Memora ndum,! Reference your memorandum NojD/K of the 1st May, The Hon’ble the Political Resident quite approves of the suggestion that the quarantine officer of the state should occasionally visit prisoners and see that xrxexs reasonably healthy conditions are being observed. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Cap t•,Ho* Political Agency &amp; H.B*M*a Conciliate, ^uccot, Recess Office, Karachi, 15th May 1931* To Saiyid Said, President of the Council of Miniatere, Muscat State, Muscat* After Compliments* With reference to our conversation the other day when we agreed that it would be a good thing if Captain leokay, in his oapacity of quarantine Officer of the Muscat State, should visit the State prisoners twioe a month (say) to see that reasonably healthy conditions ere bexag observed in the prison. The Hon’ble the Political Resident to whom I forward ed this suggestion has approved of it, and Captain ^aekay therefore earn begin hie visits whenever you like. This Is what had to be said and ealaiaa* 'iV Major, Political Agent &amp; H*B*M # a Consul, Muscat. Copy to Captain Kackay, Ageney Surgeon, iuscat, far information*h /•a. Confid ential No.244-3 of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, the 9th May 1931 From - The Secretary to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Tos The Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi Sir With reference to your letter Ko.9A of the 1st May 1931, regarding the Shaikh of Khassab, I am directed to state that while it is of course possible that the family represented their condition as impoverished as a lever to get the Shaikh released, there is also a possibility that in the absence of the Shaikh the income of his lands may have been misappropriated by other persons and that his wife may be genuinely in distress. 2. Colonel Biscoe hopes therefore that the Council will take suitable steps to arrange for the administration of the property during the Shaikh’s absence and for a suitable allowance to be paid to his wife. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. \H* M. S* 'ORWONDfi', 29th March 1931. at HBNJAM. 1 beg tb' Inforxa you that 'Ormonde' has completed her seasons work in the Persian Gulf and wish to take the opportunity of expressing my appreciation of the assistance given by MODHAPAR BIN SULEIMAN, Wali of Khasab, who has made every effort to facilitate the work of 'Ormonde’s' surveying parties, also the friendly help of the local Sheikhs of Khasab and Kumzar and, request that you will inform the Muscat Government of this. X have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Political. Agent, His Britannic Majesty’s Consulate, ‘ MUSCAT. COMMANDER. (IN CHARGE OP SURVEY). . „ ».o /v. . 9The Council of Ministers to H*H* the Sultan of Muscat and Oman* ik6 y Vo.lOq-Cot 1931. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M*s Consulate, f(L Muscat,the 1C - April 1^31t After conpliiiients. The Commander of H •S«'Grmande' while informing me that he has completed his seasons woric in the Persian Gulf desires me to convey to Your Honours his expression of appreciation of the assistance given nim hy Modhafar bin Suleiman, Wali of Kliasab, who made every effort to facilitate the work of the survey parties and also of the friendly help given by the local sheikhs of Xhasab and Omizar• Th this appreciation I am also very pleased to add my own. This is what had to be said and salaams. ^ Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Mu scat. n v £</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000281_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/41</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000281</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/41</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File No XXVIII/12 Khasab Visit of H.M.S. “Ormonde and Bombardment from 20-12-29 to 28-5-30.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-05T16:49:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (159 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 161; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-160; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of telegrams and reports between the Political Agency, Muscat, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and the naval officers on board HMS
                           Ormondeand HMS
                           Lupin. The correspondence is concerned with the ship HMS
                           Ormondeleaving Aden to carry out surveys in the Gulf and the question of whether a survey would be permitted to take place in Oman or not. While the Council of Ministers to the Sultan of Muscat and Oman granted permission for a survey to take place, further permissions were required from the shaikhs of Khassab, Bukha, Diba and Kumzar, which are parts of the region of Musandam in Oman. Some tribes from the region, the Shihuh in particular, opposed the landing of the navy ship in their territories. The Political Resident warned that the landing of any British personnel in Shihuh region would be attended by grave risk in the future.To subdue the shaikhs of Khassab, the Political Resident recommended to the Government of India that the Naval Ship HMS
                           Lupin, should be authorised to carry out a bombardment of parts of Khassab and, in the event of the shaikhs’ withdrawal to the mountains, this should be followed by a blockade of the Khassab area. British officials were also concerned with the necessity of reaching agreements with the Trucial Shaikhs and with those of the region of Musandam. The file also includes correspondence with the Council of Ministers at Muscat regarding the imprisonment of the Shaikh of Khassab, Hasan bin Muhammad.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Bukha</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Ships</topic></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Shiḥūḥ (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Musandam Peninsula </geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Khassab</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Diba</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000281#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>