<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000221_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-17T11:04:36.039Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">X u*v* tbs honour to forward herowlth s trsnslAtlea of sn order Issued oy tbs Sultan of uuaost prohibiting the laport of all kind a of IntaKlmtlnf liqucars into his torrltorlss. in Bahrain and Kuwait slallar orders war* Issuad by the Rulers Many years ago. 2* The dultan consulted the Political agent and ay self before issuing the order and undertook to aska a special essaptlon la favour of the Politic;.! agency. Re subeequently agreed that all Europeans and Anglo-lad lane should be allowed e reasonable supply under e permit system for which the polities! Agent would be responsible, the seam procedure is followed In Bahrain and Kuweit. The term 'Europeans' may presumably be taken to include Americans but the point has not oean specifically raised as the only Americans resids: t in Muscat ere aissleaerlcs who are total abstainers, the Sultan has refused to allow any ration of liquor for the Hindus and in view of the feet that most of the Frovioelal Qovsrnmants in India appear to be introducing prohibition 2 hove not thought it neeossary to neke any representation on their behalf. 3. IDs Sultan refuses to grant any formal exemption In writing for Europeans end Anglo-Indians end refers to his uadartaking la this respoet as e verbal gentlemen's agree ment. Similar concessions In Bahrain and Kuwait are not covered by cay written agreement. 4. So far aa X am aware the sultan has not yet asked the Political agent to apply his order to British subjects under article IS of the treaty of 1636, e.f. article IS of the duaeet urder-in-c ouneil, end unless the sultan agrees to issue an exemption in writing in favour of European* and Anglo-Indians, X am opposad to the promulgation of any formal order by the Political Agent. In these elreuaataneas rather e difficult situation way be erected if the Saltan asks the Political Agent to take actlonagalnat e Hindu British subject for e breech of his order, but it ia hoped that such an eventuality will not arise. It mill be noted that no penalty is prescribed for amah a broach of the Sulten's order end that as it stands it prohibits only the importation end not the Manufacture or consumption of liquor. 3. X am sending e copy of this despatch to the United Kingdom High Commissioners at Bee Delhi end Karachi. X have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir, Xour sost obedient humble servant. POLITICAE RESIT.ENT. The Rt. Hon. Ernest Bavin, P.C., ’i.P., etc., etc., etc., Poreign Office, London.TRANSLATION OF COMMUNIQUE 16 b ^ 0 i ( No. 1/46. Dated 22nd April 1948 Let it be known that we have prohibited the importation of all kinds of intoxicating drinks into our Kingdom with the effect from the date of issue of this communique. Sd. SAID bin TAIMUR</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000221_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3001</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000221</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3001</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/41 'Muscat: Prohibition of Import of Intoxicating liquors into Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1952/1952</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-20T23:03:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>A letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (forwarded from the Foreign Office), Bahrain to Ernest Bevin, Foreign Secretary, June 1948. The letter gives details of a prohibition on the import of liquor into Oman recently announced by the Sultan of Muscat. A translation of the Sultan Said bin Taimur's [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd] communiqué, dated 22 April 1948, is enclosed.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Import control</topic></subject><subject><topic>Alcohol</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000221#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>