<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:37:05.807Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ifc G^tom Mouse; / j \ BAHRAIN ifLJ ^ 14th Julyol942o NooCr/.;-: 29th JoThanio 1361 o ~ ^ 5 Ol i H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, fj'* Bahrain. I write to inform you that the Government of Bahrain appoints from time to time Shipping Agents who are licensed to^handle the landing and shipment of cargo lightered from sea-going vessels; and for this service such Agents are authorised to collect Landing Charges according to the Governments sanctioned schedule 0 I may add that no other unlicensed firm is permitted to act as Shipping Agents in Bahrain The licensed Shipping Agents now are (1) Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Coo Ltd., and (2)K.S.Hajy Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo C.I.E etc o On the 1st July ,1942, these licensed Shipping Agents were authorised to add twenty per cent to the sanctioned schedule of Landing Charges until further notice # on account of increased working costs. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant HXOIECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER.BAHRAIN^ oCP &amp;■ o&gt; THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED ■&lt;$' i 1 &amp; h Awali, I ..J: % •V'-' 1 * ' /■' r ( ■ \&amp;f Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. &gt;A- j \ v rl' )' / ■? Mr ^ 14th July, 1942. No. PA-284 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein. ♦ A** Dear Sir, Attached is a copy of a letter received today from Mr. C.C.L.deGrenier, Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrein stating that 'the Government of Bahrein appoints from time to time Shipping Agents who are licensed to handle the landing and shipment of cargo lightered from sea -going vesse s, and for this service such Agents are authorized to collect Landing Charges according to the Government sanctioned schedule. I may add that no other unlicensed firm is permitted to act as Shipping Agents in Bahrein. The licensed Shipping Agents now are:- (1) Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company Limited, and (2) K.S• Hajy Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo, C.I.E. etc. The Company v /ishes confirmation that this is so and that this has your sanction. The Company would also appre ciate receiving copies of such regulations, laws, proclamations etc. issued 'by the Government of Bahrein relative to tne aoove, and would appreciate information regarding the^proper procedure through which to apply for appointment as a 'Licensed Shipping Agents'. Is Mr. deGrenier 1 s letter to be interpreted as includ ing offloading from sea-going ships, unloa ^^ ^ ori1 lighters to shore, hiring of stevedores and lighters, cledrin^ of ships, and the duties of ship's Agents? Also, does it include handling and clearing of all cargoes imported by the Company either on its own boats or otherwise for use in the Company* s operations? Yours very tr W. P. ANDERSON. Chief Local Representative, TH3 BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.No. -Sffz of 1361 C Office of the Adviser to -X / Government, Bahrain \ /Q /L r ^ a ' te(i » 25th Raj ab, 1361 \//t ' August 8, 1942-^—^ I H. B» M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No. 1333-7/3 dated the 27th July, 1942. n I enclose a copy of the Ahlan regarding Agents for Shipping Companies in Bahrain, Any firm or individual who wishes to set up as the Agent of a Shipping line must first obtain permission from the Bahrain Government. There are at present only two Shipping Agents in Bahrain, Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &lt;Sc Co., Ltd., and Haj Yusuf bin Ahmed Kanoo, but in the past various firms have been given permission to act as Agents for Shipping lines. ^ The license which is issued by the Government containa 18 clauses which control the charges which may be levied for lighterage and relate to the duties of the Agents, Customs procedure, responsibility for care of cargo, nature of craft to be used, and arbitration. The Agents pay a royalty of 5% to the Bahrain Government from the landing charges collected by them. W There is no monopoly in the case of lighterage but at Jresent the only firm which is well equipped with a fleet of boats to carry out this worK is keasrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Limited. Until the beginning of the war this firm held the agency for 13 Shipping lines. l If s ^ Ca letter from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Deputy Manager, Mespers (now Gray, Mackenzie) dated ^ 15th February 1936 refers to the question of the Bahrain Petroleum Company obtaining similar facilities for land ing cargo. I have only the copy of this letter and have not been able to trace previous or subsequent corres pondence between the Political Agent and Mespers. ^'Referring to the Company^ questions, if a copy of the Landing Company Agreement would interest them I will send a copy to see and return, I presume that the Company is acquainted with the scale of charges. If the Bahrain Petroleum Co., is to be appointed Agent for any Shipping firm the Company should inform the Bahrain Government fa.'* which would willingly grant them a license on the same' terms and conditions as that held by the other two Ship ping Agents. - . f Mr. deGrenie^s letter refers to the scale of charges which the Landing Company is authorised to charge for the work which they do, these charges were reduced some years ^ago by 10^ and have recently been raised by 20^, represen ting an increase of 10^ over the original rates. f 'Regarding the Company^ own imports on its own boats, these I believe are dealt with directly by the Company. Adviser to the Government.&lt;8 GOTjSRNMSNT OF BAHRAIN. NOTICE. No. 28/1351. 1. The public are reminded that no one is permitted to become an Agent for a shipping or Air Company in Bahrain or Agent of any ship that loads or unloads cargo or passengers in Bahrain without obtaining permission from the Government• 2. No one is allowed to load or unload passengers or cargo in Bahrain waters unless he obtains permission from the Government to do so # 3. All applications should be in writing and submitted to the Director of Customs and ^ Port Officer. Sd/ C.Dalrymple Belgrave. Advi ser to the Government. Dated, 24th J/Thany, 1351. 24th October, 1932. S.Z.A No.1583-7/3 Political Agency f Bahrain. 6th September, 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Bahrain. t Dear Sir, V/ith reference to your letter No.PA-284, dated 14th July 1942, on the subject of the appointment of Shipping Agents Proclamation No.28/1361 issued by the Bahrain Government on 25th October 1932. All Shipping Agents in Bahrain are required to enter into an agreement with the Bahrain Government containing 18 clauses, which control the charges which may be levied for lighterage and relate to the duties of the Agents, customs procedure, responsibility for care of cargo, nature of craft to be used, and arbitration. The agreement, a copy of the form of which can be obtained from the Adviser to the -Bahrain Govern ment, also provides that Agents shall pay a royalty of 6% to the Bahrain Government for landing charges collected by them. At present the only licensed Shipping Agents are those mentioned in the enclosure to your letter under reply. 2. There is no monopoly in the case of lighterage, but at present the only firm which is well equipped with the proper craft to carry out this work is Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. 3. If the Bahrain Petroleum Company wish either themselves to be appointed a Shipping Agent or to arrange for an Agent other than the two firms at present authorised to carry out the Company^ work, you should apply to the Bahrain Government sending a copy of your letter to me. 4. Mr. de Grenie^s letter quoted by you referred to the scale of charges which a landing company is authorised to make for bringing cargo from ships to the Customs pier. These charges, of which the Bahrain Petroleum Company are presumably in Bahrain, I enclose herewith for your information a copy of .. .■ - ■ /' * If ■- 2 - 4 presumably aware, were reduced some ye^rs ago by 10% and have recently been raised \yy 20%. In the event of the Bahrain Petroleum Company applying for a licence under the Proclamtion, the scale of charges to be levied by them or their nominee will have to be settled with the Bahrain Government* 6* These provisions do not embrace the handling and carrying of cargoes imported by the Company on their own boats for use in the Company^ operations. Yours truly, r fc '^c &amp; Lltica forjPoiitlcal Agent, Bahrain.v,\e -0° The Bahrain PA-410 oleum Company limited A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, September 10, 1942. File #896.2 LAUDING, CLEARING, AND HXPORT CHA.RGB3 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Attention: Capt. N.G-.Dixon Dear Sir, /• a I am pleased to acknowledge with thanks your letter No.1583-7/3 dated 6th September 1942, in reply to my letter 'No. PA-284 dated 14th July 1942. . b I very much appreciate having received a copy of Pro clamation No.28/1351 issued by the Government of Bahrein on 25th October 1932, which, incidentally, the Company was not aware of, although the Company was aware of the existence of an approved scale of landing charges. The Company does not at this time contemplate engaging in lighterage activities or clearing of ships. It is possible that at some future date the Company might be interested in acting as Ships Agents for tankers calling at Sitra anchorage and in clearing and off-loading cargoes of freight off such vessels. In such an event the Company would make a proper application for permission to do so. It is assumed that the approved scale of landing charges would not apply to such cargoes consigned to the Company and used in the Company's operations; and also that the Company would be exempt from the Royalty of 5% payable to the G-overnment of Bahrein on landing charges in respect of goods used in Company's opera tions . Yours very truly. P. ANDERSON CHI3F LOCAL REPRESENTATIV3 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. ✓ y // w No. 1679-7/3 Political Agency,HahPeiin. 19th Septonber,1942. To The Advise * to the Government of ifehrain, Bahrain . Meiaorgtn^in m. ¥ ^ Heference your ITemorandum .1439..3^/3^ dated the 8th A'ogust 1942. &lt;\ 2# 1 enclose a copy of letter ITo.PA-410, dated 10th September 1942, frcm the Chief Local Heja^eeentative, Bahrain Petroleum Company, for yo ir information, m view of the first sentence 0 1&gt; paragraph 3 of the letter, I do not think tliat any reply is necessary to the two assiunptions contained in the final sentence. Such details can be settled if and when the occasion arises. S) for Political Agent,Bahrain.iu m 1 v Slst April, 19^5. r/v CONFIDENTIAL CO^-^1^ Vir* G. iV # Sirlth, Director of Customs d Port Officer, Bahrein. ^ ^ r D«ar Sir. 1 Pursuant to Notice Ko» 26/13'1 of the 24th October, 1932, the Company hereby applies for permission to act as agent for the following companies 1 Pacific Tankers, Inc., l^ar Emergency Tankers, inc.. Tanker's Company, Inc., and American Republic Corporstion. The Company is at present acting as sub- agents of the above tanker compenies with the authority to appoint agents but since it is doing no regular agency work for fee, it is not believed that this sub-agency comes under the scope of the above irenti ned notice. However, the Compfiny wishes the permission to act as agents for the above companies should it wish to do so In the future. :he Company also hereby applies for permission to load or unload passengers or c«rgo from s: ips in Bahrein weters# • Yours very truly, cmoinal signed byir W. P. AHDUISOK CHIEF LOCAL NTAT1VE BAHRFIN PETROLEUM COUPAnt LIMITED. THB/MA cc. POLITICAL AGENT ADVISER TO THE GOVERNMENT. FILE 280.62ooiiFiDm TIAL No. C/4S6, POLITICAL AGKNCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 24th April, 1946 The Director of Custc Bahrain Memorandmn Reference Chief Local Representative, Bahrain Petroleum Company f s letter No. CON-314, dated the 21st April, 1945, to you. 2. /ill you kindly send rae a copy of Notice' No. 28/1351, dated the 24th October, 1932, referred to therein? for Political Agent, BahrainTHE CUSTOMHOUSE: ( BAHRAIN: No.PA/.^. 7 , 25th April, 1945., VW H .B.JiPs Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandun:- o Lf-Mr* *1 Reference your No.C/485 of the 24th inst. .w I enclose herewith a copy of Notice No.28/1351?dated the 24-th October, 1932, as desired. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.Tr anslation . , No.28/1351. 1. The Public are reminded that no one is permitted to become an Agent for a shipping or Air Company in Bahrain or Agent of any ship that loads or unloads cargo or passengers in Bahrain watere without obtaining permission from the Government. 2. No one is allowed to.load or unload passenge or cargo in Bahrain v/a t » s unless he obtainr ^ r mission from the Governmex w to do so, V3« All applications should u writing and submitted to the Director of Cu&amp;v^iis and Port Officer. v vl •&gt; s/d C.Dalrymple Belgrave ADVISER TO THE GOVERNMENT. ' V J S W- Detad: 24th J/Thani 1351. 24th October 1932. _ / TII D#0 W No. C/531. V.,-. ^ Dated the 5th May, 1945 My dear Belgrave / You may reneraber that I spoke to you about Ward Anderson's confidential letter No. CON-314 dated the 21st April to Smith as Director of Customs in which the Bahrain Petroleum company applied for permission to act as agent for various American tanker companies and also applied for permission to load and unload passengers or cargo from ships in Bahrain waters. You said that you would get Smith to find out from Ward Anderson exactly what is implied in his letter. The important question is whether the Oil Company is contemplating undertaking lighterage work or not. Smith probably did not have time to make inquiries before he left| i but I suppose you will be doing so and I shall be most interested to hear the result and should like to be kept informed of the progress of this case. Yours sincerely . Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E.&gt; Adviser to the Government of BahrainConfidential. D.O.Ho. 9 Adviserate, May 17, 1945. / Reference your D.O.No. C/531 dated the 5th May, 1945. I had a talk with Anderson about his application for permission to act as agent for certain Ajuerican Shipping Companies. I understand from him that the Company wishes to load and unload its own cargoes and passengers from the ships whose Companies were named in the lett-er. The Company has no intention or desire to undertake lighterage of would use its own craft. Anderson said that the reason for the application was because the Company is thoroughly dissatisfied with the service which is provided by Gray, Mackenzie. cargo which is not destined for Bapco. The Company C. J. Pelly, 3squire, O.B.E., I.G.S., His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain.\ ^ No. C/586.' POLITICAL AGENCY, ^ BAHRAIN. f Dated the 26th May, 1945, From C.J. Pelly, Esq., O.B .3., I.C.b., Political Agent, Bahrain . V To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre . Subject ;- Bapco's request to undertake lighterage. Sir, . . VV I have the honour to enclose copies of the cor- \U respondence marginally noted and to state that though \ I have 1. Letter No. CON-314 dated 21.4.*45 from 0 considered the Chief Local Representative, The 5 the cor- Bahrain petroleum Co., Ltd., Bahrain. 0respondence 0 ending with i' 2. Political Agent's demi-official lette^ x 0 your telegram No. C/531 dated 5.5.'45 to the Adviser Q N o. 19 dated to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, jj the 4th of r &gt; 0 January to ^ 3. Adviser's demi-official letter No.988-20 0 the India Office, dated the 17th May, 1945. j yet I do not think that in the circumstances disclosed by this correspondence it is wise to advise the Bahrain Government to refuse the Bahrain Petro leum Company's request. I should be grateful if you would intimate your agreement with this view. I have the honour to- be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. I - ^ political Agent, Bahrain. / NS.10/21. Telegram S(Pad), From Political, Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1037. Dated the 4th and received 5th June, 1945. Your letter No. G/536 dated ..jay 26th. Please telegraph gist of Bahrain uoverniaent 1 notice 23 /1351 dated October 24th, 1932. 2. Is American Republic Corp/ration a tanker -j/ce service or a passenger and cargo service or a combination of both ? L- P - JAJJLO'.VAY - R.ll. I.fl. 398'yO POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, D. 0. No* c/624. Dat^. the 6th June, 1945. My dear Belgrave, Reference correspondence ending with letter No# 988 - 20 dated May 2# Colonel Galloway enquires from me whether the American Republic Corporation is (a) a tanker service, or (^)) a passenger and cargo service, or (c) a combination of both (a) and (b). 3 * I should be grateful if you could give me a reply to these queries* 4. The American Republic Corporation is referred to in Ward Anderson^ letter No* C0N-3i4 dated the 21st April, 1945, to Smith, the Director of Customs. Yours sincerely, C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, B a h r a i n.Telegram. S(Pad) From. Political Agent, Bahrain. To. Political Hes ident, 3ushire, No. 369 Dated 16th June, 1945. ^ Your telegram No% 1037 4th June. Following is gist of notice. Begins: No one is allowed to load or unload passengers or cargo in Bahrain waters or to become an Agent of any ship or aircraft engaged in these operation without the permission of the Bahrain Government for which written application should be made. - POLITICAL-No. C/651. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 17th June, 1945 To v The Adviser to the ^ Government of Bahrain, / \ ^ ] Bahrain . y Memorandum. ^ 7- I would be grateful for an early reply to my Demi-official letter No. C/624 dated the 6th June, 1946, as the Hon^ble the Political Resident is pressing for a reply. political Agent, Bahrain#. NS.I .R. nor Copy of D.O. No.W.)6 -3SF dated 12th June 1945, 'from the Adviser to the Governciont, Bahrain, to LIr. ,7.P. Anderson, The Chief Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Company ^ No. CON-314 dated 21st April _ Smith. Villi you please let me know whether the American Republic Corporation is (a) a tanker service or (b) a passenger and cargo servi (c) a combination of both (a) and (b). Foregoing copy forwarded to H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum No.c/651 dated the 17th June 1945. No reply has yet be^i received from the Bahrain Petroleum Co. With reference to your No. //^V— Adviserate, June 19, 1945. Adviser to the Govennment. 3.Z.10 ! 2~ { Awe 11 18th June, 19^5 £0|bM£ C, D. B «lgravo t Esq., Adviser to the Government Deer Sir, ^ ^ Kindly refr^r to your letter No,1156-3SF of 12th June, 194-5. The American Repvbllc Corporation operates a fleet of tankers bvt it is not known whether it also operates cargo and/or passenger vessels. However, the sub-agency to which the Co»pany has been appointed only applies to tankers. Yours v^ry truly f. P. AKPlRSOli CHIEF LOCAL KHPRESENTATIVE THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED 080.02\o\l\ Copy of letter No, COli-348 dated 18th June 1945, fron the Chief Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleuii Company Limited, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Kindly refer to 12th June 1945. 1°) your letter N0.1156-33F of The American Republic Corporation operates a fleet of tankers but it is not known whether it also operates cargo and/or passenger vessels. However, the sub-agency to which the Company has been appointed only applies to tankers. Adviserate, June 20, Foregoiyc copy forwarded to H.B .lu T s Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to my endorsement No.1187-33^ dated 19th June 1945. Wenfial. h ■ — - Adviser to the G-overnmoiit.URGENT No. C/664 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 21st June, 1945 To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. M emorandu m. Reference your endorsement No. HQS-SSF dated the 20th June, 1945, 2. Does the AGEECY for which permissior) is asked also apply only to tankers? political Agent, Bahrain.wm . c58 CONFIDENTIAL . \ N0, C// 665 * , POLITICAL ACSRCT, BAHRAIN, Dated the 21st June , 1945. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments tot The Hon'bla the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) % ^ continuation of Agoncy telegram No. 369 dated the 16 th JUno, 1945&gt; REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: 'N NA^E &amp; DATE. Description of Enclosure . SUBJECT7 copy of Tiotice No. 28/1351, |dated the 24th October, 1932 NS. ^1wmmm Telegram From To Repeated 10/21. S (Pad) S/S for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Bahrain. w ii No. 15211 Dated 6th and received 7th July 1945. IMMSDIATS . GUARD. TOP SECRET. &gt; &gt;€ t; ^ Your telegram No. 1134 June 23rd. Lighter Agency at Bahrain. 2. Matter has been taken up with Gray Mackenzie in conjunction with other interested Departments. Gray Mackenzie state that they have been acting as agents of Isthmian Line and are somewhat puzzled at reference to four shipping lines mentioned in your telegram. Although they have had minor complaints in past they have had no major complaint from Isthmian Line or Bapco and were in fact recently complimented by'Isthmian Line on their work at Ras Tanura. They consider that position has materially improved over last eighteen months and that they now have adequate facilities for dealing with Bapco•s requirements. They are however admittedly short of European personnel of quality required (and) have repeatedly pressed for release of men from Services though hitherto without much success. Matter is being (dealt) with by competent Departments here. 3. H#M.G. attach great importance to doing all that is possible to assist Gray Mackenzie to maintain their position at Bahrain. Before any advice is given to Bahrain Government regarding Bapco's application I should be glad if you could let me have more specific information as to grounds of Bapco's dissatisfaction. It is possible that it relates to an earlier period when Gray Mackenzies were less able to meet Bapco's requirements. 4. Above was drafted before receipt of Government of India telegram No. 5997 of July 5th. vi/e are in agreement with general line taKen in paragraph two. Other point raised will be further considered' on receipt of your reply to this telegram. \ ^ y RETAXANDUM I.R. 454 , 7/7/45. J.A.N.C.I.R.458 7777457 5 V political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram From To No. 1220. Dated and Received the 7th July, 1945. IMPORTAN T. India Office telegram No. 15211 July 5th. 2. Please telegraph information in paragraph No. 3 with your comments in general. =GALL0WAY= NS.10/21. Telegram S(Pad). From Political Resident, Bushlre, To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1221 Dated and received 7th July 1945. IMPORTANT. Following is repetition of Government of India telegram No. 5997 July 5th. Begins. Addressed India Office repeated Political Resident. V GUAaD . X &gt; Galloway's telegram No. 1134 June 23rd 1945. Lighterage Service at Bahrain. 2. We consider it 6f great importance that control of transport facilities at Bahrain should remain in British hands in ordt r that ?oil interests and communications in the Gulf area may be preserved. While we are anxious to maintain to the full American interests in this region we should regard elimination of Gray Mackenzie's present rights by American competition as disadvantageous generally to our position in Gulf. Principle is that existing British services should be maintained and made efficient. 3. We are inclined to question Company's right under Article No. 4.3 of Deed Of Modification to operate own lighterage service since they could scarcely (maintain) such service was 'necessary for purpose of its business' if alternative of efficient service were available. 4. For these reasons and also in view of difficulty pointed out in paragraph No. 2 of Prior's telegram No. 19 of January 4th 1945 it is recommended that Bahrain Government should be advised to refuse permission asked for. At the same time positive action is obviously needed by way of press(ing) Gray Ifeckenzie to effect early improvement in xxxxlss their lighterage service in which they should be assisted in every possible way. Ends. . . ^ GALLOWAY I_.R. ,460. 7/7745. ' V' VaV 1, J.A.N.G.CONFIDK^TIAL . (f POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, D.O. No. C/698. 1 ^ I Dated the 9th JXily, 1945. My dear Belgrave, Reference your Demi-official letter No. 988-20 dated May the 17th, 1945# Colonel Galloway has asked me to let him have more specific information as to the grounds of Bapco^ dissatisfaction with Gray Mackenzie. I should be grateful if after consulting Anderson, if necessary, you could let me have this* I must say thac it seems to be a sort of fashion to abuse Gray Mackenzie here as so far I have not come across anyone who has gone tftto trouble (or probably - has the courage) to frame a specific complaint. . 2. His Majesty^ Government attach great importance to this case and are not at all keen that permission should be given to American firms to compete with Gray Mckenzie. . Yours sincerely, Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq. 9 . C.B.S., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. % NS.\0 ** fSECRET Telegram S(3) • iJ From Political Reaidenty Bushire. To Secy .of State for lndia 9 London Repeated aorernnent of India* New Delhi. 1*11 Copy by bag* Political Agent 9 Bahrain. .X-O/r , Confidential. la ted 23rd June 1945 • BAHRAIN RECEIPT. nq..(lU Date..j/.a r ..^:.... 0 P A R D Reference cor reap end ence ending with Residency telegram Ro.lQ January 4th. A Bahrain aoyernment reflation of 1932 prohibita the loading or unloading of paaaengera or cargo in Bahrain watera 9 and the taking up of any ateamahip or air line agency 9 without Bahrain Government permission, r In compliance with thia regulation % Bahrain petroleum Company hare applied to Bahrain Goyemment fcr permiaaion (a) to act aa Agent a for Pacific Tanker a incorporated, War Emergency Tankers Incorporated, Tanker's Company Incorporated and American Republic Corporation, and (b) to load and unload paaaengera and cargo from yeasela of theae four companiea in Bahrain watera.. Bahrain petroleum Company would uae ita ovn craft. Reaaon alleged ia thorough diaaatiafaction with lighterage aeryice prorided by Gray Mackenzie. 2* While it ia important to retain lighterage work in Bahrain in Britiah ihanda following pointa render it difficult to refuae permiaaion to Bahrain Petroleum Company s (a) Inefficient aeryice proyided by Gray Mackenzie, (b) fact that permiaaion ia Bought not for general- lighterage work but only for handling cargo and paaaengera for Bahrain petrolium Company for the apeoified shipping lines.34 v - 2 - (o) probability that the Company it entitled to euoh permiBaion under Article 4(b) of Deed of Modification dated 19th June 1940 of Bahrain oil Conceesion nhich however they have so far not cited. in London with Head Office of Gray Mackenzie* If this L»oinpaiv is unable to provide satisfactory service very early there appears no alternative but to aivise Bahrain GoTernnjent to accord pennission sought by Bahrain Petroleum Company. We should otherwise lay ourselves open to charge of impeding war effort. Suggest matter be taken up confidentially - Galloway - JKG S B C R B T N0.679-S PERSIAN GUI? RSSIDENCYV BtJSHIRB. 24th June 1945. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - ^ 1316 Political Agent, Bahrain. ,^I 21 GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. D.O.No./T/i?'- 3 /y^ Bahrain, Confidential. 3? 1945. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date ti 2 r M... Reference your D.O.ITo .C/698 dated 9th July, 1945. I gather that Bapco are dissatisfied with the Landing Company owing to their hifh charges for landing goods, slowness in unloading steamers and insufficient measures which are taken by the Landing Company to prevent pilferage from cargo. Bapco would welcome some rival firm which by competition would stir the present Landing Company into greater activity. Bapco does not wish to undertake the work of landing its own cargo provided that an efficient Landing Company exists, such work is outside the normal activities of the Company whose policy is always to make use of local organisations and services provided that they discharge their duties capably. The Company first discussed the question when Wakefield was here and then let the matter drop. Recently, because it has seemed that conditions have deteriorated they took up the question again mainly with a view to stirring the Landing Company into greater activity. Bapco also complain that the Landing Company is using its best personnel and material for work at Ras Tanura where tiB Landing Company has not the virtual monopoly which it holds in Bahrain but depends for its success upon its own effioiency. It appears to me that the Landing Company by undertaking the mainland work is reducing its efficiency in Bahrain. 2. As far as the Bahrain Government is concerned we have no complaint to make concerning the Landing Comjany's service but compared to Bapco and the Services we employ them very little. I understand that the Army, Navy and R.A.F. are all dissatisfied with the Landing Company, 2/-3? - 2 - this I have heard quite unofficially. His Highness Slaikh Sulman and many of the local Arabs criticise the Landing Company particularly because they know that the amount of pilferage from cargo between steamers and the shore is very great. This fact is known to me and from police reports I believe that the pilferage, whicr. has no / become a r4j;ular trade, is carried out by the Company f s employees. It is difficult to catch the culprits especially as the Landing Company officials do not report losses to the police authorities. 4. Returning to the question of Bapco, I understand that they will willingly let the matter of agencies drop if the Landing Company will give them an assurance of improved eixiciency in future. 'Yhen the causeway which is being built along the pipe line at Sitra is completed, probably ne^t March, ships will come alongside and the Company's cargo will be off loaded onto the Company*s trucks so then the Company will not have to depend upon tue Landing Company as much as they do at present. 5. It is not for me to contradict the opinions of the authorities who are considering this matter but I should lixce to state that in my opion Bapco is not seeking to expand its iii-luence or activities by setting up a Landing Company oug iias put forward the request to unload its own caigo from steamers at bitra in order that thB Landing Company o^oula by fear of losing the Bapco contract be compelled to impi o '/ g ios methods. In the past, more than a year ago, when tal^in^ about the matter with Anderson, he asked why oLe Bahrain Government did not run a Landing Company as is, I believe, done in some other Gulf ports. I told him that v/o nad ooo many ocher activities on our hands at present, ^7 C.J. Pelly, Jsquire, O.B.^., I.C.S., L. B. hl f 3 Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram, ffrom. To, No. 412 Dated 14 th IMPORTANT GUARD 2. (a) (b) (c ^ (d) 3. dissatisfied with Landing Company. 4. I believe Bapco does not wish to undertake landing work and have put in this request in order to move Landing Company to better their service and that Bapco will withdraw request if given by Landing Company assurance of improved working in future. 5. I recommend I be instructed to send for local representative of Gray Mackenzie and to put complaints of all organisations before him and to ask him to give, if possible, assurance to Bapco. He should also be instructed by his Head Office to co operate fully in removing sources of complaints. . POLITICAL LR. 10/21 S (PAD) Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Bapco^ complaints are high charges for landing goods, slowness in unloading steamers, insufficient measures taken to prevent pilferage, use by Landing Company of its best personnel and material for work at Ras Tanurah where they have no virtual monopoly existing here. Understand Army, Navy, R.A.F., and Bahrain Government alsoLighterage at Bahrein SECRET Record of a Meeting at the India Office on 3th July, 1943 Present : Sir C. Kisch (in the Chair) Mr.G.P.Hotblack) Mr .W.J. Gordon ) Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Mr.Campbell ) Sir Geoffrey Prior (Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) Gen.R.C.Money (Ministry of War Transport) ^•k-C.Streatfield^ Ministry of Fuel &amp; power ]Vir, G.P.Mason ) Lt.Col.R.S.Grant (Tn.i. V/ar Office). Mr.F.A.K.Harrison (India Office). 1. The Chairman explained that we had heard that the Bahrein Ptetroleura Company had applied to the Bahrein Government for permission to act as agents in loading and unloading passengers and cargo at Bahrein from vessels of Pacific Tankers Incorporated, Y/ar Emergency Tankers Incorporated, Tankers Company Incorporated and the American Republic Corporation, alleging dissatisfaction at the services provided by Gray Mackenzie. He invited Mr.Hotblack to give a statement of his Company's position and their difficulties in order that it might be con sidered what could be done to assist them, 2. Mr.Hotblack said that Gray Mackenzie were the Agents of the American Isthmian Line at Bahrein, and that they had little knowlea^e of the Shipping companies mentioned in the Political Resident's telegram. They thought that the peak period for unloading cargo at Bahrein had now passed and that they now had adequate barges and tugs at Bahrein to deal with the Bahrein Petrol eum Company's probable requirements. They had, however, experienced diffi culties in securing the necessary European personnel for their operations at Bahrein and elsewhere in the Persian Gulf, owing to the difficulties of securing the release from the Anny of young, fit men with the proper qualifi cations (including language) who would be ready to take up the work as a permanent career, Mr,Hotblack said that Gray Mackenzie had had no major complaint from the Bahrein Petroleum Company though there had been occasional minor complaints in the past by the Isthmian Line, They had recently been complimented by the Isthmian Line in connection with their work at Ras Tanura, ' 3» It was pointed out in discussion that no details regarding the causes of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's dissatisfaction had been given by the Acting Political Resident, nor was it stated to what period they related. The representatives of Gray Mackenzie said the position had materially • improved over the last 18 months. 4. General Money said that Ministry of ¥ar Transport were in favour of doing all that was possible to maintain Gray Mackenzie's present position at Bahrein and were prepared to lend their weight to any reasonable requests that Gray Mackenzie put forv/ard for release of personnel from the Services. 5- Lt,Col,Grant referred to the difficulties of the War Office in releas' ing the personnel required by Gray Mackenzie, and mentioned the need of men with qualifications for cargo supervision in connection with the Far Eastern war. Sir G, Prior said he had been in contact with the G.O,C., P .A,I .C,, on the matter and he thought that only action by the War Office could ensure Gray Mackenzie^ requirements being met. The representatives of Gra^r Mackenzie stated that what they particularly wanted was the release of two named /- 2 - named individxials and tv/o cargo superintendents 6. The Hinistry of Fuel &amp; Pov/er representatives said that they wt&gt;re somewhat concerned about the future, and they they thought that Gray Ilackenzie should be prepared to deal with increasing cargo coirmitnents, e.g. large oil developments at Kov/eit and at Qatar v/ere expected shortly. The vi^v; of the meeting was that it was highly desirable that Gray Mackenzie should prepare a programme well in advance- for dealing with such expanding requirements. 7. It wcis agreed that a further elucidation of the grounds of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's complaints should be sought from the Acting Political Resident before a decision was reached as to the advice to be given to the Bahrein Government regarding the Bahrein Petroleum Company's application. Meanwhile, the requests which Gray Mackenzie had to make to the Service Depart ments for the release of personnel as stated in paragraph 3 above would receive the fullest support of the India Office and the Ministry of War Transport, ' &gt;r ' ■TOP JZlCTiET No. G/lll (J ' /^ JO /&gt;/ /J The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to BAir. No...a..7i The Political Agent, Bahrain and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. &gt;.. 1345.. Reference to previous correspondence India Office telegram Mo. 15^11 July 6th. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Residency telegram 'Jo. T/135 dated IBth July, 1945. Grounds of dissatisfaction of Bahrain Petroleum Company.86/3 Telegram S3. From Political Resident at Shiraz. To India Office, London, Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/135. Dated 18th July, 1946. / r Your telegram No. 15211 July 6th. Guard . T od Secret Following are grounds of Bahrain Petroleum Company's dissatisfaction (a) high charges for landing goods (b) slowness in unloading vessels Oc) insufficient measures taken to prevent pilferage (d) use by Jray lackenzie of its best personnel and material for work at nas Panura whtre they do not repeat not have virtual monopoly they enjoy at Bahrain. 2. Political A^ent believes that Bahrain Petroleum Company would be prepared to withdraw request if jray x ackenzie can assure them of improved service in future. 3. I suggest that head office of Gray Mackenzie be asked (a) to give His Majesty's Government undertaking that all possible steps will immediately be taken to effect improvement in service in Bahrain ( d ) to instruct Bahrain Kanager to discuss question with Bahrain Petroleum Company and give latter similar assurance. Political Agent can afford his good offices. 4. Political Agent reports that he understands that Army, Air Force and Bahrain Government are also dissatisfied with service afforded by Gray ackenzie. There is also certainly no doubt that their virtual monopoly in the Persian Gulf has'resulted in their being neglectful of the interests of steamer passengers who often have unnecessarily to put u^'wlth inconvenience that would not be tolerated elsewhere. Oil developments at Kuwait and Qatar will result in increased cargo and passenger traffic in the immediate future and present opportunity might be taken to impress on Gray Mackenzie the necessity of making proper arrangements to meet these requirements and to improve their service in the Persian }ulf generally. 5. Bahrain Oil Company's right under Article § (b) of Deed of Modification is not now a pressing question but I should be glad to have a ruling at your convenience as point may be reverted to in the future. I understand that Gray 11 ackenzie were unable to assist Kuwait Oil Company in regard to their heavy unloading programme during the next few months and that Kuwait Oil Company are making their own arrangements relying on their right under Article 6(A) of the Kuwait Oil Oancession. GALLOWAY YG.10/21 S(PAD) Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. Telegrarru From. To. No. 448 Dated Still August 1945. IMPORTAN T TOP SECRET GUARD Paragraph 3 (b) of your telegram No. T/135 dated the 18th July, 1945. now Having/heard Ward Anderson at length on this subject I am convinced that Gray Mackenzie's local representatives are not of sufficient calibre to deal with his criticisms and I would urge that you have them appoint some one of director's standing to come here for the purpose. POLITICAL LR.Telegram. From. To. No. 450 Dated 6th August, 1945. IMMEDIATE 10/21. S ( PAD) Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. TOP SECRET My telegram No. 448 dated 5th August. General Manager of Gray Mackenzie's, Basrah has arrived and come to me for advice about Bapco f s and other complaints. I hope to be able to take him to see Anderson tomorrow. No action therefore required now on my telegram first quoted. POLITICAL LR.10/21 Telegram. Q. From. Political Resident, at Shlraz. To. Political A gent, Bahrain. No. T/228 Dated and received 6th August, 1945. U:poht4NT , / Your telegram No. 448 repeat 448 dated 5th August. I entirely agree but before taking action I will discuss with you. GALLOWAY. LR.5f/r/vV Note of conversation^with Mr. Ward Anderson and nr. Beekhuis of Bapco on the subject of wSt^plication to become agents for certain American shipping lines. Mr. Anderson and Mr. Beekhuis visited me today. I heard them for about an hour on the above subject. Mr. Anderson stated that Bapco had no wish to undertake shipping agency business or unloading or to go into competition in this or any other matter except the oil business. What they wanted was efficient service in shipping agency work and unloading at charges allowing reasonable profit only to the supplier. rhis, they stated, Gray Mackenzie &amp; Coy. had never supplied. Their complaints against this ^uiu.y were: (i) Exces sive cha rges. (■■ji&gt; Gray Mackenzie 's charges to them worked out at Rs.5/12/- per ton. They could have supplied themselves in 1942 for Rs.l/8/- per ton and could ao so now for Rs.3/- per ton. Gray Mackenzies were, in fact, imposing such charges as the traffic would bear. (ii) Bad equipment . Gray Mackenzies were not properly equipped e.g. they have no slings and the company had to provide them. Recently the company lent them Af Jr yf t '' a barge to unload the 'NotitleUm'. Gray -/lackenzies' coolies were allowed to load this barge, sa that it upset, ^10,000 worth of cargo and quantities of oranges and grape fruit which apart from the financial loss made a difference 'co the morale of the camp. (iii) pilferage . There were large losses in cargoes being unloaded and not only Gray Mackenzie's coolies but their Indian supervisory staff seemed to be involved in the thefts. When the company itself unloaded a cargo of liquor, nothing was stolen. Gray Mackenzies lost 15 to 20 per cent. (iv) Responsibility . While Gray Mackenzies are paid to be agents, they accept no responsibility whatsoever for losses and whenever claims are made against them for these they take advantage of multifarious clauses excluding their responsibility. The loading notes are alv/ays inaccurate with the errors always in favour of them. Mr. Anderson went on to say that while tho periods in which cargoes of large tonnages had to be unloaded for /Bapcoi I- .1 ; ; r -2- Bapco varied in the past there would in the future be a steady high level of tonnage to be unloaded and that he doubted whether Gray 'ackenzies could satisfactorily cope with it. He said that the new Sitra pier would be avail able for working in March next. As petrol products would be loaded there, a disciplined force of coolies would be required. He knew his own company could provide such a disciplined force but he did not think that Gray ^ackenzies with their contract system of recruiting labour (which he described as the scum of the bazaar) could supply such a force. If Bapco were allowed to act as agents they would act for tanker lines only and would only unload Bapco cargo exclusively in Sitra waters. Passengers there (such as the few men going on leave in tankers) would amount to only 20 or 30 per year. Mr. Anderson suggested a compromise arrangement whereby /£&lt; (i) Gray Mackenzies would remain agents of shipping lines. (ii) the Company coolies would do the work of unloading at the Sitra pier. I told Mr. Anderson that I was aware of the complaints against Gray Mackenzies and that I thought many of them were valid. I said that the matter had gone to a fairly high level in London and that I hoped that Gray ^ackenzies would be able to guarantee the service required and I thought they would as a first step send some one in authority in th^ir company to listen to ;'r. 'Vjoohuis ; complaints; and I asked Mr. Anderson not to press his application until Gray Mackenzies had heard what they had to say and been given another chance to put things right. Mr.Anderson said he had complained locally many times and had also complained to \{t. Campbell, one of the directors of Gray Mackenzies. /;apco,.....Bapco, he said, had paid them enough money to buy the barges required for unloading, but there was no improve ment. However, he agreed to wait but said that if Gray Mackenzies were to be given another chance they should be on probation and he should have a right to appeal against them. I said that since I was aware of the complaints they could always come to me with reference to any arrange ments reached. J? 5'.8.1945.0) Note of a meecing held on 7th August, 1945, regarding Bapco's complaints against Gray Mackenzie and Company. present: Tr. C.J. Pelly, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. I'r. ' ard Anderson, General Manager, Bapco. llr. Russell Brown, • Assistant to the General Manager, Bapco. Mr. Beekhuis, Bapco. Lir. Gregor, General Manager of Gray Mackenzies, Basra. Mr. Allcard, Manager of Gray Mackenzies, Bahrein. 1. The Political Agent stated that both he and Gray Mackenzies understood :r. Anderson's viewpoint that BAPCO's relation to them was that of buyer ana seller. Mr. Anderson inquired what Bapco could do ./hen there existed no alternative seller. The political Agent said that the meeting v/as being held to attempt to arrive ac a solution of that question. 2. Mr. Anderson then reiterated his Company's complaints against Gray Mackenzie as already recorded in the Political Agent 's note dated 5.8.1945. Me said that he wanted a trained crew to work at the oil wharf (the new Sitra pier) and the question v/as - Could Gray Mackenzies provide it? Me believed that BAPCO could arrange for it more efficiently than Gray Mackenzie. He said that in future - when the new Sitra causeway and pier were complete - there would be chree forms of unloading to be done, viz.t- (i) as now at the old Sitra Pier, (ii) lighterage to the end of the new causeway, (iii) discharge from ships at the new wharf. /He added.He added that Gray /[aci^3nzie should use modern equipment such as suitable slings, etc. He and T ;r. Beekhuis said they wanted cheir own checkers of cargo. 3. Messrs. Gregor and Allcard intimated that they did not want to put labour on the oil wharf but to unload ships there in the ships. They preferred to deliver at the ship's side,(where BAPGO would have their own checkers). They had modern equipment but needed supervision - European particularly - to work it. They wanted office accommodation at Sitra for a superintendent and five rooms for tally staff. 4. v[r, Anderson indicated that he could rent zo Gray Mackenzie the office accommodation required. 5. Mr. Anderson suggested that BAPGO's future employment of Gray Mackenzie should be by a special agreement between that Company and BAPGO. r. Beekhuis sai; ^hat such an agreement would have to be subject go two conoitions viz.:- (i) Termination by notice of an agreed length of time from either side. (ii) Revision of rates as costs altered. Mr. Gregor was disposed to agree to these suggestions. He added that his firm was anxious to satisfy BAPGO f s require ments. .6, The Political Agent suggested that the conclusions of the meeting were as follows (i) Agrement in principle by BAPGO to employ Gray Mackenzie. (ii) Bapco are anxious to reach agreement in detail and will go about doing so. (iii) Provided an agreement is reached BAPGO will withdraw their request to use any other Agency. /(iv) Bapco....TOP SECRET , No. P 2. Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, (camp) Shiraz. Dated the 17th August, 1946. From C.J. Felly, Esq., O.B.S., X.C.v^., Political Agent, Bahrain (Camp) Shiraz. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, (CamjO Shiraz . Subject :» Bahrain Petroleum Company's request to act as agents for certain American shipping companies - Complaints against Gray Mackenzie and Company. Sir, &lt;1 I have the honour to refer to the correspondence on the subject above noted ending with your telegram No. T/228 dated 6th August, 1946, and to enclose herewith a note of my conversation on the 6th August, 1945, with Mr. Ward Anderson, the General Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. This was the conversation referred to in my telegram No. 448 dated 6th August, 1946. 2. As you were informed in my telegram No. 460 dated 6th August, the General Manager of Gray Mackenzie and Company, Basrah, came to see me on that date. His name is MT. Gregor and he brought with him Mr. Allcard, the Bahrain Manager of his Company. 3. Mr. Gregor showed me a telegram from his head office instructing him to go into the matter of the Bahrain Petro leum Company's complaints and to do his best to remedy them. The telegram also stated that the good offices of the Political Agent would be available to him. Having read it, I assumed that the India Office had taken action on paragraph 3 of your telegram No. T/136 dated 18th July, 1946. It was this assumption, combined with the obvious desirability of trying to reach a settlement, which deter mined my subsequent action. j \ 4. Mr. Gregor referred to BAPCO's complaints, said he was anxious to remove their causes and mentioned his Company's difficulties. After some discussion on these lines I said that I had heard Mr. Ward Anderson's side of the case but that I did not think any progress could be made until he and Mr. Gregor met. Mr. Gregor then asked me if I would bring him to Mr. Anderson and I said that I would. I arranged a meeting for the 7th August and I enclose a note of the discussion and conclusions which resulted. I am hopeful that the latter will be implemented particularly as Mr. Gregor afterwards informed me that he thought his Company could meet BAPCO's requirements. 6. Before concluding this despatch I have the honour to bring the following points to your notice: (1) At ik their meeting with me on the 6th August Messrs. Gregor and Allcard asked me what was meant by the /complaintcomplaint against their Company that it was neglectful of the interests of steamer passengers. I replied that I was unaware of the details of this complaint but that if they cared to write to me I would endeavour to obtain them. (ii) While Mr. Gregory attitude was conciliatory throughout, Mr. Allcard's seemed to be one of surprise and resentment that any criticism should be made. 6. I should be grateful for your approval of my action in affording my good offices towards reaching a settlement between the two parties to this case. I have the honour to be, Sir, your most obedient servant. Political Agent, Bahrain. NS.»/a. Telegram S.3. ^rom Political Resident at 4hlr»z # To India Office, London* Copy to Govarnnent of India* Political Agent, Bahrein# No. 1/368, Dutcd An^t, 1045. Ky telegram I^o, T/135 July 18th # TOP JJfCRET GUARD, At a meeting at Bahrain on 7th August| arranged by Political Agent brA at which he T»as present, between General Manager «t Jasra of Gray Mackenzie aitd General i«anar:er Balirain Petrole'isa Comp any following concluaicna were reached (a) Agree:lent in priooiple by Bahrain : etroleuci Corapany to continue to employ Grey l^-ackenzie (b) Bahrain P«troleuai Company are anx ious to reach agreement in detail and jrill proceed accordingly (c) Provided arfreement Is reached Bahrain Petroleum Company will wit/idr«w request to use any other arancy (d) Bahrain PotroleoM Coapany reserve right to renew request ahoild Gray Mackenzie prove unsa tisf .'2 ctory# Gray I^ackon^le'j representative expressed desire of his firm to ciGQt rcquireraents of Baiiriln Petroleum Coapany, It is to he hopad that firm will t ke sp«iedy and energetic steps to effect inDrovmrants, - CULUmAt - COriyi^vTriAL Of rice of the Political HetUdent, Persian Gulf, ?0 * C/20f^ Carap, Shiraa, i)t( .€;d the 21st August I 146, Oy Copy forwarded with oompliaents to •Secretary to the jov;rnrent of India, in the External Uepartstint, Kaw Jalht. ee i -olltlcal Ag«at, j-iuif ♦ with reference to Residency telegranj Ho, T/l35^' dated July If th f 1946, with reference to iJ&lt;.hr in letter Ko, dated 17t)i August, 1B46, AHO, 2^TOP SECRET OTfice of the Political Resident^ Persian Gulfj No. C/202. — — Camp, Shiraz. 21st August, 1946. - To „ , , The Political Agent, Bahra in. Subiect:- Bahrain Petroleum Company's request to act as agents for certain American shipping companies - Complaints against Gray Mackenzie and Company. MEMORANDUM . . K 4, s] A \ / y Reference your letter No. P 2, dated 17th August 1945. Please see Residency endorsement No. C/206 dated 21st August 1946. 2 # Your paragraph 5 (i). Copy is enclosed of India Office telegram No. 17940, dated 13th August 1945, and Residency telegram No, T/329, dated 18th August 1945. 3 # Your paragraph 6. Your action is approved. Sd/- A.C. Galloway Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. YG. 2A/S-Telegram S.3. From India Office, London. To Political Resident at Shiraz. No. 17940. Dated 13th received 15th August, 1946 Top Secre t. For Galloway from Prior. Please refer to your telegram No. T/136 July 18th paragraph 4. Sir William Currie (B .I. Director) asked me what complaint that passengers* interests are neglected referred to. Grateful if you could give me details which I could pass on to him. It appears from this that M.W.T. may be passing your telegram or full substance on to Gray Dawes so suggest you mark telegrams 'Personal' when you do not wish them to. see them, - HET^XiiNDUII - Telegram S.3. From Political Resident at Shiraz. To India Office, London. No. T/329. Dated 18th august,1245. Following for Prior from Galloway. Your telegram No. 17940 August 13th. Following can be cited. ( a ) Tenders used are without any passenger conveniences at all and ships in all Gulf ports stand out a distance of some miles in open and often very rough sea. At Muscat and Bandar .abbas not even a launch is provided. (b) No porters or proper arrangements for handling passengers' luggage. ( c ) Lack of assistance to passengers in boarding or leaving vessels, which in rough weather is often dangerous. 2 # Comparison between passenger arrange ments made by the two public transport services viz. B.O.A.C. and G.M. shows up glaring defects of latter. / ARG. - ga LLOW a Y -Telegram. From. To. No. 492 10/21 S(PAD) Political, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Shiraz. m, Dated the 8th September 1946. f&gt; sr£ • Reference correspondence ending with your telegram No. T/329 dated the iSth August. 2- Local Manager of Gray Mackenzie has enquired from me source of allegation of negligence of passengers. May I reply that I understand matter has been referred to London by you and suggest that he asks for details from his head office ? POLITICAL, LR. m/m/IH- ■ August, 1 945. Dear Mr, Hotblack, ,f ^ Many thanks for your letter of 2nd August, on the subject of Gray, Mackenzie^ services at Bahrein. I am glad you went into matters so fully. The letter is most useful to us. I shall look forward to hearing further fr&lt;—' you on receipt of your Acting General kaiser ? 3 report. Meanwhile, we are going into the question of the release from the Army of those men about whom you have written separately, and will also consider your point as to the desirability of being advised in advance of abnormal requirements by the oil companies* Yours sincerely, Sgda Co Kisch Hotblack, ^sq., 122 Leadenhall Street, £•Co3•PERSONAL 31st July, 1945 Dear Mr 0 Hotblack, You will remember at the meeting which was held at this Offioe on the 5th July/ it was agreed that the Acting Political ^ Resident in the Persian Gulf should be asked to supply more specific information regarding the causes of the dissatisfaction of the Bahrein Petroleum'Company with the services afforded by your Companyo « » : We have now-heai^d ''from him 'that the specific grounds of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's complaints are; (a) the high charges made for landing goods; (b) slowness in unloading vessels; (c) that insufficient measures are taken to prevent pilferage; and (d) that the best of Gray Mackenzie's personnel and material have been diverted for work at I.as Tanura 0 The Political Agent at Bahrein has reported too tiiat he understands that the ^rmy and RoA.P. stationed at Bahrein, as well as the Bahrein Govern ment, also feel some dissatisfaction with the services made available to them by your Company, The Political Agent believes that trie Bahrein Petroleum Company would he prepared to withdraw their application to act as agents if Gray Mackenzie can assure them of improvements of service in future, I feel it is a good thing that the grounds of complaints should thus be s ecifically stated in order that the necessary measures may be taken with the minimum of delay to remedy the situation. I understand that you will shortly be hearing from the Ministry of War Transport on the subject, and we must then sec what can be done about it. The matter is one of some .F# Hotblack, Esq, political122, &gt; Lead«nhall Street, Landon, E.C.3» 2nd August, 1945* Dear Sir Ceoil, I am exceedingly grateful to you for your letter of the 31 tit July with regard to the advioes you have received from the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf detailing the causes of the dissatisfaction of the Bahrein Petroleum Canpany with the services rendered by Messrs* Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co* Ltd© This inforaation will be exceedingly helpful to us. We had already had cocanunioated to us by the Ministry of Viar Transport the substance of the message from the Acting Political Resident, and we cabled our Acting General Manage in Busreh on the 30th July instructing him to proceed to Bahrein and to go personally into all these matters so as to get to the root of the complaints and do everything possible to remedy them, and we asked him to s keep in the closest touch with the Political Agent and if thought desirable to invite him to participate in the discussions* I am glad to say that in reply to our cable I have now received one from our Acting General Manager stating that he is prcceedirg to Bahrein today and will report fully from there. As you know, we are particularly short of an experienced Cargo Superintendent and will require a second man after the end of September. We have explored every avenue on this side to find suitable men, and our Acting General liana er is doing the same in the Gulf, but so far, although we are in touch with one or two possible men on this side, we have not as yet secured the men. We have also applied to Messrs* Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co. in Calcutta, to help us by loaning us a Cocjnander or Chief Officer, but they inform us that all suite le men are fully employed with the press of work on which they ar^ now engag&amp;d* • You will realise tiiat, althoug we have searched and are continuing to search every possible avenue to get the neceasary ii»n with the technical experience and of the right age, they are Just not available outside H*M* oer . ces today, although the position should become easier as men are demobilised* With regard to the specific grounds of the Bahrein Petroleum Company's complaints, I hope t) be able to deal with them more fully w ^en I have received a reply to my cable, but the fdlov/ing information may be helpful to you in the Kormally landing charges at Bahrein are based on cost of maintaining a fleet of barges and towing craft for dealing with the traffic to this port* During the war up to early 1943 cargo arrivals were very much reduced and the earnings did not cover the cost of maintaining our float in craft in 1942* Froci April 1943 onwards, owing to the large quantity of material being imported by the Bahrein Oil Company for the extension of the Refinery, we were able to reduce the inclusive landing charge from Rs* 5*12 to Rs« 4*^ per ton, although tae cost of maintenance of craft had substantially increased* Another factor which contributed to our being able to make this reduction was that the port was being used by the U*K*C*C* as a storage depot far cereals* (B) Such information as we have at our disposal does not lead us to think that the rate of discharge vhich has been maintained at Bahrein during the past two years compares unfavourably xith other open anchorages, but as the I*W*T. have been unable to release farther craft, we have had to do the best we could with those available for dealing with the Bahrein Petroleua Company^ cargo arrivals and ordinary commercial cargo* We do know that the overlappiAr; of stea-nei^j a at tim s resulted in a certain amount of delay. meantime* /(C)th«y be of relatiirely short duration, and although we should be capable of dealing with all normal traffic. It would facilitate us to have some viuj.oatiun of the reoulret-.ents of the oil oompaoies for barging at the various poxnts in excesa of nornal, and the duration of the period for which this excess is likely to operate* If it transpires that there will be quite an abnormal amount of b r ±tv re uired in the Persian Sulf, but that it will be for a very short period, it might be possible for the Government to make available us surplus or^ft 1'nx vthes areas to cover this period. We are proposing to send Mr. Anaour, who has had a life long experience of the Grulf. from this country in October to go fully into all these waiters, and I can assure you that everything that is possible will be done to naintain our good naae and connection for the future® Yours sincerely 9 (Sgd*) G.T. Hotblaok Sir Cecil Kisch 9 India Office 9 Whitehall f sj?.nims ig J. C I. EEIa tt JlOB 1/ Iso * Idle I an inclxnad to agree that Artiala 5 (a) of ' tiie KSacwalt 'on^my concession appmirs to put tiv t i^OG^eny ? ia . or aoMn ^t finer ground than the Bahrein OamptB? aa 1 . regards doing its ovm li^itorage # I think there is saae ' aubetanoe in th/^ point imde by the (kr^ rwaeat of India as to the % 2^ effect of rUoXe 4(b) of the Bahrein Joi^any conoeaaion. \ r Ifcrier rtiole^ the ibelkh •grnnta the rlg^it to operate j # certain faollities and apparatus so far as Bay be neooaaary for ths purpose of the Oonvt**?** buBineaa 11 - a (jmlif ioation vvJiich aeeaa to me to be appropriately viorded to onrey the intention that It ms the actual gmnt which wae to be liiaited, and that it me to be Uaited to caiiea aihere the exeroiee of the right waa shown to be neoeoaaxy* Ji the intention h d been to refer to and p-ilify the faoilitiee and c ^jparatua theiaaelves f the vordin^ does not tpptar bo appropriate and one vould^ I think^ have eapoeted the olmae to read aoiaewhat aa iollows: 'Grants the right to operate eto» such faoilitiee am&amp; isqapamtus aa nay be neoeaaary for the purpose of its laiainess** Shortly put, it seasis to xm more reasonable to read •«&gt; far as may be neoeaaary' aa meaning to the extent ti^at it iaay be necesaary for the Ooop^my to have the right' than aa referring to the facilities themselves and meaning W^an the recjuireawnta of the ousinaeE necessitate facilities of this nature % (Intlld) 21.5.4510/21 Telegram. S(PAD) From. Secretary of State for India, London. To. Political Resident, at Shiraz. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 19775 • Dated 7th and received 8th September, 1945. c U\ S Paragraph No. 2 of your telegram No. T/358 of August 21st. Gray Mackenzie are taking following measures for improv ement of services : 1. '^hey hope to despatch three cargo Superintendents before the end of September. 2. The building of an additional ? bun^ Low at Bahrain has been sanctioned. 3. Estimates for construction of a slip way at Bahrain have been received by their Basrah Office. 4. Mr. Armour is to proceed to Gulf in October. 5 # They are looking out for suitable men to send out as Assistants. 2. Copy of Gray Mackenzie^ 3 letters follow by air mail. 3, Company have arranged to transfer four barges from Ras Tanura to Kuwait to deal with increased cargo and propose to oentrat contract on a tonnage basis. They understand from their Basrah Office that both Shaikh and Political Agent are opposed to them undertaking the landing. What exactly is position of present Arab landing Company and does it serve Oil Company as well as mail steamers. v ^ \ - RETAXARDUM- LR. I.E. No. 592.10/21 Telegram. Q. From, Political Resident, at Shiraz. To. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 599 Dated 11th and received 12th September 1945. Paragraph No.3 of your telegram No'. 492 dated September 3th. reply approved repeat approved. GALLOWAY. LH. (I.R.No599). inn* ye Cf HNo. C/875. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 13th September, 1945, To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie and Company, Limited, B a hrain. Memofandum- 4. u / Reference your letter No. Bl/S/639 dated the 12th of August, 1945. 2. I understand that the Hon r ble the Political Resident has referred this matter to the India Office and I suggest you ask your London office for further details. 1c Political Agent, Bahrain, NS.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S .W .I. j/kdj 3 oc^ September, 1945» r &lt; Dear Mr,Hotblack. On page. 5 of your letter to Sir Cecil Kisch dated 2nd August you referred to the difficulties which Gray, Mackenzie have had in providing for requirements arising from large constructional programmes entered into by the oil companies in the Persian C-ulf, ve have consulted the Petroleum Division of the Ministry of Fuel and Power as to the best way in which you may be kept informed of future requirements, and they advise that much the best procedure would be for you to g^t in touch direct with the companies concerned, both in London and the Persian G-ulf - the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, the Kuwait Oil Company (through Anglo-Iranian) and the Texas Oil Company (for Bahrein and the Caltex concession on the Saudi-Arabian mainland), 3, ^ When Mr. Armour is on his visit to the Persian Gulf, the Petroleum Division also recommend that he gets inV^, ^oucn with the Petroleum Division representatives, c/o The Minister Resident in the Middle East, Cairo, and c/o His Majesty's Embassy, Bagdad, Yours sincerely, G, P. Hotblack, Esq,, 122, Leadenhall Street, E.C,3.i m/ f.s XT, 4142/45 jear ijr. Hotbl ck, IIxDji -i. 0- J-. '-lCxj j 'Ml JialiL, LOI-DOi ■) o. .!» * J© .august, 1945. ^ u\■ In continuation )! your previous coa^espondence with bir Gec-1 Lisch, v ;ho is away from the .fi^e at the moment, I write 'co a-iiiorm you that we have now heard froi the Political .^sident ' in the Persian G-ulf that at a meeting at Bahrein on the '/th August arranged by the Political Agent, and at which he was present, 'between the General iianager, Basra, of Gray, Hackenzie C: Co. Ltd., and the General Hanager of the Bahrein Petroleum Co, the following conclusions were reached (a) It was agreed in principle by the Jahrein Petroleum Co, to continue to employ Gray, i.iaclcenzie; (b) i l he Bahrein Petroleum Co, Were anxious to reach agreement in detail and would proceed accordingly; (c) provided agreement was reached, the Bahrein Petroleum Co, would withdraw their request to use another agency; (dj The Bahrein Petroleum Co, reserved the right to renew their request to use another agency should Gray, Mackenzie prove unsatisfactory. This is, I think, satisfactory so far as it goes but much, oi c urse, will depend on the extent to which it proves possible i or Gray, liackenzie to carry through with the minimum delay those measures for inprovement which are at present under consideration. G.P. Hotblack, Esq,, 122, Leadenhall street, E.C.3. Yours sincerely,}£2 9 ^eadwuuu.1 Ji^reet 9 liondoa 9 ^•0«3« ?Oth Avigumt t ^%■5^ Dear 3ir Cecil, v Further to qj r letter of 2^ith instant, I nof enclose two abridfiec oopiea of the report niede b Mr. Gregor # o t General Manager *.t ilusreh, w}to wwb specially sent dewn to Bahrain to investigate the coct^iainti) whloa harl bee*; sade. I l^r-J merely oiBitt*^. certain parts of the report wxiioh deal with pural;' daacatic mattcm and «vhi.oh have no b«ari .ng on tiic pointw at iasufc. The Mr* illuard refejrea to in ths report is our Manager at Bahrein. The report fully confirms nhftt I said at the meeting on 3th July, that our difficulties harc ar^en alcost ^uel^ tiirough our inability to obtain suitable personnel to deal with the largely 'norcased volume of traffic, but I hops, now that the war is over, we shall be able - j .robably with your kind assistance - to get the men we require* v With regard tu the que at ion of charges , you will appreciate that tlie tiaintenance of a lighterage plant in &gt;m area like the eisiiu. Gulf ia an expensive business but nevertheless our Baiireir. Mt*r-a^er is £ I oln&amp; tlosoljr into figures and 1 **ope it will be possible to make sase reduction. As already informed you, now that full3r lafeMMitinn nas beex; f^mis^ied regard ing alleged defactw in he heodltag of pe^&amp;tr^eiu, the wtter is bein ; fully investigated, and I will advise you the result in due courts* KffiSIT O IL O O^iPAhY Ife liave arranged 1c tjiciiSfer four barges from Ras Tanura to Koweit to deal with the inoreaain^ quantities eargo ther« # aud we ure proposing to cojT-vract ori a tonnage basis. Tou will ruuauber that at the meeting on $tii July Mr. Ca^bell enquired of tir 'ieoi^roy Prior wnethsr Witioipatca s^v ou^eoti-n^ being raised ly the 2hcikh, and bo oald hs di&amp; not think then woulc? be any difficulty We have, liowevor, reocdvod a trlegrom froa&gt; Busreh stating that they unoerstand both the Sheikh and the Political Atfrfnt are op oftO&lt;: to our undertaking the lauding. Perhaps you would be good enough to have a telegram sent to the Political Resident with the object of seeing that whatever objections therr may be can be overcome. In the (oeantine, we are trying to en ^elalish c ontact with Mr. £oott of the Konreit Oil Company whe is reported to be ia this counti:;. With thanks in anticipation of your assistance. Yoiors sincerely, (Sgd.) Q*#* iiotblack Sir Cecil Kisoh, K.C.I»£., India Office, Whitehall, S.wr.1. P.3. I have taken the liberty of passing a copy of the report and ay letter to you to sir Geoffrey mor, which I hope meets with your approval#S' jSJRpliawis wib laid on the Tie# of the Oil Canapcixy th^t t - ( iocci oapwrvixore ao;^loy®ci by u» ^rsts 1 nea^pcricncod and. tov- xj ..a^txe oori^roi. tiM labour working on board ahipe and in bajg ®a» Goii»oqu«ntly valufcLls oarj^o waa not handled and a cowed in the Bmnoar they were entitled to expect and he would even go 3 o far na to amy that the daaa of SuperriMrs md Cheokera provided i netead of aoting ao a deterrent to pilferage -vaaf in all probabili^Tj an en.001 t a e r rtent« b - Mr* Ward Anderson went on to say that no ueefui purpoee oouid near be serred to either oarty by .ndulginv in r«ari»Jiination» regaixiing what iiad Ua ^c^eu the paat but he felt he had'maple ^uetifioation for pXaxUng oefore the Poiitioal Agent directly f without fur tiler reference to ue» tae ;aain xrojwiM ''or their dia- eJti^faction oinoe they were confident tneir own organisation was in a poaiticn io furnish uucJi better aervioe ?JJ the mattex-s wllich forraect the coralaiut* He t **ri ¥ it olcai alno that he was not particularly interr-atea in whether ^ray or any other party aid thui '.vork for them 30 long as tnyy obtained that degree of satisfaction for wnich they were paying. The Oil Corcoany look at it in the ligiit of a aeiier end a bay or f aiid ?jf w are not In a position to e.Li to their satisfactiur. the pai-ttuular ooanodity they wish to buy - in tnis caud •&gt;roper oai-e of their cargo from ship to snore - thapr mmt look far uome other avenue by wnioh it can c*3 provided* It nr .ust bo adBltted hat not a.. uniT^asOiiabie point of view. He abroad we had nunoroua difficulties to contend eitli but maintained it wa^ our ooncem to averowie them# ^ 7. On the queatiori of tfiBxfKB advisea that based on figures which they had ooniuiled In 1^42 uhay ectxtatad that the:- tnsajseivoa «wuld hwre provided lighterage and other casentliCl usrTioaa rdth their orm oersormel in the 1 armer thoy roqilred at a cost not exceeding Rn .2/- pei' ton, ae g ainst tne scale oeing dtarred b rm. In addition theijr fi^iii^s wovid hnve aJXored for the ccropl^ta amo-T^isatiori of capital faqpeoatf.tvw on Utters and rnqftifmrnt bet .een and the ^resent time. He reitei-atea, however &gt; that on our pi-oaent assurance ^f o^ desire to improve conditions, lie was preparod to supply us vri tsx deta:i ^ 3 1 hexr mture .aan« in wler taat wc could get toother with them and work out arrsnfee- »en s wiOdi would be to cutuol advantfiige. Ho wwnt on to s^y -hac witn the nev/ Qauserey now owpleted a?:d tiw new Wharreo expected to be in operation by Jtor-di of next year, the woulc require us oo ^v.* ameiided quotations for tM following work j- 1) Liytiterage froti wiii t /S delivering Sit^a andiora^te to dcd. 4.vcij point at the old Sitra J etty• 2) Li tt htera^e rr^ti yhips delivering ai iianaa^ andioarage to dilschai'ge over the oLcl Sitra JetV* (Xt is not antici^pated that the quantity liandled in this *a^ will be Itu^e) 3) Lighteiagc frcm tiie sitra anohor^.r (ancl froa steiisaa) to t/x new Uaustrcay* if) Ligiitera^e for cargo rwoeived overside frua vessels berthed at the new Wharres to the new Cause»^y. 5) Stacking and reloading into cjotor vehicles on the new wharves. Hotoi It was pointed out that it was doubtful wl &lt;«$hc *r ws would be a. «d eventually to undertake this work t as in view 01 the prt-uaatiune necessary lor fire security purposes, it was their intention to train their own labour gsa^s a id cuec&amp;era for this sari-. Labour for warUnb ships at fchc w harves *oild hays to be providad by us in the usual wty # and 03q&gt;hasi* aaa laid npon the ccrooio for prooaatiuna being taken agftinst fire in view of the involved sirioe there wharves will also be utilised sj * delivery points for bulk oil deliveries to tankex-s etc. •2 - x request was made for estimated tonnages to be handled m nthl / over t e various discharge ^oints but to the tijse of my leaving Bahrein these had not bean received. Their proposed proeiratans extends to iS47. ^ ' During the discussion no pcference wa^ toade to the fourth point ,Bcn ^ a ^. in London f s telegram Ho. 3** i®* i»« *7 «» of our ^st personnel aterial fox• 3 • \iOrk at Has Tanura but It was €*xplMjied hy Kr* -Hoard that it rac Intended, aluost inxaadiatttly, to put into operation a new aoheme whereby all li^itorage, au ] l &gt;ezvlaiGn f labour 9 etc. would be central ised under one control from Bahrein, and it was generally agreed that this would make for sore satisfactory and efficient working* It was suggested that, to cover thr new proposed arrangenents, an agreement should be enterttd into dearly defining our obligations and embodying revised rates of oharges which the Oil Coapany insist are neo ^s &amp;arj if we are to continue to work together* It was clearly indicated that It wc can i&amp;aks our orrangeaents to fit in with their requirements they rill be pleased to c^ntinus to work with us* /*' Mr* Felly asked Mr* Ward Anderson to confirm that on our ^asuranoe that steps were being taken to put mattera right he would withdraw Bazoo's request to be penaittcJ to a»ake their own arrangements for dlsolxxr .^lag th&lt;jir oarsoes in the future and he confirmed that tills was so* Z promised that the question would be discussed fully by Mr* All card and myself, but that in the natter of ^emonnel it might take a little tiroo to coa^lote the c^ganiaatian we vlaualised in view of the difficulty in obtaining ran, and that, in any case, so far as costs were ooncemed, Mr* Alloaru aho ild be in a position in a few days t me to give them our Ideas on the question of amended quotations# This ooncluaed our tUacussions which I should add were frank and cordial on both aides* l(. The only stipulations •Bapoo' had to roajte In regard to the texms of the proposed agreeoent were that olauaes sho Od insert&lt;*! cnabl ik^; oitlier iAr%j to withdiw by giving notice for a specified period and th &amp;t provision aho id be aiade for reconsideration of the scale of oharges at psrlcdls ntorval^ to be agreed# We indicated w*» had no dbjeetlcn to those :&gt;r , ov5ja0»* 2Tr* AlJLcarA has been left to ocnolude the negotiations with the OH Compare ond to report to you when a satisfactory conclusion has been reached* /'L Mr. Pelly left far bhlraa on the evening of the 7th inctant, fdloelng our meeting with 'Bapeo' officials, so that uofortasuttely ?re did not have the advantage of his presence during the subs^mient diecuasions we had rdtli Mr* Ealxy^le Belgrave, Adviser to the &amp;&amp;remaent of Bahrein, and the rcy and R *A«F* repretjentatives* 1 called on Kr* Belofrave by appointnent on the 8th, and explained to him the reaaons for ray visit* He expressed surprise thaf the Bahrein Sovemsaent should have been assoolated with any occxplaint registered against Gray Mackenzie A Co*, and stated that he had oade none either to the Folitical Agent or to any other party* He did reo03Ieot, however, that during general uisousslons with the Pclltlcsl A ^ent the question of the heavy increase in the amount of pUfcra ^-e and amu^gllng thet was going in the Bahrein ar «a had fonood a subject and that they were all very ooncemed n the atter with the objeot of enteavouring to ensure that adeq .wte preventive parecautions were being taken* Mr* Belgrave said that It &gt;alght have been because of this that It had been aas ^iaed a specific oocplaint had been made although he was definite on the point, so far as he waa oosacomod, that no allegations were levelled ag^lnat Gr^y Mackenzie A Co* He agreed that we were working in the closest possible oo-operatiofi with the local police, t^io maintain r gular wotor boat patrols and that a ^jrt from what we were now dboing, he had no further suggestions to sake* Rooentiy there had been a number of oonvictlons in the local Courts for pilferage and smuggling and very heavy sentonooc had boan given* Mr* Bel^jrave infomec?. vo that the C r^^ernaent of Bahrein iiad recruited from TT*K* &lt;ne PoDLioe Sex^oent and tlx Oai-atablcs T ^ho were erpeoted in Eafcreln in the mar futxir©, and that it Is intended that tb«se men should be oculoyed in an eodeavosir toVeak up theje activities as they no* appeared to be organising themselves into gangs* 13 1 asked Mr* tfelgrave whether he had received oomplalita fro:;i any ^ouroe concerning the nei ^Leot on our part of passengers ombarking or disembarking at Bahrein, and he stated that he knew of no such complaint* Zt is interesting to note that a si,.liar xv^ly was ^iv^sv by Mr* BnlXy wl^rn the toalter i^enticned to him and he promised to enquire into it if we would write to him on the subject* This was done and Mr* Alloard no doubt will be sending en a oopy of the reply received*tif- Following my talk with Mr* Belgrave I had the opportunity of niewting the Axmy and R«A«9» repre^entatlv s who deal with the raovemant of all cargo and parsonnal at Bahrein - Capt* Beoboiv Is the British Amor Morementa Officer and FAieut. Balrd, the R.A.F. Liaison Officer, both of whom attend all HJT.t* meetings and are in daily oontaot with Mr* Allcard* They expressed surprise at the reports referred to in London 9 s telegram and assured cie they had net emanated from them* Prior to leaving Busreh fop Bahrein, I took the op.art unity of ascertaining from the M # W*T. Representative and the Service Departmenta concerned if they knew of any complaints against our organise 4 ion at Bahrein, and was assured that on the contrary signals had been sent congratulating all concerned, including Gray liackensie A Co*, on their perfonnance In the handling of the large quantities of materials now being dealt with at the port* I luention this as it appears to me the allegations concerns ne neglect of passengers is probably msde by the Political Staff under the raisapprehension that we have control of the allocation of passenger accommodation, which is a matter on which we act under the instruotiuns of M*W «T*, Busreh* . /■» • ^ I have been asked by Head Office to ascei'tain the root of the trouble *** there la no doubt in ny mind where thir ori/^inates — inea^erienced and incompetent 1 native Supervisors and Checkers ccdbined with lack of sufficient rnmpean Staff to maintain constant contact on board ships and on shore* This is the hub around which the whole of our landing arrangemestis revolve, and if there is faulty perfoxm&amp;nce right from the start of our operations, rm canncthope to carry out the work without adverse criticism* Owing to the demands from various sources, such as the Oil Companies toiemselves and the SerrLcea, it is extremely difficult to retain good labour but since ships can be worked with the men made available give close and efficient supervision in the matter of slinging and stowage, the cause of complaints in this regard should be eli-nlnated* Complaints over Inadequate precautions against pilferage can also be considered complementary to the absence of effective supervision throughout the period when the cargo la in our care* ^ The standard of local Supervisor obtainable in Bahrein is extremely low *** although efforts have been made to recruit trained Iraqis there has been little or no success owing to their reluctance to accept employment in B hrein in spit of the high terms we are prepared to offer* In ay opinion, if we intend to continue with this business* the only satisfactory solution would be to obtain the services of British Supervisors experienced in the handling, slinking and stowage of heavy equipment as well as possessing the ability to control local Supervisors, Tall Clerks and Labour* The type of men who could probably be used to best advantage on such work would be those I*W *T* personnel wo previously considered for es^ploy- mont on the Bahrein Petrol project, and if wo could obtain the release of two additional men, similar in Vpe to Mr* BrayshajT, they wold moet our iuasdiate . requirements* The difficulty In obtaining such releases even now is ap ireciated, and in order to ensure that assistance is sent without delay I am endeavouring to obtain the services of two experienced Supervisors from Busreh who can be sent there cn temporary duty until more permanent arrangements can be made* Bven if we have to pay unusually high wages in obtaining the services of /juoh sien It la essential that conditions at Sitra should be improved as soon as possible in order to prove to 'Bapoo' that we are taking immediate steps to put our '. use in order* V It is coos id red that we have sufficient craft and cargo gear available In the area to take cars of present and known commitments for the future, so that our requirements can be stated defiinitely to be supexvisoif persoonnel* • Following upon the question of the lit of further starf for Bahrein comee that of accommedation* The proposal to erect a new bungalow, if approved by the Company, in time will relieve the position very oonside ably as this would permit of all staff being acoo imodated in the house above the Office the two ho s at present under lease to us* This would mean that, apart from the Manager, nine or ten Assistants could be aoconmodated, if required* ^ Aa soon as it is possible to obtain supplies it will be neceasary to order Linen, Crockery, Cutlery and Glassware sufficient for two hourses* Sgc/- W.S* GRES-CR*122, Leadcnhal^. Street, London, £«C«3* 4th Sei^tcdbtr, 1543* Dear Mr* Donaldson, I am exoaadlngly obliged by your letter of the 3rd September• (1) &amp; (2) Gray Maokensie A Co. will arrange to got in touoh both hare and in the Persian Gulf with the OH Ooiipanies you naoae, and when 14r» iitnour arrives in the Persian Gulf he will, aa you suggest, get in touch with the Petroleum representative in Cairo and Baghdad* (3) we had a call frotu Mr* Soott of th&amp; XoNsit Petvoleuffi Co* with regard to tiie supply of barges for Koweit* Ha infarmed us that we should not be allowed to operate barges in i&amp;weit or to land cai-^o frotL tliem as the landing of .erohaniise in Koi^al^ is resexved for the looal organisation in tthioh the Sheik is finsnoially Interest* d« v/hat tlis Oil Cc pfcudss deairo is that we should place the bargea at their disposal on a bare ooat basis, — th ey inquire steel bargea to load some ocnstruoticnal oiaterial whicli oannot conveniently be carried by the existing wooden ba ges* (L) We have plaosd two steel barges at their disposal and another two will be tiiad® available within the next week, 'but the Oil Cotrpsnios nsst realise tliat as we are debarred from lighterage work in Koweit we aannot be ea^jsot^d to make spadai barges available at that port when they are urgently required for our own business st other ports* At the same time we are always aaadLous to abliae the Oil Companies wherever they are in the Gulf wliere we oan reasonably dr. so 9 having regard to our cwm business, tfe uxiderataad that in any oase tije siecifd barges are only required for a limited period* I think 1 should pass this runfonaation on to you as it does put a dii Terent ootu .lexion on the matter, but does not alter our willinscsss to help wiier*6flf«x v/e osn# Tours sinoerely t (Sgd« y jiOtolei-Uk B.P. Dooaldacn, h.sq,, India Offioa, VhltehaXl, S.f.1.Telegram S(Pad) From To Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Resident, Steamship Nearchus No.606. Dated 10th December, 1945 Reference correspondence ( India Office endorsement iilXT /4426/45 of September 15th. I arranged a meeting this morning between Messrs. Hanna and W^rd Anderson of BAPCO and Messrs. Armour, Gregor and Macleod (B.I.Coy., Calcutta). After a frank discussion Mr. Armour said that he would answer the numerous points raised by BAPCO on his retunn to Bahrain in early January. I shall forward details of the meeting by despatch. 2. Macleod is travelling by '•Barala' and hopes to be able to see you at Muscat on or about the 15Uu LEI. = POLITICAL =egress hmm From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Political Resident, Bushire No. C/1123. Dated Bahrain, the 12th of December, 1946 Reference my telegram No. 605, dated the 10th of December, 1945 2 I enclose a note on the meeting which took place in the Agency on the 10th of December. Mr. Hanna opened his case against Gray Mackenzies by telling Ifr. Armour that he was seriously displeased with their Agency. You will see that his complaints lie, mainly, in two categories: (i) failure to meet claims, vide paragraph 2 of the note on the meeting, and (ii) general unloading complaints. Mr. Hanna told me that he did not wish his Company itself to undertake the unloading, but that his object was that Gray Mackenzies should make an endeavour to meet the Company^ interests. 3. I shall keep you in touch with the developments on the return of Mr. Armour. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED for Assistant political Agent, 1^ Bahrain.Note on a Meeting at the Agency on the 10th December, 1945. present:- Lt-Col. A.C. GALLOWAY, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. Captain R.E.R, BIRD, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Mr. D. Hanna 0 ' Ward Anderson jj The Bahrain petroleum Company. ' Andresen fi Mr. Armour 5 ' Qregor 0 Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd. M Allcard 5 Mr. Macleod British India Steam Navigation Company. 1. Mr. Hanna said that his Company were seriously concerned about pilferage during unloading. He stated, as an example, that during last spring chrome pipe was lost overboard during unloading, etc. The place was not marked and the final result was that more piping had to be specially manufactured and rushed out from Few Jersey. There was at that time a serious risk of delaying the construction of the aviation-spirit plant. He went on to say that a ship had arrived recently for unloading which had previously been in Ras Tanura.- It berthed with all five hatches open and by the time BAPCO personnel arrived on board, which was as soon as possible, the coolies and stevedores were already in the holds and crates of electrical material had been opened, PX supplies rifled and half the contents were missing. Every attempt by per« sonnel sent out by BAPCO to keep watch over the unloading was obstructed by checkers and stevedores of Messrs. Gray Mackenzies. He said that this was typical of most boats coming in here. 2. Mr. Hanna stated that his Company had large claims totalling ^ 175,000 for losses between September 1943 and October 1945 of which 140,000 were still outstanding. His Company had estimated that claims of ^ 76,000 were attributable to pilferage and £ 100,000 to over-carriage, breakage, and rough handling. He said that the Company now were constrained to put their ovm men on the ships and in the holds to stop pilfering of cargo. ARAMCO, he said, had on one occasion paid ^ 2,100 to the crew of the ship to check the unloading. 3. Mr. Allcard admitted that with the present low standard of morality amongst labour, coolies would take whatever they can. Mr. Andresen asked what the police did to prevent these thefts. Mr. Ward Anderson gave as his opinion that trained crews were required who should be permanent employees of the landing company and should be checked in and out of their work, searched and prosecuted vigorously for any delinquencies. He said that, in his /opinion....-2- opinion, there should be proper pension plans, etc., as for his coiapany's permanent employees. He gave as his- opinion that contract unloading was not productive of good results. Mr. Allcard said that a number of the unloading staff had already been prosecuted and some 10 or 12 were at the moment in the jail at Jida. He added that the European police were occasionally posted on ships unloading, fir. Armour gave as his opinion that check should be easy in an open roadstead and J^r. Ward Anderson stated that when the construction of the wharf was complete a search of all labour would be very much easier. 4. Mr. Allcard suggested that there was a lot of pilferage of cargo before the ships.ever left America and lir . Armour that a quick survey of ships on arrival might be of some use. -6. Mr. Hanna said that to his mind it would pay Messrs. Gray Iviackenzies to employ more expensive European labour and asked whether it was not a fact that they were able to get British hands at between £.30. to £.35. a month. —v Mr. Allcard calculated that to employ 15 such men. even if it were possible to get them at those rates and without ueing a.-'le to provide the accommodation and necessary extra facilities which BAPCO alone were in a position to give, would cost the Company about £.100. a day. 6. ar. Ward Anderson said that he had a detailed lisc of complaincs regarding the unloading of s.s.'James Brett' • and he then read them out. They were roughly as follows:- (i) 24 hours after the ship's arrival no barges were unloading• (ii) Broken cases were found in the holds and coolies roaming the ship. (iii) Some broken cases were found in the holds behind ^ intact ones. (iv) Coolies carried burlap bags which appeared to be used for removing stolen articles. (v) Operators were negligent and slinging very careless. The method of removing the load from 6 sling was simply to jerk one end and scatter the cases on the deck. He said tfcjdfe with some heat that this was criminal (vi) Cargo was found in the holds that had been over- carried from Has Tanura and BAPCO were asked to take it over, repack the cases which were badly broken and deliver it to AHAMCO. He contended that this was not his Company's problem but the work of the landing agents. (vii) Kumbers of small craft came up alongside and this was in direct contravention of orders that he understood Gray Bfackenzies had issued. The excuse was that they were bringing water to coolies. In fact, he said, the coolies dran] ship's water. //(viii) No(viii) No attempt was made to repair broken cases before sending them ashore. (ix) Barges with cargo remained overnight off shore which was again in contra vention of the orders, he was told, issued by Gray Mackenzies; there was therefore every facility for undisturbed pilfering during the night. Mr. Ward Anderson stated that, in his opinion, these complaints were not particular to this ship but typical of all. 7. Mr. Armour said that he would go into the various matters with his staff and see what could be done. Messrs. Hanna, Ward Anderson, and Andresen then left the meeting and Mr. Armour remarked after they had gone ohat a large proportion of the pilferage was undoubtedly attributable to the ship's crew and also before the ship ever left the States. Mr. Gregor remarked that quite recently four members of the crew of an American ship were caught in the ventilators in the act of getting down into the hold to take beer. Mr. Armour stated that American ships 1 crews were thoroughly un-co-operative and made no attempt to assist in supervising unloading and compared this state of affairs to that in the B.I. Company where ships 1 officers are apparently responsible for watching the unloading.PSJf- • India Office, Whitehall, S.W.I, 18th December, 1945® HPIw Dear Mr. Hotblaok, • . Thank you for your letter of 13th December in connection with Gray, Kackensie^s interests in the Persian Gulf. We are much interested, of course, in nhat you have told ua about the interview between your Manager and Col. Galloway, and in the local arrangement s for the landing of passengers* The acquisition of an additior ^l launch should be a material factor towards meeting passengers* requirements. We look forward to hearing ftan you further *dien you hare Mr. Armoxar* a and Mr. Macleod's reports. We will see nhat we can do to assist you if difficulty should arise in connection with the release of your tuo Assistants from the Navy. Please let us know if there is any hitch. Tours sincerely, (Sd.) Cecil Kisch. G.P. Hotblack, Esq., 122, Leadenhall Street, E.G.3.rOXFIDKXTI a T j. Nii._ Q ilo The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents liis compliments to His Majesty's secretary of Jtate for India, The India Office, London, The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, and Imp the lioncur to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document ( b ). J** \ / tr' ( ^&gt;(S Persian Gulf Residency, British Gonsulate-Gencral f BUSHIRE. Dated ..the. ath .i^UWX.. Reference to previous correspondence: India Off ice Endorsernrnt No .Ext.4426/45, dated 15.9.45. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. s • 5 Co Bahrain Express Letter ilo. G/l^23, dated the 12th December 1945 and enclosure. X^a(Vr Go y forwarded, with corapli The Politica Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. No ^Jk DateV^.A;,^?.;. Gomplaints by the Bahrain Petroleum Company against Gray iiackenzie &amp; Co. ments, to 1 A^ent , BAHRAIN iiSi) 'l I ) C) ,I V. f Confidential A w a 1 1, !! i* k ■ ^ BAHRAIN' RECEIPT. 11 1 U' (,• C0M-S45 9th Maroh, 1946 The Manager| Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., MMM CLAlMp me iW),7l Dear Sir, . e have noticed o large number of claius, particularly for personal effects, which have been returned by you as accepting no liability for loss or damage, the packages having bet -n landed under clean receipt, i.e. no qualifications having been made on the loading notes, although investigation lias shown in a number of instances that the packages have been received in a damaged condition. V ?e brought this condition to your attention in our letter CO^-321 of 26th April, 19^b ad in your reply letter 3PC/ 82 of 30th April, 1945 you state in perti- 'While as a matter of general principle, loading note must be considered as evidence of the condition and quantity of packages delivered into your trucks, if investigation shows that packages were landed at Sltra in a damaged condition or short of mani fested quantity, and this fact is not evident from the loading note, we a ree that such packages must be subject of special consideration'• Although v.e have brought to your attention a numoer of instances **here the loading note \»es obviously in error, we have found no instaiices which were the subject of 's ecial consideration' i.e. that the claim was endorsed other than as indicated on t. e loading note. .'/tV • We called your attention, in our letter G^/Bl6 of 16th October, 19 A 5| to the fact that although we would be providing some telly clerks at Citre, we would contimae to regard you as responsible for the tally of cargo being unloaded. However, frons our observations on recent cargoes, there appears to be no serious attempt on the part of your,checkers to record the true condition of the cargo. A case in point is that among the packages re ceived ex the 'Empire Stuart' was a small suitcase, the property of F. Fulchfer,; discovered aboard ship completely smashed andcohz515 Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Lid., MMM 9th March | 1946. empty. This condition was pointed out to your supervisor by our representative aboerd ship but on landing at Sitra, no qualifications were noted on loading note #04702. the packape being landed under 'clean receipt'. Further in respect to claims, unaer the tentative agreement oy which lighterage is carried on by you for our account it is specifically stated that Gray Mackenzie shall be respon se ole lor all «cts of its employees while handling cargo either or on Com P an y property. However, in your letter Claims/ STK/97 ol 24th December, 1945 regarding our claim LC 6-7-45 you state that neither the carrier nor the landing company can accept any liability in spite of the fact that you admit that the cargo was pilfered by your employees. The Company takes a serious view of the apparent irres- ponsiblllty in the Handling of our cargo# Although It was hoped thet^af ter the meetings which took place with the repre- senv,atj es ci /cur ompany Ic^t year in which it was stressed that we expected an improvernfrit in responsibility with respect to our cargoes, some improve ne /t would 5ie noted, we must frankly state that In the handling fcf claims, v,e feel that the position In ImproT.dy ^ ^ has deteriorated rather We will appreciate your eap^ comments on the above. Yours very truly, THE BA RIIII PETROLEUM COISPANY LIMITED ORIGINAL SIGNED RY W P ANDFOSO'* |R HV.^.AKDEKSOIJ, GEivEK/ -1 SAN AG KB THBt ms c.c. 280.62 505.71 H.B.M, Political Agentv ^ j f t (oo I* , Letter IIo .Cr/3c34 dated 14-7-42 from Dire ctor of Customs, Bahrain 5. 1 Letter no.P.A. ?34 dated 14-7-42 from Bahrain Petroleum Co, Limited. A ' j £ s 1 and 2 The license granted by the Government of Bahrain to certain Shipping Agents is at page 111 of File 7/3 E.G. The licence granted by the Government of Bahrain terminated on 22-6-34, but it was decided not to pursue the question of re newing it owing to certain reasons (page 141 of File 7/3 J.O.). The schedule of landing charges is at pate 116 and 131 of 2.0.File 7/3. The Agreement lies between the Bahrain Government and the Landing Companies. The Agreement is a privileged document and would not be made public without the concurrence of the parties concerned (pages 26 and 27 of S.O.File 7/3), In the event of any dispute or difference arising between the Government of Bahrain and the Shipping Agents in regard to the alteration or revision of the landing charges the arbitration of the Political xigent, Bahrain, shall be binding on both the parties (clause 17, p^ge 114 of 2.0.File No. 7/3). •ltd. jA . Lli. 19-7-42. Llay the draft below issue ? The answer to 'in' in P.U.G. is presumably b^ application to the Director of Customs. od. in. Q. 22-7-42. There is a great deal more behind Bapco's letter than meets the eye. iit present Gray x~ackenzie act as their local Shipping Agents, and the Oil Company consider that their charges are exces sive. Bapco are therefore considering either making their own arrangements for landing and clearing cargoes or calling for tenders for their work from Bahrain Contractors. Gray Mckenzie's charges have, in particular, been very high in regard to shipments of brick for P.A.D. work at Awali - (the charges for which are met by H.L.G. event ially). I think we should take up the matter with the Adviser rather than with Director of Customs direct, oS the main issue involved is the grant of shipping agents licences to firms other than those mentioned in Director of Customs' le'ter of 14th July. Issue draft Ivlemo below. ltd. 2.B.7. 25-7-42. 3* Issued Hemo No.1333-7/3 d-ted 27-7-42 to Adviser to Bhn Govt. ^ :lOrandum No. 143'^ dated 8-^-42 from Adviser, Jhn Government. The word 'licence' referred to re ' a ' page 111-in File 7/3 2.0. The landing charges Ships Agents-are in accordance with the 'Tarif upon but the Government of Bahrain reserve the at in the P.U.C. 1: charged by the of rates' agreed right to alter any T rates at at any time during the period of licence upon satisfactory proof that the existing rates are too high or too low. Both the Compinies must be charging the same rates as no increase in the l^ndinj charges can be made by the Ships Agents, without the express aiproval of the Bahrain Government. Should the Ships agents show any cause that the existing rates fixed result in loss to them 1 they shall have the right to ; pply for revision of rates to the BahrainGovernment (Clause 4 and 5 of the licence pajs 111 refers). ltd. a.:;. 29-3-42. S;oken to Adviser. Issue as added to. ltd. Ivi. G. D. 3-9-32. Issued letter No» 1533*7/3 d-ited *3—9—42 to BapQO^ .Jcaiirainj^^ Letter No.rA.4lO d^ted^10-.--42 iron »&gt;/.L.» 3ap^o^ .3-1..ra vo\ /^N r The two assumptions mentioned therein may be com irmed from the Adviser. Draft submitted { 1. _ X t 'i. a. i»i. 16-9-42. As amended. ltd. I.G.D. i7-9-42. Issued . tio No. 1679 dated l9-9- / ±2 to i^uviser^ liaiiiain uovt. Copy of Letter No, Con- 3 14 ^ ated 21-4-45 f ror. Ba-co . I am unable to tract tiie notice or any pp m this subject, lay ask d. of C. to send us copy of the Notice ? d.f I a. 7. S-- o J n ni o C. • Lf • X • 24- 4- 1945. Issue. 3d. Il.il. H. 3ird. 24-4-45. Issued l.:emor: ndum No. Cp435 dated 24-4-45 to D of C. Bahrain^ Letter :. T oPA-344 dated 25 -4-4 5 from Di rector of Cu stoms, Baj irain x le^se see also corr.e.w. P.ii's telegram No. 19 page 24 of File 9/12. ltd. G.T. 23-4-45. I suggest tiiis might be discussed with the Adviser who should be told that the P.R. has already^stated^as his opinion that lighterage work should be retained in British hands (page 24 of File 9/l2. ). U Bahrain Government might accede to request as far as tancers are concerned but not to general permission implied in last para of ^xHiS.page At same time, it may be desirable to press for point recommended in para (2) of page 24 of File 9/12. ltd. R.E.H.B. 23-4-45. I Iriave informed Adviser xHit as at 'A'- He is going to as Director of Customs to find out demi-officially from Mr. Anderso|i what exactly his Company wants; it is not clear whether they want to operate lighters or not. sub j wlr. Belgrave thinks there may be previous papers on this ect. There well may be on some other file. Please ask 3.0. It ' 1 * §9^4^45.. to/ Z^o./^o?// ** ^ &lt; ir ^~ -2yf Sapco 's dissatisfaction with Gray Mackenzie seems to date from the 20 % increase in landing charges introduced in 1942. In May 1942 G.M. asked for a 25 ^ increase in landing charges (page 9 of F.9/12). On 14/7/42 a 20 ^ increase was sanctioned by Bahrain Govt, (s.l of F.10/21. But cf. also s.4 of F.10/21). ike same day Bapco enquired what was the procedure necessary for being appointed a licensed shipping agent (s.2), and, in their letter of 10/9/42 (s.6), if new landing charges would apply to Company cargoes if Bapco held their own agency. They seem to have been biding their time ever since. See also note at page 12 of F.9/12. The C.L.R. was also reported to have said that Bapco were thoroughly dissatisfied with the service which is provided by Gray Mackenzie (s.12), of which intercept at s.70 of F.28/25-11 is specific example, / Uay telegraph Bushire accordingly? D.F.A. rO- 7/7/45., I ^ujz- U k lllo tyo (221 7/7/nr O/kc^. U(6-) Tj. iUti P.A. CL 7 r 2-?. (X au h - - Po-Ot If- . &amp; 1*^ J 2b D.0. below to issue to Mr. Belgrave first. ■ W 9/7/'45. JV-O - Ho • ^ ' '7• f R&gt;3,. P ^O. PA' ■ ■ ■ ■ , ■ ,—1© ■ A p t INDIA OFFICE RECORDS yz-ZLQ MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/444</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/444</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/16 (10/21) BAPCO's proposal to act as shipping agents: complaints against Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (110 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order. There is an index at the end of the file (folios 100-110). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the file; it gives brief description of the correspondence with a reference number which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>The foliation system starts at the front cover with 1A, 1B and then carries on until 111, which is the last number given on the back cover of the file; numbering is written in pencil and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Political Resident at Bushire, the Financial Adviser to the Government in Bahrain, Charles Darlymple Belgrave, and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) on BAPCO's application to act as Shipping Agent authorised to collect landing charges in Bahrain and unload ships. The file collects complaints issued by BAPCO against the competitors Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. There are some documents in Arabic, with English translation.There are file notes at the end of the file (folios 100-110).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Ḥamad bin 'Īsá Āl Khalīfah, Hakim of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Bahrain Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfah</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00026b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>