<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000043_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-20T10:45:00.159Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FlLr; 0 COHV IlTvVARD TELEGRAM SECRET X29Q&amp;. Gulf. Al lotted to E. and 0. Deoartmgnt. Ci^o y to External Denartment. ^ r \'^s CYPHER TELEGRAM (Q.T.P. ^ Prarfl ^Political Resident ij/thpq^aian To Secretary of State for India. Rptd. to Governuient of India. Dated Bushire, 19.30 hours, 8th December 1944. Received 00.30 hours, 9th December 1944. ph No. 218 8. Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Government of India. £4 o Ycur telegram 26167 Po verriber 1sth•. Imoorte into Muscat from Mozambique. 2 . Political Agent reports ownership of tea and super cannot be established and must be assumed to be pfert of orders not completed. 3 , Piecegocds and mateheo awaiting shipment belong to Mozambique merchants and were to be handled in Muscat~on commission for forward sales in Persia. Muscat is not therefore particularly interested in these goods and it is hoped by shipping season situation will have changed j ntliD« i ^L. considerably. j -j , 1 INDIA Cr-/• 3J, 0.17668M- Copy to External Department. 21 »t Itormimr, 1%4. ( 5 ) I Jfirty l send you baravlth a .oojQr of a talc^raa froM the Politloal J eoicUmt in tha i*r&amp;i&gt;mn (&gt;iXf in ropiy to our tele^rttn fjo, 233^3 of 21at ctobar wiiioi t «a* aent to him aa a result of your letter L^I/SM? of l6th Gotohor* fou sill see that the tea imported from Mosa tique* into not tea intended for local oonsuDipticm but for re-export to i’orsia via Koweit. that being ao, l aenune that you «111 nor not oonsider it naosesary to Interfere with normal supplies to Ttinoat froa Jaloutta. ; fhe Polltioal Resident is evidently saneehat apprehensive on this point and asks us to tele^ph the dooUlon reached# I should like aooordingly to have your pennisaion to send him a reassuring telegram to the effect that supplies to Muscat wtn proceed as usual# lls Is also anxious lest there might be ease interference with the re-eaqxwrt of any portion of such tea which has not yet been eent formrd from ?fusoat. I assume that you will have no objection to this re-export taking place though you smy feel it neoessary to reduce iersia'a allocation by the amunt of this tea tviiioh la reading them from fAst Afrioa# In ay telegram to the fOlitioal resident I sJiould like to inform him that re 1 export will be permitted# You/ J#M# athiae, Uteq., Minietry of ^sod, Portoan Oourt, Portman Square, V#1.You will note tliat ha haa takan action at lUaoet to prevant is^ortatioa of any further oonsignoents of such tea presumably by instructing the Politio&amp;l Agent at Lliscat not to grant 'no objection' csrtifiOAtes as he did in tbs oase of the sugar which ess finding lie way to i&amp;soat fVora the same source* I m sending s copy of this letter and its enclosure to Oartsright to whom a copy of our telegram under reference was also Yours sincerely.mm - h .J y v.-. 3 : i f &lt;r ^ 6tu \ - 2 - 2 . Figure of 595,000 pounds mentioned in your telegram under reference is combined quota for Trucial Coast and Muscat. Muscat’s quota is only pounds 120,000. ^ 3. Please telegraph decision. ——— IOUTWARD TELEGRAM (If in any case the communication of the contents of this document to any person outside British or American Government Service is authorised, it must be paraphrased.) Economic and Overseas Department, E.&amp; 0. 17515/44. SECRET. CYPHER TELEGRAM Prom Secretary of State for India To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Repeated to the Political Agent, Muscat and Government of India, External Affairs Department* Despatched 18th November, 1944, 17.30 hours. 26167. Addressed Political Resident in the Persian Gulf repeated to Muscat and to Government of India. My telegram No.23593. Tea to Muscat from Mozambique. I should be glad of early reply. In meantime we have information that further 15 tons tea and following other goods under No Objection Certificates from P.A. Muscat are awaiting shipment at Lumbo. 100 bales cotton piecegoods and 100 cases matches. Cotton piecegoods are subject of world combined planning and we should like to know origin and final destination of this consignment. Can you ascertain this in Muscat? Pinal destination of matches may be of interest to the Government of India in regulating their exports of matches which are known to be in short supply. 2. Shipment of 425 tons sugar similarly waiting at Lumbo is being withheld. Copy to:- L.H.Collins, Esq., M.E.W. Miss Hobley, Ministry of Pood. T.S.Robertson, Esq., Ministry of Production, 3, Central Buildings. External Department.-}V\ I attach herewith copies of two letters I have written this morning about (1) sugair from Mozambique to Muscat and (2) tea to Muscat from the same source. You will remember that in the case of (1) the Politcal Resident told us that the sugar received from this source at Muscat was not consumed locally, but was on-shipped to Persia. He suggested that on this account there would be no object in withholding No Objection Certificates as this would merely mean the diversion of the sugar direct to Persia. The counter to this from the Ministry of Food and the Ministry of Economic Warfare is that if the sugar were shipped direct from Mozambique to a Persian port it would be necessary for the shipper to apply for a navicert and in existing circumstances this would be refused. I think you will agree that in this case we must ask the Political Resident to stop the issue of No Objection Certificates which are merely used to evade control. The tea position has not got to this stage yet, , but the Ministry of Food have threatened, 4ihri4 as amount of Muscat* s allocation of Indian tea has already- been exceeded in shipments from Mozambique, to instruct the Tea Controller in Calcutta to close down on any further shipments to Muscat. As pointed out in my letter I think they have got their figures wrong, but in any case we should enquire from the Political Resident whether this tea is consumed locally or not. h/iu7\fujEconomic A Oversea x. *,* 0.16909A4* Dear ,iiM&gt; Hobley, 18th October, 1%if I write with ref erence to Millar* a letter to you of 17th instant, regarding sugar from Portuguese Xaet tfrioa to :'ersia via ?£uaeat by dhow, and 1 enolose a draft telegram to the Politioal peeident in the Persian Julf asking him to arrange for the dieoontinuanoe of Ho jb.ieotion Oertifioatea to cover the shipment of such sugar to Muscat, in order that wfriean ship pers sill thus be forced to apply for navloerte which 1 understand in existing oirouastanoss will not be granted* I should be glad to know whether you have any oomnents to make. X am a oopy of this letter and enclosure to ..Allar and should be glad of his ocraraents also* ¥ Yours sinoersly, («gd.) W. W. NINO \\ Miss Hobley, A Ministry of Pood, \ ] \ Portaan Court, Porbaan Square, W.1 •SFAFT TSIjgRAM K^b 0 . 16909 /W Fxmi Jearetary of utata To t I^litioal .esddonfc in the Iwolan Golf. /^kiroeaQd to Bplltloal oaiderxt repeated to Gooernaeat of India. Your tele^rao Ho.T/^32 of rajptoaber. osadbique Sugar. As ultimate destination of this su^ir is Persia it should be subject of navioert applications at port of shipment shioh will in existing oirouLTStanoes be refussd. HJf.G. would aooordii^jly be grateful if you would instruct P.A* r^useit to discontinue issue of H6 Cbjecti m Oertifioatea so tliat Afrioan rfdppero will be forced to apply for navicerts,k.c- o.i6yioA4. **■ &gt; 18th Oatdbw, 1944* ap MathiAs, I write with reference to your letter IP3V%S of 16 th October on the subject of shipments of tea to j'usoat by -bow from Sast Africa. You refer to Cartwright's letter to you of 26th September and aleo to i\far laving No # 12 from Beira and you mate the total of tea approximately 521*000 lbs* Cartwright surely inoludod the shipments mentioned in Afar Savin ; To* 12 and 1 make the total of tea which has been shipped to Muscat since April roughly 150 tons* as :mentioned in Cartwright's letter. *» agree that in view of the existing shortage of tea* any tea whioh Muscat receives for her own oonsuaption from Africa should be set off against her allocation from India* but vm should like first of all to ascertain whether this tea is in fact oonsuned at Muscat. In a similar case of shipments of sugar from Mosaobique* the Political Resident in the oreian ,ulf informed us that the sugar was not oonsuned in Muscat but was on-shipped to ^rsia* and I think it is more than likely that the position is the same in regard to this tea. Ve should aooordin, ,ly like to ascertain the exact position before you instruct the Tea Controller at Calcutta to suspend shipments to uaoat. I enolose a cony of the draft telegram which we would propose to send to the Political Resident* and should be glad to know whether you have any oowoenta to mate on it. I am sending a oopy of this letter and of its enclosure to Cartwright. Yourn sincerely* W. J.M. Mathias Eeq.* Ministry of Food* portman Court* Portraan Square* V.l.mm mj&amp;R.'u o,i69ioA4# Front Jaorrtary of 3tat» Tot 1 olitioDl resident in the Persian Gulf, Addrssnsd to Poli -ioal ! resident repeated to Government of India, Ministry of R&gt;od have learned that about 150 tons of tea have boon shipped to Mi Mat ainoe April last fraa ^^osonbiqijo. in view of existing ton shortage Ministry feel bound to take suoh ahipaonta into consideration when allocating tea to i^ieoat from India, Current year's allocation is 59%WO lbs, and they suggest with- holding any further shipments for the pxesent. Is this tea oonsuaed locally or is ultimate destination ds in oaas of Sugar shipped from that souroe■■■ MINISTRy QP POOD, Port man Court, Port man Square, London, W. 1# 29th August, Dear Nind*^ For the last four or five months we have been receiving information that there lias been a steady flow of sugar from Portuguese, East Africa to India, Arabia (Kcweit and Muscat were specifically mentioned) and Persian Gulf territories# These shipments are made in dhows and cannot be controlled by Ministry of War Transport# Portuguese West Africa sugar is also being shipped round from Loanda and Lobito to Mozambique Beira and Lourenco Marques and then transhipped to these territories# The prices, paid for this sugar are considerably in excess of the prices we have paid for the whole exportable surplus of the Portuguese East African and for the S# African surplus. We are therefore alarmed that if this trade continues it will cause our supplies from these sources to leak away under the attraction of high prices# ♦ 0 9 » We have consulted M.E.W. who state that they can do nothing as exports to this area apart from Iraq and Persia do not need navicerts# I believe, however, that before any of these exports can arrive they have to be approved by the Political Resident in the case of the Arab Sheikdoms and the Political Agent in the case of Muscat. We should be grateful if you could /acquaint W.W. Nind, Esq., India Office, Matthew Parker Street, S.W. 1#mm V i\ acquaint these representatives of the position andrequest them to do all in their power to get these imports stopped* There Y^as also some mention of supplies going to India and I should be grateful, therefore, if the government of Indian attention is also drawn to the matter so that they can stop this traffic by refusing import licences* I am also copying this letter to Mr* Hankey (P.0.) and asking him to take the question up from the point of view of Saudi Arabia and also to Mr* Reid, Colonial Office, with a request to him that similar trade to Aden should be stopped* Yours sincerely, (SD.) F.E.HORLEI. tv t t I71 ® INWARD TELEGRAM E &amp; O. 16504 SECRET US1LJ A llotted to E &amp; QoDepartmgnt Qog&gt; es Circdlated « ^ CYPHER T EL EGR A M (O.T.P .) Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To Secretary of State for India, i Repeated to Government of India. Dated ' Shiraz, 16,'00 hours, 27th September, 1944. Received 22,00 hours, 27th September, 1944* Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Government of India, copy to Bahrain Rowelt and (? Muscat). Your telegram No.19676 September 6th* Mozambique sugar, , ^ ~ % 2« There are no importers in Bahrain and Koweit but in Muscat one firm has been importing sugar from Mozambique on no objection certificates issued by Political Agent, Muscat. 3, Sugar so imported is not repeat not consumed or sold in Arab Sheikhdoms but is re-exported to Persia . either direct or* via Koweit. In view of this external demand therefore discontinuance of issue of no objection certificates will only lead to a diversion of /trade</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000043_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/951</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000043</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/951</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 4741/44 'Shipment of supplies to Muscat: Mozambique sugar'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1944/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-20T22:11:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (17 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 19; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding imports of sugar, tea and other commodities from Mozambique to Muscat, and their onward export to Persia. The file covers considerations of increased restrictions on such imports and potential withholding of tea from India in order to uphold rationing. The primary correspondents are: Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Charles Geoffrey Prior, Political Resident, Persian Gulf; India Office; Ministry of Food.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Food</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Import control</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sugar</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tea</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000043#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>