<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:29.566Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">POLICY IN THE MIDDLE EAST. Si From Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Mark Sykes, Bart., M.P., to the I )irector of Military Operations. ^ sTo * S.S. KJiybe)-, Red Sea, '' 15th November 1915. I have the honour to forward to you (by favour of Mr. S. Waterfield, rolitical Agent, Tlaraoti and Tonk, Uajputana, who is proceeding to London l&gt;v i'us mail), under this cover a memorandum resuming the impressions I have received on various points as the result of my tour of the Lastern theatre. i haw dated it JMh October, as that is the last date on which I was in touch with the situation. I would therefore point out that my observations regarding the despatch of reinforcements to Mesopotamia are based on the loices actually in Mesopotamia at the end of October. I heard at Karachi that a division, less certain minor units, was under orders, but 1 have not presumed this in the memorandum, 1 have made no observations with regard to Persia or the Persian side ol the (ridf, as that region did not come within the scope of my instructions, and my previous experience gives me no assistance with regard to those parts. However, my personal opinion is that the occupation of Ahwaz is, and has heen, a source of great weakness to us, but I assume that the necessities of the Admiralty, and the maintenance of our prestige in Persia, make it retention essential. If it was merely a question of the interests of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, I should believe it would be best to abandon Ah waz and compensate the Company for any damage that might ensue. I do not believe that even if the Bakhtiaris turned against ns they could venture far afield, or co-operate with the Turks in Mesopotamia. I would also point out that my assumption of 30,00U Turks in Syria in my note on the general military situation is based on information of about 18th October. From rumours L have since heard I imagine it is possible that this number has greatly increased, from which I infer that the release of Constantinople troops began with the entrance of Bulgaria into the field. However, I still believe that the blocking of the Cilician Gates is important to us. and that we cannot afford to let the Turks assume a constant offensive against Egypt and Mesopotamia, and that we should take advantage of the snow barrier which cuts off Syria and Mesopotamia from Armenia and Anatolia to improve our position for the opening of the spring campaign. I think that the Mesopotamian operations demonstrate very clearly the superiority of our troops over the Turks in manoeuvre, and show that, where open fighting and flanking movement is possible, we can beat them on a proportion of 10 British led troops to 15 Turks. However, I must qualify this bv pointing out that, whatever the individual merit of the soldiers of the Mesopotamian force (a large proportion of which is Indian), they are led S. 2H9. A 172 by regular officers, and are perhaps more accustomed to maiiu'iu w i I mh i I m newly raised divisions of British and Colonial troops, which must be of better individual quality but perhaps collectively less mobile. I should also like to reinforce what I have said on the general political situation, with regard to the necessity of co-operation and co-ordination as regards our various theatres in the hast; and also ol urging the importance of a clear understanding among the Entente Powers, which would enable available troops to be used at available points. 11 my tour lias impressed me with one thing above another, it is the advantage which our enemy gains by using every available local asset as a part oi one harmonious scheme. 1 should also take this opportunity of saying that no matter how dark things may look, we must never forget that Turkey is undoubtedly getting exhausted in men, and that the poverty and distress in the provincial capitals of Syria and Mesopotamia is always an advantage to us, the advent of Entente troops meaning trade and paymeni in lieu of requisition and extortion. In conclusion I mention that I saw the Resident at Aden and Colonel Jacob. 1 believe that the commandant of the Turkish forces outside Aden might not be beyond the reach of financial influence ; he is isolated and cannot attack us, and doubtless dare not retire for fear of punishment; his Turkish soldiers are also deserting to us pretty freely, about '29 Anatolian Turks and 3 Syrians having come in in the last three weeks. Director of Military Operations, War Office, Whitehall, S.W. Major-General C. E. Callwell, C.B., &amp;c., &lt;^c.. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant. M. Svkes.Memorandum by Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Mark Sykes. SECTION' 1. -MILITARY SITU A TICK IX MESOPOTAMIA. \\ ith reganl to the situation in Mesopotamia there are two aspects the one political, the other military. ' ' () ' 11 ^ 11 ' 111 {11'aiy point of view I think the reinforcement of the Armv and the occupation ol Baghdad are the two most important considerations. As marfers now stand, our Army is weak in numbers and grows propor tionately weaker as the enemy gradually recuperates and reinforces at Baghdad, until he is strong enough to advance in force. It cannot be too strongly urged that a single defeat is sufficient to procure the destruction of our whole force. The population would undoubtedly rise en masse to plunder and harass our retirement if once they imagined we had turned our backs, and 1 personally doubt whether we should be able to withdraw to Basra under such circumstances. Whether we decide to occupy Baghdad or not, 1 am certain that the reinforcement of a full division is the least that the situation demands. If ue occupy Baghdad. 1 think that the military situation is much easier than before, and that, we should feel the strain less for the following reasons. Once Baghdad is ours the enemy's facilities for concentration previous to attack are reduced. Thus so long as he holds Baghdad he can dribble his reinforcements simultaneously into Baghdad by the Euphrates, Tigris, and by the Kifri road he can concentrate at Baghdad, and with the help of steamers and current advance with a fairly large force. I f we hold Baghdad the enemy must either disperse his forces or concentrate at a point on one of the three lines, and use that line only for supply, with the result that the concentration of a large force will be more difficult for him to accomplish, and his subsequent advance easier to check. If one makes a deduction of 2,000 men for the maintenance of order in Baghdad, the number of troops required to meet the enemy, if he is based North of Baghdad, would be less than if we and he maintain our present respective positions. 1 visited the dockyard at Abadan and saw the work in progress. One boat is ready, and five more are in course of construction, and should be able to take the water at intervals of live weeks from 1st November. There are many difficulties in the way of construction which appear irremediable; shortage of labour, difficulties of ground, and climate conspire to make the * work slow and difficult. From what I saw of the operations up stream 1 should imagine that the gunboats should be very valuable, but 1 think that they should have a larger ammunition supply, 200 rounds for the 4-inch being quite inadequate when it is remembered how many shots are inevitably wasted in a country when- targets are so doubtful and scattered as in Mesopotamia. The low trajectory of the 4-inch gun presents certain grave disadvantages when the gunboat has to be used in narrow waters and between high banks against enemies at medium ranges. I suggest that the Inventions Department might consider the problem of devising a suitable weapon, or mounting for an existing weapon, which could enable a shell to be landed accurately on a given point on a plain about 1,500 yards from a gun fired from the deck of a vessel at a point in a river 30 yards from a bank, 15 feet in height above the water line.4 POLITICAL SITUATION IN MESOPOTAMIA. The political situation in Mesopotamia is influenced to our detriment by the element of doubt which subsists in the minds of the people as to our actual intentions. Xotahles. —I have interviewed several notables ol Hasra, namely, the brother of the Nakib, several senior members of the Bashayan lamily, the Shaykh of Zabevr, and the notable Shaykh Abu Talib. One and all obviouslv desire certainty, and particularly that we should occupy Baghdad. The fear in their minds is that we should retire or let the Turks in again. People.—The people, whether nomads, cultivators, or semi-nomads, Sunnis or Shias, are ready to accept our rule, but equally ready to turn against us in event of any mishap. In many villages between Amara and Kurna demonstrations of sympathy are made by the Arab women \\li('n barge loads of Turkish prisoners pass by, villages it ma\ be said whose inhabitants did not hesitate to plunder the Turks in their retreat. This should be a sufficient indication of what We ourselves might expect under similar circumstances. The Shia shrines require especial consideration and treatment, but it is not necessary to make a great parade of the matter. Again, with the people as with the notables, it is desirable that there should be some certainty as to their future. Future Policy.—There is one point which I feel requires careful con sideration, and that is the connection between India and Mesopotamia. Indian and Arab civilisation and mentality are poles asunder, and I am of opinion that the introduction of Indian methods and Indian personnel should be merely temporary, and should form no part of our future scheme. Indian administration has grown up in the course of years and is based on traditions and social customs which have no counterpart in Irak. The introduction of Anglo-Indian and native Indian officials directed from India, will mean inevitably that Irak will develop on Indian lines. There can be no doubt that the native social standards of Egypt and Syria are far higher than those of India, and owing to language and racial affinity it is from those regions that the civilisation of Irak would naturally be drawn. I feel it is my duty to say therefore that in my opinion it would be a i ;?eat mishap it at the outset any action of ours should do anything to impose artilicially an alien and lower grade of civilisation upon a people who have a natural tendency to a higher and more progressive social state. The Indian currency, Indian officials in the police, the posts, telegraphs, and clerical bureaus, and the introduction of Indian law, Indian money lenders and merchants, will influence the whole country and set a permanent barrier of alien administration between ourselves and the people. Doubtless we shall sooner or later begin to employ natives of the country ; but as the tirst traditions will be moulded on Indian lines, with the result that we shall not be able at a later date to develop the spiritual and national mental resources of the urban and rural population to such advantage as we otln nvise might. Colonisation. —In saying this, I am raising no objection to hond fide colonisation by Indians, provided that the administrative personnel is purely British and Arab. There can be no objection to the allotment of lands to Indian cultivators in districts (where local inhabitants are insufficient, and where there is no prospect of nomads being induced to settle) to develop the country, provided that lhe colonists will not have the pull of the administra tion. ' They will, under such circumstances, either remain in separate communities or mingle with the people, and so become a part of Irak. If, however, the Indian peoples permeate the administrative personnel and the mercantile and financial classes, the colonists will only be another element in the Indianisation of the country. The ludianisation of Irak is not only to be avoided for the above reasons, but also because, as time goes on and intercommunication grows easy between Irak and Syria, we shall be confronted with the tendency of the Arab to reassert himself once more, and in that tendency we shall find the seeds of much political difficulty.Hiere iy also one other point which should not be lost sight of. At piesent, no matter what I he feelings of Indian Moslems may be, nor what tho exiont ol the ramifications of Indian seditionism, such influences find no equivalent among the Arabs of Irak, cither urban nor rural, and since the hcsl elements look to ns for good and firm government, it would be a mistake to put them Irom the very outset within the scope of action of subtle ami powerlul forces which will begin spreading unrest and disaffection at the first available opportunity. •With regard to the attitude of Indian Moslems in the present war, it is very difficult to generalise owing to the diversities (^f sect, race, and avocation among Indian Mohammedans, however, it is impossible to talk to Indian Moha mmedans and British civil and military officers in the Indian service about Islam in India without getting certain impressions. In the first place, basing one's acquaintance with Islam on experience in Turkey, Arabia, the Caucasus, Egypt, Tunis, and Algeria, there is one factor in the situation with which one cannot fail to- be impressed, and that is the extreme ignorance of Indian Mohammedans as a whole, of Islamic theological doctrine as taught in the schools and universities or the A1 Azhar, Damascus, &lt; 'onstantinople, and Kairawan. Indian Mohammedanism, as far as theo logical learning is concerned, appears to be at a low ebb. At first this would seem to be a matter of slight importance, but on examination irt will be found to be a considerable disadvantage to us as rulers, and to open an avenue for our enemies. In the first place it makes it easy for any charlatan to impose on Indian Moslems the most absurd ideas as for instance, that the city of Baghdad is a holy city, that Adrianople is the site of' holy shrines, that Constantinople is the ancient capital of Islam, ideas which not the rudest Anatolian would entertain. Further, it makes it very difficult to impress on Indian Moslems the absolutely hypocritical attitude of the Committee of Union and Progress, the enmity of the Turkish clerical party for the ( ommittee, and the sordid motives which impelled the Turks to war. From all I heard it was impossible not to feel that the bulk of Indian Moslems sympathised with the Turks more or less the educated because they have been affected by young Turkish propaganda, the uneducated because they have no learned theological body to keep them straight. For this state of affairs (although it is presumptuous for me to say so) I think want of touch between the Indian Government and the real tendency of development in the Near East is partly responsible. Thus the Red Crescent Society, which is neither more nor less than a revolutionary anti-theological pan -Islamic machine, was suffered to work on the fertile soil of Indian educated Mohammedan Seditionism and Indian uneducated Mohammedan ignorance for some time before the war. On the score of avoiding wounding religious susceptibilities we have never taken the field in the British Indian press against the Committee of Union and Progress, and a certain remote ness from the scene has produced an atmosphere of acquiescence and tolerance for things dangerous to our peace. As examples 1 enclose a small pamphlet 0 I bought on a bookstall, and a cutting from a British Indian newspaper, 0 each containing the seeds of immense mischief; while it may be incidentally mentioned that one may meet at Simla or Delhi young students wearing a crescent and star badge on a Turkish military cap, in itself a deliberate challenge to our authority. Our attitude is one of apology, of fear, of nervous consideration, while our enemies are working against us with weapons which, if the truth were * Xot reproduced. li s. 28&lt;».6 t i' i i r 11 -f «■&gt;» flioii* rrr'WT) \ VCTV stl'OHS lilCtOl tQlllX llllD'i, known in India, ^o.dd all f on . tin' fact that British Indian officials. m the maintenance ol tins sitUcUioii, ■ , - r 0fl i t u n i. nnu n f thp mrtif -ularlv militarv officers have not at their disposal the knouli U&lt; &lt; 1 I ffih Hitics and tlie real actions and composition ol the Coininittee to enable them to act with confidence and to speak with cenamty in conye^^ tion. I have met several young officers who were devoted to ami iii U iok . in their men, and who with true Knghsh g (wd nature sanl that it was onlj may say in the course of conversation to —, - Indians will not believe them, personally 1 agree that this will he so at lirst, but as the truth is on our side sooner or later we shall pioduee a hettei atmosphere, and at least put hostile influences on the e. British civil and mditary officials are trained in India to have a g'leat regard for religious susceptibilities ol natives, they roughly conceive luat the young Turks are the leaders ol a united people, and that lurkey is a N real Islamic power as it was in the days of Abdul llamid, consequently they are handicapped by the sense that in Indian Moslem ieeling, we are confronting a popular feeling based on a logical foundation, did they realise that they are merely facing the unwitting dupes of cosmopolitan knaves of the Committee of Union and Progress, who believe neither in Allah or the Koran, they would be heartened and stifFoned by a sense of right which is at present lacking. British, especially Englishmen, are notoriously bad actors, and nothing puts an Englishman in a worse position than the feeling that there is something to be said for the other side. I feel that it is very important that steps should be taken to make it quite clear to British military and civil' officials that from the Mohammedan point of view there is nothing to be said for the young Turks. A brief history ol' the young Turkish movement circulated as a confidential paper to all British officers either civil or military in contact with Moslems would, at least, rectify this deleterious influence. The above was written before I had an opportunity of reading the memorandum 0 prepared by the Political and Foreign Department, Simla, for my information—its date is 28th October. However, T do not feel that it contains an\ information contrary to the opinion 1 have expressed. Section I\. is to my mind exceedingly interesting and indicates a new danger. 1 he attitude ol the ' intellectuals ' towards education, and the so- called revolt against 'old-school' teaching, is identical with the attitude of the young Turks towards the Ulema, save with this difference, that the iurkish Ulema are a learned and cultivated body of well-trained clergy with considerable prestige, whereas the Indian old-school Moslems are disorganised, atrophied, and feeble, so far as learning is concerned. of India are evidently trying the same game as the theTlf f mou and I rogress—that is, to engross all political power in the hands of a clique ol journalists, pleaders, and functionaries, to oust the clerical element but to retain its power to excite an ignorant mob to resnonsible f a- ; vhe ' '^sary. 1 feel that this is a time when those sponsible foi our policy should face facts, and not allow themselves to be A ' 1 0U1 - Sch001 , lr0slei ' fanatical, bnt his reasoned wit^ tlwpt T' , may , be tem P' ed or assuaged, or even be appealeil to' and an I 1 ' s ''''f 1 of righteousness which can rti, envy , hc !!,,„„ «,£, i «L-*- has no belief whatever in rrliZn I nt sees , T agnostic and Zztgsr —-™• '•&gt;'«.'( sSs&amp;ps is insincere and move'l 5 by' i' ioi 'i!'^ '' rl' ' a ''i'''','' ''Pidse, the inlellectnal brutality fron. a KmmX ,S 1^ 0,ute ^ . vain to ^P ect ^ Ghazi . The latest ArmeTikn ' ' rev ohitionary than from a the Committee of Union ami ' ia&gt;sucl ' t ' s P'^ve this, as every action of and 1 'ogress proves this. F urthermore | wo,,!,! • Memorandum on Indian Moslems-not reprinted.submit that our greatest danger lies in British statesmen and otficials con In sing the ideals of ' intellectuals ' with those of European revolutionanVs and liberals, and therefore according them a certain respect. The Moslem ' intellectual nses the clothes of Europe, and he has lost belief in his creed, but the hatred ol Christendom and lust lor the dominion of Islam as a supreme political power remains, and he knows how to use the weapon of lanaticism among a population whose percentage of literates is as low as it is among the Indian Moslems. If one may suggest a policy in words, I feel that our educational policy in regard to Islam should be, among the upper class, to foster the study of the Moslem classic authors, historians, logicians, and theologians, and to combine with modern education the study of the history of the greater Moslem dynasties, and the development of Mohammedan Sheri law ; while among the poorer, to endeavour to impart with elementary education a real •understanding of the outlines ol' Islamic history. This policy would do much to introduce a real patriotic religious feeling among the poor, and do something to infuse the upper classes with a com prehension of the true greatness of their forefathers. By such a policy we should be at the root of the difficulty, by disentangling the confusion, of thought at present arising in the minds of the upper classes through the collision of the mass of ill-assimilated European education on the mass of Asiatic tendency, tradition, and prejudice. Similarly among the masses we should be preparing the way for the raising of a reasonable Moslem people from the ignorance and confused superstition of to-day. It might even be hoped that between the two would be produced a frugal and learned clergy capable of giving the people such good as the Mohammedan religion can offer. SECT!OX 111. GENERAL SITUATION. Fohtical. — The general political situation arising out of the war between the entente powers and the Ottoman Empire is really evolved out of the efforts of Germany and Turkey to mobilise Islam against Great Britain and Russia. It is necessary briefly to recapitulate the methods our enemies pursue. (1.) Fomentation of Indian Moslem discontent and fanaticism. (2.) In Persia the working up of tribesmen and nationalists to rebellion along the coast, private murder in the provincial capitals, pressure on the government at the capital. (3.) In Egypt the working of sympathy with the ex-Khedive and nationalist revolutionarism. (4.) In Arabia: a. Yemen, alliance with the Imam of Sana. h. Xejd, subventioning of Ibn Reshid. c. In the Kerbella area, playing on Shia fanaticism. d. In Muscat, the fomentation of the rebellion against the Sultan by means of native agents from East Africa. This policy is worked by highly efficient agents on a well co-ordinated plan, as may be judged from results. . As against this, we have certain strong positive factors and inllueiice^ in our favour, which may be enumerated as follows : (1 ) Discontent with Committee rule in Turkey itself. (9^ The dislike of the clergy for the young Turks. (3.) Arab dislike of Turks. ('4.) Disunion between Sunnis and Shias.To take full advantage of these influences it is necessary that we should adopt a definite policy and pursue it with a co-ordinated plan as do our enemies. Our task is the more difficult, inasmuch as our successes m the field are negative and defensive, and our polic}- must l»e constructn e lathei than destructive as is our enemies, however, there is notliin.u to prevent us us taking advantage of our available assets. To achieve our purpose it is iirst necessary to have a cleai uiK lei standing with our allies, particularly France and Russia, and to olttain theii a( qui escence in our policy, and, when possible, their co-opeiation. I he main point at present is to defeat the enemy and to reduce his power so that his voice, at least, will not be heard in the settling ol war and middle Eastein problems after the war is over. To defeat the enemy the destruction of the Ottoman Empire would be a decisive step ; it would paralyse once and tor all the enenn s activities m Persia, Afghanistan, and India, and thus deprive him 01 a souice of diversions and menaces with which he amuses and distracts not unl\ ns hut Russia. Further, the Ottoman Empire m Asia still remains the enem\ s most vulnerable position. From a political point of view our policy might well run on the following lines :— Line 1.- To back the Arabic-speaking peoples against the Turkish (jiovernment on one consistent and logical plan. Line 2.— (a) To support the anti-committee r l urkish paities; and (6) the influence of the Sunni Mohammedan clergy, wherever it is antagonistic to the Committee. Line 3.—To propagandise Islam in a definite and offensive manner, not making apology for our acts, but attacking the enemy on the score of injustice, crime, unorthodoxy, and hypocrisy, in our own press, in the native press, and by means of leallets. Line 1. To achieve the first of these objects it is necessary to obtain the sanction of France and Italy to an agreement as to the future treatment of the Arab peoples in the present Ottoman Empire, and to obtain from I'ranee guarantees compatible with Arab national aspnations, and to settle with France, Italy, and Russia the status of Jerusalem. Once this is done we can, the moment we take action, make proclamation of our intentions, and solidify the Arabs of Irak, Palestine, Syria, and Northern Mesopotamia against the Turks. At present the Arabs are paralysed by the fear that the Turks will return in any event owing to dissensions among the Entente Powers. If we can make so clear a statement that, dependent on our success, the Arabic-speaking people will be under French protection in one area, and English protection in another, with the recognition of Arab nationality and of Arab participation in the official administration in both areas, we shall have a clear situation and a definite backing to our success ; our primal success must, however, be derived from military action, which 1 deal with under the military situation. I suggest that our ultimate goal should be: In Arabia (1) Recognition of the independence of llejaz under the Sherif. (2) The conclusion of peace between Idris and Imam Vahyah, and the fixing of their territories, compensating Vahyah in the Aden Hinterland and Hadhramaut, if necessary, in return for the expulsion of the Turks from Yemen. (3) Declaration of an external protectorate over the Arabian littoral from Koweyt to Hodeidah. (4) Declaration of a British internal and external protectorate over an area in Southern Syria and Mesopotamia to be agreed upon with France and Russia. Declaration of a French internal and external protectorate in an area north of the British area. (5) An agreement between the Entente Powers which would ensure political and military co-operation without prejudice to the futureFn'i' 1 rh ,, I t al1an 1 or\T rit0neS ' th ' 8 - f ,eri ' itti,, « the use of British fp\ ir : an ' 01 Russian troops m any area sS t0 8t,mulate a ' Arab dema ' ;i for 'he Caliphate of the Line 2. as we are here makinjftse 'oT Tin{, l a''!iiM,ril ,,l -| t '- 8 .''■ a, j ef ' 1 nianil S em ent, the risk of compromising our Aral.ian iiationahst l \^sl| i '''inI'''i''' r ' n i^ liberals (ij the hope of revenge, and (ii; hy ^'rk^S^ of tliH Conmirttee holds office we will give no peace or m irK i t'' aS Kinpirr Imi that if they work a successful revolution we shall be prepared wU're^Ott W 't l' 6 '' at 0DC | ilS r, ' gards the independence of regions e ttonian I urks are in the majority. It is also possible thonch 1 In ^ii it(! to suggest it, that the Russian Government ini&lt;'ht be Drenared i. sHntinoMrThi ''l T ' IKisl1 , l ; i 'r al8 With regarfl 10 ,lle -lus'of (W K qh^ Mid the y berafe aloneT 3 ^ ,fe H. As regards the second portion of this line, it consists in beine prepared with a policy whereby the Ottoman Ulema shall continue to eniof then present properties and privileges in all the ancient provinces of tho oman Empire, no matter under whose jurisdiction or protection it may la I; and guarai,teeing all shrines and wakfs in Constantinople and the r'i\ iik wnh the exception of Santa Sofia, for which compensation shall be allowed. his in itself is a great asset against the Committee, as the lerna know lull well that their revenues will be lost if the Committee prosecnlp the war to a successful issue. To encourage Aran l lema to get Turkish Ulema to fall in with the idea o.l a Nienlmn ( aliphate would be profitable if carefully handled. Line 3. niis is merely a matter of co-ordination and organisation. It requires an expert political and literary staff in touch with all quarters of the Islamic areas, and with local agencies at various centres. The system should be for the central staff to give the general line to the lo* ill iiiM ih k s, and foi the ifical agencies to pursue that line m the manner most suitable. I lie general purpose is to produce an atmosphere favourable to us among Moslems generally, and to combat the propaganda direct and indirect of our enemies. As a general rule it will be found that educated conservatism and orthodoxy are on our side and modernism and ignorant fanatioism are against us, for reasons explained in my Despatch No. 17, and already dealt with under Section 11. of this memorandum. A. To mobilise our full force, we must make the situation clear to all British officers engaged in the Islamic area ; and we must as far as possible work our own press, both at home and in India and Kgvpt, by supplying' paragraphs, articles, and private memoranda, and by cheeking the publica tion of unsatisfactory or dangerous matter, ft may be mentioned here that the attuning and education of our own people is qu te as important as the influencing of our Mohammedan subjects. R We should be ready to squash without hesitation any article, paragraph, or observation in any native newspaper which was of a philo- Committee nature, particularly the kind of contribution which is subtle and indirect, as in the enclosed article in the Hindustan Review. (!. We should promote the spread of rumours, prophecies, saws, rhymes, crvptograms, and anagrams favourable to our side, by means of native * Not reproduced. s. atw. 010 agents, and especially by letting them drop on sincere ground to run their own course. I). We should co-ordinate most carefully our own issue of pamphlets and in them always be aggressive, demonstrative, and unapologetic; all our apologies and explanations should be by inference rather than direct, hor this work we require an erudite Moslem staff as well as an Knglish observation and control. MILITARY SITUATION. (1) The whole military situation has been dominated by the Dardanelles operations. Should these operations be regarded as having been unfruitful hitherto, the following considerations should be remembered. Since March about 5()O,0() 0 Turkish troops and necessary reinforcements have been immobilished and subject to heavy loss. Had the l)ardanelles operations not been in progress, it may be assumed that the I urks would have had approximately 130,0(H) men in Syria, 80,000 at Haghdad, and 100,000 additional troops in the Caucasus. Such dispositions would have immobilised a larger garrison in h.gypt, have forbidden any advance in Mesopotamia, and menaced the Caucasus and the Russian sphere in Persia. The influence on the Moslem world of a constant Ottoman offensive would have given the German and Committee of I nion and Progress agents a lar wider scope in the Caucasus, Persia, the Persian Gulf, Kgypt. India, and Arabia. As it is, these gentry have had some success, but they have been heavily handicapped by lack of moral support; the minor successes they have obtained are indications of what their power would have been had the Ottoman forces not been concentrated around the Marmora. (2) The entrance of Bulgaria into the field indicates the possible release of Ottoman forces from the Constantinople area and their despatch else where. This consideration suggests that it would be profitable to consider certain geographical and climatic factors affecting the movement of large bodies of troops in the Ottoman Kmpire in Asia. The appended map shows by a hatched line the limit of permanent winter snow enduring from about the 10th November to the 15th March, which makes mobile operations practically impossible in Armenia and Anatolia during that period. From the same map it will also be seen that there are practically only three lines along which an army can advance from Anatolia or Armenia into Syria, Mesopotamia, or Southern Kurdistan—to wit, via the Cilician Gates, via the Sivas-Kharput Road, or via Erzerum and Pitlis. The advance of an army with a fighting head of two divisions along the latter two may be ruled out until the middle of March. Thus while it is conceivable that an existing army of 50,000 men in North Mesopotamia could be reinforced along these roads during the winter, yet it would be impossible for an army to come down them as an independent fighting force. As regards the Cilician Gates road, if the southern end be blocked at the opening of the defiles during the winter, a force of 40,000 men could deny the enemy access to Syria or Mesopotamia along this road for the duration of the war, provided that the enemy was prevented from raising an army in Syria. ff the enemy dispositions are as follows :— 30,000 men in Syria ; 20,000 men at Baghdad ; 10,000 men in North Mesopotamia ; 100,000 men on the Russian frontier; 500,000 men at Constantinople ; and presuming that the participation of Bulgaria eventually releases 400,000 men from Constantinople, the enemy will have certain courses open to him. He has three fronts to consider —he may therefore decide either to (1) Concentrate during the winter at Erzerum for a late spring or early summer effort of a decisive nature against the Caucasus, and let matters rest in Syria and Mesopotamia.11 (2) Remain ou the defensive in Armenia, and devote his attention to winning back Mesopotamia and to attacking Kgypt from Syria. (.■)) Assume the offensive in all three regions. Whichever of these courses the enemy adopts, he has certain factors which militate in his disfavour. (1) The difficulty of approaching Egypt after he has passed rail head. (2) The length of communication between Baghdad and Ras-ul-Ain where his rail way ...ceases to be of real use to him. (3) The separation of his forces in Armenia from those in Syria and Mesopotamia. (4) The badness ot the eastward roads from the Angora rail head to the Caucasus. I think it is probable that (1) if he adopts course 1 he will send /)00,000 men to Armenia, 50.000 to Syria, and 50,000 to Mesopotamia. (2) If he adopts course 2 he will send 100,000 men to Armenia, 200,000 to Syria, and 100,000 to Mesopotamia. (3) If he adopts course 3 he will send 150,000 men to Armenia, 150,000 to Syria, and 100,000 to Mesopotamia. The movement and supply of such large forces will naturally be slow, and 10 per cent, losses from desertion and sickness per quarter may be anticipated. In any event, it would appear advisable, il i&gt; be possible, for 'the Allies to spare the men, to block the exit from the Sicilian Gates. If this be accomplished before the enemy's troops are released he will lia\e relatively small forces at his disposal in Syria and Mesopotamia, and no means of greatly increasing their numbers before the month ol April. As the Syrian and Mesopotamian winter is comparativelv mild this should give the Allies an opportunity of occupying practically the whole of the Arab speaking provinces of the Ottoman Lmpire, and of cutting (&gt;11 t ie enemv from his indirect activities in Persia, Afghanistan, and Arabia. if by the 10th of March the Allies could dispose of their forces as shown on Map 2 in the following strengths, with lines of communication a^. marked :— Adana - - - 50,000 Aintab - 20,000 Diarbekir - - 50,000 Aleppo - - ' 10,000 Acre-Jerusalem - - 11,000 Baghdad - 20,000 164,000 Line of communications - 30,000 194,000 the Turkish forces would be unable to reconquer their Arabian Empire owing tftL- difficulty of concentrating and deploying at the decisive ' ,1 Communication with the Russian army could be established through ' (2) TheTtwo'sinall Turkish armies, presumably at Damascus and Mosul, rnnld be dealt with at leisure. . , , . n • i (3. A provisional native government could be established m Syria and trade reopened with the whole of the Syrian poits. (4) Enemy activities in Persia, Afghanistan, and Arabia would naturally - Tl'''v'lrmioDc'ir Zor -Bagbdad trade route could be re-opened. | ^S&amp;£tor the recognition of the independence of the - n. She . r j. fC0Ul&lt; !., l ld 'Tif the event of the European situation proving (7 ) Th f e K,I lnvisaee a peace conference with the certainty that ttr^toman '•■.n.pire would be reduced to Anatolia, although Constantinople might still remain in Ottoman hands. j.p .• r fl&gt;A above scheme would consist in eliminating ■'dJSSST hSlbf .1.0 l.~ Murssh-Birejik- N.B.- the force I) • S. 289.n l irc/p Turkish army might be built W '' U1 ' ,e m ^ h impe,l0d a ' d 118 amllU,mti0n S,,I ^Sobiection -dd Kir^e^EvTwSks secure wo.a.1 Ije a ooM.v undertaking. The Initial steps in either case would possibly be as follo« s - Isi Step. Land Forces A., B., C., D.. m tj.e Gulf of Alexandretta. '^nd Step. Secure the exit of the ('ilician Gates. , Srd Stop. Land at Haifa Force E. and begin operations in .North Syria. K otes on above. (1) rhe population south of Amtal) ma\ l)e iegaid(Ml &lt;is ci no^ligeal)!' quantity. n i i • • i i t ^ i (2) In North Mesopotamia the nomads and chieftains, ootli Ivurci and Arab, may be dealt with and subventioned ; the promise to them of the plunder of Diarbekir, in retaliation for the Armenian massacres, would probably bring them in on our side, provided we are successful. (3) Hynothetically the foeces for such an expedition should be provided with ample horse transport, though the railways could be oot into working order within three momhs, with the exception of the Euphrates bridge at Jerablus, which must be assumed to be destroyed. (4) A strong proportion of cavalry is required with Forces 'D,' ' E, 1 ' and 'F.' FINAL OBSERVATION. Jn conclusion it is perhas worth considering a certain psychological idiosyncracies of Ottoman armies, which both present and past operations appear to demonstrate as a permanent factor in warfare in which they are engaged. For some reason Ottoman armies appear to be formidable in a direct offensive or in a direct defensive, but on the other hand seem to be feeble in manoeuvre, or in the face of mobile troops. Thus Ottoman troops— (1) Will hold an entrenched position the Hanks of which are secure, in face of heavy losses. (2) Will resist when surrounded beyond expectation. (3) Will deliver unexpectedly strong attacks over open country on a known objective il the enemy assumes a passive defensive. (4) Aie quickly disorganised by an unexpected development in the open, ^ and to fail accommodate themselves to a new situation. (5) riequently fail in operations necessitating combined manoeuvres. (6) Are bad at partizan or mountain warfare. As examples of the first may be cited— Omar Pasha's operations on the Danube, 185*?. I he battle of the Shipka pass, 1877, The holding of the Chatalja lines, 1912. I he Dardanelles operations, 1915. As examples of the second— Kars, 1852-53. Kars—Erzerum- Plevna, 1877-78. Adrianople, 1912. ' As examples of the third— The campaign in Thessalay, 1897. Hie Italian campaign in Tripoli, 1911 I he battle of Shaiba, 1915. 1 he attack on the Suez Canal, 1914. As examples of the fourth— The battle of Nezib, 1840 (?). I he battle of Kirk Kilisse, 1912. ])attles of Nasirie, Aniara, and Xut, 1915.rht be built immimition re a better rkish army rtaking. idretta. s in Xorth neglige able Kurd and bern of the :res, would e provided to working s bridge at ' D,' ' E,' n 13 As examples of the fifth— Mukhtar's campaign in the Caucasus, 1877. Fhe Macedonian campaign against the Greeks and Serbs, 1912. Enver's campaign in the Caucasus, 1914. As examples of the sixth— ! Me \ arious operations of the lurks in the areas, Macedonia, Zeitun, Dersim, llauran, and Yemen at various dates since 1894. ! liese (i) ii ai teristics winch, as wdl be seen, appear to survive German training, would suggest that we should (a) endeavour to fight the Turks in the opfMi on the otlensive by mobile manoeuvre | ih) where we assume a pure defensive, endeavour to confine them to broken or mountainous country; and (c) avoid attacking them in secure positions. I he key to these characteristics lies probably in the following. Turkish commanders have, owing to tradition and jealousy, little confidence in one another or their subordinates, consequently they hesitate to entrust anyone with an independent action, such as an outflanking march combined with a holding atiack. The backbone of the Turkish army is composed of Anatolians, who are extremely brave but very slow thinkers and movers; a preconceived notion of the enemy's position gets in their heads, and an unexpected development puts them in a panic. I urkish armies once away from railhead are weak in transport organisation, and supplies are liable to be lost and plundered. These factors are beyond the control of German organisation. ychological operations ph they are idable in a seem to be } secure, in intry on a e. i the open, ^uvres. I oo</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B217</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B217</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Policy in the Middle East. I. Memorandum by Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Mark Sykes.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-20T00:18:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 100, and terminates at f 106, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 100-106; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and won't be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Secret memorandum, prepared by Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Mark Sykes. The report is preceded by a letter from Sykes to Major-General Charles Edward Callwell, Director of Military Operations, War Office, London, dated 15 November 1915, which includes Sykes’s opinion on the occupation of Ahwaz, and an assessment of the Turkish forces outside Aden.The memorandum, dated 28 October 1915, is divided into the following sections:(i) military situation in Mesopotamia: the relative weakness of troop numbers in Mesopotamia; implications of taking and holding Baghdad; supply of gunboats and ammunition. The political situation in Mesopotamia: the opinions of the notables of Basra, and of the general population; future policy, particularly in relation to the connection between India and Mesopotamia; colonisation by Indians, and the risks associated with the ‘Indianisation’ of Mesopotamia;(ii) Indian Moslems [Muslims] and the War, including: Sykes’s assessment of the ‘extreme ignorance’ of Indian Muslims of Islamic theological doctrine; sympathy of Indian Muslims with the Turks and the Committee of Union and Progress; British educational policy towards Islam in India;(iii) General situation: the political situation in India, Persia, Egypt and Arabia, and three proposed lines of action in order to defeat the Ottoman Empire. Military situation, identifying the regions and fronts critical to the region. Final observation on ‘certain psychological idiosyncrasies’ of the Ottoman armies.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir 6th Baronet Mark Sykes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign policy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>