<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000281_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:44:11.882Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">The case reported was found wandering about the bazaars at Muharraq. He states the following - Name: Abdullah bin Ahmed Mohinidi. He left Qatr three months ago and landed at Hfeuta. He stayed with Esau A1 Hamr and Ali bin Esau at Hifaa. % e saw the Sheikh and was given Fs8/~. A relative of his states he came to Bahrain from Oatr only a month ago, then went to Saudi Arabia Hiadh - and returned only ten days ago - where he appears to have contracted the disease# if ,9o ^ tt ~i t0 Telegram/G.T. cO Britsgent Sherj e h. For Medics I Off icer 5 /tsdsn infected srosll pox. fll arrivals from /badrn should be vaccinated if not in possession of vaccination certificates of recent date. PoliticalINLAND: Ini mediate Class for telegrams impori-ant Express DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. Letter Ordinary To be issued on 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder Draft: FOREIGN: Immediate Important Ordinary Without priority Issued on Me morand um Telegra m No. To . Dated 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch, of above List of enclosures File No. Serial No. 19 * (Code word for telegrams.)maam 3 © TGlegrtm GTC* Pfom Briteorssul, Bushir# Pol t'ieal, Bahrain* To No. A/16 Bated 5th received 6th January 1943. Abadan infected smallpox. All arrivals from Abadan should b® vaccina.ted if not in possession of vaccination certificates of recent date. Please inform &gt;&gt; edical Officer act « Trueial Coast, Air Liaison Cffieer and Naval Oif leer-in-Charge• Copy forwarded to !• The Air Liaison Officer,Bahrain. 2. The Naval Of ficer-in-Oharge,Bahrain. No. 33 Political Agency,Bahrain 6 th January 1942. for information for Political Agent,BahrpTolegram Prora To No. Dated Received G.T.C• BritcQnsul, Bushire. Po li ti ca 1. Ba hra in A/67 19.1.43 20.1.43 a- Political Agents at Muscat ,1abrain and Kuvait circular. Moliainnerah Bushire Dashti and Kangan infected with smallpox impose quarantine restrictions. All arrivals from these places should be vaccinated if not in possession of vaccination certificates recent date. 2. To Bahrain only. Please inform A.L.O. and Naval Officer-in-Charge and T'edical Officer Trucial Coast. BritconsulPrinted in England. Aug. 1941. (9,000 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) 5/-168 25 '5 II Clerk’s Oircuit. Name. Received. CM f 1550 . RV30/R SCDE BUSHIRE 28 U 1530 BG - POLtTICAL BAHRAIN - CIRCULAR SMALLPOX PREVAILS AT BAIKHA KHOSAB BAY STOP IMPOSE RESTRICTIONS - BRITCONSUL A/443 \ V MARK YOUR REPLY Jm/i&amp;iuzC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY./ Tel From To ITo. Dated Heed. Addressed to British Consul General Bushire repeated to Political Agent, Bahrain, * Political Agent Muscat begins boom 604 Nakoda Gharaiyin bin Shai bound for (mut) India mth dates from Shatt al Arab transhipped one of the crew suffering from Typhus to a Be Hum at Pao on May 6 th. Sick man has been Quarantined here ends. $ . 9 • ^ ^3 G.T.C. Political, Kuwait Political, Bahrain 497 8.6.43 9.5.43 fv POLITICAL ^ cr'' ' 7 ^ ' ^ -a/ 71 ,/ $ rvi}i No.591-4/150. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 20th April 1943. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM 200 * ampules of small-pox vaccine are being forwarded separately for use in your area. Please acknowledge receipt. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. *(150 for Bahrain and 50 for Dubai)department/oeetce. . ■ ‘ File No, _ Serial No, totter Draft Memorandum! V-l Bahrain, November 2. 1943 2 ) e ^ Regarding your enquiry anout anti-typhus measures. This matter has been under discussion since last spring, Wakefield took some part in it. Dr. Steele and Major Holmes both wrote reports suggesting various steps that should be taken and the Bahrain Government is making enquiries about fumigators recommended by Holmes. I was not here when O’Neill last visited Bahrain and I do not know whether he discussed the subject but I know the R.A.P. are interested in any measures taken locally. The camp in question, 'which we built, has been handed back to the Bahrain Government and we are now in charge of it; it consists of about half a dozen- long barastis near Galali. O’Neill is going to the hospital tomorrow for a discussion with the R.A.P. doctor and our medical people and I have said that I would like to be present too. I enclose Holmes’ report, would you please return it. Major T. Hickinbotham, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.3 Copy of letter dated 14th September 1943 from Major R, Holmes 1^0 Residency Surgeon &amp; Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Arab Coast, Bushire, to the financial Mviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. As epidemic typhus ravaged the Persian Coast last spring there is every probability that it will recur this winter, and the Government of Bahrain should take steps to prevent its introduction into the Bahrain Islands. Strict quarantine against the whole Persian Coast should be enforced as soon as the first case is reported, special attention being given to native craft arriving from Persia,* The compaign against lice is the best means of prophylaxis and must be urgently insisted upon. Should the disease manifest itseld early notification of all cases must be given the autho rities. All cases of typhus should be strictly isolated. On admittance the head and body should be shaved and the hair burned, the patient placed in a bath of corrosive sublimate, washed, soaped and his parasites destroyed. His clothing should be burned or sent to the disenfector to be sterlised. persons in contact with cases must be palced under medical surveillance for fifteen days. These precaustions apply to ships crews, passengers, their families, crews of launches bringing passengers ashore and medical attendants. Quarters inhabited by patients, their linen, bedding etc., should be disenfected, Infected premises should be treated with sulphur gas. Articles of no value, rubbish, mats and very old clothes should be burnt. Floors should be washed with boiling solution of soda Vfo, Those engaged in the work of disenfection must wear special clothing, the most suitable wear being a one piece garment or combination, closed at the neck with endd of trousers shaped to enclose the feet. Rubber gloves should be worn. The best means of destroying the parasites infesting indi viduals is swabbing the body with Xylol, a mixture of oil and petrol, Naphthol - Benzol - NH Benzine - equal parts. pulverised on the skin effectively destroys lice. N.C.l.t - 2 - powder, as used by the British Army, composed of Naphthol.su^ Creosote. 2% Idoform. 2% ?-&gt; r«) is applied to the skin, shirt and trousers, being renewed every five days. All local treatment should be followed by a bath. Destruction of parasites on clothing is effected by means of dry or moist heat and by antiparasitical vapours. A temperature of 113° F. kills in about 3 hours. ' 122° F. ' ' ' 140° F. ' ' ' 176° F. Tf ' rt pg n 11 20 to 30 minutes. tf 10 minutes. The disenfection of personal clothing and bedding is best carried out in a Clayton Dieenfector by which sulphur gas is pumped into a disenfecting chamber having shelves and hangers for the clothing treated. A suitable site whould be chosen for the typhus quarantine station and isolation wards. All buildings should be temporary structures made od date fronds and matting, except the dis- enfActing chamber which should be of stone and plaster. The buildings which will include bath rooms, living, rooms for attendants and contact, cllkhouses, laterines, and ncessary admi nistrative buildings should be properly spaced leaving ample room between isolation wards and living quarters. The disenfecting chamber would be best served by a Clayton Disenfector which both produces and pumps sulphur gas, and is probably the most efficient machine manufactured for disenfecting rooms, clothing and bedding. Any of the leading Sanitary Engineer firms in India, or Messrs. N. Powell, Medical Outfitters, The Fort, Bombay, would be able to supply a Clayton Eisenfector without delay. The Thresh Disenfector, manufactured by Messrs. Summer- scales, Central Building, W e stminster, is another efficient machine but uses steam under pressure to disenfect clothing, bedding etc; and is unsuitable for disenfecting rooms.Disease* |4 BAHRAIN. Dated. Quarter Number of Fresh Deathes Total Number Remaks iafected Cases Reported of Cases to Date V Total Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain.IN REPLY REFER TO File no. 812.1 GGS ' %1 THE FOREIGN SERVICE OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA DEPARTMENT OF STATE Basra, Iraq, January 5, 1944 AMERICAN CONSULATE H. M. Political Agent, Bahrein Island. Sir: Bor the advice of the United States Public Health Service the Consulate is desirous of learning whether there has been any recent outbreak of influenza on Bahrein Island. If the disease is prevalent, information is particularly wanted regarding the type and severity of the disease and the rate of mortality caused by it. If the disease is not prevalent now and should break out in the future, I should like to obtaih weekly reports regarding it; but I am at a loss to know to whom an appeal for the data should be made. Such advice and information as you may be able to give me in the above connection will be greatly appreciated. American' Consul./ No.C/130 Political Agency, Bahrain, 17th January, 1944. M,.- ' From Major T. Hickinbothara, C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. I To The Residency Surgeon, I have the honour to enclose a copy of a letter which I have received from the American Consul at Basra. I shall be grateful if you will deal with this matter. For your information, I understand that there has been no outbreak of influenza since the summer of last year. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.No.C/13?. 19th January 1944. Sir 1 1 ha-ve the honour to refer to your letter No.812.1 GGS dated the f&gt;th January 1944, and to jn^orT; you that your request has boon referred to the Residency Surgeon, Bushire. I an, Sir, Your obedient servant, ' /J % Political Agent, Bahrain. To The American Consul, American Consulate, Basra. \ yWe enclose herewith co^y oi our Circular hated 11th January, 1J44, lor your information and necessary action* vca.Telegram G.T.C. From Political, Bahrain To Ambassador, Baghdad No. 57 Dated the 22nd January 1944. Reference your telegram December both 1941. 2* Ptq smallpox restrictions still being imposed by Iraq Government against Bahrain* POLITICALPrinted in England. July 1940. (5.000pads) Si-168 CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. i&gt; L } LV27/CJ BAGHDAD 9/8 25 2040 DIV BGETAT= MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ie^uaC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPYPolitical Agency, Bahrain* Dated Januaiy 19* ^ To /is Mesors Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Bahrain* liemorandum /h Keference your letter No.BI/330 dated the llth January 1944. . * V vt J) 2. _ The regulation that passengers leaving Bahrain should produce vaccination certificates was cancelled by our Notice 2445-2/7** of December 15th, 1941 •which was circulated to you. 3. Passengers bound for Iraq, however, should be in possession of a certificate of vaccination as thisYstill required by the Iraq Government. jSU/if for Political Agent, Bahrain.Prom No.195 The Secretary to the Hon*hie the Political He silent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Bated. Bushire, the 25th January, 1944. No.C/130 dated the 17th January, 1944, addressed to the Pesidency burgeon, Bushire, and to say that the Hon*hie the Political Resident sees no objection to your obtaining the necessary information from the Bahrain Government and the Agency Surgeon and. to your replying direct to the American Consul, Basra. 2. A copy of your reply may kindly he sent to the Residency Surgeon, Bushire. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, • . ^ l\ ^ / \ 6 ‘Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To 'The Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, have the honour to refer to your letter smCopy of letter dated 5th ^ American Consul, Basra, Iraq, Agent, Bahrain Islando anuary 1944 from the to H.M's Political For the advice of the United States Public Hen 1 tv Service the Consulate is desirous of eaminr whetnor there has been any recent outbreak of influenza on^Bahrain Island. If the disease is prevalent , information is particularly wanted regarding the typo and severity of the disease and the ratexof mortality caused by it. lse « sc and , , disease is not prevalent now and should break out in future, I should like to obtain weekly reports regarding it; Should -like lu nenerts regarding 1 %) but I am at a los^to tovow t? whom an appeal foy tl’e dat&gt; should be made? Such advice and information give me in the above connection appreciated. as you may be able to will be greatly No • 5* -2/7A . Political Agency, Bahrain. Da ted Ffh brua ry 1944. Copy forwarded to the state Medical kleav?r r n+ nhra i L 3 ' l ’ ,lth the foquest that he will Kinuly let mo he^ve material for a reply. for Politicil'Agent,Bahrain, ^4 a^Disease, Quarter infected Number of Fresh Cases Reported Deathes Total Number of Cases to Date BAHRAIN. Remaks \0jHm0rantmnt* From BAHRAIN GOVERNMENT ^ MEDICAL DEPARTMENT BAHRAIN Ti © i ^ Date February 27th 2944 .'B .M’s Politico wr Bahrain, Persl'^ji O ( c Agent, ulf. Memo Influenza - Bahrain ^ J ^ /»'7 l&gt; A-,, ofV^ With reference to your enquiry Ref. No. 503-2/7.A - no outbreak of any severity has occurred vet. In 1943, an Epidemic of moderate severity broke out in three waves among the Awali European community only. No specific remedies neutralised the 3-4 days '’fever**, which resolved itself without complication. Influenza has not appeared this winter. Dr. Steele or I will be able to furnish you with succeeding reports whenever necessary, and I will bear in mind your injunctions regarding that. STATE MEDICAL OFFICER.Si &gt;1 / REPORT OF INFECTiOUS DISEASE Disease, USULL i BAHRAIN Dated.;;.. Quarter infected Number of Freab Cases Reported Deathes Total Number of Cases to Date Remaks Bahrain.\ DEPARTMENT/OFFICE. Letter 1. Date of despatch. 2. List of enclosures. Draft Memorandum Telegram No. File No. Serial No. Dated .S-s (Small) H. P. 6767/A/S- 79—25-6-42—5(1.000 pad*.► » Disease, Small P&amp;x. Quarter infected Number of Fresh Cases Reported Deathes Total Number of Cases to Date Remaks Hi DO 3 ! Nl'n IS ^ rn i Total n* — / 5' Quarantine Medica4 Officer Bahrain.Bahrain. To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd.,Bahrain Messrs. Haji Yusuf Kanoo, Bahrain. Memorandum . As the Bills of Health of steamers, which have called at Abadan, show typhus prevalent it is requested that Masters of ships which -^jQiavp call^at this port be instructed not to allow any of the crew (except those on duty) or passengers other than those for Bahrain to land. Passengers for Bahrain will be examined and passed by the Q.M.O. Q.R.O. Bahrain rJ S-Bahrain.BRITISH KSSIEENCY Affl) CONSUIATa GSSHHBAL, HJSBIBS . No. g632-4/142. Bated 25th Novemher, 1944. A copy or the undermentioned paper is forwarded to: The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. for information. .. Date.... 5.?:. By order, Savings telegram No. 0/2613, dated the 22nd July. 1944, from the Chief Secretary, Aden, to the Political Agent, Muscat, received under Muscat Agency endorsement No.G.2173.6807, dated the 30th October, 1944, with enclosure. NS. P.T.O* No. 2/7,k. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 10th December, 1944. Copy with copy of enclosure forwarded to: 1. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. 2. The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, for information. Political Agent, Bahrain, Hi i 'Cony Saving telegram No. C/2613 ^ate^ 22 nd July, 1944 from the Chief* Secretary, Aden to the Political Agent, Muscat. My telegram No. 9 Yellow fever control. The following measures have been taben at this post for the control of mosquito breeding in dhows. (a) The installation in dhows of mosauito proof water tanks whenever It is uossible. (b) T^e searching of dthows for adult mosquitoes and larvae on arrival at and on departure from the port; the refusal of pratique if these be found; the oiling of a 1 ! bilges and open water tanks. (c) The control of the source from which dhows draw water. In Aden, dhows mav only fi^l their tanks from a special stand pfcpe'on the wharf; supply from water boats or f*rora storage tanks has been forbidden. (d) The exchange weekly, between ports concerned of the results of dhow examination showing the name, number, port of registry of each dhow and whether such vessel was found breeding mosquitoes. A note of the Mosquito proof water tank issued by the Port Health Officer at Aden is attached for your information. AGL.PORT HEALTH OPFIOE, ADEN. MOSQUITO PROOF WATER TANKS. 1. The tank should he constructed of metal which will not corrode in water. Galvanized iron Is very suitable; mild steel plate cement washed will also serve. 2. The tank should he provided with:- (a) an opening of the top, for the purpose of filling. This should in no case be less than 1 ft. square and should he closed with a tightly fitting lid. (b) an opening in the bottom for the purpose of drainage. This should he closed by a cap of a screw type if possible. (c) a tap through which water may be drawn off for drinking or washing. The tank should be raised above the deck on a stand to facilitate emptying. 3. The size of the tank will vary with the size of the dhow and the needs of her crew. In smaller dhows it is suggested 40 gallon oil drums may be adapted to form mosquito proof tanks, the number installed again being dependent on the vessel's requirements in water* 4. Where oil drums are used the entire top Should be removed and lid made to fit the whole circumference of the drum. No drainage opening is required with these drums. Sd./- C.N. HOWAT, Port Health Officer, Aden.? © ''OSPlri^TIAL D.O.$o.r/l£Xl v| - Political Agency, Batirain, 22nd August 1944 dear Campbell, I am sanding a oopy of the original and the suggested revised version of the form filled in by masters of vessels for the Information of the Quaran tine Medinal Officer* Will you please let me have your comments? I do not think any master* r»ould reasonably take exception to supplying the informa- tion asked for*« Yours sincerely ^aptain G. Campbell, Security Officer, Bahrain.MOYIKYJIY MEDICAL OFFICER. I^BPLY BY CC^MANDEK Name of vossol? ••• ••• Nama of conmandor? Kamo of crew? (Europeans ••• (Asiatics ••• Had vossol any communication with any port in India. ••• Exact duration of voyage from last port in India. ••• ••• Had vossol clean bill of Health from all the ports of call on route. Any contagious disease during the voyage• If contagious or infectious when did it manifest itself* Any deaths. If so, fro^ what disease? When did last dllath occur? Description of cargo for Bahrain? Any susceptible cargo for Bahrain? Number of all passengers on board? How many for Bahrain from Indian ports? How many for Bahrain from Persian Gulf p ports?. Total number for Bahrain? How inany of these are 1st and 2nd class and Europeans? Names please. Certified that the above statement is correct. Dated Bahrain. Medical Officer, Commander. the— .194 S.S s.sDear sir &lt;s), v We enclose herewith copy of our circular of date for your information and necessary action* yours faithfully,1 British India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (incorporated in England; TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. /if No. 193 EAHKnlH, 5th MARCH, CIROiLAR AU. PASSENCffiSS fRAVELLIiiCi BY B.I. BI&amp;AKKBS TO INDIA ARK HEREBY IHPOHMED MAT ‘MALL POX VACCINATIOM CERTI flCATE IS XTEQUIBED BEFORE LKAVDIG BAHRAIN. THIS CERTIFICATE MUST BK PRODUCED tiKTOUE A BOOKING CAN BE MAIT AND SHOULD NOT BE DATED MORE THAN 3 YEARS OR LESS THAN 10 DAYS BEFORE THE DATE OF DEPARTURE FROM THIS PORT. IN THE ABSENCE OF VACCINATION CERTIFICATE HO TICKET CAN BE ISSUED FROM THIS OFFICE. m.O' I BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION ■ TELEGRAMS : •FLYING' BAHRAIN. CODES s BENTLEY’S &amp; I. A. T. A. TELEPHONE : 43M. BAHRAIN ISLANDS. PERSIAN GULF. TBT .315.0660. HBM 1 g Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. 19th May 194 5, Sir, 1. I hare the honour to request your advice as to whether the health regulations of Bahrein Island are laid down by the Government of India, or whether such regulations emanate from the Quarantine Officer of the Persian Gulf. 2. If the latter Is the case will you mease let me hare full details of all the Quarantine regulations and restrictions at Bahrein, with particular reference to Yellow Fever. RWCrVKK, I have the honour to be srf, Your obedient servant, , (T.J^G . Wei ch ) . ;lon Manager.Ra. 2256-2/7. A&lt; Political Agency, Bahrain, The 31st May, 1945. To The Station Manager British Overseas Airways Corporation Bahrain. Dear Sir, p/Hl With reference to your letter No.TBT.315.0660 dated the 19th May, 1945, the quarantine regulation? in general for the Gulf are the Indian Port Health Rules, Y?hieh are followed in Bahrain as far as is practicable and applicable to local conditions, fhe Chief Quarantine Medical Officer in the Persian Gulf issues special regulations or measures to be adopted in times of epidemics, if necessary. 2 . As regards Yellow Fever, will you please refer to your letter No.BA^Vi60/M~9 of the 3 rd May, 1942, forwarding extracts from the report of the Inter-departmental Committee of Yellow Fever Control, December 1941, a copy of which was sent to the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain? 3. Briefly the rules are that no passenger arriving in Bahrain in a plane from an endemic area and who has not been inoculated is allowed to land, the reason being that there is not a yellow fever segregation camp. 4. Passengers leaving here, if by a plane from an endemic area, would be required at destination to produce a certificate of inoculation and Bahrain Petroleum Company Hospital frequently do yellow fever inoculations because there are no facilities * elsewhere. for Political Agent, Bahrain C.0 crypT^’T-nT, (W) Copy of Office ! r «mrr»n^KiRi M o. r^p/A^jp S5wi1a the IPth ’’ay 1°45 from the ^ermty Secretary to the fovemoert of Tn&lt;?5a in the ^eoartment of ^fhication Health an* Lan*s to all T %nart^ents of the fowm- eent of Tn*ia # ^afe^iar* agoInst yellow fever onarantine reetrie- tinrm of Covovrmont of In*la Officials travellinr hy air at short notice* ^very passenger 9 not In nossessfon of a vali* certificate of inoculation against yellow fever, on arrival in Tn*1a t Is liahi® to otmr^ntine restrict lions if the aircraft in which he is travelling t« (a) has rasge* thrmich an are^ Infecte* with yellow fever; or (b) carries on honr* a r^esonger ^ho has, *nrlng the rrevlmis nine ***ys* rasse* thronfl an area infecte' 3 with yellow fever # 'lo__eZi3rrr&gt;_tiop fror cnarantlne restrictions is allow*** on account of either the high rank of the in*ivi*nal or the urgency of his ^is^ion. 2* rases have occur®* In which passengers *roR the TTnite* King*ow who have been comrelle'* to change fren one aircraft to another String their ]Joiiwney from the T kilte* T ing*or to Tn*ia have ha* to he detain®* in quarantine at Karachi. Officers of the r ovemrent of India who nay have to travel to the United Kingdm?! can ensure beforehand that they are not to he subject to these orrrantine restrictions * on their return Journey hy getting thewselvos inocu lated against yellow fever* 3* Yellow fever inoculation, which is a simple and painless procedure, c^n he carried out at H^thi. ’Tie period of immunity conferred Is four years*7 BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION TELEGRAMS: ‘FLYING* BAHRAIN. CODES : BENTLEY'S &amp; I. A. T. A. TELEPHONE : 43M. BAHRAIN ISLANDS. PERSIAN GULF. XCT.2780Gr.0400. 6th January, 1946 . The Political Agent, Bahrein. ^ ’ Sir, INTERNATIONA! REGULATIONS YELLOW FEVER I have the honour to inform you that Indian Health Authorities insist on passengers being in possession of a Certificate of Inoculation against Yellow Fever on entering India and therefore, if you could arrange for all potential passengers to have this inoculation, I would then be in a position to handle at short notice, passages to India. only aircraft unaffected by this regulation are almost consistently filled to capacity with high priority passengers, the above inoculation is absolutely essential in a position to effect inoculations for Yellow Fever by arrangement with him. For your information I may add that this inoculation is not valid until 10 days old. 2 . It is further pointed out that as the 3. I understand from Dr. Snow that he is I have the honour to be, S^r,V GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. in MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. Government - Hospital, Bahrain, Persian Gulf, 8 th January, 1946. H. B. M*s Politieal Agent Bahrain. Bahrain Receipt ^e: fellow Fever Vaccine The exact new regulations have just been circularised by the Station Manager, J3.0.A.C., and 1 have also consulted with him on the subject. As regards Manama, the Bahrain Government will be res ponsible for their inoculations through the Q.M.O. Bahrain, at ohr expence. Messers: B.O.A.C. Ltd; will not recognise any other vaccine than that of (a^ the '//elcome Institute, London (bj Rochfeller. Dr. Steel is trying to re-establish contact for a supply with Hochfellers India. It is doubtful if he v/ill succeed. £ In the meantime it is essential to have vaccine here quickly and regularly and monthly. At our expense, would you very kindly cable on our behalf stating the extreme necessity for the vaccine, and request ing them to send 140 doses monthly by 'Air'. The Bahrain Govt: Medical Dept: will be responsible for all expend!tuie over this Yellow Fever procedure coming into force. Thanking you. W ellcome Institute . 1 83. Euston Road. London N. W. I STATE MEDICAL OFFICER.K v. Telegram En Clair. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Wellcome Institute, 183 Euston Road, London. N.W.I. No. 31 Dated 12th January, 1946. Grateful if you can send me regularly by air every month one hundred and forty doses of yellow fever vaccine for use by Bahrain Government Hospital. POLITICALS No.py-2/1 Political Agency,Bahrain. The January ,1946. Copy to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain Government Hospital, Bahrain, for informa tion. \Telegram From To No. Dated En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Public Health Commissioner, New Delhi. 33 13th January, 1946. Following from Baft Health Officer Bahrain Begins. Reference your No.16-115/41-PH of 13 th May 1942. Grateful if you can supply me with 220 doses of yellow fever vaccine as early as possible. Arrangements made with B.O.A.C. to take delivery from air port Health Officer Karachi. Ends. =P0LITICAL= AMO.The first line of thie Telegram contains the followingThe first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. • NLT POL H I CAL A'H I RTYON^) GOVERNMENT HOSPITAL BAHRAIN = PLEASE APPLY FOR YELLOW VACCINE THROUGH INDIA OFFICE . ' STATING REASON FOR (REQUISITION AND DOSAGE PER AMPOULE.'; WELLCOME INSTITUTION = P strain Receif?* MARK YOUR REPLY Jm/ietuaC ’ NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. f &lt;Telegram Fr om To No 0 Dated GTC Political A£ent, Bahrain. India Office, London. 47 18th January, 1946. Grateful if Wellcome Institute London can he asked to supply direct Bahrain Government Hospi tal regularly by air every month seven ampoules of 20 c.c. each yellow fever vaccine for inoculation air passengers leaving Bahrain. \ =P0LITICAL= AMO. CD &gt;The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Printed in England. Aug. 1941 . (9,000 pads) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (lNCORt&gt;ORArED IN ENGLAND.) Clerk’s Time Circuit. Name. Received. L.Me 011OLCL. SUBJECT TO COR; EOT I ON WRONG NUMBER OF WyE&lt;BS46 D KVI36/T NEWDELHI 47 1 7 2040 BGETAT . _ .. Bahrain Receipt POLITICAL BAHREIN ? G REFERENCE YOUR TELEGRAlT'OF JANY 13 TH AAA FOLLOWING FOR PORT HEALTH OFFICER BAHREIN BEGINS FACILITIES FOR YELLOW FEVER INOCULATION HAVE BEEN ARRANGED BY R A F MIDDLE EAST COMMAND CIVIL HOSPITAL BAHREIN AAA SUGGEST YOU DIRECT n ERSONS REQUIRING INNOCULATIOM TO THAT HOS n ITAL ENDS -HEALTHCOM ‘‘Dm &lt;?m/ieSua£.' — Ji'iO, US MARK YOUR REPLY NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.o. gk/t- To Bahrain, the 26 ch January, 1^6 Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltci., Bahrai n. Dear sirs, I ij Bahrain Receipt No.^JAd^ With reference to the case of suspected cerebro spinal fever reported on Barala, duttac her last call on the 20th instant, would you kindly bring the following to the notice oj, .die brinish India Steam Navigation Company. L founti chs case in question lying among the deck passengers, and when the decks were cleared for work he was removed to the upper dock and exposed to a cold wind. !&gt;he wa.. ..as practically moribund. On asking the medical officer why the man was not promptly isolated in the Sick bay, he informed me that the Cabin provided for a sick Bay was occupied oy Tally clerks. I need hardly point out the danger the passengers were exposed to, under such conditions, and the irregularity in allowing the sick bay to be occupied when it is specially provided for the treatment of sick and isolation of any infectious or suspected infectious case which may occur at any time. 3# ! did nou consider the case to be Cerebro Spinal Fever, bu^ Cerebran Malaria which has since been confirmed. oula you Kindly arrange with Messrs, the British India Steam navigation Company to have the SIck Bay always available and on no account allow it to be occupied by passengers or crew? Yours faithfully, quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. NS.To No. Dated % 8 % Telegram GTC From Political Agent, Bahrain. India Office, London. 76 30th January, 194-6. My telegram &gt;10.4/ January 18th, regarding yellow fever vaccine. 2» ‘ Grateful if first consignment sent as early as possible. =POLITICAL= AMO . No.370-2/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 30th January, 1946. Copy with copy of telegram No.47 dated the 18th January, 1946, forwarded to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain. 9^ for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. To, Thu Poiiti«r«d Agent, lahrtiim. Bkhrs-in, 27th J&amp;au&amp;rv &gt; 1&amp;46. X0.S.71...VM &amp;f/U^ -?3 A topy of th© report on the Quernati** service,sent to Chief Quarantine Medieal Officer and State Medical Officer,is forwarded for in formation. / Quwttati*# J£.dle«a Offieer, Bahrain.HiPORT ON Ttiii BAtffiAIK gJ^ AN'IINa Si^RVICa . Areas subject to Quaraatine surveillance * 1* Manama . All passenger vessels B.I. and others anchoring at Manama are visited find inspected by the quarantine Medical Officer before pratique is iven* Sailing crafts i.e., dhows, jolly boats, booms etc., arriving from the mainland.^ Iraq, Persia, Oman or Infia, are inspected by the Quarantine f l rash. Any case of illness on board among ere/ or passengers is reported to the Passport Officer, who informs the Quarantine Medical Officer by phone. The Quarantine Medical Officer then inspects the cases and takes necessary action. hen epidemics of infectious diseases are reported from the mainland, Iraq, Persia etc., the crews and passengers of those vessels in the case of small pox are inspected for evidence of vaccination and previous attack of small pox, unprotected persons are vaccinated and certificates given them, which they present to the Passport Officer, then they are^allo/ed to enter the Town. ttS* 2* Sitra. Most of the vessels calling at Bahrain arrive at this anchorage. They consist mainly of freighters and tankers. When infectious or suspected infectious diseases occur on these vessels, information is sent by radio to the agents v/ho inform the Quarantine Medical Officer to enable .him to meet the vessel on arrival. These vessels arrive at all times and infor mation of their arrival is only received after they have anchored. Pratique is granted to vessels with a clean bill of health through Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., the agents. Tankers and freighters are visited by the Quarantine Medical Officer only if infectious disease is reported aboard or if they carry passengers for Bahrain. Manama. 1st January to B.I. vessels 62. Total vessels Sitra. 15th December. Freighters. 107. Tankers 205. 374. 3. Flying boat base and Muharraq Air port. Quarantine inspection only applies to those planes which have landed in places where Yellow fever is endemic or prevalent. At present the only plane to land at such places is the *0* Class Flying boat - these planes in case of bad weather or engine trouble might stop at Bahrain. The British Overseas Airways Corporation official checking the passenger lists brings to the notice of the Quarantine Medical Officer any case of a passenger being unprotected. Such passengers are not allowed to land at Bahrain as no facilities for Quarantine against Yellow fever exist in Bahrain. This is the only measure that can be enforced. The Quarantine Staff consists of* Quarantine Medical Officer 1. Clerk 1. Head farash I. A motor launch is provided by the Bahrain Government and, has a crew of a driver, a nakhuda and two bahris.) quarantine Station . Sweeper 1* Naturs 2, (extra Waturs as required are detailed for temporary duty by the Superintendent of Police during small pox epidemics). The Quarantine Station near iiuh&amp;rraq is well situated for the purpose being entirely cut off from the island at high tide; at low tide a narrow spit of land connects it to Muharraq. It is enclosed by barbed wire and has two gates. (f**. Building s. Two long buildings with four rooms and bathrooms, a kitchen, store room, inspection room and mortuary. A cement bathing platform enclosed by thatched walls serves for bathing an^Bisinfection of clothes, bedding etc. A latrine made of corrugated zinc walls with six seats is situated near the sea and over high tide level. later s.u &gt;Dly. Cement cistern and artesian wells. No steam disinfector has yet been installed. The station can accommodate from 125 to 150 patients* As the incidence of small pox during the years 1941, 1942, 1943 and 194 / was high and there was no infectious disease hospital in Bahrain capable of accommo dating such large number of patients, cases of the dis ease together with contact: , were quarantined treated and segregated at the station. The station has therefore functioned mainly as an infectious disease hospital for the treatment of major infectious diseases in tSe’case* small pox, with the exception of one case of Typhus in May 1943. jjOi—of cagt-s, o£.,,siaall pox treated in quarantine Station. Xear. liq. ,qf capes f 1941 • 4 193 (September - December) 1942 4 # 119 1943 • • 43 1944 • • 5? 1945 # ♦ 14. The Quarantine staff is too small to carry out all its legitimate duties efficiently. The Quarantine arrangements in co inaction 1th sailing crafty is not satisfactory. As infectious diseases are most likely to be brought into Bahrain from this source I think that a Medical Officer (Sub Assistant Surgeon) be detailed to inspect the sailing crafto on arrival. Ail craft* have to report to the Passport Officer, whose office is conveniently situated in the Customs building. He ,can send information and particulars of the arrival of thi^ type of craft to the M dical Officer who could then c^rry out his inspection and report to the Quarantine Medical Officer. The State Medlc§l Officer has expressed his approval of this proposal and would lend a Medical Officer to carry out these duties. The examination of ships at Sitra will be much easier in the near future, as the pier now in progress of completion will enable steamers to come along side and instead of a trip by sea ( one hour and five minutes) by launch from Muharraq bridge to theanchorage a taxi could reach the uier in a little over 30 minutes* . Base - Bri tish Overseas Airways Corporation A Quarantine Station for Yellow fever would be too— ^—* expensive and at present unnecessary. The present arrangements may be implemented by the British Overseas Airways Corporation officials obtainin } from passengers °n c Class Flying boats a certificate - vide conies attached - whenever applicable or necessary and the air craft disinsectised. gulp fQ,r_..the segregation of passengers off Infected ships. Passenger traffic may be expected to increase and the -likelihood of an infected ship arriving at Bahrain and subject to quarantine must be taken into consideration. The State Medical Officer has I understand a proposal to make in this connection. The segregation of deck passengers would not be difficult, but 1st and 2nd class passengers would mean the provision of a furnished building with arrangements for messing the passengers. The question of extra staff, site and size of the station etc., could be discussed with the State Medical Officer if fPis proposal is approved. Victoria Memorial Hospital, ) Bahrain, ( 16 th December, 1945. Quarantine Medical Officer.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. MEDICAL DEPARTMENT Sth January, 1946 Dear Dr. Steele, Thank you very much for your Quarantine Report. Herewith are criticisms on its present weaknesses 1. MANAMA . Only a quarantine farrash visiting the small vessels. 2. SITRA . Reliance on information only. 3. »PLANES . No visiting except on information only. 4. QUARANTINE ISLAND . A disinfesting apparatus is recommended as soon as price is reasonable. A supernumerary extra dresser recommended who has had 5. YELLOW FEVER . D.D.T. must be at hand for suspect ’planes. 6 . SEGREGATION OF 1st and 2nd PASSENGERS . Their numbers are likely to be very small and 2 at one time could be taken at the Govt. Hospital. Perhaps more later. If an occasional mass infected ship ever put in, one ward could be specially isolated for the purpose as an emergency measure, to contain the persons. CONCLUSIONS. Recommended 1 Sub-Assistant Surgeon. 0 for your Department 1 Semi-qualified dresser, jj exclusively. 1 Disinfestation machine. /Yellow Fever measures will shortly be inaugurated re: preventio training. A separate station for Yellow Fever not recommended D.D.T. i cwt. powder can be spared ? in February 1946 Sd./- R.H.B. SNOW, State Medical Officer The Quarantine Medicax Officer Bahrain.HEALTH CERTIFICATE r ^ \ Flying Boat !♦ Name in block letters« 2* Date and place of immunisation against Yellow Fever. 3. Date of leaving England (State here whether by air or sea route). 4. Date of arriving at first port or place in West Africa and name of th$ port or place. 5. Route followed to Khartoum. 6. Date of arrival at Khartoum. 7. Date of arrival at Cairo. 8. Date of departure from Cairo. I hereby declare that the above declara tion made by me before the Health Officer of the £b P ort is correct. Karachi. Date Passenger's signature Address.Government of India SANITARY REPORT FROM AIRCRAFT. Name and nature of aircraft. Flag. Time of arrival Date and hour of departure Questions. Answers. 1* Pilot’s name. 2. What is the number of the crew? 3. How many passengers have you on board? 4. a) Have you had any deaths or sickness on board during the voyage and from what disease? b) Have you any sick on board now? 5# Have the aircraft, passengers, and crew been subjected to any health measures, such as disinfection, disinsectisation, vaccination, et., during the voyage? 6. a) When was your aircraft tran last in a yellow fever infected area? (see list on reverse), b) Has your aircraft been disinsectised since leaving such area? If so, state place of disinsectisation, designation and name of the health authority who performed it. 7. Have you on board any persons who have come from a yellow fever infected area? If so, state names of such persons, dates of their departure from such areas, whether Inoculated against yellow fever and dates of such inoculation. 8. How may passengers are disembarking here and where do they come from? State names, addresses in India and any other relevant information in regard to their subsequent move ments. 9. What is your next landing place? What is your final destination? 10. Name of your Agent here. To the best of my knowledge the above information is correct. Pilot!• 2 . 3. 4. 5 . 6 . 7. 8 . 9. 10 . 11 . 12 . 13. 14. 15. 16 . 17. 18. 19. 20 . 21 . 22 . 23. List of areas in Africa regarded as infected with yellow fever. Angola. Anglo Egyptian Sudan South of Khartoum. Belgian Congo. Cameroons. Dahomey. French Equatorial Africa. French Guinea. French West Africa. Gambia. Gold Coast Colony. Ivory Coast. Liberia. Nigeria. Senegal. Sierra Leone. Togoland. Uganda. Upper Volta Territory. Abyssinia. Brazil. Spanish Guinea. Eritrea. Kenya.Government of India. 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5* 6 . .8 .d .8 • V *3 *e .si •SI •dl *di • VI • «oxiex rf^w ***** Name and nature of alr?fo?t. Flag. Time of arrival Date ^$ 0 §gJjP\| f departure, cwt$qx&amp; . .csnoO a&amp;l^leQ. Pilot s name. .anooieciBO What is the number of the crew? .v^ciodnG How many passengers 0 h^fAF2Ml^6lfeMi®5lon9T^ a) Have you had any deaths or,§ifi5&amp;gs^ oa9 ^q on board during the vojSft^i^faSioioflsT:^ what diseas ? ^ .slcfiaBO •&gt;. b) Have you any sick on ho^xB9 w | a eoO bloO .01 Have the aircraft, passengers, and^oO ^iovX .II crev/ been subjected to any health measures, such as disinfection, .Bi'leaiM disinsectisation, vaccination, ^XBaeneS et., during the voyage? ,anceJ Elista a) Vi hen was your aircraft hwm lastbtolosoT a yellow fever infected area? .sbnjsrHJ (see list on rqve^AfreT siloV leqqU ♦81 b) Has your aircraft been disinseqM^tia^dA .«! since leaving such area? .Ila&amp;aH .OS If so, state nlace of disj^^^#(fe4m s 3 .IS designation and name of the healt*lfcy«j$i:‘iS *SS authority v/ho performed it. *SS 7 . Hav you on board any persons who have come from a yellow fever infected area? If so, state names of such persons, dates of their departure from such areas, whether inoculated against yellow fever and dat s of such inoculation* 3. Hov» may passengers are disembarking here and where do they come from? State names, addresses in India and any other relevant information in regard to their subsequent move ments. 9 . #hat is your next landing place? What is your final destination? 10. Name of your Agent here. To t ie best of ray knowled c the above information is correct. Pilot&amp; rnm 468/46 Bear ,/eut. X WGmuary $ 15 X enclose a copy of a telogran from tlic i^olitical Agent Bahrein, about the su ly of yellow fever vaccine for the Jlahi’ei n Govcrmaent Hospital* No. 47 ) dated 18th Jan. ) 'We have i ade enquiries frun the ellcor .e Reaearch Instit. I8j&gt;, Wusten Road, K, i, 1. who would be prepai’ed to simply the vaccine. 1 untie .ratal id, however, that in erder to transport it by air four half-gallon 'fher os flasks, as used by the would be neceasai^y, and that the e may be some difficulty in securirig tliem. We ah uld be gratel'ul if you would obtain such flasks, ant-i (if you consider tide would cor e within your province) arrange with the Wellco e Institution for the purchase of yellow fever vace ne by the Bahrein Govei’inent. Would you kindly let m know what you are able to do. Yours a .nee ely, F. A. K. HARWSON «... . ISaq., India latc*e Xw^fe.oBt, 1^. Au&gt;jL a- ^ tW ] p XUi ^ roN .. A. K. HARRISONN ° e 582-2/1. Political ^'Agency, Letter No.iCXT.468/46 dated the 2nd February, 1946 from the India Office, London, to the India Store Department Blackpool. Letter No.BXT.787/46 dated the 4th February, 1946 from the India Office, London, to the Ministry of Civil ^viation, London. Bahrain. 21st February, 1946 \ Cf pies of pies of /Che undermentioned ^forwarded to g. Officer, Bahr ;ioned papers are the State Medical for Political Agent Bahrain. Enclosure CINDIA OFFICE, IV t ’fo- \o6&gt; Department. / wT) EXPRESS LETTER (AIR HAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed.) «£• '• J $ rXX \ '■ o O m'Jr .* &amp; From To Dated No. Secretary of State for India Political Agent, Bahrein &amp;&amp; March, 1%£. D Bxto 2225/1946. ^ Your telegram'47 of 18th January and my Express Letter Ext.1324/46 of 25 th February. Supply of yellow fever vaccine and penicillin to Bahrein Government .Hospital. 2 e Arrangements have now been made for carriage by air freight. A consignment of penicillin was despatched on 19th March by B.O.A.C. Service 13.F. 21 aircraft G--AGBY. 3. The first consignment of yellow fever vaccine is due for despatch this week. The vaccine is carried in half-gallon thermos flasks, these flasks when empty will have to be returned from Bahrein by air consigned to the Wellcome Institute of Tropical Medicine, London. Grateful if you could arrange for this to be done. 4. The cost of the carriage of these consignments will be reclaimed by B. 0. A.G. from the Bahrein Government through the Accountant-General* s Department of this Office. (The issue of the above has been duly authorised) — W&amp;j'* ^ 9 . •/P^'UVr; The 6th April, 1946. Copy forwarded to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain^ in continuation of this office memorandum No.763-6/43 dated the 6th March, 1946* Agency, Bahrain, 101 . ■ 7131 ' No.1085-2/1. oliticalRepeated tos BXTKRNAL Confidential. Bahrain receipt Secretary of State for India Covernuent of India, External Affairs Department Political Agent, Bahrein 1 ^ 4 * 43 ?, 1946 . Ext.259l/46 Co :) y is enclosed of corr©soondence with Burroughs Welcome &amp; Co., about the payxoent for yellow/ fever vaccine supplied to the Bahrein Government Hospital. Understand that for purposes of calculation &gt;/ar Office reckon the price of yellow a ever vaccine at about five shillings per c.c. Burroughs Welcome s proposal seems therefore extremely reasonable. A debit for £L05 will be included in the Inward Account Current with the Accountant-General Central Revenues for April 1946 under the head 'Miscellaneous s Items adjustable in India”. H-ease arrange for the amount to be recovered from the Bahrein Government. ISSUE OP THE ABOVE HAS BEES DULY^AOTHOffiU®. ^ ^ (til V, .a itjo y © aKt.253lA6. April, i)ear -Ira, I ara deaired to aoknowiedge the receipt of your letter of 9th April, ref ere vice J'^i/UhV, regarding the supply i» yellow fever vaccine to the Bahrein Govemaent Hospital# It is agreed that tlie iiihrein Goveraaont should he asked to contribute 100 guineas towards the cost of the preparation of monthly consignments of this vaccine* A liable Order (Case 2£&gt;j is enclosed herewith* lours faithfully, 1 ^. Messrs. Eurroughs -elcowe A Co*, u 1?13*193 Kustov Bead, if.W.l.EXT. 2591/46 j BURROUGHS WELLCOME &amp; CO. 183-193&gt; Buston Road, London, N.W.l. Reference DGH/MLW 9th April 1946. EX C Your Reference Eact.2225A946 Dear Sirs, We thank you for your letter of the 28th March and we understand from Dr. Broom that the first despatch of Yellow Fever Vaccine to the Bahrein Government Hospital has already been made. 3 The Vaccine has not yet been added to our price list and is not yet normally available for commercial sale. No price has so far been established though we know that the cost of production is quite high. We are consequently unable to charge and invoice you for each consignment and we therefore suggest you make a contribution of 100 guineas towards the cost of preparation of the monthly consignments. We look forward to receiving your agreement to this proposal. Yours faithfully, BURROUGHS WELLCCME &lt;Sb CO. (Sgd.) D.G.Heath Zone Executive India Office, Whitehall, London,S.W.l.Ill © GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. To Bahrain Government Hospital Political Agent, May20th: 1946 Bahrain. M EMO : Rei ^Yellow Fe ver Inocul ations fo r ai r jd assenge rs tr av elling East from Bahrain. Yellow Fever Vaccine has been authorised for the Bahrain Govt: by India Office,who has arranged for monthly con- -signments of 140 doses to be sent air freightage packed in ice in a thermos to me direct. Two consignments have already arrived and the arrangement is very satisfactory. 2. Pending this arrangement,the R.A.F. Medical Authorities Muhhrraq have been responsible for carrying out inoculations for the whole Island,as ratified by Delhi in a telegram to you dated 17»1«46. from Health Com, New Delhi. Medical Dept: should take over this work through the Q.M.O. Bahrain. 4. Will you therefore very kindly request the Delhi Authorit- -ies to agree to this change over and to recognise the signat- -ures for inoculation of either the Q.M.O. Bahrain or the 5. M.O. Bahrain as valid and in order for all port authorities in India. 3. It is now highly desirable that the Bahrain Govt: State Medical Officer, Bahrain.by air r .m, . GOTERMCTT OF INEO. eternal Mfairs Department. LDT?^. From Foreign, New Delhi 3* To Political, Bahrain. No. D*4399-MS/46. Dated the D-0 ft ‘-v May 1946. Reference India Office express lettef No.^591/46, May 1st. Yellow fever vaccine for Government of Bahrain. 2. please arrange to recover sum of £ 105/- from Bahrain Government and* credit it to Government of India throuuji Accountant General, Central Revenues. SKpemditure is being booked under “.Suspense' head. Issue of the above has been authorised* Under Secretary to the Govt, of India. iGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, .iltf S LETTER [2^, B, This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by vast to save telegraphic H expense and undue use of the wires, but:intended to he treated, on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] J From POLITICAL BAHRAIN. To INDIA OFFICE EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT LONDON. A'o. 1714-3/1. Dated 30th May, 1946. iS3c , „ . rovat Express Letter No.EXT.222§/1946 March 26th, 1946. § » 2. Most grateful for the trouble you have taken in arranging the supply of yellow fever vaccine for the Bahrain Government Hospital. i = POLITICAL = The Issue of the above has been authorised. C. 6 ^ Assistant Political Agent, /yy Bahrain. S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M- 820)—23-7-36—300,000,IK © No. {'/[g -2/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, The^o^iay, 1946. To The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. 70 Memorandum: vith reference to/correspondence resting with my endorsement No. 1085-2/1 of the £th April, 1946, I forward herewith copies of letter No.Ext.2591/46 dated the 1st May, 1946 and its enclosures received from the India Office, London. I shall be glad if you will kindly arrange to remit to this Agency a sum of Rs.1400/-, the equivalent of £ 105. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram From t En Clair. To No. Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. Healthcom, New Delhi. 326 30th May, 1946. Your telegram January 17th, Yellow fever vaccine is now being supplied direct to Bahrain Government from London under arrangements made by India Office. Request therefore that certificate issued by Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain be recognised and all port authorities in India be informed accordingly. Local R.A.F. authorities agree with this suggestion. AMO =POLITICAL=URGENT No.1822 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 8th June, 1946. To The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum. Lt. M.L.A. Steele, Medical Officer in charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, is leaving to-day for Qatar and v/ill remain absent for three days. It is requested that a Medical Officer may kindly be deputed by you to carry out quarantine duties in the absence of Lt. Steele. for Political Agent, Bahrain C© URGENT No.1866-2/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 11th June, 1946. To The State Medical Officer Bahrain. Memorandum. ^ &gt; Refer^hce your memorandum dated the 20th May, 1946. (a) telegram No.326 dated the 30th May, 1946, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Healthcom, New Delhi, and (b) telegram dated the 8th June, 1946, from Healthcom, New Delhi, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for your information. 3. Will you kindly supply me with material for a reply to the Health Commissioner's telegram? 2 I forward herewith copies of for Political Agent, Bahrain, CG - 2,/ / . Hq(-P 6 / YELLOW FEVER s 'K W Uate ^ ^^ &gt; - telegTS i'a Re: Delhi*s enquiry telegram of 8*6*46,^the following are the answers required :- 1* Vaccine is stored ifc. the ice chamber of a F refrigerator at a temperature of 2*to 4°centigrade# A 2# Periodic potency tests cannot be carried out# Would like information how this can be done. 3* The Vaccine is received fresh every month. State Medical Officer, Bahrain#Telegram From T 066 No. Dated Your 63 P?f 11 . Vaccine is received fresh every month by air from England and is stored in refrigerator temperature 2 to 4 centigrade. Periodical potency tests not at present carried out. Grateful for instructions as to how these should be done. En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Healthcom, New Delhi. 350 l 6 th June, 1946. / ... ■ ? =POLITICAL= AMO.t r» &lt; 1 ©Itif' a^4k g&amp;^i***- i** ?&gt; f 't- 10 /^ Copy of letter No,2591/46 of the 30th April, 1946 from the India Office, London, to Messrs Burroughs 7elcome &amp; Co*, London. I am desired to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of 9th April, reference DCH/MLV, regarding^the supply of yellow fever vaccine to the Bahrain Government Hospital. It is agreed that the Bahrain Government should be asked to contribute 100 guineas towards the cost of the preparation of monthly consignments of this vaccine. A Payable Order for £ lOj^ is enclosed herewith.Cables and Radiotelegrams: TABLOID, LONDON Inland Telegrams : TABLOID HOL'B LONDON Telegraphic Codes: ABC and MARCONI INTERNATIONAL Telephone : EUSton 4477 4th.COPY. URROUGHS WELLCOME &amp; CO. (Proprietors: The Wellcome Foundation Ltd.) 183-193, EUSTON ROAD, LONDON, N.W. 1 Associated Houses: New York Montreal Sydney Cape Town Bombay Shanghai Buenos Aires ORDER NO. ^ 0 . 14619 . { U-3 CHEQUES CROSSED MDLAND BANK, LTD. TERMS—NET CASH i sold to state officer, Bahrain rovt. Hoapltal, Persian oulf. CONVEYANCE III ITO3» INDEX NO. TO*12/13&lt; date iltfe 1946 Packages are charged at cost and are not returnableNo. YKJ^ -2/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, The &lt;2A&gt;v( June , 1946• To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. ueraoranduifl; Reference Government of India, External Affairs Department Express letter No* D*4399- Ug/46 dated the 20th ivlay, 1946, copy attached. 2. A sum of Hs.1,400/-, the rupee equivalent of £ 105 has been recovered frora the o&lt;overnment of Bahrain and credited to this Agency Treasury on the 19th June, 1946. Copy with compliments to the Under Secretary to the Government of India In the External Affairs Department, New Delhi.June 18, 1946 pEKSONAi- and confidential No. 609 Mr. C.A. itodstrom ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY Manama Bahrein Island QUARANTINE As requested in the last paragraph of your letter No. 372 dated June 15th, I am attaching a brief history of all that has tahen place in connection with ;££•, Mason 1 s case of infantile para lysis, including all the precautions wet up by the Company, as a guard against the spread of the disease We shall appreciate your following through on your sug gestion of sub dtting this brief history to the Political Agent, and securing from him a statement as to when he will permit our personnel to visit Bahrein. In other words, we would like, if pos sible, to have a statement from the Political Agent as to when the quarantine against our personnel visiting Bahrein Island will be lifted. .ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY JCMtHIA QiGr-n T. V. STAPLETON By AttachmentSPATcMalT OF W.L. MA^ON *3 ■ xhfantiu n,,.sK Walter L, Mason first had pains in his back on Friday evening, June 7th. He went to the Clinic in the evening to get same medicine that was given to aid him. He went back to ids room out could not sleep well, and went to the Hospital at 9:00 a.M., on ^une 8th, where he was put to bed and treated. On June 9th, our Chief Medical Officer, Dr. T.C. Alex ander, reported that he was Making all diagnoses possible, but felt Irom the tests he was conducting that it was possible that Mason might have infantile paralysis. On Monday, June 10th, about 10:00 in the morning. Dr. Al exander offered his diagnosis, indicating beyond any possibility of^ doubt that Mason had infantile paralysis. The Company immedia tely placed a quarantine and the following points were covered: All American and Arab schools, motion picture shows and club houses &lt; 5? C fH ties at Kas Tanura and at Abqaiq, were suspended immediately. vployees were requested to refrain from gathering in large parties for social activities, arid to remain in their re spective communities, unless urgent business necessitated their traveling to another community and this to be done only on personal approval of the Department Manager. Trips to Bahrein Island were suspended for the time being, except where absolutely neceseary and approved by the Acting General manager, personally. The swimming pool at Dhahran was drained and closed. Families were requested to keep their children from gathering in a group when indoors and to restrict t,hem to small gatherings, only, out of doors. Visiting hours at the hospital were suspended and also visiting between the Aray eamp and our eo/aps. All dogs and foxes Were to be eliminated from camps. Further precautions were taken, such as suggesting that children consume i*&gt;re citrus fruits, juices and cod liver oil. me '*es3 halls and hospitals and bushes around were sprayed with D.D.T.j kitchens were given special attention, etc. It is antici pated that the quarantine in our cajnps will be lifted after a two- week period. he I oiltical Agent, at Manama, imposed a quarantine a^ains anyone landing at Manama, from Dhahran and .41 Khobar, the expiration date of which is not known here. The evening of Thursday, June 11th, Mason encountered respiratory difficulties. An iron lung was flown in from Basra, that night, and artificial respiration was being administered but despite all our efforts, the patient passed away at 2:25 A.M* Wed nesday, June Uth. Mason was buried in the new Dhahran ceisatery. one mile west of camp, at 4*30 P.M., on June 13th,The Arayr loosed a quararitine on the Airport on »June 10th, ■whereby no plane is permitted to remain on the ground longer than one and one-half hours. No individuals are permitted to alight from the plane under any circumstances whatsoever, with penalty of being confined to the Army camp until the end of the quarantine, y&amp;il and packages may be discharged and planes may be refueled, only. It is understood this quarantine will be lifted at midnight, wune 30th. The Aray permits the arrival and departure of planes from the Airport at Has Tanura, with the understanding that no one from the Dhahran area will be transported to Has Tanura for such air transportation. Free passage is permitted between lias Tanura and Manama. The length of this quarantine is unknown and will be determined by the Political Agent. Dr. Alexander has announced that the quarantine will be lifted dune 24th, in our camps (Dhahran, Has Tanura and Abqaiq), and employees may travel freely between locations; also social acti vities will be resumed at all locations including the Club House being re-opened and resumption of movies, reading room, snack bar, billiard 4 hallj swimming pool, etc. Dhahran, Saudi Arabia June 18, 1946During Dr. Snow f s visit to the V.M. Hospital yesterday morning the 24th instant, he asked me about a case of acute appendix which Messrs. Gray Mackenzie had warned him to be ready to receive. The ship it appears was bound for Hastanura but was diverted on account of the urgency of the case. I told Dr. Snow that I had not been informed of the case and knew nothing, about it. It is the Quarantine Medical Officer^ duty to examine and arrange for disposal of all ship*s reporting illness on board or occurring in port. In the case under reference Messrs. Gray Mackenzie dealt with the case without any report or reference to the Quarantine Medical Officer. Freighters and Tankers carry no qualified Medical Officer, some of these vessels have Pharmacists assistants, the sick of other vessels being attended to by the Captain, Chief Officer or Steward. Under the circumstances it is' obvious that a case of serious illness and especially one of acute appendix tfcw^ewe should be first examined by the medical authority concerned and transferred fronn the ship under his direction. On a former occasion Messrs. Gray Mackenzie reported a similar case to me. ■ The patient was however evacuated from the ship before my arrival . I met him on the road just past the Refinery seated up in a car. I took him into my taxi and tried to bring him to Hospital as quickly as possible, as he was in great pain and suffering from thirst. The taxi however broke down twice on the way ; I managed however to get hold of an empty passenger bus and took him to the Hospital. Disasterous consequences might easily have resulted under such circumstances. I have been invariably informed by Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. of similar cases and have boarded ships by day and night and cannot understand why the authority concerned on this instance was overlooked.na No.2066. Political Agency, Bahrain, ^ The 27th June, 1946. The 27th June, 1946 To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Memorandum . I am informed that on or before the 24th June, you arranged direct with the State Medical Officer, Bahrain, without any prior reference to the Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, for the transfer of an appendicitis case from a ship in harbour to the Bahrain Government Hospital. 2. As you are doubtless aware it is the duty of the Quarantine Medical Officer to examine and arrange for the disposal of all ships’ personnel requiring treatment ashore, whether the case occurs on board ship or in port. Please ensure, therefore, in future that no patients are sent for treatment ashore in Bahrain unless the consent of the Quarantine Medical Officer has first been obtained. No. 2067. Copy to: rantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. 2 litical Agent, BahrainIA OFFICE, I3?&gt; Department EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed.) From To L ited No. Secretary of State for India, Political Agent Bahrein. June 1946. Ext. 3927/46. Li7n~ m Receiot Ur ?• ttv p.ni' ^ Your Express Letter No. 1714-2/1 of 30th May. Yellow fever vaccine for Bahrein Government Hospital, 2. he are informed that there hag been some delay in returning vacuum flasks. Wellcome Institute request that empty flasks should be addressed clearly to:- A.E.Green Esq., v Yellow Fever Department, Wellcome Laboratories of Tropical Medicine, 183 , Buston Road, London. N.¥. 1 • These flasks are now difficult to replace if lost or damaged. 3. Please inform Bahrein Government Hospital accordingly. A • The isoUe of the above ha s been duly authorised.No,2255-2/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 14th July, 1946. To The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. Reference my endorsement No.1085-2/1 dated the 6th April, 1946. 2. ' India Office inform me that there has been some delay in returning the empty vacuum flasks in which yellow fever vaccine has been supplied.to you. As you know these flasks are scarg and difficult to replace, so will you kindly ensure that they are always returned punctually. They should be addressed to:- A.E. Green, Esq., Yellow Fever Department, Wellcome Laboratories of Tropical Medicine, 183, Buston Road, London, N.W.l. for Political Agent, Bahrain C.. ^ q )4 r HR.- Telegram Prom To No. Dated the Healtheom, New Delhi. 518 16th October, 1946. My telegram No.350 June 16th. Grateful for issue of instructions. -POLITICAL-Government of India. External Affairs Department. EXPRESS LETTER. From - Foreign, New Delhi 3, To - Political, Bahrain^ No. B.1623-B.P.G./46. Dated the / 5'^u October 1946. ' r Reference India Office express letter Ext.3704/46, September 19th. Yellow fever vaccine for Bahrain Government hospital. 2. Please arrange to recover sum of £ 3.18.7d. from Bahrain Government and credit to Accountant-General, Central Revenues. Expenditure is being booked under 'Suspense' account. The issue of the above has been authorised. Bahrain Receipt /10 fU L'L’Utd 1/4. i Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded for information to the Accountant-General, Central Revenues with reference to his u.o. No. TA-10-3/1761, dated the 9th October 1946. IvjO • Q W I. RCS/ 12.10.46No. 34^3 - 2/1 POLITICAL AGLNCY, BAHRAIN. Dated the 22nd October,1946 To The State Medical Officer, Bahrain . MEMORANDUM Reference my Memorandum No.1718-3/1 ^ated the 30th May, 1946. 2. A sum of £3-18-7 has been paid by the India Office, London to the British Overseas Airways Corporation in respect of freightage on a consignment of yellow fever vaccine sent to Bahrain on the 29th March, 1946. Will you please send me Rs.52/($/-, equivalent of £3.18.7 for credit to the India Office^ London. Captain, blitical Agent, Bahrain.V r th TeD-egram From To No. Hnclair. Healthcom, New Delhi Political, Bahrain. 273PH11 f 14^ Dated the 19th received 21st October, 1946. Your telegram SIS' 1 October 16th. Necessary instructions for recognising inoculation certificates issued by Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrain performed with Welcome Bureau vaccine as valid for four years has already been issued to all concerned. As fresh vaccine is received by you monthly no potency tests essential. -HSALTHCOM- I.R.No.613. 21/10/46 BR.-/ A’ 6 ! 0: (H f ) POLITICAL AGiiNCY, V BAHRAIN. Dated the j23rd October, 1946 The State Medical Officer, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference correspondence ending with your Memorandum dated the 13th June, 1946. the Government of India informs me that necessary instructions for recognising certificates issued by Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain performed with Welcome Bureau Vaccine as valid-for 4 years have already been issued to all concerned. As fresh vaccine is received by you monthly no potency tests are essential. The Public Health Commissioner with if' Captain. for Political Agent, / Bahrain. Copy forwarded to:- The Quaa^a#!. ^ine Medical Officer, i3ahrain*jfor information.ittratoraniUttn in respect of freightage on the March 1946 con- -signment of Yellow Fever Vaccine, Kakain 68^2- it niitt State Medical Ufficer, Bahrain, 0NO. &lt;3^3^ 2/1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 3oiL' October y 1946. Central Revenues, New Delhi. MEMORANDUM :., Reference Goverrraent of India External Affairs Department express letter Ko.D.1623-BPG/46, dated the 16th October 1946 regarding yellow fever vaccine for Bahrain Government Hospital. A sum of Es. 52/6/-( £ 3-18-7,) has been recovered from Government of Bahrain and credited to this Agency Treasury on the 29th October 1946. Captain. Bahrain. Copy forwarded with corapliiaents to the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, for information.Pa! PEESIM GULF HESIDE^Y BaHHaU 17th April, 1947* Hl» B&amp;JeatyU consul~G*ner&amp;l, Lushlrc Th# Political Agent, Kuwait The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, KXuseat His Majesty’s Consul, Khorranshshr His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas The Port Health Officer, Basra, informs i«e that plague inoculation is necessary for passengers from India entering Iraq, if the journey takes less than six days. reipt .Secretary to the Political J(X * y Besldent, Persian Gulf*© x? Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltb. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND; BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE : LEADENHALL LONDON. E.C. iLEGRAPHIC ADDR GRAY uO BUSREH AMA RAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUN DAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LI NG AH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE ,o 1/127. RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Please refer to your memorandum No.2066 of 27th June, 1946, which deals with the duties of the Quarantine Medical Officer at this port® We submit that after a vessel has been granted practique ship’s personnel or passengers are at liberty to employ any Doctor they wish. There is no precedent we think which obliges anyone to employ a medical adviser other than of their own choosing. We do not think it correct that medical treatment should be denied • anyone pending examination by the Q.M.O. who may not be available, with serious' and perhaps fatal results. While on this subject we bring to your notice that we are receiving comments from our Principals regarding the high medical fe§s now being charged by the Q.M.O. These fees have increased from Rs.5/- in 1939 to Rs®25/- plus transport per patient seen on board. Would you use your influence to obtain a reasonable reduction? Yours faithfully, Jj lor STEAMSHIP AGENTS.'Prstique for vessels Sitra is given through M/s Gr#y Mackenzie &amp;Co. (%£ the quarantine staff is not /Quarantiny-L ar g e enough to detail a/^iedical officer for this duty. The practice is unsatisfactory and only a measure of necessity. Tankers and freighters carry no medical officers and reports from masters are unreliable and misleading. This is wellknown to M/SGr^y MpCkenzie&amp;Co. and has abttndantly been proved. To reme^dy these defects the Q.M.O. checks up and disposes of all cases of illness occurmg in these vessels. This represents the minimum control he can exercise to prevent the importation of infectious diseases into Bahrain. I explained this matter to Dr, Pridie during his visit and asked him whether it would be in order if any local medical officer attended cases on board*and subsequent^ ly reported to QMO any case of infectious disease. He was of opinion that taking into consideration local conditions obtaining at present at Sitra, this would be relegating quarantine responsibility to unauthorized persons, who in any case could not be held responsible. Local conditions in Bahrain and especially Sitra are very different to those of large ports and can therefore furnish no precedent. High medical charges*.— If consideration is given k to the distantethe medical officer has to go^/attend cases at Sitra from Manama (36miles) at any time and at short notice, with often no information regarding the sick and then the delays caused by sick not being ready, launches not being immediately available and as not infrequntly happens he is called out to see cases of trivial illness^ reported as serious. Many times the vessels are in stream which necessitates cl^fimbing up a dirty rope ladder, ido not think under the above circumstances my charges are excessive.Medical expenses for the treatment of the sick from tankers and freighters could be considerably reduced if the masters of these vessels did not insist on getting the medical officer all the way from Manamah to treat trivial cases of illness which could be treated on board or sent to Manamah . I have re presented this matter to many of the masters • their excuse was that they had to. comply with any request from the crew 'To see a Doctor' whether reasonable or not, under Trade Uni&gt;on Rules. If this is the case, the complaint of high medical charges does not appear to be justified. asked by Mr. Tilton to use my own car to save time and avoid de-lays and to charge the N|frrick Rate. No transport charge Motor Hire:- Remarks are not understood. Iwascx per patient is made.The arrangement is in M/S Gp^y Maekenziis favour. sol- M. L. /) . S^?eie. QUARANTINE MEDICAL OFFICER.27.4*47. Nigaristan. Called to see passenger with head injury. On arrival launch not ready - in meantime saw patients in another ship. Further delayed by altercation between G.M*s. clerk and Launch driver. Teken to ship and left. A.L.O. loaned me his launch to return to the wharf. Left 11 a.m. returned 3.30 p.m. 2.5.47 Friday. Summoned to attend Chief Officer British Admiral, acute abdominal pain. Lait 11 a.m. Met Gray Mackenzie^ car with 3rd Officer at Suk al Khamis- he only wanted some medicine for a 'tummy ache'. Chief Officer was not ill. * v 17.4.47. The Dalles. Urgent message. Case of strangulated Hernia. On boarding ship patient seen sitting up having his breakfast. No strangulated hernia. 26.5.47. Archer Hope. Wanted doctor at 8 a.m. reed, memo, at 9.30 a.m. Proceeded Sitra 10 arrived 10.20 a.m. Ship never came in but proceeded direct to Has Tanura. 22.12.46 British Cavalier. Received message to attend sick at Sitra. On arrival informed by Captain dentist required not Doctor. XPORT INFORMATION BOOKLET. Information for owners, charterers and masters of Vessels proceeding to Bahrain Oil Terminal, to load, bunker, or discharge freight: No*II . Emergency Hospital cases will be treated as such and will be handled by the Ships’ agent or by Company facilities whichever is first available. Under normal conditions, however, the Ships’ agent should handle all personnel from ships other than Company's Vessels . Captain Anderson informs me that ordinary sick of The Company’s Vessels must now be dealt with by the Agents.HEAD OFFICE t 122 LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON, E. C. 3 . TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED : BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., I^td. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSREH. BUNDER-ABBAS AMARAH. LINGAH. KUT. BAHREIN. KHORAMSHAHR. KOWE 1 T. AHWAZ. DUBAI. BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR. SHARJAH. BUSH IRE. MUSCAT. RAS TANURA. EL KHOBAR. Bahrein,June 7 th, 47 , JL NO —Tanks/ 7SQ. The Quarantine Medical Officer Bahrein, Dear Sir, S, S.' GBRVAIS 11 . We have received a telegram from the Master of the above vessel that xfes: he expected to arrive at Sitra at 11-0 A,Mi. on 8 th Hune 47 ans has requested Doctor on arrival possible case of Appendicitis, We shall be pleased if you kindly boardthe vessel on her arrival at Sitra, JDG 0 lours faithfully For Gray Mack^izie &amp; Co^.Ltd, n • I S ‘ Wo J L,wt‘ ( 10 ^ 0JnU.oU{ I, / . b 9t^ii n , u, i-PM. . 0^t Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND; BRANCHES: 122, LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENE Y S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAH R Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LI NG AH BAHREIN KOWEIT DU BAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no TANKS/716 BAHREIN^... 26th. May., 19 46 THE QUARANTINE MEDICAL OFFICER, BAHREIN URGENT Dear Sir, sSEARCHER HOPE” The above vessel is due to arrive at Sitra at 0800 local time today* The Master has on board a sickman having a violent head she is bound for Ras Tanura after landing the sickman. fr *~^-%***K S / 0 ‘2 C* j pain, stiff neck glands and prostrate gland trouble. We should be / /j ^ obliged if you would arrange to proceed to the vessel immediately as UfA- u. u/ify (O-'PO Yours faithfully, FOR GRAY MACKENZIE &amp; CO.LTD P.S. We have just received a radio from the Master of the ss”FIVE FORKS” requesting doctor to board the vessel on arrival. The ss”FIVE FORKS” is due to arrive at Sitra at AM today. hjA ' 10 ' ^ - 1 ’ ImIa ‘ J tUJ^'No.^lo^-2/1. \0 C ^ Political Agency, Bahrain The 2 ^th of June, 1947. To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, ' please refer to the correspondence ending with your letter No. L/127, dated the 27th April, 1947. regarding the duties of the Quarantine Medical Officer here. 2. It is understood that pratique for vessels at Sitra is given through your staff as the present quarantine staff is not large enough to detail a medical officer for this duty, in order to remedy, as far as possible, the defects in such a system, it seems necessary to make and adhere to the rule that the Quarantine Medical Officer should be informed and dispose of all cases of illness occurring in vessels - at Sitra, at any rate. This represents the minimum control he can exercise in order to prevent the importation of infectious diseases into Bahrain. in these circumstances, all cases of illness in vessels at Sitra should at least be reported to the Quarantine Medical officer even if it is necessary in particular cases to employ other medical attendance. 3. in view of the change in the value of money, the distance to Sitra, calls at short notice, delays caused by sick not being ready, launches not being immediately available, and difficulties in boarding vessels occasionally in mid-stream, the Quarantine Medical Officer represents that his charges are not excessive; and it would seem that he has made out a very strong case to support this. 4. He states that your remarks regarding transport per patient' 1 are not understood since no such transport charge is made and he was asked by your Mr. Tilton to use his own car to save time and to charge the ordinary rate. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain..0*1698-4/2. To 1W\ PERSIAN GULF IiESIDEICY, BAHRiilN. The 31st July, 1947. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Ijuscat. The Political Agent, Kuwait.- MEivUILiBDUL, No.- Iraqi Government have imposed cholera restrictions a.gainst ail travellers by air and sea from Bombay and district. They must have official certificates of double inoculation against cholera issued not less than five days and not more than six months before arrival in Iraq. Secretary to the Political hesident in.the Persian GulfMuse a 1948 5 t, n!! lng ^- s , f e P etitl0 ^ of Quarantine Medical Officer to the CM J et n! er NO. 134-18/3, dated the 28th February to the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. Y 5 9 from Karachi r the V fnf/ e?0rted £ our cases Smallpox imported sea ports? snowing restrictions are placed on these session P o? S ? n ! erS - fr f 1 Karaoh l an &lt;3 Gwadur must be in pos- having been done'rantfth Cer t ;:Lf J cate showing vaccination as under^three y?ars than Prior to embarkation and Ouarantrte 8 ^???? 3 cates will be placed in ^ W ft&gt;b) No.735-4/19 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 15th March, 1948. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to - 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 World H?a°th : U? 6 1 loloHigenqe Station, mu Organisation, Cathay Building, Singapore Ihe Political Agent, Bahrain ' x e The Political Agent, Kuwait Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain The The The The Quarantine Medical Officer’ Kuwait Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah Quarantine Medical Officer. Dubai fhp S S^ ! i G fw y A Mackenzie &amp; Co./Ltd., Bahrain. S ?* t:L h Overseas Airways, Corporation, .Bahrain. Tne Bahrain Petroleum Company, Ltd., Awali 10 Concessions Ltd., Bahrain. ,P ie Staff Officer (Intelligence) Bahrain W* rlu m r ataff Liaison Officer, Bahrain. 15' ThePub!?KL G ??hU 1? ? ealth Services (India), Mew Delhi io. ihe Public Health Commissioner, Govt, of Pakistan Karachi. ? for Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Persian Gulf. 1 h bNO, 1451*4/19 * To PERSIAE GULF RESIDE^, BAHRAIN, 29th May, 1948• The Director, United Nations World Health Tn?^i? Gti ? n, oJ n ^ rlm Comin ission, Epilocilological ^ ^ lligence Station, 8, Oxley Rise, Singapore* % The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait. »nsf political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Tne Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrlin. The quarantine Medical Officer, Kuv/ait. The Quarantine Medical Officer! Dubai 0 Messrs, Gray, Mackenzie £ Co.^Ltd., Bahrain The g v ? rs ® as Airways Corporation, Bahrain. Dfi lra n n Pe ^ roleum Company Limited, Awali. e?^2^ eujn Concessions Limited, Bahrain. ThI Alr f Steff 1 i C iaiion t ofL leenCe), v, Kaval Base » Jufai r. mu htaif Liaison Officer, Bahrain# Tht piblie 0 He»i?h r pn’ ?‘ ea } th Services (India), New Delhi, in Public dealth Commissioner, Government of Pakistan, Karachi, i'.EA-.OHAl'.Pur:. CORHIGENDUK. s f ° Reference this Office endorsement No.735-4/19 of March 15th, £Sr tt fi ra ph.S 2 &amp;. 2,j For 'SIX DAYS' read 'FOURTEEN DAYS'. if (W,J.MOODY), CHIEE QUARANTINE MEDICAL OFFICER.NO. 1806-4/19 PERSIAN GULP RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, July* 1948. N V The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Officer, Trucial Coast Sharjah. MEMORANDUM The following is a copy of letter No. CL No.8 Ref. 74 o^-1st June, 1948, from the Director of the Epidemiological Intelligence Station, World Health Organisa tion, Singapore:- tt To enable this station to give maximum service to Health Administrations with regard to epidemi ological state of various countries ahd the many factors influencing the prevalence and dispersion of communicable diseases, it is requested that fullest particulars of the subjects mentioned below may kindly be supplied 1. Migration - Immigration and Emigration. 2. Pilgrimages, Pilgrims and pilgrim Ships and prophylactic measures adopted both when leaving and when returning to their own countries. 3. Meteorological reports monthly data will suffice. Where monthly reports are not available, weekly or daily reports may be supplied”. 2. Would you please let me have any information you can on items 1 and 2. With regard to item 3, I would be grateful if a copy of each meteorological return^ sent to Karachi could be sent also to me. CHIEF QUARANTINE MEDICAL OFFICER.No.666.1350 BRITISH AGENCY, SHARJAH. The 26th July, 1948 * 1806-4/1' ^Reference your Circular dated the 7th July, 1948. Memorandum No. 2. follows: The information requred by you is as i. MIGRATION. (a) Immigration: xhere is no noticeable immigration to the Trucial Coast besides casual visitors and regular traders from the Arab States in the Guif, India, Pakistan and Persian Ports, whose business carries them to and fro. (b) Emigration: xheie has during the past two years been an exodus of emigration from the Trucial Coast to the neighbouring Arab States m the Gulf such as Kuwait, Bahrain, Qatar and Saudi Arabia. Emigra‘ion still goes on but on smaller scale and is due to unemployment. 2. PILGRIMAGES. (a) Pilgrims fromthe Trucial Coast to Mecca: These ordinarily make the journey by sea to Bahrain and thence to the Saudi Port of AlKhobar and from there by land to the jejaz. Some travel by B.I. ships to India c-nd thence to Jedda. Very few go via Kuwait. (b) Pilgrims to Iraq: They travel by ship to Basrah and return by the same jeans. There are no special pilgrim ships nor does there exist any prophylactic measures when leaving and returning. Pilgrims are, however, vaccinated against smallpox prior to departure, 3. METECRGLCGICA I,. The Observer-in-Charge, Pilot Balloon Observatory, Sharjah, states that it is not possible to supply copies of all the meteorological returns sent to Karachi but expressed his willingness to supply the information if he could be informed of the nature of data required by you. Copy to:POLITICAL AGENCY, , , A BAHRAIN, No. 3296-22^3=’' The 9th August 1948, ' Q) i t o The undermentioned documents are forwarded in original tos The Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain, y for^perusal and return#, with reference to his Memorandum No.1806-4/19 dated the 7th July 1948. Replies to remaining queries will follow. 7c 5- f° 7 For PollticaPAgent, Bahrain. Enclosure . Meteorological data from 1st July 1947 to 30th April, 1948. NNRNo.K-255-2/1 To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 28th August 1948• The Chief Quarantine iledical Officer, The Residency, Bahrai n,, mmmwdi 0 ^ S' 1 In continuation of ay endorse ;ent No*3296-2/7 dated the 9th August, 1948. 2. The following is the information required by you, vide your memorandum No.1806-4/19, dated the 7th July 1948 :- I. MIGRATION . Immigrants to Bahrain fall into two grouos. Group (a) are those who come to Bahrain in search of employment and these are mainly from India and Pakistan with a small percentage from the Gulf Arao States. Group (b) consists of those who come to Bahrain on visits to their relatives and/or for business purposes and these are mainly from Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Persia and from the Persian Gulf Arab States. There is, however, a snail number of im dgrants from the United Kingdom,the United States of America, and Canada, who come tc* Bahrain for service with the Petroleum Companies and other firms In Bahrain. (2) iiaigTatlom The number of emigrants from Bahrain is comparatively small; it consists mainly of those who go to Saudi Arabia to seek employment with Arabian American Oil Company. Apart from this, there is fairly a large number of small merchants who frequently travel to India and Pakistan on commercial business. II. PILGRI .iAQES : Pilgrims visiting iocca travel usually by steamers to Karachi from where they catch pilgrim ships to Jedda. Some of them, however, go by ulane via Khobar and still some by road through Kuwait. Pilgrims chosing the last route are nowadays rare. On the other hand we- 2 - have pilgrims who visit the holy shrines in Iraq and Iran, and these travel by British India Ships direct to Basrah or Iran. All pilgrims and others leaving Bahrain by steamer or aircraft receive the requisite vaccina tion innocillations* These few who still use dhows, are probably never inoculated or vaccinated, but their number is lessening yearly. FOB POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN. MR'V ( 13 / 55 / 50 ) BRITISH RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. 25th April, 1950. Dear Agency, Please refer to Chapter XXIy(Health) Foreign Service Instructions regarding the notification of infectious diseases to the Ministry of Health. 2* We enclose a copy of Dr. Moody 1 s letter to the Foreign Office and the Ministry of Health , s reply. 3« Although the Ministry of Health still require notification of certain disease it is .nqted that this may be made by air mail .^instead,, of by telegram. 3 3 APR 50 O &gt;V The Political Agent, Bahrain.Copy of a latter from the Ministry of Health, ddressed to the Under Secretary of State, London 5C/93222/1/36 ministry of Health, Whitehall, London, S.W # 1 # 31st March, 1950. Sir, I as directed by the Minister of Health to refer to your letter of 28th February and to say thrt although infornation as to outbreaks of infectiou disease in the Persian Gulf ar^as named in your letter is sent to and broadcast by the Epidemiological Intelligence station of the World Healjrh Organisation at Singapore, the Minister nevertheless attaches much value and importanve to the individual Consular reports sent to him in accordance with Chapter 24 of the Foreign Service Instructions and he requests i that they may continue to be sent as and when 1 ap’ropriate• Except 'or exceptional outbreaks, bowevt I they could be sent by air mail. I am, Sir, Your oboaient Servant, Signed ?? The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Downing Street, Lormcw, s.w.l.Addr # «.5 tn^hl J 3t ? ^ bruar y the Residnecy /Q t0 the Librarianl ioreif'n Office, London. ■ (13/23/50) Political Residency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 13th February, 1950. Sanitary/ Dear Librarian, (Health ■) of roo!if? S ? r * fer 4 .! ;o P ara C ra Ph 1 of Chapter XXII f Go '® r8 f ^tlons for His ffejestvfs : orelrn Service, repaMinE the notification of Infectious diseases. . . The Persian Gulf area is, for the purposes of !« 0n diseases and quarantine S?r*?fr 1 —, ar « a covered by the Eplde-iolorlcal Slnpapore ' 00 ' /tatIon of ths ’ rrl(1 Health Orp nisaticn in §Iy.=i.,o o„if o A11 . 'Ptiflcations from those areas in the f ? 1 ’ w! ’‘°f 0 Quarantine arranpements His Majesty's Governn»rt is in part responsible, viz Kuwait, BahraiS, ‘ft® r Zv and iruclal c °ast and iuscat, are made*in accordance with the recommendation of the International Sanitary * ^cnyention 1944 , and the International/Convention for Aerial Navigation 1--44, except of course that the World Health -rranir tion has since replaced U.K.R.R.A, fiotifications ••ire ncraially sent to the Spldebiological Intallipencs .^f tlor Singapore and are published by them weekly and, ? where necessary, rent out by telegram or broadcast by radio. t’ , , 1 would be grateful if you could ascertain uff, ° f ? 9albh » whether, in view of the above tm r “ q i llre consular Officers of the areas of d i paragraph 3 above to notify them direct of the utbreak of any of „he infectious diseases concerned. f * &lt;1 , .. ,**11 ** ' : r Co paragraph 18 of the same qb 3 ‘-|i? r * Art iole 16 of the International Sanitary Convention Conv^tiOT S or 1 1944 ^ 9n a!! ’ end9d by th * international Sanitary Yours sver, SD/- w.J.Moody Medical Adviser to H.K. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The Librarian, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.( 8 th May, 1950. L.A.G.Pinhey, Esq., 0. B. E., Assistant Political A^e Bahrain. With the compliments of the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrain. With reference to paragraph 1 of Chapter XXIV (Health) of general instructions for His Majesty's Foreign Service. (i ' n ; H 3(ftegfca. Air Mail) w Ho. 1532» 2/1* Dear Ministry, © POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 13th May, I960. In his weekly Health statement for sJr the Meek ended 15th ..vpril 1950 the Medical Officer, Bahrain, has notified this Agency of,the occurrence of a stray small-pox case which is hereby reported for your information in accordance with Para 1 of Chapter XXIV of General Instructions for His Majesty's Foreign Service. Further developments, if any, will be notified to you in due course. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency. The Ministry of Health, Whitehall, London, S.W.l.-2/1 POLITICAL AGKLCT, BAHRAIN. 13th Kay, 1950. Dear Col.Moody, ird herev/ith copy of our letter No.1532-2/1 dated 13th May 1950 sent to the Ministry of Health for your information. 2. It is considered that the information furnished by the SteUL Medical Officer in his weekly Health Statement is inadequate and this should be followed by a letter whether his diagnosis is confirmed or disproved as the result of his further observation as required in Para 1 of Chapter XXIV. I think he should also inform us later direct or through you whether such infectious disease case/s was/were cured or proved fatal for completion of our records or to enable us to answer Health Ministry*s inquiry if one is received. Lieut.Col.W.J.Moody, Medical Adviser to His Excellency the Political Resident, Yours sincerely, Bahraintnt: 3S.^eL Ut, V, The Political Agent, Bahrai n y © With the compliments of the Chief Quarantine Medical Officer, with reference to para 1 Chapter XXIV of General Instructions for His Majesty's Foreign Service./Vo.* / ^ 0 I &gt; i This correspondence has been passed on to me by the Chief 'Quarantine Medical Officer. We consider that the information supplied by the State Medical Officer is adequated in that 1) The cases reported may be considered as confirmed. 2) The cases may also be considered cured unless reported otherwise under the deaths column. Should any further information be required by the Health Ministry which I consider unlikely, we can deal with it further then. &gt; «-^4 ^4 o Qm5-2/1- POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 13th May, 1950. ^ H-rX- 1 £ I forward herev/ith copy of our letter No.1532-2/1 dated 13th May 1950 sent to the Ministry of Health for your information. 2. It is considered that the information furnished by the StcJZ Medical Officer in his weekly Health statement is inadequate and this should be followed by a letter whether his diagnosis is confirmed or disproved as the result of his further observation as required in Para 1 of Chapter XXIV. I think he should also inform us later direct or through you whether such infectious disease case/s was/were cured or proved fatal for completion of our records or to enable us to answer Health Ministry’s inquiry if one is received. Lieut. Col. Y/.J. Moody, Medical Adviser to His Excellency the Political Q U Bahrain.© (ftegta. Air Mail) Ho.1632»2/1* POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. 13th May, 1950. Dear Ministry, In his weekly Health statement for cL 1- the week ended 15th April 1950 the £m£ov Medical Officer, Bahrain, has notified this Agency of the occurrence of a stray small-pox case which is hereby reported for your information in accordance with Para 1 of Chapter XXIV of General Instructions for His Majesty's Foreign Service. Further developments, if any, will be notified to you in due course. Yours ever, Bahrain Agency \ The Ministry of Health vVhitehull, London, S.V/.l</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000281_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1050</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000281</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1050</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/1 Epidemics (in Bahrain): Cholera, Smallpox etc &amp; quarantine restrictions'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-14T09:59:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (209 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the file are arranged in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 211; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-156; these numbers are written in a combination of pencil and ink, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Political Agent at Kuwait, the Government of India, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Adviser to the Government at Bahrain, the Medical Department of the Government of Bahrain, the Residency Surgeon &amp; Chief Quarantine Medical Officer for the Arab Coast at Bushire, the American Consulate at Basra, and British Overseas Airways Corporation.The main subjects are:episodes of smallpox in Abadan, Bushire, Khorramshahr, and other places in the Gulf;cases of typhus in Abadan, and reports of the number of cases of the disease recorded in Bahrain in 1943 and 1944;yellow fever vaccines supply and lists of vaccinations given in Bahrain;quarantine regulations;suspected case of cerebrospinal fever;weekly health statements for Bahrain in 1950.The file also contain letters from Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co, requesting all passengers to produce smallpox vaccination certificates before leaving Bahrain; and a report from Arabian American Oil Company regarding a case of infantile paralysis in Dhahran.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Consulate, Basra</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Typhus</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Bahrain, Medical Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Overseas Airways Corporation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Residency Surgeon, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Khorramshahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dhahran</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bushire</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abadan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Cholera</topic></subject><subject><topic>Disease control</topic></subject><subject><topic>Smallpox</topic></subject><subject><topic>Vaccination</topic></subject><subject><topic>Inoculation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000281#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>