<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000385_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T14:21:32.126Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">3.0. No. C/%£- the 23vd Mbvember lb 33 I forward herewith for your Information radin^ v/ith the line ;* Negulatlonc ieouod under the Persian Gulf btates (Mner ;ency) Order in Council 1030, amended in pencil, together with copies of Trad!np v/ith the ixemy (Specified Persons) Orders 1939, Nog. 1166 and 1333, and also a notice issued from this Agency. hese copies of the icpulations and Orders are the only copies we possess and I should be pratefhl if you would return them to no sometime on Saturday, the 35th# Copies # f the Bo v ' of Trade Orders have been sent to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government and these nay have been p.asced on to you# Grenier, 3sq#, Director of Customs : P ort Officer, yours sincere .alirain.Confidential* GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Dbpartmint, /? / EXPRESS LETTER r x y. S—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it hud been so despatched,] office of the iolitical ueuident in the Aereian Gulf* From Political ntaident* at Kuv&amp;it* 0 * T© . the Political ^gent* Kuwait* The Political ^gent* Bahrain* V The Political ^gent* Kuscat* No. 0/750 of 1939 . Daud l 6th SoTember, 1339. uubj eot » Trading with the Enemy Hegulatione. a copy of the Trading with the Enemy Regulations,dated the 16th Boveiaber 1939, made under the Persian Gulf States (-.ei-gencyi) order in Council 1939, ie forwarded herewith for publication. 2. Copy of the Trading with the Enemy ^ot, 1939, to ..hi-h the degulatione refer, wae forwarded to you under India Office Printed Letter Ho .P. 2.8450/1939, dated the 12th September 1939. 3. At the same time as the Regulations are published you should exhibit the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) Order, 1C 39, p| dated iSth September 1939, made by the Board of Trade (copy forwarded I to you under India Office Printed Letter ' o.P. 2 . 6108 /1939, dated 3rd October 1939). Any orders similarly issued by the Board of Trade or the Treaeury should be exhibited by you on receipt* s. 6. MFP —1206 S&amp;P—(M- 1723 )— 4 - 2 - 30 — 200,000 / «.7 - 2 - 4 , To Kuwait and Bahrain only * The liet of firme epeoified in the Schedule to the Specified lereons Order should be communicated to the duler of Kuwait Hule’fe of Bahrain, ^atar and the Trucial /Statee with a request that they will forbid under penalty of severe punishment all persons under their jurisdiction from having any commercial^ financial or other intercourse or dealings with the firms specified* Any additions to the list that may be made from time to time should be communicated to the hulers* 5 * To Muscat only * A similar request should be made to the Multan of Kuscat after the question of the *ar bubeidy and other assistance to the sultan h«i 8 been settled* sd. C.G.J^rior* Political Heeident in the Persian Gulf. Attested* fotf secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf• \ \Q in its to ti.fi territories*- (a) For olaoafis ia) wui (b) of Ufiotion i ;i)» subatitutfii •to puniahi'jciit with istprloon^ent of either de ear lo tion for a tern not exceeding seven years or with a fine not exceeding as«&amp; 0»000 or with both*# (b) In olause U) of the pr;vis# to tteotion i U) for •a secretary of atate* the Treasury or the lioard of Trade* substitute *the ToXitioaX Resident*• (c) For Section x (4} substitute *A prosecution for an of fii.ee of trading with the ene^y shaXX not be liiStltuted within the territories except by, or with the consent f, the Political resident or, within their respective spheres of jurisdiction, the roXltloaX ..gents at Kuwait, Bahrain or Muscat*# (d) In section 2 ( 2 ) add at the end *s provided always that no such order shall cose into force in any of the territories until it has been published therein by exhibition in the office of the lolitioal Aftat** think* substitute *The iditical Kesldent, if he thinks*• In section 3 (a) for “Board of Trade* substitute ^olitioal xtesldent* and subsequently for M the Board* where these words occur substitute *he*# IgJ Xn beetIon 3 id} omit the oords *on summary conviction* and for “fifty pounds* substitute •^•#730*# After the word “imprisonment* where it first ocours add the words *of either description*# (e) in beotion 5 (l)» for “he Board of Trade, if they / (n)*3* ■H (b) In lection 3 (4) # for oXau«€» (a) and (b) aubatitute *»to panlabment with laprlaonacnt of either deaorip* tlon for a term not exceeding fire years or with a fine not exceeding *«•25,000 or aitb botb** li) In ejection 4 (i), for , •T^eaaur&gt; ,, ehererer the word occurs, eubetitute *^olitlo&amp;X resident (J) In ueetlon 4 U} for “Hi^h Jourt or 3ourt of «itaeion ,, eubatitute 'Court of the lolitloal lieaident or of the PoXitloaX /igent of that yart of the territories in which he resides or carries on business** (fc) Cmit Section 5, ( 1 ) In Section 6 (2) add at the end **provided aXways that no such order shall co:.ie into foroe in my of the territories untiX it has been pubXiehed therein by exhibition in the of lice oi the ■« oXltical Agent** (a) Jn Section 7 UU fer *the Board of Trade eiay appoint custodians of ene^y property for ngland, Scotland and Northern Ireland res c eotlvely H substitute 'the iolitieal nesident vmy appoint custodians of encay property for the territories* and for 'Board of Trade 4 where the words subsequently occur, substitute 'Political, rissldent'* In) In Section 7 (5), omit the words 'on sum ary oonrlotion' and for 'one hundred pounds* substitute 'ks,!, 500% After the word *inipri*onRjent* whers it first occurs insert the words *of either description', (o) In Beetion 7 ( 6 ), emit the words 'on summary e-nrletioa* and for 'ten pounds' substitute 'us«l&amp;C% (p) In Section 7 (7), for 'the xohequer of the United / Kingdom// (g) •4* Kingdom* »ub®titute *the public aooount, juid ghall be applied in such manner as the Governor- General of India may direct** (&lt;i) For lection 7 (a) (b) substitute # the expression ’property^ means moveable end imisoveable property of every description and includes any estate or interest in moveable or immoveable property! any negotiable instrument* debt or other chose in notion* and any other right or interest whether in possession ;r not! and* (r) Omit Section 6 * (s) In ^eotlon 9 (i} omit the words *on smwiary ootivlctlon* and for *one hundred pounds* substitute After the word *lftprieon&amp;ent« where it first occurs insert the words *of either deeorip- tlon** (t) in section 9 (2)* omit the worde *on summary conviction* and for 'fifty pounds' substitute •lie* 750** (ti) in section u U)» tor •Board of Trade* eubatltute 'iolitical * k eeident' and for 'larliament* substitute *the Goveinment of 2niia*» (v) For lection 11 (2) substitute *ahythini£ required or authorised under this ,.ot to be done by* to or before the lolitlcal Aeeident may be done by* to or before any person authorised by him in that (w) I'or Section 12 substitute 'Any document stating that any authority or sanction is given under aap of the provisions of this - 4 ct by the iolltioul Aesident or by any Political Agent* and purporting to be signed / byby or on behalf of the *olltlo*l uoollent or Political i^entt oholl be evldenoe of the faoto stated In the document** (x) Omit section 13* (y) rwit lection 14* (z) Offllt Section 13 (3}* (aa) Section 1? (3) and the Schedule* 3 * The provielcme of iart III of the ruw&amp;it Order in Oouncllt 1933* the ^iahrain Order In Counoll 9 l9l«5 f the %atar order In Joun^ il f 1939 , and the 'uooat ^rder In Souncil, 1939 , relating to ori»lnal mats era shall apply In so far as they sway be aypli^uble, in relation to offences under this * 4* The offetiues under this 40t shall be oo^ilsable and i oil tic 1 resident in the Persian Ottlf. Kuwait mted the 36th 1 oreasber, 1939*The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf presents his complinn^ts to Politicsl Agent, Bahrain# complim^tfc 1 * 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. 3# His Majesty*s Secretary of state for India, London. 4. fhe Secretary to the Government of India, External Affaire Department, New Delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). /« '“N v/ ^ P ; r • 1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, KUWAIT. Dated .,16th N9. v cffibe r 1939 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Order No.752 dated the 16th November 1939 under Section 8 (2) of Defence Regulations No.l of 1939. muOffice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, KUWAIT. Ho. C/752 Bated the 16th November 1939. QRDiSR The powers of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf under Section 8 (l) of Defence Regulations No.l of 1939 made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, are, under Section 8 (2) of the said Regulation , hereby delegated to the Political Agents at Bahrain and Muscat for exercise within tne limits of the Bahrain Order in Council, 1913, and the Muscat Order in Council, 1939, respectively. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. Whitehall, London, S.W. 1 . 5255No. C/735-1.a/43 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th November 1939 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, b i, a a ;; i a Memorandum In continuation of my memorandum No. C/756-1.a/43 dated the 20th November 1939 I forward herewith 12 copies of Trading with the Enemy Specified Persons Order No. 1166 which may kindly be distributed amongst prominent merchants in Bahrain. I am sending copies to the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Petroleum Concessions limited, Director of Customs, Gray Mackenzie, etc, 2. I also forward one copy of Trading with the Enemy Specified Persons Order No. 1537 for your information. Further copies for distribution will be sent to you as soon as they are received and it is requested that the Director of Customs may be shown this new Order as soon as possible. for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. C/786-1, a/43 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— 1. The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain,(2 copies) 2» Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Company 1*1 mi ted, Bahrain* (1 copy) 3. Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. (1 copy) and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) for information. 2. Further Orders issued by the Board of Trade vlil be forwarded as soon as received. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated.. 30th November 1939. Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Notice dated the 21st November 1939 Issued by the Political Agent, Bahrain. • Trading with the hnemy Specified Persons Order No. 1166. 2 TEADiftS WITH THJb ENEMYr * I , W 4 ^ OVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). I z- M on ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] omo« of the i oiltleei heeideat No. ,. ^ in the ierelaa Gulf, ysv* tf •Dated 1 J£t T7 i,ihe at t.HWAK ./9 59* ^e^eated Hie Majesty'e aeeretary of i,tote for India, London* The deoret&amp;ry to the Goremnent of India, External /iffairs )e partnert, dlf olhi* The iolitloal ^eut 9 Kuwait* oim«*al A*M«. Bahrain The ^olltloal daent, Muaoat* ubjeot ; The Trading vlth the Mne^y (.•^eelfled lereone)(^endnent) (ro*2) order, IP&amp;% dated KoTember let,1939, Hade by the loard of Trade* Kefereaee ay dx^reee Letter Ho*d/749, dated the ieth Bore^ber 193-, and uonneoted oorreepondeuoe • 0* 1 have reeel ved from the India Of lice one eoy of the Order olted above, foroarded tinder undated ell|&gt; whloh doee not indicate ttiat oopiee have been sent to the * ell t leal Agents at Kuwait, Bahrain and 1 usoot, as 1 presume is trie ease* As such orders have to be exhibited by the iolltloal Agents with the least potelble delay’ 1 would be grateful if copies eould invariably be sent to them direct and the fast of each distribution be Indicated on the oo,y seut to me* sd* d*0*irlor* political Hosldent in the iersian Gulf* Attest ed* for ^o^.tarjr to tho mitlctol resident in the ierslaa Gulf, (signature) S/44. —nnr n 0| p ^ 1 ' ** (Designation)&lt; ? STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1681 EMERGENCY POWERS (DEFENCE) GENERAL REGULATIONS ORDER IN COUNCIL AMENDING THE DEFENCE REGULATIONS, 1939 LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2 ; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 26 York Street, Manchester 1; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller *939 Price bd. netA 2 4504 STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1681 EMERGENCY POWERS (DEFENCE) General Regulations Order in Council amending the Defence Regulations, 1939. At the Court at Buckingham Palace, the 23rd day of November, 1939. Present, The King's Most Excellent Majesty in Council. His Majesty, in pursuance of section one of the Emergency 2 &amp; 3 Powers (Defence) Act, I 939 &gt; an( i °f ah other powers enabling Geo. 6 111 that behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of his C- 62- lavy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows: — \ m Statutory Rules and Orders, 1939, No. 978, Articles 3 and 4 of Statutory Rules and Orders, 1939, No. 1416, Article 1 ot Statutory Rules and Orders, 1939, 'No. 1463, and para- graph (a) of Article 2 of Statutory Rules and Orders, 1939, No. 1500, are hereby revoked. 2 . The Defence Regulations, i939( a ), (hereinafter referred to as the principal Regulations ”), shall have effect as if there were made therein the amendments which by the following provisions of this Order are directed to be made in those Regulations. 3 . After Regulation one of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulation: — Interfer- -\ A No person shall— (a) do any act having reasonable cause to believe that it will be likely to prevent or interfere with the performance of their duties by per sons in His Majesty's service or the carry ing on of their work by persons engaged in the performance of essential services, or 0+ (6) do, in relation to any person whom he knows to be a person in His Majesty’s service or Note. Except for Articles i and 24. which are formal, this Order in Council reproduces the provisions contained in S.R. &amp;- O. 1939 No. 978 as amended — (a) by Orders in Council made before the making of this Order; and (b) by this Order. Amendments of each of these classes are distinguished by footnotes to the text. (a) S.R &amp; O. 1939 No. 927. ence with persons in His Majesty’s service, &amp;c.2 to be a person engaged in the performance of essential services, any act with intent thereby to render him incapable of effici ently performing his duties as such or, as the case may be, of efficiently carrying on his work as a person so engaged: Provided that a person shall not be guilty of an offence against this Regulation by reason only of his taking part in, or peacefully persuading any other person to take part in, a strike 4 . After Regulation two of tire principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — Assisting an Enemy and Sabotage. “Acts done 2 a. — (i) If, with intent to assist an enemy, arry with intent p erson does any act which is likely to assist an enerdfc an^nemy or to P re j udice the public safety, the defence of trre c ' realm or the efficient prosecution of war, then, with out prejudice to the law relating to treason, he shall be guilty of an offence against this Regulation and shall, on conviction on indictment, be liable to penal servi tude for life. (2) A court of quarter sessions shall not have juris diction to try any person upon an indictment charging him with an offence against this Regulation. “Sabotage. 2 b. — (1) No person shall do any act with intent to impair the efficiency or impede the working or move ment of any vessel, aircraft, vehicle, machinery, apparatus or other thing used or intended to be used in His Majesty’s service or in the performance of essential services, or to impair the usefulness of any works, structure or premises used or intended to be used as aforesaid: [ ! Provided that a person shall not be guilty of an offence against this Regulation by reason only of his taking part in, or peacefully persuading any other person to take part in, a strike], (2) The preceding provisions of this Regulation shall apply in relation to any omission on the part of a person to do anything which he is under a duty, either to the public or to any person, to do, as they apply in relation to the doing of any act by a person. (3) Any person convicted on indictment of an offence against this Regulation shall be liable to penal servitude for any term not exceeding fourteen years or [ x Words in brackets inserted by this Order.]A 3 4504 3 to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or to both such penal servitude and such fine. 12 Geo. 3. (4) The operation of the Dockyards, &amp;c., Protection c - 2 4 - Act, 1772, shall be suspended during the continuance in force of this Regulation”. 5. After Regulation five of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulation: — “inven- 6 .— (1) Where, either before or after the coming tions and into force of this Regulation, an application has been designs. made to the Comptroller General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks for the grant of a patent or the registration of a design, the Comptroller General, if satisfied, on the advice of a Secretary of State or the Admiralty, that it is expedient in the interests of the defence of the realm so to do, may, notwithstanding ^ anything in any Act, omit or delay the doing of any thing which he would otherwise be required to do in relation to the application, and give directions for pro hibiting or restricting the publication of informaton with respect to the subject matter of the application, or the communication of such information to particular persons or classes of persons. (2) No person shall, except under the authority of a written permit granted by, or on behalf of, the Comptroller General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks, make any application for the grant of a patent, or the registration of a design, in any foreign country. A Secretary of State may by order direct that a permit granted by such authority or person in any part of His Majesty’s dominions (other than the United Kingdom), or in any foreign country or terri tory in which His Majesty has jurisdiction, as may be specified in the order, shall be treated for the purpose of this paragraph as if it were a permit granted by the Comptroller General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks. ^ (3) A Secretary of State, the Admiralty or the Board of Trade, if it appears to him or them to be necessary or expedient in the interests of the defence of the realm or the efficient prosecution of war so to do, may give directions to any person requiring him to furnish to such authority or person as may be specified in the directions any such information in his posses sion relating to any invention, design or process as may be specified in the directions, or demanded of him by the said authority or person.4 (4) The right of a person to apply for, or obtain, a patent in respect of an invention or registration in respect of a design shall not be prejudiced by reason only of the fact that the invention or design has pre viously been communicated to a person in compliance with paragraph (3) of this Regulation, or used by a person in consequence of such communication, and a patent in respect of an invention, or the registration of a design, shall not be held to be invalid by reason only that the invention or design has been so communicated or used as aforesaid. (5) In connection with the making, use or exercise of any invention or design on behalf of, or for the services of, the Crown (whether by virtue of the 7 Edw. 7. Patents and Designs Act, 1907, or otherwise), a Secre- c - 29- tary of State or the Admiralty may authorise the use of any drawing, model, plan or other documenl^pr information in such manner as appears to the Secre tary of State or the Admiralty to be expedient in the interests of the defence of the realm or the efficient prosecution of war, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any licence or agreement; and any licence or agreement, if and so far as it confers on any person, otherwise than for the benefit of the Crown, a right to receive any payment in respect of the use of any document or information in pursuance of such an authorisation, shall be inoperative 6. After Regulation eighteen of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — ‘' Restnc- 18 a. —(i) The Secretary of State, if satisfied, with movements res P ect . to an Y particular person, that with a view to of preventing him acting in any manner prejudicial to the suspected public safety or the defence of the realm, it is neces- persons. sary so to do, may make an order for either or both of the following purposes, that is to say: — {a) for securing that, except in so far as he may be permitted by the order, or by such authority or person as may be specifiecWi the order, he shall not be in any such pllfce or area in the United Kingdom as may be so specified; {b) for requiring him to notify his movements, in such manner, at such times and to such authority or person as may be specified in the order. (2) If any person is in any place or area in contra vention of an order made under this Regulation, or5 fails to leave any place or area in accordance with the requirements of such an order, then, without pre judice to any proceedings which may be taken against him, he may be removed from that place or area by any constable or any person acting on behalf of His Majesty. L 1 ' Deten- 18 b. (i) If the Secretary of State has reasonable tion orders, cause to believe any person to be of hostile origin or associations or to have been recently concerned in acts prejudicial to the public safety or the defence of the realm or in the preparation or instigation of such acts and that by reason thereof it is necessary to exercise control over him, he may make an order against that person directing that he be detained. jAt against any person under this Regulation, the Secre tary of State may direct that the operation of the order be suspended subject to such conditions— (a) prohibiting or restricting the possession or use by that person of any specified articles; (b) imposing upon him such restrictions as may be specified in the direction in respect of his employment or business, and in respect of his association or communication with other persons; as the Secretary of State thinks fit; and the Secretary of State may revoke any such direction if he is satis fied that the person against whom the order was made has failed to observe any condition so imposed, or that the operation of the order can no longer remain suspended without detriment to the public safety or the defence of the realm. (3) For the purposes of this Regulation, there shall be one or more advisory committees consisting of per sons appointed by the Secretary of State; and any person aggrieved by the making of an order against * him, by a refusal of the Secretary of State to suspend the operation of such an order, by any condition attached to a direction given by the Secretary of State or by the revocation of any such direction, under the powers conferred by this Regulation, may make his objections to such a committee. (4) It shall be the duty of the Secretary of State to secure that any person against whom an order is made under this Regulation shall be afforded the (2) At any time after an order has been made A 4 43&lt;M P New Regulation substituted by this Order].¥ 6 earliest practicable opportunity of making to the Secretary of State representations in writing with respect thereto and that he shall be informed of his right, whether or not such representations are made, to make his objections to such an advisory committee as aforesaid. (5) Any meeting of an advisory committee held to consider such objections as aforesaid shall be presided over by a chairman nominated by the Secretary of State and it shall be the duty of the chairman to inform the objector of the grounds on which the order has been made against him and to furnish him with such particulars as are in the opinion of the chairman sufficient to enable him to present his case. (6) The Secretary ot State shall make a report to Parliament at least once in every month ascto the action taken under this Regulation (including*tfie number of persons detained under orders made there under) and as to the number of cases, if any, in which he has declined to follow the advice of any such advisory committee as aforesaid. (7) If any person fails to comply with a condition attached to a direction given by the Secretary of State under paragraph (2) of this Regulation that person shall, whether or not the direction is revoked in conse quence of the failure, be guilty of an offence against this Regulation. (8) Any person detained in pursuance of this Regu lation shall be deemed to be in lawful custody and shall be detained in such place as may be authorised by the Secretary of State and in accordance with instructions issued by him]. :^ar! n &amp;c S 18c -—C 1 ) No person shall— (a) knowingly assist a prisoner of war to escape from custody, or knowingly harbour an escaped prisoner of war; or (b) give an escaped prisoner of war any assjpt- ance with intent thereby to prevent, hirmer or interfere with the apprehension of the prisoner. (2) A Secretary of State may by order provide— (a) for regulating access to, and the conduct of persons in, places in the United Kingdom where prisoners of war are detained, and for prohibiting or regulating the dispatch or conveyance, from outside such places toor for prisoners of war therein, of any such articles as may be specified in the order; (b) for prescribing conditions to be observed in connection with the employment of, or the provision of board or lodging for, prisoners of war in the United Kingdom while else where than in places for the detention of prisoners of war. ( 3 ) The preceding provisions of this Regulation shall apply in relation to any person in respect of whom there is in force an order for his detention made either under this Part of these Regulations or in exer cise of tlie prerogative of the Crown, as those pro visions apply in relation to a prisoner of war. . (4) proceedings shall be taken, by virtue of this Regulation, against a person in respect of any act done by him when he is himself a prisoner of war. 52 Geo. 3. (5) The operation of the Prisoners of War (Escape) c - I 56 - Act, 1812, shall be suspended during the continuance in force of this Regulation '. 7 . After Regulation nineteen of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — “Changeof 20 .— (1) The following amendments shall be made Q n T' sec tion seven of the Aliens Restriction (Amendment) Get.^.Act, 1919 :- (a) for subsections (1) and (2) there shall be substituted the following subsections: — (1) No alien who is in the United Kingdom on the date of the coming into force of Regulation twenty of the Defence Regulations, 1939, shall, while in the United Kingdom at any time after that date, assume or use or purport to assume for any purpose any name other than that by which he was ordinarily known immediately before the said date. (2) Where, after the said date, any alien carries on or purports to carry on (whether alone or in association with any other person) any trade or business under any name or style other than that under which that trade or business was being carried on immediately before the said date, he shall, for the purposes of the preceding subsection, be deemed to. fnsmtTBni rt 8 be using a name other than that by which he was ordinarily known imme diately before the said date. (2a) In relation to any alien who, not having been in the United Kingdom on the said date, thereafter lands in the United Kingdom, subsections (i) and (2) of this section shall have effect as if for any reference in those subsections to the said date there were substituted a reference to the day on which he first lands in the United Kingdom after the said date ’; (6) subsection (4) shall have effect as if para graph (b) thereof were omitted. (2) No British subject who is in the United Kingdom ~egulaWto, * . , . ; :v on the date of the coming into force of this Regulat shall, while in the United Kingdom at any time after that date, assume or use or purport to assume for any purpose any name other than that by which he was ordinarily known immediately before the said date, unless, at least twenty-one days before the day on which he first assumes or uses or purports to assume that other name, he has caused to be pub lished in the London Gazette, the Edinburgh Gazette or the Belfast Gazette a notice specifying— (a) his existing name in full and the change which he proposes to make in it, and (b) the address of his place of residence or place of abode, if any, in the United Kingdom. (3) In relation to any British subject who, not having been in the United Kingdom on the date of the coming into force of this Regulation, thereafter lands in the United Kingdom, paragraph (2) of this Regulation shall have effect as if for any reference in that paragraph to the said date there were substituted a reference to the day on which he first lands in the United Kingdom after the said date. p* (4) Nothing in paragraph (2) of this Regulation shall apply in relation to— {a) the assumption or use of any name in pursu ance of a Royal Licence, (6) the assumption or use of any name in conse quence of the grant of, or succession to, any peerage, (c) the assumption or use by any married woman of her husband’s name, A(d) the carrying on of any business under any business name within the meaning of the 6 &amp; 7 Registration of Business Names Act, 1916, Geo. 5.c. 58. i n circumstances in which registration in connection with the carrying on of the business is either required by that Act or declared by any provision of that Act to be unnecessary, or {e) the assumption or use of any name in such circumstances as may be specified by order of the Secretary of State. (5) For the purposes of this Regulation and of section seven of the Aliens Restriction (Amendment) Act, 1919,— (а) the expression ‘ name ’ shall be construed as 4i including surname, and a name shall be deemed to be changed if the spelling thereof is altered; and (б) a person entering Northern Ireland by land shall be deemed thereby to land in the United Kingdom. “ Amend- Amendments of Official Secrets Acts. Official”* 20a - The amendments specified in the Schedule to Secrets these Regulations shall be made in the Official Secrets Acts. Acts, 1911 and 1920 8. After Regulation twenty-nine of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — “ Deaths occurring in conse quence of war oper ations. 26 Geo. 5 &amp; 1 Edw. 8. c. 50. 30 . (1) If, with respect to any dead body in any county borough or county district or in the district of a sanitary authority for the purposes of the Public Health (London) Act, 1936, there has been given by a person authorised by the Secretary of State to act under this Regulation a certificate that it is the body of a person who has died in consequence of war opera tions, then, notwithstanding anything in any Act, the council of the borough or district or the sanitary autho rity, as the case may be, shall, unless they are “satisfied that adequate arrangements have been otherwise made for the interment of the body, themselves cause the body to be interred in such churchyard, public burial ground or cemetery as they think “fit. Any expenses incurred for the purposes of this para graph by such a sanitary authority as aforesaid shall be defrayed as if they were expenses incurred under the Public Health (London) Act, 1936.10 16 &amp; 17 (2) Section one of the Births and Deaths Registra- Geo. 5.C.48. ti on Act, 1926 (which provides that the body of a deceased person shall not be disposed of without either the certificate of the registrar of deaths or an order of the coroner), shall not apply in relation to any dis posal of a dead body effected in pursuance of this Regulation. (3) No person who, apart from this Regulation, would be required to give any information concerning a death to a coroner shall be obliged so to give that information, if that person has reasonable cause to believe that the death occurred in consequence of war operations; and, except in any particular case in which the Secretary of State otherwise directs, a coroner shall not be obliged or authorised to take any action in relation to any death if he is satisfied tha^jjhe death occurred in consequence of war operations. (4) Ihe enactments relating to the registration of deaths shall have effect as if the information thereby required to be given to a registrar concerning the death of any person included, in a case where the informant has reasonable cause to believe that the death occurred in consequence of war operations, a statement that the death so occurred. (5) The enactments relating to the registration of deaths shall, in relation to any case in which a certificate that a dead body is the body of a person who has died in consequence of war operations is given by a person authorised by the Secretary of State to act under this Regulation, have effect as if the class of persons required by those enactments to give information con cerning the death to a registrar included the person by whom the certificate is given; and any duty imposed by the said enactments, as amended by this Regula tion, to give any information concerning the death to a registrar or to attend before the registrar and sign the register shall, in that case, be deemed to l#ve been discharged by the said person if, within the time limited for the giving of that information, he sends the certificate, together with so much of that informa tion as he has in his possession, to the registrar. (6) Where, upon information of a death given to a registrar in accordance with the enactments relating to the registration of deaths, as amended by this Regula tion, the registrar is satisfied that the death occurred in consequence of war operations, he shall, subject to any8 II such general or special directions as may be given by the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages for determining the manner in which a death so occurring is to be registered, register the death forth with in the manner directed by the said enactments. (7) In this Regulation the expression ‘ body ’ includes part of a body. (8) This Regulation shall, in its application to Scotland, have effect subject to the following modifica tions : — {a) for the reference to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages there shall be substituted a reference to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages in Scotland; (6) in paragraph (1) for references to a county borough and to a county district there shall be substituted respectively references to a burgh and to a county, and for the words from ‘ Any expenses ’ to the end of the paragraph there shall be substituted the words ‘ Any expenses incurred for the pur poses of this paragraph by a county or town council shall be defrayed in like (c) for paragraph (2) there shall be substituted the following paragraph: — ‘ (2) In any case in which a certificate that a dead body is the body of a person who has died in consequence of war operations is given by a person authorised by the Secretary of State to act under this Regulation, and in accordance with the enactments relating to the registration of deaths, as amended by this Regulation, there is given to the registrar any informa tion concemiiig. the 'death, which includes a statement that the death occurred in con sequence of war operations, the Registra- 60 &amp; 6r Viet. c. 38. manner as expenses under the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897 '; 17 &amp; 18 Viet. c. 80. tion of Births, Deaths and Marriages (Scotland) Act, 1854, shall have effect in relation to the death as if in section thirty- nine the words from ' and the registrar to the end of the section, and in section,Aia/ii qo T^ 3 M/i&gt;ia 70 D 5 &amp; 6 Geo.5.c.91. 1 Edw. 8 &amp; 1 Geo. 6. c. 30. (3) This Regulation shall, in its application to Scotland, have effect subject to the following modifica tions : — (a) for references to the Midwives Act, 1902, and to section three thereof shall be substituted references to the Mid wives (Scotland) Act, 1915; and to section five thereof; (6) for the reference to the Midwives Acts, 1902 to 1936, there shall be substituted a refer ence to the Mid wives (Scotland) Acts, 1915 and 1927, and the Maternity Services (Scotland) Act, 1937; (c) for the references to section one and to section five of the Mid wives Act, 1936, there shall be respectively substituted references to section one and to section four of th^ Maternity Services (Scotland) Act, 1937; (4) This Regulation shall not extend to Northern Ireland 10 . After Regulation thirty-six of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulation: — “ Curfew. 37. The Secretary of State may, as respects any area in the United Kingdom, by order direct that, subject to any exemptions for which provision may be made by the order, no person in that area shall, between such hours as may be specified in the order, be out of doors except under the authority of a written permit granted by such authority or person as may be speci fied in the order 11 . After Regulation thirty-nine of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — “Seducing 39a.— (i) No person shall— persons from duty [ (tf) endeavour to seduce from their duty persons and causing in His Majesty’s service or engaged under disaffection. an y public authority in the performance of functions in connection with the defence of the realm or the securing of the public® disaffection likely to lead to breaches of their duty, or] (b) with intent to contravene, or to aid, abet, counsel or procure a contravention of, sub- paragraph (a) of this paragraph, have in his possession or under his control any• 4 b, ( 3 °) 13 37 &amp; 38 section twenty-four of the Births and Deaths Registra- Vict. c. 88. t j on Act, 1874. (3) Any reference in this Regulation to a superin tendent registrar, an interim superintendent registrar or a registrar, shall be construed as a reference to a superintendent registrar, an interim superintendent registrar or a registrar, as the case may be, tor the purposes of the enactments relating to the registration of births and deaths. (4) This Regulation shall not extend to Scotland or to Northern Ireland ”. 9 . After Regulation thirty-two A of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulation: “Exemp- 33 . — (1) A local supervising authority within the tion of meaning of the Midwives Act, 1902, if it appears to jjertam that authority to be necessary so to do in order to from C Acts secure that the number of women who are available relating to in its area or any part thereof for attendance on women midwives, m childbirth, or as maternity nurses during childbirth 2 Edw. 7. or any time during the lying-in period as defined for c ‘ I ^' the purposes of subsection (1) of section one of the 20 Geo. s &amp; Midwives Act, 1936, is adequate for the needs of the 1 Edw. 8. area or that part thereof, as the case may be, may by c - 4°- an order made as respects the area or that part thereof exempt from the provisions of the Midwives Acts, 1902 to 1936, for such period and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the order, any such womeri who have surrendered their certificates under subsection (1) of section five of the Midwives Act, 1936, as may be named in the order. A woman named in any order under this paragraph which is for the time being in force shall, for the pur poses of subsection (1) of section one of the Midwives Act, 1936, be deemed to be a certified midwife. (2) Without prejudice to the power to attach con ditions to any exemption granted by an order under the preceding paragraph, it shall be a condition oi • such an exemption that every woman on whom the exemption is conferred shall comply with any rules tor the time being in force under section three of the Mid wives Act, 1902, regulating, supervising and restrict ing within due limits the practice of midwives, and it any woman named in such an order fails to comply with the said rules or to observe any other condition subject to which the exemption under the order is con ferred on her, the local supervising authority may revoke the order so far as it relates to her.forty-four the words from and if any dead body ' to the end of the section, were omitted '; (d) at the end of paragraph (6) the following words shall be added: — ‘ and no inquiry in regard to the death shall, unless the Lord Advocate otherwise 5 8 &amp; 5y directs, be held in pursuance of the Fatal Viet. c. 36. Accidents (Scotland) Act, 1895.’ (9) This Regulation shall, in its application to Northern Ireland, have effect subject to the following modifications: — (а) for the reference to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages, there shall be substituted a reference to the Registrar General for Northern Ireland; f| (б) in paragraph (1) for the references to a county borough or county district and to the coun cil of the borough or district there shall be substituted respectively references to the district of a sanitary authority within the meaning of the Public Health (Ireland) Act, 1878, and to the sanitary authority, and for the words from ‘ Any expenses ’ to the end of the paragraph there shall be substituted the words ‘ Any expenses in curred for the purposes of this paragraph by a sanitary authority shall be defrayed as expenses incurred by them in the execu tion of the Public Health (Ireland) Act, 1878, and in the case of a rural sanitary authority shall be general expenses 31 . —(1) If any superintendent registrar dies, ment °f resigns or otherwise ceases to hold his office, and there registrars n0 i n t er i m superintendent registrar, the clerk of the and deputy responsible council as defined by subsection (5) of sec- registrars tion twenty-two of the Local Government Act, 1929^ Of births shall, if required by the Registrar General of Births, and deaths. Deat ^ s an( j Marriages so to do, appoint an interim 19 &amp; 20 superintendent registrar. Geo. 5.c. 17. , (2) Every superintendent registrar or registrar shall, if required by the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages so to do, appoint an additional deputy or additional deputies approved by the Registrar General; and any person appointed under this para graph shall be deemed to be a deputy appointed under 41 &amp; 42 Viet. c. 52. “ Appoint-*5 document of such a nature that the dissemi nation of copies thereof among any such persons as aforesaid would constitute such a contravention. (2) A prosecution for an offence against this Regu lation shall not be instituted except by, or with the consent of, the Director of Public Prosecutions. Geo.^c. 46. (3) Section three of the Police Act, 1919, (which penalises the causing of disaffection among members ot any police force) shall have effect as if any refer ence in that section to members or a member of a police force included a reference— {a) to special constables, or a special constable, appointed under any of the provisions of the Special Constables Act, 1831, as amended by the Special Constables Acts, 1914 and 1923, or appointed under section one hundred and ninety-six of the Muni cipal Corporations Act, 1882, and [b) to members or a member of the police force of any railway, harbour or dock under taking. (4) This Regulation shall, in its application to Scot land, have effect subject to the following modifica tions : — {a) paragraph (2) shall not apply; and {b) for sub-paragraph (a) of paragraph (3) there shall be substituted the following sub- paragraph— (a) to special constables or a special constable appointed under the provisions of the Special Con stables (Scotland) Acts, 1892 to 1923, or any local Act, and \ (5) This Regulation shall, in its application to Northern Ireland, have effect as if— (a) for the reference to section three of the Police Act, 1919, there were substituted a refer ence to section three of the Constabulary and Police (Ireland) Act, 1919; and (b) for the reference to the enactments under which special constables are appointed there were substituted a reference to section eight of the Constabulary Act (Northern Ireland), 1922, and the enactments men tioned in that section 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 68, 1 &amp; 2 Will. 4. c. 41 * 45 &amp; 46 Viet. c. 50.i6 Propa- 39 b. — (i) No person shall— ganda. (а) endeavour ['by means ol any lalse statement, false document or false report] to influence public opinion (whether in the United Kingdom or elsewhere) in a manner likely to be prejudicial to the defence of the realm or the efficient prosecution of war, or (б) do any act, or have any article in his posses sion, with a view to making, or facilitating the making of, any such endeavour. A prosecution in respect of a contravention of this paragraph shall not be instituted in England or Northern Ireland except with the consent of the Attorney General, [ 2 and it shall be a defence to any prosecution in respect of a contravention of this paragraph to prove that the person by whom die contravention is alleged to have been committed *ad reasonable cause to believe that the statement, document or report in question was true]. [ 3 (2) If at any time the Secretary of State is satisfied that it is necessary to prevent or restrict the publica tion in the United Kingdom of matters of which the publication or unrestricted publication, as the case may be, would or might, in his opinion, be prejudicial to the relations between the United Kingdom and any country outside the United Kingdom, or to any trans actions in process of being effected, or proposed to be effected, between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and persons in any other country, he may by order bring this paragraph into operation, and while'this paragraph is in operation the Secretary of State may give such directions as appear to him necessary or expedient for the purpose of prohibiting the publication of any such matters as aforesaid speci fied in the directions except with the permission of such authority or person as may be so specified and subject to any conditions which may be imposed by that authority or person]. 3 2 &amp; 33 (3) Notwithstanding anything in the Newspapcfs, Viet. c. 24. Printers and Reading Rooms Repeal Act, 1869pro ceedings in respect of any offence under the provisions of the Act 2 and 3 Viet. c. 12, set out in the Second Schedule to the said Act of 1869 may , in England,^be p Words in brackets substituted for “ whether orally or othenvise ” by this Order]. [ 2 Words in brackets added by this Order], f 3 New paragraph substituted by this Order]. [* Former paragraph (3) omitted].'display of flags, &amp;c i^tituted by any constable or by, or with the consent ot, the Director of Public Prosecutions. (4) In this Regulation— (а) the expression ‘ public opinion ’ includes the opinion of any section of the public; (б) the expression publication means, in rela tion to a cinematograph film, the exhibi- of the film to the public, and includes the mechanical or electrical reproduction of any sounds in connection with the exhibi tion of the film as aforesaid; and (c) the expression ' cinematograph film ' includes a sound track and any other article on which sounds have been recorded for the purpose of their being reproduced in con nection with the exhibition of such a film. , } he Secretary of State may by order prohibit the display by any person in public of any flag, banner or embiem as to which the Secretary of State is satis fied that the display thereof as aforesaid would be likely to cause a disturbance of the public order or to promote disaffection, and any such order may be made so as to apply either generally or to a specified drilling** 11 n^ D 'f /n n- r0ce f c *’ n ®| for an °ff ence against the 60 Geo! 3 &amp; Unlawful Dnllmg Act, 1819, may, with the consent of 1 Geo. 4. j-f* c Director of I ubhc Prosecutions, be taken under c . 1. the Summary Jurisdiction Acts, and the penalties to which a person shall be liable on summary conviction ot such an offence shall be imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or both such imprisonment and such fine. c ^ 2 J ■ R” S i ^ e § u ^ a ^ on shall, in its application to Scotland, have effect as if for the reference to the Director of Public Prosecutions there were substituted a reference to the Lord Advocate. 39e -—(r) The Secretary of State, if satisfied, with respect to any area in the United Kingdom, that the holding of public processions or of any class of such processions in that area would be likely to cause serious public disorder or to promote disaffection, may by order prohibit, for such period as may be specified in the order, the holding in that area of processions or processions of that class, as the case may be. ! ec l et ?jy State raa Y give directions prohibiting the holding in the United Kingdom of any meeting as to which he is satisfied that the holding ' Proces- and meetings.tnsmtTaqsO 18 thereof would be likely to cause serious public disorder or to promote disaffection. (3) Any constable may take such steps, and use such force, as may be reasonably necessary for secur ing compliance with any order made or directions given under this Regulation. (4) The operation of subsections (2) and (3) of 1 Edw. 8 &amp; section three of the Public Order Act, 1936, and the 1 Geo. 6. c. 6. 0 p era ti 0 n of the words ‘ or organises or assists in organising any public procession held or intended to be held in contravention of an order made under this section or incites any person to take part in such a procession ’ in subsection (4) of the said section, shall be suspended during the continuance in force of this Regulation. . t (5) In this Regulation the expression public pro cession ’ has the same meaning as in the Public 0 |*ler Act, 1936. “ Addition- 40 . — (1) The Secretary of State may appoint ai inspec- inspectors of constabulary, in addition to the inspectors tors of con- ^ CO nstabulary appointed under section fifteen of the fq a &amp; LT' County and Borough Police Act, 1856, and the addi- Viet. c. 69. tional inspectors so appointed shall perform such duties as he may assign to them. . (2) This Regulation shall, in its application to Scotland, have effect as if for the reference to the inspectors appointed under section fifteen of the County and Borough Police Act, 1856, there were substituted a reference to the inspector appointed 20 &amp; 21 under section sixty-five of the Police (Scotland) Act, Viet. c. 72. (3) This Regulation shall not extend to Northern Ireland ”. 12 . After Regulation forty A of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — 'Visiting 41 .— (1) The Secretary of State may appoint a committees v i s iting committee for any prison that, by virtue of a for ceitain declarat i on ma de by him under subsection (3W°t V J!Tls section two of the Prison Act, 1884, is a prison ui^er Viet. c. 51. the Prison Act, 1865, and the Prison Act, 1877, and a 28 &amp; 29 visiting committee so appointed shall have the same Viet. c. 126. powers and duties as if it had been appointed under Viet c. 1 21 section thirteen of the Prison Act, 1877. (2) No visiting committee shall be appointed under the said section thirteen for a prison for which a visit ing committee has been appointed under this Regula tion. . [* Former paragraph (3) omitted].19 “ Visiting 42. —(i) The Secretary of State may appoint a fo^prisons* visitin g c o mr nittee for any prison in Scotland, and inScotiand. a visiting committee so appointed shall have the same 40 &amp; 41 powers and duties as if it had been appointed under Viet. c. 53. section fourteen of the Prisons (Scotland) Act, 1877. (2) No visiting committee shall be appointed under the said section fourteen for a prison for which a visit ing committee has been appointed under this Regula tion 13 . After Regulation forty-five of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — ' Employ- 45 a.— (1) [ J The competent authority], if it appears British 1 t ^ iat au fhority to be necessary or expedient in the ships^and interests of the defence of the realm or the efficient prosecution of war so to do, may, as respects any class of British ships other than Dominion ships, make provision by order— (a) for securing that, subject to any exemptions for which provision may be made by the order, any such class of persons as may be specified in the order shall not be employed on board ships to which the order applies; (b) for prohibiting the employment of any per sons or class of persons on board such ships unless they are holders of certificates of identity issued in such form and manner as may be prescribed by the order, and for determining the circumstances in which certificates of identity may be granted and revoked under the order; and an order under this Regulation may be made so as to restrict the employment of persons either in any capacity or in such capacity as may be specified in the order, and so as to restrict the employment of persons on such British ships as aforesaid either wherever they may be or while in such waters, or engaged in such trades or on such voyages, as may be so specified. (2) The preceding provisions of this Regulation shall apply in relation to aircraft as they apply in relation to ships, except that any reference in those provisions to [The competent authority] shall be con strued as a reference to the Secretary of State. [ 2 (3) In this Regulation and in Regulations forty- five B, forty-six, forty-six A and forty-seven, the expression ‘ the competent authority ’ means the Board o f Trade or the Minister of Shipping]. P ' The competent authority ” substituted for “ the Board of Trade,' by S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1500]. [ 2 New paiagraph added by S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1500]. aircraft. *.•rnsmitBqsO 20 “Employ- 45b.—[‘T he competent authority], with a view to abroad of P reven ti n g the employment abroad, in connection with agents for the management of British ships, of enemy aliens or ships and persons connected with an enemy, may by order aircraft. direct that, as from such date as may be specified in the order, the owner, manager or charterer of any British ship, being a person resident in the United Kingdom or a corporation incorporated under the law of any part of the United Kingdom, shall not employ in any foreign country or territory, in connection with the management of the ship, any person other than a person approved for the purpose by [‘the competent authority]; and an order under this Regulation may be made so as to apply either generally to employment in all foreign countries or territories or to employment in such foreign countries or territories, or such cla^ of foreign countries or territories, as may be specifij^ in the order. (2) The preceding provisions of this Regulation shall apply in relation to aircraft as they apply in relation to ships, except that any reference in those-provisions to [‘the competent authority] shall be construed as a reference to the Secretary of State ['] 14 . In Regulation forty-six of the principal Regulations for the words ' the Board of Trade ' wherever those words occur and for the words “ the Board ” wherever those words occur otherwise than as part of the expression “ the Board of Trade ” there shall be substituted the words “ the competent authority [ 3 ] 15 . After Regulation forty-six of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulation: — “ Power of 46 a. Notwithstanding any restriction imposed by competent an y 0 f following Regulations, a prosecution in to prose- respect of an offence against any of the last three cute for preceding Regulations may, in England or Northern certain Ireland, be instituted by or on behalf of the competent offences, authority ' ’. [ 2 ] 16 . In paragraph (3) of Regulation forty-seven of the prin cipal Regulations for the words “ the Board of Trade ' wherc^ ever those words occur there shall be substituted the words “ thr competent authority ”. 17 . After Regulation forty-seven of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulation: — “ Deserters 47 a. Any person lawfully engaged to serve on board from ships. an y gj-^p belonging to, or chartered or requisitioned P “ The competent authority ” substituted for “ The Board of Trade ” by S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1500]. [ 2 Amendment effected by S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1500]. p Amendment effected by S.R. &amp; O. 1939 Nos. 1463 and 1500].by, or on behalf of, His Majesty, who in the United Kingdom is, by virtue of section two hundred and y 7 f 5 ® 6 twenty-one of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, guilty ic . c. o. q£ offence of desertion or of absence without leave, may, notwithstanding anything contained in that Act, be conveyed on board his ship by, or under the direc tion of, any one or more of the following persons, that is to say, the master of the ship, the mate of the ship, the person having the management of the ship, any constable, any commissioned officer in His Majesty’s forces and any superintendent within the meaning of the said Act c. 67. 18 . After Regulation fifty-eight of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — F.xemp- 59, — (j) The Secretary of State may by order, to \cts such.extent, during such period, and subject to such relating to conditions, as may be specified in the order, exempt factories, any particular premises or operations or class of mines and premises or operations from the Factories Act, 1937, quarries^ if h e i s satisfied that such exemption is, by reason of \ qqq' 6 ' &amp; circumstances arising out of war, desirable in the public interest in order to secure or facilitate the carry ing on of work in those premises or in that class of premises, or the carrying on of those operations Por of that class of operations], as the case may be, or in order to promote the safety of persons employed in such premises or engaged in such operations. (2) The Board of Trade may by order, to such extent, during such period, and subject to such con ditions, as may be specified in the order, exempt any particular premises ['or operations] or class of premises ['or operations] from the Coal Mines Act, 1911, the Metalliferous Mines Regulation Acts, 1872 Geo. 5.C.50. an( j 1875, the Quarries Act, 1894, and from any 35 &amp; 36 orders or Regulations made under any of those Viet. c. 77. ^cts, or any special rules established under the V' ? 39 Metalliferous Mines Regulation Act, 1872, if the _ ic . e. 39 g oar( f are sa fi s fi e( f that such exemption is, by Yict c 8 &gt; reason °f circumstances arising out of war, desirable 1 C 4 ' in the public interest in order to secure or facilitate the carrying on of work in those premises or in that class of premises, or the carrying on of those operations or of that class of operations, as the case may be, or in order to promote the safety of persons employed in such premises or engaged in such operations. 1 &amp; 2 P Words in brackets inserted by S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1416]..tnsmti 'jr 3 &lt; ! 22 (3) This Regulation shall, in its application to Northern Ireland, have effect subject to the following modifications: — {a) for the reference to the Factories Act, 1937, there shall be substituted a reference to the Factories Act (Northern Ireland), 1938; (b) for the reference to the Quarries Act, 1894, there shall be substituted a reference to the Quarries Act (Northern Ireland), 1927; and (c) for the references to the Secretary of State and to the Board of Trade there shall be substi tuted respectively references to the Ministry of Labour for Northern Ireland and to the Ministry of Commerce. “Safety 60 . —(i) The Secretaiy of State may by order mak(^ an&lt; ^ such provision as he thinks desirable for securing th^ factory ° sa fety» health or welfare of persons who in circum- workers. stances which, in the opinion of the Secretary of State, are or are likely to be dangerous to life or limb or injurious to health, are either— (a) employed in any premises to which any of the provisions of the Factories Act, 1937, apply, in the performance of any services which appear to the Secretary of State to be essential for the defence of the realm or the efficient prosecution of war or to be essential to the life of the community, or (b) engaged in any operations to which any of the provisions of the Factories Act, 1937, apply, being operations which appear to the Secretary of State to be essential for the defence of the realm or the efficient prosecution of war or to be essential to the life of the community; and, without prejudice to the generality of the power aforesaid, any such order may in particular contain such requirements with respect to the pro-^ vision of medical attendance, nourishment, clothing, facilities for taking meals, rest or recreation, or facili ties for transport, and may impose such prohibitions, restrictions or obligations in respect of the use of machinery, appliances, materials or processes, as appear to the Secretary of State to be necessary or expedient for the purposes of the order. An order under this Regulation may be made so as to apply to any particular premises or class ofpremises or to any particular operations or class of operations. (2) This Regulation shall, in its application to Northern Ireland, have effect subject to the following modifications: [а) for the references to the Secretary of State there shall be substituted references to the Ministry of Labour for Northern Ireland; and (б) for the references to the Factories Act, 1937, there shall be substituted references to the Factories Act (Northern Ireland), 1938 19 . The functions of the Board of Trade under Regulation sixty-eight of the principal Regulations are hereby transferred to the Minister of Supply; and accordingly for any reference in Regulation to the Board of Trade there shall be substituted a reference to the Minister of Supply. 20 . In Part V of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted as the first Regulations under the heading “ General Provisions ' the following Regulations: — ' Derelict articles. —(1) Whenever any person finds an article as to which he has reasonable cause to believe that it has been lost or abandoned, and that, immediately before being lost or abandoned, it was used or intended to be used for the purposes of an armed force or was in the possession of a person who had it with him while serving with an armed force, the person finding the article— {a) shall forthwith report the nature and situation thereof, or, if the article is a document, cause it to be delivered, to a member of His Majesty’s forces being on duty or to a con stable at a police station, and (6) save as aforesaid, shall not remove or tamper with the article except with permission granted by or on behalf of a Secretary of 0 State or the Admiralty: Provided that a Secretary of State or the Admiralty may by order direct that the obligations and restric tions imposed by this Regulation shall not apply in relation to any such description of articles as may be specified in the order or determined by such authority or person as may be so specified. (2) In relation to the finding by a person of such an article as aforesaid outside the United Kingdom, para graph (1) of this Regulation shall have effect as if forwhich the officer has reasonable ground for believing to be evidence of the commission of such an offence as aforesaid. (2) If, with respect to any premises, any officer of police of a rank not lower than that of superintendent, or any person authorised by the Secretary of State to act under this paragraph, has reasonable ground for suspecting that an offence to which this Part of these Regulations applies has been or is being committed, and that evidence of the commission of the offence is to be found at those premises, and is satisfied— {a) that it is essential in the interests of the State that the premises should be searched for the purpose of obtaining that evidence, and {b) that the evidence is not likely to be found at the premises unless they are search^ forthwith, w the said officer or person may, by a written order under his hand, confer the like powers of search and seizure in relation to the premises as might be con ferred under paragraph (1) of this Regulation by the warrant of a justice. (3) No female shall, in pursuance of any warrant issued or order made under this Regulation, be searched except by a female. (4) The operation of section nine of the Official 1 &amp; 2 Secrets Act, 1911, shall be suspended during the con- Geo. 5.C.28. tinuance in force of this Regulation. 'Power to 88 b. — (1) The person driving, or in control of, any search 11 ^ roa d vehicle in motion shall stop the vehicle on being vehicles. required so to do by any constable in uniform or by any member of His Majesty’s forces being in uniform and on duty. (2) if- [a) as respects any road vehicle being on a public highway or in a place to which the public have access, or ^ {b) upon the overtaking of a road vehicle on an® occasion on which the person driving, or in control of, the vehicle has been lawfully required to stop it but has failed to do so, any constable or member of His Majesty's forces has reasonable ground for suspecting that there is to be found in the vehicle evidence of the commission of an offence to which this Part of these Regulations applies, he may search the vehicle and may seize any article25 (c) of subsection (i) of that section, have effect as if the reference in the said sub section (5) to the Attorney General included a reference to the Director of Public Prose cutions. ‘Power to 80 A.—(1) Without prejudice to any special pro- foraiation v , m ° ns c ° ntain ed in these Regulations, any person shall, on being requested by or on behalf of a Secretary of State or the Admiralty so to do, furnish or produce to such authority or person as may be specified in the request any such information or article in his possession as may be so specified, being information or an article which the authority or person making the request con siders it necessary or expedient in the interests of the public safety, the defence of the realm or the efficient a prosecution of war to obtain or examine, [ x and if any * person fails to furnish or produce any information or article in his possession in pursuance of a request duly made to him under this Regulation he shall be guilty of an offence against this Regulation. (2) A prosecution in respect of an offence against this Regulation shall not be instituted except by, or with the consent of, the Director of Public Prose cutions : Provided that this paragraph shall not extend to Scotland]. 21 . After Regulation eighty-eight of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Regulations: — ‘‘Entry 88a. —(1) If a justice of the peace is satisfied by 0? premises i n f orma ti on on oath that there is reasonable ground to obtain &lt; S ^ or suspecting that an offence to which this Part of evidence of these Regulations applies has been or is being com- offences. mitted, and that evidence of the commission of the offence is to be found at any premises specified in the information, he may grant a search warrant authoris- ing any officer of police of a rank not lower than that * of inspector, or any commissioned officer in His Majesty’s forces, together with any other persons named in the warrant and any other constables or members of His Majesty’s forces, to enter the premises at any time or times within one month from the date of the warrant and to search the premises and every person found therein, and to seize any article found in the premises or on any such person P Words in brackets added by this Older].24 “ Amend ment of Geneva Convention Acts, i &amp; 2 Geo.f.c. 20. I Edw. 8 &amp; i Geo. 6. c. 15 - the requirement contained in sub-paragraph {a) of that paragraph there were substituted a requirement that the said person shall forthwith take such steps as are reasonably practicable to secure that the nature and situation of the article are reported, or, if the article is a document, that it is delivered as soon as may be to some person in His Majesty’s service. 80 . The Geneva Convention Acts, 1911 and IQ37 (which contain provisions prohibiting the use of the Red Cross or imitations thereof without the authority of the Army Council or the Board of Trade, as the case may be), shall, in the operation of those Acts as part of the law of the United Kingdom, have effect subject to the following modifications, that is to say: — (а) in subsection (1) of section one of the said Act of 1911, for the words ‘ to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and ’ there shall bdr substituted the words ‘ to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and such fine, and also and in subsection (2) of section one of the said Act of 1937, for the words ‘ to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and ’ there shall be substituted the words ‘ in a case where the offence is in respect of the use of any design or words referred to in paragraph (c) of that subsection, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprison ment and such fine, or, in any other case, to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and also, in any case,’; (б) subsection (4) of section one of the said Act of 1911 (which requires the consent of the Attorney General to the taking of proceed ings under that Act in England or Northern Ireland) shall, in relation to proceedings ii0 England, have effect as if the reference in that subsection to the Attorney General in cluded a reference to the Director of Public Prosecutions; and (c) subsection (5) of section one of the said Act of 1937 shall, in relation to proceedings under that section which may be taken in England by reason of the use of any design or words referred to in paragraph27 f 1 ' Power to arrest without warrant. 4 “ Identifi cation of persons in custody. t found therein which he has reasonable ground for believing to be evidence of the commission of such an offence. The powers conferred by this paragraph shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any of the powers conferred by the last preceding Regulation. (3) In this Regulation the expression ‘ road vehicle ' means any vehicle designed or adapted for use on roads. 88c.—(1) Any constable and any person authorised by the Secretary of State to act under this Regulation may arrest without warrant any person whom he has reasonable ground for suspecting to have committed an offence to which this Part of these Regulations applies. (2) Any member of His Majesty’s forces shall, for the purposes of carrying out his duty as such, have the like powers as are conferred upon constables by the preceding provisions of this Regulation. (3) The operation of section six of the Official Secrets Act, 1911, shall be suspended during the con tinuance in force of this Regulation]. 88 d.— (1) The Secretary of State may make rules authorising the taking, in relation to any person in custody whom the proper officer of police has reason able grounds for suspecting to have committed an offence to which this Part of these Regulations applies, of all such steps as may be reasonably necessary for photographing, measuring and otherwise identifying that person in such manner as may be prescribed by the rules. [ 2 (2) Rules made under this Regulation shall make provision for securing: — (а) that no photograph of a person taken in pur suance of the powers conferred by this Regulation shall be published, except for the purpose of tracing that person, and that no copy of any such photograph shall be shown to any person except a person officially authorised to see it; and (б) that all photographs (both negatives and copies), and all documents relating to the measurement and identification of any per son taken or made in pursuance of the said powers shall, unless that person has been convicted of an offence to which this Part P New Regulation substituted by this Order], [ 2 New paragraph inserted by this Order].29 (4504—7) Wt. 6—1 .-j.ooo 11/39 P. St. G. 416 designed for use in His Majesty’s service, in the service of a foreign government or for the pur poses of a police force 3 * l 1 ) f he maximum penalty that may be imposed on conv ^ c ted of an offence under section five of the Official Secrets Act, 1920 (which provides for the registra- bon and regulation of persons carrying on the business' of receiving postal packets), shall be imprisonment for a term of thiee months and a fine of fifty pounds, and accord- in gly in subsection (4) of that section for the words ‘ one month and the words ten pounds ’ there shall be respec tively substituted the words ‘ three months ’ and the words fifty pounds \ (2) Notwithstanding anything in section eight of the Official Secrets Act, 1911, a prosecution for an offence under a section five of the Official Secrets Acts, 1920, may, in England and Northern Ireland, be instituted by any con stable. 4 . In section seven of the Official Secrets Act, 1920, for the words ‘ and does any act ' there shall be substituted the words f or does any act 5. In section eight of the Official Secrets Act, 1911, and in subsection (2) of section eight of the Official Secrets Act, 1920 (which provisions respectively require the consent of the Attorney General to the institution of prosecutions, and to the summary trial of misdemeanours, under those Acts), references to the Attorney General shall be construed as including references to the Director of Public Prosecu tions 24 .—(1) Subsection (2) of section thirty-eight of the Interpre tation Act, 1889, (which relates to the effect of repeals) shall apply with respect to the revocation by this Order of any pro visions of any previous Order in Council as it applies to the repeal by any Act passed after the commencement of that Act of any other enactment. (2) Any order, rules or appointment made, permit granted, warrant issued or directions or authority given, by virtue of Jfiy provisions of any Order in Council revoked by this Order wliich is in force at the date of the coming into operation of this Order shall continue in force and have effect as if made, granted, issued or given by virtue of this Order; but if or in so far as any such order, rule, appointment, permit, warrant direction or authority is inconsistent with the provisions of this Order it shall be revoked as soon as may be after the coming into operation of this Order. Rupert B. Howortk.28 of these Regulations applies, be destroyed as soon as may be after the expiration of the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, / 1939 ] • (3) In this Regulation the expression ‘ the proper officer of police ’ means any officer of police being of a rank not lower than that of inspector, or being in charge of a police station 22. In paragraph (3) of Regulation one hundred and one of the principal Regulations, the words ' The expression ‘ mayor ’ shall mean ' provost ' ” shall be omitted. 23 . At the end of the principal Regulations there shall be inserted the following Schedule: — “ Schedule. Amendments of Official Secrets Acts, 1911 and 1920. £ 1 . In paragraph {a) of section three of the Official Secrets Act, 1911, as amended by the Official Secrets Act, 1920, after the word ‘ naval ' there shall be inserted the word ' military \ 2. The following amendments shall be made in section one of the Official Secrets Act, 1920: — (1) in paragraph (c) of subsection (1), for the words ‘ or tampers with ' there shall be substituted the words ‘ tampers with or destroys ’; (2) for paragraph (e) of subsection (1) there shall be substituted the following paragraphs: — (e) has in his possession or under his con trol any official die, seal or stamp, any impression of such a die, seal or stamp, or any official paper; or (/) counterfeits any official die, seal or stamp, or has in his possession or under his control any counterfeited official die, seal or stamp, or any thing so closely resembling an official die, seal or stamp as to be calculate to deceive, or any paper so closed resembling official paper as to be cal culated to deceive and (3) at the end of subsection (1) there shall be inserted the following paragraph: — For the purposes of this subsection any die, scab stamp or paper shall be taken to be an official die, seal or stamp, or official paper, as the case may be, if, but only if, it is speciallyNo. 0/ 887 of 1939ir&gt;\ r rhe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 2 3 PEC. ,:Ui J jj &amp;&amp;&gt; / j ■ !• The Political Agent, Kuwait, 2# The Political Agent, Bahrain 5, The Political i»gent, liuscat. ' and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). for information . printed copies oi the xtegulationc (l os,2 &amp; 3 to Bahrain onl^) will Be iorwdidca cu receipt. Name and Date. Subject. India Office Express Letter ^o .P.Z,7359/39 ot the 27th November 1939, with enclosure. Regulations Nos,i ,2 &amp; 3 of 1930, made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergenqy) Order in Council, j.939.BXPRfcSS I-^TTiSK (Air Mail) From Secretary of State for India. To Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department• Dated 27th November, 1939. No.P.Z.7359/39. Reference your marginally noted letters, forwarding } for allowance the text of C.410 of i4th September ^ J.&lt;152 of 23rd September 5 Regulations Kos.l, 2 and 3 of G.466 of 25th September ) } 1939, made under the Persian Gulf States (dt&gt;ergency) Order in Jouncil, 1939. I forward for your informtion, a cop v of a letter from the Foreign dated 'Governoer ) Office stating th^t the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs approves the Regulations. Printed copies of che Regulations, the use of which may be found convenient in announcing the Secretary of Stated approval, are enclosed herev/ith. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. sd. J•?.Gibson.P.Z.7359/39. E 7126/8495/91. Foreign Office, 8.A.1. 1M 22nd ITovember, 1959. Sir, With reference to your letters of the 18th and 23rd October (P.Z.5988/39 and P.2.612^'39) forwarding the text of Persian Gulf Regulations Nos.l, 2 and 3 of 1939, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that he approves these Regulations. 2. 1 am to transmit to you herewith 42 copies of each Regulation together with 5 for the files of your department. Though the Regulations have already been issued as urgent the Political Resident in. the Persian Gulf may prefer to substitute printed copies when he announces the approval of the Secretary of State • I am, etc. sd. Stephen Gaselee. The Under-Secretary of St-.te, India Office.D.0.KO.D.4806-H/39. External Affairs Department, New Delhi, e r&lt; 3 *• December ^39 • Precautions against sabotage at the Bahrain Refinery. Bahrain Refinery. Will you please refer to Savidge's demi-official letter to you No.F.476-N/38 dated the 3rd July 1939 regarding the proposed employment of an ex-service electrician by the Bahrain Petroleum Company, for intelligence purposes ? 2. The Government of India would be glad to know whether the Bahrain Petroleum Company wishes to engage one of the civilians of whom particulars were sent to you by Savidge. \S^CRjTT C / M&lt;c . Jenusry, 194C. Please fefer to your D.O. Po. D. 48C6 -P/39 dated the 23r&lt;3* Deceniber, on the subject of precautions against sabotage at the Bahrain Refinery. I was not impressed by the qualifications of the men suggested by the Intelligence Bureau and have therefore decided not to pursue the matter furtte Yours sincerely, To Major B.v;. Fletcher, I.A. Additional Deouty Secretary Bxterbal Affairs Department Government of India, Delhi.Conf iaential The Residency^ ary 1940. Dear Weightman, uA- Will you please refer to Peel f s letter No.P#Z. 7827/39, dated the 19th December 1939, (copy sent to you direct), regarding the pre-emption of oil in Bahrain, and let me have any information that is available regarding the ownership of Kasa oil lying in Bahraini The stock of oil referred to in your memorandum No.C/356-10/1, dated the 29th May 1938, was purchased by the Bahrain Petroleum Company but it is not certain that there is a change of owner ship of subsequent consignments of oil sent from the mainland to Bahrain. Yours sincerely, H. Weightman, i£sq.,I.C.S. Political Agent, Bahrain.7 ^ Conllcientiol -•O* Wo. C/62 - 1.a/43 Dated the 12th January 1340 /, Vl vvlii yoi)/pifci:se refer to your demi-officiel letter Ito * i4 ~ s di -ted the 4th Jenuery 1U40 regarding Hasa oil ? t i! * 1 have not y et received a copy of Peel«s letter No. 7^S7/o3 dated the Ivth December 1323, so I imagine it \ mU3t htve ^ one ^tray. I qo not of course know v.hat questions are raised but it may be useful to let you know that ail Hasa 011 is i^Po^ted for refining in Bahrain is bou ht by the Bahrain Petroleum Company from the Caxifornia Arabian Company. It so happened that I verified this particular point onl : , a September la3d (Bahrain Onalioti-ed Area correspondence). Yours sincerely. few days before your letter arrived. -O - , 'f- -JH c. You will see I mentioned this point in the •ust sentence of my Express letter No. C/^32 dated the 10th The Hon»ble C.G. jLileu tonaiii. Colonel Prior, C.I.E., Poll c-ical Resident In me Persian Gulf, Camp Kuwait#INDIA OFFICE to 0) P.Z. 7611/39 60 [I IE HALL, 3 • . / • 1 • Rth DocemLer, 1939 V with reference to this Office letter No. P.Z.5740/39 dated the 25th September, regarding the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order-in-Council, I am directed hy the Secretary of State to forward copies of further correspondence on this subject from which it will he seen that, in view of io foreign Oflice (P.Z.5988/39) dated ) the coming into force of the 18th October, 1939. ) -•rom Foreign Office dated 3rd November) Muscat Order-in-Council, 1939, ^ 1939 S i° ore ign Cifice dated 10th November J it has been found desirable to 1939 S ^.•rom X' owe ign Cifice dated 2nd December; amend Article 4 of the Persian 1939. ) Gulf States (Emergency) Order-in- Council. The necessary steps having been taken to that end, i am to forward herewith three certified copies and ten plain copies of the amending Order (to be cited as 5, The Persian Gulf States (Emergency) (Amendment) Order-in- Council i939 H ) which was made by His Majesty in Council on the 23rd November, 1939. 2• I am to request that if the Government of India see no objection the text of the Amendment Order may, as provided therein, be published at an early date in “'The Gazette of India” and that the Secretary of State may be informed by telegraph of the date of publication in the Gazette or of exhibition by the Political Resident, whichever is the e arlier• o. A copy of this letter, with enclosures, is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and copies of/ The Secretary, External Affairs Department, Government of India.of the letter with ten plain copies of the Order? are 'being sent to the Political Agents at Koweit? Bahrein and Muscat* I am? Sir? Your obedient Servant? (Sgdh J. P. GIBSOftPrinted by His Majesty's Stationery Office Press, Pocock Street, S.E.i. ( 446 ir- 7 ) wt. 125 11/39 St. G. 416 AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE The 23rd day of November, 1939 Present THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN COUNCIL Whereas by treaty, capitulation, grant, usage, sufferance and other lawful means His Majesty the King has jurisdiction within the territories referred to in the Orders mentioned in the Schedule to the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Acts, 1890 and 1913, the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, 1939, and the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows: — 1 . — (1) This Order may be cited as “ The Persian Gulf States (Emergency) (Amendment) Order in Council, 1939,” and ^ shall be read as one with the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, hereinafter called “ the Principal Order.” (2) This Order shall take effect immediately. (3) This Order shall be published in the Gazette of India. 2 . The following provisions are substituted for Article 4 of the Principal Order: — For the purposes of this Order and of all regulations made thereunder, His Majesty's jurisdiction in each of the terri tories shall be deemed to extend to those persons to whom and matters to which the powers conferred by the Order mentioned in the Schedule applicable to the territory, or any subsequent Order made in amendment thereof or substitu tion therefor, apply. And the Most Honourable the Marquess of Zetland and the Right Honourable Viscount Halifax two of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State are to give the necessary directions herein as may to them respectively appertain. Rupert B. Howorth.AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE The 23rd day of November, 1939 Present THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY ^ IN COUNCIL Whereas by treaty, capitulation, grant, usage, sufferance and other lawful means His Majesty the King has jurisdiction within the territories referred to in the Orders mentioned in the Schedule to the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Acts, 1890 and 1913, the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, 1939, and the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows: — 1 . — (1) This Order may be cited as “ The Persian Gulf States (Emergency) (Amendment) Order in Council, 1939,” and shall be read as one with the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, hereinafter called “ the Principal Order.' (2) This Order shall take effect immediately. (3) This Order shall be published in the Gazette of India. 2. The following provisions are substituted for Article 4 of the Principal Order: — For the purposes of this Order and of all regulations made thereunder, His Majesty’s jurisdiction in each of the terri tories shall be deemed to extend to those persons to whom and matters to which the powers conferred by the Order mentioned in the Schedule applicable to the territory, or any subsequent Order made in amendment thereof or substitu tion therefor, apply. And the Most Honourable the Marquess of Zetland and the Right Honourable Viscount Halifax two of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State are to give the necessary directions herein as may to them respectively appertain. Rupert D. Howorth. Printed by His Majesty’s Stationery Office Press, Pocock Street, S.E.i. ( 446 ir- 7 ) Wt. 125 11/39 P. St. G. 416Printed by His Majesty's Stationery Office Press, Pocock Street, S.E.i. (446ir— 7 ) Wt. 125 11/39 P- St. G. 416 AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE The 23rd day of November, 1939 Present THE KING'S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN COUNCIL Whereas by treaty, capitulation, grant, usage, sufferance and other lawful means His Majesty the King has jurisdiction within the territories referred to in the Orders mentioned in the Schedule to the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Acts, 1890 and 1913, the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, 1939, and the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows: — 1. — (1) This Order may be cited as “ The Persian Gulf States (Emergency) (Amendment) Order in Council, 1939,' and x-v shall be read as one with the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, hereinafter called “ the Principal Order.' (2) This Order shall take effect immediately. (3) This Order shall be published in the Gazette of India. 2 . The following provisions are substituted for Article 4 of the Principal Order: — For the purposes of this Order and of all regulations made thereunder, His Majesty’s jurisdiction in each of the terri tories shall be deemed to extend to those persons to whom and matters to which the powers conferred by the Order mentioned in the Schedule applicable to the territory, or any subsequent Order made in amendment thereof or substitu tion therefor, apply. And the Most Honourable the Marquess of Zetland and the Right Honourable Viscount Halifax two of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State are to give the necessary directions herein as may to them respectively appertain. Rupert B. Howorth.AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE The 23rd day of November, 1939 Present THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN COUNCIL .-A Whereas by treaty, capitulation, grant, usage, sufferance and other lawful means His Majesty the King has jurisdiction within the territories referred to in the Orders mentioned in the Schedule to the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939: NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Acts, 1890 and 1913, the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, 1939, and the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows: — 1. — (1) This Order may be cited as “ The Persian Gulf States (Emergency) (Amendment) Order in Council, 1939,” and shall be read as one with the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939, hereinafter called “ the Principal Order.' (2) This Order shall take effect immediately. (3) This Order shall be published in the Gazette of India. 2. The following provisions are substituted for Article 4 of the Principal Order: — For the purposes of this Order and of all regulations made thereunder, His Majesty’s jurisdiction in each of the terri tories shall be deemed to extend to those persons to whom and matters to which the powers conferred by the Order mentioned in the Schedule applicable to the territory, or any subsequent Order made in amendment thereof or substitu tion therefor, apply. And the Most Honourable the Marquess of Zetland and the Right Honourable Viscount Halifax two of His Majesty’s Principal Secretaries of State are to give the necessary directions herein as may to them respectively appertain. Rupert B. Howorth. Printed by His Majesty's Stationery Office Press, Pocock Street, S.E.i. (446ir—7) wt. — 125 11/39 P- St. G. 416JL ^ f-o . P.Z.7827/39. Confidential. Ain Mail. ii s HIDIA CF?I03, V/Tilxi' X* AxJ.-J 5 S.W.l. / 19th December, 1939 i toO ( k S ( 4/1 VA u Would you pleas&gt;^efer to Powle’s telegram of the 26th August, Do.T/204,^regarding the pre-emption of oil in Bahrein, and to subsequent correspondence with the Foreign Office of which a copy was sent tc you by the air mail of 26th September. I now enclose a copy of a further letter Dated 13th December ) from the Foreign Office suggesting, with ^ reference to Weightman’s memorandum of the 29th May, 1938 No.0/356-10/1, the possibility that the Hasa oil imported into Bahrein may be the property of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, in which case the question of commandeering it, if such a question were to arise, would be so much the more simplified. Can you, from your available information or from discreet enquiries, throw any light on the matter of the ov/nership of Hasa oil lying in Bahrein? I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Caroe and Weightman. Ycuro sinoererty. ^ (Sgd.) R. PttU The Hon’ble Lt.Col.C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.(E 6229/196/91) V FOREIGN OFFICE, S.V/.l* 1Sth De cemoer, 19 39. Dear GiDson, Would you please refer to my letter of the 21st Septemoer, to Reel undur this number, regarding the pre-emption of Bahrein and Rasa oil? In P ara S ra P h 5 of that letter the view was accepted that it would be preferable not to commandeer any Hasa oil lying in tru. Bahrein refinery. We have since gone into the question more fully and, though we do not appear to have received -che text of any agreement between C.A.S.O.C. and tne Bahrein Petroleum Company, it would seem from the enclosures to your official letter P.Z.4221/38 of the 30th dune, 1938, that the Hasa oil may be bought by the Bahrein Petroleum Company. If this is so, there would appear to be no need to differentiate between Bahrein and Hasa oil, if the question of commandeering should arise, as all the oil in the Bahrein refinery would Delong to the Bahrein Petroleum Company. Can sa F whether it is a fact that all Hasa oil reaching Bahrein becomes the property of the Bahrein Petroleum Company ? b# 1 ^ sending a copy of this letter to Star]ing and Yours sincerely, Jarreit.P.Z. 7671/39 December, 193S. Bir I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to r inform you that he has received representations from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf regarding the deterioriation of cable and wireless communications in that region. After referring to.the Senior Naval Officer’s complaint of the inadequate watch kept by the Bahrein Station on 500 kc/s (regarding which you have been addressed m Admiralty letter No. M. 014904/39, dated the 5th - December), and to the desirability of a 24-hour commercial and general service at Bahrein, the Political Resident represents that since the reorganisation of the cable system in 1935 interruptions of the Karachi-Muscat and Muscat—Bushire cables have been frequent and lengthy, and that by the middle of November cable communication had not yet been restored after the last interruption, which occurred on 1st August. lie adds that the provision of a wireless station at Muscat does not afford an adequate substitute, and has resulted in heavy congestion at Bahrein. The consequence in his opinion has been that telegraphic communications in the Persian Gulf havegreatly deteriorated. The Secretary of State regrets that the Political Resident should have had cause to make these representations at/ The Chairman, Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Electra House, W.C.2. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 5 1 2 1 DEC 1939 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICEa time wlien the eiiicienc^ of overseas telegraphic cominunications is a matter of high importance. Having regard to the obligation resting on your Company to maintain the cable system in the Persian Gulf he earnestly hopes that every effort will be made by them to keep the cables in efficient working order. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,P.Z. 7671/59. Enclosure in Admiralty Covering Note No. M. 014904/39 to the ^ Under-Secretary of State for India, dated 5th December, 1939. 5th December, 1939. Sir, v/ith reference to recent correspondence between your Company and the India Office on the subject of the maintenance of a 24 hour watch at Bahrein W/T Station, I am commanded by Ny Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty bo intorm you that the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, nas reported that at present the Bahrein Radio Station only listens on 500 kc/s for 3/ hours daily, and that in view of the present importance of Bahrein as a Coast Station, it is essential that a continuous watch should be kept on 500 kc/s by this Station. 2. My Lords are in agreement with this proposal which, it is observed from your Company’s letter GM/L of the 2nd March, 1939, to the India Office could be carried out, provided it did not interfere with your agreement with tiie Air Ministry to maintain an 18 hour watch exclusively for the needs of Civil and Service aircraft, v/ith provision for extending this to a 24 hour watch, and provided certain additional staff were supplied, and they would be glad if arrangements could be made for this continuous .atch to be brought into force as soon as practicable. 3. With regard td the cost of any additional staff necessary for maintaining a continuous watch, I am to state that My Lords suggest that this might be offset by the additional revenue to be expected by your Company on account of the additional traffic handled. I am, etc. (3d.) S.H. PHILLIPS. The Chairman, Messrs. Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd., Electra House, W.C.2.■ —H No - c/10 of 1940 CONFIDENTIAL. \- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• O.K.Caroe Esquire, I.C«S 9 Secretary to the Government of India, ^ External Affairs Department, New Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). 15 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Ramp, Kuwait* Dated... 23rd-‘January'-1940 Reference to previous correspondence : To 1. India Office letter No.P.Z.7827/39 of 19th December 1939. To 2. Bahrain letter No.C/62-l.a/43 of 13th January 1940. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject, To 2. 1. India Office letter No.P.Z. - only. 7827/39 of 19th December Pre-emption of oil in Bahrain. 1939, with enclosure. 2. Letter No.C/9 of 23rd January 1940 to R.T.Peel Esqpire, CBS.,MC., The India Office, London.Copy &lt;S&gt; India Office, Whitehall, o • • 1 P*Z. 7827/39. Confidential. Air Mail 19th December, 1939. Dear ii-ior Would you pleaee refer to Fowle’e telegram of the 26th August, No.T/204, regarding the pre-emption of oil in Bahrain, and to subsequent correspondence with the Foreign Office of v/hich a copy was sent to you by the air mail of 26th September, i now enclose a copy of a further letter ing, with reference to weightman’e memorandum of the 29th May, 1938, No .C/356-lC/l, the possibility that the Kasa oil imported into Bahrain may be the property of the Bahrain petroleum Company, in which case the question of commandeering it, if such a question were to arise, would be so much the more simplified. Can you, from your available information or from discreet enquiries, throw any light on the matter of the ownership of Hasa oil lying in Bahrain ? I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Caroe and Weight man. dated i3th Dece mber ) from the Foreign Office suggest- iours sincerely, sd. R.T.Feel The Hon’ble Lt*Col.C.G.Prior, C.I.E., ■ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.u Copy. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l (E 6229/196/91) 13th December, 1939. Dear Gibeon, Would you please refer to my letter of the 21et September, to i^eel under this number, regarding the pre-emption of Bahrain and Haaa oil ? that it would be preferable not to commandeer any Hasa oil lying in the Bahrain refinery. We have since gone into the question more fully and, though we do not appear to have received the text of any agreement between C.A.S.O.C. and the Bahrain Petroleum Company, it would seem from the enclosures to your official letter P.Z .4 221/38 of the 30th June, 1938, that the Hasa oil may be bought by the Bahrain Petroleum Company. 3. If this is so, there would appear to be no need to differentiate betv/een Bahrain and Hasa oil, if the question reaching Bahrain becomes tne property of the Bahrain Petroleum Company ? 2. In paragraph 5 of that letter the view was accepted of commandeering should arise, as all theoil in the Bahrain i refinery v&lt;ould belong to the Bahrain Petroleum Company. 4. Can you say whether it is a fact that all Hasa oil 5 I am sending a copy of this letter to btarling and Jarrett lours sincerely (sgd.) H.1I.Eyres. J.P.Gibson, Esqeeim-DENTIAL . No. c/22 of 1940 . Lla) ! The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent* Bahrain. II. The Political Agent, Muscat. III. The Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, Kuwait. Dated. 2 ?. th.. &amp;n.ua ry.. 1 9 . 40 a 'n ■ Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter Mo. 0/887 dated 14 th December 1939 . 1 V Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. To I. 10 copies of Regulation No.i and 25 copies of Regulations Nos. 2 and 3 . To II &amp; III. 10 copies of Regulat ion No. 1. Subject. War Emergency Regulations■ Persian Gulf States. NOTICE. The following Defence Regulations, made by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and hereby declared to be urgent, are published for general information. These Regulations supplement the law already administered by the Political Resident and the Political Agents subordinate to him, and do not in any way affect the penalties provided under Section 121 ^ of the Indian Penal Code, under which a person who wages war against His Majesty, or attempts to wage such war, or abets the waging of such war, may be punished with death. C. G. PRIOR, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrein, September 12, 1989. Defence Regulations male under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1989. No. 1 of 1939. 1. These Regulations shall apply in the territories of the Sheikh of Koweit, the Sheikh of Bahrein, the Sheikh of Qatar and the tan of Muscat and Oman (hereinafter referred to as the 10664—1 20224territories), and shall be applicable therein respectively to all persons to whom the Koweit Order in Council, 1985, applies, to all persons to whom the Bahrein Order in Council, 1918, applies, to all persons to whom the Qatar Order in Council, 1989, applies, and to the persons referred to in paragraphs (1) and (3) of Article 8 of the Muscat Order in Council, 1915. 2. —(1) If, as respects any area or premises within the territories, it appears to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to be necessary or expedient in the interests of public order or security that special precautions should he taken to prevent the entry of unauthorised persons, he may by order declare that area or those premises to he a protected place for the purposes of this Regula tion; and so long as the order is in force, no person shall, subject to any exemptions for which provision may he made by the order, he in that area or those premises without the permission of such authority or person as may he specified in the order. (2) Any unauthorised person entering a protected place shall be liable to a penalty of imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or of a fine not exceeding 1,500 rupees or of both, and may he deported. (3) Any person who loiters in the vicinity of a protected place and continues to loiter in that vicinity after being requested by the appropriate person to leave it shall be liable to a fine not exceeding 500 rupees, or to imprisonment for one month on failure of payment. (4) The powers conferred on the Political Resident by paragraph (1) of this Regulation may be exercised within their respective spheres of jurisdiction by the Political Agents at Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat. 3. Any person doing an act within the territories with intent to impair the efficiency or impede the working of any vessel, aircraft, vehicle, machinery, apparatus or any other thing used or intended to be used for the purposes of any of His Majesty’s Forces or for the purposes of any undertaking connected with the performance of services essential for the operations of those forces or the prosecu tion of the war or the maintenance of communications shall be liable to a penalty of imprisonment for a term not exceeding 14 years and may be deported. 4. Any person within the territories without lawful authority and in any manner likely to prejudice the efficient prosecution of the war obtaining, recording, communicating to any other person, or publishing, or having in his possession any information which would or might he directly or indirectly useful to the enemy, shall he liable to a penalty of imprisonment for a term not exceeding 14 years, and may he deported. 5. Any person endeavouring in any way to influence public opinion in the territories in a manner likely to be prejudicial to the efficient prosecution of the war shall he liable to a penaltyimprisonment tor a term not exceeding one year or of a fine of 5,000 rupees or of both, and may be deported. 0. Any person whose presence within the territories is deemed by the Political Resident to be prejudicial to public order or security may be deported. ~• —(1) Any person whose presence in the territories is deemed by the Political Resident to be prejudicial to public order or security may be refused entry into the territories. (2) r l he powers conferred on the Political Resident by para graph (1) of this Regulation may be exercised within their respective spheres of jurisdiction by the Political Agents at Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat. B.—(1) 1 he Political Resident may, in the territories of the Sheikh of Bahrein and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, by order in writing— (u) direct that any postal article or class or description of postal articles in course of transmission by post shall be inter cepted or detained or shall otherwise be disposed of; (b) direct that any message or class of messages to or from any person or class of persons or relating to any particular subject brought for transmission by, or transmitted or received by, any telegraph, shall not be transmitted, or shall be intercepted or detained, or shall be disclosed to any person mentioned in the order. (2) The Political Resident may, by order in writing, delegate his powers under this Section to the Political Agents at Bahrein and Muscat for exercise within the limits of the Bahrein and Muscat Orders in Council respectively. (8) Any person who fails to comply with an order in writing under this Section shall be liable to a fine not exceeding 1.000 rupees or to imprisonment for two months in lieu of payment. 9.—(1) If, as respects any proceedings before a court held under any of the Orders in Council referred to in the first of these Regula tions, the court is satisfied that it is expedient in the interests of public safety and of defence to do so, the court— (a) may give directions that throughout or during any part of the proceedings such persons or classes of persons shall be excluded; (/&gt;) may give directions prohibiting or restricting the disclosure of information with respect to the proceedings. (2) If any person contravenes any directions given by the court under the preceding paragraph, then, without prejudice to the law relating to the contempt of court, he shall be liable to a penalty of imprisonment for a term not exceeding 8 months or to a fine not exceeding 1.500 rupees or both.10. Every document purporting to be an order issued by the Political Resident in pursuance of or having effect under these Regulations and to be signed by him shall be received in evidence, and shall, until the contrary be proved, be deemed to be an order issued by the Political Resident. 11. The provisions of Part III of the Koweit Order in Council. 1985, the Bahrein Order in Council, 1913, the Qatar Order in Council, 1989, and the Muscat Order in Council, 19i5, relating to ciiminal matters shall apply, in so far as they may be applicable, to the trial of offences against these Regulations. The provisions of art \ of those Orders shall similarly apply in cases where the persons referred to in Article 8 (iii) of the said Koweit, Bahrein and Qatar Orders in Council are concerned. C. G. PRIOR, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrein, September 12, 1939.Ui Telegram From To Repeated No. A 629 Inter. Air Headquarters, Iraq. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait Political Agent, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Dated Received 1st April 1940 2nd April 1940 r Propose Major Rose successor to Major Price as G.S.O. Air Headquarters Iraq visit Sharjah one day Muscat two days Bahrain two days Kuwait one day commencing about April 24th to meet your representatives and discuss local defence arrangements, is this suitable and have you any suggestions re: details ?Telegram Q • From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Mo. 132. Dated and received the 3rd April 1940. (Jfj) Air Officer Commanding's telegram Mo.A 629 dated April 1st. Have you any comments ?Telegram 'Inter' From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Air Headquarters, Iraq. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. No. Dated 3rd April 1940 U^t Your telegram A 629 dated the 1st April. Proposal'convenient but I think'Rose'can ^ se 0 all necessary at» Sharjah in t»wo hours and t*lnie thus saved could profitably be spent in Bahrain. PoliticalTelegram From To Repeated No. m .«v • 1940 J i! U'' -5 Ptf. 5 ! Inter. Political Resident, Bushire. Air Officer Commanding British Forces in Iraq. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. 137. Dated and received the 5th April 1940. n Your telegram No.A 629 dated April 1st. I suggest Kuwait would be glad of early visit otherwise proposals suitable.From Political Tiesident, Bushire. To Political /-gent, Bahrain, No. 143. Dated and received the 7th April 1940. o ) Three Staff Officers have visited Kuwait to examine defence nro f iects and Galloway says that they may come to Bahrain in three days time. I know nothing about them but I am taking up the matter. PriorTelegram From To Inter H.A.F. Headquarters, Iraq. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain (Pass to Resident Persian Gulf). Political Agent, I'uscat Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain Ko. A 1668. Dated and received the 17th April 1940. C Proposed visit of Lajor Rose to Bahrain and Muscat about April 24th unavoidably postponed but hopes to visit Kuwait only at an early date to be suggested later. &amp; /Yv. V/vo &gt;W&lt;V&gt;» ,The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). (it l British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated . iaUi A P ril ^-940 Reference to previous correspondence : \% x * Political Resident’s telegram ho.143 dated 7th April 1940. &lt; l U S Description of Enclosure. ^^ ^ Name and Date. Subject. India Office telegram No. 1790 dated 16th April 1940. Staff tour to Kuwait and Bahrain.Telegram jj’rom To Repeated No.1790 3 3ecretary of State for India, London. Government of India, Simla. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated 16th received 17th April 1940. y Your telegram No.1055 April 9th. Staff tour to Kuwait and Bahrain. War Office much regret failure to notify Political Resident in advance and inconvenience caused to political authorities thereby. They have taken necessary steps to prevent this occurring again. Secretary of Staten Ab a state of war no./ exists between tbe High British Government and the country of Italy the following regula tions applicable to persons under the jurisdiction of the Bahrain Government, are enacted and decreed by tiie Government of Bahrain. !• whoever aages war against tho nigh British Government, or attempts to wage such war, or abets tbe waging of such war shall oe liable to be punished with death or imprisonment and shall also be liable to fine. 2. If, ao respects any erea or prcnrisec within the territory of Bahrain it appears to tne Government of Bahrain to be neoens.sry or expedient in tue interests of public order or security that special precautions should be taiian to prevent the entry of unautnoriseu persons, they may by order declare « that area or these premises to be a protected place for the purpose of these regulations; and so loru: as the order is in force, no person shall, subject to any exemptions for which provision may be made by the order, be in that area or those premises without the permission of such authority or person as may be specified in the order. 3. Any unauthorised person entering a protected place shall be liable to a penalty of imprisonment for a t-jm not excee ding three i^oaths or of a fine not exceeding fs. i,5B0/- or of both, and may be deported.4. «ny person who loiters in the vicinity of a protected place and continues to loiter in that vicinity after being requested by the appropriate person to leave it shall be liable to a fine not exceeding !?j. 500/-, or to imprisonment for one month on failure of payiaent. 0. *ny jxjrson doing an act within tae territory of liahrein with intent to impair the efficiency or impede the working Ot any vessel, aircraft, vehicle, machinery, apparatus of any other thing used or intended to be used for the purpose of any of the forces of the high British Government or for the pur poses of any undertaking connected with the performance of services essential for the operations of tnose forces or the proaeoutior oi the* wtr or tie maintenance of communications shall be liable to e penalty of imprisonment for a term not exceeding fourteen years, amt may be deported, b. Any parson within the territory of Bahrain without lawful authority and in any manner likely to prejudice the efficient prosecution oi the war obtaining, recording, communicating to a.iy other person, or publishing, or havic,;- in his possession any information which wotuu «• ;*ight be directly o: indirectly usefua. to the enemy, shall bo liable to a penaity of imprison ment for a term not exceeding fourteen years, and may be deported. 7. Any person endeavoring in any way to influence public opinion in tne territory of Bahrain in a manner likely to be prejudicial to the efficiont prosecution of the war shall bo liable to a penalty of iririaonm nt^ for a term not excee ding one ye nr, cr of a fine of 5,000/- or of both and may be deported.fi a - 3 - * 8* Any person waoee presence within the territory of Bahrein is deeuetf by the Cov«rnr:ent of B&amp;hroi^ to be pre judicial to public order or security aey be deported* 9* Any person whose presence in the territory of baiirain is deoaed by the: rrovemment of Bahrain to be prejuaioial to public order or security iaay be refused entry into the territory of Bahrain. IQ* All previous and future proclamations issued by the Bahrain Government in connection with the war will apply with equal force to Itcly zz to SerL.cSiy* By order of JftLiad bin Isn Al&amp;helifaii, Ruler of Brhrain* rated, 11th J/jbral, lB5v. 16th June, 194Q* T*G* ■ &lt;&lt;*11The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; jjis Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents. Adviser s Office, No P/ ? S' f ~ F* Manamah, Bahrain. Dated 17th July, 1940. Description of enclosure. Name and date 3 copies of Notice No. 36/1358 dated 3, 1939 issued by the Bahrain Government. 3 copies of Notice No. 14/1359 dated 16th June 1940 issued by the Bahrain Government. Subject. War between the High British Government and Germany. War between the High British Government and Italy. Reference to s.z. \ neeGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, DEPARIMENT. EXPRESS LETTER ConflrifcntiLJL [N. H—fliis is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ Reference Political Resident *3 teiegrem No# 531 d^teti the 13th July 1340 (Copy enclosed to (l) and ( 8 )). 2 # I forward herewith copies of iaLlq3 issued by the Bahrain Government on the 3rd September 1333 in respect of Germany and the IGth June 1340 in respect of Italy# From Political Agent, Bahrain# To H#M# Secretary of State for India, India Office, Loncon# Repeated The Secretary to the Government of India, Internal Affairs Department, Simla The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire# No &gt; C/601 - i.a/43 Political Agent, Bahrein# s. 6 . MPP-400S&amp;P—fM 480)—26 7-34-2,00,000.l.a/43 Inter Political Agent, Bahrain. Air Headquarters, Habbaniyah 358 28th September 1940. Weightman to Rose. I am leaving Bahrain for good on 15th October. I hope it will be possible for you to get down here for at least two days before then. Various questions including possibility of forming Indian wing of Defence Force requires urgent discussion. Telegram From To No. Dated PoliticalCONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documenttPf^ for favour of hie viewe. British Consulate-General, BUSH1RE. Dated... 23r&lt;i 0otol,er » 1 94 0 . Gamp, Bahrain. Reference to previous correspondence : Government of India Express Letter NO.D.5811-N/40 of 2nd October 1940* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Ifldia Office letter No*P.Z 4301/40 of 6th August 1940 Subject. Persian Gulf Defence regulations*Copy. P.Z.4301/40. Confidential. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON .S *W. 1 • 6th August,1940* Dear Caroe, The Persian ^ulf Defence Regulations which v/ere issued by the Political Resident as a matter of urgency after the out break of war under the Persian ^ulf States ^Emergency) Order in Council were drafted deliberately in as simplified a foim as possible, and it occurs to us that it might now be useful to consider whether experience or further consideration locally roa^ have revealed a need to amend or supplement them in certain directions. We should be glad if you would examine the matter, in consultation with the Political Resident, and let us know whether any modifications of or additions to these Defence Regulations appear to be desirable. 2. This enquiry has been suggested by our examination of the powers available to the Political Agent, ^ahxain, in particul ar the power of deportation, in case any action had to be taken „— ta'-L / io - (e j against Philby while he was within the Political Agent*s juris diction, 1 see our telegram of the 25th July .No.4206). Apparently a deportation order by itself can have no legal effect beyond the territorial limits of Bahrain and accordingly all that the / Political Agent could do would be to cause the deportee to be removed from the area of his jurisdiction; once outside that area the deportee is a free man and the Political Agent has no control over his movements. He does not even possess the power, conferred in British India under e.g. Defence ©f India Rule 26, of specify ing the manner and route by which the deportee is to remove him self. But it may be that these limitations on the Political Agent *s legal powers are not in practice of serious consequence, as he could doubtless arrange for the deportation order to be / madenade when an opportunity oooura to set the deportee on a etea^er hound for a suitable destination ? Even the power possessed by the Government of India to specify the route would not be entirely effective since, as i have said, the deportee becomes free of control after leaving the area of the Political Agent's jurisdiction, and unless he could be put on a ship go-n 0 diiect to India, he might demand to leave it at some intermediate port. 3 . i am sending a copy of this letter to frior. yours sincerely, sd. R.T.Peel. OeK*Caroe Esq..,C• I.E*, Government of India, External Affairs Department.No•C/8S2-1•a/43• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th November 1940. From Major R.G.3.W. Alban, O.B.B., Political Agent, Bahrein, To The lion* hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. X have the honour to refer to Mr. Peel *3 demi-official letter to Mr. Ceroe, No. P.Z. 4301/40 dated the 6 th August 1940, sent under your Printed letter No.C/372 dated the 23rd October 1940, requesting examination of the Persian Gulf Defence Regulations in the light of experience gained from their operation. 2. At present the following Regulations are in operation in Bahrain (i) No.l of 1939 (Tlie original Defence Regulation which was drafted before the war and to which Mr. Peel presumably refers). (ii) No.2 of 1339 (Food and Price Control). (iii) No.3 of 1939 (Control over mails). (iv) No.l of 1940 (Control over oil Sxports). (v) No.2 of 1940 (Bxit permits for European British subjects). (vi) No.4 of 1940 (black-out). This last Defence Regulation lias presumably not yet had the approval of the Secretary of State for India. 3. These Regulations have given us all the power we needto deal with the various new situations created by the War and the ability of the Political Resident to issue fresh Regulations at once provided the.:, are urgent seems to cover our future requirements. 4. The position with regard to deportations is perhaps not entirely satisfactory but so far as I can see no amend ment of 1 ohe Defence Regulation can give us jurisdiction over ships at sea outside the territorial waters of Bahrain. In practice no serious difficulties have been encountered or need be envisaged In the future* provided British ships continue to run between the Persian Bulf and India. British and American subjects if deported will presumably always be sent to India where facilities for dealing vith them exist. Masters of mail steamers have always been found willing to co-operate and to taxe steps to ensure that deportees do not leave the ships at intermediate ports. In any case the absence of valid passports and visas would make it difficult for them to land at a port between Bahrain and India. Local inhabitants i.e. Iraqis, Rejdis and Persians etc., have practically always been deported by native craft. 5# I do not consider therefore that at present any amendments to the Defence Regulations are called for. I have the honour to be, Sir Your most obedient servant Political Agent, BahreinCONFIDENTIAL. D.O, No. c/t&gt;29 o4^ /i» - \- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Major R.G.W.Alban, Political Agent, Kuwait. ' and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. 8th December 1940. Gamp, KUWAIT. Reference to previous correspondent Major Alban’a D.O.letter No.C/882-1. the Reference to previous correspondent Major Alban’a D.O.letter No.C/882-1. 14th November 1940, and his conversation with the Political Resident on the 3rd December.1940. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Residency demi-official letter No.C/526 of 8th December 1940. Defence Regulations.Confldintlal# 3«C« Wo* C/526* offloo of tho lolltloal itkidtnt in tho oreion auXf t At .V 5 Jaap Kuwait* Couombor 8 th* 1940* IXeutiO r^for to looX'o doni-official letter Ko* r*Z* 4dci/4c dated the 6 th auguet 1940 and to your demi-official ^Apreaa letter no# &gt;• 58 1 !• r i /40 dated the L V 2 nd cotober 1940* 2# do far aa 1 can see no araenduent to Article 6 of the Jefenoe degulatlooa IWo# i of 1939} will ^Iyo the lolltloal A 0 ent Juriediotlon over a deportee onoe he la outelde territorial aratere* but 1 think that the addition of the worde 'in euuh Banner* by ouch tine and by ftuoh route ae may be specified in the order* to the existin^ article would dive him power® to suture that no de ortee travelled by other than a uritieh thi r to India* 3 # At prekent luropeane and ^ericant are deported from Bahrain by B*X* steamer and Irakis* ;;audle and iersians are usually repatriated by dhow# The passport oontrol at Bahrain ensures* at any rats in theory* that / none of the latter return# as far as ths former are concerned, we can always etrrange for a de t ortee to be refused permission to land at an Arab port* and 1erslan restrietions make it highly improbable that he would be allowed to land at an Iranian port without a valid visu# Yours sincerely, Sd. C.G. Prior. _ ‘os* .squire* J#X#J3** l#J#d#* e^retary to the Oovernment of India* External Affairs leiartoent* Hew islhl#The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to % Tfte Politicsl Agent, Bahra in. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement/{#). §\ British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated.. 1 , £ ..J^ nu£ r y 1^41 Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter Nc. c/529 of^Stii December 1940. 0 v m 4 j Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Endorsement from Government of India No- F.&lt;;92-N/40 dated 3rd January 1941. n Subject. } Proposed amendment of the Persian Gulf Defence RegulationsCCMPIDKNTIAL D.O. Nos i’. ^9^-N/40. External Affairs Department. New Delhi, The 3rd January 1941. SUBJECT: Proposed ainendraen t of the Persian U ulf Defence Regulations. My dear Peel, Please refer to your D.O. dated the 6th August 1940, to Caroe. letter -WosP.Z.4301/40 2* Ve have consulted Prior, who remarks that no amendment of Article 6 of tne defence Regulations (ho.l of 1939) will give the Political Agent jurisdiction over a deportee once he is outside territorial waters, but that the addition of the words 'in such manner, by such time and by such route as may be specified in the Order* to the existing article would give him powers to ensure that no deportee travels by other than a -British ship to India » 3* Prior adds that at present Europeans and Americans are deported from Banrain by ±5.1 .Steamer while Iraqis Saudis and Persians are usually repatriated by dhow. The passport control at hanrain ensures, at any ra-e in theory that none of the latter return. As f$r as the former are cone emeu, arrangements can always oe made for a deportee to oe refuseu permission to lanu at an Arab port, ana Persian restrictions make it highly improbable that ie would be allowed to land at an Iranian port without a /alid visa. 4 « agree with Prior, and suggest that Article 6 of the defence -Regulations (No. 1 of 1939) may be amended as proposed in paragraph 2 above. To R.T.Pec?!, Esquire, CBE., MC., India Office, LONDON. Yours sincerely, Sd/- H .V/e ightman.Confidential z ®) ■ No•C/1043-1.a/43* Political Agency, Bahrain, 6 th November 1941. To The Hon'blethe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain* Sub.iect i Proposed amendment of the Persian Gulf Defence Regulations* Memorandum Reference your Printed letter No* 78-S dated % the 25th January 1941. 2 . I would be grateful to know whether any decision has been reached on the matter in question. Political Agent, Bahrain■ v V- GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. (§) (Vt r Confidential* EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [^•®* This ia an ORIGIN A. L message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No - C/630 Of 1941. n . . Simla t ._ , 0 Dated the 12th Hovamb.r, W 41 . • xxxxxxx /A. • JSolitioal Resident, Bushire, Camp, Bahrain. To - The Secretary to the GoTermaent of India, External Affaire JUepartuent, hew helhi. Repeated H^rMaJeety’s Secretary of State for India, London. x ^he Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to hie jAenorandua ho.C/1043-1.a/43 of 6th hoyember 1941 Subject * Proposed auendment of Persian Gulf hefenoe Regulations. Demi- offioial . Reference correspondence ending with GoTernment of India letter ho.P.29S-h/40, dated the 3rd January 1941 to the India Office. 2. Has any decision been readied ? .J Attested . m od. W.R.Hay. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. n&lt;r7 for Secretary to thie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. {Signature) S/44. MFP—985 S&amp;P—(M.1597)—27-11.30-10,000. [Designation)STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1166 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY ^ Specified Persons The Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) Order, 1939, dated September 13, 1939, made by the Board of Trade. The Board of Trade, in pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by subsection (2) of section 2 of the Trading with the Enemy Act, I939( a ), and of all other powers enabling them in that behalf, hereby order as follows: — (1) Each of the persons specified in the Schedule hereto shall for the purposes of the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, be deemed to be an enemy within the meaning of that Act during such period as this Order shall in relation to such person remain in force. (2) (i) The Interpretation Act, 1889 (b), applies to the inter pretation of this Order as it applies to the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. (ii) This Order may be cited as the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) Order, 1939, and shall come into operation on the 18th day of September, 1939. Dated this Thirteenth day of September, 1939. W. B. Brown, Secretary of the Board of Trade. (a) 2 &amp; 3 Geo. 6. c. 89. (b) 52 &amp; 53 Viet. c. 63.Firm. Norsk Akkumulator Co. A/S. Norsk Telefunken, Radiotieselskap Nottebohm Trading Co. Orenstein &amp; Koppel S.A. m . Osiam-Cia Argentina de Lamparas Electricas S.A. Osram A/S. Osram, O.Y. A.B. Osram A/S. Overbeck, G. Oversjeisk Transit A/S. ... Pance, A. Ponte, B. Putrimas, Alexander Radios Telefunken Reimers &amp; Co., Fritz. Reuter, Ingenieur Byra A. Rhenania, S.A. 'iberena del Plata,” Cia. Sud- americana de Comercio S.A. Rijn-En Zeetransport Maat- schappij, N.V. Ringnes, Ellef Ringys, Planas and Nie Did- ziulis. Roechling Stahl A.G Rohde &amp; Jorgens S.A., Mattias... Ruhr und Saar Kohle A.G. S.A.B.A.T Saalman &amp; Co. Salevskis, Martin ... Address. Pilestredet 75 c, Oslo, Norway. 0 vre Vollgate 11, Oslo, Norway. San Salvador, Salvador. San Martin 66, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Luca 2251, Buenos Aires, Argen tina. Solvgade 10, Copenhagen, Den mark. Helsingfors, Finland. Pilestredet 75 c, Oslo, Norway. Cape Palmas, Monrovia. Branch at Grand Cess. Liberia. Skippergate 27, Oslo, Norway. Guayaquil, Ecuador. Bahia de Caraquez, Ecuador. Lithuania. Santiago, Chile. San Jose, Costa Rica. Keskuskatu 1, Helsingfors, Fin land. 215, Avenue dTtalie, Antwerp, Belgium. Av. de Mayo 869, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Pr. Heindrikkade 160, Rotterdam, Holland. Stortingsgate 22, Oslo, Norway. Lithuania. Zurich and Basle, Switzerland. 2 Quai Ortelius, Antwerp, Belgium. Basle, Switzerland. 4, Quai van Meteren, Antwerp, Belgium. Guayaquil, Ecuador. Lithuania.Kralja Petra 21, Belgrade, • Yugo slavia. Panama. Peru 722, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Tehran, Iran. Av. Pte. R.S. Pena 933, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Tokyo &amp; Osaka, Japan. Tehran, Iran. * Osaka and Tokyo, Japan. Turku Schweizerische Filiale der Langbein Pfanhauser Werke, A.G. Siegel, Carl. A/S. ... Siemens, A/S. Siemens-Bauunion, Cia Platense de Construcciones S.A. “ Siemens ” Bulgarian Electrical Co. Ltd. Siemens Co. Ltd. ... Kerikinkatu Finland. Isfahan, Iran. Bolivia. Zurich, Switzerland. Tallinn, Estonia. Riga, Latvia. Av. de Mayo 869, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Tzaritza, lonna 25, Sofia, Bulgaria. Technical Bureau, Dorostol, and Lulin, Sofia, Bulgaria.San Jose, Limon, and Puntarenas, Costa Rica. Sarmiento 329, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Avenida Rio Branco 66/74, Ri° de Janeiro, Brazil. 4 Rua de S. Francisco, Oporto, Portugal. Zurich, Switzerland. Telef unken Gesellschaft fuer Drahtlose Telegraphic G.m.b.H. Berlin. Telefunken Radio S.A. ... Tense, Oscar Thalheim A/S, Georg “ Thyssen-Lametal ”, Cia Indus trial y Mercantil Thyssen, Ltda. Timmermann B. &amp; Cie. ... Undeutsch, F. &amp; Co. United Agencies Co. S.A. ... Uslar, Armin Von ... Von Bergen &amp; Cia, J. Victoria-Linoleumfabrik A/S. Vorwerk &amp; Co. Vulcan Company Waffenfabrik Solothurn A.G. 2 Echizenbori i-Chome, Kyobashi- Ku, Tokyo, Japan. Santiago, Chile. Lithuania. Manta, Ecuador. Bahia de Cara- quez, Ecuador. Esmeraldas, Ecuador. Zurich, Switzerland. 13, Bucharest Greece. Tallinn, Estonia. Riga, Latvia. Belgrano 752, Argentina. Street, Athens, Buenos Aires, Valparaiso &amp; Santiago, Chile. Tehran, Iran. Panama. Obispo 258, Havana, Cuba. Bolivia. Sandvika, Nr. Oslo, Norway. Sales office: Drammensveien 6, Oslo. Valparaiso, and at Santiago, Chile. Veerhaven, Rotterdam, Holland. Solothurn, Switzerland. ET13 (3831—7) wt. 6—1 45000 9/39 P. St. G. 416 Firm. Wayss &amp; Freytag, S.A. Empresa Constructora. Weinberger &amp; Paulmichl ... Weisgerber, Erwin ... \# &amp; Co. Ltd Westfalische Transport A.G. Wille &amp; Cia Ltda., Theodor Wimmer, J. &amp; Cia. Witkopp, Otto Woermann, A. &amp; Co Wolfinger, Carl ... Zeiss, Carl Zeiss Kabushiki Kaisha, Carl Zeiss Svenska A/B. Zeller, Mozer &amp; Cia. tieriacks, Becker y Cia. ... Address. Av. L.N. Alem 168, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Athens, Greece. Ciudad Trujillo, Dominican Re public. Monrovia and branches at Since, Grand Bassa and Cape Palmas, Cape Mount, Marshall, River Cess, Grand Cess, Sasstown, Liberia. W esterkade 31, Rotterdam, Holland. Av. Rio Branco 79-81, Rio de Janeiro, and branches, Brazil. 34, Avenida 24 de Julio, Lisbon, and 18, Rua Monsinho da Salneira, Oporto, Portugal. Lithuania. Monrovia and branches at Cape Mount, Grand Bassa and Cape Palmas, Liberia. Tabriz, Iran. B. Irigoyen 330, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Tokyo and Osaka, Japan. Kungsgatan 33, Stockholm Sweden. Bolivia. Bolivia.STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1166 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY Specified Persons ^ I HE IRADING WITH THE ENEMY (SPECIFIED PERSONS) ORDER, 1939, dated September 13, 1939, made by the Board of Irade. * LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 26 York Street, Manchester 1; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any booksellerSTATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1198 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY r-' Custodian The Trading with the Enemy (Custodian) Order, 1939, dated September 16, 1939, made by the Board of Trade UNDER SECTION 7 OF THE TRADING WITH THE ENEMY ACT, 1939 (2 &amp; 3 Geo. 6. c. 89). The Board of Trade in exercise of the powers conferred upon them by Section 7 of the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, (hereinafter called the Act ’ ’) and of all other powers, enabling them in that behalf do hereby make the following Order: — 1 .—(i) Any money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be payable to or for the benefit of a person who is an enemy, and any money which is to be deemed for the pur poses of the Act to be money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be so payable, shall be paid to the Custodian. (ii) Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing para graph, there shall be paid to the Custodian in particular any money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be payable to or for the benefit of a person who is an enemy' Jt^ way of: {a) dividends, bonus or interest, in respect of any shares, stock, debentures, debenture stock, bonds or other securities, issued by any company or government, or any municipal or other authority; (6) payment of any securities which have become payable on maturity or by being drawn for payment or otherwise; (c) interest or other payment in respect of any loan or deposit whether secured or unsecured; (d) profits or share of profits in any business, syndicate or other mercantile enterprise or adventure'; (e) debt, including money in the possession of any bankers, whether on deposit or current account or whether held in trust or in custody for or for the benefit of an enemy; (/) money due under or in respect of any policy of assurance;(g) rent or other payment reserved out of or payable in re spect of freehold or leasehold property or any interest in land or any manor; (h) payment in respect of any requisitioned property; (t) payment arising under any trust, will or settlement (iii) Any money which would, but for the provisions of Section 4 or Section 5 of the Act, be payable to any purported assignee, transferee or allottee, shall be paid to the Custodian. (iv) Any money required to be paid under the foregoing paragraphs of this Article to the Custodian, shall be paid: (a) within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Order, if the money has become payable or would, but for the existence of a state of war, have become payable before the coming into force of this Order; or (b) within fourteen days after the day on which a person becomes an enemy, if the money is required to be paid to the Custodian by reason of that person being an enemy and the money has become payable or would, but for the existence of a state of war, have become payable before the day on which that person becomes an enemy; or (c) in any other case, within fourteen days after the day on which the money becomes payable or would, but for the existence of a state of war, become payable. (v) Nothing in the foregoing provisions of this Article shall taken to require payment to the Custodian of any money, the payment of which is authorised: (a) to some other person, under an authority given generally or specially by, or by any person autho rised in that behalf by, a Secretary of State, the Treasury or the Board of Trade; or (b) to a Clearing Office, under any order made under Section 1 of the Debts Clearing Offices and Import Restrictions Act, 1934( a ). Provided that the pro visions of this paragraph shall not affect any obliga tion of the Clearing Office to make payment to the Custodian of any money which is to be deemed for the purposes of the Act to be money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be payable to or for the benefit of a person who is an enemy. (a) 24 &amp; 25 Geo. 5. c. 31.3 ^ W The Board of Trade, in any case where it appears to them to be expedient to do so, may by order vest in the Custodian such enemy property as may be prescribed or the right to transfer such other enemy property as may be pre scribed. Any order so made by the Board of Trade is herein- afflii referred to as “ Vesting Order .(ii) The Custodian shall, except in so far as may be other wise prescribed by the Vesting Order, have such powers with regard to the enemy property or the right to transfer enemy property vested in him by a Vesting Order as are prescribed by this Order. (i”) A Vesting Order as respects property of any description shall be of the like purport and effect as a vesting order as respects property of the same description made by the High Court under the Trustee Act, 1925(a), and shall be sufficient to vest in the Custodian any property or the right to transfer any property as provided by the Vesting Order without the necessity of any further conveyance, assurance or document. (iv) If the benefit of an application made by or on behalf or for the benefit of an enemy or enemy subject for any patent is by an order made under the Act vested in the Custodian, the patent may be granted to the Custodian as patentee and may, notwithstanding anything in Section 12 of the Patents and Designs Act, 1907( b ), be sealed accordingly by the Comp troller General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks, and any patent so granted to the Custodian shall be deemed to be property vested in him by such order as aforesaid. 3 * (i) The Custodian shall, subject to the provisions of the next succeeding paragraph and except in so far as the Board of Trade either generally or in any specific case may otherwise direct or order, hold any money paid to him under this Order and any property or the right to transfer any property vested in him under any Vesting Order until the termination of the present war, and shall thereafter deal with the same in such manner as the Board of Trade shall direct. (ii) The Custodian, acting under a general or special direc tion of the Board of Trade, may at any time pay over any particular money paid to him under this Order or transfer any particular property in respect of which a Vesting Order has been made to or for the benefit of the person who would have been entitled thereto but for the operation of the Act or any Order made thereunder or to any person appearing to the Custodian to be authorised by such person to receive the same. (a) 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 5. c. 19. (b) 7 Edw. 7. c. 29.(iii) Any money paid to the Custodian under this Order and any property in respect of which a Vesting Order has been made shall not be liable to be attached or otherwise taken in execution. (iv) The receipt of the Custodian or any person duly autho rised by him to sign receipts on his behalf for any money j^id to him under this Order shall be a good discharge to the pUSon paying the same. 4 . No person shall, without the consent of the Board of Trade, save as directed by this Order transfer, part with or otherwise deal with the property of an}' enemy. 5 . — (i) Any person who holds or manages for or on behalf of an enemy any property shall, within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Order (or, if the property comes into his possession or under his control after the coming into force of this Order or the person for or on behalf of whom property is held or managed, becomes an enemy after that date, then within fourteen days after the time when the property comes into the possession or under the control of the first mentioned person or the person for or on behalf of whom the property is held or managed becomes an enemy, as the case may be), by notice in writing communicate the fact to the Custodian, and shall fur nish the Custodian with such returns, accounts and other information, and produce for inspection such documents in rela tion thereto, as the Custodian may require. (ii) Any enemy subject who holds or manages any property or any person who holds or manages any property for or on behalf of an enemy subject shall furnish the Custodian with suota^ returns, accounts and other information, and produce for inspef^ tion, such documents in relation thereto, as the Custodian may require. (iii) Every company incorporated in the United Kingdom and every company which though not incorporated in the United Kingdom has a share transfer or share registration office in the United Kingdom shall, within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Order, by notice in writing communicate to the Custodian full particulars of all shares, stock, debentures and debenture stock, bonds or other securities issued by the com pany which are held by or for the benefit of an enemy; and, if any shares, stock, debentures or debenture stock, bonds or other securities issued by any such company as aforesaid are held by or for the benefit of any person who becomes an enemy after the coming into force of this Order, the company shall, within fourteen days after the day on which that person becomes an enemy, by like notice communicate to the Custodian the like particulars in regard to that person.5 (iv) Every partner of every firm, any partner of which has, at any time before the coming into force of this Order, become an enemy, or to which money has been lent for the purpose of the business of the firm by a person who so became an enemy, shall, within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Or&lt;®, by notice in writing communicate to the Custodian full particulars as to any share of profits or interest due to such enemy; and every partner of every firm, any partner of which becomes an enemy after the coming into force of this Order, or to which a person who becomes an enemy has lent money for the purpose aforesaid before the day on which that person becomes an enemy, shall, within fourteen days after the day on which the partner or person concerned becomes an enemy, by like notice communicate to the Custodian the like particulars in regard to that partner or person. 6. —(i) Where, in exercise of the powers conferred upon him, the Custodian purposes to sell any shares or stock forming part of the capital of any company, or any securities issued by the company, in respect of which a Vesting Order has been made, then any law or any regulation of the company to the contrary notwithstanding, the company may, with the consent of the Board of Trade, purchase the shares, stock or securities, and any shares, stock or securities so purchased may from time to time be re-issued by the company. (ii) Where the Custodian executes a transfer of any shares, stock or securities which he is empowered to transfer by a Vest ing Order, the company or other body in whose books the shares, ^^:k or securities are registered shall, upon the receipt of the jisfer so executed by the Custodian and upon being required by him so to do, register the shares, stock or securities in the name of the Custodian or other transferee notwithstanding any regulation or'stipulation of the company or other body, and not withstanding that the Custodian is not in possession of the certificate, script or other document of title relating to the shares, stock or securities transferred; but such registration shall be without prejudice to any lien or charge in favour of the company or other body, or to any other lien or charge of which the Custodian has notice. 7 . There shall be retained by the Custodian fees equal to 2 per centum of (а) the amount of monies paid to him, and (б) the value at the date of vesting of any property which is vested in him or of which the right of transfer is vested in him.The value of any property for the purpose of assessing the fees shall be the price which in the opinion of the Board of Trade such property would fetch if sold in the open market. The fees in respect of such property may be retained out of any proceeds of the sale or transfer thereof or out of any income accrued therefrom. ^ 8 . — (i) Any payment required to be made under this Order to the Custodian shall be made to the Custodian for that part of the United Kingdom in which the person making the payment resides or carries on business, and if in any case any doubt should arise, then to such Custodian as the Board of Trade shall direct. (ii) Where any property or the right to transfer any property has been vested in the Custodian for any part of the United Kingdom, the Board of Trade may direct: {a) the transfer of the property to the Custodian of another part of the United Kingdom; (6) the payment to the Custodian of another part of the United Kingdom of the dividend or other income which has arisen or may thereafter arise from any such property. (iii) Where any money has been paid to the Custodian for any part of the United Kingdom, the Board of Trade may direct the payment over of such money to the Custodian for another part of the United Kingdom. 9. —(i) The Interpretation Act, i889( a ), shall apply to this Order as if it were an Act of Parliament. (ii) In this Order the expression “ enemy ' has the s^&gt; meaning as that assigned to it in the Act and the express? ^ ' enemy property ', “ property ' and “ Prescribed ' have the same meanings as those assigned to them in Section 7 of the Act, and references to “ the Custodian ' shall be construed as references to such Custodian of enemy property for any part of the United Kingdom as is prescribed by this Order or any Vesting Order. 10 - (i) In the application of this Order to Scotland— (a) any reference to rent or other payment reserved out of or payable in respect of freehold or leasehold property or any manor shall be construed as a reference to any rent or other payment payable under or stipulated for in a lease or any sum payable by virtue of any feu contract, disposition, contract of ground annual or other deed constituting a burden on heritable property; (a) 52 &amp; 53 Viet. c. 63.(b) for any reference to a vesting order made by the High Court under the Trustee Act, 1925, there shall be substituted a reference to a warrant to complete title granted under section twenty-two of the Trusts (Scotland) Act, 1921 ( a ); and %) “ attached or otherwise taken in execution ' means arrested in execution or in security or otherwise affected by diligence. (ii) In the application of this Order to Northern Ireland the reference to the Trustee Act, 1925, shall be construed as a refer ence to the Trustee Act, 1893 ( b ). 11 . This Order may be cited as the Trading with the Enemy (Custodian) Order, 1939, and shall come into force on the 18th day of September, 1939. Dated the 16th day of September, 1939. W. B. Brown, Secretary of the Board of Trade. (a) 11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5. c. 58. (b) 56 &amp; 57 Viet. c. 53. &lt;3S4°r —7) Wt 6— 1 15,01,0 9/39 P. St. ('..416STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1198 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY Custodian The Trading with the Enemy (Custodian) Order, 1939, dated September 16, 1939, made by the Board of Trade UNDER SECTION 7 OF THE TRADING WITH THE ENEMY ACT, 1939 (2 &amp; 3 Geq. 6. c. 89). LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 26 York Street, Manchester 1; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any booksellerSTATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1939 No. 1198 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY Custodian The Trading with the Enemy (Custodian) Order, 1939, dated September 16, 1939, made by the Board of Trade UNDER SECTION 7 OF THE TRADING WITH THE ENEMY ACT, 1939 (2 &amp; 3 Geo. 6. c. 89). The Board of Trade in exercise of the powers conferred upon them by Section 7 of the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939, (hereinafter called ' the Act ”) and of all other powers, enabling them in that behalf do hereby make the following Order: — 1 .— (i) Any money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be payable to or for the benefit of a person who is an enemy, and any money which is to be deemed for the pur poses of the Act to be money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be so payable, shall be paid to the Custodian. (ii) Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing para graph, there shall be paid to the Custodian in particular any money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be payable to or for the benefit of a person who is an enemy way of: J (а) dividends, bonus or interest, in respect of any shares, stock, debentures, debenture stock, bonds or other securities, issued by any company or government, or any municipal or other authority; (б) payment of any securities which have become payable on maturity or by being drawn for payment or otherwise; (c) interest or other payment in respect of any loan or deposit whether secured or unsecured; (d) profits or share of profits in any business, syndicate or other mercantile enterprise or adventure; (e) debt, including money in the possession of any bankers, whether on deposit or current account or whether held in trust or in custody for or for the benefit of an enemy; (/) money due under or in respect of any policy of assurance;(g) rent or other payment reserved out of or payable in re spect of freehold or leasehold property or any interest in land or any manor; (h) payment in respect of any requisitioned property; (i‘) payment arising under any trust, will or settlement. £ (hi) Any money which would, but for the provisions of Section 4 or Section 5 of the Act, be payable to any purported assignee, transferee or allottee, shall be paid to the Custodian. (iv) Any money required to be paid under the foregoing paragraphs of this Article to the Custodian, shall be paid: (а) within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Order, if the money has become payable or would, but for the existence of a state of war, have become payable before the coming into force of this Order; or (б) within fourteen days after the day on which a person becomes an enemy, if the money is required to be paid to the Custodian by reason of that person being an enemy and the money has become payable or would, but for the existence of a state of war, have become payable before the day on which that person becomes an enemy; or (c) in any other case, within fourteen days after the day on which the money becomes payable or would, but for the existence of a state of war, become payable. (v) Nothing in the foregoing provisions of this Article shall ^ taken to require payment to the Custodian of any money, the payment of which is authorised: (а) to some other person, under an authority given generally or specially by, or by any person autho rised in that behalf by, a Secretary of State, the Treasury or the Board of Trade; or (б) to a Clearing Office, under any order made under Section 1 of the Debts Clearing Offices and Import Restrictions Act, ig34( a ). Provided that the pro visions of this paragraph shall not affect any obliga tion of the Clearing Office to make payment to the Custodian of any money which is to be deemed for the purposes of the Act to be money which would, but for the existence of a state of war, be payable to or for the benefit of a person who is an enemy. (a) 24 &amp; 25 Geo. 5. c. 31.2 . —(i) The Board of Trade, in any case where it appears to them to be expedient to do so, may by order vest in the Custodian such enemy property as may be prescribed or the right to transfer such other enemy property as may be pre scribed. Any order so made by the Board of Trade is herein- flUer referred to as ' Vesting Order (ii) The Custodian shall, except in so far as may be other wise prescribed by the Vesting Order, have such powers with regard to the enemy property or the right to transfer enemy property vested in him by a Vesting Order as are prescribed by this Order. (iii) A Vesting Order as respects property of any description shall be of the like purport and effect as a vesting order as respects property of the same description made by the High Court under the Trustee Act, 1925( a ), and shall be sufficient to vest in the Custodian any property or the right to transfer any property as provided by the Vesting Order without the necessity of any further conveyance, assurance or document. (iv) If the benefit of an application made by or on behalf or for the benefit of an enemy or enemy subject for any patent is by an order made under the Act vested in the Custodian, the patent may be granted to the Custodian as patentee and may, notwithstanding anything in Section 12 of the Patents and Designs Act, 1907 ( b ), be sealed accordingly by the Comp troller General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks, and any patent so granted to the Custodian shall be deemed to be property vested in him by such order as aforesaid. 3 . — (i) The Custodian shall, subject to the provisions of the next succeeding paragraph and except in so far as the Board of Trade either generally or in any specific case may otherwise direct or order, hold any money paid to him under this Order and any property or the right to transfer any property vested in him under any Vesting Order until the termination of the present war, and shall thereafter deal with the same in such manner as the Board of Trade shall direct. (ii) The Custodian, acting under a general or special direc tion of the Board of Trade, may at any time pay over any particular money paid to him under this Order or transfer any particular property in respect of which a Vesting Order has been made to or for the benefit of the person who would have been entitled thereto but for the operation of the Act or any Order made thereunder or to any person appearing to the Custodian to be authorised by such person to receive the same. (a) 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 5. c. 19. (b) 7 Edw. 7. c. 29.\ (* any property in respect of which a Vesting Order has been made shall not be liable to be attached or otherwise taken in execution. (iv) The receipt of the Custodian or any person duly autho rised by him to sign receipts on his behalf for any money paid to him under this Order shall be a good discharge to the peHi! paying the same. 4 . No person shall, without the consent of the Board of Trade, save as directed by this Order transfer, part with or otherwise deal with the property of any enemy. 5. (i) Any person who holds or manages for or on behalf of an enemy any property shall, within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Order (or, if the property comes into his possession or under his control after the coming into force of this Order or the person for or on behalf of whom property is held or managed, becomes an enemy after that date, then within fourteen days after the time when the property comes into the possession or under the control of the first mentioned person or the person for or on behalf of whom the property is held or managed becomes an enemy, as the case may be), by notice in writing communicate the fact to the Custodian, and shall fur nish the Custodian with such returns, accounts and other information, and produce for inspection such documents in rela tion thereto, as the Custodian may require. (ii) Any enemy subject who holds or manages any property or any person who holds or manages any property for or on behalf of an enemy subject shall furnish the Custodian with sucW returns, accounts and other information, and produce for inspeoP^ tion, such documents in relation thereto, as the Custodian may require. (iii) Every company incorporated in the United Kingdom and every company which though not incorporated in the United Kingdom has a share transfer or share registration office in the United Kingdom shall, within fourteen days after the coming into force of this Order, by notice in writing communicate to the Custodian full particulars of all shares, stock, debentures and debenture stock, bonds or other securities issued by the com pany which are held by or for the benefit of an enemy; and, if any shares, stock, debentures or debenture stock, bonds or other securities issued by any such company as aforesaid are held by or for the benefit of any person who becomes an enemy after the coming into force of this Order, the company shall, within fourteen days after the day on which that person becomes an enemy, by like notice communicate to the Custodian the like particulars in regard to that person., [J ? VC1 ? ? artn f u r of ev . eiy firm ' an y partner of which has, at any time before the coming into force of this Order, become an enemy, or to w hich money has been lent for the purpose of , „ US 1 PJ S . S °f fhe firm by a person who so became an enemy, siall, within fourteen days after the coming into force of this (»r, by notice in writing communicate to the Custodian full particulars as to any share of profits or interest due to such enemy; and every partner of every firm, any partner of which becomes an enemy after the coming into force of this Order, or o which a person who becomes an enemy has lent money for the purpose aforesaid before the day on which that person becomes an enemy, shall, within fourteen days after the day on which the partner or person concerned becomes an enemy by like notice communicate to the Custodian the like particulars in regard to that partner or person. 6 . (i) Where, in exercise of the powers conferred upon him, the Custodian purposes to sell any shares or stock forming part of the capital of any company, or any securities issued by the company, in respect of which a Vesting Order has been made, then any law or any regulation of the company to the contrary notwithstanding, the company may, with the consent of the Board of Trade, purchase the shares, stock or securities, and any shares, stock or securities so purchased may from time to time be re-issued by the company. (ii) Where the Custodian executes a transfer of any shares, stock or securities which he is empowered to transfer by a Vest ing Order, the company or other body in whose books the shares, ^^ck or securities are registered shall, upon the receipt of the nsfer so executed by the Custodian and upon being required by him so to do, register the shares, stock or securities in the name of the Custodian or other transferee notwithstanding any regulation or stipulation of the company or other body, and not withstanding that the Custodian is not in possession of the certificate, script or other document of title relating to the shares, stock or securities transferred; but such registration shall be without prejudice to any lien or charge in favour of the company or other body, or to any other lien or charge of which the Custodian has notice. 7 . There shall be retained by the Custodian fees equal to 2 per centum of (а) the amount of monies paid to him, and ( б ) the value at the date of vesting of any property which is vested in him or of which the right of transfer is vested in him..dt' The value of any property for the purpose of assessing the fees shall be the price which in the opinion of the Board of Trade such property would fetch if sold in the open market. The fees in respect of such property may be retained out of any proceeds of the sale or transfer thereof or out of any income accrued therefrom. 0 * 8.— (i) Any payment required to be made under this Order to the Custodian shall be made to the Custodian for that part of the United Kingdom in which the person making the payment resides or carries on business, and if in any case any doubt should arise, then to such Custodian as the Board of Trade shall direct. (ii) Where any property or the right to transfer any property has been vested in the Custodian for any part of the United Kingdom, the Board of Trade may direct: (a) the transfer of the property to the Custodian of another part of the United Kingdom; (b) the payment to the Custodian of another part of the United Kingdom of the dividend or other income which has arisen or may thereafter arise from any such property. (iii) Where any money has been paid to the Custodian for any part of the United Kingdom, the Board of Trade may direct the payment over of such money to the Custodian for another part of the United Kingdom. 9 — (i) The Interpretation Act, i889( a ), shall apply to this Order as if it were an Act of Parliament. (ii) In this Order the expression “ enemy ” has the s&lt;^ meaning as that assigned to it in the Act and the expressn * “ enemy property ', “ property ” and “ Prescribed ” have the same meanings as those assigned to them in Section 7 of the Act, and references to ' the Custodian ' shall be construed as references to such Custodian of enemy property for any part of the United Kingdom as is prescribed by this Order or any Vesting Order. 10 .— (i) In the application of this Order to Scotland— (a) any reference to rent or other payment reserved out of or payable in respect of freehold or leasehold property or any manor shall be construed as a reference to any rent or other payment payable under or stipulated for in a lease or any sum payable by virtue of any feu contract, disposition, contract of ground annual or other deed constituting a burden on heritable property; (a) 52 &amp; 53 Vict - c - 6 3 -(3940r—7) Wt 6—1 15,0^0 9/39 P. St. (I. &lt;16 1 7 (b) for any reference to a vesting order made by the High Court under the Trustee Act, 1925, there shall be substituted a reference to a warrant to complete title granted under section twenty-two of the Trusts (Scotland) Act, 1921 ( a ); and ® (c) “ attached or otherwise taken in execution ” means arrested in execution or in security or otherwise affected by diligence. (ii) In the application of this Order to Northern Ireland the reference to the Trustee Act, 1925, shall be construed as a refer ence to the Trustee Act, 1893 ( b ). 11 . This Order may be cited as the Trading with the Enemy (Custodian) Order, 1939, and shall come into force on the 18th day of September, 1939. Dated the 16th day of September, 1939. W. B. Brown, Secretary of the Board of Trade. (a) 11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5. c. 58. (b) 56 &amp; 57 Viet. c. 53.a” The Trading with the Enemy (Custodian) Order, 1939, dated September 16, 1939, made by the Board of Trade UNDER SECTION 7 OF THE TRADING WITH THE ENEMY ACT, 1939 (2 &amp; 3 Geo. 6. c. 89). LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY'S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.a; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 26 York Street, Manchester 1; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller 1939 Price 2d . net .% STATUTORY RULES AND ORiTERS * 1939 No. 1537 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY Specified Persons The Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amend ment) (No. 2) Order, 1939, dated November i, 1939, MADE BY THE BOARD OF TRADE. The Board of Trade, in pursuance of the powers conferred upon them by sub-section (2) of section 2 of the Trading with the Enemy Act, I939( a )&gt; an d of all other powers enabling them in that behalf, hereby order as follows: — 1 . The Schedule to the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) Order, I939( b ), as varied by the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) Order, I939( c ), shall be further varied— {a) by inserting the names and addresses specified in Part I of the Schedule to this Order; (6) by deleting the names and addresses specified in Part II of the Schedule to this Order, and (c) by making the amendments specified in Part III of the Schedule to this Order. 2. —(1) The Interpretation Act, i889( d ), applies to the inter pretation of this Order as it applies to the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. (2) This Order may be cited as the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 2) Order, 1939, and shall come into operation on the seventh day of November, 1939. Dated this first day of November, 1939. /. /. Wills, An Assistant Secretary of the Board of Trade. (a) 2 &amp; 3 Geo. 6. c. 89. (c) S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1333. (b) S.R. &amp; O. 1939 No. 1166. (d) 52 &amp; 53 Viet. c. 63.1945 STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS 1945 No. 746 TRADING WITH THE ENEMY Specified Persons 'Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 7) [945, MADE BY THE BOARD OF TRADE. :e of the powers conferred upon them by and of all other powers enabling them in that behalf, hereby order as follows:— 1. The Schedule to the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) ^\mendment) (No. 1 ) Order, 1945 (b), as varied by the Trading with the 'Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 2 ) Order, 1945 (c), the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 3 ) Order, 1945 (d), the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 4 ) Order, 1945 (e), the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 5 ) Order, 1945 (f) and the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 6 ) Order, 1945 (g) shall be further varied— (a) by inserting the names and addresses specified in Part I of the Schedule to this Order; (b) by deleting the names and addresses specified in Part II of the Schedule to this Order; and (c) by making the amendments specified in Part III of the Schedule to this Order. 2. — ( 1 ) The Interpretation Act, 1889 (h), applies to the interpretation of this Order as it applies to the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. ( 2 ) This Order may be cited as the Trading with the Enemy (Specified Persons) (Amendment) (No. 7 ) Order, 1945 , and shall come into operation on the twenty-third day of June, 1945 . Dated this 18 th day of June, 1945 . Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939 (a), E. H. Hodgson, A Secretary of the Board of Trade. (a) 2 &amp; 3 Geo. 6. c. 89. (b) S.R. &amp; O. 1945 No. n. (d) S.R. &amp; O. 1945 No. 154. (f) S.R. &amp; O. 1945 No. 387. (h) 52 &amp; 53 Viet. c. 63. (c) S.R. &amp; O. 1945 No. 46. (e) S.R. &amp; O. 1945 No. 283. (g) S.R. &amp; O. 1945 No. 494. LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY'S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2 ; 13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2 ; 3941 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000385_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/166</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000385</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/166</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/A/43 II Defence Measures in the Persian Gulf.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-21T18:20:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (139 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in five copies of statutory rules and orders (folios 93-126), and a set of notes (folios 127-140). Serial numbers in red ink, which occur occasionally in the correspondence, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 141; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-91; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the implementation of defence measures during the Second World War (1939-45) in the area governed by the Political Residency in Persian Gulf generally, and more specifically in Bahrain.The main correspondents are the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Government of India; and the Foreign Office.The papers cover: correspondence from the Political Resident noting the poor security and deteriorating quality of wireless communication at Bahrain (folios 3-5, 54-56); the publication and distribution at Bahrain of Board of Trade 'Trading with the Enemy' regulations and orders (folios 6-21); copy of Emergency Powers (Defence) general regulations, 1939 (folios 23-38); papers concerning the pre-emption (commandeering) of stocks of Hasa oil at Bahrain (folios 44-45, 53, 57-60); copy of Persian Gulf States defence regulations, 1939 (folios 61-63); correspondence between the Political Agent, Bahrain and the Ruler of Bahrain, Sheikh Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah [Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah] concerning the issue by the Government of Bahrain of a public notice (
                           alan) against Italy, including a copies of the notice in English and Arabic (folios 72-77); correspondence concerning modifications of the Persian Gulf defence regulations in the light of experience gained from their operation (folios 82-92); and copies of Board of Trade 'Trading with the Enemy' regulations, 1939, 1945 (folios 93-126).The Arabic language content of the papers consists of four folios.The date range gives the main covering dates of the papers; however there is one document (a copy of Board of Trade 'Trading with the Enemy' regulations), dated 1945 (folios 113-126).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade restrictions (wartime)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000385#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>