<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000031_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:49:46.567Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">—o-fc- H f }■ \* ti* 3 6- THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT SECRET. (14377) Relations between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the Sheikh of Koweit. [E 6077/16/91] 1.—Final Record of a Meeting held at the Foreign Office, on October 5, 1933. THE following were present at the meeting :— Mr. G. W. Rendel (m the Chair), Foreign Office. Mr. K. R. Johnstone, Foreign Office. Sir A. Ryan, His Majesty's Minister at Jedda. Lieutenant-Colonel T. C. Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Mr. J. G. Laithwaite, India Office. The meeting had before it Sir Andrew Ryan's note of the 16th August, regarding the attitude of King Ibn Saud towards Koweit (see Appendix A). Mr. Rendel outlined the present political situation of Koweit. The Sheikh was tied to His Majesty's Government by his treaty engagements, but at the same time was being courted both by Ibn Saud and by Iraq. It was clear that the sheikhdom was not in a position which in the ordinary way would enable it to stand alone either as a political or as an economic entity, and that it must there fore depend on some stronger Power. He understood that it was the policy of His Majesty's Government, in view of the strategic importance of Koweit, not to allow it to be absorbed by any foreign Power, but, so far as was possible, to maintain their present treaty relationship with the Sheikh. Mr. Laithwaite suggested that Koweit was at the present moment of more vital importance to His Majesty's Government than it had been at any time, since it had bulked so prominently as the terminus of the Bagdad Railway before the war. This was the result first of the development of the air route to India and Australia, which had made the Gulf as important imperially from the air stand point as was the Suez Canal for naval reasons, and, secondly, owing to the expira tion of the mandatory regime in Iraq and the uncertainty of the future relations of His Majesty's Government with that country. So long as Iraq had been under British control, there had been a natural tendency to give it prior consideration and the less important question of Koweit had been kept comparatively in the background. But now that Iraq had attained full independence, the position was changed and Koweit had once again assumed major importance. Geographically, Koweit occupied a key position at the head of the Persian Gulf, and one trom which the Gulf could be controlled. In the event of war we could probably safely assume that Koweit would be on our side and her territory would afford us a base of operations of definite value, to the use of which, on the assumption in question, no objection could be raised on the ground that we were violating her neutrality. Further, with the development of the Arabian coast air route to the East, Koweit was likely to prove more and more vital as a station on that route, especially if our relations with Iraq should at any time become so strained that we were unable to rely on the use of the Iraqi aerodromes for the purposes of that route. Colonel Fowle suggested that in point of fact it might one day be possible to avoid the use of Iraq altogether, and fly direct from Palestine to Koweit, as the range of the aircraft using the Arabian route increased. Mr. Rendel concurred with Mr. Laithwaite's estimate of the position as regards Iraq. In view of recent events in Iraq it was possible that our whole relationship with that country might have to be modified, and he considered that both the future of the Anglo-Iraqi Treaty and of the position of the Royal Air Force in Iraq must be regarded as doubtful. On the general point at issue, he 7329 [9823] b2 observed that one of the main points to be borne in mnul was ihe fact that Koweit was not naturally independent from either the geographical or the economic point of view. It was a port without a hinterland, cut off at present by the Iraqi and Saudi frontiers from the territory which it would naturally feed, and at present denied free communication with the country behind it. Moreover, even its present trade might be jeopardised by the development of the Saudi port at Ras Tanura under the auspices of the American oil concessionaires on the Hasa coast. What was even more important was that its fresh-water supply was not derived from its own territory, but had to be imported from Iraq. It was for consideration, therefore, whether it would, in fact, be practicable for His Majesty's Government to maintain the independence of Koweit as against its neighbours, at any rate on the present basis of a rather loose and ill-defined dependence on His Majesty's Government. Colonel Fowls concurred generally in Mr. Rendel's description of the economic position of the sheikhdom. He pointed out, however, that Koweit haa always been the port of the deserts of northern Arabia, as Bahrein was the port of Central Arabia. In regard to the position of Koweit vis-a-vis of Iraq, he added that beside the influence which Iraq could exert by controlling Koweit's fresh- Avater supply, it was also powerful enough to bring pressure to bear upon Koweit over, for instance, the question of smuggling. Mr. Rendel agreed that both Iraq and Saudi Arabia were in a position to exert strong pressure on Koweit. This being so, the rivalry between them over Koweit was likely to increase, unless, of course, Saudi Arabia disintegrated. The present position of Koweit between these two States was weak, and Sir Andrew Ryan's note showed how powerful an attraction Ibn Saud could exert. The question, therefore, was whether His Majesty's Government would not be well advised to develop and tighten up their own relations with Koweit in order to strengthen its position. It had, in fact, been suggested that it might be more advantageous to convert our present treaty relationship into a definite protectorate, on, for instance, the analogy of the Hadramaut, which was now regarded as part of the Aden Protectorate, but where our treaty relationship w T ith the local rulers and obligations to afford them protection had been if anytiiing looser than those we had towards Koweit. Would not a protectorate ensure Koweit more effectively against absorption than the present attempt to maintain the sheikhdom as a kind of political vacuum in the Persian Gulf. Mr. Laithwaite drew attention to three points :— [a) At present the obligations of His Majesty's Government to Koweit were represented by their undertaking to grant ' good offices ' in respect of Koweit under the 1899 agreement, by their promise of 1907 that 'the town of Koweit and its boundaries belong to Sheikh Mobarak-us-Suba, Ruler of Koweit, and to his heirs after him,'' and their undertaking of the 3rd November, 1914. that Koweit, in the event of a victory over the Turks, would be recognised by us as an independent princi pality under British protection. They were thus very general in terms, and, in accordance with our normal policy on the Arab littoral, which dated from a period in which it was possible to protect a sea port by action from the sea, but not to afford effective help inland, we had consistently endeavoured to limit our obligations, save as regards 'good offices' to Koweit town and the immediately adjoining area. Recent experience had, however, shown that in cases of intervention from outside it was in fact necessary to give the Sheikh, at our discretion, and on our own terms, a measure of active assistance up to the limit of his frontiers and with the development of aircraft the problem of inland defence was now less difficult. This was to some extent a strengthening of his strict treaty position, as also possibly an extension of our strict treaty obligations. (h) With regard to the suggested establishment of a protectorate, it was necessary to consider what the reactions of the Sheikh would be, and also what effect the proclamation of a protectorate might have on the other Arab rulers of the Gulf. It would in any case be wiser not to make an overt proclamation of this nature, since both in Bahrein and in Qatar and along the Trucial Coast it would probably rouse3 apprehensions and might even cause the local sheikhs to turn away from His Majesty's Government and consider submitting themselves to Persia or to Ibn Saud. (c) The basis of His Majesty's Government's present treaty relationship with Koweit was unsatisfactory. In the first place, it did not rest, as was the case with Bahrein, Muscat and the Trucial Sheikhdoms, on a long series of formal treaties with the Sheikh dating back for over a century, or, as in the case of Qatar, on a comprehensive treaty, but was based only on a comparatively brief correspondence exchanged between the sheikhs and His Majesty's Government since 1899 and on the reciprocal engagements, still presumably binding since they had not been abrogated, entered into in connexion with the lease of Bunder Shweikh in 1907; secondly, there were certain gaps, e.g., we had no slavery agreement with Koweit. It might, he suggested, be possible to fill in the gaps left by this correspondence and tighten our control in that way. An example was our recent request to the Sheikh for certain undertakings in regard to air facilities in his sheikhdom, one result of which would be to concentrate effective control of such facilities, whether military or civil, in the hands of His Majesty's Government. Another instance was the recent proposed amendment of the Koweit Order in Council so as to place responsibility for jurisdiction over non-Moslem foreigners in the hands of His Majesty's Government. A gradual tightening of our control of this character, particularly if pursued as a definite policy on all convenient occasions, would, he thought, at once avoid the difficulties involved in establishing a formal protectorate and would make it very much simpler. Colonel Fowle expressed the view that there did not seem to be any inter mediate position possible between a treaty relationship with the Sheikh on the present lines and a full protectorate. The Sheikh would certainly be unwilling to agree to the sheikhdom becoming a formal protectorate, and, prima facie, he (Colonel Fowle) was not much in favour of it. He agreed, however, that it would be advisable, on suitable opportunities, to try to tighten up our control over the Sheikh. On being questioned whether he did not consider that our restricted position vis-a-vis of the Sheikh in regard to the Koweit oil concession indicated the essential weakness of our treaty position, he replied that our difficulties in that case had been due rather to the special undertakings given to the United States Government in that matter than to any weakness in our normal control over the Sheikh under the treaty engagements. Had we been able, without violating our pledges to the United States Government, to tell the Sheikh that we required him to give the concession to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company he would have done so. Mr. Rendel drew attention to the fact that in the event of serious misgovern- ment by the Ruler of Koweit such as prejudicially to affect foreign citizens in Koweit, we might find ourselves in a difficult position vis-a-vis of the foreign Power concerned. Mr. Laithwaite said that on this point he thought that Bahrein might be regarded as locus classicus. We had for many years put up with a considerable degree of misgovernment by Sheikh Isa. But when conditions at last, in our view, became intolerable, we did not hesitate to intervene and to depose the Sheikh. There were obvious arguments for doing so, for were we not to intervene when misgovernment had reached a certain pitch, it would be most difficult for us to justify a refusal to allow foreign Governments which might be affected to take steps to protect the interests of their nationals. He did not think that there need be any apprehension in the case of Koweit that we would fail to bring pressure on a sheikh who was abusing his position, once it became necessary to do so. The case for early intervention would probably be stronger now that the Gulf was so much more in the public eye. The meeting then went on to consider relations between Ibn Saud and Koweit. [9823] b 2Sir Andrew Ryan stated that he had been impressed by the apparent weakness of His Majesty's Government's position vis-a-vis of Ibn Saud with regard to Koweit. His Majesty's Government were not strongly placed when it became necessary to warn Ibn Saud to keep his hands off Koweit, since they were committed to maintaining that Koweit was technically an independent State. A case in point had been the Saudi intrusions into Koweit territory, referred to in paragraph 3 of his note, when Saudi officials had performed acts of authority within the limits of the sheikhdom. Colonel Fowle pointed out that, in fact, our treaty engagements did entitle us to prevent foreign Powers from dealing direct with the Sheikh. Ibn Saud had certainly been informed of the special relations existing between the Sheikh and His Majesty's Government. Speaking generally, he added that, in fact, little trouble was likely to be experienced with foreigners in Koweit, so long as it remained a Bedouin town ruled by a Bedouin sheikh, and not, like Bahrein, a relatively cosmopolitan commercial centre. If, however, oil were discovered within the sheikhdom, it was possible that difficulties might arise. Mr. Rendel pointed out that the Arabian air route was likely to develop quickly. If Iraq were to adopt an anti-foreign policy, and Koweit became correspondingly more important as a centre of international traffic, other countries might well wish to take advantage of the facilities there. We might well find many foreign Powers becoming increasingly interested in Koweit. We could not have it both ways, and should sooner or later have to define our position. His Majesty's Government ought, therefore, to orient their policy definitely either towards the greater independence of the sheikhdom or towards a tightening of their own control. Mr. Laithwaite agreed, and added that, in his view, our policy should be directed towards a closer control, but that it was undesirable to hasten any overt declaration of full control, such as the establishment of a protectorate would be. Such a declaration might well frighten the Sheikhs of Bahrein and of the Trucial Coast, and do more harm than good. The policy to be followed was, therefore, one of occasional minor adjustments, as these became necessary, tending to increase, or at any rate not to relax, our control over the sheikhdom. Reverting to the question of Saudi-Koweiti relations. Sir Andrew Ryan drew attention to the toleration extended by His Majesty's Government to direct correspondence on business matters between the Sheikh and Ibn Saud. This, no less than the independence formula, placed us in a weak position in defending Koweit, and the correspondence in question was of such long standing that it was difficult now for us to take the line that Ibn Saud should write to us rather than to the Sheikh. What was desirable was that we should be able to tell Ibn Saud openly that we were responsible for defending the Sheikh's interests in any given dispute. Mr. Laithwaite said that the explanation of the system of direct correspon dence between the Sheikh and Ibn Saud was, he thought, that it dated from a time when the latter was not so important a ruler as he had since become, and when we had taken the view that it was unnecessary to take too strict a view of correspondence between sheikh and sheikh. That position was now changed, and reconsideration seemed desirable. Ibn Saud was well aware both that His Majesty's Government conducted the foreign relations of Koweit and that the Sheikh had undertaken certain obligations towards us. He agreed that it was now necessary to exert stricter control over the correspondence in question and to emphasise our own special position in Koweit vis-a-vis of Ibn Saud more definitely than had been the case while Iraq was still under British control. He suggested that we might {a) check Ibn Saud when he appeared to be presuming too far with regard to Koweit—a policy which we were, in fact, now prepared to follow in regard to the Saudi-Koweit blockade; and (h) enforce stricter regulations on the Sheikh in the matter of direct correspondence. Colonel Fowle agreed. Such action would show both the Sheikh and Ibn Saud that we considered the Sheikh to be under our direction. If we did not take some such step as this, we might be in danger of finding ourselves faced with the results of a kind of conspiracy between the Sheikh and Ibn Saud. We ought, therefore, to write to the Sheikh in the sense that we noted that his privatecorrespondence with Ibn Saud had assumed an increasing importance, and tell him that that correspondence must now cease. Mr. Rendel concurred. A straightforward control of this nature would be easier to maintain, and would prevent a repetition of such incidents as the letter in which Ibn Saud had recently tried to detach the Sheikh of Koweit from his connexion with His Majesty's Government. Sir A. Ryan also concurred, and drew attention to the success with which Tbn Saud was spreading the idea that he might naturally absorb Koweit and was bound to do so sooner or later. He pointed out that such an idea could never have prevailed to the extent to which it had, if His Majesty's Government had equally definitely made known their own special position with regard to Koweit. The meeting then discussed what point in the correspondence between the Sheikh and Ibn Saud could most suitably be taken up in connexion with the reprimand which it was proposed to address to both parties. Mr. Laithwaite suggested that if it were discovered that the Sheikh had committed himself to Ibn Saud in regard to the grant of an oil concession in the Koweit Neutral Zone, this might be an excellent opportunity for checking him. The question then arose, what action could be taken if the United States Government, in dealing with whom His Majesty's Government had consistently emphasised the Sheikh's independence, were to produce communications from him regarding the grant of a concession in the Neutral Zone ? It was, however, agreed that His Majesty's Government could demonstrate from the Sheikh's treaty engagements that he had not been entitled to make any such grant without our knowledge and consent. Eventually it was agreed that the most suitable occasion for the proposed representations to the Sheikh and Ibn Saud would be Ibn Saud's letter suggesting terms for the settlement of the Saudi blockade of Koweit and warning the Sheikh against His Majesty's Government. At the conclusion of the meeting Sir A. Ryan raised the question of the pressure which might be exerted upon Ibn Saud in regard to the Saudi blockade of Koweit. This blockade had one of two purposes, either to complete the economic strangulation of Koweit and lead to its complete absorption in Saudi Arabia, or else the safeguarding of Saudi economic interests. His Majesty's Government could not possibly allow the first of these alternatives. The question, therefore, was what real force there was in Ibn Saud's suggestion that his own purely economic interests required the maintenance of the blockade. Colonel Fowls suggested that we might well revert to the Sheikh s proposal that Ibn Saud should have customs posts at a given place along but outside the Koweiti border, and that this might, if necessary, be coupled with a system of manifests for Koweiti-Saudi trade. He gave it as his opinion that even if Ibn Saud were to develop Ras Tanura, possibly with American help, this port was not likely to compete seriously with Koweit, which served quite a different hinter land. nor was there any port between the Koweit area and the Ras Tanura area which could be successfully developed as a rival to Koweit. Colonel Fowle suggested that on his return to the Gulf on the 16th October he should discuss the situation with Colonel Dickson, Political Agent, Koweit, who had great experience of the sheikhdom, in the light of the conversations at the present meeting, and should submit a comprehensive report. It was agreed that this course should be adopted, and that in the light of the Resident's report and of the conclusions of the present meeting the question of future policy in Koweit should be discussed if necessary in the Middle East Official Sub-Committee. The conclusions of the meeting were as follows ;— (1) That in dealing with Ibn Saud, His Majesty's Government should increasingly emphasise the closeness of their relations with the Sheikh. (2) That the Sheikh should be told that his personal correspondence with Ibn Saud on official matters was to cease. (3) That the issue of the. Saudi blockade of Koweit should be taken up with Ibn Saud by His Majesty's Government on the basis of their obligation to protect the interests of Koweit.6 (4) That on receipt of the despatch promised by Colonel Fowle the whole question of relations between His Majesty's Government and Koweit might suitably be referred for further discussion to the Middle East Official Sub-Committee, to which a note should be sent recording the points discussed at the present meeting, and setting forth the argu ments for and against the possible declaration of a protectorate. Appendix A. Note by Sir Andrew Ryan. Ihn Saud's Attitude towards Koweit. I HAVE been turning over in my mind for some time the possibility that it may be a definite object of Ibn Saud s policy to reduce Koweit to a position of dependence on him somewhat similar to that of Asir from 1926 to 1930. This is in the nature of a pure speculation, but it is a speculation so interesting that 1 think it worth while to collect the principal data bearing on it. It must be admitted at the outset that, if Ibn Saud had such an idea in his head,^ he would realise the need for great caution lest he should indispose His Majesty's Govern ment. His only formal obligation towards the latter is that contained in article 6 of the Treaty of Jedda, but he understands very well the implications of the words therein 'who are in special treaty relations with His Britannic Majesty's Govern ment.' On the other hand, he has seen His Majesty's Government tolerate direct correspondence on business subjects between him and the Sheikh of Koweit. He might think that they would' not react over strongly if he and the Sheikh confronted them with the fait accomyli of a political deal. 2. Apart from the correspondence, of which we have knowledge, there has been other intercourse between the rulers, notably the Sheikh's visit to Riadh in 1932, the secret messages brought by Ibn Saud's confidential messenger to the Sheikh early this year, and the Sheikh's mysterious dashes intoNejd last February, when Colonel Dickson surmised that he had gone to meet some high baudi personage, possibly Ibn Saud himself. 3. I may interpolate, as a minor indication of Ibn Saud's attitude, a reference to two occasions on which it has been suggested or hinted by his Ministry for Foreign Affairs that His Majesty's Government should not concern themselves with affairs between Saudi Arabia and Koweit. I class them as minor, because this position has never been categorically asserted. The first was when, in reply to a complaint of mine regarding Saudi encroachments on Koweit territory, which had perturbed His Majesty's Government, the reply was in effect: 'Sorry you have been perturbed. You need not have been ii the matter had been pursued through An. Nafisi.' On another occasion Fuad Bey, in rather light conversa tion, asked me why we concerned ourselves in matters between his Government and Koweit. 4. The personal relations between the two rulers are peculiar. Ibn Saud grew up at Koweit, and it is sometimes said that he has shown himself ungrateful to his former hosts. It is said by others, I do not know on what precise grounds, that Mubarak treated Ibn Saud very badly. Anyhow, through all the relations there runs a thread of old friendship, however flimsy and however frayed by frequent friction over raids, the embargo and so on. It has helped towards the settlement of minor questions. It has not deterred Ibn Saud from enforcing the embargo on trade, but the embargo on trade has not destroyed the Sheikh s ostensible friendliness towards Ibn Saud. They are 'Arcades ambo,'' as I once wrote, and they both combine some real friendship for His Majesty's Government and a healthy fear of them with a good deal of fundamental mistrust. 5. The point of my theory or speculation is that, if the Sheikh of Koweit were at all willing to be ' Asirised.' Ibn Saud could make the proposal quite attractive on the following lines, if I may venture to put into his mouth the sort of language he could use :— (a) 'You are not really independent, my dear fellow. You are under the thumb of the English. They might annex you at any moment, or even present you to Iraq. If you must be dependent on some one, whybe dependent on those untrustworthy imperialists, when you might depend, without being exactly dependent, on a man like me, old friend, fellow Moslem, fellow Arab and the one big independent man in Arabia ? (b) 'I don't like squeezing you, I really don't, with that embargo. As things are at present, I have to think of my own interests. But if your interests were mine, we could easily have an understanding. A sort of ' Zollverein' as they say; same duties levied in our ports; free competition between yours and mine; free trade over our land border. What have the English done about it ? Nothing; because they cannot get at me. ' Sois mon fr^re et je te fais vivre. Sois le leur et je te tue.' (c) 'I should not mop you up, of course. You would rule your State under an understanding with me. Indeed, if you were in with me, I might recognise a sort of influence of yours over those three Lost Tribes that you always want back. Look at how I treated the Idrisi. I made a sensible agreement with him in 1926. He remained a ruler with tribal influence. I did not take charge in his country, until he got into such a mess that he asked me to in 1930. I did not hit him on the head until the poor mutt thought he could try conclusions with me in 1932. He looked to foreigners and he got it in the neck from me. (d) 'You have had trouble with Iraq over your property there. What has England been able or even willing to do for you? If I had the right to protect you against third parties, you would find that I knew how to see you through. (e) ' Then there's oil. People are after it in my country, and in yours, and in the Neutral Zone. Why not have an agreed policy and present a common front to the West? You know what the Anglo-Persian Oil Company is. Another name for the British Government, as we saw in Persia the other day, even if we had not known it before. Take my tip and keep them out at all costs. Play about with Holmes, if you like. But don't trust him, and remember that in the long run your best policy would be to deal, like me, direct with American interests, using the others to put up the price.'' 6. It is easy enough to detect fallacies in the above imaginary address. I do not know enough about the Sheikh of Koweit to judge what his reaction to it would be, but many an Arab, not well pleased with British protectors, might find it convincing enough to be attracted into Ibn Saud's parlour. 7. I wrote the above notes in Jedda at the end of June. I thought them too hypothetical at that time to submit them for official consideration. They may, however, be worthy of some attention now that the Political Resident and I are both in this country, and Colonel Dickson will soon be available for consultation. Except that Ibn Saud continues to show a marked anxiety to avoid all compli cations, I see no material reason to modify what I wrote nearly three months ago, subject always to the consideration that I merely suggest an uncertain working theory to be tested by further examination and by keeping a close watch on future developments. August 16, 1933. Appendix B. Note. Obligations of His Majesty's Government towards the Sheikh of Koweit. (A)— Nature of the Undertakings given. By the agreement of the 23rd Januarv, 1899, His Majesty's Government formally assured the Sheikh 'of the good offices of the British Government towards you, your heirs and successors, so long as you, your heirs and successors8 scrupulously and faithfully observe the conditions of the said bond,' 1 under which the Sheikh had pledged himself, his heirs and successors, not to receive the agent or representative of any Power or Government at Koweit without the previous sanction of the British Government, and not to cede, sell, lease or mortgage, or give for occupation or for any other purpose, any portion of his territory to the Government or subjects of any other Power without the previous consent of His Majesty's Government. 2. By article 9 of the Secret Agreement of the 15th October, 1907, for the lease of the Bunder Shweikh foreshore, the Political Agent intimated that he was ' duly authorised on behalf of the precious Imperial English Government to promise, and do hereby promise, that the town of Koweit and its boundaries likewise belong to Sheikh Mobarak-us-Suba, Ruler of Koweit, and to his heirs after him, and that all Sheikh Mobarak's arrangements in the matter of customs, &amp;c., and all his arrangements at the present day shall remain in the hands of Sheikh Mobarak-us-Suba, Ruler of Koweit, and of his heirs after him, and . . . In consideration of this promise the Sheikh undertook not to levy customs dues in excess of 4 per cent, on goods imported or exported by ' the subjects of the aforesaid English Government,' save with the approval of that Government. 3. The undertakings given in writing to the Sheikh on the 3rd November, 1914, in return for his co-operation against the Turks, contained an assurance that ' Koweit shall be recognised as an independent principality under British protection.' (B)- Construction of the Undertakings given to the Sheikh. 4. As will be seen, the engagements entered into by His Majesty's Govern ment with the Sheikh are in rather general terms, and it is perhaps desirable briefly to record the construction placed upon them at various times by His Majesty's Government. 5. In 1901, when there was a Turkish threat to Koweit, the Viceroy was informed (Secretary of State's telegram No. 45 of the 4th December, 1901) that this 'appears to constitute a distinct violation of the Sultan's promise' (to respect the status quo), ' and in these circumstances His Majesty's Government are prepared to support the Sheikh, and will not tolerate an attack by Turkish troops or ships upon Koweit. The Sheikh should not leave Koweit, and should continue to observe his engagement with us.' The assurance given is clearly limited by the words ' in these circumstances ' to this particular case. More over, it is not conditional on, and is independent of the Sheikh's observance of his agreement of 1899. 6. On the 21st March, 1902, Lord Lansdowne, then Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, in a memorandum on the situation in Koweit, remarked that our obligations toward the Sheikh were ' as ill-defined as the boundaries of his principality. We have distinctly announced that he does not enjoy British ' protection '; on the other hand, we once made him a present of £1,000. and promised him our ' good offices,' whatever that may mean. When we made this promise we were, I feel no doubt, thinking of Koweit proper, if there is such a thing, and not of Boobyan or other outskirts over which the Sheikh has rights of one sort or another We might, it seems to me, explain (1) to the Porte; (2) to the Sheikh; and (3) to the foreign Powers immediately interested the objects of our policy. I should be inclined to say that our engagements to Koweit do not extend beyond the district adjoining or close to the bay of that name, and to endeavour to obtain the adhesion of the Porte and of the Sheikh to our approximate definition of that district ' 7. Later, in 1902, it was reported that Ibn Rashid was making energetic preparation for attacking Ibn Saud, then the Sheikh of Koweit's friend, and the Sheikh was warned not to take any action likely to bring him into difficulties with either Nejd or Turkey. About the same time the Sheikh informed us that Ibn Saud had with him a gun presented by the Turks, and asked for a gift of two or three guns, which it was understood were wanted for Jehara to protect Koweit against land attack. The Viceroy (telegram No. 39 of the 3rd October, 1902) proposed to reply that the Sheikh 1 s request could not be granted, 'but that, provided he complied with the injunction conveyed to him in pursuance of your telegram of the 4th December. 1901 (see paragraph 5 above). His Majesty's9 Government would charge themselves with the defence of Koweit district. The Secretary of State, after consultation with the Foreign Office (Foreign Office letter of the 13th October, 1902), replied (telegram No. 133 of the 14th October, 1902) : 'I approve your proposed reply about the guns, provided Koweit district is clearly defined as the district adjoining or close to the bay of that name.' This assurance similarly admits of being read as an assurance ad hoc, and it is relevant that when, in April 1911, enquiry was made by the Secretary of State for India of the Government of India whether the definition in question of Koweit territory had been communicated to the Sheikh, they replied that it might be assumed that it had, but that it ' only referred to our pledge to defend him against Ibn Rashid, who was threatening the immediate neighbourhood of Koweit ' (telegram of the 6th April, 1911). 8. The more specific undertakings embodied in the Bunder Shweikh lease of 1907, and quoted in paragraph 2 above, may be regarded as to some extent committing us in respect of 'the town of Koweit and its boundaries.' The phrase ' its boundaries ' is, however, very vague, and could perhaps most reasonably be construed as applying to the immediate district around Koweit town. The discussions as to our obligations to the Sheikh which took place in 1911, and which are summarised in paragraphs 9 to 12 below, appear to have turned essentially on the undertakings of 1899. 9. In 1911, in connexion with the Anglo-Turkish negotiations, the question of our obligations was examined in some detail. The Government of India, on being asked, with reference to Lord Lansdowne's memorandum of 1902, to which reference is made in paragraph 6 above, to ' define the region to which our obligation extends,' and 'whether they accepted ^ general description of boundaries in Persian Gulf Gazetteer, p. 1059, &amp;c., replied : ' We are of opinion that (1) our obligations extend to the limits of the Sheikh's territory; (2) these limits, to the best of our knowledge, are defined with fair accuracy by Lorimer, especially as regards northern portion. ...' 10. The Secretary of State for India, in the light of the Government of India's views, wrote as follows to the Foreign Office (the 8th April, 1911) :— ' Viscount Morley is not aware on what grounds the opinion expressed by the Marquess of Lansdowne in his memorandum of the 21st March, 1902, is based, but he observes that the language used is very tentative, and, so far as he knows, the subject was never pursued along the lines suggested by his Lordship, except in the case of the attack on the immediate neighbour hood of Koweit threatened by Ibn Rashid in the autumn of 1902. It will be seen from the Government of India's telegram of the 6th April that this incident does not affect their opinion that our general obligations extend to the limits of Koweit territory as described in Vol. II, pp. 1059-1061, of Larimer's Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf, copy of which is in your possession. In this Lord Morley concurs; that is to say, he thinks that, in the event of unprovoked aggression by the Turks or by Arab tribes under Turkish control, upon those limits. His Majesty's Government could not abstain from using their ' good offices ' in the Sheikh's favour. But the term ' good offices ' is a very vague one, which His Majesty's Government are at liberty to interpret at their discretion, and which they would doubtless interpret with more or less strictness, according to the nature and locality of the aggression, and all the circumstances of the case. It would, however, in his Lordship's opinion, be very impolitic to attempt, in dealing with the Sheikh, to whittle down the extent of our obligations, since such a course would fill his mind with suspicions, and could not fail to affect unfavourably our prestige in the Persian Gulf. ...' 11. The Foreign Office replied, on the 9th May, 1911, that Sir E. Grey concurred ' in the view of the Government of India, shared by Viscount Morley, that these obligations extend to the whole territory of the Sheikh, as described in the passage of Larimer's Gazetteer of the Persian Gulf to which your letter refers.' 12. In August 1911 the Government of India, after consultation with the Political Resident (Sir P. Cox), recommended that His Majesty's Government should communicate to the Turks a copy of the agreement of 1899, with a note that His Majesty's Government had subsequently informed the Sheikh that, so long as he and his heirs and successors acted up to their obligations under the agreement, we charged ourselves to support them and to protect Koweit against [9823] c10 -attack by land or sea. The Secretary of State for India, on closer consideration, found himself unable to accept this proposal. India Office letter to the Foreign Office of the 30th October, 1911, remarked :— ' The telegrams of the 4th December, 1901, and the 14th October, 1902, on which the (xovernment of India appear to base the obligation to protect Koweit by land and sea, in the Marquess of Crewe's opinion, clearly refer only to the incidents that occasioned them, and cannot be understood to have given any general undertaking. Nor, in view of the fact that it has since been decided that our obligations extend to the whole of the Sheikh's territory, as described in Lorimer's Gazetteer, would it be safe to pledge ourselves to any specific method of defending them. As was pointed out by Lord Morley in this Office letter of the 8th April last, the term ' good offices ' (which, by Colonel Meade's letter of the 23rd January, 1899, we undertook to accord to the Sheikh) is a conveniently vague one, and Lord Crewe is of opinion that it is neither necessary nor safe to go beyond it. The action taken by His Majesty's Government in 1901-02, when men and guns were landed at Koweit to defend it against unprovoked Turkish aggression, will, moreover, have made it plain to the Porte in what way we are prepared to interpret the term if necessity arises. ' 4 His Lordship would therefore suggest that the formula should run : 4 As regards No. 1, His Majesty's Government have informed the Sheikh of Koweit that, so long as he and his heirs and successors act up to their obligations under the agreement, His Majesty's Government undertake to support them and accord them their good offices,' with, perhaps, the addition that His Majesty's Government reserve to themselves the right to interpret that term at their discretion.' The Foreign Office (Foreign Office letter dated the 1st November, 1911) accepted the proposed redraft and addition, and a communication in this sense was made to Tevnk Pasha in Sir Edward Grey's letter of the 24th October, 1911. 13. The undertaking given in 1914 that Koweit ' shall be recognised as an independent principality under British protection,' may be regarded as importing a degree of responsibility for the protection of the principality as a whole. 14. On the death of Sheikh Mobarak his eldest son was informed, in March 1916, on his accession, by the Viceroy, that, ' so long as you act up to the existing arrangements with the British Government, you may expect the same support as was enjoyed by your father.' A similar assurance was given on Sheikh Jabir's death in 1917 to his brother and successor, Sheikh Salim, in March 1917. Sheikh Salim's conduct was unsatisfactory, and it was found necessary to warn him, through the Political Resident, on the 5th July, 1918, that the assurances (which presumably covered the assurance of the 3rd November, 1914) conveyed to him on his accession were conditional on his good behaviour, and that, should acts 'contrary to the interests of His Majesty's Government unfortunately be committed in future,' he would be held personally responsible. 15. In connexion with the operations against the Ikhwan in 1928, the question of the precise extent of the obligations of His Majesty's Government for the defence of Koweit was considered in the India Office, when the view was put forward that consideration of our engagements suggested that, on a strict reading, our liability could be confined to the protection of the town of Koweit, and that we are not called upon to protect Koweit territory as a whole. The history of the 1928 discussion is, however, examined in greater detail in Appendix C, to the conclusions of which attention is invited. Conclusion. 16. As will be seen from the correspondence summarised above, {a) we appear consistently to have taken the view that our obligations are conditional on the good behaviour of the Sheikh; (b) secondly, that, subject to this reservation, we are committed to ' good offices ' in respect of ' Koweit,' an assurance which has, since 1911, been accepted as extending to the whole territory of the sheikhdom, but which would not commit us to anything further than diplomatic support; {c) thirdly, that we have promised ' that the town of Koweit and its boundaries ' belong to the heirs of Sheikh Mobarak (while the payment of rent for the Bunder Shweikh site was terminated in 1907, the agreement of 1907 was not abrogated, and the reciprocal pledges embodied in that agreement shouldil apparently still be regarded as binding in so far as they are not affected by other subsequent instruments. We communicated article 9 of the Bunder Shweikh Agreement to Ibn Saud in 1928; and in 1933 the Political Agent, Koweit, and the Political Resident brought to notice the continued existence of the obligations of the Sheikh in regard to customs duties (paragraph 2 above) under article 10 of the agreement); {d) fourthly, that we have undertaken to recognise, and have in fact recognised, Koweit as an independent principality under British protection. No definition has been given or attempted of the meaning of 'British protection' in this connexion; and, while prima facie the Sheikh would apparently be justified in claiming that it represented an assurance of effective protection in respect of the whole of his principality, there is some room for discussion as to its precise implications, and it is noteworthy that no appeal appears to have been made under it either by the present Sheikh or by his predecessors. J. G. LAITHWAITE India Office, October 11, 1933. Appendix C. Supplementary Note. Question of Liability for the Protection of Koweit against Aggression from Outside, 1928-29. Akhwan raids on Koweit had taken place in 1924 and 1925, but on an inconsiderable scale. The Akhwan raids on Iraq by Feisal-al-Dawish and the Mutair tribe at the end of 1927 had, however, more important reactions on the principality. At the request of the Sheikh His Majesty's Government agreed to aerial reconnaissance over his territory ; and, with his concurrence, it was later decided to withdraw the restrictions originally imposed by His Majesty's Government on bombing in pursuit of raiders within Koweit territory. An Akhwan raid was successfully dealt with by Koweit forces at El Riqai on the 27th January, 1928, and whilst retiring into Nejd was pursued and successfully attacked by the Royal Air Force on two following days. A further raid occurred late in February, which was not opposed by ground forces, but was again success fully pursued by the Royal Air Force for two days. In view of the possibility of further serious developments, and of the recognised liability of His Majesty's Government under existing engagements for the ' protection of Koweit (a phrase the exact scope of which is open to argument), further defence measures were now taken. A temporary air base (political objections to a permanent station being regarded as conclusive) was established in Koweit: a flight of aeroplanes and a detachment of armoured cars were despatched to the town for its protection ; three vessels of the Persian Gulf Squadron (later reduced to one) were stationed off Koweit itself, and a landing party disembarked and remained on shore until the crisis had passed. All action taken was taken with the concurrence of the Sheikh, who was, in addition, allowed to purchase from the Government of India a small supply of machine guns and Lewis guns. After some discussion His Majesty's Government and the Government of India agreed that his Excellency might be allowed to purchase armoured motor cars, on the understanding that they would be used only for defence, and would not cross the borders of Koweit in repelling raids save with the concurrence of the Political Agent. The crisis, however, passed off without incident, and the special forces which had been despatched to Koweit were withdrawn during the late spring. For financial reasons the Sheikh abandoned the idea of purchasing armoured cars. 2. On the 15th August, 1928, the Air Officer Commanding, Iraq, in order to provide against all eventualities, asked permission to send car or air recon naissances into Koweit territory and to establish a defence air base at Koweit in the event of a raid. The India Office remarked (letter of the 22nd August, 1928) : ' The Secretary of State would see strong objection on political grounds to the use of Koweit territory in connexion with air operations against the Akhwan, by which Koweit w T as not directly or immediately threatened. Having regard, however, to the treaty liability of His Majesty's Government for the protection of Koweit and to the action taken with the consent of the Sheikh in the early part of this year, he would see no objection to the grant of the authority now requested when Koweit was directly or indirectly menaced, on the understanding that the prior consent of the Sheikh was obtained from the [9823] c 212 Kesident .... so far as may be practicable, on each specific occasion, and subject to the further restriction that there shall be no question of establishing a 'permanent base in Koweit territory.' As the result of considerable further interdepartmental discussion, the Air Officer Commanding was authorised on the 25th September, at his discretion, to carry out occasional reconnaissances over Koweit territory, both by air and car. ' His Majesty's Government are anxious, however, that— (1) These reconnaissances shall be carried out as infrequently and in as unprovocative a manner as possible, and (2) That the Sheikh shall be given no ground for supposing that responsi bility for the defence of Koweit has been assumed by His Majesty's Government, or that he himself has been relieved of his obligations in this respect. These considerations should be borne in mind by the Air Officer Commanding in acting under the authority now given him.' (Colonial Office telegram to Bagdad, No. 306, dated the 25th September, 1928.) 3. Approval was subsequently given in view of a threatened Akhwan raid over the border, to the concentration, subject to the approval of the Sheikh, of armoured cars in Koweit 1 ' for protection of Iraqi tribes for so long a period as one month.'' (Colonial Office telegram to Bagdad. No. 76, dated the 23rd February, 1929.) 4. In April 1929 the question of the policy to be adopted by the Sheikh of Koweit in the event of Xejdi tribesmen taking refuge from King Ibn Saud in Koweit territory arose, the air authorities suggested that the Sheikh should be asked to concur in the use, if necessary, of military force, the nature and extent of which should be determined by the Air Officer Commanding, Iraq, for the purpose of preventing any such refugees from entering or remaining in any part of Koweit territory. On the 8th May, 1929, the India Office, in a letter to the Colonial Office, remarked: 'Viscount Peel gathers that the attitude of the Sheikh is no longer in question and that he has already promised to endeavour to prevent refugees making use of Koweit territory. As regards the question of giving the Sheikh military assistance for this purpose, the Secretary of State remains of his previous opinion that it is undesirable to extend in any way the general liability hitherto accepted by His Majesty's Government for the defence of Koweit territory, if this can at all be avoided It would, on the whole, be preferable, if possible, to avoid asking the Sheikh to concur in the use of military force, but if ... . such a request is still essential, he is prepared to agree that the Sheikh should be asked to concur ' The other Departments regarded it as essential to make a request in the sense referred to of the Sheikh and the necessary instructions were sent to the High Commissioner on the 11th May. 5. The view held as regards our liability for protection of Koweit during the operations of 1928-29 is perhaps best stated in the India Office letters of the 22nd August, 1928, and the 8th May, 1929, quoted in paragraphs 2 and 4 above. While our precise liability for protection was not investigated in any great detail, the course of action adopted in dealing with threats to Koweit territory appears to have been generally consistent with the construction of our liability suggested by Colonel Fowle in paragraph 10 of Bushire despatch No. 1365-S of the 25th October, 1933.( 1 ) J. G. LAITHWAITE. India Office, February 6, 1934. (') [Note .—The paragraph referred to runs as follows: — 'The 1914 agreement states that in return for the Sheikh's co-operation against the Turks ' Koweit shall be recognised as an independent principality under British protection.' This, unlike the phraseology of the previous agreements, is a most categorical assurance, and the word ' principality ' and not ' town ' being used, would seem definitely to place the responsibility of protecting the whole of the Koweit Sheikhdom on His Majesty's Government. Personally, I cannot agree with the view quoted in paragraph 15 of the India Office note, that ' on a strict reading our liability could be confined to the protection of the town of Koweit, and that we are not called upon to protect Koweit as a whole.' It is true, as pointed out in the note, paragraph 16 {d), that neither the present Sheikh, nor his predecessors, appear to have appealed under this agreement to His Majesty's Government, but that hardly relieves us from our obligations. This does not imply, of course, that His Majesty's Govern ment's obligations relieve the Sheikh completely of the responsibility of his own defence. The Sheikh should certainly be able to deal with any small raids across his frontiers, nnd should only look for assistance from His Majesty's Government in the case of more serious incursions. This, in fact, was presumably the attitude taken up after the Akhwan operations of 1928, when the Sheikh was encouraged to purchase half-a-dozen Ford vanettes, Lewis guns, which were mounted in the vanettes, and ammunition, and when some of his men received training from the Eoyal Air Force as machine-gunners.']13 [E 7141/16/91] 2.— India Office to Foreign Office .—{Received November 22.) §i r India Office, November 21, 1933. I AM directed by the Secretary of State for India to transmit to you, for the information of the Secretary of State for loreign Affairs, copy of a letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf respecting relations with Koweit. I am, &amp;c. S. F. STEWART. Enclosure in 2. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, to Secretary of State for India. (Confidential.) . ^j r Bushire, October 2o, 1933. I HAVE the honour to refer to your letter dated the 13th October, 1933, enclosing a copy of the record of an interdepartmental meeting held at the 1 oreign Office on the 5th instant, note by Sir Andrew Ryan on Ibn Saud s attitude towards Koweit, and India Office provisional note, dated the 11th October, 1933, on the obligations of His Majesty's Government towards the Sheikh of Koweit. 1 discussed the matter with the Political Agent, Koweit, when I passed through there recently on my way to Bushire. 2. One of the two'questions (the other is dealt with below in paragraphs / and 8) discussed at the meeting was, briefly, whether, with a view to maintaining our control over Koweit, which was undoubtedly fast increasing in importance as a political and strategical centre in the Middle East, (a) it was advisable to declare a British protectorate over that sheikhdom, or (b) whether sufficient control could not be obtained over it by adopting a policy of tightening up our control over the sheikh as opportunity offered by filling in the gaps which at present existed in our agreements with him. 3. As will be seen from the record, prima facie, I favoured (b) rather than {a), and further reflection and my discussion with Colonel Dickson, who agrees with me, has confirmed me in that opinion. The objections to {a) are that, in our {i.e.. Colonel Dickson and my) opinion, a protectorate would most probably meet with considerable opposition from the sheikh, who, while valuing his British connexion, values equally highly his independence in the eyes of his fellow Arab rulers, and the outside world in general. The declaration of such a protectorate would likewise alarm the other sheikhs on the Arab coast of the Gulf. It might also involve His Majesty's Government in a measure of interference in the iiiternal affairs of Koweit' which can at present be avoided. The question of slavery in Koweit, for example, as part of the slavery question in the (juli generally, will doubtless be raised in. the tuture b\ the lecently established Permanent Slavery Committee of the League of Nations, and as we have no slave agreement with the ruler, such as exists with the other Arab rulers by which the local Political Agent can manumit slaves, the Koweit aspect of this problem offers special difficulties. So long as Koweit remains 'independent,' His Majesty's Government s responsibility in the matter is presumably limited to representations and persuasions to the sheikh. In the event, however, of a British protectorate being declared over the sheikhdom. His Majesty's Govern ment might possibly be committed to more drastic action. Finally, it is not improbable, though this is a matter outside my sphere, that the declaration of a Koweit protectorate might lead to somewhat awkward accusations from other Governments of 'land grabbing' and the like, with which we have been familiar enough in the past with regard to other areas. 4. An examination of the alternative policy {b) shows that, unsatisfactory as our present treaty relationship with the sheikh may be (as was pointed out at the meeting), we have a certain control over the ruler (see India Office note— Obligations of His Majesty's Government towards the Sheikh of Koweit), and where our agreements show gaps, these can, to a large extent, be filled up. Thus, control of aviation through Koweit, whether military or civil, would be in the hands of His Majesty's Government under the proposed air agreement {vide14 correspondence ending with India Office letter dated the 11th August, 1933, to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Department) with the sheikh, while the proposed amendment of the Koweit Order in Council {vide correspon dence ending with Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, express letter dated the 21st August, 1933, to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India) would place jurisdiction over non-Moslem foreigners in Koweit in the hands of the Political Agent. 5. A third 'gap is the habit of direct correspondence which has grown up between the sheikh and Ibn Saud, and which was dealt with at some length at the meeting. The outcome of my discussion with Colonel Dickson on this point is as follows : There w6uld appear to be two ways in which we can ensure control over this correspondence : — (1) By informing the sheikh that before despatching any official communi cation to Ibn Saud he should show it to the Political Agent, and should take similar action with communications received from Ibn Saud. This has been the sheikh s custom in the past, at any rate in regard to his outward correspondence; whether he has shown all Ibn Saud's official letters to Colonel Dickson, we do not r of course, know. After the sheikh had received our communication, which would, of course, be tactfully worded and would merely ask him to continue the practice which he already observed, he would not be able to quote officially any letters which he had not shown to the Political Agent. If, for instance, in order to present His Majesty's Government with a fait accompli on some point agreed upon between Ibn Saud and himself, he should produce a communication which had not been seen by the Political Agent, we could ignore it. Both Colonel Dickson and I think that perhaps it would be better in our communication not to refer to any particular correspondence, but to treat the matter on general grounds. The above refers, of course, to official correspondence; nothing we can do will prevent ' private and personal letters passing between the two potentates. (2) The second alternative is to insist that official correspondence between the sheikh and Ibn Saud should pass through His Majesty's Government's local representatives: the Minister at Jedda, and the Political Agent, Koweit (or, perhaps, the Resident, Persian Gulf). This is already the procedure in forced (at the sheikh s own request) in regard to the sheikh's correspondence with the Iraq Government, and so no new departure in principle would be involved. The advantage of this alternative would be its emphasis to Ibn Saud of the special relations that Koweit has with His Majesty's Government, which emphasis is apparently particularly needed at the present juncture (vide conclusion 1 of the meeting). As against this advantage. Colonel Dickson is of the opinion that the sheikh, who regards Ibn Saud, in spite of the latter's treatment of Koweit, in a somewhat different light to Iraq, might object more or less strongly to the proposal. 6. Considering all the circumstances, I would suggest that I he authorised to instruct Colonel Dickson to approach the sheikh Verbally on the following lines : That His Majesty's Government have had it recently brought to their notice that Ibn Saud apparently harbours designs of trying to reduce Koweit to a position of dependence on him, similar—for instance—to that of Asir; that it is possible that the practice of direct correspondence between him—the sheikh— and Ibn Saud which has grown up of late, even though he—the sheikh—shows the correspondence to the Political Aoent, has somewhat obscured in the eyes of Ibn Saud the fact of Koweit's special relations of protection, &amp;c., with His Majesty's Government; that it would put this correspondence on a safer and more regular footing, if it was conducted as was the correspondence with the Iraq Government, i.e., through His Majesty's Government's local representatives; that, in addition, an intimation to this effect to Ibn Saud would bring sharply to his notice Koweit's relations with His Majesty's Government; and that, finally, His Majesty's Government would be glad to learn, confidentiallv and informally, what were his—the sheikh's—reactions to the proposal. I trust T may be authorised to take this step as soon as possible, and when the sheikh's attitude has become known I will make recommendations as to which alternative should be adopted. 7. The other question discussed at the meeting (referred to at the beginning of paragraph 2 above) was the exact extent of His Majesty's Government's15 obligations to protect the interests of Koweit. The most important of these obligations, which are dealt with in the India Office note on the subject, and the one which in a sense determines any others there may be, is that of protection against hostile incursions or invasions. His Majesty's Government's agreements with the sheikh are three in number : that of January 1899, that of October 1907 and that of November 1914. 8. The agreement of 1899, as far as protection is concerned, in return for the good behaviour of the sheikh and his successors, merely promised the good offices' of His Majesty's Government, 'whatever that may mean'' as Lord Lansdowne later remarked. Our construction of this agreement appears to have been the convenient one that we could choose the circumstances in which we need, or need not, protect Koweit in any particular crisis that arose, the exact area which we were responsible for defending being left more or less vague. 9. The agreement of 1907 merely confirmed from His Majesty's Govern ment that ' the town of Koweit and its boundaries ' belonged to the sheikh of that day and his successors. This agreement in no way added, in principle, to our nebulous responsibilities for the defence of Koweit, though, possibly, read with that of 1899, it might increase these responsibilities up to the ' boundaries.' 10. The 1914 agreement states that, in return for the sheikh's co-operation against the Turks, ' Koweit shall be recognised as an independent principality under British protection.' This, unlike the phraseology of the previous agree ments, is a most categorical assurance, and the word ' principality,' and not 'town,' being used would seem definitely to place the responsibility of protecting the whole of the Koweit sheikhdom on His Majesty's Government. Personally, I cannot agree with the view quoted in paragraph 15 of the India Office note that ' on a strict reading our liability could be confined to the protection of the town of Koweit, and that we are not called upon to protect Koweit as a whole.' It is true, as pointed out in the note (paragraph 16 (d)) , that neither the present sheikh, nor his predecessors, appear to have appealed under this agreement to His Majesty's Government, but that hardly relieves us from our obligations. This does not imply, of course, that His Majesty s Government's obligations relieve the sheikh completely of the responsibility of his own defence. The sheikh should certainly be able to deal with any small raids across his frontiers, and should only look for assistance from His Majesty's Government in the case of more serious incursions. This, in fact, was presumably the attitude taken up after the Akhwan operations of 1928, when the sheikh was encouraged to purchase half a dozen Ford vanettes, Lewis guns which were mounted in the vanettes, and ammunition, and when some of his men received training from the Royal Air Force as machine gunners. 11. In conclusion, I venture to suggest that this question, the exact extent of the obligations of His Majesty's Government for the protection of Koweit, be investigated with a view to a definite decision on the subject. The question is an important one, and the advantages of having a clear conception of what our responsibilities may be in time of crisis, before such a crisis arises, are obvious. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Government of India and His Majesty's Minister at Jedda. I have, &amp;c. T. 0. FOWLE, Lieutenant-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. [E 7141/46/91] 3.— Mr. Johnstone to Mr. Laithwaite. My dear Laithwaite, Foreign Office, November 25, 1933. WITH reference to our telephone conversation yesterday, I write to confirm what I said to you about Ryan's views on the proposed instructions to Dickson, which are outlined in paragraph 6 of Fowle's official letter of the 25th October regarding Saudi-Koweit relations. On a cursory reading of that letter, Ryan concurred generally in the proposed instructions, except for the opening clause, which states that Ibn Saud intends to reduce Koweit to the same sort of position as Asir. In Ryan's view, it16 is undesirable to say anything to the sheikh in the sense of that clause, as it might conceivably come to the ears of Ibn Saud, whether through the sheikh or indirectly, with unfortunate effect on our relations with him. Ryan therefore suggests that this sentence should be omitted from the instructions. I send you this simply as a record of Ryan's remarks to me; T gather that he spoke to you in the same sense. Fowle s letter has not yet been considered by my higher authorities. Yours sincerely, KENNETH JOHNSTONE. [E 775/739/91] 4.— India Office to Foreicjn Office.—{Received February 1.) Sir, India Office, February 1, 1934. I AM directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that he has had under his consideration the proceedings of the interdepartmental meeting held at the Foreign Office on Thursday, the 5th October, 1933, to discuss relations between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the Sheikh of Koweit, and also the Political Resident's despatch of the 25th October, 1933, containing Colonel Fowle's recommendations on the tentative conclusions of the meeting in question in the light of discussion of them with the Political Agent, Koweit. 2. In the light of Colonel Fowle's views, Sir Samuel Hoare is definitely of opinion that the question of declaring a protectorate over Koweit should not at present be further pursued, and he considers that it should be possible to ensure a sufficient degree of British control over the sheikhdom by adopting a policy of tightening up our control over the sheikh as opportunity offers, by filling in the gaps which at present exist in the agreements between the sheikh and His Majesty's Government. The gaps (with the exception of that discussed in the following paragraph and of a slavery agreement) are not, in fact, very serious. Apart from the major assurances contained in the agreement of 1899, the sheikh has already given undertakings in respect of the arms traffic; he is precluded from granting a pearling, sponge-fishing, or oil concession without the approval of His Majesty's Government (though as regards oil the specific undertaking contained in the letter of the 27th October, 1913 (No. XLI on p. 264 of Volume XI of the 1929 edition of Aitchisoris Treaties), is by no means so clear as could be desired); the control of aviation, whether military or civil, in his State will pass to His Majesty's Government in the event of'his accepting the proposals which the Resident has recently been instructed to make to him on this subject; while the proposed amendment of the Koweit Order in Council, once the sheikh's con currence in this has been obtained, will place the question of jurisdiction over non- Moslem foreigners in his State on a securer and more satisfactory basis. 3. The delicate question of the direct correspondence which has gradually established itself between the sheikh and Ibn Saud remains for consideration. Sir Samuel Hoare has considered the alternatives discussed in paragraph 5 of Colonel Fowle's despatch of the 25th October, and as a result he is of opinion, subject to the views of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that the first alternative suggested by the Resident (which incidentally is, apparently, likely to prove the less objectionable to the sheikh) is the right solution. Subject to Sir John Simon's concurrence, he would propose, however, to approve the Resident's recommendation that Colonel Dickson should approach the sheikh verbally on the lines suggested in paragraph 6 of Bushire despatch under con sideration, with the modification suggested in Mr. Johnstone's demi-official letter of the 25th November last to Mr. Laithwaite. Sir Samuel Hoare would also propose that it might be left to Colonel Fowle's discretion, after the sheikh's attitude has become known, to settle the matter in accordance with either of the alternatives discussed in paragraph 5 of his despatch. The important question whether special action should be taken to emphasise at Jedda to Ibn Saud the nature of the relations which exist between His Majesty's Government and the sheikh might be considered when a report has been received from Colonel Fowle. 4. The question of the obligations of His Majesty's Government for the protection of Koweit, to which the Resident refers in paragraphs 7-11 of his17 despatch, is one of considerable importance. The general position is examined in the India Office memorandum B. 427/P.Z. 6535/33, of which copies have already been communicated to the Foreign Office. The Secretary of State agrees with the Political Resident that the agreements of 1899 and 1907, containing as they do merely a promise of good offices, the applicability of which to the whole sheikhdom as distinct from the town of Koweit is open to doubt, are not of great materia] importance so far as 'protection' is concerned. The undertaking of real importance is that given to the sheikh in 1914 in return for the co-operation of his predecessor against the Turks. 5. Subject to Sir John Simon's views. Sir Samuel Hoare, on a consideration of the position as a whole, is in agreement with Colonel Fowle's view that the phraseology of this undertaking and the use of the word 'sheikhdom' and not town would appear to place definitely a responsibility for the protection of the whole principality of Koweit on His Majesty's Government. He is, at the same time, in entire agreement with the Resident that such an obligation, if His Majesty s Government now formally confirm that they recognise its existence, cannot be regarded as relieving the sheikh completely of the responsibility of his own defence, and that '' the sheikh should certainly be able to deal with any small raids across his frontiers and should only look for assistance from His Majesty's Government in the case of more serious incursions.' Such a construction would, as Colonel Fowle suggests, be consistent with the attitude adopted by His Majesty's Government after the Akhwan operations of 1928-29, though it is relevant that no close examination of the precise obligations in the matter of His Majesty's Government was undertaken at that time. Should Sir John Simon share the views expressed in this paragraph. Sir Samuel Hoare will cause the Resident to be instructed accordingly. 6. While the Secretary of State, as stated above, would be opposed to the declaration of a protectorate, and is satisfied, as at present advised, that the desiderata of His Majesty's Government can be sufficiently secured by indirect tightening up of our control over the sheikh, he is at the same time impressed by the informal character of the engagements which have been entered into on behalf of Koweit. He would, therefore, be disposed to see advantage in consolidating the various undertakings which have from time to time been given on either side in a formal treaty on the lines of the Qatar Treaty of 1916, could this be secured without much difficulty. This would probably involve a reiteration and possibly a more formal specification by His Majesty's Government of their responsibility for protection of the principality of Koweit. Moreover, as stated in the India Office note B. 427/P.Z. 6535/33 on this subject, the assurances at present given to the sheikh are, in practice, renewed to each successor in return for his acceptance of the obligations, liability for which was accepted by his predecessors, and in 1918 it appears to have been held that our obligations held good only so long as the ruling sheikh on his side complied with his engagements. It is arguable that a formal treaty might place a heavier burden on His Majesty's Government with out correspondingly binding the sheikh. But it seems doubtful whether this view could, in fact, be sustained. Formal recognition by His Majesty's Government of a Sheikh of Koweit would presumably be necessary before the engagements entered into with previous sheikhs could be regarded as binding on either party. Any formal comprehensive treaty which might be drawn up could presumably be so framed as to make it clear that obligations were entirely reciprocal, and that the liability of His Majesty 's Government held good only so long as they were satisfied with the performance by the sheikh of his obligations under the treaty. Finally, so far as protection is concerned, if the view suggested in paragraph 5 above is accepted, that a general liability (within the limits described) for the protection of the principality of Koweit as a whole must already be regarded as resting on His Majesty's Government, no material increase of their responsibilities would be involved in reiterating their acceptance of that liability in a formal treaty, while the mere fact of reiteration might make it easier to obtain the consent of the sheikh to a consolidating agreement. The Secretary of State would welcome Sir John Simon's views on this point. 7. Subject to the views of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of State would suggest that, in view of the small margin of difference which appears to exist between the provisional recommendations of the inter departmental conference of the 5th October last, the recommendations of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and the proposals in this letter, it will be [9823] D18 unnecessary, it those proposals commend themselves to Sir John Simon, to refer the question for discussion to the Official Middle East Sub-Committee. Copies of the relevant papers might, however, once final instructions have been sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, be circulated for information to the other Departments represented on that committee. I am, &amp;c. J. C. WALTON. fE 775/739/91] 5.— Foreign Office to India Office. Foreign Office, February 24, 1934. J AM directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to request that you will lay before Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare the following observations on India Office letter of the 1st February, regarding relations between His Majesty's Government in the I nited Kingdom and the Sheikh of Koweit. 2. Sir John Simon concurs in the view expressed in paragraph 2 of that letter that the question of declaring a protectorate over Koweit should not for the present be further pursued. 3. With regard to the question of direct correspondence between the sheikh and King Ibn Sand, Sir John Simon agrees that the sheikh should first be sounded orally in the sense suggested in paragraph 3 of your letter. He would, however, suggest that thereafter the Political Resident should report further which of the alternative courses of action discussed in paragraph 5 of his despatch of the 25th October, 1933, he recommends, before adopting either, in order that His Majesty's Minister at Jedda may be given an opportunity of furnishing his observations. As at present advised, Sir John Simon is inclined to prefer the second alternative proposed by Colonel Fowle (viz., that all official correspondence between the sheikh and Ibn Sand should pass exclusively through the Political Resident or Political Agent and his Majesty's representative at Jedda), as emphasising more strongly the special position of His Majesty's Government in Koweit, and placing a more effectual check upon Ibn Saud's attempts to strengthen his own position there to the detriment of that held by His Majesty's Government. This course would, in Sir John Simon's view, have the additional advantage that the influence of His Majesty's representative at Jedda could, when necessary, be more easily exerted upon the Saudi Government, if he were the actual channel of the sheikh's communications. 4. In any case, it appears that, were the first alternative adopted, it would not be sufficient simply to exercise a discreet control in Koweit over direct correspondence between King Ibn Saud and the sheikh. For, although the sheikh's side of the correspondence would be seen by the Political Agent, there would be no indication of this fact on the document which reached Ibn Saud. If, therefore, the sheikh were to send Ibn Saud a letter which the Political Agent had not seen and which His Majesty's Government wished to repudiate on that ground, they might find some difficulty in establishing with King Ibn Saud the fact that they were justified in doing so, since, so far as he could see, this letter would be no less authentic than others which he had exchanged with the sheikh, and which he had been tacitly led to consider perfectly in order. It would, therefore, in Sir John Simon's view, be necessary to add to those of the sheikh's letters which the Political Agent had seen and approved some indication of that fact. But such an arrangement would probably in the sheikh's eyes be as unwelcome a limitation on his official correspondence with Ibn Saud as the second alternative proposed by Lieutenant-Colonel Fowle. 5. It further appears to Sir John Simon that, since it is proposed in the first place, when sounding the sheikh orally, to suggest to him that all his official correspondence with Ibn Saud should be conducted through His Majesty's local representatives, to fall back later on the first alternative proposed by Lieutenant- Oolonel Fowle would represent a weakening on the part of His Majesty's Government, which on general grounds would be better avoided. 6. A final decision in the matter must, however, evidently depend upon the report furnished by Lieutenant-Colonel Fowle after the preliminary oral approach to the sheikh. 7. As regards the obligations of His Majesty's Government in respect of the protection of Koweit, Sir John Simon agrees with the views expressed in paragraphs 4 and 5 of your letter under reply.19 8. He has also considered the proposal in paragraph 6 of that letter for the conclusion of a new and comprehensive treaty between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the sheikh, which should include inter alia the acceptance by His Majesty's Government of a general liability for the protection of the whole sheikhdom within the limits indicated in paragraph 10 of Colonel Fowle's despatch of the 25th October, referred to above. While agreeing that there would be advantage in such a treaty. Sir John Simon assumes that it is not proposed to undertake the negotiation of it immediately. Prima facie it seems inadvisable to raise a possibly controversial issue of such importance with the sheikh until the question of his relations with King Ibn Saud. and that of the projected oil concession (which appears likely to indispose the sheikh, since he may lose financially by the elimination of competition between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the United States oil interests) have been disposed of. 9. As regards the possibility mentioned in paragraph 6 of your letter, that a formal treaty might be considered to place a heavier burden on His Majesty's Government than that which they at present bear in respect of Koweit, without correspondingly binding the sheikh, I am to observe that, in accordance with the construction which is usually placed upon treaties with heads of States, any formal treaty concluded with the Sheikh of Koweit would attach to Koweit as a State, and would apply automatically to the sheikh's successors. The under takings given by the two contracting parties to a treaty must certainly be construed as reciprocal. Sir John Simon notes, however, from statements made by the India Office representative at the meeting held at the Foreign Office on the 5th October to discuss this question, that it is considered that His Majesty's Government could and would remove a Sheikh of Koweit for hopeless misgovern- ment. He presumes, therefore, that His Majesty's Government could in practice prevent the accession of a ruler who seemed unlikely to observe his treaty obligations towards them, or could, at any rate, remove a ruler who after his accession in fact refused to observe those obligations. If this be so, there appears no ground for fearing that a situation might arise in which His Majesty's Government would be faced with the alternatives either of acquiescing in a refusal by the sheikh to recognise his treaty obligations or of putting an end to their treaty relations with Koweit. 10. Sir John Simon concurs in the view of Sir Samuel Hoare that it is unnecessary to refer this question to the Official Middle East Sub-Committee, but he assumes that copies of the relevant papers will be circulated later to the Departments represented thereupon. I am, &amp;c. G. W. RENDEL. [E 1593/739/91] 6.— India Office to Foreign Office.—{Received March 12.) Sir, India Office, March 10, 1934. I AM directed by the Secretary of State for India to transmit to you, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, copy of a letter to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf respecting Koweit policy. I am, &amp;c. S. F. STEWART. Enclosure in 6. Secretary of State for India to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Si ri India Office, March 9, 1934. IN reply to your confidential despatch of the 25th October, on the subject of the relations between His Majesty's Government and the Sheikh of Koweit, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the correspondence [Nos. 3, 4 and 5], copies of which have already been sent to you and to the Government of India.2. In the light of the correspondence in question, the Secretary of State agrees that the question of declaring a protectorate over Koweit should not for the present be further pursued. 3. On the subject of direct correspondence between the sheikh and King Ibn Sand, the Secretary of State, in the light of the considerations adduced in paragraphs 3- 6 of the Foreign Office letter of the 24th February, agrees with the course of action therein suggested by Sir John Simon. I am to request that you will be good enough to instruct Lieutenant-Colonel Dickson to approach the sheikh accordingly, and that you will in due course submit a further report when the result of Colonel Dickson's discussions with his Excellency is known and you are in a position to make recommendations as to the line to be adopted in pursuing this matter with the sheikh. 4. On the question of the obligations of His Majesty's Government in respect of the protection of Koweit, you will observe that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has expressed his agreement with the views contained in paragraphs 4 and 5 of India Office letter of the 1st February, 1934, The Foreign Office print, of which a copy is sent herewith j No. 11, contains a supplementary historical note prepared in this Office on the question of the view taken in 1928-29 as to the liability of His Majesty's Government for the protection of Koweit against aggression from outside 5. The Secretary of State would be glad in due course to receive your views on the proposal referred to in paragraph 6 of India Office letter of the 1st February for the conclusion of a new and comprehensive treaty between His Majesty's Government and the Sheikh of Koweit. The matter is not one of immediate urgency, and it may well be that, as suggested by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, there may be advantage in deferring any reference to it until further progress has been made in the disposal of the vexed question of the relations of the sheikh with King Ibn Sand and the questions of oil concessions for Koweit proper and the neutral zone between Koweit and Nejd. 6. The interdepartmental meeting of the 5th October recommended, inter alia, that the issue of the Saudi blockade of Koweit should be taken up with King Ibn Sand by His Majesty's Government on the basis of their obligation to protect the interests of Koweit. Disposal of this question has been deferred pending a decision on the matters discussed in the present letter, but steps are now being taken to deal with it as a matter of urgency. 7. Copies of this letter are being sent for information to the Government of India and to the Political Agent at Koweit. I am, &amp;c. J. C. WALTON</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000031_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B431</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000031</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B431</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Relations between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the Sheikh of Koweit'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-07T14:07:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This secret memorandum, printed by the Foreign Office, contains a record of a meeting held at the Foreign Office on 5 October 1933 to discuss relations between Great Britain and the Sheikh of Koweit [Kuwait], Aḥmad bin Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ, particularly in regards to Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Aziz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān Āl Sa‘ūd]. The following were present at the meeting: Mr George William Rendel (Chair), Eastern Department of the Foreign Office; Mr K R Johnston, Foreign Office; Sir Andrew Ryan, His Majesty's Minister at Jeddah; Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Craven William Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; and Mr John Gilbert Laithwaite, India Office.The memorandum also includes three appendices:'Appendix A. Note by Sir Andrew Ryan. Ibn Saud's attitude towards Kowait', dated 16 August 1933 (folios 3v-4r);'Appendix B. Provisional Note. Obligations of His Majesty's Government towards the Sheikh of Koweit', 11 October 1933, by Sir John Gilbert Laithwaite (folios 4-6), which includes sections entitled 'A. Nature of the undertakings given', 'B. Constitution of the undertakings given to the Sheikh', and 'Conclusion', with references to various correspondence in the right hand margin;'Appendix C. Supplementary Note. Question of Liability for the Protection of Koweit against Aggression from Outside. 1928-1929', by Sir John Gilbert Laithwaite, dated 6 February, 1934 (folio 6).There are also a number of enclosures which include correspondence between folios 6 and 10.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia 'Abd al-'Azīz bin 'Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight George William Rendel</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Kenneth Roy Johnstone</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight John Gilbert Laithwaite</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000031#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>