<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000121_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:53:33.364Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">v • ^ ■ V COi^IDKim ^L 445/11/49 The Persian Gulf Hesidency, Bahrain, 3rd December, 1949. Qjt^&gt; mCt4a We enclose a copy of a report from the British Middle Bast Office to the Ministry of Fuel and Power on the visit of the Venezuelan Oil Mission for your perusal and return^/u^c. First secretary H. G. Jakins , Esq., The Political iigent, Kuwait, P4. KTelegram ?rom To o.r.p. Kuv;ait. Prodrome, Bahrain Tel. No. 256. Heptd. Prodrome, London. Tel. No. 102. Dated 10th November, 1949. CONFIDENTIAL. Addressed Bahrain telegram No. 256 November 10th repeated x r oreign Office. ms Your telegram No. 273. Venezuelan Oil Mission. \ So far as the presence of the delegates in Kuwait was concerned the visit seems to have been completely innocuous. The Arabic interpreter was left behind in Damascus and may have made arrangements there to approach Shei.-ch through other channels. 2. Only one member of partv in Kuwait spoice any English. i 1 hey saw what they were shown and had one short interview with the Bhei.ch at which conversation was entirely on trivialities. = IAKINS =CO i\ 1-1 \ Y TIAL \ ? ktl Lf? Telegrain O.T.P. from Prodrome, Bahrain. i’o Political, Kuwait. Tel. No. 273. Jated 7th received Bth November, 1949. PRIOPITY. CONFIDENTIA L. Burrow’s letter No. E 12293/1537/63 of October 13th. Saudi Arabian Government have refused to receive Mission owing to Venezuelan’s support to ISRAEL in U.N.O. His ^'ajesty’s Government are apparently committed to allowing Mission to visit Kuwait. I do not thin* you can insist on being present at all talcs they may have with Sheich and even if you do this they can always get to him through one of his underlings. Please however ceep them under observation as much as possible and telegraph me report on their activities on the conclusion of their visit repeating to Foreign Office. A more detailed report should follow by post ( mut ) is desirable.A' ^ 3n Clair. Political, Kuwait. Britain, Damascus. Tel. No. risc/279. Dated 2nd November, 1949. ILllEDIATE Grateful if you would inform Nilo Panella, Secretary of /enezuelan Oil Mission, staying at Orient Palace Hotel that 3 members of Mission expected arrive Damascus by Dakota aircraft at 7.30 p.ra. Damascus time Thursday 3rd. = JAKINS = d/ift Telegram Olair. From Political, Kuwait. 1,0 Prodrome, Baghdad. Tel. No. Misc/277. -ated 1st November, 1949. IIIHSPIATE. Cuwait Oil Company Dakota NAI /P Captain Bournvialle will arrive Baghdad this evening and will be ready to tace off at 0700 hours local time tomorrow Wednesday. 2. Please notify urgently what time Mission intend to leave Baghdad tomorrow morning so that we can meet them here. JACKSONmmmm r * ■m i'elegram i^n Jlair. Prodrome, Baghdad. -l’o Political, luwait. Tel. No. Baoed SlsL^/received 1st November, 1949. P.INEDIaTS Your Nisc/276 Venezuelan Mission now wish to postpone their departure from j3aghdad till Jednesday morning. Could iCuwait Oil Company ma ce aircraft available then instead of Tuesday morning.r * Tele gram En Clair. Erom Political, Cuwait. Co Prodrome, Baghdad. Cel. No. Misc/276. Dated 31st October, 1949. IMMEDIATE For Consul. Your telegram No.. 02061. luwait Oil Jompany will send Dakota aircraft No. DAI.7C Tuesday morning for Venezuelan Mission. It will be available in Baghdad from 7 a.m. Baghdad time onwards = JA Oil SON = Q) \^\Tel egrara yrom En Clair. Prodrome, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait. Tel. No. 02061 Dated and received 31st October, 1949. Foreign Office telegram No. 1030 11th October, 1949 to us repeated to you. /enezuelan Oil Mission have just reported to us and assed that the Kuwait Oil Company aircraft shall pi etc them up here for flight to Kuwait tomorrow Tuesday. They are wording to a very tight schedule and express the strongest hope that this very short notice will not inconvenience the Oil Company Please telegraph immediately reply. BRITISH CONSULNo/V/'i7^5/18j The Political Agency, |P Kuwait* 30th October, 1949. @ Sir, I have to inform you that a Venezuelan Oil Mission comprised of Dr. Eduardo Luengo Cabello, Dr. Ezequil Monsalve Casado, Senor Luis Monsanto and a Secretary Senor Milo P&amp;nella i - arft expected to visit Kuwait from the 5 th to the 8 th November. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, D.A. Campbell, Esq., Asst. G-eneral Manager, Kuwait Oil Co., Ltd., Kuwait.■■■■■■ E 1213]/lo37/65 »Si&lt;* uFyioE a.w.i., I3t-h October, 194 ® &amp; Dear Chancery, lou v;iil have seen ireui For ©tan orfic'’ telegram Ho. 1. or the 11th October that the Venezuelan Oil Kisalon will apply to you on its return from Persia for visas for Kuwait. The Kuwait oil Oon^iany has offered to send an aircraft from Kuwait for the party but ae the Company has no agent in Bagdad we *V* ve _ l s-nreoa that the necessary arrangements oh^uld be made through you. „ould you lease arrange therefore that when the Mission applies j-oi visas they should be acted whether they till require the K.O.U. aircraft and if so on what oate they would like it to b.. in Bagdad. Kuwait 7 ^ ^ elc e 1 ' a i ,h to the Political Agent Kuwait so that he may give the necessary inform ation to the K.O.C. ^ 0!j tbs oi tnis letter have been sent to 1 em ana iluw ait* Youra ever, SAuTJifiir DKi^AHTM 'OT. The Chancery, BAGD/iD. _COST OF LIVING INDUCEV- 12298/1537/65) CONFIPKHTIAL PORSIGN OPFIGK, S.W.1 13th October, I 949 . © ♦&lt;ith reference to the correspondence about the Venezuelan Oil ^lii 8 lon 9 1 enclose a memorandum by the Ministry of Fuel and Power which we hope will prove useful to you and Jackson as background* additional to that given in Caracas Despatch Mo, 115 - in talking to the Sheik of Kuweit about the activities of the Mission. We hope it will not be necessary the ini * iat l v © in discussing the matter with the Sheik* but we suppose that it is quite likely that he may comment on the presence of the Mission and its proposals* I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Jackson and to the British Middle East Office. Burrows) Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Rupert hay* K.C. i.B, Bahrain* i* * C. 3. X. *COST OP LIVING INDICEIn Caracas' despatch No. 115 of the 22nd September we were infonaed A regarding the purpose and personnel of the delegation which the Tenssuelsn Government were sending to the Middle Seat. We understand that tbs os in purpose of this mission is to gather information so that the Venezuelans oould appraise the future iofMot of Middle Bast pstrolstau production on the markets for Venesuelan oil and encourage the Arab States to inoreas# royalties and taxation so as to rales Middle last production oosts and improve Venezuela's competitive position. Since the Venezuelans .isy endeavour to influence the 3hei 'h of Kuwait in a manner harmful to his interests and those of the Knsoit Oil Oanpany, it is desirable to consider the advice that they may tender hia. the delegation were in London on the 4th October and laft for Pari a and Rons on the October. We understand that they will be depertii^ frea Lom* or the riddle I^st in about eight d^jrs time and would be visitii^ Egypt, Iraq, Iran, Saudi Arabia and Kuwait and that, during their st^y in Kuwait, the Kuweit Oil Oorpanj will arrange that they are taken on a tour of the oil field* 4 Tiie&gt; e is no doubt that the Venezuelans are watching Middle Beat Oil field developments with considerable snxistgr. thqy realise timt the Middle Best holds i eo rvee several times those of Venesuela end ti^t the individi*! oil wsUs give s considerably greeter average yield than in Venezuela. They know that in l%8 21.6 million barrels of Middle Bast crude entered tns U.S.A. and that Airing 1349 production in tne U.S.A. has been out bask owing to the world supply and demand position. For the same reason Venezuelan output has been somewhat reduced, the average for 1%8 being 1*34 million barrels per d* as compared with an estimated production for 1949 of 1.2 miUion barrels per dgy. In view of the high rate of taxation and heavy labour oosts (including social benefit.) in the Venezuelan oil industry, the Venezuelans ere afraid that th* be uraM 0 to maintain their oonpstitivs status in world trade. In particular that the Middle Hat mey supplant Venesuela as a source of oil for Europe. 3. As regards taxation, the Venezuelan theais i. that the Oovsrment ahare with the oil oopanies the net profits derived fros in /enesuela. Pogue, a Vice-Preaident of the Chaee National Bar •am their operations Bank, has mads a /specialspecial stu^ of the Venesuelan petroleun industry. For 19^8 his dsta on Indus try - govemsent inoome are as folloasi- Received ty Oovernnent from the oil industryi- £ millions Royalties Inoome Taxes Other Taxes, etc. Total to Government Net inoome to Oil Industry Kxoess of Governosnt receipts over Industry net inoose Ratio of Gcvernaant's receipts to Industry’s net ino&lt; 204 151 —Si- 411 377 34 52/48 The following figures are also based on Pogue *- ISS£ Total to Goverment t nilllons Gross Production Millions of Statute Tons Income per Stati a. d. 163 54*8 14 10d 1947 262 61.4 21 ^ 1948 4H 71.0 28 Ud Pros these figures it will be seen that the total annual governaent Inoome has varied greatly, the main reason for this being that the royally (at a besio rate of 16 2 /^j ad valorem) depends upon the U. S. open market price of crude oil. In 1949 tueie h&amp;b been a considerable drop in U«S» prio— of hoa*y orud. oil. and alao for fuel oil, which will bring about an appreciable reliction in the Venezuela Coveriwent’s oil revenue for 1949, both on account of royalties and the indistry’s net profits. &amp; 4&gt; in advantage whioh Kuwait has over Venesuela is that the Kuwait Oil Coupeny royalty and taxation are on a basis of a fixed rate per ton cf oU produced, (Ra. 3 annas 4)* Biis amount does not fluctuate witn the nnrket price of crude oil and therefore, with the progressive in or ease in production whioh la taking plaoa in Kwrait, the aieikh may expect an i nor ease in revenue in direct proportion to the ooqpany's output. Aw It is of oourae self erident that tha Kuwait Oil Company*a paynent par ton la low oo^ared with pcyaanta uade in Tanoauala and for that oattor with paynanta made in aorae other Middle £aat ooun tries, auoh aa Saudi drab la, where the amount is A/Od ^oldL The Aaierioan Independent Oil Ca.ipai^r's oonoeaeiom the ooverln&amp; Kuwait share of the Neutral Zone end the three ialanda alao provide for high royalty payments (/2.50 per ton, plus 7*3 oenta for tax exan^tlon)* t, £ h. The V—ewnelane may endeavour to give the Sheikh the lupreaaion that Kuwait oil has the same f. o. b* value Persian Gulf aa Tenesuelan oil at Oaribbeaii seaboard and that tharefore he should be entitled to receive realty in sons ^my related to U«S. prices of crude oil* If this should ooour it would be weil to point out to him that there la at present a world crude oil surplus and that it is in his own interest that Kuwait oil should be able to octets favourably in world trade. In this connection it is important to recognise that Kuwait has great geographical disadvantages occpared with Teneauela, la not only muon nearer to VTestern iko-opean markets, but naa tha enortaoim U. 3. market virtually at its doorstep* This is illustrated hy typical freight re tea per ton, as in early 19t9i- Kuaait - U*K* 57/6d (kribbean - U.K. &gt;2/6d Teneauela - Mew Tork Iti/Od Kuwait - Kew Tork 75 /od If therefore Kumlt rtyelty retea ware unduly ii.flated tea mere dlatant Mrketa for Kuweit oil would hare to ha surrender ad and tea total realty receivable by tha Sheikh would ha oarraapondingly reduced, even tho^h the rata par tea were maintained* For your private information, teia difference can alao ha Illustrated hr tne currant prlcee of ai-ilsr grad., of crude oil in the Oeribbaan and tea Paraten Gulf, which aret- US* X Po* barrel Qi-ude oU, Cab. i'ucrto La Crua (Bastern Tei.ezuala) / 2.59 ^ * ' Baa Tanm a ^ ^ ^ 7 , (Oaltax price ehar G ad for or-ud. oil financed by Koona.io Oo-operatto* Adjoin ia tret ion for sale in Wee tern Europe). ■ ■ ■ * • v . tith October. l')U9Jkk 12(445/1/49) N ' I'rfoo. o His Majesty’s Political riesidenc^ at Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Political , Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British RESIDENCY., BAHhAlN. 10th October, 194 9 , Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. From Chancery, Caracas, to S. American Dept., 129/2/49 of 7th Sept. Subject. Visit of Venezuelan oil mission to Saudi Arabia, Persia, Iraq Kuwait. ^ w ■ - I CONFIDES TIAL Kuwait Rwett* He W /8- . J 3479a 35167 (8)—— British Embassy CAitAUitS ( 129/2/49) 7th September, 1949 Dear Department, This letter serves as advance notice a fraternal mission to visit Saudi Arabia, Iran, alities will form the Special Mission: Dr. Eduardo Luongo Cabello. Sehor Luis Emilio Monsanto. Dr. Ezequil Monsaive Casado. Secretary: Sehor Milo Pane 11 a. * e expect to report further quite alert to the increasing demands in Iran for a larger share in the proceeds from oil. Soutn American Department, Foreign Office, London S.w.l. P.S. An interim memorandum is enclosed. that the Venezuelan Government propose to send ®&amp;ypt, Iiaq and Kuweit. The following person short ly. 3* Venezuelan oil circles are, of course, Yours ever, ^HAflOEttY.Enclosure to Caracas letter (129/2/U9) 22 * - ^ J 4 4 Tl^e following are particulars of the Venezuelan oil mission to the Middle East, which is expected to leave Venezuela on September 15th, 1949 : Chief of Mission Eduardo Luongo Cabello, engineer, bom 11«4#06 at Caribe, State of Monagas* Chief of the Department of Economics of the Office of Hydrocarbons^ Highly considered by Creole Petroleum Company for whom he formerly worked. Is an intimate of Egaha, Minister of Development. Dr* Ezequiel Mon salve Casado, teom 27* 3.18 at Carupano, State of Sucre. Professor of Mining legislation in the University of Venezuela*/ Is interested also in labour legislation. None too good a lawyer. Luis E. Monsanto , born k.ll.Ok in Caracas. Economist. Venezuelan Minister in Czechoslovakia.^ Secretary mio Panella, bom 25.8.04. in Rone, Italy, and speaks a number of oriental languages. s:^s on ror” s^X ^^rT 0 ^V 1 *' 18 b8in S allowed for tL^Sh studies. The Mission is described as a good will tour. / following^mes : 688 ^ being 8 ° Ught in Caracae for the U.S.A*, U.K*, Canada, No doubt visas for the Middl in Washington. Prance, Italy, Belgium, Holland, e Eastern countries are being sought 15th. ?hcy P a^o^vLi 1 t a Klw f ?o r rk a ^X t ° n p by air S' S «Ptenber etc. and then London If Parls ’ Gerl ® v a. Rone and Iran should be r“cted about the Ld ofTcLber f0l ^ Wed ’ L °\ d0n pause in the United Kingdom on the way^ut. y however » British Embassy, Caracas* 8 th September, 1949*Telegram From O.T.P. Prodrome, London. To Prodrome, Baghdad Tel. No. 1030 Heptd. Tehran, Bahrain, Kuwait, J edda, Cairo, British Middle East SAVING TO Caracas, Washington, ) ) ) ) Office,) for ) information. ) ) ) ) Tel. No. 86. Dated 11th received 13th October, 1949. RESTRICTED Addressed Baghdad telegram No. 1030 October 11th repeated for information to Tehran, Bahrain, Kuwait, Jedda, Cairo, British Middle East Office and Saving to Caracas, and Washington. ^ Of Co / . Tehran telegram No. 160 to you. Particulars of Venezuelan Oil Mission are given in Caracas despatch No. 115 September 22nd forwarded to you by bag. Members of the Mission are Dr. LUENG0, a technician from the Venezuelan Ministry of Economics, Dr. MANSLAVE, / professor of Mining legislation, Senhor MONSANTO, Venezuelan Minister Prague to give a diplomatic flavour and an Arabic speaKing secretary. 2. The swerve of order may have sprung from the International Labour Office Petroleum Industrial Committee’s meeting last winter. It has been nurtured by warnings of Shell and other companies operating in Venezuela that increasingly high-cost/high-cost 7enezuelan production may be endangered by a flood of cheap Middle East Oil. The timing of the Mission’s visit to the Middle East is most embarrassing to the United ..vingdom companies operating there and the discussion of its activities will need careful handling. '.Ve are considering whether we can provide you with any useful talking points. 3. -Ve shall be glad to have reports of the Mission’s activities particularly as they expect to spend a weeic in London on their return % from the Middle East. British companies operating ( in Venezuela have entertained Mission in London and the Kuwait Oil Company have offered to help them in Kuwait. Please arrange for the issue of necessary visas for Kuwait on their arrival in Baghdad from J l Tehran. The Mission expect to be in Cuwait about 5th to 8th November. SO SEA■■■■■Iw British Bmbassy CAkACAS 22nd September, 19^9 Despatch ff* 115 ■ /S' &amp; Sir, ^ T have the honour to inform vou that, yesterday a Venezuelan good will mission left for Washington to undertake from tiiere a tour of the MEL&amp;dle Xtsst. Xt had- originally oeen planned for tiie party to leave on September 15 th* They are now expected to visit Washington and New York for further briefing in oil circles. They will then go to London, Paris. Geneva, and Home, on the way to Cairo; they will return via London, arriving there towards the end of December. Selz-ium and Holland may also be included in the itinerary. 2. The ostensible reason for the tour is that the Ministry of Development, and the Venezuelan Government have received so many warnings about the threat of competition from Middle Eastern oil that the Government wish to gain first hand information about the menace. The decision to send such a mission was taken well before the devaluation of sterling was announced. 2* . As ^ported in the enclosure to my Chancery’s letter to t.ie South American Department (129/2/49) of September 7 th, the party will consist of the following personalities; tt' / K S uardo Ca bello, engineer, bom 11.4.0b at Caribe, State of I^onagas. Chief of the depart ment of Economics of the Office of Hydrocarbons. Highly considered by Creole Petroleum Company for whom he formerly worked. Is an intimate of Egafla, Minister of 1 eve 1 opinent. Dr. Exiquil TTonsal ve Casado, bom 27.3.18 at Carupano. otate of Sucre:Professor of Mining legislation in the University of Venezuela. Is interested also in labour legislation. None too pood a lawyer. Luis v. Monsanto , bom 4.11.04 in Caracas. Economist and ciplomat;served in Italy in 1947 and is now Venezuelan sinister to Czechoslovakia. Secretary , Milo Pane11a . bom 25.8.04 in Home, Italy, and was chosen for his knowledge of oriental languages. The Middle Eastern countries to be visited include Egypt Iraq, Tran, Kuweit and Saudi Arabia. * 4 4. Even before the devaluation of sterling the high cost Venezuelan economy was dangerously vulnerable to compe tition trom oil produced more cheaply elsewhere. The average Venezuelan well may pump only 300 barrels of oil a day... His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Egreign Office, L neon S.w.l.a day in comparison with th«* 5000 to 7000 barrels which frequently gush ‘from wells in the Muslim world. For some months, the oil companies have been seeking to drjve home the lesson tliat the Venezuelan problem, is no longer a mere function of discovery and production, or of labour relations and wages. The outstan-' ding requirement is to find and maintain markets abroad. Until recently, Venezuelans remained confident that the United States would require Venezuelan production in the event of war; and their complacency was enhanced by reflection upon the vulnerable position of the Arab world. It v^as, therefore, a shock to receive a warning from the American Ambassador apropos Vene zuelan leanings to bilateralism in trade agreements, that American producers might well prevail in their present desire to restrict the importation into the United States of Venezuelan petroleum products. The discovery of large reserves in the Province of Alberta, capable of easy shipment, in due course, to the north west or the United States, gave point to this warning* 5. It is likely, therefore, that the decision to send out a reconnaissance party will have been inspired by a feeling of not unjustifiable alarm. The Venezuelan Government and press are not unaware that their own success in gaining a share in the proceeds from the industry, which is never less than 50^ in any single year, is being iwdtiaiec in Iran, . :.th Incre asing success. You will notice that the growing influence of Italians, which I hove obsex*ved in other connexions, is reflected in the Vicsion, which is thus fortified with Kurope&amp;n energy and resourcefulness. 6 . I have already reported elsewhere that the Venezuelan iovemment are striving towards bilaterAlisa. a reements in their co. uerci '•! relations. Vow t .t.-e oil prov ucing co- riles are c&lt; iting i ie com 1 ruction of re:'i nn res capable of processing up to ten per cent of the national out- puton Venezuelan soil the Government are within sight of influence on the direction of a proportion of expoi^s which have hitherto been shipped to the open sea for routeing after departure from Venezuelan waters. I am currently reporting the abrogation or limited extension of certain modus vivendi with other countries which provide for most favoured nation treatment. The termination of the modus vivendi with Canada is of special interest in the generaT context of oil market development# and prospects. 7* I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Representatives at Bagdad, Cairo, Jedda, Tehran, and Washington. I enclose an extra copy for transmission, if convenient, to the Political Resident at Kuweit. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Sir, Your obedient Servant, J.H. Magowan.I # i INDIA OFFICE RECORDS .Z.Ql.Lk MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000121_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/270</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000121</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/270</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File C 5/18 Venezuelan Oil Mission'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-17T16:54:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (27 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 29; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are present in parallel; one sequence is also written in pencil, the other sequence is written in ink, but neither sequence is circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British consular representatives in Caracas, Venezuela and the Persian Gulf documenting the progress, and ascertaining the reasons for a visit by a delegation of Venezuelan officials and oil industry specialists to Kuwait. The file spells out the delegation's travel plans, possible motivations and various audiences with local rulers.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oil</topic></subject><subject><topic>State visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000121#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>