<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00003c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:00:07.767Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00003c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/121, ff 140-145</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00003c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/121, ff 140-145</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 352: Lieutenant-Colonel Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to His Excellency Lieutenant-Colonel Justin Sheil CB, Her Majesty's Minister Plenipotentiary and Envoy Extraordinary at the Court of Persia, Tehran</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1850/1850</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-21T00:46:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>6 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Samuell Hennell reports that he has recently received rukums from the Prince Governor of Fars announcing that Mirza Hassan Ally Khan, son of Hajee Kuwam, has been appointed Governor of Bushire, in place of Sheik Nasir. Hennell states that Mirza Joonee, Sheik Nasir's confidential secretary, has arrived in Bushire, accompanied by Mahomed Cazim Sooltan, for the purpose of disposing of the vessels belonging to Sheik Nasir, so that the former Governor can pay up the balance of 5,000 tomans that is demanded from him. The letter includes the following enclosures:Translated substance of a report (not dated) from the Agent at Shiraz, covering events from 23 July to 8 August 1850;Translated substance of a monthly report (not dated) from the Agent at Shiraz, covering events from 10 to 27 August 1850.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051546.0x00003c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>