<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000027_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-12-04T11:26:22.753Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">erfxr** i BRITISH CONSULATE MUSCAT [ JOT.: ] FILS NO: 8/6? NAME OF FILE: MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: MUSCAT - OMAN TREATY.ONPIDSNTIAL ■Ali s T —— ( A*£i /c/ // - British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat October 193c# From R.EvL.Wingate Ssq. I.C.ft. political A^ent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat To The Deputy Political Resident, Bashirs Sir, X have the honour to forward a report on the negotiations carried on throu^ my mediation as the representative of the British Government between the Government of H*H# the Sultan of Muscat and the tribes of interior Oman which terminated in tne reestablishment of peaceful relations on the 8th October 1930. In order make the situation quite clear X »*ave found it necessary to summarise very briefly the history and causes of tne late rising, and to £ive in some detail tne sequence of events from October 1919 till the conclusion of the ne^otia- -tions. I wish to draw the attention of Government to the admirable arrangements made by Captain Pearson commanding tue detachment of tne l/117th Mahrattae at M scat for my escort and for the tents etc for the reception of -the Oman Sheikhs. Finally I wish to brin^ to the notice of Government the excellent work performed by the Consular Dragoman, Ehtisham-ud-doulan Khan. The negotiations in question xiave been O olng on for a year, and have entailed arduous ax3U* i v. and continual watchfullness. During this period he has been indefatigable in obtaining information, and has more than once been entrusted by me witii work x*x*Mxsx*«*aa* needing the most delicate handling. At the meeting itself he a so vid excellent work.Brief survey of causes and history of the rebellion of the Oman tribes under the leadership of their elected Imam Sheikh Salim bin Rashid al Kharusi till 1915. A perusal of any history official or ot'irwise of Muscat and Oman will show for several hundred years examples of *evolutior^ # anarchy and murder almost un- -paralleled even in Arabian history. Since the expulsion of the Portuguese however there has been, except during th the periods of Persian or Wahabi domination, a r^ler b oth / combining spiritual and temporal authority/acknow- -ledged nominally by all thetribes. According to the Ibadhi sect of Islam such an Imam al Muslimin must be elected by the people, and there is no right of heredity, though often the son of the dead Imam was accepted as Imam. With the accession to the Imamate of Ahmed Albu i Saidi, the founder of the present dynasty, the system seems to have changed and the rulers of Muscat and Oman succeeded as a dynasty without the formality of election as Imam. This definite departure 0 gfYJ r Sfn W AhSed U 110,11 aurped the po»er from hia brother Said bin Ahiued bin Ahme&lt;V w * 10 elected imam. The latter retained the title of Imam till his death, but no temporal power. »rv»« -rmio &lt;vf flultan and of hi MW Q 4 /■» lasted from about 1790 till 185* marked the growth of sea power, foreign conquests, the most important of which was Zanzibar, and the removal of the capital from Rustaq in the interior to Muscat on the coast, and foreign treaties and interference, almost entirely Britii The removal of the capital to the coas^: cut off from the interior has been stated by some as the beginning of the loss of hold by the Sultans ^f#Xover the interior, as impolitic and as such/an move. This is however open to question. It is more probable that the Bu tan knew they could hope better to control with outside power and this outside power they obtained from the: r se power and their foreign possessions. ItIt 1 b a Tact however that from the death of Saiyid Said the power of the Sultansover the interior became more than ever# Attacks could only be warded oil by bribery, no revenue wobtained, travel was dangerous and there were several attempts by the mnni tribes to set up Imams of their own. An attempt had actually been made in 1849. In 1848 Azaan bin (fcais nrxt elected Imam actually ruled in Muscat, and thou#i later ejected many similar attempts were made during the reign of Turki and the earlier years of the reign of -*aisal to depose the Sultan, vho may have said to have been ^aved only by our support. Finally in 1913, after an elabor te conspiracy of several ye-rs fostered by the famous blind Ibadhi mullah Sheikh Abdullah bin Humaid as Sulimi,the (train tribee rose in a body elected Snlim bin Rashid ol Kharuei a 8 their Imam an- by 1915 hwl obtained complete control of all wa srcx-u? proper where they organised a government. It will thue be seen that for more than dO years there has be.n active opposition to the ruling house by the » Oman tribes. The causes of this opposition may he briefly summarised as follows;* (1) Religion. According to the ibadhi religion their ruler must be elected. The Sultans who had not undergone this formality were therefor* usurpers. y (2) The personal character of Sultans themselves . This deteriorated at an alarming rate, and the repeated assertion of the Oaani tribes that they were unfit to rule does not 1 *k justi- -fioation. (3) The character of the Sultans* rule. A his was corrupt to a degree, and the element of personal control and touch by the ruler hirasel which with the -'Tab will palliate even the worst forms of corruption, was completely ^entjd XXJC 3 a absent* (4) foreign interference* This appeared in the eyes of t the fanatical and ignorant Omanis to be directed against their most cherished rights such as the importation of arms and slaves* In these the Sultan s acquiesced without consulting his subjects accepting large sums of money for his acquiescence# not one penny of which money the Omanis ever saw* At the some time our policy in 2ansibar lost nothing in the telling* Several of the reasons why the Sultans were un* ble to cope with the rebellion are contained in these* But to them may be added three more* The loss of Zanzibar and its revenues* the loss of sea power owing to the introduction of steam, and finally and most important of all the effects of British influence* When considering our policy in Huscat and Uman this last point must never be lost sight of* A brief perusal of the treaties and engagements with the rulers of Muscat will show that our influence has been entirely self interested, has paid no regard to the peculiar political and socicl conditions of the country and its rulers, and by bribing effete Sultans to enforce unpalatable measures which benefitted none but ourselves, and permitting them to misrule without protest has done more to alienate the interior and to prevent the Sultans from re-establishing their authority than all the rest put together* In other words it hae been support wrongly applied, in money and not in essentials, interference in external affairs which must have seriously reacted upon internal peace and no palliative except money which was thrown into the sea or worse by those into whose hands we\ 4 put it* The result imu that we were reduced to the absurd position of supporting by armed force under our treaty obligations a ruler against whom most of his subjects wsro in open rebellion# who v.ue theoretically independent and yet who would bs driven into the sea in a day if it were not for us. The immediate causes of the 1913 rebellion were an outbrenJf of religious fanaticism coinciding with the stoppage of the importation of arias. Events from Colonel Bonn’s first meeting with the unan Chiefs in 1916 till iiojor iiaworth’s meetii^ with the some in September 1919. Balih al u arithi ar4 many Umun Gheikhs attacked in force our d femes at ^ait-al-Palaj guarding Mattrah. The attack was beaten off with serious loss to the Omanis who learnt their lesson there once and for all. The Imam however remained in indisputable possession of the interior and a constant probably menace to the coast towns which he would/have ftkAhlihiy taken had it not been for the certainty that he would be driven out in a few days with the advent of a British man-of-war. In May Lt-oclone 1 Benn the Political Agent sent a cir- -cular letter to the Oman Gheikhs asking for a conference in which peace might be arranged between the Sultan and the Imam. This did not meet with a very warm response in the interior# but after considerable correspondence a meeting was finally arranged and took place at Sib on the 16th September 1916 between Colonel Benn and Sheikh Jsa as the representative of the $ Iiuam’s party. This meeting was entirely abortive. In the Gultan’s \ * fflind the panmount idea Shut he would eventually roc over hie authority in the interior, in the Hinds of the repre- -sentatiree of the Inantheir unassailable position as conquerors and their mor 1 position as Ibadhis obeying5 the dictates of religion* The two moat important point® demanded by ths 13ultan were the return of the fort® # and the recognition of hie temporal supremacy in mem n* The®® were categorically refused by the vmanie who demanded th**t the Bultan should reform hi© government according to their idea®, that they should bo given auboidiets* anas and ao on* Ho reconciliation was possible and the negotiation© were broken off* nr JTrom this date till 1918 no further etepe were tak« taward« a aettlement. The Imam bucked up by the two great chiefs Bheikh lea bin ^alih ai harithi head of the Hinawi confederation ar» Sheikh Hixraiyar bin msir al Nabhani head of or the Ghafiri confederation consolidated hi« power in the interj On the other hand the Sultan^ government sank from bad to worse* because involved in hopeless debt ar»i reached *n unpuralleled degree of ineptitude* In ilarch 1918 during the absence of the Sultan four relations of Ghei£h Isa 1 a c?june down into buec&amp;t and wore seized by Juiyid ftadir who wua acting for the Sultan and imprisoned. Xhis resulted in letters from Sheikh low to the Sultan and the i'clitical ^gent asking for their release* The Sultan in return insisted on the return of the v luable gardens seised by the vEr-nie* arid the i'olitioal Agent declined to interfere except on thi&gt;co lines an^ the matter was dropped. In the mean time the Political Agent iMujur iiaworl had realised the imperative necessity of taking drastic measures to preserve the Sultan*• government on the coast from complete financial and actual collapse* and a loan to pay off the Sultan’s debts and arrangements to obtain the * * were service** of an experienced •. dUBtorie official wxxx m f *de. Cur victories in the great war no* mad® th® occasion a ®uitabl« onefor again approaching the uaanis wit £ view to a settlement and the i oliuic&lt;».l Agent auijcr Haw or t addressed a very strong letter to the leaders in fc; rch 1919 considerableV 6 . Considerable correspondence resulted and finally Sheikh Isa met the Political Agent at Sib on the 15th September 1919• By this time it had been realised, and the realisation was more than confirmed at the meeting, that the recognistion of the Sultan in the Interior was as impossible e as that he should reconquer Oman by force. His own territory was on its last legs. He* only stood at all with our support. The best means was therefore the recognition of the status quo and the terms discussed and which it seemed might eventually form the basis of an agreement were that the -a** Su ltan (1) should remove all restrictions on entry to the town of the coast (2) Reduce the zakat on goods coming from the coast towns to the interior to 5 percent (3) Return fugitive from justice (4} Release the four Omani prisoners and that the Omanis (1) Should guarantee not to attack the Sultan^ territoryor interfere in his government (2) Should guarantee the safety of travellers and freedom of trade (3) Should hear and decide cases against Omanis (4) Should return fugitives from justice (6) Should return the valuable gardens belongin* to two of the most important of the Sultan 1 1 subjects seized by the Omanis. 3, Brents from October 1919 to October 1920 including the final settlement. The situation therefore on my arrival October was in (X) The reform of the administration of the territory controlled by the Sultan had to be ( 2 ) taken in fex** hand An agreement was to be arranged if possible throi7 through tho mediation of the Political Agent between the laum 1 a pc.rty tho Sultan It wu.b at onco clear that these two matters were closely bound together. In the firet place the strengthening of the Sultan’s administration would /^inevitably result in a decrease in the comparative power of the Omanis • In the second place an agreement and the establishment of peace would enable l*A*'* m V r the reform of the administration to be proceeded with more rapidity. The reform of the administration was therefore tackled with vigour, and Sheikh Said bin haiiir al Kindi a | w prominent mullah of tho Ibadhi sect resident in the territories of the Sultan, and greatly respected in unan, was sent by me to Ki2wa v the seat of the lama. f to endeavour to obtain uxktntxMttm ratification of t o terms discussed at Sib. would be strongly against the return of the gardens, which ■ « 0 »' were mostly in their hands and from which the mullahs derived a lucrative income. The leader of the opposition party was Hasir bin Kashid al Xharusi, the brother of the Imam and hie 9ali in Rustaq* The mission was more than once on the point 01 success, but finally fter 4 months of negotiations and intrigue the Imam in February definitely refused ;o oheikh ^ai and Sheikh tsa to ratify the terns. The possibility of this unfavourable resulthnd be^n foreseen for some time, and a definite plan of action prepared to meet the emergency. The Omanis had been given a V fair field and plenty of favour. They had be^n with honeyed words. They had refused peace owing to ignorance and religious prejudice it is true, possibly yo t il ^ c the lukewarmness of the chief protagonist in th c' Sheikh Isa, but actually because the Ckoanio thought that8 we were not backing the Sultan with any degree of enthsiaBm and that therefore they could go ae far as they liked with imp uni ty. The Omanis were therefore to be shown that our suppoi of the Sultan was a reality, and not only that but that the Sultan was capable of retaliating very effectively on the Omanis by taxing their produce heavily when it came down to thi coast for export* Reliable information from the interior showed that owing to the long stoppage of the import of arms and ammunition the Gftnanis had largely lost their offensive power, and were by no means enthusiastic for the Imam whose puritanical fanaticism was making life intolerable, and the exactions of whose brothers had raised a storm of protest. The moment was therefore opportune for changing from a weak defensive to a vigorous offensive. It was pointed out that if certain steps were taken which involved no use of force by us, it was extremely probable that the Omanis would e see reason. Even if they did not do so for some time it would not matter as affairs would eventually autamatically adjust themselves with the increase of the Sultan’s power following on the reform of his administration* The following events therefore took place on the refusal of the Imam to ratify (1) The negotiations were broken off by me in th&lt; most insulting fashion (2) A British adviser to the Sultan appeared (3) The Sultan accompanied by me went on an official visit to His Excellency the Vicer- in India leaving the british adviser in charge of the State (4) A British warship, in pursuance of our engagements to support the authority of t Sultan on the coast, proceeded to iahsnaal Sur where the authority of the &amp;ultan h.- been9 been defiaci and inflicted puniadvent at thw f©ra«r pl^ce with «£Ood results. The position of the Xnjaaw.s at the suae womcnt greatly weakened by the sudden death of Sheikh hai&amp;iyur bin Hasir al Ik^bhani the eiobt powerful chieftain and his staunchest supporter t whose successor was an inexperienced bwj boy of 14• These events created consternation in uaan only to be Increased on my return from India by th^ publication of notices by the Sultan's government imposing &amp; penal sakat of percent on all dates and 50 percent on pomegranates brought by the Oraanie to the coast towns, instead of the customary 5 percent* The procl mationc announcing the imposition of thia penr. 1 tf^x were very carefully worded, making it perfectly clear even to the Uoanis that the tax wo.» imposed as a punishment owing to iheir refusal to give up the looted property and to c-urae to terms* Coincident with the publication of these noticei ( in kay ) a very significant incident occurred. Sosir bin Hushid al aharusi who had been suffering inconsiderable trouble from dimed bin Ibrahim, th# ruler of H&amp;s&amp;ijust within the Sultan’s territory, laid siege to iiax/tm. a eisal! expedi- -tion was organised by the iuitan’s government and ^asir bin Bashid was compelled to retreat with every appearance of ignominy, moot of his men deserting him, and might even have lost Hustaq. Such an i/icident would have been unthinkable six months previously. Trom this moment events moved rapidly •it may almost be said according to plan* Sheikh after Sheikh approa ed the Imam pointing cut that they were powerless to resist greed of his brother, and praying him to return the gurd^ns and come to terms* the Imam domiftHted by his brother proved obduratearvi dlacontcrit grow.. nnc-lly10 . finally ;&gt;h©ikh himself whose last letter 1 had torn up and refused to answer addressed n&lt;$ himself on 29th June* I seised the opportunity to write a strong »nd **** lengthy reply emplinsiBing thnt the British government wao entirely behind the Sultan in this ratter, and that I would anything neither meet him nor xsxi;* disouas/with him till the looted gardens h?\d been first returned* l took the precaution of allowing the contents of this letter to leak out before it wuo sent. ;here is little doubt that this letter dispelled any remaining doubts that the (tennis may have hud. On 21st July the Imaro Sheikh Salim bin rashid al Khar us i was murdered at JChadra. The immediate cause of his murder was stated to hobo been an insult to one of his guard. real reason of his death,which wrs confirmed from many sources, vas that the tribes were praetloally in open revolt against his rule and that of his brother f 8 , which was a cora— -binntion of utter Mffwftxyx r^li^icnj^ bigotry combined with shameless selfishness and oppression ?.nd a corv'lete disre^ird &lt; of politioas or go vernraent, all of which in addition to th.ir inherent disadvantages were resulting in e.11 sorts of trying restrictions from the Sultan’s government, which they were powerless to resist, culminating in the penal sakat. uman was now wi fhout a lender nd the greatest confusion prevailed. The *'ali« of the late I warn t;ere driven oui immediately by the infuriated tribesmen and had to flee for thi their lives. Many tribes sent tentative offers of allegiance to the Sultan*0 government. Sheikh Isa begrn to collect men in Shurkiyah, and on the other side the Sultan's government made a determined effort to regain their hold over Oman. The situation was now extremely interesting, and provided the British Government could preserve an attitude of strict neutrality, ono of two results both equally favour- -able to a satisfactory settlement would be bound to occur. ^ither12 . (ft ' 7 / iteelf in Isa*® far our he acttsd with ^reat policy 9 a» indeed he wne compelled to by the insecurity of hie pocition which depended for its consolidation on the removal of the penal J sakat. He obt' ined the retain of the gardensfrom the lau-m* wr wrote to mo ( then in India ) that he had done so, and asked for a meeting. This was finally arranged ana took place at Sib from the 23rd to 2Sth September d©2U. It is wprthy of note tfc that on this occasion, as a mark of the complete change in the political situation and in the attitude of the tribes caused by the new policy, that lea sent in letter after letti asking for meeting and actually waited for me 20 days at Khoz, while on previous occasions exactly the reverse had beenthe case. On the 21st Captain Ihomson cf the l/117th iiiahrattas proceeded with an escort of 50 men of the 117th to Sib by native sailing boat, to the house of the ^ali of Huttrah at the edge of the gardens which had been fixed as rendez vous. Tents were erected close by fdr the entertain- -nr nt of the Sheikhs. Within a few hours of my arrival from India on the 22nd, accompanied by Captain i e&amp;rson Commanding the detachment of the 117th at kuttrah. Captain kenon, M.O., &amp;nc the Consular dragoman 1 embarked in a native sailing vessel for Sib, arriving there the afternoon of the 23rd. A mesaagt was sent immediately to oheikh ^sa who was at Khoz only 2 hours distance. Karly on thu morning of the 24th Sheikh *sa accompanied by over twenty Oman Sheikhs and three hundred emnelmen arrived at the rendez vous. When they hrd dis- -mounted and entered the tents I paid the customary visit on them as their host remaining cbout 10 minutes. The first meeting took place an hour later and lasted some two hours. The question pressed by me was the authorisation of Sheikh Isa I* remembered •‘‘t will be h13 « In this connection thi^t on the occ .®ion of the luat meeting hw wo® now fu x ly /iu Jioriue&lt;i• rin^illy, he hc.virv5 stoted ond his word having be«n confirmed by other Sheikhs that he wae fully authorised by the Imam it wr.e agreed that the terms if arranfs^d would bo signed by him and the Sheikhs present in my presence, ansi that they would then ttdeo the document away and obtain the eigniiture of the Imiaa and of any other Sheikhs whom I might name. &lt;tfter the midday meal a further lonfe meeting was K id tu discus® the i.ctw 1 terms. There were present at this meeting only Sheikh fea, Said hasir al Kindi, the Consular dr^igom n and myself. Twelve extravag nt terms were put forward by the Cm^nie (u That the ir^upendenoe of Omiin should be recognised. (t:) That the aakat should be reduced to 5 £ \Z)i That the Cia^nis ehculJ be free and safe in th e Sultan* 3 territory• (4; That the British Government should not help their eimaies ( presumably meaning the ( 6 ) ( 6 ) (7) ( 8 ) (9) ( 10 ) ( 11 ) (12) Suit vn ). That nothinc should bn done against their religi on That passport* should not be ne 4ed for ther That they should be allowed to purchase cartridges. Th&amp;t the Cult, n should subsidise them That r 11 documents suoh as passports etc from the Imam should b** countersigned by the Political A gent and not by the Sultan That ^ashid bin Czaia should not be allowed in Oman Ihut Sheikh Said bin lie el r al Kindi should be guaranteed safety in the Sultan 1 * territc That the Sultan should roturn fugitive®14 from their justice* A® against this they proposed to promise (1; Not to attack the Sultan’s territory or to interfere in his government (Ji) To allow freedom of trade and travel in Uaan. Of the terms they proposed to exact from the Sultan all except (2) and (3) and (12) were clearly absurd. By a mixture of argument, cajolery and threats and the final state- •ment that if they were not prepared to accept the terms origin* ally agreed upon Z would leave at once, they finally agreed to asking only (2), (3) and (12) from the Sultan. Terms (10) and (11) were put in by Sheikh ^aid bin Nasir al Kinii only owing to personal enmity and were soon disposed of. Jix (4) was point in out as being absurd- if we were mediating/an agreement they could rely on our not backing the other side unless they flagrantly broke it. (5) was pointed out ae a sine qua non. (6) and (9) were pointed as equivalent to asking for exemptions of formalities which had to be undergone by the whole world, and as implying no disgraoebut which even British citizens had to put up with in other countries. (7) was pointed out as impossible owing to international agreement and it was added that in any case permission to import could not be given till we were sure by experience of their good intentions. (1) was categorically refused and it was explained that as they had got practical ind-pendence what more did they want. (8) was laughed at. Finally the following terms were arranged • The Sultan's government would (1) Eeduoe the sakat on all goods coining into the coast towns to 5 percent. (2) Guarantee safety and freedom for Canunis in the Coatt towns. (3) Remove all restrictions on the entry of Caanie into Rusoat and Muttrah. (4) Return fugitives from their justice and not15 not interfere in their interml affair®. ( Note. The word here used was d&amp;khillyut a kum, which i® very important as it means no more than it ft&amp;ys, their internal affairs, and the Sultan cannot argue should he choose to do so that there is any derogation of his supreme authority. On the Other hand the Cteanis are at liberty to regard it as complete independence. Noth sides are therefore satisfied ). The Ck&amp;unis would (1) Kerneln in peace with the Sultan# not attack the const and not interfere with his government (2) Permit freedom of trade and travel in Oman and guarantee the safety of travellers. (3) Would return and protect fugitives from the , , r - ‘ Sultan's justice (4) Would hear the claims of traders and others against umanis according to Sahara. It is amusing to note that the terms asked from the Sultan was originally only three, (2) and (3) being combined. When the Omanis found that they had to concede four terms to the Sultan they were somewhat upset, but the situation was saved by splitting tht second term into two . As regards the fourth term conceded by the Omanis, hearing by the ohara was inevitable as they have no other courts. It will almost certainly be necessary in this respect to warn British subjects that they should be careful to claim on ' waraqas ' ( documents ) not on account books which would not be accepted. On the morning of the 25th Sheikh Isa and some twenty Sheikhs come to write out the terms and sign them in my presence. Immediately a most difficult point arose. Sheikh Xse insisted that the peace should be between the Sultan on the one side and the • Imnm al Kuslimin ' on the other. This I refused for obvious reasons. In the first place it meant the open recognition by us of another ruler. In the second such a PeaceIS. \ peace would obviously \&gt;e resented If not disowned by the Sultar Bvory argument was U8ed t that thex*e were millions of muslems to whom their Irsum was not 1mm, that this was a political not a religious matter and so on. All to no avail till by chance 1 was able to quote to them the H&amp;dith of the peace made by th* prophet Mottomed ^ hie between him and the people of Ueeca. In the document he originally described him- -self * Eohomed rasul ullah H . The people of Mecca replied that this was absurd, if he was the prophet of God there was no question of making pcaco with him or not. The prophet saw the force of the argument and described himself plain ‘•Mohoncd bin Abdullah '• This direct appeal to their religious history carried the day, and the vsord Imam was omitted from the body of the document which simply re-id as conditions arranged between the Sultan 1 s government and lea bin !?alih on behalf of the Omfini tribes. 1 explained to them that I no objection to any on*; signing for or as an Imam al Muelimin. The document was written and the signatures affix -ed and in the evening the Sheikhs departed for the interior to obtain the signature of the Imam, and of the Sheikhs of the Beni Blyzup the Beni Ghafir and the Abriyin. Before their deoar tare 1 took a copy of the document signed and certified by Sheikh Tea anti took the precaution of warning him that the penal sakat trculd not be lifted till the document was return- -•d. The signature of the imam was obtained on the 28t September and the document returned to me on the 7th October signed by the remaining Sheikhs. The Imam also sent three letters addressed to hie three ’»alis in Semail, lluawnl and Kustaq, authorising them to hand over all the gardens to the agents of the ov;n- ~ers. In the rao&amp;ntirae 1 had obtained a similar docu- -ment from the Sultan 1 s government. Both parties are being given copies ofthe documents certified by me. The peace wr* proclaimed on the 8th and already dates and Omanis are pouring in* An enormous boom in trade ie anticipated, and the merchants are preparing to go into the interior. whether the peace will last cannot be jpretold, but it should last at least for some time. Both sides are tired and desire the resumption of normal intercourse and trade. Both sides hare got what they want. The uaanis may say they hare complete independence, the Sultan may say they only have dominion home rule. The Sultan is relieved of the expense and responsibility of ruling a turbulent and rebellious interior who hated him, while he has lost no revenue as the only revenue he ever got was the 5 percent zakat on the ooast. The Omanis manage their own affaixs under their theocratic govern ment which is possibly the government best suited to their peculiar conditions though such government would be impossible / '■ r '' in contact with the outer world. The strongest fact to the maintenance of peace is the strengthening of the Sultan s government. His finances are now in order and the state is now paying its way. There is a skeleton, quite sufficient, of an administration. $'ith a small levy corps to give him aotual and visible man power it is probable that the ^manls will think twicebefore they break their word. The position of the Political '‘gent in the future will be of some delicacy. He will inevitably be used as an intermediary over delicate questions and the greatest tact and patience will be necessary. With the minimum of inter* »f ere nee and an occasional hint much will be fcmamr however sm smoothed over. Copies of the agreements in Arabic with English translations are attached.IS TIB KAJ ! oy GO;) TICK C0MPA33X0SATX, TH ? M'I?RCI1TO. This ia wJint hna ue«n asroad upon in tho a«ttlem«nt batwean Ui« Governnant of oultm Sniyid Taimur bin ynlanl nnd Shaikh laa )v bin J&amp;lah All ti i on bolmlf of fche Omiuiis who ai^n their A name a here throu* 4 the mediation of Mr. Urinate. X.C.;;. Political Agent and ilia J ritannio i«jeaty f a Conaul, Muscat, ^ho la author- iaed by hi a Go'vemment In thie reapect to be a mediator between them. The eomiitiom stated a* follows. Jour of them concern the Government o* the Julian and four of ther&gt; concern the Omanis, ^hat concern the Omanis are these. Firstly. On all cor»uoditics brou^^it from Oman of all Vinds to Muscat, iiatruh, ;ur and all the coast towns nothing more should be taken t) in 5 percent. Secondly. For all the Omanis there should b* safety and free dom in all the coast towns. Thirdly. All restrictions on entry to and exit from uooat. Mat rail and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. The iultan's Government should not protect criminal who flee from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be returned to then if asked for and that the Sultan 9 s Government shourd not interfere in their internal affairs. Tile four which concern the Government of the dultan are stated as follows:- Firstly. All the tribes and dfoaikhs should remain in peace end amity with the Government of the Julian and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interfere in his Government. Secondly, ill travellers to Oman on their lawful business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellersshould be safe. Thirdly. All criminals and evil men who flee to them should be turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly. Tim claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should be heard and decided as is just according to the iiharah.' ' ^ V 19 ms HAWES 09 00 D WW COMPABSIONAyK, THiS XHRCIHUXk 2l5. 3HAL Thia la wliat haa baan agreed upon in tha aattleraant betwaan tha GoTemment of tha tiultan •Salyid Talmur bln Fniaal and tha Omania 9 by tha acting Vaalr 3alyld l^hammad bln Ahmad authorised by Kla — — Hi/^hnasa tha 3uXtan through tha Mdlatian of Mr # Wlngata t X # C # 3 #9 9oXltloal Agent and Hla Britannic Hajesty** Consul # Muscat t ~ho la authorlaad by hia OaTammant in this raapaot ta ba a madiator batwaaa tham. The eondltlona ara stated as follows. Four of them oonoam tha Oorammant of tha 3uXtan and four af them concern tha Omaaie* ’that concani tha C^aaaia ara thaaa* Firstly* On all eo roodltias brought from iAaan of all kinds to Muscat, Katrah, Mur and all tha ooaet towns nothing more idionld bo taken than 5 par cent* Secondly, For all tha Omanis there should ba safety and free dam in all tha coast towna. Thirdly* All raatriationa on entry to end exit from Muscat, Mat rah and all tha eoast town a should ba ramoTad* Fourthly* Tha Sultan 9 a OoTemment should not pro teat criminals who flea from tha justice af tha Omanis and that they may ba return* ad ta them if asked for and that tha Gultan*a OoTemmeat should not interfora In their internal affairs* The four which^tha Moramsaant of tha ihiltan ara stated as fallows:* Firstly* All tha tribes and Shaikhs should remain in pease and amity with tha (toTernment of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interforo in his Oeweranent* Socondly. All trarollsrs to Oman on their lawful business should bo free and there should bo no restrictions on trade and travellers should ba safe* Thirdly. All orlwinale and evil men who flee te them sheuld be turned out and should not bo protooted. Fourthly* The claims ef merchants and others against the Oman* •Is should bs heard and decided ac is Just according te the Sharah. Written at Muscat this fourteenth day ef Msharram one thousand Uir,« hurt dr, &lt;1 thirty nln, Hijwh carrMpondlng t® tw«mty-®i#»th -my mmThe letter numbered (1) is the agreement mode at Sib on September 25th, 1920, by Iso bin Salih on behalf of the Sheikhs of Oman in the presence of the Sultan*s representative Saiyid kuhammad bin Ahmad through the mediation of 2ir. Wingate the Political Agent. The document is signed by the Sheikhs representing the various tribes concerned. The letter numbered (2) is v/retten at —useat dated September 28th, 1920. It is the Sultan Saiyid Taimur’s confirmation of the terms agreed on between his representa tive Saiyid kuhammod bin AJunad at 3ib and the representative of Oman and O^eikhs. The letter bears 3a the said representative iyid Taimur’s signature and that Saij'id I'uhommad bin Ahmad andNo.ioa- S Of 1980• Brit,» ah RosidGncy and Consulato—Genor*al f Buahipe, 86th October 1920, From To Liout-Ool. A.P # Trovor, O.S.I., Offg* Political Rosidont in tJio Persian Gulf. Tho Hon'blo Mr. H.R.C.Dobbs, O.S.I., O.I.E ## Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* Foreign and Political Department* SIMLA* Sir* I have the honour to invito a reference to letter no .2052 dated 14th October 1920 from the Political Agont Muscat to my address (a copy of which was tranomittod direct to the Deputy .Secretary to tho Government of India in tho Foreign and Politic -al Department) reporting tho result of the negotiations carritf on through hie mediation between the Gbvemnont of tho Sultan of Muscat and the tribes of the interior of Oman. 2. As has boon already reported 'by telegram those nogotiati terminated successfully, and peace relations between the suit : uno Omanis were established on the basis of Hone rulo for tho latter. 3* Tho satisfactory conclusion of those negotiations, which have dragged on now for so long, reflects great credit on tho Political Agentj it is however unnecessary for ne to say much on tho subject now as this has boon recognized in the tele graphic correspondence and Mr. Wingate has received the con gratulations of His Excellency tho Viceroy on his conduct of the negotiations. 4. I neod only now romarfc that Mr. Wingate has submitted a very interesting historical summary of tho rebellion of the 0 tribes, and report on the negotiations. If the reportis printed i beg to request that I my be supplied with 6 copies. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Sd/-A.P*Trevor, Liout-Ool# Political Resident in the PorsianOuli NO. SoJ-S. The Resi Busnire, '■5th October 1020. Co^y forwarded to the Political Agent huecat for information. By order, Lieut- Socond Assistant to the Political nesiaent in the Persian Gulf‘Ltt-zj Confidential British Consulate and Political Agency Muscat 9th March 1921» To The Officer Commanding Troops Muscat. Memorandum. A slight misunderstanding has arisen over the question of permitting the entry and exit of Arabs through the wire by Hui village, xxIckx and I venture therefore to explain the present political situation* Previous to October 1920 Arabs were not permitted to pass through the picket line, which guards tne only road to the interior from Muttrah, without passes, and were always disarmed unless theywere in possession of permits. This was owing to the nostility of the tribes of interior Oman who were in open rebellion against the Sultan. It was to protect the latter in accordance with our engagements that our troops were stationed at Baltwal-Falaj. At the end of September a meeting took place at Sib between the Political Agent and the sheikhs of the Oman tribes at which terms of peace were arranged between the rebel tribes and the Sultan's government through the former's mediation. This peace cane into force on the gth October* One of the conditions of thir peace was bne removal of all the old restrictions on entry into and exit from the towns of Muscat and Muttrah. Captain Pearson who was present at the meeting immediately the peace came into force issued orders that Arabs were not to be stopped passing along the road, that passes were no longer necessary and that the wire was to be ^ept open permanently. It is possible that these orders were only verbal, but it is nevertheless a fact that movement by Arabs along the read by day or night was entirely free and unrestrict -ed from that date. This needless to say gave tne greatest satisfaction to the OmanisA few lays ago, apparently through no record being (3^ available of the change in the situation outlined above, the ilv/aye prone to suspect some treachery. I communicated with you by telephone on the subject, and the Omanis I think now understand tnat the matter was due to a simple misunderstanding The sit lation may be briefly summaraised as the existence of a signe peace between the tribes and the -.aids and attacks by the tribes on Muttrah are no longer to be fear d, in lacts the tribes have guaranteed not to do this. Militarily the only defences rkk£k and p ©caution needed at Bait-al-Palaj are those for the protection of the camp, not as before for the protection of the towns. Should the tribes prove treacherous and go back on their word we shall get plenty of warning to enable you to take such precautions as you may consider necessary. Political Agent, MuscatTV t cd 23 Jai me! j t 1337 ^ 2l!5t Frora To Mullah bl B hid -H ' ; T^-e Politic:! Agent Pc H.B.II*? Consul, TTusc?^, After Cornpli^ents, I rrceiT^d your honour d Tetter .-rid j heard that you v^nt to see me in connection rith the visit of the n-ntioned Shaikhs, it i -.n honour ard favour to me for \hich I thr-nk you. Be- 11 ^ you 3re worthy of the worldly r&lt; forus and save th». bloodshed of the people and their honour. '’Tv peep] ? heDieve these things nc\ we know your habits. The for n-r Consul • -ho was Colonel called ie and I v; e nt to the Tnan and the Cheikhs and the latter net the Consul at Tib but no agreement was made at th-t tine, hut if Cod please some thing i i j 1 co. i out thitin* . If you ask th biy nan of Ona.n you would not find any body but th -y praise Bu-S&amp;eedis for th--y 're habituated to honour and respect them, 'hey served th-n voluntarily and with love, but they did not care thuir sub- — .jc.cts and did not punish the criiiinale which is thr: most important thing in the world. Te v/ish a nan nav corn out in this tribe who v ill ohseve religion for I see th.» Cnanis are desirous of their company and tc- h&lt;.r r r th *ir words. And you said that you ^ant to discuss th, jiatters of Oman, but * t do not know vhat th - r are. TT ad -o 1 expla-'ned to us son- of them so tha t we would inform the Omanis and shcu the* their betterment • Kindly mention us e f then. ITow I an weak • nd have nothing to ride or oth r- -wise T would have reached Muscat. Put if you con'* to Tib or Barka I can oona and see you. Th&gt; ; ns\-’ar m^y b sent socr -» f®r th id ' p iaara are ne ©ne th .If they will i 3 te th newer will b&lt;= r ceived after ? long tiaeBat»d 23rd Janadj x 1337, 21st Frsa Ts Abdallah bin HasHid Al-HasHal A- L Tht pslitioal Agsnt &amp; H # B.M«s Csnsul, Muscat. After CsapliM«nts # I reotivsd ysur bsnsured lettsr and I hsard that yau want t# see ms in csnasetisn with the Tisit sf the aentisnsd Sheikhs, it ie an hsnsur and favour ts ms fsr which I thank you. Really ysu are werthy sf the worldly reforms and save the bloodshed sf the people and their honour. The people bellere these things and we knew your habits. The feraer Consul who was Colonel called as and I wont to the laaa and the Sheikhs and the latter net the Consul at Sib but no agreeMent was made at that time. But if God please sene thing will como out this tiMe. If you ask th* big non of Oman you would net find any body but they praise Bu-Saeodis for they are habituated to honour and respect then. They served them voluntarily and with love, but they did net care their sub- -jects and did not punish the criMimils which is the most important thing in the world, -fo wish a man May como out in this tribe who will obsevo religion for I see the 0«anis are desirous of their company and to hoar their words. And ysu said that you want to discuss the Matters of Oman, but we do net knew what they are. Had you explained to us seme of them so that we would inform the Omanis and shei them their betterment • Kindly Mention us seme of them. Hew I am weak and have nothing to ride or ether- -wise I would have reached Muscat. But if you come to Sib or Barka I can come and seo you. THo answer May be sent seen 2 for the Sheikhs and Inan are near to one another . If they will separate the answer will be received after a long tine.Dat«* 23r* X&lt; 1337, 21 fit Fr«a Abdullah bln itasbid Al-»I!a*Hai Tb« Ag«nt ft H.B.Jl's :«n»ul # uucaji. After Cempliaents, J received year heneured letter and I heard that yeu want to sc* a* in conneotlftn with the viait ftf the Mentioned iheikhs. It I** an Heneur and favour to ae fer which I thank eu« Really yeu are werthy ef the werldly refeme and save the bleedehed ef the people and their heneur. ''he peeple believe theee things and we knew year habits. The femer Consul whe was Celonel called me and 1 went te the laaa and the Sheikhs and the latter net the ( ensul at Sib but ne agreement was made at that time. ' ut if God please seme thing will come eut this time. If yeu ask th« big men ef ( man yeu would not find any body but they praise Bu*Saeedis fer they are habituated te heneur and respect them, 'hey served them veluntarily and with leve, but they did net care their sub- -Jects and did net punish the criminals which is the meet important thing in the world. Te wish a man may come eut in this tribe who will ebseve religion fer I see the tmanis are | desirous ef their company and te hear their words. And yeu said that yeu want te discuss the matters ef Cman # but. ho do net knew what they are. Had yeu explained te us some ef them so that we would inform the Omanis and ehei them their betterment • findly mention us seme ef them. ftew X am weak and have nothing to ride or ether •wise I would have reached Muscat, hut if yeu cone t# Liib or Barka I can come and see ywu. ’'he answer may be sent soon \ for the ''heikhs and Imam aro near te ane another • If they will separate the answer will be received after a long time.&lt;33rd Jtiu^d 1 x 1337&gt; Slat rr«Bi T# Ab^allHh bin Rashid ■b» r®li tio»i Agent 4 (*en«tU. 9 ^unuaji* After Compliments^ I received year hensured letter end 3 beuril thttt y»u w«iRt te see me in aenneotien ^itb the visit ef the Mentioned OHeikhe* It i* an Heneur awl favour to me for v/hich 3 thank you# Heally you are verthy ef the worldly refeme and save the bleed shed ef the people end their heneur* ''he peeple believe theee things and we knew year Uubite. 'he fomer Censul whe was Cel end called me and I went te the leftaja and the f'heikhe and the latter net the • onsul at nib but it# agreement wne made at that time* Tut if Ood pleaee seme thing will come eut this time# If yeu aek th&lt;# big men ef (man you weuld net find any body but they praise Bu-naecdis for they are habituated te honour and reopect then* ''hey served them voluntarily and with love* but they did net care their sub- -jecte and did net punish the criminals which is the meet important thing in t.he world# To wish a msin may oeme eut in this tribe who will obseve religion for X see the i&amp;iimls are deelreus ef their company and te hear their wards# And yeu said that yeu want t« discuss th&lt;* matters ef &lt; man# but ve do net knew what they are# Mad yeu explained te ue some of them ee that we would inform the (manls and ehev thorn their betterment • Mndly mwntlen ue same of them# ftew I am weak and have nothing to ride or «th*:r- -wise 1 weuld Have reached Muscat# but if you cone to bib or Barka I can corns and see you# ''he answer may b* sent aeon for the Sheikhs and la^ua are near te one smother # Jf t)i«y will separate th* anewor will be received after a long time#29-0 •f 1919* Political Agency and C*nsulate 9 Unseat* The 5th llarch 1919* Trea Majer L.B.H.Hawerth* I.A., Pelitieal Agent and H,B.M*s Censul, ! 4 usoat» Ts The Acting Pelitieal Kesident 9 Baghdad * Sir 9 With reference te ay accenpanying despatch Ne* 27-C dated the 5th Haroh 1919 1 ferward herewith a adpy ef letter which I have addressed te the Owan ohiefs with a view te heliing a meeting with then* I had sene tine age ebtained a grant ef meney fren the Deputy pelitieal resident fer the purpese and the attached letter was written btfere yeu intervened in the Onan questien I was nwaiting the arrival ef the neseenger Sheikh Hamad bin Said el Falaiti fer its despatch* I was ferwarding yeu a espy sf this letter fer ysur appreval befere I sent it but I received a letter fren the qazi whs is accsxapanying El Falaiti requesting ne ts send it immediately as the chiefs sf Onan are new all tegether and saying there weuld be censiderable delay if they separat ed* As the principle ef helding a Meeting with the Oman chiefs is accepted 1 have accordingly despatched the letter* It is highly probable that these chiefs have at xxi present senawhat inflated spiniens sf their strength and it was therefsre necessary ts shew them the real position in writing the letter* As yeu are aware with Arabs a shew ef kindness is apt te be received as weakness and ss ts defsat the ebjeet intended* t — ~i'$Pr by th*!* fai %4 i» nnw in h&lt;in 4 « »f th« l.inpf; • f H«jaa. In Y«»««n Pa«hu Hhh surr&lt;iiMi«r«4 and in new a prisoner in our htmdo.Atid the Hi truth of all this will undoubtedly roach you from ether aeurcee very eeon and the tint •f the il*j will shew it to theee who »my doubt* 1 an especially writing to t^ll you that it is our intention to aeoiet in the eat^bliahaent ef the Arab Govemaeut in all Arab places to govern accordiiu; te their own oustone. ;sw that they are freed fre» the tyranny ef the Turk there i^ every hope that they wilJ be able to develop on good Arab lines* bow th^t ws huve tine aim spportuni ts attend to &lt; sum it is neoeesary thtit 1 shsuld attempt ts explain to you sur poHltiu; tswarde usmn so that you wi)l be able to underntand our point of vlow. Muecut ie one of the ports used by our ships on the way to yuahiro and Basra, It is essential for the purposes sf the t d sf the world that ports thoui’ be in a bon- •dition of safety aid pekoe. Jf Vs frr^/ttrn- •m«nt ef the country ir v * *t and fi^htin^ and then the pert &gt; u.omes unsafe there is ns i* r shijia x^icVi are puesing and no an 1 safety k . th^ curd* frow them if it is lan : i is in danger* in liman there we always fi^htina and trouble eepexinlly when one Imam or«• being Atteclccd by at*** b4k« ether oleiment te the threat* In these cir* curetancee ke yeu ere eeare et «*ere ferced in 1695 te make &amp; declaratlen te all the Shelkhe ef Oman that ee weulc auppert in the perte the Sultan vhe wee in peeer and with ehem ee had rrade allia-jce and in this way we have eup- perted Sultans 'lurki, iairul and Taimur* have It is fer this reasen that ^wished te meet yeu te discuss with yeu what can be dene te impreve mutters, fer in such a natter it is enly by duscuesien that either side can understand the ether and can see if it ie pessible te meet each ethers vie**. It has never been kr;e«n that *e sheuld injure any eti* unjustly but hew can «e act ether than «e have acted if yeu de net ceme te a diecuseien with us ts er shew any desire fer friendly in- terceurse. »e have rid wish te ferce upen peeple a gevernment which ie bad and wbt which they de net desire er which ie agsiKist their custeois* And it ie at this time that 1 hear ef seme talk ef a desire te t attack Bur* X de net knew if this is true but GedA forbid that it should be for this . j would bring the Omanie into conflict with us once more and for two years 1 have been endeavouring to make this impossible and 1 write to you to say do not do this thing if it has arisen in the minds of any of you that it should be done for this will cause loss to you and we do not wish to harm you. On the contrary for if we wished we could send aeroplanes which suuu would destroy your towns and your forts and you surely do not think that you could fight against us. We have 500000 men in Iraq whom we no longer require there and afew thousand of these would be sufficient to take the whole of Oman if we wished to do. Saiyyid Taimur unlike you has always attempted to be on friendly terms with us and you will see that the ruler who has the sea ports will always have the power to put taxes upon the goods coming from the interior and going to the in terior and you will be unable to do any thing. and we have control of the sea if you desire to be a enmity with ue why should we allow rice and wheat to be sold to you or clothing and why should we allow you to sell your datos and all your trade ie with eur countries. But if you are friendly with us and ±m discuss the matters then we can assist yeu as we are new assisting Sayyid 1mm Taimur if y.u go against us then the consequences are en yeur head and net en cure as i havesaid before and htw can we be friei with these wh# will net be friends with us • 1 would ask that yeu weuld explain this te yeur brether the Imam and let him see that the present cenditien can* net ge en fer ewer and that cemmunicatien with us cannet de yeu any harm but geed while refusal te communicate with us makes it impossible for ue te help yeu and therefore must result in harm te yeu and 1 have written te Sheikh Hamyar also like this* Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.&amp;’s Consul,1'uscat•Confidential No. 205:1, dated the 14th October 1920. Fr&lt; m—It. E. L. Wingatr, Esq., I.C.S., Political Agent and Elis Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, To-—The Deputy Political Resident, Bushire. (Copy to the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla.) I have the honour to forward a report on the negotiations carried on through my mediation as the representative of the British Government between the Government of Bis Highness the Sultan of Muscat and' the tribes of interior Oman which terminated in the re-establishment of peaceful relations on the 8 th Cotober 1920. In order to make the situation quite clear I have found it necessary to summarise very briefly the history and caus s of the late rising, and to give in some detail the sequence of events from October 1919 till the conclusion of the negotiations. I wish to draw the attention of Government to the admirable arrange ments made by Captain Pearson, commanding the detachment of the l-117th Mahratta* at Muscat for my fescort and for t he tents, etc., for the reception of the Oman Sheikhs. Finally T wish to bring to the notice of Government the excellent work performed by the Consular Dragoman, Ehtisham-ud-Doulah Khan. The negotiations in question have been going on for a year, and have entailed arduous work and continual watchfulness. During this period he has been indefatigable in obtaining information, and has more than once been entrusted by me with work needing the most delicate handling. At the meeting itself lie also did excellent work. 1. Brief survey of causes and history of the rebellion of the On.an tribes under the leadership of their elected Imam Sheikh Salim bin Rashid-al-Kharusi till 1915. A perusal of any history official or otherwise of Muscat and Oman will show for several hundred years examples of revolution, anarchy and murder almost unparalleled even in Arabian history. Since the expulsion of the Portuguese however there has been, except during the periods of Persian or Wahabi domination, a ruler combining both spiritual and tempral autho ity, and acknowledged nominally by all the tribes. According to the Ibadhi sect of Islam such an Imam-al-Muslimin must be elected by the people, and there is no right of heredity, though often the son of the dead Im im was accepted as Imam. x \ With the accession to the Imamate of Ahmed Albu Saidi, the founder of the present dynasty, the ‘system seems to have changed and the rulers of Muscat and Oman succeeded as a dynasly without the formality of election asImam. This definite departure occurred when Sultan bin Ahmed usurped the power from his brother Said bin Ahmed who had been elected Imam. r ihe latter retained the title of Imam till his death, but no temporal power. The rule of Sultan and of his son Said which lasted from about 1&lt;90 till 1856 marked the growth of sea power, foreign conquests, the most important of which was Zanzibar, and the removal of the capital from Kustaq in the interior to Muscat on the coast, and foreign treaties and inter!erenc a , almost entirely British, The removal of t 'e capital to the coast cut off from the in'erior has been stated by some as the beginning of the loss of hold by the Sultans over the interior, and as sueh as an impolitic move. r lhis is however open to question. It is more probable chat the Sultan knew they could hope better to control with outside power and this outside power they obtained from their sea power and their foreign possessions. It is a fact however that from the deaUi of Saiyid Said the power of tne Sultans over the interior became more nominal than ever. Attacks could only be warded off by brib iry, no revenue was obtained, travel* was dangerous and there were several attempts by the Omani tribes to set up Imams of their own. An attempt had actually been made in 1819. In 1868 Azzan bin Qais an elected Imam actually ruled in Muscat, and though latter ejected, many similar attempts were made during the reign of Turki and the earlier years of the reign of Eaisal to depose the Sultan, who may have said to ha^e been saaed only by our support. * Finally in 1913, after an elaborate conspiracy of several years fostered by the famous blind Ibadlii mullah Sheikh Abdullah bin llumaid as SaLmi, tie Oman tribes rose in a body elected Salim bin llavhid-al-J£liarusi as their Imam and by 191 i had obtained complete control of all v)man proper where toey organised a Government. It will thus be seen that for more than 60 years there has been active opposition to the ruling 1 ouse by the Oman trioes. The causes of this opposi tion may be briefly summarised a* follows:— (1) According to the Ibadhi religion their ruler must be elected. The Sultans who had not undergone this v formality were , ' therefore userpers. ( 2 ) The personal character of the Sal tins themselves *—deteriorated at an alarming rate, and the repeated assertion of the Omani tribes that they were unlit to rule does not lack justinoation. (3) The character of the Sultans' rule .—This was corrupt to a degree, and the element of personal control and touch by the ruler himstl which with the Arab will palliate even the worst forms of corrup tion, was completely absent. •( 4 ) Foreign interference.—TUs appeared in the eyes of the fanatical anil ignorant Omanis to be directed against their most cherished rights such as the importation of arms and slaves. In these the Sultan acquiesced without consulting his subjects accepting sums of money for his acquiescence, not one penny of which money the Omanis ever saw. At the same time our policy in Zanzibar lost nothing in the telling. Several of the reasons why the Sultans were unable to cope with the rebel lion are contained in these. But to them may be added three more. The loss of Zanzibar and its revenues, the loss of sea power owing to the ictrouuction ot steam, and finally and most important of all the effects of British influence. When considering our p n licv in Muscat and Oman this last point must never be lost sight of. A brief perusal of the treaties and engagements with the rulers of Muscat will show that our influence has bf^n entirely self- interested, has p dd no regard to the peculiar political and social conditions o the country and its rulers, and by bribing effete Sultans to enforce unpa a a, e measures which benefitted none but ourselves, and permitting them to misiu.c C11FPD /A woru* in*'* &gt;*, „rf„:. s which irnut navo onuu^.j upoa interference m exiemvi which was thrown mto the sea or internal peace and no palliative exccp J worse bv those into whose hands we put it. , • ,, . ...... were reduced to the absurd position of support^ byarm.VSe ttl,de ^°”£ l y hS'SttwretiX ^KSSrSadayilitwerenotforus. . rp|,„ immediate causes of the 1913 rebellion were an outbreak of religion, ilie unmrcu n^ ca . e of importation oi arms, fanaticism coinciding with the smpp i^e 01 mo j 2. Events from Colonel Benn's first meeting with the Oman Chiefs in 1015 till Major Haworth’s meeting with the same in &amp; •pte.nb.n ■ • In January 1915 the Imam accompanied by Sheikh Isa bin S :lib-al-H a rithi and many Oman Sheikhs attacked in force our defences at Bait-al-Eala] guard- Mattrah The attack was beaten off with serious loss to the Omanis sho ea°m their lesson there cnee and for all. The Imam however remained u indisputable possession of the interior and a constant menace to the coast towns which he would probably have taken had it not been for the certainty that he would be driven out in a few days with the advent of a British m m-of-war. In May Lieutenant-Colonel Ber.n, the Political Agent, sent a circular let t , to the Oman Sheikhs asking for a conference in which peace &gt;1 ight dj a iangel between the Sultan anil the Imam. This did not meet with a very warm res ponse in the interior, but after considerable correspondence a raeotingi^H finally arranged and took place at Sib on the 15th September 1-15 between rinl-'anol Rrmn rntrl StliPllfll CS the renresontativa of the Imam’s party. This meeting was entirely abortive, in tno Sultans mind was tLep^w*.. mount idea that he would eventually recover his authority m the interior, in the minds of the representatives of the Imam their unassailable position as conquerors and their r oral position as Ibadhis obeying thd dictates of religion. The two most important points demanded by th 9 Sultan were the return of the£&gt;email forts and the recognition of his temporal supremacy in Oman. Those were categorically, refused by the Omanis who demanded that the Sultan should reform his government according to then idea*, that they should be given subsidies, arms and so on. No reconciliation was possible and the negotiations were broken off. / i From this date till 1318 no further steps were taken towards a settlena^n 1 * The Imam backed up by the two great Chiefs Sheikh Isa bin Salih-al-HarhE head of the Hinawi confederation and Sheikh Hnmiyar bin Nasir-al-Nabnad, head of the Ghafiri confideratiorr consolidated ids power in the interior. On the # other hand the Sultan’s Government sank from bad to worse, because involved ' in hopeless debt and reached an unparalleled degree of ineptitude. In March 1918 during the absence 2 the Sultan four relations of Sheikh Isa s came down into Muscat and were seized by Saiyid Nadir who was acting for the Sultan and imprisoned. This resulted in letters from Sheikh Isa to tltf Sultan and the Political Agent asking for their release. The Sultan in return insisted on the ret urn ^ of the valuable gardens seized by the Omanis, and th 0 * Po itioal Agent declined to interfere except on these lines and the matter was dropped. , the meantime the Political Agent M ijor Haworth had realised the , imperature necessity of taking drastic measures to preserve the Sultan s bovem* ment on the coast from complete financial and actual collapse, .and a loan ta h' 1 * ^ Sultan s deb;s and arrangements to obtain the services of an exper 1 * enced Customs official were made. . Ourictoric-s in the great war now made the occasion a suitable one f nl j «'ignm approachirg the Omanis with a view to a settlement and the PoliticalAgent Major Haworth addressed a very strong letter to the leaders in March ]919.^ Considerable correspondence resulted and finally Sheikh Isa met the 1 ohtical Agent at Sib on the 15th September 1919. By this time it had been realised, and the realisation was more than confirmed at the meeting, that the recognition of the Sultan in the interior was as impossible as that he should reconquer Oman bv force. His own territory was on its last legs. He only stood at all with our support. The best means was therefore the recognition of the status quo and the terms discussed and which it seemed might event ually form the basis of an agreement were that the Sub an— ( 1 ) should remove all restrictions on entry fothc town of the coast. ( 2 ) reduce the zakat on goods coming from the coist towns to the interior to 5 per cent. (3) return fugitive from justice. (4) release the four Omani prisoners. And t! the Omanis—* (1) should guarantee not to attack the Sultan's territory or interfere in Ids Government. ( 2 ) should guarantee the safety of travellers and freedom of trade. (3) should hear and decide cases against Omanis. (4) should return fugitives from justice. (5) should return the valuable gardens belonging to two of the most important of the Sultan’s subjects seized oy the Omanis. 3 Events from October 1919 to October 1920 including the final settle- ment. —The situation therefore on my arrival in October was — (1) The reform of the administration of the territory controlled by the Sultan had to be taken in Land. (2) An agreement was to be arranged if possible through the mediation of the Political Agent between the Imam’s party and the Sultan. It was at once clear that these two matters were closely bound tog.-tber. In the first place the strengthening of the Sultan's administration would inevitably result in a decrease in the comparative power of the Omanis In the second place an agreement and the establishment of peace would enable the reform of the administration to be proceeded with with more rapidity. The reform of tho administration was therefore tackled with vigour, and Sheikh Said bin Nasir-al-Kindi a prominent mullah of the Ibadhi sect resident in the territories of the Sultan, and greatly respected in Oman, was sent by me to Nizw T a, the seat of the Imam, to endeavour to obtain ratification of the terms discussed at Sib. Though at the commencement of Sheikh Said's mission circumstances seemed favourable, it very soon became evident that the influence of the &lt;c Mutawwa ” or fanatical party w r ould be strongly against the return of the gardens, which were mostly in their hands and from which the mullahs derived a lucrative income. The leader of the opposition party was .Nasir bin Rashid- al-Kharusi, the brother of the Imam and his Wali in liustaq. The mission was more than once on the point o c success, but finally after 4 months of negotiations and intrigue the Imam in February definitely refused to Sheikh Said and Sheikh Isa to ratify the terms. The possibility of this unfavourable result had been foreseen for some time, and a definite plan of action prepared to meet the emergency. The Omanis bad been given a fair field and plenty of favour. They had been moved with39 ,i hnd rcfus^ peace owm^ ^ ignorance and reli»j^u» lioneyei words, ^ey . ^ ^ ow i n g to the lukewarmness of the chief prejudice it is tru,p&gt;s i sa , but actually because the Omanis thou.ht tha we were n t backing the Su'tan with any degree of enthusiasm and that therefore they could go as far asthey liked wrth rmpumty. H The Omanis were therefore to be shown that our support of the Saltan was areaUty, and not only that but that the Sultan was capable o retaliatin, very^ffeclively on the Omanis by taring their produce heavily when it came down to the coast for export. Reliable information from the interior showed that owin ? to the Ion® 8 t 0 T 3 T)aee of the import of arms and amm mition the Omanis had largely lost their offensive pow^r. and were by no means enthusiastic for the Imam whose puritanical fanaticism was making ii'e intolerable, and the exactions of whose The mommt was therefoi*e opportune for changing from a weak defensive to a vigorous offensive. It was ponrei out that if certain steps were taken which involved no use of force by us, it was extremely probable that the Oroanis would see reason. Even if they*did not do so for some time it would not matter as affairs would eventually automatically at just themselves with the inoreasa of the Sultan's power following on the reform of his administration. The following events therefore took place on the refusal of the Imam to ratify (1) The negotiations were broken off by me in the most insulting fashion. (2) A British advis 3 r to the Sultan appeared. (3) The Sultan accompanied by me went on an official visit to His Excellency the Viceroy in India leaving the British adviser in change of the State. ( 4 ) A British warship, in pursuance of our enagements to support the authority of the Sultan on the coast, proceeded to Masaiab anl Sur where the authority of the Sultan had been defied andinfiictd punishment at the former place with good results. The position of the Imam was at the same moment greatly weakened the sudden death of Sheikh Ha uiyar bin Nasir-al Nabhani, the most powerful chieftain and his staunchest supporter, whose successor was an inexperienced boy of 11 . These events created consternation in Oman only to be increased on m? return from India by the publication of notices by the Sultan’s Government imposing a penal zakat of 23 per cent on all dates and 50 per cent on poIneg^ , a■ nates brought by the Omanis to the coast towns, instead of the customary 3 per cent. jgss Tbie pro Tarnations announcing the imp osition of this penal tax were ^- care.u ly wo ded, making it perfectly clear even to the Omanis that the taxw 5 imp sed as a punishment owing to their refusal to give up the looted property and to come to terms. . . Coincident with the publication of these notices (in May) a very significant . incident occurred, ^asir bin liashid-al-Kharusi who had been suffering coo* siderablo trouble from Ahmed bin Ibrahim, the ruler of Hazm just within the ^ Sahan s HTritory, laid siege to Hazm. A small expedition was organised yj the Sultan s Government and Nasir bin Rashid was compelled to retreat . every appearance of ignominy, most of his men deserting him, and might nave lost hustaq. Such an incident would haye been unthinkable six montW previously. Irom this moment events moved rapidly—it may almost be said accords o p an. Sheikh after Sheikh approached the Imam pointing out that 1 ^ weie powerless to resist the penal tax which seemed to be imposed sunpvowirg to the greed of his brother, and praying him to return the gardens and come to terms. The Imam dominated by his brother proved obdurate and dis content grew. Finally Sheikh Isa, whose last letter I had torn up and refused to answer, addressed me himself on 2dth June. I seized the opportunity to write a strong and lengthy reply emphasising that the British Government was entirely behind the Sultan in this matter, and that f w r ould neither meet him nor discuss any thing with him till the looted gardens had been first returned. I took the precaution of allowing the contents of this letter to leak out before it was sent. There is little doubt that this letter dispelled any remaining doubts that the Omanis may have had. On 21 st July the Imam Sheikh Salim bin Hashid-al Kharusi was murdered at Khadra. Ihe immediate cause of his murder w r as stated to have been an insult to one of his guard. The real reason of his death, which was confirmed from many sources, was that the tribes were practically in open revolt against his rule and that of his brother, which was a combination of utter religious bigotry combined with shameless selfishness and oppression and a complete disregard of politics or government, ail of which in addition to their inherent disadvantages were res ilting in all sorts of trying restrictions from the Sultan’s Government, which they were powerless to resist, culminating in the penal zakat. Oman was now without a leader and the greatest confusion prevailed. The Walls of the late Imam were driven out immediately by the infuriated tribes men and had to flee for their lives Many tribes sent tentative offers of alle giance to the Sultan’s Government. Sheikh Isa began to collect men in » Sharkiyah, and ou the other side the Sultan’s Government made a determined effort to regain their hold over Oman. The situation w^as now extremely interesting, and provided the British Government could preserve an attitude of strict neutrality, one of two results both equally favourable to a satisfactory settlement would, be bound to occur. Either the Sultan’s Government would regain their hold over the interior—this would settle affairs for the moment, though it would inevitably lead the Sullan into difficulties later—or the Oman tribes would retain their c ohesion against the Sultan in which latter case their leader could only hope to consolidate his posi tion satisfactoiily by coming to an agreement removing immediately the penal zakat. It was peculiarly fortunate that at this critical moment the British adviser to the Sultan was on leave in India It was therefore possible for the Sultan’s Government in entirely Arab hands to act without suspicion being rais- d that we were behind them. I kept conspicuously aloof, well knowing that the Omanis, if they did not come into the Sultan, would approach me to mediate. Semail was the objective of both parties, but Sheikh Isa who had meantime secured the election of his father-in-law Mokorued bin Abdullah-al-Khalili, chief of the powerful Beni Huwaha tribe as the new Imam, succee led in reaching Semail 2T hours before the Sultm’s men and the tribes naturally followed him. He immediately addressed himself to me through Sheikh Said bin Nasir al- Eindi asking for an agreement. I replied that till the gardens were returned I woiild not meet him, but that when that had been done I would mediate. To show more strongly my complete indifference I stated that I was going to India for a month, and with the pormissi n of Government went. Even then Isa’s path 'was by no means smooth. The new Imam being a Hinawi and the father in 1 iw of Isa raised the suspicions of the Ghafiris. Ahmed bin Ibrahim on behalf of the Sultan took Rustnq and would have held it but for the sudden desertion of the Beni Ghafir tribe to the new Imam. Immediately the Rusfaq situation had resolved, itself in Isa’s favour he acted with great policy, as indeed he was compelled to by the inseeuiity of his C11FPD101 /Jnnrttdpd fcr its consoHdatio: i on me romonl of the penal zaW. Indian) that he had done so, and ashed fo. a meeting . Tt .„ 0 fin „ii v arranged and took plane at Sib from the 23rd to 26th This was fina u . ortUv of note that on this occasion, as a mark of th e September 19-0. ,^1 situation and in the attitude of the tnb« complete clianse n the pohuca^t ^ ]etter after , etter asking for a ^ andtSJ waited for me 20 days at Khoz, while on previous occasions exactlj the reverse had been the case. n 9l s t Captain Thomson of the 1-llTth Mahrattas proceeded withai On the 1 ^ g., ^ na ^ve sailing boat, to the house of th tv ” 1 ?\lut“ah at the edge of the gardens which had been fixed as rendezvous, b&gt; for the Entertainment of the Sheikhs. , ...... . faw of mv arrival from India on the - 2 nd, accompanied SpS afion, 11.0.,ard ih. Consular dragoman, I ombarkod ,na naira ,i iiJ vessel for Sib, arriving there the afternoon of the - rd. -f message to sent Immediately to Sheikt. Isa who was at Khoz only 2 hours distance. Earlv on the morning of the 24th Sheikh Isa accompanied hy over (went; Oman Sheikhs and three hundred camelmen arrived at the rendezvous. ATta they had dismounted and entered the tents I paid the customary visit on then as their host remaining about 10 minutes. The first meeting took place an hour later and lasted some t '0 hours. The Quezon preyed bv me Tvas the authorisation of Sheikh I&gt;a. It will beieraeiE- hered in this connection that on the occasion of the last meeting he was not fullj authorised. Finally, he having stated, and his word baying been confirmed by other Sheikhs, that*he was lully authorised by the Imam, it was agreed that the terms if arranged ^rould be signed by him and the Sheikhs present in my presence, and that they would then take the document away and obtain the signature of the Imam and of any other Sheikhs w hom I -might name. After the middy meal a further Ions: meeting was held to discuss the actual terms. There were’present at this meeiing only Sheikh Isa, Said Masir-al* Kirdi, the Consular dragoman and myself. Twelve extravagant terms veK put forward by the Omanis:— ( 1 ) That the independence of Oman should he recognised. (2) That the z.ikat should be reduce! to 5 per cenr* (3) That the Omanis should be free and safe in the Sultan’s territory. (4) That the Brhish Government should not help the r enemies suimbly meaning the Sultan). That- rsatVnnoe cIvrmM r'. ((5) That passports should not be needed f&gt; r them. (7) That they should be allowed to purchase cartridges. ( 8 ) That the Sultan should subsidise them/ (9; That all documents such as passports, etc., from the I mam! should countersigned hy the Political Agent and not by the Sultan. ( 10 ) That Rashid bin Tdzaiz should not be allowed iu Oman. (11) That Sheikh Said bin Nasir-al-Kindi should be guaranteed safe ? 111 the Sultan’s torritorv. m (12) That the Sultan should reti «rn fugitives from their justice. As against this they proposed to promise *• — (1) Not to attack the Sultan’s territory or to interfere in his Govern®®® (!) To allow freedom of trade and travel in Oman.w. the terms they proposed to exact from the Saltan all except (2) and (3) and (12) were clearly absurd. By a mixture of argument, cajolery and threats and the final statement that if they were not prepared to accept the terms originally agreed upon I would leave at once, they finally agreed to ask ing only (2), 3) and (l*) from the Sultan. Terms (10) and (11) were put in by Sheikh Said bin Nasir al Kindi only owing to personal enmity and were soon disposed of. (!) was pointed out as being absurd—if we were mediating in an agreement they could rely on our not hacking the other s ; de unless they flagrantly broke it. (5) was pointed out as a sine qua non. ( 6 ) and (9) were pointed as equivalent to asking for exemptions of formalities which had to be undergone by the whole world, and as implying no disgrace but which even British citizens had to put up with in other countries. (/) was pointed out as impossible owing to international agreement and it was added that in any case permission to import could not be given till we were sure by experience of their good intention^. ( 1 ) was categorically refused and it was explained that as they had got practical independence what more did they want. (8) Avas laughed at. 'Finally the following terms were arranged. • The Sultan’s Government would:— (1) Reduce the zakat on all goods coming into the coast towns to 5 per cent. (2) Guarantee safety and freedom for Omanis in the coast towns.^ (3) Remove all [restrictions on the entry of Omanis into Muscat and Muttrah. (4) Return fugitives from their justice and'not interfere in their internal affairs. (Note.— The word here used was “ dakhiliy. t-a-hum,” which is very im portant as it means no more than it says, their internal affairs, and the Sultan cannot argue should he choose to do so that there is any derogation of his supreme authority. On the other hand the Omanis are at liberty to regard it as complete independence. Both sides are therefore satisfied.) The Omanis would — (1) R-emain in peace with the Sultan, not attack the coast and not interfere with his Government. (2) Permit freedom of trade and travel in Oman and guarantee the safety of travellers. (3) Would return and not protect fugitives from the Sultan’s justice. ( 4 ) Would hear the claims of traders and others against Omanis accord ing to Shaia. It is amusing to note that the terms asked from the Sultan w r as originally only three, (2) and (3) being combined. When the Omanis found that they had to concede four terms to the Sultan they were somewhat upset, but the situation was saved by splitting the second term into two. # As regards the fourth term conceded by the Omanis, hearing by the Shara was inevitable as they have no other courts. It wbll almost certainly be necessary in this respect io warn British subjects that they should be careful to claim on “ waraqas” (documents) not on account books which would not he accepted. On the morning of the 25th Sheikh Isa and some twenty Sheikhs came to write out the terms and sign them in my presence. Immediately a most difficult point arose. Sheikh Isa insisted that the peace should be between the Sultan on the one side and the “ Imam-al-Muslim ** on the other. This I refused for obvious reasons. In the first place it meant the open recognition by us of another ruler. In the second such a peace would obviously beJL V/*. # resent-d if not disowned by the Sultan. Every argument was used, that ' there were millions of Moslems to whom their Imam was not l maQ Sat this. was a political not f a rehgmus mat f an so on All to ^ avail till by chance I was able to quote to them the Hadith of the peace raad# hv the prophet Mohomed at Hudaibiyah a year before the conquest of Meow between him and the people of Mecca In the document he originally described “ vfnlinmcd rasul allah . Ihe people ot Mec ca it pint * that this u.; between men anu uic 5 v himself “ Mohomed rasul allah . the people ot .Mecca repheci that this was absurd if he was the prophet of God there was no question of making ■ Rbsura, it ne was me v,, * peace ■with him or not. The prophet saw the force of the argument and described v:„,.„ir “ Molmmed bin Abdullah”. This direct appeal to their reliffin.,. himself plain “ Mohomed bin Abdullah”. Tiiis direct appeal to their religi history carried the day, and the word Imam was omitted from the body ot tie , J , 1 * 1 . • nr o nrrnnoPfl hpf.u’ppn flip Snlfovi’n ;ioug mstory cairiea mt; tun, auu u ^ ,, , , u * Ui me document whicli simply read as conditions arranged between the Sultan s Govern, mentand Isa bin S.tlih on behalf of the O n ani tribes. I explained to them that I bad no objection to any one signing for or as an Imam-al-Muslimin, The doonment was written and the signatures affixed and in the evening the Sheikhs departed tor the interior to obtain the signature of the Imam, and of the Sheikhs of the Beni Itiyam the Beni Ghafir and the Abri/in. Before their departure I took a copy of the document signed and certified by Sheikh Isa and took the precaution of warning him that the penal zakafc would not be liftej till the document was returned. Tlie signature of the Imam was obtained on the 28th September and fie document returned to me on the 7 th October signed by the remaining Sheikhs. The Imam also sent three letters addressed to his three Walis in Semail, Muawal and Eustaq, authorising them to hand oyer all the gardens to the agents of the owners. In the meantime I had obtained a similar document from the Sultan'i Government. Both parties are being given copies of the documents certified by me. i he peace was proclaimed on tbe 8 (h and already dates and Oman’s are poming in. An enormous boom in trade is anticipated, and the merchants nre prej anng to go into the interior. w w r Whether the peace will lost cannot be foretold, but it should lost at leai‘ or some tune. Bol upsides are tired and desire the resumption of normal inter course ami trade. Both sides have got what they want. The 0 nanis mat only uo - MULS nave go.t what they want. The 0 nanis mav say lave complete independence, the Sultan may say they only liavi* nfrllh 10 ^ r , 9 Tne Sultan is relieved of the expense and responsibility on—voo a Ulb .l' eat y d rebellious interior which ba*ed him, u bile he has len omst ThA? ' 8 0n yreVe T^ eeTerg0t . WJsi;hft 6 P f ' r ^nt zakat on Ike nicnt which .‘ n; ' 11 ‘^ ,a ’ t ^ge tlieir own affairs under their theoera*ic Govrn)- though sucli fVv SSIJ '^ , e G^'fn'nent best tuiti-d to their peculiar condition it front t nTonrt? W0 ^ b8 im P ossible 111 contact with the outer world, Sultan’s Government . ma ‘ !!tenatlc ® of peace is the strengthening of the payino it s W1T oil ' . 18 finan ® es are mw in order and the State is non ivlth°a small levv ^/ 6 t 3 a - Sk f- et ° n ’ quite su!Bcient . of an administra'ion. that the hi^r r d : r ic is probab!E dolicacf' tk® He will inevita 1 ih''he*nwd°''^ Ca ' ^? enf * n .^ ie future will he of same delicac; greatest tact and‘patience ‘’ s .,? n 1 '” t ' l! 1 'me:'mry over delicate questions and tk ferenceaalanocEnTi- e be necessary. With the minimum of int« - occasional hint much will be however smoothed over. Gopies of the agreements in Araik with English tr‘iislalioiis areattaP^ # Not.printed, 1,1 ! ' C ‘ !&lt;lme ifG od the compassionate, the merciful, m nt bin; IUCJ Ulj III/. — ..t of Sdtan^aiyid T-Timnid ' !n tbo sott 'ement between the al-Hrathi on behalf of th c 0 ^ 1 ^ ^ and 8, ' eikb Isa llin Salah 1 J manis who s'g*n thoiv r.a&gt;vw»o ?’gn their names here thromediation of Mr. Wingate, I.C.S., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, who is authorised by his Government in this respect to be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern the Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the Omanis. Whet concern the Omanis are these :— Firstly .—On all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Matrah, Surandall the coast towns nothing more should be taken than 5 per cent. Secondly ,—For all the Omanis there should be safety and fieedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly .—All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Matrahand all the coast towms should be removed, # Fourthly.—lhz Sultan’s Government should not protect criminals who 11 eo from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be return ed to them if asked for and that the Sultan’s Government should not interfere in their internal affairs. The four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as follows:— Firstly .—All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interfere in his Govern* ment. All travellers to Oman on'their lawful business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly .—All criminals and evil men who flee to them should be tui ned out and should not be protected. Fourthly.—The. claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should bo heard and decided as is just according to the Sharah. Written at Sib on the eleventh day of Jfoharram, one thousand three hundred and thirty nine Hijrah, corresponding to twenty fitth day ot Septem ber, one thousand nine hundred and twenty. I have completed what was completed by Sheikh Isa bin Salah on my behalf in these conditions. Written by Imam-al-Muslamm Mohammad bin Abdullah with his own hand. I on behalf of the Imam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah-al- Khalili and on my own behalf agree to the conditions written here with the authorisation of the Imam-al-Muslamin. Written by Isa bin Salah with his own hand. &gt; (Signed) Sulaiman bin Hamyar-an-Nabhani (with his own hand). Zahair bin Ghusn-al-Hinawi &gt;» i» &gt;» »» Mohsin bin Zahran-as-Siyahi Hamaid bin Mussullam-an-Nidahi Saif bin Salim bin Amir-al-Hahasi M &gt;1 &gt;1 &gt;» » II &gt;* Khalaf bin Nasir bin Mobammad-al-Moawali (with his own hand).Thumb impression of Mohammad bin Sultan bin Mansur-al-TYahaibi (Signed) Mohammad bin Saif bin Said-al-Jabri (with hia own hand) „ Sultan bin Salim ar-Rahbi (with bis own hand). „ Khalfau bin Mohammad bin Sula:man-al-Hidabi (with Us on hand). „ Tbani bin Harith-al-Jabri (with his own hand). „ Haradan bin Sulaiman bin Saif-an-Nabhani (with his own hand' „ Muhanna bin Ilamnd bin Mohsin-al-Iiari (with his own hand) • ■ a „ Nasir bin Hamaid bin Basliid-al-Gliafiri and his son Moiamimi bin Nasir (with his own hand). d Abdullah bin Hilal bin Zahar*al*Uanai (w'ith his own Land). This official document of agreement was brought to me which is tli best sort of settlement between Sheikh Isa bin Salah on our behalf as trritlet above and the Government of Sultan Saivid Taimur through the mediataS abowiZ :; I , CS '; 1 Hl3B ; ,tan T Ma i est - V ’ s Consul at Muscat, as is writta thank God P for i au ' hor ‘“ atl ° n ' o I c T - lte . t 1 h080 lines with m y o w n hand ail a. k God for it. \1 ntten by Saif bin All bin A’mir A1 Maskari with bison In tie name of God the compassionate, the merciful. Seal. ernmenjt of the Sultan ln ^j ie se ttlemea{: between the Got Wazir Saiyid Mohamrm l h' ^n iraUr i an ^ t ^ e Omanis, by the actini through the mediation of ™ ma( ^ au ^ 10 r i se d by His Highness the Sultai tannic Majesty’s Consul CC.S., Political Agent and His Bn respect to be a mediatorVotw ’ ^ 10 18 aut ^o r ised by his Government in thi Four of thern c^SrthffW em ; P , 9 editions are stated as foliowi the Omanis What concern 0| - the Sultan and four of them cancen concern the Omanis are these:— Muscat a 'ilatral ] 111 °i** eS from °uan of all kinds! should be taken than'b^r celt 1116 C ° aSt n0t ' linS B °' ,hW ° be and freedom in al %ii'dly and ali the coasttowusfild ^ remov^ MU9Cat ’ ^ Srlfn } n ' d'e from the L 0 Ve c nmen ^ s ^ ou ld not protect criminals wb returned to them 0mani s and that they may b should not inl Pr f t askedfor a nd that the Sultan’s Governmen , W. &lt;« .Mob .„i‘*'W»- °''' 9 '' T&gt;overament of the Sultan are stated as fol with the Govermrl^^kksjihould remain in peace and ain't attack the coast SuItaa and ^at they should ^ ^ meet. should not interfere in his GovernSecondly.—k\\ travellers to Oman on their lawful business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly.'—AW criminals and evil men who flee to them should be turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly.—1 l\\q claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should be heard and decided as is just according to the Sharah. Written at Muscat this fourteenth day of Moharram, one thousand three hundred thirty nine Hijrah, corresponding to twenty-eighth day of September, one thousand nine hundred and twenty. Sealed signature of Taimur (H. H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman). (Signed) Mohammad bin Ahmad, with his own hand, on behalf of the Sultan. CllFFD—36—22-11-20- GC?3r dsi) ( Confidential No. 205:2, dated the J4th October 1920. from R. R. L. ingate, I.C.S. ; Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, To—The Deputy Political Resident, r&gt;ushirp. (Copy to the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department Simla.) I have the honour to forward a report on the negotiations carried on through my mediation's the representative of the British Government between the Government of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and the tribes of interior Oman which terminated in the re-establishment of peaceful relations on the 8 th Ootober 1920. • In order to make the situation quite clear I have found it necessary to summarise very briefly the history and causes of the late rising, and to give in some detail the sequence of events from October 1919 till the conclusion of the negotiations. I wish to draw *he attention of Government to the admirable arrange ments made by Captain Pearson, commanding the detachment of the 1-11 Mb Mahrattas at Muscat for my escort a&lt;nd for the tents, etc., for the reception of the Oman Sheikhs. / Finally I wish to bring to the notice of Government the excellent work performed by the Consular Dragoman, Ehtisham-ud-Douiah Khan. The negotiations in question have been going on for a year, and have entailed arduous work and continual watchfulness. During this period he has bean indefatigable m obtaining information, and has more than once been entrusted by me with work needing the most delicate handling. At the meeting itself he also did excellent work. « 1. Brief survey of causes and history of ths rebellion of the Oman tribes under the leadership of their elected Imam Sheikh Salim bin RashiDai-Kharusi till 1915. A perusal of any history official or otherwise of Muscat and Oman will show for several hundred years examples of revolution, anarchy and murder almost unparalleled even in Arabian history. Since the expulsion of the Portuguese however there has been, except during the periods of Persian or Wahabi domination, a ruler combining both spiritual and tempral autho itv, and acknowledged nominally by all the tribes. According to the Ibadhi sect of Islam such an Imam*al-Muslimin must be elected by the people, and there is no right of heredity, though often the son of the dead Im im was accepted as Imam, With the accession to the Imamato of Ahmed Albu Saidi, the founder of the present dynasty, the system seems to have changed and the rulers of Muscat and Oman succeeded as a dynasty without the formality of election asImam. This definite departure ocounvd when SuHan bin Alimed usurped tlie power from his brother Said bin Alimed who had been elected Imam. The latter retained the title of Imam till his death, but no temporal power. The rule of Sultan and of his son Said which lasted from about 17dO till 1856 marked the growth of s*ea pow r er, foreign conquests, the most important of which was Zanzibar, and the removal of the capital from Kustaq in the interior to Muscat on the coast, and foreign treaties and interlerenc 0 , almost entirely British, The removal of t'te capital to the coast cut off from the iiverior has been stated by some as the beginning of the loss of hold by the Sultans over the interior, and as such as an impolitic move. This is however open to question. It is more probable chat tho Sultan knew they could hope better to control with outside power and this outside power they obtained from their sea power and their foreign possessions. It is a fact however that from the death of Saiyid Said the power of the Sultans over the interior became more nominal than ever. Attacks could only he warded off by brib iry, no revenue was obtained, travel was dangerous and there were several attempts by the Omani tribes to set up Imams of their own. An att u mpt had actually been made in 1849. In 1SG8 Azzan bin Qais. an elected Imam actually ruled in Muscat, and though latter ejected, many similar attempts were made during the reign of Turki and the earlier years of the reign of Faisal to depose the Sultan, who may have Slid to have been saved only by our support. Final'y in 1913, after an elaborate conspiracy of several years fostered by the famous blind Ibadhi mullah Sheikh Abdullah bin Tlumaid as Salimi, the Oman tribes rose in a body elected Salim bin Rashid-al-Kharusi as tbeir Imam and by 191 j had obtained complete control of all Oman proper where they organised a Government. It will thus be seen that for more than 60 years there has been active opposition to the ruling 1 ouse by the Oman tribes. The causes of this opposi tion may be briefly summari'ed as follows:— (1) Religion. —According to the Ibadhi religion their ruler must be elected. The Sultans who had not undergone tins formality were therefore userpers. ( 2 ) The personal character of the Sultans themselves. — rids deteriorated at an alarming rate, and the repeated assertion of the Omani tribes that they were unfit to rule does not lack justification. ( 3 ) The character of the Sultans' n/^.—This was corrupt to a degree, and the element of personal control and touch by the ruler himself which with the Arab will palliate even the worst forms of corrup tion, was completely absent. ( 4 ) Foreign interfere nee.—This appeared in the eyes of the fanatical and ignorant Omanis to be directed against their most cherished rights such as the importation of arms and slaves. In these tho Sultan acquiesced without consulting his subjects accepting large sums of money for his acquiescence, not one p°nny oi which money the Omanis ever saw. At the same time our policy in Zanzibar lost nothing in the telling. % / Several of the reasons why the Sultans were unable to cope with the rebel lion arc eon f ained in these. But to them raoy be added three mure. I he loss of Zanzibar and its revenues, the loss of sea power owdng to the introduction of steam, and finally and most important of all the effects of British influence. When considering our policy in Muscat and Oman this last point must never be lost sight of. A brief perusal or the treaties and engagements with the rulers of Muscat will show that our influence has been entirely self- interested, has p id no regard to the peculiar political and social conditions of the country and its rulers, and by bribing effete Sultans to .enforce unpalatable measures which benefitled none but ourselves, and permitting them to misrule CllFfDG7 without protest has done more to alienate the interior audio prevent the Saltans irom re-establishing their authority than all the rest put together. In otner words it has been support wrongly applied, in money an 1 not in essentials, interference in external affairs which must have serious,y reacted upon internal peace and no palliative except money which was thrown into the sea or Avorse by those into whose hands we put it. The result v as that we were reduced to the absurd position of supporting by arm d force under our treaty obligations a ruler against whom most of his subjects were in open rebellion, v\ho was theoretically independent and ^et who W'ould be driven into the sea in a day if it were not for us. The immediate causes of the 1913 rebellion were an outbreak of religious fanaticism coinciding with the sloppage of the importation of arms. 2. Events from Colonel Bonn’s first meeting with the Oman Chiefs in i915 till Major Haworth’s meeting with the same in September 1919. In January 1915 the Imam accompanied by Sheikh Isa bin S ilih-a 1 -TIarithi and many Oman Sheikhs attacked in force our defences at Bait-al-Ealaj guard ing Mattrah. The attack was beaten olf with serious loss to the Omanis who learnt their lesson there once and for all. The Imam however remained in indisputable possession of the interior and a constant menace to tbe coast towns which he would probably have taken had it not been for tbe certainty that he would be driven out in a few davs with the advent of a British m m-of-war. * In May Lieutenant-Colonel Berm, the Political Agent, sent a circular le t r to the Oman Sheikhs asking for a conference in which peace might be arrangel between the Sultan and the Imam. This did not meet with a very warm res ponse in the interior, but after considerable correspondence a meeting was finally arranged and took place at Sib on the 15th September 1 15 between Colonel Benn and Sheikh Isa as tho-representative of the Imam’s party. This meeting was entirely abortive. In the Sultan’s mind was the para mount idea that he would eventually recover his authority in the interior, in the minds of the representatives of the Imam their unassailable position as conquerors and their mcril pv-ition as Ibadhis obeying the dictates of religion. The two most important points demanded by tho Saltan were the return of the Semail forts and the recognition of his temporal supremacy in Oman. These were categorically refused by the Omanis who demanded that the Sultan should reform his government according to their ideas, that they should be given subsidies, arms and so on. I^o reconciliation was possible and the negotiations were broken off. Prom this date till 191.S no further steps wore taken towards a settlemen*. The Imam backed up by the two great Chiefs Sheikh Isa bin SaUh-al-Harithi, head of the Hinavyi confederal ion and Sheikh Hamiyar bin Nasir-al-Nabhani, head of the Ghafiri contidefation consolidated his power in the interior. On the other hand the Smtnns Government sank from bad to worse, because involved in hopeless debt and reached an unparalleled degree of ineptitude. In March 1918 during tbe absence of the Sultan four relations of Sheikh Isa s came down into Muscat and were seized by Siiyid Nadir who was acting iOr the Sultan and imprisoned. This resulted in letters from Sheikh Isa to the . , ^ 1 itical A 0 ent as king for their release. The Sultan in return insisted on the return of the valuable gardens seized by the Omanis, and the 1 o itical Agent declined to interfere except on these lines and the matter was drooped. . In i the meantime the Political Agent Major Haworth had realised the iraperatnre necessity of taking drastic measures to preserve the Sultan’s Govern ment oil the coast from complete financial and actual collapse, and a loan to ]m\ k ui&amp;an s deo s and arrangements to obtain the services of an experi enced Customs official were made. Our a ictories in the great war now made the occasion a suitable one for again approaching the Omanis with a view to a settlement and the PoliticalAgent Major Haworth addressed a very strong letter to the leaders in March 1919. Considerable correspondence resulted and finally Sheikh Isa met the Political Agent at Sib on the loth September 1919. By this time it had h en realised, and the realisation was more than confirmed at the meeting, that the recognition of the Sultan in the interior was as impossible as that he should reconquer Oman by force. His own territory was on its last legs. He only stood at all with our support. The best means was therefore the recognition of the status quo and the terms discussed and which it seemed might eventually form the basis of an agreement were that the Sul&lt;an— ( 1 ) should remove all restrictions on entry lo the town of the coast. ( 2 ) reduce the zakat on goods coming from the coist towns to the interior to 5 per cent. (3) return fugitive from justice. (d) release the four Omani prisoners. And that the Omanis— (1) should guarantee not to attack the Sultan’s territory or interfere in his Government. ( 2 ) should guarantee the safety of travellers and freedom of trade. (3) should hear and decide cases against Omanis. (4) should return fugitives from justice. ( 5 ) should return the valuable gardens belonging to two of the most important of the Sultan’s subjects seized oy the Omanis. 3 Events fron** October 1919 to October lv20 including the final settle m ment. —The situation therefore on my arrival in October was- ( 1 ) The reform of the administration of the territory controlled by the Sultan had to be taken in band. (2) An agreement was to be arranged if possible through the mediation oi the Political Agent between the Imam s party and the Sultan. It was at once clear that these two matters were closely bound together. In the first place the strengthening of the Sultan’s administration would inevitably result in a decrease in the comparative power of the Omanis In the second place an agreement and the establishment ot peace would enable the reform of the administration to be proceeded with with more rapidiiy. The reform of the administration was therefore tackled with vigour, and Sheikh Said bin Nasir al-Kindi a prominent mullah of the Ibadhi sect resident in the territories of the Sultan, and greatly respected in Oman, was sent by me to Nizwa, the seat of the Imam, to endeavour to obtain ratification otthe terms discussed at Sib. Though at the commencement of.Sheikh Said's mission circumstances seemed favourable, it very soon became evident that the influence of the “Mutawwa” or fanatical party would he strongly against the return of the gardens which were mostly in their hands and from which the mullahs derived a lucrative income. The leader of the opposition party was hJasir bin itaskid- al-Kharusi, the brother of the Imam and his Mali in Rustaq. The mission was more than once on the point o c success, but finally after i months of negotiations and intrigue the Imam in February definite^, refu-ed to Sheikh Said and Sheikh Isa to ratify the terms. The possibility of this unfavourable result had been foreseen for some time, and a definite plan of action prepared to meet the emergency. The Omanis had been given a fair field and plenty of favour. They had been moved witu39 honeyed words* Thoy had refused poaco o hu^ to i^noraiiCG and roligion^ prejudice it is true, possibly as well owing to the lukewarmness oi the chief protagonist in the cause, Sheikh Isa, but actually because the Omanis thought that we were not backing the Sibtan with auy degree of enthusiasm and that therefore they could go as far as they liked with impunity. The Omanis were therefore to be shown that our support of the Sultan was a reality, and not only that but that the Sultan was capable of retaliating very effectively on the Omanis by taxing their produce heavily when it came down to the coast for export. Reliable information from the interior showed that owing to the lon&lt;* stoppage of the import of arms and ammunition the Qmanis had largely lost their offensive power, and were by no means enthusiastic for the Imam whose puritanical fanaticism was making li r e intolerable, an itho exactions of whose brothers had raised a storm of protest. The moment was therefore opportune for changing from a weak defensive to a vigorous offensive. It was pointed out that if certain steps were taken which involved no use of force by us, it was extremely probable that the Omanis would see reason. Even if they did not do so for sometime it would not matter as affairs would eventually automatically adjust themselves with the increase of the Sultan’s power following on the reform of his administration. The following events therefore took place on the refusal of the Imam to ratify ; — (1) The negotiations were broken off bv me in the most insulting - fashion. ® ( 2 ) A British advisar to the Sultan appeared. (3) The Saltan accompanied by me went on an official visit to His Excellency the Viceroy in India leaving the British adviser in charge of the State. /j (4) A British warship, in pursuance of our enagements to suppoit the authority of the Sultan on the coast, proceeded to Masnaab and *air w eret ie authority of the Sultan had been dolled and inflicted punishment at the former place with good r esults. the suddenlemh of ShpiJrT? W,aS a V-^ e same momen ^ greatly weakened bv oHCaud htlunlb n,y f bltt Nasir-al Nabhanif the most powerful boy of 11 , * 8 su PP or t ;er &gt; whose successor was an inexperienced return from India^thenubhea^n 011 / 11 r) ^ lxn oni 7 to bo increased on my imposing a penal zakat of 25 per cent on Ilf dal ^ 8ultan S Government nates brought by the Omanis to th, ^ * dfces au ^ 50 P er cent oa pomegra* percent. \ Umams ^ the coast towns, instead of the customary 5 T.ieprodamations annonnmnn. n * care.u ly wo ded, making it nerfpoti ^ )Slfclon penal tax were very imp- sed as a punishment owin r f, • Ciea 5 ev f n to tiie Omanis that the tax was a nd to come to te rtns. o to their refusal to give up the looted property Coincident with tl &gt; it °J curre ^ ^asi?bin liadiifUf Ltv no ^ Ges (^ u May) a very significant Sultan* G f r oni Ahmad bin Ibrahir la ,^ usl v '^ 10 had been suffering con- the s iege to Hazm ' A* 11 ’ | 1 1 0 1 ru i er Hazm just within the if* °;s e w 2 wei 1 e a po ff ^ll lkh ::i,er Sheikh «Wmcu 2 d' l th 7 l I ““ y a,most bo said according Powerless Mod the I mai n pointing out that they seemed to be imposed simply100 Owing to the greed of his brother, and praying turn to return the gardens and ^ome to terms. The Imam dominated by his brother proved obdurate and dis* content grew. a a Sheikh Isa, whose last letter I had torn up and refused to answer, a dressed me himself on 2 .)th June. I seized the opportunity to write a strong r( ;Pty emphasising that the British Government was entirely behind the Sultan in this matter, and that f 'would neither meet him nor discuss any- rung w r ith mm till the looted gardens had been first returned. I took the precaution of allowing the contents of this letter to leak out before it was sent. There is little doubt that this letter dispelled any remaining doubts that the Omanis may have had. the Imam Sheikh Salim bin Rashid-al-Kharusi was murdered at Khadra. The immediate cause of his murder was stated to have been jui insult to one of his guard. Hie real re ason of his death, which was confirmed from many sources, was that the tribes were practically in open revolt against his mle and that of his brother, which was a combi nation of utter religious bigotry combined with shameless selfishness and oppression and a.complete disregard of politics or government, all of which in addition to theii inherent disadvantages were resulting in all sorts of trying restrictions from th&lt;- Sultan s Government, which they were powerless to resist, culminating in the penal zakat. Oman was now without a leader and the greatest confusion prevailed. The 'W abs of the late Imam weie driven out immediately bv the infuriated tribes - men and had to flee for their lives. Many tribes sent tentative offers of alle giance to the Sultan’s Government. Sheikh Isa began to collect men in Sharkiyah, ami on tne othei side the Sub an s Government made a determined effort to regain their hold over Oman. ' The situation was now extremely interesting, and provided the British Government could preserve an attitude of st- iet neutrality, one of two results both equally favourable to a satisfactory settlement would be hound to occur. Either the Sultan’s Government w'ould regain their hold over the interior this •would settle affairs for the moment, though it would inevitably lead the Sultan into difficulties later—or the Oman tribes would retain their cohesion against the Sultan in which latter case their leader could only hope to consolidate his posi tion satisfactorily by coming to an agreement removing immediately the penal zakat. It was peculiarly fortunate that at this crh ical moment the British adviser to the Sultan was on leave in India. It was therefore possible for the Sultan’s Government in entirely Arab hands to act without suspicion being raised that we were behind them. I kept conspicuously aloof, well knowfng that the Omanis, if they did not come into the Sultan, would approach me to mediate. Seraail was the objective of both parties, but Sheikh Isa who had meantime secured the election of bis father-in-law Mohomed bin Abdullah-al-Klmlili, chief of the powerful .Beni Ruwaha tribe as the new Imam, succeeded in reaching Semail 24 hours before the Sultan’s men, and the tribes naturally followed him! He immediately addressed himself to me through Sheikh Said bin Nasir-al- Kiudi asking for an agreement. I replied that till the gardens w^ere returned I would not meet Mm, but that when that had been done I would mediate. To show more strongly my complete indifference I stated that I was going to India for a month, and with the permission of Government went Even then Isa’s path was by no means smooth. The new Imam being a Hinawi and the father in law of Isa raised the suspicions of the Chafin'*. Ahmed bin Ibrahim on behalf of the Saltan took Ttustnq and would have held It but for the sudden desertion of the Beni Ghafir tribe to the new Imam. Immediately the Rusfaq situation had resolved itself in Isa’s favour he acted with great policy, as indeed he uas compelled to by the insecuiity of his C11EPD101 position which depended fer its consolidation on the roraovil of the penal za t ati He obtained the return of the guardens from the Imam, ' rote to me (then in Indian) that he had done so, and asked for a meeting. T1 ,- w , s fi na llv arranged and took place at Sib from tho 23rd to 26th s , mCr ID-O ' It is worthy of note that on this occasion, as a mark of the mmnlcte change' in the political situation and in the attitude of the tribes rmed by .ho new police, Isa sent in letter after letter askmg for a meeting and actually waited for me 20 days at Kboa, while on previous occasions exactly the reverse had been the case. On the 21st Captain Thomson of the l-ll7th Mahrattas proceeded with an &lt; seort of 50 men 01 the 117th to Sib by native sailing boat, to the house of the Wa'i of Mutt rail at the edge of the gardens which had been fixed as rendezvous. Tents were erected close by for the entertainment of the Sheikhs. Within a few hours of my arrival from India on the 22nd, accompanied hv Captain Pearson, Commanding thq detachment of the 117th at Mutliah, Captain Menon, il.0.,ar.d the Consular dragoman, I embarked in a native sail- iu&lt;v vessel for S h, arriving there the afternoon of the 2ord. A message was sent immediately to Sheikh Isa who was at Khoz only 2 hours distance. E irlv on the morning of the 24th Sheikh Isa accompanied by over twenty Oman Sheikhs and three hundred cameltnen arrived at the rendezvous. When thev had dismounted and entered the tents I paid the customary visit on them mc flipir host, rpmalninsr about 10 minutes. The first meeting took place an hour later and lasted some two hours. The question pressed by me was the authorisation of Sheikh Isa. It will be remem bered in this connection that on the occasion of the last meeting he was not fully authorised. Finally, he haying, stated, and his word having been confirmed by other Sheikhs, that he was fully authorised by the Imam, it was agreed that the terms if arranged would be signed by him and the Sheikhs present in my presence, and that they would then take the document away and obtain the signature of the Imam and of any other Sheikhs whom I might name. After the middy meal a further long meeting was held to discuss the actual terms. There were { resent at this meeting only Sheikh Isa, Said Kasir-al- Kindi, tbe Consular dragoman and myself. Twelve extravagant terms were put forward by the Omanis:— ( 1 ) That the independence of Oman should be recognised. - (2) That the zikat should be reduced to 5 per cento (3) That the Omanis should be free and safe in tbe Sultan’s territory. (4) Ihat the British Government-should not help their enemies (pre* sunnbly meaning the Sultan). (5) That nothing should be done against their religion., (G) I hat pas$po;ts should not be needed fur them. (7) That they suould he allowed to purchase cartridges. ( 8 ) That the Suit an should subsidise them, (9j That all documents such as passports, etc., from the Imam’should be countersigned by the Political Agent and not by the Sultan. ( 10 ) That Bashid bin Uzaiz should not bo allow* d in Oman. (11) That Sheikh Said bin Nasir-al-Kindi should be guaranteed safe y ^ the Sultan’s territory. ( 12 ) That tbs Sultan should return fugitives from tlieir justice. As against this they proposed to promise : — ( ) Not to attack tho bultan s territory or to interfere in his Government O To allow freedom of trade and travel in Oman.102 Gi Uie terms tl»ey proposed to exact from the Sultan all except (2) and (3) and (12) were clenrly absurd. By a mixture of argument, cajolery and threats and the final statement that if they were not prepared to accept the terms originally agreed upon I would leave at once, they finally agreed to ask ing only ( 2 ), 3) and (!&gt;') from the Saltan. Terms ( 10 ) and ( 11 ) were put in by Sheikh Said bin Nasir al Kindi only owing to personal enmity and were soon disposed of. (l) was pointed out as being absurd—if we were mediating in an agreement they could rely on our not backing the other s : de unless they flagrantly broke it. (5) was pointed out as a sine qua non. ( 6 ) and (0) were pointed as equivalent to asking for exemptions of formalities which had to he undergone by the whole world, and as implying no disgrace but which even British citizens had to put up with in other countries. (/) was pointed out as impossible owing to international agreement and it was added that in any ca*e permission to import could not be given till we were sure by experience of their good intention^. ( 1 ) was categorically refused and it was explained that as they had got practical independence what more did they want. ( 8 ) was laughed at. Finally the following terms were arranged. The Sultan’s Government w’ould: — ( 1 ) Ptecluce the zakat on all goods coming into the coast towns to 5 •: per cent. (2) Guarantee safety and freedom for Omanis in the coast towns., (3) Bemove all [restrictions on the entry of Omanis into Muscat and Muttrah. (4) Return fugitives from their justice andlnot interfere in their internal affairs. (Xote. —The word here used was &lt;! dakhiliy. t-a-hum,” which is very im portant as it means no more than it says, their internal affairs, and the Sultan cannot argue should ho choose to do so that there is any derogation of his supreme authority. On the other hand the Omanis are at liberty to regard it as complete independence. Both sides are therefore satisfied.) The Omanis would-— (1) Remain in peace with the Sultan, not attack the coast and not interfere with his Government. (2) Permit freedom of trade and travel in Oman and guarantee the safety of travellers. (3) Would return and not protect fugitives from the Sultan’s justice. ( 4 ) 'Would hear the claims of traders and others against Omanis accord ing to Shara. It is amusing to note that the terms asked from the Sultan was originally only three, (2) and (3) being combined. When the Omanis found that they had to concede four terms to the Sultan they were somewhat upset, but the situation Tvas saved by splitting the second term into two. As reo-ards the fourth term conceded by the Omanis, hearing by the Shara was Inevitable as they have no other courts. It will almost certainly be necessary in this respect to warn British subjects that they should be careful to claim on “ waraqas” (documents) not on account books which would not be accepted. On the morning of the 25th Sheikh Isa and some twenty Sheikhs came to write out the terms and sign them in my presence. Immediately a most difficult noint arose. Sheikh Isa insisted that the peace should he between the Sultan on the one side and the “ Imam-al-Muslim ” on the other. This I refused for obvious reasons. In the first place it meant the open recognition by us of another ruler. In the second such a peace would obviously be103 resented it not disowned by the Sultan. Every argument was used, t,., there were millions of Moslems to whom their Imam was not l ffit[ . that this was a political net a religious matter and so on. All to avail till by chance I was able to quote to them the Haaith of the peace mace bv the prophet Mohomed at Hudaibiyah a yeir before the conquest of Mecti between him and the people of Mecca. In the document he originally desert himself “ Mohomed rasul allah The people of Mecca replied that this u absurd, if he was the prophet of God there was no question of making with him or not. The prophet saw the force of the argument and described himself plain “ Mohcmed bin Abdullah”. This direct appeal to their religion history carried the day, and the word. Imam was omitted from the body ot tii? document which simply read as conditions arranged between the Sultan’s Govern mentand Isa bin Salih on behalf of the Ora ani tribes. I explained to then; that I had no objection to any one signing for or as an Imam-al-Mualimk The document was written and the signatures affixed and in the evech, the Sheikhs departed for the interior to obtain the signature of the Imam, aJ of the Sheikhs of the Beni Iliyam the Beni Ghafir and the Abriyin. Befo their departure I took a copy of the document signed and certified by Sheikh 1 ? and took the precaution of warning him that the penal zakat would not be lifted till the document was returned. The signaturerof the Imam was obtained on the 28th September aud t &gt; document returned to me on f he 7th October signed by the remaining Sheikk The Imam also sent three letters addressed to his three Walls in Srna; Muawal and Bmstaq, authorising them to handover all the gardens to the a»e;- of the owners. . In the meantime I had obtained a similar document from the Salfan's Government. Both parties are being given copies of the documents certified by me. dhe peace was proclaimed on the 8 th and already dates and Oman’s ai* pouring in. An enormous boom in trade is anticipated, and the merchants are preparing to go into the interior. W lietlier the peace will lost cannot be foretold, but it should lost at leu or some 'nae. Both sides arc tired and desire the resun.ption of normal Mw course ami trade. Both sides have got what they want. The Omanis an' ISA C0 “P let e independence, the Sultan may say they only to of rulinca h A V 1 t’ T‘ ic ^ u d an is relicyed of the expense and responsiiiilil' no’SciA.tAr' 1 rebelli0 . U8 interior ^‘dch hated him, while he has 1- coast. The Omin' 0 ' ^ rcvori ’* e ^ e cver got was the 5 per cent zakat oa it ment which is tmJ S ’n a 4 ?'°/b ,8,r owa a ® a * rs under their theocratic Goyea- thou r »h such Oovp 31 ' . l,: ' ‘ ‘ovfriirnent best suited to their peculiar condition sWest m-mwn t? W0U H be in contact with the outer *or: Sultan’s Governliier.t nAAsA ™ 6 ° f P* 8 ?® is the strengthening oh.y paying its wav • S ^ nan ces are now in order and the State is c() With a small Tew ooriw h sk ?i eton &gt; qiite sufficient, of an administr»!i« that the Omanis will /v i UI1 ? ‘' c * ua ‘ an d visible man power it is probs* aniS WlU thlnk before they break their word. He wiUinA'tnbly beA F l 0 ‘' tiCal A 8 ® 111 “ ‘be future will be of some deli*/ greatest tact and WienA ! “ s . an mter “ediary oyer delicate questions and t- fereuce aa 1 an ocSnAv ' 1 'pessary. With the minimum of W • * occasional hint much wiU be however smoothed oyer. prihtad. Gbpies of the agreements inAr with English translations areatt amediation of Mr. Wingate, I.C.S., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, wbo is authorised by his Government in this respect to be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern the Goyernmentof the Saltan and four of them concern the Omanis. Whet concern the Omanis are these :— Firstly .— On all commodities brought from Oman of all binds to Muscat, Matrah, Surand all the coast towns nothing more should be taken than 5 per cent. Secondly .—Per all the Omanis there should be safely ai d f.cedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly .—All reslrictipns on entry to and exit from Muscat, Matrah and all the coast towns should be removed, i Fourthly .—The Sultan’s Government should not protect criminals \*ho flee from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be return ed to them if asked for and that the Sultan's Government should not interfere in their internal affairs. Ihe four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as follows:— Firstly .—All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not interfere in his Govern ment. Secondly-—kM travellers to Oman on their lawful business should be tree and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly .—All criminals and evil men who flee to them should bo turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly .—The claims of merchants and others against the Omanis should be heard aud decided as is just according to the Sharah. Written at Sib on the eleventh day of Moharram, one thousand three hundred and thirty nine Hijrab, corresponding to twenty fifth day of Septem ber, one thousand nine hundred and twenty. X have completed what was completed by Sheikh Isa bin Salab on my behalf in these conditions. Written % Imam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah with his own hand.* I I on behalf of the Imam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah-al- Khalili and on my own behalf agree to the conditions written here with the authorisation of the Imam-al-Muslamin. Written by Isa bin Salah with his own hand. »&gt; *» (Signed) Sulaiman bin Hamyar-an-Nabhani (with his own hand). Zahair bin Ghusn-al-Hinawi „ Mohsin bin Zahran-as-Siyabi „ Hamaid bin Mussullam-an-Nidabi „ Saif bin Salim bin Amir-al-Habasi „ „ „ » Khalaf bin Nasir bin Mohammad-al-Mpawali (with his own hand). &gt;&gt; »&gt; »» »* &gt;»A Isa bin Galeh . v * After Coraplirnentg, I have lately returned to Tfasoat and have perused your two letters dated 1st Janadi II 9th January 1924, In reply to the letter about ammunition I beg to inform you that I shall have to refer to the Resident in the Persian Gulf and this will take some time but I wil 1-communicate with you further on this subject in due course. In reply to the other letter I note what you say and heave also examined the agreement made by ?, r f. Tingate. I understand from the Muscat Government that the tax in question is levied on animals only and not on men or goods. I’d mention is made in the agreement of animals and hence it would appear that the agreement is not violated by this tax. However the matter is capable of discussion and it gives me an opportunity of asking you to come and see me. r from you of the condition in Oman and am al • arrangements if possible for a trip to thet , copy of letter - 4ated i^^yn 924 . to Hi * Highness the Sultan Taimur bin raienl, iiuscat. After Compliments, There is nothing particular in this side of Shnrqiyah rvhich may be written to you except that everything is calm. *e heard about your arrival to the centre of your territories and we thank God on your safe return. We received the news of the death of your brother Saiyid Muhammad. Everything is for God and is to return to Rim. God may take end leave whom Re wants and every one is to die and close ( his life). May God remove your calamity for him and re compensate you. As the son Abdullah bin sulaiman is leaving for the Rajj I am sending this letter to you with my complimenti and salutations and **a salaams to you- and the esteemed Saiyids Kadir end his brother and Said and hie brothers, prom here all 4 sons sands their salaams. This is from your servant Isa bin Saleh and was written by your servant Muhammad as dictated by his father. Ve hope that on the kings arrival the new tax on the Muslims which is inflected on the strong and the weak was removed and you are to be asked favours kindness and salaams. prom the servant (of God) Isa with his own hand.r M' aajor R. G. Kinda, I.A., ^P, A' ? v V - &amp;* 9w* /li*** 0 ^ T&lt; fha Secretary to the» hon’blo the rolitioaX Resident in the Persian Gulf, £ U 3 B I ft £ , //■ Zl,***W' t 1st March 24 •5 ^4 1 hare the honour to forward herewith Arabic and Utaglleh copies of a letter received from 3heifch lea bin 'lalAh asking for a^Haunition to be supplied to the Omanis* 2* X would poir«t out that this is the first occasion since the signing of the agreement between Hie Highness the , Sultan and the Omanis in 1920 that this Agency has been approached by the Omanis for a^unltlon and that as far as I am aware no aim unit ion has been imported by them threugh Muscat territory though it ie within tho bounds of possibil- -ity that erniall cuantities may have been s uggled Via Bebal* 3* A reference to r* Wingate v » confidential report Re* 2052 dated 14th October 1920 which giv e the text of the agreement referred to above shows that the right to purchase ( i*e* import ) cartridges was demanded by the Omanis in their twelve original terms. Mr* Wingate refused f this pointing out that it wae * impossible owing to inter- -national agreement '.and adding that ' in any case pennies- -ion■ . ' Jr ow British Agency A Consulate, ^3 Muscat, the 18th March 1924* Major R*G* Hinde, I.a*. Political Agent A Consul, MUSCAT. To Sheikh lea bin Saleh, After compliments, I have received your letter of 3rd shaaban also the one sent with Abdullah bin Suleiman with whom I had conversation* I am considering the matter very carefully from all points of view in consultation with the Muscat Oovemmenl and I have every reason to hope that within a very few days the matter will be satisfactorily settled to the benefit of both parties when I will immediately infonn you. With regard to your request for ammunition political Resident has informed me that he has referred the matter to the Government of India who will doubtless reply in course* This is what bad to be said and salaams* MAJOR, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s consul, MUSCAT*No.24. &amp; Uo. Muscat 26th March 1924. To Shaikh Isa 'bin Salah A. C . Vide Shailch Isa^ letter of 11th Shaaban 1340 in Office Pile 'Met 7 at ion betv/een Mu^^at Govt .and tin.3jmanis. In continuation ofm my letter to you of the 18th March I am pleased to inform you that the Muscat Government in the interests of the preservation of peace and the con- —tinuance of unhampered trade have agreed to remove the tax on animals now collected by them at Rui with effect from the date of this letter* The Muscat Government do not admit that the Treaty referred to b.v you in vour letters nrewents them from nlacinc a But at the same time they point out that it was not they that originally broke the treaty but the Omanis by the murder of an askari near Sur and up to this time no compensation or reparation has been made for this murder nor has any regret ever been expressed for it* In the circumstances therefore it is not becoming to the Omanis to talk of a broken treaty or of justice or equity when they themselves were the transgressors*and have made no I fear you misunderstood my reference to a visit to the invite Jebel Akhdar. My intention was you to Muscat Vide Shailch Isa^ letter of 11th Shaaban 1340 in Office Pile 'Met 7 at ion betv/een Muscat Govt .and tin.3jmanis* •yfti-igYg when it would be possible to discuss wxth you the prospects of a visit to the Jebel Akhdar but I fear it will be too late this season to go on account of the nearness of the hot weather and I will leave the matter nearness till next winter. Usual ending. Major* Political Agent and H.M's Consul, Muscat.CONFIDENTIAL. No. -S of 1924. British. Residency and Consulate-General, ' ■ Bushire, 25th March 1924. From .The Hon’ble Lieut-Col. A. P. Trevor, C.S.I., C.I.E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To 'The Political Agent, Muscat. Ammuniti on for Omanis. Sir, With reference to your letter No. 19-C dated lst/6th March 1924 on the above subject I have the honour to confirm the conversation I had with you at Muscat on the 16th instant on the subject. 2. The Omanis are not allowed to import arms and ammunition through Muscat without the permission of the Sultan, and His Highness has informed me that he is not disposed to grant any such permission. Further, since Mr. Wingate sponsored the agreement between the Sultan and the Omanis an international agreement about the importation of arras into a certain specified zone which includes Muscat has been concluded It is therefore useless for me to recommend Government to sanction the import of arms or ammunition by Omanis, as the British Government is bound not to permit this by international agreement. You will see from your records that we had great n difficulty at first about the importation of arms and ammunitio for the Levy Corps ! In the circumstances I fear that permission to im- -port ammunition cannot be granted to the Omanis. J u £ L I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 1 f X . • ' Lieut-Col., PoU-Mnni Rpsirient in the Persian Gulf.•I -Mr f .•» Pro;3 ?0 .&lt; f* 'jt ne Miacat, dated Vne 23th April 1994 y.'ra Ramzan 1^4 2. '' Tte Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul ^ muscat* Shaikh 'I sa. bin Salah al-Herithi . _ f * UJ i k i , / * # . * (M a: a. Jm ■ C I 'V \ After Complfments,• I have received your # letter dated 12th Ryazan an&amp; understood its contents, Regarding the purchase' of arns and • 1 xkixxxji£x aTTirnuni tion j to invorro you* that /„ ioWi^W3£&lt;%z* v f l3 - e? tc fJ^Hon’Dle the Poli*tical Resident in the *' I - * i * f 46 jy PepEiah Gulf* ^/fter the ^Ime ^hen ncgociations between the Omani 3 and J^scat Government were SfhaSnjgi Vou opoke about arras to Mr. Wingate t*hprc 7 /as made an International arras conven tion between the big nations of the world who f , :. *-+4 , t ' i *■ v-,** , V i« hgreed to stop Importation of arms in certain ai^as, in which Muscat is included and as such it is'now not possible to import arras into Muscat port. Even,if the Hon»ble the Political / Resident desires to do so -the Government of India agree to his recommendation it is against the said International convention to import arras into Muscjit and the Hobble the Political Resident regrets that in these circurastances his reconmendations for import of arras v/ill be uselees as under the said convention permission to import ammunition int( Muscat cannot be granted to the Omanis. I am going to India today owing to hot weather and will return after 3Nt.C-7^ ^32. (4$) Tke Political Agency &amp; H.B.U* s Consulate, Muscat, tke April 1932. ( 5 / 1 ° • fS Tc Tkc Hon f bit tkc political Resident in tke Persian Gulf, luskire. Subjeetj- Museat - Omani Treaty . M.m.randum. a,m« day. ag. *ne ShaiJck Saif bin Humaid al Sumri, a .l.s. fri.nd .f Siiailtdi Isa bin Sal.b al Haritkat wh. was sn his way ts Bahrain ts get eems parts fsr a pumping maohins, sailed #n me. The abject ef his nsit was apparently te seund me an the subject ef a renewal X • ■ ef the Museat - Omani Treaty made in September 1920 through the mediatien ef Mr. Wingat., Pelitieal Agent at Museat at that time. (Se. Mr. Wingate's despateh Ne.2052 •f 14th Oeteber 1920). 2 . There is efidently seme anxiety in Omani eireles as to whether the new Sultan will renew tne treaty. The Shaikh said that epinien in the interior held that His Highness was tee young far his important p.sitien, and that he was inelin.d to be I replied that I knew the Sultan well, mush better I rentured t. suggest than did the pe.pl. of Oman, that he had an un.emmenly eld and shrewd head on y.ung shoulders, and was by no means rash. With regard to th. renewal of th. Treaty, the Sultan would be ba.k from Dhefar s»ma time after the middle ef April when Sha Isa eeuld take up the matter with him. Omanis, with the example ef Sur before' k. tlaem, are apparent!/ under the impression that His ^5 Highness ma/ endeavour, perhaps with eur assistance, te regain seme of the eld Museat eentrel ever the interior, which misapprehension is no bad thing as it will maxe them eager te eenelude the confirmation of the Treat/, and te make the first advances. Before leaving for Dhefar in fact the Sultan spefce te me about this ver/ matter, and said that he had intended te write te Shaikh Isa on tne sub u eet, but that on further reflection had decided te let the latter make the first step. I said that I thought this a wise meve. In Arab polities it is often a ease of rie n fa ir e e^st agir . There should net be an/ difficult/ * * * 4 5 about the actual renewal therefore as both parties desire it. The Omanis, since the Treat/ was made b/ the mediation of His Majest/’s Government as represented b/ Mr. Wingate, will probably require some assurance that His Majesty* s Gevernment approve of the renewal. If I WC re given tne necessary authority^a letter from me to the Sultan sa/ing that Hia Majesty’s Government approved of the renewal, which letter His Highness could show to Shaikh Isa, would probably meet the ease. 4. SiiaikH Saif al»e ask.d me if tie late Sultan had abdicated ef hia ewn free will, er whether he had beer. \\ \ \ pressed te de so by Gerernment! I exylained to him at some length that far frem pressin* him te abdicate Gevernment, the present Sultan, yeu and myself had all taken infinite pains te try and persuade Sir Taimur bin Faisal to remain en as Sultan, both by letters and personal interviews, but in vain. That the late Sultan was a pleasant individual, and a fri.nd ef mine, but that frankly he was net fend ef work and much preierred travelling about India, Ceylon and Burma te perfenO«« ^ duties at Muscat. 5. Shaixh Saif is a nice eld gentleman, and a. I wished him t. carry baek sympath.ti. impression, efAIR MAIL 3_(R_AP 173 ( 4t) jb u zT * .lyvL £&gt; * o? No.245-a of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-Generc.l, Bus hi re, the 2t)th April 1932. From - The Hon 1 ole Lt.Colonel H.V.Biscoe,I.A., Political Resident in the Persian Orulf, To The Political Agent, nauscat. Memorandum. ,L r&amp; Your Memorandum 1.o.C.79 of 4th April 1032. ^.uscat- Omani Treaty. 2 , I have not yet referred the matter to the Government of India but have no doubt that they will approve of the renewal of this treaty, which apparently in Arab eyes is not binding on the successor of trie Ruler who signed it. 3 , 1 do not quite however see the point of your state ment that the Omanis will probably require some assurance that His Majesty's Government approve of the renewal, since thi treaty was made by the mediation of tneir representative. It seems to me that if the Omanis were reluctant to renew the treaty it might then be desirable to inform them tnat the British Government desired its renewal and were prepared to support the State in the event of their refusing to renew it. As, however, the Omanis themselves are apparently desirous of renewing the treaty, 1 see no necessity for informing tnem of the fact that tne British authorities desire its renewal. On the other hand this is a matter in whicn r-is i.ignness tne Sultan should, I think, be guided by our advice, and were he on his side reluctant to renew the treaty 1 think it would be desirable • • •&amp; desirable to intimate to him that we desired it to be renewed. as, however, he apparently is equally desirous of renewing it, advice on our part would seem to be superfluous. In fact, since both parties desire the renewal, it seems to me a matter in which we can stand aloof except to the extent of bringing the parties togetner, and this I suggest might be done oy getting nold of Shaikh Saif on his return and suggesting to him tnat Shaikh Isa bin Saleh should approach the Sultan in tne matter. This apparently you have done during your last interview, but ii you a:et another opportunity you might perhaps further emphasise the matter to him. '(xr£— Lt.Colonel, Politieal’hesident in the Persian GulfNo•C*» / 0 ( Of 1932* Tht Political Agency k Consulate, Muscat, the May 1932. To The Hon'ble the Political Reoident in the Persian Gulf, Buehire. Subject:* Muscat-Omani Treaty. Memorandum. Please refer to your memorandum No.245*S of 25th April, paragraph 3. The point of my statement was to prepare in advance for s contingency which is likely to arise. Arabs are conservative creatures and as the local representative of Government mediated last time they will probably want him to take some .^tArt in the Treaty this time also. Moreover the Omanis, who are nervous - guite without cause of course - as to the Sultan's intentions towards them will probsbly feel safer if we countenance the Treaty in some way. If thay do make some such request then it will be an advantage to have considered the situation belorehand. If they don't then I quite agree we should stand aloof. Should, however, they aek from us for some sort oi recognition of the Treaty^ then the suggestion at the end of pera 3 of my letter No.79 of 4th April would seem to represent the minimum of interference on our part, and may satisfy the omania. There will be no need fer the suggested letter of course unless the contingency arises. Lieut.Colonel.© m ) from TT.H.Soiyid Letter dated 11th Rajat) 1351 ( ^ I / '' 3aid Lin T c - imur, Jultrn of muscat ^ Oman, to Captain it.O. Al'bsn, loliticsl &gt;^ent ^ Consul, lluscat. *71th reference to our conversation with regard to the murder of one of ny clerks, 3cid 'bin Khamis Lin Ruv/aisen cl Hanoi, ot Sih during my absence in India. On my return to Kuscot the matter was put up to me. Cn perusing the correspondence, cppies of which ore forwarded herewith, I noticed that my Council of Regency had addressed Cheikh Isa bin Solih al Harithi on the subject and his answer was awaited. I then received a letter from Sheikh Isa which was of no use to which I replied. At last I received his find renly in answer to my previous letter. Sheikh Isa is wrong in stating that ohe bhcr«'» Goes not permit them to arrest the accused^because on many occasions they had arrested the accused in similar cases milch occurred in the interior on suspicion only without having any tracker. Rut in this cose the trackers have accused the people of lOiaudh who on many previous occasions had showed their enmity to ^aid bin Khamis. Sheixh Isa cm Salih is also wrong in stating in his letter that he does not see any reason to suspect the accused. Sheikh Iso has also stated in one of his letters that they, consider odd bin Lhamis as one of their sons because he had stayed ior Home time at Khaudh and had been educated with them there. This statement cannot be taken as a proof so that the charge a ainst the accused may be removed. T am pointing out dese matters and request you to represent the case to me Hon’cle the Political “esident. T am not satisfied with the replies given by Sheikh da in this important matter the consequences of which ore not wood if it is not settled in some way. In view ot the met that the ~ritish Government acted as a mediator in the rcace which was concluded between us and the Sheikhs of the interior* «m4 i&amp;ft) 4 01 -ocn, . deemed it necessary to approach you in this matteTT j iy object is that the people of Khaudh should abide by the ‘ I.tuhaiiiLiadon ohars Law and pay whet is due from them. Firstly the accused should be arrested and then investigation should jj be made by both parties. If the case is proved against the accused f •..ell and pood otherwise they will be released and will not be subjected to anythin-. I further state that Sheikh Isa bin Salih ha.- remarked that they cannot be held responsible on the mere statement of the fcKxxxic trackers. I point out that if a similar -• e happens -n our territory and they char—e one of the inhabitants or accuse him according to the statement of the tracicers we are also not prepared to accept it. T do not -o into the details of this matter as you will understand the whole cr.se from the papers which I am cnclocing herewith. If they do not act in a just manner and do not take the necetoary action in this matter it shows that they have ignored the peace which was concluded hetween us through H.ll’s Government and do not act up to its terms. There is no doubt that H.L »£ Government do not a^ree to a matter which may cause the breach of peace of a country and its inhabitants. Another murder case happened at sib some months a^o before the occurrence of the present one, md the Siyabiyyen xzjlbl of 7/adi Semeil were accused of the murder but until A nothing has been done in the matter. ^his also indicates that they do not care for such important matters which will lead to bad zxxx results. I now expect to have your opinion in this matter and - do not like to take any action until T receive your answer and your valuable views. T T Letter dated 8th Luherram 1350 ( ) from Sultan bin Said bin Auhammad and Yahya bin Humaiyed of Bani Hanah to the Council of Rcyency. 7e beg to inform you that when Said bin Khamis bin Kuwaisen arrived at X&amp;JtEidii your town Hh&amp;uch, Zahei bin Cmt ir came to me and stated that he (said) should not stay at I-Chtmdh as the3 t(&gt;K3 I 3^yao . jeen v/ere .of ter his blood. ' r e should either turn him oiT 0 ^ ■ ' n Gr (3sid) should be under our protection and v/e should be responsible for him as he (Zoher) had made a covenant ’..ith -h c m (oijfcbi^een) that he should have nothing to do with him (oaid,. e replied that we oo not approve that 3aid should jo out c •-hat . e CwO not a.jree that any untoward should happen to hia life or property. He replied that either something will happen to him or to ‘“'aid. V/e informed him that we /taould be against him if anythin* happens to ^eid. This is what had happened and facts will be communicated to you by °aid. U. H. Hot e _by H.H. This letter was sent last year by the leaders of Khaudh to the Council of T'inisters informing them of the attitude of Taher bin Cmeir who is also one of the leaders of Khaudh, whichindicates that the people of Fhaudh had some bad intention towards the deceased d a id bin hhamis.. better dated 1st w amedi I, 1351 ( 2w?\’7- / from Sultan bin I.'uhammad T 7ali of Sib, to the Council of A 'e : ;tncy. A. C. I beg to inform ^that Said bin Khd^ie bin Huwoisen al Hcnai and his wife v/ere shot in their house in the evening of Aha. 1st Jamadi I { 2 -{ •// ' Z ). The wife died at once but Said is still alive. This is what had happened and decision rests with you. He was residing in the quarter of Sheikh w aif bin Said al Hadidi. The murder&lt;ris not known and I have sent for lafirs (trackers). T T Tote by tT .^. This is the first letter from T7eli of Sib rei^orting the murder of Said bin Khomis. Statement made by Sheikh Saif bin Said al Hadidi dated wnd Jsi s-di I, 1351 ( 3/f/n ). He states that he heard that a shot was tired about the dawn. Afterwards he heard a noise and went out towards that noise. Hefound out that Sc id 'bin iChcmis ^csjsdot. 4. They scorched for the murderer hut could not trace him* They returned and reported the matter to the ’'. r ali Sultan bin l uhammed who immediately came. V r hen they were giving medicine to Said bin Khar is he stated that the Siyabiyeen have tal&lt;en their revenge and that they shall meet on the resurrection day* The ’Tali asked liuhsmmad bin Hilal to send the Qafirs (trackers). SS ter morning prayers coffee was then served in the mosque and Ji&amp;xa&amp;aoi all/went to ~cid bin lihamis’e house. They followed the track as for as the ardens outside the town where they found three footprints which were v&gt; oing towards the desert. It was a very hot dey and all were thirsty. They asked the Mali to return but they followed the tracks as far as the Kothib and halted there. Tn the afternoon they again followed the tracks until they reached £&amp; a place called al p.ithnah. The people of Khaudh viz. Zaher bin Omcir, Mubarak bin Omair and Scud bin Sultan v/hp were with the trackers told them to follow the tracks but the sun set at the same place* Mote b y H.H. This is the statement made by Said bin So if al Hadidi Sheikh of /ulad Hadid at Sib in whose quarter the murder took place. Sheikh Seif bin ^oid ol Hodidi asked him to verify the murder track of the murderer. He begen from the house where the was committed and followed it os lor as ol lithnah where Sultan bin Said has dote plant ions. He Mien followed the track os for os the -^odi al Khaudh where it ended Statemed mode by Q,uraish bin Salim ol Hadidi acted 2nd Jo modi T, 1351 ( ^ ' - )• He states that Sheikh oaif- bin ^aid ol Hadidi asked him to verify the track of the murderer* H^ ot^on -rom the houseJ. i *. , . Vn n w . : AN In T 5. w murder where the a^xJuaM/v/ae committed end followed the tracic aa far as the place called Jalban whence it went towards the Hast and passed the V/adi of Khaudh called al Bithnah where the sun set and they lost the track. The footprint which they followed from the house (where the offence was committed) there were 3 footprints as far as the end of the town was that of a slave but/juiixjQi* from outside the town up to the place where they ended. They think that the latter two footprints were those of free born persons. Statement mode by Sabhah bin Fhasaf al Hadidi ^ofir (tracker) dated 2nd aamadi I&gt; 1351 ( 3| 37 ii He be -an to follow the track from the house where the murder took place. He first found the footprint Ox a slave which was ^oing outside the town. Outside he found three^ footprints. He followed them as far as Wadi Hajrof. 'hej 10Gt then went towards the Hathib and crossed the Hawariah and ended at the date plantation of Sultan bin Said where the sun set. Letter dated 2nd Jamadi T , 1351 ( Council of ^egency to Sultan bin Said, Faher bin Cmwir ana all the Pan! Hanoh of Khaudh. have come to Sib in connection with the murder of one of the muscat Government officials, ^id bin Ahamis bin Huwaisen, and his wife. The trackers of Aulad Hadid informed us that they had followed the track of the murderers as far as the place colled al Bithnah of Ahcudh. i/e are serving the ^fir (tracker) who is appointed by the Government in order to make further enquiries about the footprints of the murderers in aadiUnn to what the pther Qafirs have done. -pe request you to help him in ascertaining the footprint oi.6. GiT I6tf el Hadidi has informed us that you were with them while they were accompanying the trackers up to the place where it ended at nightfall* Note hy JT.T-T.__ This is the letter of the Council of n m;ency to the people of Khaudh who ? re accused of murdering i&gt;aid bin Khamis. Letter di.te-d 3rd v ariadi T, 1351 ( 1 ) from .Sultan bin Said, Zaher bin Omair and all the Bani Hanon to the Council of vxppency. ^ L- v '., r e have today received your letter dated the 3rd v cmadi -) and understood its contents. You have stated that vou hove sent the Kafirs to verify the footprint, is ore at vour disposal end the ;ioce is yours and there is no objection 'he murder of Said bin Xhamis is a loss to all oi us. .e are ready to help in any matter. Not e by H.H. Reply of the people of Khaudh to tne Council Letter dated 9th “o. .adi -, 1351 ( ‘ i-4 ^ r01 ' -hsi^.h v a tin 3 E Hh to Sheikhs Saif bin Said and all Aulaa Haaia. / .C. Loat ni.jht I arrived at rhoudh. According to r letter which I hove received from the Council of Regency the C.afirs accuse the people of Khaudh of murdering 3 0 id bin Khamis. I have made enquiries but could not get confirmation of the matter. Tf you know anything which confirms the matter your people should undergo a punishment above what they deserve. You should ascertain the matter and should not *x**i*jpc say anything about which you -re not avare. T shall, ^ev,„nnn -h,. with vou. I am proceeding to ruovil anu :iu*I hb - 8 to inform you of my intention. Before your arrival I received s communication from the Council in which they hove accused the people of Khoudh of murdering Said 'bin ICahmis according to the statement of the trackers, but it was not proved^and I do not see any reason for such an accusation as there was no antecedent to lead to such a crime. T would like to have fifty of them to take oath or to have the case compromised if possible. T f you approve and have no objection please instruct Ssiyid ITosor to send the relatives of the murdererd man to me at Khaudh. If you do not like that the case be settled in that manner G od T s order will govern all and every I-uharnmadan should adhere to it. ilote by H.H. I'his is the second reply of bheikh. is a to me. letter dated 17th -onodi XT, 1351 ( p from !:.’T.38ij,id or id 'b in Toimur to Shaikh Ies kin Sr.lih.ul H- ritai. ’Xith reference to the letter which sexs you sent to my Council of ‘Wencv in connection with Said Mn irho.ie's r.urder which was ■v* — v proved by verificotion of tracks by ^efirs cjfinot three individuols of irheudh namely lubarsk bin Omoir, Xnrr.i bin ifnemis md .J-i bin Selim whose times were communiccted to you, understend from your letter thet the statement of Tafire enould not be relied upon. In reply I say that the Sham is the chief foundation and accepted by every Muslim. Verifying of tracks is one of the established proofs. Do you reject it entirely? Tf so we should not be held responsible if such incidents happen m future. In any cose the accused should be first arrested ana then enquiries should be made into the cate. There is no doubt that the murderers and his accomplices do not admit their crime. You should better take the necessary action in the matter. If you have nothing further to say besides the 3 courses which you have already informed me please let me know so that T may be sure about them. Procrastination should not be made ir. such cases nd there is no need to state more than this to you.9 . (g) H&gt;y ITote by K»H&gt; U5J This is a letter which T have addressed to Sheikh Isa bin Salih on rvj return from India on receipt of his second reply to the letter which was written to him by my Council of Regency v ’’^ en * was away in India. Letter doted 21st Jarnadi II, 1351 ( 2-1/ /&lt;? /-&gt; ^ ) from Sheikh Iso bin Salih to Saiyid ^cid bin Taimur, Sultan of Unseat and Oman. Luring my 3 days stay at Khaudh I was expecting; to receive vour letter but I received your letter of the 19th inst ( £ t Sorur. I was ^lod to hear of your welfare and understood its contents with regard to the v c: ir and your reliance on his statement. The Shara does not permit such a thin- because it is necessary that there should be one or two trustworthy •persons who should corroborate the statement before the cauL*'. ' r e A not making procrastination in the muraer out we do not wont to do anything against the religion. L* individual wno was xkj well 6C(iU*inted with the affsir ha a rejected the Kafir's Etct-aci nt. During ny atay at Khtudh 1 r-de entries from those who were close friends of -aid tin i-hm-ts hut they had nothing further to say except what they had heard of -he 'brfir's strtwmcnt. - e consider Said as one of our sons hcvcouse he stayed a long time at Khoudh where he was educated with ue. 'uhom.d bin }'hunts informed ne that r.uharok bin Cnoir one of the three individuals who have been accused by the .sfir “ the a. c *&gt; ~, v-.n • v-j + yhis is 'w h £• t hod ni ;ht of the murder \.it;h ihem ^ to he said and enquiries should he made by both of us. rot e hy r.' T . 'his is the irst reply of -helkh isa to t.e.J No. C/ HO of 1932 Th« Political Agency &amp; H.B.U'a Conaulata, Muscat the l( Peceaber 1932. To The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rush ire. UemoranduB. 1. In September last Said bin Khemis a elerk in the employ of the Muscat Government was murdered at Sib together with his wife. Trackers carried the tracks of the alleged murderers am- t to Khaudh and His Highness accordingly addressed Sheikh Isa bin |,| Salih to hand over the murderers for trial in accordance with the agreement of 1920 effected by Mr.Wingate between the Omani Sheikha and the Muscat Governafcnt. The Sheikh has uptil now merely addressed evasive replies to the Sultan, who informs roe that on your recent tour here he submitted the case to you lor your advice ts to inf course of action to be adopted. 2. His Highness has again represented the matter to me and is anxious to know your decision to enable him to take early action. 3 # The of the Sultan's conversation with me is as follows;- (i) Is the British Government going to keep the pei&lt;ee be tween the parties? ( i.e. presumably enforce the agree ment); (11) If not than HI. Highness wishes to be tree to take such action as he thinks fit without interference on our jsrt; (ill) If such action involves loss to a Brltish 6ub J ,,t h# cannot hold hisiself resyonsible./•'V 4. Should you consider it d«8ir«blt to int«rrtn« thtn I •m of tho opinion that a starn latter should i^gua to Shaikh Isa bin Salih from aither yoursalf or the Political &lt;A*ent ra- mindinc him of tha traaty obligations. 5» should t^iie be ineffective tha re-iradosition of a panel Zakat against tha offandars eould ba rasortad to. tfeantime tha handing over of any rafugeas from tha Omani Shaikhs would lapsa. 6. His Highness is of tha opinion that tha imposition of tha Zakat would certainly lead to trouble and raiding in tha Batinah, and ha appears to regard any such irtv* with trepidation. 7. In Y/ingate’s time the rusest Infantry had not bean estab lished but tha presence of troops probably had a sobering effect on tha truculent Omanis. Your fuller experience of local matters would enable you to decide whether the present force of Kuseat Infantry would be sufficient to deal alone with any trouble that might arise by Omanis raiding the Batinah, or other repercussions that might occur from the re-imposition of a penal zakat. 8. His Highness cannot at present indicate to me what line ha would adopt should he ba given a free hand. It is obvious that ha cannot be permitted to refute all responsibility should a British subject be involved through destruction of property or loss of life, but should tha individual^ trade ba affected than it should be merely regarded as ' the fortune of war n fof whieh no responsibility attaehes. I think it unlikely however that tha Omanis would deliberately harm any British subject lor fear of tha consequences. I would be grateful if you would communicate your views on the subject to n« at your earliest convenience to permit of Hi. Highness formulating his ,ro,osals. He is »ost anxious that th. matter should not hang fir. any longer, thereby encouraging th. Omanis to tha detriment of his own authority. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.I/’s Consul,Muscat.Letter dated 1st Shahan 1351 (30/11/32) frora S’aeikh Isa bin Saiih to H.B.F’s Consul, Muscat, ■a On the night of 20th Rajab (evening of 19/11/32) I received your esteemed letter of 28th October * r hich was in answer to Lay me of your communication to the Muscat Government and the reply received ijfcon them. The reply is not satisfactory because the received J^om them. The reply is not satisfactory because the (British) Government had arranged that a tax of 5 dollars should be collected in all ports on a 100 dollars and not on loads, / •f' There is nothing special ^importation of Omani goods at Sur and other places,This tax has recently been levied by the^Customs Official at Sur and I have already informed you ■ ’then it was started. You have pointed out that 0 l£ are collected on each load. That means that they have collected more than what was arranged because the nimiber of loads in each Bahar depends upon the strength and weakness of camels. Sometimes there are 6 and sometimes 7 or 8 loads in a Bahar. As to the .Bisr dates some of them kxxxxx are of no value and some of them are sold ati' loss. The best Bisr dates were sold this year at / 160 per Bahar and the inferior quality did not fetch any value. If this is the condition it is not understood why the tax is collected on loads* I await your favourable reply as the matter has been going on .for some time. Secondly the uali$of the Sultan are oppressing the people (of Oman) without any cause. One of the V.alis is Saiyid Hamad, oali of Matrah, to vhom I wrote as I did not -ant to bother you but he did not send me an answer. It is laid down in the Treaty that none (of Oman subjects) should undergo any penally unless his case is proved before the Shara. If there is anything due from anyone I have to order him to pay and they (Muscat Oovernme*#- Off icicle) have no authority over them. I wrote to the Consul at Bushire as my messengers ,r ho brought my letters to you returned without any reply and perhaps your v reply was received after a month or more. / n T J. E.No. C/3 of 1933. The Political Agency 8c Consulate, Muscat the 3rd January 1933. liT- &amp;) To The Hon’ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Busnire. Memorandum. m I enclose for your information the cojjy of a xetter recently received from Isa bin Salih al Harithi, together with the translation of the re^ly I propose issuing to him if approved by you. The case of the Sib murder has already been sub- ^ , | 'i ji mitted to you with His Highness 1 the Sultan’s representations thereon and a reply is awaited as to the course of action to be adopted. In the meanwhile I am verbally informed by His Highness that a further attempted murder has taken place at Sib, which he attributes entirely to delay and lack of action in the first instance. The constant addressing of frivilous letters of the type enclosed to the political Agent, Muscat, by Sheiich Isa is a growing annoyance, particularly when coupled with Isa’s own evasive line of action with the Sultan over the above quoted Sib case. I would be grateful, in the event of my present reply meeting with your approval, to receive telegraphic intimation of the same to avoid further delay. An indication of the general line of policy m dealing with the Omani question at the present time would be much appreciated./£3 To Oi? * tatxxiDUUX » uc ^^ Sheiich l*a bin Salin A.C i have received you letter dated *&amp;ttr understood its contents. \f\f&amp; £-yv{^/f£ 4oth T, ece...ue-r 1^32 and firstly you ata^e that the British Governsient had arrant ed that a tax of 5 dollars on every 100 dollars should be coxlected in porta. This statement ia \rtioUy incorrect and m order to refreah your memory i quote to you herewitn U,e tlrat olau »« treaty which ax'fecta th. collection of o% custom, tax on all Omani gooas eiiterint Muscat, iatrah, Sur and the coast towns. 'firstly. On all commodities brought irom Oman of ail To pretend to me that tills tax is either new or has teen increased is a waste of my Urns and your time. Oh Sheihh iya ana it is no profit to avoid the truth. fou also allege in your letter that the Wall of katrah ra oppressing Omanis, you do not state in what way or quote arijr Cf A se. You reier a^uin to the treaty and imply that it has been breached. In this connection I may invite your attention to the xact that the murderers of t-.o of His Highness’s subjects at oib in September last were definitely tracked to Khaudh. I cio not seem to have heard that, in accordance with the treat/ jto wiiich ^o u so ox ten refe r, they nave been ii&amp;nded over to tne Muscat Government. Until the Omanis fulfil tneir ^rt of the treaty I couio under no circumstances consider maxing any representatioi on their beiialf to tiie Kuscat Government nor is obligatory ior me to do so in any case. Finally i would point out to you that it is merely « waste oi time to send letters direct to the H Consul Bushire'3. uONFIDENTIAL. / n. .1°. n is No. 960-S. of 1932. British Besiaency ana Consulate-General, Bushire, 31st December 1932. To iii&lt; The Political Agent, Muscat. SUBJECT : MUS CAT - OiuAN I TREATY. l\raMr)RAlffiT T M . X pst5i Peference your meaioranaum No. C/210, aateu 20th December. Please see my Express letter No. 979-S, of today, to the Government of India, copy of which I enclose. g I will aooress you again when I receive a reply from Government. I quite appreciate the Sultan's feelings on the subject, but *hai we want, if possible, to avoid ary rupture between the Muscat State ana tne Omanis, which would only be to the detriment of both. The problem seems to be to hit upon some form of pressure which is well within the powers of His Highness to carry out, into which we will not be dragged, and which will oe strong enough to force Shaikh Isa to do something about the murderers and - at the same time - not irritant enough to raise serious trouble - as the imposition of a penal zakat woulo. ( This latter servec its purpose excellently when imposed by mi. Wingate, ana we may some occasion have recourse to it again, but I oo not think the present case is serious enough for such a step)2 C- - ■ /&lt;H 3 - Would stoppage of travel facilities for Omanis wishing to proceed to foreign parts have the aeeirea effect ? Those Omani travellers who haa no pass- -ports would be refusee them, ana those who naa won la be refusea visas by you. This would involve us to some, but comparatively small, extent. Please discuss this proposal with His Highness and let me have your views. Should he raise again the general question of our res- -ponsibility for the Treaty you shoula inform him that I have aadressea the Government of Inaia on the subject and will let him know when I hear fiom them. Lieut.Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. r&gt;0 . / • 3 3 Telegram (G.T.G.J From - Resident, Bushire* To - Political, Muscat. No. - 49. Dated and received 19th January 1933. Your memorandum No .C/3. (4 Government of India concur in view expressed in paragraph a of ray express letter No.979-S; please explain situation to Sultan.\T\) /-fi (5^ | Ho.C/16 of 1933. The Politico! Agency &amp; H.B.ll's Coneulat* Muscat, 21 st Janunry 1933. To Hie Highness Saiyid Said *in Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Highness, Ttfith reference to your Highness^ letter doted the 11 th November 1932 regard- ing the case of the murders at Sib and the evasive replies received by Your Highness from Sheikh Isa bin Salih in this connection# As verbally promised to Your Highness I referred the matter to the Hon’ble the Political Resident for his orders and instructions# I have now received a telegraphic reply from the Resident on the subject, the purport of which 1 hasten to convey to Your Highness as follows (1) When the original agreement was drawn up An 1923 between the Muscat Government on the one hand and the Omani Sheikhs on the other, Mr# Wingate (the then Political Agent) merely acted as a mediator between the parties# (2) The Gove nment of India therefore have no responsibility in enforcing the agreement on either party, though of course they are prepared to give their 'good offices', as far os the efforts of their Officers in the Gulf are concerned, in keeping the peace between the parties. At the same time I am to 8emphasise the fact that the Government ' of India cannot view with equanimity any possibility ©f the loss of life, property or trade of any British subject in consequence of any steps Your Highness may take against the Omanis. The foregoing I think clears the situation. I should be most grateful if Your Highness would keep fcfc me informed of any steps you may propose to take. Should Your Highness require ray 'good offices’* in the matter or if my consulta tion would be of use to you, I trust Your Highness will not hesitate to inform me. Your Highness's sincere friend. Major Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul,Muscat.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dei-autment. EXPRESS LETTER (N, C, This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to swe tclcyraphie. expense ana undue use of the wires, but intended to be IrealJ, on receipt, mth the same expedition as if it hud been tdearmM. To saie. time and formalities U is viorded a„d siy, al us if it hud been so desj)atoned.] nV' i From Political Resident, Bushire. To FOREIG N, New Delhi. tf&lt;&gt;t 979-S of 19 32. Hated 31st Deceraber jg* 2. SUBJECT:- Muscat Omani Treaty. jo &gt;5? Please refer to Mr.^ingste’s letter No.2052 of 14th October 1920 to the Deputy Political Resident, Bushire, copy of which was sent direc t o the Deputy Secretary to the government of India,Foreign and Political Department* 2. On the abdication of the late Sultan of Muscat and the accession of the present one last January, the latter was of the opinion that the above Treaty, originally madebetween the late Sultan and the Omani Shaikhs, would need renewal, and some correspondence passed on the subject between myself -as Political Agent, Muscat - and the late Sir Hugh Biscoe. Both parties apparently desired a renewal and it was finally decided that we 6.4 DC K l* - ll'&gt;7d&amp; t—(G*1‘&lt;J54)—24-5-31—4,00,000. should . . . .should stand aloof and let things take their course 3* No actual steps have been taken towards a renewal, but both parties, the present Sultan and the Omani Shaikhs, headed by Shaikh Isa bin Saleh, apparently regard the Treaty as still binding on them. 4. An incident has occurred of the murder of a Muscat State employee, in Muscat territory, the murderers being alleged by the Muscat State - on the evidence of local trackers, etc - to belong to an Omani village. The Sultan has addressed Shaikh Isa to hand over the murderers in accordance with the Agreement of 1920 effected by Mr. Wingate, but the Shaikh returns evasive replies. &lt; Be does not contend that the Treaty no longer exists, which confirms my impression ( para graph 3 above) that he regards it as still having force. ) 5. The following are extracts from a Memorandum received from the Political Agent, Muscat, on the subject. 3. The gist of the Sultan’s conversation with me is as follows. ( i) Is the British Government going to keep the peace between the parties ? ( i.e.presumably enforce the pgreement); (ii) If not then His Hi^iness wishes to be free to teke such action as he thinks fit without interference on our part; (iii) If such action involves loss to a British subject he cannot hold himself respons ible ♦ &gt;vX X X X X XXX X n w n M * « n « i* ii n n n n ii n ii n 8. His Highness cannot at present indicate to ine what line he would adept should he be given a free hand. It is obvious that he cannot be permitted to refute all responsibility should a British subject be involved through destruction of property or loss of life, but should the individual’s trade be affected then it should be merely regarded as M the fortune of war* 1 for which no responsibility attaches. I think it unlikely however that the Omanis would deliberately harm any British subject for fear of the consequences. I would be grateful if you would communicate your views on the subject to me at your earliest convenience to permit of His Highness formulating his proposals. He is most anxious that the matter should not hang fire ar^y longer, thereby encouraging the Omanis to the detriment of his own authority'. 6. In any advice which I may tender to His Highness I shall of coursebe most careful to emphasise that he cannot divest himself of responsibility for British lives or trade in any action that he may take. Before replying to him, however, I would be grateful for a confirmation by telegram that the Government of India concur in my views of our responsibility as to the Treaty, i.e. that Mr. Wingate was merely a mediator between the Sultan and the Omanis, and that the Government of India therefore have no responsibility in enforcing it on either party, though•f course they are prepared to gire their 'go &gt;d offices”, as far as the efforts of their officials in the Gulf are concerned, in keeping the peace between the parties. I do not propose to publish these views for the information of the Omanis, but I think they should be explained to the Sultan. Lt .-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. attestbd. JoCroning, Undsr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.R 40 * Telegram From To tq hM A GoTernment of Indie,Foreign and Political department, Wew Delhi* Political resident, at Kuwait. Ho. 142* Dated and received loth January 19 33* 979-3 of 1932* Your Express letter of 31st December 1932, MUSCAT-OMANI TRBATY* No* 2. Government of India concur in your views as expressed in paragraph 6 of letter* In this connection joai attention is invited to paragraph 5 of letters addressed to Sultan of Muscat and Shaikhs of Oman copies received y under Muscat endorsements of 17th November 1919, Nos* 117-C and 11JB-C. il/s - FOREIGN - for Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, information* / Muscat, By Order* Secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Uulf. &amp;’&gt;/,Jslo.ao-S of 1933. y i&gt;7 /^5 &gt; 7 . /'31&gt; Britisii Keaidency &amp; Consulate-General, BushiEe, tne I9tn January 1933. To The Political Agent, KUSCAT. SUBJECT; Muscat.Omani Treaty. Memorandum. h ^ My telegram Ho.49 of 19th January 1933. 2 # As you will see, Government agree with my views that we are not responsible for enforcing the terms of the Muscat- Omani Treaty, but are of course willing to give our good offices to keep the peace between both parties. There is, however, as I intimated to Government, ^paragraph 6 of my Express letter Ko.979-S, dated the 31st December 1932), no ,need to publish these views for the information of the Omanis, who may be more likely to abide by the treaty if they imagine that His Majesty’s Government is responsible for enforcing it. 3. You have doubtless already explained to His Highness that Government agree with me that he cannot divest himself of responsibility for British lives or property in any action he takes. His responsibility for indirect loss to trade is, of course, leas, but in the present condition of the State it would of course be most unwise for him to adopt any course which would interfere seriously with what little trade the State has left. 4.I /)• j? - /s ^ - 2 - l?s' 4 # As I stated in my Memorandum x*o.980-S of 31st December 1932 I quite appreciate the Sultan’s feelings in the matter, but my general Yiews are as stated in paragraph 2 of that Memorandum. We are prepared to support the Sultan on the coast, and have in fact done so as at Sur, but with regard to the Interior he must stand on his own legs. In paragraph 3 of my Memorandum quoted above I made a suggestion by which pressure might be brought on Omanis. loujwill doubtless let me know in due course what are your views, and those of his Hi^iness. Whatever action the latter takes, however, in this or any other direction, the responsibility is his not ours. If this is made clear to His Highness he is much less likely to involve himself in difficulties in the hope that we will pull him out of them if things go wrong* “T- c Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 136-3 of 1935. / ~N ] W.M Si - A '-&gt; l y-f iyp The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Jelhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s^. 2. Bubhire letter &amp;0.98C-3 of 51at Jecemter 1932 conveyed Government of^India' § concurrence gram iIo B ^h T&amp;BkMpv'' anu{ ‘ ri 1J ' 53 * . \ and Consulate-General, urrence as contained in their tele- v Sv * ,cP XCO 1 C w-J i Jr - BUBHIRE. Dated... •y-efcruary --lyiSi. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. itemorandum Uo.C/23 of 30th MUSCAT-OMANI January 1933 from the TRSA i. Political Agent, Muscat. Copy forwarded to whe for information• J Political Agent, Muscat, ? &amp; ‘ ■Ko.(? 9/ of 1933. The Political Agency &amp; Consulate. Muscat, 2^ ^March 1933. To His highness Saiyid ^aid bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that your letter dated the 25th Dhil Qadeh 1351 (22nd March 1933) regard ing the murders at ^ib was received by ra y predecessor on the same night, on the eve of his depdarture on leave. Major Bremner has left a note to the effect that he confirms the points set forth in paraal and 2 of Your Highness f £ letter. Your highness’s sincere friend, Captain, politicol /gent &amp; H.B.B’e Coneul.Busct.Confidential. \W f Ho.c/ t of 1933. The Politlcol /genoy &amp; Consulote. Mueoot, 22nd April 1933. To The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Muscat-Qmon Treaty. Memorandum. Reference this office memorandum Uo.c/28 doted 30th Jonuory 1933 and previous correspondence. 2. Lost Wednesday T hod a visit from Gheiich Muhammad bin Isa, elder son of Sheikh Isa bin Salih al Horithi, Sheikh of Oman. He brought with him o letter from his father addressed to me saying that his son would discuss with me the question of the alleged unfair Customs duty at Sur on Omani dates coming from the interior. 3 . Sheikh Muhammad iramediotely began by saying that our lost reply to Sheikh Isa on this question (vide my memo.No. 1214 doted 1st November 1932) was unsatisfactory and he asked what we intended to do towards setting this matter right according to the Treaty of Sib between Muscat and Oman. 4 # He also produced a letter from Mr. Wingate in proof of a contention of his that the Muscat °tate was charging higher passport fees than they hove o right to do. 5 # i n reply to these complaints I told him that this /gency * 08 not intereeted in heilch Ibo'b complaints, that the treaty was between the Sheikhsof Oman headed by Sheikh Iso and the sultan of Muscat, fnd that both parties should settle such questions amicably between themselves. 6&gt; i clso drew his attention to the fact that two outrages hove recently occurred at Sib in which the suspects in each cose have absconded to Oman. Sheikh Iso^in spite ofRepeatedly addressed by the State,has persisted in returning evasive replies and made no attempt to arrest the suspects and send themto Muscat for trial. I told him that if Sheikh Isa would deal with the State in a proper spirit of co-operation the State would doubtless be prepared to render him assistance in such matters as Sur Customs, etc. 7. T told him to inform his father of the foregoing conversation and to tell him that it is not the least use coming to the Political Agent with such complaints when no attempt has been mode to render co-operation to the State in such matters, for example, os the Sib murders. 8 . Sheikh Muhammad has proceeded to Bombay for medical treatment and he promised that on his return he would repeat the above conversation to his father. Captain, Political Agent &amp; H.B.lTu Consul, Muscat.COMFID INITIAL &gt;* From To Dir, No.C/ 1^0 0 f 1934. Political Agency &amp; H. B. M's Consulate, Muscat, 4th Duly 1934. Major D. £. D. Bremncr, M.C., Political Agent 6c Consul, Muscat. The ^n'ble the Political -^esiaent in the Persian ^ulf, ^ushire. Subjects* Omani Affairs. I have the honour to report that on 19th ultimo Sheikh Mohammad bin Isa bin Salih el Harithi, deputed by hie father, paid a visit to Muscat, where he w*s the guest of $iis highness the Sultan. 2. The ostensible object of the visit was to settle certain outstanding cases between Muscat and '-wan, (in cluding the case of the Sib murder reported in my letter ho.210 dated 20th December 1932), and to make representa tions regarding the alleged excessive import duties collected at Sur by the Muscat authorities. 3. Since the Sib murder of 1932 certain other murders have apparently taken place in Unan, the murderers taking refuge in Muscat territory, as the responsible Omani authorities had adopted an evasive and unsatisfactory attitude with regard to the Muscat representations, so the Muscat Government have hitherto declined to take action on Omani claims. The latter being in a preponderance the snoe has now begun to pinch the Omani corn, and hence the pre sent deputation. 4 , sheikh ^ohammad presented his cases with consum mate and tortuous skill, but the ripostes ol uit Highness in each case proved too much for him. Having lost the first round, he endeavoured to digup cases dating back in some instances fifteen years# The Sultan however flatly declined to entertain any such claims stating that they should have been presented at the time by the responsible Sheikhs, and that the only case of which he was prepared to take cognizance were those that had occurred in his own reign. 5. Sheikh ^hammad then referred to the alleged grievan ces of Omanis arising out of excessive collections at sur on imported Omani produce, his highness on examination of his records found that recoveries had in fact been collected in excess of the 5* stipulated in the Treaty. Whilst informing Sheikh Mohammad 'that in view of the fall in prices and out of personal regard for him, he haci issued orders ior a tem porary reduction of the amounts to be collected , His high ness has issued instructions to rectify the mistake. q* somewhat amusing to note that in his letter ox greeting to the sultan, Sheikh Isa stated tnat he was sending his son to deal direct with nis highness on certain matters 'a we do not want any intermediary between us”, Uhe intermediary being the british). Inspite of this fact oheikh moharnmad was also armed with a polite letter from his father to me asking me to arbitrate in any matters that his son might not be aole to get settled i This letter sheikh ^ohamnad presented to me when he eventually decided to call at the agency on his last ua* in Muscat. 7 . The main point of interest however would appear to He in the fact that the Omani continues to regard the treaty as binding and unaffected in anyway Oy a change of Eulers in Muscat* Sheikh Mohammad, in his conversations with the Sultan, continually referred to the “present existing treaty', in face of this it would oe untenable, if at any future date the Omani pleads the lapse of the treaty due to a chang. of . hulers in Muscat. 8. Finally I ««nl&lt;l &lt;•■&gt;*&lt;■ a*°**° M visit, His Hlgnnsss t» aultan -o.t panatllU.n.ly t.pt .. informed of the trend of the conversations and, in the guise-3- Qtn of aeaking my advice, readily told me of his proposed line of action in each case* X have the honour* to be, Sir, four most obedient servant, kaj or, Political /igent &amp; H*B.M f s Consul, kuscat. ASH • /Xo. 656-3 of 1934. CONFIDENTIAL. cl The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The foreign secretary to the Government of India, Si mla • and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (y). British Consulate-General, BITSHIRE. Reference to previous correspondence: „k.«nr&amp;i?v Residency Printed Letter No. 136-S of 1933, dated i4th February 1933* Letter No. C/lSO. dated 4th July 1934 from the Political agent, la-uscat usoat Omani Afxairs#</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000027_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/264</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000027</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/264</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/67 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: MUSCAT – OMAN TREATY.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1920/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-26T22:09:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (154 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 156; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This volume concerns relations between the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the tribes of interior Oman. The volume contains multiple copies of notes produced in October 1920 by the Political Agent and Consul at Muscat, providing a British perspective on the history of political affairs in Muscat and Oman from the late 18th century to the present day (ff 6-22, ff 49-53 and ff 56-60). The notes attempt to summarise the underlying causes of the tense relations between the Sultan and the Omani tribes, before going on to document events during the period October 1919-October 1920, which culminated with the re-establishment of peaceful relations, following the conclusion of an agreement between the two parties (the Treaty of Sib, concluded on 25 September 1920). Related items include multiple copies of the English text of the 1920 agreement (ff 23-26, ff 53-55, and ff 60-62), and a Photostat copy of the Arabic text of the concluding part of the Treaty (f 154).The volume also documents the Sultan's relations with the Omani tribes in the years following the treaty. There is a series of letters written in 1924 between the Political Agent and Shaikh Isa bin Saleh [Shaikh ‘Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārthī], who makes a request to import ammunition and protests against taxes that he claims contravene the Treaty of Sib. The correspondence dated 1932-1934 largely concerns the murder of a Muscat Government clerk at Sib, and the Sultan's frustration with the evasive response of Shaikh Isa bin Saleh on the matter. Also discussed in this part of the volume is the question of whether the Treaty of Sib will be renewed.In addition to the treaty text mentioned above, the Arabic language material mainly consists of correspondence between the British and Muscat authorities and various shaikhs and subjects of interior Oman (English translations are included).The volume includes copies of correspondence originally written in 1919. There is no material covering the periods 1922-1923, 1925-1931, and no material dated after 1934, with the exception of a note at the rear of the volume, which is dated 16 October 1961.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārithī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Treaty of Sīb (1920)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Homicide</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000027#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>