<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00031c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:13:47.837Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">— -./ 140. Cb-l*vK}. f To The foiltical —thr' 2 Wi-IOI tOOOTJ jf IT GEJBRAL c: , l j i Dieted the I%S' (T ^ . M I't h‘ u'i Subjects* iie ittauco facilities in India - statistics. . Sip; 1 hove tl® honour to forward herewith a oopy of letter rto.C..j*R#2h77/ 421(l)-40 dated 31.8.40 (together with its eoclosure) from tlie Chief Accountant, xtcoerve Bank of India, Central office, Bombay, to the Auditor oeueral of India. It is requested that the Statistics of the various forms of re ittaoces under t)® scheme for the two half years ending knrch &amp; Sept, may be punctually subidtted to the Currency Officers ootioerned early in April &amp; October as required therein. A© the infomation is of considerable importance both to uovertleat &amp; Uhaaercial bodies the due dates for submission of the statistics should be strictly observed. ’ I have the honour to be. fir, Your most obedient servant, * ^ ^ ^ (B»C» Gruha.) ^ ^ Assistant Accountant General. &lt; opyof letter ho.U)^H.a)77/43lU)-40,dated 31.8.1940 from the Chief Accountant, Reserve Bank of India, Central Office,Bombay, to the Auditor General of India. J ’ Remittance facilities in India and Jurma - Statistics. To enable the Reserve Bank to review the rates char ed for the various classes of remittaaces in tl® new ochec® of remittance facilities which will co t e into force as from the 1st October 1.40 and to consider t ® roone for a further amendment of the rates we require, in a form enclosed herewith, statistics regarding tl® various forms of remittances. The Imperial Bank have agreed to furnish the r®cessary infon^ation in respect of remittacce transactions at t'ieir offices and brand® s to our Central Accounts feet ion. e shall be obliged if you will kindly advise the Accountants General and Comptrollers/accountant General, Burma, to instruct the Treasury Officers in tl®ir/Uis jurisdiction to supply the relevant inforuation in respect of all re aittauce transactions at tf® Indur Treasury as well as the • ub-Treasuries of which the trnnstictions are incorporated in the Treasury accounts, half* yearly in the enclosed farm, direct* to the Currency Officer in whose circle the iroasury is situated/hangoon. These statements for the two half vears ending I arch and September may be forwarded to the uarreocy Offioersytisi’ency Officer by Treasury Officers along with the cash bal ace reports for the m^ths of *i£*rch ana September each year. 3. Tp Currency Offlcere/Curreocy officer a Q receipt of ti® statements from the treasuries in their circles/liis circle will consolidate the figures of all the ireaauries Uncluding fub-Treasuries) and advis® the totals to tl® hanager, Rerervc Bank of India, Central Accounts Section, Calcutta.Y a NO. AS?* -4/47 To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN The October, 19-44. The Currency Officer Reserve Bank of India Icbue department Bombay M i^ORAITDUM . The Return ,in respect of Resex^ve Bank of India Drafts issued during half year enatd the 30th . September, 1944 is blank. 'C ' c ' ' u • for Political Agent,Bahrain.fiS I NO* 4/47 To POLITICAL AGiiNCY, BAHRAIN, I OlC April, 1945. The Currency Officer, Reserve Bank of India, Issue Departuent, Bombay * &amp; Memorandum f The return in respect of Reserve Bank of India Drafts issued during naif year ended 3lst March, 1945, is _ N-Ji _ °(- L ' ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain,NO. )+£'*&gt; I- 4/47 POLITICAL AlLiNCY, BAHRAIN, ((jKvOctQbcr, 1945. To The Currency Officer, Reserve Bank of India, Issue Department, BOMBAY* The retain In respect of Reserve Bank of India Drafts issued during half year ended the 30th September, 1945, is- nil-. for Political Agent, Bahrain.NO. 13.8(7 -4/47 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 24th April, 1946. To The Currency Officer, Reserve Bank of India, Issue Department, BOilBAY. Memorandum : The return in respect of Reserve Bank of India Drafts issued during the half year ended the 31st March, 1946, is nil. £ for Political Agent, Bahrain. TPNO. 2&gt; 3 YD — 4/47 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, /J fL-October, 1946 To The Currency Officer, Reserve Bank of India, Issue Department, BOiuBAY. liEiJORANDILi: - The return in respect of Reserve Bank of India Drafts issued during half year ended the 30th September, 1946, is nil. Captain for Political Agent, Uu^cr / oJlahrain.NO. \ o % ^ -4/47 POLITICAL AGENCY. BAHRAIN ‘cYR. April, 1947. The Currency Officer, Reserve Rank of Indla^ issue Oepartraent, ^omhay. MMORANDUM :. The return in respect of Reserve Bank of India Drafts issued during the half year ended the 31st Lflarch ? 1947* is nil* Bahrain. 7 *No. -4/47 To The Currency Officer, Reserve Bank of India, Issue Department, Bombay. © 1 M POLITICAL AGENCY, u BAHRAIN. fhe M^October, 1947&lt; MEMORANDlIi . The return in respect of the Reserve Bank of India Drafts issued by *±x this office during the half year ended on the 30th September, 1947 is nil* 0 /{ . L Political Agent, Bahrain. f — llxT KW</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00031c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1157</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00031c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1157</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/47 Reserve Bank of India Remittance Statistics.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-11T21:18:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (14 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 16; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-15; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains circular letters of instructions from the Office of the Accountant General, Central Revenues (AGCR), New Delhi requesting the submission of half-yearly statements of remittance statistics to the Reserve Bank of India; and copies of statements sent by the Political Agency, Bahrain to the Reserve Bank of India, for the period 1941 and 1944-47.The earliest document in the file is a copy of letter dated 31 August 1940, quoted in a circular letter from the AGCR on folio 6.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Reserve Bank of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Accountant-General, Central Revenues</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00031c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>