<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000064_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:31:13.830Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000064_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/143, ff 362-364</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000064</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/143, ff 362-364</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter no. 160 of 1854 from Captain Arnold Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Henry Anderson, Secretary to the Government of Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1854/1854</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T00:18:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter and its enclosures relate to the case of two slaves recently sold at Lingah [Bandar-e Lengeh] to Indian subjects, and arrangements for their transfer to the Presidency in Bombay. There are two enclosures to Kemball’s letter:1. Letter no.142 of 1854 (folio 363) from Captain Arnold Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Commodore George Robinson, Commanding Officer Persian Gulf Squadron, dated 11 April 1854. The original letter enclosed an account (not included in the file) from the man who delivered the two slaves to Robinson. Kemball also gives details of the individual identified as having sold the slaves, and requests that Robinson assist the Persian Slave Trade Commissioner, Meerza Mahmood Khan, in helping find the individual and retrieve financial penalty from him.2. Letter no.159 of 1854 (folio 364) from Kemball to Robinson, dated 4 May 1854. Kemball writes that the two slaves have been handed over to him by Meerza Mahmood Khan, and that he sees no reason to forego the exaction of the financial penalty from the individual who sold the two children.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051557.0x000064#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>