<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ba_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T02:35:49.490Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">.&gt;.o^ PHOTOCOPYING NOT FOR DIRECT ORDERED FROM COPIES i ?silX . [Confidential.] No. 2220, dated „ 8hiraz ' the gth - (received 22nd) October 1907. ’ Bush ire, the 13 th From— Major P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To— Sir Louis W. Dane, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In view of the allusions to the Slave Trade Question in the course of the , , „ , o j . m correspondence connected with negocia- (i) From Political Agent, Koweit, to Resident, Nos. . r rr • r u ° 375 and 282, dated the 8th and loth June iqo;. tlOOS proceeding at KOWClt, 1 have the K0Weit ' N °' honour to forward, for the information of (3) From Political Agent, Koweit, to Resident, No. Government of India, copies of the 374, dated the 14th July 1 go7. • 11 ^ J ( 4 ) From Resident to Political Agent, Koweit, No. recent correspondence marginally noted ,960, dated the 8th September 1907. in Connection with the qUCStLOU of slave manumission at that port. 2. I shall be glad to know whether pending any special understanding with Sheikh Mubarek which may prove practicable at some future time, the lines of procedure indicated by me for the guidance of the Political Agent may stand, or whether the Government of India desire any modification thereof. Copy of a letter No. 275, dated the 8th June 1907, from the Political Agent, Koweit) to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) Bushire. I have the honour to forward, herewith, copies of statement and notes re corded by me in the case of an Abyssinian slave named Abdulla, and to request that you will be so good as to grant him the usual manumission certificate on his arrival at Bushire. 2. Abdulla has been made over to the Commander, H.M.S. “ Lapwing, ” with the request that he will hand him over to the Residency, Bushire. Statement. Abdulla, Abyssinian by race, a man of about 30 years of age, appeared in the Agency this morning and states that he is in the house of Abdulaziz bin Fahad who lives near Haji Muhammad Ali Marafi. He has been with him three years and has been married to a female slave of his, by whom he has a son. He was, according to his own statement, stolen away from Abyssinia and brought to Jedda, Mecca, and overland here. Last year, the French Consul at Berbera set him free and his manumission paper is at Berbera. His master persuaded him to return on a false promise made to him that he should be a free man and allowed to work for his wife and child. As soon as he reached Koweit, his master claimed him again as a slave and now proposes to sell him. He asks my assistance to help him out of Koweit, proposes to leave Koweit altogether, abandoning his wife and child and to go to Berbera where he has a sister and other relatives. S. G. KNOK, Major, 8th June 1907. Political Agent, Koweit, Note, Abdulaziz bin Fahad, an old man of about 60 years of age, came at once in reply to my summons. I read over to him the statement of Abdulla. He said that the statement regarding the French Consul was a lie, but that Abdulla s statement was otherwise true in the main, so far as it went. He added, however, that the man had been a trusted servant who had proved dishonest and that he had told him this morning that he did not want him any longer. I said, that it seemed that nothing more now seemed to be required, as both parties desired a parting. Abdulaziz replied that the only thing seemed to be that the man should divorce his wife. This Abdulla agreed to do and in my presence and in that of the following witnesses : Abdur Rahman bin Buti, Furaj, and Awayd,Chaprassis, appointed Abdulaziz bin Fahad, his master, his agent for the purpose. Through the case, Abdulaziz behaved with the utmost moderation and even liberality. He pointed out what was perfectly true that his slave was better dressed than himself. Order. The above compromise was arrived at without the slightest pressure on either side. Abdulla will be conveyed to-day to H.M.S. “ Lapwing ” and the Commander requested officially by letter to give him a passage to Bushire. A letter should also be sent to the Resident, Bushire, praying that he will grant the usual manumission certificate. Abdulla states that if he can be taken out of this place, he will find his own way to Berbera. Copies of these statements to accompany letters to Political Resident. Copy of a letter No. 282, dated the 10th June 1 goJ, from the Political Agent^ Koweit, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire. With reference to my letter No. 27^, dated the 8th June 1907, in the case of slave Abdulla, I have the honour to state that this morning, the slave informed me that he did not want to leave Koweit until the Autumn, when he would sail in one of the trading buggalows. 2. I told him that he stopped here in peril of being interfered with, and that he must not come and complain to me as he had been given a fair chance of obtaining his liberty. 3. I have now the honour to request that, if you see fit, the usual manu mission paper may be sent to me. A descriptive roll of Abdulla is forwarded herewith. Description of slave Abdulla for entry in manumission paper. Abdulla, son of Age • •• ... 30 years. Occupation ... • • • Servant of Abdulaziz bin Fahad. Birth place ... Abyssinia. Religion ... ... ... Islam, Sunni. Complexion ... Dark brown. Height ... ... • • e Six feet. Inhabitant of ... ... Abyssinia. Quarter ... ... ... Berbera. S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agents Koweit. Copy of a letter No. iggo, dated 26th June igoj, from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to the Political Agent, Koweit. § I have the honour to refer to your letters Nos. 275 and 282, dated 8th and 10th instant, respectively, regarding the case of the negro Abdulla. 2. It is always the custom to refer to the territorial authorities at all events pro forma, in connection with the manumission of. slaves, and I think Sheikh Mubarck will inevitably resent your summoning subjects of his to your presenceand disposing of such cases without consulting him, as would appear to have been the course followed in this instance. The Abyssinian in question does not complain of ill-treatment and appears to have been dishonest, and to have no serious fear of coming to harm, or he would not for his own convenience elect to remain several months in Koweit. In such circumstances I think the case will be met by the slave receiving a manumission paper on arrival here and on his undertaking not to return to Koweit. I notice that one previous case is on record which was disposed of by Captain Trevor in my absence {vide this office letter No. 1816, dated 3rd Decem ber 1905), and in which a manumission certificate was sent for the wife of one of your Consular servants ; but that case was hardly on all fours with this and the general question is one in regard to which you should proceed with considerable caution and in consultation with the Sheikh, who, it must be remembered, has at present no Slave Trade Treaty with us. Copy of a letter No. 274 \ dated 14th July igof, from the Political Agent, Koweit, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 1390, dated 26th June 1907, in the case of the negro Abdulla. 2. This case has now settled itself, for the negro has, of his own free will, returned to his master who seems to be a humane man and will, I have small doubt, treat him well. 3. I have been somewhat reluctant to refer slave cases to Sheikh Mubarek ever since my Chuprassi, who was waiting outside, informed me that in one case where I personally took a slave, who had been freed by the Basra Turkish authorities and then again kidnapped and brought to Koweit, before Sheikh Mubarek, the Sheikh’s servants spent the time occupied by the interview in speculating whether the slave would be put to death or merely flogged and imprisoned. In no case that I have referred to the Sheikh have I ever seen the slave a second time or been able to discover what has become of him. 4. In these circumstances, it would perhaps be as well to refer all refugee slaves direct to the Sheikh and leave them free to follow the advice given at their discretion. I would solicit the favour of instructions as to whether this course of action commends itself to you. Copy of a letter No. ig6o, dated the 8th September igof* from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to the Political Agent, Koweit. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. 374, dated 14th July 1907, and note that the negro Abdulla no longer desires a manumission certificate. 2. Seeing that the position was that stated in paragraph 3 of your letter the details should have been reported at the time and would have been referred to Government. As it is there is no material on which I could ask Government to base instructions. Meanwhile the course which commends itself to me is that until our relations with the Sheikh are on a more definite footing you should discourage negroes from taking bast with you as far as practicable ; but that when they do you should warn the Sheikh of the fact, ask him to enquire into the case and admit the presence of yourself or your representative at the joint hearing, and if the case is obviously one of real slavery and cruelty ask him to acquiesce in the issue of manumission certificate. If he does not prove amenable to your influence and explanations in the matter, then you should report the case in detail and I will refer it for the orders of the Government. G. C. B. P., Simla.—No. C.*5i6 F. D.—7-11-07.—14 J* D./ / ✓ V' of 1 ^ 07 * 3/( ' h ': % Office of t.he Political Agent,.loweit. P D- Vi. ■ Aoweit-3 ‘’'overaber 1007. A ( To Sir, Major S...^nox, I.A., Political Agent, .lo we it. Major P.z-.Oox,C.I.jii., Political KeBident in the Persian Crulf, iiushire. I have the honour to report, for your information and record,that a slave named Paraj bin SaTd,holder of a manumission certificate from the Political Agent,Bahrein,dated the 19th May 190 7 , appeared before me on the 27th ultimo and complain- ~ed that his master,Mhalifa uz ^aidi,had emuced him here on the promise of a wife and that on the very day when he got him to .loweit,he attempted to sell him at the shop of the dallal,Mawash. £ # On nhe evening of the 23th the matter was represented to Sheilih Tabir who said that he would mahe enruiries iniiO the case and that, ii the slave’s account was true and he had been the property of a Bahrein subject and freed in Bahrein no one in Koweit would be allowed to molest him or sell him.But that if he was the property of a Moweit subject,the Sheihh contended,that the Poll- -tical Agent,Bahrein,had no right to free him. I replied that,in that case,it would be necessary for me to put the case up to the - re sident, Bushire, for orders and that I hoped that the Sheikh would issue such orders as would avoidopening up a thorny and difficult question. In the meantime the slave was allowed to remain at the Agency for o days and fed at the expense of Government. on the evening of the ?Oth, informed me that he had made enruiries into the case and found that the slave was from Bahrein and of t^ ^ahrein owners; that he had told them that they had no right to bring and sell in Kuweit slaves bearing manumission papers from the Political A gent,Bahrein,and that he had given orders that the slave was to be allow ed to go free and that no one was to sell him. 5. The slave was informed accordingly and allowed to leave the Agency premises. 6. On the morning of the 1st ' ovember, I passed the slave in the bazaar.lt is with some satisfaction that I note that he seemed perfectly satisfied with himself which goes far to show that Sheilfh Tabir has really acted up to his promise. I 4 Sheikh -Tabir,at his interview with me I have the honour to be. Sir our most obedient servant. Political Agent,Aoweit. ///^ yTo, Major P. Z. Cox, C*I.E*, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, iJushire. Sir, I have the honour to forward hereWth (in ori- -ginal) an application from the Residency Agent, Lingah, for the grant of a manumission certificate to a slave be- -longing to a Koweiti. 2. In the absence of instructions as to the pro- -cedure to be followed in manumitting slaves owned by subjects of Sheikh Mubarek, I have the honour to request that you will issue the necessary certificate and forward it direct to the Residency Agent, Lingah. 3. I shall be grateful for instructions as to how to deal with such applications in the future. ! I have the honour to be. Sir, Tour most obedient servant. (yri \'-v' Lieutenant, H.L.M's Consul and Assistant Resident, Lunder Abbas.7 f © From Th« Asaistant Secretary to the Government of India in tha Foreign Department, To Major ? # 2* Cox, C.I.E., politioal Hesidont in the Persian Gulf Bus hire. Sir I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letta* Fo. 2220, dated 13th October 1907, forwarding, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of certain correspondence with the Politioal Agent at Eoweit on the subject of slave manumission at that port. 2. The Government of India approve generally the spirit of your instructions to the Political Agent. But einoe slaves in Eoweit territory are the/Sheikh, and since no agreement exists regarding such slaves. Political Agent no jurisdiction over them. Moreover runaway slaves who take refuge at other residencies and agencies in t?he Persian Gulf are manumitted only the fact of their taking refuge in the Agency gives the when ^when the slave agreements apply to them as is shown fcy the fact that at Bahrein and on the Arab Coast slaves who were born in slavery or who were imported prior to the execution of the slave agreements with the Sheikhs, are returned to their masters, vide paragraph 3 of Colonel Headed letter No. 31, dated £6th April 1898. The Government of India consider, therefore, that all slaves taking refuge at the Eoweit Agency should be returned to their masters through the Shoikh of Koweit, who might be asked to ascertain the facts in each case in the presence of an Agent from the Agency, and in the event of ill-treatment being proved, to take steps to prevent this in the future. The Sheikh might at the same time be infomed of the general policy of the British Government about slavery and if you see no objection requested politely to discountenance the acquisition of new slaves or any action which might compel the British Government to depart from their present desire to interfere as little as possible with him in the matter. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Assistant Secretary to the Government of India.jTo: SfZ of 1^07. Political Agency Captain F.B.Pri&amp;eaux Political Agent, Bahrain To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Sir, I have the honour to enclose for your information a copy of a letter with accompaniments which I have address ed to the Political Agent, Kowait, on the subject of a manumitted slave named Faraj bin Said whom a former owner has recently abducted from Bahrain and endeavoured to sell again into servitude at Kowait, 2. Major Knox in his communication to me suggested that I should take some steps if possible to have the Bahra owner who had tried to nullify the Manumission order pimished, but apparently he was not aware that this owner was the wife of the Kowait subject who actually enticed the negro out of Bahrain, ^• I trust that the opinions expressed in my letter to Major Knox will meet with your concurrence and approval. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Political Agent, Bahrain,No: SJ/of 1907. ir'olitiaal Agency Bahrain, ^ ^ Hovujaner 1907. ’ron. Captain ^.B.Briitaux Bnlitioal A^ent, Bahrain. To, Bolitioal Arc-nt Ko^ralt. I have the honour to acknowl^lge the receipt of your iorseuent To: 686 iate i the 9n t Noveiaber 1907 on the aubiect of the mniuoitted slave Tara,1 bin Said. statement made by the refugee nerro in my office, and of nC'* subsequent order paased then mamviitting him in the presence of a servant of the Chief of Bahrain. most unwise to tfarst himself back in Kovrait, but he seems to have been deceived by the cajolements of the 1aiy Becza and her husband together. you find it inconvenient yourself to oress the Thief of with me in thinking that it win p e undesirable that T should institute proceedings with the Chief of uahrain against the lady here which will I suppose affect her husband's pocket in Kowait* I susnect moreover that the mere confirmation of the negro's freedom by the Kowait authorities 'rill be regarded as a severe punishment by the narrow-minded quoniaa master of Farad bin Said. _ slaves imported from Kowait, it has for marc, years oast e I attach for your information copies of the In. the circttistanoes of the case the nerrro was 4. If therefore both the latter oersons are equally to blame, and if for special reasons of a political nature tith record to the general question of manumitting// been re^o^i^ecl hy x.he 'Thiel of Bahrain that* the Treaty Tiip^Teaent of 1356 prantinp fr*.eioia to all slaves brought 9 • 1 roa any T^iart^er whatsoever 11 into Bahrain territory applies not only to raw slo.ves but to all those inported from the neiphbourinp ports on both si ies of The Gulf ^?ho iaay choose to claim it, Un ier this irile a number of slave refupt es from Persia, Kat^r, Rasa, Oman ant even Xowait have at different times been. maniDiitte-i. If therefore a convenient o'&gt;port*imity occurs, I trust that you will be able to rejoind the Chief of Lowait that his subjects who import slaves even temporarily into torain are running as mch risk of losinp them as if they should take theta to India or on board a British man-of-war. I have the honour to he Your most obedient servant Oart.ain , Political Avert, Bahrain.Translation of the atater'ent of TaraJ H ln Said slave of a Bahrain lady, Ba^za bint Sultan, uife of Idalifa bin 3a i i al Jalabiiaa. Ared abont ^5 3 r ears. I oripinally ooine from Abyarf.nia. I waa 1° ytara old when I was brought to Ma i ba i sold to a Kajma man be Ion#- inp to Bin Pash id party by naiae Badr bin Safwan. He brought me to ida.jd ^nd kert me for 3 years and afterwards brought me to Kowait and soli me there to a person, Jair Sh^ian bu Abdallah, Latter keut me for a year an*l aftemrards sold me to Ohannam bin Jojaji, Latuer took me to Basra «jid kept me there for 4 years, ^hen agai he brought me to Kowait and sold me to khalifa bin Halail. tauter kept me for 2 years and then sold me to Khalifa bin Said al Jalahiraa. I remained with latter for a month after which he bestowed me as a Piit on nis itif e Basza bint Sultan xfho brought ne to Hahrain. I have now been living with her for the last ?, years. I work iurinp the pearlinr? season but my •ra^es to idV master. rrT hey do not pive me a wife nor clothe me and for these reasons I have taken refuge in the Agency and I beg that the Sahib may give me a manumission certi ficate so that I may become a master of myself. Political Agent’s Order ^ # The pseudo-master Khalifa ca-ls himself a l owait sub ject, but this wife ot his lives in iiahrain. Khalifa went out to my camp at Safira on the 3rd May 1907 to ate ^arai, saying that if the slave would not come willingly back, be did not want him. visit was not successful, ''he lady owner came to the Agency on 16th May, and said that her husband originally bro* p*ht ^araj from Kowait and gave him to her two years a *o. 'Tie slave may have been bo' n in Abyssinia. In the circumstances he will be ?iven Ms m^ciu- mission, after whi^y he will probably return to ^is nistresy to ’''as been kissing and stroking his cheeks and nronisirag * him n vri . 7&gt;/ //* /Ot-iu» P/o No ,£618 or 1907 Bushire Huh Deceiriber 1907 / My dear Knox, / 7-iuh rererence^bo the correspondence Korwarded with, my endorsemenb No.£' , '17 or boday’s dabe, bh.e Resident desires me bo bell you bhab ib is rorwarded bo you ror in- rurmabion only; you should nob bahe acbion on ib, nor should i you ab presenb speak bo bhe Shaikh on t/he subjecb. You # should however he generally guided hy bhe insbrucbions in bhe Cases or any slaves who may in rubure bake reruge in bhe Agency. Major Cox having been away on bour has nob been able bo deal wibh bhe mabber, bub will send you any commenbs he has bo » give on bhe insbrucbions or bhe Government or India by next mail. Yours sincerely, (Sd) A.P.Irevor. To P. A. KO'-JIT.Confidential 2 o No. % 1908. Office of the Political A^rem f Koweit. Ko^/eit March 1908. ' Ma i o r S. G. Knox, I. A., Po i ii i c al A.gen i , Ko we it. Major P. 2.Cox, C.I.ft., Political Ne^ident in the Persian i-uif, Nushire. I have the honour to reply to ' our letter No.97od, iatet the 31 c ot Deceiaber 1907 on the c mb.ject of Koweii slaves freed in Bahrein. 9. At an int erview v/ith ^heilth jMobaraK, I follov/ed the course directed in your letter and allied him whether hie opinion coincided with that of Sheikh Jabir in this question viz: that the Political Vent Bahrein had no rignt to free elave3,the property of Koweit owners. 3. At firet tne Sheikh replied in the affirmative but on my pointing out to hira in further details our right and Practise in Bah- r rein of twenty years standing and how the pro cedure there followed was tantamount to an order of the Sheikh of Bahrein that all s/Qaves coming to Bahrein are liable to be freed,no matter whom they belong to, lie appeared to £ he sitate and finally verbally authorised me to state that,while reluctant to pronounce on the legality of freeing slaves belonging to Koweit Prom To ^s^ RES '^X Dafe 11 .MAR .1908 owners he was of opinion that, as a matter ofexpediency, it wa»Tld be better for all such c vses to be referred to himself and rhe Political Agent at Koweit for disposal in consultation. press my concurrence and I would further ven ture to express the opinion that, in such cases, it would be as well for tne sl^ve if it appears that there has been real ill treatment to be returned to me not in nis master's custody.In other cases, where no ill-treatment is obvious it would be as well to inform tne shalve that he could appeal to tne Sneikh an'i tne Political Agent at Koweit .and a letter to me would suffice for the Present under the necessity of commu nicating to Sheikh I lobar ale any porllon of the letter No.4418 E.P., dated the 11th November 1907. I 4 In this view I have the honour to ex- D I may add that I did not find myself I have the honour to be. Your most obedient- servant. Po1 1 tic ai Agem , KoweitFrom To Major P.z.cox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, S.H# Butler, Esquire, Secretary to the Government of India In the Foreign Department, SIMLA. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department Letter No. 4418-E.B., dated 11th November 1907 on the subject of slave manumission at Roweit and to forward copies of correspondence that has passed between myself and the (1) . Koweit No. 685 dated Cnd Hoveynber 1907. | Political Agents (2) . Bahrein No.592 dated 29th November 1907, | at Koweit and (3) , Resident to rf-owtH* No. 27f&gt;6 dated Slst | ahrein from December 1900* (4) . Koweit No* 92 dated March 1908. I which it will be seen that the question of the treatment of Koweit slaves taking refuge at other British Agencies in the Gulf has now been raised. 2. The Government of India will understand that the fact that a negro only has to run over to Bunder Abbas or Bahrein to get a manumission certificate on his own ex narte statement is almost as much calculated to cause resentment in the Sheikh's mind as the manumission of slaves by our Political Agent in oweit itself without reference to him. our ultimate object in pursuing the V ji philantrop^ic policy which we do in regard to the manumission of slaves is to secure the greatest good of the greatest number and this end can best be served by gradually bringing the Sheikhs of Koweit tinder our civilising influence in this as well as other directionsdirections. This being so, I arc of opinion that the procedure beat adapted to the circumstances is that recommended by Major Knox namely that negroes taking refuge at our Agencies at other ports in the Gulf should be consigned by the first opportunity to the Political Agent for inquiry and disposal in communica tion with Sheikh Kubare#. If the Government of IndiOL concur, I reouest permission to inform the Agencies concerned in that sense, and also to let Gheikh fubarek know what has been decided, the Political Agent informing him at the same time of the views of Government as expressed in their letter No. 4418-.' *B., above quoted. I have the honour to be Your most obedient servant. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.jb.loct :- ilosion of &gt;lt olaves. A copy of the undermentioned communication io forwarded witii conplimenta to the Political Agent* Koweit* for information* with reference to the correspondence ending with his letter No. 92 dated larch 1908 ♦ By Order* *0 Captain* &amp;&amp; Aseioteuit Resident. * Resident to Foreign. Letter No. 917 dated 22nd liaroh 1908•negBirm ' Fo: 2^ of IMS. Political Agency £ lahrain,/^ -April 1P08 From, Captain F.3.Prideaux, Political Agent, Bahrain xO, Sir, Major P.Z.Cox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian C-ulf, 3ush.ire. Fith reference to correspondence ending with your, letter Fori dated the 1st January IMS on the subject of howait slaves, I have the honour to enclose the statement . of a negro named Almas bin Khamis, who absconded from his Kowaitimaster's agent recently in Bombay and proceeded here by mail-steamer with a request for manumission. 8 ’ As the case seen i s to contain elements for compli cations in the event of the master charging the slave with theft, I have thought the latter would be safer in Sushire than m Bahrain, and' have therefore recommended him to represent his case direct to you, instead of keeping him here until his master discovers his whereabouts. f T ‘ . . ^ W perha P s be P^sible to give the negro a umission Certificate on the ground that every man who set^fpot on fndian soil is, ip S0 facto, free: ana if a 1T1 ’ 3n8 claim IF P u t forward against the refugee, the , . _ ^ ^, Ullt/ ‘ ^ irraagea by Ms engaging himself J ^ tabs over the responsibility or tte^r ^ “ 03rt ‘ 1, ' e t0 practice I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant WTPwLxmX. _ captain. Political Agent, Bahrain.Translation of tKe statement of Almas bin KhamTs slave of Hamad bin Haiji of Kowait. Agedt about 25 years. Recorded on the 2nd April 1908. I originally come from Sawahil. Abdallah bin Khais as Suri brought me thence to Sur. I was then about 12 years old. He kept me in Sur for about Z months, after which he tooh me to Kowait and sold me there for 550 dollars to my present master / Hamad. The latter has been employing me on his sea-faring cargo-boat for the last 15 years. I go up to India in his boat. This year when he wanted to send me in the boat down to India I asked him to pay me 8 rupees, which he refused to do. Out later he paid me H:4/- and I got into his boat in company with the nakhoda Uuhammad bin Yasin. sailed for Oombay,and on our arrival we proceeded to the Tarni (?) island and shipped salt for Karachi. Again we returned to Oombay and there I received on loan Ea:20/- from the nakhoda. Thereon I fled from the nakhoda and came to Karachi. Prom Karachi I took passage on board a* steamer. I have now come to Bahrain and taken refuge in the Agency. I cannot bear a condition of slavery^ and I pray that the Sahib may be pleased to give me a manumission certificate.It The ^ 5- May 1908 Ha/o. / t/- * l® Oafe 13 . MAY .1908 ^SIAN G^. V Please refer to your official letter ho. 91V, dated the 22nd March 1908, which deals with the question of the treatnent of Koweit slaves takinc refuge at Britis^ agencies in the Persian Gulf. in our letter Ko. 4418- E.B., dated the 11th November 1907^6 saia ' Runaway 'slaves who take refuge at other Residencies and Agencies ” in the Persian Gulf are manumitted only when the slave ■ agreements apply to then, as is shown by the fact that at Bahrein and on the Arab Coast slaves who were born in slavery or who were imported prior to the execution of the slave agreements with the Sheikhs, are returned ' to their masters.' This statement was based on paragraph 5 of Colonel Meade’s letter No. 31, da tea the W' 26th April 189b ( which ran ' Slaves inserted to the ' Arab Coast and Bahrein subsequent to the aates of the agreenents 41. Bajarein. t. |Ha &lt;ul-Khinah. (Shargah. 3. Un-ul-K.owain • 4. Bebay. 'agreements noted in the margin, with the various Sheikhs, :*are given manumission ^certificates on taking ^'refuge at British 5. Ajman. • 6. Abu Thabi. oll , «- 'Acencies. Slaves who Agreements - „ and Sar G ph a ; lio. XXXVII with Bahrein (_Ras-ul-Khimah^: 'were born in slavery, or similar engagements with other Chiefs, : Uo. XXVIII; additional article with all s^who were imported prior the Chiefs- Vide Aitchison's Treaties, ; Vol. X, pages 133-134 and 117-118• :'to the execution of the Agreements with the Sheikhs, are returned to their masters, 'The practice in Bahrein in regard to such slaves has, 'however, been to make the masters sign papers agreeing to 'treat them kindly if returned, with the condition that 'they will be liable to be released if it is found that they are badly treated.' Colonel Meade's statement appears to have been inaccurate; for not only is it opposed to the wording of x the engagement of 1856 executed with Bahrein ( which applies to slaves brought x A similar engagement was entered into by the Maritime Chiefs of Ras-ul-Khimah f Um- ul-Kowain f Bebay, Ajman and Abu Thabi. AitMiison Vol. X, page 118. 'from any quarter what- 'soever;' but it is apparently at variance with the existing practice, as disclosed by the present correspondence, under which all slavesTTtTTTTTTv sieves can get nanunission certificates if they apply at f © i Bunder Abbas and Bahrein. Vide paragraph 2 of your letter : No. 917, aated 22nd March 1908. : If this view be correct, we should perhaps cancel the © Paragraph 5 of letter No. 591 # : sentence quoted from our dated 29th November 1907 from the : Political **gent, Bahrein,to the : letter. Political Agent, Koweit. : r _ ^ s T.'hat is the present practice at the other British Agencies to which you propose now to issue instructions in the sense of your letter; and is that practice based upon the authority of engagements similar to that relied upon in the case of Bahrein T Betting aside all other considerations, would not instructions of the kind contemplated be open to serious objection if they contravene the terms of existing Treaty Engagements,as ; for instance, in the case of Bahrein ? It is observed that the present case of Faraj bin Said has been settled satisfactorily to all— concerned. To liajor P. Z. Cox t C»I # £. i Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.V s oS 7 61 SHT.-A%. June 29tih 1908. \J ^t*^y '/t Please see your Deni-official letter 6th J.ay on the subject of Slave uanunission. I au sorry TjO have taken some time to reply, but the conn ;m 1 oation reached Bushire during T iy absence on tour, and I was r enable to deal satisfactorily with tne question which is a some what delicate one, before leaving Bushire and had to bring the navers here with me. The passage which you quote, from Foreign bepartnent letter TTo. 4418-B.B., dated 11th Bovenber 1907, apoears uo ■ne to state the nosition correctly and not to requi re can- cellation. It is rather Para^ravh of :ay letner Ho. 917 of A 22nd March which requires furUier explanation, and para- vravh 5 of Bahrein letter Ho. 591 of 29th Hovember, some modification. It is necessary to differentiate between negroes and Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla. slavesand slaves and I iiold -that, in every Slavery Agreement whio-d we have hitherto obtained from Rulers in these waters the word 'slave' where used means not 'any negro ', nor 'a negr* born in slavery or imported previous to the conclusion of the treaties', but 'a negro imported subsequent to the dar,e /fviaXoyy of the particular Agreement applicable to his case', the word 'Slave' for purposes of manumission should be inter preted with the above reservation, just as it invariably is at Muscat and in Persia and according to ny experience elsewhere in the Gulf. Prideaux’s statement in paragraph 5 of his letter above referred to is too sweeping, find is inconsistent with his own procedure in practice. In the first place there is no reason why the Sheikh or Palxrein should free negroes coming in from other localities and claiming freedom on totally different principles to those on which he agrees to the manumission of tne slaves been released by our representative at Bahrein on his own authority. All cases have beer referred to the Residency and the Resident has issued the certificates, or -efused them as he considered after enquiry. Ho doubt in cases A from Hasa etcetera where any local enquiry v/ould be oracti- im cally-possible or very inconvenient we have waived any re ference to the locality of domicile and have issued certi ficates (which after all confer no change of status except ference to locality of domicile is possible however, and nfofc too inconvenient the principle is duly observed. Thus only recently in the case of a refugee negro from the of his own smbjects. Secondly, in the past no slaves have freedom) on the statement of the negro himself. Hhere re- PersianPersian, side Prideaur pressed for local enquiry &amp;x&gt; Lin^ah before it# was decided wbetber the applicant# was entitled to receive a certificate or not. Procedure on the principle above referred to, worked well in the past when the British reoresentatives in the t r&gt;ulf consisted of the kesident and his Native Averts at Pharvah* Linvah and Bahrein. All cases were then referred to the 'Residency and certificates issued by him after due investigation. The position has been altered however oy the appointment of three more British Officers in the Gulf Ports, via.* Bunder Abba.s* Bahrein and Xoweit. and especial ly by the Bunder Abbas anpointment. There the Assistant Resident is also Consul under the Foreign office* and in that capacity exercises independent functions. It is in the latter capacity that he deals with slavery cases and I found lately that vreat ill-feeling existed on the Trucial Coast owing to the fa.ct that whereas negroes had in the ■oast been manumitted by tne resident only after full inves tigation, a practice had of late arisen for negroes in debt or difficulties to seise the nea/nest boat and abscond to Binder Abbas where they Vbtaindd certificates on their own bare statement and without reference to me or the he si dene; Agent, Sharp ah.. The Assistant ke si dents concerned were not to be blamed;they acted with praiseworthy seal, out vritJiout adequate knowledge of the history of the question or of the engagements holding among the Trucual Shei'cics regarding absconding divers. In order that I might have full cogni zance of what massed I felt called upon instruct our repre sentative at Bunder Abbas, as Assistant Resident* to refer31* all cases fron 'tlie A'^ao Coast/ (willoh is not/ in his juris diction as Consul) to me for enquiry and. instructions, be fore issuing manumission certificates. This asoect of the question, and Prideaux's state- m.ent above referred to were in my mind when I nenned para- m-anh 2 of my letter Ho. 917. Tne following is the practice at other Agencies con cerned. (-) At. r r - ,T uffQht,* Slaves are treated under the Treaty of 127Z and manumission certificates only grant/ed with the acquiescence of the Sultan after joint investi gation by iis 'iighness and our representative (vide correspondence ending \fit/i Foreign Department letter Ho. 12S9-K.A., dated Ibth August 1399). ~ ——LSUgial, Coc^qt • Certificates are or anted by the resident on report by the Hative Agent afper local investigation at which the Sheikh concerned is re presented and acquiesces or protests as the case may be. ji £?ia. Bunder Abo as, uingah, Bushire, Mohaj nmer ail wj\e??e we act under the Convention of 1382 ( 7 mage 95). The case is sent to the local Karguzar w.n.o is asked to issue a certificate. He makes his ovm enquiry in the presence of our representative and grants nr objects to grant a certificate. On a certificate being granted it is filed in the Brit ish representative’s office and a, British certifi cate granted on the strength of it. In the case of negroes arriving by sea from terri- (3) tories*v M. t/ories outi^ide Persia, we should not ordinarily refer to the 'Carguzar, Lin. less he had cognizance of the case and satisfied us that he had grounds for being consulted. The case of Kg we it coraes under a special category. Although the Sheikh has as yet entered into no Slavery Agreement he is nevertheless in close relations with us and will probably do so in tine, and I think that the principle of consulting the local authority should certainly be ap plied to his case. holding the views expressed in the foregoing it does /not seen to me that the course recommended by vr nox and en- ; dorsed by me will be incompatible with existing Treaty ; Engagements or our method of interpreting them, but if the procedure advocated of sending applicants to the Politics,! \j Agent for enquiry is thought by Government to go too far, it would perhaps be sufficient if a Kowe.it negro claiming freedom at one of our Agencies wese retained pending refer ence to the Political Agent Xoweit who would ascertain from the Sheikh if he acquiesced or had prima facie grounds for objecting to the slave’s manumission and askti for enquiry at Xoweit. Por the present however I ?^ecommend that if j practicable the first suggestion be adopted. If it gives rise to inconvenience, and I do not see why it should, the procedure night be modified and the reason explained \ to Sheikh Mubarak if he enquired the cause.r-d bjw slave w:i 6 t« ter from Abu Timbi or ot,ier ^iriolal oort# absoondino: from ala naater in or der t/O obtain freedom, .''jaa bo oo ’to t*i'ub A^erb at S:oar^ali* In b ie oase of a Soarmo ^an b\e faot» of uia ba v in«T ^©fr’e and bis bisbory are well 1 nowi looally and if bh© Sneibn w;&gt;o is in daily bcruoh wibi bli© Agency 3ms any yroumda for objeobing or ar^iny vibn b:.ie A r enb ne does so. In oases from ob ier oorte# b la owner as a rile ab or.ae bums up f and if lie has a ~ood case brings a lebber of reoomendabioa from his S.ielbJi# If ary Sheikh buinks biiab a slave of ore of his subjects has been wrongly harboured or freed he writes bo the Hesidenoy Ar^erb or, failing 'aim b-o t ie ^sidency ard objects, bub nerhacs it was nob sbricbly accurate for me bo say that t ie f»:aei n :h concerned was \abibually represented. Practically however owinc bo t ie dif fie 'Ity of comnunication between the Trucial Coast and Busnire a slave invariably remains some weeks ab Bhar^ac while his case is under bran emission bo ard from Bus lire, and if bue Sheikh concerns d any vt rounds for objecting ue has plenty of bine /msVI 'tine t#o do so* As a matter of fact, however tuney do not seem tjo oonoem t»hem©lves rtuoh» exoeoti in t#ne direct# ion of general comlaint/S as to too free \ami- -nission, unless the refugees are of the diving class f in which, cases they a^e &lt;x\±c erou'r; to demur.10th December 1908. Please see my letter Wo. 917 dated 22nd March 1908 to the Government of India, sent you with Residency iSn- dorsement Wo. 9521 of 24th Larch 1908, on the subject of the manumission of j^oweit slaves. Mr. Butler, Foreign Secretary, in a demi-official letter reference to your official letter Wo. 917, dated tlie 2nd arch last, regarding the treatment of Koweit slaves taking refuge at other British Agencies in the Gulf, I am desired to say that in view of the ambiguity as to the procedure followed hitherto, and the possibility that general orders might create greater difficulties than they would solve and raise issues of a trou blesome character, the Government of India would prefer to issue no general orders for th© present. The case which origin ated the correspondence has apparently been settled satisfact orily, and it is hoped that future cases may be dealt with satisfactorily on the merits as they arise'. I send the extract for your information and guidance* dated 24th September received by me at Shiraz wrote....'With ijor S.G. xuiox, Political Agent, lioweit.4 #&gt; ■ Please see my letter Ho. 917 of 22nd Parch 1908 to the troverranent of India on the subject of the manumis sion of x^oweit slaves. Mr. Butler, Foreign Secretary, in a demi official letter dated 24th September received by me at Shiraz, wrote 'With reference to your official letter ho. 917, dated the 22nd March last, regarding the treatment of xvoweit slaves taking re fuge at other British Agencies in the Gulf, I am desired to day that, in view of the ambiguity as to the procedure followed hitherto, and the possibility that general orders might create greater difficulties than they would solve and raise issues of a troublesome character, the Government of India would prefer to issue no general orders for the present, The case which or iginated the correspondence has apparently been settled satis factorily and it is hoped that future cases may be dealt with satisfactorily on the merits as they arise”. I send the extract for your information and guidance. jor F.B. Prideaux, 'Political Agent, Bahreini /hs^j 4 ■ lOtli December 1908 Please see my letter No. 917 of 22nd March 1908 to the Government of India on the subject of the manumis sion of ^oweit slaves. Mr. butler. Foreign Secretary, in a demi official letter dated 24th September received by me at Shiraz, wrote 'With reference to your official letter No. 917, dated the 22nd Larch last, regarding the treatment of noweit slaves taking re fuge at other British Agencies in the Gulf, I am desired to say, that in view of the ambiguity as to the procedure followed hitherto, and the possibility that general orders might create greater difficulties &amp;han they would solve and raise issues of a troublesome character, the Government of India would prefer to issue no general orders for the present. The case which or iginated the correspondence has apparently been settled satis factorily and it ia hoped that future cases may be dealt with satisfactorily on the merits as they arise.' I send the extract for your information and guidance iptain W.H.I. Shake spear. -Assistant Resident and H.B.M's Consul, Bunder Abbas.— so) British Hesidanoy and Consulate-General, Bushire, //^ December 1908. Copies of the undermentionedletters are forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for information, with reference to Residency Endorsement No. 9521 dated March 24th 1908. By Order, -JH?. Lieutenant, Second Assistant Resident. • . • . . . • . . _»_»_* _»_! Resident to Foreign Department. Letter No. 917 dated 22nd March 1908 with enclosures (l, 3 &amp; 4).ll^. 5-^ &gt;Tor of iw. J.^L S I A ^ Office of toe Pol it leal/gent * lowe 11 ///i 'P p ri 1 , .loweit. 1909. (S&gt; rTom To Sir, Hajor S.n-..inox, Political /gent, ioweit, Uajor P.S.Gox,G.I.I j., Political 'eeiuent in toe Persian Oilf, bunhire. I have the honour to forward. herewith. 1. Gop^ of Political /gent Bahrein's letter T 'To. 139, dated 26-^-09,with enclosures to the Political /gent, Aoweit. ' 2. Gop„ of Political /gent jjanhrein*s letter ^o.206, dated 4-4-09 to the Political /gent,Howeit. f. Translation of a letter T o. 9, dated rr* 3-4-09 fron toe Political /gent, Howeit, to Sheikh Jabir bin Uobarak. 4. Translation of a letter dated 18th ^abi al /wwal 1327-H,from Sheikh Jabir bin Hobarak to the Political / gent,.low eit. copies of the papers detailed in the nar- I -gin relat- -ing to the case of a refugee slave Sa* ad,belonging to a dowelti nakhoda, Sultan bin iluhaomad bin Uahmud.This is the first case of the kind that has occurred since correspona- -ence ending with letter T o. '&gt;17, dated 22nd March 1908 fron the Political ^esident in the Persian Ahxlf to the Secretary to the Hovemnent of India, foreign tepartnent, suggesting a procedure to be followed in the case of doweit slaves taking re- -fuge at the uahrein /genc u and for this reason I an reporting it in full detail. The slave Sa’aa arrived here b u toe nail of the 3th /pril 1909 ana, on the firstopportunity &gt; T rorwarcioci tiin^ in t/'h. r cliai'feo .u tAs .Agency Uoolla,to Sheikli Tabir bin UobaraX with vernacular letter ^o»^&gt;dated 17th abi al /-'Vv'vval lP)27.H=8th .April 1909,to which a reply ,translation forwarded herewith,was duly received. T was finable to consider this reply satisfactory,as,before its receipt,the slave returned to the /genCy and declared himself to be anything but reconciled to his master ana that he went in great fear of him. 4 # t therefore sent lioolla .Abdulla again to Sheikh Tabir with written instructions as to what to say to the Sheikh.I said that I was s±n- -cerely grateful to Sheikh Tabir for the efforts he had made to bring about a frienaly settlement of the case but regretted that, in view of the attitude of the s*lve,it was difficult for me to A- accept this settlement as final.I said,that,ii he would permit me to discuss the case,I would suggest that the naKhoda had lied to the Politi- -cal /gent and endeavoured to get possession of the slave under false pretences and that it would appear to be a fit punishment for his offence to establish the truth of his statement t„ mahing him free the slave.That the nahhoaa's conduct showed him to be a person unworth, of wrust an^ that,if T . was unfortunate enough to he in iia'aa'r place,! should certain^ go in Tear of him... would,therefore,in addition,suggest that ba’aa should be handed over, after being freed,to son'- respectable natehoda,to serve as a pearler and that art, surplus of his earnings should he handed over to Sultan bin Liuhammad bin Mahmud to accuit the debt due from Sa’ad viz: s.500/-»rt is per -haps almost superfluous to note that Sa’ad has not,in all probability,received a farthing of this none., which is simph the price of the man.IJj reason for sending idhe Moo 11a with, these gngg 0 C 5 tions was to give Sheihh Taoir anpl r tine to consider the case before discussing it with ne and I told Uoolla -Abdulla that, if he found that n^ proposals were unfavourably received,he should ash Sheihh Jabir to appoint an hour at which the case night be discussed between hin ana myself in the presence of the parties. 5 # /s i anticipated,Moo 11a Abdulla found Sheikh Jabir disinclined to carry out n^ suggest- -ions and ashed hin to appoint an hour for the discussion of the case .Sheikh Tabir politely in— —formed hin that he was well aware that th r ,f Gons^il^was very busy in these cayS pac king up and settling his affairs before leaving and that there was no necessity to trouble hin with the case as he was surety that the slave would cone to no ham. I thought it probable that Sheikh Jabir was unwilling to take up an.y aocioea atti- -tude in the absence of his father ana hav r therefore directed the slave to return tenpora-il., to his master,whom I have had infomed that the case will be taken up on the return of Sheikh Mobarak to Aoweit.Sheikh Jabir has also been m- -formed. 5 # iiurther developments in the case will be reportec^to y^o^j^in d^ie course. ve the honour to be, most obedient servant. Major, Political /gent,Aoweit.Gop^ of a letter TT o. 18% elated tde 26th. Llarch 1909 fron the Political /gent, bahrein, to the Political /gent, lioweit. 1 have the honour to forward, herewith, copies of 2 statements recorded in this office, for inform ation and such action as .,ou ma u deem necessar^ • 2. 1 hen the slave,Saad,appeared in the /gene., I told him that I was not prepared to give him ref^oge and advised him either to return to his master before his absence was noticed or no make his wa^ out of Bahrein as soon as he could. Two da^s later the master, Sultan bin Muhammad bin Mahmud, came to the /genc^ with the slave and reported to me that Saad had run awa^ from his boat and would not return to it;he also stated that Saad was not a slave but was one of - his paid khalasis. 4 . In these cire instances,and as the slave claimed to have been bom in ^aen and to have been originally stolen fron that locality, I info me d the T Tahhoda that I Yfould temporarily give the negro shelter in the /genCy until the arrival of the next direct steamer for iCoweit (leaving Bahrein on r^rd /pril 1909)when I would up send hir^ito yOU. It- seems possible that if this letter reaches yOU before the ^alihoda* s boat arrives in Moweit,^ ou ma u be able more easily to arrive at the truth of his statement by examining the persons whom he has named. True cop^ . y Head Clerk, Political /genCy,Moweit.Statement of Saad bin /dam slave of S^iltan bin Muhammad bin Mahmud aged about 72 „ears. I ’vvas bom in /den.il&gt; mother’s name is Hav\»a. Both m^ parents are still living in /den.The u are serving in the house of one Husain Hamad on wages 1 hen I was of good age I was stolen from /-den b„ one Muhammad bin Mubarak Jiddi with whom Z remained for 7 d - months during which period ! was taken pearling.Muhammad bin Mubarak sold me to T Tafa bin Todar of ^aboq,with whom I was for 10 „ears.He used to take me for pearling.This master sold me to Marzuc of Yanba whom I served for 7 '^ ^ ears.This man sold me to Sharif Shahad of Madina and I remained with him for 2*- „ears.i?*rom Sharif, Harbi bin Muhammad of /naiza purchased me and bro^ht me /naiza.I remained with him for about a month and a half .Harbi sold me to Musaad TT ajdi, who brought me to Mo we it and sold me to /*li bin Hamdi.I served /li bin Hamdi 1 ^ear,after which T was sold to Sultan bin Muhammad from whom I have now run awa u from his boat which arrived in Bahrein on Sunday (21st March 1^00).'; don’t receive an^ wages from Sultan.The reason wh^ t have run awa^ from m^ master Sultan is beca^uae he iltreats me,calls me bad names and does not give me an„ mone u . Recorded on 23rd March 1109 T beg that I ma^ be given a manumission certificate.L Jh Gop^ of the translation of the statement of Sultan bta. iiuhamnad bin Mahmud^ recorded in the Political /genc^on 24th Uarch 1^00. Saad is hhalasi and diver.I took him in ^ana- -dhan If26.He bore a paper showing his inaebted- —ness to his Hakhoda fbdiallah bin Tiiahima to the extent of ^s.500/-• T paia this raon^ to Abdallah bin k'laxiif x’'araj and took the paper ana the diver.The paper is in howeit.Saad did not go to ghos with hin but one ^ ear.This none., is for one jear.He is taking his food in eg house.On 10th Shawwal 1*26 also I had cone to Bahrein with this hh&amp;lasi to sell pearls which I sold to uan^as thro’igh /-‘haul /*ziz /• z ~ai„ani ana /haul liohsin v^assar for '3.4800/-. - sta^d then in Bahrein for 11 da^s.Then \&lt;e went to Tarin and ■- staged with r\, wife there for 2 da^s.On r'rd r hil v aad 1726 we started for do we it and sta^d there till 19J.ii Safar l?27.This negro lives in n„ house and sone tines brings fuel from yidhi in boat,' took Saad to work with ne in the sea in winter and to acconpan. ne to ghos in winner.' will pa. his wages.On Safar l?27,we set out fron doweit for Bahrein .He cane in the boat/ e have brought goats.' staged 2 da.s in Uuharrac one da. in Hadd and 5 da.s in iianana till this negro abs conded.He is a free naai and not a slave I saw hin in xlowert onl True cop., •A. Cop., of a levter* ?To.206, dated the 4tli /pril I'lOQ fron the Political /gent,rjahi*ein,to the Political /gent,jloweit. In continuation of letter T To.l89 of 26th ilarch 1909,1 have the honour to infom ^ou v that I an sending to „ ou to-da^ the slave, Saad, in charge of the nail officer of S.S.'Africa'.Jfa s&gt;z rs . ■ Translation of letter T To. 9, dated^ati al / j ^al 1?27.H,ecuivalent to Bth /*pril 190^ fron the Political .Agent, ao we it, to Sheihh Tahir bin Llo- barah us Sub ah. ’I fi.C. Your honour is, no doubt, aware o. the 3 onversation that took place between ^our father f Sheikh Llobarak^and itself on the subject of slaves of the people of Aoweit who i^in aw a., to Bahrein. 'The natter reached Major Cox,C.T.L., H.B.M*s Political Resident and Gonsul-^ren^ral, jjushire,and at last all have agreed in the matter that the Political ^gent,Bahrein,will not himself grant a mannunission paper to slaves of [oweit that go to him but send then -to me at doweit.I shall confer with Sheikh Llobarak and, after our conference Sheikh Mobarak will order, ^ ■the of justice nhall he done in the natter. To-da^ cane this Sa'ad through the Political P gent,nahrein,h„ nail,and he is going to „ou with the statenents, of the ahovenentioned Saad and Wahhoda Sultan hin lluhannad bin i^ahnua^ en closed in this letter.jj'ron these statements ana the verbal statement of the negro made in presence it appears that the matter is eas„.The nakhoda sa.s this is a (free naji)and is indebted to him according to the customs of divers ana the negro said to me “if the nakhoda gives ne a letter through „ ou^the Sahib, stating I am a free nan and onl. indebted to him I will repa. hin the amount of debt as far as I an able.Prom this apparently both of them are agreed.hr „our honour does not see an, objection,in oraer to satisfy the negro,I recuest yOU to order Sultanbin Uabraud to come and free tiie nan and the mannnmie f, ion paper v/ill be kept b^ me ana give a cop^ to the negro.Usual enaing. True translation. iiajor. Political Agent,Aoweit.Translation of Siioikh. Jabir's letter to the Political /gent,Aov^eit, dated 18th ^abi al /wwal l^L7.H=8th /pril 1909. /.G. e have received „ our letter dated 17th ^abi al /wwal l?27.H.and what have informed has become hnown to us.^ ith reference to the slave Sa*ad,he came to us ^esterda, and we sent for the nahhoda Sultan ibn Llahnud and compelled him to satisfy Sa'ad and we have effected a con ciliation between them and the aforesaid Sa'ad is content with his nahhoda Sultan and the nahhoda is content with the slave.The whole lot went awa^ from us contented*usual ending. True translation.zJ( I'Jo • 1909. Office of the Political /gent,foweit. ioweit /pril 1909. re EiP' 1 Jrom \ Major S.rv..,jiox,I./*., Political /gent,foweit. /3 6 S' Oaie 4. HAY.l 909 ^ \ V 1 s i a &amp;&lt;£:&gt;■ To Maj oi* P. . oox., o. l . -i_j ., Political ^e^iaent in the Persian Oilf, bushi re, Sir, I have the honour,in continuation of letter ^To.204, dated the 14th /pril 1909,to inform 0 ou that I brought the ca*e of the slave Sa’ad to the notice of Sheihh Mobarak ae Subah on the 13th /pril ana correspondence, of vhich trans lations are forwarded herewith as an appendix to this letter passed between us as well as a verbal conversation of some length. 2. I an happ., to be able to report that Sheikh Mobarak received representations in a most friendly spirit and that it has been proved to me that Sa’ad,as Sheikh Mobarak la^s down emphatically in his last letter, is a free pearler who is trying to escape his obligations as a pearl diver on a false pretence of slaver^.! have informed him that nothing can be done for him, except that on his re turn from the pearls if he refers to the /genCy,it rna^ be possible to arrange that his acco-’ints with his nakhoaa ma^if Sheikh Mobarak concurs,beexamined fa., the Agenc^ liooila to- eee that he is treated fairly.I make this reconKiendation on the ground that,according to Sa'ad's own statement,which to that extent is not controverted,he is apparently a british subject bom in /'den # ?, 9 I have no reason whatever to believe that he is being treated oppressively or unfairly and consider it unlikely that his case will trouble us again. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Ilajor, Political Agent,doweit.translation of letter dated 13th / pril 1909=27th P.ahi al r mml l?Z7-d from Major B.G. aiox, 7./Political / b e nt, loweit, to She it h Moharah us Sub ah. I-.C. T e inform ^ ou that Sa’ad before going to the Political /gent,Bahrein,was slave to Sultan bin Muhammad bin Mahmud.the above-mentioned Sultan was present in Bahrein and complained about Sa'ad to the Political /.gent,Bahrein,that Sa'ad is a free man ana that he owed him mone w on account of pearling ana he tool: him from ’ haul la bin Baraj al ^elahmeh. ihe statements of both were sent to us b^ the Poli tical /gent,Bahrein,and we sent copies o^ these statement to w our son Jabir*and Jabir saw that the matter will be prolonged. 1 e postponed the matter till ^owr arrival in the town. 1 , e informed Jabir that we shall postpone the matter till ^ our honour arrives here.Mow wish to come to ^ ou at 11 p'cloclc and rec uest that ^ou will order Sultan bin Muhaomad to be present and to bring the aocument with him so that W' 0 ma^ settle the matter whether Sa'ad is a free man according to Sultan's statement or a slave to Sultan. Jsual ending. Political /gent,.loweiti‘ran slat ion of letter aatea 13th /pril 1909=£7th Pabi al /wv^al Iff^-H from Sheikh Mobara]: us Sub ah to Major S.O..Inox, IPolitical / gent,.ioweit. A. C. T am in receipt of ^our letter dated £7th Pabi al / wwal IfS’t-d and its contents Inown. Sa' aa complained before the Political /gent,Bahrein, that he is a slave to Sultan bin Muhammad bin Mahmua ana Sultan complained that Sa’ad is a free man ana that he is indebted to him on account of pearling mone„ , de took him in his service from ibdulla bin /araj al Jalahmeh/ e , God willing, shall oraer Sa’ad ana Sultan bin Muharamad bin Mahmud and people of howeit knowing both the parties to be present before us to-morrow./nd the„ will bear witness against both parties whether Sa’ad is a slave and Sultan in the wrong or, if he is a free man and Sa’ad in the wrong, the fact of the complaint will appear from the evidence of the people ana we shall let ^ou know the result.Usual ending. irue translation. Major, Political gent, .lo we itB Translation of letter from Sheilih Liobarak as Subah, ruler of -Coweit to Major S.O-.Mnox,Political /gent. [oweit, dated 7 &gt;Otb ^abi al /vAml 1^27 H• = 2 /'/pri 1 1909. A.G. we have informed w on i.hat we should make present Sa'ad with his nakhoda Sultan bin Muhaumad bin Mahmud with him who knows both parties and v/e vail see their complaint and will inform „ ou of the result.lH/e have made them come before us and it appears that the claim of Sa’ad is opposed(to truth)and it is proved that he is a free man and Sultan bin Muhammao. bin Mahmud took him over from /b dull a bin r'araj M Jalahima according to his barwat(pearl papery for the amount of ^s.500 and Sultan sa^s since this man has deceived me, I an not safe from him that he should go with me (to the pearls).! will give him a 'barwat'.He will attach himself to some one among the people of [oweit and will pa., me mone^.This I have written that ^ our knowledge ma^ embrace the actual circumstances and doubt ma^ be dispersed and ma u ^ou remain safe. 0 seal of Sheikh Mobarak. It. is that on the 27th ''abi al /wwal ir)27.H, True translation Major, Political /gent, [oweit</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ba_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/213</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ba</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/213</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 5/183 (D 31) Manumission of slaves at Kuwait’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1907/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-19T22:36:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">per</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (66 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence contained in the file runs in approximate chronological order, from the earliest at the front, to the latest at the rear. The most recent item in the volume is a handwritten note, pasted onto the verso of folio 1c, which is dated on its reverse 18 Oct 1920. There is a typewritten index to the volume on folio 1b. It consists of eight subjects, for which page numbers (referring to the blue/red pencil numbering system) are given.</extent><extent>Foliation: The volume has been foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, with circled numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. An earlier pagination system, which numbers each recto with writing on and uses larger blue or red pencil numbers in the top-right corner of pages, runs through the volume.Condition: There is a small amount of insect damage on some pages, but this does not impair the legibility or understanding of the correspondence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence in the volume is related to a number of manumission cases involving Kuwaiti subjects heard between 1907 and 1909, either in Kuwait, or in another of the Political Agencies in the Gulf. A significant proportion of the file comprises correspondence between the Political Resident (Major Percy Cox) and the Political Agent in Kuwait (Captain Stuart Knox), seeking to clarify how best to proceed with manumission requests from Kuwaiti subjects, in light of the absence of a formal slave trade treaty between the British Government and the Sheikh of Kuwait.In a letter of March 1908, Knox wrote to Cox (folios 21-22), stating that the shaikh agreed that, as “a matter of expediency, it would be better for all such [manumission] cases to be referred to himself and the Political Agent at Kuwait for disposal in consultation.” Knox further proposed that, where evidence of the ill-treatment of the slave existed, the slave should be returned to the care of Political Agent, but where no evidence of ill-treatment could be seen, the slave could appeal to the shaikh and Political Agent. Correspondence was exchanged through August and September 1908 between Cox and Woods, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, on the issue of the procedure of manumission (folios 39-42). Woods informed Cox that, for the present, “the Government of India would prefer to issue no general orders” on manumission cases, and would be content if “future cases may be dealt with satisfactorily on the merits as they arise” (folios 42).A manumission case heard at Kuwait in 1909 involved a pearl diver who claimed to be a slave, and was seeking manumission from his master (folios 49-63). In a translated statement, the master claimed that the man was not a slave, but simply owed him a diving debt. The slave and his dive master were reconciled after the intervention of Knox and shaikh Mubarak (folio 59).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Political Agency</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ba#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>