<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000142_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:29:00.638Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">POLITICAL (EXTERNAL) DEPARTMENT.INDEXED ^ ^ !P 45 39814 All to E xterna l 'Depar tment C01I?IDSNTIAJ; COIE TELEGRAM 67^ Prom Government of-India, External Affairs Depaitment. To Chungking. Reptd.to Secretary of State for India and China Relations Officer Calcutta. Dated New Delhi 16.30 hours 18th December 1945. Reed» 12,35 hours 18th December 1945, IMPORTA NT 1 0558 Continuation Government of India, External Affairs Department telegram J1755-(&gt; December 14th. Mr. Joerg booked December 21st. Grade 4 service number 12P40. He should contact Air Priorities Board Calcutta immediately. POL »0&gt;T, ) DEC1945■■■■I CO^ N r -'r ~ waJSq telegram r-v¥.0 6 7 9.5 V' 1945'. 1 McJC / P^&amp;-&lt;yv — 948S Allot.t-aa to . asterml Department r&gt;. • k Prom To M CI^AIR TELEGRAM Government of India, External Affairs Dept. H.M, Ambassador, dhungking. Repeated to Secretary of State for India and China Relations Officer, Calcutta Dated New Delhi, 22.15 hours, 14th December 1945. Received 02.55 hours, 15th December 1945. IMPORTANT . 2753G . Reference Government of India, External Affairs Dept, telegram No . 10231 December 13th. Owing to uncertainty of date or arrival of Joerg' in Calcutta vide your telegram 536 December~13th passages booked on 17th December cancelled passages on 21st December applied for.■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■ file COPVn WAR ( 4 ) CONPIDBKTIAL CODE TELEGRAM Prom Government of India, External Affairs Dept. * To H»M*Ambassador Chungking- Repeated to Secretary of State for India, and China Relations Office Calcutta. Dated New Delhi 15.15 hours, 13th Dec- 1945. Received 13.50 hours, 13th Dec. 1945. 10231. Your telegram 625 of December 9 th* Joerg and v;ife iDooked Calcutta ■ United Kingdom on December 17th. They should contact Priorities Calcutta immediately.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000142_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1101</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000142</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1101</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 6661/45 Joerg: Arrangements for Passages [file]</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-01T11:51:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of correspondence between the Government of India, External Affairs Department, and HM Ambassador, Chungking, related to the travel arrangements for 'Mr Joerg' to Calcutta.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000142#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>