<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-20T12:24:44.359Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">0 - - ^\ t L t Confidential♦ POLl V A M D CON r ‘^ t* SCO F n y ! •' ‘ &gt;J &gt; ' ! ^ e. lQ0Cr ! : 1 5 ..., V /f3 Ho, c/3 13 of 1936. Office of the Political Heeident in the Persian Culf t H.M.S.Lupin, At Kas al Khaimah. • l !: W-'j T, Dated the 5th October* 1935, To The Political Agent* Kuwait. The Political Agent* Bahrain, y The Political Agent, Muscat. / Memorandum. Sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Air Itevigation Regulations on the Ayab Coast, A copy is enclosed of the correspondence cited in the 1, Government of India letter Ko.F.104-N/33 dated the 6th February 1935* without enclosure. } margin 2. India Office letter Ho.P.Z*1335/35 dated the 8th ) March 1935. ( 3. Political Resident’s letter Ho.384-S dated the 4th my 1935. 4. Government of India letter fto.F. 104-N/33 dated the 19th June 1935. 5. India Office letter Ho.P.£.6368/35 dated the 13th September 1935* with enclosures. Please prepare on the lines agreed upon and forward a draft King’s Regulation in respect of Kuwait SSiSa Muscat. 3. Please m^ke at the same time any general observations on the proposal that you may wish to offer. 4 , To Muscat only. It will be seen that in the case of Muscat two drafts ere required!- (a) a regulation to be published by the Sultan and enforced by him on all persons falling within his Jurisdiction* (b) /r - 2 - (b) a King’s Eagulation to be enforced on all persona to whom the liuocat Order-in*Council applies* The Sultan should not be approached at this stage for his approval to (a)* ♦ Attested* ed* G* Loch, Lieut*-Colonel* Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^or Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*Confidentjal. D.O.No.?.104-^33 Q FORKIGIf A HR POLITICAL RJSPARTMBtrT, NEW DELHI, THE fithFEBRTIARY 1935. 5 felWJts My dear Fowle, yc' Would you please refer to the correspondence enuing with your printed letter NO.1072-S °1 ^4, dated the 21st November 1934, sending us copies of correspondence which you had with His Majesty's Cterge* d 1 Affaires, Bagdad, regarding the landing of a French aeroplane in Bahrain without permisionc It appears that in this case no penalty was actually imposed upon the Frencn aviator for his breach of ■•'he Air Navigation Regulations for the territory of Bahrain (copy received here from the India Office under cover of their No.P.Z.4121/1934 of 3rd August 1934). From a study of the Regulations referred to above together with those for Kuwait, and also of those more recently promulgated for the territory of iftiscat (viae enclosure to your Despatch No. 104 2-S/34, dated the 9th November 1934, addressed to His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India) it seems clear that no penalties ha^e in fact been prescribed for breach ot these regulations. In all three cases Regu-fc tion No.!4(iii) merely states that M if any persan contravenes or fails to comply with these Regulations or any provision thereof he shall be dealt with according to the Taw*\ The difficulty is one of general application to Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat, while similar difficulties may also arise in the case of Sharjah which is a regular aerodrome, and possibly over the other Arab States on the Trucial Coast ana in Qatar, in the event of landings in those places. Persons contravening the regulat- ions now in force in Kuwait, Bahrain ana Muscat will presumably always be Europeans or other foreigners who are not subjects of the Shaikhs, and it would therefore appear possible i o. u. to issue a King’s Regulation under the Order-in-Council in i orce in each Shaikhdom, prescribing penalties for breach of the air regulations by foreigners. I an to ask for your views as to whether such a Regulation should now be issued And if so what penaltiescould suitably be enforced thereby. In this connection I forward for your information a copy of the Inaian Aircraft Act which provides penalties for breach of aircraft regulations in Inaia. It will be seen that the offence out of which the present discuss ion arose is similar to that penalised by section 15 ol the Act* 2. With regard to Sharjah, Qatar and tho Trueial Coast, generally there is of course no Order-in-Council in force giving extra territorial rights to British anc foreignsubjects. The position is explained in your bemi-oificial letter to Laithwaite N0.1669-S, dated the 4th December 1933. In these Shaikhdoms theoretically no doubt British and foreign sub£ cts are under the Shaikh’s jurisdiction, but in actual practice we would not permit a Britis h of foreign subject to be dealt with by the Rulers In this area presumably the best we could oo would be to treat each case as it arises on its merits after coming to an agreement with the Shaikh concerned for the ais ourageraent oi flights by foreign aircraft. In the case of Saarjah of course we already have an agreement which is confined to flights by British air craft only, and therefore by implication discourages flights by other aircraft. sending a copy of this letter to La it tiv.aite. Yours sincerely, Sgd. H.A.F.METCAIFB.P.2.1335/1935. INDIA OFFICE, BY AIR HAIL LOUDON, S.W. 1. 8th Harcn 1935. My dear Fowle, Won la you please refer to Metcalfe's demi-official letter to you, F.104 o l!/3.3, of 6th February, of which he sent a copy to me, about the sanctions to be appliea in the of breaches of the Air Navigation Regulation* in Bahrain, Kuwait a* A5*««**etc.? You may care to have these interim observations, 2. The regulations in qestion are based on the tiicussione which we ha&lt;i here in the spring of 1934 ana at which you (an&lt;i also Prior) were present. My recollection is that at that sfhge we rather shirked this question of the penalties to oe imposed and thought we coula leave the matter open until we had further experience - possible difficulties about jurisdict ion being one of the points which appeared to require further consideration, particularly in regard to the Trucial Coast. But it now looks on the whole as though &lt;ve should uo better to race the i«rue and endeavour to provide eorae appropriate penalty. So far as the actual Montaigu case is concerned I am rather inclined to think that it say be simplest to let it drop (since, as you will remember, it was on tne one hand impossible not to give wontaigu a reasonaoly irienaly Director reception, as he was a of the I.P.C?, while on the other he was, in fact, gate crashing, as the other groups had not. been anzious that any representative of the French interests in their company should be present at the aisneseionr. at Bahrain, It seems unlikely in these circumstances that eve if we did make representations to the I.P.C. they would carry us much farther forwara)# s . as regards the nature and scale of any penalty to be provided, the Air „insitry inform us demi-officially that in this country an offence against the Air Regulation^is punish-- 2 - aole by a fine not exceeding £.200 or by i/npriPonment not exceeding eix months, or by both a fine ^nd imprisonment. Tjnder the Indian Aircraft Coue (Clauses 10 and 11} a fine not exceeding RfiotOOO may be impoeea in India *0 4. Under the Bahrain and Kuwait Orders in Co ’ncil Y/e have jurisdiction over foregners and &lt;y er their property within the limits of the Qfderc( in the ease of the new Ku ait Order aircrait are aei initely specified, ana, ii efiect is given to a proposal recently mentioned to you that a revised Bahrain • Orcer should be prepared, we coula make similar provision in the case of Bahrain). Prima facie , therefore, though we have there would seem to be no o'cstacle, assuming that not considered the matter closely, ^;he local ruler had first agreed to the imposition of penalties on such lines as we mi£ht decide to recommend, to the raakeing of King’s Regulations under Article 70(b) of the Bahrain Order ana Article 83(b) of the Kuwait Order *for securing the observance.•• of any native or local law, or custom,whether relating to trade, commerce, revenue, or any other matter 51 , ie.ia this case, such penal provisions ior a breach of the Air Kabigation Regulations as , might be made by the Shaikhs of Kuwait and Ban rain. The Orders in Council in question further provide that such King’s Regulations may provide for forfeiture of goods (e.g. in this case the offending aircraft) and bhat breaches of the King*s Regulations may be punished by imprisonmsint not exceedirg three months or by a fine not exceeding Rs.lbOO, or by bo’-hw imprisonment and a fine. Subject to closer examination it looks on the whole as tho’gh t would be possible fir us to advise the Rulers to make provision for a fine of up to Rs. IbOO (alternative punishment of imprisonment or forfeiture of 4 the aircraft teing kept in reserve for use in particularly ilagrant cases).a 7 10; 0* A 5# Muflcat ie, of course, in a different position, since the extent of oru jurisdiction over foreigners and their property appears to be governed by Article 8 (3), (4) ®d (5) of the Muscat Order in Council, and our jurisdiction over foreigners xxxlxx practical purposes confined tocases -where the ' nant whose suo^cts they are has M agreeo with His Majesty^ lor or consented to the exercise of prwer or authority by His Majesty** Tt looks at first sight as though we hace no juris diction at all over property belonging to foieigners in Muscat,, Subject to these reservations the arrangements for making King f s KeguAtions under the iAiso; t Order in Council are similar to taore in the case of Bsna^n an* Jt wouxo appear in ta^se circumstances as though any penalties la ic. down for the contravention by persons other than British subjects er individuals covered by the Order in Council of the Muscat Air navigation Regulations would have to be imposed by the Muscat authorities themselves, but difficulties in securing that they should on our advice make provision for appropriate penalties on the same basis as referred to above in the case of Kuwait and Bahrain would not presumably be serious* b 0 The Trucial Coast and QR,tar are, of course, as Metcalfe Points out, more difficult becamae of the absence of an Order in council giving ex-territorial rights to British and foreign subj -ectEo But ( save possibly*in Qatar) the poinr, is perhaps of less immediate active importance, since, at thi; stage at any rate, there are perhaps likely to be fewer attempts by or inducements to private civil aircraft to endeavown xo land there than in the case of Baarain Kuwait or possibly Muscat* 7. The quite provisional suggestions put forward above may we hope facilitate consideration of this question* Once we have received your views ana those of the Oovernne nt of India we shall be prepared to take the question up with the Air Minstry and Foreign Office at thisend®2J // CONFIDENTIAL&gt; D.0.NO.384-S of 1935. THE RESIDENCY, BUSHIRE, 4th May 1935. SANCTIONS TO BE APPLI D IN THE EVENT OF BREACHES OF THE AIR NAVIGATION REGULATIONS ( N THE ARAB COAST. My dear Laithwaite, Please refer to correspondence ending with your endorse ment P.2.1335/35, dated the 8th March 1935. 2. To take Muscat first. Offenders wiD! be either (a) Foreign subjects (b) British subjects. Class (a) comes under the jurisdiction of the Sultan, who would doubtless consult the Political Agent in taking suitable action. As regards Class (b) the Muscat Order in Council does not contain any general clause making the breach of local regulations a pinoshable offence under the Order in Council. A King*s Regulation under Article 78(b) of the Order would therefore be necessary• 3. On the Truci&amp;l Coast and ^tar there are at present neither local Air Regulations nor an Order in Council. The introduction of both into these areas would involve difficult and lengthy negotiations wi th several Sheikhs, and in view of the fact that private aircraft have little inducement to land in this area, I do not think that either Air Regulations or an Order in Council is called for. 4. In Bahrain and for all presetical purposes in Kuwait (since breeches of the Air Regulations by Moslem foreigners are not likely to be frequent) both British and foreign subjects fall under the jurisdiction of the Political Agent, As the Orders in Council contain no general enabling clauses, King’sRegulations under Articles 70(b) of the Bahrain Order in Council and 83(b) of the Kuwait Order in Council would be necessary, 5, As regards the penalty to be imposed (paragraph 4 of your letter) it seems necessary to advise only the Sultan of Muscat (who will have to deal himself with foreign subjects) t© #nake provision for a fine of Rs,1,500/- In the Case of British subjects in Muscat and all persons in Bahrain and Kuwait the penalty is already provided in sub-section (2) and (3) of Sections 79, 71 and 84 of the Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait Orders in Council respectively. In addition to the penalties prescribed in these Sections, forfeituee of the machine could be prescribed in the king's Regulations themselves, - II , .n I. I ^ | . n i. ^ I This would seem preferable to this penalty being inserted by the Shaikh in the Air Navigation Regulations. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe. Yours sincerely, (Sgd) T.C.FOWLE.@ ll FOREICN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, SIMLA, THE 19th JUNE 1955. D.0.N o .F.104-N/33. Sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of Air Navigations Regulations in Bfehrain, Kuwait, etc. Iffy dear Laithwaite, I am desired to invite a reference to the correspond ence ending fch with Powle’s demi.official letter to you No.384-s/35 dated 4th ISay 1935, and to say that subject to detailed commentary on the draft King*8 Regulations, when prepared, the Government of India are in general agreement with Fowle*s views. Yours sincerely, sd. H.A.F.METCALFE. J.G. LAITHWAITE, ESC*., TEE INDIA OFFICE, LONDON.Copy. P.Z. 6368/35. By air mail. IHDIA OPPICB, LOHDOH.S.W.l. 13th September 1935. l^y dear Loch, Would you please refer to the correspondence ending with my demi-official letters of the 2nd August to the Foreign Office and the Air Ministry (copies of which were sent to India and Bushire by the Air Mail of the 5th August under P.Z. 4701/35) on the si bject of the sanctions to be applied for breaches of the Air Navigation Regulations at Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat ? I now enclose copies of letters from the Forex&amp;n Office and the Air Ministry, From Foreign Office dated 7th | from which you will see that ifc September 1935. ) ) they are in general agreement From 4ir Ministry dated 11th ) September 1935. ) with the proposals mentioned in —— — ~ letters of the 2nd August. The next step is, therefore, to prepare a draft of the / Regulations t o be issued by the Sultan of Muscat, and draft Kings Regulations in respect of Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat, on the lines already agreed demi-officially with the Resident /; and the Covernment of India* We should be glad if you could now take the necessary action in this sense and submit the drafts officially to the Government of India and the Secretary of State for approval. These Regulations should specify the penalties, in accordance with the various Orders in Council, to which an offender against the regulations may be liable, V viz: H forfeiture of any goods, receptacles or things in relation to which any breach is committed of such regulations M (in this case the offending aircraft); imprisonment for a period not exceeding 3 months; or a fine t not / \/ v' The Hon*tie Lt•-Col.P # G*Loch,C.I .E., / His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General, Bushirt*-2 not exceeding 1,500 rupees? or both imprisonment and a fine. 2, Yith regard to the suggestion that refuelling facilities might be refused as an additional penalty (vide paragraph 6 of herd’s letter of 7th September), fowle, with whom the question has been discussed, has suggested that a provision of this sort would be superfluous if regulations are issued on the lines suggested above. He suggests that in practice a guard would probably be placed over the offending aircraft in the event of a breach of the regulations, and that the machine (if not confiscated) would only be released after the appropriate penalty had been extracted from the offender. 3, As regards the regulations to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat, we agree with paragraph 2 of Ward f s letter. 4, I am sending a copy of this letter to Acheson. Yours sincerely, sd. .(i• J'.Clauson.P.2,.6368/35. Copy. (E 4759/17/91). 77 / FOREIGN OFFICE, 7th September 1935# Deer Clauson, In Ren del* s absence on leave I am replying to your letter No.P.Z.4701/35 of the 2nd August about the penalties to be imposed on aviators breaking the Air Navigation Regulat ionsj for the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. 2. We agree generally with the proposals you have worked out in conjunction with Fowle. As regards Muscat f we think that it is clear that the only way to proceed is to induce the Sultan to make a regulation with the appropriate penalties, which he wilj have to enforce himself on those foreigners who come within his jurisdiction. From a practical point of view, it is, of course, essential that the Political Resident should approve the substance of the regulation and the penalties contained in them, but this point will be safeguarded if the regulation drafted by the Resident and if he can subsequently ensure that the Sultan would consult the Political Agent before taking any action against a foreign aviator. 3. In order to deal with persons under our own jurisdiction we agree that a King’s Regulation will have to be made under Article 78 of the Muscat Order-in-Council, a translation of the Sultan of Muscat’s Air Navigation Regulations being annexed to it, and the King’s Regulation stating that they are binding on the persons specified in Article 8 (l), (2) and (3) of the Order-in-Council. The Regulation should then prescribe the penalties for breach of the conditions governing air navigation, and Beckett points out that it is important to note that the possible penalties are limited by the terms of Article 79 of the Order-dn-Council, which hould be borne in mind in preparing the draft. 4. /- 2 - (ip ^ 7 4* We agree that it is not necessary at the present moment to do anything as regards the Trucial Sheikhdoms* The only one of these where it seems likely that we may have to make air navigation regulations in the fairly near future and therefore to prescribe penalties of this sort is probably Qatar; we should presumably be able to do this in the same way through a King’s Regulation, in accordance with the provision for issuing King’s Regulations which will doubtless be embodied in the prospective Qatar Order-ifn-Counc il o n t* 16 lines of Articles 83-85 of the Kuwait Order-in-Council. 5. We agree with your proposals in regard to Bahrain and Kuwait, but Beckett points out that the King’s Regulations must of course be drafted so as to conform with the pr ovisions of the Order-in-Council under which they are made, namely Articles 70 and 71 mt in the case of Bahrain, and 83 and 84 in the case of Kuwait* 6. We notice that your proposals allow for the penalties being those authorised by the respective Orders-in-Council (with the exception of penalties for foreigners in Muscat where the Sultan will issue a special regulation), but we are not clear as to how you intend to bring in the possible refusal of re-fuelling facilities*. It will presumably be easy for the Sultan of Muscat to include this among the penalties imposed by his own regulation, but the Orders-in-Council do not appear to cover a penalty of this sort, (although the mention in them of 'forfeiture’ 1 would presumably cover the actual seizure of an aeroplane). It would seem however that the refusal of refuelling facilities must be dealt with by some order binding on the authorities of the aerodrome where the refuelling would take place i.e# not as part of the penalties but in the other part of the regulations* 7. /7, We agree that the next stage should be for the Resident to be invited to prepare drafts of the necessary regulations, and we presume that you will let us see them as soon as they are available# (sd.) J•G#WARD#KM P.2.6368/55 Air Ministry, Guydyr House, c'/hit ehall, London,S.^.l 11th September 1935 413895/55/C .A.I Dear Clauson. In your letter of 2nd ultimo, P,Z, 4701/35 you referred to the question ofthe sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Air Navigation Regulations at Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat. I write to let you know that the Air Ministry concur in the action proposed in paragraph 3 of your letter. Yours, &amp;c., (sgd.) P.G.Bertram M.X.Clauson Esq • p India Office, S.W.lMemo. No. B. 440. P.Z. 4121/34 Air Navigation Regulations for Civil Aircraft for the Territory of Bahrein, and Conditions governing the use of the Aerodrome at Muharraq approved by His Excellency Sheikh Hamad bin Tsa A1 Khalifah, C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrein. I.—Air Navigation Regulations for Civil Aircraft. 1. Aircraft shall not fly over or land in the territory of Bahrein except under a special authorisation issued by His Excellency the Sheikh. 2. Aircraft so authorised, when flying over or landing in the territory of Bahrein, shall comply with the following general regulations in addition to such other supplementary conditions as may be specified in the authorisation. 3. —(i) The aircraft shall be registered and bear the prescribed nationality and registration marks painted on the aircraft in the prescribed manner. (ii) The aircraft shall be certified as airworthy in the prescribed manner, and any terms or conditions on or subject to which the certificate of airworthiness was granted shall be duly complied with. (iii) The personnel of the aircraft shall be of the prescribed number and description and shall be provided with the prescribed certificates of competency and licences. (iv) There shall be carried in the aircraft the prescribed documents and journey log book kept up to date in the prescribed form and manner. In addition, if the aircraft carries passengers, there shall be carried a list of their names and, if it carries freight, bills of lading and manifest in respect thereof. (v) In this regulation “ prescribed ” means prescribed by the law of the State on whose register the aircraft is entered. 4. The aircraft shall not use as a place of landing or departure any place other than the aerodrome at Muharraq. The published conditions governing the use of the aerodrome shall be observed. 5. The aircraft and the persons on board shall conform to such orders as may be lawfully given by any authorised person. 6. Personnel of the aircraft required to be provided with licences shall on demand produce their licences for the inspection of any authorised person. The person in charge of the aircraft shall on demand by an authorised person produce any prescribed certificate, licence or log book relating to the aircraft and, if it carries passengers or freight, the list of names and the bills of lading and manifest respectively. 7. Any authorised person shall have the right of access at all reasonable times to any aircraft for the purpose of carrying out his powers and duties under these regulations. 8. The aircraft shall comply with the rules as to lights and signals and rules for air traffic prescribed in Annex D of the Convention for the Regulation of Aerial Navigation, dated 13th October 1919. 9. The aircraft shall comply in customs matters with the provisions of Annex II of the aforesaid Convention. 10. The aircraft and persons on board shall immediately on arrival from abroad aud prior to departure for abroad submit to the sanitary formalities prescribed by the Public Health Administration. 11. The time of the intended arrival from abroad at, and of departure for abroad from Muharraq Aerodrome shall be notified beforehand to the Customs, Public Health and Police Administrations. 12. Persons on board aircraft shall be in possession of valid national passports to be produced on demand to any authorised person. Through passengers not breaking- journey will not require transit visas. Passengers breaking journey or leaving the aerodrome will need visas for the State. 13. Subject to the provisions of these regulations, the laws and regulations for the time being in force in Bahrein concerning the entry into and departure from Bahrein 4061 100 9.352 of persons by sea and land and concerning the importation into and the exportation from Bahrein of goods by sea or land shall apply equally and respectively to the entry and departure of persons, and the importation and exportation of goods, by air. 14. —(i) If an aircraft flies in contravention of or fails to comply with these regulations or any provision thereof or if in or in respect of the aircraft any act is committed which is or is deemed to be a contravention of these regulations or any provision thereof, the pilot of the aircraft shall be deemed to have contravened these regulations. (ii) If any person obstructs or impedes any authorised person in the exercise of his powers and duties under these regulations, such first-mentioned person shall be deemed to have acted in contravention of these regulations. (iii) If any person contravenes or fails to comply with these regulations or any provision thereof, he shall be dealt with according to law. 15. The expression “ authorised person ” means any person authorised by His Excellency the Sheikh of Bahrein. Dated the 6th June 1934 (Safar 1353). II.—Conditions governing the use of the Aerodrome at Muharraq. 1. Liability will not be accepted by the Sheikh or by His Majesty’s Government, their servants or agents for loss or damage by accident, Are, flood, tempest, explosion or any other cause to aircraft, or for loss or damage from whatever cause arising to goods, mails, or other articles, or for loss or injury from whatever cause arising to passengers or other persons (including pilots, engineers or other personnel of aircraft) landing at, departing from or accommodated in or at the Muharraq aerodrome (even if such loss, damage or injury is caused by or arises from negligence on the part of such servants or agents). 2. The fees payable in respect of landings and accommodation are as specified in the First Schedule hereto. Landing fees will be assessed according to the maximum permissible weight authorised by the certificate of airworthiness of the aircraft. 3. Landing fees do not include attendance or other services. (For these see Second Schedule below.) 4. Supplies of fuel and lubricant for aircraft at the aerodrome must be obtained from the agents appointed to manage the aerodrome at the current rates posted up at the aerodrome. 5. The foregoing fees and charges will be payable on demand. 6. Other services which may be required will be a matter for direct arrangement with the aerodrome authorities. -44 APPENDIX. Form of Special Authorisation for Aircraft to land in Muharraq and fly over Bahrein. 1. The Sheikh of Bahrein hereby authorises the flight within the limits of Bahrein of the following aircraft of nationality : Registered owner. Type of aircraft. Registration maih. 2. This authorisation is limited to the period from to inclusive and is granted subject to the following conditions : (i) The aircraft, their crews and passengers shall be liable to all the legal obligations which arise from general legislation, from customs and excise legislation, and import and export regulations and any regulations which /-s may be laid down for public safety as well as the air navigation regulations attached hereto. (ii) The aircraft shall not use as a place of landing or departure within Bahrein any place other than the aerodrome at Muharraq and the published conditions governing the use of the said aerodrome shall be observed. (iii) This authorisation or a certified true copy of it shall be carried in the aircraft and be produced on demand for the inspection of any authorised person I ? Pp£:| r.m i* I gs-'aEfiaag; ^rom, No,19/j3 3 British Agency, Gwadur, / 9 .10.1925. To, The British Agent, Gwadur. The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M . f 3 Consul, Muscat. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your telegram No.172 dated 9.10.25 received here on 10.10.1925 reading as under:- Please ascertain from agent Imperial Airways and telegraph number of gallons of (A) Petrol and (B) oil used by machines of Imperial Airways in 1924 also number of the companys aeroplanes which passed through Gwadur during that year. and to confirm my telegram dated 10.10.1925 reading as under:- Your telegram 172 ninth Petrol 42612 oil 1709 aeroplanes 116. j j and I hope that the reply wasj^in order. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, T- v* '1 , 10 British Agent.; - f * - 2 - tjcemption from th« pa/ment of eastomo duty on potrol *m oil taportod for tho ubo of XaporUX Alrw^yo. 3« 1 hrd point od out in paragraph B of ay Kxpresa Lot tor Of tod too ^nd July 1935 t that ot the vimo the Civil / ir A«.roomento ooro eoneludod it woo not oppreoiotod that the sonotary voluo of thoeo privilogoo, toth in reopoot of A (pectally A (3)} and of B 9 would rlso oo ropidly in coneo- ^i«fico of the duplication of the air sail oervieo ot the oofi^oncoaent of thio yoar and its proposed further expansion, which it ie now planned should extend to a service of 5 days a we«k in 193? # I had therefore suggested that it should he accepted as a principle that the eua of £*dOC paid at present to the It el era should he regarded only ae ecaeiderat ion for the privileges under A # and that the Civil Air Agreeacnte should he amended so as to provide for the payment of ouetoaia duty on all petrol and oil isported for the use of laperUl Air way e* 4* It ie no# generally agreed that the Rulera in question have a clear case in equity for a jre-exaainatlon of the effect of the existing Civil Air Agjfseaente (vide paragraph 2 of Air Ministry letter Me # Q,3»95d Il/b # D.o # A. # dated the Met August 1935-. the Air Ministry, however, are averse from seeking a concession in the form suggested by me, i.e. payment of customs duty, ee it would se difficult to avoid continuing it n n the same &amp; sie in connection with the Empire Air Ueil Scheme, and have suggested (vide paragraph 6 of their let er quoted shove) that privilege B should he compensated for by an annual payment of n250 to each f&lt; ul«r in addition to the annual payment of €.500 for the privileges accorded under A, it being male dear that /• 2 k that the additional payment would eoter the extended frequency of eervicee vieuelleed In 1957 end n nw«rde. 5« I ee etiil of opinion that the eijepleet end meet eetlefeeterf way t© deal with » ie for cuetome duty to be peid on the ectieil emeent imported. Xf # however t the object ions to thie proimeel on the part of the Air tinietry are Tory etrong, the only alternative ie to fix a lump sum to be paid annually in lieu of euetomo duty. Bet in equity to the ? taere this eum ehould have some relation to the actual mount of duty the uler eurrendere. X do not knew # for instanoe* on whet b*eie the Atr Minietry euggeoted the eum of £.S&amp;0. rtitm the lump eum of £«&amp;0® to cover both A and B ■:&amp;.&amp; fixed the eervice had only recently been treneferred to the Arab route* and it wae difficult to arrive et any reliable data* The service has now been running on the Arab Cewiat for over three yeare and figure* of the importation of fuel for aircraft on the bade of a weekly ccrvice can doubt- leee be supplied by Imperial Airways. If this consumption ie multiplied by five this would give a rough ap proximo ties) of the fuel consumption when the service ic expanded to its mxiimim* i.e. at five services a week* i© 1957 . f h9 cuetome duty on fuel at r u** it and Bahrain ie that at Mu coat ie 1Q&amp;* but in order to bring the Sultan of Muscat into line with the ftwlcrc of ^uwoit and Bahrain the duty at Mueeat may r **‘ rr; -‘ ea s » feeing 6^ for the purposes cf aeccesing the ann ^ 1 vrymert under B (vide paragraph 9 of my Impress letter quoted above)• 4th thee# factors as a beets it ehouli be poeeible to arrive at a lump cum which would not only be fair to the Httler* but would be based 0 n a principle whxeh would bo /4 S'T -4 refedily by aim. 6. The preeeitt OiTil Air /gree^eats ere due to ea^ire in 195B* l recommend th»t the *yttem propoeed in sqt preceding peregr&amp;ph ehould be applied ae folloee* The financial cl &amp; use ol the airil Mr Agreement ehould be modified ee that the ems of f .500 paid et preeent for A end B i« el located to A only from the date on which Imperial Airamys eerrice w^-e dupliested f i.e. let January of thle year. Similarly* the eua ta t la finally fixed fer B ehiauld be allocated for that purpose from the name date, the aetuel aum paid to be &amp;&amp; a eliding ecale correeponding with the increaaee of aerrioee. ?• X hare for the aake of elearneee eoneidered the ^ XXoeatlon of theae suae under the separate headings of A and B* 2f f however, it is not desired from the point of view of the Air Kinietry to draw attention to the fact that a aaparate sua la aetoelly being pMd on account of B, doubtless the revised financial elauee could be eo corded as to include payments un er both heads in one figure. S. mh reference to paragraph 7 of the Air ttinistry letter quoted above. If the proposal in my paragraphs 5 and B above ia adopted l think It would be possible to indues the Sultan of Muscat to agree to non*paysies»t of euetoas duty in the first instance Insteed of the pres on t system of a refund. 9* It is, of course, not intended that the payment for B proposed in my paragraphs &amp; and $ above eheuld cover customs duty on fuel and oil imported by Imperial Air ways fer the use ef eircraft other than their own, the question of which is treated /&amp; • 5^ JS jB a pfe - tre&amp;ted ftepamtely unti«r th« Agreement* 10. Id oe&gt;hclM«ion 1 aunt point out th#t th« proouaption In p*rftgr«ph 6 of tho fir Ministry let tor quoted stovo is not likel;, to bo borne out by foots* Tbe i' ulors in question ore olreedy besoming concerned st the present increase of the lap or 1*1 Air trays Services se for os it offsets tn* financial terms ef their Agreements, end sill certainly prove difficult when it coaes to on ogressoent severing o further increase in these services unless they receive shot they consider te be e4equate componsetion* sd« f«C» ?owls, fisut,-Colonel* Political Eesident in the Persian Oulf* i^LLgotea*INDIA OFFICE, P.Z.7507/35. POLITICAL Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) Secretary of State Political ReBident in the Persian Gulf 6 th December 1935. POLITICAL .qENCY AND [CONFIDENTIAL KECORd ,&gt;ire - 13. OK;. 1935 ’ v NA .'C$ Repeated to Government of India, Foreign . and Political Department Political Agent, Muscat Political Agent, Bahrein Political Agent, Km eit. My express letters Nos. P.Z.6228/35 and P.&lt;u*7507/35 of 13th September and 25th October respectively. Muscat, Bahrein and Koweit Civil Air Agreements. When may I expect reply? The issue of the above has been duly authorised.Prom Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated 25th October, 1935- No. P.Z. 7507/35 My express letter No. P.Z. 6228/35 of 13th September. Muscat, Bahrein and Koweit Civil Air Agreements. 2. Copy is enclosed of further letter from Air Ministry enclosing letter from Imperial Airways. (Dated 18th ) 3* Right of Imperial Airv/ays to exemption (October 1935 ) ( (with enclosure) ) from duty on petrol or oil imported for their aircraft at Bahrein and Koweit would seem to depend, on strict interpretation of Agreements, on whether stocks were imported before or after date of these Agreements, viz. 23rd May, 1934, in case of Koweit and 6th June, 1934, in case of Bahrein, but I should be glad of your ^ observations on point raised by Imperial Airways. 4* Copies of this letter are being sent to Government of India, Bahrein and Koweit. The issue of the above has been duly authorised,V ^ w P.Z. 1501/35 • 3^56/D.D,C.A. AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, If.0.2. 18th October 1935- Sir, I an directed by the Secretary of State for Air to refer to Air Ministry letter dated 31st August last, numbered as above, on the question of exemption from customs duties of petrol and oil imported into Muscat, Bahrein and Koweit for the use of Imperial Airways Ltd, With regard to paragraph 9 of the letter under reference, I am to enclose herewith for the information of the Secretary of State for India a copy of a letter dated 3rd instant which has been received from Imperial Airways Ltd. Sir Philip Cunliffe Lister would be glad to be informed of the reply which Lord Zetland desires should be furnished to the company with regard to ^ their enquiry. I am, etc*, (Sd.) C. R. BRIG-STOGKE. THe Under Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l.Copy Prom Imperial Airways Ltd., Airway Terminus, Victoria Station, London, S.W.l. AKE/WOC.66 3rd. October, 1935- Dear Sir, Duty on Fuel Bahrein and Koweit. I am directed to draw your attention to your communication of the 8th September, 1934 reference S.32956/DDCA enclosing copies of the Air Navigation regulations issued by the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Koweit, and giving details of the terms of the agreements entered into between His Majesty T s Government and the Sheikhs. T am directed to inform you that it is understood that my Company’s fuel requirements at these two places have, since the date of the agreements in question, been drawn from duty paid Stocks and I am to ask what steps, in view of the information conveyed in paragraph 7 of your communication above referred to, which states :- ’’The Sheikh also agrees to exempt from Customs or other duties petrol imported for the purpose of refuelling aircraft.” should be taken by my Company to effect recovery of the duty paid. I am, etc., (Sd.) For and on behalf of IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED. The Secretary, Air Ministry, Gwydyr House, Whitehall, S.W.l.* I , CONFIDENTIAL GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Fil i tl nal— Department. EXPRESS LETTER 4 [iV, B. This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sui e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political, Muscat To Britctngul, Bushire. C/?ll Dated 20 th Deccmbar jtft 5 # Reference y#ur MeinarsndHK N#.C/3i3 af 5 th OctaLer 1935. I farwaru herewith (l) &amp; iraft Kin^’e Rc^ulctian ani ( 2 ) a draft Re^ulatian ta be issued by His Highness the Fultcn «f Muscat and Oman. 3• 'n aacaraance with the instructian* cantcinea in ptragrai^h 4 af yaur abare quated Memaranaum the Sultan has nat yet been appraached far his appraral af the draft Be^ulatian prapased ta be issued by him. 4. V.hen the Gultan’s draft Recwlatian is apprayed af by yau and I as instructed ta appraaeh him an the subject, I waula suggest that I endeevaur ta abtain fra* hi* by exchange ef letters rn assurance that befure actually taking rctian against any foreign ct in tar wha might be fauna guilty af cantruYcning the Reguletians he wauld in all coses canault the Political Agent. -POLITICAL S' 6. Mi) I —400SAP—(M480&gt;—36-7 SI—^2,00^00. VA if/ &lt; ■ X'g.K ^\CV 4 C/S Si cr;Kories* The following lie^ulations, utaae by His Britannic majesty*a Political iieaiueat in the j^eraian uuli, and allowed by one of Hi a - ajesty • a Principal secretaries of ^tatc 9 are published for general information* dated at nuahire this•••*••••day oi*••«•••• tJMi'i* tiMaViJiTlQ&amp;i* UVddV 78 Ob' 18* MUSCAT Oiuinn XV C .UVCIL f 1916* Vo. 1 of ld86. ir havi^ation. in pursuance and by virtue of the powers vested in the political resident in the * ersian Uulf under article 78 of tiie museat Oruer in council| Idlbi- 1. it is hereby notified that tne ^ir navigation regulations made by his ni^hness tne ^ultan of Muscat and oman 9 a translation of which is annexed to Uiis xte^ulation, are binding on the persona specified in . rticles 8 (l&gt; t and (d; of the Muscat truer in Council, ms. 2. my person or persons found guilty of contravening&lt;fb /fiii KegoXatioas to be ia&amp;ueci by iiia tLl&amp;htieea Xixe sultan of Muscat aud uaau« LiiUL It is heraby aotifiod tiiat all persons, subject to the jurisdiction of his dighness the of Muscat and Oman, who are found guilty of contravening the Air Navigation regulations issued by His highness, a trans lation of which is annexed to this notice y shall on conviction be liable to a fine not exceeding rupees I&amp;jw or with imprison ment not exceeding b months or with both fine and imprisonment together with forfei ture of the machine with which the offence is committed*/£'*/ {Lla, S. O. P. I.—247 P. A. Si H. B. M. Consnl Muscat— 6-12-11 500 Confidential. Feom To No. C /4 Major fl.r. Watts, I.a., Pomtical Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, His Majesty's secretary oi’ otate for xnaia, India Office, 1 &gt; 0 H D O M. Beitish Agency and Consulate. Muscat, the January J 9 MBS* ^ I )- With reference to your Printed Letter Wo, 3931 of 1936 dated the 31st June 1936, 1 have the honour to forward herewith the original copy of the special authorisation ior* aircraft to land in and fly over His Highness the dultan^ territories of kuscat and Oman for the year 1936, 3, Five copies of this authorisation have been forwarded to the Hobble the Political resident in the ^eriian Gulf, Bushire, 1 have the honour to be, dir, Your most obedient humble servant, f A kajor, Political ivgent c* H.lAs Consul, muscat,from customs ond excise legislation and Import end export regulations and any regulations which may he laid down for public safety as well as the air navigation regulations attached ^hereto. (ii) The aircraft shall not use as a i&gt;lsee of landing or departure within the territories of Muscat and Oman any place other than the aerodromes at Gwcdur and Shinoe, and the published conditions governing the use of the said aerodromes shall be observed. (Ill) This authorisation or a certified true copy of it sholl be carried in the aircraft and be produced on demand for the inspection of any authorised person. tan of Muscat &amp; C®rn. , oaiyid Said bin Toimur) r ^ ,Confidential. From To A. L. / &lt; r 1 No. /VS of 191 VL^ ifcaj oi* jti»y 0 «Vatt3 y i.A* f Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Hon*ble therolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf y Bush ire • * ^ British Agency and Consulate. Muscat, the Subject * Special Authorisation under the Civil Air agreement* ix Sir, Vt With reference to your Memorandum ^o. 607-s dated the 12th July 1935 9 -*• have ttie honour to forward herewith five copies of Special authorisation for aircraft to land in and fly over His Highness the sultan's territories of Muscat and Oman for the year 1936. 2* The original copy of this .authorisation has been forwarded direct to the India Office unuer my ho, C/4 of even date, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ Major, Political 'gent a H.M's Consul, Muscat,By Air Mail. f-Z. 19 3^'. POLITICAL AND CONFIDENT! L RECORD l^'e. -8. JAlU W6 ! &gt;“&lt;&gt; X'* h. e, ;,rs consulate; muscat, INDIA OFFICE, LONDON. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to Iv. (aIH jViXKIS'iKY, &lt;o P.Z.89P^/35. 467958/35/P.P.0.A. LOP uOn ; Y . C . 2 # 11th December, 1935 Sir I am directed by the Secretary ol State for Air to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that Imperial Airways Limited desire to obtain permission to land one of their aircraft at Koweit, Bahrein and Gwadur in connection ^ with a flight which they propose to carry out from London to Karachi and return. 2. The aircraft to be used is Vickers 'Velox' aeroplane G-aBKY, registered in the name of Imperial Airways, Ltd. 3. The landings will be made on or about the 18th December on the eastbound service and cn the 19th necembei on the westbound service. 4. In accordance with the terms of the agreements entered into with the Sultan of Muscat, ana the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Koweit, special authorisations for landings at Gwadur, Bahrein and Koweit, respectively, will be required. 5. I am, therefore, to request that, subject to the concurrence of Lord Zetland, the necessary instructions in the matter may be given to the Political nesident in tho Persian Gulf. 6. A copy of this letuer has been sent to the Foreign Oixice. I am, Sir Your obedient Servant, The Under '-Secretary of State India Office, S . W .1. (Sgd.) C.R. BRlGSTOCKE.P.z. 8744/35. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 23rd December, 1935. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Air Ministry letter of 31st August, No. S.329562/D.D.C.A. regarding the Bahrein, Koweit and Muscat Civil Air Agreements. ^ 2. The Marquess of Zetland notes that Lord Swinton concurs in his view regarding the desirability of revising the financial provisions*of these Agreements; but as regards the form which this revision should take he would invite attention to the Political Resident’s Express Letter of 27th November, 1935, No. 894-S/1935, a copy of which was forwarded to the Air Ministry under India Office printed letter of 9th December, No.P.Z.8744/35. 3. Lord Zetland agrees generally with the views expressed by Colonel Fowle; in particular he feels that ^ the compensatory x^&amp;yment should bear a close relation to the amount of duty which the Rulers actually surrender, and should not be limited to an arbitrary figure such as £250 which can hardly fail to be regarded by the Rulers as quite inadequate when the Empire Air Mail service is instituted. He is therefore inclined to favour Colonel Fowle 1 s first suggestion, i.e. that the sum paid annually to the Rulers should be equal to a 5 ~per cent, customs duty paid on the actual amount of fuel imported in that year. 4. If, however, this proposal is unacceptable to the Air Council on account of the unfortunate repercussions which it might have on negotiations in respect of The Secretary, Air Ministry, S.W.l.2 . other territories in the Middle East, His Lordship w.uld readily consider some arrangement wherebya lump sum would be paid annually to the Rulers, which would have no overt connection with the exemption from duty, though in fact based roughly on the amount of fuel consumed. Existing figures for the importation oi fuel for the use of Imperial Airways are no doubt available to the Air Council and would serve as a basis for calculating this sum, which would increase in proportion to the amount of fuel actually imported. For instance, a sum representing roughly the value of the ^resent exemption would be appropriate until the commencement of the Empire Air Mail, and a proportionately increased sum thereafter. 5. As Colonel Fowle foresees no difficulty in bringing the existing procedure in Muscat into uniformity with the procedure proposed for Bahrein and Koweit, it has been assumed in this letter that his proposals would a^ply to all three States. 6. his Lordship d„es not propose at this stage to suggest the actual alterations to Clauses 15 and 16 of the Koweit and Bahrein and Clauses 15 and 17 of the flu scat Heads of Agreement, which it would be necessary to make in order to give effect to his proposals. But there would be no difficulty in doing this once agreement has been reached on the form and amount of the payment which is to be made* 7. I am therefore to enquire whether the Air Council are prepared to reconsider the matter with a view to achieving an early settlement on the general lines su-teo^steu. above, the details of which can be arranged, byW V Jr.nucry, iCth, 12 o 6 # &lt; To His; Highnoes -Giyid *' 0 id bin Toimur, ultriR of ufjcat l OB;arj, Your Highness, T Koto the honour to iorwnrd herewith for record a copy of the 3poetol uthorieotion granted by 'four .Highness for Aircraft to land in and fly over Your Highness’a territories 9 during the year 1935. Your Highness’s sincere friend. &amp;oJor, Political Agent L H.B. ‘ Y Poneul,Muscat.POLITICAL Confident i* 1 * GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPR ESS LETTER (AIR MATL4 a-se^i. f [N.B. This is an ORIGINAL message, sent by AIR MAIL whir,h provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been tele raphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department. ] 19 6 th January 1^216. • To xx from - Politic* 1 Hevident, Bushirc* To Ktpe&amp;ted « Jecretfcry of Ltete for India, London. Government of Zndi#, Hew ^cihi. Political Agent, Cueait* Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Hue eat. lufcject t Sanctiene for hrecehee of Air navigation Hegulatione at } uwalt, Bahrain and p.uee&amp;t. reference eer) eependenee ending with Indio :f, ice letter Wo. P. -. 6*.'6t&gt;,• ld, dr ted the l&amp;th Lepte/sLer 19^5, I enclose copy of (a) a draft Regulation to be ieeued by the Sultan of t'useat, and (b; draft King** Regulation® in respect of Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat. It will be noticed that ia the penalties epee if led X have included iaeprisonaent only in default of payment of the fine. The reason for this is th&amp;! there are no suitable arrangements at Muscat for the impf . oomaerit of y.uropepns. It would be dlfiicult to Bt.g est to Hie Highness that the penalty of impr isomaent should not be ispoeed fcy his in the case of fore gnere wh le specifying it for imposition by 'he Political Agent in the ease of British and British protested subjects. 1 have therefore omitted as a primary penalty from both / S. 44. (Designation)ft- ^7 both (ft) ftnd ( b) f and X do not think that ill* Highneae will wi»h to impoaft it in tho eaftft of forftignft»*» wh«n tho polities! Aeftnt dooft not in tho oaoo of 9rit ah and British frotootod subject«• It it oxtromoly unlikely that any fcviator would doet to undorgo iaiprisonAent rathor than pay tho f^nc« from the practical point of viftw # a fins, with forfeiture of ths Ma«hinft f would appear to bo a sufficiently severe and deter ent penalty* 3* At Bahrain and Kuwait foreign effeniere, unlike at Kuecat, would fall un or the Politic*! and there would therefore be no queetlon of the local alert imprison- inn, foroignero* 2 th.nk, however v that it would be convenient to have a uniform penalty for the three itstee concerned* 4* hen the drafte have been approved end the Political Agent, Hue oat approaeheo BUit Highness, who ia expected to return from Xihofar about the middle of April, regard ng (a) he eould endeavour to obtain from Hia Kighnaaa an aaauranca that he will consult the .olitical Agent before taxing action against a fore gn aviator* •d* T.C.FO^le hieut.-Colonel* Political ftBsident in the Persian Half* nttestsa. for secretary to the political Resident in the J «rs *n Gulf*- 2 - Otherwise 'things' would he read as ejusdem generis with 'goods' and 'receptacles', which are not e.lusdem generis with aircraft, and there would he no provision for forfeiture of the machine. The issue of the above has been authorised. .deputy Secretary to the Government of India V, • \ \ .By &amp;zy Mail. P.Z. 2&gt;-tS 19 ^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to x ^ —- Air by Mail. Sea The^ 0 l^jOj^ 8 ^ci’etar^€rdVernm^tr 6 l India. &lt;F!ie Political Re^l dent in tb^dPersian ^GjMfT 3681?.Z. 375/36. WHITEHALL, S. W. 1 . 27th January 1936. \ Many thanks for your letter of 14th January, No.260663/33/0.A.1, which I am answering as Laithwaite is m India, enclosing a statement of the charges to he included under Schedule II of the Muscat Civil Air Agreement. 2. The relevant Schedule will he revised the next time that we reprint the Agreement. in the meantime e ar ° ^- 1 - c d-a o Aig copies of the schedule as amended to &lt;.he holders of the Print, viz: the Foreign Office, India, Bus,lire, Muscat, Bahrein and Koweit. I enclose 10 copies for your use. 3. Office, letter Burkett Esq., B.S., M.C., | Ministry, I am sending a copy of this letter to the Foreign to whom I suggest you should send a copy of your (without enclosure) to complete their file. Yours s2nooPQ&amp; {Sgd.) M. «J 0!P.z. 375/36. AIR MINISTRY, 260663/33/C.A.1, GTYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S 1 14th January 1936. * Dear Laithwaite, We have been in correspondence with Imperial Airways Ltd., regarding their charges for attendance and facilities at Gwadur, and have agreed to their scale for commercial aircraft. We have also induced them to lower their charges for private aircraft. It will he desirable for steps to be taken to revise the schedule in the Muscat Civil Air Agreement (R.Z.7399 and P.Z.540/3£&gt;) in accordance with the enclosed statement. Perhaps you will arrange for this to be done at a convenient opportunity. Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) W.W. BURKETT. J.G. Laithwaite Esq., India Office, S. W. 1.SCHEDULE II. Charges for Attendance and Facilities. A A (a) For Privately owned air craft. Attendance of a representative at the aerodrome, notifying the arrival and departure to the Customs Passport and other officials concerned, Customs clearance of aircraft, providing available meteorological reports, notifying fuel and oil suppliers and dispatching arrival ^ and departure messages: ^ 10 /- for each arrival and departure on the same day. 15/- for arrival on one day and departure on the next. 5 /- for every additional day the aircraft is at the aerodrome. 10 /- for each day when attendance at the aerodrome is requested hut the aircraft does not arrive. The above fees do not include out-of-pocket expenses ^ such as transport to the aerodrome, telegrams, Customs lees, meals, accommodation, etc. which will he charged at cost. (h) For aircraft engaged in -public transport. Weight (as deigned in Schedule l)not exceeding Lbs. Arrival and departure the same day. Arrival one day and departure the next. Each addit ional day the aircraft is at the aerodrome. Each day when attendance is requested but the aircraft does not arrive. i,800 3,000 4,500 7,000 10,000 j.15,000 to ''30,000 £. s. d. £. s. d. £. s« d. £. s. d. 0•15. 0. 1 . 0 . 0 . 0 • 10 . o. o.io. 0 . 1 . 0 . 0 . 1. 5. 0 . 0 . 12 . 6 . o.io. 0 . 1. 5. 0. 1.15. 0 . 0 » —5. o. 0 . 10 . 0 . 1 . 10 . o. 2 . 0 . 0 . 1 . 0 . 0 . 0»-&gt;-2 * 0 . 1 »15. 0 . 2. 5. o. 1 . 5. o. 0. 15. 0 . CO • o o 2 . 10 . 0 . 1 . 10 . o. 1 . 0 . o. Fuel and Oil. The current rates will be quo t ed by the Aerodrome agents.SCHEDULE II. Charges for Attendance g.nrl raciliti 6 s._ v (a) Eor Privately owneci aircrar ty Attendance of a representative at the aerodrone, notifying the arrival and departure to the Customs Passport and other officials concerned. Customs clearance of aircraft, providing available meteorological reports, notifying fuel and oil suppliers and dispatching arrival ^ and departure messages: ^ IQ)/- for each arrival and departure on the same day. 15/- for arrival on one day and departure on the next. 5 /- for every additional day the aircraft is at the aerodrome. 10 /- for each day when attendance at the aerodrome is requested hut the aircraft does not arrive. The above fees do not include out-of-pocket expenses such as transport to the aerodrome, telegrams. Customs fees, meals, accommodation, etc. which will be charged at co^u. (b) For aircraft engaged in public trans port. Wej^igt (as def ned in Schedule l)not ex ceding lbs. Arrival and departure the same day. Arrival one day and departure the next. Each addit ional day the aircraft is at the aerodrome. Each day when attendance is requested but the aircraft does not arrive. £. s. d. £. s . d * £• s • a. £. s. d. ~,800 0 • 15. 0. 1. 0. 0. o.io. o. o.io. o. 3,000 1. 0. 0. 1 « 5 » 0 » 0 . 12 . 6 . 0.10. 0. 4,500 1. 5. 0. 1.15. 0. 0.15. o. 0 . j-0 . o . 7,000 1 . 10 . o. 2. 0. 0. 1. 0. 0. 0 * Ad * 0 . 10,000 1.15. 0. 2. 5. 0. 1. 5. o. 0» — 5. 0 * 15,000 to &lt;$20,000 2. 0. 0. 2.10. 0. 1.10. o. _» 0 • 0 . (o) Fuel and Oil. The current rates will be quoted . by the Aerodrome agents.' SCHEDULE II. Charges for Attendance an d Facil ities.- ( a ) For Privately owned Attendance of a representative at the aerodrone, notifying the arrival and departure to the Customs Passport and other officials concerned. Customs clearance; of aircraft, available meteorological reports, notifying fuel and oil suppliers and dispatching arrival and departure messages: 10 /- for each arrival and departure on the same day. 15/- for arrival on one day and departure on the next. 5 /- for every additional day the aircraft is at the aerodrome. ]_ 0 /- for each day when attendance at the aerodrome is requested hut the aircraft does not arrive. The above fees do not include out-of-pocket expenses such as transport to the aerodrome, telegrams. Customs fees, meals, accommodation, etc. which will he charged at cost. (b) For aircraft engaged in 'public transport^ Wei .t (as defined in Scr^dule l)not exceeding lbs. Arrival and Arrival one departure day and the same day. departure the next. Each addit ional day the aircraft is at the aerodrome. Each day when attendance is requested but the aircraft does not arrive. 1,800 0.15. 3,000 1 . 0 . 4,500 1. 5. 7,000 1 . 10 . 10,000 1.15. &gt;15,000 to 30,000 2 . 0 . d. £ . s . d. £ * S * d. £. s. d. 0 . 1 . 0 . 0 . o. 10 . o. o. 10 . o. 0 . 1. 5. 0 . o. 12 . 6. 0 . 10 . 0 . 0. 1 . 15. 0 . o. ^ o . o. o. 10 . o. o. 2. 0. o. 1 . , 0 . 0 . o. j .2 » o. 0 . 2. 5. o. 1 . i 5 . 0 . o. 15. 0 . 0 . 2. 10 . 0 . 1 i . 10 . o. _L • 0 . o. (c) Fuel and Oil. The current rates will be quoted by the Aerodrome agents' * By Air Mail. p.z. ^g s ~0 ii) 3'6 POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD . ——• Date. - 7 . MAY iy^u Uf'lT No_ / H. B, M’S CONSULAH; MUSCAT, 9 / INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, r Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to jt. , ; by Mail. 3681 The Foreign Secretary, G-oV’efa-ment of India. ¥ro Political Reside.nr. in the PeraiaiLG ntf.-P. Z.2550/36. Air M ail INDIA OFPICA, , /HITjjHi-iijjj &gt; S. .v. 1. 21 st Aprils 1936. V/ill you please jfer to your express letter of 27tli November 3 N0.894-S of 1935 and connected correspondence about the possibility of revising the financial clauses of ni ^ '/T the Noweit, Bahrein and Muscat Civil Air Agreements. I now st er o_i _ 9th enclose a copy of a letter from the Air Ministry upon which we shall be glad to receive your views. The figures attacned to the Air Ministry letter show clearly the value of the exemptions from petrol and oil dutieSj and we now at last have all the cards on the table. You will see that if the increased payments to the Rulers ^ v.-ere strictly cased on the estimated increase in consumption, uney would prooably be larger than those now proposed. On the other nand we feel that there is considerable force in the argument (which the Air Ministry very strongly urged in interdepartmental discussion) that were the Rulers to observe cne now reco^niseo. international practice of granting ieutenant-colonel T.C. Fowle, C.B.E., Consul General, Bushire. -n \ r&gt; i ' 2 . drawback, their claims to compensation would disappear, tfe suggesu, therefore, that the present proposals put xorward Dy the Air Ministry, which constitute a suosbantial advance on their previous proposals, are worth sympathetic consideration and that it is probably noc too much to expect the rulers to tie themselves down for 7 years in return for the financial advantages which they would derive. laie ^inaneial benelits which will accrue to the rulers unaer each of the two alternatives suggested by the Jiir j;,llnlstr J seem to be nicely balanced. It seems unlikely L-.i^t the endurance of aeroplanes will increase to such an extent within the next 7 years that it will be possible to dispense with the present stopping places, so it appears that alternative (b) is almost as safe an arrangement as alternative (a). In either case it would be necessary to revise articles 16 and 17 of the Civil Air Agreements as well as article 15 in the case of Muscat, as it is clearly essential that the sultan of Muscat should agree to non payment of customs duty in the first instance. The choice oeeween the two alternatives appears, therefore, primarily to depend upon which will be the easier to negotiate.3. (b) might from this point of view be preferable, as it is based on a simple and logical princiiDle, moreover the figure of £150 per weekly flight compares favourably with the present actual value of the exemption at Bahrein (£ r -^0 for two flights; and appears to be almost exactly the present value at Muscat if calculated on a 5^&gt; basis (£597 at 10yo). As you will see Treasury authority has to be obtained beiore the rulers can be approached, so we should be grateful for your comments as soon as possible, o. Could you please also look into the case of the claims for refund at Gwadur mentioned in India Office lecoers of £ 2 nd October, 1935, and 5th March, 1936. ^* I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Metcalfe, Loch, watts and be Gaury. Vouis sinoerai*-&lt;?s J AIR MINISTRY, LORjX)R j W. C. 2. S. 32956 (Part II) P.77. 9th April, 1936. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for Air to refer to your letter of the 23rd December last, P.Z.8744/35, regarding the question of the revision of the Bahrein, Koweit and Muscat Civil Air Agreements, to subsequent semi official correspondence, and to the meeting between repre sentatives of the India Office and Air Ministry on the 13th ultimo. TVhile, as stated in this Department’s letter of the 31st August last, S.32956/ll/D.D.C•A., Lord Swinton agrees that in view of the increased use of the landing grounds and the still further use which will be made under the Empire Air Mail Scheme, some increase in the annual payments to the rulers of Bahrein and Muscat is justified, he is very reluctant to agree that such increase should be directly related to the quantities of oil fuel imported into these states for the purpose of refuelling the machines. I am to enclose a copy of a statement furnished by Imperial Airways shewing the present annual imports of petrol and oil and the duty charged, together with estimates of the corresponding figures when the Empire Air Mail Scheme is in operation. The Company point out that the figures are given with some reserve as they understand that further debits are to be received for the 6 months ended 30th September, 1935, suppliers having charged incorrect amounts. The Under-Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, S. W. 1.2 . It is now a recognised international practice to grant exemption from Customs or other duties in respect of fuel and oil taken on board for the purpose of operating machines to places outside the territory in which the stock is maintained, and where duty has already been paid, a Customs drawback is granted in respect of any quantities of oil and petrol supplied to aircraft for use in such c ir c urns z anc e s. If, therefore, the rulers of these tv/o States conformed to international practice, the complaint as to the apparent loss of customs revenue owing to the operation of the exemption clause in the civil air agreements, would disappear. Lord Swinton also desires to point out that, apart from the advantages which will accrue to the territories by the establishment of the civil air routes, the continued maintenance of such a route through these territories facilitates the passage of military aircraft in emergency, which is an essential requirement if His Majesty’s Government are to be enabled to come to the assistance of these rulers in time of emergency. In these circumstances Lord Swinton would prefer to base the increased rentals at Bahrein and Gwadar on the general increase in use by Imperial Airways of the facilities provided and would be prepared to seek Treasury authority for either of the following alternatives (a) Lev/ Aigrssnis-Uis for 7 years at an increased rental of £ 1,000 a year with retrospective effect to the date ,vhen che service was duplicated, viz: 1st January, 1935, covering the privileges enumerated under ’A 1 and n B TI of the political Resident’s Express Letteror 894/s of 27th November last. (b) to revise the existing agreements to provide for their continuance for a further period of 7 years . with an increased payment of £150 a year in respect of each additional service undertaken by Imperial Airways over and above the first service covered by the payment of £500 a year under the original agreement. I am accordingly to suggest that the Political I Resident in the Persian Gulf should be informed of the foregoing views and be asked to consider the possibility of negotiating agreements with the rulers of Bahrein and Muscat on one or other of the bases suggested in substitution for the existing agreements which are not due to expire until the 6 th June, 1938, and 25th October, 1938, respectively. Colonel Powle y^ill no doubt point out to the rulers concerned that under the first alternative they would receive a guaranteed annual amount, irrespective of the number of services in operation, whilst under the latter arrangement, there is a possibility of variation in the amounts payable, as in the event of an improvement in the endurance of machines employed on this route, landings at one of the intermediate stopping places might be rendered unnecessary. It is assumed that in view of the increased payments offered under either alternative, the Sultan of Muscat would agree to non-payment of Customs duty in the first instance, instead of the present unfortunate system of a quarterly refund. With regard to Koweit, I am to explain that this landing ground is not scheduled as a regular stopping place under the Empire Air Mail Scheme and it will only be used on special occasions or in emergency. Lord Swinton does not consider, thereiore, that any reason exists for an increase4. V in the annual payment of £500 to the ruler. A copy of a letter dated 5th March, 1930, which has beenr eceived from Imperial Airways, Ltd. with regard to the difficulty which is being experienced by the Company in obtaining refund of duty on petrol and oil uplifted at Gwadar from 26th October, 1934, to 31st December, 1935, is also attached, and I am to request that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may be ashed to take such action as is possible with a view to obtaining the refund of duties in accordance with the Civil Air Agreement. I am etc. (Sd.) C.R. Brigstocke/ ♦ COPY. % SAD/JG/1189. Sir, € w IMPiiiBlAL PTD • , airway Terminus, Victoria Station, London, S.'V.l. 5th March, 1936. Refund of Fuel Duties at Gwadar. I am to refer to our letter of the 12nd October, 1935, reference KHS/TLJ, 7955, to which we have not yet received a reply. In case our original letter has been mislaid, I attach a copy for your information. Paragraph 9 of your letter of the 8 th July, 1935, reference S.32956/L . 1 ). 0 . states:- n The Sultan has agreed that whilst all oil and petrol for the use of aircraft, other than Royal Air Force aircraft, will be subject to the importation duties in force, he will refund quarterly the duties collected on all oil and fuel that may have been actually issued for the exclusive use of your Company, such amounts being certified by the agents appointed as suppliers by His Majesty’s Government. In this connection I am to inform you that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, through their agents at Gwadar, have been appointed as suppliers by His Majesty’s Government for this purpose.” I am no 7 / informed by our Cairo Office that in accordance with the above, claims amounting in all to about £650 for refund of duty on petrol and oil uplifted at Gwadar from 26th October, 1934 to 31st December 1935 ft ave been submitted quarterly to the Director of Customs, Gwadar. All such claims have been rejected, and it appears evident that both the Director of Customs, Gwadar, and the Director of Revenue, Muscat, are unaware of the terms of.the agreement between the Sultan and His Majesty’s Government. I am to request you therefore to advise us as soon as possible what steps we should now take to recover the duties paid on the petrol and oil in question. I am, etc., For and on behalf of IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD. The Secretary, Sgd. S.A.DISMORE. Air Ministry, Gv/ydyr House, Whitehall, S.W.l./OO * COPY . KHS/TLJ. 7955. 22nd October, 1955. Sir, Refund of Fuel Duties at Gv/adar . I am to refer to our letter of the 21 st august last, reference ^RR/JG/334, in which your attention was drawn to the fact that there appeared to be some doubt as to the application of the provision for the refunds of duties to my Company, referred to in paragraph 9 of your letter, reference 3.32956/1.1.0.^., of the 8 th July, 1935. Ye have now received a further intimation from the lirector of Customs, Gwadar, to the effect that the lirector of Revenues, Muscat, has stated that under Muscat Government regulations no refund of customs duty paid on any articles once imported is permissible, either on re-export or uplif t, etc. This decision seems to be completely at variance with the information which you have given us on this subject, and it is thought that there must be some misunderstanding as to the position. I would, therefore, request that you advise us, as soon as possible, as to the exact nature of the present position regarding the refunds of duties to this Company at Gwadar. Yours faithfully, for and on behalf of IMPERIAL YIEWMYS LIMITS!. Sgd. S..X.DISMORE. assistant General Manager. The Secretary, Air Ministry, Adastral Pxouse, Kingsway, W.C. 2 .CONFIDENTIAL. No. 343-3 of 1936. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Tile Political /igent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). POLITICAL AGEKC* CONFIDENTIhL kecord Ihite. \ 5. .4 AY .od*o N-/./ 1 ^ h. b. ui’s British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. dth..May..1936. Reference to previous correspondence: Governinent of India’s ^jrpresa Letter Uo.F.403-N/35, dated 4th Feoruary 1936. Description of Enclosure. # Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter Ho.P.;;. 1041 /36, dated 2 bth Karch 1936 to Foreign Office. SANCTIONS FOR BREACHES OF AIR NAVIGATION REGULATIONS India Office letter No.?.Z.lG41 /36, dated 25th MHrch 1956 to Air Ministry.P.Z. 1041/1936. IUDIA cri’ics, VHlTSliAIX, IX)UPON, S.W. 1. 2Bth March 1936. ‘V- ftvernment of India’s letter of 4th } February 1936, No.F.403-N/35. ) Sir, f W W J am directeu by the Secretary of State for India to refer to India Office demi-official letter of 22nd January, No.P.Z.356/36, enclosing drafts , prepared by the Political Resident, of a Regulation to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat and of King’s Regulations in respect of Kuwait, Bahrain and «Iuccat, to be issued under the respective Orders in Council, providing sanctions for breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air -^av igat i on Re&amp;ulat i ons , and to forv*ard a copy of the express letter noted in the margin. 2. The Mfcrquees of Zetland agrees with the Government of India and Political Resident in the Persian Gulf as to the desirability of such Regulations and has no observations to make on the drafts as amended by the Government of India, except that he does not think it advisable to adopt the Government of India’s suggestion in regard to the specific insertion of 'aircraft”, at any rate in its present form. If aircraft are separately specified as an addition to the category in question it would appear to suggest that aircraft would not be included in the expression “goods, receptacles or things” which however are the only objects in respect of which forfeiture can be authorised under the terms of the relevant paragraphs of the Orders in Council. If the wording submitted by the Resident is to be altered, His ~ „ , Lordship/ The Under Secretary of State, FOR HIGH OFF I CIS. Copy sent to IndiaLordship would prefer to let it read ’’goode, receptacles, or t hings (including aircraft)’*. 3. Since the regulations provide for the confiscation of tiK aircraft. His Hardship considers tnat it would be superfluous to include, as an additional penalty, the refusal of refuelling facilities. 4. if Mr. Secretary Kden agrees with the terms of the proposed King’s Regulations with the modifications suggested, and subject to the observations of the Air Ministry to whom a copy of this letter is being sent, 1 am to request that the uenoai steps may in due course be taken with a view to the formal allowance of the Regulations Copies of the draft Regulations in the modified form suggested are enclosed for facility of reference. The Foreign Office will, however, no doubt consider whether, as may appear preferable, the Regulations should be issued under Articles 83, 70 and 78 of the Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat Orders in Council respectively without the reference to the specific sub-paragraph (b) of those Articles wihch appears in the draft enclosed. (In this connection reference is invited to Lord Monteagel’s letter of 29th May 1930, No.S.2722/2722/91). 5. I am to observe that the Secretary of State, in his letter of 4th February, No.P.Z. 463/36, suggested that a King’s Regulation might be issued under the Bahrein Order in Council to regulate the possession and traffic in arms. If Mr. Secretary Eden concurs in t hat suggestion and takes steps to allow the Regulations,the present proposed King’s Regulation under the Bahrein Order in Council will, of c ourse,P.Z. 1041/36. HID IA OPFICK, WHITEHALL, IrDSDON, 1 . 25th Itorch 1936. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to correspondence on the question of sanctions .-n to be applied in the event of breaches of the Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations ending with the Air ^ftl-tical Resident’s Express Letter of 6 th January, No. lo-f-O S36 with enclosures. A**) India Office demi-official letter to Foreign ) Office of 2£nd January, No.p.z.356/36. ) Government of India Express Letter of 4th ) February, No.F.403-K/35. ) India Office letter to Herein Office ) No.p.z*1041/5G, dated 25th March 1936. ) the papers noted in the margin. I am to enquire whether the A.ir Council have any comments to offer on the terms of the King’s Regulations in respect of Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat which it is now ^ proposed to issue/ under the respective Orders in Council, , and to the Regulation to be issued by the Sultan of Muscat. Ministry’s demi- official letter of 11 th September, Mo.41S8&amp;o/S5/C.A.l, , / 7 and to forward a copy of I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sd. J.C. WALTON. The Secretary, Air Ministry. Copy sent to India.Confidential S9»4tS»8 of 1956 British tosidenoy *' Consulats-Cei»r« 1, Bub hi re , the t??hid May, 1936. to The Poll Meal Agent, Kuwait. * POLITICAL . 0c'cy an [confidential reccr lift. ;0 A'-t; ;Vi^CAt, p. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muaeat. / Pajeetv*u Secretary of State for Inriia, linden, with one certified copy of each of the King a Begulationa, duly cowuleted. foreign Becretary to the (Joyernraent of Indian Simla, nith signed and three plain copies of each of the King’s Regulations. Subject : King’s ??egulations proriding Band Iona for breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and fcuscwt Mr navigation Regulations. ragOTUimUM. v^j£&lt;f{ Heferenee correspondence ending with *y Printed Letter Ho.343-S dated the 8th May 1956. g. I enclose copy of India Office letter .P.Z.SOXP/SC dated the S+h Pay 1936, and of the Sbreign Office letter of •• 30th April mentioned in paragraph 3 thereof, together with one certified copy, one signed copy and 30 plain copies of the Kuwait Air Navigation Regulation 1936. The certified £»***» Muscat copy (with the annexure wentiened) should be exhibited and the date of exhibition should be telegraphed to this office and to the Government of India. 3. To Muscat only . A copy of the draft Regulation mentioned in paragraph 3 of the Indio Office letter referred to is enclosed. You should reriuee*** the Rultan at the first available opportunity to issue the Regulation affect ing persons subject to his Jurisdiction and endeavour at the sane time to obtain from His Highness by an exchange of letters /letters an assurance that he sill consult you before takln* aotlon ayalnet a foreign aviator (see paragraph 4 of ny ■Express letter ho.lS-3 dated the Sth January 1936). The insue of the King's Hegulation, hoeever, need not he delaved on this account. sd. f'G+fomX*, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Konident in the Persian WIT At t rated. fdr ^cretar:^ to the Political ’Resident in the Persian r HilfoCopv. nroiA ovinGK, wm^KHAU,, a.w.i. P*Z*301£/36o 5th Mav 1936. By Air Mail . Bir # I ara directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Sovernwent of India’s KxpreBB Letter of 4th 'ternary, Woo^.403-N/35, a copy of •which waa sent to you direct, and to inform you that the Kind's Hegulationa, provid ing aa net lone for 'breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Hegulations, have now been formally allowed. I am to enclose one signature, *hree certified and forty plain copies of each of the three Regulations. I am to nrnmr# request you to issue •’•hese Regulations, after having signed, dated and numbered them in the usual manner, and to return one certified copy of each duly completed to this depart ment for transmission to the foreign Office. In this connection I am to enclose, for information, a copy of the * I ) letter noted in the margin. Foreign Office letter of j 30th April, No.B.1662/3^7/91.) ) 3. I am also to enclose a draft of the Regulation which it is proposed should be issued h' the Sultan of Muscat. 4. A copy of this letter together with one copy of each of the three Regulations is being sent to the Government of India. I am, Hir, Your obedient servant, ad. M..T.Olauson. The Hon’ble Lieut • -Colonel .0. Ifcwle,CBR., H.BoM .*8 Consulate-General, Bushire.Copy. Jt f a.w.i 30th April, 1036 c Sir I am directed by Mr. Hecretarv 'Rden to refer to your letter of 25th March (&gt;?.£♦ 1041/36) forwarding the text o^ King’s Hegulatioua in respect of Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat. these Hegulations have been prepared for issue and I am to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, one signed, three certified and 40 plain copies of each of the three Begulations together with two copies of each for your own files. 2. I am to request t v at the *?oliMcal Besident at Bushire may be instructed to issue the Kegulations a^ter having signed dated and numbered them in the usual manner and to return one certified copy of each duly completed, when the usual distribution In this country will be made. I am. Sir Your obedient servant od. Stephen Oaselc 6 The Mnder-Secretary of State, INDIA O^ICETOSGTTLA^lOH ^0 BB I r r&gt;T 7 I?T) BY HI ft HIGHNKB3 ^TO? SULTAN 0? HUB CA^ ANU OHAIU AIH UAHlGA r \tOH HRC^TLA^IOH. it is hereby notified that all persons subject to the jurisdiction of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman who are found guilty of contravening the Air navigation Regulations for Civil Aircraft made by His Highness, a copy of vfc ich Is annexed hereto, shall, on conviction, be liable to a fine not exceeding Rb*» 1500, and, in default, to simple Imprisonment no* exceeding three months; and any goods, receptacles or things (including aircraft) in relation to T 7 hich the offence has been committed, shall be liable t 0 forfeiture. ####**MUSCAT. NOTICE. The following Regulation, made by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and allowed by His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, is published for general information. T.C.FOWLE, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gidf. Bushire, &amp;&amp;nd May , 1986 . King’s Regulation under Article 78 of “ Muscat Order in Council, 1916.” No. 1 of 1936. 1. Within the limits of The Muscat Order in Council, 1915,” the Air Navigation Regulations for civil aircraft made by His ^■’ghness the Sultan of Muscat, a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall be binding on the persons specified in articles 8 (1), (2) and (8) of the said Order. 2. Any person found guilty of an offence against the said Regulations shall, in accordance with article 79 (2) and fS) of the 8 5 2 5—3 13041—32 , ^ •- liable to a fine not exceeding ^id Order, on conviction be imptison ment not exceeding 1 500 rupees and, m default, ‘o 8 ™?^ or things (including air- tliree months; and any g 0 °d s - P has been committed shall, in craft) in relation ^^^^^aid Order, be liable to forfeiture, accordance with am * . - The Muscat Air Navigation s . Tills Regulation may be Cited as -Rixrmlntion. Lieut. - Colonel , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf . Bushire, , 1936. Hi AnoWed: ANTHONY EDEN, . Britannic Majesty’s Principal ^cretary of Statesaid Order, on conviction be liable to a fine not exceeding 1 500 rupees and, in default, to simple imprisonment not exceeding three months; and any goods, receptacles or things f including an- craft) in relation to which the offence has been committed shall, m accordance with article 79 (1) of the said Order, be liable to forfeiture. 3 . This Regulation may be cited as ' ‘ The Muscat Air Navigation Regulation, 198(1.” T.C.FOWLE, Lieut. -Colonel , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 2Znd May , 1936. Allowed : ANTHONY EDEN, His Britannic Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.0 y No. 4 Si 4 -S of 1930 . British Residency and Consulate General, Bushire, the 13rd May 1930. /of g'r w \ - To The Political The Political The Political PO ! F c POLITICAL mMwm nmi -iw^ | • t :;i&gt; 5 Agent, Kuwait. Agent, Bahrain. Agent, Muscat. CONFIDENT L KLCORD 1 Me. - : jOK m 7 . ‘*’h ±ij MEMQBANDUM. The Kuwait jjahrain Air Mavigation Regulations, 193*5. Muscat ^ Reference my memorandum No.41a- W r S, dated £ind May 193o. 2. Any case falling uncer the King's Regulation quoted above should, if time permits, be reported to me by telegram, which should indicate the action proposed# before such action is actual y taken. Sd. T.C.FO/LE, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. tpt Sec etary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.&amp; CONFIDENTIAL. No. 421-S of 19S6. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat .V and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document f or record. POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD D*»e. 10. JiilV Heg, No, [/i H. B, M ‘8 GOMSUUTf; MUSCAT. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.... 27th. ■ • -May.... 195.6 * % Reference to previous correspondence: l^esiicfirjicy Printed letter hio.545—8 of 6 th May 1936, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Air Ministry letter No. 41 895/o5/C.A.l of 21st April 1936 to the India Oitfice. Subject. Sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations.Copy* P.Z.2758/36. 41 895/35/C.A.1* AIK MINISTRY, LONDON.W.C.2. 21st April, 1936. I am directed by the Secretary of State for Air to refer to India Office letter of 25th March, No. P.Z. 1041/36 and enclosures on the question of sanctions to be applied in the event of breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations. 2 . In reply, I am to state that Lord Swinton concurs with the terms of the proposed King* s Regulations to be issued in respect of Kuwait, banrain and Muscat subject to the modifications suggested by the Government of India and to the further amendment proposed in paragraph 2 of the India Office letter of 25th March to the Foreign Office. 3. Lord Swinton presumes that the wording of the Air Navigation Eegulatinns to be issued bjj the dal tan of Muscat and Oman will be brought into line with the modified terms of the proposed King 1 s Regulation. I c.m , e v c •, Sgd. A. H.SELF. % The Under Secretary of State, India Office, E.W.l. COPY GENT TO INDIA.CONFIDENTIAL. 453-S of 1956. /O t -The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* The Hon*hie Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, KCIE*,CSI.,iSVO., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 2. Captain G.S.ce Gaury, MC., Political Agent, £uw it. 5. Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain* 4. Major R*P.Watts, I*A*, Political Agent, Muscat, «■ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL KECORD Date. 10. JM. / 5 ^ | H, 8 , IVS MHSUtaD: British Consulate-General, BIISHIRE Dated... ,27.th. May. .19.36* Reference to previous correspondence: India Office letter No.2550/56 dated the 21st April 1956. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Demi-official letter Ko. 432-S of 27th May 1936 to M.J*Clausen £*sq.,Tne India Office, London*the * ! .n.-l.-'r-i of 1936. JmtmSmmminmm &gt;■ i »i »n« -imw jin Bvshlr« t the f7th May 19e6 C uld you pl©&amp;a*f to youjr Ho.f'• I* ^560/6 4ftt«4 ta# aitt April 192S6, with ft&amp;elofturw fro» the Air Ministry # Oh the subject of thft revision ot t£* finunci«l olwusot of thft Air Kuwait, B*hr*lB ao &lt;2 Mu45c^t Clvil/A 4 re«wnts• &gt;-V *v 2. ^ith r€^:gL.r^ .to. jesy view# after discuesioc with de Cfrory are as follows! The Air Ministry - vid# paragraph 10 of their letter - do not conailer that any reason exists for an Incre&amp;se In the annua. 1 payment of K &amp;00 to tne holer Sine# Kvmmtt is not scheduled as a regular stopping pleca under the Baplre Air Mall Cohere &amp;m it will only be used on special occasions or in energeoey* Kuwait under the present ftehMft is already scheduled ss si non-regular stopping pl^ce but in spite of this Xft^ftriitl Airways* planes nave made fairly frequent stops. It is&amp;y be that under the Supine Air leil Sehess, ir. spite of the fret that Kuwait will not b« a regular stopping plaee # Inperlf1 Airways with their 5 dey a week service will continue to stop on the mm average per service. Experience during 1927 will show whether this occurs or not, end If it does* and the ih*lirh in consequence applies for an increase of his presort ^amoscl runtfrl* Of S 500, the aattwr could be taken up when his present Agrcc«ent is cue for renewal in May j9£8, ■.('Ito r»g»rq to F^?gal» ui t 'i a.w»c^t . I eta of opinion th&amp;t cither of the Air Ministry* s proposals arc fair. As far &amp;» negotiations with these Eulers is cor.cfc.rned 1 propose trying to / M*J,Cl&amp;uson Esquire, Tne India Office, London,P.R. llaj or Watts• V Discussed with Major Watts, wno thinks that either of the two alternatives (a) or (b) is quite fair to Muscat, It is up to us to press the Rulers of Banrain and Muscat to accept one of tne alternatives but we should leave the choice to the Ruler himself. Major Watts thinks that to persuade the Sultan to alter his present system of giving a drawback will be rather difficult. The India Office refer to tne system of international drawbacks, the Air Ministry in their letter talk of ’exemption*. Probably the Air Minibtry are correct but if it is a case of drawback then the Sultan would appear to have a good deal on his side, I will get Political Agent Bahrain’s views from Bushire and will then reply to Mr.Clauson’s letter.** T.C.F. Kuwait i/5/36107 Confidential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, E..^ . ' 2 TTER [iV. B,-This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt,, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From - Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat. POLITICAL . GENCY AND COHFIDENTIAL RECORD Dare. 10 . No H. 6, „!'s OONSlILAff; W{!SCAl ( XtK 434-S of 1936. Dated 27th Ma y J 33 6 f Last paragraph of Air Ministry letter No.S.32956 (Pt II)FW, dated the 9th April 1936, enclosed with India Office demi-official letter No.P.2.2550/36 dated 21st April 1936, copy sent to you direct. 2. Please let me know the result of your enquiries as soon 4. as possible. Attested. \ sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut•-Colonel• Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. S. 6. MEP—1515 S&amp;P—(M-2089)—2-4-35—200,000.Telegram - G.T.C. From - Political, Muscat. To - Britconsul, Bush ire. Repeated - Foreign Simla. No. - 72. Dated — 11th June 1936. Reference your Memorandum No. 418-S of May 22nd. Regulation exhibited June 3rd. -POLITICAL-Confidential. / GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] ^oXltlcaX 9 Muscat* 10 - Brltcoaaul, Bushire• auhjaets itelunu or duty on fual at Garadur# ^ c-73. ^ 16 th Jua . i I v / iiafaranot your Kxpreas latter Mo* of 27th May I936* 2* Ob receipt on May 7th or India Office latter Mo* 4'»£*2660/36 of 2Iat *tpril 1926 I approached the wultan 1 s Hepreaantative on the question of the refund of duty on fuel at Gwadur but he infonaed tie that this was one of the subjects he was specifically forbidden by the Gultan from dealix^ with during the latter*s absence, and in any case he had no information about it* 3* The director of ^avenues was away on tour at tht time but on his return last week to Muscat X asked hi- if he knew anything about the matter* He stated that in consequence of &amp; ''o*- .unication he had received scone time in October last year from the *oain of Customs at Gwadur concerning a letter to him from Imperial Airways claiming the refund of duty, he had asked for instructions from the dultan. His Highness, according to the director of Heveauae yll\ - 2 - promised to issue a written order authorising the payment to Imperial Air May» of the amount due hut it appears that he left for Dhofar without doing so* In the absence of such authority the Director of Revenues declares that he Is unable to make any refund* 4* Under the circumstances X am afraid that nothin can be done in the matter until it is possible to get in c omm unication with the dultan which will not be possible in the ordinary way until about the end of dept ember* -POLITICAL- rA' No - 518-3 of 1936. CONFIDENTIAL. I CONFIDENTIAL^^ ECORt n , ? 0 aOt. t 93 fi i ! * &gt;y&gt; g, Xo ! &lt; z'y fl. COMSOUTf; MUSCAT, The Hon’ble the phments to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com 1* ihe Hon f ble Sir Aubrey Metcalfe,KCr5*f CSI^^MVO** Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* • 2. Major R.F.Watts, Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. y \fri Dated. 30th June 1936* Reference to previous correspondence : All India Office letter fjb *P* Z*2550/36 of 2lst April 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. t Subject. * Demi-official letter no* Revision of the financial. 517-S of 30th June 1936 clauses of the Muscat, to M.J* Clauson Bsq., fhe Kuwait and Bahrain Civil India Office, 'ondonf Air Agreements.iS] GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N % Z &gt;,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] \ From To Political Besident, Camp Shiraz* Political Agent, Muscat * Political Agent, Bahrain. V&lt;v 0/144 T)nte/1 26 til August 6' Bevisicn of the financial clauses of the Bahrain and Muscat Civil Air Agreements. ■ - Beference correspondence ending with Secretary of State for India's Express Letter No. P.Z.5688/36 dated the 15th August 1936, copy sent to you direct. Shaikh 2. On your return to headquarters please approach the Bahrain Sultan ~ V of accordingly. Muscat 3. Tc Muscat only : Please take up at the same time the point mentioned in paragraph 4 of Colonel Powle's demi-official letter No. 432-S dated the 27th May 1936, and the question of the refund of duty on fuel at Grwadur dealt with in correspondence ending/- S. 6. MFP—1515 S&amp;P—(M-2089)—2-4-35—200,000.ending with ycur Express Letter No. C -73 dated the 15tn June 1936. Ed/- Gr. LcoL, Lieutenant- Colonel# Offgs Political Resident in the Persian Grulf. Attested * rcr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Culf.INDIA OiFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l P.Z.5222/36. l 0th August, 1936. j v'/ill you please refer to the last paragraph of the Air Ministry’s letter of 9th April, No .'S. 32956 (Part IlJf.W., in regard to the difficulty experienced by Imperial Airways in obtaining a refund of fuel duties at G-wadur. I enclose a copy of the letter noted in the margin •olitical Resident’s demi official letter 1 of 30th June, N0.517-S with enclosure. ) ) ) ) which is self-explanatory. I am afraid there is nothing for us to do but to await the Sultan of Muscat’s return to his Capital. 1 am sending a copy of this letter to Brenan at the Foreign Office. T'VUii’B ,i r.r N. W. Burkett, Esq,, M.C., Air Ministry, W.C.2CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/173 of 1936. (Vo-- I 2 - I The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 7 The Political Agent, Muscat. i \ 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi. 3* The Political \gent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (4/. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, SHIRAZ. ‘ftytiTsfr Dated.... 10 th September 19 36 Reference to previous correspondence: , / IIL India Office letter No.P.2.4364/36, dated 1st July 1936.i • Z»*oGSS s * ^ s (11. II, {&gt;•. 5 ) SECRET Air Ministry, Loxidon, W.C. • 6th August, 193G Sir, *ith reference to your letter ,.. . 4004/36 ol the lot July, woo, regarding the question of the revision of the financial clauses of the Bahrein, Jioweit and Muscat civil Air Agreements, I am directs by the Secretary of State for Air to state that he concurs in the approach to the Bulere of Bahrein and . aiscat as suggested in paragraph 6 of Colonel Powle', demi-official letter of the 27th May, 1906. £ J? - ^ lord Swinton would be glad to learn in due course whether either of the alternatives (a) and (b; suggested in Air Ministry letter of the 9th April, UOo, i&lt;; acceptable to the respective Hulere. I am etc. (bd,) c.H. Brigotocke fhe Under Secretary of State, Political department, India Office, S. W. 1. SENT TO. i._IIS \ ^ ^ INDIA OFFICE, Political N?/V3- Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.D.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition a&amp; if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India, T° Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; repeated to: Govt.of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department Dated 15.8,1936. Political Agent, Muscat; ” ' Bahrein; , T y ” Koweit. No. p.z. 5688/36. I* S Your demi-official air mail letter of 27th May, No.432-3 of 1936« Civil Air Agreements. His Majesty’s Government agree that Rulers of Muscat and Bahrein should be approached as suggested in paragraph 6 of your letter* The issue of the above has been authorised. (&amp;L) J. C. WALTON.No.Z/ 3 ~j of it56» Camp Office, Ziarat, 3rd October 1956. To His Highness Salyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that Imperial Airways state, in a let oer received through the India office, that no repayment of duty on petrol and oil uplifted at Cwadur aerodrome by their aircraft has been received by them since 26th October 1934. They state that they have applied regularly each quarter for the sums due to the Amin of Customs at Gwadur who has however rejected all these claims. I have mentioned this matter to Your Highness»s representative in Muscat, Saiyid Shahab, who has informed me that he has no authority to order repayment the claims are oi course in order under the Muscat Air Agreement signed by Your Highness. As it is now nearly two years since the first repayment should have been made I have been directed to request that Your Highness will issue instructions for the refund of the amounts due up to date to be made to Imperial Airways Karachi. I would mention for Your Highness»s information that all claimsfor repayment of this duty before being forwarded by Imperial Airways are verified each quarter by the Agents appointed on behalf of His Majesty f s Government for the purpose. Your Highness’s sincere friend. Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat,Confidential. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, Dbpabtmikt, IlH. © ’OLIT ICAL- &gt;• GENCV AND jCON PI DEf’T( uTeCORD ' I EXPRESS LETTER i Jo t). S ClNSUi ^ [A. R. on ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and 'undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as tf it had been telegraphed. To Save tvmp. n U ft fnrmnl'it'iva to I ‘t r i i save time a -&lt;d formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Qffi C€ 0 f Political Resident in tiie Persian ^ulf, — Camp-, Kuwa i t« From Political Resident, Bus hire, at Kuwait, ‘UOU T. i To Political Agent, Political Agent, Bahrain Muscat, Va&gt; 0/238 of 1936. Daiai 28th Uoveufcer 153 6. Subject ; Revision of the financial clauses of the Bahrain and Muscat Civil Air Agreements. A Hi Reference correspondence ending *ith ay Express letter No. C/ / 144 duted the 26th August 1936. A copy is enclosed of India Office Express letter No.P.5666/36 dated the 6th Nove icer 19 36. Please expedite action and report. Attested. ed. i’.C.Fowle, J.ieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf. far Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.)V1 India Office. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). rU From - Secretary of State Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Dated - 6th November, 1936. No. P.Z.5688/36. 5688/36. My Express letter of 15th August, P.Z. Revision of financial clauses of Bahrain and Muscat Civil Air Agreements. me know result of action in due course. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. sd. M.J. Claus on.Political Muscat Britconsul Bushire ;\ 106 22nd December 1936* Subjecti- Revision of the financial clauses of the Muscat Civil *ir Agreement. i V \ Reference correspondence ending with your Rxpresj Letter No.C/238 of 28th November 1936. 2 * When I visited the Sultan at Dhofar on 30th November I put forward to him the alternate proposals contained in Air Ministry's letter of 9th ^pril 1936 for an enhanced rent for the use of the aerodrome at Gwadur. I confined myself to pointing out the various pros and cons of each alternative leaving him to decide himself whichever appealed to him more ( vide paragraph 3 of your demi-officic letter to Mr.Clauson No.432/3 of 27th May 1936).page.2. 3 # One point in the scheme f when mentioned, the Sultan immediately objected to and that was the period for which the new agreement was to operate. He stated that he considered seven years too long to bind himself down to any conditions and suggested two years would be more suitable. I said at once that I did not think His Majesty's Government would consent to make a fresh agreement for only two years and then have to re-open the wnole question once more. I asked the Sultan what objection he had to the period of seven years. In reply he asked if I could inform him definitely the exact number of machines that Imperial airways would fly each way during this period. I said I had no official Information on the subject but that I had read announce* ments in the newspapers that in the early part of next year five services a week would be put into operation. I added that whatever the number of machines using the aerodrome that it seemed to me that the tezros now offered by His Majesty's Government under all the circumstances eould not be considered ungenerous. He said he would consider the matter and let me have his reply shortly. 4. ? Reference paragraph 4 of your demi-official letter No.432-S to Mr.Clauson. I mentioned that it would save a great deal of unnecessary work if the 3ultan would agree to fall into line with the other Rulers in the Gulf, who own land where aerodromes are situated and allow petrol and oil to be imported duty free instead of levying the duty on entry and refunding it later. The Gultan however as on a previous occasion, when I had approached him on this point, declared he preferred to adhere to the present system of drawback. 5, I have now received a letter from the MultanSultan in which he states that he will accept the offer of £ 1000/- a year for the increased use of the aerodrome but is not willing to sign an agreement to that effect for more than two years* As I presume that this modification would be totally unaccetable to His majesty^ Government 1 would suggest that in view of the sultan's promised early return to muscat in February next the matter may remain pending until then when X could endeavour to persuade him into a reasonable frame of mind* 6. Heference the correspondence ending with India Office Letter 5222/36 of the 10th August 1936- refund of fuel duty at Gwadur* A large portion of my interview with the Hultan at Salalah was taken up by endeavouring to persuade him of the moral and legal obligation on him t o pay back the amounts already received by him from Imperial Airways and long overdue to them* The Huitaxi put forward the strange argument that as Imperial Airways had from January last year started two services a week he was only now liable to pay refund of duty on fuel uplifted by one service which, at the time of the signing of the muscat Civil Air Agreement had been operating. I made the obvious reply that there was nothing in the Air agreement to preclude the Company from operating any number of services they wished whereas unuer Section 15 of the agreement the Sultan had undertaken to refund quarterly the duties on all oil and fuel for their machines* I said that as he was fully aware Kis majesty's Government had recognised the exaims of the rollers in the Gulf for enhanced compensation on account of the Increased use of their aerodromes and that as far back as October of last year certain proposals to this effect had been put forward and were now renewed on more generous lines*^ I /i/ (iz im 4# The Sultaoi ’then asked what» was 'the exact sum due to the Company or* this account# I replied that the only details of which I had received information were of the amounts due from 26th October up to aist December 19b6 which were given as about £ 660/-* ( Vide letter dated 6th karch 1936 from Imperial airways London to the Air Ministry forwarded as an enclosure to India Office tfo# P.2.2660 of 21st April 1936). After some more quibbling the Duitan then said he would send me a cheque for £ 600/- and settle the matter on his return to kuscat in Feoruary next when the details of the remaining sums due up to the end of the year could be gone into. 7. I have since received the cheque frou* the Multan for £ 600/-. It is drawn on the Imperial hank of India Bombay. I have accordingly forwarded it to Imperial Airways Head Office in India at Karachi.No. I V of 1936. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate. Muscat, the Pnd Janucry 1936. 4* To The Manager Karachi Section Imperial Airways Limited, .iK- Mocloed Road, Karachi . Dear Sir, I took the opportunity of a recent visit to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman at Dhofar, which is in the extreme south of the State, to raise with him the question of refund of the duty on petrol and oil uplifted by machines of your Company at Gwadur. The Sultan declared that he hod never received any claim from Imperial Airways for the amount due and for this reason no order for repayment had been made. I replied that I understood that the accounts hod been submitted regularly each quarter by your Karachi Office to the Local Director of Revenues Gwadur for forwarding to the Muscat Government. The Sultan however persisted that the claii^had never reached him. He wont on to say that he would prefer in future for correspondence on all such matters to be sent through the Agency. This is the correct procedure and I would request that it may be observed in future* The Sultan asked me what amount was duo to your Company on recount of this refund. I replied that the only figures of which I had any detailed knowledge were those contained in a letter from your London Office to the Air Ministry on the subject and that gave £ 640/- as being the amount due for the duty paid on petrol and oil from October 1934 to December 1935. The Sultan finally agreed to pay £ 600/- pending receipt of the details of the accounts.which as I havep. @ hovo etated above, he dcclaree he has not seen# I hove now received a cheque for £ 600/- which I enclose herewith# ^ould you please send ac a consolidated statement showing the amount of duty paid on petrol and oil uplifted by the machines of each service from October up to the end of 1936 so that I may take up the question again when the Sultan returns to Muscat in February next. I hop® then to be able to obtain the refund of the balance of repaymentsdue• Yours faithfully. Dar# aj or. Political Agent &lt;&amp; H.B.lf’s Consul, Muscat. Enclo.l..£ tv i \ U O' /si ?*&amp; /T- Gonf ident ial # GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B, — This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain, Political Agent, Muscat. J POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD IVe. - G. JAfc W* )&gt;* K-, £ ' H, B, nVS COHSUI^E; No. 934-3 of 19 35. Dated 25th December 3ubject : Revision of the financial clauses of the Bahrain and Muscat Civil Air Agreements. A. }%b ' Reference correspondence ending with my Express letter No. C/233 dated the 28th November 1936. 2. I enclose herewith copy of India Office letter No.P.g. 5698/36 dated the 1st December 1936 to the Air Ministry* Please let me shave a reply by return of post as to how the mat+ter stands. sd. T.C.Powle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf./ ■ ii.-. Copy* P.Zo 5688/36- INDIA OFFICE, Yhi t eha 11, London 0 S#V,1# 1st Decan cer, 1936. Sir, Jith reference to your communication datecj/the 27th Fovanber No.S.32956 (pt.Il) (F.Y.), I am directed by the Secretary of state for India to inform you that a reply has not yet been received from the Political Plesident in the Persian Gulf regarding the revision of the Civil Air Agreements .;ith the Halers of Muscat and Bahrain, but titat a reminder has recently been sent. 1 am, Sir, Your obedient servant, sd. M.J.Clausen. The Secretary, Air Ministry,1 ) 73 (ti j-' • /j» c3826 j 36 AIR MIKISTRY, S.32956/C.A»l. Gwydyr House, Whitehall, S.W.l, 9th December, 1936 Dear Clauson, ,4 • 1^ i/ill you please refer/to your letter of the , No.P.2.52$^/36, 10th August last, ho,P.2.5232/36, on the subject of the difficulty experienced by Imperial Airways in securing a refund of fuel duties at Gwadur? rrom the Political Agent's (Muscat) letter of the 15th June, it would appear that the whole question was held up pending the Sultan's return to his capital which was expected to t ake place about the end of September, Imperial Airways are naturally anxious to get tnis long outstanding question settled, and I shall accordingly be glad if you will ascertain from Powle whether the Sultan has now been prevailed upon to redeem tne promise which, according- to the Director of Revenues, Muscat, he made to issue the requisite authorisation for payment of the amounts due to the Company. Yours sincerely, (Wid,) \y, ,y, Burke 11 • .J. Clauson, Esq., India Office, S, W. 1. a nik.the losses that we would sustain in consequence. Our desire Translation of a letter doted the 23rd Shaman 1355, corresponding to the 9th November 1936, from His Hignces the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Mirbat to the Political Agent, Muscat, After compliments, While at Mirbat this morning we hove received your letter No.Z/37, dated the 3rd October 1936, from Ziarat, and have perused what you have v;ritten in regard to the Imperial Airways, that they have stated in o letter received through the India Office that the duties paid on petrol and oil token bv their aeroplanes at the Gwadur aerodrome have not been refunded since the 26th October 1934, etc. Our reply is that we have not given the necessary instructions and directions about this Question neither to our Representstivc in the Sultanate nor to the Financial Deport ment, for you will no doubt recollect that when you for the first time arrived in Muscat, we discussed this question with you and made sufficient verbal explanations. We, then, asked you to write to our friend the British Government that when the Air Agreement was m*dc in Muscat and we agreed to those conditions, among which was that we should refund duties of the petrol consumed bv the aeroplanes of the said Company, there used to csll at Gwadur only two aeroplanes a week, one bound for India, and the other coming from there. We, then, understood that the duties of the petrol c onsumed by the aeroplanes of the said Company will be calculated at the rate of eight aeroplanes a month only. But after a few months the calls of aeroplanes became more frequent and the taking of petrol increased, which meant that we should refund more duties than we have imagined. At that time we spoke to you and informed you about] is that we should gain from the Conm^ny, not th*t the Coimon-v should griin Trom us. You showed your opprovnl or our demands and nroinised to write to the Government about two alternatives: First, that we should not refund all the duties of the petrol taken in excess to the quantity consumed by two aeroplanes a week, or secondly, that we should be allowed a sufficient amount over the 500 pounds, the increase of which will give us profit. Upon this the Question was suspended between us, and we have since been awaiting your reply. But up to date you have not given us any reply. We ore prepared to refund the duties of the petrol consumed by the aeroplanes of the said Company at the rate of two aeroplanes a week with effect from the 26th October 1936, recording to the agreement* Af for the petrol taken in excess by the additional aeroplanes every week, this we cannot refund until the question is settle, between us and the said Company. There is no doubt that the Government is just and does not agree that we should lose to the benefit of the said Company. Wc are confident that the Government at the time the Air Agre ement was made never intended to bring us to suflfer losses ®n a future date. We may mention that we hod addressed a letter to your predecessor in this respect* Further, the Company ought to hove forwarded the documents demanding the refund of the duties , to us and to the Trustee of the Gwadur Customs. We should like the Company to inform us of the petrol consumed by their aeroplanes at the Tntc of two aeroplanes a week from the 26th October 1934 up to date. We arc owaitinc your reply about this Question, eo as to to able to reply you as soon / as possible. Usual Ending.I— » • IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD AND ASSOCIATED COMPANIES FINLAY HOUSE, McLEOD ROAD KARACHI Telephone: KARACHI 2814 Telegrams: AI RWAY S , KA RAC H I Codes: BENTLEYS &amp; I AT. A Major R*P.Watts, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Ref. AA°/*/2867/WJ 8th. January 1937. Dear Sir, L. 4 We are in receipt of your letter No.10 1936 dated 2nd instant enclosing a cheque endorsed in our favour for a sum of £ 600/-. We are greatly indebted to you for your assistance in representing our claim to His Highness the Sultan and we are advising our Cairo Office, under whose jurisdiction Gwadur falls, to forward all future claims to your Agency. We are also asking our Cairo Office to send you a consolidated statement showing the amount of duty paid on petrol and oil uplifted byTaircraft for the period from October 1934 to date. Yours faithfully, IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LUaSW, GDA. w \ Area Accountant.•'OTjf'tr /&lt;( t&gt; ft ( ^ i i* Trcnslotion of a letter dated the ?8th Ramodhon 1355, corresponding to the 13th December 1936, from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Dhofar to the Political Agent.Muscat. After compliments. Reference the (discussions which took place between you and us on the P9th November last, during your visit to us at Dhofar. * ♦ Among the matters then discussed was the question of refunding the money taken on oils consumed by the Imperial Airways and the increments which you intended to fix for us ©•fror the £.500/- etc. I would therefore now reply as I have explained to you verbally that accounts from the said Comnany were neither received by us directly nor through your Consulate. Therefore we did not know the amount due, and payment was consequently delayed. In future the Company should send their accounts to us either directly or through you. As for the increments, we have informed you that wo should think over the two proposals you made to us and give you our reply when we returned to Muscat. We enclose, herewith, a cheque for £.600/- for payment to the Company. We are awaiting the despatch of detailed accounts, as we told you verbally. herewith. Please acknowledge receipt of the chcoue enclosed Usual Ending,JbD | &lt;1^; &gt;o - EXPRESS LETTER. (AIH I^IL) PROM: Secretary cf State for India, TO: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf', Repeated to: Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Dept., 'D 1 -i 4 -^ 1 A Political Agent, Bahrein, Political Agent, Koweit, Political Agent, Muscat. DATED: 24th December 1936&lt; No. P.Z.8966/36. • with reference to the correspondence ending with Bahrein Agency printed letter No.727-21/3, dated 14th March 1936 on the subject of the issue of special authorisations for the aircraft of Imperial Airways Limited to fly in and over Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat, copy is enclosed of a further Dated 16th letter from the Air Ministry containing particulars of ^^December additional aircraft for which similar facilities may shortly be required. If you see no objection please obtain necessary special authorisations from Gheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein and from Sultan of Muscat. The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sgd.) j. OLAU^OSSr ^P.z. 8966/36, AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, V/.G. 2. i. 513185/36/C. A. 1, 16th December 1936. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for Air to refer to previous correspondence, terminating with your letter of the 27th March 1936, No.P.Z.2053/1936, on the subject of the issue, by the Rulers of Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat, of special authorisations for the aircraft of Imperial Air*ways Limited, operating on the Company’s air services to India and the Par Last, to fly in and over their respective territories. 2. I am to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that Imperial Airways Limited have intimated that similar facilities may shortly be required in respect of the under-mentioned aircraft to be brought into use on the Empire air route to the Par East:~ Type _of aircraft. Name*' Registration marks. Short ’'Empire” Canopus G—ADHL Plying Boats, Centaurus Caledonia Castor G--ADUU G-ADHM G-ADUW I am accordingly to request that, subject to the concurrence of the Marquess of Zetland, an application may be made to the Rulers of the territories in question for the issue of the requisite authorisations. I am, &amp;c., (Sgd.) A.H. SELF. The Under-Secretary of State India OfficeGOVEKNMENT OF INDIA Confident Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B.-This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Politic&amp;l rteeident. liuahire ^ of for ^ndi* t i.onion* f r(ej irolitioal v ent, iiu3c;;t* 4tn January ^ 7*, . 2* a jor .atta, Aho ahb abi© to riuit in© Jultan at .&gt;hofar ;«hil© on tne recent oynl Air ^orce reeonnaieaance to t&lt;u t part of the vorld, on which I hnv* reported separately, «n*ite8 8 foil owe* 3* The ultan haa agreed in writing to accept the offer of ^ lv/00/- a year for the increased uae of tne aerodrome but ia not jillin^ to ai^n an a^ree lent to Ui&amp;t efi eot for ;aor© train two years* fhia is in spite of tne fact tu4&gt; ; e jor tts potnteJ out to the hultaii in the course of conversation trait ne did not think that His ('overment would consent to 'mice a fresh agreement for only two years an i then hare to rt-»open thequestion once more. X would be grateful for Hie fiajeet^’w Goversaent * s instructions on t hie matter. 11 ith re^nrd to paragraph 3 of your letter Ho. P.i. 2550/36, dated the 21»t April 1936* In epite of r Kj or atte 1 argumente the &gt;ultan declared that ne preferred to adhere to the present system of customs drawbacic. The objection to this is contained in paragraph 7 ol Air Ministry letter No.3.32956/U/l&gt;I&gt;CA dated the 31st August 1935 to the India Office. Financially there is no difference between the drawback system and the waiving of customs dues, cut I will take the matter up with the Sultan when I visit Muscat in Apr ill Major mts reports that the Sultan is retiming from Dhofar some time in February. Should the Sultan still prove obdurate I think w© will have to concede tJais point. 5 v'ith reference to paragraph 6 of your letter Ho.P.4 2550/36. tfijor Matts reports that a large portion of his interview with the Sultan at Ohofar was taken up by endeavour ing to persuade him of the moral and legal obligations on him to pay back the amounts received by way of customs duty. Finally, the Sultan, after much quibbling, gave a cheque for £ 600/- on account stating that he would go into the matter in detail when he returned to Muscat. Major Aitts has sent this cheque to Imperial Airways Head Office in India at Karachi• Doubtless the Sultan in taking up his obstructive attitude bn this point has been influenced by the fact that the present agreement is not a particularly good bargain from his point of view. ihen he hra made a new 'igreatse^t he will doubtless be more ready to refund the drawbacks regularly, but if not I propose that His Majesty's Governaent should /should deduct whatever iu owin^ to imperial Air*«*/» under this heiid from the subeidy which they will be paying the IrnTTiin. This wiXk save this eaidency the t iae and trouble spent in extracting these refunds* ed. T.G*?owle, Lieut»*Oolonei* Political Heaident in the Persian Gulf. \v *ecretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Copy. P.Z.8966/56. 513185/36/C.A.1. Air ministry, ijondon. v.C.2. 16th December 1956 Sir, I am directed by the secretary of otate for Air to refer to previous correspondence, terminating with your letter of the 27th March 1936, no. P.Z.2053/1936, on the subject of the issue, by the Rulers of Kuwait, 8abrain and Muscat, of special authorisations for the aircraft of imperial Airways .Limited, operating on the Compe ny 1 s air services to India and the Par East, to fly in and over their respective territories. 2. i am to state, for the information of the Secretciry of State for India, that imperial Airways limited have intimated that similar facilities may shortly be required in respect of the under-mentioned aircraft to be brought into use on the Empire air route to the Par 3ast:- fype of a i re ra ft. Name . Registra t ion inarms . Short » , Empire ,, Plying Boats. Canopus Centaurus Caledonia Castor Cr-ADHL -AuruL ✓ \ \ Gr-ADHM G-ADIEV 3. I am accordingly to request that, subject to the concurrence of the Marquis of Zetland, an application may be made to the Rulers of the territories in question for the issue of the requisite authorisations. I am, &amp;c., sgd. A.H.3BLP. he Under-Secretary of State, INDIA OFFICE.4963 2000 7.36 By Air Mail. rWjXtf mTf i LONDON, £ • / 9 ^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. The Politifval Resident The Foreign Secretary, Government of India. Persian Gulf.INDIA OFFICE, V/HITSHALL&gt; 3.W. 1. 2nd February, 1937* (g) P. 3.720/37- /H kV Dear Burkett, t/ith reference to your official letter of the 9th April 1936, Ho. S. 32956 (Part II) and connected / correspondence, I forv/ard i'or your infonination a cop:-' or aii Ik) o cl ** •January/ Express Letter from the Political Resident at Bushire about 1937* ^ the Muscat Civil Air Agreement. As the letter is rather obscure we thought it well to ask for an elucidation, ated / and I send you also a copy of the Express Letter in which February/ I 937 . / we have done so. We will approach you officially as soon as we get a reply. Meanwhile, perhaps you can give the matter some preliminary thought. Incidentally, paragraph 3 of Colonel Fowle’s Express Letter is of interest with reference to your letter to me of the 29 th January, No.S.32956/C.A. 1, about the refund of fuel duty at Gwadur. Yours sincerely, M. J. OLAUSDN t .7.W. Burkett, Esq.* &gt; M.C., Air Ministry,s From Secretary of State for India, To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department Political Agent, Puscat. Dated 2nd February, 1937- Io. P.S. 720/37. / )U 1 our express letter 4th January If-S. Muscat Civil Air Agreement. Efefore approaching Air Pinistry again officially I should be grateful for elucidation of first sentence of paragraph 3* Does this mean that new agreement would run tor two years iron, now (e.g. from 1st January or 1st April 1937) or from the expiration of the present agreement in 1938? (Presumably it cannot mean from 1st January 1935). And do you understand that Sultan would still expect that increase in rental should be retrospective to 1st January R9 2 . I do not of course suggest any further reference to Sul ban at this stage, and should be glad of an early reply in oraer that His Majesty*s Government may proceed with their consideration of the matter, with a view to a decision being reached before your visit to Muscat in April. -ho issue of the above has been duly authorised. 4; ,) WL J. GuAUSGhiv' g|Sl ^ -ii i ililBI ' I 3679a /50(g) INDIA OFFICE, POLITICAL Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India rp 0 Political Resident, Bushire, repeated to Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Dept., Political Agent, Bahrein, Political Dated Agent, Koweit, Political Agent, Muscat. 6th February, 1937. No. P.Z. 735/37 T t y* U Dated 29th January, 1^37. • f,nN$vH i \ • yoSv 11*0 Please refer to my Express Letter Do.?.Z.3966/36 dated 24th December, 1936, regarding the issue of special authorisations for aircraft of Imperial Airways Limited to fly in and over Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat. Enclosed is a further letter from the Air Ministry on the subject. If you see no objection please take necessary action. The issue of the above has been duly authorised (2. f ) J. Ol. UiSONP.Z. 755/37 iTo.513185/36/C.A.1 AIR MI1TISTRY, GV/YDYR HOUSE, S. W. 1. 29th January, 1937 Dear Clauson M. J, Will you please/refer to our official letter / of the 16th December /fast, numbered as above, (your reference No.PZ.8966/36 of the 24th December) containing a request by Imperial Airways Limited for the issue by the Rulers of Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat of special authorisations for certain of the Company's new 'Empire' flying boats to operate in and over their respective territories. In the case of one of the flying boats mentioned, namely, the 'Centaurus', the registration marks were given as G-ADUU. The Company nov/ tell us that they have been altered to G-ADUT. ' 1 Tmper~iTlivvays ask if, when the attention of the Rulers is drawn to this amendment, opportunity can be taken to request permission for one other 'C' class flying- boat which they are likely to require to operate in and over the above mentioned territories, viZc, 'Cambria', G-ADUY We shall accordingly be glad if you will be good enough to take the necessary steps to this end. Yours sincerely, (S d. ) W. W.. Bur ke 11 Claus on, Esq., India Office, S. W. 1. iConfidential. No.229-S of 1937 British Residency &amp; Consulate-General* Bushire, the 19th February 1937. To The Political Agent, The Political Agent, The Political Agent, Muscat, at Bahrain. Kuwait. Karachi i Memorandum. Subj ect &gt; Special authorisation certificates for aircraft j^t&gt; of Imperial Airways Limited. Jt Reference enclosure to India Office Express Letter No. P.Z.735/37, dated the 6th February 1937. Please take action accordingly. j&gt; 2. To Muscat only . If certificates of authorisation, called for in my Memorandum No.30-S dated the 6th January 1937 have not already been obtained, please have incorporated additional aircraft and amendment suggested in enclosure to the India Office letter quoted above. ad. T.C.Fowle, Lieut. •Colon el. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. few'- fiodr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Confidential. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). * T ns is an ORIGINAL mensage sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 224-S of 1937. Bu shire, Dated the 19th February From - Political Resident, Bushire. 19 37. To Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi. Subject 5 Muscat Civil Agreement- Reference India Office Express letter No.P.720/37 da t ed the 2nd Pebruary 1 937. -• 2. Does the Sultan mean that the new Agreement would run for two years from (a) now (e.g. from 1st January or 1st April 1937), or (b) from the expiration of the present Agreement in 1938, or (c) from 1st January 1935. If (a) or (b) does Sultan mean to claim retrospective payment at the rate £ 150/- per annum for each additional service above 1^he first from 1st January 1935, to the date of the new Agreement ? 4 * (c) appears lout of the question. 5. Please reply by air mail not repeating elsewhere. Att est ed. sd. T.C.Fowle, ^ieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Signature) fc*£ Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Designation)/ Confidential. EXPRESS LETTER. /■* Fr om To Political, Muscat. Britconsul, Bushire. No,K/30, dated Camp Karachi the £3rd February 1937. Subject:- MUSCAT CIVIb AIi t AGxU.iaibKT . Reference your gxpress Letter No.^24-S of 19th February 1937. / ^ , -XT'' ^ C India Office Express Letter No,P.Z.720/o7 of Lnd February 1937 has not yet been received by me but, as the next mail from Muscat does not arrive before I leave Karachi to avoid delay I am replying now by Air Mail to the points raised in your Express Letter quoted above. 3. Reference your paragraph 2 (a), I think the Sultan means that the new agreement should run from 1st January 1937. 4. four paragraph 3. The Sultan wishes to accept the increased rental of £ 1000/- a year vide paragraph 5 of my Express Letter No. 106 of &lt;;Lnd December 1936, and will claim the difference between that sum and what he is now paid with retrospective effect to the date when the service was l J «VV. ( Ai &gt; duplicated vide alternative (a) mentioned on page 2 of AiriCi —c,— Air Ministry»s letter of 9th April 1956. \6M] Major, Political Agent &amp; Consul, &gt; § Muscat.I’elegram. G.^.c. From - .dritconsul, jdushire. To - political, Muscat. . - 290. Dated a Heceived 1st March 1937. Your express letter DO.K./30 of 23rd February As I understand it, the sultan is prepared to accept a 4 years agreement at £ 1000/- per annum dating from 1st January 1935 i.e. date of duplication of service. 2 . that this is the position. Please approach Sultan and ( by telegram ?) Britconsul.Telegram. G.T.C. y-s ■f’rom - Political, kuscat* To - Political ^esiaent, P.G. at Bahrain. o • • ^ated the 5th ^arch 19d7* i Your telegram ho.290 of 1st inarch, dultan now states he desires to accept £.1000 per annum only for period of the present agreement Ci*s. to October 1958 with restropective effect from 1st January 1935J after expiry of which he desires to review the position. Political. * f /N %S. G. P. I.—247 P. A. * H. B. M. Consol Muscat—6-12-H flnn Confidential From To (Si No?? /58- of 191 xsajor i«A* $ Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, his Majesty's Secretary of State for india» India Office 9 ^ ^ y D U British Agency and Consulate. Muscat, the March /P/37 Sir, rH With reference to your Express letter ng.^. 2 . S'^66/36, dated the 24th Lecember i^36 9 i have the honour to forward herewith the original co*y of the Special Authorisation for aircraft to land in and fly over His Highness the Sultan's territories of Muscat and Uiian for tiie year 1^37. 2* Five copies of this authorisation have been forwarded to the hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. i have the honour to be» Sir* Your most obedient humble servant* Enclo. i. political Agent &amp; H.B.m* M U Major* Consul* cat.C 6 irom cu^and excise ano JUa^ert and export regulations and an/ regulations enloL &amp;a/ be laid down for ^uoiic aafet/ as sell as tiie air navigation regulations attached hereto* \llj The aircraft shall not use as a ^laoe of landing or departure within the territories of Muscat and uiaan an/ ilsee other th&amp;n the aerodromes at U*adur and ahinas 9 and the published conditions governing Uie use of the said aerodromes shall be observed* Villi this authorisation or a certified true com/ of It shall be carried In the aircraft and be produced on demandi •&gt; Confidential, From No. 3 ' ^, /58-of 191 © Major R.x . V atts, X• A• 9 Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Kon*bJLe the political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Buahire* British Agency and Consulate. March Muscat, the • ^ ^ Subjects- Special Authorisation under the Civil Air Agreement* 79 / 37 . i • IV With reference to your memorandum ho.22^-&gt;S, dated the luth February 1V37, X have the honour to forward here with five copies of Special Authorisation for aircraft to land in and fly over ills Highness the Sultan*s territories of Muscat and Oman for the year 1937, 2* The original co*&gt;y of this Autnorisation has been forwarded direct to the india uffice under my Ho« even date* of x have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, *ajor. Political Agent 6 c H.1&gt;*M*b Consul,! uscat. Sncio*5* S. G. P. I.—247 P. A. A H. B. M. Coiml Aruscat^gJ^H^^aQIL* No te. I showed Imperial Airways* letter No.3329/WJ of February 12th 1937 to th* Sultan the last time he called at th* Agency ( March 16th). He asked to be allowed to take away for a few days the first 2 pages of the claim for perusal. I gave it him and h*ve now received it back without any remarks. This question will have to be taken up when the P.R. arrives and the Civil Air Agreement discussed. 25-3-1937IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD AND ASSOCIATED COMPANIES FINLAY HOUSE, McLEOD ROAD KARACHI Telephone: KARACHI 2814 Telegrams: AIRWAYS, KARACHI. Codes: BENTLEY’S &amp; I AT.A J H, B, Ref. a/ 20/6/3389/' l T 12th February 1937. Major R.P.Watts, Political Agent and Consul, Muscat. Dear Sir, I have now received from our Cairo Office the for refun &lt;J ^ty on petrol and oil 1 nr?Lted at Gwadur auring the period from 26th October 1S34 to 31st December 1936 and in accordance with your * request contained in your letter No.10 of 1936 dated 2nd January 1937, I am passing the claim to you for favour of referring the matter to His Highness the Sultan. Yours faithfully, IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LX&amp;KCTLD GDA. I/O ’ Area Accountant. •» EL CLIMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED Stateinent of Petrol Issued at Gv/adur for use of our Aircraft at Jiwani during the period 1st July to 30th September 1936. Receipt. Date. Tins. 15 15.7.36 Augus t September Equivalent to 100 100 Nil 200 Tins 800 GallonsIMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED Statement of Petrol Issued at Gwadur for use of our Aircraft at Jiv'ani during the period 1st January to 31st March, 1936. Receipt No. 7 Date. Tins 5. 1.36 50 A7 Petrol J anua ry 115 A6 Petrol February 150 A7 Petrol March Nil 315 Tins 1260 Gallons Equivalent toIMPERIAL AI R ,r AYg LIMITED Statement of Petrol Issued at Gwadur for use of our Aircraft at Jiwani during the period 1st October to 31st December, 1935. Receipt No. Date. Quantity. 226 26.11.35 50 Tins Equivalent to 200 GallonsC 0 ? Y NO. Y/1Q/00$ Uust 0 !H&amp; Gwadur dated'11th Nov. 1956 . To: The Accountaiit, Near drst Area, Imperial Airwaye Ltd., CAIRO Dear Sir, With reference your letter No P/i/1/9+7^ a /^ dated 2 nd Kove.iber 1956 , I have tne honour to inform you that under the rules &amp; Regulations of Muscat &amp; Oman liovernnent no refun of customs duty payable paid on any article once imported. Yours faitnfully. Sgd. Director of Customs GWADUA Copy for information to Director of Revenues Muscat.COPY ho. Y /191259 CUSn’OMS HOUSE j-wadur dated 8th Aug. 135 ^* The Manager, Imperial Airways Limited Lear Eq^st Area, caiyo ^ Dear Sir, Ref: your L o date d 2Qth July JG I have ths honour to inform you that- under the i( iUbcat- &amp; Oman G-overnment Regulations no refund of Duty payable if paid on any article once imported. Yours faithfully 3gd # Director of Customs. O'.YADUR Dopy to Director of Revenues Muscat for information.■ OJU? Y No. Y/1J/16+ Oustorat; house, (iwadur aated 1 +. 5 *^^* /rr&lt;@) To: Messrs Imperial Airways Limited, ^ A I N 0 iDear Sirs, Reference your letter No. P/+/V3328/AB of bth inst. , jl have the honour to inform you that under Muscat &amp; Oman Government Regulations no refund of duty payable paid on any article once imported. Yours faithfully. Sgd. • » • • Director of Customs. G W A D U R iOopy forward to Director of Revenues, Muscat State for information.No. Y /19158 Out,tomb House, tiwaciur datea 13 th j'eb. ^b. S To: The Manager, Imperial Airways LTD. fjai ro. Dear Sir, Reference your letter To. P/p/1/pi/f dated ^c. .pb 'regarding refund of Ouotoms uuty paid on fuel &lt;Sc oil uplifted |-by you at (iwadur. I have the honour to inform you tnat under |tne Muscat Govt. Regulations no refund of duty payable paid on any article once imported. Yours gfiitnfully. Sgd* Director of uustoms. Gwadur. m Copy forwarded to Director of Revenues I Muscat State for information.&lt;J 0 p y n&lt;&gt; Wo. Y/550 Customs House. Ciwadur dated ictd Hov. 1935 * The Manager, Imperial Airways Limited, No. 2 Operating Division, 0 A I d 0 Dear Sir, i Reference your letter No. p/9/1S/AB dated 90th Oct. 1995 regarding claim for the refund of uuotoms duty paid on fuel and oil uplifted hy your Aircrafts ai G-wadur during the period from 1 st July to 90th Septemher 1599* ^ have Lhe honour to inform you that under Muscat a: Oman Government Regulations no refund of Customs duty paid on any article once imported is permissible either re-exported - or uplifted. Yours faithfully. Sgd. Director of Customs C W A D U R Copy forwarded to the Director of Revenues Muscat State for information.No. 0 1^2 Customs house, (iwaclur, dated 21 st 3ep,19^5* To Imperial Airways Limited uwadur Dear Sirs, Reference to your no F/^/1/7^5 a /^® dated 1+th instant, regarding the refund of Customs duty paid on fuel and oil up lilted j 'by you at u-wadur during the period from 1st April to pOth June I have the honour to inform you that under the State Regulations, no Customs duty is payable but even than I am forwarding your letter in original to Head Office Muscat for favour of consideration. Yours faithfully. Sgd Director of Cuetoms, owadur. Copy to Director of Revenues. Muscat State for information. forwarded in ori ;inal to the Accountant. Cairo. Sgd. A.m. Thompson. u-wadurCOPY Prom: A..P. Thompson, No. 1NT/268. CxWADUR 1 : To: Area Accountant, Cairo u-wadur Dated 12th Octobe 1935. I herewith forward letter No. 8/^48 aated 10th instant, in original, received from the Director of Customs in a cover addressed 00 me. Sgd. A.C. ThompsonCOPY wo. P/04-8. The Manager, Imperial Airways LTD. , No.2 Operating Division, Cairo. Reference your letters No. P/^/1/50C2.D/AB andp/3;/1/ 7165a/AB. dated 26th July and 12fth November 1935&gt; respectively I have the honour to inform you that I have just received reply regarding your claim for refund of Customs duty paid on fuel &amp; oil from the Director of Revenues Muscat that Under Muscat u-overn- ment Regulations no refund of customs duty paid on any articles once imported is permissible either on re-export or uplift etc. /?3 customs house, u-wadur, dated 10th. Oct. 19^5 Yours faithfully, 3gd. Director of Customs G W A D U■ S. 11. (Designation) GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. confidential. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [ . . is is an ORV, INAL mensage sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expe itious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 291-S of 1937* Dated ' titimlkre XxK&amp;eUi’ 2Stn .! reft, XXXXXXX ° / rfthe To XXX From • Political Resident, Bushi re. To Becretary of State for India, London* *ij£. i ' / Repeated Bov eminent of India, New Delhi* t&gt; f ^Political Agent, Muscat, reference^correspondence ending eierence my witn hia telegram iio*23 of 5tn Maren 1937, xxxxxxxxx Jubj ect t iluscat Oiril Air Agreement* Reference correspondence ending with your i&amp;presa Letter No.p.^.720/37 of the 2nd February 1937* Sultan has now intimated that he wishes to be pe id £ 1000/- per annum from 1st January 1935 to date of expixy of current agree ment i*e* October 1938, after which ne desires to review position* 2. I expect to be in Muscat from the Ibtn to the 22nd April, before virtiich dates I would be grateful to have His Majesty’s Government’s views in order that I can discuss the question with the Sultan* Attested* sd* T.C*Fo*le, Lie it*-Colonel* Political. Resident in the Persian Oulf* ■ for Secretary to the Political resident in the Persian Gulf. (Signature)of 1937 Mrvju-j jj^ji ir g,Ul No. of 1937. Political agency &lt;&amp;: H.B.U’s Consulate. Muscat, the April 1937. His Highness Saiyid Said bin Tairaur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. T o Jf+J (J-J ^ ^ J-V Your Highness, &lt;j . j-~~v j have the honour to refer to the ,/ recent discussion I had under instructions i_J iL-*U; from Hie Ma j eBty , 8 Government with Your r’^ *C Highness regarding the penalties to be r imposed on persons subject to Your 4_^cl i»)Uj ^ .£_«,kJI Highness's jurisdiction for infringement , '* S '' ^ i ^ ^ of the Muscat Air navigation Regulations * J ^ 1 0 'y 51 ^ for Civil aircraft, r ' T a. As requested by Your Highness I now «* forward a Draft Notification in Arabic &amp; J and English, on this subject which if . ^U^-yi jU oli approved may be issued by Your Highness. *—»' 6* tr **) I am also to suggest that, for the f * 1 ^** ^ ^3 J—PuyV various reasons 1 explained personally to Your Highness, before any action is taken jU;I qr 1 *-^ 1 J-^^ 1 under this Notification against any I 1 i ^l_*J I f 0rei g n aV iator Your Highness will agree to consult the Political Agent. Usual Ending. ^ AUi Major, ., .. ^ JJI j iU u-^’y •&amp; * j' roxitical Agent &amp; H.E.M’s Consul,Muscat.heoulatioks to be issued by Hia HIGHNESS THE SULTAN of MUSCAT and OMAN. AIR NAVIGATION REGULATION* It m hereby no til led tnat all persons subject to tne jurisdiction of His HifcLnees the Sultan of Muscat and Citan who are found guilty of contravening the Air Eavig^tion Regulations for Oivil Aircrait made by His Highness* a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall, on conviction, be liable to a fine not exceeding 2s 1500, and, in default, to simple imriaonment not exceeding three months| and any bauds, receptacles or things ( including aircraft/ in relation to which tne offence has been coiii itted, shall be liable to forfeiture*/ Q 7 / REGULATION TO BE ISSUED BY HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT AND OMAN. u AIR NAVIGATION REGULATION. It is Hereby notified that all persons subject to the jurisdiction of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman who * ~ ' ilty of contravening the Air Navigation!for Civil Aircraft made by His Highness, a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall, on conviction, be liable to a fine not exceeding Es 1500, and, in default, to simple imprisonment not exceeding three months; and any goods, receptacles or things ( including aircraft) in relation to which the offence^ has been committed, shall be liable to forfeiture.IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD AND ASSOCIATED COMPANIES FINLAY HOUSE, McLEOD ROAD KARACHI Telephone: KARACHI 2814- Telegrams: AIRWAYS, KARACHI Codes BENTLEY’S &amp; I AT.A Ref. A20/6/104/WJ 9th April, 1937 Major R. P. Watts, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. Dear Sir, I have been requested by our Cairo Office to advise any further developments in connection with our outstanding claims for refund of duty on petrol and oil uplifts at Gwadur. You will recollect that I wrote to you on the 12th February enclosing details of our claim for the period from 26th October 1934 to 31st December 1936 which you kindly agreed to refer to Etis Highness the Sultan. Our financial accounts are closed each year on the 31st March and if you can advise me of the position at an early date so that I may have my accounts clearly explained, I shall be grateful. Yours Faithfully, IMPEF ” ' ED GDA Area AccountantNote MUSCAT CIVIL AIR AGR^MBNT. Rebate of customs dues on fuel imported for Imperial Airways~~ (see correspondence ending with India Office telegram No,1242 datedThe 17th April 1937|.~ After discussion with Major Watts it appears to me that the Sultan has a strong case for the rebate system. It is true that at Bahrain the Bahrain Government do not charge customs dues on fuel for Imperial Airways and therefore of course there is no question of a rebate f but Bahrain is only used solely by Imperial Airways. 2. The position at Gwadur however is different* There fuel is imported in bulk and used not only by Imperial Airways but by K.L.M., Air Prance and casual fliers. If therefore the Sultan agreed to charging no customs dues on entry a separate acco nt would have to be made up at the end of, say, each quarter, for fuel used by Imperial Airways. This would have to be subtracted from the total araount imported and duty charged on the balance. But before these accounts were made and checked and probably sent to Cairo considerable time would elapse and in the meantime the Sultan would have to wait for his money. 3. Under the present system of rebate the Suita? takes on entry the whole of the Customs dues on all fuel imported and then when Imperial Airways have made up their accounts the rebate is paid. In other words Imperial Airways have to wait for their money instead of the Sultan. The Air Ministry’s objection to the rebate system was / 4-g- 2X1 % was that it undermined their position in other countries when bargaining for exemption from duty for fuel imparted for the use of Imperial Airways. It does not seem to me that this objection is a valid one since whether it is on the rebate or exemption system the net result is that Imperial Airways do not pay Customs dues on their fuel. 5. A point to be remembered in the sultgn *s favour is that while at Bahrain the Royal Air Force pay duty on their fuel in Muscat territory they do not. 6. In view of the above considerations I do not see how we can press the Sultan to rescind his rebate system. Rental. The Sultan is in a very strong position and I do not see that we can get him to alter his deciaipn J Watt s• A copy of this note has been given to Major sd. T.CJ’owle. Muscat. 21/4/37.Telegram Prom To Copy to Wo. T/61 Dated 25th O.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire, at Muscat. H.B. the Governor of Aden. Political Agent, Muscat. April 1937. 1 Your telegram Wo. 234 of April 23rd 1937. Buitan has no objection. He has given standing instructions to his tfali to give flights all possible assistance but as a matter of form would like previous notice from you as in the present instance. RESIDENT.Telegram H.M.’s Secretary of State f&lt;r India, London Political Resident, Bus ;ire, H.M.S.Foarey* From To Copy by mail to Government of India, New Delhi ' Political Agent, Muscat. Dated 16th received 17th April 1937. No.1242. '’IfyO Your Express Letter of Mtrch 25th. MUSCAT CIVIL air agreement. In the circumstances His Majesty’s Government feel that they have little choice but to meet Sultan's present request and you may arrange accordingly unless you can secure cny better terras. They note from paragraph 4 of your Express letter of January 4th that you will again ©deavoir to secure Sulten’s agreement to abolition of present ^ stem of Customs drawback. They attach particular importance to this and feel that if they have to meet Sultan’s wishes in other respects he should meet them on this point. They agree however that it may be conceded in the last resort. - Secretary of State for India (Copy given to Major v&amp;tta)4 GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, This is an 0 TUG IA AL M TiSS AG 7T, hy pr-sf to swe telec/ropTiic expe.t se aid undue use of the wires, hut n/tended to be treated, on receipt^ with the same e.ipedotaw us \f it had h^e.n telegraphed. To ta e Gme and formalities it is warded a d si ji ed as if it had been so despatched.] From Political Muscat* To Britconsul Bushire. So. y - W .-. iSth May 7 . Reference correspondence ending with your letter No*418-S of £2nd May 1936* 2. I enclose herewith an amendment made by His Highness the Sultan to the Draft of the Air Notification it is proposed that he should issue* 3* The Sultan states that the object of his amendment is to bring the draft into line with that of other Notifications he issues in which no mention is made that it is applicable only to those subjects under his jurisdiction* British subjects are already covered in tnis respect by the issue of King’s Regulation No*l of 1936 and though the wording of the original draft is of course preferable it seems to me that the Sultan's proposed amendment does not effect the essential meaning of the Notification*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N, B.- This is an OTHGJhs AL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sit' e lime and formalities %t is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] yjo r @) Fbom To No, J ^ 4. Dated 133 . •- 2 -- The Sultan appears anxious that the Notification should be in the form desired by him and there be no objection I recommend that it be approved* i of \ J c^ jl \ ^ ^OQ Vj €/ S. 6.r\ 'r 2276/37 ft Cypher telegram from Secretary of State to Political Agent, Bahrein, dated 16th April, 1937. No. of words 73 X. 1242 Addressed Bahrein for Resident copy by mail to \ India and Muscat. Your express letter of 25th March Muscat Civil Air Agreement. In the circumstances His Majesty’s Government feel that they have little choice but to meet Sultan’s present request and you may arrange accorcingly unless you can secure any better terms, ihey note iron paragraph 4 of your express letter of 4th January that you will again endeavour to secure Sultan s agreement to abolition of present system of customs drawback. They attach particular importance to this and feel that if they have to meet Sultan’s wishes in other respects he should meet them on this point. They agree, however, that it may be conceded in the last resort.4963 2000 7.36 By jUv Mail. 8 . M’S noMStji *' ; ^uSC^T. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, zy. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. Sea The Foreis' Secretary, Government of India. sighSecrel iticM Resi The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.P.Z.1169/37. Cypher telegram from Secretary of State for India to the Political Resident, Bushire 3 repeated to the Political Agent ; Bahrein; dated 25th February 5 1937. (No. of Words: 52 and 52). X 679. Addressed to Bushire ? repeatcd to Bahrein, copy by sea mail to the Government of India and to the Political Agents at Kuwait and Muscat. 2. Your air mail letter Ho.172-3 dated 5th February. Slavery. 3. I assume that you are considering separately ouestio of further information on details suggested by Sir George Maxwell ( see paragraphs 11 and 12 of your note of 23rd September 1936). Please telegraph whether I may expect your views in time for inclusion of any further information that may be suitable in this year f s report, i.e. early next month.REGULATIONS TO BE ISSUED BY HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT AND OMAN. ( AIR NAVIGATION REGULATION From - Soiyid Sold bin Toimur ’The Sulton of kuscot and Oman It is hereby notified to all whom it may concern that all pereone who ore found guilty of contravening the Air Navigation Regulations for Civil Aircraft made by ue a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall, on conviction, be liable to a fine not exceeding &amp; 1500 , and in default to simple imprieonment not exceeding three months; and any goods, receptacles or things ( including air croft) in relation to which the offence hoe been committed, shall bo liable to forfeiture*REGULATIOHS TO BE IHSUED BY HIS HIGHNESS THK SULTAN OF MUSCAT AND CM/Jf. AIR HAVIGAT IOH RSOULATIOI. From - Soiyid Sold bin Toiraur, The Sulton of Fuecot and c^non. It ie hereby notified to all whom it may concern that all pereons who' arc found guilty of contravening the Air Navigation Hcgulatione for Civil Aircraft made by u«' a copy of which ie annexed hereto, ehall, on conviction, be liable to a fine not exceeding ite 1500, and in default to simple imprisonment not exceeding three months; and any goods, rcccptaclce or things ( including air croft) in relation to which the offence hoe been committed, eholl bo liable to forfeiture*Translation of a letter dated the 29th Safar 1356 ( 11-5-1937) from His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, to the Political Agent &amp; H.h*M* s Consul, Muscat* After Compliments* We have received your letter Ho*54 dated 3rd May 1937 and have understood what you stated regarding the increased rental which His Majesty’s Government propose to give to us on behalf of the Imperial Airways etc* We confirm that our wishes in this connection, as stated in your abovementioned letter, are correct. Shortly after this letter we shall send you the cheque as-lced for* U.S.GOVERXAIENT OF INDIA, -.Depabthkm, EXPRESS LETTER [N ' B '~ T, Z! S T 0T 1 IGU 1 AL MrS t SAGE &gt; '»&gt; ty ^ to sa-e telegraphic ZZT f a Ti. h U ' due use °/ tk(3 wr™, but intended to be treated, on i eipt, with the same expedition as if u had bt-en telegraphed To ToLpZhZt 10 ™ 111 ^ U “ ^^^edasl/uhadleeu From Political, Muscat. To Be itconsul, Bushiro. A f &lt;\ C/64 i '''' ' 18th Moy tS3 7 , Subject:- Muscat Civil Air /pcrcemcnt Incrcoscd Rent for G w odur Aerodrome and refund of Duty on fuel. Reference correspondence ending with India Office telegram Ko.1242 dated 17th April 1937. 2 . I forward herewith copies of the letters noted in the Letter Bo.54 doted 3rd May 1937 T~ margin on the above mentioned subject, from the Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s ) Consul, Muscat to His Highness the ) 3. It will scon from the copy of Sultan. ) ) the Sultan's letter enclosed that Letter doted 11th May 1937 from ) TTie Highness the Sultan to the ) he confirms his desire, previously Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul ) Muscat. ) stated, of not wishing to bind himself per annum to accept the increased rental of £ 1000 /-^for a longer period than the expiry of the present Agreement i.e. 25th October 1938. 4. At the time of writing the cheque promised by the Sultan in his letter of 11th M 0 y for the amount outstanding on account s 6 MFP— 400S&amp;P—(M-4S0 —26-7-34—2,00,OCO. of ±cfund-- 2 — refund of duty on fuel uplifted has not been received hut it is hoped that it will he shortly when it will he forward ed as before to the Karachi Office of Imperial Airways Ltd. As regards the desire of His Majesty’s Government for the Sultan to agree to abolish the present system of Custon drawback (vide Indio Office telegram 1242 of 17th April) please see note on Muscat Civil Air Agreement dictated on April 24th by you while at Muscat?. As you will remember the Sultan was firm in assert- ing that he was unwilling to alter the rebate system in force at present.VM i- q/x^o j * POLITICAL Department. z/ 'V'&gt;; //y - From Secretary of State. To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of India, Department of External Affairs, Political Agent, Bahrein, Political Agent, Koweit, Political Agent, Muscat. Dated 5th April, 1937. ho. P.Z. 2034/37. A A Please refer to my express letter No. P.Z.735/37 dated the 6 th Fehruary 1937 ? regarding the issue of special authorisations for aircraft of Imperial Airways Ltd., etc. to ily in and over Bahrein, Koweit and Muscat. Copy is enclosed of a further letter from the Air n / Ministry, together with a revised list of aircraft for which Dated / pft.h ware/* special authorisations are required. If you see no 7. objection please take action as suggested by the Air /-n Ministry. With reference to the penultimate sentence of the Air Ministry letter, the special authorisation for aircraft to fly in and over Muscat territory during the year 1937 haa now been received as an enclosure to the letter No. 29-58 dated 15 th March 1937 from the Political Agent, Muscat. ^ he f abov* iifttt b*&lt;m duly (3gd.) M. J. CLAUSONAIR MINISTRY, 2.2034/37 GNYDYR HOUSE, 513185/36/C. A. 1 24th March, 1937 m Dear Clauson, Vill you please refer to previous correspondence terminating with your official letter, No. P.Z.1627/37, of the 11th instant, about the issue by the Rulers of Koweit Bahrein and Muscat of Special Authorisations for certain of Imperial Airways’ aircraft to fly in and over their respective territories ? We have just received from the Company a revised list of their aircraft, including the whole of their new fleet of 'C” Class flying boats and Ensign Class aircraft. The list is also brought up to date in other respects. In order to avoid further ’’piecemeal 1 * applications being made to the Rulers, we suggest, if you see no objection, that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf be requested to obtain fresh Authorisations in respect of Bahrein and Koweit. The Political Resident should also be asked to send a copy of the revised list to the competent Muscat Authorities, from whom the Special Authroisation covering flight in and over Muscat and Oman during the current year has not yet been received by this Department. In this connection it is suggested that opportunity might be taken to request the Political Resident tco propose to the Rulers that these and future Special Authorisations should be issued for 3-yearly periods- m p Yours etc (Sd. ) YMV.Burkett. M.J.Clauson, Esq., India Office, S.W.l.IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD AND ASSOCIATED COMPANIES FINLAY HOUSE, McLEOD ROAD KARACHI Telephone: KARACHI 2814 Telegrams. AIRWAYS, KARACHI Codes BENTLEY’S &amp; I AT.A . A. &gt; 7 Jh— Ref • A/20/6/388/WJ 4th May 1937. Major R.P. Watts, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. Dear Sir, Refund of duty on Petrol and Oil uplifted at Gwadur. I have pleasure in forwarding you our claim for refund of duty at Gwadur during the quarter ended 31st March 1937. I shall be grateful if you will submit this claim to His Highness the Sultan at your early convenience and also use your influence to assist us in final settlement of our previous claims. GDA. Yours faithfully, IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED., I/O Area Accountant.' ENGLIMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED. Claim for refund of Customs duty paid on Petrol re-exported on Imperial Airways Aircraft from Gwadur Quarter Ending 3lst March 1937. Uplifts at G-wadur Re-exported from Gwadur to 22422 gallons Jiwani. 1800 I! 24222 gallons Equivalent to 6055a- tins Duty @ Rs. 0.5*9.6o per tin = Rs .2195.1.10.J 4* IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED* Claim for refund of Customs duty paid on Aero Shell lubricating Oil re-exported on Imperial Airways Aircraft from Gwadur Quarter ending 51st March 1937• Total issues as per statement attached Duty @ Rs. 0.09 6 per gallon 730i? gallons Rs • 70.2.0. £• 5« 5» 2.1 f IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED- Statement of Petrol issued at Gwadur for use of our Aircraft at Jiwani - Quarter ending 3lo3.37- Date Tins. January 1937 150 February ' 150 March M 150 450 tins Equivalent to 1800 gallons* M0.r s - 4 IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD AND ASSOCIATED COMPANIES FINLAY HOUSE, McLEOD ROAD KARACHI Telephone: KARACHI 2814 Telegrams: A I RWAY S , KA RAC H I Codes: BENTLEY’S &amp; I A T A Of y '&gt;7 L/450/655/fo 14th May, 1937. The Political Agent &amp; H.B.M.’s Consul. MUSC AT. £ /tvi Sir, Aauipment for ^lying-Boat Route ^ G^dnr. K«/ /e the honour t0 refe r to the arrangements which nl r f ° T P royidln « at Gwadur such equipment as will ataE r thS ° Perati0Q of our flying-boats at that H M a/t y ° U r y b ® aware / we a ne, by arrangement with H.M. Government, apecifically exempt from the payment of duty axl equipment rtiich is essential for the operation of th« that* 0 &amp;s Tt' T f Pire air scheme?Jd ^r^sl* 118 arranged b^tween?^ concerned, such exemption has been ar. an b ed between H.M. OoTernment and the Government of Muscat. irom information which we have recently received frnm our nepresentative at Gwadur, however, it appears tLt t.n. customs officer at that station has received no instructions “‘“I 1 ’’ a 011 as first shipment of this eauipment consisting of the moorings for the flying-boats ia dnT + * arrive at Gwadur in the very near futu£? n is’dasirabi? hat our exertion from the payment of customs duty on such material should be established as early as possible. „ . W ® sll0 ^ lcl obliged, therefore, if you would be so o Od as to take up the matter on our behalf with the Qovsrnment 0 f lbsc.t,with a view to their IsSing the necessary instructions to the customs Officer at OwaL or, if necessary, to their agreeing to the question ?I 1^ f f IMPERIAL A I R WAYS LTD. 2 - is i duty being held in abeyance pending the conclusion of the necessary negotiations between the Governments concerned. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servants, IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITED, Assistan Indian Area,Telgrara - Cx.T.C. ^ ro!I1 - Britconsul, Bus?iire. r ^° “ Political, Muscat at Gwadur. Ko.491 Dated 31st May, received 1st June 1937. Your express letter Uo.C-64 of May 18th Civil Air Agreement. Please get from Sultan a letter confirming XKlj&amp;X what he informed me verbally that he v/as unwilling to agree to an alteration of the present system of the customs drawback. - Britconsul -* V ks&gt; A nA 7 nyi' GOVERNUENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESi LETTER lN ‘ D -~ This {s m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent % post to save telegraphic eij.cnse and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To ^despatched!] f0rmdU ' leS U “ mrded a ' d as if it had been Fuoii PoXiticol Hesident, Buslilre. To (1 v Political Agent, Kuwait. ^ Political Agent, Muscat, rolitical Agent, Bahrain, Xor imoraatlon qivyt X')! Ha, o5i-b of 19o7. 17th May m 7s ■ special Authorisations for air- crait oT Imperial Airways. Keference Inaio^jpffice Express Letter No. P.£. 2004/^7, dated 5th April 19^7. 2. Please obtain from the Ruler, in supersession of authorisations already grantee, an authorisation for the perioo 1st January 19S7 to Mist Deceober 19£9 for the aircraft in question. The original shouio be forwarded eirect to the Inoia Office with reference to their Express Letter quoted above anc. copies should be sent to the Government of India arm to me. i “ lJ; necessary, you should explain to the Ruler that the extension of the period of validity of the authorisatlo: is/ S. 6. MFP—1515 S&amp;P—(M-2089)—2-4-35—200,000. • 3 X.fi-la undaratandaU)lf • I concur, there fore t with Major Watta in recojamendin^ that no objection Mhould be ralaed to the proposed ataendraentt and would be glad to learn whether It la acceptable to His Majesty's Governaent. dd. T.G. Fowle• political Reeldent in the lersian Gulf. ATZ&amp;X'mp For Oecretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf*Confidential. No,350-S of 1937 British Residency 5c Consulate-General, Bushire, the 17th May, 1937, The Political cal Agent, . J MUSCAT. Subjects Authority for refusal of permission for private civil flights over the Arabian territories of Muscat and Oman, Memorandum. I'cP Reference paragraph 3 of ray Express letter No.50-S of the 11th January 1937. 2. This matter was overlooked on iry recent visit to Muscat. Please explain it to the Sultan. You should emphasise the diff icult i es, both to himself and to His Majesty’s] Government, that would result from a forced landing, inform him that the Rulers of Kuwai t and Bahrain have on this account requested His Majesty’s Government to refuse on their behalf any application for private flights over their territories, mention the difficulty and delay in referring applications to him when he is at Dhof ar, and ask him to address you a letter authorising His Majesty’s Government to refuse 0 n his behalf permission for such flights. sd. T.C.Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,ooari: :ial . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B •—This is an 0 RIQINAL message sent by AIR MAIL tchich provides a means of communieation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No -C-86/B8 Dated 'NSTPelU' the 24th Jun# ^ojJL tloal Huaoat* x. ticoratarjr or atata for i»dxa, India Ofrioo# London. 2* Sho Boo ratary to too ooTomnont or India in the Sntornal AT lair a Doiiartaantf Binia. 2«f- Xha Hon 1 bio tho ^oiiUeai Hooidoat in tho Poroian GuiT, Bushiro* •atfaorl»«&gt;Uon for Alrarmf t of D , &gt;xrway UwlVjd . ■Keferencft,^ I H«f«r«nc« India OttXoo T&amp;xpgaaa Latter Ho.It 2034/37, date, tea ftte AyriX 19S7. a. I anolosa a S^aelal Antearlaatioa far tea par lad lat January 1987 to tea 84te Oatofear 1988 far tea Aircraft af tea laparlal Airways ta land la and fly arar tea territory of Hla Hlghnoea tea Sultan af Hkiaoat and Oman. 8. Sinaa tea proaant Uuaoat civil Air Asraanoat axplraa an 28te Cotobar 1938 tea Spool al Auteoriaatlan ax tend a only to teat data. (Signature) ■ajar.TElegram - Q. (Received via Muscat on ss Barpeta.) From - Secretary of State for India, London. No.1755. Dated 24th Reed. 26th June 1937. Addressed to Bushire, repeated Muscat, copy sent by Air Mail to Government of India. Your telegram No.578 of May the 28th 404-S . Air Navigation Notification. His Majesty^ Government agree, for your information.EXPRESS LETTER. Air Mall . (Confidential.) From - Political, Muscat at Karachi. To - Briteonsul* Bushire. Ho.R-14/58. Bated, Karachi, the i&amp;th J|iLy 1937 # Subjectt- aefund of duty on fuel uplifted at Gwadur. Reference correspondence ending with youi* telegram No.491 of 1st June 1937. 2. ' I enclose, herewith, copy of ay letter to the Sultan on the above subject and of his reply thereto. 3. As will be seen from the Sultan*s letter he con firms what he had stated verbally that he is not willing to change the existing system in this matter in force at Gwadur. /- f'7 H gy Political Agent Sc H.B.M*s Consul, Muscat. 0Copy of a letter No.82/69-C, dated the 25rti June 1957, from the Political Agent &amp; H,B.M T s Consul, Muscat His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat. to i* / With reference to the conversations regarding aviation matters which took place at the Agency between Your Highness and the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf during the latter^ visit to Muscat in April I am directed to request your Highness to confirm what you then stated verbally that you were not willing to change the present system in force by which customs duty is paid on petrol and oil landed at Gwadur for Imper ial Airways Ltd and a refund afterwards given on the quantities actually uplifted by the machines of that Com pany. Usual Ending. 0 O 0 Copy (in translation) of a letter dated the loth Rabi ! Than! 1356, corresponding to the 23rd June 1937, from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat to the Political Agent &amp; H.B.M T s Consul, Muscat. y' ^ We have received your letter No.32/69-C., dated the 23rd June 1937, and have understood what you stated therein. We confirm the matter as stated by you. Usual Ending. 111rK n ■ d'-J 1 Lvju=« • * * 1 CONFIDENTIAL hBCORD Date. 13 Jl)L. io. / v^V &gt; &gt; . . / ^ ^| . ^ —L/* tj Ab\ jl I - jci^z- xX^j. —1»:/' i (S ^ y y^yj&gt; fYL^' / ’^*=&gt; Translation of the above letter dated the l&amp;th July 1937 from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Karachi to the Political Agent and H.B.M f s Consul, Muscat at Karachi. * &gt; AtSj. L&gt;^ With reference to your lettep No.33/58-C, dated the fe3rd June 1937, which We have received at Karachi, We enclose, herewith, a cheque on the Imperial Bank for the sum of £.851/1/- Please let me know the receipt of the said checue. Usual Ending.From Fated, Ziarat, the R No.£'7 of !ajor R.P.Watts, I.A., Political Agent &amp; H.B.¥»s Consul, Muscat. To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman. Your Highness, I have the honour to inform your Highness that I have today received a telegram from the Government of India that Imperial Airways aeroplane 'Satyrus” is leaving Egypt on a casual flight to India and is due to arrive at Gwadur about the 19th or ?Oth of July. I have been directed to request your High ness to grant authorization for this flight. Usual Ending Sd ' P.P. 'atts Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.’Hs Consul, Muscat 0/C.■■ -W. mg /N Telegram - C. Foreign Simla, Addre«fli4 to Bushire, repeated to Political Ills cat at 7iarat, No.1598. Dated the 14th ) Received the 15th ^ July 1957. •R-* 5 ’ Reference your express letter of June S4th No.C-35/58. 2. Intimation has been received that Imperial Airv/ays aeroplane Satyrus is leaving Alexandria on casual flight to Karachi on July 15th and arriving Gwadur 19th or Please obtain necessary authorization from Muscat. Political, Muscat at Ziarat. Addressed to Britconsul, Bushire, repeated pereign, Simla. B - J Dated the 16th July 1937, Foreign Telegram No,1593 of July 14th, Authorization obtained from Sultan. - Watts -Telegram Fr om To No.744. Q. Brltconsul, Bushire. Addressed to Government of India, repeated to Watts at Ziarat. Dated and received the j6th July 1937. d&gt;.„ jf**'*, A «! 6 ^ Your telegram 1 No.1598 of July 14th. India Office have nov intimated that flight has teen postponed for a fen days. Authorization for whole of flec;t of flying boats has been included in blanket authoriz ation referred to In Muscat express letter quoted by you. ' • Since Sultan is away Political Agent, ’'uscat should telegraph to British Agent, Gwadur instructing him to inform Wali (a) that authorization has already been granted by Sultan, and (b) of approximate dateof flight. British Agent should add that I would be grateful for any assistance which he (Walii cxn give to flying boat . 4 • British Agent himself should of course mett flying boat and render every assistance. - Britconsul -E-grferH!; im gv -a-Asi ■ ~sm, _ -4^ T! Jg.-5j&gt;? iSBraE d ~v^ ' - Wmm ■ :; *■:'? «--* !BS Sr^£ - S- ~ &amp; Telegram - En Claire. From - Politic-l, Muscat at Ziarat. To • ~ i - • Dated trie 17th July 1937. r i t i sh *gent, Gvra dur. Imperial Airvrays flying boat Satyrus is due at Gwadur on £Oth or few days later on special flight to Karachi. Inform Tfr ali that authorization has been already granted by Sultan and that Political “esident would be greteful for any assistance he could give the flying boat stop ^ou should of course yourself meet the boat and render all assistance required. - Watts -Translation of a letter dated Jamad Avrv/al y ? 1S56 (about 20th July 1927) from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Srinagar to the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat at Ziarat. Reference the Air Navigation Notification, the publication of which you have asked us to effect for information of those who are concerned. 2. T Ae have agreed to publish the Notification on condition that its contents should be applicable to your subjects, and that you should publish a similar notifi cation when Y. r e publish the same. 2. When We were at Karachi a few days ago you delivered to us the Notification with the modifications We had suggested to be included therein before publica tion. But you have not written us a letter confirming that you will publish a similar notification for your subjects. Hence We are deferring the publication of the Notification until We receive your letter to the effect desired. 4. It is also stated in the Notification that a copy of the Air Navigation Regulations is attached thereto, but you have not sent us a copy of the said Regulations. We, therefore, request that you will send us a cony thereof, as the copy We had was left in Muscat and therefore We could not make copies of the same. 5. We shall let you know at once when We impose the penalty on anyone who may violate the Air Navigation Regulations. Usual Ending.4 ./ ■ . % li §£) Confidential. iTcft f* / 8o.R-£4 of 1857. Catap Office, Zlarat, £5rd July 1957. From 0 Major R«P # Watts, X.A*, m Political Agent &amp; Consul, Muscat on recess at Ziarat, To The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, 4 A \ Sir, I nave the honour to refer to your memorandum No*555-2 dated May the 17th 1957 on the subject of obtwining authority from the Sultan for refusal of per mission for private civil flights over the Arabian terri- * tories of Muscat and Oman* k* I discussed this matter at some length *ith dis Hlgimesa and raised all the points mentioned in your letter quoted above but could not succeed in persuading him to agree to give the required authority to His Majesty's Government, The : ultan declared that ^hile he realized the inadvisAbility of allowing private civil aviators to fly aown the Arab coast, and so far as Muscat territories were concerned he would in most cases reject all sucn applications, he was unwilling to delegate altogether his authrbity to refuse permission )V all and sundry as he felt that in the case of those nations with whom he had Treaties, i,e, the United States, France and the Dutch Netherlands such an act would be likely to be considered unfriendly especially as no request for such refusal had presumably been made by the Governments of those three countries.Tk® Multan stated that he would be willing to authorize his Majesty^s Government to refuse permission ior private civil i. lights over his Arabian territories for the subjects of all countries other than those three mentioned in the preceding paragraph but^ I said that I did not think such an arrangement would be suitable* 5* Under the circumstances if His Majesty*s Government consider the matter important I see no other course but to make another attempt to persuade the sultan to issue the authority asked for when he returns from his visit to Bagdad and the Gulf about the end of September* I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. B.P.Watts Major, Political Agent k h.B.M*s Consul, Muscat.IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD AND ASSOCIATED COMPANIES FINLAY HOUSE, McLEOD ROAD KARACHI Telephone: KARACHI 2814 Telegrams: AI RWAY S , KARAC H I Codes BENTLEY’S &amp; I AT A Ref.A/20/6/1380/WJ 27th July 1937. Major R.P.Watts, Political Agent and Consul,Muscat, C/o Post Master, Zirat. Dear Sir, As arranged in the course of our recent conversation I am forwarding to you at your address in Zirat our claim for refund of duty on fuel and oil uplifts at Gwadur during the quarter ended 30th June 1937. Your assistance in obtaining settlement of our previous claims is greatly appreciated and I am grateful for your assurance that future claims will have your personal attention. CrDA. INCL. political Agency and CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Date. 3 0. JUL t-iv- Reg, No, * H, B. M’S OVULATE; MUSCAT, Yours faithfully, IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LIMITH)., Area Accountant.A IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD. CLAIMS FOR REFUND OF CUSTOMS IUTY PAID ON AERO SHELL LIJBRIXATING OIL RE-EXPORTED ON IMPERIAL AIRWAYS AIR- CRAFT FROM GWADUR - QUARTER ENDINQ 50TH JUUE, 1957 Total issues as per statement attc. V65j Gallons Duty at Rs. 0.096 per gallon - Rs. 73 . 7.10 £• 5.10. 3 G.C.Cypher Telegram from Secretary of State for Indi; to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf? dated 8th January^ 1938. (No. of words 63)* X 66*. Addressed to Political Resident. Copy hy post ao Government oi India, 'external Affairs Department, Political Agent, Bahrain and Political Agent, Muscat. My express Letter No. P. Z. 6266/37 of 25th Septemher* Aircraft au.horisafions. Please expedite authorisations required from Husc.: t authorities. Air inistry enquire whethe r permission granted oy Rulers for aircraft of Imperial nirv/ays to fly over rind lan a in Sharjah and Behai covers aircraft he longing to Associated Companies. I assume answer is in af £iriaati ve hut pie a s e c onf' i r .;.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/73</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/73</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File [IIA/1 II] II. AVIATION. A. CIVIL AVIATION. (1) Civil Air Agreement with Sultan.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:03:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (290 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 282; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-282; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence in the form of telegrams, letters and memoranda between representatives of the British Government, Imperial Airways and the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Sa‘id bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd. The correspondence in the volume is related to the following: the Muscat Air Navigation Regulations, 1936; sanctions to be applied in the event of the breaches of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Air Navigation Regulations; revision of the financial clauses of the Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat Civil Air Agreements; communications regarding the Imperial Airways’ special Christmas flight; copies of special authorisation for aircraft to land in and fly over Muscat and Oman issued, signed and sealed by the Sultan; the increased rent for Gwadur aerodrome and refund of duty on fuel; and copies of draft air navigation regulations sent by the Political Agent at Muscat to the Sultan of Muscat and Oman for amendments and approval.The volume also includes correspondence with Imperial Airways regarding their charges for attendance and facilities at Gwadur and their scales for both commercial and private aircraft. Imperial Airways in turn asked the Political Agent at Muscat to communicate on their behalf with the Sultan in matters that are related to the refund of fuel duties at Gwadur. Imperial Airways provided lists of outstanding refund claims (ff 173-195) of recoverable duty on petrol and oil at Gwadur, the lists covering the period from 26 October 1934 to 31 December 1936. The next claims were sent at quarters ending 31 March 1937 and 30 June 1937 respectively.The volume also includes correspondence between the Political Agent, Muscat; and the Political Resident, Bushire regarding obtaining authority from the Sultan for the refusal of permission for private civil flights over the Arabian territories of Muscat and Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Muscat Civil Air Agreement (1934)</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Airways</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Gwadur</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air services agreements</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>