<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-23T11:19:40.140Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">[n any further communication on this subject, please quote No. X S03/3i4D( 27/49) and address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State/’ Foreign Office, V Londori^ ajy.i. / /&gt; | \ r*| “Sir, (7^7^ I sin to correspond Pakistani 0r&lt; Embassy Tehrj _19kS from th&lt; Karachi to yi 2. I am to asked His Ma a refund of shown in thei Karachi and -8 and Mr. B e would submiti relevant voucj letter. The Under-Secretary o Commonwealth RelIn any further communication on this subject, please quote No XS03/34D(27/49) t and address— X not to any person by name but to— ' 'The Under-Secretary of State,” T? r- i n r&gt; a Foreign Office, oreign Office. S. W. 1 1ijth July, 19242 I sm directea by Mr. Seoretsry Bevin to refer to correspondence concerning iuie recruitment of Pakistani Orderlies for service at His Majesty’s Embassy Tehran, telegram Nb. 133‘5 of 2nd November, 4 91^8 from the United Kingdom High Commissioner, Karachi to your Department refers. 2. I am to state that the High Commissioner has asked His Majesty’s Ambassador in Tehran to secure a refund of expenses incurred in this connexion, as shown in the accounts of the High Commissioner, Karachi and the Deputy High Commissioner, Lahore, and Mr. Bevin would be glad if your Department would submit a claim in due course, supported by . relevant vouchers, and with reference to this letter. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State, Commonwealth Relations Office^ * Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ^ / A, V ^ ALLOTTED TO POLITICiiL DEPARTI.IENT , %(J ENCLAIR j .. .. ! i 3 TAN. PROM : ' ' TO: RPTD.TO : BRITISH EMBASSY TEHERAN D. Ki^R/^CHI i5*50 hours, 2nd Nov., 1948« P* *35 hours, 2nd »» •* ^ 9 11.35 hours, No. 1335. Addressed to Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London No. 1335&gt; repeated to British Embassy Teheran No. 274 ZSC. to British Embassy Teheran. Begins :~ Your telegram No. 21 of 28th September. Impossible arrange absolute inanity of pension but hope to recruit fall number with approximately similar pensions within next ten days. Will wire further progress when known. Ends. Copy to: Parliamentary^ Under State, Foreign Office.14982 35880—10 7 Herewith copy of telegram No i. from for repetition ^kixypilwg ,# to !^V^L*..G^ I Foreign Office, {Date) &lt;?yvrf .....J&amp;L*^.... Telegram Section. * Delete when inapplicable.C/ Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office * t r Hr ■'( ALLOTTED TO POLITICAL DSPARTMSHT . ^OiSXcD j EN CLAIR ' PROM: ACTING U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN ACTING U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN PAKISTAN RBPTD.TO : PEHAWAR ( No. 190 ) D. KARACHI, 15.30 hours, 23rd September, 1948 15-10 hours, 23rd September, 1948 IMPORTANT No*1132. Addressed Coramonwealth Relations Office No#1132, repeated Peshawar No#190 for Reed# Our No.1101 of 1?th Se ptember. Please pass following to British Embassy, Teheran# BEGINS: Recruitment of Pakistani Orderlies. Our Rawalpindi representative has.inspected six recommended candidates ranging in age from 28 to 48# Only one is pensioner although remainder are ex-soldiers. In view of your requirements in your despatch No.6 of 16th February, are you prepared to accept these, relaxing age and pensioner conditions. If you insist on candidates being pensioners and between ages of 37 and 40, this will entail further delay of at least three weeks# ENDS. Copy to :- Foreign Office - (For retransmission to Teheran). ” ' - Mr. F.S. Jones.MMBP / y 4 S'; Telegraph Section, Colonial Office, Church House, : — ' - Telegram Section, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, Message Control, G-erman Section^ Foreign Office, Norfolk House, Herewith copy of telegram No. for repetition *in cypher* to_ Cooi C - War Registry, Admiralty. Duty Signal Officer, War Office Signal Office, Montagu House Annexe. Telegram Section,r / QOJ s 35101—1 :t&gt;*,Mo With the Compliments of the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs Foreign Office, Hi? AUG, 194^.10 . (3 Fa KICK OFF 10E f ; • V. 1. I3t^ ^ug5u?t f 1948. (XS03/34i)( 58/48)) Dear Mr* Creswell, On receipt of your telegram Ho. 540 dated 6th July on the subject of new orderlies frcjci PeklstacT, we requested the CoK®aonwealth Relations Office to transmit your message to Sir Laurence Grafftey-Smith. We have now received a copy of a letter* i,o«592 of 21 st July* from the office of the United Kingdom High'Coitmjis^ioner to l ohermed Xkramullahp Secretary in the Ministry of Foreign iiflairs anc Carmonwealth Relation6 f Governrrent of Pakistan* This letter requests a decision by the Pakistan Government on the subject* in view of the fact that urgent reminders are continually being received both from Tehran and London* I think there is nothing more we can do at the moment to hasten action, but I will keep you informed of the position as known to us. Y ours sincerely, (o.itudsley) (Mrs*) M* J. Creswell,Ksq*, Tehran*tw. r* c . to C.R.O. 'with reference to their telegram i T, , T TT T 0/1 Q H No. 1181 dated 16th July, 1948'. 5111 you please refer to our letter No. 598 dated 12th May on the subject of recruitment in Pakistan of Pakistani nationals for service as Security Guards in the British Embassy at Teheran. 2. I should be most grateful if you could let us know the decision of the Government of Pakistan on this matter, as we are continually receiving urgent reminders, both from ie ieran and from London, asking when this qiiestion will be settled. R.R. Burnett tlohaiomed Ikramull&amp;h, Lsq. , CIE., Secretary in the Ministry of foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Goverrunent of Pak 1 s tan , Clifton, KARACHI.Telegraph Section, Colonial Office, - Church House. War Registry Admiralty ■'T^egram Section Commonwealth Relations Office, Duty Signal Officer War Office Signal Downing Street. Office, Message Control, German Section. Foreign Office, Norfolk House, Herewith copy of telegram No. to -v , / Trom P r Vr for repetition *i-n cypher* to FOREIGN OFFICE. (Date) Telegram Section * Delete when inapplicable.Telegraph Section, Colonial Office, Church House. War Registry, Admiralty. Telegram Section. Commonwealth Relations Office. Downing Street. Message Control, German Section, Foreign Office, Norfolk House, Duty Signal Officer, War Office Signal Office, Montagu House Annexe. Herewith copy of telegram No. ter Trom r ■P 0.-» r&lt;-f for repetition *in cyphe N ■y* to P (j FOREIGN OFFICE. (Date) Q .l # yj ^ Telegram Section. I r * Delete when inapplicable.{Begins^ Your telegram No. 2785 of 24th July and your further telegram of 29th July. Following is repetition of my telegram No. 2 Saving. [Begins] Your telegram No. 1196. . Fazal. Ahmad Khan owes rupees 500 advanced on account of Chinese tuition fees/ Request you authorize payment of sum for British Consulate Peking on behalf of Government of Pakistan. - 2, Sea passages veiy difficult to obtain and Khan B£C accordingly .have to, wait for long period in Tientsin ahdi/br hpng ,Kohg at considerable expense of Government of Pakistan if f ne travels by sea. He particularly wishes to avoid a* second class sea journey from Tientsin to Hong Kong which ’'nearly, killed” him when he came to China.. Say we there fore have authority .to' send him by air from Peking to Hong Kon 0 in any event Tgp undec.J by air all the, way, ' (ieking Shanghai Karachi via Pah American Airways) if this seemed likely to be more economical?' (It would in any case be more convenient as accommodation in Tientsin and Hong Kong is likely to be difficult). . May. we also haVe . authority to .pay freight charges on his heavy baggage which would be forwarded by sea. [Ends] Grateful for early reply. [Copies Office, nt to Telegram Sectio wning street for repe ctio Commonwea s repe ion to Fo i] 1 8 8 8 8——IHHI C.C. to C.R.O. 'With reference to your telegram No* 1181 dated 16th July* 1948* My Dear Mohammed Ikramullah, Will you pleaae refer to our lette No.592 dated 12th May on the subject of recruitment in Pakistan of Pakistani nationals for service as Security Guards in the British Embassy at Teheran. 2. I should be most grateful if you could let us know the decision of the Government of Pakistan on this matter, as we are continually receiving urgent reminders* both from Teheran and from London, asking when this question will be settled. R.R.Burnett Mohammed Xkramullah Esq.* C.I.E.* Secretary in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Government of Pakistan, Clifton. » KAHACHI^e-l o givnh fit; ci7xoii, Office, Churcfe M-Guse. telegram Section, Commonwealth Re1ations Downing Street, age Control . German Section, Forei^wr Office, irfolk House. Office, War Registry Adiujjpefity Duty Signal Officer, War OftitTe Signal ^ O^fJce, Montague Hooee Annexe. Herewith copy of telegram Ho. for repetition *in cypher- 1 to /3t •' Delete when inapplicable. A (LslaI telegram Section.mppumni S J 3 ' l * t ^ ' ’ • ^ Sat- &gt;« (XS03/3itf)(58/48)) ,NOS XEO FOREIGN OFFICE, ,/V. 8, Carlton House Terrace, ’ | , . . . ;o I S.W. i. ■ 13th July, 1948 // $k. *h Dear Harrison, i^voacj. frA **11 aj H Creswell, His Majesty^ Charge d* Affaires at Tehran^; has been in cornm uni cation recently with the United Kingdom High Commissioner for Pakistan on the question of the engagement of Indian orderlies, Creswell now asks whether we will, on his behalf, request Grafftey-Srnith to proceed with recruitment, and I shall be glad if you will have a telegram sent to the High Commissioner on the following lines 'Your telegram No. 61+4 of 12th June. His Majesty’s Chargd d f Affaires at Tehran would be grateful if new orderlies could be engaged and sent forward at once.' Your n insincerely, (E.S. Jones) P.A.K. Harrison, Esq., Commonwealth Relations Office.This is an unparaphrased version of a Secret cypher (typex) message and f j the text must first be paraphrased if it is essential to communicate it to persons outside British and United States Government Services^ Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relatio ' 0 ALLOTTED TO POLITICAL DEPARTMENT (B) CYPHER (TYPEX) FROM: U.K. HIGH COMMISSIOHER IIT PAKISTAN. FROM : U.K. HIGH COMMISSIONER IN 2: KARACHI, '13*45 hours, 1 2th June, 19k8* R: 15*40 hours, 12th Juno, 1948* D R KARACHI, 13*45 hours, 12th Juno, 1948« 15*40 hours, 12th Juno, 1948. IMPORTANT No. 644. telegram No.983 dated 7th June. Teheran Orderlies. 2. Pakistan Government is being pressed for an early decision on our No.592 dated 12th May, copied to yourselves. Have meanwhile suggest (?suggested) to representative in Rawalpindi that he should make tentative enquiries, although selection cannot be finalised before formal agreement of Pakistan Government. Copy to:- Foreign Office - Mr* Clinton Thomas.C ••j'lDFMALj ie following to United loner Karachi as my telegram ly despatc h o.l . How does the matter now stand? The need for additional orderlies is acute and I should he grateful if you could arrange lor at least two to leave as soon as possible. k k kTelegraph ^etrcion, Goliitfal Office, -^Church House, Te1e gram'Section, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street. Message Conj^ol, 'Herman/oection, Foreign Office, Norfoll^Hiouse. @ Duty Signal Officer, War Office Signal Office, Montague House Annexe. Herewith copy of telegram Ho. '’from FOnDIGH OFF (Date) it ■ Delegram SoctiohT Delete when inapplicable.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1333</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002d7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1333</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Pol. Ext 16336/48 'Recruitment of Pakistani Orderlies to HM Embassy at Tehran'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-09T23:44:42</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (24 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 26; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Thefile contains correspondence regarding a request to the Government of Pakistanto approve the recruitment of Pakistani citizens to work as security guards atthe British Embassy in Tehran. The primary correspondents are the CommonwealthRelations Office, the British Embassy in Tehran, the High Commission to Pakistan and the ForeignOffice. The file includes a divider, which gives a list ofcorrespondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at theback of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commission to Pakistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commonwealth Relations Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Pakistan</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy in Iran, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Employment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002d7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>