<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:38:44.315Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ID.O. Ho.C/1222 POLITICAL AQKNCY BAHRAIN. The 2nd November,1946 0 Dear colonel Galloway, Mr. Hussain Agar, a Persian subject and naturalised British subject, who is the Managing Director of the Etemedieh Mills, Bushire, has asked telegraphically through the British Consul, Bushire, for permission to visit Bahrain to discuss with the Bahrain Government and myself a project for setting up a cotton mill here. 2. Belgrave informs me that die Bahrain Government would be interested in discussing such a project and I have therefore informed Consul, Bushire, that there is no objection to Mr. Agar coming here. It will, of course, be necessary, should the project materialise^ for us to lay down very definite conditions as to the staffing of the mill and the treatment of the labour employed by them, as it would clearly be undesirable for Bahrain to be flooded out with Persian M experts’* or for us to allow labour to be ’’sweated” on the Bushire pattern. Yours sincerely C X • E • The Hon’ble Lt-Col. A.C. Galloway,/CUBIL , political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BahrainV TK I_. A OU K!j: mw AGAR SHIRAZ N° ^ J IX? ) Hussein Agar (Etemad) )4sbM»x 21st Nov. 1946. j G/o The Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. Lieut. Golonal A.G. Galloway, C.I.E., The Political Agent, Bahrain. Further to my verbal proposal to erect a Cotton Mill in Bahrain - I now beg to enclose my views regarding the same in writing for your consider ation . I have the honour to remain,©3 j ^ —-jL5 ) / I } Uy * Hussein Agar (Etemad) XKt.. A U M F* K M M AGAR SHIRAZ Shiraz N° 1. )The Government of H.H.The Sheikh of Bahrein grant to I.Ir.Hussein Agar (Etemad) a naturalized British subject Permission to errect and work a cotton mill in Bahrein comprising Spinning Reaving,dyeing,bleaching,finishing and printing(cloth) departements with all necessary machinery and power for this purpose. 2. The Government of H.H.The Sheikh will grant to Hussein Agar Etemad sufficient and suitable land to build this factory and adjacent houses on a lease for 99 (ninety nine) years at a nominal rental of one thousand Pupees per Annum free of any other taxation with power to build,to sink wells for water,to plant and cultivate^z^^ 3. The Government of H.H.The Sheikh will grant to Hussein Agar Etemad permission to import into Bahrein all machinery, building material for the mill and houses,equipment,spares,dyes and other chemicals and all raw materials,specially cotton,free of customs duty or any other charges. 4. The mill will sell its produce first for all local .requirements and all cloth or yarn or waste exported will be free of customs duty or any other charges. 5. Hu;sein Agar Etemad undertakes to pay as tax 10$ of its net profits(annual) to The Government of H.H.The Sheikh of Bahrein. 6. No other taxes of any kind whatsoever will be levied on the Mill. 7-^The Mill management will be allowed to bring experts and mechanics and skilled labour to work the mill,but in all cases of equal capacity preference will be given to local labour when available.9 biXKnT , D* 0« o.C/^316. The 24th November, 1946. Mr. A4ar from Bushire who, I undersWnd, is staying with you iias applied go me for permission to erect a cotton mill in Bahrain. 2. I have known Mr. Agar for a number of years, but should be grateful for your secret and confidential renarks on his financial integrity and the capital sum' which, in your opinion, he has available to invest on a project in Bahrain. Yours sincerely, J.P• Burton, , ?'anager, The imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain. NS.No. C/131.7. .. The 24th of irovefaber, X946. Dear Mr. Agar, ' Thank you for your letter rtated the 21st November, 1946* the ratter Is under consideration and T s.'iall inform you later of the result. B a h r a i n.3* war Thank you for your letter dated the 21st Novender, 1946. The matter is under consideration and I shall inform you of ■J!' ,\ Is'ie^iiie Biirp'EXPRESS LBTTEK . From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/1320. Dated the 25th of November, 1946 I enclose a copy of a letter I have received from Mr. Hussain Agar and a proposed form of agreement for erecting a cotton mill in Bahrain. 2. Mr. Agar has been well known to me for a number of years. H© started a cotton mill in Bushire which eventually paid its way. He is a well known character in South Persia and Tehran and poses as very pro-British. This, I think, he is - he is, in fact, naturalised - when it suits his book. He is a verbose person and too much reliance should not be placed on his word. He is an energetic person and if he set his mind to the task he wishes to undertake his past experience should enable him successfully to achieve his object. I think he is now a wealthy man and I am enquiring from the bank regarding his financial integrity. I shall inform you of the reply later. 3* As regards the proposal I have spoken to the Shaikh and the Adviser in general terms and we three are agreed that if some satisfactory arrangement can be come to with Mr. Agar it would be beneficial to Bahrain. 4. As regards the terms of the proposal my comments are as follows (1) All plant and machinery to be new and pur chased in Great Britain. (2) The proposed rent seems very low but I have no idea of the extent of the land required nor where it is proposed to site the mill. (3) This is reasonable and is a concession granted to oil companies in exchange for royalty pay ments. The terms finally agreed upon might follow the lines of BAPCO agreement in this respect. (4) This seems reasonable except, of course, for actual porterage and such like charges, and if a suitable royalty or percentage of profits is paid to the Bahrain Government. (5) Until capital outlay and rate of return, etc., is estimated I would prefer not to comment on this. (6) Here again we should follow the same lines as the Bahrain petroleum Company. (7) This might follow the lines of Article 17 of the commercial Agreement to the qatar Concession. For our own part we might bind Mr. Agar on the lines of Article 3 the Qatar Political Agreement. /5. The shaikh- 2 - 5. The Shailch has informed me that he will take no definite step without previously seeking the political Agent's advice and so, if you have no objection, I propose to inform Mr# Agar that he is at liberty to discuss his project with the Shaikh and the Bahrain Government. The latter, I think, should be advised either to make an agree ment with nr. Agar on the broad lines of an oil con cession or else to form a company in which a number of shares should be made available to the Bahrain public. I am in favour of the labter. &lt;3 6. I should be grateful for instructions. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.I iM '■» j • jrJ \ ♦ • • ♦ ♦ • 4A* i \ j\ J.3 •jL-i&gt; TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS, “BACTRI A' In reply please quote Our Eef ,/i' -v f) ue Q=Z/mfi€ita an ft a lan i/l4^ Jk^rt ^ aXttrU'ZLy^ Bahrain.,-..w.Q-t-ti--lJoy§mber /j? 46 Secret and confidenti c Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIFI\ ^ S ^ * With reference to your enquiry, D.O. -&gt; 0 . C/I3I6 of 24th inst., regarding Mr. Hussein Agar, I have been out of touch with him for some years, and I regret I have no accurate idea as to the extent of his present personal fortune. He has, as you are doubtless aware, made very large profits from his mill in Bushire, and he is undoubtedly very wealthy. I believe a large portion of his capital is invested profitably in the United States , and that he has large funds also in Iran. He has not discussed his project here in any great detail with me, but he has given me the impression that he is pcepared, if required, to finance the whole undertaking himself, mentioning a figure as high as £2oo,ooo. I can express no opinion as to his ability to provide this sum, but I do not consider he would be likely to make a statement of this kind were he unable to implement it. He has been a valued customer of this bank for many years, and my own experience, as Manager in Bushire, of his business integrity was a very satisfactory one. One aspect of the situation has no doubt occurred to you, but I feel bound to mencion it. All Mr. Agar f s Form 120fc ^ ,jl y\ Z*? •jLi Bahra in,... S o th November /(? 46 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. “BACTRIA” ( Page tv/o ) In reply please quote Our Ref. business successes have been achieved by his own drive and organising ability, and he has always retained a very large degree of personal control. He is not nov; so young as he once was. Lt. Col. A.C.Galloway, C.I.E.,O.B.E., H.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Form 120No. V - Of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Muharram 8, 1366 December 2, 1946. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain• Memor andum:- / s With reference to your D.o.No. c/1194 dated B3rd November 1946, regarding the visit of Mr. Hussein Agar to Bahrain in connection with setting up a cotton mill. 2. Mr. Agar called on me on Tuesday 26th and dis cussed his project, he gave me a note, which I understand he also gave to you, setting out some of the concessions which he desires to obtain from the Bahrain Government. 3. On Saturday I discussed the matter with His Highness. He would welcome the setting up of a new industry in Bahrain such as a cotton mill provided that it was conducted in a proper manner. The following is the gist of His Highness f s views on Mr. Hussein Agar’s proposalsj- 1 a. His Highness would not object to a commercial company being formed with shares to be offered to the public, His Highness and the Bahrain Government J would be prepared to purchase shares in such a company but the accounts of the company would have to be audited and inspected by a reputable firm of accountants preferably Messrs. Whirmey Murray &amp; Co. b. In the case of Mr. Hussein Agar conducting the business himself, not as a company, His Highness would be prepared to allow him to purchase, not to hire for 99 years, a suitable piece of land, probably on Muharraq island, at the local market price. If he became the owner of the land he could build upon it plant and cultivate as he desired. His Highness would give permission for the drilling of a well for the purpose of the industry. c. His Highness would grant exemption from customs duty on certain imports which would be required for the purpose of the industry but would not grant a blanket exemption for everything that might be claimed to pertain to the industry. No export duties are charged in Bahrain. The exemption on import dues would cover /saw cotton, machinery, chemicals., dyes and imports directly connected with milling but not ordinary building materials. d. His Highness would require some form of guarantee that the local population will be able to buy their requirements of cloth from the manufacturer. e. The accounts of the undertaking should be audited by the Government Auditors at the owner’s expense. 2 / Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.2 f. No Persians should be brought from Persia to work in the mill. g. Mr. Hussein Agar would be liable to pay all normal local taxes, Municipal house tax and shop tax if he sets up premises inside either of the Municipal areas and car tax on any vehicles which he may own. h. His Highness wishes to know approximately the amount of capital which Mr. Hussein Agar proposes to invest in the undertaking. i. All persons employed in the factory will have to conform to the law and the customs of the country. j. No boys under 16 years should be employed in th e factory and if women work there they should work in a place apart from the men. The factory should be subject to inspection by the State Medical Officer and must be conducted in a manner compatible with Moslem traditions. 4. From the views expressed by His Highness I realised that he would prefer Mr. Hussein Agar to float a company in Bahrain for working a mill but I gathered that Mr. Hussein Agar did not consider doing this and I think myself that such a scheme would be open to objection. Few of the local inhabi tants know anything about companies and His Highness appeared to think that it would be possible for Mr. Hussein Agar to float a company and at the same time to guarantee himself that the shareholders would not stand to lose anything that they invested. Failing a company His Highness would be agreable to allowing Mr. Hussein Agar to buy land and operate a mill with exemption from customs duties, which are almost the only form of taxation in Bahrain, on imports of cotton and materials necessary for the mill itself, in return for the payment of 10% of the profit, subject to the conditions which I have mentioned above. Adviser to the Government. S.Z.■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■ No. C/1354. The 3rd December, 1946 Dear Mr. Agar, Thank you for your letter of this morning. The matter is under active consideration and I shall Inform you as soon as possible. Yours sincerely,\ b EXPRESS LETTER , From - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/1355. Dated the 3rd December, 1946. Reference my Express Letter No.C/1320 dated the 25th November, 1946. I enclose a copy of a reply I have received from the Manager of the Imperial Bank of Iran. 2. My comments ares I think it is a fact that Mr. Agar has made large profits during the war and I should surmise that he is now looking for a profitable investment for these profits, if, as I have said before, he wishes to invest these in Bahrain, I see no objection. 3. My comment on paragraph 2 of the enclosure to this letter is that I do not agree that much reliance should be placed upon Mr. Agar's word that he wishes to spend £200,000. To me he mentioned the figure £150,000. His actual project cannot be known until after receipt of your reply - which, I understand, has been drafted - to my express letter under reference. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED. _Uw&gt;sz_' for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY Department, BAHRAIN, EXPRESS LETTER [Ns B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Resident, Persian Gulf. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No, 1107 - S. Dated the 2nd December, 19&amp;&amp;. s 'f Reference your express letter No. C/1320, dated the 25th November, 1946. Cotton mill in Bahrain. ■ 1 2. Please inform Mr. Agar as you propose in your paragraph 5 and advise the Bahrain Government in favour of a company as also proposed by you. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED // for Secretary to the rolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. G.A. C :lentiaL B \ r t_) i i&lt;&lt;j -'■EIPT. S. 6. MEP —1407 S&amp;P—(M-2339)—25-5-37—300,000.No.C/1359 The 7th of December, 1946 Dear Mr. Agar, / I have now received instructions and am at liberty to inform you that there is no objection to your discussing your project with the Bahrain Govern ment and His Highness the Shaikh* the 21st November, 1946, these you will doubtless dis cuss in detail with the Bahrain Government, but I should be glad of information on the following points:- (a) From where do you propose to acquire the plant? connected industry should be a personal venture. This may be suitable, but I should welcome your views on your forming a company in Bahrain. 2. As regards the proposals which you sent me on (b) From where would you bring M experts'* - by which you mean technicians I understand - mechanics and labour? I gather that you propose that the mill and its Yours sincerely, Hussain Agar, Esq., ^ C/o The Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrain . NS.m ^ D.O. No.C/1360. The 7th of December, 1946. Dear Belgrave, ?. i v •w Thank-you for your Memorandum No.54-15 dated the ^ eceinber » 1946. I have discussed Mr. Agar's project wiua tiie Resident and he authorises me to say that he is in favour of His Highness and your discussing the proposal in detail with Mr. Agar. We are inclined to think that the floating of a company would be more suitable than Mr. Agar's mailing a purely personal venture. 2. Some brief comments on the project as submitted by Mr. Agar are enumerated below, will you please bear them in mind during your discussions with Mr. Agar? We should like the plant to be new and of British manufacture, but you may not be able to insist on this. I mention it for one purpose to avoid the possibility of the uprooting of the Bushire mill and its transference to l ? ot Prepared to say that this is undesirable, lnCe ? deK * ver / careful previous consideration on our part is required. As regards foreign labour we have a useful oil con- nee^arise^^^^ cou ^ d used as a precedent if the • company is formed or a concession given you will iind a useful guide for the various points in the BAPCO con- cess ion. 3. With regard to the various letter my brief comments ares points you raise in your (a) We are in favour of the formation of a company, but I gather that His Highness is opposed to that. cf. your paragraph 4. Until Mr. Agar's views are known further discussion on the point is not profitable. (b) &amp; (c). This is between the Bahrain Govern ment and Mr. Agar. (d) I think that a sufficient quantity of the produce should be placed on the local market. The mill should not have a shop open to the public. 9 (e) Audit would have to be arranged. (f) I am in agreement in general principle, but 4 dou bl^ u l 1** Mr. Agar can start a mill without Persians unless he imports Indian labour. I should be glad to hear how your discussions proceed on this point. /(g) This .D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain .(g) This is a matter for discussion but see (d) above. (h) l should require a detailed project if I were you. (i) No comment. (j) The employment of labour can be guided by the Indian Factory Act. I should like to know the approximate amount of labour to be employed and the sources of foreign labour. 4. With regard to your paragraph 4, final sentence. His Highness should be advised on no account to agree at this stage to accept 10$ of the profits in exchange for the concession he is prepared to give. The approximate relative values should first be worked out carefully. It should not slip your notice that a number of years may pass after the first bale is turned out before any profits are made at all. 5. Mr. Agar, as you know, is a man advanced in middle life, and I think you should discuss with him his proposal for management of the industry both at the beginning and at some future date unless, of course, the project is to be a personal venture and the Bahrain Government has secured its own interests as regards royalties, cf. para. 4 above. Yours sincerely,n u ti' 0 ^ ( 3 j XEt,. AUDRESS AGAR SHIRAZ Bahrain, Hussein Agar (Hie in ad) SMXirt 7th Jecember,1946 N° Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.S., etc, e The Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 ' Sir, Ref. No:C/1359 Re-Proj ecte d. M ill in Bahra in. , ( I beg to acknowledge receipt of youtf^ietter of even date for-which I thank you and in reply:- 1. I shall be glad to discuss the matter with the Bahrain Government and his Highness the Sheikh at their con venience . 2. (a) The complete plant will be acquired from United Kingdom for which purpose I hope to visit England as soon as my negotiations are completed here. (b) I intend employing British technicians only and Indian surpervisors, and utilise local labour(chiefly young persons). As Mill manager I would like to bring Mr. K. Vei Hard (Belgian Born) who wasfTFl^hy years -for Manager of Mazendran Mills during the A reign of late Reza Shah and is well known to H.B.M. Consul in Shiraz. 3. I shall be very glad to form a Company in Bahrain sub ject to my holding at least half of the total capital of at least 30 lacs of rupees. I have the honour to remain, Sir, Yours faithfully, H. Agar. N®. ConfideatiaL ^AHRAIN RECEIPT. ~^onf; dential . No.C/ 1372 • POLITICAL’AGENCY, BAHRAIN. Th® 10 th December, ©■ /r The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, —* _ % Bahrain, r\ . and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE. &gt; v W political Agent's Demi-Official letter No.C/1360 dated 7.12.'46 Description of Enclosure: NAME &amp; DATE Letter dated 7th December, 1946, from Mr. Hussein Agar, Bahrain, to the political Agent, Bahrain. SUBJECT Cotton Mill for Bahrain. / J!S?\CO NFIDENTIAL . POLITICAL AGENCY, BAT-IAIN. 0 • C/ 1373 • The loth December, • y' The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compli 1 ' onts to: The Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioi ed docu- r.ent(s). REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE. Residency Express Letter No.1107-8 dated the 2nd Dec., 1946. Description of Enclosure: NAME &amp; DATE Letter dated the 7th December, 1946, from Mr.Hussein Agar, Bahrain, to the political Agent Bahrain. SUBJE CT Cotton Mill for Bahrain.BAHRAUf, xxxx 11 th 1 1946 C. Dalrymsle Balgrave Ksq., C.B.S., etc., etc. The Adviser, The Government of Bahrain. Bahrain. Gear Sir, Re eroeosea Mill in Bahrain. I thank you for arranging the honour of the interview I had with His Highness - and now beg to place my views before you for consideration. It is improbable that Bahrainis would at first subscribe any substantial sums to a Company and I must find all the req uired initial capital, therefore to help the success of the pro ject, I trust that His Highness will agree in the main to ay proposals:- 1* To grant a concession to erect and work a factory comp rising Spinning, leaving, Dyeing, Bleaching and printing cotton fabrices in Bahrain. 2. To grant lease of a suitable plot of land in Manama(as near the town as possible) for building the factory and necess ary bungalows, on a lease of say 21 years at an agreed annual rental with option of purchase at a specified price any time during the terra of the lease, and permission to drill an arte- r-\ si an well for water. 3. All machinery and spare parts, building materials needed for the factory and all raw material such as cotton, dyes, che micals required for manufacturing to be free of import duty. 4. All surplus manufactured cloths and yarn not required for local Bahrain consumption to be allowed export free of duty. I on my part undertake. 5. To pay rent for the land granted on lease yearly in adva nce , commencing now. 6. To pay as soon as the factory starts on full production, annually the sura of one lac of rupees as royalty.ga&amp;gJSi ?• To #ay frois the annual net profits of the factory five eer cent at&gt; furUier royalty. To fay on local sales of the factory (for local con sumption.) five per cant of all such sale values, (to compensate for any probable loss of revenue from the customs). I further beg to confirm the terms of my letter dated 7th December, 1946. addressed to Colonel Galloway. Trusting that the foregoing conditions will be accept able to His Highness as otherwise I fear the public will not be encouraged to join a Company and I do not consider such an undertaking will be feasible on any more stringent terms. I shall be very glad to know the decision as soon as convenient - I have already been in Bahrain(over three weeks) longer than I had anticipated. Thanking you Sir for all your past favours. Yours faithfully, (H. Agar)i) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN- n() WF I DENTIAL . 1 The f - * 3 T he political Agent, Bahrain, presents his complirr.ents to. Th# Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, { ( , a cooy of the undermentioned docu- cn d i'as the honour to send him a. copy ment(s). -e—•*-*&gt;— — REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS ’cOHKhTrfPONDENCE, Agoncy Printed Letter No. C/1373 dated tft. 10th Dece mber^ — ‘ Description of Enclosuie: NAIAE&amp;DATE Letter dated 11th December, 1946 from Mr, H.Agar to the Adviser to the Bahrain Govt, L. SUBJE CT Cotton mill for Bahrain, — ■— - &lt;• / &amp; .No. ) Advisorata, December 17, 1946. 1 ^N\V V ^ With reference to your D.O.No. C/1360 dated 7th December 1946, on the subject of Mr. Agar’s cotton mill project, the matter has progressed as follows; on Saturday, 14th December, His Highness received Mr. Agar and discussed the question in a general way intimating that he would be pleased to encourage the introduction of a new local industry into his country. Following this interview His Highness again discussed the matter with me. We decided that the soundest policy would be to accept the offer of an annual payment of one lakh, royalty, but instead of receiving, in addition to the royalty, 5% of profits/to demand a payment on every yard of cloth produced in the mill whether the cloth was for export or for local consumption. After examining the figures which are available it was decided to demand a payment of J anna per yard. 2. On the following day I saw Mr. Agar again and ascertained from him that he would be willing to agree to this proposition, that in return for exemption from customs duty on the machinery and building material required for the mill, and upon imports of raw cotton, the company would pay to the State, from the time that production commenced, an annual royalty of Rs.100,000 and also half an anna on every yard of cloth produced in the mill. 3. The value of the machinery is in the neighbourhood of £175,000, customs duty upon this would amount to about Rs.2,36,000. Mr. Agar informed me that the mill when in production would consume 600 tons of raw cotton Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. 3* .; Date .u3 /— 2 per annum, customs duty on this would amount to approximately Rs.50,000 per annum. If the cheaper grade of cotton goods generally worn in Bahrain were produced locally the State would lose the duty on a corresponding quantity of imported cotton goods, it is difficult to estimate how much this duty would amount to but in view of the probable decrease in the price of cotton goods over the next two years it may be assumed this loss of duty would not amount to more than Rs. 100,000 per annum. Against this there is the advantage to the people of Bahrain of being able to buy locally made cotton goods at a lower price than they would pay for imported goods. The concession which Mr. Agar would be granted would cost the State approximately as follows On machinery and building materials Rs.2,36,000. On imported cotton, annually 50,000. Loss in customs on imported piece goods annually 1,00,000. In return the State would receive Rs. 1,00,000. annual royalty. £ anna per yard on, say, 500,000 yards of cloth) Rs. 1,56,000. Apart from financial considerations the setting up a cotton mill would provide employmant for a type of labour which is not now employed, particularly women. Regarding the other points in your letter, (a) The machinery and plant is to be new and of British manufacture. (b) Mr. Agar would undertake not to employ Persians, other than local born Persians.(c) The company is to have a capital of Rs.30,00,000 of which Mr, Agar would contribute Rs.15,00,000, the remainder to be raised in Bahrain and in Sngland. (d) The Bahrain Government is prepared to assist Mr. Agar to acquire land by lease. (e) Mr. Agar agrees to provide sufficient cloth for local needs for sale in Bahrain. (f) He agrees to suitable arrangements for audit. (g) Mr. Agar proposes to employ British subjects and Indians as overseers etc., he mentioned one individual who is * and who has worked for him before. (h) Mr. Agar will abide by any laws or regulations regarding labour which may be enforced in Bair ain. (i) The company would have a board of 6, three of the members to be local persons with Mr. Agar as president and two other members appointed by himself. The industry would be managed by the board. 4. There are many details to be discussed but before proceeding further I should be obliged if you would inform me whether you approve of the suggested financial arrangements. Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, O.B.E., H. B. M f s political Agent, Bahrain.Bahrain, xxxx 21st December, 1946 . C/o The Imperial Bank ef Iran, Bahrain. C. Dalrymfie Belgrave Ssq., C.B.E., etc. The Adviser, The Gevernment ®f Bahrain. Bahrain. Dear Sir, Further te my cemmunicatien ef the 11th instant, and eur interview ef Tuesday last, when you stated that instead ef 6% ef net profits(eara 7 ef my letter 11th De cember, 1944) and 5$ en all lecal sales(para 8 ef my letter 11th December, 1944), the Gevernment ef Bahrain would prefer 4 pies per yard ef cleth manufacturedr I did net at the time quite realise that this was in addition te receiving ene lac ef rupees(under para 4 ef my setter 11th December, 194b). I therefore beg te point out that it would kill the project at the start te have te pay all this, which will amount te about ene anna per yard of cleth when the price ef cheap cleth in normal times would be about 3/4 annas a yard! The advantages of a factory in Bahrain are tee numer ous for me te detail here and I beg te point out that if there is ne factory no less ef revenue whatsever is incurred. I need all the help and support possible for such an under taking- therefore I beg te request that you should either accept my offer ef the 11th instant, or only 4 pies eer yard ©n production and nothing further. Please forgive me for the trouble caused you. I remain Sir, Yours sincerely, H. Agar.A » E X P K E a S L K I I K R . prom - political Agent, Bahrain, To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/1411. Dated the 22nd of December, 1946. Reference correspondence ending with my printed Letter No.c/1398 dated the 16th December, 1946. I send a copy of a letter I have received from Mr. Belgrave on the subject of the proposed cotton mill for Bahrain. 2.. You will see that we have carefully eliminated, or endeavoured to eliminate, any suggestion that the mill is in any way connected with Persia, or things Persian. Mr. Agar’s personal capital, he states, will be made up of his own money and that of members of his family, some in England and some in China. I am not commenting further since I have now received a letter from Mr. Agar in which he says he wishes to reconsider the financial aspects of the proposition. It appears that he has made a miscalcula tion. 3* In the meantime I shall be grateful if you will confirm that there is no objection to Mr. Agar’s main proposition. 4. Regarding the further financial settlements I shall address you when Mr. Agar and Mr. Belgrave have thrashed out the new points raised. Attested . Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY Political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain. NS.The Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, Bahrain and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Advisers Office, Manamah, Bahrain. No fT Dated December 22, 1946. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. 1. Copy of letter dated 21st December 1946, from Mr. Hussein Agar, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Gov't. Bahrain. Cotton Mill Scheme. * 2. Copy of letter No.197 dated 22nd December 1946, from the Adviser, to Mr. Hussein Agar, Bahrain. - ditto - L-S &gt; Reference to previous correspondence:— Adviser's D.O .No.169 dated 17t!i December 1946, addressed to Lt. Colonel A.C.Galloway, O.B.E., Bahrain. Confidential Dite- Ho-4 Copy of letter dated 21st December 1946, from Mr. Hussein Agar, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Further to my communication of the 11th instant, and our interview of Tuesday last, when yOu stated that instead of 5$ of net profits (para 7 of my letter 11th December, 1946) and 5$ on all local sales (para 8 of my letter 11th December 1946) the Government of Bahrain would prefer 6 pies for yard of cloth manufactured. I did not at the time quire realise that this was in addition to receiving one lac of rupees (under para 6 of my letter 11th December 1946). I therefore beg to point out that it would kill the project at the start to have to pay all this, which will amount to about one anna per yard of cloth when the price of cheap cloth in normal times would be about 3/4 annas a yard: The advantages of a factory in Bahia in are too numerous for me to detail here and I beg to point out that if there is no factory no loss of revenue whatsoever is incurred. 1 need all the help and support possible for such an undertaking - therefore I beg to request that you should either accept my offer of the 11th instant, or only 6 pies per yard on production and nothing further.No. of 1566 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, Dated, Muharram 28, 1366 December 22, 1946. Mr. Hussein Agar, Bahrain. Dear Sir, X have received your letter dated 21st December 1946, regarding the suggested royalty and payments to tne Government on the proposed cotton mill scheme. After* our interview on Tuesday I informed Hie Highness that you were prepared to agree to these proposals and I also wrote at length to the political Agent informing him what had taKen place. I cannot reply to you about any counter proposal without*first ascertaining His Highness* views on the matter and I shall not bo seeing him until Tuesday on which day I will discuss the matter with him again. Yours faithfully, Adviser rim ant.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 2nd Safar, 1366 December 26, 1946. December 1946, regarding the proposed cotton mill, on Tuesday December 24, His Highness again discussed the matter with me. He decided that he would accept one lakh of rupees yearly and \ anna on every yard of cloth produced in the factory in lieu of granting exemption of import duty on raw cotton, machinery and building materials imported for the purpose of the factory, instead of demanding ^ anna per yard. Mr. Agar was informed that he should consider this proposition and let me know whether such an arrangement was acceptable to him. On 26th December I received a letter from Mr. Agar of which I enclose a copy. Financially this arrangement will satisfy the Bahrain Government but the draft agreement submitted by Mr. Agar will need further consideration and I would suggest that it should be worded on the lines of the revised draft which I enclose. Regarding the political aspect of the under taking, His Highness fully realises the necessity for ensuring that no Persian capital shall be invested in the propsed company. If shares are offered for sale in Bahrain it will be possible to ensure that they are not bought by Persian subjects. This can be made a condition of the sale. Regarding the capital which is to be provided by Mr. Agar himself, the Bahrain Government has no means of satis fying itself, through Bankers 1 references or enquiry through political sources as to whether Mr. Agar and his non-persian friends are in possession on the necessary funds. His Highness wishes me to enquire whether you could have enquiries made about this point. I should be grateful if you would inform me whether you approve of the Bahrain Government concluding an agreement with Mr. Agar on the lines of the draft which I enclose. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- In continuation of my D.O.No. 169 dated 17th Adviser to the Government. S.Z; ConfidentialHu&amp;eein Agar (fitomad) c/o The Imperial Bank of Iran, Bahrein, 24th December, 1946 : C. Delrymple Belgrave, Ssqr., C.B.E. The Adviser, The Government of Bahrein. Bahrein. Heproppeed mill. Dear Sir, Further to our interview of this morning, I beg to hand you copy of draft agreement based on conversations between us and trust it meets with approval. I shall be greatly obliged if this matter could now be finally settled so that I could proceed to England to complete the purchases of machinery, etc., Thanking you Sir, Yours faithfully,Cotton Mill 1m Bahrain , Draft agraament betwaen the Government of Bahrain (hereafter referred to as the Government and Mr. Huasain Agar of Manchester &amp; Buehire 9c or his nominees hereafter referred to ae Agar). Hiereas it is agreed betvvoen the shove named parties as follows:- The Government grants to Agar permission and concession to erect and xvork a cotton manufacturing mill in Bahrein comprising of:* Spinning 9 weaving, dyeing, bleaching and printing. All the necessary machinery to be purchased in England and to be of British make. All imports of machinery, spare parts, building materials needed for the mill (and houses for the staff) and all raw material such as Cotton dyes, chemicals required for manufacturing to be free of import duty and other taxes. All cloths and yarn manufactured over and shove local Bahrein requirements (for local consumption) will be allowed export free of duty. The Government will grant a suitable plot of land (not less than 200 yards X 150 yards) on a lease of 21 years at an agreed annual rental (first payment on signing this agreement). The price of this plot of land which has been selected (on Belgrave Road behind the cinema backing on the cemetry up to the little mosque) is to be decided upon and fixed now and option to purchase outright is given to Agsr (at the agreed price) during the term of the lease and if such option is exercised then all rentals paid are to be deducted from the agreed purchase price(total amount). Permission is also granted to dig wells and to drill an artesian well for water for the mill. Hussein Agar undertakes on his part To pay the Government as soon as the mill starts on full production annually one lac of rupees as royalty. To pay to the Government three (3) pies on every yard of doth manufactured and eight (8) a?inas on every bundle of yarn sold (10 lbs. bundles). These payments and royalties are in lieu of all present and future taxes. A limited liability-company will be fonned and registered (in England). Agar and his British Friends and relatives (all British Subjects) will subscribe half of the total Capital and the balance of 50% will be offered in Bahrein to the public. No part of the Capital whatever will be offered to Persian Nationals or anyone who is a Persian Subject residing in Persia. Only British and Indian technicians (with the exception of Monsieur Veillard) will be employed and no native Persian labour from Persia will be imported by the mill without special written permission from the Government. Bahrein, 24th December, 1946 29th Muharram, 1366.Draft Agreement between the Bahrain Government, hereafter referred to as 'The Government' and Mr. -a Hussein Agar of Manchester and Bushire and or his nominees hereafter referred to as M Mr. Agar'. Whereas it is agreed between the Government and Mr. Agar as follows 1. The Government grants to Mr. Agar permission to erect and to work a cotton mill in Bahrain for the purpose of spinning, weaving, dyeing, bleaching and printing cotton. 2. All the machinery necessary for this undertaking shall be purchased in Great Britain and shall be of British make. 3. All machinery and spare parts for the cotton mill and building materials for the mill and for the necessary buildings which the persons who work the mill will occupy always provided that these buildings are contained within the land which is to be acquired for the purpose of the mill, will be granted exemption from customs import duty. Raw material necessary for the work of the mill such as raw cotton, dyes and chemicals for use in the process of producing cotton goods will be granted exemption from customs import duty. 4. Cloths and yarns manufactured in the mill which are in excess of the local requirements will be allowed to be exported free of export duty. 5. The Government will let to Mr. Agar a plot of land, suitable for the mill, not less than 200 x 150 yards in area, on a 21 years'4ise at an agreed annual rental which shall be paid each year, in advance, the first payment to be made by Mr. Agar at the time of the signing3 / - 2 - of this Agreement, The cost price of the land shall be decided upon at the time when the lease is made and Mr. Agar shall have the option of purchasing the land at any time during the term of the lease. If and when this option is exercised the amount of rent which has been paid by Mr. Agar shall be deducted from the agreed purchase price of the land. Permission will be granted to Mr. Agar to sink an artesian well in the land thus acquired and to sink surface wellas if necessary. 6. Mr. Agar will pay to the Government, annually, one lakh of rupees as royalty. This payment shall commence when the mill begins to produce manufactured cloth goods. 7. Mr. Agar will pay to the Government three pies (quarter anna) on every yard of manufactured cloth goods which is produced in the factory. 8. Mr. Agar will pay to the Government eight annas on every bundle of yarn (one bundle * 10 lbs.) which is sold. These payments and royalties are in lieu of present and future import and export duties. 9. A limited liability company will be formed by Mr. Agar in England, where it will be registered. One half of the approved total capital will be subscribed by Mr. Agar and his friends and relatives, all of whom are British subjects, and the other half of the capital will be offered to the public in Bahrain in the form of shares in the undertaking. No part of the capital will be offered or held by Persian nationals either residing in Bahrain, in Persia or elsewhere.10. Only Bahrain, British and Indian subjects shall be employed as technicians in the undertaking (with the exception of Monsieur Veillard) and no workmen will be brought from Persia to work in the mill without the express written approval of the Government. 11. The accounts of the undertaking will be audited annually by a recognised firm of chattered accountants for whose services the Government will pay a proportion of the costs which shall be arranged later. 12. All persons concerned with and employed in the mill shall be subject to the laws of the land and shall comply with all Government and Municipal rules and regulations.tmm- Of I-L I &amp; l h GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, Department, BAHRAIN. EXPRESS LETTER rj ,—This is an ORIGINAL M ESS A GE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, ivith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sane time and formalities it is worded* and signed, as if it had been so despatched,] POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF. To CONFIDENTIAL POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. 1218 - S. Dated 28th December, 1^6. Reference your express letter No. C/1411, dated the 22nd December, 1946. 2. It is confirmed that there is no objection to Mr. Agar's main proposition. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. G • A. M. s. e. MFi’—785S&amp;P—{M-1014)—18-8 33—2 00 '300 Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Daie.-.J/'/fOEXPRESS LETTER From - political Agent, Bahrain. To - political Resident, Bahrain. No.c/31. Dated the 7th of January, 1947. Reference your Express Letter No.l218-S dated the 28th December, 1946. I enclose copies of a letter I have received from the Bahrain Government, together with enclosures, on the subject of the Bahrain cotton mill project. 2. With regard to paragraph two of my Express Letter No.c/1411 dated the 22nd of December, 1946, the financial proposition now is that ^ an anna instead of £ an anna should be paid on every yard of cotton material manu factured and 8 annas on every bundle of yarn. Annual royalty is to be one lac of rupees yearly to commence when the mill is in production. 3. The following are my comments on the Bahrain Govern ments draft agreement paragraph by paragraph. Preamble. I am asking the Bahrain Government to obtain from Mr. Agar an enumeration of his nominees. This is essential since the contract is being made partly in their name. For 'Mr. Agar' should be substituted 'company'. 1. No material comment though the phraseology requires considerable adjustment and also in other paragraphs such as the substitution of 'shall' for 'will'. 2. No comment. 3. A detailed balance sheet of the value of this concession vis a vis the Company and the Bahrain Government should be quickly and care fully worked out by the Bahrain Government. 4. No comment. (There is no export duty in Bahrain). 5. No comment. 6. 'Or yarn' should be inserted, since that may be manufactured before the cloth, it is for the Bahrain Government to balance the loss of customs income due to failing off of imports against income from manufactured cloth, (see 3 above). *** 7. No comment. 8. No comment on the first sentence. The next sentence must be connected accurately with the relevant clauses of the agreement. 9. I do not like the idea of a limited liability /company^....company's being formed in England of which half the shares are to be sold in Bahrain. This may give rise to unforeseen complica tions in connection with foreign exchange, taxes, etc/ The Company should be formed, I think, in Bahrain. Half the financial control of the Company is vested in Mr. Agar, his friends and rela tives. The Bahrain Government should find out who and what these people are since they will be the main controlling interest. 10. In conformity with the policy of not allowing Persians into Bahrain the words from 'without... Government' should be omitted. This will avoid a possible infiltration of Persians at an alleged critical period. 11. No comment. 12. No comment. 4. I note that the Bahrain Government have not made any safeguards against exploitation of labour, this I think they should do. 5. Further I think that we should obtain confirmation from the Bahrain Government that a protective tariff will not be raised against the importation of cotton goods, yarn, raw materials, etc., etc. 6. The proposed plot of land is near the center of Manamah behind the cinema. The site is ill chosen as its development would result in the growth of an industrial area near the residential quarters. This would bring in its train industrial r^uisances against which Bahrain has no protective legislation. The agreement should, therefore, include a clause forbidding the blowing of sirens, whistles, hooters, and the making of such like noises. Protection against smells is also necessary and a drainage system should be provided for. It would be better for the mill to be situated somewhere - say - in the Budaiyah area when the above measures need not be insisted on. 7. I am writing to the Bahrain Government asking them to clear up the points raised above. I consider that the next step should be for Mr. Agar to submit to the Bahrain Government his prospectus giving full details of his proposed company showing capital value of shares, proportion of dividends, proposed equipment and output, etc., etc. 8. I should be grateful for instructions whether the company should be formed in England or Bahrain. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY ATTESTED . political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.D.0. No.C/32 The 7th of January, 1947 My dear Belgrave, Will you please refer to your Memorandum No.228-48 dated the 26th of December, 1946? 2. The following are some comments on your draft agreement paragraph by paragraph which occur to me. preamble. I suggest that the Bahrain Government obtain from Mr. Agar an enumeration of his nominees. This I think is essential since the contract is being made partly in their name. For ’’Mr. Agar' might be substituted 'company'. 1. I have no material comment though the phraseology might be adjusted. 2. No comment. 3. A detailed balance sheet of the value of this concession vis a vis the company and the Bahrain Government might quickly and carefully be worked out by the Bahrain Government. 4. No comment. 5. No comment. 6. 'Or yarn' might be inserted, since that may be manufactured before the cloth. It is for you to balance the loss of customs income due to falling off of imports against income from manu factured cloth. (see 3 above). 7. No comment. 8. No comment on the first sentence. The next sentence should be connected accurately with the relevant clauses of the agreement. 9. I do not like the idea of a limited liability company’s being formed in England of which half the shares are to be sold in Bahrain. This may give rise to unforeseen complications in connection with foreign exchange, taxes, etc. The company should be formed, I think, in Bahrain, but I have referred the matter to the political Resident. Half the financial control of the company will be /vested........ C.D. Belgrave, ksq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain.vested in Mr. Agar, his friends and relatives so the Bahrain Government should find out who and what these people are. They will be the main controlling interest. 10. In conformity with the policy of not allowing Persians into Bahrain the words from ’’without... ....... Government” might be omitted. This will avoid a possible infiltration of Persians at an alleged critical period. 11. No comment. 12. No comment. 3. I note that the Bahrain Government have not made any safeguards against exploitation of labour. 4. Will you please insert in the agreement that no protective tariff will be raised against the importation of cotton goods, yarn, raw materials, etc., etc.*&gt; 5. The proposed plot of land is near the center of Manamah behind the cinema. The site is ill chosen as its development would result in the growth of an industrial area near the residential quarters. This would bring in its train industrial nuisances against which Bahrain has no protective legislation. The agreement might, therefore, include a clause forbidding the blowing of sirens, whistles, hooters, and the making of such like noises, protection against smells is also necessary and a drainage system should be provided for. it would be better for the mill to be situated somewhere - say - in the Budaiyah area when the above measures need not be insisted on. 6. I consider that the next step should be for. Mr. Agar to submit to you his prospectus giving fuller details of his proposed company showing capital value of shares, proportion of dividends, proposed equipment and output, etc., etc. Yours sincerely,D • 0 • No«C/53« The IXth of January, 1947. My dear Belgrave, Will you please refer to the correspondence ending with my demi*official letter No.c/32 dated the 7th of January, 1947? 2« I now see that Mr. Agar has decided to withdraw his proposal. The grounds he gives are scarcely cogent since he must have made enquiries about obtaining machinery before he came here, if there ever was any substance in his project, of course, the Bahrain Government should not allow themselves to be rushed into a project by a company promoter of whom they have no first-hand knowledge. 3. I understood Mr. Agar to say that he had severed all connection with his mills in Persia, can you confirm that? if, indeed, he has not done so the Bahrain Govern ment are, I think, well out of it for they do not want to be ax±x linked in any way with mills in Persia. Yours sincerely, C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, ■ u r a i MS.0 wOWFVDEWTIAL. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAi ’iAIN. rJo.C/ 59 . The j.2th January, 194 ^ The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his complir.onts to: The Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and las the honour to send him a copy of the undermentior e'‘d''(3^cu- rnent (s). REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE. Correspondence ending with my toe® F.xpress Letter No.c/31 dated 7.1. »47 Description of Enclosure: NAfiE &amp; DATE political Agent*s Demi-Official ^ letter No.c/58 dated the 11th of January, 1947, to the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. v S. ^ SUBJEC proposed Cotton Mill project. / .- •'l &lt;?Ho. or 1066 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, l^th Bafar, 1366 January 12, 1947, Hussein Agar, Baquire Bahrain. Dear Sir With reference to the correspondence regaruing the proposal to set up a cotton mill in Bahrain ending with my letter No. 235 - 48 dated 26th December 1946. 2 . I should be obliged if you would provide me with full particulars of the nominees who you propose to make party to this Agreement, as you and these people will have a controlling interest in the Company it is necessary for the Bahrain Government to aquire full information about them. 3. Regarding the proposed site for the mill, the lot on the Jufair road is not thought suitable. This aroa is being developed as a site for residential buildings and the presence of a mill would be deter- mintal to them. The Government would I think consider leasing a plot of the same size east of the Fort on the land between the eastern gate of the Fort garden and the cemetery. 4. It will be necessary for the Government to insert in tho Agreement certain clausos to prevent any exploitation of labour and also to prevent any nuisance that might be caused by tiie blowing of hooters, sirens etc., and protection against smells. 5. It also appears desirable that the Company should bo formed in Bahrain, not in Itagland. Please let me hnow your reactions to this suggestion. 6 . I ahouxd be obliged if you would now submit to ne a prospectus giving full details of the proposed Company showing capital value of shares, propoAitlon of dividends, proposed equipment and output etc. Yours faithfully Adviser to the Government S.Z. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Tfe...jS&amp;.: Date.?.'?/.-. 5 ^ CONFI DENTIAL . JO.C / ~ 7 ) POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN The 194y. 81 * * J 15th January, The political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, ?.:;:d 1 is the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE. Agency printed Letter No. c/59 dated the 11th January, 1947. Description of Enclosure: NAME &amp; DATE SUBJECT Letter No,329-48 dated 12th Jan., 1947, from the Adviser to the ^ Govt, of Bahrain to Mr. Hussein Agar (Etemad). ' ^ proposed cotton Mill project.— D•0• No &gt; &amp; Adviserate, January 14, 1947. / V/ith reference to your D.O. No. C/58 dated 11th January 1947, Mr. Agar has definitely withdrawn his proposal and is leaving on the next boat. I cannot confirm that he has severed all connection with his mills in Persia, but he did mention to me that he had, or was going to sever all connection with them. © Lieut. Colonel A.C. Galloway, C.I.3., O.B.E., H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. ' 33 . /s/ P• R * ? 9 S’. irh.CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 20th January, 1947. I am desired to refer to the S enclosure to your printed letter No. C/81, dated the 15th January, 1947, and to inquire Belgrave’s reason for issuing it, since, as appears from a copy of a letter which he sent us, Agar informed Belgrave on the 9th January, 1947, that he had decided to with draw his proposals for erecting a cotton mill in Bahrain. Lieutenant Colonel A. C. Galloway, C.I.E., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. G.A.N! Confidential. x »^l i BAHRAIN RECEIPTNo. D.O. C/116 Tha 25th January, 1347. Dear Belgrave, Wlll you pleas# refer to your^ letter No. 329-48 dated the 12th January, 1947 to Mr. Agar. 2 . I am desired to inquire the reason for your issuing this letter since it appears that Mr. Agar had already informed you on the 9th January, 1947, that he had decided to withdraw his proposals for erecting a Cotton Mill in Bahrain. Yours sincerely,D .0 .No. Adviserate, January 28, 1947 5 - 3 ^ Reference your D.O. No.C/il6 dated 25th January 1947, I sent the letter to Mr. Agar because I believed that his letter saying that he had decided to withdraw his proposals was written because of our delay in continuing the negociations. I doubted that he really intended to cease negociating as I was aware that he had begun purchasing building material in Bahrain. His letter was not, however, bluff. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, Assistant Political Agent Bahrain. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECF Tprr Datepolitical Agency, Bahrain The 2nd February, 1947. D.O. flo.C/142 My dear pelly, Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No.128-3 dated the 20th January, 1947? Mr. Agar because he thought that he was bluffing. It appears that he was not. his reason for withdrawing was that the project looked as though it would not turn out to be the paying proposition he had expected. This, he said, was due to the fact that he was expected to pay royalty from capital at the outset. This statement is not in conformity with the proposed contract. It cun be noted that twice Hr. Agar agreed to the financial terras and twice changed his mind. / 4. I consider that we are well out of the deal, and I have told the Adviser that if the Bahrain Government want a cotton milling industry they are at liberty to take steps in that direction. 2 The Adviser informs me that he wrote to 3. IIP. Agar told me before his departure that Yours sincerely. C. J. Pelly, Y3 , T&gt;3vj. , G.B.H*, X.C.S.f Secretary to the Hon’ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/376</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/376</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/32 Cotton Mill for Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-04T00:12:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (60 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 59-61. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 62; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-58; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence sent and received by the Political Agent at Bahrain about the proposal for the establishment of a cotton mill in Bahrain by a naturalized British subject, Mr Hussein Agar Etemad.The file contains correspondence with the Advisor to the Government of Bahrain and the Imperial Bank of Iran regarding Mr Agar's references, the lease and the conditions for the opening of the mill. There is a draft agreement, which states that neither capital nor employees can be Persian (folios 39-42).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Bank of Iran</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Cotton textile industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>