<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00018e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T06:30:27.689Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IR.'/.RD T BLBG-RiU' TO COMROFi'TSALTH RXLy.TIOMS OFtTCE I 6 ALLOTTED TO EXTEBH/.L DEERRTMBNT (B). CYPHER (O.T.P.) FROM: POLITICAL AGENT’ KUVfAIT y *~~ D: TO: POLITICO, RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF D. Kuwait, 14.30 hours, 16'th Pehruary, 1948. R. 17.45 hours, 18th February, 1948. IMPORTANT No.155. Addressed Commonwealth Relations Office London repeated Political Resident in Persian Gulf. Your telegram No«48 February 17th (not repeated to Political Resident Persian Gulf)-. Accession of Sheikh Ahmed. 2. Date locally accepted is February 23rd. 3. Salim died February 22nd not February 21st. dates are correct. Other No distributionINT7ARD T rr I^L, t T jf)NS OFMOE ALLOTTED TO EXTERNAL DBPARTIfflNT (B). I of CYPHER (O.T.P.) PROM: POLITICAL AGENT KU'./AIT 19 TO: POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULP Hl R. »o II 1 * WC ORTANT No.153. Kuwait, 14.30 hours, 18th February, 1948. 17.45 hoars, 18th February, 1948. Addressed Commonwealth Relations Office London repeated Political Resident in Persian Gulf. Your telegram No.48 Fe bruary 17th (not repeated to Political Resident Persian Gulf). Accession of Sheikh Ahmed. 2. Date locally accepted is February 23rd. 3. Salim died February 22nd not February 21st. Other dates are correct. No distribution.No•353-3 of 1942* British Keeidenoy &amp; Goneuiate-Gonsral, i Bushire, the 14th Hay» 1942» ^ yj J ^ From • The Eon’ble Ueut#-Colonel W.R^Hay, C.I.S., Political hetident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Secretary to the Government of India, External affaire »e part me at, hew 1 elhi* Sir, ^ith reference to oorreepondence ending with my telegram &gt; ho#1/433, dated the 4th iflay 1942, 1 have the honour to forward herewith a copy of a note received from the Political ,agent, Kuwait, on the sudden illneae of Hia Highueae Shaikh Sir Ahmad al Jabir as-subah, K.O.I.S., 0 #S#I* 2, I have recently seen Major Hiokinbotham and diecueeed with him the situation arising out of the shaikh's illness# The shaikh at present appears outwardly perfectly fit, and is carrying on the business of the state and taking drives in his oar, though under the doctors 1 advice he is avoiding all kinds of strain as far as possible# The doctors report that his cardiac reserve is very alight and that any emotional excitement such as anger, fear, or the strain of concentrated and worrying thought would tend to increase the likelihood of a second and possibly fatal attack# In short, the Shaikh may die suddenly any day or live for years# 3# It will be somewhat difficult for the lolitioal Agent to carry out his functions properly especially in war tine if he is never to make any communication to the Shaikh which may cause the latter worry or annoyance# I have accordingly instructed Major Hicklnbotham that while he should as far as possible avoid discuss* ing controversial matters with the Shaikh, if at any time it becomes really neoessary to bring such a matter to his notice he must do so and run the risk of a second and fatal attack# 1 have satisfied myself alter discussion with Major Hiokinbotham / thatthat any auggestlon to the Shaikh -that he should appoint a Rsgent or associate his heir presumptive shaikh Abdullah bin Salim with himself in the government of the state is precisely the sort of thing that is likely to excite him with fatal results. The Political Agent does however propose to suggest to the shaikh that he should keep T&gt;r.i*ylrea with himself as a permanent medical officer and if the Shaikh agrees to this it may be possible to use r.i/iylrea to a certain extent as a go-between in matters of ^itate and. a cuf tr to lessen the impact of any shocks which the iolitical Agent may find it necessary to deliver. 4. Shaikh Abdullah bin Salim has long been regarded as the heir presumptive of Shaikh Ahmad and often refers to himself as '•the iriiice of Wales'*. In the unfortunate event of shaikh Ahmad’s death it ie considered probable that shaikh Abdullah would succeed him peacefully without any kind of dispute. 5 # I am ©ending a copy of this letter and its enclosure to is l£aj esty *s secretary of State for India, the uepresentative oi in ia on the Middle Kaet War Council. His Majesty’s ianbaevador. Baghdad. Hie Aftjecty’e Minister. Jedda, and. without enclosure, to the lolltical Agent, Kdwait. 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your moat obedient servant, sd • .&lt; • K • Hay • Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. * sent under rrintad Letter U0.364-S of the 14 th May 1942.(Received under Kuwait Printed Letter No.C/309 dated the 10th April 1942.) Note on sudden illneee of the Shaikh of Kuwait, 1942. I visited Hie Highness at 9.30 a.in. on the 4th April accompanied by Sir John Ward. The Shaikh looked well and was in a very affable mood. Sir Jlohn Ward left about 10 a.m. and I remained behind and discussed various business matters until about 10.30 a.m. when I took leave of His Highness who informed me that he would send letters to me to be taken by me to Ibn Saud. Various attempts were made by Ikizat JaXfar, His Highness’ Social Secretary, to speak to me on the telephone during the evening but unfortunately I was busy with preparations for my journey to Riyadh and was not in when he rang up and my one attempt to get in touch with him failed • At about 10 p.rn.Dr.Scudder of the American liissionrang me up and informed me that His Highness* condition was critical. He said that the Shaikh had had a slight heart attack at 11.30 a.m.but had thought nothing of it and had gone to ?antas to lunch with Abdullah Al-Nafici, the Saudi Government Agent. During lunch the Shaikh had had pain in the region of the heart and after returning to his house in the late afternoon had had a second and more serious attack. Izzat Jaffar at once got in touch v/ith him, Scudder, and he had examined him and diagnosed Coronary Thrombosis. Dr.Scudder considered that the Shaikh must be kept as ^uiet as possible and for that reason he desired to ke^p the gravity of his condition as secret as possible. I informed him that I would postpoaae my departure for Riyadh and asked him to see me after seeing the Shaikh in the early morning. I Immediately telegraphed to the Hon*ble the Political Resident and informed him oi the Shaikh's condition. At 8.15 a,m• on the 5th Dr.Scudder ana Izzat Jaffer called and the former stated that there was no improvement in Hi a Highness* condition although the fact that he was still alive was a favourable indication that he might survive the present attack. Xzzat Jaffer said that His Highness* two younger sons Jarir and bubah were with their father who was being looked after by his wwn servants. At my suggestion Izzat Jaffer returned to Dasman. Dr.Ucudder then discussed the case with Squadron header Freezer of the R.A.F jeedioal Service wMs was staying with me and later the Squadron Leader Informed me that hie opinion coincided with that of Dr.Scudder*s. I enquired if Dr .Scudder would like an outside opinion and he replied that while he had little doubt of the correctness of his diagnosis and that everything poasiblewas being done for the patient he would ?/elcome aiy skilled opinion and suggested Dr. Thornton of Basra. The question of ways and means of getting in touch with doctors was discussed with Mr.Scott, the General Superin tendent of the Kuwait Oil Company who arrived opportunely at that moment and at my request he despatched a telegram through one of the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company tugs lying at Shuwaikh to the General Manager of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co,pany at Abadan asking for a physician to be flown down as soon as possible for consultation with Dr.Scudder. Dr.Scudder was still very anxioue to keep the matter as quiet as possible in order to ensure rest to the Shaikh, but 1 told him that I felt that his Secretary and the two senior Government officials present should be inforried and asked him to remain and speak to them himself. I then asked Shaikh Abdullah Jabir the Chief Judge and Director of Education, Shaikh Abdullah Mubarak the Director of Public Security and Abdullah Mulla, His Highness* Secretary to call at the Agency. They arrived within a few minutes and Dr.Scudder carefully explained the position to them. Later I impressed on them the necessity for keeping His Highness as quiet as possible and limiting visitors to an absolute minimum. I understood tnat shaikh Abdullah Salim was away on Failaoha Island and told them they must / consider2 oonBider the propriety of LafoXifling him. They stated that they proposed to do so and also Hie Highnese* eHest eon Shaikh Abdullah al Abroad. Dr.Saudder said that he would have no objection to Shaikh Abdullah Jabir and Shaikh Abdullah Mubarak seeing His High ness but was opposed to any other person being permitted to do so. Shaikh Abdullah Mubarak said that he had seen His Highness earlier in the morning. X asked Oolonel Dickson to uall aud set roe and informed hiro of what had occurred and the steps X had thought fit to take. He stated that he was in entire agreement with the action that I had taken and warned me that Shaikh Abdullah Salim was of a hysterical nature and roi fe ht disturb His Highnesb. It tnen occurred to roe that it might be a pleasant gesture to offer the Ageiicy launch to take the message to Shaikh Abdullah Salim and 1 rang up his Highnesb 1 Secretory and roauQ the offer. I was wuch surprised to hear that Shaikh Abdullah Salim was actually present in Kuwait. I at once asked the Secretary to get intouch with him and ask him to call upon me as socn as possible. Shaikh Abdullah Salim arriveu about 10*30 a.m. and appeared very cheerful ana looked well. I explained exactly what had taken place and how it came about that I had not asked him to be present earlier in the morning when I saw the other Shaikhs• He appeared to be satisfied that he had not been intentionally umitued and informed me that as Boon as he was informed of His HighnetoB t condition he went to see him and was very surprised to find him cheerful. I informed Shaikh Abdullah Salim that a specialist was due at any moment from Abadan ana that I wouJL* like him to call again when he had seen the Shaikh and hear from the specialist in person his opinion of Hie xiighnese 1 condition. I also intimated that I had aeked Shaikh Abdullah Jabir and Shaikh Abdullah Mubarak and Abdullah Mulls to be present for the same purpose. Shaikh Abdullah Salim said that it was quite uiiaeoessary for then to come but that naturally he would be very pleased to hear what the specialist had to eay. I replied that I had already invited the gentlemen and did not now propose to withdraw my invitation. At 11.30 a.ro. Dr.Mac lean arrived from Abadan and after a brief talk with Dr.Scudder at the Agency went to Dasraan to see Hie High ness. I asked the Shaikhs previously referred to to be present at 12.15 p.ro. at the Agency to meet the two Medical men and hear their oxDinion. Dr.Maclean and Dr.Scudder returned from Oaaroan a few minutes after twelve noon and the former confirmed Dr.Soudder # s diagnosia and went on to stats that in his opinion Hia Hi.^hness had a reasonable chance of recovery provided another attack did not occur which it might do at any time, possibly during sleep. He further stated that it was impossible to make any definite statement one way or the other and tnat even if be did pull through he would not regain hia accustomed health and would always be liable to another and probably fatal attack. When the Shaikhs had assembled at 12.15 p.ro. Dr.Maclean clearly explained the position to them said emphasised that the moat important thing was rest and quiet, he informed them tnat he had agreed to remain in Kuwait for two or three days to collaborate with Dr.Seudder in the treatment of the case . Written at .20 p.n. on the 5th April. Apr il 6th. TTudoctors informed roe this morning that His Highness* heart / condition- 3 - MV) oonditii.on £ 4 pj.&gt; 6 &amp;xcd jdcxc Bt&amp;'Lifcj'-f 4 E»o Loxy tut tiiot un^ort.uns't? Xy general conoition had deteriorated ard an examination of Me urine had revealed kidney trouhle. In their opinion they oorsider- ad that he ehot-ld he Bended to Abadan ae soon ar poaeible where he could he more eatiafactori ly examined and a line of treatment decided Uyou« They coiiBidercd that if he rfmaincc. hero it v.culd not hvj pobwihl^ to treat hJLiu coxx^ctly and thai* the d&amp;n^c- of tne journey was leos than that Vfhich would he incurred cy hie staying here without adc-iiuatc troAtment* They a£ked my r advice and i stated that the matter routed with the Ijiaiiai hiiMeelf and Bug»,€8ied they aiiould give him their opinion in the evening when they p?id their next visit and that ti ey should inform the senior members oi af tne faiaily of their views whatever hit ni { ^hnce b decided niter their interview with, him and ask for a definite answer tomor. ow Morning* 1 aaued Jolonel Diokaon to join the conference and after hearing the Medical Officers he concurred in the line of action I auggestad*. I then instructed Abdullah Lulla to enaui'e that the member a of the family wore present at and agreed hiat iu would be setter for iihaixh Ahlullah -lali.j am himself to the doctors and not necessarily the whole family to whom meoical view couiJ. be convey r ed oy dhaikh Abdullah iiaxim* April 7th • doctors Scudder and kacleaxi oaliei upon me last evening at 7.13 p.m. and informed me that Hia Highness had agreed to go to Abadan. Some ten minutes later Shaikh Abdullah Jalim who was accompanied by Abdullah Mu I la joined ub and aaid that he would like to know whether it wes really necessary for Hie HighaeaB to Ituve. Tho urgenc.. of the situation was explained to him. He suggested deffiring the trip for three days to tee how the ghaikh progressed and the doctors replied that the aeroplane would not arrive for two days and they felt' that delay ocyond that time would be dangerous especially slz Hi s Highness had a temperature the cause of which was obecurfi. Dr .Maclean aaid that he laaakdgaM considered i t dangerous to keep Hie Highness here in his present condition hut shoula UiB conditioii became worse it might not be poeiaibie to moyo hii.. Shaikh Abdullah Salim was told that there was no question of aa immediate deciaior. being given as His Highness lu*u been asked by tl e doctors to think matters over and let them know hit wishes in the ^ morning either at tneir first visit to him or later at their mu-day Yicii. Shaikh Abdullah then informed me that he had oonaid-r^o it necessary to obtain my viewa before conaulting with tne member# of the family} he then returned to Desman. A pril 9 th . Cn the 7th April theioctors were worried by the steady fall of Hia HighneaB 1 blood pressure and decided not to risk tna journey to Abadan at present. TTis Highness suggested that he itight go later on the invitation of Vr•Jameson and while he was th«r« he could be exurnined by the doctors and have teste carried out. The doctor# welcomed this suggestion and Mr .Maclean decided to return to Abadan on the 8th and diecu## the queetion with Mr .fame- son If the Siiaikh’s condition was satiafa-otory Dr.Maolemii would ccwe by air to Kuwait on the 15th and accompany the Shaikh to toadan in the same plane . On the morning of the 9ih the blood pressure fall and Dr.Scudder eaid that he was much happier o on sequence • had ceased to in his mi rid in ■ v——wi'XT &lt;2 3 70/^2 U/ ~T%C. ku^AjoJjr OiX. ,— rT - c? - ^ &lt;r V€W Ufo^ - ^.-J Ht cUUi^ dsih j^vJ(UjLcf 7 - f a- ^o /U. ; RtC^ccl/ CU“ KcA^yfjJt ^va^vjrruifi^ K^tSSa.^. j*A. * Sce&lt;t ^de*&lt;ct \S' U T~ Mb' tyUA ttbUs, . ff.o. 'ih- £vv*t- i^-sr, 'P.A. tf.O. ( 3 / 16 MAY 1942 T&gt;e&lt;xn- X, U;gh*jW f *'• ^ ’ „V, —M^rin - . '^TSS ' /CfiJt. o&gt;&gt; ■^^.ckX^ or 1 ' £*A4 ^ 1 ‘ v ~ 0, A;®coW * A ~' ^ 2 ''' a $'*' **-&gt;» 80 ^,. U, ‘'•^duA ^ e^ co « ^ ; (S#al.) E. W. R. LUMBYH.159 C.7.39 TELEPHONE! NATIONAL 1212 Telegrams: Inland : Kuoco. Telex, London Foreign : Kuoco. London o ' ' ~° • /CUu VKUWAIT OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. P.0. Box No. 6, New Zealand Avenue, r, Walton-on- Thames. Your Reference Directors H. G. DAVIS (U.S.A.) sy 'yiLLlAM FRASER, C.B n GASS J. JAMESON, C.B.E. B. P. NEWTON (U.S.A.) G. STEVENS (U.S.A.) Our Reference i 5th May, 194?. E.W.P. Lumby, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. Dear Lumby, Thank you very much for your letter Ext.2208/42 of 2nd May, enclosing the text of a telegram from Mr. Scott in Koweit. We should be much obliged if you could have the enclosed telegram from Sir William Eraser despatched by the same method. We will of course bear any expenses incurred. Yours sincerely.FILE COPY fofy M^L Prom Political Resident in Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India. Dated S. S, 'Nearchus’* 12.00 hours, 4th May, 1942* ReccU 12.45 hours, 5th May, 1942. X T/453 . Addressed to India Office repeated to Government of India and Ambassador Cairo for MIDEAST. My telegram 265~T April 12th» Sheikh of Kow e i t * ' 2 3 . Doctors report Sheikh 8 s progress is quite satisfactory (? but that) there is and always will be danger of second attack, that any excitement of any kind is dangerous and that controversial subjects should not be discussed with him* jRECn.POL.OaP* -5IVIAY1942 i INDIA OPNQff-RLE COPY Allotted to External Depart) lent. no* o 3o_ fG'y 11367. DEGYPHER 0 F TELEGRAM. Pr om Political Agent Kuwait, of State for India. to Secretary Dated Kuwait, 12.00 hours, 30th April, 1942. Reed. 17,30 hours, 30th April, 1942. X C/454. Grateful if following message can be given to Koweit Oil Company P.u, box one Sunbury~on-Thames, Midd1 e s ex. A Begins. Sheikh suffered attack Thrombosis heart April 4th condition now much improved progress satisfactory though chance of recurrence exists. Consider inadvisable to telegraph reply earlier Scott. Ends . - REOb.POL.DCPt -1 MAY &lt;442 INDIA OFFICE■—!i^’rom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India* Dated Bahrain 14,00 hours, 12th April, 1942« Received 05,00 hours, 13th April, 1943o Addressed to Secretory of State for India Government of India Mideast and His Majesty's Representative Baghdad. Sheikh's health has much improved and there is no longer need for secrecy. Sympathetic reference to his illness is Being Broadcast from Bahrain, X T/265, RECd. POL. 0£ \ 3 APE 942 INDIA, OTT^CHVH &gt;AT Aliottea to iticzertial I&lt;eDartment ^ Copies 3 zro u.l at&gt; eel 1781 SECRET XXX /^7/V fUL 9099. 9^2 _J tel e gram. , DECYPHER OF Fi^n polltical Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India- Dated Bahrain,* 18* 10 hours, 6th April 1942, Received 02o15 hours? 7th April 1942, fil mi T/216 , Addressed to India Office Government of India Command er-in-CMef Middle East H.M. Representative ^agnaado My telegram No^2Q9 f f April 5th* 2, Doctors now consider Sheikh has reasonable chance of recovery provided he does not have another (? attack) (? within) next (? two or tnree) (? days). There will always he danger of another and more serious attack from which he will probably not recover*a XXX fn/t 9061, DECYPHER 0 F X I L E G; R A M. Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secy.of State for India. Dated Bahrain p 80*04 hours, 6.4*42. Reed. 04.00 hours, 6th April, 194-2r IMPORTANT . T/2Q9 . Addressed to Secy, of State for India repeated to* Government of* India General Headquarters Middle East Cairo and E.M. Representative Baghdad. Regret report Sheikh (feerhampore)of Koweit dangerously, ill with Thrombosis 94394 ^ i ( 47 groups DBCYPHEK 0^ ^ELBGHAM , 3404 Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) The Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India, Dated Risher, 25th June^ I935 0 Receired 4,30 Pom 0i 25th June, 1935 X 567 c Addressed to Secretary of State for India* repeated to Government of India, Jeddah, copy fcy mail Koweit, Koweit Conference 0 SheiJsh left Koweit, June 24th, having appointed Sheikh Abdullah Salim to act as ruler with full powers. Before departure he informed Saudi delegates that they were welcome to stay as long as was necessary and telegraphed to Ibn Saud to the same effect.— &lt;1Notes. Register No. P.^ Aoa if SECRET. Minute Paper. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT -V Dated 193 . Bee. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Date. Initials. SUBJECT. PERSIAN GULF . Rule of succession in tlae sheikhdom of Koweit. H 3 U~j SEEN POLITICAL COMM t 5 m 1955 Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. Previous papers :— Please see the a.o. letter to Mr. Pirie Gordon of 'The Times* of 29th January on p.2.526/35, and the report which has now been received from Col.Dickson as to the Koweiti rule of succession, support is lent to tne Sheikh's statements to Col. Dickson hy practice since the beginning of the present century, sheikh Mubarak himself succeeded by assassination; his successor, Jabir, who was his eldest son, was nominated by him; Jabir in 1917 was succeeded by his younger brother ’•as there is no other eligible candidate*, ana the succession reverted in 1922 to the present sheikh, who is the son of Jabir and the nephew of Salim. The/\ - 2 - The present sheikh is, it is gathered, not more than about 54 and may have some years before him still. His sons are understood not to be outstanding. pc*-' -r»c^ u %■m INDIA OFFICS, LONDON, 3.H. P. ;.LD12/3o. &lt;;5Ui itarca 1950. IT n ® ky Uear Fo«»le f we are most grateful for tae very interesting Infon&amp;ation eontainea in tne notes by Dickson ana Loch which were encloseu in your D.O. No. G.^4 of 11th larch, about tne Arab custom by wnicn a fuuiily such as the Jowasimi own property in coumon. as you will see, copies have been sent to the Foreign Office. It will be very useful to have tais infomation on recora. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAITE. The Hon # ble at. Col. I.C. Fowls, p w' • . j »p Busaire. —J P^.1835/S5, INDIA OFFICE# .vHUbHALL# 3 # 1V # 1. 21st J&gt;jarcii 193D. Isiy dear George# I think you iway he interested in the correspondence, which I enclose, witn Fowle on the 2f Koweitl rule ot succession and in particular in Dicksons letter of 14th February. w. kernel# C.iw.G. Foreign Office. Yours ever, GILBERT LAITEWAITE. Enclosure in weekl No. 13 28»vlAR 1935 FROM SECRETARY, SECRET DEPT. INDIA OG.-'Y otNT TOft 6^’ With reference to your demi-official letter No.P.Z.526/35, dated the 29th January 1935, on the subject of the Kuwaiti rule of succession, I enclose a copy of a demi-official letter No.C-56, dated the 14th February 1935, from Dickson. I am sending a copy of this letter to Metcalfe and Dickson. J.G.Laithwaite Esquire,C.1.E*, The India Office, London •COIglU-'iNTIiiL . POLITICAL ACSKCT U • U • A» O • C'' O O * L fhe i4th Febru&amp;ry 1935. KUWAIT V My dear Fowle Keforence India Office Printed Letter PZ.526 dsted the 1st February 19^5, enclosing copy of Laithwaite's D.O.P .526/55 of 29th January to you. about the cue at ion of Heir Presumptive in general, and to refresh my memory I attain had. a '’chatS with him on receipt of the enclosure referred to above# repeated that in purely Arab states (he excluded of course States like Iraq which are run on Briti sh-cum-fur Kish rather than Arab lines) it was against all custom and was even con sidered unlucky for neigning sovereigns to try and appoint an Heir Apparent, or attarupt to get his sunjects wo swear any sort of oath of fealty to such selected person, during Ruler 1 s his (the -fcrbirh^sr) lifetime* 4. The Arab Idee, said the Uiaikh, was that n the best men 1 ’ should win, after the deeth of the Ruler, Such 'best loan', would always appear, one would at once seize the reins of power, either peacefully, by the unanimous acclamation of the populace, or by neane of a coup d'etat - necessitating possibly but not probebly some bloodshed. 5. In small but stable mercejntile states like Kuwait, ahere the Ruler was an autocrat, and the idea of loyalty to the person of the Ruler was strongly ingrained among the various members of the ruling family, and merchant princes, the death of the Ruler vould not mean probably more th^.n a peaceful acclamation en by the people of their The Hon’ble Lt.-Colonel T.O.Fowle,C.B# .£•, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, STJSniRK. I have often had ini'ormal talks with the shaikh The Rhaikh, as he has often told mo before, againtheir new selected ShaiKh. In larger and less civilized States like Saudiyeh, there will almost invariably be a proper 'bust up' on the dacth of the sovereign, until such tiiaa as the next 'strong appears and 'makes goody In other words revolution and chaos will be the order for a tine, 6. To use the words of the Shaikh: 'I have 2 tou^h and sro’m up sont now, and a third coming on, but I trust none of the*ii will become L.h&amp;ikh. After tufts, unless he be worthy and can play the man - I want no 'craven' or 'weakling' to succeed me, and bring reproach on the mine of iUiraad his Father'• 7 # As regards cihaikh 'iaiaad al Mubarak (i haikh’s uncle) being the rightful heir: The Sheikh not only said that ho, Shaikh Ha;iad, had no particular right over others, to the throne after him, but stoutly denied that'tlie Kuwaiti rule of succession vas in any way Turk!ah or had ever depended on Gttcraan .'inaans', 8* In conclusion the haikh, ar ho lie a often done be fore, sharply criticized the attempt of Bin .*aud to select a successor in the Amir 'iiaud' and to get his tribal loaders to r,wear foalty by annuel oeth. The attempt w€ia foolish, he said, end was Linde purely to 'gull' European diplomats at his Court into thinking the Kingdom of ..eudiyeh was now run on modern llneb, and could be oonpared with European Ututea. This wee not the oa*?e, continued the Sheikh, end no one knew this better tlu&gt;n I'ln Saud htniBelf, who in private talks vlth members of his fumi-ly, was never tired of saying, ‘As long as I am your i uler I intend to rule, so bewaro, but when I am dead let the best man amoXif you win in the chaos that must follow'*9 - 3 - In this connection one must not forget that the King’s brother, Mohamed, a dour and doughty warrior who helped Bin L&gt;aud win his throne and went through all the ups and a owns of his early life, has for the last 2 years openly refused to swear fealty to ioair Saud. See my last Intelligence Summary but one. Yours sincerely, Sd.H.R.P.Dickson.(5) INDIA omcs LONDON, i.rt. 1 Lytn January 1^55 Ity dear Fowle, l irie Ck&gt;ruon ol 'Hie Tii^s 4 aent ua i'or revision a Xow uays a^o t#iie /ur&amp;bian ssction oi t#ne itatestuan* s Year Book. The paragraph which relates to K owe it reh^rks 'Although His iiijmess has two sons by his first marriage, abuullah (born IDOL' and iohanmed (born 1909) and one by his present consort, the uau^ter of the iate jieikn jt.lim ion *. ubaraK ; Jabir, (bom June ^9th, 19L6), the Heir Fresuiuptive according to the Koweiti rule of succession is the ufteiki^s uncle, Hamad ibn Mubarak (born 1894), who has a son ..ubarak'. This infornation about ths succession in Koweit was new to me. I asked pirie Gordon what his authority for it was. He replied that ' io far as 1 remember it was Colonel Jv5ore who gave me the Koweiti rule of succession', ana on sy remarking in reply that I had not hearu of It before, but that colonel lore was, of The Hoa*ble Lt*col. T.C#w. ^bwle, , Busiiir . T “'i V ' course/ *** JAN3 - a - course, an authority wno Uaa the auvantae&gt;e oi local knowleUge, he has written to say;'The Koweiti rule ot succession is Turkish, as tae option used to he and the Tunisian still is, because in tne first instance all three uynasties owed their turones to Ottoman firmans, aithou&amp;h they are of Arab, iiibanian, and xurco-Cretan origin respectively. You will remember how much Ismail hau to pay in r^ypt to ^et tiie ^orte to ciian&amp;e trie succession to primogeniture from the Turkish rule that tae eluest agnate shoulu succeed - a rule invented to ensure that a grown titan should always be at tae neua of a nomsuic tribe; later, when imperial pi'incee ceaseu to fight, it often meant that a senile aotaru succeeded to the throne of an entire which had become sedentary in its decay'. The point is one which I suppose nay be of some direct importance and we should be grateful for your comments on it. 3. I am sending copies of this letter to Dickson and to the Government of India. Yours sincerely,INDIA OmCiil *HIT3HALL. S.W.l• 26th January 1935. Thank you for your letter of 25th January. In the Ctrian article (second sentence) , •Tibbat ,, article, •Kns Bajir' should be *»Ra 9 Darbat All' (which h *| n0 ’ , b#en r e«°*ni*e&lt;1 •• the boundary between the of Bueent snd the Aden Protectorate), and 'Dibbeh' might be spelt 'Dibah* ae in the Trucial 'heikha article. The import duty on certain articles w»s raised to 10* last year, so that the relevant sentence in paragraph 4 on page 686 might be altered to read 'The maximum import duty at present charged on certain articles is iq* ad. valorem '. In the third sentence of the Koweiti article it is not true to eay that the Sheikh is subsidised by the British Government, so that this statement should be omitted. Gordon, risq. , D.S.C., Times f Printing House Square, Kany/. .. 526/3fcu 1*0*0)021, j. .1. .46th January 19 &gt;6* Many thanJcs i*or your letter ol 20th January about the new coition of the Otatesttan'e Tear Boot. I have n &gt; au^geationa to aake on your article about the fractal Oheitchs except to point out two siaall printer's errors In line 6(1 fear that I myself nay have been responsible for the second of these), viz: that the word *to H seems to have dropped out before 'the Strait of C^au£ ,, and that •top of the usanoae eninsula' should read ''tip of the usandaa reninsula*. There i have been no recent dynastic changes in any of the six Sheikhdoms. 2m In the ioweit article, the Political gent should be 'Lieutenant Goloncl h.K. .Dickson, C.!.*.*. I should be interested to know the authority for the Jtowelti rule of sueoesslon which you ^uote. if you would/ . rie Gordon Ssg., I The ’i iiat; s, Printing House d^uare. j .would like to let ja© »e© the balance of the Koweit article (incidentally the spelling noriaally uaed at this end is ’•Koweit**, though the local spelling anu that of the imprint on the stamps is 'Kuwait* imd you nay preier to salntuln the spelling you have adopted in the past), I would be gV*u to look at it* 3* I will let yo have a reply as soon as possible about toe Yemeni article* which tails outside ay sphere but about which 1 ;m making enquiries* and about the passage on the Hadraaaut* The latter irow regarded as part oi the Aden ?rot©otorate* j, Q e laithwaite.P.1229/21. Copy of telegram from Secretary of State to Viceroy, ^ Foreign Department,Dated 19th May,1921. 2546. Your telegram of 13th April 525. Koweit. Your proposal is approved. Mr. W . I should have thought the C.O.would have made some comment on the lines of their telegram to Sir P.Cox of 2nd April. As they have not, our conscience is clear in regard to the telegram of approval. J.A.S. 3.5.21. U.S.of S . The telegram may issue ? L.D.W. 18.5.21. (I regret that,owing to an oversight on my part, this has not 'been submitted before. ) Send A.H.18.5.j.l./ae P.1899/21 4222 Copy of telegram from Viceroy,Foreign &amp; Political Department,to Secretary of State for India, Dated Simla,13.4.21,Received 14.4.21,12 noon. X I.F.O.C.C. I9Q6 . 525-S. Koweit. Our telegram of the 16th March,383-S. It appears that Sheikh Ahmed has now 'been accepted hy Suhah family and Koweit notables as Salim's successor. We propose, subject to your approval, to send to him usual formal Kharita of recognition and congratulation. Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to BaghdadPAKAFERASE TELEGRAM. Erom the High Commissioner of Mesopotamia to the Secretary of State for the Colonies,(Received Colonial Office 3.55 a.m. 4th March,1921). Muscat. Reference death of Sheikh Salim of Koweit. There are three candidates for succession. I request instructions by telegraph.(One) Ahmed son of Sheikh Jabir who preceded Salim: (Two)Hamad Hejaz son of Sheikh Mubarak: (Three) Abdulla son of Salim deceased. Ahmed is on a mission to Bin Saud. Meanwhile chief inhabitants have presented a document to the effect that Subah family state they have bound themselves as follows: Firstly they must prevent any family quarrel in regard to succession. Secondly:acceptanc of any one of above three candidates (naming them in order indicated)subject to approval of His Majesty’s Government: Thirdly they willdemand as condition to be accepted by new Sheikh establishment of a council consisting of six members two from Subah family and four from inhabitants, all elected for one year. Over this Council Sheikh will preside. Political Agent considers Ahmed will certainly become Sheikh if he agrees to above conditions and matter will not be decided pending his return. Meanwhile Political Agent is asking the Subah family to appoint one of their number to take temporary charge. Sent in consultation with Colonel Trevor. Addressed to Secretary of State India Office. Repeated Foreign: Baghdad; Bushire.P.575/17. TELEGRAM PROM SIR P. COX, DATED BASRA, 6th FEBRUARY 1917. Sent to Foreign Department, and Secretary of State for India, repeated to High Commissioner, Cairo, and Bushire for information. 910. My telegram of 5th February. We had not had 82. Subject to our concurrence, which there is no reason to withhold as there is no other eligible candidate^ Sheikh Salim bin Mubarak, younger brother of late Sheikh Jabir and aged about 50, has succeeded to Sheikhship of Koweit. H.M.S. 'BRAMBLE” arrived yesterday and all is quit. Sheikh Salim has intimated readiness to accept all obligations of his predecessor towards British Government and will pay official visit tomorrow. I request authority to convey formal condolences and recognition on behalf of Government.P.4703/15 EXTRACT PROM TELEGRAM PROM VICEROY DATED 2lat DECEMBER 1915. Foreign Secret. Koweit etc. Your telegram of December 18th. Jabir, eldest son of Mubarak nominated by him has succeeded. Salim, second son who was absent on expedition against Ajitt^rman and whose attitude was doubtful has returned to Koweit and has apparently acquiesced in Jabir*s succession. Jabir professes complete loyalty to Britain. H.M.S. 'BRAMBLE' which visited Koweit left accordingly on December 10th.✓ No*3726, dated Bushire, the 7th (received 14th) Dec* 1913. *kOM: Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E*, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, TO: The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department I have the honour to reply to Foreign Department telegram No.530 S., dated the 26th November 1913, regarding Kuwait succession* 2* I think we might write to the Shaikh as follows Whereas under the terms of the Anglo-Turkish Convention the two Governments have agreed that - M x x x In event of decease the Imperial Ottoman Government will designate the successor of the deceased Shaikh, Kaimmakam by Imperial Farman* x x x x x”, and whereas Your Honour has urged that this wording affords no assurance to yourself that your 'successor'* in the Rulership of Kuwait be from among the heirs of your body, and have asked the British Government to reassure you with an undertaking to that effect, the Great Government have considered the matter and I am to inform you as follows 'The British Government have recognised the statesmanship and wise control with which you have conducted your administration and have fully appreciated the friendliness and cordiality with which you have always endeavoured to co-operate with them in their mission ot promotion of order and good government on the shores of the Persian Gulf, and in return for which they have been glad to support you in your legitimate aspirations for increasing the prosperity and civilisation of your principality. They, therefore, regard you as a true friend whose wishes for the future of/9 1$) MINUTE. Our assurances to the Sheikh are contained in Article 9 oi* the lease of 1907* which should be read in the light of the Government of Indian telegram of 10th January 1908 (both flagged below). The Government of India state that there was no intention of giving a dynastic pledge. Since that date the situation has essentially changed in that Turkey is pledged to abstain 'de toute immisction dans les affaires de Koweit, y compris la question de la succession', whereas H.M.G. are not. All that we are pledged to is not to change, 'en rien la nature de (nos) relations avec le Gouvemt. de Koweit', and not to establish a protectorate. It would appear therefore that our hands are free. The Turks are further pledged to appoint as Kaimmaham 'le successeur de Sheikh defunt'. The assurance which Sir P.Cox and the Government ol India now propose to give of course goes beyond our former assurance - that is the point of it. But it is not at all a dynastic pledge, in that it is given only to Mubarak personally, and it seems sufficiently guarded in its language. Koweit on one side and Muhammera on the other are the two pillars on which the arch of our position at the head of the Gulf rests. It is morally certain that we cannot afford to allow either of them to be weakened or to pass out of our influence. The situation at Muhammera - where the Sheikh also asks for further assurances, and where Sir W. Townley^ less than half-hearted support of him against the Bakhtiari tends towards disintegration - will come under consideration very shortly. As regards Koweit it is submitted that it is desirable to give thiB personal and strictly/✓ # No.3359, dated Bushire, the 9th (received 17th) November 1913 (Confidential). FROM: Lieutenant Colonel Sir P.Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, TO: The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign I have the honour to revert to the question of the Shaikh oi Kuwait’s desire for a dynastic guarantee, last referred to in the Government of India’s telegram of 9th August to His Majesty’s Secretary of State. Since our interview in the Shatt-el-Arab on 7th July, and the despatch of my letter No.2102 of 10th idem to Government, Shaikh Mubarak has repeatedly asked the Political Agent whether there was any reply from Government on this point, and at my recent visit he reverted to the subject of the Convention generally and the question of succession in particular. XXX X 3. He then turned to the questionof the succession, and asked me what Government had said on that point. I replied that they had apparently not found it possible to give me any special reply or instructions. I went on to explain to him that His Majesty’s Government naturally had to b e very chary of committing themselves to guarantees of this sort for all time and without conditions to safeguard them in certain eventualities, and that in his case, seeing that the Turks had agraed, in the present Convention, to abstain from all interference in the question of succession, it was consequently simply a matter concerning himself and us, and I did not quite see what reason he had to be anxious about it. Thinking it a pity to lose the opportunity/opportunity of getting at his real feelings, I continued that Captain Shakespear and I would, as he knew, shortly he going home on leave, and that we three might not have another opportunity of a cpiiet talk together, so could he not, now that we were on the subject, confide to us what he really had in mind so that we might understand the position exactly and be in a position to make any further explanation to Government that might be indicated He readily responded. He said he quite understood the difficultybf His Majesty’s Government in such questions and djd not want to nominate anybody now as his presumptive successor, nor did he press for anything in but that what exercised him was the thought, or the fear, that when the time came for him to go, some individual or individuals from among his family or kinsmen, who found themselves disappointed, might engineer active discord which, if we held aloof, might rack the principality and undo his lifework as Shaikh in the direction of consolidation and improvement. What he so much wanted was to b e able to feel assured that when he joined the majority provided that we had no reason to differ from his wishes at the time, or his testamentary dispositions if he went suddenly, we would, incase of necessity, stand by, and even intervene to regulate the situation. We told him that we quite appreciated his point of view and wadLd place it fully before Government for sympathetic consideration. 4. I venture to think that it would not be difficult to find a formula that would set the mind of our venerable protege at rest, and I much hope that Government will see their way to uevise one which will have that effect without inconveniently committing themselves.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00018e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3830</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00018e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3830</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/107 'Koweit: Rules of succession in Koweit.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-01T23:29:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (59 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 61; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the rules of succession for the rulers of Kuwait (also referred to as Koweit).The papers cover: correspondence dated 1935 between the India Office and Charles Harry Clinton Pirie-Gordon of
                           The Timesconcerning the article on Kuwait for the new edition of the
                           Statesman's Year Book; letter from Lieutenant-Colonel Harold Richard Patrick Dickson, Political Agent, Kuwait, dated 14 February 1935, concerning the question of the appointment of an heir to the Shaikh of Kuwait; the question of the succession in view of the sudden and serious illness of the Shaikh of Kuwait [Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ], May 1942; and an enquiry from the BBC concerning the locally-accepted date of the accession of the Shaikh of Kuwait, February 1948.The papers also include copies of earlier correspondence dated 1913-21 relating to the succession in Kuwait at that period.There are no papers in the file dated 1936-41 and 1944-47.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Kings and rulers--Succession</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00018e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>