<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000065_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T08:34:35.007Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">To be kept in personal possession of Political Agent . COKFIl'KVTI M Kuiiniit K&lt; No 3£jL. D,,re ' Confident ial. The Residency, D&gt;Q.Tro.S47-&gt;S&gt; Bushire, the 25th March, 1939. Ctc&lt;w (L, Could you please refer to paragraph 3 of your Express Letter Wo.c/l02, dated the 14th March 1939, in which you mention that our promise to Mubarak benefits not only Mubarak* s heirs but other members of the Subah family. 2. The following point has occurred to me. The taxation compensation of £ 22,000 is in respect of property which w&amp;s in the possession of Mubarak when the pledge was signed and since his death has been in the possession of his heirs (cf. paragraph 4 of India Office Sxpress Letter No.P.^i. 1074/39, dated the 28th February 1939. His Majesty*3 Government’s promise is given at page 265 of Aitchison Volume XI. The India Office use the expression 'heirs* while the wording of the promise was 'descend ants'. I think, however, we can take these two terms as being synonymous.) This sum, however, was arrived at on the basis of actual taxation since 1932 up*to date on all the Shaikh’s date gardens in Iraq. 3. if the heirs of Mubarak cwn all the date gardens in Iraq covered by the Shaikhs figures of annual taxation then our assessment of compensation is correct. In this connection see your letter No.C-55, dated the 4th N February 1938. b e) 4. It may be however that this is not the case and that the real situation is that the date gardens in question belong partly to the heirs of Mubarak and partly to other members of the Subah family. The division between 'heirs of Mubarak', including of / course de Gaury Esquire, MC., Political Agent, Kuwait.course the Shaikh himself, and the 'non-heirs of Mubarak' must be either (a) that the heirs own certain definite plots of land in the gardens and the non-heirs, other plots, or f what is more likely, (b) that there is no division of areas but a division in fixed proportion of the income from the gardens. 5. T 7hat we have to ascertain is the proportion of the annual taxation which the Shaikh paid on account of the heirs. (1) If it is a case of (a) then we will have to deduct from our taxation basis the amount paid by the Shaikh for the produce from lands owned by the non-heirs. (2) If it is a case of (b) then we will have to reduce our assessment by the proportion in which the income is enjoyed by the non-heirs. 6. Will you please, without if possible indicating to the Shaikh the reasons for your enquiries, ascertain fr an him how the matter stands, whether it is a case of paragraph 3 above, or, if not, of (a) or (b) of paragraph 4. 7. I am surprised that this aspect of the question has not occurred to any of the legal and financial luminaries at home, and am rather sorry that it has occurred to me ! However, now that it has occurred, vre must clear it up. Apart from any other considerations - and after all i t is the taxpayer’s money we are dealing with - this aspect may occur to some other authority. If we have to reduce the sum I mentioned to the Shaikh (which of course will not be done without reference to His Majesty’s Govern ment) it will be rather awkward, but fortunately no letters have actually passed.The Residency^ Bushire, the 30th March, 1939 To be kept In the pera onal poaaeaalon of the Pollt^csul \gent* Confident lal * D.O»yo» 2ai&gt;3 , h1 Could you ple&amp;ae refer to your Express Letter No.C/102, dated the 14th March 1939, on the subject of the payment of taxation compensation In respect of the Kuwait date gardens in Iraq. 2. I am not in favour of the alternative plan suggested in your paragraph 6. With regard to the representations from the Subah to us mentioned in your paragraph 7, this is surely just what we want to avoid. The last thing I want to do is to be drawn into their family quarrels and be put in a position of arbitrating on them. • 3. I am still of opinion that we should adhere to the decision of a Family Council. Just because the distribution of the Income from the estates is complicated, and because we want to see justice done to all the heirs of Mubarak, the arguments which the Shaikh used against the Family Council are in fact, in my opinion, arguments for it. There is the further argument that we want to make as much capital as possible with the Subah family, who are now an important factor in Kuwait, and I am sure that the idea of a Council will appeal to them since I get the strong impression that up to date the Shaikh has been appropriating to himself the major / part G. de Gauiy Esquire, MC., Political Agent, Kuwait.part of the shares due to the family* and that he will continue to do so unless there is some check on him* 4. It is true that the Shaikh informed you that Abdullah Salim was against a Family Council* but I have no doubt that the Shaikh has ’•squared** him* 5* #e can discuss the question further when I visit Kuwait towards the end of April* &lt;r ^ cConfidential. Political Agency, Kuwait, April 7, 1939. r D.0, No. C/162. My dear Sir Trenchard, Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 247-S of March 25th, 1939? I see that you say in it 'I rather wish it had not occurred to me' so that I think you will not mind my criti- zising strongly this possible new view of our obligation. If the Government did take that view, I suggest that it would (a) bring us into grave disrepute, thus working against the object we are trying to achieve, the public and honourable discharge of part of our 1914 obligation, and (b) be contrary to our commitment in 1914. clear if we imagine a similar situation today. Suppose that we are again about to land at Pao, to retake Iraq.. The night before the troops land, having in view our recent experiences over the gardens, you telegraph to me 'Please infora Shaikh as follows Begins: 'His Majesty’s Government guarantee that you shall remain in occupation of y our gardens etc. ends.' The Shaikh tells Abdulla Salim and others. Abdulla Salim and others, who have, of course, a share in the gardens rejoice. 2. To explain the latter statement I think it will be Then you, (having thought of the aspect now sugges ted by you), send another telegram 'My immediately preceding telegram. We only guarantee Shaikh’s personal share in gardens, and that of his 'descendents'. The Hon’ble Sir Trenchard Bowie, KCIE., CBE., Bushire.- 2 - AMulla Salim and Company are much depressed, hut fcou have made it clear what you mean. Eow we are going to implement this (the imaginary and qualified) promise, in case of a test, as there is no territoria] division, and AHMAD administers the whole estate, I don’t know hut at least you have said what you mean. Cox did not say so. In other words, when Sir Pe^cy Cox on hehslf of His Uajesty’s Government said 'your' gardens, he must he taken to have meant 'the gardens which you, the Shaikh of Kuwait, as head of your family occupy in Iraq'. club together to invest in an estate to he bought in the name of the head of the family, and that this was in fact, to certain h- extent, the case for some of the Shaikh’s estates, and as also.- these Aral families are always marrying their cousins I do not envy anyone the task of unra‘/ailing the exact obligation of Mubarak’s descendants vis a vis the remaining Subah and vice tax payer money we can easily do so. Je made it clear that it was in 'return' for the Shaikh’s 'valuable' (military) assis tance that we were giving the guarantee. I have never heard that Mubarak did give the specified assistance, and I don't iriaeax tihink Ahmad could prove that he did. We can step out of the whole thing on that ground if we want to do so, to the advantage of the tax payer but very much to the discredit of Great Britain in .Arabia, and extremely late in the day. 5. My main argument then is that that it is too late now to take this new view, ar| h that if we had done so, in 1914 or even in 1918, it would have landed, us in more difficulties than there have been already, e.g. at the present moment we snould be explaining to tne Iraq Government that our obligations only 3. I believe it is a fact that members of .Arab families Versa 4 I Enight add that if t h e first object is to save the cover/cover part of the gardens, and that as far as we are concerned, the Jffudir of Fao can remain in occupation of -/- ths of the gardens, i.e. that proportion of them which belongs to those of Mubarak’s family who were not his heirs. I say that having for 25 years accepted the full obligation we must also fully dischar^ it, and that acceptance of the full obligation //as the only practical course, and is the one which we have hitherto accepted in practice throughout the period since His Majesty’s Government* promise was made twenty five years ago. Yours sincerely,Confidential. D.O. No. 0/163. Political Agency, Kuwait, 7th April, 1939. My dear Sir Trenchard, Could you please refer to your demi-official letter No. 281-S of March 30th? I am sorry that my Express letter No. C/102 of March 14th was not clear . \ to you. ' I meant that if members of the Subah family did come to us about the disposal of the money we could discuss it with Shaikh Ahmad, and then consider the formation of a Council. According to my information they probably would not do so. If they did, I am not sure, unless the majority of them do so, and produce strong reasons, if we ought to agree and press the Shaikh for a family council. As you know the Arabs are individualists, and ambitious, and much better at dis rupting than building, and we should not encourage them in disruption in this instance. 2. The Subah family, faced with extinction as a power, recently gave their renewed support to the Shaikh and he was thus enabled to achieve his come back. If, however, the Subah family, of \artiich of course the Shaikh is one, become divided, not only they but the Shaikh and the State will again get into difficulties. 3. The formation by us of a Family Council against the Shaikh's wishes is thus a serious step to take at The Hon'ble Sir Trenchard Fowle, KCIE. , CPE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. the/at the present time, just 'because we shall he forming it against his wishes (our reasons - see end of your para graph 3 - may he excellent) and because the Suhah will as a result become divided from the Shaikh, and among them selves, and 'divided'they will certainly 'fall'. which is at fault hut the present administrator. I think there is a case for a very straight talk to him on this subject, and about his excessive economy in other direc tions, which has already led to trouble in the past, and will do so again, but not, I think, a good case for our changing the family system - administration which has existed since Mubarak’s day and possibly earlier. 5. In all the circumstances, therefore, and knowing your views, I am still in favour of the middle course I have recommended, and I do not think there remains any important point which I have not considered. 4. It is not the present family administrative system Yours sincerely,Confidential. To be kept in the leraonal possession of the Political /^ent. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, ‘f 7 ? Dkpaetmint, EXPRESS LETTER 2A h [iV, B,— This is an ORIGINAL MNSSAGN, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if ii had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded, and signed as if ii had been so despatched^] Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait No % 397-3 Oated 22nd April 1939. 1 Subject s- The Shaikh of Kuwait’s date gardens in Iraq. ' A Reference your letter No.2/162 dated the 7th April 1939. *■ 2. We can discuss your letter when I arrive at Kuwait, v/hich will now be either in the first or second week of May. I will let you know shortly which it v/ill be® In the meantime, and whatever decision we may finally arrive at, please ascertain how the matter actually stands. is it a t ease of paragraph 3 or of paragraph 4^a) or 4 (b) of ray ' ft' letter No .247-3 dated the 25th March 1939 ? I think you ' could do this v/ithout giving awa£ the reason for your enquiries in the course, for instance, of &amp; general conversation wi th I S. 6. MFL’—785S&amp;P—(M-1014) —18-8-33—2,00 300.1 ?} v/ith the Shaikh as to the position of the whole of the Subah Family in connection with the bate Gardens • Sd. T* (J. Fowle. Political Kesideiit in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.■&gt;&amp; r; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL), —- ” an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] Political Agency, Kuwait. No.c/218 Dated Simla New Delhi the 9th May, i$9.- To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject: - The Shailch of Kuwait *3 date gardens in Iraq.. Reference my Reference your Express letter No. 397-S, dated the 22nd April, 1939. 2. In conversation with the Shailch I understood from him that it is a case of paragraph 4 (b) of your letter No. 247-S of the 25th /arch, 1939, for 7ao, and, of 4 (a) for the Earhaniya, but of paragraph 3 for the other gardens. In making this enquiry I had to be discreet, as you instructed me, and did not therefore press for confirmation and details. 3. Another aspect which I think we should remember is that, as you rightly say, we do not wish to antagonise the Subah family. I hope that all will go well with the Mubarak clan, but it must be admitted that heirs are becoming rather few, and child mortality in Arabia is heavy. AHMAD has two small boys, his brother HAMOOD has one (Signature) small/ (Designation)small ABDULLA SALIM has no hoys, his younger brother SUBAH AS SALIM has one small boy, MUBABAK BIN MfiXfilfitS HAMAD is unmarried, but has a child brother, called KHALID. There are, therefore, so far only five boys in the next generation, of the Mubaralc Subah by Subah wives, i.e. eligible for Bulership, all afc present under 13 years of age. It might oe that the .itulership will one day have to move to one of the other Subah clans, whom we should show our fullest benevolence, so that they may not look elsewhere for patronage. Political Agent, KuwaitFrom To No. Dated the 3rd May Political Agent, Kuwait Political Resident, Bushire. C/198 , 1939. Seizure ~by Iraqi Go vernm en t o f S haikh of Kuwait *3 date gardens in Irao. Shaikh has today sent me a formal letter drawing attention to Majesty’s Government's October 1914 promise which he requests may be implemented. Ris letter follows by mail. Political Kuwaitconfidential Kuntil Ft '.‘if&gt;t ’ A vroj. '® a/ Telegram From To Q Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait, No. r 280 Dated and received the 4th May, 1939. K' Your telegram No. 0/198 of May 3rd. To save time, please send hy air mail to India Office and Government of India and Baghdad translation of Shaikh’s letter with copy of your telegram and of this. ResidentCONFIDENTIAL No - C/201 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to 1, His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London, 2, The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 3, His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires, British Embassy, Baghdad, 4, The Hon •hie the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the Bj? «L • Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. 1, 2. 3 . A&gt; \ Telegram No, C/193 of 3rd May^ 1939, from the Political Kuwait, to the Political Resident, Bushire,. ^ Telegram No. 280 of the 4th May 1939 from the Political Resident, Bushire, to the Political \gent, Kuwait. b u Translation of letter dated 13th Rabiawwal 1358 (3rd JTay 1939) from His Highness the Baler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Seizure hy Iraqi Government of Shailch of Kuwait’s date gardens in Iraq, do - do© w ( t&gt; Translation of letter dated the 13th iiahiawwal 1358 (3rd May, 1939), from His Highness the iiuler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait. After Compliments} This is with regard to the seizure 'by the Iraq. Government of our land and properties, and the damage that has 'been done to them. This sort of interference with our property hy the Iraq Government happens too frequently, without any reason, and our personal prestige has suffered consi derably of late. It is widely known that our properties in Iraq are to be protected by the High British Government according to their promise given in 1914 (aulhijja 1332) which was conveyed by the Hon’ble the Political aesident Bushire, and the High British Government has always been protecting our interests by lawful means, 'tfe hope now that she will fulfil her promise in safe guarding our interests in Iraq. In the circumstances we sinoerely hop© that you will be kind enough to forward our request to the proper quarters, as our interests lie in the hands of the High British Government. They are well known for their Justice and their kindness towards their friends. I know very well that you and the Hon*ble the Political resident are fully aware of the present situation but I hope that proper Justice is soon given to us, since otherwise it will seriously affect our prestige.Telegram - OTC From - Political A.gent, Kuwait To - Political Resident, Bushire. No. - C/204 Dated the 5th May y 1939. . ^ Shailch of Kuwait *s date garden case 'before ' ' Appeal court, Baghdad. Shaikh reports th^t case has heen postponed until May 11th. i - Political -CONFIDENTIAL. No ‘ 460-3. The Hon’ble the Political compliments to C ^ ; ^ m fe ^ . ■■'T'r gS'* Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his !• Hi a Hajeaty 9 8 Secretary of State for India, London* 2* Hie Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Delhi* / 3* Hie Political Agent, Kuwait* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... 6 . !?.??• /j ' / • ( h/ * ? V' f! T \ Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter 36*431-3 of 1st Hay 1939* H \ % Description of Enclosure. Name and Date TTT Residency telegram No*266 of the 6 th Hay 1939* Subject. Shaikh of Kuwait’s Date Gardens case*-By *it* Mail. p.z. ^-?ry 19 ^ i?|r i Knit ai■' No Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to bv ^— Mail, bea The Foreign iSp eretnrv r rr overnm^nt of India. The Po 1 itical lioniileiu in the Persian Guli'. 3681ENCLC J$ T ? C* '7 T~ r \ vy **s ORE 1 QN 9 PFIC 1 1 i 3 APR 1939 ' / V 1939 NO DISTRIBUTION. &gt;J354/59/l© ? Cypher telegram to Mr. Houstoun-Boswall (Bagdad; foreign Office, 1st April i959, 10.30 p,m. No, 104o ^ t nr V. * four telegram No. 98 [of March 30tho The Sheikh of KoweiVs date gardens], I congratulate you on success of your representations. 2. Do you see any objection to making further renresentaxions to following effect? 3o His Majesty's Government appreciate prompt action taken by Iraqi government to restrain local authorities who seem to have acted in a very high-handed manner. They have no doubt that Iraqi government will enquire into the circumstances in which this came about, since the whole episode would appear to justify serious investigation. V'NtS J Ls * L Mk From H.M. Ambassador, To J.T.QrtilgXl...Qf.£l.QG.». repeated to Buehlre Ko* T/^ering and ^oweit We* 5/Beving. point with Kabir* Kabir explained that in principle plea la for re^-hearing of appeal dismissed January 10th on aeeount of faulty security* Legal arguments have therefore to be adduced against Judgment given by Basra Court of First Instance on July 15th, 1958* Reference to declaration of Land Bettlenent will be made by lawyer In court, who will invite court to ooneider whether in view of this declaration ease should not now be transferred to Lend Settlement Court* Judgment must be made in order that Appeal Court may have opportunity to transfer case to Land Settlement, but that it would be illogical in appeal itself to call in question Jurisdiction of court to which appeal is addressed* Bagdad. London* Bate le.t..Htiy+....l£2£L No Time despatched.. Addressed to Foreign Off ice i«o* 63/ saving. Your telegram Bo* 167,/‘2^ UK' u / Orlsntal Caeretary had already diacusaad this \&gt; «) Kabir 9 a point la that appeal against Basra H OU CTOtIJMKJSmtX,I * r i ^ COPY dS 1 TELEGRAM. ^ CLAIK. MB MAIL, From H.M. Ambassador, Bagdad. jy Q r or^l ff * *,ondoru 2 ) ate gth May, 19*9. eg/^m;m. Time despatched.. Aidr^af»«l to Foreign Office Ho. 55 Spring, repeated to Buehire Ho. 8/Bering and ^oweit Ho. 4/H«Ting. My tale gram Ho. 63/aaring. ^ || - Far to reporta thet hearing of appeal wee adjourned; to be continued on Hay 11th. HOUBTOUWBOaWAXJi.By Air Mail. CO^Frn'^’TIAL | fit Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. v r ♦ &gt; A copy has been sent to by Mail. J The Forei.ii, n Scci-ctru.v, OuvTrnmen-fc of hidia. The Political Ituimlcnr, in the Persian Guik 3681c. IS CLOSURE IW FOREIGN C eO^fet’IFiQ LSTTER DATED L. NO PIS RIBUTION Telegram (en clair) from Mr. Roustoun-Boswall (Bagdad). D. 26th April, 1959. R. 1st May, 1959. No. 49. (Saving). BY BAG. Yonr telegram No. 55 to Bushire and your Mo. 127 to me. Kabir was consulted yesterday about preparations for hearing of appeal on May 4th. Partu has not yet acted on my advice to get into touch with Kabir and I have learnt that adjournment on April 11th was due to fact that he did not appear in court when the case was called. In view of these circumstances, I feel it advisable to brief second lawyer to support him (the opposing side have three) and to conduct case in the event of his failing to appear. Kabir still declines to appear in court but will suggest a suitable junior to help Partu. I assume there is no objection to my incurring necessary expenditure. Fee for second lawyer should be comparatively small and Kabir will also have to be paid a fee for his consulta tions. He will not fix a figure until the case is over. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 48 having, repeated to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Mo. 5 Saving by air mail.mmmem ■ M ¥ I \ CONFIDENTIAL. No. 495-3 ~Xl,j ,\M- 5?V '?/&lt;• The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait• and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). •v V V * rv British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 14th .M»y. 1939. Reference to previous correspondence : '/fib ft y t rn : ■*- / 53 ^ .n Residency Printed Letter 3SO.460-S of 6/5/39. Description of Enclosure. r • ' Name and Date b n VS Bagdad telegram No. 135 of n-’ ' 13th May 1939 to the Foreign Office. Subject. Kuwait date gardens case.t&gt;3/n % L h IT Telegram IT om To Repeated Hia Majesty’s Charge d'affaires, Bagdad Political Resident, Ruahire, at Kuwait. iso. 33 secretary of ‘State for foreign Affaire, London, a 0.196 political .Agent, Kuwait. ao. 20 Dated and received 17th May 1939. ,/ My telegram ho. 185 to foreign Office. It may be necessary to pay court fees Could Shaikh be moved to provide Partu with means to do this. Total probably about 200 dinars. Houst oun-BoswallTolegram ^rom To Repeated Km'ti 1 no juris ttyc ■^C R His Majesty’s Charge d'Affaires, Bagdad. Political Resident, Bushire. Ho.39 secretary of dtate for foreign Affairs, London. no.2( Political \gent, Kuwait. Dated and received 13th May 1939. .io.21 'ly telegram Ho.33. To avoid delay I have today given Partu cheque for 202 dinars for court fees. Please recover from ihaikh and remit to me. &lt;P. 4 /y. u. Roust Din-Boswall \ *1 1 V CONFIDENTIAL. No. C /Z37 \ The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R g. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). for information. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 15th May 1939 Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. ju &gt; Copy of translation of letter undated from Shaikh Muhammad al Ahmad as Subah, to H.H.the Ruler of Kuwait. V DATE GARDENS OF HIS HIGHNESS THE RULER OF KUWAIT. 2. Copy of letter dated 6th May 1939 from Shaikh Muhammad al Ahmad as Subah, to H.H.the Ruler of Kuwait.-Translation of letter from Shaikh Mohamed to H.H.the Ruler of Kuwait* Sir, Consul, regarding the reinstatement of the new gardeners he was what to do with the new gardeners put in by him* He only said document saying that he is the owner of the 'Faddaghiyah', so if we file a case against him he will produce the document* That is just what they want. As the Mutassarif was himself 1 a solicitor he knows all about the law* property without making an agreement with him as follows*, the gardener is to cultivate the land,and the owner has the . right,if he wishes to keep the gardener,or to dismiss him at the completion of the season year, without any notice* Of course, Sir, all the gardeners we have on the 'Faddaghiyah” have such agreements with us,but the Mutassarif says that you cannot dismiss a gardener without an drder from the Court. I have told him that I have various agreements with them which empower me to send them away at any time,I say that when we have a proper agreement why should we approach the Court to send away any gardener? Other land owners in Basra do the same as us* the end of each year the owner has the right to let him stay or send him off, and the gardener never objects* were tfc file a case against each gardener, this would Of course cost us much, and in the end,Sir, let me tell you they would give everty case against us. When we were with the Mutassarif,in presence of the quibbling,so after the Consul left, Tasked the Liutassarif to that the Law Court is there in which to file a case against them. I understand that bin Hamdi is in posession of a Besides,we heve never put in any gardener on our We have a clause in these agreements showing that at We do not know why the Government now object. If weTranslation of letter dated 6th May 1939 from Shaikh Muhamad bin Ahmad as Subah, Basrah, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait* After Compliments, Today I have received a letter from Advocate Abdul Jalil Partu in which he whites as follows:- ”1 went to see Advocate Yusuf al Kabir Captain Holt, They wish to engage another lawyer to be with me in order that he might be present at the Court in time if I am a bit late, but they do not want the lawyer to appear in Court with me. Their object, it seems in this, by keeping another lawyer, is that if I am a bit late he might get an adjournment of the hearing of the case* I said I would be present in time. They did not agree to this, and they are trying to get the lawyer. 2 # Then I told them that we should have an experienced lawyer so that he might be useful to me in conducting the case, but they are arranging to engage an inexperienced one at low fees. Yusuf al Kabir said that they would pay this fee from the Embassy Funds. I will go tomorrow to Yusuf al Kabir to see the new layer* rt 3# According to this, there is no need to send a letter to Advocate Abdul Jalil Partu to proceed with the case alone, and also there is no need to inform him to engage another lawyer himself. .Vq will not, therefore, send the money which he wants in advance, as the Embassy are engaging a lawyer themselves. Usual EndingCONFIDENTIAL. No. , 0/Z53 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Honourable the Political resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, at Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document)^). for information. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Bated the 19 th May 1939. Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. w Copy of translation of letter dated 11th May 1939 from Advocate Abdul Jalil Partu, Baghdad, tu Shaikh Muhammad al -ahnad as Subah, Basra. Subject. ,TE GARDENS OF HIS HIGHNESS THE RULER OF KU YAIT.Translation of let tar dated 11th Liay 19o9 from advocate Abdul Jalil Partu, Baghdad, to Shaikh Muhammad al Ahmad as Subah, Basrah. After Compliments. I appeared in the Court on the day fixed. The Court sat but I found that a fifth member was added to the usual members of the Court. I repeated my statement and, after discussion for more than two hours, I was informed of the decision which, I regret to say, contained the rejection of our second petition, and was given by a majority of votes. I learnt that in the previous session the President of the Court and another member were on our side and two members on pur apponent T s zats side. According to law, if a decision is given in this manner, the President’s side is considered to be the majority, but it appears that the Presid ent did not agree to bear this responsibility. He asl©d for a fifth member to join them and Abdul Aziz al Mutair was called who, it is understood, was on our apponent’s side. The decision was thus passed by a majority of votes. I telephoned at once to Captain Holt who ashed me to see Ustad Yusuf al Kabir whom we should meet together. I went forthwith to the place of Ustad Yusuf al Kabir and explained the situation to him. He spoke to the Secretary and it was agreed that we should submit a request to the president of the Court of Cassation asking for the cancellation of the limitation period, under paragraph 2 of Article 7 of Rules for Law Courts. If he agrees to the cancellation, for which we will have to pay fresh Court fees, I shall let you know in due course. Usual Snding.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/iao The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian ,r/nlf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of 3tate for lndia 9 London. 2. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs ‘‘'apartment, Hmm Simla* 3. His Majesty's Charge d*Affaires, Bagdad* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Kuwait* Dated » Reference to previous correspondence : \ Jo (Q Bagdad despatch No.126 (109/22/39) of 25th March 1939 to the foreign Office* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date &lt;r y 4^ Jitter dated 27th ^pril 1939 from ihaikh Muhammad al Ahmad as ^abah, Basra, to H*H« the Ruler of Kuwait* 4 Subject. &gt;haikh of Kuwait's property at 4'addaghiyah* / v/ Copy forwarded with complimi for information. «nts to Political Agent, Kuwait, U* :— 1 f CONFrnZKTlM | . ' Confidential /''' „i„ No.C/181 of 1939. £&lt;L( JU Office of the Political Heaident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Kuwait. 20th May 1939. To The Political Agent, Kuwait* Subject t Date gardens of the Shaikh of Kuwait in Iraq. I Memorandum Reference correspondence ending with Bagdad telegram No.39, dated the 18th May 1939, please recover sum from Shaikh and remit to Embassy. 3d. T.C.FOWLS Political Resident in the Persian Bulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 0/218 . Ut Sit* The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. sir Aubrey Metcalfe, K.O*I«E«fM.Y.O* Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department^ 2. Major A.C. Galloway, Political Agent, Kuwait .t/ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the documents (s). British Consulate-General, BTJSHIRE. Oaurp Kuwait. Dated 24th May 1939. Reference to previous correspondence : m j India Office Express Letter No.P.Z. 1074/39 of 28th February 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date \0 JEtesidency letter No.C/217 Subject. dated 24th May 1939 Kuwait date gardensmminMPfcv 1m ntimm—1 nn at aatAaat Um wrnmllrti ^m—ily is to 1 m atriotly interjratoO. a naw asaassaant of ooa- yem^tion will to bo aad« doduotia^ from the beets the rtembers of the Shaikh’s family other than the heirs of Mubarak. me 3hailch *otUd of oouree hare to be in 5. If His Majesty^ Government decide that the present compensation la to eVoad th«a no further aotlcm le necessary. should be revised then my comments are ss follows. (1) me division of the date gardens between ’heirs of miber&amp;k*, including of course the ftalfch him self f and the •non-heirs of mibarak* must be either? (a) that the heirs o n oerteln definite plots of (b) that there is no division of areas but a division in fixed proportion of the income from the gardens. (2) whet ee have to ascertain is the proportion of the annual taxation which the fhaikh paid on account of the heirs. 7. (1) If it is a oase of (a) then we will have to deduct from our taxation basis the amount paid by the halkh for the produce from lands owned by the non-heirs. of £ 1087 the average annual loss on property owned by formed 9 which naturally will be awkward. 6. If f however t they decide that the compensation land in the gardens and the non-heirs, other plots, or, what is more likely. (a) /(8) If It is ft ohm of (1)) then wt will have to reduce our assessment by the proportion in which the income is enjoyed by the non-hairs I asked de Gaury to try and *seert*ln verbally from the 3haikh ff without of course giving away the reasons for his enquiry, what was the position of the whole of the ;ubah family in oonneotion with the date gardens# de Gaury’s reply was that it was a ease of paragraph 6 (l)(b) for the ?ao estate# of 6 (l)(a) for the l^srhaniya estate t and the remaining estates were owned solely by the heirs of ^iubarafc# But this in the oiroumatanoee cannot be taken ae a final authorltativa statement 9 and if it is decided to re-assess the ooa&amp;ensation we shall have to request the Shaikh for an official statement* compensation on my present visit# and if he should do so 1 will put him off with an appropriate reply# 9# The ihaikh hm not raised the question of and giving eme to Oallow*y# Yours sincerely Sd.T.C.YOWLE • sent under Printed letter No.c/218 of 24/6/39. £ given • • • • •CONFIDENTIAL. No. 0/222 T6// The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London, 2. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External \ffairs Department, Xm Simla, 3. His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires, Bagdad, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 25th - •lay •1939v Shaikh Mohamet! to H,H. the Holer of Kuwait, nmmp WtammAt- Reference to previous correspondence : Besidenoy Printed Letter Ho,C/180 of 20th May 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject. (1) Letter from Shaikh Uchamed Ktnrait date gardens*Confidential, No. C/227. COS Ft! t Xo b ! &lt;5 L ^/ r -! The Hon’hie the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1, The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, 2, The Political Agent, Kuwait and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. British Consulate-General, Bushire, Dated 27th May, 1959, Camp, KUWAIT. Name and date# Subject. Political BesidenVa telegrai] No. T/108 of the 27th May, 1939, Seizure of Shaikh's date gardens.Q Political Besident, at Kuwait. H.M # s Secretary of State for India, His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. Copy by post to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Copy given to Political .Agent, Kuwait. Ho. - T/108. Dated the 27th May, 1939. Telegram Prom To Repeated to - M' Baghdad telegram Ho. 137 of April 12th to the Foreign Office and connected correspondence. Shaikh informs me that up to now his date gardens have not been released *by the Iraqi authori ties. Grateful if further strong representations could *be made. RESIDENT -■MU No. Dear Chancery, Heference Baghdad telegram No. 39 d'ltei the IBth May, 1939, to Bushire. 2, We enclose a choaue Tor I.D. 202-00 representing the amount advanced to the Solicitor AMul Jalil ?artu. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours ever, Agency. The Chancery, His Majesty’s Bmbassy, Baghdad.* 7 %v- rv,.,** J 1 »’t m » mmmrnmtm CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/244 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon *1)16 the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the. 29th May, 1939, Reference to previous correspondence it.h '&lt;11 7? , Bushire memorandum No. C/181 of the 20th'May, 1939. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. % Letter No. C/243 dated t'he 29th May, 1939, to the Chancery, British Embassy, Baghdad. Amount advanced to Solicitor Abdul Jalil Partu.By Air Mail. CONFIDENTIAL Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by M ail. cbUx-^J' •' A The FiTlUt^ll OLUBtaij, Qo¥oi»nmont^ India. The Political H^Mihont in tin. PeibitHT'O nil'. 3681?. Z. 3345/39. {'®&gt; Enclosure In Foreign Office CoTering Note No.E. 3776/39/93, dated 86 th May, 1939. \ &gt;n Y 3&gt; NO. 830 (109/42/39) His Majesty’s Charge d*Affaires at Bagdad presents his compliments to H.M’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embassy, Bagdad. 12th May, 1939. —-rvA»* ' ! Reference to previous correspondence: Bagdad despatch No. 183 dated 20th April 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Basra despatch No .8 of 29th April 1939, (without enclosure,. 2. Basra despatch No.10 of 6 th ay, 1939. Subject. Shaikh of Koweit’s properties in Iraq. 3. Bagdad despatcn No.15 of 12th May, 1939.Enclosure No. 1 in Bagdad Despatch No.230 of 12/5/39. Cq&gt; No. 8 , British Consulate Basra 29th April, 1939 Sir, With reference to your despatch No*13 (109/37/39) of 20th April regarding the attachment by the local Authorities of certain properties belonging to the Shaikh of Koweit, I have the honour to report that the latter's son Shaikh Mohammed, called here on my invitation on April 25th and gave me the following information;- 2. The tenants of the shops in Fao were instructed by the Mudir not to pay any more rent to the Shaikh* s Agents, Various fellaheen on the Feddaghiya estate were evicted and their places filled by fellaheen from Fao, Feddaghiya, and it is said, Tran. Four of these new tenants were men who had some time ago been evicted by the Shaikh from the estate under court orders. Others were persons holding papers from the Zuhair family from whom the Shaikh bought part of the Feddaghiya properties. The Taabs were not disturbed in their possession, but both they and the fellaheen were told that the property had been attached by Government and that they had nothing more to do with the Shaikh or his Agent. On April 21st Shaikh Mohammed sent his agents, one Fahad to Fao. The orders fojr the attachment were still in force. 3* On April 26th I called on All Mahmoud A1 Shaikh the Mutasarrif of Basra and asked him whether the properties in question were still being held for non-payment of taxes. I told him T understood that the Iraq. Government had given instructions for their release pending the enactment of certain legislation and I asked whether any effect would be given to these instructions. W. E. Houstoun-Boswall, Esq., M.C. , H.M.Charge d*Affaires, British Embassy, Baghdad.4 The Mutasarrlf, who is a lawyer and notoriously yerhose, went into a long description of the case from the heginning* Certain taxes amounting to nearly ID,20,000 were due from the Shaikh and had not been paid. Iraqi landlords who had to pay their taxes complained to him that it was unjust that foreigners should he exempt, and great dissatisfaction had been caused in the neighbourhood by this discrimination. To alla^' this and to prevent further criticism he had pretended to have the properties attached but this attachment had never been given any legal effect. He then produced a letter from the Tapu Department in which he was asked for Court fees which he said he had not paid and without which the attachment could not legally be enforced. 5 . I replied that whether the attachment was legal or illegal, the practical effect was the same. I repeated what Shaikh Mohammed had told me whereupon he became very excited and embarked on a long and irrelevant diatribe against what he described as the harsh treatment meted out to Iraqi fellaheen on the estates. He went on to say that he was trying to have justice done and that if he were interfered with he had better return to his legal practice in Baghdad and let the Shaikh of Koweit come and rule Basra. I again informed him that I was seeking information on one point only viz. was the attachment still in force or was it not and that there did not appear to be much justice in throwing out the Shaikh’s fellaheen who had presumably already done work on the land# 6 . The Mutasarrlf then complained that no person appeared to have any power of attorney from the Shaikh of Koweit and asked me to ascertain from Shaikh Mohammed whether he was his father’s accredited agent. 7# On 27th April I returned to the Mutasarrif* a office with Shaikh Mohammed who produced the Power of Attorney, of whicha copy is enclosed herewith. On examining this the Mutasarrlf again went off at a tangent and complained that while it gave Shaikh Mohammed power to attack Iraqi tenants in court nobody could proceed against him as the Power of Attorney contained no clause for service on him of an Iraqi had a claim or an attachment against him* 8 * I said I would mention his argument but that the Shaikh of Koweit was an independent ruler, that I was not prepared as a Consular Officer to enter into any arguments as to his rights and that I considered that such questions were better thrashed out between the Embassy and the Iraq Government* After a few more long speeches on nothing in particular the Kutasarrlf said that he would give Shaikh Mohammed a letter to the Kalmakan of Abu Khassib asking the latter to instruct the local Authorities at Pao and Feddigiyen to facilitate the re-entry of the haikh of Koweit*® agent into possession. He asked that Shaikh Mohammed should provide this agent with a proper Power of Attorney. Shaikh Mohammed agreed to this and promised to let me know how he got on, 9. I could obtain no guarantee from the Mutasarrlf that the evicted tenants would be allowed to return. I think this point is important, as the presence of the nominees of the local uthorities may cause the Shaikh constant trouble and possibly invite further interference by the i utasarrlf and his henchmen* The latter no doubt feel that the methods applied in the Judetenland might with advantage be used at Feddigiyeh* 10, Shaikh Mohammed gave me the following details which of course I cannot verify but which may be of interest. Certain of the fellaheen put in by the local authorities to replace those of the shaikh of Koweit have been asked to subscribe money for the Mudir to pay the Kalmakam of Abu Khassib* One man’s share was 500 fils which he raised by selling his last two goats* The Mudir of Fao is also said to have been bribed. This man was Mudir of Rumaitha in 1937 where he is said to have been the cause of riots* 11 ./— 11* The Mutasarrlf mentioned that when he was Minister of Justice the case of the Zuhair family versus the Shaikh of Koweit was brought to his notice. Inspite of his attempts to 'have justice done' no effect could be given to the decision against the haikh owing to the Diplomatic support which he had received* It is probably only a coincidence that dalman al Shawaf the lawyer representing the Zuhair family is, according to dhaikh Mohammed, a relative of the utasarrif * 1?* At our last interview the latter said that he would prove to me by producing his confidential instructions, that he was doing more than he was supposed to do, but that he would have to ask me not to mention what these instructions were, I said that I could not undertake to refrain from reporting any information that caiie into my possession and I would prefer not to see the letter* I have, etc., Sgd. D.F.H. BRICK-ELL, H. M. Consul,Enclosure No* 2 in Bagdad Despatch No*230 Of 12/5/39. No.10* British Consulate Basra 6 th Way, 1939* Sir With reference to my despatch No *8 of 29th \pril 1939 regarding the property of the Shaikh of Koweit at Pao and Feddigiyeh, I have the honour to report that Shaikh . ohammed called here today. 2. He stated that he had called on the Mutasarrif about the beginning of the week and found him very courteous and helpful. Having examined the powers of attorney which Shaikh Mohammed had drawn up for the use of his agent the Mutasarrif gave him an official letter to the Kaimakam of Abu Khassib* Shaikh Mohammed presented this letter and was treated with great consideration, being even invited to lunch. The Kaimakam telephoned the Mudlr of Fao and ordered him to facilitate the entry of the Shaikh’s agents into the estates and to see that the latter were handed back to them* 3. Shaikh Mohammed then sent his agent accompanied by his own clerk and a lawyer’s clerk to Fao. He did not go himself as there are heavy floods round Fao. The two clerks returned yesterday after having seen the Mudlr of Fao who told them they could take over the property. The Mudir in answer to an enquiry stated that certain of the fellaheen who had been evicted were men of bad character. 4. He stated in conversation that the case of the Zuhair family versus the Shaikh of Koweit (referred to in paragraph 11 of my despatch unaer reference; is being heard by the Court of Appeal, Baghdad on May 11th. I have, etc*, W.E.Houstoun-Boswall, Esq., MC. , Charge d'Affaires, British Embassy, Baghdad. Sgd* D. F. H. BRICKE1X H.M. Consul.Enclosure No. 3 in Bagdad Despatch No.230 of 12/5/39. No# 15. i 109/ 42/39 ) British Embassy, Bagdad. 12th May, 1939 Sir I am grateful for the information concerning the attachment of certain of the properties in Iraq of the Shaikh of Koweit, contained in your despatches No. 9 of April 29th and No. 10 of May 6 th. the iutasarrlf to instructions which the Prime Minister tells me he sent to him on May 4th. 3 . I shall be glad if you will keep me informed of further developments. 4 . I am sending copies of this despatch and of your despatches Nos. 8 and 10 to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and to the Political Agent, Koweit. 2 . I attribute the recent change in the attitude of I am, e tc. , Sgd. W.E. Houstoun-Boswall. His Majesty’s Consul, BASRA.; a 1 CONFIDENTIAL. \ ^ ■ !\ &gt;iU' No. 520-3 (S 1 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty # s Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. 2* The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla* 3. His Majesty's Ambassador, British Embassy, Baghdad. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (3* lat June 1139# British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : ^ Bushire Printed Letter lo»^/222 dated the 25th May 1935• Description of Enclosure. Name and Date \ • (Jopy of trani of ;raaflatlon &lt; letter dated the 11th lay 1939 from Advocate Abdul Jalll lartu, Ba.ihdadf to Shaikh Muhammad al Ahnad as Jubuh, Basrah* Subject. Date . Gardens of the Shaikh of Kuwait* / y Copy forwarded with compliments to The Poll tical Agent, Kuwai t. with reference to his Printed Letter No.C/233 dated the 19th May 1939.• ..w tv 2 - •• [{ *r Telegram - r From To Repeated to - H.R’s Ami) ass a lor, Baghdad. Political Resident, Bushire. Mo. 41 Foreign Office, London. Wo. 220 Political Agent, Kuv/ait. Po. 23. Dated the 9th and received the 10th June, 1939. Py telegram Wo. 39, On June 7th Court of Cassation gave judgment referring FA. case to Land Settlement. Have you been able to recover fees from the Sheikh'’ “ Mr. Hew ton -Telegram - R 7rom - Political A.gent, Kuwait. To - Political Resident, Pushire No. - C/253. Dated, the 10th June, 1939. Baghdad, telegram No. 41 of June 9th to you. 4 y 1 ■ Fees recovered and sent to Ambassador via Basra June 6th. (f-h - Political -tmmmmrsmmstmm HIS Majesty’s Ambassador a t Bagdad presents his compliments to the Political Agent at Koweit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embas sy. Bag.dad .....26th..May , 193.9.. Reference to previous corregfiondence : Bagdad despatch No. 109/42/39 dated 12th May, 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. . _ _ . i Subject. v . ( 5 ° /p Bagdad despatch No.249 Properties in Iraq of the dated 26th May, 1939, to the Foreign Office,London. Shaikh of Koweit. 0 &lt;y'-j r f JU.Mz Ik British Consul&amp;ta Basra. 19th May f 1939. ' r ith reference to my despatch Pfo .10 of 6 th May regarding certain property of the Shaikh of Koweit at .fao and Peddigiyeh, T have the honour to report that been re-instated in possession of all the property at both places. He said that for the moment the position was satisfactory but that the real test would coaie when the date crop was ready for harvesting as he was apprehensive that attempts might be made to cheat the thaikh of his just dues. His lawyer in Bagdad has no doubt informed you that the latest judgment in the Iraq Court in the dispute over certain of the 3 eddlglyeh property has been given against the shaikh. Shaikh Mohammed has now informed me that hio agents have I have etc (3gd.) D.P.H. Brickell H. Consul Houstoun-Boswall, ^sq. f Chargfe d 1 Affaires, uritish Embassy, Bagdad .Telegram ^rom r IAI i No 0 m 0 Political Resident, Busdire. Political \gent, Tu^ait. No. Dated and received the 13th June, 193 Q . Tf y telegram No. 108/T, May 27th and Baghdad despatch No. 249, Tiay 26th to foreign Office, copy to you. . u Please confirm from Shaikh that an properties attached have 'been released a] him to explain contradiction hetv/een his report and his own. 9 - Resident *1 7Prom - Political \gent, Kuv;ait. To - Politi-- 1 lesi :anu, Pushire No. - 0/257 Dr ted the 17th Dane, l n 3°. 325 of Jane 13th. 2. Full report from fhaikh has delayed hut it appears that it is only the agents who have 'been reinstated vide fonsul ^asra letter &gt;T o. 11 ,of ' r ay 19th and not the fellahin. Dmhassy's Letter !To 2^9 of M ay 26th therefore seems to overstate the matter. 3. I will send further report as soon as possible. - Politioal tgent -By Air Mail. P.Z.jWrf 19 l&lt;\ FI n :-:xt7al INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.INDIA OFFICE, P&gt;Z.3445/39 10 th une, 1939 I enclose a —QZ-21 7date cf 24 th May) which, at first 'blush, suggests that the As you will see, he draws a distinction 'between the ,f heirs of Mubarak and ’’members of the dheikh's family other than the heirs of Mubarak', and points out that the taxation figures on which compensation has been assessed relate to property in the possession of both classes; if the term 'heirs' is to be strictly interpreted ('descendants', by the way, is the word used in the English version of the 1914 pledge) then the basis of the assessment will have to be revised by deducting taxation on the property of the 'non-heirs'. It will undouotedly be awkward, as he soys, to have to go back to the bheikh on this matter, and if the distinction now ^ drawn by Fowle is a real one, it is very unfortunate that amount of compensation offered to the Sheikh of Koweit on account of losses suffered by the taxation of his date I garaens in Iraq has been over-assessed on a faulty basis. the point was not cleared up before. H.L.Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office, 3 • W • 1 « 2 /2 . © 4 ^ &lt; 2 ^ 2 . After looking into the matter however, we are of opinion that the 'basis on which compensation has been calculated is in conformity with the spirit of the pledge of 1914. Some light is thrown on the question in the descriptions of the date gardens which were supplied 'by the Political Agent in 1932 and 1934 and you may find it useful to refer to these. (See Bushire memoranda r Tp hr W y No. 651-S of the 12th September 1932 aid Nor 1087-S of the 24th November 1934, copies sent to the foreign Office with India Office letters No. P.2.5707/32 of the 23rd September 1932 and P.Z. 7729/34 of the 21st December, 1934). We are concerned only with five properties, the Mutaawa’ah, Paddaghiyeh, Ujairawiyeh, Parhaniyeh and fao estates. The first three do not now concern us, since they are stated to be owned solely by the heirs of Mubarak, the Parhaniyeh estate is said to be divided physically between heirs and non-heirs. It appears to be small and comparatively unimportant. The Pao estate, the largest of all, is not divided up but numbers of non—heirs as well as of heirs are reputed to have an interest in it. Both estates were in the possession of the Sheikh’s family for many years (at least 40 and 80 respectively) before 1914 so that it is probable/pro'ba'ble that Mubarak then shared his interest in them with others; hut these others were presumably all members of the family. The system of administration v/as described in para. 6-^5f (Annexure II of the 1934 papers referred to above in these words: 'Prom earliest times it had been an axiom in the policy of the various Rulers of Koweit, to themselves manage, for internal political reasons, the Pao estate on behalf of the family as a whole and pay out monthly salaries to individuals instead. This gave them that control over the various members and branches of the family which is necessary in an Eastern Kingdom, as it enabled the Rulers to keep the family united in the face of pressure and danger from without.' There has been discussion in the past as to whether the 1914 pledge applied to 1914 property which passed subsequently out of the possession of the 'descendanis' by sale, gift, marriage or otherwise. But although the facts, at any rate as regards the Pao estate, have been generally known for years there has not, I think, been any suggestion hitherto that the pledge applied only to date gardens which belonged to Mubarak personally in 1914 and did not extend to the whole of the Pao estate,/sTl, 4. estate, i.e. to the date gardens which were then under his control and administered hy him* This latter interpretation seems to us reasonable; there can he little doubt, that it is what Mubarak himself understood the pledge to moan; and both on the merits of the case and because matters have already gone so far with the Sheikh we very much hope that you and the Treasury will agree that the basis on which we have been working need not be disturbed. 4. It is impossible to deduce from the information available in Fowle’s letter what would be the financial result of applying a rigorous distinction between 'heirs” and 'non-heirs”. In addition to a reduction in the amount of compensation for taxation losses to be paid to the Sheikh there would also of course be a reduction in the presently accepted extent of His Majesty’s Government’s liability to compensate the Sheikh in the event of his being dispossessed of the Fao and Parhaniyeh estates. 5* I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Wright.Translation of copy of letter dated 31st May 1939 from Shaikh Muhammad al Ahmad as-Subah, Basrah, to the British Consul, Basrah. After Compliments. You are undoubtedly aware that when I met H.E.the Mutasarrif and both of us agreed to the arrangements which are known to you, he gave me a letter to the Qaimmakam of Abul Khasib who, in turn, gave our agents a letter to the Mudir of Fao Nahiya. The Agents went to Fao and delivered the letter to the Mudir of that Nahiya. When the Mudir read the letter he told my agent that he can recover the rents and also informed the tenants to pay the rents to my agent, but he continued putting his hand on the meat and fish markets without any reason. I, therefore, submitted a petition to the Qaimmakam of Abul Khasib on 23/5/39 in that respect and requested him to instruct the Mudir of S'ao Nahiya to raise his hand from the meat and fish markets and to hand them over to us with their rents. The petition was forwarded to the Mudir of Fao bmt I have not received any reply so far. As regards our properties in Faddaghiya, our agent proceeded to that place but remained in his house as he could not go out lest he may have any trouble with the fellahin who were appointed by the Mudir of Fao at the time of the seizure of the properties. I tried on several occasions to turn those fellahin out and to re-instate our previous fellahin but the Mudir of Fao objected to that and instigated the new fellahin to oppose us and to disregard our orders. No doubt the presence of those fellahin/-- 2 - fellahin in our properties contrary to our wish, will create a lot of difficulties for us. It would, therefore, be desirable to have them turned out and our own re-instated so that there may further trouble in future# Usual Ending.Translation of letter dated 30th Babi Thaniral35Q( 18-6-39) from. Shaikh Muhammad al Ahmad as-Subah, Basrah, to H.H»Shaikh Sir Ahmad al Jabir as-Subah,KCIB # ,CSI#, Ruler of Kuwait. After Compliments. I left Basrah on Wednesday .and visited our properties at Mutawwa^ and Faddaghiyah. I found the new fellahin,put in by the Mudir of Fao Nahiya in place of our old fellahin, doing harmful acts to the properties such as leaving the animals to go about in the properties, and, in addition to that, they are neither looking after the properties nor preserving them against damage by water etc. No doubt the presence of the said new fellahin, who are not obeying our orders, contrary to our wish, will be harmful to the properties. All this is, of course, due to the Mudir. I wi^t to Fao in the afternoon, visited Governmant officials and invited them to lunch on Friday. After lunch I discussed with the Mudir about the matter but he started quibbling. Sir, the harm done by the Mudir did not affect Faddaghiya only but had its effect on our Fao properties also, as during my stay of 4 days at Fao I understood that the Mudir was instigating the farmers of Fao to send petitions to the Government and claim one half and one quarter of the properties, according to papers in their possession. They actually sent in petitions to the Government at the instigation of the Mudir whose presence in Fao has become a sources of trouble for us. Usual EndingGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. . — Department. EXPRESS LETTER V. B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.) In continuation of my telegram No. 0/257 of the 17th Muhammad in Basra. It will he seen from the letters that the Shaikh^ agents have 'been reinstated at Fao and Faddaghiya. It is not actually stated that the Shaikh’s agent has Been reinstated at Muttawa hut His Highness the Shaikh informs me that the agent has heen reinstated there. 2. It will also he seen that the meat and fish markets at Fao have not heen handed over to the Shaikh’s agents. 3. The necessity for the reinstatement of the Shaikh’s fellahein is amply brought out hy Shaikh Muhammad. Confidential From Political Agent, Kuwait To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire No. 0/260 Dated 2 i s -fc June, 193 9 Shaikh of Kuwait’s properties in Iraq A • June, 1939, I enclose translations of two betters from Shaikh Political Agent Kuwait.7 4 L a^ 1 ^ CONFIDENTIAL Kturn it Receipt Bagdad 17th June, 1939 Dear Agency, ^ ' Your letter No. C/243 of 29th ultimo. We thank you for the cheque of ID.202/000 and enclose herewith our official receipt for the amount. Yours ever CHANCERY The Political Agency KOWEITNo. 109/51/59 . % H CO -V ; ’ ' STIAL 73 HIS Majesty’s Ambassador a t Bagdad presents his compliments to the Political Agent at Koweit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Embassy.., Bagdad. Reference to previous correspond^ :h No. 109/44/39 date Description of Enclosure. , 193.9, • ia Bagdad despatch No. 109/44/39 dated 26th May, 1939 Name and Date. Jo. 277 Bagdad despatch No.277 of 10th June, 1939, to the foreign Office, London. Subject. Shaikh of Koweit’s properties in Iraq. (P. n K-a-y it, pjOi.ncloeuro Ho. 1 in bagdad despatch N o. 277 of 10.6.39. -teKlgtered . No. 12. British Consulate, Basra. let June, 1939. Sir i t 1 have the honour^tp report that on receipt of Your excellency’s telegraiu No. S of May 29th regarding tne property of the Shaikh of Koweit, 1 requested Shaikh Mohammed to call and see me. 2 . he came here yesterday and I informed him of the tenour of the statement made by hia father to the Political Resident and aaKed him for an explanation. I reminded him that on 19th May he had declared that hia agents had been re-instated in possession of the properties at Feddigiyeh and Pao, so I could only presume that either he had not reported this to the haikh or that the latter was under some misapprehension. I finally asked him to write a report on the present position of the case ao that tnere would be no further misunderstandings one way or another. A copy of JU f ^ hie letter togetner with a translation it enclosed herewith. 3. The Fish and eat . arkct referred to was built by the Port Authorities to replace an old insanitary market which had previously occupied the site. At our laat interview Shaikh Mohammed said that he expected it would shortly be handed over to his agent. 4. He mentioned too that he had been told by some Judge in Basra that the a^tac^ment referred to in paragraph 4 of my despatch No. 8 of 89th April had not been cancelled or withdrawn although it was not being given any practical effect. /ItIt would of course clarify the situation if this court order - ,, fafce , * or not - could be cancelled as while it is still in existence there ie always the to ;jptation for the local authorities to act on it to the prejudice of the dhaikh. More important however, is the failure of the authoritiae to allow the ex-employees of the Shaikh to return to their holdings. I do not know whether diplomatic representation o n this point would be advisable or whether I should again take the matter up wi^ ' ~ *^ ^ ~ _ my last attempt to right this injustice is as completely unsuccessful. reported in paragraph I have etc. , (Sgd. ) D.F.H. Brickell, H.M. Consul.Translation * Letter dated Slat May f 1939 from Shalich Mohammed al iiraad-al- 8 abah to H. B.M’s Consult Basra. • •••••••••a flth respects f The outcome of our interview with the ^uiaaarrlf and the arrangements agreed to by him are well Known to you. The Mutasax*rif gave me a letter to the ^aimiaaQam Abul Khasib* and the Qaimmagam in turn sent our agents with a letter to the liudlr of Fao Rahiya. Our agents # therefore f went to /ao with the letter from the aimuiagam and delivered it to the i;udlr of Fao* After perusing this letter the .ludir of Fao told our agents that they were at liberty to collect rents from our properties, and likewise ordered the different lessees to pay the rents due to our agents. The only exception made is in the case of Fish and Meat Markets without any reason. I, under the circumstances, wrote a letter to the Qalgimaqam t Abul Khaasib on the 23rd May 1939 on the subject requesting him to in truet the Mudlr of Fao Nahiya to deliver the Fish and Meat Market as well to our agent with the rents realised. I have likewise written to the Mudlr of Fao Rahlya, but so far have received no reply. As regards our estate at Feddigiyah, our agent went there as arranged, but finds himself in adverse circumstances, and therefore is afraid to leave his house in case he is siolested by the Fallehln installed therein by the Mudlx* Nahiya when the properties were attached. We have tried our best to eject thes&lt; F allahln with a view to replace them by our old Fallahin * but oi no avail. Mudlr Nahiya objects to this being done. The result is that these new F allahin do not care for us or for our orders and consequently their existence in our properties is detriment* to our interests. The best thing, therefore, is that these Fallahin be turned out from our property, and our old Fallahin re-instated for our future good. In the end please accept my best respects. Yours sincerely, Sd. Mohammed-al-Ahmad-al-Sabah.Enclosure Ho. 2 in Ba; iio- SZZ a spatch li th June, 1949* ijr a#^r 1 venture to l&amp;vofco Tour .uceelieno/’s porse&amp;el b*±p for the Otfurljr enh iimU. setUo&amp;^etit of the trouOlo&amp;ooo oftolr of the ottodkeemt of eortoia yraportiee to ^a»ra belonging to the .&amp;&amp;!*&amp; of i.oeoit. inforaou tr» houetoon^^ooeeli thnt the lt%qX Authorities concerned hod given orders for these otteohMnts to be oeneelled end lor the properties to be restored to the unfettered control of the uhnifch* A fee dejrs ego, in epite of four assurance to i-r* Houetoun^toeeall # 1 received e report from ..oeeit that the local authorities of the Basra Ilea were atill interfering in the haiich , » control of these properties. i thereupon ashed our Consul at Basra to send m a report oa the eituatlen. After ftahing eareful eaauiriea* the ;ga«ul Inforaec m that the kudlr of &gt;ao continues to refuse to allow the Mialfch*s agent te re-eetsbllsh in it la tamseeea&amp;ry far ne to recapitulate the facte which axe already tm^Si inr to fc/Ur uce X will oalr recall that* so lvn&amp; ago as ^aich hi# &amp;.«CgU»£ftC¥ aixm KWi^Ah^hAih* a.c.v.c. *3479 15099 (4) J. Wo. 117/64/39 . to S'** /TV (loN (IZO HIS Majesty’s Ambassador at Bagdad presents his compliments to the Political Agent at Koweit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Emt&gt;a.9.8y.* Bagdad... a u 1.3th. June , 1939. Reference to previous correspondepeTlP Bagdad telegram No. 23 of June 9th, 1939. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. A &gt;. 2 &amp;£ Bagdad despatch No.288 of 13th June, 1939, to the Foreign Office, London. Subject. Shaikh of Kcwei^s properties in Iraq. 0 . 4 Lm - MrItlan vauasay, -iagduda I3t)i vTun 0 9 19^9. Ur Of A, ^, r. flth r«f«r#noe to ay tolegr** 9o.22Q of June 9th f I have the honour to transmit to Your tordahlp herewith a translation of the Judgment of the Court of Caenatlon referring the Faddagiilyah oaae to the president of the land Jettlea&amp;nt Committee In the Fao ? ahiy&amp;h. II* X am sending copies of this despatch and Its enclosure to the Political Heuldent In the 4 eralan Gulf and to the Political Agent, 1.0 we it. 1 have the honour to be with the highest respect, My cord, Your Lordship’s most obedient, humble cervant. The dlght honourable The Viscount Halifax, !-• 0. , G. C. C. 1. , G# C* X. JK. ,ENCLOSURE IN FOREIGN OFFICE COVEBINQ letter o*teo _ __ ^2 JIM r mi* (S 43^7/39/93). (117/68/39) BHITI .H BMBA8UY, My dear Baxter, I enclose a short note by Holt on the present position of the Faddsghiyah eppeol case. If our last device fails, it will be a very difficult mutter to prevent execution of the judgment given against the ihaikh. v. «• Baxter, KBq.-poaLt (S 4327/39/93) fflc /addughlyah, rp jrertj;,..o £ &lt; ? n i l _. S ; a 8 jj|.t I learn privately that the position is et present as follows* When application was made for the appeal to he considered under .Article 7 (ll) of the Courts Proclamation of December, 917, and the necessary fees (f^OO) were paid (our telegrams to the Foreign Office hos. 166 and 2o0) f the President of the Court of Cassation sent instructions to Basra for the other side to be served with notification of this application. Up to Wednesday, May 3lst, this had not been doxie but efforts are being made to hasten process. When service has been effected, the other side have eight days in which to reply before further action can be taken by the Court. Meanwhile, a determined movement is apparently being started in t),e Court of Cassation against the thesis that the ordinary courts are barred altogether from hearing oases concerning land in an area declared a Land Settlement j rea. This is serious because it has all along been hoped that if the appeal could be brought before the Court (Land settlement having been declared in the Fao Kahiyah in which the ‘addaghiyah property is situated) the Court would x^asa it to Land Settlement and execution of the judgement against the Bheikh of oweit given in the Basra Court of First Instance Ins^ summer would be prevexited. The new theory which is being developed will, if adopted, also uraet our idea that new cases oaimot. be brought in the Court of First Iristance concerning land in a settleuent Area, though it seems doubtful whether it can in fact be carried thus far. The position regarding the Faddaghiyah appeal is very uncertain, and there are Judges who ©re working hard to find reasons for not passing the case to Land Settlement. There is, X gather, a similar case before the Court and much depends on how that goes.Baghdad, Iraq. 13th June, 1939. I acknowledge, Excellency's personal letter of the ; H)7) upon My dear Ambassador the subject of alleged obstruction by the Administrative authorities of the Basra Liwa to the agent of the Shalk of Kuwait as regards the return of his fellahin to the Faddaghiymh gardens and the collection of rents at Fao« initiated inquiries and as a result 1 have come to know that no approach whatever has been made by the Shaikh's Agent either to the Mutasarrif Basra, the ^aln&amp;aqam of Abul uhasib or the Mudir of Fao in the matters in which interference is alleged. troubled on the subject of the Bhaikh'of Kuwait's propex^ilea in Iraq and 1 reaffirm the assurances given to Mr* Houetoun- Boswall last March. the Llwa authorities to ensure to the Bhaikh his full legal rights, and it is requested that, in the event of the Shaikh's Agent encountering any difficulties, he should immediately make representations to any of the administrative authorities referred to in paragraph 1 above. Immediately upon receipt of your letter, 1 1 regret that Your Excellency should have been Most definite instruetlone have been conveyed to My dear Ambassador, Yours sincerely, (Sgd) Moury Said. His Excellency Sir Basil 0. hewton, K.O.M.a., H.B.M's Ambassador, aACHBAu) .P. Z. 3938/39. (E.4235/39/H3J. inclosure in Mr. Ba^gallay^ Covering Note, dated 22nd June, 1939. FOREIGN OFFICE, o.W.l, 23rd June, 1939. Dear Wright, Will you please refer to Peel’s letter V.Z.3445/39 of 10th June to me about compensation for Istihlak tax on date gardens in Iraq? . ^ 2. You will have seen from thl^letter that tae Political Kesiuent has suggested that the amount of compensation offered to the oheikh of Koweit on account of losses suffered by the taxation of his date gardens in Iraq may have been over-assessed on a faulty basis, and that it may therefore be thought necessar to revise the basis of the assessment for compensation by deducting therefrom the amount of taxation on the property of members of the Sheikh’s family other than the heirs of Sheikh ubarak. ' w 3. We agree with the India Office, that whatever the right view to take of this problem may be, it would from the political point of view be most unfortunate if we had at this stage to tell tne Sheikh that we had now decided to offer a smaller sum than that originally calculated. Ve have gone so far with him that I feel it would be a mistake to turn back now if it could possibly be avoided. To uo so would cause great offence and, as you know, we are anxious t^at the matter should be disposed of without further delay and without leaving behind it any feelings of unjust treatment. 4. At tiie same time, the arguments in paragraph 3 of Peel’s letter seem to us to be sound and we agree that the basis on which compensation has been calculated is in conformity at least/ (s&lt;? S.H.Wright, Esq., Treasury.2 . least with the spirit of the pledge given to Sheikh Mubarak in 1914. 5. We very much hope therefore that all concerned will * feel able to decide that the Koweit assessments should be allowed to stand. But I do not tnink that it in any case affects the ohelkh of ohai ierah’s heirs. The compensation wnicn we are offering them is calculated according to the taxation ratio of their estates during certain years to the estates of the heirs of Jheikh ! ubarak. The fact that these estates may be now found to belong to slightly different people than we thought does not alter the ratio. Yours sincerely, bgd. John Colville, (for L. Baggallay;.CON FIT) i STIMs Knn'oic JU.dj l GOVERNMENT OF .INpJ^.^ n &lt;ueJ 1 Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N. B, This is an ORIGINAB MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To Political Resident, Bushire, Political Agent, Kuwait, r kOL * No. 643-S of 1939 Dated 12th July 1939 ti&amp;tx.. Subject* Shaikh of Kuwait*s date gardens in ’Iraq. Reference correspondence ending with letter dated 13th June 1939 from the Prime Minister, ’Iraq, to Sir Basil Newton, copy sent to you by Embassy, Baghdad, 2, Please let me know how the matter stands. Have the Shaikh’s fellaheen been reinstated ? 3* The situation in regard to the Shaikh’s ownership of Faddaghiyah is, for the moment, satis- -factory as the result of the decision of the Court to transfer the case to the X»and Settlement Committe 4 /vide s. 6 . ifFP—1196 SAP—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.' 2 * So. 1 = S' r vide Baghdad telegram No» 41 (Bo*23 to you), dated 9th June 1939. Please impress on the Shaikh that he should take no step in regard to the property without reference to you, other- -wise we may have a repetition of the upsetting of the apple cart consequent on the Shaikh*s telegram to the Basrah Court (vide Baghdad telegram Xo TO &lt;7 No .6 to Poreign Office (No.2 to Kuwait) dated 13th January 1938 and connected correspondence). You can remind the Shaikh tactfully of this incident. / sd/- T.C.Fowle Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTKSTj&amp;D. »r Secretary to tne Political Resident in the Persian Gulf-. rs~*••« '■ • ''-J 1 ^ ,l| . 'J |I&gt;T ''~—~~ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Confidential, [N.B. —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition os if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature if a responsible officer of the Department.] No. C/281. To Political Agency, Kuwait. Bated Simla m&amp;i' the 20th July, r Ncw &amp;flhi 19 39- Political .Resident in tJie Persian Grulf, Busnire. Subject: - Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens in Iraq.* /Ho • V Reference y — h ¥% Express Letter No, 643-S of the 12th July, 1939, Tour paragraph 2. The Shaiich imorms me that a nuhber of the fellahein have been reinstated, but I will let you have a full report later, 3. r Your paragraph 3. The Shaikh fully understands and has firmly stated, that he will take no action without first consulting us. Political Agent, Kuwait. &amp;fe, sQUUi, , rBy Air Mail. F.Z. 10;^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to grWs by ^ - r Mail. ■; A /l Tho Foyuii;!! 0uJielai&gt;, Govermn^tit ofd^frdia. The Political Hesident ill the hersian-UJf. 3681P.Z.4348/39. S.32453/18. TESJiSUEY CEA13ERS, WHI'TSHiJiL, S.W.l. 12th July, 1939. Dear Peel, \ Would you hl'ease refer to your letter of 10 th ultimo, (P.3.344^/39) to Baggallay about the compensation 23rd ultimo on the same subject (copy of which I suppose has gone to you). for standing to what has already been said to the present Sheikh about the amount of the compensation, irrespective of the merits of the case, but we should like to size up the merits separately first. If a good case on merits can be made out, then we are saved the necessity of considering the always disagreeable question of acquiescence or not in the results of a mistake. the word 'descendants 11 in the English translation of the 1914 pledge to Sheikh Mubarak covered 'non-heirs' as well as 'heirs', but your letter appears to make the question primarily one of 'ownership or administration'. In your second and third paragraphs you refer to the basis on which the property was actually administered in 1914 and you contend that Mubarak would have regarded the pledge as covering not only the gardens owned by him personally but also those owned separately or in combination by his family but controlled and administered by him. Mow that Mubarak himself is dead, his actual area of ownership or administration would appear to be no longer relevant but I take your contention to be that, if the 1914 pledge covered Mubarak’s area of administration as well as his for the Sheikh of Koweit, and Colville’s letter to me of t ;/e realize that there may be strong arguments The question raised by Fowle is primarily whether . T .Peel Esq., M. C *, India Office. area/2. r^V area of actual ownership, so it should he regarded as covering also such area as is actually administered by the present heirs. That seems the most that could he claimed on that line of reasoning. I gather from your letter and its enclosures that the Fao estate is in fact administered hy the present heirs just as it was hy Sheik Mubarak in 1914. The share of the non-heirs in the Farhaniyeh estate apparently is not, hut you say that estate is an all and comparatively unimportant. This point, i.e. whether the 1914 pledge covered gardens in the administration of Mubarak as well as those owned hy him, seems a primary one. The word used in the English translation of the pledge is 'possession'. As there seems to he no talk in the file of reference hack beyond the translation to the Arabic original when points are in dispute, I take it that no copy of the original Arabic pledge was made or that it is now no longer extant. But as the present question is one of compensation for tax liability, the incidence of the tax on the property owned ^ hy the non-heirs but administered by the heirs should presumably bo the guiding consideration. It would seem to be implicit in any reasonable claim by the heirs for compensation in respect of the tax in past years on the property administered (but not owned) by them that they had in fact finally paid the tax on the administered property. Equally it should be implicit in the inclusion of compensation for the future in respect of the administered property that the heirs should continue to pay the tax on it. Alternatively in either case the heirs should hand out to the non-heirs the proportionate share of the latter in the capital payment made as compensation//Tjs, J&amp;lr 3. irtf compensation. Is it known v/hat tho position is in this rcspoct? If the problem is to be looked at from the angle, as suggested in your letter, of ownership or administration, tho question whether TT desccndants ,T covered non-heirs as well as heirs would become secondary. But the latter question would still have scope as regards that part of the Farhaniyeh estate owned by the non-heirs which is not administered by the heirs. And the whole problem can still be looked at from this angle, rather than from that of ownership or administration. Here too I am assuming that we cannot now ascertain the true meaning of the Arabic word in the 1914 pledge which is rendered 'descendants 11 in the English version. There was I find some discussion in 1929 on the use of 'descendante TT in the English version, but it was as regards its use instead of the more usual term - according to Colonial Office letter 68214/2$ of 11th October, 1929 - 'successors',. The Foreign Office in a letter E.5244/125 of 19th idem said that 11 descendants' would appear only to include the actual heirs of the Sheikh r s body. (There is no mention of looking up the Arabic word). The word used in the English translation of the pledge to the Sheikh of Mohammerah is 'heirs', and prima facie one would have expected the same word* or words with the same meaning, to be used to the two Sheikhs in 1914. The letter to Sheikh Mubarak containing the pledge to him says in fact that 'I have addressed a letter to the Sheikh of Mohammerah similar to this I am writing you'. 'Heirs' is the basis on which the question of compensation in the Mohammerah case is being approached. the question is to be decided from the angle/ In so far asangle of the meaning of 'descendants* 1 , it would seem also to be implicit, at least on merits, that the pon-heirs should get their appropriate share of the total compensation if that is assessed on their tax also, ''as otherwise the heirs receive an openly uncovenanted benefit. Finally we should bo grateful if you would enlighten us as to the distinction between heir descendants and non-heir descendants in this connection. Does the former mean descendants on the male side only or only some of those? I don T t know whether illegitimacy enters into the distinction in Arab conditions of life. I am sending a copy of this letter to Baggallay. Tours sincerely, (Sgd.) S.E.bright.TSL3GRAM - 'Q’\ F r om - Political iigent, Kuwait on recess at Karachi. To - Political Resident at Shiraz. No. K/l. Dated , — 6 th August 1939 j My express letter C/281 of 20 th July. Shaikh’s date-gardens. 2 . The situation is that(a)all Shaikh’s fellahin have returned except at Faddghiya and (b)meat and fish markets at Fao not returned to Shaikh’s control. Shaikh Muhammad informed me in Basra that he was making a representation to the Mutasarrif. I have not yet heard if result has been achieved but am expecting a letter from the Shaikh. GALLOWAYCONFIDENTIAL. No - ^305 of 1939. i vH The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• His Msjssty 9 * rabaseador, Bagdad* 2« His Majesty*s Jonaul, Basra* 3* His Majesty's Secretary of State for India* London* 4* Die Secretary to the vfeTernnient of India* External /iffairs Department* Simla* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^J^. British Com.ulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..7.t&amp;.*&gt;Uw.4e&amp;t..l5i£9.f. Ctop* shir as* Reft rence to previous correspondence: jM3 Letter dated the 13th June 1939 from the Iraqi srime sinister to His Majesty's iVmbaesador* Baidad* Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. fele^ram _ ui^ust 1939 /ro» the loll tisal /it* Kuwait* at Karachi• Copy forwarded* with compl Agent* Kuwait, a Subject. Bhalkh of Kuwait's date ijardens in Iraq* ments* to i Karachi e Political'% .Mft / HiLSGl^ai - n Q t » From - Political Agent, Kuwait, on recess at Karachi, To - Political Resident at Shiraz. No. - K/27. Dated - 19th August 1939. My telegram K/l of 6 th August. Shaikh informs me that meat and fish markets were returned to his control on 9th august. Situation regarding fellahin unchanged. -Galloway-CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/3B4 A'o / The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty's dtocretary of 'itute for Zndla» London* 2* Hie ujeaty'e ^isbaeaador 9 Bagdad. 3* The ^eoretary to the CSoveriicient of Xiidia in the External affaire iZepartmentf UiBla* 4* Hie Hajeaty'a doneul# iiaera* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). I- 1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. at Jiiraa* Dated K«».V. &amp;&amp; * Reference to previous correspondence: ^ Jb- ^7 i ^ r Reeidenoy Printed letter 0*^305 of 7th m^et X939# Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Kuwait tele grass ^*K/27 Kuwalt date garden«« of 19th August 1939* 7 ^opy forwarded with complimenta to Political Agent, Kuwait, / at Karachi, for information.p.z. 5955/39. INDIA OIT&amp;'-ICE, V/tUTEHA.T.D, S. V/. 1. ^Ist October, 1939&lt; C. t). Will you please refer to your letter ITo. S/ 3243 3/lQ of 12th July, regarding the Sheikh of Koweit's date gardens. 2. We have had made a translation of that portion of the Arabic version of the 1914 pledge -which is rendered in the English version as: 'that your gardens -which aro novr in your possession, viz. the date gardens situate between fho and Qurnah, shall remain in your possession or in ,^-v the possession of your descendants 'without being subject to the. payment of taxes or imposts'. The literal translation of the Arabic words used is: ,r Your gardens of date palms which are at this moment beneath the grasp of Your Honour, situate between Eao and Qurnah, shall remain in your control and the control of your successors without there being upon them anything of taxes and imposts'. We aro advised that the phrase 'beneath the grasp' appears etymologically to imply property of which the Sheikh had entered into personal possession by right of ownership, but the phrase 'in your control' ''-v appears to cover property over which the Sieikh or his successors exercised /absolute S.H. V/right Esq., Treasury, Whitehall, S. W. 1.- 2 - absolutc control mthout-noco&amp;sarily • enjoying'•personal oraioroliip-*- • Tlie- Arabic word w'hich has boon rondcrod as 'successors 1 ’ is aldhlaf (plural of khalaf). This moans, in the* first place, 'successors', and its cognato form 'khalf' is used in the Qur'an to moan 'succeeding generation' (of a community in a perfectly general sense) . When the word 'father' is ex pressly used (khalaf abihi) the word then comes to denote quite strictly 'son', in the sense that a son succeeds his father in the administration of his property. Dr. Arberry, who translated the Arabic for us, was not prepared to say whether in Mohammedan law the tern 'klahaf' can include descendants other than direct male issue, or political successors who are not necessarily related to the original owner. Incidentally we had better avoid using the terms 'heir' and 'non-heir', partly because they do not appear in either version of the 1914 pledge and partly because according to Mohammedan lav/- parents, grandparents and other older relatives are entitled to share in an inheritance. Thus their use may obscure the issues. It is quite possible that on the strict interpretation of the English version and to a lesser extent of the Arabic version of the 1914 pledge, the figure of £1,087, on the basis of which, we have calculated the payment to be made to the Sheikh in respect of future taxation, may include taxation on some property which was not covered by the pledge; o.g. property which, although controlled by Mubarak and by the present ' Sheikh, was not owned by Mubarak. On the other hand, the figure of £1,087 may conceivably not include taxation on some property which was covered by the pledge; e.g. property which was owned by Mubarak and which is /nowI or 'descendants 11 of Lfubarak other than the present Sieikh. 4. It seems clear that, partly by reason of the difference betrreen the Arabic and English versions of the pledge, and partly omng to our ignoranco of the precise legal position of some of the date gardens, any examination of the question ho 77 far the figure of £22,000 which has been offered to the Sheikh in compensation for future taxation is too high (taking the letter of the pledge as our criterion) TTOuld be likely to present considerable difficulties. V/o should have to rely largely upon the Sheikh for information as to the legal position of the gardens and as to the extent to which the application of the strict language of one or other version of the pledge would result in a revision of trie figure of £22,000. It is unlikely that the Sheikh would be very forthcoming, and it is certain that the controversy which would probably arise round the points at issue would make the conclusion of our negotiations with the Sheikh for the settlement of this tiresome dispute more difficult. The Sheikh would certainly contend that the sledge has hitherto boon treated as covering all gardens controlled by Mubarak and now controlled by himself. In this connection you Trill remember that our plan is to make the Sheikh a 'take it or leave it' offer of a fixed sum, the amount of which wo would refuse to discuss. If wc make /''V enquiries of the Sheikh at this stage on the points indicated, the Sheikh might soize the opportunity to bargain for a higher figure of compensation calculated on a different basis. In any case it seems doubtful whether /a9MW a strict application of the language of either of the t-yro versions of the pledge ttouIq result in a material reduction in the amount of compen sation to be paid to the Sheikh, and you TTill of course appreciate that the more delay there is in the settlement of the dispute, the bigger ndiLl bo the bill in respect of past taxation. V/e therefore hope that the Treasury v/ill agree that v/e may instruct tiie Political Eosidont in the Gulf to press his negotiations vith the Sheikh to a conclusion, -without suggesting any revision of the total figure of £22,000 already offered to him in compensation for future taxation. V/e are, however, ready, if you wish, and if the Foreign Office agree, to instruct the Political Eesident that, if ho thinks there is any foundation for a fear that the payment to the Sheikh ^22,000 in respect of future taxation might prejudice our freedom of action in the event of the Sheikh claiming, at some time in the future, compensation in respect of any loss of property which may not be covered by the strict language of the 1914 pledge, he should tell the Sheikh that it seems possible to us tliat the figure of £1,087, on the basis of -which that of £22,000 has been reached, may possibly include taxation on some property which is not covered by the strict language of the pledge, but tnac, in the interests of an amicable and speedy settlement, we do 2 iot propose to go into this point in respect of condensation for future taxation. 0 * As regards your apprehension that wo may be proposing to pay compensation to the Sheikh in respect of taxation payable by others than himself, the fi^iire of £ 1,087 is the annual average of the L-.' •: /taxationtaxation paid by merchants on dates exported by them from gardens under the Sheikh's control and of the taxation paid by the Sheikh's agent. Moreover you 7 h.ll recall that the Slieikh is being required to set up a family council to 7/iiich payment mil be made, and to give us a discharge on behalf, not only of himself, his heirs and successors, but of the 'other heirs of Sheikh Mubarak and their heirs'. Por the reason indicated at the end of paragraph 2. of this letter, ttc had bettor ask the Resident to alter the phrase 'heirs ' •whorover it appears in the suggested form of discharge to 'heirs and successors'. 7 . I am sending a copy of this letter to Baggallay. v O!fr*fli airto«*S%k (Sgd.) R. PEELs* By Air Mail. CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt . . No 2 0'5 Dated 33////Jy . INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. L ; A copy has been sent to by x^yJL. t* CLe. bv o—j- Mail.P.2.7107/59 S.W.l 14th iToverhoer s 1959 Would you please refer to Wright f s letter of the 10th November (No.S.52455/19) about the assessment of compensation for Iraqi taxation on the Sheikh of Koweit f s date gardens. We propose, if you agree, to instruct the Political Resident as in the second sentence of paragraph 5 of Peel ; s letter of the 51st October. a (Sgd.) j. p. GiBSOP# H. L. Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.l.By Air Mail. I ^ p.z. a INDIA OFFICE, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to | , Air ■ , .. b y si^ Maih 4hte- - ^ '/ . ® li-p lie ^ P.Z. 7268/39. INDIA OI'FTCE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1 . 27th November, 1939. Would you please refer to Fowle's letter No. C/217 dated the 24th May and connected correspondence resting with tne demi-official Treasury letter of the lOtlj^Hb-.^ November (a copy of which was forwarded to you by airmail on the 17th November) on the subject of taxation compensation in respect of the Koweit Date Gardens? I now enclose copy of further correspondence on this rr 4 -^— 1 - — * ^ xle P 0 ^ 11 ^ raised by Fowle it has been decided that it would compensation to be paid to the Sheikh. The proposal already made to the Sheikh therefore still stands. please take tne earliest favourable opportunity to press for the acceptance of the proposals of His Majesty's government, in accordance with the instructions which^were 4- T- \ U V)' given to Fowle in our Express Letter of-the 28th February before he raised the question of a revision of the amount phrase seems to come nearer the meaning of the pledge. Demi-official to Foreign Office 4 - ^ ^1 -IX t\ t , ^ -i- ^ ^ ^ dated 14th November,1939. ) subject with the Foreign Office. Demi ofxicial from Foreign Office dated 18th November,1939. ? / 2. You will have seen that ) after careful consideration of oe inadvisable to attempt a reassessment of the 3. 7/ill you accordingly, if you see no objection, of compensation. These instructions require, however, one or two modifications in the light of the recent correspondence with the Treasury, namely (i) In place of the term 'Mubarak's heirs' reference should be made to his 'heirs and successors', since this The Hon'ble. Lieutenant-Colonel C.G. Prior, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf2 . (ii) In informing the Sheikh of His Majesty’s Government’s desire to redeem their pledge to Mubarak and that in calculating the average annual loss from taxation for the years 1932-35, on which the proposed compensation for future taxation losses is based, it is possible that taxation of sane property which is not covered by the strict language of the pledge may have been included but that in the interests of an amicable a,nd speedy settlement His which he should set up to represent the heirs and successors concerned, and formal discharge for their liability for compensation for present and for those which may be experienced hereafter. The Sheikh ^ -^3 first condition (vide has been considered essential in order to avoid any miscarriage of the payments. As regards the second condition the Sheikh should be required to sign a discharge of our liability on behalf not only of himself, his heirs and successors, but of the other heirs and successors of Sheikh Mubarak to compensate his heirs and successors you should explain Majesty’s Government do not propose to go into this point in respect of compensation for future taxation. 4. The Sheikh has already been informed that His Majesty’s Government’s proposal is subject to two conditions, viz. (l) that payment shall be made to a Family Council (2) that he should give His Majesty’s Government a taxation losses both for those actually incurred up t 0 the Fowle’s telegra 14th March), but this condition and/3 and thein heirs and successors. 5. I am sending a copy of this letter to Garoe and to Galloway. 3incci**8ty* (Sgd.) R. P EE - L- &gt;•' JtiO) 2. 7107/39 INDIA 01 PICE, \7HITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. 14til November, 1939. 'If My dear Baggallay, , Would you please refer to Wright’s letter of the 10th Novembof* (ho. B. 32453/19) about the assessment cf compensation for Iraqi taxation on the Sheikh of Koweit's date gardens. We propose, if you agree, to instruct the Political Resident as in the second sentence of paragraph 5 of Peel’s letter of the 31st October. Yours sincerely, (3d.) J.P. GIBSON. H.L. Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office. S.W.l.1 P.Z. 7268/39 (E 7515/39/93). FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 18th November, 1939. Fear Gibson, A ' ^ Will you please refer to Wright’s letter S.32453/19 X' to you of the' 10th November and your letter P.Z.7017/39 . // f to me of the 14th November about the assessment of compensation for Istihlak taxation on the Sheikh of Ko¥/eit’E date gardens in Iraq? We agree that instructions may now be issued to the Political Resident on the lines set forth in the second sentence of paragraph 5 of Pee lx’s letter of the 31st 7 hr Octo ber. ’We also agree to the alteration of the phrase ’’heirs” in the draft discharge to 'heirs and successors'. We ourselves, in our despatch No. 524 to Bagdad of the 10th November about the heirs of the Sheikh of Mohammerah, used the phrase 'heirs and assigns'. The truth is that it does not look as if any English phrase can be found that really quite meets the case. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wright. Yours ever, Lacy Baggallay. T.P. Gibson, Esq.CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt No_\^LL—T)ule.J INDIA OFFICE, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to 0 f? '^veLi.^v ^ by'^ Mail. The Foreign Secretary, Government oi India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gnib-ENCLOSURE FC^IQW^OFFICE RINO LETTER -^T'O No® 524c (E 7137/39/93)o Sir, f ^ : —FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W, 1 . 1939. Your Excellency will 'be aware that His Majesty 1 s Government have for some time had under consideration the question of granting compensation to the heirs of Sheikh Mubarak of Koweit and Sheikh Khazal of Mohammerah for the losses suffered by the heirs since 1932 on account of Istihlak taxation on the produce of the estates in Iraq of these two Sheikhs, the tax-free possession of which was guaranteed to them by His Majesty's Government in 191 I 4 .. 2 0 In the case of the Koweiti estates His Majesty's Government have been able to accept the figures submitted by the present Sheikh for losses in the years 1932-3 to 1936-7. This provides a satisfactory basis for calculating the amount of compensation due to him and to his co-heirs. The method of calculation in this case has been to strike an average of the losses in the years mentioned above (£1,087) and to multiply this figure by twenty, so as to give the Sheikh and the other heirs twenty years’ purchase in respect of the future. The figure reached in this way has been rounded up to £ 22 , 000 . it has also been decided that the heirs will be paid past proved losses for the seven years since 1932. The amount actually to be paid to them may, indeed, have to be slightly reduced owing to a • /doubt His Excellency Sir Basil Newton, K.C.MoG,,, e’;c. , etc. , etc., Bagdad.mmam doubt having arisen as to whether the estates administered by Sheikh kubarak in 1914 were all actually owned by him, and if it is established that they were not wholly owned by him it may be decided that the 1914 pledge only covers the estates of which he was the owner, as opposed to the administrator?) No final decision on this point has yet been reached, but, whatever the decision is, it will not affect the estimated amount of the taxation losses on the Koweiti estates as a whole, although, as I have said above, it may lead to some reduction in the payment made to Sheikh Mubarak's heirs® 3. For the reasons given in Mr, Ogilvie-Forbes's despatch No.300 (202/13/34) of 12th .July, 1934, and Sir Archibald Clark Kerr’s despatch No 0 499 (577/3/36) of the 7th October, 1936, it has not proved possible for His Majesty's Government to accept the similar figures for losses due to Istihlak taxation submitted by the administrator of the estates of Sheikh Khazal. Nor has it proved possible to devise any practicable means of reaching a satisfactory estimate of what these losses in fact have been. His Majesty's Government have, however, felt justified in concluding, from the estimates for the now abolished land tax made annually by the authorities in Iraq, on the estates both of the Sheikh of Koweit and of Sheikh Khazal in the years preceding 1932, that the income from the latter was then,and may reasonably be assumed to have remained, a little less than half of that from the former. 4* I realise that this is a method of estimating the losses on the i.ohammerah estates v/hich might not be acceptable in a Court of Law, but I do not regard this as /a■l c I a matter in which it is essential for legal forms to he strictly followed, provided that His Majesty’s Government are themselves satisfied that the heirs of Sheikh Khazal are not being treated unfairly^ In the case of the Sheikh of Kov/eit His Majesty’s Government have a legal obligation, which is still in force, to a ruler whose goodwill is, incidentally, of considerable importance to them. I am advised, however, that the position with regard to the heirs of Sheikh Khazal is rather different. The promise made by His Majesty’s Government in 1914 was a promise to the Sheikh of Mohammerah in his capacity as an independent ruler, and was legally dependent on his continuing to be so. The Sheikh is now dead and had indeed ceased to be an independent ruler before his death; and although His Majesty's Government regard themselves notwithstanding as under a moral obligation to pay fair compensation to the heirs this compensation is in their view in effect an ex gratia payment. They therefore think it unnecessary to negotiate with the heirs, and although it is no doubt desirabl to obtain if possible a complete discharge from each recipient in return for any payment made this is not strictly speaking essential and it might be sufficient in practice to secure a receipt only. 5. In all the circumstances, therefore, I feel that the losses of the heirs of Sheikh Khazal can justifiably be assumed without further investigation to be less than half of those of the heirs of the Sheikh of Koweit, and the compensation to be paid to them has accordingly been fixed upon the basis that it should be as nearly as possible exactly half, subject to certain modifications in the /methodmethod of calculation which the absence of any agreed figure as to actual losses in respect of Istihlak taxation since 1932 has rendered inevitableo The calculation has been made as follows: the assessed average annual loss on the Koweiti estates from 1932/33 to 1936/37 (£1,08?) has been divided by 2 and the resultant figure has been multiplied by 27 (20 years in respect of future losses and 7 years in respect of past losses since 1932), The total 6 . In his despatch No. 612 of 31st December 1936, Sir Archibald Clark Kerr reported that there were in all 28 recognised heirs of the Sheikh of i*Iohammerah» Of these 13 were sons and 14 were daughters and there was one widow 0 Sir Archibald Clark Kerr added that all the sons and daughters are entitled v/ithout exception to movable property and to mulk and miri property also, the sons, however, receiving twice as much as the daughters. The widow is entitled to movable and mul k property, but so far as miri property is concerned she is entitled to trees and buildings but not to land* He went on to explain that in Ottoman Law the division of property amongst the heirs should be made in the following manner; after the widow’s s^are of 1/8 of the movable and mul k (immovable) property has been deducted, the remainder is split into 40 shares, of which each son is entitled to two shares and each daughter to one share. This position was confirmed by His Majesty’s Minister at AV' Tehran in his despatch Ho.540 (133/17/36) of 25th December, 1936 . As l have explained above, His Majesty’s Government regard themselves as having a free hand in assessing and distributing the compensation to be made to the heirs in view of its ex grati a nature, and I do not consider it necessary reached in this way is £ 14 &gt; 674 - 10 o 0 CI Q b to make any attempt to estimate whether the widows share should he less than 1/8. It will, I think, he quite sufficient if her share is fixed at £ 1 , 834 . 6 . 3 ., or 1/8 of the compensation, (which may, however, he rounded up to £ 1 , 835 ) and if each of the sons receives £ 642 . 0 . 0 . or 2/40 of the remainder and each daughter £ 321 . 0 . 0 . or 1/40 of the remaindero 7. Subject therefore to any further observations which Your Excellency may wish to make, I shall he glad if you will now address a communication to each of the heirs, except Sheikh Chassih, on the following lines. 8 . You should start by saying that His Majesty’s Government are prepared to make an e x gratia payment in full and final settlement of past losses due to Istihlak taxation since 1932 and of prospective future losses from this or alternative forms of taxation on land or produce. You should then inform each one of the amount which His Majesty’s Government are prepared to pay as his or her share of the compensation due in respect of the estate as a whole, and should say that this payment will he made in each case if the heir concerned is willing to sign the following form of discharge: 'I e. o do hereby acknowledge the receipt 'of the sum of £ , paid to me on behalf of His 'Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom; and so far 'as my rights and interest in the estate of the late Sheikh 'Khazal of Mohammerah are concerned I accept this payment 'as a full settlement, binding equally on me and my heirs / 'and'and assigns, of any claims which, as a result of the pledge 'given to Sheikh Khazal of Mohammerah in 1914» the heirs of 'Sheikh Khazal have made or may make upon His Majesty’s 'Government in the United Kingdom for the losses which Sheikh 'Khazal or they have suffered since 1932, or which they may 'suffer in the future, by reason of the Istihlak or any 'other tax hitherto or hereafter levied on landed property 'or agricultural production in respect of lands which they 'hold in Iraq as heirs of Sheikh Khazal'. 9* As and when each heir signifies his willingness to sign this receipt, arrangements should he made for him to do so in return for a cheque for the amount concerned, or, in cases where it is preferred, a letter notifying him or her that payment will he made into a specified hank in Iraq, Persia or the United Kingdom. 10. As you are aware. Sheikh Chassib has an English wife who is living with her children in destitution in this country. His Majesty's Government regard it as very desirable that Sheikh Chassih should, if possible, be brought to make provision for this family. In his case, therefore, instead of saying that the money will be paid to him on his completion of the discharge, you should inform him that His Majesty’s Government are prepared to pay the amount in question, but consider that it is his duty to make provision for his family in the United Kingdom. They trust therefore that he will agree to his share of the compensation being paid direct to Mrs. Gladys Chassib. If he declines to notify his agreement to this procedure you should report to me for further instructions. For your own information, His Majesty’s /Government******Governmenc may in that event decide to retain the money indefinitely or to pay it to Mrs* Chassih without Sheikh Chassih s express consent. This is, however, a point on which no decision has yet been taken c 11 o It is possible that some of the heirs are resident- in Persia, and you should in any such cases consult with Hie Majesty’s Minister in Tehran, to whom a copy of this despatch 12 e In conclusion, I would draw attention to my despatch No 5 13k of the 9 th March in which Sir Maurice Peterson was the intention of His Majesty’s Government to make a payment I am not aware whether an opportunity has yet occurred of making the proposed communication, but in any case the Iraoi Government should be informed now of the sums that are beinp paid* instructed to inform the Iraqi Government, unofficially, of to the heirs of Sheikh Khasal on account of taxation losses I am, with great truth and respect, Sir, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) (Sd.) LACY BACJSGALLAY/ (EnclosuW fc -N °f'®r i939 3 (IDVEfttNO ,^fc«-TT.EI* DATED 7840 ! l inUTED DISTRIBUTION . 1953 j Telegram: (en clair) frou Sir B. Newton (Bagdad). 4th December, 195b. D. (By Bag) 4th Deceuber, 1959. R. 1.15 p.u., 10th December, 1959. No. 140 Saving. h l' 2 ' * Your despatch No. 524. v M i suggest that distribution would be uade easier if His Majesty’s minister at Tehran were to address proposed communication and make necessary payment to widow and heirs living in Iran while I deal with those living in Iraq. I assume that the share of the late Abdul Hamid (see Eastern Deoartment letter No. E. 5954/59/95 of June 21st) ■*' \ i should be distributed to his heirs. Addressed to Foreign Office No. 140 Saving en clair by bag, repeated to Tehran No. 20 Saving en clair by bag. ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER No. 51 i-£ 0 EC 1939 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL DEPT. INDIA OFriCE OePY SENT BY AIR MAH of. jfyt, to*, tjr aifi v/jy . L- ft** d*- ^Ji . ( . c-i o\ uwe in vokeiqn offic* !5 *) r 14 DEC 1839 _ ; ET This Document is tha Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should ba (E 7891/39/95). Code telegram to Mr. Kept under,. Loci and Key ] * - * c -~ - j • 7840 | , LIMITED DIS TRIBUTION . Roberts (Tcliran). Foreign Office, 15th December, 1959. 9 e 30 p.m. No. 146. (R). X' 5 * Bagdad telegram No. 140 Saving [of December 4-th: compensation to heirs of Sheikh of Mohammerah]. ^ I shall be glad of your observations by bag. Addressed to Tehran No. 146; repeated to Ba dad No. 54 Saving by bag.CONFIDENTIAL. - ^ No. 33-S of 1940 Con Fid ek t ja l m ——— y Kuwait Receipt Nm 6 Dated ^ ^ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documentors). 'N British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ...®.f ...9* Reference to previous correspondence : India Office letter No .P.Z.7268/39 of the 27th November 1939* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. , ^ Bushire telegram Nb.l5&gt; dated the 6 th January 1940. Shaikh of Kuwait’s date gardens. fijl/ Telegram ^ i'rom Political Resident, Bushire, To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Govemioent of India, Rew Delhi. Copy by post to Political Agent, x^uwait. No.15 Bated the 6 th January 1940. i&gt; \ Your demi-official letter No.P.Z. 7268/39 dated 27th November 1939 x&gt;aragraph 4. Shaikh of Kuwait’s Bate Gardens. In my opinion we are already asking too much in pressing Shaikh to agree to payment being made to kamily Council but as Political Agent thinks he may agree I will not press this view now. »i 2* I thin* however ue will certainly refuse to give Vormal discharge M himself when pay ments are not made to him personally and it appears only logical that body *ho receive funds should sign discharge. &gt;ay I substitute *the family Council** for 'he* in second condition. I assume that Shaikh would be member of family Council. PRIOR G.T.if Telegram Q ^rom Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Hesident, at Kuwait. Copy tent by sea mail to Government of Indie, $ew Delhi, tfo.440 D&amp;ted 27th received 28th January 1940. Important Please give copy to Political Agent. A m 2. Your telegram No.15 Jsnuery 6th. Hia Atajecty’s Government approve your suggestion in paragraph 2 provided that Shaikh is a member of family council. It is important he should sign, whoever else signs as well. 3. This will necessitate amendment of form of discharge of which there will now be two, since com pensation for pas t ?loss es is to be paid to bhaikh only. He-drefts will be sent you shortly by air mail. J*e taxandum Copy given to P.A.. Kuweit.; CONFIDENTIAL ■ y 7471 Wt 234H1/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, Political Depai Kuwait Receipt MM^ Dated — //i '‘ EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. Repeated to Government of India, external Affairs Department. Thx^red ” ” Political Agent, Koweit. Dated 9th February, 1940. No. P.2.793/40. &gt; ip o Reference my telegram of the 27th January, 440. Compensation for taxation losses ' on Sheikh of Roweit's date gardens. 2 . A copy of correspondence with the Foreign Office is To Foreign Office, 18th January, without enclosure. enclosed for your information. From Foreign Office. 6 th February,) will telegraph subsequently on with enclosure. ' U ) 1 learning Treasury views regarding draft forms of discharge and computation of 'past” losses. 6 . Meanwhile I should be glad to learn if you see any strong objection to retaining, as the dividing line between 'past 1 ' and ’'future” losses, the date last spring when H.M.G.’s proposal was communicated to the Sheikh. If on our part there has been delay in pressing the proposal (due to consideration of the point raised in Sir Trenchard Fowle’s sne^no letter of the 24th May, No.C/217) on the other hand this did not prevent the Sheikh from assenting to the proposal put to him, and clearly he cannot be allowed to benefit by delay for which he Is responsible. I may not however be fully apprised of all that has passed between the political authorities and the Sheikh on this subject, and it may be that certain local considerations would suggest that the refund of actual past losses should be calculated up to a somewhat later date than early last year. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (Sgd.) R. PEELP.Z. 793/40 FOREIGN OFF! 6 th February, 1940 (E 274/110/93) Dear Peel Z.103/40 of 18th January about Your letcer compensation for Istihlak taxation on the Koweiti date gardens. 2 . A 3 you were informed on the telephone, we for our part see no reason why the Family Council should not sign the discharge for any sums paid to them, so long as it is understo d that in ary case the discharge is signed the Sheikh, 3 . I see that the third paragraph of your letter proceeds on the basis that the Sheikh is entitled to compensation in respect of the year 1939, as well as for the periods agreed upon last year: that is the years 1932 to 1938, and twenty years purchase for future losses. It is certainly awkward to talk now about :, past ' losses if we mean losses for the years 1932 and 1930, and future” losses if we mean losses in respect of the years after 1938. However, to increase the amount of compensation to be paid to the Sheikh because of the delay in reaching a final settlement with him, would seem to put a premium on the negotiations dragging on indefinitely, and in the suggested redrafts of the two discharges which I enclose, v/e have gone on the assumption that the amount to be paid, whether to the Sheikh or to the Family Council, will be the same as when the matter was broached to him last year. If it is decided to throw in an extra year’s payment, the drafts would of course have to be altered accordingly. 4. So far as we are concerned, we see no particular objection to your proposal that the losses for 1937 and^ 1938 (and 1939 too, if payment in respect of last year is sanctioned) should be calculated on the basis oi the average for the years 1932 to 1936. In fact this seems to offer some advantages. Actual losses for the y^ars 1937 and 1938 (or 1937-1939) might prove to be less than the average of 1932 to 1936, but then they might prove to be greater (the Sheikh would have an interest in showing that they did)-and, if they did, the question might then oe raised whether 922,000 could be regarded as adequate compensation for ’future’ losses. To increase tnat amount would, however, not only be undesirable in itsell, but would be awkward from the point of view of the Mohammerah heirs, since we have already fixed the amount to be paid to them, and since this is supposed to be, roughly speaking, half what will be paid to the heirs of Sheikh Mubarak. 5ISS'] / \ 5* Moreover, as you say, accepting an average will save a lot of trouble all round, and considerable delay. 6 . You wifi remember that we calculated in this way the whole amount to be paid to the Mohammerah heirs, as it seemed impossible in their cases to get any satisfactory figures for actual losses in the years since 1932. 7. It would, of course, be a great simplification to drop the distinction between 'past' and 'future ’ 1 losses, pay the whole amount to the Sheikh and get a receipt from him alone. I suppose, however, that the objections to that still stand. I am sending a copy of this letter to V/right of the Treasury. Yours ever, (Sd.) Lacy Baggallay.Copy (E 274/110/95) DRAFT DISCHARGE B Y FAMILY COUNCIL IN RESPECT OF 'FUTURE ' LOSSES . We, the undersigned, 'being the members of the council which has 'been set up to represent in the matter referred to herein the heirs and successors of the late Sheikh Mubarak of Koweit, on our own 'behalf and on behalf of each one of us both jointly and severally and on behalf of call other persons having any right or interest in the estate of Sheikh Mubarak do hereby both jointly and severally acknowledge the receipt of the sum of £22,000 paid to us on behalf of His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom, and we jointly and severally accept this payment in full settlement and discharge, binding equally on us and each one of us and on our heirs and successors, and on the other heirs of Sheikh Mubarak with their heirs and successors, of any claims which we or any one of us or our heirs or successors have made or may make upon, ami of the liability of, that Government, in respect of the pledge given to Sheikh Mubarak in 1914, to compensate us for the loss which we or any one of us or our heirs or successors have suffered since 1939 or may suffer in the future by reason of the Istihlak or any other tax hitherto or hereafter levied on landed property or agricultural production in respect of lands which we or they hold in Iraq as heirs and successors of Sheikh Mubarak, and in view of this payment made to us for ourselves and for eacn one of us and for the other heirs and successors v/c hereby both jointly and^scverally guarantee His Majesty’s Government against any liability towards the heirs and successors of Sheikh Mubarak in respect of such taxation since 1939*p.z. 793/40 Copy - (E 274/110/93). DRAFT DISCHARGE BY SHEIKH ID RESPECT OF M PA ST f&gt; LO SSES. I, the undersigned on iny Ov.n behalf and on behalf of all other persons having any right or interest in the estate of the late Sheikh Mibarak of Koweit do hereby acknow.ledge the receipt of the sun of £X paid to me on behalf of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom, and I accept thrs payment in full settlement and discharge, binding equally on me, my heirs and successors, and on the other heirs and successors of Sheikh Mubarak with their heirs or successors, of any claims which we or our heirs or successors have made or may make upon, and of the liability of, that Government, in respect of the pledge given to Sheikh Mubarak in 1914, to compensate us for the loss which wo suffered prior to 1939 by reason of the Xstlhlak or any other tax levied on landed property or agricultural production in respect of lands which we hold in Iraq as heirs and successors of Sheikh Mubarak, and in view of this payment made to me, for myself and for the other heirs and successors, I hereby guarantee His Majesty's Government against any liability towards the heirs and successors of Sheikh Mubarak in respect of such taxation -prior to 1*939 •P.Z.102/40 , INDIA OFIICE, 7vHITERALL, S.W.1. 18 th January, 1940. Dear Eyres, . ^ I enclose a copy of a telegram from the Political Resident (a copyof which should already have reached you) about the approach to the Skeikh of Loweit regarding the payment of compensation in respect of Iraqi taxation on his date gardens. 2. Provided that the Sheikh is a member of the Family Council there would seem to be no objection to Prior's suggestion that the discharge should be signed by the Council and not by the Sheikh alone. Do you agree? If so the form of discharge will require amendment, and as only compensation for future taxation losses is to be paid to the Family Council a separate discteirge from the Sheikh in respect of past losses will be required. I enclose a suggested redraft. 3* For calculation of the amount of compensation to bo paid in respect of past taxation losses we ought to receive from the Sheikh and check the actual figures for 1937 &gt; 193 ® and 1939 * Vvould there be any serious objection to our proposing to the Sheikh that, for the sake of convenience, actual figures should be dispensed with and the calculated average annual loss for the years 1932 - 3 ^ applied to the subsequent period? This would save a good deal of clerical labour all round and would probably not make a substantial difference in the total amount to be paid to the Sheikh. .4. 1 am writing similarly to Wright. H-M.Eyres , Esq., Foreign Office, u • W • 1 • Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) R. Peel.P.Z.102/4C INDIA OFIICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.1. 18th January, 1940. Dear Wright, I enclose a copy of a telegram from the Political Resident (a oopyof which should already have reached you) about the approach to the Skeikh of Loweit regarding the payment of compensation in respect of Iraqi taxation on his date gardens. 2. Provided that the Sheikh is a member of the Family Council there would seem to be no objection to Prior's suggestion that the discharge should be signed by the Council and not by the Sheikh alone. Do you agree? If so the form of discharge will require amendment, and as only compensation for future taxation losses is to be paid to the Family Council a separate discharge fram the Sheikh in respect of past losses will be required. I enclose a suggested redraft. 3 . For calculation of the amount of compensation to be paid in respect of past taxation losses we ought to receive from the Sheikh and check the acoual figures for 1937* ^938 an d '1939* Would there be any serious objection to our proposing to the Sheikh that, for the sake of convenience, actual figures should be dispensed with and the calculated average annual loss for the years 1932 — 3 ^ applied to the subsequent period? This would save a good deal of clerical labour all round and would probably not make a substantial difference in the total amount to be paid to the Sheikh. 4. 1 am writing similarly to Eyres. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) R. Feel. S. H. Wright, Esq., Treasury, S.W.1.~'cOSFWRSTI^ '&gt;6 i N ' U © ic-Z cs J / A 1 Q H.M’s Secretary of State for India. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Political Agent, Kuwait. Government of India. 824 Telegram Prom To Repeated to Copy t&gt;y mail to Mo. Dated the 17th and received the 18th February, 1940. My Express Letter No. P.Z.793 of February 9th. Treasury concur draft forms of discharge and in proposed calculation of undetermined past losses on basis of average for years 1932-36. They share Foreign Office views regarding extension of actual past losses beyond 1938 as to ^ihich * I await your views. /X 2 , I regreWthat statement in paragraph 3 of my telegram of January 27th that compensation for past losses is to be paid to Shaikh only overlooked orders contained in paragraph 3 of my Express Letter Mo. P.7.1074/39 of the 28th February, 1939, i.e. that compensation for both actual and future losses should be paid to family council. •% If you see no objection, these orders should still stand and form of discharge by family council should be amended by altering amount of payment and omitting words 'since 1939 H where they occur. - INDIA OFFICE -' , . iMHb'-/ 1 'HliMMMaMMTM / OOltjrwSKTUi, CONFIDENTIAL . No. C/172 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, ttew Delhi, The Political A^ent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). .V British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp, BAHRAIN. Dated . 25 th. Fe bruary 1^40 Reference to previous correspondence: ^ j u £ India Office telegram No.824 dated the 17th February 1^40. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. f Subject. Residenc/ telegram No.T/142 dated the 25th February 1940. Compensation for Taxation losses on Shaikh of Kuwait's Date Gardens. n Zi- V /)Ttlegr&amp;ai Q From Political nceident, in Bahrain. To H.^.Secretary of State for India. Copy by mail to Secretary to the tiovernment of inxda, External Affairs Department, ^ew Delhi. Political Agent, Kuwait. Bo.T/142 Dated the 25th February ls&gt;40. Correspondence ending with your telegram No.884 February 17th. Compensation for taxation losses on Shaikh of Kuwait's i&gt;ate Uardena. 2 » 1 concur in computation of undetermined past losses on basis of average for ia32-l*36 i.e. £.1087/- per year. 3 * As approach to Shaikh in Spring 1*3» was merely verbal and was not followed up by us 1 consider that compensation for past losses should years c over/1B32—lD3a. 4. Total compensation to be offered would therefore amount to £,30684/- (actuals 1832-Ii?36 £.5433/-, average Is37-1D3D £.3261/- future losses £. 22000 /-). 5. if this is approved I will take action accordingly RfcSlDkJiTINDIA OEFICL, VrKIIEHALL, S.W.1. P.Z. 1192/40 28th I'ebruary , 1940. Ifear Baggallay, h Would you please refer to your letter of the 6 th February, No. E.274/110/93 &gt; i n the matter of compensation for losses by taxation on the Sheikh of Noweit's date gardens. 2. From subsequent correspondence with the Political Resident (of j 1 which copies have been sent to you) resting with his telegram of the. f 25 th February (additional copy enclosed) you will see that (i) We have reverted to the position (from which we departed by mistake) that compensation for both actual and future losses should be paid to the Family Council. Only one form of discharge will therefore be required; and (ii) Prior is of opinion that compensation for actual losses should extend to and include the year 1939* We share this view. We fully agree that the Sheikh should not be given any encouragement to prolong the negotiations indefinitely, but the responsibility for the long delay in following up the first and verbal approach to him was certainly not his. We think it would facilitate the negotiations and avoid an unnecessary irritation to the Sheikh if the actual losses were calculated up to the end of 1939* It would be emphasised to Prior, and if need be to the Sheikh, that that period is final and will not be extended if there should unhappily be delay in reaching a settlement. 3» We hope that you will be able to accept this view, and we should be glad to have an early reply so that Prior may get down to business with the Sheikh as soon as possible. Yours sincerely, L. B^ggallay, E.'q., Foreign Cffice, (^4) R, S.V'.I.i Itf P.Z. 1192/40 INDIA OmCE, V/HITEI1ALL, C.W.1. 28th February, 1940. / / / Dear Wright, Would you please refer to your letter of the l^th February, No. S.32453/19 &gt; i n the matter of compensation for losses by taxation on the Sheikh of Koweit's date gardens. 2. From subsequent correspondence with the Political Resident (of which copies have been sent to you) resting with his telegram of the 23 th February (additional copy enclosed) you will see that (i) We have reverted to the position (from which we departed by mistake) that compensation for both actual and future losses should be paid to the Phmily Council. Only one form of discharge will therefore be required; and (ii) Prior is of opinion that compensation for actual losses should extend to and include the year 1939* We share this view. We fully agree that the Sheikh should not be given any encouragement to prolong the negotiations indefinitely, but the responsibility for the long delay in following up the first and verbal approach to him was certainly not his. We think it would facilitate the negotiations and avoid an unnecessary irritation to the Sheikh if the actual losses were calculated up to the end of 1939* It would be emphasised to Prior, and if need be to the Sheikh, that that period is final and will not be extended if there should unhappily be delay in reaching a settlement# 3 . We hope that you will be able to accept this view, and we should be glad to have an early reply so that Prior may get down to business with the Sheikh as soon as possible. Yours sincerely, / ^ (Sgd.) R. PEEU S. H. Wright, Esq., Treasury, S.W.1.■»o. t n i&gt; Political Agenoy 9 Kuwait. Jferch 4 t 1940. Dear Chancery g 3 V.'ith reference to Baggallay’s letter to Oibson No.8 4697/28/93, dated the 15th August, 1938 on the subject of the Bashlyeh estate we enclose a copy of a letter from *-*haikh Ahmad*a son ** 4 ihanunfid in Basra from which you will see that lawyer Partu is proposing to petition that the Beshiyeh case be submitted for adjudication by the iand Settlement Commission. Instructions were sent to Partu to act in accordance with paragraph 4 of Baggallay’s letter, but we do not know what action he finally took, nor do we know Why the Bashiyeh case has cropped up again suddenly. Perhaps Brickell would be able to find that out. grounds on which it is proposed to base the application are (a) Passage of time; and (b) that the appeal is to be made in the name of the heirs,, and not that of Shaikh Ahmad since he is debarred being already under Judgment. It seems to us that neither of these grounds is likely to hold water since in Suit No. 373/1932 Abdulla of Zubair weraus Shaikh ^hmad and others the defendants were the Shaikh aJl£ t&amp;g, hglEg,, and nasaage of time was ruled out as not acceptable, Tide line 6 of page 4 of the Judgment, a copy of which was forwarded to you under It appears from the copy enclosed that the this/ e Chancery, British ESrnbassy, Baghdad.thla office Printed letter No. 551 of 1st NoYember, 1933. 2here is no statement to show that the above Judgment was given on the 'Bashiyeh* ease, but from some of the numbers of the tapu documents ouoted, and the whole story of the case it appears to be so. 4. His Highness has asked for our advice in the matter which is difficult at the best of times so far as the 'Date Gardens w are conoerned 9 but when in the dark as to what has happened it is worse still. V/e should, therefore, be grateful if you could let us know the position, and give us your advice from the point of view of Iraqi law. he are sending a copy of this letter to the Residency. Yours ever, AOKNCY. /o«^ ps- (/*- F) r Ik- tpz) (Copy of translation of letter dated the 16th February, 1940, from Muhammad Si Ahmad, Basrah to His Highness Ruler of Kuwait. I have talked to lawyer Abdul Jeleel Birtou about the Bashiya case, and we ha-ve read all the decrees issued against us. Ihe adTocate proposes that we should submit a petition to the lend Settlement Committee in the name of the late Shaikh Mobarak's heirs, with the exception of your name, because you were sentenced by the Courts of First Instance, and Appeal and the sentence is final f as for the other heirs, they have the right to object. So we shall submit a petition in their names building our plea on 'Lapse of time', and perhaps we shall get some result* Naturally this will be done after your approval. If you agree to this, I beg you to give orders that I may instruct the advocate to submit the petition.N-- CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/96 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian (lulf, at Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 7th - March, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence^/^ • : 25 DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. *l-^d i UK Name and Date. Subject. Letter No. C/95 dated the 4 ; th March, 1940, from the Political Agent, Kuwait, to the Chancery, British Emhassy, Baghdad. t hh l Bashiyeh Estate. ifc. ; .Of X cfIn Telegram. From. To. Repeated. »r&gt;tt Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, at Kuwait. Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy by mail to Government of India. No. 1233. Dated 13th, received the 14th March, 1940. /•i' Your telegram No. T7l42 of 25th February: Kuwait Date Gardens: His Majesty*s Government agree that compensation for actual losses should extend to and include 1939. But it should be made clear if necessary that no extension beyond 1939 will be considered even if a settlement should be delayed. Treasury desires that to avoid risk of difficulties in currency transactions you should make no definite commitment to Shaikh as regards manner ii which compensation will be paid without reference to me. (7^ h . % RETAXANDUM.i 5 # A • Ku 'a sit CONFIDENT T$ legrem Q yrom Politic el Heaident* at .&lt;uwsit To H.M.becretsry of i&gt;tete for Indie, london Repeated Government of Indie, external Affaire Depertment, Copy to Politicel Agent, Kuwait ^ * ITo.T/211. Dated the 21 st &amp;eroh 1940. totally opposed to formation of .Family Council which he said gree t *ould create/difficulties where none now existed* At present all were drawing allowances happily but Council would set one section against other* They would then appeal to him aa Ruler while he would not be in position to do anything* If matter was taken out of his hands he would take no part and we could pay money into bank and leave them to make 'some arrangement•* 2 * I have always regarded proposed Family Council as gratuitous insult and cannot discover any incidents in paet that woudd justify it* de Gaury warned Fowle in April 1939 that formation by us of Family Council would divide al Subeh from shaikh with disastrous results. He added that present system had existed since Mubarak^ day and possibly earlier and recommended its continuance* 63• Political Agent agrees generally with my views but considers that if concession is made we should press for more efficient control of gardens and suggests this would be useful outlet for Abdullah Selim*s energies* He also thinks better lawyer is required* I see no objection to this but strongly Your telegram JJo*1233 Kerch 14th I discussed proposals today with Shaikh* He is- 2 - yr reccmiriend that compulsory Family Council (which no full- po#«r Huler would tolerate) be thrown overboard and Shaikh^ sole receipt accepted* After all we are only making payment to save our feces and Shaikh who is no longer pinched for , , v _ to his relatives money and nas snown mere generous attitude/can be relied on to make equitable distribution. RESIDENTConfidential , D.O. No.C/122. Political Agency, Kuwait. 21st March, 1940. My dear Colonel, Will you please refer to my printed letter No.C/96 of the 7th March, 1940? 2. I have been informed that the Land Settlement Commission reached Basrah a day or so ago. It may therefore be necessary to act speedily if the Bashlyeh case is to be transferred to Land Settlement. 3. It is also for consideration whether His Majesty's Government are satisfied that their interests tre being sufficiently well watched during the sitting of the Commission by Muhammad, His Highness* son and agent in Basrah, and lawyer Partu. The Hon'ble Lt.Col. C.G. Prior, C.I.3., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Yours sincerely, at Kuwait.l£k Telegram From To Copy given to No. E Political Agent, Kuwait. H.M's ^'bassador, Baghdad. Political Eesident at Kuwait. C/125 Dated the 22nd March, 1940. Date G-ardens. I should be glad to know how question of appointment of Jardine stands. (I have seen Resident copy of Houston-Boswall's letter No. 94 of 4th Marcfh, 1940, to Foreign Office my copy not having arrived). 2. Shaikh Muhammad has arrived today and stated that Iraq. Government have refused permission to lawyer Partu to leave Iraq[ and it is therefore impossible for Shaikh to instruct him. It is understood Commission is actually at work in Basra and matter is therefore urgent. - POLITICAL -Telegram. From. 'Q,'. Political Agent, Kuwait. To. British Consul, Bushire. Repeated. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. No. C/126. Dated the 23rd March, 1940. My telegram No.C/125 of March 22nd to Baghdad: I discussed this morning with Shaikh question of briefing second lawyer who would be allowed to come to Kuwait. He said that he thought that the Iraqi Government would prevent that person also from entering Kuwait. However that may be it is doubtful if any other lawyer will undertake onerous task - c.f. difficulty with Kabir last year - Baghdad telegram No.49 Saving of 26th April, 1939. 1 ^&gt; . 2. Perhaps if Partu keeps Consul Basrah fully infomed that could meet the case. POLITICALTelegram. From. To. No.98. Dated and received the 25th March, 1940. British Consul, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. CONFWUNTIAU . No Q. 5 i /t 1 Your telegram No. C/126 March 25rd Date Gardens: Please telegraph result of your representations to Shaikh regarding (a) Employment of better lawyer. (b) Replacement of Shaikh Muhammad by heavier artillery: BRITCONSULr-s confidential Kuwait Receipt Ua o2 7^ Dated 3- 7 ■ 3;_^ Telegram. From. To. Repeated. Dated and 'R'. His Majesty 1 s Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. No.12. British Consul, Bushire. No. 8 . Your telegram No.C/126: It seems probable that permission to leave Iraq has been refused Partu because he is a Reserve Officer. If this is so, additional lawyer not liable to military service might be employed to go between Partu and Shaikh, or alternatively Shaikh Muhammad might act on behalf of his father in consultation with Partu. It would be well that Consul, Basrah, should be kept informed of what is happening but he should not be expected to take responsibility of giving legal advice. Meanwhile, efforts are being made to have all Land Settlement proceedings in Fao Nahiyah suspended until British Land Settlement Officer is appointed. No reply has been received yet from Foreign Office about Jardine.Telegram. 'R'. From. Political Agent, Kuwait. To. Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad NO.C/128. Dated the 27th March, 1940. Baghdad telegram No.12 of March 26th: 2. I have again discussed with Shaikh question oi engagement of second lawyer. Shaikh while expressing willingness does not think this step necessary yet. He prefers that Shaikh Muhammad should act as go between him and Partu. He adds that he does not wish unless absolutely necessary that a second lawyer should be made cognisant of his case and the connected documents. 3. In view of Ambassadors last paragraph I think that if Partu keeps Consul informed and Shaikh Muhammad visits Kuwait occasionally for Shaikh’s instructions that should be sufficient until we hear whether Land Settlement is actually to take place or not. POLITICAL.% /^1 mam !1 Telegram. From. To. No.C/132. Dated the 28th March, 1940. 'Q'- Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. , .n'* A ■ ■ Your telegram No.98 of March 25th Date Gardens: Reference (a) please see my telegram ^No.C/128 of March 27th. ' • Regarding (b) Shaikh is averse to suggestion. Letter in this wee^s mail. POLITICAL, &gt;Telegram. From. To. No.0/134. Dated the 28th March, 1940. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. Private and Personal: Reference (b) of your telegr&amp;m No.98 March 25th I see now that something on those lines has been tried before and I think failed vide De Gaury^s demi-official a No.271 dated the 23rd August, 1938, to Weightman. I am now writing you Shaikh T s objections and my comments. POLITICAL.Confidential /-s D.O. WO. C/133. TO) Political Agency, Kuwait, 28th march, 1940. Will you please refer to my telegram K6. C/128 of the 27th March, 1940, which replies to (a) of your telegram to. 98 of the 25th March? 2. With regard to (h) of your telegram. I did not discuss that raatter with His Highness before leaving for the Easter week-end as I did not wish to go away and leave him with an unpleasant subject to think about in ay absence. I need not, however, have worried for I now see that the idea is not new at all, but has been tried out and failed. 3. Kis Highness was most averse to the suggestion on the grounds that he has greater trust in, and control over, his son fuhamrnad than Abdulla. His Highness also thought that Abdulla might act without his knowledge, and be over-inclined to study his own interests. I do not see how that could well be as all the 3ubah are in the same boat so far as the Date Cardens are concerned, but there is something in the first objection. His Highness said that Abdulla showed no inclination to work, but only to talk and make believe that he was a clever person. He gave as example of this inertia Abdulla^s half-hearted attitude as President of the Council, and his delegating of revenue powers entrusted to him to his half-brother fahad as Salim. There is no doubt that Abdulla takes but little interest in the Council, and as for the delegation of his revenue powers there may be some truth in the statement for Fahad certainly sits in the The Hon’ble Ideut-Colonel C.C. Tior, CIK., Political resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. so-called/z 1 so-oalled Treasury # and Fahad ani AMulla hare the reputation AMulla was easily swayed, witness his lending himself as figurehead of that party in Kuwait which recently attempted to upset the established order* This is quite true, and, of course, should be borne in mind when it is a question of the employment of Abdulla in Basra where, I imagine, temptations are many for those persons whose work is connected with the Iraqi Courts* since \bdulla has already been tried out as 'Inspector of the Subah Estates' - vide de Gaury^ demi-official letter No. 271 of August 23rd, 1933, to tfeightman, and has proved a failure* This, I regret to say, I overlooked, perhaps because of the complete absence of any results during the six months in which he was 'Inspector', and this at a time when there was great activity in Date Gardens matters* It is evident that he gave up his duties on the Shaikh Ahmad f s return to power, though there is nothing on record. Abdulla was not directly concern ed with all this but it is obvious that he did little even when matters in his branch were under action, for instance latihlak Tax, eviction of the Shaikh’s fellaheen etc* Since Abdulla has already been tried out as Controller of these estates and been found wanting, I now consider that there is nothing to be gained in re-employing him* The duties it would be difficult to overrule the Shaikh’s objections which are well founded* of acting in concert in most matters. His Highness added that Ate need not, however, enter into these questions now and responsibilities would be even heavier than before, andcancelled but he added that thrugh he agreed that a British Officer waa neceeaarsr he feernd that It would be hard to find one aa the two latent ^eeruita to the departeent were too Inexperienced to work Independently ana the three other British Land fcttleeent Officer* wera alre^uy tally iKo vied* f. F-url la aha went on to apeak with regret of in# failure of the effort that he had wade laat eue^er to perauiKie Vr* t» V. Sardine to coae back to T r*p # art aeked whether ^la * howerneent could net ar^nire to wend ^r. Jardlne back If only to ca^ry out the aettleeent work In the F«o Fahiyah. Tt la of considerable importance thrtt « final aolutlon of the whole oueatlofi of the title of the halkh of * owe It to bin eropertlea In *&gt;,&lt;*.16 be reached a« econ aa possible and it would eemi to be in the Intereate of Me tfaleety’a noweiwMint that **n. ^irrd'no's se-wt«ea bhould be wade awmilable for thin w^rk cither by aeoondrcnt or in ao«e ether way. ?:ot only ia no other officer at present available but uj*. yardlne ia hlmeelf particularly well Qualified to carry out thie work by his paat experience and detailed knowledge of local eouaiUoma lu the Bears llwa. ? * 1* these e 1 reu«tstances 1 vontui'e to rtecuaeieisi that th* roapiblllty of aatisfyliuf the * r&lt;*e Mnieter’a do ire th«t 'r. yard'ne should return for « period to wowv'hr a and ettlewent officer in Iraq ‘ifeould be evrn»tbet&lt;er?!y exewtned. v _ ^• understand from the eemlMorriclel oorm*on**ence that paused laet emmmer betmeen ry rhanerry and the ( ecretari t of the Pigh fommlaaionar in ^nleatlre that aubjeet to the consent of the &gt; acre t ary of ft ate for the Col ortlajsTranslation from Al wnqayt* Al Jraolyah Fo, 17glci dated 8 &gt; 8«4r &gt; &gt; iLSik^. In view of the proviaionb ol article 14 (a; of lend Claims Settlement T,»w Ho. 29 of 195* t I hereby announce that T shall atari land settlement wot*k in the under-mentioned lands 14 days after the r&gt;uVMeatl r»n of this notice in the official Oaaette ?- Heme of Tenda. *nown Aa dumber of ^apu ^e^cieter, If any. nit T»andar ''UQata’ah. And other nit &gt;&gt;»elifa ''uqata'ah. rronertiea Al FaddaiorMyah ^uo»ta f ah. situated in ^ao Al r»aure uqnta^h. Hehiyeh acoo^dinff Al ra'ameer Vuqata'ah. to their administrative Al Fao Vuqata*ah. boundaries. persons having anyth ng to do with these or adjacent lands must submit their claims within 14 days from the date of publication in the Oilicial Gazette, giving particulars regarding the cate/ory and oaueranip of the above-mentioned lands and their rights and other connexion with these lands, and the houndafrlea and area thereof, to the r e adquarter8 of this oomMttee situated in Houae ho. 59/1, Al ' uwaffao street, AT rraihms Quarter. Dated 3rd February, 194^. President of “?th Psnd Settlement Committee, District.2 too) '11 Tr anslation from Al ^agayl* M Tr a gi yah Ko, 1774&lt; 1ftt R ,2.4 , l,aw Z of 194 for tha ffrlta—off* of T rr-core Buwb and the Orant of rompenfi&amp;tion to yultaalffie. With the approval of the Senate and the Chamber of peputlea* I hereby oruer tht enactaent of the following lew :- Article S « ^a N A auai of I.t?. gT^73/6?^, d^e frow the 'halkha of Tofroit and Kuh same rah In respect of .larlb tax for the years rrlor to the date of com 4 ™? Into force of the Lew for the ^ollaction of T Btlhl»)c on Agricultural Products, shall he written-off* Article 7* This law shall come into force from the date of Its publication In the official gaxette* Article 6 . The minister of Finance la charsred with the execution of this law. Done at Bagdad thifc 2nd uay of Muharrara, 1559, and the 1 th day of talruary, 1^4u. AMul Tllah, Taha al Fashlml. Nuri el Acting minister of finance. ] rime Minister* ••••••*2-( Telegram. From. M (i n . Political Agent, Kuwait. To. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. URGENT. Repeated. No.C/145. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated the 3rd April, 1940. Your telegram No.12 of March 26th: PARTU reports that President of Commission demanded from him on the 1 st document purporting to prove w inheritance of the heirs of Mubarrak tt . President states that he is satisfied that lands have been in possession of heirs for a long enough period and he only requires above-mentioned document before he registers land as Sdbah land but unless document is produced within one week he will enter lands as Iraqi Government property. Shaikh states that such a document cannot be produced within the limit prescribed. I should be grateful for immediate instructions as to whether Shaikh should submit such document to this Commission as soon as he is aole (if so the limit set by the President must be extended) or whether Shaikh may be informed that this Commission will be cancelled. POLITICAL.CONFIDENTIAL So AJy ^ Dated __ Telegram Q Political Besident, Bushire. H.M’s AmlDassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. H.M’s Secretary of State for India. From To Repeated to Copy hy post to Government of India. Mo 134 Dated and received the 4th April, 1940 IMPORTANT. A Kuwait telegram No. 0/145 of April 3rd. Kuwait Date Gardens. ment proceedings will he suspended, I consider that it would he dangerous to Shaikh not to produce the required document as soon as possible. Political Agent should advise him to do so. I should he grateful if you would move Iraq Government urgently to obtain postponement of time limit for production of document. 3. I am repeating India Office Kuwait telegram referred to. 2. As we have no guarantee that current land settle- v a A/ Telegram 'R' To Repeated From His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad Political Agent, Kuwait. No.15. Political Resident, Bushire. No.9 Dated and received the 6 th April, 1940 Your telegram No.C/145: Nuri Pasha told me on April 3rd that he had written to ask Minister of Justice to stop work of Iraqi Land Settlement Officer. Nevertheless, wisest course for Shaikh would seem to make every possible effort to produce required document within specified time and to ask for additional time if he is unable to do so. It seems strange that he or his lawyer should not have ready such an essential paper. Meanwhile I shall continue my efforts to secure suspension of Land Settlement proceedings until British President is appointed.No Telegram. From. To. Repeated 'Q'. JKawait Receipt,. W D at'd With A v&gt;s Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy by mail to Government of India. No.1685. Dated 9th, received the 10th April, 1940. A irl Your telegram No. T/211 of March 22nd: Kuwait Date Gardens: In the circumstances you are authorised to with- draw condition regarding family council. Form or discharge will then be (that for?) Shaikh enclosed with my Express letter of February 9th but suitably amended, viz; by omission of words n prior to 1939 w at the end, and by substituting for these words where they first occur of following 'up to and including 1939 or which we or our heirs or successors may suffer thereafter'. I agree that any action that Shaikh can be persuaded to take for a more efficient control of date gardens will be beneficial. Reference last sentence of my telegram No.1233 of March 13th treasury now considers that payment should be offered in Sterling or Iraq dinars. No special currency restrictions on payment are necessary. RETAXANDUM. Id t « * uJO lA *IS I u it L u I 5 \ i ir' r 'i ^ ■l£i. r CONFIDENTIAL CONgJDEXTIAL . No - 83-5 Of 1940. I Kuwait Receipt/ / 1 No 3 ^ Dated ' / V/^O . The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• His Majesty 9 ■ Secretary of State for Indi&amp; 9 London• 2« The Secretary to the Horernment of India # External affairs oepartment f Hew Delhi# and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document J \ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. .25£h. ii arch • I9b4£« Reference to previous correspondence: British Biahaesy Bagdad despatch Ho*94 of the 4th Parch 1940 to the Foreign Office* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. A .0/3 u Telegram No*0/125 of the 22nd March 1940 from the Political Agent# Kuwait* Copy forwarded, with Agent, Kuwait Subject. Shaikh of Kuwait's date gardens in Iraq , application of land settlement* onrpliments, to the Political c omi- f.4CONFIDENTIAL . No. 101-S of 1940* The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* Hie Majesty’s Secretary of State for India* London• 2* The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 1940. Reference to previous correspondence: ■(!■■■ * 1 L o • 8 3 ifi Residency Printed Letter 1&amp;o*83-3 of 25th i- March 1940* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. -IT* /f 1* Telegram No ,8 dated the 25th March 1940 from His Maj e sty’s Ambas sador, Bagdad. |b t 2* Kuwait telegram Ko«G/l26 of 27th March 1940# Copy forwarded, with Political Agent, K Shaikh of Kuwait’s date gardens in lra&lt;i . application of land settlement* complimente, to the jwait • /CONFIDENT] A T i^\ Kuwait Receipt No 3^1 Dated Telegram R From His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. To Political Resident, Bushire, No. 10 Repeated to - Political 'Vgent, Kuwait. No. 16 H.M's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. No. 116 Dated and received the 10th April, 1940. . | F* Your telegram No. 134 to India Office. 2. Minister for Foreign Affairs informed me April 8 th that he had sent letter that morning to Departments concerned asking for settlement &amp;£ work in Fao^ to he suspended. He regretted that action had heen delayed owing to his sudden departure to visit Ihn Saud. He arrived in Basra this morning and promised that he would also take action on the spot. 3 . I hope that his action will he effective and that work will he stopped until British officer is appointed hut I suggest that Shaikh should proceed at once to have all necessary documents prepared for establishing his claims before the Land Settlement Court. It is already over a year that properties were placed under Land Settlement. - AMBASSADOR. -. (314/2/40) / 2 ^) 2s&gt;i BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD. 20th March, 1940. -a' ci) Dear Agency, / We are replying to your letter No. C/95 of March 4th. 2. We are sorry-rthat we have no knowledge of what action Partu took on the instructions, which you tell us, were sent to him from Koweit in 1938 about the Bashiyah case nor do we know what new development, if any, has prompted Muhammad al Ahmad to write a letter about this case to the Shaikh. 3. Perhaps the best course would be for the Shaikh to summon Partu to Koweit for a consultation. He will no doubt be able to explain both these two points and also to give details of the course of action which he now proposes to follow. 4. As regards the legal aspects of the matter we have nothing to add to the sipirjiing up contained in Baggallay^ letter to Gibson No! E 4697/28/93 dated 15th August, 1938, except to mention that so far as we know no Land Settlement Court has yet been set up in Pao (see Bagdad despatch No. 94 of'March 4th to the Foreign Office) which could Political Agency, KQWH1T.- 2 - give judgment on an appeal about the Bashiyah property but admittedly this may not necessarily mean that there is nothing to be gained from the tactics which Partu now seems to wish to adopt.(276/S/40) v^: Dear Agency, With re nee to the second paragraph of Embassy telegram No.12 of 26th March,to you and to the second A Ibb paragraph of your telegram C/128 of 27th March to Bushire, we enclose herein a copy of a minute made by the Ambassador after a talk which he had with the Prime Minister on March 26th about Land Settlement operations in the Fao Nahiyah. 2. We should welcome any positive information that you may be able to give us about the work if any that is being carried on by the Iraqi Land Sett]ement Officer (see paragraph 3 of Bagdad despatch No. 94 of March 4th to the Foreign Office of which a copy has been sent to you). 3. We are sending a copy of this letter to the Residency at Bushire.. Yours ever, CHANCERY. Political Agency Q-fi y V’ L . 1 $ 1 U* ROWS IT.MINUTE. I spoke to the Prime Minister this morning about the Iraqi Land Settlement Officer at Pao e He said that he had written to the Ministry of Justice pointing out that a British Officer should be appointed and would see that effect was given to his instructions* I said that it was important that no decisions should be given by the Iraqi Land Settlement Officer and explained that I was doing my best to arrange the secondment of Mr* Jardine in the manner that His Excellency had himself suggested. Meanwhile it would be better to suspend any work by an Iraqi Officer as his employment would appear to be an infringement of a written arrangement. (intd. ) B. C.N. 26th March, 1940Telegram* From. To. Repeated. 'R'. Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty^ Ambassador 9 Baghdad* Political Resident, Buahire* Dated the 24th April, 1940. No.185. Correspondence ending with Baghdad telegram No.16 of April 10th: 2. I saw lawyer Partu yesterday and he informed me that the Land Settlement Commission was still working and had started to measure Faddaghiya though the President had been called to Baghdad a few days ago. 3* Shaikh has not yet finished preparation of necessary documents and I have today impressed on him the necessity of completing these as soon as possible. POLITICAL.CONFIDENTIAL. No.C/189 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to Tho Hon*bit) the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. / 9 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 29th April, 1940. Eeference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. r ^ Subject. S v Demi-official letters Nos C/187 and C/188 tiatea the 29th April, Shaikh of Kuwait’s Date Gardens 1940, from the Political Agent, Kuwait,to the lihibassy at Baghdad.Confidential, Political \genoy 9 D.O. No, C/137 Kuwait f 29tU Aj?rll t 1940. Dear Chancery, We thank 2/40 of the 20th r ?aroh Baahlyah case. you for your letter No. 314/ 9 1940 9 on the subject of the 2, Lawyer Partu told the Political \gent on the 23rd of April that the appeal in the Bashiyah case was not In the narae of the heirs of 'hibarrak, but only in that of Shaikh Ahmad. The Political Agent pointed out tne discrepancy between this sta tement and his copy of tne Judgment, but in view of Partu's statement promised that he would advise the Shaikh that an appeal on the lines proposed by Partu might be tried, 3, We are sending a copy of this letter to the Residency, Bushlre. fours ever. Agency. The Chancery. His Majesty*a mbassy, BAGHDAD,■ Confidential CON FI DENT IAL \yo Kuwait Receipt/ /\ No_ Dated //AA K0.152-S 2 - British Residency and Consulate General » Bushire&gt; the 11th April 1940. To p w 6 &lt;w t r ik/ The Political Agent&gt; Kuwait. Subj e ct : Compensation for taxation losses on the Shaikh of Kuwait* s date gardens. Memorandum \ ' 1 1 / Reference correspondence' ending with India Office telegram ^0.1685, dated the 9th April 1940 2. I enclose the English version of my le tte r ifo . 151-S , dated the 11th April 1940 j to the Sliaikh of Kuw : ait&gt; commun icating the proposals of his Majesty*s Government. Please have the Arabic translation added and forward the letter to the Shaikh. Two spare copies are enclosed, one for your records and the other for teturn to this office after trans lation has been added. 3* On receipt of the Shaikh*s reply (which please have translated at Kuwait), if he accepts the proposals please enquire from him and report whether he wishes payment to be made in sterling or in Iraqi dinars, and to which bank. Sd. C#G. PRIOR Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. CMCONFIDENTIAL. 2 - No - C/194 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The lion’hie the Political Besihent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 29th April, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire Memorandum No. 152-S of the 11 th A . \&gt;. 0 prll, 1940. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Letter No. 151-S of the llth^Apri 1940, from the Hon’hie the Politi Resident in the Persian Gulf, to His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait. cal Subject. Compensation for taxation losses on the Shaikh of Kuwait’s date gardens.Confidential Political Agency 9 Kuwait ITo. C/201 6th ^ay, 1940 To The Hon•hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject: - Compensation for taxation losses on the Shaikh of Kuwaiti date gardens. Heference your memorandum No, 152-3 of the 11th \pril f 1940, reply, and the signed discharge in original. It will he noted that he returns the discharge without comment heyond thanks. Since the discharge is signed presumably nothing further ie required. 2 I enclose 3. The Shaikh states that he wishes the money to he oaid into the Ottoman Bank, Basra Political Agent, KuwaitTiiANSL^TION Fro-n - His Highness the Huler or Kusiait, To - The Hon # hle Lieut-Colonel C.G. Prior, or ., Political Besldent in the ersian ^ulf• No. - V6-1311 Dated the 1st Hay, 1940. After Co^liiaeiits, i I have received with pleasure Your Excellency’s letter No. 151, dated the 11th April, 1940, and thank you for your kind attention, appreciation and high consideration for which I am bound to express to Your Excellency my gratitude. In return for your support to which I am accustomed, and for that Which I still receive on all occasions from H.B.H’s Oovomment, I wish there victory and success from the depths of ay heart. I submit to lour Excellency the discharge in settlement of the question of the estates concerning which an undertaking was given to my grand-father the deceased Shaikh Mubarak al Subah by His r a,jesty*s Government. In conclusion I beg to offer Your Excellency my highest respects and sincerest compliments, and pray God for your preservation. Usual Ending.—— CONFI ri\L Kuwai No (■&lt; &lt;&gt; 7 Deue l 4kJ Telegram ?rom To Mo. Q Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. 228 Dated and received the 7th May, 1940. &lt;V ■ Your Printed Letter No. 0/194 of April 29th, Please expedite Shaikh’s reply. - RESIDENT - : A'Q'. Telegram. From. To. No.C/205. Dated the 8th May, 1940 Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Kuwait. Your telegram No.228: A 1A Reply was received on 1st May and is being sent by mail of about 12th. POLITICAL.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 291-3 of 19 40. CONFIDENTIAL K&amp;u (■&gt; L Receipt No ^ ^ ^ Dated £!■ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Kuv.’ai t. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment /{s^. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated . . 1 . 9 . 4C ? •.2 ^ Telegram From To Rape ated Political Reeident» Buehire. Secretary of State for India? London# Government of India? Simla# Poet copy to Political Agent? Kuwait# 13 o# 26 b i&gt;ated It)th May 1*40# / A v' Your telegram 1685? April 9th# KUWAIT DATS GARDENS* 2# Sheikh has signed discnarge and asks that money be paid to Ottoman Bank? Basra# - BRITOCNSUX -CONFIDENTIAL. No - 313-S CONFIDE NTIAL Kuwait Receipt lotted J=iJL^£- 2^ l%0 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his cora- pliments to His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated ... l&amp;tfc.. Mfty.. 19.4.0.•, Reference to previous correspondence : A ^ Political Resident’s telegram Eo.265 dated 15th May 1940* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. A Letter No*1^6-1311, dated the 1st May 1940, from Shaikh of Kuwait, with signed discharge in original* Subject. Kuwait Date Gardens*CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/248 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to The Hon•hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the - 22nd May, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence : ^ ^ &lt; Vi Kuwait Printed Letter No. C/189 of the 29th April, ,1940. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-Official letter No.C/247 of the 22nd May, 1940, from the Shaikh of Kuwaitis Date Gardens. Agency, Kuwait, to the Chancery, H.M*s Brabassy, Baghdad. \L C Confidential D.O. No* C/247. Political Agency, Kuwait, 22nd Nay, 1940. Bear Chanceiy, ^ . 1 With reference to our letter No.C/187 of the 29th April, 1940, we learn that an appeal has been lodged as suggested hy Lawyer Partu. We are sending a copy of this letter to the Residency, Bushire. Tours ever AGENCY. c The Chancery, His Majesty^ Embassy, BaghdadConfidential« Political Agency, Kuwait, 25th May, 1940. D.O. No. C/254 ITill you please refer to your telegram ITo. 134 of the 4th April on the subject of the Date Gardens? the 'Inheritance Deed* has been prepared, and I asked him again this morning. He replied that it was not ready, and when I pointed out that much more than a month had passed since he had told me that he would prepare it immediately, he vaguely mentioned the diffi culties inherent in its preparation. There is no doubt in my mind that His Highness is procrastinating in this matter, and I feel that it is time that this was stopped. It is obvious that we cannot be expected to implement any undertaking if His Highness persists in putting obsta cles in the way of the Courts in Iraqt which we think may be detrimental to our interests. I suggest, there fore, that I may be authorized to inform His Highness that if he does not follow our advice in this matter we shall be forced to hold him responsible for any consequences. I have more than once asked His Highness if The Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel C.G.Prior, CIS o w—w .ur.xJ. xv-Jx , UXo a , ♦ Political Besident in the Persian Gulf Hushire.————— —II —— CONFIDENTIAL Kuwait Receipt __ No ^ / Dated ^-9 ^ ft? 2SSJ Telegram, From. To. Repeated Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy by mail to Government of India. No.2577. Dated 28th, received the 29th May, 1940. Us Your telegram No.265 of May 15th: Ambassador Baghdad instructed by telegram on May 25th to pay £30,694, half of 61388 to Shaikh’s account with Ottoman Bank. RETAXANDUMTelegram. From. To. No.388. Dated and Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. received the 30th May, 1940. / \ Your D.O. No.C/254 of May 25th: I agree. *1CONFIDES JLX 11 * Ji i J St, y No $ f 3 Dated ^ ' «* r ' u o&gt;4^ zxi Telegram. From. To. Repeated 'R'. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. No.17. Political Resident, Bushire. No.15. Dated and received the 4th June, 1940. r°j Your telegram No.0/183: Iraq Government state that land settlement on Shaikh’s properties has been stopped pending appointment of Good to carry on this work. Can you confirm? PRODROME. (®. a c , C ^ )1'R” • Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated the 8th June, 1940. Your telegram No.17 of June Shaikh Muhammad reports that Committee is still working and due to hear a case this morning. 4 th: From. To. Repeated No.C/273. POLITICALx BY BAG — CONFWKXTIAL o^Xf~ vu it Receipt r j COPY OF TELEGRAM. ' ^ 2 SI. p uForeign Office. London. 7 From H.M. Ambassador, To Bagdad. ^ , 18th May f 1940* 42/SAVING. No Time despatched Addressed F.0*» repeated Kowelt 4/^aving, and Buehire 8/Saving. »y telegram No. 10 to Bushlre repeated to you No. 116. 2. Minister for Foreign Affairs has informed me that Government now propose to create a separate land settlement area, to cover the properties of the Shaikh of Kowelt in the Fao Nahlyah and to appoint Judge Good (now President of the Basra Court) to carry out the settlement therein leaving the Iraqi Settlement Officer already appointed to continue the settlement of the rest of the Nahlyah. Judge Good has agreed to accept this appointment. 3. Disadvantages of this arrangement seem to be (1) Good*s lack of experience in settlement work j (2) Fact that if Good is Settlement Officer he will presumably not be able to preside over the Special Court in manner envisaged in para. 10 of Embassy letter to Minister for Foreign \ Affair. No. 347 of July 8th, 1936.^ : ' V These points do not however seem to offer adequate grounds for objection to Iraqi Government proposal. NKWHON. (9462) Wt.47903/320 3,000 3/39 A.&amp; E.W Ltd Go 685 (11266) Wt.22036/320 3,000 7/39 ^'Q'. Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty^ Ambassador, Baghdad. Political Resident, Bushire. 15th June, 1940. My telegram No.273 of June 8th: Shaikh has informed me that Shaikh Muhammad has written saying that there was strong rumour that Good would be appointed Settlement Officer for Subah properties. Muhammad had heard nothing officially. Telegram. From. To. Repeated. No.C/284. Dated the POLITICAL1 / CONFIDENTIAL. No. 412-S of 1940. CONFIDENTIAL JCuwait Receipt No 9 Dated &amp;Q *' ^ 7M.&amp; The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document , British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 15th June 1940 Reference to previous correspondence : A ^ Bagdad telegram No.42/Savlng of 18th May 1940 to Foreign Office. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Foreign Off ice ' telegram No.170 of 28th May 1940 to His Majesty’s Ambassador, Bagdad. Subject. Land settlement for properties of Shaikh of Kuwait. (Um L &lt;foa ' 1 ^4« copy. P.Z. 3078/4 0. IE 1878/110/93) ^r- \a No.170 iH) Code telegram to Sir B.Newton, ^Bagdad) Foreign Office, 28th May,1940,9 p.m. v ' 4 lour telegram No*42 Saving (of 18th Mays land settlement for properties of Shaikh of Kuwait). 1 agree. 2 , if Iraqi Government have definitely decided that they do not require services of Mr.Jardine, please inform Government of Palestine accordingly reference Bagdad despatch No.94 (of 4th March) repeating to me. IConfidential Political Agency, D.O. NO. C/316* Kiawait, 8th July, 1940. My de^r Colonel, Will you please refer to my telegram No. 284 of the 15th June, on the subject of the Bate Gardens? 2. Abdullah Salim has asked me to request that Good be instructed to proceed with the Settlement now, and not wait till the autumn as he apparently intends, or has been instructed, to do. 3. Abdullah Salim also told me that the 'Inheri tance Deed' has been prepared. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Embassy, Baghdad. Yours sincerely, The Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel C.G.Prior, CIE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.CONFIDENTIAL. No - 0/318 The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to His Majesty's Ambassador, Baghdad. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 8th July, 1940. Reference to previous correspondence : DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. # Name and Date. Subject. D,0. No. C/316 of the 8th July, 1940, to the Hon'ble Lieut-Col. C.G.Prior, CIE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Date Gardens.■ no. 5w -8/e. Dear Chancery t 17th August, 1940, l 'V a tfith reference to your let 4 No.65/30/40, dated the 5th July, 1940, we enclose a receipt, in original fran the Shaikh of Kuwait, for I.D.30,694. Yours ever, *GimCY. The Chancery, British i^nbassy, Baghdad.mmm y * 276/29/40 * ^ HIS Majesty's Ambassador Bagdad presents his compliments to the political Agent at K 0 weit, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Kinbassy. Ragdad. CONFIDr.XTlAL Kuv'di. Lt-ceipt Nolfr' Da.Lt' i 2nd..AugUS.t , 19..40.. Y —^jo .&gt;1^ Reference to previous correspondence : Bagdad telegram No.4/Saving dated 18th May, 1940. Description of Enclosure.Vo. 361 • (276/29/40) British Rwbassy, Bagdad. 2nd August ,1940, Vy Lord, t ^Ith reference to my saving telegram Vo, 42 of Vay Iftth, T have the honour to transmit to vour Lordship herewith a translation of a Gazette notification appointing Fr* Good to conduct land settlement operations in the properties ownod by the halkhs of vowelt and Huharamerah In certain cpeclfied localities in the Basra Liwa* 2, I am sending copies of this despatch and ita enclosure to the rolltical Resident in the vcrsian Gulf and the political Agent at Koweit. I have the honour to be with the highest respect. My Lord, vour Lordship’s most obedient, humble rerrant. ,3,t 1S** - ' The Right Honourable The Viscount Halifax, e tc •, e tc •, e tc •Kxtract from Al Waqayi’ A1 Iraqiyah No. 1817 of 22nd July, 1940. principal Contents . 1. Notification by the Directorate-general of Tapu and Land r ettlemeni . By virtue of the authority vested in me in clause Article 1, of Land Claims Settlement Law no. 29 of 1938, amended by Law no. 44 of 1939, T hereby declare the lands belonging to the shaikhs of Koweit and vuhammerah in the undermentioned localities in Tsasra Liwa to be a district for land settlement purposes, where land settlement operations will be conducted under the cognizance of Mr. Good, President of Civil Courts, Basra, as Chief Land Settlement Officer in addition to his original appointment; Saiyid Arif al Arif to remain, however, Chief Land settlement Officer in the remaining section, not belonging to the said two Shfcikhs, of the Fao district announced as district for land settlement purposes by the notification published in Al Waqayi’ Al Iraqiyah No. 1677 dated 9th January, 1939. Localities. Shatt-al-Arab Abul Khasib Al Haritha Fao Al Siba Al Faddaghiyah Kut al Khalifa Fut al Zain Al Mutawwaah. MTNT r *?KN 0* JUSTICEmmmmmmk ________ MKk. Telegram From To No. C/455. Q. Political Agent Kuwait. Political Resident Bushire. Dated 7th October 1940. Shaikh has shown me letter from Shaikh Muhammad in which he states that &amp;ood has asked Partu for documents in support of Faddaghiya case to which latter replied that all had heen submitted and were with records. Partu fears that Good may request an assistant who may influence decision against Subah. 2. As it is important that there should be no hitch because of non-submission of documents by Subah I suggest Good might be asked how case is progressing and if any further documents are required. For instance although I was told the inheritance deed had been prepared (my demi-official letter No. 316 of 8th July 1940) from recent discussion with Shaikh I am doubtful of veracity of statement. It is not clear if Good wants such a document. Political. y) iDraft Translation of letter dated the 21st Sha’han 359 (23rd Septemher 1940) from Tr oharmnad Tl Ahmed to TTis rfighness the Euler of Ku;ait. After Compliments. 3ir, The 7addaghivya case which was trans ferred to the 'Tand Committee^ is now in the hands of the ’’President of the Courts” ^asra r (j^njlishman), for his decision. He xhas 'been examining the documents of the case for a long time hut up till now xhe has issued no decision. I have interviewed Abdul j^cel Pftrto, the Advocate, /ho has informed me that the ' ashed him today if he had any documenis^p^ luis case ? The advocate’s answer that he had no documents besides ..those on the,file which belonged of his opponent and to jre and that nothing else remained but the decision. Txhe President ((Englishman) said ”T have no assistant to help me in this case and no clerks”. The advocate thought that this president cases.and fears lest he may write for an Assistarb who may mislead him /ith the result that the decision will not be in favcir of the Cub ah. Txhe advocate has advised me to write to Tour Highness about this important dase that you may , Gg\) the get in touch with*® H ‘ to‘draw that: President's attention to this matter. Everything rests with you. Usual ending. be too 7eak to ive •' decision ow such rDEPARTMENT. BRANCH. ft M tte L l. Mer orandum File Ni. Serial No. Class for taleorama Ordinary Exprcsi 1 T rgc'Qt* Priority'* Clear Linef To be issued on 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading : Case or Diarv No. If post eopv of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures •Only for Foreign Telegrams. fNot for Foreign Telegrams. Issued on Telegram l No. Dated D. 0 • 'to P.H. 1st October 1940/ 19 To ( T !y deai\ Co lone 1 N , / P / - CP. T 7ill\you please /efer to Sir Basil Newton’s lettt^ No. 361 of^ the 2nd’August,’194G, concerning [the Shaikh or^Kuwait’s date gardens ? 0, I enclose\a translation of a (Code word for telegrams.) x Oni ohai^OQ O. . 1 to the Shaikh (which the letter showed me this momihgjfor suc\ action as you jnay think fit. 3. i spoke to His highness about the 'Inheritance Deed' hut co’iild get fio direct reply out of himXdespiue S. 5 . MGIPC— SI— 24 t 3 (S&amp;P) irFP-(M- 214 S)— 8 - 12 - 37 — 90.000 Pad*.The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement^a). British Cousulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated A 4 .^... 00 .?. 0 ?!* 1 .'... 1940 Reference to previous correspondence : A v '' Kuwait telegram No#G/455 of 7th October 1940 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. British Embassy Bagdad telegram No.25 of 10th Shaikh of Kuwait's date October 1940* gardens in Iraq. i ftouJ Iul '5ELEGRAM Ambassador, Bagdad# Political Resident, Bushire. Prom To No• 25 • Dated 10th received 11th October 1940# \y^ ' y &gt;3 Your telegram No #698. 1 think it would be embarrassing to Good as judge in the case if i were to make such enci.ulri.es # Surely Shaikh’s lawyer should keep him informed. - NEWTONConfidential Political Agency, D.O. No. C/12 Kuwait, 9th January, 1941. T !y dear Colonel, The last time I was in Basra I took the opportunity to ask Good privately how the Land Settlement of the Subah Date Gardens was progressing. obtain which he requested ray help. He added that the Shaikh was adopting an obstructive attitude, and that Partu, the Shaikh’s lawyer, was ready to throw his hand in as he could get nothing out of the Shaikh. The requirements are in some cases Ithbat Wuratha , and. in others statements of the persons in whose names property should be registered. I have a list, with which I will not bother you, of Good’s present requirements. 3. I have not, of course, gone into details with Good as to whether all these documents are essential before the lanl can be registered in our favour (i.e. to safeguard the payment of compensation by His Majesty’s Government against the guarantee) or not. I have gathered that most of the lands are secure, and that if the documents now required are not forthcoming, Good will register the land in the name of the Subah, and leave it at that. This may be enough, but on the other hand it may not, and the essential fact for us to keep in mind, I think, is that His Majesty’s Government have at last succeeded in securing the appointment of a Settlement Officer acceptable to them, and that we must see that he is not hampered in the settlement by the Shaikh. The Hon’ble Lieut-Colonel C.G.Prior, CIE., Political Besident in the Persian Gulf Bu shire.2 - 3-(,i 4. If you agree to the above, the question arises as to the best way to obtain the information required without its being too obvious that I am in touch with Good. I do not see any real reason why I should not let the Shaikh know this, but it might somehow repercuss on Good later, so I suggest the best course is for me to inform the Shaikh before I go to Basra next time that I propose to see Tartu to find out how the Land Settlement is progressing. He can have nothing to say against this. With the information I can obtain from Partu (which will coincide with shat Good has written) we can write to the Shaikh and tie him down to definite answers. 5. The time is past when we can expect the Shaikh to help us in Bate Gardens matters, and we must, I think, act so as to ensure a settlement by the present commission despite any obstructions the Shaikh can put up. Yours sincerely,1A 0 GONFIDaHTIAl . D. O.N0.62-S. 2M The Residency* Bushire * the 21st January 1941» CONFIDENTIAL \ Kiiuxi it Receipt No b Dated ±lrft /y&gt;l X ,0/ Will you please refer to your demi-official letter Ko.G/l2&gt; dated the 9th January 19 41, on the subject of the Land settlement of the al Subah Date Gardens ? 2* I concur generally, and approve of the suggestion in your paragraph 4* - Major A.C# Gglloway, Political Agent, Kuwait*Telegram ITrom ' T o. Political \gont, Ka.vait. Political Resident, Pahrain. C/116 Dated, the 21st Pehmary, 1941. ng^T-O^ICIAX . L. ^ Your demi-official letter No. 62-3 of January 21st. 2. Documents have for nost part been submitted though there is difficulty over Ttnbat Taratha for certain 7 ao lands. n O • I no.v le^rn that Tracis are introducing a hill to amend settlement law precluding registration of land in the name of foreigners fi.e. non-Iraqi subject''. T propose to proceed Pasra early next veek and obtain full purport from POOD. Grateful for your approval. - Political - Telegram Prom To No. Q Political Resident, Pahrain. Political \gent, Kuwait. T/25 Dated the 22nd ^nd received the 23rd Pebruary, 1°41. Your telegram C/116 Tebruary 21st. Tr isit to Pasra approved. - ResidentD.O.NO.C/132 The \gency, Kuwait, 5th ' T arch, 1941. Tr , r 1 e‘'.r Colonel, Tith reference to your teie^raai ;46.T/£5 of the 22nd Mnu^ry^ I saw Good on the subject of the amendment to article 9 of the land Regis tration Taw and although he was aware of the proposal he had not taken any action. He was not sure if any amendment would have retrospective effect on land held before the passing of an amendment, if ever one is passed. 2. He promised to write to tne Xinbassy without mentioning me, and I will let you know the result in due course. ^ r ours sincerely, cf The Hon’ble Ileut-Col. J.G.Prior, CIS., Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf, Busiure.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000065_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/151</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000065</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/151</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 2/5 XII 'Ownership of HH Shaikh of Kuwait's Date Gardens in Iraq'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-20T11:18:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (268 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 270; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 2-269, and ff 18-269; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a continuation from IOR/R/15/5/150. It contains correspondence, memoranda and legal papers regarding law suits brought against the Shaikh of Kuwait [Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ] by the heirs of the former owners of the Al Faddaghiyeh, Al Bashiyah and Al Fao properties. The papers discuss: the seizure of the Fao estates by the Mudir of Basra, the eviction of the Shaikh's
                           fellaheen, and the eventual return of the properties and the fish and meat markets to the Shaikh's control; legal assistance for the Shaikh, following the conscription of his lawyer, Abdul Jalil Partu; the establishment by the Government of Iraq of a separate Land Settlement Area to cover the properties of the Shaikh in the Fao Nahiyah; and the appointment of Judge C Good to carry out the settlement procedure. The papers also concern the question of compensation to be paid to the shaikhs of Kuwait in respect of a) property potentially lost through litigation, and b) income lost through the imposition of
                           Istihlaktax, as well as proposals to discharge HMG from further obligations to the Shaikh regarding the garden properties.The file primarily consists of correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Foreign Office, the India Office Political Department, the Political Agent at Kuwait, and HM Ambassador to Iraq. It also contains letters received from the Shaikh of Kuwait (Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ), the Shaikh's son and acting representative in Basra (Shaikh Muḥammad Āl Ṣabāḥ), and the Shaikh's lawyer, Abdul Jalil Partu, as well as copies of outgoing letters to them.The file contains the following legal and case documents (English translations unless otherwise stated):Copy judgement of the Court of Cassation regarding the referral of the Faddaghiyah case to the President of the Land Settlement Committee in the Fao Nahiyah, ff 103-104.Correspondence between Shaikh Ahmad, Shaikh Muhammad, and Abdul Partu, regarding the Tapu deeds for the properties, and the registration of appeal documents with the Courts, ff 170-176.Land settlement notifications from
                              al Waqa'i al-Iraqiyya, ff 198-200, 255.English and Arabic copies of the compensation offer to the Shaikh, plus a draft discharge agreement, ff 218-224.A private note by Judge C Good of the Basra Court of Instance, to Major Galloway, regarding the Land Settlement Procedure, ff 261-262.The file is continued under reference IOR/R/15/5/152.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Muḥammad Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Basrah</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><subject><topic>Taxation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000065#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>