<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003ba_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:18:05.032Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IZ/Zo % PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 11th March, 1949. (12/9/49) i. I forward herewith a copy of a telegram received from the Foreign Office in reply to one from Galloway enquiring whether the Colonial Prisoners Removal Act (compare Article 1G of the Qatar Crder-in- Council) could be useu for the removal of an American prisoner to the United Kingdom. 2. With reference to paragraph 5 of the enclosure, I hope shortly to inspect the accommodation available for European prisoners in the Bahrain fort myself. In the meanwhile, I should be glad to know whether in your opinion a European or American prisoner could reasonably be lodged there for a period of up to six months. If not, do you think the Bahrain Govern ment could be persuaded to provide new accommoda tion or improve that which already exists? C.J. Pelly, Esq., CBE., Political Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. BAHRAIN R TEIPT.- n...,Pat.*4 Mjlf}&gt; Telegram m From Foreign Office, London, To Political Resident, Bahrain. Telegram No. 105 Dated 2/3 received 4th March 1949, Important/Confidential . Adaressed to Bahrain telegram No, 105 of 2nd IV.arch repeated for inforrration to Kuwait, Kuwait telegram No, IS to you. There are no legal objections to removal. 2, Home Office are (have) however disturbed at (made the) following stipulations: a) Prisoners not to be removed until period within which they may appeal has lapsed. b) Prisoners to have at least six months of their sentence left to serve on arrival in the U.K. c) Cost of removal to be borne by the Foreign Office if the Oil Company do not meet. 3, If the need arises in the particular case you mention I hope you can improvise tolerable p'rison accommodation for the first 30 days or the whole of the sentence if less than six months. I understand Bahrain Fort has been used for such purposes in the past and would hope that some expedient could be found at Kuwait. If not you might consider an order of prohibition under article 23 of Kuwait Orders-in-Council, This method which allows no appeal could only be- used with great care and if evidence clearly establishes guilt and I should wish to be consulted when it is proposed to use it against a United States citizen. 4, Alternatively Political Agent might thus use his influence to have the offence compounded, 5, I shall be glad to have your comments on the possibility of persuading the Shaikhs of Banrain and Kuwait to build (or properly adapt a building for use as) a prison suitable for non-Asiatic prisoners. Responsibility of the Shaikhs cannot in view of the large number of resident European population seem clear and cost would be small. Provision has been included in the new draft Orders-in-Council for the removal of prisoners between all Gulf States with the intention that non-Asiatics might be given the most suitable prison accommoda tion available, 6, It has been informally suggested to Kuwait Oil Company that they might employ an official upon any legal side of the Company business at Kuv ; ait who would be responsible for acting part-time as legal Counsel for the Company employees. The Company are actively pursuing the question and meanwhile are providing counsel in important cases. = SECRETARY OF STATE =S.O.No.C/R-92. POLITICAL AGENCY, Bahrain, Dated 16/17th March 1949. Dear Sir Rupert, In my opinion a European or American prisoner could reasonably be lodged in the Bahrain Fort for a period of up to six months. In fact in 1946, as Political Agent, Bahrain, I sentenced a Naval Officer named Webster to six months imprisonment; Galloway, I think, reduced the sentence to three months, but Webster spent this confined in the Fort - and this was in the hot weather. I do not know the exact position at the moment, the previous accommodation may have been re-allotted, but, if necessary, I have no doubt it could be made available. This is in reply to your semi-official letter No.(12/9/49), dated the 11th March, 1949. Yours sincerely. 9 His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE, CSI Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.(12/11/49) MINUTES. Mr. Belgrave informed me that there is one cell suitable for European prisoners in the police fort at Bahrain. He has no objection to a prisoner from Kuwait being accommodated in this provided it is not already occupied. (Signed) W. R. HAY. 18th March, 1949. aTHE PEHSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. (12/31/49) 30th May, 1949. Dear Jackson 9 Please refer to your letter No,C/II4(32/11) of the Ilth May, 2, I have inspected the cell for Europeans here which Cochrane a^suios me is in accordance with United Kin gdom standards. It is 10 1 x 12 1 and about II• high. It has two windows with a double grille and no glass. There is a flush lavatory in the corner with the plus outside which has to be pulled by the sentry as occasion arises. There is a low wooden board bed fixed to the floor, Cochrane says a concrete slab is more usual and more satisfactory, A mattress and bed linen have to be provided. Food for European® prisoners is supplied when required from the kitchen of the British Sergeant who lives in the Fort, 3, The above may perhaps give you something to go on with in your next approach to the Sheikh, I think two cells for Europeans should be sufiioient in the first place. Apart from prisoners you may find it nece ssary to confine European lunetics as has happened in Bahrain, 4, So far as Asiatics are concerned, I would suggest that if the Kuwait authorities allow it you should inspect their prison and make quite sure that it is not suitable for Asiatics under our jurisdiction before you ask for special accommodation to be provided, 5, I have not answered all the questions raised in your two letters, some can be dealt with as they arise, e.g, if the Sheikh refuses to pay for the accommodation asked for, I shall refer the matter to the Foreign Office, end others must await the arrival of the Judicial Adviser who is expected in the early autuinn. If when discussing the question with the Sheikh you find an opportunity of persuading him to employ a British sergeant for the purpose amongst other things of looking after European prisoners, so much the better. G.N, Jackson, iiiSQ,, M, B, £• , Political Agent, KUWAIT, Yours ever, Sd/- W,R,HAY,c Q ^ X THE POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. No.0/167(32/1) 23rd June, 1949. Dear Sir Rupert, ^A Pletse refer to your letter No.12/31/49 of 30th May, 1949. 2, I hc .ve taken up the question with His Highness of jcrovidlng prison fr.cccmirodatlon here for Europeans and Americans, He has agreed to build the necessary accocuLOdation and has said that, as soon as the State Architect returns from Ramdhan leave (he is a Lebanese and appears to be reasonably qualified), he will go into the whole question with his new police officers whom he hopes to have here fairly soon. 3. The idea at present is to build a new police barracks inside the Naif Fort with quarters on the first storey for one of the British police officers. Alongside the barracks it is intended to provide prison accommodation for Europeanf and Americans so thaty they can be supervised by the British police officer and probably fed from his kitchen too. The Naif Fort has a large uncongested area inside and this plan appears to me to be^good one. 4. I havo also inspected the existing prison r accommodation which is situated in a separate •• building about a quarter of a mils from the Naif Fort. I agree with Andrew (his letter No # R/I34 (32/11) of I2th August, 1948) that it is not really suitable for Asiatics subject to our Jurisdiction, except possibly the least sophisticated of them. The Sheikh has, however, agreed to set aside one court-yard solely for persons subject to our Juris diction and to have tt cleared up and made more habitable. This should meet our needs. Yours ever, Sd/- G.N.JACKSON. H.E. Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN,tm rmsiAti quit *k£iumci 9 AAHrJOJ. (12/34/49) 12th 19*9. uv / In t ara $ of foreign Ofiic® Mo. 105 ol the 2nd March I was &amp;s*.ed for ay cog ent# on the possibility of porsuaaing the bheikhs of Xaw&amp;it ana ^ahrUn to build a prison suitable for -i aon^siatic prisoners # I fcrtvard hercvith a copy ^ of ny letter 12/31/49 of t.he 30th Uay to Jackson ana a copy of his reply* 2, fou eill se^ xroK ay letter that a suitable cell for Europeans and aaericfcCf alr«ady exists in Bfehraiiu It is very rarely occupied and I hardly think it necessary at present to address the Bahrain Qovern&amp;ent to ooild a second cell on siuiilar lines. 3« Xhe result of the approach aade by Jackson^ to the ^heUch of £ii«4iit appears very satisfactory* As I have already reported| vide ay letter to you Ho. $7/7/49 of June 2Ist 9 he has asked Keap to obtain lor hia the services of three British police sergeants, 4 # X aiR seruiicg a copy of this letter to Jackson* £urrcun, Esq. ^ Foreign Oilice, LuD.O. No Adviserajte, October 8, 19U9. \%/ With reference to the question of the % ^American prisoner from Kuwait, I enclose Urherewith correspondence on the subject of liropeans prisoners which please return when one through. i lo H. G. Jakins, Esq., H. E, M*s Political Agent, Bahrain.No,0/516-68. POLICE FORT Bahrain, dated 26th September, 1949, o Dear Mr, Smith, Reference our recent conversation on the subject of the Jail for Europeans and Americans, At present we have no proper and adequate Jails for EuropearB and Americans, This matter has been considered two years ago and a letter was written to the P,A, about it, a copy of the letter is attached herewith. No reply so far as been received, But however we have in the mean time one room which is being used as a lock up for Europeans and Americans. It is very much similar to those being used in England, Yours sincerely, Sgd, Khalifah bin Mohammed A1 Khalifah. G,W,R, Smith, Esq,, M.B,E,, Actdmg Adviser to the Bahrain Govt,Government of Bahrain Police Department. No. 996 of 1366/1947 Office of the Commandant State Police, Bahrain Dated 4th Dul-Karda,1366 16th September, 1947. To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. At present, the State Police Prison has no properly arranged accommodation for the confinement of persons com mitted from the Agency Courts and who are of western na tionality. I propose providing such accomrodation and wish to put the whole matter of such prisoners on a proper basis. I would therefore be grateful if you would inform me what you would consider proper in connection with the following:- CELLS;- Size, ventilation, lights, beds, fans if necessary, etc. MEALS:- Type of food, number of meals per day and approximate times. WORK:- The type of work ix a prisoner could be employed on and for how many hours per day and during what periods of the day. FORM OF IMPRISONMENT:- Prisoners may be committed to rigorous or simple imprisonment. What would be regarded as the essential differences? SANITATION:- What would be considered proper bathing and lavatory facilities? Sgd. for Commandant, State Police.No.C/L-371. Political Agency, Bahrain, October 13, 1949. Dear Smith, I return herevvith the cor respondence you were good erough to send me with your note No.2860-16 of October 8. 2, I wonder If Hyde has any knowledge of prison standards at home. Yours sincerely, H.O. Jaklns G .W.R. Smith, Esq., Manamah.C~D No. of 1369 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 5th Muharram 1369 October 27, 1949. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - f J^ * Reference your letter N o. C/L-37'' dated 13th October 19U9. I enclose herewith a note submitted by Sub Inspector Hyde about prison standards in England. Adviser to the Government. TXjr Cfl ^J.H. / No. of 1369/1949. Office of Traffic Branch. State Police, Bahrain. Dated, 2nd, Muharrara, 1369. 22nd, October , 1949. S upe rintemdent, State Police, Bahrain. With refernece to letter No» C/L-371. from H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain, and attached reports asking for information of prison standards in England. The Prison Service in England is a seperate department from the Police Service. The following report is based on some knowledge of prison conditions and the treatment of prisoners by Police before sentence. CELLS:- MEAISi- WORKi- Similar to the present one now in use at the Fort. This cell measures approx imately 12 feet by 9 feet and 12 feet high. Ventilation appears adequate. Lights should be covered by wire and out of reach also fans if found to be necessary. Beds, usually a wooden platform with canvas covered matteessjknd pillow for easy cleaning. Usually three meals per day of plain food, such as bread, margarine, meat, fish, cheese and potatoes. Tea, coffee or cocoa. All food is rationed, each prisoner is allowed for example 6 ounces of bread per day, 4 ounces of meat per day etc. Times of meals would be to suit local conditions© In all cases prisoners are expected to sweep and clean their cells, wash houses etc, and clean cooking utensils. Also keep the jail generally clean and tidy. I believe that persons undergoing Simple imprisonment are only required to do work inside the jail. Sentence of Hard Labour means that a prisoner is sometimes required to perform some task eutside the jail, When considering the type of work most suitable, a prisoner is, whenever possible, given a task in which he can ply his trade. The number of hours and time of day for work would depend a good deal upon the climate. FORI! OF IMPRIS ONMENT i - SANITATION:- All prisoners are required to do some form of work. Prisoners undergoing Simple imprisonment are usually allowed some amenities at certain times of the day, namely. Cigarettes, reading and contact with other prisoners. Rigorous imprisonment (Hard Labour) requires a prisoner to work longer hours and less privileges. All prisoners arc able to earn a remittance of sentence for good behaviour. In England, three months per year. Local Prison Regulations should be made known to prisoners when entering prison. A water closet would be necessary for each cell which could be flushed from inside the cell. For bathing facilities I would suggest communal showers with hot and cold water. In all items shown above, local and climatic conditions would have to be considered. State Police.No .C/L-399. Political Agency, Bahrain, November 5, 1949, \b A Dear Belgrave, Many thanks for your memorandum No.59-16 of 27th October, enclosing a note submitted by Sub Ins pector Hyde. 2. I assume th:t this note is in the hands Shaik/i Khalifah and that no further action is necessary / in connection with Smith's letter No.2860-16 of 8th October. If however there is any further information which I may be able to obtain for you, please let me know. Yours sircerely, J.A .F. Crethin C.D. Eelgrave, Esq., C .E .E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. - JNo - C/R-513. Political Agency, Bahrain. H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to fhe Political esidency, Jufair, and forward herewith a;'copy of the undermentioned document(s) ^ Reference to previous corresponds 5; Residffjcy c.s, No.l?/34/49 of Ji^ly 12, 3949. Description r Subject ^ \jo* Letter dated 22nd October, Prison standards in 1949, from Sub Ihspector Hyde England. of the Bahrain State Police to the Superintendent, S^ate Police. 1 Dated November 6, 1949,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003ba_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/587</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003ba</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/587</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 18/20 Accommodation for European and American Prisoners in Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-06-17T00:03:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers written in crayon (red for incoming, blue for outgoing correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system comences at 1 on the front cover and terminates at 19 on the last folio before the back cover. The numbers are written in pencil and appear in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomaly: 1, 1A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns enquiries into the nature of prison accommodation available in Bahrain for European and American prisoners, and includes correspondence from Sir William Rupert Hay, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agent, Bahrain; and the Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.The papers also include copies of correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Gordon Noel Jackson, Political Agent, Kuwait; and the Foreign Office, London about proposals for the construction of prison accommodation for Europeans and Americans in Kuwait, May-July 1949.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Prisons</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0003ba#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>