<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-27T14:22:43.790Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">t Confident i&amp;l&gt; %(t -T^l- ilo.lOl-S of 1932. , 'ia &lt;=vrt^ SP / (a) British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 18th February 1932. From - The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Political Agent, Muscat. r\ No.S.11004/44 of 6.2.32. Sir, y I am directed to forward herewith copy of a letter received from the Air Officer Commanding, regarding the installation of a fuel tank at Khor Jarama. The tank at Yas Island is embedded in cement and is to all intents and purposes invulnerable. The local Arabs have actually broken off some of the fittings of the tank, but it does not affect its utility in any way, and if a similar tank is installed at Khor Jarama, Colonel Biscoe does not think it will be possible for the local Arabs seriously to damage it, though it might be desirable perhaps for the Royal Air Force to appoint a couple of chowkidars, who would also be useful in getting supplies and rendering assistance generally whenever a flying boat landed in the Khor. The Hobble the Political Resident would be glad if you would kindly approach the Muscat State regarding this matter and ascertain from them whether they have any objection to the installation of the tank. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.'r-rff- &amp; © 'r-rff- &amp; © (?) Rafer^nce j - s. 11004/44. AIR HF.ADmART] , ' IRACJ CCMMAUP, HINA 101. 6th Fobrunry, 1932. I1^TALJ^ I : I I0N .A- m.l A r&gt; ’ &gt; KHQR ^ RAM. Sir, I havft th»3 honour to refer to the discussion which I hAd with you during the cruise in the PERSI AN QULP last December regarding the installation of a petrol tarile in KHOR JA bvMA. You will renember / t&gt;mt I selected as the moat suitable site for such a slffie- the sandy beach in the Horth-T^st corner of the Khor * opposite which the ilangoona anchored dur5.ng their stay there. 2, In view of the heavy swell which ia apt to arise in the Harbour of MUSCAT, flying boata can only take-off from that harbour lightly loaded. The weather conditions, however, at KHOR J A RAMA ai'e suitable in any weather and it is desirable, therefore, that the main refuelling point for flying boats on the route from MUSCAT to ADEN should be located in the sheltered waters of KHOR JARAMA. 3. I should be glad to have your confirmation that there is no political objection to the placing of a fuel tank at KHOA JaAA&amp;A, of a similar type to that which has already been placed at YAS Island. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Se vant. (SGD.) C L COURTNEY. Air Vice-Marshal, Conmanding ’Iraq Command. The Hon’ble Political Resident in the Persian Aulf, The Residency, B U S I I R .i Ho. 3 ? Political Agency &amp; H.B.K’s Consulate, I'uscat, 3 February 1932. /'V To H.H. Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. A. C. The Hon'ble the Political Resident informs me that the Air Officer Commanding in Iraq wishes to instal a petrol tank at Khor Jeremah for the refueling of flying boats which may call there. The tank will be similar to one which has already been established at Yas Island. It will be tobeded in cement and therefore it will not be possible for any local Bedouins to harm it. May I inform the Resident that Your Highness has no objection. U.E. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Lt-Colonel Consul. PTo - Lt-Colonel T.C. Fowle, Consul and Political Agent, Muscat. Dated 23rd Shawal 1350 (,/-3-32). A.C. : 3 I received your letter Do.38 of 28th February 1932 asking permission to instal a petrol tank at Khor Jerameh, as intimated to you by the Hon’ble the Political Resident on behalf of the Air Officer Commanding Iraq. I am very pleased to allow the Government Air Force tc establish a petrol tank at Khor Jeramah and request you to inform the Hon f ble the Political Resident accordingly. But will you kindly let me know what place of the khor you are selecting for the purpose? In conclusion please accept my high regard. 8 d. Said bin Taimur.f 0 Telegram .From political Resident. To political ^,ent, Muscat. No. x149 Dated and received 9th February 1932. The Air Ministry aesires to ^ut two 4^)0 gallon jje.tr ol tanks at IChor Jar amah has the btate any objection? Rejjly sent that State has no objection. T.C.F. 9/2/32. iTelegi-aiB From fcl/36 r */ \ 7 R 2? Secretary cl' State for Inula, Lonoon. ) To Governrneotof Inula, ForejgnM Political Department, New Delhi. No 760 Repeated to Political Resident, K.M.S.Shcreham'* 761 f Dateu received 9tn March Important. Air facilities between Aden ana muscat. Air Mnistry uesire to construct two aOOC gallon fuel tanks at Khor Jarama, site already selectee. ^hey v/o’ilu be ccnagneu to Muscat ana transport thence arranged locally. Please telegraph your views. 2. On tne near future, but not at the moment, similar installation may be aesirea at or near Ma s i r a h Island. Seere ta ry of $ tate for ±rdia. Copy to Political Agent, Muscat for information. tTnuer Secretary to Political Resident in toe Persian Cull./ tU/26 Telegram R ^7 (E) From Political Reeident, M.M.S.Shoreham. To GoveiTiment of Inaia, Foreign &lt;&amp; Politics! department. iNew delai. Pepeatea to Secjetary of £-tate for Inaia, London. No T /06 Latea 9th March 1932. hi for Inaia. Telegram No 760 irom Secretary of State Muscat State agree to installation of tanks at Knor Jaiama, ana I see no objection. /hi 2. I am informed taat F.pyal^ Force now desire to store petrol in tins in small building at Masirah ana not in tanks. Flying boat ana Pol tical Agent are going tiieie stiorlly ana v.ill aiscuss mattei witn local Sueikh. Pesiuent. Copy to Political Agent, Muscat for information 9/3/32 TTrder Secretary to the Pol tical Resident in the Per sian Gulf. ■'HI'British hesiaenqy &amp; GOiieul^te-ueneral, Busnire, the ioth April x9Z'c. A copy of the unaenuen ti onea paper is lorwaraea to tne Politioax Ao^ut, muscat, ref .ce cor res uonaence enaia^ with tnis oifice letter no.rdx-b of tne xbtn February x93&lt;:, for favour of disposal in direct - —-r-- with Air neadquarters, Iraq Conuuand, jja^ncad. it is requested -that copies of all correspondence should ue furnished for the information of the Hon'ble the political Resident. % )bb His Highness tne Sultan»s acqiiiesence in the installa tion of the tanic does not appear to have oeen received in tnis office. .by order, secretary to the political Resident in the Persian sulf ******** Letter no* GE/b/8Pi/SH/ 5, dated the 7th Apri-*- from the Chid engineer, Air Headquarters, Iraq command, naghdad; to the Hon’ole the Political nesident in the % Persian Gulf, nushire* cu. 1 C*. ^ r ^ .■No.C- of 1932. The .Political Agent/ &amp; H.B.M* a Coneulate ft. Mueeat, the ^Xpril 1932. To Meesra K.JB.Naeib bin Mohammed &amp; Son Contractors, Mueeat. Memorandum. I have received a communication from t] ^hicf Engineer, Iraq Command, to the effect that it is^roposed to install petrol and oil tanks in Khor Jaramah. His Highness the Sultan has already given his permission. It is suggested that the contract for the installation might be given to your firm. In the first instance it is desired to arrive at the approximate cost of the work. Could you therefore furnieh an approximate estimate which will not be considered as a formal tender. The details of the work to be executed are as follows p- (a) The inetallation will consist of two 4,000 gallon petrol tanks, each about 14 feet long and 7^ feet, in diameter, weighing approximately 2£ tons each, and two 250 gallon oil tanks each about 5 feet long and fast diameter, weighing £ ton each. (b) The above tanks will be supplied by the Air Ministry and will be delivered to the Contractor at the wharves at Muscat, together with certain fitments and pipe connections, which will entail a total weight of tanks and fitments of approximately 3 tons. (e) The Contractor will transfer these stores to dhows provided by him, eonvey them to Khor Jaramah, land them, and transport them to a locality on the foreshore which will be indicated by a representatives of the Air Ministry. (d) Holes are to be executed for each tank of approximately the following dimensionst- For the 4000 gallon petrol tanks ~ 17 feet long by 9 feet wide by 11 feet deep. For the 250 gallon oil tanks - 7£ feet long, by 5 feet wide by 6 feep deep. (e) A layer of eonerete 6 inehes thifik is to be laid at the bottom of each hole, the tank set thereon, and the eavity is then to be filled in with concrete till the top surface of the eonerete is 2 feet below gmund level*in tk« «as« of the petrol tanks, and 1 foot below ground level in tke ease of the oil tanks* The eomposition of eonerete will be 1 part of Portland eement to 3 parts of washed sand to 6 parts of broken stone. The quantities of eonerete will be approximately 750 foot eube for eaeh petrol tank, and 120 foot eube for eaeh oil tank* (f) The Contraetor will be required to supply the eement, sand and broken stone, and water free from salt, for making the eonerete* (g) The Air Ministry will provide a fitter for the conneeting up all pipes and fitments, and the Contraetor will be required to supply the fitter with sueh unskilled labour as he may require for the purpose of lifting and hafcdling the pipes and fitments* (h) The work of the eontraetor will be supervised by an Overseer supplied for that purpose by the Air Ministry* (i) The Contraetor will be required to bear all charges in connection with tne transport, subsistenee, and aceom~ modation of his workmen* The Air Ministry will arrange for the subsistenee and accommodation of the Fitter and Overseer provided by them, but the contraetor will be responsible for conveying these two men between Muscat and Xhor Jaramah, and for supplying them with water, fit for drinking, during their stay at Khor Jaramah* (j) The Contraetor will provide all necessary tools for the work to be performed by him, but the Air Ministry will provide the tools and stores required by the fitter* It is understood that during the Yearling Season, you may experience difficulty in obtaining dhows, and workmen* It is therefore requested that separate approximate prices may be quoted for the work (a) during the pearling Season, (b) not in the J»e(rWling Season* political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscata*.C-&lt;T'3 0{ 1932 The FoXitical Agency it H.B.M’e Consulate /($ © Muscat,the 29th April 1932 From LieuteColonel T.C.Fowle, C.BeE., Political Agent &amp; HeB.M's Consul, Muscat* The Chief Engineer, Iraq Command, Hinaidi, Baghdad. Subject:- Petrol and Oil Tanks at Khor Jaramah* Sir I haye the honour to inform you that extracts of &gt; paragraphs 3,4 and 5 of your letter KoeC.E/B/821/32/3, doted the 7th April 1932, to the address of the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, were for warded to K.B*Hasib bin Mohamed &amp; Son and I attach a copy of their reply agreeing to carry out the required work for Rs* 5,000/-. I hare the honour to be Sir Your most obedient serrant Political Agent &amp; M*B*M v s ConsulHo.C- of 1932. The Political Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat,the 29th April 1932. J A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Secretary to the Political Resident in the ^ Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference his endorsement V Ko.229-3, dated the 15th April 1932, with the compliments of the Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscatf Letter Ho.C- ‘fJ , dated the 29th April 1932, to the Chief Engineer, Iraq Command, Hinaidi, with enclosure.- ? IBushire, 4th May 1932. Sir, »(^ With reference te paragraph 4 (c) of your letter No. CE/B/821/32/3, oatea 7th April 1932, I am directed to state that the Muscat State has asked to be informed of the site on which it is proposed to install the petrol and oil tanks at Khor Janaatna, and to request that if the approximate site has been decided on its location may kindly be communicated direct to the Political Agent, Muscat, with copy to this office. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, 0 a — / £4* Capt Secretary to the Political Kesiaent in the Persian Gulf. To The Chief Engineer, ’Iraq Command, Rotjal Air Force, Hinaidi, IRAQ. Copy to the Political Agent, Muscat, with reference te his memorandum No. C-90, dated 2bth April 1932. w■V f No. CE/B/821/32/ Office of the Chief Engineer, 'Iraq Command, Hinaidi, 2* M ay, 1932. Sir, PETROL AND OIL TANKS AT XHOR JORAMAH. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your iL ; &gt;letter No.^C.93 of 1932, dated 29th April, 1932, with its enclosure. 2. It is presumed that the provisional quotation of Rs.5,000/=, received from K.B.Nasib bin Mohamed &amp; Son, will not be seriously affected by the information as to the site proposed for the tanks, conveyed to you in this Office letter No. CE/B/821/32/11, dated 16th May, 1932. 3. A further communication will be addressed to you, should it be decided to place a definite contract with K.B Nasib bin Mohamed &amp; Son. Colonel, Chief Engineer, 'Iraq Command. Lieut.-Colonel T.C. FOWLE, C.B.E., Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, MUSCAT.No.C- /QZot 1932. 3^1 22 . The Political Agaac./ ^ H.a.Ji ’j Consulate, Muscat, 7 * •fune 1932. To His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan oi Muscat &lt;Ss Ozan, Your Highness, With reference to Your Highness*s letter dated the 1st March 1932, I have the honour to ini'orm you that the approximate site chosen for the petrol and oil tanks at Khor Jaramah is on the sandy beach in the ftorth hast corner of the Khor, which was used as a camping ground for the Muscat infantry during the recent 3ur operations. Your Highness*s sincere friend, Lt-Colonel Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul.Ho.C- of 1932. The Political Agency Sc H.B.M’s Consulate, Muecat, 7th June 1932. X7 ft 3ir Petrol &amp; Oil at ^Ctior Jaramah. With reference to ^aragraiih 2 of your letter No. CE/B/821/32/19 dated the 20th May 1932, 1 have the honour to inform you thc.t the frovivSional quotation of Ls.5000/- will not hfc ttfieoied ad no location of any Arte h«* 0 been mentioned. 1 nave ti*e honour tc be. Sir, lour mG*»t obedient servant, i t-Colonei, Poxitical ^ Cotidul&lt; to The Chief Engineer, Iraq Command, 'iinaidi**1 If0.C_y33 of 1933. Ths Pnlltl«al Agency &amp; H.B*K 9 a Coneulote. Muaoot, June 1933. To Tho Council of Hegcncy, Kuooet .tote. i After Compliments. I om informed by tho Royol Air Force they eenire to place petrol storage tonka at bor Jchroma. This ie not a nev* ecUcme but It hetfj been under ooneideretion for the last yefir. Fnginoero and workmen r/lll be arriving here very eoon and will proceed to Ilhor Jerama by Sedan. It will be necosenry for them to engage local gur.rde end moke arrangements for water supply at 'itor J or uni anti I wUl be grateful if you will kindly order the Sheikh of Aac ol Had to meet the noxt flying boat that arrives at Ahor Jtirmaa in order to tauke orrongemecta about tneee tninge. X should be glad uleo if you vill would send an Interpreter with the next flying boot who will ranke whatever Arrangements are required with tho Sheikh of Roe al Had. The camp will be quite o big one and work la expected to ge on for at least one month. This ie whf-t had to be said and selcntap Captain, Political /gent &amp; H.B.K f e Consul, Muscat.C[l*( •f 1933. The I'olitiaal Agency &amp; H.B.M’b Consulate Muscat, 16th June 1933. Te The Ceunell of Kegeney, Museet State. After CompliinentB. Vlth reference to ny letter Be. /133 dated 12th June 1933 on the ^ oubjoet of placing patrol tunks by the Royal Air - oroo at xChor JaraMa, I hove the honour to inform you that a flying boat will arrive at nuacat on the 20th instant. I shall be highly obliged if you will kindly inform your representative to be ready to ge te Xher Jaramah by the same flying beat. This la what had te be said and salaams. Captain, pelitical Agent &amp; Consul,KuaectLetter No.220 dr ted 23rd Safer 1352 (17th June 1933) / fron the Council of fto£ency, Muscat State, to LrJor c.L.TJ. Brenner, ’\C., Foliticel A^ent B Tr .:.l'*e Consul,r?u£cet(^j ^ - c - V/e have received your letter f, o.l4x doted the 16th June 1933 infornins us that o flying boat vill arrive on the 20 th instant end that our representative should he ready to go to rhor Jarana hy the sane flying hoot. m he Council have decided to send Saiyid FeTuud hy the flying * hoat to !ihor Jarame in order to study the situation and to i-iake the necessary arrangements for the erection of the petrol tanks. 7 e have today sent some persons in advance to meet Saiyid i'ahnud on his arrival thereaSCTION OFFICE To The Honourable, Political Agent. MUSCAT. W &amp; B. H.A#F. B^A S R A H sz/t /33. 'g&amp;l lo Sir, The hearer of this letter,Hatha Singh is my Works Supervisor engaged on duties in the Persian Gulf.He is pro- -ceeding from Sharjah to Muscat about the 14th June for the purpose of making preliminary local arrangements in connec- ~tion with the work shortly to be commenced on the installer -tion of the bulk petrol tanks at Khor Jarama for the Royal Air Force* In this connection I should be very grateful if you would be good enough,if the occasion arises,to see that he is afforded any facility or assistance that might be re- -quired in the course of his arrangements# An officer from the Department will be arriving at Muscatabout 21st June and I should be extremely obliged if you would discuss with him our proposed programme of % work which I trust will meet with your approval#Your advice to him on any relative matters would be very much appreciated* I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servantHo . c/$(&gt; of 1933. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate Muscat* ^ July 1933* To The Council of Regency* Muscat State* After Compliments* I have the honour to express my extreme gratitude to four Honours for all the assistance you hare afforded in securing dhows for carrying the Royal Air itorce materials to rfhor Jarama* This is 'what had to be said and salaams* Major* political Agent &amp; a Consul, Muscat*o O (10/7/33) Letter No,^34 dated 16tii Rabi 1,1352/irom the uouncil of Regency, Muscat btate, to Major C.E.U.Bremner, M*C*, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul* Muscat. A*C \7e have received your letter i^o.C/133 dated 12th June ^933 intimating that the R*A.F. desire to erect petrol tanks at Khor Jarama and that engineers would arrive at Muscat and thence proceed with labourers to that place. You have also stated that the scheme is not a new one but it has been under consideration since the last year and asked us to make arrangements for guards, etc. The Council sent aayid m ahmud with you to Ahor Jarama where he, as you are aware, made the necessary arrangements for guards and water. We hope tnat the work will be carried out and completed satisfactorily and that the Qfficers of the K.A.F. will return quite satisfied with the guards and the assistance that has been given to them. TJ. E // 1(Telegram W/T § From - Political, Muscat. To - 203 Squadron, Basra. No. nil. Dated 30th. July 1933. Following for Sqdn Ldr. ChicJc begins If original flying boat indefinitely delayed consider another should come earliest possible as Khor Jarama unvisited for considerable time now. Ends. Telegram W/T From iC 2134 To 203 Squadron, Repeated Basrah, Muscat, P.A. and W &amp; B. figgdii No.Cy/53 dated 1st August. Situation Khor Jararaa satisfactory work will be Seen. C.E.U.B. 1 / 8 . completed in 4 daysif Hi tHEJSsioi ANo.K/ of 193 Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Coneusee.t Recess office, Killarney Hotel, Karachi, August 1933. To The Council of Regency, muscat State. After Compliments. I have learned that the building party from Khor Jarma has returned after the successful accomplishment of their mission. 1 ^ould take this opportunity of again thanking Your Honours for all the assistance you have been good enough to afford me in carrying out of this w 0 rk. This is what had to salaams. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.HHHH — —</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/94</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/94</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 2/18 II. AVIATION B. ROYAL AIR FORCE. (3H) R. A. F. Landing Ground at Khor Jarama’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:02:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (39 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 41; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file includes correspondence concerning the British Air Ministry’s request for the installation of a fuel tank at the landing ground at Khor Jarama. The installation contract was given to Khan Bahadur Nasib bin Mahomed and Son, Naval and Landing Contractor. The file also includes correspondence with the Government of Muscat and Oman regarding granting permission for the work to take place, and arrangement for
                           dhaws[dhows, sailing vessels] to carry the Royal Air Force (RAF) materials to Khor Jarama.The main correspondents in the file are: Air Headquarters, British Forces in Iraq; the Political Resident, Bushire; the Political Agent, Muscat; and the Government of Muscat and Oman.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Khor Jarama</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Air force</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>AHQ Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Air Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Airfields</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002e6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>