<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-12-05T15:56:04.842Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">FILE COPY -GREAT- - •G€OR&lt;jE' - -STRf ET LONDON St. Michael’s Roaa, BOUHR BMOUIH, -StWtJ- Bants. Replies to this communication should be addressed to the Comptroller-General, quoting 28986/40. Your reference COPY rENT L'Y AIR MAIL at &lt;( t Bournemouth 7280. Telephone : WfitteharH ■9049 — Telegrams : Advantage, Pari, London After 5.30 p.m. Bournemouth 7284. 23ru December 1940. rr- ju Would you refer to India Office communication of the 7th October (P.Z.2626/40) about International Traders of Karachi. We have had a telegram from the company stating that their business has ceased owing to import restrictions on American radios and they therefore urgently require the agency in India for British radios. They ask us to advise manufacturers to send them details of their gooas. This we should normally have done excepting that, on looking through the 'Who's Who in Afghanistan' sent under form from the India Office on the 22nd October (P.Z.5698/40), we did not like the Soviet connections of Ahmed Shah. As the goods in question were radio supplies, we thought it would be advisable to obtain Foreign Office views on the degree of assistance which we could give. My own view was that since, as I believe is the case, our radio manufacturers have enough export orders, we might have replied that we regretted that no manufacturers seemed to be in a position to take up further agencies. If he had approached them direct and they had asked us for information, G.E.Crombie Esq., India Office, Whitehall, London, 3. W. 1. 1 KCd. NT. 1 pi {ENCLOSURE /|^ e AIR MAIL LETTER 1 26 DEC 1940 No. - ? 11 jaw 1D41 litjOjA OFFIC Ej FROM SECRETARY INDIA OFP.Cc.we could have suggested that International Traders were not entirely suitable. However, unfortunately, I find that Internationa Traders have also telegraphed direct to the Radio Manufacturers War Export Group, who have advised their members to communicate direct with the Karachi firm. If your view, and that of the Foreign Office, is that it would be unwise to have any dealings with International Traders, we can, I think, probably approach the secretary of the Group and through him try and persuade any manufacturers who may have shown interest, to let the matter drop. If, on the other hand, neither you nor the Foreign Office have any objection to the Soviet connections of Ahmed Shah, we need take no action. I have sent a copy of this letter to Mr. Mackenzie. P.s. Mr. Monier Vi/llliams was seconded to the Board of Trade a year ago and perhaps you would not mind asking your Registry to send the Afghanistan documents in future to me:* ’) jr ■ b w hiInformation regarding the firm,International Traders of Karachi. Please refer to your demi-official letter No. P.2.1365/40, dated the Uth JMarch 1940. of importers, exporters and manufacturers* representatives. It was started in 1934 by Ahmad Shah (W. ^Afghanistan 148) who is its sole proprietor. The concern has branches in Peshawar and Karachi. According to the report of the bankers Ahmad Shah is well to do and respectable and conducts his business on satisfactory lines. The firm has no connection with the Afghan National Bank. 3. In July 1939, import and export licenses were issued by the Government of India at the instance of the Afghan Government in connection with the in$&gt;ort of high explosive shells from Henry Disston and Sons, Inc., Philadelphia through this firm. 4. I am to add that Ahmad Shah is still believed to be anti-British and in touch with the Soviet iSmbassy at Kabul and that in present circumstances we do not think I that the purchase of war material by the Afghan Government ( through his firm should be encouraged. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to Kabul. 2 The International Traders of Karachi are a firm© ^ /* BRITISH LEGATION, KABUL. 30th March, 1940. Reference your letter No. P.Z.1365/40, dated the llth March, 1940. 2. From enquiries made here it appears that Ahmad Shah Khan is an influential trader of Kabul and is the owner of the fim 'International traders of Karachi'. There is no connection, as far as is known, with the Afghan National Bank. 3. It is possible that he is making these enquiries without the knov/ledge of trie Afghan Government in the hopes of doing business with them. 4. Ahmed Shah Khan is originally from Peshawar district although now an Afghan subject. Further details about him are to be found in Who f 3 \frio in \ Afghanistan No.148. 5. I am sending a copy to Hay. G. E. Crombie, Esquire, India Office, London. / ,vi AY .940 INDIA offihe iKing Charles Street, Y/hitehall, S. W. 1 &gt; Dear Sir, We have been asked to make enquiries v/ith a view to supplying H.E.Shells for Rapid Firing Tank Model Guns for shipment to the Hoyal Afghan .loverniaent from this country or France or U.S.A. I Before taking any steps in the matter we shall be obliged if you will inform us whether at the present time the supply of Kunitions of war to this territory is prohibited or discouraged. ^ We would advise, confidentially, that the enquiry comes to us from The International Traders of Karachi, w hose head offlae —in-^ t Kabuli Afghanistan, and who have a branch office at Peshawar, the proprietfc^ being Ahmad Shah. , We should be much obliged for any recent information you could give us regarding this concern which would be treated confidentially. We would of course be prepared to send a/N 8058/5/97) J \ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 22nd July, 1939• Dear Fraser-Tytler, On receipt of your letter No,824 of March 16th on the question of .303 ammunition, I wrote to Mr.Thornhill of Imperial Chemical Industries, and I now enclose a copy of a letter from him, which should give you material for a further approach to the Afghan Prime Minister. over* Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Kerr Fraser-Tytler, K.B.E., C.M.G., British Legation, Kabul.In any further communication on this subject, please quote m No. A/ ^&gt;0 S2&gt;J 2&gt;joj and address— not to any person by name, Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Jxmdon, S.W. 1. THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^&lt;A&gt; J-nduo^ an d&gt; by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith the draft of a which it is proposed, subject to the concurrence of dfav ^ ^JicksrvcL to address to $AA&gt; &lt;&amp;. &lt;^l frU on the subject of QyYnyyrix4ynxJuO0Tru ^ r JUuX cl a i^ h ^ ^ M*' 3«/^ Foreign Office, JOL-LC, &amp;j ,193^ gJi/YyV7&gt; asn&gt; RECo. POL. DEPt. 2^JUf* \939 INDIA office Reference to previous correspondence: d.C. V 'rV 3 /?/ i 18 —F.o.p. 6000 11 I 20 ( 4687 )(0^ 1 1 z 5 &lt; tn i Registry No:n 3053/3/97. Draft. Sir K. Fraser- Tytler, Ka'bul. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. June, 1939. Dear Fraser-Tytler, On receipt of your letter No. 824 of the 16th March on the question of .303 ammunition I wrote to Mr. Thornhill of Imperial Chemical Industries Limited; and I now enclose a copy of a letter from him, which should give you material for a furtherNOTHING TO BE WRITTEN IN THIS MARGIN.N 3053/3/97. FOJEIGN OFFICE, S.V.l. June, 1939. Dear Fraser-Tytler, On receipt of your letter No. 824 of the 16th March on the question of .303 ammunition I wrote to Mr. Thornhill of Imperial Chemical Industries Limited; and I now enclose a copy of a letter from him, which should give you material for a further approach to the Afghan Prime Minister. Sir K. Fraser Tytler, Kabul.* replenish their stocks* h riwe Minister r.eid that ns m natter ©f fact *’their rtock. were hardly adeouate for their require-? nte. h d barely sufficieiit .or u.* in the '’field, end hed little or none to ape re for target ’•or^etlce, ’&gt; did rot thinh hie brother weratld bny fr^n ’•Imperial Chemical Induatriea, whoe price* were very 'MU :h, out if the Corapany were prepared to ^rant ao»e •’eonceseionB an oh «e agreeing to receive ay meat by w inBtal^ ntrJ t he. would be v ry glad to ne gotiate v»ltii them* T replied that X had no idea wheth*r the Conpcny '’would consider any conceaaiona of na ur® but I '•would pens hie Buggcstiona on to thes. ^ I should l&gt;e £l*d of your comraentfc cn the suggestion * 3 ut forward by the Afghan rime ilinistar* Ycur 3 GVeV tbdj UAUBEHCfcJ p. Qhj i-omc i -ax p' Bri \diih Ic ill !^u£Ll3»l y &lt; .4icu^ # i Dear Collier, .iOalvi you aJUicily refer to cori-aaponafenc a aridin^ iPtd^U your letter u&gt; ^r* UtioriUilll of Ui« imperial Chassical inJuayries hiML**&amp; ae&amp;M &amp;'*€ K4Ui ^mmpy &lt;K ^u/V^}* 2* I iHHMKied ?rtoe litriiat^er at a roc oat Inttirviaw &lt;ri taa aub^eot of #303 ma eadd I proaumd that in view of Ute large auwiica of wnmiitian no^ in Afghanistan trie AT ( mm QWemaeilt wre not at present in trio market for further aup^liee# I would be grateful however if he would reointi the ,-;ini«iter of KetiOMl Defence that imperial Chemical industries ^rere the ssoat notable manufacturers of a-s-iunition in Europe and that tiiey would be glad to tender for sup-lies for the Afghan &lt;Kw«P»aeflt vdiefi the latter required to replenish their stocks. 3. Hie yriism Minister said tost as a matter of fact their stocks were hardly adequate fen* their requirements. Tney £ied barely sufficient for use In the field, and ^lad little or none to spare for target practice. ii* did not think his broilier would buy from imperial OnemiMl inoustries, ^hose prices were vary high, 'but if the Crntymy were pr^artd to grant some con- ca^oicns such as agreeing to receive p*qia*i»t by instalbients, he would be very glad to negotiate with tiiem. I replied that I had no idea wiws umt* the company would consider any conceesiotia of ti'iis nature but I would puss his aug^.estions ot 4 to them. 4. 1 an u«*«aii»*, a copy ui thJU&gt; letter 'to p#el ana Metcalfe. Yours ever, Sd/- V?. K. Fraser-iytler. L* Collier .qsquii^e, C.^.d., noreign Office, London .FOREIGN OFFICE, S,W.l. 31st January, 1939 (H 441/3/97) 720 9 Dear Mr. Thornhill, Thank you for your letter JAT/CB of the 24th January about the supply of small arms ammunition to the Afghan Government. I have noted with pleasure your company T s appreciation of Colonel Fraser-Tytier f s action in this matter, which is being conveyed to him as requested. J.A. Thornhill, Esq., Government Contracts Section, Imperial Chemical Industries Limited Millbank, S. ¥. 1.(N 157/3/97) 20th January, 1939. Dear Mr. Thornhill, I have now received the comments of the Minister at Kabul on your letter of the 1st November last about the supply of small arms ammunition to the Afghan Government, and I fear they are not encouraging. This is what Colonel Fraser -Tytler says: - 'We reckon that between the years 1930 to 1937 the Afghan 'Government have bought or received 42^ million rounds of .303 ammunition. In addition they have ordered from Czechoslovakia 11 million rounds 7.92 mm. Small Arms Ammunition for their 'light machine guns. I understand that this ammunition cannot 'be used in .303 rifles. 'oince 1936 however, when they made their request for 15 taillion rounds Small Arms Ammunition, they have received 7^ 'million rounds .303 from us, and have received or will 'shortly receive 11 million rounds 7.92, that is a total of 184 J.A. Thornhill, Esq., Government Contracts Section, Imperial Chemical Industries Limited. Millbank, S.W.l.u 18^ million rounds Small Arms Ammunition. u We believe that a certain amount of the ammunition ‘^acquired between 1930 and 1934 is obsolete, particularly the ‘bonsignments of 18 million bought from Fleming in 1931 and ,, 1932, but even so, expenditure of ammunition is very small in 'this country, and it seems unlikely that they will wish to 'make further purchases in the near future. I will however 'make a note to sound the Prime Minister on the subject on 'some convenient occasion. You will realise of course, and 'in fact Mr. Thornhill admits as much, that the Imperial ’Chemical Industries’ prices are very high compared with 'those of Czechoslovakia, and I rather doubt the Afghan 'Government being willing to afford Imperial Chemical 'Industries ammunition unless the Czech stuff is hopelessly 'unsatisfactoryV I do not think that there is anything that I can usefully add to these comments; but I will of course let you know the result of the discussion which Colonel Fraser-Tytler proposes toI :&gt; have with the Afghan Prime Minister on this subject at the next convenient opportunity. 4 (ScU COLLIER.Dear collier. , f Brltlab Delation 9 r.abul* '1 QO f \u,ui iimoisbibQr* 19^# I sJ t— 1939 v.ouXa you KinUly refer u&gt; /our les»^r daoe^i Uie ?t»h Xoveutoer, lD 3 o (K MO/Uj/V?) to -r, fhomhill of Imperial Cjieidoal Indus tries Lira! ted, a copy of widen was sent to me witli your endorsement of the bth Jiuveidier ? V,e recKOii that between tne years Ibbu to lb37 tlie Ar^itun Govem^ient have bought or received 42^ million rounds of *303 munition* In add tion triey nave ordered from C^ecnoslovaAia 11 million rounds 7 *D 2 mm* ;imuH j-yrms ^monition for theii’ ii*jnt machine a^is* I understaiiu that thie ammuAition cannot be used in *303 rifles* 3 ixice lb 36 however, wi*n they mde tneir request for lo million rounds tamall Arms ^^fiunition they have received *?U ioiHlon rounds *303 from us, and have received or will shortly receive 11 million rounaa 7 #b 2 , that is a total oi 13^ million rounds i:&gt;iunil Arms .A^-iunition* 4 # Km believe that a certain amount of the ammunition acquired between 193u and 1934 is obsolete, particularly the con- siipimexits of 13 million bou^at from plemiri^ in 1931 ana 1932, but even so, expend!tui^e of as^nunltlon ie very small in tnis country, and it seetas unlikely that they will wiah to siake furuier purchases in Hie near* future* I will however make a note to sound the I rricie vjniater on the subject on some convenient occasion. You I will realise of course, and in fact Mr* Thornhill adt^its as much, that the lmj&gt;erial Cheidlcal industriee* prices are very high com pared with those of czscnoslovaxia, and I rather doubt the AftJ&amp;att Government being willing to afford Imperial ciiexdLcal incus tries ammunition unless the Czech stuff ia nopelessly unsatisfactory* 5 , I am sending a copy of this lettex' to Peel and itetcalfe* Collier Require, C*h*G*, ^*oreign Office, London • Yours ever, Sd/- \v* K. prase r- Ty tie r &lt;A1H HAIL * no. tm . f pTz ! 6357 [ 19o7 British L«£atioii f Kabul* 17Ux September 1^37 \ Ilcn-K. \?le*** refer to I abul telegraja flo * 16 dated the 16th February Iv 37, regarding the purchase of rifle ^munition by the Afghan ovenaaent frosa Imperial Chemical Indus tries* Eajor Macanii is at present away on tour and I am writing to let you know that the T/inister of defence told ^ajor Lancaster at an interview on weptezaher lotli that 'Uie Afiihan Government had no urgent need for the supply of a further 7^ millions rounds of u&amp;all Arms Ammunition but that he would ask the f rime Minister wh&amp;t his would like done* Ke stated that he had fUll confidai.ee in Uie products of Imperial Chemical Indus tiles but stressed the point tiiat It was important that they should quote the lowest possible price, • I am seiidin; copies of this letter to Colonel r arsons ami to i umbold. Yours sincerely* L.C©~lier, naq# f C.M*G. f Fore Jpu tffice* Lomion. 3d/- M* Worth-CONFI E L’lAL AID.PERSONAL. 11th l ay, 1937 . Your Ref - P.Z. 2860/37 H.A.F. Rumbold, Esq., ‘rhe India office, hHITEHALL, London, S.V. 1. Dear Mr. Rumhold, Many thanks for your letter of the 6th May, which I have read with much interest. I should like to add that we much appreciate your having given us the information contained therein, which will he treated in confidence. Yours sincerely,Draft Paper. P.Z.a860/37 Department. 7.7 Personal J.A. Thornhill, Esq., Imperial Chemical House, Millbank, Westminster, S.W. Northern Department , Foreign Office , For concurrence. See P.Z.2772/37. (Intlld.) H.A.H(umbold) 30/4 b tL IV'\ Confidential Thank you for your letter^ of » 'bd' v - 27th April 'regarding Afghanistan. The munitions referred to by the 'Statesman” as passing through Karachi for . Afghanistan are/probably a consignment of 75 m.m. mountain guns with ammunition which was landed at Karachi early in April. They have been bought by the Afghans in Europe, almost certainly in Czecho-Slovakia. The reference to \a, i£oe. CaV-Co.^ a- rifles Y is probably to the .303 weapons, which, as you know, the War Office are selling to the Afghan Government, and which are going out to Karachi in small consignments. We have not heard that the Afghans have been negotiating- for any other rifles. ^/(TuAo ^HHIliialMHttflHttl A f ' i A/-, ^ © | '1501 THE Under-Secretary of State 1 31 * -^.ffairsi presents his N ivcn \^\fj compliments to the Under-Secretary of St Lit 6 ToFTndiaT and is directed by the Secretary of State to enclose herewith gl. fifijt&amp;'L -(Va. lerMuziv cL l- 3 l^i . for transmission by the earliest opportunity to His Majesty's Minister at Kabul, Ae^exjoJ^ 2. Should the Secretary of State for India have any observations which he thinks could be usefully embodied in this communication, it is requested that it may be returned immediately to this Department, with a note to that effect, in which case no further action would be taken here pending the receipt of the observations of the Secretary of State for India, to be communicated in accordance with the usualCopy (N 591/2/97) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 9th February, 1937 r 4 Dear Mr, Thornhill use ; S937 I -^ank you for your letter JAT/CL of 22nd January about I enclose a copy of a telegram to Colonel ^raser-Tytler which was sent on the lines which you suggested, I understand that in conversation v/ith Mr. Rumbold of the India Office you concurred in its text as sent. The cost will be recovered from you in due course. the supply of ammunition to Afghanistan Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) Laurence Collier J.A. Thornhill, EsclDraft Paper P.Z.1104/37. political Department DRAFT LBTTifiR. J. A.Thornhill , Esq., Imperial Chemical Confid e ntial. Industries , Ltd. , Millbank, S.W.l. A telegram has been received from H.M.lffinist er, Kabul, in which he says that the message contained in your letter of 22nd January to me was communicated to the Afghan Foreign Minister. Colonel Fraser-Tytler did not, however, use the discretion which he was given to say that Imperial Chemical Industries might accord slightly easier terms if necessary. Subsequently^on 14th- Tooruary^ H. R. H. ?with Major Lancaster, the Military Attache. Prime Minister, had made arrangements while he was in Europe for the supply of ammunition. After the latter’s return (he will probably reach Kabul about 10th March) and after the discussion of the Army Budget, Shah Mahmud hoped, provided th^t Muhammad Hashim hnd not made other arrangements, to be in a position to invite the Lahore representative of your Company to go to Kabul to discuss terms. He appeared anxious to purchase from Imperial Chemical Industries, although he said that your price was high—added that he had refused offers from Sirdar Shah Mah N-Vs « -^1 Sold l&amp;jaAT V\£ Shah Mahmudovas uncertain whether a H.R.H. Sirdar Muhammad Hashim Khan, the 5000 2.37 5667 he /he suspected that the ammunition^ though cheap would not he fresh. bhah Mahmud gave Major Lancaster the impression of hoping for a slight reduction in price and somewhat easier terms of payment, hut you will prohahly wish to await Muhammad Hashim ! s return to Kabul before taking further action.fcn/yh, (COPIES CIRCULATED A1\D TO FOHEIG1J- OFFICE o) (107 groups 0 ) 893 DECYP HE R OF TELEGRAM From His Majesty 1 s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,VV V India Office, i Y'f.wv Dated ReceiTed Kabul, 16th February,1937 0 8 e 35 a,m 0 , 16th February,1937, i Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, repeated to Foreign, New Delhi 0 Forminka 15, bi' // paragraph No 0 2o (sic) Ammunition,, 2 0 (sic) Contents of Paragraph No 0 l of Forminka 15 were communicated to the Foreign Minister, and the lar Minister discussed the case with the Military Attache at an interview on the 14th February, 3, Shah Mahmud was uncertain whether Hashim, while in Europe, had made arrangements for supply of ammunition or not, . On the latter 1 a return, and after discussion of Army Bjidget, the War Minister hoped, provided Hashim had not made other arrangements, to be in a position to invite Imperial Chemical Industries representative at Lahore to Kabul to discuss terms 0 4, War Minister appeared anxious to purchase from loCoI, although he said the price was high. He had refused offers from Czecho-Slovakian and Belgian firms because he suspected that the ammunition, though cheap, would not be fresh, 5 0 He gave the impression of hoping for slight reduction in price and somewhat easier terms of payment, February , RECb. PSt. irEPr. 1 I C? FEB1937, INDiA OFFi®l£— CXV-v J\f 2 C f I submit a draft telegram as suggested by Mr. Thornhill and a draft reply to him. ? Copy his letter, minutes and drafts to 1.0* for concurrence. (Signed) B.A.B.BURROWS 25/1 (Signed) G. VEREKER 25/1 (Intld) L.C(ollier) Jan 25th.'v'Vy Northern Pepartment . gorel^n Office. By arrangement with the Foreign Office Mr.Thornhill called on me on 21st January to discuss his answer to Mr.Collier*s letter of 15th January. He told me that Imperial Chemical Industries propose to quote £6,500 per million for cartridges with bandoliers, which compares with £6,975 offered by the Government of India for cartridges without bandoliers and the £6,250 per million paid by the Afghan Government to I.C.I. in 1934 for cartridges without bandoliers. ?^r.Thornhill also told me that his firm propose to ask for the following terms of payment:- 25 per cent with the order, 45 per cent on shipment and the balance spread over two years. He asked me what I thought the reaction of the Afghan Government would be. I replied that the Afghan Government would certainly ask for a much smaller initial payment and for the payment of^balance to be spread over a longer period. They would, however, be unlikely to frighten the Afghans off so long as they indicated to the Afghans that they would, if necessary, be prepared to consider more lenient terms. The main f ctor in the situation would,—fcowre*^ be the prices quoted by &lt;ny competitors they may have.In this connection I told him that the Germans were prepared^to e-ell arms to the Afghan Government and were ready to give extended credit. 7e had, however, no reason to think that they were quoting for small aims ammunition. !r.Thornhill also told me that I.C.I. hove been asked to tender for 450,000 tons of blank nickel coins and the value of the order is about 750,000. He promised to let me have details of it. 7/hen we receive them they may throw a good deal of light on the currency policy of the Afghan Government. .\ \(H 77/2/97) FOREIGN OFFICE, 3.7.1. 15th January, 1937 Eea r Kr, Thornhill Vereker here on the 18th November you will be glad to hear that we have now received a telegram from His Majesty's Minister at Kabul, in which he says that the Afghan Minister for Defence informed the Military Attache to the Legation on the 2nd January that he would be glad to receive at once a Quotation from Imperial Chemical Industries for the supply of 7,500,000 rounds of ’503 ammunition with bandoliers and charger-packed. His Royal Highness stipulated that the quotation should be for the delivery of the ammunition at Land! Kotal and for the supply of the full order within one year. He asked that the quotation should state the terms of payment, which should, if possible, be by instalments, and added that if the purchase were decided on, your agent at Lahore would be asked to go to Kabul to settle details/ J.A. Thornhill, Esq.wmmmmum details, Kis Royal Highness said that the Afghan Government were well satisfied with the ammunition previously supplied by Imperial Chemical Industries and would like to get all their future requirements from your Company* but that they found your prices high. He expressed a hope that lower quotations might now be possible, 7e would be ready to telegraph to Colonel Fraser- Tytler, for communication to the Afghan Government, the answer which your Company wish to give to this approacho Your® SinoamlyDraft Paper P.Z. 114/37 Department. J.A. Thornhill, Esq., Imperial Chemical Industries Ltd., Millbank, S. W. 1. Mr. Waltpfi ': ' Northern Dept., Foreign Office : It is suggested that the Foreign Office should send to D.M.I. a copy of Katodon No. 4, and if they concur in the action suggested in this draft, a copy of their letter to Mr. Thornhill. ■ We have received a telegram from His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul in which he that the Afghan Minister for Defence ✓ informed the British Military Attache at Kabul on 2nd January that he would be glad to receive at once a quotation from Imperial Chemical Industries for the supply of 7,500,000 rounds of *303 ammunition with bandoliers and charger-packfl* * stipulated that the quotation should be for the delivery of the ammunition at Landi Kotal and for the supply of the full order within one year. He asked that the quotation should state the terms of payment which should, if possible, be by instalments If the purchase is decided o^your Oigent at Lahore would be asked to go to Kabul to settle details. His Royal Highness said that -h-i-a Government was well satisfied with the ammunition previously supplied by Imperial Chemical Industries and would like to get all their future requirements from your v&amp;cV: Company^but found your prices high. He expressed a hope that lower quotations might now be possible. We would be ready to telegraph to Colonel Fraser-Tytler, for communication I to the Afghan Government, the answer which 'your Company wishes to give to this approacSECRET y 1937 ^J(m groups) 114 i FHB/DIA 62. DEOYPHER OF TELEGRAM. (COPIES TO FOREIGN Prom His Majesty*s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office*. Kabul, 4th January, 1937o 4th January, 1937 p 4~20 pome i Receired XXX Demi-official for Collier, repeated to Walton and Metcalfe« Your letter dated 24th November ? N/6362/(? 693)/97o ' ^ 3 ) Ammunitiono 2 e Shah Mahmud informed Military Attache on 2nd January that he would be glad to receive, at once, quotation from Imperial Chemical Industries for supply of 7,500,000 rounds of ammunition with Bandoliers and charger~packed« Landi Kotal, and for supply of full order within one yearo Quotation should state terms of payment, which should be by instalments if possible* 3o If purchase is decided on, agent at Lahore will be asked to come to Kabul to settle details* 4o He said he was well satisfied y^ith the ammunition previously supplied and would like to get all his future requirements from I*C*Io but found their prices high* He hoped lower quotations were now possible* x X 2* He stipulated quotation should be for delivery at Fraser Tytler 4, January 4th * x ,, Para« 2 M was telegraphed twice, as shewn* SEOO. S 5 JAN 1937 1I— . La IVith Mr. Laurence Collier^ Compliments.^7 FOHtIIQff OFFICE, S.w.l. J 24th NoTember, 1936. (N 5362/593/97) Dear Fraser-Tytlcr, T enclose a copy of a letter frorc Tmperlal Chemical Industries about an enquiry from a Belgian firm with regard to the supply of ai;»iunition to Afghanistan. After consulting with the India Office we as&amp;ed rr* Thornhill to call, told him the terms on which the Cknremment of India are selling ammunition to the Afghan Government, and pointed out that the Afghan Government had already considered completing their requirements, which appeared to amount to 15,000,000 rounds, from Imperial Chemical Industries, as reported in your telegram No. 80 of 11th September. We suggested to him that the Afghans, in their usual way, had probably been making enquiries in various quarters to see if they could do better than with his firm, and added that we had already he^rd from you (your telepram No, 58 of 7th July Lieutenant-Colonel .£. Fraser-Tytler, C.L.G. , &amp;.C.SMH (i¥ July) that they hsd ©t leeet coneidered getting aamplee from Pel glum some time ego. If, however, foreign firms bed to get their supplies for the Afghans frora Imperial Chemical Industries, it looked as though the latter would always he able to quote cheaper prices and there did not therefore seem to be any cause to fear that they would not eventually obtain the contract. I r. Thornhill asked that, in reporting this matter to you, we plght mention that the representative at Lahore of Imperial Chemical industries in India would be willing to go to Kabul and help in negotiating a contract for the additional 7,500,000 rounds. lie added that no doubt you would inform ^hah Kahmud hisaeli or the fir&amp;’s desire to tender for the supply of ammunition, as their representatives In India had already established relations with him in the case of a previous contract for 4,000,000 rounds, which had been most successful. presume that, in view of your telegram go. 9n of 23rd ctober, you will now act ss suggested by r. Thornhill...■MM**? wmmmmmm ^.1. Cl ?-l 9-1 bO^^t. P-lkSUb^b. I understand that Mr. Thornhill's remarks on the telephone did not add anything to this letter. We have offered the Afghans 7,500,000 rounds of .505 ammunition, and they will accept this - see 1^5258/59^97. But they originally wanted - and still want - 15,000,000 rounds - see e.g. N 4159/595/^7. The Afghan Government have already considered completing their requirements from I.C.I. - see N 4625/595/97, though Colonel F. Tytler has not yet apparently thought it opportune to give them the message in our telegram No* 60, N 4247/595/97 that I.C.I. were willing to tender. He will presumably do so as soon as our offer is clinched. The Afghans in their usual way have probably been making enquiries in various quarters to see if they can do better than with I.C.I. Kabul telegram No* 58 in N 5509/595/97 shows that they at least considered getting samples from Belgium. If foreign firms have to get their supplies from I.C.I. it looks as though the latter would be able to quote cheaper prices. I do not think Mr. Thornhill need be worried. The best way of dealing with this letter might be to speak to Mr. Thornhill in general terms on the lines of the above minute (and then inform the War Office,): but we must first get the views of the India Office* ? copy India Office with minutes* Y/ar Office ref. stating this. (Sgd.) B. A. B. BURROY/S. 2 . 11 * Mr. Thornhill's verbal message seemed to me to be rather/rather odd, and therefore better committed to v/riting.SECRET FCN/ETP/D1A (X43 groups) 4741 Y? (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom His Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Officeo Dated Kabul* 23rd October? X936« Received 23rd October? 1936? 2-30 p®mo XXX Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* repeated to Foreign? New Delhi® Correspondence ending with Foreign wire No®300* dated the 10th October* 1936® Arms® Afghan (revernment accept the fell owing proposals® 3® (a) Arms® First batch of 3*000 to be delivered In Karachi in the middle of December® Remaining batches of 2*500 each to be delivered at monthly intervals thereafter® Arms to be addressed to the Consul? Karachi? who will take them over and arrange onwards despatch® Landi Kotal In the middle cf December® Remaining 4 j ,500?000? rounds of ammunition to be delivered as soon as possible at ter the 1st April* 1937* at the rate of 1?000?000 a month® will be paid by Afghan Government on December 16th* and on 15th of each succeeding month ujo to and including September 15th* 193 Second and all subsequent instalments £13?646 on May 1st? 1938? and succeeding: years® Ammunitione First instalmento Rupees 2c Foreign Minister has informed me orally that the &gt; Ammunition® 3,000*000 rounds to be delivered at (c) Payments® Arms® First instalment® £i*364*X2s iX $ 25 eh oueooeal ;ng ■*, » Please wire whether I can confirm above officially® Fraser Tytler 98? October 23rdqf) SECRET 4064. (COPIES CIRCULATED) IL0JL±_.0_B 0.-1 T E l J 8 R A M, From His Majesty s Minister, Kabul, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Office ? Londono Dated Kabul, I1th September^ 1936c' Received 9 porno* 11th September* 1936c XXX /i&lt;gv?b|u. Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs^ repeated to Foreign, Simla, Forminka 60o Paragraph No®So 1 have already discussed with Prime Minister question of purohaa# of ammunition from Imperial Chemicals, vi d e paragraph No«5 of Katodon telegram 64, and he is considering the possibility, vide paragraph N 0 o 8 of Katodon telegram 69o But he cannot come to any decision until he knows how much amnunition His Majesty's Government is prepared to let him have® It would therefore be preferable, *rom tii© local point oi view, to defer further cornmunication on the subject oi IqCoIo until 1 can at the same time ini'orm the Prime Minister of the amount of ammunition he can expect to receive from His Majesty’s Government,, IlM ^lrUer BD, „ Se ptember 11.Minute Paper. i P.Z.6179/36 1 At* * A . VS^- l j7J i r ^ ■ Department, i 7 / y Please see the letter from Imperial Chemical Industries of 20th August forwarded to us under Foreign Office No.N.4247/593/97. It is preferable that the Afghan Government should obtain their ammunition from a British rather than from a foreign source, and, as it appears unlikely that the Government of India will be able to supply all the Afghan requirements, the possibility of the Afghan Government dealing with Imperial Chemicals is to be encouraged rather than otherwise. The Afghan Government have apparently already considered dealing with Imperial Chemical Industries (see Katodon No.69 of August 13th), but it might be as well for Colonel Fraser- Tytler to inform them specifically that I.C.I. are prepared to make a tender. A draft telegram accordingly is submitted. 2956 6000 7/344013 1000 8 35 mm DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN' AND f/jIJTICAE I/EPARTMENT. / (R^lainflla&gt;- H.M. 1 S MINISTER, KABUL. REPEATED GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. P .Z, 6 179/36 Addressed Kabul repeated to India. Government of India telegram of 23rd July No.1657. Ammunition for Afghanistan. Please inform Afghan Government at your discretion that they may he able to purchase .303 ammunition on favourable terms from Imperial Chemical Industries.jrv - I Copy. (N 3780/693/97) FOREIGN OFFICE, SjW.l.r ; •—■ v- 18th August, 1936. Confl .ential Dear Mr. Thornhill, With reference to Collier’s letter of 6 th June, No.N 2726/593/97, regarding the supply of ammunition to the Afghan Government, I am able to inform you that we have now had a reply from the Government of India to your suggestion that, if the Afghan Government accept the offer made to them by the Government of India, Imperial Chemical Industries might supply the ammunition. The Government of India regret that they do not see their way to accept this suggestion. The present state of negotiations with the Afghan Government is that they have given no reply to the offer of His Majesty’s Government and there is reason to think that they are trying to see whether they can obtain better terms in foreign countries. In a recent discussion between His Majesty’s Minister and the Afghan Prime Minister, the latter mentioned the possibility of his Government dealing direct with your Company regarding ammunition, but stated his preference for dealing with His Majesty’s Government if possible. If the question is discussed between your Company and the Afghan Government, we hope that you will let us know. It would incidentally be interesting to know whether Shah Mahmud discussed this question when he visited your Company's works on June 29th. As Collier informed you in his letter of 6 th June there is no objection from the point of view of His Majesty’s Government J.A. Thornhill, Esq.Government to your submitting a tender to the Afghan Government for the supply of .303 ammunition and we are now willing to authorise His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul by telegram to inform the Afghan Government at his discretion that they may be able to purchase such ammunition from your subsidiary company on better terms than those offered by the Government of India. I should be grateful if you would let me know whether your Company would like us to do this. Yours sincerely, ISA) ... . .'£KER #SECRET CWP/AW. (118 gr&amp;ttp*) 3640. PBCYPK3B 0? TIL 3,0 B A From His Majssty 1 * Hinistsr at Katoul to ssorotaiy of Stats for forsign ( 10PI4S affairs, India Offios. CIHCUXAT^)) Dated Kabul # IHh /;AgU«t # 103^. Fs^eired 13th taurast. I036 t 5.15 p.m. XXX asoond of our Parts . 5. In 1934 Afghan Clovsrnment considered question of establishing uniformity of armament for the Afghan Army. Military authorities had been in farour of German Mausers but adriee given to the Prime Minister by Maeonaohie (Katodon 101 of 1934) had decided him in favour deoimal 303 rifle. Afghan Government now wished to complete armament of regular arny with decimal 303 rifles and provide all garrisons with adequate reserve of email arms ammunition* to withdraw other types whioh would be used to replace obsolete rifles now with tho police and compete (si© ? complete) armament of the (? police.) some of whom had hitherto been unarmed. Jut rifles without adequate supplies of ammunition wore useless. Prime Minister believed that 1.00) rounds per rifle was not sxeeseive. but hie Government had reduced offer to 600 rounds. This would satisfy (? Afghan Government) immediate requirements but he asked this ammunition should be supplied at some (eio ? sar?e) time and on the same (? basis of) payment as the rifles. Fraser Tytlsr 69. au 13th.SECRET 102 fW-ae?/ - a ( i»i gr»up®. ) j x a ^ V A,J+ Trm 364&amp;. (COPIES Hia Majesty 1 ® Miniater at Kabul to acr Jtary of for Foreign Affair©, India offioe. Kabul, 13th Auguot, l\&amp;&amp;. ] eoeired 6«45 p*®., 13th Auguat, 1 C J36» XXX 6. 1 said I did not think, aa regarde quantities, the Afghan Government 1 ® requirements were ooneidered good ,;:rounda by military experts* Question w&amp;a one of supply and fin?j\oe. Us Government was en^;aged an a vast (?re~arnaaeat) prearanne (iwhioh was) (t taxing) their (?resource«) to the full* (?Xn spite of) that they had offered to supply the Afghan Government with munitions and aeroplanes on very easy terms end in shat seemed to them adequate quantities* (^Afghan Goveraient^) present request would Inorease flnunoi&amp;l oomitments of His Malesty 1 # Government by nearly £(?1QQ,000) and, thoo^h I would put Prime Minister^ arguments before theta, I thought it unlikely that they would increase their present offer* 7* X suggested possibility of eompronise, whereby Hie Majesty•* Government might undertake to increase present offer in any one year by addition*ML instalment if Afghan Government were able to show that military operations had seriously depleted their reserves* prime ; inister said that this would not meet the case* it was never wise for the Af^iua ( ovenuaent to seek direct help of His Majesty 1 a Government during the course of any disturbance. Besides difficulty of transport might make it impossible for munitions to reach danger point in time* ItSECRET © it/wb ( 107 groups. ) 2^ 1L^ a ,fc From Hia Ma*j*3lyr , a ^iniater at Kabul 5644. (COPIES ClBCUl*AfKD) to aorotary of tat© for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Bated Kabul, 13th August, 1936. Beoeired 0. p.»., 13th AUf u»t, 1936. XXX nA^iLi mi# S. jprise Minister codded that Afghan Qotor.mmt did not wish to be a burden to their friends. He had put their requirements frankly before me and he naked that His Majesty 1 a Bovemment should supply with rifles* ae much immunition as they were able and willing to let them hare. or the balance, he would negotiate with or elsewhere. He asked that decision of His Majesty’s Govern eat should be conveyed to him as soon as possible. Military Attache who was present confirms my opinion that offer in present form is not acceptable to Afghan Goveriiraent. I suggest that Ris Majesty’s Government might consider offering say half the quantity asked for (7,500,000 rounds) with rifles cm 6 year Instalment basis on condition that no more is supplied till this is paid for. S. irime ! inirter , s attitude, though friendly and grateful for the present offer, wua quite firm. £aa&gt;a«g . MdMk»■ *SECRET 0164/6260 ( The War Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 11th August, 1936 Dear Referenoa your latter P.Z. o32l/36. dated 8th August 1936, enclosing a copy of a suggested draft letter to the I.C.I. with regard to the sale of ammunition to Afghanistan, I see no objection to your writing on these lines. Incidentally, it would be interesting to know whether Shah Mahmoud discussed this question when he visited the works on 29th June. He was not accompanied on that occasion by an officer from here. As requested in your letter I am sending a copy of this letter to the Foreign Office.P.Z.5321/36. Minute Paper. poli t ic al Department. OJC ?-~L e^VM^V 6\^ Xcf' rxc^ \Wvs. vSwl^a vro Kcoa\ j G'jo ' &lt;S\j ^ VGt Co\.-AQ c ^-’ ^ 'G. *bl j ‘JjG A i. I think that we should accept the riew of the Government of India and encourage Imperial Chemical Industries to tender forthwith to the Afghan Government and that we should instruct Colonel Fraser-Tytler to tell the Afghan Government that they may be able to purchase ammunition from Imperial Chemical Industries on better terms than the Government of India have offered. But I do not think that we should try to make the prospect of a deal with Imperial Chemical Industries appear to the Afghans to be dependent on their acceptance of our rifles, because even if the Afghans refuse the rifles they can still buy ammunition from Imperial Chemical Industries. Also it seems redundant to intimate to either the Afghans or the Company that the Government of India would accept no responsibility for the quality or the punctual supply of the latterm's ammunition, as presumably the contract would be negotiated directly between them. If H.M.Minister got heavily involved in these negotiations it might conceivably be desirable to give such a warning, but we can wait and see how things develop. i 2'. We must accept Government of India 1 s refusal of Imperial Chemical Industries^ offer to take over their obligation, but their reasons seem so thin that I suggei v SWvvV: tere,^, they should not be passed —on to Imperial Chemical Industries. A draft letter to Mr.Thornhill is submitted for issue from the Foreign Office if they agree. 4424 5000 1/36 »u«„ y Have you any observations ? v/ ^ QgXjJ ?T*0J. A.Thornhill, Esq.., Imperial Chemical Industries, Ltd., Draft Paper. P.Z. 5321/36. CONFIDENTIAL. Department. Millbank, S.W.l. Will you please refer to my letter of 6th June, No.N.2726/593/97, regarding the supply of ammunition to the Afghan Government. We have now had a reply from the Government of India to your suggestion that, if the Afghan Government accept the offer made to them by the Government of India, Imperial Chemical Industries might supply the ammunition. The Government of India regret that they xiannatraTccept your--offer-. The present state of our negotiations with the Afghan Government is that they have given us no reply to our offer and there is reason to think that they are seeing whether they can obtain better terms in foreign countries. In a recent discussion of frhe Q oirci-wiient of Iw^ia ! B eggiM. 1 -of ammunition between H.M.Minister and the Afghan Prime Minister, the latter mentioned the possibility of his Government dealing preference for dealing with H.M.G. if possible. If the question is discussed between your Company and the Afghan Government, we hope that you will let of 6th June there is no objection from the point of view of the Government to As I informed you in my letter your/ 3938 5000 7.35your submitting a tender to the Afghan Government and we would now he ready to authorise H.M.Minister at Kabul by telegram(at his discretion)to inform the Afghan Government that they may be able to purchase ammunition from your subsidiary company on better terms than those offered by the Government of India. I should be grateful if you would let me know v/hether your Company v/ould like us to do this.FRB/FCN/DIA* I 1&gt; - z - I ' 5550 ; ^ l 1936 j •-*'-(153 groups) SECRET 346 4 o (COPIES CIHCULATED) PE CYPHER OP TELEGRAM o From His Majesty ? s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Office* Dated Kabul* 3Iet July* 1936o Received 31st July* 1936* 5-30 pomo — XXX Fi rst cf Two,, Parts * Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Fcreigno Correspondence ending with Katcdcn 58* Arras o 2o I discussed this case on the (? 28th) with the Prime and Foreign Ministers* They had apparently taken no steps to discuss the terms offered by Hay (Katodon 52) and the Prime Minister asked me for (V fresh) copy of aide memoipe * 3c He stood out very strongly for payment in 6 instal ments and* after some argument* I said that His Majesty J s Government might perhaps accept this provided the Afghan Government agreed to pay first instalment on receipt in Kabul of each batchc 4 0 Prime Minister said that the Afghan Government did not wish to dispute justice of this proposal but* owing to the fact that payments into the Afghan treasury were greater at certain periods of the year* Afghan Government would prefer a certain latitude in making the first payments* He suggested fixing a period* say three months* within which payment must be made* X said I realised his difficulty (which is* I believe* genuine) but that X did not think His Majesty*s Government would accept his proposalo End of First Part* Second Part followsa Fraser Tytler 64, July 31stSECRET FCN/DIA* (119 groups; 34£&gt;fcSo D S 0 Y ZJj Prfiin (COPIES CIRCULATED) g ft OF TELEGRA Uq_ His Majeety^s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Officeo Dated Kabul* 31st July* 1936, Received. 31st July* 1936* 2^30 poin* XXX Second and ,Last Par_t * If p however, the Afghan Government would fix a date on which payment eould he effected. His Majesty s Government would no doubt be able to arrange for delivery of arms to coincide with this date® 6&lt;. As regards ammunition, he asked why His Majesty s Government could not supply 15.000,000, rounds in one batch. I gave number of reasons against this proposal, and emphasised the advantage (V to the,omitted) Afghan Government of receiving fresh batch of ammunition each year. Prime Minister himself mentioned possibility of the Afghan Government dealing direct with Imperial Chemicals but stated his preference for dealing with His Majesty's Government if possible^ 6„ I also mentioned terns under which rifles would be delivered* vide paragraph NOoS* Forminka 4/« Vo Prime Minister did not appear although (sic* ? altogether) satisfied with the above proposals* but said he would consult Ministry of Defence and let me have an answer as soon as possible. pyaser-Tytler 64*^ July ftlgjL*I UC/AW, PECYPHER Qg TB LB GJLA From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Government of Indias Foreign and Political Department, ^o Secretary of State for India* Simla, 23rd July, 1936* Received 23rd July, 1936, 7*15 14- n!l &gt; 1657, lfi&gt; \ XXX Addressed to Secretary of State, 1657, repeated to KafcUl, 156* Rumbold 9 8 official letter No*P.Z«3721/36, 8th June, regarding the desire of Imperial Chemical Industries to tender for the sale of ammunition to the Afghan Government c 2, Latest indications are that Afghans are postponing reply to Minister possibly in order to obtain better offer from Belgium* Since it is our policy to induce the Afghans to purchase their requirements in arms and ammunition from a British source., whether Government or commercial, over which His Majesty’s Government have control, we would prefer i-hat Imperial Chemical Industries should get the order for the ammunition rather than that it should go to a foreign firm* We therefore suggest that Minister might be instructed to inform Afghans at once that, if they accept His Majesty^s Government’s offer of rifles, they may be able to purchase ammunition from Imperial Chemical Industries on better terms than those we can offer and thereby induce them to conclude bargain* We could not, in any case, agree to suggestion that I*C*I* should take over our obligations in respect of ammunition, as a whole, since we should then be held responsible for meeting possible complaints from Afghans regarding quality, delay, etc* We should, on the other hand^ have no objection to direct deal between the Afghan Government and the I*C*I«, it being made clear to both parties that the Government of India accept no responsibility for quality or punctual supply*ail -■ - i’rom His Majesty 5 e Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* Dated Kabul^ 7th July* 1936 w Heceived 7th July* 1936 b 4 C 30 from Foreign Office* XXX Katodon* personal* From Hay for Co:ilier f repeated Walton and Metcalfe* Correspondence ending with Forminka 47 s June 30th. Rifles* Afghan Ministers are repeatedly postponing discussion regarding of arms and ammuniticnp ostensibly on grounds of Fraser-Tytler* s illness* it seems possible they may be making enquiries in other quartera s and it is significant that they hare recently applied for f&amp;siXitfs® for transit through India for on© c303 rifle and a thousand cartridges from Pabriqu© national©d 5 Armes de Guerre # Belgium* Hay, 58, J uly 7* Hots* This telegram was addressed by Kabul toPrcdroBSe London s and correctly sent by the Cable Company to the F e 0* this delayed its receipt in the 1*0*— Sccctv. ^ The For. Secy, to the G. of I., F. &amp; P. Dept.-, SIL r 8JUN 1936 Sir, I am directed by the S. of S. to refer to Lt.-Col. Fraser-Tytler’s d.o. letter to Vr. Collier of 26th Parch, No. 824, regarding the desire of Imperial Chemical Industries to tender for the sale of ammunition to the Afghan Govt. A copy is enclosed of a despatch which is being sent to H.M. Minister, Kabul, on the subject. ^ 2. If Imperial Chemical Industries should make a tender and supply tne Afghan Govt, with the ammunition they require by a direct contract, there would seem to be some advantage in this course, as it would lighten the liability on the Afghan Reserve Fund. I am to enquire whether tne G. of I. agree on this point. 3. It seems preferable, hov/ever, that 11.P. I mister, Kabul, should not inform the Afghan Govt, of the possibility of supply on better terms from Imperial Chemical Industries^unless and until they take exception to the terms offered by the Gt of—i. If the Afghan Govt, accept Mc* 4 f lr*» OU-^ the G. of I.’s terns, it, v;i±i be seen from the penultimate- para, of Mr. Thornhill’s letter of 20th x May that it wo nl n bo poo sable t oar range with Imperial Chemical Industries that they should take over the G. of I.’s obligations/obligations in respect of animunition as a whole, melading the liability on account of credit, and such an arrangement would seem to have the same advantage as that referred to in para. 2 above. 4. The S. of S. would be glad to S know the views of the G. of I. on the instructions contained in para. 4 of the enclosed despatch to’Lt.-Col. Fraser-Tytle (Sd.) H. A. F. RUM BOLDi H f &lt;. I—I I 1 Ml . V******^^. i H f &lt;. I—I I 1 Ml . V******^^. THE Under-Secretary 7 of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed 2. Should the Secretary of State for India have any observations which he thinks could be usefully embodied in this communication, it is requested that it may be returned immediately to this Department, with a note to that effect, in which case no further action would be taken here pending the receipt of the observations of the Secretary of State for India, to be communicated in accordance with the usual procedure. ^ by the Secretary of State to enclose herewith a despatch for transmission by the earliest opportunity to His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul. Foreign Office, S.W. 1, 5417 11977No. 61* FOREIGN OFFICE, S. W. 1. 6th June, 1936. (N 2726/593/97). Sir, With reference to your semi-official letter to K r. Collier No. 824 of the 26th Narch last, I transmit to you herewith copies of two letters from Imperial Chemical Industries Limited regarding the supoly of ammunition to the Afghan Government and of the reply sent to Nr. Thornhill f letter of Nay 20th last. A 2. The letter of 20th ' T ay was written to confirm a conversation which Nr. Thornhill had at this department on 13th Nay, arid at which he stated that his firm would probably be able to offer better terms to the Afghan Government than those offered by the Government of India. Nr. Thornhill was told that he would be informed if and when the Afghan Government made any difficulty about accepting the Government of India s terms, so that his firm could then make an offer. 3. Nr. Thornhill added that if the Afghan Government accepted the Government of India's offer and the Government of India wished to avoid having to deplete their own stocks of ammunition in consequence, Imperial Chemioal Industries would probably be ready to supply the required ammunition to the Government of India who could then deliver it to the Afghans without disturbing their stocks. 4. Pending the reply of the Afghan Government to the offer in respect of ammunition which you were authorized to make in my telegram * 0.38 of the 5th u ay last, you should not without further reference to me inform the Afghan Government Lieutenant-Colonel W.K. Fraser-Tytler, C.H.G., V.C., etc., etc., etc., Kabul. of/of the possibility of supply direct from Imperial Chemical Industries on better terms. if, however, the Afghan Government make difficulties regarding the terms of the Government of India’s offer you have discretion, if the Government of India agree, to inform the Afghan Government of this possibility* 5. I enclose a copy of a letter on this subject which is being addressed to the Government of India. I am, with great truth and regard, Sir, v our obedient Servant, (^or the Secretary of State) '&gt;4 . • * *'*•• ■ ■&gt;' V 1 'V •(N 2726/593/97) FOREIGN OFFICE, S. W. 1. 6th June,1936. Dear Mr,Thornhill, I am writing in reply to your official letter to me of 20th May to confirm what I said at our conversation on 13th May about the supply of ammunition to the Afghan Government, namely, that we will let you know as soon as possible if and when the Afghan Government make any difficulty about accepting the terms on which the Government of India are prepared to supply them in order that your firm may be able to put in an offer at once. We could of course have no objection to your Company submitting a tender forthwith to the Afghan Government (without disclosing your discussions with His Majesty’s Government), but if they do this we should be grateful if you would let us know. We are informing the Minister at Kabul and the Government of India of the position, and we are submitting to the latter your suggestion that Imperial Chemical Industries Limited/ J.A. Thornhill, Esq.■ Ml Limited might supply the ammunition to the Government of India for re-sale to the Afghan Government. We shall not fail to keep you informed of any further developments. (Sd.) LAURENCE COL S.R* © n.x, 'bTavKb. Minute Paper. political Department. Y'O* cxcct\QT Ck \-*&gt; ^,0 £*-4. Cs^.vratj ^fo Please see P.Z.2892/36 regarding Imperial Chemical Industries'• desire to sell ammunition to the Afghan Government. The Foreign Office have seen Mr. Thornhill of I.C.I. and he has confirmed by letter that I.C.I. could sell ammunition at a lower price than the Government of India's offer. They would also be prepared to consider the questicr of credit. The Foreign Office have referred to us drafts to Colonel Fraser-Tytler and Mr. Thornhill. Mr. Collier refused in his interview with Mr. 'Co ^usVYwcV Thornhill^to pass on an offer on behalf of I.C.I. unless and until the Afghans object to the Government of India's terms. I understand Mr. Collier's view to be that such action might diminish the political value of the Government of India's offer. There is, however, the possibility of I.C.I. putting in an offer direct to the Afghans (they have already written to the Afghan Legation to invite Shah Mahmud to visit their cartridge factory at Birmingham^cuAi Ehere seems no objection to this course. Mr. Collier tells me that this possibility was w\r not discussed at the interview, &amp;*** he sees no objection to a hint being included in the letter to Mr. Thornhill that I.C.I. may tender direct. As a matter of fact they will probably prefer to rely on the Government of India agreeing, in the event of the Afghans accepting the Government of India's offer, to allow I.C.I. to take over their obligations under that offer. A re-wording of paragraph 4 of the Foreign Office draft to Kabul is suggested, and a draft to the Government of India is added. Military Secretary, For any observations. 3939 5000 7/35K l&gt; I■* *1 *&gt; (iZ^' 1 . VaVLt. CO^v V^nU-^ V- I ^ X H cxtiw | p,,- V r.6x 'iX V-AW \1»4d L, ‘ ^ V.' V ■ ii This is the letter which Mr. Thornhill promised to send to confirm his conversation with Mr. Collier recorded on N.2221/593/97. On the whole it seems that it would only complicate the negotiations to inform the Afghans now of the ❖ possibility of supply direct from I.C.I. But the offer to supply the Government of India with the required ammunition for re-sale to the Afghans might be very useful, and I suppose that the Government of India would not want to make a profit on the deal and might x therefore be enabled to quote a lower price. It would however be necessary to make payment to I.C.I. conditional on the receipt of payment from the Afghan Government. I submit a draft despatch to Kabul for India Office concurrence, as proposed in the minutes on N.2221. If the India Office agree to this procedure they will doubt less draft a letter to the Government of India which could be enclosed in the despatch. (Signed) B.A.B.BURROWS. 2*3.5. I must also reply to Mr. Thornhill. Draft to him confirming what I said at the interview, and adding that the Government of India and the Minister at Kabul are being informed of the position and that the firm will be told of any further developments affecting them. (InitcL) L.C. May 23rd. I made it clear at the interview that they would only be told if and when they objected to the Government of India's terms. (Initd.) L.C. May 23rd.N 2726/593/97. \7^ May 6 i am writing in reply to your Mr. J.A. Thornhill, Dear Mr. Thornhill, (Impei'ial Chemical InciuEtries Limited), Millbank, official letter to me of 20th May to confirm i what X said at our conversation on loth *aay about the supply of ammunition to the nfghan Gov rnment, namely, that we will let you know as soon as possible if and when the Afghan Government make any difficulty about accepting the terms on which the Government of India are to supply thcm|in order that your firm may be able to put in an offer Wq, cc*\t Vxcxoq. 5\^«OrCov\ to 'ADu.C Cov&gt;\50&gt;.w^j- W ** j ' v.e^v&gt;Jv-v vaS ^Ow*T 0»OCvOv\ . at once. Ve are informing the Minister at Kabul and the Government of India of the position, and we are submitting to the latter your suggestion that Imperial Chemical Industries Limited might sup.ly the ammunition to the Government of India for re-sale to the Afghan Government' 11 m N 2726/693/97. Vl&lt;xvA Lieutenant Colonel Fraser-'rytler, (Kabul) • No: w h co^&gt;^ e^dosc^ nc - , •^Vov^WW's % - lo vA *rV^ r~' - t '*• r' v-..i t May 6 Sir# Mth reference to your seiai-orficial letter to Mr* Collier No. 824 of the 26th March last# I transmit to you herewith copies of two letters from Imperial Chemical Industries Limited regarding the supply of ammunition to t Oovei'nment, 2. The letter of 20th May was written to confirm a conversation which Mr. Thornhill had at this department on 13th i-uay# and at which he stated that his firm v,oald probably be able to offer better terms to the Afghan Government than those offered by the Government of India. Mr. Thornhill was told that he would be informed if and when the Afghan Government made any difficulty about accepting the Government of india’s terms# so that his firm could then make an offer. Mr* Thornhill added that if them 4. Pending the reply of the Afghan Government to the offer in respect of ammunition which you were authorised in my telegram, No.38, of 5th May, to make, you should not, without further reference to me, inform the Afghan Government of the possibility of supply direct from Imperial Chemical Industries on better terms. In the ^^rudArCes v-«£x\'&lt;v c Us event^of the Afghan Government taking e-xception to^the terms of the Government of India’s offer you have discretion, if the Government of India agree, to inform the Afghan Government of this possibility. Copy of a letter which is being addressed to the Government of India on the subject is enclosed.I saw Mr. Thornhill this afternoon, and found that Imperial Chemical Industries would be glad to take this business and would be prepared to offer better terms to the Afghans than those of His Majesty’s Government. I accordingly arranged with Mr. Thornhill that we would let him know as soon as possible if and when the Afghan Government made any difficulty about accepting our terms, so that his firm could at once step in with an offer. He will confirm this attitude in writing after consulting his directors. Mr. Thornhill added that, if the Afghan Government did accept our offer and the Government of India wished to avoid having to replenish their own stocks of ammunition in consequence, Imperial Chemical Industries would probably be ready to supply the required ammunition themselves to the Government of India, who could then deliver it to the Afghans without disturbing their stocks. I said I would submit this suggestion. (Signed) L. COLLIER 13th May, 1936 As the Kabul bag has just gone, we can await the letter from the I.C.I. before writing a despatch. Bring up May 20th. (Intld) L.C(ollier) May 14th.Register No. P. Z. 2892/3 6 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. .better Telegram from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Chap*fian Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Air AFGHANISTAN. Request of Imperial Chemical Industries to be put in touch with the Afghan War Minister with a view to tendering for the sale of small arms ammunition to the Afghan Government. Northern Department, Foreign Office. v; A Copy of to k b FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Minute. Previous Papers :~ 1140 1000 8.32Minute Paper, political Department. Please see Colonel Fraser-Tytler’s letter No.824 of 26th March, and Imperial Chemical Industries' letter of 22nd April. 2. The Government of India have expressed their readiness to sell to the Afghans 2^ million rounds of •303 ammunition a year for six years at a price of Rs.93,000 ptC cwCWCovv ' (£6,975)J, payment to be made one year in arrear (i.e. the delivery of the second instalment of ammunition would be effected on payment being made for the first instalment). V&gt;c It would clearly^of convenience to H.M.G. and the 1 Government of India if Imperial Chemical Industries supplied the 15 million rounds of *303 ammunition which the Afghan Government desire. It would save the Government of India from the necessity of replenishing their own stocks immediately in respect of the rounds supplied to the Afghan Government and would result in a transference of the liability for the credit involved from the new Afghan Reserve Fund to Imperial Chemical Industries. At the same time, as the Afghans have asked the Government to sell them ammunition and as we have already offered them 6 million rounds on terms similar to those indicated in para.-l, it is suggested that we should not withhold or even postpone the offer to the Afghan Government in respect of ammunition which the Government of India have agreed to make. 3. It is therefore suggested that Mr.Thornhill might be asked to call at the Foreign Office and informed confidentially of the offer which we intend to make to the Afghan Government regarding ammunition. He might be told that it is most unlikely that we would improve on our offer [and that if Imperial Chemical Industries can give the Afghan Government better terms we should be glad to see them get the business. Mr.Thornhill might be warned that the 4424 5000 1/36 Afghan/Afghan Government will certainly ask for long credit terms and he might also be told, without the fact being unduly emphasised, that while the Afghan Government show every intention of honouring their obligations and while their financial position seems to be gaining strength, there is inevitably a risk involved in giving credit to an Oriental! Government. Imperial Chemical Industries might be asked to inform us of the decision which they reach in the light of the information given to them and we could undertake to inform the Afghan Government or the War Minister of their desire to tender, subject to their offer being bettei* than the Government of India’s, a.nd subject to the state of our negotiations with the Afghan Government for the sale as far as I can make out from the papers regarding the 1934 sale of 4 million rounds by Imperial Chemical Industries to the Afghan Government, the price paid was £6,250 per million rounds, i.e. £725 less than the Government of India’s present offer. of ammunition existing at the time. It is relevant that, Military Secretary, I should be glad of your observations. - ‘S*® • V“o VCcNauV } V. CA- (S^ mjvvVv ^Voi\aVvCI\ j IqWqj- Aavc^s »cce a 'boVOAfghan Government will certainly ask for long credit terms and he might also be told, without the fact being unduly en ir fj ir Gc t c of tc tb th of of as 19 In £6 Go Mi1 Confidential British negation, Kabul 26 Ui .arch 1936. ;emi official z&lt;q* 824 » 7 Dear Collier, I forward herewith a copy of a letter received from the Imperial Cheioical ^ntiustries (India) Limited itriu of 2 ^ reply tiiereto# You may perhaps conaider tne uesiraoility of passing the corresponderice on to tiie Departiaent of overseas ‘rade so that tiiey ^ay be readj' to reply to any enquiries receivea from tne Imperial Chemical xudustries* 2* I did not feel inyself at liberty to tell tne imperial CheEiieal Industries (India) Limited that the Afghan iov«*ry&gt;aeut were negotiating for the purchase of rifle ^Munition from his Majesty’s iovorraaent# 3* I am eending a copy of tills letter and its enclosares L. Collier .isq*, C, Si* 1. , Foreign Pifflee, to walton and Metcalfe 3d/- W.K* Fraser-Tytler* Yours sincerely, LondonNo*824* British --egation, Kabul. 26th March 9 1936. Messrs Imperial Chemical Industries (India) Ltd., 18, Strand Hoad, Gentlemen, V*ith reference to your letter U/6 of the 2nd March, I have at present no confirmation of the report you have received regarding the purchase by the Afghan Government of rifle ammunition this year from Czecho—Slovakia to the approximate value of six lakhs of rupees, and consider that it is probably untrue* 2* I regret that I cannot at present give you any information of the Afghan Government’s intentions regarding their future supplies of ammunition. If your home office are interested in the matter I would suggest that they should refer to the Department of Overseas Trad*, though I cannot of course say whether that Department would be able to tell them anything* Yours faithfully, 3d/- W*K*Fraser-Tytier His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul*(x) (67174) Wt. P1606/1 Gp. 163 2000 1-20 W B &amp; L Name_ Regt. This file to be brought up on Reminder on \ Papers are only to be removed from, or placed within, this jacket by the REGISTRY</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2202</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2202</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/35 'Afghanistan: sale of ammunition to the Afghan government by Imperial Chemical Industries and others'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:52:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (142 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 143; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence regarding contracts to supply the Afghan Government with ammunition. The Government of India had agreed to supply 2.5 million rounds a year for six years, and the file primarily concerns negotiations between the Afghan Government and Imperial Chemical Industries Limited, over the supply of further ammunition.The majority of the correspondence is between Imperial Chemical Industries Limited and the Foreign Office, regarding the quantities of ammunition to be supplied, and price and payment options. The file also contains communications received by the India Office from the British Legation in Kabul (William Kerr Fraser-Tytler), reporting on meetings with the Afghan Prime Minister and War Minister, and commenting on the Afghan Government's arms-supply arrangements and negotiations with arms firms in Belgium and Czechoslovakia.The file also contains a small amount of correspondence (dated 1941) between the India Office, the Government of India External Affairs Department, and the Department of Overseas Trade, regarding a request made by the firm International Traders of Karachi for permission to import British radios into India and Afghanistan.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Imperial Chemical Industries</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Afghanistan</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>