<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000051_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T08:19:30.285Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Compliment of the Cuatoms 1 Case No. 279,at for the years,1941, 42. After the examination of the Document* of the aforementioned case,it became quite clear that the Nakhoda Salih Ahmad el-Reweijeh,had tried to smu^le the {joods mentioned below,with particulars. His intention was to sell these goods in Iraq,trying to avoid the payment of Customs Dutie*. His purpose was made quite evident by the fact of finding the goods hidden under the water tanks inside his boat,according to the reports of the commitee who examined the said boat. The denial of Nakhoda and his crews of their knowledge that the goods were hidden in their boat,is not to be i considered,owing to the fact that the goods were found hitmen in the boat &lt;U c*-0 yand were not registered as belonging to the crews, the3^foFye__, the Nakhoda is responsible for any contravention on board the ship. We,therefore, pronounced our last decisslon which is as follows Kind of goods. Price &amp; occurence Tax. Tax alone. I.D. Fils. Occurence I.D. Tax. Fils. to 25 Kilos Tea. Q,pieces 12/500 1 375 00 250 2 Ladies Dresses Art. Silk. 00/300 0 150 00 000 2 Ladies Dresses Cotton Ready made. 00/150 0 030 r-v o ients.Suits, Cotton R.-made. 1/500 0 300 -- 12 Yds.black Cotton Cloth,Pieces. 00/250 0 050 005 1 Kilo Soap 00/100 0 00 a -- --- 1 ' Sugar 00/050 0 016 -- 003 1 ” Tobacco 00/250 0 330 ** *• ^ I. ,0.15/100 2 759 -- 258. Owing to the aforementioned evidences in regard of this case and according to the Powers.delegated to me,as per Article No.159 of the Custom* Regulations No. 56 of IDU^and by the indications of Article No.A 144(3) of the same Law,I decided to condemn the Nakhoda Salih Ahmad el-Reweijeh only, and to fine him with the sum of I.D. 5/- ,and in case of unpayment of this amount ,this case will be seen by the 6ourt of Summary, to enforce the Article No.163, of the aforementioned Law,and to give the said .Nakhoda the free choice of retaining the goods with the • • boat by paying a Ransom Fine of I.D.10/- according to Article No.160 of the Customs Regulations. Bonus:- Bonus will be given to those who discovered this case,when Protest and Appeal are over. Inspector Mikhael Abdul-Ahad■y. / Translation of letter No.R/6/170l7 &lt; 3-ated the 2nd March, 1942, from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait, to the Political Aaent, Ku r ait. © After Compliments, . \j^ ' T have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Excellency’s letter Ncu40, dated the 26th February, 1942, regarding the ca ;e o'' Ho&gt;hudha o° tie water boom, who was found to be i possession of some smu^lcd goods. I wish to express my thanks for your valuable and kind remarks and in'the meantime'I ~a?fi very sorry that such thing had happened. Your Excellency knov, very veil, that the export of any goods was recently forbidden to any other country except Saudi-Arabia. It is unlikely that I would allow any export while I issue strict orders th t nothing is allowed to be exported in the regular vay. I can as are you V- t T strictly orohibited the s^ ' :lin ' of any kind of goods to Iraq and anyone /ho dares to do so is liable to severe punishment, moreover, hen I received the information of the case of the said Nokhudha, I ordered that he must be examined and as the result of questioning him, it as found out that the ^oods but still I ordered that Nokhudha should receive his punishment, being v sponsible for his boat, and the sailor who caused this trouble was fined and sent to jail. He will not be employed by any water boom at anymore. All water booms hereafter will be examined carefully and hope that nothing will occur in future. Usual Ending.T).0. *?o.0/183 Political \genoy Kuwait, 11 til T ^rcb, 1942. lly dear Ringrow, * \ . Tnank you for your letoor )*0.?fo.l of 26th January, 1942. T enclose a copy of a letter from His Hjgnness vhioh T received in reply to an enquiry in rega’Ti to this case. Everything possiole is oeing none here to check smuggling. Yours sincerely Ungrow Esquire, Ureotor of CustOfas Basra.No. 0/286 / 7/. S A A) The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Secretary of State for India* Londoru THe Secretaiv to the Government of India, External Affairs Departinent, New Delni &gt; V^The Political Agent, Kuwait . and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the document^). undermentioned British Consula’e-Genpral^^^^^Sfil. Dated Camp, Banrain British Emhassy Baghdadi Note No* 153 dated 16 th March, 1942 to Ministry of Foreign Affairs* Kuwait - Iraq smuggling.NfeMM' Received under Baghdad Printed Letter No. 448/4/42 dated the 16th March, 1942. No. 155o -v His Majesty’s Emhassy presents its compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to address them on the following matter. The Moweiti aoverniiient have reauested that an approach should he made to tne Iraqi Government with a viev/ to obtaining the cancellation of Customs Regulation No. -30 of 1935 and the re-opening of transit - trade from Iraq, to Koweit. 2 e The Ministry will recall that the above-mentioned j Regulation was brought into force because the Iraqi authorities believed that goods moved through Iraq, to Koweit were frequently smuggled bock again into this country, ''’he Koweiti authorities point out that for some time no smuggling has occurred and represent that the retention of the restrictions imposed by Regulation No. 30 of 1935 is therefore unnecessary | and harmful to the commercial interests of both countries. 3. Nevertheless should the Iraqi authorities regard the setting up of such arrangements as a condition for the cancellation of the Regulation in question the Koweiti Government are willing that a system of manifests should be established to cover all goods exported from Koweit to Iraq and from Iraq to Koweit. 4, The Embassy has the honour to request that the Koweiti Government’s proposals should be cornminicated to the competent Iraqi departments for consideration and ^ould be glad to be informed o^ the result in due course. His Majesty’s Embassy avails itself o^ this opportunity to renew the expression of its highest consideration. British Embassy, Baghdad. 16th March, 1942.INDIA OFFICE RECORDS</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000051_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/134</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000051</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/134</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/2 VII Contraband Questions with Iraq. (Kuwait-Iraq Smuggling)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-27T22:47:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-11; these numbers are also written in pencil and circled, but are crossed through.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Director of Customs and Excise, Basra and the Political Agent, Kuwait, related to a case of a Kuwaiti nakhuda who had been fined by the customs office for smuggling goods from Kuwait. In turn, the Political Agent, Kuwait, passed the case to the Shaikh of Kuwait to deal with the nakhuda. The file also includes a letter sent by the British embassy, Baghdad, to the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs. The letter is about the Kuwaiti Government asking the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs to amend certain customs regulations related to smuggling.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Excise</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><subject><topic>Legislation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000051#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>