<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000094_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:51:50.831Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Memorandum on the state of Affairs in Persia by Major-General Sir II . Rawlinson. • 1. Sir Henry Wolff, on arriving in Persia, seems to have been much impressed with the gloomy aspect of affairs. He noticed at once that the Persians were naturally a more intelligent and genial race than the Turks, more eager for instruction, and more fitted for progress; but at the same time it was evident that they were suffering from a long course of misgovern- ment. There was a feeling of almost despondency abroad, a general sense of insecurity of life and property, and the expectation, apparently, that the occupation of the country by Russia was imminent and inevitable ; nor did the character and surroundings of the Shah afford much relief. His Majesty was jealous, timid, suspicious, and avaricious; not insensible by a,ny means to the benefits of civilization, but dreading its approach to Persia as a danger to his own absolute power, and a restraint upon his insatiable rapacity. 2. Sir Henry Wolff’s instructions, framed after the usual official type, directed his attention to the necessity of immediate and far extended reforms, to the importance of developing the resources of the country, and improving its means of transit and communication, and in fact generally to the creation of a “strong, friendly, and independent” Government at Teheran. 3. These instructions he was bound to obey, yet with such intractable materials at his disposal, how was any progress to be made towards the objects in view? The Shah would certainly not initiate any substantial reforms of administration, nor establish institutions tending to invigorate his subjects, nor would he even admit of European interference, except in so far as it might conduce to the strengthening of his individual authority, or minister to his passion for accumulating wealth. 4. Not being able to see his way ahead, Sir Henry D. Wolff seems to have taken counsel of his Russian colleague. Now, British Ministers at Teheran, being to a great extent isolated and self-dependent, have always been obliged to make use of extraneous aid, in order to acquire a position which might enable them to carry out their instructions and exercise a beneficial influence on the country. Sir John Malcolm, for instance, turned out the French by means of gold. Sir Harford Jones obtained possession of his famous “ preliminary Treaty ” by bluster and personal violence. Sir John McNeill acquired his extraordinary influence at the Court of Feth Ali Shah mainly through the support of the Taj-ed-Dowleh, the Shah’s favourite Queen. Others have availed themselves of the good offices of prominent ministers' and even of the “ Ulema.” I myself, during my brief tenure of office, aimed almost exclusively at gaining the personal confidence of the Shah, while Prince Malcom Khan, who is a shrewd observer and a man of great ex perience, recommends an appeal to the masses, asserting that, if the public feeling is once enlisted in favour of reforms, Shah and ministers will follow suit without a murmur. 5. It was reserved for Sir Henry Wolff to suggest the regeneration of Persia through the joint instrumentality of the Russian Legation, and, bold as the suggestion may appear, he is not wanting in arguments to support it He argues that the dead lock at Teheran has been hitherto mainly caused by the antagonism of English and Russian interests, the Shah being indisposed to make concessions to one power for fear of offending the other, and more especially in regard to matters affecting the Shah’s personal position • he quotes the universal belief that His Majesty would prefer dealing with’ the two Powers together than with either singly, inasmuch as a joint concession involves a less sacrifice of dignity, and gives a greater security in the future. For instance, if England and Russia, having exchanged pledges for main- 17158. I. 1591.2 taining the integrity of Persia, were to approach the Shah with a joint re commendation in favour of opening up the country generally to European enterprise, of promoting trade, strengthening the hands of justice, and guaranteeing security of life and property, and, if they could assert at the same time that such measures were essential to the prosperity of the country and to the Shah’s enjoyment of tranquillity during the remainder of his reign, Sir Henry Wolff was assured that His Majesty would adopt the views of his European advisers, and subordinate his policy to theirs. In fact, a part of this programme was actually realized in the publication, presumably at the instigation of the Legations, of the Shah’s recent proclamation, which, if honestly carried out, may yet be held to constitute a charter of Persian liberties, and to inaugurate a new era of reform. 6. But here I must pause and ask what grounds are there, beyond this proclamation, which, after all, may be merely tentative, for supposing that Russia is acting in good faith in offering to coalesce with us ? I myself look upon Sir Henry Wolff’s proposed Convention, with its mutual obligations and responsibilities, with the gravest suspicion. “ Timeo Danaos, et dona ferentes.” What possible reason is there for believing that Russia has suddenly changed the whole bent and tenor of her Eastern policy ? Why should she desire Persia to become a flourishing and independent State, standing in the way of her own territorial aggrandisement ? Is it credible that, after the Russian press has been inveighing for months against granting to England any facility of access to the north of Persia from the Persian Gulf, denouncing it indeed as an invasion of Russia’s right of monopolizing the trade of Central Asia, the Czar’s Government should suddenly turn round and offer to co-operate with England in encouraging transit by road and railway, or by river and canal, through this very region, intermediate between Bushire and Teheran ? The only explanation that Sir Henry Wolff suggests is that Russia may find herself debarred by the state of her finances from pursuing an active policy in Persia, and may thus be compelled to fall back upon a compromise. I would rather suggest myself, if there is any reality in Prince Dolgorouki’s overtures, that Russia may think she sees in her joint mediation with us in Southern Persia a means of destroying our influence in that region, and possibly of establishing herself in some con venient position on the shores of the Persian Gulf, where we should find her a disagreeable and even a dangerous neighbour. 7. The practical question seems, however, to be, Is there any cause for immediate alarm? Sir Henry Wolff evidently thinks that a crisis is approaching, being led into that belief by persistent rumour on the one hand and by certain observations of the Russian authorities on the other hand with regard to the partition of Persia between England and Russia, which may be significant or may be sheer gossip. Certainly there is nothing in the official proceedings of Russia to indicate immediate danger. She is showing restlessness it is true on. the Khorassan frontier, which liiay eventuate in a further accretion of territory at the expense of Persia, but this is a local grievance, connected with her position at Merv and Sarakhs, and hardly affects the general question. Again, she has been exercising of late a some what unusual degree of pressure at Teheran, which has shown itself in the removal of the Zil-i-Sultan from power, and in the appointment of her creature, the Amin-i-Sultan, to the first post in the Government of the Shah, but intrigues of this nature are normal at the Persian Court, and do not mean anything serious. 8. When I look abroad, indeed, at the condition of Europe, and at our state of military preparation both in India and in England, I cannot believe that Russia, from a mere lust of conquest or without some definite end in view, would, at the present time, attack the integrity of Persia, a step which she must know would involve her in immediate hostilities with England along the whole line from Batoum to Merv. 9. The Persians, it must be remembered, are a long suffering race, and their cup is not yet full. They may very well linger on in a sort of suspended political animation for another generation, the sport of fate, and subject to the rival influences of England and Russia, unless, indeed, some great &amp; * . 4 * I ■3 calamity should intervene, such as the death of the Shah, or the horrors of a disputed succession, which might wake into activity the elements of disorder that, though concealed, are undoubtedly at hand. 10. The most unfavourable feature probably in the whole range of the Persian question is the geographical position of the seat of Government, not so much on strategical grounds—for if war broke out with Russia it would matter little whether an invading army had to march 200 or 500 miles in order to seize and occupy the capital—as on account of the moral effect which a sense of military insecurity must naturally exercise on the nation at large. Teheran, in the immediate neighbourhood of the Caspian Sea, is notoriously at the mercy of Russia, and this feeling of utter helplessness weighs, no doubt, on every Department of the State. To an outside observer the prospect is not, perhaps, quite so depressing, for we have the example of Bokhara before our eyes, where Russia has been coquetting for the last 20 years, eager for annexation, and yet recoiling from the responsibility of assuming the government of an exclusively Mahammedan country, notwithstanding that the ITzbegs are far less numerous, less warlike, and less fanatical than the Persians. It is my belief that Russia will think twice before she under takes a serious invasion of Persia, yet I should greatly desire to see the capital, with its reported five millions of treasure, removed to the central position of Ispahan, not so much on military grounds as in order to give confidence to the people, and for the greater convenience of administration. 11. Another matter for serious consideration is the question of the succession, which may crop up at any moment and lead to the gravest con sequences. It is devoutly to be hoped that a contest may be avoided, though the outlook at the present moment is anything but reassuring. It is under stood, indeed, that, according to the existing arrangement, Russia is pledged to the recognition of the Veli Ahd, who resides at Tabriz, and has always been, more or less, under her influence, this adoption of his cause being due not to any personal fitness or any special claim of the Prince on the Emperor’s support, but simply to the acceptance as a matter of form at St. Petersburg of the Shah’s edict of some years back which proclaimed his second son to be heir apparent, in deference to the usage of the Kajar dynasty, which for many generations past has limited the succession to the Crown to the issue of ladies of the royal tribe. The Veli Ahd is said to be quite unfit for the duties of such an exalted position, and, although supported by a certain party at Tabriz, to be generally unpopular in the country. If no steps, therefore, are taken in advance to smooth over the difficulty, there will assuredly be a crisis of great severity in the country when the Shah dies, for the Zil-i-Sultan, with the right of primogeniture on his side, and supported by the whole military strength of central and southern Persia, will prove a most formidable adversary. A life and death struggle indeed between the brothers would be the natural consequence, to be followed by Russia’s intervention in the north, and possibly by England’s in the south. Negotiations with Russia to avert such a catastrophe have probably occupied the attention of Her Majesty’s Government as of more importance than the discussion of impracticable railways or of hypothetical reforms. 12. I now venture to add a few words on the general question of railways in Persia, a subject on which I am afraid I hold views that are not quite in accordance with those entertained by Her Majesty’s Government.- 1 do not myself think that Persia and Turkey are very favourable countries for experimentalizing with railways. The people are generally indisposed to change, and still more to locomotion, and they have no idea of the value of time. To familiarize them with railways as an engine of civilization, as a means of improving the condition of a country, and especially as a profitable investment of capital (for the Persians are essentially a commercial people), it would be necessary that the earliest essays should be attended with ex ceptional advantages, that is, that the first experimental lines should pass through centres of population, that they should be accessible to feeders, and should present no great engineering difficulties, the economical results being thus patent to observation. But in our Persian projects we have entirely overlooked these considerations. For our first test line, from Mohamrah to4 Teheran, we have selected the most inhospitable country, and the most inaccessible tracing in all Persia. The navigation of the Karun would no doubt create a certain amount of local traffic at Shuster and Dizful, but beyond that point we should have everything against us. The physical difficulties in ascending the mountain chain so as to reach the plateau of interior Persia would be not inconsiderable, while we should further be brought in contact with the wildest tribes in the whole extent of the Empire. 13. There is not a town or village in the country for hundreds of miles, nor hardly an acre of cultivated land. Knowing the country, indeed, as well as I do from personal observation, I cannot believe it possible to build a railway through the Lur and Bakhtiari mountains except at an enormous expenditure, altogether disproportionate to the value of the work, and even if the railway were built the resident tribes are, I believe, irreclaimable, and would render regular traffic impossible. As for the hope of obtaining a dividend on a capital of five millions and a half to be expended on such a line, the idea seems to me preposterous, and it is therefore with a feeling of extreme relief that I learn of the final resolve of the Home and Indian G-overnments not to guarantee any rate of interest on the capital to be raised, a resolve which must of course lead to the entire abandonment of the scheme. 14. At the same time, apart from financial considerations, I have the greatest desire to see railways introduced into Persia. The opportunities they would afford us of becoming acquainted with the tribesmen and peasantry of the country, of conciliating their good will and improving their condition, would, in a political point of view, be simply invaluable. Whether in a country so sparsely populated and so poorly supplied railways could, under any circumstances, be made remunerative must remain an open question; but, at any rate, in order to give the experiment a fair chance of success, it would be indispensable to follow the only true artery of trade in the south of Persia, leading from Bushire, through Shiraz and Ispahan, to Teheran, where, except for a short space between Bushire and Shiraz, there are no engineering difficulties, and where the inhabitants along the line are both civilized and friendly. After what I have already said, it can hardly be necessary that I should deprecate any joint action with Russia in such an enterprise. She could not possibly render any executive assistance, whereas she might cause us a good deal of political embarrassment. London, 26th June 1888. H. 0. Rawlcnson. is L</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000094_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C59</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000094</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C59</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on the state of affairs in Persia by Major-General Sir H Rawlinson'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1888/1888</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-02-18T12:15:28</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (2 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 9, and terminates at f 10, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum was compiled by diplomat Major-General Sir Henry Creswicke Rawlinson, and discusses various subjects relating to the state of affairs in Persia including:the perceived nature of the Persian people;the perceived character of the current Shah of Teheran [Tehran] and concerns over the future succession;the style of governance in Persia;English-Russian relations and the involvement of both countries in Persia;the views of Sir Henry Wolff on reforms in Persia and the appropriate action for the English to take;the proposed building of railways in Persia.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir 1st Baronet Henry Creswicke Rawlinson</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Teheran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000094#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>