<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000ce_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:23:40.683Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Collection No. Serial — Subject. 23 CIVIL ENGINEER FOR KUWAIT , A Previous References. Later References. 3 i--” S. 97—(Green). MFP—700 S&amp;P—(M-1107)—4-10-39—100,000.Telegram Q Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire Prom To No C/106 Dated the 17th March, 1939. Engineer for Ku w ait State . Shaikh has written to me asking us to arrange as quickly as may he possible for an Engineer capable of directing construction of landing quay and other municipal works in Kuwait. Length of appointment six months, salary as low as possible consonant with efficiency but amount to be decided by British authorities with whose decision Shaikh will agree. Shaikh has in mind a British Indian Muslim, preferably knowing Arabic, but leaves choice to us. 2. Would it not be possible to send the Assistant Engineer MURTEZA who is conversant with local conditions artf. would be under our control, at the same time being cheap, as Shaikh wishes.? - Political5 CONFIDENTIAL . No. c-htf The Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to * The Honourable the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIKE. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). for information. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the l?th March, 1939. Reference to previous correspondence: His telegram No.0/106, dated 17th March 1939. DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE. Name and Date. Subject. Translation of letter No.H/6/1151l dated 15th March 1939 from His Highness the Ruler of Kuwait to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Civil Engineer for Kuwait.1939 from His Higiaaeas the auler of Kuwait to the Political Agent f Kuwait. ' 0 . Tbe cause of writing this ooriial letter is that we require a Civil Kngineer to direct the new rorks on the Port and its quays, ye request Your Excellency to provide an Indian Engineer for this purpose, so we shall he much grateful if you will try your heat in selecting tne proper Engineer who has experience and who is suitable for this work. Thanking Your Excellency In anticipation.» V &gt; ^ j , CONFlD$Sll\l s ± • (f) D.O. No,3£3&gt; Ktiivni! U\-cfi/&gt;t xM^ 'laji. 18th March, 1939. Please refer to your telegram I^o. c/106 dated 17th F e bruary. 2. The Assistant Engineer is leaving by the Up-mail on Monday and I have telegraphed you his probable date of ar rival. 3. Will you please have the Shaikh^ requirements ex plained to him. He will be able to advise on the best and most reasonable way to have the work carried out. If the work is such that the Assistant Engineer can himself super vise it without detriment to his official duties sir Trenchard will be prepared to give the necessary authorisation. In this connection please see S.R.ll of the Compilation of Funda mental Rules and Supplementary Rules. 4. If it is possible for the Assistant Engineer to carry out the work will you please go into the question of honor arium with the Shaikh, and submit your proposals. In this G. H. de Gaury, Esquire, Political Agent, Kuwait.jV, i. &amp; 2. this event there will be no objection to the Assistant Engineer reicaining in Kuwait to commence the preliminary wo rk. 5. If the work is such that it will not be practicable for him to supervise it in addition to his normal duties then I am to suggest that the quickest way to obtain a man would be by advertisement in the Indian papers. 6. It would probably be possible to have the candidates interviewed by Colonel D. G. Johnston, C«I»S.» the Chairman of the Karachi Port Trust thereby ensuring that the shaikh obtained a nan capable of undertaking the work. Sir Trenchard would be prepared to write to Colonel Johnston. r ^c ^CONFIDENTIAL ^om Identlal Ktnniit h’ : No }2&gt;0 Don I 3&lt;5p GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ~ Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N,B. — This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication mart expedition* than the ordinary mail and i* cheaper than the telegraph. It i* intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sire time and to o &gt;riat^ formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 212 -*i To .v« pea ted Dated Buehire 9 the Ne 18 th March 19 39‘. Hie Majesty 9 e ieoretary of 'tate for lridla 9 London. the secretary to the Ooveriinent of India in the eternal d’faire iepaxtuent, :&lt;ew ^elhi • rhe political ment 9 Kuwait. V Reference auhjtot » .n^ineer for uwait Hunicii ali ty. iteferenoe correspondence ending with my Express Letter Jo.J/ 114 , dated the 3 rd May 1937 * The shaikh of Kuwait has applied for the services of an en^irteer from us to carry on municipal work in uwait 9 arid I oia making arrangements. it is satisfactory that the shaikh continues to turn to us for expert employees# It is also satisfactory that he now proposes to spend Kuwait revenues on the improvement of his ~»tate instead of putting these into his own pocket as has been his practice hitherto* In this I see the influence of the Jouncll which he has just S 8 tabllshed 9 and for the formation of which I have always besn strongly in favour 9 •''I? '^ H K/ !^0 ^T) vide my express Letter k&gt;*J/ 334 9 dated the 18 th Juiie 1938 * if the shaikh had at that time taken His Majesty 9 s Govenssent*s advice and mine the troubles in Kuwait of the last six months probably would Md.t’kx have been avoided* &gt;d*T.j.]rowu«i lolltioul Resident in the lerslan Gulf• attested (Signature) (Designation) SfAt ^ebretary to the j olltioal v»al&lt;dS3it-trruShw~-iiar-ed)sqa Julf*Telegram From To No. GTC. Political Hesi&amp;ent, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. 35 Dated the 18th and received the 19th March, 1939. MTJRTAZA leaves hy Up Slow on Monday March 20th and will arrive Kuwait on Wednesday or Thursday. - Resident Telegram From To No. GTC Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire. C/116 Dated the 19th March, 1939. Your telegram No. 35 of March 18th. Is the visit of MURTAZA in connection with my telegram No. C/106 of March 16th? Please confirm. - PoliticalTelegram Code From No To Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Resident, Bushire C/142. Dated the 29th March, 1939. Your telegram No. 36 of March 20th. Shaikh would like MURTAZA to make plans of several projected works hut MURTAZA says he wishes to return to Bushire to do accounts on April 2nd. 2. Now that Shaikh is at last ready to make these improvements I hope Engineer may stay. Do you agree? PoliticalTelegram From To No. GTC Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. 185 Dated and received the 30th March, 1939. Your telegram No. C/142 of March 29th. MURTAZA can stay another week. If necessary I will explain to Accounts authorities that he was on tour under my orders. - Resident - A7 iwt-ajyc * I *Politioal Agency, Kuwait, 14th April, 1939. D.O. Ho. c //72 My dear Sir Trenchard, Could you please refer to the correspondence ending with your telegram No. 185 of J'arch 30th, 1939, regarding Assistant Engineer ’Turtaza*’ 2. As you know, he Is now temporarily returned to Bushire, having given to the local authorities certain plans, estimates etc. for a harbour aal landing quays. 3. His Highness the Shaikh, who was pleased with Hurtaza 's work, and most grateful to you, asks if he can be sent back here as early as may be possible for supervision of the building work am the making of other plans. The Hon ble Sir Trenchard ?owle, KCIE.. OBE ic political Resident in the Persian'oulf '' - / Bushire. — »r-v /V D. 0 . No. 550 24th April, 1939 Vj dut&lt;U ~b&lt;. Cu^ Please refer to your D.O. letter No.G/172 dated the 14th \pril 193 9 to Sir Trenchard regarding Assistant Engi neer Murtaza. 2. It would appear that the Kuwait Government desires the services of the Assistant Engineer in both of the fol io v/ing categories: (a) As a consulting engineer for the preparation of p la ns , etc., (b) As an Executi^ Engineer for the supervision of actual construction work. 3. Sir Trenchard desires me to say that there is no objec tion to the Assistant Engineer undertaking work under (a) above, if and when required, during his visits to Kuwait on Government duty, but he is not prepared to permit him to carry out the duties of supervision under (b). In order to carry out proper supervision of building operations it would % be necessary for him to remain in Kuwait permanently until . de Gaury, Esq. , M.G.» litical Agent, Kuwait /tneirtheir completion and this is not possible. On the other hand, if he undertook supervision during his short visits to Kuwait on Government duty we would lay ourselves open to criticism for any inferior, and probably concealed work done during his absence. * 4. While permitting the Assistant Engineer to undertake work under (a) the Kuwait Government must realise that a reasonable fee will have to be paid by them for his services, a third of which, under the Rules in force, will go to Govern ment, and in computing such fee regard must be paid to this fact. 5. Sir Trencnard has decided tnat the fee for the work already done by the Assistant Engineer should be Rs.200/- which, he desires me to point out, is a distinctly low figure, and for which the services of a competent Iraqi engineer could not have been obtained. 6. Will you kindly explain the position to the Shaikh and request him to pay this fee of Rs.200/- to us through your office at an early date ?D.O. No. C/192 Political Agency, Kuwait, 29th April, 1939. Will you please refer to demi-official letter No. 530, dated the 24th April, 1939, from Bushton? Mr. Murtaza almost as soon as he arrived here me know that his fees for his work and his allowances here would make a total of Rs. 700/- per month. (This amount included Rs. 10/- for 'Transport allowance' although he was ■being provided with transport hy the local authorities, as well, as had heen suggested hy me, a house and servant) 4 I considered this sura ridiculously high and I let him know it. A little later he announced his immediate return to Bushire. I then sent you ray telegram No. 0/142 of March 29th. 2. The Shaikh now 'believes that he will return to continue (a) plans and (h) supervision, Just as would an | engineer from Iraq or elsewhere, and he told me that he would pay him well on completion of his work. I understoo&lt; when I was hinting that he should treat the Engineer, when he arrived very well, that it would he much more than Rs. 200, and that the Shaikh was so grateful to you for the quick despatch here and our assistance that he was anxious to treat him generously. In any case there is no question of the Kuwait Government not realizing that a reasonable sum must he paid and I shall hope to send you the amount for his work so far (fc. 200) hy the next mail. 3. In view, however,* of the fact that most of the future work will merely 'supervision', which is of course beneath the qualifications of ?^r. Murtaza, I recommend that a different engineer he sent next time. ’he Hon •hie Sir Trenchard Fowle, KCIE, OHS. Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf* Bushire.a D.O. Ifo.fcDS -53/12 4 th May, 1939 Please refer to your demi-official letter No. C/192 dated the 29th kpril, 1939, to Sir Trenchard on the subject of the employment of the Assistant Engineer by the i£uv.ait GovernE£nt. 2. Sir Trenchard is pleased to learn that the Shaikh is gratified with the work already done by the Assistant Jingine er. 3. With regard to your request however that another engineer should be sent to undertake the work of super vising the actual building operations I am to refer you to para 3 of my demi-official letter No.530 of the 24th April. The objections mentioned therein to the employ ment of t he Assistant Engineer would apply to any P.W.D. subordinate we might send and I am a ccord ingly to say that the Political Resident is not prepared to allow G.S.H. de Gaury, Esq., M.C., Political Agent, Kuw ait. /anyany Government servant to undertake the work of supervision as contemplated by the Shaikh.Political Agency, D.O* No. ^4/ 6th June, 1939. Kuwait TTy dear Rush ton, Jlth reference to the correspondence ending with your demi-official letter No. 603-53/12, dated the 4th May, 1939, on the subject of the employment of the Assistant Engineer by the Kuwait Government, a Supply Bill for te. 200/- is enclosed. Captain H.D. Rush ton .U T JlJJ. « XVbtOXl vvyxx. , Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000ce_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/211</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000ce</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/211</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/23 Civil Engineer for Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-08T22:47:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (22 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 24; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-23; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding a request made by the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah for the Political Agency in Kuwait to find him a suitable engineer to oversee an expansion of the country's port.The correspondence discusses Shaikh Ahmad's initial request, the appointment of an Indian engineer named Murtaza, his subsequent arrival in Kuwait and the payment for his initial spell of work in the country.Much of the correspondence is between British officials but the file also contains a limited amount of correspondence between Shaikh Ahmad and the Political Agency in Kuwait (in Arabic with English translations) including his request for assistance in hiring an engineer (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Civil engineering</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000ce#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>