<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000163_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T05:17:58.976Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram X. From - Citili Commissioner, Baghdad. To - Secretary of State for india,London,repeated No. Foreigoi Simla. 7733 Dated - 16th. September 1913. ?rom a perusal of recent correspondence regarding oil concessions in Mesopotamia it seems possible that one aspect of the question has not yet been placed before H .M f 8 Govemment. If the future administration of Irak is to be self supporting it is essential that it should be in a position to derive the fullest benefit consistent with Imperial exigencies from the at present undeveloped mineral wealth in its boundaries. Until such an administration representing the interests of the inhabitants of Irak his been formed and the political status of the country decided it would I submit be indefensible to apportion mineral or other rights therein so far as navi^tioi^ri ^hts are concerned this has been specifically reco^iized by H.M 1 s Grovemment As far as is at present known there are four oil bearing areas, viz. 1. Naft Khan a 2. Hit. 3. Chia Snrkh 4. Tus Khurmati and Gil. to thesd may be added the oil bearing region near Koweit. It seems unlikely that oil will be struck else where. Of these areas the first has been most favourably reported on and is about to be tested and if need be developed by the A.P.O.C. No reply has been received to the proposal made from here on July 27th to the ?ar Office that the n v ij Company should be instructed to keep an account of all . expenditure incurred on the above operations with a view to payment out of military funds. If payment out of military funds is open to objection I should not hesitate to recommend payment fron: Ks2. from the Revenues of the Occupied Territoriea. As already explain^ the Anglo Persian Oil Company has a claim to preferential treatment in respect of the first and third areas but not to the others. I doubt however whether they could establish more than the ri^it to be given first refusal. Tne terms on which they are permitted to work the deposits would be a matter for eventual settlement with the Administration of Irak subject to the approval of H.M.G. Both on political and economical grounds it seeras to me that there are strong objactions against giving to concessions for mineral erploitation^indi vicHials or to uncontrolled firms and the case against giving rights in the Middle East to bore for oil to more than one firm also appears to be strong. I share the dcutts expresccd in correcponience at home as to the fitness of the A.P.O.C. as at present constituted to uniertake development, in this area. The system whereby the Company's affairs on the spot are controlled by Mana^inr Agent,who are also merchants,and whose various branches in India, the Gulf, and liesopotarda are all bent on making as much as possible from th^ J.®rent Company leads to s difficulties in practice ajad to inefficiency in some directior I venture however to express the o.oLiioa that^the management of the Company both at home and abroad cculd be ntrengthenfd and could be made independent of peconda.ry ccmercial concerns,there would be much to be for entrusting it under Government control both ft home and in Mesopotamia, with the Imperial task of developing th^ oil resources of S. Persia,the Gulf and Mesopotamia. Addroased Secretary of ^tate for India,repeated Foreign Simla. Political Baghdad. 1; / j tc~ Telegram R® Clear Line* / from Politioal lia^hdad® lo 3« of 3.f or India, London, repeated foreign Delhi and 10 prodrome Tehran# M o. isaoi Datsd 4th UOTember 1919. Raport received from Mosul November 3r4 that Mr.J.H.Bill Indian Civil Servioe and Captain K.H.3oott.3l8t^|ubjabl8. Indian Army,respectively Politioal Officer,Mosul and *XM9 Mr». 'ere attacked and killed by a body of about 100 Kurds near Bin. Kapra in the Zab Valley, Horth-Bast of Mr* to which place they 'era returning from 3arian after inspecting recruits for yroutier aendamsris posts supplied by leading local Chief; one of gendarmes with them escaped and brought new® to Aqra* perpetrators who apparently belong to Zibar Tribs attacked Aqrs at dawn on the ard about 300 strong Gendarmsris post wes unable to hold out and retired# gome of local Kurdish Sendarmafis are reported to have joined enemy and aeroplanes which reconnoitred over Mr* on Uovember 3rd were heavily fired on* It is difficult for me to adequately express my feelings at the loss of these two capable and gallant cifioers. Mr.Bill agreed to take up the post of Politioal officer Mosul at my urgent request and had recently initiated negotia tions with Kurdish Cribes in Amadia Region which promtaed to result in a satisfactory settlement. His personality, judgment. experience and personal courage alike combined to ma^e him a public servant of rare value® Captain Scott was a capaole young officer of high prom.se who joined me last year from the 15th Division and had spent about a year in the Moe^-i. ^xvidioiia He had already made himself respected and liked by all classes® I will report further developments when known® La:or L.J. Haider,Sudan Civil Service will succeed Mr.Bill as Politict.1 Officer* Addressed India off ice, repeated Delhi and Tehran# G£iro and Constantinople informed® Political gaghdadTelegram, En. cl. From - political, Baghdad. To - Mrs. Bill, c/o political, Bushire, No. 13190. Dated 4th rlovenber 1919. Political. For Mrs Bill. BEGINS. Grave disturbancea have broken out in the AqnaJi region Northeast of Mosul wh^ra Mr. Bill with Captain Scott was touting, facts not yet definitely ascertained but grave fears are entertained for his safety. ENDS, Teleg^ram. En, cl. Prom - Wilson, Baghdad. To - Mrs. Bill c /o P 0 litical, Bushire. Bated 5th November 1919. PRIOKITY.' Though reports now to hand are not absolutely conclusive I fear there can be little doubt that I^'r, J .H .Bill was killed on November second along with Captain K.a.,Scott wao accompanied him. Details are being sent to Bushire by separate telegram. I cannot find words with which to express my sympathy with you and my sorrow at the death of a colleague who it was a privilege to know and work with. i 1 Wilson./&gt; * Telegram, En. cl. From - W'lson, Political, Baghdad. To - P 0 litical, Bua^ire, Mo. 13269. Dated 5th November 1919. For Mrs, Bill. All possible steps have been taken' to get definite news, I will inform you earliest possible. Wilson Political, Telegram, En. cl. From - Mansons, Shiraz, To - Mrs, Bill, Shiraz, Bated fith November 1919, Our deepest sympathy. Maneon9, Telegram. X mx Ohit, From - Fraser, Shiraz, To - Mrs £&gt;ill # Bushire, Dated 6th November 1919, Deepest sympathy from all Soper, Fraser,Ov Telegram Pron P creign ,13iinl a 1 To Political^ushlre Repeated Baghdad N0.1583/S Dated 6th received 7th Ncventoer 191© # «fl Please breaJc the newo to Lira JH11 that her Husband has been IdLlled In the Mooul district by abend of tfUrds ^If ycxi have not already dene so Please ccnvey to lirs Mil His Excellency the Vicercy^s deepest regret and sympathy ,» The Foreign Secretary ai behalf of him- • self end the Political Department begs to offer Mrs Mil en sincerest ccndolences xaxSfian^ Mr Mil 1 s death by nhich the Defartment have loot a most capable and gsilent oTficer ,•«Telegram, Qode, From - Political, Baghdad. To - political, iiushire, iro # 1333«. Sated 8th received 7tii Uovenber 1919. I am arranging direct paaaago for Mrs, Bill with governess and child by •Prams Ferdinand' I hope to divert tjfck it to call at Buenire about 13th, please confirm. Political. Telegram. Code. - From - political, Bughire. To - P 0 litical, Baghdad. No.1351. Dated 7th November 1919, Your 13336. Mrs. Bill extremely grateful for arrangements you are making for direct passage by 'Franz Ferdinand'. Passage for Mrs. Bill and child only required. Politi cal.Te legr am P ^ 1 From PoliticalyBbghdad To Politicalshire &gt; No ,13400 Dated 8th received 9th Novenlber IS 19 Please give the following to !!rs Bill Begins The fact of the death of your hueb-sid sa^d Captain Scott has been placed bey aid dcubt by news Which has been received today They were treacherously attached and killed instsntly His effects will be sent to reach you before you leave I am applying in due course for the rensicn to which his family wculd be entitled had he held the rank cf Lt-Colcnel ^at the date of his death en aotive service Whatever pensicn may be admissible under Civil Rules is of course entirely serarate ^and my application is additlcnal to this Political -7- ' I - - - - i ,ii. iofi aotlh/.ML'U T©10grarn, Code, FroTT. - political, baghdad, To.- political, Buahire, No.14038. Dated Slat received 22nd November 1919, Following received from India Office. bEOINS. Lord Ourzon has heard with deep regret of the death of Mr.J.H.Bill, Indian Civil Service, and Captain K.H.Scott Slat Punjabis at the hands of the Kurdish tribes at Aqrah. Mr. Bill's excellent work as british Consul at Shiraz and Assistant to the political Heaident in the Persian Gulf and later as Deputy Political Hesident at Busriire are remembered with appreciation by the Foreign Office, and Lord Curzon feels that His Majesty's Government can ill afford to lose the services o' two such able and devoted officers. ENDS. Mr. Montague adds in a subsequent telegram that he desires to associate himself with the sentiments expressed by Lord Curzon in his above telegram. « political.Telegram P. From Cox,Baghdad. To Trevor,BuBhire. Wo. 5§0-S Dated 15th received 16th April 1921. Per so aal and Very Secret. I am sending you 2 messages in the four immediately following telegrams, which cannot be despatched fr6m here for fear of leakage, and which I beg you will' be so kind as to send en clair from Bushire and arrange with the Assistant Superintendent Telegraphs to have sent confioertially i am sending translations as well in order to assist you with the decyphering and for the purpose of spelling out the Arabic Indian Foreign Office cypher code 1917 is being employed. Cox*Telegram P. From Cox, Baghdad. To Trevor,Bushire. No• 581-£ Dated 15th received 16th April 1921. The English translation of the first telegram to King Hussein 1, Mecca or J eddah is as follows:- The Arabic Nation arose and your Majesty was the leader of it towards victory of the Arabs and success was your helper. But the regions of Iraq still renain in a state of uncertainty; accordingly we beg Your Majesty to despatch one of your honoured prog one y to rule overus that he iray help over us that he may help the country and release it from danger of quarrels and other discords. And the order is'with you. Signed for the 'Al Ahd' party by Jaafar Al Askari and Hamdi Pacha ji and Muhi ud Din. And for ^Harras' party by Ifuri Al Saeed and Bahjat Zainal ends. Cox.Tele gram P. From Cox, Baghdad• To Trevor,Bushire. Wo.582-3 Dated 15th receivod 16th April 1SJS1 Peraonal• The English translation o r the second telegram to King Hussein, liecca or Jeddah is as follows. Begins, ^ . , I t^g the despatch of one of your progeny that he may occupy throne of Iraq. Signed Naji A1 Suwaidi A1 Abbasi. Cox. Telegram P. From Cox,Baghdad. I'o Trevor, Bushire. Wo. S Dated 15th received 16th April 1921. Hussein begins. arsh al Irak. Arabic text of the second telegram fcyr King cv Astarham if ad ahad anjaQj^um li^ yetarreshah li Signed Naji Al Suwaidi al Abbasi.. 23/19 Telegram P. From Sidney, Bushire. 10 High Comnissioner,Baghdad. Ho. 622 • # Dated 17th April 1921, Clear Line, Your telegram dated th© 15th April No. 583 -S was badly mutilated. Please repeat with special reference to the following groups, 61-55, 57-63,121-129,161-166. Trevor is away on tour in Arabistan. Gidney.22/lS Telegram P. From Hi :h Commsssioi er, Baghdad. To Admiral,Bombay. Repeated Political,Besra for Navy, Bushire and Secretary of State for the Colonies,Londoru JhoSSS-S o* Zth, Dated 17th received IBth April 1921. C^lear Line^ Very-Urgent. Salyid Talib Pasha, a well known notable of Hesopotamia, having made a very menacing speech on a sBmi-pullic occasion, threatening to resort to force in cert in eventualities I have deemed it necessary in the interests of law and order and in consultation with the General Officer Commanding in Chief to deport him, and have recommended to the Secretary of State that he sould be sent to Ceylon. He left last night the 16th inst by river for Fao. Could His Majesty's ship at Muscat or H.M.S.Triad proceed to Fao at once to take him over and convey him to Bombay for transhipment to Ceylon. Perhaps the Lawrence could be spared if one of His majesty's ships cannot be despatched. Hicom.Telegram P. From If a vy, Bombay. To Admiralty/ Repeated Marine*,Simla and Political Resident,Bushire. Y?ds 48 Dated and received 18th April 19£1, Clear Line. A Clear Line telegram has been received from Baghdad reuueeting that a man of war may be sent immediately to Fao to deport Saiyid Talib to Ceylon, I have ire true ted H.M,S,Cyclamen to carry ou-t this duty. Navycom. Telegram P. From Political,Bushire, To Trevor, Ahwaz. No. 626 Dated 13th April 1921. Priority. H.M,Cyclamen has been detailed to convey Saiyid Talib to Bombay» * Political•- Telegram ?• From High Coramissioner,Baghdad. To Admiral,Bombay. Repeated S.N.O.,Persian Gulf, and R©sid nt. Ko. 593-S Dated and received 20th April 1321. Clear Line. A tolegra^ has been received from S.N.0,,Persian Gulf, that there is no accomodation on H.M.S.Cyclamen exept a space screened off on deck. Saiyid Talib t s status is that cf a political exile of high rank, and he requires first class accomodation. His movements and attempted communication should be kept under surveillance, but otherwise he should be made as com- ortable as possible and treated with every consideration. The accomodation on board R.I.M.S.Lawrence would of course be . ar ^.ore si liable,if she is available at once, but it is urgent , that he should not be delayed in the stream at Fao. I trust that if it is at all possible the Resident will spare the Lawrence immediately. Hicom. Telegram ¥ m clair. trom High Commissioner,Baghdad. To Resident,Bushir©. Ito. 1173 Dated and received 20th April 1921. Clear Line. Please repeat your reply to my telegram No. 593 to adress Expedite, Basra. Hicom23/19 Telegram En. cl• From S.N•O.Persian Gulf Buahire Radio. To Political, Bughire. No. 1917. Dated and received 20th April 1921. Urgent. Have asked Bushire Radio to repeat to Resident urgent cypher message from Baghdad which concerns him closely. Please inform me when this has 'been done and where Resident is at present. Telegram En. cl. From - Political, Bushire. To - S.N.O.Persian Gul? Bushire R^dio. No. 644. Dated 20th April 1921. Urgent. Your radio 1917. Resident expected Shushtar Arabistan some time 2lst. Hicom's telegram 598-S repeated to him clear the line and Hicom informed accordingly. S.N.O.P.G. Political•!3/l9 Telegram ?• From Gidney,Bushir©. To Trevor, Ah,waz. No. 641 Dated April 1921 Clear Line, Fdilowing is a repetition of telegram No.59D-S from High Commissioner,Baghdad to Admiral,Bombay, and repeated to S. j S.O . .Bushire for H.&amp;. fc. Cyclamen and Resident. Begins end &amp; • If you can spare Lawrence I haTe as&gt;ed Lincoln to ascertain whether Sheikh can lend you Ivy for return journey, and to let you know clear line. Please address your reply * to High Commissioner,Bagiidad, and repeat to Expedi te,Basra. Gidney Telegram P. From Sidney,Bushire To High Commissioner, Baghdad Mo. 645 Dated 21st April 1^21. Clear Line. Trevor is absent on tour in the Oilfields and els ar line I have repeated your telegram Wo. 539-8 to him/ « He is due at Shushtar sometime on the 21st. I have requested him to address his reply to you repeating to expedite Basra. Gidney.Telegram I , From Gidney,Bus ire. To Lincoln,Mohammerah, -No .642 Dated 21st April 1921, Clear Line. R. I .I.'. S. Lawrence is urgently and immediately « reauired by the High Commissioner,Baghdad. In case the Political Resident can spare the Lawrence will you ask the Resident Sheikh if he will kindly lend/his yacht the Ivy for the return journey to Bushire, and inform Resident clear line c/o Political, Ahwaz. I shall 'be glad if you will treat this- matter as very .urgent. G-idney.h Telegram P. From Lincoln, Mohammerah. T o aidjaey, Bushire. Ho. 105 Dated and received 21st April 1^21• Clear Line. Your te 1 egr sm Ho• 64-2 dateo t e 20 lii April l^ol. Sheikh is at present at Ahwaz, so I have wired Ahwaz to taVe neosssary action and telegraph result to you and Baghdad direct Lincoln. Telegram P. From Gidney,Bushire• To Political,Ahwaz. No. 645 Dated. 2l3t April 1921. Clear Line. Please inform Resident repeating here whether Sheikh can place Ivy at his disposal, but do not telegraph Baghdad. Gidney•Talegram P. From Trevor,Buohiro. To Higb Gommissionor,Baghdad. i Repeated Admiral, Bciatoay, Bushire and Mohammerah Dated and received 21st April 1921. Clear Line . Your telegram of the 21st April 5S3-S5 Lawrence has to proceed to Bombay as soon as possible aftor the end of the month for a two months refit, and it is particular ly important for me to visit Trucial Oman before she e;oes. i had therefore arranged a tour of Bahrain,Katar and Coast directly I have finished this trip. It is therefore excessively inconvenisnt for me to lend Lawrence now,but it can be done if Saiyid Talib cannot be conveyed to Bombay by any other means. Trevor. * Telegram p. From »&lt;allis # Ahwaz. To Resident,Shushtar. Repeated Bushire. ■«o. 262 Dated and received 2l3t April ld21. Clear Line. Bushire telegram Uo. 645. Sheikh is willing aii to lend Ivy for journey to Bushire. She is at present at Mohammerah. I.T.'.T., Basra shoujjjl) be instructed-to send Captain and Engineer to ta]-:e Ivy to Basra to oil and collect crew and prepare generally for the voyage. .13/19 Telegram Bn. CI• (Clear Line) Pron - High commissioner, Baghdad. To - Trevor, Ahwaz. Repeated to Bushire, Mohammerah and Admiral Bombay. No. 1197. Dated and received 21gt April 1921. Very many thanks your telegram re 'Lawrence 1 *. Matter is absolutely urgent and I can soo no other solution and beg that 'Lawrence' may be spared and 'Cyclamen' c~n I hope take you to Bahrain and Muscat but I greatly regret having to ask you to inconvenience yourself so much. Hicom. Telegram En. cl. (Clear line) Prom - Trevor, Shushtar. To - High Commissioner, Baghdad. Repeated Admiral Bombay, Political, Bushire. Wds. 48. Dated and received 22nd April 1921. Clear Lineo Your 1197 in view of urgency of case 'Lawrence' will be spared. Kindly wire Director R.I.M. date of starting so that he will know when ship will be available at Bombay for refit. Trevor.23/10 Twlegram ?• From Admiral, Bombay• To High Gommissloner,Baghdad. Repeated Resident and H.LI. S, Cyclamen. hds.36 Dated and received 21st' April 1^21. Clear Line. Reference your telegram No. 59B-S. The only ship available afi far as the Navy is concerned is H.M.S.Cyclamen. Request that I tody be informed as soon as possible whether Saiyid Talib will be conveyed to Bombay by R.I.M.S.Lawrence. Navy com.*3* 23/19 Telegram P. From Cox,Baghdad. To Trevor,Bushire. No. 645-S Dated 29th and received 30th April 1921 to 584-8. Personal. Please refer to my telegrams Nos.590-3 7.hen were they sent from -Bushire? Cox Telegram P. From Trevor,Bushira. To Cox,Baghdad. Ho. 696 Dated 30th April 1921. Priority. iersonalo On April l?th a clear line telegram was sent to you asking for repetition of your telegram No. 583-3 w.ixoli ..an received 'badly mutilated. As no reply wis forthcoming it was .assumed that the telegrams had been sent by some ot;ier route(e .g. Aden) j consequently telegrams have not been transmitted from here. If despatch is now reouired kindly repeat 583-S, but I ould ooscrve tiiat as neErly all telegrams through Basra are received badly mutilated, and there is no good Arabic scholar -:ere it is most difficult to get message correct^ there is also coi ic. I q erable c.iance of leakage here. In the circumstances it ii,M, Le better to derpatch messages via Aden or elsewhere if iere is no objection on other grounds. Trevor. fi 1—-ft SS/19 Telegram R. from High Commissioner, Baghdad To Trevor,Bushire. % No, 657-S Dated 2nd received 3rd May 1921, /j OJ ^ Your telegram 622. Clear Line not received here please malre full enquiriep and inform me of result. Telegrams have now been despatched by another rout e. Cox. Telegram R # l?rom Poli tical, Eushire • To High Commissioner,Baghdad No. 7S2 Dated 5th iay 1921, Your telegram No, 657-3 of the 2nd May, AssisLant Superintendent,Bushire reports that our Clear Lin© legram No, 622 was despatched from here on April 17th and Baera intimates that they received it the same day.and transmitted it rirect to Baghdad who state they never received it. Political.Priority . T SLTORyw (Code) NO.271 Dated 25-4-21 From Trevor, Ahwaz Tc Ad raira1,Bomb ay, .uly telegram cf 23rd, How hear that O.C. H.LI.S. Cyol-ua*,! has auggeatod that he sheuld take n(» and party tc flushlrs stop I had not. soagested this as I thought it was not permissible. If however you !jan icindly allow this it would be great convenience to me as ivy liapossible having no Captain cr &lt;3rew and mail steamers very orc^l/ded. *****23/19 Telegram R. From Polltical # Kuwait« To R0sident,BuBhire # N0 .131/C Dated 24th reoalved 25th August 1U21, Your telegram No.1423. High Commissioner telegram No.553 of August 20th begins. Your telegram 124/0. Following is text of my telegram July Slst in reply to your telegram No.117. Begins. I told Sheikh (there is no?) objection to Said Isa's release but I understood he was returning to Mohammerah. I should prefer that t he did not (go to?) Najf at present and if you find it difficult to delay his departure for a month say he can proceed to (Arabistan? but must remain there for a short period before coming to Iraq. Above subject to Resident's concurrence. Addressed Kuwait repeated Bushire. 377 Ends. Wire If not received. Ends. I also had not received. Political. Telegram R. From PoliU cal,Kuwait. To High Commissioner,Baghdad. Repeated Resident,Bushire. N0 .132/C Dated 24th received 25th August 1021. Your telegram No. 877 dated the 21st July. As month which you mention has elapsed do you still object to Said Isa going to Mesopotami.? Political.7. I.** 1 — ,l -'' ' I PK-RT Si hS'2 Office of H. £. The High Commksioner for * Iraq, 'QnahJaJ 19t h January 1922 t 1 direction of His Excellency the High Commissioner for ' Iraq, copy of correspondence as marked awarded with compliments to ;— The Hon*tie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire (1 copy). IHitt Rl-Siono I . -V -J - - - ' ji Httmii'- ' ir « S ecretary to H (?. The High Commissioner for ' Iraq. i Despatch No. C.0/120 dated 9th Deceirber 1921 from the High Cominissioner,Baghdad to the Secretary ^f State for the Colonies,London. /m.. \S lNo. C.O./120. T he R esidkxcy, Bayhdad, the 9tli December, 1021. S ir, With reference to tlie correspoiidence concluding with your telegram No. 205, dated 28th June, 1921, 1 have the honour to submit for your con sideration the following observations and proposals in connection with the rectification of the northern frontier of 'Iraq. In this connection also plea.se see my telegram No. 755 dated 3rd December, 1921. It may be assumed that when the Treaty of Sevres was drawn up the question of the Northern frontier of 'Iraq was considered to be one of academic rather than of practical importance, in view of the provisions made in Section III (Articles 62-64) for the future autonomy of Kurdistan, and for the protection of Assyro-Chaldeans and other racial and religious com munities. During Hie time that has elapsed since the drawing up of the Treaty, circumstances have considerably changed and, while the question of providing safeguard-, for the Christian communities on the frontier lias become increasingly pressing, the fulfilment of the measures proposed in Section III has become highly problematical. In the event therefore of the non-materialization of these measures, the frontier as determined by the Treaty ceases to be an academic question and becomes a practical issue, and I consider it of the greatest importance that the defects inherent in the Treaty frontier from the point of view of the 'Iraq Government should be fully appreciated. It is from tin's point of view that the question is approached in t!iis despatch and that the proposals contained in it for the rectification of the Treaty frontier have been framed. I.—POLITICAL OBJECTIONS TO THE TREATY FRONTIERS • /!)• 1 would first draw your attention to my telegram No. 40 dated 19th April, 1921, wherein are summarised the reasons for the rectification of the frontier, as delimitated by the Treaty of Sevres, in such a way as to include the district ot Amadiyah and the Nestorian countrv within the confines of Iraq. Ihese reasons not only are still valid, but have increased in import- ance owmg to the continued maintenance of administrative control over the districts m question by the 'Iraq Government, which has encouraged arge numbers of Christian Assyrians to return to their homes in this neighbourhood. (2) Moreover, further detailed examination of the whole question and consultation with local experts has only served to strengthen mv conviction that some such rectification of the Treaty frontier is essential to the future peace and security of the Mosul division. The Treaty frontier cuts across inogiaphical and geographical boundaries; it severs from Mosul Lai^e numiers of Muslim Kurds who are economicallv dependent for that town- 'TT , ' 1 : '' lhe -Wrim, C^iristians who nave tiie strongest moral claims to our continued protection. II.—MILITARY CONSIDERATIONS. AmJuvah dtfr.vl 'i-Ttl ' t m ! litar T K™vmds, the retention of the hio-li ovnnn l within iho Traqian boundary- is most desirable Tlte in —EXPLFSION OF AMADIYAH I?f THE TREATY. excluded from 'WiTJXlwtl 1 omv^ madiV 'l' , was doubt tlmt tliey sufficient it +1, +* f + a - 0 V. T l&gt; lc i wn llie an ^ I not this connection, however I venturp tn • 1Ustlf ^ illp . po uj-se adopted. In , iowe^er, i venture to invite your attention to Foreign Officeletter to the Colonial Otlice No. S. 5070/43/93 dated lOth May 1921. in which it is statefl that the terms of the Treaty ot Sevres regarding the northern boundary of 'Iraq 'were drawn after full consultation with the British authorities in Mesopotamia.' The views of the Acting Civil Commissioner for Mesopotamia on this subject are contained in his telegram Xo. 10852 dated 8th December 1918, to the Secretary of State for India in reply to a telegram asking him to telegraph in words suitable for insertion in the draft Treaty a definition of the frontiers of 'Iraq. The relevant paragraph in the Civil Commissioner's telegram is as follows: — 'Amadiyah is a big Kurdish centre which it is essential to control if wa. are to repatriate Assyrians, Armenians, etc. now on our hands. It cannot be controlled from the north as roads are blocked in winter by snow and in spring by the flooded state of the valleys. Proposed frontier brings Amadiyah into 'Iraq: also the Hakki (HarkiP) tribe whom 1 imagine no one else w 7 ants.' (2). I would also refer to Map No. 2 attached to the text of the Treaty of Sevres. It will be seen that the former northern boundary of the Mosul Wilayat is marked by a chain-dotted line and that this chain-dotted line has been mainly adopted as the basis of the Treaty boundary, it being stated iu Part II, Article 27, Section II, Clause (3) of the Treaty that the frontier shall follow 'the northern boundary of the Mosul Wilayat.' The text continues 'modified however, so as to pass south of Amadiyah.' It will be observed that the chain-dotted line on the map attached to the Treaty does in fact pass south of Amadiyah and, if this line was accepted as correctly defining the Wilayat boundary, the modification quoted above, as it appears in the text, seems meaningless. In view of the many considerations already cited which emphasize the importance of retaining Amadiyah within the 'Iraq boundary and of the circumstances noticed above, I feel bound to draw your attention to the possibility of an error having arisen in the text of the Treaty and to suggest that the clause in question should have read;—'The northern boundary of the Wilayat of Mosul, modified, however, so as to pass north of Amadiyah.' * x (3). A further complication arises from the fact that the chain-dotted line, purporting to define the boundary of the Mosul Wilayat in the map attached to the text of* the Treaty, is incorrect. The origin of the error appears to date back to a period some twenty years ago when Amadiyah was temporarily excluded from the Mosul Wilayat; after a two years' trial the an-angement was found to be unworkable and was accordingly cancelled by the Turkish Government. Whether or no an error is contained in the text of the Treaty, it would appear highly probable that the incorrect cbr&gt;in- dotted line has influenced the actual delineation of the frontier. The boundary of the- Mosul Division as now administered is shown by a irr^ew line in the mao enclosed with this despatch (Appendix IV). The boundarv represents, as nearly as it is possible to ascertain, the original boundary of the Mosul Wilayat wiith one exception, namely that Faishkhabur and a small corner between the Khabur and the Tigris originally belonged to Jazirah. The return of Faishkhabur, where 900 Christians were massacred during the war, is unthinkable. It will be seen that the correct Wilayat boundary line differs considerably from the chain-dotted line and from the red line marking the Treaty frontier. It would therefore appear that the frontier as defined on the map attached to the Treaty does not in fact correspond with the frontier as defined in the text of the Treaty, and may therefore under Article 20 be ignored. (4). It would accordingly seem advisable, if and when negotiations are re-opened with the Ottoman Government, to reconsider the boundarv ques tion as a whole with a view to remodellins* tl&lt;e frontier as defined on the Treaty map (hereinafter referred to as the Treaty Frontier) in the light of the facts of the local situation and with special reference to the Assyrian ques tion. IV.—PRESENTATION OF THE CASE TO THE OTTOMAN GOVERNMENT. Before proceeding to give my proposals in detai'l. I Venture to sum marise the considerations that mi&gt;ht be urged by His Mjai'estv's Government in the event of negotiations on this subject being opened with the Ottoman Government vix : — 1 • The Treaty Frontier, cutting as it does across geocraphical and tribal divisions, must make foi continual friction and unrest among the frontier tribes. Such friction and unrest is likelv to be increased by the presence within and adjacent to the Turkish frontier of a large and necessarily dis affected Christian population and would prove a constant source of embarrassment k) the Ottoman Government.3 3 The Amadivah District, being difficult and, at certain seasons, almost impossible of access from the north, cannot be effect.vcly controlled from that side. 4 In the event of hostilities breakins: out as a result of tribal disturbances, Amadivah could be virtually isolated by forces operating from Dohuk and Aqra and, with the additional possibility of an Assyrian rising, the furkish position in that district would speedily be rendered untenable. 5 Our only motive in proposing a rectification of the Treaty Frontier is our desire to establish a strong and settled frontier based on natural features and on the existing facts of the local situation, which shall give promise of per manence; to the mutual advantage alike of the Ottoman and 'Iraq Govern ments. 6. As an earnest of our sincerity, we are prepared, if the above consider ations demand it, to surrender territory allotted to 'Iraq by the i reaty o CI V.—PROPOSALS FOR RECTIFICATION OF FRONTIER. (1) I am alive to the fact that the nature of our proposals must depend largely on the ciroumstances in which negotiations with the Ottoman Govern ment are conducted and that, in order to secure the inclusion of the Amadiyah and Assyrian tribal districts within the 'Iraq boundary, it may be necessary tc surrender territory in exchange. I have therefore endeavoured to provide for all eventualities by submitting four proposals of which, it is hoped, one will prove appropriate. These proposals are given in the order of their desirability; the first representing what would be from our point of view the best possible frontier, and the fourth representing the furthest concessions which I am pre pared to recommend in order to secure the inclusion in ' Iraq of the Amadiyah district. The frontier lines represented by each of the four pro posals are indicated on the map enclosed with this despatch. I would emphasise he fact that owing to the fluid character of tribal boundaries and to the unreliability of the maps available, it is impossible at this stage to lay down a detailed frontier. The frontier lines therefore, as described in this despatch and as marked on the accompanying map, should be taken only as the most general indications of the boundary subsequently to be defined in detail by a Boundary Commission (as provided for in Article 29 of the Treaty). (2) The frontier lines proposed in each case may be defined roughly as follows:— First Proposal. —The boundary as now administered with the addition of an area bounded approximately on the North by lat. shewn on map thus - - _ 37° 30' and on the east and west by long. 44° and * 43°, respectively. [Detailed descriptions of:— (i) the boundary as now administered and (ii) the boundary of the area which it is pro posed to include, will be found in Appendices I and II enclosed with this des patch.] Second Proposal. —The boundary as now administered, with the addition of the area described above under first proposal, from shewn on map thus + + + the Tigris to long. 44° 5' thence a line running in a S.E. direction, crossing the Sukuchuk Su N. of Kolitha and continuing: S.E. to the western end of the watershed S. of Rudbar-i Barasgir; thence along the watershed eastwards to the Persian Frontier. Third Proposal. —The boundary as described above under second proposal except between longs. 43° 40' and 44° w r here the bound- shewn on map thus .... ary line would follow the summits-of the Gurajar Dagh and Shirindari Dagh. Fourth Proposal. —The boundary as at present administered. This pro posal may also be extended, if necessary, to include— shewn on map by green line — [i) The surrender of the area which it is proposed to surrender under the second proposal. {ii) The surrender of the area which it is proposed to surrender under the third proposal. VI.—COMMENTS ON PROPOSALS. First Proposal. —Taking as a basis the boundary as defined on the map attached to the Treaty, this proposal involves the following alterations:— (1) The surrender of a fertile strip of territory, bounded by rivers Tigris, Khabur and Hazil and by the Treaty boundary on the west, south, east and north, respectively; and the inclusion of an area between the rivers Hazil and Khabur and to the north of the Treaty boundary {see map).Note;— (a) These two minor adjustments are rendered necessary by the fact that the Treaty Frontier does not accord with tribal divisions. In the first instance it includes within 'Iraq a portion of the Slopi tribe which is dependent on Jazirah and in the second it excludes from 'Iraq sections of the Sindi and Guli tribes who are dependent on Mosul. The retention—more correctly the adoption as an administrative boundary—of the Treaty Frontier would thus tend to produce local disorders and general unrest. (b) I am aware that the river boundary, which the first of these modi fications would involve, is open to criticism from a purely military point of view, but I venture to think that in this instance the political considerations are sufficiently strong to overrule the military objections. (c) The surrender of the strip of arable land north of the Khabur would be an indication of our sincerity as suggested above in Section IV, para. 6. The area to be included on the other hand is mountainous and rugged and of little economic value. (2) The inclusion of a considerable area representing the Amadiyah dis trict and the Nestorian tribal country generally. Note:— (a) The pre-war boundary of the Mosul Wilayat at this point was was not satisfactory in that it separated from Amadiyah the summer pastures of a number of Assyrian and Kurdish tribes who were, and aro, economically dependent on that town and on Mosul. This fact, which was unimportant when the boundary was merely one between two provinces, may be the cause of serious difficulties if the same boundary is adopted between Turkey and 'Iraq. (6) The inclusion of the Assyrian country in 'Iraq would facilitate the repatriation of those now prevented from returning by their fear of the ven geance of the Ottoman Government, from which we are under moral obligations to protect them. (c) The Assyrians, whose homes were thus included in 'Iraq, would become 'Iraq subjects and therefore eligible for enrolment in the 'Iraq Levies, from which they are at present debarred by Article 207 of the Treaty of Sevres. In view of the fighting qualities of the Assyrians, this consideration is one of no little importance and ensures an adequate means of defence for the frontier proposed. (d) If these tribes are not included in 'Iraq, they will feel that they have nothing further to expect from either the 'Iraq or the British Governments; their predatory instincts will consequently be indulged to the full at the expense ot Iraqis, Hiitish, Kurds and 1 urks impartially. Furthermore it is not im probable that the Assyrians, finding that they can no longer look to the British for munitions and support, will turn again to their old friends the Russians thereby offering a fresh field for Bolshevik propaganda and enterprise. (e) The area which it is proposed to include comprises those tribes of the sedentary Kurds and Christians who are economically dependent on Amadiyah, and the country of the main fighting Assyrian tribes. It is curious that the boundary proposed, though traced without back-reference, is practically identical with the boundary of the Assyrian enclave proposed in August, 1919 and shown on the map forwarded to the Secretary of State for India with the Civil Commissioner's despatch No. 23268/119/48, dated 4tli August, 1919. Srro?u/ Proposal. In addition to the alterations contained in the first pro- posai, the second proposal involves the surrender.of a wedge-shaped area east '• ^ 111 111 len ^ th V 15 miles in depth at its broadest point on the Persian frontier. Note It is hoped that, should the trend of negotiations with t^e Ottoman Government make it necessary for us to offer a quid pro quo in exchange for Amadiyah and the Assyrian country, the surrender of this area in addition to that given m Section \ I para. (1) will be sufficient to meet the case. Third Proposal. -This proposal involves an addition to the area to be sur- rem crcd under . econd / roposat of the Nerva Raikan country, which is enclosed Append 'r I llT tier by a prono,mced saliellt - dn this connection see Xote :—It is not without some misgiving that I contemplate the possibilitv the surrender of the Ncrva Raikan country. It is an area which is depend ent upon Amad.yah and it is also the home of several Assyrian communis who are now returning. Moreover its surrender wo.ld make an awkward salient of he Assyrian country which it is proposed to include in 'Iraq Nevertheless before falling back on the fourth proposal, I am prepared to recommend Z surrender of this area if the inclusion of Amadiyah and the Assyrian connfrv can only thus be ensured. a i counrry Fourth Proposal—This proposal abandons the claim to the Assvri-in tHh-.l country (described in Appendix II) which lies outside the bonndary ™ at prlV sent administered and adopts the latter boundary as the frontier. It may also be taken, if necessary, to include the surrender of the areas which it is proposed to surrender under the second and third proposals. N 0TE . ( a ) i n v iew of the strong: reasons for the inclusion in 'Iraq of the Assyrian country, which have been enumerated above, it is with great reluctance that I include this final proposal. If, however, it proves absolutely impossible to obtain the inclusion of both the Amadiyah district and the Assyrian country, I consider that we should make every effort to retain the former, even if it should involve the abandonment of our claim to the latter. (&amp;) With regard to the suggested extension of this proposal so as to in clude, if necessary, the concessions contained in the second and third proposals; it is possible that the position may be such that the addition of one or both of these concessions would turn the scale and procure the acceptance of the proposal. In this connection 1 would refer to the notes given above on the second and third proposals. (c) Finally I would emphasise the necessity of regarding this proposal as a last resort and one only to be adopted if and when every avenue has been already explored whereby it may be possible to achieve the rectification of the frontier in the way which I believe to be most advantageous both to ourselves and to the Ottoman Government. This despatch has been seen and approved by the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, (Sd.) P. Z. COX, High Commissioner for 'Iraq. The Right Honourable WINSTON E. CHURCHILL, P.C., M.P., Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, London.APPhNDIX J. »*4 j; NORTHERN BOUNDARY OF MOSUL DIVISION AS NOW ADMINISTERED. 1. From the junction of the rivers Tigris and Khabur along the Ivhabur eastwards to its junction with the Hazil Su, northwards along the Hazil Su to a point due West of Mahri Nar Dagh, excluding the Slopi tribe, due east along tribal boundary between Goyan to the north and Sindi and Guli to the South, excluding Nerva and turning N.E, to include Belo and Margi, to the Khabur river S. of Hadrish, south along the Khabur to Rusi, turning east along the tributary of the Khabur to Alamun, north east between Alanuin and Bide, S.E. along ridge between Maidani and Dashtani to the Zab river below Zeri, south along Zab river to point marked Fort, along ridge eastwards, north of Baikar, north east along western ridge of Nerve Raikan to Ghara Dagli, along eastern ridge S.E* Then S. including Nerva, Raikan and the Muzuri Bala, crossing Shamsidinan Su W. of junction of the Shamsidinan Su and Rudbar-i-Shin, S.E., skirting the summit of Shirin- dari Dagh, E. along watershed on lat. 37 to the point of intersection of the Rukuchuk Su with long. 44° 15'. 2. At this point the Mosul Divisional boundary ends, the remainder of the frontier representing the northern boundary of the Kirkuk Division. The latter boundary which runs through mountainous and little populated country, has never been clearly defined. I*t will therefore be convenient to adopt from here to the Persian frontier the boundary as delineated on the map attached to the Treaty. This line follows, approximately, the water shed S. of the Rudbar-i-Haji Beg. *Owing to inaccuracies in the map, it is impossible to define correctly the administrative boundary at this point and, for the sake of convenience, the Treaty frontier has here been followed. See Appendix III. h APPENDIX II COUNTRY OF THE TRIBAL ASSYRIANS. 1. The area which it is recommended to include is the country formerly occupied by the tribal Assyrian Christians, the Tiari, the Tkhuma, the Jilu and Baz. 2. South of latitude 37° 30' thfe Great Zab enters a deep gorge. On both banks of the river are several short deep valleys at right angles to the main stream forming the district of Upper Tiari with a large number of Assyrian villages. South of this on the Kight Bank is the large and fertile valley of Lower Tiari with its centre at Ashitha, the whole valley being previously Assyrian and the habitat of the most powerful section of their community. To the \V est of the liari district are the '' Yailacjs or summer pastures of the Tiari Assyrians. 4. Opposite Lower Tiari on the Left Bank of the Zab is a long valley called Salabeqan occupied formerly by Assyrians and the seat of a Malik or chief. This valley leads to the district of Tkhuma. another Christian tribe, to the nortli of which stands the Walto Dagh the summer pasture of the Tkhuma. 5. Just South of the Jilu Dagh is the Christian district of Greater Jilu, a series of fertile and picturesque valleys whicli drain into the Rudbar-i-Shin, a large mountain torrent which forces its way through limestone ridges to join the Zab below Amadiyah. 6. Below Jilu is the District of Baz, with a group of Christian villages surrounded by orchards and terraced fields. 7. West of Ba^ is the little valley of Tovi with a Kurdish village of that name. Beyond rises the Ghara Dagh with precipitous sides but open summit used as summer pasturage by the people of Baz.APPENDIX III. NERVA RAIKAN DISTRICT. 1. In the map (Appendix IV) the Nerva Raikan District is inaccurately sliown, and as a result the administrative boundary, as defined in Appendix 1 and as marked on the map, can only be taken as approximate at this point. For the sake of convenience the administrative boundary is shown as coinciding: with the Treaty boundary in the Nerva Raikan neighbourhood. The rough sketch map attached, however, shows more accurately the actual position of the administrative frontier. 2. This point, though of minor importance, serves to illustrate the impos sibility of giving at this stage anything more than a general indication of the different boundaries, as is stated in Section V para. 1 of the despatch.Telegram Code» From - High CoimnisBioner, Baghdad, To • - Resident, Buehire. No. 716. Dated 26th received 27th June 1922. 1% Please inform me whether huts at Eenjam erected for Iraq deportees are still standing# If not about how long will it take to erect accoramod tion for fed bout dozen. Highcoma # Telegram Code# Prom - Resident, Bushire# To - Political Bandar Abbas. Ho. 1146. Dated 27th June 1922. Following telegram received from Baghdad. Begins. Please infom. •..•.•♦••...•.•••.••about. Ends . Please report. Resident./) Telegram P. From High Commissioner, Baghdad To Resident,Bushire. No•309-S. Dated and receiTed 2^th June 19^2. You need not be alarmed^ by my telegram Ifo«716 as the in-rormation asked for is ^or propaganda purposes. At the same time I should be glad of this information by telegram either er/clair or in code® Hishcoma The Residenoyt No. ^7^ -s« Bushire # 27th Juno 1922• Tho fcrcgoing copy of telegrajn is forwarded, with compllmento, to the Assistant Resident and His Majesty' Consul, Bandar Abbas, for information, with reference to this office telegram No* 1146 dated the 27th June 1922• By ordor # Captain, Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf®!3 /l9 Telegram Code. pron - Politioal, Bandar Abbas. To - Resident, Bushire. No• 05• Dated and received SOth June 1922. Your telegram dated 27th June 1146 Huts are still standing. Politioal. Telegram En olair. prom - Resident, Bushire. To - High Commissioner, Baghdad. No • 1166. Dated 1st July 1922. Your telegram 716 June 26th. Huts are still standing in deportee camp at Henjam so ample accommodation available for about dozen and more if necessary. Resident.23/19. Telegram P. From Hi':h Commissioner, Baghdad. To Foreign,Simla• Repeated Bushire. NO.609-S. Dated 4th reoelved 5th September 1? Reference my telegram Wo.605-3• With your a-proval I am anxious to deepateh to Henjam agitators who have been arrested and others aha*® who may be arrested shortly. They will not exoeed 12 in number and I understand accomodation still exists for them and the British Officer in eharge of the guard. Request that Amy Headquarters may be moved to instruct the Officer Commanding, Troops in Persian Gulf to arrange for the necessary guard in conbultat- Ion with the Resident at Bushire. I am addressing Col.Trevor direct in regard to other details. High Commissioner23/19. Telegrain P. From High ConmlsBioner, Baghdad. To Resident, Bushire. So.610-S. Dated 4th received 6th September 19k From your telegram 1166 I understand that accomodation is available for at least 1&lt;2 depo JG • I am ansioua to send 5 at once and probably a few more later. Can you malre same arrangements for furniture and supplies as in 1920. Deportees are socially of .^ood standing, and should be treated accordingly. As soon as permission is received from India will you please inform me by what date you will be ready to reoeive the deportees# % Hi^hcoma. Telegram P. From Resident, Bushire. To High Commissioner,Baghdad. 30.1474. Dated 5th September 1922. Priority . Reference your telegram dated the 4th Sept. ito.609-S. I think that the Persian Government may event- if deportees are despatched to Henjanv ually have something to say in the matter/now that they are taking an active interest in these parts and Karguzar has recently visited Henjam and impressed on Arab Sheilrh Persian sovereignty over the Island. Do you think Minister had better be consulted in regard to this. Trevor.23/19. Telegram R, From Resident, B^shire. To Consul,Bandar i^bbas. No•1471. Dated 5th September 1922• High Commiasioner is wiring about sending •5 depo tees to Hanjam at once and possibly more later. He asks how long; it would take to get furniture etc. as before and make tandobast to receive them. Please let me 'now about this. I have meanwhile pointed out that I think Persian Government aay eventually wish to say something on •matter and s ggested ho should ask Legation. Trevor.23/19. Telegram R. From • Consul,Bandar Abbas. To Resident,Bushire. Ko.l7a/C Dated Sth received 9th September 19 Your telegram Ho.1472. I am awaiting report of Telegraph Superintendent,Henjam and of Officer Commanding, SjfcE4iLX&gt;3tB Bandar Ibbaa who returns from Hen jam tonight. Only- matter lively to cause delay is feeding arrangements as party small for contract purposes and former contractor exorbitant, I do not lenow whether military supply or naval contractor could he}:jb this time. | Present guard HenJam, Indian Officer 19 men Punjabi Mussulmans would probab?Ly need slight increase. Customs periodical' 1 y resuscitate ouesticn o^* Hew Customs house at Henjam. Fagan.23/19. T el egram P • From High Commissionbr, Baghdad. To Residert, BusMre, No.e^-S. Datud 9th received 10th September 19r2. Reference your telegrar No.1474. Matter Is urgent and I would prefer to act first and meet any difficulties if raised later# We have previous precedent in case question shoulo arise. Highcorna. Telegram P. from Resident, Bushire. To H i gh Conni s si on c-r, ^aghda '. No.1508. Dated 11th September 1922. I telegraphed to Consul,Bandar ^bbas immediately after I received your telegram Ifo.SlO-S. He replies that there is no difficulty attac -ed to receiving deportees except that of food; former contractor has demand ed exorbitant rate as he states 5 is foo few for profit. However I do not see why 5 Mhould not be fed locally in sa^e way as Telegraphs and others feed. Present guard of 1 .0. and 19 I.O.Rs will have to be increased by 1 B.C. and perhaps 10 I.0.£ ls. Trevor#Telegram Code# prom - Cox, Baghdad# To - Resident, Bushlre, No. 55. Dated 19th received 20th January 1925. I am leaving for London 19th for conference regarding Middle East Affairs. Expect to be absent for 5 weeks Dobbs functioning during my absence. Cox&lt; Ji cohglsettia: . s. c&gt;- JOjp'b seceetabiat op h.3. the hioh cokmissioner k)r ' iraq, A , •— Sir, dat^d. stl 1 . juiie, 1923. 1.L' 1|wv I \ ■ i l.tjixv ' - dbmia. htwc^ci I ein. dir^ctftd to inform you that the Anglo- Persian Oil Company are anxious to have the opportunity of pressing the correspondence marginally cited with a view Despatches .Nos. 31 and 32 dated l-5-1014( to fixing the from the British Comiriissioner, Turco- j Persian .Frontier Commission, to the 1 quantity of oil Secretary of State, Foreign Office, and { Telegram No. 13 dated 12-7-1914, from the which the British Commissioner to the foreign I Office. I inhabitants of the Transferred Territories and the adjoining districts have 'been accustomed to take free of charge in connection with the draft agreement of the oil concession now under negotiation with the 'Iraq (iovernment. 2. The documents noted are filed in files JJos. 15/29 and 15/30 in the Turco-Persian Frontier Commission series of files at Bushire, and His Excellency the High Commissioner would he obliged if you would 'be good enough to furnish him with copies of these reapers, should the Political Resident see no objection for the information of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. - ~ v' 9 ' The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident i have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, actiitg secretary to h.e. the high cott'13si0i t ^ k)r f iraq,. 7 at Bushire. vo 2?-^ I, ■ ■23/19 . Telegram R. prom Gastrell , Ahwaz . To Resident , Bushire, No . 172 • Dated 6th received 7th July lj23- Shaikh's Basra Agent reports that he has reliable information that three hundred and fifty [Jlemas from Najaf , Kasmain and Kerbala have been allowed to leave Iraq , It is expected they will enter Persia via Kermanshah and the major ity via Mohammerah. This is protest against the deportation of Shaikh Med hie by Iraq . Can you obtain confirmatidm from High Commissioner ? Submit sudden influx of large number of religious malcontents . would seriously affect British interests in Arabistan, Diz- ful and Shushter would would receive them with open arms and trouble would surely ensue . G-astrell, Telegram R. prom Resident , Bushire , To High Commissioner, Bagahdad ,, No . 693 • Repeated Minister, Tehran^ No. 139• Dated .7th July 19-3 • Following from G-astrell, Ahwaz , uegins (text of telegram 1/2 above) ends , I have no further news since Tehran tele;ram No. 73 dated 14th April which protested ^strongly against de portation of Mu J tabids to Persia but concur in aastrell's estimate of effect on British interests in Arabistan of guch influx of religious mQ-lcontents . 6r KnoxTelegram R, From Resident, Buflhire, To G-astrell , Aliwaz . No . 694. Dated 7th July 1923 . I have repeated your 172 of 6th July to Baghlad and Tehran with following comment ' I have - . - (down to end of telegram 139/693 ante) . Knox23/19- / Telegram R, Prom Minister, Tehran . To Resident , Bushire Circular No . 4 , Dated Rth received 9th July 19^3 Iraq G-overnment have deported prominent Persian divine , Mahdi El Khalisi t towards Hedjaz for issuing decrees against Iraq elections . Nine of' major and twenty-six of minor Ulemas and priests have voluntarily left Iraq shrines as a protest, bei^g provided with a special train as far as the frontier in order to prevent demonstrations . They are n ow proceeding towards Kermanshah on the way to Tehran . Above information will enable you to correct erroneous reports which will doubtless he circulated. I leave it to .your discretion what method to use , with warning , however t against being drawn into any public controversy . Loraine. Telegram R . Prom Qastrell, Ahwaz . To ' Resident, Bushire, No. l/^-• Repeated Minister, Tehran, No. 6l. Dated and received 9th July 1923• Qlemas : Basra A^ent reports that eight import ant with same number of lesser left Iraq via Kermanshah route . • | Gastrell.■t/\9 r. Tel e* rars FroM r is;h Commissioner, Ba^Ma:'. » . To Resident, Busliir®, 1 ^0.275 -3. Dated th reeeired 10th July 19^', Knalis v?as deported by le \1 order of the Iraq (rCTern^ent anc started on pil^rina^e to eeca. Peason for deportation was his violent opposition to the Iraa Gort., Kthieh finally inyolyed hi?* and his adherents in conflict -vitii t i police. s a protest against the deportation, nine other Persi an 'ajtaii a* started to leare for Persia, i t and their journey iras faciLated by the Iraq GrOTt. They crossed th© KermnsL ti frontier on July 2nd. &lt;o Uleia, so far as knovsn, is leaving yia oh-a t era i. In reply to teleirarr (4 g;ruops iUtilated) s inister asking ;e to assist in arranjinj a cq -- roi^ise if possible, I sent the following t elc rarr : 'Your telej;ra-: s .Ho ,97 an 100 ate July rt „ .The Iraq Groft . has no objection to Khali si :i. t ) rersi . .Ie .. sent in t ie f iru^tio:- of .:e jaz inste of Persia in order to 1 eet your wis les, as expressed in preyious corr s spondence. tiis slip will reac i . c en about July 11th, an I I a- telegraphing to Resident, :: ; en to detain hi* there until further notice, or if Khali.-i cefinitely e«ideb to ^o to Persia instead of to Hedjaz, to arrange lis departure for Bushire, Secondly re?;ar in*; the su^^estion that ne.*;oti it ions should be entered into to per it of Khalisi's return to Iraq, I fear that the Iraq aort. consider that out of the question, so far as tney ca i at present foresee. in-; Feisal himself went to the ertrese linit of jj[ complaisance arc even of humiliation in previous negatiations Tit i Kha isi, to induce hi ' to withiraw fro v - agitation aranat the Iraq Govt., and the latter only iove:' v« :en force 'oo do ao by ^jalisi ! 3 illegal opposition to the ele-. tind the turbulent conduct of his adherents, it watl notorious that the ne^t step confceraplatec by KhaligJ the issue- of a decree proclaiming the deposition 01 •• Kinr. anxious thou*: 1 the Iraq viOTt ..are to rreet the] oi' the Persian G-o y t. an yourself, they cannot bt ^ to expose bheraselyes and their whole future to a rij ci'-tr ■ er. Tiircly as to other Persian Ule^aa . T iese publicly cast in tneir lot with KhalAsi, and their J ■rtoull in the opinion of tne Iraq 'rovt. .nd of Myselfj equally an*;eroua. I wish it emphasised that th« 1 ^cal prestij -vi Fcisal and of ais G-oirt, has beer immensely increi eyen n.ions, is by their firr: ac tion when confronts tne violent and seditious attitude of these foreigner an if they were to retrench now they would lose htay - eputr.-vtio:&gt;. iney naye acte^.j entirely on their o »Tn initiative, although I as bound to say that they h Tc y co : p 1 e t e sy ■ pa thy in a difficult situation, Thei onia.. tribes ana chiefs hare accepted the situation qii and show erery disposition to follow the policy of tfc Iraq (lovt.' 'li hco fa. wammele was ^lisi a of • the d e tjpi Tits; diesq; :ir r-:i r s elf 23/19. Telegram Prom To R. Minister, Tehran. Resident, Bus hire. Circular No . 6 . Dated 20th received 21st July 1923- With the approval ot His Majesty's Government I am proceeding July 2l6t to Baghdad to seek Xisr solution of CTlema question compatible with the interests of* Persia and Irai in conference with High Commissioner. I shall return by air . Loraine .His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's' a ( at ^^^ l A a ^ Aju an d transmits herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule Reference u&gt; ■ v- ot ft jUj. ip\\\ ( JPl 4L A itCopy of a leiegraiu irom tne Higii Cominissioner for Iraq to the Secretary 01 State for Colonies, Wo.22^, cLat'ed utn April IbZi* A fatwa declaring tuat it would be unlawiui to aeip tne Iraq Government against the TurKs if latter mvaaea Iraq nas been issuea oy three Persian muj tanids AduI Hasan Ispaiiani, Manai AlKnalisi and Munammad Husain ai Wayini. A copy certined by one of tnem nas been photographed by order ox tne Iraq Govern ment. Tne original is said to nave been sent to Angora. The question of the action to be taiten is to be consiaered lomorrow by the Iraq Government. The decision may possiuiy ue to deport tne tnree Mujtanid^ to Persia immediately on tne ground tna t tms del lance of tne Iraq Government cannot be tolerateu. I warn you of tms possioiiity as I quite understand tna t ix the Iraq Government insist on deportation it mignt be embarrassing to .you, but I am unaule to interfere, for tnat would create tne worst possiuie impression. Tne Iraq Government are acting in tnis matter entirely on tneir own initiative. Tne auove is a copy of a telegram wmcn I nave aaaressed to His Majesty's Minister at Tenran. Telegram -P. ?rom - U.E. the High Commissioner lor Iraq, Baghdad. To - Tne Poreign Secretary to tne Government 01 India in tne Poreign and Political Department, Simia. wo.266-s. Da ted (and reca.) the 27th June 1923. Clear tne Line. By order ox Iraq Ministry of Interior prominent Persian devme wno nas ueen issuing decrees against elections is ueing deported in tne direction of Hedjaz with four companions. As Iraq Government wish to get rid of tnem immediately, and to avoid ooat wmcn calls at Persian ports, and as tnere is no direct boat for some time irom here to Aden, I nope tnere win ue * noTelegram P* From - His Exceiiency the Hign Commissioner lor Iraq, Bagndaa. To - Tne foreign Secreiery to tne Governmeut of India, foreign and Political Department, Simla. tAaaressea Tenran No#103 repeated to London Foreign Oflice Wo.346). No.271-3. Dated and reed. 2nd July 1^23. Qif^r tn p. Lin*. Nine leading Persian Ulemas of Kerbeia and Najai with 2o minor personages are insisting on leaving Iraq for Persia via KrianiKin as protest against deportation towards Hedjaz of Mendi-ei-Knaiisi. Tney are being provided with special train by Iraq Government in order to prevent miscnievous demonstrations m routef 'i 'hey reach Persian frontier tonight. So far situation has been accepted quietly by Shiah population. Their purely voluntary departure could evidently not be prevented by Government of Iraq, and I trust there will be no untoward results in Persia. foregoing rexers to my telegram No.9^ dated June 27th to Tehran ana Secretary of State for tne Colonies No. 336. ■ i 11 Telegram P. From - His Majesty's Minister, Tenran. To - The Foreign Secretary to tne Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. (Addressed London Forei^i Uftice repeated to Baghdad lio.102) No.224. Dated and reed, oth July 1^23. I learn tnat on 5th July mullas 1 Conference decided on boycott of British goods, closing bazaar here and in other principal towns and organised demonstrations. Violent campaign has begun in newspapers alleging txiat Great Britain nas operuy declared war on Isiam and th^ t British authori ties have expened divines from Iraq wno came to Persia, inere is aj.so talk: of Jenad being prociaif! ed in mosques uy .enran ^uj tanids. i Government frightened, mercnants nervous ox disturbances. Russians juuiiant uljn 2Z/19. Telegram P. From linister, Tehran. To 3ushire, Ispahan, Kerman, Phiraz, Meshed, Kermanshah, Tabriz. Circular No.3. Dated 2rd received 4th August 192Z. Iraq divines. At Baghdad I found the Arab Govt, unwilling to accept any compromise or to worry much about the Persian situation^ the'departure of the divines having greatly facilitated (?) theirs. After much talk, the idea now is that the matter is an Islamic question and should be treated between the two Islamic G-ovts, without third parties intervening. This is a sound position, if it can be established, as it disengages our responsibility for action which the Arab Govt, took on their ,own initiative and authority. The Persian Govt, mmst now decide whether or not to approach the Arab Govt, themselves. Iduch will depend upon the attitude of the priests of the exodus, but my forecast is that they will remain fairly quiet for fear of prejudicing their chances of return, to enjoy their properties, houses and pecuniary pickings in Iraq, Agitators and Bolsheviks will of course continue to provoke anti-British demonstrations and other follies to the best of their ability. In any case, the more we keep in the background the better. The above is for your personal and confidential information and guidance. Loraine.\/ ?:5/l9, and 37/37. Telegrarn P. From Resident, Bushire. To Minister, Tehran. Ko.178/852. Dated 25th. September 1923. r Jlie Governor has received a telegram from the Prime Minister that on his arrival at Bushire, which is expected early in October, Khalisi is to be given a 'splendid' reception and the town is to be decorated, public holiday given etc. The Governor apprehends that this will mean nothing else than an anti-British demonstrat- -ion, and he implied that he regarded and all Bushire will regard these instructions as tantambunt to Official sanction of such. He expressed his inability to stop or even mitigate the effects, especially as he is already * sufficiently suspect of pro-British feelings, e.nd is uncertain as to the present situation in Tehran; for it is freely rumoured here that the War Minister has been forced to leave the capital and that the anti-British party are left in sole possession of the field. I should be grateful for an indication, if possible, of the present position. Knox.—-—^ — -»!*• fm 37/37 and 23/19. Telegram P. Prom Resident, Bushire, To Minister Tehran. No. 182/865. Dated 30th September 1923. a Your tilegram Ho.174, I fcfeve had no opportunity of consulting the Governor, but I do not want representations made. The S.S. 'Akhbar' arrived this morning and I do not think that anti- -British demonstrations will amount to much. Knox. tmiMgxmmxja&amp;x % &amp;MmxxxxxttX*x±fimKXtx%JBjihiTx • zazzzzzzzzzMiaizzBzzzBhi:a.Bzz%nzMi&amp;z✓ 23/19 &amp; 37/37- Telegram R. prom Resident, Bushire. To Minister, Tehran. noi 187/872. Repeated Baghdad and Shiraz- Dated 3rd October 1)23. Mehdi al Khalisi arrived on 3CthL and is staying with Governor . There was public holiday on day of arrival but no hostile speeches or demonstrations or any sort have taken place and whole visit has passed ofl' very juiBtly so far , Khali sl , who knows alomst no J ersian , being very reticent. Resident.■ fl Telegram P. From Resident, Bushire. To Llinister, Tehran. I0.I88. Repeated to Baghdad, Ispahan and Shiraz. No.873. Copy by European assistant Engineer of the A.P.O .C., who had just arrived at Bushire, under influence of liquor held up a motor car in which were the governor and I.ahdi al Khalisix, neither of whom of course he recognized. Eis B^cellency had him arrested and sent under charge of xne Keaa of Police to the Residency, where he remained xhe night. Sir Arnold Wilson, who was luckily in Eushire was . able to see nis excellency ohis mcrning and apologise ror this unfortunate incident, which it .is hoped will be settled by the immediate dismissal of Trower, who will be sent from Persia at once. It is still to be decided whether Khalisi also wishes a personal apology from Wilson. The most absurd rumours are circulating that this affront to Khalisi was deliberately engineered by us, but Eis Excellency and Khalisis also, I understand, are treating the affair very sensibly. The incident is particularly regrettable in view of the successful efforts of the Governor to avoid anything like anti-British colour to Khalisi's visit. post to Simla. Dated 3rd October 1923. After dark yesterday evening, one Trower, a please see my immediately preceding telegram. Knox.Boc^-..F.^ kESIDENCV. i j)qy-yi 2.^'- Street. Reg. No Z-Z^ Date f.'.fl.i; 1925. OONflO^TIAL RECORDS. I !■! I 'j J I have the honour to transmit herewith, for your infor at ion, thre^ copies ox a report by Kis -'ajesty's Goverrr^ent on the Administration of Iraq for the period from A )ril, 1923, to Deceriter, 1924. I shall he glad if you will forv;: rd copies to the Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrein. I haire the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, POLITICAL RESIDEITT 11T THE PSRSIAM GULP, BUSHIRE.British Reaidency and Consulate-General, j Buahlre, 12th August 1925. To '•lie -folitical Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORAMDUK . A oopy of the undermentioned document is forwarded to you in aoccrdance with the instructions contained in Colonial Office despatch ho. 15, dated the 22nd July 1925 By order Capt., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Report by Kis Itajosty's Government on the Administration of Iraq for the period from April, 1923, to December, 1924.m PERSIA CONFID ■ (No. 499. Sir, I H the Higl: subject oi (Secret.) Sir, I Summary some of tl Persian a Kurds. 2. In regard to Governme to assist n % . •. -J . ilwC lalw/- a/ft at i.v. - (No. 291. Sir, THE deporting being susj secret des the Persia but not f military ^ 2. E\ and the Ii in Tehrai antagonis be coimte( reverse w( 3. I Tehran in friendly d in a more co-operati as betweei anomalous by Persia [it — — —[This Document it the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.] \ 11 § + J ■ r , P ERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [October 13, 1925. J S ection 3. E 6248/2164/34] No. 1. Sir P. Loraine to Mr. Austen Chamberlain.—{Received October 13.) (No. 499. Confidential.) Sir, Tehran, September 26, 1925. I HAVE the honour to transmit herewith copies of a despatch from the High Commissioner at Bagdad, together with my reply thereto, on the subject of the arrest of Persian Kurdish chiefs of the Urumia district. I have, &amp;c. PERCY LORAINE. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Sir H. Dobbs to Sir P. Loraine. ^Secret) Sir, Bagdad, August 17, 1925. I HAVE the honour to invite your attention to paragraph 15 of Intelligence Summary No. 20 of the British military attache, Tehran, wherein it is reported that some of the Persian Kurdish chiefs of the Urumia district have been arrested by the Persian authorities and deported to Tabriz on suspicion of assisting the Turkish Kurds. 2. In view of the failure of the Persian Government to take similar action in regard to the Persian Kurds who have been assisting the Irak Kurds against the Government, it would appear that the Persian Government shows greater readiness to assist Turkey than Irak in this respect. I have, &amp;c. H. DOBBS, Hiqh Commissioner for Irak. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Sir~P. Loraine to Sir H. Dobbs. (No. 291. Confidential.) Sir, Gulhek, September 26, 1925. THE apparently invidious action of the Persian authorities in arresting and deporting some of the Persian Kurdish chiefs of the Urumia district owing to their being suspected of giving assistance to the Turkish Kurds, to which you refer in your secret despatch of the 17th August, would appear to be explained by the fact that the Persian Government has forces at its disposal in Azerbaijan at the present time, but not further south, where operations of any kind on the part of the Persian military would be very considerably more difficult. 2. Even though friction may unfortunately at times exist between the Persian and the Irak Governments, it hardly follows that Turkey is at the moment favoured in Tehran at Irak's expense. Indeed, owing to the traditional and deep-rooted antagonism which has long been in existence between Persians and Turks, and may be counted on in the long run to survive ephemeral political manceiu res, rather the reverse would seem to be the case. 3. I trust that if the contemplated visit of the Air Officer Commanding to Tehran materialises, this and similar questions may be tne subject of fiank and friendly discussion between Sir J. Higgins and the Persian Prime Ministei, ending in a more complete understanding of mutual difficulties and opening the way to co -operation in their solution. It must also be remembered that the whole position as between Irak and Persia, since the institution of the British mandate, has been anomalous, and that this anomaly can only be removed by the recognition of Irak by Persia and the placing of the relations between the two neighbouring countries [1097 n—3]on a more regular and permanent basis. 1 have felt for^a long time that this question of recognition, to be followed by the negotiation of a treaty of amity, is the radical element in the difficult situation which His Majesty's High Commissioner in Bagdad and His Majesty's representative in Tehran have been called on to handle during recent years. I trust and believe that the matter of recognition will very shortly be settled in accordance with the wishes of His Majesty's Government, of the Irak Government, and of your Excellency, and it may reasonably be expected that a basis will thereby be created on which a much more satisfactory situation can be built for the future. Another adverse factor has, of course, been the uncertainty whether England's assistance to Irak is to continue or to cease, and whether the Mosul Vilayet is to remain with Irak or be returned to Turkey. These two questions are of profound importance for Persia. If our determination and ability to stay in Irak and to retain for Irak the Mosul Yilayet w T ere clear, that position would suit her best and she would shape her course accordingly. So long as uncertainty exists on either point, ordinary prudence demands that the Persian Government should rather sit on the fence, even at the risk of being reproached, by England or Turkey, with a disposition to come down on the wrong side. I have, &amp;c. PERCY LORAINE.' question ie radical 1 Bagdad le during diortlv Hp the Irak d that a •n can be certainty ether the questions '0 stay in ould suit ity exists it should Turkey, AINEDowning Street, aueHRE PESIC^NCV* i ^ /J, J an uary, 1926. I have the honour to transmit herewith, for your information, three copies of a report by His Majesty 1 s Government on the administration of Iraq for the period from April, 1922, to March, 1923. I shall 'be glad if you will forward copies to the Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrain. 2. I regret that y ov/ing to an oversight; copies of this report were not sent to you at an earlier date. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, 'HS POLITICAL RESIDENT I IT THE PERSIAN GULF, BUSHIHE. hh mm mm mmmmmmmmmrn **5|li No. 51-S. of 1926. British nesidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 15th February 1926. A copy of the undermentioned publication is forwarded to the Political Agent, /uiwait . Bahrain By order. Capt., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Report on ? Iraq Administration, April 1922 - :-arch 1923. t /v a.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] [January 11, 1927. J Section 1. E 161/161/34] No. 1. Sir H. Dohhs to Mr. Clive.—(Communicated hy Colonial Office; received in Foreign Office, January 11, 1927.)| (Confidential.) gi r) Bagdad, December 16, 1926. I HAVR the honour to invite your attention to your despatch No. 391, dated the 18th November, 1926, forwarding an account of an interview between Major W. A. K. Fraser and the Chief of the Persian General Staff, and to forward herewith a note by Mr. Cornwallis, the adviser to the Iraq Ministry of the Interior. 2. I am in agreement with Mr. Cornwallis's appreciation of the respective attitudes of the two Governments towards each other, and I consider that it redounds to the credit of the Iraq Government that they have been so persistently reasonable aud helpful, in spite of the lack of consideration (to use no stronger a term) which thev have met with at the hands of the Persian Government. In this connection I would invite attention to my telegram No. 182, dated the 16th October, 1926, and to the aide-memoire on the subject of Sheikh Mahmud and Salar-ed-Dowleh which were handed to you by Mr. Bourdillon during your recent visit to Bagdad. I have, &amp;c. H. DOBBS, High Commissioner for Iraq. PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. Enclosure in No. 1. Memorandum. (Confidential.) IN returning with thanks Major Eraser's note, received with your No. 14738 r dated the 6th December, 1926, on his interview with the Chief of the Persian General Staff, I cannot conceal my disappointment that the military attache should not have made a more vigorous riposte to the animadversions of General Shaibani. In considering frontier incidents, it will be best to clear the ground by admitting frankly that there are certain sectors where neither Government has control. It would be absurd to allow incidents in such areas to exacerbate relations; on the contrary, they should serve to bring home to both sides the need of vigorous co-operation wherever possible, so that each Government can extend its control to them. Thus, there is at present no Government in the Kala Diza and Shar Bazher kadhas and Panjwin opposite the Persian districts of Sardasht, Bana. The Sardasht incident of last summer was therefore quite outside the power of the Iraq Government to prevent; indeed, as is shown below, it was the direct result of a glaring instance of Persian refusal to co-operate. On the Persian side the Avroman, opposite our kadha of Halabja, has been completely out of control for many years. Persian tribesmen have been prominent in every subversive movement on the Sulaimani border for many years past, Mahmud Khan Dizli has diverted the waters of the important Dilani Canal for several summers, Iraqi officials and forces are frequently attacked, and if our control of the mountain villages on the Iraq side of the Avroman is light, it is entirely due to the hostility of tribesmen on the Persian side. The Iraq Government does not attribute this state of affairs to any malevolence on the part of the Persian Government; it knows that there is no control in the Avroman. The Iraq Government feels that wherever it has been in its power it has not failed to prove its earnest desire to co-operate with the Persian Government, and can point to many concrete examples, e.g.:— 1. The elaborate and successful arrangements made to apprehend Salar-ed-Dowleh when he emerged from the Avroman into controlled territory. 2. The suppression of the bands of Majid Kadir Aga. 3. The expulsion of Jahangir Kalkhani. [iel-i]4. Ihe prompt settlement of the Khanikin Koda incidents. 5. The removal from the frontier of the Vali of Pusht-i-Kuh when in disfavour with the Persian Government. 6. The recent despatch of a military column with the object of capturing or expelling Reza Niraizhi, wanted by the Persian Government. 7. The rejection of many overtures from Persian tribesmen seeking admission to Iraq territory, &amp;c. In contrast, search of the records has failed to produce a single concrete example of Persian co-operation and goodwill. The Iraq Government points to the following examples of unfriendly acts, chosen almost at random :— 1. The churlish refusal to recognise Iraq. Iraq has been recognised by several Great Powers and attaches little importance to the Persian attitude except in so far as it is symptomatic of a lack of goodwill in a neighbour with whom Iraq is anxious to live on terms not only of friendship, but of active co-operation. 2. The countenance given to Sheikh Mahmud, the facilities given him for supplying himself in Persia and the failure to make any attempt to remove him from the frontier. 3. The release of the Pizhder Agas in spite of the most urgent representations of the Iraq Government. This unfriendly act was aggravated by the acceptance of their ransom from Sheikh Mahmud, thus putting thera under a permanent obligation to this rebel leader. It eventually recoiled, as other similar failures to co-operate are bound to recoil, on the Persians themselves in the shape of the Sardasht disaster. 4. The refusal of the Persian Government to honour its side of the Khanikin settlement in the very trivial Haush Kura caravan case. 5. The failure to take any steps to settle the Gangir water question by preventing the diversion of the Iraqi share of the water to the Saumar cultivation' or adopting the joint recommendations made by Manshur-ul-Mulk and the Iraq representative for a permanent settlement. 6. The encouragement given to Sheikh Falih-of the Bani Lam to settle on the border opposite the Government estate from which he had been expelled, in spite of our requests for his removal. 7. The failure of the Governor of Dizful to give satisfaction in any of the many cases referred to him by the Mutessarif of Amarah. 8. The failure to check the depredations of Muhsin-el-Abjal. 9. The commandeering of Iraqi transport in Persia and maltreatment of the ' drivers. It would be wearisome to continue the list of examples. That co-operation is not impossible is, I think, shown by the work now proceeding on both sides ol the frontier by mutual arrangement on the Rawanduz-Sauj-Bulak road. Although the appeal originally came from Persia, the Iraq Government claims no particular credit for ^ responding; the mutual benefits are so obvious. The mutual benefits of the suppression of frontier disorder are equally obvious. ■Can the Persian Government ever be brought to see it? K. CORNWALLIS, Adviser to the Ministry of Interior. Ministrii of the Interior, Bagdad) December 9, 192l».disfavour )turing or mission to 3 example following jy several de except 3our with of active him for :o remove tations of by the ng them recoiled, Persians Khanikin reventing vation 1 or and the e on the expelled, lie many t of the 3n is not 3 frontier e appeal red it for obvious. tenor. Secretariat of H, E. the Hi^h Commissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad, the ./. 192 7. to The Counsellor to His Excellency the Hi^h Commissioner for Iraq presents his compliments 7 the Secretary tO/Hon''ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushirei'i' ^ and is directed to transmit. .for..his ...ini'.arma.ti.on,. the papers noted below on the subject of... ^^\®...^.^.t'.^chinent _0!f ...'.^.ra^i.S . 10...th e,.f .ri t-.?•. Consulates for training in consular work. Date. January,1927. SBUflKx Description. High Commissioner's despatch to the Colonial Office, with its enclosure. U^Ut-^7 XL*. V I* ^ izqo. * ^.c.o./ / THE RBSIDBNCY. !&gt;^hdftd ,the y Jpnu «ry, 1Q27. 7 Sir, I here the honour to enclOBe e letter which I have receired on the subject of © propossd thet Minister, '4 .1-1927. 'Iraqis should be attached to Tritish Consulates for training in consular work, I understand that, if the proposal is approved, the &gt;rime inister intends to suggest that, in the first irstance, sn 'Irsqi should be attached to the Consulate General at Tushire. The proposal appears to me to be unobjectionable, end I see no reason why 'Ireqis should not si so be sent for training to t emmnshah and Teyrout or wriascus, if the 'Iraq Government wish th?»t this should be done. I should be grateful for an e^rly eypresslon of your views. 2. A copy of this despatch is being sent to His Britannic Majesty's Minister at Tehran, the fon'ble the loliticnl ! esident in the erslan Gulf, His Britannic K aj esty* s Consul General at eyrout, and Consul st Damascus. A. tr / ic^ r* I have the honour to be, sir. Your most obedient, humble servant, 3d.- H.DCPFS. HIGH COan/lSSIOKilK FOB , IRA(i. THE RIGHT HOKOURA'PLl L.C.\- .S.A&amp;'ERY t F.C. .A , 'SCR^TARY OF STATS FOR THE COLONIKS, DOWXIBO STREET, LO^IBOS, S. V. 1 .•5 3./(?. S 1$55—2,000—9-14—(E2) CONFIDENTIAL, Spl—Resdt P G 118 No. 23-3. of 1927. Forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information. 'Z ^^ T ' C ^ Q ' * { thio offioc dated tlae 2. ''he Political Resident will report on the desirability of the High Commissioner's suggestion as soon as he has tdM to study it Bushire: The 3rd February 1921.. Jw Secretary i4fto the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Suo.1 ect : Suggestion to attach an Iraqi to the Consulate General, Buehire, for training in consular work- List of Papers, r v 1 ^ Despatch No. C.0.117, dated the 7th January 1927, from the High Commissioner for Iraq to H.lT's. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. Resubmitted with refer-nee to r.R's note dated. 2/2/27. J.C. L.H.eittial. ^5 D. O.No.D. 530-N. h /♦® FOREIGN 3c POLITICAL DEPARTI^UT, ITew Delhi, the 7 -2 Uarch 1927. Proposal that Iraqis should be attached for training in Consular work to British Consulates. 1 v^ux jOUflOEHTIAL With reference to your endorsement llo. 23-3/27 dated the 3rd February 1927, I am desired to forward herewith for your personal information copy of a letter from India Office to Colonial Office, Ho.458/27, dated the 9th February 1927. Mj €\ The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel L.B.H.Haworth, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (With 1 spare copy).'M'-L requested that i thi» subject tin namber may be to— Under Secretary &lt; Political I l 'Mer sec Colonia14 40B requested that in any further commwnl- this subject the under •mentioned letter ptf am ber way he quoted, and the reyly ^ed to— fto Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. 1. Aba/27. © WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. yth February 1927. £ lr, 1 ora directed by Uie secretary of tats for xiujlu to refer to your letter of the 26th January, NO.40132/27, supportthe proposal of the i -rime i..laieter oi iraQ that IraQlc si 'iouid oe attacl^ied for tralulu^ to iirltieh ^oiibulatee. Xhe tiorl of blrneuhead feele taat the Question 1 b one prlrai..rlly for the coutlderation of the ecretary of tato for Forol^i Affaire but subject to hie views he cannot regard with fi vour a propoBrO. .-hlch In cl^ect tilvet to subjecte of IraQ an advemtege which le denied to British Incllane, who, ac Mr. Becretary Amery 1 b doubtleee awaro, are not eligible for f.dtnl cion to the ulplonn, tic and Consular ServlceB. -M b aspect ol the proposal would be particularly marked If Iri qlr were attadied to British CouBulates In Perelf; and Lord Birkenhead trusts thf t, If it Is decided to approve it on general grounds, Persia may be excluded from its fcope, or at least those areas in I 'ersia where Inuian InterestB are conriaeruble and the consulates are maintains^ by the Uoverniaeut of lndia« A copy oi' this letoer has been rent to the Foreign Office. I am, air. Your obedient Beintent, l 'M«r Secretary of Otate. (Sd • ) L • D • Wa ^ely. Colonial Office.CCJFIDKHTIAL. D .0 . Ho. 76-S• 16 th iiarch 1927. Proposal that Iraqis should be attached for training in consular work to British Consulates. rJb y cCc^*^ Your demi-official letter ho. I3.530-H., dated 2nd March. 1 was glad to receive the enclosure. X had already drafted saying that Bushire was too close to ^raqt and it would be awkward having in our offices an * Iraqi who might not be at heart well disposed to Great Britain or our policy. Turther that lersia had not yet acknow- •ledged 'Iraq, and 1 suggested soiie place other than ^ersia. It woulo have Bade things difficult• indeed irapossible from every point of view. - W A.E.B.Parsons, E.S .O., C .B.E., 'y■ Secjf. to the Govt, of India, P. &amp; P.I)., New Delhi.54/15 66/ 250) BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. J?0Rii]IGIT 0^1 2nd^ ^.'ar cn 19 27. / n bir, With, reference to the Hi^h Gomniissioner xor Iraq's despatch to the Secretary of State icr txie Colonies , ITo.G.O./ 17 of January 7th last, relative to the proposed training of Iraqis in His .lajesty's Consulates, copy of which is already in your possession, I am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from the India Office to the Colonial Office on the subject together with the Colonial Office reply. I 2. I shall be glad to receive your observations on this question at as early a date as possible. 3. His Majesty' s Minister at Tehran and His ■ T ajesty's Consular Officers at Beyrout and Damascus are also being consulted. I am. Sir, Your obedient servant, tenant Colonel L.B.H.Haworth, etc., etc., etc. v Bushire. H»'}173/1566/250) 1927 • 24th February, 1927# Sirv | i an directed by Mr« Secretary Amery to acknowledge the receipt of India Office letter No.F 458/27 of the 9th of February, regarding the proposal that Iraqis should be attached to certain British Consulates for training In Consular work, and to state, for the Infomatlon of the Earl of ^irkenhoad, that It Is not proposed that Iraqis should be trained in Consular work with a view to their admission to the British Consular Service. 2. The Iraq Oovemment contemplate the establishment. In accordance with Article 6 of the Anglo-Iraq Treaty of the let or uctooor, 1922, of ^.raql Consulates abroad and they are anxious that Iraqi personnel should receive training In Consular woric prior to the establishment of such Consulates. 5. Mr. Amery caused Lord Birkenhead to be Informed of the proposal put forward by Sir H. Dobbs and to be Invited to accede to It In view of the fact that some of the British Consulates concerned are maintained by the Oovemment of India. Mr. Amery trusts that. In view of the explanation now furnished, lord Birkenhead will feel able to withdraw his objections to the proposal put forward by Sir K. Dobbs. 4. Mr. Amery would be glad If an early reply could be returned to this letter, a copy of which Is being forwarded to the Pbreign Office. I am, etc., (Signed) A.J. Harding. * Secretary of State, f0 Utlcal Department, India Office.Ho. of 1921 m Sir, The Britiah Residency and Consulate* General, Buehlre, 18th. April 1921c I have the honour to aoknowledge the receipt of your deepatoh Mo. 3. (K:634/l5 66 /260) dated 2nd. March 1927, en the subjeot of Irak Consuls-being attached for Instxtiotlon to this Residency and Consulate^General* In reply to paragraph 2 of your letter, I hare the honour to say that I think it would be undesirable to have Irakis in so intimate a relationship at Bushire® An IrrJc subject, unless he were pro British in temperament, misht fine his opinions in opposition to our interests. Indeed it does not follow that because he were pro British that he would continue so in the future. The present time has many important questions thre notuye, such as the oil fieles anc meai ure. c j for their protectio the air route by Arnbia and the British position in the Persian Gulf, in which an Iraki might not see eye to eye with us* He would instantly ^et to know what was being suggested or being done, he would follow the itineraries of the Political esicent and his Political Agents, and would in general get to Know too much* I am ef opinion that such an official could learn his work in Palestine or elsewhere with lessfai possible danger to ue # As Persia has not recognised Irak f the attachment of an officer would preeumably be difficult at present, and this would perhaps form a convenient answer to the request* A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Govern* ment of India in the Foreign and Political Department and to H^JM^s Minister, Tehran, T)UtNo. of i 927 ' A copy oi the under mentioned paper is forwarded to Minister at Tehran for information^ in continuation of this office ttfle^raca 49, dated 19th. April ^1927. Bushire The 19th. April 1327. % order. Captain. Under Secretary to the Political Kesioer /it in the Persian Gulf. Despatch So, 23. dated the 18th. April 1927. Irem the folitica Resident 3n the Persian Gull to K.Jt.'s Principal Secretary of State ior FcreiKn Aliairs. London.- Telegram P From Resident Bushire To Tehran No. 49. Dated and despatched 19tho April 1927,, Question of posting Iraqis to Bushire for instruc tion in Consular worko Foreigm Office has asked me for ray opinion, I am replying that the Iraqi is not a British subject and may not necessarily be well disposed to us, and nay not in any case remain so. His presence in so intimate a position would not be desirable, I suggest his being posted somewhere further away, where we have no Political interests on v/hich Iraqis might hold opinions. Also Persia has not recognised Iraq. HAWORTH. ill ifii it&gt;.949/27 llfDIA OPFICii, WHIXiiHALii, LOUliOti, 3.W.I. nth March, 1927. / Sir, X am directed by the 3eoretar^ 01 Hate for India to acknowledge the recei t of Mr. iiarding'B letter of the 24th /ehruary, ilo.40132/27, regarding the proposed attaohmont of Iraqis tvj certain British Consulates for training in consular work. 1 am to express the regret of the Secretary of State, who was quite aware of the facts stated in Mr. Harding^ letter, that he is unable to agree to the attaohment of Iraqis to any consulate maintained by the Government of India, or in an area in v; ich indian interests are considerable. A copy of this letter has been sent to the foreign Office. I am, eto., (3d. ) M.C. Seton. Under Secretary of State, GOLOflliuL OmCii.- . view of the fact that some of the British Consulates concerned are ; ;mtained by the Government of India. Mr. Amery trusts that, in view of the explanation now furnished, Lord Birkenhead will feel able to v. ithdra*. his objections to ti e ^rojos&amp;l jut 'orv.c rd oy oir K. Dobbs. 4. Mr. Amery v /ould be ^lad, if an early reply could be returned to this letter, a cop^ of ' ich is be in j sent to e 1 o- - C _ f w • I am, e t c.» Sd. A. J. Harding The Under Secretary of State, Political Department, India Office. 1.949/27. India Office, White -all&gt; London, S. 11th ''arch 1927. c ■? -« -Ix , •I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acl:-o^/lec^e the receipt of Mr. Kardin^'s letter of the 24th February, Iio«4ixo2/27 re-ardin^ the proposed attachment of Iraqis to certain British Consulates for trai in-_ in consula. v/o . I am to express the regret of the secretary of -tate, who v/as quite aware of the facts stated in . in^* l . - &gt; is unable to a.jree to the attachment of Iraqis to any consulate maintained by the Government of India, or in an area in v.hic i inc.ian interests are considerable. A copy of this letter has been sent to the Foreign c. Vice. I am, etc., Sd. II. G. Seton. ^•cier Secretary of 3tate&gt; Colonial Cf-ice. True Irore tendent, Department-01• p.O.No .595-N May //- E7, Proposal that Iraqis should 'be attached to British Consulates for training in Consular work. BUSHlRE RESIDENCY. S •■■■' *1 fteg. ^o. Date ••• 9 !.L. /I'c-i 7 J C0hH0EMiAL| nL^OP.. - y In continuation of my demi-official letter NO .D.919-N, dated the iith April 1927, I am desired to forward herewith for your personal information a copy of a further letter No.P 919/27, dated the 14th April 1927, together with its enclosures received from the India Office. To The Hon^lole Lieutenant-Colonel L .B.H.Haworth, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e. (With i spare copy.) 7.P. 1919/27 LbTDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 14th April 1927. My dear Bray, In continuation of ray letter of the 17th March Uo.P.949/27 to Howell, I enclose copy of the marginally Letter from Foreign Office dated) noted further correspondence 1st April. ) 11. ) relating to the proposed attach-aent -ditto- dated 13th Apr of Iraqis to His Majesty^ Legation at Tehran and to British Consulates in Persia and elsewhere for training. Yours sincerely. Sd/- L.D.Wakely. Sir Denys Bray, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., G.B.E., I.C.S.P.1637/27. SIJCLOSURE IN POREiail OFFICE COVERING LIFTER I | NO.K3037/1566/2DO, DATED 1ST APRIL. 1927. of Fe of Ira FORKIGN OmCS. S.w.l. 31«t larch, 1927. With reference to your iet/ter m.w bruary 25tli last recardimj the proposed! or iragia m consular work at Britisli consulates, I am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to inform you tnat he has received a copy of the India Office reply tIo.P.949/27 of the llth instant to -^.Harding'3 letter of the 24th ultimo, and to state, for :t. &gt;ecret&lt;'ry Amery's information, that His IIajesty f s M inister at Tehran, Uis ^ajestj's Consuls-General at l3eyrout and Bushire and is ajesty's Consul at Damascus are beinr; consulted in the matter. A further coinramicatlon will be made to you on recei ^■1 am A I F # Gye # our letter No.40132/27 trainingLRINC LETTER DA I ED Colonial Offloo, JoT/ning 3treet. L||^/302/65) 14th Maroh, 1927. SlXt I am directed by Mr. Secretary -vmery to refer to Colonial Office letter of the 9th of March, »unbared ae atoOYe, regarding - inter alia • the auggeation thtt, until Persia haa recognised Iraq, an Iraqi should tu? attached to the British Legation at Tehran in order to assist Mr, Ulire in the cen si deration of questions affecting Iraqi interests# and to transmit her^ 1 1. , for the information of Secretary 3ir Austen Chamberlain, a copy of a telegram on the subject which has been received from the High Oomaission «r for Iraq, 2, Mr, Amery would be gJad to be furnished with a oo]w of Mr, aiive^ letter of the 5th of February, to which __ Sir n. i)obbs refers, and to be advised what reply should, in Sir fasten Chamberlain's opinion, be returned to 3lr H, aototos* tologrsua. I am, etc* (Signed) A,J. Harding. Nader Secretary of State, milSIGH omcie.PAHAPmiA-lS THiaORAMi ?roin the Hl^i Uonnal as loner for Iraq to the 3 eo rotary of for th« Colonic Xiated 2nd llarch 1927® (HaoftlYftd Colonial Offloo 2«5 2nd Maroh 1927)» I 1 Addro9»ed to Soorotiixy of 3tato for tho Colonies Ko t 106 repeated to Tehran U© # 37. Attachment of Iraqi to Tehran Legation see my letter to 3huokburgh Ho, 156 of 20th January. 1 have put suggestions contained In wlIre 's private letter to me of 5th February (of which he sent copy to Ollphant) privately to the Premier who sees no objection. 1 should be glad to be Informed whether I may now put them forward officially.Jtebruary Sth, 1927# 62/302/65). /v Uy d*xT ijoUbs, I have be«n pondering yovur oonfldentlai letter o January 20th rolatln? to the euggeetion of your Prime Minister that pending Per elan recognition of 1 J-raQ and Iraqi repreeentatire should be attached to this Juegation in order to help us in looking after 1 lit'-qi intereete and to keep us acquainted at firet hand with the fiewa and neede of 'Iraq, 4saui &amp;ing t'mt it la eyentually decided to attach an 'Iraqi representative to the ^egat To i, he would, appear to have two poeeible spheres of usefiilliess# va) ca assist the Vice Uonsul (b) to as-ist the Jh?inceiy In dealing with our numerous Ferso-Iraq oases# .is regarde (a) the /ice Consul tells flie that an 'Iraqi might be T«ry uneful In dealing «lth atplloatlone for 'Iraq nationality, paa»port» otootora w.lort havo to oo . transmitted to Baghdad, He would require to have a really £00d knowledge of English t\nd Persian and his usefulness would of course ver; r much depend on his ability and character* As regards lb) there arc obvious object lone to his working in the Uhanoery as we obviously caanet let him loose in our archives. If on the other hand a separate room could be found for him - a somewhat difficult matter with our limited aocojamodation - he could be #iown c^rt iin files relating to claims and other frontier matters# while he could interview the camel drivers who constantly worry us 'Woo) I twiy ' HI I 3lr Konry H,0. Jotobo. K.O.S.I., K..0.U,0., Hla Majesty's High Uo.-nalB8lonor for Iraq, Baghdad,us about their aXaims against th« alimentation ^oo^rtlent. But on the wl'tole it would rather be a oaae of our teaohlng him than of hie toeing muoh help to us« I think therefore that if an f Iraqi 13 to toe aent here he had better be att *ohed to the Yloe-Jonsul *te wiiere he could work in the eacie room ae the probationer. Hie work would be Consular but we should always be free to consult him on relevant pelltlcal meat ions - and to show him auoh of the political files as are not open to objection. The extent of our oonfldence would of course depend on his character. I Imagine, aubj act to the Tlewe of the foreign Office that he would be attached to the Legation as assistant Probationer Vice Consul and that we should notify his appointment In that capacity to the Persian Gowerniaent. I an sending copies of thie oorreeponcionoe prlT .ttely to OliphaBt at the foreign Offioe.23/19. Telegram From To Repeated P. llo. 137-S. High Co:TriEsioner, Baghdad. Governinent of India, 'i .la. . 1' T s . Minister, 'ehran, Resident, Bushire, Secretary of State for Colonies, London, 11 o. 320. T)ated and received ilth July 1927. During 10th Iluliarrara celebrations in Kadhinain mosque fracas occurred in courtyard shrine. liunediate cause still obscure but directly quarrel started participants in procession made determined attack on unarmed leaTi? party ox Shiah soldiers from Iraq army who were attending the ceremony under their own officers and attended by nixitary police armeci v /ith revolvers. Three civilians killed four in jure c . One side conjectures 38 they would . Kiot ended immediate- -ly troops were withdrawn, no attempt being made zo at :a,Civ police who were restoring order. r 'o prevent retaliation ICadhimain has been put out of bounds ior army,and troops ao present confined to barrakks. Mope you will ce abxe .o correct exaggerated rumours. TIIGK coMasf)ioir:H. Secretary to 'nesiden:, : : ushire. Resident, at SLiraz. Telegram From To Unnumbered. Dated 12th July 1927. Foregoing message sent as received to save tiie- Chick has books. PRIOR.11 D.O.No•595-N. July To Proposal that 'Iraqis should be attached to British Consulates for training in consular work* / f~/ &lt;^1 /)fife 6 U CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS In continuation of Parsons• demi-official letter Mo. 595-H, dated the 11th May 1927, I am desired to forward,for your personal information,a copy of a further letter no. P.3113/27, dated the 23rd June 1927 and enclosures, received from the India Office* &gt;■ h The Hon^le Lieutenant Colonel L*B.H*Haworth Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. m Jl With 1 spare copy. T&amp; el ; ijP.3113/27. /?7 India Office, Whitehall, 23rd June 1927# ■ ^ 1 from Mr •.Gye to Mr.Wakely ,ted 21st April. : from Foreign Office datea 21st June# My dear Bray^ In continuation of my letter of the 14th April I enclose copy of the marginally noted further correspondence i about the proposed attachment of 1 Iraqis to His Majesty^ Legation at Tehran and to British Consulates in Persia and elsewhere for training in consular work# Yours sincerely, Sd/- L.D.Wakely* Sir D* de S»Bray, ^-•.C»I»E», G#S# I •, C , Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla.ffOREIGHOFFICB, S.HT.l. April 218t 1927. (K.4674/1566/250) Dear x.Wakely, i moil: li:'. ■ . ^T.Hall of the Colonial Office has written to me about the proposed training of Iraqis in certain consulates and has asked me to let you have our views. His letter is dated March 30th and a copy has been sent to Patrick. I enclose copy of my reply from which . you will see how we feel about it. Yours etc. (Sgd) Ernest Gye. L.D.Wakely, Esq., C.B., I, [,4674/1566/250 FOREIGB OFFICE, S.W.I. April 2l3t 1927. Dear Mr•Hall. V 'ith reference to your letter 40132/?? of March 30th, relative to the proposed training of Iraqis at British Conaulates, we d) not feel we can express an opinion on the merits of theaeheme until we have received the considered views of all those whom it will most immediately affect, i.e. the inister at Tehran and the Consuls-General at Beyrout and Bushire . As you know we consulted them when the scheme was originally put to us and you may like to see the first reply - from Damascus - of which I enclose a copy. J .H. lall, sq. , D«o.0•, »^ •,4625 /1566/250) i&lt;o • 38 • British Consulate, DK&amp;IASCUo* l8th arch 1927. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch ~.o.l4 of the 2nd aroh (K # 2634/15-6/250) and attached correspondence relative to the proposed trnhning of Iraqis in certain Consulates, among others Damascus. 2. Although the plan is in the best spirit of the mandate, I cannot view with equanimity its application in Syria. 3. The first effect would be to cheapen the position of a Consul in the eyes of the local population to accept an Iraqi on the footing of a Student Interpreter is to admit the eqality of the native, and a dangerous error in a country like Syria. 4. Moreover the presence of an Iraqi probationer in this Consulate could not fail to give umbrage to the Frencii Delegation, who cannot be expected to see in it anything but a further insidious attack on their own positions. If I may invite a,reference to the concluding para, of your despatch i^o.lOB (Secret) of the 1st November last (E.5933/52/89) you will recollect that you furnished me with the most precise instructions ' not merely to maintain a negative attitude of aloofness, but oy evincing a sympathetic understanding of the difficulties with which the ^rench authorities may be confront*«»ed to gain their confidence and so eliminate any suspicions, however unfounded, they may at present harbour in respect to the actions and motives of British officials in the liear East'. The appoint lent ol Iraqis to iiritiah Consulates in even the most remote countries will infallibly be used by Syrian nationalists as a stick to beat the French; and if one is actually paraded in my O-ifice in tne focus of Syria, I cannot imagine by what arguments I could •onwince I onsieur Pierre Alype of the sincerity of -British professions of sympathy. 5. Copies of this despatch are being forwarded to His Excellency the High Commissioner at Baghdad and His ajesty's Consul-general at 3eyrout. I have etc. ( )gd) B.C.HOLE. lUJ/. Consul. ajesty's Principal Secretary of Slate for Foreign Affairs, etc. etc. etc. Foreign Office, S.W.I. Copies to; Baghdad (x.o.22) and iieyrout (i.o.27).£.3113. Ho.K.6803/1866/250 / The Under Secretary of State for foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and by direation of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under mentioned paper. Foreign Office. 21st June 1927. Reference to previous correspondence* Letter from -r. Gye to r. Wakely, K.4674/1566/250 21st April 1927. l^ame and Date . To the Colonial Office (with enclosures) 18th June 1927• Sub.1 ect . Proposed training of Iraqis in consular work at British Consulates.;,6803 /1566/250. FOREIG x. OFFICE. S.W.I. 18th June 1927. Sir, With reference to foreign Office letter i^o .K.3837/1566/250 of arch 31st, relative to the proposed training of Iraqis in consular work at certain British Consulates abroad, I am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to trai.snit to you the accompanying copies of despatches from His - ajesty's inister at ehran, and His lajesty^ Consuls General at Beyrout and Bushire on this subject. A copy of a despatch from His ajesty's Consul at Damascus on the same question was transmitted to you in r.Gye's private letter l^o.K,4674/l566/250 of April 21st to Ft •Hall, 2. In view of the various considerations urged in these despatches, and more especially of the objections put forward in para.s 2 and 3 of Colonel Haworth's despatch of April 18th, as well as on general political grounds, the Secretary of State considers the proposal that Iraqis should be attached to British Consulates for training to be open to serious objection and impracticable. 3. He realises, however, the desirability of offering the Iraq Government any assistance which may be possible to enable them to create an efficient and capable consular service of their own, and he would therefore be prepared, should Mr.Secretary Amery concur, and should it be found practicable for the Iraq Government to make the necessary financial arrangements, to offer the Iraq Government the services of a senior British consular officer for the purpose of helping to form and train an Iraqi consular service on the general lines of His ajesty's Consular Service. 4. The question whether such am officer could not at the same time undertake a certain amount of ordinary British commercial work in Iraq is one which might also be taken into consideration, I am etc, (Sgd) E.F.CROWE. 'Hder Secretary of State, COLONIAL office. ■■■■■■Hi[u Ilo. 137. Britioh Ugation., ^ 24th Liar ch, 1927. follov/ing observations. the training facilities thus afforded them will not be particularly invidious rora ^he Indian oom,. Oi view. 3 I realise however that this aspect 0^ the question may assume an importance in ooes not seem to possess in .ahran, and should 11, be ( scided bliat it provides a sound reason for not attachinr ' Traoi3 to Gonsulai' astablishmenjs . 1 „ controlled by the Goverraaent of India I do not consider that 'Iraqi intorests would dg very materially a.i^ct^ •provided that it were found posojbje to attach (Iraqis to so.ie of His A 'ajeaty'a Consulates in /estern Persia, including Ahwai which is now raainlv under the control of the foreign Office. Intha_ case I consider that the 'Iraq Soverriinent would have little cause for complaint# 4 are is can tiave no valid let^l grounas for objecting to such nominations, buL I s lould be ga.a.d to be reassured on this points I have etc., (Sd.) R .H. Clive. At.Hon 1 ble Sir Austen Chamberlain,CI • ,1 .P*# FOREIGrN OFFICE.zi/v /1666/250 ) CONSULATE GENERAL, BEYROUT. April 13th 1927. Copies to - Baghdad. Damascus• lo .74. Sir, With reference to your despatch ivo.34 (K.2634/1566/250) of 'arch 2nd relative to the proposed training of Iraqis in His ajesty's Consulate3, I have the honour to report that, ao far as I am concerned, I should have no objection to an Iraqi being attached to this post for instruction provided that it was clearly understood that he was a member of my staff for general duties and in no way specially designated to watch over Iraqis and their interests. Otherwise I might be inundated with petty complaints from Iraqi students and others which would normally settle themselves. Further, complete abstention from interference in local politics would have to be guaranteed. 2 Although the terms of the Anglo-Iraq reaty of October 10th 1922, and what they imply must be perfectly well known both to the French and to t^ose natives of this country who are interested, I thought well privately to ask the French Acting High Commissioner whether the presence of an Iraqi on my staff or on the staff at His -ajesty's Consul at Damascus would be likely to prove embarassing to the French authorities. After some little delay lonsieur De Reffye has written to say that, while he does not see any real objections to the proposal, he would for reasons which are obvious, prefer that any raqi entlemen selected for training should commence J.is consular eduction at Beyrout rather than at Damascus. I have e tc. (Sgd) H.E.oATOW. His i.Tajesty 1 s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, etc. etc. etc. S.W.I.n Downing Street, BUSHIRE P /0f2 Reg. No. Date . Q»et«tetnr, 1927. v ! / 2 '2^2-1 COUFiDdi.TiAL nLGGaDS. I have the honour to transmit herewith, for your information, three copies of a report by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Council of the League of Nations on the administration of Iraq for the year 1926. I shall be glad if you will forward copies of this report to the Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrein. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, {for the Secretary of StateJ $&gt;v 2 POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULF, BUSHIRE. P.A. No. 40b-3 . of 1927. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire , 4th December 19^ . A COPY of the u .rn. publication is forwarded to the Kuv.'al 't Bahrain Cv*' 0, Capt., 3c cy. year 1926 - tm Downing Street. 8 Septem^ex; J 928. BUSH F.£SIDE^ !^ ' Rw. No. m OOKHOBiTUL ^GOBOS. I have the honour to transmit herewith, for your information, three copies of the report by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Councij of the League of Nations on the administration oflraq for the year 1927. I shall be gl d if you will forward copies of this report to the P olitical Agent s at Kuwait and Bahrein. The report is being published in this country on the 15ta of September. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, THE HONOURABLE THE POLITICAL RESIDENT IPP IN THE PERSIAN GrJ_?• ' I(J NO. Bur- - pCpi^r-Mz-s y f No.... .. //fJ.Z 1 Ckt* .. &gt; /3jz %«, ^iirl[i£Ml;iL fi£GuilOS. ; Downing Street. November,] 928. Sir, With reference to my despatch Tr o.3 of the 8th of September forwarding copies of the report by His Britannic Majesty's Government on the Administration of Iraq for 1927, I have the honour to inform you that certain errors in the Customs figures shown on pages 100 and 102 of that report have been brought to light. 2. I have accordingly to transmit to you copies for ?«i C0 _i_Qf each of two correction slips .and to request that these P .1Q2. may be distributed in the same manner as were the copies of the report forwarded with my despatch under reference I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, i, humbl e s e rv an t, v * 1 / /t^c a- THE HONOURABLE, THE POLITICAL RESIDENT, IN THE PERSIAN GULF.CONFIDl [E 839/8J ( Report by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Iraq for the year 1027, CORRIGENDA. padk 100. 11.—F oreign T rade . I mports. The total value of imports (including goods in transit) during the financial years 1925—'26 aiul 1926—2/ was as follows . 1925-26 ... ... ••• ••• R®- 16,97,56,368 1926-27 ... ... ••• ••• ^ s - 15,46,12,362 In the table shewing the value, in lakhs ot iiipees, ot llie principal commodities imported for home consumption, substitiit'e the following :— 2. Sugar 3. Tea 4. Liquors and Wines W2o-2t). lis. (lakhs.) 83 39 10 1026-27, lis. (lakhs). 82 40 10 Report by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Council of thr League of Nations on the Administration of Iraq for the year 1027. CORRIGENDA. P acje 102. T he T rade B alance. For the table shewing the relative adverse trade balances in lakhs of rupees for 1925-26 and 1926-27, substitute the following 1925-26 ... 1,697 1,209 4S9 239 250 1926-27 ... 1,546 1,033 514 82 432 {No. 1.) Sir, I HA the consuh Inspector t 2. A from Lond on my voyi Basra. I rather tha voyage to which, if 1 Foreign D( afford me t 3. I leave. Six strained s: elaborated aircraft. Secretary, 4. Ii morning, t following immediate observed i was fortun Political I interesting situation ii upward cv (as is the c on a comrr that His 1: that, retur until the common V 5. A Customs c gentleman instructior Persia exc regulation an affable endeavour call at thi Murphy, make the exchange lay in the 6. C and, with i with, two Lingah pr but 1 was customs d [71[This Docament is the Property of His Britannic Majesty 's Government.] PERSIA. February 16, 1929. CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 1. [E 839/839/34] No. 1. Consul Selous to Sir Austen Chamberlain.—{Received February 16.) (No. 1.) Sir, Basra, January 7, 1929. I HAVE the honour to report that I arrived in Basra to-day and took charge of the consular building and premises at this port from Mr. R. F. Jardine, Administrative Inspector at Basra, who had been in occupation of the consulate until my arrival. 2. As I had occasion to inform Mr. Lancelot Oliphant previous to my departure from London, it has been my object to make contact with such departments or stations on my voyage out as I am likely to come into contact with during my commission at Basra. I therefore decided, upon reaching Bombay on the 14th December, that, rather than proceed immediately by the fast mail, it would be better to continue my voyage to Basra by the slow Persian Gulf mail steamer sailing on the i9th December, which, if boarded at Karachi instead of at Bombay, would allow me time to call at the Foreign Department of the Government of India at New Delhi and at the same time afford me the opportunity of meeting my colleagues in the Gulf. 3. I reached New Delhi on the same day as the Foreign Secretary returned from leave. Sir Denis Bray had arrived from Bagdad in great haste by air in view of the strained situation at Kabul, so I was unable to see him as plans were then being elaborated for the evacuation of women and childrem from the Afghan capital by aircraft. 1 was, however, very kindly received by Mr. Acheson, deputy Foreign Secretary, who expressed satisfaction at my demarche. 4. In due course I boarded the slow Persian Gulf mail at Karachi on Sunday morning, the 23rd December, and arrived at Muscat on Christmas night. On the following morning I went ashore and, after a walk in and about the town and immediate suburbs of Muscat, where an unexpected talent in wood-carving was to be observed in sundry beautiful doorposts and lintels, called upon the consul, whom I was fortunate enough to find at home, being but just returned from a visit to the Political Resident of the Persian Gulf at Bushire. Major Murphy afforded me interesting information and, inter alia, gave me an appreciation of the slave-trading situation in the Gulf, which would appear at the moment to be on one of its periodical upward curves. Domestic slavery in Arabia, I gathered, was a not unhappy state (as is the case, within my own experience, in Morocco), but the lot of slaves working on a commercialised basis on the pearl banks is a harder one. In conclusion, I learnt that His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman was not in residence ; it appeared that, returned from his visit in England, he is at present marking time at Bombay until the beard which Islam favours, but which, in courteous deference to the more common Western custom, he had discarded, shall have grown again. 5. At Jask, on the Persian coast, the Persian Inspector-General of the Persian Customs came on board, passenger for the next port. Bunder Abbas, trom this gentleman I received the unpleasant information that, as the result of recent instructions received from Tehran within the fortnight, no foreigner may land in Persia except his passport be vise at a Persian Legation or consulate. This new regulation affected me, as I had no Persian visa. The Inspector-General of Customs, an affable, much travelled, and multilingual gentleman, promised me indeed to endeavour to make things right for me at Bunder Abbas so that I might laud and call at the British consulate, which had been apprised of my movements by Major Murphy. Nothing came, however, of this promise, and I was unable to land and make the acquaintance of Mr. Richardson, my contact with whom was restricted to an exchange of letters in the course of the long day during which steamship ' Bandra lay in the roadstead. 6. On the 29th December we reached the Persian port of Lingah soon after o r M., and, with the assistance of the steamship company's looal agent, I was able to go ashore with two of the ship's officers, in the character, I believe, of a ship's officer myself. Lingah presents an attractive and prosperous appearance as seen from the roadstead, but 1 was informed on shore that trade was dropping, the reason siven being the heavy customs dues. This information tallied with a remaik of the s dp's captain to me to [716 q-1]2 the effect that so much smuggling went on along this part of the Persian Gulf coast that more than half of the considerable quantity of cargo on board his vessel for Dabai, on the Arabian coast, would without doubt find its way across to the opposite shore. I was able to spend an agreeable hour with Dr. Hill, the vice-consul, who is to be congratulated on being a married man, for his only British companions are the manager of the Indo-European Telegraph (wireless) station and his assistant. 7. After spending over twenty-four hours at Dabai, the steamship 'Bandra' reached Bahrein, chief centre of the pearl-tishing industry, on the opening day of the New Year. Here, on my landing in the afternoon, 1 was most hospitably welcomed and entertained by Colonel Barrett, who drove me in his automobile through the environs of Manama, the chief city of the group of islands ^forming Bahrein. It was a pleasant surprise to see so cleanly a little city and to note how much its municipality has done in seven years. This includes a newly reclaimed foreshore or ** bund,' a road system, and municipal cleanliness, which was particularly noticeable in the poorer quarters, where the dwellings consist of matting and bamboo fencing. Incidentally, the necessity for a road system of a certain kind will be realised when I mention that there are something like 150 cars in Bahrein to-day. These figures may be compared with three for Muscat and one for Lingah. A further interesting feature was the discovery and drilling of an artesian well in the garden now being prepared for the Sheikh of Bahrein alongside his new palace in the outskirts of Manama. The island water is, however, somewhat too charged with magnesia to make it pleasant for drinking purposes, and the Europeans consequently obtain their potable water from the steamers of the British India line. 8. I had looked forward to landing in Bush ire, Persia's premier port, and calliog upon the Political Resident. Unfortunately, however, my purpose was defeated, for the steamer, arriving after nightfall, managed to discharge all her Bushire cargo during the night, and sailed for Koweit at 8 a.m . on the 4th January, reaching this latter port at sunrise on the 5th. Here I had better fortune, and, landing early, again met with a most friendly and hospitable reception at the hands, this time, of Colonel More, the Political Agent, who drove me round the city walls, both inside and out, and gave me much interesting information concerning Koweit's military history in recent times arising out of Ibn Sand's lack of authority over some of his tribes and about the principal local industry, which is shipbuilding. I had in fact been greatly interested in the very considerable number of sailing vessels, some so large as to exceed 300 tons, which lay in serried ranks within the series of small waterports which line the seafront of the city. They exceeded anything I had seen at either Lingah, Dabai, or Bahrein, and it needed no great strain on the imagination to see in Koweit's seafront a twentieth century reproduction of one of England's lesser but thriving seaports in mediaeval times. 9. In conclusion, and with reference to the second paragraph above, I would be grateful to learn whether, given the special circumstances of the case, I may be authorised to claim my expenses in proceeding to New Delhi and subsequently joining ship at Karachi. I am persuaded that my action in taking personal contact with the Government of India was a not unhappy one and calculated to increase the value of my later meetings with the officials of the Indian Government in the Persian Gulf. T have, &amp;c. G. H. SELOUS.IOWMIHG STRiiiST, f 4 September,1929. Km, - /w fh+ 2 i [ mom I Sir, I have the honour to transmit herewith, for your information 3 copies of the Report oy His Majesty ! s Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the administration of Iraq for the year 19 28. I shall 'be glad if you will forward T&lt; copies of this Report to the Political Agents ao Kuwait and Bahrein. 2. The Report is 'oeing published in this country on the 17th September. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. - ^ ^ ^ v/ y ^ AONOUHAHjE THB POLITICAL RESIIMTT. I IT THE PERSIAN GULF. i^IIIfr Downing Street, September, 1950. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my despatch No. 2 of 4th September 192^, and to transmit to you herewith 5 copies of the Report by His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdomof Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Iraq for the year 1929. I shall be glad if you will forward copies of this Report to the Political Agents at Kuwait and Bahrein. The Report is being published in this country on 15th September. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, )H, POLITICAL RESIDENT IK THE iBESIAN GULP. /o ** Co.ies sent to Bahrain and Kuwaxt under (f/, ^0. 535-3. of 3-10-1930.94, Downing Street, , 1S31. I have the honour to refer to my despatch No. 18 of the 17th September, 1930, and to transmit to you herewith three copies of the Special Report by His Majesty f s Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Irelanci to ti.e Council of the League of Nations on the Irogress of 'Iraq curing the period 1920 -31. I shall be glad if you vvill forward copies of this Report to the rolitical xlgents at Kuwait and Bahrein. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servant. , L H - J HOKOUKABLii THii POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THil PiHSIAN GULP.'/W i uoy/iung street, 3 October, 1931. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my despatch ^o. IB of .the 17th September 1920, and to transmit to you herewith three copies of the Report by His Majesty's Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the administraoion of Iraq for the year 1930. I shall be glad if you will forward c^ies of this Report to the Political ^ents at Kov /eit and Bahrein. 2. The Report has already been published in this country. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, HONOURABLE, ACTING POLITICAL RESIDENT vtyf- it! tr3 PERSIAN gulf.-8 Confidential , No.179. v* n ) Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated tbe 10th October 1932. n (o From n-l o • V' IM To Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P .Dickson, C.I .E., Political Agent , Kuwait. The Hon'ble the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, BushIre. Sir, I have the honour to report that last night at a dinner given by the Anglo Persian Oil Company's represent- ative to tte Shaikh and myself ths latter informed me in private conversation thet during his recent visit to Baghdad, King Faisal asked him how he thought His Majesty f s G-overnment would react If he visited the Arab States of the Persian Gulf. The Shaikh said tint he replied as follows:- 'If ycu were to try and come officially not only would we Arab Rulers object, but His Majesty's Government would certainly raise difficulties, a private visit on the other hand would be quite a dlfierent matte and Your Ivlajesty would be welcome as far as Kuwait was concerned The King replied ^yes those are my views also'. The above is forwarded to you for what It is j worth. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.Confidential. 1(0.792-3 of 1932. British Reaidency &amp; Consulate-Oeneral, Bushire, the 19th October 1932. From - The Hon'ble Lt.-Colonel T.C.-o^le f C.B.E.» Bolitioal Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Foreign Secretary to the Oovernment of India, Bew Delhi* InauirY bv H is Majesty King Faisal of 'Iraq, as to his Tisiting the ^rab State s of P ersian Gulf * $ v v Sir, V I hare the honour to forward herewith for the information of the Government of India a oopy ©f a let.&amp;r .. j 179, dated the 10th October 1932, from the Political Agent, Kuwait, on the subject mentioned above* 2. It would, in my opinion, have been more politic for the Shaikh of Kuwait to have refrained from expressing any opinion as to the possible reaction of His .ajeaty's Government to such a proposal than to have stated that Kis Majesty's Government would certainly raise difficulties. 3, Should His Majesty at any time express a desire t visit the Arab States of the Persian Gulf my opinion as to political desirability or otherwise will depend on one conditions prevailing at the time* I think, however, that various •••-2- various grounds 9 expense to the Arab States concerned amongst others, an unofficial visit would be preferable to an official one. I am sending copies of this letter to His Majesty's * Secretary of State for India and His Majesty's Minister, ♦ Baghdad* * sent under P.L. 1T0.793-S of 19/10/32, I hare the honour to be. Sir, Touf most obedient servant. lt«-Colonel, \ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait, for information. By Order. Confidential Assistant.pin -p Jov/ning Street, 1st October, 1932. Sir b' hijf I have the honour to refer to my despatch No.11 of the 3rd October, 1931, and to transmit to you herewith three copies of the Report by His Majesty's Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Iraq for the year 1931. I shall be glad if you will forward copies to the Political Agents at Koweit and Bahrein. E. The Report has already been published in this country. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, ti HONOUHABLJ: THE P0LITIGA1 RSSIiMfT IN THji P1SSIAN GULF. ff- } W'*' Zlu n Town. Telegram E 30. ^om H.M's Minister, Baghdad. To Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, London. Repeated to High Coimnissioner, Cairo. High Commissioner, Trans-Jordania. H.M's Minister, Jedda. H.M^s Minister, Tehran. Government of India, New Delhi. Political Resident, -bushire. Consul-general, Beirut. No. 42. lotted 9th received 10th November 1932. I reached Baghdad November 8th accompanied 'by my three diplomatic secretaries. I presented my credentials to King this morning. / Humphrys. o^1 Goveriraent of India. 5breign and Political Department. axpHBss I&gt;h:TT5R (AIR miL) * Ho .D. 4535-H/32. Dated Sew Delhi, the // ' November 19 32. To l^trl Secretary of State for India, London* A Reference Bushire letter Ub .792-3 of 1932, dated the 19th ictober 1932. Enquiry by His /Jfejesty King Faisal as to his visiting ne Arab States in the Persian Gulf. • We are generally in agreement with Political Resident's views. • •. •. • TH3 ISSUB OF TH3 ABOVE HAS BE5N AOTHORISSD. Sd.R.H*3urnett. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Copy for information to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3y order, e to., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, (copy sent to Kuwait under P.L.No.873-3 of 25th Novr»193^;.pfttl -U tM, ^ fvu^. vv ^ ^ 13 \ OIL FROM MOSUL WORK ON THE PIPE-LINE DESERT ENTERPRISE From Our Special Correspondent AMMAN, TRANSJORDAN The construction, which has just been begun by the Iraq Petroleum Company, of a pipe line to bring oil from the Mosul oilfield to the Mediterranean is one of the most important projects of its kind which have yet been under taken. It involves laying heavy steel pipes over a distance of nearly 1,200 miles, a great part of which lies in rocky and waterless desert. A little imagination is required to realize what this means. The pipes, each of which weighs nearly a ton, have to be hauled by motor- transport to wherever they have to be laid. When engineers are constructing a road they follow the easiest gradients and avoid incon venient obstacles. Not so the constructors of a pipe-line. They have to work straight forward. Consequently the tractors which haul the pipes TUB. Ae^na^-^rttta^ ''^JeshKhibur h &gt; \ {Mosul; have to go up hill and down dale, over rocks and into deep nullahs, following a line drawn on a map. Every 10 yards they have to stop and drop a pipe, and when their load is finished they have to go back over the same road and fetch another. With every trip their journey lengthens, until they may be plying backwards and forwards over more than 100 miles of desert between the base-camp and pipe- head. When the pipes are strung, gangs of men dig a trench in which to bury them. Digging a trench through solid rock or loose boulders is no easy job. It calls for explosives and pneumatic drills. Then come the welding gangs, which join the pipes together and lay them in the trench. They need electrical plant and cranes to handle the pipes. All this plant is not stationary, but constantly shifting over difficult ground. The gangs of men need stores and water, the tractors need petrol, oil, and spare parts, and all this in the heart of a desert. About 120,000 tons of pipe have to be moved under these conditions, and a preliminary to it is the laying of 1,000 miles of light telephone over the track to be followed, so that the work ing parties can always be in communication with their headquarters. Already there are 6,000 men at work. By the middle of next year there will be 20,000. Ten million pounds is spoken of as the probable cost.14 immense machine, driven by a brawny American, which churns along at about a mile an hour, leaving a trench 3ft. deep in its wake. Its work has to be supplemented by gangs of men with pneumatic drills and explosives to deal with the solid rock. After them come the welding gangs, which, with the help of a varied apparatus of cranes on caterpillar wheels and weld ing plant fed from equally mobile generat ing units, join the ton-weight pipes to gether in sections of five or six at a time and lower them into the trench. Trenching and welding gangs both work from a big canvas camp situated at Taiyibi, where the plateau begins to break away into the valley of the Jordan. Here are gathered together a hard-bitten band of men, British and American specialists accustomed to coping with waste places and gangs of native labour in the remotest corners of'the earth. They are a race apart, intent on their work and apparently indifferent to their surround ings, true sons of Martha. Presently, when they have welded and earthed their pipe over a section of 30 miles or so, they will strike their camp and move on to another pitch farther on in the desert as unconcernedly as if they were laying a water main in a London suburb. BRITISH SUPPLIES Being an international concern, the Iraq Petroleum Cooipany has distributed its orders for material for use on the pipe line to British, American, and Continental manufacturers. Messrs. Stewarts and Lloyds, Limited, are supplying a large section of the pipe-line, and orders have been placed with British manufacturers for different types of heavy six-wheeled motor-lorries. CHINESE BUDGET BALANCED FINANCE MINISTER'S REFORMS from our correspondent SHANGHAI, D ec . 21 The Budget of Mr. T. V. Soong, the Finance Minister, is a creditable proof of his firm handling of expenditure since he resumed the office last January, when owing to the exhaustion of the patience of the bankers, the credit of the Chinese Government was at its lowest. The reduc tion of the machinery of taxation to three main departments, the abolition of likin and the institution of the nucleus of Civil Service have helped in bringing about the improvement. The anti-civil war movement also has assisted in keeping down military expenditure. China's financial future depends on the avoidance by the Government of internal and external complications. Although the Communists have been cleared from Hupeh, they are reforming in Kansu and Shensi, and may become troublesome unless the recent resumption of Chinese- Soviet relations be used to consolidate Nanking's victories over the Reds. Still, the mere fact that the Budget is balanced and has improved the standing of Chinese securities is commendable, especially in the light of the desperate financial position a year ago. CHINESE AMBASSADOR TO THE SOVIET Mosrov^uu iu,0; ' •'-The Soviet r,r*\&gt;prr&gt;. 40-RATm COIV CRE fron The { to 40 a ment ha Body Organiz confere, January confere nationa For the the I.L (' Hour 5s.) des possibil ment '1 method; effected, authorit and, fin: national the pres Exce{ some ir by redu dischar^ cussion wage n volume, out, firs duced 1 wages h —in nu reduced has bee tionate next, tl made t because tions, C to regu Neve nationa be indi portanc desirab recomn tion of the wo differer recomn G Two report, fact and reductio aspects ( the cha rcgulatic ' In i doubt b as the e difficult to ignor in proli Unless : to gainf who arc the ecor combim as satis siderabi is depri to the d duces is cussion? of the r considei discussitThe establishment of Ui^ s organiza tion for the task has caused some stir in the Middle East. At Baghdad, as well as at Haifa and Tripolis, the two Mediterranean termini of the line, people are speculating on what this enterprise will mean—what wealth it will bring to these ports, and how far the barren country whifch the line traverses will be opened up for the future. The Arabs whose territory it touches must be wondering, too ; but they keep their thoughts to themselves. For the present they are clearly satisfied that it brings them work and money. The line starts from near Kirkuk in the oil field and runs south-west to the Tigris, crossing that river at Fatha, not far from Baiji, the rail head of the Tigris railway. Thence it con tinues to Haditha on the Euphrates. Here the line divides, and the northern or French fork runs almost due west into Syrian territory to end at Tripolis, while the southern or British fork continues south-westward into Transjordan until about 37deg. E., where it turns north eastward. It crosses the Jordan about 20 miles south of Lake Tiberias and reaches the sea near Haifa. Work has been begun simultaneously from four bases—from Kirkuk, from Fatha»on the Tigris, using the Tigris railway, from Mafrak in Transjordan on the Hejaz railway, and from Tripolis. The first two gangs are working west ward. When the Kirkuk gang reaches the Tigris it is to leap-frog over the Fatha gang and continue along the northern fork until it joins hands with the party working from Tripolis. Meanwhile the Fatha gang will continue along the southern fork until it meets the Mafrak party. A REMOTE CAMP On a recent visit to the Mafrak camp I found the work going ahead steadily. The camp lies in the middle of a great plateau as flat as a table-top. To the north are the blue ranges of the Jebel Druze; to the north-west—a good 80 miles away—the snow-capped ridge of Her- mon, but to the east the plain seems to stretch indefinitely. There is nothing to break the sky line but a string of camels making their way down to the Hejaz, or a distant trail of dust showing where one of the company's tractors is ploughing its way out to pipe-head with its load of pipes. A few months ago Mafrak was nothing but a spot on the map and a railway station, but now there is a great compound full of huts, offices, stores, and motor repair-shops, and all that is required to maintain a popula tion of several hundred men. From it the pipes and the telephone line stretch east and west side by side. Just beyond the horizon to the east begins the lava-belt, the most difficult area which the line has to traverse. For more than 100 miles the plain is formed from the ejections of an ex tinct volcano, which appear in places as solid basalt, in others as loose boulders of all sizes up to a cubic yard. Even when a rough track has been cleared the surface is a merciless test for wheeled vehicles, something like what a fresh patch of road metal, unground by the steam roller, represents for a bicycle. Over this the 10-wheel Scammell tractors with their immense balloon tires bump their way slowly day after day, carrying their 10 tons of pipes, clouds of fine lava dust eddying from under their wheels at every lurch and smother ing the eyes, noses, and ears of their crews. The pipes are now strung well half-way through this area, and a water-line has also been laid for about 30 miles to supply the pumping station H.5, which will be situated in the middle of the belt. This will be the last of the pump ing stations on the southern fork, and will send the oil on its final stage across the Jordan valley and to the sea. Westward from Mafrak cultivation soon begins and the line runs over rolling country which produces the best wheat in Transjordan. Following the string of pipes one comes upon a crowd of Arab villagers gazing in awe at an »ment has couseiiie6 10 the appointment of Dr. Yen Hui-ching [W. W. Yen], the Chinese representative at the League of Nations and the Disarmament Con ference, as Chinese Ambassador in Moscow,— Renter. Dr. W. W. Yen represented China in the exchange of letters at Geneva on December 12 with M. Litvinoff, the Soviet representative, by which diplomatic relations were restored between China and the Soviet. ORDERS FOR BRITISH ENGINEERS PETROL STORAGE TANKS FOR PALESTINE The Whessoe Foundry and Engineering Company, Limited, of Darlington, and the Motherwell Bridge and Engineering Company have jointly secured a contract for petrol storage tanks at Haifa, Pales tine, for the Iraq Petroleum Company, Limited. The contract is worth £160,000 and was secured in the face of world wide competition. Manufacture is to be at Darlington and Motherwell and will entail the use of 8,000 tons of British steel. It was announced yesterday that the Birtley Company, Limited, ironfounders and engineers, of Birtley, County Durham, have secured three orders for coal-cleaning plant, valued at £40,000. The orders are for the Dawdon Colliery] Durham, owned by Londonderry Collieries, Limited, Czechoslovakia, and Holland. The Birtley Company describe this year as a record, as since January the number of employees have doubled. INFLUENZA EPIDEMIC IN AMERICA from our own correspondent NEW YORK, D ec . 21 Influenza, in a comparatively mild form, is spreading rapidly through the Southern States and is beginning to pene trate the middle Atlantic and New England States, Only in the Far West and South-West, where the epidemic began, is it on the wane. The Federal Public Health Service announced to-day that reported cases of the disease now numbered 33,823, as against only 3,086 a month ago. It esti mated the total number of cases at 10 times that figure, most cases going un reported either because they are treated at home or because men and women in this time of unemployment are unwilling to risk losing their jobs by taking sick leave. THE BULGARIAN CABINET from our correspondent SOFIA, D ec . 21 Just as M. Mushanoff was about to present the formal resignation of the Cabinet to the King in order to get rid of M, Dimitri Varbenoff (Agrarian), who has refused to resign the Ministry of Justice at the Prime Minister's request, the Agrarians intimated that they wished to have one of their number appointed to the Ministry of Communications, which is at present held by M, Stoyan Kostourkoff (Radical). They offered to surrender, in exchange, their reversion to the Ministry of Education, which is being vacated by M. Constantine Mouravieff (Agrarian), who is about to return to the Diplomatic Service. It is feared that this move may precipitate a Cabinet crisis. CONSCIENCE MONEY The Chancellor of the Exchequer acknowledges the receipt of £10 from O.A.P.P.Z.705/33. IRF REWMNCY. //V' flONfiOWTiAi neoosw; ^REIGN OFFICE, S.W.I. (E 461/461/91) 3rd February 1933. My dear Lalthwalte, f As I toldorally, on receiving your official letter No.P.Z.7097/32 of the 7th December about possible visits by King Feisal to the Arab States of the Persian Gulf, we considered that there was objection in principle to such visits and felt inclined to suggest to you that this should be made clear to the Political Resident, but wished to consult Humphrys on the subject. I understood from you that you thought the India Office would probably agree with such a suggestion, if we made it. I now enclose copies of our letter to Humphrys and his reply, from which you will see that, while agreeing that, in principle, such visits should be discouraged, he thinks unfortunately that it may be aifficult for him to put Feisal off a visit to Koweit, and assumes that the Political Resident will try to prevent the Sheikh of Koweit encouraging such a visit. Will you let us know what the India Mffice think on the subject and what instructions they would propose to send to Fowle, in order that we may write to Humphrys? I write semi-ofXicially as I understand from Johnstone that this will suit you best at your end. Yours ever, (Sd.) GHRISTOPHiiH Laithwaite, iisq. COPY SENT TO. (Copy with copy of encloBuree sent to Kuwait under P.L.N0.199-S of 3/3/33)son.- (E 6535/6054/91) POHEIGN OPFI 02, 3.W. 1. 29th December 1932. W dear Humphrys, I see that Fowle sent you cilrect a copy of his despatch to India No.792-S of the 19th October, ahout King Pelsal's recent enquiries on the subject of possible visits by him to the Arab States of the Persian Gulf. Powle proposes to treat each case on Its merits, when It arises; and trie Governruent of India have expressed agreement. But we here are disposed to think that any visit by King Feisal to one of these States would be in India principle undesirable. The/Office, we understand semi officially, are inclined to agree. There seem to us to oe various inalcations that King Feisal wishes to try to bring Kowelt gradually into closer connexion with Iraq, and that he would favour anything which would tend toward an agglomeration of Arab States under his own aegis. As regards Kwelt, it has been laid down by the C,I,D. as recently as 1929 that 'as regards Koweit, it is better on the whole that-—while endeavouring to secure so far as possible that Kowelt shall not be identified with Iraq, we should defer the establishment of a formal protectorate until circumstances appear-j^to .make this more clearly deblrable.' You will see then that our view is entirely against any closer connexion between Iraq and Koweit. As regards the trucial Sheikhdoms, a visit by King Feisal would, it seems to us, be highly embarrassing in view of the traditional policy of allowing them no direct contact with foreign Powers. J We/ tcellency 31r Francis Humphrys, GGMG., GCVO., 1^3iii., o ., etc., o tc., etc 1■■ an We feel, therefore, that it would he well to lay uowri deiinltely that any desire of King Feisal to visit the Arah States of the Gulf should he firmly discouraged# It would, of course, he for consideration, if the case arises, whether such discouragement could he administered without risking a disproportionately serious political reaction, out it might very well he desirable for the Resident or yourself to have a definite ruling to go on that in principle H.M. Government are against such visits, as inmediate action would prohahly he required. I should therefore he grateful to know your views on this matter before discussing it further with the India Office. Yours, etc. (Sd.) GEORjrlii KENDEL. (Intd.) G.F.A.W.l1« © (E 461/461/91) (72/2/33) British iSinbassy, Bagdad. 11th January 1933 dear Renael, Please refer to your letter E 6535 /6054 /91 of the 29th Decuiiiber on the subject of possible visits by King Faisal to the Arab States of the Persian Gulf» I agree that, in principle, such visits should be firmly discouraged unless there is some very special reason for making an exception. In the case of the Trucial shaikhdoms, it should not be difficult for me to dissuade King Faisal from carrying out any intention he migjit have of paying them a visit. The case of Kuwait seems to me to be on a different footing and, though I am personally against the establishment of any closer connection between Kuwait and IraQ than exists at present, it will obviously be much more difficult to convince King Faisal of the justice of our claim that Kuv ^iit is out of bounds for him. You will remember that the Shaikh of Kuwait paid King Faisal a visit in Bagdad last summer, while I was absent in Europe, and it might be claimed by Faisal that it would be discourteous on his part not to return the visit. Then there is the interminable question of the date gardens, and the prevention of smuggling from Kuwait into 'Iraq which has lately assumed rather serious proportions. The Director ol Customs recently told me that he estimated that more than £60,000 worth of goods had been smuggled into 'Iraq from Kuwait during the past year, and that a member of his staff had been shot dead in an affray with Kuwaiti smugglers. It/ i&amp;NDEL, ESQ., C.M.G.matfti iii l r i ni 17$ It is true that both these matters are not proper subjects for King Faisal to tackle personally, hut it might not he easy to put him off a visit to Kuwait for the ostensible purpose of arranging a settlement of such outstanding questions, though the real object of the visit would undoubtedly be political, while, therefore, I should like to be Instructed to use my Influence to preverfc the King paying a return visit to Kuwait, I assume that every endeavour will b^made at the other end to prevent the jjhalkh himself encouraging the Idea should the question arise. Yours, etc., (Sd.) F.H. HUMPHRYS. i ►icobfrid^jjitial. Tm khisiukkcy, D.O.Ho.id^ti-S of 1935. Bush ire, the 17 th karcn 1955, / v . Please refer to Foreign Office letter No461/461/ 91, of 5rd February iy35, to the India Office, on the subject of a possible visit of Kin^ jPeiaal to the Arab States of the Persian Gulf, and connected correspondence. 2. Vith regard to the States other than Kuwait, I daresay arguments can be found with which His Lajesty rn^y be discouraged from visiting them - should he des- re to d d so. &gt;•1° 3. Vith regard to Kuwait, personally 1 a ^ree with Humphrys f views, as expressed in his letter of 11th Janutry, that it would be difficult to convince King Faisal that .:uwFit was out of bounds for him. It will also be far from easy for me to 'discourage' the shaikh, should King Faisal at any time make a definite proposal to nim as to a visit. -he only way I could effect tne necessary discouragement would be to inform the Shrikh that we objected to His Majesty visiting him. The Shaikh in order to cover himself,I according to his own story, vide enclosure to my letter 1 o. ^ of i9tn. October lust, he has already informed the King that tne latter would be welcome as an unofficial guest), would of course inform the King of ray advice. His Majesty would be huffed, the Shaikh embarrassed, and our opposition mi^ht wall giva the visit a fictitious importance which it rni^ht otherwise not possess. V H.: .F.Metcalfe, iiad., C.I.S., M.V.O., Foreign Secretary to the overnmei t of India, New Delhi.-2- n ■ 4. I quite concur with the Foreign Office opinion (vide .^endel's letter of 2yth December VJ32) that there are various indications that King Feisal would like to bring Kuwait into closer connection with •Iraq, and with the Foreign Office view that such closer connection is undesirable, but as under the engagement of 1914 with the iihaiich of Kuwait M the Principality of Kuwait is recognized as an independent Principality' U.GM3, page 84, paragraph 46), I do not think that a visit of His Majesty to Kuwait can affect this independence to any appreciable extent# The visit should, however, be a private one, and - as the bhaikh himself has already informed the King that a private, and not an official, visit would be welcome - there should be no difficulty about this. b, I suggest therefore that I instruct Dickson to take a suitable opportunity of informing the Shaikh in the course of conversiition that should the question of the King making a visit to Kuwait 'arise*, (it is not improbable that His majesty mi^ht write directly to the Shaikh on the subject), we have no objection, provided - as the Shaikh himself hrs stated - that the visit is a private one, but that naturally - in view of the special relations which Kuwait has with His Majesty 's Government - any proposal of a visit must come through the proper official channel,i.e. the Ambassador at Bagdad. I have no doubt that this message to the Shaikh will find its way to King j? 1 eisal, and may perhaps form a salutary reminder to the latter that we have a special position vis a vis Kuwait. Should His Majesty then propose a visit he will have to do it through British oilicial channels, /cnannels, wiiich means tJmt He will ipso facto recognize our relations with Kuwait. i suggest that we on our side make no difficulties if the proposal is actually made by the King, but treat it as a matter of no prrticular importance, lettins; it be generally known that His Majesty is merely visiting Kuwrit privately in return for the visit which the Shaikh paid him last year. I am sending copies of this letoer to liump^irvs and Laithwrite.I ^7A Confidential , D.C ,No:C/124. itical Agency, Bahrain,the 25th March 1933. hfvAji. (Lt^S ' ^ ^ ^) With reference to our conversation during my recent visit to 1.Letter dated 21st February 1933 from H.B.M 's Consulate,Baghdad,to the Political Agency,Bahrain. 2.Letter No:C/123 dated 25th March 1933 5 Bushire,! from Lieut Colonel Gordon Loch,Political5 Agent,Bahrain,to C.Empson Ssquire, I enclose H.B.M's Consul,Baghdad. 1 j a copy of the marginally noted letters which have passed between me and the Consul at Baghdad on the subject of statistics about motor cars. 0 rhe Hon'ble Lieut Colonel T.C.W.Fowle ,C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. *1 Vt V/J ^ r i- * »Confidential , D.O, 'o:C/123» Political V^rency, ahrain,the 26th arch 1933# My dear Empson, ill you kindly refer to your letter dated the 1 Ist February 1933 about statistics of motor vehicles in 1 ahrain• r*. I am asking' the ahrain 'overnment to ^ive me such firuree as they have. Jn the ^e^ntime I am writing to sry that, /hile am only too frlad to place at your disposal :iy information /ou r ay want for commercial purposes,! hope that you will not include Bahrain in any reports about 'Iraq,as it would be inadvisable to do so, having re-ard to the independent position of Bahrain. Yours sincerely, lops on esquire, *8 Consul, Baghdad, Sd/- G.Loch,vv-f Forwarded with th Secretary, Political Department, India Office. •USHIPF ^E^DfNCY. a a Pllt.. sgmwitu,, 4eq0k08 India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W. 1..0. No. X1772/33. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 6th April 1933. 1 \V.1 We sent to you {and to Bushire) by the air mail of 10th February copy of a demi-official letter frcm the Foreign Office dated 3rd February, No.E.461/461/91, covering correspondence with Humphrys on the subject ol possible visits by King Feisal to the Arab states of the Persian Gulf and setting out the Foreign Office views on the subject. We entirely share the views of the Foreign Office and agree that it is desirable in principle that such visits should be discouraged. In the case of Koweit the position, as Humphrys points out, is less easy than in other cases, for His Majesty would probably in practice have little difficulty in finding a pretext for a visit. In all the circumstances, the best course seems to oe that the Resident and the Political Agent, Koweit, should, as Humphrys suggests, do what they can to prevent the Sheixh himself encouraging the idea should the question arise. I am sending a copy of this letter to Fowle. Yours sincerely. The Hon'ble Mr .H. A. F.Metcalfe , C.I.E., M.V.O. , Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department.D.O.Bo.D. 1277-11/33, hot drlhi, The /3® April 1933, ft , Please refer to Bowie's deai -official )\1^ letter Jfo .2a8-3 of 1933, dated the 17th torch 1933, on tne subject at possi'ble Tlslte lay King Faisal to the Arab States of the Persian Oulf, copy of which was sent to you direct, 2. we agree generally with Bowie's Tiews. Since he thinks that it will ce far frco easy for niM to discourage the Sheikh of Kuwait, should Kinf Faisal at any Clme aake a definite proposal to him for a visiti fe con si aer tiitst the euggewtion made in paragraph 5 of his letter would prove a good solution of this rather awicwfird. situation. In our opinion a private visit arranged through us need have no important political reactions* a refusal to permit Tlalt whether conveyed rar*aalJLjr tiirougti His Majesty's Ambassador or through the Sheikh informally would give the whole affair quite unnecessary prominence. therefore recommend that if the Secretary of State sees no objection ^owle2Z/19 •0 .1 Telegram X From H.E.M.'s Ambassador, Bagdad. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 5. Dated 2nd ( received 3rd) May 1933. King Feisal left to-night for Basrah for 3 days * 't and may possibly suggest visiting Kuwait in his yacht Kearchus. _ HUMEHRYS - Telegram From To Repeated X Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Government of India,Foreign and Political -Oepart ment, Simla. No. 351. Dated the 3rd May 1933. beings: Addressed Kuwait repeated Foreign. Correspondence ending with my Printed letter 447-S of 29th April. Following from Ambassador Bagdad dated 2nd May w King Feisal Nearchus' Ends.tumrn v i 23/19 Telegram XX. 'Prom foreign Secretary to the Goverrirnent of India, Simla . To Political ^enideht, Bufihire. Repeated Political Agent, Km/ait. Secretary of State for India, London. Ko. 1131. Dated (and received ) 4th May 1933. IMMKDIA m E. Your telegram of 3rd instant, TTo. 351. TOTTG FAISAL'S VISIT « ^0 KUWAIT. You are authorised to tal&lt;e action as suggested in Fowlers letter of the l^th Tiarch, ^o. of 1933. -tohbigh. No. 1131. Telegram XX. 'From Political Resident, Bub hire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 353. Dated 4th May 1933. IMMKDIA frr R. Government of India telegram of 4th May, Pleasetake action accordingly.letter to the Indie Office and of the aoet recent letter from the Indie Office to the Oovemaent of c ^ 0 ^^479-3 a of 0 9/5/3?^ a ^^« 447-S of 29/4/33.ru? 11 C0H7IDBNTIAL. No. 91. From POLITICAL AGrENCY, KUWAIT. , pu8h1w c restcxtncy. ^ 9t j 1 jjgy 193a4 Am -i oonfioential h600808 Lt # «Colonel H.R.P.Dioksoii, C.I.E., I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hoi^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . King Faisal's proposed visit to Kuwaiti Sir, ,/)./ Will you please refer to yoxir telegram No.353, dated the 4th May and immediately preceding telegram from Foreign Simla (No»1131, dated the 4th May 1933) • I have the honour to make the foil owing report on the action, which I took next day in the matter, and the re percussions my words had on the Shaikh. S # As the Shaikh was in camp on the 5th May and it did not appear likely that he would come in to the Town, it being Friday, I sent for his Confidential Secretary and explained fully and carefully that should King Faisal, con trary to my expectation suddenly express the wish, whilst in Basra, or ever in future suggest a visit to Kuwait, His Majesty's Government wished His Excellency to understand tint they (His MaJesty^s Govemment) would raise noobjection to such visit, provided (a) that the visit was a private one; (b) that any proposal of a visit should come througki the proper channel i.e. the Ambassador in Baghdad. This in Triew of the special rslationa whioh Kuwait had uith- 2 - 4^7) With His Majesty*s Government# 3 # The Shsiiklis* Secretary, a shrewd and clever Tn*m said he quite saw Government's point of view, and would see that my message reached the Shaikh without fail, 4« On Saturday evening I was dining, together in company with the Shaikh with Mr.Chisholm of the A.P.O^C. After dinner I took the opportunity of taking the Shaikh aside and personally explained with sane tact, what His Majesty^ G-ovemment*s views on the matter were, and I repeated what I had told his Secretary the previous day. 5 # The Shaikh, scmewhat to my surprise, replied as follows, •Mf you mean that I am to inform King Faisal of what you have told me, should he ask to visit my State, why, then you are mistaken: Such action is entirely your Government's business# The reply I shall send will be ♦Your Majesty is welcome and doubly welcome*, any other course would be unfriendly and not in accordance with Arab ideas of hospitality n » 6. As I did not consider the Shaikh's reply parti cularly satisfactory, I decided to inform him, by official letter, of His Majesty's Government instructions in this matter# This was done on 8th May# 7. In the meantime King Faisal has made no move in the matter, nor do I think he has any intention of coming to Kuwait this Summer# 8# In mentioning the Shaikh's rather stupid' reply to me, I would remind you of the various letters, which I have written frcm time to time (especially those dealing with Oil questions) with regard to the ppparently growing tendency of the Shaikh not to accept my advice and counsel as he should do# 9# The Shaikh, I do not think, would have answered me/fV - 3 - me in the way he did, some months,back, and though I say it reluctantly, I cannot but put down this change in his conduct to the bad teaching which he has received from Major Holmes. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, v Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent,KuwaitT).0. Ho. 837-8 of 1933 Th« Hentdcncy, Bushlre, the 23rd May 1933 Is P Please refer to eorrespondence endlnp with Oorernnent of India telegraw Ho. 1131 of 4th May 1933. on the duhjeot of Klni* Tfalaal vlBltlng Kuwait. Tha threatened Tlalt did not take place, hut T*ien Tllcteon approached the Shaikh, on the llnee augpeated In ay demi-official letter Ho. 228-3 of 17th March 1933, the latter said that. If King Faisal ever augpested to him a rlslt to Kuwait, he- the Shaikh - would be unahle to answer that the King should first put the proposal through the proper chainels! all the reply that he oould pend^ according to Arab Ideas of honpltalltyjwould be 'welooBa* It waa 'up to' us to approach His Majesty on the subject if we Baw fit. j&gt; # VThile paBBinfc through Kuwait recently on return from London I mentioned the matter to the Shaikh, itio repeated what he had already tolc* T)ic v son. I did not eec my way to preBB the matter# At the sane ^ine I think it important that King Faisal should realise that Ituwait/ H.A.I 1 , Metcalfe, Ksq., K.V.O., lb reign Secretary to the OoYernmert of India, Simla.Kuwait 1b In sneclnl relations rfith tia # and that he should not vlsi 4 ^ It ufcthout an intimation to that effect to the Amhaafsado^. Tn these clrcunstaroeo the onlr course would seem to be for Humuhr/s, If he saw no objection, to convey the necessary advice to His ;^ajesty. s ' X an scntflnr eonicf of this letter tn the 'muassy at Baprtad an^ to &gt;he Xndia ft'lce.'v- CONFIDENTIAL. No. 5 3«-S of 1933. The Hon'bfe the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to His Majesty's Anbassador, Baghdad, T. G. Laithwaite, Ksq., The India Office, London, Lt.-Colonel H.l.''. 'Oickson, C.I.I',, ^litical Ap-ent , TCtm a it, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ^ British Residency and Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. cf c t Dated... . Hay.. 1933.. Reference to previous correspondence : Governr^ent of India ''eleoran No, 1131 of 4th May 1933. Description of Enclosure. 'n.O. letter JTo. 531-3, dated J?3rd May 1933, to the '?oreipn Secretaiy to the OovemTnent of India, SiTnla . ^ossihle visits 'by Kinp: Faisal to Kuwait,|/ Cj- POLITICAL AGENCY, 110 • 100 • _ KXTfTAIT. ( &gt;' f'Dated the 20th May If53, '7^ ' hi till From a V:';-,7. I./ - — To Lt.-Colonel H.R.P^Dickson, C.I # E., I.A,, Political Agent, Kuwait; The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. BUS H I R 3 . Oi(i i King Faisals visit to Kuwait. Sir, I have the honour to enclose, for your records, copy of my Confidential letter No.92,dated the 9th May 19o3, to .lis Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait intimating the wishes of His Majesty's Government, should His Majesty King Faisal express a desire to visit Kuwait at any time. 2* The above is in continuation of my Confidential letter No.91, dated the 8th May 1935. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, r ' Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait. 7SS- 8 - Ir^ L r ;l ^ I i-J Xr of H1# Majesty King msal, but In ^ it* 1 iAnJi Qf tho special relations wbloh 4*u^i — * * ■ l -^ ^ ml^ u* t 2^1 (1j ■ &lt;: • 4 . -. . .. (w) «-*ujl l+~*~ yi (^/ujl ^lu'v^ j j 4j exist between Kuwait and His Majesty's GoTernment, they would like the follow- * well ing to be/understood:- (a) That any suoh visit should be a private one. (b) That any proposal of suoh visit should ooiae through the proper official channels, i.e. the British -iobassador,Baghdad, and the Hon^le the Political Resident. • f 1/^*1 JkU J yfi* This is what had to be said, and I remain with deepest respect etc. Lieut .-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000163_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/382</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000163</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/382</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 23/15, 19 I (D 89) Mesopotamia - General'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-29T15:45:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (219 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>A bound correspondence volume. The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled and can be found in the top right of the recto side of each folio. A second foliation sequence which is also written in pencil, but not circled, runs between ff 5-207. In addition to this, a very short sequence runs between ff 2D-4. Circled index numbers written in red crayon are also present in the volume.Foliation anomalies: 2A, 2B, 2C and 2D; 27A and 27B; 88A and 88B; 159A, 159B and 159C; 163A and 163B</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>All the contents of this file relate to Irak [Iraq] between 1918 and 1933.The file includes:A report of the killing of Mr J.H Bill (Indian Civil Service) and Captain K.R Scott (31st Punjabis, Indian Army) by a Kurdish tribal force near Aqrah in 1919 (f 7).A copy of a telegram sent to King Hussein of Mecca requesting one of his sons to be sent to occupy the throne of Iraq (f 27b).A letter from P.Z Cox, the British High Commissioner for Iraq to Winston Churchill, Secretary of State for the Colonies regarding the borders of Iraq (ff 50-52).A rough sketch map of the Nerva and Raikan districts of Iraq (f 54)A map of the Turco-Persian frontier (f 55)A cutting from
                              al awqaat al iraqiyya(The Times of Mesopotamia) containing full text (in English) of the Anglo-Iraq Treaty 1922 (f 64).A detailed report concerning the practicalities of travelling from Baghdad to London via Aleppo and Beirut (ff 79-83)A copy of the Anglo-Iraq Treaty of 1926 (f 104)Other matters discussed in the file include a proposed visit to Kuwait by King Faisal of Iraq, an idea for Iraqis to be sent for training to British consulates in the region and reports concerning the activities of 'anti-British' Persian clerics (
                           mujathids) in Iraq.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Raikan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Nērva</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000163#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>