<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00012d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:00:33.264Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential The Residency, D.O.N0.444-S of 1932 Bushire, the 1st July 1932$ I went down about three weeks ago to Shargah, hoping Meuo to find everything plain sailing; unfortunately this not the case. I had five days of interminable discussions with the Shaikh and even now he has not finally signed the agree ment. I was very much handicapped at the time by the fact that I did not take with me an Arab munshi as the Shaikh produced a most villainously worded letter which he wanted me to sign and also I was of course entirely in Isa’s hand and would have welcomed the assistance of some one like yourself who speaks Arabic as an Arab does. It is probable that I may have to go down again and if so I should be very grateful if you would see your way to accompany me. I have made no definite plans yet but in the ordinary course I should go down by fast mail to the Quoins and tranship to a sloop off there. In this event if I sent you a telegram could you join the mail at Basrah provided I was able to give you two or three days’ notice ? An alternative would be to get a flying boat to bring you down but I know you wu’eBfc. not care about flying and would prefer coming down by mail. Lt.-Col.H.R.P.Dickson,C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait.C OMTIDUNTIA L • D,0,Uo*n6 # Political Agency, Kuwait# Dated the 12th July 1932# I only received your D*0*No#444#3# dated 1st July late on Saturday evonlng the 9th of July. 3o I hope you will not think me casual for taking so long to reply. 2. I shall be delighted to asrlst you In anyway possible In your negotiations at Shargah, and can catch the fast mall from Basrah either on £&gt;aturday the 23rd July or Saturday 30th July, provided you will give me the 2 or 3 days 1 notice suggested by you. 3. I cannot very well get away this oaming ‘Saturday (16th July) because of the /oalr Faisal's visit. Ho Is here now, together with his brother the Amir l.ohomed al Abdul Aziz as-Saud and the Amirs Faisal and Turkl (grand sons of Bln Baud) who all arrived on the 11th from Rladh to greet their brother and escort him back home by overland^ 4. At present there Is no Immediate prospect of Faisal*s getting away before Sunday, as many of the cars, which have arrived for him are litterally on their last legs, and 7 of the drivers have gone into Basrah to buy spares etc. 5. They left last night and incidentally I hear their two care ' , orashed ,, near Bafwan. Hesouere have gone to help. 6. All is well here and Faisal's reminiscences, especially as regards Bussla, are most interesting. He ‘says he was more Impressed with what he saw there than in any other country. - 2 - The Hon'ble Lieu tenant-Colonel Bir Hugh Blscoe, K.B.S. , Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, Bushlre.AIR MINISTRY. ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, W.C.2. 25th July, 1932, Dear Dickson, I have just seen your wire of 23rd July saying that the agreement regarding the requirements at Sharjah had been signed; this is just a line to congratulate you on getting it signed so promptly. two days before he died I had a private letter from him giving me the Gulf news and hoping to get an agreement with the Sheikh as soon as he arrived, I hope his successor, whoever he may be, will follow in his footsteps, as in my opinion he did more to enhance British prestige in the Gulf than any of his predecessors. keeping with your position and better adapted to hot weather conditions. I hope to be out in Iraq by December, when I shall take the opportunity of visiting you at Koweit. Again, congratulations on the good work you have accomplished. Biscoe's sudden death was a great calamity. Only I trust by now you have a house at Koweit more in Please give my regards to Mrs. Dickson. Yours sincerely, /fuv V. Lieutenant Colonel H.H.P. Dickson, C.I.E Political Agent, Koweit. • *1 © / Confidential. D.O.No.516-S of 1932. THE HESIDE1JCY, Bushire, the 26th July 1932, £L/t CMuuJi I am forwarding to you herewith copies of correspondence and documents as under:- To enable you to take up story where P.R.left off. Copies of all these are with Government of India and Secretary of State for India, To report progress of work and your opinion re:lorry if you think fit, No copies of these are with Government of India and Secretary of State. X'N 1 0 1. P. R.’s Express letter No.400-S of 21st June 1932. 2. P. R.’s draft agreement. 3. P. R.’s draft letter of assurance to Shaikh. 4. P. R. f s last telegram to Government of India (No.411 of 14th July 1932;. 5. Copies of all telegrams between you and the Govern ment of India and the Secretary of State for India 6. Agreement signed. 7. Your letter to Shaikh. 8. Telegram from Mackay re: progress of work. 9. H * n re: lorry. 10. Your reply re: lorry. The important dates of the tour were:- 17th July, 18th • 19 th ' 19 th ' 20 th ' 21st ' P.R., you and I left Bushire in s.s. 'Vita”• Transhipped to H.M.S.'Bideford” off Tanb Island. 3.30.a.m. P. R. died before reaching Shargah. Went to Henjam. Met S.N.O. in 'Triad”• Buried P.R. at sea, about 6 miles out from 'Bideford' about noon. Left 10 p.m. for Shargah. Arrived Shargah, broke news to Shaikh. Returned Shaikh’s call ashore. Spent day ashore in Isa’s houselR.A^; discussions with Shaikh, etc. all day. 22md. Lt.Colonel H.R.P.Dickson,C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait•* 5 * V Agreement and letter drawn up in morning. Shaikh came aboard 2 p.m. Agreement signed 1920 hours. Went to supper with Shaikh^9 to 11 p.m. ^Left Shargah mid-night. Arrived Bushire. Copies of agreement and letter in English and Arabic have been sent by this air mail to Government of India and Secretary of State for India with remark that you are forwarding despatch at first opportunity. The despatch should be addressed to the Government of India and copy sent to the Secretary of State for India. #e would be glad of a copy here for record. I hope this is all the information you require. You mentioned that you would impress on Government the fact that it was of the British the Shaikh was afraid and that compared to them his fears of his people and other Shaikhs were only secondary. % r FYa I L I \ 13 . By Air Mall. V 'V Confidential • E X jp H E a a L E J 1‘ Ut, Tirom - The itolitioal heel dent in the Persian Gulf* To - The foreign Secretary to the Goverrraent of India# Simla* Copy to- H.il 1 #. Secretary of Statefor India# London. The Air Officer Commanding# Iraq Command# Baghdad. BO. 400-S of 1932. Buulilre, dated the 21st June 1932. 1 ^ Reference *y telegram Bo. T-77, dated the As 19th June 1932. Arabian Air Koute. Ab reported therein I have ^ust spent three days at Shargah. I met Colonel Day, Chief engineer. Iraq Command# there and ne discussed the arrangements that should be made for the construct ion of the rest house. According to the instructions he had received from the Air Ministry it was proposed that the rest house should be built by him out of Air jforce funds. We came to the conclusion# however# that it would be preferable that the building should be constructed by Aha the Shaikh and that he should receive rent for it as originally contemplated by me. In the first place it would in any case be necessary to work through the Shaikh. The rest house will be buAlt of stone and cement and the stone is only procurable from the islands off the Trucial Coast. It is necessary therefore to get the Shaikh to send out boats to fetch the stone and also to supply the requisite labour# transport, etc. Any outside contractor it uld find very great difficulty in arranging this.3* Farther, on political grounds 1 consider it very nuch preferable that the houee should he built by the Shaikh and he his property, rather than that the British Ooveraraent should build a fort in his territory. As His Bajesty^ Oo▼eminent are aware, the Sheikha of the Trucial Coast are rery apprehensive lest the estab- lishnent of the air station should involve the loss of their independence and interference in their internal affairs. The building which it is proposed to con struct is not an ordinary rest house such as exists at 3halka or at Jask but may ouch more aptly be described as a large fort with watch towers, parapets, firing step, loop holes, etc., a building of this nature constructed by the British trovemiient on the shaikh's territory would* I think, definitely increase his apprehensions and it is much better that the fcddk build ing should belong to him. 4. The Chief Kngineer informed me that while no aocunats estimate had yet been drawn up, it was calcula ted that the cost would not be less than £ b,e00. how the Shaikh cannot finance the construction of a building on this scale. 1 recommend, therefore, that the British Government should advance him such sums as he may require to pay for materials and labour and the Chief Kngineer will supply doers, window*, steel joists and corrugated iron sheets, #ilch are not obtainable locally. The work will be under the supervision of an officer of the Royal Bngineers and an Indian supervisor of the Koyal Air Force forks Department will be permanently located at Shargah until the work is completed. It is calculated to take about a year. I trust that His Maje8ty*s Government will approve of this arrangement and, if so, that they will authorise me to advance to the shaikh auch sums as may be necessary from time to time gp toI -A (/T&gt; a -3- Rb • 40^000 and to make an iamodlato adranoo of Ho* 10 9 000* A oe»n«igiraent of cement baa just arrlted at Debal and it is Tory desirable that the shaikh should purchase the amount required without delay as it is not always obtainable. Further adranoes would only be giren after the superrlsor had certified that it wao necessary. It will # of course c be essential to keep the Shaikh with some money in hand, The site for the rest house was selected by the Chief kngineer in consultation with Lieutenant Commander Calpin of Imperial Airways 9 a representative of the Royal Air Force and Commander Harding, R.H. It is on the edge of the aerodrome so that machines will taxi straight into a barbed wire enclosure adjoining the rest house. 5. I went to Shargah hoping thatthere would be no difficulty in concluding a final agreement with the Bhaikh. Unfortunately my expectations were not realised, and the Shaikh's brother of whom he stands in great fear, were still maintaining an obstructivs attitude, despite the fact that the Shaikh had promised them a large portion of the subsidy. 6. IMrwtJy, 'Very great pressure continues to be brought to bear on them from Debai to obstruct the establishment of the air station and the Residency Agent informs me that they receive daily four or five letters from Debai, urging them not to yield in this matter, while emissaries from Debai are constantly in Shargah to ascertain how matters are progressing. The motive that actuates the people of Debai is, 1 believe, the fear that they may lose the mail steamer. Debai was formerly a smaller place than nhargah. It is now much larger and wealthier, simply and solely owing to the fact that the mail steamer calls there and it has become the emporium of the Trucial Coast. If the mail steamer called at Bhargah Instead there is little doubt that wmy/4 many of the merchant a would transfer their offices to feargah. The Ruling family of Debai derive a large income from house iproparty, which would ias^iately fall in value* It is not unnatural, therefore, that the people of Debai should do their utmost to retain the mail steamer* 7* The two points on which the discussions turned were, firstly, the guarantees regarding in dependence and non-interference and, secondly, the transfer of the mail steamer* I drafted a letter info 2 m- ing the Shaikh in general terms that the British Government would respect his independence and would not interfere in his intsmal affairs, he showed this to his relatives and they contended that this was inade quate and asked that the guarantee should be in a much more explicit and detailed form, namely, that there should be no Interference with his personal servants—* male and female — or with his divers and that no one should be allowed to take refuge in the rest house, etc* To all these points 1 was prepared to agree and 1 had repeatedly assured the Shaikh that Imperial Airways were entirely a commercial concern and that their employes would have no official position and that in fact their position would be analogous to that of the British India Steam Navigation Company’s representative at Debai* The Shaikhly families of the Truclal Coast are, however, quite the stupidest people with whom it has ever been my misfortune to deal —a country yokel from a remote village in Kngland or Scotland is a highly intelligent individual compared with a Truoial Shaikh,— and discussed for hours onong themselves as to whether the draft letter re Ally covered every conceivable point, etc*C' 3 &gt; V •m\) «• • to. Ah an example of their mentality, 1 may mention Xks that they ashed me to declare that the aerodrome would he a civil one and not a military one. 1 enquired whether this meant that military aeroplane* could not land on it. They replied that this was not their intention at all hut that if irt was declared to he a civil aerodrome then in the event of a war between Great Britain and torsi a, the tors lane would not he entitled to bomb it l It will, 1 think, he realised that it is exceedingly difficult aid wearing to the temper to argue with this type of mind. However, X had finally evolved a draft ifclch satisfied the ;&amp;alkh, also a letter regarding the za&amp;il steamer in which 1 said X would address the Company regarding the possibility of the mall steamer calling at 3hargah and would let him icnow the result, ana he said he would show it to his brothers and come off on the 17th morning to '^horeham* to sign the agreement, ne arrived on board and said they wanted one or two verbal alterations in the letter of guarantee and further that they insisted that Z should definitely undertake that the stall steamer should call at Sizar gad before he signed. X pointed out that it was quite impossible for me to give an under taking until X had referred the matter to the British Inaia nteam navigation Compahy. Bis ouselon ensued lasting several hours and finally the shaikh hurst into tears and said he was pleading for Ui» life and that if he signed without getting this undertaking he would certainly he murdered when he got ashore, lie said that he had told his brothc rs that they had blackened his fao&lt; and that he was ashamed to haggle with me in this manner and finally he said he was so wearied of the whole business/- 6 - busliuiss that he would leave tfeft town am let then do aa they pleaetd. Whether hie fears are justified 1 do ai not know hut there is not the snallest doubt that he Is extremely apprehensive and having regard th the frequency with which Shaikhs on the Crucial Coast are nurtlered by thrir relatives 1 think he veuld probably run sone risk* In any case despite ny assurances it was impossible to get hln to affix his signature to the agreement. 8* AM it was essential to avoid delay 1 told hin that I would refer the matter of the nail eteamer by telegram to the Government of India and to his majesty's Govemaent and asked him whether in the meanwhile he would start colle otlag material * This he assured m he would do without any delay and. 1 have asked the Heeidenoy Agent to keep him up to the mark* Purthrr he said we could, of course, send an engineer down and start the work as soon as we liked and that lie would be personally responsible for his safety* dille therefore the Inhabitants of live Trucial Coast cannot be expected to work with the rapidity ef contractor* in more civilised places, especially at this time of the year when many of the boats are away pearling, X hope that by the time the representative of the Chief Knglneer arrives at Shargah a good deal of material will have been collected and that he will be able to make a start* It is essential, however, that the nhuikh should be provided with funds and I therefore solicit tele graphic sanction to the payment to him of ils* 10,000* This money will be disbursed by the He si deucy Agent who will assure himself that the Ghalkh actually is Bending out boats, buying cement, etc* 9. If arrangements can be made for the mall steamer© v &lt;u &gt;7 ethaner « i ther to pay an additional oall at idtar«ad or to subotituto Bhargah for J*bal aa a port of oaJJL {Xtn former oourtio would bo proforadio if foanlblo)* thin thoro ou^it not to bo any further difficulty in gelUing the Bfcnikh to oi^n on agroonent owon if hie&gt; brother a should still proiro obotructivo, uh l think thoro will bo •o much preaeuro by the people of ftharnnh that the brothere will bo unable to reaiat it. should # however, thie not bo the ease then we atoll have to tovt reeort to more draatie mawurea. The no at influential of the mutlkh’a brottora i« rtoiich jiutoiiinart, who ie by tto aane mother and in a Mud; More forceful peraonality. m can not allow one sum tcjobatruct Uie air route and overawe the inhabitants and to be a constant focus of unrest in fthargah* and should he persist in thie attitude I think it will be necessary to depart him or order hin to reside outside iftmriph. 10. 1 enolaee herewith a translation of an agree ment wkiich 1 hope the shaikh will ultimately sign* Zt will be seen that 1 have increased the subsidy to ks. 3yl4d&gt; Sft,e00. Of this Increase Mu toSMW in accounted fbr by the pay of ten additional guards. 1 com icier that it Is deal ruble to have 56 instead of 86 as originally contemplated; tills increase Is the re fore automatic. The total mount payable for guards, therefore, now oocaes to lOt. 9,360. The rent for the rest house has been increased from Hs. 200 to He. 300 per mensem. The building is a large one and evtn mskltift allowance for the fact tiiat doors, windows, steel joists and corrugated iron sheets will be supplied by Ooveramnt it will probably coat the Hh&amp;ikh about He. 60,000. The rent therefore comes to about 7% on the outlay. This cannot be oo no Me red as excessive. He will however receive no rent for about ten years aim if this is deducted and also the/the wages of the guards the actual cash the Bhalich will receive in the near future will be only about is excessive. The flhqikh will have te subsidise five relations as well as Minor individuals ana will also have to kee? the beduin who levy blacknail on the True is 1 Shaikhs quiet. There have been lately a great arany oases of robberies on the Trucial Coast simply be cause the shaikhs nowadays art not in the position to make to the beduin their customary payment, with the result that these latter gentry carry off camels and rob wayfarers and carry them off for sale into the interior. Once it is know that the bhaikh of Sharg&amp;h is in receipt of a subsidy from the British Government he will be regarded as the capitalist of the coast and the demands Made on him will be greater than before. had coat in to call on the fthalkh and it cost him Hs. 58 and a square meal for the whole party to get rid of them and this state of affairs will increase, moreover the Shaikh will very definitely have put a pledge in pawn, as any Bedu who is not satisfied will be able to creep up to the vicinity of the rest house at night and fire a couple of shots somewhere in the direction of the gx rest house, not with aay idea of killing or Injuring anyone but simply to get the Shaikh into hot water. This sort of incident, while probably not likely to do much harm, is certainly calculated to alarm passengers and is just the sort Of thing that we want to avoid. 1 consider It essential, the refers, that the Shaikh should have funds to enable him to satisfy his relatives and to keep these Beduin quiet. He himself told me that for the first year or two at any rate he would derive little personal benefit from the subsidy Onr 11. The very day that X was at Shurgah 3&lt;$ beduin I think he is right, but if he can get the nail steamer then 1 do not think he will worry about this, ibater on.on # when the air station is definitely estahliehed and accepted he will doubtless he able to relax his pay ments to some extent 9 and will derive aoxse personal benefit • It will be seen that It is proposed to limit the agreement to 11 years, with the jjrovieo timt thr payments will only be made for suoh period as the facilities are utilised* The shaikh pressed very strongly for this, snd as I was anxious to make things easy for him and had been authorised to do so 1 accepted It* Personally I think it Is in our interests, as I think that in 11 years* time, provided we do not interfere more than is absolutely neoesaaxy in the affairs of the Truolal Shaikhs in general and those of flfaargah in particular, eveacy Shaikh on the coast will be asking for the air station to be transferred to his domain, and it will be possiblejtc^reduoc oon aider ably payments to the Shaikh of Shargah. SD/ H. V. B1SCQK, l.t*-Colonel, itolltlcal Hesideot in the Persian (lulf.Acmstmt mmmm iiiaiKE bultam xyljk vF I'll * aEUfitoi aov^aiia iarr fob tbjs isa^ABLiaK- ^«T OF AH ALci aiATIOH AT JiOU^AH. It having been Intimated to ma 9 ik|: ih&amp;llth t uit&amp;n hiH Ua^r 9 Lioutenant Oolonal Sir Hugh ^lsooa 9 i olitioal kmXamt in tha rertiiaa &gt;ulf 9 that the High British t^ovarmaant desire to estah* -Xish an air roote along the Arab Coast for the aeroplanes of the Imperial Airways Goap&amp;ny v heroineftar referred to as the Company )$ and that they wish to have an air station at ^h&amp;rg&amp;h at wnioh British aeroplanes oan land, I hereby agree to grant to the said Company the following facilities i - 1* The company may select a land- -lag ground at 3harg&amp;h 9 and may put on it such m&amp;rAs as are neow sary 9 and their aeroplanes may land on that ground* a* I will construct a rest house for the passengers and staff of the Company on a site to he seleoted by the Company and in aooordanoe with plans drawn up by them, and under the super- -vision of an Engineer of the British Government* a* The Company shall have the right to Import 9 free of duty, petrol and spare parts for aircraft 9 provis- -ions for the passengers and staff, and whatever may he required for their service. A. ihe Company *ti&amp;y fcumi their employee** to reside in the rest house* hut neither they nor the passengers shall enter the town of ^hargah without the permission of the Shaikh.2 \Y 1 furtbor aco®pt full responsibility for too protootion of tbo staff ana pass* *ong«rs of tb© Uompany axiO tfcxsir aircraft so far as ay depend.antst relativos and subject© are conoemedf and furtuer for their protection as far as possible against marauders from outside ay jurisdiction. 1 will supply bo goartts am 2 ueaa guards. In return for the above t it is agreed that the -British aovemiftent shall make ae the following payments a* (i) fay tor £5 guards and two chiefs at the-rate of ft* 20 p,m. for each guard and is. 40 p.m. for e&amp;oh of the two head guards, papaent to com* •Bence from the date the guards are appointed. (ii) lieat for the dir Station 800 p.nt,, payment to coBmence from the date the first ccwaffierolal aero- -plants lands. (UD h«nt for the Best House «s. 300 p «M« the Oovernment shall adranoe me by instalments such sums as may be oonsidered reasonable by the Engineer supervising the work for the construct* •ion of the building, and no rent shai: be payable to m© until all the sums advanced have been repaid. fhe 3everaffi6nt will supply doors, windows and steel joists and corrugated iron. (iv) for the responsibility that I have accepted, a personal subsidy of i** dOO p.».. to oomaenoe from tst July 1932. ^v) A landing fee of h* 5 for syary commercial aeroplane that lands on the anvsyte aerodrome. Ho charge shall be m^de for aeroplanes belonging to the Hoyal Air Faroe• The Jompany and their employees shall not deal direct with the ahaikh.tovt througli tba ,\mUXena'$ Ag-snt or Volitical Kaaiaaot. Thia agreaitent shall be for eleven years hut jaysante will only he aade tor so long as tho facilities are utilised.In connection with the agreement for the aerodrome at Shargah which you have signed, you have expressed a fear lest the establishment of an air station might involve inter ference with your independence and freedom. I therefore write to inform you that the British Government will respect your indeperidenoeand complete freedom and will not interfere in your internal affairs or with your servants, male or female, or your divers. Further the representatives of the Company residing in Shargah will have no official position, but will be representatives of a commercial firm. And no evil doers shall be allowed to take refuge in the rest-house. Further the guards shall be entirely under your orders, and you will be entitled to forbid any of your people to enter the rest-house, except the employes and servants of the company and persons sent by the Residency Agent. And if, which God forbid, any incident should occur, the British Government will not exact punishment except after enquiry and investigation, and the punishment of your subjects will be with you. But if the offence has been committed by persons from outside your jurisdiction you will do your best to tace them, but punishment will be with the High Government. Finally, ^am glad to inform you that it has been arranged that the mail steamer shall call at Shargah. I hope that this will bring prosperity to you and your people.Telegram: From: To: Repeated: No.411. R. 27. Political Resident, Bushire Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla# Secretary of State for India,London# Dated 14th July 1932. My telegram No#408, of 13th July. ARAB AIR ROUTE, l have just received letter from British India Steam Navigation Company, Calcutta, saying that they are willing to arrange fortnightly call at Shargah in addition to Debai* I therefore propose to give Shaikh formal assurance on subject and am leaving for Shargah 17th July from which date please address all telegrams except those of routine nature to warship 'Bideford', Henjamradio. RESIDENT■ ■ Copy Telegrams R.^? From; Dickson, Political Agent, Kuwait, H.M.S. 'Bidef ord*• To: Government of India,Foreign and Political De par tment, 3imla• Repeated Secretary of State for India,London No. T.79. Dated the 19th July 1932. IMMEDIATE. Reference Bideford’s telegram reporting /-s Political Resident’s death. Do you wish me proceed Shargah and continue negotiations with Shaikh. I know lines on which Political Resident intended to proceed as he was taking me to interpret and assist him; also Under Secretary is present who has been to Shargah on each visit and is au fait with situation. Personally I do not favour this course at present as news of Political Resident’s death will have to be known and might easily be interpreted as divine interference. On other hand I see no harm calling and giving out news Political Resident’s death at Shargah and expressing hope that in view of Political Resident’s great eagerness to bring matter to successful conclusion Shaikh will raise no further difficulties with his successor. Am remaining in Bideford for the present. / - DICKSON -COPY. Telegrams Proms To Repeated No. 1611. Dated and R.* 27. Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. DICKSON, V/arship 'Bideford*. received 20th July 1932. IMMEDIATE . Dickson’s telegram 'o.T.79 of July 19th. we agree that he should call at Shargah and act as proposed but should leave further negotiations to Fowle who has been instructed to assume charge pending permanent appointment. - FOREIGN -Telegrams Pr om R. * 27 DICKSON, 'Bideford', Henjamradio. To Secretary of State for India,London. Repeated Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Political, BUSHIRE. No. T.81. Dated and received 21st July 1932. IMMEDIATE . Reference Government of India’s telegram -Wo. 1611 dated July 20th. In anticipation of your concurrence, and feeling necessity that some action should be taken at once, I proceeded Shargah in 'Bideford' and broke news of death of Political Resident. To my surprise I found atmosphere very favourable for proceeding with negotiations for civil air route. Shaikh of Shargah himself pressed for conclusion of agreement under my auspices and was strongly supported by Residency Agent, who is of opinion that success is in sight. There is no question that esteem in which late Political Resident was held here and his known anxiety to settle this matter is responsible for this favourable atmosphere, which may not last. Under these circum stances I think opportunity too good to miss and recommend that I now be permitted to proceed with negotiations. I feel certain I may achieve final settlement, and such opportunity may not occur again. DICKSON -(2$) Copy Telegram: From To: Repeated G.T.C. Secretary of State for India,London. Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Simla, lio.1931. DICKSON,'Bideford w ,Henjamradio. No.1932. Political Resident, Eushire, No.1933. Dated 20th ( received 21st ) July 1932. IMMEDIATE . Your telegram of 20th July, No.1611. His Majesty’s Government regard it as of first urgency to secure Shaikh’s signature to agreement and commence work on rest house but they share your view that negotiations should be left to Fowle on whom, however, urgency of a decision at the easliest possible date should be impressed, tfe are inclined to doubt whether in the circumstances any really useful purpose will be served by courtesy visit by Dickson of the type proposed but are prepared to leave decision in this matter to you. /\ -Secretary of State for India- ]Copy- Telegram: Fr om: To: Repeated R.’2®* Secretary of State for I ndia,London* Government of India &gt; Forexgn and Political Department, Simla, no*1937* DICKSON, H.M*S* w Bidef ord H ,lienjam. No*1938. Political Resident, Bushire. No,1939. Dated and received 21st July 1932. MOST IMMEDIATE - Dick son* a telegram -Wo.T.Sl and Government of India’s telegram No.1618 of July 21st. SHARGAH. His Majesty’s Government agree that Dickson should negotiate and trust he will succeed in conclusion of agreement, to which they attach first importance. -secretary of State for India-K. * 27 Copy Telegram: H.* 27. Froto: Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Simla. To Political, Bushire. No. 1631. Dated 22nd received 23rd ^uly 1932* Following telegram from Government of India to Secretary of State for India No«1618 of 21st July,repeated to Col.Dickson, beginsi- 'Dickson’s telegram of July 21st, iio # T/81. 'We agree that Dickson should now proceed with negotiations'. Ends. Foreign -y&gt; AliMEiittxK mXIKM tiHAXKH »UL!l Aii AIM MNJJ9i Of OHAHUAH, AMU 1MM MME1BH UOYKHKikifiia 1 JtoH fM MmAMMimacMS! o* AM AlH ft'mxuii Al’ Ur AH. It hAYine been intiaaten to »«• uultan bin ttaqar. tttoaiicn oi tihargaia uxic its tiliagee # by ^ieutenAin uolonei Hir Hu&amp;i Bieeoe, jPoiitioai iteeinent in the Persian dmUT. fcnat the High British aoremaent aesire to establish an air route along the Arab Coast for the aeroplanes of the imperial Airways Company (hereinafter referred to as tht Company), and that they wish to liars an air station at hhargah at whidi British aeroplanes can land, X hereby agree to grant to the said Company the foHoeing facilities 2 * i. The Company may select a landing ground at shariah, and may put on it such marks as are necessary• and their aeroplanee may land on that ground. 8. X will construct a rest house for the passengers and staff of the Company on a site to be selected by the Company and in accordance with plans drawn up by them, and under the super vision of an engineer of the British Government, The house and fixed fittings to be considered as my pro party. A. The Company shall nave the right to import, free of duty, petrol and spare parts for aircraft, provisions for the passengers and staff, and whatever may be required for their service.4* Th* Cocvaay may 8«na the ir employee to reside In xm root house, hut neither they nor the passenger* shall enter the town of shargah without my permission, Z further accept full responsi bility for the protection of the htaff and n passengers of the Company and their aireraft 9 eo far as my dependents, relatives end subjects are concerned, and further for their protection as far as possible against marauders from outlsde my Jurisdiction. I will supply 5b guards and H head guards• In return for the above, it is agreed that the Brltlah uoremawnt shall maJce w&amp; the fbllosing payments :• (i) #ay for 5b guards and two ohlofs at the rate of ho, go p.m. for each guard and Ho, 40 p.m, for each of tho two hoad guards, payment to ccmttenco from the date the guards are appointed. (ii) rtent foac^Uie air at at ion Hs. aou. p.m., payment to eemmenoo from tho dato tho first commercial a or o piano lands, (ill) Hont for the best houso Hs, 500, p.m, Tho Govommont shall advance me by instalments such sums as may be considered reasonable by the engineer supervising the worn for the construction of the building, ana no rent shall bo psyablo to mo until all tho sumo ad van cod have boon ropaia. Tho Government will supply gratis doors, windows and stosl Joists and corrugated iron.Wrouu Li tut ••Colonel Nicies on, C • X • L« on behalf of rhe lion* ble the lolitioal Resident In the Persian Gulf • To* Sultan bin £;a&lt;ger 9 Shaikh of 2&gt;hargah« SHAH CUE, 22nd July, 19^2* In eonneotion with the Agreement for the Aerodrome at shargah, which you hare signed,you hare expressed a fear lest the establishment of an Mr Station milht inrolre interference with your independence and freedom* 2* 1 therefore write to Tour Honour to inform you that the Britieh aorern- ment will reepeet your and your euoceeeore* independence, complete free dom and authority orer your subjeete and properties and will do nothing to take away your lands from you, and will not intorfere in your internal affairs or with your serrants, male or female, or your diroro, and if any of the Coastal Shaikhs attempt to threaten you owing to tho Agreement which we hare come to, the Britieh uovernment will support you. 3* Further, the representatives of the Company residua^ in Shargah will have no official position, but will be representatives of a commercial firm* 4* And no evil-doers shall be allow ed to take refuge in the rest-houee* &amp;• Further, the guards shall be entirely under your orders, and you will be entitled to forbid any of your pooplottownsmon or otherwiso, to enter the rest-house, except the employes and servants of the Cflmpany and persons eent by the Residency Agent* 6* And if, whieh God forbid, mny incident*/l!a - 2 - A incident ehould occur, the Briticlx OoTcrnacnt will not exact puniehaent except after enquiry and inTeatigation, and tiie punishment of your subjects will be with you, 7. But if the offence has been committed by persons from outside your jurisdiction you will do your best to trace them and inform the ftorernment, b t punishment will be with the Hl^h Oovernment* 8, Finally 1 am glad to inform you that the aoTernment has undertaken that the mail steamer shall call at ihargah* 9* l hope that this will bring prosperity to you and your people* ad/* H.K.P.Dickson, Li out *00101101, ^ h«Vbie the FelltUal resident in the e ra xin Julf. ( rCopy, Telegram: R.^?. From: DICKSON, w Bideford w , Henjamradiii. To: Secretary of State for India,London. Repeated? Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Political, Bushire. No. T/83. Dated 22nd seceived 23rd July 1932* ♦ IMMEDIATE . Agreement signed 1920 local time today. Details follow. I am returning Kuwait* DICKSONCopy Telegram: From: To Repeated No. T/85. R« * 27• DICKSON, H.M* S • •Bideford** • Government of India,Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Secretary of State for India,London. Dated 23rd July 1932. EASTERN AIR ROUTE . My telegram -No.T.83* following in two parts* PART 1. Reference draft agreement enclosed in Political Resident’s Express letter No.4C0-S of 21st June 1932. Following are modifications contained in agreement now signed by Shaikh. l Clause 2. Add H The house and fixed fittings to be considered as my property” . Page 3, add following provisosi- Should British Government require to renew this agreement at the end of the above period they may do so provided 3 months* notice is given me. Should there be any dispute as to the text of this agreement the English wording shall prevail. In return for agreement I handed Shaikh a letter drafted on lines of paragraph 7 of Political Resident’s letter referred to above assuring him: 1. That British Government will respect his complete independence. 2. That Company shall be strictly commercial concern. 3. That guards will be entirely under his orders. 4. That he will not be asked to punish anyone but his own subjects though he may be expected to assist Govern ment in tracing any evil-doers should any incident occur. 5 , # • • •MB © - 2 - 5. If any Coastal Shaikhs threaten him as direct result of the agreement, British Government will support him. 6. British India mail will call at Shargah. PART 2 . Progress of work on landing ground. Engineer officer appointed by Air Officer Comnanding,Iraq Command, to supervise work, visited site during negotiation. He considers sufficient cement and stones have been collected by Shaikh to commence construction as soon as other necessary material can be obtained from Basrah. These he will send down by mail and will revisit Shargah after a fortnight and start construction. He does not consider work will be far enough advanced to use Rest house in first instance, but will erect temporary shelter and protection to enable landing ground to be used as night halt for Imperial Airways* staff and passengers from 1st October. - DICKSON -Telegrams Froms To* Repeated G. T.G. H. M.S#'Bidef ord w ,Shargah. AVIATION, Baghdad. Chief Engineer, Hinaidi,0.C.203 Squadron,Basrah. Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf Division. Bo. 1100. Dated the 21st July 1932. From Mackay. n ave inspected site and discussed with Dickson, Senior Political Officer at Shargah, and Isa. Conditions considered favourable for early settlement. Dickson has requested authority from London to continue negotiations in place of Political Resident. Shaikh does not appear to realise the importance to us of time element and though he will undoubtedly fulfil his promises I anticipate considerable delay due to this factor. Shaikh has collected sufficient stone to commence Rest house but has no means of transportation to site. I do not consider that sufficient progress will be made by October to permit of use of Rest house perimeter for defensive purposes. Temporary defense post and camp will be necessary. In order to get stores to site mechanised transport will be essential. Have endeavoured to hire local lorry without success. Animal transport not available in sufficient quantity. In order to overcome this difficulty request very early sanction other to purchase Ford or/30-Cwt lorry at Basrah and ship to Shargah. Cost to be met from advance already made by Political Resident. Lorry to remain Shaikh’s property on conclusion of work. Am signalling Basrah to despatch on 30th July by mail steamer, defense stores and native supervisor. Am returning by air to Basrah tomorrow and propose returning Shargah in about two weeks time. Bideford remaining Shargah for the present. -BIDEFORD-Copy © Telegrams I’r om: Tos Repeated “o.CE/72. enclair. Chief Engineer, Hinaidi. W. 8c D* Basrah. Resident, Bushire. Dated 22nd received 23rd July 1932. Your 1100 21/32. Following for Mackay. Confirmation requested that Shaikh agrees to air headquarters acting as private agent for buying for him in Baghdad a new 30-cwt lorry of suitable make. Bills for purchase and shipment to be sent to Political Resident, Persian Gulf, for settlement and debited to account of cash advance to Shaikh for construc tion of rest house. State whether Political Resident agrees t these financial arrangements. Report whether shipment from Basrah can be arranged by sloop. State arrangement proposed for disembarking vehicle on Trucial coast. - Chief Engineer, Hinaidi© Copy U Telegrams enclair From* DICKSON,H.M.S. *»Bidef ord” To; AVIATION, Baghdad. Repeated Mackay, No.203 (F.B.)Squadr©n,Basrah. No. T.84. Dated 23rd July 1932. Your CE/72 of 22nd July to Mackay. Am en route Kuwait, matter will be taken up by Political Resident, Bushire, who is being informed. DICKSON -mm mm Copy * Telegram en clair From DICKSON,H.M.S.'Bideford'. To AVIATION, Baghdad. Repeated MACKAY, Aerbtwo, Basrah. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf ^ivisiooi. No.T.87. Dated the 23rd July 1932. In amplification my 84/T question purchase of lorry was discussed this morning by Under Secretary to Resident fcnd myself. Am strongly of opinion that it would be mistake to suggest to Shaikh that lorry be bought out of funds adtanced to him as it would make him suspicious. Shaikh anxious for minimum amount money to be advanced to him so that repayment may be made as soon as possible, thereny rendering time when he will start receiving rent shorter. I agree that lorry is necessity but think that it should be a government charge to be recovered later from Imperial Airways who will certainly need it. Meantime owing to urgent necessity of starting work suggest lorry be purchased forthwith and question of payment adjusted later• DICKSON -Confidential. flo.t&gt;27-S of 1932. British Kesidency &amp; Consulate—Creneial Bushire, the 30th July 1932. From - The hon’ble Lt.Colonel T.C.Fowle,C.B.E., Officiating Political Resident in the Persian To - Lieut.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwai t. Sir, I have the honour to state that the Government of India have asked me to convey to you the following message from His Majesty's Government to them i - * His Majesty's Government have learnt with great w satisfaction of conclusion of Shargah agreement. ' Please convey their congratulations to Dickson”. The Government of India add that they desire to associate themselves with the congratulations sent by His Majesty's Government. I have much pleasure in conveying the above message and would add my congratulations to those of His Majesty's Government and the Government of India. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Lt.Colonel Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.© I ^ 7^ Confidential, D.O.No. 529-3 of 1932. /^N The Residency, Bushire, the 30th July 1932. ©iwi. ^VoVk/VOX Many congratulations on your Shargah coup. Official pats on the back from His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India are in this mail. There is one point which strikes me, and that is there is no mention of a W/T station at Shargah in the Agree ment with the Shaikh. I understand from Chauncy, with whom I discussed the matter, that this point was purposely not mentioned to the Shaikh in any of the conversations that Sir Hugh had with him, as far as Chauncy knows, for the reason that under Clause 2 of the Agreement,( H the house and fixed fittings to be considered my property'), the Shaikh might have claimed the W/T installation for himself. The in stallation can doubtless be made under Clause 3,'whatever may be required for their ( the Company’s) service'. Does the Shaikh know, however, that W/T will be installed ? Presumably yes. But whether so, or not, when it - the W/T - begins to be installed will he on his side begin to make difficulties ? I don’t suppose that he himself will, but pefchaps the opposition party, headed by his had brother Muhammed, might do so ? I know nothing about the local conditions at Shargah, and of course you are an expert in them. So I would be grateful fdr your views, which could you please let me have as soon as possible. lit.Col• H.R.P.Dickson,C.I#E., Political Agent, Kuwait.C onfidential No.125 # &lt; Politioal Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 4th August 1932. Prom To Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, K\wait. His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. The India Office, London. Sir, Acting under instructions from the Hobble Ike Political Recident in the Persian Gulf, I hare the honour to forward a copy of my confidential despatch No. 121 dated the 4th August 1932 to the address of the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, on Hie subject of the 'Shargah' Negotiations. I understand that copies of the w agreement* as signed by the Shaikh of Shargah as well as 'letter of assurance* which was handed to the Shaikh by me, have already been forwarded to you by Air Mail. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Polit leal Agent, Kuwai t.Confidential , No*126# Political Agency, Kuwait# Dated the 4th August 1932. To Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.P.Diokson, Political Agent, Kuwait# The Hon^le the Political Resident in tiie Persian Gulf, Bushire# Sir, I hare the honour to forward herewith a copy of my confidential despatch No# 121 dated the 4th August 1932 to the address of the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla# 2# I am enclosing two spare copies, one of which I would ask you to send on on to the Air Officer Commanding in Iraq if you see no objection to such course# I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, 1 / Lieut-Col#, Political Agent, Kuwait.D.O.No.124« (Q) Political Agency, Kuwait. Bated the 4th August 1932. Reference your D.0.Ho.589.S. dated the 31st July. Firstly let ns thank you for your very nice congratulations on our Shargah coup. Between you and me Denison of H.U.S.Bideford and Chauncy deserve a large measure of credit. The former for tine his unfailing patience and courtssey with the Shaikh and other miserable sinners, and for putting himself out so much to make me feel at home and comfortable. Chauncy I have already told you in a private note, could not have done better The heat was vile all the time at Shargah but always Chauncy was cheery and keen witted. I do not think we shall have the slightest trouble with the Shaikh in the matter. 'Sherika' (l.e. Xtaperlal Airways), would of course put up an engine to provide electricity for their Hesthouse, and would have to have its own private wireless set to keep in touch with their aeroplanes, and neighbouring stations Hast and Best He seemed to take this quite as a matter of course, and never raised any questions. The fact that a W/T will be a purely commercial affair and not owned by Qovemzasnt, is of course an advantage, as it allays suspicions. regarding W/T station at Shargah. 1 mentioned quite casually to him that the No doubt once the route is got going. Airways will The Hon'ble Lt.Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf-2- %) &gt; will grant facilities on special occasions to the Shaikh and his farourites to despatch private messages* I don’t know whether there are any difficulties in this direction, but it will help enormously in Airways’ relations with the Shaikh, if they can assist him occasionally* At present the B*I* fortnightly mall is flooded every time it reaches Dabai with commercial telegrams from merchants to India 9 so everyone knows about the advantages of wireless* Under clause 8 of the Agreement I personally explained to the Shaikh that n the House and fixed flttlngs n ^ _ A. was meant thejagAn b^UflLMt §39SS.$ SiMoWMt fireplacen , waU- cupboards , steel beams etc*, anything in fact built into the actual house* His Wazlr suggested that it might be possible to include internal electrie fittings (less actual lamps and fans) as is done in India and other countries* I replied that no doubt this could be arranged but that the engine and external wiring would certainly not be included* toy reply would no doubt convey the clear meaning that wireless engine or materials did not oems into the picture A ) Thirdly * In my report on the Shargah negotiations sent by this mail, I have recommended that we proride arms for the 'Air Station Guards'* There seems little doubt that Bisooe promised this* Bren if he did not, I most certainly recommend that it be done* We can easily get some short *303 rifles of a slightly obsolete pattern for the purpose, an d the local effect would be out of all proportion to the cost incurred* 1 suggest that the matter be taken up at once by you, as well as the braes badges* Fourthly * Z have a feeling that K*B*l8a has not quite played the game by us in this business # He certainly did not assist me as he ought to have done* He wields enormous influence on the Truolal coast but throughout the x negotiations he struck me as being sticky and unwilling to co-operate* I know hie difficulties and that he has largelylargely to hunt with the taats hounds and run with the hare* But in suoh e big thing as the Shargah Air Station, it was up to him to throw all hie wel#it into getting the business through* from shat he hinted to me 1 rather suspect he has in some way eonmltted himself with the Shaikh of Dabai. He oertalnly paid several visits there just before we arrived, an£ he told me that Shaikh of Shargah wee terrified lest we changed our minds and went back to the Dabai idea, but the rr idea was a good one, he added*P erson al letter M IlaJ ‘ ' ’2,U Prom - Lieut.- Col. L.R.x .Dickson, .'oliticcJl ^ent, I'ir. xit, To - li. B. T Isa bin T ^bdul Latif, C.B.L., Residency Agent, Shargah (Bear Dubai). Dated the 6th august 1932 (4th Rabi T Thani 1351). xi.fter compliments, This is to inform you that I duly arrived back in Kuwait and gave yours and Shaikh Sultan bin Sacar T s Salaams to Bis excellency the Ruler of Kuwait. The news that the agreement had been signed at' Shargah gave great pleasure to Shaikh Ahmad who desires me to convey his good wishes and congratulations to Shaikh Sultan and you. Since my return I have written to Lady Biscoe and to Sir Hugh Biscoe f s son in India, and have given them all particulars of the Political Resident’s sad death. But what has to be has to be, and man cannot alter God Almighty’s decrees. I trust you are keeping well and that it is not and told too hot at Shargah. I -duly wrote ix/Colonel Powle, the acting Political Resident, about rifles for the aerodrome Guards at v Shargah. I trust that you and the Shaikh will get these* in due course. Usual ending.Personal letter. i^rom - Lieut.- joI. H.3.P.Dickson, Lolitict.! Agent, Iiuw&lt;-it. To -* Shaildi Sultan bin Saqr, Shaikh of Shargah, Shargah (Hear Dubai)• Dated the 6th August 1932 (l-thRabi T Thoni 1351). kkfter oompli'nents, I write to inform you that I arrived bade safely at Kuwait and gave your Salaams to Shaikh Ahmad as promised. Ke was very pleased to hear that you had signed the Agreement and offers his oongratulations te you. His strong advice to you is to continue to grasp the hand of the High Government in closest friendship and cooperation; do this always and nothing but favours and rewards will come to you he says. I also endorse these words of your friend and well wisher tie Shaikh of Kuwait. Tor the rest , this is what had to be said, and I hope you will get all your desires. In the matter of rifles for the aerodrome Guards, I have referred the matter to the ron r ole the Political Resident, and I trust everything will turn out to your satisfaction. It is rumoured that Ibn Rifadah has been beaten and killed by Ibn Sa’ud's forces. Usual ending.t Personal . Iko Political Agency, Kuwait* Dated the 12th August 1932* r*&gt; I have huet received your note of 25th July, congratulating ne on Ihe Shargah coup* 2* Xt was nost generous and thoughtful of you to send me such a cheery and kind message, and I feel much encouraged* so 3* It is little touches like yours which do/much to help the wheels go round, for situate as I am in rather a lonely little Kuwait, one sometimes feels that nobody really cares or appreciates what one does with climate and other things handicapping one* 4# Entre nous, I do not think I have ever had such a hard 3 days* fi^ht as I had with the Shaikh of Shargah* The heat was terrific, one’s temper was ragged, and I had scarcely recovered from Biscoe’s tragic end* He practically &gt; died in my arms after a whole ni^it Y s struggle. 5* Last but not least I had to combat the efforts of a host of intriguers all determined to prevent the shaikh, a most weak, obstinate and frightfully suspicious person, from signing the agreement we wanted from him* 6* It was a regular'tug of war' between the Shaikh and Myself lasting on the second day from 8*a*m* to 9*p m* (all alone on shore in smelly and hot surroundings), and on the third day from 10*a*m* till 7*30 # p*m* on H*M*S*Bldeford* I wore him out in the end and won* Xt was a stiff fi^it* 7* You are right about Bisooe. He was a very great chief and perfect gentleman, and did wonders to enhance our prestige* Pray God we get another like him* Air Yloe Marshall C*B.Burnett, C*B*, C*M*G*, D*S«0*, Etc*, Klngsway, W*C*2*3* Hoping you are very fit and well* 9* I hare not got my new house yet f but I do not think it la far off now* P«3* The wife is in England with the ohildren t address e/o Eastern Bank* London* E.C.3* &gt;&lt; r &gt; c ' © Translation of a letter . From - Sultan bin Saqr al-Qasim, Shaikh of Sharqah, Trucial Oman. To - The Political Agent, Kuwait. No. Nil. Dated the 11th Jamad Than! 1351 (12th October 1932). After compliments, I have been honoured with the receipt of your esteemed letter, conveying to us news of your good health, and noted its contents, especially with regard to your giving our Salaams to the Honourable Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Sabah, ibr which kind representations I cannot but thank you sincerely. Shaikh Ahmad’s wishes for our progress and prosperity are no doubt due to his high morals;. May he be best rewarded for same • Further I beg to inform you that I have done my best in what has been decided between you and myself, by fulfil- ing all duties, and bringing affairs together after an aversion of the canmunity, whom I have always beai promising the best of hopes from the Government’s side, but I regret to say that up to date it has not been arranged that the commercial steamers should call at our port of Sharqah, as has been decided between the Government and ourselves. It has therefore become necessary for me to submit the matter to you with a request that you, being the Government’s representative to us in this question, may kindly fulfil your promise to us, and that you will not disappoint our good hope and let our enemies laugh at us. I have written to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf about same, and hope that you will also endeavour in the matter, and let me have an early reply. , Please give my Salaams to H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al- ffabir as-Sabah etc.,British tutsiaency ana Co ns uJL at central Buahire ( the 9th August 1942. Ho. obo-»&gt; of 1VA8 cn&gt; fron The Hon'bls X4.eut»•Colonel i .O.tf. yowls, C.h*’i. # yo The Foreign ttsoretary to the Cowenuasnt of mala. the 2Bth July 1952, X hats the honour to stats that Colonel Dickson lias asked as to convey to His Majesty's Govsrnraent and the Government of India his appreciation of their asssages of congratulation on the ooncliwlon of the Bhargah Agreement • Z aa sending a copy of this letter to hie Bftjesty'e as erst ary of atats for India. X have ths honour to be, Mir, Your moot obedient servant. Officiating ^olitieaX He aidant in the iter uiamm] Claim Mir 9ith reference to your telagraa Mo. load, dated 31)/ T . C. »• jrowle, ^••Colonel Offg. ajlitical item dent in Urn Persian Gulf Copy forwarded to the i-olitical Agent, Kuwait; for information ay ufder, Confidential AssiatantTranslation of a personal letter , fffc Frcm ~ Saqr bin Sultan al-Qasim^/Shaikh of Shargah. To - Lieut.- Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, Kuwait. Dated the 11th Jsmad Than! 1351 (12th October 1932). After compliments. With regard to the gun which you so kindly promised to me. I have been always expecting same. Will you therefore be so good as to send it to me?Personal &amp; Private Political Agency, Kuwait Dated the 19th Janad Than! 1351 » (20-10-32) To Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr al-Qasim Esq&lt;», Through the Residency Agent, K. B. f Isa bin ’Abdul Latif, Shargah, Trucial Oman, | After compliments, I have received your letter dated 11th Jamad Thani 1351. I am very glad to hear that you are well and that everything is going on so nicely with the Rest House and other matters arranged by me. With regard to the calling of the mail steamer, I understand from the Secretary Captain Gastrell, who has been staying with me, that the Hon’ble the Political Resident has addressed the British India Steam Navigation Company at Calcutta the in the matter, and I am sure very shortly that you will see/up mail calling at Shargah according to your desire. Be sure that the Political Resident will not fail to arrange the matter satisfactorily. Regarding the gun which I promised to your son - I hope to get it soon from England when it shall be sent to you</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00012d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/282</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00012d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/282</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/8 Sharjah Aerodrome Agreement'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-08T16:56:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (82 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 83; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-81; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence on the construction and financing of the Sharjah aerodrome. The file also contains a few papers that mention the sudden death in 1932 of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at the time, Sir Hugh Biscoe while en route to Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Air Transport</topic></subject><subject><topic>Military aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00012d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>