<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000319_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:02:05.990Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Con Jidenttal. 0 ., MESOPOTAMIA: CUSTOMS TARIFF. I. - Letter from Sir L. Mallet to Sir A. Hirtzel. British Delegation, Paris, My dear llirtzel, 15th April 11)19. 1 he question of the Onstoms d'ariff in former Turkish territories requires further consideration, as no definite conclusions have been adopted by the sections so far as I am aware. \Ve agreed with the French in the Sykes-Pieot Convention to retain the pre-war I urkish larill in force for _?0 years and to set up no internal barriers between the Arab States. The Economic Section feel that we cannot now well maintain the principle of I I pei - cent, for 20 years in the new Arab States, for reasons which are fairly obvious. They think that the starting point should be 11 per cent., but that some arrangement ought to be come to by which the Arab States would be allowed to increase their tarilf by the consent of the League of Nations, if such increase is really necessary for their financial stability. Sir Hubert LI. Smith sees no objection to the Arab States themselves forming a Customs union without any internal barriers, but he is doubtful as to their trade relations with what remains of Turkey, and is disposed to think that there is more case for duties being levied on such.trade. W ith regard to this 1 cannot contemplate with much confidence a proposal which would necessitate obtaining the consent of the League of Nations to the increase of the Arab Tariff and I understand that it is not contemplated to give the League any such right of interference in other mandated territories. Their duties are limited to seeing that there are no preferential tariffs. If, however, it be agreed at the outset to establish one tariff for all the Arab countries, including Palestine, it follows that no increase or diminution could be effected in one of those countries without previous understanding with all the others including Palestine. That is a different thing from consulting the League of Nations. We have two things to consider—the interests of Mesopotamia and of Palestine (on the supposition that we become the mandatory of those States) and those of the British and British Indian traders. There is no particular reason why they should clash, a&gt; it would be of no advantage to the Mesopotamians or Palestinians to clap on duties which would diminish foreign trade, nor would it benefit British trade if those countries were too poor to pay their way. It is probable that Faisal will be strongly in favour of a Customs Union; contending as he does that the Arab countries are one, and 1 imagine that this would also be in our interest. It would be useful, however, to have Colonel Wilson’s views and those of the Foreign Office on the question, and if you would be so good as to consult him while he is still in England, 1 should be grateful. (Signed; Louis Mallet. II. - Memorandum by Lieut.-Colonel A. T. Wilson, Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. dated 16th April 1919. 1. I am unaware of the grounds on which the agreement referred to in the second paragraph of Sir L. Mallets letter was based, but the decision is one which would be wholly unacceptable to Mesopotamia. 2. Ad valorem tariffs are by no means ideal instruments for raising revenue intelligently, unless power is kept, and used, to modify the tariff whenever circum stances render it desirable : c.^., (id valorem tariff' on alcohols has been abolished m Mesopotamia in favour of a tariff based on quantities. The fomiei sets a piemium on the worst liquor, the latter penalises inferior spirits. 3. The Iraq State mav wish to protect local industries against the competition ol cheap Indian) labour. I have already been urged to reduce the Customs duty, on certain kinds of leather, and to increase the duty on manufactures ol leather. s 34 40 4/101. ] should therefore strongly deprecate any undertaking pledging the Iraq State to any particular kind of tariff. 5. We are already taking 11 per cent, in Mesopotamia, and I propose very shortly to increase it to 15 per cent., the figure to which the Powers, 1 understand, agreed to allow the Turks to raise the tariff before the war. This is necessary for revenue purposes and scarcely admits of discussion. That the League of Nations should be consulted beforehand is a startling proposition and one which should, I submit, be opposed to the utmost. I submit that Great Britain as mandatory is the sole judge in such a matter, and that to require us to refer internal matters such as our financial stability to the League of Nations—which has no independent information can only involve (1) delay, ^2) disaster. 6. The objections to a Customs union with other Arab countries are very strong; it may come later, but to press it now will certainly cause difficulties. 1 have discussed the question with Colonel T. E. Laurence, who told me that Faisal would by no means forego either transit duties or duties on imports from Mesopotamia, and that he depended upon such duties for much revenue which was indispensable. 1 fancy that when railway connection between Iraq and Syria is an accomplished fact it will be fairly easy to come to an agreement on the subject, but ! would urge that nothing be done in the matter now. 7. I would conclude by mentioning that the Arab chiefs in the Gulf might be concerned in this matter, as also is Ibn Sand, and I anticipate that they would view with alarm any such proposals, and that if Iraq is to be called on to pay 4O0,0O0L or so a year in respect of pre-war Ottoman public debt, it must be given full liberty to raise money as may seem best to it. 16th April 1919. A. T. Wilson, JA cut.-Colonel, Officiating Civil Commissioner.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000319_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B319</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000319</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B319</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Mesopotamia: customs tariff'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-24T15:20:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (1 folio)</extent><extent>This file consists of a single document.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 38, and terminates at f 38, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains a letter from Louis Mallet, British Ambassador at Constantinople, to Sir Frederic Arthur Hirtzel, Secretary for the Political Department of the India Office, dated 15 April 1919. It also contains a memorandum by Lieutenant-Colonel Arnold Talbot Wilson, the Civil Commissioner in Baghdad, dated 16 April 1919. Both items relate to potential changes to the customs tariff in former Turkish territories, and discuss the potential benefits or problems with proposals such as creating a custom union between Arab states, and with involving the League of Nations in decisions relating to any increases in tariffs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to the Ottoman Empire</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Civil Commissioner, Mesopotamia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Tariffs</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000319#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>