<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001cd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:56:17.870Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">RELATED FILES i PUBLIC RECORDS ACT, 1958 (See paragraphs 24, I to 24, 4 of Part D of Digest of Office Procedure) When the officer dealing with this file considers that it is unlikely to be used again, or when the file is automatically closed at the end of a three-year cycle, the Higher Executive Officer (or Officer of higher rank) responsible for the subject should recommend in the appropriate space on the back cover of the file whether the file should be destroyed after a prescribed period or preserved. If he is unable to form a firm view, one of the spaces for “Consider at First/Second Review” should be signed: where this is done, a note must be placed on top of the file as the last paper giving reasons for deferring a decision. CROSS REFERENCED UNDER:— PRECEDENTS NOTED UNDER :■9 HM '/ VKVS. (!) No. V^y “ L^yg' Of 1916. POLITICAL AGENCY. BAHRAIN, the 28th July 1916. o To 7 ol *^v /y w ^ r • . ' • . ^rJ Xa J V J '' , r ;w '‘ €L - J ^-. ei' ^JJ( Jlyi.,| &gt;WJ.U-^ . &lt;-f CslyL iL.' yy-t'^'it, .Jf , x,. • */*r - -1 A . . * w&gt; ^ His Excellency Shaikh Isa tin Ali A1 Khalifah, C.S.I., « Chief of Bahrain, BAHRAIN. After Compliments, For many years, • Your «» Excellency in your Customs Department has been charging 2^ import duty ad valorem on all goods entering Bahrain which have not been intended for local consumption but for transhipment to other ports. Now in April of this year Your Excellency is sued an order raising the duty on tranship- ped goods (except for piece goods ^ales which remained as before) to 5$ . * 2. My predecessor. Major Stewart, ad dressed you on this subject, but as no representations had been made at that time by merchants or others regarding this rai- si^og Oi the Customs duty, he did not see * the nacessity of further troubling Your A Excellency in the matter. Now however I have,received a communication from Sir Percy Cox, Political Resident, forwarding :n which ^nSaud protests against this raising of the above duty, as itf wilL. be p the ca-use of much harm to the trade of Hassa. Sir Percy Cox has directed “me to . r p report to liim on the matter, and I .would be •/^N Political ^&lt;?partment, Bombay Castle, arch 1917. From J • B. 0. Jukes, Esquire, . ^ '^gS/AN 'M r.y. To deputy Secretary to Government,Bombay. The Political A^ent, ^ahrein. ii’, I am directed to ^orvrard herewith, for your information, a copy of a License No. * ^’n dated the 2to^ March - 1917,granted - to Mr.Gangaram Tikamdas of Bahrein for the export to Bahrein of - - 5 cwts blasting powder and S00 coils (5000 feet) safety fuse - - -Ho BAmUIN* The 31at July 1016. The Chief Politioal Offioer # BASRAH. I \ Memorandum, Your Ho.8394 of 26th June. It wan nonewhat delayed in the Pont hence ny delay in renlyinp. The case stands an follows: ' Goods imported into Bahrain for local consumption are charged 5^ ad valorem inport duty. Hp to the 19th April of this year floods transhipped in Pa rain for other ports - Hassa and Qatar - were charged 2?^ provided they wore fcept in the Cub tons Import Yard until transhipped. Honurrafle and all ordinary port charfles were and are made in the usual Tnannor, In addition to the import duties. .2• On the 19th April 1916 Shaikh Isa issued a Customs notice that until the end of the war the import dutv on transhipped cargo destined for other ports should he 5# ad valorem, in stead of 2%% as formerly, with the exception of bales of piece-goods on which the duty would bo levied as In the nast.' 3. dThe past treatment of transhipped piece-goods is as follows. Provided an invoice in produced import duty ad„ valorem is charged. In practice however invoices a^e hardly ever produced, the apparent reason being that the invoices are.sent straight to .tho ultimate port of destination in Hassa.. When invoices are not forthcoming hero, up to about 4 or 5 years ago the order of the Shaikh was that every hale should be treated as if were worth Ra.4oo/- and that Rs.8/- ahould be charred on it. This'works out at 2^ ad valorem # nominal rate. Merchants took advantage of this to import goods in .bales of Rs•000 /- and over, when the Shaikh ordered that every bale* ^ shouldshould be treated as if It wore worth Ha*600/- and Un.15/- ohar^ed on It. Thin riveo nominal rate ol* interest at 2^$ ad valorem, i.o. if there 5s exactly Rn.dOO^- worth of nloce- goods in the bale. If more the merchant raina, if lean the . rs _ *fK morohant nuffora. But T a^ informed bv the Director of ^uat Customs here that on an average the bales for trano-abinnont r&gt; have from Ha.800/- to Rs.lOOO/- worth of voodB in them. The whole Customs arrangements with regard to import duties on trans-shipped piece-goods seems hap-hazard, but the result is that piece-goods apparently roooive favoured treatment in comparison with other trans-shipped merchandise, since the merchant can - and seemingly does - nay less than the nominal rate of by increasing the value o^ his bales. By the new order of the Shaikh this year, piece-goods receive still more favoured treatment when compared 7/ith other trans*-shipped , merchandise. 4. Bin Saud in his letter seems to make two protests. One - at the beginning of his c letter - against any trans-shipment charges being made at all, the other, against the recent in- ? creaGoo in the import duties on suoh trans-shipped broods. -From the local point of view here, I think it would bo quite impract!cab] e to approach Shaikh- Isa with any surgestiorjfto do awav with his trans-shipment charges in tAto. ^ith rorard to the faeoond, in the matter of imported piece-goods Hassa would in practice onlm seem to pay 2%%, or less, trans-shipment charges (vide para 3). So the point at issue is the rise from 2^/6 tc~5;£ ad valorem duty on other trans-shipped goods. 5. I informed Shaikh Isa that you hai forwarded me a letter from Bin Baud protesting against the increased Customs duties in question, and asked him to verv kindly let me have a rerly on whi^ch I could base my report to you. I was oaroful to put my queries in suoh a form as would not offend his ausoepti- •«* ^ bilitiea, which I see from previous correspondence are in- * * * m dined to be tender on the matter of Customs, and reqolvery / from-him a reply couohod in friendly terms to the following ^ m * effoot. , % - y** (1) Accoiviinr to the friendl’' convention between theof Bahrain and the Ooveronent of Honbay, article 4 of Slot May 1861 (Altohloon, Vol• ,XTI payo 160) t^e ObolVb oan obar/ro up to $°/l ad valorem duty* ,(2) That therefore hin oharTinsr for many voaro only » ^ ad valorem wao only an act of rnyioe, and oannot be held ayalnat him aa a reaoon for oontinuiny it* (3) That hi3 reason for the nrooent ralein* of dutieo io due to hia financial difficulties canoed by fallin* off of Cuetoma receipts on account of the war* (The Sheibh’c notice rAiaing the dutiea aaye that the onhantfod dutlea will be in * force until the end of* the war)* # ( 4 ) That Bxn_Baud hineoif oharvee 8^ innort duoa on ?ooda going into Haaaa* 6* The 8heikh aeena to have mane a fairlv strong case for himaelf• Articlo^4 of the oonvention quoted, refers only..to the goods of Hritioh subjecto, and if it had been to Bin Baud’s advantage we could have quoted it in hie favour - as T suppose in view of the Alliance between us and Bin Baud, the latter and his people can be rranted the oa^e favoured treat- iflont as f British subjects* As it la however it is a very ~strong authority on the side of the Sheikh to charge-up to his 5&gt;£* 1 can find no other treaty or enra^nnent w v iob^ lays down anything limiting the Sheikh's power to irmoainr Customs dues* Hib statement {^) seems also reasonable, and I believe hie statement (3) is aloo correct, though Bahrain trad© has taben a turn for the better this year* his statement (4) io likewise confirmed from enquiries I have made* Of courn* the -3/S referred to is not on trans-shipped g&lt;^ods, which in the point at issue, buc 1 'suppose the Sheikh wishes to show t^at generally speaking his rates compare favourably with other Gulf ports* 7. Under tho circumstances I have not re-addressed tho _ jbsikh on tho subject* As ho has a nrlma facie stron^^case did not. think it advisable to precis him in the matter with out further instructions, and will await them before procee ding further in the case*8# It m &amp;7 be noticea that the non: Cuetona rlutloa are only In foroo till the mr 1 of the T7ar, so i'' it ia oonaiderad that nothin/* oen bo lone r.t proeent the qneation can be tab on up afresh when poaoo io dooiared - though of- course that may be still a long vrav off. Officiating Political Agent, BA TTT Uin.9 ■P I H 1C P 0 B T YARD B ‘ A H R A I N. N 0 X ICE. id It is hereby noLified to all the Merchants Of Bahrain (1) That any claim for the shortages of goods against the Import Yard must he made to the Manager Import Yard - v/ithin 15 days from this date. (2) That after the expiry of the above period no such cla im will he entertained hy the Import Yard. (3) That a separate claim he made for each steamer with - full details as regards marks, nature aid amount of the goods short received. Bahrain, Dated 1st October 1916 (i.e. 3rd zulhaj 13o4). Director of Customs &amp; Import yard. ' Copy forwarde to H.B.M’s Political Agent for information. - - I ■ I OfcT V 4 ) ■2L4 H R M '• y - - *Telegram.?. From Loch Bahrain To 7 Trevor Buahire No. 7? C Dated 11.5.17 (12.3c)' Anxious enquiries have been made by Shaikh 1 Isa in letter &amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; as to when next steamer is coming as food is becoming very expensive and scarce. Kindly inform me If v/e nay* expect a. ship.- „ Since March 23th no merchant steamer has called at Baiirain.I : J . .. ! N telegram.P. Froui Trevor Bushire « ♦ To Loch Bahrain No. 8Q7 Dated: 12.5.17 Reed. 13..5*. 17 (Q.35) # Please see your No.77 C. It is not known to any o? the Steamer Agents here if vessel is proceeding to Bahrain in near future, ratters is complicated by Quarantine. Before I telegraph about it to the Government of- India can you inform me • . * ' (a)Vfhat amount of cargo the merchants of Bahrain have ordered and is no..* lying at Karachi or Bombay Bahrain ^ (b)- .rnether at you have any goods for export. . * Telegram.?. From Loch Bahrain To * Trevor Bush Ire- No; 80 C Dated 15.5 ; 17 (7.40) 7ith ^reference to your No.897 it appears a Japanese steamer is n * loading for this port. Reply to your questions vdll be postponed y''s' tifhtion may be eased by above sailing. Please try to find out answers to Llajor Trevpr *s que tions as data will be useful. Also if Japanese steamer is coming and if th t hvill ease market.•0 'll Telerrer- From Loch Bahrain . To Trevor Bushlre No. 81 C Dated ^16^5.17 (7.30) ' I'y tele^rc^m No.80 C. I non learn that 1300 tons of freight for Bahrain is being brought by the Japanese steamer. At Karachi there remain 155''' tons and at Bombay ?55C . '4 iJ \ i JPD. of 191 7* POLITICAL DEPARTMENT: Bombay Castle, 191.7« From J • S.C. Jukes, Require, dLyJ&amp;yi&amp;x 'Ji&amp;t&amp;IMMv. Deputy Secretary to Government, Bombay. To The Honourable the Political Resident . in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRT. m C Sir, - - r I am directed to ^orr'ard herevith, for your - - - T K information, a cony od a License Ko • dated the Liarch 1917 , granted to Ivir.Gangaram Tikamdas of Bahrein and Bombay for the export tohB^hrein of 5 cwts blasting novrder and 300 coils (500(5 f^*et) safety fuse consigned to Lr.Gannramm Tiicamdas of - ... Bahrein. I have the honour^ to be, fir. Your t ost obedient servant. Deputy Secretary to Government. JT No. #60 of 1917. British Residency and Consulate-General,' Bushire, 1st April 1917. Forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for informa- tloh and record* f ; i iCONDITIONS. c 1. This License is granted subject to all the provisions of the Indian Arms Act, 1878 (XI of 1878), and of the Indian Anns Rules, 1909 2. Ihe articles shall not be conveyed by any route other than tuat specified in Column 7 j and bulk shall not be broken, nor shall the consignment be stopped, before the articles reach the place of destination. 3. An account of the contents of each package shall be legibly written thereon; and, where the articles are conveyed by rail, each package shall be marked with the word or expression “Arms” “Ammunition” or “Military Stores,” as the case may be, so as to bo readily recognizable by the “Railway authorities. No of 191 . Political Department : Bombay Castle,- 191 Copy- forwarded to the fon information.CONDITIONS. 1. This License is granted subject to all the provisions of the Indian Arms Actr 1878 (XI of 1878), and of the Indian Arms Rules, 1909 2. ihe articles shall not be conveyed by any route other tlnrn ~toat specified in Gjolumn 7; and bulk shall not be broken, nor shall the consignment be stopped, before-the articles reach the place of destination. 3. An account of the contents of each package shall be legibly written thereon; and, where the articles are conveyed by rail, each package shall be marked with the word or expression “Arms” “Ammunition” or “Military Stores,” as the case may be, so as to be readily recognizable by the Railway _ authorities. No. of 191 . Political Department : Bombay Castle, Z 191 . Cofjy forwarded to the for information. for Secretary to Government,C U S T.O M HOUSE, v Bahrein. Date , -Ed.'Uh-.J.UDe-. 191? Dear Captain Loch A Jorne. .time hack I had written you s-chlt, requedting to aak Meddra Gray P8U&gt;''&amp; Co to fumi.ih ud with the copy of **&gt; their Export Manifest. - It is since long time that their present steamer Palitan 371 ”has departed from here hut up to the moment I have not received the E. Manifest from them-. I shail therefore thank you &amp; remind you to kindly do the needful in the. matter. Yours Jincerely,No.548 Political Agency. Bahrain, the 28th June l^l? t Tc, 4 Tho Director of lustOTns Bahrain. \ Dear Dir, V'tth' ref erence to your note of June 2&lt;?tb , 1 'P 1 r/ , . reprardinf*: ^esera ''ray,Paul and Covta export manifeata, I meant to have opoken to you on the subject,but it shipped except on production of an export certificate from you,and if that ia the cage,you already have the fi^urea j^fijthe raanife3t,ao T do not quite aee why a copy of the manifest is v/anted. If I am mistaken or there is some particular reason for vour having a copy will you e please ; let me know. plipped my memory. 1 understand / that no poods' are 'ours faithfully \ Captain Political Arent ,Bahrain7 ^ / Ik €?f STOM HOUSE Bahrain, dated the 2nd October 1917 H.B.lFs Political Agent Bah rain. Ref: Your letter Ho:548 of 28th June 1917.- X' I beg to state th c t I had insisted upon having ^th£ export manifestcopy o^ B.I.S.H &amp; Co’s steamers and in. reply to which Messrs Gray Paul « Co declined to send us the sameon the plea that the company does not issue any shipping order without the Customs pass and your honor likewise ordered that the ex port manifest was not necessary. Now leaving the previous cases I lay before your hon our the instance in v/hich Messrs Gray Paul &amp; Co have very recetit ly N issued the shipping order No:2l on 30th ultimo for A R 6CBdls wet dates without the Customs pass. The cargoalready shipped per S.S.Ban Kong Liong Voy: I. ~ Iregretat their so doing and am at a loss to under stand as to why Messrs Gray Paul &amp; Co should have any objection in sending us the' desired copy when it is convenient to us to compare the same with the Customs passes issued and correct thj I errors if any. Under these circumstances T shall once more request yourhonqrto look to this matter and ask Messrs Gray Paul Sc Co I . * to send us the export manifest copy regularly as before, or in otheT case there is great possibility for Customs to suffer a great deal. I have the honor to be,~ Custom House Bahrain.'■'No. 114 1. c POLITICAL A G K N C Y. &gt; * Bahrain, the 8th November 10 T7. ' To , The Director of Customs, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM. I tour letter No. CG/23 of October 2nd, 10 37. I understand Messrs Gray, Paul and Company are addressing you regarding the issue of shipping order No. 2 1 of October 3 It and^hope that the matter will be adjusted satisfactorily. Captain, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain(3k) No. CG/24 of 1917. CUSTOMS HOUSE, Dated IOth November 1917, H. B. M'b Political Agent Bahrein. Sir, I have the honor to-confirm receipt of yours No:II4I of „ 8th November 1917. ^ * As stated I did get reply from Messrs Gray Paul &amp; Co who state that the sipper informed them that the Customs was closd -^&gt;n the -evening before the steamer left where as the shipper here states that he never came to Customs. But I really regret how could they bellifcve the Customs to be closed on Wednesdays (as the ship 1 ert, this on Thursday). Had it been Friday it wajild have been to a certain extent believable but that too, the Customs was not closed on last Friday. However I have given the man the pass as desired by Messrs - Cray P&amp;ul &amp; Co in lieu of their friendship and have given them • in fnll our arguments for our demand and requested them to arrange to send us the desired manifest copy to which I have got no reply. * In conclusion I request you to kindly so arrange that manifest copy be sent to us regularly as before. I have the honor to be Sir, Your obedient servant 7. i &amp;SL fi f Dj. rector, \W HouseBal Customs HouseBahrein. n s . £ \ —RECOMMENDATION 1 : 0R DISPOSAL RECOMMENDATION SIGNATURE DATE DESTROY AT FIRST REVIEW (i.e. within 5 years) DESTROY AT SECOND REVIEW (i.e. after 25 years) PRESERVE CONSIDER AT FIRST REVIEW CONSIDER AT SECOND REVIEW</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001cd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/958</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001cd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/958</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Customs dues Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-07-17T21:17:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (36 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 36; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-35; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file discusses the decision by Shaikh Isa [ʻIsá ibn ʻAlī Āl Khalīfah] in April 1916 to raise the customs duty on the transhipment of goods through Bahrain, as wartime conditions had resulted in a difficult financial situation for Bahrain.This decision was prompted by a drop in the number of steamers calling at Bahrain and a subsequent rise in the cost of food and other goods which many feared could lead to famine. Included in the file is a petition from a group of Arab merchants to Shaikh Isa asking him to do everything in his power to get more steamers to call at Bahrain to ease the situation.Also included in the file is correspondence with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Chief Political Officer at Basrah [Basra] regarding a complaint from Bin Saud (‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd), Ruler of Najd over the Shaikh of Bahrain's decision to increase transhipment charges. The complaint is dismissed as the political authorities concluded that Shaikh Isa had been well within his rights to increase the customs duty.Other matters discussed in the file include correspondence with F T Maharaj, Director of Customs at Bahrain regarding proposals for the construction of a new pier at Bahrain, and export licences from Bombay for blasting powder and fuses that would be required in the construction work.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs policy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001cd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>