<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003b2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:46:00.829Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ir' THE RSSIiSNCY, ADffl f 20th January 1937. 3ir I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 78035/36 of 4th March 1936 to the India Office, copy of which was communicated to me under India Office endorse ment No. H.3. 1624/1936 of the 12th March 1936, in which approval was &amp;iven to the appointment of Mr. P.C.Davey as my Aide-de-Cainp and Private Secretary for not more than one year in the first instance so as to leave open the question of dealing with the appointment after the separa tion of Aden from India. 2. Mr. Davey’s term of temporary employment will expire on 2nd March 1937. He lias proved himself suitable in every my, and I recommend that, he be confirmed in the post from the date of the termination of his temporary period. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, tSd) B.R.Reilly, Resident etc. The Right Honourable ♦G.A.Omsby G-ore P.C., Secretary of State for the Colonies, Downing Street, 3.7,',1.■JK ft' GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Foreign and Political Department. r 11 5 5 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR i^AlkJ ^ 7 _ [N.B. -This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] 424-3/37. DM N™i*' ihe Pebr!,ar y 197)7. To Secretary of State for India, London. \ Ah\ n Reference ^ telegram Mo.792, aated oth March 1936. Chief jp Commissioner, Aden, in his despatch No.15, dated 20th January 1937, v to Colonial Office (copy to the Government of India) has recommended j confirmation of Davey as liide-de-Camp .and Priv/ite Secretary, with | effect from 3rd March 1937. Government of India have nonobjection. b Would be grateful for early orders of His Majesty’s Government. The issue of the above has been authorised. Ik. Under Secretary to the Government of India. 1 (With 2 Sc.).Draft Paper. P.Z .836/37. (0 / poli ti cal Department. DRAFT LETTER. U.S. of S. , Colonial Office. Express letter from Govt, of India, dated 28th January 1937. Telegram to Government of India d'ated 16th February 1937. A C ° Py t0 r &lt;357 Xir Ministry, with ^reference to Air Ministry letter to Colonial Office of 5th October.^7V|5^ /k fa ' 1 zvt'LC''y r '£ v'' r ! -n s I ;, 0 -8 2 5^31937 Y, POuii.v a. | bUiti-r DEPT. INDIA omct ^ TO_i Accountant-General, for any observations. 2 3 FEB 1937 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of 6th November, No.78035/36, and subsequent correspondence on the subject of the appointment of Flying Officer J.M.Southwell to act as temporary A.D.C. to the Resident at Aden for a period of 3£ months from 2nd September 1936, and to enclose copy of the correspondence noted in the margin. 2. In view of the fact that Flying Officer Southwell was not eligible to draw the pay and allowances of his rank in the Air Force during the period of his secondment, the Secretary of State for India has approved the proposal of the Government of India that he should be granted the ordinary pay of the post during his tenure of the appointment and that Mr.Davey should also be paid his full leave salary during the 16 days of his leave on average pay. 3. In these circumstances Flying Officer Southwell’s pay will presumably be issued from ■ oivili-an funds and will be adjusted through the Aden Civil Accounts in the usual manner, no adjustment with the Air Ministry being required. 4. A copy of this correspondence « is being sent to the Air Ministry. (S^d.) M. J. CLAUSONGOVERNMENT OF INDIA foreign and Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a meane of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No.-'•4778-56. . a Dated —the January 29 57, New Delhi Datei w~h^.Ahe If# January To Secretary of State for India London. Chief Comiiiissioner Aden’s letter ho. 8741 Hovember 28th regarding Southwell’s employment as Aide-de-Camp, a copy of which has been forwarded to the Colonial Office. In view of the circumstances explained therein recommend that Southwell be granted full pay of the post and Lavey may also be allowed to draw his full leave salary for the period of his leave on average pay. \7ould be grateful for sanction by telegram. The issue of the above has been authorised v Under Secretary to the Government of India (Signature) S. 44. MFP—367 S&amp;P—(M-508)—16-7-35—10,060. (Designation)V cLo^tl^oU ( 9 . Dj^&lt;J^vvv^&gt; 0 ^ I ^ 3 (f) . The 15th December 1936. No. 708-E. —Flying Officer J. M. Southwell, Boyal Air Force, is appointed to officiate as Aide-de-Camp, to the Chief Commissioner and Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden, with effect from the afternoon of the 2nd Septembef 1936. Foreign and Political Department, Notifica tion No. 586-E., dated the 15th October 1936, is hereby cancelled.No .51* i 9147 Tho Hesidency R E 0 EIV E D f Ad on» Bee ember 1936 . ■J4D£Ci936 Sir» C. O. HEQ 1 I hevo the honour bo forward for your information copies of my let tor No. 8741 doted 28th November 1936 addressed to the Government of India and of its enclosure# on the subject of the pay and allowances of Flying Officer J.N.Southwell, Royal Air Force my officiating Aide-de-Camp I have the honour to be. Sir# Your most obedient# humble servant# Resident etc. The Right Honourable W.G.A # Orrasby-Gore#P.C.# Secretary of State for the Colonies# London. WBF*Letter No*8741 dated 28th November 1936 from the Chief Commissioner! Aden f to the Foreign Secretary to the Grovernment of India* New Delhi. Subj ect:-Appointment of Flying Officer J.M.Southwell, Aide-de-Camp to the Chief Commissioner and Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden. I have the honour to refer to the Government of 1 ndie Notification No.586-2 datod 15th October 1936 notifying the appointment of Flying Officer J.M.Southwell, Royal Air Force, to officiate as Aide-de-Camp to the Chief Commis sioner and Resident and Comrrrnder-in-Chief, Aden, in addition to hifl O'v n duties with effect from the afternoon » of 2nd September 1936. 2. I have now been informed by the Air Officer Commanding British Forces in Aden, that as Flying Officer Southwell holds a Short Service Commission in the Royal Air Force, he is not eligible for secondment and that he has been wholly released from his duties in the Royal Air Force and granted leave without pay for the period that he is acting as Aide-de-Camp to me. I attach a copy of the Air Officer Commanding's signal No.P-144 dated 17th October 1936 to the Air Ministry who have given their approval. In the circumstances 1 request that an amended Notification be issued deleting the words 'in addition to his own duties.* 3. Further, Flying Officer J.M.Southwell, having been granted leave without pay, draws no salary from the Royal Air Force during the time he acts as Aide-de-Camp and it will therefore be necessary to grant him pay from the Civil Department. 4. The Air Officer Commanding informs me that * lying Officer Southwell's rate of pay in the Royal Air Force was 18s/2d per diem plus 7s/l0id allowance per diem. This MThis amounts to Rs,539 for a month of 31 days and Rs* 522 for a month of 30 days. 5. Mr. Davey has been granted 16 days leave on average pay combined with two months and twenty-nine days Extraordinary Leave* Therefore for the first period of 16 days there will be two officers drawing the Mde-de- Gamp's rate of pay. I recommend that * lying Officer Southwell be permitted to draw the same rate of pay as the Aide-de-Camp viz. Rs.566-11-0 per mensem for the period of his employment as Aide-de-0p,mp. This will amount to Rs*lf983-6-0 less the difference of he officiating allowances of Ra.388-15-0 which/is at present receiving at Ra. 111/2/• par mensem. It will also be seen that this proposal involves a small increase of Rs.302/3/- as both Mr. Davey and Flying Officer Southwell will be drawing pay during the 16 days leave period of the former on average pay. The amount involved is small and I recommend that it be sanctioned. 6. I suggest that the expenditure be met from the anticipated savings of Rs.2,700/- under ’Non-Voted* already reported to Government for surrender under my letter No.8164 dated 7th November 1936. 7. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Colonial Office./ xo•••• A.H.Q. Aden. From., lir Ministry. P.144 17th October. Your P.37 of 1 Oct. Officers selected for A.D.C. epoointments nre normally seconded from Koyal Air Force for period of appointment but as F/0 Southwell holds Short Service Commission he is not eligible for such secondment antf it is necessary to make special arrangements. It is proposed that officer should be granted leave without pay during period of detachment from air force duty. Such period will not count as service on the active list or towards short service gratuity but his active list service will be extended by the amount of bbave taken. Colonial Office have been asked to accept cost of officers pay and allowances as a charge against their votes, disability or death arising out o' officers employment while on leave would not bo regarded as attributable to conditions of R.A.F.Service for purposes of retired pay or pension or for medical treatment. Officei should not be reouired to carry out flying practice during present appointment. Final arrangements will be signalled as soon as possible.REFERRED TO CluAsT Dept.(Mu, &lt;5^ v^^.^anications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following Number quoted: 78035/36. Sir, p. z 7 ~] 7 O P 7 J / u U V J Dovming Street. 9 36 NovemUer, 1936. '' n r o. / i I am directed by Mr. Secretary Ormsby Gore to enclose a copy of correspondence with the Air Ministry on the subject of the appointment of Flying Officer J.M. Southwell to act as temporary Aide-de- Camp to the Resident at Aden for a period of 3^ months 2. It has been ascertained from the Air Ministry that Flying Officer Southwell will receive x pay and allowances appropriate to his rank in the .r Force. 3. On the assumption that the Secretary of State for India in Council has no objection, a claim for a moiety of the charges made by the Air Ministry will be debited to the India Office in the books ofy COPY, 549345/36/3. 7. A. AIR MINISTRY, LONDON, ¥.0.2. 5th October, 1936. Sir, I am commanded by the Air Council to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for the Colonies, that the Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in Aden, has, at the request of the Acting Resident, detailed a Royal Air Force officer to act as temporary Aide-de-Camp for a period of 3-J months during which the Aide-de-Camp to the Resident will be on leave. 2. Flying Officer J.M. Southwell was selected for this appointment, the duties of which necessitate his entire detachment from air force duty. Officers selected for Aide-de-Camp appointments are normally seconded from the Royal Air Force for the period of the appointment, but as Flying Officer Southwell holds a short service commission he is not eligible for such secondment and it is necessary to make special arrangements in his case. 3. Similar circumstances obtained in the case of Flying Officer M.N. Oxford who was appointed as Acting Aide-de-Camp to the Acting High Commissioner for Iraq in 1931, vide Colonial Office letter 88343/31 of the 15th October, 1931, and the Council consider that the conditions approved for that appointment would satisfactorily meet the present case, except that it does not appear necessary to fix a special rate of emoluments for the appointment. 4 . The Under Secretary of State. Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W. 1.4* In this event Plying Officer Southwell would he granted leave without pay during the period of his detachment from air force duty, which commenced on the 2nd September, 1936, and his pay and allowances for this period would he chargeable to Colonial Office Votes. The Council would be glad to learn at an early date whether the Secretary of State is prepared to agree to these arrangements. 5. I am to point out that disability or death arising out of the officer^ employment while on leave would not be regarded as attributable to conditions of Royal Air Force service for the purposes of retired pay or pension or for medical treatment. j. am, etc. , (3gd. ) J.3. Ross• 1956 . Sir* X am directed by Ur* secretary Oraeby Gore to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 5th of October, No. 549345/36/3.7. A. regarding the appointment of Flying Officer J.M. Southwell as temporary Aide-de-Camp to the Resident at Aden for a period of 3^ months and to request you to inform the Secretary of state for Air that the arrangements referred to in that letter are agreed to. 2. Accordingly, on the receipt of a claim for the pay and allowances of Flying Officer Southwell for the period of his service as Alde-de-Caap adjust ment will be effected direct with the Air Ministry. 3. a copy of this correspondence is being forwarded to the India Office as a moiety of the charges involved will fall to be borne on the revenues of the Jovemment of India. I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant. THisI 33CE3fASY, AIM MINISTRY. ©lgm.&lt;rn H ft OOWEI4.EXTRACT PROM THE ADEN GAZETTE DATED 12th SEPTEMBER 1936. No._6554, dated Aden, 9th September 1936. Reference this Residency Notification No.1721, dated 10th March 1936. Mr•P.C.Davey, Aiae—de—Gamp and Private Secretary to the Ghiet Commissioner and Resident and Commander—in— Chief, is granted, under Supplementary Rule 285 leave on average pay for 16 days combined with 2 months and 29 days Extraordinary leave with effect from the afternoon of 2nd September 1936. Plying Officer J.M.Southwell, Royal Air Force,is appointed to act as Aide-de-Camp to the Chief Commissioner and Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden, with effect from the afternoon of 2nd September 1936 vice Mr.P.C.Davey.EXTRACT PROM THE ADEN GAZETTE DATED 14th MARCH 1936. No. 1721, dated Aden, the IQth Mamh 1936. Reference this Residency Notification No.8694, dated 18th December 1935. With the approval of His Majesty’s Government and of the Government of India, Mr.P.C. Davey is appointed Aide-de-Camp and Private Secretary to the Chief Commissioner and Resident and Commander-in-Chief, Aden, with effect from the forenoon of 3rd March 1936, vice Lieutenant P.R. Hulton, Royal Artillery, transferred.Extract from Suppl e mentary Rul es. (Made by the Governor-General in Council under the fundamental rules.) Divisi on XVI II. Leave earned by temporary and o fficiating servic e. ^Rules made by the Governor-General in Council under fundamental rule 103 Other Government servants. 285. ; Leave may be granted to any other Government servant without a lien on a permanent post while officiating in a post or holding a temporary post, provided that the grant of the leave involves no expense to Government.) On this condition such a Government servant may be granted - (a) leave on leave-salary equivalent to full pay up to one-eleventh of the period spent on duty, subject to a maximum of four months at a time, or (b) on medical certificate, leave on leave- salary equivalent to half pay for three months at any one time, or (c) extraordinary leave for three months at any i one time. Exception . In the case of a Government servant officiating in a permanent post, or holding a temporary post, in a vacation department, leave granted under clause (a) of this rule shall be on leave-salary equivalent to half-pay; provided that such a Government servant may be granted, under the clause, leave on leave-salary equivalent to full pay to the extent of one month for each year of duty in which he has not availed himself of any part of the vacation.Chief Commissioner, Aden, and repeated by the former to Secretary of State for India* Dated New Delhi, 16th April, 1936* Reoelwed 16th April, 1936, 6*45 p*m* 388~H* Your telegram 2496j 9th April. No objection to DaYey wearing proposed uniform. Addressed Chief Commissioner, Aden; repeated Secretary of State for India. rr 17 APR 192 'PPiCFA\t±9 vD FILE COPY * - &gt; • : 2430 19-3 « I (59 words.) D &amp; C 0 D E 1976 . OF TELEGRAM. From Chief CoimiiBSioner„ Aden, to Foreign Secretary to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, and repeated by , ^ former to Secretary of State for India. Dated Aden, 9th April, 1936. ^r\ ' Received 2.30 p.m., 9th April, 1936. ^496. Your telegram dated March 15th approving of the appointment of Davey as my A.D.C. and private secretary. May be authorise (sic) to wear uniform of Government of India civil officer in civil employ f fifth class, as sanctioned in your telegram 1226-E dated September 22nd, 1930, to Government of Bombay, • in the case of Jackson, who was A.D.C. to Sir Stewart Symes from 1930 to 1931. Addressed Foreign, Dow Delhi, repeated to Colonial Office and India Office.FiLt ‘ / gch/aw. (2 1 8 7 3 193 (&gt; |3». iCw- DBCYPHER Qg T E L -S G R A M. rrj if ( ° 1532/ ^ Vj Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Chief Commissioner, Aden, and repeated by former to Secretary of State for India. New Delhi, 14th March, 1936« Received 14th March, 193^ ,8*45 p.m s XXX 6j?4. Addressed to Chief Commissioner, Aden, and repeated to Secretary of State for India* Your telegram of the 24th ultimo, 15. Appointment of Davey as your Aide-de-Camp sanctioned on the terms approved by the Secretary of State in his telegram 792, March 5th. r ? ■ MAR 1936 W** - c78035/36 Colonial Office, Downing Street, S.W.l. , d March, 1936. liy dear Claus on, Will you please refer to your letter No.P.Z.1352/1936 of the 27th February regarding the appointment of an Aide-de-Camp and Private Secretary to Reilly at Aden? We have now received a second telegram from Aden dated the 3rd March on this subject. The telegram has been repeated to the India Office.. We have been considering the matter and, so far as we are concerned, we are prepared to agree to the appointment of Davey at a salary of Rs.6,800 per annum, and have no objection to his appointment being designated Aide-de-Camp and private Secretary. While we agree that the appointment should be on an indefinite agreement, we think that the Resident should make it clear to Davey that the M. J. CLAUSON, ESQ* Ef:CLOSURE IN WEEKLY Lrrf#n appointment 11 12 mar 1936 rCUY;CAL AND DIPT. INDIA OFFICE to. F.iO, I 0GPY SENT Tilappointment is for a period of not longer than a year in the first instance. This will leave open for later consideration the question of how the appointment is to be dealt with after the transfer takes place. If you agree, perhaps you will telegraph accordingly. Yours sincerely, * * *Q' V p\L£-C-OP^ j , z*. f 4 3&gt; 1 5 5 6 19 3 3 SECRET /Qsr' - W C^) Q^ 2 - , /'/ ^ A UCA1M, (67 groups*) (COPIES CIRCULATED) O JLI-P HER OF TELEGRAM, i.&lt;rom Chief Coznmissioner, Aden, bo Secretary of State for India* repeating telegram addressed to Government of'India, Foreign and Political Department,, XXX Dated Aden, 3rd March, 1936. Received 10.40 a.m., 3rd March, 1936. Jit 11/M^ Addressed to Foreign, Delhi, repeated to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (India Office) and Colonial Office,, fafX f Reference my tele gram 15, da ted 24th February, I shall be giatefiu for the appointment of Davey as Hulton is under orders of transfer to India and, for reasons explained, no other officer of the garrison can take his place* As an Aide~de~ Camp ia necessary, Dayey is now commencing work and I am anxious to regularise his appointment at once* It will be terminable on either side at any time* *in SECRET xt/jgs/shb/wb DBCTPHEB Proa (COPIES CIRCUIATED) i -! o c; 9 ^ ■ { 117 g¥oTipHT-)— “ - isD^vt-Ct 1137 ” OP TELEGRAM, yc[7~* Resident and Coimiander in Chief, Aden, to GrOYernment of India, Foreign and Political Department, and repeated by former to Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Aden, 24th February, 1936 0 Received 2 porno, 24th February, 1936, XXX v&gt; rt\ 4 S?f 15o Addressed to Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India, repeated to Secretary of State for India and Colonial Office 0 Referring to my telegram 2, January 8tho Air Officer Commanding unable to furnish Aide-de-camp to replace Hulton, March 1st, as only possible Qi$i~ /i» officer has accepted employment elsewhereo Subject to your approval, I propose to appoint Davey on an indefinite agreement on payment of Rs:6,800 per annum on analogy of appointment of Jackson in 1930, vide Bombay Gazette notification, 5711-16076, November 21st, 1930o Davey is available in Aden immediately p and is son of the late Charles Davey who was Government Agent at Perimo He is 21, educated Eastbourne College, knows colloquial ArabiCo I recommend appointment be designated Aide-de-Camp and Private Secretary as before 0 Grateful for immediate reply 0/ KB/AW. # J O k &gt; (4 (19 groups) . © SECRET Vn? V&amp;iK:' 238,i.Puarbwj iACft BBCYPHSR Qg T g L S 0 R A Prom (C0PXB8 circulatbe) Dated Government of indl*, reign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram addressed to Aden* Hew Delhi, 15th January, 1936. Received 15th January, 1936, 1.15^^.^ y$i. : 130 , -M Addressed to Chief Commieaioner, Aden, repeated to Secretary of State for India* Your telegram of the 8th instant, 2, Ho objection to your postponing question of the selection of the permanent Aide-de-camp for the present* pai. dipt, i EUAH1S36 V' OFFICEIT/MiL FILE COPY ¥ . zr 210 (111 groups*) © SECRET (COPIES CIRCULATED) DJLCJ LP-H E R OF T E T, E (, RAM. From Resident and Commander in Chief, Aden, to Government of India, Foreign and Political Eepartment, and repeated to Secretary of State for India* XXX Dated Aden, 8th January, 1936* Received 3p.m*, 8th January, 1936, Addressed to Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India, repeated to Secretary of State for India* (p_ ^our telegram o:i the 7th instant, 36, Owing to difficulty in obtaining: permanent Aide-de-camp, I have been privately enquiring about a relative of mine now in England, who might be suitable and whose name I am thinking of submitting to Govofnment if he is able ci.ad willing bo be appointed* Meanwhile, Air Officer Commanding 5 Auen, has agreed, subject to possible military requirements, to continue providing me with a local military Aide-de-camp until the summer, when Colonial Office have unofficially told me that, if my present appointment is extended and subject tc approval of the Government of India, they wish me to go to England to discuss details connected with transfer and future administration reports icr Aaen* I, therefore, suggest that selection of permanent aide-de-camp be postponed (? omission) I am ir. England, when I can personally see Prinsep and any other candidates who may be available*— 0 &gt; r\ fyl IT/DIA. FlU*i : ; 182 ! 1030 (49 groups) -E—G-S I_E_l4_E_S_B_A_M&lt; SECRET Prom (COPIES CIICULATED) Dated Received Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, to Chief Commissioner, Aden, and repeated to Secretary of State for India, New Delhi, 7th January, 1936, 7th January, 1936, 6 p.m. xxx £6« Addressed to Chief Comnissioner, Aden, sent to Secretary of State for India# Correspondence ending with your telegram of the 4th ultimo, 120. Major D.Wo Macleod Prlnsep, late Skinner's Horse, Is willing to accept employment as your Aide-de-camp on teims proposed in our telegram 2841, October 11th, 1935 Prinsep is a widower« Please telegraph whether you have any objection.FIL£_£QeY ( T&gt; 7,, ^ n’/Aw a (6£: groups) ; Li 7 09 i'': 6316, D 3 0 Y PHBR OB TELEGRAM. Prom {COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Re»id€!nt and Commander-* in-Chief at Aden to Foreign Secretary to GoTermnent of India, Foreign and Political Department and repeated by former to Secretary of State for Indiac Aden, 4th Be camber P 1935* XXX ReceiTed 4th December, 1935,, XX o 30 a a m 9 V 120 , Addressed to Foreign and repeated to Secretary of State for India, My telegram of the 30th ultimo, Morphew, My present aj.de-da-camp leaves Aden for India this month and I have obtained temporary loan of services of Lieut, F c R^Hulton f R 0 A«&gt; as aide-de-camp from December X5th, I am writing to ask for his appointment to be gazetted, HuXton is due to leave Aden towards the end of February,fkb/dia From Chief Commissioner, /\aen 9 zo B-£JLX.ffiER &lt; (COPIES CIECULATED) Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department„ and repeated by former to Secretary of State for India, Dated Aden, 22nd November* 1935« Received 22nd November, 1935, 2-45 p,m, xxx yi^ ll3. o Addressed to Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India, repeated to Secretary of State for India* Your telegram of the 20th instant, 3138* I do not wish to have Grice as Aide«de~Camp, I have met him and do not consider him to be suitable, and, in any case, married Aide-de~ Camp would not be satisfactory* I shall be glad if post can be filled as proposed in your telegram of the 11th ultimo, 2841* If this cannot be done at once, I suggest temporarily continuing previous plan of appointing political probationer as personal assistant*PBCYPHBB OF TELEGRAM. Prom GoYernment of India, Foreign and (COPIES Political Department, to Chief CIRCULATED) Commissioner, Aden, and repeated to .Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Kew Delhi, 30th November, 1935 Received 11 0 45 a 0 m e , 30th November, 1935, XXX — . 3138 0 Addressed to Chief Commiesioner, Aden, sent to Secretary of State for India 0 Correspondence ending with your telegram of the 34th ultimo r 99 0 A subaltern CoWoSo Grice, 3^19 Hyderabad Regiment, has since become available for employment as your Aide-de-Campo Please telegraph if you have any objection 0I* Draft Paper. P.Z.7665/35. Department. 0 4 f\ U.3.S. , C.O. I.J.1EDIATE. Sir, 8 K G. of I. telegram of 11th October, No.2841 / iij .. CD { I- Q- O ‘ft *”7 i&gt; r * /' f - * . L- i , i'jLi lA'tn, r'vt* 1 *' ui' ■tk j 4 T- ^ ^ f , dJ ^ r J- n f r w« r&lt; s. of s. telm. of 23rd October No.3415 Aden telm. of 24th October, No.99. I am directed by the S/S for I. to r efer i m r..n. —cUe-—letter of 2nd - ^tGry 1935~ and uonu ect^ d^ corresp 0n denc i regarding the^Personal Assistant to tl e Resident at Adeiy^and to forward a coj y of the telegram noted in the margin * far ? , regarding the filling o ^ thB^r-^vstjr I am to enquire whether the S/S r the Colonies agrees to the appoint ment and rate of pay proposed, i.e. Rb. 700 per mensem. j%. It will be observed that the G.cf I. do not mention pension or passage contributions. The Marquess of Zetltnd proposes to ascertain the^G^—ef I »-*-0 intention in regard to these two poinls but would suggest that their con siden tion can be reserved for future discussion and need not delay the decision upon the main question. 9.Z- I am also to forward a copy of the telegrams noted in the margin froi which it will be seen that the Chief Commissioner at Aden has agreed in principle to G. of I.»s proposals. The favour of an early reply i£ requested. 0. WALlOiS, 3761 5000 5.35Nt)€&gt; FILE &gt;Z. ) 7655 1955 j SECRET 7i?(. jgs/dia. (42 groups) 5707, 73&lt;?3. • flJLCJLE-tLBLS- „?,£ ,-U, l From Chief Commissioner 3 Men, to Secretary of State for India* (COPIES Dated Aden, 34th Octobers, 1935* CIBOULATED) Received 34th October, 1935, 11*15 a^nu XXX 1^- 9g® Mdressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Government of India* Reference to your telegram of the 33rd instant, 3415, addressed to Government of India* Following was my reply to Government of India telegram 3841 s 11th October* IQQ* Your telegram of the 11th instant, 2841« I agree, but request that officer selected he not too seniorofhb/dia. '.^7 % • ‘7 f: 9 groups) ^ u O 5677* X JE-L_K Gram . From Dated Received Government of India, Foreign aad Political Department to Secretaiy of State for India. New Delhi, 22nd October, 1935, 22nd October, 1935, 4..30 p 5 m„ 1209*. instant, 2841, reply. Our telegram of the llth Would be grateful for earlyTelegram from Govt, of India, For. &amp; Pol. Dept., to S. of S. for India, d/- 11th October 1935. The Military Secretary T s circular has not resulted in any applications being received for the appointment of AJ3.C. from officers of the Indian Army. This is with reference to our telegram No.£542 of the 20th September. No British Service officers are availabl owing to existing shortage. It is therefore proposea to send you a suitable officer from those about to be retrenched from the War Block years for a period of 2 year on a rate of Rs.700 per mensem in addition to pay allowed for special unemployed list. It is hoped that you will agree and telegraph your reply urgently. Addressed to Chief Commissioner Aden, and repeated to Secretary of State for India with request that he obtains the agreement of the Colonial Office.SECRET © 692 ^ 2 . 73 &lt;Wj 5 \ NT*'*' (68 groups) 5522 c O^SXP HSR OJL-^XJJUl£JJLik From Grovernment of India ? Foreign and Political Department y .to Secretarv of Rtfif.A for TnrHa (COPIES CIRCULATED) XXX Dated Simla, 11th October, 1935* Received 1*30 pdiu, 11th October, 1935 (Y ^ SMLs, Qur telegram_of^ the 20bh ultimo, £M2 . No Indian Army officer has applied for the post of Aide~de~Camp in response to Military Secretary's circular* Owing to shortage, no officers in the British service are available* Propose, therefore, send you suitable war block officer for two years on fixed pay of Rso700 per mensem exclusive of special unemployed pay 0 Trust you will agree* Please telegraph reply urgently* Addressed to Chief Commissioner, Aden, repeated to Secretary of State for India with request that agreement of the Colonial Office may be obtained,. &amp;H v . ^ tloiaalai Office 78035/35. Downing Street, S.W.l July, 1935. &lt;rtP J~ My dear Walton Your letter of the 13th June P.Z. 3968/35 about the performance of the duties of the Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden. We see no objection to the proposal in the telegram from the G-overnment of India of the 7th of June concerning the employment of Lieutenant Morphew. Yours sincerely, C*'- J. 0. WALTON, ESQ.FILE COPY / h. JU. JGS/1)IA. (71 woni \ 1 '.j O i E) 19 b 5 j 3083 U .E-C, ..Q D i: ■ Q.p _X £_ L...E G RAM, From Goverment of India» Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla P 7th June, 1935. Received 7th June, 1935, 3^30 p c m Q yf?/£ , Cotton, Political probationer, who wae employed as Personal Assistant to the Chief Commissioner, Aden, left for Abyssinia to take up his special duties. He will thereafter be sent to the Punjab for district training. As no Political Officer will be available until October, Chief Comaaissioner has employed, from 30th May, Lieutenant Morphew, RoA« , to perform the duties of his AoD.C* in addition to his own duties. Trust His Majesty*s Government have no objection to this arrangement and to the grant to Morphew of the usual allowance of £100 per annum, your telegram dated 6th July, No,1701.Jr /z ^ /ff &gt;C Golonial Office, Dovming Street,S^W*1. ^ July, 1934. My dear Laithwaite, Your letter of 26th June, P &gt;4188/3 4, about the performance of the duties of Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden. We see no objection to the proposal of the Government of India. Yours sincerely. _ J.G. LAI mil Tii, ESQ.,J6XED file COPY b J */&gt;' Jr. JL 4188 wn.-'- araean: CT-io FCK/MMo (70 words) 3629 0 D_B,0 0 D B OF T E I» E G R A M. From GoYernment of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 22nd June, 1934. Received 1 0 45 pom*, 22nd June, 1934&lt; ^4 471-J2o Burton, political probationer, at present personal assistant to the Chief Commissioner, Aden, will he sent to the Punjab for training on the 1st July, As no Political Officer will be available until the autumn, it is proposed to employ R.P.Dodson Mackenzie, R.A., to perform the duties.of A.D.C. in addition to hie military duties, Trust His Majesty's Government will have no objection to proposed arrangement and to grant to Dodson Mackenzie of allowance of £100 per annum, vide Colonial Office letter l^vh May, 1933, enclosure to weekly letter ROo20, 18th May, 1933 0t 17935/33. /*v (No.P.Z.2682/33) of the 10th of kay enclosing a copy of a telegram from the Crovernment of India about the performance of the duties of Personal Assistant to the Ohief Gommissioner. We see no objection to approval being given to the proposed arrangements. letter of the 9th of May numbered as above stating that the War Office and the Treasury have agreed to the grant of an allowance at the rate of £100 per annum to a local military officer appointed to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Resident during the Personal Assistants absence on leave. You will by now have received our Yours sincerely, C) '.PV BY AIK MAIL ENCLOSURE NO. 20 18 MAY, 1935 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE 4Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following r^'jmber quoted : 17 93 5/33. j\ Sir, With reference to the letter from this Department of the 12th of April, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister to request you to inform Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare that the sanction of the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury and of the Army Council has now been obtained for the payment of an allowance at the rate of £100 per annum to the local Military Officer appointed to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden during the Personal Assistants absence on leave. 2. Their Lordships have also agreed to the refund to the Resident of the sum paid by him to the Military Officer, who acted in this capacity in June last, and to a charge to United Kingdom funds of a moiety of the sum thus refunded. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant, THE UNDER SECRETARY OE STATE, Q 0 p Y SENT BY AIR MAIL of INDIA OFFICE.S(i “ .7 i . .ii602/;&gt;3. INDIA OFFIC.i, vMiim&amp;u., d.- 10th la* 1933. 1. -_/ H.H. Dowell Colon ii a* ^ dear Caweli 9 I enclose copy oX a telegram from the Govem&amp;ent of India which is, I think, self-explanatory,, fhere has been considerable discussion between our two departments am the far Office in regard to the grant of an allowance to a military officer lent to perform the auties of personal Assistant to toe Chief Uombdssioner ana I understand that the i&amp;r Of a. ice have now agreed to waive their objections to the grant of such remuneration in tne special circumstances of Aden and that the Colonial Office have received Treasury sanction to an arrangement of this nature* 2* I trust in these circumstances that you will see no objection to the gr-nt of approval to the Government of India's proposal* The case is in any event very straightforward, for the War office have never, I think, taken exception to the grunt of an , *M&gt;t C.k.Gi, “ ei&lt; * w “ ' WfEKLr L€Trti a * 1,M ' / 1 oHlc ] NO. .19 II.HAY. (933 | aCM SiiCRETARV pq:: T! .. L Secr et dept, india office °allowance wfcen the post can he regarded as vacant and, as you will see. Hie Government of India emphasise taut in the circumstances described by them it will be permanently vacant for all practical purposes* Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAITE.rr FILE COPY PZ - r\ r- f -\ ' ) ,1 O J / ’933 f/s/y s l! 1, ftli JG-S/MM (52 words) D-J-C--Q—DJ.— - a F T E L £ a R A M, 2630 Prom Dated Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of Stale for India, Simla, 5th May, 1933*&gt; Received 7,15 a^rru 5th May, 1933, 4 12E, Rose, Personal Assistant to the Chief Commissioner, Aden, has been granted long leave from early in June on the grounds of health. He will not return to Aden on the expiration of his leave. As no political officer will be available until the autumn, Reilly proposes to appoint, in the meanwhile, Lieutenant K.A.P, Fergusson^ Royal Artillery, to perform the duties of A.D.C, in addition to his own duties, military duties, on an allowance at the rate of £100 per annum. Rose ? who is on deputation while holding post of Personal Assistant to the Chief Commissioner^will automatically revert to Political Department cadre when he relinquishes charge, and will proceed on leave. The post of Personal Assistant will therefore be permanently vacant for all practical purposes. In the circumstances, we trust there will be no objection to grant to Fergusson of proposed allowance; half of which will be debited to Colonial revenue. Should be grateful for orders by telegram. .I © INDIA OF/IGS t • v an 1 ill ALL, W* I • istli April 1933 ly dear i-etCAlfe, I write in continuation ol my d.O. of 17tli February, no, P.Z.841/S3, about the payment of an allo*;a3ce to a local Military Officer appointed b. the / Ohlef Goihiiasioner at Aden to perfona the duties of ioroonal Assiatant, to enclose copy of further correspondence, from which you will sea that the Aar Office have now waived their objection unu that the Colonial Office have approached the freasury for approval of proposals on the lines previously mentioned to you. As the « r Office have been the real obstacle so far we very much hope that a solution on the lines aesired is now in sight. Yours sincerely J.G. LAITH?/AIT«; Xfce , MrtcalXe, * i * * # M* J t ^oreigii to tae Govermtat of Inula,,B 12b Communications on this subject shoi;ld be addressed to— The UndeksSecretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— I P.Z. 2128 ^ 'CZlAt- e*-0 'TuXstCf- £ fi ■4 , flu /favUa A*—y* &amp;LM. 9 ° Reference to 'previous correspondence: '\ 0 Letter jy^ m the Colonial Office of the «2^/ ^^C^\*^cKAy /^33 Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the17935/33. 2128 ia33 1 2 A P m &gt;lr, fith reference to the letter from this Department of the 8th of December, 1952, fto.97885/32&gt; ;^y and subsequent semiofficial correspondence regarding the payment of an allowance to the local military officer appointed to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden during the substantive holder*s absence on leave, I am directed to transmit to you, to be laid before the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury* copies of further corresoondence vrith the v/ar Office on the subject. 2* In view of the fact that the Army Council have now waived their objections to the grant of such an allowance, I am to request their Lordships 1 sanction for the payment of an allowance at the rate of £100 per annum to the military officer who acts as Personal \ Assistant 333 CHj -TARY, TREASURY,Assistant to the Resident during the Personal Assistant’s absence on leave, and for the refund to wie Resident of the sum of £4.3 # 4d. paid by him to the military officer who acted in this capacity in June last. I am, oir, Your most obedient serv-nt. (Signed) H. R. OOWELL./' COPY 2128 'm WAR OFFICE v LQXDOli, a.W.l. 8th March, 1933 0179/98 (y.2.) 31r I am commanded by the Army Council to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 23rd .February, 1933, ho, 17935/33, relative to the payment of an allowance to the local military officer appointed to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden* to Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister*a representa tions regarding the nature of the appointment and they are now prepared, in view of the special circumstances, to waive their objections to the issue of remuneration at the rate of £100 a year to the military officer who is called upon to perform the duties of the Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden during the Personal Assistants absence on leave* is filling a substantive vacancy the position is as stated in paragraph 5 of your letter. The Council have given careful consideration I am to confirm that when a military officer I am, etc*, (ogd.) A.h. Widdows. The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office,(Ill 188) Wt 14425/2914 10,000(2) 10/32 HASP Gp 112 ^12 b Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— p / -t!• A • I 0Q7 £ U J / Titwt- Subject: (X** aMir*&gt;&amp; fax- / J Reference to previous correspondence: Letter to fmn vJ^ of the /tf \r 1 ' ^ Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER No. 9 2 hiAit 1835 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Colonial Office, Downing Street, /o /© 193./ .iir I em directed Ijgr iir Philip eunliff®»liat«r to say that Ho Has Had oador Ills eoasidorattoa your lottor of the 24th .ior«^bor 9 So# 01*?9/^8 (?,2) on tho aubjoot of tho p^fsaont of an allowance to the local military officer appointed to perform tho duties of Fersonal Assistant to tho Resident at Aden during June 1932, which has also been the eubjoet of informal discussion between tho departments concerned, 2* iir Philip Cunl iff lister now diroots me to say that ho fully appreciates the importance att ched by the Amy Council to the maintenance of the principle embodied in Amy Regulations that the duties of an officer on leave *h 11 be performed without extra expense to public funds and that in conee^uenee no officer tlijt i&gt; d .d of -itim. WAR Of FICR .officer ©an re©©I t© additional payment for ©arrylng on thooo duties. He does not in toy way 4©elre to eonteat the principle in qtuootion or to suggest ienmant of it. dut in His view the payment now under consideration presents &lt;guito apeeial features of its own and, in the light of a fuller explanation ef the position, ho would suggost timt the xmy Council mitiht find it possible to ‘.-gree that, without prejudice to the principle, spec 11 arrangemento might he made to covor the infrequent oaooo which may from time to time occur of tho temporary perform* nee by a military officer stationed at Men ef the dutiee ef l&gt;ers©it&amp;l Aooistant to the He si dent during the absence on leave of tho subst^ntivo incumbent in addition to hie own military duties. ft. the duties of the post in question are essentially of a civil character. Tho post n*y be. and has in fact invariably, since the Eesident at Men cessed te be General Officer Cemmanding at that post in 1937. boon held either by s civilian or by a retired military officer. Moreover, coy allowance granted te a temperasy incumbent is paid from civil funds and no part4* part of it i« borne by the war Office* The Secretary ef State ie eatiefied from the an iuirie» which he has made that it ie eeeentiel to the eetiofnctory performnnee of the duties of the Beeldent that that officer should hare at hie dispeeaX a Personal Aeeist mt and that great iaeonrenicnoe ia caused by *iy vacancy in the appoint* »ent, even for a very brief period of time* In the paet 9 ae the nay Council are aware, it has been found possible to meet difficulties caused by brief leave vacancies by arrangement with the Officers Ci—lending the military unite stationed at Ade^ who have been good though to mofce available the services of one of their officers* But the iscretary ef State is apprehensive that difficulty ary be found in securing the services of an officer if he is required not merely to underVdce duties additional to his ordinary military work but receives no r&amp;sunsr&amp;tion of Any kind in respect of his duty as Personal Assistant. The post of Personal Assistant does not unfortunately carry any allowance which could be made available for a temporary incumbent.4* Having regard to these circumstances and to the difficulties which might be caused to the Resident by the absence of afiy officer ^aho could ( in emergency erising out of the le^ve of the substantive incumbent^ yerfom the duties of Personal Assistant, the Secretary of 3tate would venture to suggest that the Army Council might be prepared to consider the matter further and to agree, ae a special case and without prejudice to the general principle referred to above, that, in nuch emergencies, a Military officer permitted to act &amp;e Person &amp; Assistant should receive remuneration at the rate of *&amp;GO per annum, which has In previous correspondence been generally agreed ae a suitable figure. 5. Vhe Secretary cf it»te uacieretande from previous correspondence that the difficulties seen by the Amy Council apply only in the case of officers appointed to officiate in leave vacancies and that, if and when m Army officer is allowed to act as Personal ao sistunt luring a substantive vacancy in the pest, they would net (on the understanding that such acting service was for a limited period only) secT' P-^.9172/3. D 'V ^ ? J 'j / i v*^ y TREASURY CHAMfeERSjQ WHITEHALL 7th February, 1933. Lear Howard, Consideration of your letter of the 16th ultimo (17935/33) has necessarily had to he deferred during the busy period of 'Estimates' 1 . Would it not he hest if you sent now to the War Office the reasoned and persuasive letter of which you speak? If it produces a favourable response then we can do what is necessary without having to treat the present case specially and without prejudice. Best to avoid 'special cases' if at all possible. Reilly paid the allowance in the full knowledge that sanction for payment hc.d been refused so he cannot grumble at either further delay or even an ultimate refusal. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) H.R. Foyle. wDraft Paper. pz 33 I pclitical Department. D^^ 1 T The Hon'Tle Ar. H.A.F. Metcalfe, #-» ^ . I. , k. /.O. , Sgpaty Secy, to the G.of I. F.&amp; P« Depb. rtrnent. 1C P H ’ 5000 11.3: TTFJ. 17 FEB 1353 Ivy dear Metcalfe, tAJiy thanks for your letter of the 24th January about the payment of an allowance to a local military officer appointed by the Chief Commissioner of Aden to perform the auties of Personal assistant. The position is briefly that the 'Jar Office, on general grounds of principle, maintain that tney cannot make any payment to a military officer who performs auty during the leave of a substantive incumbent.. Tne conaitions at Aaen are obviously rather special ana both we ana the Colonial Office (with tne sympathy of the Treasury) have done our utmost to 3ring tne War Office round on this point (not only with reference to the Immediate case of the A.D.C. who was employed in June 1932, but with a /lew to reaching sane sort of permanent arrangement.) with this end in view we hau an informal aiscussion on the 13th January which was attended by the 7/ar Office and Colonial Office. The War Office emphasised that they attach great importance to the point of principle, but/but were ultimately persuaded to agre$ that conuitions at xvuenvare somewhat special. It was ueciaea tnat trie i simplest course woulu he that the | Go Ion la 1 Of f ic e shouId in the f or st ^ place ask the Treasury Tor approval, in the inaiviaual case which has been under consideration,Tor a reTuna to iteilly oT the amount which he had paid , out oT his own pocket, this to he without prejuaice to the decision as ^ regards the Tuture,[ana that rth^ysholl then write a persuasive letter to the War OTTice Con the general lines oT the araTt oT which I enclose a copy) setting out in greater detail than had hitherto been aone the arguments in Tavour oT a- special arrangement at ; z 4 (OL, Art ^ Aden. 7/hile the War ^TTice representatives coula not commit their Department, we were given to unaerstand jthat such an approach woula he sympathetically consiaerea. 3. We will keep you in touch with any developments and will do^ our utmost to get things settled on lines satisTactory to the Aesiaent ana the Government oT India. Yours sincerely, J. G. LAITHWAITE./•/ould you please refer to my demi-official letter NO.D.5646-E/32, dated the 15th September 1932, regarding the payment of an allowance to a local Military Officer appointed by the Chief Commissioner of Aden to perform the duties of Personal Assistant, I gather from the Colonial Office letter No, 97885/32 of the 8th December 1932 with enclosure addressed to the Secretary of the Treasury(copy sent here with the India Office letter No.50,dated the 15th December 1932) that the ./ar Office refused to sanction any payment solely on the ground that under British Army Regulations, the duties of any Officer on leave have to be performed without extra expense to public funds. I have discussed the matter with Reilly during his visit to Delhi and it seems to us that this argument is hardly applicable to the present case. The Officer who went on leave was a Civil Officer and any Civil Officer appointed to perform his duties would have been entitled under Civil Rules to receive additional payment forperforming Civil duties during the oeriod of the Civil Officer^ leave should not be entitled to the benefit of Civil Rules, especially as we are not asking the 7ar Office to pay. Reilly points out that the decision is likely to be embarrassing if it is followed in future, since it will effectually prevent him from giving his Civil Personal Assistant short leave in future. He finds that the grant of a few weeks leave to his Personal Assistant is of considerable advantage, since it enables young Officers of the Political Department to go across to the African Coast for sport and recreation which is good for him and also popularises service at Aden. Such a concession will not be possible, if the Chief Commissioner cannot count on getting a young Military Officer on loan for this short period to carry on with the Personal Assistant T s duties. It would obviously be uneconomical and impracticable to send on all such occasions a young Political Officer from India for so short a period and it is more convenient from all points of view to follow the present system. If however we are not to be allowed to give the substitute any compensation for his work, he obviously cannot be expected to do it. If it would be . possible for you to get the .Tar Office to reconsider the matter, not so much with reference to the Officer appointed inin June 1932 as for the future, both Reilly and the Government of India would be much obliged. J. G. Laithwaite, Esq., India Office, London.© Downing Street 17936/33 !I? j , 1933 liy dear Foyle, iou v/ill no doubt renxeiiibtjr our conwera&amp;tion on the telephone on the 3rd January on the question of the reiabure#ment to Colonel He illy of the amount he had paid to the Qiilitriry officer who acted as his Personal Assistant. Our last official letter on the subject is that of the 16th December (So. 97686 'SS) and your reference is .19172/3. have a discussion with the Tar Office and India Office on this subject, and this took .lace at the India Office on the 13th January. Importance to putting their point of .rinciple on record, but, as a result of discussion, it was finally agreed that the simplest way out of what is a real difficulty would be th'.t, in the first place, w© snould treat the present case specially and ask I mentloner, to you that we ^ro -osed to The &amp;r Office attached considerablet^g 'PreaBury for sajiction, prejudice to the principle inTOlred, to the refund to deilly of the amount ^hich b^e has paid to hie Aide-de-camp. Secondly, that we shofeb# send a reasoned and persuasive letter to the War Office pointing out the quite special ciroumstanoes of Acen and the ciffioulties with which the Resident is liitoly to be faoed, if, as the result of ar Cffice insistence that no allowance should be granted, it is impossible for him to find an officer to act as lersonal Assistant Jurinp the absence on leave of the substantive holder of the post. Cleverly, while unable of course in any way to commit his people, was Inclined to thinfc that the ar Office might, on receipt of such a letter, agree to a special arrangement in the case of Aden without prejudice to the general principle. I hope in these circumstances you will now be willing to sanction a refund to 1cilly in this particular case, and we then propose to write to the ' ar Office on the general question. Yours sincerely, / /&lt;fd t(, /Ww N.1212 5000 !&gt;/32 Minute Paper. political Department. The difficulties which have arisen over the payment of an allowance to a military officer acting | in a leave vacancy in the post of Personal Assistant jat Aden were discussed informally with the War Office (Lr. Cleverly) and Colonial Office (Mr* Howard) on the 13th January. The War Office emphasised that they attach much importance to the point of principle, hut ultimately agreed that conditions at Aden were somewhat special anu suggested that the simplest course would he that in the individual case at present under consideration we should ask the Treasury for approval to a refund to the Resident of the amount which he had paid out of his own pocket, this to he without prejudice to the decision as regards the future, and that we should then write a persuasive letter to the War Office setting out in greater detail than had hitherto heen done the arguments in favour of a special arrangement at Aden. While Mr* Cleverly was unahle to commit his Department he gave us to understand that so tar as he was concerned such an approach would he sympathetically considered and that there might he some prospect of a satisfactory solution. ■• ^ agreed, owing to Mr. Howard’s approaching transfer and in the interests of disposing of this natter, to send him rough drafts for the War Office and the Treasury. Copies of these are attached.Draft Paper. S- T . political Department. P.J. Howard, Esq., 0*E.E Colonial Office. Sc I cL (C/Sl My dear Howard, As arrangedafternoon I enclose a very rough draft of a letter to the war Office. Cleverly, however, before he left suggested to me that we should do best to approach the Treasury in the first place for sanction to refund to Reilly the amount already paid out by him, without prejudice to the general principle, and get this out of the way, holding up our formal letter to the War Office until it has been disposed of. I imagine this is sound and I enclose a rough draft to Foyle( ^ VtA f-VVv ^ i\n^ IU.S.3. War Office. 10(13 4000 7.32 Draft Paper. © political Department, DHAPI jSTTLP C-0 - Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to say that he ha^iad under his consideration War Office letter of the 24th November, No. 0.179/98, on the subject of the payment of an allowance to the local military officer appointed to perform the duties of Personal Asst, to the Resident at Aden during June 1932, which has also been the subject of informal discussion between the departments concerned. 2. Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister now !directs me to say that he fully appreciates the importance attached by the .army Council to maintenance of I the principle embodied in Anriy Regulations that the duties of an officer on leave shall be performed without extra expense to public funds and that in consequence no officer can receive additional payment for carrying on these duties. He does not in any way desire to contest the principle in question or to suggest abandonment of it. 'K in his view the payment now under consideration presentsquite special features of its own and in the light of a fuller e xp la na t io n /explanation of the position he would suggest that the i%rmy Council might find it possible to agree that, without prejudice to the principle, special arrangements might he made to cover the infrequent cases which may from time to time occur of the temporary perforimnce hy a military officer stationed at iiden of the duties of Personal Asst, to the Resident in addition to his own military duties, which might he hold to jUolify sumc aagraa of-spagri 1, frrjnQ'iaQruitiQR. 3. The duties of the post in question are essentially of a civil character. It may he, ana has in fact invariably, since the Resident at Aden ceased to he a G.O.C. at that post in 1927, been f held either hy a civilian or hy a retired military officer. Moreover, any allowance granted to a temporary incumbent is paid from civil funds ana no part of it is borne hy the War Office. The Secretary of State is satisfied from the enquiries which he has made that it is essential to the satisfactory performance of the duties of tne Resident that that officer shoula have at his disposal a Personal Asst, and that great inconvenience is caused hy any vacancy in the appointment, even for a very brief period/Draft Paper. Department period of time. In the past, as the Army Council are aware, it has 'been found possible to meet -^rno-pgon^ Comnanding the military units stationed at Aden,who have been good i if he not merely is required to undertake duties additional to his ordinary military work hut receives no remuneration of any kind in unfortunately carry any allowance which could be made available for a temporary incumbent. 4. Having regard to these oy the absence of any officer who * rill I •&lt; A dz iTh. RfrUir tuumcJ :ould in emergency^perform the duties 3f Personal Asst, the Secretary of State would venture to suggest that the Army Council might be prepared to consider the matter further and to agree, as a special case ana without prejudice to the general principle Referred to above, that in such (lay arrangement with the Officers jrespect of his duty as Personal Asst. :The post of Personal Asst, does not which might be caused to the Resident 10«3 4000 7.32 emergencies/emergencies a military officer permitted to act as Personal Asst, should receive remuneration at the rate of £100 per annum which has in previous corresponaence heen generally agreed as a suitable figure. 5. The Secretary of State understands from previous correspondence tnat the difficulties seen by the Army Council apply only in the case of officers appointed to officiate in leave vacancies and that if and when an Army officer is allowed to act as Personal Asst*during a substantive vacancy in the post they would not (on the understanding that such acting service was for a limited period only ana-in—order^ to meet an emergency) see objection to his receiving remuneration at the rate of £100 per annum, and I am to ask for confirmation of this.i political Department. Draft Paper. H.R. Poyle, Ksq. , Treasury. DM 1 llttlr . ty dear P’oyle, We discussed tne question of the Aden A.D.C. with the India Office and War Office on 13th January. The War Office attached considerable importance to putting their point of principle on record, hut as a result of discussion it was finally agreed that the simplest way out of what is a real difficulty would he that in the first place we should treat the present case specially and ask the Treasury for sanction, without prejudice to the principle involved, to the refund to Keilly of the amount which he has paid to his A.D.C. Secondly, that we should send a reasoned and persuasive letter to the War Office pointing out the quite special circumstances of Aden and the difficulties with uhich the Resident is likely to he faced if, as the result of War Office insistence that no allowance should he granted, it is impossible for him to find an officer to act as Personal Asst, during the absence on leave of the substantive holder of the post. Cleverly, while unable of course in any way to commit his people, was 10(&gt;3 4000 7.32 inclined/1 (a) Duties of the post are essentially civil. (b) It may be, anh has usually since 1927 actually (e) Any allowance granted to a temporary incumbent is paid from Civil funds ana no part of it is borne by the war Office. concerned are; (a) £asual, during the leave of the substantive incumbent. It is difficult to expect an officer to do supply without some that leave vacancies should be filled without extra cost,-we are not here dealing with a military leave vacancy but with a vacancy in a civilian post for wnich a military officer is being made available. (b) Semi-permanent, between permanent appointments. This may be of varying length. It appears been,held by a civilian or a retired military officer. 2. The only types of vacancy with which we are technical War Office point is concerned that/that the War Office, while not enthusiastic, see no objection, in fact, in such a case to the full allowance at the rate of £100 a year being paid to a temporary military incumbent. We are not concerned here with the situation which would arise in the event of a Resident wishing to take a serving military officer as his permanent A.D.G. and Personal Assistant.Notes on Personal Assistant (or A.D.C. ) to the Resident at Aden. P.6198/30 but see j P.5658/28 where the Resident describes the A.D.C. as 'pretty busy'. P.Z.2121/31. P.6198/30. P.2460/30 and 6198/30. P. 2 j Z° T. zu&gt;lSc P.Z. 5939/32. * fe\ -wJkj ol Necessity for Personal Assistant . - The post was described by Sir Stewart Symes in 1930 as hardly a whole time job, but he added 'It is really impossible for a Resident at Aden to do his job without some personal assistant^'. W ^* Telegram from Sir 3. Symes, dated 25th February, 1931 - 'It is really impossible for Reilly to act here without an A.D.C. and appointment of Personal Assistant from Political Service, if approved, must take time to arrange'. Duties . - Cypher work, returning calls on ships, receiving visitors, e.g* Protectorate Chiefs, social and domestic duties generally. The idea of Sir S. Symes was that when the Third Assistant Resident (Political Department) was replaced by a Bombay Provincial oervice Officer, the former should reappear as 'Personal Assistant' (Political Department) and do A.D.C. and secretarial work with the Resident. Former arrangements for A.D.IU “ Hnder the Indian administration when the Resident was invariably a haj or - General of the Indian Army, the post was usually held by an Indian Array Officer, and until 7th March, 1925, wnen new rates were introduced under Army InsurucolOiis, an Officor officiating as A.D.C. received Rs.250 per mensem in addition to pay of rank. ^ / ) Present position under the new regime . - The troops at Aden are, of course, no longer drawn from the Indian Arruy, and so new arrangements have had to be made lor appointing a Personal Assistant or A.D.C. for the Resident. x The Government of India are glad ^o nave an opportunity of filling the post from the Indian Political Department, but cannot/ i■t 1, , ^ £ The Resident wanted an Indian Political cannot guarantee that an officer of that Department will always be available. A Political Department Officer is apparently the best solution, but the Personal Assistant or A.D.C. is a personal officer of the Resident and it seems clearly impracticable to fetter his choice or require that the Personal Assistant should come from the Indian Service (e.g. in the case of a Colonial Service Resident) even if such an officer is available. If the post were to become a cadre appointment of the Indian Political Department, an agreement with the Colonial Office would have to be reached. Since 1928 the substantive post has been held by (1) Captain Taylor, late Indian Amy (1928) who did not prove a success; (2) Captain Ropner, a retired Indian Amy officer (1928-30); x (3) Mr. Jackson, a civilian (1930-31) who left Aden in February, 1931, with Sir Stewart Symes; and subsequently Officer but there was not by an Indian Political Department officer, one available. When the substantive post is vacant or when its holder is on leave, it is necessary for the Resident to secure the temporary services of an officer of the T'|/Ua* S . Oarrison. Besides the R.A.F., there are at Aden h detachments of the Royal Engineers, Royal Artillery and f r i — f A Signals. In two cases a milHar^Hcer has^^ ^ ^ officiated as Personal Assistant/^hd in both instances' ^ difficulty has been experienced in regard to the payment ~ of an acting allowance since the War Office contend that c u -1* P.Z.7425/32. O’-ntii / 2 *under British Army Regulations the duties of any officer on leave have to be performed without extra expense to oublic funds and that in consequence no officer can receive additional payment for carrying on these duties. In the case of Lieutenant Tapp, who acted as Personal Assistant during Captain Ropner’s leave and until/ 2. *7/6/?/amI fo?) until Mr. Jackson arrived at Aden, and again in 1931 when Mr. Jackson vacated the post, the War Office objected to any allowance at all being paid during the period when Captain Ropner was on leave, but they agreed to the payment of an allowance of £100 per annum (instead of Rs.250 per mensem which the Government of India had recommended) during the period when the post was actually vacant. Vr un h°) * The second case is that of the Army Officer who acted this summer during the absence on leave of Lieutenant Hickinbotham. The War Office objected to the payment of any allowance in this case, but the Resident paid the officer the allowance out of his own pocket. It is hoped that we shall be able to reach a more satisfactory arrangement with the War Office since clearly the Resident cannot do without a Personal Assistant, and, as Colonel Reilly has pointed out, an Army Officer cannot be expected to carry out these duties in his spare time without some extra remuneration. It is not clear to what Army Regulation the War Office refer, but Article 1480 of King's Regulations reads as follows:- 'Except where prescribed by the Pay Warrant, provision will be made, without extra charge to the public, for the temporary oerformance of the duties of Staff Officers when on leave'. If this is the Regulation in question, it would seem that it is meant to apply in the case of one amy officer acting for another but that it could hardly be held to apply in the present case since the duties of the Personal Assistant are purely civilian duties. It has been suggested to the War Office that civilian rather than army Regulations should govern the grant of an allowance to the officer who acts as Personal Assistant, but they have simply ignored the point. It/*A\J * \ . -&gt; ^ C/e-rCr^ I 97335/32 . My dear Laithwaite, . 139 rest, “January, 1933. ft 5 ^- t JjO With reference to your letter of the 25th of October^ Lo. P.Z. ^939/32, regarding thq appoint ment of a local military officer to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden, I have now heard semi-officially from the Treasury that they feel unable, in view of the War Office * attitude, to sanction the re-imbursement to Reilly of the amount which he paid out of his own pocket to the military officer who was appointed his Aide-de- Camp during the absence on leave in June last of his Personal Assistant. I told Poyle that we had in mind the desirability of reaching a permanent arrangement which would apply to future similar cases, and proposed to have a meeting between representatives of your Office, the War Office and the Colonial Office to discuss the matter. ^ J.G. LAITMAITE, iisti. He m -mur. * t Ke thought it would be a good idea to have the meeting now and, if we could shake the rigid attitude that the War Office have so far maintained and get them to withdraw their objection, no opposition would, I am sure, be raised by the Treasury. &lt; I am therefore at your disposal and will attend the meeting as and when you care to arrange it. On telephoning you yesterday I v/as^ informed that you had been away ill and were convalescing at Brighton. I hope you will soon be quite fit again. Yours sincerely,B 12 b vl( D Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, •* Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number Quoted :— 0)- mowing number ai Subject .• il ^ (rL+„ (Xu ‘l $*(■*+*/ t* ■ * —j 4 i % Reference to previous correspondence 0 Letter r ^~ the Colonial Office of the from jj j / * VP Wl r \KJ/7 Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. *5 0_ '15 DEG. 1932 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND Colonial Office, Downing Streotj-Qp^-j p-_- &gt; , 'C£ 8 193 X (R7682) Wt ’t 1593^537 10,000 2) 11/30 H &amp; SP Gp 112- IT Service* Vote,a* approved in your letter ^191?g/3 eftf&gt;th June* I AB9 t Sir,0179/98 (F.2.) Tiif! War Office, London, L. //«X* 24th Isovember,1932* Sir, 1 am conuaanded by the Array Council to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated 15th November,1932 Ko.97685/32 regarding the payment of an allowance to the local military officer appointed to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the fiesid^nt, Aden, during June,1932, and to st^te that they regret that they did not appreciate that a reply to your former letter dated 16th September,1932 was expected. 1 am to explain that the An y Council are unable to re com: end that any additional pay should be issued to the officer acting as Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aen, in the present case, for the reason that he was acting while the holder of the appointment was on leave. Under British Array regulations, the duties of any officer on leave have to be perfor ad without extra expense to public funis and in consequence no officer can receive additional payment for carrying on these duties. The present case differs in this -aspect from that referred to in your letter of the 16th rarch,1931, No.89313/31 where there was an actual vacancy and the grant of an allowance not contrary to British Amy regulations. If the Colonial Office, in vi^w of the foregoing, still proposes to seek Treasury approval for the reimbursement of the Resident of the Allowance paid by him out o f hi s own salary The Unier Secretary of State, Colonial 0ffice,S.W.l.My dear I aithwaite, 97885/32. With reference to ^our letter of the 25th October , (No.p. Z. 5939/32) regarding the appointment of a local military officer to perform the duties of personal Assistant to the desirable to reach a permanent arrangement which would apply to future similar cases, and, as soon as the particular case under corisiderauion is disposed of, we agree to your suggestion that a small meeting, composed of representatives of the India Office, War Office and Colonial Office, should discuss the matter. Yours sincerely, Chief Commissioner at Aden, we agree that it is1 • 4.5939/7) &gt; INDIA omcs. mTSHALL, S/2.1 25th October, 1932. Please refer to Metcelfe f e demi-official letter of If th September, a copy of which wap pent to you on 5th October with our No. P.£.5939/32 regarding the appointment of a local military officer to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Chief Coramisaioner, Aden. We note that the Colonial Office have already taken action on Feilly’e letter to the Govorrrnent of India of 13th August and approached the War Office on the question of paying an allowance to the officer who acted for the Personal Assistant during the latter’s absence on leave last June. e entirely m re© with the line tm t/Colomel Office are taking* You will observe from Metcalfe*s letter that tils kind of problem is likely to arise again in future • rvi tit it is (#sirable to reach a pemanent arran^ faraent to govern it. Ve fully agr e with the Goverment of Iniiia’s views. At the same time we think it might Howard, Inq., O.B.S., c®nplic»t«/ Colonial Office, S.f,lcomplicate matters? to raise the general point at this eta£e # and subject to your views we are inclined to think that it might be preferable, therefore, once you reach a satisfactory eolution of the present difficulty, to have a email meeting between you, the War Office and ourselves to discuss future arranga^ents. Will you let me know if you Agree? v ours sincerely, J - G- LAITHWAITE.might suitably be discussed an iniormal meeting between representatives oi the War ufiice, colonial Office and this Office* Would you siggest a date j.or / sucn a meeting or would you preier tnat we / shoula ta^e the matter up in oliicial correspondence?f; . , i ' n?) ••0«1TO. D* 36 46-j/32* J 03 2 c/jL(Xa. lAfr\*~XA- Cfv* tr'j* / &amp; CP. 1 S i ill 1 a; a? fV 1 e Septemter 19 32, lv- y*-e^ fa - f£y / n I em desired to refer to correspondence ending with your letter No. F*Z*4068/32 dated 15th July 19 32* ahd to enclose a copy of a letter from Reilly No. ^302/56 35, dated 13th August 19 32, in tfiich he asks that the decision communicated in your letter may he re-considered. The appointment of Personal Assistant to the Chief Commissioner at Aden is not home on the cadre of the Political Department of the Government of India* and while the Goverrxnent of India are glad to have the opportunity of filling this post CL whenever they are able to do so, they cannot gursntee that an officer of the Political Department will always he available for it. If at any time an officer of the Political Department cannot he made available, it will again he necessary for the Chief Commissioner to obtain the services of a military officer for appointment as Aide-de-Camp. For this reason it scans important to arrive at some definite understanding about the pay of a military officer who is appointed Aide-de-Camp. I see from the enclosure to your letter of 15th July that the Axmy Council on this occasion opposed the grant of any additional pay to the officer who was temporarily appointed to fill the post of Aide-de-Camp. There seems to he no difference in principle between an appointment for one month and is *• 2 — \| and an appoinlznent for a longer period; and I am desired to invite a reference to letter from the War Office to the Colonial Office No. 48/Xbroad/273 dated 27th March 1931* which indicates that the Anny Council at that time were of opinion that the grant of an allowance at the rate of £ 100 a year was not unreasonable. Sanction to the payment of the allowance at that rate was actually conveyed in India Office letter No. P.Z.2716* dated llth June 1931# The Government of India are unaware of the reasons which led the Army Council to oppose the recommendation in the present instance; hut in the circumstances of the case as known to them they are inclined to support the Chief Commissioner^ request for re-c on si de rati on of the decision. I am to request therefore* if you see no objection* that the question may be taken up with the Colonial Office again and that tiiey may be asked not only to re-consider the decision which has been reached in the present case, but also to consider what allowance (if any) should be granted in any similar case in future. To J.G. Laithwaite* Esquire* India Office* London. (With 2 spare copies)From Nq. A/392/66 J5. The Residency* Aden, 13th Anguat 19 32. Lieutenant Colonel B.R. Reilly* C.I#E.* O.B.E.* Chief Commissioner, Aden. To The Secretary to the Government of India» Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Appointment of a local military officer to perform the duties of Personal Assistant to the Chief Commissioner, Aden. -rX-X-X-X Si r, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. D.3096-S/32 dated the 29th July 19 32. I note with regret that His Majesty’s Government are unaBle to approve of the proposed grant of an allowance at Ihe rate of £.100 per annum to the local military officer who was appointed to he my Ai de- de-Camp from 6 th June 19 32 to 28 th June 19 32 in accordance with Government of India Gazette Notifications 37 - 7 -£ Nos. 396-Sedated 13th July 19 32 and 403-E dated 21st July 19 32. 2 . A considerable amount of work devolved on this officer in addition to his military duties .riiich he was performing at the same time, and I do not feel justified in securing his services without remuneration. I have therefore paid him the equivalent of the allowance which I recommended for him from my own salary. 3 # X venture to submit that a military officer cannot reasonably be expected to undertake duties of this nature in addition to his own without any additional pay, and at the same time that the payment ought not to be a charge on the Chief Commissioner. As the post of Personal Assistant is not a X cadre appointment of the Indian Political Department, and as the Government of India have statedthat they cannot undertake always to find apolitical Officer for it* it may from time to time he necessary to ask for the services of a military officer as Aide-de-Camp; hut it may he difficult to obtain them if no allowance Can he offered. 4. In the circumstances I shall he grateful if the question can he reconsidered. 5* In this connection I invite a reference to the Government of India letter No. F. H3(2 )-E/28 dated 7th September 19 31 addressed to the Government of Bombay in the Political Departaent in which an allowance at the rate of £.100 per annum was sanctioned for a temporary military Aide-de-Camp in circumstances similar to those of the appointment of Lieutenant K.A.P. Fergusson. I have the honour to he* Si r* Your most obedient servant, Sd. B.R. Reilly* Chief Commissioner*X (R9720) WtlSlir/2750 10 , 000 ( 2 ) 12/31 HASP Gpll 2 12|&gt; —f iis subje INDIA DIRECT, tjpmmunications on this subject should be addressed to— 5 ^Thb Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, ' London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— fife JlAl P. Z. ! rfr |q Subject: tlM £% far *1 Reference to 'previous correspondence: r Letter jkam^ le Colonial Office of the /bt h i ?z Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the enclosure Colonial Office, Downing Street, / C AuLt^.L~ 193Copy. II 160. Aden, 17th August§ 133£* Sir, I havo the honour to enclose a copy of a letter which I have addressed to the Government of India on the subject of the allowance which I fecommended for the Military Officer who was appointed to b© my Aid©-da-Camp during the absence on leave of ray iersonal saistant in June last, together with a copy of the Government of India’s letter £.309$-ii/32 dated £9th July, 193a, to which it is a reply. 2. I hope that His Majesty's Government may bs willing to reconsider their decision in the circumstances that I have explained. I have, Ac., (signed) B.;U ieilly. Jesideut, to. WA/-39JJ/5635. w ' y ? i i l The Heaidenoy, adan, 13th August, 193S. lieutanant Colonel 3,H.Reilly, 0#1.3., O.B. w, Chief Comriiisaiontir, ulen. To The Secretary to the Govern, ent of India, foreign and Polltioal Separtoient, Sisdn. SUflJKCTi • Appointment of a local military of'icer to perform the duties of personal isslatant to the Chief Com isaioner, Aden* sir* I have the honour to refer to your letter So. h.3G96-;i/3£ datod the 29th Culy, 1932* I note with regret that Hi© M&amp;Jeaty'e Governm«nt are unable to approve of the proposed grant of an allowance at the rate of 2100 per annum to the local military officer who was appointee to be my Aide~de-C&amp;i&amp;p from 6th June, 1932, to 20th June, 1932, in accordance with Government of India Ga&amp;ette Notification© No©* 336-B and 397-H dated 13th July, 1932, and 403-^ dated 21st July, 1932. 2* A considerable amount of work devolved on this officer in addition to hi© military duties which he was performing at the same time, and I do not feel justified in scouring his services without remuneration. I have therefore paid him the equivalent of the allowance which 1 recommended for him from my own salary* 3* I venture to submit that a military officer cannot reasonably be expected to undertake duties of this naturenature in addition to hie own without any additional pay, find at the aauie time that the payment ought not to he &amp; charge on the Chief Conamioeioner. $8 the poet of i’erscnal Aant&amp;tant is not a cadre appointment of the Indian iolitioal Department, and as the Government of In i have stated that they oaaaot un rtake Jv. y... to find a iOlitical Officer for it, it may from time to time he neoeouary to aal for the services of a military officer aa Aide-de-Campj but it may he difficult to obtain them if no allowance can he offered# 4. In the circumstances I shall he grateful if the question can b© reconsidered* h# In this connection I invite a refer* nee to the Government of India letter No. P. 11.3(2)- /£8 dated 7th September, 1931, addressed to the Government of Bombay in the Political Department in which an allowance at the rate of £lwb per annum was sanctioned for a tern; or : ry V military Aide-de-Camp in circusistances similar to those of the appointment of lieutenant &amp;• 5 #P. Pergusson. I have, &amp;c#, (Signed) B.H.Heilly. Chief Coiuuiss lonerxt —«— Ho. 13.3096-^/32. From yiie Uador Secretary to the Gorerhiaaiit of In ia in the Foreign and j olltical Department. The Chief Commieeioner, Aden. Dated Simla, the 29th July, 1932. Appointment of a local military of ’ioer to perform the duties of icraonal Aaai&amp;Vint to the Chief Commissioner, Aden. Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram No. 3829, dated the 7th June, 1932, I am directed to say that His Majesty'a OOTernment have sanctioned your proposal regarding the appointment of a local military officer to perform the duties of your Personal Aaeietant during lieutenant HicJilnbothem’s absence on leaTe, but they are unable to approve of the proposed grant to him of an allowance at the rate of floe per annum. 1 have, dsc., (Signed) C.G.K.Kdwards.i y Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State,. Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. Number quoted \ Sir With reference to your letter (p.4^2657/32) of the 24th of May regarding the proposed appointment of a local military officer to perform the duties of personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden during the latter’s absence on one month’s leave, 1 am directed by secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Listei to request you to inform secretary Sir Samuel Hoare that after consulting the Army Council, he concurs in this appointment. 2. The Army Council have stated, however, that they are unable to recommend that any additional pay should be issued to him, and, after consulting the Lords Commissioners of the Treasury, Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister regrets that this proposal cannot be sanctioned. I ni, Sir Your most obedient servant, J DIA OFFICE.' * r /: ■isi ') / ) / IMPQHgA&amp;x, JL Jane/^5 8 97665/32• Sir, With reference to your letter 1.19178/3 of the 15th April, 1931, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffts- ister to transmit to you, to he laid before the lords Commissioners of the treasury, a copy t V iJ&amp;* of a letter frora the India Office regarding the propueed appointraent of a local military officer to perform the duties of the Personal Assistant to the Resident st Aden during the latter*s absence on one month’s leave, 2. Sir Philip Cunliffe.lister agrees with the View expressed by the India Office that it would be impossible for the Resident to be without a Personal Assistant, and having regard to the fact that the sun of £4*3,4. only ie in question so far as Imperial funds are concerned, he trusts that Pheir lordship* may be moved to approve the proposal at a very early date, I aa. Sir, Your most obedient servant. fH - 31 CHETaRY, TREASURY, 'k-ZT'S,iAR Oi’i'ICi.. Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister to transmit to you, to be laid before the Army Council, a copy of a letter from the India military officer to perform the duties of the Personal Assistant to the Resident at Aden during the latter 1 s absence on one month* s leave. 2, 3ir Philip CunliPfe-Lister v^ould be glad if the Army Council would to ive permission for the local military officer to undertake the extra duties. I am. Sir, Your most obedient servant. - TH UJOhS 3 - C!U 1’AHY OF S'i'iUV ,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003b2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1456</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003b2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1456</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 1/20 'Aden Staff and Establishment: Personal Assistant to the Chief Commissioner'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-25T22:10:55</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (146 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 146; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Aden Resident (later Chief Commissioner), the Colonial Office, the War Office, the Foreign and Political Department for the Government of India, and the Treasury, regarding the appointment of military officers as Personal Assistant or Aide-de-Camp to the Aden Resident.The correspondence dated between 1932-1934 concerns the objection of the War Office to paying for extra duties performed by military officers in their spare time. An argument is made that an exception should be made for the Aden Protectorate, particularly for temporary appointments to cover leave.The correspondence dated between 1934-1937 concerns suggested appointments to the post, and the pay and allowances to be drawn by the applicants.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 1).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief Commissioner, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Personal Assistant to the Resident, Aden</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003b2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>