<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002ee_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:01:52.108Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">300- I C ■ A. /t „ ' /y ' .y . ' ^ ' I. A d i c, . £xc*S&lt;.'..y~ t 'f-M-* .7)0 1 ' -3/ &amp;.. ;f ' /Z mmnw* wtth shrrtf frtr^. ^ ^ . &gt; 'hs-o- t • 5^- i . • V 1. Sherif Feisal, accompanied by Lieutenant- '-olonel i. a .Lawrence, visited the India Office on Friday the ?7th December, 1916, and was entertained at tea by the Secretary of State. During some preliminary oonrereation in Mr. Montagu*e room, in which only the Secretary of State, Sir T. Holdernesa and Sir J. Dunlop-Sraith took part, the Sherif dwelt upon the solidarity of the Arab movement and the essential unity of the Arab race, A more general discussion followed at which Lord Islirurton. Sir A. Hirtzel, Sir Hamilton Grant, and Mr. Shuckbur^i were present in addition to those already n^med. Colonel Lawrence interpreted throu^Jiout for Sherif i Feisal. Bin Sand, The Sherif discuseed the relations between Bin Saud f Emir of Kejd t and the Hejaz authorities. He explained the nature of the Wahabi moTement, of which Bin Saud is the figure-head and the leading spirit. From the point of view of doctrine, he has no objection whatever to Wahabism. But it is essentially a militant creed, and is being made to serve political ends. The /ahabis are intolerant of anybody and everything outside their own sect. If, for example, they rained possession of the Holy Places, they would exclude all non- Tkhabis from the pil^rima^e. So Ion# as Wahabisrn was confined to Nejd,lieja, no one in the Hejaz had any desire to interfere with it. But they cannot tolerate ite appearance in the settled area west of the desert. That is the sipnificanoe of the Khuma incident. Khuma is the first settled tillage weet of the desert, and so lonp; as it remains under the influence of Bin Saud, it forms aii outpost of ''ahabism in the sjsttled area. Sherif Peisal is'determined to expel the'Ilchw«n' (i.e. the ni itant i from the Tillage. He proposes to do so in the immediate future by force of arms. He will direct the campaign in person, and anticipates no difficulty in achieving his object. The matter is a Mill one, and need not occasion His Ilajesty's Gcrernment any preoccupation. He will be quite satisfied with dririnp; the Wahabis back into the desert, and has no intention of carrying? the campaign into Bin Saud's own country. There isone alternative, tis :- that the lejas people should themselTes embrace Wahabism. Feisal is quite prepared to take this course, if the British Government wish; but it would mean closing down the pil^rima^e to all non-Wahabis for the future. 3. Svria. Feisal explained the circumstances which led to the Arab revolt in 1916. The Arab movement before the revolt wa» represented by local Arab Coranittees in different parts of the Arab world. In the northern provinces (Syria, Iraqyi etc.,) the Arabs were at the mercy of the Turks, and the local Cormittees were consequently powerless. Only in the Hejaz was any action possible, and it was accordingly in the Hejaz that the . revolt!P ('/£v Jfr revolt sturted? but it directed from the first towards the emancipation of the Northern provinces, quite as much aa of the Hejai itself. The authors of the revolt turned naturally for assistance to the Br.tish Government as the only European Government that pursued nn eniiphtened policy towards subject races. In Great Britnin the Srabs have always felt, and still feel, complete trust. He instanced his own attitude in regard to I esopotamia, on which subject he had not said, and did not intend to say, a single word: he had full confidence that the British Government would do what was ri*ht. But he has been greatly disturbed by certain recent developments, and particularly by the terras of the Sykes Pico^ Afree^nent, the tenor of which was not made known to him until lon^ after its conclusion. He had no Idea, • usn en^ed in too struggle against the inks, that any agreement of the kind wa« in existence, or that Arab ripjits in Syria had been barpsined away in advance. Syria is the granary of the Hejas - ^iich in itself is a barren and Yalueleas country - and its poffaession is absolutely essential to the Arabs, If frmch Influence is dominant in Syria, it will inevitably spread to the llejaz itself. The Arabs dislike and distrust French raethodsj (Peisal corapared the French to a particularly raali^ant type of leech found in Arabian wells); they see the results of French policy in North Africa, where nothing whatever has been done to encourap-e Arab culture and they have no desire to corae under the influence of a nation whose civilisation they ffigwrd in no way superior to their own. They fully recognise the exigenciesexifrencies of the Anglo-French Alliance, and the obligation upon Great Britain to keep faith with her Ally. But thin obligation should be discharged at the expense of Great Britain herself, not of the Aeabs. ■Reminded of the recent Anglo-French Declaration, eisal aaid that he appreciated the effect of this instruraent as modifying the SJkes-Picot Agreement; but he had gathered from an interview at the Foreign 'lice that, it the French Governraent insisted on its rijjJits under the Agreement, Great Britain would not be in a position to refuse. He hinted that, in that event, there wouW be war between the Arabs and Frenoh in the near future. He had observed with some disappointment, during his stay in England, what appeared to him to be sipps of weakness on the part of the British Government. Mr. Montagu undertook to lay the Sherif's representations before his colleagues. 4. Palestine. Questioned, in the course of the discussion, on the subject of Palestine, Feisal remarked that the Arabs were under deep obligations to tin Great Britain, and that it would ill become them to make difficulties over a question of which they regard the British Government as the best judges. The Aiabs recopjiise that many conflicting interests are centered in Palestine. They admit the moral claims of the Zionists. They regard the Jews as kinsmen whose just claims they will be glad to see satisfied. They feel that th« interests of the Arab inhabitants may safely be left in the hands of the British Government.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002ee_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B309</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002ee</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B309</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Interview with Sherif Feisal'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1918</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-10T12:30:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 14 and terminates at folio 17, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum, authored by John Evelyn Shuckburgh, dated 30 December 1918, concerns a meeting at the India Office, London, between Sir Edwin Samuel Montagu, Secretary of State, and Shaikh Feisal [Fayṣal bin Ḥusayn al-Hāshimī], accompanied by Lieutenant-Colonel Thomas Edward Lawrence acting as interpreter, on 27 December 1918. The meeting was also attended by Sir Thomas Holderness and Sir James Dunlop-Smith, as well as Lord Islington, Sir Frederic Arthur Hirtzel, and Sir Hamilton Grant. Subjects of discussion included relations with Bin Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd (Ibn Saud)], Emir of Nejd [Najd] and the nature of the Wahabi [Wahhabi] movement; Syria and the circumstances of the Arab Revolt of 1916; and Palestine and the Zionist movement.There is a pencil note in the top right hand corner of folio 1 that reads: 'Sir A. Grant. Do you think this is a fair representation of what Feisal said?' signed J E S and dated 30 December. This is followed by a note in the top center of the folio that reads: 'Yes. Excellent, I think', signed A H G and dated 31 December.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Secretary to the Political and Secret Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia 'Abd al-'Azīz bin 'Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Iraq Fayṣal I</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Palestine</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arab Revolt (1916-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002ee#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>