<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000092_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T16:59:18.095Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ml i i CONFIDENTIAL. No.C/440 Of 1940. 1ft The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to !• The Political Agent, Bahrain 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait. 3. The J?olitical Agent, Muscat, J and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment • British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. J Camp, Bahrain. , -v' Dated... .6th November 1940 • Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Government of India letter No.D.457l-W/40 of 2nd October 1940, with enclosure Subject. Movements of military aircraft •sy Cofy. Confidential. N o. D • 4 571-W/40* From - The Under Secretary to the GoYemment of India in the External Affairs Department, To - His Britannic Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Nepal* The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# His Britannic Majesty 1 s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Afghanistan# His Britannic Majesty's Consul General in the French Establishments and the Portuguese Possessions in India, jeondicherry. Dated Simla, the 2nd October, 1940. Movements of Military aircraft # Sir, i am directed to forward for information and guidance if occasion arises a copy Letter from the Government of mdiaj T of the communication External Affairs Department, ^o.D.457l-) noted in the margin. W/40, dated the 2nd October 1940. i have the honour to be. Sir, iour most obedient servant, sd. R.K.M.Saker. Under Secretary to the Government of India. Confidential# iio •D.457 i-W/40 # From - The Under Secretary to the Government of mdia in the External Affairs Department, To - The Chief Secretary to the Government of the North West Frontier Province, Nathiagali. The Hon'ble the Agent to the Governor General, Resident and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan, Ziarat . Dated Simla, the 2nd October 1940. Movements of ^i litany aircraft # Sir, i am directed to say that a case has recently occurred in which information in regard to the movement of a military aircraft was communicated through an en clair telegram. During war-time it is essential to maintain complete secrecy in regard to the intended movements of military aircraft in order to avoid the danger of compromising certain codes and cyphers of the Royal Air Force and to ensure that no information which is likely to assist the enemy comes to his knowledge. 2. For the reasons given above i am to request that no information pertaining to the movements, etc.of military aircraft should be communicated en clair to any authority in or outside inaia. if there is no objectfon, the position may kindly be explained to all officers subordinate to you# i have the honour to be. Sir, xour most obedient servant, sd. R.X.M.Saker. Under Secretary to the Government of India.British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agtrit 9 Muscat# The Political Agent, Kuwait. &gt; The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (s). / y If Dated. 45 th.. I anaa iry. .19^1# Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. \ Governraent of India 1 e letter Ko* D.5341-.V/4C, dated 17th December 1940 with enclofcure. Subject. FoYemente of military aircraft. /u gonfidsntiai From To No. D. 534i-W/40. The Secretary to the ^overniiient of India in the External ^iTaire Jepartraent, 1. Hie Britannic Wajtety'fc Envoy Extraordinary ^ and I^inifcter Plenipotentiary at the Court of Tepal# 2. The Hobble the Political Reeident in the Persian tiulf. 3. Hie Britannic ll^ajeBt^ , e Envoy Extraordin ary and 'inister Plenipotentiary at the Court , of /ifghanietan, Tabul. N \ 4. Hie Britannic Majeety'e Coneul-General, Pondicherry, 1 Dated Kew Delhi, the 17th Decerber 1940. Movementt of milita y aircraft. bir, / \ ■' In continuation of the letter from th® 1 Government of India in th« External affaire Department No. D.4571-W/40, 1.Letter from the Jhiei Secretary to the g vernment of the North Weet Frontier Province, N01I686-P, without date. 2• Letter to do ^0. D.534l-W/40f dated the 17th ecember 1940. dated the 2nd October 1940, I am directed to enclote a copy of the corree onience noted . in the margin. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your mofet obedient eervant, R.F.M.Saker. for Secretary to the Goveri.ment of India. Movemente of military aircraft. I am'directed to r^er to your letter ':'o.D.4571-W/40, dated the 2nd October 1^40 and to re^uett that, if tnere le no objection, details of the actual incident may kindly be gieen. 2* t has been repretented that in tome cafcea (e.g. an immediate cdi for aid by licouta Officer) it will not be pot^itle to comply ai.d that in others there may be the pOkeibility of eerioue delay ae Political Cfficere have not got the neceLeary staff to encode or decode every signal that has reference to the movement of an aero la^e.CiOUFIDi^NTIAL NO.D.5341-W/40. From The Under Secretary to the Ciovernnjerit of India in the External ..fiaire Department, To The ^hief Secretary to the Ciovermnent of the Korth Weet Frontier Province, Dated New Delhi, the i7th December 1940. SUBJECT : Movementfc of military aircraft. Sir, With reference to your undated letter j:o.l6e6-P, I am directed to ay that a certain Officer referred in a telegram to a jrivate adire.e to the date on which a military aircraft was flying. The Oificer ie not etationed in the .North we11 Frontier Province. Thie led to the ietue of the inetructionb contained in the letter from the 9overnment of'India in the HiJtternal affaire Department Ho: D,457l-rt/4X), dated the 2nd October 194c* f 2« The Government of India agree ihat in caeee of extreme emergency where no other courte ie possible the restriction imposed in their letter referred to above may e relaxed. 1 have the honour to be Sir, Your mofct obeiient servant, Gd/- H # T ' # M.3aker, Under btcretary to the Uovernraent of India. Copy with a copy of t.^e letter replied to, forwarded for information to: The Hou'ble the ^gent to the Governor General Heeident and Chief (jommissioner in jaluchi ttan. The Resident in 'Kashmir.Wt. S6569/2597 1,485,000 2/3« D.P.W. T51-1253 &gt; ivj 'v Form 348 (Medium) To: Date:— Ref; Defence Officer, Persian Qulf, at Baiirain. Political ^gent, Baiirain. 7til December, 1^41. DEF/S-4/41. &gt; In confirmation of my telephone converaation yesterday, I have to inform you that Flighta by R*A.*\ Aircraft trill be taking place over Bahrain during the next few days. They will probably land at various points on the Island. major, DEi'EHCE OFilCEii, PERSIAN GULF. Copy to: Adviser to the Bahrain Government. f r L '/m* (1^ 9•i England. NOV. 1940. (500 pads ) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. FROfc DOHA. BLENHEIM Z7907 CRASHED APPROXIMATELY 10 ILES S W OF DOHAH AAA CREW UNNJURED BUT PLAiiE CO PLETE WRECK OFF STOP CREW NOW AT PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT MTAR DUKHAN CAMP STOP ^ FURTHER DETAILS TOI&gt; ORROV.' INFORM MAJOR HEWITT AMD KSKKXIXX POLITICAL AGENT - DICKSON - CONFIRMATION COPY. ORIGINAL PHONED TO MAJOR HEWITT AND POLITICAL. AGENT . MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ie 'uat, HO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.£ Political Agency, Bahrain, 21st December 1941 To 3haikh Abdullah bin ^asim A1 Thani, C.T.S,, Huler of Qatar. After Compliments, I send this by hand of Wing Commander Alloway of the Royal Air Force who has come to examine the aeroplane which fell down near Dohah. I wish to express the deep aopreciation of the British autho rities f or the care and attention you paid to the men in the v/recked aeroplane and to guarding the remains of it. I present my best wishes for your health and my salaasms to shaikh Hamad. Usual Ending.r PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. D0/Msc/9188 29th December, 1941. Dear Wien I was in Qjatar the Shaikh made it quite clear to me that he expected to be reimbursed for the services of the guards he placed over the Blenheim from 16th to 22nd December. I do not know whether he has written to you in this connection but he gave me to understand that he would like me to mention the matter. As you know, however much he is paid, it will be con sidered inadequate. My personal view, if it is of any use to you, is that the R.A.F. could with advantage forward Ks.50/- with any letter of thanks which may be sent. Actually I asked the Shaikh to put^a couple of guards but I believe he had as man^ as eight the following 4a.y» Yours sincerely. ——- Major R.G.Alban, O.B.E., H.B.M, 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain.Political Agency, D.O. No. C/1201 Bahrain, the 31st December, 1941 Reference your demi-official letter No. DO/ Msc/9188 dated the 29th December 1941. I have addressed a letter of thanks to the Shaikh on behalf of the Royal Air Force and forwarded fts 50/- with it. Many thanks for your kind advice. Yours sincerely. u A E. V. Packer, Esq., Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain. .4. /Telegram 3. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, Muscat and Britconsul, Bushire No. 2 Dated the 2nd Jar uary 1942. Air Liaison Officer reTDorts installation of portable wireless transmitting and receiving set in Royal Air Force Rest House Manama for ooeration in connection v/ith the large numbers of military air- craft passing through. Presume no objection. - PoliticalC/23 The Political Agent, Preseats his complimeats to :— The Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. and has the hiooir to send hitn a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for Information. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 5th January 1942. Reference to previous correspondence : / 1 Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Letter No. C/1200 dated the 31st December 1941 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, i - - - - - to the Ruler of ^atar. Subject \\ Accident to R.A.P. plane near Oatar.h 5- % Telegram G. Britconsul, BUvShlre. To Political Agent, Bahrain Repeated Political Resident, at Muscat. No. 16. Dated 4th received 5th January 1942. . |3- v our tePegram No.2 of January 2nd. H.A.F. wireless set. 2. No objection (c.f. Article 1 of Bahrain Civil Air Agreement and connected letters re: facilities (mut) military aircraft) but please inform Bahrain Government. BMtconsul. l 7'iL Confidential No. C/28 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th January 1942 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government bahrain Memorandum I write to Inform you that a portable wireless transmitting and receiving set has been Installed In the Royal Air Force Rest House In Manama for operation In connection with the large numbers of mllltgry air craft passing through. Political Agent, BahrainD« 0, No. C/182 Dated the 8th February 1942# Reference my pred jlal/ p.tf letter No. C/1201 dated the Slat December 1941. 2. You may be Interested to hear that the Shaikh of oatar has returned the present of Fs 50/- sent as a tip for the guards which he placed on the Blenheim which came down in his territory. He says t- n I beg to return the amount to you and to say that I have already rewarded the guards, and the Hoyal Air Force should not trouble about such trivial matters'. v ours sincerely, V. Packer, Esquire, Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. V BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULP. D0/Msc/2817 9tli February, 1942 Dear i /fl /P' iiJ Many thanks for your D.O. No.C/182 dated the 8th February 1942, I believe that the R.A.F. actually paid the guards Rs,30/- and took receipts with the knowledge of the Shaikh. When I was there at the time the aeroplane crashed he made it very clear that he expected to be reimbursed for any expense on account of guards over the plane. I can quite understand, however, that he would not wish it to be generally known, particularly in Bahrain, that he was accepting any recompense in such circumstances• Yours sincerely. E. B. Wakefield, Esq., I.C.S., The Agency, Bahrain.-&gt;? Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. No.395. Dated 2nd June 1942. Important . Air Liaison Officer Bahrain requests all possible steps be taken to trace missing Boston aircraft last heard of 7.30 hours G.M.T. May 31st at point fifty miles north of Bahrain. Aircraft was bound for Shaibah from Sharjah. If aircraft came down on water crew may be in dinghy. Suggest Nakhodas of all dhows leaving port during next few days be asked to keep careful look-out. Political.i P.O. No.C/7Sl , The Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd June 1942. * h I enclose a copy of a telegram I have Just sent to the Political Resident and to the Political Agent Kuwait. Could you kindly take steps to have a request conveyed to all Nakhodas of dhows sailing Northwards from Bahrain to keep a look out for traces of the aircraft or for the dinghy in which the pilot and crew may po *ibly have escaped. Yours sincerely. &gt; C. Dalryfiple Belgrave Esquire C.B.E., Adviser to the Government, Bahrain.D.O. No. 9^7 l( lo cs Bahrain, June 2, 1942. -? * ^ Reference your D.O.No. C/751 dated the 2nd June, 1942, I have arranged with deGrenier to rquest all Nakhudas of dhows sailing Northwards from Bahrain to keep a look out for traces of the aircraft. E. B. Wakefield, Ssquire, I.C.S., H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain.S~\ i\) ^ Telegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain (reference his telegram &gt; No.396 June 2nd) for Air Liaison Officer. Repeated Air Officer Commanding, Iraq. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. No.1104. Dated and received 10th June 1942. Immediate . ' Missing Boston forced landed at Tahiri on Persian coast 135 miles south of Bushire map reference 27 degrees 35 minutes north 52 degrees 20 minutes east. Crew of four unhurt aircraft total loss. Letter from crew written June Ist arrived ^ushire June 10th by runner and requests me arrange transport. Only available method is by launch which would be most hazardous from here in present weather and with craft available. •2. in the circumstances suggest Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf be asked to arrange for diversion or despatch to Tahiri if any suitable vessel available. 3. Crew require change of clothing, skin ointment, cigarettes, and money for stay. They are at present staying with local Customs official. 4. Please inform me of action taken. - Britconsul -' Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No.420. Dated 11th June 1942. Important. — Your 1104 June 10th. By Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf 1 s orders vessel left Bahrain for site of accident 04.00 hours this morning. Aircraft has located personnel end dropped 5000 riyals, food, clothing and medical supplies. Personnel drew message on sand 'O.K.'. y Air Liaison Officer has reported separatel to A .H .Q. Political.Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Telegram Q. From To No,424. Dated 13th June 1942. ,^-&gt;1 My 420 June 11th. Personnel have arrived Bahrain in good health. Detailed report will follow. Political.'luo D.O.Mo.e /ag?. rh« Agenoy. Bahrain, the S3rd June 1942. in paragraph 101 of ay Inttlllgence SuMary for the first half of June X gave an account of the adventures of the crew of the Boston aircraft which was lost on May Slat. You may be Interested to have a somewhat fuller account of what happened* 2* ihe causes which lad to the aircraft losing Its way are •ielng Investigated l?y H#A # F. authorities and 1 will not therefore touch upon then. The pilot of the SostoiKfinding himself over the Persian coast with only a oaall supply of petrol left,flew along It looking .for a suitable place to land* The country was mountainous and he finally selected a atrip of a and uncovered by the tide which was low at the time. The landing was bumpy but the aircraft stood the strain well and was undamaged when It came to a stop* The pilot had no Idea where he was when he came down; but after about forty minutes three Persian villagers came on the scene* The pilot then ascertained his position by reading out the names of places from his map and by getting the villagers to point In their direction* By these means he established his location as being four miles 3outh- ^ast of Barak* T*o miles away, further down the coasti was a house* They went to this ^n&lt;I| as they had come without emergency rations| asked for food and were given four eggs and a loaf of bread* They then went back to the aircraft and tried to taxi It on to higher ~ ground above the tide level* In making the attempt the machine dug Itself in and was seriously damaged* 3* After study of the map they decided to walk to Kangan f and. at 5*30 p # m* f when the heat of the day had decreased, they set off on their Journey* As they approached Barak they saw an armed party approaching and became somewhat apprehensive of the reception they would get* However! the party was led by the &gt;halkh of Barak (whose name they afterwards discovered was Canaan Kasourl) who was most amicably disposed and offered them food bedding and shelter* A there was a prospect of getting donkeys for their onward Journey they decided to stay the night at Barak. The next morning the Shaikh of Barak asked to be shown the aircraft, so they returned to the site of their forced landing. The aircraft had been partly submerged by the tide but they managed to salvage a certain amount of kit and equipment* the equipment salvaged Included four para chutes which were subsequently locked up In the ohaikh* s house at .:i&amp;rok« At the airmen's request the Shaikh of Barak place*) a guard over the aircraft to prevent pillage by local inhabitants* 4* Cn their return to Barak they found waiting for them a number of donkeys (normally used for carrying water) which had been seat for them by the Officer In charge of the Customs post at Tahlrl* On these donkeys they rods to Tahlrl where they were given a warm welcome by the Customs Officer whose name was reportoJ to me as iing Sadruddin 3uddedor* The Customs Officer told them that, in view of the shamal that was theKs. blowing t It would be impossible for them to get to Bushire by sea* He also advised against their 4olng the Journey by land as, he said, it would take them a fortnight to arrive there while It was not impossible that they would be / attacked The Hon'ble Lleut*-Colonel w # n*Hay C*l *S* f Political Haaldent in the Persian CJulf, Bushire*-2- f r.W J r i' attacked on their way by bandits. The map carried by the airmen marked a British Hesldency at Bushlre; and the airmen accordingly decided that their best plan would be to send a message to Bushlre asking for help. The Customs Officer, who assured them that a runner could reach Bushlre within a week, gave them pen and paper on which to write their message. 6. During their stay at Tahirl they were well fed though they noticed that food was by no means plentiful in the village. For breakfast they had eggs and bread, while for the mid-day and -s, evening meals they ate rice with furnishings of meat dates veget ables etc. They saw many people making their way Westwards along the coast and were told that these were people who were driven by lack of food to look for work at Abadan. Almost every day of their stay, they told me, the Shaikh of Barak and his followers went out to raid the tribe to the South of them with whom they had a feud. In the course of these affrays three of the Barak men were killed. Apparently the place where the aircraft landed was in the w No Man 1 s Land !t lying between the territory of the two quarelling Shaikhs. All of the arms which the airmen saw in the possession of the ihaikh of Barak and his followers were old. They were of Russian or German manufacture and the newest which they noticed was a Mauser manufactured in 1917. 6. In the forenoon of June 11th the airmen heard an aeroplane overhead. This aeroplane, a Blenheim, was the one which had been sent out from Bahrain with stores of food medicine etc. The Blen heim was flying along the coastline about 50 yards out to sea at a height of under 50 feet. The Blenheim speeded byi the airmen wira waved violently, but still the Blenheim went on. They thought they had not been seen and were beginning to despair when suddenly the Blenheim swept roun^i in a circle back towards theaw It subsequently transpired that the pilot of the aircraft had not noticed them but his air gunner sitting behind had seen them waving, i eanwhile in the intervals of their waving the airmen were writing out in large letters the word r, Here ,, in the sand. The Blenheim circled over them several times. The first time it dropped a message saying that a ship would arrive the next morning and that in the meantime they were going to drop a number of bundles of food clothing and medicine. If the pilot of the Blenheim saw that they were recovering these bundles he would drop finally a bundle containing 5000 rlyals (money which with the assistance of Mr.Qunn I had collected from the Bahrain bazaar in the early hours of the morning). All the packages were dropped with extraordinary accuracy on the shore beside the airmen. Tahiri villagers collect ed them as they fell and put them into a pile. The airmen then wrote in the sand 'O.K. Thanks'* and the Blenheim flew away over the sea. 7. On the morning of June 12th H.M.S. '•Sea Belle' arrived and took the airmen on board. With them went the Customs Officer who was given % lunch and with whom the airmen were for the first time able to converse coherently through the n Sea Belled' inter- .preter. The 'Sea Belle 11 then went to the site of the forced landing. Anything of value on the aircraft was then recovered before the frame was destroyed. The only things of value which / were not recovered were the parachutes which had been locked up in the Shaikh of Barak's house. The Shaikh was away on a raid and the airmen were naturally reluctant to break into his house during his absence after the kindness that he had shown them. Nothing had been stolen from the aircraft after the Shaikh had placed guards on it. 8. The airmen pressed Sadruddin Suddedor, the Tahiri Cus toms Officer, to accept a present of money in return for all that / hehe had done for them. He steadfastly refused any payment y saying that any help he had given was no more than a very small repayment of the debt which he owed to English-speaking people for the edu cation which he had received at the American Mission at Kirmanshah. Bventually, though he would accept nothing direct from the airmen f he took 1500 rlyals from the Captain of the w Sea Belle n for dis tribution among the poor of his village* The airmen spoke to me again and again of the kindness with which they had been treated by the Tahirl Customs Officer who seemed y they said, to be a man who was both liked and respected in the neighbourhood. He was deferred to by local Shaikhs as well as by humbler folk. 9. My object in writing you this letter is partly to supple ment the account given in toy Intelligence Summary and partly to enquire whether it would be possible to secure for the Tahlri Cus toms Officer recognition of his invaluable aid to British airmen. I do not know what form this recognition could take. I do not think a present in money would be appreciated - in fact I think it would be refused. But it may be possible to secure promotion for him in the service of the Persian Government, Prom all that I heard about him he seems to be a man of good status whose pro motion to a post of much greater responsibility would be in ho way incongruous. If this suggestion could be carried out it should also have a good propaganda value as indicating that favours to the British do not go unrewarded. Yours sincerely,THE OFFICE OP TIS AIR LIAISON OFFICER,BAHRAIN. / Circular No.l SECRET. Dated 25th. June, 1942# v A'-'' FLYING OVER BAHRAIN ISLA1TD. The following extract from a recent ruling has been received from Air Headquarters, Royal Air Force in T Iraq,and is passed for information to all concerned. 'Air Crews are briefed to avoid, as far as possible, the Main Island of Bahrain in good visibility. In poor visi bility they should be permitted to approach as close as it is considered necessary and fire the colour of the period on approaching the harbour'. Squadron Leader. Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Copies to: vfi # B # LI ! s Political Agent, Bahrain. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government. The Defence Officer, Bahrain. Naval Officer in-Charge H # lI # Naval Base,Juffair. Air Headquarters, Royal Air Force in f Iraq. Headquarters 215 Group, Royal Air Force, Basrah.SEChBT . No.C/844, Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th June 1942 To The Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum. I return herewith the draft which you left with me the other day. I concur fully with what you say in it. I myself would, however, reduce still further the places over which pilots are asked to avoid flying, and I suggest the omission of Manama Town from the localities specified in para 4 of the draft. From the political viewpoint there is no objection to aircraft flying over Manama town but, of course, you may know of objections from the service aspect of which I am ignorant. 2. If you have no objectioh will you please let me have a copy of your letter when it issues. Politi _9nt, Bahrain.- ^ — nQ P.A.F. Form 98^,. S.575A. (Mava!). Call IN and Preface OUT MESSAGE FORM Oflice Serial No. Office Data Stamp TO (Above thif line is for Signalj use only). PP fk) AoAS 'a i^A. Your/My Number and Date FROM * / j i. o f3 (Write horizontally) i v f rvw '• * - v/ ; 'v-w ' | i C\A*t Originatot's Number ■■ ' ^ 'w--. i^-v, 3 ct 2 S 'o /&gt; ' v—i ^ 1 l'? ej ,5 - -t _ ^ » : 3j 35 40 50 55 HI SO Tbls meiScge must be sent AS WRITTEN ■nd mayf be sent by W /T. Signature t Originator to insert 'NOT' if message ist be sen^ IN CYPHER Originator's instructitns* Degree of Priority * -'■'■'''r: 1 - Q^^ZftZA This message must be sen^ IN CYPHER and niay+ an^^art of/Tie route. (Below this line !%for Signals use only.) byitem in Time in Reader Sender bystrtn out Time out Rrader Sender System out Time out Reader Sender T.H .I. ^ - TIME OF ^ . origin ny y T.0 R. ♦ TKc Signal Department is responnible that these details are transposed to the appropriate portion of the message form and that all possibility ^ compromising distinguistiini; signals, etc., by omitting to remove their signification from the address, etc., is avoided. Befora delivery of the «ess aft these details are to be re-inserted in P/L. -If Iu o Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. T.0.0. 2100 hrs. Dated 85th received 26th January 1^43. T.O.R. 1410 hrs. T.O.D. 1950 hrs. 1 imikdiiitk For A.L.O. Bahrain. Your telegram NO.0945C January 25th. VISIT OF AIR COMMODOftE COLEMAN. Yes repeat yes. Please telegraph date and time of arrival. - BRITCOiNSUL - Telegram From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.303. T.0.0. 1100 hrs. Dated and received 26tn January 1943. T.O.R. 1410 hrs T.O.D. 1950 hrs. IMMEDIATE For A.L.O. 1/^- telegram No.302 January 25th. Please telegraph whether party will arrive by flying boat or plane. i - BRITCONSUIj - -V3 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Telegram From to No.7S. Dated the 28th January 1943. IMMEDIATE From A.L.O. M' Your No.319 January 27th. Party delayed. Time arrival uncertain probably tomorrow or 30th. Party travelling in Hudson plane and proceed from Bushire to Basra. - poxiitical - Copy to Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain.5. Telegram From To No.340. T.O.O. 0830 hrs Dated and received 2jth January ij43. T.0»R. iiiO hrs T.O.D. 1125 hrs Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. IMUlBIA'IE u3 Your telegram No.721January 28th. For A.L.O. H.M. b. CAP'EI'OWN is due January 30th and we shalx be fully occupied with her so January 31st would be preferable if possible. - BRIT CONSUL -a Q Confldent.ial No. C/309 To Political Agency, Bahrain, 3rd March 1943. The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Memorandum I understand that a Wellington aircraft made a forced landing near Bidyah on the Shamailiyah Coast in the middle of February and that the machine was badly damaged and one of the crew killed. I do not seem to have had any report from you about this though I presume that arrangements to guard the air craft and salvage valuable equipment were made through you. If, as I have been told, local Arabs rendered good assistance and proved helpful they should be most liberally rewarded so that help will be forthcoming if similar accidents occur in future. Rewards should, of course, be paid promptly as well as on a liberal scale. 2. Will you please let me know what has been done and whe ther the O.C., R.A.F., Sharjah, kept you closely informed of all developments and consulted you in regard to rewards. If the rewards which he proposes to give are in your opinion not sufficiently generous I am prepared to supplement them from funds at my disposal. 3. I have also had no report from you about the aeroplane which crashed when carrying Lieutenant Hailey in it. In that case also I should like to know whether rewards were paid on an adequate scale to the people who proved helpful. 4. Please let me know v/hether there have been any political reactions in respect of the Arab who was killed during the bombing practice. i Political Agent, Bahrain. # | f d : 1 II 1 1Confidential^ 11 . note. f 6; v On Friday 19th February 1943 p/o A»B»C# NUnn called j ci i, ^ &lt;5 OH.l on me and asked me to give him a etatementi far record f regard -ing the warning given to the local fflOQCXK inhabitants about the bombing which took place on Egiday 12th February 1943o After explaining to him what I am writing below he asked me to put it in writing* I promised to writhe a note to the Commanding Officer confirming what I said verbally to F/O Nunn® On 11th February 1943 f/L Moore called in my office in the afternoon (between 3 and 4 p.mo) and asked to see me* My clerk told him that i was not well and confined to bed. f/L Moore wrote the following note which he asked my clerk to show me when I come to officet- f1 A quantity of equipment has been stolen from the' M R.A*F* bombing range. The losses includei- 11 'Flags an&lt;ff flag?ole3 ,, 'Targets' 'Measuring instruments' 'I had hoped to discuss the matter with you this' 'afternoon and to suggest that the Shaikh of Sharjah' 'should take some action. If you could visit the' 'camp tomorrow morning the C.O* cJLould discuss it' 'with you. 'We are going to carry out practice bombing with live' 'bombs tomorrow. The flags which are nonnally hoisted' 'at the range have bean stolen so there will be no' 'visual warning to people in the vicinity. Can you' 'ensure that the Shaikhs and people of Sharjah and' 'Dibai are warned that it will be dangerous to go' 'near the range any time during daylight hours' 'tomorrow.' At 6 pom© my clerk brought f/l Moore» s note to me. As I was not then in a fit condition to do any work, I instruct •ed my clerk to go to the Shaikh at once and to inform him of f/l Moored note. Also to request the Shaikh kindly to see the Commanding officer immediately, discuss the natter with him in detail and arrange things before the morning. The Shaikh sent me a verbal reply with my clerk that he was complying with my request. I understand that the Shaikh met the Commanding Officer the same evening and arranged matter? with him.At 9 Si .m* on Friday 12th Pebiyary 1943, although not quite fit^ I went to see the Commanding Officer but was told by the Adjutant that the Commanding officer was not present (flying). On 12£h p.m# I heard that an Arab by name Khamis bin Sa'id Aba^s-Safi of KhanCSharjah) village received some injuries on account of a bomb bursting near him and splinters getting into his body. He was on his way from the village to the desert to cut grass. I received no report about this incid^mt either from the RoAoF. or from the Shaikh© When f/o A.B#C*Nunn was with me on 19th February 1943 the Shaikh happened to call on me. I asked him about the case and he told me that Khamis was seriously ill on Thursday and that his brother asked the Shaikh for some help and^gave him some money from his private purse. Khamis died on February 19th in his village. The bombing ran^e is in an open desert accross which there are tm ny camel and motor roads wMch are frequented by various people from different p &lt;trts of the Trucial Coast, 0 tyut/yt/ Batinah and the interior of 7^moino When the Commanding Officer asked the Shaikh^ parmis'S -«ion to use this area as a bombing range, he, of his own accord, promised to detail one askari(guard) at each corner of the bombing range to keep away the people from the area while the bombing is taking place. I understand from F/0 Nunn that this practice has been stopped and replaced by poles with small red jglags which are being kept flying all the time in the bomb -ing range® Dated 22nd February 1943. &gt;. r .J.*■■(-!.on 'Go NO o C/177 '^/3 (6) British Agency y Sharjah. 24th February 1943 Copy forwarded for information, toi- 1. The Commanding officer R.A*F*Station f sharjah. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ i OAr\ Residency Agent,SharJahoe^O British Agency, - shjcrjahd 10'oh j 1943 &lt;» MM&lt;&lt;H i&gt;q ^ef^rence yuur ueiuor, aiduw ko. G /309 dat^d Jre March 1043 I that I \. T as late in sending you a r^ort about the Wellington which crashed at SA2I DH.VDJ. T AH» I nade a complete (ii) of ny News H* reporo about the incident in par*.17(ii) of ny News ^^port ]'o«4 for the period ending 28th February which missed the lastvnail bux» will reach you with, this letter. ^ indeed Shaikh i:uharaiaad bin Hamad of ^uj air all was very helpful»As soon as he go* the news he sent two special messengers to me from Fujairah and he proceeded to Dhadnah to look after the aircraft 4. - Before the arrival of the Shaikh of Fujairah my private servant HUhiiDfcKti bin SaliiQ heard about the crashed aircraft^he proceeded to Dhadnah and did every thing he could to help the occupants of the aircraft and to protect the valuable equipment which he took with the men to Khor Pakhan and kept it locked in a safe piace until they all were picked up by H.I.I.3.Hiravati* 5. As soon as H.L.I.S.Hiravati arrived at Sharjah on 20th February I went to the _i«A.F&lt;»Gamp in order to get information the occupants of the aircraft about the help which the local people rendered to them. The H.Ao^o men were not capable of give -ing me any useful infomation buo they carried a letter from / A«- my s ei-vant in which he gave me some information about ^incident • j tried to soe Colonel ''.de— /atteville j . viio w s a pas ^n^er on board the crashed aircraft but was told that he was still on board H.M.I.S.Hiravati® I said wO the Defence Officer then on duty th?,t I wanted to know fror the Colonel in^etail about tlie behaviour and help which tlie local people did fox' them. I asked that if it was not possible for me to see him to request him i s ' *- 2 - kindly to s^nd me a note containing the information I wanteds T T e x jronis3d todo so 'bu^ five d /s passed and I did loo ?et tlie report® T then went to the Adjutant and asked him about the Colonel when he told me that he had already left for India® He however, showed me his report wricn I took to my office and copied® While I was talking to the Adjutant the Commanding Officer came u^ and he told me that he intended to come and see ttu, me to ask ny opinion about ^reward® This of course was the result of my tcilk with some H»A®F® Officers on 19th to whom I suggested that a good reward should be given in such cases otherwise the Arabs would ' ut take so much trouble. I explained vhe amount of trouble and the expense to which I have been put on account of the One Officer said that he would speak to the Commanding Officer and aaked whether Rs.lOOO/- would be a good present. I replied yes, but that every thing depended on the ai ount of services rendered and the funds ^which the H.A»F. could afford to pay (in the previous case of the Blenheim when I asked how they would pay the reward I was told the amount was to be collected by donations)6 a. I said to the Conmandin^ officer that, jood reward should be given and he said that he was prepared to pay whatever I suggested. As the salavage of the wrecked machine was still going I asked the Commanding Officer to inform me as soon as the work was over about the amount of services rendered, guards and etc., so that I may be able to give my opinion. The Cofomanding Officer promised to do so but I have not yet received any® I went twice to see the Commandii^g officer but he was not there. 5* I could not keep the men of the shaikh of Pujairah wait -ing and had to give them lis&lt;&gt;20/- each and food for the road® They left for Fu^airah on 17th February with a letter of thanks to the Shaikh. I think a sum not less than Hs®1000/- should be given to the Shaikh of Fujairah. L T y servant spent Hs.120/- and I paid this amount from my private purse and also ^jnd^rrmi him for his exceptionaly good services of which I am very pleased. I will send a bill to the-3- C RttA#F» and request tliein to refund the anount of HSol20/- to me in due course» 60 para 3 Regarding the Blenheim which crashed on ist February I have Already reported this in para 12 od! uew^' Repoi't 110.3 of 1943 which crossed your letter. As I was made to understand that the reward was to be collected by donations I asked the H.A.F* to ^'ive Muhammad bin Lahij Rs^lOO/- only which they did on 3rd as soon as they finish » -ed work on the crashed aircraft. I fed iiuhamrnad and his brother for one day and also gave them food for the road» The human act of ruhammad in helping the two H.A*F® men for five miles and also coining to 3harjali in tlmt wet ai^d stomy day# deserved more than what I had recommended. Also Saif bin -^arad who will -ingly offered his camel may be given a sum of lis650/- Cn (3th i:arch MuheBBSd^hiS father and brother OflM to me. I entertained them anu then gave them is&lt;&gt;30/- and also iice 1 i, little rice, dates and coffee for ihe ro^d. 7. Few days before the crash of this Blenheim 1 toured the area round Dhaid and talked to many of the Bani Qat&amp;b, Khawatir and Tunaij tribes about the help which they should render to the H.A*F. and other British officials they may find in the desert and also to send me information about them at once» is well educated and can influence the interior tribes to tour British Officials whom they may find in their area on account of forced landing or other reasons. I received assurances from the I.u^im Bani Ka'ab Albu Shavis and the Dhawahir that they would do every thing to comply with my request 9. Para4 There was no political reaction(a) because the man was not killed instantly and(b) living in a village which is hardly visited Toy outsiders. The H.A.F. have sent me a letter 80 About two months ago I also sent a speclul man who that area anu speak to them on my behalf so that they may help- 4 - ^ yesterday asking my opinion about the amount 01 compensation which they should give tohis relatives® I recommended that o'.ey should be given not less than Rs&lt;&gt;400/-• If tl.is case occurBed to a bedouin or any other person of importance his relatives would have demanded full blood money in accordance with the shara 1 law® A copy of the Adjutant*letter ITo.712/p ft l. dated Sth !!arch 1943 and my iteply ^lTo&lt;&gt;0/223-6/3(3) dated 10th liarCh 1943» are enclosed herewith for your information® Res idency Agent,Sharjah«■ N#. C/368 ?• Political Agency, Bahrain, 14th March 19^3. The Residency Agent, Sharj ah• memoranda Please refer to your confidential memorandum No. C/228- 6/3 (B) dated the 10th March 1943. 2. Vv ellln ^ton aircraft i It seems to me that the P.A.F. at Sharjah have not in the past sufficiently recognised the importance in their own future interests of giving promnt and generous rev/ards for assistance rendered after the occur rence of accidents, I have today seen Squadron-Leader Patrick and have emphasised to him the importance of ensuring he^p for the future by the grant of generous rewards for assistance given in the present. I have also drawn his attention to the importance of his consulting the Political authorities in these matters. 0S 3. I have advised him, as soon as salvage of the wrecked Wellington is completed, to send the Shaikh of Fujairah a reward of Hs. 1000/-. I have advised him also to consult you in regard to the wording of the letter which accompanies the reward and T have said that the letter with the money should be delivered through you. The money should, I suggest, be sent to the Shaikh in payment of the services rendered by the guards, etc., appointed by him. It might be a good thing, when you send the letter and the money to the lhaikh, to let it be known what amount is being paid so that, if the Shaikh keeps the money for himself, his followers will know that it is the Shaikh and not the H .A .F. who has been ^ \ ungenerous. This detail, however, I leave to your discretion. If, after hearing details of the services rendered by the / from Shaikh of Fujairah and his guards you consider Is. 1000/- funds insufficient, you should still accept that amount from the whic I R .A .F. and add to it/any amount up to Rs. 1000/- that you am in a consider suitable. The whole amount can then be sent to position the Shaikh with a suitable letter acknowledging on behalf to pro- of the British Government his good services, vide. 4. I send herewith a sum of Rs. 200/- for payment to your servant Mohammad bin Salim in recognition of the excellent services rendered by him. The sum of Rs 120/- which you have paid from your private purse should be recovered from the R .A .F. 5. 'ilonr-eltii aircraft ; Please pay to Wohammad bin Lahij a further sum of R 100/- in recognition of the assistance given by him at the beginning of February. Rs. 50/- should also be given to Saif bin Qarad for the use of his camel. * 6. I send herewith a sum of Rs. 600/- to be utilised as follows (1) Rs. 350/- to be distributed as specified above. (2) Rs. 30/- to reimburse yourself for the money given to Mohammad bin Lahij, his father and his brother. ► (3) /-. i •,v sSf-i —i(3) The balance of Rs. 220/- should be kept by you and you may use it at your own discretion in making payments for future services rendered in circums tances similar to those which form the subject of this letter. I will, of course, send you further funds when these are exhausted . % 7. It is in my opinion most important that British officers should acquire a reputation throughout the Trucial Coast for generosity in rewarding assistance given to/cbodAooc or stranded service personnel • 'hen the R. A.F. consuTt you about rewards you should recommend that they be given on a liberal scale. v ou yourself should not hesitate to reward generously services rendered and you need only telegraph to me for autho rity in cases where the reward which you orooose to give exceeds Rs 200/-. Political Agent, BahrainFrom:- Rear Air Headquarters, R*A«F* •Iraq and Persia. To The political Agent, Sharjah. Date:- 20th March, 1943. Ref :- C*2^142/6/12/p.l CQIIFIDBNTIAL « RKWARD FOR ASSISTANCE TO CREW OF \VRBCK3D AIRCRAFT. !♦ The Air officer Commanding has had under cons id -eration the conduct of a Bedouin Arab and his wife who on the 2nd and 3rd February 1943, rendered assistan -ce to the two survivors of a Bisley aircraft B .A.101, which had crashed 35 miles east north east of Sharjah. 2. The Bedouin Arab took the survivors a distance of several miles to his tent, where he and his wife gave theo food and shelter for the night, while the Bedouin journeyed to Sharjah by camel to bring assistan -ce. But for the intervention of these Bedouins, one if not both survivors would probably have parished. 3. As a mark of appreciation felt by the Royal Air Force for this kind and effective help, the Air Officer Commanding has directed the payment to the Bedouin concerned of a reward of 200 Rupees. 4. It is requested that you will be good enough to read and hand to him a translation of this letter. (Signed) . W.S.H. Muir. w/cdr. for Air V^ce Marshal,imm.. , s'l D.0.No #442-6/3 (B) ^| £ • British Agency, Sharjah* Dated the 9th Uay 1943* Dear ll±si£ Conaan^ier, \ ^ I had accasion, more than a month ago, to speak to your predecessor about the possibility of a Bedouin traveller blundering into your cunp by night and being shot by a sentry, and I attempted to make clear to him the very sertious consequences of such an event. I told hii^ it w*s highly desirable that the portion of the camp facing t&gt;e desert, from which side unsuspecting wayfarers might be expected to come, should be fenced off. He said that he had not sufficient wire, but I gave it as my opinion that a line of kerosene tins topped by even a single stranu of wire would be sufficient and I understood' him to sqy that he wouldtake the necessary action* ^ 2o Bedouin frequently travel by night ana this time of year and some of them come from long distances to visit Sharjah and Dubai so that, although I have warned all the Shaikhs and have asked them to pass on the warning, it is probable that many of theft Bedouin of the hinterland are unaware of the danger of entering camp limits bv nieht and of the procedure to adopt when challanged. 3* It would be difficult to exaggerate the seriousness of the consequences which would arise if tribal blood were shed by any one in our employ. Tribes^men would probably retaliate by trying to kill a member of the R. a -F . and the position of crews of aircraft making forced landings in the interior would be unpleasant, political repercussions might be more serious still. I bave noticed a certain number of armed British sentries on your camp lately and this vaster increases the urgency and import an -ce of the question. British personnel cannot be expected to know Arabic or to distinguish a Bedouin Shaikh frou a local thief and I must ask you to take ad^uate steps as soon as possiole to obviate the danger of such an incident occuring. Yours Sincerely. Sd/ Ll.P.O'C Tandy• Wing C□i^andar Ho uherai^ D. F -C • f •, Commanding uxficer, R.A.F. Station, SHARJAH . Copy forwarded with compliments to the political A^ent, Bahrain®N# .484-6/3(3) 7^ The PQlitical Agent, Bahrain. (P British agency, bharjaiu juated tJie 34 th nay 1^3 &lt;v Subject :- jirlrg at ,^ a .F&gt; plane * A Bisley aircraft of the squadron here was found to have a 'bullet-hole in the exhaust on returning from putrcl on 22nd Hay and this must have been caused either during the bombing demonstration here on 21st, when flying flying over Kuus-al-jebal on 22nd, or while flying down the coast from Ras tl Khaimah after patrol on that day. As it is highly improbable that the aircraft was fired at over Sharjah, and unlikely that any one on the coast would fire at it, it was almost certainly fired on over Ruus-al-jebal. 2. , It is hoped that it will be possible for the bultan of Kuscats representatives on the ttuu4-al-Jeb«l coast to restrain the Shihuh from this particular form of exuberance. us?- political-^flUer ,Trucial Coast. Copy to:- The Officer Commanding, R.A.F.Station, bharjah o /ty' V \ £ c rv.iT {j) 1AD0/2006/1/S. \ 1 No 1 Aircraft Delivery Unit, Royal Air Force, Middle East. 21st. May, 1943. H.B.M. Political Agent, Bahrein, Persia. On 31st. May, 1942, P/0 Pickering, then of this Unit, was captain of a Boston aircraft that forced '^nded on the 'beach at PAJRAK about 150 miles south of /'MSHIRE. P/0, Brockman, P/0 Ayre and W/0 Davies were passengers in the aircraft. The four parachutes belonging to these officers, were salvaged and were left in the care of the Sheik of Parak when the party proceeded 'by donkey to TABIRI. Twelve days later the party was rescued from TABIRI 'by H.M.S. Seabelle II, and a party was sent to Parak to recover the parachutes, but the Sheik was away at that time, end his retainers said that they knew nothing of the parachutes. The captain of the Seabelle could not wait for further investigation. On arrival at Bahrein the loss of the parachutes was reported to the Officer Commanding the R.A.F. establishment, who passed on a report to the Political Agent, who later interviewed the rescued party and promised to carry out a full investigation. It is understood that a letter was sent to the British Consul at Bushire, requesting him to ask the Sheik for the parachutes when he made the next duty tour of the coast. Nothing further has been heard of the matter by this Unit and action has been taken for the 'write-off' of the parachutes. Headquarters, R.A.F., M.E. have now asked for a statement showing the result of the investigations by the Political Agent at Bahrein a-nd the British Consul at Bushire, including an explanation of what the Sheik said happened to the parachutes. The numbers of the parachutes, which were all Pilot type, are 73509, 113311, 71613 and 76285. Statements from the addressee of this letter and the recipients of the copies, will be much appreciated, so that this matter can be concluded. (R._ . for .Ving Commander, n ^D) F/O, Commanding, No 1 Aircraft Delivery Unit, Royal Ai r Force,M idd le East . Copies to :- H.B .M. Consul, Bushire, Persia. O.C., R.A.F^ Station, Bahrein. H .Q., S-ifTGroup, R .A.F., M .E.n D.O. No. C/836 Pollti: al Agency, Bahrain, the 19th June 1943 ■ a ?■ ^lo^se V/ill you please refer to letter No. IADU/2006/1/S, dated the 21st May 1943, from No. 1 Aircraft Delivery Unit, Royal Air Force, Middle East. 2. These parachutes were referred to in paragraphs 3 and 7 of my confidential demi-official letter No.'C/897, dated the 23rd June 1942, to Colonel Hay- I also wrote a manuscript letter to Colonel Hay asking if steps could be taken to recover the four parachutes. I believe that the parachutes were restored to the Royal Air Force but have no confirmation of this- 3. If you are able to give all the information required by No. 1 Aircraft Delivery Unit will you please let me have a copy of your letter ? Yours sincerely. Captain J.B. Howes, H. M. Consul, Bushire. eM r dCalifornia Arabian Standard Oil Company Dhahran, Saudi Arabia September 6, 19A3 n His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Dear Sir: For your information, an R.A.F. Beaufighter, LX-885, landed at Dhahran today at 8:^.0 G.M.T. after being unable to land at Bahrein on account of low visibility. We are accommodating the crew of two at our camp this even ing, and they expect to proceed to Bahrein tomorrow morning, Sep tember 7* We are sending a special message to the Air Liaison Officer over our Awali Circuit reading as follows; ''For ALO. LX-885 Dhahran 8: AD G.M.T. 6/9 Stop 0^:00 G.M.T. 7/9 Bahrein report requested ends Ohliger,' Very truly yoursConfidentialo N 0 •C/1090-6/3(B) British AgancyiSharJaho Dated the 19th October 1943. To f aAio The Coramanding officer, ^ ^ R.A.F.Station, 0 cr i ^ '\\v subjact t Payment to the Shaikh of Fu-ialrah . MlSMOHAMiXJM. / \ tt Reference letter aHAH/l26l/ACCm dated the 14th October 1943 froni Administrative officer and imprest Holder. R.Aoi^o station, Sharjah, Paiforce# ' 2 * ^ Immediately after the accident in question the Residency Agent did nis utmost to secure from Lieutenant-colonel K*De Watteville ^•E»who was a passenger on the wrecked aircraft, a statement of the services rendered by the Shaikh and his men, but was unable to do so* LAter the Defence officer promised to obtain a written statement from the Colonel but this was not received by us. Ho details can, therefore, be given but it is understood that guards were supplied for the protec- ^ ich they presumably guarded from the date of the forced landing until its removal. The Shaikh himself went tothe scene of the accident to supervise operations, so far is as known no rations or stores were supplied. 3# . in the case of an aircraft which crashes in an uncivilised country not under British suzerainty, and amongst semi-savage tribesmen whose attitude towards foreigners v-ithin their limits tends to be hostile it is vital to secure their good-will and that of their chiefs by the payment of prompt and generoua rewards for assistance rendered. The object of paying the reward might be defeated if we were to demand detail ed accounts from them, such as can reasonably be demanded in India or I raq where the people are under the control of law and of Governments allied to us. Political Officer,Trucial Coast. 0 -.. . , ? 0 Pyt wi tji copy of the letter to which it is a reply to the To wlth rafer6nC6 to his confidential mamorandum Mo.C/368 dat«d 'hh* 1A+Vi tqaq oi^uiu No.0/368 dated the 14th March 1943. r ^ \copy. Froo;- Air Headquarters, Iraq and Persia,jt.A» F«Paif6rce. 10 :- Poli'c.ical ufi'icer/nrucial Coaso British a . ency,;5k rjah. Dao • 19th February 1944. kef m\y290i/2o/auct. Tel«]3xt:3i57. C1V3H&lt;D ^V/SLi.IlIGTOlT' AI^CIUFT ICC.748- TC JHX IC CF FUJAI IUI. 'Jith reference to your letter Ilo.c/1090-6/3(±5j dao-.d the _-9th October 11343, to the Cona'andinj officer, xt.A-K.^taion ^harjah, v/ho forvarded that letoer to tiiis. headquarters unuer cover of shah/ 1261/Accts dated the 21st October, X943, according to information held at t^is -^headquarters, the fol-o-uin^ sums were paid from K*A*K Gharjah public funds in connection with the crash at SAHDENAH on 14th February, l ( &gt;i3 July 1943 - 'Reward' to che shaikh lis. 1,000 Au w ust, - l .943 - Payment ta Khan nahadur ns. 160 ko • 1 3 4 .60 SSZTst rr « : 2. it hsb been necessary to refer the subject to the rt ir Ministry c.nd, consequent on instructions no\/ ' go hand, it io recuired the.t,if possible, further deoai-s be furnished re UJ &lt;irdin 0 ja^iaents which are staged to be 'rewards' but which includes such items as jupplyin w ^uaras, supervision of op iratioifkand,presui .ably, aire of 0.11 jw , animals and/or supply of fresh food,and services rendered generally 3. Accorain^ly, it is requested that you will state whether you are in a position to certify as to the reasonableness of the a. -sunt paii- in relation ^o the services, etc. rendered, including reas; nable renumeration to the Shaikli for personal assistance as organiser or supervisor of the operations involved. 4. 5t is .indicated in correspondence that certain payments c: 'c made by your servant ^Muhai jaad bin tfallin) were these j^a^iaents additional to the ks.a .,000/- or inclusive ? Ccin you also say exactly \;hat guards for the damaged aircraft were supplied by the bhaikh, for aow lon^ \,he aircraft remainded at oalidenali and what avera^ e wa, e per day was paiu ? o. Any other detailed iafomation you can supply oulc be appreciated, and i. is requested tliat you will reply as soon as possible in order taat the sub J jet u. j oe cleared satisfactorily .vithout further _ielay. adA Illegible ( tt %.! t-itoit - //bjk.) for staff Officer i/c adi.iniatration. di^roia to Date kef i^ir Headquarters, J-raq &amp; Persia, H»A*F»Paif(ar«e Political Ajent,liharjah. 18th February 1944. IIUQ/2350/lC /p.l 1 v Tel.Kxt;357 cj •^r.L^r' itvz UF': ~ /^LI OF jniij Ab Reference is made to your ietter U•0.Uo•8x7-34/3 a daxed the 2nd August 1943 to win^ Uoiarnander ?otherhaia,u.j?*#(j. Sharjah, re lative to the above subject, a copy of which levoer \was forv arced oo tAl:- : 7 eaclquf. rters under cover of 3tation,oharjah letter . SHAk / x259/ACGT3 datjd 25.9.43 2. According to information held at this Headquarters, the following is the financial position in connection \^ith the crashes;• Bills ^ubiai Q-ued by the Wali; - Ri Ai Hires of coilies, donkeys and watclu en. 579.12. Fresh rations supplied ..... 114. 4. -do- anu hire of col cullies 336. -. Total as.1,C3C.— Amounts actually paid 'uhi ^ou ^h ^harjah Public Imprest Account;- 9th July x943 4th xiu^ust, jl 943 22nd Septamber 1943 (should have been RS.200/) 29th September 1L43 (for food etc.) 30G. - 20C. - 4CC. - 504. 4. .,404. 4, 'rc'^7 3. it will be seen froi the above that there is an s ^parent overpayment of Ks.374/4 but ohere are , inaicax-ions that the first payment may have been in connection itSL an ec.rlifc^r crash or forced landiii^ of a 'Vincent' aircraft. The receipt of the ^haikli of chinas (Hs.300/- on 9th July 1943), is supported by a receipt ^iven by f / q . buchai.an to F/Lt. Coombes on 31st i::ay v^943 , but it hao been stated in oharjah letter lJo.244/706/36/p.l dated the 3rd llovember, 1943 that no 'Vincent' had ever crashed or forced landed at chinas. J-t woula be appreciated. 4. J-t has been necessary to refer the whole subject to the Air Ministry and consequent on receipt of certain instructions, it is requested that yau will say wLetlar you are satisfied that the total crashes and subsequently 5. Your earl v ^ reply is requested in order that this lon^ out standing ma - oer luay be settled tothe satisfaction of all concerned. Sd/- Illegible (H .A .MUHTOK - W/CDH.) For Dtaff Officer i/c Ad: ;inistrati©n.lat AU^Uo-O 1943. Wo.2^i4 squadron, iioyal A±r Force, Iraq t ixi Poraia. acci:mjt of alhchaft bu\.43c ut shii^lb 01^ 30'tli aplill) 1^3. In coni-cGLion \v' ioh tlie above i.entioned accident, it is desired now to make ecme form of payment to tlie \7ali of biiinas. of Over a period/nearly three months, he hat shown every courtesy and consideration to Personnel, havin_ supplied w uard£ food labour throughout this time. In June he received 'ohe sum of 'mpeet 300 and he had now made it known that h« woulc appreciate a further jift of 12 bags of rice, 2 ba^s of wheat and G maundo of sujar. It is considered however, that in view or tht i.any services rendered by the vvali to the R*A*F«, a furtlier ex-^ra'oia par ent in cash could well be made. \ r our comments oi: this will be appreciated. ^d/rt i^.hotharhatu I v'in c ^ Comi anu er, Coi U-.enain^ • II u. 2^i4 squadron, d* A* f. Political Ajent, Sharjah. - D.O.LTo.817-34/3^ British Agency, vjharj ah. 2nd August u.943. c Dear \;in w Commander, Kindly refer uo your letter ;.o.2^1/706/36/?.1 daoed the 1st August -^943. A i )en,ii'G is enclosed for ohe purchase of 8 bi 0 s uc-ud Khan rice, 2 ba^s wheat, 10 bajs Karachi rice ana 6 maunds su^ar in uubc i, a all of which should cost i ^ proxii ately :{s.4S8/-. in addition to this I su^isx you make the Shaikh of ohinas a p 'e sent of ks.20q/- in order to brinj the tot; 1 amount of I.iai regard to the neighbourhood of jts. r,000/- which, in my opinion*minimum he should receive. He has also expressed a wish for 2 bicycle tyres am four tubes, xhese will be available locally in about two months time and I am sure the Shaikh would much appreciate it if you send them to him. Yours sincerely. Sd/- 1,1.p.0* c Tandy. M ;in£ Gomi ander .^.Tlotherham j.v.C-, Commanding officer, A . . oilojah. LAir Headquarters, Iraq &amp; Persia, R*A«F«, Paiforoe* The Political Agent, BAHREIN. 7th MAECH, 1%4. ^ ^ IRA&lt;l/2350/l0/P.l/A3CT. Tel .Ext; 357 . CRASHED H BISLBr M AIRCRAFT - PAYMENTS TO WALI OP SHINAS. Reference is made to memo, 323-5i«/5D dated the 16th February, 1944, from Political Officer, Trucial Coast, to you, copy to this Headquarters* 2» The contents of that communication have been duly noted and it is nan required that, in particular, a certificate or statement be furnished on the basis of para .4 of this Headquarters letter of even number dated 18th February, 1944, to the Political Agent, SHARJAH, a copy of which letter is now held by you. 3* It would be appreciated if such a certificate could be forwarded by you in the light of information in your possession. m P -(H.A. MURTON, W/CDR.) ^Staff Officer i/c Administration. {} Copy to;- Political Officer, Trucial Coast, British Agep^y, SHARJAH. - . a- i L.Reference. TH3 0PPIG3 OP THE AIR LIAISON OPPIGSR, BAHRAIN. 12th March, 1944. H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, CRASHED 'V /ELLmGTQN' AIRCR/ iFT FIX. 7^.* The enclosed copy of letter was received 'by the Air Liaison Officer. 2« This is a matter with which you are dealing and we enclose the copy referred to. (C.H.WALLACE P/o) Adjutant, R.A.P. Station Ba hrai n,prom:- Air Headquarters, L Iraq &amp; Persia, R.A.P., PAIPORCE# %o i'he Political Agent, BAHREIN. Date:- 6th MARCH# 1944® Ref :- IRAQ/290i/SS/ACCi'• i'el&gt;Bxt: 557# CRASHED 'WELLIiMG'rOi^ 1 AIRCRAFT hx.748 - PAYMj^TS to sheikh op pujairah. -TW Rgference is made to memo, C/320-6/3( B) dated the 26th February, 1944, from the Political officer, xrucial coast, to you, copy to this Headquarters# 2« The conteuts of that communicatiolu have been duly xioted and, as it would seem that certain detailed information may be in your possession, it would be appreciated if you would send copies of, or appropriate extracts from, your memo, g/368 dated 14th March, 1943, and the Residency Agentfs memo. C /228-6/3 (B) dated the 10th November, 1943, (referred to in paras. 2 and 4 respectively of the memo, quoted in para.i above)© TP -yO 3o It is desirable that further details should be supplied to this Headquarters in connection with th» subject of this letter, and, in particular, that a certificate or statement should be furnished on the basis of para # 3 of this Headquarters letter of even number dated uhe i9th February, i944, to the Political Agent, Trucial Coast, a copy of which letter is now held by you# jo (Jif ^ , x Z 7 (H.A.MURTOn - W/CDR. ) &lt; vstaff officer i/c Administration# Copy to:- Political officer, crucial coast, British Agency, SHARJAH#7IO.C/479. From To Political y^gency, Bahrain, 15th Inarch, 1944. Sir, Major T. Hiekinbothorn, o .B .'f;, , Political Agent, Bahrain. Thu Staff Officer i/c Administration, Air Headquarters, Iraq &amp; Persia, h.a.f., Paiforee. I have the honour to refer to your memorandum No.IRAQ/ 2360/10/P.1/ACCT. Tel.Ext.367 dated the 7th March 1944 and to inform you that I am satisfied that the total amount paid is reasonable for the goods supplied and the work performed, \ inclucr'ng proper and reasonable remuneration to the V /ali for the services he rendered personally as organiser at the times of the crashes and subsequently. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient e ervant, 0/r Politicfil Agent, Bahrain. ' ,— ■ — ■ ' ■'— 9P No.C/788. Political y\gency, Bahrain, 18th May 1944 To The Staff Officer i/c Administration, y\ir Headquarters, Pa5*forco. I x j , { V r MEMORANDUM ©. Reference your memorandum No.ITIAQ/^OlA^/ACCT. dated the 7th May 1944. 2. I certify that the amount paid was reasonable in relation to uhe services rendered. I do not consider that to reopen the case at this stage would be advisable or profitable. Political Agent, Bahrain.i Telegram From To No. 93. S(Pad). Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. ' &lt; 9 Dated the 9th February, 1945. IMMEDIATE- . Single engined air-craft force landed Daiyir on Persian Coast bearing 2752 N, 5157 £. Pilot unhurt. Naval vessel with mechanics and guard of Indian troops leaving P.M. today 9th February to render assistance. \ • R. M. - POLITICAL - ifh± 41 s Z- f • yi - Translation of letter dated 5th Shauwal 1364 (11-9-45) from 1 Id bin Mohammed bin Jasim al-Moraikhi, resident oT'Sir Island, a dependency to Abu Dhabi,at Bahrain to the Political agent, Bahrain. (~XT) } a.c. I beg to say that you issued an order, enclosed, to give any possible assistance to the persons in the two planes which landed at Jazirat Yas, belonging to Abu Dhabi. We did our duty and help and did our best for them - I, 'Id bin Mohammed bin Jasim al Moraikhi and my brother Hadhir bin Mohammed al Moraikhi. We collected about thirty more persons and served the men in the two planes. We did all our best service for the two planes. We worked for 3 days. We paid all the expenses and food. We bought all their necessities until they left. We offered our services and we are the grateful. We will Inshallah keep a watch for any plane or person who come to our side. We will honour any service necessary. We are in the service of God and vours. We request you to consider our application for a (monetary; help, U.E. Translation of the enclosure. To all whom it may concern. A.C, I have received information that two planes belonging to His Majesty's Government, have landed at Jazirat Yas. You should afford all possible assistance to the persons in these planes for vhich you will be rewarded for your services in this respect, Sd, T.Hichinbotham. Political Agent, Bahrain, 23rd April 1944. BaKraia ReceiptReceived from the Political Agent, Bahrain the sura of Rs.lOO/- (one hondred only) being our reward for the assistance we rendered in Yas Island for the two aircaft which landed in April 1944. (r-i wf . m Mohammed bin Jasim al Moraikhi i : ' Hadhir bin Mohammed al Moraikhi Bahrain, 15-9-45. ft-Telegram GTC From P.O.T.C. Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. . 306 Dated arid received the 19th March, 1946. • • • • • On March -T8th R.A.'P. Wellington from Shar.jah flying low over S.S. Afghanistan anchored off Abu Musa struck main topmast. Aircraft rudder carried aw?y and belly landed island. Crew uninjured and returned Sharjah same day by launch. Details follow^ in letter. =POLITICAL= AMO. Hahvaia Receipt no &lt;.1-5..-^t i V/.Wo. Translation of letter from Nakhuda Hassan bin Khuda Rasan, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, I beg to state that there are two aeroplanes which crashed in Iran some years ago - one in Bandar Shirino - one in Bandar Beedah Khoon. I am prepared to bring them to Bahrain if you issue me letters to Shaikh Sulaiman bin Shaikh Hatan of Kangoon and Shaikh Abdul Rasool in Nakhal Taqi to assist me in loading them in a boat and bring them to Bahrain. I approached the Adviser to the Bahrain Government who referred me to you. U.S. BAHRAIN receipt , L.S-tateraent of Nakhuda Hassan bin Khuda Hasan of Bahrain, taken at the Political Agency, Bahrain on 8th May, 1946. About one month ago I heard from some Persian people who came from Iran to Bahrain that there are two aeroplanes - I do not know their type - crashed In Iran. One of them was burnt by fire. This plane is now lying on the beach of Bandar Beedah Khoon about 1^- miles on the east of Beedah Khoon village. This plane crashed there, but actually I do not know the date of its crashing ^ whether It was one month or one ydar nor do I know anything about the airmen, because I heard about the planes only. The other one crashed on the beach a bit north of Shirino village. According to the statements of Shirino village, conveyed to me by the informants that a warship - I do not know what nationality - came there and fired the engine of this plane. About the airmen I know nothing nor the date of crashing. As I have learnt that these are British planes, I thought that they will be of use if brought to Bahrain. For this reason I submitted an application to the Advisor of the Bahrain Government and the Political Agent, Bahrain, offering my services to the Government to bring these two planes from Iran to Bahrain by hire. u #v L.T.I, of Nakhuda Hassan bin Khuda Rasani/t Adviser, I beg to advise you that two aeroplanes fell down on the beach of persia, one in Shirinow bander and the second in Khoon's bander. If you like to bring them to Bahrain you may please write a letter to Sh. ^ulaiman in Bander Rangoon and Sh, A.R-asool in Taq.i' garden in persia in order to help me in loa ding the aeroplanes in the boat. Hassan bin Khuda Resan. JM. ; ///?/?? / • } ■ J 6 li U l i !V/ 10 The question of the ownership of crashed R.A.F. ^ aircraft and their removal from Persia particularly to Bahrain might cause considerable disturbance. It is particularly sq.now that British troops have been withdrawn from Persia. If they are wanted -aireraft, they would undoubtedly have taken steps to remove them long ago. The applicant may be informed verbally that if his services are required he will be called in. 12.5.»46. H -h. ^ C,L^r^ PA* kfa:- ^ 1 ^ s* ^ 5- s'' u f 'I s</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000092_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/275</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000092</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/275</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 7/10 Mishaps to R.A.F. aircraft’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-04T00:24:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (96 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest items at the front of the file to the latest at the end. The office notes at the end of the file (folios 93-98) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover, using pencil numbers written in the top-right corner of each recto. The following foliation anomalies occur: 1, 1A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letters, telegrams and other papers in the file relate to various forced landings or crashes of Royal Air Force (RAF) aircraft, as well as other incidents involving the RAF, in and around the Gulf, during and immediately after the Second World War. The principal correspondents in the file are the Political Agent in Bahrain, the Political Officer on the Trucial coast (both posts being occupied by numerous incumbents), and a number of RAF officials.The key events and topics discussed in the file are: reports of a crashed Blenheim aircraft near Dohah [Doha] in December 1941; reports of a missing Boston aircraft in May 1942, and the subsequent discovery of it having made a forced landing on the Persian coast while skirting prohibited airspace above Bahrain; reports of a crashed Bisley aircraft near Sharjah in March 1943; the recovery of aircrews and salvage of aeroplanes; the treatment of aircrews by local inhabitants, including payments to guards requested to protect crash sites; and an incident in February 1942 in which a man was accidentally killed at the bombing range at Sharjah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Air accidents</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000092#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>