<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023655870.0x000011_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T00:05:28.545Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100023655870.0x000011_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/28, ff 1C-87</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023655870.0x000011</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/28, ff 1C-87</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter no. 1584 of 1822, from Secretary to Government, Political Department, Bombay, to Lieutenant John MacLeod</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1822/1822</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-01T01:09:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>87 folios</extent><extent>Physical Condition: Text is missing due to insect damage on folios 3 and 4.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Informs MacLeod that Captain William Bruce has been removed from the position of Resident at Bushire and he has been selected to succeed him.Enclosures:Copy of letter no. 35 of 1822 from William Bruce, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Shiraz, to Mountstuart Elphinstone, President and Governor in Council at Bombay (ff. 11-15);'Translation of an agreement proposed by His Royal Highness Hossain Ali Mirza [Ḥusayn ‘Alī Mīrzā] through his minister Zakee Khan [Zākī Khān] and discussed between him and William Bruce Esquire Resident at Bushire on the 30th August 1822' (ff. 16-21);Copy of letter no. 117 of 1822 from F Warden, Poona, to James Parish, Acting Secretary to Government of Bombay, dated 27 October 1822;Copy of letter no. 1491 of 1822 from James Parish, Acting Secretary to Government of Bombay, to Captain William Bruce, Resident at Bushire, dated 1 November 1822 (ff. 26-29);'Draft of a letter from the Honorable the Governor in Council to His Royal Highness Hoossein Allee Meerza [Ḥusayn ‘Alī Mīrzā], the Prince Regent of Fars' (ff. 30-32);'Draft of a letter from the Honorable the Governor in Council to His Highness the Imaum of Muskat [Imam of Muscat] (ff. 32-33v);'Draft of a letter from the Honorable the Governor in Council to the Shaik of Bahrein [Shaikh of Bahrain] (ff. 33v-34v);'Minute of the Honorable Governor' (ff. 36-38);Letter no. 236 of 1822 to from Mountstuart Elphinstone, President and Governor in Council, to Willock, His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at Tehran, dated 7 February 1822 (ff. 38v-40);Letter no. 234 from F Warden to Captain William Bruce, dated 7 February 1822 (f. 40v);'Translation of the Cowlnama or written Engagement from the Imam of Muscat' dated 1 Jamada al-awal 1213 or 12 October 1798 (ff. 42-43v);'An agreement entered into by the Imam of the state of Oman with Captain John Malcom Bahadur Envoy from the Honorable the Governor General Dated the 21 Shaban 1813 [sic] Hejree or 18 January 1800' (ff. 42v-44);'Correspondence with Captain Moresby regarding the Salve Trade' (ff. 46-54);'Sketch of the articles proposed by Captain Morseby to His Highness The Imam of Muscat for the prevention of the foreign slave traffic' (ff. 54-58);'Translation of a letter from the Imaum of Muscat to the Governor of the Isle of France [Sir Robert Farquhar]' (ff. 59-60);Copy of letter no. 1338 of 1822 from James Parish, Secretary of Government of Bombay, to Fairfax Moresby, Captain of His Majesty's Ship Menai, dated 21 September 1822 (ff. 61-62);Copy of letter no. 63 of 1822 from Simson, Deputy Secretary of Government of Bombay, to James Parish, Secretary of Government of Bombay, dated 21 September 1822 (ff. 63-69);'Substance of a letter from His Highness the Imaum of Muscat to the Honorable Mountstuart Elphinstone, Governor of Bombay, Dated 22 Zeehujee [Dhū al-Ḥijjah 1237] or 9 September 1822 (ff. 70-71);Letter from Moresby to James Parish, dated 22 September 1822 (ff. 72-76v);'Translation of a letter from the Imaum of Muscat to the Governor of the Isle of France' (f. 77);'Translation of a letter in Arabic from the Imaum of Muscat to Governor of Zanzibar' (ff. 77v-78);Copy of letter no. 1342 of 1822 from James Parish to Fairfax Moresby, Captain of His Majesty's Ship Manai, dated 23 September 1822 (f. 79);Copy of letter no. 1350 of 1822 from James Parish to Fairfax Moresby, dated 24 September 1822 (f. 80);Copy of letter no. 58 of 1822 from William Simson to James Parish, dated 24 September 1822 (ff. 80v-82);Copy of letter no. 1351 of 1822 from James Parish to Fairfax Moresby, dated 24 September 1822 (ff. 82v-83);Copy of letter no. 1363 of 1822 from James Parish to Fairfax Moresby, dated 27 September 1822 (ff. 84-85);'Draft of letter from the Honorable Mountstuart Elphinstone Governor of Bombay to His Highness the Imaum of Muskat' dated 1 August 1821 (ff. 86-87).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023655870.0x000011#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>