<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T11:23:14.905Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IffTREATIES AND UNDERTAKINGS IN FORCE BETWEEN THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND THE SULTANS OF MASKAT AND OMAN 1845-1914Treaties and Undertakings in force between the British Government and the Sultans of Maskat and Oman, 1845—1914. Note .—In the event of doubt hereafter arising aa to the precise interpretation of any portion of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text ihall bo considered decisive.] No. 1. AGREEMENT BETWEEN HER MAJESTY THE QUEEN OE THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND IRELAND AND HIS HIGHNESS STUD SAEED BIN SULTAN, 'THE SULTAN OF MUSKAT,' FOR THE TERMINATION OF THE EXPORT OF SLAVES FROM THE AFRICAN DOMINIONS OF HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MUSKAT—1815. Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland being earnestly desirous that the export of slaves from the African Dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muskat should cease, and His High ness the Sultan of Muskafc in deference to the wishes of Her Majesty and of the British nation, and in furtherence of the dictates of humanity which have heretofore induced him to enter into engagement with Great Britain to restrict the export of slaves from his dominions, being willing to put an end to that trade and Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and His Highness the Sultan of Muskat having resolved to record with due form and solemnity this further restriction of the export of slaves, and Her Majesty having given due authority to Captain Hamerton, Her Representative at the Court of the Sultan of Muskat, to conclude an agreement with His Highness, accordingly His Highness Syud Saeed bin Sultan, for himself, his heirs and successors, and Captain Hamerton on behalf of the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, her heirs and successors have agreed upon and concluded the following Articles :— Article 1. His Highness the Sultan of Muskat here engages to prohibit, under the severest penalties, the export of slaves from his African Dominions and to issue orders to his officers to prevent and suppress such trade. Article 2. His Highness the Sultan of Muskat further engages to prohibit, under the severest penalties, the importation of slaves from any part of Africa into his possessions in Asia, and to use his utmost influence with all the Chiefs of Arabia, the Red Sea, and the Persian Gulf, in like manner, to prevent the introduction of slaves from Africa into their respective territories. Article 3. His Highness the Sultan of Muskat grants to the ships of Her Majesty's Navy as well as to those of the East India Company, permission to seize and confiscate any vessels, the property of His Highness or of his subjects, carrying 43 F. and P. D. 3on slare trade, excepting only such as are engaged in the transport of slaves from one port to another of his own dominions in Africa between the port of Lamoo to the north and its dependencies, the northern limit of which is the north point of Kuyhoor Island in 1° 57' (one degree and fifty-seven minutes) South Latitude and the port of Kulwa to the south and its dependencies, the southern limit of which is the Songa Manora or Pagoda Point in 9° 2' (nine degrees and two minutes) South Latitude, including the Islands of Zanzibar, Pemba and Monfea. Article 4, This agreement to commence and have effect from the 1st (first) day of January 1847 (one thousand eight hundred and forty-seven) of the year of Christ and the 15th day of the month of Mahaneerun 1263 (twelve hundred and sixty-three) of the Hegira. Done at Zanzibar this 2nd (second) day of October 1845 (one thousand and eight hundred and forty-five) of the year of Christ and 29th day of Ramzan 1261 (twelve hundred and sixty-one) of the Hegira. (Sd.) ATKINS HAMEETON, Captain. On behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, her heirs and successors.No. 2 {a). LETTEE TO HIS HIGHNESS THE SAIYID THUWAINI BIN SAID BIN SULTAN OE MASQAT EROM HIS EXCELLENCY THE VICEROY AND GOVERNOR-GENERAL OE INDIA, DATED 2ND APRIL 1861. Beloved and esteemed Eriend ! I address Your Highness on the subject of the unhappy differences which have arisen between yourself and Your Highness's brother, the ruler of Zanzibar, and for the settlement of which Your Highness has engaged to accept the arbi tration of the Viceroy and Governor-General of India. Having regard to the friendly relations which have always existed between the Government of Her Majesty the Queen and the Government of Oman and Zanzibar and desiring to prevent war between kinsmen, I accepted the charge of arbitration between you and in order to obtain the fullest knowledge of all the points in dispute t directed the Government of Bombay to send an officer to Muscat and Zanzibar to make the necessary enquiries. Brigadier Coghlan was selected for this purpose, an officer in whose judgment, intelligence and impartiality the Government of India reposes the utmost confidence. Brigadier Co^hlan has submitted a full and clear report of all the questions at issue between Your Highness and your brother. I have given my most careful attention to each of these questions# The terms of my decision are as follows :— —That His Highness Syud Majid be declared ruler of Zanzibar and the African dominions of His late Highness Syud Saeed. 2 n d,—That the ruler of Zanzibar pay annually to the ruler of Muscat a subsidy of 40,000 crowns. —That His Highness Syud Majid pay to His Highness Syud Thowaynee the arrears of subsidy for two years, or 80,000 crowns. I am satisfied that these terms are just and honourable to both of you: and as vou have deliberately and solemnly accepted my arbitration, I shall expect that you will cheerfully and faithfully abide by them and that they will be carried out without unnecessary delay. The annual payment of 40,000 crowns is not to be understood as a recog nition of the dependence of Zanzibar upon Muscat, neither is it to be considered as merely personal between Your Highness and your brother Syud Majid. It is to extend to your respective successors and is to be held to be a final and permanent arrangement, compensating the ruler of Muscat for the abandon ment of all claims upon Zanzibar, and adjusting the inequality between the two inheritances derived from your father. His late Highness Syud Saeed, the venerated friend of the British Government, which two inheritances are to le henceforward distinct and separate. I am. Your Highness's Sincere friend and well-wisher, (Sd.) CANNING. F oet 'W illiam; The 2nd April 1861. 43 F. and P. D,No. 2(&amp;). TO HIS EXALTED EXCELLENCY LOUD CANNING, GOVERNOR- GENERAL OE INDIA, ETC., ETC., ETC. In the name of the Great God I After compliments.— A.t a most propitious and favourable time we were honoured with the receipt of your esteemed letter and were highly gratified with its contents. What Your Excellency has stated is most satisfactory to us, more especially as regards your award betwixt us and our brother Majid. We heartily accept the same, and are at a loss how to express our regret for having occasioned you so much trouble, and our appreciation of the kindness which has been manifested towards us in this matter. We thank God for your efforts on our behalf, praying also that your good will may be rewarded and that you may never cease to be our support. We further pray that our sincere affection may always be towards the Great (British) Government, and that it may increase continually: moreover, that your exalted affection and noble solicitude may always be exercised towards us, and that we may never be deprived thereof. As regards our brother Majid, we pray God during our life time he may never experience anything from us but kindness and hearty good will. Eurtliermore, we rely implicitly on your arbitration between us (being carried out). What your exalted Excellency may require in any way from your attached friend, a hint alone will suffice for its accomplishment, and we shall feel honoured in executing it. We pray finally that you may be preserved to the highest honours and in the most perfect health. We send you the salutation of peace as the best con clusion. Erom your truly sincere friend, the servant of God, who confides in him as the Giver of all good. 4th of El-Kaada 1277 (= 15th May 1861). (Sd.) THOWAYNEE BIN SAEED BIN SULTAN.5 No. 3. ARTICLES OE AGREEMENT AGREED TO BEFORE LIEUTENANT- COLONEL LEWIS FELLY, HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S FOLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE FERSIAN GULE, AND LIEU TENANT-COLONEL HERBERT DI8BROWE, HER BRITAN NIC MAJESTY'S FOLITICAL AGENT AT BIRKA, MUSCAT, BY HIS HIGHNESS SYED THOWEYNEE BIN SAEED BIN SULTAN, THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT, UNDER DATE THIS 17 th DAY OF NOVEMBER 18&amp;L Article 1. My ancient and faithful ally, the British Government, is at liberty to con struct one or more lines of telegraphic communication anywhere within the territories appertaining to the State of Muscat. Article 2. The British Government is further at liberty to construct one or more lines of telegraphic communication in any territories which I may hold in lease from the Shah of Fersia. Article 3. I engage for myself, my heirs and successors, to respect and abstain from all and every interference with telegraphic operations carried on by the British Government in or near the territories of Muscat. Article 4 s. And in the event (which God forbid) of any of my subjects or dependants committing an act of aggression or trespass on the said telegraphic lines and stations or other telegraphic material, I will immediately punish the offender and proceed to afford full redress upon the same being brought to my notice. Article 5. Nothing in these articles shall be held as conferring any dominion or sovereign right on the part of the British Government over the territory of Muscat through which the line may pass, neither of any additional dominion or right on my part as Sultan of Muscat, over territory which I may hold in lease from the Shah of Fersia. Article 6. In like manner nothing in these articles shall be held as invalidating or derogating from the title of the British Government to the station of Bassadore that station having been freely granted to the British Government by my late illustrious father of blessed memory, the late Imaum Syed Saeed bin Sultan, on behalf of himself, his heirs and successors. Article 7. Nothing in these articles shall be held as invalidating any article of any Treaty entered into by myself or forefathers with our ancient and faithful ally, the British Government, from the year 1798 downwards. 48 F. and P. d. 7s Dated Birka, Muscat, 17tli November 1864. Signed in our presence by Syed Thoweynee bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat, this mil day of November 1864 and sealed in our presence by His Highness's Minister, Hajee Ahmed at Muscat, this 18th day of November 1864. (Sd.) LEWIS PELLY, Lieut.*Col., Her Britannic Majesty's Political Jtesident, Persian Gulf. HERBEET DISBROWE, Lieut.-Coly Her Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Muscat. Seal.7 Ko. 4. CONVENTION BETWEEN THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND HIS HIGHNESS SYXJD THOWAYNEE BIN SAEED BIN SULTAN, THE SULTAN OE MUSCAT, FOR THE EXTENSION OF THE ELECTRIC TELEGRAPH THROUGH THK DOMINIONS SUB JECT TO THE SOVEREIGNTY OF HIS HIGHNESS IN ARABIA AND MEKRAN, 1865. Article 1. That the British Government shall be at liberty to construct one or more telegraphic lines and to erect telegraph stations in any portion of territory sub ject to the sovereignty of His Highness, both in Arabia and Mekran, which shall be most convenient to them. Article 2. That the cost of materials, landing charges, labour, housing, provisions, etc., etc., shall be paid by the British Government, who will make any arrange ment they consider most convenient regarding their own supplies, labour, etc., the Sultan of Muscat undertaking that no impediment of any sort shall be thrown in their way in collecting them ; on the contrary, that every protection and assistance shall be given on his part. Article 3. That His Highness the Sultan of Muscat shall afford protection to the best of his ability to the lines of telegraph, the Telegraph Stations, and the persons employed in their construction and maintenance. Article 4. Should any disagreements arise in the possessions of the Sultan of Muscat, situated near Arabia, between the Telegraph Officials and the subjects of His Highness, the said disagreements shall be referred to the British Political Officer at Muscat, if they cannot be satisfactorily settled on the spot. Article 5. In like manner should any disagreements arise in the possessions of the Sultan of Muscat, situate in Mekran, between the Telegraph Officials and the subjects of His Highness, the said disagreements shall be referred to -the Assistant British Political Officer at Gwadur, if they cannot be satisfactorily settled on the spot. Article 6. This Convention, together with any supplementary Articles that may hereafter thereunto be added, is to be considered dependent for completion and effect upon the approval of the British Government. Done at Muscat this nineteenth day of January in the year of Christ one thousand eight hundred and sixty-five, corresponding with the twentieth day of the month Shaban of the Hegira one thousand two hundred and eighty-one, day of the week Thursday. (Sd.) HERBERT DISBROWE, Lieut-Col., Her Britannic Majesty's 'Political Agent ht Muscat, on the part of the British Govermient, 43 f. and p. i).No. 5 («). TREATY BETWEEN HER MAJESTY AND THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT FOE THE ABOLITION OF THE SLAVE TRADE, SIGNED AT MUSCAT, APRIL 14 th , 1873. Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and His Highness the Syud Toorkee bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat, being desirous to give more complete effect to the engagements entered into by the Sultan and his predecessors for the perpetual abolition of the Slave Trade, they have agreed to conclude a Treaty for this purpose which shall be bind ing upon themselves, their heirs and successors and Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland having appointed as her Plenipotentiary Sir Henry Bartle Edward Fr^re, Knight Commander of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath, and Knight Grand Commander of the Most Exalted Order of the Star of India, he having communicated to the Sultan of Muscat his full powers found in good and due form, and the afore said Sultan of Muscat, Syud Toorkee bin Saeed, acting on his own behalf, they have agreed upon and concluded the following articles :— Article 1. The import of slaves from the coasts or Islands of Africa or elsewhere into the dominions of Muscat, whether destined for transport from one port of Sultan of Muscat's dominions to another, or for conveyance to foreign ports, shall entirely cease, and any vessels engaged in the transport or conveyance of slaves after this date shall be liable to seizure and condemnation by all such Naval and other Officers, or Agents, and such Courts as may be authorised for that purpose on the part of Her Britannic Majesty and all persons hereafter enter ing the Sultan's dominions and dependencies shall be free. Article 2. The Sultan engages that all public markets in his dominions for slaves shall be entirely closed. Article 3. The Sultan engages to protect, to the utmost of his power, all liberated slaves, and to punish severely any attempt to molest them or reduce them again to slavery. Article 4. Her Britannic Majesty engages that natives of Indian States under British protection shall, from and after a date to be hereafter fixed, be prohibited from possessing slaves, and in the meanwhile from acquiring any fresh slaves. Article 5-. The present Treaty shall be ratified by Her Majesty and the ratification shall be forwarded to Muscat as soon as possible.*' In witness whereof. Sir Henry Bartle Edward Frere on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and Syud Toorkee bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat, on his own behalf, have signed the same and have affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat this fourteenth day of April, one thousand eight hundred and seventy three. (L. S.) (Sd.) H. B. E. FRERE. SYUD TOORKEE BIN SAEEIX 43 F-and p. d. * delivered to the Sultan iu September 1873. 10No. 5 (&amp;). PROCLAMATION.* To all whom it may concern let it be known that we have entirely forbidden all traffic in slaves either publicly or privately and that in the event of our finding any one engaged in the same in our dominions or dependencies he will forfeit his property as well as his personal safety. (Signed) TURKI BIN SAEED. Dated 19th Safar 1290 corresponding te 17th April 1873. True translated purport. (Sd.) S. B. MILES, Captain, Her Britannic Majesty's Acting Political Agent and Consult Muscat. 43 F, and P. D.10 No. 6. TREATY OE FRIENDSHIP, COMMEECE AND NAVIGATION BETWEEN GREAT BRITAIN AND MUSCAT, 1891. Signed at Muscat, March 19th, 1891. Ratifications were exchanged in 1892. Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, and His Highness the Seyyed Eeysal bin Turki bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, being desirous to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which now subsist between the two countries and to promote and extend their commercial relations, have named as their plenipot entiaries to conclude a Treaty for this purpose, that is to say :— Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Companion of the Star of India, Her Britannic Majesty's Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ; and His Highness the Sultan of Muscat in person; who had agreed upon and concluded the following Articles :— Article 1. The Treaty concluded between the British Government and Sultan Seyyed Saeed-bin-Sultan, Sultan of Muscat and Oman on the blst May, 1839 (17 Rabia 1st, 1255), is hereby cancelled and declared void, and the present Treaty, when ratified, shall be substituted for it. Article 2. Subjects of Her Britannic Majesty shall, for the purposes of this Treaty, include subjects of Native States in India in alliance with Her Majesty, Such subjects shall enjoy, immediately and unconditionally, throughout the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, with respect to commerce, shipping and the exercise of Trade, as in every other respect, all the rights, privileges, immunities, advantages, and protection of whatsoever nature, which are or hereafter may be, enjoyed by, or accorded most favoured nation. to the subjects or citizens of the They shall more especially not be liable to other or more onerous duties, imposts, restrictions or obligation of whatever description, than those to which subjecrs or citizens of the most favoured nation now are, or hereafter may bo subjected. Article s. The two High Contracting Parties acknowledge reciprocally to each other the right of appointing Consuls to reside in each other's dominions wherever the interests of commerce may require the presence of such officers ; and such Consuls shall at all times be placed in the country in which they reside on the footing of the Consuls of the most favoured nations. Each of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own subjects to be appointed to the Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party, provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the Sovereign whose subjects they may be. The public func tionaries of either Government residing in the dominions of the other, shall enjoy the same privileges, immunities, and exemptions which are enjoyed within the same dominions by similar public functionaries of other countries. Article 4. There shall be perfect freedom of commerce and navigation between the High Contracting Parties; each shall allow the subjects of the other to enter ail ports, creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes, also to travel, reside, 43 f. and P. P. u Lin, 11 nn, fl,'l.(Tiinni .IW n.nffirtffill.lWli...I■ —11 pursue commerce and trade, whether wholesale or retail, in each other's dominions and therein to hire, purchase and possess houses, warehouses, shops, stores and lands. British subjects shall everywhere he freely permitted, whether personally or by agent to bargain for, buy barter and sell all kind of goods, articles of import or native production, whether intended for sale within the dominions of His Highness or for export and to arrange with the owner or his agent regarding the price of all such goods and produce without inter ference of any sort on the part of the authority of His Highness. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat binds himself not to allow or recognise the establishment of any kind of monopoly or exclusive privilege of trade 'VYithin his dominions to any Government, Association or individual. Article 5. Subjects of Her Britannic Majesty shall be permitted throughout the dominions of His Highness the Sultan, to acquire by Gilt, purchase intestate succession or under will, or any other legal manner, land houses and property of every description, whether moveable or immoveable, to possess the same ; and freely to dispose thereof by sale, barter, donation, or otherwise. Article 6. His Highness the Sultan shall be permitted to levy a duty of entry not exceeding 5 per cent, on the value of all goods and merchandise, of whatever description, imported by sea from Foreign countries into His Highness's dominions. This duty shall be paid at the port in His Highness's dominions where the goods are first landed, and, on payment thereof, such goods shall thereafter be exempt, within the Sultan's dominions, from all other custom duties or taxes, levied by, or on behalf of, the Government ol His Highness the Sultan, by whatever names these may be designated, and no higher import duty shall be claimed from British subjects than that which is paid by subjects or citizens of the most favoured nation. This duty once paid shall cover from all other charges on the part of His Highness the Sultan, goods of whatever description coming from foreign countries by sea, whether these are intended for local consumption or tor transmission elsewhere in bulk or otherwise, and whether they remain in the state in which they are imported or have been manufactured. •There shall, however, be exempted from payment of all duty the following, namely:— (1) All goods and merchandise which, being destined for a foreign port, are transhipped from one vessel to another in any of the ports ol His Highness the Sultan of Muscat or which have been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Sultan's Custom houses to await the arrival of a vessel in which to be re-shipped abroad. But goods and merchandise so landed shall be exempted only, provided that the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the ship, handed over the said goods to be kept under Customs seal and declared them as landed for transhipment, designating at the same time the foreign port of destination and also provided that the said goods are actually shipped for the said foreign port as originally declared, within a period not exceeding six months after their first landing and without having, in the interval, changed owners. (2) All goods and merchandise which, not being consigned to a port within the dominions of the Sultan, have been inadvertently landed, provided that such goods are re-shipped within a month of being so landed and trans ported abroad. Should however, such goods or merchandise, here spoken of, be opened or removed frcm the custody of the Customs authorities, the lull duty shall then be payable cpi the same. (3) Coals, naval provisions, stores and fittings, the property of Her Majesty's Government, landed in the dominions of His Highness for the use of the ships of Her Majesty's Navy. (I) All goods and merchandise transhipped or landed for the repair of damage caused by stress of weather or other disasters at sea, provided the cargoso discharged shall be re-shipped and taken away on board of the same vessel, or if the latter shall have been condemned, or her departure delayed in any other manner. Article 7. No article whatever shall be prohibited from being imported into or exported from the territories of His Highness the Snltan of Muscat, and no other expert duties are to be levied on goods exported from those territories except with the consent of the Government of Her Britannic Majesty, such consent being subject to the conditions that may be laid down in the notifica tions intimating the same. Article 8. It is agreed and understood by the High Contracting Parties that, in the event of an arrangement being entered into hereafter between His Highness and the powers having Treaty relations with Muscat, and to which Great Britain shall be a consenting party, whereby vessels entering the port of Muscat shall be charged with shipping, tonnage or harbour dues, such dues to be administered under the control of a special Board for the improvement of the harbour and construction and maintenance of light houses, etc.; nothing in the aforementioned provisions shall be construed so as to exempt British vessels from payment of such shipping, harbour, or tonnage dues as may hereafter be agreed upon. Article 9. It shall be at the option of the British subject in each case to pay the percentage duties stipulated in Article 6, either in cash, or, if the nature of the goods allows of it, in kind, by giving up an equivalent amount of the goods or produce. In the event of payment being made in cash, the value of the merchan dise, goods or produce on which duty is to be levied, shall be fixed according to the ready money market price ruling at the time when the duty is levied. In the case of foreign imports, the value shall be fixed according to the market price at Muscat, and in that of native goods and produce by the market price at the place where the merchant shall choose to pay the duty. In the event of any dispute arising between a British subject and the Custom house authorities regarding the value of such goods, this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one, and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should, however, these experts not be able to agree, they shall choose an umpire, whose decision is to be considered final. Article 10. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat engages by the present Treaty to provide and give orders to his officials that the movement of goods in transit shall not be obstructed or delayed in a vexatious manner by unnecessary Customs formalities and Regulations, and that every facility will be given for their transport. Article 11. British vessels entering a port in the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, in distress, shall receive from the local authorities all necessary aid to enable them to re-victual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage. Should a British vessel be wrecked off the coast of His Highnesses dominions, the authorities of His Highness shall render all assistance in their power to the distressed vessel in order to save the ship, her cargo and those on board ; they shall also give aid and protection to persons saved, and shall assist them in reaching the nearest British Consulate; they shall further take every possible care that the goods so recovered are safely stored, and kept for the la13 purpose of being handed over to the owner, Captain, Agent of the ship, or British Consul, subject always to rights of salvage. His Highness's authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is at once informed of such disaster having occurred. Should a British vessel, wrecked on the coast of His Highness's dominion, be plundered, the authorities of His Highness shall, as soon as they come to know thereof, render prompt assistance and take measures to pursue and punish the robbers, and recover the stolen property. Likewise, should a vessel of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, or of one of his subjects, enter a British port in distress, or be wrecked off the coast of Her Majesty's dominions, the like help and assistance shall be rendered by the British authorities. Article 12. Should sailors or others belonging to a British ship of war, or merchant vessel, desert, and take refuge on shore or on board of any oi Ilis ilighness's ships, the authorities of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, shall upon request ol a Consular official, or, in his absence, of the Captain of the ship, take tuo neces sary stejis in order to have them arrested and delivered over to the Consular official or to the Captain. In this, however, the Consular officer and Captain shall render every assistance. Article 13. Subjects of Her Britannic Majesty shall, as regards their person and property, enjoy within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat the rights of ex-territoriality. The authorities of His Highness the Sultan have no right to interfere in disputes with subjects of Her Britannic Majesty amongst themselves, or between them and members of other Christian nations j such questions whether of a civil or criminal nature shall be decided by the competent Consular autho rities. The trial and also the punishment of all offences and crimes of which British subjects may be accused within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan, also the hearing and settlement of all civil questions, claims, or disputes in which they are the defendants, is expressly reserved to the British Consular authorities and Court®, and removed from the jurisdiction of His Highness the Sultan. Should disputes arise between subjects of His Highness the Sultan or other non-Christian Power, not represented by Consuls at Muscat, and a subject of Her Britannic Majesty, in which the British subject is the plaintiff or com plainant, the matter shall be brought before and decided by the highest autho rity of the Sultan, or some person specially delegated by him for this purpose. The proceedings and final decisions in such a case shall not, however, be consi dered legal unless notice has been given and an opportunity afforded for the British Consul or his substitute to attend at the hearing and final decision. Article 14. Subjects of His Highness the Sultan, or any non -Christian nation, not represented by Consuls at Muscat who are in the regular service of British subjects within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan ol Muscat, shall enjoy the same protection as British subjects themselves. Should they be charged with having committed a crime or serious offence punishable by law, they ?hall, on sufficient evidence being shown to justify further proceedings, be handed over by British employers, or by order ot the British Consul, to the authorities of His Highness the Sultan for trial and punishment. Article 15. Should a subject of Her Majesty residing in the dominions of His High ness the Sultan of Muscat be adjudicated bankrupt, the British Consul shall 1415 take possession of, recover and realise all available property and assets of sueli bankrupt to be dealt with and distributed according to the provisions of Eng lish Bankruptcy Law. Article 16. Should a subject of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat resist or evade payment of the just and rightful claims of a British subject, the authorities of His Highness the Sultan shall afford to the British creditor every aid and facility in recovering the amount due to him. In like manner the British Consul shall afford every aid and facility to subjects of His Highness the Saltan of Muscat in recovering debts justly due to them from a British subject. Article 17. Should a British subject die within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Museat, or dying elsewhere leave property therein, moveable or im moveable, the British Consul shall be authorised to collect, realise and take possession of the estate of the deceased, to be disposed of according to the pro visions of English law. Article 18. The houses, dwellings, warehouses, and other premises of British subjects, or of persons actually in their regular service, within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, shall not bo entered or searched under any pretext, by the ofiicials of His Highness without the consent of the occupier, unless with the cognisance and assistance of the British Consul or his substitute. Article 19. It is hereby agreed between the two High Contracting Parties that, in the event of an agreement being hereafter arrived at between His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and the various Powers with which His Highness shall be in Treaty relations, including Great Britain, which must be a consenting party, whereby the residents of district or town shall, without distinction of nationality, be made subject to the payment of local taxes, for municipal and sanitary pur poses, the same to be fixed and administered by or under the control of a special Board, nothing contained in this Treaty shall be understood so as to exempt British residents from the payment of such taxes. Article 20. Subjects of the two High Contracting Parties shall, within the dominions of each other, enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all such forms of religion, and the right to build edifices for religious worship. Article 21. The stipulations of the present Treaty shall be applicable to all the colonies- and foreign possessions of Her Britannic Majesty so far as the laws permit excepting to those hereinafter named, that is to say except to— The Dominion of Canada. Newfoundland, The Cape of Good Hope. Katal. New South Wales. Victoria. Queensland. Tasmania. South Australia. Western Australia. Kew Zealand.15 Provided always that the stipulations of the present Treaty shall be made appli cable to any of the abovenamed Colonies or foreign possessions, on whose behalf notice to that effect shall have been given by Her Britannic Majesty's Representative in Muscat to His H ighness the Sultan within two years from the date of exchange of ratifications of the present Treaty. Article 22. The present Treaty has been executed in quadruplicate two copies being- written in English and two in Arabic. These are understood to be of similar import and significations ; in the event, however, of doubt hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive. The Treaty shall come into operation within one month after the date when the ratifications may take place. Article 23. After the lapse of twelve years from the date on which the Treaty shall come into force, and on twelve months' notice given by either party, this Treaty shall be subject to revision by Plenipotentiaries appointed on both sides for this purpose, who shall be empowered to decide on and adopt such amendments as experience shall prove to be desirable. In witness whereof Colonel Edward Charles Ross, C.S.I., on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, and Empress of India, and His Highness Seyyed Feysal-bin-Turki, the Sultan of Muscat, on his own behalf, have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat, this 19th day of March 1891, corresponding to the 8tli Shaban of the year 1308 Hijreea, (Signed) EWAKD CHAELES EOSS, Col, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Signature in Arabic of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Note. The English, not the Arabic, text was signed by both parties, and must in consequence be regarded as authoritative. PEOTOCOL. The undersigned, in proceeding to the exchange of ratifications of the Treaty signed at Muscat on the 19th March 1891, between Her Majesty the Qneen of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, and His Highness Seyyid Feysal -bin-Turki, Sultan of Muscat, have agreed to the present Protocol, which shall have the same force and validity as if it had been inserted in the body of the Treaty itself. It is agreed that under article 23 of the said Treaty either of the High Contracting Parties shall be at liberty, after the expiration of twelve years from the date on which the Treaty has come into force, to terminate the said Treaty at any time on giving twelve months' notice. In witness whereof the undersigned, duly authorised, for the purpose have signed the present protocol, in quadruplicate, and have affixed thereto their seals. Done at Muscat, on the 29th day of February 1892. (Signed) A. 0. TALBOT, Lieut .-Col., Political Resident, Persian Gulf. (L. S.) Signature in Arabic of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat.10 No. 7- AGREEMENT REGARDING THE CESSION OF TERRITORY BY THE SULTAN OE OMAN, DATED 20Tn MARCH 1891. Praise be to God alone, The object of writing this lawful and honourable Bond is that it is hereby covenanted and agreed between His Highness Seyyed Feysal bin Turki bin Seyyed Sultan of Muscat and Oman, on the one part, and Colonel Edward Caaries Eoss, Companion of the Star of India, Her Britannic Majesty's Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf, on behalf of the British Government, on the other part that the said Seyved Fevsal bin Turki bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, does pledge and bind himself, his heirs and successors, never to cede, to sell, to mortgage or otherwise give for occupation, save to the British Govern ment, the dominions of Muscat and Oman or any of their dependencies. In token of the conclusion of this lawful and honourable bond Seyyed Fevsal bin Turki bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, and Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Companion of the Siar of India, Her Britannic Majesty's Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, the former for himself, his heirs and succes sors, and the latter on behalf of the British Government, do each, in the presence of witnesses affix their signatures on this ninth day of Shaaban one thousand three hundred and eight (A.H.), corresponding to the twentieth day of March (A.D.) 1891. E. C. ROSS, Colonel, Foil Heal Resident in the Persian Gulf. Signature of His Highness SEYYED FEYSAL BIN TURKI BIN SAEED, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. LANSDOWNE, Viceroy and Governor-General of India. Ratified by His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General of India, at Simla on the twenty-third day of May 1891. H. M. DURAND, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. 43 F. and P. D. 1717 Ko. 8 (a). TRANSLATION OF PROCLAMATION ISSUED BY THE SULTAN OF OMAN REGARDING THE SUPPRESSION OF THE ILLEGAL IMPORTATION OF ARMS INTO PERSIA AND BRITISH INDIA, 1898. Be it known to all who see it that we have given permission to British and Persian vessels of war to search vessels carrying their and our flags in our territorial waters, and to confiscate all arms and ammunition (weapons of war) in them, if those arms and ammunition are intended for Indian and Persian ports and if they are the property of British, Persian or Muscat subjects. We have also given permission to those vessels of war to search Muscat vessels in Indian and Persian waters suspected to contain arms and ammuni tion for Indian and Persian ports, and to confiscate the said arms and ammuni tion. (This is written) that it may he known. And salaams. TTritten the 19th day of Shahan 1315 A. H. (13th January 1898). No. 8 (ft). TRANSLATION OF NOTIFICATION. Be it known to such of our subjects as see this that, whereas the British and Persian Governments have represented to us that they are desirous of preventing introduction of arms and ammunition into India and Persia and that there is reason to think that many are exported from Muscat and taken to those two abovenamed countries, we have resolved to join them and to assist them as far as it lies in our power in suppressing this trade in arms and ammunition between Muscat and India and Persia. We therefore warn (our subjects) that all the arms and ammunition sent to those two countries will be confiscated and those engaged in this trade will be punished, as the introduc tion of arms and ammunition into India and Persia is prohibited by the Gov ernments of those two countries and therefore illegal. In future, our Muscat flag will be no protection to vessels carrying the said arms and ammunition from our dominions to India and Persia. ( r lhis is written ) that it may be known. And salaams. Dated the 19th of Shaban 1315 A.H. (13th January 1898). (Sd.) FEYSAL-BIN-TURKI. ; F and P. D. 18TRANSLATION OF AN UNDERTAKING GIVEN BY THE SULTAN OP OMAN ON THE 31ST MAY 1902 TO THE BRITISH POLI TICAL AGENT AT MUSCAT, REGARDING THE SUR COAL- FIELDS. In the name of God the High. From— Paisal bin Tueki , Sultan of Maskat, To— Major P. Z. Ccx, Political Agent, Maskat. After the usual compliments- —Regarding the communication you made to me on the subject of the Geologist's report and the views of Government on the subject of the coal deposits, Your Honour is at liberty to inform Government on my behalf, that for the present I have no intention of entering upon the work myself; and that in the future if any Government or Company ask my permission to embark upon the mining enterprise in question, I will cot accord such permission without first communicating with Government, in order that they may themselves take up the wcwk with me if they feel so inclined. This is what had to be written. May you be preserved. 43 F. and P. D. 1919 TRANSLATED PURPORT OF A NOTIFICATION ISSUED 13Y HIi HIGHNESS THE SULTAN ON 17TH OCTOBER 1903 REGARD ING THE IMPORTATION OF ARMS AND AMMUNITION INTO THE BRITISH AND ITALIAN PROTECTORATES IN AFRICA. To all whom it may concern. Be it known that in pursuance of an understanding come to by the Gov ernments of Great Britain and Italy, the importation of arms and warlike stores to those portions of the African Coast and Islands (including Socotra) lying to the North of Ras Aseer {i.e., Cape Guardafui), which are under the British Protectorate and also to those parts of the African Coast which arts under the Italian Protectorate, has been prohibited. Accordingly at the request of the British Government pursuant to her understanding with the Government of Italy I hereby notify the said prohibition. Be it therefore known that any native craft transporting arms or warlike stores to the localities in question will incur the risk of confiscation, and that I have granted authority to British men-of-war to search on my behalf vessels which there is reason to suspect in this connection in Muscat and Oman waters, and similarly to search Muscat craft on the high seas if reason exists for suspecting them. Furthermore I hereby grant authority to Italian ships of war also to search suspected Muscat vessels either in territorial waters or on the high seas. (Signed) FEISAL BIN TDRKI, Sultan of Muscat, Dated Muscat 24th Rajab 1321 (=17th October 1903). 43 F. and P. IX 20No. ll{n). NOTIFICATION BY HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OP MASKAT AND OMAN, DATED MASK AT, THE 4TH JUNE 1912. Whereas large quantities of arms and ammunition are at present stored without proper control in private buildings, distributed in this our town of Maskat, and thus exposed to the risk of attack, robbery or fire, we impressed by the strious menace to the safety of our capital arising therefrom, have resolved to remedy this state of affairs, in accordance with the needs of the times and the requirements of our municipal administration, by the con- struction and establishment of a special customs house magazine or arms ware house for the storage of arms and ammunition under safe precautions. It is proposed to introduce this warehouse arrangement from on or about 1st September next. It will be conducted on the following general lines :— Firstly. —On or after 1st September all arms and ammunition or parts thereof imported into my territories will be taken direct from the steamer to the special arms warehouse, to the control of which a special Superintendent will be appointed by us. Secondly.— Similarly all arms-dealers in my territories will be required to deposit stocks remaining in their hands on 1st September in the said warehouse. Any trader offending against this regulation will, in addition to other penalties, render all future consignments of arms and ammunition arriving in his name liable to confiscation, unless and until he complies with this regulation in full. Thirdly. —No arms will be allowed to issue from the warehouse until duty has been fully paid thereon to the Customs Superintendent in the usual way. Fourthly. —The withdrawal of arms from the warehouse will be regulated by the issue of special licenses prepared by the Superintendent and counter signed by myself. Fifthly. — S wq X i licenses will not be granted to traders but only to approved individual purchasers or their duly authorised agents on the production of satisfactory proof that the number, quantity and destination of arms, ammuni tion, etc., to be withdrawn from the warehouse are free from justifiable objection. Sixthly. —All arms issuing from the warehouse will be marked with a special warehouse mark and serial number. Seventhly. —Special rules will be drawn up providing for and regulating the issue to approved traders of sample stock for exhibition in their shops. Eighthly. —Rules providing for the collection of arms warehouse charges, on stocks therein deposited, will be drawn up on the analogy of the present Customs House Eegulations for the levy of such fees on general merchandise. Ninthly. —Special rules will be drawn up governing the transfer between traders' stocks deposited in the arms warehouse. Tenthly. —Special relaxations will be arranged for in favour of flint-locks r muzzle-loading gun powder and caps in reasonable quantities. Lastly. —Detailed rules embodying the above principles are under prepa ration and will be published in due course for the further information of ail concerned. SAIYID FAISAL'BIN-TUHKI. No. 11(6). NOTICE BY HIS HIGHNESS Sill SYUD EAISAL-BIN-TCJUKI, G.C.I.E., SULTAN OF MASKAT AND OMAN. The following draft rules for the establishment, maintenance and control of the Arms Warehouse are published for the information of all concerned. 43 P. and P. D. *il21 The said rules will be held to apply to all arms and ammunition or parts thereof held in our territories by traders for sale on the date of the introduction of the said rules, and to all such arms, ammunition or parts thereof as may be thereafter imported into our territories. On, or about, but not before, the 1st September 1912, a subsidiary notice will be issued in due course confirming these draft rules and notifying the date on which the rules so confirmed shall come into operation. Draft Rules. Hide 1. —All arms, ammunition or parts thereof held by traders for sale to the public within my dominions shall be deposited forthwith in the Arms Warehouse in accordance with these regulations. The AVarehouse Superinten dent will grant a detailed receipt to the depositor for all such arms, ammuniti- tion or parts thereof in the form attached and marked A. Utile 2. —After the expiry of one month from the date on which these rules come into operation, all arms, ammunition or parts thereof, found in the possession of traders (except in accordance with the provisions of rule 15 hereinafter mentioned), contrary to the provisions of rule 1 aforesaid, shall be confiscated. If the offending trader be a Maskat subject, he will be severely punished ; if a foreigner and amenable to my jurisdiction, he will be liable to expulsion from my territories. If the offending trader be a subject of any of the Powers in treaty relations with me, information will be laid against him to the Consul of the Power, whose subject or protege he may be, and the aforesaid Consul will be requested to deal with him according to law and treaty and the spirit of these regulations. Bule 3. —In addition to all or any of the penalties imposed by these rules, should any trader be found guilty in the proper forum of offending against the provisions of rule 1 aforesaid, all arms, ammunition or parts thereof, held in the Maskat Arms Warehouse to the credit of such offending trader, or that may subsequently be deposited in the Arms Warehouse in his name under the provisions of rule 4, will, without further sentence of forfeiture, be liable to confiscation. Bide 4.-^-All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, which may hereafter be imported into Maskat territory, will be taken direct to the Arms Warehouse and there deposited. Rule 5. —For the more effective carrying out of the provisions of the preceding rule, the masters of steamers importing arms and ammunition or parts thereof will be required to produce on arrival and furnish to the represent ative of the Warehouse Superintendent who will attend on board, the copy of a separate manifest, and in the form attached and marked 13, showing all arms and ammunition and parts thereof, destined for importation into my territories and carried on board their vessels. Rule 6. —All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, destined for import into Maskat, but not detailed, or incorrectly or insufiiciently described, in the separate manifest (form B) especially with regard to the marks on the packages or the name of the consignee, shall, as soon as such arms, ammunition or parts thereof have left the ship's tackles become liable to conBscation. Exception. —The sole exception to the operation of this rule shall be in the case of arms, ammunition or parts thereof, landed by mistake in good faith and clearly destined for some other port, to which the import of arms and ammunition is not prohibited. The burden of proving that such arms and ammunition were intended for import to a port, to which the import of arms and ammunition is not prohibited, shall lie on the steamer's agent, importer or consignee. No claims under this exception will be entertained after a period of three months from date of landing of the goods, in respect of which the claim is made. Rule 7. —All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, deposited in the Arms Warehouse in accordance with the provisions of rule 4, shall be claimed by the consignee within a period of three months from the date of deposit in the Anns Warehouse.22 On such claim bein^ made, the 'Warehouse Superintendent will, subject to the provisions of rules 8 and 8 {a) immediately following and after due veri fication of the Bill of Lading and steamer s agent s delivery order, grant a detailed receipt in form A above-mentioned. 7?..; c $ —As soon as, in accordance with the provisions of rule 4 aforesaid, arms and ammunition or parts thereof are brought to the Arms Warehouse to be there deposited, the Superintendent, Arms Warehouse, shall notify the Superintendent of Customs of the arrival of such arms, ammunition or parts thereof by form attached and marked C Arabic ( ^ )in order that duty may be collected thereon by the Superintendent of Customs. hula 8(a) -As soon as such duty has been paid, the Superintendent of Customs shall immediately return to the Superintendent Arms Warehouse the form marked C duly endorsed with a certificate that tlie duty has bccu fullv paid on the arms, ammunition and parts thereof noted in the lorm aforesaid, and the Superintendent, Arms Warehouse, shall m no case grant the detailed receipt in form A unless and until he shall have received hack the form marked (J duly endorsed as already described by the Superintendent of Customs. . . &lt;. .&lt;1 jtule q Failure by consignee to comply with the provisions or either of the three preceding rules shall render the arms, ammunition or parts thereof liable to confiscation. Issue of arms, ammunition or parts thereof from the Arms JFarehouse. Rule 10. Anv person proposing to purchase arms, ammunition or parts thereof from any'trader, owning arms, ammunition or parts thereof stored m the Arms Warehouse in accordance with the provisions of rules 1 and .J. above, and duly claimed under the provisions of rnle 7, and on which duty and warehouse charges have been fully paid in accordance withthe provisions of rules 8 and 16, respectively, will be permitted to withdraw arms and ammunition or parts thereof on the production of, and to the extent covered by, a license in form marked D and attached. On the application of the trader concerned, who must be present at such withdrawal, the Warehouse Superintendent shall draw up the license aforesaid and submit it for my approval and signature. Rule 11 —It shall be the duty of the Warehouse Superintendent to refusa to draw up any such license, should he have reason to suppose- (a) that the purchaser whose name it is proposed to enter in form B as ' bearer' intends to resell the arms, ammunition or parts thereof to any other person ; (h) that such purchaser is already, whether by license in form D pre- viouslv issued or otherwise, in possession of arms, ammunition or parts thereof, whence it may be inferred that the arms, ammu nition or parts thereof, covered by the license under question, are not required solely for the personal use or protection of the purchaser. Rule 12.—U shall further be the duty of the Warehouse Superintendent to ensure that— (а) all rifles issuing from the Arms arehouse under the terms of any license issued in accordance with the provisions of these rules, shall be clearly marked on the barrel before withdrawal with the official mark and on the butt with the serial number of issue; (б) no more tban 200 rounds per rifle per annum shall be issued from the Arms Warehouse to any holder of a license under form U ; M in the event of a license under form D being issued for ammunition onlv which must not in any case exceed 200 rounds per annum pe/ purchaser, the purchaser produces, for the inspection o{ the Warehouse Superintendent, the weapon in respect of which the ammunition is required. 2323 21 Bulel3—0n the production of the weapons as directed in accordance with the provisions of liule 12 (&lt;?), the Warehouse Superintendent shall pro ceed to satisfy himself that the weapon is duly marked on the barrel with the official mark of the Arms Warehouse and on the butt with the serial number of issue. If it is found not to be so marked, the Superintendent sliall, atter marking the weapon with the marks and number of the Arms Warehouse, refer the question of the legality of possession of the weapon to me for orders. The burden of proving that the weapon was innocently come by and not in infringement of the^ rules of the Arms Warehouse, will lie on the owner and should he fail to prove innocent possession, the weapon shall be liable to con fiscation. Bule 14. —(Xot in force.) Rule 15. —To meet the needs of traders who may desire to expose in their shops a sample of arms and ammunition for sale, a trader's license in form L Arabic form (*&gt;*&gt;) can be procured by them from the arehouse Superin tendent. A trader holding such a license will be permitted to withdraw trom the Arms Warehouse one sample weapon of every kind of which he may have stock Wins in the Arms Warehouse under the provision ot Rules 1 and 1, 7 and 8 aforesaid together with 200 rounds of ammunition per sample _ weapon. This stock of ammunition may be renewed under the trader s license t\\ ice a } ear on the personal guarantee of the trader that it is not for sale but merely practice 5 * ammunition. Rule The Warehouse Superintendent shall have power to frame rules for the charge and collection ol; Warehouse charges not exceeding 2 per cent per mensem arf on all arms and ammunition or parts thereot stored in the Arms Warehouse and for the discharge of such obligations, when over one month in arrears, by the appropriation to the State of an equrvalent portion of the offending goods. Ride 17. —The Warehouse Superintendent shall frame rules to be approved bv me regulating the transfer between traders of arms, ammunition or parts thereof stored in the Arms Warehouse except (1) that no such transfer shall be valid without the consent of the traders concerned ; (2) that it shall be reduced to writing and subject to the certificate of the Warehoue Superin tendent to be confirmed by me that all charges leviable under these rules have been fully paid; (3) that it shall be duly registered by the arehouse Superintendent; and (4) that the fees to be charged for the registration of any such transfer shall not exceed BIO for each such transfer.F orm A. MASKAT ARMS WAREHOUSE. (To be retained by the depositor.) Serial No. (1) Name of steamer in which imported and date of importation. (2) Number of rifles. (3) Description of rifles. &lt;+) Quantity of ammunition. (5) Dated 191 Description of ammuni- Remauks. tion. (6) (7) Warehouse Superintendent.Form B. MASKAT ARMS WAREHOUSE. Port of Return of Arms and Ammunition destined for Maskat shipped per S.S. ' ' cleared for the Versian Gulf 191 . D esceiption op contektb op cases. Number and description of Quantities. Small Arms. Make or action. Bore. Single or magazine. Cartridges, Nature of arms for which intended. Ball or shot. Other munition. Invoice value. Name and address of makers. Name and address of ship pers or exporters. Name and address of shipping agent. Name and address of consignees. E emaekb. o Captain S.S,Marks and Nos. The Superintendent, Maskat Customs Department. The arms, noted below, hare been received this day ex S.S. ' ' and have been duly deposited in the Arms Warehouse. Number and description of packages. Quantities. Description of contents of cases. Invoice value. Name and address of consignee. R emarks. As soon as duty shall have been fully paid on the above, kindly return this form with the certificate below duly signed. (Signed) Dated. .191 . Arms Warehouse Superintendent, The Superintendent, Arms Warehouse. I hereby certify that the import duty DMed. .191 . leviable on the arms, noted in the above form, has been fully paid, (Signed) Superintendent, Maskat Customs.27 28 F orm D. LICENSE TO WITHDRAW ARMS, AMMUNITION OR PARTS THEREOF FROM THE ARMS WAREHOUSE, MASKAT. Please permit the bearer ' son of nationality , to take from my stock in the Arms Warehouse the following:— Dated Recommended. (Signed) Arms Tradert Maskat. Dated . Warehouse Superintendent. Approved. (Signed) [ 1 Sultan of Maskat and Oman. Seal of His Highness the Sultan. Verified, and issued. (Signed) No. . Warehouse Superintendent, Mask at. Dated N.B. —This document should be made out in duplicate, the original will be held by the purchaser of the goods and carefully preserved as a license to explain his possession, while the duplicate will be retained by the Warehouse Superintendent as a voucher.29 MASKAT ARMS WAREHOUSE. Traders* license to keep sample arms and ammunition on his htisiness premises. Please permit the bearer son of URS nationality &gt; to take from my stock in the Arms Warehouse the following sample arms and ammunition ;— I guarantee that the above arms and ammunition taken as^ samples will not be sold to any purehaser without special permission in writing from His Highness the Sultan and that the ammunition will only be utilised in practice and testing weapons. Recommended. Dated (Signed) Arms Trader, Maskat. Warehouse Superintendent. Approved. Seal of His Highness the Sultan. (Signed) Verified and issued. No. Bated Sultan of Mashat and Oman. Dated (Signed) Warehouse Superintendent, JV.JB. —This form should be made out in duplicate, one copy will be retained by the Warehouse Superintendent as a voucher while the original will be retained by the trader and should be carefully preserved by him in order that it may be produced, should the reason for the possession of his sample arms be challenged.29 30 No. 11(c). NOTICE. From Faisal bin Tueki, To All who may see it: that the Notice dated together with the rules annexed to it, from rule first to rule twelfth, on the subject of the arms trade, and in the matter of the regulation and establishment of the Arms Warehouse, will come into force (practice) from this date, that is, the ^t^ptemb^r 80 that it be not hidden. And about the two remaining notices and the rest of the rules another notice will follow: so that it be not hidden. -nn+rw/J 18th Ramazan 1330 ■ Uaiea 1st September 1912' Signature of His Highness the Sultan. No. ll{d). PROCLAMATION BY HIS HIGHNESS SAIYID FAISAL-BIN-TURKI, DATED THE 23ED EAMZAN 1330 HIJEA (EQUIVALENT TO 6TH SEPTEMBER 1912). To all who see this the sale of arms or ammunition or component parts thereof, intended for sale to the public, or their removal from place to place in my dominions is prohibited from this date except through the special Arms Warehouse which we have constituted in Maskat, and every person of our subjects or our pret&amp;^s or our dependents who assists in the sale or removal mentioned above will be severely punished, that it may not be hidden and peace. \ No. 11(e). NOTICE. From Faisal bin Turki. To All who may see this : in view of our promise {vide our notice dated that a further notice would be forthcoming, now this is the notice promised therein. We have determined to act upon four rules, viz,:— XIII, XV, XVI, XVII. Strict action upon them should continue with effect from the 1st September 1912. So that it may not be hidden. T»o + rwrl 24th Shawwal 1830 jjaiea 6th 0ctober 1912 . Signature of Bis Highness the Sultan,30 tfo. 12, NOTE. We, the undersigned, have agreed to what follows : that the Treaty of Friend ship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Oman, signed on the 8th day of Shaban 1308 H., corresponding to the 19th March 1891, will be prolonged by this writing, notwithstanding all, or any, correspondence between his late Highness Syud Faisal bin Turki and the Glorious British Government in the matter of the revision of that Treaty. And it will remain in force for a period of five years from this eleventh day of February 1914, corresponding to the 15th Rabi al Awwal 1332 H., unless a suitable Treaty by agreement between His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman and the Glorious British Govern ment be substituted for that ancient treaty aforesaid. In confirmation thereof we, that is, I, Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Maska^ and Oman, with my own hand, and I, Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., duly author ised agent for that purpose on behalf of the Glorious British Government, have signed this writing and four copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Masqat this eleventh day of February 1914, corresponding to the 15th Rabi al Awwal 1332 H. Seal of Sultan of Masqat and Oman. (Sd.) TAIMUR BIN FAISAL, {in Vernacular), Seal of Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. (Sd.) S. G. KNOX, Major, Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul. 43 F, aud P, V. 31india office records 'CROFILMTREATIES AND UNDERTAKINGS IN S-ORCE BETWEEN THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND THE SULTANS OF MASKAT AND OMAN 1845-1914. ft /I nTreaties and Undertakings in force between the British Government and the Sultans of Maskat and Oman, 1845—1914. Xote .—In the event of doubt hereafter arising as to the precise interpretation of any portion of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive.] AGREEMENT BETWEEN HER MAJESTY THE QUEEN OF THE U .N IT ED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND IRELAND AND HIS HIGHNESS SYUD SAEED BIN SULTAN, 'THE SULTAN OF MUSKAT,' FOR THE TERMINATION OF THE EXPORT OF SLAVES FROM THE AFRICAN DOMINIONS OF HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MUSKAT—1845. Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland being earnestly desirous that the export of slaves from the African Dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muskat should cease, and His High ness the Sultan of Muskat in deference to the wishes of Her Majesty and of the British nation, and in furtherence of the dictates of humanity which have heretofore induced him to enter into engagement with Great Britain to restrict the export of slaves from his dominions, being willing to put an end to that trade and Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and His Highness the Sultan of Muskat having resolved to record with due form and solemnity this further restriction of the export of slaves, and Her Majesty having given due authority to Captain Hamerton, Her Representative at the Court of the Sultan of Muskat, to conclude an agreement with His Highness, accordingly His Highness Syud Saeed bin Sultan, for himself, his heirs and successors, and Captain Hamerton on behalf of the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, her heirs and successors have agreed upon and concluded the following Articles :— Article 1. His Highness the Sultan of Muskat here engages to prohibit, under the severest penalties, the export of slaves from his African Dominions and to issue orders to his officers to prevent and suppress such trade. Article 2. His Highness the Sultan of Muskat further engages to prohibit, under the severest penalties, the importation of slaves from any part of Africa into his possessions in Asia, and to use his utmost influence with all the Chiefs of Arabia, the Red Sea, and the Persian Gulf, in like manner, to prevent the introduction of slaves from Africa into their respective territories. Article 3. His Highness the Sultan of Muskat grants to the ships of Her Majesty's Navy as well as to those of the East India Company, permission to seize and confiscate any vessels, the property of His Highness or of his subjects, carrying 43 F. and P. D. ^on slave trade, excepting only such as are engaged in the transport of slaves from one port to another of his own dominions in Africa between the port of Lamoo to the north and its dependencies, the northern limit of which is the north point of Kuyhoor Island in 1° 57' (one degree and fifty-seven minutes) South Latitude and the port of Kulwa to the south and its dependencies, the southern limit of which is the Songa Manora or Pagoda Point in 9° 2' (nine degrees and two minutes) South Latitude, including the Islands of Zanzibar, Pemba and Monfea. Article 4. This agreement to commence and have effect from the 1st (first) day of January 1847 (one thousand eight hundred and forty-seven) of the year of Christ and the 15th day of the month of Mahaneerun 1263 (twelve hundred and sixty-three) of the Hegira. Done at Zanzibar this 2nd (second) day of October 1845 (one thousand and eight hundred and forty-five) of the year of Christ and 29th day of Eamzan 1261 (twelve hundred and sixty-one) of the Hegira. (Sd.) ATKINS HAMEETON, Captain. On behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, her heirs and successors.No. 2 (a). LETTEE TO HIS HIGHNESS THE SAIYID THUWAINI BIN SAID BIN SULTAN OE MASQAT EKOM HIS EXCELLENCY THE VICEROY AND GOVERNOR-GENERAL OE INDIA, DATED 2ND APRIL 1861. Beloved and esteemed Friend ! I address Your Highness on the subject of the unhappy differences which have arisen between yourself and Your Highness's brother, the ruler of Zanzibar, and for the settlement of which Your Highness has engaged to accept the arbi tration of the Viceroy and Governor-General of India. Having regard to the friendly relations which have always existed between the Government of Her Majesty the Queen and the Government of Oman and Zanzibar and desiring to prevent war between kinsmen, I accepted the charge of arbitration between you and in order to obtain the fullest knowledge of all the points in dispute 1 directed the Government of Bombay to send an officer to Muscat and Zanzibar to make the necessary enquiries. Brigadier Coghlan was selected for this purpose, an officer in whose judgment, intelligence and impartiality the Government of India reposes the utmost confidence. Brigadier Coghlan has submitted a full and clear report of all the questions at issue between Your Highness and your brother. I have given my most careful attention to each of these questions. The terms of my decision are as follows:— —That His Highness Syud Majid be declared ruler of Zanzibar and the African dominions of His late Highness Syud Saeed. 2 n( l t —That the ruler of Zanzibar pay annually to the ruler of Muscat a subsidy of 40,000 crowns. Srd.—That His Highness Syud Majid pay to His Highness Syud Thowaynee the arrears of subsidy for two years, or 80,000 crowns. I am satisfied that these terms are just and honourable to both of you : and as you have deliberately and solemnly accepted my arbitration, I shall expect that you will cheerfully and faithfully abide by them and that they will be carried out without unnecessary delay. The annual payment of 40,000 crowns is not to be understood as a recog nition of the dependence of Zanzibar upon Muscat, neither is it to be considered as merely personal between Your Highness and your brother Syud Majid. It is to extend to your respective successors and is to be held to be a final and T)crmanent arrangement, compensating the ruler of Muscat for the abandon ment of all claims upon Zanzibar, and adjusting the inequality between the two inheritances derived from your father. His late Highness Syud Saeed, the venerated friend of the British Government, which two inheritances are to le henceforward distinct and separate. I am. Your Highness's Sincere friend and well-wisher, (Sd.) CANNING. Fort William j The 2nd April 1861. 43 F. and P. D.No. 2(&amp;&gt;. TO HIS EXALTED EXCELLENCY LORD CANNING, GOVERNOR- GENERAL OE INDIA, ETC., ETC., ETC. ix the name of the great god ! After compliments. —At a most propitious and favourable time we were honoured with the receipt of your esteemed letter and were highly gratified with its contents. What Your Excellency has stated is most satisfactory to as, more especially as regards your award betwixt us and our brother Majid. We heartily accept the same, and are at a loss how to express our regret for having occasioned you so much trouble, and our appreciation of the kindness which has been manifested towards us in this matter. We thank God for your efforts on our behalf, praying also that your good will may be rewarded and that you may never cease to be our support. We further pray that our sincere affection may always be towards the Great (British) Government, and that it may increase continually : moreover, that your exalted affection and noble solicitude may always be exercised towards us, and that we may never be deprived thereof. As regards our brother Majid, we pray God during our life time he may never experience anything from us but kindness and hearty good will. Eurtherinore, we rely implicitly on your arbitration between us (being carried out). What your exalted Excellency may require in any way from your attached friend, a hint alone will suffice for its accomplishment, and we shall feel honoured in executing it. We pray finally that you may be preserved to the highest honours and in the most perfect health. We send you the salutation of peace as the best con clusion. Erom your truly sincere friend, the servant of God, who confides in him as the Giver of all good. 4th of El-Kaada 1277 (= 15th May 1861). (Sd.) THOWAYNEE BIN SAEED BIN SULTAN. l. s.No. 3. ARTICLES OE AGREEMENT AGREED TO BEFORE LIEUTENANT- COLONEL LEWIS FELLY, HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S FOLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE FERSIAN GULE, AND LIEU TENANT-COLONEL HERBERT DISBROWE, HER BRITAN NIC MAJESTY'S FOLITICAL AGENT AT BIRKA, MUSCAT, BY HIS HIGHNESS SYED THOWEYNEE BIN SAEED BIN SULTAN, THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT, UNDER DATE THIS 17 th DAY OE NOVEMBER 1864. My ancient and faithful ally, the British Government, is at liberty to con struct one or more lines of telegraphic communication anywhere within the territories appertaining to the State of Muscat. A rticle 2. The British Government is further at liberty to construct one or more lines of telegraphic communication in any territories which I may hold in lease from the Shah of Fersia. A rticle 3. I engage for myself, my heirs and successors, to respect and abstain from all and every interference with telegraphic operations carried on by the British Government in or near the territories of Muscat. A rticle 4. And in the event (which God forbid) of any of my subjects or dependants committing an act of aggression or trespass on the said telegraphic lines and stations or other telegraphic material, I will immediately punish the offender and proceed to afford full redress upon the same being brought to my notice. A rticle 5. Nothing in these articles shall be held as conferring any dominion or sovereign right on the part of the British Government over the territory of Muscat through which the line may pass, neither of any additional dominion or right on my part as Sultan of Muscat, over territory which I may hold in lease from the Shah of Fersia. A rticle 6. In like manner nothing in these articles shall be held as invalidating or derogating from the title of the British Government to the station of Bassadore that station having been freely granted to the British Government by my late illustrious father of blessed memory, the late Imaum Syed Saeed bin Sultan, on behalf of himself, his heirs and successors. A rticle 7. Nothing in those articles shall be held as invalidating any article of any Treaty entered into by myself or forefathers with our ancient and faithful ally, the British Government, from the year 1798 downwards. 43 F. and P. d, 7Dated Birka, Muscat, 17tli November 1864. Signed in our presence by Syed Thoweynee bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat, this l7tli day of November 1864 and sealed in our presence by His Ili^hness's Minister, Ilajee Ahmed at Muscat, this 18th day of November 1864. (Sd.) LEWIS PELLY, Lieut.-Col., Ller Britannic Majesty's Political Resident, Persian Gulf. HERBERT DISBBOWE, Lieut.-Col, Hex Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Muscat*J&amp;5 © No. 4. CONVENTION BETWEEN THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND HIS HIGHNESS SYUD THOWAYNEE BIN SAEED BIN SULTAN, THE SULTAN OE MUSCAT, EOR THE EXTENSION OE THE ELECTRIC TELEGRAPH THROUGH THK DOMINIONS SUB JECT TO THE SOVEREIGNTY OE HIS HIGHNESS IN ARABIA AND MEKRAN, 1865. Article 1. That tlie British Government shall be at liberty to construct one or more telegraphic lines and to erect telegraph stations in any portion of territory sub ject to the sovereignty of His Highness, both in Arabia and Mekran, which shall be most convenient to them. Article 2. That the cost of materials, landing charges, labour, housing, provisions, etc., etc., shall be paid by the British Government, who will make any arrange ment they consider most convenient regarding their own supplies, labour, etc., the Sultan of Muscat undertaking that no impediment of any sort shall be thrown in their way in collecting them ; on the contrary, that every protection and assistance shall be given on his part. Article 3. That His Highness the Sultan of Muscat shall afford protection to the best of his ability to the lines of telegraph, the Telegraph Stations, and the persons employed in their construction and maintenance. Article 4. Should any disagreements arise in the possessions of the Sultan of Muscat, situated near Arabia, between the Telegraph Officials and the subjects of His Highness, the said disagreements shall be referred to the British Political Officer at Muscat, if they cannot be satisfactorily settled on the spot. Article 5. In like manner should any disagreements arise in the possessions of the Sultan of Muscat, situate in Mekran, between the Telegraph Officials and the Bubjects of His Highness, the said disagreements shall be referred to the Assistant British Political Officer at Gwadur, if they cannot be satisfactorily settled on the spot. Article 6. This Convention, together with any supplementary Articles that may hereafter thereunto be added, is to be considered dependent for completion and effect upon the approval of the British Government. Done at Muscat this nineteenth day of January in the year of Christ one thousand eight hundred and sixty-five, corresponding with the twentieth day of the month Shaban of the Hcgira one thousand two hundred and eighty-one, (lay of the week Thursday. (Sd.) HERBERT DISBROWE, Lieut.-Col., Her Britannic Majesty's Political Agent at Muscat, on the part of the British Government. 48 F. &lt;md ?. I&gt;.No. 5 (a). TREATY BETWEEN HER MAJESTY AND THE SULTAN OF MUSCAT FOE -THE ABOLITION OE THE SLAVE TRADE, SIGNED AT MUSCAT, APRIL 14 th , 1873. Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and His Highness the Synd Toorkee bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat, being desirous to give more complete effect to the engagements entered into by the Sultan and his predecessors for the perpetual abolition of the Slave Trade, they have agreed to conclude a Treaty for this purpose which shall be bind ing upon themselves, their heirs and successors and Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland having appointed as her Plenipotentiary Sir Henry Bartle Edward Erere, Knight Commander of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath, and Knight Grand Commander of the Most Exalted Order of the Star of India, he having communicated to the- Sultan of Muscat his full powers found in good and due form, and the afore said Sultan of Muscat, Syud Toorkee bin Saeed, acting on his own behalf, they have agreed upon and concluded the following articles :— Article 1. The import of slaves from the coasts or Islands of Africa or elsewhere into the dominions of Muscat, whether destined for transport from one port of Sultan of Muscat's dominions to another, or for conveyance to foreign ports, shall entirely cease, and any vessels engaged in the transport or conveyance of slaves after this date shall be liable to seizure and condemnation by all such Naval and other Officers, or Agents, and such Courts as may be authorised for that purpose on the part of Her Britannic Majesty and all persons hereafter enter ing the Sultan's dominions and dependencies shall be free. Article 2. The Sultan engages that all public markets in his dominions for slaves shall be entirely closed. Article 3. The Sultan engages to protect, to the utmost of his power, all liberated slaves, and to punish severely any attempt to molest them or reduce them again to slavery. Article 4. Her Britannic Majesty engages that natives of Indian States under British protection shall, from and after a date to be hereafter fixed, be prohibited from possessing slaves, and in the meanwhile from acquiring any fresh slaves. Article 5. The present Treaty shall be ratified by Her Majesty and the ratification shall be forwarded to Muscat as soon as possible.* In witness whereof. Sir Henry Bartle Edward Erere on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and Syud Toorkee bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat, on his own behalf, have signed the same and have affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat this fourteenth day of April, one thousand eight hundred and seventy three. (L. S.) (Sd.) H. B. E. ERERE. SYUD TOORKEE BIN SAEEDv 43 F.and p. d. * DtHvereJ to the Sultan in September 1873. 10No. 5 (&amp;). PROCLAMATION.* To all whom it may concern let it be known that we have entirely forbidden all traffic in slaves either publicly or privately and that in the event of our finding any one engaged in the same in our dominions or dependencies he will forfeit his property as well as his personal safety. (Signed) TURKI BIN SAEED. Dated 19th Safar 1290 corresponding te 17th April 1873. True translated purport. (Sd.) S. B. MILES, Captain, Her Britannic Majesty's Acting Political Agent and Consul, Muscat, 43 F. and P. D.TREATY OF FRIENDSHIP, COMMEECE AND NAVIGATION BETWEEN GREAT BRITAIN AND MUSCAT, 1891. Signed at Muscat, March 19th, 1891. Ratifications were exchanged in 1892. Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, and His Highness the Seyyed Eeysal bin Turki bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, being desirous to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which now suljsist between the two countries and to promote and extend their commercial relations, have named as their plenipot entiaries to conclude a Treaty for this purpose, that is to say :— Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Companion of the Star of India, Her Britannic Majesty's Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ; and His Highness the Sultan of Muscat in person; who had agreed upon and concluded the following Articles :— Article 1. The Treaty concluded between the British Government and Sultan Seyyed Saeed-bin-Sultan, Sultan of Muscat and Oman on the 31st May, 1839 (17 Rabia 1st, 1255), is hereby cancelled and declared void, and the present Treaty, when ratified, shall be substituted for it. Article 2. Subjects of Her Britannic Majesty shall, for the purposes of this Treaty, include subjects of Native States in India in alliance with Her Majesty, Such sub jects shall enjoy, immediately and unconditionally, throughout the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, with respect to commerce, shipping and the exercise of Trade, as in every other respect, all the rights, privileges, immunities, advantages, and protection of whatsoever nature, which are or hereafter may be, enjoyed by, or accorded to the subjects or citizens of the most favoured nation. They shall more especially not be liable to other or more onerous duties, imposts, restrictions or obligation of whatever description, than those to which subjecis or citizens of the most favoured nation now are, or hereafter may bo subjected. Article 3. The two High Contracting Parties acknowledge reciprocally to each other the right of appointing Consuls to reside in each other's dominions wherever the interests of commerce may requirq the presence of such officers ; and such Consuls shall at all times be placed in the country in which they reside on the footing of the Consuls of the most favoured nations. Each of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own subjects to be appointed to the Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party, provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the Sovereign whose subjects they may be. The public func tionaries of either Government residing in the dominions of the other, shall enjoy the same privileges, immunities, and exemptions which are enjoyed within the same dominions by similar public functionaries of other countries. Article 4. There shall be perfect freedom of commerce and navigation between tho High Contracting Parties; each shall allow the subjects of the other to enter all ports, creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes, also to travel, reside, 43 f. and P. D.itf 11 pursue commerce and trade, whether wholesale or retail, in each other's dominions and therein to hire, purchase and possess houses, warehouses, shops, stores and lands. British subjects shall everywhere he freely permitted, whether personally or by agent to bargain for, buy barter and sell all kind of goods, articles of import or native production, whether intended for sale within the dominions of His Highness or for export and to arrange with the owner or his agent regarding the price of all such goods and produce without inter ference of any sort on the part of the authority of His Highness. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat binds himself not to allow or recognise the establishment of any kind of monopoly or exclusive privilege of trade within his dominions to any Government, Association or individual. % Article 5. Subjects of Her Britannic Majesty shall be permitted throughout the dominions of His Highness the Sultan, to acquire by Gift, purchase intestate succession or under will, or any other legal manner, land houses and property of every description, whether moveable or immoveable, to possess the same ; and freely to dispose thereof by sale, barter, donation, or otherwise. Article 6. His Highness the Sultan shall be permitted to levy a duty of entry net exceeding 5 per cent, on the value of all goods and merchandise, of whatever j : i— — c - p —:— countries into His Foreign Highness 's descrijDtion, imported by sea from dominions. This duty shall be paid at the port in His Highness's dominions where the goods are first landed, and, on payment thereof, such goods shall thereafter be exempt, within the Sultan's dominions, from all other custom duties or taxes, levied by, or on behalf of, the Government of His Highness the Sultan, by whatever names these may be designated, and no higher import duty shall be claimed from British subjects than that which is paid by subjects or citizens of the most favoured nation. This duty once paid shall cover from all other charges on the part of His Highness the Sultan, goods of whatever description coming from foreign countries by sea, whether these are intended for local consumption' or for transmission elsewhere in bulk or otherwise, and whether they remain in the state in which they are imported or have been manufactured. There shall, however, be exempted from payment of all duty the following, namely:— (1) All goods and merchandise which, being destined for a foreign port, are transhipped from one vessel to another in any of the ports of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat or which have been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Sultan's Custom houses to await the arrival of a vessel in which to be re-shipped abroad. But goods and merchandise so landed shall be exempted only, provided that the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the ship, handed over the said goods to bo kept under Customs seal and declared them as landed for transhipment, designating at the same time the foreign port of destination and also provided that the said goods are actually shipped for the said foreign port as originally declared, within a period not exceeding six months after their first landing and without having, in the interval, changed owners. (2) All goods and merchandise which, not being consigned to a port within the dominions of the Sultan, have been inadvertently landed, provided that such goods are re-shipped within a month of being so landed and trans ported abroad. Should however, such goods or merchandise, here spoken of, be opened or removed frcm the custody of the Customs authorities, the lull duty shall then be payable on the same. (3) Coals, naval provisions, stores and fittings, the property of Her Majesty's Government, landed in the dominions of His Highness for the use of the ships of Her Majesty's Navy. (i) All goods and merchandise transhipped or landed for the repair of damage caused by stress of weather or other disasters at sea, provided the cargo •»12 so discharged shall be re-shipped and taken away on board of the same vessel, or if the latter shall have been condemned, or her departure delayed in any other manner. Article 7. No article whatever shall be prohibited from being imported into or exported from the territories of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, and no other expert duties are to be levied on goods exported from those territories except with the consent of the Government of Her Eritannic Majesty, such consent being subject to the conditions that may be laid down in the notifica tions intimating the same. Article 8. It is agreed and understood by the High Contracting Parties that, in the event of an arrangement being entered into hereafter between His Highness and the powers having Treaty relations with Muscat, and to which Greafe Britain shall be a consenting party, whereby vessels entering the port of Muscat shall be charged with shipping, tonnage or harbour dues, such dues to be administered under the control of a special Board for the improvement of the harbour and construction and maintenance of light houses, etc.; nothing in the aforementioned provisions shall be construed so as to exempt British vessels from payment of such shipping, harbour, or tonnage dues as may hereafter be agreed upon. Article 9. It shall be at the option of the British subject in each case to pay the percentage duties stipulated in Article 6, either in cash, or, if the nature of the goods allows of it, in kind, by giving up an equivalent amount of the goods or produce. In the event of payment being made in cash, the value of the merchan dise, goods or produce on which duty is to be levied, shall be fixed according to the ready money market price ruling at the time when the duty is levied. In the case of foreign imports, the value shall be fixed according to the market price at Muscat, and in that of native goods and produce by the market price at the place where the merchant shall choose to pay the duty. In the event of any dispute arising between a British subject and the Custom house authorities regarding the value of such goods, this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one, and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should, however, these experts not be able to agree, they shall choose an umpire, whose decision is to be considered final. Article 10. His Highness the Sultan of Muscat engnges by the present Treaty to provide and give orders to his officials that the movement of goods in transit shall not be obstructed or delayed in a vexatious manner by unnecessary Customs formalities and Regulations, and that every facility will be given for their transport. Auticle 11. British vessels entering a port in the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, in distress, shall receive from the local authorities all necessary aid to enable them to re-victual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage. Should a British vessel be wrecked off the coast of His Highness's uominions, the authorities of His Highness shall render all assistance in their power to the distressed vessel in order to save the ship, her cargo and those on board ; they shall also give aid and protection to persons saved, and shall assist them in reaching the nearest British Consulate; they shall further take every possible care that the goods so recovered are safely stored, and kept for the 1313 purpose of beinp: handed over to the owner, Captain, Agent of the ship, or British Consul, subject always to rights of salvage. His Highness's authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is at once informed of such disaster having occurred. Should a British vessel, wrecked on the coast of His Highness's dominion, be plundered, the authorities of His Highness shall, as soon as they come to know thereof, render prompt assistance and take measures to pursue and punish the robbers, and recover the stolen property. Likewise, should a vessel of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, or of one of his subjects, enter a British port in distress, or be wrecked off the coast of Her Majesty's dominions, the like help and assistance shall be rendered by the British authorities. Article 12. Should sailors or others belonging to a British ship of war, or merchant vessel, desert, and take refuge on shore or on board of any of His Highness's ships, the authorities of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, shall upon request of a Consular official, or, in his absence, of the Captain of the ship, take the neces sary steps in order to have them arrested and delivered over to the Consular official or to the Captain. In this, however, the Consular officer and Caj^tain shall render every assistance. Article 13. Subjects of Her Britannic Majesty shall, as regards their person and property, enjoy within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat the rights of ex-territoriality. The authorities of His Highness the Sultan have no right to interfere in disputes with subjects of Her Britannic Majesty amongst themselves, or between them and members of other Christian nations; such questions whether of a civil or criminal nature shall be decided by the competent Consular autho rities. The trial and also the punishment of all offences and crimes of which British subjects may be accused within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan, also the hearing and settlement of all civil questions, claims, or disputes in which they are the defendants, is expressly reserved to the British Consular authorities and Courts, and removed from the jurisdiction of His Highness the Sultan. Should disputes arise between subjects of His Highness the Sultan or other non-Christian Power, not represented by Consuls at Muscat, and a subject of Her Britannic Majesty, in which the British subject is the plaintiff or com plainant, the matter shall be brought before and decided by the highest autho rity of the Sultan, or some person specially delegated by him for this purpose. The proceedings and final decisions in such a case shall not, however, be consi dered legal unless notice has been given and an opportunity afforded for the British Consul or his substitute to attend at the hearing and final decision. Article 14. Subjects of His Highness the Sultan, or any non-Christian nation, not represented by Consuls at Muscat who are in the regular service of British subjects within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan ol Muscat, shall enjoy the same protection as British subjects themselves. Should they be charged with having committed a crime or serious offence punishable by law, they shall, on sufficient evidence being shown to justify further proceedings, be handed over by British employers, or by order of the British Consul, to the authorities of His Highness the Sultan for trial and punishment. Article 15. Should a subject of Her Majesty residing in the dominions of His High ness the Sultan of Muscat be adjudicated bankrupt, the British Consul shall 1415 u tate possession of, recover and realise all available property and assets of sueli bankrupt to be dealt with and distributed according to the provisions of Eng lish Bankruptcy Law. Article 16. Should a subject of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat resist or evade payment of the just and rightful claims of a British subject, the authorities of His Highness the Sultan shall afford to the British creditor every aid and facility in recovering the amount due to him. In like manner the British Consul shall afford every aid and facility to subjects of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat in recovering debts justly due to them from a British subject. Article 17. Should a British subject die within the dominions of His Highness Sultan of Muscat, or dying elsewhere leave property therein, moveable or im moveable, the British Consul shall be authorised to collect, realise and take possession of the estate of the deceased, to be disposed of according to the pro visions of English law. Article 18. The houses, dwellings, warehouses, and other premises of British subjects, or of persons actually in their regular service, within the dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, shall not be entered or searched under any pretext, by the officials of His Highness without the consent of the occupier, unless with the cognisance and assistance of the British Consul or hi&amp; substitute. Article 19. It is hereby agreed between the two High Contracting Parties that, in the event of an agreement being hereafter arrived at between His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and the various Powers with which His Highness shall be in Treaty relations, including Great Britain, which must be a consenting party, whereby the residents of district or town shall, without distinction of nationality, be made subject to the payment of local taxes, for municipal and sanitary pur poses, the same to be fixed and administered by or under the control of a special Board, nothing contained in this Treaty shall be understood so as to exempt British residents from the payment of such taxes. Article 20. Subjects of the two High Contracting Parties shall, witbin the dominions of each other, enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all such forms of religion, and the right to build edifices for religious worship. Article 21. The stipulations of the present Treaty shall be applicable to all the colonies- and foreign possessions of Her Britannic Majesty so far as the laws permit excepting to those hereinafter named, that is to say except to— The Dominion of Canada. Newfoundland. The Cape of Good Hope. Natal. New South 'Wales. Victoria. Queensland. Tasmania. South Australia. Western Australia. New Zealand.15 18 Provided always that the stipulations of the present Treaty shall be made appli cable to any of the abovenamed Colonies or foreign possessions, on whose behalf notice to that effect shall have been given by Her Britannic Majesty's Eopresentative in Muscat to His H ighness the Sultan within two years from the date of exchange of ratifications of the present Treaty. Article 22. The present Treaty has been executed in quadruplicate two copies being written in English and two in Arabic. These are understood to be of similar import and significations ; in the event, however, of doubt hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive. The Treaty shall come into operation within one month after the date when the ratifications may take place. Article 23. After the lapse of twelve years from the date on which the Treaty shall come into force, and on twelve months' notice given by either party, this Treaty shall be subject to revision by Plenipotentiaries appointed on both sides for this purpose, who shall be empowered to decide on and adopt such amendments as experience shall prove to be desirable. In witness whereof Colonel Edward Charles Eoss, C.S.I., on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, and Empress of India, and His Highness Seyyed Feysal-bin-Turki, the Sultan of Muscat, on his own behalf, have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat, this 19th day of March 1891, corresponding- to the 8th Shaban of the year 1308 Hijreea, (Signed) EDWARD CHARLES ROSS, Col., 'Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Signature in Arabic of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Note. —The English, not the Arabic, text was signed by both parties, and must in consequence be regarded as authoritative. PROTOCOL. The undersigned, in proceeding to the exchange of ratifications of the Treaty signed at Muscat on the 19th March 1891, between Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, and His Highness Seyyid Eeysal -bin-Turki, Sultan of Muscat, have agreed to the present Protocol, which shall have the same force and validity as if it had been inserted in the body of the Treaty itself. It is agreed that under article 23 of the said Treaty either of the High Contracting Parties shall be at liberty, after the expiration of twelve years from the date on which the Treaty has come into force, to terminate the' said Treaty at any time on giving twelve months' notice. In witness whereof the undersigned, duly authorised, for the purpose have signed the present protocol, in quadruplicate, and have affixed thereto their seals. Done at Muscat, on the 29th day of February 1892. (Signed) A. C. TALBOT, Lieut.-Col., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, (L. S.) Signature in Arabic of His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. (L. S.)16 No. 7. AGREEMENT REGARDING THE CESSION OE TERRITORY BY THE SULTAN OE OMAN, DATED 20TH MARCH 1891. Peaise be to God alone, The object of writing this lawful and honourable Bond is that it is hereby covenanted and agreed between His Highness Seyyed Eeysal binTurki bin Seyyed Sultan of Muscat and Oman, on the one part, and Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Companion of the Star of India, Her Britannic Majesty's Political Presi dent in the Persian Gulf, on behalf of the British Government, on the other part, that the said Seyyed Eeysal bin Turki bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, does pledge and bind himself, his heirs and successors, never to cede, to sell, to mortgage or otherwise give for occupation, save to the British Govern ment, the dominions of Muscat and Oman or any of their dependencies. In token of the conclusion of this lawful and honourable bond Seyyed Eeysal bin Turki bin Saeed, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, and Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Companion of the Star of India, Her Britannic Majesty's Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, the former for himself, his heirs and succes sors, and the latter on behalf of the British Government, do each, in the presence of witnesses affix their signatures on this ninth day of Shaaban one thousand three hundred and eight (A.H.), corresponding to the twentieth day of March (A.D.) 1891. E. C. ROSS, Colonel, Tolltical Resident in the Fersian Gulf. Signature of His Highness SEYYED EEYSAL BIN TURKI BIN SAEED, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. LANSDOWNE, Viceroy and Governor- General of India. Ratified by His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor-General of India, at Simla on the twenty-third day of May 1891. H. M. DURAND, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. 43 F. and P. D, 1717 No. 8 (a). TRANSLATION OF PROCLAMATION ISSUED BY THE SULTAN OF OMAN REGARDING THE SUPPRESSION OF THE ILLEGAL IMPORTATION OF ARMS INTO PERSIA AND BRITISH INDIA, 1898. Be it known to all who see it tliat we liave given permission to British and Persian vessels oi war to search vessels carrying their and our flags in our territorial waters, and to confiscate all arms and ammunition (weapons of war) in them, if those arms and ammunition are intended for Indian and Persian ports and if they are the property of British, Persian or Muscat subjects. 'We have also given permission to those vessels of war to search Muscat vessels in Indian and Persian waters suspected to contain arms and ammuni tion for Indian and Persian ports, and to confiscate the said arms and ammuni tion. (This is written) that it may be known. And salaams. TVritten the 19th day of Shaban 1315 A. H. (13th January 1898). No. 8 (&amp;). TRANSLATION OF NOTIFICATION. Be it known to such of our subjects as see this that, whereas the British and Persian Governments have represented to us that they are desirous of preventing introduction of arms and ammunition into India and Persia and that there is reason to think that many are exported from Muscat and taken to those two abovenamed countries, we have resolved to join them and to assist them as far as it lies in our power in suppressing this trade in arms and ammunition between Muscat and India and Persia. A\e there!ore warn (our subjects) that all the arms and ammunition sent to those two countries will be confiscated and those engaged in this trade will be punished, as the introduc tion of arms and ammunition into India and Persia is prohibited by the Gov ernments of those two countries and therefore illegal. In future, our Muscat flag will be no protection to vessels carrying the said arms and ammunition from our dominions to India and Persia. (Ihis is written ) that it may be known. And salaams. Dated the 19th of Shaban 1315 A.H. (13th January 1698). (Sd.) FEYSAL-BIN-TURKI. ;r and P. D. 18fife TRANSLATION OF AN UNDERTAKING GIVEN BY THE SULTAN OE OMAN ON THE 31ST MAY 1902 TO THE BRITISH POLI TICAL AGENT AT MUSCAT, REGARDING THE SUE COAL FIELDS. In the Dame of God the High. From— Faisal bin Tueki , Sultan of Maskat, To—M ajor P. Z. Cox, Political Agent, Maskat After the usual compliments. —Regarding the communication you made to me on the subject of the Geologist's report and the views of Government on the subject of the coal deposits, Your Honour is at liberty to inform Government on my behalf, that for the present I have no intention of entering upon the work myself; and that in the future if any Government or Company ask my permission to embark upon the mining enterprise in question, I will not accord such permission without first communicating with Government, in order that they may themselves take up the work with me if they feel so inclined. This is what had to be written. May you be preserved. 43 F, and P. D. 1919 © No. 10. TRANSLATED PURPORT OF A NOTIFICATION ISSUED 13Y im HIGHNESS THE SULTAN ON 17TH OCTOBER 1903 REGARD ING THE IMPORTATION OF ARMS AND AMMUNITION INTO THE BRITISH AND ITALIAN PROTECTORATES IN AFRICA. To all whom it may concern. Be it known that in pursuance of an understanding come to by the Gov ernments of Great Britain and Italy, the importation of arms and warlike stores to those portions of the African Coast and Islands (including Socotra) lying to the North of Ras Aseer {i.e.. Cape Guardafui), whicli are under the British Protectorate and also to those parts of the African Coast which are under the Italian Protectorate, has been prohibited. Accordingly at the request of the British Government pursuant to her understanding with the Government of Italy I hereby notify the said prohibition. Be it therefore known that any native craft transporting arms or warlike stores to the localities in question will incur the risk of confiscation, and that I have granted authority to British men-of-war to search on my behalf vessels which there is reason to suspect in this connection in Muscat and Oman waters, and similarly to search Muscat craft on the high seas if reason exists for suspecting them. Furthermore I hereby grant authority to Italian ships of war also to search suspected Muscat vessels either in territorial waters or on the high seas. (Signed) FEISAL BIN TURKI, Sultan of Muscat. Dated Muscat 24^ Rajab 1321 (=:17th October 1903). 43 F. and V. D&gt; 2020 No. NOTIFICATION BY HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF MASKAT AND OMAN, DATED MASKAT, THE 4TH JUNE 1912. Whereas large quantities of arms and ammunition are at present stored without proper control in private buildings, distributed in this our town of Maskat, and thus exposed to the risk of attack, robbery or fire, we impressed by th« serious menace to the safety of our capital arising therefrom, have resolved to remedy this state of affairs, in accordance with the needs of the times and the requirements of our municipal administration, by the con struction and establishment of a special customs house magazine or arms ware house for the storage of arms and ammunition under safe precautions. It is proposed to introduce this warehouse arrangement from on or about 1st September next. It will be conducted on the following general lines :— Firstly. —On or after 1st September all arms and ammunition or parts thereof imported into my territories will be taken direct from the steamer to the special arms warehouse, to the control of which a special Superintendent will be appointed by us. Secondly.— Similarly all arms-dealers in my territories will be required to deposit stocks remaining in their hands on 1st September in the said warehouse. Any trader offending against this regulation will, in addition to other penalties, render all future consignments of arms and ammunition arriving in his name liable to confiscation, unless and until he complies with this regulation in full Thirdly. —No arms will be allowed to issue from the warehouse until duty lias been fully paid thereon to the Customs Superintendent in the usual way. Fourthly. —The withdrawal of arms from the warehouse will be regulated by the issue of special licenses prepared by the Superintendent and counter signed by myself. Fifthly.— licenses will not be granted to traders but only to approved individual purchasers or their duly authorised agents on the production of satisfactory proof that the number, quantity and destination of arms, ammuni tion, etc., to be withdrawn from the warehouse are free from justifiable objection. Sixthly. —All arms issuing from the warehouse will be marked with a special warehouse mark and serial number. Seventhly. —Special rules will be drawn up providing for and regulating the issue to approved traders of sample stock for exhibition in. their shops. Eighthly. —Rules providing for the collection of arms warehouse charges, on stocks therein deposited, will be drawn up on the analogy of the present Customs House Regulations for the levy of such fees on general merchandise. Ninthly. —Special rules will be drawn up governing the transfer between traders' stocks dej^osited in the arms warehouse. Tenthly. —Special relaxations will be arranged for in favour of flint-locks, muzzle-loading gun pow T der and caps in reasonable quantities. Lastly. —Detailed rules embodying the above principles are under prepa ration and will be published in due course for the further information of all concerned. SAIYID FAISAL-BIN-TURKL No. ll(fc), NOTICE BY HIS HIGHNESS SIR SYUDEAISAL-BIN-TrTRKI, G.C.I.E., SULTAN OP MASKAT AND OMAN. The following draft rules for the establishment, maintenance and control of the Arms Warehouse are published for the information of all concerned. 43 P. and P. D. ai21 22 The said rules will be held to apply to all arms and ammunition or parts thereof held in our territories by traders for sale on the date of the introduction of the said rules, and to all such arms, ammunition or parts thereof as may be thereafter imported into our territories. On, or about, but not before, the 1st September 1912, a subsidiary notice will be issued in due course confirming these draft rules and notifying the date on which the rules so confirmed shall come into operation. Draft Rules. Hide 1. —All arms, ammunition or parts thereof held by traders for sale to the public within my dominions shall be deposited forthwith in the Arms 'Warehouse in accordance with these regulations. The TV arehouse Superinten dent will grant a detailed receipt to the depositor for all such arms, ammuniti- tion or parts thereof in the form attached and marked A. Unle 2. —After the expiry of one month from the date on which these rules come into operation, all arms, ammunition or parts thereof, found in the possession of traders (except in accordance with the provisions of rule 15 hereinafter mentioned), contrary to the provisions of rule 1 aforesaid, shall be confiscated. If the offending trader be a Maskat subject, he will be severely punished ; if a foreigner and amenable to my jurisdiction, he Avill be liable to expulsion from my territories. If the offending trader be a subject of any of the Powers in treaty relations with me, information will be laid against him to the Consul of the Power, whose subject or protege he may be, and the aforesaid Consul will be requested to deal with him according to law and treaty and the spirit of these regulations. Rule 5—In addition to all or any of the penalties imposed by these rules, should any trader be found guilty in the proper forum of oil ending against the provisions of rule 1 aforesaid, all arms, ammunition or parts thereof, held in the Maskat Arms Warehouse to the credit of such offending trader, or that may subsequently be deposited in the Arms arehouse in his name under the provisions of rule 4, will, without further sentence ot forfeiture, be liable to confiscation. Rule 4.—All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, which may hereafter be imported into Maskat territory, will be taken direct to the Arms \\ arehouse and there deposited. Rule 5. —For the more effective carrying out of the provisions of the preceding rule, the masters of steamers importing arms and ammunition or parts thereof will be required to produce on arrival and furnish to the represent ative of the 'Warehouse Superintendent who w 7 ill attend on board, the copy of a separate manifest, and in the form attached and marked B, showing all arms and ammunition and parts thereof, destined for importation into my territories and carried on board their vessels. Rule 6. —All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, destined for import into Maskat, but not detailed, or incorrectly or insufficiently described, in the separate manifest (form B) especially with regard to the marks on the packages or the name of the consignee, shall, as soon as such arms, ammunition or parts thereof have left the ship's tackles become liable to conBscation. Exception. —The sole exception to the operation of this rule shall be in the case of arms, ammunition or parts thereof, landed by mistake m good faith and clearly destined for some other port, to which the import of ajms and ammunition is not prohibited. The burden of proving that such arms and ammunition were intended for import to a port, to which the import of arms and ammunition is not prohibited, shall lie on the steamer's agent, importer or consignee. No claims under this exception w T ill be entertained after a period of three months from date of landing of the goods, in respect of which the claim is made. Rule 7. —All arms, ammunition or parts thereof, deposited in the Arms 'Warehouse in accordance with the provisions of rule 4, shall be claimed by the consignee within a period of three months from the date of deposit in the Arms Warehouse.22 On such claim being made, the Warehouse Superintendent will, suhjoct to the provisions of rules 8 and 8 {a) immediately following and after duo veri fication of the Bill of Lading and steamer's agent s delivery order, grant a detailed receipt in form A above-mentioned. -R u l e 8.—As soon as, in accordance with the provisions of rule 4 aforesaid, arms and ammunition or parts thereof are brought to the Arms Warehouse to be there deposited, the Superintendent, Arms \Varehouse, shall notify the Superintendent of Customs of the arrival of such arms, ammunition or parts thereof by form attached and marked C Arabic ( ^ )in order that duty may be collected thereon by the Superintendent of Customs. jt nle8 f a )—X8 soon as such duty has been paid, the Superintendent of Customs shall immediately return to the Superintendent Arms Warehouse the form marked C duly endorsed with a certificate that the duty has been fullv paid on the arms, ammunition and parts thereof noted m the form aforesaid, and the Superintendent, Arms Warehouse, shall in no case grant the detailed receipt in form A. unless and until he shall have received back the form marked C duly endorsed as already described by the Superintendent of Customs. # # p • i Bute 9 —Failure by consignee to comply with the provisions of either of the three preceding rules shall render the arms, ammunition or parts thereof liable to confiscation. Issue of arms, ammunition or parts thereof from the Arms Warehouse. Rule 10. Anv person proposing to purchase arms, ammunition or parts thereof from any*trader, owning arms, ammunition or parts thereof stored in the Arms Warehouse in accordance with the provisions of rules 1 and 4 above, and dulv claimed under the provisions of rule 7, and on which duty and w arehouse charges have been fully paid m accordance with the provisions of rules 8 and 16, respectively, will be permitted to withdraw arms and ammunition or parts thereof on the production of, and to the extent covered by, a license in form marked D and attached. On the application of the trader concerned, who must be present at such withdrawal, the Warehouse Superintendent shall draw up the license aforesaid and submit it for my approval and signature. • - Bu l e a—It shall bo the duty of the Warehouse Superintendent to refuse to draw up any such license, should he have reason to suppose (a) that the purchaser whose name it is proposed to enter in form D as ' bearer' intends to resell the arms, ammunition or parts thereof to any other person ; (h) that such purchaser is already, whether by license in form D pre viously issued or otherwise, in possession of arms, ammunition or parts thereof, whence it may be inferred that the aims, ammu nition or parts thereof, covered by the license under question, are not required solely for the personal use or protection of the purchaser. 'Sale 12.—H shall further be the duty of the Warehouse Superintendent to ensure that—• («) all rifles issuing from the Arms Warehouse under the terms of any license, issued in accordance with the provisions of these rules, shall be clearly marked on the barrel before withdrawal with the official mark and on the butt with the serial number of issue; (i) no more than 200 rounds per rifle per annum shall be issued from the Arms Warehouse to any holder of a license under form D ; (c) in the event of a license under form D being issued for ammunition only, which must not in any case exceed 200 rounds per annum per purchaser, the purchaser produces, tor the inspection of the Warehouse Superintendent, the weapon in respect oi which the ammunition is required. 2323 24 Utile 13—On the production of the weapons as directed in accordance 'with the provisions of Rule 12 (c), the Warehouse Superintendent shall pio- ceed to satisfy himself that the weapon is duly marked on the barrel with the official mark* of the Arms Warehouse and on the butt with the serial number of issue. If it is found not to be so marked, the Superintendent shall, after marking the weapon with the marks and number of the Arms Warehouse, refer the question of the legality of possession of the weapon to me for orders. The burden of proving that the weapon was innocently come by and not in j'ifiiTgxnent of the rules of the Arms AVarehouse, will lie on the O'w nci and should'he fail to prove innocent possession, the weapon shall be liable to con fiscation. Rule 14. —(Xot in force.) Rule 15. —To meet the needs of traders who may desire to expose in their shops a sample of arms and ammunition for sale, a trader s license in form E Arabic form ( ** ) can be procured by them from the arehouse Superin tendent. A trader holding such a license will be permitted to withdraw from the Arms Warehouse one sample weapon of every kind of which he may have stock Iving in the Arms Warehouse under the provision of Rules 1 and 4, 7 and 8 aforesaid together with 200 rounds of ammunition per sample _ weapon. This stock of ammunition may be renewed under the trader 's license twice a year on the personal guarantee of the trader that it is not for sale but merely practiceammunition. Rule 16. —The Warehouse Superintendent shall have power to frame rules for the charge and collection ot Warehouse charges not exceeding 2 per cent per mensem od on all arms and ammunition or parts thereot stored in the Arms Warehouse and for the discharge of such obligations, when over one month in arrears, by the appropriation to the State of an equivalent portion of the offending goods. Rule 17. —The TVarehouse Superintendent shall frame rules to be approved by me reo-ulating the transfer between traders of arms, ammunition or parts thereof stored in the Arms Warehouse except (1) that no such transfer shall be valid without the consent of the traders concerned ; (2) that it shall be reduced to writinsr and subject to the certificate of the Warehoue Supeiin- tendent to be confirmed by me that all charges leviable under these rules have been fully paid; (3) that it shall be duly registered by the Warehouse Superintendent; and (4) that the fees to be charged for the registration of an} such transfer shall not exceed RIO for each such transfer.F obm A. MASKAT AHMS WAREHOUSE. (To be retained by the depositor.) Serial No. (1) Name of steamer in which imported and date of importation. (2) Number of rifles. (3) Description of rifles^ (4) Quantity of ammunition. (5) Dated .101 . Description of ammuni tion. (6) R emarks. (7) Warehouse Superintendent.MASKAT ARMS WAREHOUSE. Port of Beturn of Arms and Ammunition destined for Maskat shipped per S.S. ' cleared for the Versian Gulf 191 . Marks and Nos. Number and description of packages. Quantities. Descbiption ov contekts or cases. Small Arms. Make or action. Bore. Single or magazine. Cartridges. Nature of arms for which intended. Ball or shot. Other munition. Invoice value. Name and address of makers. Name and address of ship pers or exporters. Name and address of shipping agent. Name and address of consignees. R emarks. Captain S.S*j'ORM 0. To The Superintendent, Maskat Customs Department. The arms, noted below, have been received this day ex S.S. &lt;{ ' and have been duly deposited in the Arms Warehouse. Marks and Nos. Number and description of packages. Quantities. Description of contents of cases. Invoice value. Name and address of consignee. Remarks. As soon as duty shall have been fully paid on the above, kindly return this form with the certificate below duly signed. (Signed) Dated. .191 . Arms Warehouse Superintendent, To The Superintendent, Arms Warehouse. I hereby certify that the import duty Dated. -191 . leviable on the arms, noted in the above form, has been fully paid. (Signed) Superintendent, Maskat Customs.27 28 Form D. LICENSE TO WITHDRAW ARMS, AMMUNITION OR PARTS THEREOF EROM THE ARMS WAREHOUSE, MASKAT. Please permit the bearer n * son of nationality , to take from my stock in the Arms Warehouse the following:— Dated (Signed) Arms Tradery Maskat. Recommended. Dated Approved . J i Seal of His Highness the Sultan. Wixrehome Superintendent. (Signed) Sultan of Maskat and Oman. Verified, and issued. (Signed) No. . Warehouse Superintendent, Maskat, Dated iT-.B.—This document should be made out in duplicate, the original will be held by the purchaser of the goods and carefully preserved as a license to explain his possession, while the duplicate will be retained by the Warehouse Superintendent as a voucher.2&amp; Form E. MASKAT AHMS WAREHOUSE. Traders* license to keep sample arms and ammunition on his htisines» premises. Please permit the bearer son of nationality »to- take from my stock in the Arms Warehouse the following sample arms and ammunition :— I guarantee that the above arms and ammunition taken as samples will not be^sold to any purchaser without special permission in writing from His Highness the Sultan and that the ammunition will only be utilised in practice and testing weapons. _ Eecommenaed. (Signed) Arms Trader, MasJeaf* Dated Warehouse Superintendent. Approved. [ I Seal of His Highness the Sultan. Verified and issued. No, Dated (Signed) Sultan of MasJcat and Oman. Dated (Signed) Warehouse Superintendent, N.B.—This form should be made out in duplicate, one copy will be retained by the Warehouse Superintendent as a voucher,while the original will be retained by the trader and should be carefully preserved by him in order that it may be produced, should the reason for the possession of his sample arms be challenged.29 No. 11(c). NOTICE. From Faisal bin Tueki, To All who may see it: that the Notice dated ^ together with the rules annexed to it, from rule first to rule twelfth, on the subject of the arms trade, and in the matter of the regulation and establishment of the Arms Warehouse, will come into force (practice) from this date, that is, the ^4'' so that it be not hidden. And about the two remaining notices and the rest of the rules another notice will lollow: so that it be not hidden. TiofnrJ Ramazan 1330 U let September Signature of His Highness the Sultan. No. PEOCLAMATION BY HIS HIGHNESS SAIYID EAISAL-BIN-TUEKI, DATED THE 23KD EAMZAN 1330 HIJEA (EQUIVALENT TO 6TH SEPTEMBER 1912). T ? ? ll0 i s ® e , tllis t J ie sale of arms or ammunition or component parts thereof, intended for sale to the public, or their removal from place to place m my dominions is prohibited from this date except through the special Arms U arehouse which we have constituted in Maskat, and every person of our subjects or our pret^s or our dependents who assists in the sale or removal mentioned above will be severely punished, that it may not be hidden and pCclCC- No. 11(e). NOTICE. From To Faisal bin Tueki. All who may see this : in view of our promise Me our notice dated ^ZZim that a further notice would be forthcoming, now this is the notice promised therein. TTTT W ehaTO determined to act upon four rules, t Vi 1 re, , rlct actl011 u P on them should continue with effect from the 1st September 1912. So that it may not be hidden Dated 18! ' ! 6th October 1912 Signature of Bis Highness the Sultan, soWe, the undersigned, have agreed to what follows that the Treaty of Friend ship, Commerce and Navigation between Great Britain and Oman, signed on the 8th day of Shaban 13U8 H., corresponding to the 19th March 1891, will be prolonged by this writing, notwithstanding all, or any, correspondence between his late Highness Syud Faisal bin Turki and the Glorious British Government in the matter of the revision of that Treaty. And it will remain in force for a period of five years from this eleventh day of February 1914, corresponding to the 15th Rabfal Awwal 1332 H., unless a suitable Treaty by agreement between His Highness the Sultan of Maskat and Oman and the Glorious British Govern ment be substituted for that ancient treaty aforesaid. In confirmation thereof we, that is, I, Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Maskat and Oman, with my own hand, and I, Major S. G, Knox, C.I.E., duly author ised a^ent for that purpose on behalf of the Glorious British Government, have jdgned this writing and four copies and have affixed our seals thereto. Done at Masqat this eleventh day of February 191^, corresponding to the 15th Eabi al Awwal 1332 H. Seal of Sultan of Masqat and Oman. Seal of Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. (Sd.) TAIMUR BIN FAISAL, {in Vernacular). {Sd.) S. G. KNOX, Major, Folitical Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul. 43 F. sud P. I?. 31 I l IHis Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Kaisal, Sultan of Rmscat and Oman and Dependencies. Desiring to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which now subsist between them and to promote and extend their commercial relations by the c6nclusion of a new treaty to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation signed at Muscat on the 19th March, 1891, which terminates on the 11th February, 1939, Have accordingly appointed as their pleni potentiaries: - His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty): For Great Britain and Northern Ireland: Lieut,-Colonel Sir Trenchard Craven William Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf: r For India; Lieut•-Colonel Sir Trenchard Craven V/illiam Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; The Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies (hereinafter referred to as the Sultan), in person; V9 Who have agreed as follows:- ARTICLE 1. For the purposes of the present Treaty— (1) The term 'territories of His Majesty' or 'territories of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and India, and any terri tories to which the present Treaty applies by reason of extensions under Article 19 or accessions under Article 20; and the term 'territories of the Sultan' or 'territories of the one (or the other High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean Oman and its Dependencies. (ii) The term 'nationals of His,Majesty' or 'nationals of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean all subjects of His Majesty and all persons under his protection, wherever domiciled, except nationals of Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar, Abu Dhabi, Dibai, Sharjah, Ajman, Umm-al-rQaiwain, Ras-al- Khaimah and Kalba and, for the purposes of Articles 13, 14 and 15, nationals of the States of the- 2 - of the Aden Protectorate and nationals of Zanzibar of Omani origin vho own property in Oman; and the term 'nationals of the Sultan' or 'nationals of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean all the Sultan's subjects, v/herever domiciled. For the purposes of Articles 2, 3, 4, 6, 6, 13, 14 and 16 the word 'nationals' shall be deemed to include corporate bodies created under the law of the territories of the High Contracting Party concerned. (iii) The term 'British vessels' or 'vessels of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty 1 shall mean all ships registered under the law of any p^rt of the British Commonwealth of Nations, including any territory under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty except Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar, Abu Dhabi, Dibai, Sharjah, Ajman, Umm-al-Qaiwain, Ras-al-Khaimah and Kalba; and the term 'Omani vessels' or 'vessels of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean all ships registered by the Omani Government and entitled to fly the flag of the Sultan. (iv) The term 'British aircraft' or 'aircraft of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean all aircraft registered under the law of any part of the British Commonwealth of Nations including any territory under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty except Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar, Abu Dhabi, Dibai, Sharjah, Ajman, Umm-al-Qaiwain, Ras-al-Khaimah and Kalba; and the term 'Omani aircraft' or 'aircraft of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean all aircraft registered by the Omani Government. (vjf) The term 'foreign country' shall mean in relation to His Majesty any country or territory not under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty, and, in relation to the Sultan, any country or territory not being a part of the territories of the Sultan. ARTICLE 2. (1) There shall be perfect freedom of commerce and navigation between the territories of the High Contracting Parties. Each High Contracting Party shall allow the nationals of the other to enter all ports, creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes, also to travel, reside and pursue commerce and trade, whether wholesale or retail, in his territories provided, as regards nationals of the Sultan, that they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulations applicable in the territory of His Majesty in question to the entry, travel, residence and departure of all foreigners, and provided that nationals of His Majesty satisfy and observe the conditions applicable in the territories of the Sultan in regard to the entry of foreigners5 foreigners and that, in proceeding Troin the plsce where they reside in the territories of* the ^ultcin tn another place in his territories where foreign subjects do not already reside, they shall, before doing so, notify in writing the local Omani authorities of the place where they reside, and such authorities sha] 1 inforni them v/hetriei the Intended destination is suitable for theti to travel^ to or not; if the authorities in question notify the said nationals in writing that the intended destination is unsuitable, and if the said nationals persist in travelling to their destination, or if they should fail to notity the local authorities of their intended movements, they will proceed at their own risk. Further, subject to the provisions of Article 9, each High Contracting Party shall allow in his territories the nationals of the other,,whether personally or by agent, freely to bargain for, buy, barter and sell goods, articles of import or local production, whether intended for local sale, use or consumption, for export. (2) Should the Sultan wish to establish any monopoly in anv part of his territory such monopoly will be arranged in such a way that it will not be detrimental to the trade in which nationals of His Majesty are at the time occupied in that part of his territory. ARTICLE 3. (1) Nationals of His Majesty shall enjoy through-^ out the territories of the Sultan with respect to commerce shipping and the exercise of trade all the rights, privileges, immunities, advantages and protection, of whatsoever nature, enjoyed by the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other foreign country. (2) They shall not be liable to taxes, duties, imposts, restrictions or obligations of any description whatever, other or more onerous than those to which the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other foreign country are subjected. (3) In all that relates to navigation and the treat ment of shipping, the Sultan undertakes to treat British vessels not'less favourably in any respect than Omani vessels or the vessels of any other foreJ-gn country. The provisions of this Article relating to vessels apply also to the passengers and cargoes carried therein. ARTICLE 4. Nationals of His Majesty shall be permitted in the territories of the Sultan to hire or to acquire, by gift, purchase, intestate succession, will, or any other legal manner, land, houses, and property of every^ description, whether movable or immovable, to possess the same, and freely to dispose thereof by sale, barter, donation or otherwise on the same conditions in respect of immovable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the most favoured foreign country, and in respect of movable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of the most favoured foreign country. ARTICLE 5.- 4 - ARTICLE 5. (1) Articles p.roduced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty imported into the territories of the Sultan, from whatever place arriving, shall not be subjected to duties or charges other or higher than those pai^d on the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No other or higher duties or charges shall be imposed in the territories of the Sultan on the exportation of any article to the territories of His Majesty than such as are payable on the exportation of the like article to any other foreign country. (3) The import duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty and on goods imported by nationals of His Majesty shall' be paid at the port or other place in the Sultan 1 s territories where the goods are first imported, and on payment thereof such go6ds shall thereafter be exempt within the said territories from all other customs duties. (4) Customs duties shall not be levied in the territories of the Sultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty or imported by nationals of His Majesty in the following cases, namely:- On goods which, being destined and mani fested for a foreign country, are tran shipped from one vessel or aircraft to another in any of the ports or airports of the Sultan or which have been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Sultan's custom-houses to await the arrival of a vessel or aircraft in which to be reshipped abroad; but goods so landed shall only be exempted if the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the vessel or aircraft, handed over the said goods to be kept under customs seal, and declared them as landed for transhipment, designating at the same time the foreign place of destination, and if within a period not exceeding three months after their first landing the said goods are actually shipped for the said foreign country as originally declared and without having in the interval changed owners, and if all customs charges are paid before they are reshipped. On goods which, not being destined and manifested for the territories of the Sultan, have been inadvertently landed, provided that such goods are left in the custody of the customs authorities and are reshipped for a destination abroad within two months of being so landed, and that all customs charges are paid before the goods are reshipped. (a) (b) (c) ..•.- 5 - (c) On coal, fuel and oil, Naval and Air Force provisions and stores and fittings , the property of His Majesty, landed in the territories of the Sultan for the use of the ships of His Majesty's Naval Forces and the aircraft of his Air Forces; duty shall, however, be payable if any of the goods thus exempted are sold or otherwise disposed of in the local markets. (d) On goods transhipped or landed pending the repair of damage caused to the vessel or aircraft by stress of weather or disasters at sea or in the air, provided the cargo . so discharged shall be left in the custody of the customs authorities and be re shipped abroad within a period of three months from the date of the original landing and that all customs charges have been paid. (5) In the cases referred to in paragraph (4) above customs formalities in respect of landing, examination, clearance and shipment of goods are to be observed. (6) All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultan's custom-houses after four months from the date of their original landing shall be disposed of by the Sultan's customs authorities by a public auction after notifying the steamer or aircraft agents concerned. Their sale proceeds, after payment of the auctioneering charges, customs duty and charges, shall be kept in deposit for a period of one year and refunded to the owner if the claim is established during this period, after which no claim shall be entertained (7) In this.Article the words 'customs charges' shall mean charges other than customs duties and may include landing, transit, weighing, wharfage or ground rent, super vision and overtime fees, it being understood that all such fees will be assessed on a reasonable scale, ARTICLE 6. (1) All customs duties leviable in the territories of the Sultan shall be paid in cash and not in kind. \ (2) The value of the goods on which duty is to be levied shall be fixed according to their market price following the normal usage of trade in Muscat. (3) The Sultan's Government shall have the right to fix the valuations for customs purposes of any descrip tions of goods for any period, provided such valuations are fixed by a tariff board appointed by the Sultan, consisting of equal numbers of the Sultan's nationals and nationals of His Majesty representing the merchant community, and presided over by the Director of the Sultan's Customs. (4) In the event of any dispute arising between a national of His Majesty and the Customs House authorities regarding the value of any goods, this shall be determined by reference to two experts, each party nominating one, and the value so ascertained shall be decisive. Should- 6 - other or however, these experts not be able to agree, they shall choose an umpire, whose decision is to be considered as final. ARTICLE 7. The Sultan's Government has the right to charge all vessels entering any of the ports in the Sultan's dominions with shipping, tonnage, or harbour dues, to be administered under the control of a special board appointed by the Sultan for the improvement of the harbour and construction and maintenance of lighthouses, &amp;:c. ARTICLE 8. Internal duties, taxes or fees levied within the territories of either High Contracting Party for the benefit of the State, or of organs of local or municipal government, on or in connection with goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the other Party, shall not be/greater than the duties, taxes or fees levied in similar circumstances on or in' connection with goods of national or any other origin. ARTICLE 9. (1) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the importation into the territories of the Sultan of any article, from whatever place arriving, produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty which shall not equally extend to the importation of the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the exportation of any article from the territories of the Sultan to the territories of His Majesty which' shall not equally extend to the exportation of the like articles to any other foreign country. (3) Exceptions to the general rule laid down in the foregoing paragraphs may be made only in the case of— (a) prohibitions or restrictions imposed in the interests of public security; (b) prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms, ammunition and implements of war, or, in exceptional circumstances, all other military supplied; (c) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of public health; (d) prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of animals or plants, including protection against diseases, degeneration or extinction, as well as measures taken against harmful seeds, plants and animals. ARTICLE 10@ ARTICLE 10. The Sultan engages by the present Treaty to provide and give orders to his officials that the movement of goods in transit shall not be obstructed or delayed in a vexatious manner by unnecessary customs formalities and regulations, and that every facility will be given for their transport. ARTICLE 11. Either of the two High Contracting Parties may appoint Consuls to reside in the territories of the other, subject to the consent and approval of the other as regards the persons so appointed and the places at which they reside. Such Consuls shall at all times be accorded in the country in which they reside treatment and privileges not less favourable than Consuls of the most favoured foreign country. Each of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his own nationals to be appointed to Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party, provided always that the person so appointed shall not begin to act without the previous approbation of the High Contracting Party whose national he may be. -c a S)&lt;£ ' ARTICLE 12. 0) I—I £-• . N ' i ^ (1) British vessels or aircraft coming to the c territories of the Sultan, in distress, shall receive from 'g c the local authorities all possible necessary aid to enable « o them to revictual and refit so as to proceed on their voyage or journey. o CO -p £ ^ (2) Should a British vessel or aircraft be wrecked a-h off the coast of or in the Sultan's territories, the authorities of the Sultan shall render all possible assistance cr to save the vessel or aircraft, its cargo and those on co board; they shall also give all possible aid and protection '2jc persons saved, and shall assist them in reaching the c B nearest British Consulate; they shall further take every possible care that such vessel and all parts thereof, and . ^ g all furniture and appurtenances/including any which may have been cast into the sea. or the proceeds thereof, if sold, as well as all papers found on board such stranded or wrecked vessel, shall be given up to the owners of such vessel, goods, merchandise, &amp;c., or to their agents v^hen claimed by them, or to the British Consul. (3) The Sultan's authorities shall further see that the British Consulate is as soon as possible informed of such disaster having occurred. (4) Should a British vessel or aircraft, wrecked off the coast of or in the Sultan's territories, be plundered, the authorities of the Sultan shall, as soon as they come to know thereof, render prompt assistance and take all possible tneasures to pursue and punish the robbers and recover the stolen property, (5) Likewise, should a vessel or aircraft of the Sultan, or of one of his nationals, enter a port in His Majesty's territories in distress, or be wrecked off the coast of or in His Majesty's territories, the like help and assistance shall be rendered by the authorities of those territories. ARTICLE 13.- 8 - ARTICLE 13. (1) The Consular authorities of His Majesty in the territories of the Sultan shall, subject to ?ny right of. appeal which His Majesty may provide, try and determine— (i) all criminal charges against nationals of His Majesty; (ii) all civil suits in which nationals of His Majesty are defendants; (iii) all'bankruptcy cases in which the bankrupt or the person whom it is sought to make bankrupt is a national of His Majesty; (iv) all proceedings connected v/ith administration of the estate of a deceased national of His Majesty; (v) all questions of personal status where the person whose status is in question is a national of His Majesty, always provided that where such pereon is a Moslem the Consular authorities m^y remit the case for decision by a Moslem religious court of the Sultan on such conditions as they may determine and shall so remit the case if any other party to the proceedings is a national of the Sultan. (2) All criminal or civil cases in which a national of His Majesty is complainant or plaintiff and the accused or defendant is a national of the Sultan or a national of a third country shall be tried and determined by the courts of the Sultan. 'The national of His Majesty shall have a right of appeal to the Sultan, in accordance with the procedure prescribed in the Omani courts, against any decision given against him in any such case if the Consul of His Majesty shall so request. If the Sultan should be absent the appellant may, if he so desires, ask that his appeal may be heard by « the Sultan's representative. (3) A national of His Majesty shall not be arrested nor his property seized, nor his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied by him entered and searched without his consent, by an officer of the Sultan save under an order signed by the Consul of His Majesty, and any national of His Majesty arrested and any property of a national of His Majesty seized shall be placed in the custody of the Consul of His Majesty; alv/ays provided that, in case of necessity for the prevention of breaches of the peace or a breach of a law or regulation of the Sultan which has been made applicable to nationals of His Majesty under Article 15, the authorities of 'the Sultan may without such an order arrest a national of His Majesty or take charge of his property or enter and search his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied by him, but in this case the proceedings shall be at once reported, and the person arrested and any property seized handed over without delay, to the Consul of His Majesty. ARTICLE 14. I In the exercise of their respective jurisdictions under paragraphs (1) and (2) of Article 13, the authorities of the Sultan and the Consular authorities of His Majestymmmm shall afford every possible aid and facility for satisfaction of the rightful claims of the nationals of one Hi^h Contract ing Party against nationals of the other. ARTICLE 16. The Consular authorities of riis Majesty will, at the request of the Sultan, apply in the exercise of their jurisdiction under Article 13 all laws and regulations of the Sultan which it is desirable to apply to nationals of His Majesty in the territories of the Sultan, including, in particular, laws and regulations imposing taxation or duties and policeand municipal regulations. ARTICLE ,16. (1) The provisions of Articles 13, 14 and 15 shall apply to nationals of the Sultan or of another foreign country who are in the regular service of the Consul of His Majesty as if they were nationals of His Majesty, provided that, if any such person should be charged with a crime, the Consul will allow the charge to be tried by the authorities of the Sultan. (2) No criminal or civil proceedings shall be taken before the Consular authorities of His Majesty against any national of His Majesty in the service of the Sultan unless notice of the proceedings has been previously given to the Sultan or his representative. ARTICLE 17. Nationals of the two High Contracting Parties shall, within the territories of each other, enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all forms of religion, provided that such exercise does not wound or outrage the relitious suscepti bilities of the country in which it is proposed to be practised, and the right to build edifices for religious worship in places specified for the purpose by local authorities. Nothing shall be done by either High Contracting Party that ma}/ - disturb existing places of worship belonging to nationals of the other. ARTICLE 18. All the provisions of the present Treaty providing for the grant of the treatment accorded to the most favoured foreign country shall be interpreted as meaning that such treatment shall be accorded immediately and unconditionally. ARTICLE 19. (1) His Majesty may through his Consular Officer at Muscat give notice of his desire that the present Treaty shall extend to any of his colonies, overseas territories or protectorates, or to any mandated territory in respect of which the mandate is exercised by his Government in the United Kingdom, or to any of the States under his protection, except Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar, Abu Ehabi, Dibai, Sharjah, Ajman, Umm-al-Qaiwain, Ras-al-Khairnah and Kalba, and the Treaty shall be extended to any territory specified in such notice as from the date thereof. (2) • • • • •- 10 - (2) After the expiry of a period of tv k 'o years from the coming into force of the present Treaty either High Contracting Party may, by giving twelve months' notice, terminate the application' of the present Treaty to any territory to v»hich it has been extended under the provisions of the preceding paragraph. ARTICLE 20. (1) The High Contracting Parties agree that His Majesty may by notification given through his Consular Officer at Muscat accede to the present Treaty in respect of any Member of the British Commonwealth of Nations whose Government may desire that such accession should be effected. Any such accession shall take effect as from the date of notification thereof. (2) After the expiry of a period of two years from the coming into force of the present Treaty either High Contracting Party may, by giving twelve months' notice, terminate the Treaty as regards any country in respect of which notification of accession has been given under paragraph (1) of this Article. (3) Any notification made under paragraph (1) of this Article may include any dependency or mandated territory administered by the Government of the country in respect of which notification of accession is given, and any notice giVen under paragraph (2) of this Article shall be applicable to any such dependency or mandated territory which was included in such notification of accession, ARTICLE 21. (1) So long as in any territory referred to in Articles 19 and 20 to which the provisions of the present Treaty are not applicable, either by virtue of accession under Article 20 or by notice of extension under Article 19, goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the Sultan are accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country, goods produced or manufactured in such territory shall likewise enjoy in the territories of the Sultan treat ment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) Goods, the produce or manufacture of Palestine (including TransJordan), shall not be debarred•from the benefits of this Article by reason only of any special customs privileges which may be accorded in Palestine to goods the produce or manufacture of any State the territory of which in 1914 was wholly included in Asiatic Turkey or Arabia. ARTICLE 22. (1) The present Treaty has been executed in quadrupli cate, two copies being written in English and two in Arabic. These are understood to be of similar import and signification; in the event, however, of doubt hereafter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive.(2) The present Treaty shall be. ratified, and ratifications shall be exchanged at Muscat. It shall come into force on the 11th day of February, 1939, if ratifications have been exchanged before that date, or if they have not then been exchanged on the date of exchange of ratifications. ARTICLE 23. (1) The present Treaty shall remain in force for a period of 12 years from the date of its entry into force. Unless one of the High Contracting Parties shall have given to the other notice of termination one year before the expiry of this period, the present Treaty shall remain in force until the expiry of one year from the date on which such notice shall have been given. (2) A notice given under this Article shall not affect the operation of the Treaty as betv/een the terri tories of the Sultan and any country or territory in respect of which notification of accession has been given under Article 20. It shall, however, apply to any territory to which notification of extension has been given under Article 19. In witness whereof Lt.-Col. Sir Trenchard Craven William Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B;E., on behalf of His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, on his own behalf, have signed the same and affixed thereto their respective seals. Done at Muscat, this Fifth day of February 1939 corresponding to the 15th Zilhejjah of the year 1357 Hejira For Great Britain and Northern For Muscat and Oman and Ireland: Dependencies; (SGD.) SIR T.C. FOlfVLE (SGD.) H.H. SAIYID SAID BIN TAIL UK. (Political Resident in (Sultan of Muscat), the Persian Gulf.) For India:IN THE NAME OF GCD THE CCMPAoSICNATE, THE U^fec/lRJL. ^5^) This is what has been agreed upon in the settlement between the Government of Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal and Shaikh Isa bin Salah bin Ali al-Harthi on behalf of the Cmanis who sign their names here through the meditation of ir. Wingate, I.C.S., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, who is authorised by his Government in this respect to be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern the Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the Omanis. What concern the Gmanis are these. Firstly. Cn all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Matrah, Sur and all the coast towns nothing more should be taken than 5 per cent. Secondly. For all the Omanis there should be safety and freedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly, All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Matrah and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. The Sultan's Government should not protect criminals who flee from the justice of the Cmanis and that they may be returned to them if asked for anu that the Sultan's Government should not interfere in their internal affairs. The four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as follows Firstly. All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should not inter fere in his Government. Secondly. All travellers to Cman on their lawful business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly. All criminals and evil men who flee to them should be returned out and should not be protected. FourthlyFourthly. The claims of merchants and others against the Cmanis should be heard and decided as is just according to the Sharah. Written at Sib on the eleventh day of Moharram one thousand three hundred and thirty nine Hijrah, corresponding to twenty-fifth day of September one thousand nine hundred and twenty. I have completed v/hat was completed by Shaikh Isa bin Salah on my behalf in these conditions. Written by Imam-al- Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah with his own hand, I on behalf of the Imam-al-Muslamin Mohammad bin Abdullah Al-Khalili and on my own behalf agree to the conditions written here with the authorisation of the Imam-al-Muslamin. Written by Isa bin Salah with his own hand. Signed Sulaiman bin Hamyar An-Nabhani with his own hand 11 Zahair bin Ghusn Al-Hinawi -do- ' Mohsin bin Zahran As-Siyabi -do- ' Hamaid bin Mussullam An-Nidabi -do- ' Saif bin Salim bin AMr Al-Habasi -do- 11 Khalaf bin Nasir bin Mohammad a1- Moawali -do- Thumb impression of Mohammad bin Sultan bin Mansur Al-Wahaibi Signed Mohammad bin Saif bin Said Al-Jabri -do- ' Sultan bin Salim Ar-Rahbi -do- ' Khalfan bin Mohammad bin Sulaiman Al-Hidabi -do- ' Thani bin Harith Al-Jabri -do- ,, Hamdan bin Sulaiman bin Saif An -Kabhani -do- 11 Muhanna bin Hamad bin Mohsin Al-Ibri -do- ' Nasir bin Humaid bin Rashid Al-Ghafiri &amp; his son Mohammad bin Nasir -do- 11 Abdullah bin Hilal bin Lahar Al-Hanai -do- This official document of agreement was brought to me which is the best sort of settlement between Shaikh Isa bin Salah on our behalf as written above and the Government of Sultan Saiyid Taimur through the mediation of Mr. Wingate, I.C.S., H.B.M's Consul at Muscat as is written also with special authorisation. I write these lines with my own hand and thank God for it. Written by Saif bin Ali bin A'mir Al-Maskari with his own hand.IN THE NAME CF GOD THE COMPASSIONATE, THE iviERCIfUL. This is what has been agreed upon in the settlement between the Government of the Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal and the Cmanis, by the acting Wazir Saiyid Mohammad bin Ahmad authorised by His Highness the Sultan through the mediation of Mr. Wingate, I.C.S., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat, who is authorised by his Government in this respect to be a mediator between them. The conditions are stated as follows. Four of them concern the Government of the Sultan and four of them concern the tmanis. What concern the Omanis are these. Firstly. Cn all commodities brought from Oman of all kinds to Muscat, Matrah, Sur and all the coast towns nothing more should be taken than 5 per cent. Secondly. For all the Omanis there should be safety and freedom in all the coast towns. Thirdly. All restrictions on entry to and exit from Muscat, Matrah and all the coast towns should be removed. Fourthly. The Sultan's Government should not protect criminals who flee from the justice of the Omanis and that they may be returned to them if asked for and that the Sultan's Government should not interfere in their internal affairs. The four which concern the Government of the Sultan are stated as follows;- Firstly. All the tribes and Shaikhs should remain in peace and amity with the Government of the Sultan and that they should not attack the coast towns and should interfere in his Government. Secondly. All travellers to Oman on their lawful business should be free and there should be no restrictions on trade and travellers should be safe. Thirdly. All criminals and evil men who flee to them should be turned out and should not be protected. Fourthly. The claims of merchants and others agiinstI IA - 2 - the Cmanis should be heard and decided as is just according to the Sarah. Written at Muscat this fourteenth day of Moharram one thousand three hundred thirty-nine Hijrah corresponding to twenty-eighth day of September one tnousand nine hundred and twenty. Sealed signature of Tairaur - (H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and Oman) Signed Mohammad bin Ahmad - with his own hand, on behalf of the Sultan.COPY The Sultan of Muscat to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, February 10, 1932. (After compliments) I ACKNOWLEDGEE with pleasure the receipt of your honoured letter dated the 9th January, 1932, in which you informed me that my father had abdicated from the Throne of His State and has appointed me as his successor. You state that you have informed His Majesty's Government of this and that the High Government have been pleased to recognise me as Sultan of Muscat and Oman, I would request you to convey my thanks to the High Government, I am writing to inform you that I have, in conformity with the orders issued by ny father, ascended the Throne of the Sultanate today and have intimated to the members of my family the decision of my father to abdicate from the throne and that he has nominated me to succeed him. They have approved of that and have accepted me as Ruler of the State. I would request you to inform the High Government that it is not hidden from me that I shall endure in my rule by the continuance of their help and assistance to me and ny Government in the same manner as my ancestors were helped by them. And it is hoped that you will assure the aforesaid Government that I have accepted all the obligations to the High Government descending to me from noy father and that I am determined to follow his policy in all my relations with Government and that I rely on ths help of the Government and declare that in accordance with the wishes of my father I will be guided by its views in important matters, as I am assured that the Government will not be pleased except in what profits ny State and desires the maintenance of the independence of our Government and Sultanate.~ And since, nowadays, there are no other representatives of those Powers in Muscat with whom we are in treaty relations, we would request His Majesty's Government to inform the Governments of the United States, Prance and Holland of our accession. In conclusion, I thank Your Honour for your sincere wishes and hope that our friendship and union may continue. Yours sincere friend. SAYYID-BIN-TAIMUR,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/737</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/737</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Treaties and Undertakings in Force between the British Government and the Sultans of Maskat [Muscat] and Oman, 1845-1914'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-04T11:23:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 volumes (91 folios)</extent><extent>There is a list of the treaties near the front of the volumes, on pp. 3 and 39. The list refers to the text of each treaty by means of serial and page numbers. The loose papers filed at the end of the second volume are not in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence in use runs through both volumes. It commences at 1 on the second folio after the front outer cover of the first volume and terminates at 89 on the inside back cover of the second volume. These numbers are written in pencil, are enclosed in a circle, and can be found in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. A second foliation sequence is also present between ff. 37-88. These numbers are also written in pencil and circled, but have been crossed out.Both volumes have a printed pagination sequence numbered 2-30, which is mirrored in the Arabic portion of both.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The first volume is
                           Treaties and Undertakings in Force between the British Government and the Sultans of Maskat [Muscat] and Oman, 1845-1914(Government of India Foreign and Political Department). The treaties recorded cover the slave trade, Zanzibar, telegraphs, commerce, cession of territory, arms traffic, and the Sur coalfields. The texts of the treaties appear in both English and (from the rear of the volume) Arabic. A note below the title on folio 4 [folio 40 of the second volume] states that in the event of doubt arising as to the precise interpretation of any portion of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text was to be considered decisive.The second volume is a further copy of the same document. This is part of a file that also contains some loose papers. These are: text of agreement dated 28 September 1920 between the Government of Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Sheikh Isa bin Salah bin Ali al-Harthi on behalf certain Omanis, signatories to the agreement; letter from Sayyid-bin-Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr] to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf acknowledging receipt of his letter informing him of the abdication of his father and his appointment as successor as Sultan of Muscat and Oman; and transcript of treaty between the United Kingdom and Sultan Saiyid Taimur bin Faisal [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman, dated 5 February 1939, which replaced the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation of 1891.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">scribe</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārithī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">scribe</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abū-Shahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hormuz Isle</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>