<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100025473056.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:02:03.383Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■ — ——FIRST EDITION, 1922. Officers are particularly requested to bring to notice any errors or omissions in this publication. Such communica tions should be addressed through the usual channels to—* The Senior General Staff Officer, M. 0.-3, Axmj Headquarters, Simla.* — ifiDi * 1(Volume III) [A.BDLL HAMID (Sardar-i~Ajal). —2nd son of Shaikh of Muhammerah. Deputy Governor of Ahwaz since 1917. He is firm and maintains good order. Carries on family tradition of friendship for British. * ABDUL HUSSEIN KHAN.—Bakhtiari, son of Ghulaffi Hussein Khan. Governor, Behbehan. Did a lot of looting in Burburud in August 1916. \ ABDULLAH KHAN MUSTOUFI.—Formerly BritisK -rigent at Shustar. A spendthrift and always in debt. In 1919 acted as Governor of Arabistan. ABDUL KARIM KHAN ( Sardar-i-Lashhar). — Son of tt Shaikh of Muhammerah. Married the daughter c Ahmed Chalabi, February* 1919,2 ABDUL MEJID KHAN (Sardar-i-Kishwar). —3rd son of Sheikh of Muhammerah. Is Deputy Governor of Muhammerah. Married a daughter of Agha Jaffar, a wealthy Persian merchant of Basrah. A most unpro mising young man and has not given satisfaction as Deputy Governor. ABDULLA KHAN (Sardar-i-Sharaf) .—Son of Sheikh of Muhammerah. ABDUL QASIM KHAN, BAKHTIARI.—Son of Zargham- us-Sultaneh, Commanding 200 Bakhtiaris with Kiza Quli Khan. Was with Turks opposing Russians at Qasri-i-Shirin, but subsequently left them, and came to Kharkeh River. On being attacked on May 29th, 1916, by a British squadron from Shush, he, Mirza Agha Khan and Riza Quli Khan and 70 men attempted to swim the river, but only four men and Abdul Qasim escaped, the others being drowned. Those who were captured were handed over to Chiragh Ali Khan, (q.v.). ABD-US-SAIYID (Mulla ).—Governor of Ahwaz in 1914. Now of no importance. AGHA ABDI.—Held the appointment of Deputy Governor of Muhammerah for several years. A man of ability and some force of character, but uned uca ted. His sons are traders.! 3 AGHA AMIK KHAN.—Joint Deputy Governor of Behbehan on behalf of Bakhtiari Khans, March 1922. t AGHA KHAN (Haji ).—Deputy Governor of Hamadan. Arrested by the British during the Great War. AGHA . NURULLAH.—The influential Mujtahid of Isfahan, who fled thence on approach of the Russians. A rebel deputy to the Teheran Parliament in 1917, but did not take his seat. At present in Isfahan. AGHA MOHAMMED HUSSEIN (SMrazi) alias AGHA KAROON.—Son of Haji Qurban Ali (Shirazi). Is a wealthy merchant of Muhammerah and at present is tax collector of the town. AHMADAYAND DEHTUI.—A small tribe of Lurs, of minor importance, fighting strength about 200 robbers. Their chief, Mehr Ali Khan (Salar-i-Sultan), is friendly with the British. They were represented at Colonel Zakharchenko’s (q.v.) meeting on July 19th, 1917, by Farukh Khan (Samsam-ul-Ayalah) and Malek Miaz Khan. ~ ~ ' ~~ '4 &amp;HMAD MIEZA {Notable of Behbehan). —Shaikh-nl- Islam ? is chief of the Kanavat Mahallah and a wealthy and most influential person, aged about 40., He is the Behbehan agent of the Bahmai Chiefs, and is on friendly terms with the Bakhtiari Chiefs whose (Sardar-us-Zaffar ? s) Munshi-Bashi he was at one time (1906-1907). He is a personal friend of His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz. He has two sons and three daughters. ALI AKBAR KHAN {Salar-i-Ashraf). —Bakhtiari Khan, Born about 1879. Takes no part in tribal affairs. Addicted to drink. Salar-i-Ashraf. Acting Xlkhani, March, 1912. In 1916 was recruiting in Urujan with notorious pro-German democrat. J ALI MARBAN KHAN.—Important Chief of the B air an- wand section of the Lurs. Remained loyal to Russians when remainder of Lurs went over to Turks. Appointed by Russians, Governor of Burujird in 1916, but was turned out by the Turks. Joined the Turks in January 1917. v ’ALI MUHAMMAD KHAN. —Bakhtiari, son of Sardar Zaffar. In charge of sowars in Chahar Mahal but turned out by Yice-Consul on account of openly expressed pro-German sympathies. Educated in 0. T. C.ATJ MUHAMMAD KHAN.—Kuhgalu eliief. In 1917 was defeated by the Baklitiaris. Can raise 2,500 fighting men. 'ALI MURAD KHAN {Salar-i-Bahadur) —Bakhtiari, son of Sardar Zaffar. Joint Governor of Behbehan, March, 1917. [MJ MURAD KHAN.—Kuhgalu chief. Was defeated by the Bakhtiaris in 1917. Can raise 2,000 fighting men. ALI NAQI (Shaikh ).—Known as Shaikh,- Shirazf. Reached Kerman from Bandar Abbas in May, 1915, to preach Jehad } but was seized by the Governor- General. ALI REZA KHAN.—(1) Governor of Char Mahal. Educated Belgium and England. A good type of Bakhtiari Khan. A son of Ghulam Hussain Khan.i 6 r ALI REZA KHAN {Mirza ).— (2) Notable of BelibehrOi^ Mirza All Reza Khan (Bahadur-i-Divan), son of Mirza Sultan Muhammad Khan/ son of Mirza Manza Khan, descended from the notorious Mirza Kumu, who was Governor of Behbehan Circle in 1869. Mirza Kumu claimed that his family had migrated from Mecca and that they were descended from the Prophet. This family has for centuries lived in Behbehan, and its senior member usually acts as Deputy Governor, and, in the absence of any Governor appointed by the Central Government, as Governor of the town. On the appointment of Xlias Khan, Bakhtiari, Sarim-ul-» Mulk, • as Governor of Behbehan in 1909, one of tlia latter’s first acts was to imprison Mirza Ali Riza and loot bis house and property, on the plea that the latter was a reactionary. Later, however, Mirza Ali Riza was restored to the post of Deputy Governor on the departure of the Bakhtiari Governor from Behbehan, which post he was still filling in the summer of 1910. He is a wealthy man, aged about 55, and has 4 grown up sons and 4 daughters. AMANITLLAH KHAN (Sardar Hishmat) —(1) BakK- tiari, brother of Ibrahim Khan, with whom he is on bad terms. [Well disposed to the British. * AMANULLAH KHAN.—'(2) Son of Ghulam Riza Khan, (q.v.). Wiali of Pusht-i-Kuh. [Well disposed to wards the British. • (AMIR-I-AQDAS .—See Hussein Aei MirzAr AM TT?-T-AZAM (Suliman Khan Kalhur).—See KiLHllEL-. The Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh married his sister. 'AMIR-I-MUJAHID .—See Yusuf Khan. AMIR JANG —See Muhammad Taqi KhatI 1 AMIR QITLI KHAN.—Governor designate of Behbehan, February, 1919. Governor of Ram Hormuz in 1921. He has since returned to Charbar. ANAYEH (Shaikh of tlid Bavi tfnfre)’.—Wag persuaded by Hajjt Rais to come into Ahwsiz, though suspicious of tlic intentions of the Shhikh of Muhammerah in August 1915. JA-ZAD-UD-DOWLEH (Sultan Hamid Mirza ).—Born about 1875. The only son of Ain-ud-Dowleh. Went to Europe with Muzaffar-ud-Din Shah in 1902 and 1905. Governor of Saveh in 1915. Disinherited by his father. A spendthrift and useless.13 BAQIR KHAN {talantar)—Born about 1870. K Shushtar notable. Head of the Mugehi quarter and its gang of roughs. Drunkard and opium smoker ; has lived a life of unparalleled vice and crime and for years, murder, rape, extortion, forced labour, usurpation of landed property have been merely daily incidents in his records, only momentarily interrupted by a period of imprisonment in Muhammerah. In Sep tember 1915 he gave His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Ahwaz a verbal undertaking to seize and hand over any German agents attempting to come to the town. He was responsible for the looting of Shushtar Bazar in autumn of 1916 . On the appointment of a British Political Officer to Shushtar in December 1916 he made his usual protestations of loyalty, but was soon found intriguing and was deported to Basra in February 1917 , and thence to India as an officer prisoner of war. He is a large land owner and belongs to the pro-Bakhtiari party in Shushtar. A plausible and pleasant manner conceals the monster he really is. On his return from India he proceeded to Kermanshah in accordance with orders of Persian Government. The citizens desire his return to Shushtar. CHASSIB (Shaikh, Sardar Ar/a) .—Shaikh Khaz’al’s (Shaikh of Muhammerah) eldest son and heir was born in 1891. He was Governor of Ahwaz in 1912-13 but was said to be puerile and neglectful. Even the Shaikh was doubtful whether the Arabs would accept him as Chief. Deputy Governor of Muhammerah in 1919. Dismissed frpm this post in 1921. CHffiAGH ALT KHAN (Sardar Met)—Collected his band of robbers, west of Isfahan, with intention of attacking town m July 1918.EZRA.—An Anglophile Jew, who has acted' as medium of communication with the Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh. , T . j#' EARHAN-AL-ASAD.—Bom about 1850. Prom an early age head of the Bait Saad Arabs. Also known, as A1 Kathir of Shushtar. Headquarters at Qaleh Muchaishir on left bank of Diz below Deh Nau. Originally powerful and independent, but after many vicissitudes is in complete subjection to the Shaikh of Muhammerah to whom he pays his revenues. His tribe together with the Bakhtiaris were responsible for the insecurity of the Shusktar-Dmful road. They have, under pressure, given up their ways to a large extent. He is said formerly to have stood aloof from acquaintance with Europeans ; at present his tendency has disappeared or is well concealed. A broken pathetic old man, sodden with opium, he seems to be rapidly losing control over the mixed tribal elements under him. He fled for refuge to Bakhtiaris when Sheikh of Muhammerah attempted to arrest him in 1921 and has now been succeeded by his son Bandar. PATHULLAH KHAN (Sardar ArsTiad) Bakhtiari .— Married to Bibi Miriam, but, driven away by her. When her property was confiscated in 1916 Fathullahi Khan was invited to return to Bakhtiari and take it over. Has signed an agreement with the British. GHULAM HUSSEIN KHAN ■ Born about 1865. Former title Shahab-us-Sultaneh. Was Ilbegi during 1905 until dissensions arose among the Khans and he was deposed and reinstated several times till he reverted to the post in June 1907. Lackscourage and is unreliable. Has no conscience and is dominated by an unscrupulous lust for money. Captain Lorimer, wbo bad seen a good dfeal of bim^ re* ported most unfavourably as to his character in Feb ruary, 1909. He said, ** his false promises are, as a rule, inspired by purely mercenary motives ”. - it is difficult to detect anything attractive in his character. C. P. Churchill does not agree and finds him,“by far the best of the Khans.” Threw in his lot with Sardar i-Asad when he saw the latter had won in July, 1909. ^Went to the Bakhtiari country in the winter of 1910-11 as acting Ilkhani with Sardar Bahadur. ^ Conducted arrangements with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company for purchase of land. Returned to Teheran in August 1911 and took a prominent part in the operations against Sardar Arshad, September 5th, 1911, and Salar-ed-Dowleh, September 27th, 1911. Went on to Hamadan and returned to Teheran in December. Appointed Minister of War, November 30th, 1911. Well spoken of by Sir W. Townley, 1913, and appointed to Kerman. Lorimer (Kerman) said in October, 1913—“ destitute of pluck and good faith, inferior to Amir-i-Mufakkham, estremely plausible and obliging when it suits his book.” Sir W. Townley said “much changed since Lorimer knew him (some years before) ; like all Bakhtiaris, has to be ridden on the curb ” Governor-General of Isfahan for the earlier part of 1915. Ilkhani, September, 1915, until July, 1917, when he resigned. Behaved well in British interests in summer of 1916, but since then has become soured by general repressiye measure undertaken against tribes. Sons, ’Ali Reza Khan, Amir Mansur Khan and Salar Akram. Hindered Haji Khusro Khan’s efforts to restore order. Is avaricious. Pro fessed himself entirely friendly to the British (April, 1918). Appointed Governor of Isfahan in June, 1918, and adopted a truculent attitude towards the British. Minister for War in June 1918. Later, Governor of Teheran with absolute powers. 1920-21 Governor- Generat of Isfahan. Is now well disposed to British.COLONEL HAIDER QULI KHAN PASYAN (Chief Staff Officer, Isfahan Division ).—A native of Tabriz gives the date of his birth as A. H. 1266 (A. D. 1852) but appears to be about 45 years of age. Studied in a German college, being attached to a Grenadier Regiment and also to Flying Corps and Infantry Detachments. Knows German which he keeps up by reading. ^ Entered the Gendarmerie 11 years ago as a Captain. Was in command of the Isfahan Gendar merie until the amalgamation of the Persian forces and the arrival of the General Officer Commanding in February 1922. A remarkably smart officer, the Gendarmerie under his command were exceptionally well drilled and showed good discipline. A strong sup porter of the ear-Premier Seyed Zia-ud-Din. GHULAM REZA KHAN.— Pusht-i-Kuh, Wali of. GHULAM SHAH KHAN, of Pusht-i-Kuh. -Favourite son of the Wali HABIBULLAH KHAN.—Bakhtiari Khan, son of the late 1 siandiar Khan. Educated in France. Well disposed towards British. , 1 ( Mtrza ) —About September, 1915, arrived at Muhammerah from Teheran as Ins pector of Customs in Arabistan. Placed in temporaryHAIDAR QULI KHAN ( Ftisad-us-Sultan ).—A Bakli- tiari Khan. Educated in Switzerland. Is an Engineer* HAJI ABDUL QASIM.— See Malik-ut-Tujjab. HAJI ABDUR KARIM KHAN {Bakhtiari) .—Joint Deputy Governor of Behbehan on behalf of Bakhtiari Khans, March 1922. HAJI KHUSRU KHAN (Sardar-us-Zaffar) Bakhtiari.— Bom about 1858. Was Ilbegi for a short time in 1906. Has been to Europe, but knows no European language. Threw in his lot with Sardar-i-Asad in 1909. Took part in the engagement against Salar-ed-Dowlek, in September, 1911. Governor of Hamadan, October, 1911. Governor of Isfahan, January, 1911. Was described at the time as a rapacious rascal, and friend of Russia. Governor-General of Kerman in 1915. Dismissed at instance of His Majesty’s Legation for helping Germans and replaced by Sardar Nasrat. Became friendly to the British at the end of 1916. At that time described as a strong man, enjoying great influence and popularity among tribes. Agreed to come to India for 8 months, but visit was can-* celled. Proposed by Captain Noel for Hkhaniship, vice Sardar Muhtasham. Flighty and ill-balancedr: and locked upon as a lunatic by Teheran Khans, whooppose Ms nomination. Appointed by Kbacs, TMinm, July, 1917. Eestored unexampled order on the Lynch Road, and took energetic measures to punish male factors in Cbaliar Mahal. Conducted successful ex pedition against Kuhgalu in June 1918. Resigned likhaniship in October 1919. Sincerest of all the Khans in his friendship for the British. K. B. E. 1919. Ap pointed Ilbegi in 1921. HAJI MUHAMMAD ALI.-^S'ee Rais-p^Tiujak. HI SAM-Ug-BtfLTAKE H.—Son of the late Hisam-us- Sultaneh, Abnl NaSir Mirza, who was son of the late Hisam-us-Sultaneh and second cousin of Muzaffar-ud- Din Shah. He commenced his career in the military service. Received his title on his father's death. Married a daughter of lmad-ud-Dowlah. Was Sent as Envoy Extraordinary to England in 1887 On the occa sion of the Queen’s Jubilee. Held the Governorship of Arabistan in 1891, and that of the Persian. Gulf Ports from March to December 1896. Governor of Lnristan, 1898-99 ; died June, 1899. The present Hisam-us- Sultanek was a favourite Chamberlain of Muzaffar-ud- Din Shah and accompanied His Majesty to Europe in 1905,,HISHMAT-UL-MAMALEK .—See Amanxjllah Khai?/ HAJI SAIYID HUSSEIN.—Aged 60, is chief Mujtahid of Belibehan -—a wealthy man of the Behbehan Mahaileh (Quarter). He has 2 sous and 3 daughters. HUSSEIN ALT MIR2A (Amir-i-A qdas) .-Appointed Governor-General of Isfahan in September, 1917. Treated Zil-es-Sultan with scant courtesy on his arrival there. He uid not assume Governor-Generalship of Isfahan. IJLAL-US-SULTANeH.—S bn of the late Sadteud- Dowleh of Isfahan. Brother of Mu’tamid-i-Khaqan, Qawam-ud-Bowleh, and Sadiq-us-Sultaneh, Chamber lams of Muzaffar-ud-Din Shah. Was in 1903 Governor of Shahrud. Appointed Governor-General of Arabistan, Ma^ } 1912. ,.21 1 of JAVAD KHAN—Karguzar at MuHammeraK, relieved i4 December, 1918 and went to Teheran. JAVAD KHAN (2)—SARDAR IQBAL.—Bakhtiarf ibout Khan, son of the late Isfandiar Khan. irza, ili Hie liis ' * time iau, il0 ' KHABIR-US-STTLTAN.—Telegraph master of Isfahan np ^ to 1921 when he left for Shiraz. A quiet and well lQ ° disposed man. IZAZ-ED-DOWLEH.—Son of Mufakham-ul-Mulk. Ap pointed Inspector of Southern Finance, September .iitifi 1922. 1916, KHAN BABA KHAN.—A Bakhtiari, son of Haji Ali Quli Khan. Educated in England for about 5 years. Returned to Persia about the end of 1916. Strong pro- Turkish sympathies : dabbles in Bolshevism and should rap ' be regarded with suspicion.22 |£HAZ’,A,L KHAN (Bh^ih'h, G.C.I.E., K.C.S.I.), of Muham- merah. ( tiar(Jar-i-A qdas ).—Was bom in 1861, and succeeded his brother in 1897. He is to all intents and purposes independent of the Persian Government. He has always been consistently friendly to the British, and now, in his old age, depends more than ever on British advice. He is a capable and sensible man ; his influence reaches as far as Dizful, where the Lurs even respect him. He owns much territory in Mesopotamia. He threw in his lot with the British against the Turks in 1915. LUTF ALI KHAN (Amir-i-MufaJekh ).—In attendance for some years on Muhammad Ali Shah before and after he came to the throne. (January, 1907). Not liked by other Khans ‘because of the influence he obtained with Muhammad Ali, which he used to their detriment. When the Bakhtiaris marched on Teheran under Sardar-i-Asad in 1909 he remained loyal to his master and his small following fought that of his cousin. A man of no education and an intriguer. On good terms with Nasir Khan. Appointed Governor of Luristan and proceeded to Burujird, April, 1911. Defeated by Salar-ed-Dowleh, September 6th, 1911. Arrived in Teheran end of October, 1911. Is said to be in sympthy with the er-Shah. Arrested the Minister of the Interior in February, 1912, and after wards fled to Kemereh. Appointed Governor of Kerman in summer of 1912. Appointed Governor of Kermanshah beginning of 1915 ; resigned in summer of 1915 and went to live with his Princess wife at Kemereh (Khomain). Retired thence to Burujird when Russians advanced. Was in touch with the Turks in 1916 while at Kemereh. Appointed Governor- General of Ispahan. Has been the most persistently hostile of all the Khans. Relieved by Nasir Khan23 % (Sardar-i-Jang) and left Isfahan in December 1918. Appointed Ilkhani 1921-22. Old and stupid. [Very, religious. MANSUR KHAN.—Is the son of Mulla Abdul Saiyid, adviser to Shaikh Sultan in Ahwaz. He himself acted as private Secretary to Shaikh Sultan. He is known to be a keen intriguer and politician, and was refused a post in the S. P. R. because of his previous bad character. At present he is in the service of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company at Pusht-i-Kuh. MEFATEH-UD-MULK (Saji) .—Appointed Governor of Arabistan in August 1918. Professes good will towards the British but is said to have worked against British nominees. Karguzar at Baghdad, 1920-22, but is now living in Teheran. Dismissed from Baghdad on complaint being made by British High Commissioner of his disgraceful conduct. MEHDI QULI KHAN.—Captain in the Gendarmerie af Isfahan in 1915. Military chief of the Turkish MissioU in Teheran in 1916. MIAZA SULEIMAN KHAN.—Governor of Yezd, August 1922, a noted ' Democrat.'\ 24 MDTAS.—Belgian Director of Customs at Ah-cvaz in September, 3.915. Very excessive frauds were proved against him. ,. ' . ....... ... /,. . .. MIRZA ABDULLAH KHAN'.—Deputy Governor of Dizful, November, 1921. MIRZA ABDULLAH MUSTOUFI.—Succeeded Vaqar-ul- Mulk as Kajil of Arabistan, 1919. Speaks French fluently. Of strong personality ; is intolerant of inter ference or advice ; recognises value of our support and needs it. MERZA MUHAMMAD ALI .—See Saiyeb Hajx. \ JdlRZA MUHAMMAD KHAN . Dowpeh. Muzaitae-ud-MURTAZA QULI KHAN.—Bakhtiari Khan, son of Najaf Quli Khan. Took part in operations against Salar-ed- Dowlek, September 6th, 1911. Represented the Bakh- tiaris in the Majlis, 1911. An enemy of the Nasir gang. Appointed llbegi in 1912. Governor of Yezd end of 1914. Left for Bakhtiari Hills summer of 1915. Has charge of all his father’s properties. Was hand in glove with the Turks. Hindered Haji Khnsru Khan’s efforts to restore order and intrigued against the British and the Persian Government. Appointed llbegi 1921. Is now well disposed towards British. MUHAMMAD KHAN (Salar-i-Azam) .—A Bakhtiari Khan, son of Haji Ali Khan. Openly joined the Germans in 1916. MUHAMMAD BAQIR MUJTAHID (Haji).—Arrived at Isfahan from Najaf via Teheran in June, 1915. ** Bidabad quarter was illuminated. Refused to see any but a few of the elder clergy owing to illness. Treated by Doctor Carr. Said to be strongly anti-Turk and to stigmatize them as “ Kafirs MUHAMMAD BAQIR, (Shaikh) .—Bora about 1865. Son of Shaikh Muhammad Hasan. Resides in Dizful. A fine and extremely rare type of Muslim divine. Hoshares all the good qualities of his father. He is now the principal member of the family, as his father, .though in almost perfect possession of his senses, has made over to him the management .of most of his affairs. Is very .friendly to British. MUHAMMAD HASAN, AGHA SAIYID Aged 60, is of the Kauavat Mahalleh. Has 5 sons and 2 daughters. Notable of Behbehan. MUHAMMAD HUSSEIN {Saiyid ).—Was formerly Lynch’s agent at Ramuz. Helped escape of Qasim’s gang, which murdered the Imam Juma at Shushtar in 1917. Engaged in smuggling arms from Arabistan to N. Persia (February 1918). MUHAMMAD MIRZA. —Bee Mulk Aka. MUHAMMAD NAZIM-US-SHARIEH {Agla Saiyid).— Aged 48. Is one of the Ulema of Behbehan, Is a rich and influential man, living in the Ivan a vat Mahalleh, .Notable of .Behbehan,27 not MUHAMMAD REZA KHAN (Sardar-i-Fateh). —Bakh- tiari Khan. Bom about 1886. A pleasant young man ika withoir much character, and fond of drink. Distin- ! gnished himself in operations against Mahomed Ali and received the title of Sardar Fateh, December 1912. Unsatisfactory as Governor of Yezd. Showed im provement when Deputy Governor of Isfahan in 1915. Represented Khans of the South in 1919. Is leader of young Bakhtiari party. Well disposed towards British. MUHAMMAD ZAMAN KHAN.*—The principal notable of the pro-Muhammerah faction in Shushtar; posses sed of no property, he lived, as head of a quarter and its gang of roughs, by extortion and violence. Deported to Muhammerah in December, 1916. rly in’s 'in h ^ ; ' ;tsn MUHAMMAD REZA (Shaikh ).—Bom about 1354. A religious leader in Dizfitl and a man of some scholastic attainments. He commands considerable influence and respect among the people. He devotes his efforts towards promoting the general welfare of the people. In the last few years his influence has increased con siderably, but he has failed to keep aloof from cliques and intrigues. MUHAMMAD TAQI KHAN (Amir Jang ).—A Bakhtiari Khan, son of Haji Ali Quli Khan. Went to Europe in 1914 to be operated on. Speaks English. Ilbegi in 1916, Governor of Sultanabad in 1918. Eairly friendly to British, : ^( 2S MUHAMMAD YUSUF KHAN.—Late Deputy Governor of Ahwaz. Has been selling women across the border. Owes Sliaukat-ul-Mulk and his relations about 5,000 tomans. Absconded into Afghanistan: returned *to Ahwaz on 25th December, 1915 to fetch away his family. Mujtahids— ^lBDUS SAMAD, Haji, Saiyid {son of Saiyid Ali, born about 1254 H., say 1839 A. £&gt;.).—The head of one of the two great religious houses in Shushtar, and popu larly known as a “Mujtahid”. He studied for four teen years as a youth in Najaf and returned to Shushtar, where he was regarded with respect, in creased by the fact that he took no part in local politics. This state of affairs was subsequently altered by his son, Saiyid Jafar, who set himself assiduously to cul tivating' the favour of the local governors. In league with the Sardar Mukarram he finally brought about the destruction of the well known family of the Kalan- tars. This involved a breach with the other great religious house, that of Shaikh Muhammad Ali, and enmity against them was pursued with great animosity resulting in the flight of Shaikh Murtaza, son of the now deceased Shaikh Muhammad Ali. On the Sardar Mukarram’s deposition in 1907, the people of Shushtar rose against the Saiyids, whom with full justification they regarded as tyrants, and drove them out. At the same time Shaikh Murtaza returned and was received with open arms. Saiyid Abdus Samad and Saiyid Jafar eventually made their way to Najaf where they still remain (February 1909). The family owns considerable property in the Mianab and the Kharran. In 1914 Abdus Samad was reported to be governing Ahwaz very satisfactorily, being capable and energetic, died 1921.29 \ JAFAR, SAIYID (born about 1864).—The principal son of Saiyid Abdus Samad of Shnsbtar and practical director of the affairs of the family. He received his education from his father, but soon devoted himself to secular affairs. He is a self-seeking, greedy, and mischief-making Shushtari of the worst type. / MUHAMMAD KAZ1M (Shaik)—Read of one of the two religious houses in Shushtar, having succeeded his brother, Murtaza. A man of inferior attainmentec Has adopted a friendly attitude towards the British, MUIN-UL-MULK.-—Opium supervisor Isfahan. Unpopu lar with respectable section of Finance Department and with clergy. MUIU EL-MEM ALIK.—Controller of indirect taxes, Is fahan—dismissed September 1922. MtTLK ARA (Muhammad Mirza)^ .“Born 1862. Son of the late Mulk Ara ? Abbas Mirza ; who dfed in 1897,&amp;5kl Was one of Nasir-ud-Din Shah’s brothers. Aceoftb panied his father to Russia on the occasion of the Czar’s coronation in 1896. Speaks French. Appointed Governor of Iraq in April, 1904 and dismissed January, 1906. MtJSTAPA QtfLl KHAtf.—B&amp;kbtiafi youth of 22. Joined the Turks in August 1916, but returned in a short . while, hopes of pardon having been held out to him. * NAJAF QULI KBtAN( 8amsam «Rakhtiari Khan. Born about 1846. Was Ilbegi 1903-05, and Ilkhani frOiii 1905 onwards with his Cousin, Ghulam Hussein Khan as Ilbegi, until dissensions arose, when he was deposed for a short tiiiie. In December 1903 he marched oh Isfahan and took oyer the Governorship of the town, expelling the Shah’s Governor. Captain Lorimer wrote in February, 1909, as follows :— “He is violent in his passions and, generally speaking, blunt in his manner and, though not above deception or bluffing, is not skilled in the nicer forms of fineBsi .,» “ His narrow-mindedness, and the violence of his feelings and his lack of restraint in expressing them, have laid him Open to the charge of being a little mad.” Appointed^ Governor of Isfahan, July 1909, by the Nationalist Government. Appointed jPrimo JJinister and Minister of War, July 26th, 1911. Reformed Cabi net November, 1911. Resigned January, 1913. GovernX 32 PUSHT-I-KOH .—(The Wali of )Glmlam Reza lOian, hereditary ruler of the Lurs of Pusht-i-Kuh. Born about 1864. As a member of the “League of the South” is an ally of the Shaikh of Muhammerah and of Saulat-ud-Dowleh* Qashqai, also of Nizam-us- Sultaneh. The League was formed in 1909 to protect its members against Bakhtiari predominance in Persia, In March 1915, the Wali was reported to be joining the Turks against us, but he himself declared that he only wished to be a peace-maker. He w T as given about £1,000 by Turks and Germans and was pro mised £5,000 and 1,500 rifles. He was, on March 20th 1915, reported to be at Shush with 8,000 men, but the next day the force w r as given as 1,400 horse and 2,000 foot. On November 13th, it was reported that Von Kanitz, formerly German Military Attache at Teheran, had recently spent three days with the Wali, who had agreed, under certain conditions, to attack the British on the Karun. In 1912 he visited Mr. Lorimer, Resident at Baghdad, who described him as anxious minded, not a man of ability or force of character. Was visited by a party headed by a German doctor who offered 100,000 liras to him if he would capture Amara and deny passage to Russian and British troops through his territory. The Wali said he did not wish war to enter his territory as he was neutral. Refused permission to Sherif Bey to allow Turkish troops to cross his territory. Dr. (Mrs.) Stead reported, in August, 1917, that he had accepted £10,000 from the Germans “ as it was thrown at his head. ” His eldest son, Amanullah, and his brother, Shahab-ud-Dowleh, told her that they were anxious to have relations with the British and were willing to raise the country against the Wali. The Walks winter quarters are at Gavi, near Badrah, whence he passes in spring to Amolah and later in the summer to Arquois, near Deh Bala. Gavi, Amoleh and Arquois are merely names of localities where Mu tents are pitched. His eldest son and his brother have their own separate camping headquarters.' !EIie following are the sons of the Wall t— 1. Amanullah KBan, Amir-i-Bahadur-i-Jang, held title of Sardar-i-Jang till 1916. 2. Ghulam Shah Khan, Sardar-i-Ashraf. 3. Isfandiar Khan, Amir-i-Harb. 4. Ali Quli Elan, Sardar-i-Firnz. 5. Yadullah Elan, Ashraf-ul-Mulk. 6. Khalil Allah Khan. 7. Amir Quli Khan. 8. Hasan Khan, Sardar-i-Amain * 9. Nasirullah Khan. , 10. Malik Mansur Khan. 11. Haidar Quli Khan. 12. Qudratullah Khan. Note.—Nos. 1, 4 and jerhaps 5 are the sona of Valiah Khamim, his first wife. No. 2, is son of a Balavandi (small tribe east of Hululan) who was already married when the Wall took her. She is now dead, but also had a daughter who married Salar-ud-Dowleh ; the only one of his daughters whom the Wali has given in marriage. Nos. 5, 10, and 12 are sons of Agha Sulani, his favourite wife. No. 8, is son of Sahab Khanum, sister of Nazar Ali Khan of Pishkuh, also sister of Shahab- nd-Dowleh, the Wall’s only (half) brother. No. 11 is a son of a sister of Suliman Khan Kalhur. Since Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s operations in Wall’s country commenced, Wall’s attitude has changed and now he pro fesses great friendship with British. QASIfvI 'A LI MUHAMMAD (Fayar Muhammad Masiq ).—^Accompanied Shaikh Anayeh of the Bavi tribe into AhWaz in August 1915. A Shaikh of the Bavi.QULI KITAK.—A Slrashtar notable of the tistral type. ■t Illiterate, penniless, drunkard, opium-smok;er, liber tine and hooligan. Attached himself to the pro- Mnhammerah or pro-Bakhtiari party according to circumstances. In September, 1915, promised H. M. Vice-Consul, Ahwaz to arrest any German attempting to enter the town. In 1916 was concerned with Baqir Khan (q. v.) in looting of Shustar Bazar. In Feb ruary, 1917, he displayed considerable physical cour age in arresting with his own hands a notorious des perado concerned with his own son in the murder of a brother notable. Corpulent and pathetic, he rea lises that for the present the game is up, and is mainly concerned with getting off as lightly as possible from the countless claims against him and therefore shows a marked anxiety to please. Was deported to Muham- merah in 1916 to be under the eye of the Sheikh but • was allowed to return to Shustar in 1921 under the Sheikh’s guarantee. RAHIM KHAN.—A Bakhtiari Khan, son of Yusuf Khan. At outbreak of war was at school at Beirut. Now with his father. Pro-American. RAIS-UT-TUJJAR, OF MUHAMMERAH .—(Haji Mu hammad ’Aliof Muhammerah —Born about 1850. A native of Behbehan ; but has resided at Muhammerah for very many years. Was the right-hand man of the late Sheikh Mizal and was implicated in the plot resulting in his murder. Now conducts the whole of the present Sheikh Kh’asal’s Persian affairs and possesses great influence over him. He is an importantmerchant’ and has^ grown very rich. He is very pleasant, especially to Europeans, but much disliked and distrusted by the Arabs. He has great influence in the south-west of Persia. He is agent for the Muin-ut-Tujjar. He has travelled over the greater part of India, including the Native States of Central India. He travelled to Teheran in 1902 to settle the Sheikh’s difficulties over the establishment of Belgian Customs at Muhammerah. His son, Mushir-ut-Tujjar (bom about 1883) travelled via India to Mecca in 1903. The Bais has an interest in the English carry ing trade-on the Karun in the form of an annual subsidy of 4,000 Krans (Burton, February, 1904). Is also in charge of the passport service at Muhammerah. Decorated with the C. I.E., in 1914. Most of his work is now done by his son Haji Mooshir-ul-Tujjar. REZA KHAN JUZDANI.—Robber chief west of Isfahan. Was a tenant on one of Zil-us-Sultan’s estates near Isfahan and it is said was encouraged by the Russians, before their occupation of Isfahan, to give trouble to the Bakhtiaris. He has taken as partner in his more recent depredations, Jafar Quli Khan Chirmini, a neighbour Jof his. In October, 1917, their takings from caravans were said to amount to 500 Tomans a day and they were offering 21 Tomans bonus to every sowar who joined them. Some of the locally enlisted Persian. Cossacks deserted to them, and the only men the local Russian Commandant could rely on were Azarbaijan Turks. In July, 1918, he collect ed his band west of Isfahan with intention of attack ing town. Pleavily defeated by S, P. R. in June 1919, but he himself escaped capture. Captured 21st June, 1919 and hanged by Sardar Jang.36 SADR-TJD-DOWLEH.—Eldest son of the late Sadr-ud- Dowleh of Isfahan, -whose other sons are :— Ijlal-us-Sultaneh, Mu’tamid-i-Khaqan, and Mu'ta- xnin-i-Htizvir, all Chamberlains of Muzaffar-ud- Din Shah. He was Governor of Sabzavar in 1903, and Governor of Kum, 1907-08. SADIQ KRAS.—(Sagvmd Lur) succeeded Sartip Khan as chief of the Sagwand tribe with a salary of tomans 700 per mensem. Friendly. Resides near Dizful. Sided with British in 1913-14 over Railway survey. April 1922 went to Luristan owing to quarrel with the Deputy Governor of Dizful who superseded him. Was implicated in robbery of Lynch caravan but pardoned. Competent but headstrong and over bearing. SAID-UL-MULK.—Appointed Karguzar in Muhammerah, December 1918. Elected Deputy for Shushtar in the Majliss, May 1919. SAIYED, HAJI, (Mirza Muhammad 'Alt) .—A native of Mahallat, a small province near Isfahan. A great traveller. Has been to Mecca several times and has toured in Europe, America and Asia a good deal. Speaks French, Russian and a little English as well as some other European languages, very well known among all clases in Teheran, both Persian and Foreign,Was implicated in a revolutionary plot in 1890 or so and was imprisoned at Kazvin together with Mirza Reza, the murderer of Nasir-ud-Din Shah (before the events of May 1st, 1896). Was in very close touch with the revolutionary party of 1901 which was broken up by the exile of Quavan-ud-Dowleh, Muvaqqar-us- Sultaneh, Vazir-i-Humayun and others, but enjoyed the protection of the Amin-us-Sultan. Said by some to be a Babi and by others to be a follower of the late Saiyid Jamal-ud-Din. His brother was a Professor and Director of the great Muhammadan School in Moscow. Was employed for two years in the Foreign Office at St. Petersburg. Born about 1845. Appoint ed tutor to Sultan Ahmad Shah, August, 1909. SAIYID YADULLAH.—Governor of Yezd-i-Khast. As sisted tiie enemy during the Qashqai rising in 1918. SAIYID YUSUF.—Brigand of Isfahan province. Pub licly hanged in November, 1921, at Isfahan. » SARDAR AZAM.—August 1922—appointed to command Kashan Force. SARDAR-I-AKRAM {Nazar &gt;A.li Khan) .—Born about 1860. Chief of the Amari and the principal figure in the west of Luristan. Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh. Hisheadquarters are at Tarkhan. He has indirect control over a large number of tribes. He is usually at variance with the Persian Government authorities!. He was pursued with armed force by the Salar-ud- Dowleh assisted by the Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh in 1903, who did not, however, succeed in capturing him. In 1907 the Salar after he had raised the standard of revolt against his brother, the Shah, made his peace with Nazar J Ali Khan, married his daughter, and when pressed at first took refuge with him. In 1908 he seized and imprisoned at Khurramabad the Sardar-i- Mukaram, the Governor of Luristan, but was later obliged to flee. In the beginning of 1909, he was refusing to hand over the revenue which he had collect ed from the Baranwand and others by the request of the Governor, the Amir-i-Afkham. He and the Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh are old enemies, though' for political purposes they sometimes relax their enmity. At one time prior to 1913 he was caught and imprisoned but was again released. He is a man of some energy and ability, but he is addicted to drink and opium. Was with the Turks in 1916. Tried to come to terms with the British in April, 1917. Helped the British against the Sinjabis by raising levies. BA RDAR-I- J AN G. — (See Nasir Khan). Ilkhani of the Bakhtiaris, born about 1869. One of the best of the Bakhtiari Khans, being credited with pluck, and de termination. In 1912-14 he was in charge of the Bakhtiari Road, during which time he maintained some order, and also showed a friendly attitude towards Great Britain. A rival of S ardar-i-B ahadur. Has been very loyal to the British in 1914-15, and to this day enjoys the reputation of having been the best Ilkhani since 1907. He resigned early in 1915, and on account of his enmity with Sardar Arfa assumed an unfriendly attitude towards the British,89 but did not take part in any active propaganda. He is now working entirely with the British^ and except ing Zafar, is the only one amongst the senior Khans who can be trusted with a responsible position. He is at enmity with Murtaza Kuli and Mujahid. Is at present in Teheran where he sits in Majliss as Deputy for the Bakhtiari. SAEDAR SAIYID.—Appointed Governor of Luristan, June, 1912. SARIM-US-SULTANEH:—(Sabdar-i-Ashraf)’. ' See Wali of Pusht-i-Kuh. SARTIP KHAN.—Sagvand Lur, friend of Pazal Khan, and inimical to British. Killed in 1920 by his own relatives. SHAHAB-TJD-DOWLEH.—Brother of Ghulam Reza Khan (g.r.) Wali of Pusbt-i-Kuh. Well disposed towards British.40 SHAIKH ABDUL HUSSEIN — Born about 1872. He* belongs to a former ruling family of Bushire which has now fallen on evil times. He was 14 years in Burma in the employment of a British firm at Rangoon and married a Burmese wife, a British Indian subject, by whom he has several children. In 1901 he return ed to Persia and obtained the post of Director of Im perial Customs at Shushtar which he held till 1917. In the end of 1907 he obtained a transfer to Ahwaz w^here he has 3ince remained in charge of the Customs. He is very intelligent and is well educated, speaking and writing English fairly well. He is of a jovial and sociable temperament, and seeks the acquaintance and friendship of Europeans. He affects, probably with sincerity, particular regard for the British. Is now in the service of the Imperial Bank of Persia, Ahwaz. •SHAIKH ABDULLAH (AM^).—Head of SabaeH community in Persia. SHAIKH ABDUL MAJID.—Governor of Muhammefah, February 1922. Very unpopular owing to severe methods of oppression. Regarded as most cruel of Shaikh's sons. SHAIKH HAIDAR.—(Bom about 1857). Shaikh of the A1 Kathir Arabs. Residing to the south and south west of Dizful. Headquarters usually in Husainabad41 tract In neighbourhood of Shush. There has been a long continued antagonism between Shaikh Haidar and Shaikh Farhan Asad, which reached a climax in 1904, when Haidar was defeated and plundered by the latter, on this occasion the Pagvand completed the work commenced by Farhan, but Haidar has mar riage relations with the Sagvand, and as a rule can count on them for some amount of assistance. After a chequered period of misfortune, during which he had to reckon among his enemies the Sardar-i- Mukarram and Shaikh Khazal, he re-established his fortunes in 1908.. In that year with the aid of the Sagvand and the moral support of the Shaikh of Muhammerah, he thoroughly defeated Farhan, and regained the support of his own tribe, who had largely deserted his cause. Shaikh Haidar bears a good reputation among Arabs for his personal qualities. He is lacking, however, in force of character, energy and initiative. He has 8 sons. The eldest, Shaikh Hasan, is of no practical merit. The next, Abbas, is a friend of the Ahwaz Consulate, and has on occasions given practical proof of his friendliness. He has since been dismissed by the Shaikh of Muhammerah and now resides in Naseri. ' SHAIKH HANDLAL KHAN (Born about 1867).—Son of Shaikh Muhammad, by Persian mother, brother of Shaikh Khadzal. Represented the latter’s authority at BandarPNasiri since about the year 1897 up to 1909. He has an ill-defined jurisdiction in the surroundin district towards the Jarrah-i-Shakha to Bandi-i-Kil and some oistance down the Karun. His powers are % however, strictly circumscribed by the distrust of T Shaikh Khazal, without whose orders he can take no | step of any significance. He has one son, Shaikh f&gt; ouitan, a boy of some 14 years. Commander-in-Chief ■ Ls389CGS *— —- * *to Shaikh of Muhammerah. Governor o£ Ahwaz till 1909 whence he was removed owing to suspected com plicity in a plot against the Shaikh. Capable man, resembling the Shaikh in character. Has no ambition regarding succession. Would be amenable to British influence. SHAIKH JABXR KHAN.—Son of late Shaikh Abdullah of Chaab, and by birth Shaikh of Chaab. Born about 1868. Lives near Muhammerah under eye of Sardar- i-Aqdas and has a pension with his half brother Atab. Is very friendly to British. i SHEKIAT MEDAR.—A local notable of Isfahan., Celebrated the change of Governors in 1918 by open ing his granaries and spending about 8,000 tomans to bring the price of food down. SULTAN ALI KHAN, SHAHAB-U S-SULTANEH.—* Appointed Deputy Governor of, Isfahan in 1918. Very unsatisfactory and secretly works with Murtaza Quli Khan. Has distinguished himself by shameless rapacity,. SULTAN ALI KHAN (Shahab-U§-Suttaneh ).—Bakhtiari Khan, son of Haji Abbas Quli Khan. Bom about 1883. A pleasant well-meaning young man without43 V conspienotis ability. Came to Teheran in November, 1915 in command of 300 Bakhtiari sowars. Tried to be friendly. ^ , i SULTAN ^ MUHAMMAD KHAN (Sardar^As7ijaa)\^ Bakhtiari. Born about 1870. Brother to Ghulani Hussein Khan (q.v.), Governor of Isfahan, January to October, 1910 and again in May, 1911. Dismissed for incompetence in 1912 on representations by His Majesty’s Legation. His Majesty’s Consul-General in Isfahan said his tenure of office had been marked “ by a minimum of efficiency and a maximum of rapacity.’^ Was in Teheran in 1914 and went to Bakhtiari country at the end of 1914. Governor of Isfahan in 1915^ throughout period when Germans made themselves masters there. He did nothing to stop them. Resign* ed in March, 1915. Is reported to have countenanced the confiscation of the Imperial Bank of Persia by the Gendarmerie. A very unsatisfactory Governor. Ap pointed Ilbegi, July, 1917. In January, 1922 ap pointed Governor-General of Isfahan. Very well dis posed towards British. Resigned Governor-General ship of Isfahan in October, 1922 on account of serioui illness. TARDOKF .—Vide Tartov. TARTOV (or TARDOFF).—Appointed Bolshevik Consul- General at Isfahan in November, 1921. Took up his post in May, 1922. *44 T yiQAR-UL-MULK.—Governor-Genjeral of Arabistan, February, 1918. A particularly venal and rapacious official—socially very polite, pleasant and hospitable. Resigned and was elected as a member of the Majliss for that district, 1919. Appointed Governor of Iraq in July, 1922, . [VAZIR-I-AFKHAM (Sultan Ali Khan ).—-A Chamberlain of Muzaffar-ud-Din Shah’s. In opposition to the Amin-us-Sultan in 1902-03, in consequence of which he was appointed Governor of Sultanabad (Iraq). , Was allowed to return to Teheran in November, 1903 and gradually regained influence and became Principal , , Private Secretary. Is a son of the late Abdur Reza Khan Yazdi, who was killed by order of the late Muayid-ud-Dowleh for revolutionary tendencies in the reign of Fath Ali Shah. Accompanied Muzaffar-ud- Din Shah to Europe in 1905 with the official title of Minister of Interior. Sons, Amin-ul-Mulk, and Amin- i-Baqaya. Speaks no foreign language. Appointed Minister of the Interior, November, 1906. Became Chief of Cabinet in March, 1907, which post he held until May, 1907, when the late Atabak-i-Azam became Premier. He was then appointed Vazir-i-Darhar (Minister of Court). Is a reactionary. [WAHID-US-SULTANEH.—Karguzar of Arabistan, Nov ember, 1921. [FAMIN-US-SULTANEH.—Son of the Zil-es-SuItan. Governor-General of Isfahan, 1916-17. His sole aim would appear to be the acquisition of wealth. In Feb ruary, 1917 he was replaced by his. brother, Akhbar Mirza.YAVAR FAKIR.*—^Appointed Commandant of the Arabistan Force. k Went to Muhammerah in March, 1922. YUSUF KHAK (Amzr-rMujahid) Bakhtiari Khan. Bom about 1870. Went to Europe at the end of 1907 and returned with Sardar-i-Asad with whom he marched on Teheran, July, 1909. Entrusted his small son to an English lady at Isfahan to bring up. Said to be a libertine and an intriguer. Has a fine appear ance and good manners. Took part in engagement of September 5th, 1911, against Sardar Arshad. While in Teheran in 1911 made a great many enemies owing to his stupidity and tactlessness. Caused trouble in 1913-14 by attempting to seize lands belonging to Haidar Khan of Haiat Baud and his relations. Came to Teheran at the end of 1914 and then went to Europe. Is related by marriage to the Shaikh of Muhammerah, with whom he is on intimate terms. Appointed llbegi, summer of 1915. Was very unsatisfactory in 1916 and gave much trouble at the end of that year, being finally dismissed. An unscrupulous intriguer. Not well disposed towards British and is loathed by afl the other Khans, * Z AHIR-UL-MULK (Moyayad-ud-Dowleli) .—^^Governor- General of Arabistan, November, 1921. An able and -experienced man who has held successfully importaht appointments. He is full of ideas for administering Arabistan but lacks force to put them into practice. Is well disposed towards British. Is jealous of in fluence of 'Shaikh of Muhammerah. Tied from Arabistan in September, 1922 under the curses of the populace and was rescued by Ahwaz Consulate motor car and sowars. He is an intriguing and unscrupulous man. L89CGS—250—16-1-23—GCRS—</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100025473056.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/11/5</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100025473056.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/11/5</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Who's Who in Persia (Volume III) Arabistan, Luristan, Isfahan &amp; Bakhtiari'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1923/1923</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-28T00:04:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (27 folios)</extent><extent>The biographical entries are arranged in alphabetical order from front to back, with cross-references where required.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 29; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The first edition of
                           Who's Who in Persia (Volume III) Arabistan, Luristan, Isfahan &amp; Bakhtiari, compiled by the General Staff, India, comprises a biographical dictionary of individuals, families, and tribes connected with those regions in 1922.It also includes a genealogical tree for the Bakhtiari Chiefs (folio 10).The volume was published by the Government Central Press, Simla, 1923.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>General Staff Branch</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bakhtiari</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Luristan</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government Central Branch Press, Simla</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Isfahan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military intelligence</topic></subject><subject><topic>Biographies</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100025473056.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>