<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00032a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-21T12:49:30.751Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Circular. No. 2, Foreign Office, April 9, 1904. 3c . A question has arisen concerning the flag to be flown on the boat used by Consular Officers when engaged on official duties. Lord Lansdowne has been in communication with the Admiralty on the subject, and the Lords Commissioners have laid down that the Consular flag, which is a personal distinguishing flag, must be flown at the bow, and not at the stern, which is the accepted position for the national colours. No further flag is necessary, but if for some special reason it is desired to fly a flag at the stern, this should be the Red Ensign. I am to request you to bring these remarks to the notice of the Vice-Consuls under your superintendence, for which purpose some extra copies of this Circular are inclosed. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, His Majesty s ConsulHis Majesty's Consul No. 3. A r ':. a*a Sir, Foreign Office, May 2J, [904. I am directed by the Marquess of Lansdowne to state that the King has sanctioned the provision of a distinctive flag for use on shore by His Majesty's Consular Officers. The new flag is the Union flag, with a badge in the centre bearing the Tudor crown on a white medallion; it will be supplied in two sizes, 8 breadths (12 feet by 6 feet) and 4 breadths (6 feet by 3 feet). 2 +- Separate badges for insertion in the Union flags at present in use will be furnished on application. / am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, F. A. CAMPBELL.K -&lt; His Majesty's Consul Circular. [ 41181/07 Foreign Office, January 14, rgoS. It has been brought to the notice of the Secretary of State that there is an absence of uniformity in the practice of His Majesty's Consular Officers with regard to the flying of the national flag over their residences or offices. The flag should always be flown over His Majesty's Consulates-General and Consulates, except in cases where the regulations of the country or of the place in which the Consul resides do not permit of the hoisting of the flags, and where such regulations are applicable generally to the Consular Body. For those of His Majesty's Consuls - General and Consuls who are unable, owing to local regulations, to fly the flag always, and for all of His Majesty's Vice-Consuls and Consular Agents, the following regulations have been drawn up :— The national flag should be flown on the British national holidays enumerated, and on the national holiday of the country in which the Consulate is situated, this formality being necessarily governed in each case by local custom.The flag should always be flown during the stay in port of one of His Majesty’s ships. On the occasion of local official celebrations local usages in the matter should be observed, it being as a general rule desirable that the flag should be flown on all occasions when the observance of the ceremony would be regarded as complimentary to the Government of the country, or when its omission might be calculated to give offence, On the accession, or death, of a foreign Sovereign, or on the occasion of the birth, vttarriage, or deaths of a member of a Royal Family locally represented by a Consular Officer, the flag should be flown at the mast-head, or at half-mast, according to circumstances , These instructions are supplementary to, but do not supersede, those contained in the General Instructions to Consular Officers* I am, Sir, 1 • \ Your most obedient, humble Servant, W. LANGLEY.List of Occasions on which the Consular Flag should be hoisted, either at the Mast-head or at Half-mast, according to circumstances. BRITISH NATIONAL HOLIDAYS. 1. The King’s Birthday, 3 ^ 1 1 2. .The Queen’s birthday, iMUjtecetabez. jj/ Coronation Day, L Prince of Wales’ Birthday Zrd Jnaft ? ^ (h r\fr *1^ J U\S^ 6. During the stay in port of one of His Majesty’s ships. 7. On the birthday or at the death of the Sovereign of the country in which His Majesty’s Consulate is situated. 8. On the national holiday of the country in which the Consulate is situated. 9. * On the accession, or death, of a foreign Sovereign, or on the occasion of the birth, marriage, or death of a member of a Royal Family locally represented by a Consular Officer. 10.* On the occasion of local official celebrations. Subject to the discretion of the Consul.Ftoil, To, s Ko. Lf lQ of 1EC&amp;. it* T « IIOLiaAIiL , i SC X * I 0 ^ » k3 » Poliuical Agent &lt;fc 71.3.:I*s Consul, M U S C A T. The Political Reeident in the Persian Gulf*, B U 3 H I R P. BRITISH AGIHCY &amp; C0H3ULATL. Muscat, S3rd Anril 19GS. ■ ' | Sir, It has ‘been the custom for the Political Agent here, when afloat, to fly the fla^ which I believe is called the 'Union Viceroy’s' at the stern of his boat and no flag in the hows. Several naval officers have told me that this is irregular tut I have not been able to ascertain for certain what would be the correct flags to fly, and I therefore subLlt the matter for your instructions. 2.- In Chapter IV of the General Instructions for His Majesty's Consular Officers it is stated that when afloat Consuls sheuId hoist, at the bow, the blue ensign of Ilia Ma jesty's Fleet with the Royal arms in the centre of the fly, and at the stern, if anything, a red ensign. I imagine,however, that these instructions should not necessarily be regarded as applying to the Pritish represen fci Ubmfj ® ^ “tative liere since his prir ar^ rui-'cticn is that of* Political Agent to the Government of India and his Consular duties are of less importance. S.~ Pending receipt of your instructions as to what fla^; or flajs should 'ce flown in future when afloat* I am;of 1909. © U o. British Residoncy and Oonsulate-cjeneral, 'iX' • Buaiiiro, ** Ma y 15°9. A copy of the undermontionod oornmunication is forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent and His Hajesty^ Consul, Kuscat, for information, with reference to his letter j.o* 430 dated 24th April 1909. ,/ By Order, Lieutenant, Second Assistant Resident - --- - J Resident to Foreign. Letter No* dated J?5? Pay 1909. ^ MNo. of 1909 • British Residency anci^Jonsulate-uenorai, i'V * Busliire, ^ q ' Hay 1909. i^rom To Lir, ilajor P*Z. Jox, Political President in the I^rsian Gulf. L.ii. x3utler, Jsquire, G.i. — Oecretai'y to tho Government of India In the Foreign Department, . SIMLA. £ .^V have the honour to forward a copy of a letter addressed No. 430 dated 24th April 1909. { to ne by tho Political Agent, Fuscat, on tho subject of the pattern of flag to be flc^n by him when afloat in the harbour. 2. When so afloat, his status is that of a Political Agent of the Government of India in Indian Gators and he is saluted by Gaval Vessels as such, by Population. It appears clear, therefore, that the view that the Political Agent should fly his distinguishing flag i.e. Political Jach 'Uninn Viceroy^ Pattern' in the bow; and ordinarily no flag in the stern, is correct. If any flag is flown in the stem, as may be necessary on occasion when the Political Agent’s boat is afloat in the harbour without him, tho flag flwwn should apparontlyhe the hod ns^gn; unless it is customary for Government Officials in India when afloat in rowing boats to fly the Blue ihsign with Local Govern ment Badge, in the stern. Onv) y x&gt; 4 o ions. Cn this latter point I request the favour of instruct- /o I have the honour to be Sir, O' four most obedient servant, (S4j 9 -lGsx. ilajor. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*■ ! I • ' // © Copy of a letter : To. 2841 -Lst.B., dated the 20 th August (received 2 nd September) 1909 , from the deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign department, Simla, to Ilajor P.S. Cox, C.S.I., C.I,L•, Politica.l Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I am directed^Co acknowledge the receipt of your letter Go, 120 cf, dated the 22 nd May 1909 , on the sub ject of the pattern of flag to be flown by the Poli tical Agent, Muscat, when afloat in the harbour, 2 . In reply, I am to state that, when so afloat, the Political Agent should fly the M Union Viceroy* s ,f flag at the bow, and the Blue l.nsign at the stern if the vessel, or boat, is the property of the Government of India, otherwise the Red Ensign should be flown at the stern. Then the Political Agent*s boat is afloat in the harbour without him, the Blue, or Iced, Ensign should be flown at the stern according as to whether the vessel, or boat, is, or is not, the property of the Government of India,, and no flag should be dis played at the bow, 3. I am to add that the Blue Ensign referred to above is that sanctioned for use on Government craft, with the device of the late Honourable East India Com pany on the fly. C?o ‘To. ^ 23 / of 1909 . British Residency Consulate-General, Bushire, ^ September 1909 . Forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Muscat, for information, with reference to this Office endorsement TTo. 1204 dated 22 nd May 1909 . ft (/ . /? /\£LS/f Major, i First Assistant Resident, ( In charge of Residency ). * ACircular. n t ^ . man [ 19618/11 ] Vv* \ r M i\C \ K WM Foreign Office, M \ June 21, igu. Sir, out* The Circular despatch from this Office of the 14th January, 1908, laid down certain Regulations with regard to the flying of the National Flag by His Majesty's Consular Officers over their residences or offices. These Regulations still hold good, but, owing to the accession of His Majesty King George V, it is necessary that the following list of “British National Holidays ” should be substituted for that contained in the above-mentioned despatch :— 1. The Kings Birthday 2. The Queen's Birthday - 3. Coronation Day - 4. Prince of Wales s Birthday - 5. Queen Alexandra s Birthday- 3rd June. 26th May. 22 nd June. 23rd June. 1st December. Additional copies of this Circular are enclosed for His Majesty's Consultransmission to the Consular Officers under your superin tendence. 1 am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, W. LANGLEY.Circular. // / His Majesty's Consul [ 42674A2 ] /3 7 -f Foreign Office, October ji f 1912. Sir, The Secretary of State has had under\ consideration the instructions issued in his Circtilar No. 41 18 1 1 07 of the 14th fanuary, 1908, as to the flying of the national flag over His Majesty's Consulates and Consulates-General. It was therein laid down that, except at posts where the local regulations forbade it, the flag shoidd be kept hoisted over Consular offices every day throughout the year. I Jus practice, however, is open to objection, because flags so exposed very soon becom'e torn and faded, and their constant renewal causes considerable expense and trouble. The Consulates are, moreover, already sufficiently marked by the Consular shield over the doorway, which renders the flag unnecessary as a means of indicating the locality of the Consular building. It has therefore been thought advisable to cancel the instructions contained in the Circular as to the permanentHis M f hoisting of the flag. From the receipt of the present Circular flags need only be flown on the occasions mentioned m the list attached to the previous Circular; Consular Officers should, however, fly their flags at any time if they think it desirable, paying due regard to the practice followed by their foreign colleagues. / am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, ALGERNON LAW. tA£, ' 'v a CirciL [ 49318/Circular. His Majesty's Consul [ 49318/12 ] /U/&amp; Foreign Office, November 22, 1912. tu Sir, With reference to the Circular No. 42674! 12 of the jist ultimo respecting the flying of Consular flags, Secretary Sir E. Greys attention has been called to the fact that the list of ''British National Holidays' attached to Circular No. 41181107 has now become obsolete. &gt; ' I am therefore to transmit the following revised list of ' British Anniversaries ” on which the flag should be flown, and to instruct you to substitute these dates for Nos. 1 to 5 of those given on the earlier Circular :— 1. The Kings Birthday, 3rd June. 2. The' Queen's Birthday, 26th May. 3. Accession Day, 6th May. 4. Coronation Day, 22nd June. 3. The Birthday of Queen Alexandra, 1st December. I am, S Sir ' Your most obedient, humble Servant, ALGEKNON LAW. . v hi 1 IrjT- , ^ I;/ H[ T 3957 212/350 ] J* Circular. m : 5 &gt;: BC/ ^ k A&gt;*Le4?. ^ i ^CAVV Mjnnwr' Foreign Office, Sir, M November 2, 1921. lb ^ \V—. WITH reference to Foreign Office Circular No. 49318/12 of the 22nd November, 1912, I am directed by the Marquess Curzon of Kedleston to transmit herewith, for your future guidance, a copy of Chapter IV of the revised Consular Instructions in regard to flags and official insignia, and the occasions on which the Consular flag should be hoisted. 2. Copies of this Circular are enclosed for transmission to the , ^Consular Officers under your superintendence. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, EYRE A. CROWE. His Majesty’s Consul (45/1921) '^7 f 2 . /V. 112—4 a [6728]Go )y of a lot.“tor lio* 104-^ , du cecl Si/ f ila,, GiiO 2«5ro. Sop oembGr 19 *' 4 &gt; from the Secretary to the Government of India in the ?oreipn and Political Department, to His Ihxceilency the ITaval Comm and er-in -Chief, His 11a j e s ty * s Shipp and Vessels, Hast Indies Station. Hlyinr of the Kuwait flag by His lajesty's Shii'S when firing salutes in honour of His Hxcellency the Shaikh of Kuwait. Wit! reference to the correspondence ending with the letter from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Ho. 2639-K.B., dated the 23rd June 1906, I am directed to transmit a coy of the letter cited in the Letter from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ) margin and to' Pushire, Ho. 440-3, dated 3.rd August 1924 and enclosure.) suggest that should Your Excellency see no objection, instructions may be issued to His majesty’s Ships sLUQLxlfisxxxtss in the Persian Gulf to fly the Kuwait Flag when firing salutes in honour of T -is Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait on re^ei^t of a visit from him. Go. y of a letter No. 1202, dated H.H.S. ,, GHA'HiAH n , the 8th October 1924, from His Excellency the Naval Commander t ^ -in-Chief, His Majesty’s Ships and Vessels, Host Indies Station, to the Secretary to the Covernment of India, Foreign and Political Department. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Ho. 104-h of 23rd September 1924 and to inform you that I have no objection to the proposal that 11. It. Ships should fly the Kuwait Flag when firing salutes in honour of Hit: Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait on receipt of a visit from him. 2. I am issuing necessary orders to H.H.Ships of the Hast Indies Station.—&gt;-^pp INDIA .OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM* % »</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00032a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/130</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00032a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/130</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/5 Instructions regarding flying of flags, half masting flags etc'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1925</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-23T22:02:38</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (21 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 23; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-16; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains Foreign Office circulars, correspondence from the Government of India and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and notes by the Political Agent, Muscat concerning the pattern of flag to be flown by consular officials on official duties, and over consular offices, both generally, and on special occasions.There are no papers dated 1916-20.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Flags</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00032a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>