<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:30:42.497Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. /^/ / ? of 1359 Office of'the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Moharram 20, 1359 February 28, 1940 i © i * 2^4 A- From C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith a letter from Havildar Bandmaster Amar Singh on the subject of his land the present lessee of which refuses to vacate it; and to request that the authorities concerned may please be requested to help in the matter. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government.' i ** J I xO The Commandant, The Bahrain iolice, Bahrain. Sir, Most humbly and respectfully I bug to state that I had leased my land to a certain man called Man Singh of Mohan iura, district amritsar, lunjab. I wished to transfer my land to my brother who will cultivate in it himself. I have written a letter to Man Singh to vacate the land but he refused to do so. ^s it is very difficult for me to go on leave, I shall be obliged if you will kindly write to the Deputy Commissioner, Amritsar, to order him to vacate the land. lor this act of your kindness I shall always pray for y^ur long life and prosperity. I beg to remain, Si r, Your most obedient servant. (Sd.) iim&amp;r Singh. Pi 26.2.40. Noh i fte jo ^ corn tr rleUi M ^ U well Tu la^J o,KOr.&lt;f/ » i-Uic. —wco //• was r JMAn - CMC J /Me 1 ^ 3 ^ , f i /lv€ 'j'tv !&lt;? La&gt;^VO&gt;W f)v« a^l.ca ^ &lt; 51 €-4 (SIA f\U l t,j 4 ^ h'”* • 71 ^ f l n L J m /w, , esse* $^p, s/a l^r S'-p — m© No. i] 4-C/l The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Leputy Gommissioner, Aariisar , and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) for favour of necessary action or advice as to rfhat action the petitioner should take. I The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated the 30th March 1040. ■ **y?*— Reference to previous correspondence:From No.S.Ij.J/JU-A# j Political and Eervice^ Department. Bombay Castle, February 19U0 Dr. H. Sorley, Cbief Secretary to tbe Oovern^ent of Bombay, Political and Services Deoartment. Tbe Honourable tbe Political Resident in tbe Persian Gulf, ^usMre. ' CO 7 Subject:- Release of Yusuf Hassan alias Vosein a native of Bahrein, under section U of Act III of 13614.. /I/ h (% Sir, I a- directed to refer to tbe letter from the Govern ment of Bombay in tbe Political Department No«l4.990-B, dated 2cith bay 1^?7 and to forward berewitb for your information a copy of this Department Resolution No.3.!*5/5k- of to-day’s date regarding tbe release of Yusuf Hassan alias .osein, a native of Bahrein \nder section h of Act fll of rx I have tbe honour to be, Sir, v our most o'edient servant , For Chief Secretary to tbe Government of Bombay, Political and Services Department. HNG Copy topetber with a copy of its accompaniment forwarded with compliments p or information to tbe Political Apent, Bahrein. JRelease of Yusuf Hassan alias Mosein, a native of Bahrein under section 4 of Act III of 1864. ^GOVERIiMEhT OF BOMBAY. Political and Services Department. Resolution No.S.43/34. Bombay Castle, 5th February 1940. Read Government Resolution, Political Department, No.S.43/34, dated the 25th August 1922. Read Government Resolution, Political Department, No.499.0, dated the 28th May 1927. Letter from Mr.W.R.G.Smith, C.I.E., Bar-at-Law, Commissioner of Police, Bombay, No.720/C/36/P.C.B., dated the 20th January 1940. Rith reference to Government Resolution Political No.4990 dated the 28th May 1927 and my letter No. 5934/C/277 dated the 5th September 1927, I have the honour to report^ tiia.t lusuf hassan alias Yusuf Mosein returned to British India in contravention of orders of deportation and was arrested on che 9th November 1939. He was dealt with by me under the provisions ol section 27(2A)-17-02 of the Bombay City : 'Police Ac u and as he was-^ wanted by the Poona Police in connection with a case under sections 380 and 114 of the Indian Penal Code, he was transferred to the Court of First Class Magistrate, Poona on the 28th November 1939. An intimation was given to the District Magistrate, Poona regarding his being a foreigner deportee to enable the Poona authorities to deal with him under section 4 of the Foreigners Act alter the disposal of his case in Poona. A copy 0 . tne letter to District Magistrate, Poona was also forwarded to the District Superintendent of Police, Poona for information. He however, Criminal Investigati January 1940 and was externment orders he the Bombay City Poll magistrate, III Cour imprisonment on the undergoing his M rm Bombay. presented himself in the office of the on Department of this city on the 3rd put under arrest. As he contravened the was charged under section 128-17-02 of ce Acu. He was convicted by the Presidency t and was sentenced to 1 month’s rigorous 17th January 1940. He is at present of imprisonment in the Arthur Road Prison, 0 . / have nowyreceived information from the District up.rmcenaent of Police, Poona that the above foreigner was discharged on 7.fch December 1939 for want of sufficient evidence ana that action under section 4 of the Foreigners Act was not t axen a s the oificcrpcalmg with the case did not receive --receive intimation of his being a foreigner in time. He has three convictions for cheating and one for escaping from lawful custody and has no honest means of livelihood in Bombay and therefore his further stay in British India is not desirable. I therefore, request that Government may please be moved to pass orders under section 4 of the Foreigners Act III of 1864 to take effect on the expiry of his present term of imprisonment, directing him to remove himself out of British India by sea to Bahrein in Arabia on his undertaking not to return. RESOLUTION : The Government of Bombay is pleased to direct under section 4 of Act III of 1864, that Yusuf Hassan alias Mosein a native of Bahrein, should be discharged on the expiry of his present term of imprisonment on condition that he removes him self from British India by sea from the Port of Bombay to Bahrein and undertakes not to return. 2. The Superintendent of the Arthur Road Prison, Bombay, should keep this Resolution with the papers of the foreigner in accordance with the orders contained in Government Resolution No.S.43/616, dated the 11th April 1928, and the Commissioner of Police, Bombay, or the District Superintendent of Police concerned as the case may be, should make the necessary arrangements and report to Government whether or not, the foreigner has fulfilled the condition on which he is discharged. By order of the Governor of Bombay, V.H.Vachhrajani. Deputy Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political and Services Department. G.R.No.S.43/34, P. &amp; S.D. dated the 5th February 1940. To ■ The.Inspector General of Prisons, Provine of Bombay, The Inspector General of Police, Province of Bombay,© % The Deputy Inspector General of Police, Criminal Investigation Department, The Commissioner of Police, Bombay, The Superintendent of the Arthur Road Prison, Bombay, The Accountant General, Bombay, The Passport Officer to the Government of Bombay, The Home Department, The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire,(by letter). Y.V.B. 2.2.40.. ^ht -39/8. Dated the 16th March 1940 To The Political *vgent, Bahrain. 6) me?:qiiiduii Subject - Deportation of Yusuf Hassan alias Mosein, a native of Bahrain, from Bombay. Reference this office telegram No.67 of 23rd February 1940. 2 . I am directed to forward, herev/ith, a copy of letter NO.1890/C/36/P.C.B., dated the 22nd February 1940, together with its enclosures, from the Commissioner of Police, Bombay, to the address of the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with the request th^t the arrival of the above named individual in Bahrain may please be inti mated to the Commissioner of Police direct with a copy to this office. By order,■■■ 1 — (Copy of letter No.1890/C/36/P.C.B. dated the 22nd February 1940 from the Commissioner of Police Bombay, to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.) i Subjec t: R&gt;reigners - Yusuf Hasson alias Mosein, a native of Bahrain -- under Section 4 of the Foreigners Re-deportation of. With reference to Government Resolution, Political and Services Department, Bombay, No.S.43/34 dated the 5th February 1940 and in continuation of this office telegram dated 22nd February 1940, I have the honour to inform you that the foreigner deportee named above left Bombay for Bahrain per s.s.'Varela' on the 22nd February 1940. 2. Copies of his Finger impression slip and his photo are enclosed herewith for your information. 3. His arrival in Bahrain may kindly be made known to this office.(“ i Deported under section 4 of the foreigners Act ill ride U.K.P.&amp; £&gt;. V* Wo* bm 43/34 dated 14-11-39. Ittf.jaL No. Full Name ■) with alias j YUSUI Father's or Husband's_ • _ Name with alias ) MOSeiH Oasto— irab Tillage .Bahrein District-— Bshr e in Apparent age on 16-2-40* Prisoner's Signature or mark ii unable to write. Profession-— nil. Religion— ( 4 . Police Station— Province— between Bahrein 49 and 50 years ConvictionsP. SL fll « Q. L., J. D., No. 7100. dated 3-10-12 A FINGER PRINT SLIP 0. BL D., No. 6703/2, dated 25-7-29.] Classification No. Bight Hand Left Hand Left thumb. Lett ring. Left little. RIGHT HAND Plain prints of the four Angers taken sunul taueoualy. LEFT HAND Plain prints of the four fingers taken simultaneously. [Fold.] Signature of Officer in verification of the fact that the prints above ware tAk^n before him and that they are t.h w prints of the convict named on the reverse. (Signature) (Bank of Officer) d • z - Slip prepared on -2 ■’’by ° ^y^Bank ' — Slip tested on bj’ Bank Classified at Bureau by Pat© Tested do. Date — . cnoor In ahnrgQ, mention of Crime Branch, District District*iith reference to your letter Ho* 16£0/U/*56/i'*C.£* dated 22m February 1940 to the Honourable the iciiticul Keeident in the ierei^ui Giuf, I have the honour to inioria you that the deiortte lueuf llaban alias Mosein arrived in Bahrain ^er Varela on £8th February 1S40. I huic the honour to be, Hir, Your mo&amp;t obedient tervadt , C(U For Political ^ent, Bahrain. I Ho. 120-S.O. Oopy forwarded to the Secretary to the lionourahle the iolitical he si dent in the iersian Gulf reference his memorandum No. 341 dated 16th Larch 1940.Bahrain, tha 2nd April 1940. From H. Weightman, &amp;squire, xolitical iigent, Bahrain. To The Gommissioner of ioiice, Bombay. Subject:- Deportee Yusuf Hasan alias losein. Sir, With reference to your letter Ho. 1890/0/36/r.C.B. dated 22m February 1940 to the lionaurubie the icliticul Kecidcnt in the iersiau Guif, I have the honour to inform you that the deportee Yusuf Hasan alias Hose in arrived in Bahrain per S.S. Varela on £8th February 1S40. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servadt , CA For Political iigent, Bahrain. l No. 120-h.O. Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Honourable the iolitical Hesident in the xersian Gulf reference his memorandum No. 341 dated 16th March 1940.■■ © Letter -o.101/9 dated 2 Bth February 1940 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. The Bandmaster's petition in original may be forwarded to the deputy Commissioner, Amritsar, for favour of necessary i 1 ’ 1/' action. / 3- L' *^0f - mm P.L a No. 114 dated 30th ^arch 1040 to D.C .Amritsar issued. A.P.A. The bandmaster reports that he has received an intimation from his brother to the effect that the man against whom he has complained has handed over the land to his brother and that he has no further claim. Our letter (flag A) to D.C. Amritsar may be cancelled and paper filed. . ^-7 '\</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1886</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1886</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File C/1 II Correspondence with Bombay &amp; Karachi on Miscellaneous Matters'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-03-29T09:54:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (16 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged by topic; the petition of Amar Singh is towards the front of the file (folios 2-4), and the extradition case of Yusuf Hassan is towards the rear (folios 5-13). A set of file notes can be found between folios 14-17 at the back of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 18; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 5-9; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file covers two topics. The first is a petition from Havildar Bandmaster Amar Singh dated 26 February 1940 regarding a lessee — Man Singh — that is refusing to leave his land (see folios 2-4); this petition is forwarded by the Bahrain Political Agent to the Deputy Commissioner for Amritsar, as the land in question is located in Mohan Pura. The outcome is noted on folio 16.The second topic is the extradition of Yusuf Hassan (alias Mosein) from Bombay to Bahrain; see folios 5-13. This includes brief details of his custodial history in India and his convictions; a finger print slip (folio 11) and a portrait photograph of Yusuf Hassan (folio 13) can be found within.The file notes (folios 14-17) contain additional details on both of these cases.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Yusuf Hassan</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Deportation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Land ownership</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00026d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>