<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000131_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:35:43.630Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">OUTWARD T&amp;LSGRAM 'h Inforiaation Department Circulation Mr. Har -ison Mr. Cover1ey-price (• .' 0 Mr. Silver Tel. Branch Spares ,, t-h. CYPHER TELEQ-R^'iM O.T.P. SECRET Prom Secretary of State for India / &amp; *K£nSllM* To G-overnment of India. Department of Information and Broadcasting Despatched 18.10.44 05*45 hours I ORTAHT 25341 Thapar from Joyce. Your telegram 13280 of 13th October. Guidance on aitut,tion in Egypt. Following is background repeat background supplied by Foreign Office and should not be quoted as such begi ns Recent crisis in ; gypt, vhen the King dismissed prime - 'Minister and Leader of the 'aid, Nahas pasha, was culmination of a aeries of differences between them and was a rarely internal affair. King resented what he regarded as attempts by Nahas to assert his own authority and to increase his own popularity at expense of that of Throne, and sought to rid himself of a prime Minister who had maintained his position largely thanks to British support. Nahas resented what he regarded as unconstitutional interference by King in affairs of government and was apparently disposed to provoke a crisis which would curb the power of the palace. The final clash came over a minor issue, in which Nahas knew he couTjd not count on British support. ie had indeed pledged ourselve!T to him in 19ii2 to collaborate 'without interference in internal affairs or in the composition of, or changes in, Egypt’s* Government'. His intention to resign, possibly with a feeling that the British had let him down, was forestalled by the King, * ho dismissed him. From point of view of His Majesty’s Government, it is to be regretted that the personal and unofficial attempts made by His Majest ’s Minister, in the absence on leave of His Majesty’s Ambassador, to smooth over the dispute were unsuccessful, for Nahas pasha and his Government loyally^ iraodemented the Anglo-*Egyptian Treaty and stood steadfastly by their Ally in the darkest days of the North African campaign. But the new prime Minister, hmed Maher .Pasha, leader Of the Saadist party, always considered that Egypt should have actually entered the war on our side, and since assuming office he has oublicly declared that Egypt will fulfil her obligations under the Tnaty and will give all assist nee required until decisive victory is won both in Europe and the paciiic. There is also reason - to believe th t certain Egyptian claims which have been aired in the press and which might, if pressed now, prove embarrassing to His Majesty’s Government, will not be pursued until after the war. 'wo or three of the members of the new Cabinet have bad records vis a vis ourselves, and it therefore remains to be seen how far the prime Minister’s words will be implemented, but so far the situation is satisfactory. Meanwhile it is undesirable to 'play up' the new Government in the face of the ,;aid, who are still the largest party. Fortunately there have been very few minor local disturbances, but we must expect the Government uo /di. 3 paragedisparage their predecessors and to purge from office many of Diahaa pasha*a nominees* ?e look to Egypt to continue to implement the Treaty fully and to co-operate in the coramm war effort, and we welcome any signs that she is doing so. ie for our part shall of course continue to do our best to meet Egypt’s essential requirements, in proportion to our many commitmentsv eonnected with the war effort of the United Nations, but we expect her not to make unreasonable demands. ENDS.disparage taeir predecessors and to purge from office many of Kahas pasha^ nominees. Ke look to Egypt to continue to implement the Treaty fully and to co-operate in the common war effort, and we welcome any si^ns that she is doing so. /e for our part shall of course continue to do our best to meet Egypt’s essential requirements, in proportion to our many commitments v. connected with the v/ar effort of the United Nations, but we expect her not to make unreasonable demands# ENDS« •»V, J * — ■No. 300/40(4-2-1). ROYAL CONSULATE OF EGY1 BOMBAY. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. I have the honour to inform you that we have been officially informed by our Home Authorities that Her Majesty Queen Farida of Egypt has given birth to a daughter on the 7th of April 1940, and that the Royal Princess has been named Princess Fawzieh. I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to you the expression of my highest consideration. Sir, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, SdA Ahmed. Gab?, Consul for Egypt. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S LETTER /A I • -2 25- date RECEIVEDNo t D. 2048-0/40. N From x The Uider S«cretary to the government of India in the external Affairs Department, To Monsieur Jihmed Oabr, Consul for igypt at Bombay, . imtt. Dated New Delhi, theApril 1940, Sir, I m directed to acknowledge, with thanlcs, tlie receipt of your letter No* 300/40(4-2*1), dated the 9th April 1940, conveying the happy news of the birth of a daughtet to Her Majesty Queen Farida of I have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient servant, 3d. I. S#G-onsc Ives , \ . ■ / ■ v for Dhder Secrotary to the Government of India.cc and —n&lt; “Xhfe U^»cu&gt;r-Sei \' ‘Xbfe k V inico^on on this subject, pieiye quo nytyersori by narie, but to-# In any further communication on this subject, pleiye quote No -not to an U. 4-0** ^ treign Affairj compliments to *€«- o-f Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents Tii^ pm ivwr -— - » an( j ? direction of the Secretary of Sta transmits herewith copt^&gt; of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, '7 , 193&lt;5. Reference to previous correspondence : i ^ ^ ^J, 'JzS- Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Similar letter sent to 'Jr* C‘ O ' :?'3&gt; 14 6130 17148 ( 4 )4-OJtg jr THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOY EGYPT AND SUDAN CONFIDENTIAL. July 25, 1 Section 1.. [J 2995/42/16] Copy No. 7 6 Sir M. Lampson to Viscount Halifax.—{Received July 25.) (No. 823 E.) My Lord, Alexandria, July 9, 1938. WITH reference to my despatch N o. 444 E. of the 20th April transmitting a copy of a note on the budget estimates for the financial year 1938-39, presented to the Council of Ministers by Ismail Sidky Pasha, then Minister of Finance, I have the honour to enclose a copy of the Finance Commission’s report on the budget,^) which has been laid before the Chamber of Deputies. 2. This report is, in general, merely a recapitulation of, and running commentary upon, Ismail Sidky Pasha’s budget note. The Finance Commission, however, whilst endorsing in their entirety the contents of this note, have supple mented Ismail Sidky Pasha’s observations in respect of :— {a) The stability of the Egyptian pound. (5) Commercial relations with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. {c) State functionaries. 3. As regards the Egyptian pound the Finance Commission add, in alluding to Ismail Sidky Pasha's statement that Egyptian currency had remained stable owing to its backing by the pound sterling, that the Egyptian currency also owed its stability to the soundness of the State budget, the favourable commercial balance, and to the facts that no loans have been contracted and that the reserve fund has been preserved almost intact. The result had been to maintain the value of Egyptian State bonds despite marked fluctuations in the value of public securities in London and New York. 4. On the subject of commercial relations with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, the commission stated that it was, in their view, incomprehensible that no official commercial relations existed with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, and that such relations ought to be resumed without delay in order to explore the possibility of regaining the market for Egyptian cotton which formerly existed in that country. 5. The Finance Commission have dwelt at great length on the question of State officials, which has been in the past, and continues to be, a source of pre occupation to successive Egyptian Governments ever since the general revision of grades of State officials carried out in 1921, which had the effect of increasing the range of salaries attainable by each grade and of providing for automatic annual increases, with the result that the State budget has been heavily over weighted in respect of civil service salaries. 6. This question was examined by the Zaghlul Cabinet in 1924, and in 1926 a commission was appointed by Parliament to enquire into the number of State employees and the distribution of their duties, with the object of reducing as far as possible the existing expenditure on salaries. 7. In 1928 the same commission was charged by the Chamber of Deputies with the duty of drawing up a new cadre reducing the number of grades and the scale of annual increases of salaries, and in 1931 a new T cadre was actually drawn up which reduced the range of Government salaries and scaled down the rate of annual increases, but these changes were attended by so many qualifying conditions that the work of revision failed of its full effect. 8. The Finance Commission in its report on the budget for 1936-37 stated that the policy of the Government in regard to State officials was inspired by the following principles :— (1) To leave untouched the acquired right of existing officials as regards their salaries. [357 bb—1] (9Not printed.v 2 (2) To secure an effective reduction in the cost of public administration, including such things as transport expenditure, special allowances, and other supplementary charges. (3) To suppress at once all superfluous posts and to reduce the scale of pay allocated to each post, but such reductions not to apply to existing ^ holders of such posts. 9. The same Finance Commission went on to express its satisfaction that the Egyptian Government were fully alive to the necessity of reducing expenditure on salaries, which absorbed 45 per cent, of the public revenues. 10. This alarming increase in expenditure was attributed to the high scale of salary allotted to senior posts and to the automatic increases granted from year to year. The commission pointed out that the maximum of one grade could exceed the minimum of the grade above it, with the result that a subordinate official might be receiving a higher rate of pay than his superior in a higher grade. This question of State officials had developed into a chronic evil which had engaged the attention of successive Governments without producing any effective remedy. Any measures taken in hand had never got beyond their initial stages, either because the Ministry which initiated them had given place to another, or because they were surrounded by so many conditions and formalities that they failed to produce any radical effect. 11. Ismail Sidky Pasha's budget note stated that a solution was not impossible if the question were handled firmly, and the following suggestions are made by the present commission : (1) To draw’ up a new^ scale reducing the gap between the minimum and the maximum of each grade. Such new scales to be applied only to new officials or to those promoted from one class to another. (2) To promulgate a law stabilising the conditions of employment, in order to guarantee uniformity of treatment in all branches of the State service. (3) To facilitate the resignation of officials against suitable compensation. The question of pensions should also be examined. 12. I he hinance Commission concluded by stating that the most efficacious solution would be to increase the number of working hours for State officials, and to fix the salary of each official in proportion to his output of work. 13. The commission drew attention to the growth of the commercial exchanges between Egypt and the Sudan, which showed an increase of approxi mately £E. 200,000, as regards both imports and exports, in 1937 as compared with the preceding year, and it was hoped that this tendency to develop closer com mercial relations between the two countries would be fostered, particularly by the interchange of commercial missions which exercise a general beneficial effect, apart from their purely commercial utility. 14. As regards trade with the United Kingdom the commission drew attention to the fact that Egypt’s favourable trade balance with that country fell from £E. 5.015,000 to £E. 4,270.000 in 1937 and that, in spite of a much larger crop of cotton in 1937, exports of this commodity to the United Kingdom showed a decline in value in comparison wuth the preceding year. Although this decline is small the commission expressed the opinion that the cause should be ascertained and a remedy found, as the development of the growth of long staple cotton in other countries was a factor which Egypt could not afford to ignore. 15. In alluding to the question of the Aswan hydro-electric scheme, the commission endorsed Ismail Sidky Pasha’s statement that the Government should proceed with its realisation but should surround it with all the technical and financial guarantees required, having regard at the same time to the regulations governing public adjudications. The commission expressed the hope that, in addition, no decision would be taken until the question had been submitted to Parliament. 16. In regard to the question of the Egyptianisation of limited liability companies working in this country, the commission had no new suggestions to make. They agreed with the views of Ismail Sidky Pasha as to the necessity of revising the rules governing Egyptian limited liability companies and of adoptio ns a general policy the decision to grant no new^ concessions or to renew old one^s3 on their expiration. The commission endorsed, however, the recommendation that the concession of Egyptian Markets, Limited, should continue to be exploited by private commercial enterprise, but that at least half the capital should be reserved to Egyptians. d 17. An unqualified approval was expressed of the decision to negotiate with the powers concerned the suppression of the Caisse de la Dette, as it was con sidered that the continued existence of this manifestation of foreign control over the finances of the country was incompatible with Egypt’s position as an independent State. 18. As regards the fiscal measures proposed by Ismail Sidky Pasha, the commission have no pertinent comments to make. 19. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Department of Overseas Trade. I h VA /VT’A 'miles w. lampson.■THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HI’S BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT EGYPT AND SUDAN. CONFIDENTIAL. May 2. 1938 Section 3. -lJ 1787/42/16] Sir M. Lampson to Viscount Halifax.—(Received May 2.) Copy No. (No. 444 E.) My Lord, Cairo. April 20. 1938. I HAVE the honour to transmit herein a copy of a note on the budget estimates for the financial year 1938-39. presented to the Council of Ministers by the Minister of Finance^ 1 ) Ismail Sidky Pasha. This comprehensive document falls into three main parts, namely :— ' (1) General economic situation. (2) Egyptian Government’s economic and financial policy. (3) Budget estimates. 2. Apart from the question of cotton, the first section does not call for detailed comment, as it consists for the most part of a general review of world trade and of an examination of Egypt’s overseas trade in 1937. Reference is also made to Egypt’s commercial balance, to the stability of Egyptian Govern ment bonds, and to the note issue. 3. As regards Egyptian cotton, the note draws attention to the danger presented by the increasing production of long-staple cotton in other countries; in 1930-31 the production of Egyptian long-staple cotton exceeded the combined output of other countries by 150,000 bales, whereas by 1936-37 the Egyptian output had, on the contrary, been exceeded by 1,838,000 bales. 4. In order to maintain Egypt’s position as the leading grower of long- staple cotton, it is proposed to put under cultivation reclaimed land in the north of the delta, to reduce the costs of production, sale, ginning, pressing and transport, and to supply chemical fertilisers at cheaper rates. 5. An endeavour will be made to persuade those countries which take little Egyptian cotton in proportion to their total trade with Egypt to increase their offtake, and a permanent propaganda committee is to be formed by the Ministry of Finance, which will devote its energies to the objects enumerated above. 6. As regards the second part of the note, it is stated that the completion of the Assouan and Gebel Aulia barrages will enable the Egyptian Govern ment to maintain cultivation throughout the year in all existing areas under cultivation, and with the surplus water still available, to bring under perennial cultivation some 450,000 feddans of land in Upper Egypt, to irrigate 50.000 feddans of land in Lower Egypt, which is at present only cultivated during the flood season, and to reclaim 400,000 feddans of waste land in the north of the delta. 7. Future irrigation plans include the construction of a barrage in the Sudd and another at the outflow of Lake Albert, but these, however, are long-term projects and will take some years to complete. Other more immediate projects are the construction of a barrage to replace the temporary dyke at Edfina] the strengthening of the Esna barrage, and an all-round increase in irrigation and pumping schemes throughout the country. 8. Other interesting points in this selection of the note are the following : (a) Attention is drawn to the fact that the Government oil refinery at Suez, which is capable of an output of 74.000 tons per annum, actually produces onlv 47.000 tons, and it is stated that the necessary credits will be granted in order that the refinery may be equipped to undertake its full production. (b) As regards the Assouan iron-ore fields, it is stated that a Government committee has been appointed to study the exploitation of these deposits, and to consider the possibility of linking up this question with the Assouan hvdro- electric scheme. There is a significant interpolation in the note in this connexion, which is, no doubt, intended as a direct reference to the controversy which has (') Not printed. [307 b—3J'1 surrounded the adoption of the fertiliser scheme put forward by the English Electric Company (Limited). The note stated that, whilst the Government are determined to carry out this scheme, they will, in doing so, demand all necessary financial and technical guarantees, and will ensure that its execution is carried out in conformity with the rules governing public adjudications. (c) It is proposed to make graduated reductions, from 20 to 50 per cent., in land taxes which do not exceed £E. 20 per annum. {d) Extensive schemes for the promotion of public health in villages and for the supply of drinking-water in rural districts will be carried out. (e) After stating that a sum of £E. 4 million will be needed to cover increased expenditure, a preliminary examination is made of certain of the new taxes which it is proposed to bring into force. Both the income tax and the stamp tax were under consideration by the preceding Government, but the note states that both of them were undesirable in the following respects :— (i) The income tax was based primarily on the rent paid by the taxpayer, but this is an inequitable basis for the assignment of income tax,- as it unduly penalises those concerns which have had an unprofitable year, while it allows to escape too lightly more flourishing concerns and those whose turnover and profits are high in relation to the rent of the premises they occupy. (ii) The previous Stamp Tax Bill contained many objectionable features, the principal one being that under the disguise of stamp duties it introduced what were, in effect, a number of new taxes. Both projects have accordingly been remodelled. The note observes that the fiscal system in Egypt hitherto in force was unjust, as the incidence of taxation was badly distributed, but that the existence of the Capitulations made it impossible for previous Ministers of Finance to effect any fundamental reform in this connexion. The establishment of new taxes, it is added, was arrived at only after preliminary consultation with Egyptian and foreign personages of note in the world of finance and commerce. There will necessarily be some delay in the application of these new sources of revenue, and they aie not expected to yield more than £E. 1 million during the next financial year. (/) In an examination of the position in regard to land mortgage debts and a recapitulation of the various measures which have been taken to assist the owners of agricultural lands, it is very rightly stated that the assistance continuously given by succeeding Governments has bred in the agricultural classes an unfortunate belief that they can continue indefinitely to postpone the payment of their mortgage debts, and a direct warning is given to defaulting debtors that the Government will have no option but to allow mortgagees to foreclose and to take over their lands. (q) The Ministry of Finance is anxious to increase the number of Eo-yptian limited liability companies, and with this object in view State subventions and concessions for the exploitation of mineral wealth are reserved to such companies The note points out that during the year 1937 twenty-two companies with a total capita of £E. 736 000 were formed, as against eleven companies with a total capital of £E. ol2,500 in 1936. In this connexion it is important to notice that the Ministry of Finance intends to modify the regulations governing the formation of Egyptian limited liability companies, and that these modifications will relate principallv to the proportion of share capital to be reserved to Egyptians and to Egyptian renre sentation on the board of such companies, to the end that they may become effectively Egyptian. The note does not state whether the measures which are to be taken in this connexion will be retroactive in their effect but it is presumed from the wording of the note that once the necessary legislation is passed the formation of Egyptian limited liability companies will be authorised onlv on condition that more than 50 per cent, of the capital is subscribed bv Fffvntians arid that Egyptian directors are in a majority on the board ^ F It was established during the discussions at Montreux that the Question of whether any particular legislative measure is inconsistent with article 2 of the Montreux Convention is one of fact to be decided on the merits of the ease Until the actual texts of the proposed legislative measures are available judgmentThus showing an apparent increase of 1.839.180 3 must therefore be reserved. It is clear, however, that such legislation might, in fact, prove to be discriminatory, and the actual texts will have to he carefully examined from this point of view. (A) Another significant remark in the note is that concerning concessionary companies. It is stated that, as far as possible, the Government will refrain ft ft from granting any new concessions and from renewing existing ones bn their expiration. The Government will, in future, take over and administer such concessions itself, provided they are such that the State can do so with advantage. Particular mention is made of the concession granted to Egyptian Markets (Limited), whose concession expires on the 31st May, 1938. In view of the purely commercial character of this enter prise, the Ministry of Finance is of opinion that it would be preferable to cede the concession to an Egyptian limited liability company in which at least half the capital must he reserved to Egyptians. The concession will be granted for a period of twenty years and. with‘the consent of the State, will be renewed for a further period of ten years. The share of the Government in the profits of this concession will be 60 per cent, greater than that obtained from the existing concessionnaires. (i) A long section in the note deals with the measures to be taken to regulate the conditions of service and of pension of Government officials, and to reduce superfluous staffs. O’). The Ministry of Finance has drawn up proposals for the suppression of the Caisse de la Dette and for the administration of this service by the State. The Council of Ministers will be asked in the near future to authorise the Ministry of Finance to negotiate with the three Powers concerned for the suppression of the Debt Administration. (k) The note states that on the 30th April, 1937. the Government’s Reserve Fund amounted to £E. 34.046,317. The reserve falls into two parts, nmnely :— A liquid reserve amounting to £E. 25,009.281; and A frozen, or engaged, reserve amounting to £E. 9,037,036, which is invested in, or loaned to, agricultural and industrial institutions. 9. The third part of the note deals with the budget estimates for 1938-39. Treaty obligations, amounting in 1938-39 to £E. 500,000, the Government’s policy of agricultural reform, a heavy increase in military expenditure, the inheritance of supplementary credits authorised by the last Government, and the abolition of the National Defence contribution imposed on Government servants which had been estimated (by the previous Government) to produce a revenue of £E. 1,100,000. have made it necessary for the Government to find new revenue amounting to £E. 5,900,000. As a first step to meet this situation departmental credits were scaled down by £E. 850,000. which includes a reduction of £E. 250.000 in the annual contribution made to the Sudan, whilst an increase of £E. 1.210.000 is anticipated in the yield of existing taxes, with the result that towards the additional expenditure of £E. 5.900,000 the Ministry of Finance is able to find £E. 2,060,000. This will leave a deficit of £E. 3.840,000. It is proposed to cover this amount in the following manner :— £E. Increase in the incidence of certain existing taxes... 730,000 Estimated yield of new taxes ... ... ... 1,000.000 To be drawn from the general reserve fund ... 2,110,000 10. The cost of national defence will reach a figure of £E. 4,069.000, and it is stated in the note that the first division will be brought up to full strength and will be fully equipped, and as soon as this is done, the formation of a second division will be undertaken at once. It has also been decided to increase divisional strength to 25,000 men instead of 20,000. In connexion with the strengthening of Egypt’s defence forces, it is proposed to create a specialised industry in Egypt for the manufacture of military material. 11. Revenue for the coming financial year is estimated— £E. To be 38.843.000 As against (for the current financial year) ... 37,003,820&gt; &gt; If, however, account is taken of the fact that the national defence contribution at present in existence £s to be abolished, it will be seen that the total revenue co be raised in 1938- 39 shows an increase of £E. 2,939,180. which will be found— ME. (а) ^Ry new taxes ... ...' ... .... ... 1.000,000 (б) Normal increase in the yield of existing taxes 1,209,000 (c) Increases in actual scale of certain existing taxes ... ... ... ... ... ... 730,000 The principal individual source of increase is from customs duties, the yield of which shows a rise of £E. 1.192,200, but the note does not state whether this increase is anticipated as the result of a greater volume of imports, or whether increases are*contemplated in the existing customs and excise duties on certain classes of goods. Other notable increases which are budgeted for are the Govern ment’s share in limited liability companies, which has risen from £E. 330,660 this year to £E. 746,500 in 1938-39, an increase mainly derived from the sugar company, and a payment of £E. 300,000 by the Suez Canal Company instead of £E. 200.000 as hitherto. 12. Expenditure during the coming financial year is estimated to be £E. 40,932.000, as against £E. 36.992,820 during the present year, an increase of £E. 3,939,180. The rest of the note is devoted to a survey of the credits allocated to each Department, which it is not necessary to discuss in detail, but amongst the credits authorised it is interesting to observe that the sum of £E. 110,000 is earmarked for the Suez oil refinery in order to increase its productive capacity, whilst the export bounty on citrus fruits is maintained with a grant of £E. 24,000, and a sum of £E. 20,000 has been allocated to the encouragement of tourist traffic. 13. As was to be expected from Ismail Sidky Pasha, the note is an able document, and the new estimates have been drawn up in a spirit of financial orthodoxy and of fiscal moderation, but the strong undertone of economic nationalism is unmistakable, and if Sidky Pasha continues in office as Minister of Finance, it is to be expected that the investment of foreign capital in Egypt will be more strictly controlled, and. in certain directions, will be subordinated to Egyptian interests. 14. It will be all to the good if Sidky Pasha and his successors recognise in principle that the Egyptian Civil Service should be placed on a non-political basis, specially desirable in view of the relative incompetence and lack of business experience of the average Egyptian Cabinet Minister. It is unfortunately unlikely that these aspirations will do more than to counteract to some extent a growing tendency in the reverse direction. 15. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, &amp;c. (For the Ambassador), D. V. KELLY.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOYERNMENT May 11, 1938. Section 1. [J 1925/42/16] Copy No. f ,- Sir M. Lampson to Viscount Halifax. — (Received May 11.) (No. 491.) My Lord, Cairo, May 2, 1938. I HAVE the honour to enclose herein an important document which was communicated to this Embassy on the 4th April by the Minister of Finance,(') and which embodies the first attempt made by the Egyptian Government to meet the cost of putting the country’s defences on a sounder footing than they are at present. The additional revenue required is to he obtained from three new taxes— a tax on income derived from property other than realty (“ movable property ”), stamp tax and inheritance tax. 2. The enclosure consists of the following elements :— (a) A letter of the 23rd March, 1938, from the chairman of the Fiscal Commission to the Minister of Finance (pp. 1-3). (b) A speech by the Minister of Finance to the Fiscal Commission on the 4th January, 1938 (pp. 7-10). (c) A note of the 15th January, 1938, laid before the Council of Ministers by the Minister of Finance (pp. 11-22). (d) An extract from pp. 20-21 of the note of the 25th March, 1938, to the Council of Ministers on the 1938-39 budget (pp. 23-25). (e) A note of the 8th February, 1938, by the chairman of the Fiscal Commission, on the draft Movable Property Income Tax Law (pp. 31-68). (/) A complementary note on the same subject by the chairman of the Fiscal Commission (pp. 69-75). (g) Draft Movable Property Income Tax Law (pp. 74-94). (h) Explanatory note by a member of the Fiscal Commission on the draft Stamp Tax Law (pp. 97-100). (i) Draft Stamp Tax Law (pp. 101-119). (j) Explanatory note by the chairman of the Fiscal Commission on the draft Inheritance Tax Law (pp. 123-127). (k) Draft Inheritance Tax Law (pp. 128-142). These documents reveal the care with which the Ministry of Finance have studied the means, as represented by the three new revenue-producing laws mentioned above, of providing fresh revenue to meet the enhanced cost of the defence of Egypt. 3. In his speech of the 4th January to the Fiscal Commission, the Minister of Finance, in summarily reviewing the need for increased revenues to the extent of some £E. 4 million annually to meet the higher cost of defence, drew attention to the uneven incidence of Egyptian taxation, which, whilst reaching many through the land tax, none the less failed to touch many others, and imposed on some a burden heavier than they should bear and on others too light a load. Thus, developing this thesis, he stressed the need for a tax which would take toll of capital or movable property (which, he observed, incidentally, had trespassed considerably on the domain of real property in the form of mortgages or long-term loans) and pointed the way to taxation of income not directly derived from land— a modified form, in short, of income tax. Ismail Sidky Pasha next confessed himself strongly in favour of an inheritance tax, observing that this was a form of taxation which should already have been in existence long ago, and showed a wise appreciation of practical difficulties, at the same time condemning certain dispositions (which clearly were present in the draft law at an earlier moment) whereby retroactive force was to have been given to the tax. His Excellency next alluded to the “ Patente ” Law, which has been in draft form for some time. (*) EGYPT AND SUDAN CONFIDENTIAL. 7,COO | v,.&gt; \ J v w L . 2 -ii- (*) Xot printed.expressing his dislike of it and his hope that the commission would delay the introduction of this measure as long as possible or else embody it in some tax. He wished to avoid imposts of vexatious or inquisitorial character. He also warned the commission against a tax on loans, as this would fall on banks, which would already be taxed under the projected impost on movable wealth. A point, he concluded in this connexion, which had given him much preoccupation was the method whereby to touch the income derived from movable property and accruing to companies “ en nom colleetif ” or of other constitution without limitation of liability, and to private persons, merchants and manufacturers. 4. In his note of the 15th January to the Council of Ministers (pp. 11-22 of the enclosure) Sidky Pasha outlines with succinctness and lucidity Egypt’s fiscal system as evolved under the influence of the capitulatory system, and describes the trend which its future development in an independent Egypt should follow on the dual bases of equal taxation for all and restraint in the imposition of new taxes. His Excellency foreshadows the eventual need for the introduction of a general income tax, but observes that this should be the last and crowning work of the fiscal edifice, not being brought forward until— (а) The population has been familiarised with the other and simpler taxes which it is proposed to place on the Statute Book. (б) The real need for the revenue derivable therefrom has arisen. 5. To meet the new calls on the budget Sidky Pasha advocates the immediate adoption of a tax on income derived from property other than realty, an inheritance tax and a stamp tax. 6. Examining the first of these proposed measures in some detail, the Finance Minister enumerates the various sources of movable property income as follows :— (1) Agricultural land. (2) House property. (3) Commercial profits. (4) Industrial profits. (5) Dividends accruing from stocks and shares. (6) Interest on loans. (7) Professional services. (8) Salaries, wages, allowances. Of these, only (1) and (2) at present paid a direct tax to the State, whilst under (8) the servants of the Crown paid a stamp duty, devised and so called under the capitulatory regime in order to impose what was in effect an earned income tax. In regard to (3), (4) and (7), the Ministry of Finance had in 1932 elaborated a law—-the ,£ Patent^.” Law—to tax these, which had elicited various emendatory recommendations by the Powers to whom it had been submitted for acceptance. The basis of taxation set up in this draft measure of 1932—rental values—had never appealed to the Ministry, and its choice was attributable to the capitulatory regime. This principle was, however, admissible in respect of (7) as being a method of taxing the business of professional men without intrusion into matters of professional secrecy. Regarding (5), it was only fair that, where earned income was taxed, unearned income should also bear its burden. Apprehensions that this would lead to the flight of capital from Egypt could be scouted, since the tax in Europe on unearned income was much heavier than what would be proposed for Egypt. The rate contemplated was 10 per cent., and this would only be attained after an interval of some years and starting from 5 per cent. The tax would also apply to (6), every precaution being taken to prevent the incidence of the tax being transferred from the lender to the debtor. Special measures would be taken to this end. The tax on earned income (8) should be lighter than that imposed on income from other sources, and the adoption of a sliding scale from 1 to 3 per cent, and exemption for small wage-earners is advocated. 7. The establishment of an inheritance tax is briefly recommended by Sidky Pasha with the comments that this is an impost easy of collection and unprovocative of hostility inasmuch as, whilst other taxes affect the product of the taxpayer’s own efforts or of his own property, this one merely affects property accruing to him without effort on his part. 8. Sidky Pasha’s allusion to the stamp tax is still more brief. It is a tax very generally in use, not onerous in its incidence, and productive of a not negligible revenue.9. I will now briefly review the outstanding features of the three draft laws. 10. Broadly speaking, the draft law creating a modified form of income tax submits the following to taxation :— (a) Income from investment (articles 1 to 5). (b) Income from money lent or deposited (articles 13 and 14). {c) Commercial and industrial profits (articles 27 to 34). (d) Earned income from salaries, &amp;c. (articles 62 and 63). (e) Earned income from fees (article 73). The tax (articles 6, 13 and 35) on (a), (b) and (c) is 10 per cent., but will be started at the 5 per cent, level in 1938 and 1939; thereafter it may be gradually raised (by simple decree, i.e., without reference to Parliament) to 10 per cent, by increases not exceeding 2 per cent, for a biennial period. The tax (article 64) on (d) is a graduated one and operates as follows :— (i) On incomes not exceeding £E. 60 : No tax. (ii) On incomes from £E. 61 to £E. 120 : 1 per cent. (iii) On incomes from £E. 121 to £E. 300 : 2 per cent. (iv) On incomes exceeding £E. 300 : 3 per cent. Finally, the tax (article 74) on (e) is based on the rental values of (a) the occupational and (b) the residential premises occupied by professional men, at the rate of 5 per cent, in each case, or of 10 per cent, where occupation and residence are carried on under one roof. For ease of reference, an index of the various sections of the draft law is enclosed herein. 11. Problems of interpretation may be expected to arise, amongst which a knotty one will be that of estimating what part of the capital of a foreign company a fraction only of whose activities take place in Egyptian territory (article 29) is to be assessed for Egyptian commercial profits tax. What part, for example, of the total capital of the Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Company (Limited), or of Barclay’s Bank (Dominion, Colonial and Overseas) (Limited), is to be considered as the appropriate counterpart of the business effected and profits earned in Egypt ? Companies are invited (article 4) to make an annual declaration to the revenue authorities indicating the amount of their profits during the financial year last past. Such declarations may be contested (article 43) by the revenue authorities and referred, if necessary, to the court of first instance sitting as a commercial court. A point of importance which falls to be noted regarding the taxation of joint-stock companies is that, whilst the drafters of the present law uphold the principle that the payment of a profits tax by a company provides no reason why income tax should not be paid on dividends received by its shareholders, it (the law) nevertheless allows the company (article 32) to deduct from the amount of profits tax due by it the amount of income tax deducted by it from the dividends due to its shareholders. Whether this dispensation will endure time alone will show. Pages 33 to 35, 56 and 51 of the principal enclosure to this despatch deal with this question. 12. Income tax is also due (article 5) by Egyptians or foreigners residing in Egypt on dividends derived from stocks and shares of foreign companies. It is admitted that difficulty will be experienced in preventing evasion of the tax on such dividends, but reliance is placed on the provisions (articles 11 and 12) imposing upon banks and credit establishments collecting such dividends the duty of withholding the amount of the tax and passing it to the revenue authorities. 13. It is to be noted that Egyptian income tax is due on interest derived from capital placed in Egypt even where the creditor has neither de jure nor de facto an Egyptian domicile (“ ni domicile de droit ni domicile de fait ) (article 13). 14. Certain exemptions (article 38) from payment of the profits tax are provided for. These are— (ft) Co-operative agricultural societies constituted under Law No. 23 of 1927. (5) Co-operative consumption societies whose activities are restricted to centralising members’ orders and delivering the commodities ordered at the members’ respective storage points. (c) All seats of learning and all associations whose object is other than the accumulation of wealth. [307 1-A] b 215. Private persons and partnership firms engaged in trade (article 39) pay no profits tax on the first £E. 100. • i 16. The case where commercial enterprises have made a loss instead oi a profit is provided for in article 56. French law has been followed in that the losses of one year may be carried forward to the profit and loss account of the ensuing year, and if a deficitory position is then still revealed, the same operation may he repeated up to a limit of three years as against the five allowed in b ranee. ^ 17. Unclaimed funds (articles 25-26) are to he forfeited to the State on completion of the period of prescription. This latter has, apparently, not yet been fixed; whilst the prescriptive period in the common law is fifteen years, the Fiscal Commission hesitated between five and ten years, and eventually left the point to the appreciation of the Government. 18. Turning to the draft Stamp Tax Law. the salient feature which strikes the reader is that, whilst the last preceding draft Bill went much further than its title would appear to justify (attributed, no doubt rightly, to the capitulatory regime), the present one adheres strictly to the lines associated with a stamp tax. Thus, broadly speaking, it will be applicable to— (a) Documents and registers of all kinds, whether Egyptian or foreign, including those in existence at the time of promulgation of the law should they figure in any kind of transaction after that date (articles 1 and 8). (b) Oral contracts recognised by law when invoked in court (article 2). (c) Advertisements of all kinds (article 3). The tax will be applied (article 4) by various means, such as stamped paper supplied by the State, adhesive stamps, apposition of a seal by a special office, apposition or affixing of a control plate, or any other means indicated by the regulations. It will be dimensional, graduated, proportional or special (article 5). The dimensional tax will apply to two sizes of paper. The graduated tax varies in accordance with certain features of the document subjected to a stamp due. The proportional tax has percentage for its base. The special taxes are those varying according to the nature of the document where neither the dimension of the paper nor a stated amount therein comes into play. 19. All documents upon which the proportional tax falls to be paid (article 9) must state the value of the agreed transaction which will serve as a basis for assessment of the tax. 20. The right of disclosure (article 12) is accorded to revenue officers against all businesses, bankers, merchants, commission agents, brokers, commercial agents, exchange agents, publicity agents, publishers and printers during the customary office hours and at the place of business for examination of all books, registers, securities and all other documents subjected by the law to stamp tax. 21. The dimensional tax (article 25) is applied to documents relating to personal status, arbitration, compromise, insurance, extracts from official archives, gifts, undertakings, extracts from commercial books, mandatory powers, divisions, annuities, petitions, articles of association of all companies, contracts of cession of profit deriving from property other than real, and sales. 22. Premiums on life, illness and bodily accident assurance pay a propor tional tax of half of 1 per cent, (article 26). Similarly, insurance premiums on transport by air, land or water are subjected to a 2 per' cent, tax (article 27) and to a stamp tax of 10 milliemes (article 39). On all other insurance premiums a proportional tax of 3 per cent, is due (article 28), whilst half of 1 per cent, is payable on the capital sum mentioned in annuities or, where no such mention is made, on an amount equivalent to ten times the annuity (article 29). 23. All banking transactions are subjected 'to a proportional tax of one-quarter of 1 per mille, with a minimum of 5 milliemes and a maximum of £E. 25 (article 30). 24. All Stock Exchange transactions give rise to a proportional tax. (r/) All shares and debentures already quoted on the Bourse at the date of promulgation of the Stamp Tax Law, or subsequently to be so quoted, will be subjected to a proportional tax of one-half of 1 per mille (article 31). This will 'be payable annually by the businesses, companies, communes, provinces or other collectivities whose shares or stock are quoted on the Bourse. Irregularities in regard to payment of this tax may lead to a request from the Ministry of Finance to the Bourse to cease quoting the securities affected. The tax is payable on the totalvalue of the securities, the value being determined by the average price during the six months immediately preceding the due date for payment of the tax. In the case of a security issued outside Egypt, the concern involved may submit proof that only a part of its capital circulates in Egypt, (b) All purchases or sales of Egyptian or foreign securities are subjected to a graduated tax running from a minimum of 25 milliemes on transactions between £E. 5 and £E. 100 to a maximum of £E. 10 on transactions exceeding £E. 20,000, which is due by both seller and buyer (article 32). (c) All sales of securities not quoted on the Bourse pay a proportional tax of half of 1 pei* cent, of the sale price (article 33) and a stamp tax of 10 milliemes (article 41). Nevertheless, if the company or corporation concerned elects to pay, and regularly pays, the proportional tax alluded to at (a) above, the two dues just described will be dropped in favour of that mentioned at (b). (d) All “ future ’ ’ operations in the Commodities Bourse must be confirmed by a note of contract issued by the Bourse Commission. Such contracts in respect of raw cotton or cotton seed give rise to a stamp tax of 1 millieme per cantar of cotton or ardeb of seed (article 34). 25. A 5-milliemes stamp tax will be payable on various documents, including, inter alia, crossed or uncrossed cheques, travellers’ cheques, circular letters, instructions to banks to transfer funds, bank statements of account involving calculation of interest due, dividend warrants, and receipts for more than FT. 50 (article 37). Similarly, a 10-milliemes stamp tax will be payable on certain mercantile marine documents (article 40), permits, declarations and authorisations delivered by the police or other administrative authority, weighing certificates, sales of securities not quoted on the Bourse (article 41). A 20-milliemes stamp tax will be due on warrants (article 42); one of 30 milliemes on leases, cessions of lease, renewals of lease, certificates of the “easier judiciaire,” certificates delivered by Chambers of Commerce, legal announce ments (article 43); one of 50 milliemes on endorsements of commercial bills if on a separate paper, letters of guarantee, surety bonds (article 44), consumers’ agreements for supply of gas, electric light or water, and hire of instruments or meters (article 45). Various other more specialised cases of the stamp tax are given in articles 46 to 51. 26. Advertisements and handbills by others than public authorities pay (with certain exceptions) a tax varying according to the size and the method employed (articles 52 to 63). To take a few examples, printed notices and hand bills on ordinary paper pay'half a millieme per 25 square decimetres or fraction thereof; notices inserted in the programmes of places of entertainment pay FT. 5 weekly, luminous signs pay FT. 8 per square metre or fraction thereof for the first year, and half-rate in succeeding years. All notices describing a shop, business or industry are exempted from advertisement tax. 27. Articles 64 to 77 set forth various forms of incidence of the stamp tax on contracts of transport. Thus, to take a few examples, all waybills in respect of sums of FT. 20 or more are subjected to a special tax of FT. 3 and a propor tional tax of 3 per cent, of the price of transport (article 64); railway, tram, omnibus and aeroplane excess luggage bills of FT. 20 or more, payable by passengers, pay a proportional tax of 10 per cent, (article 65); a stamp tax of FT. 20, 10 or 5 is payable on all sea-travel tickets of first, second or third class respectively. 28. There remains the Inheritance Tax Law, which is the third Bill in the trilogy of revenue-producing acts laid before the Council of Ministers by the Minister of Finance. In a short preamble (see (j) of paragraph 2 above), the chairman of the Fiscal Commission discussed the various methods employed by different States (particularly Great Britain and France) to tax property at the moment of its passing on the death of its owner to the heirs, and defines the system adopted in the present draft Bill, which is to make the incidence of the tax depend on two factors : (a) the amount of the property inherited by an heir; and (b) the degree of relationship between an heir and the de cujus. Attention is drawn to the alleged fact that the arrangement whereby agricultural land shall be valued at sixty times the annual tax (article 36) clearly favours heirs, a provision which has been thus cast for economic and psychological reasons, and to the further fact that the attitude of English law has been followed in regard to estates which have already been subjected to death duties within three years of a further death involving another change of ownership (article 17), the dues in this case being halved.71 6 0 29. Offspring, ascendants of the first degree, and their partners (husband or wife) of a deceased person pay inheritance tax on their individual shares at the following rates (article 1) : — Per cent. From £E. 101 to £E. 2,000 3i From £E. 2,001 to £E. 5.000 5 From £E. 5,001 to £E. 20,000 * From £E. 20,001 to £E. 50,000 10 Above £E. 50.000 ... ... ... ... ... ... 12^ Small estates not exceeding £E. 100 in value pay no tax; in the case of larger estates the first £17. 100 is free of tax. 30. The above rates are (i) doubled in the case of (a) ascendants beyond the first degree and (b) brothers and sisters; (ii) tripled in the case of (a) nephews and (b) other collaterals to the fourth degree inclusive; (iii) quadrupled in the case of all other heirs (article 1). The inheritance tax is halved in respect of all property which the de cujus has himself or herself acquired by inheritance within the three years immediately preceding his or her death (article 17). 31. The tax is applicable (article 2) to— ■ (1) All property or rights of inheritance in Egypt or abroad left by a person of Egyptian nationality wheresoever resident. (2) All property or rights of inheritance in Egypt or abroad left by a person of non-Egyptian nationality having, or having had, one year before his or her death, either de jure or de facto, an Egyptian domicile ( i£ domicile de droit on de fait ”). (3) All property or rights of inheritance in Egypt left by anyone of non- Egyptian nationality having no residence,' nor residing in, Egypt, or who, having had such residence, had ceased to have it for more than a year before his or her decease. 32. Valuation of estates (article 36) is to be effected on the following lines :— (a) Agricultural lands : sixty times the annual tax. (b) Built property paying the built property tax: fifteen times the rental value having served to fix the tax. (c) Egyptian and foreign securities quoted on an Egyptian Bourse; the average price quoted on the Bourse on the date of decease, or, in the absence of a quotation on that day, the average price on the last day of quotation. (d) Life interest and bare ownership are to be valued respectively as follows :— (i) if the beneficiary is 20 years of age or less, the life interest is estimated at seven-tenths, and the bare ownership at three-tenths, of the total property; (ii) if the beneficiary is over 20, the value of the life interest is diminished by one-tenth of the value of the whole property, and the value of the bare ownership is increased by the same amount, in respect of each period of ten years. If the beneficiary is over 70, the proportion is fixed at one-tenth for the life interest and nine-tenths for the bare ownership. (e) £C Wakf ' interests are to be calculated on the same basis as life interests. (“ Wakf ” = “ pious endowment.”) (/) In regard to a ground rent and to lands encumbered by a ground rent, the respective values are to be estimated at one-third of the value of the whole property to the owner of the land thus encumbered and at two-thirds to the ground rent. 33. A taxpayer dissatisfied (article 38) with the amount of the tax assessed against him oi* her by the ad hoc commission of the revenue authorities (article 37) has a right of appeal within a period of three months to the courts of first instance. Where the amount of tax assessed by the court is lower than the amount claimed by the commission, the Treasury shall return the difference to the taxpayer. No mention is made of the judicial costs involved, which one might expect to see7 ♦ laid at the door of the State where the taxpayer has succeeded in securing a lowering of the assessment. No mention is made of appeal from the court of first instance. 34. Time may show that the three draft fiscal laws examined in the preceding paragraphs require amendment or recasting at various points, and their application will no doubt give rise to considerable difficulties in the early A years, but the impression which I gather from a first perusal of these Bills is, prima facie, one of congratulation for the Egyptian Government, who seem, thanks to the capable and constructive leadership of Ismail Sidky Pasha, to have made a sound and commendable initial effort to create new sources of revenue sufficient, one may hope, to meet increasing State expenditure. It is not hoped to collect more than £E. 1 million from the new taxes this year, but it is expected that next year they will produce £E. 4 million of additional revenue. These estimates must necessarily be a matter of guess-work, and, if arrived at from conservative premises, may prove to be considerably below the mark. 35. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Governor-General of the Sudan and to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, &amp;c. MILES W. LAMPSON. Enclosure. Index of the Draft Egyptian Laic setting up a Tax on Income Derived from Property other than Realty. Book I .—Tax on Income Derived from Property other than Realty. Title I.—Movable property. Chapter I. Taxable income (articles 1-5). Chapter II. Rate of tax (article 6). Chapter III. Determination of taxable income (article 7). Chapter IV. Recovery of tax (articles 8-12). Title II.—Debts, deposits and sureties. Chapter I. Incidence and rate of tax (articles 13-14) Chapter II. Determination of taxable quantum (articles lo-lb). Chapter III. Recovery of tax (articles'!7-24). Title III. Forfeiture to the State of unclaimed funds after prescription (articles 25-26). Book II—Tax on Commercial and Industrial Profits. Chapter I. Taxable businesses (articles 27-34). Chapter II. Rate of tax (article 35). Chapter III. Taxable profits (articles 36-37). Chapter IV. Exemptions (articles 38-39). Chapter V. Determination of taxable pronts Section I. Companies limited by shares (articles 40-46). Spction II Companies other than companies limited by shaies, and private persons (articles 47-55). Section III. Provisions common to all businesses (articles 56-61). Book III .—on Earned Income. Title I—Salaries, wages, allowances and pensions. Chapter I. Incidence of the tax (article 62). Chapter II. Determination of taxable quantum Chapter III. Rate of tax (article 64). (article 63).S ^ Chapter IV. Declarations— Section I. Declarations by employers (articles 65-68). Section II. Declarations by earners of salaries, wages, pensions and annuities (article 69). Chapter V. Recovery of tax (articles 70-72). Title II.—Profits of non-commercial professions (articles 73-78). Book IV .—General Provisions. Chapter I. Chapter II. Chapter III. Right of disclosure and professional secrets (articles 79-85). Sanctions (articles 86-87). Other provisions (articles 88-95).COPY 465/1/38. (J 2192/42/16) BRITISH EMBASSY, CAIRO. 16th May, 1938. Dear Bill, In paragraph 32 (f) of my despatch No. 491 of the 2nd May, 1958, transmitting the text of three new draft fiscal laws, the words 'ground rent' were used as a translation of 'hekr'. On reconsideration of the matter I am not quite happy about this translation. 'Hekr' is a term applied to land owned by the Ministry of akfs (pious endowments) and leased to private individuals for building or other purposes. A clause in the contract stipulates that after a given period of time the Ministry of bakfs has the right to reclaim possession of the land and to demand the demolition of any buildings on it. Will you, therefore, be good enough to have the words 'ground rent' replaced by the words 'hekr right' in the three places where they occur in the paragraph in question. Yours &amp;c., (Signed) Miles W. Lampson. V. Cavendish-Bentinck, Lsq. , Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.Co.,/ of letter Il.’.turthe'11th ..ri^ 1938, fron the Chief Secretary fo_ tiie. Covemr.ent of ^ J Bombay, . olitical L Services Department, to tne Secretary to the Government of India, External ^fairs Department. Anniversary of His Hajesty King Farouq’s accession to the Throne. Ib/Lh I am directed to forward, for the information of the Central Government, a copy of a letter from the Consul for i ypt at ‘Bombay, dated, t .e 31st ' arch 193B, intimating that the 6th Hay of each year has been fi^d as the anniversary of T Hs Ha to the Throne. King Farouq T s accession Copy of a lette^irom the Consul for Bombay dated the Dtfit Harch 1938. I haBe the honour to inform you that the 6th Hay of each year has/been fixed as tne anniversary of His Majesty 'inf/Farouq. T s accession to the Throne. Availing myself of this opportunity, may I renew ■ r ou the assurances of my highest estim /tion and Bideration.\ r' / ' In any furtlier communication on this subject, please quote n°. £ 6 / f / ^ /3 / and address —not to any person by watn^/but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for compliments to C'Lc — m y -u~ * JL.J « ^ “7 9 o '-N presents his ’ the Secretai of the under-mentioned paper. an( ^’ b y direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Foreign Office, - 7 FEB , 193/. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. (?• If tiA 3 , : v *(8 FE&amp;i„ ^ ^073^1- Similar letter sent to 14 6130 15844(4)COPT m (r 6S?6/807/16) 290/4/37 BRITISH EMBASSY. CAI'0 # December 9th, 1937. Denr Ponnie, T enclose b copy of Bn interesting circular letter recently sent out by the Financial Secretary to Governors and Heads of Departments on the financial position of the Sudan* It unfortunately indicates the probability of a rather serious reversal during the coming year of the present satisfactory financial position of the Sudan Government* This is partly due to the heavy fall in cotton prices and partly to the prospect of a reduction in the Fgyptian Government’s annual subvention. It is particularly unfortunate that this should be occurring the very year before the Sudan Government can embark on their first conversion scheme. It is fortunate they have accumulated a large reserve fund. I have ascertained from the Sudan Government that they have no objection to your sending a copy of this letter to the Treasury if you thought fit. Yours &lt;*c., (Signed) Miles ^.Lampson. H.I. Campbell, Eso., ^.M.G., Foreign Office, S.^’.l.J FDK/177-16-4 Finamce Circular No, 42(1937) ^ SKCRF.T . FINANCIAL SECFKTARY*S OF* to KHAT?TOT% 22nd November, 1937. 1938 BUTaIET- The 193R Budget proposals have only just 'been received by the Finance Department but I am writing no\~ to give you advance information as to the general considerations which must govern our financial management during the coming year. This procedure is abnormal but will, I hope, prove to be helpful. It is, as I shall explain further on, prompted by interesting, aonorms1 and, in some important respects unique, features of tne present financial situation. (a) Taking first the revenue side of the account, we must be prepared for an exceptionally heavy fall in receipts from cotton which will affect directly the budgets of the Irrigation and Agricultural and Forest© Departments. Owing to the high-record American crop now being gathered the value of this fto us) all-important commodity has fallen some 30 and neither the statistical position of cotton nor the trend of world consumption indicates that there will be any substantial recovery of price in the near future. On the: contrary, with world stocks at about 50 million bales and world annual consumption running at some 30 millions, it looks as though we must face a protracted period of low values, couuled possibly with some recession from the level of Sudan production attained in 1937. (b) M.S. Lush, Kao., M.C.(b) Another important head of revenue is the £E.750,000 Egyptian contribution which the Sudan Government has received comfortably, quarterly and In cash for the past twelve years. The withdrawal or reduction of this contribution now rests in the sole discretion of the Egyptian Government ’’subject to fair notice'. At the introduction of the current Egyptian budget the continuance of the contribution was the subject of strong* and not unreasonable criticism. The subject has since been freely ventilated in the gyptian press and, the Tgyptian Government, confronted now with the aftermath of the Anglo- Egyptian Treaty in the form of a heavy bill for re-armament, is considering the question of an early reduction - as opposed to a total withdrawal of the contribution. There are no grounds for assuming that the present Egyptian Government will act harshly or brusquely in this matter but a serious loss of revenue from this source is a contingent possibility which must be kept constantly in mind. The subject is still suh-judice in Egypt. All that I can say at this stage is that it appears highly probable that this contribution will be cut to the extent of at least £E.250,000 per annum and at most £F.375,000 per annum in the next Egyptian Budget, which starts next May. (c) Sugar. This is one of our most lucrative revenue sources. -orld prices have advanced over £2 per ton and, on a current turnover of a little over 30,000 tons per annum, we- must accept a fall in receipts of about ££.70,000 and we must in the latterIsttc?* months of’ 1938^ be pr*eT)fi 7 , «&gt;rl To^ a eontraotion of consumption with its additional loss of revenue, (d: Customs. This form of indirect taxation wilj, in the absence of variations of the tariff, folio- the trend of sugar receiptfi. The record volume of exports in 1937 should it suffioient impetus to maintain receipts during the early months of 193f, hut the fall in cotton values mst he expected to bear adversely on both of these revenue producers during th; latter half of the year, * ve.. Railways, Coming to the largest revenue- earning Department of the Government it is satisfactory to record that there should be no difficulty in obtaining the contribution repul red for the Government Budget, in spite of the heavy additional expenditure which will arise from the Increase in price of materials such se steel and coal (including th&gt; higher cost of of ocean freight), (f) Other Heads of revenue. On balance thea; may be expected to '»ome out about £”.129,000 on the plus side. Direct taxation should produce an additional £15.20,000 and Interest rnd Business Profits Tax an extra £E.100,000. Increases and Decreases in revenue from Posts and Telegraphs, Public Works Department, Medical, Veterinary, Surveys, Legal, Education, Stores etc., will probably cancel themselves out.(g) Total 1’evenue* Taken by and large the net fall In revenue as between 193? and 193P may be anything between £ T :, 1,000,000 and £1,500,000, and you will appreciate that a revenue contraction of this magnitude is a serious matter for a budget of £: .4,600,000* 3. Taking the expenditure side of the Budget it must be borne in mind that in 1937 we are spending some £'.760,000 more than we spent in 1933, the year when retrenchment forced expenditure down to its lowest level. The 1938 expenditure proposals as submitted (i.e. prior to scrutiny by the Finance Department) are no less than £K.488,000 in excess of the total 1937 budget vote. They include nothing in respect of barracks for Egyptian troops: an exceptional liability for which the estimates of cost are not yet available. Of this £&gt;.488,000 a sum of £8.382,000 is in resoect of 'extraordinary* expenditure for whi^h the total demands amount to £F. 8 &amp;q, 000 . In all three chapters of the budget there are demands which are unavoidable and which must be met. For example the Personnel Chapter will require provision for normal increases of pay, the Services chapter will have to cover the rise in the pensions charge, and in the Extraordinary chapter provision must be found for re-votes which, owing partly to delay in deliveries of imported materials and partly to the priority which has had to be given to urgent work on aerodromes and military barracks, are expected to amount to some £E*170,000* 4. The total demands for 1938 (exclusive of anything for Egyptian barracks) amount to £E.8,032,000. Assuming as at this stage I must, that the Egyptian contribution will next May be cut by £E.260,000, the present 1938 revenue estimateestimate will be reduced to iT .4,674,000, leaving a gap to be bridged amounting to £E*368,000* The above figures show that our financial prospects are, owing mainly to the fall in cotton values and the contingent reduction of the Egyptian contribution, substantially less promising than they were a year ago* we shall get less for what we sell, and pay more for what we buy. Tn suite of the fact that we are drawing to the close of the moot favourable financial year the Sudan Government has ever had the good fortune to experience, the time has come, not for retrenchment, but for a judicious application of the brake on expenditure. 5* It may perlieps be asked whether this is not a proper time to utilise the protective and equalising reserve we have built up during the past few years? This brings me to the final and most important point I have to make. In previous notes on the financial position I have from time to time referred to the Sudan Government’s option to repay in 1939 the outstanding balance, HE#6,100,000 odd, of the Guaranteed Loan, and to the necessity of making every effort to rid the country of the exceptionally onerous debt service attaching to that Issue. The method of repayment will be conditioned by the state of the money market at the time in question but it must be assumed that it will involve some measure of re—bor owing either in the form of a public issue of or a loan from the Government’s Bankers. In either cases it will be essential to exploit this option to the fullest advantage of the taxpayer and to present a thoroughly credit-worthy picture of the Government’s financial position. At the present moment th^ picture is a good one. We can point to a sequence of five balanced budgets and to a powerful reserve position. OurOur finnnclal year 1938 is the last before the date of maturity of this invaluable option, the only one in our whole debt structure* The year 193S will therefore come into the picture and, should it brin^ with it a budget deficit the picture will be mined. It is for this reason in particular that the 1938 budget must be balanced without droving upon reserves, a practice which in any case and in any year can only be resorted to when every orthodox method of attaining equilibrium has proved inadequate* The bridging of a gap of 35%OX) will present certain difficulties but they are not insurmountable. Many desirable new services will, in consultation with Governors and Heads of Departments have to be eliminated from the estimates but, unless economic conditions deteriorate during 1939, it will I hope be a matter of postponement rather than abandonment. Having regard to the amount of re-votes carried over from 1937, the 1938 extraordinary expenditure chapter, the one which obviously will have to provide moat of the economies, will none the less keep the engineering departments fully occupied throughout the year. Our expenditure hsa advanced considerably during the past three years and a point has been reached where a pause, not T hone n protracted halt, is clearly indicated. And I would add that in any form of progress an occasional holt for stock-taking and breath-taking is no bod thing, 6. I have endeavoured to explain the position as clearly as possible, firstly because I have always held that there should be no mystery about our finances, and secondly because I know from experience that economies c?'n satisfactorily be effected only thx^ough the co-operation of Governors and heads of Departments.In gratefully acknowledging the fact that this co-operation has elwgys been promptly and unstintingly afforded T am confident that it will enable the Government to produce a soundly balanced budget for 1938. (Signed) F.D. Hugmsru FTFMTST a, SFCFFTAHY. P.S. This letter la marked secret because it includes references to the I'gyptirn contribution. The rrct of Ite contents is non-confident Addressed to ; - All Governors and Heads of Departments1 ■ mm'ioverrtifeer &lt;.&gt;i 0» *v ! ‘&gt;. Co: • '•-:r v . ..:a rtland, Onion of Sonth Africa an. Irel .*-nti ■ o&amp;x / « (f e r* t 10 p * n * 2 91 h I'C c c : m 9er, 11.-o /) Circular telegrara 9 No.lSS^ Confidential, The foil owing ncasage for the wine Mini : *« r ^ 3e gi ns: - &amp;y telegram Circular B of December 3rd ilo., 14 4 2 0 His Majesty’s Ambassador at Cairo 9 in pursuance of his instructions ? has been using his good offices as a friend of both parties and representative of an allied country with a view to inducing Egyptian Prime Minister to broaden the basis of his Cabinet by the entry into it of Ahmed Maher, the President of the Chamber but bo far by Ahmed Maher’s refusal to join the Cabinet, Sir Miles Lampson's efforts have been frustrated,, Attitude of Maher is probably due to his Knowledge that in the event of the dismissal or fall of Nr has Pasha he might well be King Parouk’s alternative choice as prime Minister, King Farouk has also been warned ,tn the gravest terms by his Majcsu,/ s Ambassador of the possible dangerous consenuenoes of dismissing' a Prime Minister who still coramands an overwheiming majority in Parliament, •fhe continued existence of the Blue Shirts , a para- ' military body which 7/as raised by the ‘#afd Party and is maintained by the present (tfafoiet) aoverndjent, i,« one of the greatest obstacle^ to reconciliation between the King and Hahas, Although King Farouk am demanded the diebaxidment of this body &lt;, his Prime Minister has not been willing to do more i\p to the present than to issue orders that the activities of&amp; hap&amp;l-iio &lt; ch'tnae tt? improve the eha/icts of in &gt;iue cjui’ee whe tiisbandinent of the ^ at ^ on * ^ certain number of the other obstacle©, &amp;~''h raire constitutional leeues of .^ome Importance. ..edaliKcly to ?^e eettied, while others, for the time being, may be ©helved* Concurrently with £ir Lampaon ^b action tijere has been contact between Jil f.ahcr Pasha, tl-.e chief oi the confidence with the » vir.e V inieter and act© a© liaison between Kahae Pasha and Sir ]■• hampBon) In an endeavour t© find a basis of agreement« Although this contact has not un&amp;lminished mutual auepicion of the principal© in the dispute. breach between Plug :• nrouK una Knhas I'seho would appear to be most px^obable, unl-ee-; n greater readiness to coaprumlHe is shewn by both sides. Message exids« been ervtirelj^ unfruitful, real progress is hindered by the •TV U . he ei t int ton thu© rej\ - .a ina uneasy and cm openI P. Z, 8425 J 19? 7 J PAHAPHRASE TELEGRAM CIRCiJLi\R To the Governments of Canada, Commonwealth of Australia, New Zealand, Union of South Africa and the Irish Free State (by bag). (Sent 10 p.m. , 29th December, 1937.) Circular telegram B Ro«153, Confidentialo The following message for the Prime Minister. Begins:-’ My telegram Circular B of December 3rd Kodi+SL His Majesty^ Ambassador at Cairo, in pursuance of his instructions, has been using his good offices as a friend of both parties and representative of an allied country with a view to inducing Egyptian Prime Minister to broaden the basis of his Cabinet by the entry into it of Ahmed Maher, the president of the Chamber, but so far by Ahmed Maher's refusal to ^oin the Cabinet, Sir Miles iiampson’e efforts have been frustrated. Attitude of Maher is probably due to his knowledge that in the event of the dismissal or fall of Nahas Pasha he might well be King Parouk’s alternative choice as Prime Minister. King Parouk has also been warned in the gravest terms by His Majesty’s Ambassador of the possible dangerous consequences of dismissing a Prime Minister who still commands an overwhelming majority in Parliament. The continued existence of the Blue shirts, a para-railitary body which was raised by the V/afd Party and is maintained by the present (v/afdiet) Government, is one of the greatest obstacles to reconciliation between the King and Nahas. Although King Parouk has demanded the disbandment of this body, up to the present other than issue orders that the activities of the Blue Shirts should be kept within harmless channels, his Prime Minister has not been willingwilling to do more. Th«j King hae 'been urged t&gt;y I^is Majeety^ Ambassador to regard Nahas pasha’s issue of even these orders as an effort at condliatlon, to profit by it to bring the quarrel with hahas to an end, and by so doing to improve the chances of securing in due course the disbandment of the organisation, A certain number of the other obstacles, which raise constitutional issues of some importance, seemlikely to be settled, while others, for the time being, may be shelved. Concurrently with Sir M. Lampson’s action there has been contact between All Paher Pasha, the Chief of the Royal Cabinet, and Amin Osman PrAsha (Under Secretary in the Ministry of Finance who occupies a position of special confidence with the Prime Minister and acts as liaison between Bahas Pasha and sir M. Lampson) in an endeavour to find a basis of agreement. Although this contact has not baeb entirely unfruitful, real progress is hindered by the undiminished mutual suspicion of the principals in the dispute* The situation thus remains uneasy and an open breach between King Farouk and Bahas Pasha would appear to be most probable, unless a greater readiness to compromise is shown by both sides. Message ends.P.Z, 7933 - /Q i • v PAK/'.' ®usb ciacui.Af msoa% 195 7 j To 0ove2Mrii'flSULt»B ojT C&amp;TiBQtXf %\ib 0 oKSiionwealuh ol Hew Zealand, the Union of South Africa* »nd the li^ish Free State (hy hag)» (Sent 4 pern, f 6rci Deceive1937.) Secret (f&amp;rcujBp Telegram 3^ Ho.X42» Following for Prime Minis teg preaident orthe Sxecutive council. Begins. Recently the relations between the King of Egypt and nahaa pasha, his prime Minister, hare become so embittered, largely owing to an utter incompatibility of temperament, that there is a danger of an open break between the two* His Majesty's Ambassador at Cairo has, by counsels of modera tion to both King Farouk end Ifahas pasha been doing his utmost to prevent such a breach, which, in the present disturbed state of general International relations, would be unfortunate and might have undesirable repercussions. Although these endeavours have had a b toadying effect* Sir Miles Lampson has serious misgivings that the break may come, and has re ones ted ins tt*uo 11 oas • THens instgiietions have now been sent- in the following sense* His Majesty 1 e Ambassador is to press Hahas pasha to broaden the basis of his Cabinet, and he is to urge Kihg Parouk to cooperate on this broadened basis with his present Government* Arguments such as the fact that his assurirfeaa of the support of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom have always been conditional on Ills Majesty's behaving constitutionally and wisely will also be at Sir Milos Lamp son*s disposal if necessary. Ends.MM THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT * &gt; EGYPT AND SUDAN. CONFIDENTIAL. R 5 1 August 23, 1937. Section 1. J 3662/20/16J Copy No. Mr. Kelly to Mr. Eden.—{Received August 23.) (No. 946.) Sir, Ramleh, August 12, 1937. I HAVE the honour to submit the following report on the series of festivities which have been held in Cairo and Alexandria on the occasion of His Majesty King Farouk’s coming of age. 2. His Majesty was accorded an enthusiastic welcome on his arrival at Alexandria on the 25th July. The steamship Nil, on which His Majesty travelled from Marseilles, arrived off Alexandria early in the morning and was met by a squadron of twelve aeroplanes of the Egyptian Army Air Force and by two coast guard ships, the Emir Farouk and the Emira Fawzieh, which fired a salute of twenty-one guns and escorted her into harbour. The Khedivial mail steamship Mohammed Ali-el-Kehir also joined the escort. The steamship Nil dropped anchor at 8 a.m., and a number of Egyptian notables, including the two Regents, some princes and nabils, the Prime Minister and Cabinet, went on board. Incidentally, the Prime Minister and his Cabinet, for the first time on record, were dressed in grey frock-coats, a sensible break in the tradition that had hitherto decreed the wearing of the conventional black so markedly unsuitable to the Egyptian summer. Shortly afterwards His Majesty proceeded by launch to Ras-el-Tin Palace quay, where His Majesty was met by Sir Miles Lampson and the Diplomatic Corps. 3. From the palace His Majesty drove through the decorated streets to the railway station and was given an ovation by large crowds. At the station there was yet another assembly of personages, including a number of ex-Prime Ministers, to greet His Majesty. It was noticed that His Majesty singled out Ali Maher Pasha, and informed him that he wished him to proceed immediately to Cairo. This incident was popularly held to confirm the belief that His Majesty is determined to keep in close touch with Ali Maher and ultimately to appoint him as his “chef de cabinet.' 4. As is usual on these occasions, the Royal train stopped at the main stations en route to Cairo to enable the assembled crowds to express their loyalty. At Cairo the train went direct to Koubbeh Palace station and His Majesty made no public appearance on that day. 5. On the 29th July the formal investiture of Farouk as King of Egypt was marked by a short and simple ceremony in Parliament, when His Majesty took the oath to the Constitution before the Senators and Deputies assembled in the Chamber. Accompanied by the Prime Minister, the King drove in the state coach, escorted by cavalry and mounted police, from Abdin Palace through crowded streets to the Parliament buildings. Preceding His Majesty’s coach in two other coaches were the Regents and palace officials. Queen Nazli and her daughters, the princes and nabils, all the chief dignitaries of State, the Diplomatic Corps and Egyptian and foreign notables filled the boxes and galleries of the Chamber. The Queen and Princesses occupied a special central box with boxes on either side filled by Egyptian ladies. 6. The Queen was warmly applauded on arrival, when the entire assembly arose and clapped their hands vigorously. Her Majesty left her box again shortly afterwards to watch the arrival of her son and, on her re-entry, Mme. Nahas, who was among the ladies in a neighbouring box, made herself, I am told, conspicuous by failing to rise from her chair—an unhappy but typical gesture of the Prime Minister’s “ helpmate.” 7. Otherwise the ceremony passed off without incident and, in spite of a heat-wave, in comparative comfort, thanks mainly to the recent installation of air-conditioning plant in the hitherto notoriously ill-ventilated Chamber. [82 z—1] 1078. King Farouk arrived punctually at 9 a.m., followed by the court officials and the Cabinet. Speeches were read by Xahas Pasha and by the President of the Senate, and His Majesty, who appeared quite self-possessed, then read the oath. His Majesty’s quiet and dignified bearing created a favourable impression. The ceremony terminated with prolonged applause. 9. Later in the morning His Majesty held his first levee at Abdin Palace, when a very large number of Egyptian and foreign notables were received. During the course of the levee the Minister of War, in the presence of senior officers of the army, presented King Farouk with a field-marshal s baton. 10. In the afternoon the Queen-Mother held a reception for ladies at Abdin Palace, and in the evening King Farouk made his first broadcast to the nation. A copy of His Majestv’s broadcast is enclosed. ' 11. The same night His Majesty entertained his Ministers and a number of leading foreign and Egyptian notabilities to a banquet at Abdin Palace. Some 1,500 guests were also invited to attend the subsequent soiree. 12. On the following day, Friday, His Majesty drove to El Rifai Mosque to say his prayers and to visit his father s tomb. His Majesty then entertained the ulema to lunch, and in the afternoon a large tea-party, to which some 5,000 guests were invited, was held in the palace grounds. In the evening the Prime Minister gave a banquet and a reception in His Majesty’s honour at Zafaaran Palace. 13. The celebrations in Cairo culminated in a military review, held at 7 -30 a.m. on the 31st July, when His Majesty reviewed his troops on the parade ground at Abbassieh. About 6,000 troops of all arms were on parade. The light tanks, field-guns and bridging equipment loaned by the British forces and the two newly-acquired howitzers provided tangible evidence of the incipient modernisa tion'of the army, and were well handled. Most impressive also, and most picturesque, was the trot past of the Camel Corps of the Frontiers Administration forces. The whole review was, indeed, a great success and a striking tribute to the untiring efforts of the head of the British military mission and his staff. 14. His Majesty left Cairo on the 5th August for Alexandria, where a further series of celebrations were held. On the afternoon of His Majesty’s arrival a reception was held at Ras-el-Tin Palace, to which all the notables of Alexandria were invited. In the evening His Majesty drove from Ras-el-Tin to Montaza Palace through brilliantly lit streets lined with dense crowds. On the following evening His Majesty attended a tatoo given by the Alexandria police in the Municipal Stadium. 15. On all these occasions manifestations of popular enthusiasm have marked His Majesty’s appearance in public. There can be little doubt that the young King has caught the popular fancy. The policy inspired by the palace entourage and by Ali Maher of showing the King to his subjects on every possible occasion^ aided/no doubt, by the King’s youthful and pleasant bearing, has borne fruit. The popular craving for hero-worship which brought such adulation to ZaMdul. and later to Zaghlul’s successor, appears to be finding a new outlet in the person of the young King, and in the process it would seem inevitable that the leaders of the Wafd must temporarily suffer some eclipse of the outward popularity which they have so long enjoyed. I have, &amp;c. D. V. KELLY. Enclosure. Extract from the Journal officiel du Gouvernement egyytien of August 1, 1937. Message de Sa Majeste le Roi a son Peuple bien-aime. Mon Peuple bien-aime, JE vous adresse mon salut le meilleur. Mon voeu eut ete de pouvoir serrer la main a chacun d’entre vous pour vous exprimer a tous ma profonde gratitude et mon immense affection, et vous dire combien j’apprecie I’amour sincere et le parfait loyalisme que vous m’avez manifestes. Je suis heureux, en assumant mes pouvoirs constitutionnels, de vous faire part de ma ferme resolution de respecter la constitution et les lois de la nation Igyptienne et de sauvegarder 1’independance de la patrie et Tintegrite de son</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000131_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2767</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000131</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2767</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 15/4 'Internal Affairs: financial situation'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-12T22:00:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (121 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 123; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence between ff 20-97.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and a booklet relating to the financial situation of the Egyptian Government and the process of fiscal reform.Included in the file is:a copy (ff 20-90) of the booklet 'Projet de reforme du regime fiscal' published by the Egyptian Government, Ministry of Finance, Fiscal Commissiona letter (ff 104-110) from the Financial Secretary of the Sudan Government on the impact of a reduction in subsidy by the Egyptian GovernmentThe file features the following principal correspondents: HM Ambassador to Egypt and the Sudan (Sir Miles Wedderburn Lampson); the Under-Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs; the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Viscount Halifax); and the Financial Secretary, Sudan Government.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Finance</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Financial Secretary</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Public services reform</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Dominions Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Egypt</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x000131#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>