<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ea_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T12:21:57.823Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. 1684*, dated Bushirey the 2nd June 1914. From—Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. With reference to the instructions conveyed in your telegram No. 248-S.*, dated 21st April, on the subject of jurisdiction over Hasawis, domiciled or resident in Bahrain, I have the honour to report that I duly communicated those instructions to Shaikh Isa of Bahrain and, at his request, addressed him in writing on the subject. 2. A copy of the written communication made to the Shaikh is enclosed for the information of the Government of India. No. 266, dated Bnshire, the 28th May 1914. From—Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To— Shaikh 'Isa bin 'Ali Al-i-Khalifeh, Ruler of Bahrain. After complements. At the friendly and pleasant interview of the 21st May 1914, when you were so good as to visit me on board R. I. M. S. “ Lawrence,” I mentioned the matter of Hasawis and who was to hold jurisdiction over them, and I informed you that the letter which the ’Amir had sent to you had been referred, as you already know, to Government, -who had the whole question, a very complicated one, under consideration. A case which occurred the other day when some Hasawis were punished * by: you was referred to me by Major Trevor, as he w as not anxious to make any declaration in a matter •which was under reference to Government. When the case came before me, I also considered that the directions of Government should be obtained. Temporary directions have now been received and are contained in Major Trevor’s letter to you, No. 525, dated 11th May 1914. As, however, you have asked me for those directions in writing, I repeat to you what I told you at the interview I have referred to above, and remind you that they are only temporary ^and that the final orders of Government on the subject will he sent later and will of course be communicated to you. The temporary orders received are as follows :—In the past, Najdis, Hasawis, Qatifis and others have been treated, when in Bahrain, as under the protec tion of the High Government and the Political Agent, Bahrain, has exercised jurisdiction over them. Pending the receipt of further instructions from the High Government, such persons are to continue to he treated in the future as in the past and cases in which they are concerned are to bo dealt with by the Political Agent, Bahrain, while the matter is still under consideration. (Usual ending.)CONFIDENTIAL. No. Cf. 164 , dated Bushire, the 22 nd (received 29 th)August 1914 . From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. With reference to correspondence ending with my No. 1684, dated 2nd June 1914, to your address regarding jurisdiction over Hasawis domiciled or resident in Bahrain, I have the honour to enclose the translation of a reminding letter received from Shaikh Isa on the subject. The communication has been duly forwarded through the Political Agent. Should Government approve, I propose to reply that, as Shaikh Isa pro bably knows, there are several important questions pending as a result of the outbreak of the war and it is inevitable that minor routine questions must come in for a certain amount of neglect. I have however, forwarded a copy of his letter to Government and no doubt orders will come in due course, when they will be communicated to him. Translation of a letter, dated the From— Shaikh Isa bin Ali Al Khalifah, C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain, To—M ajor S. G Knox, C.I.E., His Britannic Majesty’s Political Resident^autT^ Consul-General in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments, and enquiries after health, I have received your esteemed friendly letter No. 266, dated, Yst^Mayand understood about the question of the Hasavis and the person who has the right of jurisdiction over them. At the time of our pleasant meeting and friendly conversation when your honour had come here in “ Lawrence ” on 25th Jamadi al Akher 1332, you had informed me that the letter which was sent to me by the Amir had been submitted to the High Government, that those instructions were only temporary, that the final orders in this respect shall be sent afterwards and that the orders will be conveyed to me as soon as they come. In all circum stances I have confidence in the justice and good intentions of the Government and now again I repeat to your honour and hope from your kindness and good disposition to submit it from me to the High Government that I am not at all aiming at any other object in this matter and have no secret purpose. I request that neither you should entertain such an idea nor should the High Government that there is a deep meaning in this matter. All that there is, is that as the Amir deputed unto me the jurisdiction over his subjects I am naturally responsible for them to him and it is not proper and agreeable for my Government to be deprived of their rights in it. Besides your honour might understand on account of your high wisdom that that course would do harm to my Government politically as it will be counted as my descending from the Ruling capacity. I am certain that the Government would not like it and never entertain it. I always think that it is the High Government that upholds my Government and that they wish welfare and progress for my Government. And what harm does it do if the Amir be under the High Turkish Government and I do not enter with him into important political affairs that I do not approve of. It is nothing except the question of jurisdiction over subjects and that is one of the friendly matters that always take place between the Government. If the Amir rules over my subjects in his country, will he become under my Government ? No ! not so. Every one is independent in one’s own country and in the rule of one’s own territory. I have genuine hope that the High Govern ment will approve (of my request) when they know the real fact which no doubt you will submit to them from me. This is what had to be said and may you be preserved and- protected for ever. ,Ci 03 FD-' 44 —GCBP Simla.Confidan tial„ Docket Telegram. Prom Knox, P.R. Bushire. To Keyes, P.A. Bahrain. No. CP. 3 % Dated 10.14 For information. Resident's letter to Shaikh Isa No. j£f'. dated October 1914.Ho, zt.ki'd of 1914 British Residency &amp;. 3 on: : ulate-G&gt;eneral. f- Busliire, /2 c)ctober 1914. His Excellency, Shaikh * Isa bin *AU Ai Kh&amp;lifah, C. 3 .I Ruler of Bahrain, Bahrain. A.C. Your friend has received and read attentively t*Ihb representation Your Ex- i&gt; dat»ed 1/oh Ramzan 13 I oellency 10th August 1914. { — lyas good enough to forward through the Political Agent, regarding .jurisdiction over Hass- avis resident in Bahrain. It has also been forwarded for consideration to tte High aovemrcent, but Your Excellency must be aware that there are several important questions pending as a result of the out break of War, and it is inevitable that minor routine questions must come in for a certain am ount of neglect • Ho r ever no doubt orders will come in cue course, when they vrill immediately be ocaamunioat- od to Your Excellency. s (ScO &amp;■ f. T . , . L i cut —C ol onel Offgj Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL, Docket Telegram. From - Knox, Resident, Bushire. To - Keyes, P.A., Bahrain. D • 0 • • Dated J -10-14. I am sending you officially reply approved by Foreign, to Shaikh Isa’s representation regarding juris diction over Hassawis. Please explain to him at the same time that there is no question of his or Ibn Baud’s con templating any deep political move in this matter but there are important political considerations involved in any change of the status quo. The recent excellent reports I have received from yourself of Shaikh Isa’s admirable cooperation with yourself for the welfare of Bahrain in cline me personally to give the most sympathetic conside ration to his wishes in this matter but please ask him not to worry us just now with these trifles. The whole political situation of Al Ahsa is in a state of flux and Government cannot reply at this moment. Incidentally, why Shaikh Isa should desire to burden himself with the weari some squabbles and disputes of the Bahrain Hassawis passes my comprehension. i rf ■ / / !n Extract from Newa datai. 25th January 1217. 22. The Amir one night arreatod one Najdie named Ahu Daher of Kharj and irrroriaoned him. The next morning he took him to Shaikh.’laa. This man had been deported bv Shaikh ’laa 2D veara ago for stealing in the Amara of Shaikh Majbel. Shaikh ’Taa then wanted to cut hia hand, but Shaikh Khalid having inter vened Shaikh Mejbel nardoned him. Therefore he waa onlv deported. Owl A-b*. * ^1 ^ ^ lx ^ I flit 9 lex• 'T' Telegram,R. Prom Loch Bahrain To Trevor Bushlre No. 16 C. Dated 15.?.17 ^ Your confidential 324 October Qth 1014. isH'jn Question of jurisdiction over Has vis again raised. Shai&amp;h personally ordered ffiik detention of boat belonging to Hasawi by seizure of rudder. Shailth is inclined to fee obstinate .Should De glad to knovv if orders from Government of India may be expected.until jfurther instructions frortr -t^s ' * Hiprh (rovornment had been received, such 4 I ^ / peraona were to continue to be treated in tbe future aa in* tb© paat, and that, while the matter waa finder consideration, their canes were to be dealt with bv the Political Airent at Pahraln* Subaequentd ;, A't&gt;fo ^ftlltioai ^eeident informed r our Kxcellenov that the lettere which had passed between vou on this *■'' 1/ subject had been fomvarded to the * T irh Government for their oonsideratlort,' but that owin^ to the ’'ar there was sure to be delay in dealing with such a question/ ’our Excellencv no doubt realises that at the present time when war is . being waged all over the world, the High Government have much very urgent work to do in regard to the war, and that consideration of the majority of questions not closelv connected with the l \ #• War has to be postroned or dealt with slowly. I myself worked in Simla and Delhi from the outbreak of the war till I came here, and can assure ^our Excel lency that the Officers of the High Government have hut little leisure from the problems and resnonsibilities of war. ’ . , V* «./- 5 V From xr our Excellency's knowledge of statecraft it will be apparent to our Excellency that any question such f as a change of jurisdiction needs.full A and careful consideration. I feel sure our Excellency will agree with.me in thinking that it would be easier to devote time to . the consider-tion of such3uch natter af1&gt;e«^the v/ar • f J od b6 jwillinr* been brought to a oucoeosful oonolunion, and I nereonallv venture to think that/the Hip*h Govern- mpnt would anpreciat^ the noatnonenent of this queetion till then. .At the* sane tine I will not fail to brinp' t^e • • v I contents of v our Kxcellenov’s letter to the notice of the hobble the Resident and enquire whether^ it hao beep posilfaje 0 to oonnider the question* • * ^ ' \ \ I must, however, request that until the receipt of new instructions nothin* be done to alter the statue quo. An regarda ’Abdullah bln Sa'ad I have not, ae our Excellency eays x en- quired Into hie case, but, an you are aware, I 4' always willing to make full enquiries and obtain reparation in any case which is pronerlv brought to mv notice, ’'hen I was visitin^ v our Ewcel- «• « lency’s son, Shaikh 'Abdullah, vesterdav , J I understood that the claim against 'Abdullah bin Sa'ad amounted to F.tfoo/-; ♦ I am &lt;^rd^rip* the man .to yive security * that he will anpear before me toporrow and bey that otfr ^xcellenov will yive instructions.for the immediate return of the rudder of the boat. 'If Yoijr Excel lency will Mndlv send the plaintiff to the Court tomorrow morninr T will deal with the^ane a“t once. ’hat is what had to be said may you be preserved and salaams. Captain, n olitical Avent, Bahrain. OwvC ^ uvir /Vo.*Telegram.R. From Trevor Bushire % To Lock Bahrain No. £300 Dated 16.2.17 Reed 17.2.17 % Your telegram No. 16 G. Nothing received from the Government of India who have made no sign m the matter from the first. Am asking Sir P.Cox of whether from his recollectlon/attitude of Foreign Department he thinks it likely that they .1H make any pronouncement on the subject.Telegram.R. Tremor Bushire Loch Bahrain 324 Dated 13.2.1? Reed.19.2.17 (9.00) I-'y telegramNo.300. Political Resident considers it is no use asking G-overnment of India to issue orders in the matter nh'. T , and thi if you can Without undue inconvenience or weakening your ' position burk issue for period of war , it r ill be coi^nient otherwise you should be guided by the following Begins. Since question was last agitated (raised ?) position has changed , suzerain foreign power^ Turkey has been eliminated and inderjendenfce of Bin Sa'ud recognised. Latter nas also become ally ( fully a re bound ? we are fully bound) to see that interests, of his subjects are. safeguarded. Tnen question was last discussed Shaikh ’Isa (band ? himself) said and I m think wrote that he had reciprocal agreements with sever. 1 Arab Chiefs regarding adherence to protection of subjects. If he has such an agreement v/ith Bin' oa’ud will he kindly say so and produce it . If he had not we will ask Bin 3a’ud what his own wishes are. In any case -e must reserve right as in all % cases in our intervention in case of serious miscarriage of justice Bnds. If Shaikh ’Isa produces agreement you should * telegraph.Please see your demi-official letter of December 18th,1916, regarding Salyid Sadiq Hassan. If the Order in Council is to be brought into force on August 2nd ,1917, I should like to hare him here ee scon as possible • There are obylous reasons, but I have another to urge - I want to get the vernacular office into order before launching out on such a venture* For some months I have been s/orking with Iiltraa ’Abdul Husain helped by the daftri , as up to the present I have not boon able to get a second vernacular clerk, though I hope to soon* The former is, I think, doing his best as he had a fright, but ae head of an office is futile. Keeping the place straight is a Job like the Augean stable of old ! A second point is about Hasawis and other Arabs with whose rulers ^l^l^/Shaiiih ^sa claims to have agreements. In the recent rudder case I thought it unlikely that Crovemment would have considered the question , and as X had to write at once to get the rudder returned , I sent uhe dhaikli a letter tolling him that Government Trere busy with war ;ork etc.etc* which pacified him for the moment. The matter touches his dignity (in which I certainly sympathise with him) and I have no doubt that as soon as we broach the Order in Council he will re-open the question. Though I have not been able to study the matter sufficiently to put forward an official opinion, it seems to me the moment would be propitious for a graceful surrender of our Jurlsdict3on , keeping only a right of intervention in an extremity of injustice, thereby ridding ourselves of an ever present cause of friction and , incid entally^ a good deal of petty litigation. It would also help wonderfully in smoothing over the khidmah question. Of course there are other sides to the question , but as I said above it is «ure to be raised and giving then will be giving twice. Do you think anything of the sort is possible, otherwteit might be politic to postpone the Order still longer ? On the other hand I venture to think it would be well to get the order going while evBjryone la thinking of other things. Yours Sincerely, Major A*P.Trevor C.I.Ee Bushire « . i/■&gt; H.M. AGENCY, BAHRAIN. NO MINUTES TO BE WRITTEN HERE See also File LAST Year’s INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. No. IOR 7 / NEXT Year’s File No.:. INDIA OFFICE RECORDS MICROFILM Date Name Process No. of exposures 1 fa-to'St 7 2 0 3 4 5 6 REFER.TO THE SPECIALIST CONCERNED Wt. 26427 D4I5 5m 10/50 TCP/JR /3</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ea_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/11</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ea</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/11</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File A/15 Jurisdiction over Hasawis'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-20T10:56:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (18 folios)</extent><extent>The contents of the file are arranged in approximate chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file is foliated from the front cover to the inside back cover using pencil numbers in the top-right corner of each recto. The following foliation anomalies occur: 1a. Folio 10 is missing, as a result of the verso of folio 9 being labelled 10.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The correspondence in the file relates to the question of jurisdiction over Hasawis living in Bahrain, and is raised by specific incidents occurring in 1914 and 1917 in which Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah, chief of Bahrain, ruled on the measures to be taken against certain Hasawis for their debts or indiscretions. The correspondence is chiefly between the Bahrain Political Agent (Captain Terence Keyes in 1914, Captain Percy Loch in 1917), the Political Resident (Major Stuart Knox in 1914; Major Arthur Trevor in 1917), and Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah.In a letter dated 28 May 1914, Knox wrote to Shaikh ‘Īsá to state that the Hasawis, when in Bahrain, come under the protection and jurisdiction of the Political Agent (folio 1a). However, a further incident in 1917, in which Shaikh ‘Īsá authorised the removal of a rudder from a boat belonging to an Haswai in Bahrain, led to further correspondence from the Political Agent (Loch), restating that Hasawis, and well as Najdis and Qatifis in Bahrain, come under the protection of the High Government and Political Agent (folios 13-15).The file’s cover appears to be a later addition to the file, because it was in use in 1952 as the cover to another file (number 13/12) entitled ‘Ministry and Civil Aviation, Bahrain - Civil Aerodrome Circulars’. These details appear on the inside back cover of the existing file, as a result of the 1952 cover being turned inside-out to be used as a new cover for the older (1914-1917) file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002ea#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>