<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T04:53:39.818Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Collection No Pros. Serial. Nos. n Subject. i Interview of the LI embers of the a! Knalifah Family with the Political A^^nt,Bahrain. -^4 Previous Reterences. Later References.Translation of a letter dated 30th,Muharram 1352(25/5/33) from Khalifah bin Hamad A1 Khalifah, to Lieut-Colonel Loch, Political Agent,Bahrain. After Compliments, I beg to state that to-day I have come to your place (Agency)but unfortunately I did not get an interview with you. I have some work which I want to tell you. I wanted to come to you at Bushire but before doing so, I consulted Shaikh Hamad in the matter and he advised me to wait till your return. Since it is customary that when I have work or some talk I ask you for an interview,therefore I have now some thing over which I want to talk with you. I fefcl confident that you will not disappoint me. 1 do request you to grant me an interview for which I will be very grateful to you.r Translation of letter d?ted the 4th,Safar 1352(28th,May 1933 from Khalif?!! bin Hamad Al Klialifah, to the Political Agent Bahrain, After Compliments. On the 30th, ultimo I submitted a letter to Your Excellency and asked therein for an interview with four Excellency for discussion but unfortunately I could not have an interview with you* pay. As you are aware I have a family and servants for whom my previous pay was not sufficient and therefore I cannot manage if further reductions are made in my pay. Colonel Barrett in the presence of His Excellency Shaikh Hamad and it was decided that no reduction is to be made in my pay* But in the year of 1350 it was reduced^ sum of Rs .20/- and a further reduction of Rs ,55/-£*#e#'also made this ye ar* my case and extend help to me and give me a reply to my request as my pay is being withheld* I like to speak to you about the reduction in my YJm are aware that my previous pay was sanctioned by Colonel Prideax, the late Political Resident and by I, beg, therefore, that you may kindly look into Usual Ending*I/: g- .-******* ^ (j^0^4 - ^ Translation of letter dated the 14^h Rabi-el-Awal 1352(7.7.33), from Shaikh Khalifah bin Hamad Al Khalifah, to the Political Agent, Bahtain. After Compliments. I have had an interview with you and talked to you about* about my straitened circumstances and requested your help to me regarding the cut which has been done in my pay since three months. Now, I again request that you will kindly allow me to see the Political Resident so that I may talk with him in this respect as I informed Shaikh Hamad about this and he directed me to have your permission lor doing so. I firmly hope that you will be good enough to favour my request. Usual Ending.No. 7V3/V.0. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 11th July 1933. To, The Adviser, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM. I enclose herewith copy of letter from Shaikh Khalifah bin Hamad Al Ebalifah and that of my reply, for your information. Sd. G.Gastrell Political Agent, Bahrain. \ u I: 'H Vi r\ ^ /^. // No.744 Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 11th duly 1933. To. Shaikh Khalifah bin Hamad al Khalifah ’ \ I After Compliments, I have received your letter dated the 14th Rabi 1 al Auwal 1352 and have understood its contents. i regret,however, that as the Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel T.C.Fowle,C.B.E., Political resident in the Persian Gulf is going away at once for about three months to ittigland, it will not be possible for you to see him at present. Usual Endings. Sd. E.Gastrell Political Agent, Bahrain. » r- /J&amp; Translation of letter dated 20th Hajab 1352 from Shaikh Khalifa bin Hamad A1 Hhalifah, to the Political Agent,Bahrain. £ - / 2 ~ After Compliments. I had to come and visit you at your arrival at our • country but with much regret l was busy then, as it is incumbent on me to visit you therefore I would be very glad if yoa will be kind enough to fix a time for the purpose as Immmmm %■ P.A* &amp; Shaikh * Abdullah bin •Isa al Khalifah has sent his clerk to say that he wants to call on you just now if convenient* He is now in the office of the Adviser* For orders,please* 27 . 1 C 34—Statement oi mmiammaa Dm aIi bin Aftfliad al ICbialitaa* « My t'atner ciieci wnen I was 6-7 years oia, leaving my elcer Drotner and my sister. Alter my iatner T s deatn, Sdaiidi f Isa bin T Ali toolc over all tne estate 01 my latner sucn as date-gardens, cattle, douses, siiops etcetera, ana nanaed it over to my elder brother Admaa bin aIi. Alter Shaikh*sIsa T s death, I was given two date-gardens situated at Mam Village which yield an annual income oi Ks.1100/-. I am also receiving now Rs.60/- a month. In the past, being a minor ana ignorant, I aia noc put lorwara any claim for my share out oi tne inheritance oi my late lather. Last year, however, I approached His Highness ohaikh mr Hamad and claimed my and my sister f s full snare ol the inheritance out ol my father T s estate. He referred me to the ndviscr and Shaikh f AbdulIan bin ^sa. They talked over the matter. Shaikh Adbullan then said that the matter should be deterred until his mother f s return from the Haj. Although his mother came oack irom the Haj and the matter was discussed again, .no result has been achieved and therefore it was kept m abeyance. 1 did not approach His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad again, as I have many expenses to make and my present income is too small to meet my expanses and seeing that no result has been achieved, I came to approach His Majesty f s Political Agent, with the request that he ipay kindly intervene with a view to settling tins matter.No. 251-X/lb. | The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—- The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.Translation. / To, Political Agent, Bahrain. Alter Compliments. I beg to inform you that 1 had alreaay spoken to you in the Agency about the estate of my lather Ali bin Ahmad al Khalilah and that Ahmad bin Ali took possession of the whole estate and I dia not get anything therefrom except the date-gardens at Sihat Mani which is not enough to cover my expenses. I have repeatedly been seeking justice but of no avail. I spoke to you about this would verbally and you told me that you/ informs me of the result after you receive a reply from Shaikh Hamaa to your letter. Now a long time has passed and I aid not get anything. I, therefore, request and implore you to intervene in this matter and get it settled for which act I shall be grateful to you. Usual Ending. Sd. Muhammad bin f Ali bin Ahmad Bated al Khalifah. 17th Jamad Awwal 1356 (26-7-37)-translation of a letter dated 15th Kajab 135G k21st September 1937^ from %hai:imad bin Ali A1 K^alifali, -B a hraln, to the -Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. 1 beg to state that i have submitted to you a / . letter dealing with my case with my brother Ahmad bin Ali A1 Khalifah in connection with my share in the legacies of my father the late Ali bin Ahmad A1 Khalifah. 1 to ok. shelter with you on the subject and a long time has elapsed. I have lately been informed that Bis highness Shaikh hamad would deal with the matter and settle it, out no result has been achieved as yet. i therefore request you kindly to let me know if any settlement will be effected shortly. Op if there is any dealy in it, 1 beg to request you to increase m y pay until the case is settled. 1 am repeating my request to you so that you ^kindly arrange to settle the case as soon as possible, usual Ending.Bahrain, 27th Raby Awal, 1358 To The Polictioal Agency Bahrain. Sir I have the honour to offer rqy letter to you, to say that, the salary Rs.38/- wioh I am geting from the Bahrain Government is not suffeoient, because I have got a big family onsist of a mother, wife, sons and servent. Sir, I have spoken to the Adviser to The Bahrain Government, and he answered me that (The Government could not give you more than you are geting). Therefore I am requesting you please if you will kind enough to order for the increment. I hope that you will do so. Thanking in anticipation. Your most obedient servant, Jaber BAn Hamad Bin Mohammed Alkgalefa.Please say in each case that I am going on tour in a few days time but will return after about two weeks and will then be glad to see him. I will then let him know a time# O Vv r i (i.L • 30.6.33 p • a . &gt; Letters to both the Qadhi of Sanabis and to bhaikh Khaldfah bin Hamad written and are submitted for signature. Shaikh Khalifah has sent in another lettervattached) , the translation of which is at flag-^A'. 1.6.33 r m ' I promised interview to one of the Al Khalifah and anotherQadhi ?) on m£ return from tour. Where are the papers ?. G «L« 21.6.33 P.A., Shaikh Khalifah bin Hamad and the Qadhi of Sanabis asked for interview vide translation of their letters A and B, but as you were going on tour you repliec* that you will see them after you return from tour. The papers are submitted as ordered. 21.6.33 Shaikh Khalifah on 26.6.33 at 09.00 hours. Qadhi of Sanhis on 26.6.33 at 10.00 hours. But in case of Qadhi is that hour a suitable one- if not please ; speak. Remind me on 24.6.33. G.L. 21.6.33. P.A., &amp; Letters to Shaikh Khalifph and the Qadhi of Sanabis are herewith submitted for signature. 10.00 hours is aCT' - 2 - suitable time for the Qadhi of Sanabis. J. 22.6.33 'fhese two visitors came on 26th June 1933. 2. Shaikh Khalifah came about the cut of his allowance. There are seperate papers. 3. The Qadhi merely came to pay a call. Has P.A. returned such a call. Gali* 28.6.33 ' ■ 4 P.A., Your predecessor once returned the call of the Qadhi of Sanabis. ^ 28.6.33 Please speak. G.L. 29.6.33 Also I gather of the Qadhi of Llanamah. Better put up on my return. G.L. 29.6.33 ■I Original note filed with papers re the Qadhi of Sanabis. / 30.6*733 » VSubject: Asks permission to see the Hon'ble the P. R. Inform .him that Colonel Fowle is goinp away for about three months to England, so that it will not be possible to see him until after his return. Draft please. We should send copy to Adviser. 9.7.33 Draft of letters to Adviser and Shaikh Khalifah bin These papers were sent tothe Court room on 9.7.33 but wer not seen by P.A. I am sending them up to you as it is possible that Colonel Loch might like to see and sign them himself. Letters written and submitted for signature,please. P.A., Hamad are submitted for approval,please 9.7.33 P.A. , Submitted for orders,please* 11.7.33 Letter dated 20 th Rajab 1352(20.11.33) from Shaikh Khalifah bi Hamad al KhAlifah to the Political Agent, Bahrain* Request for interview. P.A., Before your departure to Buahire Shaikh Khalifah askedyour permission to go to Bushire and see the Hon’ble the P.R. about the cut of his allowance to whom you replied that a.s the P.R. was going away at once to England it was not possible to see him then. / Submitted for orders. Ll* ^ $ / C/ Of- w 22 Please see P.l (Confidential File 6/10). I mentioned tnis case of Shaikh Khalifan bin Hamad to the Resident who agreed that the matter was an internal affair wnich the Shaikh should settle. 1 explained that I showed it to him as Shaixh Khalifah had tnreatenen to go across to see him at Bushire. Shs-ikh Khalifeh bin hamad has come with his son liuhamma.d and ask to see you. He says that he has some private work about which he has corae to see you. Submitted for order*,please. A, P.A. 27.2.34 fr'l) •'t' &lt;&gt; 1 * ABefore I left someone asked for an interview — Khalifa bin Muhaiunad ?? Please put up file. G • L» 7/4 P.A. I do not recollect anybody to have come for an interview with you before you left other than Shaikh Raonia bin .kohd A1 Khalifah who came to pay his respects to P.R. 2. As regards Khalifah bin Hamad, he came for an interview long before your last departure for Qatar, but, as you were buoy then, you could not see him. Your order was communicated to him by the H.M.verbally. /jfN File No.K/15 submitted pi. 8.4.34 _ • lu* i l Mir \r- /O &gt; P.A# ohaikh ’Abdullah bin f Isa al Khalifah has sent his / clerk, Ibrahim bin Hasan, to say that ne wishes to pay Ll* his respects to you ana asks when it woula A convenient lor you to see him this morning. Shaikh ’Abaullau is now in the offcie of the ^aviser. Submittea for orders,please. 12.11.34 | Ltw. 'KA- / of LoiUU^, **~&lt;a&amp;*&gt; £y\ / 1-i K/15 S.No.19 f&gt; -G- [¥&gt; i Letter dated the 29th Rajah 1353(7.11.34) from Shaikh Rashia bin Muhammad al Khalifah to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject: Interview. A.P.A. Today is Thursday and the time given by Shaikn nashid has already passed. Submitted for orders,please. 8.11.34 ■« ^ PiU* A ' ,A ' ^ / g/o Wr \rb 4-ft f) W/,/ P.A. Draft is submitted for approval. The Farrash did not bring the letter to me yesterday (Friday) nor did he inform me that ne kept a file on my table on which tnere is an urgent slip so that I could draft the letter earlier. Shaikh Rashid is at Muharra^ and I do not think that this will enable him to come at the time fixed and you may like to chairge tne same. For orders,please. ^ _ L - Lari'- /+/*■ ($- u.' A &lt; Abdullati bin Jabar ( Secretary to His Excellency the Shaikh) came here ana askea me to tell you that His Excellency will be expecting you ana A.?.A. in me ^asar tomorrow at 4.30. Arabic (9.40. A.M.) lor your visit ana a little alter will pay his return visit. . /t ej.12.3o» 4.1b. P.H. ViJU ^ A OrJJL* |vr ^ ^ e - .i . . 've.aovoV (5 V°,As directed I went to B^iharraq yesterday and saw Shaikh Muhammad bin Isa. After conveying your compliments I said that you sent me to enquire about his health because you heard that he was unwell. He said he is much better now and he can move about and have his meals. He asked me to convey his compliments to you adding his best thanks for your kind enquiry about him. He said he intends to visit Man amah shortly when he will have the pleasure of seeing you also. For information. 14-1-37</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1970</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1970</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File K/15 Visits and Interviews of Members of the Al Khalifa family with the Political Agent, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-16T22:03:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (51 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 53; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 6-52; these numbers are also written in pencil, but, where circled, are crossed through.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence pertaining to requests for audiences and visits by members of the al-Khalifa family with the Political Resident and Political Agent in Bahrain. Most concern matters of personal finance and state allowances.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Local relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002c1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>