<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-11T08:26:31.369Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">M. A. Hashid Esquire, M.A. Director General of Customs Sultanate of Muscat &amp; Oman Muscat. Tq His Britannic Majesty’s Consul &amp; Political Agent, Muscat. Dated the 30th October,1950 Sir I have the honour to state that when the Muscat Government was in search of a Director General of Customs in 1946 the Resident in the Persian Gulf addressed the Government of India and asked for the services on lopn of a suitable officer from the Indian Customs Service. The Government of India selected three individuals and while the Resident was on tour in India they were summoned to appear before him at Delhi. I was one of the three and the one finally chosen by him. My first period of secondment to the Muscat Government was for three years from 25th May 1946 to 24th May 1949. Subsequently an extension was offered and accepted by me and sanctioned by the Pakistan Government. I was selected by the Bengal Public Service Commission*^ and appointed to Customs Appraiser Service class II of the Calcutta Customs House on the 5th September 1940 and later confirmed in the appointment from the same date. Prior to partition I opted for service with the Pakistan Government and my option was accepted. My seniority in the Calcutta Customs House was known to me but I have no idea what position has been alloted to me in the Pakistan Customs Service. I understand that on the termination of my deputation here on the 24th May 1951 I shall be posted to the --Karachi Custom House and as my services were loaned through the Consulate and the Residency I should be most grateful if you would be so kind as to ascertain from the Collector of Customs Karachi what my seniority will bo. Copies of the documents noted below which concern ry case are attached for facility of referenceAppointment le tter• Extract from Establishment list of the Calcutta Custom House. Terms of deputation. Govt of India, Finance Dept (Revenue Division) letter C ! T o. 749 - Adm CE/45, dated the 24th April 1946 Acceptance of option to serve in Pakistan. Govt of Pakistan, 1 Minsitry of Finance (Revenue Division) letter C No. 849 -Adm/ 47, dated the 30th March 1948. Letter from Collector of Cus toms Calcutta NO. Sll- 17/47A dated the 29th May 1948, to the Collector of Customs Karachi v/ith which to be forwarded my Service Book and Confidential file Pakistan Governments agreement to the extension of my period of deputation. Government of Pakistan, Ministry of Finance (Revenue Division) Office Memo No. C 176- A C E/49, dated the 28th November 1949, to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Common Wealth Relations, Karachi I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servantC.No. 849- Adnin./47* Govcrnmeait of i 5 akistcin. Ministry of Finance (Revenue Division) Karachi, the 30th March 1948. From A.A.Burney, Ssqr., ^ . Deputy Secretary to the Governxnent of Pahisten, The Collector of Customt;, . Sir, Subjects- Rashid (jir.M.A.) , Calcutta Custom House, on deputation to Muscat as Director General.,of Customs - Final option of, for Pakistan - Posting of. I am directed to enclose a copy of letter aated the lOtn January 1948 from T'lr• M.A.Rashid Appraiser, Ct'lcutuc. Customs House, on deputation to Muscat as Director General of Customs end to say that on reversion from fi^oeign service Mr. Rashid v’ill be posted to the Karachi Custom House. I have the honour to be, Sir, I'bur most obedient servant, 3d/- A.A.Burney Deputy Secretary to the Government of Pakistan. Copy with copy pf the letter referred to forwarded to:- 1. Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Comnonvealth Reis tions with tho request that they may kindly ascertain and intimate to this Division the date upto which Mr. Rashid will remain on deputation to foreign service. 2. The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of Finance (Revenue Division) with the remark that no intimationof Mr. Rashid^ provosipnal optioh for Pakistan was received by this Government. 3. The Collector of Customs, Calcutta, with^the request that the Service Book and Confidential file of Mr. Rashid may be transfered to the Collxctor of Customs, * Karachi* 4. The Accountant General, Pakietcn, Revenues. 5. The Political Agency and K.MMs Consulate Muscat, with reference to his endorsement Mo. C/48/8/15, dated the 18th January 1948 with the request that copy of complete correspondence regarding Mr. Rashid’s deputation to Muscat may kindly be sent for record in this office. 6. M. A# Rashid Esquire, Director General of Customs, Muscat and Oman. By order, etc., Deputy Secretary to the Government of Pakistan.lleno C.! r o, 600/40 @CD jlr. Md. Abu Has heed is inforraed that he is offered the post of an aoaraiser in the jrade of a.200-15-380 (Efficiency her) 20- 500. He will be on probation for a period of one year from the date of apoointment and will be considered for confirmation on approved service. hV is directed to report himself for duty at his own expense as soon, asconvenierit• He vfil_ be rocpiired to pass the usual meciical examination by the Staff Surgeon, if he has not already undergone such examination. He should also state the natui’e of his present appointment (whether temporary or permanent) pay etc. Before he joins the post. Custom House Sd/- F.H.Innes. Calcutta. 27th August, 1940. Collector of Customs. Hr. Md. Abu Hasheed, Rubbani Cottage Bhagalpur City.Cony of an Office Memorandum I r o. C.17G-ACE/49, dated the 28th November,1949, from the Government of ^akifiU n Hinistry of Finance (Revenue Division) to the ?!inistry of Foreign affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Karachi. Subject: Establishment - Mr. K.A.Rashid, /ppraser -aivchi Customs T7 ;oUi:-.e-r Deputation of as Director General of Customs , Muscat- Eb.tension of the period of. Reference Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations Memorandum l T o. /»A-3/20/49, dated the 15th November, 1949 on the above subject. 2. The Gover:iment of Pakistan agree to the proposed m .U extension of the period of deputation of Mr. Rashid, on the existijig terms and conditions for a further period of two years, with effect from 25th May 1949. Copy forwarded to 1. The Accountant ^eneral, Pakistan Revenues, Karachi. 2. The Collector of Customs Marachi.HEGISTffgl) No. S. 11-17/47A From To 0. Erishman, Esq., B.A., GOLIiEGTOH OF CUGTaiS, CALCUTTA The Collector of Customs, Karachi. ^ated the 29th Hay 1948. Subject:- Rashid (mr.r.A.), Appraiser, Calcutta Custom House, on deputation to I'uscat as Director General of Customs - Filial option of, for Pakistan - Posting of. Sir, Reference letter C.Ho.849~Admn./47 dated the 30th March 1948 from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of Pakistan to your address, a copy of which was endorsed to this office. 2. I forward herewith the Service Book and Confidential File of Mr.M.A.Rashid, formerly an Appraser of this Cdstom House, on deputation to Muscat. Sd/- 0. Krishnan, COLLECTOR CUSTOMS. Memo.Mo.S.11-L7/47A q/- 25.5.48. Cox^y forv’arded to Mr. M.A.j^ashid, Director 'eneral of Cus toms, l 'uscat 6 Oman, Cueton House, Muscat, w ith Heference to his letter dt ted the 12th March 1948. COLLECTOR OF GT E TOMS. «■C .No. 749-Adm. C .E/45 Government of India Finance Department (Revenue Division) New Delhi, the 24th April 1946 From The Under Secretary to the Government of India, To The Collector of Customs, Calcutta. Sub: Transfer of Mr. M.A.Rashid Appraiser Calcutta Custom House, to Muscat on Foreign service. Please refer to the correspondence resting with your letter NO.S.20-21/45C, dated the 16th February 1946. 2. The Governor General in Council is pleased to sanction the transfer of Mr. M.A.Rashid, an appraiser in the Calcutta Custom House, to Muscat on foreign service as Director General of Customs, with effect from the date he relinquishes charge of his present appointment on the following terms :- Period: For a period of three years in the first instance, of which the first six months will be on probation. Services liable to be terminated without notice on completion of three years and before completion of that period on two months notice by either side. Pay: Rs.550 (Rupees five hundred and fifty) a month ( with free quarters) rising to 650/- (Rupees six hundred and fifty) with an annual increament of Rs.50/- (Rupees fifty) from the date he hands over charge of his duties at Calcutta up to the date of his return. Leave: Under the Rules as applicable to him while in service at the Custom House. Leave salary and pension contributions: In accordance with the rates prescribed by the Governor General in Council from time to time. Travelling allowance : (a) For himself and family as on transfer unaer the Supplementary Rules of the Central Government for journeys to end from Muscat; (b) According to State Rules for journeys if any, performed during foreign service. Joining time: Both on transfer to and reversion from foreign service will be regulated under the Supplememtary Rules of the Central Gove rumen t. 3. He should arrange to reach Muscat as soon as possible. He should also arrange for his passage himself, but particulars about his shipping agents, passages required etc. should be furnished to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, who will assist him in obtaining them early. He will require a passport and should obtain it from the Government of Bengal. 4 5 4. The total expenditure involved will be met by the Sultan of Muscat. Sd/- A.N.Puri Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy forwarded to :- 1. The Hon*able the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf - 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. Bushire. 3. The External Affairs Deptt. 4. The Accountant General, Central Revenue. 5. The Accountant General, Bengal.X (2)S '■ 3 W 7749 The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 4c, 31st December, 1949. t ^U4*&gt; -,&lt; 40 /w 1 ^ 36 refer our letter Ro. 3^6/4/49 of 6 th October about Mr. Rashid f s deputation to the Muscat Government. 2. We enclose a copy of a letter ho.A.A.-3/20/49 oi 9th December from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth relations, Karachi, and enclosure, sanctioning the extension oi iiis deputation period for another two years from 25th May, 1949. tAJL S' / Y S/£ . srs \Jh ii 1 Major F.C.L. Chauncy, The Political Agent, Muscat. ’■■■■■■ ■H Copy of an Office Memorandum :^o. C. 176-ACK/49, dated the 26th November, 194-9» from the Government of Pakistan Ministry of Finance (revenue Division) to the Ministry of Foreign affairs and Commonwealth Relations, Karachi. Subject: establishment - Mr. M.e. Rashid, appraiser Karachi Customs House - Deputation of as Director General of Customs, Muscat - extension of the period of. Reference ministry of Foreign affairs and Commonwealth Relations Memorandum Ro.AA-3/20/49, dated the 15th November, 1949, on the above sub- j ect. 2. The Government of Pakistan agree to the proposed extension of the period of deputation of Mr. Rashid, on the existing terms and conditions for a further period of two years, with effect from 25th May, 1949. Copy forwarded to:- 1. The accountant General, Karachi. 2. The Collector of Customs Pakistan nevenues , Karachi. yCopy of an Office Memorandum I\o. C. 176-ACE/49, dated the 28th hovemberj 1949f from the Government of Pakistan Ministry of Finance (Revenue Division) to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Kelations, Karachi. Subject: Establishment - Mr. M.a. nashid, Appraiser Karachi Customs House - Deputation of as Director General of Customs, Muscat - Extension of the period of. Reference Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Commonwealth Relations Memorandum Ro. aA- 3/20/49, dated the 15th November, 1949, on the above sub ject. 2. The Government of Pakistan agree to the proposed extension of the period of deputation of Mr. Rashid, on the existing terms and conditions for a further period of two years, with effect from 25th May, 1949. Copy forwarded to:- 1. The accountant General, Karachi. 2. The Collector of Customs Pakistan revenues , Karachi. tCOPY MIKIbTBY OF FOREIGN AFPAIRS &amp; COMMONWEALTH RELATIONS KARACHI No.AA-3/20/49 Dated the 9th December, 1949. Dear Residency, Kindly refer to your letter No.358/ 4/49f dated the 6th October, 1949* regarding the seconoment of Mr. M.A. Rashid to Muscat as Director General of Customs. 2. We enclose herein a copy of the Government of Pakistan, Ministry of Finance (Revenue Division) office memorandum No.C. No.176-ACE/49 i dated the 28th November, 1949f conveying Government of Pakistani sanction for the extension of the deputation of Mr. Rashid to the Muscat Government. Yours sincerely, Ministry. Enel: One. The Persian Gulf, Residency. Bahrain. 87/8/ a/3CsCustom House Muscat. January 11, 1960. Sir, In continuation of your letter No. 13/8/16/49 dated the 17th August 1949, I have to say that I have not been informed of the sanction to rqy deputation with the Muscat Government for a further period of two years from the 35th May 1949. Since a very consierable time has passed, I request that I may kindly be informed of the position at an early date. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, x&lt;h Director Genej^al^bi Customs. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul &amp; ^TT^- The Political /igent /// *o • Muscat. Uzu a/n ' &lt; '- r ^ Ue. c&lt;jvua AK A. tLdLcl* U^Ola £. CUVUJ?h PTc* . “ • 4</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/202</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/202</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/16 III Director-General of Customs, Muscat.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-18T23:52:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 17; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file relates to Mohammad Abu Rashid, currently employed as Director-General of Customs in the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. The correspondence records that Rashid was appointed on deputation from Customs House, Calcutta, and that, prior to partition, while still in Muscat, he had opted for service with the Government of Pakistan. Writing to the Political Agent in October 1950, while still on deputation in Muscat but due to be posted to Karachi the following year, Rashid requests information regarding the level of seniority that he will have in his new post.Other correspondents include the following: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Persian Gulf Political Residency; the Government of Pakistan's Ministries of Finance and Foreign Affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Muscat and Oman, Director-General of Customs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Finance</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Employment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003d1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>