<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00028e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:37:45.057Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">3 ii0 * wnuitai ok/ici, s.w.t. (SA 1132 / 1 ) /th Siovembe ', 1950 . Sir, 1 enclo e the opifrlnal typed copy of Bahrain ? ■ &amp;Xng'* Kemulation Mo. 2 of 195 C, together with two certified copies and 4-2 plain printed copies* * • the certified copies should be signed 'by br* ^©lly, who was political Resident at the ti®« when the King’a Regulation was made, and returned to the foreign Office. I am, with great truth and respect. Sir, Your excellency * s obedient errant, (For the secretary of itate) His excellency Lieutenaat Colonel Sir Rupert hay, K.C.l. .., r, , etc., etc., etc., Bahrein*Unclassified, No,R-454 Political Agency, Bahrain, 22nd November, 1950, Dear Andrew, Your letter of the 17th November (345/21/50). 2, I return herewith the two certified copies of King*s Regula tion No.2 of 1950 as desired, duly signed. R.McC. Andrew, Esq., The Residency, Jufair.y v ..l-.-v ' &amp; Roferofic o No 0 (70-228). With the compliments of H.MoPolitical Agent at Bahrain to The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. King^ Regulations Nos.I &amp; 2 of 1960. Additional copies are on sale at the Agency at Re.l/- each. Bahrain, November 29, 1950.P' no. y- y/t of 1370 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 22nd Safar, 1370 December 3, 1950. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- Reference your No. VO-2128 dated 29th November, 1950. I should be obliged if you would supply us with 6 copies of each of the King’s Regu lations Nos. 1 and 2 of 1950. I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs. 12/- lU/' 'dO -being the cost. \ st n y AY. L Adviser to the Government.' 0 1 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. (VO-235). December 13,1950. Sir, I acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 3rd December (503-9A) and of your cheque for Rs.12/- 2. Six copies each of King*s Regulations Nos.l and 2 of 1950 are enclosed herein. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, for Political Agent,Bahrain. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00028e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1919</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00028e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1919</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File VO-E/27 KING'S REGULATIONS. - Issue &amp; Sale of''</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1950/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-06-07T22:01:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-7; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the issue and sale of King’s Regulations. The main correspondence is between the Political Agency, Bahrain, the British Residency, Bahrain, the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave), and the Foreign Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Legislation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00028e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>