<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001a6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:45:42.777Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">8 34827—2 '? C ^ X-NNVOVV W5 ‘fLo sSx, /*- z 5 ; UiK I fS % I / V ith the Compliments OF THE INDEXED Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs . H.o.i£\c&gt; ? ' r&lt;i iqpL°t.h-5 \\0* O^Zc* pi : , v Vagp 51 ' fc Foreign Office, \^* •^o.«-ftik_ , 1945 -,1484 Wt 26166/268 1m 10/41 FA Gp744 42 (2!&gt;fcj/4/4£i;. -WS- 7^ ■ HIS Majesty’s - at BaCJaJ presents his compliments to and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents, e&amp;assy, British. 7tii February 8 # 194 Reference to 'previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Copy of despatch i«o.5 addressed to !.•^•Consul- Get eral, Basra, dated the 7th February, 1946. Subject. Iraqi visas for Pilgrimage. Copies to* Mosul Attars Kirkuk ^ ' F.C* v fHFG f Bahrein. Kueeit Bshreln. Muscat* Covern^nt of India. Governiaent of raklstan*BRITISH EMBASSY, BAGDAD. 7th February, 1948 With reference to paragraph 2 of my despatch to you Ko.52(l84/9/47) of 22nd October 1947, I have now been assured by the Political agent Muscat that he does not issue visas for Iraq to Oman’s unless the applicant first deposits the sum of Rs.40C/-, and that any sums expended on the repatriation of destitute Omani pilgrims will be refunded to Eis Majesty's Consular Officers in Iraq. 2. I have therefore informed the Iraqi Government that Eis -.lajesty's Consular Officers will assume the responsibility for the repatriation of destitute pilgrims from the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman as well as from the Sheikhdoms mentioned in my despatch under reference. 3« I attach a specimen copy of the travel document issued to natives of Kuwait and the Trucial Coast, hatives of Bahrein travel on regular Bahrein passports. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant ( ’ . y British Consul-General, British Consulate-General BASRA./ y &gt; No.2060-^9A. tNDEXe’ Dear Chancery, Will you please refer to the correspondence resting with your letter rfo. 184/4/47 dated the 9th August, 1947&gt; on the subject of waiver of deposits from pilgrims from the Persian Gulf Sheiididoms visiting the holy shrines in Iraq. — 2. The views of the governments concerned have been ascertained and the positions is as follows:- (a) KUWAIT The Kuwait Government have given the necessary assurance in respect of pilgrims £rom that area. (b) BaKKAIN The Bahrain Government have also given the requisite assurance, and have suggested that pilgrims repatriated should be provided with deck passages, with food, from Basra to Bahrein, and where necessary, Third Class train fares to the port of embarkation together with a small allowance for food on the journey. A daily allowance of the equivalent of Bs. 2/- per head should also be paid to the pilgrims when they have to wait for passages at Basra. (c) Till TiiuCIaL COAST No guarantees have been ta cen from the Trucial Coast Shaikhs as by the present practice a pilgrim is given a visa for Iraq only after a local merchant of standing has given a letter guaranteeing reimbursement of repatriation expenses. This is considered satisfactory. (d) MUSCA T The Sultan of Muscat and Oman has requested that the Iraqi Government should as at present continue to take deposits from pilgrims proceeding from his territory to the holy shrines in Iraq. There is thus means of obtaining refund of expenses incurred by British Consuls in repatriating destitute pilgrims belonging to Muscat end Oman on application to the Political Agent, Muscat. 3. A deck passage, with food, to the pilgrims home port, together with a third class railway fare to the port of embarkation and a daily allowance for the period of halt ata port awaiting passage, at a rate equivalent to Iis,2/-, as suggested by the Political Agent, Bahrain, may be taken as the ordinary rule for guidance by British Consular authorities in repatriating destitute pilgrims belonging to the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms other than that of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. The Chancery, British Embassy, Bagdad.2 4. The British Consulfcr re/resentativ© reijatristing a ciestitute pilgrim should obtain i statement from him giving his full ho i© address and personal particulars, also a receipt, in duplicate, for all the amount expended on him, and send it to the Political Agent Kuwait in respect of Kuwait anu to the Political ;;gent, Bahrain in respect of Bahrain an the Trucial Sheikha or ,s. The Political Agents x* ill take i/a.euiate steps to have the amounts reimbursed to the Consular authorities concerned, A copy of this letter is being sent to the Politica l Agents at uv/ait and Bahrain, Yours ever, HI SIL^CY£ ,v ' 4 INWARD TELEGRAM, Lj„ Z- .g.x 2S612 Allotted to Communications antj. ' Overseas Department, COF, ^DENTIAL CODE TEL SIR AM Prom Government cf India, Communications Dept» To Secretary of State for India, Dated New Delhi.80=. 30 hours, 30th September 1946, Received 18,00 hours, 30th September 1948,. 8463 Your telegram 17048 19th September, Charter flights for Ka,)3 pilgrims. Permission foreign governments concerned, has been asked for.— —ir COPY. r —~ ' ' ! i OUTW ifjRJDTT ELEGRAM &amp; 'U. C* l' Ll GDOO M Vc CorrjTPdnl c at i ciiq Vi^^XXYier ge g &amp;■ ,i&amp; rjrrtr^rit &gt; C. A 0. ij846/46. COrrB'IDENTIAL COPE TEI^ORAM. From Secretary of State for India. To Government of India* Communications Department He'peated to Political. Resident, . Persian Gulf, Bahrein. Deep* 23.40 hours, 19th September 1946. vroAQ^ Your telegrams No 7950 and .7962 dated 12th and 14th • September. He will inform you as soorT'ag permission of Air Ministry for use of aerodromes at Kamaran, Aden and Riyan ho.s been obtained, v 2, Assume you are awaro that permission of Govern: ents of Iraq., Palestine and Transiordon will be required for India Air Travel Service Charter flight, that prior notification of flight must be given to Government of Sgypt, and that you have taken necessar action. 3, Permission of Sultan of Muscat will also presumably have to be obtained and Rulers of Bahrein and Sharjah notified. 4, Assume also that you have permission of Ring of Saudi Arabia for all repeat all proposed Mecca flights. 5, I am repeating your telegrams to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf as parts two md three.of this telegram. Copy to Mr Warren, Air Ministry. ' Mr E.Ratcliffe-Cousins, C.S.I*, C.I.K. Ministry of Civil Aviation. Extarnal r•fnort ^ Mr R.G.Ballcwi 11, F neign Off!ee, Bent by Mr Franca./ INWARD TELEGRAM f Allotted to Goiri nunicat 1 ons and Q- 7eraeas. CQHFIL'ENTIAL CODE TELEGRAM From Government of India. Communications Dept, Secretary of State for India To Dated New Delhi, 04*40 hours, 14th September 1946* Reed, 02*30 hours, 14th September 1946, IMPORTANT * ' • 7962. Continuation of this Department’s tele&amp;ram 7930 dated September 12th, 1946. Air travel facllitiec for Haj pilgrims. The India Air Travel Service Ltd have proposed a charter flight from Bombay to Jsdda and bach* Flight consists of 2 aircraft. Registration marks VT-AUH and VT-AU1* F?,iglit will leave Bombay on October i2th and arrive Jadda on 21st via Shariah, Bahrein, Margilraschid, Lydda Cairo and (?MacMaan), Leaves Jedda November 9th and arrives Bombay 12th via Aden, Riyan Salalah and Haselhadd, Planes will carry total of 18 passengers. Kindly obtain permiss ion of Air Ministry to use aerodromes in Kamaran Aden and Riyan.INWARD TELEGRAM 2!i960»N ■■ L v Allotted to External Departme.) t. COHPIDBNTIAL CODfi jTBLEaRA^ 1 .b’rom Government of India, Communications Department a Dated To Secretary of State for India* New Delhi, 22*05 hours, 12th September, 1946. Received 20.10 hours, 12th September, 1946. IMPORTANT. No. 7950. In response to public demand, arrangements are being made by Government of India for travel by air of Haj pilgrims to Mecca* The Commonwealth Relations Department, who are in charge of arrangements, have chartered a DCS aircraft from Indian National Airways,for the purpose. Registration marks of aircraft VT-ARH. The aircraft will make a total of .3 flights from Delhi to Jedda and back. The first charter will leave Delhi October 13th, will night stop in Karachi and Salalah reaching Jedda October 15th evening* The aircraft will return empty to Delhi. The second charter leaves Delhi October 29th reaching Jedda October 31st, return from Jedda with 17 passengers on November•9th, night stop at Salalah and Karachi, arriving Delhi on November 11th. Thethird and last charter leaves Delhi empty about November- 24th and returns from Jedda with a load of passengers. Kindly Cbtain permission of Air Ministry to use airfields at Riyan, Aden and Kamaran.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001a6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1169</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001a6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1169</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 6299/46 'Travel facilities for pilgrims'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-10T09:52:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 17; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to travel arrangements for residents of the Persian Gulf on the Muslim pilgrimage to Mecca, particularly regarding fees and repatriation responsibilities. The main correspondents are as follows the Government of India, Department of Communications; the Secretary of State for India and Burma; the British Embassy in Iraq and the Persian Gulf Political Residency. Matters discussed include the Government of India's plan to offer travel to pilgrims via an Indian National Airways chartered aircraft from Bombay to Jedda, and the permissions they will need to obtain from rulers of the region to do this. Folios 5 to 11 contain correspondence detailing the decision to waive deposits usually charged to pilgrims travelling from the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms of Kuweit, Bahrein, Oman and Muscat, and the Trucial Coast, costs of which will be absorbed by the British Consul, Basra.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Department of Communications</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy in Iraq, Baghdad</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mecca</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Muslim pilgrims and pilgrimages--Saudi Arabia--Mecca</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001a6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>