<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000067_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T16:41:58.985Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">slc;^i £.0. Uo. 0/311 Diited the 24th November 1^40 I wonder if you coaid very kindly let me iiavc jonk, information as to the aisposai of a consignment of some. 60,000 gallons of petrol (probably aviation petrol) vaich arrived in Dhahran by the tanker cruiser ^Prusa” possibly some t.rO nionths ; go# .'he uestion is whether this aviation petrol has been sent to baud! .Arabia, Jeida, and the purpose for which it is lively to be used by the Saudi authorities as it seems ratner a large consignment. I anouid be very grateful for any information tn.,t you could give me# F. ft# Oaiiger, lsq* # Cariforni^ ^r^oian Standard Oai Company htd..%Confidential* No.504. Sir, -o (s) Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.Naval Base, Bahrain. 26th November, 1940. I have the honour to request that you 'will be good enough to approach the Bahrain Petroleum Company and ask if it -would be possible for them to give me details of any cargoes off loaded by the Company at Bahrain or by the California Arabian Standard Oil Company on the mainland which are destined for ports on the Red Sea. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, JOMMODOHE SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, 1RSIAN GULF. The Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain.D«0* No.C/923-28/19 Dated the 27th November 1940 I have been asked to collect details of any Bahrain mainland for ports on the Red Sea. cargoes off loaded at which are destined 2. I hesitate to trouble you so often but would be most grateful for any information you can give me about such consignments. M.H. Lipp, Esq,, Bapco. F.W. Ohliger, Esq., Casoc.01 SI Q and S # Groups 77 * H07V25.11.40* Following received from Ccmmander.in.ChiefEast Indies Station begins - Can you suggest any way of checking whether oil and other supplies from Persian Gulf are being sent to Italian East Africa either across Arabia or by Neutral ships or dhows. Any difference between cargoes loaded in Persian Gulf and cargoes off loaded at declared destination might indicate intermediate smuggling, ends. 2. Apart frora oil can you'suggest any methods of tightening up control of reporting of cargoes loading at Persian Gulf Ports for enemy destination. TOC * HOVs/ 25.11.40. aaK. 5 * •i i/:* IFrom To Political HesidenxY-tm Tboord the ’’Nearchus' 1 Political Agent, Bahrain Political Agent, Kuwait No. T/615 Dated and received 27th November 1940. i Senior Please Naval Officer’s telegram No. telegraph your replies to me ResidentNAVAL MESSAGE. For use in Siemalto. r.iur.c. I.D.C. P.A.Bahrain, P.A. Kuwait FROV S.N.O.P.G. P.A. Vuscat N.O.I.C. Basrah. Vice Consul iChorranshahr. TOO * 0548z/£G.U.40. Request dhows may be warned that it will be at their ovn risk and peril if they navigate witidn 20 miles of coast cf Eritrea British Somaliland and Italian Somaliland. Due regard is paid tc British, Allied and Neutral legitimate shipping entering and leaTing the Ited Sea, but dhows trading with Somaliland are not of course ’’Legitimate shipping'. TOO - 0548z/?6.!3.40.From To Telegram M S M Political Resident, on board the 'Nearchus' Political Agent, Bahrain Political Agent, Kuwait Copy given to Political Agent, Muscat No. T/616 Dated and received 27th November 1940. v v (x Senior Naval Officers telegram No. 0547z/26 November 26th. Pleasetake action accordingly. ResidentNo. C/926-28/6 To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th November 19$P. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN ' » Memorandum Would you kindly issue a warning to all the dhow- owners and nakhudas in Bahrain that it will be at their own risk and peril if they navigate within 30 miles of the Coast of Eritrea and British and Italian Somaliland ? im Political Agent, Bahrain. aTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED A*/ Awali, C\ i y*L [/r (i,® Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, V No. PA-257. November 30, 1940. 1 t / His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. M- Dear Sir, In reply to your letter D.O. No/^C/QES-EB/lQ of 27th November addressed to kr. Lipp, I have to inform you that on our present schedule we have no cargoes destined to Red Sea ports. Should any of the routes be revised to include Red Sea portjs, I will inform you. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDGOVERNMENT OF BAH RAIN. CUSTOMS DEPARTMENT. 2nd December, 194o., 2nd Dhul Qaada, 133^ In reference to our conversation regarding exports from this State, it is the practice to issue to every native craft plying between Bahrain and the mainland ports of Saudi-Arabia an 'Export General Manifest', which is supported by Shipping Bills taken out in triplicate by each separate exporter. This arrangement came into being at the treaty made between the Rulers of Bahrain and Saudi-Arabia several years ago; and the local mudirs are expected to reciprocate. This manifest is issued only to the above ports; and for other exports, including craft departing in ballast, the Shipping Bill suffices for our records. Some time ago I suggested that this system should be extended to all Arabic speaking ports. We have no means of proving that the exported cargo reaches t^e port of destination, because it was thought that an insistence u^on the triplicate Shipping Bill being returned here would be (1) impossible, especially as regards the Iranian littoral, and (2) impolitic, because the illiterate nuhhudas would be bothered by formalities and consequently our export trade would diminish. The recent extension of the re-export period on optional cargo from twenty to ninety days to any port, however, considerably widens the trading scope of the local exported; and, while at the present, by far the greatest proportion of our exoorts go to (a) the mainland ports of Saudi-Arabia, and (b) to the Persian littoral, with some seasonal exports to Iraq and to India, I believe that the local exporters will take advantage of this extension, and steadily export much further afield than at present. For this reason I feel that an Export General Manifest ought to accompany every craft which leaves this port, in ballast or otherwise. The question then arises as to the advisability of proving that the exported goods actually arrive at their manifested destin ation. This could be done by arranging for the Bahrain manifest to be returned here duly endorsed by the local Customs Authority at the Port of Destination especially if such authority would, in its turn, issue a manifest covering exports to this port, when we would r.;iprocate. This practice already exists in a modified degree with the Kathiawar ports; but I doubt if effect would be given to it on the Persian littoral. I suppose it would be possible to arrange this with the Arabic oorts,(including Aden) and Iraq, and India. It is conceivable that exports might leave this port, consigned to another port, but whose ultimate real destination is an enemy country. With the above system in force the proper arrivals of craft could ultimately be checked, and any missing ones enquired into. For this reason I suggest that the system of Export General Manifests should be applied to every e*ary craft leaving this port; and a copy of same should be rendered to Yourself, so that suitable steps may be taken to prove the arrivals. Believe me, Yours sincerely, To: - Major R.G.Alban, I.A., H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN:\ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER Confidential 1]$^—This is m ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by yost to save telegraphic 7 /* * 7 _ _ 7 . i . ~ l ~ &gt;■/ / /-v 4 4 st s§ s\ . t Your telegram No* T/615 dated the 27th November 1940* 2* The only means of ascertaining oil supplies across Arabia appears to be by enquiry from the California Arabian Standard Oil Company who are prepared to give what information they have* As regards oil supplies by neutral ships it is possible that Japanese tankers which periodically call here may go to Italian Hast African ports. Measures to prevent this cannot be suggested here* 3* Oil and other supplies by dhow. Enquiries show that practically no dhov/s go from Bahrain to the Red Sea* The Director of Customs is prepared to arrange for check as far as possible of cargoes from Bahrain off loaded at India and expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, 1 o save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain* To C/936- 28/19 Political Resident, Camp Bahrain* Dated 2nd December 1940 m Vo the Arabian ports* S. 6. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34— 2,00,000. 4/-.4. If I receive information of any shipments of oil, etc., either from Bahrain or from the mainland which appear destined for Italian East Africa I shall of course follow the matter up at once. Political Agent, Bahrain. S)cs /l /] Telegram TfgH 0 Poixtj.eal Resident, at Muscat Political Agent, Bahrain. T/626 (as amended by telegram No.T/635 dated 3rd December 1940) 29th November 1940. Forxowing from Senior Naval Officer, telegram No. 0847 begins: From information at your disposal can you give me any ^nd^cation of volume of dhow traffic trading from the Persian Gulf and Arab Coast to soutn and west. Lnas. Please report. Resident - r .The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• a. 3. Tlie Political Agent* Kuwait* The Political Agent* Bahrain* The Political Agent* Muecat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement &amp; British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. L*T.»e archus, ,1 nasu— Dated.... 4 *t- ••'Qe oembejr. . 1 fl4.0 • Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Tele graft No *4 of 28 th November 1940 from Governor* Men* fisport of dates from Persian Gulf to Red Sea and Somali coast areas*Telegram Inter From Governor, Aden. To His Liajesty’s Consul, oaara. Ho.3. Repeated Political Hesident, Bushire • No.4. Dated the 28th November 1940* (delayed under Bushire telegram Ho.806 dated and received the 29th November 1940.) Shall be grateful if dhow maeters exporting dates from Persian Gulf to ded bea and Somali coast areas may be warned of danger of naval seizure should they attempt to ship to Somali coast and if they may oe informed of increased demand for Sesame in Aden. Attempts to find other date markets through Aden are being made • - Governor, Aden,Telegram M S' From Political A 'ent, Pahraln. B To Political Resident, at Kuwait No. 4-4-T Dated 9th December 194C \\ Your telegram No. T/635 dated 3rd December. 2. Less than half a dozen dhows per annum leave Bahrain for Muscat Zanzibar and Malabar Coasts. V - PoliticalTelegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Officer, Trucial Coast,Sharjah No. Dated 9th December 1940. Kindlyrenort whether there is any / dhow traffic from the Trucial Coast towards Aden or the African Coast. - Political -T elegram From To GTC • Political Sharjah. Political, Bahrain. No.685 Dated 10th December, Your telegram 448 December 9th. Yes traffic considerable. EH ■ f rl V(5 Confidential n D.O.No. C/972-28/19 Dated the 15th December 1940 I have to thank you for your letter No. PA- 257 dated the 30th November 1940 and the Information contained therein. It is presumed that no cargoes from Bahrain are sent to Arabia for overland transport to the Red Sea. Dr. R. A. Kennedy, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Yours sincerely, L BAHRAIN %onfidentlal D.O.No.C/973-28/19 Dated the 15th December 1940. D.0.No.C/§2; u I don*t know If my letter D.O.No.C/923 dated the 27th November ever reached you, but I mentioned in it that I have been asked to collect information of any cargoes off loaded on your side which may be destined for Red Sea ports either overland or by sea. 2. I would be most grateful for any information on the subject which you may care to give. F. W. Ohliger, Esq., California Arabian Standard Oil Company. DHAHRANS 1320b. For use in Signal Department only. Across NAYAL MESSAGE. Originators Instructions: r CodressTlaindress I (Indication of Priority, • No. of Intercept Group, etc.) Groups: TO: FROM: 10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45 System P L Code or Cypher Time of Operator P.O.O.W. Receipt Despatch 50 Date it ; V 1 !No. C/976-28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, 16th December 1940. To The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum I am sorry to trouble you so often but could you kindly send me in duplicate fortnightly summaries of cargoes and destination of dhow traffic from Bahrain. u Political Agent, Bahrain.r No. C/977-28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, 16th December 1940. To v The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, \ Sharjah. frlemo random Would it be possible for you to send me every fortnight summaries, in duplicate, of cargoes and destination of dhow traffic from the Trucial Coast - at any rate from Sharjah and Dubai 7 Political Agent, Bahrain.THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN 15th December, 1940., 15th Dhul ^aada, 1359., % I forward herewith a file containing copies of Export General Manifests of exports and/direct transhipments from the State of Bahrain from 1st December to 14th December, 1940, as desired, please. u4&lt; ^ ^C ^ C THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-278. December 16, 1940. V 4 V / v His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, In reply to your letter C/972-28/19 dated December 15, 1940. No cargoes from The Bahrein Petroleum Company are sent to Arabia for overland transport to the Red Sea. I have no knowledge of what may be sent by other concerns or individuals for conveyance by the over land route. Yours very truly, Chief Local Representative, / THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD.yVr California Arabian Standard Oil Company Dhahran, Saudi Arabia December 16, 3 PDRSOITAL \ Dear Major Alban: ‘/hen I was in Bahrein about two we discussed the substance of your letter No. 0/911. Since returning to this side I have found that we have no record of a shipment of petrol arriving here by the tanker cruiser 'Prusa'. The Saudi Arabian (Government did receive shipments of petroleum products about the time indicated in your letter. The products received were: On the 5. S. Utahan : Arrived Has Tanura August IP, 1940. 1. 926 55-gallon drums of aviation petrol (actually 50,000 U. 3. gallons) 2. 37 55-gallon drums of aviation lube oil (actually 2,000 U. 3. gallons) 3. 10,000 15-gallon drums of ordinary petrol (actually 150,000 U. 3. gallons) Of these items, the entire shipments re ceived under 1, and 2 are now at A1 Phobar stored in their original containers. The petrol under 3 originally was transshipped to Jubail by dhow, but recently has been moved to Manifa and Sa^aniya by dhow. On the S. 3. Steelworker : Arrived Aas Tanura August 22. 1. 10,000 15-gallon drums of ordinary petrol (actually 150,000 U. S. gallons) This petrol was sent to Jubail by dhow, and some of it has been moved to the interior by motor trucks. In addition to these two shipments there have been a number of smaller shipments to this side of ordinary petrol for the account of the Saudi Arab Government fromPi - 2 - Bahrein during the past year. A record of these can be made available to you if you care to have it. Sincerely, FWO :RDhahran, Saudi Arabia December 16, 1940 MAJOR R. G. ALBAN, 0. B. S., His Britannic Majesty 1 3 Poli Bahrein. i W Dear Major Alban': side for ports on the Ked Sea, I wish to advise you that there have been no shipments of petroleum products from the mainland to Red Sea ports. The only shipment from the Persian Gulf was the cargo of the tanker 'Helka' which was loaded out of Bahrein, and the details of which you are familiar. 7/e will advise you when and if there are any shipments off the mainland in the future. Sincerely,No. C/995-28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd December '40 To The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. V Memorandum l Reference your memorandum No. PA/G/29/514 dated the 15th December 1940. 2. The file containing Export General Manifests is returned herewith with thanks. Political Agent, Bahrain,3SC3ST Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd December 1940 D.O. No. C/993-28/19 In continuation of my demi-official letter No. C/918 dated the 26th November 1940, I forward V herewith a copy of a letter on the subject now received from Mr. Ohliger. It will be seen that Mr. Ohliger now says that he has no record of any petrol having arrived in Dhahran by the tanker 'Prusa'• Yours sincerely, W Commodore Cosmo M. Graham, R.N., Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf.1 ^4 ^ Confidential &lt;/\ i 3 of No. C/994-28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd December 1940 Sir, I have the honour to refer to your confidential letter No. 504 dated the 26th November 1940. V ^ ^ t 2. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited report that on their present schedule they have no cargoes destined for Red Sea ports nor do they send any cargoes to Arabia for overland transport to the Red Sea. Should any shipments be made to Red Sea ports they have promised to inform me. b 3. Th • California Arabian Standard Oil Company have also replied stating that there have been no shipments of petroleum products from the mainland to Red Sea ports. The only shipment from the Persian Gulf was the cargo of the tanker ,, Helka M which was loaded off at Bahrain. They have also promised to advise me should there be any shipments off the mainland in the future. 4. As regards shipments across Arabia by the Califor nia Arabian Standard Oil Company this has already been referred to in my demi-official letter No. C/918 of the 26th November 1940. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant L Political Agent, Bahrain.-Tv ISjext al Mlxibix, ' v ^?,~ IKalyrain (E) $exxmn (&amp;nlt A local importer of some note, Hajy Abdul aziz Aly Al Bassam, received tl following telegram:- DNB 6/R ADEN 13...18...2o3o. LC. ABDULAZIZ BASSAM BAHRAIN. CABLE PRICES KEROSENE PETROL GIF ADEN SHIPMENT DHOW BAZARA. . . Having regard to recent official notices etc., I have advised Hajy Abdulaziz to have nothing to do with this kind of business, which appears to me to be of a very unusual character. Believe me, Yours sincerely, To: - Major R.0.Alban, O.B.E., I.A., The Agency, BAHRAIN:Confidential No. C/9^2 Political Agency, Banrain, 21st December 1940 To The Senior Naval Officer, Persian uuxf. Memorandum The Direcuor of Customs informs me that a local importer of some note, Haji Abdul Aziz All al B&amp;ssam, received the following telegram i DNB 6/R ADEN....13....18....2030 LC. ABDUhAZIZ BASSAM BAHRAIN CABnE PRICES KEROSENE PETROS GIF ADEN SHIPMENT DHOW BaZARA. The Director of Customs says that he has advised Haji Abdul Aziz to have nothing to do with this business which appears to be of a very unusual character. 2. Possibly the Aden Authorities might be interested in this telegram Political Agent, Bahrain. /ITelegram 'S' % Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 862 23rd December 1940 . c-v / r Your telegram Do. 447 December 9th. Please confirm figure is only half a dozen. From To No. Dated - VFrom To No. Dated Telegram 'S M Political Agent, Bahrain Political Resident, Bushire 471 24th December 1940 Your telegram No. 862 December 23rd. Confirmed. - Political - r fConfidential D.C.No.C/707-8/8 © Sharjah, 18th December 1940 Will you please refer to your memorandum No.C/977- 28/19 of 16th December 1940, regarding census of Dhow traffic on the Trucial Coast ? Sharjah but these really only amount to a permit to leave. Presumably, your enquiry is in the nature of a war measure and it might therefore be possible to induce these rulers to expand the present system sufficiently to record details of cargoes and their destinations. This would of course involve employing at least one extra clerk in each of the respective Customs and the point arises v/hether Government or the rulers concerned are expected to pay for this extra staff. 3. Abu Dhabi has a similar system. keep no check on outward traffic but they do keep some form of records of imports for taxation purposes. It might there for be possible to expand these systems to check up on 2 Records of outward traffic are kept at Dubai and 4 Ajman, On al Qaiwain, Ras al Khaimah and Kalba Major R.G.E.Alban, O.B.E. Political Agent, Bahr In • exports // exports but again the question of expensed arises# 5. A further point is that my office, as at present constituted, could not possibly translate and consolidate into one fortnightly summary in English the numerous Arabic records which are to be expected, if this system is adopted. The most we could do, without extra staff, is to collect the Arabic records and send them to Bahrain for further action*Political Resident, Pushire. Political Agent, Bahrain Political Agent, Kuwait Political Agent, Muscat 864 Dated 23rd December 1940 Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf's telegram No. 0622 Z December 13th. Please take action accordingly sending me copies of your reports.D.O. Ho. C/1004-23/19 Dated the 31st December 1940 /V NK Rererence your demi-official letter No. C/707-8/8 dated the 18th December 1940 about dhow traffic. 2. I do not think we need bother about detailed records of cargoes; it will be quite sufficient if the following information can be got from the various ports of the Trucial Coast s f- * r . ’i* Type of vessel. Reg. No. Name of Vessel Name of Nakhuda Cargo Destina tion Date of sailing i.e. Boom Dates, dried fish etc. 2. Also we do not need to worry about small boats but only about the large ocean going craft which are likely to go far afield. In a small town the departure of one of these is quite an event and I think everyone would know all about it. The Shaikhs should therefore be able to let you know whenever a big boat sails from his area without any trouble to himself beyond writing the letter. 3. I should be inclined to ask them to write to you when ever a big ship leaves their area, giving you the above infor mation which you might if you will send me at once as it comes in, as the Naval authorities want to know all departures witnout delay. Captain R.D* Metcalfe, I.A., Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Yours sincerely. u wD.O. Ho. C/1005-28/19 Dt-ted the 31st December 1840 V Many thanits for your note of the 21st December about the message received by Haji Abdul Asia All A1 Bassam about Kerosene and Petrol, 2. I nave passed It on to those Interested and any further such items of Interest will be welcome. Yours sincerely. Director of Customs, Bahrain/'-N No. C/1006-28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 31st December 1940. To The Director of Customs and Port Officer, 3 A a h A I N Memorandum Reference my memorandum No. C/976 dated the 16th December 1940. 2. It would be much appreciated if the details asked for could be sent as soon after the departure of each dhow as possible as the information loses its value if delayed. The information need not be very detailed, only sufficient to enable the dhow to be recognised again and cargo checked in Type of vessel Reg. No. Name of vessel Name of Nakhuda Cargo I lestina- tion Date of sailing E m X y z Dates 10 bags Fish 10 mds Kersosene 5 tins etc. Basra Karachi etc. 25/12/40 . . Only details of large sea-going craft are required. m Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram ^rom Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah No. 1 Dated 2nd January 1941 Urgent Please enquire and telegraph estimate of number of large ocean-going craft on whole Trucial Coast, Political -THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 4-1-41. 6th Dhul Haj, 1359., u H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN: MEMORANDUM: - t- ^°\ u v H4\ your* C/loo6-28/19 of the 31-12-39. , may I mention that I have already arranged to communicate the required information daily (as occasion arises) direct to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf; and, with your approval, I will continue to do so. Under these circumstances, I trust that a fortnightly report to Yourself will be acceptable for records purposes, especially as the telephone service is not very good, please. lyU* . 'syU i DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN:No. C/12 - 28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, 7th January 1941. To The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No. P^/HL/9/549 dated the 4th January 1941 regarding dhow traffic. 2. The arrangement is quite satisfactory.Oar SECRET i, ur TO. P.R.P.G. N.O.I.C. Basrah. (R) P.A. B«ahraln ^ P'ROM 3.N.O.P.G. P.A« Muscat. P.A# Kuwait. 17^ I.D.C. VOPOZ 87/2. Groups 111 TOO = 08372/10.1.41. Follcrcring received frcsn C—in-C.,E.I. begins - (i) A case has occurred of 4 dhovrs sailing froci 3urr in Sultanate of Hihiscat for Zanzibar and Mombassa being sent into Mogadishu by Italian Aircraft. One vras released as cargo was unacceptable but three others with cargoes of dates were detained. (ii) Nakhudas of British dhows are to be instructed, and neutral dhows advised, to keep at least 120 miles from Italian coasts and only to make landfall on British Coast. Remind them of 50 mile dangerous zone off Italian coasts and encourage them to ignore Italian aircraft orders. TOO * 0752/6.1.40. ends. 2. Request appropriate action may be taken. TOO » 0837z/10.1.41. 0c 10 g.joD J roia -From To Mo. Dated Telegram Inter Political Resident, Eushire Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat Political Agent, Kuwait. 44 11th January 1941 Senior Maval Officer’s Mo. 0837Z January ICth. Please take action accordingly.SECRET ; '.Q.tA r !,4&gt; Sir, \&gt;‘ ' Office of enior Naval Officer, Persian &gt;ulf• H.M # Haval Base, Bahrain# l?th January, 1941# VISIT AND SEABCH OF NATIVE I have the honour to inform you that X have received instructions from the ComniimdeTvLrv-Chief, aat Indies Station that, in order to discourage illicit traffic *hich is undoubtedly being carried on, the Khor Kuwai patrol should from time to time exercise right of visiting and searching (Slows leaving the Persian Gulf and if necessary take them into Khor Kuwai for further examination. Zm It would be appreciated if the authorities to rhest a copy of this letter is addressed could establish and give me early information of any vessels suspected of such trading which may depart from ports under their observation. 5. I m forwarding a copy of this letter to the Naval Officcr-in-Ohargo, Basrah for similar action in connection with dhows leaving the Ghstt-el^Arab. I have the honour to be, Sir, lour obedient Servant, (Copies to i- The Political Agents, Kuwait, Bahraini and Muscat)SECRET No. C/40 - 28/19 I Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th January 1941. To The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Memorandum The Naval Authorities here have informed me that in order to discourage illicit traffic which is undoubtedly being carried on, they intend from time to time to exercise their right of visiting and searching dhows leaving the Persian Gulf. They therefore request early information of any vessels suspected of such illicit trading which may depart from ports under your observation. 2. I should be most grateful if you would kindly assist by forwarding the required information. Political Agent, Bahrain.No. C/42 - 28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th January 1941. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN Memorandum Reference my memorandum No. C/926 dated the 30th November 1940. 2. Would you kindly remind once again all the nakhudas and dhow owners in Bahrain that it is dangerous to navigate within 30 miles of the Coast of Britrea and British and Italian Somaliland and advise them that they should keep at least 120 miles away from Italian Coasts and should make landfall only on the British Coast. They should complete3.y ignore any orders they might receive from Italian aircraft. Political Agent, BahrainNo. C/43 - 28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th January 1941 To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Memorandum Please widely circulate amongst all nakhudas and dhow owners on the Trucial Coast that the Italian Coasts in Africa are dangerous to navigation and that they should keep at least 120 miles av.ay from the Italian Coasts, making landfall only on British Coast. They should also he advised to ignore completely any orders they might receive from Italian aircraft. u Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER Confidential [N. —This TsS ci/tb OBIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, 1 o save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire No, C/52 - 28/19 Dated 16th January 'ii , • Dhow Traffic , hr r Reference your telegram No. 44 dated the 11th January 1941. 2. I have asked the authorities concerned to warn the nakhudas and dhow—owners in Bahrain, Qatar and the -rucial Coast accordingly. L. Political Agent, Bahrain S. 6. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—20-7-34—2,00,000.27 'elegram ’’S' Repeated No. Dated Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait Political /igent, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. 61 17th January 1941 ’ , ' V , '-VV 1 *' Senior Naval Officer’s telegram 0837 Z dated January 14th. Dhow traffic. Please comply.SECRET No. ' C/77 - 28/19 The Political Agept, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:*- The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undsrmentioned document (s ) for favour of compliance The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 23rd January...19.41 Reference to previous correspondence: i This Agency demi-official letter No. C/1004 dated the 31st December 1940 Description Of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. P» / f 1. S.N.O.P.G* s telegram No. 0622z dated the 13th December 1940 2. S.N.O.P.G’s telegram No. 0837z dated the 14th January 1941 Dhow TrafficConfidential No. c/78 - 28/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his comph'men's to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and has the honour to send him a copy of the trad^rmentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 23rd January 1941 Reference to previous correspondence: Description Of Enclosure, Name and Date. j Subject. Retun of Dhow Traffic during fortnight 15th January in Bahrain ending 1941.%(5 SECRET No. C/88 - 28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th January 1941 / Sir, I have the honour to refer to your telegram No. 0837z dated the 14th January 1941 about dhow traffic. 2. The arrangement aa far as Bahrain is concerned is that the Director of Customs informs the Naval autho rities direct as soon as any dhow leaves Bahrain with all the necessary particulars, and sends a consolidated state ment to me once in a fortnight, a copy of which is forward ed to you (vide my Printed letter No. C/78 dated the 23rd January 1941). It is presumed therefore that telegraphic information to you of dhow traffic will not be required for Bahrain. # to comply with your suggestion made in the telegram under reference as far as the Trucial Coast ports are concerned. 4. I hope this procedure has your approval. 3. I have asked the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, leer, Trucial Coast, Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be, Sir, L Political Agent, Bahrain. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian GulfCONFIDENTIAL. Na 53-S of 1941 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat, / iv/ith a re^uett The Political Agent, Bahrain,') ! that euch action The Political Agent, Fuwait, ) | ae ie -.otBible may I be taiien to meet the I Company'e withes* The Senior .Naval Officer, Pertian Uulf, for information* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.l9.th. .J.anuaJfy..l9.4A*. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Vice Consul, *horram^hahr f e telegram ' o* 1172 dated 14th January i941. Unautnorited shipments of kerosene oil from Persian Gulf*79/59 Telegram « From To No, 1172. Dated 14th received V Vice Coneul, Khorramehahra Political Resident, Buehire 15th January 1941. Following from Anglo-Iranian Oil Company begins, Certain kerosene ehipmente have been made in last few months from Muscat district to Aden and Hed Sea area in dhows. This is unusual and for other commercial reasons we are anxious to prohibit sue h un&amp;uthorised shipments from all Gulf ports. We have instructed all our agents suitably and would be grateful for any assistance you can give to prevent ships leaving areas in question. Snd - BRITCONSUL - AVM 19/1/41Confide .tial No. C/83 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th January 1941. To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, Memorandum / Copy of telegram No. 1172 dated the 14th January 1941 from the Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr, is forwarded to you with the request that if any such shipments of kerosene are taking place in your area the matter may kindly be reported to me L Political Agent, Bahrain, in §;W',4' 3EGIIST ITo .S/66-S/8 • British Agency, Sharjah, 2Cth Januc ry 1941, To, The Political A 0 entj Bahrain* Lienor a ndum Tour memorandum No.0/40-28/19 of 14th January 1941. * 2 . ’/ill you plear e explc in in more detail vh- t exactly k meant by the term ” illicit traffic ' ? Does it mean trade with enemy countries or.trrde in contraband with neutral countries as well ? If the latter, may I have a list of conuraban* articles ?SEC 1 K t D.O.No.C/102-23/19. Dated the 29th January 1941- Dear Metcalfe, \ Your memorandum No.3/66-8/8 dated the 20th January 1941. 2. The Contraband Hat la much too long to send you and In any case includes nearly every article of trade. 'Illicit' traffic means really taking goods of any sort either direct to an enemy country or by way of a neutral country. 3. The object is to prevent the enemy getting possess ion of co. modities which would help him to continue his resistance - these might be fuel oils etc., cotton, food stuffs and so on. We should use our discretion of course and only report cases of a distinctly suspicious character. Yours sincerely, (rk ^ 1 |4^. Capt in d. D. Metcalfe, Political Officer Trucial Coast, 3 H A n J A H |SECRET No.507 , Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. H.M.Naval Base, Bahrain. 29th January, 1941. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.c/88-28/19 of 26th January, 1941. The arrangements which exist in Bahrain at present are entirely satisfactory. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain. COMMODORETHE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN 2nd Beoruary,1941., 6th Mahurrurn, 136©., H. B. M’s Political Bahrain. £ Ref. your memorandum. No:C/1006-28/19, dated the olst December, 1940. 2. There hf-ive been no movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 31st January, 1941, please. *.Confidential D.0.No *0/111-8/8 © Sharjah, 3rd February 1941® Will you please refer to your Confidential memorandum No.C/83 of 28th January 1941, regarding kerosine shipments from Muscat ? 2. I have been able to discuss this question with Mr.Barker and Khan Sahib Husain of the .Anglo-Iranian Oil Company who were also informed of the position by their Company. It appears that a certain Muhammad bin *Ali of Sur, Muscat bought up all available supplies.about 800 tins in the Dubai bazaar a short while ago and, it is alleged, shipped them to Makalla. This happened before our control of big sea going craft was instituted. 3. Khan Sahib Husain has been instructed to ensure that retailers shall in future keep no stocks surplus to the absolute minimum required for local consumption. Major R.G.E.Alban,0.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential C/143 - 28/19 No. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. / Bahrain. I j' and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated /SV/J /gw Reference to previous correspondence: S.N.O* s telegram No.0837 z/14/1/41. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Telegram No.145 dated the 12 th February 1941 from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, to the Poli tical Agent, Bahrain. Subject. 4 ^ Dhow Traffic• / ^ o A ■ ’ 'p • y % S •-•'X ^ ACONFIDENTIAL. No. i£)7-b of 19 41 r 1 a The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The P G Iiticsl Agent» Behrein * and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (s). rv £ British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated, 13th February 19 41* Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1* Ahwaz telegram No. 53» dated the 26th October 1940* 2* Ahwaz letter No. 9£(22/7/253}&gt; dated the 30th December 19 40 . Subject. Shipment of shells from Bahrain by S.^. Wgrina. Its. © ry' T e Icgram From Tc Repeated « S H King, Ahwez* s Minister, Tehran. H.M f s Ambassedor, Bagdad# Political Resident, Bubhire • Copy by post to Vice Consul, Khorramshahr. No. 53 Bated 26th received 27th October 1940. ,s- yr Your te le grain No* 79 and my letter dated 21st September. I am informed new that consignment of shells which arrived Bandar Shshpur during August by dhow are being sent to Bandar Pahlevi as al&amp;c 29 cases shells shipped in British Indian ship W 0 rina which left Bahrain at end of August Hi - KING - ■To H. M* Ambassador» Bagdad# * H. M* Consul-General» Busiiire , With compliments from H«M« Consul# Ahwaz NOo 98. BRITI3K CCNSUIAT3# (22/7/253) jj AHWAZ. December 30th, 1940 Sir, With reference to my telegram No, 53 of October 26th, 19 4C, which was repeated to Bagdad and Bushire , regarding consignments of shells arriving in Iran from Bahrain and suspected of being in transit for Germany and to your reply, telegram Nc, 96 of Nov, 7th, 1940, stating that enquiries showed that no such goods have arrived at Pahlevi and that the exportation of shells was prohibited, I stn now info rmed that the 29 cases of sea shells whipped in the British s. s, Warina from Bahrain last August have been cleared l^y Abdul Karim Qumeshi, a merchant and Government contractor of Ahwaz, and are being forwarded immediately to Said Rais of Tehran who is know here as a German buying agent • The shipper of these goods in Bahrain was a certain M,A, Bushiri, 2. As regards the thousand bags which arrived at Bandar Shah- pur by dhow , details are difficult to obtain but I am again creditably informed that they are in fact being forwarded to Pahlevi and that 600 bags are already tberc awaiting shipment. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Mgjesty’s Ambassador at Bagdad and His Majesty’s C on s ul-Gane ral at Bushire. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, / Sd. A.H. KING H.M’s Consul Sir Reader W. Bullard, K, C.M.G,, C.I.E., His Britannic Maj e sty * s Minister ,etc. » etc., British legation, Tehran.Sh ipment of Kerosene from Uulf P o rts t o the Red Sea Ar ea• A. CONSIGN :.ij£N T S ARRI J&amp;V R&amp;D SKA ARIg. Date of Advice Name of Craft 1 ) 6 - 12 - 40 - 2 ) 6 - 12 - 40 - 3 ) 10 - 1 - 41 All TARHANRAN 4) i o 1 - 41 J KHAR 5 ) 21 - 1 — 41 M U R 2 0 O K AS ADVISED BY CAIRO VIA LONDON. Number of Tins Alleged Port of Origin Port of Di scharge 600 Muscat nakalla 380 M Not stated 800 « M 120 M M 500 m n 2400 h• informat ion _re the se shi p ments a scertained lo ca lly* iix Muscat 20/26-1-41 in regard to shipments ^3) and (4^ it is stated that one Majid Muscat agent for dashvedi of Makalla, bought supplies from local herosene dealers and arranged export. The supplies for ^0) are stated to have been provided by a Muscat dealer named Khimji Ramdas. Supplies alleged to have been loaded at Dubai for export to Makalla by two or three vessels emanating from Sur. Alleged that supplies shipped from Muscat to the Sultan's Dhofar territory by Haji haqir Haji Abul-Latif have subsequently been forwarded to theRed Sea Area. 2 . Hlx Duoai 17 - 1 - 41 . In December 1940 one Mohammad Ali, merchant of Sur, bought 800 tins from dealers in Dubai and these were shipped for Sur/Makalla by the native craft ’'3AN300K H , Nakhoda Mobarak Bin Abdulla of bur. $. Steps taken by A.l.O.C. to s uppress t r affic . 9-12-40 Muscat instructed by telegram to prevent further exportations. lb - 12 - 40 All ^ulf Ports circularised with the instruction that no sales may be made for export beyond their legitimate sales areas. 5 - 1-41 H.B.M's Political Agent at Muscat advised for his information of shipments alleged to have been made from Muscat. 13 - 1-41 Telegram sent to H.B.M's Political A e gident at Bushire requesting assistance in prevention of further shipments Telegrams have also been exchanged witheMuscat and Dubai, investi gating shipments as they have been reported to us. Our Agent at Muscat advises that all sales to dealers have been stopped (which we interpret as meaning wholesale deliveries have stopped and other sales are closely controlled) and an inspector has been sent there for a full enquiry intoenquiry into the matter. He arrived on the 3rd February and has instructions to discuss with H.B.M’s Political Agent any further measures that may oe necessary, as on the ^9th January our agent reported that the Director of Customs informed him that exports from Muscat territory to British territory cannot be forbidden by him without instructions from the Political Agent. D. iiinquAries received by o ur Agents for s uppli es to the Hed Sea Area , which have not been implemented in view of our Circula r of the 15th Decembe r 19 i0_._ Unauiry Made at Date intending Buyer Bo. of Tins De stination D Kuwait o -12-40 - 8000 Hadeida/kakalla 2) Khor*3hahr •* i lb -12-40 Mohd.Ilatruk &amp; Baser Abdul Mohsin Kerafi bOOO to 10,000 Hydramut Ports 3) Bahrain hast week December Yusaf All Akbar 10,000 Makalla 4) -do- -do- Abdul Aziz Bin Ali 10,000 -do- £&gt;) -do- -do- Suleiman Aumad Kl Bassam 5,000 -GO- -do- 4 -12-40 iiaj i Baqir Haj i Abdul-hatif (Muscat) 20,000 ha kalla/Aden. 00O00Confidential No C/154-28/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated, the 18th February 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and- Date. Subject. r Return of Dhow traffic during the fortnight ending 15th February 1941.Confidential No. C/200-28/19. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated_lst March 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ Memorandum No.C/195-8/8(c) from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast to the Politi cal Agent, Bahrain. Dhow Traffic.THE GUST01:HCUSE: BAHRAIN 2nd Harch, 1941., 4th Eaffar, 13bO., 0 * H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. MEM OR ANDUM : - In reference to your No;c/lOG6-26/19, dated the 31st December, 1940, I enclose herewith, in duplicate, a statement showing the movements of Inrge sea-going craft during the fortnight Rndinp- 28th February, 1941, please. Enclosures:--Confidential No. C/240-29/19. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated the 13th March 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Return of Dhov during the fortnig* 28th FebruH. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM:» ^ In referenc e to your No:C/1006-28/19, dated the Slat December,1940, I enclose herewith, in duplicate, a statement showing the movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 15th March, 1941,please. ^ 6 Enclosures: -Xr-'Confidential No. C/246-28/19. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 4he 16th March 1941. Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure. Return of Dhov for the fortnight 1941. Traffic nding 15th March* Confidential No. C/278-28/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated, the 27th March. 1941. Reference to previous correspondence: / S.N.O's telegram No. 0837z dated 14th January 1941. Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum No.C/270 dated 23rd March 1941 from the political Officer Trucial Dhow Traffic• Coast to the Political Agent, Bahrain. x' YOU T * . \ i \ • fj //W / V \ v \ 'lA /Telegram From Inter To Chief Secretary, Dar es Salaam Political Agent, Bahrain. No. (Mutilated) Dated the 3rd received the 4th April 1941. Following dhows have left Lindi for Chitaalla. (a) FATELKHEIR master SALUM ABDALLAH v/ith 100 tins sesame oil. (b) NASSOR with 371 bags sesame. (c) FATELKHIR master Khamis Said with 240 bags sesame. Chief Secretary.Confidential No.C/310-28/19. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 7th April 1941 To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum I have received information that the following dhows have left Lindi for Chitaalla. (a) 'Fatelkheir” Master Salum Abdallah 100 tins sesame oil. (b) f, Nassor' 371 bags sesame (c) 'Fatelkhir'* Master Khamis Said 240 bags sesame. 2. I should be grateful if you would let me know whether you know these dhows. They may possibly be coming here. I am unable to locate Chitaalla on any map. u. Political Agent, BahrainConfidential No. 0/315-28/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian 9ulf, Bahrain* and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) X I cannot locate Chitaala* The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated the 7th April'1941 Reference to previous correspondence: Description i&gt;f Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /\r / v Telegram dated 3rd April ^ 1941 from Chief Secretary, Dhow Traffic* Dar es Salaam, to the Politi cal Agent, Bahrain*Telegram Inter, From Chief Secretary, Dar es Salaam. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 274. Dated and received the 9th April 1941. Following dhows have left K^ALE for BASRA (a) GHANIMA (b) AMANTTALA, both with cargo of mangrove poles. Chiefsec fc snoP&amp;r * ^ e /- c ' /bUccct KTHE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: No PA/NC/.^ \ ' 14th Rabia.I•, 1360 ., loth April, 1941. To: - F B.M‘s Political Agent, l,*iHRAIN : • MEMORANDUM: - /V ’ In reference to your N Q :C/31o-28/19 of the 7 - 4 - 41 ., the name Nassor' is believed generally to be used for an Indian craft; while the name 'Fath al Kheyr' is known to me to have been given to several Arabian and Indian craft. The port of Lindi is believed to be in Africa: while it is guessed that the port of Chitaalla is an Indian port; and the sesame oil, known locally as gingelli oil extracted from the sesamum, is dealt with in the neighbourhood of Surat in India. in x r, , A note is bein s kept of these craft; and, should thev call at Bahrain, the arrivals will be reported to you, please.No. Confiaentiel C/bbS - 28/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated__19tll April 19 4 1 Reference to previous correspondence: S.N.O’s tel gram No. 0oc7z dated 14th January 1941 Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Mer^randum No. C/b25-o/8(c) daoud the ^4th April .941 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Dhow Traffic.L Inter (10) Chief Secretary, Dar es Salaam. Political Agent, Bahrain. Telegram From To No. 294 Dated and received the 18th April 1941. © r ? /M [c*■■ fiA No. C/o4o - 28/19 Politicel Agency, Bahrein, the 20th April u41. To The Senior Nevel Officer, Persian Gulf. The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum \ I have received information that, the following dhows have left Kwale about 18th April 1941: (1) w SALAMTI” for Bahrain with a cargo of mangrove poles; (2) 'SAMHAN” for Qatar with e cargo of mangrove poles and incense. L Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram Inter (10) From Chief Secretary, Dar es Salaam, Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 307 Bated 23rd receivedthe 24th April 1041 .Telegram From Inter (10) Chief Secretary, Dar es Salaam. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 331 Dated and received the 30th April 1941. Following dhows left Dar es Salaam with cargo direct for porms given after ti eir names : A1 Aipan Mukalla A1 Mansur - Makalla Sadalkarim - Sehud Fatalkheir - Sehud Fatalkheir - Shaher El Jessar - Shaher El Jessar - Sehud 50 bags Millet 18 bags Maize 2 cases Kerosene 269 bags Millet 116 bags Maize 125 bags Sesame 14 tins Shee - 246 bags Millet 61 bags Millet 5 bags Maize 1 case Sesame oil - 150 bags Millet 237 bags Millet 50 bags Maize 110 cases Ohee 16 bags ground nuts 3 cases Kerosene 218 bags Millet 10 bags Starch. 2 . Following dhows left Dar es Salaam with cargo for transhipment at Zanzibar to ports given after their numbers : Z 83 Z 48 Shaher - Makalla 206 bags Millet 2 bags Maize 10 cases Ghee 44 bags Sesame 25 bags ground nuts 30 cases GheeNo. Confidential % -k l ' i C/398-28/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. D ated„ 3rd May 1941 Reference to previous correspondence: Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. / Telegram No. 331 from the Chief Secretary, Dar es Salaam, dated the 30th April 1941 X Subject. Dhow Trafficno spa/hl/.*! H.B.M’s Political Agent, BaT^ain. THE CDSTOTJIHOUSE: BAHRAIN 4th May, 1941., 8th fy/Thany, 1360., i-EmaAmiM:- Ref. your memorandum No:C/10C6-28/19, dated the 31st December, 1940. 2. There have been no movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 30th April, 1941, please. OF CUSTOMS AND ^ PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN^ r / TConfidential 'I No.C/434-28/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th Vay 1941. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum Inf emotion has been received from thelchlef Secre- - i tary, Dar es Salaam that the following nlhows have left ; v ale via Zanzibar with cargoes of mangrove poles t«» (i) for Bahrain 'Fatal Kher' (master Mohammed Xhalfan) and 'Fatal' (master Abdullah Famed). (11) for Arabia - 'Hleean'. t/ No: PA/Hl/ / THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN 18th May,1941., 22nd R/Thany,1360., H. B. M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN* MEMORANTOM:- Ref. your memorandum No :c/1006-28/19, dated the 31st Decern'oe r, 1940. 2 # There have been no movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 15th May,1941,please. sTelegram From To S Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain No. 489 Dated and received the 21st May 1941. Senior Naval Officer’s telegram No. 0837 z/ January 14th. Senior Naval Officer has intimated that telegraphic reports of dhow sailings are no longer required.I\z ® THE GUSTOLHiOUSB: BAHRAIET: 2nd June, 1941., 8th J/Awal,1560*, H. B. M’s Political Agent, BAHRAI N. MEHORANBUK:- Ref. your memorandum No:C/1006-28/19, dated the 31st December, 1940. 2. There have been no movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 31st May, 1941, please. STRICT OR OP CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAV No:PA/HL H. B # M*s Political Agent, BAHRAIN. THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 17th August, 1941., 2jth Rajab, 1360 ., Ref. your memorandum No:C/1006-28/19 f dated the 31st December, 1940. There have been no movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 15th August, 1941. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. ,THE CUSTOLEHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 1st September, 194-1., 10th Shabban, 1360 ., H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM : Ref. your memorandum No:C/1006-28/19, dated the 31st December, 194-0. There have been no movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 31st August, 1941 . / DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. WNdip* CONFIDENTIAL . No - 0/370 of 1941. @ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. 2 * 3. 4. 5 . 6 . The Political Agent, Kuwait* ^ The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The Political Agent, Uuaoat* H'M’s Consul, Kerman* HtM’s Vice Consul, Bushire* H.M’s Vice Consul, Khorramshahr• for favour of comment, to H.M f s Minister, Tehran for information, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). m Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, jJamj^Bahrain* D a ted ... 2 .. Augu e t- • -1941* Reference to previous correspondence !S j % i 1 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India Letter NO.D.2329-N/41, dated 30th June 1941 with enclosure«• Kmployment by the enemy of dhow traffic*S E C R E C T. D.Q.N0.D.2329-H/41. External Affairs Department, Simla* The 30th June 1941* «► Employment by the enemy of dhow traffic. Dear Colonel, I am desired to forward a copy of a demi-official letter from the Intelligence Bureau (Home Department, Government of India) No. 29/For/4l(fr) dated the 9th May 1941, and to request that if you see no objection, action on similar lines may be taken in respect of the areas with which you are concerned and the r esult com.unicated to the Government of India in due course. Yours sincerely, Sd/- A.S.B.Shah. The Hon»ble Lt.-Colonel C.G. Prior, CIE., Political Resident in he Persian Gulf; i 1 / r. y * No. 29/For/4l(l) Intelligence x^ureau. Home Department, GOVEKNMENT OP INDIA. New Delhi, dated the 9th Nay 1941. Dear Please refer to this Bureau's Secret D.O.No.36/for/40 dated 3lst December, 1940, in connexion with the employment by the enemy of dhow traffic operating between Iraq, Iran, India, and Sast Africa. Snquiries so far made confirm the existence of regular dhow traffic between these countries, but there is as yet no evidence of enemy control or of the use of these dhows for the conveyance of information. What has emerged, however, is the fact that surveillance ever this traffic cannot be rendered really effective from the security point of view through existing agencies much as the Customs. i A, '• v In view of the dangers inherent in the situation, and particularly in view of the recent information that two parties of enemy agents, one including the Sami Pir, are likely to approach India from the Middle Bast in the near future, the view taken here is that everything possible must be done to improve intelligence in connexion with this dhow traffic. It is felt that only by the effettive organization of intelligence can we hope to tackle this problem at all successfully. We are, therefore, writing to ask if you will again examine the position carefully to see how intelligence at ports used by dhow traffic can be improvedi it is known for example that, in Purandhar, one particular agent deals with almost all the Arab traders who visit that Port, and it is possible that such is also the case elsewhere. Such persons would be useful as agents and would probably not demand exorbitant renumeration in return for their help. At the same time it would probably be beneficial to employ in the same way one or two men of the dhows’ crews provided suitable persons can be found and provided again that you have an officer who can understand and control persons of this class. In due course we shall be glad to have any information you manage to secure so that we can circulate it to all concerned or otherwise make use of it. Yours sincerely, Sd/- B,V.Drake, for Iff.K.Johnston. Tp 1. K.R.Eates, Esquire, I # P. Supdt• of Police, i/c S.B. &amp; C.I. E., Sind, Karachi. 2. M.Worth, Esquire, I.C.S., Secretar to the Hon’ble the Resident, W. I.State®,Rajkot. 3. J.G.Maxwell Cumbleton, Esquire, D.I.G., of Police, W.I. &amp; Gujrat States, Rajkot. 4. C.W.E.U’ren, Esquire, I.P. Deputy Commissioner Of Police, S.B.II, Bombay. 5. J.Abernethy, Esquire, I.P. Asst, to D.I.G. of Police, G.I. ., Bombay Province,Poona. 6. Lt.-Col. G.P.Murphy, Resident for the Madras States, Madras Agency Camp. Copy toi- 1. J.R.Harris, Esq., I.P., Central Intelligence Officer, Karachi 2. F.W•0’ Gorman, Esq., 0.B.B.,I.P. , Central Intelligence Officer, B 0 mbay, 3. H.Keene,Esq., I.P. Central Intelligence Office, Madras. Sd/- E.G.Drake, for Assistant Director (P). r ■ V : vSECRE T Mo. S w* Office of the Poiicicai Agent, Bahrain, Camp Karachi, the 6th September 1341 To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, camp Bahrain. Subject Employment by the enemy of dnow traffic Memorandum . )'* deference your Printed Letter Wo. C/270 dated the Slst August 1341* 2. An intelligence service for dhows traffic including Bahrain, Qatar and the Trucial Coast could be organised at the cost of some additional expenditure. How efficient the service would be is difficult to say in view of the number of obscure anchorages in tnis Agency at which dhows can call for water and provisions without anyone on shore being aware of who is on board. 3. The service would require an agent in every anchorage where boats are likely to call and there seems no reason to anticipate any great difficulty over this. Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 CNo: PA/HL/ P.y.f'. T.&lt;Z B M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. THE CUSTOimOUSEs BAHRAIN: 18th September ,194-1., 27 th Shabban, 1360 ., MEM( Ref. your memorandum No:C/1006-28/19, dated the 31st December, 1940. 2 . I enclose herewith, in duplicate, a statement showing the movements of large sea-going craft during the fortnight ending 15th September, 1941. Enclosures— /I DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS U AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN ‘'K^ / Political Agency, No.C/916-28/19. Bahrain, the 22nd September 1941 To J The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum A / Reference my memorandum No.0/1006 dated the 31st December 1940. Movements of large sea-going craft. 2. The fortnightly statements required. are now no longer / •f for Political Agent, BahrainTelegram From To No. 138. Dated and received the 28th January 1942. Political Resident, Dushire Political Agent, Bahrain. 1 f\ Follovving is repetition of Aden telegram dated January 25th begins ’’Addressed Government of India, No.20, repeated Political Resident, Bushire,No.4. Authorities in Eritrea have instituted a system of identity cards with photographs for all members’of dhow crews using their pDrts.- Security officer Aden is most anxious that similar system should be instituted here. Would you be prepared to adopt similar scheme in Indian and Persian Du If ports ?”. Ends. 2. Please telegraph your views. Residentf Confidential 4 ” No. C/129 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th January 1942 To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, B A H B A I N Memorandum The authorities in Eritrea have instituted a system of identity cards with photographs for all members of dhow crews using their ports, and the Security Officer in Aden is very anxious that a similar system should be instituted there. The Government of India have asked whether such a system is feasible in the Persian Gulf ports. 2. Prima facie, it would not be difficult to adopt this procedure in Bahrain though I am doubtful about the Trucial Coast, in respect of which I am making separate enquiries. I shall be grateful to know your views on the feasibility of introducing the system in Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrainwmm J From To No. Dated Telegram G.T.C. (3) Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah 78 29th January 1942 Please telegraph your views as far as Trucial Coast is concerned on the following telegram ■ from Aden v*\ IV'* 'Authorities in Dritrea have instituted a system of identity cards with photographs for all members of dhow crews using their ports. Security Officer Aden is most anxious that similar system should be instituted here. Tr ould you be prepared to adopt similar scheme in Indian and Persian Gulf ports ?' - Political -&lt;35 From To No. 132 Dated 30th January IS42 ^ Your telegram No. 78 January 29th. Unless we take responsibility ourselves, local conditions and lack of proper administration by Trucial Coast Shaikhs make introduction of identity cards system practically difficult. Besides there are no photographers here and system of identity cards cannot be introduced without having a photographer ana an official -appointed and paid by us specially for this work at each independent state. - Britagent -*r Confidential. No. of 1361 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Moharram 15, 1361 February 2, 1942. H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memo random: - Reference your memorandum No. C/129 dated 29th January, 1942. The number of Bahrain dhows which travel between Bahrain and other Gulf ports is compara tively small and it would not be difficult to insist on the crew carrying passports with photographs on them. I presume that what is required is photographs only of dhow crews who visit foreign ports. It would be difficult to apply this rule to all dhows as during the diving season over 200 boats contain ing between seven and eight thousand men sail from Bahrain. Scarcely any Bahrain dhows or launches go to Aden or the Red Sea Ports. Adviser to the Government.From Telegram To Political 'gent, Bahrain. Political Pesident, Pushire No 93 Dated 3rd February 1942 v our telegram No. 138 January 28th. 2. Bahrain could arrange identity cards with photographs for crews of dhows visiting Men Africa India. On Crucial Coast however system impracticable with existing facilities. British Government would have to appoint both administrative official and photographer in each Shaikhdom. Identity card system without repeat without photographs might be managed but lends itself to abuse and object of system would thus be defeated. PoliticalCONFIDENTIAL. No. 167-S of 1942. &gt; ‘I 1 *' o &gt;0&gt;.- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents hip compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, y The Political Agent, Muscat, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of (he undermentioned document^. British Consulate-General, BU8HIRE. Dated. .cttLFsto&amp;ry:. 194?.. Reference to previous correspondence: the 3rd February 1942. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. A . 212 ^ Residency telegram No dated the 6th February 1942. Identity Cards for dhow crews.s. Telegram From Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, E.A.D., New Delhi. Governor, Aden. To Repeated No.212 Dated the 6th February 1942. 2 Reference Aden telegram Ho.4 January 25th Arrangements could be made for issue of identity cards with photographs at Bahrain and Kuwait but not on Trucial Coast. Considerable difficulty would be experienced in Muscat especially at outlying ports but it might be possible to issue an order for crews of craft going to Aden and African ports to obtain cards from Muscat before sailing. Saudi Arabian ports have also to be considered where enforcement of system even if Saudi Arabian authorities were willing to agree to it would presumably be a matter of difficulty. Persian dhows rarely visit Aden and Africa. Aden and Africa are now all on high seas and will not start on further voyages to these ports until after the monsoon. In any case there would be no point in introducing system before August. successfully applied to a limited number of ports I am against its adoption in the Gulf unless very strong necessity exists. 3. Generally speaking dhows trading with 4 On the whole as the scheme could only be - BRITCONSUL - NPG -—__Weit si 4Wxxirir t lUaJ Sslmxbs, i&gt;uu-»ian (&lt;5ulf. , . # I notice that Hajy Yusuf hm Aiimed ralcroo is planning to send hence t° Manila (in the Hadramut) twent/thousand gallons of jcerosene packed in five thousand ^oar-^allon tins, by one of his sea-gain# booms. ° ° ^ T nie an interesting adventure lop I do not remember such an enterprise before and am readly interested to suppose that there mi^ht be so many as five thousand empty tins locally available. When Italy was actively concerned in warlike operations along the Hed . c&lt; littoral, one took close notice o^ such activities like the above; and I stopped some consignments of petrol from leaving this port Fri?rf= f ° r !Iakalla . but presumablv for ^ritrea, where payment was to be made*in gold. I would be glad to hear if you are interested 111 bhe above adventure in any way or oerhans could favour me with any opinion therein. Believe me, Yours sincerel 1 ih.B.Wakefield Esguire. The Agency, I'ANAJOH. I.C.S.T el egram Q. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Governor, Aden. Reoeatad Britconsul Bushire. Fo.705. Dated 20th October 1942. © Local merchant proposes shipping twenty thousand half forty thousand gallons kerosene to Fakalla. Is any objection your end? - POLITICAL -Telegram Inter. Krom (iovernor, Aden. To Political' Agent, Bahrain. No.b. Dated ssoth received £6th October 194*;. Your telegram No,705. Kerosene to Mukalla. No objection. -uuVrttiMUK-D.O.No.C/1628 . Bahrain y the 26th October 1942 The Agency Reference my demi-official letter No.C/1598 dated 20th October 1942. The Governor of Aden has telegraphed that there is no objection to the shipment of 20,000 gallons of Kerosene to Mukalla• Yours sincerely, C.C.L. de Grenier Esq., Director of Customs and Port Officer Bahrain•Ko. /‘?‘7/-S r&gt;sr of 1361 Office of the k&amp;visev to the Government, Bahrain Bated, £Oth Shawal, 1361 October 31, 194^. The Director of Ous-coms and Port Officer, Bahrain, r Memorandum:- Anmed bin Tusuf Pakiiroo has enquired from me whether there is any objection to his exportin from Bahrain 5,000 tinB of paraffin to Makalla in the Hadhramcut in tins which he is exporting from Dubai for this purpose, I do not see any reason against this export provided that tho tins used to contain the paraffin are obtained from outside Bahrain. The export is by native craft. Adviser to the Government, cc HBM’s Political Agent, Bahrain, for information, S.Z.! i!'* a SLf P A &lt;\^ *JLAJts&lt;^ . k - l ^ EjE, i .s_P^L. To. C/370 dated Slat August 1^ 41 . ’/here Bahrain is concerned, it would appear that the Customs Department is the only one which is fully in touch with the movement of dhows. If however, action as in para 3 of enclosure 2 is considered more suitable pernaps V /s Boo lai or Jassim might be able to help. Submitted ltd. H.J.N. 25/8. e n °I only to consider Bahrain but o a tar and ohe irucial Coast as well. An■ enemy agent wishing, | say, to smuggle himself from Iran to India would hardly oe likely to touch at thejRahrain Customs ; but if hr v/anted iood and water, etc., would probably call down the coast. In another communication, P.A. Muscat and P.R. have tacitly admitted that it is very difficult to aoolv °^e Navicert System to? dhows and it seems that any fur ther control of this traffic could only be exercised by a patrol of fast motor boats at sea. Possibly, the T avy nave had this in mind, during their recent census and purchases of motor dhows. T ill Messrs, Boodai and Jassim kindly advise whether there are in Bahrain and down the coast any agents.!. on the lines of the one quoted in Purandhar who would be in a position to assist ? ltd. This could easily be arranged in Bahrain but we require two agents ; one to deal with Arab and one with Iranian dhows. On my last trip to Oatar I have arranged with a reliable person on the Customs staff at ( Doha to work for me when required. The R.A. might if arrange for the Trucial Coast. ltd. A.B. i M ■ 1.9.41.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000067_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/710</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000067</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/710</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/19 Export of oil and other articles from the Persian Gulf to Italian East Africa (dhow traffic)’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-12T21:04:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (156 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 146-157) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the back cover with 158; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 3-145; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. Pagination: the file notes at the back (ff 146-157) have been paginated using pencil.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises correspondence and reports relating to outward trade from Bahrain and the ports of the Trucial Coast to the ports of the Red Sea and East Africa, in response to concerns that some cargoes (and in particular oil) were reaching Italian East Africa and Italian-occupied British Somaliland. The principal correspondents in the file are: the Political Agent at Bahrain (Major Reginald George Evelin William Alban); the Director of Customs for the Government of Bahrain (Claud Cranbrook Lewis DeGrenier); the Political Officer on the Trucial Coast (Captain Roy Douglas Metcalfe); and the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf (SNOPG: Commodore Cosmo Moray Graham).The file includes:correspondence concerning regular checks on the frequency of cargo-carrying dhows (and the nature of the cargo they are carrying), travelling from Bahrain, Muscat and the Trucial Coast, to the Red Sea and East Africa, including: a secret telegram from the SNOPG to the Political Agents in the Gulf, dated 13 December 1940, requesting frequent summaries on cargoes and destinations of dhow traffic from the Persian Gulf (f 24); assessments of the extent of dhow traffic from the Gulf to Aden and beyond (ff 16-21, ff 39-40); regular reports, from early 1941 onwards, from the Director of Customs at Bahrain on dhow traffic from Bahrain (beginning ff 57-58), and from the Political Officer on the Trucial Coast (beginning f 74); regular reports of dhow traffic and cargoes headed north towards the Gulf, sent by the Chief Secretary at Dar es Salaam [Dār as-Salām] (from f 96); a letter from the Political Agent to the Director of Customs at Bahrain, dated 22 September 1941, informing him that regular reports on dhow movements are no longer required (f 131);correspondence between the Political Agent at Bahrain and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) and California-Arabian Standard Oil Company (CASOC) on whether oil and other supplies were being transported from Bahrain to Saudi Arabian ports, either overland or by sea (ff 3-6);warnings from the SNOPG and other officials that dhow traffic travelling in close proximity to the coast of Italian East Africa does so at its own risk (f 9, f 49, ff 53-56);proposals for the searching of dhows in order to intercept illicit traffic (ff 51-52);information on shipments of oil products, such as kerosene from Gulf ports to the Red Sea (ff 80-81);correspondence concerning the introduction of identity cards for dhow crews using Eritrean ports, and British proposals to introduce a similar system at Aden and the Persian Gulf ports (ff 132-139).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000067#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>