<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:03:37.060Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">HUPP*'PART II. /r&lt;0 LOiiNS OP TH E PR OVING I. L GOV^JHPKT S_.„ MADRi,S GOVSRM^El^T. 7. I ssue of Nev/ Loans. In paragraph 3 of Chapter I and paragraph 4 of Cnapter III of Appendix I of the Special Officer's report it is stated that at the time of issue of a hew loan the parent Public Debt Office prepares the initial vouchers from the advices of total amounts of Scrip issued to the various Public Debt Offices received from the Calcutta Public Debt Office. In tne case of the Madras Government loans it was seen that no advices of the scrip issued to the other Public Debt Offices were received in the local office from the Calcutta Public Debt Office and that the ledger was posted from the duplicate copies of the vouchers received from the, Public Debt Offices after verifi cation with the statements of issue of scrip received from them. /• . r- 8• Interest payment so (a) Interest Check Regis ter 3 per ce n t M ad ras Lo an 1352. 33 Note No. C. 000238 93 ii 000136 114 d Ms 00567 In these cases the notes were cancelled^for credit to the Imperial Bank of India Subsidiary General Ledger account on 25-7-1938. Payment of interest for the half year due on 1-3-1938 has not been noted in the Register. Page 120 Note No.Ms.000872 Cancelled for credit to Reserve Bank of India Subsidiary General Ledger Account on 10-8-1939 - Payment of interest for the half year due on 1-3-1939 has not been noted in the Register. Page 97 Note No. G&lt; 000131 G. 000132 \ The notes were cancelled on 12-S-1938&gt; and 16-8S®1938 respec tively. Payment of interest due on 1-3-1938 has not been noted in the Register. • V ' r &lt; X \■^Bi ■*7 i '^sZTb$ v&gt; L• T Qffict of the Military Secretary to the Viceroy- New Delhi 5 'the March 1939. From The MILITARY SECRETARY to HIS EXCELLENCY THE VICEROY, The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. F Sir, I have the honour to request fthat you will be good . / k enough to authorise the Agent, Imperial Bank of India, New Delhi, to advance me during the financial year 1939-40, with effect from the 1st April 1939, amounts on account of the following grants under Demand for Staff, Household and Allowances of the Governor General, which are administered by me and will be drawn, as usual, by cheques (1) C.- Expenditure from Contract Allowance (Unaudited). / (2) G/- Tour Expenses - G.-2 - Other Charges. Rs. 1,66,C^V-. 1,46,100/-. 2 . The favour of an acknowledgment of this letter is requested. I have the honour to be, 4 .. Sir, You 3 $*Tnost obedient servant, Milit Lt.-Colonel, Be'cretary to the Viceroy. Copy to the Agent, Imperial Bank of India, New Delhi. / ' 0 w* ^ ^ _(*&gt;) l^V OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL. CENTRAL REVENUES. NEW DELHI. NO.C2-31-88, dated the ^ Copy forwarded for information end guidance to the C * &gt; ^ $ tfAt * St M l U — (Hohnn Bohari Lai) Deputy Accountant General* Conlral R^vonuoe. «*r .Copy of letter NO.D.4908-F/44 dated the 6th Way 1944 from th 0 Aeeietant Secretary to tho Govrrnm^nt of India* Finance Dopar^xirnt to I’ossrs.Thos# ond Cook and Son (Brnkors) Bom boy. Subjects- Determination of tho axTangrmrnt made v/ith Mosers. Thos , Cook ond Son (Bankers) for drawing pay* Pensions^ etc. I am directed to inform you that the Governor General in Council has decided to terminal' tho arr ingomcat for dravting pay, pensions, annuities* .ftc*,. on tho basis of a bond of idomnity rxecu*od by you on tho 2nd May 1936 and to state that tho arrangrocn+ shall bo determined on &lt;ho expijry of 14 days from iho date ^f issue of this loiter. •Copy of letter n* BY# CY* No» 1377/AtS4l2A-45 f datwd 30th January, 1945, from th© Currency Officer, Reserve Bank of India Issue Deptt* Bombay, to Ail Treasury Officers and Sub-Treasury Officers in the Bombay Issue Circle* Ret- Conduct of GOveromait Business of the Sub Treasury at Gudivada and Xaking over of the Currency chest from the Bub Treasury by the Sub-branch of the imperial Of indiax at Gudivada* We have to advise that the sub-branch of the Imperial Bank of India at Gudivada, Kistna District;, will with effect from the 2Tth January^ 1945 v conduct Government business of the sub-treasury at Gudivada and trke ever the mirre-noy chest from the eub- treasury * as from that date remittances at that centre under the scheme of Remittance facilities in India and Banna will be draw, on an I by the imperial Bank of India&gt; We shall, therefore, be glad if you will me^c the follow*’ ing amen dm ait in the list of officers of the imperial Bunk of Indial forwarded with this office circular letter 3Y*0Y« No* 3245/Res*10-1-40, dated the 21 st September 1940i- be corrected in due course« Under * MADRAS' enter 'GUDIVA lA SB** The Reserve Bank of indidSTreasury k&amp;vncidi) private check Sigial Book -will /] . * rti i f a n .. ^ 1 a X 4? J Mo, 0 5-1-393 Copy Office of the a«S*C,R* New Delhi* ^ f f forwarded for information^o the 3 Bahrain Reccim MM.™* •••--' M L ' ^ ^ - — L/( (1WHAN1 B5;dARI ULt) |eputy Accountant jsneralfDivisional Acununtcmt. s /'K* • Tun ol work »s g^Ten Lx t^e est^Bixtr, should he entorod Wr« fas th# of exxh work included Sclv'dale of Work* Expendiutnre, W. A. Torui 61, or in the Scnt'du'O of 3epoo*t Dorics, Takxxi Works, or Debits to Stock, F. W. A* For»s 65, 66 and 75L la all other caafti, the name of the SohHale ahotild be firen. * f Only such porli'-nUrs arod he entered as are uecenaarj to avoid errors in the posthif of ebarge* is Schedule DocVotm J In the ease of Tr nsfer Entry d^hitr the supportiug rouchers, if oxcee&lt;Mnt» Its. 25 eacV, should al«o be attached, their particulars quot'd below each catrj, and the anaoan* of the petty Touchers being spec^x* 111 the ook’.nn for remarks. la tho case of Transfer Cm'Jts a rc c erenoe to thr Schedule Dorkot in which the oorreepondlny debit u shown shun 14 he j»ir&lt;r&gt; in the came column.w ' r 0 /* OUL' ^-v^vaJ!^ ^Jl/- V/v^J tAT^ &lt;Xr* C&lt;?^wa^O C&gt; V/^ * -fyev^ W \^*^»v^ 'W-yyvAi&lt;v. ^*^vva#4 '^pjylA.v Vv-sa&gt;^{*&lt; y - 2 - altered either hy the Treasury Officer or in your accounts even if any misclassification on the part of the Barkis detected hy the Treasury Officer or in your office while con^lmg the ? Accounts, the necessary adjustment^ in recti!ication oi the JV' • '*•$'- *y- , ^ ^\o^/ . misclassific^tlon- hein'^^l^ys % made^through the head 'Adjusting Account between Central and Provincial^Governments'. KAd^ this procedure : Veeh 'followed your figures of Reserve Bank -• ‘ ’ -..r ' ^ V* f '.v‘d ^*-^* ^‘* ^ • Z. ^ * Deposits-Treasury'and those reported by the Chief Accountant, Reserve Bank’’of India* against the branches ol %he'l mperia 1 'VnUL' c ^ / vt~ ^ US H ct-u* Bank would have agreedy&amp;nd the misolaccif ioat i-en -^ptifiod on the booSs^^f the Accountant General ; Central Revenues, iwther, the correction of the figures of Reserve Bank Deposits in ; your accounts has resulted in a double adjustment of the sum of^ • : Rs 3.71.995-4-2 in the Central Civil Accounts, viz, lirst in the Central Civil Accounts of the United Provinces for April i937 under 'Reserve Bank Deposits - Treasury' and aga.in in the Accouht of the Accountant General, Central revenues, lor lay 1937 undef 'Reserve Bank Deposits- Central accounts cilice, Reserve Bank' as the'latte^lijl^’icer is advised''by -the Cehtf^i Accounts Office of, the Reserve Bank of adjustments 'iiiade- * ■ ’ l ■*’ r . .... • v . . against the balance of the Central Government ,* vide sub-para- v. x * • * 1. ■* \ % * \* under para 28(ii) of the memo referred to above. This-has left* X . «V*vdLJt\j the difference as it was. -The necessary readjustment steewM be., made in your accounts (Central Section) lor July 1937 restoring 4 ’'.' T i . the original figures of Reserve Bank Deposits as per .Ban^ s. classifications under intimation to this office, lo further., adjustment at the Central Accounts Office will be necessary as the adjustment originally made will stand v 2 . I shall be glad to know at an early date the action -^' r )i * taken on this letter. 7c. ' '1‘., for Controller of tne’Currency, ‘ mmm HilHHHHiFrom — The Resident at Jaipur To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Memorandum No. 44/9* : ^H/39 Dated Jaipur,the s# Ja. January 1940 Verification of expenditure up to September 1939. Reference - Your letter No. TC 14-2-2221, dated the 12th December 1939, to the address Of the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Resident for Rajputana, •j ' ■» r ^ on the above subject. India was received on the 29th August, 1939, ^vide your endorsement No. TC 2-3-1258, dated the 28th August, 1939, when the Statements of expenditure 'Ut&gt; • for June and July 1939 had already been forwarded to^the Secretary to the Hon«ble the Resident for Rajputana: hence the discrepancy. The progressive total in the office copy of the Statement for July 1939, was therefore, corrected on receipt of your above- 2. Intimation of the book adjustment of Rs. 16/ during.June 1939 on account of cost of the map of mentioned intimation Resident at JaipurNo: C 1=4/58 To OFFICE OF THE IcGoCJU NEW DELHIo Dated the 27th 315ay 1946© '63 ' All Civil Audit and Accounts Officer ^ including those of Posts and Telegrapns and Railway Department and also all Treasury Officers undet the Audit control of the A 6 G e C 0 Ro New Delhi including some other specified Treasury Officers and the Agent ? Imperial Ban!: of India 5 Hew Delhi* Subjects- Authority for payment 0 .. Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith three : four ( for the Accountant General, Bengal and the Comptroller Orissa) five, (for the Accountant General, U c Po and the S A ■ . . Accountant General, Punjab) specimen signature of Mr: 3,.h* Bose, Assistant accounts Officer, who has been empowered to sign authorities for payment issuing from this office with effect from the 27th May 1946 (forenoon). The Specimen signature of Mr: R. Bose, Assistant Accounts Officer, forwarded with this office letter No: C 1-4/213 dated 20.10.45 may please be treated as cancelled With effect from that date. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. M. A.Khan. 27.5.1946. NAME. Mr: E.K.Bose Mr: S.K.Bosu Mr: ScK.Bose ( Mohan Behari Lai ) Assistant Accounts Officer. DESIGNATION. Asstt: Acct. Officer 1. Asstt: Acct. Officer 2* Asstt: Acct. Officer 3, SPECIMEN SIGNATUREPlease address farther correspondence on the subject to the C. M. A. section N. C., Rawalpindi, qnoting this office No. A/986 To . »!\v \ \y ) Office of the Controller of Military Accounts, NORTHERN COMMAND. ,; t October, 1940. Rawalpindi The Accountant Genera}., Central Revenues, New Delhi. ){ Subject:- Analysis of Progress Register for July, 1940, vM. , - ' / • • e •••• • V References- Your No. ACB, 12-1-2409 dated 26.9.40. &lt;5^ Outstanding balances tinder Head III &amp; IV have been verified and found correct. Head III The debit of Rs 42/2/- has been written back at 6H- cr. item 4 for 8/40.? As regards the erroneous credit amounting to Rs 62/10/- kindly refer to cr. items 3(a), 5 &amp; 9 for 8/40. JSB. 1/10 \ \ y % V \ V* / v i&amp; ® OFFICjl Or '1113 A'-'^uUNx'iiNi 1 GriliiwiL C ji'j j.xu*Xi xt juV -_*j x'Jxii.j xJjxIL-ii-i- • No*C 5»-l-P63. D^ted the Copy forwrrded to:- (l) The Political A r, :Qnt, Kuv/rit. (n) H.B.M’s Consul, Kenanxi. (3) ' w Khurnms'hr* (4) '» » Zahidon, {5) M ” Bunder Aob«s, (6) T? ” General, Ipjorospn. (7) •» ' u Ahvaz (Irsn)*- (B) The 'Political Agent, Bahrain. (9) D.FA, TAB and GAL 5 . Sections including TiM. Bahrain Receipt . &amp; / y . (K.K. .) rj^ t Deputy accountant General. (s^• ) Copy of letter tlo.By.Cy*No.9722/Res*12 a** 46 dnted the 8 th October,1940 fron the Reserve Bank of India, issue Deptt; Bombay to All Treasury Officers, Sub-Treesury Officers, Agents, Imperial Bonk of India and Clerks-in-Chur {re, r rreasui’y Pny Offices of the Imperial Bonk of India, in the Bombay Issue Circle. ..emittance Tbcilitios in India and Burxnn-co-operutive Bonks and Societies situated in the Indian States. PI -’se refer tx poire graph SC of Appendix III to the Nev; scheme of Re littonce Facilities in India and Burmo. The dr u;ings at concession rotes l-'id dovm in paragraph 1 of the Appendix are at present available to the Co-operative Banks and Societies formed and functioning under the Co-operetivSocieties Act, Act II of 1912 or any other Co-operative Societies Acts for the time being in force in the Provinces only. It has now been decided in consulta tion with the Government of* Indio, to extend similar facilities to the Co-operative Banks and Societies situated in Indian States also which will hencefirth mjoy the same remittance facilities as those enjoyed by their counter-parts in British India. The following correction slip to tho booklet detailing the scheme of Remittance Facilities ^ill be issued in due course. No. 25. page 16.. Para 3C.. Appendix III (as amended by Amendment Slip No. 7) Delete the stop and add ”or in tho Indian States', after the word 1 Provinc es’.T i certify tnat I have satisfied myself that the eighty sum tf 48C-_0-0_ (Rupees fo ur h undred and Z cnly diu.un under Rule 17(b) of the Oener: 1 Provident Fund t (Oenbri.l Services) Ruies, from the General Provident Fund Recount No. __D-152 of Mr. Pup Lai , \ d^s ^stmit 5 on Bill ho. misc. 59 , dated the Ixox. 17th_May 1937, was actually disbursed to him on the 2!st_May 1937, and the payee’s receipt taken on the .icquit L:\nce rolls nic int ined in this Department. Dated S inile , the Ml May 1937. ^ocixxixijxi Forwarded to the Accountant General, Central Revenues iMw Delhi, for record in his office.mmmmmmmmmmtKKRBrn ■ From To ■'”h The Director, Hegional Met Centre. Karachi. The Treasury Officer, Bahrain. GS. Ko. R-37/M^3 Sth July, 1947. 'T ,Vr A Ml @) 3? f? , '.§ri J Sir, I have the honour to inform you that Mr. Hashmatulla^ Khan, Assistant Adminis native Officer has been posted to this oliice with effect fvoi 4-7-47 and I have authorised him tc sign, on my behalf, pay bills, T»A. bills, contingent bills etc. of the establishinent of this office. Mr. Hashmatullah •s specimen signature ( in triplicate) is enclosed^ I have the honour t s be- c; ,, Your most obedient servant. S RESIDENCY ' tin Director. Karachi SPSCIKEIi SIGfiATURE OF MR. KASHKaTULLAF KHAN ASSISTaKT ADKIIiISTRATIVE OFFICER REGIONAL MET OEM IRE, KARACHI. ;rfl. Notes for insertion below the Appropriation Account of Grant No. 76 - Miscellaneous for 1936-37. Subhead N - Payments arising out of Military Lands Scheme.- Disposal of buildings.- Three buildings (book value Hs. 1,85,000 roundly) forming part of the Bombay Military Lands Scheme property were sold in situ for fis.12,200 for demolition and clearing the site for the new joint bui!^ring of Central Government offices in Bombay.Nature of objection. 25. The maximum ni i n i mam subscription payable by the subscriber in whole rupees on his pay of Rs. in respect of 31st March 19 is Rs. per month and not Rs. per month. The #1|0r ^ payment at Rs. per month up to date should be his next pay bill, quoting this as authority on the bill as well as on the schedule. 26. The subscriber having paid Rs. in April 19 , should continue to pay it throughout the year. The £^omT P*7 m * n t iheuld be adjusted in his next pay bill, quoting this as authority on the bill as well as on the schedule. 27. Please furnish details showing how the sum of Rs. been arrived at. has 28. The date of payment of subscriptions paid in cash has not been stated in the Remarks column of the schedule. 29. The subscription for the duty period from to at Rs. f&gt;er month is Rs. , which should be recovered from the next bill ef the subscriber. 30. Please explain the excess recovery or point out credit for the outstanding balance of Rs. . See in this connection this oft ce communication No. , dated the 31. The amount of instalment in payment of the advance should be mixed U] shown separately not be mixed up with the usual monthly subscription, but should be ly in the eolumn “ Refund of withdrawals 32. The schedule for the month of has not been received with the bill far that month. P lease furnish it now and note that such schedules should be invariably attached to bills in future. 33. Please intimate the rate of pay of the subscriber drawn by him in in respect of 34. Please furnish voucher in support of charge and explain the cause of • Reply. 35. The order of payment on the enclosed bill has not been signed. Please return after completion. 36. As the voucher has not been stamped, it ie returned herewith for completion and return. 37. The Insurance Company's receipt for Rs. drawn in for payment of premium should be forwarded to this office for the necessary endorsement. 38. Please state what amounts were deducted from the pay bills 39. Please state whether any advance was granted during the twelve months prior to his death, resignation or retirement. 40. Please state the actual date of death, retirement or resignation and furnish copy of orders per nitting him to bis appointmenteFFICE OF THE ilCCO T n T T 'T GE EIUL. CEIITR ;L B^VEFDES . NE'’ DELHI. C. 1-4-751. De ted the, 22 . 3.40 * ZAPIUfllfi All Civil ^n.c'it epc .ccounts 0: fleers incluc ine ,those of the Posts pne 1 Telefrerhs end Leilr^s' Departments end all Treasury Officers, under the audit of the Accountant Ge' erc 1 9 Central .Pievenues , her' Delhi including sone other specified Treasury Officers and the gent, Imperial Bank o: 0 India, New Delhi. ^ SUBJECTS- ^ rr TKQPiI T3r FOR P\Y1 Sir, I have the honour to forward three, (four for Accountant General, Bengal, 4.G. Bast Bengal, and Comptroller, Orissa) five for the A.G.U.P., a.G. hast and West Punjab and *i.G. Pakistan) specimen signature 8 of Pr. C.K. Dutt. Assistant Accoun's Officer who has been empowered to sign authorities for payment issuing from this offioe ”lth effect from POth Ilarch ’48. The specimen signatures of Hr. P.C. Chakarvarti, assistant Accounts Officer forwarded with this office letter ho. 0-1-4-732 dated 16.3.’48 may nlease be treated as cancelled from that date. No*. To I have the honour to be, Sir , Your most obedient servant. \ . U- (F. Vr . b:in:;u) DEPUTY ,CCC T 0. T Cl .: -.L. C^ii .L'ri -L .Pu j vh i. jjjS . Name and Designation of the officer . Mr, C.K. Dutt, assistant Accounts Officer. Hr. C.K. Dutt, Assistant ''ccounts Officer. IS. Mr. C.K. Dutt. Assistant Accounts Officer</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1139</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1139</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/23 A Advices from A.G.C.R., New Delhi, of changes of officers empowered to sign authorities for payment'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-11T21:17:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (55 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, and terminates with a set of notes at folios 52-56. Circled reference numbers in red and dark blue ink, which occur throughout the file, refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 57; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 1-47; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains advice letters from the Office of the Accountant General, Central Revenues (AGCR), New Delhi, to the Political Agency, Bahrain, containing specimen signatures of those accounts officers of the AGCR who were empowered to sign authorities for payments issuing from the Office, and specimen signatures of those whose authority had been cancelled.The correspondence is written on re-used paper; the versos therefore contain random, unrelated information. In the order in which the papers stand, folios 16, 26, and 50 have been reversed; the letters from the AGCR appear on the versos (upside down).The date range gives the covering dates of the main items of correspondence; the last dated addition to the file is an entry in the notes on folio 56 dated 30 May 1948.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Accountant-General, Central Revenues</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00030a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>