<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00037a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-14T11:18:07.192Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">, : i- , , . .1. of the Under Socretary ef S^at^ for Fa^jign Affairs With the Compli Ho. F 4520/3527/61. My dear Minister, In my letter of the 12th Jul^’ I promi ed to let you know the result of our enquiries about the deferment of Mr# George Savery, whose case you raised in your letter of the 9th July# I am very glad to be able to inform you that this case was reviewed, in the light of subsequent in; ormation, by the District anpower board, who have decided to ^rant Mr. avery deferment to the 20th February, 19h4; if,at that date, conditions remain unaltered, it is open to his fim to submit an application for a further period of deferment# Yours His Excellency General hingha chum she re Jung Baiiadur Hana, K# i^# b. , Nepalese Legation, 12A&gt; Kensington alace Gardens, W.8#tl* ith the Compljm^ni^ of the gfUj Under Seec^t^ry of r ate ! L, r*.for Foreign Affair-. ^ 372V3527/61 27 jiil ! 94 * *r. ^cUWl 26th July, 1^3* X am dii^ected by -ir* secretary 1 den to request that furttiei* considerations umy be ^iven to the case or * r. re or ^e Javajry (W • d • * • 17927)» an eiipioyee or ..eaars Key *er dona and Coiapany Limited#or J-Xfin^ham house, rundei street, r •G#2#, a re‘.raeat ior the determent of whose call-up was sent by the Coraptiny to the' Jiatrict aanoower Board, ,bui*y Bridge Hcuae, on the 30th June, r’he reply oi the liotriot Board of the 5th July stated that this request could not bo oouplied with. 2. i esers Keyaer oons and Qoupmy IJLmtted have acted as buying agents for the Govern; *mt of Kepel for a considerable nuirifjcr of years end I r. Savery is stated to be toe one tien left in the coir^any (the othere having already been called up) who has close and first-hand knowledge of the contracts end enquiries made by the Nepalese Government mi of all the technical details involved* 3* In view of the great servicea rendered by U\e Nepalese overn ent in the present war to the couee of the United Nations through the reeruitiienfc end provision of Gurkha troops in all theatres of war and of woriciien for constructing airfields etc* in Indie,, this Department' and the India Office ere anxious to do all that tuey can to n*?et Nepal’s requirements for goods, the supply of which in present circuit cnee a presents considerable difficulties. In addition to the actxiai allocation of such goods, it is essential that here should be efficient uaoiiineiy for the fhe secretary, ministry / studying of Labour and National service. K,i.India Office, Whitehall. t London, S#V/. I* 15th July, !k&gt;#F*3527/35&gt;27/6l, regarding Mr. George Savery of IJesBrc. r.eyraer, Son &amp; Company Limited, to say that m? hwe had some dealings vvith this CJoiupany* and have recently given them assistance in shiiJping certain e:&lt;ports from this country to Nepal* We have had no ocmtact vdth L!r. George Savery jpersonally and do not loiow an^-thing of liis work with regard to Nepal# There is jx&gt; doubt, however, that Keyner*s ere a most reputable firm and that they have given valuable assistance to the Nepalese GoveiTi.ient for mauy years# V/c are in favour of doing what we can to assiatb thora and a^ee that there would be advantage in pressing for deferment of the calling-up of Mr# George Savery# Since the Nepalese Minister has T.S#Bromley, Esq#, Far Eastern Department, Foreign Office, S#W.l# approached/fKt. K Messrs. Keymer, Son and Co. have been Nepali Export ‘ Agents and Advisers for many years and although at present owing to shipping restrictions they must have considerably less to do, it is no doubt true that they have many projects on hand and post-war plans. Mr. Rumbold and I saw the Manager some months ago ,in connection with exports to Nepal generally, and we learned that Keymers had supplied the ropeway system and the cartridge factory. In fact they had assisted in most of Nepal's development schemes and knew a very great deal about the country and the people. I met him again with Ladfor Keymer at the Nepalese Legation and noticed that she and her company were held in much esteem and regard there. I think there is no doubt that they are a most reputable firm and that in assisting them to retain the services of a valuable and experienced employee we shall be doing the Nepalese themselves a good service. Mr. Savery is over 40 and is in Medical Class 2 classification. I am inclined to agree with the Foreign Office that there might be advantage in pressing for his deferment®AdOQ 11 Vj ^ FOREIGN OFFICE, 1- r S.W.l. , (F 3527/3527/61) : S^=5^- 5tl:i y 1943. U u ^ Dear Miss Rolfe, { CM Q I ^ i o ^ I enclose herein copies of correspondence, which is self- explanatory, with the Nepalese Minister about the retention by Messrs. Keymer Son and Company of the services of Mr. George Savery. We are inclined to think that |there might be some advantage in pressing for deferment in view of the considerable services rendered by Nepal to the allied cause if the facts given by the Company are exact and if it really does provide valuable assistance to the Nepalese Government. We have however no information about them and I should therefore be grateful if you would let me know what answer you think should be returned to the Nepalese request. V 0 S w ^ (T.E. Bromley) Miss C.I. Rolfe, India Office.j 3^7/572 //6l). ITepalese Legation, o London^ 8. . / 9th July, 1943. Dear Dunhar, . I have h.een approached hy Messrs. Keymer, Son &amp; Co., Ltd., o£ SJfinpham House, .-Jnundel street, V/. C. 2 ~ who have 'been acting as buying agents for the Government of Nepal for the last j. orty-two years, and who have been responsible for the success ful completion of many projects of a highly technical nature undertaken by my Govern «ent - in regard to the retention of the oorvices of Mr. George Savery, a m rnber of their staff. f -is this is a matter which concerns the authorities of this country, and in v/hich my inter vention vrould be out of place, I am sending you herewith copies of correspondence received by' me from Messrs. Keymer, Son and Co. Ltd., and shall be glad to know if I can suggest anything to them to assist them out of their present difficuHjt Hobert Dunbar, Hso. , K. C. , Foreign Office, 3 . ’ • 1 . 'nth/K3YIHR, SOU &amp; CC. , LTD., .(!) Effingham House, .'j?undel Street, London, ft. 6, 2. 8th- &lt;&amp;i2y , 1943« Your Excellency, -/L J Ir. George 3avery» ^ o We have written to the above matter, and we the 3Cth June and of the Board T s reply* - t he Han ’ r oweif CpL^ard inf regard t o enclose 'copies of-'iiujy letter of While-earefu] not to involve 1 'Yoiir Excellency in any “way, v/e- felt that we must leave r no stone unturned, leet _ the authorities should blame us“later on and say «hat'if we had only put the natter in -its proper li^ht deferment or exemption ni ;ht have been granted. ,7^-are now faced- with the difficult position which ill arise from Hr* Savery’s immediate cdll-up;' in vis*.; of his personal knowledge of the past history and”pro-sent -ve -—i- v-' ^ ^ s u. v . miyx kj p'X ^ ot u w o a ^ &lt;j o.x j' j iix &amp;_&gt; .i ^ . i _i. - -X be a considerable handicap to us in dealing with the great variety of business dealt with here for your Govern, ent* Hany projects are on hand, including- propositions for the supply and installation of textile, cement, oil and pumping plants, anc road-making, as well as electrical extensions and -the improvement and development of the existing facilities for making explosives and manufacturing munitions of war; to say nothing of plans for the encourage ment of cottage industries on a broad basis* All these projects should develop continuously, even where war conditions prevent the immediate execution of many of them. These matters are of first importance to the National development of Nepal, and in view of the outstanding services rendered to the British Government by your Country we ask Your Excellency to consider whether it would be possible to approach the India Office or foreign Office, His Excellency General Shingha Shumshere Jung Bahadur Rana, IE 3. Nepalese Legat ion 12a, Kensington Palace Gardens, W. 8. explaining/ -j* , etc.tom t * explaining*'out* pouiiion as it affects Fepal, ana enlistin w their sympathy on your behalf for the purpose of securing the continhcince of -Mr* -Savery’s services to us in the interests of TTepal* His call-up Humber is V. .. P. 17927* We hi:.ve been associated with Hepal for many years; the existing ropeway, bridges, electrical and water supply* installations were supplied by us and much care ful attention to detail and technical knowledge contri buted to their success, in conjunction with the fine work-done by the Nepalese Authorities themselves. As a result, we have bden entrusted with further orders, and have had the pleasure of investigating further possibilities, sometimes .proposed by ourselves and- sometirnes emanating fro a Nepal. We 'hope to continue to give useful service in furthering the National inter-ests of Nepal in every way in our power; but we feel that our • -rk ..y be much impeded if lose'the services, of Hr* 3avery for ^the^remainder of the war* We remain, etc., For and on behalf of K3YM3R, ION &amp; CO. , LTD. , A (Signed) K. C. Ceager , Director. t ■In reply to your letter of 30.6.45 regarding the deferment of calling-up of the above-named employee, I have to inform you that the District Man-Power Board has considered your further representations but has been unable to change the decision already notified to you. Yours faithfully, (bigned) E.W.E. Clayton Smith, for District Man Power Board Messrs. Keymer, Son &amp; Co., Ltd., Effingham House, Arundel Street, W.C.2. N.S.210.Cover for Enclosures in Weekly Letter No. P.Z dated from Secretary, Political and Secret Department (External), India Office, to v Foreign Secretary, Foreign and Political Depart ment, Government of India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00037a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/845</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00037a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/845</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 4003/43 'Retention by Messrs Keymer Son and Co of services of Mr George Savery –q[uestio]n of deferment of call up'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-22T22:27:13</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (9 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists primarily of letters between the Foreign Office and Keymer, Son and Company Limited. In their correspondence, Messrs Keymer request deferment of the conscription of one of the employee's because of their value to the company.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Nepalese Legation, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Keymer, Son &amp; Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ministry of Labour (United Kingdom)</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medical missionary work</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Conscription</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00037a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>