<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00027a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:00:36.882Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Mi DELHI, iA^ ! l°? r 9 ^ e 3^- February 1939. Presentation of a set of meteoro logical instruments to the Iranian Government. ydth reference to the correspondence ending Y/ith your demi-official letter No. 108/38/38, dated the 8th December 1938, on the above subject, I am desired to inform you that a new set of meteorological instruments was handed over, suitably packed, to the Iranian Consul at Bombay, personally by the Meteoro logist, Bombay, on the 14th January 1939. A copy of this letter is being sent to India Office and Consul, Kerman. Yours sincerely, Sd/- W. R. HAf. H. J. Seymour, Seqaire, (Mr., 0Y0. T J 4 »» r «~&gt; A JN+ » a* .?»■* 4 IrtO v» His Majesty a Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Cou of Iran, Tehran. Court ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S LETTER NO. DATE RECEIVED 4-'-2 11-2-1939— • / Copy 19 58, October mait o£ I the Directb 1 £&gt;4* * letter JNo. o PYLM't Fo Q, niia.l (mu t5r j ‘TTSTi'STsr 609, aatea the 4tli aecretary to the Gove fcC ha jpartment o£ Communications, Observatories, Poona. to^ Free 'gift oi a set oi meteorological instruments to the Iranian Government. l^T I am airected to refer to the letter from this Department No. K 609, dated the 18th February 1938 and to say that on reconsideration the Government of Inula are of the opinion that it will not be appropriate to present to the Iranian Government a set of meteorolo gical instruments which are in a damaged or worn con dition. They have therefore decided that a new set, as in the list enclosed, out of the stock of instru ments maintained in the Meteorological Department, should be made over to the Iranian Consul at Bombay for transmission to Iran. The serviceable instru ments already transferred from Henjam to Bunuar Aboas ana such of the fixed instruments of the Hen jam Observatory as can be made serviceable, should be used as a duplicate set in the recently established Observatory at Bundar Abbas. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S LfTTI No. DATE fr '*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00027a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/263</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00027a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/263</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 7184/38 'Iran: Gift of a set of meteorological instruments to the Iranian Govt.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-03T22:02:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of correspondence regarding the gift of a set of meteorological instruments to the Iranian Government from the Government of India.Correspondents include: the Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department; and the Government of India, Department of Communications.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Department of Communications</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Gifts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Meteorological equipment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00027a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>