<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100031940825.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-06T17:51:43.279Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100031940825.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 23392</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031940825.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 23392</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Taḥrīr kitāb al-majisṭī تحرير كتاب المجسطي  Ptolemy بطلميوس  Ṭūsī, Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad  طوسي، نصير الدين محمد بن محمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1549/1549</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-31T10:41:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. iv+160+iv</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 238 x 140 mm leaf [133 x 65 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencilRuling: No ruling visible; 25 lines per page; vertical spacing 19 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Nasta‘līq; the scribe is Ibn ‘Alī Muḥammad Ḥusayn (ابن علي محمد حسين; see colophon, f. 160r, lines 2-9)Ink: Black ink, with rubricated headings and tables and diagrams in redBinding: Red leather case binding with central medallion and four pendantsCondition: Minor water damage towards head of volumeMarginalia: Marginal notes by multiple handsSeals: Ff. 2v, 160r and 160v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The
                           Almagest(كتاب المجسطي), an Arabic version of the Μαθηματικῆς σύνταξις of Ptolemy (Claudius Ptolemaeus; c 90-c 168), in the annotated edition (تحرير) of Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad al-Ṭūsī (نصير الدين محمد بن محمد الطوسي; d. 1274). This was the most influential and enduring astronomical text to have survived from the ancient world and its Arabic translation, and al-Ṭūsī's annotated edition in particular, had an immense impact on the medieval world-view in both Christian and Islamic lands.The text is divided into thirteen chapters (مقالات) further subdivided into sections (فصول), and contains numerous diagrams and tables.Contents:Chapter One (المقالة الأولى; ff. 3r-20v);Chapter Two (المقالة الثانية; ff. 20v-33v);Chapter Three (المقالة الثالثة; ff. 33v-45v);Chapter Four (المقالة الرابعة; ff. 45v-62r);Chapter Five (المقالة الخامسة; ff. 62r-79v);Chapter Six (المقالة السادسة; ff. 79v-95r);Chapter Seven (المقالة السابعة; ff. 95r-104r);Chapter Eight (المقالة الثامنة; ff. 104r-115r);Chapter Nine (المقالة التاسعة; ff. 115r-131r);Chapter Ten (المقالة العاشرة; ff. 131r-135r);Chapter Eleven (المقالة الحادية عشر; ff. 135r-144v);Chapter Twelve (المقالة الثانية عشر; ff. 144v-150r);Chapter Thirteen (المقالة الثالثة عشر; ff. 150r-160r).The text contains numerous diagrams and tables.This text of this copy was completed in Muḥarram 955/February-March 1548 and the diagrams were completed in Jumādá II 956/June-July 1549 at Qazvin by Ibn ‘Alī Muḥammad Ḥusayn (ابن علي محمد حسين; see colophon, f. 160r, lines 2-9, transcribed below).An ownership inscription to lower left of the colophon (f. 160r, transcribed below) records that ‘Abd al-‘Azīz al-Raḥbī (عبد العزيز الرحبي) purchased the manuscript on 1 Rajab 1132/9 May 1720 for a price of 4
                           ashrafīdinars.Folio 2r contains a geometrical proposition with one figure that is said to be taken 'from the notes of shaykh Abū al-Qāsim ‘Alī ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Samsāṭī' (من تعاليق الشيخ أبي القاسم علي بن محمد بن السمساطي) and is written by a hand other than that of the main scribe.Begins (f. 2v, lines 2-8):أحمد الله مبدأ كل مبدأ وغاية كل غاية ومفيض كل خير وولي هدايةوأرجو حسن توفيقه في كل بداية ونهاية وأصلّي على عباده المخصوصينبالعناية والدراية سيّما محمد وآله الموسومين بالنبوة والولاية المتقدمينمن كل عماية وغواية وبعد فقد كنت برهته من الزمان غاز ما على أن أحرّرلنفسي وسائر طلبة العلم من الإخوان كتاب المجسطي المنسوب إلى بطلميوسالقلوذي الذي هو الدستور العظيم لأصحاب صناعة الهيئة والتنجيم تحريرًالا يفوته مقاصد ذلك الكتاب النظرية ومناهجه العليّة ...Ends (f. 159v, line 5 [below tables]-160r, line 1):فلنختم الكتاب وأقول وإذ قد وفقني الله تعالى أيضًا لإتمام ما قصد بهوإيجاز ما وعدته فلا قطع الكلام حامدًا لله تعالى على آلائه ومصليًّا علىجميع أوليائه خصوصًا على خاتم أنبيائه والبردة من آله وأحبّائهColophon (f. 160r, lines 2-10):تم الكتاب يوم الأربعاء من شهر محرم الحرامبعون الله الملك العلامسنة 955فرغت من إتمام أشكال هذا الكتاب الموسوم بتحرير المجسطي للمولى الإمامالمحقق والمدقق أستاذ المحققين وأسناد (؟) المدققين أفضل علماء المتقدمينوأعلم فضلاء المتأخرين نصير الحق والدين محمد الطوسي في أواخر شهرجمادى الآخر سنة 956 ببلدة قزوين وأنا الفقير إلى الله الغني ابن عليمحمد حسين غفر الله ذنوبه بحقمحمد وآله المعصومينOwnership inscription to lower left of the colophon (f. 160r):ملكته بالشراء الشرعي وأنا الفقيرإلى الله سبحانه وتعالى عبد العزيزالرحبي (؟) بقيمة قدرها أربعةدنانير أشرفية في غرة شهررجب سنة 1132</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Claudius Ptolemaeus (Ptolemy)</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad Ṭūsī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Astronomy--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><subject><topic>Ptolemy, active 2nd century. Almagest</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100031940825.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>