<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000207_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-05T11:03:52.316Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(10858) Wt. 21358—P172 20m. 8/46 G.S.St. Gp. 620 \ * No, a/' J DEPTL. No....Sxt r 252.2/4Z. DRAFT TELEGRAM CODE CYPHER X From .S.ecre t ary., of.. St ate.. .for. Commonwealth Relations To Poli.tioal..Reaident,. Persian Calf. Repeated to. v Hi; o\\o *jO tfiXir f&gt;nm Denaliiaeft. Your telegram / V No.T/180 of 15th December. We see no objection to continuance of New Year*s Day celebrations. As regards Proclamation Day e»iig»bpat lows we are not sure what the historical background of this is but assume it is in connection with Queen Victoria's Proclamation of 1st January, assumption of title of Empress of India. V/e should have thought it better not to link New Year's Day celebrations with this Proclamation. 2. Your paragraph 2 confirmed. 1877 o: iW'V ^ \\cx^o . Inward Telegram to Commonwealth Relations Office ALLOTTED TO EXTERNAL DEPARTMENT CONE. CODE PROM : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN TIJE PERSIAN GULP Undated D. No.T/180 Donaldson from Hay It has been customary in the past to celebrate (? New) Years (? Day) (2 corrupt groups) proclamation day with certain (corruptJs in Gulf Agencies. (?In) Bahrein and Koweit those consist chiefly (? of) (? formal) calls on Political Agent by Rulers and deputations of notables and merchants and exchange of good wishes.after carefully considering propose to allow this practice to continue. 2. (Corrupt group) Royal Navy have informed (? me that) His Majesty’s (? salute) is now 21 (? not) 31 guns. Please confirm'iHupr.' 'KjiWMHRPPUMi © FROM : POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIAN GULP D. Undated R« 7«30*p*m. 13 th December, 1947 No*1/180 Donaldson from Hay* It has been customary in the past to celebrate (? New) Years (? Day) (2 corrupt groups) proclamation day with certain (corrupt )s in Gulf Agencies. (?In) Bahrein and Koweit those consist chiefly (? of) (? formal) calls on Political Agent by Rulers and deputations of notables and merchants and exchange of good wishes after carefully considering propose to allow this practice to continue. 2. (Corrupt group) Royal Navy have informed (? me that) His Majesty’s (? salute) is now 21 (? not) 31 guns. Please confirm■■■ mmam mOM © POL.11013/47 OUTWARD TSLBGHAM Political D.G. Prom To ’WORD CODS Secretary of State for OoLTmonwealth Relations Foreign, Karachi. Despatched 11.40 hours, 11tn October, 1947« No.12351 Announcement was made today that His Majesty the King has decided that Sunday, November 9th shall be observed as Remembrance Day. The Two Minutes Silence will be observed througxiout the United Kingdom at 11 a.m. The King feels assured that there will be general co-operation in the observance of Remembrance Day as there has been in previous years in the observance of Armistice Day. Copy to Political Dept. -.0. for Pakistan.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000207_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1218</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000207</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1218</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 2446/47 'Observance of celebrations in Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-18T22:03:19</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8, these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of letters and telegrams between the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations, London, and the Political Resident in Persian Gulf regarding the arrangement of different celebrations in Persian Gulf.Related matters of discussion include the following: Celebration of Armistice Day, Remembrance Day and New Year.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Celebrations</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x000207#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>