<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000148_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:17:40.225Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY Lett er No. PA^J Manama, Bahrein Island, December 22, 19^5. UahraVi No- hz. ( Date. &lt;Z£- It. . U4. His Britannic Majesty f s Political Agent, Manama, Bahrein Island, Persian Culf, ATT: CAPTAIN R«E»R, BIRD Dear Sir: Please refer to the verbal conversation I had with you several days ago over Indian National employees returning to India from Saudi Arabia, In many cases it would be much simpler for us and the Individualrif we could havejiim appear before you for cancellation of his Service Agreements instead of going all the way to Bombay to appear before the Protector of Emigrants, As a matter of fact, the Protector of Emigrants has indicated to our Bombay Agent that in these cases where the men cannot appear in person at Bombay, he would prefer that they sign off before you in Bahrein, I attach hereto copy of letter No,g4U of December 9, 19^5 from ray principals In Arabia on this subject together with copy of the H B rt form of declaration. Will you please advise me whether or not you have any objection to Aramco Indian employees signing off in Bahrein before you. ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY By: c. i. rodWrom BAHREIN REPRESENTATIVEDECLARATION 1945 Date I hereby declare that I have no complaint to make against my employers the Arabian American Oil Company under the terms of my agreement and that all my dues have been paid to me. I have made this declaration of my own free will and responsibility. D SIGNATURE OF EMIGRANT COUNTERSIGNED (COPY)ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY l&amp;jgl Dhahr^n f Saudi Arabia December 9, 19^ No. 8UU MR. C. A. RODSTRQM Arabian American Oil Company Manama CANCEL LATION OF ACRE EMENTS A As you know Indian Nationals returning to India from Saudi Arabia or Bahrein are required either to appear before the Protector of Emigrants for cancellation of theit Agreements or to forward to him through our Bombay Agent a 'B' Form of Declaration in the event they are unable to appear at Bombay. Most of the latter cases arrise in instances of Indians proceeding to their homes via Karachi; in such instances these men are handed a 'B' Form of Declaration before they leave Saudi Arabia with instructions to have this counter signed by a British Official authorised to di&gt; so on thehr arrivals in Karachi and forward to our B&amp;mbay Agent to enable him to complete the Emigration formalities. Because of the difficulty in getting Indians disembarking at Karachi to to complete these formalities the Protector of Emigrants,.has requested in the instance of the Bahrein Petroleum Company that the 'B' Declaration be completed in Bahrein before the Political Agent. From the attached correspondence it will be seen that the matter has been under consideration^by the Oovermnent of India and the Political Agent. Our Bombay Agent now writes us enquiring if we would be able to adopt the same procedure. We would appreciate your contacting the Political Agent in regard to this matter. If the procedure can be instilled we suggest, if agreeable to the Political Agent, that we continue to with hold Rupees 25- 0-0 from the settlements of Indians returning home, this sum to be repaid them by your office upon the presentation to you of the ’’B” Declaration properly completed and countersigned by the Political Agent. This Declaration will then be sent to us for forwarding to Indian ARABIAN AMERICAN OIL COMPANY SOD. By: J. G. HOSMERTHE POLITICAL AGLNCX, HAHKAIN. Dated the 8th July, 1948. JMLUil CONFI^htiai. No. C/L.70 To. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain* Subject:- Syed Has shin Siddike V Memorandum: - Syed Hasshin Siddik, Adenese, who was to have been deported by plane by the Arabian American Oil Company is believed to have left for Bahrain by native boat on the 7th July. He is reported to have made inflammatory and communistic speeches to the Adenese workers in Dhahran. He is of medium build and wears spectacles. ^ 1 sh °uld be grateful if the Bahrain Government would take steps to prevent his landing in Bahrain or keep him under proper surveillance should he have already landed here. Sd/- CiJ.PKLLX. ATTx.dtr.n- for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Politicai Agent, Bahrain. L.c£) Immediate No. ! to it Of 1367 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 5th Ramadhan 1367 July 11, 1948 Reference your memorandum No.C/L.70 dated 8th July 1948, your memorandum reached me after the man had landed in Bahraim. He held a British passport and came with the Aramco employees and was presumed to be one of the Aramco’s employees. His passport was sent to the Agency by the Pass port Officer as usual. 2. He made no local contacts and no speeches • while he was here, he went about with some persons j from Aden who live here. .vj to 3. He left Bahrain at 11.30 A.M. yesterday for .• * H. B. M's Political Agent Bahrain. Memorandum: - Saudi Arabia ^t/^wc**** -r _ Adviser to the Government.will* — -</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000148_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/885</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000148</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/885</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 39/16 (10/3) ARAMCO labour'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-22T20:58:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 7-8. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file. Most of the documents listed in the notes, dated from 5 January 1946 to 12 July 1948, have been removed from the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence from Arabian American Oil Company (ARAMCO) representatives regarding Indian nationals returning to India from Saudi Arabia or Bahrain. There is also a request from the Political Agent at Bahrain to the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain to keep under surveillance a man from Aden, suspect of having made communist speeches in Dhahran.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Communism</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000148#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>