<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ea_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T10:54:42.082Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM T '5VV : A. &gt;' * .^eleFram i 3 From Foreign Simla To ^eaident no. V 1 3 dated and reed 5th Jan. 1913. ABU MUSA OXIDE&amp; Your letter 2894 Nov. 3rd. Has exportation completed by Dec. 3l8t? Foreignno. PC at 1913. British K© *1 lenoy .-Anti Gonaul Genoral 0* Jushlro dated Oth 1913« 4r dn Vl(A /r&gt; Wh© 'ealdenoy Agent LIHGAH itTtor oo pllraonts# In contl uatlon of previous oorreBpondence I wri^e to Inforrn you that if by the tine you receive this Hasan ^anaiyeh hue not renovei his pear from Abu luaa aa directed, you should proooed to Abu usa with tho necessary boat, and arra^pe for the removal of hie pear i#vX aninals and lighters from the Island# H»I # •S» ,, Lavn?ence w is proc^edinp to Linr — and 1 am requesting the Oon'nanrler to talre jou over to the island and brin/r you baoP', ani / ivo yoi such a oiotanoe as may bo necessai^y for t-h-j removal of the fear. You tihoui i give iA asan S3&lt;.naiyeh m opportunity Of g«ln? with you hlmaelf, or aendlni- iisnad; hut do not be delay d on his account. You hould make a list o^ the artioles ta)en for your own information and mine, but do not give ^aean any receipt. On arrival of tho goods at Lingah detain such articles as would fetoh i^- eold the amount needei to nay the .xponseu of removal, if H.san as taJ'en over any or all of th articles from you, take hie receipt for t 5 en. Please send a report of your procee-Unrs bi«k by K.l.l • .;. w JL,awrenco w « Lieut* Col• Lriti^n ^esilent and • •'s Gonaul General etcKo / of 5013 iTie Resident, in the Persian Gulf • To The Officer C wmandin* .S« n Lawrence H ^ated , Hushire January 10th 1913 • In superoQooion of my telephone instructions of yefeter- -day , I have the honour request that on arrival at Linj^ah and after dropping * r Homer there or at Tanb , you will convey the Hen- -idency Agent and anyone whom he wishes to take vrith his# , to Abu yjjj Muea island and assist him in arranging for the removal from that i I ] island to Lingah the gear , animals and lighters of Hassan bin /.li oaaiaiyeb , in accordance with the instructions contained in the en- -closed letter for the Residency Afrent , of which ^ attach a copy f your information • After completing these duties please proceed to Abadan etc as a previously arrnged U I have the honour to be Sir Your obedient servant /i^ ' ^ Lieut Col; . Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ,Telegram. X.T. Prom - 'Lawrence' Henjam. To - Resident, Buehire. Words, nil. Dated and received 12th January 1913. \ New and Agent absent at Naband. Saw brother of latter; Hassan refuses to go Musa, and Hamad is in Bombay; have arranged tow boat to Musa leaving responsible man to remove eleven donkeys etc. The Assistant Agent accompanies me. Hassan asks for three months to remove his property, but has been told your orders. Gilladari not at Lingah, so am wiring Biscoe for information. Leaving here at daylight. 'Lawrence'. Telegram. X.T. Prom - Resident, Bushire. To - 'Lawrence' Hen^am. Dated 12th January 1913. Agent's brother must be responsible for removal of anitoals and gear from the Island forthwith. As long as he understands that and is arranging to carry on well and good. On your way back you might be able to meet New and 'Philomel' and inform Residency Agent my what has passed and of/definite orders. Cox.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [January 13/ CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [1837] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Offi — 13.) THE Under-Secretary of State for India presents his compliments to the Under- Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and forwards herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State, copy of enclosures in a letter from the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, dated the 12th December, 1912, relative to Abu Musa oxide. India Office, January 11, 1913. Enclosure I in No. 1. Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox to Government of India. (Confidential.) Sir, Bushire, November 3, 1912. WITH reference to the letter dated the 15th December from His Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Count Metternich, in which was intimated His Majesty's Government's consent to Messrs. Wonckhaus shipping all the oxide lying already mined at Abu Musa, provided that the final shipment was made before the 31st December, 1912, I have the honour to attach a copy of a report received from the residency agent at Lingah, showing that Messrs. Wonckhaus and Co. are doing their best to get away all the oxide before the year expires. 2. 1 venture to enquire what the position is as regards the second memorandum of His Majesty's Government, dated the 6th December, 1911. It would seem that if the German Government have not yet replied to it, and if in the meanwhile Messrs. Wonckhaus have been permitted to possess themselves of all the available oxide by the end of the year, the latter will be in a strong position for assuming an uncompromising attitude in their negotiations with His Majesty's Government. • I have, &amp;c. P. Z. COX, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Residency Agent, Lingah, to Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox. Lingah, October 26, 1912. I BEG to state that I inspected the two heaps of oxide near the mine in the Abu Musa Island on the 23rd October, 1912. Most of them have been taken to the sea shore by the labourers of Hassan-bin-Someieh, and all the two heaps will be brought to the shore by the end of October. The heap of oxide near the mine called Hadhra, which was near the sea, has also been removed and placed in bags. The quantity placed in bags up to now comes up to 9,000 (nine thousand) bags and the rest remains loose, and they (the labourers) are awaiting more empty bags, which Hassan- bin-Someieh has promised to send at an early date. According to the information given to me by Hassan-bin-Someieh, he has arranged to ship 5,000 bags of oxide to Bombay by the sailing vessel ' Shah Jahun,' and proposes that the vessel should call at the island in the beginning of November to ship the 5,000 bags. He is also negotiating to arrange for a steamer of the Bombay and Persia Company to ship the remainder of the oxide. [2759 n—1]Enclosure 3 in No. 1. Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox to Government of India (Telegraphic.) P. ~ Bushire, November 19, 1912. MY letter of the 3rd November. Since our second memorandum was delivered there have been no local signs that any attempts to collect further evidence with a view to rebutting it have been made by the Germans, so if no reply has been received by His Majesty's Government, their delay must be due to other reasons. In the meantime they are receiving considerable windfalls by the sale of oxide mined before Wonckhaus's coDnection with Abu Musa was established, and not in fulfilment of any of his contracts. If therefore no reply has been received, it may be advisable to explain to His Majesty's Government that the position is apparently as above, and to express hope that no further concessions will be accorded if the German reply is delayed or is received in an uncompromising shape. £ rr*r. m—mi[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government. 1 ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [January 13.] CONPIDENTTAL. Section g. [1839] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—(Received January 13.) THE Under-Secretary of State for India presents his compliments to the Under- Secretary of State for oreign Affairs, and forwards herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State, copy of a telegram to the Viceroy, dated the 2nd January 1913 regarding Abu Musa. ' India Office, January 11, 1913. Enclosure in No. 1. The Marquess of Crewe to Government of India. (Telegraphic.) P. India Office, January 2, 1913. ABU MUSA. Please see letter from Cox of 3rd November and your telegram of 2nd December. Please let me know whether any oxide remained to be exported at the end of the year. [2759 n—2]CONFIDENTIAL H. B. M 1 b Vic«-CcntoUlate and AbL.it&gt;tant R«bidency, Linc«h, l^th January 1913 • Uahadijir A^ha Bed«r for the r«:Tioval of Hat;ban Sumaya'b gear from Abu Mut»a, I hear todaj'- that Herr Robenfeld ^ent off a 'beat yesterday to Han jam with a telegram for Buahir®, po^tiilDly pl«adinf: for more crace to bhip oxide and 'btlay the removal of Ha^ban 1 b c e 9'r. Ac^a Beder in vited Hatban to accompany him to Abu Muba or bend hi^ a^ent, but, after conbultation with Herr Ro^enfeld, he refubed to have anything to do with it, and hib bon Abdullah Hab been '^latin^ it round the Bazaar that they will refuse to take deliver^'- of their gear here. Local gObbip is? interebted and, in view of Herr Roberfeld Habban and Coattitude^I think it would be damaging to our preutige to concede anything. Agha Bed^r ib reporting to you by 'Lawrence', but he hab not yet heard of the above development. Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K. C, I. R., C, S. I., Political Rebident and H. B. M'b Conbul General, B U S H I R R. In connection with your ord^rb to KhanTELEGRAM P From Resident To Foreign Delhi no. 167# dated Jan. 27th 1913. Your telegram C 53 ABU MUSA OXIDE Qwing to absence of ■'•esidency agent there was been dome d'ei-ay in replying to the reference mg lo tne reierence. • the'5000 oad bags m On 14th Nov. the 7 5000 oad bags mentioned in the enclosure A to my letter 2894 Nov. 3rd was effected. No further shipment was made up to Dec 31st and it appears from report dated 17th from the Residency Agent that Ktur Hasan Samaiyah^ gear has,b-en removed from the Island. in the meanwhile, Messrs Wonskhau^b Lingah Agent is believed tp have telegraphed to the German Consul Buahire asking him to obtain a further pm\*, but met with an advesee response to his request.[This Docmnent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.! ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [January 17.] Section 1. [2531] No. 1. Sir L. Mallet to Councillor of German Embassy. •.7&lt;r SIR LOUIS MALLET presents his compliments to the Councillor of the German Embassy and, with reference to the conversation which took place on the 9th instant relative to the question of the red oxide mines in the island of Abu Musa, has the honour to state that, if Herr Wonckhaus will be good enough to adopt the proposal that he should visit this country in order to set forth his objections to certain of the suggestions for a settlement in the last British note, representatives of His Majesty's Government will be very happy to receive him. Sir L. Mallet ventures at the same time to suggest that it might assist discussion and facilitate an early settlement if His Majesty's Government were furnished, previous to Herr Wonckhaus's arrival, with some written indication of the nature of the objections which he desires to raise to the British proposals. foreign Office, January 17, 1913. [2759 r— 1] rr (2 V\j 1 —[This Document is the Property of His Britannic M ajesty's Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND AHABIA. [January 30.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [4639 J No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—(Received January 30.) THE Under-Secretary of State for India presents his compliments to the Under- Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and forwards herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State, copy of a telegram from the Viceroy, dated the 29th January, 1913, relative to Abu Musa oxide. India Office, January 80, 1913. Enclosure in No. 1. Government of India to the Marquess of Crewe. (Telegraphic.) P. Januaru 29, 1913. ABU MUSA oxide. Please refer to your telegram of the 2nd January. Following report received in reply from political resident, Persian Gulf;— ' Please refer to enclosure to my letter of the 3rd November, 1912. The 5,000 odd bags alluded to there were shipped on the 14th November. Up to the 31st December, 1912, no other shipment took place, and it appears from the report of the 17th January from the agent that the removal of Hasan's gear from the island has now been effected. It is believed that in the meanwhile Wonckhaus's Lingah agent asked the German consul, Bushire, by wire to get further respite for him, but that the reply from the csnsul was not favourable.' i [2759 W -l] j L /Hi' ty rom. To, Fo: L+iT of 1913 . Camp Tanh Island. r)ated» I9'th February 19IS C.J. Homer, Esquire, 0/C Persian fmlf Light House For^s, The Political Resident and Consul General, in the Persian Gulf, 'Bu. shire. oir. 'T^ith reference to your verbal enquiry on the occasion of your recent visit to this island as to — the cost of the temporary roads constructed for conveyance of material from the beach to the lighthouse site* I have the honour to report as follows: The main road which extends from the bouth beach, where the lighthouse material has been landed, to the lighthouse site, is 12,540 (2 miles - 3 furlongs) in length of which about 7 furlongs goes over the hill and in this section there was a great deal of heavy roc 1 ? ex- -cavation and some side cutting'. The branch road from near my present camp to the East (South-^ast really) beach is 3,7^0 ft: in length most of which is over fairly flat ground with roc 1 ! excavation, in two or three places only. The total length of both roads is 1^,300 ft: (nearly 3 miles and. I furlong) and the cost of building this was Es 1,018/-. This wor'rs out to just about one anna per running foot of road. 10 to II feet wide. Inhere the — road goes over flat ground the cost is about 7 pies per running foot. •I LUu* jU //; ■ psic .Asff -y -i /f ■ • ■ ' !jCL /&amp;*- /f/V 73 - L.B.C. ^ rpf 0 / 0 Persian Gulf Li^ht House ^orts. I have the honor to be, Sir, ! T ost Obedient Servant.• - (J Duplicate. [Form 2 c 6. [Account Form 65, Dr. Offi s' Mess, % \ t ^.gs.LiAWRENCE, 9&lt;/Z3 Army Regulations, India, Vol X, Part I, Passages, Sea, para 51^. ssin^^^V' jZ 3^^^, .. ... Messini Wines Cigars Whist Library subscription for use of books during passage. Total Pvupeesf No- No. 1617, dated Bushire, the 18th (received 26th) June 1911 (Confidential). From— Lieutenant-Colonel P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit, for the information of the Government of India, a statement of expenses incurred during the past year by the Residency Agent at Lingah in connection with visits to Abu Musa on my behalf and emergent petty repairs carried out on the sheds there. Since the dispute with the German firm arose in 1906, it has always been necessary for me to have a representative on the island while any mining or shipment of oxide has been in progress. Accounts previous to these I was able to settle out of the proceeds of the sample shipment of oxide taken by Messrs. Strick m June 1909, but it will be remembered that since the dispute began, the rent for the Concession formerly drawn by Shaikh Sagar, or Salim, from the island, has been under suspension and although the precautions and repairs connected with which this account is presented have been carried out in the interests of the suit, and therefore in the interests of the Shaikh, nevertheless the latter would certainly not relish having to pay and I would be glad if the Government of India would be pleased to sanction the disburse ment of such expenses, incidental to the course of the case, from Government funds. If desired, I would give the Shaikh a memorandum of them and saying that Government were pleased for the present to disburse these sums, but will reserve to themselves the right to ask him to reimburse them when the oxide industry is resumed and he is deriving income from it. Statement of expenses incurred hy khan bahadur agha Bedr, Residency Agent, Lingah, in connection with th' red oxide mines at Abu Musa. Particulars of charges. Amount. Total. Rbmabks. £ a. p. R a. p. Cost of hurdles and rope for Ibrahim's lodging . 2 0 0 Salary of two servants ..... 25 U 0 Dailv food from 6th to 24-th April 1910 . 28 8 0 Present to Abdullah, employe of Shaikh Suggar. 3 8 0 Boat-hire from Lingah to the S.S. Naseri and 6 0 0 back. 65 0 0 Repairs to the Godowns, Abu Musa. Cost of 20 hurdles ..... 20 0 0 Do. 3 scores chandals , 36 0 0 Do. 30 baskets ..... 7 8 0 Coolie-hire on above ..... 2 4 0 Boat-hire from Lingah to Abu Musa 25 0 0 Wages of Masons, etc. ..... 20 0 0 110 12 0 962 F. D —8 K —51-54—Sept.Btatement of expenses incurfed hy khan S ahad UR A qha B edr, Residency Agent, Lxngah, tm connection with the red oxide mines at Abu Musa —contd. Particulars of charges. Amount. Total. rbkibei. Second Trip. R a. P- R a. P- Boat -hire from 1st to 6th September 19 1U . 42 0 0 'Wages of 14 coolies @ R1 each (including food) for six days. 84 0 0 Wages of two ship-carpenters @ R2-8 each (including food) for six days. 80 0 0 • v : : : Cost of materials for repairing two lighters 10 0 0 166 0 0 Third Trip. Boat-hire to Abu Musa ..... 35 0 0 Wages of two servants (R18-11-10 and 3-2-11) . 62 6 0 Daily food for the above period *117 0 c 214 6 0 Total •• 556 2 0 No. 1591-E.A, dated Simla, the 29th August 1911 (Confidential). From— The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To Liedtenant-Colonel P. Z. Cox, C.S .I., C .I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. 1 am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 1617 (Con fidential), dated the 18th June 1911, forwarding for sanction a statement of expenses, amounting to 11550-2-0 incurred by the Residency Agent, Lmgah, during the past year, in connection with visits to Abu Musa on your benali, and emergent petty repairs carried out on the sheds there. 2 In reply I am to inform you that the Government of India agree to bear the expenditure in question as a charge against Indian revenues I am to add that it is considered inadvisable to ask the Shaikh of Shargah to re imburse the amount, or even to share it. Exd - P M. Mf !,^nd 43 CONFIDENTIAL. tjP RBCEIPl c J-\ Mo. | Date 5 APL.^13 . V v^' No. 738, dated Bushire, 1st (received 10th) March 1913. SI AN G From —Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K C.I.E, C .S .I, Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. I have the honour to refer to Foreign Department letter No. J591 -E.A., dated 29th August 191 1, and to submit herewith for favour of sanction, a state ment of expenses amounting to Rs. 301-8-0 incurred by the Residency Agent, Lingah under my instructions, in connection with Messrs. Wonckhaus' or Hassan Samaiyeh's operations on Abu Musa Island during the year 1912. It has been no less necessary this year than before, for the Residency to keep representative on the island while work has been going on. 2. Having regard to my reduced allotments during the financial year now drawing to a close, I find it will not be possible for me to meet the expenditure by reappropriation, and therefore beg that special provision may be made. Statement of expenses incurred by Khan Bahadur Agha Bedr } Residency Agent, Lingah. Wages of head watchman for 5 months and 7 days (ending 25th November 1912) @ Rs. 30 per mensem Wages of assistant watchman for same period @ Rs. 15 per mensem Boat hire from Lingah to Abu Musa and back for above watchmen ... Ropes and hurdles for temporary huts of watchmen Cost of passage of Khan Bahadur Agha Bedr and his assistant from Lingah to Abu Musa and back by native sailing vessel ... Table money paid to R. I. M. S.' Lawrence '' for two days in January for Agha Bedr, and his assistant's passage from Lingah to Abu Musa and back ... Rs. A. P. •57 78 •5 7 32 12 Total o 8 o o o o o o ... 301 8 o II C93FD—44—i7'3.i3—GCBP Simla- ^ Uo. 1. Sir L« Mallet to Councillor of German jeiDbaesyo Sir Louis Mallet presents his compliments to the Councillor of the uerman ismhassy and # with reference to the conversation which took place on the 9th instant relative to the question of the red oxide mine* in the island of Abu Musa, has the honour to state that, if Herr Wonckhaus will be good enough to adopt the proposal that he should visit this country in order to set forth his objections to certain of the suggestions for a settlement in the last I British note, representatives of His Majesty's Grovernment will be very happy to receive him. Sir L# Mallet ventures at the same time to suggest that it might assist discussion and facilitate an early settlement if His Majesty 's uovernraent were furnished. previous to Hsrr Wonckhaus's arrival, with some written indication of the nature of the objections which he desires to raise to the British proposals® Foreign Office, January 17 # 1913„Confidential. / ^7 I D»te 20.MAH.1913 ' / ♦ &gt;/ 30 • A* A copy of the foregoing Memorandum ie forwarded to the political Resident in the pereian (*ulf # for infor mation, with reference to the correspondence ending with hie telegram ^o, 167, dated th^ 27th January 1913, 3y order, etc,, secretary to the Government of India, Foreign j^partment., Simla; The / ^ ^ March 1913. Memorandum from Sir L. Mallet to Councillor of the German iaahassy, uo. 2531, dated the 17th January 1913, i With one spare copy, r?K -X (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) 'dfo &lt;2/ /#&lt;?'. To The Residence Apent Sharpah. A»C* Uith reference to my letter RP dated 25th February to vour address ;ahn Bahadur Agher Badr writes that besides the ^ r )0 bags of oxide 1 ing at the landing nlace there is also a considerable heap of the s lying near the flagstaff. This also should not be interfered with. tuff S 18—5,000- 5-12No . - 1»A. Tii« Deputy Secretary tt th# Gorernment of India in the yoroign Department, Lieut.-Cel. Sir ?• Z. Cox, K-C.I.E., C.S.I*, PeliticaX Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Simla, the April 1913, In reply to yeur letter No.738 Cenfidential, dated the 1st March 1913, I am directed to conyey sancticn te the expenditure ef Rs.301-8-0 incurred 'by the Residency Agent, Lingah, in connection with Messrs. Wenckhaus # or Hassan 3amaiyeh f s operations on Abu Musa Island during tne year 1912. K* ■ XT'* \ w $ tA &amp; / 0* i! - \ 1 \f AQ I have the honour te he, Sir, Your most obedient serTant, v Deputy Secretary to the frevsri&amp;nent of Indi«. II IIIy* Copy of a letter from 'Isa bin f Abdul Latlf to the Politi cal Resident in the PerBian O^ilf, Dated 17th Muharram liSd {» 20th February 1908)• I beg to bring to Your Honour^ notice that I have heard that is Honour Sh -'tikh ^aqar bin Khalid has in accordance wltb v. vr'vice d : the xalted and Imperial Govemnent arranged to wemit Ha ean bin T Ali Somaiyah that if the Gernan Oompany asked him for the shipment of the oxide lying down on the chore o^ f &gt;ie island, and which ie ready for shipment, he is to sr .ip the same on certain conditions* As I am an original partner in the said lease, It has become necessary for me to represent to Your Honour as follows:- A period of ten years has now elapsed since the beginning of the lease. It was at first arranged between us, the part ners, that no sale or transaction can be completed without the consultation o; all. It is now ten years that this lease has been current and # during this period, Haji Hasan bin # A11 ::omaiyah has excavated much oxide from the mine on the Abu usr lolan ; and he Is constantly accumulating the stuff there so t at the oxide mayjbe ready for sale when a buyer is forth coming. Hence I presume that he has sold probably a Quantity o ght thousand tons or oxide since the beginning up to now, and it is likely that there is on the island a quantity of six thousand tons or more which has been excavated from the mine a long tine ago, and a p?trt of this consists of the quantity which, as I stated above, has been brought to the sea-shore for ahinment in the Germ n stealer. I have continually demand ed an account from him, but have not received It. Ha^l Hasan has given absolutely nothing to anyone, and I am afraid that owing to the cessation of thin lease, Hajl Hasan may enter the whole of this oxido in his own account. Seeing that the oxide now available was excavated before Hasan contracted with JoncchauB, to which contract we did not agree, and that atany rite it» axcavatlon was before the nullification of the lease y aiyar, I ooneldep mysolf entitled to mv w share In all that has been excavated from the mine. I &gt;6 therefore to rcprenont ray condition to Tottr Honour and to solicit from you that Bajl Hasan should produce before you hin account frora the beglnnlnc to the end, so that no change and alteration may occur in the account and that the distribution 'nay be effected proportionately, and every one should receive his dividend. hi- lo what had to be stated and nay you remain presenred.Statement of •ina bin 'Abe! 1 Latif re^ardin^ the Oxide Company. Dated 17ih uharrarri 1526 (= 20th February 1908). in regard to the affairs of the Company in which I am a partner # the facto of the caae are aa followa:- The Company at first consisted of 3 partners, viz, I mysolf, ilaji Hasan bin ijomaiyah and his son •Abdullah bin Hasan, hen v^e obtained the lease we gave a share to lla huda •All Ahmad Lalih. V/hen Shaikh Saqar returned from the ilaj, he also requested us for a share and we c ave ^ to him on the Ist Rabl II 1326 ( 3rd May 1908) and so the Company consisted of five men with equal shares. After the lapse of six months, l.e« in the month of Ramazan, my cousin, Yusuf bin 'Abdullah asked S aikh Saqar to sell his share to him and the Ghailch sold his share to the said Yusuf as he had derived no advantage (there from )• Yusuf remained a partner for two years and as he obtained no profit on this share during those years xk he sold his share to Ha.11 Hasan bin Somaiyah. Conse- i quently H ji Hasan held two shares, his son 'Abdullah held one share, Nakhuda 'All one share and I held one share. Several times I paid Shaikh Salim my share of the annual rent as well as some of the expenses. I did not at all give a oower of attorney to Ha.il Hasan, so that he me may act an he liked without consulting/ in the matter of the lease. On the contrary, it was inc mbent on him that in every transaction he should act after consult ing us as was agreed upon in the preliminary agreement between ourselves and Ha.^i 'All Ahmad Sallh./Since the ^ ' ■■ beginning of the lease up to the date of his contract with Wonckhaus the German, Ha,11 Hasan has frequently shipped oxide to Calcutta, Bombay etc without informing ui5,-as he ou;;ht- according to what had been stipu lated, but If we heard regarding the shipment and asked him about It, he would then Inform us of It. The list of his shipments, as reported to us by him and others Is recorded with us and its quantity Is 800° tone approx- imately.^y Whenever wetn never v© as od him about the settlement of the account o. the oxide, he would give ue an evasive reply. L?y father used to correspond with hira on my behalf. On the 18th Rabi II 1384 (= 11th June 1906), Haji Hasan Informed ray father Of ip transaction with ^onckhaue the German, but forwarded neither the original of the agreement nor a copy thereof, and i r1 not at a11 ra ©ntion the conclusion of a written contract in tnl- matter. He only mentioned to my father that he had sola to vionc chaue 200^ tons per annum and If more (oxide) was excavated It wouXd be taken by the Ger-ian. My father wrote to Haji Hasan esnecially on several occasions warning i in against giving any foothold or contr?ict to outsiders. In re-ly he used always to give assurance that he would not enter into any bargain except the sale of oxide to those who mi^ht . Bavin that Ha ? i Hasan has concluded a contract in this matter, we protested against his doing so, demanded from him a copy of the contract an* repeated our demand until he forwarded it. It was written in English, and when we nerueed its translation into Arabic, we found certain things t ereln which are undesirable. I disagreed immediately and I -ifornad hlra of my disapproval of this contract arvl co~- olalnad to 3halkh Saqar in the matter.TELEGRAM.P. From Secretary of State for India . To Viceroy. Repeated Resident. Foreign . Secret. Dated and received 3.6.13. With reference to previous correspondence on the subject of Ahy Musa. It is requested that you will forward your views on the German proposals,set forth in the papers which have be 3n sent to v&lt;5u by the mails of the 16th and 23rd of May, at jts early a date as possible. /JJ^U bS (Translation.) Respecting Abu Musa. Hamburg, March 10, 1013. WE beg leave to point out the following objections to the compromise suggested by the British Government for the settlement of the Abu Musa case;— 1. After our former experiences with Sheikh Seker, who claims the right of cancelling, at any time and without indicating his reasons, concessions granted by him, we have no confidence that a fresh concession from him would enable the mines to be worked steadily and on a technically sound basis. As regards the transfer of the concession to ' suitable persons,' the parties concerned—the British Government, the sheikh, and ourselves—are scarcely likely to be able to reach an agreement as to the persons to be considered as ' suitable.' On the other hand, the fact should be taken into account that, in view of the circumstances of the case, we ourselves have the first claim to consideration in any concession which is granted, since it is we who would have the greatest interest in the mines being worked in a rational way, and since we are in every way competent to carry on the work. Moreover, the position created by the granting of the concession to a third person would be uncertain from this point of view also: that there would always be the possibility, if not the probability, of conflicts in the future. But who is to be the competent person to settle such differences of view arising in the future, and who is responsible for the damage incurred by the person working the mines for failure to carry out the contracts of delivery ? 2. As regards the further proposal that we should be reinstated in our contract rights for a period equal to that during which the contract was interrupted, i.e., for about two years and eight months, it must be observed that such a proposal does not take sufficient account of the present situation of the oxide industry. The preparations extending over several years for carrying on this industry must be regarded as entirely lost, and the work will, for the most part, have to be undertaken anew. Two to three years will elapse before we reach approximately the point at which we were at the time of our forcible ejection from the island of Abu Musa. The further period to be allowed to us would therefore have expired before we could bring large shipments on to the market. It should further be borne in mind that, if we accept the present compromise, we should not be in a position to guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide to our customers. Every purchaser of oxide would insert in any fresh contract a condition that we should guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide over a considerable period of years. It is precisely the existence of these conditions in the oxide industry which caused us to adopt the prolongation clause in our contract with the mining companv. From the above it will be seen what difficulties we should encounter were we t accept the British proposals. We therefore beer leave to submit the follow T inor counter proposal:— Sheikh Seker to grant us, under the guarantee of the British and German Governments, a concession for all the oxide mines on the island of Abu Musa for a period of six years, and on the conditions laid down in the original concession of the mining company. We ourselves to work the mines and to make use of them as we think fit. During this period the concession can on no account be withdrawn. Sheikh Seker shall further be obliged, after the expiration of the first six years of the concession, to renew it for a further period of six years on the same conditions, if no •other applicant is forthcoming. Should there be any other applicant, we are to be entitled to tender with him. The British Government have expressed the w 7 ish to be furnished with a complete and detailed statement of our claims for damages. The direct losses which we have sustained through the interruption of the w T ork on Abu Musa are as follows :— (I.) Our advances to the mining company, and the value of the deposits on the island which have been either destroyed or removed, 13,106 M.(2.) The damage sustained through the Louise,' The value of this shipment can be proved, by comparison with the ' Stolzenfels' shipment, to have been, at the lowest estimate, 20 M. per 1,000 kilog. Of this we still have about 469 tons lying unused; we only very rarely succeed in selling small quantities of this, since the oxide has been rendered useless for nearly all industries by the presence of salt deposit and fine sand. In addition we should be compensated for storage expenses, the interest thereon, and insurance expenses. It is well known that the quality of the 'Louise' shipment suffered from the oxide having been left lying unprotected for a period of tully six months after the interruption of work, close to the shore to which it was being taken for shipment. Sandstorms and spray and exposure to the weather must greatly affect the quality of oxide, because, firstly, the colour became darker; and, secondly, the colouring properties of the oxide had considerably diminished owing to the action of salt, sand, and w T eather. The damage under this head can be proved to amount to 78,500 M. 31 pf. &gt; e endeavoured at the time to Induce the sheikh to allow at least a few of our people to remain on the island in order to protect the oxide' from deterioration by covering over with planks the quantity which had been carried to the shore for shipment; our request was, however, not granted. (3.) A lump sum to cover the cost of putting the mmes again into a state of repair. We estimate that a sum of 30,000 M. will be necessary for this. We cannot turnish documentary evidence in regard to- this amount. On our making enquiries of oui'local representative in regard to the amount necessary for the repair of the mines, the above sum was indicated to us as being absolutely necessary. (4.) A suitable compensation for the employ^ of the firm (two Europeans and ten natives) for the serious danger to which they were exposed by the firing on Abu Musa, ' M. (5.) Suitable compensation should also be paid in respect of the-jjeneral damage sustained by our firm through the interruption of mining operations. • The Interraption of the Industry and the resulting failure to deliver the oxide was a shock to our whole business, since our reputation suffered heavily not only in the Persian Gulf but also in Europe; this involves a diminution of the vital power of our enterprise, and means an actual monetary loss. v *' It would be better to reserve more detailed statements in regard to points 4 and 5 for verbal discussion. ^ Should the British Government not be disposed to agree to a prolongation of the contract for periods of six or twelve years as the case may be, we would be prepared to renounce our claims in this respect on payment of suitable compensation, (Signed) EOBEET WONCKHAUS and. G o. To the JForeign Office, Berlin.u sL ;l 'J r TELEGRAil.P. From Foroign. To Resident. No. 157 3. Dated and received 11.6.13. iibu Musa Island. With reference to Secretary of State's telegram dated June 3rd , it is requested that you will forward as soon as possible your views regarding the state- -ment dated March 10th made by Wonckhaus which the India Office despatched to you on the ^ 16th of last month.hi V - Meinoranduni. The correspondence mentioned heloic is herewith transmitted to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with a view to avoiding delay in the event of the Foreign Department of the Government of India desiring to communicate with him on the subject. A copy of this memorandum and of the correspondence is also being communicated to that Department by to-day s mail. Assistant Secretary, Political Department. INDIA OFFICE, 23rd May J(J] 2 Oil for Tamb Island Liahthonsa . 'Report by the Director General of Stores, India Office, dated 2nd May 1913* m Persian Gulf: Abu Musa Oxide. j From Foreign Office, 21st May and enclosures, - ^ (I)11 {17fclS/l3) believe that the manf? advanced can huv« been very con- alderiihle. A p for the second, the deBtinjctlon of tfepofiit* referred to 1b irenunably destruction by exyonure to the veather, but rir F. Orey c^oes not knovr by ^on nny ox it e Imp been removed except by ^e ?Fr». W5nckhtu« thennelve^. Further Infornetlon would there* fore have to be supplied by the flm with refsrenc# to thlB itm. Itttrn £ of the claim rprean* t-o ^lr E. Grey to be entirely unjvntlfled. The oxide by the •Louise* Vrti-f; Uio^d to leave by H 1f T^euty'n Govern ment cs* em act of grace in o/der to render easier the position cf Mwors. Wondch^ue, Any rrofit v.httever frofi! thiB fihij.^nt nnuRt therefo:*® b€ regarded an pure gain for the firr and Hip ^rJeFty'r Grov^mment csJUiot t^nit ^ny clalfi baped on the fact - if it be a fact - that the qu* lit:' of the mineral 1 p inferior to that of previous conPignraentB or that there hai? been a difficulty of diupofiing of it. It appears to Sir E. Grey that if the claim under (5) 1b valid at all it concerne a question which should b« eettied between the Sheilch andi the mining company, a nst* . 'Ic (Translation.) Respecting Abu Musa. Hamburg, March 10, 1013. WE beg leave to point out the following objections to the compromise suggested by the British Government for the settlement of the Abu Musa case:— 1. After our former experiences with Sheikh Seker, who claims the right of cancelling, at any time and without indicating his reasons, concessions granted by him, we have no confidence that a fresh concession from him would enable the mines to be worked steadily and on a technically sound basis. As regards the transfer of the'' concession to ' suitable persons,' the parties concerned—the British Government, the sheikh, and ourselves—are scarcely likely to be able to reach an agreement as to the persons to be considered as ' suitable.' On the other hand, the fact should be takeir into account that, in view of the circumstances of the case, we ourselves have the first claim to consideration in any concession which is granted, since it is we who would have the greatest interest in the mines being worked in a rational way, and since we are in every way competent to carry on the work. Moreover, the position created by the granting of the concession to a third person would be uncertain from this point of view also: that there would always be the possibility, if not the probability, of conflicts in the future. But who is to be the competent person to settle such differences of view arising in the future, and who is responsible for the damage incurred by the person working the mines for failure to carry out the coutracts of delivery ? 2. As regards the further proposal that we should be reinstated in our contract rights for a period equal to that during which the contract was interrupted, i.e., for about two years and eight months, it must be observed that such a proposal does not take sufficient account of the present situation of the oxide industry. The preparations' ] extending over several years for carrying on this industry must be regarded as entirely lost, and the work will, for the most part, have to be undertaken anew. Two to three years will elapse before we reach approximately the point at which we were at the time of our forcible ejection from the island of Abu Musa. The further period to be ^ allowed to us would therefore have expired before we could bring large shipments on to the market. It should further be borne in mind that, if we accept the present compromise, we should not be in a position to guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide to our customers. Every purchaser of oxide would insert in any fresh contract a condition that we should guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide over a considerable period ■of years. It is precisely the existence of these conditions in the oxide industry which caused us to adopt the prolongation clause in our contract with the mining companv. From the above it will be seen what difficulties we should encounter were we t accept the British proposals. We therefore beg leave to submit the following counter proposal:— Sheikh Seker to grant us, under the guarantee of the British and German Governments, a concession for all the oxide mines on the island of Abu Musa for a period of six years, and on the conditions laid down in the original concession of the mining company. We ourselves to work the mines and to make use of them as we think fit. During this period the concession can on no account be withdrawn. Sheikh Seker shall further be obliged, after the expiration of the first six years of the concession, to renew it for a further period of six years on the same conditions, if no other applicant is forthcoming. Should there be any other applicant, we are to be entitled to tender with him. The British Government have expressed the wish to be furnished with a complete and detailed statement of our claims for damages. The direct losses which we have sustained through the interruption of the work on Abu Musa are as follows:— (1.) Our advances to the mining company, and the value of the deposits on the island which have been either destroyed or removed, 13,106 M. [6181 f , uyi ( l \ a UX U &gt;l 4 a Ll(2.) The damage sustained through the 'Louise.' The value of this shipment' can be proved, by comparison with the ' Stolzenfels' shipment, to have been, at the » lowest estimate, M. per 1,000 kilog. Of this we still have about 469 tons lying unused; we only very rarely succeed in selling small quantities of this, since the oxide has been rendered useless for nearly all industries by the presence of salt deposit and fine sand. In addition we should be compensated for storage expenses, the interest thereon, and insurance expenses. It is well known that the quality of the ' Louise ' shipment suffered from the oxide having been left lying unprotected for a period of fully six months after the interruption of work, close to the shore to which it was being taken for shipment. Sandstorms and spray and exposure to the weather -must greatly affect the quality of oxide, because, firstly, the colour became darker; and, secondly, the colouring properties of the oxide had considerably diminished owing to the action of salt, sand, and weather. The damage under this head can be proved to amount to 78,500 M. 31 pf. ^ e endeavoured at the time to induce the sheikh ito allow at least a few of our peoplp, to remain on the island in order to protect the oxide from deterioration by covering over with planks the quantity which had been carried to the shore for shipment; our request was, however, not granted. (3.) A lump sum to cover the cost of putting the mines again into a state of repair. We estimate that a sum of 30,000 M. will be necessary for this. We cannot furnish documentary evidence in regard to this amount. On our making enquiries of' our local representative in regard to the amount necessary for the repair of the mines, the above sum was indicated to us as being absolutely necessary. (4.) A suitable compensation for the employes of the firm (two Europeans and ten natives) for the serious danger to which they were exposed by the firing on Abu Musa, M. (5.) buitable compensation should also be paid in respect of the general damage sustained by our firm through the interruption of mining operations. The interruption of the industry and the resulting failure to deliver the oxide was-a shock to our whole business, since our reputation suffered heavily not only in the Persian Gulf but also in Europe ; this involves a diminution of the vital power of our enterprise^ and means an actual monetary loss. It would be better to reserve more detailed statements in regard to points 4 and 5 for verbal discussion. Should the British Government not be disposed to agree to a prolongation of the contract for periods of six or twelve years as the case may be, we would be prepared to- renounce our claims in this respect on payment of suitable compensation. (Signed) ROBEKT WONCKHAUS and G o. Td the Foreign Office,, Berlin.1) Trans lat i on. German fimhassy, April 5th 1913. Your Kxcellenoy, With reference to Sir Louis Mallet 'a communication of January 17th last, No. 2531, I have the hononr, umie^ instructions from my Govemmen1 9 to transmit herewith the accompanying communication f^O' the firm of Robert Wonhhaus * This document con~ tains a statement of the objections of the firm to the proposals of the British Govern/aent for settling the case, I should be grateful if Your Excellency would inform me when the proposed direct negotiations of Mr. R. Wonkhaus with representatives of the British Government should begin. I have Ac., fSigned) LichnowskyTELEGRAM.P. From Foreign. i 1 o Residant • No. 171 s. Dated and received 17.6.13. With reference to my telegram No. 157 S on the subject of Abu :.iuea Island, when may a reply be expected?Telegram - P. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Foreign, Dimla, No. 1094. Dated June 19th 1913. V/ith reference to and in continuation of my telegram immediately preceding this. The grant of a concession to a foreigner would in any case be inconsistent with the advice given by me authoritatively to the oheikhs. We should, in my opinion, rule this out, as it would create a bad impression. If it should be possible, the most satisfactory course would be to buy Wonckhaus out completely, and then alio?/ him to compete on the same footing as others. It would seem in this connection that in order to strengthen his position in regard to Hormuz, Strick might find it of considerable advantage to participate in the Abu I.lusa Concession. Firstly, he would probably be able to mix,the Abu Musa product with the Hormuz quantity, and in this way sell a greater quantity of the former. Se condly, if there was to be any hitch in the Hormuz ar rangement, he could fall back on the Abu Musa industry. In view of the above considerations Strick, in order to secure our support to his nomination, (in association with Esa bin Abdul Latif and Hassan Samaiyeh - if the exclu sion of the latter is found to be impossible), might possi bly be ready to put down a lump sum, which could then form part of the compensation that Wonckhaus would have to be given. In any case, I recommend that Strick be sounded on the subject and His Majesty's Foreign Office could possibly instruct Captain Wilson to approach him, and give the message as an informal communication from me, if they do not wish to appear in the business themselves. Instead of compensation it might be arranged that the new Company should give Wonckhaus advantageous rates forfor a certain period* -- f it is found impossible to buy hir out altogether. They have no heavy royalty to pay as in the case of the Ilorinuz material, and so could quite easily afford to do this. i/ N Telogram - Code. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Foreign, Simla, No. 1095. Dated IQtli June 1913. Your telegram 157-S. of 11th June. To answer in detail on all points would entail correspondence with Lingah or visit to spot. ohort of that following are my views on Memorandum of 10th March. Firstly . In my opinion, so far as the mine is concerned, there is nothing in the contention that some time must elapse before it can be profitably worked. It is only a question of finding market. Paragraph 2. First clause. Suggestions that preparations of several years are entirely lost is baseless. Supposing that oxide exists there is no reason why Concessionnaires should not guarantee to supply any customer with so many tons per annum. Counter proposals appear to be totally unaccept able. As regards statement of claims. Clause (i). No deposits have been destroyed and only one small shipment removed: but in any case the amount claimed is inconsiderable. Clause (2). I believe that suggestion as to results of ex posure are imaginary. All through history of concession it has been the custom to dig in a leisurely way at slack times and stuff has habitually lain for months, and sometimes for years before shipment. I have it on expert authority that » exposure to air or spray causes a hard crust to form on which the surface of heaps/effectively protects their inside. Such a thing as covering with planks, I believe, to be quite un usual. I recommend disputing this claim altogether. Clause (3). Amount claimed for this purpose is absurd; there is nothing to be done but clear a little debris due to a small land slip from under-digging. We might avoid this claim by offering to do work ourselves. Clause (4). There is no justification for compensation. ClauseClause (5), This claim is greatly exaggerated and dif ficult in any case to assess except arbitrarily. I a^r of opinion that, however, it is the most convenient head for settlement of the case by payment of a lump sum.[This Doctiment is the Property of Kis Britannic Majesty s Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [April 18.] CONFIDENTIAL. S ection 5, [17815] No. I. Prince Lichnowsky to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received April 18.) (Translation.) Your Excellency, German Embassy, April 5, 1913. WITH reference to Sir Lonis Mallet's communication of the 17th January last, I have the honour, under instructions from my Government, to transmit herewith the accompanying communication from the firm of Robert Wonckhaus. This document contains a statement of the objections of the firm to the proposals of the British Government for settling the case. 1 should be grateful if your Excellency would inform me when the proposed direct negotiations of Mr. R. Wonckhaus with representatives of the British Government should begin. 1 have, &amp;c. LICHNOWSKY. Enclosure in No. 1. (Translation.) Memorandum respecting Abu Musa. Hamburg, March 10, 1913. WE beg leave to point out the following objections to the compromise suggested by the British Government for the settlement of the Abu Musa case :— 1. After our former experiences with Sheikh Seker, who claims the right of cancelling, at any time and without indicating his reasons, concessions granted by him, we have no confidence that a fresh concession from him would enable the mines to be worked steadily and on a technically sound basis. As regards the transfer of the concession to ' suitable persons,' the parties concerned—the British Government, the sheikh, and ourselves—are scarcely likely to be able to reach an agreement as to the persons to be considered as ' suitable.' On the other hand, the fact should be taken into account that, in view of the circumstances of the case, we ourselves have the first claim to consideration in any concession which is granted, since it is we who would have the greatest interest in the mines being worked in a rational way, and since we are in every way competent to carry on the work. Moreover, the position created by the granting of the concession to a third person would be uncertain from this point of view also: that there w 7 ould always be the possibility, if not the probability, of conflicts in the future. But who is to be the competent person to settle such differences of view arising in the future, and who is responsible for the damage incurred by the person working the mines for failure to carry out the contracts of delivery ? 2. As regards the further proposal that we should be reinstated in our contract rights for a period equal to that during which the contract was interrupted, i.e., for about two years and eight months, it must be observed that such a proposal does not take sufficient account of the present situation of the oxide industry. The preparations extending over several years for carrying on this industry must be regarded as entirely lost, and the work will, for the most part, have to be undertaken anew. Two to three years will elapse before we reach approximately the point at which we were at the time of our forcible ejection from the island of Abu Musa. The further period to be allowed to us would therefore have expired before we could bring large shipments on to the market. It should further be borne in mind that, if we accept the present compromise, we should not be in a position to guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide to our customers. Every purchaser of oxide would insert in any fresh contract a condition that we should guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide over a considerable period [2884 s—5]of years. It is precisely the existence of these conditions in the oxide industry which caused us to adopt the prolongation clause in our contract with the mining company. From the above it will be seen what difficulties we should encounter were we to accept the British proposals. We therefore bee^ leave to submit the following counter proposal :— Sheikh Seker to grant us, under the guarantee of the British and German Governments, a concession for all the oxide mines on the island of Abu Musa for a period of six years, and on the conditions laid down in the original concession of the mining company. We ourselves to work the mines and to make use of them as we think fit. During this period the concession can on no account be withdrawn. Sheikh Seker shall further be obliged, after the expiration of the first six years of the concession, to renew it for a further period of six years on the same conditions, if no other applicant is forthcoming. Should there be any other applicant, we are to be entitled to tender with him. The British Government have expressed the wish to be furnished with a complete and detailed statement of our claims for damages. The direct losses which we have sustained through the interruption of the work on Abu Musa are as follows :— (l.) Our advances to the mining company, and the value of the deposits on the island which have been either destroyed or removed, 13,106 M. (2.) The damage sustained through the 'Louise.' The value of this shipment can be proved, by comparison with the ' Stolzenfels' shipment, to have been, at the lowest estimate, 20 M. per 1,000 kilog. Of this we still have about 469 tons lying unused; we only very rarel}' succeed in selling small quantities of this, since the oxide has been rendered useless for nearly all industries by the presence of salt deposit and fine sand. In addition we should be compensated for storage expenses, the interest thereon, and insurance expenses. It is well known that the quality of the ' Louise ' shipment suffered from the oxide having been left lying unprotected for a period of fully six months, after the interruption of work, close to the shore to which it was being taken for shipment. Sandstorms and spray and exposure to the weather must greatly affect the quality of oxide, because, firstly, the colour became darker; and, secondly, the colouring properties of the oxide had considerably diminished owing to the action of salt, sand, and weather. The damage under this head can be proved to amount to 78,506 M. 31 pf. We endeavoured at the time to induce the sheikh to allow at least a few of our people to remain on the island in order to protect the oxide from deterioration by covering over with planks the quantity which had been carried to the shore for shipment; our request was, however, not granted. (3.) A lump sum to cover the cost of putting the mines again into a state of repair. We estimate that a sum of 30,000 M. will be necessary for this. We cannot furnish documentary evidence in regard to this amount. On our making enquiries of our local representative in regard to the amount necessary for the repair of the mines, the above sum was indicated to us as being absolutely necessary. (4.) A suitable compensation for the employes of the firm (two Europeans and ten natives) for the serious danger to which they were exposed by the firing on Abu Musa, M. (5.) Suitable compensation should also be paid in respect of the general damage sustained by our firm through the interruption of mining operations. The interruption of the industry and the resulting failure to deliver the oxide was a shock to our whole business, since our reputation suffered heavily, not only in the Persian Gulf but also in Europe; this involves a diminution of the vital power of our enterprise, and means an actual monetary loss. It would be better to reserve more detailed statements in regard to points 4 and 5 for verbal discussion. Should the British Government not be disposed to agree to a prolongation of the contract for periods of six or twelve years as the case may be, we would be prepared to renounce our claims in this respect on payment of suitable compensation. (Signed) ROBERT WONCKHAUS and G o. To the Foreign Office, Berlin.2 [This Docmnent is the Property of His Britanaic Majesty's Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [May 21.] CON FTDEXTIAL. skction 3. [17815J No. 1. Foreign Office to India Office. Sir, Foreign Office, May 21, 1913. WITH reference to your letter of the 21st ultimo and previous correspondence relative to the question of red oxide on Abu Musa Island, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith a translation of a note from the German Ambassador at this Court forwarding a translation of a letter from Messrs. Wonckhaus and Co., stating their objections to the proposals for a compromise contained in the note addressed to Count Metternich on the 6th December, 1911. Prince Lichnowsky also enquires when the direct negotiations between His Majesty's Government and the firm, the suggestion for which was made on the 9th January by the councillor ot the embassy in a conversation with Sir L. Mallett and accepted by the latter on behalf of His Majesty's Government in his note of the 17th January, should begin. As regards Messrs. Wonckhaus's first objection, I am to state that Sir E. Grey is disposed to admit that the considerations advanced are not without force and that, while he would he unwilling, for political reasons, to see a concession for the working of the mines granted to the firms themselves, he would consent to give to them, through the German Government, an assurance that, in the event of the grant of such a concession to a person or persons agreeable to His Majesty's Government, the latter will use their influence with the Sheikh of Sharga to ensure that he shall abstain from vexatious interference with the rights and operations of the con- cessionnaires. Sir E. Grey is further disposed to recognise a certain justice in the second objection in view of the fact that some time must necessarily elapse before the mines can again be profitably worked, and he would accordingly be willing to consent to some extension of the two years and eight months originally suggested. ' While admitting to the above extent the validity of the considerations advanced hy Messrs. Wonckhaus, Sir E. Grey must nevertheless regard their counter-proposal as wholly inacceptable. If nothing had occurred to interrupt the regular fulfilment of their contract, the firm would have had the right to buy a maximum of 5,000 tons of oxide a year for four years at 15s. 6d. a ton, whereas they now demand for themselves, in consideration of a nominal rent the entire profit on all the mines on the island for six years with the practical certainty of receiving it for six more. It is clear that, were this demand entertained, they would find themselves in a position infinitely more advantageous than that which they would have occupied under the original arrangement, and one to which the Sheikh of Sharga would without doubt strongly object. Sir E. Grey regards as equally inadmissible the claims for damages put forward in the statement which follows in Messrs, Wonckhaus's letter. The item numbered 1 deals in reality with two separate claims. The first of these, on account of advances to the mining company, could be made the subject of enquiries on the spot, though it is hard to believe that the sums advanced can have been very considerable. As for the second, the destruction of deposits referred to is, presumably, destruction by exposure to the weather, but Sir E. Grey does not know by whom any oxide has been removed except by Messrs. Wonckhaus themselves. Further infor mation would, therefore, have to be supplied by the firm with reference to this item. Item No. 2 of the claim appears to Sir E. Grey to be entirely unjustified. The oxide shipped by the 'Louise ' was allowed to leave by His Majesty's Government as an act of grace, in order to render easier the position of Messrs. Wonckhaus. Any profit whatever made from this shipment must therefore be regarded as pure gain for the firm, and His Majesty's Government cannot admit any claim based on the fact—if it be a fact—that the quality of the mineral is inferior to that of previous consignments, or that there has been a difficulty of disposing of it. It appears to Sir E. Grey that if the claim under No. 3 is valid at all, it concerns a question which should be settled between the sheikh and the mining company, and [2917 x—3]inm. that the claim that Messrs. Wonckhaus and Co. should not only receive the concession for working the mines, but also be paid the amount necessary to put the mines in order is a preposterous one. Items Nos. 4 and 5 appear entirely inadmissible. As regards the former, the employes of the firm were not injured, and, when fired on, were in a place where they had no business to be. They have, therefore, no right to complain of any fright or inconvenience which they may have suffered in consequence of an act done at their own risk. The latter claim appears to Sir E. Grey to be completely unsubstantial, and to belong to a category which His Majesty's Government have been unwilling to consider in the past. Sir E. Grey is disposed to think, in view of the last sentence of Messrs. Wonckhaus's letter, that the best solution of the whole question would be the payment of a lump sum to the firm which should take no account of separate and detailed claims. Before, however, making any proposal of this nature to the German Government, Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn the views of the Marquess of Crewe on the subject. I am, accordingly, to propose that Prince Lichnowsky's note should be referred to the consideration of His Majesty's consul-general at Bushire, through the Government of India, and that, in the meanwhile, his Excellency should be informed that while Messrs. Wonckhaus's communication will be carefully examined. His Majesty's Govern ment must say at once, without going into details for the present, that the counter proposal of the firm is entirely unreasonable and unsuitable even as a basis of discussion, as, to quote one example only, appears from the difference between their position under their original contract and that which they now to seek to obtain, and that if this attitude is seriously maintained, it appears unlikely that any useful purpose would be served at present by the proposed direct negotiations between His Majesty' Government and the firm. I am, &amp;c. LOUIS MALLET.&gt;7 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Goveminent.1 ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1. [June 4.] Section 14. India Office to Foreign Office.—(Received June 4.) India Office, June 3, 1913. IN reply to your letter of the 21st May on the subject of the Abu Musa oxide coucession, [ am directed to iuforiu you that the Marquess of Crewe concurs generally in the criticisms of the bee re tar}' of State lor foreign Affairs on the German proposals, but that he will await the views of the Government of India and the Resident in the i eisian ( « liU , to whom copies of your letter and its enclosures have been communicated, before discussing in detail the various points at issue. A copy of a telegram which his Lordship has addressed to the Government of India on the subject is enclosed herewith for your information. With reference to the last paragraph of your letter, Lord Crewe would suggest for Sn R. Grey s consideration that the terms of the proposed ad interim reply to the German Ambassador might be modified, with a view to rendering its tone somewhat less unconciliatory, and that it will sullice to inform his Excellency, after promising careful examination of Messrs. Wonckhaus's proposals, that 'His Majesty's Government, without going into details for the present, think it unlikely that the counter-proposal of the firm will be found to aiford a suitable basis of settlement, as, to quote one example only, appears from the difference between their position under the original contract and that which they now seek to obtain.' I have, &amp;c. T. W. HOLDERNESS. Enclosure in No. 1. Marquess of Crewe to the (lovrrirment of India, (Telegraphic.) P. ABU MUSA. I shall be glad to receive at the earliest date possible your views on the German proposals referred to in the papers forwarded by mail on the 16th and 23rd ultimo. (Uepeated to Resident, Persian Gulf.) June 3, 1913...— i~ 1^.7 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] - ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA, CONFIDENTIAL. [June lO.j Section 6. [25514] No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Prince TAchnowsky. &lt;1^ 7 Your Excellency, Foreign Office, June 10, 1913. I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note of the 5th April relative to the Abu Musa oxide concession. I have the honour to state in reply that the proposals of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Co., as formulated in the letter enclosed in your Excellency's note, will be carefully examined, but that His Majesty's Government, without going into details for the present, think it unlikely that the counter-proposal of the firm will be found to afford a suitable basis of settlement, as, to quote one example only, appears from the difference in their position under the original contract and that which they now seek to obtain. I have, &amp;c. E. GREY. [2950 k—6] - —. 'h \iz i Memorandum. The correspondence mentioned below is herewith transmitted to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with a view to avoiding delay in the event of the Foreign Department of the Government of India desiring to communicate with him on the subject. A copy of this memorandum and of the correspondence is also being communicated to that Department by to-day s mail. A ssistant Secretary, Political Department. INDIA OFFICE, 6 June 191 3. Persian Gulf: Abu Mnsa Oxide ' To Foreign Office, 3rd June.It is reqvmted that in any further communication i on this subject the nmler-mentioned letter ansi number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to— The Under Secretary of State for India, I'olitwal Department, India Office, 1935b London. S.W. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W, r r \ 1913* SrcC Sir, In r^j. ly to your of ist U&lt;*y t No. 17S15, on ibm snbjBCt of th&amp; Abu Musu oxid* concs&amp;sion, I um dtmet0d to inforri joa that ttanju*** of (7rm** concurs goMruUy in tha ori$i6im* of th* X+crvtary of State or or#*gn Affutru on th* j roj osaja, but thafi h&amp; will as^it the Vi#** if Vn* Gvu*nyi&amp;nb of India an*, the Jtesinmt in tn&amp; P+rsiim Gulf, to uihom coj i is of your l*tt&amp;r una i &amp;nvlobure* huoa omm oonami oat ad, b&amp;fore iiisau **tng in dtiuij th* ihinoiis j oint* at i&amp;sim. A co/:y of a t&amp;l&amp;gr&lt;m 'tiioh His Lorushij ha* uiidresstd to th&amp; roverymtmt of Inau on th&amp; subj not is znclozad h.&amp;r&amp;viih for your irtfonut*; ion* '^ith r&amp;f&amp;rm\Q4 to th* l^st jjaragr^/h of your Istt&amp;r, Lord trmm would si*g&gt;j*s ' for Sir a \ Grey's consideration that the t&amp;ms of the / rv/os &amp;u &lt;iii interim reply to the Oemtm Mbas&amp;dd&amp;r might b* modified, with a pi0&amp; to mndering its tone somewhat less unconoiliatory and that it will suffice to infom If is Vxeellenoy, after promising tarefbl anamination of Messrs* Wonak*- haus 's proposals, that 'His Majesty's Ocvemnmt, **itho\it going into Mtiil* for t e / resent, think it 'unlikely that the coxmter^propesal of the ftm will be foimd to afford a sui tab la basis of set.) Imnent, as, *to quote one lumyfJle only, apj ears from the difference 9 between their position tmaer the original contract *and that which they now seek to obtain* 1 ' I have the honour to be. Sir, Yo:ir mst obedient Servant, The Under Secretary oj State, FOREIGN OFFICE.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [June 30.] Section 12. [30016] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—(Eeceived June 30.) THE Under-Secretary of State for India presents his compliments to the Under- Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and forwards herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State, copy of a telegram from the Viceroy, dated the 28th Jnne, 1913, re Abu Musa. India Office, June 30, 1913. Enclosure in No. 1. Government of India to the Marquess of Creice. (Telegraphic.) P. June 28, 1913. THE following two telegrams—(A) and (B)—have been received from the Resident in the Persian Gulf with reference to your telegram of the 3rd instant regarding Abu Musa - (A.) ' It will be necessary to communicate with the vice-consul at Lingah or to visit the locality in question to enable me to reply in detail on all the questions referred to me ; but, short of such action, my views on the memorandum of the 10th March are, firstly, that, so far as the question of the mine is involved, the contention that it cannot be worked at a profit for some time has nothing in it; the difficulty of finding a market is the sole question. Secondly, there is no foundation for suggestion made in first clause that several years' preparations have been entirely thrown away. If there is oxide there is no reason why concessionnaires should not guarantee to supply so many tons per annum to anyone who will buy. The counter-proposals made appear to be impossible to accept. Thirdly, as regards the statement of claims:— u First Clause. —No destruction of deposits has occurred; one small shipment only has been taken away. However, it is no very great amount that is claimed. 'Second Clause. —I believe the suggestions as to results of exposure to be imaginary. All through the history of the concession the custom has been to dig in leisurely fashion in slack periods, and the stuff has habitually been allowed to lie for months—sometimes for years, before being shipped away. An expert authority on these matters tells me that effect of exposure to air, or dew, or spray is to form a hard crust on the surface, which effectually protects the interior of the heaps. It is quite unusual, I believe, to cover them with planks. I would suggest that this claim be disputed in toto. ' Third Clause. —The sum claimed for purpose here mentioned is preposterous amount. Nothing remains to be done save to clear away a little debris, the result of a slight landslip from under the digging. This claim might be put out of court by our offering ourselves to carry out the work. 'Fourth Clause. —No justification for payment of compensation exists in my opinion. 'Fifth Clause. —The claim made here has been much overstated; any estimate save an arbitrary one is difficult. But I think that it forms the most convenient head under which a lump sum in settlement of the case might be paid. ' (B.) ' Grant of concession to a foreigner would in any case be inconsistent with the advice which we gave the sheikhs authoritatively, with resultant creation of bad impression; this must, in my opinion, be set aside entirely. The most satisfactory [2950 cjcj— 12] fiilcourse, if possible, would be to buy out Wonckhaus entirely and let him compete in the open market. 'Tn connection with this point, it might be to Strick's considerable advantage to be participator in the Abu Musa concession for purpose of strengthening his position in respect of Hormuz, for (a) probably he would be able to use the Abu Musa stuff for mixing with the quality produced by Hormuz, thus selling nore of it, and (b) if the Hormuz arrangement fails to go right, he would have the Abu Musa article in reserve. He might be prepared, in view of these considerations, to pay down a lump sum (which would go towards compensation of Wonckhaus) in order to be our nominee, together with Esa-bin-Abdul Latif and (if we cannot keep him out of it) Hassan Samiyeh. In any case, I would recommend that Strick should be sounded on these lines. If the Foreign Office wish to keep out of the matter, perhaps Captain Wilson could be instructed to sound Strick as bearer of informal message from myself. If it proves impossible to buy Wonckhaus out entirely, it might be arranged that new companies should give him advantageous rates for a certain period. This would be instead of compensation, and they could afford it, since they have not to pay a heavy royalty as is case with the Hormuz product.' The views of the Resident have our general concurrence. The buying out of Wonckhaus entirely is, in our opinion, far the best solution, and the one which would most probably avoid further trouble.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Maj esty's Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [July 10.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 3. [31741] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office. —{Received July 10.) Sir, Whitehall, July 8, 1913. WITH reference to correspondence ending with my letter of the 3rd June, 1913, as to the Abu Musa oxide question, I am directed to invite attention to the Viceroy's telegram of the 28th ultimo on the subject, copy of which was communicated to your Department ou the 30th idem. The Marquess of Crewe concurs generally in the views expressed by the Govern ment of India and the Resident in the Persian Gulf, and he shares the conclusion at which they have arrived, and which, as would appear from the twelfth paragraph of your letter of the 21st May last, has the assent of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that the most satisfactory solution of the question would be the payment of a lump sum to Messrs. Wonckhaus and Co. in extinction of all their claims. His Lordship would suggest, however, that Sir P. Cox's detailed observations should be awaited before any further communication is made to the German Government. In the meanwhile, it would seem premature to open direct negotiations with the firm. I am, &amp;c. T. W. HOLDERNESS. 12985 /c—3]t. &gt; Memorandum, The correspondence mentioned heloiv is herewith transmitted to the Political Resident in the Persian Gvlf, with a view to avoiding delay in the event of the Foreign Department of the Government of India desiring to communicate with him on the sal A copy of this memorandum and of the correspondence is also being communicated to that Department by to-day s mail. MimUrtant Secretary, Political Department. INDIA OFFICE, 11th July I9l3. Per si an Gulf' Abu Musa Oxide. To Foreign Office, 8th JulyIt is requested that in any.f arther communication an this subject the under-mentioned letter and , number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. W r . P. 236? INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W, 8th July 2923* Sir, 'ith re fGrwica to oc Gndancv ending vith my latter of the 3ni Juna 2923, No. P. 2935b, as to the Abn Mnsa Oxide question, I am directed to invite attention to the Viceroy's te2eQran of the ? th ultimo on the subject, copy of which was cmnmicoted to your department on the 30th idem* The Marquess of ^rewe concurs generally in the views ej:j ressei by the Covemwenr oj Inuia ana the &amp;siJ~ ent in the Persian Oulf, and he shares the conclusion at which they have arrivei, and Mich, as wouli a// ear from the 12th paragraph c/ your letter No* 17825 of the 21st Muy last, has the assent of the Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, that the most satisfactory solution of the question would be the payment of a lumj sm to Messrs* Wonckhaus A Ho * in extinction of all their claims* Fis Lordship would suggest, he yever, th^t Sir P* Opx 's iietailed observations should be a aited before* any further communication is made to the fteman Government * In the meanwhile it would seem premature to open direct negotiations with the firm* I hov* the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient : ermnt. . * * The Under Secretary FOREIGN OFFICE.II — Confidential. a • a intfn Ko F..A. IK A copy of the undernientioned paper? is forwarded to the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf, for information. \X s ^ ~/U Date By order, etc., Deputy ^ecreti\ry tc the Government of India, Foreign Department, The Simla; SP July 1913 # Letter from Fcreien Office tc India Office, dated the 2lst ilay 1913. Letter from India Office to Foreign Office, dated the 3rd June 1913. \ Telegram to His Majesty's SecretaryState for India dated the 28th June 1913, &gt; ^ ( With one spare copy) #^3 (COPY) 17815/13. foreign Office, iky 2lst t 1913. Sir, with roferencQ to your latter of thQ 2lst ultimo and previous correspondence relative to the question of red oxide on A.bu Musa island, I an directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith a translation of a note from the German Ambassador at this Court forwarding a translation of a letter from Messrs, lilfonckhaus and Company stating their objec tions to the proposals for a compromise contained in the note addressed to Count Metternich on December 6th, 1911, Prince Lichnowsky also enquires when the direct negotia tions between His Majesty's Government and the firm, the sugges tion for which was made on January 9th by the Councillor of the Embassy in a convaraation with 3ir L, Mallat^ and accepted by the latter on behalf of His Liajesty's Government in his note of January 17th should begin. As regards Messrs. Ifibnckhaus' first objection I am to state bht Sir E, Grey is disposed to admit that the considera tions advanced are not without force and that, while he would be unwilling, for political reasons, to see a concession for # the working of the mines granted to the firm there elves, he wouldwould consent to £;ive to them, through the German Government, an assurance that, in the event of the grant of such a conces sion to a person or persons agreeable to Kis Majesty's Govern ment, the latter will use their influence with the Sheikh of Sharga to ensure that he shall abstain from vexatious interfer ence with the rights and operations of the concessionaires. V Sir Grey is further disposed to recognise a certain justice in the second objection in view of the fact that some time must necessarily elapse before the mines can again be profitably worked, and he would accordingly be willing to consent to some extension of the two years and eight months originally suggested. uhile admitting to the above extent the validity of the considerations advanced by Messrs. Rmckhaus, Sir E.Grey must nevertheless regard their counter-proposal as wholly inacceptable If nothing had occurred to interrupt the regular fulfil ment of their contract, the firm would have had the right to buy a maximum of Five thousand tons of oxide a year for four years at Fifteen shillings and six pence a ton, whereas they now demand for themselves in consideration of a nominal rent the entire profit on all the mines on the island for six years with the practical certainty of receiving it for six more. It is clear that, were this demand entertained they would find # thenselvesthemeelves in a position infinitely niore advantageous than that which they would have occupied under the original arrangement t and one to which the Sheikh of Sharga would without doubt strongly object c % Sir Grey regards as equally inadmissible the claims for damages put forward in the statement which follows in Messrs 0 Wonckhaus 1 letter. The item numbered (1) deals in reality with two separate claims. The first of these on account of advances to the mining company, could be made the subject of enquiries on the spot though it is hard to believe that the sums advanced can have been very considerable. As for the second, the destruction of deposits refened to is presumably destruction by exposure to the weather, but Sir 1. Grey does not know by whom any oxide has been removed except by Messrs.Vfonckhaus themselves. Farther information would therefore have to be supplied by the firm with reference to this item. Item 2 of the claim appears to Sir E.Grey to be entirely unjustified. The oxide shipped by the 'Louise' wa3 allowed to leave by His Majesty^ Government as an act of grace in order to render easier the position of Liessrs # hbnckhaus. Any profit what ever made from this shipment roust therefore be regarded as pure gain for the firm and His Majesty , s Government cannot admit any claimclaim based on the fact - if it be a fact - that the quality of the mineral is inferior to that of previous consignments or that there has been a difficulty of disposing of it # It appears to Sir S. Grey that if the claim under (3) is valid at all it concerns a question which ahculd be settled be tween the Sheikh and the mining coinpany t and that the claim that Messrs, 7«onckhaus and Company should not only receive the con cession for working the mines but also be paid the amount necessary to put the mines in order is a preposterous one. Items (4) and (5) appear entirely inadmissible, Ls regards the former, the employes of the firm were not injured and, when fired on, were in a place where they had no business to be, ihey 4 have therefore no right to complain of any fright or inconvenience which they may have suffered in consequence of an act done at their own risk, The latter claim appears to Sir E, Grey to be completely unsubstantial and to belong to a category which His Majesty^ Government have been unwilling to consider in the past. Sir E, Grey is disposed to think, in view of the last sentence of Messrs,Kbnckhaus* letter, that the best solution of the whole question would be the payinent of a lump sum to the firm which should take no account of separate and detailed claims, / Before however making any proposal of this nature to the German Government, Sir E, Grey would be glad to learn the vieuvsof the Marquess of Crewe on the subject. I am accordingly to propose that Prince Lichnowsky^ note should be referred to the consideration of Eis Majesty^s Consul General at Bushire through the Governnient of India and that, in the meanwhile. His Excellency should be informed that while Messrs. Wbnckhaus 1 communication will be carefully examined His Majesty's Government must say at once without going into details for the present that the counter-proposal of the firm is entirely unreasonable and unsuitable even as a basis of dis cussion as, to &lt;iuote one example only, appears from the difference between their position under their original contract and that which they now seek to obtain and that if this attitude is seriously maintained it appears unlikely that any useful purpose would be served at present by the proposed direct negotiations between His Majesty's Government and the firm, % I am, etc #f Sd/- W # Langley, The Under Secretary of State, India Office 0India Office, Whitehall. s Pol935 b London, S # W 0 3rd June 1913 # Sir, In reply to your letter of 2lst Lay, k) # 17ei5, on the subject of the Abu Liusa oxide concession, I am directed to inform you that the Marquess of Crev-B concurs generally in the criticisms of the Secretary of State for Foreign iffairs on the German proposals, but that he will await the views of the Government of India and the Resident in the Persian Gulf, to whom copies of your letter and its enclosures have been communicated, before discussing in detail the various points at issue. A copy of a telegram which His Lordship has addressed iL^^lto the Government of India on the subject is enclosed herewith ^ tid ( ^for your information. With reference to the last paragraph of your letter. Lord Crewe would suggest for Sir E # Grey f s consideration that the terms of the proposed ad interim reply to the German Ambassador might be modified, with a view to rendering its tone somewhat less unconciliatory and that it will suffice to inform His Excellency, after promising careful examination of Messrs. ^ 'flonckhaus' proposals, that H Eis Majesty's Government, without going into details for the present, think it unlikely that the countercoimter-proposal of the firm will be found to afford a suit able basis of settlement, as, to Guote one example only, appears from the difference between their position under the original contract and that which they now seek to obtain' 1 # I have, etc Sd/- T. Holderness4: Telegram -P. from - His Excellency the Viceroy, Simla, I'o - - Kis Kajesty's Secretary of State for India, London : Jfcr T, Dated the 28th June 1913 # Eeference your telegram dated the 3rd instant,Abu Masa. Ife have received the following telegranWfrom the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Pirst begins; To answer in detail x x x xx payment of lump sucu £iids 0 Second begins: i concession x x royalty to pay. Ends. life concur in Sir p. Cox t s views generally, Por the best solution in our opinion, would be to buy '.^nckhaus out altogether, lids course would be most likely to save trouble in the future.A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information, in continuation of the endorseiaent from the GoTermaent of India in the Poreifn Department No•1593-E,A. (Confidential),dated the 17th July 1913. Deputy Secretary to '^he Gorermaent of India, Foreign Department, Simla;. The August 1913. Letter from Sir Edward Grey to Prince Lichnowsky, dated the 10th June 1913. /T-stfi . ASIATIC TUHKI ^ Y AND ARABIA. CONFIDENTIAL. (June 10) Section 6. (25514) /'S »■ ■ M m NO. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Prince Lichnowsky. Poreien Office June 10, 1913. Your Excellency, I hare the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note of the 5th April relative to the Abu Kuea oxide conceseion, I have the honour to state in reply that the proposals of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Co., as formulated in the letter enclosed in Your Excellency's note, will be carefully examined, but that Ris Majesty* s Goverruaent, without going into details for the present, think it unlikely that the counter proposal of the firm will be found to afford a suitable basis of settlement as,to quote one example only, appears from the difference in their » position under the original contract and that which they now seekl 1&amp;- Asiatic Turkay and Arabia. CONFIDENTIAL. ( Jun e 10) Section 6. (25514) Ko.l. Sir Bdward Grey to Prince Lichno^rtiJcy. Foreign Office, June lO^QlS. Your Uxcellency, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note of the 5th April relative to the A'bu Wusa oxide concessicj I have the honour to state in reply that the proposals of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Co., as formulated in the letter enclosed in Your Excellency 1 • note, will be oar^fully examined, but that His Majesty*s Government, without going into details for the present, think it unlikely that tne counter - proposal of the firm will be found to afford a suitable basis of settlement, as, to quote one exan^le only, appears from the difference in their position under the original contract and that which they now seek to obtain. I have etc., Sd/- E. Grey .telegram.p. From Foraign To Resident. No 316 S. Dated and received 19.8.13. (6.50 pal.) With reference to your telefrram No 1093 dated 20th of June in regard to Abu Musa , it is requested that as early as possible a detailed report on all points may be forwarded. Foreign. telegram.^ From Birdwood. To Resident. Jask Radio. No 1439. Dated 20.8.13. (8.6. a.l.) Following from Foreign August 19th . Begins (Here were inserted the original figures of 316 S.) Ends. Foreign.CON FID E N T I A L No A copy of the undermentioned paper forwarded to the Political Resident in the iersian Gulf, for Information in continuation of the endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign Department No.1754-E .A., (Confidential), dated the 5th August 1913. 1 By order, etc., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign Department, Simla; /£ The -^August 1913 letter from India Office to Foreign Office Ko.P-2567, dated the 8th July 1S13.(Cb No. P-2567. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON. S. W. 8th July 1913. .« Sir, With reference to correspondence ending with ray letter of the 3rd June 1913, No.P-1935h, as to the Abu Musa Oxide question, I am directed to invite attention to the Viceroy's telegram of the 28th ultimo on the subject,copy of which was coranunicated to your Department on the 30th idem. The Marquess of Crewe concurs generally in the views expressed by the Government of India and the Resident in the Persian Gulf, and he shares the conclusion at which they have arrived, and which, as would appear from the 12th para graph of your letter No.17815 of the 21st May last, has the assent of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that the most satisfactory solution of the question would be the payment of a lump sum to Messrs. Wonckaus and Co., in extinction of all their claims. His Lordship would suggest, however, that Sir P.Cox's detailed observations sjiould be awaited before any further l IP o communication is made to the German Government. In the qaeanwhile it would seem premature to open direct negotiations with the firm. I have etc., Sd/- T. W. Holderness The Under Secretary of State, FOREIGN OFFICE.telegram No. 2798, dated Bushire, the 14th (received 22nd) September 1913 (Confidential). From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K .C .I.E., C.S .I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. With referenee to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department No. 316 S., dated l ( Jth August, I have the honour to submit some further observations on Messrs. Wonckhaus' objections and counter-proposals in connection with the settlement of the Abu Musa case. 2. I am generally familiar with the conditions existing on the island, but my present remarks are made after a special visit for the purpose and after discussion with the Residency Agent and Hassan Samaiyeh. The purport of the latter's statement to tiie Residency Agent and myself is also attached. It will be seen that I have little more to say than has already been repre sented in my telegrams of 19th June, and I need only reiterate the view that the most satisfactory course will be to give Messrs. Wonckhaus a lump sum which will buy him out completely and leave him, if he wishes to go on trading in oxide, to buy in the market on the same footing as others. l2.lo.is 0- Messrs. Wonckhaus* observations* Resident's comment. After our former experiences with Shaikh Seker, who claims the right of cancelling at any time, without indicating his reasons, concessions granted by him, we have no confi dence that a fresh concession from him would enable the mines to be worked steadily and on a technically sound basis. The parties concerned—the British Government, the Shaikh and our selves—are scarcely likely to be able to reach an agreement as to the persons to be considered ' suitable ^ We ourselves have the first claim to consideration in any concession. But who is to be the competent person to settle such differences arising in future ? And who is responsible for the damage incurred by (reason of) the person working tjie mines, for failure to carry out the contracts of delivery ? If we and the Shaikh are in accord as to the individuals to whom the fresh concession is to be given, Messrs. Wonckhaus may be confident that the mines would be worked satisfactorily. I gather that we should merely con template eliminating Abdulla bin Hassan from the syndicate on personal grounds and substituting a suitable British or British Indian merchant or firm on whom we could rely to work the concern properly. The assurance through the German Government con templated by the Foreign Office should fully meet the case. The parties concerned are the British Government and the Shaikh. All Messrs. Wonckhaus are properly con cerned about is to get the oxide that they want, f.o.b., on reasonably favour able terms. They are also, no doubt, anxious to see that the interests of their friend, Hassan Samaiyeh, do not go to the wall; but if the latter is admitted into the new concession they will have no cause for anxiety on this score. This is begging the question. We consider that Messrs. Wonckhaus have no claim except to be in a position to buy oxide. The Shaikh of Shargah under our advice. The concessionaires who would be British subjects and personally amen able to British jurisdiction.I (2) As regards the further pro posal that we should be reinstated in our contract rights for a period equal to that during which the contract was interrupted, i .e., for about two years and eight months, it must be observed that such a proposal does not take sufficient account of the present state of the oxide industry. The preparations extending over several years for carrying on this industry must be regarded as entirely lost and the work will for the most part have to be undertaken entiicly ixhg w« Two or three years will elapse before we reach approximately the point at which we were at the time of our forcible ejection from the island of Abu Musa. The further period allowed us would expire before we could bring large shipments on to the market. It should further be borne in mind that if we accept the present com promise we should not be in a posi~ tion to guarantee the regular delivery of the oxide to our customers. I submit that His Majesty's Foreign Office are mistaken in thinking that there is any justice in this second objec- tion. The paragraph is entirely misleading and inaccurate. Messrs. Wonckhaus' contract with the concessionaires was on an f. o. b. basis and they had nothing whatever to do with any ' preparations extend ing over several years'. The work had been going on and mined oxide slowly accumulated lor seven years before Messrs. ^Vonckhans came on the scene, and it is to be noted that no oxide has ever been mined for Wonckhaus. What he has shipped has been what was already mined before his contract. Hassan Samaiyeh says he would bo able to start mining oxide for ship ment in two months, and we could, if necessary, do it considerably quicker. There is no question of the work having to be undertaken entirely anew, unless it be desired to break fresh ground and start a new mine alto gether. As regards the existing mine: at the time the last - digging went on some non-oxide debris broke away from above the spot where the men were digging, and after personal inspection of the mine with expert companions, I can say that 50 coolies for _ one week at the outside would be required to clear the debris and put the mine in the state it was in before. There is nothing to prevent the new concessionaires from undertaking to supply so many tons per annum sup posing that geological examination indicates that the stuff is there. Hitherto the mine has been worked on a very small scale, and has never turned out or needed to turn out anything like 5,000 tons per annum. In the present cutting there is only room for about 70 men to work, and if a greater output were required the cutting would have to be enlarged in order to accommodate more workers. We, therefore, beg leave to submit the following counter-proposal Shaikh Seker to grant us, &amp;c. The direct losses which we have sustained through the interruption of the work on Abu Musa are as fol lows 1 (1) Our advances to the mining This appears to be altogether too fanciful to require comment. Hassan Samaiyeh states that he took (n Uur advances io ilc mimug ^ company, and yalue of the deposits Es. 2.000 (£ 133) as an advance from #on the island which have either been destroyed or removed—13,106 marks (£ 655). &gt;■ (2) The damage sustained through the ' Louise ^ * * It is well known that the quality of the ''Louise' shipment suffered from the oxide having been left lying unprotected for a period of fully six months after the interruption of work, close to the shore to which it was taken for shipment. (3) A lump sum to cover the cost of putting the mines again into a state of repair. We estimate that a sum of 30,000 marks will be necessary for this. (4) A suitable compensation for the employes of the firm (two Europeans and ten natives) for the serious danger to which they were exposed by the firing on Abu Musa. (5) Suitable compensation should also be paid in respect of the general damage sustained by our firm through the interruption of mining opera tions. Messrs. Wonckhaus in the first instance, and the sum went into his general oxide account with Wonckhaus. He says the account is not actually closed, but it is practically squared and there is nothing to speak of on one side or the other. Possibly he may be very slightly on the wrong side. Wonckhaus' contract being f. o. b. f he can have no claim for any oxide on the island. The answer to this claim is clearly that indicated in Foreign Office letter of 21st May to India Office. But even supposing that they were entitled to make any claim, the grounds on which they now base it will not bear the least scrutiny. Both at Hormuz and at Abu Musa it has been the custom for the respective conces sionaires always to keep a few coolies at the mining work, amassing stuff for subsequent export, when orders are received. The mineral often lies for months and even a year awaiting ship ment, but the fact is that tUe action of dew and ordinary atmospheric moisture is to form the surface of the oxide heap into a hard crust which preserves the contents from sun and weather. It is quite safe as long as it is left like this. It is in the actual handling on the sea shore, in shipping, that in windy weather you get an admixture of sand, just as you do in coal. Such a thins as covering the mineral with planks or protecting it in any way is unknown. To put the mine in the same state as it was before and at the time that Wonckhaus made his contract, w T ill consist merely of clearing a little debris which has crumbled away and fallen from above. We can do it for 600 rupees. Messrs. Wonckhaus* claim is lidiculous. Moreover, the mine does not concern him, but the oxide f. o. b. It would appear that 'Haji Ali Gel , mani, , ' Brown's companion on the occasion in question, is classed as a European. Claim can only be regarded as entirely inadmissible for the reasons stated in Foreign Office letter dated 21st May. If Messrs. Wonckhaus have any justifiable claim at all, it must, I thinkj be regarded as falling under this head.4 Statement made by Hassan Samaiyeh in answer to Residents enquiries made in the presence of the Residency Agent at Lingah and Khan Sahib Haji Abdur Rezak of the Bushiro Residency. Lingali, 27tli August 1913. Hassan Samaiyeh states under examination :— I took an advance of Rs. 2,000 from Messrs. 'Wonckhaus in the first ins tance. The item was debited against me in my general running account with them. I do not remember informing my partners at Shargah ot having taken this advance. I have shipped oxide for Messrs. Wonckhaus 3 or 4 times. Our account is not finally balanced up, but there is little or nothing outstanding on either side, there may possibly be something very inconsiderable due from me. I began excavating oxide the same year I got the concession and used to keep about 50 coolies working from time to time. I have shipped alto gether, I suppose, about 20,000 tons. I have not yet rendered any account of this to Esa bin Abdul Latif. My custom was to have a small gang of coolies permanently working and collecting oxide so as to have it ready for shipment on receipt of an order. It has never been my custom to put anything over the oxide as a protec tion, for this reason that the first night's dew is sufficient to form a hard crust over it which preserves the contents from all weather. I have kept it a year or more lying there without deterioration. My contract with Wonckhaus was merely to deliver oxide f. o. b. He had no concern with my preparations. I should be prepared to start regular excavation of oxide for shipment, as hitherto, in two months from time of warning. Hitherto I have never employed more than 60 or 70 men and the digging space is limited. If it were desired to employ more men the width of the excavated space must be increased. Before me. Lingah, i 27th August 1913, ) P. Z. Cox. Foreign Office Prew—Na. 419—24-9-13—laifcrlid) ilcutfdjco lonfulat. N2 333. jhiras, September 8 u Dear Sir Percy, nv 1 The old.Abu Musa affaire gives rise wing question which I beg to submit to you wit for your kind assistance. As I have not got here the flies I 8 au fait, but as far as I know our Governments an agreement by which shipments of red oxyde J are not to be carried out after a certain dat&lt; a letter from M? I&gt;S Wonckhaus &lt;5: Co. at Linga b' 1 requested me to get your acqiescence that the^ a quantity of about 1000 tons of oxyde lying i shipment on the beach, about 200 tons of It b« put into bags. The shipment is intended to In( I think, even if the date fixed inlaifcdid) jDcutfdjeg Sonfulat. N2 333 t/ZH 1 Ihiras, September 8l:h 1913. '- 'p. Dear Sir Percy, The old, Abu Musa affaire gives rise to the follo-^ 1 wing question which I beg to submit to you with the request for your kind assistance. As I have not got here the files I am not quite au fait, but as far as I know our Governments have come to ; an agreement by which shipments of red oxyde from Abu Musa ; are not to be carried out after a certsin date. I got now a letter from Wonckhaus &amp; Co. at Linga by which they requested me to get your acqiescence that they might ship ^ a quantity of about 1000 tons of oxyde lying ready for shipment on the beach, about 200 tons of It being already Dut into bags. The shipment is intended to India. I think, even if the date fixed in the agreement was already passed, it might perhaps be possible to induce ^ the other party to consent to the shipment without causing any prejudice. * | May Sir Percy Cox Kis Britannic Majesty's Consul General and Political Resident in the Persia] Gulf B u s h i r e .May I ask you to consider the question and if you think it suitable, to kindly induce the other party to give their consent and to fix all necessary condit ions? As I shall probably stay at Shiras for an other month I might ask you to send your reply here.22nd September e. 13 I have duly received your letter of the 8th in con nection with the Abu Musa question* The arrangement between our Oovemnente that all shipmenta were to cease by December 31st 1912 wao explicit, C K. and since the expiry of the period, all Hassan Sama^y^h'e V gear and belongings on Abu Musa were removed. Our Govern ments are now discussing the terms of an amicable compromise, by which it is hoped that the matter will soon be laid to rest. Meanwhile my instructions not permit me to en courage any further export by Messrs Wonckhaus or the Oon- cessionnaires and so unless I receive fresh instructions I am afraid I cannot move in the direction you request. When shall we have the pleasure of seeing you back here f I hope you have enjoyed your time at Shiraz. At Bushire we have had a mild hot weather on the whole, but nearly every body has had a spell of illness of one sort or another. With kind regards. sneleur W. Vassmuss, Imperial German Consul, Bushire.M V c TELEGRAM.P. From^ Secretary of State for India, To Viceroy • Repeated Resident. Ko Nil. Dotted 1.10.13. Received 2.10.13. (12.30 p.m.) With reference to your telegram dated June 28th in regard to the Island of Abu Musa. As the result of negotiations of an the acceptance of informal nature/a lump sum on the basis of the seconfl point of th .i British proposal for settlement has been agreed to by Wonckhaus/ (reference is invited to Sir Edward Grey's note dated 6th of December 1911) by which all rights are finally extinguished^/. It is proposed by the Foreign Office that the Board of Trade should in the first instance ex- -amine the islaim under this head which Wonckhaus has under^ .taken to submit. To this proposal I am giving my concurrence. T- w The mail of September 26th takes the papers in ths-1 connection.P5 laipiid) Deutfd )C0 lonfulot. MS 387. Ihiraz Ath October 1£13 fr^ XAV 1 I 'be^ to acknowledge with best thanks the receipt of your letter dated 22nd September by which you informed me that for the present,according to- the arrangement be tween our Governments, no shipments of oxyde must be done from Abu Musa. I hp.ve informed Mers. V'onckhaus &amp; Co. at Linga accordingly. I am spending a very agreable time at Shiraz and shall continue to stay here to the end of this month. I am glad you had a mild Eushire summer. Sir Perc?/ Cox His Britannic Majesty's Political Resident in the Persian Gulf atBushire . u;I**' to'I 1 [This Document is the Property of His Britaimic Majesty's Government] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [September 24.] CONFIDENTIAL. Sbction j [42511] No. 1. Foreign Office to India Office. Sir ' wtttt ^ ^ Foreign Office, September 24, 1913. 'A 7 A T. r ^ creilce t0 your letter of the Sth July, relative to the question of red oxide at Abu Musa, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to inform you that M 6 ^ ernian Charge d Affaires recently telephoned privately to this Office to say that r. iirowu, a representative of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Co., was inLondou and to suggest that advantage might be taken of this gentleman's presence to discuss the matter informally m the hope of arriving at a speedier settlement than could be reached Dy lurtner omcial correspondence. , suggestion haying been accepted, Herr von Kiihlmann and Mr. Brown called lortnwitn and were received by Mr. Norman and Mr. Malkin. 1 he vanons items of Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim for compensation on account of osses suilered through the interruption of their business were first summarilv examined, and the objections raised by Sir P. Cox mhis telegram of the 28th June (copy of which was enclosed m your letter of the 30th June) to certain of them were pointed out. i .! ^ 7* . Wlt hin the Marquess of Crewe's recollection that this claim was formulated y e nnn m accordance with point 1 of the proposal of His Majesty's Government 6th December^lOn 1 ) W m Sir E * . Gre y ,s note to the German Ambassador of the In the course of this examination it was ascertained that the text of the T/ )y Wonckhaus enclosed in the note of Prince Lichnowsky of . . (copy of which was enclosed in the letter from this Office of the 21st Mav) contained an error which had led to some misunderstanding. follows 1 - 0 —- lfteentl1 paragrapl1 of tlle memorandum runs, in the English translation, as the island^&amp;c advai lf eS t0 the minin g company and the value of the ' deposits ' on In this passage the word ' objects ' should be substituted for the word ' deposits n has aCdyW m^eby'the 1 ' 8 ' the disappearance of which complaint to HW* e nffi r0r i r 0S ? ) thT0U ? h 't 11 ® substitution in the original German text communicated ' GegenstSnde ' y Lichnowsky of the word ' Grundschichteu ' for the word i' ,y 01 ' 1 Ku,ll ' riann ev entually observed that, so long as the main question at ^^ (^t with under point 2 of the proposal for a compromise above referred to) as satisfactorily settled, the claim for compensation under point 1 was relatively f an ',i m wel1 be lar ? eI y re d u c e d and met by the payment of a lump sum without further enquiry as to the justice of its various component items. As regards the mam question, to which the discussion then passed, Mr. Brown at ^ th 1 MeSSrS - co ' ld uot carry on the business satisfXily ess they themselves were the actual concessioDnaires, as they could not trust the tit 1 k 8 / regl v 0 . nS t0 Ch00se for oxide of the quality required, to clear ^ f tt 6 shipment so as to guarantee punctual delivery. He admitted, how- evei that Hassan Samaiya was satisfactory from this point of view, an admission by the German^ firnf rVed incidentall y' that this individual is entirely controlled Herr von Kuhlmann and Mr. Brown were informed that there were, in the view of s S rious objections to the grant of the concession to ' a ?d Mr . Brown thereupon somewhat abruptly declared that in that case the firm would be glad to dissociate themselves from the whole business for a reasonable consideration. ? T0W11 J 11611 f orward orally the proposal embodied in the enclosed orandum, and was told that it would be discussed with your Department before [1863 1]iden, 2 another meeting, at which a representative of that Department would be asked to be present, took place. The proposal was accordingly discussed unofficially with Mr. Shuckburgh and it was decided that the suggested grant of a concession to Messrs. Wonckhaus and its sale by them would introduce an unnecessary complication into - the negotiations and that it would accordingly be preferable to pay to the firm a lump sum on the basis of point d of the British proposal for a compromise, which the firm should accept in full discharge of their claim under that head and in final extinction of any rights which they may have acquired in respect of Abu Musa oxide either under their contract with ~\ Hassan bamaiya or by any other transaction whatsoever. It was thought that a considerable part, at least, of the sum required might be derived from the proceeds of the sale of a new concession to a British firm. At a second meeting, held at this Office on the 12th instant, at which, in addition to the four persons who attended the first, Mr. Shuckburgh was present, this proposal was submitted to the Germans and at once accepted by them. They were then informed that the figures presented by Messrs. Wonckhaus in connection with their claim would probably have to be submitted to some impartial tribunal, to which Mr. Brown raised no objection. Mr. Brown undertook to furnish the necessary details within a week or two and I am to state that, when these aie received, Sir E. Grey would propose, subject to ' Lord Crew s concurrence, to submit them in the first instance to the Board of Trade The question of the tribunal to which the decision of the amount to be paid is to be' referred, should that course prove necessary, would appear to be one which cau conveniently be considered later. I am, &amp;c. EYRE A. CROWE. Enclosure in No. 1. Statement made Mr. Brown.—{Communicated by German Charne d'Aifaires September 16, 1913.) ; W E propose to settle the case as follows :— 1. That our direct losses be refunded to us. ihese have been stated in our last memorandum. Where we have not mentioned the sum, we suggest to appoint arbitrators both parties agreeing to abide by their decision. 2. That the Sheikh will ^rant us a new concession for a period of six years on the terms of the original one. AVe, on the one hand, agree to sell through His Majesty's Government to the Sheikh or any other suitable person or persons, and you, on the other, agroe to buy this concession from us at the price which we bought in our original contract, viz. 155. Quantity, 6,000 tons per annum. This, in our opinion, is an exceedingly fair proposal. When the Sheikh withdrew the concession, he gave as the principal reason that we were getting the oxide too cheap. If we sell to him at this admittedly cheap price of 15s., he ought to be doino- a good business. Whether the Sheikh is wealthy enough to pay the sum of Z. we do not know but the deposits of oxide in the island being practically unlimited, we presume that the mines would provide ample security for a loan, that the Sheikh might make on the strength of same.' T o. 2J - v .A. i. oopy o:: Vne uiiderr'nntio ted teleFrain is ^orwnrc^ed to the olitical Resident in the Persian Cul.t, ±ot information, in continuatiori of the endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign Department M0.1948-K .A. (Confidential), dated the 20th August 1913. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign Department, Simla ; The Oc October 1913. Telegram from His Majesty's Secretary of State for India dated 1st October 1913. vr ith 1 spare cony.Telegram - P. From - Kis I/ajesty's Secretary o.t State for India, London. To --- i.ic Excellency the Viceroy (F'oreign Department), (Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf). Dated the 1st (received 2nd ) October 1913. AU Musa Island. Your telegram of the 28th June. Ac a result of informal negotiations ''onckhaus has agreed to accept in final extinction of all rights a lump sum on the basis of point two of British proposal ior compromise (vide, note by Sir E. Grey of December 6th 1911). It is proposed by Foreign Office that claim under this head which Wonckhaus has undertaken to put -orvc.rd should in the first instance be referred for examination to Board of frode, I am expressing ny concurrence. Papers sent to India by nail of last week.Telegram - P * r i V r Prom - His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, To His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign Department). (Repeated to Political Resident In the Persian Gulf). Dated the let (received 2nd ) October 1913. Aby Musa Island. Your telegram of the 28th June. As a result of Informal negotiations Wonckhaus has agreed to accept In final extinction of all rights a lump sum on the basis of point two of British proposal for compromise ( vide note by Sir E. Grey of December 6th 1911). It Is proposed by Foreign Office that claim under this head which Wonckhaus has undertaken to put forward should In the first Instance be referred for examination to Board of Trade. I am expressing my concurrence. Papers sent to India by mail of last reek. LondonBombay, dated 23-9-1913. Dear Sir, Bhader bin Mhmd Amin I wish to so that I want to be contractor of red thing yeroo of Bhoomoosa for 3-4 years ago so I wish that please you will write about its matter and will send its sample and will write its price I hope that you will write about its all matter and I have written a letter to Mr.Husoon Bhoomoosa about this on subject but still did not come answer to it. I think and hope that you will give me answer and will send to its sample. As to you will write i + s answer of pharsee langway. your faith fully Gordhandas Valjee our address Bombay Burcout Vergadi Mr.Harsandass Nathu^ house ft il h cu t* &lt;fy &lt;rt L ft it i n nztiytI f I0^ (42oll/l3) exanlned and the objections ralged by 8lr ». Cox In his telesran of June £?th (copy cf '&lt;fl:lc^ v&amp;c sncloeed In your letter cf June rsoth) to certain of thr- wera pointdct out. It will oe vvltfcln the Marquess of Creve's recol lection that t,his clalTT! was forTil&amp;ted by tho flm In accordance with point 1 of the proposal of 'Is alos- ty* s Government for a co^romlae put forward In Sir E. Grey's note to the German Arabassador of December 6th 1911. In the course of this examination It was ascer tained that, the text of the memorandum bj- ss are. v nckhaus enclosed In the note of Prince Licrnowsky of April 9th (cop;/ of • hich was enclosed In the letter from this Office of ' ay 2lBt) contiiinad an error which haa led to some rnitamderstsndinf;:- The 15th paragraph cf the ^eTorandu^ T' n . , in the English trinslation as follows:- '(l) Our advaTiCefe to the ' inlnp; Hompan^ anJ the Vii.XU6 Oi thS (ScpOblts on th8 iL:lfcinc&gt;, • •••••(I251l/l3) In thib paesagc tl-3 word obi sets- should be sub- etitutad for the word and the reference is to the lTpl 3 r 'entB reapsctinr * he d lt:a^,j9ara ,n r s of hlch Th3 error &amp;ro68 through th&lt;3 subBtltutlon in ori ginal f/emaTi text corrrcimlcatsd to this Office fc;/ Prlncs Mchnori8'&lt;y of the word nrundschlchtar 'or the word 'rPfrstfci ^. Hsrr von KHhl^ann event'iall,, obuerve^ ' hat so lonir as ths Tiiiin (iuestlon at I ssub 'deslt h 'mder point 2of tla proposal for a coiprc nlse above refer. red to) ■■ satisfactorily settled, the del. f^r conpensatlon under poln' 1 flas relatively i'''important an-5 mlglit «ell bs lai'Kal,. redrcad unci met by tfce pay neat of a lu^ap aura without further enquiry as to the Uu-tiCo of its various, coij, on ant Ite^.e. An regards the t!iair question, to which the dis cussion then passed, Mr. Brown at first contended that Ve^re.. Wnclchaus could not carry on the business sxt'Sfactor lly unlesa they thenaelv-rs were the actual co' plaint has already beer, made by the fir-. concessiormair^s(4?, 511/13) The proposal was accordingly dlscuusad unofficially with Ffr. Shuc^cburgl. it was decided that tf?. sug gested grant of a concesblor to MessrB, WCnc'rhaue and its «ale by the^ would introduce an unnecessary ccn- plicatior into the nagotiutions and that it would ac cordingly preferable to pa&gt;' to ths firm a sum on the basis of point 2of thy B:Mtioh yrooo. 1 f - a compromise, which the firs should accept in full dis- ch rge of th»3ir clai^ under that head, and in final extinction of any rl^fits which they may have crqi ^ired in aspect of Abu ^isa oxide either under thei^ con tract vjth F&amp;ssnri Pnnaiya or by any oth#T tr^taction whatsoever. It was thought that a conBiderable part at least of the sum required mi^ht be derived fro~ the proceeds of the sale of a na . r concession to a British firm. At a second meeting held at thib Office or- the 12th instant at which, in addition to the four percore who attended the first, ? 'r. Shuckburrh was present, this proposal was submitted to the Oermans and at once accepted(4t91l/lS) accepted t&gt;y them. They wars then Informed :hat the figures presentod by IteMft# Wnckj:auB in connexlor with their clnlm would proDttbi^ htve to be submitt^ci bo sjome impart 1^1 tribunal, to which r • F^ovn iciisad no objection. ■fr. Srovn undertook 'uo furnish the necessary de tails within a wee.K or two and I am to state %hat ,when thyBS u&gt;*t r'iC3ived, 3i r . Gi»y would pvt^pote, subject to -tord Hre e'b concurrence, to submit th^n in tha first instance to the WoffM of Traan. $ The ivsbtior. of the tribunal to v/Mci. the deci sion of the amount to bo p^dd it to be referred, should that course provtj necessary, -oull appear to be one which cioi conveniently ba considered later. I a'n, Sir, Your mo^t obedient, himnle Servant, feigned) Eyre A tQNm*.|v7 Statement made by Mr. Brovm. We propose to settle the case as follows;- (1) That our direct losses be refunded to us. These have been stated In our last Memorandum. Where we have not mentioned the sum, we suggest to appoint Arbitrators, both parties agreeing to abide by their decision. (2) That the Sheikh will grant us a new concession for a period of 6 yeara on the terms of the original one. We on the one hand agree to Bell through HI b Majesty's Government to the Sheikh or any other suit able person or persons, and you on the other, agree to buy this concession from us at the price which we bought in our original Contract viz. 15 b . Quantity 6,000 tons per annum. This in our opinion is an exceedingly fair pro posal. When the Sheikh withdrew the concession, he gave as the principal reason that we were getting the Oxide too cheap. If we resell to him at this admittedly cheap price of 15s. he ought to be doing a good business.Bane. Whether the Sheikh is wealthy enough to pay the sum of £ we do not know, hut the depoBlts of Oxide In the iBland helng practically unlimited, we preBume that the mlneB would provide ample security for a loan, that the Sheikh might make on the strength of(431: 7/U). of caritwnafiitlon to tw pala to tho flnn. The proposal at present undor dieoisslon is thut a sura should be paid to the finn as corapanbatlon for the loss suffered by the: throu ti the Interruption of their business in consequenc# of the cancellation of their contract by the Sheikh of Sharga and 31r B. drey presumes that such conponsation wo'ila amount to a sutsi leas than the firm mi?ht have hoped to rat^ko if their contracts hud bean carried through in the most favourable condition^ an&lt; vithout the s.'.irht^et hitcfi. It is however on this aseunption that the firm, in the present cornunication, would appear to b^se thoir claim ;aid it is therefore, as it seams to Si' E. Rrey, necessury eventually to re for tht* iuestion of the a o'int of compenbation actually due to son» Independent tribunal possessinp: the business oxperience necessary to fix it. I sib accardinsi^ to btate that, s bjfict to any observationu which the KarqutM of CJrewe mny wish to133 Iran si at ion (4313/) £ .. . u d A K U U in continuation oi ouo convcisatiou lie:, t. ino.ij lirovm, of the fin i of Robert »#onclciiauti and ^ocipany, iiaciourgi had at the Korei^i Office on uha subject of the Abu-^usa CASe, tl 16 fir'*; nave Guo-jiiud uo viiuu Oi.a folio-. , parti culars which should be ta^en as a oasis ior ©otii.iatin. 1 , the compensation for the canceliation ox v^ho cv&gt;,.ti;vCt. i'liG oontrrct rice for Lno to oi 20 c'.ift. ibu- s •d • rasa amounted to lb/6, the freight alter deduct ion wi one s .d. usual 5% commission 14/5, marine insurance urf ., discharging 9d ., the usual discount on sale, recri ming a sale price of 65/-, 6^c. A ^on therefore cost t ie lim :5J A/ landed at Harnourg. The fin: calculated Uie average sale price as 65/-. , trie avera,';e net profit thus working 8 f * out at 35/3 per ton. The price of 15/6 'ia fixed by the agreement of the firm of ..oncknaus with the dniii ; company and a cony of this agreement is presui ably in the )OBaossion of the Foreif^ Office. Che fim can produce vouchors showinr the froir; t rates actually paid . Insui'tuico and dischargingqf Ho. dasH of 1913. British Residency and Consulate-General. !3uahlro,£j ! Octobor 101^ # To Hi3 ! ajo^ty'a Vica-Conaul, L i n g e h« Gir, ?/itli ruforonce to your letter No # 369 f dated 10th Octobor 1915, enoloalng a letter to Khan Bahadur Agha Dadr from Gordliandas Valjee in regard to Abu l^UBa oxide, I have the honour to requeut that you will direct Khan . Bahadur A^^ha Badr oo reply that the Abu ituna oxide trade la at present under auapenoion and that in coneequence ho ia unable to dibouaa the question at present. 2. The original of the letter in question is returned herewith# I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Section 2. Foveicjn Office to Indici Office. o- Foreign Office, September 30, 1913. lr ' WITH reference to the letter from this Office of the 24th instant relative to the question of red oxide on the Island of Abu Musa, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith, translation of a communication from the German EmWy!* enclosing particulars supplied by Mr. Brown which it is suggested, should bo taken as a basis for estimating the compensation to be paid to the linn of Messis. Robert Wonckhaus and Co. on account of the cancellation of their contract While it is in Sir E. Grey's opinion, desirable that the Board of J rade should be asked to check,'so far as possible, the accuracy of the figures quoted in this paper, he thinks it inadvisable for His Majesty's Government to endeavour to settle on tins basis direct with the German Government the amount of compensation to lie paid to the firm ^ ^ resent xin der discussion is that a sum should be paid to the firm as compensation for the loss suffered by them through the mterruption of their business in consequence of the cancellation of their contract by the bheikh of Sharga, and Sir E. Grey presumes that such compensation would amount to a sum less than the firm might have hoped to make if their contracts had been carried through m t ic most favourable conditions, and without the slightest hitch. It is, however, on 111s assumption that the firm, in the present communication, would appear to base then claim and it is therefore, as it seems to Sir E. Grey, necessary eventually to refer the question of the amount of compensation actually due to some independent tribunal •nossessinor the business experience necessary to fix it. _ , • , tu t I am accordingly to state that, subject to any observations which the Marquess of Crewe may wish to offer. Sir E. Grey is disposed to submit the figures supplied by the firm to the examination of the Board of Trade, and to ask them at the same time for their advice as to the tribunal to which the fixation of the amount ol compensation due should be referred. J am, (Xc. EYRE A. CROWE. • German Embassy, September 18. 1913. [1863 gg—2] * \ r .i m? [This Docmnent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Govemment.] ASIATIC TU RKEY AND ARABIA. [October 3.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [44995] N 0 - 1 - Tndia Office to Foreign Office.—{Received October 3.) g^ r India Office f October 2, 1913. I x\M directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 24th September, 1913 reporting the result of the recent informal negotiations with the representative of Messrs. R. Wonckhaus and Company in regard to the question of red oxide on the island of Abu Musa. . ^ Atr 11. u 'L'he Marquess of Crewe learns with satisfaction that Messrs. \\ onckhaus nave ao-reed to a settlement of this troublesome question on the lines advocated m Str T. Holderness's letter of the 8th July last, viz., the payment to the firm ot a lump sum in extinction of any rights which they may have acquired. It remains only to iix the precise amount to be paid, and on this point his Lordship understands that a detailed claim is likely to be received from Messrs. Wonckhaus during the next lew weeks. He concurs in the proposal of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that the claim, when received, should be referred in the first instance to the Board ot Irade for examination and report. _ . . , , t ^ ■ r The question of the division as between British and Indian revenues ot any sum that may ultimately be paid to Messrs. Wonckhaus will be considered at a later date. I am, &amp;c. LIONEL ABRAHAMS.MmMr — ■» ♦ - . Confident i'xl, Ng» ^ 4 ^ IT^A b ■fc A f-ES/b^V P HtEIPT *»• 20.N0V.1II 3 A co^y of tnu undarmentionwd papers ib forwarded to tnc Poliblca.1 Resident in tJae Parsi*n Gulf, for information. in continuation of the andor&amp;eiuent frora the Government of India in trie ^oreipn 'department, No. 2336-1^.A. (Confidential) dated the Cth October 1513. 'By order, stc,, iftvll' Itv deputy Secretary to the Government of India. Tor^i-gn Department, Simla \ fir The/^/'. November Letter from 'Foreign Office to India Office, dated the l^ith September 191^, witn enclosure. Letter from India Office to To reign Office, No. 4057, dated the 9th OctolDer 1913. (With i spare copy)[This Docmneiit is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Govemment.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABU. [September 24.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. / [42511] No. 1. Foreign Office to India Office, Sir, Foreign Office, September 24, 1913. WITH reference to your letter of the 8th July, relative to the question of red oxide at Abu Musa, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to inform you that the German Charge d'Affaires recently telephoned privately to this Office to say that Mr, BrowD, a representative of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Co., was in London, and to suggest that advantage might be taken of this gentleman's presence to discuss the matter informally in the hope of arriving at a speedier settlement than could be reached by further official correspondence. This suggestion having been accepted, Herr von Kiihlmann and Mr. Brown called forthwith and were received by Mr. Norman and Mr. Malkin. The various items of Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim for compensation on account of losses suffered through the interruption of their business were first summarily examined, and the objections raised by Sir P. Cox in his telegram of the 28th June (copy of which was enclosed in your letter of the 30th June) to certain of them were pointed out. (It will be within the Marquess of Crewe's recollection that this claim was formulated by the firm in accordance with point 1 of the proposal of His Majesty's Government for a compromise put forward in Sir E. Grey's note to the German Ambassador of the 6th December, 1911.) * In the course of this examination it was ascertained that the text of the memorandum by Messrs. Wonckhaus enclosed in the note of Prince Lichnowsky of the 5th April (copy of which was enclosed in the letter from this Office of the 21st May) contained an error which had led to some misunderstanding. The fifteenth paragraph of the memorandum runs, in the English translation, as follows:— '1. Our advances to the mining company and the value of the 'deposits ' on the island, &amp;c. . . In this passage the word ' objects ' should be substituted for the word ' deposits,' and the reference is to the implements, respecting the disappearance of which complaint has already been made by the firm. The error arose through the substitution in the original German text communicated to this Office by Prince Lichnowsky of the word ' Grundschichten' for the word ' Gegenstande.' Herr von Kiihlmann eventually observed that, so long as the main question at issue (dealt with under point 2 of the proposal for a compromise above referred to) was satisfactorily settled, the claim for compensation under point 1 was relatively unimportant, and might well be largely reduced and met by the payment of a lump sum without further enquiry as to the justice of its various component items. As regards the main question, to which the discussion then passed, Mr. Brown at first contended that Messrs. Wonckhaus could not carry on the business satisfactorily unless they themselves were the actual concessionnaires, as they could not trust the natives of those regions to choose for shipment oxide of the quality required, to clear the mineral before shipment so as to guarantee punctual delivery. He admitted, how ever, that Hassan Samaiya was satisfactory from this point of view, an admission which shows, it may be observed incidentally, that this individual is entirely controlled by the German firm. Herr von Iviihlmann and Mr. Brown were informed that there were, in the view of His Majesty's Government, serious objections to the grant of the concession to Messrs. W T onckhaus, and Mr. Brown thereupon somewhat abruptly declared that in that case the firm would be glad to dissociate themselves from the whole business for a reasonable consideration. Mr. Brown then put forward orally the proposal embodied in the enclosed memorandum, and was told that it would be discussed with your Department before [1863 aa— 1]another meeting, at which a representative of that Department would be asked to be present, took place. The proposal was accordingly discussed unofficially with Mr. Shuckburgh, and it was decided that the suggested grant of a concession to Messrs. Wunckhaus and its sale by them would introduce an unnecessary complication into the negotiations, and that it would accordingly be preferable to pay to the firm a lump sum on the basis of point 2 of the British proposal for a compromise, which the firm should accept in full discharge of their claim under that head and in final extinction of any rights which they may have acquired in respect of Abu Musa oxide either under their contract with Hassan Samaiya or by any other transaction whatsoever. It was thought that a considerable part, at least, of the sum required might be derived from the proceeds of the sale of a new concession to a British firm. At a second meeting, held at this Office on the 12th instant, at which, in addition to the four persons who attended the first, Mr. Shuckburgh was present, this proposal was submitted to the Germans and at once accepted by them. They were then informed that the figures presented by Messrs. Wonckhaus in connection with their claim would probably have to be submitted to some impartial tribunal, to which Mr. Brown raised no objection. Mr. Brown undertook to furnish the necessary details within a week or two, and I am to state that, when these are received, Sir E. Grey would propose, subject to Lord Crew's concurrence, to submit them in the first instance to the Board of Trade. The question of the tribunal to which the decision of the amount to be paid is to be referred, should that course prove necessary, would appear to be one which can conveniently be considered later. I am, &amp;c. EYRE A. CROWE. Enclosure in No. 1. Statement made hy Mr. Brown.—{Communicated by German Charge d'Affaires, September 16, 1913.) WE propose to settle the case as follows :— 1. That our direct losses be refunded to us. These have been stated in our last memorandum. Where we have not mentioned the sum, Ave suggest to appoint arbitrators, both parties agreeing to abide by their decision. 2. That the Sheikh will grant us a new concession for a period of six years on the terms of the original one. We, on the one hand, agree to sell through His Majesty's Government to the Sheikh or any other suitable person or persons, and you, on the other, agree to buy this concession from us at the price which we bought in our original contract, viz. 15^. Quantity, 6,000 tons per annum. This, in our opinion, is an exceedingly fair proposal. When the Sheikh withdrew the concession, he gave as the principal reason that we were getting the oxide too cheap. If we sell to him at this admittedly cheap price of 155., he ought to be doing a good business. Whether the Sheikh is wealthy enough to pay the sum of I. we do not know, but the deposits of oxide in the island being practically unlimited, we presume that the mines would provide ample security for a loan, that the Sheikh might make on the strength of same.IncU'a Office to jtoruign Offica No. P-iOoV, Uatud the 9tb October With reference tc your letter of the ^Oth September 191^, ^o. 43137, iss to the A'fcu Miisa Oxide question, I am airected to inform you that the Marquess of Cre-.*e concurs generally in the vie;vs expressed 'by the Secretary of State for .Foreign Affairs regarding Uassrs* Wonciavaus 1 ^ claims to compensation, and that ud i^rees to the prcpobxi to submit the figures su^^liuu t-ae fxrm to the e^Amxnation of tne Board of Ti iac and to bvlicit Ciic iavice of tnat Department as to the tribur-.u. lo vvixiun the fixation of the amount of compensation due should 'be referred*!&gt; 0 w J a j . ' TELEGRAM.P. From Foreign • To Resident • No 526 S. Dated 24,11.13. Received 25,11.13, (7,00 a,^,) Oxide on iibu Mijsa,y It is requested that the original statemeat nade by Hassan Samaiyah dated August 2?th ray I be forw .rded v/ithout- delay to the India Offi^oe , Your letter Wo 2^98 dated September 14th prave cover to a copy of the document in question. Foraign,|33 42i37/i3. ^oroi^n Offics, SepLtJ^it^r SOti^, 1913. Sir:- W igai r«ldrtincc to txuj ^ettur from txiib ofiico of txia 24th. inbtint r&lt;iJL*tiva to question oT rau oxiao Cix tixo lo±jJiii W r ALu luba.! I Jkm ui-xcOtwa SoC4rdLaX\/ Sir £d*aru. (fX^y to to you ti&lt;tr**iith trinexitxon of % conLnuni- cation frcm tlia Gera-in Xabaaey, enclosing ^^rticul'-irs, supplied 'by Mr. Prc/m, wUicii, it ib augg^bted, should 'be t'^en is x b'Abis for esti^i^ting tne coifl^ttnaiitxon to 'be io tan firm of Messrs. Robert Woncicnaus and Coiipany on tccount of the cancellation of their contract. Wiile it is, in ^ir !?• Grey's opinion, desirable that the ?oaru of Trads should 1 3 asked to check, so fAr as possible, the accuracy of tite figures ^uotedin this paper ne thinks it in^dvibable for TTis Majesty's Govern^ient to endeavour to settle on this basis, direct with the German Go^ernmsnt, the amount of compensation to be paid to the f irnu The propus-tx at present unaer discussion io tuat a sum s.iouxa be paid to txio firm as compensation for ti.ic aosb suffcrea by t^em whxough the Interruption of lue+r bu&amp;mesb in consequence ox' tuc canc^ixation of tuiii contract by the SheiiCh of S^*rga and Sir E. Gr*?^ presumes tii-it sucii couipons xtion would aiflOunt to a £&gt;um le^b t-naui tho firm m^ght h-A've hoped to if their contracts had been earned through in the nost favourable condition *nd without the slightest hitch. It is however on this assumption that the firm, in the present communication, vsrould appear to base their claim and it is therefore, as it seems to Sir 7, Grey, necessary eventually to refer the Ciuestion of the amount of compensation actually due to some independent tribunalmii /&lt;S P. J947. India. Office, WxiiteJa.%il, London, 3.W. iincL Oc^ot^r xvxc. Sir iii&gt;t pt .a u L I im directed to 'ic.cncwledgu tJrj No, 4&lt;ioli dated the 24 th September i^i^, roportxng the res ait of the recent informal negotiations with the representative of Messrs. R. Woiicldaaue &amp; Company in regard to the question of red oxide on the island of Vbu Musa. Tiie Ifarques® of Crewe learns with satisfaction that Messrs. WonclihauE hav? agreed to a settlement of this troublesome ^Tiestion on th^ lihes advocateu. in Sir T. Hoidc^rua^Js , s letter of the Bth July last, No. vis. the payment to the firm of a lump sum in extinction of any rights v/hich tney may iiave acquired. It remains only to fix. tiiQ precise amount to 'be paid; and on thiu point His Lordii-uip understands th-it ^ detailed c^iim is xxHely to 'be received from Messrs, Woncidaaus during tx^e next few weexs. He concurs in the proposax 01 tne Secitita.rj of State for Foreijn Affairs that the claxm, waen received, snouxa be referred in the first instance oo tjrie Boara of Trade for % examination and report. The iuestion of the division as 'between British and Indian revenues of any sum that may ultimately 'be paid to Messrs. Wonclchaus will 'be considered at a l^ter date. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- Lionel -Vbraijams. Under Secretary of State, foreign Ol'fioa.[This Doccmcnt is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Governmpnf ] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [September 20.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [43137] No. 1. Memorandum communicated hy German Embassy, September 20. (Translation.) -V- IN continuation of the conversation which Mr. Thomas Brown, of the firm of Robert Wonckhaus and Co., Hamburg, had at the Foreign Office on the subject of the ' Abn Musa ' case, the firm have supplied me with the following particulars, which should be taken as a basis for estimating the compensation for the cancellation of the contract:— The contract price for the ton of 20 cwt., f.o.b. 'Abu Musa,' amounted to 15s. 6^., the freight, after deduction of the usual 5 per cent, commission, 145. 3d., marine insurance ti^d., discharging 9d. r the usual discount on sale, reckoning a sale price of G5s., (S^d. A ton, therefore, cost the firm 31 s. Sd. landed at Hamburg. The firm calculated the average sale price as G5s., the average net profit thus working out at 33s. od. per ton. The price of 15s. i )d. is fixed by the agreement of the firm of Wonckhaus with the mining company, and a copy of this agreement is presumably in the possession of the Foreign Office. The firm can produce vouchers showing the freight rates actually paid. Insurance and discharging are not supported by special ^ vouchers, but the charges are in conformity with the usual rates. As to the prices actually realised for the oxide shipped on the steamship Stolzenfels,' particulars are given in the annexed extract from the books of the firm.* As may be seen from these figures, the calculation of an average sale price of 65s. is a low estimate, for the prices realised relate to a trial shipment of 700 tons; if the continuance of the operations had allowed contracts extending over a long period to be entered into, the firm would, they declare, have realised still better prices than in the case of the first shipment. I . The Imperial Embassy would be glad to be informed up till what date the representative of the firm of Wonckhaus is to submit his documentary evidence to a mercantile expert here in London, and what further points, outside the submission of this evidence, still require to be explained and proved by the firm. German Embassy, London, September 18, 1913. [1863 m—1] * Not printed.L '7, j( t I a [This Docmnent is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's (jovenun^j ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [October 10.] £ Section 1. No. J. India Office to Foreign Office.—-(Received October 10.) ^' 1 ' wrrn e ^ n , India Office, 0etcher 9, 1913. WiiJi reference t) your letter of the 30tli September, 1913, as to the Abu Musa oxide question, I am directed to inform you that the Marquess of Crewe concurs generally in the views expressed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs regarding* .Messrs. Wonckhaus s claims to compensation, and that he agrees to the proposal to submit the figures supplied by the firm to the examination of the Board of Trade and to solicit the advice of that Department as to the tribunal to which the fixation of the amount ot compensation due should be referred. I am, &amp;c. LIONEL ABRAHAMS. [1908 k- •t r (Lit? [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [OCIOIkt ,)!.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. [47043] Na L Foveicjn Office to 13oavd of f vade. Foreign Office, October 31, 1913. WITH reference to the previous correspondence regarding the claim of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Co. to compensation in connection with the red oxide indus ry in the island of Abn Mnsa, of which copies have been communicated periodically TOur Department, t am directed by Secretary Sir JOdward Grey to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Board of Trade, copies of farther letters from the German Embassy and the India Office on the subject. - It will be seen that Mr. Brown, the firm's representative, has now supplied particulars which, it is considered, should be taken as a basis for estimating the compensation to be paid to Messrs. Wonckhaus and Co. account of the cancellation of their contract by the Sheikh of Sharga Sir E. presumes that such com pensation might well amount to a sum less than that which the firm might ha\e hoped to make if their contracts had been carried through in the most favourable conditions and without the slightest hitch, whereas Mr. Brown's figures appear to be calculated on the latter assumption. He considers, therefore, that it will be necessary to refer e question of the amount of compensation actually due to some independent tnbun possessing the business experience necessary to fix it. * a I am accordingly to request that you will inform the Board of 1 rade that he would be grateful it they would cause the figures supplied by Messrs. Wonckhaus to be examined, and furnish him with their views as to the reasonableness ot the claim. Sir E. Grey would be glad to receive at the same time any suggestions which tie Board may be good enough to offer as to the tribunal to which the fixation of the amount of compensation due should be referred. I am, (Xc. RALPH PAGET. • German Embassy, September 12 [42511]; ditto September 18 [43187]; India Office, October 2 95]; ditto, October 9 [4f&gt;0 ( .)3] ; ditto, October 15, 1913 [4/043J. [44995] [1908 7J?—1]Dated (11.30 a.m.) Please see my letter No *3798. The enclosure doee not purport to be Hassan's siened or sv/orn statement ; it is my record of v^iaL Wii\\ mLclLw ^ by him before me and two other v /itnesses. An affidavit has been givan by one of the latter that the document records truly and accurately the statements which ^assan made in reply to my questions , and there is no doubt the second would give It must be within the cognizance of the Government of India that when Hassan is within reach of^ Abdul] ah and the Agent of Messrs Wonckhaus and Coy , he is completely under their influence, iilone he is a comparatively guileless old man ; on this occasion I found him by chance alone on a vessel in the harbour at Lingeh , and seized the opportunity of getting the statements which are recorded out of himTiiLiliGR-rt.i.i . P • From Seoratary of State for India. To ^ FoBeign. Repeated Resident. Is O Nil. Foreign Secret Dated 13.liJ.13. Received IP.l^.l^S. (8.00 a.m.) Island of ^bu llusa. Please refer to your F.S.telerram dated December 12th. c It is requested that orflers may he issued to y Lorimer to send the affidavit immediately to the India Office . *n affidavit should also be obtained from the other witness as soon as possibleFrom Foreign. To Resident lio D.o. 25. Dated 19.1^.13. Received 20.12.13. (8.00 a.m.) The Secretary of State was informed of the purport of your predecessor's telegram i^o 1964 dated December 2nd in regard to the island of Abu ..usa, vrith the addition that , should it be required , an affidavit would no doubt be given by the second witness. Flease act in accordance with telegram dated December 13th from the Secretary of State , which was repaated to yuu Foreign.NO. 57/3 of If) 15. Britlah Realdoncy and ConBulate-Gen^ral, IBushlre, ^ / Docamber, 191(5. 'hi Sir, 'Vlth referenca to India Office talerram dated IPth Dacenber, 1913, to Hi a Excellency tho Viceroy, repeated to 3uahire, ard in purauance of telegraphic Instruetiona from India, I have the honour to forward, duly attested by me, the Affidavit of •Chan Sahib Haji Attdur Rizaq of this Reaidency in regard to the converaation on the Abu i -'.uaa Oxide caae between Bir Percy Cox and Hassan Sumaiyah, during their meeting at Lin^eh. I further have the honour to inform you that His , ( llaleaty's Vice-Consul at Lingeh haa been instructed to i' t ll ^ obtain from Khan Bahadur A^ha B^dr, Reaidency A^ent at r Iiingeh, and atteat a similar document, which he will U' then forward direct to tho India Office, I have the honour to be Sir, Your moat obedient servant, I.C.S. Offg:Political Reaident in the n ersian 3ulf. The Political Secretary, India Office, London.* - , L- Translation of Affidavit by Khan S^heb Haji Abdur F.ftzaq of the Buehire Beeidenoy, c. I # the humble one, Abdur E^zaq, give evidence before God that on the 27th of August in the present year in the harbour of Linpoh in the nan-of-Wir ' Sphinx' in attendance on the distinguished Colonel Sir P,Cox t Kesident and Consul General of the illustrious Government in the Persian Gulf t Haji Hassan bin oanuiyah of his own free will and accord came on board the man-of-war 'Srhinx' from a merchant ves sel, and of his own free will ^nd voluntarily in the presence of this humble one made the following admiseionR in reply to the questions of His Honour the Residont, First of all he admitted that he took an advance of Es 2000 from I'essrs Wonckh^us. The item was debited etc etc (as in I. emorandum by Sir ^.^•Cox dated Lingeh 27th Aupust 1913. Enclosure to 3ushire letter Ko# 2799 dated 14th Sep tember 1913 to the Secretary to the Government of India in the roreign Department),Confidential. / «(&gt;• hp / of 1913. British Heeidenoy and ConBulato-General # y BtiBhire, ^5/ * Docomber 1913. To Hie Majesty's Vice-Consul t L I U a K H. Sir. I haTe the honour to inform you that when Sir ?• Cox ▼isited Lin^eh at the end of August of this year, he chanced to meet one HaBsan Samaiyah, the holder of a oonoession for the excavation of iron oxide on the iiland of Abu T'usa. AB you are doubtless aware, there have been discussions between His I f j.;jesty's Government and that of Germany in regard to the carrying out of a certain contract between the concession -n.dre and the Genr^n firm, Messrs Wonckhaus h Coy, and in this connection Haeean Sacxiyah, on he occasion of his meeting with Sir ?. Cox, made certain statements, which were recorded by the latter, in presence of the Residency Ajpent at Lin#eh and Xhan Sahib Haji Abdur F.izaq of this Residency. The record of this conversation (English copy enclosed) was incorporated in a letter from Sir ''.Cox to the Government of India, who have now asked for affidavits from the two witnesses above mentioned. A vernacular document embodying the titataments made by Hassan Samaiyah to Sir Cox in the presence of Khan Bahadur Agrha Badr is forwarded herewith. If the said document correctly ernresseB, as it no doubt does, the substmce of the state ments referred to. Khan Bahadur Agha 3j,dr should cor)y it with his ov/n hand and sign it in your presence, -.nd you should cer tify his signature by your own and by the Consular seal. When the affidavit has been duly completed, I re uest that you will forward it to the Political Secretary, India Office, under cover of the letter which you will find enclosed ready for your signature.I further request that the matter may bo treated ae urgent. I hayo the honour to 'be Sir, Your most obedient eervant. I.C.S. Offf: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Hie Kajasty 1 b vice-Conoulate, and ABbiatant Reeldencyt Lln^oh, Deco^bar, 191*. Tilth reference to India Office telerran da tod ISth Docer.bor, 1915, to Hl« Excellency the viceroy, and in purauance of Inotructiona received by ne from the Political Resident in the Feraian Gulf, I have the honour to forward, duly attested by me, the Affidavit of iChan Bahadur Airha 'air, Residency A rent at Llrreh in regard to tiie contreraation between #ir Percy Cox and Hassan Gumaiya on the Abu Muea Oxide qusstion. during their meeting at Lln^reh. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obe li ent servant. His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Lin-eh. I.No. ^2^ of 19IS. British Raaldency and Consulate-/onaral, n Buahlre, JJ 3 Da camber, 1913. 11 v Sir, t V.'ith ref.aranco to ray latter No. ' da^-el 21 ^t Decarrbar, 191^, I have tha honour to raquast that tha translation, now forwardad, of the openInr clauses of the Affidavit of Khan Sahib Haji Abdur Ri2a&lt;| may be substituted for that enclosed therein# I have 4 -the honour to be Sir, Tour most obedlant servant. I • C* S. OffgtPolltical Rasllant In the Persian auif. he Political Secretary, India Office, London•— n?&gt;B Translation of Affidavit by Khan Gahib Haji Abdur Rizaq of the Bushire Rasidoncy. I, the humble one, Abdur Rizaq, jrive evidence before God that on the 27th of August in the present vear in the harbour of Linfreh in the man-of-war 'S-ohinx' when I was in attendance on the distinguished Colonel Sir P.Cox, Resident and Consul General of the illustrious Govemnent in the Persian Gulf, Haji Hassan bin Sama^yah of his own free will and accord ca-? on board the ran-of-war 'Sphinx' from a merchant vessel, and of his own free will and voluntarily in the presence of this humble one made the following admissions in reply to the questions of His Honoiar the Resident. First of all he admitted that he took an advance of Rs,2000 from Messrs V/onckhaus, The item was debited etc etc (as in Memorandum by Sir P-Z.Cox dated Linpreh S^th August 1913. Enclosure to Bushire letter No.^7^8 dated 14th Lepte^ber, 1913, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department.)C o nfldentlal. / * HESl &amp;^ v H EC El FT \ th n^e&gt; a ). 3 W I : No. £&lt;?-E.A. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information, in continuation of the endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, No. 2655-S.A.(Confidential), dated the 15th November 1913. By order, &amp;c., for Assistant Secretary Foreign &amp; PoliticalJ^p^rtment, Simla; The f* January 1914. e Government of India. Letter from Foreign Office to Board of Trade, dated the olst October 1913. (With one spare copy)(COPY) Asiatic Turkey and Arabia (October 31) Confidential. (47043) No. 1. Foreign Office to Board of Trade. Section I. Foreign Office, October 31, 1913. Sir, With reference to the previous correspondence regarding the claim of Messrs. Robert '//onckhaus and Co to compensation in connection with the red dixide which industry in the island of Abu Musa, of/copies have been communicated periodically to your Department, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Board of Trade, copies of further letters from the German Embassy and the India Office on the subject. It will be seen that Mr. Brown, the firm's representative, has nov r /^u|)plied particulars v/hich, it is considered, should be taken as a basis for estimating the compensation to be paid to Messrs. C/ Wor^haus and Co. on account of the cancellation of their contract by the Sheikh of Sharga. Sir E. Grey presumes that such compensation might well amount to a; j : -f' • r : rc J ; -i . : a sum less than that which the firm might have hoped to make if their contracts had been carried through in the most favourable conditions and without the slightest hitffh, -hereas Mr. Brown's figures appear to be calculated on the latter assumption. He considers, therefore, that it will be necessary to refer the question of the auount of compensPtion actually due to some independent tribunal possessing the business experience necessary to fix it. I am accordingly to request that you will inform the Board of Trade that he would be grateful if they vould cause the figures supplied by Messrs. Wo^ihaus to 136 e ■ air.ined, and. furnish him with their views as to the reasonahlenecs of the claim. Sir E, Grey would 'be glad to receive at the same any suggestions which the Board may be good enough to offer as to the tribunal to which the fixation of the amount of compensation due should be referred. I am, etc., Sd/- Ifc.lph Paget. German Erbassy,September 12 (42511); ditto. September 18 (42137); India Office, October 2 (44995); ditto October 9(46093); ditto October 15, 1913 (47043).Telegram, p. Prom Secretary of State for India, To Viceroy repeated Resident. No. Nil. Dated 9th, received 10th February 1914 ( 8 am.) Oxide on Abu Musa Island. It ib requested that you will inforia me i - Firstly, r/hetiier T.'onokhaua made any ahipment of oxide under contract before that on the 'Louise' [(page 115 Vol 4^7^ April 1908. Secondly. Tihether any of the oxide which was mined at the ri Ue TThen the contract was cancelled j (25th October 1907? page 295 Vol s| had been mined before the contraot[(page 55 file 14/115 Vol 2)] was entered upon June Ist 1906. —iiiiwun i»I | I* | i | »'»IIII It is also requested that you will telegraph list and [(page 266)) value of the tools belonging to ^onckhaus jL which were left on the Island off the Hamburg-Amerilea vessel.I H- [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] [January 10.] Section 1. No. 1. Board of Trade to Foreign Office.—{Received January 10.) Wt** /jj *0' i * H n*i Sir, Board of Trade, January 9, 1914. I AM directed by the Board of Trade to refer to your letter of the 31st October, and its enclosures, regarding Messrs. Wonckhaus and Co.'s claim to compensation in connection with the Abu Musa red oxide difficulty, and to offer the following observations thereon for Sir E. Grey's consideration :— 1 The Board note that, while it is proposed to compensate Messrs. Wonckhaus in respect of their losses owing to the non-fulHlment of their contract of the 1st June, 1900, for the purchase of red oxide mined in Abu Musa, His Majesty's Government refuse to recognise any claim on the part of the firm as shareholders in the company which held the concession for mining in that island, more especially as their share in that company was purchased at a date when they must have been aware that the concession had been cancelled. 2. As regards the claims now under consideration, the Board apprehend that these are as follows :— (a.) That the firm's direct losses be refunded—the counts of the claim being set out under five sub-heads (see enclosure to Prince Lichnowsky's note of the 5th April). (b.) That a lump sum be paid to the firm to compensate them for the profit which they might have been expected to make i but did not make) had their contract with Hassan Samaiya been uninterrupted. It is understood that this proposal has been accepted by Messrs. Wonckhaus and the German Government, and that the sum paid is to be in final extinction of all rights which the firm may have acquired whether under the contract or otherwise. 3. As regards (a), the Board are disposed to think that Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim under sub-head (1) might in principle be allowed in respect both of advances to the mining company and of implements lost on the island. It would, however, be incumbent on the firm to adduce satisfactory evidence as to the amount of such advances not repaid, and it would also be necessary for them to establish the precise nature and value of the implements destroyed or removed. 4. The Board understand, as a result of semi-official communication with your Department since the date of your letter under reply, that the shipment by the steam ship 'Louise' (item 2), which consisted of 1,810 tons of oxide, was made in April 1908, in pursuance of the permission granted in Sir E. Grey's note to the German Charge d'Affaires of the 10th January of that year. Thus three months were allowed to elapse between the date on which operations on Abu Musa ceased and the date on which permission to ship the oxide already on the beach was accorded, and about three months more elapsed before Messrs. Wonckhaus availed themselves of this privilege. The claim here is mainly one on account of deterioration of the oxide during this period of delay, but the Board note that, in Sir P. Cox's opinion, no substantial deterioration can have occurred. If, however, the fact that deterioration did take place could be established, it would seem to have been due partly to the firm's own inaction and partly to circumstances beyond their control. The extent to which these circumstances should be allowed for w^ould largely depend upon the length of time the oxide in question had already been lying on the beach before the cessation of operations, and, for the purpose of any reference to arbitration, information on this point would have to be secured. 5. The Board concur in Sir E. Grey's decision not to admit claims under item 5. Item No. 3, of course, disappears in view of the facts that the mines under present arrangements are not to be handed over to Messrs. Wonckhaus and that their claim as shareholders in the original mining concession is not to be recognised. The Board also note that Sir E. Grey is not prepared to make any allowance in respect of item 4. [2001 k—1]6. As regards the substantial part of Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim comprised under head (6), viz., that arising from the loss of anticipated profits under their contract with Hassan Samaiya, I am to state that— 7. As the Board understand the matter, the quantity of red oxide to be shipped per annum under the contract was from 2,000 tons np to a maximum of 5,000 tons, and the period of the contract four years, the firm having, however, the option of renewal for a further period ' at the same price and condition, or at any rate at the price of other serious buyers.' 'The concession was terminated by force in October 1907, i .e., about one year and four months after the commencement of the contract on the 1st June, 1906, and two years and eight months before the date on which it would in ordinary circumstances have elapsed if not renewed. It is assumed that the firm desire their claim to be considered as one to cover the whole period of their contract, subject to a reduction on account of oxide actuall}- shipped. 8. It is understood that the quantities of oxide actually shipped by Messrs. Wonckhaus were as follows ; in April 1908, by the steamship ' Louise,' 1,810 tons ; in May 1911, 300 tons ; on the 14th November, 1912, 5,000 bags. The Board are not aware of the weight of a bag of oxide, but, having regard to the third paragraph of the contract of the 1st June, 190(j, 5,000 bags would appear to amount to about 6,000 cwt., or 300 tons. In addition, it is understood that 400 tons were shipped by the steamship 41 Nasin,' in May 1910, on account of Hassan Samaiya, in fullilment presumably of the third paragraph of Messrs. Wonckhaus's contract with him. 9. The Board also understand that at the time when operations on the island ceased there were lying on the beach the 1,810 tons shipped subsequently by the 'Louise,' as well as 400 tons which that vessel did not remove, and that, in addition, 3,000 tons of oxide had been deposited near the mine. The Board are not, however, aware (1) whether any shipment of oxide was made by Messrs. Wonckhaus under their contract before the ' Louise ' shipment; and (2) whether any of the oxide mined at the date when the concession was cancelled had been mined before the commence ment of the contract (Ist June, 1906). If it should be possible to answer both these questions in the negative, and if the quantity above referred to (about 5,210 tons) represents the total output of the mine during the expired period of the contract (about one year and four months), it would appear that Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim in respect of that period can only relate to the difference between the 5,210 tons and the total amount shipped by them (2,410 tons—excluding the shipment of 400 tons on behalf of Hassan). In the contrary event, allowance would have to be made accordingly. As, however, Messrs. Wonckhaus were definitely granted permission on the 15th December, 1911, to remove all the oxide which had been mined and not already removed, provided they did so before the end of 1912, they cannot, so far as the Board are aware, properly blame anyone but themselves if they did not avail themselves of this privilege in its entirety. The Board are therefore of opinion that a claim to compensation should be admitted only in respect of the unexpired portion of the contract (viz., two years and eight months). 10. On the other hand, the Board are disposed to think that some allowance (say for two years' shipments) might be made to the firm in consideration of loss under the renewal clause of their contract. But it must be observed that the words ' at any rate at the price of other serious buyers ' appear to ^contemplate the possibility of the contract, if renewed, being renewed on terms less advantageous to Messrs. Wonckhaus. 11. I am, however, to point out in this connection that, whilst deposits of red ochre are very widely distributed throughout the world, certain kinds derived from the islands of the Persian Gulf (principally Hormuz) are understood to have special qualities as regards shade. It is also understood that these varieties, for which there is much demand in the trade, cannot be replaced from other sources. The market for red oxide of this kind is, however, limited, and, with the Hormuz deposits working, it may be questioned whether the market could (without a considerable resultant depreciation in value) have absorbed more than the minimum (2,000 tons) of Abu Musa oxide allowed to be shipped by Messrs. Wonckhaus's contract. Nevertheless, it would seem that, if the 5,210 tons above referred to were actually mined during the expired period of the contract, the annual output during that period at least was considerably in excess of 2,000 tons. 12. If, therefore, allowance be made for shipment at the minimum rate of 2,000 tons per annum for the unexpired period of the contract plus 4,000 tons in considera tion of loss under the renewal clause, the total amount of oxide for which Messrs, Wonckhaus would receive compensation would be 9,333 tons, or roughly 10,000 tons.If, for the moment, the figure of . r, .3s. M. per ton which the firm claim to have been 8 acce P ted ' woulf l result in an estimate for compensation of lD,D_5t, to which some sum would have to be added to meet the first two items of the Head (a) ot the claim, the other claims under that head being disallowed. It will of course be requisite that the firms figure of 33 5 . 3d. profit per ton be most carefully examined by the arbitrators who may be appointed to investigate the whole matter lo. \\ mist the Board are of opinion that compensation to Messrs. Wonckhaus mig it properly be based on the general principles indicated in the fore ^oincr paiagraphs, they are not m a position to check Messrs. Wonckhaus's figures or to advance any estimate-other than the very rough calculation contained in the immediately preceding paragraph—of the amount of compensation to be paid to that lirm In particular they have no information as to (1) the average market price of red oxide on the continent during the unexpired term of the contract, or what that price would have been had the contract been permitted to run—i.e., whether the prices would have been depressed by the addition of the produce of the Abu Musa mines to the worlds supply; (2) what the average cost of freight, insurance, and commission for the carriage of the oxide to Europe would have amounted to in the period ; (3) whether it would have been possible for the Abu Musa Company to have mined more than, or as much as, the 2,000 tons per annum stipulated in the contract during its unexpired portion ; and (4) whether the quality of the oxide from the Abu Musa mines was up to average standard. ^ 14. The foregoing points, together with the items 1 and 2 of head (a) above referred to, might, in the Board's view, properly form the subject of an investigation by competent arbitrators, to whom the evidence available from Messrs. Wonckhaus's books m respect of the trial, shipment, and from other sources could be submitted. s regards the tribunal to which this enquiry should be entrusted, the Board note that the ( rerman Government m their Memorandum, copy of which formed one of the enclosures m your letter under reply, appear to contemplate the submission of the case to a mercantile expert in London, and they are accordingly disposed to suggest for bir E Greys consideration that, for the purposes of a commercial ascertainment of the facts, no better tribunal could be suggested than a court of arbitration appointed by the London Chamber of Commerce. 15. Information with regard to the two points referred to in the paragraph of this etei, numbered 9, may perhaps best be obtained from Messrs. Wonckhaus direct beiore any reference is made to arbitration. I am, &amp;c. GEO. J. STANLEY. IFrom Birdv/ood. To Foreifn. Repeated India Office. iSo . ■ /JOj. Dated 14.2.14. (7.20 p.m.) ^ office tele r ram of i'o'br &gt; uar , y Qtli. ^'bu ^usa oxide. First, ^ur records on this point are very rneaFre and not reliable . I can only find a reference to t^e following three shipments:- (a), ss 'Janadia' reported to he ^oin^ to visit Ahu I/usa il . T7 %S H* 6 about v.ay lOO^ but no amount mentioned. (b). ss 'Kasiri' reported to have visited Ahu Musa about June 1907 and removed 6000 cwts for shipment to Hamhurr via a Uf Bombay. (o). ohipment by Teutonia of 000 tons of loose oxide aV t August 10 , hut in this connection please see para^rapn 4 oj- ^asqat letter 414 of ^u^ust 5th 1007 to the. d^ar^t and Government of India reference wreck of the Teutonia. KM5 ^ K | X Second. 1 can find nothing on our recordsbearijn^ on this T ' question. exactly Third. I a.!'] a liutle uncertain what imDlements ^are meant, l-iu complete list of articles claimed by /onckhaus as belonr:- -inr to them and as having disappeared from the island will he i'oi nfl in enclosure 1 to the Resident's letter No ^104 of ^ -rr 7JV xl iJovember 20th 1910 to the Government of India . This claim ^ U 1' has not yet been finally adjudicated on. ^part from these articles the German Consul put in a claim Ox two la: ^e planks valued at pounds four eash, the property of the Hamburg -Araer ilea Company and which he alleged had 'Heen left on the island by the ,, Louise ,, in ^pril 190R. -^.TZE ^2*6 addressed Government of India repeated India Office. Birdv/ood.-Of PICE^40*4i. No lU of 1914 BUSH T.W, 2 FRIiRUAR^ 1914 LM3-. THE RESIDENCY A r ENT AT SHARGA.H A • C • j s' 47 T write 'bo rGQUBst. 'Lhat/ yon. will ^0 ^ood Gnon^H very urgently to supply me if possible with the follow ing information:- ;(1) ^id Mes-rs TVonckhaus and Coy: make any shipment of teed oxide under their oontraot before the shipment made hv the steamship •'Louise' in April 1908?.Tf so,how many shipments were made,what, was the cmantity of ea^h shipment,on what datss Were the shipments made and fvhat were the names of the steamers?. (2j. L {ad any of the red oxide mined at the date of th Q cancellation of the contract he-n mned 'Hefor^ th o tnencement of the contract in June 1906?. r&gt;0' Captain, First Assistant to the Political Resident in th^ Persian Gulf. (In charge current duties.) ' 'A^ IK j &amp;&amp;&amp;[&gt; - &amp; Uo' , y 1I rf TELiiGHAM P. From Foreign, Delhi Birdv/ood, iiuahire. 26.^,14 iveceived 27.2.14 (8.10 a.m.) D.S.122 The following refers to your telegram no. 21. You ■hould telegraph the result of your inquiries on the subject of A^u Muaa island, whioh we presume you are making of the Residency Agent at Lingeh, to the India Office direct. Foreign. TELEGRAM H. From Birdwood, Bushire To Foreign, Delhi, lo. 242 Dated 27 .2.14 (10.55 a .m.) Your D.S. 122. Am enquiring from Residency Agent. Birdwood• iIT ♦ V« i ikiWS ■ m* ni Tole^ram. To O.C HfenJam, Urgent . Dated 4th March 1914 ( 3.40 p.m.) I should be glad if following message could be sent over urgent to Khan Bahadur Abdul Litif Residency Vrent Shargah. I understand slow mail of Marek 6th does not call Dibai. Can you possibly arrange for native boat or any other means • Please do your best and let me lrnow» Meaaage ia as follows. Begins.. 'Takun tatasawar beann ketabena nomreh arba'a ra teseen muvarrakheh arba'a va eshreen February qad abtal mazmuneh va la yakun ta # amal al-eqdam beayye nahj fizalek va tarjaa alketab/ elina. Captain Birdwood Haib Awwal x, al-Balyuz. ^ Ends • Cover should be addressed in both English and Arabis characters as also the message itself if you can find anybody to do it. Resident. Sent to Hanjara and Arabic text collated. *Telgram. From C .C.» Hanjam. To Resident C/C O.C. Words 41. Dated and received 4-3-14.' . .) Can you Inform me if following is what should be forwarded to Shargah. Begins. H Consider my letter No.94 of 24th February cancelled and ignore contents returning my original letter immediately' Ends. Reply urgent. C.C.Telegram. From Resident Buahiro. To C.C• Han J am• Dated 5th March 1914, 8 a.m.) Your 41/14. Yes translation you give is correct but there is no need to translate message. All I want done is tc have message posted as received by you in Arabic and English characters. Resident.Telegram. Prom C.C. Hanjam. To Resident c/p O.C. Bualiire. Wds 39. Dated 4-th March 1914. Transport will cost Rb 50 (fifty) and translation Rs 5. Are you prepared to pay these monies please. Translation in your nil/4 cannot be despatched earlier than tomorrow mornini;. Please reply quickly urgent. O.C. BS. K Telegram. From Resident Bushire. To C.C. Hanjam. Dated 5th March 1914. Tes, I am prepared to pay Rs 55 in all Resident. —111 Telegram. P , j » qv C • G. Han;]am, Please give this to Resident and tell him It ic from the Postmaeter Bandar 'Abbas regarding mails begins pos^ ' Outward subsidiary steamer leaving Karachi lat '''arob will call extra at Debai.Ciose bag for Debai and send it by that steamer. P.M.G.Bombay. w Tell Captain Birdwood the Barala is now at Bandar ♦Abbad and is calling at Debai,so I have sent his X.T. words nil /4 to Khan Bahadur Abdul Latif,Residency Agent, ?)hargah to Debai by post and to cancel all previous communication on this subject and let me have his reply. r . I r.r? 5 TKLEGHAk P From Secretary of State, India Office To Birdwood, Bushire. Dated 4.2.14 Received 5,3.14 (8 a.m.) F. S. Oxide. I am wqcKtiMjc awaiting a reply to my te^spram of 20th February. When may I expect to receive it JTiiLJiGRAM R. From lirdwood, luahire To Foreign, rep. India Office Mo. 271 Dated 5.3.14. f( India Office telegram of February 20th and their re minder of March 4th. Oxide. Residency Agent had already left Lingeh before any message from me could reach him and he ia now at Bushire (ii,ni of R.) He ia certain, he sayo as regards the second question, that some of the oxide mined at the date of the cancellation of the contract was stuff which had been mined before the contract had been entered upon. However he is not in a position to state the quantities without first making enquiries at Lingeh, but he is of the opinion xxa that all such oxide was used only to mix with the superior product obtained after the contract was entered upon, being stuff which the German firm had ,, not approved' • (R) as regards question (1) Residency A ^ent can give no reply without reference to his records. Under ordinary circumstances and using mail steamers information will not be available till about Uarch 2lrd but I will try and arrange special trip to Lingeh by R.I.M.S. Lawrence. Birdwood.O jl C. No/^ J of 1914 Brit/lsli Pesidenoy and Consulat/e-General Bushire, r t,h Ma vnh 1914 To: KiM BAHA^UB 4QA BT-^EP., Residency Agent at, Ling eh, (B u s h i r e } A.C. , I write to request that you will he good enough, very urgently,to supply me if possible with the fol lowing informationr- Cl) Did Messrs Wonckhaus and Coy: make any shipment of red oxide under their contract before the shipment made by the steamship'Louis M in April 1903? 1^ so,how many shipments were made,what was the cuantity of ^arh Shipment,on what dates were the shipments made,and what were the names of the steamers?. (2) Had any of the red oxide mined at the date o^ the cancellation of the contract been ^ined before the commencement of the contract in June 1906? Captain, P 1 irst Assistant to the Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf, (In charge current duties.) ir ^ ilvfA;'. CsMl ^ A/ .-'rrf/e /T^LKGKAM.Rm Fron Hesident Xnox. To Foreign repeated India Office. NO. 2.S7 Dated 9.2.x4. ) Birdwood^ telegram No 271 of March 6th. Much regret that owing to urgent 'buoy work Lawrence will^ not ue available . Information requited aho Id reach about Maech 24th. Addressed Government of India repeated India Office.pBEHj * o - vt#- sv Memorandum. life correspondence mentioned below is herewith transmitted to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, with a view to avoiding delay in the event of the Foreign Department of the Government of India desiring to communicate with him on the snbi A copy of this memorandum and of the correspondence is also being communicated to that Department by to-day's mail. A ssistant Secretary, Political Department. INDIA OFFICE, 13th Feb. 19lA . _pu Mmom. Letter to Foreign Office, ICth Feb. 1914,• It is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter ami number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to The Under Secretary of State for India. p. 2 5 Political Department, India Office, London, S.W. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W. 1 t&gt; -ebruary 1914. air. I am directed by the ^fjcretary of State for India to afikrowled^e the receint of your letter Uo* 1233 dated .^uth January enclosing copy of a letter from the Board of Trade re^ardirv, ? e»3rs. loncKhaus' claini to compensation in reipect of ibu ^usa o/ide. vhe arouese of Crewe naa cauued LKe telegraui, of which a copy ia encioeed for ^ir . C^rty' a informtion 9 to be addeteeed to tha (iovornrnent ^f India asking for information on the two oointe raieed bji the I jaid of xradt) in para. 9 of their letter t and calling for a list and value of any inplo! ent« Lelonginif. to 1. eaarB. fonekhauff that may have be^n left on the island. Hia Lordship ia advised that in 'onnation on these points can prol tly be ehtained fro ti e residency et l^uahire, and he ic of opinion that seers, 'onckhaue ahould not he. e»:ed for their vrreiow of the faclr urtil at any rr.te u kv I j has h^er. reccivtid frc n Us -ovemmant of indis^. ie would •Uf;;ett Iso for Mr . 'r^y'g considera tion, U r .t on recsl t of t^ie infor ation, it would be ae well obtain the expert viev» of . r. 1 trick infor- faally and confidentially, onnthe merits of the substan tial portion of essrs. onckhaua* claim ( vide paras. 6-12 of the Board of Trade 's letter) and on the minor . Hion of the alleged deterioration of the oxide shipned by the s.s. 'L^uioe'. Ife would further suggest thet perhapa the most convenient meana of obtaining The Under Secretary of State, r * FOREIGN OFFICE.I i ' I *f [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.] TURKEY. TFebruary 7.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [5706] No. 1. Abu Musa Oxide: Note hy Sir P. Cox on Board of Trade's Letter of January 9,1914.— {Communicated hy India Office, February 7, 1914.) 1 BEG to offer some comment based on local knowledge on details of the Board of Trade letter of the 9th January to the Foreign Office. His Majesty's Government start with the premise that they refuse to recognise Messrs. Wonckhausas members of the concessionnaire company, or discuss any claim based on that pretence. The contract entered into by W onckhans with the concessionnaires merely provided for his obtaining oxide f.o.b. on- ships sent by him to fetch it. This is the only position we need recognise. We contemplate— (1) As regards claim (a) (1) the advances, according to Hassan's statements, only amount to 2,000 rupees. (2) A\ hat was first interpreted as ' deposits ' on the island is now corrected to 'objects,' i.e., implements which are said to have disappeared from the island. I should like to offer some explanation on this point. Hassan Samaiyeh at the time of the cancellation of the concession by the Sheikh of Shargah was warned to remove his coolies and gear from the island at a certain date. He neglected to do so within the time specified, and was then warned that if he did not do so they would be removed for him. He refused to comply, and everything was therefore put on lighters and transported to Lingah, where Hassan was told that he could take or leave the stuff as he pleased, and that no claim could be entertained in regard to it. He then took it. Subsequently, when he was allowed by us to ship some of the accumulated oxide for Wonckhaus he took some gear back again, and between shipments the roof of his locker store-hut fell in and the islanders were said to have removed a few things. Hassan Samaiyeh then, at Wonckhaus's instigation, put in an extravagant claim, which included things which he said he had lost when his gear was thrown out of the island under the circumstances above mentioned. The German firm first claimed that the gear was partly owned by them as members of the concession, but this claim was not recognised. They were told that, seeing that Wonckhaus's contract was f.o.b. and that he had himself stated publicly in a letter to the press that ' there never were any goods of ours on the island,' he could really have no title to make such a claim, but as he stated that some landings, planks, and three or four iron buckets belonging to a Hamburg-Amerika ship had been left there, we contemplated paying them the value for these, if their presence there could be proved. My opinion, therefore, is that we should refuse to consider their right to identify themselves with Hassan Samaiyeh's claim for the concessionnaire's ordinary loading gear (bags, crow-bars, &amp;c.), but that we should refund him the small amount due for the few articles above mentioned without further question. It should be a very small amount. The list and value is on record at Bushire, and I do not think it would be worth while bothering about the evidence. To prove it would mean the Resident proceeding to Abu Musa or Shargah to hold a further court and involve expenditure of coal amounting to more than the value of the things. Any investigation requiring the evidence of Hassan Samaiyeh's account books would be very unsatisfactory, as no accounts have ever been shown by him to his partners, and we know that he cooked his books, under Mr. Brown's directions, after the cancellation of the concession, and they have since been in German keeping. (a) Refunding direct losses. (b) Paying a lump sum for loss of business resulting to them. [2034 g—2]The question of deterioration is a difficult one. From the history of the oxide trade I believe the claim on this account to be in a great measure mythical. In the Board of Irade letter the local conditions existing at the time of the execution of the Wonckhaus contract do not seem to be quite understood, I beg to offer some explana tions. I he original concessionnaires obtained their concession in 1898 (?). They started regularly mining oxide a few months later, and their plan of operations was to keep about fifty coolies on the island extracting the oxide in a leisurely way, and accumulating heaps of it with which to fulfil orders when received. At the time Wonckhaus was contemplating taking up the oxide trade (190(5) and making a contract with Ifassan Samaiyeh (in 1906, seven years after the work had been going on), the first thing he did was to visit ihe island and examine the several heaps of oxide lying ready for disposal (at least three different spots had been worked). After examining the heaps, which had probably been there for years, he entered into contract to buy the oxide f.o.b. (June 190(3). In was in August 1906 that we heard of it, and in hebruary .1907 that the Sheikh of Shargah cancelled the con cession. To the best ol my belief, very little, if any, mining went on after August 1906, and none especially for Wonckhaus. Hassan simply continued to keep his footing there with a few diggers until he was expelled in October 1907. The Germans in their case quoted ' The fact that the Company is not in a -position to extract at the proper time the quantity which they must keep ready for deliveries due in the coming months.' It is to be remembered that during the years 1899 to 1906 Hassan had been mining small quantities all the time, but had sold very little, and that to India ; and that at the time his concession was cancelled there was oxide on the island which we now know fairly accurately to have amounted to 5,000 tons odd. None of that was mined after the cancellation of the concession (October 1907), and to the best ol m} 7, belief, based on experience of the normal working of the concern, not more than 500 tons was mined between June 1906 and October 1907. \\ ith reference, therefore, to the doubtful points raised in paragraph 9 (1), to the best of my recollection no shipment was made for Wonckhaus before the''Louise' shipment. Ihis can be verified at once from the Bushire record if it is not on record here. (-) To the best ol my belie! nearly the whole, and in any case the major proportion, ol the oxide lying on the island at the moment of the concession being cancelled had been mined before the commencement of Wonckhaus's contract; and between the commencement of Wonckhaus's contract (June 1906; and the cancellation of the concession not more than 500 tons was mined. I would lay stress on the fact that we allowed \\ onckhaus to carry away the mined oxide in spite of protests fiom the bheikh of fehargah and the other concessionnaires, primarily because His Majesty's Government seemed to have understood at the time that it had been mined for W onckhaus—which it had not but mainly for the specific object of discounting Wjinckhaus s claim ior loss of business. As a favour we resigned the whole of the 5,^10 tons on the island to W onckhaus, so that he might not have the pretext that he had been put to loss. In my opinion, having regard to the normal scale on which the mining was always carried on up to the time of W r onckhaus's contract, and which scale W onckhaus showed no inclination to (get) modify, Hassan Samaiyeh could not have mined moie than, and with great difficulty as much as, 2,000 tons per year ; W 7 onckhaus merely stated a maximum of 5,000 tons in order to make quite sure that Hassan should have none to spare for anyone else. Let us presume that he could have taken 2,000 tons per year, from June 1906 to June 1913—seven years. Then he would have taken 14,000 tons. In point of tact, we have given him the opportunity of taking 5,000 odd tons, so he may con- cenably have lost the sale^ of 9,000 tons if there was a market, but it is very doubtful if there was one. This figure is much the same as that at which the Board of 1 rade arrive on different lines in paragraph 12. 1 recommend that the information be obtained by telegram from Bushire, and without reference to Messrs. A\ onckhaus. When that is obtained I would suggest that, before we do anything further, the expert views of Mr. Strick be taken informally and confidentially as a preliminary measure, on the position as we now have it. He would probably be able to make useful comment, and I could be used to get his views if Government do not wish to communicate with him. P. z. COX. February 6, 1914.I,'o. 3 of 1914 The Residency Agent, L i n g e h . (1) Question. What amounts,and on what dates oxide shipped prior to shipment by S.G. 'Louise ' by the German Firm. Answer, .On the 25th March 1906 by • S. f, LIohaminedi H of at Persian Company for transhipment/'arachi for Pamburr 700 tons. On the 2nd of June 19 nr 7 by 'Naseri' Bombay at' Persian Company for trabshipment /ro^bay fcr Hamburg 6000 bags total weirht being 7CC tors. 16tl Jvly 1907 by L.L.'Teutonia' Hamburg American for Humburg 900 tons. 9th to 16th April 1908 by S.S.'Louise' Hamburg American 1810 tons. This information is from the reports of the Residency Agent extracted from letters submitted to the Residency at the above mentioned times. Question, wrb there any oxide ready excavated from the mines on the date of the cancellation of the contract which could be said to have been excavate'! prior to the contract having been c;! ?gred in T une 1906. Answer. Before signing of contract,there were several mounds of red oxide already extracted but the German Firm after contract visited Abu ,r usa, inspected oxide, did not approve it and had some more extracted from the large mine of which he approved. They then excavated oxide therefrom and shipped for German Firm. But Hasan bin r.umaya mi^ed the oxide from the large mine with that rejected by German Firm especially in the case o^ S.S,'Louise'. After cancellation of contract no oxide was excavated. ThereThere was certainly oxide lying on Abu Musa island at the date of the cancellation of the contract that had been mined before the contract was entered into viz: June 1906.Telegram R. From Ma.jor S.G. Knox, Resident, Bushire. To Foreign, repeated Secretary of State for India. No. 347. Dated 25th March 1914 ( 11.10 a.m.) Secretary of Stated telegram of February 20th. Oxide. Enquiries made at Lingeh hare elicited the following:- Firatly . 1906. March 25th Bombay Persian Steamship Muhammadi. For transhipment Karachi for Hamburg 700 tons. 1907. June 2nd Bombay Persian Steamship Nasri. For trans hipment Bombay for Hamburg 300 tons. July 16th. Hamburg-Amerika steamship Teutonia for Hamburg 500 tons. 1908. April 16th Hamburg-Amerika Steamship Louise 1810 tons. Secondly . At the date of the cancellation of the contract i much of the oxide, which had been mined before the 1st June 1906 when the contract was entered upon, was still lying on the island. Knox.JUAx^s ^&gt;rv^~ ^'- ^ ^ ft, &gt;M^yv- I ^ tc rcJ Abu Muaa . Government are conaidering Wonckhaus' claims for com pensation. In the course of these Wonckhaus has pretended that all the Oxide rained on the island and taken away eventually was mined especially for them after June 1906 (date of their contract). I have expressed the belief that a large proportion of it was mined in the ordinary desultory course before Wonckhaus contract, and that very little was mined especially for Wonck- ^ haus, for the mining stopped altogether in October 1907, and I am t positive that most of the 5000 tons odd which has since been accounted for in one way and another was lying there before that - it certainly could not have been mined between June 1906 and September 1907 because we know what work was going on then, and the yearly amount dug did not I believe amount to more than 500 » tons. You must distinguish between the amount mined and the amount of excavated stuff (in heaps) removed from various parts of the island to the spot from which it is shipped. Please make sure that Agha Badr understands what is wanted. (2). Then there is another point with regard to which it may be useful for you to know ray point of view. In October 1907 or thereabouts, as Hassan refused to remove his gear when ordered to do so by Trevor, he was warned that everything would be removed by us at his own risk. He refused to do so (under German advide) and the stuff was then dumped at Lingeh. Hassan thereupon took possession of it again at his own risk. Subsequently he put in a claim for things lost or stolen from the island, which included things said to have been lost then, and from any time since he obtained his concession. I attempted to hear the case but it is of the highest impor tance to maintain that our representative at Dingoh on Persian Coast has no jurisdiction; a case against a Trucial Chief must be held either (in this case) at Sharjafe or Abu Musa, in presence of Shaikh 1 s representative. This requires a lot of arrangement and I was twice at pains to arrange it at Abu Musa* At the first hearing HassanHassan was asked to produoe his proofs as to what was on island and what stolen and what as alleged belonged to the Hambvgg Amerika Linie ( a few plans and sling buckets). He replied that his proofs were in his accoiint books which were with the German, in Basrah or Germany. He was told to get them and the enquiry- was adjourned. Some months later he said he had now got them and I went to some trouble again but then the German refused to hand them over. I refused to accept that position, and had to adjourn again, and took no further action. The value of the things belonging to the Hamburg Lin^e is small and might be paid to them. The value of Hassan's things is no concern of the Germans and we can deal with that when the case with the Germans is finished. The question may not come up but if it does that is my line. (3). Although Bushire Office said they had no trace of list of shipments made from Abu Musa, to the best of my belief Abdul Latif sent in a list of shipments reported before the Wonckhaus con tract in connection with his own claims against Hassan. Agha Badr ought to hare record of all visits of ships subsequent to June 1906. P.Z.C.a I* A (j-y C ^r f (rrv ^ y o-^ ^ y\ •' 1 ' (-+- fasJ). i^CL (vO^^}We&lt; Ol ^-t^Vvw# • /I 11 , $ * I H * kvwi^ A'e. I 3 12 - I' 1 * 'I if I beg to offer »o«« cunu^nt baaed on local knowledge on del&amp;ils of tht iioard t f Trade letter of January 9th to the Hrti&amp;n office. Ilia V&amp;jeety*» Uoverni«ent Blart lith the prtmist that they rafuse ia ryco^ii^e eosra. i/onchhauB ae fflo«bf»rs of the ConcesLdommirs Covp&amp;ny, or discusfl any claim based on Umt prdtenc(9» The contract eiit«red into by Aonckhaua with tho Concesfiioiinaircs merely provided for hie obtaining oxide 'f.o.b. 1 v»ri aiips cent by hia to fetch it. This is Lhe only poaition we need rtco&amp;aloe, e contetnplate (a) Refunding direct loasee, (b) Fa/ii^ a iu&amp;p auu. for loss of buainees resulting to Uiem. Board of irade para, Z) (1) as rogfiriifi claim (a) (1) the advances HCCorUu; ic xasar^a :■.• iU. umtn only iou t to » rupees. (2) What was first interpreted aa 'depos its N on the ialand 9 is now corrected to'objects \ i*e« inpiesMints which are said to have ciisappaared fro^ the islawl, 1 should like to offer some explanation on this point. Fassan aamaiyeh at the time of the cancellation of the cu .cesaion by the- 1 sikh of . ^ar :ah .was earned to ret»ave his coolies and gear from the islajrid at a certain date. I e neglected to do so within the time specified, and was then warned that if he did not do so they would be re oved for him. He refused to corapljr and everything was therefore put on lighters and transported to Lirv^ah where Hassan was told that he c uld take or leave the stuffstuf an he pleannd, end that no claim could b« enter- tainod in re wrt to it. '&gt; ther. took it. jubeaouently when he wae allowed by u? to ship some of the accumulated oxide for onckhaue he took fame gtar back a-ain, and between ihipaenta. the roof of his locker hu % utore/f^li in # and th# iftlandem ner® said to havo reiaoved a few thinga. aa*an ^amaiyeh then at onckhaun's iniiif: ation out in an ertravs ^it claim, which include tbin^» which he ?jaid ba had lost whea hi a .;ear ^ ia throva out of tn« i aland undar the circumBtancaa abovfj-menti^ned, iha Uerman firm first claimeci that the kwut waa oartly ownad by them as 'lambara of tha conceajjion, but this claim waa not recoKniaed. hey war#: old that aaeing' that ^onckhaua contract wa« 'f.o.b^ and that ha had hiraaalf atatad mibljolv in a latt#r to tha # f)raaa that Hhara n«irer wara any .^ooda of oure on tha island 11 he ^ttar to London 'Standard 9 dated 17th he could really hawa no uacamber 19^8, referred to in Buahire .eaidancy Letter dated title to make auch a claim, 12th January l9Ui i?19vvS&gt;) to Oawtnmnt of India. but aa he stated that some landlnga, plank«, and r or 4 iron buckets helon&lt;in^ to a ! aiwbur^-Aifterika ahir) had bean loft there, wc contamplatad paying them the value 0 r these, if their presence there could be proved. My opinion therefore Is that we should refuse to consider their right to idenU^y themselves with i aasan Samiyeh's claim for the concea^ionnaire's ordinary loadirvi gear (baga, crow-bare, .c.), but that we should refund him the a&amp;all a^nount due for the few artic lea above mentioned without further Question. It should be a very waall araount. he liat and valu g iA-PJi. recor d at Buahire. and I do not think it would be worth while botherinjj; about the evidence. To prove it would&gt;1 Awuld laean tb« I esideni procaedin^ to ^bu ypa or r^rs^ah to hold a further court and involve expenditure of coal a^iouiitito iaorf than the value of the things* A/iy inv*mti ation roquirin^ the evidence of I aeaan Samaij^ *» account looks would be very uneatisfactory, as no accounts lave ever boi fi shown by him to bie partners and we know that he cookod hi« booka under r, rovn # 8 direct:ons after the cancellation of the corc^eKion and they Imve aivice been in German ict5epirv;. (Fara. 4 of I uard of .rado letter). Ihe quetstion of deterioration ia a difficult on®. rorr* the hi«tory of the oxide trade 1 believe the claim on this account to be in a great meaaure fflythical. In the &gt;oard of Irade letter the loc? 1 conditiona exicting at the time of the erecution of the 0x 'tckhau3 contract, do not teem to be quite understood I bo^ to offer xom explanations* The original Concess- ionn&amp;ircs obtained their conoeeaion in 1096 (?). they started r^ularly ainia ; oxide a fe^ fcontba later, and their plsax of operations was to keep about (x coolies on the island extractii^ the oxide in s leisurely way and accujmiiatin^; heaps of it ^ith which to fulfil orders when received. At the time tonekhaus was contemnlatin^ iakin j up the oxide trade (19(6) and makin : a contract with Hassan Sstaalyth {In seven years after the work had be^n jcinj on), the first thing he did was to visit the island and examine the several heaos of oxide lyin^ reedy for disposal (at least three different spots had been worked). After examining the heaps, which had probably been there for years, he entered into^cantract to buy the oxide f.o.b. (June 19u6). It was in August 1906 that we heard of it, and in 'ebruary 19w7 that the Sheikh of hargah cancelled the concession, to the best _________ ofof my belief very little if any mining went on after August 19^6, and noni? eareci ally for onckbaus. Katsan eirwply continued to kBep hi^ fooiii^ there *ith a few dig ere until ha -ma erivolled in October 1907. The ienaan? in their casR qui;tod The fact that the Company i» not in a position to extract at the Drop^r time the quantity which they mufit keep roady for deliteriee due in the coming months*. It i« to b© rofirobered that during the years 1899 to 1906 Raetian had been siinine: w»ll quaritities all the time but had sold very little, and that to India; at end that/the time hi a concession was cancelled there was oxide on the island which we now know fairly aocur- to ha^ve amountea bo 5000 u :&lt;c. ^one of thifi^ wtw ^ired aft^r the cancellation of thf? Concession (Oct» 19 7) and to the best of Wf belief, b.*-.s^d on erp«*rienc?. of the ol tht concern not moro than &amp;50 tons mined between Juna 190€ and Ccto&gt;&gt;er 19 7. rith reference therefore to mm. Uie doubtful T&gt;ointa raised in para, 9, (1) to the bt»«t of my recollection no shipmenit ?va:3 md« for onckhaua before the ^Louiee* shipment* Thio caxi b« verified at once frorji the i uehire reeerd if it is not on rocord here, ('0 .'o the best of m belief iieerly th^s ^holo, in ftnjr case the rizjorpropertuq &gt;r the oxide lyia^ on the ieland at the moment of the concession being cancelled bad be or minei before the cora isonc fmont of .onckhaus 1 s contract; and between the cowiencarrjent of onc^aus^ contract (June 190c) and tl^e crinceilation of the Conceasiion, not nwre than fttu tons was mined. I would lay stress on the fact that we allowed ^onckhaue to carryft i c&amp;xvy away the 'lined oxids in spite of proUst# from the oheikh of her ph and the othar concesaionnaire«, ^rimrilj: because is ajesty 1 * Cvrerjamni seemed to have u} durstood at the lima that it had bsm mined for «onckhau8 - *hich it had not-, but tmitly for the s acinic object of disjcountirv^ Wonckhman's claim for loaK of busine«a» A? a favour wb retired tha whole of the 521\ tone on the island to fonckhaui, so that he might not haTs the vrviwri that he had bo^n put to losa. In wy opinion, baying regard to the normal scale on ?rhich the rsinin: nn alway® carried on up to thB time of onckhaut'ji contract, knd which acala WonckhauB showod no inclination to modify, asBan mvaiyeh could not hafr mined wor^ than, and with ^reat difficulty as mneh aa, 2000 t^na par year; ^onckhaue merely stated a mriimin of 5000 tona in order to make quite sure that , T 's.»fian ahoulcl have none- to a pare for anyone cine. T -.et an prasunie that he could haY» taken 2tU: ton® mr year • fro Susrut 190C to Jane I9ii - 7 year*. then he would have taken l^OCC Was. In point of fact we hare ^iren him the opportunity of takia; 6000 odd tons» so he my conceivably ha?t lost the sale of 9 ,000 tons if t hart? web a -r iarket, but it is very doubtful if there was one. ''his figure is much the *cm na that at which the r ^ard of Yade arrive on different lines in para. 12, ara, 1^« 1 rocoa* tlml the 1) fonoation be obtained by tele- grain fron: Buehire, ami without reference to easrs* ./onckhaus. ^hen that is ottained I would su^^st that before we do anything further the expert views of 'r. vtrick be taken informally and confidentially as a preliminary:LiAK BAKATJP AQA BS^P, PiilS I'nBNCY 'AGENT AT DRAFT—(For Approval). P olitical R esidency , P ersian G ulf. N o. / &amp; Dated ^^4^ 4/ 191^, t ttvtrtt-f iu , l &gt; Fnile he was recently at London,the Hon'ble Sir Percy Cox discussed thd Abu Mnsa Question wit&gt;. the Hlqh Authorities there and submitted a note to them in regard 0 a certain conuriiinication addressed by the Boa^d of Trade to H.B.jI's Foreign Office in this connection. r -[e lad suggested that this note might be communicated to with a request that you will offe^ such corroboration R.n^ orrection as you can, A true translation of the note is forwarded here- iith,and I request you to read the same very carefully a.nd to write to me such views, and confirmation as you tiro are able t-o suggest.You are^ivell accuainted with the* ietails of this case to recmire any special instructions on the subject and I trust that you will be able to tamzxiixttaxx send me an answer at an early r:ate. Mai or Political Pesident in the ^evsian ^ulf.^ '^t'' H [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Govemment.] TURKEY. [February 11.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [6295] No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office.—(Received February 11.) Sir, India Office, February 10, 1914. I AM directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 30th January, enclosing copy of a letter from the Board of Trade regarding Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim to compensation in respect of Abu Musa oxide. The Marquess of Crewe has caused the telegram of which a copy is enclosed for Sir E. Grey's information to be addressed to the Government of India, asking for information on the two points raised by the Board of Trade in paragraph 9 of their letter, and calling for a list and value of any implements belonging to Messrs. Wonckhaus that may have been left on the island. His Lordship is advised that information on these points can probably be obtained from the Residency at Bushire, and he is of opinion that Messrs. Wonckhaus should not be asked for their version of the facts until at any rate a reply has been received from the Government of India. He would suggest also, for Sir E. Grey's consideration, that on receipt of this information it would be as well to obtain the expert views of Mr. Strick, informally and confidentially, on the merits of the substantial portion of Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim (vide paragraphs 6-12 of the Board of Trade's letter) and on the minor question of the alleged deterioration of the oxide shipped by the steamship 'Louise.' He would further suggest that perhaps the most convenient means of obtaining Mr. Strick's opinion would be to entrust this task to Sir P. Cox, who is available for the purpose and has an intimate local knowledge of the whole question. I am, &amp;c. T. W. HOLDERNESS. Enclosure in No. 1. The Marquess of Crewe to the Government of India. (Telegraphic.) P. India Office, February 9, 1914. PLEASE report by telegraph whether Messrs. Wonckhaus shipped any oxide from Abu Musa under their contract prior to the shipment made in April 1908 by steamship Louise' ; also whether any of the oxide ready mined when contract was cancelled had been mined before the 1st June, 1906, date of commencement of contract; also the list and value of the implements (from Hamburg-Amerika steamer) which Wonckhaus left on the island. (Repeated to Bushire.) [2034 1—2]V'* c- £ |p ' fio* . ? v \ im ^ // JMeniovanduni. &amp; vN^/ G x) f 1 ^ ^ The correspondence mentioned heloiv is herewith transmitted to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, ivith a view to avoiding delay in the event of the Foreign Department of the Government of India desiring to communicate with him on the subject. A copy of this memorandum and of the correspondence is also being communicated to that Department by to-day's mail. fi : Assistant Secretary, Political Department. INDIA OFFICE, 1~/ 191 L/-. m* I]- 1 *-', J* II in rtqufstcd that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to The Under Secretary of State for India. Political Department, India Office. London, S.W. P. 9:x INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W. 241b Varrb J 914 •Co: nica- ted to P . l , 7th Feb. 1914. Sir. &lt; it) reference to ry letter of the th February 1914, a). 1 ♦ o&lt;,b, reaDOcuin the /vbu usa xif^e rue«tiuri # I am Uirecoea 1/ a secretary ot i»t#ite i'or India to ©nciOBe, to be laid before the ecretary of tate for orei v i4 affaire, tra report of e private interview bpt»'t;&lt; n oir i ercy Cox an(j ir. . brick on thr eubjeet of ■j a are, lonckltauB^ rlaime to comocnpation. he iiitervi^, it should bo explained, took nlace before ir *. ^ox's dnnarturp lor India, ap the reeult of an infornal discueeion at tbie v ffioe in whicV membere of your svepurtment look part, it will be neon thai the inlerfiew o a private character, and that ir J-, Cox was careful not to com at Hie Kajeety's Uovernwent in any way. i he arqueaf* of Crewe would pu ; '.eat that a copy of the report should be coawunicated to the oard of rade, with reference to their letter of the 9th January last, and that the Board enould be atked to reviee, in the li jnt of r« trick'■ views anri of the criticiame contained in hir P. Co*'» note of the ( th ebruary *, th«ir reconmndatione as to the baisia ofi which eooqpeneation ehould he calrula- ted. he revieion mi ^t be carried out, if mcesaery, in coneuitation with ir, trick, who, it will be aeen, haa cxpresaed hia readinese to asaiat, Vin ' ajeety's Government in the matter, l4&gt;rd Crewe hopea that by tl ie means a suitable sum may be The Under Secretary of State, FOREIGN OFFICE.bp fixed in round figure which will bo &amp;cc opted by the firm in finat scttlaaont of thfiir 5rhole claim, and that t&gt;.o ref«r«ne« of the case to arbitration faay thus bo ; 'lave the honour to be, Cir, 'our jflost obediftDt servant, ^T-V.rcMtncss.ABU JU3A 0X1 UK J had a private talk with r. iitrick today regardirv; t: a Abu i uaa case. !he following is the giat of what passed. He is familiar with the history of the 1 eland and wifh th# calient facts of the Tesent case, but 1 just ^Te him a short roautfifc of then and wont on to Bay that we had agreed with the Cernan parties to settle the dispute by fr ienoiy coaiproKiise and that onckhaus had recently put i ; ' ^ i8 cleim * 5 mentioned that as 1 happened to be at home, ttevernment were asking for views or information from me regarding various points in issue, and although uy locfj I K'lor lei e enabled 'lie to answer so^se of ihdir queries. Uiere -'ere several points regarding which 1 should be '/cry .lad to check and fortify ary own knowledge or beliefs, by his export information. ] laid stress on the fact that i was referring to him quite privately and that he 'Bust Kindly regard our interview as a private and corJ iaential consultation between : r. Frank Strick and ^ir i . Cur. t o reaiily assented but asked me to let his assist- ant, r. olmes, join us aa he was the best acquainted with the subject. . r «i »ad thm the heads of ^onckhaun's claim - then I nsad liaeaan oaaaiyeh'i sUtscent, vhey entirely corro borated the assertions to the affect that the oxide does not deteriorate, an: that a protective crust naturally foraa on it. hoy also stated that no protective cover- in sue- as planks or tarpaulin was ever used or neededii for i:ormu2 txide. They corroborated 'assarts rcrtiarks as wo the paucity 0l ^ spac:- and inar.'ility to eniploy naore than or 6w iien under present conditions. : r Strick was inclined to think that the miner Cride improved rather than deter iorated from keeping • and incidentally, (speaking off Kand&gt; he was sceptical of ! assan havinf: disposed of any thing like ; ,tU tone of the stuff, as alleged. They believed that their records would aho» all the German shipments. questioned re ^ardin^ the pointo specified in nara. U oi the J oard of ; J rade letter of 9th January 1914, they expreiBed the view tliat prices would certainly have become eureeued by the addition of e supply from Abu Hosa. They stated that they could give ali the necnss- ary iaforaaUun regarding average freight, if.surance and comnussion duri% tiny particular period by reference to their records and expressed the opinion that unless they hud orked the mine on on entirely different and more expert basis the concesaionnaires could not have got more tnan 2,otO tone and probably not as ouch. Inally that none of the Abu . usa uxid. subseouently shipned oarac up to the rirat 8hip'..ent (ItolzonfelB ?) ii, quality. aving got ao fur, i reaiinded sr. i'trick of the purely private character of our present conversation, but continued that 1 should like to surest to 'is a Jetty 's orei^ office that they should consult him themaelves. ould he have any objection to bein ; consulted or givin,/ testimony as an expert sitness? Fe replied that he would have nu Ji jecliori *;':atever - he would be happy to do ao. Ahen told the rouf^h figures of essre. onckhaus's cbim (working out to about 16,000) both he arid r. ndbtes expressedexpressed the opinion that it vbr extravagant and would not bear inveati Ration. r. .trick said 'adviae Joveru* rnont to offer bim 25 ner c^nt of that and then spring a •thousani or two if nocR3«ary. inally : r, itrick aaid that they could call a Or. or I rofoenor ?u . who was scientifically expert in te»tin ; . the quality of oxide, and in all niattors conuec- ted with the mineral. r, trick (rhoee jehire /igent ^r. alcola waa for ierly ono of the Abu )&lt;uoa Concession aires) has shipped ...bu usa Uxid« himself and has on record preoiae descriptions of the deposits; chnrts of the island and probably ?aucb infonaation that would be useful. would be inclined to recommend in view of the abore, that r # alkin meet t . t trick or ncrhaoe prefer ably r. olrcec, and .^o through the papers with him, see in regard to what points they could gire help, artd then see what their records can produce that would be of%%) Buohir©, 18th April 1914. Dear Sir Percy You will recollect having wtltten to me on board the P &amp; 0 regarding the Abu Musa oxide question. I have since had another search made through the records and we have unearthed the accompanying letter and statement of •Isa bin 'Ab^ul Latif which seems to be the nearest thing to the lfc»t of shipments you recollect# It was, as you see, written in 1908 and though it does not contain anything very precise. It ■ erves to confirm the genirral idea that most of the oxide was excavated before Hasan contracted with Wonok- haua. It certainly mentions that 'the list of his ship ments, as reported to us by him and others, is recorded with ua and its quahtity is 8000 tona w . But we have no trace of that list and I do not know how far it can be relied on# The figures, in view of Aqa Badr's renort given in my No. 347 of 25th March, 1914, seem exaggerat ed and I do not know how far anything that emanates from those sources, ♦Abdul Latif and his family could be re lied on* It would however if thought advisable be easy to quote 'Isa^ letter to him and ask for that list. Would you kindly let me know if you think this should be done. Yours sincerely, (sd) S.G# Knox Sec .w~&lt;U/ JHHHDRAFT—(For Approval). Political Residency, Persian Gulf. No.JM_ Dated ^ igif ro:- Tiffi PBSI^ENCT irsOT AT A» O • 9 SHAPOAH. In a statement dated 17th Maharram 1^26, Di-n Abdul Latif in connection with, the red 03 3n the Abu Musa island,the following passage 'Since tne beginning of tne lease up to b.is contract with Y'onckhaus ,the r erman Jiaj i gently shipped oxide to Bombay♦ Calcutta,etc: ♦ forming us as he ought according to what had '3d,but if we heard regarding the shipment and about it,he would then inform us of it. Hct: lis shipments as reported to us by hi^ and otlji corded with us and its quantity is 3000 tons made by Isa :ide question Occurs:- .ne date of s an has fre thout in- T^een stipulate aslred him. 1 he list of ers,is re- iiDDrox imate 1V. 1 Emd let me have as early as Doasibe^l list of the shipments togetM I should be glad if you will mal^e encuiries from Isa e and ful1 jr with all cm.TDle details in regard to the same Major Political Pesident in the Persian 'ulf,TflB PESinENGY A r BNT AT LINCSH. A.G • 9 I write to remind you about the Pesident' be good enough, to send aVreply^j^gfl^; DRAFT—(For Approval). P olitical R esidency , P ersian G ulf. No. $ Dated ^ 191^ 34 dated the loth April 1.^14,forwarding a translation of he Note submitted by the Hon'ble ^ir Pemy Cc Foreign Office in London on the sub.jectof the mines on the Abu Musa island, and to request j. 3° s letter Fo x to the red oxide that you will Captain, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian r ulf. 'oy)/ .yDated the loth May 1914) (Confidential). From— M ajor S. G. K nox , C.I .E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. I enclose a translation of Residency Agent at Lingah's remarks on your note of 6th February 1914, a copy of which has been sent to Hirtzel. Urgent enquiries are being made from Isa through the Residency Agent at Sharjah as regards the shipments of oxide mentioned by the former in his statement of 20th February 1908. (Translation of the remarks offered by the Residency Agent at Lingah.) The Aha Musa question, —As to the fact that the exalted British Govern ment refuse to recognise Wonckhaus as a member of the company of conces- sionnaires or to discuss any claims based on that pretention, this is most advisable, because Wonckhaus , contract with Hassan bin Somaiyah was Only for this purpose that when Wonckhaus sent any steamers for the shipment of oxide, Hassan bin Somaiyah should deliver the stuff f.o.b. by his own lighters : and WoncKhaus has absolutely no right to interfere with the shore and the mines. (As regards the intention) (a) to pay direct losses, (d) to pay a lump sum for the loss of work occasioned to them. In connection with (a), the remarks made by the Hon'ble Sir Percy Cox are correct. In addition to them, I deem it incumbent upon me to represent those facts of which I am well aware. Hassan biu Somaiyah's allegation for the loss of certain articles on the island has been made at the instigation of the members of the firm of Wonckhaus, so that the latter may obtain the means of interfering with this question and supporting the unfounded claim of Hassan bin Somaiyah. It is obvious that Wonckhaus had absolutely no right to interfere with the internal affairs of the island and the working of the oxide mines, so that he may possess any implements on the island. At the time when the exalted British Government gave permission for the shipment of oxide by the S. S. ' Louise ' r I was commissioned to the Aba Musa island to supervise all the matters connected with this affair. There were four iron measuring buckets (on the island), two of them being large and the others a little smaller: and these were intended to be used in weighing oxide on board the ' Louise ' to ascertain the quantity shipped. When the shipment of oxide *was finished, I desired to weigh (the contents of each of) those buckets on toard the Louise ' and Hassan bin Somaiyah agreed to this in the beginning, but when we were about to weigh them, he disagreed at the instisation of the Manager of the Firm of Wonckhaus and Mirza Husain the Dragoman, who were on board the steamer, and replied that they would haye them weighed at Lingah. Two of the four buckets—one large and the other small—were brought by them to Lingah by the ' Louise but they again disagreed to have them weighed at Lingah, and they (therefore) only estimated the weight of the oxide shipped by the ' Louise The other two measuring buckets which remained on the island formed parts of the articles delivered by me to Hassan bin Somaiyah when the gears were brought to Lingah from the island— for which I obtained a receipt, dated the 12th Safar 1331 (20th January 1913), from Hassan bin Somaiyah, the original of which exists in the Bushire Resi dency. In the course of the shipment of oxide by the S. S. ' Louise', four planks of wood were used as landings to facilitate the shipment of oxide by the lighters, and when the articles were brought over to Lingah from the island, I delivered three of the four planks to Hassan bin Somaiyah and took a receipt, dated 4ith Rabi-ui-Awal 1331 (11th February 1913), from him which isnvailable in the Bushire Kesidency. The remaining one of the four planks was removed from the island by a certain Muhammad bin Fahad by order and permission of Hassan bin Somaiyah : and if the latter denies this, it would be possible to demand the same from Muhammad bin Fahad. The yalue of each plank may amount to Us. 20 at the most. In the face of these facts and of the existence of receipts, there is no necessity to make any reference to Hassan bin Somaiyah's account books, which have been cooked by the members of the firm of Wonckhaus since the cancellation of the concession and which continue to remain in the said firm up to now. Under these circumstances, how do the British Government agree to pay compensation for such articles which have been taken over by Hassan bin Somaiyah and for which he has passed receipts ? With reference to the question of the deterioration of oxide, the facts are as stated by the Hon'ble Sir Percy Cox. The works on the oxide mines in this Gulf began with the Hormuz island and then with the island of Abu Musa : and the system of work is this— Any quantity of oxide excavated from the mines is collected in heaps without being stored in godowns or covered with anything. It remains under the sun, moisture, dew, rain and air for years and undergoes no change at all, because the margins of the heaps are so hardened by dew and moisture in the beginning that the air does not affect it at all, and it remains preserved. As regards the explanation given by the Hon'ble Sir Percy Cox regarding the original concessionnaires, it is the true position (of the case), and I beg to represent the information I possess in this connection. While negotiating the contract with Hassan bin Somaiyah, Wonckhaus proceeded to the island and approved of some oxide, but, in point of fact, the oxide excavated since the date of the contract (June 1906) which was made by Hassan bin Somaiyah with Wonckhaus up to the date when the Shaikh of Sharjah cancelled the con cession, was not over 500 tons approximately : and this was also shipped in the course of the shipments made by the S. S. 44 Teutonia ' and 4&lt; Louise ' because it was Hassan bin Somaiyah's principal object and desire to get rid of those heaps of oxide remaining on the island which had been excavated 5-6 years before the contract of June 1906. As a matter of fact, the oxide remaining on the island is the remainder of the former heaps which had been mined within the aforesaid period before the contract of June 1906. Portions of these heaps were shipped by the steamers enumerated below and the remainder exists there. It is certain that there is no oxide on the Abu Musa island which had been especially mined for Wonckhaus. In regard to the doubtful points contained in paragraph 9, according to the records and copies of the Agency reports which had been submitted to the Residency at the time of shipments, the following shipments have been made On the 25th March 1906, before Hassan bin Somaiyah's contract with Wonckhaus, the S. S. ' Muhammadi'' of the Bombay and Persia Steam Navi gation Company shipped 700 tons which were transhipped at Karachi for Hamburg. On the 2nd June 1907, the S. S. 44 Naseri ' of the Bombay-Persia Steam Navigation Company shipped 6,000 bags = 300 tons of oxide which were transhipped at Bombay for Hamburg. On the 16th July 1907, the S. S. ' Teutonia'' of the Hamburg-Amerika Line shipped 900 tons for Hamburg. This ship was lost with the oxide. On the 9th-16th April 1908, the S. S. ^Louise' of the Hamburg-Amerik^ Line shipped 1,810 tons for Hamburg. It becomes clear from the shipment made by S. S.' Muhammadi' that the oxide available on the Abu Musa island had not been mined specially for Wonckhaus and also that most of the o^ide shipped by S. S. 14 Teutonia' and ' Louise' was from the heups mined before the contract of June 1906 con* eluded by Hassan with Wonckhaus. From the date of the contract made in June 1906 up to the date of the cancellation of the concession by the Shaikh of Sharjah, only the aforesaid quantity of about 500 tons had been mined and shipped iji the course of the shipments; made by S,. S. ' Teutonic' aad „ Louise ' as I have represented above.In connection with (5), regarding the payment of a lump sum for the loss of work occasioned to them, I am unable to represent anything as I am not aware of the facts concerning the payment of compensation. But I beg to state the information I have obtained in regard to the arrangement between Hassan bin Somaiyah and Wonckhaus. It was this : whenever Wonckhaus contemplated to ship oxide, Hassan bin Somaiyah used to take from him a sufficient sum for the expenses of the coolies and the lighters; and they used to settle the account of the value of oxide without delay as soon as they finished shipment, and left no account to remain pending between them. In regard to the question dealt with in the Note. I be^ to represent certain facts below, so that you may include the same if you deem it fit to do so. With regard to the original concessionnaires. As the original concession obtained by Hassan bin Somaiyah from the Shaikh of Sharjah in 1898 was not based on the Laws of the Shar'a (legal) or the Urfi (civil) Courts, which are the basis for all commercial and other transactions in this Gulf, local difficulties arose for the Shaikh of Sharjah, and the latt o r cancelled the concession under these circumstances. In the same way that the aforesaid Courts considered the Sliaikh of Sharjah justified in this, it follows that the contract made by Hassan bin Somaiyah with Wonckhaus in June 1906 is of the same nature (as the original concession, and must be treated as such). At the time when the Shaikh of Sharjah gave the notice of cancellation to Hassan bin Somaiyah and Co., the oxide remaining on the island was the right of the Shaikh of Sharjah and the concessionnaires had no title whatever therein. As the original concession was not in conformity with the current laws, it was null and void from the beginning. If the Shaikh of Sharjah's cancellation of the concession held by Hassan bin Somaiyah and Co. was without any justification, the concession naires would have had some w r ay to dispute it. It is understood from the Note that Wonckhaus claims that Hassan bin Somaiyah used specially to mine 2,000 tons oxide per annum and to prepare it for shipment, and that there was a good price for the stuff in market, and that Wonckhaus has incurred a loss owing to the prohibition. To answer Wonckhaus's claim. From the date of the contract made in June 1906 by Hassan bin Somaiyah with Wonckhaus up to the 16th July 1907, has been a period of 13| months, and there was no obstacle, in any way, during this period for Hassan bin Somaiyah and Wonckhaus. In the course of that time they shipped only two consignments—one of 300 tons by the S. S. Naseri ' on the 2nd June 1907, the whole of which was from the oxide mined 5-6 years before the contract on June 1906, and the other of 900 tons by the S. S. •* Teutonia ' on the 16th July 1907—most of which was from the oxide mined 5-6 years prior to the contract of June 1906 and some of which was from the oxide excavated in the course of the said contract as I have stated above, and nothing more was shipped. Had there been any truth in his claim, how could he be satisfied with these two consignments ? It is clear that neither Hassan bin Somaiyah could have mined and prepared that quantity, nor was the stuff in demand. When Wonckhaus shipped those two consignments, he had other objects and intentions. Further, it is certain that both these two consignments were from out of the former heaps as has been stated above. Under these circumstances, how can it be admitted that Wonckhaus required 2,000 tons oxide per annum and that there was a good market for the stuff and further that he could have been supplied and Hassan bin Somaiyah could have mined and prepared (that quantity) ? Had this been the case, why did Wonckhaus not take 2,000 tons of oxide from Hassan bin Somaiyah during the 13$ months when there was nothing to prevent both parties ? This point fully explains the nature of the said claim. If the exal'ed British Government intend to settle the case by paying Wonckhaus a certain sum with a view to preventing the matter to drag on for a long time and putting a stop to Wonckhaus* interference with this question, it would be good, if the sum is not great. Tprtlgn A PoltL D»pt, Prwi-vNo. 2i9—20-5-14—44.— •• 1 1 s [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] - : '6 TURKEY. CONFIDENTIAL. [April l .J Section 2. [13248 No. 1. Foreign Office to Board of Trade. Sir, Foreign Office, April 1, 1914. WITH reference to your letter of the 9th January regarding Messrs. Wonckhans and Co.'s claim to compensation in connection with the Abu Musa oxide question, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you the accompanying copy of a report of a private interview between Sir P. Cox and Mr. Strick on the subject. 0 The interview took place before Sir P. Cox's departure for India, as the result of an informal discussion at the India Office, in which members of this Department took part. It was of a private character, and Sir P. Cox was careful not to commit His Majesty's Government in any way. Sir E. Grey would be grateful if the Board would be so good as to revise in the light of Mr. Strick's views and of the criticism contained in Sir P. Cox's note of the 6th February (of which a copy was forwarded to your Department on the 10th of that month) their recommendations as to the basis on which compensation should be calculated, I he revision might be carried out, if necessary, in consultation with Mr. Strick, who, it will be seen, has expressed his readiness to help His Majesty's Government in the matter. The only other expert whose name occurs to Sir E. Grey is Mr. M. Ellinger, but there would be obvious difficulties in approaching him on the subject while he is connected with the Muin-ut-Tujjar in the Hormuz oxide case. ' The Marq uess of Crewe entertains the hope—which is shared by Sir E. Grey— that by the above procedure it may be possible to fix a suitable sum in round figures which will be accepted by Messrs. Wonckhaus in final settlement of their whole claim, and that the reference of the case to arbitration may thereby be avoided. In conclusion, I am to enclose herein, with reference to paragraph 9 of your letter under reply, a paraphrase of a telegram from His Majesty's consul-general at Bushire, :&amp; from which it will be seen (a) that three shipments of oxide were made from the island before the ' Louise shipment of April 1908, and (6) that much oxide mined prior to the 1st June, 1906, was still unshipped when the cancellation of the contract took place. I am, &amp;c. EYRE A. CROWE. [2098 a—2] * Not printed.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government.] TURKEY. [April 1.] OONFIDEN i IAL. S ection 2. [Amended Copy.] [13248] No. 1. Foreign Office to Board of Trade. Sir&gt; Foreign Office, April 1, 1914. WITH reference to your letter of the 9th January regarding iMessrs. Wonckhaus and Co.'s claim to compensation in connection with the Atm Musa oxide question, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you the accompanying copy of a report of a private interview between Sir P. Cox and Mr. Strick on the subject. The interview took place before Sir P. Cox's departure for India, as the result of an informal discussion at the India Office, in which members of this Department took part. It was of a private character, and Sir P. Cox was careful not to commit His Majesty's Government in any way. ^ Sir L. (^rey would be grateful if the Board would be so good as to revise in the light of Mr. Strick's views and of the criticism contained in Sir P. Cox's note of the 6th February (of which a copy was forwarded to your Department on the 10th of that month) their recommendations as to the basis on which compensation should be calculated. The revision might be carried out, if necessary, in consultation with Mr. Strick, who, it will be seen, has expressed his readiness to help His Majesty's Government in the matter. The only other expert whose name occurs to Sir E. Grey is Mr. M. Ellinger, but there would be obvious difficulties in approaching him on the subject while he is connected with the Muin-ut-Tujjar in the Hormuz oxide case. The Marquess of Crewe entertains the hope—which is shared by Sir E. Grey that by the above procedure it may be possible to fix a suitable sum in round figures which will be accepted by Messrs. Wonckhaus in final settlement of their whole claim, and that the reference of the case to arbitration may thereby be avoided. In conclusion, I am to enclose herein, with reference to paragraph 9 of your letter under reply, a paraphrase of a telegram from His Majesty's consul-general at Bushire, from which it will be seen (a) that three shipments of oxide were made from the island before the ' Louise ' shipment of April 1908. and (6) that much oxide mined prior to the 1st June, 190G, was still unshipped when the cancellation of the contract took place. I am, &amp;c. EYRE A. CROWE. Enclosure I in No. 1. Ahu Musa Oxide.—Aote by Sir P. Cox on a Conversation with Mr. Strick. (Private.) 1 HAD a private talk with Mr. Strick to-day regarding the Abu Musa case. The following is the gist of what passed :— He is familiar with the history of the island, and with the salient facts of the present case, but I just gave him a short resume of them, and went on to say that we had agreed with the German parties to settle the dispute by friendly compromise, and that Wonckhaus had recently put in his claim. I mentioned that as I happened to be at home. Government were asking for views or information from me regarding various points in issue, and although my local knowledge enabled me to answer some of their queries, there were several points regarding which I should be very glad to check, and fortify my own knowledge or beliefs, by his expert information.' I laid stress on the fact that I was referring to him quite privately, and that he must kindly regard our interview as a private and confidential consultation between Mr. Frank Strick and Sir P. Cox. He readily assented, but asked me to let his assistant, Mr. Holmes, join us as he was the best acquainted with the subject. [2098 a—2]I read them the heads of Wonckhaus's claim—then 1 read 1 lassan Samaiyeh s statement. They entirely corroborated the assertions to the effect that the oxidedoes not deteriorate, and that a protective crust naturally forms on it. 1 hey also stated that no protective covering, such as planks or tarpaulin, was ever used oi needed ior Hormuz oxide. . ... They corroborated Hassan's remarks as to the paucity of digging space, and inability to employ more than fifty or sixty men under present conditions^ Ah. btiick was inclined to think that the mined oxide improved rather than deterioiated fiom keeping—and incidentally (speaking off hand), he was sceptical of Hassan having disposed of anything like 20,000 tons of the stuff, as alleged. 1 hey believed that their records would show all the German shipments. i f rp i Questioned regarding the points specified in paragraph 13 of the Board of irade letter of the 9th January, 1914, they expressed the view that prices would certainly have become depressed by the addition of a supply from Abu Musa. I hey stated that they could give all the necessary information regarding average freight, insurance, and commission, during any particular period by reference to their records, and expicssed the opinion that unless they had worked the mine on an entirely dillerent and more expert basis the concessionnaires could not have got more than 2,000 tons, and probably not as much. Finally, that none of the Abu Musa oxide subsequently shipped came up to the first shipment [? Stolzenfels] in quality. Having got so far, I reminded Mr. Strick of the purely private character oi our present conversation, but continued that T should like to suggest to His Majesty s Foreign Office that they should consult him themselves. Would he have any objection to being consulted or giving testimony as an expert witness ? He replied, that he would have no objection whatever—he would be happy to do so. ^ hen told the rough figures of Messrs. Wonckhaus's claim (working out to about 16,000L), both he and Mr. Holmes expressed the opinion that it was extravagant, and would not bear investigation. Mr. Strick said, ' advise Government to offer him 25 per cent, of that, and then spring a thousand or two, if necessary.' Finally, Mr. Strick said that they could call a doctor or professor, A. B., who was scientifically expert in testing the quality of oxide, and in all matters connected with the mineral. Mr. Strick (whose Bushire agent, Mr. Malcolm, was formerly one of the Abu Musa concessionnaires), has shipped Abu Musa oxide himself, and has on record precise descriptions of the deposits; charts of the island, and probably much information that would be useful. I would be inclined to recommend in view of the above that Mr. Malkin meet Mr. Strick, or perhaps preferably Mr. Holmes, and go through the papers with him, see in regard to what points they could give help, and then see what their records can produce that would be of assistance. P. z COX. March 11, 1914. Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Major Knox to Government of India. (Telegraphic.) P. Bushire, March 25, 1914. PLEASE refer to the Secretary of State's telegram of 20th February regarding oxide. I transmit the results of enquiries which were made at Lingah. The answer to the first question is :— March 25, 1906.—Bombay-Persia steamship ' Muhamm '; 700 tons for tran shipment Karachi for Hamburg. June 2, 1907.—Bombay-Persia steamship ' Nasrias ' ; 300 tons for transhipment Bombay for Hamburg. July 10, 1907.—Hamburg-Amerika steamship ' Teutonia'; 500 tons for Hamburg. April 10, 1908.—Hamburg-Amerika steamship ' Louise ' ; 1,810 tons. The answer to the second question is that a great deal of the oxide that was mined before the contract of 1st June, 190G, was entered upon was still lying at Abu Musa at the time of cancellation of the contract.No 101 nirbei 3th June 1^14 PROM: - TO:- TiE Pj3SI T )ENC v ArEINT &gt;T STiAPJAH. TH3 POLITICAL PSSI^BNT IN TOD PBPSI^N r ULF, A.C. , of t I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt your letter No223 dated Fth May 1014 regarding the consignments of oxide sent by f iaji Hasan bin Som.aiJ'eh from the mines on the Abus Musa island. I beg most respectfully to represent to you tHat I have made inquiries from Isa bin Abdul Latif ^bou' the said consignments ,and that I ha TT e o^tair.^d from him a list of the consignments of which he was infd^.- ed by Haji Hasan afore-said: and you will find the same herewith, (^e^is of the consignments:-) Consignments sent to London to a pa^ty whom Isa do^s not know. Consignments sent to Bombay,some of them to one named iiaji Salman; and some to Yusuf bin Ibrahim, Al-Yusufian Atub Arab,of Bombay. Consignments sent to the firm of 'Havid Sassoon in Cal cutta. U-O Consignment sent to iCaracJii^the agent there being un known to Isa. Two consignments sent to Hamburg to Wonckhaus ,the Ger man. All the above-mentioned consignments of oxide were sen: abroad from Abu Musa by Haji Hasan bin Somaiyieh with out the permission and(previous)knowledge of Isa bin Abdul Latif. Subsequent to the above consignments.Ha&amp;i Hasan bin Somaiyeh concluded a contract,of his own ao^o^d, with Wonekhuas,the fwrman,without the permission ajid consent of the partners. Since the date of the cont ract up to now,Isa bin /bdul Latif does not know t! quantity of the oxide sold by Haji Hasan to r *onckh the German. It is possible that Tigrane Malcolm,who is onfe of the partners in the oxide business,possesses more in formation than Isa bin Abdul Latif(in this connection) i.e aus^4 s (0-6) 196-4,000-7-13-(K2*) Spl—Resident Persian Gulf 2 (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) (TPANSLATIQK OF BICCTOSTIEB. ) . LIST showing the consignments of oxile sent abroad by Hasan bin Somaiyeh from the mines on the Abu Musa is lane, from the year 1316 to 13^0(1303-1.10^) 000000 aj 1 Consignment sent by S.SVArabistan to London t ) o —-— ex S.S. 'Seorate'(. ; ) Scar0dale(f) to London, Consignment sent to Bombay by sailing ^raft. Consignment sent to Bombay by sailing craft Do sent to Bombay by S.S.Henry Balkou T)0 sm t to Bombay B.P.S. j ; t . Co 's s te3mer 47 /i i'\n 9FC) TOOO T2C) .^70 '00 2000 Consignment sent to Karachi by sailing craft. r 0 Consignment sent to Calcutta by S.S. ,, Lond r, e ,, 300 Do-- sent to Calcutta by S.S. T ''arda. 2000 Sold to Wonckhaus the Cerman, . ^ '00. Consignment sent to Hamburg through 'Wonckhaus the ' r 'erman 00 &gt; 011° 0. TgOO Perhaps Haji Hasan bin Somaiyeh has sent more than the nbo^p but Isa bin Abdul Latif's information goes so far.All tl^e consignments described above come up to ''400 Tons. (Signed)Abdul Latif, lihan Bahadur, Residency agent in the Trucial Oman. m rji[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Ma,iesty s Government.^ TURKEY. L June 11.j CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. [26237] No. 1. Board of Trade to Foreign Office.—{Tieceived June 11.) Sir, . Board of Trade, June 10, 1914. WITH reference to your letter of the 1st April, regarding the Abu Musa oxide question, I am directed by the Board of Trade to state, for Sir E. Grey's information, that they have been in consultation with Mr. Strick on the subject generally, and particularly in regard to certain points (shown in the accompanyirg questionnaire*y A which was submitted to Mr. Strick), the determination of which appeared to them necessary before anv reasonable estimate could be framed of the snm to be offered as compensation to Messrs. WonckhauK The enclosed memorandum, which has been prepared in this Department, contains an account of an interview with Mr. Strick, who was accompanied by Mr. Holmes, together with certain observations on the information supplied by those gentlemen. The last three paragraphs of the memorandum contain references to points on which it was not necessary to consult Mr. Strick, but which have been included for the sake of completeness. Sir E. Grey will observe that in the light of the further information now available, the Board are disposed to think that an offer of 3,000?. would not be unreasonable as a complete settlement of Messrs. Wonckhaus's cluims. I am, &amp;c. GEO. J. STANLEY. Enclosure in No. 1. Memorandum respecting Aha Musa Oxide. Mr. Strick, accompanied by Mr. Holmes, called at this office on the 20th May ; two letters on this subject, copies of which are appended to this memorandum, had previously been received from him. In the course of this interview Mr. Strick confirmed the information contained in his letters, and further elucidated certain points. 1. Mr. Strick and Mr. Holmes again laid stress on the fact that oxide does not deteriorate by being left unprotected for long periods. Indeed, its quality is even said to improve as a result of the evaporation in such circumstances of the moisture which is present after it has been mined ; and Mr. Holmes would be prepared, if desired, to adduce expert evidence in support of this contention. As regards the admixture of sand in the ' Louise shipment, Mr. Strick explained that such admixture is to be attributed solely to the primitive methods of mining carried on at Abu Musa, and is not to be accounted for by exposure on the sea shore. It appears that the ' mines ' are in the nature of open workings, and the practice has been to excavate the vein of oxide without regard to the overlying strata, with the conse- quence that there have been frequent falls of sand and stones from the ' roof ' ot the vein—the debris being allowed to remain mixed with the oxide or only imperfectly removed. Incidentally it may be noted that the damage to the ' mines' indicated in item (3) of the claims set out in Messrs. Wonckhaus's letter of the 10th March, 1913, to the German Foreign Office was evidently due to these piimitive methods of working, and could not, therefore, properly form the ground of a claim against His Majesty's Government, even if they were disposed (which they are not) to recognise Messrs. Wonckhaus as partners in the Concessionnaire Company. Mr. Strick and Mr. Holmes were accordingly emphatic in their opinion that Messrs. Wonckhaus's claims as regards the deterioration of the ' Louise ' shipment are wholly unfounded. Indeed they regard that shipment as a fair sample of the quality of oxide ordinarily derivable irom the Abu Musa mines. 2. As regards the quantity of oxide capable of being shipped from Abu Musa in a [2165 Z—2] * Not printed.2 year Mr. Strick considers that this could not exceed 2,000 tons, or the minimum quantity stipulated for in Messrs. Wonckhaus's contract of 1906. Mr Holmes explained that shipping arrangements at Abu Musaare more primitive, it possible than the mining methods themselves. There is nothing but an open roadstead and the oxide lias apparently to be shipped from boats pushed out from the shore by native&amp;\ a mode o procedure which renders it impossible to ship more than 10 tons a day at the outside. On account of the heat prevalent during a laige part of the year and variations in weather conditions, it is not possible to allow for more than 200 days during \\ nc i shipping operations can be carried on. ^ ^ It Ts apparent, therefore, that during the unexpired period of their contract (two years and eight months) Messrs. Wonckhaus could not have expected to ship more than 5,500 tons of oiide. . „ , • • t v j i „ ^ 3. It has already been stated that the ''Louise shipment is beheved to have represented a fair sample of average Abu Musa oxide. It is true that Messrs. Wonckhaus stipulated in their contract that the oxide should be of the 'same quality as the 700 tons shipped by Mr. Robert Wonckhaus' in March, 1906 (i.e., the trial, shipment by the steamship ' Stolzenfels '), which it is claimed was sold at an average price ot 6o 5 . per ton. Mr. Strick is, however, at a loss to understand how this oxide could have been sold for more than 555. per ton, which would be a lair price tor the very best qualitv of oxide producible in Abu Musa, which can only be procured in extremely limited quantities from one small working. He is positive that 60s. a ton could not have been obtained for it, unless it was sold at infrequent intervals and in very sma quantities as the exigencies of demand might permit. Indeed, 65s. is the price ot Hormuz oxide, which^being the finest qualitv on the market, is considerably superior to the best quality of Abu Musa oxide referred to above. Had a large amount ot inferior oxide from Abu Musa been brought into competition with the Hormuz supp y the sale price of the latter would, in Mr. Strick's opinion, have been speedily reduced, with the result that Abu Musa oxide would have been displaced, and lett on i less is. Wonckhaus's hands. The market, it is alleged,*can only absorb from 6,000 to 7,000 tons of oxide a vear from all quarters. . , 1 , The selling price of Abu Musa oxide in Germany, according to Mr. fetnck, would be about 40s. a ton. Even that price could, in his opinion, only be maintained with difficulty, having regard especially to the length of time (over two years) which elapsed before Messrs. Wonckhaus were able to sell the 1810 tons which they shipped by the - Louise '—a delay in no wise to be accounted for by inferiority of quality ot that- particular shipment, but (as has already been indicated) by the limited character ot t e market for oxide and the competition of the Hormuz output. , , • ]A 1 In the light of these statements it appears to the Board that it would be unreasonable to frame an estimate of the compensation to be paid to Messrs. W one khans on any other basis than the average selling p' ice in Germany ot Abu Musa oxide 40s. a ton. To take as a basis the price of 65s. a ton (that claimed by Messrs. vv onckhaus as the selling price of the trial shipment) or even 55s. a ton (the highest price at which, in Mr. Strick's view, any Abu Musa oxide could be sold in Germany, when moreover only a very small quantity of oxide of this quality is to be found on the island at all) would seem to be extravagant. In any event, if Messrs. Wonckhaus have any claim at all (on the strength of their contract) in respect of a higher price than 40s. a ton such claim would appear to lie against Hassan Samaiya who led them to believe that large deposits of good quality oxide existed on the island, and not against His Majesty s Government. TT , -ir • i &gt; j x: v 4. As regard's freight charges from Abu Musa to Hamburg, Mr. btnek s detimte assertion is that 17s. 6^. should be allowed for this item and not los. the amount quoted by Messrs. Wonckhaus in respect of the trial shipment of the otolzentels which has already been referred to. The statement in which among others this item is given, formed one of the enclosures in the Foreign Office's letter ot the 14th October last. Mr. Strick is prepared to accept Messrs. Wonckhaus's figures lor the other items as a basis on .which the average cost of Abu Musa oxide c.i.f. Hamburg may :»e calculated. . .. „ u i . 5. The question whether, and how far the price of oxide generally would have been depressed by the addition of an annual supply of 2,000 tons of the Abu Musa produce to the world's supply is of course somewhat intangible. Mr. btnek, however, is confident that such au appreciable depression would have occurred, that he considers it is extremely doubtful whether Messrs. Wonckhaus could possibly have carried out their contract at a profit had it been permitted to run. Had the firm shipped anything like 2,000 tons a year and attempted to sell this quantity in competitionwith the much superior produce of the Hormuz mines, the price it could have secured would have been so low as to render the venture almost unremunerative and Messrs. Wonckhaus would probably have had large stocks left on their hands whic i thev could onlv have unloaded very gradually even at the low price obtainable in these circumstances Mr. Strick considers it inconceivable that _ Messrs. one aus would have availed themselves of the renewal clause ol their contract; indeed, financially, he thinks they may deem themselves fortunate to have had their contract terminated after one year and four months of its operation. If this is anything like an accurate statement of the facts, it would seem that Messrs Wonckhaus cannot reasonably look for compensation in respect of the renewal clause of their contract It is'now possible to estimate the amount of compensation which may be allowed to Messrs. Wonckhaus on the basis of the foregoing, ihe c.i.f. price per ton ot Abu Musa oxide at Hamburg may be calcula ed as follows . Per Ton (of 20 cwt.) s. d. 15 O'O Cost price f.o.b. Abu Musa as per contract .. .. • • • • 1^7. Freight—17s. Gr?.—less 5 per cent, commission .. • • ' 0 3-6 Marine insurance | per rent, of 40s. .. • • 0 9*0 Discharging ' , ■ ' ^ ' ' ' 0 4-8 Discount 1 per cent, on sale price, 40s. .. • • • • • • Total 33 6*9 The average sale price being 40s., the net profit per ton on this basis would be 6s. 5-Ard., or a profit of 1,7131 6s. id. on the total of a,333J tons. That this estimate is a fair one, is illustrated by the fact that Mr. stuck consiueis a nrofit of 20 per cent, on the selling price to be excellent and more than could ordinarily be expected. The compensation allowed to Messrs. Wonckhaus on the above basis is equivalent to a profit of over 15 per cent, on the cost price. The estimate moreover takes no account of the fact that Messrs. Wonckhaus have been allowed to remove large quantities of oxide since the termmation of theu contract. It appears from information supplied by the Foreign Office and the India Otbce that, excluding two shipments of 700 tons each by the •'Stolzenfels ' and the ' Muhamm which were made in March 1906 (i .e., before the commencement of the contract) and excluding also a shipment of 400 tons in May 1910. by the Nasin apparently for Hassan s account, the shipments of oxide made by Messrs. Wonckhaus since the commencement of this contract were as follows . ■■ Date. Vessel. Quantity. June 2. 1907.. July 16, 1907 April, 1908 .. *May, 1911 .. : November 14, 1912 Total ' Nasiri' .. ' Tentonia ' ' Louise . (?) (?) .. Tons. 300 500 (? 900) 1,810 300 300 3,210 (? 3,610) _ ' U least 3,210 tons were, therefore, shipped by the firm since the commencement of their oontract, of which no less than 2,410 tons were shipped after the termination of the contract in pursuance of His Majesty's Government s permission. Zs% there remains the question of the amount which should reasonably be allowed to Messrs, Wonckhaus in settlement of their direct losses, \ iz., in respect advances to the mining company and of implements lost on the island (see paiagiap of the Board sletter of the 9th Janoary) fs - g ards ^vances to the mining company ^^lUoffice's tetter of 'he m/ebiwvTt, according to Uassans statements these amounted to only 2,000 rupees. It appears further that i mt of'comnensation to be allowed for implements—comprising apparently some amount t oompeus. i s l a ud—is extremely small. According to a telegram ^ His Mailsty s residenoy at Bushire. copy of which was communicated to the Board^iy the lndia Office, the planks which were the property of the Hamburg-4 Amerika Line and left on the island by the steamship ' Louise,' were valued at 4L each.* It would appear, therefore, that a round sum of 150L should cover claims under both heads. In view of all the considerations set out in the preceding paragraphs a sum of l,86oZ. 6s. 8d. —or in round figures 2,000L—might not unreasonably be offered to Messrs. Wonckhaus in settlement of all their claims. Nevertheless, as an act of grace and to give Messrs. Wonckhaus the most complete satisfaction, the Board are disposed to suggest that this sum might be raised to 3,000?. This would assume a selling price for Abu Musa oxide of little short of 45s. a ton—a price which according to the facts set out above, Abu Musa oxide, if sold in considerable quantities—could never have realised; and it would assume an average net profit per ton of over 30 per cent, on the cost price, as compared with Mr. Strick's outside estimate of 20 per cent. Commercial Department, Board of Trade. o * See (26032), where 1Z. Is. is given —L. 0trji c 28th June 1914. In continuat on of my dernl-official lat^or dated 10th ay 1914, ^rith ^hich was forwarded a tr n lation of the remarks offered by the Residency ^ent at Lingoh, I now forward the encloure to a letter,received from the .esldoncy Agrnt i -harjah, givinr; such details an he has been able to fuml -h In regard to oxide shipped by Hassan bin Sa- :aiyeh durin the period 1516 H - 1320 H (1099-1902). I d - not forward the letter as It seems to contain not ling relevant to our pur^se# ith reference to point (2) of Foreign*s denl- official telegram dated 1st May 1914 to ne, I wo^d ask whether any further re^nort is ex-nected from me he Hobble Lieut-Colonel Foreign .^eorotary. S I U h A.COffilDKi-ffJnL- r\ ■ - &amp; forrion m\ gtptlturat, Simla, the ■'''-'.ly &gt;0-1 x t-m. im b'jshi^ rstrN^Y JWsjrr •'v a &gt;* • „ 7- 'Vith reference to the last paragraph of your demi-official lettc^ dated the 28th June 1914 / to Sir Percy Cox / regarding the Acu I.'usa oxide case, T am desired to say that we do not expect any further report from you in connection with nir A. Hirtzel's letter to you / dated the 13th &gt;T arch 1914 To Llajor S.G. Knox, C.I.J.., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. tfc A xvy&lt;r of U a SI^ / . ^i/Uuu^^ [.Aa might now be recognized as shaikh of Ras-el-Kl^aimah and given a copy of the Treaties etc?. Or would be better to let thinjvs ^stay as they are till Shaikh Salira departs in the ordinary course of nature. You^ reported in 1912 that he was over 80, and might do/this soon^but apparently he is going strong and may last for years yet. The Residency Agent has never reminded and Shaikh Salim has made no sign, so matter is not pressing and perhaps we might let it stand? )J\% Bushire, 12-5-15. AT. ./-v J ^ 'J ' X ^ Lu ' Si ^/u^eL . AW; s- v' ^ - t*~U/V L^9 fyi^ 1 Csf VnOFFICE NOTH. Translations of a number of papers found in the archives of the German Vice—Consulate d&gt;alin/T '^^u I.usci 1 1 .in^i.■ r, ■ Operations there, were sent to 'olitical Resai 1 i ' iri h0 Persian Gulf, on 26th January 1916, ^.nd by his iireoti^r a copy was sent to the Political Secretary India Office on 2lst February 1916. These papers are filed with other translations from archives of the German Vice-Consulate, Buahire. [&gt; 'h - Bushire, 10-9-16</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ea_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/261</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ea</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/261</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/115 VIII B 17 Abu Musa Red Oxide'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:16:21</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (249 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation starts with the first folio and continues through to the final folio. The folio numbers are written in pencil in the upper right hand corner of the recto side. Foliation anomalies: (1A, 1B,1C, and 1D, 64A and 64B, 173A and 173B, 237A and 237B.)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the mining of red oxide on Abu Musa island. Correspondence discusses the removal of the mining equipment of Hassan bin Samaiyah. Correspondence also discusses the application of Wonckhaus to ship red oxide and negotiations with the Foreign Office over the termination of Wonckhaus's mining rights.Correspondents include Khan Bahadur Aqa Beder, Residency Agent, Lingah; Sir Percy Cox, Political Resident Persian Gulf; C.J. Homer, Officer-in-Command, Persian Gulf Lighthouse Works; Residency Agent, Sharjah; Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, India Office, London; Foreign Office, London; W. Wassmuss, Imperial German Consul, Bushire; Karl Lichnowsky, German Embassy, London.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Lingah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Robert Wönckhaus and Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>German Vice-Consul, Bushire</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Hassan bin Samaiyeh</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Abu Musa Island</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Ferric oxide</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mining</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000ea#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>