<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00035f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:31:46.901Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">.. '' T $ I ( &lt;£&gt; So. ..., uc &gt;, % RegrNo.~ttz ^-y 2 6FOVW35 J illr. f i *3 jTCftw-.tA'A '3'T'-- '3 , : lH i iJ r . The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to • • (1) The Political Agent, Muscat. (2) The Political Agent, Bahrain* ( 5 ) The Political Agent, Kuwait. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Uc Dated .fftoCTMT. A .93 5 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No*P.Z*7663/34, dated the 14th January 1935, from the India Office,London, 1934. to the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office,Londoij f with enclosure* Subject. Foreign Jurisdiction (Prohates) Order in Council,^ith refer odcq to Foreign Office letter No INDIA OFFICE 14th January 1935 »* HIT SHALL. LONDON , S •¥•! 3. ^.•1156 9/1981/250 of 14th Decemher 1934, transmitting a copy of the draft of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Prohates) Order in Council, 1934, 1 am directed hy the Secretary of State for Ino.ia. to say that he has no observations to offer on the terms of the new draft Order. I am, Sir Tour obedient servant 3d/- 0.0.W a lton The Under Secretary of State Foreign Office. Copy sent to IndiawmmmmmuBMmmmm 6 K 11569/1981/250. &lt;L S.W.l. 14tti Deoem'ber 1954. Sir, 1 am directed, 'by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit herewith., to he laid helore the Secretary of State for India, a copy of the draft of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Prohatej Qrder-in-Council, 1954, which has heen approved hy Parliamentary Oouneel together with a memorandum prepared hy the second Legal Adviser of this Department commenting on this new draft order. Sir John Simon would he glad to receive any observations which Sir Samuel Hoare may wish to offer on the draft order, which as will he seen, applies to Koweit, B ahrein and Muscat. 2* Sir John Simon desires to submit the Oraer to the i^rivay Council early next year. I I am, Sir, your obedient servant, Sp/*■ D.J .Scott* The Under Secretary of State, India Office.In CQuncil lo This order may he cited as *the foreign Jurisdiction (Prolate) Order in Council, 1934”. 2. (l) This order extends to all persons and to all property subject to the jurisdiction conferred on the court in matters of probate and administration by any of the Orders in Council mentioned in the Schedule hereto, or by any Order in Council substituted for any of them. { 2 } This Order shall be oxhioited in the public office of the highest of His Majesty's Courts established by each of the Orders specified in the first Cchedule, and shall take effect in the places referred to in each of the ssid Orders one month after the date on which this Order is first exhibited in that place as aforesaid. 3. The provisions of this order shall be deemed to be supplementary to the powers conferred upon the Court by the Tirincipal Order for the exercise of its jurisdiction in matters of probate or administration and shall have effect subject to the provisions of the Principal Order. 4, In the construction of this Oa?der, unless there be something in the subject or context repugnant thereto:- (a) all words or expressions defined or interpreted by the Interpretation Act, 1889, shall, unless otherwise defined in this Article, be interpreted in the same sense as in tliat Act provided; (b) all rules of construction enacted by the said Act shall have effect as if this Order were an Anglish Act of Parliament; (c) the following words and expressions shall have the meaning hereby assigned to them:~ means the Court having jurisdiction under the Principal Order or the Buies made thereunder in matters of Trobate and Administration. P.T.O.~ 2 s H Worn Oil al B e Dr e s. en t g, ti?e w meaBs the executor or adminis trator for the time heinK of a deceased person, means the Order under which the Court exercising Jurisdiction is established, including therein any Order amending or substituted for that Order* real and personal property, w Be pres ?n i;. a t i on means probate of a will or letters of administration ♦ 5* There will he payable upon the grant of representa tion in respect of the estate of a deceased person, being property within the limits of the 1‘rincipal Order, such fees in ace ordanoe with the value of the estate as may be prescribed by Buies of Court made under the Principal Order. 6, The estate of a deceased person shall, for the purposes of this Order, not include property held by the deceased as trustee for another person, but shall be deemed to includes- (a) Any property (i) taken as a d onatio mor tis ca us e made by the deceased person; or (ii) taken under a disposition, made by him purporting to operate as an immediate gift ipiter yivos whether by way of transfer delivery declaration of trust or other wise, -which shall not have been bona ,fid$ made three years before the death of the deceased person; or ixii) taken under any gift by him when ever made, of w hich property bona fide possession and enjoyment shall not 'nave been assumed by the donee immediately upon the gift and thence-forward retained to the entire exclusion of the donor or of any benefit to him by contract or otherwise; provided that this para graph shall not apply to any gifts inter vi vos which are made in consideration of marriage, or w hich are proved to the satisfaction of the includes things in action and any interest in CourtCourt to have heen part of the normal expenditure of the deceased person and to have been reasonable to have regard to the amount of his income or to the other circumstances of the case, or which do not exceed in the aggregate one hundred pounds in value or amount! (h)Any property to which the deceased person having been absolutely entitled has caused to he transferred to or vested in himself and any other person or persons jointly, including therein any purchase or investment effected by such deceased person either 'by himself alone or in concert or by arrangement with any other person, so that the beneficial interest therein or some part thereof passes or accrues by suvivcrship on his death to such other person: (c) Any property passing under any past or future settle ment made by the deceased person by deed or any other instrument not takingeffect as a will, whereby an interest in such property, or the proceeds of sale thereof, for life or any ether period determinable by reference to death is reserved either expressly or by implication to the settlor, or whereby the settlor may have reserved to himself the right by the exercise of any power to restore to himself, or to reclaim the absolute interest in such property, or the proceeds of sale thereof, and the term 'settlement' in this paragraph shall include any trust, whether expressedin writing or otherwise, and if contained in a deed or other instrument effecting the settlement, whether such deed or other instrument was made for valuable consideration or not as between the settlor and any pther person: (d) Money received under a policy of assurance effected by the deceased person on his life, where the policy was wholly kept up by him for the benefit of a donee, wheth or*- 4 _ '7 © whether nominee or assignee, or a part of such mo. in proportion to the premiums paid hy him, where the policy was partially kept up hy him for such benefit. 7. In arriving at the value of the estate, an allowance shall he made for reasonable funeral expenses and for aebts and incumbprances due to nersons resident within the limits of the Principal Order, and for debts and incumbrances due to persons resident outside those limits to the extent to which it is shown to the satisfaction of the Court that the property of the deceased situate in the country in which the person to whom such debts are due x*es:id8s, is sufficient for their payment, but an allowance shall not be made:- (a) for any debt incurred by the deceased cr incumbrance created by a disposition made by the deceased,unless such debt or incumbrance were incurred or created b ona fide for full consideration on money or money’s worth wholly for the deceased's own use and benefit and take effect out of his interest; nor (b) for any debt in respect whereof there is a right to reimbursement from any ether person or estate unless such reimbursement cannot be obtained; not (c) more than once for the same debt or incumbrances charged upon different portions of the property; not (d) for any debt charged on property of the deceased,not subject to the jurisdiction ol the Court in matters or probate and administration, except to the extent that such property is insufficient to meet the charge. 8c Subject to the provisions of this Article and of Article 12, every application for a grant of representation shall be accompanied by an affidavit to be made by the person applying for the grant giving particulars of the estate of the deceased person and of the value thereof and of the deductions permissible under the last foregoing Article, and no representa -tion shall be granted until all the fees then shown to be payable have been paid5 Provided that the Court may, in cases where difficulties oror delays arise in ascertaining the gross value of the estate or the permissible deductions therefrom, or where the appli cant for representation is unable to pay the fees until re presentation lias been granted (the reasons whereof shall appear in the affidavit), gram; representation upon an under taking by the personal representative bo pay any fees payable on the value of the estate v.^eih have not been paid, and the Oourt may in its discretion require a bond or guarantee for the due performance of the undertaking or may require the deposit in Court of such sum as it may think necessary for the purpose of securing the payment in due course of such fees as aforesaid® 9.(l) Every grant of representation -hell near a cor tiftr eat© in writing under the hand of the proper officer of the Court stating the amount of the fees that have been paid together with the gross value of the estate and the permissible deductions therefrom; (a) ^here the representation has been issued under the terms of the proviso to Article 8 of this Order, the grant shall bear a certificate stating that the value of the estate is set out as far as could be ascertained at the date of the issue, and that the applicant for representation has given an undertaking and furnished a guarantee or made a deposit, as the case my be, and on completion of the administration and on payment of any further fees payable in pursuance of the said undertaking, the said certificate shall be confirmed or amended accordinglya 10# It an estate includes property, which is settled, or anyother property which does not vest in the personal representative or any property which is the subject of or is charged with the payment of a legacy, any fees paid out of the ©general estate in respect of any such property shall, unless the will contains an express provision to the contrary, be repayable out of that property to the general estate. 11# If at any time after the grant of representation it6 it appears that - (*) ar error has heen made in the affidavit accompany ing the application for representation with respect of the value of any property or in assessing the amount of any permissible deduction; (h) any property has been omitted or erroneously included in the affidavit; (c) any error has been made in the omission or in fusion of deductions in the affidavit; representative in any case where the effect shall the be to increase the value of the os tan 9 upon which fees are payable, shall, and in any other case may, make an affidavit (hereinafter referred to as a 'corrective affidavit') settling out the corrections to the affidavit: Provided that the Court shall not be bound to consider any corrective affidavit after the expiration of three years from the date of the death of the deceased person* 12. (l) there no application for representation has been made or all such applications have heen abendoned, the Court may, on an application being made on behalf of His Majesty, grant representation for the purpose of securing the payment of f*es in res pect of the value of the estate to such person as the Court thinks fit, and the representation may be limit ed in any ••ray the Court thinks fit, (z) In any such case as aforesaid the affidavit setting out the value of the estate shall not be required to be filed, and no fees shall be required to be paid, before the garnt of representation, a nd the person appointed shall file the said affidavit and pay the fees payable in respect cf the estate within such period as the Court may direct, {%) Nothing in this Article shall effect any other powers possessed by the Court of granting representation. is# The Court may at any time, whether on the filing of a corrective affidavit or not, reconsider the value, as previously ascertained, of the estate of a deceased person, and(?) where it appears as the result of such reconsidera tion that any fees have 'been paid or deposited in excess of the proper fees, the excess fees shall he repaid to the personal representative or such person as the Court may direct; (h) $hcre it appears as a result of such reconsideration tha t insufficient lees have heen paid, the amount of the additional fees shall he payable; and (c) where representation has heen granted in respect of the estate and fees have heen repaid: or addition al fees have heen paid under this Article, the Court may order the personal representative to produce the grate ol representation and the certifi cate referred to in Article 9 hereof shall he amend ed accordingly? 14, The Court may at any time, for the purpose of ascertaining or reconsidering the value of the estate of the deceased person and the permissible deduction therefrom:- (a) appoint a fit and proper person to hold an inquiry; or (b) by order require any person, subject to its juris diction to furnish either by affidavit or otherwise to the Court or to the person holding such inquiry a s a f or e s ai d s u c b i n form a t i on an cl top r o &lt;1 u c e such hooks and documents as may he in his power possession or control touching the estate of the deceased person; or (c) appoint a competent valuer to make a valuation of the estate or any part thereof; or (d) direct such other inquiries on the matter as it may think fit; And any such appointment, requirement or direction may he made in one Order or by successive Orders as the Court in its discretion thinks fit and the costs of or incurred in relation to any such Order, shall he paid out of the estate\( © &gt; 8 - !| of the deceased person and shall rank as a preferential debt due to His Majesty# 15« If any person subject to the jurisdiction of the Court shall refuse or neglect In act in accordance with any Order of the Court made under the last foregoing Article, he shall he deemed to he guilty of contempt of Court and shall he punishable under the provisions of the Prinoiapl Order. 16c (1) All fees payable under the provisions of this t Order shall he a debt due to His Majesty and shall bear interes at four per cent per annum as Iron) three months after the date of death. UO) All such fees as aforesaid shall be payable by the /personal representative bu !: r . -pr* for any fees in excess of the assets which tie has received as persojpbil representa tive, or might, but for his ov/n neglect or default, have received. (3) Ahe r e the personal representative fails to pay any additional fees payable under Article 13 of this Order being fees for which he is liable or fails to pay any fees which he has undertaken to pay under Article 6 of this Order, he shall be guilty of a contempt of Court, and the Court may in addition to any penalty which it may impose under the provisions of the Principal Order in respect of the contempt, order him personally to pay the said fees. 17. Where any person takes possession of, or inter meddles with, any part of the estate of a deceased person he shall be liable, in addition to any other person who may be liable under the foregoing provisions of this Article, to pay such fees as would be payable in res pect of that part of the estate if he had been granted representation in respect thereof Provided that - (a) no fees shall by virtue of this provision be payable twice ovor; (bj nothing herein shall effect the liability under the provisions of the if’incipal Order of any p er 3I •* 55-o Viet ,6 - 9 - person taking possession of, or intermeddling with, any property as aforesaid to a penalty or to a payment of double fees. 18. $'h.ere tbe Gonrt has power to @’1®® reseal a grant of probate or letters of administration or confirmation issued by a Court ox 1robata in the United kingdom cf Great Britain and Northern Ireland, or in an^/ British possession to which . the Colonial if obates Act, 1 892, fox 1 the time being extends, the provisions of this Order shall apply&gt; and fees shall be paid on such resealing as if it were an application for and the issue of representation under ini': r 5 rr. 19. (i) The Foreign Jurisdiction (Irobates) Order in Council, 1908, is horeby i*epeo 13c ♦ {2j Notwithstanding the repeal of the Order afore said, ail Buies approved or confirmed by or under any Order s o repealed, shall continue and be as if this Order had not been made, and the same nay be revoked, altered or otherwise dealt with under this Order, as if they had been made under thi s Orel er • (3) Civil proceedings begun under any of the Orders in Council repealed by this Order, and pending at the time when this Order comes into operation shall, from and after that time, ba regulated by the provisions of this Order, as far as the nature and circumstances of each case admits. FI 13 T BOH lyULS. The China Order in Council, 1925. The Egypt Order in Council, 1930* The Ethiopia Order in Council, 1934. The Morocco Orders in Council, 1889-1933 (Consolidated)• The Koweit Or&amp;er in Council, The Bahrein Order in Council, 1913. The Muscat Order in Council, 1915. ..-iZCgg10 Momorandum 'by the Second Legal Adviser of the The attached draft Probates Order inOonncil has been prepared with the assistance of the Treasury Solicitor, Parliamentary Counsel and Judge Sir Wasey Sterry of H.B.M, Supreme Court in %ypt. It is to take the place of the Probates Order in Council 1908 and the reason for the preparation of this Order was that a/decision of the full Court in %ypt had revealed serious defects in the Order of 1908* The judgment of the full Court in the case in question is attached hereto, marked 'A** The whole object of the Probates Order in Council is to provide the machinery necessary for the collection of Probate fees* This machinery is supplementary, and in case of conflict subordinate to the Principal Order in Council in force in all the countries to which it applies* The Principal defect in the 1908 Order which w§s revealed in the judicial decision in Sgypt, which lias beon referred to above, was that under Article 13 of the present Order, it seems to be imposs ible to collect additional Probate fees where the estate has been undervalued in the original affidavit of the personal representative unless such pers onal representative makes a corrective affidavit* But it has been thought necessary, in addition to correcting this obvious drafting error, to confer upon the Court expressly the powers set out in Article 11,12,13 and 14 of the new draft Order* In addition to this, one or two further amendments have been made which seem desirable and Articles 6 and 7 of the 1908 Order have been redrafted, and it is hoped that in their present form they are clearer* The period twelve months to three years and a proviso excepting certa gifts from the operation of the clause has been added in recent with regard to donatio morti has been raised from accordance--mg ) 12 /&gt; of 135 1 o.-wiatOoKQUXQH Vs oi^aai’ p,.aK &amp; amoth si^ J U 1) G ii_SN T . Sir MIG&amp;LESL F.J*McI&gt;OK^ELL: Fdrag Bwek died on the 18th April, 1920, having h# his will dated 21st January, 1920, Op the 23rd June, 1920, Clement Dwek swore a declaration for prolate purposes valuing the deceased’s estate at £ 58,445.11,4* Op the 24th June, 1920, he paid to the Registrar of H.B.i.Consular Court at AlexandiriS^ the Court Probate Pees amounting to £ 1,755, calculated on such valuatio in accordance with/f the rate pres crihed hy the First Schedule to the Pules of Court of 1914, item 25, and on the same date a grant of probate was made to him, power to make a similar grant to his co-executor Gabriel Shama being reserved. On the 5th August, 1920, Gabriel Shamaswore a declaration valuing the deceased’s estate at the same figure of £ 58,455.11.4, and probate was granted to him jointly with Clement Dwek. On the 7th June, 1927, - almost seven years later - Clement Pwek and Gabriel 3hama filed a notice of motion at the Registry of H.B.1.Consular Court, Alexandria, stating that application would be made on the 13th June, 1927, to the Judge in Chambers for an Order authorising the Consular Authorities to repay to them as Parag IXvek’s executors £ 1,149 being the amount over-paid in respect of estate duty due on the estate of the said Farag Dwek. This notice of motion, it may be convenient to state here, was not served on any re presentative of the Crown. On the 8th June, 1927, Clement Dwek swore an affidavit in support of the said motion, in which he stated that the realisation of the estate of the late Parag Dwek established that the calculation of its value at £ 58,455 was an over estimate, inasmuch as the actual amount realised was only appointed Clement Dwek and Gabriel -hama as his executors• n-13 b £ 20,153.11,9.; that the amo-unt due at 3 $ on the sum so realised was £ 506; and that there was$ consequently, due and owing to the estate £ 1,149 representing the amount overpaid to the Registrar on the 24th June 1920* On the 13th Ju^e, 1927, on the ex-parte application of Counsel o'- Clement and Gehriel Shama, Platt J• made an order that the executors do recover from the Consular Authori ties at Alexandria, £ 1,149 the amount overpaid hy them as estate duty in respect of the late Parag Dwek*s personal estate On the l^th August, 1927 - as appears from the corres pondence - £ 1,149 was paid from H.d.r.Consulate Ceneral at Alexandria to the executors. On the 6th June, 1931, on the ex-parte application of the respondent, an order was made appointing Mr.Robert Rainie Brewis, a chartered accountant, to hold an enquiry as to the personal estate of the deceased and to report as to the value of such estate within the jurisdiction of the Court. On the 16th June, 1931, the writ in the present action was issued^ claiming, inter alia, to set aside the order of the 13th June 1927, directing the^payment of the £ 1,14S to the executors• On the 23rd May, 1932, Mr. Brewis by his certificate certified the value of the estate of the late Parag Dwek at £ 60,122.4.8. No application to vary this certificate was made and it was duly confirmed by the Court. Cp the 4th November, 1932, the present action was triad and judgment given for the plaintiff-respondent setting aside the Order of the 13th June 1927. Prom that judgment the defendant Gabriel Shama appeals. In arriving at a decision in this case it is necessary in the first place to consider in detail the relevant provisions of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Probates) Order in Council 1908. Article 5 (l) provides for the affidavit with which the person applying for prehate or administration must accompa his14 - 17 his application* Article 5(2) provides for corrections in the original affidavit being made by a further affidavit, to be sworn by the person who applied for the grant of probate or administration* Article 9 provides that the Court may obtain further information, by affidavit or otherwise, regarding the estate from any person, or may direct enquiries concerning it, and then goes on 'the information or report so received shall be rt deemed to be a portion of the affidavit of the applicant *for probate or letters of administration - . Finally, Article 15 lays it down that where a further affidavit is sworn under Article 5(2), and the Court is satisfied either that a larger fee or a smaller fee should have been paid on the grant of probate or administration,the Court may direct a further fee to be paid as may be due, or may direct such sum to be repaid to the applicant as may seem jUSto That is to say, it is only when a further affidavit correcting an error in the first affidavit is made by the person who applied for probate or administration, and to whom a grant of probate or administration has issued, that Article 13 comes into operation. To give any other meaning to Article 1 3 is to reduce the first line of that article to anullity, and as was said by Jessell M.R« in Yorkshire Insurance Company v. Clayton (1881), 8 at p.424. 'Although it may not always be possible to give 'a meaning to every word used in an Act of 'Parliament, it is a general rule that it is 'right not to treat word surplusage if a meaning 'can be fairly given to them'. The same canon of interpretation of course applies also to legis lative enactments by His Majesty in Council. By treating the words in Article 13 'where a further 'affidavit is sworn under Article 5(2)' as presenting a condition precedsnt upon the fulfilment of which alone the remainderremainder of the article can he held to operate, we can fairly give a meaning to the article, which, it must not he forgotten, is concerned with the revenues of the Grown and is therefore a legislative instrument which calls for a strict interpretation* This being so, I am hound to hold that Article 13 is not applicable in the circumstances of the present case and that the appeal on behalf of Gabriel Shama must succeed. As the Grown l^rosecutor in this case was suing as an officer of the Crown in performance of a public duty, we make no order as to costs* As to the appeal on behalf of Clement Dwek in which we have already held that Counsel should not be heard, we order that e$ch party bear its own costs both here and in the Court below • 20th January, 1933. Ag tn Costs; Mr. s. Alexander quotes Halsbury, Vol.24 p.743, par. 1600* In suits by or against Crown, costs are given for or against Crown. Mr.Perrott says this is statuory. Court points out that case in Halsbury is for revenue penalties. Halsbury, Vol. 10, p.12, par. 26, costs may be given against Crown 22 and 23 Victoria 26 Section 21. He Carbonite 1923 2 Oh* 504, 1924 2 Oh. 53 Mr. Herrott cites Halsbury, Vol.23, p. 207. As to costs on the argument before us, we give costs to Gabriel Shama, below and in this Court, and order Clement Dwek to bear his own costs here and below. No payment of costs pending appeal. Mr.Mazwell asks for leave to appeal to Privy Council in forma pauperis. Says he has an appeal as of right I have not^heard and have a right to be heard . Cites Benwich p*170 p.169, 1926 edition. Mr.Herrott gives notice of appeal. Leave to appeal granted to both applicants*- 16 (3 Security in &amp; 500 0 Necessary steps to 'be taken within 3 months. 20th January, 1933. SIB HERBERT C. STBMGrE : I concur in the judgment of the President o 20.1.^5. SIB WAS ST S TERRY: I have not much to add hut I should like to say a few words» ^e have had some discussion as to whether the order of the Oourt in 1917 was a ministerial of a judicial act, and I should like to deal with that point first* The duties put on the Oourt under the Foreign Jurisdiction (Brohates) Order in Council in Article 9 seem to resemble duties put on the Commissioners of Inland Bevenue under the Finance Act, 1894, and as there is no provision for the Crown being represented and bo suggestion that the Court’s determination under Article 13 is inter partie s , I still remain of my former opinion that the act of the Court was a ministerial an® not a judicial one. 1 he next point on which considerable emphasis has been laid by the appellants is that the money sought by tt Crown is afee and not a duty* I quite agree, though the point comes oddly from the parties who asked the Judge for a return of estate duty and obtained an order for the return of estate duty. The Crown, however, does not press that point, otherwise I should have been Inclined to say that the Order and appli cation for repayment we re both bad a b initio » &amp;e are then to assume that the case is to be considered on the footing that the application for repay ment was for repayment of fees and that the order for repayment related to fees. Now the importance of this is it is said that no acti nn! 0 - 17 - &gt;0 action for return of fees can lie unless there has 'been some promise to pay and therefore that the Grown here cannot recover fees when once they have been approved by the Judge. this In my view, however trueZ^ay or may not be as an exposition of the law of fees in general, the form of proce dure laid down in the -Foreign Jurisdiction (iErobates) Order in Council necessarily implies a promise to pay an both sides, on the part of the Grown and of the subject. It is assumed in Section 13 that the case will arise where too great or too small fees have been paid, and provides for the necessary adjustment, and that though the act of probate for which the fees are paid has been issued. But granted that probate fee s are not irrecoverable, is that sufficient in the present case ? I leave out the guestion of fraud which has not been alleged, for it has not been put higher than a mistake on the part of the Judge in accepting the then present value of the estate instead of the value at the time of Barag Dwe^s death. The other members of the Court have discovered a point which was not made to me in the Court below and has escaped the ingenuity of counsel on the appeal, but which appears to me to be irrefutable. It is this that it is by Article 13 alone that fees are made re payable, and that that article in terms limits Hie case to one where a further affidavit has been filed, which seems necessarily to imply that it is by this further affidavit that the Court is to be satisfied. There is no power in this Court to correct the wording of Article 13* though it may be that there is a draftman’s mistake. There was apparently an attempt to adopt the procedure of the Customs afcd Inland Revenue Act, 1882, in these matters, but under that procedure, if the Commissioners are satisfied the value of an estate is insufficient, they can compel the applicant for probate to file a corrective affidavit under severe penalties. P.T.O.^hat is sontemplated, so This is not the case here© far as the Order in Council lays it down, is , first, the filing of an affidavit; second, under Article 9 enquiry, if need he, before prohate is iss ued; third, a corrective affidavit; hut if once prohate has heen issued, then the enquiry under Article 9 is useless, unless the applicant files a further affidavit, or presumably in case of fraud. It might he argued that the report should he considered part of the further affidavit, hut Article 9 says distinctly it is to he part of the affidavit, which can only mean the affidavit referred to in Article 5© The result is that I concur with the judgment pronounced by the other members of the Court. 20•1•1933.3 0 JUL 1935 Bahrain . le ffl Qx a iiaijffl I forward, herewith, a copy of despatch Ho* 28 dated the 23th June 19S5 from the Foreign Office 2 ' , ^ London together with two certified copies and thirty 30 1/^ plain copies of 'The Foreign Jurisdiction (Prohates) \ n 4 Order in Gouncll, 1935 M . 2* Copies of this Order should he exhibited in the usual places in your Office on the 10th August 1935 stating that the Order will come into force from the 1st September 1935* rwt W, 2 (&gt;■) % ^ c n r v 3 ' 3. Please telegraph on the 10th August 1935 that the Order has heen exhibited. By Order, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No# 28 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W#1 28th June 1935. (K 6996/674/250) Sir, I am directed hy Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to transmit to you herewith eight certified and 120 copies of ’‘The Foreign Jurisdiction (Probates) Order in Council, ISSS*# Copies of this Order should he exhibited in the usual places in Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat and notices should be published in those states in any way you consider suitable and practicable stating the date on which it will come into force, which should be the same in all three cases# 2# You will inform me by telegram of the date on which the Order will be exhibited, which should be as near 5th August as possible, and of the date on which it will come into force. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd) S. GASELLE. The Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel T.C. Fowle, etc#, etc*, etc.. C.B #E. , Bushire*1 I 3 l. 1 /! Telegram G-* i1 . C* Prom - Political Agent, Bahrain. To - Politic-1 Resident, Bushire. No# - 182 Dated - 10th August 1935. Your letter No.1562 dated the 30th July, Oraer-in-Council exhibited 10th August. -Political- -— -—-0 TELEGRAM Prom To No. G.T. CODE. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 709. Dated and received 14th August 1935, yf My letter dated 30th July No.1562. Will Order come into force from 10th September repeat 10th September. - BRITCONSUL - v .. ..i.* .at..,.Were we ever consulted aoout this ? No, Out</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00035f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1192</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00035f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1192</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/10 Foreign Jurisdiction (Probate) Order in Council, 1935.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-18T14:55:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (30 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 28-31).</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 32; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-31; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the issue by the Foreign Office of the
                           Foreign Jurisdiction (Probates) Order in Council, 1935, and its application to, and publication in, Bahrain.The date range gives the dates of the earliest document in the file (an enclosure on folio 20) and last dated addition to the file (an entry in the notes on folio 31); the covering dates of the main run of correspondence are 17 February-15 August 1935.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Probate</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign Jurisdiction (Probates) Order in Council, 1935</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00035f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>