<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000298_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-15T14:48:18.539Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&lt;s (C : i Letter dated 4tli Jamadi II, 1347 (17.11.28) from Sheikh. 1 uharora^d hin IJMsir al ilruaudah ^air of Ja r alan, to the Comwander T T.I'.S. ,, Cyclajnen u . Heed. 22.11.28. A.C. I have received your letter dated 14th ITovenher corresponding to 30th Jarnadi I, 1347 which you had v/ritten 'by order of the -British ITaval Conuaander in Chief Vice Admiral Bertram 3 Thesiger, C.B., and in accordc^nce v/ith your instructions T have come to 3ur with a viev; to come to Puscat hut I found the sea too rough and the wind unfavour able and could not get a sailing boat. I have sent this letter by a small boat. I request you to send me a steamer so that I may come soon to I-use at. You may either send one of H.M.S. Ships or tne Sultan ship. I am exepecting the arrival of the ship so that 1 tu y embark on it and come soon as it t; kes some time to travel by sailing boat.Letter dated 4th Jamadi II, 1547 (17.11.28) from Sheikh T T uharnmad 'bin : T asir al Hamudah, Anir ol Ja f alan, to I’ajor r r .p. rurphy, T.A., .Political Agent and H.B.r’s ConBul T'uBcat. ^ecd. 22.11.28. A.G. I have received your letter asking me to come to see you. I have now arrived at Aiqa with a view to come to see you, hut I regret to say that i found the v nd unfavourable and I am obliged to ask ydu to send me either the Sultan snip or a -nritish Government ship so that I may be able to come soon in compliance with your order* u wing to unfavourable wind delay will occur in my coming travel (if I SBEHHe by sailing boat) and so I beg you to comply wit with my request.Caj transittion or a xeuter dated. / tu Jamtai II, ^^47 (t.C&lt;,n Hot ember x 928 ) iron, aneiicii j.sa Din aaiiu ai Hantin. to major U.P. Eurpiiy, I.A., Political Agent ana ri.B.r's consul, muscat. meed. &lt;SO-ll-i28» After compilaosnts . I Deg to state titet on tiie Una instant (15.ll.H8) I received your letter anted 25tk Jamaai I (9.11.28). iou nave written that tne political .«esiaent has asieea you to mi ora ne tuat H.B.H's GOTernment is giTing due attention to tne.an airs at Sur out tuat they ao not iiKe to taJce any action oeiore tue nt- w.m. the BUltan ana hare asjcea ne to Keep amirs in tueir present condition until tuat tine, nod willing 1 will act as desired oy you as X am coniident aoout you. I have receirea news toaay tnat the Political ..esi&amp;ent accompanied oy the heir-apparent Sayia Said Din iaiamr has Tisited Bur. tnat you nare Domoarded tne xort oi tne imiTaris and tnat you nave gatnerea the Janabeh under tneir oneiicn. he have oeen pleased to near tnis and hope tuat the'result would DC good. Kit I hope tuat we will meet each some time. P.S. Please iniorn the Political resident that I am gratexul to him and the hovemnent for tueir action and hope that the cloth (flag) which was hoisted oy Aeni JBU All ft Aiqa will oe removed as it would oe a cause for trouble and disturDance.ino. I X \ of roiitical Agency &amp; Consulate, Muscat, 2iina fiOTemoer TO Ciieijda ciuhajnrnad oin iMasir al namudaii, Amir of Ja’alan. A.C. I have received your letter dated 4th Jaiuadi 11, i347« his Excellency had seen your letters to the resident and i&gt;o me asxing for an interview and thereiore he aeciued to gi/e you an opportunity to see him. As you were unable to come, ,it does not riatter. nis Excellency is departing from here today and so what is written m my previous letter still holds good. u. E. ::aj or, political Agent and h-.B.M* s Consul, : us cat. v &lt; C r L*k\ .Telegram..v^ode; From Ke si dent, Aden, l 1 political,xiuscat. j;ated 28-11-28 v^eceived 29/11/28; Ali bin AbdullaH bin 8alein Mahomed al namooda said to be Amir of oaaian having visited Mokalla is expected to arrive here on 29th rjovember* is he entitled and do you wish him to receive any special attention. lie sident, Aden. Telegram ^cypher). From roll ti cal,muscat, resident,Aden, no.158 dated 29th November 1928. : inis vr&gt;a-n is sheikh of a v^ahabi tribe m oaalan stop Their activities in hoisting ibn 8aud‘s flag at aur,esta- -biishing customs houses,interfering with caravan^route and proclaiming independence from muscat has very nearly led to general conflagration and is at present engaging attention of government. ne has with him one Abdulla nabshi English speaking villain. They are presumably proceeding to visit ibn baud, i shall be glad of information regarding their movements ar and activities. rolitical.Telegram From political Besiuent, Bushiro, Government of India* New Delhi# 3ecy# of State for Incia, Loi^ion No. 1170 Latter will give copy to Secy, of State for Colonies, Ko. 131. i Following from Political Agent, Muscat, Novemher 22nd, begins. \mir i*eplied that he is not Fnds • /55/134. * Telegram From To Repeated Commander In Chief, 4 Iast Indies Squadron. Admiralty, No. 633. (Government of India, New Delhi. Political Resident, Bushire. Time 1601. Dateded 22nd received 23rd November 1923. * not reed. Bushire. * X tiavQ 'bs©!! unable to s©© Isader referred to in my telegram No. 523. Following is appreciation to date on leaving Muscat. Tribes are remon^ -lily uuiet but while Ibn Saul's flag and customs house are at /iqa, there is likelihood of attack by Hinawis, who are merely holding back in the hope that we shall take action after return of Sultan. There is bound to be trouble over control of 3ur eventually. If it is considered necessary to have stable conditions for trade etc. at Sur which is for His Majesty's Government to decide, it will be imperative to send a battalion there to occupy the town. If desired to attempt to quiet tribes inland a much stronger force will be required. To relieve battalion at Sur local levy could probably be raised and trained in two years, paid for by increased revenue at Sur. It is improbable that there will be an attack on Muscat itself. C. i. C. post copy to Political Agent, Muscat. Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.35/134. Telegram P. Political Resident, Bustiire, . Government of India, New Delhi From To ) No. 1205. Repeated Secretary of State for India. ) Latter to give copy to Secretary of State for Colonies, No. 132. Dated 24th November 1928. It was on the possibility of Wahabi inter- -ferenae and aggression and consequent political dislocat- -ion that the proposals for the location of a battalion at Sur were based. That there would appear to be no possibility of this is indicated by subsequent reports. Fora the present therefore Sur may be viewed as domestic problem of Oman. As such it is no new one and probably not now one of extreme urgency. It must however be faced as part of the whole question of Muscat, which has already drifted far from the ppsition it occupies in theory and now shows a tendency to move further. The Hinawis, who have fallen out with the Bani Riyam and are threatened by them with attack from the rear should they attack the Bani Bu Ali, weem likely to avoid precipitat ing matters. I agree with Commander in Chief that we can obtain effective control of Sur only by locating a battalion there but it seems to me that his limit of two years :fcxxx£sxxx for its location seems optimistic and that the occupation is more likely to be semi-perman- There seems to me to be no advantage in attempting to interfere inland. Were Sur to pass into other hands its actual retaking and occupation would be a matter of little difficulty. And we could always without occupation impos* a blockade to bring pressure on the tribes of the interior. On the other hand the2 estaolishment of Sur as a port under other control than Muscat would practically emasculate the State finances hy its use in preference to Muscat if trade were afforded reasonable security and lower dues were levied. Further there is the present loss of dues resulting from the ineffective control at Sur. The question seems to he how far His Majesty’s Government is prepared to advance on the present policy, of fern bolstering up the Muscat State by heavy expenditure on battalion and what is $xxxk± practically equivalent to occupation. The foregoing is with reference to telegram No. 633 from Naval Commander in Chief to Admiralty. JOHNSTON. Post copy to Political Agent, Muscat Under » the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Sur 1.0 Lue i‘Gicai. uuscat* Keoeivoa iibt-ii 0 ^PteLiber 1926* n T beg to state that on the night oi ^1/9/28 v/hen a caravan by which I sent rice and money lor the purpose oi purchasing dates left my nouse it was attacked by the ■^u war is. The reason oi their so doing is due to the detention at ruscot oi one oi tneir slaves who is an accomplice in the natter oi looting the lutiya u Husaini’ f . As soon as liasir bin All in Whose house we are living came to Know about trie matter he brought tne caravan oacK to ny nouse. /e tnen reported tue matter to bay id Shahab. r . r e are mucn ingutened lest tuey may attack us at our nousejana Kill or plunder us. ur tuey may loot tue hutiyas wnicn arrive irom India* They may ao so as no punisnment was inflicted on them (lor their former miscmeij. Tne people are much afraid because if they (the Fuwaris) do anytumg no one taKe tnem to task for their action. U;/ *-**■*-*--. -*-'*■■*■** ******-***** i lJri\ Translation of a letter dated 7tn Jamadi-el iu-:har lo47 (20th novernher 1928; from Isa hln Saleh Al-narthi to tne Council of ministers to H.H* the Sultan oi i.usclu. After Compliments, i have received your letter together with that of the Consul, i an glad at trie interesting steps taken hy you. The information about the arrival oi the Admiral in his ship and bayid Sa’id, the Heir-Apparent and his party reached us. The coalescence of Janahah and alliance to their snaikn are better thah their dispersion an d i disunion, ihey should be observed lest no one of then should commit cny infringement of law and regulation, ihere is no doubt that your hand is long and powerful, ray Cod help you toward inprovements and good acts, herewith the reply of the Consul.2 A.C. I have Been your letter dated ^2tfi Jenadi TJ to the lu^nia Jerasa with rejj;: rd to hia refusal to pay the Chinese noney to his a^ent. I bej to et;te that I htre ordered hia to r tt ch the money until they settle their question with the Customs f udir at Cur becmase as you Know the Chinese shipped goods from Cam Ournatin - nd did not pny CustoMs duty, fln his departura hK the Customs Pudir obtained an undertaking from him to the effect th*t if he does not }uc«g produce a proof to show that the Customs Departnent has no right to mice any claim, he would be liable to payment of duty on the goods which were shipped by him. ~he time of the :juar&lt;- ntee has expired and he has not returned. The Customs Iludir informed me that lie (ciiinese ) has got sone money with Jeram * nd that his a u ent intends to tfike the money ; nd leaTe the place.* I have attached the money until the question is settled either by production of a proof or by payment of Customs duty. As you are our friends you will not agree that our dues- be spoiled. Letter dated 14th J; ma.di 'I, 11547 (27.11.28) from heikh v uhd. bin JMssir to Ray id 'hahnl? ^ali of oor. A. C. \ Yesterday 1 received your letter stating that the Chinese had shipped goods from Tkam Qurmatain but had not paid Customs d duty on same. The Chinese srys that he |iad paid. He is not present but will be coming shortly. He has got goods here and I request you to release his money. On his arrival he will settle with the Customs either by production of a decisive proof or by p. yr'ent of duty on tne goods which was shipped from umm qumat; in. s you have mentioned we do not agree that your clues be s oiled. The Chinese friend intends to go now but he v/111 return, j le; se allow nis money to be paid to nim. tt. rpay the Customs duty, itaye they got a receipt from the Customs? You i re aware aoout tiiese rules • I haYe relerred the matter to the Capital and avail an newer* You may «* Iso represent the matter to the Capital £nd we shrll xct up to t^eir (’ectrion* TT T* • ’ •Letter dated 16tli Jaxiaxii 1347 (29th. lTovenu5er 19&lt;-8) from Spy id Shahah 7/hli of Sur to the Council of rinisters to H.H. the Sultan of ? r usca.t and Oman* A.C I he^ to state that on the 10th Jariiadi II (2o*ll*^c3; the Customs ITudir at Sur came to me and informed me that the Agent of the Chinese who bought fish intend to leave and that they have got a sum of $ 300 with Jeram agent of Lhimji R&amp;mdas He asked me to attach the money until the question ol payment of Customs duty on goods wnich were snipjjed by the Chinese be settled* l have already reported the matter to you. ihe period of the Chinese undertaking has expired and his agents intend to leave* As it is said that he does noo intend to return I attached his money which he has deposited with the Eunnia. Sheikh I'uhammad bin Hasir has ilso written to the Eunnia asking him to pay the money. Some correspondence v 7 c*s exchanged betr/een us copies of which I enclose herev'ith for your information. Letter dated 12th Jaxiadi II. i347 (2o*ll*2^) irom ..uieikh Huhammad bin Hasir to Jeram Eunnia The agent of the Chinese has informed me that he asked you \ to pay him nis money which was deposited w r itn you but you hove refused to do so. Please p&amp;y him nis dues at once and do not put me into unnecessary trouble. 1 shaj.1 send a messenger to your (government. TJ. E Letter dated 12th Jamadi II, 1347 (25.11.28) from the ^/aii of Bur to Sheikh ruh; mLiad bin Hasir al namudah. A.C I have seen your letter dated 12th Jamadi T IA Ar 2 . rit A.G. I have seen your letter dated 12th Jamadi II to the u^nia Jeram with regard to his refusal to pey the Chinese money to his * agent. I 'beg to state that I have ordered nim to attach the money until they ,settle their question with the Customs rudir at Cur because as you Know the Chinese shipped goods from Umm ^urmatin and did not pay Customs duty, hn his departure ha: the Customs Pludir obtained an undertaking from him to the effect that if he does not p-rgsrE produce a proof to show that the Customs Department has no right to make any claim, ne would be liable to payment of duty on the goods which were snipped by him. The time of the guarantee has expired and he has not returned. The Customs Iludir informed me that he (Chinese; has got some money with Jeram and that his agent intends to take the money and leave tne place. I have attached tne money until the question is settled either by production of a proof or by payment of Customs duty. As you are our friends you will not agree that our dues be spoiled. Letter dated 14th Jnmadi II, 1547 (27.11.28) from Sheikh ? T uhd. bin liasir to Sayid Shahab Tali of Soor. A.C. Yesterday I received your letter stating that the Chinese had shipped goods from Tjmm Qurmatain but had not paid Customs d duty on same. The Chinese says that he £ad paid. He is not present but will be coming shortly. He has got goods here and I request you to release nis money. On his arrival he will settle with the Customs eitner by production of a decisive proof or by payment of duty on tne goods which was shipped from Iftnn qurmatain. As you have mentioned we do not agree that your dues be spoiled. The Chinese friend intends to go now but he will return. Please allow his money to be pc id to nim. IT. T. i;\7ali bt Sur to Gheikh I’uhLciinmad Tain ITaoir ai Hanudah. il* 0 • Letter dated 13th Jamadi II, 1347 (26.11*28) from the I have received your letter dc. ted 14th oamadi II in reply to mine and understood its contents, xou have mentioned that the Chinese has paid tne Customs duty. If he has done so he I he^ to state that money of the Chinese has.'been attached illegally. If the Customs I'udir has got a prooi he should produce it. The friend of tne Chinese has got witnesses who give can/evidence that they have paid the fees due from them. If you wish the witnesses will come to see you otherwise please release the money. I await your reply. Letter dated 16tn Jamadi XI# -*-347 (29.1 j-. 28) - ron oayid Shahch Wali of Goor to oheikh I uh.c imfl.ad 'bin Lssir. t have received your letter o.ateci the i.6th Jaisu di IT asking that the Customs ITudir snould produce a proof with \ re. a rd to his claim against tne Chinese on account ol non payment of Customs duty. The chief proof is the guarantee given I hy the Chinese in his own handwriting. Secondly as a rule a receipt would he furnished hy the Customs to those who pay Customspay the Customs duty, nave they got a receipt .rom the Customs? You are aw re about these rules . I lave retired the natter to the Capital and await an answer* ^ r ou may ilso represent the matter to the Capital end we shall ect up to their decision.better dated 17t?i o ra; di TJ # 1347 (30.11*2Bj from 'belJch w.-jnlr 'bin ruh- raa^d Chief of r^ma to the Council of Inistera* A.C. V/ith re^i.rd to /\mir ruhammad bin Uuoir I beg to at- te that he is staying at Aica and Sayid fhahab is staying \ ith us at al Cat* Cnyid 'ha.hab must eosimunlooted news to you* As regi rds the Tfutiah the 'Tama and Fuwaris are naming armngenent for the settlement of the matter ; nd you will receive the necess;ry information about same* Handan bin Waoir al nanudah nnd his followers h; ve left for your parts. You should discuss matters ijroperly with him* uhnamad bin X'lasir is staying at iqa expecting their return* 'he Thikhana md Ghialin are still m int; ining the same attutude towards the reni J3ul All &lt;• nd we the frama and uwaris ere malntaing X our old attitude* 'he truce will expire at the end of this month (13.12.28) and from tiie oeginning of Rajab there would be no truce be twees us (Arama &amp; Fuwaris ) ; nd them (J3eni )m Ali).\x - •■N • tater^ent of AJaimJi Kamdas. ffiiinji iiamdas states (1) Cninaman Ji*baaiipoo wiio deals in fisii in bur and v&lt;ho keeps his account with the firm of hhimji itamdas at iiur has an agent at sur in the person of Aimed Kaghia /‘ an Arad• aaiyid Shahah wall of Sur wrote to ii.naiadas's firm and asked that out of the account of the Chinaman the sum of jrf.300/- should he retained on account of Customs dues due from the Chinaman. The agent of the Chinaman came to lUiimji Kamdas and asked for ^the settlement of the Chinaman's account.lie was toid oy n.Kamdas that the i&amp;li had oraered him to keep ihe sum of ^.300/- on account of customs dues, fine agent did not agree to this and ashed that the whole amount should he paid to him. On being refused he went and informed the Amir of Jaalan who v/rote to h.uamdas to pay up hStiAIffiaun* all amount to Ahmed Kaghia as the Chinaman was staying in Aiqa and was thereiore under his protection and that K.Kamdas nad no right to withhold his account, ne threatened him to report 5*him to the Consulate at Muscat. K.Kamdas replied he could not disobey the ■.Tail’s orders nor could he j displease him (Amir) and requested the matter be settled between the Wall and himselx. * v 2) Re looting 01 nis Dhow. Sai^ bin Sultan Sheikh of the xaajaala^and the oheiKns i of the Arama and Fuwaris came to K.Ramdas and asked mm to compromise the case.They threatened him say- -ing it was no good for him to prolong the case and insisted that he should settle it. K.Ramdas replied he could do nothing as the case was in the hands of the Consul. They again pressed for settlement of the case at Sur and asked him to reduce the claim by .I Hs.150/-and the balance they would pay. They impress-4. TljQ Ami rs reciuest thit a no olD^ection certificate f^r the r'nc wuxcli //ere ^ranted to ti em 'by the O-cv a nrent xo.3t year j lurid he cent to them. The Political v^ent, Irocat, wrote to them that the anno would he granted on condition that the ransom' of the Bunnia would he refunded. T he amount was paid although it had nothing to do wit a the question of the 0 rant of the Government, hut they have not received the arms s yet ,s the Consul guaranteed to them. 5. The Amirs request you to advi e your friend, id Tax ..ur, 3uxt .m of husecut, to hand over the cartxid- for -aes which was purcu^sed them on payment through tne late 3aiyiu Baisal anu ha.s heen wept with ha.. in deposit since io5i (1013). Saiyid Taimur, according to his letters intends to pay money to them instead of the cartridges hut the^ do not require money as they are in need of tae cartridges,^ wwich were bought hy taeir own money. •j. The Ai. irs request ycur just Government to' certify on certificates which are issued hy them to their subjects „nu dependents owners of boats similar to those of the Sultan of Socotra ana otaers because their subjects exper- -ience ^reat difficulties in getting certificates from Muscat. Moreover if it becomes necessary for the A^irs to g^ on a journey it would be a disgrace to the., to take a passport from other Chiefs and count themselves subjects of Muscat. The Amirs do not agree to this cs it «ould be an insult to them ana their family. 7. The irs request Your Honour to despatch the letter addressed to the Italian representative at Magdesho v. i up regard to the claim of Rashid bin Abdullah bin Rashid ; a nd Saleem bin Abdullah bin Mater of Rani Bu Ali who were plundered last year by the Somalis during the fight with tne Italians wth a request to pay the cIubs of tne A irs subjects like ouhers ./no were plundered during the Somalis fieating. As the claimants are always approaching the AiWxrs about their dues ana they ( Amirs) are afraid that tney ( the claimants) may ^olest. the Somalis who are making trnffiim to triose j.arts they request you to communicate v;itU the representative of the said Government and o.otain a reply from him oefore the termination of tnis season as the Somalis ..ill shortly xxxt visit these parts. Dated x4 th June 1928. 3d/- Adhullah Salih. Messenger of the Amirs of Sur Jaalan. ( at Busixire)C0NBI15EN XIAL. JNo. 434-B, of 1928. Britich Residency and Consu late-Gen e ral , Buahire, the 4th Becember 1928. ■prom The Hon 1 hie Bir Frederick Johnston, it.G.X.B#, G.S.I. # I.C.S., Political Resiaent in the Persian Gull’, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political iiepartment, hew Delhi. In continuation of my letter ho. 423-S. # dated the 2drd November 1928, I have the honour to forward copies of the letters noted in the margin from ihe Sir Lionel iiaworth*s Political Agent at Muscat, letterto which Isa bin Saleh refers is the one reported in the former’s telegram ho. f-ib, uated uhe 23rd. October 1928. 2. A cop^/ of this le uter and of its enclosures is being forwarded to xha His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. I have the honour to be , Sir, your most obedient servant,\ / I Letter dated 7th ^ajah 1347 (20th December 1928; from Sheikh ,7asir bin ;..li al Hashshar to Haji 7ubeir. A • C • I be^ to state that Z have already written you a letter and nope it has reached you. There is no news worth mention ing in Sur except that today the I’akhana killed two men of the former heni Omar Askaris on the way leading to the-JJalad. Although a truce was effected between the parties by Say id Shahab 3 days ago they (Kakhana) violated the said truce. As soon as we heard the shots we went out and found that the culprits were running to their fort. T 7e referred the natter to Sayid Shahab who decided to rep.resent the matter to you and action will be taken according to your order. ^e have told Sayid shahab that we are ready to help in any action which may be taken to the interest of the i Government and to protect him against them (Takhana’. He has asked us to wait until he gets orders from the Capital. '—fan —tOtOvv.Letter tinted 2ZM Jaiuaai II, x347 (bUi ^eoewter i9Hb) xroiu tluyiu Stiahab biii Faisul, 'oil oi oo tiie council ot r’itilett.-re to rt.M* tue SultMi 01 ; ucc^t Oi-iein* r.UwOc-t* ^ r I be^ 10 oUitc triat mere is no news \;6rtii ueriLionmy; except that Sheiich Isa bin Saiib has arrived r t badiyeh rnd tbe j^eni j l u Hasan have paid hiti a visit. The details are ^iven in the two letters which are enclosed herewith. xesterday I’unanitad Din Hasir proceeded to his place bee; use tne Poru* have ^one to see nin in compliance with rds request. They had called on him oeiore ind at present about 16 men oi tnem nave gone to see him. The truce between j^eni jju Ali and the oanaoen \ ill expire at tue end of this month (13.12.28). Said an nr l hie al Hashimi intends to make another truce uetween then for a period of one year and perhaps it could be arranged. The truce between jbeni Oman ASKnris and the Makhana will also expire on the bth oi next month (18.12.28) and I am ^oing to make another truce nsxxxim ror a period of 4 months between them. 7 snail report further developments. U. T. Letter dated 16th Jamadi -I. 1347 (29.11.28) from Sheikh tfulih bin Said to Say id sn.ah.ab bin raisal Tali oi Jr&gt;ur A.C. I am writing this letter iron the country oi ^eni bu Hasan. There is no news out what may please you. As tne messenger was leaving tor your parts I deemed it necessary t to write and enquire after your health. j -^q inform you that Sheikhs H&amp;nud bin Mumaid f nd t r uhammad bin Amer bin Ali proceeded to see the Hinawis and Sheikh Isa bin Salih on the 12th instant (26.11.28) in order + o (liscuss the aSfaiTS XiikxKXE. v/hich happened between them • ,nd oeni hhafir. They have stated that ^eni Ohafir are opposing them without any reason and although they2. ( T Tinawis j are aw .‘re about it zncy ao not support them. They have asked the Hinawis to help then in viev/ of their friendship with them as r&gt;eni Ghal'ir (do to their friends)# Tf the Hinawis do not help they are going to refer their affairs to you (Thascat) and ask your help# Letter dated 19th Jamadi II, 1347 (2.12.28) from Sheikh Salih Din said to Sayid Thahab bin Faisal, T^ali oi Sur. * n iV • • I beg to state tnat I have written this letter iron Halan (^adi heni Khalid). m here is no news except that the Sheikhs of neni ^u Hasan had gone to see Sheikh Isa bin Salih# 'Hey have entrusted all their affairs to him and the latter havj referred to the Imam* The Sheikh and the Imam ha^e negotiated over the matter, 'he Sheikh has informed then (Beni lu Hasan) that they have exchanged views with the Council in tnis connection. 'he msalihah (in JaSalan) went in company with Beni Bu Hasan in order to apologise for the incident which had taken place nut the sheikh did not accept unless by order . of the Imam# i—Snei-tn Hoia&amp;an Din I'lasir aj. iiaiauclali uroiner ox Sneij^n '’'uiiaimaoa bin i'iasir *‘U-'iir nl Ja 4 ulan &lt;iij;ed about 26 yenra i ccoi panieci by 40 wen arr iv eci r.ULcat on the hrd December 19^8. On the 4th he called on the P.A. The Council or J inicters were present in the Electing. Sheikh Hrrndan said that his .borhtrr won sorry cJ^Vl for not being^to coiue to I'uscf t as at thrt tine when A he was called by the Connander in Chief the wind was unfavourable and prevented him iron coning, ne has been sent by him to discuss, natters. The r.A. told him that he was unaware about matters which the Commander in Chief wanted to duscuss with his brother and that as mentioned in P.R r D letter all matters should remain until the arrival of H.H. the Sultan and the P.R. Sheikh Hamdan said that Deni Bu Ali have always been friendly and helpful to 1 uscat and in the same way they expect the 7'uscat Government to help them, '’’he P.A. told him that it was for then to obey and carry out the orders of ’’liscat Government As Sayid ruhammnd bin Ahmad President of the Council of rinisters was sick and could not come from Batrah to ruscat Kaji Zubeir and Sayid Said accompanied by Sheikh Hamdan went to r.atr; h on the 9th December. In the meeting Sheikh TTamdan said that since olden times Beni Hu Ali have been friendly to 7'uscat Govt, and have always supported them and carried out their orders but some misunderstandings took place between the two parties since the visit of the V/azir Thomas to Sur. The T 7azir intended to demolish the forts built by the Janabeh but the Fuwaris and Arana did not agree. Me decided to attach one of the dhows belonging to Arama section and when he wanted to tow that dhow5. / S2 ') they have ri^ht to do (2) their interference vith the orloirs of tribes at Hur and (3) hoisting a foreign flog* Sheikh Hand on St-id that the flag was not Ibn Saud*s flog as niarepresented by others hmt it is their own* Zha. He could not give a satisfactory answer when the Wuzara asked the reason for changing their previous flag* As regards the Custons he said that they have opened one at their own territory Aiqa ^ nd that they would get # 2000 per annua which does not effect the Kuscat State revenue. The T/uzora told him that Aiqa is only a place for the residence of themselves ; nd their people and they have no right to establish Custons, etc. and station forces there like a Government. Sheikh Handan said that this question nay be discussed on arrival of 'v»H. the Sultan* Tie further st: oed that Huhaiunad bin Hasir wants the present V/ali to be removed and that the appointment of Sheikh Said bin Sultan tt l Hajatali as ^animah Sheikh over the Janabeh was not necessary* The VAizara told him that Sayid ohahab has not instigated the Kinawis against then but v/hen a foreign flag was hoisted and a Custons was established at Aiqa all the nations of Oman were agitated and joined hands with each other to take action in the matter. Sheikh Handan then asked the Council of Ministers to accompany him to Sur as if they do so all misunderstand ings would be removed, tie said that a meeting would be held at Sur* ^he Sheikhs of Janabeh would be called in the meeting and instructed to keep peace and tranquility. Sayid Shahab would also be told to be on . friendly terms with the Amirs. The Wuzara accepted his proposal rnd decided to take Sheikh Sheikh rumdan and his men by n al Said’ 1 to Sur. On the 10th December the President was again consulted whether Haji Zubeir and Sayid Said should go with Sheikh Handan to Sur or not.4 - He firat agreed Hvit then he said that it was not advisable to do so without the inioruation of ohe P»A. and if they telegraph to bin they ni^ht not receive an answer in tine* They therefore £;ave up the idea of £join£ to Hur and a-s they had pronised Sheikh Handan to take him hy 'Al Said” they wanted to put hiifl off by some ne&lt;. ns* They decided to uell him that 'Al Said' was out of order and was not fit to proceed to Sur. Sheikh Hamdan came to see me at 7~o0 p*::* on the lith December. He enquired about the policy of the .British Hovernnent towards T'uscat and whether the -British (Government would support Huscat. I told him that this point has been made clear to them by P*A* on many occasions end there was no need for me to say anything. On asking me to tell him whet it was I told him that Muscat is treaty with the -British (Government who will support Muscat when they ere asked to do so. He said that the British Government are^friendly to thejff Anirs of Ja f alan as he. 1 . ore. He further stated that the .jwirs were prepared to giv certain concessions to the British Government in Ja’alan if the British Government assure them that they would support them. He as^ccci the nai.ie of the Resident and that was given to him. On the 12th he sent a letter addressed to the P.R. When*Sheikh Hamdan was disappointed of getting L: 'ill Said' to travel to Sur he left with^nen by his own sailing boat on the 14th December 1928. • and his’ men were Sheikh Handan/stM the guest of Huscat State during his stay in Muscat ind their expenses were as follows Cash 470 dollars 6 bags rice 6 naunds coffee 3 5 halwa 1 basket datesTo British Residency and Gonbuli te-General, • . BuL^ire, ti e 1 Jth Dece l-er 1928. Shaikh Isa 'bin Saleh, Oman. A.C. I was glad to receive your letter and to hear of your safe arrival and of the prosperous state of affairs. I have recently arrived here and have so far made 'no plans regarding any tour, hut when I cone to Ifuscat I shall he xry very glad indeed to see you and shall give the 15 days notice required. Meanwhile I trust you will maintain that peace and friendship which has existed, and will continue to maintain those fi*e»dly relations with the Muscat. State which are to the benefit of both. u. Sd/- F. \V„ J o 1ms ton, Political Re-ident in the Persian Gulf.1*1)02 to subnit translation of an extract of a newspaper which was received in I'uscat on the 19th uecenber 1928. 'he paper was addressed to Tsnail Offend! Principal of T r uscat school. I ost of the people in ruscat suspect K.S. Iluharinad 8aid to he the. writer of the article because two weeks before the receipt of the paper in ruscat one of the friends of K.3. in Jaffa named Yusuf who is said to he a teacher in a school at Jaffa had cut the same article and sent it by air nail to P.S. who had told his friends about it and the news was spread in the town, t is said that the K.S. is always corresponding with the said teacher'Yusuf who was some years ago in ruscat.Extract from newspaper ’’Palestine” -o.7*5 uc^ted ^CtK jawadi I. 1347 ( l&lt;t- «- 71 % ) published in Jaffa. Keceived £•?/j •in Lius cat on the 19th December 1928. Suzerainty of I’uscat and Oman Pasture for trouble and disturbance and School for Imperialism. have published in the month of lishrin al Thani(AVw-A ) the text of the speech which was delivered in the name of the British Government by Sir Robert Holland in the gathering which was arranged for the farewell of ,r .H. Sultan Taimur bin Faisal after visiting the British country. It was said m the speech 'That many departmental reforms had been made in the suzerainty of Kuscat and Oman, the Customs departments have been put in order, roads have been reconstructed, schools have been opened, a large programme has been made for public works,'and that the financial position of the country has been laid down on a strong foundation with the help of a British Adviser that is J r. iciias Afterwards we have seen letters which had been sent by one of the notables of ruscat to his friend in Palestine and discovered that the condition was not as stated by Sir Holland in his speech. The soldiers in the forts at Snail, Jlezva, Azki, ITakhal and Rustaq. have rebelled against their Government and have reinforced their troops b^another tribe ■ called Beni Ruwaihah. 'he reasor^f their revolt was that their Imam, Huhamuid bin Abdullah al Rhalili, intended to replace them by some other people. They were annoyed with’him and at last came to a conclusion to leave at his post as Imam on condition that his uaily allowance should be 5 dollars and his power should be limited to religious affairs. Other affairs should be transferred to two persons who were disputii the imam's authority since olden days and they are Sheikh ruhammad bin Isa al 'arithi who was appointed as 'Tali and ^ Sheikh T'uhonmad Said bin Jtasir al Fundi who was appointed,s ) as Q.adhi. Beni dhafir intend to appoint Sheikh Yahya son of aMMi Salim as Imam but to this Sultan Taimur and his son Said do not a^ree. therefore one of the -»eni Ohafir named Ahmad bin T brnhin bin C&gt;ais proceeded to Bahrein on ground of coing under the medical treatment of the American* doctor but el ter- wards it wrs found out that he has been deputed by the Cman Bat ion to covenant with H.1I. King Ibn Saud ^hio called i or his interview at Riadh. During the absence of this A fiSsenger al TTaiaudah of Beni Ghafir hoisted Ibn Saudis flag for a few i days and then one of their Amirs named Ali bin Abdullah al Hamudah lowered down the flag and notified his independence from the Yuscat Government and began to collect taxes for himself* Hot being satisfied with oil o± these he attacked one of the forts belonging to Sultan iaimur and occupied it. Ihese affairs are going on but the Government of Kuscat are surprised what to do. In one of the letters received from r.uscat it is mentioned 'that the town is getting desolated every day, that merchants are shifting from it, that bribes are taken openly in Justice Court what was established a few years ago by the Sultan and Colonel 'tingate with the concurrence of the British Government, that cases are not settled in that Court, that the Sultan is aware about all these affairs but is unable to speak a word, and that 'the inhabitants are in confusion and perplexity’2 'here is a rumour in T'uscat to the effect that oayid ^aid uon of Sultan Sayid 'aitmr would succeed his father on his return from England where he had obtained the agreement of H.i:. King (ieorge V on the subject, that the present Council of rinisters would be dismissed and that no otcei j inister v/o.^ld remain for the new Sultan except one that is Hr. Bertram Thomas. Sayid Said as it is said is imprudent, inexperienced ;;nd desirous of associating with mean and ignorant persons and 9 the people are afraid of his violence if he succeeds the Sultanship. A short period ago it happened to him to go to3* 'N ' L s~\ / 5 ' c }) to Sohar in conpany with Captain \7alker an ’in^liBhraan for the purpose of collecting r!akat (alns) hut the hultcn of Cohar sent some one to inform then 'before their arrival that he would not fire any salute for them as he had no gunpowder: that action shows the extent of hatred which is exj.st.-ng 'between the neir-apparent and the h r alis* 'he disturbance in the country is so much that Shahah bin ’hiisal, ^ T ali of Cohar, fixed a telephone line between the fort and the Customs hut one of the .hairs of the ,rabs named T ''uhamnad bin llasir bin Abdullah cut that line one month a - ter its constructions and until now it has not heen repaired* As regards the revenue according to letters it is decreasing owing to had administration of Government authoriti and the had ruling of the Council of ministers- The salary of the employees has not been paid for the months of Tamuz and Ah (July f August)* Thousands of rupees are due to the merchants hy the Government who are not able to repay* The people in ruseat are hungry and for this reason many places arc put on fire so that the people may be able to plunder somethir|| for their living. 'his is a description of the condition of the inhabitants of Tuscat which greatly differs from what has heen stated by Cir Holland. Perhaps the readers have already cone to know that there is something s.ecret going on in order to create ^ disagreement between this Cultan; te and h*l_* King ^bn oauci • nd this secret fire would be suddenly kindlee( at a time when its blaze would be required by the Government who intend to affirm their influence on the coast of the Persian Gulf* j■£* would be proved that Sultan j.amir has aodicated in favour of his son Said and- that rr* Thomas the English youth j will act as his only GTazir we would then be able to decided that the Sultanate of ruscat and Oman has been given to the | ,r outh who has recently come out of school to be tiained in Imperialism, Li&lt;te nV ( G^Vo W. ^ C, X xx M h «'L Telegram (Code) tA /c w/T // ^ 4 * /~k /-N j’rom.......Resident, Busiiire, Xo Political, Muse at, Ko.1279 dated ^6-12*28. Government of India telegram of yesterday 3024-8.Begins liuscat. Government of India woula oe glaa if you would develop in more detail oy mail proposals adumbrated in your telegram of December Idtd, i2oo. In view of strong opposition from Oman tribes which ^t would bound exite proposal to remove five per cent limitation on Muscat Customs dues would require very careful handling. How would you propose to negotiate this.iends. iriease telegraph your observations. Resident. Telegram (Cypher; 7rom .political,Muse at, To Resident, Bu sh ir e, no. 163 dated 27 —jl2-2o. Sheikh Isa bin Saleh’s co-operation would perhaps be desirable corollary to uhis proposal. After consultation with and obtaining approval oi Sultan l suggest if you think it advisable tnat Isa may be approached with a viev/ to obtaining such co- -operation. he is willing to meet us to discuss presen situation and is oh friendly terms with president of Council of Ministers through whom i suggest negotiatioi be carried out. I have every hope to believe that - -tertaimnent of him and presents on fairly lavish seal would result in obtaining such oo —ope^-a-icn. Ir r political.(ol Letter dated Ja * a lan lOtli Rajab 1347 (^5 / / ld / / d8; iron Sheikh I'uhai.jaad bin Rueir al iitinudah to T'ajor 0urpliy, Political Aaent F- R.P.T^s Coneul, ITuecat. Reed. 30-12-28. - • ^ k • » A. C. t h^ve already inforned you that T 'i/ould lilce to niscuss aorae natters with the Hon’ble the Joliti^al resident and ^our honour. T an very sorry 1’or not being able to have an interview with H.1C. the Coiaiaander-in-Chief ■ r ice Adiairal Sir Pertrara S. Thesiger when he called ne to I'uscat. T could noo ci.o so c&lt;s the sea v;as rough and the weather was unfavourable. v now beg-to inform you that I am very desirous to meet the non'ble Sir Frederick Johnston, r.G.l.L., '.3.:., the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Your Honour before thi time appointed for our interview at Hur with a view to discuss with you some matters privately. After you having been acquainted with facts God willing we will meet each other egain at the fixed time at Hur. I request you to ask the Hon’ble .Sir Frederick Johnston, K.C.T.L., C.S.T., to permit ne to go to Rushire in order to discuss matters with him. T have a sanguine hope that you will allow me to cone. T 7e are obedient and able to carry out the objects of the Rritish Government when they want us to do *_o. T deputed my brother Hamdan to discuss the ns u^ers which T had in view with you but he informed ne that he could not do so as v our nonour was on the point of depsirture. If you deem advisable you nay communicate with the non'ble Tir Frederick Johnston by telegraph to ..-^et s.m e; rly replw • ^lease send me an answer by the messenger and salaams.^ (ill I Vfe-, from ^heikH. t* Letter dated iOtd nnjaL 1M7 (23-12-28) I.Tuhaiiiaad bin wasir al Karaudah, .Jiir oi JaL^l^n, tne lion’bie Sir Frederick jolmaton, K.C.I-L., Kecident m une Feraiau dual. r J.\* J • 1 nave received your letter dated 24th Hoveubcr 1228 correEpondinji to Uth Jaiaadi TI. 1347 in reply to nine and was acquainted with its contents. T was unable to tfo to ruscat when I was called by H.II. the Connander-in-Chief / ’ r ice -Admiral hir 'ertraia 2. 'hesoear. 1 no\i bea you to peruit me to cone to JJushire so that I nay discuss differences which occurred between us before the tine which has been fixed for our interview at S5ur. After you have beeone aware of our objects the question can Le settled easily by L 0 ' 1 '* It is obvious that others cannot spoil our -credir by making false and unfounded representations. YIe are more obedient and powerful than others to put into clicet the objects oi the British uovernnent when they want us to do so. I have a sanguine nope that you will axlov. rm to come ? nd see you.Uk/Zi: |r Letter dated 10th r ?; jab 1347 (23.12.28) frora Sheikh T'uh^rnmnd bin ITasir al naraudah to H.2. T ' r iGe Adniral Gir Bertram S. Thesiger* Uecd* 30*-i2-28w A. C. I am very eorry for not bein^ able to cone and pay a visit to you at T'uecat* I hope you i/ill notirpermit me to order to discuss my aiir.irs privately, ,/e are ready to comp! ] with xjlzl any order tnat you may ask us to do. I hope you will allow me to hi ve an interview \ ith you. If you desire I have pleasure to meet you even in India. U.* / litittliUjiHUfl* ^ (H- no&gt;4f -S. of 1928. Britibh Residency and Consulate-General], Bushire, 18th December 1928. . Copy of the undernoted telegrams is forwarded to the .Political Agent at Muscat, for information with a request that he will examine the question of a blockade and report by telegraph on Government of indiaiteiegram No. 2817-55., dated the 14th December 1928. By Order, for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subje ct :- SUB. List of papers. 1. felegram from the Government of ino.ia, foreign ana Political Department, hew Delhi, x^o. 2815-S., dated 14th Decemberl928. 2. - ditto - ho. 2817-S., dated 14th December 1928 . 3. Residency Telegram ho. 1265, dated 16th December 1928.. *'&gt; m -■ Telegram P. From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, new Delhi. To ii.M’s. Secretary of state for India, London, 28ib-L&gt;. T ?epaated Political He Bident, hushire, 281 b-S* Uo. 281b-8• Dated 14th (received Ibth ) December 1928. IL We agree generally with the Political Reaident. So long as present relations with Muscat remain unaltered we are not prepared to consider occupation of Sur by regular battalion which might be semi-permanent. If no decisive step is to be expected from various factions in the near future and possibil ity of Wahabi interference is remote, our immediate concern is simply the safeguarding of the finances of Muscat. There seems no doubt we could ensure this if international considerations admit control of sea trade of Jur. Hecent bombardment of Abu All’s fort has probably been useful earnest of our intentions^ t we think that except for Political Kesident lo watch situation no further action is required at present. In the laeantime we are asking; him to examine question of blockade Deference is to Political neeiaent’s telegram 120b, dated 24th ultimo, regarding bur.Telegram P. Prom Government of India, foreign and r-oiitical Department, Dew Delhio To Political heeiaent, hushire. Do. 2817-S. Dated XMXk find received i4th December 1928. Please examine the question ot geneial blockade with particular reference to respective interests of various factions in Kur, general interests of krench and other powers ana foreign ports with which tne trade is connected. Poregoing is with reference to my telegram Do. 2815-3. of the x4th December. - FORKIGD. ,r::'*~ L ,T.T-TZ*Te le gram P. Ii From Resident, Bus hire. To Government of India, Pqreign and Political Department, newDeihi, bo. x26b. Repeated H.M’a. Secretary of State for India, London, no. 1265r nol26&amp;. Dated 18th December 1928. Reference telegram no. 2815-S. , dated the,- 14th December 1928 from the Government of India, regarding 3ur. Ae pointed out in paragraph 76 of India Oflice memorandum on Muscat there seems no doubt that main diffi culty in Muscat is financial caused by five per cent limitation and effective control of Bur will not material* ly better hiat financial position. At present Kazis, Askaris public works ano. other essential public services are starved and Sultan hasnot at his disposal funds necessary to Arab ruler to entertain ana maintain relations with Shaikhs and their retinue. Bis un willingness to associate himself with public affairs may in some degree be attributed to this latter. Consequently situation in liur would appear to be system of the gradual disintegration of the Muscat State which, in these infectious times, is bound to result in from present conditions in rotate ana the only means to prevent its spread would seem to be he actual co-operation in Government of the ruler, whether the present full an or his son, with adequate means to entertain his subjects. I would therefore suggest a serious examination of the question of the removal of the five per cent limitation on customs dues at Muscat. It might be worth while giving some temporary assistance to enable the Bultan to recover control and consolidateconsolidate his power if, by doing so , -he bvate couxd 'be put on proper financial and atuainistrative footing* Otherwise any assistance so far from being temporary will only be a commitment leading to fui'ther calls ii things drift on as at present. - itKSIDKKT.m. 1^1 of 1928. Political Agency &amp; TI.B.IT’b Conculrt*, I'uacat, 31st i&gt;ece»bcr 1928. O'Neil. ■^yy^ Ll. —' / ^ A ^ J {^d/Lg* 6 ( ^Jl ^i^yu &gt; ^£7 J ^ Ur/v 'j^j rVf* :. O Tne council or wlnlsters to His Highness tho oultan or fUBcat and iMan, l£uBcat. Af t ^ r C oi ipl i»o n t u • ^ould you pleace let m« hare your views regarding the question of the general blockade of Bur. 7.t we were to stop fill vessels ut ing the port what would be the result? With what foreign ports is the trade concerned? Are there any French or other foreign - 1 interests tnere? !?ow would it aiiect the trice in the interior? Would It have any meet on the ^eni pu All? Would sheikh Isa bin fcallh object? Would the tribes in Fhnrqiyah and B&amp;diyah be able to send their crops and obtain their provisions through ruscat? I shall be glad if you would let me have your views in ae such detail as possible. M&amp;jor, political Agent A:. H.P.’Vs Consul, ruscat.Translation of a letter no *1 dated 7tn January 192* from tfte council of Ministers to nis Highness the sultan ci Muscat and Oman to Major G*H.lLurpliy &gt; I*A* political Agent and i-W-b.n 1 3 Consu 1 ,mus ca t, After/i Compliments. vve have received your .letter no.141 dated the 31i December USB asicing for our views witn regard to the gener. fclochade of Cur and enquiring firstly about the stepping boats 'wmen visit our and the result of that action. *e are of opinion that the boats should not be stopped from traffic with a view to ship the goods jhich are imported into Cur from tne interior of Oman and outside, with tne presence of a military force special arrangement should be made for tne boats which belong to the people of bur by nun- and departure according to customs regulations and a customs si snould be estabiianed at tne entrance of the creeic.^vnen these are done tne result would be good in future. conn ection of pur_trade with foreign countr ies. bur trade is connected with India,Aden^iiiohalla, Zanzibar and nasran. interests of France and pt # coun trie s. j.tO foreign Covemment have smy interest there. France was interested in certificates of boats but tnat has also been ceased. nffec t on tribes m the interior . it would not have bad effect on the tribes of the interior but if there would be no disturbance and peace be established at our it would be agreeable to them, hffee t on_ He.nl rsu Ali. iesjtne presence of a force at bur would have an effect and v/culd put an end to tneir objects and intentions at bur against the Muscat Government and would stop them from in terf erring with the goods which are exported from bur to nadiyah and other towns of bharqiyah.btie i&amp;i lea bin ^aXeJa^ titxei&amp;n lea would not object to tirua plan but would approve of xt-vlde ilia previouo oorreopondence with the &amp;uacat Crovernnent pereuading them to ta«e action a^ainet anyone who loaves interference at bur such aa neni hu All* i noe a o f ^nargiyah a iid n adiya^ » •*ed. Ao mention-by ue above if boat# are not prevented from traffic trie tribe# of i*narqiyah and hadiyah would come to bur aa ueuai m order to exj»crt tneir good# and remove their im ports. Usual ending*From. *,political,-Muscat, To s i d en t, ±$u shi r e, no. Id-rC• dated oth oar ai'j Keference your letter no. 461-2.dated 13th December. no x^ei-ch or otner foreign interests involved. Dftows trade with India,Aden, ncfcaiia, Zanzibar.East Africa and uasrah. mows number about 150 of these 130 belong to oeneben and eight ot ten to au aocut one twelfth of ejc^orts are from nu All remainder chie-il iioan ; 1 s territory, nu AH absorb about one fifth of imports and Jenebeh about one seventh. Dhows leave sur at end of rnonsocn return just before monsoon. Strict -blockade Would doubtless affect Jenebeh, who are the carriers, and bu Ali most as tribes m X 2 :ai ‘s territory could deal through Muscat -though at greater expense Of dhows at bur only two have taken trouble to register according to Muscat Government rules, and some pressure could do-bule^s be effecteli by msistance on the production of proper papers v. when they visit our ports. political.Translation oi a letter dated llth JanadI IX* 1347 (24tn. Uovemoer 1928) iroti SneiKh Isa Din t&gt;alin to tde !{on 1 ole the Political -riecident &amp; consul cenerc-l Bushire* rieceiTea in ruse at 29/11/28. A.C. T Deg to inTorn you tnat I have sarely arriYed at my country c:nci tnanii uoa tnat tuere is notning v/orth mentioning but good. X promised in my previous letter to send you ; : n intimation with regard to our interview. I am re; dy to nave an interview with you with a viev; to strengthen tne iriendsnip whenever you desire and i hope that it would result into good* The time can ne lixed oy you and 1 pray vrod ror nelp and may you oe prosperous and salaJins. P.S. TThen you have decided to come and I received your letter to tnat enect 15 days* tine is required oy me (to make the necessary preparations)* r cH r L~ ^(&amp;,wj ) Letter Lo.118 dated 5th Lecenber 1928 from the Council of llinistere to h.H* the Sultan of Hus cat and Oman to I.Iaj or G.P. Ilurphy, I.A., Political /^;cnt and P.B.lPs Consul, Kuscat* A.C. 7/c heg to subrait some points about Sur and they are as follows:- Since the 2nd Janadi II, 1347 (16/11/28) when T MI. the Admiral, T . r our honour and ourselves returned from Sur the condition is quiet there. You are Ui are about the actions which are being taken by al Haiiudah, the Sheikhs of Beni Ali, as was explained by us to you. One of the important thing is the question of establishment of a Custom house at Aiqa which they have no right to do as it would cause deficeit to the revenue of the I’uscat State. In confirmation of this is the present dispute which is going on between the Chinese and the Customs Department at Sur. The Chinese refused to pay duty to the Customs of the Yuscat State on the ground that J^eni Du Ali had recovered \ duty from them. This is the result of their actions. They interfere with the affairs of the subjects of the Sultan and misrepresent natters to them and afford help to some of them in consequence of which they show disloyalty and disobedience to the Government. Ye have already submitted other questions concerning Beni Bu Ali and explained that owing to their interference VI at Sur the people of the interior of Oman have agitated as they absolutely do not agree that -^eni Bu Ali make the least interference in the affairs of Sur. The Omanis were agitated when they noticed their (Beni Bu Ali’s) interferem but when the Council of ninisters proceeded to Sur and aioott shew some sort of force and they came to know that the high Government-would xxfxaxct support the Government of H.H, the Sultan of T'uscat and the Political ll esident wrote a letl letter to Sheikh Isa bin Salih informing him that he would make arrangement and take action in the affairs of Sur at tl the time fixed by him, the Omanis have kept quiet at presentpresent* r ?he Council of rinisters Ik ve nov/ received a letter from Sheikh Isa expressing his thanks ( 2 nd appreciating the prompt action which was taken hy the Council with the assistance of the British Government in these affairs, '.7e be^ to brin^ to your notice that in our opinion it is necessary that' decisive action should be taken and force be used at Sur and therefore we request you to represent our views to our friend, the ui^h Government. Sheikh Tlandan bin Uasir, brother of Sheikh ruhammad bin Nnsir al Hamudah has arrived at nuscat and states that he has come on behalf of his brother and that they are loyal to the Muscat Government but we do not confide on such statements as they say so but do not prove it by action. The inhabitants of Sur are now waiting to see what would be result in future. /3rTelegram (codey From roll ticaijKuecat, To iiaj or murphy, su. sliire, *0. 1471 dated 8th Uecemher 1328* Following is gist of letter received from the Council. Besides referring to the' case of ^yr\ the’Chinaman and actions of Amirs the/state(l; ' &lt;r the Amirs have no right to establish customs ( house at Aiqa which would reduce states revenue ^2; Their interfejrance with Sultans subjects in Sur and misrepresentation of matters result dis- -loyalty and encourage^ agitation in interior (3; Council ask decisive action may be taken in Sur and request you represent their views to Government (4) that although Amirs brother now m tiuscat acknowle*dges loyalty and obedience to \ muscat Government they do not believe in such statements (5() inhabitants of Sur are awaiting to see further developments and future result. /5S4ajuA ’ political •Telegram (Code) To • jr'olitical*Museat &gt; Ko. 8258 dated 13tiri December x922* /cur telegram dated 29th 1!ovbmber ^0.158 8heikh All bin Abdulla left Aden for Kodeida 11th December intending to visit imam's son and there- -after Jeddah, On arrival at Aden on 3rd December anchored yacht off Union Club and expected treatment as honoured guest but received only cold civility and Resident did not accord interview, behaved mildly here and associated only with Muscat traders and apparently did not engage in propaganda, Hesieent.4 No. 4^6-3. oT 1923. British Rosiuency ond CJonsolate-G-eneral, Busuire, 26th Noveahor 1928. The undermentioned papers are forwarded to the Political A.gent, Muscat^ By order, ’ _ t., Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 1. Copy of Political Resident's letter to the Govt, of India No. 423-8, dated 23rd November. 2. Letter from the Political Resident to Shaikh Muhammad Lin Nasir al Hamudah, \jnir of Ja'alan, No. 272, dated 24th NovemLer, for transmission to addressee. 3. Uopy of 2 for ^jency records. A k suuc /y^■ CONniiSNTIAI,. V No. 423-3. of 1928. British Rasidanoy and Consulate-General, Bushire, 23rd November 1928. From The Hon*hie Sir F.W.Johnston, K.C.I.S., C.S.I., ICS Political Resident in the Persian GrUlf# The foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, b*/lG '3 New Delhi. I have the honour, in continuation of my letter No. 404-S dated 12th November 1928, to forward letters noted in the margin from the Political Agent, Muscat. The statement of the Amir of Jaalan is inter- -esting, that he is not flying a foreign flag hut his own, m I am replying to the Amir informing him that I am glad to receive his assurances as to his correct behaviour and think that he will he well advised to act as suggested hy Major Murphy. A copy of this letter and enclosures is being forwarded to His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India. I have the honour to he, Sir, Tour most obedient servant, Sd/- F. W. Johnston. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.No of 1928 No. 2 ~J3 of 1928. British Bosidenoy ^nd Consulate-General, Bushire, the 24th November 1928. To Snnikh Muhammad bin Nasir ;1 Uamudah, amir of Ja’alan. After Oompliments. I havo received your letter dated 17th Jamadi If 1347, to tne address of my predecessor, the !on*ble Lieut-Colonel Cir L. laworth. I am glad to receive your assurances as to your correct behaviour. I think you will be well advised to net as suggested by ”ajor Murphy in his letter No. 144, dated the 12th November 1928 (28th Jnmadi I, 1347). . U.B. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.n C&gt;t V ! Letter dated 27th Jnnadi IT. 1^7 (lOtd -ecencer 1928) from Sheiith Hawdan oin No sir al rianudah to ttie rionlcl _ _ .rvPSiiClCnt JjriCl .H. • ^ 1?.^..Johnston, K.C.I.TS., C.S.I., olitlGci ^coia Consul General ]-5ushire. need. 12-12-^8. '\h A.C. T beg to state tnat l have cone to 1 ’uscat on oehrli oi ry or other, ruhannaa bin aasir. Amir of ou*alrn, to apologise iron H.B.IT'S consul at muscat m oraer to convey sane to H.E. trie , Vice Admiral wuo aSKed my orotner to cone ana see am at muscat out it did not tuice place at tnat time as you nvre neard.tne wlnd , vas not favourable lor travelling iron Bur to muscat.^ I an authorised to discuss ooout the friendly relations which was existing between our predecessors and yours with H.r.r’s Consul T'uscat but 1 could not discuss trie whole natter with him as 1 only met him one time. I hope you will scxiWatxJKXB* continue your rriendsmp. 7/e are willing to carry out every triing tnat you nay ask us to do. hod willing we will not disobey you. we have got country and a large number of people. 7e would like to make an agreenent .„Uh you in every respect and to renew our relations and treaty v. with you. hod willing on your arrival at Bur you will cone to an agreement 'Mth tne Amirs us you desire. perhaps you nave neurd tnut we nave noisted Ibfcn Saud's flag at Bur. mis' news is absolutely unfounded and on your s’•rival at but we will make it clear tnat it was a mere accusation against us by our enemies. ■ve are r-iendiy to the Tuscnt Government and we are their supporters nnd tney are adopting tne sane attitude towards us. You should be rest assured.Tv Letter dated 26th Jtuaadi II. 1347 (9th Lecenher 1928) r i ce-AcLniral from Sheikh T^uhajnraad hin TTasir al Haiaudah to T Tie Excellency / .3. Thesiger, C.B., C.H.a., Coramander-in-Shief. Heed.10-12-28- T am sorry for not having the pleasure of meeting you and t hope that we will meet each other some time. I heg to inform you that I have sent my Brother Handan Bin Basir to I uscat in order to discuss some matters with the I’uscat Government and H.B.E’s Consul and perhaps you have heard about iu* I hope you will preserve the friendship which was existing betv/eei my predecessors and yours as it is recoraed in the ^on^ulcte at I uscat• U. 11.Confidential* iio.l of U2*. Political Agency anvi Consulate, Muscat 2nd January 1^2^# From Major G. P* Murpjay, X.A., Political Agont and Consult Muacatf To The Hon'ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rlj UiiiiCii Sir, X ha.Te the honour to report that nous v/as received here on the 24th December that two AsJcaris of tne jiali of bur had been Killed by men of the Maichana section of the Jenebeh at bur. The history of tne trouble,as related to me oy tne Council of Ministers, is as follows:- There is a feud of old standing between the Maioiana section of the Jenebeh and the Hifthm tribe. borne years ago,some of the Hishm wished to enter bur and sent a party accompanied by some of the Bani Umr As-taris of the wali in order to negotiate a truce. The MaKhana section shot one of the Asicaris accompanying this party and in retalia tion, the AsKaris shot tne murderer. Truces had been arranged between the parties at various times and tne trouble *as more or less in abeyance until its present re crude stance. baiyid Mahomed,the president of the Council,is of opinion that the Beni Bu Ali have instigated the present case. The party of Bani Umr Asicaris in question have been in bur some time and this does not refer to the party sent last year in place of the wahabi AsKaris. I have the honour to be, bir, Your most obedient servant. Maj or, ?Musca t*p. r* • Telegram From Political Resident, Bushire To Repeated No. 40. Government of India, New Delhi. Secretary of State for India, London. Dated 18th January 1928. Any repressive action at Sur would presum -ahly he taken 'by the Sultan himself, assisted 'by H.i-*s. Government, in which case it DUt —closure oi a pCTTIT, when other nations do not seem to he involved. I have consulted Thomas and at present juncture do not mmxmx think that immediate repressive measures are required at Sur and would on general question prefer to await full report which I have asked Political Agent to submit after consultation with Sultan and Thomas on their arrival. Reference is to your telegrams 2815-3 and 3024-S of 14th and 25th Decemher respectively. R^SIDSNT Post copy to Political Agent, Muscat. Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram P /'-*-• Prom Govermaent of India, foreign and rolitical l)e ^ar trie n t, new Del . To H.H’u. Secretax^' of State for India, Lonuoi Repeated Political Peoiaent, Bumiire. Wo. 304-f&gt;. Dated 22nd (received 2ord ) January 1929. Vide Bub hire telegram dated 18 th January, Ho. 40-L. Die cue b ion witii tiie Amir will preoumably take place shortly after the Multan, vrazir and rolitical Agent have net. Oovernxaent of inuia'o view on the wider question of hub cat policy will be sent on receipt of report from the Political Keoicent. Reference your telegram no. 17th. Post copy to the Political A t ,ent, Muucat, for information. Bur, hire. 23rd January 1929.Letter aiaxccl t najan 1547 ( ,7 tn January 19^8 ) iror., 7 ay id 8hahabTin ^aiflal, ^ali of ^ur, to the Council of Ministers to H.TT.the 'ultan of ruscat ^ Oman, necci. .,.-1-29. A.C. . t bee to st;te th; t cone days ago ShelKh Gaia Din Sultan al !*aj f ali sent me a letter addressed to, him Dy Ali Din Sul a inan &lt;*\nd ruhamnad bln Rashid of 7'aKhana section i/ho coinnitted the murder and were made to escape (Iron Sur,. A copy or that letter is enclosed herev/itn. J called the Ilaichana and warned tnem tnat they would De held responsible for any action which may be taKen by the oirenders. rn the afternoon of yesterday slave of ji; sir bin Ali al Hashshar was Kidnapped iron yu Gads Iran hills. TThen the Kidnappers were pursued and surrounded they released the slave and ran away, '’‘he Kidnappers were Ali bin Bulaiman and one of the fiashayekh (sub-section of al ralchatirah). ^he offenders after Killing the two men (of neni Omar} proceeded to al Hanudah vrio apparently did not give them any assylam. A certain Caiman who is a dependant of al Hanudah took them to the al rtashayekh, sub-section ol al Tf akhatirah ; who are not in treaty with al nanudah. The^, accepted to keep them and expressed their willingness to support them. [ request you to warn tne Makhana triat tney v, r ould be held responsible i or any action wmch may oe committed oy tne murderers. Letter dated ibth Rajab 1347 (28.12.28) from Ali bin Suleiman and ruhammad bin Rashid to Sheikh »aid oin Sultan 'P Ha j * ali and ail the iFanabeh. viz Ifakhana, .rana, (.rhialin and 'vuwaria. rje beg to state tnat you nave especially started fighting &gt;V \/ith us. You intend to do away vrlth out lives and property. You have icillcd our camel. CV l Letter dated ‘^bth Hcija'D 1347 (7th. *Januf).ry 1929) Iron Sheiich Haalr Din l/iuharoiaad ot Araaa section to the council oi Ministers to H.H.the Sultan of fuscat F Ouan*itecd* 12-1-29. A - f I *beff to state that yesterday a nan was Kidnapped on the way leading to the jialad. Che Kidnappers were the son oi 'dulairian al MaKhaini ana the at nasnayeich al Jabal. Say id G ha hah called tne iaaichana ana warned then tm t they would ce held responsible any action which nay be taicen by the son oi Sulairaan. Some people pursued the kianappers. The neni Ciaar also followed then and v/hen they (kidnappers) sc-ijcvKsaai saw that they would he overtaken by the pursuers they released the slave, beat him and ran away. llease write to the hakhana warning then that they would be responsible for any action which may be cormitted by the son of Sulairaan.. Other news will be connunicated to you by ''ayid ^hahs b bin ^aisal.Letter dated 26th najah J.347 (8th January ±929) from the TTakhana section of Sur to the Council of Ministers to ?&gt;.n. the Sultan of rusoi-t c. Ox^un. Heed. 12-1-2 -j. A * : ±- * i/e have received your letter dated the 13th Hcijalx (26.12.28) intixaating aoout the incident v.-nich occurred t 0 the \Bakris. Yea the nurdererd rxn were not -■xkaris but as we have already informed you they were our dependants aradbqsa. . have to retaliate for them and we hope to do so. We are pleased to see that you ere adninistering justice in the affairs of the subjects. ~&gt;ayid hfiahab arranged for a truce rnd peace has been established, 'layid Hhuhab has warned both parties and we have accepted the truce m order to keep and tranquility. Abdullah bin Wall:., Chief of tseno Omar iskaris, is taking some actions by his own accord without the agreement and orders of the Government. ..•here is nothing particular Between us and trie Askaris. We have accepted the truce and you can decide between us ; nd Abdullah Din mafia who is the auffcfor of ail , these trouhles. You should instruct him not to commit any thing irregular. We are,God willing, as you expect,obedient and submissive to you*fr / (Tit) Letter dated 6th Kanazun 1347 (17.2.29) from Sheikhs Salim Lin .,Ldullah and tiaiadan Lin naeir al Hamudah to major G.P*Murphy, T .A., Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul Muscat. * T e In ve alrerdy sent :/ou i letter informing you c Lout the death of our brother Mir Huham ad ’bin T^asir al Hamid ah and asking for the renewal of the friendly relation which s oxi; ting LetY'oen our predecessors and you If^t we fid not receive r n mswer. c h‘ ve no\/ especiv lly seriu a n* n on our feh;If to converse this matter with you. 'e hope that you a ill Le ;ood enough to he: r his representations and renew our fri&lt; n hip ; nd r L; tiono with gour ro .a.' nt. e »^^e ready to comply v/ith your wishes except the important affairs which may require consultation \ i/ith our orother ./e hope you v.ill send an answer Ly this messenger. Thanking you in anticipation and sal; «... i lk, m Please send this letter to the Hon’Lie the Kesident at '^ushire.H0.3&amp;-£-0f 1929. rfr- lit ’f\Y^ Political Agency and H*B*M* s Consulate, Muscat 26th February 1929• T# The Hon*ble the Political Kesident in the Persian (julf, Bushire. Memorandum* it,&lt;n In continuation of my Memo.25-C*dated the 11th translated February 1929,1 for ward,herewith,a/copy of letter dated 6 th Mamazan 1347 (17-2-29) from Sheiichs Salim bin Abdullah and Hamdan bin Basir al Hamudah to my address on the subject of the death of their brother the late Sheiich imhammad bin Basir al hamudah Amir of Jaalan and my reply to them. Major, political Agent and H.B.M's Consul,Muscat. *2^Y r\ 4 'i* '^xtruct jTron nev.Ljj per ”j-ioura.' puLliehea in Cairu^cu ted. loth February 1929* 2 ound the argument of ^raaia al Khalili eind the et tenents of the other p&lt;rty. \n Arabian Aiir apealcs. m q the eloquent \. r riter and faithful p; triot Say id liuheiiuiad Ali Tahir aiay always he prosperous* * offer you ny .reetinys : nd ‘eat coi pliments. - have reed whit has appeared in your newspaper ’Shoura* 1 Tos* 203 and 204 under heading ’aryui.ient of the v nan of Cr.ian al Khalili written by Isa bin Sa-ih al harithi ayainst Britain and the Muscat Gavermaent* I was surj d to see the d*ring of the writer, his false allegations and boldness to accuse us of having comiitted treachery and hoisted i foreign fxag without being in possession of any proof in hand. Firstly he alleged that we had hoisted a foreign flag which we had obtained frora the T 'ing of TT ejaz and ITejd in our town Aiqa which is situated near bur. Tr e has also once alleged that we are under the Government of T 'uscat and in axxgxxxdi-atix r another place he has stated that we are under the Government of 'bn Baud. m hese statements are unfounded bee; use such arguments have nothing to do with him neither concerns the 'hiara of Oman nor Isa nor the I'us cat Government but this affair concerns the British Government only because she is the master of all seas especially the coasus oj. the Indian n .:ea. In reality the nan is an in^ertinent. The British Legatie Chief of the Persian Gulf asked us officially ’'Have you hoisted a foreign flag m your town ^wiau besides your a;sm.-i. flag 1 ' we replied ^v/e have not hoisted a foreign flag other th n our own usual one”. This is the real fact but the ravings of ' r sa are unfounded. .Vs to bis statements sometimes that we have separated ourselves from the Muscat Government and sometimes from his Government consisting of all district*and the Cult, nate of Oman as alleged by him and that w r e h; e no _. led ourConfidential, Ho,P,4937-N. i'rom The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Hon^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire, / L Dated Hew Delhi, the // *. December 1926 Questionnaire regarding Sur, Sir, I am directed to forward a w Questionnaire regarding Sur H and to request that the Government of India ruay be fumibhed with the information referred to therein, 2. A copy of this letter and enclosure is being forwarded to the Political .agent, }&amp;iscat, direct. I have the honour to be, Sir Your most obedient servant. Sd. A.E.B. Parsons, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India Copy,with a copy of the enclosure, to the Political Agent, Muscat, 'X Attested, Superintendent Foreign and Political Departmentm l?' Questionnaire regarding 3UR« 1» %at landing facilities are there at Sur for troops, animals and heavy vehicles ? 2. Water Supply # (a) Total number of wells available and their approximate capacity. (b) How are the wells lined ? (e.g. with brick ?) (c) Diameter of wells. (d) Depth of surface of water below ground level. Does this vary with time of year and if so how ? (e) Height of water in wells, i.e. distance from bottom of well to surface of water. (f) Minimum daily yield from wells, in gallons, which could be relied on. Does this vary with season of year. (g) Kow much water would be available for troops after the needs of the inhabitants had been met. (h) What noseibilities are there of obtaining water from other places along the coast within reasonable distance of SUR, and if these possibilities are worth consideration what means of transport exist. (i) Would it be possible to sink fresh wells after troops had landed. If so what localities are recommended ? 3. Supplies . (a) ’.Yhat local supplies are obtainable. (b) What quantity (approx.) would be available for troops ' after the needs of the civil population had been supplied. (c) Are there any possibilities of extending cultivation. 4. Transport . (a) ’/That local forms of transport are there. (b) Gould these be used for any purposes and in what quantities. (c) Are there any restrictions to movement in the vicinity of Sur. * 5. Accommodation . (a) Is there any suitable covered accommodation available for housing troops. (b)(b} If not, would tents be suitable or would it be necessary to provide hutting. If the latter, is material available locally. (c) is the selection of camp sites entirely governed by water supply. 6 . Defence . (a) 7/hat are the most suitable positions for defence (i) of the town (ii) of the troops, taking as a basis a minimum strength of i Bn. (b) What points of local tactical importance should be occupied.^ 7. Eng i neer Store s. (a) What defence stores would be required and in what quantities, e.g. barbed wire and pickets for v/ire entanglements, sandbags, picks and shovels. (b) What water supply stores would be required ? Pumping plant Pumps for wells Piping Portable tanks for storage of water Portable filtration plants. 3. Are any sites available near 3ur, suitable for use as landing Grounds. Estimate in man hours the amount of work required in preparation.® T TIAI. No. 47^'^ of 1923. British Residency and Oonsulate-Greneral, Bushire, 22nd Decemhar 1223. To The Political A^ent, Muscat. III Ml I IfU: un MBMORANDUM. Please furnish answers through this office to the Questionnaire regarding Sur forwarded under cover of Foreign and Political Department letter No. D.4S37-N, dated 11th December 1923, copy of which has been forwarded to you direct. By order, For Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GulfConfidential. /z4 »0.48-C of 1929 # Political Agency and Con 8 ulate # Muscat 1st April 1929 # Prom Major Cr. P. Murphy, I*A., rolitical Agent and Consul, Muscat, To The Hon 1 Die tne rolitical Kesident in tne rersian trulf, Sir, Hushire. with reference to your Memorandum Mo.4?4~S dated 22nd December 1923,1 have the honour to forward,herewith,answers to trie questionnaire regarding Sur which was forwarded to me under cover of Foreign and Political Department letter No*D»4937H dated 11th December 1928, I regret it has taken me a considerable time to obtain these answers. The questions had been submitted to the Council of Ministers who referred several questions to the Wali at Sur and my replies are based on these answers,which have been received a few days ago ,and on information received from other sources* I have the honour to be, 8 ir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Political Agent and H.B.M^s Consul,Muscat*Answers to questionnaire regarding SUB. It. There are three small badans available at Sur suitable for landing troops but not mules or heavy vehicles. Khan Bahadur Nasib 9 the Haval Contractsr and Landing Contractor at lu&amp;Asoat whs made all ari'angements for landing troops at Matr&amp;h in 19139could send 3 big badans under their own sail and 5 big badans tewed by steamer from Muscat and could undertake all landing arrangements. The people of Sur swe him over 2 lakhs and he would be as anxious as any one to see settled condi* — tio.i b there. There are ne piers* Badans would have to be beached and heavy vehicles etc removed at low tide/^. 2. (a) There are said to be 95 wells in Balad as Sur which are used both as a water supply for the town and for cultivation. It would be difficult to gauge their approximate capacity. The Council of Ministers recommend three named SanghahfHasa and Sabarkhah. (b) These three wells are lined with stones and cement. (c) Their diameters are 11 feet 21 feet and 28 feet respectiv- -ly. (d) The depth of water is between 15 and IS feet.lt does not vary with the seans-of the year but the water level rises i after rain (usually in the cold weather), ve) 2 te 3 feet. (f &amp;«) 1 have been unable to ascertain their minimum daily yield or the amount which would be available for troops after the needs of the inhabitants have been met but water is plentiful and X understand there would be sufficient available gut for a force of 10 9 GOO men. (h) There are 11 wells at S&amp;kaikrah (next Sur creek)»built of stone and cement 12 to 15 feet deeptheight of water It te 2 feet 9 diameters varying from 16 to 24 feet. There are 2 wells at Sanaisleh but they do not contain much water. Donkeys and camels are available for transport of water.(i) It would seem unnecessary to sinlc more wells. 3. Supplies. (a) Rice and wheat imported from India,are available in Sur. Dates from Sharqiyah are plentiful, dodder is available from Balad as Sur. wood is available locally. Chickens,eggs and miiic are plentiful. Dal,Sugar and meat are available, jfresh vegetables are not obtainable but could be grown in Balad as Sur. (b) rroduce arrives from the interior daily. Supply is probably governed by the demand and it would be difficult to gauge the approximate quantity which could be made available for troops. (c) There is plenty of ground available for extension of cultiva tion. 4» Transpor t• About 50 doniceys and 50 camels are available in sur. More coul&lt;2 be obtained from the interior.There is no wheeled transport in the country. The roads through the town are broad but the road between jaaqriinatain and Balad as Sur would need some worJc on it before it would be suitable for wheeled transport.The country round sur is of an open nature which offers few res. -trictions. 5» Accommodation. (a) ho. (b) Material is available locally for the coustruction of huts but Jfcnxix this may not be necessary as tents would be suit- -able at least for the greater part of the year. Sur is not surrounded by roclcy hills and does not experience the intense heat of Muscat. There is usually a cool breeze blowing throughout the year. (c) Yes. 6 f Defence. The most suitable position for the defence of the town and of the troops would appear to be on the low ridge called Red which rises 50 feet high from stony flats and x runs from south east to north west at a distance of two miles behind the town and between the town and Balad as Sur. ThisThlc ridge ia studded wrtlx squcure blocic-iioueea and eosraaajode both the town and ^alad as Jur vdicre the water mpply is situated* Juaiaaer aterea* X am not qualified to ans'ver these questions# rreertimhlily sufficient engineer stores would be required for the defemoe of the pariweter camp and any 3 plcqueta the Officer Cocm&amp;mUng laay place in bloe£- •houseetever the water eupply and in any other suitable point of Yantage* A supply of guncotton for the deciruotion of any bxocic^noueel which it is not prepoaed to occupy but wmch might afford ahelter to sniper wouixl probably be inquired* (b) ’Hie supply of pumping plant piping tanice and filtration plant would be a question fox* an e:igineer of floor to answer and would presumably on the rwtmbsr of troops and the site selected* b* Plat ground is available near isj^nalslah ^hich mignt be suitable for a landing ground* X ioa not qualified to ceti^te in mar; k . irb tne araount of ^/orit required in preparation but I should say &amp; oompan could clean ouiiicient ground in a few hours* tQior al Jarsnahgan in length &amp; situated 12-£ miles inlet from the sea ion irg a eijitllov; b&amp;ninf*yj^r ilc^_eant of mr would probably form a suitable baee for ceRplanep and flying boats. Major* roiitioai .&lt;\geht ani • Con suit sub cat*.movers to questions v/itn re ;,rd to 3ur&lt; n ) 1. V/itn re ;; ra to 1; ndm ; or troo] s ond otner t-rticies, trie an Intis which '.re s.v; iij.bie ;.t Sur re CcU’eia c.nci donkeys * ^'icre - re dnov/s oieo. ^ T ; ter sn 'Ily« There : re three suito!ule wo ter wells called c ’an;; hah, has a s-nd ’■'ahailchah. The de^th of these wells fror tne -round to the surfoce of the vater V' ries hetuoen 15 to 13 feet and fror. the our^-ce of the water to tie botton carries he tv:: on 2 to 5 feet, '’heir water do not decrease’ during trie seasons of the year but incre ses when there is nuch r; infail* Their dianeter: the first one is 11 feet, the Second 21 feet and the third 2S fret* They are huilt 'by stones id ce? ents. These v/ellc are in the fa lad near the fort* There are 7 roads iron tne seashore to tne fa lad* Two of then naaiely ai Tajj a nd Saj|aisla h roads a:re s. .oath hut it is necessary to have then rev-' ired ; nd levelled so that carts ana « vendclds nsy be able to run o^er then. T'ley -: re loi _ roads but fanaislah at they re snoo-th. ter is also obtains’le at Salailtrah a?nd / a shorter dist- nee than the wells which werep'irstly w.entioned in the .holad* ''here are in one spot at hakaikrnh 11 wells iron i.-nich the \ x ' inhabitants who are living near the- seashore are tahin^; their ou ly. ''heir lepth fron the “round to the surface of the water varies between 12 to 15 feet and the hei ;ht of the water iron the bottom of the well up to the surface of the uniter varies ' etween 1-J- to- 2 feet, '’heir diaueter varies ’ etr-een If to 24 feet. They re built by stones and eerient and their water does neither decrease during tne seasons of the water nor when the ^eople take tneir supply but increases during rainfall. There . re two. otner wells at isa.^lslah nd the road leading to then is smooth but they do not cont- in nuch water* 3. stores. (a) '’he foodstuffs which - re av- liable at fur are- rice and wheat which are imported fron Indio nd dates which are*fronZ (*b) quantity oi trieae stores can do o 1 trained in th.e ') O. Z; i i; r * (c) giipII area of round can V-e o])t^:lred for cultivation* ^ * ’’’r-' nt: ' ort. (a) AS ve !irve already mentioned before cane Is and donkeys are only r ' il;d le there. (b ) xibaut 50 cartels ; nd 50 donkeys : re available but it is possible to pet no re of then 1'ron other pl/ces when required. (c) There is no restrictions for the raovenents of the troops st tur neither on the seashore nor in the Palad. 5 * Ts'cllinQ (a / There ore no suit; ble houses for the dwelling of the troops (b ) Tents re suitable for then and houses can be built in tine of need. PuilcUn.p materials such as stones, mud, lines and rood can be obtained at Pur. ( c } 'Toter is far fron the seashore of Tur but if the station be p r;de at the a 1 &lt; t d tlie water is c..ose to i .. 6. Defence. There are 4 places i.high“i 3 .re Suitable for military A osts. They are h.oa, al Tajj, Tub a iL-aX-nicl and al path. 7 * - ^n^inc e r1np stores. (a) Barbed wire is ^ood for making; enclosures and pickaxes and shovels re suitable articles for work. (b) Pumps and other necessary pipes i.re pood for takinp out w a t e r fro n v; ells. ranks • re suitable for EisrcxRxxnsK water similarly riasaks skins J. 'bese would be carried by animals, ’he 5 water can reserved ■’'n bip tanks. (i, r a ter be . 'he bi ; rest place near Bur which is suitable for nnp round is Banaislah. 3No. 115-S. of 1929. British Resi&amp;eriijr and Consulate-General a -vs 4 1 1 QOO From- The Secret 9 .ry to the Hon’hie the Political Pecident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Political Agent, Muscat. Memo randum. Reference your memorandum Ho. 28-C., dated the 26th February 1929. The enclosed letter is forwarded for transmission to the addressees through the Muscat State Authorities, By Order, Secretary to the Po].itical Resident in the Persian Gulf.No M3 of 19S9 British BesicLenoy &amp; Oonsulate-General, Bushire, the 17th April 1929. I To Salim hin Abdullah and Hamdan bin Nasir, Amirs of Ja’alan. ATter Oompliments. I have received your letter of the 6th Bamazan 1347 and convey to you my sympathy on the death of your brothei Muhammad bin Nasir on whom be peace etc. U.E. Sd/ F. V. Johnston, Political Besident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram* From...The Resident, Aden, To The Political, Muscat, Dated..The 11th July 1929. /fo71 07 Shaikh Ali bin Abdulla referred to in my telegram dated 13th December No.A-8258 left Jedda 6th instant for Massawa. Copy by post. Ag: Superintendent, Residency Office, Aden.j *3=0 Ho . ^S-s. .929. &lt;7$.. /fr&gt; &lt;fZ Britisli Assidency &lt;?c Conaulwte Gerierc,!, 5U! irw the J ~ September *329. A co^y of the -undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Politico.! A^ent, Muscat, with a request that the rton’ble the Politico.! Resident nay he furnished with his viev^s thereon. '^4 m 'N - By order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum from the Senior Hava! Officer, Persian Gulf, H0.44/B/44/3, dated the 22nd Aujust 1929 and enclosure, re^ardinj affairs at t&gt;ur.Senior naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, fl.M.S.’•Triad* 1 at Muscat. Coimnander-in-Chief, sast Indies Station. (Copy to the honourcitle the Political nes~‘ ent in tne Persian Gulf). ^ate - S2nd August x929. no. - 44 .B/ 44/3 From - The To - The The attached re^^ort from the Commanding officer, H.M.S. 'Cyclamen'• concerning affairs at Sur is submitted for the information of the Commander i - Chief. The r; -^ n view of tne history of Sur for t o uast century id would seem that no permanent improve-e t is li :cely to be achieved there without very radical treatment, app-ica Lion of such treatment however could hardlv considered without raisin^ the larye question of the po icy of the Government of India to wards f&gt; ~ mud cot State. 3d/- H. B0Y3S,n p’ rs ,T -r&gt;T n pi rf r * COOTrDlffTIAL Prom Date To The 9th The Cornmandi n w Of fi j er, H.M.S. Cyclamen' August ±929 jnio.05 Senior JUaval Officer, Persian Gulf. at sur. S U in confirmation and amplifiw^tu. .. v « U^ow/1th August, I have the honour to sh it the re x wrt with reference to the s^tuation at Sur. f o11owin' h.H.S. 'Cyclainen' anchored August. A boat immediately came Abdullah, Amir of hini Bu Ali, wa expected 'to arrive b„ man of war Ali bin Abdullah was not on board off Sur at .i.730 on 8th off and inquired if Ali bii s on board ae he was . un beiii^ informed that the boat returned to Aiha 3. It v/as observed on arrival that the jreen and red (Wahabi) fla^ was flying over Aida ii spite of the assurances which (according to my recollection; were ^iven to the Commander-in-Chief, .Bust indies station that this flay v/culd in future not e flown. rt was furtl or observed Oxi a. t t j.n s flag late* 1 • uled down and not flown again durinj A.M.S. 'Cy clamen * s n visit. 4. The Wali of Sur visited H.J■.S. 'Cy r c 1 amen' at O' OC on 9th August, ne stated to the Commandinj officer that although e j hing was ^uiet at the moment he thought there would soon be trouble as the Beni Bu Ali were agitating for independence fro*:, Muscat. Their A-iir, Ali bin Abdullah, v; s expected back daily from a visit to Italy where he had rone to enlist support for a risi:^ against the Sultan of un n, similar visits to the lemen and to Ibn Saud having been unsuccessful. 5. The Wali further stated th^t it was i .comi increasingly difficult to obtain payment of customs dues from the Beni Bu Ali, and he feared attempts to make them pa v . wo ul ^ only ^ recipi tate trouble. Me also stated fut the ringleaders were known and that the numbers of their followers were increasing. 5. in conclusion the Wali stated that although since the death of Muhoned uin nasir, which took ^lace shortly after the events of last .November, the situation had been quiet it was now be w innin^ to become troublesome again. 7. A Customs representative came on board and informed the Commanding officer that the arrival of one of H.M. Ships had coused considerable fear among the p-eorjle, but the •vali*s view of this Y/as that although they mere frightened while a ship was there they very soon for_ out when she hs ^one. SD/- 7/.S. CA?.SC1T?No. 580-S of 1929. British Residency 4tna Consulate-General, Bushire, 3lst October 1929. Prom To The Hon’ble Lt.-Col. C.C.J. Barrett, C.3.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The P^reign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. Sir, I liave the honour to inform you that a certificate was issued recently to one Muhammed bin Abdul Aziz (subject of Ibn Gaud) by Ibn Samd(» authorities at IFeddah , des cribing him as having been born in Jaalan and a subject of the Government of Jaalan. The certificate was endorsed by His Majesty’s Agent and Consul at Jeddah on the 5rd July 1929. 2. The individual in question v^as engaged by Ali bin Abdullah (Amir of Bani Bu Ali) and sent jutx to Jaalan for the purpose of religious teaching. He speht about three months in Jaalan but finding things unsatisfactory there and having received no pay is reported to be returning to flujd via Bahrain. 5. Presumably the object of the entries on the certifiaate was to show that the Amirs of Jaalan are an independent authority recognised by Ibn Gaud and also to claim that His Majesty’s Agent at Jeddah, by endorsing the certificate, had recognised the justice of the Anir of Jaalan’s claim to independence of Muscat. 4. I recommend that His Majesty’s Agent may be informedinformed that Government do not recognise the independence of Jai^Uin, but consider the Amirs to be subjeicts of the Muscat State. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, SI)/ C. G. J. Bar re 11. Political Resident in tiie Persian Gulf. Copy to the Political Agent at Muscat, reference his letter Ho. 77-C, dated the 23rd October 1929. Attested: for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Boveinber 9, 1929.Ho. 602-S of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 9th -November 1929. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Muscat for information. 2. Ho reply has been sent to the writer and in case of enquiry from Sur he should reply that no representations not submitted through the Muscat Government will be con sidered . By Order, for Secretary to the Political Kesiuent in the Persian Gulf. 4 AMIRS OP J A f ALAH. Letter from the Resident and Coramander-in-Chief, Aden, Ho. C-635, dated 28th Septeraber 1929 (with enclosures;.COPY. /&lt;Hfc Confidential. Ho. C. 65b. The Kesiciency, Aden, 28 September 1929. From k esident and Coramander-in-Chief, Aden, The Hon’ble the Folitical Resident in the Fersian Gulf| Rushire. Sir, 1 have the honour to inform you that Shaikh Aii bin Abdallah bin Salim Mahomed al Haraooua, 'Amir' of Jaalan, with 14 companions, arrived at Aden on the 3rd December, 1928, via Mukalla on their way to the Yemen and Hedjaz. Ref ore his arrival he wrote to roe ffora Mukalla requesting that he might be treated as an official gu.st during his stay at Auan. A telegraphic enquiry from the Political Agent, Muscat, revealed that the Shaikh had lately been engaged in dubious activities, 1 therefore refused to grant his request and avoided an interview with him. e The Shaikh left Adf.n on the 11th December for 3. Hodeida and after visiting the Imam at Sanaa reached Mecca ©n the Ibth February las-c. He remained in the Hedjaz until 6th ffiuly when he left for Egypt via Kassowa and arrived here the 10th instant. On his arrival he called on me at the Residency 4. with a letter of introduction from a mutual friend at Cairo. He told me he had visited Egypt to consult a doctor about his health, and tried to discuss Muscat politics. i refused to be drawn into such discussion. He then asked me to transmit a letter to you which 1 agreed to do and enclose herewith. Muscat. He left Aden on the 24th instant for Mukalla and I have the honour, Ate. :a)/ gCOPY. / y ■ / 4 ' 4 ) Translation. In the name of God* the most merciful and munificent. From Aden Rahi al Aichar 1^4 8. To Buehire, Persian Gulfc September 1929. Through the Government of Aden. To The Hobble the Political and Consul-General, of the Government of His Majesty Hie King of Great Britain in the Here isn Gulf. After/fc. Complimen ts. I have the honour to inform your Excellency that I reached Aden from Egypt on my way home, and that I deem it necessary to submit to you the following: Our Amirship continues to be a friend of the Government of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, as was detailed in our petition dated 10th January 1925: Our friend therefore should be our friend, and our enemy your enemy, as was mentioned in a latter *jb of Consul Major Grey. We are also friends and allies of the Sultan of Muscat in accordance with the agreements which were explained by the Government of Muscat in their general proclamation dated 1556 issued under the signatures of 1919 the Sultan and his Minister Captain McCollum. We enclose its translation for your perusal. We, in the name of friendship and respect for rights and equality, entertain genuine hope that the British Political Officers will not interfere in our interior, in con - nection with the aggression that tooic place in Jamadi al Awwal and the threat made by the Consul at Muscat to the tribes. We attach herewith a true copy of the warning issued by the Consul. The rights and privileges for our ancestors, ourselves and our tfcibes, in money, arms, etd. which were2 were earned by dint of sword have been stopped by the Muscat Government for the last 16 years. One of the conditions was that the Muscat Government has no right to interfere in the Ghafiri country, which is under control, and if the Muscat Gov ernment has intentions against flani Ghafir, we have the right to interfere in the matter and to stop the Govern ment at the limit which was agreed upon. Ana it was customary for our father to receive on demand, from the Sultan of Muscat, monetary payments and arms. All these rights have been stopped by the Mufjcat Government 'who aa adopted this policy by trusting in the power of Great Britain so as to deprive us of our legal rights and privileges, and to achieve its certain aims ana objects which may produce results that cannot be praised as is not hidden from you. We have firm hope* that your Just Government wj deal with this matter with wmdom and kindness and restc our rights just as they restored the rights of the ITaeer tribes above Sohar, through His Excellency the Resident Colonel Haworth, and Gauld Haraud bin Hamad, the late Wall of our, in accordance with justice and equality. Till the time of Major Haworth and Mr Wingate the procedure of the communication between us ana the officers of the British Government was that they reachec us direct. This has changed for the last Xh. year, and now letters (of the British Consul) reach us through th&lt; Wall of Sur and the Council of Ministers. Some tines they come open and some times^ they bear an enaorsement of the Ministers in red ink. This is against the usual custom and our senoe of respect does not tolerate that others should come to know of our secrets. We have constantly been asking for the Consul to come to Sur, ir accordance with the customs of J5ir Percy Cox and Mr Wingate, who never delayed their meetings in Bur, but the new Consul excuses himself from coining to Sur.introduction he turns us to the Ministers. \7e do not know what is his object in doing so. In any case it is impossible for us to submit to the said conditions, as we are Separate from tne Muscat GoTernment and independent &lt;in our affairs just Xxx. like the other Arab ruling chiefs. There do not exist between us and the Gorermient of Muscat any relations i other than those of friendship arid goo£, ne ighbourhood. We beseach orders of the Government of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, through you, to the following effect : That the letters may be sent to us direct according to the old customs. That when circumstances require the presence of the Consul of Muscat to make acquaintance, to aiscuss im portant matters and to remove misunderstanding, he should come to us in Cur am as is customary. That agreement be accorded to passports being issued by us to the travellers from our coasts, entered under our Government, as when they go out without pass ports, they are put to difficulties and are charged at least Rs. b/- on the coasts of xhx Italian Somaliland, if they do not hold passports from us. ]?or the saiie of facilities and as a consideration for our economical interests, wc see it rightful for doing so, keepir^; in view th£ fact that the Arab rulers benefit by this pro cedure. Presently, our passport was endorsed during our this journey, at Aden, Jeddah, Hgypt, Mussawwa, etc., just like other Rulers. The permission for ten rifles and 2QQ rounds (Mauser) cannot be sufficient to replenish our Amirship, to defend against the mischief makers and to keep peace and security in the interior. The cause of the trouble is our friendship with the British Government from old ana—- I €TO ) - 4 - and protection of interests of its subjects as it is attributed to us that v;e are the helpers of the British Goyernment. It is no tiling beyond our standing for the requirement of friendship and good neighbourhood. We accompanied the engineer of the OiJ/ana Petrol Company in 1926 and we expedited the journey wf l£r Thomas to Dhofar, in addition to thetft^stay. They clamour with displeasure about the flag hoisted by us. Sometimes they say it is a British flag and sometimes call it Bin Saud’s flag and similar other mischiefa are made although their efforts are frustrated. We request you to submit for orders of the British Government and to asx them in our name to permit us not less than 300 Mauser rifles with necessary quantity •f rounds. On receipt of the permit we are nrady t© buy them with our own money, as it is not possible for us to maintain peace in the country in the present statw kJur when we do not possess sufficient quantity of arms. As regards the ammunition which is a deposit for us with the Sultan of Muscat, about 25,000 rounds, which we purchased with our money in » we reierred 1912 to him and asked for delivery. His last reply was that he will deliver to us ammunition in exchange, as the original one was used by him for his own defence. In this reply satisfactory that he used it and that one may appropriate the right of others for his own interests, but to the harm of the other ? We can, however, make it easy for him. He may find quantity of ammunition for us, He may pay the value of the last store anu the balance will be paid by us. We request you to submit the matter to the Government who may settle the difference in a good way as we have no intentions except peace, conciliation and good neighbourhood. f AsAs regards the case of our tribe B&amp;ni J5u Ali who are entered mnder our rule, pending against the Italian Governnent at Makdushoh since 1926, we had submitted it to the late Resident last year anci hanued over to him a letter of the Italian Agent, and lie said that he would take necessary steps to recover the right of the aboveinentioned. We referred to the Italian Consul, Aden, and he promised. The benign maian Government had submitted the matter to London in 1926 according to the latter Gated 19th October 1926 Iron the British Consul at Muscat. I request Xour Honour to give suitable importance to what we have written and what we may get/ written through our Hepresnntative and lavour us with a reply in detail. You should not believe what our enemies may write as it is without any truth. We are always ready £or good understanding, co-operation and conciliation. With my best salaam and respAet to His Excellency the Governor General and Vicerfy of His Majesty the King of Great Britain and ali Officers of the Benign Government and to whoever hola a your high position. Yours sincerely, KD/ Ali Bin Abdullah Ai Hamudah. Ruler of the Amirship of Jaalan and its dependencies in the East of Jazirat ul Arab.COPY. Translation of a general notice in Arab written in a full of sheej) of paper. ' Notice is hereby given for the information of the public in general that a party of the people of Uru^an wh« throw the Youke of allegiance to the Government of Maskat and coloured their hands (in the committance of plundering) without a join to themselves and without having a right in the eyes of the lane of religion on the garden belonging to the Wall Ilohainiaed son of Ahmad and Rashid son of Aziz and who looted their houses together with the belonging? therein and disagreed to give them back t© their aforesaid ovmera unless comes between them the British Government. in spite of the fact that at first hey sought the British Government to stand as a security and afterwards they refused. Hence their operation and their usurpation has been fully manifested and this is an operation xxjthxhiji which is disproved by religion and wisdom as well. And by doing s© they have gone against the enjoyings(?; up on the commands of God and strict biaings of his pro phet. In punishment to these oppressors and the persons forming their gang we have issued an order the duties of to be exhausted at the rate of 25 per cent on dried dates and the dates from U rain an on Eastern Countries and 50 per cent on the power grat^tiea being exported and £h the issue of this notice and this increase m the rates ©f duties is not a permanent one, but it is in return of the operation done by these tyrants and their co- operators. Therefore we ik* xfc forewarn the pur chasers of dates dried dates and pxa pomegranates to take every care and to keep it in view of trie time of purchasing these goods from the aforesaid sellers and to prepare an account (i.Sr of sale and purchase^ according to this.This duty leyled in punishment is not binding an the goads imported. The/ duty on imports are to be exacted as the usual current merchants rates. Whether they may be in cash or in capital. All the goods in kind of dates dried dates and pomegranates xxXk ■which are exported must be accompanied by a certificate passed by the Customs Office at Muscat. $hoT&gt;ing that • i duties hare paid on these goods in case of the goods exported without a certificate in question would be liable to be detained. As for the dates fetched from the country belong ing to Bani Ghofir and Bani Boo Ali which formed the part of the estate of the Amir of Jaaian who are the allies of Muscat Government they are not to be charged except 5 per ceng as usual. Dated the 18th of Ramzan 1558. SD/ Captain D. A. McCollum, rime Minister of Muscat Government.COPY. \5 24 Translation. To All Shaikhs of al Aramah, al Fuwaris, al iluklianah, al Ghiyalin, and all tribes in Soar. Let it be known that we have received instructions from the Political Resident in the Gulf asking us to explain to yo.u all that Government of His Majesty the King do not intend to leave the affairs ijjx At Sur in the present unaatisfactory condition, and they will hold you responsible for any incident tliat happens from you, and will take severe steps against you. SB/ G. P. Murphy, Major, Political ftgent and H.M.’s Consul, Muscat.P.A. A certain sheikh fluhamad bin Ahmad al Adsani who is originally from Hasajfr and now resident oi* Sur came to muscat yesterday I met him today and on enquiry irom him about news he stated that there was no important news but shortly alter the arrival ot Sheikh Ali Din Abdullah in ja'alan some printed papers were circulated among the inhabitants oi Aiqa and sur. It is a iorm oi travelling permit* I attach a specimen oi it which I got irom Sheikh Xkutuxk&amp;A nuhamad* Besides this he says that al Hamuda have printed a special iorm lor sale deed^which he could not get* |UNo. jg. Travel 1 ing Pen ait. The hearer of this letter subject oi the Government of Ja^lan and its dependencies, who is Known to os, is proceding to The authorities of Great rowers are requested, according to terms of friendly relations and union betv/een iriendly Powers, to allow him (bearer) to pass and to afford him the necessary assistance and facilities* Descr iptio_n_._ Domicile ih J&amp;'aran Age Height Complexion Colour of eyes Colour of hair Dintinctive marks. Issued in Beni Bu Ali country in Ja’alan on 15 Signature. Governor of Ja’olan and its dependen cies in the hast of Arabia in Uman. (sd.) Ali al Hamudah (Seal)Confidential i'ditioai Agency and H.B.M 1 B Consulate jiuscat 31st December 1929 from Maj.or G,^*ikiurphy, ±.A., political Agent and H.ii.M's Consul, Muscat To The Hon’ble tne political liesxaent in tne Persian bull, Dushire# Sir, X have the honour to forv/ard,herev/ith,a translation of a ±js letter from His Highness Sir Saiyid Taimur bin faiaal,j£*C.I.i.,C.S.I; Sultan of Muscat and Oman asicing for the assistance of His Majesty's Government in dealing with affairs at sur. His Highness is of opinion that ever since the time when french intrigue was undermining the State's authori ty, the ±sani Hu Ali and Jenebeh tribes have been encroaching upon his sovereignty; that the process has been slow and confined each tim«^to such steps as they considered would not provoice the intervention of the nritish Government and that by this means the impression had got abroad that we had no serious intention of assisting aim. In an effort to arrive at some conciliation with Sheiich Ali bin Abdulla,of tne Ham Hu Ali,His Higiineas left Muscat on the 1st instant on board tne 'A1 ^aid* secretly and alone. Mr Thomas and myself were the only persons aware of the purpose of nis journey His Highness interviewed bneiich Ali bin Abdulla at Khabba, a port of the Ham Hu All. The interview was unsatisfactory. His Highness informed me on his return that it was evident from Ali bin Abdulla's demeanour towards him that Ali was determined in his efforts to establish his authority over bur and convinced of the Sultan's im- -potence to checic him. I recommend that Sheiich Ali bln Abdulla should be inform- -ed that i/overnment do not recognize the independence of Jaaian butconsider the Amirs to he subjects of the Muscat State and that they should be warned that Government will support His Highness in his demand that they should remove their flag from Aiqa pull down the fort they constructed there and desist from levying tolls and interfering in Sur affairs. I recommend also that His Highness should be reassured that some measure of assistance will be forthcoming. I have the honour to be # Sir Your most obedient servant^ Ma j or 9 rolitical Agent and H.H.M's Consul 9 Muscat■iiiiihii ■■■■ !111 ■ini mi Translation ox a letter datea 2bth Rajab lb46 (27tR December 1929) 1'rom H.H* Sir Saiyia Taimur bin Raisal, K.G.I.E*^ 0*3*1., Sultan oi tuscat Oman, jvuscat, to Major G.P.Hurphy, I.A., Political Agent &amp; Consul,Muscat* Reed*28-12-29* After Compliments* Tith reference to your letter dated the 19th December 1929 with regard to the letter from All bin Abdullah, Sheikh of Ban! Eu All, to the Resident who asked you to acquaint me with its contents, and with reference to my conversation t with the Resident on the subject and the resident f s request for my opinion with regard to the highhandedness and irregular actions of the Sheikhs of Bani Ru aII at Sur and its suburbs. I have already discussed rue matter v/itn you ana- confirmed it by my letter dated the 18th Muharram 1347 (6th July 1928). I have explained what was necessary at the time, but the Government did not pay attention to this important affair* I now repeat my request to my friend the •Government to support my State and in addition to what I have already stated I explain the transgressions tna audacity \ of the said people (Bani Bu Ali Sheikhs) at tmr where they have not the least right to do so* As to the remark made by the said Sheikh in his letter ^ to the Resident about the notice issued by my Wazir in 1338 (1919) to the effect that they were our friends and allies you are aware of the reason which necessitated the issue of that notice* The reason v/as that I levied a temporary tax on the Omanis, my subjects, who were not obeaient to my xha Government in order to distunguish between a rebel and a loyal* iis to the assistance which you mentioned in your letter to the inhabitants of Sur it was a sort of assistance which I expected#As to his statement about the rights and. priveieges enjoyed by his predecessors end iiinseli', X ari not ev.ere that he has been deprived oi any concession or privelege and as far as I know he and his leaders are enjoying then until the present tine# He has a salary which he receives it iron,the Treasury of my G-overnwent every month and it has not been changed up to now* llso when any oi his ioilowers or himseli cone for our visit they will be treated with hospitality as other tribes and bheikhs* The said Sheikh has no authority over the other sections of Ban! Ghafir who are settling in the neighbourhood ol his country* There are only friendly relations and arrangements between them in connection with their all airs with the Hinawis and others at «Ta t alah* The relation ol Bani Ghai ir tribes at Ja t alan with us is the same as that of Bani Bu All and they would be treated with hospitality like them. Their status is equal end I do not make any preferance in regard to my orders and hospitality to them and you knov; the conditions of the tribes among the Arabs* * He has remarked that we are relying on the support of the British forces* There is no doubt that we cannot do without it and he and other bheikhs are aware about it* ihey undoubtedly know that the support of the British Government to my State is only to preserve order and peace* It is not a new thing but it is a favour which was enjoyed by my predecessors and we are enjoying same in our country up to now* He has demanded that in usages and customs he should be treated as zne Sheikhs of Haim* I have not changed any usgge concerning the Bani Bu 10.1 tribe ana even v/e have not treated them ss we treat the Haim* He Vt/as not salistiec. as the Haim but he acted beyond his ano. his ancestors f limits at bur* I undoubtedly do not agree to your corresponding with him direct* The correspondence should be done tnrough the Gouncil of ministers of my Government if I am not present in the Capital* As regards the endorsement by the representatives of myfriend the Government on the Travelling Permits ?;hich he wants as he imagines to put it into eiieet, I do not expect you to recognize and. endorse them. You are aware that sheiJdi Isa bin Salih al Harithi and his followers do not travel from Oman without a Passport from the muscat Government and I do not think that you and the Resident are unaware about these facts. How could these people' have any superiority over others in enforcing travelling permits? Letter of introduction can oe given to them like other Sheikhs who travel to foreign places. I would like that a letter of introduction may be granted if a Passport is issued by my Government and if you are asked to do so as usual. I will admit that X did not attach the cost of ammunition [ which was deposited with me and some time ago 1 ordered the Council of ministers of my Government to pay it to them, but they themselves did not demand it. It is ready end will be paid by my Government to him as soon as they ask for it. I request you to forward this my letter to his nonour the Resident and I hope that I Ytrould be supported in suppressing them and stopping their aggressions. Inaddition to what I have already stated I will explain their transgressions at Sur* (1) They have levied a tax on caravans and sailing craits (2) They have erected ouildings at Aiqa, a village of Gur, where they had no such Duilaings oeiore. They have done so in order to oppose the execution of the orders of my Government in that part. hoisted it at Aiqa. They attempted to interfere with the traffic and highways and to disturb the peace. All their actions create disturbance and are against the orders of my official at Sur.axx I may add that I have got letters from them in which they admit that they have no right to interfere in the affairs of Gur. They are ready whenever you want to see them.V 4. I have a sanguine hope that His Honour the resident and tiy iriend the Government v/ill pay attention to this important matter which would result in instigating the other subjects of my Government to rebellion* They will be encouraged if the Government do not support and do not pay due attention to this matter* I have already pointed out in my previous letter that other Sheikhs are looking forward to see how the Hritish Government is going to support my State in suppressing these people* I expert to receive nelp and assistance as soon as possible* I have already snown you the letters which I received from bur and stated that they intend to force the inhabitants of Sur to submit to their wishes. You will observe that such mischievous action on their part will create disorder in the affairs of my Government* We shall not give them any chance to attain their objects and shall stop their high handed actions at Sur* I have already repeatedly warned you of the transgressions of tnese people* I am sending herev/ith a letter which I have received from the Sheikhs of Bani nu nasan of Ja'alan who are partners of Bani Bu All in J‘a t alan so that you may be aware how they are making propaganda among their neighbours and what they intend to carry out in future at Bur** I do not think that my iriend the government consider Ja'alan a separate country from Oman. The history would give evidence that it is under the authority of Muscat. My Government and myself await a favourable answer irom the (British) Government* usual Ending*■ Translation of a letter dated 29th Jania&amp;i II* 1346 (2nd December 1929) from Sheikhs Hamud bin iiumaicl bin Rashid and kuharaad bin Aaier bin /JLi of Eani Du Hasan to H.H*the Sultan of muscat and Oman* After Compliments• ¥e beg to inform you that on the 24th instant (27/11/2^ the Bani uhafir held a meeting in the place of All bin Abdullah in bani Bu Ali country* All bin Abdullah asked them to sign a paper accepting him as the Amir of Bani Ghafir of la t alan and promised to protect their boats at sea and the subjects (on land)* Some of them signed and some are still waiting* It ?/as arranged between them to meet on the coast of Sur in order to force the four sections of Janabeh to sign as Bani Ghcfir did* After completion of their affairs they will submit their representations against you to the British Government* This is the information which we got and it is incumbent upon us to inform and warn you about it* You are of higher opinion*■■ Confidential, Ho.7-C. of 1930. Political Agency and H.B-M's Consulate, Muscat 6th January 1930. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, liushire • u Memorandum. Reference my letter Mo.90-e.dated 31st December 1929, a copy of my letter Mo.133 dated 19th December 1929 which should ha’fce therewith been enolosedZis forwarded herewith. It will be noted that Hie Highness has du nged his mind about having the letter to Ali bin Abdullah sent direct. Major, Political Agent and Consul,Muscat.EXTRACTS PROM FIL3 ON QUESTION OP RAISING CUSTOMS DUTIES TO 7i^. !. Prom Major G.P.Murphy, Muscat, to the Secretary to the Hon f able the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. N0.40-C of 1929, March 12th, 1929, With the death of the Amir Mahomed bin Baser, and in the absence of the Amir Ali bin Abdulla in the Hejaz, there is no influential Sheikh of the Bani bu Ali present with whom negociations would serve any useful purpose and it will be necessary in any case to postpone any discussion as contemplated in Foreign tel egram No.304-S dated 22nd January 1929, until towards the end of the year. His Highness considers that if he went to Sur and ordered the Bani bu Ali to remove their flag and customs post and cease from interfering in Sur affairs and then was not in a position to enforce these demands, he would merely be giving an exhibition of his o^n weak ness. He is therefore reluctant to undettake any such discussion unless the British Government were ready to support him by placing a sloop at his disposal with au thority to bombard Aiqa should he request them to do so. The late Amir Moharaed bin Naser was a man of considerable personality and his ambitions were at the root of the recent troubles. There is therefore a possibi lity that his death may relieve the situation at Sur very considerably. 2. Prom India Office letter No. P.6567 of 27th Novem ber 1929, to the Foreign Office. Some improvement might result from the consol idation of the Sultan^ authority at Sur and the imposi tion there of an effective customs regime. On this the Secretary of State is consulting the Government of India;- — — ——r - w India; but the question presents difficulties of its own, and even should these be surmounted, it would probably be some time before any material increase in revenue from this source could be secured. 3. Prom India Office letter NO. P.6148 of 28th November 1929 to the Government of India. The Secretary of State would be glad to learn whether the Government of India are satisfied that the increase in the tariff which they suggest would not be • neutralized by a diversion of trade to Debai and Sur, or by an increase in smuggling. He would also be glad of the views of the Government of India as to the prac ticability of establishing the Sultan’s authority and an efficient customs control, at Sur. 4. Prom Political Agent, Muscat, to the Hon’able the Political Resident, Bushire, No.lO-C, 10th January,1930. A certain part of Oman proper being equidis tant from Muscat and Sur, diversion of trade from one por to the other does take place but such diversion depends very largely on tribal questions. The Muscat authorities do not consider that any appreciable deviation of trade or increase of smuggling w 0U i(i result from a small in crease in duties. As regards the practicability of establishing the Sultan’s authority and an efficient customs control at Sur, I would refer you to my report Incfcia Office B416 P6815/28 There are two questions at Sur, (l) The question of interference in affairs at Sur by the Bani bu Ali and their attempt to establish an independent State. $2) The lawlessness of the Jenebeh of Sur.ONFIDENTIAL. D.O. No. i Busbire, y ^ ^be Besidenc^/, ^ January SszsxiLax 1930. In the course of* our discussion with the Sultan His Highness said that be would let me know wbat rex&gt;ly be wanted me to give to the Amir Jaalan. I presume you will be s end uing me bis letter shortly. As regards Baris Ali, my office here are unable to suggest anyone for the post of British Agent, Gwadur, so I suggest you should try to get an elderly retired Indian Officer. lajor G. P. Murphy, O.B.E., Political Agent, - Muscat.1 ;&gt;th Jti'iuary, \ J60 /('- 1 ' 1 jreBume your D.0. &lt;o,6.S. Gated Vth January -ae itton altor receipt ol my letter JO.C. dated ^ st 'ecembor. I regret a copy of my letter to dis Hi^rmess w as inadver tently omitted at the time, and ae die Hi^phnees's reply ^ae not altogether to the point the raatter '’as not clear. His Highness ''as reluctant to dictate to us *'nat ae w it,hed ’'ritten to the dani ou All. He .iae, however, e oated the acts of a^reef ion by tne flani ou Ali to ’'nich he takes exception. He also declared to Tn^icas suuse- ^uently tnat he never ''iened your letter to O o direct to tne iiani ou Ali. I shall try and ^et the services of an elderly retired Indian Officer for J^adur t as you su^^estBritish Residency and Consulate-Crenerl, Bushire, 17th January 1930. ^he Political ftgent, Mus c at. Memoranduni &gt; I am directed to forward herewith a letter addreesedto Shaikh Ali bin Abdullah Haraudan, for delirery* and T attach a translation fox youi information and record. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.The Britieh Reaidency and CoriBulate-Genej Buehire, 15th January 1930. To Shaikh All bin Abdullah al Haraud&amp;n* After Compliments, Your letter addressed to ay predecessor, Colonel Barrett, and sent through the Resident at Aden has been placed before me, and I hare discussed it with your Suzerain, His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, and it is at his request that I an replying to you direct. The first thing ehich I wish to is make quite clear to you that Jaalan is part of the territories of Oman, and that the British GoYernment do not recognise you as an independent ruler. I will now reply to the various points raised in your letter. You state that in the pro clamati issued on the 18th Ramzan 1338 you sure described as the allies of the Muscat GoY ernment. This proclamation announced the imposition of a penal zakat against certain persons vino had refused to obey the orders of the Muscat Government. The Beni Bu AJLi had not at that time refused to submit than* selves to the ordersof the Muscat Govern ment and had kelped the Government: those who- 2 - m vliohere (U«ob«&lt;li(si&gt;t w«re demerit a as 4 ri?b«is # wblle ths Bn All w#rs dss- aribeti as allies. This die* not saean that Umy wsrs 1 miependent of the (m(Oi Gowrn- »ent. • i You state that your ancient ri^tSj, and priTileges imire been stopped by the Hus cat GoTcmwent. !Ci» Highness tells ae that this is not true, and that your salary is paid to you re^iiarly by ilk* Muscat Gov- ermaent, also that when you or yaaoc any of your followers visit His Highness you sill be treated sith hospitality «ui other J'iiaiichs and tribetinen. His Highness adds that you have no authority over the other sections of t'm Beni (Uiafir. who are settling in Uk* neighbourhood of your country. The relation of the Beni Ohaflr trills at Jaslan is the sane as that of the Beni bu All and they will be treated vti th hospital ity like thess. 4? It iu pot&gt; si bis that soise times conoBunicutions miy have been addressed to you direct by officers of Uae High Govern ment. X m writing to you direct now, but it is at the request of His Highness the ffultan. amt may Imve been ilie siofte on pre vious occasions. It is not a ri t h X tiiat you cm claim, and since you are the subject of Kls Highness you should in future oend all letters for the '‘oiltidal Agent through tlie Muscat -'tate authorities. As X hM$ already infornetd you. you are not separate frma the Huecat Goveriiiaent. For this rea&amp;oi you have no right to it*sue passports and any docunrnta purporting to be passportsissued by you will not be recognised by the I British authorities, and the holders will hare much trouble. I am informed that you are still interfering in the affairs of Sur: that you are levying unauthorised duties and p taxes there on caravans and sailing craft and that the flag which you say is your flag is still flying, and that you do not obey the orders of the Wali at Sur. You have no right at all to interfere in trie affairs of Sur or to levy taj^es there, and I call on you to cease at once all inter ference in the affairs of Sur, which is the port of Oman, and it is only the flag of Itxx Oman which may be flown there. You make various requests regard ing arias and ammunition. Hie Highness in forms me that the cost of the ammunition deposited with him is ready and will be paid by the Muscat Government to you as ^Loon as you ask for it. But as regards mm your request that you should be allowed to buy 300 Mauser rifles, with a suitable quantity of ammunition, I write to say that I am not prepared to advise His Highness the Sultan to let you have any rifles or ammunition at all until you liave definitely ceased all interference at Sur. Oh, Shaikh Alifi take heed to my advice, cease your interference with Sur, and tue coastof Oman. Attend to the affairs of your tribe in the interior of your country, and loyally support the -&gt;uler of Oman, His Highness the Sultan of Muscat. 0 the rwCOT an slat ion Ji^ ITT the Nane of God the nost merciful and raunificier.t. Vrom Wen TTaM al Alchar 1346^ to Buehire. Persian Gulf. Septemljc r 1929. Througli tiie Government of Aden. To The Hon’hie the Political Resident ai^ Oowul-Genera! of the Government of His Majesty ' JJ Great Britain in the Per. ian Guj. . After Compliments. I have the honour to inform ^our T^oellency taut 1 reach ed Aden from Egypt on my way home, one. that I deem it necessary to submit to you the following. Cur Amirahip continues to he a friend of the Govern ment of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, as was detail ed in ou’lf petition dated the _Oth January 192«3i 0 l Priei i, therefore, should he your friend, and our enemy your enemy, as was mentioned in a letter of Consul Major Grey. •Ve are also friends and allies of Hie flultan ol Muscat in accordance with the agreements which were explained by the Government of Muscat in their general proclamation dated the 1338 issued under the signatures of the Sultan and 1919 his Minister Captain McCollum. We enclose its translation for your perusal. We, in the name oi friendship anti xespect for rights and equality, entertain genuine hope that tne B.iti^ Political Officers will not interfere in our interior, in -on- nection witli the aggress ion that toon place in Jaiaad i al and the threat made by the Consul, Muscat, to the tribes. We attach herewith a true copy of the naming issued c f Consul. The rights and privileges for our ancestors, our selves and our tribes, in money, arms, etc., which were earned by dint of sword have been stopped by the Muscat Government for the last 16 years. One of the conditions was that the Muscat Government has no right to interfere in the Ghafir\ country, which is- p - islander our control, and if thf l.'Tuucat Governmt'nt daB i n t &lt;»n t. i nn« acrjiiriHt, 'Rani Ghaf*ir^ iwf have the to limit which vas agreed u^ion. And. it v?ae custoraary for father to receive on demand, from the Hu It an oi ca u, monetary payments and arms. All tiiese rights have been stopped by the Muscat Government who adopted this policy by trusting in the power of the Government of Britain so $ as to deprive us of our legal rights and privileges, arc. to achieve its certain aims and objects, v/hich may pro duce results that cannot be paraised as is not hidden from you*- ’Ve have firm hope that your Just Government will deal with this matter with wisdom and kindness and res tore our rights just as they restored the rights of the Nae’em tribes above Rohar, through Hit Excellency the Resident Colonel Haworth, and. Ray id Hamud bin Hamad, zhe late Tali of Sur, in accordance with justice and e quality. Bill the time of Major Haworth and Mr Tingate, the procedure of the communication between us and the officers of the British Government was that they reached us direct. ,n his has changed for the last year, ana now letters (of British Consul) reach us through the Wali of Rur and the Council of Ministers. Rome times they come open and some times they bear an endorsement of the Ministers in red ink. Biiis is against the usual custom I and our sense of respect does not tolerate thatfothers should come to know of our secrets. Y/e have constantly teen asking for the Consul to cone to Rur, in accordance neVer delayed their meetings in Rur, but the new Consul excuses himself from coming to Rur. Whenever we as&amp; him for a pass or a letter of We do not In introduction he turns lis to the Ministers, know what is his object in doing so.Will ■■■■I I T III rn - 3 ~ M)' In any case it is impossible foi' us to submit to the said conditions, as we are^dparate from the Muscat Government and independent in our affairs just like the other Arab Ruling chiefs. ''here do not e^ist between us and the Government of Muscat any relations other than those of friendsliip and good neighbourhood. We be s each orders of t lie Gov e rn men t o f H i s Maj e s t y the King of Great Britain, through you, to the following effect: . the letters may be sent to us direct juzzjzxi according to the old custom. ''hat when circumstances require the presen^^of the Consul at Muscat to make acquaintance, to discuss important matters and to 2 'emove misunderstanding, he should come to us in Bur as is customary. That agreement be accorded to the passports being issued by us to the travellers from our coasts, entered under our Government, as when they go out with out passports, they are put to difficulties ana are charged at least Hs. b/- on the coasts of xh* Italian Somaliland, if they do not ho})d passports from us ^ Kor the sake of facilities and as a consideration for our economical interests, we aee Xh it rightful for doing so, seeping in view the fact that the Arab rulers benefit by this procedure. 'Presently, our passport was endorsed during our this journey, at Aden, Jeddah, Egypt, Mussawa, et., just like other Bulers. 'he per)|ission for 10 rifles and. 200 rounds (Mauser) cannot be sufficient to replenish our Amirship to defend against the mischief makers and to keep peace and security in the interior. The cause of the trouble is our friendship with the British Government from old and protection of interests of its subjects as it is attributed to us that we are the helpers of the British Government. It is nothing beyond, our standing for the requirement4 requirement of friendship and ^;ooo neighbourhood. We accompanied the Engineer of the Oil and Petrol Company in 19P6 and vre expedited the h» lirnr : / of Mr Thorr ' iaB to gla.Q and similar other mischiefs are made eithough their efforts are frustrated. We request you to.submit for orders of the British Government and to ask thcri in our name to permit us not less than 300 Mauser rifles with necessary quantity of rounds. On receipt of the permit we are ready to but them with our own money, as it is pot possible for us to t. maintain peace in the country in the present state when m+ we do not possess sufficient quantity of arms. ,\s regards the ammunition which is a deposit for us with the Eultan of Muscat, about 23000 rounds, ir~ — * — 1912 to him and asked for delivery. His last reply was that he will deliver to us ammunition in exchange, as the original one was used by him for his own defence. Is this reply satisfactory that he used it and that one may appropriate the right of others for his own interests, but to the harm of the other ? We can, however, make it easy for him. He may find quantity of ammunition for us. He may pay the value of the last store and the balance will be paid by us. We request you to submit the matter to the Government who map settle the difference in a good way as we have no intentions except peace, conciliation and good neighbourhood. As regards the case of our tribe Bani Bu Ali who are entered under our rule, pending against the Italian Government at Makdushoh since 1926, we liad submitted it to the late Resident last year and handed over to him a- &amp; - letter of the Italian Agent, and he said, that he Goulet take necessary RjijULau* steps to recover the rights of the above mentioned. We referred to the Italian Consul, Aden, and he promised. The benign Indian Government had submitted the natter to London in 19S6 according to the letter dated 19th October 1928 from the British Consul, Muscat. I request your Honour to give suitable im portance to what we have written and what we may get written through our representatives and favour us with a reply in detail. You e ho Hid not believe wha^ our enemies/may write as it is wiifiout any trutju. We are always ready for good understanding, ^o-eperation and conciliation. With my best salaams and respect to His Excellency the Governor General and Viceroy of His Majesty the King of Great Britain and all officers of the Benign Government and to whoever holds your high pos i tioH/f-Jar* Hote on eituati on in BUR t 1930 » fry CajsitU*. $' fr*fffrc* [jrCce^ (La*^ f\t~ A' H' Q ■ 4* S^Ial 1. I visited SUR between the dates 13th and 22nd January where I stayed with the Agent of Khimji Ramdas of Muscat « v the leading KXXKtaocfe Indian Banyan meroahnt there and also with the Wali,Saiyid Shahab bin Faisal a brother A* of the Sultan at Balad es Sur about 2 miles inland* ^ u &gt; , / I 2. The town of Maqrimatain on the W side of Sur creek is occupied by the *ienebeh and Aiqa on East side chiefly by the Beni Bu Ali tribe (Wahabis)* The Arama and Fuaris sections of the Jenebeh are at feud with the Makhanna and Ghialin sections* The feud dates from 1913 and the split in the tribe has been sedulously encouraged and fostered by Ali bin Abdullah Sheikh of the Beni Bu Ali and self- -styled Amir of Jaalan who has championed the e%use of the Makhanna and Ghiyalin sections of the Jenebeh* He lives at the headquarters of his tribe at the village Belad Beni Bu Ali about 40 miles inland,and is represent- »ed at Aiqa by one Isa bin Mahe-a-man of no importance* 3 * Security does not exist in SUR; no man leaves his homse without being armed even if it is only to cross the skxm street;nor may a man visit a quarter of the town other than his own except in company with some men of his /• u own faction escorted by a rabi’a* or guarantor from the faction occupying the quarter he wants to visit* There are no lights in the town and the people are careful not to show a light at their windows at night for fear of \ attracting rifle fire* ^S&amp;pasmodie shooting at night witnesses to the constant alarm of the inhabitants* The situation at Belad es Sur,though similar, is very much less aoute than that just described in regard to SUR* 4* Very/ few customs dues are taken at SUR and these live mainly from the Indian Banyans who/fcaotK in Maqrimatain under the protection of the Arama-the most powerful waran i section of the Jenebeh* There are,including families about 30 Indians in Sur.The principal exports are dried dates which are brought dovn from V« interior and shipped to Indian ports in hagalas - «ea going dhows« Goods shipped from Aiqa, where the Beni Bu All influence is predominant,evade all customs payments except such as the Sheikh of the Beni Bu Ali is able to enforce for his own benefit. There is~very tall prominently-placed flag etc in Aiqa but I saw no flag flying from it during my visit. The W8li,who lives in a fort at Belad es Sur, has no civil or other authority whatsoever in SUR and very little in Belad es SUR. fie can do nothing and admits it. He ■- : - r ' 0 u his fort which is garisoned by 25 askarM Paid and armed by the State. He has not been considered a suoeess and is to ue transferred,on the return of the Sultan from Dhofar about the middle of February. He will be succeeded,! believe, by the present '.Tali of Saham -a mem, I understand, of firmer character The Beni Bu Ali are themselves at feud with their neighbours in Jaalan,the Beni Bu Hassan. This feud dates from 1812-13. While 1 was in SUR I heard that a truce of 6 months had been arranged between these two tribes to take effect from approximately the ■beginning of January♦ From my conversation with various persons in SUR and from my own observations I am certain that the people of all classes are heartily weary of the constant sta^of insecurity which. there and would welcome effective governmental control which is at-present entirely lacking. The person chiefly responsible for the present state of affairs is All bin Abdullah, Sheikh of the Beni Bu Ali and if he ana his tribe m were brought under control and his pretensions to an inde- -pendent Amirate definitely and finally quashed it should be possible to find a way to heal the rupture which now exists between the 4 sections of the Jenebeh,thus removing another source of continued friction and preparing the way for conso- -lidating that tribe and reducing it to order. Summit up, 0* the situation at SUR is the result of de- -plorably weak Government or rather the total absenoe of any government. The tribes in consequence are completelytf) O-xXl 0-2^0 It^ho- out of control* The situation is so out of hand that it is certain that the resources of the Muscat State / unaided, are quite incapable of dealing with it* rUrd&lt;r&gt;~~ cr/Note on situation in SUR, January 1930. 1. 2 . I visited aUR between the dates 13th and 22nd January where I stayed with Ji Ram the Agent of Ahinyi Ramdas of Muscat and the leading Indian Banyan merchant there&gt; and also with the wali»Saiyid ahahab bin Faisal a brother of the bultan, at Balad es bUR about 2x miles inland. The town of Maqrimatain on the west side of bur creek is occupied by the Jenebeh and Aiqa on hsat side chiefly by the Beni Bu Ali tribe (Wahabis). The Arama and Fuaris sections of the Jenebeh are at Feud with the Makhanna and Ohialin sections. The feud dates from 1913 and the split in the tribe has been sedulously encouraged and fostered by Ali bin Abdullah*Sheikh of | 'i the Beni Bu Ali and self-styled Amir of Jaalan who has championed the cause of the Makhanna and Grhiyalin xke! sections of the Jenebeh. He lives at the headquarters of his tribe at the village of Belad Beni Bu Ali about 40 miles inland, and is represented at Aiqa by a man one Isa bin Muhammed/of no importance. Security does not exist in SUR; no man leaves his house v.ithout being armed even if it is only to cross the street; nor aay a man visit a quarter of the town other than his own except in company with some men of his own faction escorted by a rabi'a* or guarantor from the faction occupying the quarter he wants to visit. There are no lights in the town and the people are careful not to show a light at their windows at night for fear of attracting rifle fire. Spasmodic shooting at night witnesses to the constant alarm of the inhabitants. The situation at Belad es SUR, though similar, is very much less acute than that just described in regard to SUR. Very few customs dues are taken at SUR and thesePage -t 2 i these mainly from the Indian Banyans who live in Maqrimatain under the protection of the Arama - the most powerful section of the Jenebeh. There are, including families^ about 30 Indians in BUR. The principal exports are dried dates which are brought down from the interior and shipped to Indian ports in bagalas - sea going dhows* Goods shippe* ed from Aiqa» where the Beni Bu Ali influence is pre dominant, evade ali customs payments except such as the bheixh of the Beni Bu Ali is able to enforce for his ov&lt;n benefit. There is a very tall prominently- placed flag staff in Aiqa but I was no flag flying from it during my visit. The wall, who lives in a fort at Belad es Bur, has no civil or other authority whatsoever in Bur and very little in Belad es SUR. He can do nothing and admits it. He rarely stirs out of his fort which is garisoned by 25 asicari paid and armed by the Btate. He has not been considered a success and is to be transferred, on the return of the sultan from Dhofar about the middle of February. He will be succeeded, 1 believe, by the prsent wall of Baham-a-mn, I understand, of firmer character. The hem Bu Ali are themselves at feud with their neighbours in Jaalan, the ±&gt;eni Bu Hassan. This feud U \ \ dates from 1312-13. while 1 was in Bur I heard that a \ truce of 6 months had been arranged between these two tribes to talce effect from approximately the beginning of January. Prom my conversation with various persons in SUR and from my own observations I am certain that the people of all classes are heartily weary of the constant state of insecurity ?/hich prevails there and would welcome effective governmental control which is at present\ jeage - i 3 *• present entirely lacicing. The person chiefly responsible for the present state of affairs is Ali bin Abdullah* aheiich of tne beni Bu Ali and if he and his tribe were brought under control and his pretensions to an independent Auiirate definitely and finally quashed it should be possible to find a way to heal the rupture which now exists between the 4 sections of the Jenebeh, thus removing another source of continued friction and preparing tne way for consolidating that tribe and reducing it to order. 8. Bummed up* the situation at BUR is the result of deplorably weaic Government or rather the total absence of any Government. The tribes in consequence are completely out of control. The situation is so out of hand that it is certain that the resources of the Muscat Btate* unaided, are quite incapable of dealing with it.Mote on situation in aUR&gt; January 1^30« 1* 1 visited bUft between tne dates 13th and 22nd January where I titayed with Ji ham the Agent of jQairaji hamdae of Muscat and the leading Indian Banyan merchant there# and also with the Wali#3aiyid bhahab bin Faisal a brother of tne bultan, at Balad es bUH about 2 miles inland. 2. The town of Maqrimatain on the West side of Sur creeic is occupied by the Jenebeh and Aiqa on Bsat side chiefly by the Beni Bu Ali tribe (Wahabis). The Arama and Fuaris sections of the Jenebeh are at Feud with the Maichanna and dhiaiin sections. The feud dates frou 1913 and the split in the tribe has been sedulously encouraged and fostered by Ali bin Abduliah#3heiich of the Beni Bu Ali and self-styled Amir of Jaaian who has championed the cause of the Maichanna and Ghiyalin mmii sections of the Jenebeh. Ke lives at the headquarters of his tribe at tne village of Belad Beni Bu All about 40 miles inland# and is represented at Aiqa by a man one Isa bin imftaiamed of no importance. 3. Security does not exist in SUKj no man leaves his house without being armed even if it is only to cross the street; nor any a man visit a quarter of the town other than his own except in company with some men of his own faction escorted by a rabi'a' or guarantor from the faction occupying the quarter he wants to visit. There are no lights in the town and the people are careful not to show a light at their windows at night for fear of attracting rifle fire. Spasmodic shooting at night witnesses to the constant alarm of the inhabitants. The situation at Belad es SUR# though similar# is very muon less acute than that just described in regard to SUR. 4. Very few customs dues are taMen at SUR and thesethese mainly from the Indian Banyans who live in Page -i 2 f Maqrimatain under the protection of the Arama - the most powerful section of the Jenebeh, There are, including families, about 30 Indians in BUK. The principal exports are dried dates which are brought down from the interior and shipped to Indian ports in bagalas - sea going dhows. Goods shippe ed from Aiqa, where the Beni Bu Ali influence is pre dominant, evade all customs payments except such as the oheiich of the Beni Bu All is able to enforce for ms own benefit. There is a very tall prominently- placed flag staff in Aiqa but I v^as no flag flying from it during my visit. The «ali, who lives in a fort at Belad es Bur, has no civil or other authority whatsoever in Bur and very little in Belad es BUIt. lie can do nothing and admits it He rarely stirs out of his fort which is garisoned by 25 asxari paid and armed by the Btate. He has not been considered a success and is to be transferred, on the return of the Sultan from JDhofar about the middle of jfobruary. He will be succeeded, I believe, by the prsent Wall of Saham-a-maii, I understand, of firmer character. The Beni Bu Ali are themselves at feud with their neighbours in Jaalan, the Beni Bu Hassan. This feud dates from 1812-13. while I was in Bur I heard that a truce of 6 months had been arranged between these two tribes to taice effect .from approximately the beginning | of January. t prom my conversation with various persons in BUR and | from my own observations I am certain that the people of all classes are heartily weary of the constant state of insecurity which prevails there and would welcome effective governmental control which is at presentra^e - j 3 *- present entirely lacicing. The person chiefly responsible for the present state of affairs is All bin Abdullah, rineiidi of the beni Bu Ali and if he and his tribe were brought under control and his pretensions to an independent Amirate definitely and finally quashed it snould be possible to find a way to heal the rupture wnich now exists betwaen the 4 sections of the Jenebeh, thus removing another source of continued friction and preparing the way for consolidating that tribe and reducing it to order. Summed up, the situation at BUR is Hie result of deplorably weaic Government or rather the total absence of any Government. The tribes m consequence are completely out of control. The situation is so out of hand that it is certain that the resources of the Muscat State, unaided, are quite incapable of dealing wi th itREPORT ON SUR. .JAN LAKY 1^30. Landing facilities. Transport. 3. Communications- Roads. There are six small bedans avail able at Sur for landing troops and baggage but not mules, transport venicles, or guns. A large niiinber of 'horis' (open boats; are available w hich could be used for landing small articles of baggage: i.e.raen's kits etc. Ships ’^ould jrave to anchor in ox^en anchorage off the to^n in from 8 to 11 fathoms and dis tant from shore 6 cables or slightly over 1200 yds. There are no piers: all craft ^ould have to be beached. The beach is 2 mile long and is commanded on both east and ' r est sides by nigh ^round surmounted by to w ers callable of holding 10 men. On the eastern side there are 2 toners and on western 5. These are all visible from the sea. There is no ^heeled transport available. About 50 camels and luG donkeys are available in SUR, but more could be ob tained from the interior. About 300 donkeys could be obtained from Belad-es-Sur and Ul lages around. Donkeys are used for transport of w ater, in skins. (a) Roads through the to^n are broad and suitable for all forms of M.T. A broad ♦ all-weather track with hard surface and suit able for all forms of M.T. exists between SUR and BSLATt^S-SUR about t^o miles inland,inland, ^here the ’^ater supply is located and ^here caraping o rounci ^ould need to be situated At point -''here this road enters the valley of E3LAJD-KS- SUR and % mile from to^n some ^•ork is required to improve it, A platoon of men working for 2 hours could accomplish this. This road is called EL EEJ. (b) No telegraph or telephone communi cation exists, Tooden poles (bullies) are available for carrying telephone lines. There are over 80 large wells in BELAD-ES-SUR used as a -^ater supply for the to^n and for cultivation. Three are recommend ed. These are named SAMAGrHA (nearest to camp ing ground), HESA and SABAIKHAK and are lined ^ith stone and cement. Diameters: 11 ft., 21 ft., 28 ft. Depth to ^ater: 15 to 18 ft. Depth of water: 2 to 3 ft. Tnis does not de crease in summer but rises after rain. The above is the average depth of all the w e n £ . The Arabs rarely take the trouble to dig deeper than is necessary to give them this head of water. Majority of wells are stone lined and fitted with overhead gear made of cut palm trees supporting a pulley. '7ater is drawn up in large s*ins by bullocks. A few wells have reservoirs for storage of water, capacity about 3500 gallons. There are 11 wells at SAKAIKRAH, 1 mile from BELAD-ES-SUR. Stone lined; diameters varying from 18 to 24 ft; depth 12 to 15 ft; depth of w a ter ?£ to 2 ft. The water from these is slightly bracxish and is used. —— I'——— ■ is used for cultivation. It could be used by trooi)6 for w ashing. At SANAISALAH, a small village on the coast 1 mile ''est of SUR, there are 2 ^ells. These suffice only for the needs of the villagers. Sufficient water exists in BELAD- ES-SUR for 2 battalions after the needs of the population have been met. The water supply could be increased by deepening the w e ii s# Eresh wells could be dug # if thought neces sary, anywhere in the valley. ( H ) Rice, wheat, dall, sugar, matches, imported from India, are available in 3UR. Oil from Abadan (Anglo-Persian Oil Co.) is shipped from Muscat* (h) Local supplies are chickens, eg^s, ^oats, milk, fish, fuel, and dales. Fresn vegetables are not available but could oe ^ro^n in BBIAD-ES-SUR. Ground is available for extensive cultivation. The only animal food obtainable locally is lucerne; donkeys are largely fed on dates, especially on a journey. There is no grazing except for camels and goats. Bhoosa is not available, nor bar- ley. ( c ) The only product from the interior is dry dates called 'besr* ( ) w h.ich are largely exported to India. Ji Ram, an Indian Banyan and SUR representative of the firm of Khimji Ram Lass of Muscat would he a very useful man to retain as general agent by a force landing in SUR. He has had 10 years in the place and is widely known and highly respected by both townspeopletownspeople and tribes of tne interior 6. Accommodation. 7. Camping-ground 8. Engineer Stores. No accommodation exists for hous ing troops. Tents would be suitable for the greater part of the year. SUR has a much better summer than Muscat f not being surrounded by rocky hills as is the latter place, and a cool wind blows throughout the year. Material is available locally for hutting. The most suitable site for a camp ing ground is on tne S.E. extremity of the low ridge called HKD which rises from 50 to 100 ft. in height and runs from S.E, to N.W, at a distance of 2 miles from SUR. At its S.E. extremity it dominates at close range the town of BKLAD-ES-SUR and the water supply there. There are two towers on this ridge; SAMAGHA near the camping ground and JERABI about 1000 yds. away. On another and neigh bouring ridge overlooking the motor road where it enters the valley of BELAD-ES-SUR, there is a third tower called AIS. There is a gar rison of 3 to 4 askers in each of these 3 towers ^hich are built on the same principle as those in the KHYBER. It would be necessary to hold these towers by picquets. After some necessary repairs they could accommodate a section of men. This site would be the most suitable for the defence of the town of BELAD ES- SUR and of the troops themselves. None are available locally. Defence stores, wire, etc. would have to be brought. PlentyUBBWB (g) Plenty of etone is available and near for con struction of san^has. Pumping plant; pumps; piping; portable tanks for storage and filtration of water relative to the size of the force would have to be brought, 500 yds. of piping would be required to convey water from wells to camp. Camping ground is 100 ft. above level of surface of ^ells. 9. Landing Ground Extensive flat ground is available in vicinity of SANAISALAJI wnich migut be suitaole for an aerodrome, I nesitate to pro nounce on its fitness as the surface, in parts, is a shallow crust which sinks under the heel.1 ^— ; mw h| j r M _|f Let \tT(pv&lt;1- Wo. ^OS-S of 1029. f f British ariu C«ii«ui»t e-(ieneriil, Bushire v 5iat J)ec«-‘! brr 1929. Prom To 'he Hon * ble Llcut^Coloncl il. V. Bisooe, ?olitl«al T'ecicen t in the i J erBian Gulf, r he -oreign Georctary to the Goverrttaent of inuia, 3ew Delhi. Sir, ft / With reference to lay letter No. 580-• , dated the diet October 1929, i have the honour to forward a copy of m letter from the 'olitienl Jluaeat, No. 86-C, dated the 12th December 1929, enclosing sample of a travel permit iseued by Ali bin Abdulla, Amir of the Bani Du Ali tribe of Jaalan. I agree with Uie views exprcsned by Major Murphy and would request tliut the British and Indian passport authorities may be warned against recognising the document. I am sending a copy of tills letter to the r evident at Aden. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most died lent servant. /3‘ ( l ^ (SGD) H. V. Biscoe, Political Resident in the !r er..iHn Gulf. L-.-Colonei. Copy for information to tbg Political Agent at Muscat. ///p / for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 31st December 1929.M I fill ■ C, Translation ol a letter dated 6th Ra^jal 1S46 (8/12/^9) irom Sheiidi id! bin Abdullah al Hauuda of lanl Bu idl to h.H* the Bulte.n ol xeuscat ana Oman* Reed* 29/11/29* A.C * God willing one of my brothers will visit you in the Capital and will inform you of matters which will be agreed by all and then an agreement will be eifected between us as you desire* God willing the anairs will be arranged between us satisfactorily* There will be no aiixerence and you snould not feel the least displeasure.ana salaams* w V Please give my compliments to the heir-apparent* Say id ITadir, all your brothers and sons, YTazir Thomas and the Council of ministers* 3.y brothers and sons send their compliments to you. rnmim.— Confidential :no* 30-C. of 1930. Political Agency and iUis.M v 0 Conoiaate Muaoat 12th March 1930# To The Hon’ble the Political Heeident in the Perninn ttulf Bir*)HlKK letter from flheikh Ali bin Abdullah of the Bnni Bu /\li to your address* I also enclose translations of letters from him to His Highness the ^ultan and to me* 2 * Sheikh Hamdan who came here attempted to have a private Interview with me but in deference to the wishes of the Oouncil # I refused to see him without a representative of the Muscat ^tate being present* He attempted this both through my Munshi and again through Rev* Van ^uroem the American Mi so ionary* Muhammad bin ^alim # mentioned in the letter to His Highness dated 15th December is stated to have posted a letter to your address and then returned to Bur* I gather from His Highness that as Bheikh Hamdan had no authority to agree to nnythlng # no result was achieved by th£$r meeting* I have the * onour to be # Sir, Your most obedient servant. t Political Agent and H.B.H'b Coneul, MueOBt .Letter dated 10th Ramazan 1346 (iOth February 1930) from Sheikh All bin Abdullah al Hamudah of Rani Ru All to Sir Frederick W. Johnbton, K.C.I.E., G.S.I., Political resident in the Reraian Oulf&gt; Bu&amp;hire* Reed* 5~3“30» A. C. I have already sent you a letter on the 12th K&amp;jab 1348 (14th December 1929) describing in detail the result of my conversation with Rultan Taimur who stated that we should stop the tax which we have levied on our subjects at our town Aiqa and not to hoist any flag other than the usual muscat flag even if we had a special flag oi of our own* I beg to state that the proposals which have made by the Sultan are fundamentally illegal and would interfere with our departmental independence as the -British Government consider the position of both of us equal* We have not entered into an official negotiations with them (Muscat Govt. ) so that we may know whether these proposals have been made by them or by the -british Government on behalf of the tiultan* how we beg to request the British Government to advise the Sultan not to interfere xxxft in our internal ail airs* We say that we do not accept these proposals and ao not take them as a basis for negotiations* In snort we would not deal with the muscat Government unless we receive a reliable information from you that (the proposals) have been made by them (Muscat)* We request the British Government to administer justice between us as both of.us ere under their protection. U. ELetter dated 10th Ramazan 1348 (10th February 1930) from Sheikh Ali bin Abdullah al Hamudah of Bani im /0.i to Sir Frederick W. Johnston, K.C.T.L., C.S.T., Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire. Reed. 5-3-30^ A.C. I have already sent you a letter on the 12th Rajab 1348 (14th December 1929) describing in detail the result of my conversation with bultan Taimur v/ho stated that v/e should stop the tax which we have levied on our subjects tit our town Aiqa and not to hoist any flag other than the usual Muscat flag even if v/e had n special flag of of our own* I beg to state that the proposals which have made by the Bultan are fundamentally illegal and would interfere with our departmental independence as the British Government consider the position of both of us equal. ,r e have not entered into an official negotiations with them (Muscat Govt. ) so that we may know whether these proposals have been made by them or by the British Governnent on behalf of the sultan. now we beg to request the British Government to advise the bultan not to interfere xx&amp;iK; in our internal affairs• We say that we do not accept these proposals and do not take them as a basis for negotiations. In short v/e vrotuLd not deal with the Muscat Government unless we receive a reliable information from you that (the proposals) have been made by them (Muscat), ve request the British Government to administer justice between us as both, of us are under their protection.Letter dated 13th Rajah 1348 (15th December 1920) from Sheikh All bin Abdullah of Bani Bu Ali to K.HVSaiyid »aimur bin Faisal, Sultan of iiuscat* A.C. I have already informed you that my brother Hamdan is coming to see you* You may discuss ail your nit tiers v/ith hxm* He will give you an anst«rer but the question would be referred to me so that we may come to an agreement which may oe uo the interest of both parties* Iiy messenger Liuhamad bin balim is also paying you a visit* he intends to go to .nushire* I hope you will give him a passport v/ithout delay and afford him assistance* liy friend, my brother muudan owing to considerable rain and xa&amp;ft roughness of the sea m was not able to leave and was delayed* Insha-aliah as soon as the sea becomes calm he will come to see $££&amp; and discuss matters with you* U. E. f D* Letter dated 24th Rajab 1348 (26th December from Sheikh Ali bin Abdullah of Bani Bu Ali to TI.K.the bultan ox Mua c at &amp; Oman • A • C • There is no important news to be communicated to you but j good. 1L have already despatched some letters which I hope you have received them* I intended to send Hamaan but owing to rainfall he could not come* irrom the 24th Rajab (26/12/29)' the sea became calm and Hamdan was able to start but as you informed me of your intention to go to Lhofar he did not dp so* If you intend to delay your Journey please let me know so ! that iay brother come to see you* If you have made up your mind to go we shall have an interview v/ith you on your return to fhe Capital when all matters would be discussed v/ith you. j Tnsha-allah we will come to an agreement which would be to the interest of both parties* uther matters v/ill be communicated to you by bheikh Rashid bin Hamad and iusufLetter dated 10th Ranazan 1348 (10th February 19300 from Sheikh All bin Abdullah al hamudah of iiani Bu All to Tlia Highness the Sultan of unseat &amp; Oman, unseat. A.C. I have received your letter dated the 28th Rajab 1348 (30/12/29) and was acquainted with its contents, liy brother liamdan is coming to see and discuss v/ith you about the matters which you conversed with me at hhabbeh. Insha-allah no difference will happen between you. Hamdan r s delay was on account of the rain. U. E.ALetter dated 10th Ramazan 1348 (10th February 1930) irom Sheikh All bin Abdullah of ban! Bu All to Major G.P.Kurphy, I. A., Political Agent £c H.B.IPs Coneul, Muscat* A.C. There is no news to be communicated to you* as tiy urotner tisuiidan is leaving lor the purpose of seeing the bu.Ltan I deemed it necessary to send you my greetings* Hamdan is coming to see you* Insha-allah you will be kind to him and assist (advise) him in some affairs about which he is unaware.From Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 252, dated 14th March, 1930. Following from Foreign,' No.753-S. Your letter December 28th b88. (iovt. of India are ready to support Sultan Trith Naval Force and to .... possibil ity of air action at Sur but.feel that measures ^hich you advocate are little more likely to secure permanent results than those which have already been taken unless Sultan can maintain permanently at Sur sufficient force to make his authority What force State Infantry do you estimate would be required for this purpose? What would be additional expenditure involved by increase in muscat xniantry necessary to iuaintaj.n detachment of size Estimated at Sur? From Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Muscat. No.253, dated 14th March, 1930. Reference my immediately preceding telegram 252. In paragraph 118 of your report on Sur you seemed to consider that Muscat Infantry could not maintain themselves at Sur unless situation had been completely stabilised by presence of Indian Infantry for prolonged period. Please wire your views questions raised by uovt. of mdia. iou w ill doubtless consult vyalxer.From Political Agent, Muscat To Resident, Bushire. No. 33 C % dated 17th March, 1930. k 'v-tl Your telegram 253 of March 14th. I have con sulted O’Connor and Walker. Estimated minimum addition al number required 350 including one British Officer 4 Indian Officers, 24 N.C.O.’s and 200 Punjabis from India. Consider force consisting entirely of Mekranis might be unre 1 iable • Recruitment and train ing of Mekranis is difficult whilst owing to physical defects principally eyesight it is doubtful whether more than 150 could be obtained. Above addition would enable 425 to be sent to Sur in first instance gradually reducing to 100 when position is stabilized, say after 2-fc years including 6 months preliminary training. Estimated cost of additional force first year Ks311 thousand, second year 230 thousand, third year 145,000, subsequent years 61,400. Muscat State should be able to meet cost of detachment in subsequent years from increased Sur rev enues. Figures for first year could be reduced by about 20,000 if Government issued equipment at cost price.j; - - 7 . • • -• - ■- • Confidential * . Ho«34-C. of 1930. Political Agency and H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat 18th March 1930. Prom Major G.P .Murphy, I.A., Political Agent and H»B.M , s Consul* Muscat* To The Hon’hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Sir* Bushire. With reference to my telegram No.33-&lt;5 ,dated 17th March 1930, I have the honour to forward,herewith,letter Ho.52 dated 16th March 1930 from the Commandant,Muscat Infantry,together with enclosures in which he has worked out (1) the cost of raising and equipment of an additional strength of 350 men together with their maintenance for 1 year. (2) estimated annual expenditure for the upkeep of such a force for subse- -quent years. (3 J estimated annual esqpenditure for a detachment of 100 men at Sur. 2* After consultation with Captain R.L.O*Connor who recently visited Sur,Captain A.R.Walker and Mr B.S.Thomas, I am of opinion that it would be dangerous to land a force of less than 400 men at Sur. The landing would require to be support- -ed by H.M.Ships. 3 Such a force,when once permanently entrenched in a commanding position should be sufficient to bring the town under control and ward off any attack by the Bani Bu All tribe. This tribe has a reputation for attacking at night. Their usual method is to set fire to the huts of their enemies at night and fire at them as they emerge from the burning huts. 4. In 1821,they made a night attack on the British camp at Sur. I would therefore recommend the provision of a couple of search lights. These have not been provided for in the esti- -mates and prices are not available here. After the despatch(2V*) ^ : of my telegram^ Captain Walker has submitted a supplementary estimate for tents and mosquito nets# These would appear to be necessary# &amp;• After the position at Bur has become stabilized and the JBani Bu Ali have accepted the situation, a force of 100 men should be sufficient to maintain the Sultan’s authority there. I have the honour to be, Sir r Your most obedient servant,,r ••• • 0^ i$3C mu cmuii. Subjeot. Estimate °f ax^enaas* From. ^‘ho Commandant Muaaat Infantry Bait©l-Falaj f * 0 . Iha Poli^ioal ^ H.B.k's Uonaul umn. ^ n!raf i B j i tai Frtlgi \ l h9/, 6 .^aCflll-I'a-ai Sir, I ha »9 tha honour to submit an aj^roximat® sstimat® for th« possibl® inorsaa® in the ®i -9 of the Mue oat Lovy® ( In oompilin« thia aatimate I ha»e baaed the prioea of armament® and oertain atoraa on paat purohaae® of the aam®, or similar, artielea landed m Muscat. Aa regard. Machine gun., the prioe. shoen are probably 'fery inaoourate aa I hate no ^.rioed Tooabulary o« stores. I consider that two are essential* ^he present Machine guns of the Infantry are old Nordenfelts and entirely worn out. The sum shown against 'Hutting i® that required for huts made of date etrande whioh make a satisfactory shelter in the hot weather but doee not afford adWiUate proteotion fror rain. A corrugated iron roofing oould be erected in the cold weather to overcome this difficulty at no very heavy cost but if a detachment is to be left permanently in S u r, some sort of bar-acks will eventually have to be built. In considering the composition of the foroe. II ha?o daoidad that, in flaw of tha refutation of the inhabitanta of the oountry round Sur# stiffening of the usually recruited Baluchis from Gaaaur and ^ekran ?ith Punj&amp;bi ^uaalmans is a frims nacesaity, Xq recruit 35 c Baluchis fould be no aasy matter and, in addition, bad eyesight is very prevalent among them* My Indian Officers inform me that there would be no difficulty in raising ex-soldiers of good ty^e and under 3c ye^rs of age, from Cambellfore district. IU ^his would give a nucleus from which junior &amp;.#. Os could be obtained and f aciliwite truning. Material from which C, Os can be made is difficult to find even for the present strength* A strength of 350 would make eight strong platoons of about 44 rifles. command these and train them would require an additional staff of a British Officer, 4 Indian officers, 8 Havaldars and 16 Naiks. All of these would have to be obtained on loan or otherwise from the Indian Army -tith, perhaps, a reduction in d&amp;iks to eight. In view of the fact that the force will be is an insolated and perhaps a difficult situation at times, I consider that the officer should be one with experience and not below the rank of Captain. ^raining should not commence before the beginning of August as the olimats is too severe to to allow any real hard work to be done. In five months the Levy ought to be a fairly efficient force. In view of its small numbers and the past history of expeditions to Sur I consider that even six months spent in training would not be time wasted. Without the staff and Indian ranks enumerated above, ficienoyJO!ixlUt'plUU &lt;n. mu$: z% ^^7^/'' 3o Ht&gt;. 157-4* • of 1950. British Keoldcncy ana Coni»ulate-Ki«««ral # 2bth Aiaroh 1950. Wrm Th« Hon’hlo lisut.-Colons1 K.V. Biscos # i.A., iOlUioal Kssiu^nt in tus Persian ouif* TO The foreign Jisoretary to tiis oovermaent of India, U t m 1 a. fio. 54-C. of m*&lt;m mum mmtm mm &lt;•**•*• 16-3-1930. SIT UAT IPX X- aiR. Sir, lith reference to my telegrsia Bo. 274 of the 19th March 1930, 2 have the honour to forward herewith a letter deceived from the ^litical Agent at Muscat giving details of the coot of raising, equipping and maintaining the additional strength of 550 «»n which it is estiiaated would be required to stabilise the situation at &gt;ur permanently. 2. The total expenditure involved la Ho. 6,86,000 spread over a period of three years aftea which it is estimated that a detachment of a hundred &gt; men only would be necessary and the cost of their maintenance could be met from the customs receipts. It is, of course, beyond the power of the Muscat State to finance an additional fores during the first three years and tills expenditure wouj.d have to be borne by the Government of Inula. 3 . The Government, of India in their telegram Bo. 755-8, dated the 10th Jlarch 1950, stated that they felt that the measures advocated in my letter Bo.2 ho. 688-G of the 28th Dooeisber 1929 were lit tin store likely to eeoure peraaneut results thaa tliose ahloh iuul already been taken, and 1 fully appreciate the force of this view. It aould certainly be preferable to raise an additional force to hold 'Jur as a penaanent m&amp;eure but the price to be paid is high and l tm not aware whether the Goverraaent of India would be willing to incur the expenditure involved lie read point at lesue Bee** to ne to be 4 tlie fighting qualities of tits Ban! hu til and the amount of resistance they are in the last resort pre pared to put up. 1 fully agree with the estimate submitted by Mag or Murphy of the force required which has been prepared in consultation with Captain talker and Captain u 9 Connor, who had himself recently visited Sur, if the situation is considered from a purely military point of view and I feel some dlffldenc&lt; in offering any alternative suggestion because 1 have no personal knowledge of the Ban! Mu All, but l ana inclined to doubt whether they would maintain a recalcitrant attitude if some puisishment was inflicted upon them and they were shown that it was the determi nation of the British Gove nine nt to enforce the authority of the Muscat State on the coast. 1 agree that action by a warship alone would be entirely is always given of the intention to bombard, a fort or tower is knosked down after it has been evacuated, and no one is any the worse. we have at our disposal nowadays however another weapon, naoely, ths aeroplane. It has never been used yet in the ^rwian Gulf except, of course, in the hinterland of huwoit which is far removed from Oman, and the moral effect on the tribes would be considerable. It is quite possible that the presence. 3 - presence of * flying boat «lth a .Hip might prow insufficient. sur. Iwawror. Is only »4 nlies froa :«uaunt skiers the aoyal Air itorce hare a saall base «nd there ecu Id not I think be any difficulty in placing say a flight - tt8cat t0T ‘ “ necessary• a ceupl. of Month. -* they could boab 3ur several ti»e. If neccosary chculd tiie Bani ^ Alt nalntain their contumacious attitude. Under the circumstances I personally doubt uhether thsjr would resist for long. U a-y l««ver be contended that as eoon ae the flight wore withdrawn the aunl 3 u All would reoocupy 3ur wd again reduce the local nuaeat authorities to Impotence. 'ihls risk could be eliminated however if they were coapelled to furnish hoe tags s for good behaviour and one or two of their leading men were compelled to reside in muscat f.r some year, to ocas. farther. ^ o.nneotion I would invite attention to paragraph 2 of the not. of the situation in BUT prepared by Captain ^Conner on 3 ur. a copy of which was fSrwarded for the imoma- tion of the ooverniaent of India. As Captain O'Connor therein points out Ail «» Abdulla, ^urkfa of the Bani Bu All. who is largely responsible for the present attitude of the tribe, lives himself only forty alias inland, that is within easy reach of air- craft. Hitherto he has considered hiasnlf in com plete security because he know, that th. muscat *t*t. do not poseess any military fore, sufficient to attack hie own dwelling and that it is inaccessible fro* the sea. The presence of aeroplanes at or however would. X think, speedily make hit* realise that he was no longer so inaccessible as formerly and cause him to reflect, and if necessary the fact could be emphasised by sending a machine or km two to fly over *T?n&lt;i«r DbO. letter Bo. ? 0 *S. of- 4 - over hits village. for the above reaaone X aa diapooed to think tliat if the authority of the ISueeat State was 8 up ported by one of Hie Majeaty’a ahipe, and mm aeroplanes acting on Uie lines suggested above• it sould, in all likelihood 9 prove effective and adequate and that by these ah? an a the tribe could be eoxapelled to give hostages * it would be vezy much cheaper tiian the raising of a special force to occupy 3ur and would certainly seeia worth trying. If the Government of India so desire X could approach the Air Officer Consaanding, Iraq Coiamand, regarding Ute feasibility of the measures whi^ X have outlined and communicate his views to them. X have the honour to be • 3ir # your aost obedient servant t (SCS)) H.V.BISCOK, Lt.-Colonel, Political Hesident in the Persian uulf. Copy to the Political A^ent at Muscat for information. B2 r Order, for Secretary to tlie Political He •iclent in t&gt;ie °er:;ian Gulf. Buehire, 28 tf. ? r x-c} 1930 .Letter dated 30tix Ste*al 1248 (SOtn A^ril 1V30) trom the -Tali of aur to Saiyid said tin Taintur, ruscat. I Leg to etate that the nam ru Haoan SheiKhs of the Jabal who are under Shei.ih rlamood om. nun,aid raided naiad as t&gt;our and looted more than 2U'J sheep and feOats. i request you to inform the aani nu Hasan and their followers to desist from causing trouble for sur so that no misudderstandmg*and hostilities may ha^en between us and nani Hu Hasan and their followers. 1 nope to receive your instructions m this matter. 1 have arrangea for ^urty to pursue the raiders and recover the looted animals,B»0.22-C, Muscat 12th February 1930, I forwardtherewithtfor your information a copy of a note made by O’Connor on the situation at bur. To The Hon'ble Lieut.Col. K.Y.Biscoe,I.A. # rolinaal Resident in the Persian Gulf, mb' BushireN ■ ■'mcar IV c Letter dated 5tii iml naderi 1348 i.6tn Ayril *»• i — ' .. i &lt;1 ^ t?c nna* chief oi ..rai a* - * aair bin auhainad u«i. ale. to Saiyid, aaid bin Tannur, Wsoat. \ A* • I Leg to inforr you that Auiad Hatudah have written to the , a--cnan&amp;n, chialin and r una) ad d i AH ai • to close traffic and cease their dealings with ham x,u -'.asan. , /e objected to this matter and did not allow them to do such an acj action and told them tnat they must hot carry out any action Without our agreement and the consent of the government, mea -e pointed out this matter to them they informed Auiad Hamudah and told us that Auiad. Hamudah could come themselves if they intend to carry out the matter. Oh hearing this v.e went to see ' all Sa_f bin seder and acquainted him with the facts and sent a special messenger to you m the hope of receiving an early answer Decision rests with you. The disturbance hich is happening m the town is created by Abdullah Dabood who is maxing ^trigues arong the Fuvvaris. He intends to unite the 3 sections (Puwaris, . uhiaim «• Mathana) and make them the allies of ham nu All. we request you to write a threatening letter to him (A idnllah advising him to abstain from such affairs. Te observe that the Su.-ris have some object in view as he (Abdullah) has changed their minds, '.e expect to receive a early answer. U. £. Jilil Ucden 1348 (6th ^ril i- Letter dated 5tJi c bin i ,0 rt.H.tne buitan of * uscat &amp; Oman, r iscat. ■oin •j QVir j aii * tclfib. to tne uo'.ii.jii c j. i litis 'wt ri lineiiCh ivasir bin i unauad and A. C 9t) beg to state-that the MaKhana, uhm.Iin an.r h hi nr. A~ al , !aj .ali have received letters from Auiad narcudah who told them to close traffic. They intended to do so tut we objected und did not allow them and told them that they :no'.ld not tane : any action without the- government•s orders. Tney said that theywould delay action if tiie matter rests in tne hands ox tne uovernii.ent, 'but Aulad u.ai.udah wouxd come (to sur lor tnis pux-coe. themselves. 'Ye have i; formed the vali Saiyid Saix bin oi the matter and have sent this letter with a messenger xn the hc^e of receiving an early and favourable ansv/er. eci.-o: ./ith you. &gt;e beg to mfon you that we observe that ^aiyid Abdullah Dabood has deceived the Fuvaris and it is necessary ohat you should punish him and send him a threatening letter. U. h. 'I setter dated 5th hml Q,adeh xZ-46 (6th April id50) from Saiyid ouif bin neder, oi Our, the Oc umcal of ministers cO n. a. tne duitah 01 ixusea u t. wmax^.. .. C. I beg to inform you that the gueimn of Arama* hasir tin xunairad, and his party, came to see me stating that Aulad Hai udah nave written to the Majechana* Ghialin a:u, i uhamad bin All ai haj’aii asKing them to close traffic and leaiiugs with the ■ inhabitants of Ja’alan and uhai- di ah. Tl:ie ^ fi intended to carry out the action but the Arama objected and said ; that they were their partners m the town and such sort of affairs must not be done without the order ol the uocernment. I axu reporting the matter to you with the request to send me cxn early answer as Ai hai udah may come to i&gt;oor for this purpose ve'ry snortly. U . h .From Foreign. To Political Muscat. No 1327-S dated 1st May 1930. Addressed Political Resident Bushire repeated P.A. Muscat. Your telegram of March 19th.274 Please obtain and forward an appreciation from O f Connor shoeing possible role of force required its disposition ^hen in occupation incl uding number of posts which it would be necessary to place.probable strength and armament of hostile element and the direction from which attack might be anticipated. It is unlikely that Punjabis or other Indians would be made available.Appreciation SUB* The following appreciation is forwarded in accordance with Governnent of India telegram Ho* 1327-3, dated 1st Kay 1930, to Political Resident, Buehire, repeated to Political Agent, Muscat* The undermentioned papers should he referred to in conjunction with the appreciation* 1. Letter Ho. 137-3, dated 28th March 1930, from the Hon’hie the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf to the Foreign Secretary to the GoYera- -m@nt of India* 2* Letter Ho* 34-3 of 13th ./Arch 1930 from the Political /gent and K.H’s* Consul, Muscat, to the Hon’hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, forwarding letter Ho* 52, dated 16th March 1930 from the Commandant, Muscat Infantry 3* My report on 3ur dated January 1930, copy attached*Appreciation SUE 3y Capt. B« L. 0*Connor 1/9 Jat Bogiaent. 9th April 1930 Reference map •JSnvirons of Z\xr** Possible role of force required* 1* The role of a force despatched to 3ur would he primarily a defensive one* It should he able (a) to defend Itself and the towns of Sur and Belad es 3ur from attack It may he requireu (b) to supply escorts and guards for State authorities and to prevenl interference with the functions of the local administration* (o) if air action is employed, to co~operate with the Royal Air Force as necessary! provide aerodrome Dispositions in a* (a). The water supply for Bur is occupation* obtained from Belad es Sur, a village about li miles Inland; water is trans ported to Bur in skins by donkeys* The force should therefore encamp at Baled es sur, where it can control the water supply* A suitable position for a casp is on the ridge called Sed, overlooking from the Sast the village of Belad es SurThis ridge is flat topped and risns alwufc 50 feet higher than the surround- -ing plain* It doninates Balad es jur and the approaches to the wells» which fall within effective rifle range. It flanks the aain caravan road from the port of Hur through Belad os sur to the interior, passing through the Beni Bu Ail and Beni Bu Hasan country. It would he necessary to hold the towers called SAMA§HA and J&amp;BABI on the ridge %SD and the tower called •AI3 i aile Horth-gast of the pal* groves of Belad as Stir* Saaagha and Jerahi control approaches to Belad es Sur fro* South and ast. ^hriTr towers are huilt on the same principle as our blockhouses in the Khyher. They require repairing hut could he made to &amp;ccom*odate 3-10 men each* At present there are three men in each* It may also he necessary to occupy the small fort on the road to the Interior and about Biles from Belad es sur. 3arly information of a threatened attack fro* the South could thus be obtained* It is at present held by 7 men of the Beni Bu All tribe and is not under the control of the Wall* (b) the Wall of Sur lives at Belad es Sur and has about 60 armed tribesmen taskers) • Their dispositions are Wall 9 s residence and fort 16 men Samagha tower 3 ' Jerabi • 3 * AiS • 3 * Jinah fort - 35 Jlnah■i (try Jinah fort is a larga, square, walled enclosure with towers at eack angle and a large tower inside# The walls and towers are in a ruinous condit&lt; -ion. It co/fvars the Western approach* -es to the town# These askers are of the Bani amt trihe in restem Hajar and Imve the reputation of loyalty. They are armed with British rifles and are Bedu. They receive no training. probable strength and armament of hostile elements# 5# (a) The trihe most likely to give opposition is the Beni Bu All# The Shaikh is All bin Abdullah Xl Hamudah. % He lives at the tribal headquarters at Belad Beni Bu All, a large village sit uated about 40 miles inland. This tribe might with its allies be able to raise 1000 - 1500 men but it is improbable that it could collect more than &lt;3fc)0 or ^00. The village of Aiqa, on the sea, separated from k&amp;qrimataln ISur) by a narrow creek, is occupied by the Beni Bu All# It could raise about 70 men# ,Lgnebeh&gt; The Jenebeh of Sur are divided into four sections# Two of them, the Kakhanna and Ghiyalin, are at feud with the other t^w, the Arama and -uaris. The lakhanna and Ghiyalin are allied to the Beni Bu All, who would use every endeavour to enlist their help# The fighting strength of the l^akhanna and Ghiyalin sections is about 250 - 300 rifles# I That_ # 16 ' ; ^ (l4o) That of the Araiaa and I uarts, wtio are well disposed to the Government at present is about 400 rifles. They are a seagoing tribe and a large number are at sea for long periods. During the worst of the Gouth- -ast monsoon there is a lull in their seagoing aotiviti' Hfij’ SfrvpC ikely that *mh of the £-4*~h *jm. , 1 ^ ■**.£ if ^ ^ ' ^ ^ ^4^4 JeneJ^eh would be drawn into hostilities T l against the kusoat State. ^the sea and their town is iiuita open to bombardment by Ships. Beni Su ijasaan. This tribe have a long stand* -ing feud with the Bmni 3u Allrand it is unlikely that they would assist the latter. The village of Belad Beni 3u ££t Hasan is about 3-4 miles from Belad Beni 3u All. Recently, in March 1930» the Beni 3u H ssan raided the villas© of Belad es »ur. Until this occurrence they had been on good terms with the State Government. They number, with allies, about 700-800 fighting men and could raise about 3 tjQ* 4&amp;Q . P ftTmmf- The tribes of Sur and Jaal&amp;n are armed principally with Martini Henrys but there are also a fair pro- -portlon of British pattern magaslne rifles and some Turkish rifles. The supply of ammunition may be taken as 100 to 150 rounds per man. In* Directions from which attacks might he anticipated* Composition of force* mmmm In addition they can and do make their own rounds with lead and gunpowder, using fired oases and fresh caps* 4. Attacks might come from any direction and might he delivered from all directions at the same time* A comon method of attack of a village is for a few men to creep up hy night flre the r#e&amp; huts while the remainder shoot hy the light of the flames* . i fhe most likely direction from which attacks might he anticipated are AJu the Jouth East and &lt;ast as the ggound on those sides affords oovei'ed approaches* 5* The estimate of the force required to oooupy Belad es Star was given as 400, of whoa £00 were tq ae IunJahls * and the rest Baluchis* But if Indians are not available, as suggest- -ed in Government of India telegram No* s 1327*8 of 1st May 1930,1 have grave doubt* of the wisdom of sending a force composed entirely of Baluchis* But should this he decided on, the strength of the force should, in my opinion, be increased to $00 men* &gt;1. Landing facilities 2* Transport* 3. Coiumunioations- Hoaas. KBPOifl! QM 3Uii . JANUAitY 1930. Thera are six small hedans avail- aisle at Bur for landing troops and baggage but not mules, transport vehicles, or guns* A large number of 'horis*(open boats) are available which could be used for landing small articles of baggage:i*e*men’s kits etc* Ships would have to anchor in open anchorage off the town in from 8 to 11 fathoms and dis tant from shore 6 cables or slightly over 1200 yds* There are no piers: all craft would have to be beached* The beach is i_mile long and is commanded on Doth east and west sides by high ground surmounted by towers capable of holding 10 men* On the eastern side there are 2 towers and on western 5* These are all visible from the sea. There is no wheeled transport available. About 50 camels and 100 donkeys are availa le in SUB, but more could be ob tained from the interior. About 300 donkeys could be obtained from Belad-es-3ur and vilr lages around. Donkeys are used for transport of water, in skins. ^a) Hoads through the town are broad and suitable for all forms of M.T. A broad all-weather track with hard surface and suit able for all forms of M.T.exists between SDH and BJ2LAD-BS-BUH about two miles inland,(243) inland, where the water supply is located and where camping ground would need to he situated. At point where this road enters the valley of BSLAD- SS-SIfR and i mile from town some work is required to improve it.-^A Jlatoon of mon working for 2 hours oould accomplish this. This road is called JSL FliiJ. (h). No telegraph or telephone communfcaation exists. Wooden poles (bullies) are available for carrying telephone lines. There are over 80 large wells in BSLAD-BS-STO used as a water supply for the town and for cultivation. Three are recommended* These are named SAILAGrKA (nearest to camping ground). HBSA and 3ABAIKHAH and are xined with stone and cement. Diameters: 11 ft.,21 ft.28 ft. Depth to water: 15 to 18 ft. Depth of water: 2 to 3 ft. This does not decrease in summer hut rises after rain. The above is the average depth of all the wells. The Arabs rarely take the trouble to dig deeper than is nece ssary to give them this head of water. Majority of wells are stone lined and fitted with overhead gear made of cut palm trees supporting a pulley. Water is drawn up in large skins by bullocks. A few wells have reservoirs for stor age of water, capacity about 3500 gallon 5*gallons* Xiiere are 11 wells at SAKAIKHAH, 1 mile from BjSLAD-B 8&gt;BUH* Stone lined? diameters varying from 18 to 24 ft$ depth 12 to 15 ft; depth of water li to 2 ft* The water from these is slightly 'brackish and is used for cultivation* It could he used hy troops for washing* At SANAISALAH, a small village on the coast 1 mile west of SITR, there are 2 wells* These suffice only for the needs of the villagers* Sufficient water exists in BELAD for 2 battalions after the needs of the population have been met* The water supply could be increased by deepening the wells* fresh wells oould be dug f If thought necessary, anywhere in the valley. (a) Bice, wheat pda11,sugar,matches imported from India, are available in BOB* Oil from AbadanlAnglo-rersian ©il Co.) is shipped from Muscat* lb). Local supplies are chickens, eggs,goats,milk,fishifuel and dates. ITresh vegetables are not available but could be grown in B3LAD-ES-SUB. around is available for expensive cultivation* The only animal food obtainaole locally is lucerne; donkeys are largely fed on daces, especially on a journey* There is no grazing except for camels and goats. BhoosaBhoosa is not available,nor 'barley# * ’■.yyAJ Note* 6* Accommodation. 7* Camping-ground* i (o) The only product from the interior is dry dates called* 1 hear M ( J which are largely exported to India. Ji Bam, an Indian Banyan and BUB representative of the firm of Khimji Bam Bass of Muscat would 'be a very useful man to retain as general agent by a force landing in SUB* He has had 10 years in the place an is widely known and highly respected hy both townspeople and tribes of the interior. No accommodation exists for housing troops. Tents would be s^itaole for the greater part of the year. SUB has a much better summer than MMsoat, not being surrounded by rooky hills as is the latter place, and a cool wind blows throughtout the year. Material is available locally for hitting. The most suitable site for a camp ing g: oimd is on the S.3. extremity of the low ridge called 1SD which rises tfrom 50 to 100 ft. in height and runs from S.3. to N.W.at a distance of 2 miles from SUB. At its 3.3.extremity it dominates at close range the town of BBLAD-BS-SUB and the water supply there. There are two towers on this ridge; SAMAGHA near the camping ground and JBBABI about iOOO yds. away. On another and neighbouring ridge overlooking the motor road where it enters the valley of BBLAB-BS-SUB, there is a third tower called AIS. There is a garrison of 3 to8. iSngineer Stores, v ■ i 4 askersjln each of these 3 towers are huilt on the sample principle as those in the KHYBSR. It would he necessary to holJL these towers hy pioguets. After some necessary repairs they could accommodate a section of men. This site^ould he the most suitable for the defence of the •4 town of 33ELA33-3S-31XE end of the troops themselves. None are available locally, Defence stores, wire, etc, would have to he brought. Plenty of stone is avail able and near for construction_of sanghas. Pumping plantj pumps; piping; porta ole tanks for storage and riltrat- ion of water relative to the siae of the force would have to he brought, 500 yds. of piping would he required to convey water from wells to camp. Camping ground is 100 ft, above level of surface of wells, iSxtensive Hat ground is available in vicinity of SANAISAIAH which might be suitable for an aerodrome, I hesitate to pronounce on its fitness as the surface, in parts, is a shallow crust which sinks under the heel, sd/. O’Connor. CaptHesidency office, Subzabad* Here /itfa a fair copy of my meRomndum H0.83-C of tlie 8th instant, a rongh copy of 'vxuch was sent Ir.st weeJc to catch the mail. ' riease remove the .tatter from your fife., and eubstitute ■tbs fair copy* roliticai Agent K.b.U'b Consul, MuscatBSS^asaHEK? tmmB aoMifiP}a&gt;TXAL / L . —r -‘ ’ 24D ;,o* 63-C of i ^30» rOXitXcai Agency &lt;k iuM*£ 9 9 conouiate, 4Kuocat» uue uUi wuly 1^30• 7o 'ine .lon^oxe xne ^oXxtiosU. in tne rersi-au uuir, jiusniro* subject:• S U a » memorandums Sinoe xay arrival here I have spent some time in studying the SUH question by a perusal of the Agency files and in conversation with various individuals, including mV* Thomas, during these conversations X have been careful to get other peopled views without expressing my o*u. As I see it the bUH problem reduced to its simpleat form is as follows. 2. Limits of responsibility . The ^uscat state, ( and consequently ourselves), as elsewhere tnrougnout tne Sultan 1 s territories, is only concerned with the Coast -the port of aim including a1 Q,A. over this area tne State cun oe expected, and should receive assistance from us, to exercise a more or less efxective control. Xne interior or JaALAH, though nominally under the Sultan, has been, is and probably always will os virtually independent. 3. The hAfti iiH AL1 . The Barn hu All are a tribe of tne interior, and if they contented themselves with asserting tneir independence in that area alone, tneir attitude - nowever truculent- oouid bo ignored by the ot&amp;te ana us. They, however, as you are aware, not only proclaim tnemoolves independent of the sultan but also lay a definite claim to AI3A, and a claim- which tney2. 24 *v) nave exercised- to certain dues on diiows maJcing use of the harbour. In addition they also indulge in mischievous intrigues in 3UR* p THK JliiiSBhH . 3UR is occupied by certain elements of the JSiiEBEH, as AIQ^A just oppoeite is occupied by certain elements of tne BAHI BU AH* The Jenebeh it may oe noted ?.ro also a strong tribal confederation in the interior. The Sur Jenebeh in pre-war years were apparently more or less united- as far as any Arab tribe can be said to be united, and thus to some extent at all events formed an opposition against the interference oi the Bani Bu Ali in bur. In 1913 a blood feud started, which h^.s continued since, dividing the four sections of the tribe inhaoiting bur into two factions (a) AhAhA and iTOAKlS versus (b) juuOiAjaA and (iiUAiJLn. The Bani hu Ali have taxen advantage of this split to secure the allience of (b). 5 . Attitude of the tribes . Practically all the Oman tribes belong to two main divisions: GHA^IKI and ftiAhAttl. The Bani Bu Ali and the Jenebeh belong to the former, while the tribes of the IMAM and ISA Blh SAI&amp;H for instance belong to the latter. There is apparently not much love lost, however, between the aur jenebeh and the Bani Bu Ali* The former do not join in tne latter’s claim of independence# and admit that they are under the Muscat State. This admission need not be taxen as snowing a fervent loyalty but at any rate places them in a somewhat different category to the Bani Bu Ali. 6. gu scat I nfa ntry for Bur . I am not prepared for the moment after such a short time in Ku8cat ; to suggest any definite line of policy with regard to Sur# though I hope to do so after a further study of the situation. I am# however, definitely ruid strongly against tne proposal to send a large force of Muscat Infantry to sur unless the situation there alters very much for the worse# and until all other methods have been tried without success. The3 (2r£&gt;) praaont situation at fftir dooe not* in my opinion* call for any auoh drastic measures* On tne political aide the proposal naa Tarioua disadraiita^co* while on the finr.ncial side* though financial reaeone were adduced for its support- it would not seem to aave imch to recoimn«irid it# Mr* ihoms infoms me that the total possible revenues from the Sur Customs *. ouid he about / dU«000 per &amp;unusi» of which for the last h years aoout p 3o f juo has been collected annually* this toeing at least as anoh as for any previous quinquennial period- find perhaps more* in order therefore to increase this ^ 3U»UQ0 to jt dOfUOO it was proposed to raise a force which would coot tne Indian Government a large sum in l&amp;Khs of rupees annually* for at least three years, while the expense of the force thereafter would fall on the husu&amp;t state and apparently swallow up almost all the extra revenue thus gamed# If it was possible and safe to send a small force of Muscat Infantry to bur* tne question vouid taxe on a soaewnat different complexion# ?* I*aral and Air Action # If military force in the onape of sending a large body of troops to bur is ruled out* the question of pressure by naval and air action arises- snouid need for such pressure occur# with regard to air action# if we wish to tacxle the banl jju All seriously for any reason tnen air action would be needed for the obvious reason tnat this tribe* except for ths few elements in Aiqa* inhabits the interior out of range of guns# Xf» however* we wished to put pressure on bur alone then I tain* that it might be possible to do this by naval action alone# It may be objected that previous naval action m November 1926 had no permanent effect, but I venture to su fo , est that this was because action was confined to the demolition of a single fort of no particular importance# To produce the necesnary effect at fcur naval action will nave to be in the nature of a bloccede and destruction of dhows (wrier tne Arab valueo far more than ms nouse)* such as was successfully carried out at Aha»ab#(Xhe political rand internationaJ. object!one to a ’’biocjcade’ 1 could be avoided ao indicatnci in political heaident^ t&lt;3le£iram Hio. 4ti ox* the 10th January 19‘49)* Tne harbour at our is exceptionally \ 7 ell adapted to a blooicade, as a glance at a chart -will show. 0# Move ment s of Sur dhowa « in connection with naval action the movements of the sur dhows on which the popula tion cf that port practically live are of importance* They are as follows* In August and September, before tne commencement of the north-east monsoon which blows from October to April, the fc»ur dhows sail to -oasr&amp;h where they load up with dates, and return to sur, and other local ports, though some go straight on to India etc* After a short stay in sur they leave again about the end of September for India, Zanzibar and Aden talcing tne hasrah dates with them for sale* Having sold uieir cargo they load up with rice etc and return to bur at the end of the north-east monsoon i.e* March-April* During the oouth-wast monsoon , say from *Tune to beptember, all the dhows are laid up in bur harbour* The best period for naval action therefore would appear to be* (1) In early August to prevent the dhows getting out of bur. (2) In March and April to prevent the dhows getting into bur. (3) In April and May to destroy the dhows in the harbour* v* present situ at ion in bur * Mr* Thomas has recently received a letter from tne wall of bur to the following effects (a) That the situation is normal* (b) Tnat the effect of tne Khasab operations nas had a salutary effect on the local inhabitants* (c) That the Bani Bu Ali have removed their *Wali M whom they had placed at Aiqa, and that for the rom^rt at any rate their influence seems to be the wane.(It may ha note^ that tno’»#rh the Ban! Bu All*3 flag has disappeared their flagstaff at Aiqa is still standing.) C V^ kajor roiitical Agent u: K.B.M*s Consult Muscat.CONlflPMTIAI, 250. d3-C of 1930. ^5^) political Agency &amp; H.i3.M»s uonouiate, Muscat, the 8th July 1930. Xo Xhe Hon’hie the political hesident in the Persian Oulft Bushlre. Buhjectt* a J 3 . memorandum. Since my arrival here I have spent some time in studying the SUK question by a perusal of the Agency files und in conversation with various individuals» including iff. liiomau. During these conversations X have oeen carefui to get other people's views without expressiiAg /iiy own. As i see it the 8UR problem reduced to its simplest form is as follows. 2. Limits of responsibility . The Muscat State, ( and consequently ourselves), as elsewhere throughout the Sultan* s territories, is only concerned with the Coast -tne port of SUR including AIQA* Over this area the State can oe expected, and should receive assistance from us, to exercise a more or less effective control. The interior or JAALAN, though nominally under the Sultan, has been, is and probably always will be virtually independent. 3. The bAhl i&gt;U ALX » The 23ani hu All are a tribe of tne interior, and if they contented themselves with \ asserting tneir independence in that area alone, their attitude - however truculent- could be ignored by the \ State and ue. They, however, as you are aware, not only proclaim themselves independent of the sultan but also lay a definite claim to AIQA# and a claim- union theyI ' ■ % i ■ i. i M. 2 . ft nave exercised- to certain dues on dhows zaaiung' use of '23'4 : ) the harbour* in addition they also indulge in mischievous intrigues in &amp;UH» JOH ia oocu^iea toy certain eiewents of the as AIQA Just opposite xa occupied by ccrt&amp;xn oisments of tne 4Ai&lt;I hJ Aia* iho oenebon it may so noted are aioo a strong tribal comederation in tne anterior* ihe Sur jrenoben in pi*s-war years were apparently more or leas united- aa far as any Arab tribe can be said to be united, and thus to some extent at ail events formed an opposition against the interferenoe of tne hani hu Ali xn aur* xii 1913 a blood feud started, wmon a s continued since, dividing tne four sections of tne trios inhabiting ;&gt;ur into t^o factions (a) AiiAaA and j?U*AH13 versus (b) MauQaAiXA and aiUAiin* The Bani bu Ali have taxen advantage of tms split to seoure tne allienoe of (b)* 5. Attitude of tne tribes * practically ail the Oman tribes belong to t.vo main divisions: GhAfffHI and HAbAvi 9 The i&gt;ani du All and the Jenebeh belong to tne former, while the tribes of the I*A&amp; and idA Bib oAUlH for instance belong to tne latter, mere is apparently not muon love lost, nowever, between the bur Jenebeh and the dkni Bu All* The former do not Join in tne latter^ claim * ^ &lt; of indepenconct, and adnit fcn&amp;t they are under the muscat btate* This admission need not be ta^en as showing a fervent loyalty but at any rate places them in a somewhat different category to the Bani Bu Ali* 6* muscat infantry for bur * I am not prepared for the moment^after auon &amp; snort time in muecatjto suggest any definite line of policy with regard to Sur, though Z hope to do so alter a further study of the situation* I am, novever, definitely and strongly against tne proposal to send a large force of muscat infantry to Bur unless the situation there altera very much for the worse, and until all other methods have vesn tried without success* The3 py-' t % r present situation at 3ur does not, in my opinion* call for any sucn diastic measuroB*i On tne poxi ical Si ^ e proposal has various disadvantages, 'while on the financial side- though financial reasons were adduced for its sa ; t orL- it would not seem to nave much to recommend it. Mr. 'ihomas informs me that the total possible revenues from the Sur Customs would he about ^ 80,000 per annum, of which fo± the last S year** about / 30,000 n&amp;s been collected annually, this being at least as nuoh as for any previous quinqueM^ial period- and perhaps more* In order therefore to increase this 4 30,000 to 80,000 it was proposed to raise a force wnich would coot tne Indian Government a large sum in laiehs of rupees annually, for at least three years, while the expense of the force thereafter would fall on the Muscat gtate and apparently swallow up almost all the extra revenue thus gained. If it was possible and safe to send a frinaii force of Muscat Infantry to bur, tne question ould taice on a somewhat different coM^-^exicn. 7 . ^jayal and Air Action. If military force in the shape of sending a large body of troops to bur is ruled out, the question of pressure by naval and air action arises- should need for suoh pressure occur, with regard to air action. If we wish to tacKle the Bani Bu All seriously tor auy reason tnen air action would be needed for tne obvioue reason that this tribe, except for tne few elements in Aiqa, inhabits the interior out of range of guns. If, however, we wished to put pressure on bur alone then I tain* that it might be possible to do this by naval action alone. It may oe objected that previous naval action in Mcvembcr 1928 md no permanent effect, out I venture to suggest that this was because action was confined to the demolition of a single fort of no particular importance. To produce the necessary offset at bur naval action will nave to be in tue nature of a Blockade and destruction of dho*&amp; (whicn tne Arab values far more than his house), such as was successfully carried out at Ahasab.(The politicaland international otojmotions to a 'blocKadc* could be avoided a.^ iridlCci^ud ixx rolltioal teiefcraa ho* 40 of ton 13th jramar/ 1^39). i’xici harbour at aur is oxceptioiaiiiy veil adapted tu a bioai£i*dOf as a glance at a chart will oh cm# i 3# yoveiflen te of aur dnnws# in connect ion vlth naval action 1/45 aovemonts oX the uur dnov.s on ^hioh trie popular tion of that port practically live art of importance# Tney are as foliowB# In August and oeptomoer, before tne oormenceraent of tne nortii^east monsoon whion olOMe freat October to April* the t»ur dhows sail to xiasrati where they load up with da tee* and return to our* and otnar looal ports* though soiue go straight on to India etc# After a snort stay ia dur tmy leave again about the end of bop timber for India* Zanzibar and Aden taking t e haerau dates with tneun for sale# naving sold their cargo tney load up with rice etc arid return to tiur at the ex^d of tne north-east Fionsoon i*e* -&lt;e&amp;rch»April# During the south-west idonsoon * say froxu June to fcieptetutoor* all the dhows are laid up in Sur harbour# Tire best period for naval action therefore would appear to bes (1) In early August to prevent the dhows getting out of tfur# (2) In aAroh and April to prevent the dhows getting into bur# (3) In April and Hay to destroy the dhows in the harbour# 9# pre sent situ ation, in jiur* iir# Thoxans nao recently received a letter from tne well of bur to the following offsetx (a) tnat tne situation i# ncmal* (b) That the effect of tnu oiiuiA-b operation© has hac^ n salutary effect on the local mm^oitants# (o) That the Bani Du All have removed their ^Wali* whom they had placed at Aide* and that for the moment at soiy rate th?ir Influence seems to be* v 1^] iranslation of a letter dated 24tn i/iuharran 134^ (22nd June lu30) from bneiida Ail bin ADduiuah ai nai^bdan, Amir of oa^lan, to H.H, the Sultan of jzuscat &lt;5c Oman, A.C. I have received your letter dated the Dth Dhil hejjeh 1348 (5/5/30) and was acquainted with its contents, fou have remarked that delay In affairs is not advisaoie and that 1 should communicate with your son said and your wazir inoinas who are authorised to discuss matters on your oenaif wnen we meet at sur. lour object is that i should change my flag into a red one and not to levy tax on my subjects, we understand from this statement that we are under restriction, that we have no authority in our country and that we should be followers of Muscat without any lawful reason on tneir part. we say that since the establishment of our Government in Ja'alan and from the time of my father and grandfather they were always independent and we are enjoying the same and we are not followers of any (iovernment neither muscat nor others, xf you desires us to change our flag you should write a bond bearing your signature and that of the uritish government to t&amp;e effect that we are independent in our country viz.from Aiqa up to the end of our boundary as it is Known by geography, and that tne concession of all mines in our country shall rests with us. when such bond is received we will change our flag as you have desired. As to the -ritish protection it is extended to both of ud in an equal manner. U. E. (V'C'U'-n. C*. (XU. r Yvx \ ^ * curwv^ , L^r\ Cv&amp;ua. ^ M i •'j rt ^ rs, ir'k .&gt; Telegram Code. T rom To JJated Political, i.uscato nesiaei;t, j-uoiiire. 64-0. Stii ^uly 1950. buoject to your approval x propose leaving here on recess on or aoout 24th instant, hut li oj putting on my going by one v/eeji 1 cou-lcl accompany you to SUR i would preier to do that unless the huscat boils with which I am at present aulictea ao not disappear in which case i should like to leave on 24th. i sent you a despatch by yesterday’s mail giving my views on BUR. Latest iniormation indicates that all is cpiite there now. Iolitical.v pf H'-fl-Kf irf itl7/jo Qo) Confidential. No.349-S of 1930. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 15th July 1950. To The Political Agent, Muscat. Suh.j ect s Sr- . Memorandum. Reference your memoranduin Ho*83-C, da^eu 8 th July 1930. I recently discussed the question of 'bringing pressure to 'bear on Sur, or rather on the Beni Bu All, with the late Senior Naval Officer, who had himself visited the place. He stated that there was no difficulty about preventing dhows from leaving Sur ; the Sur dhows are very large and the water on the bar is so shallow that they are towed outside the 'bar with absolutely nothing in them. The mast and other gear are subsequently taken out and put in the dhow outside the bar. Nothing would be simpler than for one of His Majesty’s ships to prevent those dhows leaving Sur. On the other hand the large majority of these dhows belong to the Jenebah and as they acknowledge the sovereignty of Muscat there would be no justification for stopping their dhows: I understand that your predecessor stated that out of some 150 dhows at Sur only about 8 or 10 belong to the Beni Bu Ali. Thus at least nine out of every ten of the Sur dhows would have to be allowed to proceed. ^ The question then arises whether the detention of the Beni Bu Ali dhows would bring the Amir of Jaalan, who lives in the interior and who would► f 'll - 2 - would presumably not be seriously inconvenienced by the detention of a few dhows, to his senses. These dhows belong presumably to a small section of the trite who live on the coast, and I do not know how far their detention would affect the trite as a whole. It is this question 0 that I propose to investigate when I go to Sur, but 1 should be glad if you could obtain the views of the Muscat State authorities on this point. 4 # Prima facie it seems somewhat improhahle that the tribe who, as far as I am aware, live principally in the interior and exist on their date groves, herds, etc., would be seriously inconvenienced by the detention of dhows belonging to a few of their members who happen to reside on the coast. 5 # Please address yoiwrexily to me 'c/o the Senior Faval Officer, H.M.S.'Triad', Henjam'. (SGD$&gt; H. V. BISCOE, Lt.Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confidential. v^\ ✓ No.K/l of 1950. / Political Agency, Muscat Recess Office, Karachi. 28th July 1930. To The Hon’hle the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. I intercepted your memorandum No.349^s of the 15t July 1930 here on my arrival from Muscat today. The office typewriter is packed up, and I am writing this in a hurry to try and catch the Air Mail which closes shortly. s/L* 2. As I see the Sur situation ou^ object with regard to Sur is two fold (a) to prevent the Bani Bu Ali from interfering in Sur (b) to make the Janabeh pay up their Customs dues. It is true that the Janabeh acknowledge^ the Sovereignty of the Muscat State (vide para 2 of your letter under reference) but not to the extent of paying up their full dues. It is Xxxx the Janabeh who occupy Sur and it is from them that the Sur dues are due. 3 . in this connection it would appear necessary to have from the Muscat State some clear statement as to which sections 0 f the Sur population pay these dues (i.e. the Rs.30,000 mentioned in para 6 of ray memo 83-C) and which defaults. Is it the case that all the importers of goods pay only a fraction of what they should, or do some pay the full amount of their dues and others nothing at all. 4 b With this information in our possession we would then consider the advisability of bringing pressure to bear on the Janabeh to pay up what they owe. The extent to which back dues would be demanded from them, would be a matter for consideration. 5# If the Bani Bu Ali (see para 3 of my memo.83-6) refrain in the future, as they appear to be doing for the moment, from interfering in Sur affairs, they can be left to themselves and their truculent letters can be ignored.•s Pr^ma facie the most hopeful way of countering their inter ference in Sur would be to try and detach from them the Makhana and Ghialin sections of the Janabeh, A step in this direction would be /v compose^ bloodjfde'd which at present splits the .Tanabeh xioutiM in half.. 5 , I regret that as not being in Muscat I am unable to confirm from the Council of State the portion of Sur dhows owned by the .Tanabeh and the Bani Bu Ali # but certainly the greater portion of these dhows belongs to the former. T.C,Fowle Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat.Telegram ■V / From Resident Triad Henjam Radio To Major Fowl/e Karachi Mo.T/106 D.and R. 11th August 1930. I interviewed Sheikh of Jaalan at Sur yesterday* He has promised to refrain from flying his flag and issuing passports. It may be useful for you to know this. When you interview Sultan who will I hope be duly grateful for efiorts we are making on his behalf. Resident. -Confidential No.416-3 of 1930 British. Hesidency and Consulate-General Bushire, the 16th August 1930. From: - The Secretary to the Hon 1 hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To - The Political Agent, Muscat. Sir, I am directed to forv/ard for your information a copy of a despatch that the Hon^hle the Political Resident has addressed to the Government of India regard ing the situation at Sur. 2 . It will he seen that Shaikh Ali has agreed to refrain from flying his own flag at Aiqa and from issuing passports and has thus abandoned his claim to he regarded as independent of Muscat. Colonel Biscoe trusts that this news will he a source of gratification to His High ness the Sultan. 3, You will see from the despatch that the Hon’hle the Political Resident considers that every effort should he made to compose the differences between the four sections of the Jenneheh and that he himself urged upon the leaders of the Jenneheh tribe the advisihility of composing their differences. He would he glad if you will urge upon the Muscat authorities the necessity for keeping closely in touch with thethe situation at Sur and using such influence as they possess to bring ahout a settlement there* If the J7ali is unable to do this possibly a visit by Shaikh Zubair or some other influential person to Sur would bring about a settlement, to which the Political Resident attaches much importance. Colonel Biscoe cannot help feeling that the Muscat authorities have been very lax in their administration of the customs at Sur in the past and tnat prompt measures should be taken to rectify matters and that, while it is obviously desirable to proceed slowly in the first instance, a start should, at any rate, be made by replacing the present Director by some, one who has no previous connection with Sur and who can be counted on to conduct the administration with a reasonable degree of honesty. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant y*”' Capt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*authority of the Muscat Utate at that port* 4* Ib order to aake thia deepatoh oelf-contained I would veature t© auiasarioe briefly the eituatioa at Bur as it has existed for sorae years past* Bar is a well built towa of some 10 f 000 iBhabitaBts situated on the coast about 95 Edits south of Muscat* At the bach of the town is a large creek, the entrance to whteh ie a Tory narrow channel to the ^outh of the town* On the oppoeito side of the entrance is the small haslet of Ai&lt;|a* Bur is entirely peopled by Arabs of the Jennebeh tribe, while iqa belongs t© the *aai Bu All. There is a loa^-standing blood feud between the Ban! Bu All and the Jennebeh, but the Jennebeh who consist of four sections - the Arams, the Fuwarls, the ;4akhanneh and the Ohialin are also divided amon^, theaaieives, and since 1915 there has been a blood feud between the Arams and the &gt;'uwaris on the one hand and the akhaaneh and the hialin-on the other. Affrays have taken place between the two contending parties; a number of lives have oeen lost and Bur is at present an armed eassp in which no man stirs abroad without a rifle and a dagger. The Jennebeh are largely a sea-faring tribe and possess some 60 lar^e dhows and many smaller craft, v~The former leave rur about the middle of August and pressed to Basrah where they load with dates which they sell either in India or in Aden and from india some of the dhows proceed to &amp;4at Africa whence they bring cargoes of timber^ etc.,while others brin&amp; Indian aerchaa- dise such as rice, piece-goods etc. ,direet to Bur. The voyages generally last from the middle of August to about—iuu.ii.now .■■i—i wf &amp; about Afrii or and on them the population are large!/ dependent for their lireliho d though the/ alee own a few date &amp;revee in the interior* &amp;• the ) ani hu /li on the other hand are eoeentlai!/ an inland trite and their headquarters are at Jaalan where the/ own exteneire date plantatioae* the email eettleaent of the ani Bu All at Al^a on!/ own about 7 or 8 dhowe* The Shaikh of the Baal Bu All la one All Bln Abdullah, a young wan who is largely in the hands of his relatives and who, as the Government of India are aware, has recently clainted to be an independ* ent iiuler* These pretensions have taken the form of hoisting his own flag at Al^a, Issuing passports in hie own name to members uf his tribe# and the levy ..g of taxes on the Jenneueh dhows entering the &gt;^ur creek, this claim is of e mparatively recent origin and in the past the ani Bu All have on several occasions rendered asaistanoe to the ul an of useat* The Shaikh ie still in receipt of a regular allowance from useat for eervicei rendered in I69i^and the limirs of Jaalan have been accorded in return for assistanee rendered In 1870 the privilege of importing goods through Sur free of euetess duty* 1 was given to understand during the interview which I had with shaikh All that the chief cause which gave rise to these pretensions was the visit of some iutt 0 lo-ierslan Oil Company geologists to that part of Oman territory in 1925 and the rumoured intemtio of the kueeat Government to grant mineral concession* in Ban! Bu All territory* The Baal 8e All appeared to betoe afraid that c^Qceaaioaa would o% ^raat^d by thm Huawat Qorer&amp;jz&amp;at to a European or othar ayjfidieate mna that th^r would receive no share of the re*ultifi&amp; profit and aoeing the weaknesa of the ubeat Ad&amp;i&amp;is* tration they imd advan ced thia claim in the hope that if admitted it wo Id prevent the Unseat Croverameat giving cojBtceaalcKs ia their territory* £• Owing to the diaa^nal^ne among the Je&amp;nebah the Baiii Ba All have of late years succeeded in inter fering in various ways la our affairs* the Aramn ana the ^uwaris are more powerful ti-an the other two — recticue of tha l^aneheh and the latter in order te obtain support against the former have sought the aid of the ani Bu All and adopted a submissive attitude towards thsm in iaaay respuets* lor instance* 1 was Informed that the tanea on dhows entering tne $*r creek had only teen paid by the -^akhaaneh and the Ohlalln and had never been paid by the Arasaa and the x uwaris« 7* When X visited Muscat last hece^er hie Highness appealed to me to re-establish his authority * at Sur and It therefore seemed necessary firstly^ to try and induce the hiaikii of the Ban! Bu All to abandon his pretensions to be independent of Muscat anu^secondly to put an end if possible to the prevailing feuds at ^ur so that the luseat State might be able to assert its authority 9 and obtain incidentally enhanced revenues from the Customs receipts* d* ^n arrival at Bur X had a long discussionV '&gt;6 6 Ml Mr discasslon with the WeJU who informed ismi firstly ti-at the attitude of the Baal Bu All was considerably less ag&amp;res*- ire than it had teen formerly| no efforts hare been made to lery taxes on the dhows entering the bur ereekf the so called *£ali* of Aiqa had bcea removed and there was for the moment no eyen interference by the aai Bo All ia bur affairs# he attributed this to two causes} firstly to a letter i had addressed to bhaifch All informs, him that the British Ostwramint could sot reeagsiee hie claim be regarded as as independent Holer and secondly to the strong action taken by the British Gcrernment in support of the Muscat State recently at AhasBab. ^e stated how* ever that as loo&amp; ce the J ■n web eh were di Tided amon^ theme el res the Ban! Bo All would always hare scope for intrigue and interference in Sor affaire and informed me that he had been enduavoutin, to compose their differences* as he felt thr t if this 00 aid be done they would present a uni ted front to the Ban! 1 u All and would ihemselres resist any attempts by the latter to Interfere# 9# In the afternoon therefore X went ashore at bur and met the leading men of the four sections of the Jersehch* 1 found them on the whole as attractive people* much mere ririle asd out-epoken for iast&amp;see^ than the Arabs of the frucial Coast or other places on the lersias Gulf littoral# ihey all a eared me that they were heartily slek of the existing state of aifairs and would gladly co*operate to «ake peace f but the difxioul y was that there was no one with sufficiest authority or personality among them to make peace or impose hie authority upon all the four sections# The iuscat StateState bad efileiaXljr reea^nieea one sneaker of the Majaleh - thv &gt;liaUtbl3r faally - a* head of the sur Jeztnebeh but while the Areata and the luwaria aceeyted him the Makhanneh mm the Chialio did met and had another candidate. I im^TmmamA apmn them howeTer the advantagee of union urged them to put an end to the existing dissensions and su&amp;g^sted that they mighf. appeal to the Muscat authorities to nominate an independent arbitrator, rhey did not definitely re4fcet the proposal and as they seemed to be tired of the existing state of affaire I am hopeful that somethin** may come of it. Anyhow disc use! one are in progrese and the *ali told me that he thought it would be possible to mahe pease between the four sections, X am bringing these facts to the notice of the uscat authorities and trust that the* will co-operate and endeavour to bring about a settlement, if this can be done then I think that the Baml Bu All will have very much less opportunities for interference in SHur affaire in the future, 10, the following morning 1 went ashore at Aiqa and interviewed the leading members of the ani Bu Ali community, Ai$a coasts of an imposing flag staff fixed in the gresmd and on the arrival of the mail— ol—war a much faded flag, the original colours of which seem to be red, white and green, had been hoisted. As there was no one in Aiqa who had any authority to dissuss the natter I sent word to sanaixh Ali that I would be returning to Sur in 3 days 1 time and a steed him to come down and see me, and then left in iUl.S^Triad* for Khor Jmrama the newly discovered sanitarium^ where the climate is m&amp;tqr degrees cooler than any where else on the Omen coast or in ths7 the : •r»i*n the SMiior K*r»l ffleer w»» aruttoue to visit it in ordsr to *** ® la to rscu^er^te* Thres d»ys latsr ws returned to *ur and that after no n shaikh Ali mm on board with ©oae of his relations. A jroion «d diso salon took ^lace» the out come of which however was ultimately satisfactory since the ‘ haikh gave me a definite assurance that he would no Ion er fly his own flag at Aiqa and would cease to issue his own passport*, d* advanced various alleged grievances which he had against the Muscat 3tate, but 1 told him that it was obvious that the otate could not listen to his grievances sc long as he persisted in his claim to independence. I was confident however that if this claim was abandoned any grievances he had against the Muscat State wo -1- be sympathetically considered* He advanced the question of mineral concessions and asked me whether the Muscat State were entitled to greust coneessione is his territory without reference to him* I said timt x could act answer a question of that nature off hand but cited the analogy of the rakhtiari tribe and the i^/rey concession and informed him that while the ^ersraa dev rn- mt nt took royalties the ^akhtiari tribe also had derived very substantial financial benefits from the concession and that if any similar concessions were ^ranted in man. of which however 1 had heard no rumours whatsoever ; I thought it pro table that the tribe within whose territory those Genoeseions were granted would inevitably share in the profits. finally 1 advised the shaikh to go and visit the 3ultas when he returns from India and he seemed inclined to do so. the refusal to allow him to fly hisConfidential* tfo*K/ 7^/ of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate.Muscat. Recess Office at Karachi. 23rd September 1930. % I From. Major T.C.Fo w le, C.3.B.. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. To, The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Subject:- Sur. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No.416-S of 16th August 1930. 2. I am glad to note that the Hon’ble the Political Resident, in his letter to Government, confirmed the views I had pre viously expressed to him with regard to the policy of composing the differences of the Jenebeh (my letter No.K/l of 28th July para 5 ) ; and of there being no necessity for action, on our part at Sur at present (my letter No.63-C of 6 th July para 6 ). I 3 . X have taken the opportunity of Mr. Thomas 1 s presence here to discuss the matter of Sur Customs with hiix., and enclose / herewith a copy of a D.O. letter which he has addressed to me on the subject. It will be seen that with regard to exports,the taxes on dates and fish,(practically the only commodities sent out of the port) t are considerably less than those taken else where in the State i.e. at Batinah and G-adur respectively, the reason being that Sur is distinctly less under control than either/these areas. M$. Thomas is of opinion that to raise the duty on these commodities to the same flat rate as else where would probably require force, or a threat of it, from H.M’s Government. He thinks that some increase could be made.2 but that this should be done very cautiously, (para VI of his letter). The Political Resident is also of opinion that caution is necessary, and so am I. It is H easy to get one rupee’s worth of crops out of the ground by putting two rupees into it', and to increase the Sur revenues to the extent of for this reason entailing - jpixJtJiXBxgrauuui alone - our active intervention, would hardly be worth while. The object is of course to strike the happy mean. 4. The chief leakage with regard to imports is by the use of dishonest manifests. (Para V of Jfr. Thomas's letter). It is the business of the Sur Customs officials to check these documents, but here they me^t with opposition, and the State as yet has not sufficient prestige to give them the necessary backing. 5 . ^ith reference to the matter of the Sur Customs personnel. It will be seen from para VII of Mr. Thomas's letter that measures have already been taken to check the maladminis tration of the Sur Customs Director^by sending there an 'appraiser' under orders which virtually place him over the Director. Mr. Thomas likewise informs me that Saiyid Said is visiting Sur very shortly to make enquiries on the spot. The Director General of Customs, Iskander Effendi, is also return ing from leave almost immediately, and his views should be of value with regard to a new Director. Under these circumstances I venture to suggest that the question of^new Director De left over for the moment until I return to Muscat-at the end of next month, when I win take an early opjortunity of visiting Sur, and that the representations which the Political Resident wieheS me to make to the State (on the subject of the Customs adminis tration at Sur) be likewise postponed until then. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Major, Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, MuscatCopy of a letter dated Karachi 18th September 1930 from Mr. B.S.ihomae, Finance Minister, Muscat State, to Major T.C.Fo w le, Political A^ent &amp; H.B.M *6 Consul, Muscat, on recess at Karachi. Customs leakage at Sur. The points ^hich discussed yesterday are as follo^c.- (i) The nature of Customs leakage is t^o fold affecting exporte and imports in a like degree. (II) In theory an export tax is not Customsi in practice, in the Muscat Etate^ it is and lias been )i)imemorally so and can be regarded to square ^ith Oommercial Treuiies^ae Zakat^ w ilch is otherwise uncollectuble in the interior^. This export tax in the Batinah is a flat 5 £ of assessed value except in .case of firewood 7| %. In Eur^ ho^ever^’-here exports consist chiefly of (a) Bier (i.e.e dried dates) from Sharkiyah and J&amp;’ulan, (b) Dried fish^ this system of a percentage Value does not hold. (Ill) The •Bier’ tax at fur is a tax on each camel load of of the commodity arriving from the interior. If I remember rightly l£ dollars - I increased it recently against the fall in the exchazige and in the degree suggested by the -all who considered any bigger incren.se may cause trouble. X doubt whether tVie yield of this tax is more than «..£■ % of trie value. (IV) Fish catches at Sur bear a normal tax based on auction value, in accordance with old usage. . If another more rigid eystem, that of farming Government’s share to a contractor as is done in Gwadur were practicable - which it is not under present conditions and without the application of force - it T^ould I consider produce some Re.8000/- a year - about t^ice as mu*4a* as the i resent yield. The Gwadur system referred to is to auction Government* share of iiTO of the catch for the ensuing year to a contractor. He is a fish merchant, meets each boat, Government # c share fc*To of each variety of fish caught takes2 . Yb (223) for his own, and at the end of the month pays into Cuetoms total value in accordance with a schedule of variety values embodied in his contract. (V) Imports into Surjlargely for Sharkiyah and Ja’alan^ consist of rice, coffee, sugar, piece-goods and the usual miscellaneous list of Arab wants. The manner of leak^ is largely as follows: The dhow Captain-Cum-Shipper at the Indian port cook the manifest. It is simple to show cargo destined entirely for Sur, to be sho^n only in part going there, the remaining half perhaps marked do w n for Mukalla or some South Arabian port. The dho~ on arrival at Sur thus escapes proper appraisement: indeed for years past Customs offici. Is have from time to time been prevented from boarding! they must accept manifest figures. (VI) The difference of the proportionate Customs yield bet ween Sur and Batinah is due to the fact that the former is dis tinctly lets under control than the latter, and if an attempt were made to increase the Sur percentage up to the Batinah level it w ould require rforce. or a threat of it, from H.M’s Government. X Perhaps some increase can be made, but this should be conducted '''ith caution and effected very slowly. (VII) As regards the Customs personnel^as a result of complaints I sjent a new appraiser to Sur s^me three w eeks ago under orders which virtually place him over the present M # amur. The suggestion of the latter^ removal is one I sug est that sju£&amp; should await 4he return (expected almost at once) of the Director G&lt;fnei^l of Customs, Iskandar Effendi, from leave in as he himself has been stationed at Sur as ITamur, under stands the individual motives of the locals ^0 desire changes, and has an intimate knowledge of his own staff, and the suitabilit c of this or that candidate as a IPamur.Cann^ijUal. So.K/ •7 V of 1S3C. i'oliticaX Agency &lt;1; ?f.B,3r t e Consuls e 9 3fuBcat« Office at Kai*achi. i^rd September 1^30. Trern, Major t.C.^le, 0.3.3.. Politiefei /w^eat a Coneul. '1'iie Secretary to tae Hou’ble the Political Hesi^ent in the fereian C»alf. Buehire. tabject:- Sar« Sir. I have the honour to eeknowi«dge the receipt of your letter Ho.416-? of 16th August 1^30. 2* I am glad to note that the Hon’bio the Political Ttaeident. in hie letter to loverattettt. coufimed the viewe 1 had pre viously expressed to him with r*,&gt;rd to the policy of compoeiiig the differenced of the Jeneboh (my letter fco.K/1 of htth July vara 5)jand of there ooing no nec«ti:ity for action on our part at for at present (my letter No.83-0 of 6th July para 6}. 3. I have taken the opportunity of Mr. Thoaa» # e presence • i hure to dieouee the matter of our Caetuma with hii*., and enclose herewith a copy cf a h j. letter '^lich ne iiae addreviced to me f on the rubjset. It will be eo«n tnut yuth regard to ev-portS^he t&amp;&gt;os on datoc and fiah. (practically the only conimouixy cent out of the port), are considerably leea than those taken elee- vr.ere in the ftate i... -t Batinah and G*^adur respectively. ‘ the reason being that fur ic distinctly less under control than either these area*. Thomae is of opinion that to raise /s the duty on these corvoditlet to the easie flat rate as else where would i.robi-bly require force, or a threat of it, from H.iPs jovernment. He thiuka that some increase could oe made.but tnat true should be done very cautiously, (para 71 of hie letter). The Political Keeident xe also of opinion that caution is neceeoary. s,nd so am I. It la^eaey to one rupee*s ^orth ol crops out of the ground by putti^ t^ro rupees into it* # and to incroate the Sur revenues to the extent of entailing - Ifyn dwtotl alone - our active Intervention, ^ould hardly be «orth ^hile. The object is of eourte to strike the happy mean. 4. The chief leakage with regard to imports is by the use of diehoneat menifeste. (Para V of &gt;Tr. Thoma8 , s letter). It is the business of the 6ur Custom© officials to check theee doc^ents, but here they meut ^ith opposition, and the rt&amp;ie as: yet has not sufficient prestige to give them the neceaeary backing. o. ^ith reference to the matter of the Sur Customs ; ^rsonnel. It «ill be seen from vara VTI of IFr. Thomases letter truit measures have already been taken to check the r?i&amp;lT&amp;duiinis~ tration of the f or Cuetoms I&gt;irucLoi. by ©ending there an * appraiser* uiiiet oruore *l\i cu virtuully [ lace him over the irector. IXt* Thomae likewise inforiis mo that Saiyid Zzild is visiting Pur very shortly to makt enquiries on the spot. The director ren^ral of &lt; ustoms, Ickarider i flcndi, 1&amp; ulao return* ing from leave almoet i itiediately, and nis vio^s should be of value ~ith regard to a new Cirector. Under thece circumstances &lt;L J venture to suggest thfct the question of new Director be left /N over for the moment until I return to Xuscat at the end of ne*t month, ~*hen 1 ~ill u*.ke an early opportunity of visiting fur, and that the representations ^hich the Political ^oeidont ^ieheS me to make to the State {on the subject of the Customs adminis tration at Sur) be IKe-'ise postponed until then. I have the honour to be, fir. Your meet obedient cervant. ( &lt;iA) 7T C * ^(\^Cc Major, t . oliticul Agent and Censul, -l. dForwarded for information and necessary instructions. I have in the meantime asked the petitioners to pay the have duties demanded under protest and &amp;&amp;&amp; also forwarded a copy of the petition to the Wazara for tneir observations wnich will be forwarded to you on receipt, by next mail*FINANCE MINISTRY* MUSCAT STATE, No.....69.. Dated September fagZ0 Dear A Drief note on the points yon raised in Karachi. I Administration of debts and estates . The present practice whereby you disburse moneys received from Zanzibar and elsewhere to Arab subjects,after confirmation of 'identity by the State,is one of long standing. I have spoken to the Council who are prepared to take such administration over,if and when you consider the change of system desirable II Motor car public Notice of 24 Kabi* al Awwal. Saiyid Sa’id tells me that the holding up of cars at Matrah is a customs requirement and i$ necessary at this and certain other seasons of the year. It is proposed to apply the reg ulation as unobstructively as conditions admit. Ill Customs leakage at Sur Saiyid Sa’id has just returned from a fort night’s tour there in Al Sa’idi - a most succ essful tour. He succeeded in patching up the cuarrel between the two opposing factions, the policy you proposed you may remember in your report to P.B. The Bani Bu Ali appear to have lowered their flag at Aija for good and actually flew the red.FINANCE MINISTRY, MUSCAT STATE, Dated 19 red flag and fired salutes for Saiyid Sa’id. c. The situation is mu^li improved. As regards para III of my note to you in Karachi on customs leakage the D.G.Gustomspf the State,Iskander Effendi has just returned from leave from Egypt and I have directed him to change the Ma♦mur of Sur,Muhammad Ali, as soon as convenient. He is of opinion that the complaints against ^ this ma*mur are chiefly due to the latter’s insistence on proper customs collections : regards the allegations of corruption which I have heard about as a put up job by merchants (i) for ousting him,and (ii) securing the succ ession of a man who 7/ill realise it is not to his interests to be too conscientious. The E.G. will however carry out my instructions in the course of the month. I enclose two letters from the Ma’mur him self. Saiyid Sa’id informs me that the bisr tax of Hollars !•£- per camel load was paid by all Arab subjects promptly and without demur and most British ones except the two influential Baniais Kimji Bamdas and Shabika who however paid it under protest. The frivolousness of the supposed hardship iOo, a .C. Vjl 't i/i FINANCE MINISTRY* MUSCAT STATE, 19 Dated 3. is shown in a comparison of Sur figures for 1929 and 1930. 1929. 1930. Bps.^ Dollars Bps.- Dollars Actual market | value per j hahar. ) 300 = 350 280 *- 350 Tax per camel 3 load 4 I 2 (7 camel loads - 1 hahar -0^ . . . A Incidence of tax approximately.^ Legally the tax should he as it is fact elsewhere throughout the Sultanate. Thus it is that the State is still losing 40^ of its dues. OcULou— —ITo No.K//&lt;&gt;7 of 1930. Political Agency &amp; H.B.M’s Consulate^Muscat. Recess Office at Karachi. 9th October 1930. z The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum. I enclose herewith an extract from a D.O. letter dated 27th September from Mr. Thomas. As ''ill be seen the situation at Sur, for the time being at any rate - it ^ould be premature to count on its continuance for too long - is much improved, and the visit of the Hon’ble the Political Resident seems to have had a salutary effect. The Jenebeh have patched up their quarrel, and the Bani Bu Ali have actually flo*~n the State’s flag. 2. A most satisfactory feature in connection ''ith this ’change of heart 1 on the part of the Suris, in view of the greater responsibilities which he may have to assume in the future (if the Sultan persists in abdicating) is the part that has been played by Saiyid Said. 3 . Tith regard to the Customs Ma’mur. There may be something in the Director General’s contention that the complaints against the Ma’mur are not altogether disinterested. At any rate now that the Customs Department is actually tightening up its administration the zeal of the Banias for reform appears to have slackened, and I have received a long protest from them against the enhanced *bisr’ dues. Prima facie Mr. Thomas’s remarks would appear to dispose of the complaint, but I win go into the matter further when I return to Muscat. Major, political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.Letter L T o .66 dated the 15th November 1^30 from the Council of Ministers to K.H,the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, to Major T.C.Fo^le, C.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrein. A. C. Reference our conversation T 'ith regard to the letter of Beni Bu All, ^ T e beg to enclose herewith for your information copy of Beni Bu all’s letter to the T/ali (of Sur) as v/ell as the answer which the V/ali sent to them in accordance with our instructions. U. E. Letter undated from Sheikhs Ali bin Abdullah and Hamdan bin Nasir, Amirs of Ja’alan to the V/ali of Stir. A. C. V/e have received your communication which you had addressed to the Beni Bu Ali with regard to Sayid Abdullah al Dhahab. Some words were used in the letter which we did not like and you have no right to interfere in the affairs of the Aiqa port. Whenever you want tc deal in a matter which concerns us v/e request you not to communicate with Beni Bu. Ali who are our subjects and have no authority to answer Governments. You know that the al Hamudah are the only auhority to deal ™ith the affairs of their country and no one else. As regards the al Bu Said Government they are our friends and there is no difference between us; their enemies are our enemies and their friends are our friends. This is ' ,T hat had to be said and salaams. Letter undated from the Wall of Sur to Sheikhs Ali bin Abdullah and Hamdan bin Nasir al Hamudah, Chiefs of Ja’alan. A. C. I have received your letter dated 15th (name of monthnot mentioned)and understood it contents from the beginning up to the end with regard to the letter which I sent to the inhabitants of Aiqa in connection with Sayid Abdullah al Dhahab. You should know that Aiqa is a part of Sur and has never, neither in the past nor recently, been separated from it. The T/ali of the Government has the right to communicate with the inhabitants of that place in all affairs If according to the instructions of the Government./you have anything to say or any other question you should communicate with the Muscat Government. * Salaams 1^1 'if 3 JTelegram-Code. Prom Britconsul, Muscat, To Britsonsul, Bushire Mo.17. Dated 23rd January 1931. Y Reference para 3 of your letter No.572-8 dated the 16th October. Hedgcoc-k: has been going into question here and would like to visit Bur for day or so as soon as possible for enquiries on the spot. I would like to accompany him. Any chance of a sloop being available?~r^r- 3 / Telegram- Code. From Resident, Bushire To Political, Muscat, No.69 Dated &amp; Received 31st January 193i. Your No.17. ft ■Your No.17. As Senior Naval Officer now at Muscat please try and arrange matter with him direct.Telegram Code. From Political, Muscat# To Resident, Bahrein. Mo. 180 Dated 5th February 1931. Correspondence ending with your telegram Mo.69. Hedgcock and T going to Sur on 6 th on AL SAIYID returning 9 th or 10 th to study conditions on spot ,*ith view to discuss with you on arrival.lo. 31-C of 1931. Political Agency ft H.B.K'a Coneulat©, Muscat.the 12th February 1931 TO The Hon'ble the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. Bushire. object:- S U ft. 5 lr. y In continuation of my tele gran no. 180 of 5th February. I hi.ye the honour to report that Mr. Hedgoock end ayeelf left Muscat, on the Ptate gunboat *Al Saidl* 1 . at 10 A.M. on the 6th Instant for Pur and returned at 1 A.M. on the 11th. le encountered very rough weather on our way do^n and reached Pur, after putting for some hours Into Xhor Khairan. at ? A.M. on the 7th. Disembarkation at Pur was a matter of some difficulty owing to heavy surf, and the hurl (small native boat) in which Mr. Hedgeoek and T landed was partially pooped and nearly swiped. However eventually our party, the Pub* ass latent urgeon - whom T had t^ken to treat the local inhabit- nts. Mr. Iskander Hanna, Dlrector-fteheral of Custans, the Agency Interpreter, servants and kit , was landed safe and sound. *?e stayed at the customs House, and were reasonably comfortable. e were hospitably received by the ^all and Sheikh Kasir bln Mi of the Axama section, and the demeanour of the Inhabitants was friendly. ve visited Balad-as-Sur In company of the r/all, and also mads a prolonged inspection of Aiqs. e made detailed enquiries on various aspects of the 3ur problem from numerous individuals and I think, with the information already on the files, sms now in a position to Envisage the Sur problem with its many ramifications. 2. I took the opportunity to gather the Sheikhs of the Jenebeh together in the presence of the wall and to2 * ’/ £ V — congratulate them on the sensible way in which, they had composed their differences, as a result of v.hich the town was now enjoying period of peace and quiet which it had not Known for some time* I told them that I would inform the Council of State, and yourself »hom I was going to see on Friday, of this continued satisfactory state of affairs* 3* It appears that sheiich Kasir bin All of the Arams section is on bad terms with sheiKh Kasir bin Hohammed the paramount oheiKh of that section* X asKed these two heiKhs to stay behind when others had gone, and in the presence of the Wall &amp; sited them to try and compose their differences* As the cause of the quarrel between the two is a serious blood feud 1 do not Know what effect my exordium had, but it may serve to Keep them quiet for the time being* lerhape later on the Council might try its hand at composing the feud* 4* The visit of the Sub-Assistant Surgeon, whom I had taxen with us with the object of showing the people of Sur that we tooK a friendly interest in them, and that they need not always associate our visits with bos&amp;ardments and such liKe, was a distinct success* He treated some two hundred cases during the three daye he was there* 5* *e lei t Sur at 11 A*lf* on the 10th* .e had intended visiting Khor Jerama, but ware unable to do so owing to the threat of more bad weather, and reached Muscat after another rough passage* Previous bombardments etc at Sur * 6* Since it is more or less certain that the sur problem will not be solved without the exercise of force, or the threat of it by His Majesty's Government - the Muscat state being too wsaK to enforce Customs control by itself - it may be instructive to study briefly the history of the past bombardments stc at Sur*m i 7* One of the earliest on record «aa In 1366 when, on the Jenebeh haTln^ plundered British subjects, and having refused to pay the compensation of $ 27,700 H*K*3.'Highflier' bombarded the town, and burnt or confiscated its dhows* (For * this and the following incidents, as well as for other X Ji/xj 3JL useful information about Sur see I ajor . urphy*s Report on 6 3ur dated the 10th October 1923)* In 1375 a god own of a British Indian subject was looted by a section of Jenebeh, but it was not until two years later that the Political Agent, j usc&amp;t, was authorised to appear off the town in H*X*S« 'Teaser' and demand compensation which was paid* In 1918 H«H»Jultan visited 3ur, fined the Jenebeh Hs*14,000 and imprisoned 26 Sheikhs* In 1919 the iuscat Customs were reorganised, but the inhabitants of Sur refused to allow the new Customs House to be built, and In 1920 Captain McCollum - the then azxr • visited Sur in H*M*3* H Britomart'* The Jsnebeh agreed to accept the new arrangements, but smuggling soon began again and the new Customs House was not built* In 1923 , the authority of the Council having been openly flouted. Captain Alban, then in command of the Muscat levy Corps, In company with SheiJch zubair the Minister of Justice, proceeded to Sur in the 'A1 said!' with three machine guns and 150 levies* Blood feuds were composed by sheikh Zubair, jt 6,400 Customs dues were recovered from the merchants, a fins of j£ 4,000 was taken from the Jenebeh, and a site for the Customs House selected* This energetic domiciliary visit would seemi to have achieved complete success* Yet the Customs House remained unbuilt, and before long quarrels amongst the Jenebeh started once more* In 1927 Mr* Thomas, who was then azlr, proceeded to Sur in the 'Al Said!' to induce the Jenebeh to pay up 2&amp; laichs which they owed to iC*B*Hassib and other merchants in zuscat, and to demolish forts which the Jenebeh had built contrary to the orders of the Council* Neither were the debts paid, nor the forts demolished, and on leaving Sur with a captured Jenebeh dhow in tow the 'Al Saidl' was fired on* TheCouncil fined the Jenebeh / 10»000, but • as far as I Jcnow • have neber been able to recover it* In AuieuBt 1928 about 15 of ?u war is Jenebeh looted a dhow belonging to a British subjectt and coamitted various other misdeeds* In October of the same year oertain members of the Counsil proceeded to aur in the 11 Al baidi* f escorted by H.M.S* 11 Crocus'** and bombarded a fort which the Fuwaris culprits had occupied* the gun carried by the *A1 £aidi* is too small to have any appreciable effect on the fort* Ho trover* the Fuwaris feigned submission* and the Council returned to Muscat* Pirectly the Council*s bach was turned the Fuwaris reoccupied the fort* In Koveaber the 'Cyclamen'** accompanied by the 'Effingham* - the flag ship of the East Indies Squadron • visited Sur *ith the political Agent on board* bombarded the Fuwaris fort* demolished it* and left for imscat* But the long projected Customs House still remained unbuilt* and the town was soon once more plunged into disorder by the quarrels of the Jenabeh Conclusion to be drawn from the Bombardments etc at Sur* 7* A, I venture to thinh that one very important conclusion can be drawn from the incidents detailed in the previous paragraphs they show that we have had no settled policy at Sur* Some outrage* or act of dieobedienoe to the Muscat State* is perpetrated by the Saris* Action in the shape of a bombardment etc of the town is ta^en* This action in itself is occasionally quits successful* but it is never followed up* the effect is purely ephemeral* and the town relapses into its former anarch!a1 and semi-rebellious oonditioi In other word* to compare a very small problem to a very large one* our policy in Sur* (and that of the Muscat State)* has been what it was in former years on the Berth est Frontier* dubbed by its critics as that of 'tip and ran'* or more harshly of 'burn and scuttle'* More recent develo^enta* S* More recently affairs in sur have taken a slightlyfk U&gt; j y 2//$ happier turn. In my letter K0.83-C of 8th July 1930 I stated that — on the negative side «- I was definitely against the proposal of sending a large military force to Sur until all other means had heen tried, and that - on tne X ^7 *25^positive side ^vide my letter flo.Kol of 28th July 1930)- a r- attempt might he made to compose the differences oi the Jenebeh in order to consolidate ttiera into a more or less solid block against the intrigues of the Bani bu Ali. Both these views had your approval# The project of sending a military force has been dropped for the time being, and as a result of your visit to Sur in August of last year the Bani bu Ali hauled down their flag rat Aiqa, and the Jenebeh began to compose their differences. Said Saiyid followed to Sur this up v-ith successful visitjjfin September (vide my letter L ' K bo.TC-10? of 9th October 1930). Since then I have paid two viaits to Sur - one in the 'Triad* last November and again a few dayu ago. The net result has been that the town which m.a in a state of anarchy - is quiet, the Jenebeh united, and as far as Mr.Hedgeock and I could ascertain inclined to be friendly both to ards us and the State, and the influence of the Bani bu Ali in the town much decreased. That this state of rffairs is likely to last indefinitely, or even for very long, is unlikely! blood fueds still exist between the principal sheikhs, vide para 3 above. The Council should direct their energy towards composing these fueds, even if the composition is only of a temporary nature, tc allow time for our plans to nature. In this connection I may remark that, from what. I heard at Sur, / 5c.id Saiyid made very good impresaion on the Jenebeh on his visit of last September. A Sheikh for Alqe, , In the seme way that we have had some success 9 at least temporarily - in forming the Jenebeh into a block against the Bani, bu Ali, it way be possible to form the Bani bu Ali elements in Aiqa into a similar block against thet'fy rest of tiLeytribe* The line to taUce ould be for the council to recognise the headman of Aiqa as a SheiJch 9 offer him a monthly subsidy and allow hi® some other financial advantages in the shape of free registration of his dhows ^he Council would be the body to say whether such a policy is pr&amp;cticable f and X propose suggesting this to the® { to Said Saiyid privately in tne first instance $ at an early opportunity* ilr+HecLcttod* a xveoort* 1 enclose hr• hedgeocic^ report on Sur Customs t the crux of the Cur px v obieEu roughly speaking hraiiedgcocK's main argux^ento run as follows: - 1* The Muscat State is nearly bankrupt* ito financial ro-e&amp;tabxrshment depends on the enforcement of Custer® dues* 3*dur - after Muscat ana xatrah - is the richest Customs pwxa in Uaaait bul it is not under effective Customs control of the Jueo&amp;t btate* 4* To enforce this control, and all that this control implies, t*o customs posts must be built at dar» one in -uqruat in and in Aiqa* The one in Alqa to be garrisoned by 25 men of the Muscat levy* 5. If effective Cueto®a control is not established shortly at uur t such control as exists will in all probability become less and less* This *111 in its turn react unfavourably on the other Qia&amp;ni ports i*e. by diverting trade to the practically *free port* of Sur, and by encouraging other porte to resist Customs control* Ths inevitable result *ill be that the financial re-establish* fiient of the State will be rendered very difficulty if not impossible* and its disintegration will be brought a long step nearer* 11* Speaking generally 1 agree with tne above viewe*If the Ban! hu Ali prere amenable it may, kewerer, be possible to dispense with the post at Aiqa* Measures for enforcing Customs control IX, ^ith regard to the all important question of what measures we should adopt to enforce Customs control at Sur I hare, to isake the following tentative suggestions* tentative since the issues involved are complicated and far reaching and 1 should like a little more time to examine some ef them. As, however, you are arriving tomorrow I feel it will be a distinct advantage for there te be some suggestion ready for your consideration, which will, at any rate, form a basis for discussion whether finally adepted er net. E. • &gt;&lt; 13 . In my memorandum Ho. 83-C, dated the 8th July 1930, I pointed out that owing to movements ef the Sur dhows, and to the configuration of the Sur creek, it would be quite easy for a sleep stationed at the mouth ef the creek, in May, te prevent dhows entering the creek, and in August to prevent the dhows leaving. The exact dates of the entering, and leaving ef the dhews, vide Mr Hedgcoek's Report, are - respectively - 15th May te 15th June, and 15th August te 15th September. What I have in mind is that on about 15th June when all the dhows are safely laid up in the creek, the Council should announce that ne dhew will be allowed to leave the creek until the Jenebeh and the Ban! bu Ali - the parties concerned - agree to an effective Customs control.8 14. The Council would let it be known that they had the support of His Majesty^ Government, and a sloop would, if necessary, be stationed at the mouth of the creek to see that dhows did not come out. 15. With regard to the Jenebeh. By far the greater part of the larg# number of the dhows which 'monsoon* in Sur belong to the Jenebeh; the dhow trade is their life, and a threat to it is a threat to their existence. Short of accepting the Council*s terms I see only one ^ard* that the Jenebeh can play; a threat to the lives or property, or both, of the British Indian subjects - some twenty Bannias - at Sur, but reply to that would be that any outrages on British subjects would be met with the severest penalties, fines or otherwise, and as the dhows would be still in the creek thetfc^penalties would not be difficult to enforce. From what I have been able to gather, however, I do not anticipate much opposition from the Jenebeh. 16. The B&amp;ni bu Ali are a different proposition, but can be divided into two parts those at Aiqa: and those in Ja’alan. The former are in much the same position as the Jenebeh since they are seafaring folk, and own the balance of the dhows, about a dozen in number according to present information, which do not belong to Jenebeh. Jenebeh 3 w m t ' 17. The Ja’alan/are the crux of the situation. As yvujLh.xn v you are aware they claim Aiqa, and it is.this claim / do n-ot trvcrw oCfvcnds auwcL So 'v^oC -(rC 'vy hh c/vv ^3 cx/isC*-' 1 3 / * which Tenders Customs control ineffective.other hand a fairly large quantity of dates is exported from Ja*alan all of which goes via Sur, and the holding up of these dates would undoubtedly bring pressure to bear on the Bani bu Ali. Bates from Bani bu Hasan, and the Sharkiah tribes under the Imam, are also exported via Sur, and we-'f 7 do not want of course to penalise these tribes* It ai^ht be possible t however^ tnrou^h the Custoas administration to discriminate between the Ja v alan dates and the others* and to forbid merchants to purchase the former since t^eir export wouid not be ^ezmitted* It may be noted as a most important point that the Bani bu Hasan and the Snarkiah tribes 9 who are Hinavis* hare no love for the Jenebeh and the Bani bu All vho are Ghafiris* In fact (vp is+zo more than once of late years Sheikh lea bin Salih has °h 14 written to the Council and to the Political A^ent objecting ^ in the strongest terms to the interference of the Bani bu Ali in Sur* intercourse with the Bani bu Ali and Jenebeh Sheiichs* id* I feel on a perusal of the files that until recently intercourse with the Jenebeh and Bani bu Ali has been conducted at M long range 1 * by means of letters rather by personal intercourse* which is generally preferred by Arabs* On the issue of the announcement by the Council referred to above in para 13» an invitation would also be issued to the Jenebeh and Bani bu Ali Sheikhs* particularly to Sheikh Ali bin Abdullah» to come to discuss the question at muscat with the Council* yourself • if you so desire • • and myself. It would be pointed out to the Sheikhs that nothing new was intended* merely the collection of dues which had been the right of the State fro«i time immemorial* That as far as the Bani bu Ali are concerned tneir claim to Aiqa* only dating from 1924* is quite untenable* and that it was hoped that all concerned would accept the situation sensibly* That if* however, they refused. His diajesty's Government would firmly support the Council* and any regrettable consequences hioh the tribes might suffer they would bring upon their own heads* It is quite possible that if the situation was put to them in this way the Sheikhs might prove reasonable*MBBaMBRnHMm 10. Support of His Majesty^ Government. 19. It will be seen that my suggestion naturally requires the support of His Majesty^ Government, but only to the extent of a single sloop. When putting up the suggestion to Government, if you approve that it should be put up, ( and I would like again to emphasise the fact that it is at present a tentative one subject to further consideration), I think stress might fairly be laid on the fact that w« are now attempting to solve the Sur problem once and for all, and in the interest as much of the people of Sur as of the State, since Customs control at Sur will also mean the establishment of general administration control, and the establishment of law and order instead of the customary anarchy. In this connection it might be noted that the State will do its best, if funds permit, to provide a doctor and dispensary for Sur, a humane intention* which I trust they will be able to carry out. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. 31a j or. Political Agent &amp; H.B.lPs Consul, ^ Muscat.Fin a i 'I a a oat. 11/2/31, To the Political Agent and H.M.B.'s Consul, Muscat. Goverruient Control at SUE. -^ne chief problems at Sur during recent years have been three: (a) The claim of the Bani 3u All to Ai^a as an independent port. (□) Tne blood feud between the four sections of the Jenabeh, nich has enabled the Bani Bu Ali to interfere in Sur. .=) Smuggling by the Jenabeh dhow-owners. a:.u (b) are of comparatively recent origin: lfa 3 and 1913 respectively; (b) was settled in 1930. For many years past (c) has been extensively practiced, and still Is; it has recently been aggravated by the sucoess of (a). At the moment, Aiqa is a free port of the Bani Bu Ali, though no foreign flag is now flown there. This state of affairs may possibly be due to failure on the P art of the State of liuscat to follow up and consolidate the diplomatic results of the Political Resident's la at visit to Sjir # 8 ) Prior to 1933, Alqa was definitely under the administmtive and customs control of the Government of Muscat and Oman, m that year the Bani Bu All made their first claim to Aiqa as an independent port of the Emirate of Ja‘lan. Since then they Have substantiated their claim to it, even to the extentleft ?/?&gt; during 1938 of compelling each ianabah dhow-ovmer to i &gt;ay a tax for the use of the Sur creek. Confirmatory evidence of the abovse y statements is contained in Appendix A 3) The acquiescence of the G-overnniQnt of Muscat in the Bani Bu Ali 1 s hold over Aiqa has reacted unfavourably on Sur. Though, next to Muscat and Matrah, this port is the largest in Oman, its revenues from customs and zakat are insufficient to pay its own customs officials and the Wall and his staff. As will be seen from the figures in Appendix 3, the revenues of last year are easily the lowest on record. To all intents, Sur also is a free port. ^ over Sur is vital to Muscat. This was recognized many years ago by the French and by successive Sultans, and is grasped today by too present Council of Ministers. The existence wfchin a h * nt Tec ' °- Muscat of the virtually free port of Sur-Aiqa oonstitues a threat to the financial stability of the State, e.~. ^a) ihe loss of customs revenue i ‘ T a b t SUr - ? ust0ias ought to oroduce over one lakh n a ahd w^rw^^^rroT^rc^e^to^^. 1 ^ U ’favoSrabL P ^i S - ^ e 3 S °f control at Sur reacts un- and by encouraging oopositio' D L a l' rertlas soods to Sur * dues and consequent laxity in collection? ent ° f 0USt ° a3 (b) Tne danger that the proposed increase in the customs tariff *uay not produce extra revenue, because of £e IrTTorTlr 0 ^ 11 ^ —^ ^ carry goods to the caravan routes fr^’shemy^to^u^ “ ea£ urq, of s -“ ^ Tle p ‘‘“ lns or &gt;«na» or IM « remote but noo improbable contingency. The Bani Bu Ali ? fty ^ effe ° UV6 their ParU£l contr ol over Sur, and this tae Imam and Shai to Isa bin Salih will not tolerate: see their various letters to the Councilof Ministers. Having raised their tribes and drivort out the 3ani Bu Ali frois Sur, they mi^ht insist on retaining it as a corridor to the Interior, or only yield the port to the Crovemiaent of Muscat on condition that commodities to the Interior were either exempt from customs duty or paid merely nominal transit dues. Financially, this ’ oulc couple ;ml v . cripple the State of Muscat, 5) The first essential is the re-establiai ment of the State's autnori ty in Sur. Spasmodic attempts to do this in the past nave proved abortive, TChat is req^uired is a carefully-piarmed constructive policy, with ample preparations and a determination to carry it through even though it take several months to achiev&lt; Without this it might be riser to leave Sur alone. Once effecor. administrative control has been gained, it will be possible to consider the tightening up of the oustons control. 0) It is claimed that the volume of trade in and out of Sur is equal to that passing through Mat rah, whose customs collections d ’ re RB p 50 ’ 000 P* r - -ocai enquiries show that Sur is the port f ° r thG rlCl1 3harqlyah distrlct ' 14 towns in Badia, W adi Band Khalid. Wadi Bani Jablr and Bildan'al Harith. 65 ,, of the goods landed at Sur are destined for these places; of th remaining 2W *° Ja ' 1 “ “ a W 1 - ,» Sur „ 4 „ 4PPT..U1, 60(&gt;as bj Jnaian ueroh&lt;uit&lt; P-P Puoto.a duties; reel do not pea,, throush th. cuetous. W Smuggling takes the f 0 n owtn g forma . ^U 30 ut (i) Sur is not the nnr&gt;t ^-r , t t ^ P ° rt 0i the —n-goin S dhows belong, ing to tne Jenabeh: these Bioi Sun. &lt;Por aet ua ” r “ y ^ s dalloH “ 1 “ t0 a * t ' ■hUlng and lylm 3,0 aon Sun, ^ ^ . »P m to , 4 -. - “ 1 Khor Jarainalj, ten cargo i„ a o * 3 ^ ' r ° ;: iJJr * Here the larse dil0Ws ^load their 8 ° S “ 11 ' * »^« smuggle th. contra-7 c b-'ii't- band goods into the Khor Sur, and land them literally at their owners' back doors. (See attached sketch-map), it will be ob served that the customs station at Sur is well away from the mouth of the Khor Sur, and apparently only aapable of dealing Yd oh coastal vessels coming from the north. There is a customs hut, a structure of reeds, at Bat*-*' on one side .of the entrance to the Khor, while on the opposite aide Aiqa has not BO ' 1U0i:l as thiE &gt; nor any representative of the local govern ment. Until recently the Bani Bu All maintained their own’’ Wall there. (il) The Jenabeh make extensive use of faked manifests, teoort Tiil) Caravans enter Bur at night, via the Sikalkra road. Uv) Caravans come down the Shama Pass, and at low tide pass along the southern shore of the Khor Sur into Aiqa . - After the sea “S°ins dhows have disposed of their cargoes a. Knor Jiramaii, they load up with fish, sharks' fins and fish maws brought up from Bashkarah etc. ' A further loss is caused by the ^ow-owners' refusal to comply with the Dhow Registration regulations. S) The following measures for estahn - -ox establishing effective control of customs cind sdiulni + c-u.niru strati on are suggested. ■ S3UC ° f 3 xxociaaatiun by the Council of hinlators ‘ ' 6 “* ““ t '» - in inportlhE ^ M exporting s „„ 4 . , t Snr P S °°*‘ ^ on ’ and the penalties to be incurred for infraction. ' b ) This harbour contra v ' - of Rep 01 t0 b6 Prlfflari ^ enforced by the use - x t.e. the armed steamer A 1 Said, with the moral support of H.B.IJ. * s Navy. The Al S ,1 . , ^ Said’s crew would be backed by a machine tnm oe gun detachment from the Muscat Levies t ^al with recaicitrant dhows reDel „ L ^ 6S t0 or assist in the defe ' P ° 8 ^ b ° ardilS defence or evacuation of the post mentioned^ 30^ in (c) belov;. It may be mentioned here that t e A 1 Said was purchased four years ago for this very purpose, but beyond one or two ineffectual visits to Sur has so far done little to justify her maintenance charges of Rs 3 b ,000 p.a. (c) T.iC eotablishment of a strong fortified customs post near the sea, as an outward symbol of government’s authority on the const, and as a means of enforcing harbour control. This post should, at any rate to begin with, be manned by a contingent o_ aoout 2b of the Muscat Infantry. The ideal site exists at 0x1 e extre *Q e e nd of the Aiqa promontory, where a half-completed •' - fort already exists. (See A on attached sketch-aap) (a) ihe more efficient manning of the various government-owned forts round Sur, also their repair and in one or tie cases re building. These can be garrisoned by askaris on about Rs 10 P ' m * net ' T; ' le Wali ' s Present force of 13b should be nearly' sufficient for this purpose. The forfcc of particular importance for customs control are ( ' ^ISliSfmentlonerinlci^^h; nrst^ouiriont^l the .eu.jrykukS!' ’ ,o “'&gt;*• ' a “• of cargoes there. S** qp), ' n to i reve nt the landing (iii -Khor e Sw 1 at i Blthah a to'de^^ith^ 11 ^ °h Sh ° re of the Khor Sur. See B on attac^a m= h bro uSbt into the landed at the new customs wha£f P ’and IiTh S °? d3 mUSt be payment oj. customs dues .' 8 Thi^ aeasur^vm i ^ ,, cleared on xnxo measure win dispose of 7 (il) post at the southern end or Aiqa and at ' -irnghi, a Janabah village a mile or so north of Sur 9) The above measures cannot safely be put into force without the “ 0ral SUPP ° rt ° f ° ne ° f H - M p s warsMps. it is unlikely that ta6 ^ W0Uld b6 Called u P° b to ^re a single shot, but she should have authority to use her guns ( 1 ) in defence of the servpnt - - hy an overwhelming f^cfL^he^efCrce^o^tf^^^ (U) as a punitive measure if sa t1 UtleE ' . .. measure, if sanctioned by the Political3^r ($*) mm xioaxclent, in retaliation for repeated acts of aggression against the government* Tnis authority shouldjlf possible be secured before initiation of the proposed measures for tightening control at Sur. As the process of establiahing effective control may be a slow on«, it is desirable that the Indian Government should be prepared to station a ship - not necessarily the same one - at Khor Aarama, tilC nev '^ G.iscovered sanatorium', for some months* In tnts respect iu io a Ixutle unfortunate that a tour of the Gulf #by all the Sl00pS is Gonte mplated, but perhaps the importance of the ur q^eowion may induce the naval authorities to alter their programme to the extent of one ship* tae Muscat sovernaent runs the rish of U) 3 COllision ^e Ba,!! Bu All, who aay tafce to ar.s in t of tneir claim to Aiqa as an independent port of ne nail a.te ca Ja'lan. At the same time, the effective establidiina!t of the State's authority at Aiqa is the measure * 0 st i ike iy to put ‘an end to this threat. The Bani Bu Ali have been less truculent since the death of their Mir Mohamad bin Nasir, and at the moa ent are on -d teras with the Jenabah and the Bani Bu Hassan, as wen 0,5 T,ltl1 tileir h6reddta ^ ene ^es the G-hafirl tribes of ° ~ Int erlor. To prevent an ebmn + &lt; ebullition on the part of Shaikh AH bin Abdulla it misiht he tn , . + be as ' ,el1 to bring home mm that his inland fastness forty HU e s fr + , 11 “ ' r ° pl “ e ' •■’* «»» * m.naij r,* - -•*. - .. headquarters. A protest from Shaikh Isa bin —■—..... t . ul ,r s ? as - 1 * * r — ri^nt to take customs dues (b)7- « of b%. (It is not proposed for the present to apply to Sur the enhanced tariff, if eventually sanctioned.) Shaikh Isa and the Imam have already acquiesced in this demahd of 5^ in other ports supplying the Interior. ^ (c) Converting the Jenabah s present semblance of loyalty into open hostility. At the moment they are friendly to the central government, and have every reason to dislike the Bani Bu Ali for the indignities recently heapeduupon K y- 3,cr' them - see Appendix A. If the Jenabah once see that the government is in earnest, they will probably have enough sense to realize, on the one hand their impotence in the face of the State*s sea-power (the armed Al Said), and on one otxier their ability to pass on most of the customs dues to the tribes of the Interior, possibilities. Ox uhese^ the least likely to happen is (b). As regard the State Bight perhaps with skilful diplomacy secure tae cooperation of the Jenabah and of th e actual inhabitants of Aiqa, the maritime Bani Bu Ali. The most dangerous possibility is ( a ;. it is doubtful whether the Amirs of J^lan will acquiesce in the government’s establishment of a fortified post in Aiqa, yet this is essential if the Bani Bu Ali are to be prevented from again appointing their rs ° Wn Wali and ^sterns of fid als. On the other hand, the more prepared and the more resolute the two governments are, the smaller the chances of a conflict with the Bani Bu All. 11) To sum up, (a) During recent years the State of Muscat's hold over Sar and its neighbourhood has gra/idually weakened. (b) This weakening of control is affecting customs colletior* not only at Sur, but all up thafeoast.So- (c) If more effective control is not established, most of th e benefits of the proposed increase in the tariff rates may be lost. ^ (d) Complete loss of control at Sur may jeopardize the very existence of the State in its present form, i.e. may reduce it to a mere Muscat-LIatrah enclave. (e) The local tribal situation is at ^resent favourable to an attempt to reassert the Central Government's authority. (f) The financial advantages outweigh any possible adminLstnative d 1 s ad v ant r ; e s . tg) The fuller the preparation, and the greater the determination to re-establish authority, the less likelihood of resistance, (n) The size of the task is sufficient to warrant the State of Y b ?&gt;// 12 ) Lius cat asking for the cooperation of H.B.M.G. For easy reference, a summary is attached CAppendix!) of the various requests of the State. Ij. you concur with the above views, I should be grateful lf ; ’ ou Would take up v.ith the Hon'ble the Political Resident the question of restorlns the autherlty of the State of Muscat in Sur and its environs. I , u ay add that the general outline of these proposals has been discussed with Saiyld ^ j-v-c, 'imid has his approval. tl- • Financial Advisor, muscat State.I I ^3074 Appendix A. ' : Gradual assumption of control of Aiga &amp; Sur 'by the Bani Bu •Ali. 1) In 1870 Saiyid Turki, in recognition of their services in connection with his attack in Matrah, granted the Amirs of the Bani Bu *Ali exemption from the payment of customs on the goods imported for their personal use#' through Sur. In practice this means exemption of zakat on the Amirs* own dry dates, and import exemption on 100 'bags of rice. 2) In 1888-9 relations 'between the Bani Bu *Ali and the Jenahah were strained and fighting 'broke out. Eventually the Bani Bu *Ali agreed to allow the passage of the Khor Sur to remain entirely in the hands of H.H*s officials and to abide by his decision in all local matters. 3) Extracts from the Customs Registers show that as recently as 1923 goods imported through Aiga paid customs duties to the Central Government. 4) In 1923 the Amirs claimed in writing that Sur belonged to them and that the Sultan had nothing to do with the# peart. 5) In April 1928 the Amirs established their owni Customs post at Aiga. Their customs officer wrote to the State customs official at Sur demanding a refund of customs on a boat which they claimed belonged to the Bani Bu VAli. 6) About the same time the Bani Bu ’Ali occupied Balad asjsur with a view to commanding the water supply of Sur and thus obtaining mastery over the Jenabah. Peace was eventually made on the following terms. (a) The Aramah and Makhana sections each to destroy one of their forts. All sections of the Jenabah to pay to the Amirs for one year # 20 on each of their boats. Two Jenabah shaikhs to call upon the Amirs at Aiga. I2 . ?) The Amir of the Bani Bu 'Ali endeavoured to prevent date caravans coming to Sur from Badiyah. Eis object was believed to be to induce caravans to come to his new customs post at Aiga, He also tried to persuade British Indians to transfer themselves to Aiga, offering to charge 2-%% instead of 5%. 8) On 50/9/28 the Amirs ordered their customs official at Aiga to count the vessels entering Khor Jarama and Khor Sur as they intended charging anchorage fees.Appendix Customs Collections at Bur The ftojrl-ovring receipts at Sur during the last ten years have 'been as under. Amount in rupees Year 45.531 1921 56,576 1922 50,728 37,457 42,751 1923 1924 1925 37,813 1926 33,154 1927 40,180 1928 34,945 24,826 1929 1930 The HancUhook of Arabia, compiled in 1916 ,estimates that the Sur customs should yield g' 50,000 (Rs. 75,000 at the then prevailing rate of exchange). Present day estimates put the figure at one lakh of rupees at least. More effective customs control at Sur may he expected to yield an additional Rs.50,000 p.a. on a conservative estimate .Appendix S, Movements of the Sur Dhows. **&gt;• The sailing dhows of Sur can he divided into two lines the India line and the Basra-Zanzibar line. All the Sur sailing dhows lie up during the siftruier in Khor Sur. They begin to enter the Khor between May 1st and May 30th. The Zanzibar line leave for Basra between Aug.15th and Aug.30th. They return to Sur (Khor Jaramah) between Nov.1st and Nov. 30th and then leave for Aden,Yemen,Mukkala and Zanzibar, returing to the Khor Sur in May. They make one journey per annum. The India line starts leaving the Khor Sur for India betv/een Sept. 15th and Oct. 15th, After making four journeys to India and back they beging to ^ie up in the Khor Sur between May 1st and May 30th.Appendix D The following is a summary of what is asked from H.B.M.G. (a) Permission for one of H.M.'s v/arships to he stationed more or less permanently for the next few months at Khor Jar amah. Authority, to be obtained before any operations begin, for the ship to use its guns in certain emergencies. See para.© above. Authority for an aeroplane to fly over the headquarters of Shaikh Ali bin Abdulla, 40 miles inland. Permission for any aeroplanes or seaplanes that may visit Muscat during the next six months, to fly over Sur. Authority to purchase, if a free grant is out of the question, two pairs of Lewis guns with mountings, to strengthen the somewhat obsolete armament of the A1 Said. Also ammunition for the Lewis guns and three pounder, if our present stocks are inadequate. Also the loan of a searchlight. Permission for the Al Said to obtain coal during the Sur operations from one of H.M.•s ships, if no other source is or can be made available. SCO Mills bombs.* I f o ! yj&gt; No, 40-C of 1931. The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate Muscat,26th February 1931, The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I H K. Memorandum, Please refer to my letter No#31-C dated the 12th February 1931, paragraph 17. In order to make the argument clear the following sentence should be inserted after the word *ineffective ,, which closes the first sentence^ and before the phrase 'on the other hand' which opens the second:- 'They do not own dhows, and so would not be directly affected by the measures envisaged in paragraph 13 above.' Major, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M’s Consul,Muscat.jli British Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bushire. 28th. February 1931. No. 87-3 of 1931. From - Secretary^ to the Political Pvesident in the Persian Gulf. To The Political Agent, Muscat. Sir, I am directed to acknowledge your letter No.31-C dated the 12th. February 1931, regarding the situation at Sur. 2. The Eon’ble the Political resident discussed the matter with you and Mr. Hedgcock during his recent visit to Muscat. He agreed with the view that the action taken in the past has had little permanent effect chiefly because it has not been followed up , and that it is essential if any permanent results are to be obtained, that every opportunity should be taken of asserting the rights of the Muscat State and of punishing , if possible, breaches of any settlement that may be arrived at between the dif- -ferent sections of the Jennebah , etc.. He also agrees as to the desirability of imposing customs control at Aiqa, and with your view that discussions with the chief of the Bani Bu Ali have been conducted at too long range hitherto. I am therefore to suggest that the Muscat. Stale should endeavour to get in personal touch with Shaik Ali of Ja* alan , either by inviting him to Muscat , or arranging a meeting between him and the representative of the Muscat State, and if necessary yourself, at Sur. 3. From his own personal experience of Shaik Ali, Golonel Biscoe does not think that he will resist any rea-action taken by tiis Majesty’s Government at Khasati; the fact that the Hon’hie the Political Besicient has himself discussed matters with Skaikh Ali at Sur; the more fre- -quent visits of ships to Khor-Jaramah and other places in the vicinity, all must have impressed upon his people that His Majesty's Government are behind the Muscat State. This in itself is a valuable asset and will make them think twice before resisting altogether the demands of the state. Secondly, it is so obvious that their maritime trade can be controlled by the sea that a hint to this effect will probablyjsuffice, and Colonel Biscoe does not think that there is any necessity at present to consider the question j of sending a sloop to Sur. The Honourable the Political Besident therefore hopes that the Muscat State will take the necessary steps to get in touch with Sheikh Ali and to tighten up generally their control over the Sur customs, and will be interested to hear in cue course the results of any measures they may take. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant Secretary ^ to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf.Provisional scheme for the introduction of more effective G-overment control ajs SUE. l) The chief problems in Sur have been three: (a) The claim of the Bani Bu Ali to Alga as an independent po^Tt,. (b) The blood-feud between the sections of the Jenabeh, which has given the Bani Bu Ali a chance to interfere in Sur, (c) Extensive smuggling on the part of the Jenabeh dhow- owners # (a) and (b) are of comparatively recent origin, and have been settled during the past year, (c) has been for many years past and still is extensively practised. The present aim is the establidi ment of more effective Government control at Sur. Unless carefully handled, this is lively to lead to a recrudescence oflta); at the same time, it is the measure most likely to .,ut a final end to It. The clai, of the Bani 3u All Independence, as long as it Is confined to the Interior, can be ignored. 3) Once effective control has been establish^* in Sur ar;d environs, an attempt can be made to curbl(c). At present 3ur is to all intents and purposes a free port. This is perhaps one of the reasons why the Bani Bu Ali are at the moment quiescent. *ext to Unseat and Uatrah, Sur is the largest port in Oman. Last year its wp,,* to meet the ' 3 Were lnSuff J-clent u the cost the Customs officials , - oiiicials and the Wall and iUs4) staff. Weak Customs control at Sur reacts unfavourably all up the coast. As iong as a virtually free port exists within a hundred miles of Muscat, there is a danger that when the enhanced customs tariff comes into force, so much trade may be diverted to Sur as largely to nullify the beneiit of the increased dues. Improved revenue collections depend to a great extent on the Government's success in tightening customs control at Sur. --iis is an essentia.! but by no means an easy task. It requires careful planning, ample preparation, and a deter- mination, once it is begun, to carry it through even though it tahe several months to achieve. Without this, it.would he wiser to leave Sur alone. It is said that one-third of the population of the Interior, including the rich Hijrein tribe, receives its supplies through Sur. Of these supplies few if any pass through the Custom. Estimates of the loss through SaU g e i ln6 vary fro, half to one laich per annu,. The Handbook of Arabia, coraolied in 101 ^ oof* + 16f estlma tes that the Sur Customs should yield £ 50,000 (Rs ? c . nnn v;, 000 at the then prevaiiinr rate of exchange) The actual collections during the last five years were.- Rs 37,92b 33,154 40,180 x929 .'* 34,945 1Q30 -.. 24,826 Financial benefit to the Central Treasury zaore &lt; , treasury as a result of “ CUSt0;li8 oonfcr °l ^ Sur aight be put Vi lonally at P.s 50,000 p.a.5) To gain this sum, the Government runs the risk of (a) reviving the £Jani Bu Ali^s claim to Aiga (see para.2 above). If the proposed operations are brought to a success ful conclusion, the threat from this quarter will be disposed of once and for all. To prevent an ebullition on the part of Shaikh Ali bin Abdulla, it may be as well to bring home to him that his inland fastness forty miles from the sea is no longer secure :rom bombardment; this might be achieved if an aeroplane were to drop a friendly aessage yi - e.g., a request to visit the P.A. - over the shaikh's headquarters. (b) a protest from Shaikh Isa bin Salih. He would, however, uave a weak casus belli, as Muscat will only be exercising immemorial right to take customs dues of 5$. (it is not proposed for the present to apply the enhanced tariff, if eventually sanctioned, to Sur) The proposed aeroplane flight over Ja'alan would probably not be without its effect on Shaikh Isa bin Salih. (o) converting the Jenabeh's present semblance of loyalty into o^en hostility, with the possible result Q f a Jenabeh- Bani Bu All alliance. The threat 0 f a blockade of Sur and Knor Jarana^wiil probably make the yenabeh realise their impotence, once they are convinced that H.B.H.G. is m earnest, 6J ^ According to local ieports, smuggling is said to take the i Oil owing forms: one of the , one o, tne objects of tne proposed prellmi..- ary visit to Sur is to confirm these on the spot. - Import ( 1 ) Apparently Sur is not the P ort of the ocean going dhows belonging to the ifenabeh; these craft merely aestivate m the Khor Sur. The real port seems to be Khor Jaramah, ten miles from Sur. Here the large dhows unload their cargo into smaller vessels, which by night smuggle the contraband goods into the Khor Sur, and land them literally at their owners' back doors, (see attached 3 VO0ketch*m&amp;Jp), It will be observed that the Customs Station at Sur is well away from the mouth of the Khor Sur, and apparently only capable of deali -5 with coastal vessels coming from the north. There is a Customs hut, (a strructure o^ reeds, I believe) at Batih on one side of the entrance to the Khor, while on the opposite side Aiga has not so much as this, nor any representative of the local govern- saeht. Until recently the Bani Bu All maintained their own Wall there. The Jenabeh make an extensive feets. Sxpor t (iii) Caravans enter Sur town at night, via the Sikaikra road. (iv) Carav ns co.ae down the Shaaa Pass and at low tide pass along the southern shore of the Khor Sur into Aiga. vv) Alter tne sea-going dhows have disposed of their cargoes at Khor Jlra^a, they load u , with fish, snarks' fins and fish aawa brought up from Lashakhir. A further loss of approx. Rs 3,500 p.a. Is caused by the dnow-owners' refusal to comply with the Dhow Registration regulations. rrevp nt.atl 1 ' T “ e to a , rocl » au •totto, the .» ot procedure to f o U ...d ln “ 4 Sooa. et dor „d . na ties to be incurred for infraction « ' lr “Ction. Axso a similar notlfation concerning dhow registration. (b) AS resards to build a strong customs t t ° ca^Loms post at Batihequipped if necessary with a searchli 3 ht, and to eataolish a customs post at Aiga. (c) All goods imported into Sur must be landed at tne custoiir 1 . vharf, and v/iil be-cie red on ayiaent of the customs dues. This measure will dispose of 6(ii). (d) As regards 6(iii), the manning of Sikaikra Fort (said to bb vacant) by customs askaris would be advisable. A post at the Shama Pass would also be necessary until control over Aiga was made effective. (e) 6(v) could be dealt with by the establishment at Khor Jarana of a customs post to collect the export tax on and to prevent the landing of cargoes there. The present post at Has al Hadd might be withdrawn and stationed at Khor Jaramah. (f) The proposed posts would be manned by askaris. Ef the present garrison of 70 Is insufficient, additional askers at about Rs 15 p.m. could be enrolled. It is not proposed to garrison these posts with the Muscat Levies, except perhaps a very s ia axl contingent at Batlh of picked shots to act as snipers. vl) To assist these posts, the araed steamer Al Said would ta^ioned ^t &gt;-nr, and would patrol between tnat place and Khor Jiramah. Here crew would be supported by a aachine gun detachment from the Muscat Levies, to deal with recalcitrant dhows or repel a possible party . It may be mentioned here that the Al Said was purchased four years ago for this very purpose, but beyond one or two ineffectual visits to Sur has so far done nothing ' 0 justify her maintenance charges 0 $ Rs 36,000 p.a. 0i) The above measures cannot safely be put into force witnout the loral support of one of U.K.'s warships. It is unlikely that the ship would be called upon to fire * ^ , '” t - b “ ■ 1 “»“ to ua .armed force i) in defence of the members of the government if attacked by an overwhelming force in the performance of their duties. ii) as a punitive measure, if sanctioned-by the political Resident, in retaliation for repeated acts of aggression against the government. This authority should if possible be secured before initiation of the proposed for tightening control at Sur. - inanoial necessity compels the bta,te of .nuscat to employ o^e Al Said as a preventative vesselj the presence of a sloop may prevent an Incident calling for the active inter vention of II.3. :.G. As the process of establishing effective control at Sur may be a slow one. it is desirable that the Indian Govern ment should be prepared to station a ship - not necessarily tne same one - at Khor Jaranah, ithe newly discovered sanatorium; for some months. In this respect it ia a little unfortunate that a tour of the Gulf by an the sloops is contemplated; but perhaps the importance aT the bur question may induce the naval authorities to alter tneir programme to the extent of one ship. For the salce of easy reference, a summary ia attached (Appendix A) of the various items of assistance which the btnte of muscat would be grateful *o have from H.B.’r.G.V Appendix A, II The following is a sununary of ' hat is asked fro i H.B.M.Or, '(a) Penaission for one of H.II.'s warships oO he stationed more or i.ess permanently at K&amp;or Jiramah for the next few months. (k) Authority, to be obtained before the above operations bepin, for the ship to use its puns in certain emergencies. (See para.IJ (h) above) (c) Authority for an aeroplane to fly over Shaikh All bin Abdulla’s headquarters, 40 miles inland. (d) Permission for any aeroplanes or seaplanes that may visit huscat during the next six months to fly over Sur. (e) Authority to purchase, if a free grant is out of Jthe question, two pairs of Levds guns with mountings, to strengthen the somewhat obsolete armament of the A1 Said. Also a .munition for the Lewis guns/ and three pounder, if our present stocks are inadequate. Also the loan of one, or erha_ s two searchlights. (f) Permission for the A1 Said to obtain coal fr m one of 1 ' ships during the 3ur operations, if no other source is or can be made available. (g) Three copies of the “Sur and Environs’* map.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000298_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/64</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000298</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/64</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File XXXVIII/5 VOL I. SUR Nov: 1928- Feb: 1931’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-15T23:03:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">guj</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (340 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 340; these numbers are printed, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-338; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains letters and reports related to tribal disturbances at Sur. The correspondence is mainly concerned with the issue of the Amirs of Ja'alan [Emirs of Ja'lan] Bani Bu Ali rebelling against the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and claiming the following rights: to rule over Sur, to pay no customs taxes, to interfere with the affairs of the tribes of Sur by force, and to establish their own customs in the village of Aiqa [Al ‘Ayjah].The volume also includes correspondence regarding the following: petitions raised by the Sur Hindu traders; the settlement of the account of a Chinese merchant; the death of one of the Amirs of Ja'alan, Shaikh Muhammad bin Nasir Al Hamudah, on 4 February 1929; and the visit of Sa‘id bin Taymur al Bu Sa‘idi to Sur to settle the problems there.The volume also includes: copies of questionnaires related to Sur; a list of the estimated expenses of the Muscat Levy; various reports on Sur; and reports regarding the building of two customs posts- one at Aiqa and one at Muqrimatain [or Maqrumtain], Sur.The main correspondents in the volume are the following: the Political Agent, Muscat; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Government of Muscat and Oman; and the Amirs of Ja'alan.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Hināwī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Ghāfirī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Banī Bū Ḩasan (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Council of Ministers</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh 'Īsá bin Ṣāliḥ al-Ḥārithī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Finance</topic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000298#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>