<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051546.0x000042_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:00:07.767Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051546.0x000042_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/121, ff 158-161</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051546.0x000042</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/121, ff 158-161</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 381: Lieutenant-Colonel Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to His Excellency Lieutenant-Colonel Justin Sheil CB, Her Majesty's Minister Plenipotentiary and Envoy Extraordinary at the Court of Persia, Tehran</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1850/1850</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-21T00:46:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This letter concerns the origins of a gold watch, which was recently sold by the Agent at Shiraz, Mirza Mahmood. The letter includes the following enclosures:Translation of a letter, dated, 17 September 1850, from Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, to Mirza Mahmood, in which Hennell states that His Excellency Lieutenant-Colonel Justin Sheil has not accepted Mirza Mahmood's explanation regarding the fate of Mr Tasker's watch.Translation of an extract of a letter, dated 24 September 1850, from Mirza Mahmood to Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, on the subject of Mr Tasker's watch.Translation of a letter, which is not dated, from Hajee Mahomed Jaffer to Samuel Hennell, Resident in the Persian Gulf, in which Hajee Mahomed Jaffer repeats a statement from an earlier dispatch by stating that he purchased a watch from a man named Moollah Mehdee and sold this watch to Mirza Mahmood. Hajee Mahomed Jaffer states that the watch that Mirza Mahmood sold to Mirza Abdool Bakee strongly resembles the watch that was bought from Moollah Mehdee, although there is some doubt in it.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051546.0x000042#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>