<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001d0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-20T11:13:42.479Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">COPY /] No, 515. (E 4772/1486/34) His Majesty’s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of regulations issued by the Mohammerah Port Officer. British Legation, Tehran, July 16th 1935. Reference: Tehran despatch No* 172 of the 17th April, 1935. Despatch No. 58 with enclosure dated July 3rd, 1935 from H. M. Consul, Ahwaz./. ') 4 - COPY BRITISH CONSULATE, ‘ AHWA2, July 3rd, 1935. Sir, With reference to my despatch No. 56 of July 2, I have the honour to forward translation of a further Circular issued hy the Port Officer ^at Mohammerah, calling upon shipping firms to furnish the Finance Department with a copy of the ship’s manifest on arrival of all vessels. It states that, in case of failure to comply, permission will not he given to discharge cargo. 2. The Agents of the British India Steam Navigation Company say that they are at a loss to understand what value a ship’s manifest can have to the Finance Department heyond extorting &amp; further stamp fee from steamers which already have to pay twenty six rials on manifests and declarations required ty other departments. Apart from the extra trouble and expense involved, there is no objection to giving the Finance Department a copy. I have, etc. (Sd. ) A.E. Watkinson. H.B.M’s Consul for Khuzistan. H.M. Knatchbull-Hugessen, Esquire, G.M. o. , His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, etc., etc., etc., British Legation, Tehran.c COP Y \ j TRANSLATION Dated 12* 3,14 (3. 6*35), No. 14/8. CIRCULiiR All shipping firms are hereby required to furnish the Finance Department with a copy of the respective ship’s manifest on arrival of their vessels. Otherwise no permission for the discharge of their cargo will he granted. FOR MOHAMMERAH PORT OFFICER, (Sgd). Amanpour, 1st Lieut.No r IQ) His Majesty's s Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of Mohammerah Port regulations# . Reference:- Tehran despatch Ho# 172 of the 17th April, 1935# 1. Mohamaerah port Office Amended Circular dated the 5th January, 1935# 2# Mohammerah Port Office Circular Ho. 11/3 dated the 26th March, 1935. H.B. The above documents were forward to H.M#Legation at Tehran, from H.M#Consul at Ahwaz, under printed Letter Ho. 32/I7II/21 dated 23rd April,1935.Amended (i?r anal at Ion. Dated 15-10-1312 5th January,1935, Circular, Owners of River Craft or their agents when issuing bills of lading are bound to affix and cancel Revenue Stamps to the value of Rials Two in accordance with article 26 of the Income Tax Law. They are required to comply with the following ytesns; .■j- 8,6. Owners of River Craft should refer to Finance Department to have their Bill of Lading books duly stamped arfi sealed. Ho Dill of lading is to he issued from hooks which have not been stamped. If a bill of lading ia issued in triplicate, the original should be stamped. 4th. i$o bill of lading is allowed to be issued on unprinted Forms. Contraveners of the above article will be dealt with seriously. (Signed) F. von Croise for MOHAMMERAH PORT OFFICER.Cirouiar* Notice is hereby given to all river craft that they should hereafter submit their bills of lading to Finance Department for sealing and stamping, failing which they will be dealt with seriouslye (Signed) Von Croiae, 1st Lt., for Post (? Port) Offieer,Mohammerah.Ho# 172* Q ; British Legation Tehran# 17th April, 1936. air With reference to my despatch Ho* 74 of February 12th last, I have the honour to transmit, herewith, copies of two despatches from His Majesty’s Consul at Ahw&amp;s, enclosing translations of further regulations issued by the port Officer at Mohaaaterah# 2 With regard to paragraph 4 of Mr Watkinson’s despatch of February 86th, X have been informed in confidence by the Anglo-1 rani an Oil Company that one of their tankers recently came into collision at night with an unlighted dhow in the Shatt-ei-Arab# The Basra Harbour port held an enquiry and found that the blame rested solely on the dhow, but the case was subsequently taken up by Halb Sarhang Bayendor who gave a decision against the Company and fined the latter a Rials 28,000 # sum of Rials twenty two thousand. Th© Company are not prepared to agree 3 that a judgement of this nature can be issued except by the Courts acting in the proper form and are taking the matter up at Tehran on the grounds of procedure# They consider Bayendor * &amp; decision In this particular ease to be a bad miscarriage of justice, since they were given no opportunity of stating their view# As this incident would appear to have a direct bearing on the question which !- f r# Rat kin son raises and may make it apparent whether the naval /autho ight Honourable Sir John Simon, G#C.S.I. # etc., etc# § etc#, The Foreign Officeauthor!ties Intend to act as judieial authorities themselves, or whether, following an enquiry hy them, a ease will he handed over to the ordinary Courts for trial, I am deferring the Isa^fr.ef ‘ ihstruotions to Mr. Watkinson pending any result which may emerge from the Company 1 e demarche at Tehran. Ab regards the question raised in paragraph 3 of my despatch under reference, His Majesty’s Vice- Consul at Mohammerah reports that he has not registered the launch nor has he been requested to do so. he has, moreover, been informed, when he asked to be supplied with copies of all regulations issued, that it was the intention of the port authorities to regard Consular craft as privileged, and he was merely asked to cooperate by observing the speed limit of six knots in the Kama. 6. I am sending a copy of this despatch (without enclosures) to His Majesty^s Consul at Ahwas (Ho. 14). I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, your most obedient, humble servant, (Signed) H.M. Knatchbull-Hugessen.K. XFP Ii anv further communication on this subject, please cftaote no. c.,u 4 8bXl4'^G/j/A'. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. l.&lt; THE Under-Secretary of State for ^ Affairs presents his compliments to JlS 4. L-r*-OLC £1*Ssl ^ 0 ^ 6 ^ and, by direction of the Secretar^ of State, transmits herewith cop (&amp;4 of the under-mentioned paper. n A 'oreign Office, , 193b . ir- o M '1U Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure.kQpy s / / 10.74. (S 148fl/1480/f!4) nritleh Legt iion, Tehran. 12 th February, 1955, Sir, I hfeve the honour to tfisnsmlt, herewith, a copy of &amp; despatch from His M&amp;ls&amp;ty** Consul at Ahwas reporting the establishmeat of a ort Office at Mohsaaersh and enclosing translations of certain regulations which have been issued for the control of shipping. 2* It Is not Known under what authority these regulations were promulgated but, while it would be possible to address m enquiry an this point to the Persian (Government, I doubt whether any advantage would be gained by so doing* The Persian Oovemneat are certain to uphold the authority of Hath Sarhaag Bayandor in this matter and I think that the regulations should therefore be regarded as official* In so far as they concern the Ki run and Hohasmerah they appear to be innocuous, though the circular of 17th November, which mentions the Shatt~*1~Arab, may become a s&gt;:)urce of trouble* 3# It seems possible that the launch maintained by His Majesty’s Vice-Consulate at Hohamaersli may have to be registered under these regulations* It would appear « uita reasonable that this should be done, though I should expect that the payment of any fee would be waived as a matter of courtesy* 4* I am sending copies of this despatch (with enclosure) to His Majesty’s Ambassador at aghdad (Ho* 10), and a co y, without enclosures, to His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwe* (No*4)* X have, etc*, (For H*M* minister) (Sgd) F.H* Loaley The Fight Honourable Sir «T ohn 'l i mo n , ci • C • u«I • etc*, etc*, e c*i ,m * 73 Foreign Office*I h&amp;vn tat honour to Torw^rd hor^with translations of circulars Issued reoontly fey tho Comsadsat of the rsien end ©■ 5 rusunieei&lt; 0 d to ms fey the Ms®opote®i&amp; forsie Corporation, him!tod* sad fey the Aaglo-Arslan Oil Compttny* Limi ted* regarding the sstefellsteent of the MohsmiHirsa Fort Office. Thia office, which, clelsia to hsve JU'd^diction over the Port of HohetmauirsJh and H. the Fiver Kamsa e» far ue Ahw^a, was eet&amp;felished on lith Sovoafeer last. it is understood ih&amp;t Sultan Mysador* brother of the Cowsndeat of the Persian Navy, who is at present afeuent in Italy, is to fee f’ort Officer* Lieutenant Von Kreuse, a naturalised Persian mb^ct of Rusai^n origin, is temporarily in charge. Bo far no representative has been appointed in Ahw&amp;ji fc ,nd no copies of these regulations have been sent to the ^was offices of .■■■#sopotsmia ^ersla Corporation Limited nor of the Angle Persian Oil Com any nor of the various small Persian owner* of river craft. Nor h&amp;s His Majesty's Vice-Cons a at HThsuutrtli been Infomod fey the Persian author!ties of the existence of any of these regulations* although a motor launch is known to fee maintained at the consulate. 2. The circulars issued fey Msife a&amp;rhsng Bsyandor relate to the establishment of the Port Office and order recipients to conform to official instructions to be issued by that office, a subsc uent circular, dated !?th November, 19*4, end addressed to other Government apartments, states that preliminary InveatiHtitlon an! arbitration fe the Naval Authorities oa technical joints in connexion with accidents and maritime matters , , on f. Kaatchfeull-Hugeaben, Psn., His Britannic Majeety , s minister, etc., etc., , British Legation, Tehran.on 'the Efenm and th© Shut* fend at Saa w Is within th* oompstcne® or thoss fettthdrltlss f t vugh subssqusnt rsferenc© of cXalaui to th© Civil Courts is ©fivig^gsd. Two previous ttlrcul&amp;rs wsre Issued by the Co&amp;GBUM&amp;dant of the llavy on 19th June, 19-id, and ;i8th Oepteraber, 19dd, respectively, regarding the a .©borage of steamers, dhows and mehsllae at the mouth of the Hlvc^r Kama end at the Customs House t-iid the loading and unloading of cargo by barges, and regarding pollution of the Upper B&amp;haesfctr and the timxi at Mohsaaeraii by stem-wheelers end other craft, 4* The remaining el rattlers are signed by the Acting Port Officer* They provide for reportlug to him within two weeks the number, name and flag of all steamers ^d motor boats plying' on the Karan River with a view to subsequent survey and issue of a licence, and for coaaunication of various details required for survey * s nd i»*m® of a survey certificate. Failure to comply on the part of owners will entail revocation of permission to ply on the river* The Port Office regulations also provide for the crew and lighting of vessels moored in the river and prohibit overloading* They also lay down the number of crew required on vassals from 1 to 100 tons and of the crew of craft being towed* And the number of tugs for barges in the Port of Mohammerah is flxsd* 5. The existence of such regulations is undoubtedly for the general benefit of shipping* It will bo interesting, however to see what powers the Persian N&amp;vy has or proposes to oxorcls© to enforce the various regulations* I eat not reporting to the Boardof Trk&amp;# t In with standing inatruotloa^, ponding reooipt of your vimm to whether the..e regulations &amp;re leaned tsy a properly conetltu^rd authority* Moreover the regulation* issued ao far do not *eee f to affect any but pirely local shipping. It ie undereteed that tie Meeopoteaia terete corporation and the i' • /’ V # Anglo-'^r^i&amp;n Oil company, who‘are the only British owner® of j eomiirciei river craft affected, are taking step* to comply with the regulations issued up to the present* ». A eooy of thi* dospetch la being sent to the Honourable the Political Resident in the*'Permian oulf, Buehire, (Ko, 198)* 1 have, etc*, (Sgd) Am Mm watkinson* H* B* M* s Qomm, FOB KHUEISTAM*s^-sakjxii^ command of KfeVfei Forces of the Uoutfc. The following rogialibtiOBS provisionally fixed with .regard to anehorago for all stenaera &amp;nd sailing ahios (dhows) as well as sailing boats. (?auhailaa) which enter the mouth of f the Karunt- k , 1. .Anchorage in the E&amp;r\m in the portion between its luncti m with the cihatt and the confluence of the stream J&amp;ssebi is prohibited, U* Sailing vessels which arrive from abroad and must undergo Customs formalities will anchor in front of the Customs Stores at s distance of aO meters from the right bank one after another* and* as soon as they have completed their Custom® business they will move in up the Karan ivtr* $. Barges which take delivery of cargo from the Customs must also place themselves in signis file like sailing vessels (dhow®)* and must not proceed towards the middle of the Karan beyond the line fixed for anchorage of the letter ./i- (selling vessels)# Moreover they must not stop longer then tea hours, 4, Barges which lead any cargo in the one prohibited as per Article 1 above* will proceed in the way stipulated for then as per article 3 above. Acting Commander of Mouth Heval Forces, Major Sgd. Tlr ;i,-q aDieted 6th Mahr, 1318. (88th Sept., 1933) ^ l- .fi IL tf R. •# 12-jmmsLM ,M}j±jLMM£k. wail,, wh@r#a« mom ^tern-wheelers throw their oily m&amp;tter end bilge water from eteariera into the Seran river and ua this is against the mguletione* it is hereby notified that in future any craft In the Earun area# whether in the upper portion of utmmmhir or opposite Mohamennh f throwing oily matter or water of dark colour or any other dirt into the river f the craft *111 be held under arrest for a period from one to three months and drivers thereof will be auupended from being in charge of gay work in the transport business for a period of six year*®. This arrangement will come into force with effect from 15th day of Mehr Mah (?th Oct.)* ■jgd* Capt. Clhulam Huasain # For Acting 0#c* south Havel Forces.Copy of circular l«tur Ho.l of Ixth ffovemb&amp;r* If-4, frost the ohmaeriOi ort Officer«&lt;* Ta order to register tad feacertutn the c&amp;ptclty tad tttworthliitttt of ste&amp;ai#r® i^id attat of trtatport ply lag cm the Xtrua rlvty # owners in general tro hereby notified th^f they should submit to the Port Office of the on them Htvsl Force, not later tht,n ^6th Hovenfeor, 1934 a list showing their ttetmere sad ^otor bouts with details of nnuber, name end the Flag under which they are running after which date the Port Office authorities will survey the craft and the necessary Fermit and Certificate will fee issued* I * Conveyances Cannot ply after ^6th November, 1934, unless the survey is undergone and a Feralt obtained* igd* It* Von Kreu&amp;e* For ilohsamersh Pert Officer.-) o 3^ Copy or Circular letter *io.a '14 of Ii5th noves»h»r, 10'H, froa the Mottuaerfeh &gt;ort Officer. tb n» iwi wam&gt; mm f0r lii * m&amp;4 tam® of survey Certlfle&amp;t* d©tteil«d infomution on the following p tnta should h® submitted to this Office am c&amp;riy ss possible Heme of owner of ireeeel, M^ie of Cmmm&amp;ar or responsible person in charge. Type of ship. Year in which built. Piece where built# Of what material made# number of decks. Humber of airtight hatches# Deep or flat bottom, number of bilges. Jteoeaesry e^ulp«esits deck gear etc. Anchoring gear# iiife saving *&lt;1 Ipeent# Fire egtlnguiehing appliances. Over all length in metres. Over all breadth. Hett tonnage# arose tonnage* Height of the mala deck from water level when in ballast and when loaded. Draught of steamer - in bsliest and when loaded. Cspseity of cargo end paseengsrs. Humber of crew, Humber and type of Bt&amp;m whistles. Engine 1 type, system, horse-power, speed and fuel reserve* .tores capacity, including water. (Sgd) X*t. Von Xreuae# For Mohsnsersh port Officer.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001d0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/173</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001d0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/173</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 5840/35 'Mohammerah Port Regulations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-07T22:06:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description (used for referencing) commences at f 141, and terminates at f 170, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 141-170; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to the establishment of a Port Office at Mohammerah [Khorramshahr] and accompanying port regulations.The discussion in the volume relates to the following regulations:Accidents relating to water transport on the Karun, and Shatt al-Arab and in the Persian GulfAnchorage for ships entering the mouth of the KarunThe establishment of a Mohammerah Port OfficeCustoms and taxes levied on water craftThe exemption of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company (APOC) from taxes based on its concession agreementA report on an accident involving an Anglo-Persian Oil Company tanker (folio 146)Discussion of the political significance of the regulations issued concerning the Shatt al Arab waterway.The principal correspondents in the volume are: Mohammerah Port Officer (Lieutenant F von Kreuze); Commandant, Southern Naval Force; HBM Consul for Khuzistan (A E Watkinson); HM Ambassador to Iran (Sir Hughe Montgomery Knatchbull-Hugessen); Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Sir John Simon).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commandant, Southern Naval Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commandant of the Imperial Iranian Navy</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consul, Ahwaz</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Shatt al Arab</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Karun River</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Harbours</topic></subject><subject><topic>maritime transport</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x0001d0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>