<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002fb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T12:30:31.554Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">*Copy. tio 2, © Sir t ' ritish Consulate, IV J nave the honor to acknowledge receipt of your Despatch Ho 1233 of December -atrder on Turkish territory of the C with / is son ,h is nephew .and t T have drawn the attention of out rareir a memorandum embodying -mio.icated to him through my Dragoman ,ara of which a copy is inclosed herewith J'ohsin Pa^ha stated in reply f that he naa already received a report on the subject from his Suh- - oro. mates or the spot,ana that the arrest and punishment of rr oraer~o satisfy the Sheikh the laws of Turkey required it proeeaure.hut in the meantime he would like to know what was the real object of the mur i'ain land at a place where they hoc. already incn^red the emi tn / dc Lieut:Colonel C.Kenball &amp;c dc : ' British F'U -ih i re.&amp; , 0 Copy, T 1 /v A- x J3 ■ Memoranawn t On the 3rd of December a ho ay of Araks he longing to the BeActc-'A section of the ALnurra trite treacherously attack- ~ea Sheikh Selman bin Diai j f cousin o* the Sheikh of Bahrein who was on the Mainland on a hunting excursion at a place called Al-Daraya about thirty or forty miles south'of Katif The attack took place in the early morning,while tl e victim vere asleep, and S eikh Selman,his son, ana his nephew vjith 23 followers were murdered in cold blood,on hi 3 of his party escaping. His Excellency the Vali has no doubt already received a full report of the above incident f but in case he desires further information it can be obtained fromHJVs Consulate., It is unnecessary to point out the desirability of afford oing satisfaction to the Sheikh of Bahrein for the murder of his relatives by the prompt arrest and punishment of th&amp; guilty parties,and of thus depriving him of pretext for taking the law into his own hands.It would immensely add to the difficulties of the already complicated ? ituattan in this part of Turkish Arabia,were the Sheikh of Bahrein, aesparing of obtaining satisfaction from the Ottoman Authorities ,to himself organise an expedition against the Al-lturra. (British Consulate Bvsreb .Veer 28f r I&amp; of 19 Iritish ReslCicncy xnji h Bushire, // ^ January 1901. December 1900.for favor of necessary enquiry ana report. By order, /?c First Assistant to the Political Resident in the f Persian Gulf, Copy forwaraea to the Assistant Political Anent, Bahrein with reference to his le* * 3 ! w From No: /A^of 1901 British Residency ana Consulate-General, Bush ire, 7 * February 1901. Lieut-Colonel C, A, Kemhall, Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To f The Assistant Political Agent f Bahrein . Sir, With reference to the correspondence which has passed between us on the subject of the murder in Turkish territory / &gt; * -ii of Sheikh Salman bin Diaij El Khalifah i with his followers^ I have the honor to inform you that the matter was - _ _ ^ reported by me to the Government of India, by whom a repre sentation has been made to the Secretary of State for India on the subject. You may inform the Sheikh of Bahrein that the Government of India have received the news of the outrage with deep regret I have the honor to be Sir, Your most obedient servant 0 ff? : Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4J* * 1 f- Cop y of a letter from H.B.M's, Consul ,Bussorah,to .E.th Governor-Cejieral^Fussorcih,A'o 72 daied Julj lu t lJOl* Excellency, of On the yth^June last I had the honour to inquire verbally of Your Excellency what measures were being ta^fi to discover and punish the perpetrators of murder of Sheikh Selman of Bahrein and his companions. Your Excellency replied that the Behaih t^i h e j to which the criminals belonged^ad dispersed i^io the interior of the country and would not return until ihe Date Season;and that in consequence no steps could be taken in the matter before K en, 1 now hear from Bahrein through the 1 rioish Consul-General at Bushire that at the end of June, a po.r^y of the tribe in question was on the llainlavd opposite Bahrein, but that the Turkish Authoriti es of the Sanjak of El-Has s a were doing nothing whatever lo discover the auilty persons. Since I first drew Your Excellency 's attention to this affair in December last J have observed with regret an entire inability on the part of the Ottoman Authorities to realise the gravity of the situati on,!-is llajesty 's Government in any case will not,! am sure &gt;le^ pass unpunished the wholesale murder of persons unde^ Bri tishNo: 0 f I 902 - British Residency and Consulate-General, Bush ire, March 1902, From Lieut-Colonel C, A. Kemball, Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein, Sir, V/ith reference to the case of the murder of Sheikh Selman bin Diaij al Khalifa and his followers ^t El Deriyah by the Behaih section of the Al Murrah tribe, I have the honour to ask you, as it now seems probable that the Turks do not intend to take any steps to bring the murderers to /\ justice, to consider carefully and report to me at an early date what other steps are possible with the view to obtain redress for the Chief of Bahrein, The tribe to which the offenders belong are, 1 under standunderstand, at the present time living in the interior within the limits of the jurisdiction of the Mutasserrif of A1 Hassa. At certain seasons however of the year 1 understand that they come down to the Coast ana in habit some place on the bay markea t Dahat S a lwa / on the chart, South of Bahrein, Whether this place is con- si derea to be within the limits of Katr J ao not know. It might be possible for the Chief of Bahrein^]) subsidizina some other tribe living in the vicinity t to obtaiiijsome sort of rearess from the Behaih. It is however that such a measure would be unsatis factory, as the Chief might have to give the tr l be^ who woula then have taken his quarrel upon themselves f a place of haven in Bahrein / and this might prove a constant drain on his resources. It seems difficult therefore for the Chief to undertake his own measures for obtaining redress. If however the Behaih tribe come at certain seasons of J r ' the year within the limits of Katr, it might be possible for the Chief of Katr to arr Whether the Chief of Katr woula be willing to do so and for what consideration, pointpoint t however, as well as on the feasibility of the suggestion, and the general practicability of obtaining rearess for Sheikh Isa now that the Turks are not likely to take any action, 1 shall be glaa to have your views to assist me in submittinn a further report to Government on the subject, I ao not unaerstand that the offending tribe have any boats or fixed place of resiaence on the Coast / ana a boat expea-- tion from one of His Majesty's ships could not therefore be undertaken , I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obeaient servant Offg: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,No *8/ 0 British Res idency avd C onsulate-General 9 Bush ire t ^May 1902. From The First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To The Assistant Political Agent, Bah rein. Sir, With reference to your letter No 98, dated 3rd instant^ regarding the murder of Sheikh Sulman and his companions by the Behaih, I have the honor to request that you will be so good as to inform me whether there is yio possibility of the whole case being set at rest by the payment of an indemnity to incluae compensation for all those who were murdered. If, however, this is not possible, you will furnish me with more particulars regarding the means which the Chief of Bahrein proposes to adopt for the settlement, throughthrough Sheikh Ahmed of Katr t of the matter of the murder of his relatives. I have the honor to he Sir, your most obedient servant. u* Captain &gt; First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.@ No htoi of 1902. British Residency and Consulate-General t Bus hire f /^A U G U S T&gt; 1902. To The Assistant Political Agent, BAHREIN. Sir, I have the honor to forward .for your informati on and favour of very early reportja copy of Government of India's letter No 1340 E.A. &gt; dated 4th July 1902 together with copies of despatch No 217 dated 10th May 1902 from Sir N. O'Connor to His Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and of a translation of a communique of the Turkish Minister of the Interior to the Turkish foreigrv Mi nister. 2. With reference to paragraph 2 of Government of Indians letter above quoted read in connection with the statement of the Turkish Minister of the Interior i information seems also to he called for as regards vhe connecti on between the Diiwasir and the Amameroh if any such exists, as our records shew the feud to have originated between the Behaih section of the Al-Murra tribe and the Amamerah and not the Duwasi r.V. V. ^SWb Duwcis i r. 3. Some confusion also seems to exist between the Fehaih and AlMdj sections of the Al Murra, as we understand that Eashid bin Megarih is Chief of the former and not of the latter as stated by the Turkish Minister. 4, Lastly it is desirable to establish the correctness or the reverse of the statement that Sheikh Rashid the head of the raid and his son and ten or more followers o # it we re killed, as our information is not in agreement with this. I have the honor to be. Si r, Your most obedient servant, Captain, Fi rst Assislant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confidential. No 1340 E .A. From The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Fo re ign Department. To Lieutenant Colonel C. A. Kemball, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Shiraz. Dated Simla, the 4th July 1902* Sir, I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your 4 letter No —— dated the Gth June 1902, regarding questions S. A* arising from the murder of Sheikh Selman bin Diaij el Khal- ifah, and to enclose a copy of a despatch of the same date Secret, No 24 with enclosures^ from the Secretary of State for India* Your observati ons upon the Turkish state- \ ment enclosed therewith will be awaited and should be fur- nished with as little delay as possible* 2. I am to invite you to explain the position of the Devassir (or Dowasir) tribe of Bahrein. If they are sub jects of the Bahrein Sheikh, and if their compli city in the murder, in 1898 or 1899, of a son of the Behaih Sheikh is established&gt; it may be possible, in view of the fact, ihatthat the Behaih Sheikh and another of his sons were killed in the attack upon Sheikh Selman and his party, to pro pose a settlement based upon compensati on for the excess of lives lost by the Bahreinese and for their plundered property. The precise connection, if any, between the ■V party of Sheikh Selman and the party of the Dowasir tribe who crossed at the same time to the mainland seems to re- quire further elucidati on. 3. The Government of India are disposed to consider that the suggesti on that the Sheikh of Bahrein should negotiate with the Behaih section of the Almurra through Sheikh Ahmed bin Thani of El Katr might, if it were adopted, lead to compli cati ons in connecti on with the recommend- ation which you have separately preferred in regard to the desire of Sheikh Ahmed bin Thani to come under British protection. I am to invite an express i on of your views upon this point. I have etc, (Sd). H. Daly, Deputy Secy to the Govt of India.y No 217 My Lord. Annex S* Sir N. O'Connor to Foreign Office. Consto,nti nople, 10th May 1902, With reference to my despatch No 207, of the 5th instant, I have the honor to forward herewith translation of a lettev from the Minister of the Interior Affairs respecting the murder of Selman been communicated to me by Tewfik Pasha. I am not in a position to judge * arguments of the Minis oer of the Interi or t but the state ments he makes may be in great part correct. Before I can proceed further with the case it will be necessary that the Minister's letter should be submitted to His Majesty's Resident at Bushire for his observati ons. I take this opportunity of informing your Lordship, with reference to your Despatch, No 111, of the 8th ultimo t that without making a formal complaint, I have called the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs to the dis courtesy shown by the Turkish Officials at El Katif to Mr Gaskin and the Commander of His Majesty's Ship ''Sphinx % on the occasion of their recent visit to that place. I have etc, (Sd) N. R, O'Connor. The Marquess of Lansdowne, K.G. , etc, etc., e &amp; c.,Annex 4. Translati on of a Communication from the Minister of the Interior to the Minister for Foreign Affairs t dated 3rd May 1902, The son of Rashid bin Mekiarikh, Chief of the Elhidj section of the Almareh tribe, was murdered in the year 1816 (1899) by the Devassir tribe of the Island of Bahrein In the year 1816 (1900) the son of Sheikh Selman, one of the Sheikhs of lahrein, proceeded to Maakdan in the neigh bourhood of Katif on a shooting expedition, together with Abdullah bin Hassan of the Devassir tribe, and in con sequence of the murder of Rashid bin Mekiarikh, the tribes (in that neighbourhood), *n accordance with the custom of vendetta, attacked the Bahreinese and killed over twenty of them. The British Embassy asked that the assassin of Sheikh Selman, together with his accompli ces, should be seized and punished. In consequence a lengthy correspondence has passed between the Porte and the Vilayet of Basra, and the Vali sends now the copy of a joint report received by him from the Mutessarif and the Military Commandant of Nejd* According to this report, when Sheikh Selman, his son and the Sheikh of the Devassir tribe, Abdullah binIP bin Hassan, without appealing, as they should have do\ to the Caimacan of Katif, were in that neighbourhood, be cause Sheikh Abdull &amp;h aforesaid of the tribe of Deuassir had killed the son of Rashid bin Mekiarikh, Ro.shid, in r&gt; order to avenge the death of his son, together with his followers t attacked them. A battle took place in which fourteen Bahreinese were killed; Selman bin Deidj, the cousin of Sheikh Issa of Bahrein, and his son Deidj-bin Selman, his nephew Abdurrahman bin Rashid, and of the Devassir Sheikhs Abdullah bin Hassan, were among the killed. Thirteen of the Has a and Kati f tribe were also killed, and among them were the head of the attacking party, Rashid bin Mekiarikh, and his son. In the letter addressed b'j the Sheikh Issa of Bahrein to the Ituvessarif of Nejd, it was alleged that 93?6 reals worth of property was taken from the Bahreinese; th*s claim seemed to be much exaggerated, more especially as the carrying of Martinis is prohibited by the Government (I presume the Mutes sari f means the value of the arms lost cannot be properly claimed (ini ti ailed A.B.)); if the pro perty is estimated at its real value, it will be possible io extract this money from the Elbidj tribe. As a matter of fact the whole affair is the. consequence of the murder of the son of Sheikh Rashid bin lAekiarikh by thethe Devassir tribe, and is the usual vendetta to which the tribes always resort. On this occasion it is the Bahreinese who have been the cause of the occurrence: without appealing to the Government they ought not to have gone shooting in that district; such a proceeding was irregular. Crimes committed in this manner in the % desert are to be expiated by the punishment of the in stigators: such is the law, Chapter i.. Section 2; yet, notwithstanding, Sheikh Has hid, the head of the raid, and his son have been shot, in law the death of the ac~ cused stops proceedings. If it be necessary, however, to settle the question according to tribal custom, and if one compares the losses sustained on both sides, and the fact thectthe Bahreinese were the original aggressors, the Bahreinese at most can only ask for their fourteen dead 800 reals each. The Elbidj tribe has not since this In cident come into the neighbourhood of El Has a, but never theless one of ohe Sheikhs of the tribe, Abdullah b*n Tafio, has been seized and imprisoned. The answer returned by the Ministry of the Interior to the Vali is that as, according t.o the information' thus given. Sheikh Rob hid the head of the raid, and his son have been killed, and of his followers ten or thirteen have been also killed, it is therefore impossible to punish or prosecute anyone* TheThe real value of the property taken shouldhe assessed, and with the blood money due to the Bahreinese killed should be taken from the other tribe y and, in accordance with the tribal custom, you should settle the matter In this manner and pacify the two parties. Constantinople, 7th May 1902. /^c;i; 7^ Copy of a letter No 17 dated 4th Acting Consul,Bussorah ,to Captain Vere de Vere Hunt,I.A., I First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Rush ire. &amp;/ In reply to your letter No 662 of July 30 in regard to the re-appearance of the Behaih honour to inform you that the Vali from the Mutesarrtf of Nefd stating on accouTit of the pasturage and that if he sees any liheli~ hood of their doing harm he will at once take measures to prevent it % I jVO . of 19 British Residency and Co / ' Bush ire, //4 -August 1903. Copy forwarded to the Assista for mformat ion,with reference Captain, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, In charge current duties*British Residency d Consulate-General, Bushire, /^j ^ July 1903. /in. O j d ' ^ ^ ' ^ y In continuation of my official letter No:620, dated 16th instant, I enclose for your confident!al information 1. Letter to His excellency the Naval Commander~in~Chief,hjast Indi es Stati on,No:670-4,dated Ibth April 1903. 2. Letter from --Do No:920,dated 26th April 1903. copy of the marginally noted correspondence regarding the sug gestion made by the Chief of Bahrein to he allowed to equip an armed dhow to act against pirates in Bahrein waters You J. C. Gas kin as qui re, Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein.c;'B You will notice thai Che Chief's proposal as it stands will not bo approved.No. 675 E., dated Simla, the 16th April 1903 (Confidential). From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To—His E xcellbncy R rar- A dmiral S ir C. C. D rtjry, K .C.I.E., Commanding His Majesty^s Naval Forces, East Indies Station. I am directed to forward an extract from a letter from tlie Political No. 167. dated the 8th December 1902 (para- Resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding graphs 3 and 4). a suggestion made by the Chief of Bahrein that he should be permitted to employ an armed dhow in pursuit of pirates. Your Excellency is, no doubt, aware that the vicinity of Bahrein and of the neighbouring mainland coasts has long been the scene of somewhat frequent piratical outrages, and that, after a period of comparative immunity, there was a recrudescence of this crime during the past year. Your Excellency has also been informed of the activity which has recently been displayed by the Turks in connection with the affairs of the El Katr peninsula. 2. Under the terms of the Agreement which he executed in 1861, the Sheikh of Bahrein is bound to abstain from any act of aggression or retaliation at sea, and any departure from the principle of this Agreement might be attended by undesirable risks. At the same time there would probably be considerable advantage in making some special arrangement for the patrolling or policing of the waters in this neighbourhood ; not only on account of the increased security which should result, but also from the point of view that earlier and more accurate information might, if suitable measures were adopted, be obtained as to the condition of affairs on the neighbouring mainland. In the circumstances, I am to invite any suggestions or advice which Your Excel lency may be in a position to offer on the subject. The alternatives which present themselves to the Government of India are— (i) the maintenance at Bahrein of an armed dhow of the class that has, it is understood, been recently employed with good effect in checking piracy and the trade in arms in the Gulf of Aden and the .Red Sea; or, (ii) the maintenance by the Sheikh, at his own expense, of a dhow manned by his own subjects, but which would be commanded by a junior British officer lent from the Royal Navy or from the Royal Indian Marine, to ensure that it was only employed for proper purposes. 3. If Your Excellency is able to propose any precise arrangements, I am to request that an estimate of the probable cost may, if possible, be fur nished. On receipt of Your Excellency's reply, the Government of India propose to address His Majesty's Secretary of State. No. 676 E. (Confidential). A copy of the foregoing letter, with enclosed extract, is forwarded to the Military (Marine) Department, with the request that, if there is no objection, the Foreign Department may be furnished with the views of the Director of the Royal Indian Marine on the proposals so far as it may affect his Department. Fjpciga Office Presa—No. 198—12.5-03—60.the men who committed the murders and he is therefore unable to say whether any of the persons named by the Porte are the real culprits. I shall be obliged if you will furnish me with such information on the subject as you may be able to obtain % 3. Meanwhile His Majesty's Ambassador has informed the Porte that the payment of a sum of Rs 35,140/- as blood- money and compensation should be paid^nd the Wali of Basra has been instructed by the Porte to take the neces sary action in accordance with the Ambassador's demand. Meanwhile it is proposed to allow a reasonable time to eltapse for the execution by the Wali of the orders trans mitted to him before allowing the Sheikh to take the matter into his own hands m 4. You should take a suitable opportunity of informing the Chief of Bahrein that the matter is still receiving the serious consideration of His Jftofesty's G-ovemment and that it is for the present advisable that he should not take any independent action in the matter. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Offg: Political Resident, Persian GulfT R A N S L A T I 0 N No; 55763. Enclosure to Sir N m 0'Conor's despatch No:50, dated the 26th January 1904; to the Marquess of Lansdotme. Tne G-ovemor-G&amp;neral of t oj Busscrah been questioned on the subject Salman bin DiaiJ and his relations, ject of the note in Turkish, communicated Embassy to the Porte under date (old style) i telegraphs on information furnished by the Governor of Nejd that the crime in question was due to the animosity existing between the &gt;r the tnfie of ElbehidJ, which tribe is notorious for its 7&gt; deeds of murder and pillaging of caravans. The attack of of which Sheikh Sal/nan and his relatives were the victims was committed by Ebou Mekiarih, Muhammed bin Nejdan, Ali Ebou MoUakib,, Ebou Ketife, Hassan Cherimit and Toritor(?sic^} 9 'Vvyvt' . Seeing that these persons, who were also concerned in the attack, m the locality called Tinofe, on a convoy which Sr was on its way to Ad J i re escorted by Turkish troops, were killed m the engagement which they had with these troops andJ that these said persons were alone implicated in the murder in question (of Sheikh Selman etc,) there can he no reason for demanding from the ElbehidJ tribe the payment of an indemnity. Moreover the members of the said tribe, on account cf the pursuits directed against them, have fled into the desert of Nejd % &amp;1 (No. 132.) Sir, 'WITH reference to your Excellency's despatch No. 115 of the 23rd Feb ruary, I transmit herewith copies of correspondence which has passed with the India ()ffice on the subject of exacting reparation for the murder of relatives of the Sheikh of Bahrein by members of the Behaih tribe. T our Excellency will observe that His Majesty's Government do not con sider that the action taken by the Turkish Government can be accepted as adequate. I have accordingly to request that you will inform the Turkish Government that, as they have been unable to obtain compensation from the Behaih, His Majesty's Government can no longer dissuade the Sheikh from resorting to such steps as he may think necessary for this purpose. They will, however, use their best elTorts to insure that he shall take no action against the Behaih so long as that tribe remain in territory recognised as Turkish. A copy of a despatch to the Government of India on the subject is also inclosed for your Excellency's information. I am, &amp;c., (Signed) LANSDOWNE. The Marquess of Lausdowne to Sir N. 0'Conor. Foreign Office, April 12, 1904.1 {Received on 6th June with Political Secretary's letter No. 21, dated the 20th May 1903.) Poreign Office to India Office. May 9th, 1904. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 2oth March, I am directed by the M-irquess of Lansdowne to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty's Ambassador at Con stantinople on the subject of the murder of Sheikh Selman and his followers near Katif in December 19 )0. It will be seen that Sir N. O'Conor hesitates to act upon the instructions recently sent to him until he hears whether the persons stated to have been killed in the engagement between the Turkish forces and the ofi'ending tribes are or are not the same as those accused of the murders. The only information which has been received on this subject is contained in the Note from the Porte, enclosed in Sir N. 0'Conor's despatch No. 50, of the 26th of January last, supplemented by the assertion of the Turkish Minister of the Interior, as reported in Sir N. O'Conor's further despatch No. 115, of the 23rd February. Lcrd Lansdowne notes that both these despatches have been communi cated to the Government of India and that in Mr. Secretary Brodrick's des patch No, 11, of the 19th February, in which Sir N. O'Conor's No. 50 was enclosed, it was suggested that Colonel Kemball should endeavour to ascertain whether the individuals mentioned in the Turkish Note wer ^ those actually con cerned in the murders. No reply appears to have been received to this sug gestion. It would in Lord Lansdowne's opinion be desirable to ascertain whether the Sheikh of Bahrein has been made aware of the statement of the Turkish | Government that six members of the offending tribe have been killed, and that besides these six individuals no other person was implicated in the murders. I am to suggest that Colonel Kemball should be requested to report by tele graph on this point. In the meantime Lord Lansdowne would propose to inform Sir N. O 'Conor ' that an enquiry will be addressed to Colonel Kemball as above suggested, but ' f that, unless any further information can be obtained from the Sheikh or from the Turkish Government, His Excellency should make the communication to the Porte as directed in Lord Lansdowne's despatch No. 132 of the 12th ultimo. Sir N. 0' Conor to Marquess of Lansdoicne. I am, etc., (Sd.) T. H. SANDERSON. Constantinople ; 19th Jpril 1904. No. 286. Mr Lord, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Lordship's despatch No. 132, of the 12th instant, in which Your Lordship requests me to inform the Turkish Government that as they have been unable to obtain compensation from the Behaihi for the murder of Sheikh Selman and other relatives of the Sheikh of Bahrein, His Majesty's Government enn no longer dissuade the Sheikh from resorting to such steps as he may think necessary for this purpose.I hesitate to act on these instructions until I hear whether the persons who were killed in the engagement of the offending tribe with the Turks, are or are cot the same who are accused of the murder of the Sheikh. If their identity is established, our only claim is a financial one, and I do not suppose His Majesty's Government would readily sanction a punitive expe dition which may possibly lead to serious trouble, for merely a pecuniary satis faction, some part of which may be extracted peacefully from the Ottoman Government. I have, etc.. N. R. O'CONOE. aNo. 143 of 1904. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. .FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. SECRET. External. To The Right Hon'ble St. JOHN BUODEICK, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Simla, the 11th August 1904. Sir, 'With reference to your telegram, dated the 17th May 1904, and in continuation of our telegraphic reply, dated the 17th June 1904, we have the honour to forward, for information, a copy of a report received from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, together with copies of certain connected papers, relative to the murder, in December 1900, of a party of Bahreinese near El Katif by the Behaih tribe. 2. Prom the details now furnished, it will be observed that the persons * sir n . o 'Conor 's despatch No. 116, dated reported, by the 'Wall of» Rasrah, to 23rd February 1904. have been killed in a fight at Zernaka between a Turkish convoy and Bin Mekiriah and his companions, were not those actually concerned in the murder of Sheikh Selman and his followers; and that the real perpetrators of the outrage are still at large, and presumably f Enclosure to Sir N. O'Conor's despatch No. 50, witMn Turkish jurisdiction. The COnten- dated 26th January 1902. tionf of the Governor Of Nejd that the murder was the outcome of animosity is also refuted. Mr. Gaskin's letter No. 219, dated the 12th December 1900, formed one of the enclosures to our Secret despatch No. 7, dated the 27th January 1901. A copy of his letter No. 9, dated the 27th January 1901, and also of Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball's letter No. 4 S. A., dated the 6th June 1902, in which the purport of Mr. Gaskin's references dated, Tespectively, the 3rd and 17th May 1902, was included, are now enclosed. 3. In view of the attitude adopted by Sheikh Isa in refusing to accept our advice in regard to the administration of his Customs revenues, we have deemed it advisable to withhold for the present from the Chief any inti mation regarding the concession which His Majesty's Government are pre pared to make to him in the matter of avenging himself on his enemies on the mainland, and we intend, with your approval, to make no communication to him on the subject pending the receipt of the orders of His Majesty's Govern ment on the proposals put forward in our Secret despatch No. 85, dated the 21st April 1904, for a revision of the arrangements for British representation at Manama.If there is likely to be delay in the issue of these orders, 'we would suggest that, in order to prevent the possibility of the Sheikh's case being prejudiced by delay, the fact of the murderers being still at large, and in Turkish territory apparently, might be brought to the notice of the Porte. As the Sheikh is precluded from proceeding against them while in that territory, the advisability of again pressing for the payment of pecuniary compensation mieht also be considered. We hare the honour to be, Sie, Your most obedient, humble servants, (Signed) AMPTHILL. „ KITCHENER. „ E. P.-G. LAW. » E. E.. ELLES. » A. T. ARUNDEL. DENZIL IBBETSON. H. EKLE EICHARDS.(Copy) deceived oh Zra October 7vith Political Secretary^ letter T T o.?8, aatea 16tli September 1904. India Office, 8th September 1904. Sir, In continuation o^ Sir ^oaley's letter of ZZm jTine last relative to steps to be taken in consequence of the inability o^ the Turkish authorities to punish the per petrators o^ the outrage on a relative o^ the Sheikh o^ Bahrein, I am airectea by ^.Secretary Broarick to en close, -^or T jora Lansaovvn? s information, a copy of a letter from the Government of Tnaia. It vvill be seen that for the reasons stated in the Sra paragraph of their letter, the Government of Inaia ao not propose to give the Sheikh of Bahrein authority to avenge homself pending the revised arrangements for their e representation at Bahrein Vvhich wre sanctioned in the Se- of State's despatch of Btih August last, and vvhich, it may be expected, Vvill be carried into effect shortly. Mr. Raskin's report of 11th June, however, categori cally denies the allegation that the guilty members of thethe Behaih tribe have since been billed in an engagement with the i ir&gt;s. Mr, Brodric 1 ^: 'woula, therefore, suggest that Sir . 0 f Conor shoula now be instructed again to approach the xnr\ish O-ovemaent on the subject, ana to warn them, in accor dance with the terms of 'Oora Lansaowne's despatch TT q . 13£ o ^ the l£th -April last, that if satisfactory reparation is not made by them without further procrastination, d.M. Govern ment will be unable to dissuade the Sheikh from taking the matter into his own hands. I have etc.. (sd) iU Walpole. Vhe Unaer becretary of State , foreign Office.con No: 5724 VB A copy of the foregoing communication is forv/aro- ed. to the Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf for infor mation, in continuation of the endorsement from the Government of India in the foreign department, No:5414 h/B•, dated the 10th October 1904. By order, etc.. sd 0. Somers Goc^s. Assistant Secretary to the O-overnment of India. j?'oreign department. bimla; 'ihe 2nd November 1904. ( ^opy ) enclosure in ^'.O. covering letter of September 27th, 1904. K foreign Office to bir N. O'Conor. No. ^3. September 24th, 1904. bir. V.ith reference to Your Excellency T s deBpatch No.236 cf April 19th, I transmit herewith copy of a letter fromfrom the India Office enclosing correspondence from the Govern ment of India on the subject of the murder of Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe. r ihe information obtained by the Officiating Pe si dent in the T* Persian riul^is to the effect that the persons who were reported by the Turkish Government in February last to have been killed in an encounter with Turkish troops were not those actually concerned in the outrage.but that on the contrary the offend ers are still at large in Turkish territory. T n view ot the continued failure of the Turkish Government to exact any reparation for the murders there seems no reason for further delaying the representation which Your Excellency was instructed to make in my despatch No.1^2 of April 12th , and which was to the effect that ii.M.Government can no longer restrain the Sheikh of Bahrein from resorting to such steps as he may thin 1 ' necessary for the purpose^though they will use their best endeavours to ensure that he shall take no action against the Behaih so long as that tribe remain in territory recognised as Turkish. I have accordingly to request that you will make the re presentation already proposed. T am, etc., ( M ) Omitted. No: /tyo'o of 1904 British Residency and Consulate General^- Bushire November 1904 A copy oi the foregoing correspondence is forwarded j or inf ormation to the Political Agent Bahrein in continuation ofp - — - India Office, London, 25th November 1904. Secret. No. 56 To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the Secret letter of your Excellency's Govern- Fersian Oulf: as to reparation men ^ i n the foreign Department, for the murder by the Behaih tribe dated 11th August last, No. 143, of a party of Bahreinese near El as to the murder of a party of Bahreinese near El Katif by the Behaih tribe, I forward herewith copies of correspondence* with the * To Foreign Office, dated 8th September ^ Oreign Oflicc on the subject. 1904. and'enclosure' date&lt;, ^ Sep '' ,,ber 1904 ' 2. It will be seen from the From ditto, dated iGth November 1904, despatch of 11 is Majesty's Charge and d'Affaires at Constantinople of the 26th October last, No. 832, that the Turkish Government have been informed that His Majesty's Government had a rig!it to expect that the Porte would make some more effectual attempt to bring the offenders to justice, and that otherwise they could not reasonably continue to restrain the Sheikh from taking the matter into his own hands. 3. In these circumstances His Majesty's Government do not desire to place any further restrictions on the Sheikh's liberty of action, provided that he does not attack the Behaih while they remain in territory recognised as Turkish. Should, however, tlie Turkish Government make a successful effort to bring the offenders to justice before the Behaih move down to the coast beyond the limits of Turkish territory, it will be necessary to advise the Sheikh to refrain from molesting them. 4. Having regard to what is said in the third paragraph of your letter of the 11th August as to the attitude of the Sheikh, I leave it to your Excellency to decide as to the moment when an intimation should be made to him in accordance with the conclusions arrived at by His Majesty's Government. 1 have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship's most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) St. John Brodrick. S. 58. t i w C'ENCLOSURES. Enclosure No. 1. India Office to Foreign Oflior, India Office, Sir, 8tli S j ptemher 1901. In continuation of Sir A. Godleys letter of 22nd June last relative to steps to be taken in tonsequence of the inability of the Turkish authorities to punish t^e perpetrators of the outrage on a relative of the Sheikh of Bahrein, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Brodrick to enclose, for L'ml Lansdovvne's information, a copy of a letter from the Government of India, No. 143, (Secret), dated 11th August 1904, and enclosures. It will he seen that, for the reasons stated in the third paragraph op their letter, the Government of India do not propose to give the Sheikh of Bahrein authority to avengo himself pending the revis-ed arrange ments for their representation at Bahrein which were sanctioned in the Secretary of State's Despatch of 5th August last. No. 33 (Secret), and which, it may be expected, will be carried into effect shortly. Mr. Gaskins report of ] lih June, however, categorically denies the allegation that the guilty members of the Behaih tribe have been since been killed in an engagement with the Turks. Mr. Biodrick would, therefore, suggest that Sir N. O 'Conor should now bo instructed again to approach the Turkish Government on the subject, and to warn them, in accordance with the terms of Lord Lansdowne's Despatch No. 132 of the 12th April last, that if satisfactory reparation is not made by them without further procrastination. His Majesty's Government will be unable to disuade the Sheikh from taking the matter inio his own hands. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State, Horace Walpole. Foreign Office. Enclosure No. 2. Foreign Office to India Office. Foreign Office, Sir, 27th September 1904. With reference to your letter of 8th September. I am directed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, the accompanying copy of a Despatch to His Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, relating to the murder of Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State F. A. Campbell. for India. S. 58.Annex. The Marquess of Lansdowne to Sir X. O'Conor. No. 338. Foreign Office, gir, 24th September 1904. With reference to your Excellency's Despatch, No. 286, of 19th April, I transmit herewith copy of a letter from the India Office enclosing correspondence from the Government of India on the subject of t he murder o^' Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe. The intormntion obtained hy the Officiating Resident in the Persian Gulf is to the effect that the persons who were reported by the Turkish Government in February last to have been killed in an encounter with Turkish troops were not those actually concerned in the outrage, but that on the contrary the offenders are still at large in Turkish territory. In view of the continued failure of the Turkish Government to exact any reparation for the murders, there seems no reason for further delaying the representation which your Excellency was instructed to make in my Despatch No. 132, of 12Lli April, and which was to the effect that His Majesty's Government can no longer restrain the Shpikh of Bahrein from resorting to such steps as he may think necessary for the purpose, though they will use their best endeavours to ensure that he shall take no action against the Behaih so long as that tribe remain in territory recognised as Turkish. I have accordingly to rv'quest that you will make the representation already proposed. I am, &amp;c., His Excellency the Right Hon. Lansdowne. Sir N. O'Conor, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. Enclosure No. 3. Foreign Office to India Office. Foreign Office, Sir, 16th November 1904. I am directed by the Marquess of Lansdowne to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, copy of a Despatch from His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at Constantinople relative to the murder of Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe. Mr. Brodrick wili observe that Mr. Townley has warned the Porte that His Majesty's Goverment can no longer reasonably continue to restrain the Sheikh from taking steps to exact his own measures of reparation, though, should the Turkish Government make a successful effort to bring the offenders to justice before the tribe moves down to the coast, it may still be possible to recommend the Sheikh to hold his hand. Lord Lansdowne would, however, suggest that the Government of India should now bo informed that His Majesty's Government do not desire to place any further restrictions on the Sheikh's liberty of action on condition that he does not attack the tribe while they remain in territory recognised as Turkish. His Lordship also proposes to approve Mr. Townley's language as reported in his Despatch. I am, &amp;c.. The Under Secretary of State E. Gorst. for India.Annex. Mr. Townley to the Marquess of Lansdowne. No. 832. My Lord, 26th October ]904. Constantinople, With reference to your Lordship's Despatch No. 338, of 24th September respecting the murder of Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe, I have the honour to report that I have informed the Minister for Foreign Affairs that the statements furnished by the Government of India entirely dispose of the assertions of the local authorities in regard to the alleged fate of all the assailants of Sheikh Selman. I also presented him with a memorandum containing the information with which the Embassy was now in a position to supply his Excellency, concerning the names of the leaders of the assault, and other particulars mentioned in Mr. Gaskin's letter to Major Cox of 11th June. I added that the British Government had a right to expect that the Porte, with these details in its possession, would make some more effectual attempt to bring the offenders to justice, otherwise we could not reasonably continue to restrain the Sheikh from taking the matter into his own hands. The Marquess of Lansdowne, K.G., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. I have, &amp;c., Walter Townley.6 (Received on 16th January 1905 with Political Secretary's letter flo. 53, dated 30th December 1904.) VERSIA AND ARABIA. [12th December.] CONFIDKNTIAL . Section 3 t No. 1. Mk. Townley to the Marquess of Lansdownb. —(Received 12th December). Constantinople, 6th December 1904. (No. 942) My Lord, With reference to ray Despatch No. 832 of the 26th October, respecting the murder of certain Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe, I have the honour to transmit herewith copy of a Memorandum by Mr, Marinitsch, Acting First Dragoman, showing the steps taken by the Porte to give effect to my representations. The measures reported scarcely seem to have advanced matters much, or to offer any speedy prospect of tbe required redress being obtained. I have, etc., WALTER TOWNLEY. Inclosure in No. 1. Memorandum by Mr. Mabiniisch. [ Foreign Office Despatch No. 888 of 24th September iPOiJ Constantinople, 6th December 1904. With reference to the murder of Sheikh Selman and his followers, I have the honour to report that the Meraorandura drawn up on the last information supplied to the Government of India, which Mr. Lamb presented to the Minister for Foreign Affairs (see his Memorandum No. 348 of the 20th October 1904), was referred to the consideration of the Minister of the Interior. I have had several interviews on this matter with Memdouk Pasha, and I did not fail to impress upon His Excellency the necessity of having this affair brought to a satisfactory solution, the mora so as the fresh information now supplied by the Government of India to this Embassy, and communicated by the latter to the Sublime Porte, will, no doubt, facilitate the action of the local authorities. His Excellency Memdouk Pasha, taking into consideration tbe fact that the Vali of Bussorah had just reached his post, thought it advisable, in order to acquaint him with the details of this affair, to instruct Talib Bey, the ex- Mutessarif of Nejd, who is at present in Constantinople, to draw up a full report on it, expressing, at the same time, his personal views on the matter. Talib Bey has already presented his report to His Excellency. It seems that in Talib Bey's opinion it will be almost impossible to seize the remaining culprits owing to the nomad habits of the Behaih tribe. Talib Bey thinks that the amount claimed as pecuniary compensation for the plundered property is exaggerated, as the murdered Sheikh and his followers were merely on a shooting trip and could not, therefore, have brought with them so much luggage. The Minister of the Interior did not indorse Talib Bey's statements ; he has simply mentioned them to me for the information of His Majesty's 4088 f. d.i' ftt- tv, Embassy. On the contrary, His Excellency requested me to give full assurances to His Majesty's Embassy to the effect that he will continue to use his best eliorts with a view to having those who are implicated in these murders arrested and punished. His Excellency is, however, afraid thai tlie measures to be taken by the Turkish authorities to thafend will prove abortive, owin- to the lack of proper means of communication between Bussorah and the Sandjak of ^ejd, which is at so great a distance. Memdouk Pasha called my attention to the inconsistency, from the point ot view both of the Sheri and the criminal Jaws, of the demand of the Sheikh o ahrein to the effect that three of the principal men concerned in these outrages should be executed in satisfaction for the lives ot Sheikh Salman his son Diaij, and his nephew Abdur Rahman-ibn-Beshid, for whose murder the L/Diet cannot accept compensation. t&gt; i ,^ 9 Excellen cy's opinion, owning to the wandering nature of the Behaih tribesmen, there will be no possibility whatsoever of obtaining evidence as the witnesses who should be called before the Court will never appear. m fetter now addressed to the Vali of Bussorah, His Excellency Memdouk Pasha laid stress on the fact that the local authorities should try to lay hands on the culprits when the tribesmen next come, as they usuallv do vilayet ^ ear purpose of exchanging products, close to the limits of the . In conclusion, the Minister of the Interior stated to me that under present circumstances he was unable to give categorical instructions to the Vali but ie has directed him to make fresh and full enquiries into this matter and to S dec™ ' 8 iBVCStisati0nS ' in OTder tbat tlle Sublime foke my H. MARINITSCH. rrt. A ^ // ■ 2. I*; &lt;?• A; : 4iXtS0 O I. 0. P. 0.—No. 4088 I. 0.-27.1.1805,-85.—W. IVC. 183 &amp; &lt;4iix i i.j.lr- jat A1 . orr^ fio :wc aUbsldizei to a saall e:: by the Tur^lah CHyvcraamt for the sAfe-paasag-e their rmci it mmt ujifrt-ioi^b pi'foaujiiably be j^ec^arded as ?uri!:lah territory, .It rfc:Tiats,therefore,that If the Ohlef of iJa'irela. is penalttort to send pja exnedltlon gainst the I!eh?&gt;dh on the aainl'md, it -.fill either be operating on iMtiittedly utar'slaJi soil or else in Katar # f«id in tho latter oase the question of thu status of that Peninsula will pro bably beoone aoout^.ly and prs'ip.turely proiainent. In my hunihle opinion the ■neniission vrtiich His Majesty's Oovemnent oonteaplate erantinpr to Sheikh Bsa to taice Iiia oi,n. aeaaures for revtsorring hiaself shoxild empha*- tloally be vrltWield. I hwe endeavoured to ahow that the three outrages ten. ah. have already occurred are wi* all inoi dents ox' the one feud, a Jid if the next ^preasive action is taken by tho BPhreini3 ,it will be inposalble to put a Unit upon the ovila vrtiich may enarie. The B-Jireinia* in conaequtnce of their commercial oonrection with Hofuf an Katif are always in a vulnerable position whilst the Behalh are e .Tbreaely difficult to touch when guard, and .moreover,jud^inf? frou j-ay observations of the condttot of '.'■neikh l^sa 's •soldiers* in ray f.m recent little orpeditions after the pirate Ahraed bin Belunn, I believe tJiat whilst a fair fight would be avoided to tho utinost ©JTbont of their novffT' a number ot jt orders of innocent persons would quite poasibly ressilt TJhioh wo^Ald involve the Chief in difficul ties of sp'ch greater mra^itude. 7 * TTufkish aoverment have Bxpued that the Bahrei- nis f&gt;Teentitled to no conaideration^beoause they landed on 'ttifrish soil iidthout penAission and with arms in their hand r Th^ (the Torka)profeas to rep-&gt;xd the Arab tribal law, wfolc • the lii*6 o.t 021© rienbox* of 'the fv^prossivo tribe to he taken In rerenre for the life of a wrlher of another tribe, reg^cllesa of the question -whether the indi vidual la rxdlty or Inrocent^no inconsistent with the Islatulo Code nnci the orlnln«a laws of tho Knptre, They have pointed oTrt that ^helltfi PaaMct ^ln I uiareh ajicl Ms clicr soFi, vmre theiaaelves killed in th© att^ok tip on the 4— '■vmm f Bahrein! s # 3# l ore luportanti than t&amp;ese points^I think, are the yts facte that vftien the flr^t Asaaarl was killed by the Behaih, ^singular:of Ammra 7 no application for redress was rnade to the Residency by the Chief of Bahrtiizit^d that if the retaliatory z rorder 01 SheilcJi v ?.aahid # s son xms coraiuitted T/lthout the knowledge of Sheikh Hsa#whioh I conaider very doubtful ,ro Gi r iii3 of disapproval vrerv at ar^ rate after*- Ivif wtwdQ otproaaed by him at sub.lecti^ ^ction^ 9* In these oirotaastajaces,I do not thj.nJr it is neces^j^ry that aiho ild sixnport the CJhief in his demnd for the ©xeoutloa of three £mr&amp; hap-haaardly aeleoted aei;^ bers of the Behaih or for their surrender to hiaw I am dontt- ftil ivhether -re ahmild press for the full peoi^niary coi r r^en- sat ion denuded,but if this is done the mount — adding 2400 dollars (I W60/~) for the il/vcc of the Tliief's orm 3 relatives — would be l &gt;.- T 58,5(X)/-, md I tliinJc that t3ie prompt pejMPent of this # or any lesser siua rtiloh zi% r he con sidered suitable, should be demanded of the Turkish Govern ment in firm Iwnmpe# 10 ♦ 'The attitude of Sheikh 'sa hiiaself towards the Bedouin of the mini wl in ry opinion ia rsost weak ejad im- satisfactory• »vexy year hundreds of Hajlr and A1 lorra,besides the ITayixii of Katar, cross over to the Islands to draw their annual subsidies and f presents' fiXEa yet the Chief,pnd A of the it-m sections of the 3eni Hajlr^SheiMi Ifasir bin Jlibarak A1 Abdallah is now generally i^eco&amp;rdsed as the leader of the Mal:hadthdthaba in virtue of his nother having been the daughter of a fomer Sheikh, and Ahned bin Sali!U%n,tliA pirate, lives for oi 3 ht nonths of tlie year in the encampmen't of the A1 J ?iJhar^\ad,having laarried the sister of their Ohiefi. If all the Beni I^jir and the numerous sections of t^ie A1 Uorr^h. were rigorously forbidden to visit Bahrein until Bom suita le treatment had been raeted out to the members of their tribes ^md the other persons rrhom they :xarboured,who ' T 6ro kTJo^w. to be Bheikh Bsa f s ene£.iies,a nuch XTK)re satisfactory condition of affairs would be inaugurated for--Jiafereijs ' ifor Bajfirein# At the present* hovrever$ tlio CSxiof# apart from Ms uniTillliignosa to adopt t^xia line of 9xroion # would probably find it iinpoasible to eiri'orof. sucli a prohlMtioh v/ithoTit onr Msistance^as his penuanent anied followers arc so few in nurriber. Before leaving thia subject I xaentio^t as inst^aioe of Sheikh that a few v/eeks aco v?hen the KEdSHaalcaa of Katif was ^©arohii^g for all the i^erabers of the A1 Iraliaiaiaad Sheiiih^ f^dl^* wit&amp; a viow to putting pressure upon then to deliver Ahaed bin Selmtm,the son of one of the arrastod aen and a cousin by mrriag© of the pirate leader fled to Bahrein for safety and reid^-ined hero openly for a few d^s f thoW;;h he had disappuared again before I heard of his visit# This xoan Kamd bin Taaui# apparently has contrived to ingratiate hixuself with the Chi of and is always given a welcorae 'to these Islands# 11 • To revert to the question of the Behaih bloods feudal believe that ordinarily the ^ii^lest xaetliod of re pressing such an affair is to extort a heavy guarantee or a nunber of hostac^-s fron bo'Ui partiea for the future min- tenanoe of the peaoe# In the oaae of Bahrain maah a course is not necessary# as there is no likelihood of any of the Behoih visiting Sheikh Slaa 1 » territories Miile the feud l.asts# I would reoo c ...r. I # liovrever f tliat the Turkish Govemnent be requested to take sorae auch action in regard to the Behaih and that if they declare their inability to do 30 .^nd aIi»o mkm ary delay in paying- the oojapcnsa/tion^tixey % s'nouia be tpld that in tJio olZHsuostaaoea doclino acs' longer to rococnize tho euberdlaatlffla of the iAhaliaran tribtia to tiu. Eaaa CJovuiTOoent*Rmi th»,t we will tak# our ovm iaeaaxiros for doaling vdth thaa ilireot, I believe that by an effective blockade of the l^thaharaa and Katar Coasts for oOiae ijontlis,so a» to prevent all Bedouin cabling to Bahrein or ^oin^ to the pearl-b &gt; jx!cs we could cause a very heavy pecuniary loas 'bo the tribes and would probably re duce- them to a nore genuine subndssion thf\n has ever been done before#[Confidential.] No. 431, dated Bushire, the gth (received 18th) September 1905. From— imajor P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—S. M. Fraser, Esq., C .I.E., Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. I have the honour to submit, for the consideration of the Government of India, copy of a report which I have received Bahrein No. 279, dated 2l3t August 1905' from t^poKtical Agent, Bahrein, with reference to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department endorsement No. 416-E. B., dated the 31st January 1905, to my address, on the subject of Sheikh Esa's blood-feud with the Behaih tribe. 2. A study of the question has brought Captain Prideaux to the following conclusions :— (a) That if Sheikh Esa is now given the free hand, hitherto withheld, to exact reparation from the Behaih himself, he must necessarily violate territory under Turkish influence in the process, or raise the question of the status of Katar in an acute form. (^) That reprisals on Sheikh Esa's part if effective will further aggravate the existing feud. (c) That judging by recent experience, it is doubtful whether his men would face any serious fighting. They would more probably do no more than murder a few innocent people. For these reasons he deprecates the grant of permission to Sheikh Esa to settle accounts with the Behaih in his own way. 3. As an alternative he suggests that we should press the Porte energetically on the Sheikh's behalf for pecuniary compensation and demand prompt payment of the Rs. 38,500 due. This amount includes Rs. 2,400 dollars blood money for the lives of Sheikh Esa's three relations; a form of relief which the Sheikh has hitherto declined to accept but which, I understand the Political Agent to suggest, should be pressed on him. If that is his meaning, I concur on this latter point, as, if the settlement is arranged through our intermediation, the delivery of three Behaih to Sheikh Esa for execution does not commend itself to me. 4. Reverting to the discussion of possible measures for the termination of the feud, Captain Prideaux recommends that the Turkish authorities be called upon to intern for a time several of the Behaih, as a guarantee for the future good behaviour of the tribe, and suggests that if the Porte expresses its inability to take this course and at the same time delays payment of the compensation demanded, we should retaliate by declining to recognise any claim on its part to exercise jurisdiction in the maritime tract between Salwa Bay and Katif (and also presumably in the Katar peninsula except at A1 Bidaa (P. Z. C.)), and should notify our intention to take measures to deal with the tribes direct, prefer ably by the institution of a blockade of the Dthaharan and Katar Coasts. 5. In forwarding the Political Agent's communication, I venture to offer a few observations in comment of it. If Sheikh Esa is allowed to take his own measures for exacting reparation from the Behaih, Captain Prideaux holds that he must necessarily operate ' on admittedly Turkish soil, or else in Katar, etc.,' as the Dthaharan Coast tract between Salwa Bay and Katif is frequented by tribes ' who are subsidised to a small extent by the Turkish Government lor the safe passage of their mails, and must therefore presumably he regarded as Turkish territory. ' If this be accepted, the stipulation imposed by His Majesty's Government that Turkish territory must not be violated, would render nugatory any per mission given to Sheikh E^a to exact his own revenge.7 I am doubtful however as to the correctness of this view. We have never, I think, recognised Turkish jurisdiction over this Dthaharan Foreign Office to India Office of 8th February tract, at all events Up i O February 1904 1904. Received with Foreign Department No. (vide the reference manjinallv noted) : ^s-e a., dated 28th march 1904. although on the other hand I notice that in the Military Report on Arabia published by the General Staff of the War Office in December 1904, the tract in question is included in territory under Turkish jurisdiction, whereas the Katar Peninsula is excluded ; but this ex position is doubtless not authoritative. Furthermore, in a later communication which I have just received from Bahrein No. 304, dated the 2nd September 1905. him and am forwarding separately, the Political Agent refers to the authority of the Turks in Dthaharan as only nominal and reiterates his recommendation that we should ourselves take action against the tribes. I think this latter view regarding the Dthaharan tract is the correct one, and if it is accepted as such, then the objection to Sheikh Esa taking his own measures for vengeance for fear of the violation of Turkish territory, loses most of its force. 6. At the same time, both from the point of view of our own prestige and having regard to the latent possibility that Sheikh Esa's embarkation upon measures of reprisal may result in an indefinite prolongation of the vendetta, I incline to the opinion that it would be much better for us to insist on payment of compensation by the Porte, and failing compliance, to take the matter into our own hands and deal with the tribes ourselves ; a course which will be in itself a challenge to Turkish pretensions on the Dthaharan Coast, and an ex posure of the Porte's inability to exercise jurisdiction effectively, even if it possessed the title. The obstructive apathy and impotence of the Turkish authorities seem to afford ample justification for any action that would bring the matter to a settle ment, but whether the pursuit of either of the courses above mentioned is prac ticable at the present time, depends upon the policy of His Majesty's Government, and is therefore a problem beyond my province to discuss. In any case, I fear that the blockade of the Dthaharan and Katar Coasts suggested by the Political Agent cannot be regarded as practically possible without a large increase of our Naval resources in the Gulf. One thing, however, cannot, I submit, be gainsaid and that is, that if we have any regard for our interests and prestige among the inhabitants of the Arab Coast, we cannot afford to be trifled with by the Ottoman Government any longer, and are bound to take effective steps to insure that Sheikh Esa's grievance is redressed in some form without further delay. No. 279, dated Bahrein, the 2i3t August 1905. From— Captain F. B. Prideaux, Political Agent, Bahrein, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to refer to correspondence ending with your office endorsement No. 208, dated the 14th February 1905, on the subject of the blood- feud between the people of Bahrein and the Behaih section of the A1 Morra tribe, and to submit for consideration the following observations. 2. In the first place I would point out that the account given in Mr Gaskin's letter No. 178, dated the 24th August 1902, to Colonel Kemball's address, is apparently not quite accurate in some respects, as I have interrogated Sheikh Esa regarding the circumstances of the Behaih Sheikh's visit to Bahrein, and his reply seems to show that as far as the feud between the Behaih and the Amamara was concerned the advantage remained with the latter even after Sheikh Rashid bin Muqareh had returned to the mainland.3. Sheikh Esa has informed me that Sheikh Rashid, the Behaih Chief, came over to Bahrein about 3 months after the retaliatory attack made by the three Amamara on Sheikh Rashid's young son, with a view to getting satis faction from the Chief for the boy's murder. Presumably he did not consider that Amamara were justified in visiting upon his own family their vengeance for the act of his four tribesmen, and professing for the time being to regard himself as one of Sheikh Esa's subsidized feudatories he appealed to him for the punishment of the guilty Amamara. One of whom at least was and is still a trusted servant of the Bahrein Chief, 4. Sheikh Esa says ' I told Sheikh Rashid that his son was murdered for the blood of Abdallah AI Mutawwa of the Amamara tribe, that the two tribes should settle their feud amongst themselves, and that the matter was no con cern of mine. If, however, Sheikh Rashid would abandon the feud, it would be so much the better. Sheikh Rashid replied that he had only peaceful inten tions. I then gave him as a token of my friendship a horse worth 600 dollars and cash and other things to the value of 200 dollars. This gift was in no way connected with the blood-feud between the Behaih and the Amamara. Bin Muqareh promised to continue loyal and friendly to me and went away apparent ly quite satisfied. His subsequent action proved his insincerity.' From this account it is not difficult to understand that Sheikh Rashid must have been chagrined at Sheikh Esa's refusal to punish the Amamara, his subjects, and that the Bahrein Chief's gift was made chiefly in connection with his foolish custom of subsidizing the mainland Bedouin whenever they come to the Islands to renew their assurances of loyalty and service. Sheikh Rashid no doubt saw the wisdom of dissembling his dissatisfaction while in Bahrein, but it is not surprising that he should have left, determined in his mind to wreak vengeance in future upon any of the people of Bahrein who should fall into his hands, and the more nearly connected they might be to the Chief the greater satisfaction would be his. 5. In the course of my recent work connected with the Persian Gulf Gazetteer, so far as it relates to this Agency, I have satisfied myself that the southern boundary of the Katar Peninsula is regarded by all the Arabs as a fairly straight line from Salwa at the Apex of the Gulf of Bahrein on the west to the Khor al Odeid on the east, passing one well-known well named Saqaq about midway between these two points. The whole of the country north of the Salwa Apex as far as the Katif Oasis is known as Dthaharan, and this District as well the country due south of Katar up to the Oman border is frequented only by tribes, the Ejman, Beni Hajir and Al Morra, who are subsidized to a small extent by the Turkish Government for the safe passage of their mails, and it must therefore presumably be regarded as Turkish territory. It results, therefore, that if the Chief of Bahrein is permitted to send an expedition against the Behaih on the mainland, it will either be operating on admittedly Turkish soil or else in Katar and in the latter case the question of the status of that Peninsula will probably become acutely and prematurely prominent. 6. In my humble opinion the permission which His Majesty's Government contemplate granting to Sheikh Esa to take his own measures for revenging him self should emphatically be withheld. I have endeavoured to show that the three outrages which have already occurred are all incidents of the one feud, and if the next aggressive action is taken by the Bahreinis, it will be impossible to put a limit upon the evils which may ensue. The Bahreinis, in consequence of their commercial connection with Hofuf and Katif, are always in a vulnerable position whilst the Behaih are extremely difficult to touch when on their guard, and moreover, judging from my observations of the conduct of Sheikh Esa's 'soldiers' in my two recent little expeditions after the pirate Ahmed bin Selman, I believe that whilst a fair fight would be avoided to the utmost extent of their power a number of murders of innocent persons would quite pos sibly result which would involve the Chief in difficulties of much greater magni tude. 7. The Turkish Government have argued that the Bahreinis are entitled to no consideration, because they landed on Turkish soil without permission and with arms in their hands.They (the Turks) profess to regard the Arab tribal law, which permits the life of any one member of the aggressive tribe to be taken in revenge for the life of a member of another tribe, regardless of the question whether the indi vidual is guilty or innocent, as inconsistent with the Islamic Code and the criminal laws of the Empire. They have also pointed out that Sheikh Rashid bin Muqareh and his elder son were themselves killed in the attack upon the Bahreinis. 8. More important than those points, I think, are the facts that when * singular Of Am.nwa, the firs l t . Ammari* was killed by the Behaih, no application for redress was made to the Residency by the Chief of Bahrein, and that if the retaliatory murder of Sheikh Rashid's son was committed without the knowledge of Sheikh Esa, which I consider very doubtful, no signs of disapproval were at any rate afterwards ex pressed by him at his subject's action. 9. In these circumstances, I do not think it is necessary that we should support the Chief in his demand for the execution of three more haphazardly selected members of the Behaih or for their surrender to him. I am doubtful whether we should press for the full pecuniary compensation demanded, but if this is done the amount adding 2,400 dollars (Rs. 3,360) for the lives of the Chief's own 3 relatives would be Rs. 38,500, and I think that the prompt payment of this, or any lesser sum which may be considered suitable, should be demanded of the Turkish Government in firm language. 10. The attitude of Sheikh Esa himself towards the Bedouin of the mainland in my opinion is most weak and unsatisfactory. Every year hundreds of Ejman Beni Hajir and A1 Morra, besides the Nayim of Katar, cross over to the Islands to draw their annual subsidies and 'presents' from the Chief, and yet of the two sections of the Beni Hajir, Sheikh Nasir bin Mubarak A1 Abdallah is now generally recognised as the leader of the Makhadthdthaba in virtue of his mother having bf»en the daughter of a former Sheikh, and Ahmed bin Selman, the pirate, lives for eight months of the year in the encampment of the A1 Muhammad, having married the sister of their Chief. If all the Beni Hajir and the numerous sections of the A1 Morrah were rigorously forbidden to visit Bahrein until some suitable treatment had been meted out to the members of their tribes and the other persons whom they harboured, who were known to be Sheikh Esa's enemies a much more satisfac tory condition of affairs would be inaugurated for Bahrein. At the present time, however, the Chief, apart from his unwillingness to adopt this line of action would probably find it impossible to enforce such a prohibition without our assistance, as his permanent armed followers are so few in number. Before leaving this subject I may mention as an instance of Sheikh Esa's weakness that a few weeks ago when the Kaim-makam of Katif was searching for all the members of the A1 Muhammad Sheikh^ family with a view to putting pressure upon them to deliver up Ahmed bin Selman, the son of one of the arrested men and a cousin by marriage of the pirate leader fled to Bahrein for safety and re mained here openly for a few days, though he had disappeared again before I heard of his visit. This man, Hamad bin Tami, apparently has contrived to ingratiate himself with the Chief and is always given a welcome to these Islands. 11. To revert to the question of the Behaih blood-feud, I believe that ordi narily the simplest method of repressing such an affair is to extort a heavy guarantee or a number of hostages from both parties for the future maintenance of the peace. In the case of Bahrein such a course is not necessary, as there is no likelihood of any of the Behaih visiting Sheikh Esa's territories while the feud last. 1 would recommend, however, that the Turkish Government be re quested to take some such action in regard to the Behaih and that if they declare their inability to do so and also make any delay in paying the compensation, they should be told that in the circumstances we decline any longer to recognize the subordination of the Dthaharan tribes to the Hasa Government, and that we will take our own measures for dealing with them direct. 1 believe that by an effective blockade of the Dthaharan and Katar Coasts for some months, so as to prevent all Bedouin coming to Bahrein or going to the pearl-banks' we could cause a very heavy pecuniary loss to the tribes and would probably reduce them to a more genuine submission than has ever been done before. G. C. PrtM, Simli.—No. C. 490 F. D.—27-9-05 67—R. S. W.For of 1906. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, January 1906, V « Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for in- . formation, with reference to his' letter To:279 dated 21st August 1905. Ey Order, Jj t 'Li Lieutt: Second Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Crulf. despatch to the Secretary of State for India, I T o;2 External ■Hated 4th January 1906. I &lt;&lt; nNo. 2 of 1906. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. EXTERNAL. To T he R ight H on'ble JOHN MORLEY, O.M., His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. F ort W illiam, the 4th January 1906. S ir, We have the honour to transmit to you copies of a despatch* from the • No. 43i, dated the 9th September iocs. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf together with previous correspondence as 19 ?^ r ,. , ^ n , marked in the margin relating to the Pereion OuTf, No' 107! I 116811011 of obtaining reparation for the 1905 with enclosures. murder of certain Bahreinis by members (3) Letter from the Political Resident in the nf tliP H o I iqi 'V i fr-i'Vi/i «« ^ ' i i Persian Gulf, No. 432, dated the 10th September . litliaill triDC On the mainland 1905, with enclosures. opposite the island of Bahrein. The Political^gent at Bahrein has examined the question afresh in view of its more recent developments, and it will be seen from his report to Major Cox that he has arrived at the following conclusions:— (a) That if Sheikh Esa is now given the free hand, hitherto withheld, to exact reparation from the Behaih himself, he must necessarily violate territory under Turkish influence in the process, or raise the question of the status of El Katr in an acute lorm. {h) That reprisals on Sheikh Esa's part, if effective, will further aggravate the existing feud. {c) That judging by recent experience, it is doubtful whether the latter's men would face any serious fighting. They would more probably do no more than murder a few innocent people. For these reasons he deprecates the grant of permission to Sheikh Esa to settle accounts with the Behaih accordicg 10 his own ideas. As an alternative he suggests that we should press the Porte energetically on the Sheikh's behalf for pecuniary compensation and demand prompt payment of the Rs. 38,600 due. This amount includes Rs. 2,400 dollars blood-money for the lives of Sheikh Esa's three relations; a form of relief which the Sheikh has hitherto declined to accept, but which the Political Agent apparently suggests should be pressed on him. Captain Prideaux also recommends that the TuHdsh authorities be called upon to intern for a time several of the Behaih, as a guarantee for the future good behaviour of the tribe, and suggests that, if the yw I^orte expresses its iuability to take this course and at the same time delays pay ment of the compensation demanded, we should retaliate by declining to recog nise any claim on their part to exercise jurisdiction in the maritime tract between Sal wa Bay and Katif and also presumably in the Katar peninsula x except at A1 Bidaa ; and that we should notify our intention to take measures to deal with the tribes direct, preferably by the institution of a blockade of the Dthaharan and. Katar coasts. Major Cox substantially concurs in Captain Prideaux's recommendations except as regards the proposed blockade of the Dthaharan and Katar coasts;that is, ho considers that wo should insist on payment of compensation by the Porte, and failing compliance, take the matter into our own hands and deal with the tribes ourselves; and he considers that such a course will be in itself a challenge to Turkish pretensions on the Dthaharan coast, and an exposure of the Porte's inability to exercise jurisdiction there effectively, whatever their rights de jure may be. The present matter has now been the subject of negotiation with the Turkish Government for five years without any practical advance having been made towards the reparation to which the Sheikh of Bahrein is entitled; and it appears to us that an effort should now be made to effect a final settlement of some kind in one direction or another. It will perhaps be advisable at this stage to review the pros and cons in regard to the policy that should be adopted. On the one hand, we are in the position of having already taken up the case at Constantinople with the knowledge of the officials and local Chiefs, includ ing the Sheikh of Bahrein. Due regard must of course be paid to Major Cox's and Captain Prideaux's views, both owing to their intrinsic force and to their being put forward by the officers on the spot, who should be speciallv qualified to express an opinion on what the effects of our attitude on local British prestige are likely to be. It is no doubt highly desirable not only to impress Sheikh Esa witn a sense of the value of our protection, but also to make the Turkish officials on the mainland feel that we take our position seriously as protecting Power over Bahrein, and will hold them responsible for injury caused to the subjects of the protected Sheikh by Arabs over whom they claim to exercise authority. On the other hand, it is becoming increasingly clear that the permission which we are authorised to give for the Sheikh to exact reparation himself would be practically useless by reason of the proviso that he must not enter Ottoman territory./ We understand that the tribe but rarely quits Turkish territory to wander in El Katr ; and even if an attack were organised on the occasion of one of the Behaih's infrequent visits to the promontory, they would probably have little difficulty in escaping into Turkish territory, before punishment could be inflicted. It will be seen, moreover, that the Political Agent is more than doubtful of the wisdom of attempting or permitting reprisals. In the light of the fresh information now supplied, it would appear that the murder of the Bahreinis by the Behaih was one of three outrages which were all incidents of one feud, and apart from the fact that we have hitherto espoused the cause of Sheikh Esa as one deserving of reparation, it is not clear that the case belongs to a class which calls for the active intervention of the British Government. In such a quarrel it might be considered alike impolitic to grant the Sheikh our sanction to revenge himself in debateable territory (thereby making ourselves responsible for his action) ; or to press the Turkish Government further either to exact punishment which clearly lies beyond their power; or to give compensation, which they have a reasonable case for refusing. Though such a solution would not perhaps be very satisfactory, it is arguable that we had better now accept the Turkish assertion (which is no more capable of disproof than of proof) that 37 out of the 60 individuals have been accounted for, tell the Sheikh that we are not prepared to press the Turks to take any further action in the case of an outrage arising out of a tribal feud, and advise him that the further remedy lies in his own hands (as pointed out by Captain Prideaux) by'the exclusion from Bahrein of members of any tribes'which are in a position to exercise pressure upon the Behaih with a view to their coming to a settlement. To come to the other suggestions of the local officers, we consider that our interest in the affair is so trifling as to place beyond the range of serious consideration Major Cox's suggestion that we should take the matter into our own hands and deal with the tribes ourselves, as well as Captain Prideaux's scheme for a blockade of the Dthaharan and Katar coasts. Moreover, it appears to us doubtful whether Major Cox does not overrate the effects upon our prestige and interests of inaction in a case which the inhabitants of the Arab coast must recognise to be a blood-feud between two tribes, and not in any way an outrage by the Turks against the British Government.After carefully considering all these points we have arrived at the conclusion that there are two possible alternatives: (1) to press for compensation from the Porte; (2) to drop the case. The other proposed courses of action may, in our opinion, be ruled out as impracticable. Unless therefore His Majesty's Government are prepared to press the claim for compensation at Constantinople, we do not propose to pursue the matter any further so far as the Turks are directly concerned. We have the honour to be, S ib, Your most obedient, humble servants, (Signed) MINTO. ^ KITCHENER. A. T. ARUNDEL. DENZ1L IBBETSON. H. ERLE RICHARDS. J. P. HEWETT. E. N. BAKER. C. H. SCOTT.'J 0 B ushire. Nov ember i.on 6 . /W i - A// to*#icL J £ ocsf j Please refer to this office endorse ment Mo: 16?7 of 17th July 1906. It does not appear from the records in this office that a copy of Resident's letter No: 497 of Frd March 1906 has as yet been forwarded to you. I therefore enclose a printed copy of the same for your information. T 'ith reference to the enclosures to the Govt, of India's letter forwarded to you under the endorsement above quoted, I am directed to inform you, that though Mr. Morley 1 s despatch Ho: 10 dated 16th March 1906 is not es pecially a reply to the Resident's letter No: 497 dated r^rd March 1906, still in view of the fact that it was for warded by the Government of India for guidance with refer ence to that letter, it must be assumed that the views ex pressed in Mr. Morley's despatch are final and that no further communication on the subject is now to be expected. Captain i? ; . B. Prideaux, I.A. , % Political Agent, Bahrein. SWsJty J* at ^5No. 497, dated Bushire, the 8rd (received 13tb) March 1906 (Confidential). From— M ajor P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department endorsement No. 136, dated 12th January 1906, on the subject of the murder of Sheikh Selman by Behaih tribesmen. It will be seen from the account of my recent interview with the Sheikh of Bahrein (letter No. 74 of 25th ultimo), that it was our action in connection with this case which was the first subject advanced by the latter in the light of a grievance. 2. Presuming that His Majesty's Secretary of State will endorse the views expressed by the Government of India in Government of India to India Officp, No. 2 of 4th ^hc last few lines of tbeir despatch January 1906. marginally noted, I understand the position to be that the final disposal of the case may now be considered to rest between the Government of India and Sheikh Esa, and that the former contem plate informing the ruler of Bahrein that in view of the explanations furnished by the Turkish Authorities, which cannot be disproved, they are not prepared to press the case further, as against the Porte, either in the direction of obtain ing compensation or any other form of redress. It is not altogether clear to me, however, whether having made this inti mation, Government are still prepared to consider the question of leaving Sheikh Esa free to take such measures as may seem to him suitable, or whether they would specifically restrict him to the course suggested by Captain Prideaux, namely, that of excluding from Bahrein members of any tribes which are in a position to exercise pressure upon the Behaih with a view to their coming to a settlement. I have frequently seen a course somewhat parallel to this resorted to in Somaliland, in cases where one refractory tribe, debarred from the amenities of the Port has clandestinely sent its trade-goods through, or has been furnished with supplies by, a tribe not under the ban; pressure being then put on the latter. This, however was under a well-organised administration by British officers. I much doubt whether such a course could be effectively worked in Bahrein under existing conditions, nor do I think that advice tendered to him in this direction would be acted upon by Sheikh Esa or would in any way remove the grievance which he now nurses in connection with this case. On the other hand, the Sheikh would have no colourable grounds for further complaint if our restrictions on his own liberty of action were with drawn, for it is primarily this that he has himself solicited. 3. In this connection I respectfully invite reference to the observations recorded in paragraph 5 of my letter No. 431 of 9th September 1905, in which I expressed^ some dissent from Captain Prideaux's conclusions as to what is admittedly Turkish territory. In dealing with these papers the Government of India made no special comment upon this point, but in any case I do not think I shall be guilty of inconsistency if I ventured to recommend a reversion to the course proposed in the letter from the India Office to the Foreign Office dated 24th August 1905. 4. There is one other seemingly practicable course which, I think, would be worth a trial, if it does not conflict with views held by the Government of India as to the inexpediency of our having direct dealings with the Behaih our selves, and that is that the Political Agent should be authorised to send a representative to the Behaih Sheikhs concerned under the safe conduct of some neutral Sheikh, with a view to the arrangement of a meeting of influential representatives of the tribes, party to the vendetta, before the Political Agent, either at Bahrein or at some convenient neutral spot, at which our Agent, as Arbitrator, might be able to effect a settlement.' 2 If Sbeikh Esa did not concur in the adoption of this course, we should have all the stronger reasons for 'washingour hands off the case; on the other hand, if the Uehaih refused to respond, there would be less grounds for our imposing further restrictions upon the Sheikh's liberty of action. What I fear is that unless we take some further action in one of the two directions now suggested, the case will inevitably continue to rankle in Sheikh Esa s mind and will be periodically brought up by him as a grievance whenever he is in need of an excuse for showing disinclination of his own to act upon our advice in some other matter. I trust thereiore that the Government of India will see their way to humour him to some extent. 5859 F. D. Eid.—L. G. G.v ^ 'Y (Ml .No: /^37 of 1906/ British. Residency and Consulate-General, Bus hire, /' Ju&amp; 1906. /O? Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for information and guidance, with reference to /by J ^ By Order etc., Lieutenant, Second' Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Foreign Department Endorsement No: 1936-E .B. dated 12th May 1906, with enclosures. — —V Confidential . -N q A copy of the foregoing despatch is forwarded to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information and guidance, with reference to the correspondence ending with his letter No: 497, dated the 3rd March 1906. By Order, etc. , (sd). R. E. HOLLAm Asstt; Secy: to the G-overnment of India. Foreign 'Department, Simla; The 12th May 1906. Secret Despatch from His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, No: 10, dated 16th March 1906, with, enclosures.INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, I 16th. March 1906. Secret. No:10. TO HIS EXCELLENCY THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE GOVERNOR GENERAL OF INDIA in COUNCIL. My Lord, With reference to your Excellency's letter No: 2 Persian Gulf: the murder of j( (Secret) of the 4th Jan- Bahreinese near Katif. I uary last, relating to the question of obtaining reparation for the murder of certain Bahreinese by members of the Behaih tribe, I en close herewith a copy of further correspondence with the .*-To Foreign Office, dated 8th February i Foreign Office • 1906. I I on the subject. From cli-c/lo , dated 2nd March 1906, and ? enclosure. J g. Your Excel lency will see that His Majesty's Government approve the second alternative course proposed by the Government of India, and do not intend to pursue the matter any further so far as the Turkish Governmei t are directly concerned. The Sheikh of Bahrein may, however, be advised that the further remedy lies in his own hands by the exclusion from Bahrein of members of any tribes which are in a position to exercise pressure upon the Behaih to induce them to come to a settlement. 3. Sheikh i:isa should at the same time be informed that His Majesty's Government will not countenance any excessive action on his part in pursuance of this policy. I have the honour to be. My Lord, four Lordship's most obedient, humble servant, (sd). JOHN MORLEY. . L / r iENCLOSURES , Enclosure No:l. India Office to 'Dhe Foreign Office. India Office, Sth February 1906. Sir, With, reference to previous correspondence as to the murder of Bahreinese by the Behaih tribe, terminat ing with Sir H. Walpole's letter of 24tii August last, I am directed by Mr: Secretary Morley to transmit, for the in formation of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, copy of a letter from the G-overnmait of India, dated 4th. ultimo, together with its enclosures, reporting the result of further enquiries into the matter by the Political Officers in the Persian Gulf. 2. The 'roveimment of India state that they have come to the conclusion, after careful examination of the informa tion which has been supplied to them, that there are two possible alternatives (1) to press for compensation from the Porte, (2) to drop the case. S. . In the circumstances it appears to Mr: Morley that, unless Sir N. 0'Conor wishes to reserve power to press the claim for compensation, it would be desirable to adopt the second alternative, and to drop the case, and he would be glad to be favoured with Sir E. Grey's views as to the course to be followed. 4. It will be observed that the Government of India ap parently contemplate informing Sheikh Esa, in the event of the claim being altogether dropped, that the further re medy lies in his own hands by the exclusion from Bahrein of members of any tribes which are in a position to exercise pressure upon the Behaih with a view to their coming to a settlement. Mr: Morley sees no objection to such a coimnu- nicationcoimunication being made to the Sheikh, provided it ij clear to him that no excessive action on his part vrilj countenanced by the British Government. I nave etc., A. aO'nLEY. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. m iae b Enclosure No:2. Foreign Office to India Office. No: 6905. Foreign Office, 2nd March 1906. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 8th Febru ary, regarding the murder of Bahreinese by the Behaih tribe I am directed by Secretary E. Grey to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Ambassador at Constantinople on the subject. Sir E. Grey concurs in the view that this case may now be allo-wd to drop, and he sees no objection to the communication, referred to in 'ohe last paragraph of your letter, which the Government of India propose to make to Sheikh Esa, provided that it is made clear to him that no excessive action on his part will be countenanced by His Maj e s ty 1 s Gove rnment. I am etc., E. GORST. The Under Secretary of State for India.i ' s&gt;- Annex. Sir N. 0'Conor 'bo Sir E. Grey. 11^ No: 100. Constantinop1e. 19tii February 1906. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your Despatch No: 59 (4844) of the 12th instant, enclosing a letter from the India Office in which Mr: Secretary Morley expressed the opinion that, unless I desire to reserve power to press upon the Sublime Porte a claim for compensa tion for the murder of certain Bahreinese by the Behaih tribe, it would be desirable to drop the case. Considering that reasonable efforts were made, although unsuccessfully, by the Turkish Government to discover and arrest the culprits, and as there were grounds for believ ing that the murder was committed in consequence of a ven detta between the parties, I am disposed - go agree with Mr: Morley' s view that yhe case is one which can properly be allowed to drop. - Ill i fi ir Edward Grey, Bart, M. P. &amp;c. , &amp;c. , &amp;c. , I have etc. , N. R. 0' Conor. 4 /No. 920, dated Trincomalee, the 26tli April 1903 (Confidential). From—His Excellency Reab,-Admiral Sie , C. C. Deury, K .C.I .E., Commanding His Majesty's Naval Forces, East Indies Station, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. In reply to your confidential letter No. 675 E. of the 16tli instant, be pleased to inform His Excellency the Viceroy in Council that I consider that the Agreement made with the Sheikh of Bahrein in 1861 to abstain from any act of aggression or retaliation by sea should still be adhered to, as, if it was cancelled, complications might easily arise. 2. I would first desire to point out that in my opinion the results achieved by the use of armed dhows in the Gulf of Aden have not been as great a success as is generally supposed, and it is a very demoralising service for officers and men. 3. The best course appears to me to be that I should be informed every year when the pearl fishery is to begin and end, and I would then endeavour to arrange for a'gun-boat to police those waters during the time the fishery was being carried out. 4. If it is decided that an armed dhow is necessary, I am of opinion that she should be commanded by a Eoyal Indian Marine officer who would require a commission from the Admiralty; the vessel would fly the white ensign and be under the orders of the Naval Commander-in-Chief on this station, and be a tender to the Senior Naval Officer's ship in the Persian Grulf. She might be provided and maintained by the Sheikh of Bahrein and partly manned by his subjects, as his interests are primarily affected, but he could have absolutely no control over her movements and actions on the high seas. 5. With regard to paragraph 3 of your letter, the Consul-General ^ at Berbera has recently bought and equipped two armed dhows, and could give you all details, so as to enable an estimate of the cost of one to be arrived at. As far as I am aware, they have each one 3-pounder quick-firing gun. Two Europeans, one as Captain and one as Mate. The Captain receives £120 a year. The services of his dhows are confined to the territorial waters of British Somaliland. 6. The dhows recently employed by the Hoyal Navy in the Gulf of Aden for the suppression of the arms traffic were hired by us at the rate of Bs. 225 a month, which included the services of the native crew. The guns, fittings, &amp;c., were supplied by the ships to which the dhows were attached. Foreign Office Press —No. 199—12-5-03—60.No: 3^ British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, /S'^ April 1904. U 0 r o . ' From Lieut-Colonel C % A. Kemball,C.E Offg: Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf; To The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrein„ Sir, I have the honour to invite your attention to the pre vious correspondence on the subject of the murder of Sheikh Salman bin Diaij\ 2 m I enclose for your information copy of a communicatioru (translated in this Office from the original French) from the Porte to His Majesty's Embassy at Constantinople giving the further particulars which were promised with regard to the punishment alleged to have been inflicted on the offend ing tribe. Sir O'Conor in forwarding this communication to the Marquess of Lansdowne writes that he cannot find that the reports we have received have ever furnished the names of the</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002fb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/28</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002fb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/28</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File E5. Murder of Sheikh Selman bin Diaij and 25 others on the 3rd December 1900 at Deraya by the Behaih'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1900/1906</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-30T11:23:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (126 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: This file has two foliation numbers in the top right hand of each folio. The primary number is enclosed by a circle and begins on the first page. The secondary number is not enclosed by a circle and begins on the first page of text.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British officials at Bahrain and Bushire; Captain Oldham on board HMS
                           Lapwing; Shaikh ‘Īsá bin ‘Alī Āl Khalīfah, ruler of Bahrain; and the
                           kaymakam(Ottoman governor) of al-Qaṭīf.These correspondence concern the murder in 1900 of Salmān bin Di‘aj Āl Khalīfah, cousin of Shaikh ‘Īsá, together with some twenty-five others, at the hands of the ‘Behaih’ section of the Āl Murrah tribe while on their annual hawking trip on the mainland of Eastern Arabia at al-Darayah, some thirty to forty miles south of al-Qaṭīf.The file contains details of the murder itself (folio 7), as well as subsequent dealings with Turkish officials and the Āl Thānī family in order to avert revenge attacks (‘blood feud’) by the Āl Khalīfah family (for example, folio 45) between 1902 and 1906. There are incidental references to the outbreak of plague in the Gulf in 1903 (folio 76).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Homicide</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002fb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>