<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000c7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:08:12.352Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ the Trucial and Oman hinterland as possible. The Company’s Geologists believe that there are no insuperable physical difficulties in the vay of such exploration, which they would probably be able to carry out with the help of good guides and perhaps fairly generous presents to the de facto rulers, It is clear, however, that such movements would require the concurrence of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ' Prom the Company’s point of view the step most desired 'would be a comprehensive definition of boundaries and authorities in the area, concerned 0 . or, failing this, permission to metke its own arrangements for further exploration. The idea under which the Company started that the hinterland was necessarily under the control of one or other of the coastal rulers - can no longer be entertained c (Intd.) T.H.L.784iA n IN DIA OFFICE, Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Sec e1iar ^ 0:f State for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Repeated to Government of India ,External Affairs Departs tw 7 M Political Agent.Muscat «^ Dated 7 th August ,1937. ^ j - /£- t'3J. To sent, No.. p* A 37. w / Do. P.Z. 4683/37. Your telegram of the 3rd July, 673. Muscat Oil. Copies are enclosed of draft Political Agreements and Exchanges of notes in respect of (A) the Muscat Concession (B) the Dhofar Concession. These drafts are being communicated to the Company. Please telegraph, if you have any observations to onei You will observe that they follow closely the Shargah and Debai models. If y0 u have no observations and if the Company concur the Political Agreements will be concluded and the date of signature telegraphed to you. , above i la s been duly authorised The issue of the above nab&amp; » P.z. 4683/37. THIS AGREEMENT dated the day IP/ of One thousand nine hundred and thirty seven is made BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY ! S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called !, His Majesty’s Government”) of the one part and PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED (hereinafter called ”the Company u which expression snail where the context so admits he deemed to include ibs successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part* |l WHEREAS the Company has obtained a concession dated the 24th June, 1937, from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman (hereinafter called ”the Sultan”) (A) in respect of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman excluding Dhofar and Gwadur (B) in respect of the District called Dhofar, and whereas certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty s Government as follows:- The Company shall be and remain a? British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE Concession between the Company and the Saltan shall be transferred by the Company to any other person or corporate body without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Government. It is understood that His Majesty’s Government will not in any case give their consent to the tiansfei concession to any person except on the condition tha„ the transferee shall be and remain a British company registered Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. (A) the Sultanate 3 f THE employees of the Company in ^ Dliofar shall at all times be British subjects^of the Sultanprovided that, with the conoont of His Majesty*s dent in the Persian Gulf) h Government (or the Political Resi such persons of other nationality as are required foi tl efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. 4. THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Sultanate Authorities through a Chief / Local Representative in Muscat ? who shall he a Bricish subject. s \ '/' The approval of His Majesty’s Government shall be required for the person so designated® He will be ordinarily resident i Muscat and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Sultanate authorities 5 which shall, except ^ * i n routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty’s Government in Muscat or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the ^Persian Gulf may from time to time designate, 5. SUBJECT to the terms of the Agreement between the Coni 36 any and the Sultan the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sultan and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him, 6. ANY right given to the Company unaer its agreement the Sultan to utilise means of transportation by aii shall subject to any general regulations for civil airciaf^ made y which are binding on British subjects. the Sultan - - J &gt; v 7. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Concession between the Company and the Sultan the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall noo include in tne area to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations the surface of any sites which may have been selected by or behalf of the Sultan or His Majesty’s Government fox defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or in connection with the % m 'M 1 ! jI 8 9. 10 . |-r 3. development ox harbours,provided that with the consent oi His Majesty’s Government which shall not oe unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use j. or -re purposes of its operations such harbours aerodromes or seaplane bases as may be developed oy the oulcan or xlxo Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable accominodauio^ a*v ad 1 able elsewhere. Subject to the terms ox the agx cement between the Company and the Sultan harbours developed b^ tne Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control. TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if &gt; maintained by the Company shall be for use only in ios business and as provided in the concession , and snaxl constructed and operated that their operations shall rou interfere with the operations of such, wireless, telegrapn or telephone installations as may be establishedjby the bulvai or His Maje sty 1 s Government, or their agent. XH the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty's GovernmeAo shall be the sole judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all the oil produced m (A) The Sultanate in accordance with the terms of the ^ (B) Dhofar Schedule hereto. THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the _\ Sultan before working in any particular area, in order that .ition to fulfil his respo nsibilities^ j X\ the Sultan may be in a pos p- 'GEGle nroteoHon of the Company . The Sultan snail not L » unreasonably withhold such permission, and in any case in which the Company feels that the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily resected the matter shall be referred for decision to use io-.it-.-al Resident. -H u 4'' vA Vt - fX . f -vA) t..- A ^ f' JIF WITEESS whereof on 'behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set ms hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written TTTt; SCH EDULE above re ferred_t£ pre -enrpt ion Claus e . Xn the event ox a state of national emei o* v.ax (of the existence of which His Majesty's Government shall be the sole judge) - (1) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sultan to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have m (A)the Sultanate to produce oil fuel that snail oompxy with^the a Admira1ty specifications at the time provided that (A) the Sultanate oil be of a suitable kind and quality lor (B) Bhofar this purpose. (£) The Company shall use its utmost endeavocno uO increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government. (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to dell '’ er or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right or pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenientplace of shipment or at a place of storage in to he determined by His Majesty’s Government. (A) the Suitanate (B) Dhofar In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company, Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty 1 Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political 'Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Geo.V. c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force, (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause.* To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of (A) the Sultanate oil or products sold to other customers and (B) Dhofar of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty's Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in (A) the Sultanate, and in such event the Company (B) l]o far shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause (3). -SIGHED SEABED AND DELIVERED by ) the said ) on behalf of His } Majesty's Government in the ) presence of:- ) IHE COMMON SEAL of Petroleum Develepraent (True ial C oast} Limited was hereunto affixed in the prssenc e of:-DBAFJ? Ho .1. \ After Compliments, His Majesty T s Government have been furnished with a copy of the Agreement signed by Your Highness on the 24th June 1937 granting to Petroleum Concessions Limited, ^ (A) your territory an oil concession in respect of (b) Bhofar excluding Bhofar and Gwadur ~ on the understanding that the Agreement is subject to the approval of His Majesty ? s Government. 2. Under instructions from His Majesty's Government I now enclose a copy of an Agreement which has been concluded between His Majesty’s Government and Petroleum Concessions Limited in London on 3. It is desirable that there should be a clear understanding as to the position which would arise in certain eventualities in connection with these two Agreements and I am to inform you that in these circumstances the understanding described below has been reached with the Company i- (a) Should any of the terms of the Agreement between Your Highness and the Company be inconsistent or in conflict with the ■terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London the Agreement between Your Highness and the Company will to the extent of any such inconsistenc, or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Ma j e sty ’ s Gov eminent. (b) If the Company should fail to observe any of the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on or if the alleged failure haring been disputed by the Company/ f •i.j 'XIV. TRADE &amp; COmiSRCS . A. MINES AND MINERALS. (1) Oil concesion in Muscat Vol.(2]l From - ^ m Jr**- Previous number#A Telegram - 3 ’ rom - Froa the Secretary of State for India, London No.1541. Dated the 1 st June 1937. Received the 2nd June 1937. Received from Muscat at flwadur on 2nd June 1937, under Agency telegram Uo.640. Addressed Bushire, repeated to Government of India; Bahrain and Muscat. Your telegram 47 3 of May the 25th. 2. Oral statement on the lines of paragraph Uo.9 has been made to Representative of Petroleum Concessions Ltd who stated HOLMES already has drafts of Sharjah and Ras al Khaimah Concessions and discretion as to financial terms within total amount which Company are willing to spend on Trucial Coast. 3. Company are telegraphing to HOLMES to hurry on with Sharjah and Ras al Khaimah negotiations and if he can conclude them at once he will do so and then go immediately to Muscat. They expect for certain reply that this cannot be managed whereupon they will send Mr.LERMITTS OR SOMEONE ELSE TO MUSCAT, Ugency of matter has been impressed on fchK them. MILES cannot be made available by the Anglo-Iranian for this purpose. 4 . in a telegram to the Company HOLMES states that he hears Sultan of Muscat is proceeding to England shortly. Do you know anything about this? oOo--'‘ l ' Telegram - q. Froin - Secretary of state for India. Ho.1538. Dated Received tyj 3 y Received from Muscat at Gwadur 2nd of June 1937, under Agency telegram Ho.639. Addressed to Bushire repeated India and Muscat. Your telegram 478 May 26th Muscat Oil. 'view of Sultan ^ direct approachs to Standard Oil Go. (vide correspondence enclosed with Rumbold 1 s Air Mail letter to you PZ3347/37 May the 26th, copies to India &amp; Muscat) it seems essential whole matter should he discussed with His Highness as soon as possible. 3. Standard Oil Go’s attitude is that although they .. ft bound to send direct reply to Sultan they recognize that proper channel of communication is through the Political Agent and their replies have been designed to secure this end. If therefore you see no objection Political Agent should be instructed to press Sultan to submit any reply he wishes to make to Company through official channels. In this connection you will note Rumbold f s D.O.letter May the 26th that there is no objection to’Sultan being told that H.M.G. are aware of his correspondence with ' / v&lt; ‘ 'Y s * i | Oil and its purport, 4. If considered necessary Sultan should be remin^ded of his obligations not to grant oil concession without con sulting political Agent and without consent of H.M.G. you 5. Do/consider that he should be also told that for reasons given in para 2 of ray telegram Ho. 481 of February the 10 th/ ! ■■■»-oGo-»- - 2 - the 10th H.M.G. regard Petroleum Concessions Ltd. as definitely having priority and cannot approve his entering into negotiations with Standard Oil Co. at this stage. u * ~ communicate with you separately regarding your telegram 473 Hay the 25th.Tel egram - q. Political, Muscat at Gwadur. Britconsul, Busliire. Prom To N 0 .G 6 . Dated the 3rd June 1937. Muscat Cil. A!) Reference India Office telegram 1541 of June 1st. I hope that some Representative of Petroleum Concessions Ltd v/ill come to Muscat as quickly as possible. HOLMES had written me that he v/as arriving about the end of May but as I had heard nothing further by then I tele graphed him that Sultan wantj^ to leave for India on 18th June (vide my D.O.Fo.2 of June 1st) and requested him to hasten his visit to Muscat. He now wires that LERMITTE is being sent immediately. 3. I think any more deitay in opening negotiations with Sultan by Company v/ill be unfortunate as I gather he is under the impression that he is not being quite properly treated in this matter. - political -vyj Telegram - From - Srit consul, Bushire. To ' . Political, Muscat at Gwadur. ITo. 503. Sated 3rd, received 4th June 1937. * h ^ /(' India Office telegram lTo.15 38 June 1st. Pending the receipt of RUMBOLS’s letter please telegraph your views on suggestions in paragraphs 4 and 5 of telegram under reference, I am inclined to agree with H.M.Cr s suggestions hut do not see how we can go so far as to sajr 'Cannot approve' in paragraph Uo.5 as there is no thing in our agreements with the Sultan to this effect. Instead of this we could say H H,M.G. feel very strongly 0 that Petroleum Concessions Ltd at this stage should priority A in negotiations' or something to this effect. 2 - In addition to the undertaking of 1923, we could generally support our requests to him regarding Oil on his accession letter of February the 10th 1932 re being guided by H.M.G's views on important matters. 3. With reference to paragraph 4 of India Office telegram 1541. Have you heard anything? Lfe i ■ , f - Brit consul -Telegram - q, 1?roro - Britconsul, Bushire. To * Political, Muscat at Gwadur. Fo.517. Bated the 5th June 1937. Received the 6 th June 1937. Addressed to Secretary of State for India, i epeat ed to Political Agent, Muscat, copy sent by Se; Mail to the Government of India. Paragraph Fo.3 of your telegram Fo.1541 of June 1st. 2 * Political Agent, Bahrain informs me that V HOLMES has recomme^ed to the Company that LERMITTE ALIFGTOF be sent to Muscat at once to open negotiations, I trust that LERMITTE ALIFGTOF is being sent immediately as Political Agent, Muscat telegraphs that the delay in the Company f s opening of negotiations with the Sultan is having a bad effect on the latter. 3. In the meantime Political Agent, Muscat should inform the Sultan that a special Representative is being sent shortly from London to open negotiations. Britconsult&amp;mmmmmmam Telegram - q. ^om - Political, Muscat at Gwadur. To - Britccnsul, Bushire. No. G 7 Mated the 7th June 1927, y Muscat Oil. \ k Your telegram No.to3 of June 3rd. I agree with your vie?/s expressed in your paragraph No.1. 2. Your paragraph No.2. You may remember that at one of our interviews with Sultan during your visit to Muscat he said that his father had privately repudiated the 1923 undertaking given by him and the Sultan therefore considered it was no longer binding on him. In view of this statement I think any requests re oil v/ould be better supported by a reference to the accession letter of February 1932. ; 3. Your paragraph 3, please see my telegram No.G 6 of June 3rd. HOLMES I think has mixed up England with India. Sultan has made no mention of proposed early visit to England, Wat t sTelegram - - - q From - - - - ^itconsul Bushire To - - - - - Political Muscat No - - - - - 533 Dated &lt;Sc Beceived 9th June 1937, For Political Agent Muscat# Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Political Agent, Muscat Political Agent Bahrain for information of LEHMITTE copy by post to Government of India. Your telegram No. 1585 of June 7th. Sultan intends leaving Muscat for Kashmir on June 18th. Political Agent Muscat should try and persuade him to await arrival of the Petroleum Concessions Ltd. Bepresentative Dritconsul.* ' V a i iJ y Telegram — 1917 C.C* From ----- Britconoul Buohirc To ----- - Political Muscat No - 131 Dated June 9th &amp; Received 10th June 1937* Addressed Political Agent Bahrain repeated to Bushire and Muscat. Beferenee to Political Resident telegram No. 533 of June 8 th regarding departure of Sultan of Muscat for Kashmir on June 18th. 1. One LERMITTE is catching today's East Bound Air M&amp;il ( to Karachi) and thence catches mail to get to Muscat on June 16th. 2. I request Holmes to meet him todat at Plane to hand over all details concerning Muscat concessions.Telegram Q From Secretary of State for India To ----- - Political Muscat No* 1585 Dated the 7th June 1937 &amp; Received 12th June 37. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Muscat copy sent by Air Mail to Government of India. Company have instructed LERMITTE to proceed to Muscat as soon as WARTISLAW arrives from Syria and relieves him at Bahrain. 2. I agree that Political Agent Muscat should inform Sultan that special Representative arrives shortly to open negotiations.Telegram - 1917. Prom - Political, Muscat. r Britconsul, Bushire. No. Dated the 12th June 1937. Muscat Oil . [! l Your telegram No.533 of 9th June I have persuaded Sultan with difficulty to postpone his departure for India until 25th June but he declares he will not under any circumstances delay longer. 2. In letter received today from Sultan ( which I am forwarding by next Mail) he states that if terms offered ar* satisfactory he will grant concession for portion only of his territory to Petroleum Concessions Ltd and other portions to another or other companies. 3. -tfrom conversation I had with Sultan yesterday I am convinced that whatever terms are now offered by Petroleum Concessions he will endeavour to obtain better from the Standard Oil Company of California and in any case intends to give them a concession for a portion of his territory. 4. If my presumption proves correct do you wish me to impress on Sultan that His Majesty*s Government feel very strongly that no concession even for portion of his territory should be given to any non British Company.Telegram - From - Britconsul, Busiiire. To - Political Muscat* No. 552. Dated 15th June 1937. Paragraph No.l. \/) 1 Your telegram No.69 June 12th. Do you mean July 25th or June 25th ? Telegram - - - Q From ----- Political Muscat To ----- - Britconsul Bushire No - - 71 Dated the 15th June 1937* Your telegram No. 552 of June 15th.4 Telegram - ^ Prom • Political, Muscat. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No. 75 Dated the 16th June 1937. i w , y) Reference your telegram Ho.517 of June 5th. Muscat Oil. 2 . lermitte arrived yesterday evening and had interview with Sultan today. Sultan stated that he had divided up his territory into 3 separate groups each of which would have to form separate concession (a) Gwadur (b) Dhofar (c) remainder of all Muscat territory including Oman.* yo\ 'o 3. Sultan in his letter to me of 11th June(vide my telegram 69 of June 12th) had written that he would grant only portion of his territory to Petroleum Concessions but Lermitte informs me that Sultan this morning definitely stated he was not adverse to granting all 3 groups if terms were satisfactory. Lermitte has cabled his London Office for instructionsTranslation of a letter dated the 1st Rabi* Awwal 1356* corresponding to the 11th June 1937, from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat to the Political Agent &amp; H.B.M*s Consul, Muscat* After compliments* formerly we gave you the trouble of Our request to you to find out for us a Company whom We could grant a concession for the exploitation and developement of Oil in Our territories* During your last visit to us when We were at Dhofar, you informed us that there was a Company •f-* | who desired to take such a Concession* After our return from the said town to Muscat and at Our first meeting with you in the month of March last, you intimated to us that a man named Major Holmes would arrive in Muscat to repre sent that Company with a view to negotiating and coming to an agreement with us. On this We expressed Our thanks to you. Here again We thank you for all the trouble you have J&amp;- taken in this connection. But while three months approxi mately have passed since you informed us that he was gwmrug arriving at the end of May last, yesterday you informed us that he was not arriving and that another man would arrive in his place, who represented the same Company and was due ju to arrive on Tuesday next. We were intending to leave 7 for India,ax as you know, on the 18th of June, but in consideration of the profits that are expected to be gained by Our Government, we have postponed Our departure for one week in order to meet thej^ man who is coming on deputation 4- from the Company. Further* you will remember that We t'i have pointed out to the Hobble the Political Resident when he was here and in your presence, that it was not our intention to grant this Company a Coneession for the whole of Our territories, but for a portion to be specified by us , and that for the rest of Our territories we would grant Concessions to other Companies who desire to take them. Any Company who would offer easire terms and greater amount*would be the one desired by us. After We havez - z agreed with the n»n coiaiKg Companies to whom We could , We shall endeavour to get other grant Concessions, God willingly. Usual Ending*JL GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. in. B, —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by 'post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched^ From Political Muscat* I I I To Britconsul Bushlre. No. c.ia/ft tktei • 17th JUMe m 7 ' Muscat Oil * . Reference telegram llo.69 dated 12th June 1937. L 2. X forward herewith translation of a letter dated lith *mne 1937 received from the Sultan of Muscat on the above mentioned subject. 3. As will be seen therefrom only ^oint of importance raised by His Hijiiiiiess is his declared intention to give a concession for oil for only a portion of hin territory to Petroleum Conoeseions Limited and that only if they bid the highest. Other companies he states *ill also be given concessions. 4. In the above connection however, please see paragraph 3 ofBy Mail. V.z J/dL / 19 INDIA OFFICE, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to ^ hy^^ Mail. - ^ Sea 4963 2000 7.36 y nt of India. Persian Gulf. Tpe Foreign Secr etary, Governme fee Poiitipdl Resident in the PerP.Z.2926/37o li IVLaj &gt; 1937 o ) Sir, In reply to your letter of the 24th Maroh 5 No. p o c. 27/28/30, 1 an directed to inform you that His Majesty's Government see no objection in principle to the use of aircraft for transport or survey in the Persian Gull area, provided (a) that the consent of the Sheikh concerned is obtained beforehand and the area over which the Company would propose to fly explained to him., (b) that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf or the political Agent concerned is kept in close touch with the Company l s plans and is consulted as to the suitability of the aircraft and equipment (e.g, wireless). which should in any case conform to the regulations regarding airworthiness etc. which apply in Bahrein (or Muscat), (c) that any air survey company ivhich may be employed is a British firm of undoubted repute under entirely British direction and employing British nationals or natives of the Arab State concerned. 2. As regards the specific proposals of the Company, His Majesty's Government are of opinion, after consulting the local political authorities, that it would be best to postpone any air survey (or the use of aircraft for transport) on the frucial Coast until the concessions have actually been obtained from the Rulers. The use of aircraft is provided for in the draft concessions, and when these are obtained there will be a certain The Managing Director, obligation/ petroleum Concessions Limited, Ciuy Gate Hcuse, Finsbury Squ.-..re, IhC.2^ Pw h V obligation on the Eulers concerned to co-operate in the matter. But in the meanwhile it ’would not be possible to count on the Rulers 1 co-operation except as a special favour (for which they might expect some return), and it would appear undesirable at this stage to ask more favours of them than is absolutely necessary. a. The same reasons against aiiy innneciiate acoion apply to Muscat with greater force, in view of the fact that the negotiations with the Sultan have not begun. 4. As regards Qatar, the previous permission of the Ruler is specifically required (under Article 6 of the Concession) for the use of aircraft. His Majesty's Government see no objection to the Company approaching the Sheikh (through the local political authorities) for the necessary permission, but they are anxious that flights over the extreme southern section of the territory lying within the boundary of the oil concession should, as far as practicable, be avoided or at any rate limited to a course lying ’well within the concession line. rnej would also like to oe informed xhrougn the loccu. x'Olitic&lt;_x authorities well in advance before any regular flights are begun in the southern area. 5. Since His Majesty's Government have had this matter under consideration, there have, as ivou know, been reworts of differences arising between tne Sheikh Qatar and certain tribesmen in the neighbourhood of nuoaiah. The Company will of course appreciate that these occurrences might necessitate some postponement of the approach to the Sheikh which is envisaged in uhe pi seeding paragraph. I am, Sir, y our ob edient S e r vant, fSd.) J. 0. WALTON,By jfcir Mail. P-Z-iMJ 19 Ll INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, !ImL Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A. copy lias been sent to j ^ - ^ Sea The Forej^n^So i The Political f )JLjl f\ CA/k 4963 2000 7.36P,Z* 3165/1937 / O/Jf AxR MINISTRY, ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINaaiTAY, w.c.s 3.41014/D.0.I. SECRET . 10th May, 1937. Dear Clauson, Further to my letter S.41014/D.0.I. , of E8th April regarding the application of petroleum Concessions Limited to employ a civilian firm to undertake air surveys of their concessions in q,atar, on the frucial coast, and in Muscat, we have now ascertained that the Air Officer Comm ndmg in f lraq has no objection from the point of view of defence in respect of Qatar. I am sending copies of this letter to Brenan and Seal* Yours sincerely, (SD.) G.C.Pirie. [.J.Clauson, Esq., India Office, S.W.l I |i/ f J GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). — Via Bahra in. [N.B •—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] * No. 398-3 of 1937. Dated e. To XX Nmmu' xxxxxxx Political dent* 27 th Mr.y Bushire 19 37* W*. n TO Beferenoe XXKXXXJPOC Hey eat ed His f o ecretary of State for India, London* Secretary to Gorermaen t of India in tiy® External Affairs department, Simla Political Agent, Muscat 7 s Subj act: Muscat Oil* Reference tqy aeraoraiMium Ho»0/i49 of the Bth May 1937* I enclose coyy of a letter dated the 12th May 1937 from Major Frank Holmes forwarding draft oil concession Muscat 1937/c* I have no spare copies of the draft 9 which could doubtless be obtained from Petroleum Concessions Limited in London* 2* The draft differs in the following respects from the previous 1937/B: (a)* Article 1 ( a) * The last sentence has been omitted* I originally suggested this omission (paragraph 3 (2) of my Express letter UomQ/Zd of the Sth -(arch 1937 but. as it .had not been deleted when other etr age* were made, agreed that it could stand (paragraph 3 of my Express let er Wo*c/b4 of the 7th April 1937)* (Signature) , ^ 3. 44. (Designation)-g- Aa the India Office do not attach importance to it® retention (paragraph® 2 and 4 of Mr.Glauson f a letter Io.?.2.21Sg/37, dated fee 17th April 1^37) I auggest that we should raise no objection to its deletion* (b)» Article 17* The words w under the coni it tone specified in Article 12 hereof 51 has been omitted* The retention of the reference to Article 12 ?y©uld have been preferable but ns that is the only Article in the concession relating to declaration of safety there is no risic of ambiguity* 1 there fore do not think that the omission matters, and suggest that it should be concurred in. (c). Article 23 , The name of the subsidiary Company has been altered to 'Petroleum Development (Muscat) Limited'. This is an improvement, and may be concurred in. 3. I would be grateful for a reply by telegram in order that I may inferm Maj or Holmes with as little delay as possible that the above alterations have been approved. ad. T. % ?Ofle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*Telegram - $ From - Secretary of State for India* No. 1658 Bated 16th. ) June i937. Received 17th) Addressed to Bushire Repeated to Muscat Copy by Air Mail to Government of India. Your telegram 551 of June 14th. I agree, except that as regards (b) it might be well to remind Sultan that approval of Government is necessary for grant of oil Concession to anyone.ss EXPR ESS T T E R (AIR MAIL). Prom Secretary of State for India To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf repeated to the Government of India., External Affairs Department and to the political Agents at Muscat‘''and Bahrein, Dated 5th June, 1937. ho. P.Z.3623/37o My telegram No.1538 Enclosed is a copy Concessions Limited from com Petroleum Concessions Limited ) dated 3rd June. ) Co Petroleum Concessions Limited ) dated 5th June. ) ) him by Mr. H, J. Wratislave. dated 1st June. Muscat oil. of correspondence with Petroleum which it will be observed that the Company are sending Mr. B.E.de R. Lermitte to Muscat to conduct the negotiations and are replacingP„Z.3623/37. IKD1A. OFFICE, TOIFEIFVLL, S.W. 1 5tli June, 1937. Fear Mr. Lewisohn, 1 write to thank you for your letter of the 3rd June lTo.366 in which you state that the Company are sending Mr. Lermitte to Muscat to conduct the negotiations and are replacing him by Mr.H.J.Wratislaw. So far as this Office is concerned we see no reason to question these arrangements and we are informing the Political Resident accordingly. yours sincerely, m.) J. C. WALTON. F.Lewisohn, Esq., C.S.I.,C.B 0 E., Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, London, E.C.2PETROLEUM C ONCES S1ONS LIMITEDe ;&gt; P Z.3603/1937. Ro.366 CITY-GATE HOUSE, PiNSBURY SQUARE, LONDON, EoC.2 3rd June, 1937. Dear Mr. Walton, Wi ch. i ef erence to our telephone conyorsation of chib arternoon, I 'Vvrito to Gonfirm that we have been unable to secure the services of Mr. Myites for the Muscat negotiations, With your concurrence we are therefore sending Mr. Lormitte to Muscat to conduct the negotiations, and are replacing him by Mr. H. J. Wratislaw. Mr. Lermitto was sent out to Bahrain at the beginning of the year, to act as Assistant to our Bahrain Manager, Mr. Packer. Mr. Packer being now on leave, Mr. Dermictc is acting as Manager. Particulars of Mr. Lcrmittc were given m Mr. Longrigg^s letter PC.46/188 dated the 26th October last to Mr. Clauson, which letter v/as acknowledged by Mr. Clauson in his letter P.Z. 7701/36 of the 28th October. Mr. H. J. Wratislaw is the son of Mr.A. C.W:ratislaw, C.3.,C.M.G.,C.B.E., who was Consul-General at Salonica during the war and subsequently Consul-General, Beirut. Mr. H. J. Wratislaw is a British subject, who both before and after the war was employed as an Inspector under the Ottoman Public Debt Administration. During the war he v/as interned in Turkey. Ho joined the Iraq petroleum Company in May, 1932, and in September last he was transferred to Petroleum Concessions Limited and sent to Jeddah/JL 1? J- f 2 . Juddali as Branch Manager^ Potrolcimi Dovolopmont (Western Arabia) Limited. He happens to be on leave in Syria at the moment, and to be the best man immediately available to relieve Mr, Lermitte, who has been instructed to proceed to Muscat as soon as Mr. Wratislaw arrives. It might be helpful to us if the Political resident could oe advised by you that these moves have the India 01fice r s approval. Yours sincerely, (3d.) P. Lewisohn. Walton, Esq., C.B.,M.Co, India Office, Whitehall, 3.W.1By Air Mail. s INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to JLw. by £ oa MaiL 4963 2000 7.36COPY. The PALACE, Muscat. 17th April 1937. TO ^ Messrs. The California Standard Oil Company Ltd., 6, Lothbury, London, E.C. Dear Sirs; We thank you for your letter dated 30th March 1937 and confirm the contents of communication to Mr. P.A.Davies dated 28th February 1937 requesting him whether if would be possible for the company to under take examination on the spot by their experts on terms to be mutually agreed similar to Bahrein or Saudi- Arabia. We thank you for the assurance of assistance contained in your letter and would request you to send us a copy of the terms on vAiich the company has started work m Saudi-Arabia. We would also be pleased to receive proposals from you on which you are prepared to examine and develop the petroleum resources of some parts of our dominions. yours faithfully, (Signed) - Said bin Taimur . Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman.COPY. CALIFORNIA STANDARD OIL COMPANY, LIMITED, 6^ Lotilbury 5 London., E.C.S. May 21st 5 1937. HoH.Tlie Sultan of Muscat and Oman* Tde Palace* Muscat. Your Highness* We are instructed by our principals to acknowledge the receipt of and to thank you for your kindly enquiry dated 3rd May* and to inform you that they are prepared to make such proposals as you suggest for the examination and development of the petroleum resources of some parts of Your Highness 1 s Dominions. Our Principals enquire if they would be in order in assuming that by the reference to 'some parts' of your Dominions* Your Highness intends to convey the fact that there are others interested at the present time in examining and developing the petroleum resources of parts of your Dominions. If this is so* would you be good enough to tell us which part or which parts of your Dominions are available to our Principals to consider for the purposes of formulating and forwarding their proposals Your Highness will* we trust* appreciate that it is essential that our principals should know what part or parts of your Kingdom are open to them before they could advise you what* - if any* are the proposals they could put forward„ Our principals further enquire what would be the correct procedure for making their proposals having regard1. to the Treaty relations now existing between Your Highness and His Britannic Majesty's Government &gt; that IS; whether their proposals to your Highness should be made directly to Your Highness or to Your Highness in conjunction with His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent at Muscat. We are sending the original of this letter by airCONFIDENTIAL. No - 338-3 of 193 /. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. ^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s), British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... .y. .4^3.7. Reference to previous correspondence: ''ofll h (2) only. Political Resident’s Printed letter No.c/76 of the 12th April 1937. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. political Resident’s telegram Ho.473 of t ie 25th May 1937. Petroleum Concessions Limited.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 454 -.S of 1937, s'/ © m \ The Hon’ble the Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. 2. The Political Agent, Muscat. J and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). V*i % British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... XXXU. .1.93.7.*. Reference to previous correspondence : To(l).only. Residency Printed letter No.445-S of 8 th June 193 7. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident’s telegram No.543 of the 11th June 1937. Muscat Oil,Telegram %* From Political Resident, Ruahlre* To Secretary of State for India, London# Copy by poet to Governraent of India, Internal Affaire Bepartment, Simla* » *» 11 w Political Agent, Muscat# Ho. 543# Dated the 11th June 1937. Paragraph 4 of your telegram Ho#1541 of 1st June* Holmes got mixed up between .England and India see my telegram Ho#533 of 8th June# Bri tconsul*Telegram Q. Prom Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Muscat. No. 1646. Dated 17th j received 18th ) June 1937. Your express letter No. 398-S May 27th. Muscat Oil. No objection to alterations. -RETAXANDUM. 6 ITelegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 570. V Britconsulty 5^ ^ lo - Britconsul Telegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire To Political Agent, Muscat. No♦ 574. Dated 17th (received 18th ) June 1937. a' &lt; a India Office telegram No. 1658 of June 16th. Please take necessary action. 2 . Paragraph 2 of your telegram of dune 7th. We do not accept Sultan’s repudiation. yfe h 3. Paragraph 4 of £our telegram No. 69 June 12th This point is covered by (b) of my telegram No. 551 June 14th. L/* / 3JL Telegram H.35. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Muscat. No. 585. Dated 18th (received 19th ) Mune 1937. © A Your telegram No. 75 June 17th. It is I should think quite impossible for Lermitte to conclude his negotiations by the 25th June ^ £uvC c on u . j[ s (i ue to leave for / o Kashmir. Another week -C x &gt; s negotiation after that might advance things materially. The present Muscat climate however is I imagine not conducive to successful negotiating. Would iL be possible ( for ? ) Lermitte to continue his negotiations with / C/1 cv-,- t a t Karachi for a week or so after which the Sultan cou±d leave for Karachi 1 You could accompany them to Karachi on recess ( to ? ) keep in touch. If you see no objection please broach above suggestion to Lermittewho can put it to the Sultan.32 Telegram Q. Prom Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bush ire. No 88 Dated 24th June 1937. ? Muscat Your telegram No. 585 of 18th June. Oil. 2. Oil Concession was signed to day after exhausting negotiations. Details by post. 3. There are still several matters to discuss with Sultan so I propose to leave on recess for Karachi with him and keep in touch vide your telegram quoted above. 4. Lermitte leaves by same steamer for Karachi en route Bahrain by air. - Political. . If i 1CONFIDENTIAL, No. 47 2-S of 1937 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Muscat • and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents ( 9 $. yf .. ■ 1/3. ^ British Consnlate-Generai, BUSHIKE. Dated..A 8 .H 1 ,/.H n . e ,.f..^ 2 , 7 Reference to previous correspondence: India Office telegram JNo. 1658, dated 16th June 1937* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Subject. Political Resident’s telegram No.584, dated 18th June 1937£. p. INDIA ODFICE, milTEHALL, S.Yfol 26th May, 1937. Dear Mr. Lewisohn, I told you some little time ago that we might want to suggest certain verbal amendments in the common form of the xoolitical agreements to be made between His Majesty's Government and the company in respect of any future oil concessions in the Persian Gulf. You also, I think, said that the Company might want to suggest certain small amendments. I have now looked into this matter and enclose a draft which, as you will see, differs in certain small particulars from the text of the Debai political agreement. It has not yet been approved officially here, and I will not do any more about it until you let me know whether you see any objection to these amendments and whether you have any others to add. It would, of course, be the ideal thing, if possible, to get the text settled in time for it to be used in respect of the next oil concession which may be obtained after the Debai concession. But I believe it is quite possible that certain of the other irucial Sheikhs will be ready to give your Company concessions directly the Debai concession is agreed, and in exactly the same terms* If this is so it would obviously be undesixable, and there would probably not be time, to altei uhe Debai text for these Sheikhs, but the revised text wou-td be available for use as and when It is possible, to introduce it. Yours sincerely, wisohn, Esq.,C3I.,CBE., _ . etroleum Concessions Ltd., (Sd.) M.J.Clauson. 39, Finsbury Square, E.C.2THIS AGREEMENT dated the day of One thousand nine hundred and thirty seven is made BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY 1 S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called 'His Majesty's Government') of the one part and PETROLEUM Development (Trucial Coast) Limited (hereinafter called 'the 'Company' Y/hich expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees) of the other part .* WHEREAS in the event of the Company obtaining a concession from the Sheikh of (hereinafter called 'the sheikh') certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty's Government 5 the company has agreed Y/ith His Majesty's Government as follows 1. THE Company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain* and its chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 2 . THE concession between the company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred by the Company to any other person or corporate body without the prior consenc in writ mg of His Majesty's Government, It is understood that His Majesty's Government will not in any case give their consent uo the transfer of the concession to any person except on the condition that the transferee is a British company registered m Great Britain and having its principal piece of business m Great Britain* and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE employees of the Company in shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh* provided that* with the consent of His Majesty's Government (or the political Resident in the Persian Gulf in the case of/Ox -Loreign native labour) ^ such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. THE Company m all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Authorities through a Cnrix Local Eepresontative in the Persian Gulf, who shall oe a hr in six subject. The approval of His Majesty’s Go c emmem, shall be required for the person so designated, he will oe ordinarily resident m or Bahrein and Wx.ll be responsible for the Company’s local relations with authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty’s Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBJECT to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the political Officers subordinate to him.. ART right given to the Company under its agreement wirh the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty’s Government, and approved by the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 1\ T 0TWITESTiilTDllTG anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government for defence purposes/JL (7 O, purposes^ :cor aerodromes ; aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph, installations or in connection with the development of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty»s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His MajestyHs Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the agreement between the company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control. TELEGRAPH , wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty T s Government, or their agent. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty's Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre-emption of till the oil produced in in accordance with the terms of the Schedule heret o. THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the company. The Sheikh shall not unreasonably withhold such permission, and in any case m which the company feels that the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted/restricted the matter shall be referred for decision to the Political Resident. - l1 * ^ ie event of notice of termination of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh being given on the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the terms of tha present Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government, the arbitration provisions of the said Agreement between the company and the Sheikh shall apply if the Company considers that notice of termination on such grounds is not justified, and in that event the Sheikh shall not cancel the said Agreement until arbitration takes place in accordance with the said provisions and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within the reasonable time which shall be fined by the arbitrators for so doing. IN WITNESS whereof on behalf of His Ma jo sty f s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written. THE SCHEDULE above referr ed to pre -emption Clause . In the event of a state of national emergency or wan (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge)- (1) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that oil be of/5 * * of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. (2) fhe Company shall use its utmost endeavours increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof the Government to the extent required by the Government. (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same* do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage m to be determined by His Majesty^ Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the company shall pay the amount duo for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is duo to causes beyond the control of the company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the company* and* in default of such agreement* the question shall be referred to two arbitrators* one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the political Resident) and the other by the Company* with power to appoint an umpire m case of disagreement* such arbitration to be held m England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 yiet. c.49* 24 and 25 Geo.V. c.14) of the Imperial parliament* or any for—.—. 6 • statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) ^he price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty's Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the. last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty's Government, if so required, particulars of the quantifies, descriptions and prices of oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty's Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty's Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and pr emiscs of the Company in and in such event the company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf oi Hi^ Majesty's Government. compensation shall be paid bo bho Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to h^v^ been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty's Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall bo settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government ana the Company/Telegram - Q. (Received via Muscat on ss Barpeta.) From Britconsul, Bushire To Political, Muscat No* 626 Dated 25th June 1957 Reed. 26th Your telegram No .88 or June the 24th. (a) Was concession for whole of Sultan’s territory or only part? (b) Did you make to Sultan general communication referred to in my correspondence ending with my telegram No.574 of June the 17th? (c) Was it stated in concession actually signed or by accompanying exchange of letters that con cession was subject to the approval of H.M.G? (d) Did you inform the Sultan during the present negotiations alternatively previously that H.M.G. would require Company to enter into separate political agree ment with them? 2. With regard to (c) and (d) see paragraph No .6 India Office telegram No.826 of March the £7th 1956, copy forwarded to you ..•««••• express letter No.C—27 of March the 9th 1956. 5 ^ If you have not by any chance taken action on (b), (c) and (d) please do not take action until you receive instructions from me. 4 Your letter dated May the_ 2 6th . Urge reply as I must telegraph to H.M.G. without Brtfe onsul - delay.Telegram - Q. From - Political, Muscat on board ss Barpeta. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No.R-1. Dated S7th June 1937. (Despatched from Gwadur on 28th June.) &lt;=/ | Your telegram No.626 of June 25th. (a) Two separate concessions were signed (l) for Dhofar (2) for remainder of Arabian territory of Sultanate. (b) This part of your telegram was badly mutilated. I shall endeavour to decypher from confirmatory copy sent Karachi on my arrival there June 29th. (c) This was not stated in concession or in accompany ing exchange of letters but Sultan and Lermitte were informed that concessions and certain additions insisted on by Sultan were subject to approval of H.M.G. (d) Sultan was informed previously and from subsequent conversations it is evident that he fully understands the point. Company did not apply for Gwadur. - Political -Telegram - Q. From - Britconsul, Bushire. To - Political, Muscat at Karachi. No.642. Dated and received the 29th June 1937. /* Important . Your telegram No.R~l of June 28th. Re (c) and (d) was Sultan informed verbally or in writing? - Britconsul -Telegram - Q. From - Political, Muscat at Karachi. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No.R-3. Dated the 30th June 1937. / (.1 Important, Your telegram No.626 of 25th June. Your telegram No.574 of 17th June instructing me to take oertain action arrived on 18th June when negotiations with Sultan had commenced and general atmosphere was so unexpectedly favourable and hopeful that at that stage I considered I should await developments before taking that action. In my opinion the signing of the concession has made it unnecessary. Your telegram No.642 of 29th June. Verbally. - Political -A Telegram - Q. From - Political, Muscat at Karachi. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No.B~5. Dated 1st July 1937. Your telegram No.626 of June 25th. Your paragraph 4 not understood, please telegraph No. and subject matter of my letter dated May 26th refensd to. - Political -L % Telegram - From To No,669, Dated 2nd Reed. 3rd Q. Britconsul, Bushire. Political, Muscat at Karachi. July 1937. -h Your telegram No.R-5 of July 1st. Please telegraph after checking your reference what is subject with which your telegram deals. My telegram 626 June the 25th which you dealt with Oil and made no reference to any letters of yours. - Britconsul - POLITICAL GENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Date. 3 - JUL .oJ/ rte* N* /y. H, B, M’S CONSULATE; MU8QT. [POLITICAL / CENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Date. 3 ~ JUL .jo/ Reg, ^o,/g. H, I. H'8 CONSULATE; MUSCAT, Telegram - Q. From ~ Briteonsul, Bushire. No.673. Dated and received 3rd July 1937. Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Government of India and Muscat. My telegram No.584 of June 18th. Muscat Oil . Concession was signed at Muscat June the 24th. This celer^ity reflects credit on Lermitte and Watts. 2. Separate concessions were signed (one) for Dhofar (two) for remainder of Arabian territory of Sultanate. Company did not apply for Gwadur. I am awaiting further details by post. 3. Communication to Sultan referred to in correspon dence ending with your telegram No.1658 of June 17th. My instructions to Watts to take action reached him on June 18th By then negotiations with Sultan had already commenced and • general atmosphere was so favourable that Watts considered that he should await developments before taking action. 4. it was not stated in concession or by accompanying exchange of letters that concession was subject to approval of H.M.G., but Sultan and i were informed accordingly by Watts verbally. 5. Previous to negotiations Sultan was informed verbally by Watts that H.M.G. would require Company to enter into separate political agreement. 6. I presume that on receipt from Company of copy of concession by H.M.G. political agreement will be signed after which notes as in case of Dubai will have to be excnanged between Sultan and Political Agent? I suggest that drafts should be sent me and Political Agent by A.ir Mail, 1 i tjz fy Telegram From To No.674. Britconsul, Bu shire. Political, Muscat at Karachi. Dated and received 5rd July 1937. Paragraph No.S of your telegram No.88 of June 24th. Please telegraph when I may expect details byJL Telegram - Q* From - Political, Muscat at Karachi. To - Britconsul, Bushire. No.R -9. Dated the 4th July 1937. Reference your telegram No.674 of July Srd. Details are being posted to you by Air Mail leaving Karachi July the 6th.Telegram - Q A From - Political, Muscat. To - Britconsul, Busnire. Mo. 75 Dated the 16th June 1937. Heierence your telegram Mo.517 of June 5th. Muscat Oil. 2. Lermitte arrived yesterday evening and had interview with Sultan today. Suitan stated that he had divided up his territory into 3 separate groups each of which would have to form separate concession (a) Gwadur (b) Dhofar (c) remainder of all Muscat territory including Omani 3. Sultan in his letter to me of xlth June(vide my telegram 69 of June 12th) had written that he would grant only portion of his territory to Petroleum Concessions but Lermitte informs me that Sultan this morning definitely stated he was not adverse to granting all 3 groups if terms were satisfactory. 4. Lermitte has cabled his London Office for instructions.CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to i • The Secretary to the OQvvimxi nt oP India in the Department of External Affairs* Simla Z» fhe Political Agent* Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). x ipt- ■&gt; 7 . British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. Reference to previous correspondence: ^tndia Office Express Letter 3099/ 37 dated 11th May 1937. U S Description of Enclosure, Name and Date, Subject, Political Resident's telegram .473* dated 26th May 1937. Standard Oil Company and Muscat.§ Muscat 24th June 19 37* rr r J.C, H.E.M’s Political Agent, Muscat, Pear Sir, 4 I enclose herewith in duplicate, certified copies of aminendments to Agreements signed to-day 'between the Sultan of , Muscat and Oman and Petroleum Concessions Ltd.z. Notes ©n alterations in agreements 1* Tiie words “His Highness” were erased in order to bring the agreements into linej with the treaties at present in force between the Sultan and H.B.ttfa Government. The words * in whom is or shall fce vested for the time Government being the responsibl ity for the control and/agx*M»mt of th *3 Sultanate of Muscat and Oman' were erased for the same reason. age 5. The words 'of which the Company tfc* shall be the sole 7 The words”as far as possible” were taken dislike to. rflcle 16 age B* 3 * The words ' as mentioned in article 6 ' appear in the age 11# London was considered too far he having fill now only rtlcle 13 ( c) Judge” were taken dislike t© rticle 26 (•) visited India# . . ■' ' Vv owdfcrv VTelegram - C. C. From — Political, Bahrain* No.246. Dated 1st July 1937. Received 5th July via Muscat under their 739. Addressed to Sloop, repeated to Muscat. Your telegram of 8th June. Presume that 33. Is it not? Lermitte through Wratislaw begins:- 'Inform Political expect to arrive Bahrain July the 11th by Air. Successfully concluded Muscat. n - Political - \lo.iuae/io. Catea, Raraohl, tae 5th July 1937. From Political Ag«nt f Muscat at Ear&amp;ohl To tarn iiontbia the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Busaire* of July 4th*, 1937* I forward herewith details of the Oil Concession granted by Els Highness txi« Bui ten of Muscat and Oimn to Petrol owa Concessions Ltd* the hultan has given two separate eonceasi:&gt;ns for his Arabian territories (a) for Bhof&amp;r (b) for the remainder of the sultanate* The Petroleum Concessional Ltd were not interests in Gwadur and did not therefore ap;ly for a concession for that place. 3* The hult&amp;n nas insisted on certain alterations, chiefly deletions being made in the draft ooaoasslons and some additional articles being incorporated. The alterations together with the nece^^ary Insertions are given In the following paragraphs and the additional articles in the attached schedule. 4 , xce references &amp;re to the articles numbered in tae Printed Draft Concession tiie latest revised copy of -mien If received from Major Holmes at Hiiarjah on May 16th and of which a copy, I understand, was also forwarded to you. (i) kttzv :ns flr^t after the As mentioned In ny telegram Mo.k~l of Juris 27th words 'This is an agreement made at** insert the words 'Muscat on the twenty fourth clay of June/(IS) Article £6 (q). Delete tne word ^London^ and sub^tltu’ce 'Muscat »\ (14) Article 27 Li.ne_A. After the words 'at the' insert 'Eastern Bank Ltd*, Karachi w , h. 1 the draft of the Dhofar Coneession the details of the additions, alterations and insertions mentioned in para graph 4 above are similar except in the following instances*- (a) Reference to item (4) in para 4 above* Article 1* (a) Line r. of Draft * Delete the words 'Sultanate of Muscat and Oman' and substitute 'tne district caxled hhofur'* Line 7 . Delete the words 'Sultanate of 'Muscat and Oman- and substitute n the district called Dhofar'* (b) Reference to item (6) of para 4 above* For 'one lac of rupees' read 'thirty thousand rupees'* (c) Reference to itm8(7) of para 4 above. - Article 4 of Draft . For 'five thousand a month' read 'three thousand a month'. For 'three hundred thousand in all' read 'one hundred and eighty thousand in all'. (d) Reference to item (8) of para 4 above* Ar ticle 8 of, Draft. For '3j 00,010' read '1,80,000'. (e) Reference to item (9) of para 4 above, Artlcl« 6 ImI of Irtut. (a) Bor 'one Uuadred thousand' read 'thirty thousand'm* ViiobacJ* Mow Qn# &amp;$£le(I .A. _$n LI . ^ X oJ: 1 i.A (i*X) vi^disixi ^aricf &amp;z' aMow s^a (tllw&amp;z on# aotce^onoO ifrloxU &amp;tL# to ai# &amp; «d ^t/?q ai bnB yCrrol^lbbd a/lX *$mn$zal sttJtwoliot $&amp;$ at $qeox&amp; inttmle 9as »toc&amp; .4 dq^iB # avocfa # rsi {^) u©ii o# ooxi^f/alon (b) • , r , 4. 0 , ?! x Ji«.T ^ *,, ‘ . ^S;0 t.t%k, baB inouaU to &amp;$ mw$ IsiB,* a blow oia s &amp;&amp;ilso e#i&gt;2rio cdiffi b£tB n ii3s;C * . sOuaM ‘to ®v a-o-rc:*w »iicr b^IIao M;.j” Bisfi ’'ns.nO £&gt;££B . rt *mloiiu; * ©vod a to (b) i«e^i o# soco^xoiob (d)(b) For ’Eighty four thoumnS* r#-ad -‘forty eight thousand w • (c) For Tl ninty .thousand ^ 1 road w sixty tiiousand w * 0 ^ Hiregard to toe various Ite&amp;s ^.ntioiied ih paragraphs 4 and 5 above the only ones which appear to call for oossmeirM *?• tht followl'^41- (f)f (^) (4) were insisted upon by the Balt&amp;n iii order to bring the wording of the Agreement into line with that of the treaties In force between hi« and Hi 3 Majesty 1 # Government, Xtee. (4) eugge-1# the question of the Sul tan* s reepon.eibi.lity for the safety of the eii.ployeee of the uoapaay wa ,n working in his tarrltori,*. I refer to this point in anotiier part of ay letter. Items (ID) and ftl). • the word*, deleted were objected to by the Mltoft, Item (IB), the words were in the Arabic teat but had been omitted evidently through an oversight from the ingllah version. Item (14), bondon wa# objected to by tae Sultan aa being too far away, additions and amendments to tiie articled ^or incorporation la the Craft of the Concession as e«ntion,d in By paragraph 3 above are given in the attached seaednles asarked •fe' and *B» respectively. The only iteis wnich calls for oom ent is 8o»4 of 'A'. me sultan declare... that now h* ha4 got into peraonal touen with Petroled Conee^ion, Ltd terough their Representative «r. Ler.»itte, he did not wish that 4,y shoula transfer their rights to any other Company. ate objection was overcome by aa,ing the worn* «airect subsidiary in front in line 6 of Article : 3, of the word «Coa.pftny« 8./Telegram From To No.R-16. Dated the - Q. Political, Muscat at Karachi. Britconsul, Bushire. 8th July 1957. / Your telegram 669 of July 2nd. Last 9 groups of your telegram 626 of 25th June read begins:- Your letter dated May the 26th. Urge reply as I must telegraph to H.M.G. without delay. Ends. - PoliticalTelegram Q. From Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi. To Political hesiaent, Bashire. No. R-22. Dated 12th duly 1937. Reference my express letter R-82 July 5th. Lermitte having received instructions from his hondon office paid to Sultan yesterday for the 2 Concessions Rs. 1,30,000 initial payment together with Rs. 48,000 as three months advance of monthly payments.p,Z.3842/37. Express letter from Secretary of State for India to political Resident in the Persian Gulf repeated to Government of India,External Affairs Department,Political Agent,Bahrein,Dated 3rd July,1937. Please see letter from petroleum Development (Trucial Coast)Ltd.dated 11th June (copy enclosed to Bushire and Bahrein, copy sent to Government of India by sea mail of 24th June) forwarding a note regarding the status oz the territory immediately to the west of the Oman mountain range. 2. I should be glad of your observations on the points raised by the Company, and in particular on the question whether, in the event of a clear and comprehensive definition of boundaries and authorities in this area being impossicle for the present, the Company might be permitted to make its own arrangements with the various fi’ival leaders in de f acto control of the area. 3. It is understood that the Company are anxious to consider their programme of exploration for next cold weather at an early date and it would be convenient to have your views as soon as possiole. (sd.) M.J.Clauson. The issue of the above has been duly authorised/ y P.Z.3637/37. PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TPUCIAL COAST) LIMITED PC.28/367. City-Gate House ? FinsDury Square ? London? E.C.2, 3rd June? 1937 Dear Mr. Clauson? Your letter P.Z.2910/37 dated the 26th May. The verbal amendments which you have suggested in the common form of the Political Agreements to be made between H.M.G. and the Company in respect of future oil concessions in the Persian Gulf have been duly considered and found to be unobjectionable. The Company has three small amendments to suggest. Clause 3 . It is suggested that the words ’’foreign native labour” might conceivably give offence? and that they should be replaced by the words ”artisans or other workers not indigenous to. Clause 7 . It is suggested that there is no valid reason for excluding from the concession area sites selected for defence purposes? etc.? provided the Company is precluded from occupying the surface thereof except with the specific consent of H.M.G. To give effect to this suggestion it is proposed that the following alterations should be made in Clause 7:- In lines 3 and 4? substitute for the words ’’and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations” the words ’’the surface of”? And before the words ’’such harbours” in the twelfth line insert the following:- ’’such sites as aforesaid (which right shall be exclusive) and ”C) v 2 . I enclose a re-draft of Clause 7 embodying these alterations. Sub.J.-i j rU^se 4 of the Pre-emption Clause . Should oil be produced it is probable that the oil v/ould be sold to shareholders at a privileged rate, which v/ould be below the free market price. It is therefore suggested that after the v/ords 'to other customers' in the fifth line of the second paragraph of this Sub-clause ? the v/ords '‘other than shareholders' should be inserted. Yours sincerely* (Sgd•) F. LEWISOHN Clauson, Esq.* India Office* Whitehall * S.W.l.RE-DRAFT OF CLAUSE 7. 7. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy the surface of any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government for defence purposes ? for aerodromes? aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or in connection with the development of harbours? provided that with the consent of His Majesty’s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such sites as aforesaid (which right shall be exclusive) and such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control.- 2 - the general liability under the agreement of the Sultan*a suecess ora. The deletion of this phrase in no way lessens the Sultan* a responsibility for the safety of the personnel etc. of the Company which is clearly laid down in Article 17. (3) Schedule A. Amendment no.3 Article 23. There is no objection to the substitution of the words rt to any direct subsidiary Company’* instead of M to any other Company'S (4) Schedule A. Amendment iso#4. Petroleum Concessions Limited are a British Company and if the ex-t err it or ial rights granted to British subjects by the Muscat Treaty of ,1891 give total exemption from taxes except those definitely mentioned in the Treaty ( a question on which I am addressing you separately;, then this tax would be in contravention of the Treaty. On the other hand, as the Company themselves, who are aware or should be aware of the Treaty, have agreed to pay I do not think we need obj ect. ( b ) schedule A. Amendment jso.6. 'The Sultan ioay apply to the Company to send the person concerned - if a foreigner - out of the Sultanate'. The Company can of course dismiss aqy foreign employee. If this foreign employee is a non- British subject the sultan can deport him, but if a British subject then he falls under the jurisdiction of the political Agent, and the Company will have to apply to the Political Agent for deportation of the individual complained of. Such an application would rarely be necessary since once an individual had been dismissed and paid off by the Company ne would hardly choose to stay on in mscat as a gentleman at large. 1 do not think /-3- &amp; think that any action is necessary on this amendment. 4. I have made no comments on the financial terms but the qultan would appear to have made a good bargain. i have already commented on the commendable celerity with which the concession was obtained (vide paragraph 1 of ray telegram quoted above) and it may be that the activity of the Company and their representa tive in Muscat, in contrast to their dilatory methods on the ^racial Coast, was partly due to the stim^las applied to them referred to in paragraphs 2 and 3 of your telegram Mo. 1541 of the 1st June 1937. sd. T.C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian uulf. At test ed« for secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.&gt;fSf vei GOVERNMENT OF INDU, confidential Department, EXPRESS LETTER [jV. B—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Subject: Truci&amp;l Coast and Muscat Oil# Reference India Office Sxprees Letter ao.^.Z.3843/37# dated the 3rd July 1937. 2. X aee no poeeibility of a clear and coaprenene ive definition of boundaries and of authorities in this area being at all possible. This being so I imagine that the only thing to do would be to let the Company make its own arrangements, as far as they are able to do so, with the various tribal leaders in de facto, control of tne area, in other words for the Company to feel their way. ny tais means some rough idea may be obtained as to what rulers have effective control POLITICAL AND From Political Resident, CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Bush ire. Date. 2 6. JUL 193/ Kegr, No,/?-///;/'. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Political A&amp;ent, Muscat, at Zii——~ No. 556-1 of 1937 thied 19th July over /over what areas* 5* Tiie Company will of course have to keep in close touch with Political Agents Bahrain and Muscat through the Residency Agent, lharjah, and will have to progress discreetly to avoid being shot up* 4. Please let me have your views as soon as poss bl@ t and I will reply to the India Office.By Air Mail. p.z. wVin POLITICAL AGENCY AND INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, CONFIDENTIAL record Date. 2 3. Jl)L. 1937 1W, No, /1 f- H, B, M'S CONSUL AT f; MUSCAT Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to 4963 2000 7.36CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/159 of l 967 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian compliments to Gulf presents his Major R. r. Watts, I.A. Political Agent, Muscat, at liarat. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s), I POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD IVe. 4 - AUG. 1937 - Jtfif | H, B, y.VS C0NSUtAT£; MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BITS HI RE- Bated..tJJXA.&lt;ixGi..3.Uiy.#. .lid}-*? • Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Express Letter No.556-S of 1957 anted the 19th duly, 1957. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Bahrain Agency Letter No. Trucial Coast and Muscat C/559-25/4 dated 10.7.*57. Oil. Residency Letter No.C/158 dated 25.7.*37, to Capt. T. Hickinbotham. political Resident’s teiegian No.T/125 ci ted 26.7.’37 to Political Agent, Bahrain.So.* C/5SS- 35/4 Po lit leal .Agency f Bah^t-ln^ the 10th ML^ 193?* From Captain f* Hlclsliibotiia&amp; # I*A., Political Agent* Bahrain* fo the Honourable th© Political Besiclent in %hm Persian Gulf* Bua&amp;ire* Sir* 1 have the honour to refer to India Office Ek- pros© letter Bo* P*2* 384^3? dated the 3rd luly 193?. I have had the tpeetion #iich form the substance of the enclosure to the India Office letter under reference under consideration for bqw&amp; tlm and last a»nth I tent,: tlve enquiries itiile I was on the frueial Coast and I had intended to pursue investigations on ay return to Siarjah, but the arrival of this letter has brcm^it natters to a head and I am, therefore, address ing you on the subject without being in possession of the amount of knowledge which X consider necessary to give a clear end decisive answer to the questions raised by the letter under reference* Um ill our treaties with the fruei&amp;X Bciaiklis, with three exceptions, arc what sight be described as factor- nal treaties* fhe ^jxceptions are the General Treaty of 15^ ho* 19 (page ?34b of J&amp;feehlson* s Tree-ties* Engage- mnts anci Eanads 1&amp;2B) which provided for the suppression of plunder and piracy by land and by sea and the Agreements of 19&amp;S! j^loau 34 and 35 (at page £61 of Aitchison»s Treaties,/-y /£ s S fy^aties, Engi;.go®ents and Batiads) ffhich pPOTidad for the e^erclaiag of the aright of api^oTal W His fc|®#* ty*s ^rena^nt before an Oil Concession could bo given to a foreigner. Until recent years our only contacts of Ippertwse were with the Coast line end we were prir^* elpally concerned with the ^iiatenance of peace an the High Seas. He were not anxious for eoffiidtisents in the interior of the States which bordered the frucial Coast and* therefore* we have even to the present day refrala^d as «cti as possible from direct or indirect interference in their private affairs. Our treaties with the excep tions noted above were designed %o suppress piracy* sup press arms trade* and to oppress tb© slave trad#* aM for this .purpose they were made with the filers cised control on the Sea Coast* We have never endeavor-' #4 to enter into treaty relations with the CSiiefs who exercised power in the interior* B* fhe advent of Oil mist alter our policy on the fra ctal Coast and in sy opinion the tiise has now com wim m will have to penetrate into the interior and get In touch with the Balers of 2rib#$ living boyond the areas over the fracial Bmlkhs exercise control. We are faced wito two problem* fhe first of these is m&gt;st dif ficult* ana th&amp;t is the demrcation of interstate bouix2a- ries* the secom problem is to decide #iat tribal rulers actually exercise control in the areas which lie east and south-east of the fracial Bh&amp;ilshdoas. 4* fhe necessity for the demarcation of interstate boundaries is brought about by the individual concessions which/-© - ftiieh 8®mem±®m h±wlt®&amp; mtm obtaiBing tvom the mo$Mw on the frueial toast* PetroXeu® toneessioas Id lilted quite naturally ar# ansJlous to taiiow exaetly for what airaunt of territory they are buying cosoe^sioas aad the earn ti^ the frueiaX ftiaiklri is anxious^ ^epeeiali; ih the event of Oil being discovered^ to cl&amp;is. as such territory as he possibly can* fh# present boundaries bet ween the States are not demarcated with agy accuracy and I as doubtful if any of fete frueiel aisildxs thewelsee can accurately describe where their territorial boundaries run* It is probable that the wandering tribes and the persons living on the edge of the States concerned to know roughly where the boundaries lte 9 but there are la.i*ge areas Mxieli no side hm been ansdous to claim* Areas in ^aich there is no water t no vegetation and no graaing for flocks and easels* fhe advent of oil has made these are s potentially as rito m areas where tlxere Is water and gracing and now the indi vidual Bm3Mm are anxious to claim m such laM f however barren, as they possibly can* this will give rise to boun dary disputes between the axaiklxs, even along benssdaries ^lic^i are fairly dearly defined, that is, the northern aM southern boundaries of the various States* Already a dispute has arisen between the iSi&amp;lMi of Aim Hiabi aisd the aiaiMi of mbai regarding their satual .frontiers * Hie tra cing of the northern boundaries and the southern boundaries of the individual States could probably be done without a great deal of difficulty by a Political Officer and the Hesl&amp;eney Agent acting in consultation with the representa tives of the Shaikhs on either side of the boundary* this will of course take time but it will be relatively easy work cospared with the task of deciding what I aay describe as the/-©^rcising considerabie eoutrol in the mtm of Jebei ii'ii* i#cl^i!s@d W imd mrWtmi'&amp;s m far as the eastern boundaries of Has al Kbali^h and southward as far as flaiw&amp;iu flies© eacruiries of min© are very superficial and it is prob. ble tliat a consi derably larger area is claimed the l^isd Sltab the»» selves^ I gather that they are acknowledged as having e certain area Miieii would lie rcm#ily ‘between the points t have ssentioned and that ttey exercise consider- able control - so such control timt the Bt&amp;lMx of pariah for last, no© ^uld find it difficult to interfere with them. Becentiy the p&amp;ramuzm Sb&amp;t$s&amp; of the 'Beni ICit&amp;b, bln Hi # ccused the aialidi of Has al aaimsh consider-: 'ble anxiety, Ooiiig further south we e&amp;m to the Buraiai area .and it appears 'to m tout Buraiist is not moiely under the m&amp;£Mi of Mm Hiabi as X had pre vious^ believed* He occupies two or three of the villaJ ges on the Burr; imi plain £-nd he has a representative li ving at the village of Ai Aisu ihis represent: tiw # Xb- r ^h iv bin Utli^xu exercises control in the absence of the Shaikh, rue control is only exercised over that part of -BuralM of ^bu iiubi. ihe s^jor portion of Biraiml# is X believe, in the hands of the Halm* £h© Mlm are a tribe which ex- tmod for soaie distance to the ^otith^ east and north of Biraiml and are ruled by two brothers, iSiaim Sager bin Sultan and efmlhh H&amp;h&amp;mmd bin Salten* X understand that the youngw broths* ShnlMt Sag^r Mu Sultan escercises cortrol over tw@-tMrds of tm tribe &amp;* opposed to the onm—third undem 1 the control of his brother MMh&amp;WB&amp;e* menagala im taTO tfom 3&amp; ^bleh is tribe living In tlw Boraint area and itesc' ebief is Saqar bin auXtan al Hamt mo writes hiimelf as Cliief of Buv&amp;iiit* Ee la said to own an area about tb# si a# of too Sbaiish- dom of 4 |wn de addressed a letter to tba ResMeaey i^gont in October of last jmx to the effoet that he ms anxious to couse into relations with us end h© inritea sosi© one to go to kis country for the purpose of discus sing an ugree^ant which he mished to negotiate (nothing has been dons)* Then going further south-east we cone to 'the ar^a between BuraAtH at'id Bbri* This is said to be under tha control partly of the Bi ^taads partly of the iuroor tribe md partly under the control of the Ibrien £tudkh * ^Mullah bin Bsi^iid. It Is clear that &amp; considerable amount of touring will have to be done before we can say that me mow ar^thing about tails part of the world* and the sooner it is undertaken the better* I do not know to ..mtofc extent the persons rnd tribes that I have mnt toned are said to be- under the con trol of the Suit an of Unseat but I do mim that they el&amp;ia independence* Unfortunately as I have not got Jjorrisasr with m — I left tlx® book at a^srjah inteMli^ to return. th#r^ mim quicker than I have been able to do — I have been unable to refer to tills lyork of reference with regard to the area and tribes I have s^tioned. 6 * It seem to me that the msomr we op^a up oom-uni- eittiou with trie- tribes of the interior the better and that can best be done by extensive tours by the Political 4 fent t 'Baiirtiin^ and the iiesidency igent* Shariah* during the eoadng cola weather* tic mist ascertain before we endeavour to■■ Jm demrcate or trace frontiers is in aetmi control of the areas to be traced and to ^£k&gt;% if any one ly or wrongly the Shaikh in control ov^es allegiance til we have decid ed this question - and it can only decided by personal eontnot ©d it is not passible for us to trace frontiers any likelihood of pcrsmnene©.* X am not in favour of permitting employees roieum Concessioris limited to become- political officers and negotiate agreements with the people they consider be d© facto rulers* they are not experts in work sort as X presusie Petroleum Concessions Id. sited mm for their knowledge of surveying and not for diplomatic abilities* X thli&amp; it would be unwise us to permit the Coapany to enter into agreements which we too* nothing and with persons with whose status we are uncertain* It would lead to endless trouble ami in the event of any unfortunate accident occurring such as the murder of one- of the survey party we should find ourselves surrounded by a mss of agree- mmtB with petty Shaikhs ami possibly discover that the principal ruler Mid never been consulted and was bound by agreement and, therefore, refused to- tate any pu nitive action* He would mat cert inly disown agreements between the Cai!|&gt;any sand Chiefs whom he considers to be subordinate to him* a* It would be advisable for the Company to be per- suadecl to confine the majmr i&gt;ortion of their activities to the northern part of the Peninsuls #iere the problem is not so great, and leave this cold weather for us to ciideavour to *£dfc© contacts and penetrate into th# cast and south-eastern portion of the frucial Coast BhaiMidoi^ with/-with a view to obtaining a toowle&amp;ge of tii© t&gt;eopie &amp;nd th© coimtx^? and coising to ai^r agraewats wiiich j»e^ soesi neeosoarar to faailiteto the work of the Company in future years, if tiie Co^any eonsider it essential to oontime work in tne m&amp;Ws&amp;mmt&amp;m area that is ibu UmiM and be yond, then I thii^c that as soon as possible I and the hesidenc^r Agent at Sharjah should proceed to Bur&amp;iai with a view to getting in touch with the -people, in particular the leader of the Bu Shamis and the leaders of the B&amp;iu* Um the advent of the Air liaison Officer is within the next two or three days to be equipped with a li#it aircraft ^iauld. very such assist us in our task of obtain ing contact, for he will be just as anxious to obtain con tact with the Xaeal people in the interior as the Officers of the Political DepartE=exit* X think that Vm Hoyal Mr force say be interested in flying directly from Abu Dhabi to Baaeat and the est&amp;bMshjpent of a landing ground at l^tralffii might b© eonsiaereb favourably b v them* 0se could be made by the Political Agent of the facilities offered by the presence of the Mr liaison Officer and his aircraft to proceed to such places as Baraial fairly often during the cold weather and. for periods at a tiiae* It would always h@ possible to sum., tents by camel transport to BuraiM under the care of the BmiMi of Abu Dhabi and for me Political Agent, etcetera, to arrive later by Mr, the cusp being struck after his departure. 10* X regret very mica that the information contained in this letter is very sketchy and by no mtm&amp; accurate, hub the Inaccuracy is due to the fact that X have no local knowledge of me areas concerned and X have not found, soL n n I to eontinu© ^miuiries with tho obj^et of obtaining tsore knowledge of the area in ciuestion* ii# I Jiot© neked ^oadinacm to sign for ns aa I cannot get the letter faired before leading for ahmrjsh* X have the honour to 'he. Sir, lour aost obedient servant, Sd/~ B.L. Tginiinson. fox Political A, I i IOffice of the Politic in the Persian Gulf, Camp Shiraz. D.O.Ko.C/lM The 25th July, 1957. My dear HicKinbotham i Could you please refer to India Office express letter Ho.P.Z.354K/u7 of 3rd July, 1037 and your letter Ho.C/S&amp;i^SJd/A aateo the 10th July, 1937 on the subject ox Petroleum Concessions LirBlted’s desire to explore In the hinterland of Trucial Oman. they talk of carrying out their exploration by giving presents to the de facto rulers, is that it will not be a cese of buying their way, as a traveller often has to do through tribal territory, but of buying oil rj-Khtaj. As 1 see it, when bhaikh X, the ae fa£t&amp; petty biiaikh of the Y araa&gt; i S approached by the Company to allot, an exploratioi party to enter nis area in return for a cash present, lie will think to himself that if he agrees he sill thereby surrender his rights to oil in the X area. Before giving permission therefore he will, X imagine, want a sepatate concession from the Company. As there are presumably manj such petty Shaikhs in the hinterland, this will involve tne Company in a series of expensive concessions, ana their position would become impossible. g. There is, I think, however, little doubt that all the territory which the Company wish to explore belongs oe Jure either to some Trucial bhaikh or to the Muscat State, with both of which parties the Company has concessions. The oil rights of the petty ae_Xa£to Shaikhs would therefore not arise. Doubtless some of the claims Wbfet tiie Company, I think, do not realise, when -/of the Captain T. HlcKinboth&amp;m, Political Agent, Bahrain.//&lt;/ oi' the Truclal Hhaiiihs will clash as between tneiBselve. ana as between one or more of them and Muscat, e,g. Baraimi, to which the Multan lays claim, but they need not be gone into for the moment. i SUB— dm It seems to i-e therefore that the first step is for you and Watts to ¥?o-rk out respectively from the Trucial Coast Shaikhs, and from the Sultan, what part of the ninter- land is claimed by themrespectively, with the grounds fur their claims* This first step ought noz to take very long as it is merely a case of the parties concerned putting up their claims, and does not involve any inspection of the areas nor, at this stage, of reconciling r^vai claims, 4* The next step woulu be to test how much area the Trucial Coast Shaikhs effectively control* It seems to me that no amount of examination can clear up this point, which can only be ascertained by test cases, I think therefore that some area, Y, to which the Company wish to send an exploration party should be enosen* The Trucial Shaikh in whose territory Y was situated would, in his capacity of overlord address tne petty Shaikh, X, to the effect that exploration party was visiting it* Should X make no difficult-' ies well and good* If not, it would be up to the Truei&amp;i Coast Shaikh either by force, bribery, or diplomacy, or ail combined, to bring X round* from tne Shaikh’s point of view it would be decidedly to his advantage to have i area explored, and he could bribe Sheikh X by offering him either a substantial present from the money he had received from the Company or by promising him a percentage of tne royalties if oil were subsequently found in Y area* The above procedure may seem somewhat tortuous, and will of course take time, but X thina it is tue best in the circumstances, ana until we Know how things from the de facto point of view stand in the hinterland it would be -/betterTelegram From R. 17 nL Political FeM.runt, Bub hire, at Shiraa. To Political Agent, Bahrain Copy by poat to Major Watte, Ziarat. Ho. T/125 Dated 26th July 1937. 4 Your letter Ho. C/539 of 10th July. When Company talk of carrying out their exploration by giving pre^ente to the he facto Shaikhs they no not reallee that it will roost likely be a cane of buying oil LS£&amp;*&gt;JL and not merely passage through territory. Since there are presumably many finch petty Shaikhs in the hinterland this will Involve Company in a eeries of ex pensive oil agreements which will make their position impossible. that all the territory which the Company wish to explore belongs M jure either to some Trrcial Shaikh or to the would therefore not arise. 3 . But whatever policy we adopt first step is for you to ascertain from Trucial Coast Shaikhs what portion of the hinterlana is claimed respectively by them, ana the grounds of their claims. 4 . Thie should not take very long as it is merely a ease oi the Shaikhs concerned putting up their 2 . There Is, I think, however, little doubt Muscat State, with both of which parties the Company has concessions. The oil rights of the petty de facto Shaikhs t •/5. Please instruct Residency Agent to begin thie investigation which I would grateful if you could complete on yonr way to recess* Question ol Crucial frontiers was exacined by Loch in i Q 35 but thi« was in connection with Saudi frontier and did not co^er moat of hinterland where Company wish to explore .* FOWLS,CONFIDENTIAL / (W) 590-3 of 1937 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Secretary to the uovernraent of India in the External ilffairs Department, Simla* g* Captain T.Hickinbotham, I.A* Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi* 3* Major H.I.Watts, I*A. / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). __________ India Office Express Letter iyo* 1,2.384^27, dated 3rd July, 1937* only * U}* Political Resident’s letter (2) India Office letter petroleum Concessions Lim- 4834/37 of 24th July, 1937* ited of area adjacent to (3) petroleum Concessions Lim ited letter P*C*28/ o, 4l6of 21st July, 1937,. to India Office* l4} Bushire letter ?b. 589-3 of 5th Autdist, 1937, to India Office. 1 ♦ 'Bie Hon’ble It*Col*A*E*3,Parsons, C.B.E*,B.3.0. — • .fM, « MM, Political Agent, Muscat, at Ziarat* ^ mm POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD Gate. 12.AUG. 133/ h p g &lt;7/ H, 8, M’S CONSULATE; MUSCAT, British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated 5 th • AM gu st*,' -19 37 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Tfo * C/158 of 25th July, 1937 to Captain Hickinbothara. proposed exploration byAir Mall (non secret) India Office* Whitehall, S.W.l. 24 th Jul^-, 1937 • 4634/37 My dear Fowle, Would you kindly refer to our Express Letter of the 3rd July 23b* p*3*3842/37 shout the proposed exploration by letrolema Concessions Ltd*, of the area adjacent to the Osan mountain range t I now enclose a further letter fro© the Company which explains Itself* We Tery much hope that it may be possible for you to let us have your views on this before you come horse* Yours sincerely, 3d* J*C. WAX,TOW*P.Z. 48 34/37. pe troleum Concessions Ltd., City-Gdte House, Finsbury Square, London, JS.c.2. P.C.28/m&gt;. 416. 21st July, 1937. Bear Mr. Walton, I write to remind you of my letter of June 11th and the attachment thereto on the subject of conditions in the hinter land of the Trucial Shaikhdoms, west of the main Ctean range of Mountains. It is still our intention to send Geologists to pursue exploration of this area (or as much of it as possible) in the forthcoming Autumn. At the same time, the question of this region has become more, rather than less, interesting to us since we acquired a Concession for the territories of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Ihe area immediately concerned is that of Jebel -fi*ayah and country of the south and south east thereof, country east and south of the Barairal Oasis with Jebel Hafit, and to the south and south east thereof. Ihe question which interests us is, to what extent may our ; arty, which will be, as before led by Mr.T.H. Williamson, expect the blessing of, or prohibition of restriction from the Political Kesident if it endeavours to make its own way into these territories, guided only by various decrees of Geological interest ? Or what procedure of^form- / ality can be suggested to secure the party the maximum ireedom \ of movement, consistent with Safety V As the time is now near when our Autumn programme must be established, such assistance as you can give us towards answering these questions will be greatly appreciated. Yours sincerely, Sd. Stephen H* Longrigg. J.C. Walton, C.i3*&gt; M.v*. India Office, London.4963 2000 7.36 By Air Mail. p.z. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, '1 ik /^?*) Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. ' | POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL hecord —..vy —• Date, 1 4. AUG. 1937 Reg, H. B, ITS CONSULATE; MUSCAT, A copy lias been sent to by Mai1 ']&gt;'%. 3842/37. PC. 28/374. D.O. P2TH0L5TJM mWLOSmM (CRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED, City-Gate House ? Finsbury Square 5 London^ E.C.2. 11th June, 1937. Dear Mr. Walton, As agreed hetvveen us yesterday afternoon, the ICth instant, I am sending you a short note containing such information as we have on conditions in the hinterland south and south-east of the Trucial Coast. It would appear from this that certain areas which might possibly contain conditions favourable for oil are outside the effective control of the Trucial Coast rulers, with whom we are already in touch and from whom we hope to obtain concessions. The question which therefore arises - that is, with whom we ought to deal in such cases, and with whom you are willing that we should deal - is one which we cannot long delay facing, and this for two reasons: firstly, the extent of their effectively controlled hinterland eventually affects the value- of concessions which the Trucial shaikhs may grant for access to the inlying areas. v Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) Stephen H. Gouring. SncJ /V alt or: India Office Whitehall842/37. KCt'T OK COKDITIOKS IK TBS HIKTBRLAKD SOUTH aku south-east op the trucial coast. P.C.L. Geologists v/ho worked on the Trucial Coast, generally hased on Dubai, during the cold weather of 1936/37, report that not the least interesting area is likely to lie immediately to the west of the Oman mountain range, running south-east to north-west and south to north. Tre area concerned thus includes presumably the inlying portion^ or the territory under the real or nominal control of the Trucial Coast rulers. The Company is, however, without information as to the distance inland covered by the effective authority of these rulers, as well as their boundaries inter se and the extent to which nomadic or shepherd tribes in the interior are to be regarded as their subjects. In respect of the area under particular reference - that is, the crescent west of the Oman ranges - there appear to be other possible claimants to power. These are, firstly, the Sultan of Muscat and Oman himself, doubtful as it may be how far his authority extends westwards of the mountains: secondly, the Imam of Oman (understood to be m some suit 01 relations with Ibn Saud) whose status appears to be quite independent of the Sultan of Muscat: thirdly, the inlying tribes themselves, and in particular the Beni Chittib (wno seem to control the Jebel Faiyah area and to owe no real allegiance to the Shaikh of Sharjah, who claims them), the Beni Cha'ah (possibly controlled to some extent by Bas-al- Khaimah) , the IIa 1 urn (who occupy Baraimi and label al Ao ' the Abu Shems (occupying Jebel Hafit and part o, ,he Baraimi Oa.s is ) . The Company's position is that it is anxious to send its Geologists to explore this country and, in feet, as much ofCompany the matter has been referred to arbitration under Article 26 of the Oompany T s Agreement with Tour Highness (which it is hereby agreed shall be applicable to the case) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which should be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then in these cases, as in the cases mentioned in Article 21 of the Company’s Agreement with Your Highness, but in no other, the Company agrees that you will be entitled to terminate the Agreement between the Company and yourself, and thar axl (A) t errit ory properties of the Company within (B ) Dhofar excluding Dhofar and Gwadur shall become your property and that they will hand over to you free of cost land granted to the Company by you and any lands or buildings which the Company may have bought and any houses or ^ buildings constructed by the Company and all other (A) yorr _ irremovable property of the Company within Tb] iihoxux territory excl uding 'Dhofar and Gwadur — — including the producing wells and borings which shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. fv v h A _ 4- -, 4- V| -1 a. 1 AT. T, ft T* f.n thfi It is assumed that You^ Highness will be guided by the advice of His Majesty’s Government in regard to exercising the right of termination of the Agreement under the terms of paragraph 3(b) above. Ma j e sty * confirmation of their acceptance of the arrangements in question and will communicate such confirmation to dourCompany the matter has been referred to arbitration under Article 26 of the Company T s Agreement with Tour Highness (which it is hereby agreed shall be applicable to the case) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which should be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then in these cases, as in the cases mentioned in Article 21 of the Company 1 s Agreement with Tour Highness, but in no other, the Company agrees that you will be entitled to terminate the Agreement between the Company and yourself, and that all (A) TQ ur territory properties of the Company within (B) Dhofar excluding Dhofar and Gwadur shall become your property, and that they will hand over to you tree of cost land granted to the Company by you and any lands or building which the Company may have bought and any houses or buildings constructed by the Company and all other (A) : Irremovable property of the Company within (B) Ihoxar territory excl uding Dhofar and Gwadur including the producing wells and borings which shall be handed over in reaso.uabl^y good order and repair. k' A /\ 4. Please let me have a reply to this letter to tne effect that Tour Highness understands the nature ox the arrangements as set out above and bhao you ai e r ie ! ^ ©b to agree to them. On receipt ox your repig His Majesty’s Government will obtain iron the Company j. vxm«l c o nf i r mat ion of their acceptance of oij.e ari question and will communicate such confirmation to lour .Hi ghne s s, ! i? p Usual Er/ding.After Compj.iinente, In rejjly to your letter Ko» equivalent to the miorir, you that I have taken notice of the conditions set out in your above mentioned letter and that I agree to them* dated the I beg toa h Alter Compliments, reference to the Agreement signed by Your Highness on the 24-th June 1937 granting Petroleum Concessions Limited an oil concession in respect of 1 1\ excluding Dhofar and Gwadur I nave oeen directed by His Majesty 1 s Government to inform you that uxiey are prepared to accord their approval to the concession provided Your Highness accepts the following condition, namely that should you wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a Branch or Agency in your territory, as mentioned in Article 27 of the Concession, consult you willA^&amp;Eto His Majesty*s Government s&amp;gixmt&amp;k before entering into any negotiatifnlYHl? orf Ba£k? 881 On receipt of your reply accepting the above condition the formal approval of His Majesty’s Government to the Concession will be communicated to Your Highness and to the Company. Usual Ending. a - 1i i DRAFT Ko.4. After Compliments, In reply to your letter No. equivalent to the to inform you that should I wish to grant permission to a Baiiic to open a Branch or Agency in my territory, I will consult His Majesty’s Government before entering .into any negotiations with or granting any concession to Bank. Usual Ending.(•JL* DRAFT No.5. After Compliments, With reference to your letter dated trie equivalent to the accepting the conditions set forth in my letter ho. dated equivalent to the &gt; 1 directed by His Majesty’s Government to convey to four Highness their approval of the Agreement concluded oy you on the 24th June 1937 'with Petroleum Concessions (A) your territory excluding Dhqfar Limited in respect of (B) Lhofar. and Gwadur. Usual Ending.P,Z.4683/57. India Office, Whitehall,S.w.l. 6th August, 1937. I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the letter from this Office dated 83rd July,1937, ho.±- .2.4578 j 27, regarding nhe forma 1 ities connected with the grant of an oil concession by the Sheikh of Sharjah to petroleum Development (frueial Coast) Ltd., and to the telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf dated 3rd July, of which a copy was sent to your Department on the 9th July under p.2.43£5/37, regarding the grant of two oil concessions to Petroleum Concessions Ltd. by His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. £. Copies of the two Muscat concessions have now been received from Petroleum Concessions Ltd. The texts do not appear to differ in any material respect affecting His Majesty's Government from the draft which was originally submitted by the Company in March 1936. The concessions have already been signed, and it is accordingly proposed 'Muscat Political Agreements' on the same lines as the Sharjah Political Agreement which is about to be concluded with Petroleum De ve1opment (Tru cia1 C o a st)Lt d. A draft which has been prepared for this purpose is enclosed herewith. ^ Under Secretary of State, Pcreign Office.b . 3. Alter the signature of the Political Agreement it is proposed to exchange notes with the Sultan and the Company which will he substantially identical with the Sharjah holes. A copy of the draft Notes is enclosed, 4. The drafts have been sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for any observations which he may have to offer and are subject to the concurrence of the Company - which is being consulted - in their terms. If any substantial changes are made a further communication will be sent to you, 5. I am to enquire whether the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs concurs in the above proposals and in the signature of the Political Agreements on behalf of His Majesty’s Government by an Under Secretary of State of the India Office. The favour of an early reply is requested. 6. Similar letters are being sent to the Admiralty,Mines Department and a copy to the Air Ministry. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, J. C. WALTONBy 'Aw Mail. P.Z. w t D i INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to CONFIDENTIAL RECORD ——. D “te. 20. AIG. 1937 ^ e g. H, 3. wo (’IQNMJlm ! : by^ Mail. Sea TU. caJ i •The Foreign Secretary, Govern ment of India. . The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf?INDIA OFFICE&gt; P*Z. 4610/37. 15 th July, 1937 My dear Longrigg, You told rne some time ago, and we subsequently had a confirmatory report from the Resident, that the Sultan of Muscat had granted two concessions to your Company. We should he grateful if you could lee us have at your convenience copies of the concessions. We shall then, of course, have to go through the formalities connected with the political agreement* We understand that it was not stated in, or m connection with, the concessions that they were subject to the Sultan and Lermitte were orally informed to tms eUeci by the Political Agent, who previous to the negotiation explained to the Sultan the position regarding a s effect political agreement. (Sd) M.J. CLAUSON. City-Gate House, E. C* o* sions Ltd*,II / V' CONFIDENTIAL. No. 647-S of 1937. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to X • 15ie Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. 2» The Political Agent, Muscat* fkiffiy 1 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). POLITICAL aC .•LmCV AND confidential record . —' Date. 3 - SEP. 1937 Reg, H, 8, M’S CONSULATE; MUSCAT, Mill British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. T sted 26.th..Au^ust• X&amp;Zfl Reference to previous correspondence: India Office Express Letter no. P.Z. 4683/37 dated 7th August 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. political Resident’s telegram No. 867 dated 26th August 1937 Muscat and Dhofar draft political Agreement.Telegram Q, From PoliticaX Hesldent, Bushire. To Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by air mail to Government of India, Simla. n ** n n ” PoliticaX Agent, Muscat. No. 867. Dated 26th August, 1937. Your Express Letter No.P.Z. 4683/37 of 7th August. Muscat and Dhof&amp;r draft Political Agreement. Only suggestion I have to m&amp;Ke is substitution oi inrord 'applied* for 'approved' in Article 6 of draft agree ment with object of salving His Highness 1 sovereign conscience. 2. Draft exchanges of notes. Sultan may possitly jib at references to guidance ( draft 2 ) and approval (drafts 3 and 4), when drafts are in due course put before him* Perhaps terms could be toned down without unduly affecting substance. BBITCGN8UL4 rJ n 3 ^ Telegram - Q, From To No.T/157. Dated 6th Received 7th Resident at Shiraz. Political, Muscat at Ziarat. September 1937. India Office telegram No.2202 September 4th (which should reach you on September 11th). Muscat Oil Agreement. Please telegraph any comments or suggestions.From To 'xsmm Political, Muscat at 71arat. Britconsul t Bushlre, Confidential ^ No*H~18S* Camp Office^ Clara Bated 10th September 1937* Subjecti-» TrnoML Qoa^t, .011^ Kaference your express letter $0,556-8 of 19th July 10??* paragraph 4, p In view of paragraph Z of Sir Trenchard fowled demi-official letter to Hicklhbothem Bo.C/15* of ;5t-h July 193*/, copy to I presume that the only action no?? ropulred. from mo 13 to approach the Sultan on ay return to Muscat and to endeavour to ascex tain from him what par t ol* the Truci&amp;l Coast Hinterland is clalmoa by him with the grounds for his claims. Folltleal Agent k H*B.M f s Consul, Muscat..aasyiiss ii iw» '3a.nai% f&amp;miM tUvlilloH ,&amp;%£ttexs@ t JMnmi*# **&lt;&amp; mo 7.1 oT t ^o.mc qmMO ♦?6at TOifsevtr-oa ^oJt f&gt;«tAC . lJ5i^fie5i.lxrcD .liO laatiM bos ^^03 &gt;alain? -tio®tfJtra i^.w w»-*. to £i«—0&lt;u»C *0*1 . &gt;.,■ . '• ,f s - .3d*’ i - jf.' - *•* : •.'. \ •'' T /^ivrgat.tiq *Tsri; q bi&amp;doae-tT it3 to S ,'fcsi S «i S .T t 0 w*Jtr al B'AO.oH oa •i»s.i»x i'sior;l'c-.l«9fe 9 » 9 X»o« ~ iUa ' M '' Jk:ti fmiteetcX '^.eacs W *s &lt;V:c _iol aod .to ecl ' ) dozeivue oiat ok sett fco-s-’t:.«&gt;•£ ...tax ftoi^oa nia^ttsoae o# wov^fcae o? bas i'eosKE oi n-jmai ^ ai a»sJwtfnia aoO , - c * . iat; ^ ^ rao ^. - ' ' . ' . \ “Nayj % lumoO e»M.o,g ^/ CONFIDENTIAL. No. 6b2-S of 1937 • The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Hon'fcle Lieut.-Colonel A.E.B.Pars ons, CBE. ,DSO«» Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla 2 • Maj or R .P. Watts, 1A., # / Political Agent, Muscat, at Ziarat. 3. Ca-Ptain T* *Hickinbothan, IA., Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). POLITICAL AGENCY AND CONFIDENTIAL RECORD »- —■ Date. 1 0. SEP. 1937 yf/L * Reg, No / ? 1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE H. B. M'8 CONSULATE: MUSCAT, * Dated...2.7 th. .Aug us.t., 1 9.3.7. - Reference to previous correspondence * To( 1)&amp; (2)only Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Demi-official letter Bo. 651-S of the 27th August 1937 to M.J.Claus on Esquire, The India office, London, with * enclosures) Ho.lV74-B5/4, Ofiiet? of the A^ent, Baiu-felii ob ree«^« at KaraeM* Bifeted ISth August 19S7 From To Cmptain X* Hiekinbotham Z*A* f Folitlefti Agent, Bahrain at Karachi The Honourable the Political Ke«i4#at in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, hm Sir, 1 haw the honour to refer to your telegram Ko* X/l£5 hated July 27th 13S7 am to enclose reports dated the 4th of imgmt and 11th of August together with sundry papers from the iiosidoncy Agent Sharjah# 1 hove dreom a sketch map of tho peninsula and haw marked In as far as possible such of %m places mentioned by the Kosidoncy Agent Sharjah m I how betm able to identify with tf*e aid of Volume II Geographical of Borimor^ s •G&amp;sottoor of the Persian Gulf*# AMI# by no moams ^ceurato tlds sketch map is more aeeur&amp;b# than 11 Arabia and the Persian Gulf® 1916 I inch - $2 miles and the sap attached to Writer* § ^Gsxetter® 1 inch * axiea as X have been careful to copy the Muiralty chart for the coast line and place the villages by cross hearings and distances from the descriptions given in the latter press of Larimer Volume XI# For instance S&amp;maih in ahu Dhabi territory is correctly shaem as being aoutii of has Ghunadhah and not slightly north as Is the ease in oast maps# the hills are very inaccurate and they have been put in merely to indicate high ground, and not the formation and -/ extent oftWfitti of the -higii ground* • 1 have col-.'-ui' 1 . • areas by the individund Shaikhs for mm of Identification* &amp;* i have one or two consents to make on tlm oiaiEs of the various Shaikhs* He is eisining an area shich includes territory ; thieb he ha©' hlaseif told me belongs to a alba i*e* he is claiming the whole of the $e4£ el - wor the greater part of which he stated in Bahrain belonged to Kalba* X suspect that be has also encroached on the dultanate of Muscat and the ShaikMasu of Sharjah* the Beni hit&amp;b ere the do facto rulers of a considerable fraction of the territory claimed by this Shaikh* this is an ~ -ecurate statsaaat of his territory and he controls the whole of It* Aimaiu fhiB is an accurate description of tills khaiah 1 a: area* Ee soMro ; l^ the whole area* X am not surprised at the dhaikh refusing to stste fdiBt are# he csflaihs* *^here is no doubt tost a very largo area belong s to tale hhaJUli but at the mm time it is equally certain that he is unable to control one tenth of ills area* At present his effective control only extends as far as hli gardens beyond the aerodrome* He */ »cy beha capable of t*rlbisag thvm in uu... ihcxo control to actoowladga Mu otarlor^shfp but f urn m little doubtful# M# tfouid not at present be abls to $o m far as bhaM •.li-tiiout spandlng a considerable «w In presents# Ha is claiming vary much mr&amp; than he in antltleil to in a nouthmriy direction# There has ba-n a bouaaary dispute in progress for some tine between Dubai and Abu Dhabi regarding the southern boundary of Dubai and the matter was submitted to arbitration# BiaSlllal of Bur&amp;imi a well known and highly respected tiiaikh who v?as with Dir P* 2 # Cox In 3.905 on his ex petition to Xbri and BurUmi # was appointed arbitrator* In dune th© arbitrator had succeeded in narrow!: 4 the area ia dispute to a strip of barren territory# not far south of J#b@X Hi# The actual line has not yet been agreed, upon as the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi was beir.g eery obstinate# The arbitrator who la ©Tor eighty urn who I set in Dubai in dune told tie he oas goi g to Abu Dhabi to put the bheii h of Dubai* s ease as he eonvinced that th# bhaiiih of Dubai was making a reasonable request# I asked his if he hoped to be able to bring about a settle- ^#nt And he said that he would do all he could tp perfuaae tne bhaliih of Abu Dhabi to come to a settlement but he was doubtful of the result* He described tke Ih&amp;iKi* f Abu Dhabi as 11 an obstinate bedu** and said that if he woaic iiot listen to reason then as far as he m% concerned he coulc a g0 to hell® • Shaish laid bin Maxtum can wiki does control the urea claimed fey him# /Abu Dhabi/ / /; / 7 . ^ , i i i -/ y ; I have not had the time to chmk tm 4geat f e .report but 1 will do so ami compere the $ present cX&amp;lsas witli thoso put forward wheii Colonel Cordon Lmh cmrtma out his im®$tt%%tlom in tst&amp;r-Sam;la ira boundary question in tfhe present olsiJ&amp;s in tiie north extern into what the Slmlich oi lAibal oonsiders &amp;m his territory « Xn my opinion the present northern ci&amp;lm of ibu I/uitbl is correct but JebeX All should be ineludeo in tubal anti not in Abu iDfcsibl territory* In the west the Ql&amp;Xm is too ambitious* it now includes the whole of the Buraiisl oasis* the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi Ima never previously claimed aore than seven of the villages of this oasis* mho elate to be Indwpwndent of Muscat and Abu Dimhi occupy torn# of the Bur a tel villages* 4* I am not In possession of tee facts am events on which the hhstehs base their elates but I am endenwoW- to obtain them and will forward teem as soon as possibleCopy I $ot« on the boundary olatmod by the Ruler of 8h&amp;tk&amp; Rashid bin Himaid* On th# sea it extends to a point about li miles southwest from the tosrn* Tem this point tne line rums south east to imrb Al brain - a distance of about 2 milts* From Jarb Al qabrain the lino runs oast to Ai Muwainat (about one sailed and then to fall ah (about one ailet and the Wagfcia (about one mile)* From Haghis the line runs north east to Sbt fawi hi hulaiw which is about % milm frm t^ghis, Wrm M &gt;Salaiw the line runs north mat to ^aruar which is about half a mile from Al Hul&amp;iwa and thence to M 4aura Al Fauqaniyah and Ax laurah Al fatty ah on the Kimur of yman about one ails from Adman town towards the met* Adman being separated from Hiariyah by the rrfcfcur. ^he anaihh also claims Hanamah Tillage which has a mi#j and date garden of 4000 trees. fhe Tillage is situated &amp;t the foot of the hills at a distance of about 40 mils® north east of Adman* fne area of mnsoaah which Is claimed by the snaihh of Adman is about 2 mils# in di&amp;meter« 4th August 19M*/ goafidentlal g.O.!lo.q/17d. Offio# of th® Mlttlml Heal dent in the P#?ei&amp;n mlt $ Cmpg Bahrain* dated the 17ta .Au^uet 1937* Many th&amp;aka for your letter , ia.?/74-3&amp;/4 dated the 13th Attguet 1937 on the eubjoet of True isl Coast bouadar iee $ with its eaelosuree, includi ag the mup f which mnz hare involved a gooi deal of work wad will be jaaot useful. 2* The general result of your enquiries nmm to tend towmrde the altuatloa which euito ua f that praotically all the area required by the Comp&amp;qy for their operations is ©lafcaed do Jure by aoae Truolal Shaikh or other t and when Sharjah submit® hie claim the blank in tnm middle will doubtless be filled up* 3* With reference to your last paragraph. 3$©w that we got the general idea I do not think that it is either necessary or adviea.hie to go further into the matter, which' ©an better be done in the autumn, when there is an officer on the spot. ?# have inevitably mad to worry the Shaikhs a good deal of late ard I think it it t ime we gave tnm a rest. If you have issued any 'instructions to the .h A gent to make further enquiries yogi can instruct him to drop them for the time being. Yours sincerely* sd. T.C.Fowle* Captain T. Uckinbotham*Ij«»* ‘oliti«ml Agent* Bithrain* at Karachi.By A ir Mail. p.z. 5Wvl V /(W ^ 3S / INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, £ . Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by Mail. v 4963 2000 7.36 Tbe-Foroign Government of India. ■ “^Plie Political RoAiiltni'iii tllg'Ppi picu-l (Tuli.P,Z* 5645/37. Cypher Telegram from Secretary of State i or India to Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. Dated 4th September* 1937. 101 words. Addressed to Political Resident, copy by air mail i GoYernment of India and Political Agent, Muscat. Your telegram No*867 of 26th August, Muscat Oil Agreement. Draft 2. it is difficult to see what other form of words will meet the case but perhaps risk of Sultan objecting would be lessened If relevant sentence of Draft 2 was omitted and a new paragraph added to draft 1 on following lines:- 'It is assumed that Your Highness will be guided/ by the advice of His Majesty’s Government In regard to exercising the right of termination of the agreement under the terms of paragraph 3 (b) above. 3* Drafts 3 and 4 . These might be altered to provide that the Sultan should 'consult' His Majesty’s Government. 4. Please telegraph your observations on above suggestions. 3* D raft Agreement . I am proposing to omit 'and approved by Political Resident in the Persian Gulf' from Article 6.&gt; 0 , By Air Mail. p.z. C irO - ] 19 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by Mail. Tlin Piilitie'd nuAieknn: TirTlnrPersran Otilf.w- I pst^y u : Q i ac bp Shei 1ms open their mouths rather wide* the Political Resident has therefore suggested that as a first step the local Political Authorities should ascertain from the Rulers concerned what part of the hinterland is claimed hy them respectively, together with the grounds for their claims. This first step should not take long (it is already well advanced) and when this has been done a provisional ruling can be given as to the do jure position in any case in which the claims of two Rulers conflict. 3* The final step would be to discover how.much territory the Rulers concerned effectively control* and in the Resident’s view this can best be ascertained by test cases. He has accordingly suggested that some area to which your Company wish to send an exploration party should be chosen fox'' the purpose and that the Ruler in whose territory the selected area is situated should then, in his capacity of overlord, address the petty ae facto Sheikh concerned to the effect that an exploration party was visiting it. Should the Sheikh raise no objections all would be well, but if difficulties were encountered it would be for the Ruler to bring the Sheikh round. Prom the Ruler’s point of view, it would be decidedly to hi s/ 1 IhiB aavanta ge to have the selected area explored, and GhlS 0bdect rnight ' be achieved hy offering an inducement to the petty Sheikh concerned in the shape of a ^tibotcaiuial Present irorn the money received from the Company or by the promise of a percentage of the royalties if oil is subsequently found in the area. 4. We recognise, of course, that the above procedure might involve some alteration in the Company’s nuturnn plans, but in the opinion of Sir Trenchard Fov/le 13 tne best in the circumstances. I should add that we see no reason why the Company should not start work in the near future in any areas in which the de jure position is not in dispute and in which no difficulty is likely to arise in regard to the de facto position. 5. oh* Trenchard Fowle will be working at the India Olxic^ -i. xOiii the doth September and the opportunity might then be taken of talking the matter over with him. Yours sincerely,?i 2, 5803/37. pG. 28/448. F) PETROLEUM CONGE88IONE LIMITED, CITY-GATE HOUSE. FINSBURY SQUARE, LON uQN, E# 0,S * 1st SepteLaLer, 1937. Dear Mr. Walton, I write to thank you for your letter P. Z. 5407/37 of August 31st, which confirms our conversation of the same date in your office. It is probably within your knowledge that the situation Y/hich you visualise in the third paragraph of your letter was in fact encountered by our Geological Party last winter, and it is in that same area that we wish now to pursue further explorations: namely, around Jebal Faiyah and to the south of this along the v/estern face of the mountains. Here our party found the tribesmen quite unwilling to accept the advice or orders of the Shaikh of Sharjah, as the latter was forced to confess. If we wait until the Shaikh of Sharjah (or other Trucial Ruler) feels disposed to part with money in order to buy the Company a right of entrance into the hinterland, or until such Ruler and a Shaikh of the Interior agree on an oil Convention between themselves, it seems likely that we should wait a long time. Almost all areas in which there are (in the words of paragraph 4 of your letter) neither de jure nor de facto difficulties were visited by our party last season, and we had hoped to recommence work, from some date late in October, in the areas to which we were then not able to obtain acceso. The opportunity to discuss the matter with oir Trenchard Fowle, which you kindly suggest, would therefore oe much appreciated. J.C.Walton, Esq. , C.B. , India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. Yours sincerely, Sgd. Stephen H. Longrigg. i/ , o W' 1 ^ &lt; Telegram Q. From H.M’s Secretary of State for India. London. To Political Kesident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Muscat. PoliLical Agent, Bail rain. C opy sent by air mail to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. No. 2288. ted 17th (received 18th ) September 1937. (Relayed under Bahrain telegram No. 1011 of 18th September 1937). if - d / Fowle’s letter of August 6th No. 5d9-S. 'pVoiJbsed exploration by Petroleum Concessions Limited.. Please see letter from Company dated September 1st copy sent by air mail of September 8th, Matter v/ill be discussed with Fowle and company towards the end of this month. Meanwhile please let me know what stage has been reached in programme (of) delimitation of boundaries together with any observations you may wish to offer on tne Company's letter. - Secretary of State for India. i I L 'Hh-l i iTelegram Q. From Political Agent, Muscat, at Karachi. Poliuical He si dent, at Shiraz. No. 1023. Dated 21 September 1937. Your telegram No. T/157 of September 6th. 2. Reference to India Office telegram No. 2202 of September 4th paragraph 2 thereof. I think the Sultan will probably object to tne words ’’will be guided by” as too binding. Some such expression as ’’will give careful consideration to ” wouj/ in my opinion be more readily acceptable to Sultan. 3. Suggested alteration and omission made in paragraphs 3 and 5 of India office telegram are very advisable. - WATTS.• i Telegram From To Q, Political Resident at Shiraz. Secretary of State for India» London. Copy by air mail to Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla* Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat. No.T/199o Dated 17th September 1957. Your telegram No.£*202 of 4th September. Muscat Oil Agreement. I agree that all alterations proposed are suitable. I have been unable to obtain comments of Political Muscat, but do not delay further as observations may be required in time for board meeting on 20th. CAROE rnrnrnimmp. 2.5407/37. Confidential. Bear Mr. Longrigg, Vij on lei you please refer to i 4 - 4 - ^ 1 CxCx t0 y° ur letter of the 11th June &lt;uid the sub se quent c 0 nnee t e i p -i r-m 0 ^ 0 ± u ' LCCLoa correspondence ending with «y letter of the 2 7 th July, No.P.2. 4834/37, regarding conditions in the hinterland of the Trucial Sheikhdoms WeSt ° f tae main 0raan ran e e of mountains, on which subject WS haVe n ° W recelved tlle of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. There appears to he little doubt that all the ten itoiy vnircn your Company now wishes to explore belongs / - ~ ,e e ' ' Jller ‘ to one of ' the Trucial Sheikhs (from practically all of whom the Company has obtained options or concessions) or to the Sultan of Muscat. We fear, however, that if any attempt is made to explore the territory in question before more is known of the d e facto position, the Company will (apart from other difficulties) find themselves put to considerable expense since the prospect of oil being discovered might make some of the numerous i&gt; Longrigg, Esq. , petty/ Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., City-Gate House, E. 0.2.petty de facto Sheikhs open their mouths rather wide. The Political Resident has therefore suggested that as a first step the local Political Authorities should ascertain from the Rulers concerned what part of the hinterland is claimed Toy them respectively? together with the grounds for their claims. This first step should not take long (it is already well advanced) and when this has keen done a provisional ruling can he given as to the de jure position in any case in which the claims of two Rulers conflict. 3 . The final step would he to discover how rnucn territory the Rulers concerned effectively control? cu.ui in the Resident’s view this can 'best he ascertained by test cases. He has accordingly suggested that some area to which your Company wish to send an exploration party should 'be chosen for the purpose and that the Ruler in whose territory the selected area is situated snould then? in his capacity of overlord, address the petty de facto Sheikh concerned to the effect that an exploration party was visiting it. Should the Sheikh raise no ok jeer ions all would ke well, kut if difficulties were encountered it would ke for the Ruler to kring the SheiKh round* rrom tae Ruler’s point of view, it would ke ciecldeul^y go his/3. hie advantage to have the selected area explored, and this object might he achieved by offering an inducement to the petty Sheikh concerned in the shape of a otan.nal pi^oent from tne money received from the Company or by the promise of a percentage of the royalties if oil is subsequently found in the area. 4. We recognise, of course, that the above proceduie might involve some alteration in the Company's Autumn plans, but in the opinion of Sir Trenchard Fowls it is the best in the circumstances. I should add that we see no reason why the Company should not start work in the near future in any areas in which the de jure position is not in dispute and in which no difficulty is likely to arise in regard to the de facto position. p. Sir Trenchard Fowls will be working at the India Office from the 20th September and the opportunity might then be taken of talking the matter over with him. Yours sincerely, ?d Dv, &lt;5. T,Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to by r i%c Foreign Secretary, Political Resident in the Persian GuMp.z. 5837/37. p.C.44b/449 PETROLEUM COHO33$IONS LIMITHD. CITY-GATH HOUS3, P1KSBUEY SQUARE, LONDON, E.C.2 2nd September^ 1937, Dear Clauson^ In the course of the aerial exploration of the eastern portion of the Aden Protectorate, which this Company hopes to undertake during the first weeks of 1938, it is possible that our geologists might be tempted to make one or more prospecting flight over the western end of the ,Sultanate of Oman, over which, as you are aware, we have recently obtained a Concession from the Sultan. Article 13a of each of our two Concessions from the Sultan of Muscat and Oman, gives us the right to maintain aircraft. We could probably obtain without difficulty the right to use R.Aolh landing ground along that coast if necessary. At the same time Article 6 of the Political Agreement (into which we shall no doubt enter in respect of Oman as m respect of the prucial Sheikhdoms) binds us in respect of air transportation, to be subject to the civil aircraft regulations made by the Sultan or by H.M.G. My immediate point is, do you think it likely that objection woulu be taken to any prospecting flight which our aircraft might undertake over the extreme western end of the Sultanate of Oman? It would be understood that (unless we had in the meantime made other arrangements) the responsibility would be ours. if/ J. Clauson, hsq., India Office, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1t ix There are inexistence any civil Aviation Regulations coverin„ that territory, to which we ought to adhere, could you very kindly acquaint us with them? Yours sincerely, (Scl.) Stephen H. Longrigg.By Air Mail. P.Z. S'lScfl 19 S Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to JL by Mail. - J •Sea- I The PolitTrnl l- )r “- v “ ] ^ nT iri f b^ Persian Gulf. c b / oe_ (Lo^J 3 4963 2000 7.36P. Z. 595/57. E. 4804/12/91. II* Vv* 1. Tth S^pt«bw s 193? Sir, ' vrith rafarcsice to ^oar latter of the Sth Au-gmt (: ;i *Z#4603/3f) on the object of oil eonTOaBlona In maimt, I m directed by Mr* secretary Etei to state, for Information of the Marqaesa of that Hr* 1 agrees with tee propoeala eontalned in 2 -and 3 of tfoxir letter, imd also to tee aj l olitical Agre^smantss on behalf of Eis by an under Secretary of state of tee India Oftkwmt 2. With regard to tee text of tee draft political agreement f Mr* K&amp;cn would .auifgest one miner mvmdmmt nmacly teat, In par&amp;gmnh 10| tee words ' 4? lfhe .mltar shall not onreapceably wltehoM sute pernios ion, m&amp; m ml#it be emitted* It wmxm to Mr* Mam teat team# werde# which r - adc! nothing to the sonae, mre open to te«s criticism that Hi© Majernty 1 © (lOTerment purpert to be ©aylng what tee taler of Muscat (i.e* a teird party) will do* tee second sentence of peregreph 10 shonld, he sUsiPSts, begin ,f ln any omc in white**** ,f 3* Oopiea of tel© letter are beta;: ®mxt to the Mr Minietry and r-etrolemri Depertemt* I am, etc* , (sd*5 0 *w*m The under Secretary rf state, India Office*CON F1DK.UT1AL ♦ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, \ [N* B'—This is an ORIGIN AL MRSSAGE, sent by post to scire telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Muscat* Hi Political Resident* Bus'nire C-98/82. thied lath October 19371$$ Muscat-Trucial Coast Boundary . Reference correspondence ending with your telegram No. T-231 of 25th September 1937. I discussed this matter with the Sultan at the last interview I had with him a few days ago. He has taken up an unsatisfactory and stubborn attitude over the question and where as he had previously promised to have enquiries carried out and a search made among the Btax^e records ~ vide paragraph 2 of my express letter No. 34 of 23rd March 1936 - he now declares that he sees no reason why he should put himself to the trouble of working out his boundary and collecting evidence to support his claims chereto. His argument is that the parties interested, i.e. the Trucial Shaikhs should put forward a statement as was done/■ - 2 - done by Ibn Saud over the eastern limits latter* s dominions, showing what they claimed as the boundaries of their districts and the Sultan would then say whether he accepted them or not. 2. I pointed out to the Sultan that it was equally to the advantage of his State as well as to £hat of the Trueial Shaikhs that the ambiguity con cerning their respective boundaries should be cleared up especially at the present time when an active search for oil was about to be carried out in those regions. I asked the Sultan what he proposed to do if Petroleum Concessions Limited, to whom he had sold the right to prospect for oil any where in the Arabian portion of his dominions, should declare that during the coming autumn they desired to examine ground in the vicinity of the supposed boundary and wished to be informed what exactly were Hie limits of the Sultanate. The Sultan replied that in that event he would want to know from the Company the exact places they wished to visit; he would then state whether they were within Muscat territory or not and if so he would send representatives to act as guides for the Company*s employees in their journeys provided the particular places were considered safe for such a purpose. 3* I mentioned that not only the Trucial Shaikhs but Ibn Saud was putting forward claims to the ownership of Bairami (vide your telegram Ho. T-216 of 24th September 1937). The Sultan became indignant on hearing this and declared Bairami definitely belonged to Muscat, one of the chief proofd of which was that he paid the Heaoman a retaining fee S On a previous occasion the Sultan admitted that he received no payment of taxes from that district and I gathered that tney never had seen paid - certainly not/not regularly 4 A definition of the western land boundaries of Muscat State though no doubt not by any means an easy task, owing to the absence of properly maintained records and above all to the backward condition of the State AdministBation, is far from being impossible, but I think that the Sultan has not the least intention of carrying it out nor will he willingly co-operate in the work of any investigation under the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, grot to the Trucial Coast Hinterland next autumn - vide your telegram quoted in paragraph 3 above. that if he persists in his refusal to co-operate and put forward a statement at least of his claims to Bairami and his boundary in that neighbourhood and other parties interested are able to make out a prima facie case for themselves, His Majesty f s Government may accept their claims as against the Aiuscat Govemmenf ex parte. 5. In my opinion the Sultan should be informed Maj or, Political Agent and H#M*s Consul, Muscat. V**f@l ©gram From Political a«aidont» ^anlr« # at Snimi Secretary of State for lul la.» London* Copy fey poet to Government of India, internal Affair# 'Department» Simla# and Political Agent# 'lueoat HO. T/212. Dated tne 22nd September, 1937 ) f I In continuation of ay telegram T/199 of I7tn September* 1PISGAT OIL AOIt^ Political Agent now makes further suggestion tnat Sultan ?Afiy object to words ‘•will be guided' as too binding' and suggests «wUX give careful cons iaeratto.« 2 . I fear tmt any sued alteration will erapty perase of its content and not secure to His llajesty f s Governmont su bat a nee of control. We my trust tn&amp;t Sultan’s expectation of financial advantages will turn tne scale wUncut further concessions in form of notes to be exc^nged. Oar oe*CONFIDENTIAL. No - o/2 4b of 1937. i The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grdf presents his compliments to 1. Tne Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairo Department, Simla. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. Tne Political Agent, Muscat.,/ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (Ah/ * ' * —_____ — i' { &lt;% H D Office of tne Political Res ideir in tne Persian Gulf, rjamp, Shiraz. COuFiDEP'J 1 . j n..,re. uIk 193/ HECOHD N,, !__— h. b. :,vs bonsou'-; on. I SHlhbEc Dated ^t.n ^September, 1937 Reference to previous correspondence: India Office telegram Ho. 22-6 of tne 17tn September, 1937. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident's telegram Ro.T/216 of tne 24th September 1937. Trucial Coast Boundaries,SWMW deolUM with Hi® Ht*jesty*» Oovornmssit*?? «ppr ot«X t# optrate in interior and -question 01 junsa let ion w juXcI eome to a nead^ (it) Political ^?»&gt;irain h«e sent fresa report expressing apprenension of efforts fey Bin Saud to estsfelisn authority at Baraiai, Ope rat im® fey Comp^-riy ©houid do something to counter ©non activities without need for any challenge* ( iii) Eulf^n would realise %mt m^ut ciaha ufiaupportea fey autnority must in mu give way to facts# am *ai t ht proceed to clear hi© mind a baut hie frontier* ( iv) In any case it eeome lively tnat Odeapm^ must fee resigned to proa peat of lengthy negetiati one as accompaniment of peaceful penetration la disputed territory* «* 01B&amp;‘fice of tne Political Resident m tne Dated the 27 tn September, 1937 UO.G/265 Of 1937 Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz. To The Political Agent Muscat. exploxat ion of the 'western portion of the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman. Reference India Office Printed Letter No* P.Z.3837 dated the 8th September 1937 copy sent to you direct. Dharbat Ali, the western limit of the Sultan's territory, over the province of Dnofar* a Special Authorisation will be required from the Sultan, in which the area that can be flown over could be specified. Ir&amp;q Command) at Salala and Murbat, and the Sultan exercises effective control over the coast of Dhofar. If, therefore, he accords permission and accepts responsibility there does not appear to be any objection, from the point of view of security, to flights over the coastal tract between Ras Dharbat Ali and Murbat, provided that it is made clear that aircraft should not penetrate further inland than the limit up to which the Sultan accepts responsibility. 5. East of Murbat the country is barren and inaccessible, the Royal Air Eorce emergency landing grounds are far apart, and the Sultans control is nominal. I am therefore inclined 2 The proposed flights would extend eastwards from Ras 3 Under Article 1 (i) of the Muscat Civil Air Regulations 4 There are Royal Air Force landing grounds funder the to /Telegram Q. From H.M*s Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Government of India, External Affairs Department Simla. Political Agent, Muscat. No. 2500$ Dated (and received ) ISJii October 1937. Important . Longrigg Petroleum Concessions Limited is anxious to see Sultan of Muscat personally to discuss oil matters and could meet the Sultan in India during the week commencing November 18th or at Muscat during the week commencing November 24th ( October 24th? ). He would welcome Political Agents presence at any meetings. If you see no objection please instruct the Political Agent to sound the Sultan and ascertain his wishes. Company do not propose to attempt any explora tion in the coming season but Longrigg would make preliminary enquiries of Sultan as to means of explor ing the south eastern coast. He would also like to sound the Sultan as to the possibility of meeting the Imam personally in regard to the question of exploration in the hinterland controlled by the Imam. Fowle whom I have consulted sees no objection to the Sultan being approached on this point. If you also see no objection please instruct the Political Agent to sound the Sultan in advance on the question of Longrigg’s meeting with Imam. Retaxandum.F.82 Teleeram 0. h i. From Political Hesident, Bushire, Political Agent, Muscat* No* 982. Bated (and received ) 16th October 1S37. 4- m India Office telegram No. 2500 October 15th. Please take action accordingly and telegraph report ft Beference paragraph 1. I am inclined to think it important that you should be present at any meetings between the Sultan and Longrigg. Beference paragraph 2. As regards the hinterland have you any infonnation regarding degree and territorial extent of the Imam 1 s authority ? Please f ' ''' •• ■. ■ bear this in mind when sounding the Sultan* - Caroe*Telegram q &gt;1*1 From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Resident, Bush ire. Repeated India Office, London. No. 106. Bated 18th October 1937* Important . f 1 1 Reference India Office telegram No. 2bOQ 15th October. I interviewed the Sultan today. He said that he would be ready to see Longrigg and discuss oil matters. He would prefer meeting to be at Delhi. He definitely and strongly objects to idea of Longrigg meeting the Imam. 2 * To Bushire onl y. Your telegr *82 16th October, paragraph 4. authority cannot be easily answered as situation in the Oman at present appears to be somewhat in a state of flux. The Imam is still the sole ruler of the Oman but with authority which shows signs of dwindling in the outlying regions. Nevertheless no expedition could travel any distance into the interior unless sponsored by him. '^he degree and territorial extent of the Imam 1 s - Political.Telegram q. From Secretary of State for India, To Political Resident, Rushire. Repeated Political Agent, Muscat. No. 2542. Dated (and received ) 19th October 1937. London^ hN*&gt; \ COBl&gt;\ \ \ Important . ■ Addressed to Political Residant repeated to Political Agent, Muscat. ^.telegram of October 18th No Longrigg enquires if he may see the Sultan at Delhi on November 20th (he is not due to reach Bombay 18th November). Will this date suit His Highness ? Reference the latter^ 106. - RETAXANDUMF.82 Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Muscat. Political Hesident, Bushire. Hepeated Secretary of State for India, No. 108. Dated 20th October 1937. ; 1 Important . t : ^ J India Office telegram No. 2542 of 19th October. Sultan now states that as he leaves Delhi on 22nd November and Longrigg is comiig to Bombay he suggests meeting should take place in Bombay where Sultan will be from 23rd to 30th November. He would prefer this as it would give ample time for unhurried discussions. - POLITICAL.1^ f By Air Mail. P.Z. (5 lixj 19 V INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 2*1 , °| . *0 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to --f l. 6232/37 i IxTDXA OFFICSS, mi ITIEALL, S.w.l. 25th September 1937. My dear Longrigg, Please refer to your letter of the 2nd September, Ho.P.C.44b/449 and connected correspondence about the possibility of aerial survey flights over the extreme western end of the Sultanate of Muscat. So far as His Majesty’s Government are concerned they would have no objection to occasional prospecting flights of this nature being made, provided always that the Company adhere to any 1ocal civil aviation regulations and that , should they intend using any landing ground in that area they take steps to ensure that there is no likelihood of hostilities on the part of the local inhabitants. Before any survey is made over Muscat territory the Political Agent, Muscat, should oe informed. It seems to us, after consultation with Sir Trenchara Powle, that the next step is to secure the Sultan’s consent, which could probably best be done by a telegram from us to the Resident. We are prepared to send such a/ H.Longrigg, Esq., Petroleum Concessions Ltd., City Gate House, Finsbury Square f E.C.2.AMuscat telegram No, 108 October 20th. Longrigg agrees to meeting at Bombay. HETAMNDUM.1-7 Telegram Q. From J-ndia Office ^oodon* To Political Agent, Muscat. No. i&amp;M. Dated and received 27th October 1907. Addressed to the Political Resident in the ksx Persian Gulf repeated to the Political Agent, Muscat, copy sent by air mail to the Government 0f India. 2. Your telegram ho. 212-T 22nd September. Muscat Oil Agreement. 3. After consultation with Fowle it has been decided to postpone signing the Political Agreements until the Sultan’s concurrence in drafts and in proposed exchange of notes has been obtained. If therefore you see no objection please instruct the Political Agent Muscat to approach the Sultan according ly- 4. Drafts to be shown to the Sultan should be identical with those enclosed with my express letter A *o. P.Z. 4683/37 dated the 7th August with the following modifications vizs Political Agreement Article 6 * aubstitute ’’which are binding on British subjects” for ”and approved by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf”. lib . . Draft 1. At end of paragraph 3(b) add sentence h ~r 2-c c l suggested in paragraph 2 of my telegram Ro. 2202 September 4th. v Draft 2 . Omit paragraph 2. D rafts 3 and 4. These should be altered to provide that the Sultan should ’’consult His Majesty’s Government before entering into any negotiations with or granting any concession to Bank”. RBTAXaNDUM.INDIA OFFICE, POLITICAL Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). ^ ' -“This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India Your tel eg . . ^ itber. Conditions in the hinterland of the Irucial Coast, etc. Copy is enclosed of a record of a discussion with Mr. Longrigg, representing Petroleum Concessions Limited, and of a letter addressed to him as a result of that discussion. You will see that the Company are prepared to postpone any exploration work for the present. There is time therefore for the Assistant political Agent to complete the investigations of the position and for subsequent negotiations between the Shaikhs and the tribes in the hinterland. Fowle proposes to visit the Trucial Coast immediately on his return, to review the situation on the spot. Longrigg’s proposals for visiting the Sultan of Muscat and the Imam of Muscat have been dealt with separately. No. P. Z. 6341/37 The issue of the above has been duly authorised. 0t) J. C. WALTQtt,CONFIDENTIAL i ^ PSRSIAK GULF OIL Mr. Longrigg called by appointment on the 29th September to discuss the question of Petroleum Concessions Limited exploring in the Trucial Coast hinterland, etc. Mr. Walton, Sir Trenchard Fowle and Mr. Symon were present at the interview. Mr. Longrigg explained that the Company’s geologists had covered most of the accessible parts of the territory concerned and that the Company now wl shed to push on with the exploration of the remaining areas. The exploration party would consist of Mr. T. P. Williamson and Mr. R. Pomeyrol, both of whom were permanently employed by the Company. The Company did not propose to engage any special staff for the work. Messrs. Williamson and Pomeyrol were proceeding to the Gulf area forthwith and would be available if work could be found for them in the Trucial hinterland. An important reason for making a complete exploration was that the Company had definitely decided to commence boring operations in Q,atar and that the extent of their operations in that area would, to some extent, depend on the reports of their geologists in respect or the other territories in which the Company were interested. {Machinery xor tne ^atar operaoioxxs iiao. aixe•■.Au.y been ordered but at the moment the Company were reluctant to commence actual opera cions pending, a d^ci oi on regarding the .Bahrein unallotted area, since iney feared that if oil was discovered in commercial Guantiti eiX quantities in Qatar ‘before a decision was readied regarding The unallotted area they might find tnemselves obliged to considerably increase their present olier to the Sheikh of Bahrein), Min Longrigg agreed that the proposed exploration was not a matter of vital urgency but, at the same time, he wished to avoid giving the impression that his Company were not interested in developing oil resources in all the territories for which they had obtained, or hope to obt ain, c onees si ons. \ ^ Mr. Longrigg then went on to explain that there were three areas in which Ms Company wished to pursue further explorations, vis: (a) Jebel Payah and the country of the south and south-east thereof; country east and south of the Baraimi Oasis with Jebel Hafit, and to the south and south-east thereof; (b) The Muscat areas, controlled by the Imam and the Beni Bu Ali tribe; and (c) The south-east coast of Muscat as far as Dhofar. The Company were not interested in the north eastern coastal belt along by Sohar - Muscat - Ras-al- Had, Mr. Longrigg said that it had been the Company's intention to undertake (a) during the coming winter and to deal with (b) and (c) during the winter of 1938-39. After a full discussion, during which the difficulties in the way of undertaking further exploration until more is known of the position in the Mntadand were explained, Mr. Longrigg agreed that it might/r mighu be best lor the Company to give up all ideas of exploring in the Tracial hinterland during the coming winter. It was suggested to Mr. Longrigg that it might facilitate matters if the Company could indicate the particular areas in the hinterland in which they were specially interested. He replied that the Company were interested in the whole of the territory covered by (a) above and in fact all the foothills of the western slopes of the Western Hajar, but that owing to their limited knowledge, it was almost impossible for them to specify particular areas. As regards Muscat territory, Mr. Longrigg said that his Company fully appreciated the difficulties which they were likely to encounter. He was, however, proposing to leave England during October and hoped to see the Sultan personally (either in India during the week commencing the 18th November or at Muscat during the week commencing the 24th November) with a view to discovering what areas the Sultan regarded as He also had an idea that it might be useful if he could see the Imam of Oman with a view to discussing the possibility of the Company r s geologists exploring the territories controlled by the Imam. He asked that this suggestion should be considered. As regards the south-east coast of Muscat, Mr. Longrigg said that what his Company had in mind was to survey this area from the air. They had an idea to charter a steamer on which would be based an aeroplane or flying-boat. Mr. Walton expressed graveJL. ^ js) Q,x' fc d. CO As regards tJae f i aerial survey unless the Sultan was pre; guarantee the safety of tile party, territories controlled by the Imam, the difficulties would be even greater. Mr. Longrigg agreed and stated that these were further reasons for his wishing to discuss matters with the Sultan. Meanwhile the Company were prepared to postpone any exploration for the present. Symon t INDIA OFFICE, 7th October, 1937 [ 1 II 1 -'I P.Z.6341/37. INDIA OPPIGB j NHIDEEALL, S.H. 1 12th October 1937. ( I promised to ’/rite to you regarding the discussion on 29th September with you and Sir Trenchard Fowle on the subject of conditions in the hinterland of the irucial Coast and adjacent territories. You will remember that the conclusion was that it would be in the interests of all concerned to adhere generally to the procedure suggested by the Political Resident and outlined in my letter of 31st August ? that no attempt should be made to explore the Trucial hinterland until more is Imown of the be factjo position ? and that the de facto, tribal authorities in the hinterland should be approached through the de jure Rulers from whom the Company already has or obtains concessions. though this procedure involves some delay in conducting further explorations it seems preferable to proceed gradually. You pointed out that your Company is definitely interested in exploring the possibilities of the S«HoLongrigg ? Esa. ? - Petroleum Concessions, Limited, City-G-ate House, Pinsbury Sauare, E.C.2 areas/areas of i J cs concossions ? otic chough. g chac in cho circumstances they would he willing to fall in with the proposal to postpone any exploration worh for the present,. w e a re therefore instructing the Acting Political Resident accordingly. The reasons which render it desirable to proceed with caution in the case of the Trucial hinterland were thought to apply with eoual and pernaps greacei foice in the case of Muscat territory. The importance was recognised of obtaining the Sultan’s written convene before any attempt is made to begin exploratory work (eicher oy land or sea) in any part of the territories concrolled by His Highness. 'e understand that the Company does not, propose to commence exploration in Muscat territories for the present s but that you would like to interview the Sultan (either in India or at Muscat) to discuss oil questions and make preliminary enquiries as to the means of exploring che south-eastern coast, and we are taking steps to ascertain (by telegram) whether an interview with His Highness can be arranged. ' 7 e are also consulting the local Political authorities on your suggestion that you might sound the Sultan as to the possibility of your meeting the Imam of Oman/</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000c7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/424</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000c7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/424</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 14/1 II Oil concession in Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-23T22:23:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (221 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 217; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-217; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to oil concessions in Muscat territory.The discussion in the volume relates to the following main issues:Correspondence with officials of Petroleum Concessions and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) LimitedDiscussions with Standard Oil of California regarding the awarding of a separate concession for DhofarThe proposed exploration by Petroleum Concessions Limited of the area adjacent to Oman's mountain rangeThe negotiations concerned with an agreement for an oil concession in 'Muscat territory'Demarcation of boundaries between Muscat and the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms.Included in the volume is a copy of the draft agreement between HM Government and Petroleum Concessions (Trucial Coast) Ltd (ff 59-65).The file also includes a report (ff 106-114) by the Political Agent, Bahrain (Captain Tom Hickinbotham) to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, giving his views on how the 'advent of oil must alter our policy on the Trucial Coast' and the necessity of penetrating into the interior and communicating with the tribal rulers there. He also discusses the ramifications of this including the demarcation of boundaries. Another document (folio 127) of interest is the 'NOTE ON CONDITIONS IN THE HINTERLAND SOUTH AND SOUTH-EAST OF THE TRUCIAL COAST' prepared by Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited. The note concerns the company's assessment of tribal boundaries and implications for development of oil concessions.Also included (folio 17) is a handwritten letter in Arabic by Sultan Sa'id bin Taimur to the Political Agent, Muscat concerning arrangements for a survey of Dhofar province.The principal correspondents in the volume include the Political Agent, Muscat (Major Ralph Ponsonby Watts); the Secretary of State for India; the Private Secretary to the Secretary of State for India (M J Clauson); the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr]; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Petroleum Concessions Ltd (Stephen Hemsley Longrigg).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Private Secretary to the Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oil</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000c7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>