<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000ba_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:18:37.077Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Kuwait. No.C/66 Dated the 15th March 1943. To The Political The Political The Political Agent, Bahrain Agent, Kuwait. Agent, Muscat. Memorandum Please furnish monthly statements showing, in tons. Q Tt *4 ^ &lt;1 v.t Vv ^ - 4 ^ 'l a . ^ the details of rice, wheat and wheat flour, sugar, tea and cotton piecegoods imported into your area during each month, commencing with March 1943. The statements should be tele** graphed at the end of the month to which the figures refer, in the form indicated below. For the purpose of economy in telegraphing, the following form should be used and the order adhered to;- Place Month. Commodity, quantity imported, quantity exported, existing stocks (not applicable to cotton piece- goods), period of sufficiency in months (not applicable to cotton piecegoods), quantity r*'. exported to Saudi Arabia (the last mentioned not being applicable to the Trucial Coast, Muscat or Gwadur). Thus a typical message would read as follows f, Bahrain January Rice 1400 nil 1600 one 800 Wheat and Wheat flour 460 nil 270 two ISO* ngures m respect of the Trucial Coast, and the Political Agent, Muscat, in respect of Gwadur and, if possible y ' Dhof ar• SdA C.G. Prior Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 3d/- J. Croning for Secretary t o the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Y j3 ^ Poll tier 1 Agency, lah-*ain, the 8th April 1943. I'he director of Customs and ^ort Officer, Bahrain. 'Memorandum T ' r i 1 1 you kindly send me at the end of every month a statement in respect of rice, wheat and wheat flour, sufrr/tea and cotton' piecegoods showing in tons (a) the ouannity imported (hd the quantity, exported and 'c' the quantity re-exported to Cnudi A&gt; ’^hia during they&gt; month ? hi It would be appreciated if these statements could kindly b sent most promptly. Id/- y.C. Pixon for Political Agent. Bahrain.29/20 Telegram From To No. 277 Dated the 0 Political Agent, Bahrain. Politic''! Resident, Bushire. 12th April 1943. v our ITemorandum 7/66 Narch 15th. BAHBAIN NABCH. Pice 110 nil 46^ one 110. Wheat and wheat flour 400 nil 592 one nil. Sugar nil nil 157 1-^ nil. Tea nil nil 23 2 nil. Piece goods 65 5 - - T^-. 2. Above figures for wheat and wheat flour do not include 1600 tons flour imported here for Fastern Saudi'”Arabia and other gulf Shaikhdoms. They do include the 400 tons for Bahrain. 3. Fstimates short oeriods sufficiency cereals due to seasonal demands of nearllng fleet. 4 4. ^i mires for Trucial Toast will follow when received. •~n j P^T ! rT, 1 r,r L -Telegram ^rom To O.T.C. ^.C.T.C., Sharjah. Political Agent, Pahrain. No. 337 Dated -1th received 13th April, 1943. only as the figures for innort direct from T ndia other ports will not be known ? fo r some time . 4. No separate figures are available for c and other piece goods. Pice 1194 nil 2403, 3. Wheat and wheat flour nil nil 915 3. Sugar 13 remaining figures will follow. Tea 21 91 remaining figures will follow. Piece goods 3 5. reference your Memorandum No. 7/490. 2. i nresume that for these purposes °atar is included in ny area. 3. following figures refer to Shariah and following figures refer to Shariah and Dubai 3FAPJAH / DIT3AI/l( j it rrom To No* 354 29/20 and 29/1 Political Officer, Trucial Coast, oharjah i olitical Agent, Bahrain* Dated 16th; received 17th April 1943. Reference my telegram r;o. 337. 2. .egret that the figures for wheat were v;rongly given. They should he as follows Wheat and flour Nil 483 1. Some of wheat is unedihle owing to long storage. ^ugar 56o tons in stock 2 months. Tea o* 3^9 tons in stock 10 months. r 3. Please intimate price ef^2C0 tons flour received from Bahrain hy DSSAi 3 as we wish to distrioute it to mercnan^s • - Political -29/20 Telegram From To No. 326 Q Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire Dated the 6th May, 1943 Your Memorandum C/66 March 15th Figures for April. BAHRAIN. Rice 586 nil 540 1^ 199. Wheat and flour 1441 nil 1266 2 186. Sugar nil nil 41 ten days nil. Tea nil nil 19 2 nil. Piece goods 7 nil - - 6. In addition to above 800 tons wheat has arrived Bahrain consigned to Persian Government. TRTXIAL COAST . Rice nil nil 1713 2. Wheat and flour 1208 nil 1443 2^. Sugar nil nil 438 2j. Tea 10 78 200 4. Piece goods 6 5. Copy forwarded to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, for information. - POLITICALTelegram From TO Q Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1266 Dated and received the 1st June, 1943. My Circular Memorandum C/66 March 15th. Statement should in future show also barley/dari/millet under one head. - BRITCONSUL -f \ N*. C/762 Political '^ency, Bahrain, 3rd June 1943• To The Director of Customs, Bahrain* Memorandum ^ 3. Reference my memorandum No. C/491 dated the 8th April 1943. y 2. V ill you kindly also include barley/dari/millet in your monthly statements in future, under one head ? for P Critical Agent, Bahrain. ipit^Telegram ^ XXX From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 399 Dated 5th June 1943. \ Your memorandum C/66 March 15th, Figures for May* Bahrain Rice Nil Nil 397 2 Nil Wheat 1130 Nil 1500 2 210 and flour Barley 900 Nil 900 4 Nil Sugar 120 Nil 119 it Nil Tea Nil Nil 11 1 Nil Piecegoods 138 1 — — 38£ / , / Trucial Coast / Rice Nil Nil 1100 it V*heat and 1667 Nil 2778 3 flour ' V r Sugar 42 Nil 308 2 i Tea Nil 50 IbO 3 / Piecegoods 35 Nil Figures for barley will be telegraphed later. - Political - No. C/774 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th June 1943 Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah information. Please note that some alteration has been e in the figures under wheat and flour, and also that the ort of tea from the Trucial Coast is supposed to be pro- ited when stocks fall below six months* local requirements.% Cereals Poaitlon on 30th June 1943 - Bahrain and Trucial Coast BAHRAIN In Bahrain stocks of careals are sufficient In quantity to last until the end of November 1943 though rice will be exhausted during July* Stocks amount to approximately 5,000 tons made up as follows *• Bice •• Australian Wheat •• Flour •• Barley •• Indian Wheat (arrived by 'Braganza' on 30th June 1943) • • • • • • 150 tons 1,550 ' 300 H 600 ' 2,400 H 2. It is possible that stocks of wheat will be further supplemented by tanker shipments from Australia in the course of the next five months* I suggest that the position be reviewed at the end of September 1943* In the meantime supplies of rice, even in small quantities, would be very welcome* THUCIAL COAST 3* Stocks in Dubai and Sharjah amount to over 5,000 tons of which 1/^th consist* of rice, J^Lha of barley/millet and i^r.hs of wheat. These stocks will last until the end of October and probably into November* During the next few months withdrawals from stocks will be much below average owing to (a) good rains, abnormally extensive cultivation and excellent crops in the hinterland and (b) availability of local dates* The primary necessity for the Trucial D ^ Coast is the import of two flour mills (vide express letter No. 1205- 36/1*B, dated the 7th June 1943 to Foreign, New Delhi, repeated to Political Resident) without which it will be impossible to dispose of the barley/millet from Iraq provided by the ff*E*S*C* 4* I suggest that the supply position on the Trucial Coast be reviewed at the end of September 1943* ?/,/,!EXPHESS LETTER From To No. C/900. Dated the 4th July 1943. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Camp Bahrain. \ Your memorandum C/66, March 15th. Figures for June. BAHRAIN. r — fU’fr,' Rice Nil Nil 150 1 Nil Wheat &amp; Flour 3,600 Nil 4,250 5 Nil Barley Nil Nil 600 3 (Weeks) Nil Sugar 120 Nil 131 1 Nil Tea Nil Nil 1 Nil Nil Piece-goods. Note 1 52 Nil - - 20 i In addition there is in stock at Bahrain 4,500 tons wheat and 300 tons barley earmarked for Saudi Arabia. Note 2 1,622 tons wheat and flour were re-exported to Saudi Arabia in June. These stocks belonged to U.K.C.C. and were not included in Bahrain stock figures previously given. TRUCIAL COAST Figures will follow. Political Agent, Bahrain, &amp;/(«■29/J,0 Telegram G.T.C* From Residenty Agent, Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 719 Dated and received the 7th July, 1943. Your telegram 477 July 5th. Tea figures of 150 tons at end of May was not repeat not correct. According to inveniray made lately existing stock on 30th June 290 tons. 2. Total figures for barley dari and millet 1746 half 3492 tons and not 1256 which is due to mistakes by Sharjah Customs when converting bags into tons. Difference of 4 tons presumably due to loss in ? transaction . All this is still in stock. 1 - BRITAGENT - ft ?/?/« NCJ29/20 Telegram Q From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political RpSident, Bushire. No. 516 Dated the 4th August, 1943. Your Memorandum C/66 March 15th. Figures for July. BAHRAIN. Rice nil nil 60 fortnight nil Wheat and flour 303 nil 3833 4 Barley nil nil 600 3 nil Sugar nil nil 15 4 days nil Tea 23 nil 20 1 nil Piece-goods 94 3 - - 39j Note (l) Stocks of wheat aid flour (3833 tons) include 2400 tons wheat ex •Braganza' earmarked for Bahrain but still held by UKCC agents. 3000 tons of wheat were re-exported to Saudi Arabia during the month from UKCC stocks. flats .LUi) In addition there is in stock in Bahrain 1500 tons wheat and 300 tons barley earmarked for Saudi Arabia. TRUCIAL COAST. Figures will follow. rlo ^ V 4 nil - POLITICAL -IT/tC' , Telegram G.T.C. From ■Residency Agent, Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 839 Dated 5th August 1943. Bice Nil Nil 1531 2 V/heat &amp; flour Sugar 500 8 Nil Nil' 4080 536 3*jr Tea Nil 45 216 9 Piecegoods 60 Nil - - Barley, Dari &amp; Millet Nil Nil 1746 9 2. Stock 1531 of rice is according to inventory recently held. Britagent -From Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire T© No.C/1077. Dated the 8th August 1943 \ Continuation of my telegram No. 516, dated the 4th August 1943* Trucial Coast figures for July 1943 are as followa;- Rice Nil Nil 1531 2 Wheat &amp; : ) 500 8 4080 6 Flour ) Barley ) dari ) Nil Nil 1746 5 millet ) Sugar Nil Nil 536 Tea Nil 45 216 4* Piece- ) 60 Nil goods ) Note Stock of 1531 tons rice is according to exhaustive inventory recently undertaken which shows for first time all quantities privately held however small. Polite*JaP*gent, Bahrain.D.0.NO o C/952-34/3A 0€*SY British Agency Sharjah.* Dated 13th Sept your demi-official letter No.C/1193 dated 7th September 1943. ^ 5-1 2. ' I am sending herewith a list showing the figures for Fay,June,July and August which is a copy of our tabular statement upto date* yours sincerely® Ma. ■Q A tr o A T t\T**■» 29/1 and 29/20 Telegram From To Repeated to wo. Political resident at d hiraz political i\gent, nuwalt Political Agent, Bahrain Bolitical Agent, ^uscat T/921 Dated 29th received 30th September 1943. fvly circular memorandum Wo.C/6 March 15th. in future please furnish separate figures in respect of tl) wheat (2) wheat flour (3) barley/millet having regard to existing stocks and consignment promised by MESO and due .shortly, and assumption that 30^ cereal requirements will in future be met by barley/millet, your requirements (a) wheat (b) wheat flour for each of next six months commencing from uctober 1st. - rrior -Telegram Frem Te Ne. Dated Q Political Agent, Bahrain Political Resident at Shirpz 645 3rd October 1943. Reference year telegram ho.T/921 September 29th. Require ments of wheat *nd flour. 2. Bahraini total monthly requirements of cereals are 900 tons. Flour is not repeat not required and the monthly v/heat and barley/millet figures based on percentage given in your tele gram are therefore 630 and 270 tons respectively. 3# Wheat . Following consignments for Bahrain consumption have been promised by M.E.S.C.s- (a) 600 tons in paragraph 1 of Cairo telegram No.400 Mides Wise. September 15th. Q?ay Mackenzie subsequently revealed however that their balance for delivery to Bahrain Government amounted to 506 tons only. Of these about 106 were consumed in September; remaining 400 are for this month. (b) 600 tons in paragraph 3 of the same telegram for November consumption. 4. Bahrain will thus require following amounts of wheat in tons in addition to those mentioned in previous paragraphs- For October 230; For November 30; For December to March inclusive 630 each. I have not taken into account the extra 150 tons applied for in paragraph 1 of your telegram No.T/784 September 16th for October consumption, as I have seen no reply from M.E.S.C. Barle y. At end of September about 480 long tons remained of the 600 metric tons issued by U.K.C.C. to Bahrain Government. Figures of roquirements are therefore as follows:- October and November Nil Dec ember 30 January to March inclusive 270 each. 6 . Figures for Trucial Coast will follow on receipt of monthly stock position for September. PoliticalTelegram From Te No. Dated 29/1 &amp; j 1 - 0 0 Pelltlcal Agent, Bahrain Pelitlcal Resident at Shiraz 646 3rd October 1943. Demi-Official. Reference my telegram No.645 ef tedny regarding Bahraini cereals requirements. 2 . Figures were based on estimated consumption ef 900 tons monthly. Increase ever 824 tons communicated in this Agency telegram No.179 3rd March due te experience gained in last few months. It has been discevered that Bahrain*s population now considerably exceeds figure recorded in 1941 census and monthly figures sent to you show that actual consumption for five months April to Au^st has averaged 890 tons. Arrival of construction men and increase in air services would account for additional ten tons. Consumption in Trucial Coast however is well below 2463 tons given in telegram referred to. 3. Total monthly cereal ration in Bahr-in is 20 lbs. I do not know how this compares with rations elsewhere in Gulf. Would It be possible fer Bahrain to apply for increased quota of 1000 tons, in consideration of reduction in Trucial Coast quota by aegeral hundred tons, and so be able to increase rations? This might be justified by the changes in *local economic conditions which have considerably affected figures of consumption in dif ferent areas. 4. I would have awaited Wakefield’s return before sending telegram but his plane is not ceming today as expected and I should prefer not to burden him with arrears. I believe he concur in enquiry in previous para. this would Pelitical29/20 Telegram From TO No. Dated G.T.C. Political Agent, wahrain Residency Agent, Sharjah 657 5th uctober 1943. Your telegram 1C1B uctober 5th. p.v 2. Please fcheck and repeat figures for tea, which appear to be wrong in view of last month's balance of 128 tons. - Political -Telegram G.T.C. From Kesidency i\gent, Sharjah To Political Agent, Bahrain No. 1029 Dated and received 6th October 1943 Your telegram 657 uctober 5th. Stock on 1st October 102 half 204 regret mistake Export of tea &amp;as been stopped since 4th October. % Britagent ► -O-cco .Ct.t A-xj-, ft-tCc©/* &amp; a ^ * 1R. 7SS- rs• No*C/1047-34/3a* British Agency, Sharjah* Dated the 9th October 1943* To, The Political Agent Bahrain* Venoranduin* Reference your memorandum No.c/1288 dated the 29th September 1943* are correct and in accordance with the figures received monthly from th c local authorities. Although the quota of tea has been fixed as 18 tons the local authorities have not been asked to keep within the 18 tons fixed owing to the large quantity then in stock. I have no™ asked Dubai tockeep within ^.3 cases daily, namely th Dubai consumption and export to the rest ghaikhdoms The figures given about the monthly stock including Qatar should not exceed 13 cases daily5 ^ S 22/20 G.T.C. Political Officer, Truciai Coast, Sharjah. Political /gent, Bahrain. Telegram From To Mo- 1^80 Dated 9th received 10th November, 1943. © Reference my telegram 1166 November 7th. A check of the tea stock has reveaied an error in last 3 months figures. These should be 152 119 and 110 tons instead of 128 102 and 85 tons given. Error due to illness of Head of Customs much regretted. NCJ - POLITICAL - //f /&lt;? /o /n /± 3ftXPRESo bbXThK . From To No. C/1552 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Bahrain . Dated the 11th November, 1943. Your Memorandum No. C/66 March 15th. BAdRAIN OCTOBER Rice Nil Nil Nil Nil Nil Wheat 860 Nil 630 1 Nil Flour Nil Nil 261 5 Nil Sugar 188} Nil 300 Si 415} Tea Nil Nil 32 1 * Nil Piece Nil i} &lt;N» • Nil goods Barley 60 Nil 270 1 Nil IRUClAIi CQAb'I QCTQBhR . Rice Nil Nil 43 4m Wheat Nil Nil 2030 i} Flour Nil Nil Nil Nil Barley etc. Nil Nil 718 ' 1 } Sugar Nil 10 526 Si Tea Nil 3 85 5 Piece goods 25 Nil - «•» Political Agent, Bahrain.1. Date of despatch 2 . List of enclosures. * DEPAKTMENT/OFFICE. File No. Serial No. Letter Draft Memorandum Telegram No, ' Dated / S5 (Small) B. P. 6767/A/S-1G9—10-2-42—50,000 pads.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES r HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. EC.3. TEL.EORAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY COOES USEO: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUNDAR-SHAHROUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LI NGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT Bahr e in } IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no..L/630. 21st November, 1943. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, .v\'4r U. K. C. C. STORES /• jrr In reply to your letter C/No, 1567 of 18th instant, we give you herewith details of U.K.C .C. Stocks on hand on 15th November : Wh eat - 1220 tons (approx) ex 3S. 'STEVENSON TAYLOR' B arle y - 60 tons -do- ex S3• '3- SANG' Sugar - 405 tons -do- 7130 tons -do- ex T/V.'BRITANNIA' ex M/V.'DALGOMA'. In addition to the above, we nave now received 255 tons Sugar ex T/V.'PAN GOTHIA' which vessel discharged her cargo on 17th idem*&lt; EXP fins 3 LETT® m st From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident at Bahrain. No. C/1711 Dated the 8th December, 1943. Your Memorandum No. C/66 March BAHRAIN NOVEMBER. Rice Nil Nil Nil Nil Nil Wheat Nil Nil Nil Nil Nil Flour Nil Nil 140 2} Nil Sugar 8 Nil 179 Nil Tea 12&amp; Nil 42 1 Nil Piece-goods 77} 17} - - Mil Barley Nil Nil 135 Nil TRUCI/'L COAST NOVEMBER. Rice Nil Nil Nil Nil V/heat Nil Nil 2354 If Flour Nil Nil Nil Nil Sugar 573 62 985 4} Tea 41 Nil 116 2 f Piece-goods 23 Nil - - Barley N.B. Nil Nil 645 1’ Sharjah reports an error in figures submitted for September and October. These should read SEPTEMBER - Wheat and flour 2873 , OCTOBER - Wheat 2750 Barley 1218 if Political Agent, Bahrain. NCJCOPY. /?/// f D.O.No. C/1299-34/3 k . §ubject:- Rice. British Agency, Sharjah. Dated the 5th .ecember, 1943. &amp; Dearlvlajor Hickinbotham, M ^ Kinaly refer to your D.O.No. C/1580 dated the 17th November, 1943. , j. 0 . r • ^ ^ regret tha^ir we h ve discovered an error inthe xJubai Custom s t igures for food^stuffs in hand, which has been ' reported in my telegram No.1288 dated the 4th December, 1943. This erior goes back to October (before I returned here from Bahrain) and arises from approximately 2000 bags of wheat, containing 224 lbs each, .eing reckoned as 164 lbs each. Our monthly consumption of all food grains no. works out as follows:- September(Ramdhan) October November 1313 tons. 1047 ' 1012 ', , , 30 ^hat it appears that our consumption in October was not above average. ' 3 * _ ^7 estimate of Dubai’s population at 100,000 was ^ S11 P °L^ he u ? e f 1 ’ T for which 1 apologize. The figures should have ou 6 ?! ,0 ? 0 4 . W ^ ich 1 think is approximately right, although the o laikh maintains ^ stoutly the population of Dubai with the bedouin ae^endent on ii is not less than 30,000. at 13p:lbs per head one ag oj rice suffices for 12 people so that 4000 bags should have been consumed by 48,000 people. In addition to this many ships left Bubai for the 1943-’44 trading season, and these had to be provisioned. Lorrimer s estimate of the population was made in the early years of toe century since when there has been a large influx to the Trucial Coast, and to Dubai in particular, from Lingah, Hormuz, Bandar Abbas, Jask and o her smaller towns in South Persia, and a further influx to Dubai from other Trucial Coast towns has occurred in the last year. . , 4 * , 1 am doing my utmost to ascertain the present stocks held by private persons but no one is in a position to Five ^?$»r at ? 4 . risures for his neighbour’s stocks and the task in a verv difficult one. All that is certain is that the stocks in the bazaar § 0&lt; * 0lvns ( v 'hich, you will note from our memorandum No. V r • 3 ^ dated the , 27th duly, 1943 were only ascertained by the use of stringent measures) have been exhausted and that rice can v now be obtained in Dubai only by force or by threats. This rice, unfortunate iy, was not a Government supply like the ./heat, barley etc., but was ordered, imported and paid for privately by merchants. c , . 1 doubt if smuggling from ;atar is still goinp on Shaikh fiamad bin Abdullah was deeply impressed by the serioasnees“of the stf rice situation ofi his visit here and since his return I hear that he caught the youngest uarwish brother smuggling rice and told hi_; no., to. ( This was related by the miscreant himself to Cantain Nelson of the Khuziatan) Yours sincerely, (Sd.) h.p.0’C.Tandy. To. Matyor T.Hickinbotham, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.li ^ a ($p 'is ■ I cQ/lQ 1 X9 /l 3 Telegran Inter ’O’. From Political Resident, Bushire* To Political Agent, Bahrain. No .4. Bated and received the 1 st Tanuary, 1944. IMPORTANT. Following is repetition of telegram No. hides rise 634 dated the 27th December from Cairo,Begins. Addressed Political Resident Bushire Hides rise 634 London Baghdad. Your telegram No. 2338. * We understand from U.K.C.C. Baghdad that stocks on Trucial Coast on November 30th were. (a) 1999 tons ex Braganza. (b) 516 tons ex Ksang and Baroda. 500 tons ex Kweiyang. (d) Total 3015 tons against ?monthly requirement of 1250 tons of wheat and ?65C tons of barley. 2. Please telegraph immediately whether this is correct or not. 5 . l!ust insist that flour stocks are taken up equally with wheat otherwise flour will deteriorate. -BRITC ON ST JL- /• - Ho l b f A 'l+ Li Telegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.5. Dated and received the 1st January 1944. IMPORTANT. ? € My immediately preceding telegram a. Please telegraph early comments. -HRITCCNSUL-2 r ,JO C 22/2. . Telegram From To Repeated to S. Political Resident, Bushire. F.E.S.C., Cairo. India Office,Lordon. H.T’s ambassador, Baghdad for Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 39 bated and received the 5th January, 1944. B.POITnNT. Your telegram Mides Fisc.634 December 27th. It transpires that Political Officer Trncial Coast reported errors in September and October figures totalling g— additional 1798 repeat 1798 tons and the sufficiency dates were accordingly set forward till January 15th. Bahrain unfortunately omitted to keep me informed of this and I was still ma&amp;irg an earlier date of December 15th giver by them. 2 . The figures qi oted by you appear approximately correct but Stoner should be able to confirm additional arrival at Shariah. 3. Your paragraph No.3. Political r-gent is being instructed accordingly. HWD - BRITCONSUL -2 J /so liM lol 79/143# yroia To Telegram 3# ?rom Political Reeident, Bush ire# To H#M•Ambassador, Cairo for M#S#S«C# Repeated Inlia office, London# Ho# 39# H#M#Ambassador, Bagdad for K#S#3.C# &amp; U#K#C#C# Political Agent, Bahrain (Saving)* Dated 5th Januaxy 1944# IMEORTAIST, Your telegram MIDSS MISC 6 ber 27th. It transpires that Political officer Truolal Coast From Political Resident in elan Gulf# reported errors in the September and October figures totalling an additional 1798 tons and the sufficiency dates were accordingly set forward till January 15th# Bahrain unfortunate ly omitted to keep me infoxmed of this and I was still working on earlier date of December 15th given by them# 2# The figures quoted by you appear approximately correct but STQNCR should be able to confirm them on arrival at Sharjah# 3# Your paragraph 3# Political Agent is being instructed accordingly# CONFIDENTIAL * British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BRI TOONSUL No# 15-S• Bushire, the 5th January 1944# Copy forwarded, with compliments, tp The Political ^gent, Bahrain, with reference to Bahrain telegram No#9, dated the 2nd January 1944*! iel Fr 09 To No • Dated it Heed* (i.T.C. Political, iiharjah. political, Bahi^aiii. 48 5-1-44 IMMb’JJiATii. Stock situation* Stock oi Government Cereals will be exhausted with in another 1 * 0 rt- / night even at present greatly reduced scale v consumption* Kesuits are already evidently in increa&amp;ea demand lor dates which has caused a sharp rise m prices in the last week and semi starvation amongst poorer classes, g. Svery expedient is being used to encourage xjc: import of dates but situation is nade much more dixT'icult by complete lack of information as to date of arrival ol next consign ment of gram already 4 weeks overdue. 3 . #e have been compelled to stop supplies of grain to Bedouins and 1 cannot answer for security of situation unless we can renew them soon* POLITICO/ 23/20 29/1 Sc 29/22 &amp; ($61 X.L.No. '^l-S dated 6-1-44 from P.R. Bushire. 1 . 2 . 3. 4. 5 . • • • * • • • • • • • • • • • • • ♦ • • 6. Cereals * Stoner Vvill press for more rapid supply of stock figures for M.E.S.C., j said w- should endeavour to neet^ them over this, but emphasised difficulty of obtaining reliable figures on Trucial C6ast. I emphasised that we had no desire whatever to see States given greater supplies than they could legitimately consume. 7. He expects to return to Bushire and make recommendations after further consultation, with me. 8. He also has proposals for backloading Gulf cereals entirely by dhow. I have said that this is only practicable (possible) for Kuwait.29/20 Telegram From To u.T.C. Political Agent* Bahrain. Political Officer, Trncial Coast, (E.O.)No. 20 Dated the 6tii January, 1943. Your telegram 12 January 4th. Sharjah. 2. Your telegram 1288 December 4th gave your wheat and barley etc. stocks as 2999 tons on November 30th; Now you show your stock as 2159 tons on December 21st. Thus your consumption, for December was only 840 tons as against an estimated consumption of 1900 tons, please let me have your explanation immediately. - P0 ill'll Can9/20. IM' &amp; § 71 lelegram From GTe. Political Officer Trucial. Coast, Sharjah. Politic a 1 Ag on t, 3 ahr ai n . Chief reason of low consumption appears to he abnormally low export to others. Ho mistake of the tohnl yet d i -cov- re 1. Gray Mackenzie 1 s Agent has giv - &gt;toner figures of about 130C half of 2600 tons for stocks at the end of December. I have given him no definite figures but he nay adk hsr then from yours and I suggest you give him the same figures. T have tried t r g•ve him 4 he impression that stocks will be totally exhausted between the 15th and the end of the month. Stoner hopes to arrive Bahrain tomorrow noon. 4. HAD. - P01ITICAI - 8 - /• '4 4% /I*. 4 ^iiqw WO *41-34/3A To, The political,Ag^nt, Bahrain* Bri'uiali Ajency,Bii«rjah* —x /&amp; L»ated the 5th January ^944* ( - 3ub.j act ; Food 3u;;plias . Keference ny telejran Wo. 12 dated the 3rd January 1944. 2 . J-t will have been noticed that the total consumption of food grains for jjeceitber waseonly 840 tons against an average tbtal nonthly consumption of 1110 tons. The reasons for this Were as follows:- Qatar were allotted a permit to export 750 bags wheat end 750 bags barley etc. as this month^J supply. This is the pro portion being consumed «roery where on the Truci^l co^-st ex- 9 cept in uubai when barley etc. been exhausted. Their agent refused to take the barley as ha said he had instructions to take only wheat, ^atar, in fact took only 15 tons during the n average of131 tons, rjm a 1 • al adxij Bukha 3 and jibah appear4. to have paken in woveober supplies sufficient for two months and thus have exported nothing in December. Their average monthly^onsumption of grain is about 29 tons and Abu Dhabi also took 49 tons loss thah its normal demand so that pul i teen drawn on for 194 tens less whan normal# Our next months consumption will therefore probably be 194 tons more than normal or, say, ^310 tons. For comparison it mav be mentioned that export of grain from sharjah/Dubai to the Trucial coast towns ^ nd Qatar in December 1943 were 498 tons against only 141 tons this year. Three factors which were estimated as likely to cause a rise in our grain consumption at this time of year appear now to have opera ted as expected. These v/eres- 3xhaustion of supplies of rice. Return of the pearling fleet. Provisioning of boats for the sailing season to Indict and Afri c^J \lthough careful search has failed to reveal to date error in our calculations of the amount of grain in hand, is always possible that a mistake has crept in and,even though our figures appear to show that we have grain for nearly two months mere, I have not felt justified in estii^t-; ing our supplies at more than on^ month. Our average monthly consumption of sugar appears to be a little over ICC tons but I have eftimated the 823 tons remaining as only 3 months &gt;upj ly X int . to begin release lad ion su r for barter forthwith. The procedure l propose to follow is being reported separately. It is impossible to estimate the rate at which it will be exported but it is possible taut thi ; ia*y r 5ach 150 tons par month and l so, the total mow in Du. i ill last 3 ha only# “ 5 * consumption appears to be not more than about 10 tons monthly, a figure much less than that previously estimated. Government control has brought aoout a fall in the orice of tea in Persia *'nd Irao and much of the tes^in Dub: i is changing^hmuds aw a loss. It has therefori not been possible wo formulate^ scheme for barter of this tea fo~ fo^^ imports and merchants are being allowed to export 74 tons be ; ^ the excess over six months estimated local consumption. Incident: liv Indian merchants have received information that the export of tea from Cali u o -#U'- cen freed -rom control ana liave be m offered any-' ouantiti^^' they wi§!? to import. 'Telegram From Q Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To No. 47 Datea the l^th janaary, ld44. A 1 Your Memorandum No. C/bb March 15th Bahrain LLCiiMBBR. Rice nil nil nil nil mil Wheat nil nil 300 2 nil Flour nil nil 62 i nil Sugar nil nil 92 i nil Tea 2Z nil bU 6 nil Piecegoods Barley 9 nil nil nil nil nil °2 nil TRUCIAL COAbT DhChMBBR Rice nil nil nil nil Wheat nil nil 1744 1 Flour nil njU nil nil Sugar nil 8&lt;d3 3 Tea nil nil 134 6 ^iecegoods nil nil - - - Barley nil nix 410 1 Not e Letter follows. - UiiU -I/O •131-34/3.4 To, British Ajency,Sh, rjah. Da'oed ohe 21st January 1944. &amp;T The Political ^ent, Bahrain* iubject : Food statistics* irij2-;o:huiDUi . ? rr yj -* Reference your memorandum ho * 148 dated tlie January 1944. 2. The figure of 2,000 bags given in my D• 0.No• C/1299—34/3 a dated the 5th December 1943 was a typo^rajjhic^l error for 20,000, which is much regretted. The amount in question was the total whe; t discharge of 2,000 tons of 3•5•Bra 0 anza.'This accounts for the differences inti- Liaoed to you in my telegram No.1288 dated the 4th December 1943, i.e. the increase of 578 tons in the dctobef figures and for a similar pro portion oi the increase of 1720 tons in the November figures, the remain aer o^ which appears to have been due to a separate error by 'the Dubai cu^ uolis• At the end o- oooooer tlie Sharjali custoits told us that they han c4 ^ons of barley and at the end of November they informed us that this was a mistake for 1 584. This accounts for the increase of 500 tons barley. I am very sorry that these errors should have occurred but i be- leive that 'the figures sent in December and oanuary were accurate, anu I will see oo it th^t the actual quantities a grain present are check ed by me or one of my staff in future. J * ^ii^ 1 regard tothe question of our anticipated consumption, I was under the impression that it was understood in Bahrain that our consumption was nowhere near the ^,800 or 1,900 tons a month on which, odder oo ensure ohat we are sent suppli-s in good tine, we base the estimates in our monthly stock telegrams. As for back as January 1943 ohe when Political Agent estimated our consumption at 1425 tons per mont couxiuential memorandum -^o.'w/SO/ of 20th January 1943 to the Residency A^ent), and again in March he put our monthly rice consumption at 1,000 tons - there was then very little wheat being consumed - vide kix paragraph 3 of his telegram No. 178 dated the 3rd March 1943 to the Hon'ble the Political Resident. Your weiejram No.797 of 23rd November 1243 seems to imply that _l 250 tons per month was considered sufficient grain supply for the ’Crucial Const and when I visited Bahrain in Decem ber I left a list showing that our average monthly consumption durin^ th« six months April - September was 1110 tons. A copy of this list, brought up to date, is enclosed. .^ar did not in November import supplies sufficient for tto 4.months but deliberately refused to take their December allot/ment oif barley with the intention of demanding this la ^er in wheat. (This demand has Since been made and chey have been told that they must consume the baLle *» ra in as '^be rest of the Trucial Coast). It is difficult to ensure uhat the monthly sujbply for each outlying dhaikhdom is shipped in the month to which it relates because often one month’s supply does not constitute a complete boat-load ana they therefore prefer to t; ke two months supply at a tii^e. Purtlier, although penults may be issued for cheni co export jrain during any moiith the/ may defer shipment, owin^ oo inclement weatlierpother causes, unoil the succeeding; month. Except ^atar die Quantifies involved are no o lar e. Heierence paragraph 4 of your me. iorandum under reference. At die end oi October only 430 bags of rice remained in the market of Buoai available tor purchase. It was impossible to ascend in the quant ifies in the possession of householders which diey were not prepared wo sell, -he position appears to be that, although stocks in die market Bn are exhausted, those in die possession of private persons are not and it appears reasonaole to anticipate chat the gradual exhaustion of these noarded supplies will 'increase the demahd ‘for other grain. 3o fax; only eleven boats have left Dubai for Africa and thirteen for India and, as you point out, their provisioning should not have been taken into account! 6 * is probable that the apparent drop of 2#0 tons in our consumption during December would disappear were it possible to obtain j'l an accurate statement of the stocks held at the end of the month in outlying Shaikhdoms, buo ic is quite impossible oo obtain figures from Abu Dhabi, Aalba, Fujairah and the Auufi-ul-Jibal ports in time to include diem in our monthly stock telegram early in the month. Practically no c ars are now operating, and statements would have to come by camel or sailing ooat. I shall do my best to include figures from Ajman, Urn alJt (§&gt; 8 ? Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. HCAO OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E C 3 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY COOES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSREH A M A RAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ BUN DAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE ... L/92 RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Bahre in. 3 1st February, 19 44 'V H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Referring to your letter No. C/£l^ of 27th ultimo, we give you herewith details of U.K.G.C. stocks at 31st January, 1944. I IaJP Yours faitnfully, Sncl:Director of Customs and Port Officer,No*183-34/3: Britisli ency,bharjah• Dated the 3rd February -^b4^ To The Political A^ent Bahrain^ I BI.OAUiDUL. Reference my telegram No * 182 datea ‘die Bra February 1944* During January exports to Trucial Coast to\jis ware about normal and the fact that the total consumption of the Trucial Coast is still some 200 tons below last year's average is due to low con sumption in Jhurjah and Dubc i. The reason for this in Sliarjah is tiiat consumers are refraining from buying anything buu the very minimum of mixed grain as they ./realise that they will soon be able to get a percentage at least of white flour, in Dubai there was a hu t ,e demand for wheat immediately the adulterants were exhausted and the Food Company on my instructions, cut down their issues of wheat tojohe very minimum in order* to conserve it for mixing with the flour, /hereas, while mixed grain was available, bedouin anu others were ^iven whatever quantity they asked for, during January they have been given only a small pro portion of their demands. 3. Reference paragraph 5 of your memorandum No*148 dated the 15th January t'..44, as explained elsewhere there are no stocks actually held by Lessrs:Gray Mackenzie. The merchantile firms in mubai ana ^harjh! holding grain stocks are the two Food companies whose books and stocks I have personally examined, together with the stocks in the customs, no proper count of grain in ware-houses is possible as, owing to lack of storage accommodation, the ware-houses are filled to the roocf and it is impos&gt;ible to gst in at the door. The only solution to this is that we should build ware-houses* duff leant money for this probably be avail able ana I should like to discuss th-j: project with you' on your forth coming tour* ^ ^ Js v ' Political _Gray, 3 HEAD OFFICE : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES t BUSREH BUNDER-ABBAS AMARAH LINGAH KUT BAHREIN KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT AHWAZ DUBAI BUN DA R-SHAHPOUR SHARJAH BUSHIRE MUSCAT RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no...L/128 Bahre in.,. 15 tn February, 19 44 • \&gt; - \V° H. B. M’s Political A^ent, B a h r ein. X LSI Dear Sir, V/e enclose Inerewith. details of* stocks on hand at 15th February, 1944, held by us on account of U.K.G*C* Yours faitnfuily, Enel:A F S/25 0/ 29/ 343 /7&lt;S) l/IlDDlfi FAST SUIPLY CEFTRF. General Headquarters, Middle Fast, CAIRO. 12th. January 1944. P.R.P.G. Bushire. Copy to MESC(L) Paiforce. UKCC(Mebod) MV/T London. SUk,^ 1&gt; oi Cereals to Trucial Co^st . 1. Furtiier to our 250/29/291 of 11th. December, we have now received further statistics concerning the stock position on the Trucial Coast. 2. We understand that on the 15th. June 1943, stocks at Sharjah and Dubai amounted to 5628 tons to which must be added the cargoes of the s/s M BRA-GANZA W and the s/s *KWEIYaNG* i.e. 2500 tons, making a total of 8129 tons. On the 30th. November it is stated that the stocks were as f o Hows: - DUBaI . 1999 tons Wheat ex. H BRAGAFZA* arrived 27.6.43. SHARJAH . 516 tons Wheat ex.'FSANG* arrived May. 'BARODA' ^ June. 500 tons Wheat ex.'KWEIYANG' m 3.7.43 . Total 3015 The s/s 'EMPIRE ENVOY' which should reach the Trucial Coast eventually will bring the stock position up to the f oil owing:- DUBAI. 4300 tons Wheat/Flour/Barley.' SHARJAH 1616 ' * ' ' Total 6015 3. From the above, and presuming that the 1100 tons of Rice included in the June totals have been consumed, the con sumption from the 15th. June to 30th. November would appear to have been 5113 tons, say a monthly consumption of 930 tons. 4. if you agree that the stocks after the arrival of the •EMPIRE ENVOY' will amount to 6015 tons as above, we would, again ask for a telegraphic reply giving us a clear indica tion as to when you consider that the next consignments should reseh the Trucial Coast. We consider it most import ant not to hold too large stocks in this area, as there will inevitably be heavy depreciation when the hot weather starts, and it would now appear that you are holding 5 months* stocks. We would further emphasise the extreme importance of consuming stocks of 4 lour with first priority as obviously these stocks will be most liable to deterioration. 5. We c^n only express our regret at the delay in the sailing of the 'EMPIRE ENVOI' for reasons beyond our control. Ae hope that the present and future position of Bahrein will have ueen seuurw* uy m+'x'x vu. But here again we would emphasise that there will inevitably be certain stocks of Flour at Bahrein and other Persian Gulf Ports, and we consider it absolutely essential that thisi Flour should be consumed as quickly as possible in preference to Wheat in order to avoid any loss from deterioration, and we are most grateful to have received your telegram No.39 dated 5.1.44. 6. We do most sincerely hope that Capt. Stonor*s visit to you has been of value, and we anxiously await his return with a full report on the whole situation. Sd» F-E..CAAV&amp; BG for Director of FoodA * M Political Agent, Muscat No. 599 Dated 9th received 10th March 1944 i.Iy circular Memorandum No.C/66 of March loth, 1943. Cereal Stock Position. 2. Please expedite your report for February. Britconsul2 a/80 &amp; &gt;^u Telegram From To Wo. 246 Datea tne 11th March, 1 j44. Political Asent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Your Memorandum c /66 March Banr ain February Vi/heat nil nil 2 £3 nil 3 weeks Flour nil nil 875 nil 3 montns Barley nil nil 525 nil 6 weeks Rice nil nil 19 nil - Sugar nil nil 244 nil 7 weeks Tea nil 2- 55 nil 5 weeks Piece goods Ij 5 - - 4| - Irucial Coast February Wheat 1580 nil 2300 5 Flour nil nil 1745 4 Barley 280 nil 1275 3 Rice nil nil nil - Sugar 525 315 6 78 4 Tea 1 50 95 6 Piece goods 4 nil — — Id tons rice taken over from an absent merchant’s godown. - POLITICAL - CWJTelegram Q From To Heoeated to Tup. 6 76' Political Resident, Bushire. Political, Fuv.ait.Reference his tel. iro.188 I.iarch 8th. Political, Muscat Reference his tel. No.C/392 March 8th. Political, Bahrain.Reference his tel. No.246 March 11th. Do figures include U.K.C.C. stocks ?Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: head ornce: 122. LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. EC.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS; GRAY CODES USED: BUSREH AMA RAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO. L/167 BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE Eahreirij 14tn Marcn a 19.44. H. 3. M's Political Agent, B a n r e i n.' Dear oir, U. K.C , C. STOCKS - MI D -MiAxiCH Tnere is no change in the stocks shewn in our letter No. L/l^Jof kind instant. Yours faithfully,I ' I I I •! •! •! •! *1 I *1 'n fc# a 1 1 Telegram From To No. 276 Dated the 20th March, ld44. 29/20 G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjali. ® m3 10^ IMPQRTAiMT Your telegram 557 March 3rd. 2. Wheat and barley, please explain differences between your figures of 1580 (half 3160) and 280 (half 560) and figures given in paragraph 7(a) of enclosure to my printed Letter C/407 February 29th. Also check figures in your column 3 with those in my paragraph 7(b) and explain differences. - POLITICAL - NCJ I i Vi _ •Telegram U.T.C. From political, Sharjah. TO Politics1, Bahrain• No. • 469. Dated and received 21st March 1944. IMPORTANT. %} til Ket'erencG to your telegram No.276 March 20th. 2 # Figures given in your note oi 23rcl February/- for quantity discharged by CHANGON in Dabai does not agree with Gray Mackenzj-e’s bill which gives 229 half ol 458 tons barley and 1042 half of 2084 tons'wheat. Apart from these your figures make no allowance /'-'N for shortage. As shortage liad not been measured by February 29th X allowed a 4 per cent shortage on manifested quantity. Actually this was too little and quantity landed ware approximately wheat X497 tali of 2994 and barley 288 half of 676.@ &lt;S) I wi:i give definite figures as soon as I receive confimation from Gray Mackenzie which I have now been awaiting for over a month. 3. Previous Stock. My figures give complete stock as instructed in your memorandum No *148 of January 15th and not merely those in Customs. POLITICAL.9 ft No, C/51o Political Agency, Banrain. Dated the 21st March, 1^44* To Messrs Gra.y Maiikenzie 5c Co. Ltd., Banrain# MBMGitAhDuM. Reference yooi* lettex- Nol L/32 dated the 1st February, 1944. 2. I enclose an extract from a copy of M.L.B.C. telegra® No# 5 Saving dated tne 3th March, 1344. You will note tnat the figures do noi^ agree with tnose forwarded to me under cover of your letter under reference. I shall be glad if you will explain how the difference nas occurred. NCJ H.B.M l s. political Agent, Banrain.2T- i i I *t •! •! •! M I *1 .0* U tJL XI ko (g) (/&lt;? G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, True is 1 Co£ j 3 t, Sharjah. Telegram From To ho. 286. Dated the 22nd Parch 1944. II PO-tTArT y ^ r our telegram 469 March 21st. 2. Figures in my note of 23rd February were obtained irom Dray Mackenzie &lt;5c Co and \ ere examined and I presumed checked by you in Dharjah. 3. BARLEY rr our telegram 357 gives import figures for February J-s 280 tons. In your telegram under reference you state quantity -landed was 288 tens. My note gave total quantity to be landed as 304. Which is correct ? T /IiEAT l^y note gave rf Changon n as 1321 your telegram 357 as 1580 your telegram 469 as 1497. Mhich is correct ? -PCI I^ICAI -J f mrm i i 1 •! *1 •! *1 *1 I '0 Telegram Q From To No. 287. Jateci the 22nd ixrch 1944 6 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. \to ' 1107 v our telegram £74 larch 16th paragraph 2. 2. Tpucial Coast figures were given in the order asked for in your Lemorandum referred to. 3. Barley figures are 280 tons half 560 landed during February none exported and 1275 tons half 2550 present in the country at the end of the month being sufficient for three months approximately at issue rate of 450 tons half 900 a month. » -PCI ITJCAL—felegram Q From Ambassador, Baghdad. To Political Agent, Bahrain Repeated to Political Kesident, Bushire telegram No.Sncom 37* No.Kncpm 39. Dated the 24th and received the 25th March 1944. Following for Gray Mackenzie* v our monthly stock telegram for March must be followed by stock certificate in quadruplicate from your branch repre sentatives certifying quantities of each cereal ( also sugar at Bahrain ) not paid for on March 31st. -AlSABLhJXT?- l r/.?/{,&lt;&lt;I I I *t «| *i «| *1 I •! '0 I From ® iu ijuJP Liljij Lj IiF'FXj^H HtBtM* 3 . political Agent, 3&amp;arain. Messrs Gra^ Mackenzie &amp; Cp. Ltd., Baarain. To No. C/5B3 Dated tne ^otn March, 1J^4. dated the 24th March, 1344, from U.K.C.C., Baghdad :- Your branch representative should furnish a state ment in quadruplicate after issuing your montlily stock telegra* for March. The statemeiii/ should show quantities of cereals not paid for on tne 31st of March, and should also include sugar at Banrain. / hk H.n.M ! s. Political Agent, Bahrain. S- NCJlelGHrar.g n/z'o G.T.C. /X 7 . 22 / jX({ 2 i i^rom TO ^iO Dated Political, Sharjah. Political, iiahrain. 481 23rd March 1944. * • ara 286 March 22nd. xnportan t . Your telograi' 2. figures could not be checkjed hero when your note v^as seen here as dray Mackenzie had not at time that submitted figures to this office. 3. Barley . ITy telegram 357 as drafted and encode ed gave 280 tons as landed in February . Correct figures 288 tons. \ \0^ y/hcat. My telegram 357 gave total imports during the month that is cargo of Kingyuan and Changon. The total wheat landed during February is believed to oe ±497 tons but Gray Mackenzie have not yet confirmed in writing that shortage amounted to 159 tons on manifested quantity of 1656 tons.i ' I •! *1 •! •! *1 I *1 r if?a From TO no - Political officer, Trucial Coast,Sharjah- - Political Atfent, Bahrain* — 507-34/3A p^. Dated the 26th March 1944* Reference ray telegram bo *481 March 23rd* shortages in cereal shipments* 2* Gray Mackenzie*s Agent has now confirmed that the short ages on the January and February arrivals of cereals are as follows Dubai 158,675 lbs * ' y Flour ex*-s*S*i5npire Fnvoy (landed in January) Barley ex-y. 3 .empire i&amp;woy (landed in January) Wheat ex-S*S*King Yuan Wheat ex-3.S.Changon Barley ex-S.S.Changon NIL Total 158,675 lbs. Dubai 156,800 1 lbs* Shariah NIL Total 156,800 1 lbs. Dubai 72200 lbs Shariah 5776 u Total 77976 lbs. Dubai 268250 lbs. Shariah 40515 Total 308765 lbs. Dubai 3808 lbs. Shariah NIL Total 3808 lbs. 3* As the manifested quantity of flour was 2000 tons anil the shortage is now given as 71 tons it appears that the quantity landed in January was 1929 tons and this figure should be subsituted for that of 1991 tons given in my telegram No*182 February 3rd. The shortage of 9 tons shown by the latter figure is alleged by the Dubai company to be due to short landing o^jbags and not to slack bags which Gray lilackenzie do not admit* I hav££tne agent to settle the point with the food company and 'the customs and it may be that the figure for flour may have to be altered again if It is decided that the number of bags landed was really short* Similarly the figure for barley received during January, given in the same telegram as 999 tons should now be altered to 930 tons. 4 . For the wheat (landed inXFebruary) Gray Mackenzie now give the total manifested quantity as 1654 tons and the shortage as nearly 173/tons so that the figure of 1580 tons wheat in my telegram no* 357 3rd March should read 1481 tons. The final figure for the shortage on the barley landed in February now appears to be 2 tons on a manifested quantity of 300 tons so that the figure of 280 in my telegram No*357 3rd March should be amenaed to 298 tons* 5* As the food companies are paying Gray Mackenzie*s bill 1 full without deduction for shortage the Trucial Coast is paying fo 316 tons of grain which it has never received, and our 'sugar fund' id out of jacket by more than Rs. 132,000/- on this account* Gray Mackenzie r s Agent here tells me that the company is claiming this sum from the U.K.C.C. and I shall be grateful if everything possible is done to see that the claim is pushed. 6* Gray Mackenzie f s Agent has asked me to give my opinion as to the amount of shortage due to pilfering between the ship and theI •! *1 i i - 2 - shore at ijubai, while giving 40^ to 50% as his estimate* ihe total shortage in cargoes landed at Dubai is about 295 tons and, in rnjr opinion, iw is not possi]®e for as much as 1 118 - 147 toils to have been filched from the lighters # x consider that the maximum loss due to pilfering from lighters was not more than 10^&gt;. as regards responsibility for this there is no question chat the grain was at the time in Gray Mackenzie *s charge ani that it was their responsibility if they suspected pilferageyto report the matter to the shaikh and demand restufotion of their property and punishment of the offen ders* No sijch complaint was madeo 7* It is hoped, in future, to avoid such loss and the ensuing complications and uncertainty as to grain on hand, by separa ting slack bags from full ones on the ship* ihe slack bags will be specially escorted ashore and weighed at once* ihis will be facilitated if smaller consignments are sent in future and storage will also be easier* Political off icer,Trucial uoast&lt;&gt;1 -- gjr; ii ' i i I »| *1 *i *1 *1 I *1 i i v 5i r \ Telegram 29/20 .1.C. m &amp; Poiit/icai Agent, Bahrain. Political 01 ficer, Trucial Coast, Shar.]aii, From To No. 315 Dated the 30th March, 1944. Reference paragraph 5 of yoor Express Letter No. 507 ifcrcn 26th. I assume that you nave tauen over your full quota for March and that no payment has yet been made for goods not delivered. The difficulty will presumably arise in Aprit wnen you take over the remainder of the 'Empire Envoy', 'Kingyuan* and 'Changon' cargoes ? please confirm. :MCJ political - y .• /Telegram 2d/20 G.T.C. From Political Officer, fruciai Coast, Snarjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain, Wo. 546 Datea ana receivea the 1st April, 1044. Your telegram 515 March 30th. We iiave tuKen over our full quota for March tuo months quota vvhicn we have not received in full e.g. Gray' Mackenzie have 'handed over'. Ail Kingyuan wheat. Empire Envoy barley in Dubai, and Changon wheat in Sharjah. W T e have ^aid for these consignments in full but taey nave been delivered snort by amount shown in paragraph 2 of rry Express Letter 507-04/3A March 26th. WCJ - PO-uIlTChu -I t i ». I?s OPS TELEGRAM' 49 COPIBS Lr % m To Pron s M # Yf # T p LOIIPON s M.-SoS.C. W. 1366 SAVINS D,, 24th March 1944 Add^oss^d M.V,.T. London No* -4566 Saving, repeated to BASRA for M # W # T* &amp; H 0 . 4 B Saving, BAGHBAB &lt;4J for M.K.S.C* &amp; U**K # *a.Ce No e 186 Saving, BUSHIBS for P.R.F.G, Noo 19 Saving, JSBBiiH Ro. 6$ Saving t BAHg^IIL-f^r Political Agent Bo. 10 Saving&lt;/ KOWBIT for Political Agent 7 Saving, SEA^AH EC.- 4 Savingo PERSIAN GULP CSESALS_/ y Reference yoar Saving A,425 and our Saving 1249 * ©11 figures in tona 0 % • 1 0 In the light of figures which we have now received allowing movements of cereals in the Gulf during February,, we are able to **mend the stock j&gt; 03 ition shown in our Saving 1249, ©b follows j 2. ’ Free stocks held on 1st March for U.E»C*C. a/c Wheat * 10,460 Flour 1 6«gl5 Deduct releases for March coxisumption, at revised figtire : Add expected arrivals dumping March s . Marie Bakke - 7,430 Tankers - 940 Bsttested stooc on 1st April* 18,675 11,750 8,370 Gulf position is, therefore, secure provided that the programme of Australian loaders promised in your p^rns 2 &amp; 5 is adhered to without fail - namely, March 8,000, April 7,000, May 7,000 ? plus 3,000 presumedly from tankers. This pro gramme will enable us to carry out the policy agreed with P 0 R*P»G, of fflaintaining a reserve in the territories equivalent •0 one month® s consumption. At the same ttee^ it will provide a esill margin for stock building up to 10,000 as an emergency reserve fos Persia. The creation of this reserve remains high up In our programme as oui latest advices from Teheran stress the inadvi &amp;&amp;b :ll i ;y/.. { ,mm:-'9 Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: head orricc : 122. LEADENHALL STREET. LONDON. EC.3 TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES USED: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BUSREH BUNDER-ABBAS AMARAH LI NG AH KUT BAHREIN KHORAMSHAHR KOWEIT AHWAZ DUBAI BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR SHARJAH BUSHIRE MUSCAT RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. • Baxir e i n j 6 tu Ajr .i l &gt; 19 44 . The Political .vgent, We enclose Herewith our statement showing balance of U.K.C.C. stocks on hand as at tne end of march, 1944, for your inforLiation and records. Yours faithfully, for GRAY, IKACKSrnL’E CO., LTD.tl/tt ( LXPkEbb LEITEH Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Bahrain. 10th April, 1044. a s-r Your Memorandum C/66 March 15th 1943. BAiittAIR MARCH Wheat - Nil 417 * Nil Flour - Nil 820 4 Nil Barley - Nil 599 6 Nil Rice 407 Nil 412 3 Nil Sugar 252 ii 410 Si Nil Tea Nil i 33 1* Nil Piece- goods 39* 2J TKJCIAL CO AS! ! MARCH 33 Wheat Nil Nil 1454 3 Flour Nil Nil 1446 3i Barley Nil Nil 1084 3 Rice Nil Nil Nil Nil Sugar 326 62 790 4* Tea 13 98 81 6 Piece- goods 1 Nil - - From To Ho. C/614 Dated the Political Agent, BahrainXl/t Subject:- Cereals - Trucial Coast, M.S«3.C«. GAIKO. Copy *- P * A a • BAiSeh? * TjfecBAGbAk' l^CC J3ASKA, lf«/T BASRA, 13 j&amp;rll 44, !• According to a statement today received by the UKCC from Gray Mackenzie, Bahrein, the following was the stock position as at 1st Feb 1944:- SHARJAH Wheat - 123 Tons. fey Flour - 400 Tons* Barley - 351 Tons. DUBAI. Wheat - Nil Tons. Flour - 1600 Tons. Barley - 1000 Tons. These figures show minor discrepancies 2 . figures included in the P.A’s report dated 23rd Feb, but it is proposed to accept the figures as above as the correct ones* 3. SHARJAH - The following summarizes events since 1 ; (a)* Stock as at 1 Feb 123 Wheat 561 Barley 400 Flour* (b). Arrived since 1 Feb 'KING YUAH' BO N Nil N Nil M 'CHANGON' 264 N 61 N Nil If TFT W 412 H 400 (c)* Delivered to Sheikh FHB. 335 130 80 MARCH. 124 221 180 Total 'W SET £66 7 (d). Stock as at 1 April. Nil Wheat 61 Barley 140 Flour. 4* Agent werei- Consumption requirements as agreed with Political FSB. MARCH, 80 Wheat 90 w It— F 7 o 80 Flour 90 VTo 80 Barley. 5. Consumption Feb &amp; March Held by Sheikhdom as at 1 April H n Gray Mackenzie ^ n M 90 n N 170 rf' 1 ' - 457 Wheat 260 Flour 351 Barley - 170 170 170 - 557“ 66 161 T•. - Nil 140 61 - Wheat 230 Flour 242 Barley to sheet 2/-V 6. Basis the agreed quota of 90 tons each Wheat # Hour snd ' &gt;■ Baxley requirements are thus covered until the second half of June. In addition* S3 M BARALA M now loading at Basra is scheduled to lift 210 tons Wheat for Sharjah, 7, BUBAI - The following summarizes events since 1 Fehi- WHEAT FLOUR BAKLEf (aj Stock as at 1 Feb ... (b) Arrived since 1 Feb • . • • . • -■■m 1666 1555“ 'KING YUA1T' ... • •« • •. 280 Mil Nil 'CHANGON' ... • •. 1040 • I'll 240 1^20 1600 1240 (c). Delivered to Sheikhi- FEB «• • ... 200 400 300 MARCH • . . •«. 720 720 720 §20 li&amp;o 1020 (d). Stock as at 1 April • . • • • « 400 480 220 6 . Consumption requirements as agreed with P.A werei- WHEAT FLOUR BARLEY FEB ... ... '355 •■“355 *355 MARCH ... 360 360 . 360 Total - 680 680 6&amp;6 9. Deliveries as per para 7(c) above • • • 920 1120 1020 Consumption Feb &amp; March • • • • • • 680 680 680 ileld by Sheikhdom as at 1 April • » o 240 440 346 ** ' Gray Mackenzie w N • • • 400 480 220 Total - 640 ¥20 5e6 10• Basis the agreed quota of 360 tons each Wheat* Hour and Barley* requirements ate thufc covered until about the beginning of June. In addition* S3 'BARALA' now loading at Basra is scheduled to lift 160 tons barley for Dubai. XX. SHARJAH Sc DUBAI - I'rom the above it will be seen that both Sheikhdoms are now holding on their own account at least one month’s reserve. This in addition to the approximately one month’s quota stated to be distributed amongst the shops. Arrangements have been made for quota quantities to be released by Gray Mackenzie during April* and further shipments will be arranged to enable similar releases to be made month by month. DAW/gkw. / - ^ Major.. Middle East Supply Centre (Liaison).V' //(toft Jo &amp; 2 . I should therefore he grateful if you could:- j.- , , (fh Confirm the figures in the attached statement particularly the quantities stated hy the UKCC to have been taken up hy you during Pel and March. , . Cb). Advise me of the actual stocks now held hy the Bahrein Govt as opposed to HESC 'Tool'stocks held hy Gray Mackenzie. . It would he of great assistance if you could send me at the beginning of each month details of the quantities actually rec eived hy the Bahrein Govt from Bray Mackenzie during the jocHdiKg?: preceding month* It would appear that on various occasions important discrepancies have existed between the quantities that MESC have authorised the UKCO to release and the quantities which have antua.llv been taken up and paid for. 4. I with the summary contained in^my letter MESC should also he glad to know if yeti e 1/38/452 of 13 April. }kl e in agreement &amp;jor., M E S C (1). OAW/gkw.mm&lt;7 C Dh;* '’ ■^pf’erence attached returned herev^^th. The under noted are the deliveries to the Bahrain Governiaent ex U.B.C.C. stocks* February TT arch V/hea t 1250 tons 710 tons Flou r 400 tons Barley 410 tons. 160 tons. The item of 559 tons flour issued to Saudi Arabia in February is really the balance of an amount allocated for January. The deliveries to the Saudi Arabian C*overnment in TT a~ch aue as per shown in the statement. I also confirm that we held in Government stores as on 1st April the quantity as shown by Fa jor Warner. Bahrain Government stocks as at 1st A rv ri‘&gt; were 410 tons Wheat, 599 tons Barley and 775 tons flour. To: Fa,]or T H.B.T .Hickinbotham, C.I.E., O.B.E., rM s Political Agent, BaHr*ain.f Ho. C/68S Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the *&lt;Jbth April, 1944. UtU To M.h.S.C. CLjP.A.I.0., Baghdad. MEMORANDUM Reference your letters Nos. MESC/b3/4b^ aated the loth April and MESC/38/453 dated tne 17th April, 1944. 2. I am in agreement *ith the summary contained in your letter under reference of the 13th April. 3. I enclose a copy of a letter from the Director of Customs, Bahrain Government, addressed to me after he had examined the enclosure to your letter of the 17th April which I trust will at least in part answer the questions contained in that letter. H.B.M* s. Political Agent, BahrainV Subject : In dian suuar stock s• I was surprised to find on 15th of this month that Indian su^ar stocks had been exhausted in inibai when, from our office records, which are, of course, based on returns from the uubai customs, there should have been over 300 bags in hand* I have, accordingly, checked the imports, consumption,and exports of sugar from June 1943 to date and it* is clear that 14656 bags have been imported and 14258 have been consumed or exported legitimately leaving 398 bags unaccounted for. 2 * xhis is explained by the fact that the jubai customs brought onto their books as received the complete manifested quantities and did not deduct the amounts short or lost while unloading which are as follows:— (i) (ii) (iii) dji^pu, June 269 bags short owing to the sinking of alighter and 2 bags lost overboard. This is confirmed by Gray Mackenzie*s agent. 269 bags were sold by auction. Tsinan. November % 43. 52 bags damaged and sold by e auction. Wosang. November 4 S 43. 40 bags damaged by sea-water and sold by auction. Our receipts in June and balance at the end of the month were therefore 27 tons too much and 27 tons should be deducted from the balance on hand at the end of every month from june 1943 to date on account of item (i). similarly on account of item (ii) and (iii) 9 tons should be deducted from our receipts in November' 43 and from the balance on hand at the end of that and succeeding months. 3 . The above shortages account for 363 bags out of the total of 398 ana no explanation appears to be forthcoming for the remaining 35 bags except that they*represent the sugar lost during transport, storage, re-packing, etc.^ As io io public knowledge that the coolies pilfer the su^ar wherever possible a loss of a quarter per cent on this account over a period of 9 months seems to me remarkably little. 4. A separate error has come to light in the figures for sugar in stock sent in at the end of March which should be increas ed by 2/^ tons before making allowance for the shortage explained above. The corrected figure for sugar in stock at the end of March is 774jtons which may please be substituted for that of 790 tons given in my|* / telegram No.571 dated the 3rd April 1944.f&amp;b'O FROM * TO _^GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD. The Political Agent, Bahrein Bahrein Enel. 1 A Dear Sir, 44 tfe enclose herewith our statement showing balance of U.K.C.C. stocks on hand as at the end of April, 1944, for your inforaiation and records. Yours faithfully, for GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO., LTD. /llJ- ^f&gt; ffk BriXatfc nt, 31ia r.j a h. Political, Bahrain. 773. and received :th Kav 1944. Telegran Prom To ITo. . lated v our telegram 423 ray 7th. /hen Sharjah and ^ubai - submitted therr figure v s at the beginning of the month I drev their attention to the excess over the allot- nent. Po satisfactory explanation was given except tliat they were not aware of quota fixed and were issuin' food generously. I have ? warned the authorities and food companies to keep 'within the quota fixed and steps ;erec-- v 29/20 Telegram From To No 1176 Dated 13th and Received 14th May, 1944 Q Political.Resident, Bushire* Political Agent, Bahrain-* &amp; iS'&lt; My memorandum No C/66 March 16th 1943* Monthly stock returns. 2. In future stocks held on U.K.C.C. account should not repeat not be included in your monthly statements# If necessary they will be ascertained on enquiry# 3. Will Kuwait and Muscat telegraph April figures of existing stocks other than U.K.C.C. (mut) each commodity. Will Bahrain telegraph similar figures for Trucial Coast only, 1CH - POLITICAL - f* H** ( ~29/20 @ §) H'&amp; y-' G.T.C. political Agent, Bahrain* nesidency Agent, Sharjah* Telegram From to Mo 455 Dated 15th way, 1944* Your telegram Mo 745 May 3rd* 2 . Are figures given by you exclusive or inclusive of b.! U*K*C*C* stocks* -»-f the letter then please deduct u*K*C.C* stocks and telegraph actuals held by you. ICH - POLITICAL -29/20 Telegrcm G.T. C. From Residency /gent, Fhprjeh. To Political /gent, Pehrain. No 822 Dated and Received 17th May, 1944. Your telegram No 455 May 15th. Figures held by us on May 1st exclude repent exclude U.K.C.C. stocks of Wheat 916 (half 1832) Flour 745 (half 1490) Barley 468 (half 926) ICH - BRIT/GENT - ll29/20 Telegram C From To No 469 Beted 21st May, 1944. Political /gent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Pushire. / 160 &amp; vour telegram Yo 1176 May 16th. Trucial Coast figures exclude repeat exclude U.K.C.C. stocks. - POLITICAL - ICHmm*■ r Continuation of Telegraro No* 2607 Saving, Addreasedi ?^*7,T.,London - Prom: M*E*S.C* Total releases of wheat and flour 6 ^ , ^89 * This is 33o less than previously reported to you 4* Arrivals during larch were: Uarch 1st British Embassador 162 - ' 24th Coliaa The arrival , in liarch of these two tankers corrects our as.tlmate of expected arrivals listed in our two Savings 1566* para&gt;2 and 1926 f para&lt;6* 5* The summary of the foregoing is therefore? Stocks at Liar eh 1st Arrivals during M Stocks at Liar eh 31st Detfuqt ? March releases Stocks at April 1st-* This compares with a total of 9?695 estimated in our Saving 1926, The difference arises from the adjusted stocks per para* 2* from the adjusted releases per para* 3* from the actual tanker arrivals per para* 4* and fir .i-uoicn now made among April commitments of the sale cf 3000 flour to Persia which was previously shown as a March commi tment* For this last* see note to para* 7 below* 6, Arrivals notified since April 1st? per para*2 n it 4 18*117 Har&amp;f Bakke WearfieId To Abadan Storanger To Bahrein, Queens toil Heights To California Standard To Abadan Gervais To 7*430 319 471 22 ? 807 7o April commitments were; Persian Government ^ Koweit i^xs cat ' Bahrein Truc^al Coast East Saudi Aiabia klOC PAIC Sundry releases j&amp;S&amp;S £12HE 3,000 520 400 , 570 ^ Ljj? zoo v x,® f’A 535 990 •Qtn This is- the parcel of flour- bought fey the Persian Govt* to offset their sale to India of 3000 Zabul wheat* %'ids our Saving 1926* para,7*$ ! %€ Continuation of Telegram ffo. 26.07 Saving♦. Addressed M.' 7 .T.London - From 2 fi.E.S*C. Total April releases of wheat and flour 8 *. Free stocks held on UKCC account on April 30 th are therefore estimated at:- 10,394 £l££. 1,831 12,225 9. 10 , Expected arrivals during May:- Glenbeg British Chivalry Kron Princessen 10,220 ■ 340 ;oo iudSi Allocations for consumption in May are ►- - PAIC 790 AI0C • 1,620 Kovxeit 310 310 . Bahrein * 660 15? Trucial Coast 450 450 reseat . 400 East Saudi Arabia* * ‘ 4^^f 790 1,620 620 815 900 400 S7G U,^ The allocation to East Saudi Arabia is provisional. On April 1st their quota of ’^heat/Flour was reduced from 2000 id 1155* It is at present Under discussion to reduce it still further* The proposal is to limit East Saudi Arabia to 15,000 a year all cereals, with effect from January 1st, 1944, In a full year the ba 650* However* reckoning that East Saudi Arabia has already received since January 1st about 6000 tons all cereals, the monthly seal-?, of Theat/Flour May 1st to Deceffibcx* 3lst \?ill be 579 only* This is, however, subject to confirfiiationo 12. The for^arcL position at May' 31st may be estimated thus s’ Stocks at 'Sia? 1st, per para t 6* 12,225 ■&amp;d&amp;i Expected cargoes, per para.9- il»Q£Q 33^285 May consump11 on 5 per para* 10 ,5.715' ,Stock at May 31st iiaZfiw.ii ■ &amp; w» n Continuation of Telegram No * 2607 Saving» AddressedsU^./^T.London ^ Froas iJ.K-3*C* ^13* from information received from Persia it would appear that Teheran is adequately covered until next harvest* Persia is therefore unlikely to require the 7000 reserve - the balance of the 10^000 . originally planned «- for which we have been programming * Nevertheless ? we still consider it prudent to continue stock piling for this purpose until the success is assured of the 1944 Persian wheat collections scheme* lists AoC.D, •-&lt;ap '*• * t* ay *- MftBOD (2) F312SD4/P0A FS/TSS29/20 G.T. C. Politic?! Agent, Eshrsin. Residency Agent, ^hrrjeh. . ('74 Telegram From To No 498 Dated 29th 1944. M.E.S.C. telegram No 6 Saving dated May 15th to you. 2. Please confirm that figures given by M.E.S.C. telly with local U.K.C.C. figures. - POLITICAL - ICH/ .~w 'V i 29/20 Telegrsra From To No 1281 Dated 1st and Received 2nd June, 1944. i political Resident, ^ushire. Political /gent, Bahrain. Personal for } ibotham. 2. Please include this surplus in return for May, from which month my returns to M.E.S.C. will ?commence. - BRITCONSUL - ICH29/20 Telegram From To Repeated Mo 24 Dated ord , 1 . Political 2 . ex 'Queenstown Heights') Parley i74 (half 343) Rice 260 (half 520) Flour 548 (half 696) 3. Estimated consumption during /pril and Mey:- Fheat 1308 (half 2616) Flour 516 (half 632) Parley 116 (half ?236 ) Rice 260 (half £20) 4. Therefore anticipate stock at June 1st to be paragraph 1 plus second paragraph minus third paragraph name ly: - Wheat 320 (half 640) Flour 807 (half 1614) Parley 657 (half 1314) 5. £11 figures in tons- 6- In view of foregoing suggest only small quantities of cereals be released during June to enable Government stocks to be reduced. 7. Consider Pahrain should make every endeavour to consume flour holdings as these are likely to deteriorate if stored for too long a period. Inter '0' H.M’s Ambassador, Baghdad, M.E.S.C. Ceiro.Telegram No 38 Political Resident, Pushire. Telegram No 25 Political Agent, Pahrain. and Received 4th June, 1944. Following from M.E.S.P.I.I.C. Cereals for Bahrain. Bahrain Government stock as confirmed by Agent at April 1st were:- Wheat 410 (half 820) Flour 775 (half 1550) Barley 599 (half 1198) Releases in fpril and May amount to :- Wheat 1218 (half 2436) (this includes cargo - AMBASSADOR -iy )l6 Telegr&amp;m # inter '0' Frora^ Political /gent, Pehrrin. Politicrl Besident,Punhire. No 519 y ted 5th June, 1944. f) ; 7' i$/) m HLf' June 3rd. 2 . Reference M,E.o.(L)P.A.I,C. telegram No 24 Figures for April 1st in above quoted telegrr® exclude 7 half 14 tons crushed wheat and 45 half 90 tons of ^ 1 mixed flour. My Express letter No C/614 April 10th and all other reports include these amounts. 3. My telegram No 518 June 5th includes an additional 410 half 820 tons of barley and 162 half 524 tons of wheat which the Bahrain Government inform me they hold. The barley surplus is due to the great dislike of the local population for this form of nourishment. - POLITICAL - ICH \IfjlO EXPRESS LETTER From Political, Baiirain, To MESCO, Cairo. Repeated. Britconsui, Bushire. No. C/662 Dated the 5th June, 1944. ; UKCC stocks - Bahrain and Trucial Coast . Your Savingram No. 18 May 15th. 2 9 With regard to U.K.C.C. stock figures on March 1st the following differences have been noticed from figures obtained from Gray Mackenzie and Company, Bahrain and the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah tons tons tons Political A^ent, Bahrain. Bahrain . Wheat 3482 half 6964 Flour 1101 half 2202 Trucial Coast . Wheat 1284 half 2568 jmCJ /c • d.B. M f s.1 S1 From H.B.M* s. Political Agent, Bahrain. To Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co, Ltd,, Bahrain. No. C/863 Dated tne 5th Jane, 1944. J.K.C.C, stocks . Reference your letter No. L/291 dated the 6th May, 1944. I would be grateful if you could please expedite yrir report for May. NCJ / H. \ H.B.M's. Political Agent, Bahrain &lt; 2c^. \- s \/ry * Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) ‘TrD. /£*) &amp;fL . HEAD OFFICE : 122 . LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON. EC. 3 . TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY CODES used: BENTLEY S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE CODE BRANCHES: BUSREH AMARAH KUT KHORAMSHAHR Ahwaz BUNDAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH IRE RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR BUNDER-ABBAS LINGAH BAHREIN KOWEIT DUBAI SHARJAH MUSCAT IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE NO. L/3q2 . Bahre in, 7th June, 19 44. The Political Agent, V/e enclose herewitn our statement showing balance of U.K.C.C. stocks on hand as at 31st May, 1944. Yours fa it nfully, for Cl o. ^ 3 ■ ’ll I• N0.C/947-34/3A BHITlaH AGENCY, SHARJ.AH. DATED THE 5th JUNE 1944 lei \ To memorandum. The Political Agent, Bahrain© Reference your endorsement No©C/79S dated the 21st May 1944* 2 # x enelose herewith a statement showing the position of cereals on the Trucial coast from 1st April to 1st June 1944 which differs from the figures given in letter No© MESC/38/502adated the 11th May 1944 from M.E.S.G., Baghdad to M.E.S.C., Cairo* Residency Agent,Sharjah*To umxm (MftWt?*) Fi-om s*- E* S»C«. 350# 3079 8AVTHG D* ?th Jime , 1944 Adores Bed to Londloa (MWT) Ho* 3079 Saving, repeated to:- Baghoad, M.E.S.G.(L) A 0*K*G*C.(5) Ho e 39U SAVING. Basra, M*?/*T* &amp; U.K.0.0% (3) No* tS SAVING Bushlre, P.E,PcG, No,35 SAVING Soweit, Political Agent Nod 3 SAVING Agent So*20 .SAVING Sharpe, Political Agent No* 7 S/^ - NG E5uacat, Political Agent No* 3 SAVING tfe&amp;a&amp;fi M.E.S.CU BepresentatiY© 350*111 SAYING. CSBEQSALS IN IMS PERSIAN GULP y.1 stoc&gt;; fignrss are xn tons, further to our Saving 2607, I, Free stocks of Wheat and Flour held on U#K.O.C* aceotaiAt in the Persian Gulf Area on Jure let m*e estimated ns follows 'cli&amp;at 15*170 Flow* __S20 Total 13 ?740 This compares with cur former estii^ate of 17^570 a difference of 1 - 330^ This difference is acco^mted for hy the muddle over the Queenston Heights (see para*2) arrivals during ttey ho log below expectations (see para* 4/ &lt;uid by ad^u&amp;tffients in the conuiiitBianto (see para*5)* 2. - The tanher Queens ton Heights arrived at Bahrein in April with a cargo of 227 wheat for the Bahrein Petroled Comparer* However, ! the Cosapany already held Sufficient stooks for their own require- laonts $ anci offered thib shipniont to tho Bahrein Gov or A.usent which accepted it* In consequence of this* the Maj release to Bahrein had to he reduced by 227» At the same time, it was pointed out by Baghdad to the*Bshx'ein Petroleum Company that privuxe arrangements of this nature created confusion, and that it would ho approc-t&amp;ted if the Company would communlcs-te with net ore taklA^g bclh action in the future*- CWe may*add that as recently as March, the Company wrote to this Centre complaining t.: at i ey * ; .ao. .reov*2 *’ ^ ^ no direct shipment of Australian wheat sine© July 1943 end enlisting our support in urging that tan&amp;ers should again b© nominated for Bahrein* Our reply to the Company was repeated' to you as Saving 1823. 1 ?V,C,, f (£*/&gt;*V v-^O w 3* As a result of the esaapade of tlie Queens ton Heights, free stocks held in U*K*C.C* account on May 1st should he amended to read. 10 ? 170 N */« Wheat Flour Total(gx® m , ' « 2 Continuation it telegram addressed to London (MOT) Ho«3079 Saving from M.K*S.C» . . 4« Arrivals notified to us during May were : 8 to domain 720 Olenbeg - 9 &gt;100 Xron Princes sen 500 10,320 is 740 less than previously estimated* 5* May commi tments were %~ Wheat Flour Total So we it 650 t48 v .650 Bahrein 422 570 East Saudi Arabia 558 942 1,500 Trucial Coast 760 ^70 ' 930 Muscat 400 • 400 PAIC 790 790 AXOC 1,680 60 1,525” 1,680 Sundries ■'57253 60 It will te noted that Bahrein* s q.uota haa been decreased by 227 to compensate for the direct discharge in April ex Queens ton Heights, and that East Saudi Arabia ie still budgeted for at the old figure, which accounts for the major portion of the increase over the total shown in para* 10 of our former report* 6* Expected cargoes during June are Clydebank 8,000 British Chivalry 340 8,340 June commitments are ?- Xoweit 650 ] 9001 500 ^ Bahrein Saat Saudi Arabia Trucial Coast 900 Muscat 400 Paic 740 AIOC 1,,680 Sundries 60 57555 _* It is hoped that the P*R*P«0. yogs. t £n Koweit and Bahrein, to you as Saving 2745* ,2 4f//fp ^ C recommend a reduction to B^ishire, repeated NOTE 2* If the new quota of 40,000 all cereals for Saudi Arabia 'Surlng 1944 is approved, East Saudi Arabia will be allocated 1,000 a month until the end of December w*e*f* May 1st* May releases, •however, were authorized at 1,500* therefore the June release will I/ry - ■' ■■ Telegrem From To Reported To 27 29/JL6 T nter m J n /mhrosrdor, Trghdrd. Politicfl rgent, Drhrrin. Politicrl Resident, ^ushire. Tel 26 TE2C Criro,' ( r rving) 0 'M repeated to Bahrain To 21 D ushire No 26. 1« It is our intention to release no repeat no cereals from pool stocks to Bahrain during June. 2. , Please inform this office repeated to p aIro what stocks are held by Government repeat Government at July 1st ICH - /IIP/S 7 DOB - injm; *:) If/p No. C/956 Politicsl Agency, Behrain. Dated the 21st June, 1944. To M.E.S.C.(L) P.A.I.C., Baghdad. Reference your letter No. MESC/38/502 dated the 11th May, 1944. ' &lt;&gt; 2. The attached statement has been received from the Residency Agent, °harjah, to whom a copy of your letter under reference was sent for verification. 3. You will note that due to an uneven consumption rate there are differences in the figures. Political Agent, Bahrain. NCJ'IPS12505/PGV^ /:z 11 ho MIDDLE EAST SUPPLY CENTRE, 10, SHARIA TOLUHBAT. CAIRO. 5th JULY 1944 Political Agent, Bahrein^ \ Cereals Stocks y \\% We acknowledge your C/862 dated 5th June, 1944. 1* Our Baghdad Representative supplied us with stock figures at 1st March, 1944, received fran Gray Mackenzie, as follows : (a) BAHREIN Stock at 1st Marj 1944 Adjustment to final outturn figures Yftieat 3482 - 161 3321 Flour 1101 jb 1 111 ! (b) TRUCIAL COAST Sharjah 124 Dubai. 1120 1244 2* We have accepted these figures as correct. COPY TO: Assistant Director Food (Supplies). JC BAGHDAD. FKPG, BUSH IKS. M2SC(L)CHQ PAIFORCE./ Subject i- Cer ea l? - Tyucial Coast. M •ij *S .C • j C sir o • rzo$\ {&amp;$!) i 7 7 Tel Ext 151 GHQ Palfofce MESC/3«/^&gt;4 28th Jun 44 Copy to P.A. Bahreini U.K.C.C., Baghdad for action on para 7* U •K eC »C • y Basra • M.W.T., Basra for action on para 7* Further to our 38/502 dated 11 May 44. 1. We have now received from the Political Agent, Bahrein (his C/956 of 21 June), a schedule of releases, receipts and remaining stocks as at 1 June which he has received from the Residency Agent, Sharjah. 2. The stocks now reported greatIv/ differ^from the anti cipated position set out in our letter quoted above, but as they are reported actual ground stocks, we intend basing cur future release instructions and shipping requests on them. In this we would ask U.K.C.C. and M.W.T. to note para 7* 3« It is reported that at 1 June, the following quanti ties were held SHARJAH Wheat Flour Barley Stocks held by the Sheikhdom Stocks held by Gray Mackenzie 91 213 117 23 121 (Our 38/502 figure for easy ref) 304 (317 117 50 144 182) DUBAI Stocks held by the Sheikhdom Stocks held by Gray Mackenzie 551 609 562 244 524 1160 562 768 (our 38/502 figure for easy ref 520 200 360 ) Note 1 Stocks reported to be held by Gray Mackenzie were released by us during May but apparently delivery had not been effected when this stock return was prepared. 4. The differences apparent, comparing our anticipated position as at 1 June with the stock figures now reported, are due to (a) differences in the stocks as at 1 April, (b) fluctuations in actual consumption figures. 5. (a) SHARJAH stocks as at 1 April. Sheikhdom stocks now reported As shown by us in 38/502 DUBAI stocks as at 1 April. Sheikhdom stocks now reported As shown by us $ the same letter refers 327 162 156 287 90 181 727 664 647 240 440 340 6. (b) • • •6 . (b). From the stock return under review it is noted that, month by month, the quantities of cereals actually consumed vary considerably 5 for Instance, for the month- of April Sharjah’s consumption is reported as - 182 wheat, 140 flour, 137 barley or approximately 1 -£ months quota, whereas during May the consumption was - 54 wheat, 45 flour, 57 barley or roughly half a month’s quota. Over these two months it will be seen that Sharjah consumed more than its agreed quota. Dubai, on the other hand, consumed less tham its quota over the same period - the total quantities con sumed being 576 wheat, 5 o 2 flour and 623 barley. 7* Next Action . Will UKCC please release, and MWT please arrange space for the following to be shipped in August 1 To Sharjah 360 wheat. 180 barley. T 0 Dubai 645 wheat. 326 barley. plus any outstanding quantities that may be then awaiting shipment against our release instruction 38/524 dated 2 June 44. 8 . When shipment of the quantities mentioned in para 7 has been effected, the Trucial Coast will have sufficient cereals to cover its needs until the end of October 9. Recapitulation of the foregoing is therefore SHARJAH Wheat Flour Barley Stock as at 31 May - see para 3 Plus releases made in our 38/524 304 117 144 of 2 June 180 - 90 Plus releases in para 7 above 360 - 180 Consumption at agreed quota rates 844 117 414 for June, July, Aug, Sept, Oct. 900 wheat and flour 450 DUBAI Stocks as at 31 May - see para 3 1160 562 768 Plus ’’ESANG” shipment 2 June 75 - 394 Plus releases made in our 38/524 1440 - 320 Plus releases in para 7 above 645 - 326 Consumption at agreed quota rates 3320 562 1808 for June, July, Aug, Sept, Oct. 3600 wheat/flour 1800 10. All figures represent tons. 11. The assistance given us by the Political Agent in forwarding the stock-state is greatly appreciated and it would be most useful if similar returns could be rendered periodically - monthly would be ideal but it is appreciated that this may not be practicable. (R. L. Mclntire) Major. M.E.S .C.(L) . ATB/epMo. C/1124 . . ^; Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the 29th July* 1944. To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. MhMOEAJ^DUM ^ t Reference your memorandum No. C/947-54/3A dated the 5th June, 19 44. please send me a similar statement, in duplicate at the beginning of each month. Political Agent, Bahrain.Talegrara From To Ropoetod Political Resident at Shiraz* Cairo* H.M^s* Ambassador 9 Baghdad* No* T/ 101 * Dated the 14 th July 9 1944 * &lt;g) §) 3?]'l (For U.K.C*C.) Following arc figures in tons of stocks held in Sheikhdoms on June 30 th* WHEAT FLOUR RARLKY RICE Kuwait 2 0 0 277 129 . Bahrain 84 601 916 160 . Trucial Coast 2410 306 1316 Muscat 710 16 392 - PRIOR - Qwmmuii * No. C/42. Office of the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz, the 14 th JUly, 1944 . Copy forwarded with compliments to? The Political Agent, KuwaJJ^* The Political Agent, The Agent, Uussat.No. 1205 Dated INPCHTANT 3rd (received 4th) August 1944. ■ Your telegram 668'August 3rd. Tea stacks 21 tons.V*$&gt; I ^ CEREALS POSITION ON 1st AUGUST ; ON THE TRUCIAL COAST. S H A R J A H Wheat Flour Barley Gray Mackenzie s^ock on Isx. July - - - Arrivals during July — — - Total - - - ^Released during July — — _ Gray Mackenzie stock on 1st August - - - Shaikhdom stock on 1st July 398 46 ’• ? 154 Receipt during July - - - Total 46“ 154 Consumption during July 50 20 57 Shaikhdom stock on 1st August 348 26 97 D U 3 A I Gray Mackenzie stock on 1st July - - - Arrival during July (Wo-Sang) 323 — _ Total 323 - - Released during .July 323 — — Gray Mackenzie stock on 1st August - - - ^ Sheikhdom stock on 1st July 2Q12 262 1162 Receipt during July 323 ~ — Total 2335 262 ms - Consumption during July 497 201 400 Shaikhdom stock on 1st August 1838 61 762ry © &lt;*/3 Political Agency, Bahrain. Battel the 7th August, li^44. Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain. MBMOtudjLUM ld44. Reference your letter No* L/362 dated the 7th June, 2* • Kinaly expedite your returns for the 15th June, and the 1st August, 1^44. ii.B. M* s. Political A^ent, Bahrain.r* Telegram From To No T/207 Dated 6th, Q. Political Resident, at f^iraz Political ^gent, Pahrain received 7th August 1944. Personal. io i Your telegram 672 July 20th. Existence of this stock cannot be denied.^/ Please reply to M.E.S. C. that figure 559 tons reported in your C/682 £pril 26th. was an error and that correct figure is 922 tons reported in my telegram No. 1296 June 12th. -Prior- MB. IR. 684 Dt. 7/8/44.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSREH AMA RAH BUNDER-ABBAS LI NG AH BAHREIN KOW E IT DUBAI 122. LEAOENHALL STREET, LONDON. E.C.3. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE GRAY khoramshahr Ahwaz bundar-shahpour bushire MUSCAT No, UKCC/G/17 RAS TANURA EL KHOBAR Bahrain, 9th August jg 44 The Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir, As requested in your letter No.C/1160 of 7th instant, we enclose herewith two statements showing balance of U.K.C.C. stocks on hand as at 30th June and 31st July 1944, and trust same will be found in order. Originals of these statements have already been sent to U.K.C.C.Ltd.,Baghdad. Yours faithfully, &amp; CO., LTD MS. Enel• 2B ahraini 1st August 1944Telegran From To 29/20 &amp; 29/22. Inter Ord. MSS'', Baghdad Political Agent, Bahrain No MES^/30145 (18X300) Dated 17, received 22nd August 1944. im 6 Secret, ^ereals for Truoial ^oast. vour ^/HOS dated August 9th states that Sharjah held following stocks on August 1st. Wheat 348 half.696. flour &lt; 71'*7/72 26 half 52 barley 97 half 194. Your ^/1156 dated August 6th states Political Officer Sharjah confirms that at Same date 3 half 6 months supply held in territory and no deliveries necessary until October 1st. Please confirm which report is correct. Mt? I.R. 740 Dt 22/8/44.Telegram iiQ From To No T/S16 Dated 21st, received 22nd. August 1944. IMPORTANT. Political Resident, at Shiraz Political Agent, Bahrain 4p Please telegraph to Embassy Paghdad for Ministry of Transport Supply Centre, Trucial Coast cereal stocks on July fclst. broken down into Sharjah end Dubai. MB. I.B. 732 Dt 22-8-44 -Prior-Telegram From U.'jL' . 0. To Political Ac'ent, Ba ,rain. Re a idency e t, Saar j an. No. 752 Da tea the 24th AtL 0 ust, 1944. IMMLDIiiTJj Your memorandum C/119b August 2nd. 2. As a result i a vir.n ^ 0 u I re^'Orted in my express letter No. nil July 2Jt;i that Trucial Coast stocas were sufficient to carry on for three montns and that no further shipments required until October 1st. please confirm tnat tnis is so and that deficit stocks at Snarjan will be implemented from Duoai. Also confirm tnat issues made in one montn are for consumption in the succeeding month. - POuil' ICaii - 1MCJTelegram I^ter_ Ord. From Political /gent, Bahrain To. Prodrome, Baghdad No. 761 Dated 27th August 1944. Ii^UKTMT. Following for k'ir]rjle irpat ^nnnlv npnt.-pp. 2. Figures given in my letter C/1165 August 9th are correct. Political Officer Trucial Co?st , s report contained in my letter C/1156 August 5th is based on total Trucial feast figures. Deficit in Sharjah stocks will be met from stocks held at Dubai. 6. Political Officer Trucial Coast f s report that 6 months | supplies in hand must be viewed in light of fact that issue in July is for,August consumption i.e. nil stock report on October 1st will mean population has one months supply. Necessary however, for U.K.C.C. to guarantee shipments by 1st October. -Political- MB.■ n -tT— i &lt;•» / ,nr ■I . r ?2 Telegram From To. No. 762 Dated 27th August 1944. IMPORTANT. Political Agent, Bahrain Prodrome, Baghdad Political Resident has asked me to telegraph Trucial Coast’s cereal stock figures on July 61st, to Ministry of Transport Supply Centre Baghdad. Fe think this must be mistake for Middle Bast Supply Centre. Latter should have received figures concerned and authority inquestion may be referred to them if necessary. -Political-Telegram Prom Q* Political Resident at Shiraz. To Middle East Supply Centre, Cairo. Repeated H.M’s. Ambassador, Baghdad. (For M.E.S.C.}. Mo. 1/234. Dated the ath August, 1944. Confidential BAHRAIN RECEIPT' Following are figures in tons of stocks held in Sheikhdoms on July 31st. vVheat Flour Barley Bahrain 1640 480 820 Trucial Coast 2186 78 859. Muscat 1316 16 833. Rice 48. 2 * Kuwait figures will follow. - PRIOR - J «R .B «M . Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz, The 9th August, 1944. Copy forwarded with compliments toi- The Political Agent, * Kuwait. The Political Bahrain. The Political Agent, Muscat.f BY AIR MAI L. V?. ! w,'- HEAD OFFICE: 122 . LEADEN HALL STREET, L 0 ND 0 N.E.C. 3 . TELEaRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUS R E M. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BAN DAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE no. UKCC/BD/190 Bahrain, Bist August 193 44. United Kingdom Commercial Corporation Ltd*, Baghdad. Confidential. BAHKAFS RECEIPT.^ Dear Sirs, D at a.«.* • We enclose herewith our Month^ly Stock List in duplicate for the month of August 1944, showing details of your stocks at Bahrain and trust same will be found in order. Yours faithfully, for CHAV, W MS* cc* UKCC - Basra, . with one copy of the/above monthly return. / &amp; G0. f LTD. Political Agent v - Bahrain, with one copy.J try 29/20. Telegram Cypher. From M.E.S.C., ^aghded. To Political .Agent, Bahrain. No. mESC/c4659. **oted the 16th and received 19th September, 1944. KESTKICTEQ . Grateful if you would reconcile Gray Mackenzie and Sheikhdom stocks Sharjah and Dubai shown by you June 1st with Sheikhdom stocks July 1st. K.ivi. *A.a h' Telegram • From To • No. 1002. Dated the 6 th November, 1D44 20 /20. Dn clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer Trucial Coast, Sharjah C 2 IMPORTANT , Your telegram No. 1616 dated November 2nd. Figure for barley omitted by you in coding Please repeat, - POLITICAL - Telegram Fn clair. From Political Officer Trucial Coast, Sharjah. To Political Agent, Bahrain.• No. 1633. Dated the 6 th and received 7th November, 1944 . Your telegram of November 6 th. Figure for barley 623. POLITICALTelegram From To No. 1003 . 2. for period G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Political, Sharjah. Dated 6th Nov. 1944. IMPORTANT -.our telegram 1616 November 2nd. '.That were your wheat and flour imports under review. PoliticalNo.C/1617.1235, BlIrloH AG3NCY, 3HAIVAH. 2C7 DAT2D TH3 2nd N0V3.1BER 1344. rVU I enclosed herewith a statement showing the cereals postion as on the 1st November 1944. Political officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. Copy of enclosure/to hJSC Baghdad under P.L. No.C/1593 Dt. 9/11/4* R.h.EXPRESS LETTER . From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident at Bahrain. No. C/1594. Dated the 8th-November, 1944. Continuation of my Express Letter No. C/1588 dated November 6th. Trucial Coast . Whea t 1417 Nil 1426 4. Flour Nil Nil Nil Nil. Barley 896 Nil 628 li. Rice Nil Nil Nil Nil. Sugar Nil 2 619 3. Tea Nil 1 164 4. Piecegoods 'Nil Nil *• • 7a Political Agent, BahrainL M u of/;o 79/200 A Teleiraa From To Hoyoated So.T/P29 Dated the 9th November 1944. /£J' Political Resident, at Bahrain. Middle .TSast Supply Centre, Cairo. Prodrome Baghdad, for Middle Bast Supply Centre. My telegram Ho.T/826 November 8th. Truoial Coast iMhe^t 1426 half 2852 barley 628 half 1256. - RESIDENT - iio. C/467 Office of the Political Resident Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, 9 th Mot ember 1944. Copy forwarded with oomplimenta to - The Political Agent, KUWAIT . The Political BAHRA IN . vr The Political ^ r T T rCAT , in oontin\a» tion of Residency endorsement Mo. C/463 dated the 8 th Movember 1944.Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To P.O.T.C. Sharjah. No. Dated 1074 / 4th December 1944. IMPORTANT. yll @ I Your telegram 1748 December 3rd. 2. Please telegraph import figures in respect of wheat flour and barley. -POLITICAL- AMO. jf-cW MPCrcT P /u</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000ba_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/773</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000ba</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/773</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 29/20 I Bahrein &amp; Trucial Coast Stock Position and Statement of Bahrain Imports, Exports and re-exports of certain foodstuffs’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-27T21:17:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (317 folios)</extent><extent>Files papers are arranged more or less chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 319; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-299; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This is a correspondence file about the importation of essential food commodities and cotton piece goods from India to Bahrain and the Trucial Coast ports of Dubai and Sharjah, under the quota system and the export licensing restrictions imposed by the Government of India during the Second World War (1939-1945), due to wartime shortages. The file contains the correspondence of the Political Agent, Bahrain with the Political Officer for the Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent, both Sharjah; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Director of Customs and Port Officer for the Government of Bahrain and the shipping agent Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited, Bahrain. They exchange information about existing stock levels of imported quota foodstuffs such as rice, wheat, flour, tea, coffee and sugar, as well as cotton piece goods for clothing. They also discuss arrangements for the timely shipment and distribution of new supplies, for local consumption in Bahrain and the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms, as well as re-exportation to Saudi Arabia in exchange for other essential commodities in short supply. Included in the file are numerous lists that were regularly compiled and circulated by the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain; the Political Officer for the Trucial Coast and the Residency Agent, both Sharjah and also Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited, acting as agent for the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation (Iraq) Limited. These lists show existing levels of essential food stocks in Bahrain and the Trucial Coast shaikhdoms, how long these were expected to last and details about shipments of new supplies from India, to maintain or replenish exhausted stocks.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited, shipping agents</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Middle East Supply Centre</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Food resources</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food statistics</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000ba#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>