<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002c6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:00:07.192Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ituM CL. 30NPID5NTIAL, D.O.lTo.D. 4398-F/34. &gt; T)eBr 8ir 'Richard, foreign and Political Departs . New Deliii; ftie 19th October 19 34. I '} j 3x Will you pleaee refer ti our express letter ro.B. P3^6-R/34, dr,ted let Tune 1934 regarding the cost of s-imply of 200 . 22 rifles with a cessories end ammunition? The Army ‘Department heve enquired whether these munitions sre likely to be required by the Afghan Government, as if not, the consignment, which was eet aside in anticipation of a demand by th*t Government, is desired to be released for utilisation elsewhere. 2. Y/e shall be glad to be informed wriat tne position is. If on the analogy of a previous case - vide co rre suonden ce ending with our demi-of f i ei ax letter No.F. 187-P/30, dated 23rd February 1933 - you wo hid prefer to let the natter drop, we will certainly concur, but on the underatending stated in '9iat letter. Yours su cerely» Gd.G.K.Garoe» Sir Richard ‘ r 'aconachie, KBR* &gt;GIR. , His Majesty's Rrvoy Extraordinary and Finister plenipotentiary at the Court of Afghanistan, Kabul. tfcU.CiiUrtE IN INDIA FOHtlGN SEOfiFTAHV’ Letter N 0 l173 Oa :: 29 NOV. 1934 ^ I ZJE: .1934Demi-official No. 336/4l(E) . British Legation, Kabul 29th October, 19 34« 'S c Dear Oaroe, Please refer to your confidential demi-official letter TTo.D* 439S-P/34 of the 19 th October. I I have discussed this question with Loc/Cjiart and consider it both useless an 1 undesirable to press ; the Afghan Government in the matter. I therefore agree that it may be dropped; the understanding you mention being of course implied. I believe the real reason why the Afghan Government have not proceeded wi tin the purcnase is their scute shortage of ready money. Yours Sincerely, Sd/- R. R. Idac jna chi e. O.K. Caroe, ^sq. » . Denuty Secretery to the Government of ndia in the Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi.Government of India* Foreign and Political Department. 5XPRS3S LETTER. From To Foreign, Simla* British Minister, JQafcul. No .D.2386-]?/34. Dated the / June 1934. Enquiry hy Afghan Government regarding cost of .22 rifles with cleaning accessories and ammunition. -x-x-x-x- Reference your telegram No. 360, dated 19th April 1934 and subsequent reminder. 2. The estimated cost of the stores at the present rates are as follows t- Rifles No. Mk.IV* 200 @ 76/- each. Tools cleaning Brushes, 200 @ -/3/- each. Gleaners, 200 @ 1/10- each Rode No. 6, 200 © -/ll/- each. Rimfire ammunition 600000 @ 11/8/*- per 1000. Plus departmental charges. Rs. 15,200-0-0 37-8-0 325-0-0 137-8-0 6900-0-0 1130-0-0 23,730-0-0 3. The rates prevalent at the time of issue plus 5% departmental charges and actual cost of freight and packing will he charged. The cost of special packing, if any, will he charge able in addition. 4. The rifles with connected stores are available. The ammunition however will have to he purchased from England and delivery will take 3 months from date of placing order* 5. If no objection, Afghan Government may he informed accordingly. THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. SD. cue. CAROS, Deputy ^secretary to the Government of India.♦COSTFIDjffrTIAL. Demi-official ITo. 225-( s). Dear Metcal f e» a n SJ To ro ' . ‘ British Legation, Kabul, T\ ' -i£ a if- j' » | 4th Decerater 1932. .? ; 'V • s 8 » y Please refer tcT'thB* corresrpo'ndence resting with Freser- LE C 0 ! 1632 Tytler^ memorandum TTo. 225 of the 29th October 1932 regarding an enquiry from the Afghan Government as to the probability of their wishing to purchase a more aims from the Government of India. The object of this enquiry is not stated but I suppose that the Government of India have arms available which they wish to dispose of advantageously, and if so the enquiry would perhaps have had to be made in any case. At the same time, if I had been here when the subject arose, I should have been inclined to deprecate such an enquiry, which inevitably leads to requests by the Afghan Government for concessions of some kind, if not actually for a free supply, and tile refusal of such requests merely makes matters more difficult than they would have been if the enquiry had not been made in the first instance. A copy of an office note by Fraser-'Tytier dated October 18th last which I enclose will show you what I mean. Fraser-Tytler reminded the Foreign Minister in a demi-official letter of October 29th to which there has been no reply. In the circumstances, is there any chance of the Government of India agreeing that the enquiry should be allowed to drop unanswered? If Faiz Muhammad were eventually to answer without further pressure, I should of course report what he said. Yours sincerely, Sd. R. R. Maconachie. H.A.F. Metcalfe, Ssquire, CIS., MVO. , Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, - Kew Delhi. ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S Letter No 52 vt. Dated ? MAR. 1933 Sacea . 2X. MAR. 193300 P Y I told Jbreign Minister that as I had received no reply I presumed that Afghan Government did not want any more arms from Government of India. Foreign Minister said they did want aims but they wanted them on a credit basis to be paid for in instalments. I reminded him of what Minister had said in 1931. Foreign Minister said Afghan Government had been very disappointed to receive this reply. They had a credit with both France and Geimany which they were paying off by instalments and it seemed that His Majesty’s Government were not being as friendly as they might be in their present attitude. I reminded him of our experience in Amanullah’s time* and said that I certainly could not and would not recommend a reversal of policy advocated by Minister. Foreign Minister said he would let me have a definite reply in a day or two. Keep pending. 3d. F-T. 18/10/1932.A &amp; Foreign end Political Department Few Delhi f the Fehruery 1933* D.O.FO*?, 187- ?/30 Proposed puroheee by the Afghan Government of erme end ammunition from the GoTerrment of Indie* -x-x-x-x-x* Pleeee refer to your demi-offi clml letter Io* &amp;2S*(H)*» dated the 14th December 1932* The enquiry Wee made not because the Gorerrvnent of Indie wished to dispose of surplus arms edventageously f for thorn to rogsrd the supply of 5000 units es a liability which they mi^ht be celled on to meet et short notice* If you prefer not to prose the matter further with the Afghan Government the Government of Indie are quite reedy to let tho question drop» but it should be understood that in that ease they may find it difficult to produce the weapons# etc* * immediately 9 if called on to do ao without notice* but becsuee they wished to know whether it was necessary Yours sincerely» 3d• H* A* ?• ketcal f*e&lt; Sir Richard Maconaohis# K*B*S*# C*I*%# His KaJeoty 1 s imvoy attnordinpry end Miniater Plenipotentiary st the Court of Afghani at an# Kabul*COBFIPSISTIAL No. 152 • His Majesty’s ^J^Xliater presents his compliments to the Secretary of State KABUL, IGth November, 19S1 for Foreign Affairs and has th honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. Reference to previous con espondence. Kabul despatch No.58, dated 11th May, 1931. Descbiption of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. To The Afghan Prime Minister : H0.127-P, dated 6th November 1921 • Sale of arms to the Afghan Government. Copy sent to :— The Secretary of State for India. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.\ 7583 \ ! Q ^ i , Copy of a personal dated 6th November, 1931, from**His Ifejesty^ Minister, Kabul, to the Afghan Prime Minister. -o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-o- In my letter No*60-P, dated May 11, 1931, I informed the Foreign Minister that His Majesty f s Government had*agreed to the supply of 5,000 rifles with bayonets, etc, at a price of £12^18-0 per unit of one rifle, one bayonet, scabbard and minor accessories, and l^/,000 rounds of ammunition, and to debit the cost of this supply to the credit of £75,000 which is the second instalment of the loan granted to the Afghan Government. This supply has now been made, and I have the honour to inform Your Highness of the details of the account £75,000 r Rs.10,00,000. 5,000 units at £12-18-0 (i . e.Rs . 172 ) aHs. 8,60,000. Balance due ... Ra. 1,40,000. This balance of Rs.1,40,000 is being credited to Your Highness' account with the Peshawar Branch of the Imperial Bank of India.I r* / / ^' c v j I V~ , • C* O l tUo - si linrosi©^ a tc vq-oO tXiwfjdl f ‘isd'sifilM si : •. . ( .^; x ( .leieiiii f astirhA etif ct -y-O“o-o-O-L -O~ o- 0 — o- 0 - 0 - 0 -O—O—O—O- f IoCI 1 11 ^J8 i^sJs ( l-oa.ov nl 8 IF ^ n^.ieno'? orfd- J 5 oiinolni I asXli'i OCO^ to v.r. oj/b exf^ oc[ Di&gt;e'i^ 3 'Luti dasciicneYOO t iiu i-^q l-oj- £!} &gt; •' o i o t Ovl * t a^eno^d’ rfvtLvr t °* *“• .itoiii.’iw.o* to aJbru/oi 000 ,\jX br!« .ssiio^-pooe . ^ 1 ^‘ X0 xXo^ywn P. i *^3 to X300 erfX tif'ei hboI stit to Jnea-rlB^anl J&amp;«oo©8 9 dt si rfeiilw C 00 r 3 Va .^nonmevco s/iX od- betzAir OT/srf I .ortz; ,S-fcBfi!i rrt?9d v/on sjb/ 1 ^Xqqxfs sirf^ 1 aXifitoi) orfo to aas/id'^iF *ijjoY rmutrri oi li/ono/l srlt ~: ^rrx/000.9 oocf to ooo.eva . « 0, -X;, X.2&gt;: ad-inu 000.3 •^ svx.Ri.o.i) o-ex-sxt . 0* G«• • &lt; X . be .. 1 .be -r 0 ^rioc si 0oC,0t^ t X,8fi to oonalacf b id? ^^ ■ ' C • jsX Qr 1 .'! xlGiw tnirooofi T ssortft^iH ti/oY ojX . 3ii)ffl to 5inj8&amp; Xjgi’xaqffil orfif to sx/i) son.ftI.eg1 No. 136 R I 71 KABUL, Qotol)#r \ — His Majesty’s Kinister, Kabia presents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. A 5*^ T Reference to previous correspondence. ••••«» Descbiption of Enclosure. Name and Date. To:- The Foreign Secretary to the Got eminent of India. Memorandum Ko. £25, dated 23rd October 1931. Subject. Damage to arms purehatea by the Afghan Government.His Kajssty’s ?£inist#r t Kabul* @ f I . A the Foreign Secretary to the Governicent of India in the Foreign and lolitical Department, Bern ^elhi* emorandum Ho. EE5. Dated 23rd October 1*31• 'urchaae of a me by ^f^tem Government . Please refer to correspondence on the abore subject ending with my endorsement despatch Ho. 48 # dated 18th april 1931* 2* 1 enclose a list, certified by the Military a ttache of tr*ia ..elution, o'* arms formirv part of the consignment purchased by the Afghan OoTernment which were received in Kabul In a damaged condition* 3* It is understood that moat of this damage was caused when an Afghan Government lorry fell over a precipice in the Kfcyber Fao^* Although the Government of Inula la of course in no way responsible for this accident, it is su^ested that on general grounds it would be desirable to replace the damaged articles free of coet to the ^fghan Government, and to debit the comparatively small sum Involved, apparently about Hs* 725/- to the •Heserve'. If this •uggeetlea is approved by the Government of India, th# method of despatching the58. tf Ij \ \ 'T • i No. —' KABUL, 'J V ' 11th May 1931. J •; ■ • „ . , Minister / ' His Majesty s presents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. “ / Reference to previous correspondence. Kabul despatch No.48, dated 18th April 1931 Descbiption of Enclosube. To Name and Date. The Afghan Foreign Minister, N 0 . 6 Q-P, dated 11th May 1931 Subject. Sale of arms to the Afghan Government. Copy sent to :— The Secretary of State for India. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.Copy of a personal letter ITo*60-p, dated 11th May 1931, from His Majesty^ Minister, Kabul, to the Afghan Foreign Minister. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Your Excellency 1 s personal letter dated April 16, 1931, and to intimate that His Majesty T s Government have agreed to the supply, as requested, of 5,000 rifles, with bayonets, scabbards, and minor accessories, together with 1,000 rounds per rifle (all of the same type and quality as those previously supplied), at a price of £12-18-0 per unit of one rifle, one bayonet, scabbard, and minor accessories, and 1,000 rounds of ammunition; the cost of this supply being debited to the credit of £75,000 mentioned by Your Excellency. In regard to the second proposal made by Your Excellency, I have the honour to state that His Majesty's Government have no objection to making a further supply of munitions up to the same total quantity as that specified above, in such instalments as may be desired by the Afghan Government, against a previous deposit in cash by the Afghan Government of the price of each instalment. The price at which such future supplies could be made cannot, however, be stated precisely at present. As I have informed Your Excellency, the price of £12-18-0 charged per unit of the present supply is a specially favourable one, and I am authorised to state that the price which may be charged in future for supplies of munitions up to the total amount mentioned above would be not less favourable in its relation to the cost price of such articles at the time of their supply.2 The reasons for the inability of His Majesty's Government to accept in full the proposal i for munitions to be supplied on loan have been orally explained to Your Excellency, who will I am sure appreciate them since as the wise have said :- 'A loan is the scissors of friendship”.COPY OF P*£« 3069# Tdlagram XX No.587 dated (and Heed) 27th April 1931. From Minister, Kabul. To Foreign, Simla. Your telegram of the 21st instant, N0.192-K. I suggest Government of India oould obtain quicker a reliable information from Railway authorities regarding date of arrival at Peshawar of consignment from Suwrpe. I should be glad to hear date when ascertained.Telegram XX No*224-K., dated the 2nd May 1931* Prom, Foreign, Simla# To Minister, Kabul* (Repeated Norwef, Peahawar, Ko*1226-S) Pleaeeby telegram urgently date on whioh 5000 \xnits being supplied by Govt, of India should arrive Land! Kotal* earliest date possible as far as Arsenal are concerned is Hay 9th. Approximate total weight of consignment will be 211 tons. Rifles will be packed in bundles weight not exceeding one maund each.Telegram XX No w 223-K, # dated 2nd May 1931. ?rom Foreign, Simla, So Minister, Kabul, (Repeated Norwef and Baluchistan Ko 1225-3)• Your telegram Ho.587 of April 27th. Afghan arm* purchase 3 . Following telegram* from Cuetome Karachi are repeated. First. Ho.454 of April 28th. Medina . 2,000 casee cartridges despatched Peshawar 27th April night, a. Second of April 30th. begins . 143 cases rifles and 2,000 cases cartridges since despatched Cham&amp;n and 429 oases rifles and 4,000 cases cartridges despatched Peshawar 28th April night. Jnds. Further telegram follows..I«M t* *fi« , .&gt;-CSS.o?: xx msissI*': » mX:M% # rx&amp; x e*r o ^ ®©t*? ilsulKi ot • {f-5SSI C i^rC ? - r j&amp;ft« ^OWTC irfwxa^i umvtmtO saiiroXX®! COU^-^ &lt;^BNW .CiicqA lo •&amp;k2L XinqA rtotS'Z 't&amp;wjuit**1 0qB*&amp; ePs&amp;iiitic&amp;o ■,&gt;*&amp; Cdllli 8©CA0 S£X ,xf^ ,$ Ii*iqA lo Jtaoo#t rtj^RAt£L oo^le »&lt;?»*•••.oi*r.t*r.nc *o*ao OCO,S y*. i&gt;orloi^c;e#iv aeRx&gt;o 000«* Abji ©ellit ©oe^o .awoilod . a-bn- ^rf-s.ia XliqA x#8S Vpresents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the undermentioned paper. t /y Reference to previous correspondence. 'Katodon' 79, dated April 17 , 19J1. Descbiption of Enclosure. Name and Date. F*rom; - The iU'ghsm ^ 02 * 0 i&lt;;n Minister, ci ^tucl 11 16, 1 &gt;51. Subject. Sale or ar 2 is to the Government. Copy sent to The Secretary of State for India. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.XraisXation Letter from tac- ^igian j^'orei/.n Mini a ter to His mLi • Heferene© ray oonversation with Your Excellency regarding tho purchase of ar*m8 out of £.75,000, in the course of which Your Excellency finally said that the price of one rifle, together with bayonet, on© thousand cartridges, oil bottle, etc., would be £.12/18/-. My Government is in need of more arras to equip the army, and accordingly agrees to buy five thousand rifles and fifty lakhs cartridges at the aforesaid price, and hopes that tneee arms may be ckllv^rod from Ik la in ..on cays* tine. Further, my Government desires that five thousand rifles and fifty laiths cartridges may be given to us by way of a loan, at the same price, to b© paid in five years and in five instalments, and it is requested that my Government should not be charged interest on this loan. I am anxiously awaiting an early reply in this matter.Minute Paper. Department. ♦5 Please see Mr.Maconachie’s telegram of 17th April on P.Z. 2390/31 below. It will be remembered that the original Afghan demand for material fas^istance~ ” i*-L: ijfnt- 9 .* * 0 ' Tt^tC 7^- £ ^ made to us last July was 20,000 rifles with lOOOrounds of ammunition. In the light of the reccmmendaticns of the Minister and H.M.G. it was decided to grant the Afghans 10,000 rifles with 500 rounds of ammunition each. The Government of India, in recommending action on these lines said 'We contemplate the possibility of repeating the gift after a suitable interval if this proves necessary and if the conduct of ITadir and conditions in Afghanistan justify this. \7e should, however, prefer to have no commitment on this at present”. The Cabinet approved the gift\and also approved ”the Government of India’s proposal that a similar gift should be contemplated later on if circumstances render this desirable”and the Government of India and the Minister were informed that H.M.G. vf t J agreed with them that” it may be psss^Ie at sane later date to make a further gift of arms as proposed in para. 4(b) of your telegram of 22nd July”.but that ”no ccmnitment should be entered into either now or later without my prior sanction”. /«. t Xrp y 2, Thefrifles in question were made over to the (in+rm* I j POL (/*¥ Afghans iv? tinyear. The first instalment of£L00,00G in respect of financial assistance was paid to them last October. It was decided early d+sh* t^e^y^S-4: [/-% .irry-ti r sh OUl d tfils~~year Uiat/t-iai an 1 cy-d £75,000 be paid /to the Afghans^ ?aad £25,000 held as a secret reserve, the existence of which should not be known to the Afghan Government, for meeting occasional * imf1 &amp;r demands for assistance/37 Minute Paper. Department. assistance in kind. 3. On receiving intimation that the amount of the second instalment of financial assistance to he given above was £75,000, the Afghan Government intimated their desire to apply part at any rate of this sum to the purchase from the Government of India of rifles of the same type and quality as had been granted them as a gift last summer. After discussion with the Minister and x zu felt the Government of India a fixed concession price of K Rs.172 per unit (i.e. one rifle, 1000 rounds of ammunition and minor access ories)was made. Fran the present telegram it appears that the Afghan Government are anxious immediately to purchase 5,000 units at the concession price fixed by the Government of India and to secure a corresponding quantity on a basis of deferred payments spread over a period of five years and not carrying interest. 4-. The Minister recanmends acceding to the first Afghan request (i.e. 5,000 rifles, etc. on payment). The reasons he gives in support of this recommendation are, X I submit, convincing. It is desirable frem our point of view, on general grounds, that the Afghans should buy their arms requirements fran British rather than fran foreign sources. The expenditure involved (£64,500 apart from carriage charges) will eat up almost the whole of the second instalment of financial assistance and so will eliminate any possibility of this being used to form a nest egg abroad. We know fran various sources that the liquidation of the situation in the north has been seriously hampered by shortage of men and material, and it is in general to our interest that the Central G overnment/ 47'J3a 5000 10.30Minute Paper. 5V, Department. Va»/ flZ CC+X £Z*y OLAS***- (+-Mu^ jc*- Ck !? Ch~ J 1 Government should re-establish its authority completely at as early a date as possible. The Minister is satisfied that the Afghans have no ulterior motives. Finally, other considerations apart, there can be no question that they have co-operated with us in a very loyal manner in the last six or eight months on the frontier amd that we have no cause of complaint at their attitude. They may, in these circumstances, reasonably expect a certain willingness on our part to gD to meet them. Subject to the concurrence of the Government of &gt;c India and to the required material being available, I submit in these circumstances, that approval should be given to the supply of 5,000 units at the Government of fa/ India’s concession price against/credit of £75,000. t- It is rather inconvenient to be faced with a demand for a supply on this scale at (apparently) ten days’ notice, and even if we accept the Foreign Minister’s explanation that the Afghans are anxious to camouflage these arms as part of the Fleming consignment, it is exceedingly unlikely that they will be able to hoodwink the Soviet by doing so or that the facts ¥. curigd rmfr come out. In any case even allowing for such delay as can be arranged in the transport of the Fleming contingent across India, it may take some little time to get the required number of units together. But we need not go too closely into this. If it pleases the Afghans to think they are really hoodwinking the Russians, that is not our affair. Tfrre-qtre * t i of tho necessity fur bpeuifiu Cabinet H fir, r.ti-aa dealt- with nw. 6- The Afghan request to be granted the same quantity t o/Minute Paper. Department. *■ 'Ll*. [\a+Z+^ cz^. . to be paid for in five annual instalments free of interest is not supported by the Minister and, if only for the reasons given by him in para.4 of his telegram is open to objection. We should probably have considerable difficulty over the period in question in recovering our money fran the Afghan Government and the friction which might result would be un fort unate ,sa*i In any case we have treated the Afghans generously and there is no case for an extraordinary concession of this nature at the moment. At the same time the Minister is, it is suggested, right in his proposal (para.3(b)) that we should sweeten the pill by informing the Afghans that H.M.G. are prepared to supply the quantities in question in such instalments as might be required, subject to prior cash deposit, and, again*, subject to the Government of India’s views, it is suggested that action on these K lines may be approved. Mr.Maconachie will have an additional asset in bargaining with the Afghans in the grant of a concession rate for the transport through India of the rifles which have been purchased by Messrs.Fleming (value about Rs.63,000) to which the Government of India have now agreed,and which he proposes to use in this connection (see Katodon 80 of 'SSnri-April below) Question of necessity of Cabinet sanction for present proposal. y The Cabinet took note on 13th November 1929 that^Aw^J 6k (/+■ V*0 JUl cm t &amp;L. jw (The sale or gift of arms to King Nadir was not in conflict with their previous decisions on the subject of the sale of arms and ammunition to foreign Governments. On 17th December 1929 they agreed that the decision not .to dispose of surplus munitions and arms to foreign Governments/ 47t)3A 5000 10 30Minute Paper Department, &lt;*ruUc^f- Governments should not debar tise. gift by the Government of India to Afghanistan. They subsequently (compare para. / above) decided in July 1930 to approve the Government of India’s proposal for the grant of a similar gift (to that of 10,000 rifles and 500 rounds of ammunition eachTf already approved^if circumstances should render this desirable. For practical purposes the quantity of 10,000 rifles Gmm which the Afghans have now r asked 'Corresponds precisely in amount to the ’’similar gift” approval to the making of which by the Government of India if circumstances rendered this desirable.Was given by the Cabinet last summer, and I submit, on the principle that the greater includes the less, that it is unnecessary to ask for further covering sanction either Ctt: to the proposedr sal.e of 5,000 units to the Afghans -SSW4 A. offer to sell corresponding quantity later. But if this view is approved, the Secretary of State will no doubt wish to circulate an explanatory memorandum to the Cabinet. In a draft will be 4793 a 500(1 10.30 cImjl o-t CL*~+t ^ 4 (fo- Y ^ a* kzy s tf 24 gl^j^ tf- AA~f Z2- (&lt;* .y*,n ' ’ ^ EXPORT OF JAR LXiTiliR IxjLS A i'.D ;/RRSlUP3. A 3 I U S T 55 (30) { 0 24th September 193\» 8 . \AA ClU*A&gt;.-f X X Having regard to the fact that the Cabinet f s policy had failed to prevent or limit purchases of war material by foreign countries, and had tended to stimulate the manufacture of war material in foreign countries, to the detriment, not only of the armament trade, but of the general trade in this country, the Cabinet agreed - (a) To cancel their previous decision 'that the disposal of G-overnnent owned arms and munitions of war to foreign states, whether directly or through private contractors, should not be sanctioned'. (Cabinet 42 (29) Conclusion 7; and Cabinet 27 (24; Conclusion 5;• (b) That in future the three Service Departments should have authority t sanction such sales, unless in any particular case the Secretary of State for foreign 4ffairs deems them undesirable. (c) ^hatif any difficulty of principle snouldjarise m carrying out this decision, the question w should be referred to a Cabinet Committee composed as follows? The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (In the Chair) The Home Secretary, The President of the Board of Trade, and the Minister or Ministers at the head of the Service Department or Departments concerned in the particular case. (d) That the wider question of removing bstacles from the export trade of this country in warships and war materials, raised in the Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty, should be reservedfor consideration at a later meeting of the Cabinet, after the return of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs from Geneva. MM* r~' i . y jrl/pjm/it/jgs/dt (183 groups) DECYPHER 0 P FILE CC1 \ r? ! 2 505 • iosi 2580 TELEGRAM 3 SECRET fo D An n iu (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom Government of India# Foreign and Political Department# to Secretary of State for India« Dated Simla# 21et April, 1931o Received 8 0 45 poffio, 21et April# 1931« xxx 1137~S a Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Minister at Kabul, 192~K* Katodon 79 0 We agree to grant Afghan Government’s first request and have already issued orders to arsenal in anticipation of His Majesty’s Government’s concurrenceo Consignment of 5000 units can be made ready for despatch in five days' timeo Actual despatch can# if necessary# be timed so as to synchronise with arrival at Peshawar of the consignment from (? Europe)* If this is considered necessary# Minister can presumably arrange to have us informed of date of despatch of latter from Karachio After (7 deduction) of cost of arms, balance of second instalment loan will be paid to credit of Prime Minister, Imperial Baht# Peshawar, as suggested in Maconachie’s paragraph Ho«&gt;2o For reasons indicated by Minister, we agree that second request would best be met in manner indicated in paragraph No*3* We are prepared to supply 5,000 units against previous deposit in cash of price of each instalment, but cannot bind ourselves (7 to) arms at future date at price now quoted, which is irreducible minimum at present day rates* We have no objection, however, to Nadir being given assurance that when material up to limit indicated is required, this will be supplied/supplied at rates not less favourable, with reference to cost of manufacture at the time of delivery, than those at which present consignment is being supplied®» A - SECRET 2374 2526 o (35 gromsp) Wfi a 1 8 FRB/MM* DECYPHER 0 Prom Hi a Britannic Majesty’ Minister at Kabul to (COPIES Secretary of State for CIRCULATED) Foreign Affairs, India Office« Dated Katal, 17th April, 1931. Received 8.45 a^nu, 18th April, 1931, ^XX -r Forminka 39 and Government of India’s &gt;* * — telegram April 14th, 1083-S. ^ ^ grateful foi^assen^ to grant of concession, but shall (? only) use (? it if) this appears advisable, e.g*, in order to mitigate results of attitude recommended in Katodon 79 in regard to Afghan request (b), Maconachie 80.FHB/M. (36 groups) (COPIES CIRCULATED) IMMEDIATE. i’lLJi 0c* ■u- /-A ^y. SECRET DECYPHER 0 F 2581, TELEGRAM© From Hia Britannic Majesty^s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office* Dated Kabul, 2lst April, 1931 0 Received 7«30 aodo, 22nd April, 1931© XXX My telegram of 17th instant. Part 1© For 'per 5,000 units' read 'per unit, of 5,000 units*' Error regretted© Para* 2*(b)© Word in question is n quantity(ies) n © Maconachieo NoB* The above repetition was asked for by the TelegraphSECRET FO pm n i l A M .V DET/RRA/DTo (149 groups) YhA L DECYPHBR OF TELEGRAM* J2 0 ^ 3 ( of £U 75^000 ^ at price of £12c 18 bo“ per 5^000 units, same type and quality as supplied October last) (unit equals 1 rifle, 1000 rounds of ammunition, bayonet? scabbard and minor accessories)* And also (b) supply at same price same (V quantities) as above, to be paid for in five annual instalments {? free of) interests. Keeping in view the military and financial considerations, so far as I can appreciate these, and subject to availability, X recommend as regards (a) request should be treated as urgent and granted, balance of money being paid to credit of the Prime Minister (? with) Imperial .Baht, Peshawar® (b) Afghan Government be informed that His Majesty's Government have no objection to future supply of these quantities and that delivery could be made in such instalments as might be required at any time but/ From Hie Britannic Majesty’s Minister IX (COPIES CIRCULATED) at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office* Dated Kabul# 17th April, 1931* Received 11c15 a»mo f 18th April, 1931® XXX FIRST OF THRE JL2.*' Paragraph Ho»l of my telegram dated 12t3j April* ?l c 2» Foreign Minister in personal ('f letter) requestsi. SECRET BTP/DH. (206 groups) D3CYPHER OP TELEGRAM, 2539. (COPIES CIRCULATED) From His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at KaBul to Seoretaiy of State for Foreign Affairs India Office. Dated Kabul, 17th April, 1931. xxx Received 2 p.m., 18th April, 1931. SECOND OF THRSB PARTS , 4* My reasons are* (1) grant of (a) would obviate possibility of nest-eggs (apprehended by Government of India in telegram 2364, July 22nd, of which however there has been in fact no indication) and of sterling remittance by Afghan Government; (2) urgency is explained by Foreign Minister privately as due to desire to import (a) consignment simultaneously with arms purchased in Europe (due in Karachi, April 14th) and, for benefit of Russian Embassy, to represent both consignments as so purchased; (3) as possibility of supplying 20,000 rifles has been envisaged in Secretary of State for India telegram 2502, August 2nd, paragraph No a 4, my recommendations conflict with previous decision only in regard to allowance of ammunition per rifle, but (? please see) same telegram and paragraph,, Afghan Government lays great emphasis on allowance of 1,000 rounds of ammunition, pleading colossal wastage by present troops who have to fight before they are trained. Military Attache considers this argument represents facts inevitable inin existing conditions. Bight ammunition convoys are known to have been sent north since December 5th,, My information goes to show ( ? that no ) such ammunition reserve is being built up as would constitute military danger to India* Old reserve in the Ark blew up during the capture of Kabul by Shah Wall, Kabul ammunition factory is not working and its plant is credibly stated to be worn out. Maconaohie 99 (sic ? 79)SECRET FRB/DR. (104 group a) 2640. DECYPHSR OF TffLBGRAM. From Hia Britannic Majesty’s Minister at From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Office. Dated Kabul* 17th April* 1931« XXX Received 2 p&lt;,in*, 18th April* 1^31* Last of 3 Parts* 4* As regards (b) s inevitable difficulty of recovering finance and exchange position* my telegram 225* December 24th (A 887-S ? July 21st* 1925 0 I should be in favour of stating V* these reasons, if necessary* frankly to the Afghan Governments and tend to make Afghan Government look elsewhere for arms which they seem determined to have. 5, I regret that Afghan ^ilatoriness compels me to aek so frequently for urgent consideration of references from here. arrears (in view especially of the instability of Afghan and Despatch 31* March 12) would (? lead), as I understand (? experience of) His Majesty’s Government with other Oriental (? debtor) states shows, to friction with the Afghan Government, and compare Government of India’s telegram on the other hand, absolute refusal might arouse suspicion Maconachie 79.•i. V D ECYPHER OP TELEGRAM. From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for (COPIES India. CIRCULATED) Dated New Delhi, 14th April, 1931., Received 8.45 p.m,, 14th April, 1931, XXX I MPORTANT « 1083 ~S.c Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Minister at Kabul, I 66 » K. Katodon 71. Afghan request for concession in railway rates on military stores ia^ m should have preferred to refuse if only because m believ# tj-.f-k have never given it to Nepal. As, however. Minister is satisfied that good grounds exist for granting n eesion, we support his proposal and agree that expenditure Involved may be met from reserve of £25,000. Minister will no doubt make it clear to Afghan Government that concession has been granted as epseial case, and is not to be quoted as precedent. We suggest also, in order to cloak real nature of transaction, that Afghan Government be asked to pay ordinary public rates and that difference be credited to them in cash'along with second instalment of loan. Besides bringing, home to Afghans that concession represents sura of appreciable magnitude, (? it, omitted) would obviate account difficulties.4 IWP/DH. SECRET (140 groupa) 2433. H_E C Y P H EJB-- 0 F _ T b L E. .G. B iLM . From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Received Hie Britannic Majesty's Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office, Kabul, 12th April, 1931o 8 p c m e9 12th AprU'l, 1931, XXX Government of India telegram April 4th 6 987 S e I corrsnunicated this reduction to the Foreign Minister who said the Afghan Government had counted on price (? not ) speeding £ 12 . 1 said Rs, 172 could be (? taken) as firm figure, and have heard nothing more* 2. Telegram 992, March 19th, from Secretary of Stats for India* Arms purchased by the Afghan Government, Foreign Minister asks as special concession, in view of their financial (? omission), that railway freight in India may be charged on this consignment at military and not public rate* Cash value of such concession by the (? Government of India) would be approximately Rs. 62,000* 3, Unless decision in Government of India memorandum 147 p May 29th, 1924, (chpy forwarded to Secretary of State for India with Foreign Secretary's letter Mo, 41May 28th, 1925) is to be regarded as final (? in all) circumstances, X recommend grant of this concession for reaeon(s) stated by Foreign Minister as special case, not to form precedent, end debi^/of cost to £25,000 reserve. As consignment is expected to arrive at Karachi ApriX 14th, decision on paragraph No* 3 is requested ;ently j —Notes. Minute Paper. S~7\ Register No. p.z- DCCJ 31 SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Hec. 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... /*' U. H ORATT OF ASSISTANCE TO AFGHAN I ST AIT. • Question of purchase of Arms in India at concession rates. Copv of to FOR INFORMATION. I Lu--, A ^ slm Previous Papers .*—• SEEN F’OLITICAL. committee. - 6MAY 1931 The G. of I. are able to reduce the price from Rs. 185 to Rs. 172 (for rifle, bayonet and accessories and a thousand rounds). This still leaves a big gap between the G. of I.»s minimum price and the suggestion of £10 made by the Afghan Government. Presumably if any further reduction were offered the cost to the G. of I. would have to be debited against the sum of £25,000 which they have reserved against small material gifts out of the total of £200,000 sanctioned for financial assistance to Afghanistan. There would sppetr to be a considerable disadvantage in utilising the reserve in this way, as a une reserve in rnis wa^ ( A /uau n^Auti^yx h* ^ &amp;*« a^v4'cA Sod gift made in this manner might pass almost 44-75b 1000 5.30 unnoticed/...unnoticed; if any part of the reserve were to he utilised oh rifles it would he preferable to arrange for the Afghan Government to purchase as many as they can afford at the price of Rs. 172 and receive a certain.additional number free of charge. This suggestion has not been made either by the G. of I. or by Mr. Maconachie and we need not make it from here. The arms -in question are short post-war conversion rifles with Mark VII ammunition and are in every respect the some as those used by our forc-ei in India and are guaranteed absolutely serviceable. It will be noted that there is a very large difference between the price of Rs.172 per unit and the price at which the Afghan Government are obtaining old rifles from War Office stocks through Messrs. Flemings; the latter ^ applicant* for an export licence g4Lve ,£42,000 . es the declared value f.o.b. of 3,000 *303 magazine rifles, Enfield pattern *14 and 8 million rounds of Mark VII ammunition; the War Office were unable to give any guarantee in respect of either rifles or ammunition but they expressed the opinion that there is no danger of’the rifles proving unserviceable and the Afghan legation w f ere informed accordingly. t ^ y* C \ Iatmj&amp;'Cvw SEEN Political committe*. - 6 MAY 193123 ro SECRET j 2266« RRVM. (66 groups*) D E C Y P H E R OF T B L E a R A M,_ From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India* Dated New Delhi, 4th April, 1931. Received 9 a.m*, 4th April, 1931. IMPORTANT * -f 987-S. Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Kabul 130-K. , ^ -f * Katodons ^ 49) and 60. Delay, which is much regretted has been due to necessity of scrutinising charges in detail• This has now been done and we find that we are able, by reducing (? all) charges to absolute minimum, to supply rifle complete with bayonet and accessories and 1000 rounds of ammunition for Rs.172 in even Rs. Both arms and ammunition would be of same type and quality as those delivered to Afghan Government in September last* XXX . uj\/ &gt; ?4U-'&gt; c’.' v &gt; . I■# &amp; EBA/AW. (COPISS RLE COPY 19S5 v I3?l (26 groups) DECYPHBR 0? TELSGRA^ * u Prom His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office, OIHCULATED) SECRET XXX Dated Kabul through Peshawar, 2nd April, 1931* Received 3rd April, 1931, 7« 50 a,m« May I expect a reply shortly to jry telegram of the 18th ultimo, 49, regarding sale price of arms? If reduction to extent cannot be granted, perhaps something less would be possible* Maconachie 60X te Paper. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Rec. 19 To Secretary of State... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... Date. Initials. * m * m SUBJECT. i- - r. . y - jt J J'09-c . Copy of /*2 hi * Fo FOR INFORMATION C- C. (lITAffiT/DH. (148 groups) D JL C Y PHER OP TBLEGRAM. SECRET ro PM! f\ h h p- faA \*s 1907. (£' 3. 3 Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Received His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Kabul, 18th March, 1931, 7,45 a.m., 19th March, 1931, — i.1* 79f Your telegram of 21st ultimo, 13. I informed King on March 5th of allotment of £75,000 as second instalment. Afghan Government have intimidated (siO' intimated) informally that they wish to purchase. \ .LvjiT t * •’ l$&gt; - with at any rate portion of this, rifles and ammunition of same type and Quality as those delivered last September, and have enquired price. I have informed them that price of rifle with bayonet and accessories as before and 1,000 rounds of ammunition would be approximately Rs, 183 (this includes departmental and I understand Indian customs charges). Afghan Government asks before proceeding further whether this - figure could be reduced to £10 and if so, indicates * , wish to make further purchases in future at this (?rat©)* I propose to defer detailed reeommendatione until , definite request is received but on general grounds 4 55“7 7 (yim telegrams 1359, dated let September, 1924,from Government of India and 1882, 10th July, 1925, from the Secretary of State for India) it seems desirable thatMs&amp;gRftcMe. 4 , a . 2 s, thati such reduction (?should be) granted If poeslble without prejudice to decision regarding quantities to be supplied on receipt of formal request.IT/MMo (49 groups,) DECYPHER QF TELE From Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary (COPIES of State for India, repeating telegram CIRCULATED) from Minister at Kabuli Dated New Delhi, 4th March, 1951. Received 2.30 p.m,, 4th March, 1931. 654-S. XXX Fi rst of 2 parts* Please telegraph prices at which following (if such request were made and grant of it approved) would be sold to Afghan Government i (? rifles) ii ammunition iii bayonets with scabbard, all to be of exact same type and (? character) as those recently presented by Government of India,SECRET FHB/MM. (61 groups«) 1515 D E G Y P HE R OF T E L E Gr R A M, &amp; From (COPIES CIRCULiiTED) Government of India. Foreign end Political^Department, to Secretary of State for India, repeating telegram to His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at Kabul. Dated Delhi, 4th March, 1951. Received 5.30 p.m., 4th March, 1931. XXX 654-S. Second and Last Part. 1'our telegram of 28th ultimo, No.498. Prices are as follows:- (1) Rifles, complete with pull-through and oil bottle, Rs.72 annas 5 each. (2) Ammunition, Rs.75 per thousand rounds. (3) Bayonets and scabbards, Rs.12 each. Departmental charges, etc., would come to between 10 and 15 per cent in addition.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002c6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2171</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002c6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2171</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/2 'Afghanistan: purchase of arms by Afghan Government from financial assistance granted by Government of India'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:51:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (65 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 66; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence regarding the provision of a £75,000 grant of assistance by the Government of India to the Afghan Government, and arrangements for the supply of arms and ammunition. The correspondents are: the Government of India's Foreign and Political Department; HM Envoy and Minister at Kabul (Richard Maconachie); the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; and the Afghan Minister for Foreign Affairs.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Weapons</topic></subject><subject><topic>Financial aid</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002c6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>