<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:14:32.933Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">iTILS NO. 7/3 - JUDICIAL. WO HONG OF % KUWAIT OKDEH IN COUNCIL, 1949 j Opened: May, 1949. * Previous corr: Old file No. 32/11(ii)13/8. 13/9. The Political Agency, Kuwait. No. 0/89(13/9) 16th April, 1949, Dear Sir Rupert, s' Please refer to my Savingram No. 0/71(13/9) of the 5th April, 1949. 2 . -*■ question that arises out of Dr. Akopiantz’s case is that of the extent of our responsibility for the protection of American interests in Kuwait. ^ JQsk •/ ( . 3. IVe appear to have acquiesced tsg the American Consul at Basra looking after certain aspects of American interests: he comes here to deal with their passports, and he is to be invited t&gt;o observe proceedings in Criminal cases in which Americans are involved - Residency letter Nor^i2/8/49 of the 11th March, 1949. This does not extend, however, to his having any dealings with the Sheikh except through the Political Agent; and we do not^appear to have admitted that he is solely responsible for protecting United States interests. ’/ere we to do so and to refuse to accept responsibility ourselves we should later find it very difficult to maintain our resistance to the establishment of an American Consulate here. 4. In Dr. AKopiantz f s case the American Consul refused to interfere on his behalf; and Dr. Akopiahtz repeatedly asited for our protection of his interests. 5. If American citizens have a good prima facie case (which I gather Colonel Galloway did not thin* Dr. Akopiantz had) I think we should do as much as we can to help them; but I s.iould be grateful for your instructions. Yours sincerely, sd. g.n. Jackson. H.E. Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, Bali rain.K. $ RESTHICTED . (149/29/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDEN BAHRAIN. 23rd April 1949. e^r Ci (D Please refer to your S.O. letter C/89-(13/9) of the 16th April about our responsibility for the protection of American interests in Kuwait. I fully concur in the lines expressed in para 5 c.f. my letter (214/2/49) of the 9 th April. ^ a fo. v/r G.N. Jackson, Esq., M.B.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. CONFlDhNTlA'?/^ 3 /^ The Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain, 12/25/49 30th April, 1949 Please refer to your letter No, C/ 93(32/11) of the 23rd April, to the engagement of counsel by Americans from Basra, nor do I think we can ordinarily object to any accused person of any nationality engag ing counsel if he so desires. As you know, a qualified Judicial Assistant is shortly to be appointed to this Residency and when he arrives one of the questions he will have to look into is that of applying the Legal Practitioners* Act or possibly of framing rules on the question. 3. McLintic told me that he was thinking of recommending that the company should employ two Indian pleaders, one as a police prosecuting inspector and the other for defence purposes. I doubt if there will be enough work for them to do unless their services are made available to all and sundry, an idea which I do not like very much at first sight. If the proposal shows signs of maturing I should be grateful for your views on letter, I agree that it is undesirable that an American consular officer should take upon himself the defence of an accused person though there is of course no objection to his giving him legal advice. 2 I do not think we can possibly object it 4 With reference to para 4 of your G.N. Jackson, Esq., M.B.E Political Agent, Kuwait.7/i- CONFIDENTIAL. 12/24/49 The Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain. 30th April, 1949 s' Please refer to your letter No.C/98 (32/11) of the 25th April. * the 25th April. . ^c\ My letter (12/14/49) of the 25th March 2 contained ray personal views and should not be treated as a judicial circular, and you have full discretion where cases can only be compound ed with the leave of the Court to allow such composition or not. 3. In suggesting composition wherever possible, both the Foreign Office and myself were thinking mainly of the immense amount of trouble and in some cases expense caused to Government by the lack of prison accommodation suitable for Europeans in the Gulf States and the necessity of sending prisoners to the United Kingdom to serve their sentences. These consider ations are entirely practical and not judicial and it is er^tire-ly for the Political agent to decide what weight should be given to them in any particular case. para 10 of your letter, as I am informing you in reply to a separate reference, there is only accommodation for one European prisoner at Bahrain and that may not always be available. 4 With regard to the opening clause of G.N. Jackson, Esq Political Agent, Kuwait.No. C/U6(7/2) The xtolitical Agency, Cuwalt, May 18, 1949. 3a[fl «!&gt; K' I enclose a letter I received from the Kuwait Oil Company which will give you an idea of the State’s reaction to the Kuwait Oil Company’s attempt to settle out of court a case in which a Kuwait subject was billed. hp &gt;/!&gt;-) 2. I also enclose a copy of a letter I wrote to the Kuwait Oil Company from which you will see how the case was settled. I have also spoken to SheiKh Abdulla &amp;ubara£ about the case. X i, Yours ever, ( Ifcyi. H.E. Sir Bupert Hay, KCI2., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. asr■ ^ ✓ The Political Agency, Kuwait. No. 0/118(7/2) My dear Sir Aipert, 19th May, 1949. Please refer to the fourth sentence in paragraph 5 of your letter No. 122/26/49 of the 2nd May to Burrows. 2 # j find your reliant that*the Kuwait Police can only deal with persons subject to the SheiKh’s jurisdiction* difficult to reconcile with / 1). ,\ ' ^ ill 1 ° ' para 2 of Dredge’s Confidential letter No. 358-S of the 10 th February, 1948 , which ran as follows: ’I am desired to say that it is considered that any ;Jtate by virtue of its inherent powers and its obligation to maintain law and order can arrest through its police or other force any persons who commit crimes whether they are forei?$ners or not. here foreigners are arrested over v/hom jurisdiction has been ceded they should of course be produced at once before the authority who is competent to deal with them.’ 3 . I agree that Jabir al Ahmed was wrong in fining a Pakistani, because we have jurisdiction over Pakistanis; but it appears to me by no means so certain that he was acting outside his rights in arresting the Pakistani. 4 # The Special Police were empowered by us to deal with persons subject to pur jurisdiction within the Kuwait Oil Company’s premises at a time when there were none of the Sta^e Police inside the Company’s limits. I agree that from our point of view it is desirable that the Special Police should continue to perform this function/ H.£. Sir Hupert Hay, KCIS., C3I., Political Hesident, Persian Gulf Kesidenoy, Bahrainthis function, unless the Sheixth is prepared to employ trained British personnel to do it. So far, the State Police stationed inside the Company’s limits are cooperating with the Special Police whenever arrests of persons subject to our jurisdiction have to be made. Long may this continue, and I shall use my influence to try to ensure that, through goodwill, it does continue; but, the State Police having been admitted to the Company’s premises, I do not thin* we will be on very firm ground if we try to insist as of right that they make no arrests of persons subject to our jurisdiction. In any case there are a number of persons subject to the Order in Council who are nothing to do with the Company and who may have to be arrested outside the Company’s limits and therefore outside the jurisdiction of the existing special Police Officers. For such womt as this the Political Agent here, as in Bahrain, has to rely on the State Police. with the State Police Installed on the Company’s premises we can hardly deny them the right to arrest persons subject to our jurisdiction within those premises and at the same time expect them to do this for us outside uhe Company’s premises. 5* In Bahrain we relied on the State Police for years, long before Special Police were appointed and before the Sheirch employed British Sergeants. Both of these date only from the middle years of the war. Yours everICuvmit. No. (7/2) 31st May, 1949. Dear Hesidency, In acoordance with Article 89 of the Kuwait Order in Council of 1935 we are sending this report on the wording of the Order for the year 1948. CIVIL GASES . No civil case was tried during the year. CHlfclNAL CASES . 19 criminal cases were tried during the year. -fhe accused in 11 of these were convicted and fines amounting to i&lt;s. L150/- were recovered. Only one of the convicted persons appealed to the Political Resident and he was acquitted. Pive persons were bound down under Chapter VIII of the Criminal Procedure Code. 1AIXZD CA3H3. No oases were entertained under Phrt V of the Order in Council, and it appears from Agency letter No. 126 of the End August, 1948, that Pfcrt V of the Order in Council was not being administered. ^'he administration of justice under the Order in Council was rendered difficult by lacic of proper prison accommodation. HEGICTNATION . By December 1948 the number of British Subjects had risen from the 1651 registered in 1947 to over 5500. Of these 3491 were registered in the Agency, fhe fees prescribed by Article 63 of the Order in Council were not collected after April, 1948. Yours ever, AGENCY. I'-r/ . The Persian Gulf Residency, BAHRAIN.The Persian Gulf Residency Bahrain. 122/31/49 3tth May, 1949 Please refer to your letter No. C/ 118(7/2)'^of the 19th May. was loosely worded. What I was chiefly at pains to point out was that the presence of State Police at Ahm^di did not mean that the company f s Special Police officers would no longer be required. I agree that the position is as stated in Dredge f s letter^ No.358-S of the 10th February, 1948, to which you refer and that there is no objection to the State / Police arresting foreigners, ard^ in fact^ it is their duty to do so if circum stances demand provided they are produced at once before an^authority who is competent to deal with them, and I am grateful to you for bringing the point to my notice. In the Kuwait Oil Company T s camps the company’s Special Police might perhaps as a matter of convenience be regarded as the competent authority in cases where the persons arrested are the Company’s employees but this is a matter I leave to your discretion. S 9 I am very glad to learnparagraph 4 of your letter that the State Police and the Special Police are co-operating satisfactorily. 4 . I am sending a copy of this letter and of your letter under reply to Burrows. 2 I am afraid my letter to Burrows [ G.N« Jackson, Esn., M.B.E., The Political Agent, Kuwait. 7ESTABLISHED 1841 E. B. Badger &amp; Sons Company The Political Agency Kuwait Attention: W* N* Jackson, Political Agent SUBJECT: Search Warrant Dear Sir: Please advise to whom an application should be made by an American Court in order to produce in that Court the original, or a photostatic copy of the original, of a cable allegedly sent through the Kuwait Office of Cable and Wireless, Ltd# bv a former employee of E. B. Badger &amp; Sons Co. on February 11, 1949* Would this application involve contact with any British or local tribunals in Kuwait? PLEASE ADDRESS ALL COMMUNICATIONS TO THE COMPANY Field Office Mena el Ahmadi, Kuwait May 17, 19^9 Very truly yours E* B. Badger &amp; Sons Co. DBE:mt Supt. Of Construction cc: F. L* Doherty, Boston office Boston Construction office London office FileNo. V//S3 (7/2) The Political Agency, Kuwait. June, 1949. Dear Sir 3upert, I enclose a copy of a letter I have received from Evans of E.B. Badger and Sons Company* 2* I was approached more than two months ago by Colonel Underwood, the Chief Security Officer of the Kuwait Oil Company at that time, asking me to get him a copy of the telegram, which was thought to have been sent by some employees in connection with a strike. I refused to issue a search warrant because no case had been filed in my Court and because Col. Underwood could not show me that the copy of the telegram was required in connection with any proceedings under the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure (Act V of 1898). 3. In my view It would not be legal, even if we have an extredition agreement or treaty with the United States Covernnent, for the Political Agent to require production of a telegram under Section 95 of the Code of Criminal Procedure for use by an American Court, because the copy of the telegram is not 'wanted for the purpose of any investigation, inquiry, trial or other proceeding under this Code', i.e. the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure. It is for consideration whether Evans should be told this or not. I incline to the view that he should be. 4. If you approve therefore, I propose to reply to Evans as in the attached draft/ Unless you wish to make any alterations that cannot conven iently be telegraphed, could you very kindly telegraph your approval? H.E* Sir Pupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Hesident, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.■MBt. (0 bj /X No. M/ (7/2) The Political Agency, Suwait• June, 1949. Sir, I have to refer to your letter of the 17th May, 1949, and to say that application would have to be made by an American Court through the American State Department to the Court of His Britannic Majesty T s Political Agent at Kuwait. 2. •‘‘he Kuwait tribunals have no jurisdiction over Cable and Wireless Limited. 3. I would add that, in my view, as the law as applied by the Kuwait Order in Council of 1949 stands, it would not be legal for the Political Agent to require the production of a copy of the cable for use by an American Court. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, D.B. Evans, #sq., E.B. Badger &amp; Sons Company, Field Office, Mina el Aiimadi, Kuwait.E. B. BADGER a SONS COMPANY Field Office Mena el Ahmdi, Kuwait June 15, 19^9 The Political Agency Kuwait Attention: W, N. Jackson, Political Agent SUBJECT: Search Warrant Referring to our letter of May 17 th on the above subject, we respectfully request a reply at your earliest convenience• Very truly yours E. B. Badger 5c Sons Co. D.' B. 'Evans Supt. Of Construction DBE:mt cc: FileThe Political i^ency, Kuwait. c une, 1949. $.10 Please refer to the^Correspondence restirif, ./ith your letter No.l22/3G/49 of tne 3Gth May, 1949. 2. Sonetime a^jo I had occasion to take up with the Kuwait Grovernnent the case of an Indian v/ho had been arrested .by the Kuwait Police and was not produced in ray Court, as a result the bhaikh sent abdullah Mulla to roe to discuss the exercise of jurisdiction over Indiana and Pakistanis in the town. He 'was roost friendlv and expresseo the Shaikh’s desire to cooperate with us to the fullest extent possible, and to fall in line vdth our wishes on the subject. He particularly wanted to know what should be done with Indians and Pakistanis found drunk and disorderly in the brothel area at nijit or fighting in the town. 3. He went on to explain that, outside the formal Civil and Criminal Tribunals in Kuwait, simple cases were settled by bhaikh bubah as balim, Chief of Police, in a suimary way. He continued that until Calloway came here it had been the practice for cases in which Pakistanis and Indians ./ere involved to be settled by one or other of the Shaikhs without reference, in tho first instance, to the Political il^ent. Abdullah Mulla explained that the disposal of cases was expedited in this way. 4. I replied that jurisdiction over certain persons had been ceded lo us, and that when these persons only were involved we could not share it or allow the Kuwait Tribunals or the Shaikhs first to hear the case and ourselves only take it up if the parties were not satisfied. I continued that I alv/ays endeavoured to settle immediately cases that v/ere reported to me and that, when the new Assistant Political i^ent arrived, we should always be able to do so ’without any delay at all. I added that I vzould also deal with mixed cases strictly in accordance with Part VI of the Hew Kuwait Order in Council. b 7 Abe ullah Mulla then went on to say that they also wanted to comply vdth our practice in respect of the arrest of accused persons, subject to our/.... H.b. Sir '(upert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.b.I., Political Hosident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.to our jurisdiction, and wished the powers of police officers in this respect to be explained to them so that they could as far as possible comply with our procedure, I have let him have a short explanation| of the powers and duties of police officers as laidj down in Chapter V of the Criminal Procedure Code, 6. Since I saw Abdullah Mulla, two cases in which Pakistanis were involved have occurred in the town. The Kuwait Police arrested them, and produced them in the .agency Court within an nour of arrest.No. ( 1 / 1 ) ^La\ /M)-UmA4a. j Ploase refer to our conversation about the exercise of jurisdiction over Indians and / i 1 I / P^ikistanis. 2. Court jurisdiction over forei^iers */}io are not subjects 01 Muslim States has been ceded by His Hijmess and his predecessors to His Majesty’s Government, The procedure for settling cases in which onlv persons subject to our jurisdiction are involved is laid down in Parts IV h V of the Kuwait Order in Council of 1949; arid the procedure for settling cases in which both persons subject to our jurisdictioi and to that of His Hl^mess are involved is laid down in Part VI. I recently sent you copies of this Order in Council. 3. There remains the question of the rights and duties of the police in respect of persons suoject to our jurisdiction. To work m the Kuwait Oil'Company*s premises Col. Galloway appointed 6 persons - all Hritieh or Americans - as Special Police Officers to deal with persona in the Kuwait Oil Company’s premises who are subject to our jurisdiction. I am informed by the Kuwait Oil Company that the Kuwait Police since posted there under Jhaikh Jabir al Ahra d as Subah are cooperating with them most cordially; and I know I can expect this sincere cooperation to continue. Outside the Kuwait Oil Company’s premises, I rely for the performance of Police duties in respect of persons subject to our jurisdiction entirely on the Kuwait Policej and I understood you to say that you would appreciate a short sumnary of the duties and powers of police officers in respect of the arrest of persons subject to our jurisdiction because it was His Hi^iness* wish that the Kuwait Police should comply» as far as practicable, with our procedure when they have occasion to arrest persons subject to our jurisdiction. 4. In our lav/ the powers and duties of the police to make arrests are laid down in Chapter V of tiie Criminal Procedure Code. For all practical purposes they can be summarized as follows: Any policeman may arrest a person if issued with a warrant by a Magistrate to do so. Any policeman, without a warrant and without an order from a Magistrate, nay arrest any person who has been concerned in/ Abdullah LIulla oaleh, hsq., K u w a i t. • * Iff 15 l * M.b.h2 / -■■■■» v*. 1 in a cognizable offence, or against whom reasonaole complaint has boen made or suspicion exists of his having been so concerned, and any person who obstructs a police officer m the execution of his duty. He may arrest also any person having in his possession, without lawful excuse, any implement for house-breaking, or any stolen property. / A x More responsible x^olice officers may arrest any person v7ho is found trying to cpnceal Ids presence with a view to committing a serious offence, or who lias no ostensible means of subsistence, or who 9 annot give a satisfactory account of himself, or who is by repute an ha ri tual robber, or who has committed an offence or, being accusec of having committed an offence, refuses to give his name and address to the police officer or gives a false name and address. Cognizable offences referred to above are carefully defined in our law; but for the purposes of the Kuwait Police they can be regarded as the more serious offences prejudicial to public tranquility and good order. Persons arrested should not be subject to more restraint than is necessary to prevent their escape. Ho police officer should keep an arrested person in custody for more than 24 hours without producing him before the Political iigent. £)• I hope this will be of assxstance to you and I shall be glad to discuss it further if you wish.The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 85/49/49 gth June, 1949• Please refer to your S.O. No.C/102 (32/11) of the 26th April. letter I have examined the position about Section 3C powers and so far as I can make out, only the Political Agent, Bahrain, has such powers. A King's Regulation was issued in 1930 rendering Section 30 of the Indian Code of Criminal Procedure applicable to Bahrain, but I have been unable to find any Regulations applying it to other Agencies. G.N. Jackson, Esq., The Political Agent, Kuwait.The Political Agency, Kuwait, No. C///^ (7/2) jj/£ June, 1949. Please refer to your 8.0. letter No. 85/49/49 dated 8th June, 1949. 2. I think it would be useful if a King’s Regulation could be issued rendering Section 30 of the Criminal Procedure Code applicable to Kuwait also-a^d I should be grateful if this could be done. Perhaps the Bahrain regulation conld be taken as a model. H.E. Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.The Political Agency, Kuwait. No. M/ (7/2) &amp; June, 1949. Sir, I have to refer to your letter of the 17th May, 1949, and to say that application would have to be made by an American Court through the American State Department to the Court of His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent at Kuwait. 2. The Kuwait tribunals have no jurisdiction over Cable and Vireless Limited. 3 . I would add that, in my view, as the law as applied by the Kuwait Order in Council of 1949 stands, it weo’ld net be legal for the Political Agent to require the production of a copy of the cable for use by an An.ericen Court. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, i. Evans, Esq., B. Badger &amp; Sons Company Field Office, Mina el Ahmedi, Kuwait.&gt;4/11/49) 11/ PERSIAN GULP RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 7th July, 1949. CONFIDKSTIAL T&gt; CAA. 4 The Foreign Office have ruled that a Political Agent is a Judge of his Court from the date of his appointment as Political Agent and that no separate order of appointment by the Secretary of State is required. Other judges of the Political Agent*s Court can only function from the date on which the Secretary of State signs the document of appointment and it is not possible for appointments to be back-dated. In these circumstances, I am to ask you to give this Residency as much notice as possible, if necessary by telegram, of the date from which you want any officer appointed as a Judge of your Court. i' —^ . Q G.N. Jackson, ksq. , , Political Agent, Kuwait. r. /s ; f /I ^14/5; 7/2 Telegram Jode {i’roni Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Kuwait To Tel. No. 137 Dated and received 7th July, 1949 REST HI CT 2D Wilton cannot function as a judge in your court until Secretary of State has signed document of appointment and document cannot be bacs dated. If you wish, Wilton so appointed, telegraph Foreign Office repeating me. As far as can be foreseen, he is lively to remain in Kuwait until middle August. HAYmmmmm The Political ii^ency, Kuwait. No. G//^ 7 / (7/2) A' July, 1949. Dear Sir Dupert, $ 2’ Please referto your telegram No. 187 of the 7th July. 2. I have not asked for Wilton to be appointed as a Judge in iny Court because he is not yet qualified by training or experience to try cases. - 4 3. wliile he is here, I intend to show him his way round the Codes, to give him past cases to read, and to have him sitting in Court when I try cases. He should be ready to start trying cases ordinarily tried by Third Class Magistrates by the time hh gets to Bahrain. Yours ever, H.E. Sir Rupert Hay. KCIE.,,CSI., Political Resident ? Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.1 ( 1 ' 3» ,1'^fihSIAN GULi RKSIDEWCY, (85/58/49) BAHRAIN. 16th July, 1949. ZDej^v. -J cktle^r-^, 5. /I In your letter No.0/174(7/2) of the 29th June, you have recommended that a King^ Regulation should be issued making Section 30 of the Criminal Procedure Code applicable to Kuwait. I am wrangling with Beckett on the subject and will let you know the result in due course. . foCiU.J. G.N. Jackson, Esq., M.B.E. , Political Agent, KUWAIT.INTRODUCTION TO CRIMINAL LAW AS APPLIED TO KUWAIT We derive our extra territorial jurisdiction in Kuwait from the Kuwait Order in Council of 1949. Our jurisdiction extends to British subjects and foreigners as defined in Article 4 of the Order. The Sheikh has jurisdiction over his own subjects, that is Kuwaitis prorer, and over Kuwait subjects as defined in Article 4. Kuwait subjects include nationals of other Muslim States when they are in Kuwait. V/e too have jurisdiction over certain Kuwait subjects in the circumstances provided for in Article 8 ( 1 )(a)iii), although in practice there are no Kuwait subjects registered in the Agency for the purposes of this Article. 2. The Order in Council provides for the appli cation of certain British and Indian Acts to persons subject to the Order in Council, i.e. to British sub jects and to foreigners. The Acts aoplied are men tioned in Part II of the Order, and in the Schedule at the end of it. The Order in Council also provides subject to the Order in Council and Kuwait subjects are involved (Part VI). When complaints are received from Kuwait subjects against persons subject to the Order, the cases ere settled in the Political Agent's Court. When the reverse is the case, the cases are entertained in the Political Agent's Court and trans ferred to the Kuwait Tribunals for settlement. The reasonable customs existing in Kuwait (Article 89). This Article was almost certainly inserted as a ******* for the settlement of cases in which both persons Political Agent is required to recognize and apply result/result of the negotiations leading up to the cession by the Sheikh of Jurisdiction to us; and for this reason the Political Agent is under a certain obliga tion to make concessions to local sentiment when there is conflict of legal systems in mixed cases. 3. The Political Agent has both criminal and civil Jurisdiction. For the present I do not propose to discuss civil law because, in practice, we have only about one civil case to every twenty criminal cases. 4. Of the criminal law the most important Acts applied to Kuwait are the Indian Penal Code, the Criminal Procedure Code, and the Evidence Act;and this introduction is confined to a discussion of these Codes. The Indian Penal Code contains the sub stantive criminal law and consists of defined offen ces with the maximum punishment that can be awarded for each. The Criminal nrocedure Code contains the procedure to be followed in the investigation and trial of cases, for the prevention of offences, etc. 5. Cases are to be tried in four different ways according to the seriousness of the crime. There are sessions cases ordinarily triable by a Jury unless a Magistrate is acting under special powers conferred upon him by Section 30 of the Criminal Procedure Code; warrant-cases; summons- cases; and cases tried summarily. The Political Agent is, according to Part III of the Order in Council, a District Magistrate and Sessions Judge. As such he can try sessions cases, but Courts of Sessions have no original Jurisdiction (Section 193, Criminal Procedure Code). Before the Political Agent/....Agent can proceed as a Sessions Judge it is necessary for the case to be committed to him after an enquiry conducted in accordance uith Chapter XVIII of the Criminal Procedure Code. A Sessions Judge cannot himself conduct an enquiry and then judge the case in Sessions; and in this Agency an enquiry would have to be done by the Assistant Political Agent. You should therefore make yourself familiar with Chapter XVIII. 6. Warrant-cases are defined in Section 4(w) of the Criminal Procedure Code. Offences punishable with terms of imprisonment exceeding six months are tried as warrant-cases. The procedure is laid dov/n in Chapter XXI. 7. Summons-cases are cases for v/hich the punish ment is less than six months* imprisonment. Whether or not a particular offence should be tried as a warrant-case or a summons-case therefore depends on the maximum punishment that can be awarded. This can be discovered from the Indian Penal Code and also by studying column 7 of the Schedule II of the Criminal Procedure Code. In fact the procedure to be followed in all cases is indicated in this Schedule. Incidenta lly column 4 of the Schedule does not show whether the case is a warrant-xx or summons case. . It only indicates how the attendance of the parties is to be secured. 8. Certain warrant-cases and summons-cases can be tried summarily (Sections 260 and 262, Criminal Procedure Code). The only difference is that the record of cases tried summarily need not be written out so fully so that cases can be settled more expedi tiously. Ordinarily only unimportant cases are tried summarily/... _summerily. The amount of imorisonment thet may be awarded in summary trials is limited to three months (Section 262), and there is no appeal unless the amount of fine exceeds Rs.200 (Section 414), 9. The ways in which evidence should be recorded in all but summary trials and the form in which judg ments should be written are laid down in Chapters XXV and XXVI. Christians give evidence on oath, Hindus and Muslims on solemn affirmation. The procedure for examining the accused is explained in Sections 342 and 364. What offences may be compounded are detailed in Section 346. The framing of charges is explained in Chapter XIX, although in practice commentators usually give specimen charges in their notes &amp;n each offence (see Law of Crimes, Ratanlal and Dhirajlal). When more than one accused may be tried jointly is explained in Section 239. The accused may also be tried in one trial for a number of crimes (Section 236). 10. You will see from column 3 of Schedule II of the Criminal Procedure Code, that in certain cases the police may arrest offenders without a warrant, while in others they may not. Cases in which they may arrest without warrants are known as cognizable cases (Section 4(n), Criminal Procedure Code). Cognizable cases are ordinarily those of a serious nature in which it is necessary for the Crown, represented by the police, to act immediately in the interests of the safety and convenience of the public. There are other offences which are also criminal but which affect only the nrivate rights of certain individuals or are not so serious as to require the immediate intervention of the police in the interests of the public. These are non,* cognizable/...- - non-cognizable offences, and the police cannot investi gate them without an order from a Magistrate. When the police receive a complaint of this nature they refer the comnlainant to a Magistrate who may either entertain the case (Section 204), or, if he is not satisfied that it is genuine, proceed under Chapter XVI of the Criminal Procedure Code. In certain circumstances compensation can be paid to injured parties out of fines recovered (Section 545). 11. You should also read Chanters IV, V, VI, VIII, XIX, XXXIII, and XLIVA of the Criminal Procedure Code. Sections 528^ and ^ of Chapter XLIVA are important xna when European British subjects, Euroneans, and Americans are accused. They can claim special privileges: the sentences that can be awarded to them are limited - Sections 29-^, 32^*, and 34 A Criminal Procedure Code and in cases tried by jury or with the help of assessors they have certain rights in respect of the composition of the jury (Section 275) and the choice of assessors (Section 284^). 12. Of the Evidence Act you should be familiar with at least Chanters II, VII, IX and X. 13. In Kuwait ordinarily we denend for our police work on the State Police Force; but to overcome the obvious difficulties arising out of the increase in the Euronean and American population we have appointed 6 Snecial Police Officers under a King*s Regulation issued for this purnose under Article 85 of the Kuwait Order in Council. We are trying to get the Sheikh to bring a part of his Police Force up to a standard of efficiency that would enable us to dispense with this arrangement; and for this purpose he has been advised to employ British personnel.&lt;fl) - g - a di^ded lojalt.y end that the system is by no means ideal; al , J ' Lt : 4J' 0 06 h °P ed t ^st the Sheikh has got hold of police officers sufficiently well qualified to provide a oeucer system. r&gt; ^cathweli’s attitude is naturally distressing to opccia1 Pcl3ce Officers who wonder whether their prospects in tae Company are net affected by thejfcr hPvir^ to work as Gpecial Police Officers; but Jordan f s £®'®£?f nti y e .,- rully iR J- he administration of the Order hx ^ourcil end as supporting the Special Police Officers, iius is to keep you informed. 1 do net recomrend any action at present. ^ 5 / C H.E. Sir Jhipert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in tho . Persian Gulf, Bahrain, A&amp;FOiuiilGN OFlICii, S.W.l. 6th august, 194-9. ky dear Hay, I am answering your letter of the 6th July (85/55/49). I will first begin by quoting a minute by my colleague Vincent Evans: 'Section 30 of the Code of Criminal Procedure authorises the Local Government in certain territories to invest the District magistrate with powers to try as a Magistrate all offenees not punishable with death. It seems to me that when a District Magistrate has been invested with this power under Section 30, it is a power of a District Magistrate. Article l6(2)(i; of the Bahrain O.-in-C, and the corresponding provisions in the Os.-in-C. relating to the Court of the political Agent shall have the power and jurisdiction in criminal matters of a District Magistrate. 'I am not sure therefore why section 30 cannot be made applicable in an appropriate manner by King 1 s Regulation to Kuwait, Qatar, the Trucial States and Muscat, (it Wc..s applied under the old O.-in-C. to Bahrain) and the Political gent’s Court invested with power to try cases under it. 'Th^ere is one other small point. Article 17(1) of the Bahrain O.-in-C. provides for the powers of the Central Government and of the Provin cial Govt, under the Code of Criminal Procedure to be exercised by the j. of S. I can find no provision in the O.-in-C. as to who shall exercise the powers of the 'Local Government'. Possibly 'Local Govern ment' is the same as 'Provincial Government?' While this, I think, gives you the answer to the question which you have asked, my own comment is as follows. First, this is a question which I hope you will go into with Haines when he arrives. Secondly, we have got to get away from these absurd technical tangles arising from the fact that we are applying the Indian Code of Civil Proce dure. We must set out in amending Orders-in-Council precisely what powers we think the various Courts should have and then leave applica le to the Persian Gulf terri tories only those parts of the Code of Criminal Procedure which regulate other matters, such as evidence and the conduct of the proceedings. I don f t want, unless it is essential, to be botching the old machine still further by making King f s Regulations, as I see it at the moment, you have probably got what you want in Bahrain but not else where. Yours sincerely, ud/- w.e. Beckett. Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E. , C.S.I., BAHRAIN.L i) I „ ^ J L; ^.1 I I ^ I «J ...^r^&lt;.&gt;&lt;,' i .~iJ ^^ -i—— 4 -^ i l J-' ■ l ^ J——A ^ I 4 X I fc L^;-, l^,a-^. ji —fcj 4 Li^ I 4 &gt;-L ^yj l I j J Jl J t rl 4*- 1 ■' {J^t- jJj 4^-——y-. I ^j^-— ^—^'*4 4u ! L^ l i ^ 6^^^,’'. :Jj n; * Ullu. 1 w.L i jj L'-. j—&gt; w j.—i ’jj&gt; ^ ^.i J o , lj_A * J. JJ \a~C 4 / jJ^l I^Jyi jJj • a-u L&gt;- v i l £?“!^l &lt;jJI Translation of cony of letter from Public Security Department, reference No.A/4 dated 8th Septerrber, *49. to His Highness. &amp;fter Compliments, Regarding the letter received by Your Highness from Political Agency on the subject of the man named Dad Rahman, I wish to state that this person was found at Ahmadi with a tent in his possession and he was arres ted and then his place was searched and some articles belonging to the Kuwait Oil Company were found there. He was thus arrested for investigation, and as he is not known here and was not in possession of any identity papers no action was taken against him. He was released five days ago and he returned to his work. This report has been sub mitted to the authorities concerned regarding the theft. Usual ending.copy for file 7/2 THE POLITICAL AGENCY KUWAIT 25th September| 1949 No.R/215(3Vl) Dear Residency, We a^ee with Uie remarks in pariietraph 2 ef your letter No• 12/36/49 of the 14th September to the Eastern Department* Once an emploYee has been convicted in a criminal proceeding he is liable to dismissal by trie Company and, according to the contracts their senior staff employees si^ji, the Coapany are under no 2.^ Regarding your third paragraph* Boforo a person subject to our jurisdiction can be deported judicial proceedings under Article 26 of the Order in Council are necessary. In paragraph 3 of their telegram No.105 ef the 2nd Maron, 1949 f the Fereign Office have stated t in respect of two persons accused of a criminal offence* that this method is only to bo used with great care. There are even more valid objections to the deportation of employees at tho request ef their employers; and the proceedir^s contemplated in Article 26 of the Order in Council are not, we think - if only from the point ef view of industrial relations - ordinarily the kind ef proceedir^e that should be initiated by oil companies* Nor de we think that oil companies should even be allowed to pay for the deportation of their employees, for that give rise to a feeling amongst employees that our judicial administration is paid for by the Oil Company and that our Courts are therefore subject to the Company’s influence* We hope you will agree that it is essential not only that our Courts should be absolutely independent and impartial but also that they should manifestly be seen to be se. 3* We are sending a copy of iihia letter to tho Eastern Department. ion of dismis Yours ever. igency* ■ r&gt; 4 t \ • \ V N &gt; Tho Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain*^pIso 7/2 At COPY XO.K/Z3J? (13/2) THE POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT, October, 1949. Dear Gethin, Please refer to your letter No.356/4/49 of the 23rd September, 1949. P. I satisfied myself about this demand before rrviarding the parers to you. Many of the guns and cartridges will be bought by visitors froa Sandi Arabia who will take them away with them. You wi:il Z be to hear that at the outset I Informed the applicant that he would have to buy Belgian exchange with his own dollars. 4. The Kuwait Governrent have not issued any regulations controlling the sale and possession of arms and ammunition. Nor, as far as I know, do they intend to do so at oresent. There are many other asrects of their internal administration in respect ° J w v* 1 V;an * tJleiD issue regulations* such as regulations to enforce the Air Navigation Rules ( a C * ra j^ as k 001 ? sent to the Kuwait Government for their ccr sjoerataon), a nd regulations to control the sale of other dangerous drugs. A Motor vehicles Regulation and a Quarantine Regulation are also necessary as. too, is a regulation to define the law about accident compensation in mixed cases. All of these are urgent questions, but it will be necessary to rake the law effective for us to issue parallel legislation. This means the drafting of King*s Regu- SS * sin ? le ha^ed on the political &lt;nd judicial sides with a good deal of case work, this can only be a^ne Dit by bit; and I should prefer to tackle these questions in order of importance. Ve are already able effectively to influence the import of t h rou f h Present licensing system and I propose f pr: ?? rity J st ^ers which are at present subject little n any control at all. I regard motor vehicles and dangerous drugs - such as methyl alcohol - as far more lethal things than shot guns. Thirteen of our subjects have already lost their lives by these year » wh ile happily not one has been killed or wounded by a shot gun or rifle. Yours ever, Sgd. G.N. JACKSON. J.A.F, Gethin, Eso., Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.'zrm Haines has asked if it will be possible to prepare certain statistics and information about the Courts and their work, to be ready for him on his arrival. He has set out the sort of thing he requires on the attached sheet. I should be very grateful if you could produce these figures for him. He also asks for a note of the pov/ers exercised by the judicial officers and Courts in civil and criminal matters. He would like this as soon as possible, before his arrival. Can you let me have this also, in duplicate? -s/ . G=&gt; CONFH)' S'TIAL. Kw' in k ccif t G.N. Jackson, Esq., Political Agent, Kuwait. iStatistics of the work done during the past 12 months under each of the Orders-in-Council. Court of the Political Agent . (a) Criminal matters. (i) Number of cases triable by a District Magistrate. (ii) Number of cases triable by a Sessions Judge. (I am assuming that these officers have different powers in Inuian Law). (b) Civil cases. (If there is any difference in the class of case tried by a District Court and a Principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction then the total numbers of each class of case). (c) Probate jurisdiction. (i) Number of probates issued. (ii) Number of letters of Administration with will annexed issued. (iii) Number of Letters of Administration issued. (iv) lumber ol Administrations by the Court (under 1500 rupees) (v) Number of Administrations by an officer of the Court. The Chief Court (a) Criminal matters. (i) Cases tried by the Chief Court. (ii) If the Court has Appellate jurisdiction - the total number of appeals heard. (b) Civil Mattwrs. (i) Total number of cases heard during the last 12 months. (ii) Total number of eases civil appeals heard from Court of the Political Agent. Joint Courts Number and classes of cases tried. Registration ,. It would be useful to have an idea of the number of persons subject to the jurisdiction of the Court under each order in Council.Note of the powers exercised by the following in Civil and Criminal matters:- (1) District Magistrate (2) Sessions Judge (3) District or Principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction (4) District Judge (5) High Court of Judicature (6) Highest Court of appeal for the districtir No. ^ THE POLITICAL AGENCY KUWAIT, 31st October, 1949• 9 Please refer to your letter No.84/14/49 of the 8th October, 1949. 2. I enclose the figures you asked for. 3. When Sir Rupert was here he himself wrote to Haines and gave him a note on the powers exercised by judicial officers in Civil and Criminal matters. I enclose a copy of his letter and its enclosure. l J.A.F. Gethin, Esq., Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. A© Past 12 months . Court of the Political Agent, Kuwait (a) Criminal matters. * (i) 31 (ii) There have been no cases ,this year triable by a Sessions Judge that would not also be tried by a District Magistrate. (b) Civil cases - 6 (c) Probate Jurisdiction - Nil. Registration British subjects 6000 approximately Foreigners 860 approximately.1,0 • C/J$ 7 ( ?/2 ,y\ THE KtLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT, JJtut Octob?r, 1949. I I enclose a copy of a short note'I prepared for Wilton es an introduce t.lcn to the Isw here v.'hich I understood you to cay night be useful to other new arrivals. H.E. Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE.,CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.Telegram Code * 7o From Prodrome, London To Prodrore, Bahrain (telno 703 Neverber 16th) Repeated \ Political, Kuweit (for information) No. 101 Dated the 16th received the 18th November, 1949. CGNFII^TI^L . We have received a visit from PHINEA.S QUASS a barrister recently engaged for defence in two Criminal cases before the Court of the Political Agent Kuwait concerning ''essrs. Cunningham and Burgess. He asserts that Article 16(3) of the Kuwait Crder-in-Council does not provide for an appeal to the Cheif Court from: judgement of the Political Agent’s court in a criminal case. In Civil cases the Chief Court is empowered under Article (3)(l)(b) to ' hear appeals from the c r urt of the Political Agent n but in criminal cases it has only powers of a High Court of Judicature which according to Quass merely gives it a power of revision on questions of law and does not enable it to hear appeals on questions of fact. He suggested difficulty might be overcome by appointing an additional judge to the court of the Political Agent. It would’ then be possible in his view for one judge to hear case in the first instance as District Magistrate and then for the other judge to hear the appeal as Sessions judge. This he says would have been procedure in India. 2. Whatever procedure in India we feel sure t'pat it was not + he intention of the order for the court of the Political Agent to hear the appeal from' itself which is what Quass* solution would amount to. The intent ion surely was to give the right of anneal in crii inslcs ses to the Chief Court against the decision of the Political Agent's court as regards both law and fact and it i ay be that there has been an error in drafting and that paragraph should have been so set out that words ' and shall hear appeals fro&gt; the court of the Political 4gent ' applied to cririnal as well as to civil cases. 3. We should like to have your views urgently and in particular as to whether powers of the High Court of Judicature are as limited as Quass thinks they are. We suggest you should ask Judge Haines to exarrine ratter and rake any recomrendations which he ray think desirable for the arendment of Article and of corresponding Articles in other Orders. SOSFA.Telegram Enclair From Predrome, Bahrain Pelitical, Kuwait No. ?88 Dated and received the 19th Never her, 1949. hear these appeals which must be heard by you as Judge of* Court of Sessions. appeal petition nad has applied for extension of time -for filing to enable him to consult Councel regarding additional facts. He wishes to adduce time for filing expired on 31st October and it is for you to decide whether you will extend the time under Section 404 of the Criminal Procedure Code. If you refuse and order of commital should be made fixing the date from which sentence is to run. Your telegram No. ?58. Chief Court has no jurisdiction to Cunningham still refuses to sign HAY.Telegram Code From Political, Kir. ait x o Prodrome, Bahrain No. 263 Dated the 20th November, 1949 Your letter No. 194/11/49 of July 7. I presume that I have been officially appointed to Kuwait.Telegram From Prodrome, Bahrain Ci lode No To Repeated Prodrome, London (telno 548 November 22) Political, Kuwait (for information) 290 Dated the 22nd received the 23rd November, 1949 Priority. Your telegram No. 703. Haines has already drawn my attention to point raised by .^uass and I have discussed matter fully with him. We agree that under Orders in Council as they stand appeal to criminal cases from orders passed by Judge of the Court of the Political Agent acting in the capacity of first class Magistrate can not be heard by the Chief Court. As there has been a change of incumbent at Kuwait we have informed Jaicins that he should hear appeal from JacKson f s orders in his own capacity as a Sessions Judge. We are doubtful however if even this is strictly legal. 2. »Ye are considering what amendments to the Orders in Council are necessary and will submit our recommendations by bag.Telegram ISnclair From Political Resident, Bahrain To Political Agent, Kuwait No. 301 Dated and received 3rd December, 1949 Secretary of State appointed Gethin Judge of your Court November 25thFOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.1 14th Eovernber, 1949 (K 10332/90/250) Dear Agency We understand fro Bahrain that v/e are exp^fcted to reply to your letter C/251 (7/2) of the 16 th October about the fees to be charged for supplying copies of court proceedings. 2. We agree that the Indian Court Fees Act of 1870, Schedule 9, Article I has been superseded by the new Consular Fees Order in Council, and that fee nunber 83 should in future be charged for services of this nature. British Political Agency, Kuwait. Yours ever Consular Department</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/303</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/303</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 7/2 I Working of Kuwait in Council, 1949’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-19T14:44:15</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (62 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arrange in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, the exceptions being enclosures, which are sometimes of an earlier date than their covering letter. A set of file notes can be found towards the back of the file between folios 61-63.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 64; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence respecting questions arising from the implementation of the Kuwait Order in Council; the main correspondents are the Kuwait Political Agent (Gordon Noel Jackson and Herbert George Jakins) and the Persian Gulf Political Resident (Sir William Rupert Hay). The sort of questions raised include the extent of the powers of the State Police, the desirability of additional King's Regulations, and the appeals procedure for criminal cases heard at the Agency Court.The Arabic language content consists of a limited amount of correspondence — with English translation — between the Political Agent, officials of the State Police, and the Shaikh of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmed al Jabir as-Subah [Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ]. An introduction to criminal law as applied to Kuwait can be found on folios 31-35.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Kuwait Order in Council</topic></subject><subject><topic>Criminal law</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00015a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>