<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000049_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T01:01:28.807Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. (10793) NUMBER AND DATE SHOULD BE QUOTED IN REFERENCE TO THIS LETTER THE SECRETARIAT, ZANZIBAR. / £ - / x May, 1939. I am directed to inform you that this Government has for some time past considered it advisable to control the importation of lethal weapons into this Territory, ^he importation of swords and spears was accordingly- prohibited under the Customs Management Decree except under a written permit issued in that behalf by the Commissioner of Police. S. It is not the desire of this Government to place any undue obstacle in the way of any reputable person bringing with him a sword for use on ceremonial or other lawful occasions, but it has been brought to notice recently that individuals on occasion bring with thern a number of swords for distribution to their friends. ^future it is intended to restrict the permission to one s?/ord for any individual entering this Frotectorate; and any additional swords will hereafter be retained by the Customs Authorities for clearance in the usual manner and import dues will be collected in respect of them. The British Political Agent, BAHREIN. PXN. 'TLX^- ■4. In order that as little inconvenience as possible mas'- be caused to people of your Territory this Government would be grateful if wide publicity might be given among the persons likely to be affected of the intention to restrict the import of swords in this manner. 5. I enclose copies of pamphlets which are being distributed to outgoing dhows, and I am to suggest that use might be made of these to bring the matter to the notice of interested persons. I have the honour to be Sir Your obedient servantNOTICE BY THE ZANZIBAR GOVERNMENT. In future the importation of swords and spears will only be allowed by Permit to be issued by the Commissioner of Police at the time of reporting to the Immigration Authorities on entry into this Protectorate. Each person will only be allowed to import under permit one sword or spear and all others in excess of one will be detained by the Customs people to be cleared in the usual manner. This information is circulated to save inconvenience to intending visitors to this Protectorate who are advised not to attempt to import more than one sword. A. I. SHERINGHAM, Commissioner of Police. ^ (y* *3^^ *9 J 3 ^ ^1&gt;- aA* (3 J (3 ft •A^lj dAA (jl I j) [&gt;y J) I J) dAjU.)^ cS'NOTICE BY THE ZANZIBAR GOVERNMENT. In future the importation of swords and spears will only be allowed by Permit to be issued by the Commissioner of Police at the time of reporting to the Immigration Authorities on entry into this Protectorate. Each person will only be allowed to import under permit one sword or spear and all others in excess of one will be detained by the Customs people to be cleared in the usual manner. This information is circulated to save inconvenience to intending visitors to this Protectorate who are advised not to attempt to import more than one sword. A. I. SHERINGHAM, Commissioner JWi ^ Cx A ' V j 3 ^IjL C j '&lt;.♦=1' »i .A Jl V U a As-lj AJ^ I A^aell Jl IyL V jl j J*.NOTICE BY THE ZANZIBAR GOVERNMENT. In future the importation of swords and spears will only be allowed by Permit to be issued by the Commissioner of Police at the time of reporting to the Immigration Authorities on entry into this Protectorate. Each person will only be allowed to import under permit one sword or spear and all others in excess of one will be detained by the Customs people to be cleared in the usual manner. This information is circulated to save inconvenience to intending visitors to this Protectorate who are advised not to attempt to import more than one sword. A. I. SHERINGHAM. Commissioner 4.^11 J Jyo jj.fi JJiJl ftib.ll jrLyl V S ^ &lt;3 jWi i J'O' 4 d' ili/V ^ ; =eJl I-I a As-lj ^fi Aj^l Abseil di-A Jl Iy iy ji jdl) jljNo. 883-9/6. y Political Agency, Bahrain, the 30th May 1939, To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. / J- Memorandum . I enclose 10 copies of a notice issued by the Zanzibar Government on the subject of the control of the importation of swords and spears into that Protectorate. 2. The Chief Secretary has informed me that it is not the desire of the Government of Zanzibar to place any undue obstacle in the way of any reputable persons taking with them swords or daggers for use on ceremonial or other lawful occasions; but it has been brought to the notice of that Government that individuals on occasion take with them a number of swords for distribution to their friends. 3. The Zanzibar Government in future intend to restrict the permission to one sword for any individual entering the Protectorate; and any additional weapons will hereafter be retained by the Zanzibar Customs authorities for clearence in the usual manner and subject to the collection of import dues. In order that as little inconvenience as possible may be caused to persons travelling from Bahrain, the Zanzibar Government will be grateful if wide publicity might be given of that Government's intention to restrict the import of swords and daggers in this manner. In particular, perhaps all nakhudas of dhows trading with Zanzibar might be notified. ^ Political Agent, Bahrain.I 5' /* \ i iA I I The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tlx® jo 1111 ca 1 A. ^.s tiX • If us cs t • Tiw Political Agent • Bahrain. ^ The Political Agent «• Kuwait* and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. *ith a request to bring tne mtisr to the notice of interested persons* British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... J7.th.. J.une ♦. .19^9,.. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. r e ' ' Name and Date 7^ Copy of letter Ho. o95{ 10793) dated the 12th Hay 1939, from the Chief Secretary to the Government of Zanzibar. /f* 5 - 4 copies of 'Hotice by the Zanzibar Government 0 Subject. Import of lethal weapons into Zanzibar.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000049_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1338</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000049</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1338</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/6 I Arms &amp; Ammunition. Rules and Regulations re- import of arms and ammunition into Foreign Countries'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-13T14:37:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: This file has a foliation number on the front top right hand corner of each page. The number is uncircled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between Hugh Weightman, the British Political Agent in Bahrain, with Samuel Burnside B McElderry, Chief Secretary to the Government of Zanzibar, and Charles Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government. These correspondence concern the control of importation of lethal weapons (for example, swords, spears and daggers) into Zanzibar and the implementation of a restriction to one sword for any individual entering the Protectorate. Included within these correspondence are copies of a 'Notice by the Zanzibar Government' in English and Arabic, signed by Anthony Ilex Sheringham, Commissioner of Police, proclaiming this new restriction.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Zanzibar</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms control</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000049#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>