<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000399_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:10:00.486Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I Cunfidential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B % This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sa&gt; e telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt,' with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] From Political, Bahrain. To:- Resident, Dfepeated:- lucum, A r 0 # C/6O. Bushire. Aarship Shoreham. Dated E9th January it is understood that it has recently been given out on the Italian wireless (broadcasting) that an Italian Line ol Steamships will run to the ~ ersian Gull' by arrangement with the Persian Government. A Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent,Bahrain. S. 0; L&gt;CPP—11078&amp;P (G-1254) -24-0-81—4,00,m17 GO^OiKNMENT OE INDIA; Qonficiential Department. EXPRESS LETTER r N.B—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save tele graphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is icorded and signed as if it had been so despatched. ] From Political, Bahrain. My express Letter of January k^tii,C/60. I hear continued rumours o! the coming to the Persian Gulf ot Italian steamers,their speed,size,good coohing and so on. I should be grateful if I might be given any inlonnation that may be available and particularly whether there is any indication of their intending to come to Bahrain or the Trucial Coast. Since writing the above,I have been told that an Italian ship visiteu the Shatt-al- Arab recently,but that she was small and dirty. Possibly she has nothing to do with this projected To: - Resident Bush ire Repeateas- Ko. c/205-16/5 Warship Shoreham. Dated ; arc h laieut-Colonel, Political Agent,Bahrain. MGLPC—SI—31(CSP)DCF—{G-1227) -21.3-30-4,00,0:0.CONFIDENTIAL. 2 No. C/123 1934. The Hon hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The -^11+ical Agent, Bahrai n e and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Office of the -Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, GAMP, BAHRAIN* ,, v*»* * ssajaas. Dated 27th March 19 34, Reference to previous correspondence : Political Afrent Bahrai n f s Express Letter J'Jo. C/20f)-16/5 of 10th March 1 934, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No©93 of 22nd February 19 34 from Hie Majesty’s Mini s t er, ^ehran , to th e Forei gn Office. Subject. Mew Lloyd-‘'‘riesti na steamship service to the -Persian Gulf.Wo. 9 3 Brit id 1 , iiegation, TEHRAN. 2®n&lt;3 ?ebru8ry 19 34 to: B.O.r. Ho.O”. (B).34. INDIA No«, 39 BAGDAD Nool8 e BTT3HIBM No 0 32* ASWAZ. No,.!?, Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch -WOo26 of January 11th US 7g00/' 7 900/34^ instructing me to submit xpy observe tiers upon the new Lloyd-^riestino steamship service to the Persian Gulf. I have also received your despatch .no *74 of yebrue ry 8th (E 828/338/34) transmitting the views of the Political Resident, and a copy of Gir Brancis Huraphrys * despatch No*0(A) .4 of February 5th upon the same subje ct . 2. r fhe information ^.±11 ch 1 have been able to gather about the new venture in ’'ehrar confirms that contained in Sir Francis Humph ry s ’ despatch. rhe Mesopotamia Persiar Corporation are acting as agents for the Lloyd- ^ries+ino and Mr. Spence, the Corporation ’s representati yc at Ahwaz, went +o ^andar Shahpur to meet the ' l7 enicia ,, on her arrival (see my despatch ho.43 of Januar 3 r 31st). In view of the close relations existing between the Corporation and the British India Steam Navigation c omoany, I uresume the. t the Corporation would hardly act in this capacity without the approval of the steamshir company. It may even be + ^a+ some under standing exists bet we on the British India and idoyd- ^riestino companies, as the former are, i am told, more worried at present by the competition of the Ban sa Line, 'Die Bight Hohourable Sir John Simon,G.C.S. I etc. , et who * »50^ nho are quoting rates to European ports fj fty per cent lower than the British rates, rather than hy the prospective conpet it i on^bf the Lloyd-^ri estino 3. I am not aware whether such cargo is ordinarily carried hy Lloyd ^riestino steamers to Bombay and thence trarshipped to -British India steamers for conveyance to % ports in t he -Hersian Tmlf. if so this freight will be lost now that there are through steamers from Italy to the Gulf. But it seems t o me more likely that most of the cargoes will consist of freight which would otherwise have been carried, possibly by 3tri ck Line steamers, from ports on the North Sea. In any case the present programme, one round voyage in two months, is not very formidable .though it will doubtless be expanded if it proves a success. 4. ‘-lie immediate reason for the institution of this service has doubtless been the contracts obtained by Italian firms during the last year for the construction of various sections of the '’ran s-.fc'er si an railway. i need hardly say that the account of these contracts given in the 'Sole* 1 of December 13th last Isee Rome despatch i^o .0 .‘r. 1AJ ,1^6 of December 14 th, 1933 j is greatly exaggerated. Ihe contracts do not cover the whole railway, in fact they probably cover less than ten per cent of the total line to be constructed, and they do not extend to any works not directly connected with the railway. nevertheless they are in themselves of substantial value; they bavelfed to-o the introduction of Bra,ny hundreds of Italian »i* 3 nxHra artisans and workmen, and t he y d oubtle s s have led, and will lead, to extensive imnortati or s of Italian material and mach ine ry. bo/-3- 5, -*hese cargoes, ever with the cement trade to Iraq, may not be sufficient to render the new service profitable in the absence of subsidies from the Italian Government, but they are possibly sufficient to provide a comBercial motive for the ^etivities of that Govemmen*~ 1 find it hard to believe that the Italian Government can have political aims in Persia in the sense of haibouring designs upon -Persian territory or of wishing, or still less expecting, to acquire such a dominating position in the counsels of the Persian Government as will ensure them the support of Persia in major international affaire. 1 am equally sceptical about their aims in Iraq and in the Arab States of the Gulf so long xx it any rate as these are clearly marked as British preserves, although I realise that undue activity on the part of I + aly in these stages might force His Majesty’s Government into the uncomfortable position of having to announce open protectorates. 6 0 The aims of the Italian Government in all these countries is, 1 surmise, to find new outlets for Italian trade and new spheres of employment for -Ltaliar subjects. To achieve these aims they will use every art and artifice to penetrate new markets, to secure concessions and contracts and to ola ce Italians in government or private empliry, and the exercise of these arts and artifices nay sometimes be indistinguishable from political activities. in cry case, the extension of Italian interests in Persia, i:f at-then ly expense of important 'Pritish interests, is certrinly most deplorable, though not more deplorable than the extension of Japanese or German interests, and doubly deplorable when it is secured by unfair competition such as shipping subsidies* This last question is, as the Political Resident lias pointed out, one that cannot be treated locally*For the rest I can only su^’eot that if the competition to British shipping is serious even without the subsidy ( and there appears to he some grounds for doubting whet he it would nrove so) and if it is necessary to maintain the British India service on political grounds (for his Majesty’s Government , unlike the Italian Govemment.have political interests in Persia), a system of subsidies must be instj tuted irrespective of what the Italian or other Governments may or may not do, *7e I am sending copies of this despatch to the Department of Overseas 'rade (No •0.''. (B ). 34), to the foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No. 39^, to Hie Majesty’s Ambassador at Baghdad (No.18), to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (No.32), and to His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwaz (No.17). I have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most ohedi^t, humble s er van t, (signed) R.F.Noare*n, \ CONFIDENTIAL . From ... The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, u u q 'flUnDPUAxiii i r* 10th March, 1934 ? a service of Lloyd Triestino Steamers is now in operation between the Persian Gulf and Mediterranean. 2.- According to advertisements in the 'Messager de Tehran' the most recent sailings were to have been 3.- From the same source it appears that Persian officials receive a special reduction in fares. 4.~ I regret I have no information regarding the standard of cooking on board. I will, however, take the earliest opportunity of sending you supplementary information on this point. Date ... 30th March, 1934. To The Political Agent. Bahrain . (Copy to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.) (No. 17/515.) ITALIAN STEAMERS IN PERSIAN GULF. C*./2 04r~ ILlS With reference to your Egress Letter fated I T O o n V* T T *4 ss f T 1 /-\ /-X *4“ “I /-N *4- /-v -r* ^ &lt; Bushire Bandar Shapur.. Mohammerah ... 25th March, 28th March, 30th March. ^ CAPTAIN, SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULF.To f Q ! Political Resident, at Muscat Secretary of State for India, London Repeated to:- Government of India Ad en Bahrain Kuwait Kerman Copy given to Political Agent, Muscat. No. T/51 Dated and Received 23rd April 1937. An Italian subject Pastori with a visa for Muscat issued by Passport Control, Aden, arrived at Muscat on April 13th by slow mail from Karachi. Pastori stated that his object in coming to Muscat was to obtain labour for Eritrea. He left Muscat on slow mail of April 21st ostensibly for Bandar Abbas without an Iranian visa. = ResidentTELEGRAM T Q ! From - Political Resident at Muscat. To - Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy given to Political Agent, Muscat. No. - T/57 Dated and received 25th A.pril 1957. My telegram No.T/51 A.pril 23rd. Past^ori should not be allowed to enter your area without previous reference to me. - REBIDENTCQflFiDhfllliiJu No* C/ 317 - 16/5 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th april 1937 II To Memorandum : The Adviser to the For your information Bahrein Government, Bahrain Intimation has been received that an Italian subject named Pustori i/vith a visa for Muscat left there by slo 7 A r mail of April 21st ostensibly for Bandar Abbas, but was not in possession of an Iranian visa* Instructions have been received tn&amp;t he is not to be permitted to enter the area of Bahrain without previous reference to the honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for Political Agent, BahrainTelegram From To No. Dated G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. 88 26th April 1937. , Italian subject Pastori left Muscat on slow mail 21st April ostensibly for Bandar Abbas but had no Iranian visa. Do not permit to enter your area without reference to Political Resident. Political.TELEGRAM From To Repeated No. Dated ! Q 1 Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident at Muscat with the request that he will kindly give Political Agent, Muscat copy. Political Agent, Kuwait. 89. 26th April 1937. 51 dated 23rd April. landed at Bander Abbas 22nd April. He was of document which he stated was landing permit by Iranian Consul in Karachi. V/ritten report n with him on Baroda will be forwarded to Bushire POLITICALTullio Pastori joined the slow mail steamer Baroda at Muscat on the 21st April 1937. During various conversations that I had with him he made the following statements. (a) He was a geologist. (b) He had been employed in Abyssinia for 30 years and afterwards in Khartoum. His work in Khartoum was in connection with a wood contract from Abyssinia. (c) He had recently travelled extensively on the continent in connection with some petrol concern. (d) He had more recently been employed by an American Count at Aden who wished to enter the Hadhramout in search of antiques. (e) He had stayed with the American Mission in Muscat t and had called on the Sultan. (f) He was at present under contract to supply 10,000 coolies to a company employed by the Italian Govern ment to construct a road from Assab five hundred kilometres into the interior of Abyssinia. The coolies must be men accustomed to heat as they would work on the first 400 kilometres in the Danakil country. The coolies would receive as. 20/- a month for the first four months and then Rs.25/-. They would also receive food. They would be on a one year contract. Fourteen thousand had been recruited from the Yemen «na Aden. More being required he had come up here. Muscat had proved unfruitful. Coolies would be transported by the Moghul Line. He was receiving fis-10/- per coolie enrolled out of which he expected to spend as .5/- in bribes. (g) The Assab road was designed to be completed as soon as possible and act as the only outlet for Italian Abyssinian products thereby causing damage to the port of Djibouti. (h) He does not speak Persian or English. (i) Was employed by one Nesbitt in the Danakil country some ! Isome year ago. (j) Professed strong anti Mussolini views. Personal consents . He is a liar and he is mentally unbalanced as well if he expected his wild denunciations of his countrymen and obviously exaggerated stories of exploration to be believed. 2. Reference paragraph (d) above On my way through Aden on the 11th April I saw His Evcellency the Governor and in course of conversation he mentioned the American Count who I gathered was an Italian naturalised American and had been refused permission to enter the Protectorate at Mukalla as he was more interested in oil than antiques. 3. Reference paragraph(f) above From enquiries made from persons recently resident in Aden I understand that no coolies or at least not enough to attract the notice of idle persons have been recruited through Aden. 4. Our conversation was in Arabic.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER COijFlDL^lTx.ii S (.V. Tt.-TMsis an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition ns if it had been telegraphed To sace time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From PolitiCcJ. Bahrain. To /'■'N Political Rcsiacnt, Bu shire. C /5 rkuei Z'JUx il 133 7 13 Reierence my telegram of £6th April 1937, 39. PACTJEI. I enclose, for inform-: tion, a written report of my con versations with Pastori on board the £.S, Barode. X si 1 ! &lt;f A Bd/- T. HicKinbothc.m, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTEBTLi). ^]c Assistant Poiiticax agent, Bahrain. b$3 S. 6 . MF i’—400S&amp;P—(M-480J—26-7-34—2,00.000.© telegram To tfroa Repeated political Reeident, Buahire, at Mueoat, political Agent, Bahrain.^ Political Agent, Kuwait. Governor, Aden, with reference to hie telegram Ho.32, dated the 21»t April 1937. Copy by poet to Secretary of State for India, London. &lt;i * * « Government of India, Department of eternal * i. a \ «a*1 Ck _ origin but hie paaaport a naturalised ^jaerican aubject accompanied by hie wife a British subject by birth arrived in SGisoat on 13th April from Aden without previous notice in o ota pan/ with Pas tori. 2 # Prorok stated he was an archaeologist but hie actions euggeeted that he was also interested in Oil, According to a subsequent telegram from Aden both Pastor! and Prorolc are suspected to be concerned with Italian Oil inter sets. 3. The Sultan has refused peraieeion for Prorok to pursue his •archaeological* investigations in his territory and the couple left for Iraq to-day by s.s.BASDRA* 4. Prorok has a visa for Bahrain and Kuwait issued by Aden. His wife has no visa for these places but her pass 'Sty telegram T-51 of 23rd April. Count Prorok believed to be of Aolish or Hungarian port is endorsed for them and in the circumstances under my instructions /2 - &amp; H instructions Political Agent Muscat has given her transit ▼ Isas for these places. They should accordingly be perm tted to land and stay if they so wish. - Resident./ A n\ &amp; n Telegram q. yrom Political Resident, Bushire, at Muscat. To Political Agent, Kuwait, Political Agent, Bahrain, No.T/73. Dated the 28th April, 1937. j&gt;n (fuc ~&gt;) Uy immediately preceding telegram. At Bahrain Proroks are staying with Dr. Dame. 2. Apart from their suspected connection with oil couple in themselves are quite pleasant espec ially Countes s and while keeping an eye on them please give them generally any assistance they may require. 3. If you have an opportunity please get details of Prorok’s passport. Ve have details of the Countess’s. - Resi dent.[N-B. — This ia an ORIGINAL mesaage aent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more ecpeditious t an the ordinary mail and ts cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended tu be tre e , on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sure time and to obvta e formalities it is dratted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature oj a responsible ojjicer of the Department. ic g Of th© POlltioal Resident No. c/lOO of 1937 o Dated in the Persian Gulf, •v&amp;wter Camp, Muscat# Sto ’ ihe 28th April, &amp; prom To Political Resident, Bushire, at Muscat j political Agent, Bahrain* -/ Political Agent, Kuwait# His Excellency The Governor, Aden, His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. The Secretary to the Government of India, Department of External Affairs, Simla, Political Agent, Muscat* Subjects count Prorok# My telegram Ho*T,72 of 28th April 1937, There seems to be no doubt that Prorok is in lact an archaeologist but on his present travels at any rate, there are various indications that under fcover of this profession he is working for Oil interests, 2. On arrival here he stayed with Dr. Harrison, of uhe American Arabian Mission, who interested himself considerably^ on their behalf. Dr, Harrison got into touch with a Shaikh in the interior, who is an old patient of his, with a view to facilitating Prorok’s journey inland! the ostensible object of the said journey being to examine ancient inscriptions. 3. / S. 44. MFP—1374 S&amp;P—(M-2043)—15-1-36—10,000. (Signature) (Designation) it. i•3 y 6* Prorok and his wife left to-day for Iraq as already reported. Both are much disgruntled with the Sultan^ refusal to grant them travel facilities, but I am of opinion that it is extremely fortunate that the latter took up the attitude he did. It would be most undesirable for an American-Italian Combine either to get a hold in Muscat or to be in a position to compete against Petroleum Concessions Limited, who are shortly about to open negotiations with the Sultan. sd. T.C.Powle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attest ed* for Secrkfciry to the Political Resident in the Pers ian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/102 Of 1937. The HoD’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* Hi a KxettXleocy Sir Bernard Reilly f XC2*G. * CIS. t OB.£. f Governor and Commander-in-chief, Aden. 2. ®rjor W.H.H&amp;y, CIS.# Deputy Secretary (Foreign) to the Government of 2nd ia, Simla. 3. MeJ or R.P. Tatte, X. Political Agent, Muscat. and has the honour to transmit to him a xxxxxramxxyxxTrxxyxxTrvyxxxxxxzxxx 4. 5. Captain T Captain A • Hickinbothaa, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. •C.Stevart, I. » t J Officiating Political Agent, , . .« and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Golf, ^^Bi^iS^fisulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 29 tfc‘ •xpr*il;-• * 195 ? . \riCONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resideot in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* Ills Majesty's secretary o£ tor India. 2* Foralgn secretary to the uoverouient u£ India 9 i&gt;S|&gt;art&amp;ent or internal aTfairs f 3* nis i^xceJULenc^ the Governor and uoi^rijiaer- in- Cliler oi* ^oapr^ 4* The Political /%ent f hahraiiuv^^ The Political a^ent f JUieait* and has the honour to transmit documents (s). to him a copy of the undermentioned office of the Political Resident in the Persian British Consulate-Genera1, W fii^HIRE. -april-aiK&amp;^v Reference to previous correspondence: Political Residents tele&amp;raia Mo. T/51, dated 23rd april 1237. Description of Enclosure. 1. 2 . Kerman telegram No. 11, da tea 28th april 1237. Subject. PA 3 T 0 HITelegram Q His Majesty^ Conaul, Kerman* Political iieaiaent, Buahire, at Muscat. Mo. 11 J^om To Repeated His Majesty's Minister, Tehran. Ko. 18 iiated 28th received 2Uth April, 1237. Js In continuation of uy endorsement Mo. 26 of April 26th in post forwarding copies of previous telegrams on the subject. 11 informed him that approximately ten thousand labourers in bandar abbaa and district would be willing to accept employ ment but could not take any action unless he received orders from Tehran. j^&amp;stori assured Governor that 60JIKNTM Company at A6SAB would be glad to give written official under taking signed By Italian Minister at Tehran to repatriate labour ers after completion of work (construction of roans in xuhlTRBa). with Xranain Government. If he is unsuccessful he intends to proceed to Basrah. My telegram Mo. 10. Pastori interviewed Governor on April 26th who Pastori left for Tehran on April 27th to negotiate urltconsul (Copy given to Political Agent, Muse t)mmHo. Nil. Dated and received 13th May 1937, I have an uneasy feeling that Prorok may be trying to double back to Muscat either by British India or by the Strick boat on which he has given out that he is returning to Europe. Please keep a watch on him and refuse a visa for Muscat if applied for on the ground that he was asked to leave Muscat by the Sultan. 2. When Prorok leaves you should report to the Political Agent Muscat who should if necessary ensure that Prorok is not permitted to land at Muscat. = Britconsul =I * GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Ok PA RIMINI, CONFIDEKPIAL , EXPRESS LETTER [S. B, —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sa^e telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition r&gt;s if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent* Bahrain* Political Hoaident Bus hi re* s No, C/376-16/5 Dated l^th Her/ m 7* CQUITT PRQRQK* _ Keferonce your telegraLi ho. nil dated lota : ay 1037* ilie Proroks are reported to have re-die covered a cave at Jabal Qikhan and spend several hours a day digging there* They have so far made no important find* Their nrecent intention is to proceed to Aden by the a.3.'Florista ” or an oil tanker, ihey have been behaving in an unsuspicious way and ha/c apparently talsen no interest in oil matters* They nev nal:e an application for permission to explore and excavate the tombs here* I am being informed of their movements. &lt;fj c S. 6. MFi'—400S&amp;P—lM-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000. (I /s7v Captain* Political Agent, Bahrain*As much as I would like to see investiga- 6th May* tion go ahead my check with institution of international standing shows unanimous opinion man in question not favourably regarded and strong probability only interest is to get sufficient local colour to promote pubjacation of book for personal benefit (stop.CONFIDENTIAL. rf - No c/377-16/5. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Honourable 'the Polit-icrl Kcei CiGn't in the Peroisui Oalf 3 BUSHIHE* and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire telegram No. nil dated the 15th May 193 1 . Description of Enclosure. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. 15th May 1937 Dated Name and Date. Subject. Note dated the 6th Hay COUNT PROROK 1937*•—COPY. © Air Letter from Messrs Frank C. Strick &amp; Co*(Basra) Ld*, Basrah 14th. May, 1937. Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ld.. Bahrein. Dear Sirs, PASSAGES* m reply to your letter No. OSA/224 of the 8th. inst., we could paxxifeijc probably arrange for the vessel which will be callin| at your port to pick up the two camels about the last week of this month, to also pick up the two passengers you have in view for Aden. We xgxftk 'egret we cannot* quote to Marseilles as we have no steamer proceeding to that port. For your information the passage rate from your port to ADEN is £25. each, and we shall be glad to reserve accomodation on receipt of your confirmation. Yours faithfully, for Frank C. Strick &amp; Co. (Busra) Ltd.. (Sgd) Francis Seed.American passport no.535 issued by the Consulate General of TT.S.A. at Paris, France dated September 11th 1936. FRANCIS BYRON KHDN DE PROROK. Description of bearer:- Height 6 f Hair Brown Eyes blue place of birth fiiXICO City* Date of birth October 6th 1896. 0 c cupation IR C&amp;AE 010GIST. Particulars of sundry British visas. 1) British Passport control Office, iaris. Dated 26.11.36 No.76881, ¥isa for Palestine (traveller) Good for any number of journeys within 12 months from the date\ hereof. 2) S;f 4 Good for Ira*, Koweit. Bahrain and Muscat in Transit. Sd For Commissioner of Aden. Date 10/3/37. 3) No.80/37. 3 ^ Seen good for Aden m transit. Validity one year. British Consulate Cairo. luxate /1/37. 11 'Cood^for Karachi in transit to Iran subject to Consular Visa from the Iranian Consul. Seal of the Passport Officer, ^iden. Sd Sinclair. Passport Officer jiden. 8/4/37. Landed at Karachi on Arrived per S.S.Bendra up and landed at Baferain on the Autho rity of visa no. 274 (Item 2) Seal of the Passport Officer .Bahrain. Sd. J.Ahmed. 20/2/56. 1/5/37.British passport no. C. 31921. Issued at Paris by British Consulate General date 20th Novem ber 1936. Ctess GERTRTTDE MONICA DE PR0R0K (Maiden name PICKERING). The holder previously travelled on Foreign Office passport no. 618383 of 30th ^pril 1928 issued in her maiden name. Date and place of birth. Horsforth , England. 5th October 1911. Residence, England. Height 5/Vi” . Colours of eyes, brown. Colours of Hair, Fair. Endorsement so on paBC.jk British Emnire (Reg. 6 and 7). all Countries in Europe, incl uding the union of Soiiiet socialist republics and Turkey, Egypt, Syria, Palestine Irac, Koweit, Bahrain, Trucial Oman (Crossed of at Aden; and the United States of America. Muscat ^entered at Ade] on 10/3/37. Lahded at Karachi on 8/4/37. A) Visa no.125 of 1937 dated the 27th April 1937. Seen at H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat. Visaed for the journey tc Iraq. Sd Major. H.B.M’s Consul, Muscat. B) Transit Visa 126 of 1937. Dated the 28th /ipril 1937. Seen at H.B.M’s Consulate, Muscat. Visaed for the Journey to Bahrain. Sd Major. II.B. r ’s Gonsml, Muscat. CO Transit visa no 127 of 1937. Dated the 28th April 1937. Seen at 1 l‘,B.!'’s Consulate Muscat. Visaed for the Journey to Koweit. Sd Major. K.B.I *5 Consul, Muscat. ’'British subject by birth? n The Wife of a citizen of the United States of .America' Arrived per S.S.Bendra up and permitte. to land at Bahrain on the authoiiby of visa no. 126 (item B) Seal of the Passport Officer, Bahrain. Sd. J .iJuaed. 20.2.56. 1.5.37.TELEGRAM Q % Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat. Governor and Commander-in-Chief, Aden. Political Agent, Kuwait. 111 . 20th May 1937. Your telegram No.nil dated 13th May (not sent to Aden and Kuwait). Proroks said to be leaving by S.S. STORANGER tanker 21st May for Aden where they propose transhipping. From To Repeated No. Dated POLITICALConflcl^ntlal Lio* C/409-16/5 political Agency, jjahrain, the Zlsz May 1937% To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. C0U3ST PHQHQK. Reference paragraph 5 of your telegram No T/73 dated the 28th April 1937* 1 * i enclose the aeiialxs of Prorok 1 ^ ^asspor-* for Political Agent, Bahrain, C/ /V Press Cutting from 'The Hindu', Madras, the 9th May 1937. 0O0 * * * QUEEN OF SHEBA’S MINES Leader of a French expedition to Southern Arabia, Count Byron dc Prorok claims to have discovered the old caravan trail from the kingdom of Sheba to Jerusalem over which the Queen of Sheba was borne when she i visited King Solomon. He also claims to have discovered in the desert mountains of the Yemen of the gold mines of Ophir, which made the Queen of Sheba the richest woman in the world in her day. “ I believe that one of the richest archaeological fields known to science can be opened up in Southern Arabia,' adds the French man. ' At present all exploration work must be done secretly because of raiders and because of the local super stitions attached to the dead cities of the dc&lt;?i&gt;rf ” 1 - I A.P.A. Perhaps this might interest youl 27-5-37.mm TELEGRAM From To Repeated No. Dated f Q 1 Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain, at Sharjah. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Muscat. Governor and Commander-in-chief, Aden. Political Agent, Kuwait. 132. 10th June 1937. Proroks left Bahrain by S.S. Vasna on 9th June. Proposed itinerary stated to be Basrah Baghdad Haifa. = POLITICAL ~47J The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. tne Political Agent, Muscat. 77^ 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. The Political Agent, Ku^it. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (^yj or necessary action. British Consulate-General, BU SHIRE. v^\ Dated.. Plat.. JUhO*.. IW Reference to previous correspondence : b 3* Political Heaident'a impress letter no.G/107 01 t ae Isu may 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. India Office letxer ho. p # 2.31^4/57 dated the 20tn May 1937* Subject. pastori .V Copy. P.Z.3194/37. IUDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL,S.W.l CONFIDENTIAL 20tn May 1937 My dear Fowle •fill you please refer to tne correspondence ending wit ft your confidential Express Air Mail letter No.C/l07 dated 1st May, regarding tne Italian, Pastori ? It is a little disquieting tnat an Italian snould apparently be wandering about tne Gulf, endeavouring to obtain Arab labourers for employment in Eritrea but tnere does not seem to be any reason to take serious action as regarding Pastori’s visit to Muscat, particularly as ne seems to nave failed in nis object; at tfte same time it migftt pernaps be wortft wftile, if you see no objection, giving some friendly warning to tfte Sultan of Muscat, and to tfte ruler of any otfter state wfticft Pas tori (or anyone else bound on a coolie- catcfting errand for Italian colonies) migftt subsequently visit, to tne effect tnat it cannot be guaranteed, from tne information available to His ?Iajesty*s Goverrment, tnat anybody wno enters Italian employment in Eritrea or Abyssinia will find tnat tne conditions of work are altogetner nealtny or suitable. lours sincerely sd. H.A.F.RumboldThe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. The Hon’ble Lieut .-Colonel A. 'S. 3.Parsons, CBE. ,DSO., Secretary to the tfo/ernraent of India in the External Affairs Department,«imla. 2. or R.P. Vatts , I.A., Political Agent, lluscat, at Karachi. 3. Captain ?• Hidcinbotn&amp;m, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. / 4. Captain a. i.de Caury, MC., Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned doc»- ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHTRE. Dated... .SOth. J.une .1937^.. Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident's HXpress letter jmo.C/IO? of 1st May 1937. Description of Enclosure. Su bject. “Count de ProroK'. Name and Date. fV? — Dea^official letter JS(o. t&gt;04-B Jof the 30tn June 193 7 to M.J. Claus on Esquire, The India Office, London.Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.INDIA OFFICE, 3154/37. Secret. 1C 'Sx'd June, ^3?. My dear Fowle, Will you please refer to your a r interestin letter to Clauson of the 29th April u. 0. No.0/101 on the subject of L f affaire Prorok. In this connection you will he interested to see the enclosed copy of a letter (and enclosures) which we 1935* Apart from the fact that Pi^orok appears to he discredited in scientific circles he is apparently not Office letter (and enclosures) was sent to the Government of India with India Office letter No. P. Z. 2429/35 aated 11th April 1935. I also forward, as enclosure No./2, a copy of a secret note containing some further information regarding Prorok and Pastori. I am sending a copy of this letter to Hay (with a copy of enclosure No. 2 only) and (with a copy of hoth enclosures) to Watts, Hickinhotharn (at Bahrein) and Stewart received from the Foreign Office in entitled to the rank of 'Count’ 1 . A copy of the Foreign (at Kuwait) Yours sincerely, The Hon.Lt. Col.Sir T.C.Fowle, KCIE., CBE., His Majesty’s Consulate Genera Bushire. Consulate General, (Sd) H - A - F - RUMBOLDP. Z. 2429/35. No.L 1703/1703/405 CONFIDENTIAL. FOREIGN OFFICE 3 . W. 1 4th April, 1935 Sir I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you herewith for j^uch action as the secretary of State for India may consider necessary a copy of a letter of the 15th ultimo from the Royal Geographical Society regarding the expedition of Count Byron de Prorok to the Yemen. 2. Early last year de Prorok led an expedition to Abyssinia for the purpose of exploration and excavation work. In this connexion I am to enclose a copy of a letter of the 11th January, 1934 from the President of the Royal Anthropological Institute together with a copy of the reply thereto of the 18th January, 1934. The expedition achieved little of scientific value and from information furnished by His Majesty’s Minister at Addis Ababa and from other sources it appears that de Prorok is discredited in scientific circles and should be treated with all reserve. 3. A similar letter has been addressed to the Colonial Office. I am, etc., 3gd. S. Gaselee The Under Secretary of State, India Office.P. Z. 2429/35. &lt;3 ROYAL GEOGRAPHICAL SOCIETY, Kensington Gore, London, S. W. 7. 15th March, 1935. Sir, I am desired to forward for information and any acoion that H.M. ! s Foreign Office may think called for, a copy of a letter received by the President of this Society from Mr. Henry Field, of the Field Museum of Natural History at Chicago, together with a news cutting from the T Sunday Pictorial’ of March 3. So far as this Society is concerned all that we can say is tnat the Count de Prorok was at one time a Fellow of the Society, but has ceased to be a Fellow since 1932. Yours very faithfully, (Sd.) ARTHUR R. HINKS, Secretary. COPY. (L 1703/1703/405) The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.*Cable Address - Museum, Chicago. FIELD MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Private and Confidential Roosevelt Road and Lake Michigan HF: JJH. Chicago February 21 9 1935 My dear Sir Percy: I see by an International News Service press dispatch dated February 20th that Count Byron de Prorok is now on his way to search for the u long lost capital of the Queen of Sheba' somev/here to the East of Sana. As you know this is one of the most important archaeological problems of the Near East and one which deserves the most careful and delicate handling in view of the local political situation. According to this dispatch 'members of the Trocadero Museum of Paris, which is sponsering the expedition, will accompany de Prorok'. I have written to Dr.p.Rivet at the Trocadero as I am confident that this is inaccurate in view of his bad reputation on French soil. You will no doubt recall that the 'Count' has posed as a Fellow of the Royal Geographic Society and that his last expedition was said to be sponsered by the Royal Italian Geographical Society which was earnestly denied by their President. I am sure you will agree with me that everything should be done to prevent this charlatan from doing any damage which will prejudice the local governments against further scientific exploration or archaeological investigation and I should be very glad if you would investigate the matter and request the Foreign Office and Air Ministry to act as they see fit in this matter. I am perfectly prepared to have you quote me in confidence to the Foreign Office or to the Air Ministry, but I naturally rely on you to treat this letter in confidence. Sir Percy Cox President, Royal Geographical Society, Kensington Gore, London, England. With all good wishes, Yours sincerely, (Sd.) HENRY FIELD.News Item copied from 3 March, 1935, issue of London 'Sunday Pictorial'. COUNT WHO DEFIED A CURSE. TO HUNT FOR THRONE OF QUEEN OF SHEBA. New York, Saturday. Count Byron de Prorok, the archaeologist, is on his way to Hodeida, the Red Sea port of the Kingdom of Yemen, whence he will set out to search for the lost capital of the Queen of Sheba. Count de prorok believes that the capital of the Queen’s empire lies 800 miles from Hodeida in the midst of the Hadramaut, in the desert interior of Southern Arabia. After being present at the unsealing of the tomb of Tut-ankh Amen, the Count was a member of a party which unearthed the 'curse stone' of Carthage, on which was inscribed - 'Whoever overthrows this stone shall be shattered by Baal'. Ten of those who were with him on that occasion have since died, the Count states. Fortunately, he is not superstitious.Copy. (L 265/265/405) ROYAL ANTHROPOLOGICAL INSTITUTE 52, Upper Bedford Place, London, W. C.l. The 3 11th January, 1934. Sir, The Egyptian Gazette of (about) December 14th, 1933, contained an article describing 'one of the largest scientific expeditions of recent years'. The party is said to be under the leadership of Count Byron de Prorok, F. R. G. S. , and 'under the auspices of the International Anthropological Institutes of the British, French, Italian, Egyptian and Ethiopian Governments.' Among other things, the expedition intends 'to search for the body of Alexander the Great and King Solomon's Mines, and will also seek proof of the Atlantean theory of the origin of man. ' i. snould like to say that the soi-disant Count Prorok has no connection whatsoever with this Institute, nis expedition has received no support from us. we are informed by French Anthropologists that Count Prorok is not a Count and that his name is Cohn, not Prorok. hq are of opinion that the Sudan Government should be advised to keep a close watch on this man's movements and that he should be prevented from excavating and collecting surface material. The article in The Egypt ian Gazette states that tne expedition will proceed from the Sudan into Abyssinia to investigate 'the strange Dolmens', and suggests that etary of State iV for Foreign Affairs.5'7 it will observe the slave trade which 'rumour insists' is still in existence. It is added that in nearby Somaliland the expedition will have an opportunity also of observing the effects of 'the hashish trade, also said to flourish through secret channels. ' It is not for me to comment upon some of these statements, but I should like to be permitted to say that as a scientific Institute we view with grave concern the harm that may be done in Abyssinia by incompetent handling of the megaliths. We venture to hope that it may be possible to inform the Abyssinian Government, through the British Minister, that this expedition is not, in any way, connected with this Institute. I have, etc., Sgd. Edwin W. Smith. President,Copy. FOREIGN OFFICE, 3.W. 1. (L. 307/265/405) 18th January. 1934. CONFIDENTIAL . Sir, With reference to your letter of the 11th instant, regarding the scientific expedition of Mr. B. de prorok to Egypt, the Sudan and Abyssinia, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that copies of the article in the “Egyptian Gazette” had already been sent to His Majesty’s High Commissioner at Cairo and to His Majesty’s Minister at Addis Ababa. 2. The former has since been instructed by telegraph to notify the Government of the Anglo-Egyptian Sudan of the facts as disclosed in your letter under reply, and to suggest to them the desirability of keeping a close watch on the expedition’s activities. His Majesty's Minister at Addis Ababa was also informed of the facts by telegraph and instructed to inform the Ethiopian Government unofficially that Mr. de Prorok has no connexion with either the Royal Geographical Society or the Royal Anthropological Institute. 3. I am to add that Sir Miles Lampson has since reported that the Sudan authorities have been fully apprised of Mr, de Prorok’s lack of qualifications as an archaeologist. I am, etc., i Sgd. S. GASELSS. The President, Royal Anthropological Institute, 52, Upper Bedford Place,COUNT BYRON DB PRCROK . Addr. 9 rue de Lota, Paris XVI. Aged 39, born Mexico. Described on his notepaper as Editor of the monthly review, 'ETHIOPIA”. During the Italo-Abyssinian War, Count de PROROK was suspected of being concerned in gun-running activities in the Red Sea. Secret information received about that time suggested that the French suspected de PROROK of being an Italian agent and that the Italians suspected him of being a British agent. On 9.2.37 a certain Colonel N. KORDASHEVSKI of Jerusalem, v/as in touch with the Count, who was then a.t ^2, uiiar-i-a Antikhana Cairo, regarding a proposed trip to discover a hidden city in Arabia, apparently Sheba. According to available information from Palestine, this K0RDASH2VSKI claims to have participated in a number of adventurous expeditions, including the ROERICH expedition to Tibet in 1927/28. The India General Staff Summary of Intelligence for the week ending 29.5.28 shows that a Colonel XOKDASHEVoKI did in fact accompany the Roerich Expedition. He carried letters from General Knox to the effect that his sympathies were pro-British. De Prorok and his wife left for Karachi by the s.o. 'Volpi' on 3.4.37, the latter stating that she was proceeding to the Deccan. They were accompanied by Tullio PASTORI and took with them a car and a Dodge truck with a body specially adapted for desert work. Prior to their departure from Aden, de Prorok and pastori confided to a reliable source that it w r as their intention to meet xriends at Muscat and to make arrangements to penetrate Rub al Khali in/2. m the autumn, where they intended to search for traces of an ancient civilization. As regards Tullio PASTOHI, he is an Italian trader of about 50 years of age, who has spent the last 20 years 'living rough' in Eritrea, Abyssinia and the Sudan. He at one time became bankrupt in Eritrea and got into disfavour with the Italian authorities -who refused him an Italian passport and re-admission into Eritrea. On another occasion, however, he crossed the Sudan border and visited Tessenei, where he was entertained by Italian officers. More recently, whilst in Aden, he was apparently refused permission to visit Addis Ababa. During their stay (from 8.4.3V to 11.4.37) in Karachi, the de Proroks and Pastori did not come to unfavourable notice. They gave out that they were archaeologists. Their passport particulars were as follows: Count Byron Khun de PROROK: Wife: American passport No. 555, issued in Paris, 11.9.36., visa No. 274 issued Aden 3.4,37 British passport C/31921, issued fans, 20.11.36., valid for B.n. aged 25. b. Korseforth. England. Tullio PASTOPT. Passport No. 389726, issued Bucharest, 28.3.34. (Italian), visa No. 5. issued Aden, 2.4.37. d. Padua, Italy, aged 52, »■—««•£ P.Z.U644./37. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, O * W t x&lt; BY AIR MAIL. loth Jul. , 193 7 1 6J-&amp;JL -2— l/&gt; Would you kindly refer t/ your demi-official letter dated 29th April, D.O. No. (//101 of 1937, about tlie Proroks? I had a call from this couple the other day. They had been sent on from the Royal Geographical Society, where they had made enquiries about the possibility of a journey into South East Arabia. They said that their object was to find out how they should set about obtaining permission for an archaeologicial exploration which, so far as I could make out, would be in an area somewhere to the south of Sharjah. They seemed extremely vague as to where exactly they wanted to go, but apparently their idea was to start in from the Trucial Coast. I explained that the Sheikhs in this area are in special relations with His Majesty’s Government and that the proper way of enquiring about facilities for travel in that area would be to write to the India Office explaining/ T^o Hon’ble Lt.Col. T.C.W. Fowle, K.C.I.E. , C.B.E., British Consulate-General, Bus hi re.2 # explaining what they wanted to do. I said that, as they were probably aware, it is not a part of the world suitable for anybody except the most experienced travellers, and that in any case His Majesty's Government, m view of their responsibilities, would have to consider the matter from the point of view of security etc., apart from the necessity of securing the permission oi the various Sheikhs. There would also, of course, have to be consultation with the local authorities. I promised, however, that any communication which they night send uO the India Office would be treated with every sympathy and with as little delay as possible. They quoted you, of course, as an old friend, and •cliey said that the Royal Geographical Society would be only too glad to give us full information about them. I re.trained from telling them that we already had quite enough information without asking for any more. I have heara no more from them since their call vmich was about a week ago), so perhaps they are not puioUin. : their idea. They also seemed to have in mind soue scheme for travel in the Hadramaut, and they may nave transferred their attention to that. Incidentally, 1 caught sj -Ght of them the other day at Philby’s lecture uiie Royal Central Asian Society about his trans-Arabian joarney ending in the Hadramaut (about which Lady Fovle has/no doubt told you - it was an amusing evening)# I send you this line in case we may have to consul you, on the basis of an application from them, as to the best means of turning it down. Possibly the simplest way would be to get the Sheikh or Sheikhs in question to say that they a re rot prepared to grant facilities, if this could be arranged without undue trouble, I am sending a copy of this letter to Watts and Hickinbotham. M.. J CLAUSO,, ^ cannot/ soy ’tnc.'t .l found fiio Countess venv particularly attractive. She seemed rather a hard-faced woman, in complete control of her husband. Possibly she is more alluring under Eastern skies.' 0 JBy Air Mail. INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. 49G3 2000 7.3618, Quai d*Orleans, * P. Z. 4799/37. /r Paris. July 20. Dear Sir, On returning from Arabia recently I was able to obtain, from local sources, the position of the lost ancient city of Ubar in the Rub-el-Khali, S.Arabia. Mr. Hinks of the Royal G-eographical Society advised me to get in touch with you in regard to the necessary permission to explore this part of the Arabian desert. I visited the India Office and was asked to write down a rough outline of the project. I should like to organise a party from Shargah or Muscat, and penetrate two hundred miles into the Rub-el-Khali to the position of the mined city. I am willing to take an official representative with me and also a representative of the British Museum if they are interested. The sole objective of the Expedition v/ould be to photograph, film and study the antiquities of the site; specimens of which I have seen. Mr. Phil by does not believe in the lost city, but my information is absolutely reliable. I should like to leave in October if possible; paying all expenses and leaving a deposit at Shargah if desired. Needless to say, I have had twenty years of desert exploration; Mr. Hinks can tell you further details (for career 'Who's Who' and 'Encyclopaedia Britannica'). Very sincerely yours, (3 d.) BYRON DE PR0R0K.CONFIDENTIAL . ^ No. 574-S of 1937. &amp; Ihe Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. Major R.P.Watts, LA., Political Agent, Muscat, at ZIARAT. 2. Captain T. Hickinbothara, IA. , political Agent, Bahrain, at KARACHI. J and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment India Office letter No.P.Z.4644/37 of the 16th July 1937. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. l)at,d.... 3l ; cl ... Au « u8t 1937 Reference to previous correspoi Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi.official letter No. 573-S of the 3rd August 1937 to M.J. Claus on Esquire, The India Office, London. PROROKSqogrfixrasTlAi,* T),0«^o«S73-B» The ^ea Idency, Bushire, zne 3xtt August, !937* / / OouXcl you plaaa.e refer to your deml-ofriei&amp;l letter So. 4644^S7 t dated tne l«tn July l^37 f ret Prorofce. 2. It would be moat uadeslrefale for this couple to go 9 arcnaeoioging 9 on tne TrueU1 Coast, especially this winter when we snail nare Petroleum Concessions Limited operations in that area on our nanus. however, if their application for permission to travel materialise# we will doubtless be able to turn it down on some plausible excuse or other. I’m sorry you did not find tne Countess attractive. &gt;e gustibua -, end as you say .astern shies may maice a differenct. Cfc&amp;f standards, especially in tne hot weather, can hardly be up to those of /hitehall. * I am sending copies of this letter to fatte and Hlofcinbotham. H.J. Claus on Inquire, The India Office, London. Yours sincerely, sd. T.C.S’owle. \ * sent under Printed letter »o.574»^ of tne ^ 3rd Auguat 1V37./ mm * Express Letter (Air Mail). Prom Secretary of State for India To Political p L esident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Political Agent,Muscat, repeated to Political Agent,Bahrein. Bate d 7th August,193 7. No .P.Z. 5114/37 . 2 - 7- Your demi-official letter of the 30th June 1937,Ko.504-S, Prorok. A, Please see letter da^d Both July,co_y by air mail of 24th July No.P.Z.4799/37, requesting permission for expedition into Rub 1 al Khali. It appears that part at least of itinerary would traverse Muscat territory. I should be grateful for your advice as to a reply. The issue of the above has been duly authorised. (3d.) J. C. WALTON,GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Confidential. Department. JBXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— ft a * ORIGINAL message sent la AIR AT 4 TT j expeditious than the or dinar u mnlandi, wh ' ch P rn ''' de * a means of communication more 'cespt, mitk the intended to le treated, forma/ihe* it is dratted in the form of a^tel n b telegraphed. To sace time and to obviate responsible officer of the Department^ '■gram. It is authenticated by the signature of a No. 638-3 of 1937. Buelvire, Dated , (Jie xXiMI 1 August, 193'!. From To Repeated Political Resident, Bush ire. Secretary of state for India, London. Politicel Agent, Muscat, at Ziarat. 0 Polixical Agent, TaHrain, at Zaracni. / Your Express letter No. P.z.8114/37'of tde 7tn August. PSOTOK'. T suggest Prorok be informed as regards Muscat tiiat the Suit,an has already refused him permission for archaeological researches in the interior. since in any case tne party’s security in a region so far fran the coast can not be guaranteed it is impossible to pursue the matter further. 2. as regards the proposal to start from Sharjah, Prorok ca» be informed that the security of travellers using a base on the Trucial Coast can in no case be guaranteed owing to disputes over boundaries and jurisdictions in the interior. Should Prorok continue to press his project, I consider he chould be clearly informed tnat no visa for landing in Muscat or on the Trucial coast will be granted. The fact that ne previously obtained entry to Muscat on a visa granted in Aden suggests / {Signature) S. 44. MFP—1374 S&amp;P—(M-2043)—15-1-36—10,000. (Designation)suggests the propriety of taking steps to ensure observance of the convention that no British passport authority should grant this or other individual foreigner facilities for Muscat, or the Trucial Coast (and I would add Bahrain and Kuwait) without previous reference to the Political Agent concerned in the case of Muscat, Bahrain and Kuwait, or to t.ie Political Resident in the case of tne Trucial Coast• sd* 0. X. Car oe. Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested Resident in the Persian GulfCONFIDENTIAL. / V No * C/122 of 1938. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agent, Bahra in. ^ 2. Commanding Officer, H.M.S. Bideford. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (&amp;). Office of tne Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, on 3ide£o,r*U llT , ^ n Dated 2nh”F6t!yua*iy *19*38; Reference to previous correspondence: Name and Date. Subject. Residency telegram No.T/cO, dated 27th February 1938 to India Office. Visit of Italian warship ERITREA. t i . V' - - ■ r J • '% ■ • »t«- •. * 4 «*- ' ' j. x atj? ft • * /~\ '--V. '\,V ,telegram from To Tt Q n Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Political Agent, Bahrain. Repeated Senior Officer (l) Colombo. Mo. 1251/2 Bated 15th received 16th March 1338. Have you any information whether Italian warship Eritrea intends to visit Bahrain. - SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER - Telegram 'Q' From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. Repeated S.O. (l) Colombo. No. 76 Dated 16th March 1938. Your telegram 1251Z, March 15th. I have no information. - POLITICAL -telegram en clair. From Senior Officer (l), Colombo Political iigent, Bahrain. To No. 0915 Dated 18th received 19th March 1938. Your telegram 16th March undecypherable verify piease/check and repeat. Our telegram of 16th March repeated to Navyntell in Reporting Code on 19th March 1938. - NAVYNTEDD - n(yC*&amp;) Telegrams:— S ^ ^ H K T . • ' AIRGENARCH HABBANIYA AIR HEADQUARTERS, BRITISH FORCES IN IRAQ. Telephone :— HABBANIYA 342. S.10894/6/l/Air.'1 1 . 0 _ Dear ( I have received a letter from Goldsmith of Headquarters, British -forces in Palestine and Trans- jordan, of which I enclose a copy, asking me to trv and obtain from you a copy of your report on Pastori’s activities in the diiif. -fhe question we must ask ourselves, I think, is, are these activities Pastori's activities or Pastori’s alleged activities ? I feel that Zacharia had rather a vivid imagination- and appeared to have difficulty in separating facts from fiction. I take it he is still hanging round the door of Headquarters in Pales bine trying to impress upon those concerned his potential value and the danger Pastori might create for us. 1 found that Zacharia was good at building a house but could never complete even the top storey let alone place a roof on it and for this reason he was most unsatisfactory to work with. Are you going on recess this year ? I expect you are in the middle of the most sticky and objectionable part of the year and even here we have not been spared by the hot weather and have already touched 116° in the shade with a humidity 10$ hi her than is usual. ^ Yours cv*. H. Weightman Esq., The Agency, Bahrain.COPY. n* 6ECn^T_ &amp; r^riSQ^AL. G.s.l/B/P.142. iieadquarters British forces, Palestine &amp; Transjordan, Jerusalem. 8th June, 1938. Subject:- PASTCRI. Dear ^ • to the abovrmentionedT' ^e r have 01 iu®? C h Wi 1 th ^ easard information from London in which they JfpTd!' 3 Uie War Office had no idea thT^ his (Pastori hat activities in the Gulf were so extensive and that reports from other sources (presumably uafth^ he was an adventurer etc, would appear to he entirely b, :L?: k ” “ say ti, “ f ~' «* -«« ' i I bonder ir it would be possible for vnn ?oralt^ 0 2! lot of work for him on this caseT'' ^shoul^have did &amp; as he_is o &amp; ut Jote'fbu^^/loJiucW^senf 6 ^ 8 prove us — ^ - Yours sincerely, (sgd)P. Goldsmith. Squadron Leader J.P. Eomvile, M.B.E., ^ir Headquarters, British Forces in ‘Iraq, Habbaniya.—— Secret. 7 ? D,C, No. C/466 Dated the 18th July 1938 P 1 . ilx you please refer to your Secret letter No 0.10394/6/1/Air.'I* dated the 7th July 1938. 2. Someone must have been pulling Goldsmith's le T . I wonder if he or someone else could get hold of a copy of this terrifying report from the Political Agent, Bah rain, as I personally should be extremely Interested to see it Yours sincerely Squadron Leader J.P. Domvlle, M♦B f Air Headquarters, British Forces in ^raq, Habbaniyah.Secret No. C/251-16/5 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th April 1939. Sir, I have the honour to report that the Italian steamer S.S. 'India' (Lloyd Triestino Line) is expected to arrive at Sitra at 3 p.m. to-day, the 16th April. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ • Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. r, L v The Officer Commanding, H.M.S. Bideford, Jufair.(Original in file 14/4 - page 29) Received under P.R’s P.L. No.C/527 dated 4th October 1939. Secret D.0.No.D.286-W/39 External Affairs department, 20th September 1939. Treatment to be accorded to Italian and Japanese subjects. Dear Major Prior, I am desired to enclose, for information and such action as you may consider necessary, a copy of a Secret demi-official 1 tter from/the Government of India in the Home Department, No. 21/73/39-Political (W) dated the 11th September 1939, which has been addressed to all Provincial Governments and local Administrations in India. v ours sincerely, Sd/- C.A.G. SavidgeSecret, 2.0.No. 21/73/39-Political (V/) Government of India- Home Department. Simla, the 11th September 1939. My dear The policy of Government requires that the utmost care should be taken at present to avoid action which might provoke the Italian and Japanese Governments or influence them towards changing their present declarations of neutrality. 2. Nevertheless, from the Security point of view, nationals of these two Powers must inevitably be regarded with suspicion. The fact that Italy and Japan have not immediately declared war on the side of Germany, does not in itself make them any more friendly towards Great Britain. In India there is reason to believe that some nationals oi both Italy and Japan are actively engaged on espionage work. There are reasons also for believing that, with the removal of male merman subjects to internment cams, the responsibility for hostile activities subversive to the internal peace of India cuid to ner defence plans may have now passed in some degree to neutrals favourably disposed towards Germany and to suborned Bri wish subjects. In the case of Japanese, a further ground, for regarding them with suspicion exists in the expansionist policy of Japan for creating a 'New Order in Asia'. 4. It is, therefore, desirable that the activities of Italians and Japanese in India and neighbouring countris should be kept under close observation by secret Intelligence means. It is equally essential, however, that the methods adopted should oe really secret and unobstruc^ive, and that no executive action should oe taken against Italian or Japanese subjects in connexion with suspected propaganda or espionage activities without fully satisfactory /-X4 - 2 - satisfactory evidence. In cases where action is considered desirable a reference should be made to the Central Govern ment (Home Department) unless the delay involved in such reference would be in itself dangerous, -as might be the case if a question arose of prevention of an overt act of sabotage. Please acknowledge receipt of this communication. Yours sincerely, 3d/- E- Conran-Smith.The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Politicel Agent, Bahrein 2* M *E #1 *0 •, Cairo. 11 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents ^r. for information. /-n 1 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. &lt;i/*' Dated S.th.JBTQ.V.e.mbfi*. 3.939 . 2. Political Residents telegram No.T/441 dated 9th November 1939. Application of Riccio Igiio for vise for Bahrain. ? tTe legram From Q Britconsul, Bushire. To Political Resident, at Kuwait. No.503 Dated and received 8tJi November 1^39. Following from Bandar Abbas No.T/b dated the 7th November for Political Resident begins. Italian subject RICCIO IGNIO geologist and mining engineer age 47 has applied to me for visa for Bahrain object of visit is to try for employment there. He has been working in Persia for seme years with Kampsax. His Passport is in order. Do you approve temporary permit limited to 7 days if he fails to secure employment ? He will return to vlrsn if not successful. Ends For favour of reply direct to Bandar Abbas. We have no information about him here. Br itccnsulTelegram Prom Q, Political Resident, at Kuweit. Britconeul, Bender Abbee. To No .T/441 iteted the 9th November 1 j39, Your telegram No. T.5 November 7th. Permit should not repeat not be granted. Prior G.T.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000399_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/554</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000399</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/554</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 16/5 ITALIAN SHIPPING ACTIVITIES'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-13T14:18:03</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (96 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 2-87 and between ff 88-95 respectively; these numbers are also written in pencil, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence, but they are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence concerning Italian shipping in the Persian Gulf and individuals representing Italian interests. Topics covered include:British concerns about an American archaeologist, Count Prorok, a naturalised American subject (ff 18-72). Suspicions were harboured that he was working for the Californian Arabian Standard Oil Company. The Sultan of Muscat refused to issue him a visa to travel into the interior of Oman.also discussed are the activities of an Italian, Tullio Pastori, recruiting labourers for Eritrea (ff 76-78).visit by the Italian warship,
                              Eritrea, to the Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Byron Khun Prorok de</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Shipping regulations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000399#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>