<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000086_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:51:42.926Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Perso-Afghan Frontier. Report on Hashtadan. Colonel J. W. Ridgeway to Earl Granville. No. 45 (Confidential). Camp Sinjao, My Lord, ' 24th May 1885. I have the honour to submit, for your Lordship’s information, copy of the correspondence quoted in the accompanying list, regarding the disputed Hashtadan lands, on the Perso-Afghan frontier. 2. Hashtadan is a valley about 30 X 20 miles, which, for at least two generations, has lain waste owing to Turcoman raids. Lately a Company has been formed at Mashad, of which the present Governor General of Khorassan is the trading member, for the cultivation of the tract, and two months ago labourers were sent and operations commenced for the repair of the aqueduct in its north-west extremity. The Afghans took umbrage at this and appealed to Sir Peter Lumsden, who referred to Her Majesty’s Minister at Teheran. On the 2nd April Sir R. Thomson telegraphed that the Shah had instructed the Governor General to send an officer with explanations. 3. On the 15th April Mr. Merk was deputed by Sir Peter Lumsden to inquire into the dispute. He arrived at Hashtadan on the 16th, and reported that the Persians had been at work for some w T eeks, but that on the 12th April the Afghans had sent 20 irregular infantry with orders to stop the work; while, on the 15th idem, the Governor of Karaz arrived at Hashtadan with 30 Persian troopers. Mr. Merk arranged that, pending inquiry, the Afghans should retire to Kafir Kala and the Persians to Karez. The ground was then surveyed, and the Afghan claims recorded. No Persian agent had arrived, and therefore the inquiry was necessarily ex parte. Your Lordship * i/'*j u i at o observe that Mr. Merk’s opinion* was in favour * Vide Enclosure No. 8. r* i v a c i i • r of the Afghan claim. 4. After Mr. Merk’s return to the British camp the Persians again began work, and troops were sent by the Governor General to prevent interference with them. Sir Peter Lumsden accordingly addressed Her Majesty’s Minister at Teheran by telegram, pointing out that no agent had been 'deputed in accordance with the Shah’s instructions. He also addressed the Governor General of Khorassan to the same effect, and asked him to cause work to be suspended until the dispute had been decided. On the 5th May the Governor General replied that he was not authorized to discuss the matter, and that indeed no discussion was necessary, as the land was indisputably the property of Khorassan. On 7th idem, Sir Ronald Thomson telegraphed that the Governor General had been desired to explain the Persian claims to Sir Peter Lumsden when he reached Mashad. Sir Peter Lumsden had a con versation with the Governor General at Mashad on 11th idem regarding the dispute, but no conclusion was arrived at, as the Governor General said that the question must be settled at Teheran. 5. On hearing from Sir Peter Lumsden to this effect, I had an interview with the Amir’s agent, Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan, and pointed out to him how inopportune it was to raise the question at the present moment. To this the Kazi assented, but he assured me that the Amir attached very great importance to the dispute, and he feared that, on hearing of the proceeding of the Persians, His Highness would order some strong measures to be taken. Accordingly, on the 13th, I telegraphed to the Government of India suggesting that the Amir should be advised to let the matter drop for the present. 6. Being about to move my camp to the vicinity of Herat, I thought it desirable, before leaving the frontier, to ascertain—if I could do so quietly— 15277. I. 524. A\ he orS1 ^ s ^ c ,°[ the question. I accordingly instructed Captain De Laessoe-Mr. Mcrk being away on another duty—to ride out to Hashtadan and, without appearing to make any formal inquiry, to obtain any infor mation he could pick up on the spot. ^ V. 1 have the honour to enclose copy of Captain De Laossoe’s report, join lordship will observe that its conclusion is in favour of the Persian claim. Without further inquiry 1 do not pretend to form a definite opinion on the subject. ,! 'i( 1 susrgest for your Lordship’s consideration that, if possible, the matter be deferred until the whole question of tho Porso-Afghan fronlier from the vicinity of Kafir Kala to Chali Zagak, and perhaps the disputes in Seisten, can he taken up and decided. There is no doubt that, it this he no done, similar disputes will crop up in other parts of this h ?V UeVeryet demarcated, and where, in consequence of the cessation of Inrcom.-m raids, land has in many directions again become culturable. It seems desirable that the frontier should he laid down as a whole In one officer, and not piecemeal by different persons. 1 have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble servant, J. W. Ridgeway, Colonel, Assistant Commissioner iu charge, Afghan Earl Granville, K.G., boundary Commission. Ac., &amp;c. I I I J I .List of Enclosures with Despatch to Earl Granville, No. 45 dated 24th May 1885. No. i. „ 2 . „ 3. „ 4 . » 5 . „ 6 . „ 7. „ «. „ 9. „ 10 . „ H. „ 12 . „ 13. „ H. 15. From Kwi Snad-ud^lm Kbau to Sir Peter Lumsden, dated 23rd March 1885. lo Nazi Saad-ud-oin Khan, dated 26th March 1885. Telegram from Sir R. Thomson, No. 42, dated 2nd April 1885 ''wUh , „ul'ttt MiniSter f&lt; ’ vFoWign Affairs to H-Britannic Majesty's Minister, Teheran, From W. Merle, Esq., dated 16th April 1885. To Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan, dated 17th April 1885. From ditto, dated 18th April 1885. From W. Merk, Esq., dated 27th April 1885. From ditto, dated 1st May 1885. I elegram to Sir R. Thomson, dated 2nd May 1885. To Governor General of Khorassan, dated 2nd May 1885. From ditto, dated 5th May 1885. Kxtract fi™ Report of Khan Baba Khan to Colonel Ridgeway, dated 6th May 1885 Felegram to Her Majesty’s Ministers, Teheran, No. 65, dated 7th May 1885 * hTmI^h's 10 ’ leltCr fr0m Sir PCU '‘ Lums ‘ len 10 Colond Ridgeway, dated Mashad, „ 16. Telegram to Government of India, No. 549, dated 13th May 1885 „ 17. Ditto to ditto, No. 557, dated 14th May 1885. „ 18. From Captain De Laessoe, dated 22nd May 1885. ENCLOSURES. From Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan to Sir Peter Lumsden, dated 23rd March 1885. A.C.--I have spoken to you regarding Hashtadan, a place near Kafir K*] a where there was some old karezes which hare been left uncultivated, and + t ^ at imder tiie Herat Government- I said that I would write to the Naib-ui-Sukumat of Herat to people that place with the Bismin tribe and from other places, so as to work the old karezes and also begin to repair the fort of Kahr Kala which would enable us to protect that place. If Hashtadan is not colonized, Kaiir Kali cannot be protected. I ha\ e now learnt from the Naib-ul-Hukuinat that a partv of Persians have come to Hashtadan and have begun to cultivate the Lind there, afthoagh Hashtadan is nearer to kuLsan than Karez, which is the eitreme ItW of the Persian frontier. H the Persians take possession of Kvrii- Kala must also be left to them. As the Naib-ul-Hukuma: does not negotiate on frontier matters v-rii any one without your advice, he has asked me to bring the matter to tout notice, :uui to obtain toot permission and advice as » how he should deal with the 1 enama im this mMu. He ask* whether he is to p, i c prevent theiu ;, or whether you wish to do so. 1 therefore' venturi' to write this and to request your advice on the matter to enable me lo reply lo ihe NatKal^Hitkuinac.To Kazi Saad ud-din Khan, dated Tirpul, 26th March 1885. I have received your letter of the 23rd March, bringing to my notice that the Persian authorities have lately taken steps to colonize Hashtadan, a place near Kuhsan, and which you say belongs to the Governor of Herat. As Colonel Stewart and other British officers are now in the neighbourhood, I beg to inform you that the matter will be inquired into as far as practicable. (Signed) P. S. Lumsden, Lieutenant-General. No. 3. Telegram from Sir Ronald Thomson to Sir Peter Lumsden, No. 42, dated 2nd April 1885. Governor General, Khorassan, has been instructed by Shah to send officer to you with explanations as to Hashtadan. No. 4. Prom Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs to Sir Ronald Thomson. A. C.—With regard to the land of Hashtadan-i-Jan and Bakharz, I have the honour to state that I informed His Majesty of what your Excellency said. His Majesty said that those lands belonged, and still belong, to the Jam district, and were never included in Afghanistan, but that on account of want of safety in those parts, they remained uncultivated for some time. As your Excellency is now writing to Sir Peter Lumsden, he will obtain information and send it to you. With regard to the “kanats,” I have to state that, even if the chain of the wells extends to Afghan territory, you are well aware that it is possible for a chain of wells of a kanat to extend from one country to another. In some cases a kanat extends to 10 farsaks. Asaf-ud-daula has also been informed of the above. Of course your Excellency will write to Sir Peter Lurasden and order that no one should interfere, and for information to be sent to you. No. 5. From W. R. Merk, Esq., C.S., to Sir Peter Lumsden, dated Hashtadan, 16th April 1885. I have the honour to report that I arrived here this afternoon. The Persians have been constructing new karezes for some weeks past, with a view to the cultivation of the Hashtadan plain. On the 12th April, 20 khassadars, under Jabber Beg, arrived here under orders from the Governor of Herat to stop work at the karezes, but to avoid a collision. Yesterday the Persian Deputy Governor of Karez and the agent of the promoters at Mashad of the scheme for cultivating Hashtadan arrived here with some 30 Persian sowars. Both Afghans and ^ Asians are located in a ruined enclosure called Kila Kulukh Pardai, close to the old castle of Hashtadan. 1 have arranged with the Afghans and Persians that both sides are to withdraw to-morrow morning to Kuhsan and Karez respectively; that the Persians may leave two men at Hashtadan to take care of wind lasses, &amp;c., which are too heavy to move at once; and finally that neithersideis totefce any steps for the cultivation of Hashtadan for the present and till the receipt of further orders as regards the Persians from Asaf-ud- daulah and as regards the Afghans from the Governor of Herat. The ' ,1 ? ; T ca, , y agreed to my suggestions, informed me that the cultivation of Hashtadan was directed by Asaf-ud-daula, and that the cost and profit of the undertaking is shared by him, the Malik-ul-Tuiiar and the ustachar-ul-Mulk at Mashad, in the following proportions,—Asaf-ud- daulah two fourths, the other two one fourth each. I shall remain to see that the agreement is properly carried out, and then move on towards Koh Charegli, in order to admit of this tract being fully surveyed. I trust that the arrangement I have made is approved. No. 6. To Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan, dated 17th April 1885. Prom a report received to-day from Mr. Merk, at Hashtadan, I am suiprised to hear that, on 12th instant, 20 khassadars were set to stop ail work at the karezes at that place. It is evident that this action mieht easily have provoked a collision with the Persian authorities, and vou no doubt understand how desirable it is at the present time to avoid anv misunderstanding with the Persian Government. You will also understand how impossible it is for me to help and advise you in frontier matters if such serious action is taken without my knowledge 1 shall be glad to receive an assurance from you and the Governor of Herat that no troops will be sent across the frontier in any direction without previous notice to me. In order to prevent collision Mr. Merk has arranged that the Persian sowars, who arrived on 15th instant at Hashtadan, should withdraw to Karez and that your khassadars should retire to Kuhsan pending the inquirv which he is about to make. ^ J (Signed) P. S. Lumsden. No. 7. Prom Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan to Sir Peter Lumsden, dated 18th April 1885 I have received your kind letter, dated yesterday, and have understood its contents. With regard to Mr. Merk’s arrangements that the Persian sowars, who had arrived at Hashtadan on 15th instant, should retire to Karez, and that our khassadars should return to Kuhsan, pending the inquiries which are being made by Mr. Merk, I beg to state that I am very glad to hear this and that the arrangements made are excellent. But I am in doubt whether! by saying that our khassadars should return to Kuhsan, vou really meant Kuhsan, or whether they should retire to their former post at Kafir Kala from whence they came and where they were on duty. I am certain that when Mr. Merk made these arrangements the khassadars must have returned to Kafir Kala to join their party. If your Excellency wishes them to return to Kuhsan I hope you will be pleased to inform me, so that I may issue orders accordingly. No. 8. Prom W. Merk, Esq. C.S., to Sir Peter Lumsden, K.C.B., &amp;c., &amp;c., dated 27th April 1885. In continuation of my letter of the 16th instant, I have the honour to icpoit that the provisional arrangement therein stated was duly carried out on the morning of the 17th. The Afghan khassadars retired to Kuhsan; the Persian sowars went back to Karez; two Persians were left at Killa Kulukh Pardi to take care of windlasses and other implements that were 15277. Htoo heavy to be moved at once; and the Persians and Afghans agreed to to leave matters in statu quo till the receipt of further orders from their respective superior authorities. 2. I would now submit a map of the locality in dispute, with its neigh bourhood, drawn by Sub-Surveyor Hira Singh, together with the result of my observations and inquiries, which latter, according to my instructions, have been cx-parte from the Afghans only. I marched from Tirpul to Kafir Kala, thence to Kuluhh Pardi and via Hashtadan to the Persian villages of Farizna and Karat; and returned to Tirpul by Charkila and Ckashma Dozan. I found Kafir Kala occupied by 100 Afghan khassadars. The plain in front of this post, as far as Dogaru, was at the time of my visit impassable owing to recent heavy rains; and traffic between Kuhsan and Persian territory took, as it generally does under similar circumstances, the southern route via Killa Darband. 3. The tract claimed by both Afghans and Persians is the drainage basin of the stream which, issuing at the Dahana Shorao, flows between Kafir Kila and Dogaru under the name of Kal-i-Kalla, and falls into the Heri-Rud near Toman Agha. The boundaries of this area have been coloured green on the accompanying map. With the exceptions noted below, it is at present entirely unoccupied by either Persian or Afghan subjects. The nearest Persian villages are Parizna and Karat. The area in question consists of a grassy steppe, covered with camel scrub, and having a gentle and uniform slope from the surrounding hills towards its centre. It bears many traces of having been extensively cultivated in former days ; fallen-in karezes are frequently met with, old irrigation channels can still be seen, while the mounds of Kulukh Pardi, Hashtadan, and Char Kila, the ruins of a masonry mill at Dahana Shorao, a large brick reservoir at Kulukh Pardi, and other remains show that a considerable population must have inhabited villages the ruins of which are dotted over this once fertile plain. Its soil is still arable, except where, in the central portion of the basin, a “ kavis ” has been formed in the course of time, the result probably of the ground having become waterlogged in consequence of the closure of the irrigation channels and cessation of cultivation. 4. Although the Shorao basin was once well cultivated, and is still capable of being reclaimed, it is quite clear that for at least two generations, if not more, the whole plain has been waste and unoccupied. It is situated in the very track of Turcoman raids upon the Persian districts of Khaf, Birjand, and Chain on the one hand, and on the other upon the Afghan settlements at Ghorian and Zindijan in the Herat valley, at Sabzawar and Anardarra. Till last year neither Persian nor Afghan patrols could venture to enter this plain, and caravans used the direct road from Herat to Khaf, across this basin between Ghorian and Karat, only by stealth, or under the escort of such of the inhabitants of the neighbourhood as entertained secret relations with the Turcomans. 5. At present the eastern and southern portions of the plain are grazed over by flocks belonging to shepherds from Ghorian, whose tents I found pitched at Chashma Dozan, Chat Nakhchir, Chat Surkh, and Robat-i-Turk. (I may mention here that an unsuccessful attempt was made last year by men df Ghorian to reopen the karez at Ali Agha, in the vicinity of Chashma Dozan.) At the north-western corner of the plain, between Kulukh Pardi and Hashtadan, operations to excavate karezes were commenced about six weeks ago by the agents of a Company formed at Meshed for the reclamation of Hashtadan. As I have already reported, the Persians in charge of the works informed me that the chief promoter of the scheme is the present Governor of Khorassan, to whom falls one half of the profit or loss of the undertaking, his partners being the Malik-ul-Tujjar and the Mustasshar-ul- Mulk at Mashad. The central section of the basin is at present unoccupied in any way. 6. The Afghans claim the whole of the area within the green boundary on the following grounds:— (1.) That in the time of Amir Sher Ali Khan it was settled to be within the Afghan border (principally as regards responsibility in con-neotion with Turcoman raids), at a meeting of Afghan and Persian officials; the Cabul Government being represented by Shaghassi Samad Ali Khan, Governor of Ghorian, and Mahomed Sarwar Khan, Hakim of Kuhsan; and the Persians by Mir Masum Khan Shaghassi, deputed by the Governor of Khorassan. (2.) That when, during the governorship at Herat of Sirdar Muhammad Umar Khan, and about one or one and a half years after this tract had thus been declared to be Afghan territory, Yusuf Khan Hazara (a Persian subject) commenced to dig a karez at Hashtadan, he desisted at once from his project on being prohibited by the Afghan authorities. ' The Afghans who accompanied me to Hashtadan, Naib Muhamad Alam Khan, brother of the Sarwar Khan mentioned above, Naib Khudadad Khan Kuhsani, Nauroz Mirgan Kuhsani, Islam Kuhsani, and others, informed me that in former days the old caravanserai at Dogaru was the point at which the Persian and Afghan escorts of travellers made over or received charge, and where the border patrols were in the habit of meeting. In wet weather, when the direct road was abandoned for the Killa Darband route, the Dahana Sanjiti or Killa Darband itself, as might be most com venient, was the place at which caravans changed escorts, and up to which Afghan sowars patrolled. They also said that Afghan outposts visited the Shorao basin, including Hashtadan, but I doubt this strongly. 6. I would add that the country west of the Koh Charag range is admittedly Persian territory; that the Koh Yalkhar is claimed and occupied by the Afghans,* who state that the frontier is at the Chah Surkh Kotal; and, lastly, that if this Persian claim is approved, and the Shorao basin falls into Persian hands, a wedge of Persian territory will be pushed to within 15 miles of Shabash and 20 milus of Ghorian, separating Kuhsan from Yalkhar and the environs of Ghorian. As the strip of waste country, from 20 to 50 miles in width, which divides Western Afghanistan from Eastern Persia, is gradually being reoccupied, now that Turcoman raids are a thing of the past, similar boundary quarrels seem likely to crop up in the border lands south of the Sharao basin; and without a knowledge of the general alignment of the frontier in that direction, it appears difficult to judge of the effect that the transfer of the whole basin to one Power or the other would have as regards the intrusion of Persian territory into Afghan, or vice versd. But the effect of the occupation of the Persians of the whole basin (I under stand that they claim it up to Dahana Sharao) with regard to Ghorian and the left bank of the Heri Bud is clear. Possibly a boundary drawn from Dahana Sanjiti to and including the Kulukh Pardi mound, thence to the northern extremity of the Koh Chareg, and along its watershed up to the Chah Surkh Kotal, might sufficiently meet the requirements of the case and the claims of both parties. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) W. Merk, Political Officer. No. 9. % From W. Merk, Esq., to Sir Peter Lumsden, dr^d 1st May 1885. Sir, In connection with my report, dated the 27th April 1885, regarding the Perso-Afghan 'boundary dispute at Hashtadan, I have the honour to submit, as bearing on the question, the following extract of M. Lessar’s account of his journey from Ghorian via Khaf to Mashad, given at page 244 of Marvin’s “ The Russians at Merv and Herat.” M. Lessar appears to have travelled by the direct route from Ghorian to Chashma Dozan, and thence across the Shorao basin to Karat. He says :—“ In the broad valley lying “ beyond (evidently a spur of the Chasma Dozan hills) were numerous traces of * Shepherds from Ghorian have pitched their tents at Chah Surkh and Rabat Turk,“ Tekke forays, in the shape of ruined settlements and robats. . . . The “ locality (the broad valley) on the whole is not particularly well supplied “ with water. Near the middle of the road runs a small stream from the “ northern mountain spurs, called the Shorao. . . . At three quarters of &lt;c a mile from Shorao the guide showed me the Perso-Afghan frontier, which, “ however, was traced on the maps considerably further to the east. The “ guide said that formerly, before the country was abandoned by its in- ' habitants, Shorao was an Afghan settlement.” 2. The central portion of the basin* is known as Shorao, and, as I have mentioned in my report, the remains of villages are scattered round Shorao, the karezes converging from the higher and outer edges of the basin towards its middle. If Shorao was an Afghan settlement, it is almost impossible that Kulukh Pardi and Hashtadan should have been held by the subjects of the Shah, since the cultivation of these two villages must have been in the immediate vicinity of Shorao, and since the nearest Persian settlements of Parizna, Karat, and Hindu Kila are situated at some distance, and separated by a belt of steppe from Kulukh Pardi and Hashtadan. 3. In the report to which reference has been made above, I omitted to state that the Persians had commenced to excavate and reopen karezes at Kulukh Pardi itself and a small distance to its north, the general direction of the karezes under construction being towards the centre of the basin, in conformity with the slopes of the ground. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) W. Merk, Political Officer. No. 10. Telegram to Sir R. Thomson, dated 2nd May 1835. Governor, Khorassan, not yet deputed official referred to in your telegram 2nd April to represent Persian Hashtadan question. Desirable he should be ordered to without delay. No decision can be made until he arrives. In meantime, both Persian and Afghan troops were ordered away pending decision; but Persians with workmen have again turned up, and this may lead to difficulties. (Signed) P. S. Lumsden. No. 11. To Governor General of Khorassan, dated 2nd May 1885. A. C.—I have just learnt to-day from the Afghan authorities that the Persians have recommenced work at Hashtadan, and the excavation of karezes at that place. I desire to draw your Excellency’s attention to this circum stance, as the question of the adjustment of that portion of the border is waiting the arrival of an officer to be deputed by you by order of His Majesty the Shah, as communicated to me in a telegram from the British Minister at Teheran dated 2nd April. May I request, therefore, that your Excellency will give the necessary orders for the suspension of the work until the matter shall have been adjudicated ? (Signed) P. S. Lumsden. No. 12. Erom Governor General of Khorassan to Sir P. S. Lumsden, dated 5th May 1885. I have received your letter regarding the Hashtadan land to-day, and have fully understood its contents. * Of map attached to Report of 27th April 1885.9 ^ 2 - * o /A® first P^ce. I am not authorized to discuss the matter, but I write lx this much, for your Excellency’s information, that this Hashtadan is whatever ° f thiS and requires no Action Some years ago, when Major Napier, a British Engineer nrenared a man of hat frontier, which was published in London, lie 01^7 Hashtadan as it ought to have been placed, as part of the Bakharz district and as the soil of this Government. I have got that map with me, and wiU 8 “w it to any person that you may direct. There is no doubt in this matter 7t is 7my (LvcrnmTft 6 col “ion of the undisputed landed property No. 13. Extract from Report of Khan Baba Khan to Colonel Rideewav dated 6th May 1885. ^ At Kafir Kala I heard from Nasir Khan, Sadbashi of the Khassadars that ^ ie Persians have again commenced work on the karezes of Kulukh Pardi H ' Kai \ ez ’ Gh a ffar Sultan, Chief of Karez, who has seen Mr. Merk told me that orders have been sent by Asaf-ud-daula to Yusuf Khan Sartip (Hazara) Governor ot Mohsmabad, to commence the work on the Kulukh Pardi karezes and not to stop ; to send 100 Bakharzi sowars to that place to be always present there; not to stop the work even if the Afghans protested against it; to answer harshly if the Afghans spoke harshly. The Asaf ud daula also wrote to Yusuf Khan to direct the Afghans to discuss the mat'^ t leherau oi at Mashad, and not on the spot. This order was received ten days ago, and the Bakharzi sowars are now at Kulukh Pardi. Ghaffar Sultan with one or two other influential men, and Gul Mahomed Khan son of Yusuf Khan, Hazara, also went to Kulukh Pardi, and returned after the work was commenced. The chief merchant, Abid Kasim Khan, who is in charge of this work, has gone to Khaff to get some labourers for the work. • Ihe work has been commenced for nine or ten days. The Bakhn™ sowars are now at Earmandabad, midway between Karez and Kulukh Pardi where there is plenty of grass and water. They left Kulukh Pardi because there was no water there. uccause No. 14. Telegram from Sir Ronald Thomson to Sir P. Lumsden dated 7th May 1885. Minister Eoreign Affairs now states that it was not intended to send an official to your camp, but to Hashtadan, to meet officer deputed by you to make inquiry on spot. Governor General Khorassan will be ordered to explain Persian claims when you reach Mashad. No. 15. Extract from demi-official Letter from Sir Peter Lumsden to Colonel Ridgeway, dated Mashad, 11th May 1885. You will see by one of the telegrams from Sir Ronald that the Teheran authorities suggested that I should settle the Hashtadan business with the Governor General here. I had a long meeting with the Asaph-ud-daula heic to-day, and entered on the Hashtadan question. I pointed out to him ow peculiar it was that with 700 villages to repopulate and reclaim in Jam “ U d have g° ne out of his way to enter on the cultivation of Hashtadan’ doubtful m tenure, &amp;c. In support of his claim he produced Napier’s map, it 1 showed him that even that map would go against his claim, as the 15277. 0drainage of the Shar An (Sharao) must all go to Afghanistan. He then changed the subject, and said that he had so much to do immediately, that the Hashtadan matter was one that must be settled at Teheran, and could not be done by him locally. I pointed out that it was a matter which at the present time it was very inconvenient to reopen, &amp;c., &amp;c. No. 16. Telegram to Government of India, No. 519, dated 13th May 1885. Kazi seems to think not improbable that Amir may order strong measures regarding Hashtadan dispute. If so, there will be collision with Persians. Could he not be persuaded to let matter drop for present ? Persians continue to repair aqueduct there. (Signed) J. W. Ridgeway. No. 17. Telegram to Government of India, No. 557, dated 14th May 1885. My telegram, No. 549 of 13th May. Kazi says Amir attaches more importance to Hashtadan than to Panjdeh. (Signed) J. W. Ridgeway. No. 18. Prom Captain de Laessoe to Colonel Ridgeway, dated 22nd May 1885. Sir, I have the honour to report that, in accordance with your orders, I went to Hashtadan, on Friday, the 16th May, and returned to camp on Sunday the 18th. Mr. Merk has already reported very fully on the subject of the present dispute, and I shall limit myself to a few corrections and additional explanations. Hashtadan is a valley about 30 miles long by 20 miles broad, surrounded by mountains on all sides, except in the N.W. corner, where the northern and western mountains are connected only by a low range of hills, hardly marking the limit between Hashtadan and the plain in which Shahr-i-Nao and other Persian settlements are situated. The western mountains, generally called the Bakherz mountains, are by far the highest and most important. Prom their foot an even and somewhat steep, three to four miles broad, slope descends to the lower comparatively level part of the valley. On this slope are situated the Persian settlements of Pirizuch and Kardt, and on its continuation beyond the Hashtadan is a line of other Persian settlements. This slope is further important as being the source of all the karezes in the Hashtadan valley. Prom Karat, a small stream carries the surface drainage of the western part of the valley towards Fer- manabad, whereas the drainage of the remainder forms the Shurao, which, beginning near Pirizuch, runs through the centre of the valley, leaving it through the Hahana-i-Shurao, and joining the Heri Rud, N.E. of Dogaru, near which place it takes the name of Kal-i-Kalla, The Shurao is now dry except in early spring, immediately after the rains, The Hashtadan valley is sup plied with water exclusively from karezes, of which a large number exists all starting, as already mentioned, from the slope of the western or Bakherz mountains. When these karezes were in working order they supplied even more water than required for the cultivation of the valley, and the surplus was, through the Shurao, carried down to the Harband-i-Shurao district which, situated four to five miles west of Kafir Kala, was irrigated exclusivelv</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000086_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C49</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000086</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C49</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Perso-Afghan frontier. Report on Hashtadan'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1885/1885</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-29T10:32:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>Following the opening letter, the enclosures proceed in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence for this description commences at f 192, and terminates at f 197, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 5-206; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.Pagination: the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the disputed Hashtadan lands, on the Perso-Afghan frontier. It begins with a confidential letter, dated 24 May 1885, from Colonel Joseph West Ridgeway, Assistant Commissioner in charge, Afghan Boundary Commission, Camp Sinjao, to Earl Granville [Granville George Leveson-Gower, 2nd Earl Granville], Foreign Secretary, London.In his letter, Ridgeway summarises the current dispute, which began in March 1885, when the Persian authorities took steps to cultivate the disputed land, which had reportedly remained uncultivated for two generations. Ridgeway reports that on 12 April the Afghans responded by sending twenty irregular infantry with orders to stop the work. On 15 April, the Governor of Karaz (also spelled in the file as 'Karez') [Kārīz, Iran] arrived at Hashtadan with thirty Persian troopers. Ridgeway states that the matter was only temporarily resolved by William Rudolph Henry Merk, political officer on special duty with the Afghan boundary commission, who arranged that, pending inquiry, the Afghans should retire to Kafir Kala [Islām Qal‘ah, Afghanistan] and the Persians to Karaz.Ridgeway includes with his letter a series of enclosures which document the ongoing dispute. The enclosures are as follows:No. 1 Letter from Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan, agent of Abdur Rahman Khan, Amir [Emir] of Afghanistan, to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, member of the Council of India and Afghan boundary commissioner, dated 23 March 1885No. 2 Letter from Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, Tirpul [Tir Pol, Afghanistan], to Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan, dated 26 March 1885No. 3 Telegram from Sir Ronald Ferguson Thomson, Her Britannic Majesty's Minister, Teheran [Tehran], to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, no. 42, dated 2 April 1885No. 4 Letter from the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs (unnamed) to Sir Ronald Ferguson Thomson (no date)No. 5 Letter from William Rudolph Henry Merk, Hashtadan, to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, dated 16 April 1885No. 6 Letter from Sir Peter Stark Lumsden to Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan, dated 17 April 1885No. 7 Letter from Kazi Saad-ud-din Khan to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, dated 18 April 1885No. 8 Letter from William Rudolph Henry Merk to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, dated 27 April 1885No. 9 Letter from William Rudolph Henry Merk to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, dated 1 May 1885No. 10 Telegram from Sir Peter Stark Lumsden to Sir Ronald Ferguson Thomson, dated 2 May 1885No. 11 Letter from Sir Peter Stark Lumsden to the Governor General of Khorassan [Khorasan], dated 2 May 1885No. 12 Letter from the Governor General of Khorassan to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, dated 5 May 1885No. 13 Extract from a report of Khan Baba Khan, Native Agent, to Colonel Joseph West Ridgeway, Assistant Commissioner in charge, Afghan Boundary Commission, dated 6 May 1885No. 14 Telegram from Sir Ronald Ferguson Thomson to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, dated 7 May 1885No. 15 Extract from a demi-official letter from Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, Mashad [Mashhad], to Colonel Joseph West Ridgeway, dated 11 May 1885No. 16 Telegram from Colonel Joseph West Ridgeway to the Government of India, no. 549, dated 13 May 1885No. 17 Telegram from Colonel Joseph West Ridgeway to the Government of India, no. 557, dated 14 May 1885No. 18 Letter from Captain Albert Frederick de Laessoe to Colonel Joseph West Ridgeway, dated 22 May 1885In his letter Ridgeway makes special reference to the final enclosure, Captain Albert Frederick de Laessoe's letter, which concludes in favour of the Persian claim. Ridgeway suggests that, if possible, the matter regarding Hashtadan should be deferred until the question of the Perso-Afghan frontier can be resolved outright, preferably by one officer.It should be noted that the list of enclosures which follows Ridgeway's letter incorrectly states that item no. 10 is from Sir Ronald Ferguson Thomson to Sir Peter Stark Lumsden, whereas in fact the telegram is from Lumsden to Thomson.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Afghanistan</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Governor of Karaz</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Governor-General of Khorassan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Commissioner, Afghan Boundary Commission</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commissioner, Afghan Boundary Commission</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Afghan Boundary Commission</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>William Rudolph Henry Merk</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Albert Frederick Laessoe De</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Mashad</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kafir Kala</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Karaz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Hashtadan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundary disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000086#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>