<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cd_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-17T11:47:27.219Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">29th December, IS Department, Bo compliments to India Office ( transmit herew pondence in co legislation re Enemy.\ BOARD OF TRADE, ^ GWYDYR HOUSI LONDON, S.W. C. 1866 2 Department, Board of Trade, presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State, India Office (P. Department), and begs to transmit herewith copy of certain corres pondence in connection with the special legislation relating to Trading with the Enemy. 2^th December, 1917.l ^ V xiLHOUDA HESKEL. W.E.Eady Egq. , Secretary, Po'reign Trade Department, ^ Manchester House, London, S.W, • 6 Dickinson Street, Manches ter. 13th December, 1517. ^ ! J I Sir, E.R.H. 1 Hale Baghdad '33 H shipped per s. s .'Air is tan' to Basra, iiOth June, 1914. By this mail I am informed by my Agents, Messrs. Lynch Bros. , Ltd.’, of Basra, that the above bale (part of a large consignment of my goods going out to Bagdad before the war, to be sold there on my consignment account) has been delivered in accordance with Government orders to The Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns on the 27th October, 151 6, I presume at Basra. As I am an English (British subject) I presume these orders have been given in error, and I should be glad of your advice as to how I must proceed for the recovery of this bale. Should this letter not concern your Department, would you be good enough to place the matter into the right channel? I remain, Sir, Yours faithfully, (Sgd.) YEHOUDA HESKEL.(£&gt; ^h,\ny further commiinicatior) should be adc jeed to-- THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, The following letter and number should be quoted:— o. 1866 a JOLASTA, LONDON. WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. Telephone No- •- 3840 Victoria- 29th DacsMber, 1917 Sir With reference to your letter of the 18th December, addressed to the I-'oreign Trade Department, relative to certain which you shipped to Basra before the war for consignment to Bagdad, I am directed by the Board of ^rade to suggest that you should communicate in t.h* matter direct with the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerne, addressing that officer at Basra. I am Your obedient Servant, Yehouda Heskel isq. , 6 Dickinson Street, Manchester.C. 13465. ference Ko.P.4714 ihe Assistant Department, Bo an compliments to t. India Office, an ✓ copy of certain with the special Trading with the 28th December, 1C. 184-65. Bo&amp;rd of T rade G^ydyr Hotis' c 5 l London,, S. TTr . 1 eference No.P.4714 of SCtJ^November^ 191 r&gt; . ^ghe AssietapidSecretary, uorrtnprciai Department, Board of Trade, presents his compliments to the Under secretary o... State, India Office, and begs to transmit herewith copy of certain correspondence in connection with the special legislation relating to Trading with the Enemy.Any further communication should be addressed to— ♦THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted:— °- ^^Ugraphic Address: JOLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No-; 3840 Victoria- BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), © GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. 28th Dec^ber, 191 Gentlemen, I directed by the Bofcrd of Trede to refer to your letter of tne 7th December to the *r 'Irede Intelli/^nce Deoprtment relative to * shipment of worsted y*m Vnich you ptete con^irned by you before the ^ar to Ba^dfd and to state that, po far ap the ^necial legislation reletin/^ to tr^diryr th the enemy ie concerned, the Board **ill offer no objection to your deliv^int the yam to eaere. nuchati Freres of Banded if you are able to obtain JnrirTiineten themof from the Controller of Hostile Tredinm Concern? in Basra, ^ith whom it ie understood that you h^ve been adviaed by the Foreign Office to communicate. I am, Gen tl emen, Your obedient bervant, ipsrp. ersden and hunter, 2 ?&gt;, Cheaneide, BRADFORD.The Assistant Secretary, Comme Department, Board of Trade, presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State, India Office, (p.Dept.) and begs to transmit herewith copy of certain corres pondence in connection with the special(COPY) The Secrets Board c Whj Sir , We to whom we to Bagdad ^ Weborny, E&lt; opened brar Military ci we must obt can be grai The such as are Uniform etc sanction oJ it would be the necesss The(COPY) EDWARD STIIXWELL &amp; Son, Limited, 25, 2 6 &amp; 27, Barbican, LONDON, E. C. J / u The Secretary, ' — Board of Trade, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.l. 5th December 1917• Sir , We are instructed by the Secretary, War Trade Department to whom we have applied for a licence to export certain goods to Bagdad via Bombay, ordered from us by Messrs, Leach and Weborny, Bombay (a very old established firm who have recently opened branches ay Basra and Bagdad for the convenience of their Military customers in the Expeditionary force in Mesopotamia), that we must obtain permission to trade with Bagdad, before a licence can be granted ue. The goods are all Military Uniform Buttons, Trimmings etc, such as are needed by Officers at the front for replacements of Uniform etc, and as the firm in question must obviously have the sanction of the Indian Military Authorities to trade there, or it would be impossible for them to open up a branch, we hope that the necessary permission can be given us. Thanking you in anticipation. We are, Yours faithfully, FOR EDWARD STILLWELL &amp; SON, LIMITED, (SIGNED) K. J. PERCIVAL. Director..*ny further communication addressed to — the assistant secre at the address given opposite. The following letter and num be quoted:— C - Telegraphic Address: COLASTA, LONDO Telephone No.: 3840 Victorii Gentlemen, Wi I am dired the epeci&amp;I concerned, fceeera. Le* An] consigned : duties must to be prese should shof ultimate cc It may at any Basra. Th transport a time and th freight up foodstuffs. Hesere. Kdward ^ti 2b. 26 &amp; 27^.ny further communication should be addressed to — the assistant secretary, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted:— c. 122&amp;3 Telegraphic Address: COLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria. BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. 15th D«c®mtoer 1917. Gentlemen, With reference to your letter of the 5th December, I em directed by the Board of Trade to atate that, ao far a* tv-e special legislation relating to trading with the enemy is concerned, they will offer no objection to your trading with Messrs. Leach and Weborny of Bagdad. Any goods which you may despatch to Bagdad must be consigned in the first instance only so far as Basra where all duties must be paid in full on their arrival, but the documents to be presented to the Customs Authorities in thie country should show that Messrs. Leach and Weborny of Bagdad are the ultimate consignees of the goods. It must be clearly understood that military reouirements may at any moment necessitate the suspension of transit beyond Basra. The Board understand that it is unlikely that rail transport will be available for commercial freights for some time and that it is et present practically impossible to provide freight up the river from Basra for any merchandise except foodstuffs. Messrs. Edward Stillwell &amp; Son,limited, 25, 26 A 27. Barbican. The.The Board ere informed by the War Trede Department that export licences will be required for the shipment to- Bagdad Tie Basra of goods of which the exportation from the United Kingdom is prohibited to all destinations abroad or abroad other than ports and destinations ports and destinations,/in British Dossessions and 1 rotectoratei COPY) The Secretary Commercia Gwydy Vede Department e shipment to* tation from inatione abroad or, s and Drotectoratei Servant, WCOPY) HENRY S. KING AND COMPANY, 65, Cornhill, LONDON. s ^; 13th December 1917. The Secretary, Commercial Department, Gwydyr House, Whitehall. Dear Sir, We have recently received orders for various Athletic and Sporting Goods from our clients, Messrs. Leach &amp; Weborny of Bagdad. On applying to the War Trade Department for permission to ship Fishing Tackle to these clients, we were advised that it would be necessary for us to apply to you for permission to trade with this lirm before licence could be granted. We have had business transactions with this firm for many years at Bombay. They have just recently opened a branch at Bagdad and we were advised by them that they had received permission from General Sir Stanley Maude to start trading. % We shall be glad to have your formal permission to enable us to obtain licence from the War Trade Department. We are, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully. (SIGNED) HENRY S. KING &amp; CO.board of trade, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. With r«f«renc« to your lotter of the 13t»* vecombtr, t cun airectod by tho Jiof'rct of Tr*a* to rticio th*t t &lt;*o far r* ups del le, leletlon rdetlr* to tretflnc with th* enemy ie concerned, they will offer no objection to your tradnr wlt&gt; Kerere. leech end Webomy of Ha«d*d. Any yoode which you mey deeoetch to h^ded wuet be connived in the firet inetenee only eo fer *e neere whpr* ell Outle* smet be peid in full on their errivnl, but the document* to be oreeented to the Cueto«e Authoritiee in thin country should show that »e**re. leach and weborny of H*«ded ore the ultim&amp;tc concifeinee® of the fcoodo* it wet be clearly understood that Military renulroier.tr «.ay at any aeaent neceseitate the sunpenrion of transit beyond Basra. The hoard underatand that it ir urllKely that r * 11 Iranapart will be orrliable for commercial frelchts tor none time and that it ie at present proctlcelly impossible tn provide freight up the river from hasps for any uierchondise psssrs. henry 8. t ing and Company, * X °* T&gt; 65, Cornblll# - 'f * 0 e 3 e ^ny further communication should be addressed to — the assistant secretary, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted :— — 1 Telegraphic Address; t'LASTA, LONDON. Telephone No. 5 3840 Victoria.’tfction fr©m ** port* ©nd *ctor«t#* % rvrnt, Department, Board of Trade, presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State India Office, Political Department, and begs to transnit herewith copies of certain correspondence in connection with the special legislation relating to trading with the ensny. -t 17th Decanter, 1917.ILFORD, Limited. ILFORD, LONDOF, Dec. 12th, ly]7. 'flie Oecretary, Board of Trade, 7 /hitehall Gardens, 3. 1. i.’c have a Concif'nnont of about 11,000 Packets of Photo- graphic Paper to be sent to i r. Victor, Official I’hotographor, J esopot-i dan Ixneditionary Force, Ba ; .dad. •&lt;e have received intimation from the Controller of the London Postal Service, that Parcels addressed to this Opnsi. jneo would be forwarded in the \my Lails; and we are inotructod by the Secretary of tho V^ar Trade Department, 4 Central Buildin,'^, estmineter, S. T. 1., that if you will, grant pcrxiiesion to reauna trade with Bagdad, then our application for a Licence to exioort will be con niderod. /e shall eeteai it a favour if you will grant us the necessary pemiasion in writing, so that we can forward this to the ar Trade ©partraent and obtain the Licence. We are, Sir, Your obedient servants, ILFORD LIMITED. (Sgd.) ? 1-anaging Director.Any further communicntioi addressed to— THE ASSISTANT SECR i at the address given opposite. The following letter and nui be quoted:— 0. 1140 Te^^raphic Address: ^OLASTA, LONDC Telephone No.: 3840 Victoi Gent] me December oo far n the encs your eon in your you to o War IVad oacro. Ilford L Ilford.1- Any further comrnnnicntion should be addressed to— THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted:— 0. 1 140 Te^^raphic Address: ^OLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No-: 3840 Victoria- BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1, 17th Dccaber, 1V17. Gent] gd on, With rcfcrrrico to your loiter of the 12th December 1 m cUrocte '. by the 1 oar?) of Vr do to st^to that, oo far the special elation relating; to trading vith the enemy is concerned, they will offer no objection to your sending the packets of photo* raphic paper mentioned in your letter to ir. Victor at Jingdad. It 'Till, as you arc a;mro, also be nocoecory for you to obtain a liconco to e^ort the pauor from the Var Vrad© !)er&gt;arti -ont# 1 ou, Gent! a:^on, Y ur obedient dcrvmit, ^.gned) H.THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED* 4 Crosby Square, London, E. C. 3* 12th December, 1917. The Assistant Secretary, Board of Trade, (Coinmercial Department), Gwydyr House, V/hitehall, S. W. 1. Dear Sir, With reference to our letter of the 18th September for your information we beg to advise that we are financing a shipment of 5 bales of cottons to Basra. The merchandise has been shipped from this country to Bombay in the s. s. ,! Walton Hall ,, and transhipment will be arranged from Bombay to Basra by our Bombay Branch. The relative documents are to be delivered in Basra to Mr. Saleh S. Sassoon of Bagdad. I am, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, (Sgd.). Manager.1 ^ THE EASTERN BANK-LIMITED, 4 Crosby Square, LONDON. E. C. 3. 12th December, 1917. The Assistant Secretary, Board of Trade, (Comm erc ial Departm ent), Charydyr House, Whitehall, S. W. 1. Any further communication f addressed to-- THE ASSISTANT SECRE' at the address given opposite. The following letter and nnmti be quoted:— 0. 15344 Tt/*(fraphic Address: Vlasta, London Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria Gentlemen Dear Sir, With reference to our letter of the 18th September for your information we beg to advise that we are financing a shipment of 11 Bales of Cottons to Basra. The merchandise has been shipped from this country to Bombay in the s. s. M Mahanada ,, and transhipment will be arranged from Bombay to Basra by our Bombay Branch. The relative documents are to be delivered in Basra to Mr. Saleh S. Sassoon of' Bagdad. 1 am, S Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, (Sgd.) ? Manager. December : of which &lt; S. Sassoor point out firms name 29 th Septe been previ financing refer to t this Depar should in dealing di: than those Board for i Bssrs.The Eastern I 4 Crosby Sour E. ^ . o •1 r Any further communication should be addressed to-- THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted:— 0. 15344 WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria- 17th December, 1917 Gentlemen member for ig a shipment s been shipped id transhipment •anch. The Saleh S. With reference to your tao letters of the 11th December relative to certain shipments of cotton in respect of ’V ich documents are to be delivered in Basra to lx.Saleh 3. Sassoon of Bagdad, I am directed by the Board of Trade to point out that 1 r. Sassoon is not included among the Bagdad finns named in your 1etters of the 18th September and 29th September and that his name does not appear to have been previously submitted by you to this Department. The Board will offer no objection to your financing shipments to lx. Saleh S. Sassoon, but I am to ( 'efor to the letter C.14030 which was addressed to you from t is Department on the 14th Beptanber and to say that you should in future obtain the approval of this Department before dealing directly or indirectly with any Bagdad finns other than those whose names have been already approved by the Board for the purpose. member for ig a shipment 5 been shipped id transhipment ’anch. The Saleh S. pssrs.The Eastern Bank Ltd., 4 Cr * uare. I am, Gentlemen, Your obedient ServantCOPY . A. D. BASSOUS, 4, New London Street, LONDON. E.C. 3. De cemb er 10 th 1917. To The Secretary, , Board of Trade, (Commercial Dep r House t eh all Owydyr mii s rtment), ’ S.lH r . 1. Sir, Please be good enough to let me know at your convenience if there is any objection to my trading with the following firms of Bagdad: Abraham Kashi, Esq., Elyahoo Bassous,Esq., H. Astarabadi, Esq. , Saleh Hayeme, Esq. • Hoping to be favoured with your early reply. I remain, Dear Si r, Your most obedient Servant, (SGD.) A. D. BASSOUS. ‘jT'*Ary further communication s addressed to — THE ASSISTANT SECRE1 at the address given opposite. The following letter and numb( be quoted:— c 17956 Te* j'-aphic Address: COLASTA, LONDON Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria. Sir, With re directed b; special lej concerned, the four f and unders No.C.16610 -A. D. Bassous isq. 4 New London Str^ E. C. 3.% ' 0*% Ary further communication should be addressed to — THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted:— c. 17956 Ter ^Vaphic Address: COLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria. BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT). GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.1. 13th December, 1917. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 10th December, I mm directed by the Board of Trade to state that, so far as the special legislation relating to trading with the enemy is concerned, they will offer no objection to your trading with the four firms in Bagdad named in your letter on the conditions and understanding set out in the Board 1 s letter to you No.C.16610 of the 20th November. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) H. FOUNTAI! D. Bassous Isq. , 4 New London Street, E. C. 3. A&amp; &amp; m % The apcoihpanying communication transmitted, with the compliments of the Secretary to the War Trade Department, to which Department the subject would (Re appear to appertain The Registry, War Trade Department, 4. Central Buildings, Westminster, S. W. 1 NOV 1911); 2 9 NOV..1317 (J 9411.) Wt. 61357—435. 2000. 4/16. D &amp; S. (J 20764.) „ 60053—664. 2000. 3/17. „MARSDEN &amp; HUNTER. Telegrams : MARKSMEN. BRADFORD. Cable codes: ABC 4th &amp; 5th Editions. Lieber’s Standard. .. 5 LETTER. 23 CHEAPSIDE, BRADFORD. Telephone: No. 1869, (Oup Ref. '-28th. 1I0VH. 1917. The Secretary, iVar Trade department. LONDON. ^ ’ Dear Sir, On the 24th. June 1914 we invoiced to Messrs. MOUCHATI FHSRES, BAGDAD, 10 hales Worsted Yarn, G.G.A.C M Bag-dad 3818/3827, to he paid for against documents on arrival at Bagdad. We are now informed that these ha 7 es were transshipped at Bombay from the s.s. T ^1 OF POONaE T to the British India Company T s steamer ^ALAMCOTTA*, and that they were appropriated in December 1916 by the CONTROLLER of HOSTILE TRADING CONCERNS. , We shall be glad if you can give us any information concerning these bales, or x ailing that put us into communication with the CONTROLLER of HOSTILE TRADING CONCERNS, as we do not know his address. If this is a matter which does not concern your Department, please let us know to whomm—~r Any further communioat addressed to— the assistant sec at the address given opposite. The following letter and i be quoted:— 16991. C. legraphic Address COLASTA, LO til Telephone No-: 3840 Viet Sir, With i directed \ special l* concerned, four firm* understanc of the 201 D. Bassous Esq., 4, hew London StAny further communication should be addressed to— the assistant secretary, ! at the address given opposite. BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, The following letter and number should be quoted:— C. 16991. ilegraphic Address: COLASTA, LONDON. WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1 Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria. 23rd Movember, 1917 Sir, With reference to your letter of the 20th November, I am directed by the Board of Trade to state that, so far as the soecial legislation relating to trading with the eneny is concerned, they ’^ill offer no objection to your trading with the four firms in Bagdad named in your letter on the conditions and understanding set out in the Board’s letter to you No.C.16610 of the 20th November. I am, Sir Your obedient Servant D. Baa sous Kaq., 4, Be 1 ? London Street JU.C. 3..16610 elephone No. 140 Victoria (5 lines.) ‘ „ .... . t !oz 7 ' „ The Assistant Secjretary, Commercial Department, Board of Trade, presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State, India Office (P.Dept) and begs to transmit herewith copy of certain correspondence in connection with the special legislation relating to Trading w ith the Enemy. (* (21 NOV 1917 . :*L RESilxP'Rc.CiW .0 ' A ' R£^ 20th November 1917. 7 O/A OBOARD OF TRADE % C.16610. 1 . 3 3 6 (COMKBRCIaL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W. 1. 20th Noyember 1917. ; Gentlemen, ifith reference to your application made through tteaere. Beneon Rowlett Mad Company for permieeion to aend to Bagdad two tone of tin for which you hare obtained an export licenoe Mo. W. T. D. 351224/17 KT, I am directed by the Board of Trade to etate that, so far ae the special legislation relating to trading with the enemy is concerned, they will offer no objection to your trading with Mr. Sion Shlomoo Aboodi of Bagdad. Any goods which you may despatch to Mr. Aboodi must be consigned in the first instance only so far as Basra, where all duties must be paid in full on their arrival, but the documents to be presented to the Customs Authorities in this country should show that fcr. Aboodi of Bagdad is the ultimate consignee of the goods. It must be clearly understood that military requirements may at any moment necessitate the suspension of transit beyond Basra, and the Board understand that it is unlikely that rail or steamer transport will be available for commercial freights for some time. Bassous, Esq., Sew London Street, &amp; • C . 3. TheJ. Rabourdin i 1 The Board ore informed by the War Trade Department that export lieencee will be required for the ehipment to Bagdad ria Basra of gooda of which the exportation from the United Kingdom le prohibited to all porta and deetlnationa abroad other than porta and deatinationa in Britiah ioaaeaaione and Iroteetoratea notwithstanding that auch gooda are allowed to be chipped to Bear* without special licence. (/i C q 2 a LL *-» &lt;u i- rtJ o u (U on on C o s o D a &lt; WOR The export licence which Meeare. Benson Hewlett end Company left at thie Department ie returned herewith. 1 am. Gentlemen, TCLEPHON! avenue 31 AGENTS f D’ELECTRO- de dive PARIS. TAL — 20,000 s »t Dives &lt;C Your obedient Serwant,* No / 147/31 Chief Political Office, Basrah Ceptemher 1917. The Political Secretary, India Office. London 3.W. Sir, In reply to your letter No.p^af/^W^ 1 811 directed to enclose for your information a copy of a despatch which I have tftis day addressed to F.U’s Foreign Office on the same subject. I have your most the honour to he, Sir, obedient servant, fcfTTvrrl &lt;?f 'J'rrxJl 11 f\.l Captain, By.Chief Political Officer. r •O''* \ Or ; f \ \ 1o s ;o. Chief Political Office, Basrah Tih Septenher 1917. TBc Under Secretary of State for foreign Aifairs, London S.W. Sir, With reference to your despatch ho*4 (io744c/J) dated July IBth 1917,1 am directed to state that the 100 sheets copper .(of 16 S.W.G) in question were requisitioned to meet urgent Military requirements. 2 # The value thereof at current market rates viz. Bn.135/- Bombay April quotation plus Bs.2/- freight making a total sum of Bs.32320-16-9 was credited by the ilit iry authorities concerned to this office. 0. This sunt,less certain administrative expenses is held at the disposal of the holder of the relatxve Bills of Lading. 4. A copy of this despatch has been sent to the India office,who have also been addressed on the subject by ressrs.Babourdin and De iclins. I have the honour to be, sir, Your most obedient servant, s b (\T. Captain, ry.Chief Political Officer.Letter from Under Secretary.. Secretary of fptate Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State . Previous Papers:Draft tp Messrs. Pritchard, Englefield &amp; Co JoKQXrU*. ifcy Gentlemen, Adverting to your letter of the 3rd October 1917 to the U.S. of S. for Foreign Affairs, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India (to whom your letter has been transferred for disposal) to express his regret that he is unable to comply with the request of Mr. Smouha for letters of introduction to General Sir F. Maude and Sir Percy Cox. r&gt; • * ’ ^ ^ n , , .in any further communica tv&gt;n on this subject, please quot\ ? i In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote and address— /1D17 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. A 1 R * &gt;3 &gt;i / %r &amp; fey ’ *• The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith mpy j #f the under-mentioned Reference to previous corresponttOtCe*. Ony to kidia I Letter X om ^oreign Ojjice: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ 7 \j L 12 ]P. &amp; O.S^. Uo. S.S. liyanza Port Said, 10th Septr 1917 c/o Mr J• Smouha 18 Princes Street, Manchester. Dear ILr Bell, /ill you please dismiss the matter with Mr Ed^ar, anct ask him to try and pet me letters of introduction from the foreign Office and from the 'flar Office to Sir Percy tox the Political Agent fcr the Gulf, and to General Maude the C Military Governor of Bagdad. The Letters of introduction should be in duplicate and should be forwarded by different mails for safety. I have been advised that I shall need these letters in order to conduct the business of casual Bros, at Bunder Abbas, or to make any decis'ion there and especially wit/ly regard to my investigation of the works on behalf pf the Mashal engineering Co., and my decision as to whetner to dispose of it or otherwise, a letter of introduction to General Maude would be very useful. iou had better get Mr Littlehalss to go to Edgar with you, as he would help you to point out the importance of this business and would see that the whole thing was undertakert in the proper manner to the Foreign Officeand the *'ar Office. It will be pointed out that I have been granted powey* of attorney by Mashal Bros. Ld. and the Aashal Engineering Co. Ltd. to handle their affairs there. Please have this seen to immediately, as I want the letters of introduction sent as quickly as possible. 1/ours truly, J• Smouha. n.S. The Letters should be posted to my Office at Basrah. fat xuT Bell,* % In my further oommunnm- on on this subjeet, pleuAe quote and address— rhe Under-Secretary of State f Foreign Oifioe, London. / *9 The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs present, his compli/nents to the Secretary and, by directum of tHe Secretary of State, transmits herewith ef. the under-mentioned papers- war.— ria—wnwnr «*anr*r« r *****»■ i.», Foreign Office, U- ' 9 , 19*7 Reference to previous correspondence /setter Foreign Office : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. ■ i &amp;■ fU rbej t- - L ^ 8-a 1 oSo^crL /&lt;-; *( 1 OCT 1917; ; Similar letter sent toANTONIO SEFI &amp; C c Telegrams, Sepr, London Tel 2314 London Wall. Code, 57” Edition A B C. oTdvised that been taken ove -sorah. TTe are advl I.ondon Agency 1914,and for Ottoman Bank Military Auth goods had bee The following jji; 10 Packag spares JJM 18 Package -tings JJM !:achi] value ?.!achi: value TTe enclose del re have added current with j charges ,-but 1ANTONIO SEFI &amp; C? Telegrams, 'Sepi* London Tel: 2314 London Wall. Code, 5T” Edition A B C. f A. Q. | H. Bi 8efi. / Blackmore. : 3 9 5 L A. C. ''//s/ff/t. is s.e..pt.e.mb..e.r. iy£&amp; L ‘ -- } * j To the under'oaEPSt&amp;ry 0 f state, (Political C&gt;ept&gt; WHITER A^l^L Sir, We-are advised .by the Imperial Ottoman Bank^gdSd 1 tWohch their a^dad in 1 I I.ondon Agency,that the under noted goods w e had or .hich ^e ?.u.cl entrusted the i il7s of Trading to the Imperial Ottoman Bank for collection, have been requisitioned by the British i military Authorities at ^agdaUjand receipts for the requisitioned goods had been given to the Imperial Ottoman Bank at B a£:c iad. We are d'dvised that the affairs of the Imperial Ottoman b ank at Bagdad have beentaken over by the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns at Bus-' -sorah. The following Machinery has been requisitioned Jj;; 10 Packages containing One 15 BHP Crude On Engine and 2 cases spares shipped per 'Tangistan' invoice value £210- 4-6 JJM 18 Packages containing One 26 BHP Oil Engine and 9' Pump and fit- -tings shipped per ’^^vuistan ,, invoice value £349-14-1 JJM Machinery shipped per 'Avristan' of ^hich no details beyond the value have reached us,-invoice value £23-11-3 JJL Machinery shipped per n Criqua M of which no details beyond the value have reached us,-involve value £191-19-0. I ) We enclose detailed invoices as far as practicable,by which you will see re have added the accrued interest to the 30th inst:,at the usual rate current with clients,also the approximate warehousing and duty charges,-but for the rent w e have no details whatever,and up to the,&amp; naa oihotma ' ^ r s tobno ’ t ~ ft 0 92lvf/5 . ^ -tce - *1 r r Cl 01 *“ jT» Irion ' u 'I -V present have no been asked for rent, nor have ~e paid any. 7e bee apply to you for the payment of the value of our goods •*hlch have been requisitioned by the rilitary Authorities at Bagdad. r.lTe nay mention that todays cost of the respective machinery is at the least 50^ higher than that of 1914 invoice values. sre. Sir, Yours obediently, % Before advice reached us if the requisitioning of the before mentioned Machinery, ve had written to the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns at Bussorah respecting this machinery, as well as further Machinery at Bagdad, also of various sums encashed on our beha^x by the Imperial Ottoman Bank at Bagdad,and for which the Bank had referred us to the Controller of Hostile irfiding Concerns# - t s n■j Vo David Sassoon &amp; C° L T . D /'/ */,/*///. ////w/ E C (C V' y *&gt;/t 13th Septcuiber, 1917. The Under-Secretary of State for India, India Office, S.W. Sir, .F •&gt; 7 12 H-Z 1 i / » .— we have the honour to enclose for your information copy of a letter written by us, in June last, to the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns at Busra, together with copy of the reply thereto which reached us yesterday. The only Symbols of Ownership issued relative to the Goods in question were the Documents to which reference is made in our letter of 14th June, which for the reasonsgiven therein we are unable to produce. It is in the highest degree unlikely that these documents are still in existence. In*the circumstances we beg respectfully to ask that Official instructions may be given to the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns to release the goods in gcoordance with our request. We are of course prepared to enter into an indemnity to hold the Authorities harmless from all consequences of such action,so far as any claims might be made by third parties. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servants, SASSOON A C«., Ltd. Dlreoitfr,Copy of Letter from Messrs. David Sassoon &amp; Co., Ltd., 12, Leadenhall Street, E.C. *6 The Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns B U S R A. 14th June, 1917 'TAMCISTAN” SAILED EROM U.K. JULY 1914 We are informed by Messrs. Frank C. Strick &amp; Co., Ltd., that the undermentioned cargo of ours ex. the above vessel and shipment is now in your hands. The goods in question were shipped by us to the order of various clients in Bagdad, but have not been paid for and are therefore our property, and the relative Documents were sent to our Bagdad Agency in July and August 1914. Our Bagdad Agent is at present in Constantinople, and we have not yet been able to arrange for another member of our staff to take his place. We shall be obliged if you will kindly give instructions to release the said goods to Messrs. Frank C. Strick &amp; Co., Ltd., Busreh, to be sold for our account. PARTICULARS OF CARGC P. B. R. P. A. 3. id . A. 3. h 1C 31 ab s 20 10 10 1 Case Gold &amp; Silver Thread Yours faithfully, David Sassoon &amp; Co., Ltd (Signed) Cecil J. Longcroft. D: Director • •Ho. G u C / 289 . Basra, August, 1917. From the Controller of Hostile Trading Concerns, B U S H A. To, Messrs. David Sassoon &amp; Co., Ltd., 12, Leadenhall Street, E.C. I- 0 M D 0 M. Memorandum. Heference your letter dated 14th June, 191?. four claim for 50 slabs of tin. and one case Gold and Silver thread cannot be entertained, unless such documents proving the ownership are produced.Minute Paper. Department.-Sr yJ' In any further c&lt; on the subject, pleat ko.169736, and address— The Under-Secret Forei The Under IndV 4^' 's&amp;r yJ' In any further communication ?)n the subject, please quote ro.l69736/C/144. and address— The Uuder-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 6 4 8 i ; 3! 7 &amp; Foreign Office S*W*1. September 7 1917. N Sir;- With reference to your letters P.2907 of July 31st. P.3384 of August 29th. and P.3497 of the 3rd. instant, I am directed hy Mr.Secretary Balfour to state that he feels unable to agree to the suggestion of Sir Percy Cox that the Baghdad establishment of Messrs Mashal . Brothers and The Mashal Engineering Company should be regarded as a hostile alien firm up to the date of the British occupation of Baghdad and as a British firm thereafter. 2. Mr.Jacob Mashal appears to have been acting in Baghdad merely as agent and trustee for the two firms, both of which are undoubtedly British, and in the circumstances it seems to him only fair that the business carried on in Baghdad should also be considered British, and that a claim in respect of the property requisitioned by the Turkish Government should be accepted for registration by the Foreign Claims Office. I am, 'r m jJ v o O*' _ \ sir. Your most obedient, humble Servant, , iCOPY. MASHAL BROTHERS LIMITED. Telegram:- T, Mashal, Manchester, A.B.C.Code 5th Edition Telephone:- 4960 City. 12 , Sackville Street, ^ .MANCHESTER. 4th August, 1917. Sir » With reference to the interests of this Company and of the Mashal Engineering Company at Bagdad, Turkey-in i', sia, and to the position of Mr.Jacob Heskel Mashal in relation thereto. This Company was registered on the 4th Oct., 1907 and is numbered 95119. The Mashal Engineering Company, Limited was regis tered on the 10th February, 1912 and is numbered 120185. Enclosed is a list of the Shareholders of this Company. They are 19 in number, 16 of them being English, 2 naturalized English Subjects, and one, Mr. Jacob Heskel Mashal, and Ottoman Subject; Mr. J.H.Mashal’s holding is 1525 shares of £1 each. All the shares are fully paid. Enclosed also is a list of the shareholders of the Mashal Engineering Co., in v/hich you will note that this f Company, Mashal Bros., holds practically half. Of these shareholders two are naturalized English, the fourth being English. r The Directorate is the same for both Companies. The Engineering Company was at first a part of this Company, but as its affairs grew it was decided to form it into a separate Company. This Company had at Bagdad before the war assets to * the value of £2000/£3000, consisting of cotton goods on consignment and sundry debtors in connection with the sales of the same kind of goods. The interests of the Mashal Engineering Company at Bagdad are a charabanc service, which ran between Bagdad i/J and Backcubs, to the north-east of Bagdad on the road toPersia, the plant being four hallford Charabanc and two Argyll touring cars. In addition to this there is a repair shop and engineering works, with an assortment of .nglish ; machinery and tools and stores; unfortunately we are infori: ed that the Turks have taken SO : fo of the machinery and ^ools The six motor vehicles are reported to be safe. With the exception of a brief letter lately to nand, containing little information, neither correspondence nor accounts has been received from the works at dagdad since the 20th October, 1914, on which date the accounts to the 30th April, 1914 were forwarded. A few telegrams have come to hand in the last few months, which are at your disposal for inspection. Owing to difficulties in trading in Turkey for Englisb limited companies before the war, the Directors here decided to have their Bagdad interests held in trust by Mr, Jacob Mashal,' the trading to be done in his name. Conseqi ntly the business of this Company and the Mashal Eng. Co. a Bagdad is known th&amp;re as that of Mr Jacob Mashal. Ihe following is a copy of a minute in this connection:- 'Directors Meeting, Mashal Bros. Lt., ist Aug.,1912:-I 'Bagdad business, question of mode of tradi ^S it 16 ?’ 6 ; 'Proposed by Mr. Birch, seconded by Mr. Littlehales, 'and carried. 'That owing to the trouble and difficulty experience! 'in Turkey and Turkish Dominions for all Limited -uiabi 1 'Companies, which are not registered in Turkey, it wasl 'resolved to discontinue direct trading in tne Company j 'name and to conduct the trading in Turkey by an agenc 'reuresented by Mr. Jacob Heskel Mashal, who is here yI 'authorised to trade in his name, as agent of the Comp&amp;l 'in Bagdad or any other Turkish towns.” The management of Mr. Jacob Mashal at Bagda has been most unsatisfactory and has resulted in nothing but ll especially to the Engineering Company. As a consequence , the Directors have granted to Mr. O.P. Lightfoot, before t| t war the engineer in charge of the works at Bagdad, and no4 resident at Hamsdtn, in Persia, power of Attorney for both companies, authorising him to proceed to Bagdad at the first opportunity and take charge of the works and what re mains of the assets of ..ashal Bros., Lt.The Company holds a letter, written h Mr. Menasht lesxiel I.Iashal as attorney for his brother Jacob, acknowledg ing that the assets of both companies at Bagdad are held in trust by Jacob Mashel, who manages them in his name for their benefit. Mr. Jacob Mashal’s interest is merely his shares in iviashal Bros., Ld., a salary of £2000 per annum as manager, and a commision which consists of 45$ of one-half of the net profit of Mashal Bros., Ld., after 5$ to the shareholders generally. He has no other interests. &lt;ve shall have pleasure in giving you any further information or submitting documents in any connection. Yours faithfully, / MASHAL BROTHERS LIMITED. (Sgd) J.A.NEAL. Secretary. THE MASHAL ENGINEERING COMPANY LIMITED (Sgd), J. A. NEAL Secretary.Mr. Joseph Smouhs (Nat British Subject) COPY. N.B. 51 *f) o 3 00OX E 51. The Mashal Engineering Co., Ltd., Shareholders List. IVIr. Menashi Mashal Present address: Wat. British Subject. Mashal Bros., Ltd., Mr. Elric Birch English Present address: Present address: N.B. 3000 Mr. Joseph Smouhs, Present address: Nat. British Subject. £6102. Baersh proceeding England. 12,Sackville St., Manchester. Belvedere, Bath Bd Bournemouth. 18, Princess St., Manchester. Mashal Bros., Ltd., 12, Sackville Street, Manchester• List of Directors. II Mr• Elric Birch. ( English) Belvedere, Bath Bd, Bournemouth. Mr. B.H.Littlehales, Fairholme, Wilmslow. (English). Mr. Joseph Smouhs, 18 Princess Street, Manchester. (Nat.British Subject) Mr. Menashi H.Mashal Present address:- Baersh, proceeding (Nat.British Subject)England. usual address:- 26, Lansdowne Bd, Lidsbury. The Mashal Engineering Co., Ltd., List of Directors. Mr. Elric Birch. Belvedere, Bath Boad, Bournemouth. Mir. Menashi Mashal (Nat. British Subject) Basrah, Proceeding England. Mr. B.H.Littlehales, (English) ' Fairholme, Wilmslow. (representing MashaL Bros. Ld.) 18, Princess Street, Manchester.TELEGRAM EROM SIR P. COX, .DATED 16th JULY 1917. (Received India Office 11.50 a.m, 17th July ) 2634. Application has be©n made nere on behalf of Lugard Brothers who claim to be British firm with head office at Manchester in respect of machinery goods etc. commandeered by Turks from bagdad branch which seems to have operated as a Turkish concern and whose manager, Jacob R.Ma^shal was a Turkish subject. Part of commandeered machinery, etc. now in hands of our military authorities and part taken away or destroyed by Turks. In many cases receipts were given Marshal by Turkish authorities whereas they granted none in case of British firms. Supposing that attitude of Manchester firm has been correct since beginning of war, I would suggest treating Bagdsd Branch as hostile alien firm up to date if our occupation and as British firm thereafter. Practical effect of such treatment would be that no claim against Turks would be admitted for registration by Foreign Claims Office and any property commandeered by Turks and captured by us would be considered lawful spoils of war and remain our property while firm would start business afresh as British firm with effect from the date of occupation. o Addressed Secretary of State and repeated tte* Foreign.potkl ;?J OF’1M. 3. .1. 1917. ( ! I ata directed by Mr. 3ecreti ry Belfmr to tnuiarnlt to you herewith a copy of e latter fxtxn Messrs. J*B&amp;bourdln and Demollns respectln^&gt; one hundred sheets of copper of French ori in shipped liO^i Antwerp to Bf sra on the B.3. *Taiigist«' n* before the war* and to request that you will furnish a report as to the circumstances In which these feoods were taken over and the presexit position rega rd in*, tnaai* I am, dir. Your most obedient, humble 8erv nt, i Lieutenant Colonel Sir P.Cox nc •, •, Basra&amp; All Quotations subject to Market Fluctuations. J. Rabourdin &amp; Demolins. TELEPHONE, Avenue 3115. AGENTS FO SOCIETE D ELECTRO-METALL DE DIVES, PARIS &lt;5y, SjlacecAfi t. c/i ETALL |c,RECEIVED Capital — 20,000.000 Fns Works at Dives (Calvaoosi. A ns. 7 JUL1917 nc/oWj e.C. 3. jily 6th, lei' The BOARD OP TRADE, 'Trading with the ENemy Act, Sir I 2851 isory Committee' Parliament Street, S.W, kov: Re« Car go shijpjped from Ant werp to BASRA Jlz. SqS, 'TANGISTAR w a consignees Meaere SCHAMASEK GOURGE &amp; COo In July 1914 a few«eks before the declaration of \ War,100 Sheets of Copper were shipped at Antwerp to the above consignees* We learn from Messrs P. STRUCK A Co, Shipowners, of Leadenhall Street E*C* that these Goods have been discharged at Mahammarah and taken over by the Con- -troller* We should feel much obliged If you could supply us with any informations concerning the above or if you could direct us to the Department which deals with these matters*Copy. C. 10582. (131482). C\ ostv Board of Trade, (Connaercial Department), Gwydyr House, T/hitehall, London, S.W.,1. 2nd July, 1917. Sir, I a.n directed by the Board of Trade to refer to your letters Ho. 109650/C of the 14th June, No. 118105/0 of the 16th June, Ho. 117172/C of the 18th June, Ho. 1229^1/C of the 23rd June and Ho. 123805/C of the 26th June on the subject of the resumption of trade with Bagdad with regard to the firms in respect of whom ^.ord Robert Cecil desires to learn whether they may be considered as 'approved' firms for the purpose of such trading, I am to state that the Board's information is as follows:- Of the seven firms named in the penultimate paragraph of your letter of the 14th June, ilessrs. E. D. Sassoon, 17, St. Helens Place, E.C., are merchants trading with the East Indies, China, etc. They were established in London in 1887, and have houses also at Manchester, Bombay, Calcutta, Shanghai, and Ho g Kong. They are in a large way of business, and of undoubted reputation and good credit. Messrs. Charles I. Sassoon ond Company of Manchester are merchants trading with the East Indies, China, The Under Secretary of State, FCRLIuN C 'TICE.China, and Persia* They were established in 1882, are in a ^ood way of business and quite respectable. Hr. H. A. fanklyn of 17 Manchester Avenue is.a general merchant and ajent and represents French manufacturers of brushes. His firm was established in 1884, is considered respectable and is doin^ a moderate business. Messrs. Pocock Brothers of Southwark Bridge Road are shoe manufacturers. They were established in 1852 are in a very good way of business, are respectable and of good credit. Messrs, a. Picard and Company of 45 Great Marlborough Street, are iron and steel merchants aid motor and engineering Contractors. They were established here in 1911 and have a house in Paris, The firm are in a good way of business, and respectable and of good credit. They are presumably a French firm. Mr. Picard is the resident partner in London of the firm of Gustave Oppenheimer of Paris, and he is trie Honorary Secretary of the French Relief Committee. The Board consider that all the above named firms may be regarded as 'approved 11 firms for the purpose of trading with Bagdad. With regard to Messrs. J. Taylor and Sons of Manchester, I am to say that it is not cdear which is the firm referred to, and to request that the Board may be informed of the full title and address of the firm in question. As regards Messrs. J. Bolzani and Company of Bradford, I am to say that the case of tnis firm has been considered by the Advisory Committee under trie Trading with the Enemv Amendment Act 1916 and I aiu to enclose %/ a copy of a note of the Recommendation made by that Committee. A supervisor of the business was subsequently appo in tedappointed by the Board, and, since the consideration of the case, Lr. Bolzani, has been prosecuted and fined for making a false representation for the purpose of obtaining a licence to export goods. The Board do not consider that Messrs. J. Bolzani and Company should be regardeo. as an 'approved' firm. With reference to }/our letter of the 16th June, I am to say that Messrs. David Sassoon and Company Limited of 12, Leadennall Street, E.C., are merchants and bankers trading with the East Indies, China, and Persia. They were established in London in 1860 and registered as a Company in 1901. They have houses also at Manchester, Hong Kong and Bombay. They are considered as a first class firm, are in a very large way of business, of undoubted reputation and of the highest credit, and they should unquestionably be regarded as an 'approved' firm. Enquiries are being made with regard to the firms referred to in your letters of the 23rd and 26th June. In connection with the general question referred to in your letter of the 14th June, I am to enclose copies of correspondence on the same subject which has passed between the India Office and tms Department together with copies of letters which the Board caused to be sent to the Commissioners of His majesty’s Customs and Excise, and to Messrs. Selim Homsy aid Company who are one of the firms mentioned in your letter of the 14th June, and I am to say that,, in order to avoid the possibility of duplicate i and even diverse decisions, it would app ar to be desirable that the task of iving permission to firms in this country to trade with Bagdad should be undertaken by one Department only. I an further to suggest, for Lord Robert Cecil’s consideration, that where the question at issue relates solely to ti'B status ard reliability of firms in the UnitedUnited Kin ;: jiom, the most appropriate Department for the purpose would seem to be the board of Trade rather than the Foreign Office or the Foreign Trade Department, and that where (as in the cases referred to in your letters of the 23rd and 26th June) questions of the status of firms in Bagdad as well as of firms in the United Kingdom are involved it might also as a natter of convenience be left to this Department to send the reply after consulting where necessary the India Office. I am however to say that the Board will of course be glad to consider any arguments in favour of the announcements to the firms being issued by your Department or by tie Foreign Trade Department should Lord Robert desire to advance any. A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. I have, etc., (Signed) H. Fountain.DRAFTTelegraphic Address; ' PUBLIC TRUSTEE, LONDON.” Telephone : HOLBORN 2400. Any further communication on the subject of t^^Viter should be addressed to— “ The Public Trustee (Trading with the Enemy), Kingsway, W.C. 2,” and the heading “ Trading with the Enemy,” and anv additional reference, should be quoted. PUBLIC TRUSTEE OFFICE, KINGSWAY, LONDON, W.C. 2. 9th July, 1917. N.B.—Please quote the) following reference “Trading with the Enemy- Ref erence Lo. 695. Sir, In reply to your letter o r the 3rd instant, I am directed by the Public Trustee to say that the suggestion made in the penultimate paragraph of your letter of the 3rd instant to the Foreign Office your reference P. 2665, is quite satisfactory,as it will ensure the . :aking of any alterations in the quarterly summary returns from India which may be necessary in view of the settlement of accounts between Indian subjects and Baghdad 1 am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, /C PrincipaL C1erk. be Under-Secretary of State, (Political Department), India Office, S.V/. 1.With reference to your letter P.2665 of the 3rd instant, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to inform you that he concurs in the reply which Mr. Secretary Chamberlain proposes to make to the Viceroy of India in respect of payments to Baghdadi Traders, subject to tne concurrence of the Public Trustee, with wnon hr. Bali our presumes your Department will communicate direct on tne I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.rrr In any further communication on the subject, please quote No. 127721/C and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 27 i 3 imm e diate Foreign Office S.W.l. July ,1917. Sir: - With reference to your letter No. P.2476 of the 27th ultimo relative to the resumption of trade with Baghdad I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to inform you that he concurs in the suggestions contained therein in regard to unapproved firms who may in the future make enquiries on the subject. Mr. Balfour also concurs in the proposal that all questions arising in this connection in regard to trade between India and Baghdad should be left for decision by the Government of India in direct communication with Sir Percy Cox. In regard to the suggestion contained in the last paragraph of your letter under reply to the effect that Mr. Secretary Chamberlain should instruct Sir P. Cox to furnish lists of 'approved firms' at Baghdad with v/hom British Merchants may be authorised to trade, I am to state that Mir. Balfour would be glad if some action in the sense indicated were taken, but would suggest that it should be left to Sir Percy Cox to decide whether it would be simpler to furnish a list of approved firms or a list of firms in Baghdad with whom British mer chant The Under Secretary of State, India Office..merchants should a pt trade. As enquiries in regard to Baghdad firms are constantly reaching this Department Mr. Balfour would he glad if instructions could he sent to Sir P. Cox hy telegraph. I am Sir Your most obedient, humble Servant/ further communication should bo addressed to— THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, ■ at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted:— 0. 10582. ^•^legraphic Address: COLAST A, LONDON. Telephone No-: 3840 Victoria- Sir, &amp; BOARD OF TR/COE, f J, P. C* N (W (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, I WHITEHALL, / s / j :• I ' / LONDON, S.W. 1. 2nd July 191?. With further reference to your letter of the 12th May, (ho.P.1873) and to previous correspondence relative to the resumption of trade with Bagdad, I am directed by the Board 01 i.rade to transmit herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a letter on this subject which the Board have caused to be addressed to the Foreign Office. T I have the honour to b Sir, Your obedient Servant, Copy to India Under Secretary of State India, f Political Bepc-iment, IhBIA OFFICE.&lt; Any further commnnica addressed to— THE ASSISTANT SE&lt; at the address given opposite. The following letter and be quoted:— O- 10582. ^^^legraphic Addrest COLAST A, LON Telephone No-: 3840 Vic Sir. I am direc No.109650/C of No.117172/C of No.123805/C of with Bagdad wi Cecil desires firms for the information is Of the sqm letter of the l.C. are merc± were establish Bombay, Calcut of business, t Messrs. Charle trading with i in 1882, are : Mr. H. A. The OPFICiAny further communication should be addressed to— THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. BOARD OF TRADE, The following letter and number should be quoted:— i (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), C. 10582. GWYDYR HOUSE, legraphic Address: COLAST A, LONDON. WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1 Telephone No-: 3840 Victoria. No-; 3840 Victoria. Sir I am directed by the Board of Trade to refer to your letters No. 109650/C of the 14th June, No.118105/C of the 16th June, No.117172/C of the 18th June, No.122931/C of the 23rd June and No.123805/C of the 26th June on the subject of the resumption of tradi with Bagdad with regard to the firms in respect of whom Lord Robert Cecil desires to learn whether they may be considered as ’approved” firms for the purpose of such trading, I am to state that the hoard’s information is as follows:- Of the seven firms named in the penultimate paragraph of your letter of the 14th June, Messrs. E. D. Sassoon, 17 St. Helens Place, E.C. are merchants tradii \3 with the Last. Indies, China, etc. They were established in London in 1887, and have houses also at Mancheste; Bombay, Calcutta, Shanghai, and Hor^ Kong. They are in a large way of business, and of undoubted reputation and good credit. Messrs. Charles I. Sasoon and Company of Mancester are merchants trading with the East Indies, China, and Persia. They were establis in 1882, are in a good way of business and quite respectable. *r. H. A, V/anklyn of 17 Manchester Avenue is a general merchant of State, and# Vfn and agent and represents French manufacturers of brushes. His firm was established in 1884, is considered respectable and is doing a moderate business. Messrs. Pocock Brothers of Southwark Bridge Hoad are shoe manu facturers. They were established in 1852 are in a very good way of business, are respectable and of'good credit. Messrs. A. Picard and Company of 45 Great warlborough Street, are iron and steel merchants and motor and engineering Contractors. They were established here in 1911 and have a house in Paris. The firm are in a good way of business, and respectable and of good credit. They are presumably a French firm. r. Picard is the resident partner in London of the firm of Gustave Oppenheimer of Paris, and he is the Hon. becretary of the French Relief Committee. The Board consider that all the above named firms may be regards as 'approved” firms for the pumose of trading with Bagdad. ;ith regard to Messrs. J. Taylor and Sons of Manchester* I am to say that it is not clear which is the firm referred to, and to request that the Board may be informed of the full* title and address of the firm in question. As regards Messrs. J. Bolzani and Company of Bradford, I am to say that the case of this firm has been considered by the Advisory Comnittee under the Trading with the Lnemy Amendment Act 1916 and I an l am to enclose a Committee. A i thj^oard, and, been prosecuted purpose of obtai consider that Me 'approved” firm. ^ith refer an Messrs. David Sa are merchants anc They were establ 1901. They hav&lt; They are considej business, of und( should unquestior being made with ] 23rd and 26.th Jur In connectior of the 14th June, subject which has together with cop Commissioners of Homey and Company the 14th June, an Implicate and eve:I is doing a ;hoe manu- iry good way • torough btreet, ; Contractors. i Paris, e and of good jard is the nheimer of Paris, dttee. •ns may be regardei gdad. inoijester, I am ; to, and to le and address of •adford, I am to the Advisory .ct 1916 and I am am to enclose a copy of a note of the rteco^endation made by that Committee. A supervisor of the business was subsequently appointed by tb — oard, and. since the consideration of the case, Mr. Bolzani has Je9n P r08ecut e d fined for'making a false representation for the ouroose of obtaining a licence to export goods. The Board do not consider that Messrs. J. Bolzani and Company should be regarded as an 'approved' firm. With reference to your letter of the 16th June, I am to say that lessrs. David Sassoon and Company Limited of 12 Leadenhall Street, iS.C. are merchants and bankers trading with the East Indies, China, and Persia. Ihey were established in London in I860 and registered as a Company in 1901. They have houses also at Manchester, Hong Kong and Bombay. They are considered as a first class firm, are in a verj-large way of businesr, of undoubted reputation and of the hi^iest credit, and they should unquestionably be regarded as ah 'approved' firm. Enauiries are being made ith regard to the firms referred to in your letters of the 23rd and 26.th June. In cjnnection with the general question referred to in your letter Of the 14th June, I am to enclose copies of correspondence on the same Object which has passed between the India Office and this Department together with copies of lettere which the Board caused to be sent to the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and Excise, and to Messrs. Selim Homey and Company who are one of the firms mentioned in your letter of tbe 14th June, and I am to say that, in order to avoid the possibility of duplicate and even diverse decisions, it would appear to be desirableru. T,at4^r from ^ ^V-KVv-v that the task of giving permission to firms in this country to trao* with Bagdad should be undertaken by one Department only. I am further to suggest, for Lord Robert Cecil's consideration, that where the question at issue relates solely to the etatus Mid ^ . reliability of firms in the United Kingdom, the most appropriate . . Department for the purpose would seem to be the Board of Trade rather than the Foreign Office or the Foreign Trade Department, and that where (as in the cases referred to in your lettersof the 23rd and 26th June) questions of the status of firms in Bagdad as well as of firms in the United Kingdom are involved it might also as a mat.,er of convenience be left to this Department to send the reply after consulting where necessary the India Office, I am however to say that the Board will of course be glad to consider any arguments in favour of the announcements to the firms being issued by your Department or by the Forei^i Trade Department shod Lord Robert desire to advance any. A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Under Secretary.. Secretary of State. / Committee Under Secretary .. Secretary of State. ,fr ?neri) Ji FOUNTAIN. Preirious Payers7-r COPY OF TEL LJ Uo Fkom Viceroy, Commerce &amp; .Lficlugt] Dated 23» 6 . 17o Kjjx ^ived at India Office 7 ——rZ. 72C0o Return of eneny property include amounts due fcy Indian firms to Baghdadi merchants. Firms ask permission to discharge liabilities in Baghdad. &lt; May we give L *■« «■&lt; permission in such cases ti miin^rtnd. b&gt; (?, v telegrams dated 11th ?&gt;Jay and 11th June^notifying Public Trustee of details, k/e presume that Indian creditors may ’ now accept payment from Baghdad fen satisfaction of claims. Returns will be dul^ amendedoIn any further communication on the subject, please quote and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 122998/C. Tmrn pdlate . • (VfO. With reference to the letter from this Department No. 109650/C of the 14th instant, 1 am directed by hr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a letter from the Eastern Bank Limited stating that the Chief Political Officer at Basra is of opinion that they should not defer repayment from their Baghdad Office of the amounts owing by that branch on current accounts and fixed de posits and enquiring whether this Department has any objection to their instructing their manager to make such payments accordingly. 2. Mr. Balfour proposes to inform the Bank that he sees no objection to this proposal and 1 am to en quire whether Mr. Secretary Chamberlain concurs in this view. Trni ^ediate . • MO. 1 am Sir Your most obedient, humble Servant The Under Secretary of State, India Office.copy&lt; (122998) Sir, The Eastern Bank Biraited, 4, Crosby Square, London, E.C. Bagdad. 20th June,”* 1917. o c p n i D B ! ,I / As advised to you in our letter of the 15th ultimo our Branch in Bagdad has been re-opened and we are now acting in that City as Bankers to the Government of India. We intimated to our Manager in Bagdad that we nad advised the British Government here that the Turkish officials had appropriated all securities and valuables in the Bank’s possession in Bagdad, whether belonging \ to the Bank or in their custody, and asked him to arrange to postpone all payments and claims until after the con clusion of the War, acting so far as possible with the concurrence of the British Government representatives. The following telegram dated yesterday was received this morning from Basra:- 'In order to ensure public confidence in administra- 'tion Chief Political Officer does not approve 'that we defer payment deposits Bagdad. Telegraph 'quickly instructions.' This matter has been placed before our Directors and they are willing to comply with the wishes of the Chief Political Officer should you be of opinion that this is advisacle and we propose telegraphing to our Bagdad Manager authorising him to repay the amounts owing by the Branch on Current Accounts and Eixed Deposits but The Under Secretary of State for Eoreign Affairs, Foreign Office, S.W. 1.but before doing so we shall be glad if you wi^.1 kindly confirm tnat this is in accordance with your wishes. We might mention that the amount involved that we may be called upon to pay,, reaches some eleven tnousand pounds but our claims against the Turkish Government and our customers exceed by a great deal the above mentioned sum. A statement of the Bank’s claim against the Turkish Government has been lodged with the Director of i'oreign Claims Office, our last communication being dated 25th April 1917. I am, etc, (Signed) Manager&gt;r June, 1917, -tha .^ubjec^ of—tmoo mth iia/rh^nd y in which you raise the question of 'approved firms' at Bagdad, 1 am to explain that Mr. Chamberlain’s telegram to the Government of India of the 11th June, to which you refer, merely purported to give effect to what appears to be the clear intention of the 3rd paragraph of the War Office letter of the 5th May, 1917, No.121/Trade/1378 M.I.6.A., copy of which is enclosed herewith. So far as concerns trade between India and Baghdad, Mr. Chamberlain is oi opinion that the question as to what constitutes an approved firm, and what steps should be tahen in order to ascertain whether or not firms are approved, may be reasonably left for decision by the Government of India in direct communication with Sir Percy Cox. As regards trade between Baghdad and the United Kingdom Mr. Chamberlai: would be prepared, if Mr. Balfour or Foreign Trade Department think it desirable, to instruct Sir P. Cox to furnish this Office with lists of 'approved firms' at Baghdad, which ie ( 011150 ) Wt.W 10588 H35 6 50,000 11/ Aji.y further subject shoul^Ur^uressed to— ^iV Secretary, War Office, Londo and the following number quote (A&lt; hA The to and is C( informatii a copy c the subje(019150) Wt. W10588 H35 6 50,000 11/16 J. P. &amp; Co., Ltd. H16/1433 \ Any further cBg^JfSwieation on thin subject should her j»4aressed to— ( Secretary, War Office, London, S.W., and the following number quoted. IX I ’ LC*J }\0 Form No. 3 1: WiR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W., m ■ i b 191 i i &lt;1.U The Secretary of the War Office presents his compliments and is commanded by the Army Council to transmit for ^he f*- a copy of the document noted in the subjoined schedule on the subject of cs, ^r v ° -iJUIn any further oommunication on the subject, please quote N °- 117172/C and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir, (V?) I am directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to acknowledge receipt of your letter P.2320 of the 12th instant, transmitting copies of telegraphic correspondence with the Viceroy of India relative to the question of trading with Baghdad. 2. Mr. Balfour notes that you have informed His Excellency that permission to trade with Baghdad is to he confined to approved firms both in India and in Baghdad itself. Mr. Balfour would he glad to learn what exactly is intended hy 'approved finns' in Baghdad, and. who is to decide which firms are approved and which are not, and what steps should he taken in order to ascertain whether or not firms are approved. 3. In this connection I aim to refer to the Foreign Office letter of the LO ~ mstarrt. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, The Under Secretary, of State, India Office. h/and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 1C9650/C Sir, With reference to your letter P.187 3 of the 5th instant I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a model draft which it is proposed to address to firms who enquire whether trade with Bagdad is now permissible. I am to explain that the accompanying draft will he sent only tt&gt; firms concerning whom the Board of Trade have first been consulted and who are approved | by that Department. Other firms will be informed that Bagdad cannot be declared to be in friendly occupation within the meaning of the proclamation and that therefore trading cannot be permitted. I am to add that Messrs Shasha, the firm referred to in your letter of the 12th ultimo, are not approved of by His Majesty's Government and have accordingly been informed in the sense of the preceding paragraph. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant The Under Secretary of State India OfficeNo. 104512/0. Draft. Foreign Office., June 1917. With reference to your letter of the relative to your desire I to trade with Baghdad, I am directed by Lord R # Cecil to inform you that although Baghdad cannot actually he declared to be in friendly occupation within the meaning of the Proclamation of February 16th, 1915, there is no objection to your trading with that city, making payments there etc., 2« Goods should however, only be consigned as far as Basrah in the first instance, and it must be clearly understood that military requirements may, at any moment, necessitate the suspension of the transit of goods for trade purposes. 1 1917 Gentlemen,In any further commumoa- , |((U on this subject, please quote /dfii'6 a® 17 J »ncl address— The Under-Secretary of State^ Foreign Office, London, f (£) s * The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for cUck and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop lCo of the under-mentioned papers Foreign Office, i, , 1917 . Letter to 'frrrm. Reference to previous correspondence Foreign Office : P * !O 2 J Ouf 1 Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. lu ■ 7i\e/tMteu/Zlc^ ^ Zje^oJtCi 9u d /^Oy 3/ !'U) tcUiaU*-r~ ^ °Ui ■105356/J I Pi Aire U:n Office 5.W.1 May 3in 1917 a .-.3 ■ 31 r ( I m directed oy Lord ^ooert Cecil to idcnow- the receipt of your letter of the ^th Ineti at on the mihjoct of soode ahltnofl from Mesopotetnla in 1A4 which i re at miseut in Vno Prise Court um\ to exorase hie thaake for the very clear and useful atatefsent which aaeompanied your letter mvi which ie now he lag forwarded to ;3ir Percy Cox In order that Din ihaamUwt on the various shippers &amp;c, of these goods may be obtelned. I am at tho aerae time to transmit to you co &gt;ies of the corroeoondence noted in th&lt;? m rf;in. A letter, similar in term to that aiifressed to rs* Frederick luth and Company, tu s also boon sent to ‘laears* U **lamuel and Company A delira H-xiaey and Comprpy; Incu, Colt, I nee and toscoe; T!ie teat era Bartr Limited tel sears* licit aana and Company' t who have from time to time applied to this departns.it for InfoitMtion ae to the treatment of those goods. I am. Sir, Your , o x»di m hum »le Servant, Majesty 1 ?? Procu ra Uor Gene r^l ,Nc.3 J5356/J) PICS. 5. .1 May :;ist 1917 3ir, With raforeace to your tale, ns, Mo.??!-? of the 3rd Initi nt, and irev lou ! corresion leoce respoctln;; the t reatnoat of goods shi^iad from Mesopotamia to this country oafore the outoreek of ».ar with Turkey, I an diractad by Lord ‘looert Cecil to transit o you for your Iulo( ruction, the accompailiyini co )i»j8 or letters from the Indlr Office am the Procurator 9 #mm| on tho ^uuject. You rill gather from thin correspondence that it he n been decided to continue the proceedings in the Prize Court in reapoct of those goods, end that due consideration will thereafter be accorded to the el* imanta in deservia cases. In order that His Majesty 1 s Government may be iu possession of info laetion which would enable them to deal with tho rth tter on these lines a schedule pi the clr* lias has beeu ore pared by the Procurator General and forms an enclosure to his 1otter. I should bo 4 i? :5 if you vmld bccordiiuly famish mo wttll a left as reger. i© merits of f shipoers of the various con ^iuinents, and the / other persons in Mesopotamia mentioned as interested, shownf ' AND CXMPAinr t 12, Tokenhouse Yard, E.C.2. London, 23 d. Iiay 1917. alr 4 1917' 1 I - J _apnrij ji m ents of Produce Ito.a form cciod, by Persians ajid others to tids country, for. x^isation. Referring to our correspondence on this subject which culniin.^ted in your reply of 23rd. April (No.79544/J) we should like to place on record the case of Iiaji Abdul Hussein liahrany in the hope that it may receive favourable consideration at the hands of the British Government. In September 1 14 this person intended shioninj to us HA77 Bales Wool per B.B* ,, Arum ,, , the steamer however left Busreh without taking any cargo, and eventually, towards the end of October, the wool was shipped by the 'Linar&amp;a' which arrived here in December 1914. The wool was seized ana condemned by the Irize Court. Our claim in respect of advances made by us on tills shipment has been placed before the Prize Clairs Com attee, but we venture to hope that His ajesty 1 ! Government will reconsider tiieir attitude in the matter, in view not only of the Persian nationality of Mr. Bahrany as shown by tne enclosed copy of a com unication dated 19th. May 1917., we received from the Persian Legation, and a cony of tire tel eg alluded to, but also on the general grounds of the appeal already made on behalf of firms trading in Mesopotamia. It will no doubt, after the war, be considers desirable that these shipments to this country, i eluding as they do such essential articles as woe valuable gums, opium, skins tan ed and untanned, of State snoulysr should be encour^ed, and not drive i to other c markets, notably to Prance, where they have throughout the war been allowed to nass unmolested. In view of the Procla. lation issued by Lieutenant General oir Stanley Maude at Bagdad, British firms doind business in the ^ast would find their position very difficult, should they have to inform their clients that their goods had been coififiscated by the British Authorities, and that they were also liable for the legal charges incurred in their defence. &lt; • • 1 We- are, etc., (Signed) l ? redk. Huth and Company. l&amp;A : v /3 b. 0T' V Iviessrs. i^rec 12, Tokc; V /3 L'. PERSIAN LEGATION. LONDON, 19th. i .ay 1917. Gentlemen, I am in receipt of your letter of yester day’s date, and beg to say that we have received two telegrams from our Consul General in bagdad certified copies of hot i of which 1 herewith en close. Kindly acknowledge receipt. I am also sending copies of these two telegrams to i essrs. Gelira Horn sey and Coraoany, of 37, Gt. Mary Axe., K.C. Yours faithfully, (Si ned) F. Noury Secretary. Messrs. Frederick Huth and Comoany 12, Tokenhouse Yard, K.C.* • — - “ * Sir, With reference to your letter of the 12th Lay No.P.1873 regarding the resumption of trading with Bagdad, I am directed by the Board of Trade to transmit herewith, for the informa tion of the Secretary of State,copies of letters on this subject which they have caused to be addressed to the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and Excise and to l essrs. Selim Eomsy and Company who ere considered to be quite respectable. I have the honour to be, Sir, The Under Secretary of State, Po1itical Departm ent, India Office, Your obedient Servant,BOARD OF TRADE, (Commercial Department), GWYDYR HOUSE, V WHITEHALL, LONDON, S. W. 1 23rd I ay, 1917 Sir, I an directed by the Board of Trade to tnngyii't herevith a copy of corres‘-x&gt;iridey?ce which has passed between the India Office and this Depart ent and a copy of a letter which has been cent to essrs. Selin a isy and ;.a pany in co meet ion 'vith Ian enquiry by Uie fiim rqp.rdin^ the resuiption of trading ai th Bagdad. 1 am to request that the Ooraridssionerc of Lis Ja;esty’s Customc and .'Ixcise will be so good as to cause stops to be taken to secure that any goods which the fir.i nay export fras this country for J agdad shall in the first instoaace be consiojied only as far as ^asra* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, e Secretary, Custom House, E. C.C. 6106 : • BOARD OF TRADE, (Corumerc ial Departsent), GWYBYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LOlIDOl', S.w.l. 23rd l ay, 1917 Gentlemen, With further reference to your letter of the Zlst Larch I an directed by the Board of Trade to state that they understand from the India Office that no objection will be offered to your tradii^ with Bagdad provided that any (joods which you may despatch thither are consi^ed in the first in stance only as far as Basra where all duties must be mid in full on their arrival. It must, however, be clearly understood that military requironents may at any moment necessitate the suspension of transit, and the Board understand that it is unlikely that rail or stewner transport will be available for commercial freights for some time. I am, Gentlemen, Your obedient Servant, Lessrs. Selim Ilomsy &amp; Co., 37 St. Mary Axe, E. C. 3. • •••£?AM jL’OF'-ff&amp;l In Any furtJier communica tion or. this subject, please quote No /$/f // /19 and address — The Under-Secretary of 5*6 Foreign Office, r?./ Ix)nd^* his co, of Sti paper. Uwmmmnmmmp 1C1131/G. ■i ..'-■-I- 11 W « 'HSM OPFXOtf . ., 1 . 1 . Jay 2i&gt; ,1917. Gentlemen, with reference to your letter of the 18th instant relative to your desire to trade with liaghdad, I am directed t&gt;y Lord Robert Cecil to inform you that although Baghdad cannot actually be declared to be in friendly occupation within the meaning oi the proclamation of February 16th,1915, there is no objection to your trading with that city. It should however, be clearly understood that military require* ments at any moment necessitate the suspension of the transit of goods for trade purposes. 2, 1 am to add that the above information has been communicated to the Trading with the ,ne;ny Branch of the parliamentary Counsel’s Office. I am, Gentlemen, Your most ouedient, humble servant, srs. Selim Homsy and Company 37, st. f ary Axe, * K. C. 3,1 44, Whitworth Street, ^ MANCHESTER. Telegrammes “SHASHA, Manchester.” Telephone No. 5536 Central. A.B.C. Code:- 5th Edition, e The Secretary, India Office, LONDON. Dear Sir, I shall be much obliged if you will let me know If I may now trade with Bagdad. Yours faithfully, J. M. SHASHAc y In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 92125/C. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. A i 947 ! 9! 7 /?73 Foreign Office S.W. 1. May IO ,1917. Sir:- I am directed t&gt;y Lord R. Cecil to refer to the War Office letter addressed to the India Office 121 Trade/1378/M.1.6.A. of the 5th instant relative to “ftie resumption of trade with Baghdad, and 1 am to request that Lord Robert may he furnished with a copy of your letter therein referred to. 2. Enquiries v/hich have been received at this Office on the subject of commercial relations with Baghdad have hitherto been referred to the War Office, and I am to enquire whether in the future they should be referred to your Department instead. Iix 20466 I 468 1000 4/16 DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE Despatched TO 4- Foreign Secret. Cox’s telegram VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. 8th April. Trade with Baghdad , War Office do not regard Baghdad as in effective military (Retamilla) to be repeated to Sir P. Cox. occupation within meaning of Trading with tha Enemy Proclamation of 1915, but see no objection to [lA FA NJ?0 XAS'Ra'} informing individual enquirers that trade is now permissible provided they clearly understand that military requirements may at any moment necessitate suspension of transit and provider] facilities only given to approved firms. No formal Notification or announcement necessary. Board of Trade are being asked to take^steps to enforce proviso regarding consignment to Basra as suggested by necessary Cox. Please take/action in India. Addressed Viceroy, repeated Cox.XU further communications on ,s subject should be addressed The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W., #n ,l the following numl&gt;er quoted. U ''T2l/cra&amp;e/l378. M April 191 am comrnan informati reasons g 1917, Bag military the Bnems course pi reply, pi to unders necessity purposes, given to activity Office, ] penartmej The Under Secret IITDIA 01- . All »U further communications on [^g subject should be addressed 'tr The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W., ' ,„(! the following numlier quoted. 1 12l/ira&amp;e/l378. Sir, i 87 3 1917 WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W. 5^, Llay 1917. fi IU5'J With reference to your letter P.1436 of the 16th Auril 1917 regarding the resumption of trade with Bagdad, i ^commanded !y the Army Oouncil to acquaint you for tne information of the Secretary of state for India reasons given in my letter Ho.l2l/Trade/l378 0 - ^ ^ ' ,q 17 BaSdad cannot at present be regarded as in ef. w 17 military'occupation within the meaning of the grading with the Enemy (Occupied Territory) proclamation of 1915. fphe Council, however, have no objection 1.0 the course urocosed in the last paragraph of your letter now unue -•e-olv provided that individual enquirers are ° learl y to'understand that military requirements may at necessitate the suspension of the transit of gojda purposes. '“‘he Oouncil consider that facilities should only be o-iven to approved firms, in order to prevent commercial activities' becoming a cloak for espionage. Pcmies of this letter are being sent to the foreign Office, Foreign 2rade department. War Trade intelligence Department and the Admiralty. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, INDIA OFEIGE.f ^JL cm* ta*». 'i( .„ * /-wif* ' &gt; ■ Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. R. Si S., T 7.T.2222. 191 . Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 18th April, 191? 1 r* Cla-imsagainst enemy aubjects. For information and any observations (in regard to the claim with r°ference to p*oods /—■ sta.ted to have been destroyed at Basra.). (SD.) L.DFFAKFLY. T '. r ith regard to the Basra claim, it is duly submitted in accordance with the instruc tions, in the form of a statutory declaration, but it is unsupported by any documents, or by the evidence of nny other person than the claimant. He expressly states that he holds no documents or receipts for the goods. The Government of India have sent on the claim, without comment, and it may be regarded as on ’’accepted case” and passed on as proposed. (SD.) E.II.CLARKE.BAGHDAD. Lieutenant-General Sir Stanley Maude has issued a proclamation at Baghdad, of which the following is the English test:— “ To the People of BaghdadYtl^LL^/f 0 1. In the name of my King, and in the name of the peoples over whom he rules, 1 address you as follows :— 2. Our military operations have as their object the defeat of the enemy, and the driving of him from these territories. In order to complete this task, I am charged with absolute and supreme control of all regions in which British troops operate 1 ; but our armies do not come into your cities and lands as conquerors or enemies, but as liberators. ?&gt;. Since the days of Halaka your city and your lands have been subject to the tyranny of strangers, your palaces have fallen into ruins, your gardens have sunk in desolation, and your forefathers and yourselves have groaned in bondage. Your sons have been carried off to wars not of your seeking, your wealth has been stripped from you by unjust men and squandered in distant places. 4. jSince the days of Midhat, the Turks have talked of reforms, yet do not the ruins and wastes of to-day testify the vanity of those promises ? ■ 5. It is the wish not only of my King and his peoples, but it is also the wish of the great nations with whom he is in alliance, that you should prosper even as in the past, when your lands were fertile, when your ancestors gave to the world literature, science, and art, and when Baghdad city was one of the wonders of the world. 6. Between your people and the dominions of my King there lias been a close bond of interest. For 200 years have the merchants of Baghdad and Great Britain traded together in mutual profit and friendship. On the other hand, the Germans and 'Turks who have despoiled you and yours, have for 20 years made Baghdad a centre of power from which to assail the power of the British and the Allies of the British in Persia and Arabia. Therefore the British Government cannot remain indifferent as to what takes place in your country now or in the future, for in duty to the interests of the British people and their Allies, the British Government cannot risk that being done in Baghdad again which has been done by the Turks and Germans durimr the war.f I :■ : / 7. But you people of Baghdad, whose commercial prosperity and whose safety from oppression and invasion must ever be a matter of the closest concern to the British Government, are not to understand that it is the wish of the British t Jovernment to impose upon you alien institutions. It is the hope of the British Government that the aspirations of your philosophers and writers shall he realised and that once again the people of Baghdad shall flourish, enjoying their wealth and substance under insti tutions which are iu consonance with their sacred laws and their racial ideals. In Hejaz the Arabs have expelled the Turks and Germans who oppressed them and proclaimed the Sherif Hussein as their King, and his Lordship rules in inde pendence and freedom, and is the ally of the nations who are fighting against the power of Turkey and Germany; so, itideed, are the noble Arabs, the Lords of Koweyt, Nejd, and Asir. ir from (/v 8 . Many noble Arabs have perished in the j cause of Arab freedom, at the hands of those alien rulers, the Turks, who oppressed them. It is the determination of the Government of Great Britain and the great Powers allied to Great [Britairi, that these noble Arabs shall not have suffered in vain. It is the hope and desire of he British people and the nations in alliance vith them, that the Arab race may rise once more to greatness and renown among the peoples of the [jarth, and that it shall bind itself together to this md in uni tv and concord. To Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State.... —Minute PaperDraft Paper Department Th&lt;=* Secretary, WAR OFFICE, INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL S.W.l. fC?April, 1917. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 3rd April, 1917, No. 121/Trade/1374/M.I.6.A, regarding the resumption of trade with Bap-dad, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose, for the information of To Sir P.Cox, 24th March, 1917 &lt;r\rA •* M M Q4- 1 -n A-TiV*-? 1 w the Army Council, copy of telegraphic correspondence on the subject with the Chief Political Officer, Expeditionary 9th April, From « »» » No. T.1057. / / Force 'D”. Mr. Secretary Chamberlain would be glad to learn whethe^, in the opinion of - the Army^Hncil the views expressed by Sii^FT Cox in his telegram of instant afford grounds for Wdifying the decision conveyed in Mr. CubittMs letter to the Foreign . Y^. tk\ CjktUA- Office 0 f the 1st April; and wliftthajr in fha 4- nnn naajr j6binotion to his aopi^aohin; 11 the ?[„ 1 irr ril, iriw^oritino with a Miew to Cc—•» ■ ■ T 1057. Yc to resumption bi that no rail or be available for will be confined craft as may be met. Appears p and there is no are regulated wi Commander has no it would 4*** that relating to Trad' occupation Baghd; and trade therew; goods must be cor Basra where all cU&lt;*0&lt; Dated 8th April 1917. ^ Received at 1.0. 10 a.m. 9th Telegram from Sir P. Cox. T 1057. Your telegram of 27th. No objection in principle to resumption but Amy Cornnander would like to make it clear that no rail or steamer transport for commercial freights will oe available for some time yet and that consequently transport .ill be confined to dribblets by caravans and by such few native craft as may be available after military requirements have been met. Appears probable that this may cause congestion at Basra and there is no spare storage available there. If shipments are regulated with due regard to these considerations Amy Commander Las no objection to proposal. If nronosal is armroved relating to Trade during the /War intimating that from date of occupation Baghdad shall be treated as friendly occupied territory and trade therewith shall be lawful subject to provision that goods must be consigned ±*b in the first instance only as far as Basra where all duties must be paid in full (^ arrival . I. cf noxd'qrauB^i 10 Iibi on iair ©XijBli. v/ •' r&gt;ru^n:^ ei ®cf ® c ^JBIO 81 .^6(3 on 8i « 18 l:d biUi ;w Lei J x, &gt;*i a &gt;n e^rf lebaBiisnoO Any further communication should be, addressed to—^' t ' THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY; : ^ -*•*) If ^ it the address given opposite. The following lett toted:— C. 6106 S' The following letter and number should be quoted:— v 1 jyfj j- BOt T&lt;^te:raphic Address: uOLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No. s 3840 Victoria. OARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W \ hT LUC LbiT oi fii ( x*il floiiBcrircoc ©Lxii I I Id filer- 1 *' 1. 4th April, 1917. Sir, I sun directed by the Board of Trade rtertransnuo to you heravith a copy of a letter from Uessrs. Selim Eomsy • .nd Company relative to the resum ption of trading relations with Bagdad. In this connection I tain to refer to the provisions of the Trading with the Enemy (Occupied Territory) Pro- » clamation 1915 and to say that the Board would be glad to be advised as to the reply which should, in Lir. Secretary Chamberlain's opinion, be returned to the firm. Ihave the honour to be, , *■SELL: HOi.SY &lt;k UG. LONDOE. E. C. 51st March, 1917 —57 St. Mary Axe. E.C.3. &gt;■ &gt;. 1405 The Assistant Secjret, j /* Board of Trade, Commercial Department, Gwydyr House, V/hitehall, S. W. Sir, In view of the occupation of Ba^daL by the British forces we presume that, in accordance with the terms of the Proclamation of 5th November 1914, it is permissible for us to resume trading reltions with that place and we should estean it a, favour if you would confirm this. YIe are, Sir, Your obedient Servants, (Sgd.) ei;LIM IIOMSY a CO.6 I noxd'qrauc c\ In any further communica- on this subject, please quote w. i TU f'Ua'V V&gt;9i7. nl address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 31 1H L Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copl^-o of the under-mentioned papery Foreign Office, Cj , 1917. Letter to from Reference to^ffrevious correspondence Forei£}rf'X)fhce: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ « W/cvx (XJ-—i ■ (Similar letter sent to 4 !r T\, (C ) 1 •)+ 2/ts7~ P. Ccof. . 12l/Trade/l378. M.I.6.A 3 1st April , 1917 Sir tVith reference to your letter No.W.57572/17 of the 25rd March 1917 enclosing a copy of a letter from Messrs. Arditti Brothers enquiring whether Baghdad may he considered as in friendly occupation within the meaning of the Proclamation of the 16th February 1915, I am commanded by the Army Council to acquaint you, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that operations are still in progress in the Baghdad Vilayet, and it is therefore premature to declare Baghdad to be in effective military occupation. I am Sir Your obedient Servant (Sgd.) B.B. Cubitt e Under Secretary of State, FOB- IGN OFFICE.T——■■i * In any further communica- f tion on this subject, please quote No. W. S J 5') 1- / 1917 , and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ITI In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. SJ 5^ and address— /I9I7, The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned papers Foreign Office, z g. ? 1917. Reference to previous correspondence : Letter 1° Foreign Office : from 0 Description of Enclosure. - Name and Date. Subject. j Avt a&lt;L r-j (XsT—tifotOC ffy-xr* 9' / (, $ 9 L(26MAR1917)' (Similar letter sent to —- .).....IS. ; ■ Sir:- 3 . ARDITTI BROTHERS, 11, PETER STREET, MANCHESTER. f “I 1 i 1242 ' i lilLi. J 1917. You will much oblige by informing us whether Bagdad is now in friendly occupation within the meaning of the Proclamation of the 16th February, 1915. Thanking you in anticipation, we remain, etc. (Signed) 3. Arditti Brothers. N.B. We are writing you on the advice of the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel.-iiia me si 5loorr c i :- r M'J &gt;..5757^/17. 1C* i • [ C i, March iiSrd, 1917 air:- I an directed by Mr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you, herewith, to be laid before the array Council, a copy of a letter which he has received from Messrs, i^rditti. Brothers, enquiring v/hether Bagdad may be considered as in friendly occupation within the meaning of the Proclamation of the 16th February, 191a. I am to enquire whether the rmy Council see an: objection to such firms being informed that they may reopen trade with Bagdad. I am, Your moat obedient, humble Servant, o ^rBdfrxooi oiu. iivva^ v ference Paper. Register No. R. &amp; S/W.T.2381. Political and Secret Department. Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 11th April 191 1917 . Licences no longer to be fequired for the export of goods to Basra which appear on Section B of the Prohibited List. Political Secretary, Letter from Foreign Office; suggest^ that proposal be accepted &amp; G. of I. invited to take corresponding action. (Sd.) P.J.Turner, Kershaw. Secretary, R. &amp; S . Dept. ' 1 - 4 - 17 - I agree that the F.6. proposal may be accepted, and that the G. of I. should be addressed as proposed. I think that the necessary action should preferably be taken in the R. &amp; s. D p pt&gt; (Sd.) J.E.Sbuckburgh. 12.4.17.itiriiiia i¥ ' i imii ilinMBiiW '&lt; From Wary of *at. e ll&gt; Vieero,,, Foreign Department, 1 &lt; \th A ovember 1914. Foreign Secret. Following telegram sent tn u • . ' tatives abroad, dated 9t,h November — 1 Majesty s represen- =«p-= to be eoimfdered ‘as BrltlahArnT' of ''^pt Kgyptians are henceforth tlescribingth^rn^ ^R^ T establish fact that they were born f ’ h ‘ ! vever ' be m l'ire,l to JV any part of Ottoman tlon,inions othirllmn riX fnUvir!f‘(H;r led (roverninent or have taken special steps to retain OtPa,^, n^onaht^' 0 '' 3 ' T From Sir P. Cox, 2Sth November 1914. (Addressed to India Office.; repeated to India.) &lt;0 B. dated :i 8 th November. Civil population, Basra, lias received us well and mercantile element is separately quite ready to come under British protection. Also we have proclaimed that we have no quarrel with friendly resident population. In these circumstances it would be wise in my opinion if we refrain from treating consignments of Basra merchants nowon the high seas as enemy cargo. Can I be authorised to reassure enquirers on this point ? From. 1 iceroy, 30th. November 1914. «. , ( ^? reign SeCret ' P^laraation, &gt;W Cox telegraphs 27th November l ollowing is summary ol proclamation issued over my signature on behalf of General Officer Commanding: - ' ' ne ' alt _Reminds public that Great Ihitain greatest Mohamadan power alwavs ^ood fnend lurkey, and repeatedly urged Turkey against being invei&lt;ded into this wai, and tn the event of her abstaining undertook with her allies Turkey - ''''T'r i''' in,| epemlence, but misleld by Germanv Tritain '''p ' K&gt; , ller llostlle behaviour forced war upon Great ntam. Ilntish expedition consequently despatched and had occupied Basra ami neighbourhood and British flag had now replaced Turkish flag and administration in this region. But though at war with Turks pi .overnment British had no enmity or design against the local inhabitants andweie prepared to be their friends and protectors. Under the British seclilaflffah's Tb^ Pr0te f^' ,lml l&gt; ' tl ' 111 '-eliKious and ser ma, aftaiis. I hey were at liberty to pursue their normal avocations and business without apprehension, and troops had received strictest instructions to tieat population with utmost courtesy and consideration and same attitude was expected from them. u Tins is sent with reference to your telegram of 24th November.” From 1 iceroy, 2nd December 1914. Foieign Seciet. Basra. Cox telegraphs 27th November :— May inhabitant of Basra formerly subject of Turkey, but now willing to become subject of Great Britain, be treated on the basis of instructions recently issued by His Majesty’s Foreign Office in the case of inhabitant of Egypt. t f xT COmn J en( ^ n ^ rilct ^ ons s ^ in ^ ar t0 ^ 10Se re P e ated in your telegram ox 10 th November be issued as regards Basra.From Viceroy, 2nd December 1914. Foreign Secret. Basra. Reference (’ox telegram 70B, dated ^ 8 th November. We support his proposal regarding cargo consignments of Basra merchants, now on high seas. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department 9th December 1914. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 2nd December. Basra Cox may mform merchants that cargo now on high seas helongino to Basra merchants ts not to be treated as enemy cargo and should bt lelea'd 1 nze Courts should be informed accordingly.TELEGRAM TO Foreign S Foreign Office Basra whose in legal point of annexation or protected oers special corsid assistance.I Vanessa Department. C\*V TELEORAjV. TO VICI^ CY, _DATED^ 1st JANUARY 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 2nd December. Basra. Foreign Office circular regarding Egypt does not apply to Basra whose inhabitants continue to be Ottoman subjects from legal point of view pending formal change of status by annexation or otherwise, and cannot be considered as British protected persons. But Cox may trea.t such persons with special consideration and give all possible unofficial assistance.• .4 ' LP 3353 1 Foreign Secret. Your ^(^’‘FoSgn''^'-® a-k » are n - a, ' i ' &gt;! 'T' From Viceroy, 2lst May 1915. Your telegram o£ the 22nd ultimo. Following telegram has been received from officer on special duty under the Political Resident in I ersian . _ “ Import of copper here seems to be practically suspended ' ^ne Custom House figures show imports of December-January 8 tons, Janua.t February 4 tons, since then, nil. . , i “ During corresponding periods last year about oO tons mipoi ei . “ No certificates have been issued here fruni tlww. 0^ ■ , • “ fu these circumstances there appears to be no chance ol any teaching. enemy by this route. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, also telegraphs as follows . “There, have been no imports of copper to Basra since our owupation. Present blockade arrangements would ellectively prevent leakage ol imported.’ From Secretary of State to Sir P. Cox, Basra, 15Pi September 1915. Foreign Secret. Australian Government enquire whether all exports u Basra of Turkish Arabian produce are subject to approval of British from authorities. What reply ? From Sir P. Basra, 16ft September 1915. fP 33531 Regular British Custnls’Lve except foodstuffs are on same lines as in India. From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 9th November 1915. (Repeated to Sir P. Cox.) Foreign Secret. Cox’s telegram of 28th November and my predecessor’s telegram of 9th December last. Cargoes of Basra merchants on high seas ForSign Office raise question of according similar treatment to cargoes ot Amara merchants. W hat are your views ?From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 17th Mai/ 101G. No ^293. Will you kindly ascertain and telegraph existing restrictions on import of Iruit into United Kingdom applying to (iates. It is unnecessary for me to point out the serious effect that prohibition of import into United Kingdom of this commodity would have on local prosperity and local revenues here. From Secretary of State to Sir P. Cox, Basra, 1 Oth June I'jlfi. (Repeated to Viceroy, Foreign Department.) [P 22131 Your telegrams of 17th May and 9th June. Dates. Customs have been requested to permit importation of dates from Basra as if emanating from British territory, fruit from which is exempt from prohibition. Board of irade enquire whether same should apply to dates from Mohammerah YY hat are your views ?t ! ot.. a* aA* tt ° Any further communication i the subject, please quote No. /^4450//±4 id add re. The Controller, Foreign Trade Department. Telephone: Gcrrarcl 8640. For eign Trade Department, Lancaster House, St. James, 0 J^ ■ s.w.i Elst ..1 rc.T 1917. Sir, I am directed by Hr. Secretary Balfour to transmit to you barewit to be 1 in before Mr* Seoratary Chamberlalsu copy*of a letter dated the loth instant from Messrs. Snasha, of Manchester, enquiring wnether they, may trade v;itn Bagdad. In view of the terms of the Trading witn the Enemy (Occupied Territory) ^reclamation, 1910, there would appear to be no legal objection to the resumption of commercial relations with Bagdad, but Hr. Balfour would be glad to be informed wnether t iere is on military grounds any reason way sucn relations snould not be resumed forthwith. rt. similar letter has been addressed to the ~ar Office.Maroa 1917 • x/ie controller. Foreign Trade lepartiaent, London, S*’• Lear Sir, I shall be glad to knov if it will be in order for me to trade with BaGLAL as I understand it is now in tne hands of the British. Yours faithfully, for J.M. 3HASHA. (Signed) J.H. House.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/566</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/566</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3104/1915 Pt 3 ‘Mesopotamia: trade with Baghdad’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-22T22:30:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (187 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 3104 (German War: conquered territory, Mesopotamia: trade) consists of 9 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/564-572. The volumes are divided into ten parts, with parts 1 to 8 comprising one volume each, and parts 9 and 10 comprising the last volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 189; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Papers relating to trade between Baghdad and Basra in Mesopotamia [Iraq] and Great Britain, in the wake of Britain’s military invasion and occupation of Mesopotamia during the First World War. Subjects covered include: the resumption of trade between Britain and Baghdad; enquiries made to the British Government by British firms asking if they may resume trade to and from Mesopotamia; enquiries relating to goods seized and condemned by the Prize Court; the resumption of trading at Baghdad by a number of firms ‘approved’ by the British Government’s Board of Trade; enquiries by commercial firms relating to goods looted or destroyed during the military invasion of Mesopotamia. The file’s principal correspondents are: the Foreign Office; the India Office; the Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India; Henry Fountain of the Commercial Department of the Board of Trade.The file includes a single item of correspondence in French: a copy of a telegram from the Persian Consul General in Baghdad (f 144).The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Baghdad</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International trade</topic></subject><subject><topic>Seizure of vessels and cargoes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>