<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000e1_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:26:40.180Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">GOVERNMENT OF INDIA FINANCE DEPARTMENT Simla, the 1th January 1943. NOTIFICATION No. D.13-S.D.|42. —The following resolu tion by the Secretary of State for ludia is pub lished for general information :— THE INDIAN CIVIL SERVICE PROVIDENT FUND RULES Dated June 3, 1942, f, Leopold ( harles Maurice Stennett Amerv. one of his Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, in virtue of the powers conferred by sec tion 247(1) and section 250(1) of the Govern ment of India Act, 1935, hereby make, with the concurrence of my Advisers, the following rhe8e Rules lna ^ be cited a * s the Indian ( ml Service Provident Fund Rules. (2) They shall come into force on the 3rd day of June, 1942. 2. In these Rules unless the context other wise requires— (1) ' Account Officer '' means the Audit Officer so designated by the Auditor- General of India. (2) ' Child ' means a legitimate child and, m cases where tlie Account Officer or if any doubt arises in the mind of the Account Officer, the Solicitor to the Govern ment of India or the Legal Remembrancer ' : oi a person employed in connection with tke affairs of a Province. (7) ' Leave ' means any variety of leave prescribed in the Fundamental Rules. (8) ' Year ' means financial year. 3. Every member of the Indian Civil Service other than a member appointed before the 1st April, 1937, to be a Judge of a High &lt; onrt. shall subscribe monthly to the Fund an amount, which shall be a sum of whole rupees, fixed by himself, but not less than four nor more than 12| per cent, of his emoluments for the month : Provided that subscription shall be optional— (a) for a member of the Executive Council of the Governor-General ; (b) during leave on minimum leave salary or leave salary under Rule 88 of tiie Fundamental Rules or while the subscriber is under suspension during which reduced remuneration is drawn ; (c) during leave preparatory- to retire ment, but if the subscriber after electing not to subscribe during a period of such leave subsequently returns to duty he shall sub scribe at the rate of 4 per cent, of the leave salary drawn by him during such leave. 1 rovided further in the case of a member appointed to serve in the armed forces of the Crown duritig an emergency that the amount .of his subscription to the Fund shall be cal culated on the emoluments he would have drawn if he had remained on duty in civil employ ment and that subscription to the Fund shall be optional while he is serving outside India. 4. Interest at the rate determined for eacb year according to the method of calculation prescribed by the Secretary of State shall be credited to the account of each subscriber ns from the 31st March of each year subject to the following conditions :— M 1 Interest for 12 months shall be credited on the amount at the credit of the subscriber on the 31st March of the preceding y?ar ]e«s any advance taken during the vear • (2) Interest shall be credited for each month of the year upon the sum by which the minimum amount at the credit of the subscriber between the close of the fourth day of the end of the; month exceeded the amount on which interest is credited under sub-rule (1). subscriptions paid hy deduc tions from emoluments bein? treated for the purpose of tliis sub-rule as having been .deposited in the Fund on the first Jay of the month in which pavment is actuallv made ; ffl) if thp total amount of interest allowed under sub-rules (1) and (2) contains a frac tion of a rupee, it shall be rounded to theIG, GOVERNMENT OF INDIA FINANCE DEPARTMENT Simla, the 1th January 1943. NOTIFICATION . v v ''S r No. D.13-8.D. j42.— The following resolu tion b\ Hie becretary of State for India is pub- lished for general information :— THE INDIAN CIVIL SERVICE PROVIDENT FUND RULES Dated June 3, 1942. 1. Leopold ( harles Maurice Stennett Amery, one of Ills Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, in virtue of the powers conferred by sec tion 247(1) and section 250(1) of the Govern ment of India Act, 1935, hereby make, with the concurrence of my Advisers, the following rules ;— 1. (1) These Rules may be cited as the Indkn ( n il Service Provident Fund Rules. (2) They shall come into force on the 3rd day of June, 1942. 2. In these Rules unless the context other wise requires— (1) 'Account Officer' means the Audit Officer so designated by the Auditor- General of India. (2) ' Child ' means a legitimate child and, in cases where the Account Officer, or if any doubt arises in the mind of the Account Officer, the Solicitor to the Govern ment of India or the Legal Remembrancer (or other corresponding officer) to the Pro vincial Government as the case may be, is satisfied that under the personal law of the subscriber adoption is legally recognised as conferring the status of a natural child, in cludes an adopted child. (3) ' Emoluments means pay as defined in the Fundamental Rules (Sterling over seas pay being converted at such 'rate of exchange as tke Secretary of State may pres cribe), leave salary and remuneration during suspension. (4) ' Family ' means the wife or wives and children of a subscriber and the widow or widows and children of a deceased son of a subscriber, widowed mother, unmarried uisters and minor brothers, but if a sub scriber proves that his wife has been judi cially separated from him or has ceased under the customary law of the community to which she belongs to be entitled to maintenance, she shall be deemed to be no longer a member of the subscriber's family in matters to which these Rules relate, unless the subscriber in dicates in writing to the Account Officer that she shall continue to be so regarded. the Indian Civil (5) ' Fund ' means Service Provident Fund. ^61 '' Government ' means the Governor- General in the ease of a person employed in connection with the affairs of the Federation and the Governor of the Province in the case of a person emplo3'ed in connection with tke affairs of a Province. (7) ' Leave ' means any variety of leave prescribed in the Fundamental Rules. (8) ' Year ' means financial year. 3. Every member of the Indian Civil Service other than a member appointed before the 1st April, 1937, to be a Judge of a High Court, shall subscribe monthly to the Fund an amount, which shall be a sum of whole rupees, fixed by himself, but not less than four nor more than 12^ per cent, of his emoluments for the month : Provided that subscription shall be optional— (a) for a member of the Executive Council of the Governor-General ; (b) during leave on minimum leave salary or leave salary under Rule 88 of the Fundamental Rules or while the subscriber is under suspension during which reduced remuneration is drawn ; (c) during leave preparatory to retire ment, but if the subscriber after electing not to subscribe during a period of such leave subsequently returns to duty he shall sub scribe at the rate of 4 per cent, of the leave salary drawn by him during such leave. Provided further in the case of a member !• After rule 3, there shall be i the following rule:- 3A. (1) iLVery person who on the ; was a subscriber to the inond shoJ to elect whether he will be -'ovdii 5 and 12 or by rule 12A# (2) unless such person has m months from the date of the publ: this rule in the official (^azet was on leave on that date, withfl of his return to duty, notifief the Account Officer that he elec med by rules 5 and 12 or by rul case may be, he shall be deemed elected to be governed by rule 1 (3) An election notified tol officer or deemed to have been n final, and if a subscriber who 1: is deemed to have elected to be rule 12 A has previously made a under rule 5, the nomination shl to- have been cancelled. (4) if such person died on c date of the publication of this Gazette of India v/ith no electi( deemed to have been made, actioi taken in accordance with rule 1: v5) if such person has died 3rd dune 1942, but before the d publication of this rule in the India one payment in accordance'! vb; oi sub-rule vl) of rule 12 maae before the last named date be token in accordance with rulSv. r• jJi s —rule vl) of rule 5 ? for 'the words 'shall soon as may be after joining' the mnd send to the Account officer a nomination', there shall be substituted the following v/ords :- 'sliall, umess he haSj or is deemed to have, elected for the provisions of rule 12 A, send to the Account Officer, as soon as may be after the comirg into force of these rules or after Joining c flind, hichever is later, a nomination'/ V 2 ,0^ Jb^ Sv^ tiearest whole rupee, 8 amias counting as the next higher rupee ; (4) Before the amount at tlie credit of a subscriber in the Fund is finally paid, hi^ account shall be credited with the intere.si ui) to the montl^ preoedinpr that in which the payment is made^or up to the end of the sixlJi month after the end of the month in whieh he quitted the service or died, whichever of thqse periods is less ; (5) The rate of interest is liable to revision on the 1st April of each year without notice. 5. (1) Each subscriber shall as soon as may be after joining the Fund send to the Account Officer a nomination conferring on one or more persons the right to receive the amount that may stand to his credit in the Fund, in the event of his.death before that amount has be come payable, or having become payable, has not been paid : .Provided that if, at the time of making ths nomination, the subscriber has a family the nomination shall not be in favour of any person or persons other than the members of his family. (2) If a subscriber nominates more than one person under sub-rule (1), he shall specify in the nomination the amount or share payable to each of the nominees in such manner as to cover the whole of the amount that may stand to his credit in the Fund at any time. (3) A subscriber may at any time cancel a nomination by sending a notice in writing to the Account Officer : Provided that the subscriber shall along with such notice nend a fresh nomination made in accordance, with the provisions of suWutes (4) Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-rule (3), a subscriber shall along with every nomination made by him under tbr? Rule send to the Account Officer— (a) a notice to the effect that in the event of any of thre nominees predeceasing him. the nomination in respect of the deceased nominee shall forthwith stand cancelled, and (b) if the nomination is made at a tmie when the subscriber ha.s no family, a notice to the effect that in the event of his there after acquiring a tamily the nomination shall forthwith stand cancelled. (5) Tpimediately on the occurreilce of any event by reason of which the notice of cancel lation referred to/ in sub-rule (4) becomes operative and the nomination to which that notice relates /Consequently stands cancelled, the subscriber shall send to the Account Officer a fiesh lamination made in accordance with the provisions of siflvrules (1) and (2). (6) Every nomination made, and every notice of cancellation given, bv a subscriber shall, to the extent that it is valid and operative, take effect on the date on which it is received by the Account Officer. 6. fl) Government may sanction the pav- ment to any subscriber of an advance corsist- m g o. a sum of whole rupees and ordinarily not exceeding in amount three months' pay from the sum standing to his credit in the Fund. (2) An advance shall not be granted i.der thi« Kule to. any subscriber until at least twelve months have elapsed from the date of repay ment of the last instalment of any previous advance unless Government considers, for reasons which shall be recorded in writing, thai this restriction may be relaxed. 7. (1) An advance shall be recovered in sush number of equal monthly instaiments, each being a sum of whole rupees, not less than twelve or more than twenty-four, as Govern ment may prescribe : Provided that— (a) No recovery shall be made wh-le the subscriber is on leave, or under suspension during which reduced remuneration is drawn ; (b) recovery may be postponed by Govern- ment during the recovery of an advance granted to the subscriber otherwise than from the Fund ; (c) a subscriber may if he so desires re pay more than one instalment in a month. (2 It at any time under the provisions of Kule 6(2) an advance has been made ^o a sub scriber before one previously made has been completely repaid, each advance shall be treated separately for purposes of recovery. (3) After repayment of the advance interest 1 hereon equivalent to one-fifth per cent of the advance for each month or part of a month of I he period between drawal and complete re payment of the advance and rounded off to the nearest rupee, is payable in one instalment, if the advance has been repaid in Twelve instal ments and in two equal instalments if the advance has been repaid in more than twelve instalments. s . I incuts towards a policy of insurance ot any description on the subscriber's own life may. at the option of a subscriber, be substi- tuted for subscriptions to the Fund, subject to the following conditions :— (1) No amount shall be withdrawn before the details of the proposed policy ha-e been -x submitted to the Account Officer and accepted A by him as suitable. (2) Tf the payments substituted be less than the minimum subscription required bv Rule 3. the deficiency shall be rounded to the nearest rupee in the manner provided in rule 4(.y), and paid by the subscriber as a subscription to the Fund. (3) Government will not make any pav- ments to insirance companies on behalf of subscribers, nor will they take steps to keep the policy alive. Tf a subscriber records on his pay hill that he is making pavments to an insurance company, the Account Officer shall recover the deficiency, if any due iimler sub-rnle (2) and demand periodic-allv to see the receipts or certified -opies of the receipts showing that such payments have been made. Failing the production of such receipts he shall make the necessary dedue-V- from the subscriber's einolumeiujj «ntl pay them to his credit in the Fund, and biiaJl require the subscriber to furnish a eerlitic-ate by the insurance company either that the policy has lapsed or matured, in which case the amount realised by surrender or on maturity shall be ntated in the certuicate, o' that premiums have not been paid, as the i-a»se may be. Should a subscriber prefer, he may make the usual deduction from his pay bills for credit to the Fund and arrange witli the Account Officer to draw from the Fund as required the sums necetSbary to pa/ pre miums or to recoup premiums already paid,' provided that no amount shall be withdrawn to meet any payment made more than 12 months before the withdrawal. Any aunif. already at credit ot the subscriber in the Fund may be withdrawn for the purpose ot making payments under this rule, .provided that the amounts withdrawn shall bi rounded to the nearest rupee in the manner provided in Rule 4(3). Such withdrawals shall b'? treated as advances for the purpose of Rule 4(1) only, and not for the purposes of Rules 6 and 7. (4) If any policy lapses the subscriber shall pay to the Fund the amount of pre miums paid with interest thereon, and if any policy matures he shall pay to the Fund the amount of premiums paid with interest thereon, or at his option the sum realised. (')) Once .a policy has been accepted by ai Account Officer for the purpose of being financed from the Fund, the terms of the policy shall not be altered nor ^shall the policy be exchanged for another policy without the prior consent of the Account Officer to whom details of the alteration or of the new policy shall be furnished. 9. A subscriber may withdraw from the amount standing to his credit in the Fund any sum of whole rupees required to provide supplementary pensions for Im wife, sons and daughters of any of them under the Indian Civil Service Family Pension Fund Rules 10. The amount standing to the credit of a subscriber in the Fund is not liable to forfei ture in the event of his dismissal or removal from the service or of his quitting it, before he becomes entitled to annuity. 11. Except as provided in Rules 6, 8 and 9 the amount standing at the credit of a subscriber in the Fund shall not be withdrawn until he quits the service or dies : Provided that a subscriber who has been granted leave preparatory to retirement or, in the case of one serving in a vacation Depart ment, has been allowed vacation with such leave, or who while on leave is either permitted to retire voluntarily or is required to retire on the grounds of ill-health, may withdraw the amount standing to his credit at any time between the commencement of the leave or vacation a.s the ease may be, or the date of such permission or requirement as the ease may be, and the date of actual retirement, but if he returns to duty at the end of his leave lie shall repay to the Fund the whele amount withdrawn by him with interest thereon. A subscribe:.* who exercises the option allowed by this proviso shall not subscribe to the Fund after such with- • i 3. In rule 12 for the words 'on the o.ea of a subscriber 11 there shall be substi tuted the words 'If a^subscriber other than one who has, or is deemed to have* elected for the provisions of rale 12A dies. ,, In the Fund or the part thereof to which the nomination relates, shall be paid to his nominea or nominees in the proportion specified ia the nomination. (b) if no such nomination subsists or if such nomination relates only to a part of tLe amount standing to his crelit in the Fund, the whole amount or the part thereof to which the nomination does not relate as the case may be, shall notwithstanding any nomi nation purporting to be in favour or any person or persons other than a member or members of his family be paid to the members of his family in equal shares, Provided that no share shall be payable to— (1) sons who have attained legal majority ; son who have (2) sons of a deceased attained legal majority ; (3) married daughters whose husbands are alive ; (4) married daughters of a deceased son whose husbands are alive ; if there Is any member of the family other than those specified in clauses (1), (2), (3) and (4) of the proviso. Provided further that the widow or widows and the child or children of a deceased son shall receive between them in equal parts only the share which thai son would have received if he had survived the subscriber and had been exempt from the provisions of clause (1) of the first proviso. (2) When the subscriber leaves no family, if a nomination in favour of any person or 4. After rule 12 there shall be inserted . the following rale:- ^ tf 12A. un the death of a subscriber v/ho has, or is deemed to have, elected for the provisions of this rule the Account ufficer shall take steps in consultation with (government to as cert air- the person legally entitled to receive the amount at the subscriber's credit, and shall pay the amount to that person. But if a widow or children survive the deceased subscriber, then, unless the Account Officer has received from him a direction to the contrary in writing, Es.5,000 of the sum standing to tlx) credit of the subscriber at the time of his decease, or the whole of such sum if it be less than F .5,000 shall be payable to the widow, or ix there be no widow, to the 'idov; 0-- the children as the case may be.'tioKs ti'oni the subscriber's emoiumetitji and pay them to his credit in the Fund, and biiail require the subscriber to furnish a cerliticate v-, ■' C* i V mmibs Ari!7 provided that no amount shall be withdrawn to meet any payment made more than 12 months before the withdrawal. Any ^um.^ already at credit ot the subscriber in the Fund may be withdrawn for the purpose of making payments under this rule, .provided that the amounts withdrawn .shall b3 rounded to the nearest rupee in the manner provided in Rule 4(3). Such withdrawals .shall b 1 ? treated as advances for the purpose of Rule 4(1) only, and not for the purposes of Rules 6 and 7. (4) If any policy lapses the subscriber shall pay to the Fund the amount of pre miums paid with interest thereon, and if any policy matures he shall pay to the Fnnd the amount of premiums paid with interest thereon, or at his option the sum realised. (5) Once .a policy has been accepted by ai Account Officer for the purpose of being financed from the Fund, the terms of the policy shall not be altered nor ,shall the policy be exchanged for another policy without the prior consent of the Account Officer to whom details of the alteration or of the new policy shall be furnished. 9. A subscriber may withdraw from the amount standing to his credit in the Fund any sum of whole rupees required to provide supplementary pensions for his wife, sons and daughters of any of them under the Indian Civil Service Family Pension Fund Rules 10. The amount standing to the credit ot* a subscriber in the Fund is not liable to forfei ture in the event of his dismissal or removal from the service or of his quitting it, before he becomes entitled to annuity. 11. Except as provided in Rules 6, 8 and 9 the amount standing at the credit of « -' , - in the F''^ by him with interest thereon. A subscribe:.' who exercises the option allowed by this proviso shall not subscribe to the Fund after such with- rawal unless and until he returns to duty. 12. On the death of a subscriber before the mount standing to his credit has become pay- ihle or, where the amount has become payable, efore payment has been made :— (1) Wheai the subscriber leaves a family— (a) if a nomination in favour of a mi -niber or members of his family subsists, the amount standing to his credit in the Fund or the part thereof to which the nomination relates, shall be paid to his nomine 3 or nominees in the proportion specified ia tho nomination. (bj if no such nomination subsists or if such nomination relates only to a part of the amount standing to his crelit in the Fund, the whole amount or the part thereof to which the nomination does not relate as the case may be, shall notwithstanding any nomi nation purporting to be in favour of any person or persons other than a member or members of his family be paid to the members of his family in equal shares. Provided that no share shall be payable to— (1) sons who have attained legal majority ; (2) sons of a deceased son who have attained legal majority ; (3) married daughters wiiose husbands are alive ; (4) married daughters of a deceased son whose husbands are alive ; if there Is any member of the family other than those specified in clauses (1), (2), (3) and (4) of the proviso, Provided further that the widow or widows and the child or children of a deceased son shall receive between them in equal parts only the share which that son would' have received if he had survived the subscriber and had been exempt from the provisions of clause (1) of the first proviso. (2) When the subscriber leaves no family, if a nomination in favour of any person or persons subsists, the amount standing to his credit in the Fund or the part thereof to which the nomination relates shall be paid to his nominee or nominees in the proportion specified in the nomination, and if no nomi nation subsists it shall be paid to the persons legally entitled to receive it. 13. Ail payments from the Fund shall be made in India in rupees. 14. As soon as possible after the close of ear.h vear each subscriber shall be supplied vith a statement of his account in the Fund which hall show the opening balance as on 1st April tf the year, the total amount credited or lebited during the year, the amount of iuicrest redited as on the 31st March of the year, and he closing balance as on that date.V 15. (1) Until the commencement of Part II of the Government of India Act, 1935, refer ences in these Rules to the Qovernor-Ocneral sliall be construed as references to ihe Governor-General in Council. (2) In the discharge of his functionK under Ihese Rules the Governor shall exercise his individual judgment. 16. The Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rule^i, dated 24th September 1924, are iiercby repealed. Given under m}- hand this 3rd diiy of June, 3942 L. S. AMBRY, One of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State. L. T. GHOLAP, Deputy Secretary to the G-overnment of India. No. D.13-S.D.j42. Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners ; the High ' Commissioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Government of India fincluding the Financial Adviser, Mili tary Finance, the Financial Adviser, Communi cations, the Additional Financial Adviser Supply Finance, the Joint Financial Adviser Munitions Production, Calcutta ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply, the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor-General, and the Secretary to the Governor-General, Public J ; the Political Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Pri vate Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Masters, Calcutta and Bombay ; the Master, Security Printing, India ; all Accountants General and Comp trollers ; the Deputy Accountants General under the Accountant General, Posts and Tele graphs, and the Accounts Officer. Telegraph Check Office. Calcutta; the Director of Rail way Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control ; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway. Calcutta. Eastern Be.sgal Kail way. Calcutta, Great Indian Peninsula R&lt;iil- way, Boii)bay, North Western Railway, Lahore, iihd Burma Railways, Simla ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Con troller of Supply Accounts (Civil) and the Deputy Controllers of Supply Accounts (Civil), Calcutta and Bombay. By order, etc. II. C. BEAUMONT, Under Secretary fo the Government of India L123FmD—2,572—6-2-43—Glir S-J** UOVERNMENT OF INDIA FINANCE DEPARTMENT NOTIFICATION Simla, the 14:th January, 1943 No. D. 13-A.-S.D.|42.—With reference to the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, made by the Secretary of State on the 3rd June 1942, the following instructions are issued by the Government of India; for the guidance of subscribers to ' the Fund and Account Officers:— , 1. Subscriptions {Rule 3).— (1) Where the subscriber draws emoluments (other than leave salary or reduced remuneration during suspension) from a Government Treasury in India, the amount of subscription will be such as may be deducted by him from the bill on which he draws the emoluments. The amount may be varied by the subscriber during the year within the limits prescribed in rule 3. (2) Irf the case of a subscriber on leave the amount of subscription will be such as he may intimate to the Account Officer in India before proceeding on leave. If during leave the subscriber will be drawing minimum leave salary or leave salary under Fundaraemtal Rule 88, he should intimate to the Account Officer in India whether he wishes to subscribe and if so the amount he will bo subscribing. No alteration will be permissible'in the amount so fixed for the period of leave. If the sub scriber fails to intimate before proceeding on leave he will be deemed to have exercised his option in favour of subscribing during leave at the minimum rate of 4 per cent, of his leave salary and deductions will be made accordingly. (3) The instructions in sub-paragraph (2) will apply mutatis mutandis to a subscriber under suspension during which reduced re muneration is drawn. (4) In the case of a subscriber transferred to foreign service or sent on deputation out of India the amount of subscription will be such as he may intimate to the Account Officer in India before proceeding to join his new duties. The subscriber should also intimate to the Account Officer the amount of his emoluments while on foreign service or deputation out of India and any change therein in order to enable the Account Officer to verify whether the rate of subscription is within the limits prescribed in rule 3. (5) Subscriptions to recovered— the Fund will be (i) in respect of emoluments drawn from a Government Treasury in India or a Colonial or Home Treasury, by deduction from the emoluments ; (ii) in respect of sterling overseas •&gt; pay by deduction in India from pay ; and (iii) in respect of emoluments drawn from any other source, in cash, the sub scriber remitting the amount direct to the Account Officer. (6) All subscriptions made by a member together with interest on such subscriptions calculated under rule 4 should be credited to his account in the Fund. J. yominations {Rule 5).—Nominations under snb-rulQ (1), and notices of cancellation under sub-rule (4should be in such one of the forms appended to. those instructions as is appropriate in the circumstances. 3. Recoveries on account of advances {Rule ' • Recoveries on account of ad .ances will commence on the first cccasi. or which, after ilie advance is mat 1 , :u'» .vioer draws pay ioi a lull montn, ana wlL be e/c'ected. in the manner provided in paragraph jl above for i ealisation of subecriptions. Kecoveries made l»y deduction from emoluments will be treated i or the purpose of calculating interest under i ule 4 as having been credited to the Fund on Uie first day of the month in which they are made. 4. 1 aymenls towards policies of insurance [Rule S).—A\lien a subscriber diverts or with draws money from tiie Fund to pay the first premium on a policy of insurance (or, if the policy be a single premium policy, to pay that premium,) under rule 8, he should furnish the Account Officer with a certificate in the follow ing form :— ''In lieu of subscription]with the sum of ; ■ ; a month tolwithdrawn from the Indian (Jivil Service Provident J^und, I propose to pay a premiumjsingle premi um of Rs.. j£ _ . monthlyj quarterlyjhalf-yearlyjannually, on a policy of insurance on my own life with Company, ihis insurance is an endowmenti a whole life insurance for Rs j ^ ..payable aftetry .years or death whichever is earlier [on my death 3. Recovery of the amount withdrawn under I he proviso to rule 11.—Where a subscriber has to repay to ine Fund under the proviso to iiili 11, the whole amount withdrawn by him Government will determine whether the amount should be repaid in .one or more instalments and in cash op. securities or both. 6. Final payments {Rule 12).—(1) The Account Officer will be responsible for making final payments under rules 11 or 12. If pav° ment is made under rule 12 any person claim- ing payment should send a written application to that Officer. In a case where there is doubt or dispute, but only with regard to a portion of the amount standing to the credit of a sub scriber, the Account Officer should authorise prompt payment of that portion in regard to which there is no doubt or dispute. The per sons to whom any amount is payable from the un( ' should make their owJi arrangements to receive payment in India. i-/ It the person to whom any payment is to be made from the Fund is a lunatic, pay ment should be made to the authority entitled under the law T to receive payment on his behalf. (.'&gt;) Sums not claimed for a period of six months after they have become payable will at the end of the year, be transferred from the account head ' Indian Civil Service Provident2 Fund ' to the account head ' Deposits and treated under the ordinary rules relating to deposits. Such transfer does not however affect the fiduciary capacity in which the sums are held by Government. 7. Statement of account (Rule 14).—(1) The Account Officer will assign a number to the account of each subscriber^ and when paying subscriptions in India, the subscriber should quote this number. (2) Subscribers are required to satisfy them selves as to the correctness of the annual state ments. Errors, if any, should be brought to the notice of the Account Officer within six months of receiving a statement. If no state ment of account is received by the lat of Octo ber, the subscriber should communicate with the Account Officer. and APPENDIX. Form* of Nomination. I. When the^ subscriber has a family wishes to nominate one member thereof. I hereby nominate the person mentioned below, who is a member of my family as defined in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund.Rules, to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount has become pay able, or having become payable has not been Name and address of nominee. Relationship with subscriber. Age. , , at. D»ted this day of 19 Signature of subscriber Two witnesses to signature. 1 2...: II. When the subscriber has a family and wishes to nominate more thani one member thereof. I hereby nominate the persons mentioned below, who are membe&lt;rs of mv familv as de fined in rule 2 of the Indian' Civil ' Service Provident Fund Rules, to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount has become payable, or having become payable has not been paid, and direct that the said amount shall be distributed among the said persons in the manner shown below against their names :— Name and address of nominees. Relationship with subscriber. Age. ''Amount or share of accumulations to be paid to each. ■ i 19 , at Signature of subscriber ; Two witnesses to signature. 2 •Noro.-This eolmnn shonld bTSikd in ao asTo cover the whole amount that may stand to the credit of the subscriber in the Fund at any time III. When the subscriber has no family and wishes to nominate one person. I, having no family as defined in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, hereby nominate the person mentioned below to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount lias become payable, or having become payable has not been paid Name and address of nominee. Relationship with subscriber. Age. .19 .at. Signature of subscriber. Two witnesses to signature. o Name and address of nominees. Relationship with subscriber. Age. *Amount or share of accumulations to be paid to each. - Dated this 1Q Signature of subscriber Two witnesses te signature. 2 \ - . ouuuju ue micu in so as to cover the whole amount that may stand to the credit of tie subscriber in the Fund at any time. Forms of contingent notice of cancellation. I. Where nomination is. in favour of one or more members of the subscriber's family. Without prejudice t® my right under sub- rule (3) of rule 5 of the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules to cancel the nomination made by me on whenever I thmkfit, I hereby give notice that in the event of any dece with stand cancelled. Dated this .day of. at Signature of subeciiber. Two witnesses to signature 1 2 IV.. When the subscriber has no family ami wishes to nominate more than one person. I, having no family as defined in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, hereby nominate the persons mentioned below to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount has become payable, or haying become payable has not been paid, and direct that the amount shall be distributed among the said persons in the manner shown below against their names :— ?»*_ .19the said nomination shall- (a) in the event of the person/ anv n-r fort^ilhl^nd^ance 1 '-^ 1 ?^ -^' th0 301(1 - Nfn.II. Where nomimation is in favour of one or more persons not being members of the sub scriber's family. i Without prejudice to my right under sub- mle (3) of rule 5 of the Indian Civil Service Provident I^und Rules to cancel the nomina tion made by me on , whenever I think fit, I hereby give notice 1 hat i»-th« ftvent f tlw person any of the thereunder predeceasing me^pp-irT the event of my here after acquiring a family as defined in rule 2 of the^saia rules, the said nomination shall f uj ^I i with.-..^tand ^an^elled. Dated this dav of Signature of subscriber Two witnesses to signature. 1.... « L. T. GHOLAP, Deputy Secretary to the Govt, of India. at, 19 No. D. 13-A.-S.D.I42. Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners • the High Commissioner for India, London • the several Departments of the Government of India [including the financial Advised Mili tary Finance, the Financial Adviser Commu nications, the Additional Financial Adviser, Supply F inance, the Joint Financial Adviser, Munitions Production, Calcutta ; the joint Financial Adviser, Supply, the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor-General, and the Secretary to the Governor-General (Public)] ; the Political Department; the Crown Finance Officer ; the Federal Court; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Secretaries to His Excel- hncy the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India ; the ■ Mint Masters, Calcutta and Bombay ; the Master, Security Printing, India ; all Account ants-General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Accountants-General under the Accountant General, Posts and Telegraphs, and the Ac counts Officer, Telegraph Check Office, Calcutta ; .the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control • Ihe Chief Accounts Officers East Indian Rail- 'ay, Calcutta, Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta, Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay, North Western Railway, Lahore and Burma Railways, Simla ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; the IHrector ol Audit, Defence- Services ; the ( hief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil) and the Deputy Controllers of ' Supplv Accounts (Civil), Calcutta, and Bombay. By order, etc., H. C. BEAUMONT, I nder Secretary to the Govt, of India. U24rinD—2,572—6-2-43—OJPS\ ^ . «•. ■ •' ■GOVERNMENT OF INDIA FINANCE DEPARTMENT NOTIFICATION Simla, the 14lh April 1943 No. F. 23 (3)-R.-IIi42. —Th&lt;3 following order made by the Secretary of State for India is published for general information :— I ' ' The Indian Civil Service Provident Funds Jtules, 1942. I, Leopold Charles Maurice Stennet Amery. one of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, in virtue of the powers conferred by Section 247 (1) and Sec tion 250 (1) of the Government of India Act. 1933, hereby make, with the concurrence of my Advisers, the following amendment to the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, 1942, namely :— In sub-rule (4) of Rule 4, after the words ' pay ment is made,' the words or tendered ' shall be inserted. / Given under my hand this 9th day of February 3943. (Sd.) L. S. AMERY, One of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State.' L. T. GHOLAP, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. No. F. 23 (3)-R.-II|42, Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners ; the High Commissioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Government of India [including Financial Adviser, Military Finance, the Financial LSFinD—2250—21-4-43—GIPS Adviser, Communications, the Additicmal Fiiumcial Adviser, Supply Finance, the Joint Financial Adviser, Munitions Production, Calcutta ; the Joint I* inancial Adviser, Supply, the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor General, and the Secretary to the Governor General (Public)] the Political Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Secrelarics to Ihs Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of uevenue,; the the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Master ; the Master,. Security Printing, India ; all Accountants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Accountants General under the Accountant General, Posts and I'elegraphs ; and the Accounts Officer, Telegraph Chock Office, Calcutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control ; the F/nancial Advisers and the Chief Accounts Officer, East Indian Railway, Calcutta, Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta, Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay, North Western Railway, Lahore, and Burma Railways, Simla ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Oftee ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil) and the Deputy.Controllers of Supply Accounts (Civil), Cal cutta and Bombay. By order, etc., II. C. BEAUMONT, Under Secretary to the Government of India, VjjEITISH I^SIDEiTClN^H^CONSUIATE -GENEEAL N 0 . 323-67/47 • Jated I5ushire ? the 4th i^elTy. 19 ^4 to A copy of the undemientioned paper(s) .'S^are forwarded The Political The Political The Political His Britannic His Britannic His Britannic for information endorsement No. Agent f iiuscat, Agent, Bahrain, Agent. Kuwait, Majesty's Consul, Bandar Alabas, majesty's Consul, Kerjoan, Majesty's Consul, Khorrsjnshahr, / Mo - s' 7 ice with reference to this office, „ , dated the I 3 ™ 1 APrll, 19 43 . SuA. jBy order, Secret Besiden Enclos ure(s) tical Gulf 1. Government of India finance department Notification No.i}\23(8)-H # Il/43 dated the 11th OctCber, 1943, 2 # Government of India, Finance -Department Notification NO.D.38-SV43, dated the 14th October, 1943.Provided that subscription shall be optional during any period of extra ordinary leave without leave salary or leave with leave salary under Rule 88 of the Fundamental Rules or while the subscriber is under suspension during which reduced remuneration is drawn. Provided further in the ease of a member permitted to serve in the armed forces of the Crown during an emergency, that the amount of his subscription to the Fund shall be calculated on the emoluments he would have drawn if he had remained on duty in civil employment. 4. Except as provided in sub-rule (6) intemt at the rate determined for each year according to the method of calculation prescribed by the Secretaj^ of State shall be credited to each subscriber as from the 31st March of each ye® subject to the following conditions — (1) Interest for 12 months shall be credited on the amount at the credit of the subscriber on the 31st March of the preceding year, less any sums withdrawn under Rule 7 during the year ; (2) Interest shall be credited for each month of the year upon the sum by which the minimum amount standing to the credit of the subscriber between the close of the fourth day and the end of the month exceeded the amount on which interest is credited under sub-rule (I), subscriptions paid by deductions from emoluments being treated for the purposes of this sub-' rule as having been deposited in the Fund on the first day of the month in which payment is actually made ; (3) If the total amount of interest allowed under sub-rules (1) and (2) contains a fraction of a rupee it shall be rounded off to the nearest whole rupee, eight annas and more counting as the next higher rupee ; (4) Before the amount at the credit of a subscriber is finally paid, his account shall be credited with interest up to the month preceding that in which the payment is made or tendered,' or up to the end of the sixth month after the end of the month in which he quitted the service or died, which ever of these periods is less ; (5) The rate of interest is liable to revision on the 1st April of each year without notice ; (6) Interest shall not be credited to the account of a Muhammadan sub scriber if lie informs the Account Officer that he does not wish to receive it, but if he subsequently asks foj* interest, it shall be credited with effect from the 1st April of the year in which he asks for it. 3. (1) loach subscriber shall as soon as may be after joining the Fund se^k to the Account Officer a nomination conferring on one or more persons the righ to receive the amount that may stand to his credit in the Fund, in the event of his death before that amount has become payable, or having become payable has not been paid : I ro\ ided that if, at the time of making the nomination the subscriber has a family the nomination shall not be in favour of any person or persons other than the members of his family. (2) If a, subscriber nominates more than one person under sub-rule (1), he shall specif\ in Hie nomination the amount or share payable to each of the nominees in such manner as to cover the whole of the amount that may stand to his credit in the Fund at any time. (3) A subscriber may at any time cancel a nomination by sending a notice in writing to the Account Officer : Provided that the subscriber shall along with such notice send a fresh nomi nation made in accordance with the provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2).(4) Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-rule (3) a subscriber shall along with every nomination made by him under this Rule send to the Account Officer— (a) a notice to the effect that in the event of any of the nominees prede ceasing him, the nomination in respect of the deceased nominee shall forth with stand cancelled, and (b) if the nomination is made at a time when the subscriber has no family, a notice to the effect that in the event of his thereafter acquiring a family the nomination, shall forthwith stand cancelled, (5) Immediately on the occurrence of any event by reason of which the notice wf cancellation referred to in sub-rule (4) becomes operative and the nomination which that notice relates consequently stands cancelled, the subscriber shall send to the Account Officer a fresh nomination made in accordance with the pro visions of sub-rules (1) and (2). (6) Every nomination made, and every notice of cancellation given, by a subscriber shall, to the extent that it is valid and operative take effect on the date on which it is received- by the Account Officer. 6.—(1) The account of each sub^briber who either joined the Indian Civil Service after 4th January, 1923, and has elected to join the Fund under the option allowed by the Rules previously in force, or has joined the Indian Civil Service after the institution of the Fund shall, subject to the provisions of sub- rule (2), be credited on retirement or previous death with the sum of Rs. 6,000 and the accounts of other subscribers shall be credited with the amounts speci fied in the Schedule to these Rules. (2) This contribution shall not be paid to any subscriber who is dismissed or removed from the service or who resigns without being entiUpd to a gratuity or annuity. (3) If a subscriber retires under the Premature Retirement Rules the amount of the contribution shall be cletermined by the Secretary of State. 7. Subject to the conditions hereinafter stated ;— (a) subscriptions to a family pension fund approved in this behalf by the Secretary of State, or payments towards an insurance policy may, at the option of a subscriber, be substituted for the whole or part of the sub scriptions to the Fund ; (b) any amount standing to the credit of a subscriber in the Fund may be withdrawn to meet :— || (i) payments towards an insurance policy ; (ii) purchase of a single payments insurance policy ; (iii) payment of a single premium or subscriptions to a family pension fund approved in this behalf by the Secretary of State. • Provided that no amount shall be withdrawn to meet ^any demand or pur chase made or effected more than 12 months before the withdrawal. 8.— (1) If the total amount of any subscriptions or payments substituted under clause (a) of Rule 7 is less than the amount of the subscription payable to the Fund under Rule 3, the difference shall be rounded off to the nearest rupee in the manner provided in that Rule and paid by the subscriber as a sub scription to the Fund. (2) If the subscriber withdraws any amount standing to his credit in the Fund for any of the purposes specified in clause-(b) of Rule 7, he shall, subject to his option under clause (a) of that Rule, continue to pay to the Fund the \ subscriptions payable under Rule Si9. If the Interest of the subscriber in the family penaion fund ceases in whole or in part from any cause whatsoever, the account of the subscriber in the Fund shall forthwith be reimbursed by the amount of the refund secured by the subscriber from the family pension fund, which amount shall in default of reimbursement be deducted from the subscriber's emoluments by instalmenta or otherwise as may be directed by Government. 10.—(1) Government will not make any payments on behalf of subscribers to insurance companies nor take steps to keep the policy alive, (2) The policy shall be on the life of the subscriber himself and shall, un less it is a policy expressed on the face of it to be for the benefit of his wife 3nd| or his children or any of them, be such as may be legally assigned by the suj^ scriber himself to the Governor-General or the Governor of the Province undc. whose administrative control he is serving. (3) The policy may not be affected for the benefit of any beneficiary other than the wife and|or children of the subscriber or any of them. 11— (1) The policy shall within three months or, if the headquarters of the insurance company are outside India, within such longer period as the Ac count Officer, if he is satisfied by the production of the completion certificate (interim receipt), may fix, after the first withholding of a subscription or with drawal from the Fund in respect of the policy be delivered to the Account Offi cer, but if it is not a policy expressed on the face of it to be for the benefit of the wife andior children of the subscriber or any of them, it shall be assigned to the Governor-General or the Governor of the Province under whose administra tive control he is serving, before such delivery. | (2) If the policy is not delivered within the period of three months or such longer period as the Account Officer may have fixed, any amount withheld or withdrawn from the Fund in respect of the policy shall, with interest thereon the rale provided in Rule 4, forthwith be paid or repaid as the case may be by the subscriber to the Fund, or in default be ordered by Government to be recovered by deduction from the emoluments of the subscriber by instalments or otherwise. (3) Notice of assignment of the policy shall be given by the subscriber to the insurance company and the acknowledgment of the notice bv the insurance company Rhall be sent to the Account Officer within three months of the date of assignment. 12. (1) Save as provided by sub-rule (2) of Rule 14 when the subscribcr -^P^ (a) quits the service, or (b) has proceeded on leave preparatory to retirement and applies to the Account Officer for reassignment or return of the policy, or (c) ^hile on leave lias been permitted to retire or is required to retire on frrounds of ill-health and applies to the Account Officer for reassign ment or return of the policy, or Cd) pays or repays to the Fund the whole or any amount withheld or withdrawn from the Fund for any of the purposes, ^other than in respect of a family pension fund mentioned in Rule 7 with interest thereon at the rate provided in Rule 4, the Account Officer shall make over the policy to the subscriber, having first reassigned to him any policy assigned to the Governor-General or the Governor i6 ' / ■ 1 •.■■■■ • • Providod that if a subscriber to whom elanse (b) or clause (c) applies, re- tnnis to dnty any policy so reassigned or made over shall, if it has not matured or been assigned or charged or encumbered in any way, be again assigned to the Governor-General or Governor as the case may be, and again be delivered to the Account Officer as the case may be in the manner provided in Rule 11 and thereupon the provisions of these Rules shall so far as may be, again apply in respect of the policy ; Provided further that if the policy has matured or been assigned or charg ed or encumbered in any way the provisions of sub-rule (2) of Rule 11 shall apply. (2) Save as provided by sub-rule (2) of Rule 14, when a subscriber dies ^before quitting the service, the Account Officer shall make over the policy to the beneficiary if any, or if there is no beneficiary, to such person as may be legally entitled to receive it, having first reassigned any policy assigned to the Gover nor-General or the Governor to such person as may be legally entitled to receive it. 13. Save as provided in sub-rule (2) of Rule 14, if a policy delivered to the Account Officer matures before the subscriber quits the Service and before his death the Account Officer shall make over the policy to the subscriber, who shall pay or repay to the Fund the whole of any amount withheld or withdrawn from the Fund in respect of the policy with interest thereon at the rate pror vided in Rule 4 and in default the provisions of sub-rule (2) of Rule 11 shall apply, but if the policy has been assigned to the Governor-General or the Gover nor the Account Officer shall realise the amount assured and shall deduct there from the whole of any amount withheld or withdrawn from the Fund in res pect of the policy with interest thereon at the rate provided in Rule 4, and shall place the amount so deducted to the credit of the subscriber in the Fund, the balance if any being, at the option of the subscriber, paid direct to him or placed to bis credit in the Fund. 14.—(1) If the policy lapses or becomes assigned otherwise than to the Governor-General or Governor, charged or encumbered, the provisions of sub-rule (2) of Rule 11 shall apply. (2) If the Account Officer receives notice of an assignment otherwise than an assignment to the Governor-General or the Governor, of, or a charge or encum brance on, or an order of a Court restraining dealings with, the policy or any amount thereon, the Account Officer shall not make over or reassign the policy or realise the amount assured by the policy or dispose of any part thereof, but -^shall refer the matter to the Governor-General or Governor as the case may be. 15. Except as provided in Rule 7, the amount standing to the credit of a subscriber in the Fund shall not be withdrawn until he quits the Service or dies : Provided that a subscriber who has been granted leave preparatory to re tirement or, in the case of one serving in a vacation department, has been allow ed to combine vacation with such leave or who while on leave, is either permitted to retire voluntarily or is required to retire on grounds of ill-health, may with draw the amount standing to his credit at any time between the commencement of the leave or vacation as the case may be, or the date of such permission or requirement as the case may be, and the date pf actual retirement, but if he returns to duty at the end of his leave he shall if required to do so by Govern ment pay to the Fund the whole amount withdrawn by him with interest there on. A subscriber who exercises the option allowed by this proviso shall jiot subscribe to the Fund after such withdrawal unless and until he returns to duty-6 16. On the death of a subscriber before the amount standing to his credit has liecome payable or, where the amount has become payable, before payment has been made. (1) When the subscriber leaves a family— (a; If a nomination in favour of a member or members of his family subsists, the amount standing to his credit in the Fund or the part thereof to which the nomination relates, shall be paid to his nominee or nominees in the proportion specified in the nomination ; (b) If no such nomination subsists or if such/nomination relates only to a part of the amount standing to his credit in the Fund, the whole amount or the part thereof to which the nomination does not relate the case may be shall, notwithstanding any nomination purporting to be in favour of any person or persons other than a member or members of his family be paid to the members of his family in equal shares ; Provided that no share shall be payable to (i) sons who have attained legal majority ; (ii) song of a deceased son who have attained legal majority ; (iii) married daughters whose husbands are alive ; (iv) married daughters of a deceased son whose husbands are alive, if there is any member of the family other than those specified in clauses (i)» (')» (iii) and (iv) of the proviso : Provided further that the widow or widows and the child or children of a deceased son shall receive between them in equal parts only the share which that son would have received if he had survived the subscriber and had been exempt from the provisions of clause (i) of the first proviso, (-) When the subscriber leaves no family, if a nomination in favour of any person or persons subsists, the amount standing to his credit in the Fund or the part thereof to which the nomination relates shall be paid to his nominee or nominees in the proportion specified in the nomination, and if no nomination subsists it shall be paid to the person legally entitled to receive it. 17. All payments from the Fund shall be made in India in Rupees. 18. As soon as possible after the close of each year each subscriber shall be supplied with a statement of his account in the Fund which shall show the opening balance as on let April of the year, the total amount credited or debited^^ during the year, the amount of interest credited as on 31st March of the year- and the closing balance as on that date. 19.— (!) ITnti 1 the commencement of Part II of the Government of India Act. 1935, references in these Rules to the Governor-General shall be construed as references to the Governor-General in Council. (2) In the discharge of his functions under these Rules the Governor shall exercise his individual judgment. 20. i he Indian Civil Service (non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules, dated 2nd December, 1930, are hereby repealed. Given under my hand this 29th day of March, 1943. L. S. AMERY, One of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State*No. D-38-S.DJ43. n ^ Copy forwarded to all Chief CommiKsionera ; the High Commisiioner for India ; the several Departments of the Government of India [including the I' inaneial Adviser, Military Finance, the Financial Adviser, Communications, Additional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance, Joint Financial Adviser, Muni tions Production, Calcutta, Joint Financial Adviser, Supply ; Joint Financial Adviser, Food ; Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor General, Secretary to the Governor General (Public) and Secretary to the Governor General (Reforms)] ; the Political Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Reve- nue ; the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Masters including the Officer-in« Charge, New Mint, Lahore ; the Master, Security Printing, India ; all Account ants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Accountants-General under the Accountant General, Posts and Telegraphs ; the Accounts Offcer, Telegraph L jieck Office, Calcutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control ; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta, Bengal and Assam Railway, Calcutta, Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay, North Western Railway, Lahore ; the Director of Railway Clearing -Accounts Office ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil), Controllers of Supply Accounts, Calcutta and Bombay and Controller of Food Accounts, By order, etc., A. S. LALL, Under Secretary to the Oovernment of India. Li S^FinD—2,560—30-10-43—GiPS \14 Copy af Govt, of India Resolution TTo .F .30(l)-H-11/44 dated the 28th February, 1944. It is announced for general information that the rate of interest on deposits and also on balances at the credit of subscribers to the General provident and other similar funds on the 31st March 1944 as deter ined by the apnroved mehtod (vide G of I , Finance lept Resolution NO.F.37-V.H.II dated the 6th lece ber 1930), is 3*y per cent and that this rate will be in force during the financial year beginning on the 1st April 1944 except in the case of sunscribers who are entitled, under the rules of the Funds, to a higher minimum rate of interest. The funds concer ned are;- 1. The General Provident Fund. 2. The Contributory Provident .^und (India) 3. The Indian Civil Service Provident Fund 4. The India Civil Service( Non-European Members) Provident Fund. xxxxxx ■ exxxx (original in File 15/8)No. D.38A-S.D.|43. &gt; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT Simla, the IMh October 1943, NOTIFICATION With reference to the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provi dent Fund Rules, made by the Secretary of State on the 29th March 1943, the following instructions are issued by the.Government of India lor the guidance of B^ifccribers to the Fund and of Account Officers :— 1. Suhscripiions (Rule 3).—(1) Before proceeding on extraordinary leave without leave salary or on leave with leave salary under Fundamental Rule 88, the subscriber should intimate to the Account Officer in India whether he wishea to subscribe during such leave. No alteration will be permissible in the option so exercised for the period of the leave. If the subscriber fails to intimate be fore proceeding on leave he will be deemed to have exercised his option in favour of subscribing during leave and deductions should be made accordingly. (2) The instructions in sub-para. (1) will apply mutatis mutandis to a subscriber under suspension during which reduced remuneration is drawn. (3) A subscriber transferred to foreign service or sent on deputation out of India shall, before proceeding to join his new duties, intimate to the Account Officer in India the amount of his emoluments while on foreign service or depu tation out of India and any change therein in order to enable the Account Oiii- cer to verify whether the rate of subscription is in accordance with Rule 3. (4) Subscriptions to the Fund will be recovered :— (i) in respect of emolumeuts drawn from a Government Treasury in India or a Colonial or Home Treasury, by deduction from the emoluments ; ^ (ii) in respect of sterling overseas pay by deduction in India from pay ; • • and (iii) in respect of emoluments drawn from any other source, in cash, the subscriber remitting the amount direct to the Account Officer. - (5) All subscriptions made by a member together with interest on such s^cnptions calculated under rule 4 and Government contribution under rule 6 snould be credited to his account in the Fund. 2. Nominations {Rule 5).—Nominations under sub-rule (1), and notices of cancellation under sub-rule (4), should be in such one of the forms appended to these instructions as is appropriate in the circumstances. 3. Contribution by Government (Rule 6).—In the case of a subscriber on foreign service, a contribution of lis. 15 a month should be recovered from the foreign employer towards Government 's liability under rule 6. Such contri bution is payable during duty only. 4. Payments towards policies of insurance or subscriptions to a family pen sion fund (Rule 7).—When a subscriber desires to divert or withdraw money from the Fund to pay subscriptions to an approved Family Pension Fund or a premium towards a policy of life insurance under Rule 7, he shall intimate to his Account Officer on his pay bill or by letter the fact of, and reason for, the reduction or withdrawal of money as the case may be. In the latter case he may also make necessary arrangements with the Account Officer for the with drawal of money from the Fund. tUWiaD ^(2) The Account Officer sliall demand periodically to see the reeeipti or certified copies thereof showing that the amount so withheld or withdrawn hai bten duly applied. Failing the production of such receipts he shall order the recovery oi any amount by which subscriptions have been reduced or any amount withdrawn, with interest thereon at the rate prescribed in Rule 4 from the sub scribers pay or leave salary in one or more instalments as it thinks ht. 5. Assignments and Re-assignments {Rules 11, 12 and 13).—Assignment* lintler rale 11 and re-assignments under rule 12 or 13, as the case may be, should be in such one of the forms appended to these instructions as is appropria^^ in the circumstances. fP 6. Recovery of the amount withdrawn under the proviso to Rule 15. When a subscriber has to repay to the Fund under the proviso to rule 15 the whole amount withdrawn by him, Goveruiuent will determine whether the amouf^ should be repaid in one or more instalments and in cash or securities or boih. 7. Final payments {Rules 15 and 16).—(1) The Account Officer will be responsible for making final payments under rule 15 or 16. If payment ia made under rule 16 any person claiming payment should send a written appli cation to that Officer. In a case where there is doubt or dispute, but only with regard to a portion of the amount standing to the credit of a subscriber, the Account Officer should authorise prompt payment of that portion in regard to ' || which there is no dispute. The persons to whom any amount is payable from the Fund should make their own arrangements to receive payment in India. (2) If the person to whom any payment is to be made from the Fund is a : &gt; 1 una iic, payment should be made to the authority entitled under the law to re- cehe payment on his behalf. (3) bums not claimed for a period of six months after they have become payable will, at the end of the year, be transferred from the account head Inaian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund ' to the account head Deposits ' and treated under the ordinary rules relating to t pusits. Such transfer does not however affect the fiduciary capacity in which the. sums are held by Government. 8. Statement of account (Rule 18).—(1) The Account Officer will assigi® a number to the account of each subscriber, and when paying subscriptions in India, the subscriber should quote this number. (') 'Sub.sctibers are required to satisfy themselves as to the correctness o^ the annua statements. Errors, if any, should be brought to the notice of t» Account Officer within six months of receiving a statement. If no statement ot account is received by the 1st of October, the subscriber should communicate with the Account Officer (3) The Account Officer shall, if required by a subscriber, once, but not more an once, m a year, intorm the subscriber of the total amount standing to hifl written^ 16 U of the last month for which his account has been thereof. APPENDIX A Forms of Nomination ! I. WTien the subscriber has a family and wishes to nominate one member I hereby nominate the person mentioned below, who is a member of my laimly as dehned in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members)3 Provident Fund Rules, to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount has become payable, or having become payable has not been paid :— * Name And address of nominee. Eelatinnfliip with subscriber. Age. Dated this day of 19 , ^t Signature of subscriber Two witnesses to signature. i r 2. II. When the subscriber has a family and wishes to nominate more than one member thereof. f I hereby nominate the persons mentioned below, wlm are members of :ny family as defined in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service (Non-Enrnppan Members) Provident Fund Rules, to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount has become payable, or having become payable has not been paid, and direct that the said amount shall be distributed among the said persons in the manner shown below against their names :— 4 * •Amonft or ffJiara of Name and address of Eelatfon^lp w th Age. accumnlntto be nominees. subscriber. paid to each. • V ' # Dated this day of Signature of subscriber i ° ' Ttvo iciinesses to signature. 1 2 .ia , at •Note.—This column should be filled in so as to cover the whole amount, that may stand to the credit of the subscriber in the Fund at any time. III. 'When the subscriber has no family and wishes to nominate one person. I, havinsr no family as defined in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service (Xon- 'European Members) Provident Fund Rules, hereby nominate the person men.' tionod below to receirs the amotml that may stand to my tftedit in the Fund.f in the event of my death before that amount has become payable, or having Age, Name And address of numinee. t Relatitnship with subscriber. i % 19 , at Signature of subscriber Two witnesses to signature, 1 O IV. When the subscriber has no family and wishes to nominate more than ona person. I, having no family as defined in rule 2 of the Indian Civil Service (Non- European Members) Provident Fund Rules, hereby nominate the persons men tioned below to receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund, in the event of my death before that amount has become payable or having become payable has not been paid, and direct that the amount shall be distri- Name and nddress of tiominees. Relationship with subscriber. Age. •Amount or share of accumulations to be paid to each. &gt;«t • ■ .. .19 , at e- Dated this day of Signature of subscriber .... Ttco uriinesses to signature, 1 2 •Note.—This column should be filled in so as to cover the whole amount that may stand to the credit of Ihe fiubscriber in the Fund at an y time. Forms of contingent notice of cancellation. I. Where nomination is in favour of one or more members of the subscriber's family. Whhout prejudice to my right under sub-rule (3) of rule 5 of the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules to cancel the . nomination made by me on whenever I think fit, I hereby give notice that in the event of the person nominated there .19 M fiersens t* fiu j ceasing me, the said nomination ^/shall' forthwith stand cancelled. ' Dated this I ! day of Signature of subscriber .. j , Two witnesses to signature. 1n II. Where nomination is in favour of one or more persons not being mem bers of the subscriber's family. Without prejudice to my ri^ht under sub-rule (3) of rule 5 of the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules to cancel the nomination made by me on whenever I think fit, I hereby give -lite ~ nominatechtKereunder, prede- notice that m-4be-event-of auy of th^ porBono ceasing me, or 2 of the sa Dated this in the event of my hereafter acquiring a family as defined in id-JttleSp^he^^aiti: nolulnation shall forthwith standr cancetlea. T mo wiinesses to signature, 1 ... 2. .. day of Signature of subscriber .19 , at APPENDIX B Forms of Assignment a) I A.B , of hereby assiprn unto the Governor General in Council the within policv of assurance as security for payment of all sums which iindor Kn'e 14 of the Indian Civil Service (Non -European Members) Provident Fuiul Rules I may hereafter become liable to pay to that Fund. I hereby certify that no prior assignment of the within policy exists. Dated this day of 19 , at Signature of Subscriber. One Witness to signature. (2) We, A.B. (the subscriber^, of and C.D. (the joint assured), . in consideration of the Govprnor General in Council agree- in* at our request to aeeetrt tmymente towards the within nolW of assnra™ m snhstitntion tor the subscriptions nayahle by me the said A.B. to the Tmli n Civil Servic (Non -Enronean Members) Provident Pnnd for, as the ease may be to jecent the withdrawal ot the sum of Rs. from the snm to the credit of the said A.B. in the Tndian Civil Service fNon-Enropean Members) Provident Pnnd for payment of the premium of the within policy of as^iranee herebv iointlv and severally assign un*o the said Governor General in Council the within policv of assurance as security for payment, of all sums which un ler Rule It of the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Prov.dent Fund Rules the, said A.B. may hereafter become liable to pay to that Fund. We hereby certify that no prior assignment of the within policy exists. Dated this ^ ^ ., Signature of Subscriber and the joint Assured. One Witness to signatures. /// l z) o (3) T CD wife of A B,. and the assignee of the within policy, having at the request of A.B., the assured, asrreed to release my interest^ in the policy m favour of AB in order that A-B. may assign the policy to the Govemo*6 4 Ooneral in Council who has agreed to accept payments towards the within policy of Assurance in substitution for the subscriptions payable by A.B. to the liiu'an Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund hereby at the request and by the direction of A.B. assign and I the said A.B. assign and cou- im unto the Governor General in Council the within policy of Assurance as security for payment of all sums which under Rule 14 of the Indian Civil Ser vice (Xon-European Members) Provident Fund Rules the said A.B. may here after become liable to pay to the Fund. 'W e hereby certify that no prior assignment of the within policy exists. Dated this day of ..19 , at Signature of the assignee and the subscriber. ^ One Witness to signatures. on ( j ) Cancellation of the assignment in Form 1 in favour of jjfovernment if one is already in existence ; (ii) Execution of an assignment in favour of the subscriber and his wif® as joint tenants in the following form :— 1 (here state name and description of the assured) do hereby assign and transfer the benefit of the within policy and all moneys receivable thereunder or in respect thereof to myself and my (here state relationship and name) to hold the same unto myself and the said or survivor as joint tenants and I declare that on the death of either, the receipt of the sur- M\or shall be a sufficient discharge to the Insurance Company within named. Dated the day of 19 Witnesses :— (1) r A ■ • &gt;■ (2) i • and (Signature). ^ Hii) Execution of an assignment by the subscriber and his wife in form ao. 2 in favour of Government. N-.te The assignment may be executed on the policy itself either in the sn isci i.ier s handvrriting or in type, or alternatively a typed or printed slip con aiiung the assignment may be passed on the blank space provided for the purpose on the policy. A typed or printed endorsement must be duly assigned and il pasted on the policy it must be initialled across all four margins. Forms of Re-assignment Aii sums which have become payable by the above-named A.B. under Rule 14 of the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules having been paid and all liability for payment by him of any such sums in the future having ceased the Governor General in Council doth hereby re-assign the within policy of assurance to the said A.B. and C.D.jA.B. Dated this day of 19 Executed by Account') Officer of the Fund for and on behalf X Y of the Governor General in Council ^ (Signature of the Account Officer), in the presence of I » • • . V w J - • (one witness who Bhould iu M hia deiijna^ lion and ftddrtsa)^ ■ ■ I1 I (2)' v - v ' The above-named A.B. having died on \he day of 19 , the Governor General in Council doth hereby re-assign the within policy of assur ance to C.D. (Full particulars of person legally entitled to receive the policy). Dated this day of 19 Executed by Account' Officer of the Fund for and on behalf of the Governor General in Council fc in the presence of Y Z (one witness who should add his designa- . tion and address). Z Y (Signature of the Account Officer). (3) The Governor General in Council doth hereby re-assign the irithixi policy to the said A.B.jA.B, and C.D. Duced this day of 19 . Executed by Account' X Y (Signature of the Account Officer). Officer of the Fund for and on behalf of the Governor General in Council in the presence of Y Z ^ (one witness who should add his designa tion and address). L. T. GHOLAP, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, No. D.38-A.S.D.143. Copy forwarded to All Chief Commissioners ; the High Commissioner for India ; the several Departments of the Government of India, [including the Financial Adviser, Military Finance, the Financial Adviser, Communicaiions, Additional Financial Adviser. Supply Finance, Joint Financial Adviser, Muni tions Production, Calcutta, Joint Financial Adviser, Supply ; Joint Financial Adviser, Food ; Secretary, to the Executive Council of the Governor General, Secretary to the Governor General (Public) and Secretary to the Governor General, (Reforms)] ; the Political Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Reve nue ; the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Masters including the Officer-in- Charge, New Mint, Lahore ; the Master, Security Printing, India ; all Account ants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Accountants General under the Accountant General, Posts and Telegraphs ; the Accounts Officer, Telegraph Check Office, Calcutta ; the Director Of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control ; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta, Bengal and Assam Railway, Calcutta, Great ludiau Peninsula Railway, Bombay, North Western Railway, Lahore ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil), Controllers of Supply Accounts, Calcutta and Bombay and Controller of Food Accounts. By order, etc., A. S. LALL, Under Secretary to the, Q over Client of India, U40FiaD—2,550—5-11-43—Q1PS: % P. ^2 (2)-R .ni43 7 ' 1 ^ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA FINANCE DEPARTMENT Stmlfir. the 30^A, March 1944 NOTIFICATION r l Governor General in Council is pleased to mAke the following amendments in the Forms of contingent notice of -cancellation in Appendix A to the procedural instructions issued in connection with the Indian Civil Service (Non- European Members) Provident Fund Rules and published witli the notification of the Government of India, in the Finance De partment No. D .--vS-A .-S.D.|4^. dated the 14th October 194 &gt; aainely — i/\l) In Form T of the said Forms, after the words ' the said £Li&gt;raination M , the words ' so far as it relates to the person, * predeceasing me ' shall be inserted ; ^ (2) In Form II of the baid Forms, for the words and figure ' in the event of - t ^-^ elsou , nominated thereunder pre- nuy of the persons deceasing 'me, or in the event of my hereafter acquiring a family as defined in rule 2 of the said rules, .the said nomination shall forthwith stand cancelled the folloVving shall be substituted, namely :— u the said nomination shall— ^ (a) in the event of „ thc .P ers o n nominated there- l ■ ' any of the persons under predeceasing mq, forthwith stand cancelled so far a'5 it relates to the persons predeceasing me, or k\(b) in the event of my hereafter acQuiring a family as v..-fined in rule 2 of the said rules forthwith stand can celled in its entirety.' K. R. P. AIYANGAR, Addl. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. No. F. 32 (2)-R.IIl43. -Copy forwarded to all Chief Commission era ; the High Com- miwioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Oovernmout of India [including Financial Adviser, MilitaryFinance, the Financial Adviser, Communications, the Addi tional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance, the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Munitions Production), Calc&gt;&gt;*&lt;a ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Cotton Textiles) ; the • ait Financial Adviser (Food)] ; the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor General, and the Secretaries^to the Governor General (Public), (Reforms), and (Personal^—- the Political Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the F, .eral Court ; fhe Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy ; the Oontral Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Masters, Calcutta and Bombay ; the Officer-in-Charge, New Mint, Lahore ; the Master, Security Printing, India ; all Accountants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Account ants General under the Accountant General, Posts and Tele graphs ; and the Accounts Officer, Telegraph Check Office, Calcutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officerei under his control ; the Financial Adviser and Chief Accounts Officer, East Indian Railway, Calcutta, Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta, Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay, North Western Railway. Lahore ; and Burma Rai 1 - ways, Simla ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Con troller of Supply Accounts (Civil) ; the Controllers of Supply Accounts (Civil), Calcutta and Bombay, and the Controller of Food Accounts. By order, eitc., j - v B. GRICE, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. LlwfluD—SfiO -12 4-44—fW.S„ No. F.23 (7 )-R .nl43. GOVERNMKNT Of INWA. *■' . . FINANCE DEPARTMENT. iSimia, the 25th November, 1943. NOTIFICATION. The iollov^ing rcuoiution by tlie Secretary of State lor India is published 'for general iuiormaUou :— ^ '♦'THE INDIAN CIVIL SERVICE PROVIDENT FUND RULES, 1942. xj Leopold Charles Maurice Stennet Amery, one oi His Majesty's Priccipal Secretaries of- State, in virtue of the powers conferred by section 247 (1) and Section 250 (1) of the Governmeut of India Act, 1935, hereby make, with the concurrence of my advisers, the following amendments to the - 5 l^iau Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, 1942, namely— p. | ' After rule 3, there shall be inscrte4 the following rule 3A. ^1) Every person who on the 3rd June 1942, was a subscriber to the lund shall be entitled to elect whether he will be governed by rules 5 and 12 or by rule 12A. (2) Unless such person has within three months from tlie date of the publication of this rule in theiSfiicial Gazette or. if he was on leave on that date, within three months of his return to duty, no tilled in writing to the Account Officer that he'elects to bo governed by rules 5 and 12 or oy rule 12A as the case may be, he shall be deemed to have elected to be governed by nuc 12A. ^ (3) An election no titled to the Account Officer or deemed to have been made shall be final, and if a subscriber who has elected or is deemed to have elected to be governed by rule 12A haa previously made a nomination under rule 5, the nomination shall be deemed to have been cancelled (4) If such person died on or after the date of the publication of this rule in the Gazette ot India with no election made or deemed to have been made, action shall be taken in accordance with rUle (sf If such person has died on or after the 3rd June 1942, but before the date of the publiea- tion of this rule in the Gazette of India and payment in accordance with clause (b) oi sub-rule (1) of rule 12 has not been made before the last named date, action shall be taken in accordance with ^ le 2 2 Di sub-rule (1) of rule 5, for the words 'shall as soon as may be after joining the Fund send to the Account Officer a nomination ', there shall be substituted the following words . to the Account umcer a n , elected for the provisions of rule 12A, send to i^e tint OffiSr, as soon as may bo after the^commg into force of these rules or after ^ 3 rfnlfl/Z^htwor-l'^deVhTa^criber' there shall be substituted the word, /if a, snb&amp;criber other than one who has, or is deemed to have, eleeted for the previous of rule 12A dies.' l^l^lfS^r credit, „a sha.,™, the/~N J nmount to that peison. But if a widow or children survive the deceased subscriber, then, unless the Acsount Officer has received from him a direction to the contrary in writing, Rs. 5,000 of the sum standing to the credit of the subscriber at the time of his decease, or the whole of such sum if it be less than Ks. 5,000, shall be payable to the widow, or if there be no widow, to the children, or to such person as may be authorised by law to rooeive payment on behalf of the widow or the children as the case may be.' Given under mv hand this 20th day of October 1943. (Sd.) L. S. AMERY, One of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of (Sd.) L. T. GHOLA. , Deputy Secretary to the Government of No. F.23(7)-R. II143. Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners ; the High Commissioner for India, Lond^ several Departments of the Government of India [including the Financial Adviser, Military Fir the Financial Adviser, Communications ; the Additional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance Joint Financial Adviser, Munitions Production ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply ; the Financial Adviser (Cotton Textile), Bombay ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Food)] ; the F| Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the 1'ederal Court j the Secretary to the Executive cil of the Governor General ; ihe Secretaries to the Governor General, (Public), (Personal (Reforms) ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; and the Private and Military Secretai His Excellency the Viceroy. , 4 ^ i Copy also forwarded to the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General ; the Misters, ' Bombay and Calcutta; the Officer-in-Charge, New Mint, Lahore*; the Master, Se Printine, India ; all Accountants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Accountants (icnoral the Accountant General, Posts and Telegraphs, and the Accounts Officer, Telegraph Check ! Calcutta ; the Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta, Eastern Bengal Ra Calcutta; Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay, North Western Railway, Lahore and r Railvavs Simla : the Director of Railway Audit and all Ranway Audit Ufhcers undei his cot the Director -)f Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts ; and Controller of Food Accounts. ^ By ^ A. S. LALL, Under Secretary to the Government of iNo. 1 R C '-6 r, /^7 BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE-GENERAL, BUSHIRE, dated th* Jrne, 1944. A copy of the^undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Ag&lt;5nt, Muscat, . Th^ Political Agent, Bahrain,- The Political Agent, Kuwait, H|.s Majesty 1 s Consul, Bandar Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr, for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement N^'. the ,1944 By order. Not if' c-1on from the Government of India in the 'imnce Department No. ^ '3( 6 )-*.-I/'' 0 ~ dated the 15th, Arvi 1 , 1944, f'M Received with External Affairs Department endorsement No. ^.A6-A//^ dotted the ^9th. Mav , 1944. H.m ' N ■ -V- No. F. 23(6)-R.II[42. Government op India. FINANCE DEPARTMENT Simla, the loth April, 1944 NOTIFICATION following order the Secretary of St^e for India is published for general information '* Indian Civil Service {Non-European Membtra) Provident Fund Rules, 1943. 1, Leopold Charles Stennett Amer^, one of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, in virtue of the powers conferred by section 247 and section 250 of the Government of India Act, 1935, hereby make, with the concurrence of my Advisers, the following amendments to the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund \ Rules, 1943, namely :— In rule 2, after sub-paragraph (1) insert the follow ing sub-paragraph (1A) ' Anglo-Indian M has the meaning assigned to that expression in paragraph 26 of part I of the First Schedule to the Govern ment of India Act. 1935 '. In rule 3, for the words ' every non-European member of the Indian Civil Service ' substitute the words ' every non-European (other than an Anglo- Indian) member of the Indian Civil Service'. Given uAder mv hand this 8th dav of March, 1944. , &gt; . (Sd.) L. S. AMERY, One of His Majesttj's Princiml Secretaries of State. B. C. A. COOK, Deputy Secretary in the Government of India. I '— i No. F. 23(6)-R.IIl42. opy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners ; the High Commissioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Government of India [including Financial Adviser, Military Finance ; the Financial Adviser, Communications ; the Additional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance ; the Joint FinancialAdviser, Supply Finance (Supply), New Delhi ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance, Bo^ty ^ the Deputy Financial Advisere, Supply, Laii^e, ( awnpqre and Madras ; the Joint Financial Ad^r r. Supply Finance (Munitions Production), Calcutta ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Cotton Textiles) ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Food)] ; the Secretary to tlie Execiitive Council of the Governor General and the. Secretaries to the Governor General (Public), (Reforms) and (Personal) ; the Political Depart ment ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military arid Private Secretaries to His Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Masters. Calcutta and Bombay, the Officer-in-Charge, New Mint; Lahore ; the Master, Security Printing, India ; all Accountants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputv Accountants ^General under the Accountant General. Posts and Telegraphs ; and the Accounts Officer! Telegraph Check Office, Calcutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officens under his control ; the Financial Adviser and Chief Accounts Officer, East Indian Railway. Calcutta ; Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta ; Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay ; North Western Rail way, Lahore ; and Burma Railways, Simla ; '^le Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; tho Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil) ; Controllers of SumJv Accounts (Civil), Calcutta and Bombay ; the Controller of Food Accounts ; and the ^ v ief Accounting Officer to the High Commissioner - for India. By order, etc. B. GRTCE, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India L82FinD—1000—1-5-44—GIPS/No. 2070-67/47• BHITISH B^SlXmCTf AND OONSUIAl^ OjSHSHAL, HJSHIEB, Dated 14th. Septem 'Der, 1944. hy A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to:- 1. The Political Agent, Muscat, 2. Ihe Political Agent, Bahrain, 3. ihe Political Agent, Kuwait, 4. His Majesty's Consul, ^andar AtToa' 5. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, and 6. His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshah in continuation of this office letter No. 1330- 67/47 dated the 2nd. June, 1944. Letter No. F, 23(8).E # 13/44 dated the ^nd. March, 1944, with enclosures from the Govt, of India, ianarice iteparlanenb received under Govt, of India ilztemal Affairs Department endorsement No. P.55-V44 dated lath. liay, 1944. for Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, NSNo. P.-23(8)-R. III44. 1 y GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Simla, the 22nd March, 1944. Fhom B. GRICE, E squire, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, to All Provincial Governments. Subject ;— The Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, 1942. S ir, •[With reference to your letter No. M.-1718(5)lX.-60- 1943, dated the 6th December 1943]. I am directed to forward for information a copy of the correspondence!(letter), noted below from which it will be seen that Accountants General are being asked to obtain from the subscribers to the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund contingent notice of cancella tion in the revised forms i— (1) Letter from the Government of the United Pro vinces No, M.-1718(5) IX.-()0-1943, dated the 6th December 1943. ['J) Letter to Accountants General and Comptrollers No. P.-23 (8)-11.11143, dated the 22nd March 1944. I have the honour to be, • ' ^ Sir, Your most obedient servant, B. GRICE, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. No. F.-23 (8) -R.-II|43. Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners ; the High Commissioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Government of India (including Financial Adviser, .Military Finance, the Financial Adviser, Communications ; the Additional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Supply) ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Bombay); the Deputy 1' inancial Advisers, Supply Finance, Lahore, Cawnpore and Madras ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Muni tions Production), Calcutta ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Cotton Textiles); the Joint Financial Adviser (Food); the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor General, and the Secretary to the Governor General (Public), (Reforms) nnd (Personal) ; the Political Department ; the Crown Fi nance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commis- *[ ] To the U. P. Govt, only.sioner, Railways ; the Military -and Private Secretaries to ilis Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India j the Mint Masters, Calcutta and Bombay j the Otificer-iu-Charge, New Mint, Lahore n&amp;e Master, Security Printing, India ; the Deputy Accountants General under the Acc'ouniant General, Posts and Telegraphs ; and the Accounts Officer, Telegraph Check Office, Calcutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control ; the Financial Adviser and Chief Accounts Officer, East Indian Railway, Calciltta ; Eastern Bengal Rail way, Calcutta ; Great Indian Peninsula Railway, Bombay ; North Western Railway, Lahore ; and Burma Railways, Simla ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil) ; the Deputy Controllers of Supply Accounts (Civil), Calcutta and Bombay ; the Control ler of Pood Accounts ; and the Chief Accounts Officer to the High Commissioner for India. By order, etc., B. GRICE, Assistant Secretary to the (fovernmrnt of India. Extract from letter No. M. 1718 (5) X.-60 -1948. dated the Gtii December 1943, from I'viteo Provinces Government, to the Finance Department, Government op India, Simla. ^ * ♦ * • * v, 2. I am also to inquire whether, in view of the Government of India notification No. P.-23(8)-R. Il!48, dated October 11. 1948, and the Provincial Government's notification referred to above, nominations with contingent notices of cancella tion, in the old form, which have already been submitted, by subscribers to the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund, vviil now require to be corrected. If such a correction is necessary, I am to say that the Government of India may if there be no objection, kindly issue instructions to all Accountants General of Provinces which have adopted the Government of India's notification mentioned above, directing them to return the contingent notices of cancellation in the old form, to the sub scribers concerned, for correction, quoting at the same time, the relevant notification of the Provincial Government concern ed by means of which the amended form of contingent notice of cancellation has been adopted. L227FinD—1,000—124-44—-GIPS/ No. F.-23(8)-R.III44. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. « Simla, the 22nd March, 1944. From, B. GRICE, Esquire, Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. To, At.T j Accountants General and Comptrol lers. ♦Subject :— The Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rides, 1942. Sm, . I am directed to say that subscribers to the Indian- Civil Services Provident Fund who may elect to be governed by rules 5 and 12 of the Fund Rules, 1942, may be asked to execute contingent notice of cancellation in an appropriate revised form and to send it to you with a covering memorandum saying that notice in the revised form is being sent with reference to rule 5(4) of the Fund Rules ai^ that it should be substituted for the previous notice on record in your office which should be cancelled. The relevant notification of the Provincial Govern ment concerned by means of which the amended forms of contingent notice of cancellation have been adopted may be quoted at the same time for the information of the subscribers. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, B. GRICE, Assistant Secretary to the Gcfbernment of Indict. L228FinD—1000—12-4-44—GIPSv? \ yr- &amp; 0 P! BRITISH RESIDENCY AJJD CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIH?!. No.2270-67/47. Dated 10th October, 1944. (p^T) A copy of th^iindermentionad papers is forwarded to: Political Agent, Muscat, y Political Agent, Bahrain, Political A^pnt, Kuwait, His Majesty 's Consul, Bandar Abbas, f^O Ilia Hajestj's Consul, Khorranshahr, His Majesty's Consul, Kermn in continuation of this office letter !Io.2070- 67/47 dated the 14th September, 1944. 3y order, Bataram Accev;- * Secretary to tlie Political Resident m tlie Persian Gulf. iiaoiiaii. Letter froc the GoYernmant of India, Finance Department to the Accountant General, United ProTinces, Mo. F.22(13)-R.11/44 dated the 22nd July 1944, together with a copy of letter replied to. (Receired under endorseirient No.F/56-A/44 dated the let September, 1944.) kT., • No. F. 22(13)RIII44. qoveenment op india. . FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Simla, the 22nd July, 1944. F roj^ F. M. CALLAWAY, E squire, ♦ • * V'nder Secretary to the Government of India. To T he ACCOUNTANT GENERAL UNITED PROVINCES, ALLAHABAD. S ubject :— Amendment in the Form of Contingent Notices of Cancellation required to he submitted in connection with the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, 1942. S ir, With reference to your letter No. Fmid.R|949, dated the 30th May 1944, and in continnation of this Department letter No. F. 23(8)-RII|4o, dated the 22nd March 1944, I am directed to say that subscribers to the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund who elect to be governed by rules 5 and 12 of the Fund Rules ]942, and who executed contingent notices of cancellation in the forms prescribed in the Appendix to the procedural instructions issued with Government of India, Finance Department, Notification No. D.13.ASD142, the 14th January 1943, prior to the amendments made under Finance Department Notification No. F. 23(8)-RII|43, dated the 11th October 1943, need not be asked to execute contingent notices of cancellation in the revised form if in their form of nomination they have nominated only one person to receive their fund balances. 2. The same holds good in the case of similar contingent notices of cancel lation executed b}' subscribers to the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund and the Secretary of State's Services (General Provident Fund), in the forms prescribed for those Jfunds prior to the amend ments made under this Department Notification^ Nos. 32(2)-RHj43 and V. 22(17)-RTI'43, dated the 30th March 1944 and The 31st January 1944, res pectively. • ♦J 8. Subject to what is stated in paragraph 2 above, the instructions in this- Depjjrtmmt's letter No. 23(8)-RlI|43, dated the 22nd March 1944. should be put wtffi effect, mutatis mutandis, with respect to subscribers under the Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules, 1943, and the Secretary of State's ^ rvices (General Provident) Rules, 1943. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, F. M. CALLAWAY, Under Secretary to the Government of India. K No. F. 22(13)RII|44. Copy # (with a copy of letter replied to) forwarded to all Provincial Governments ; all Chief Commissioners ; the High Commissioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Government of India [including the 1* inancial Adviser, Military Finance ; the Financial Adviser, Communications ; the Additional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance ; the Joint Financial Adviser,. Supply Innance (Supply), New Delhi ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply 1' inance, Lombay ; the Deputy Financial Advisers, Supply, Lahore, Cawnpore, and Madras ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Munitions 1 ioduolion), Calcutta; the Joint Financial Adviser (Cotton Textiles), Bombay ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Food)] ; the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor General and the Secretaries to the Governor General (Public), (Reforms), and (Personal) ; the Political Departm^t ; Hie (iow n I'inance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Sectetaries to His Excellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India ; the Mint Masters, Calcutta and Bombay, the Officer-in-Charge, New Mint, Lahore ; the Mastei, Security Printing, India, ; all Accountants General and Comptrollers, in continuation of this Department letter No. F. 23(8)-RII|43, dated the 22nd March 1944, the Deputy Accountants General under Jhe Accountant General, Posts and Telegraphs ; and the Accounts Officer, Telegraph Check Office, Cal cutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his * Except in t|e case of Accountant General, U. P.c 3 control ; the Financial Adviser and Chief Accounts Officers, East Indian Rail- way, Calcutta ; Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta ; Great Indian Peninsula Jiailway, liombay ; North Western Railway, Lahore ; and Burma Railways, Simla ; the Director of Railway Clearing Accounts Office ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil) ; ( ontiollers ol Supply Accounts (Civil), Calcutta and Bombay ; the Controller of Food Accounts : the Chief Accounting Officer to the High Commissioner for India and the Government of Burma. By order, etc., F. M. CALLAWAY. Under Secretary to the Government of India- Copi of letter No. fund.r , 949, dated the 30TH may 1944, from office of the Accountant General, Ijnited Provinces, to Government of India, Finance Department. Slbject : Amendments in the Forms of Contingent notice of cancellation required to he submitted in conmectdon with the Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules of 1942. I have the honour to invite a reference to the notification of the Govern ment of India in the Finance Department No. F. 23(8)-RII|43, dated the 11th October 1943, promulgating certain amendments in the forms of Contingent notice of cancellation in the appendix to the procedural instructions issued in connection with the I.C.S. Provident Fund Rules. A question has arisen whether the submission of a ' Contingent notice of cancellation ' in the revised form is necessary even in cases where the nomination is in favour of a single member of a subscriber's family (Form No. 1) or of a single person not being a member of a subscriber's family (Form No. II). The phraseology of the forms of the original contingent notices (as they stood before the aforesaid amendment) is, it would appear, sufficient for cases where a single person is novated as the sole beneficiary. The amendment in the forms made by the insertion of the words so lar as it relates to the person predeceasing me ' r appears to have been necessitated by the consideration that, where the nomi nation was in favour of more persons than one the original form of contingent notice of cancellation was liable to lend itself to the interpretation that the death of any one of such nominees would render the entire nomination void and nugatory. As this would be contrary t^the provision of the substantive Rule 5 (4) (a) of the I.C.S. Provident FuSd Rules, which lays down that in the event of any one of the nominees predeceasing the subscriber the nomi nation in respect of the deceased noiliinee alone shall stand cancelled, this amendment appears to have been designed to make this intention clear in the form of Contingent notice itselff This anomalous position has probably arisen \from the fact that a common form has been devised for Contingeni notice of Cancellation for cases where the nomination is in favour both of one and of moie than one person, and the amendment, which was primarily intended to coa er cases of the latter class alone has, unintentionally perhaps, rendered itself applicable to the other class also. In this office, some 11 Contingent notices of Cancellation ' in the original form in respect of nominations made by I.C.S. officei s in favour of one person only have already been received and recorded after acceptance, but it is for consideration whether, in the circums-tances stated abo\e, fresh Contingent notices in the revised form should be obtained from the officers concerned in such cases. It does not appear to be necessary to do so, as such Contingent notices in the original form would serve the purnose equally well. 2. I would request to be favoured with early orders in the matter, as in the Government of India, Finance Department, No. F. 23(8)-RIl!44, dated the 22nd March 1944, it is specifically directed that subscribers to the I.C.S. Provident Fund who may elect to be governed by Rule 5 and 12 of I.C.S. Provident Fund Rules, 1942 should be asked to execute Contingent notice of cancellation in an appropriate ' revised ' form. - ; &gt; - . - L547FmD—1,000—31-7-44—OIPSRes. P. G. 32. No - 2635-67/47 * British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, tha^^ NoTeml5er , iy 44. ^ V v&gt; K .o A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to^ The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain,^ The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's ^Sfee-Consul, Khurramshahr, for information and guidance with reference to this office endorsement \\&gt;w No. 2270-67/47 , dated the 10tb October, 19 44 I p. 33 Palstsw 'vjcerol so jkf By order, Secretary t:o\ the Political^lesident in the Persian Gulf. Letter from the Government of India in the N lE2(2)RaiA5' datedthe 28th Septn, 19 44 ilnance Department (Eeceived N i.46-V44, with External Affair Department endorsement dated the 7th November. 19 44 ^ Nti MGIPC—S5—163 Pol Res Bushire—10-1-39—2,500.I I■No. P.32(2)-RJIl43. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. Simla, ihc 2Sth September 1944. NOTIFICATION. Tlie following amendments by the Seerotary of State for India are published for general information:— 'Indian Civil'Service {Non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules, 1943. ^ ^ Amendments, dated August 9, ,1944. I. Leopold Charles Maurice Stennett Amery, one of TIu&gt; Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, in virtue of the powers conferred by section 247(1) and section 250(1) of'the Government of India Act. 1935, hereby make, with the concurrence of my Advisers, the following amend ments to the Indian Civii Service (Noni-Eiiropean Members) Provident Fund Rules, 1943, namely:— 1. After sub-clause (6) in Rule 5 the following shall be inserted— (7) Nothing in this rule shall be deemed to invalidate, or to require the replacement by .a nomination thereunder of a nomination made before these Roles came into force under the corresponding rule heretofore in force. . 2. Rule 13 shall be reconstructed as follows— 13. Save as provided in Sub-Rule (2) of Rule 14— (1) If a policy delivered to the Account Officer matures before the subscriber quits the Service and before his (^eath, the Accounts Ofilcer shall m«ke over the policy to the subscriber, who shall iinjnedia- lely on receipt of the policy moniies from the insurance company pay or repay to the Fund either— 1 (a) the whole of any amount withheld or withdrawn from the Fund in respect of the policy, together with interest thereon at the rate provided in Rule 4, or (b) an amount equal to the amount assured, together with any accrued bonuses, whichever is less, and in default the provisionb of Sub-Rule (2) of Rule 11 shall ^tpply. (2) If a policy assigned to the Governor General or t!he Governor , irfatures before the subscriber quits the Service and before his death, the Accounts Officer shall realise the amount assured, together with any accruod bonuses, and shall either—- (a) place the amount so realised io the credit Of the subscriber in the Fund, or (b) if the amount so realised is greater than the whole of the amounit withheld or withdrawn from the Fund 1 in respect of the policy, with interest thereon at the rate provided in Rule 4, deduct therefrom the whole of the amount so withheld or withdrawn and place the amount so deducted to the credit of the subscriber in theFund, the balance being at the option of the subscriber, paid direct to him or placed to his credit in the Fund. These amendments shall lia\e effect, and be deemed always to have had effect, from the 29th March, 1943. Given/ under by hand this 9th day of August, 1944. L. S. AMEHY, One of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State. K. R. P. AIYANGAJl, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. ' ' No. F.32(2)-R.II!43. '/ Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissions; the Higfr Commissioner for India, London; the several Departments of the Government of India fincludng Finaincial Adviser, ^lilitat^' ]&lt; inance; the Financial Adviser, Communications ; the Additional Financial Adviser, Supply Finance ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Supply) ; the Joint FirJincial Adviser, (Supply Finance) 1 , Bombay; the Deputy Financial Advisers (Supply Finance), JLahore, Cawnpore and ^Madras; the Joint Financial Adviser (Supply Finance) (Munitioais Production), Calcutta: the Joint Financial Adviser (Cotton Textiles); the Joint Finlaneial Adviser (FocdJ 1 ; the Secretary to the Executive Council of the Governor General, the Secretaries to the Governor General. (Public), (Retorms) and (Personal); the Political Department; the Crown Fhianfce Officer; the Federal Court; the Financial Commissioner, Railways; the Military and Private Secretaries to His ExeeUency the Viceroy; the Central Board of Revenue; the Auditor General of India; tho Mint. Masters, Calcutta and Bombay; the'Officer-in-Charge, New Mint, Lahore; the Master,, Security Printing, India; all Accountants General and Comptrollers; the Deputy AceonrSants General under the Accountant General. Posts and Telegraphs; and the Accounts Oflicer, Telegraph Check Office, Calcutta; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control, the Financial Adviser and Chief ACcoilnts Officers, East Indian Railway, Calcutta, Eastern Bengal Railway, Calcutta, Great Indjan Pen'insula Railway, Bombay,. North Western Railway, Lahore; and Burma Railways. Simla; the Director of Audit, Defence Services; the Chief Controller of Supply Accounts (Civil); Controllers of Simply Accounts (Civil), Calcutta and Bombay; the Controller of Pood Aec its, and the Chief Accounting Officer to the High Commissioner for Im^a; Government of Burma, Controller oi Supply Accounts New Delhi. By drder, etc., F. M. CALLAWAY, Under Secretary to the Oovernment of India. LSilFiuD—1,200—13-1044—GI^SNo. F. 23 (4)-R.IIl44 government of india FINANCE DEPARTMENT * Simla, the 1th December, 1944 NOTIFICATION The following resolution by the Secretary of State for India is published for general information :— ' THE INDIAN ClflL SERVICE PROVIDENT FUND RULES-, 1942. I, Leopold Charles Maurice Stetanett Amery, one of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State, in virtue of the powers conferred by Siection 247 (1) and Section 250 (1) of the Gov ernment of India Act, 1935 (a), hereby make with the concur rence of my Advisers, the following amendment to th0 Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules, 1942 (b), namely : After Clause (2) of Rule 3A, the following shall be inserted, ' Provided that, if Government is satisfied that any such person has failejd to notify within the prescribed period because he was not aware of this rule, it may permit him to notify in writing to the Accounts Officer concerned that he elects to be governed by Rules 5 and 12.' Given under my hand this 26th day of October, 1944. I (Sd.) L. S. AMERY, One of His Majesty's Principal Secretaries of State.'* (Sd.) B. C. A. COOK, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. No. F. 23 (4)-R.IIl44 9 Copy forwarded to all Chief Commissioners ; the High Com missioner for India, London ; the several Departments of the Government of India [including Financial Advisesr, Military. I Vv Finance ; the Financial Adviser, Communications ; the Adui- tioual Financial Adviser, Supply Finance ; the Joint Financial Adviser, Supply Finance (Supply) ; the Joint Financial Ad viser (Supply Finance), Bombay ; the Deputy Financial Ad visers (Supply Finance), Lahore, Cawnpore and Madras ; the Joint Financial Adviser, (Supply Finance) (Munitions Produc tion), Calcutta ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Cotton Textiles) ; the Joint Financial Adviser (Food)] ; the Secretary t* ,the Executive Council of the Governor General, and the Secreiaries to the GWernor General (Public), (Reforms) and (Personal) ; the Political Department ; the Crown Finance Officer ; the Federal Court ; the Financial Commissioner, Railways ; the Military and Private Seexetdries to His^xcellency the Viceroy ; the Central Board of Revenue ; the Auditor General of India ; vthe Mint Masters, Calcutta .and Bombay ; the Officer-in-Charge, New Mint, Lahore ; the- Master, Security Printing, India, all Accountants General and Comptrollers ; the Deputy Account' ^nts General under the Accountant General Posts and lele- graphs 5 and the Accounts Officer. Telegraph Cheek Office, ( al- cutta ; the Director of Railway Audit and all Railway Audit Officers under his control ; the Financial Adviser and thiol Accounts Officer, East Indian Railway, Calcutta ^Lastern Ben gal Railway, Calcutta ; Great Indian Peninsula Railway, l.om- bay • North Western Railway; Lahore ; and Burma Raihyajs ^ Simla ; Bengal Nagpur Railway, Calcutta ; Oudh and 1 irhut Railway, Gorakhpur ; Bombay Baroda and| Central Jndia Ka way Bombay ; Madras and Southern Mahratta Railway, Mad ras South'Indian Railway, Tri-hinopolv ; the Director of Audit, Defence Services ; the ChM Controller of ^pply Re counts (Civil) : Controllers of Supply Accounts (Civil) C al cutta and Bombay. ; the Controller of Food Accounts, and the Chief Accounting Officer to the High Commissioner for India, and the Finance Department, Burma Government; the Con troller of Supply Accounts. Ndw Delhi and Chief Accnui s Officer (American Purchases). / ^ By order, etc., (Sd.) A. HAMTD, Assistant Secretary to the Government of lnd\&lt;w . . L1180FinD(25)— 1 ,200—23-12-44— gipsf / No. 2282-23/5. The Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political ReBident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to ^The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The political Agent, Muscat, The political Agent, Kuwait♦ and is directed to transmit to In'm a &lt;;opy of the undermentioned documentx British Resid BAHRAIN , Dated.. . .SQ tfo.. .Qc tpb ej... .19 47 Reference to previous correspondence: In continuation of Bushire Residency endorsement No. 602-67/47 to Bahrain, 603-67/47 to Muscat, 604-67/47 to Kuwait, dated 7th February, 1945• Description of Enclosure — — — ————— Name and Date. Subject. Government of India. Llnistry of Finance Notification No. F. 22(6)-Est. .v /46 dated 1st September, 1947.u 1 I ?y No. F, 22 (6 )-Est # V/46. Government of India. Ilinistry of Finance. New Delhi, the 1st September 1947 # I. r 0TIFI CATION The following amendment made by the Secretary of State xo:..- India io published for general information:- .:'i-'il S ervice Provident Fund Rules. 191^1. i . Francis, Sari of Listowel, one of His Ilaiesty's • riiicipal iK.cretM'ics of State, i ' - - * JfS ® :: y Section 24 ?(1) and Section J ^ J. i J w &gt;-&gt; 1_&gt; J w? in virtue of the powers conferred ^7\ r. v ,. ■, 1 250(1) of the Government . :j ; -; nclia Ac S 1^35, hereby make, with the concurrence of my ^(ivxcori; t i olio wing amendment to the Indian Civil Service a i'ia (..cnt uiiu i les, 1942, namely:- J.n Uulo 5 or the said Rules - l 'T 0vi ^ 0 t( ? sub-rule (3) for the words, figures and ci.eto ■ ;ub-^ulcs (1) and (2) ,f the words :7 this mle ?r shall substituted. ^,0 i-or tut-rules (4) and (5), the follov;ing sub-ru^es shall .oe suostitutod, namely;- '(4) A subscriber may provide in a nomination ~ (a) in respect of any specified nominee, that in the event oi i-.iuG predeceasing the subscriber, the right confer red. upon that nominee shall pass to such other person as may be r pecified in the nomination; t 0 ) t'be nomination shall become invalid in the event oi the happening of a contingency specified therein: proviuoa that ii at the time df making the nomination tho^SL -scrioer has no family, he shall provide in the noLi:'^ tion that it shall become invalid in the event oi .is subsequently acquiring a family. (5) Iivn.K &lt; xately on the death of a nominee in respect of whom no special provision has been made in the nomina tion under clause (a) of sub-rule (4), or on the occurronce of any event by reason of which the nomination boc^nuvj invalid in pursuance of clause (b) of sub-rule (4) &lt;-i' th( ^revise thereto, the subscriber shall send to tit. Account Officer a notice in writing cancelling; the nomination, together with a fresh nomination made m acordanco with the provisions of this rule 1 '. Clvon under -ty hand this 23 day of July 1947. Sd/~ Listowel One of His Majesty's'Principal Secretaries of State. Sd/- R # P # Sarathy. Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. )VVl1.,10.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000e1_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1490</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000e1</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1490</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 15/49 I.C.S. PROVIDENT FUND RULES.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-21T00:17:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (42 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically. They are followed by file notes (folio 44).</extent><extent>The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Foliation errors: 1, 1A and 1B; 2 and 2A; 3, 3A and 3B; 7 and 7A. Foliation omissions: 40. Pagination ranges: 1B-8; 18-23. Correction slips numbered 1A, 2A, 3A, 3B and 7A are partly stuck down and obscure superseded text on pages 1B, 2, 3 and 7 respectively.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains several printed circular letters, memoranda and published notifications by the Government of India. These were forwarded by the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to the Political Agent, Bahrain and others for information and guidance.Indian Civil Service Provident Fund Rules 1942, as published in the Finance Department Notification dated 7 January 1943; also instructions, guidance and amendments, 1944 and 1947;Indian Civil Service (Non-European Members) Provident Fund Rules 1943, as published in the Finance Department Notification dated 14 October 1943; also instructions, guidance and amendments, 1944 and 1947.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000e1#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>