<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000f3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T03:32:38.546Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROMindex to irile 14/135. Captain BirdwoodJc report 2^-29. Deceased gent * s debts 13-16, 40-4'.., ^6 . risohief with landing arrange ^ents of B .I. ''-100. Shaikh's excuses 9'-100. Quarters for Agent - agreement between shaikh c-nd Residency Agent 55-79. Shaikh fails to carry out agreement, o .0-^2. •' f ' ' ' • y - Shaikh's excuses for not allowing B.I. Agent to land 3. % X . precis• B.I.Agent dies at Debai. i: ew arent sent out. snai^h refuses to allow hin to l'nd. Oo^nt Bird coo. ',o^s I - in to Debai. He is landed. £5.1.Agent finds groat difficulty In obtaining quarters, ^osideiicy ^©nt hcr^aii ^rra:ir^es it after rauch difficulty. Letter of warning sent to s'laiMi o Dotal, question of debts of Ifete B.I.As-eri to Coy settled&lt;r 3 Telegram. X.T. From - Consul, Bunder Abbas. To - Resident, Bushire. Words. 1S5. Dated and received 6th October 191C. * / Very urgernt. Your 1101 Mirza Ismail proceeded to Debai to examine accounts and put Abu Tafib in charge. On arrival of steamer Sheikh's man informed them that he had orders from Sheikh to forbid either of them landing. ▼ Residency Agent was away at Ras-el-^Kheima. Captain induced Sheikh's man to send letter of recommendation from New to Residency Agent ashore to Sheikh. Ship was delayed three hours to permit of reply being received, but finally left without reply. Mirza Ismail says that he heard locally that Mohammed Khan nephew of late Agent I'Ohammed Ibrahim had gone to Sheikh and asked him to oppose new Agent being sent there. Biscoe. Telegram. En. cl. From - Resident, Bushire. To- Consul, Bunder Abbas. No. 1105.. Dated 6th October 1912. Urgent. Keep Mohamned Ismail for present. Cox. Sent. D.F.S.Tologran - X.T. From - resident, Buahire. To - 0.G.'Lawrenco', Fao u/o C.G. a^O. 1109. Dated 7th October 1912. •flease proceed Moiia^nnerail. Uray Mackenzie, Busreh, has been asKed to coimnunicate with you there this evening and may want to send a repreeentative back here by 'Lawrence'; if go please comply. Resident• Telegram - En.cl. From - Resident, Bushire. To - Gray (= Gray luackenzie) Busreh. Dated 7th October 1912. Following for 'Lawrence' -ohanm'srah. Begins, 'If Gray Mackenzie desire send representative Bushire please bring him. Resident. Telegram - X.T. From - itesident, Bushire. To - 0.0.'Lawrence' u/o G.C. Wo.1110. Dated 7th October 1912. ky last message missed you. lou need not necessarily Arrive before Wednesday morning, so if you have not been ikiOhammerah, please do so if time admits and bring Gray Mac kenzie's representative. Resident• pi1 Telegram. En. cl. From - Resident, Buchiro. To - Consul, Bunder Abbas. No. 1123. Dated 3th October 1912. ,, Lawr0nc^ ,, xvitli Birdwood will call and piok Mohammed Ismail on Frida.y or Saturday. Cox.■ !S - m $ -L /^? Brltisb 3nbia Steam navigation Company ''Eimiteb ' - ^ ^ tVoa^m, 5th October 1912. Lieut-Col Sir Percy Z. Cox, K.C .I .E., H.B.M 's Political Re±»ident &amp; Consul Gtiitfal, B U SHIRE. W« have the honor to confirm our telegram t# you yesterday 1 » date advising that Mirsa Mahomed lamail, whom Bahrein Agents had sent down to Dubai to repraaent tha Company there, owing to the death of Haji Jlahomed Sferaiilm! Was not allovred, 'by order of the Sheik, to land at that port, and ask ing you to use your good offices ta aaalat ua to ^rr&amp;Ajta fa^ him return to IXihai without further delay as tha position is serious seeing that at the present tima wa have na one ta represent the Company or to receiva oar«a frm -ateawarf and deliver same to consignees. We note from your reply^ithat you are already In communication with our Bushire Agents, and trust tbat evtry- thing &amp;as 'been satisfactorily arranged* Sir, We have the honor ta be, Sly, Your obedient servanda, Agents.ho * Z/ [p of 1912 * british Reslddnoy and Consulate Buahir®, October 1912. ? To Sheikh Butti bin Soheil, Chief of Debui. A *0 • Ihe Agentu of the Britiah indlu uompany informed me a few dayp ago that their agent K.t Jebai Muharsmad Ibrahim havlnf died suddenly at Bahrein, they were obliged natural ly to send another representative there to take over ohargt of their agency. Knowing your reluctance to receive a European at present, they sent their Muhammadan employe Muharmad Ismail and an Assistant also a Muhammadan to take over charge. instead of yonr being obligsd for thoir consideration of your wishes, I now learn from them with the greatest surprise that you have refused to allow these two persons to land at your port, and that the ship which took them after being delayed for some hours on this account, hsad to take tbeni away to Bunder Abbas. 1 am at a loss to understand the reason for your action but it is said that you allowed yourself to be made the tool of some mischievous intrigue on the part of the late Muhammad Ibrahim's relations, in any care the matter is so urgent and serious that I have thought tt necessary to de pute my Firftt Assistant, Gaptain Birdwood, to proceed in the R*I.M.S. 'Lawrence' with a representative of the Briti sh India Company, and having picked up j uhanmad isrhall and hie Assistant at Bunder Abbas, to go on to uebai, and on receipt of this letter 1 must insist on your at once receiving Muhanmad Ismail and his companion on shore and giving them every assistance* t'urtheriTiore, ae soon as this letterletter r«aoheR you, you should procd^d on board and gir« Captain pirdwood an explanation of your previous refusal to allow these persons to land in the firat insteince. Even now yoi are rendering yourself liable for compensation to the Company for the loss and inconvenience to which ycur ill-advised action has put them. If you fail to act at once in accordance with this letter, i shall have to send a very unfavourable report to Government, and am of opinion that they will regard the matter very serioui a ly and will not at all tolerate such action from you. This is what had to be explained and salaams. (sa) r.Z .Cox, .Lieut-Colonel, Political Renidert in the Persian Gulf.12. Ho, &lt;%! J of 1912. British Residency and Consulat®-.G«n«ral, BushiOctober 1912. (b To i'he Hesldenoy ^g»nt, Shar^ah. A • U • ihe Pirat AeaistaDD, Captain birdwood, will b« on board the ,, Lawrenoe ,l and will send you this letter, un rncsipt of it you should proceed on bttard or depute jrour sc v n hlsa to accompany him to Jeba| and arrange for the lending of ituhamraad Ismail and his assistant to take over charge cr the xiriuish India Agency in succesBion to the late fcuhammad Ibrahim# Captain Birdwood will show you the letter which 1 have written to Sheikh Butti and you should by all means induce -hoikh Butti to receive ^uha-nmad IsTTiail on shore and ^l?e him necessary aosistance. if there ia need for it, you must arrang» to stay at Uebai for some time yourself and see that ft-.uharnmad Ismail's mtt*±m affairs progress satis factorily. The Admiral is now in the Gulf and if sheikh Eutti ^ives any more trouble in this matter 1 think the patience of Government will be exhausted and they will not tolerate any )rore obstruction ^rom him. ^ou should therefore lea7e no etcte unturned to get c-he matter tiatisfactorily settled in Captain Birdwcod's presence. (sd) F.Z.Jox, Lieut-Colonel, Political Kesiient in the Persian Uulf,\V SA ILIN G DIRECTI ONS PC'R, THE F IR ST ASSISTANT. You will find Mr. Spenca on board the n Lawrenc© H . You will firet prooeod to Eunder Abbaa and take on board Mr. Muhaimriad Isirail and his assietant (as Mr. Spence may arrange with you). Prom Bunder Abbas you will proceed to Ras-al-Khaimah and pick up the Residency Agent or his son, if where, and if not, proceed to Shargah or wherever he may be, to take him on board, and then ^o on to Debai. On arrival, the Residency Agtnt should go off A ? ith the letter to the Sheikh and endeavour to bring him on board; he will probably ccme, but if he complies as regards luhammad Ismail it will not be #/orth while raising acute isauo ever the point of visit and you had better accept any reasonable excuse or, if he is seedy go and see him ashore. If you fail to set tle matter with him satisfactorily, you had better proceed to Henjam to communicate. After finishing with Debai, return here celling at Tanb en route. While there I should be ^lad if 'Lawrence' would give the flag-custodian at the villa 6 .&gt; a halyard for haul.ing up the flag with. He had none when 1 was last there. You can tell Abdul Latif for Sheikh Sagar^ in formation that ^ou are going to look in there and ask him if he jiae any letter or individual lie would like to ser.d over. I also asked Abdul Latif to send one of his relations there to meet the 'Griqua' to see that all went well with her discharge o^ material, ^-B. You should not discuss Tanb with Sheikh Salim or allow latter to be brourht into the questici . Cct.8th,1912. P.Z.GOX.No, cf 1912. H. B. and Aiiuiataat Rebidenov ^ } 6th October 1912 To, evident and Consul General, B U S H I R E. Sir In connection with the death of Haji Muhammad ILranim, Agent, Meabrb, Gray Paul and Company at Dibai and Landing Contractor of the British India Steam Naviga tion Company at the ^ame place, which occurred at Bahrain on L-he 28th September 1912, I have the honour to inform you that Messrs, Gray Paul and Company of Bahrain bent a bpccial representative,Mirza Muhammad Ismail, by S. S. 'Barjora' which arrived here on the 1st instant, with in to true ..ions to proceed to Dibai in the same ship to take over Cjiarge of the firm 1 ^ Agency and businetot., 2. Messrs. Gray Paul and Company, Bahrain, addressed ;i!c cl1 ioially on the toubject, pointing out that any delay in taking over charge at Dibai would possibly mean the overcarriage 01 cargo and loss to all parties. They fur ther requested me to send Khan Bahadur Agha Beder or a opecial representative of this Vice-Consulate to Dibai to assist their Mirza Muhammad Ismail. This, I waa unable to do, but as the news cf Muhammad Ibrahim's death would V.. leach Dioai on ^ ^e arrival of S« S, 'Barjora' 1 on the 2nd instant, I gave Hirza Muhammad Ismail a letter to the Residency Agent, Sharjah, a translation of v/hich is here with enclosed. A rumour raacJied Lineeh yesterday that Mlrza Uuhaamad Ismail wab not allowed to land at Dltai and that the Shaikh had taken charge of deceased' b property. Messrs. Oray Paul and Company, Bahrain, also in- formedIt* informed me t.-iat the late Haji Muhamnad Ibrahim owed the firm some Rb, 6000/- on account of Lingeh indent hubireab, Ab the deceased way during his lifetime a Persian suh- Ject employed hy a British firm, I applied to the Deputy Governor and on the forenoon of the let instant we joint ly sealed the offices and four go-downs 'belonging to the deceased at lingeh, 4. On the 5th instant the eeal cf the deceabed's offices was hrolcen hy the Deputy Cloverncr and myaelf, and the following was extracted:- 1 large general Account Book, 9 small Account Books, 1 letter Copy book, Cash, Rupees 600/- (six hundred only.), after which the offices were again sealed as before. A Majlis' 1 0^ local mercnants v/as called to examine the Ac count. Books which were fcuiid to be apparently in good order, written upto the 4th Ram^an 133O (r 18th August 1912). It was agreed that the amount of ready cash,Rupees 600/-, should be taken by me for payment to Messrs. Gray Paul and Company in part ^.1 im ..-rt of their claim, which has been done. xt was further agreed that the large General Account Book which, after examination, was sealed by the Deputy Govern or and myself, should remain in the custody cf the former, and the nine small account books and the letter copy book should be handed over to the following persons, appointed to prepare a full and up to date account of the deceased^ trade transactions :- Hulla Ismail (Lingeh Agent of deceased.)• Khalu Baqar (Heir of deceased). HaJi Zainal, Uulla Muhammad Rafia. Deceased also had considerable trade transactions at Dibai, apart from his Agency of Messrs. Gra}' - Paul and Company, and landing Contractorship of the British India Steam Navigation Company; and seemingly the settlements cfcj estate at 'both places will finally have to te adjusted at lingeh or Di^ai, I have the honour to be, Sir, '''our most obedient servant. H• B. M f 8 Vice-Consul and Abfaistant Resident, I I N G E H,\s Copy of letter Fc % 342, dated Ibt OctoTber 1912, frcm K. P, ':'b Vice-Consul and Abbistant Rebident, lingeh, to Khan Bahadur A.dul latif, Rebidency Agent, Sharjah, /6 ■a. / A. C., I inform you a 'bout Haji Muhammad Ibrahim, Agent of ?!ebbrs. Gray Paul and Company and landing Contractor of the B. !• S. N. Company, that he has died at Bahrain, and that, therefore, it has 'become necessary for Me&amp;brs, Gray Paul and Company to appoint an Ag;ent, on their behalf, for the dispatch of the affairs of their steamships in ..■.is bamo way ab did the late TTaji ivluharamad Ibrahim; and, for the settlement of the affairs of the Company. Con sequently, the bearer of this letter, Agha Muhammad Ismail now comes to you, on behalf of Messrs. Gray Paul and Com pany,and I request and desire you to use your bebt en- ueavcurs in tne matter of abbibting him in everv v/aj'*. Similarly, I inlorm you that I have received an official letter from Mesbrb. Gray Paul and Company, that the late Huji I^u-'iammad Ibrahim is indebted to the Company, and for this reason, you should secure all the left property of deceased, such as, go-downs, house and any other thing, and keep it in your custody, with the knowledge, in tne presence of Muhammad Ismail, till the time of its disi)osal. That is all which needed description. &lt;. &lt;_&gt;C v Sf 7^- txH J f.f. UP , 1 irV JU ^ s t tus£/ - ^Telephonic Koaoa^f#, From Resident Subzabad. To kesere ttray Paul &amp; Coy Buehire. i &gt;&amp;ted 15th October 1912. Blrdwood telegraphs as follows 'Messrs Gray Paulas man landed at Debal and 'satisfactory assuranoee received from the ,, Sheikh , ^r/ Bushire, 14th October, 1912, Lieut-Col. Sir Percy Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf &amp; H, B. M 1 b Consul-General for yars , etc., E U S H I R E. Sir, We have the honour to confirn our sundry oonversa- tions with your goodself, wherein we informed you of the death | of our Apent at Dubai, Haj i Mohamed Ihrahim Ahwazi, and that we had sent two of our employees to Dubai to look after the work of the Company at that port. We subsequently informed you that the Shaikh had not allowed these two men to land, and as at present there is no responsible person to look after the Company ! s interests at Dubai , this action on the part of the Shaikh will in all prob ability cause a serious loss to this Company. We have the honour therefore to request the services of your good offices to assist us in any way you may think best, so that no further impediment may be placed against the landing of our two employees at Dubai, j In conclusion we trust H. M 1 s Government will hold the Shaikh responsible for any loss this Company may incur through his not allowing our two employees to land and thereby ^eventing the work of the Company from being carried onui/ tfa / Thanking you in advance. We have the honour to be. Sir, Your most Agents, B. I. S. If. Co., itd.Z'? - ^ ^ PA- \ ( \.io.&lt;J-' 'yuroV |&gt; k V1' ^1 DEBAI. From Shargah I prooaoded the sama day l.a,, on October 13th. to DeTai. K.P,Abdul Latif and K.S«Haji Abdur Razak land©! at onca on arrival, intervia^Qd Sheikh Butti^and handed him your letter. Khan Bahadur 1 3 report on the inter7iew is attached herewith, i'ha Sheikh in accordance with your instructions caiiie off to see Tne in the afternoon. Ha was accompanied by Sheikh Butti bin Rashid. He began by saying that Muhammad Ismail had arrived v^itjiout notice and without letters of introduction from your self, and that he did not know who they were. That while the question of their disembarkation was still under consideration and correspondence between ship and shore a wind sprung up^ wnich prevented further communication. I told the Sheikh that 1 would inform you of what he said but the excuse given hardly seemed to me an adequate reason for refusing to allow the men to land and putting the Company and everyone else concerned to considerable extra expense and trouble, and that if he had c losen it was obvious that he could easily have let the men land and mal:a the necessary enquiries afterwards. However, I said my more immediate concern was in regard to the future and that i should be glad to know what he proposed doing. He then said firstly, that Muhammad Ismail had a bad. reputation both while at Bahrain and Lingah for being hasty tempered and not kaaping a sufficient curb on his tongue. He pointed out that Ms own townspeople were but ignorant Arabs, and also quick tempered P — : - ,tlf / 3 tampered; that a haBty word might easily l9ad to a i re.ca3 foe which he would be held reponsible. 1 '' 3 sai(i he had received a petition from various merchants in t-he to.wn requosting that the new British India Agent should be a man who was acquainted with local usages and customs. Aa regaris the first point I remarked that his original excuse for not allowing the men to land was that he knew nothing about them whatever. I then pointed out that Vuhanmad Ismail vaa not the permanent Agent but only making a stay of ten daya or so in order to instal/ Aboo Taleb but in any case 1 felt certain that Mr Spence who was on board wouj-d give Muhammad ixx T email a hint to be tactful in hi3 ways. As regards the second point I said it seemed to me that ^9 the persons chiefly concerned were the Company themselves ai a that, the latter coy^li hardly be expected to take into account Lhe objections of individual merchants, possibly in terested parties. The Sheikh then expressed anxiety as to the scope of Muhammad Ismail and Ahoo Taleb's activities, more especially as re- ra -ia -heir interference in local politics and intrigues. I at once replied that their work would be confined solely to the business of the firm, mercantile pursuits and the charge of the post o^ice in exactly the same manner as the late in- c 9 a nd tnau J would ask Mr Spenco to warn his represent atives accordingly. The Sheikh expressed himself as satisfied. I then asked Mr Spence to come in and introduced him to the bnei-ivh. explained to him the result of our interview and he r'-a( ily consented to warn his men as desired. I now informed the Sheikh that L'r Spence was anxious to examine the firm's books and the Sheikh offered to send them off. I said however that it •va^ getting late and that-if he saw no objection I would land the next morning to return his call and bring Mr Spence and his two men ashore with me. To this he consented. We landed accord- . x. a, , oa i led on him. After the visit wa all embarked accompanied by the Sheikh on the Lawrence's steam cutter■ 17 4 2S ©utter and steamed up the creek to Gray Paul's office. A ^resh cool breeze was blowinland the Sheikh appeared delight ed with hie trip, remarking that this was.the first time a steam launch had been so far up the creek. He arrived at the Agency's offices in an excellent temper and after the usual Dur 1 ar Spence went off into another room to examine the books, which he Informs me appeared to be in good order and correct. In the meantime the Sheikh expressed the hope that kasxidtgii he might prepare a mid-day meal for us and as there seemed erery likelihood of ^e examination of the books lasting some four or five hours T perforce accepted. T&gt;ie Sheikh's atti- tu id rtS.o ^l^asant ana affable throughout though I should not be surprised if the new Agent meets with considerable passive r o btr*action from various Interested parties. A sample of v/hat may be expected occurred almost at once. The land-lord of the building occupied as an office by the firm announced that as Aboo Taleb was a married man he would be unable to continue t ae lease a: ' ^hat- the office must be vacated forthwith. After some heated discussion between Abdul Latif and the gentleman concerned I pointed out to the Sheikh the absurdity of such a request and saiu that the new Arents must be allowed a reason able time to look round and settle down and it was arranged accordingly. After leaving Gray Paul's Agency the Sheikh took us through the bazaar ^ which was closed owing to Sheikh Mohamed bin Murr's dea^h) and another Durbar our 3rd, was held in the Hindu quarter with the usual accompaniment of Hilndu sweets, coff ee etc, to sa^- nothing of two gramaphones. We then adjourned to the S ei.vh's house for lunch, shortly before which Sheikh Butti received news by letter from Sheikh Hamdan bin Zaeed that Sheikh Tahnoon was dead. The Sheikh seemed considerably upset at the newa^sw^possible oonplioatlona with the bedouin In the interior. I may here mention that Mr Spence requested me -o raise the question of the sequestration of the late Haji Muhammad 1 s5 ¥uharins ,iV Ibrahim 's property more aapeoially in oonnsotion rat-. 31X lioats which were the property of the late Agent but ' cV W9ra US9d ^ h im for the Coitpany's business all of wno8-.3 landing arrangements wars thus in the hands of their own agent. I Loli '.r Spence that the primary objeut of our^ v iait was -110 ;lu© instalation of hia ropraeantative in ra- gar:i to whioh I anticipated obatruction in any case and that I vaa unwilling to raise mora aide issues than were absolu tely necesrary. Further Mr Spence could not giro me any idea of the late Agent's probable liabilities nor could he assure ma that, his Lin^ah,.properties would not be sufficient to cover t am. T pointed out that in any case it would not be possible for me to demand that the boats should be placed at t. diaposal of his raprasentatires as a^set off against possible debts which the late Agent might owe the Company. ?'r Spence then requested that I should if possible come to soma definite arrangement with the Shaikh in regard to land- a, ing arrange- nts generally. I igz&amp;zt&amp;c* in reply that tix matter of this kind involving as it doubtless a Urge num- . or of local 1ntarests could not be settled in a day and that 11 v.oul in t:y opinion be much better to laave the matter to be settled by his representatives with fie helj of our Agent. At my Interview therefore with the Sheikh on board ship I-con tented myself with impressing on the Sheikh that 'i^L obliga tions in regard to the new Agents did not close with merely letting taem land but that it was also incumbent on him to see that they did not meet with concerted obstruction from interested parties both as regards their business generally •as well ac in regard to the landing of cargo. I further mentioned that the lata Agent was probably in debt to a cer tain extent to the Company and that it was advisable that his effects should be duly sealed up and looked after until the exact amount was known. I understood that this has already hue ' ao:ie the Sheikh but instructed Abdul Latif to make ^ cortaj ;i on tnis point and insist on its being done, if t the6 the necassary action had not already been taken. I finally A J Insod Abdul Latif to POBAjLti at DotXljL &amp;f9 tiUMLLriamrnad Ismail le^t which will I mderstand be in about a fort- ' time arid also told the latter in !T r Spenoe's presence that, if in difficulty as ra^ards either his own business or the post office he should at orce appeal to Abdul Latif ard not/to fight the Sheikh on bis owj . n As ragai' xs '-he post office^ vvithout p•p• ^ I am not sure how the late Haji Muhammad Ibrahim came to be appointed Post master. I rather think ve merely asked Gray Paul's if the., j . any objection to their Agent doin^ the work, the quee- - ion o^ remuneration being one for settlement between the Agent and ourselves. In any case I asked Mr Spenoe to in struct his Agent to carry on exactly as before until the matter had I sen further considered. It will perhaps be necessary to write to the Postmaster General on the subject. As regards Muhammad Ismail he seemed to me to be &amp; man o^ considerable intelligence and capacity, and I under stand from Mr Spence is a much trusted Agent of the firm laving been in their service for some forty years: he is however an individual who thinks no small bear of himself an ro -i3 attitude while at Debai it seemed to me he looked on himself as a very superior person whom a hard fate had cast amongst savages. I think it would be as well if his stay at Debai were as short a one as possible. Abco Taleb v.id not striiie me as a man of mucl ^character and should not I think give trouble in the way of local in trigue unless it be from .veainess. I cannot help thinking their beSo interests if ^ ]Lne u-ompany were to look out for some capable Arab knowing local customs and usages to run their business at Oebai. The landing que s- tion^I think sure to give trouble. Vhen Abdul Latif and —— ' mwm A iur Reza c landed to deliver your letter the Sheikh mention- - I.■ ■».|«IIIImr— , tx;• SH ■ i n Mir i*i&lt;lll i IIH' wfttfr.i.iii'Btv.a ©d thd. u ti.c d iiad bwen diff louit i: regarding the MMilMMMMiaHUHtMMttk waees of boatmen in the late Agent's time and hinted at the cr&gt; , ^ possibilityi. 0^, oTar the landing arrangements himself and at t} ^ r )urbar in the Bunia quarter,one of tn ar number _ •' ^iitly put forward as spolresman^ approaohod m© or A the general question of ^ landing of oargo by the B.I.Agent. 1 re fused to disouss the question and referred him to Abdul Latif As regards the late Agents estate 1 understand frocTlTrTfew that by agreement with the Deputy Governor and with the oon- currencQ of the heirs the whole estate so far as it concerns Lingah has been put In charge of ore named Ismail who is given six months in which to wind up the estate and is to receive a f je of ps 500. It is beliered that the assets will amount to at least T^SQOOO ample to cover all claims against the estate. As cegards the Debal portion of the estate therefore the tntvix hsjAtC of interest to tlie B.T.Company is thj i^osseasion of the six boats belonging to the late Agent. Vv yew thinks he will b : easily able to arrange for their sale to Messrs Gray Paul ♦or for th•: i' hire to the SsicpKsy Oompany, '/ahamiiia I Israil as also doubtless Abdul Latif are sure to be sul fitting soon a report on the landing question and I suggest that this be a- - ' .111 &gt; ***** II ■ v.aited before taking further action. Messrs Gray Pauls mivht tiien address us on the whole question their requirements. Mr Spence mentions that their Lingah office is under Bahrein and their Debal office under Bus hi re and that lt..would therefore be convenient if they could address Mr Hew direct as regards the Lingah part of the estate and communicate with us on all matters witn connected with Debai. There is another point which I dont know if you will think worth pursuing or not. I£ appears when that/Muhammad Ismail left Bahrein he was given a letter by r * Vacpharson to ?r r Kew. The latter inj/his turn ^ave him a lettyr for Abdul Latif. On arrival at Debai the ship was boarded by the Sheikh's men to whom Mohammad Ismail handed the letter for Abdul Latif as wall as one from himself to the Sheikh. Mr Spence in forms me that the Sheikh's men on being handed the letter ^or AMul Latif threw it on the deck and refused to take delivery of i ^ presumably because Abdul Latif was not in Debai) until ^ ^' to -lo so by the Oaptain of the ship . Until I arrived at Lingah I was quite unaware that Few had written any letter at allall to Abdul Latif and thorefore mada no enquiries about it. Abdul uatif made no mention of the letter to Abdur Rezak or my- Felf nor did the Fhellih refer to it though he Tnen ion^d the letter from Muhammad Ismail, I car only eupposo therefore if it is true that the Sheikh's men actually took delivery of the letter for Abdul Latif the.t they destroyed it. . r . r r Spenc ^ lid mention to n.e before our arrival at Debai some dispute about a letter but nevt r mentioned Kew's name and 1 supposing that he referred to Muhammad Ismail's letter to which the Sheikh also ref rred at our interview, did not attach much importance to the incident. Ar regards the Sheikh's mer going on board E.I. ships Mr Wew tells me that tbe action of these ^.en is giving rise to con- o± '.arable comment. It appears they are now in the habit of swarming on board the E.I.ships on arrival ar 1 arbitrarily re fusing permission to passengers to lard. I told Vr New we had .received no cor plaint ourselves nor had Tr ^perce heard of any objections ' eing lodged by Captains of Ships. 19 /10/12c *n only adviae th) Shaikh to endeavour by sho./tn^ friendliness and asolatanoe to tiie Oorapany and their Agents, to oause them to drop the olaiin or their ovm accord* If they press it I shall not be able to rafuso to send it on to uovermnent# Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Lieut-Colonellieut -Col .Sir ?6rcy Ocx, K!#']! Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E. Sir, 4^ We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your favour Fo .2627 of the 19th inst. in which you inforred us that the inatter in connection with our two eniploysc^ landing at Dubai had heen satisfactorily arranged, Fe would ask you to accept our best thanks for all the trouble yo\i. have taken in this connection. We have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your most ohe servants , Agents, !• Co., Ud,No, 366 of 1912. - • -P • ' u lii, t s and Afaijib'tcin't HebicisnCjTj linoeh, • i5.0cT.ui2 *' 20tn 0ctober 1 9 12 - To, \ f * __ • . The Political Reaident and Consul General, B U S H I R R. Sir, ^ In continuation of my letter Mc. 351, dated the 6th Octo'ber 1912, on the bubject of the yettlement of the ebtate at lingeh of the late Haj i ''^ujiaramad Ibrahim, I have the honour to inform you that there is one item of deceabed'to property at Di'bai, which appears as a debit in tli® lin^eh Account 'books, and which, I think, should come within the settlement of the lingeh estate. 2, T3iis item is in resx^ect to ^00 caaes of Kerosene oil purchased here and lately bent to Di'bai for sale and for which payment has not yet he en made. I am given to underbtand that about 23O cases have already been bold at Dibai, leaving about 270, wliich are now under seal. The deceased^ heirs now desir® to sell off the balance of 270 cases of oil at Dibai, and transfer the whole amount realised on the sale of the 500 cases to lingeh, in order to bettle the transaction. If you approve , I would beg to abk you to be so good as to issue the necessary instructions. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. H. B. H's Vice-Consul and Assistant Resident, L I 2J G E K.Hi jfo ri October { ( j\2 Y u o I }ilite tlie honour to acknonlo^o receipt of your letter. He*566 dated cOth October 1912, regarding the aale of certain oases of oil loft by the late Hajl Uuharmad Ibrahim at Debai* On the whole, seeing that the estate is apparently quite solvent, I ara of opinion that a Joint adjustment of the real estate left at Lingah and Debai would result in confusion; and that it would bo preferable that they should be dealt with independently and the results eventually trans ferred to the heirs• In any oase I will await a further report from Ghargah subsequeRt to the arrival of liUhaainad Ismail, before taking further action# I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# % . -•-f ^ ^ 3 Vice-consul and Assistant Resident, L i n g a h.HS - H Ra,-Ab.-Ps. Total 'brought forward. .45854-- 8-- 5 IIABILITIBS . Anountb due 'by the late Haji Muhamaad Ibrahim... . 1 72BO-- 7'- 6 Balaixce Ro...265^4-- 0-- 9 4. MeBtsra* Gray Paul and Company^ claim araounting to Ra. 6555/9/5 liaa 'been paid in, with the exception of a few rupees in dispute concerning the date of application of interest on a certain order. I have received another claii!! from Messrs. Gray Paul and Company, amounting to R^% 2^59/9/' &gt; a c a; ^ nb ^ ^ ie Muiia:n:iiad Ihra^iiia in his capacity'' as Landi^ig Contiac.-or ao Dihai, 'but, this cannot 'be deal', wit-i until tne Sritisj.! India Company submit a ctatement of their Bombay, Calcutta and Karachi a.^encj-' accounts with the deceased, who I understand has money due to him by the Company. r' % jn regard to the question of ^00 cases of Kerosene oil at Dibai, the value of which appears in tne Lint ei1 account au a credit, it now appears that it has net teen included tr taken at, part cf the deceased's real eu-ate at Dibai, tecaube, I am informed ty MUlla Ismail that re deceased's nephew named Mir tin Atdur Rasul lias sold the entire quantity and has the proceeds in his possession. This Mir is not re. arded as a rtopensi 1- /out- a.id feared he may male a away witn the mo .iey. In the circumstances, I would be2: to recommend that Mulla Ismail raay £0 to Dibai to collect the amount realised by Mir on the sale of 5^® case© of oil, and tnat; ne ;aa&gt; c ^loo be f iven written authority to examine (only) the affairs at Dibai of the deceased/on behalf of the heirs. Other than the question of the Kerosene oil, I do not think any disposal at Dibai should be made until the British India Company furniskfurnish their accounta with the deceabed, and llebbrb. Gray Paul and Company decide the question of landing ar range men ta, I have the honour to 'be, Sir, Your mo fat obedient aervont, H. B. M's Vice-Conaul and Abbibtant Reaident, L I N G K H.yi^ dod&amp; -1^ ^7 yL Q' November ^12 / h , With reference to your letter No»S95 dated loth November 1912 f I enclose a letter # in original, for trano- micolon to the Residency Agent, Shargah, by the hand of .lulla Ismail In case he proceeds to Debal. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# /&gt; Vice / , and Assistant Resident, L i n g a h.|) December (341? 1 have the honour enclose two letters for the Residency Agent, Debai, (translations attached^ one for favour of delivery to Mr# Baird and for despatch with his representative to Debai as indicated. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedietit servant. /? 3 Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the ersian Culf. Vice j and Assistant Resident, L i n g a h ••To (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) No 22 dated 18th January 191 3. The Residency Agent, Shargah. A • C • j Your letter No 527 dated 30th Beer 1912, re garding the housing of Messrs Gray Paul's Agent. I have also received a complaint from that firm on account of the want of co-operation experienced by them from Saeed bin Makhtoom. Your have no doubt been informed by Mirza Mohamed; the house of the former Agent was not sufficient for him and his family, and you should not accept such a letter from the young Sheikh of Debai as he wrote on 17 Moharram. If accommodation cannot be rented for ;.Iirza ^.ohd in one of the houses of the Bin Lootas or some other British subject, you should insist on the Sheikh co -operating with you to find.other ac commodation for him. (Sd) P.Z. Cox, Lieut-Colonel Political Resident in the P•^• S t8—^ 000 _OFFICE NOTE. To The Renidencv A^ent Sharpah. L A.C. With reference to your letter No. 42. I wrip to enquire whether the Sheikh or you have yet made any arrangement for the housing of the B.I.S.N.Cc/s Agents. 3,000-5-12u, * fsh- L lk ~ k-id To The xie a idoney Agont, Shargaii, A.O. In continuation of my flo.139 dated 6th Apt. regarding the house acoonmiodation for the B.I.Agent at Debai, I trust you are taking steps to see that the Company f 3 Agent ex periences no more trouble in thia matter. I expect thia from you withOvt fail. At the same time I may mention that it ia reported to me that the house of the Bin Lutaa ia being offered for sale and pequest^you will report fully on the aubject if the rumour it is true. I think you have mentioned^yoursalf^ t»ut the papers are not 1 t vritn me at the moment of writing. Lt. Colonel Political Reaident in the Peraian Gulf. &amp;&gt; lli-% 74 ''■To of 1913. To r ^iiif The Shaikh of Dehai. &amp;.G. Tiv -rite to send you acknowledgements and thanxs for ta v .in^ definite ste_)s in consultation v. itli t'l\e Fesidency .Agent to provide accommodation for iiesrrs Gray Paul's Agents in Debai. I am very ^lad that \ ith 0 our co^jera^ion the matter is no\»' settled. ZZ. C&lt;?X Lieut-Colonel Political Resident in tie Persian Gulf.B y S H 1 » * 2Hh Ifey 1313. Lt. Col fir PJC.O0 ; K.C.I.S., O.S.I. Political Resident in the Persian &amp; H.B.M 1 s Consul Oenerpl for ^ars fcc. B U S H I B I . Sir, We have the honour to refer you to the interviews the writer has had with yoi/goodself regarding house accomodation for our representative at Dubai • You will recollect that a few days ago the writer informed you that our representative had come to an arrangement with % the Sheikh, through the Political Agent ^at Vat port, hereby the former had agreed to hulld two rooms on the tor- of some go downs 1 close to the toilding at present occupied hy our re- -presentafive. Pdr your inspection we now heg to send you the agreement which has heen come to with the Sheikh, ana which aPr ^•''s to he in order. There is one point however on which we ere no. ijuite cer -ain whether It would he advisable to agree. You will observe that the lease has heen made out in the name of our representative Mr. Mir^a Mohamed, and in a letter the writer Tas received from himi he v.rites as ander, ^ «-rrPorR in the lease is on ' The reason why my name apP 6 ^ 8 • accint »f the Mine «o el« d-—' * _ - direct 1„ of th. fl»., ...I ' «'» ' Md '' me to agree to It, 1 have done „ = - to whv the Sheikh is unwill- He however gives no reason ao to wn a- f mir firmi and it appeae -ing to ^rant the lease in the name h7 appears to us that if at any time we wished to transfer Mr. Mirza -oha 'ncd, and to place somebody else in charre at Dubai that the Sheikh would be in a position to repudiate the lease and we should then have, in all probability, the same trouble as we have just experienced. We have therefore the honour to request you to 'be food enough to inform us ^aether you consider the agreement which we are sending you is sufflciefltly binding on the Sheikh, or whether it would not 'he advisa&gt;0e to have a clause inserted something to ihe effect that this 'building is for the use of Mr Mirza Mohaned, &amp;/or any other representative Messrs Gray Paul &amp; Co. may send to represent them at Bubai. We have the honour to he, Sir.No* Ot 1913» British Roaldency and ConBUlate-Genoral, Buahlro, ^y^iiay 1913. v TO 'oosro Gray Paul &amp; coy, Asento British India Gtean navigation Coy. Ltd. a u s u i n e. Y 1 Gentlenen, .it]: roforenoe to your latter Ho. R/3I0 da tod 27th Inatant, regarding house acoonnodatlon for your rarrooonta- tlve at Dabal, I have the honour to Inform you that In hie report on the aubjoct,which I was about to mention to you, the 'oaidericy Agent doeo not refer at all to anyone by name but speaks throughout of ''essrs Gray Paul's Agent' and 'The , M „ &lt; and alBO Agent'• In reply to him I will aloo use the same temB/in writing to the Sheikh. I think thlc will nake the position sufficiently good both for yourselves and this Residency, and would advise you to loave It at that rather than risk delay from opening dlscuBBion on the subject. I am, Gentlemen, Yourc faithfully. Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.-' m t'41 'Bushire, 16th June 1913. Xii ©lit C ol • Sir Psrcy Z» CoXj K!*C«X»B a | Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Sc H. B. M's Consul-General for 5krs, etc., BUSH IBS. Sir, JTpus e AccoiriTTiodat ion fit Dubai. With reference to the interviews the writer has had with your goodself and to correspondence exchanged between us in connection with the ahove matter, we have the honour to in form you that in accordance with advice to hand from our Dubai Agents the Sheikh has so far failed to carry out his part of the agreement to build the house for our representative, and as the time in which he agreed to build this hou 8 e has now expired, we shall esteem it a favour if you could kindly see your way to represent the matter to the Sheikh, so tnat no further delay my be caused and that the Sheikh may be made to hold to his part of the agreement. Thanking you in anticipation. We have the honour to 'be. Sir,Ho. itjt joV 1913, British Heeidarxcy and Consul a oner al %ohire # /Cj June 1915 t Gentlemen, &lt;1 0 x ^ ■ /In aoknowlodginr, receipt of your letter Vo. RjbteV, I have the honour to say that I have written tBT strict injunctions to the ReoMe-cy Agent to eee the matter through without further delay. I have the honour to be. fore Gray Paul ^ Co,, u b h 1 r e. Ger tlernen, Your most obedient servant. Lieut- Colonel, Political Kesidsr.t In the Ferolar (Julf.e/ / fb Bush ire, 19 th June; 1933. lleut-Ool. Sir P. Z. Cox, K.O.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U $ H I R E. Sir, 8S 33 \r We have/the honour to acknowledge receipt of your favour TTo.1909 of date, and would ask you to accept our 'beet thanks for having written to the Residency Agent at Duhai in connection with the house acconmodation for cur representative at that port • 1 We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most oWdienl servants.-i ,y s K0.&lt;3/3^ of 1913, British itosldency and Conaulate-Oenoral. K Dushlro, /3 July 1913. A copy of the undermentioned letter la forwarded, with oompllmente, to Messrs Gray Paul &amp; Co., Bushlre, for information, with reference to their letter H o,r/347, dated 16th June 1913. /%£ Lieut-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No^SSO, dated 38th June 1913 from the Residency Agent, Shar^ah, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. V Vo*I?1Z ^rwtsige N {k IH A\ - , , 15.Jlll.W3 47 rJ f? ^ . \ Vj// •4j/siAft..§: Bushire, 13th July 1913, *ii c f Ueut-Ool. Sir Percy Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C. S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. Sir 0 w e have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your favour No. 2134 of date, in nthich you hand us a copy of a letter received from the Residency Agent at Shargah, in connec tion with the house accommodation for our representative at Dubai, and we thank you for same and also for all the trouble you have tayen in connection with this ma'tter* r 1 y w 0 have the honour to he, Sir, Your most oh^dient mJ/ No. 355 dated 30th Sentenber 1913 The Residency Ap^ent, Shargah. A. C. It has come to my knowledge that Shaikh Butti bin Rashid is giving way to his old habits and indulging in intrigues in connection with tiie B.I. Coy : s office and landing a.ranpements. I write to authorise you to call upon fhaikh Saeed to warn him and also to give him a direct warning from me that he must desist absolutely from his mischief making intrigues and that if he fails to do so, Goverhment will be asked to authorise tvis being obliged to ma^e his home outside Debai territory for the future. (sd.) P.z,.Cox. P.R.CONFIDENTIAL. .^^v Tres/S 4* fff. £/, £ - K H °' **73 \ D * e irOGT.ISi} *■ • • icc'- onoulate and Aboiatant — £. lingeh, ky Cf&gt; / 9th October 1913, In convsrbaticn tccla^/' the Khan Bahadit tavs me an ite :a of newa, rscardint Diliai affairs, whidh I pa»a on for what it is worth. The day before (ftth Octoloer) , he paid a visit to Shaikh Sultan 'bin liuhaiaraad of Braiiti, Onaii, who recently arrived hers to catch a pilfriri ship to the neajaz. In conversa tion the Braiiti S^iaikh mentioned tiiat you had recently written a letter to Shaikh Sa'id of Diliai, regarding the establishment of a Consulate, Post Office etc., and that, on receipt of your letter, the Shaikh, the Residency Agent and a few notables of Dileai discussed the project and arrived at the conclusion that the only way of evad ing the suiject was for Shaikh Sa'id to pay a visit to the interior, antedating; his departure a few days, bo ab net to loe present when you visited Diliai. It see^o hardly prooalile, because, if suc.-i a letter l-iad &gt;een sent to Ditai, the Reoiiene;' Aeent would ■We Wound to forward it on to the Shaikh, wnersver ..e happened to se. The 'Liinto' told ae that you paaaed down to Muscat .y the '^ex' last/ Sunday, and, I an ther.fc.-e aendins a duplicate copy of this letter to you tr .ere. I hare Ween seedy f»r the past week with a o;u; id, which the Doctor says is Influenza; Wut, aw feeling I a oit liettejr now. r •xj &lt; t An . Lieutenant Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K. C. I. E., C. S. I.. Political Resident and Consul Cr«ne.-al, B 1J S H T R E.PBOM, . T o 4S3 ''a'oed :';':nd llovenner 1:51, The T'esldency A^ent Saat5(;ah To, The Politiaal 'esilent in the Persian r -ulf l': l.C , In reply to ypur letter ITo o59 dfCted the 3oth Beptr: 1^)1^ re.^.rd.in ^ the inclination of Shaikh Butti bin Pa: shed to nalie intrigues in connection with the ^ebai branch of the , ritisn Xrlia Conpany, I beg nost respectfully to state that Shaikh Butti was not present at ^ebai when T received your letter under ©eference^ and that I considered It ie- sira 1° to approacn i/he Gnief of ^ebai Y . r hen Shaikh But/ti happened to be there. So ; I infom.ed both of then v^en Shaik .^utti arrived at ^ebai . Shaikh Butti conveyed his apology to ne both verbaily and in writing, stating that he has done no intrigues what-' ever in regard to the affairs of the British India Coj: . Tfe. Chief of 'Oebai infom.ed ne likewise, both verbally and in writing, that he has not co^ie to know of any objectionable action on the part of Shaikh Butti in regard to the British India Go: The letters fron both the Shaikhs are suhnitfced herev;ith and the decision rests with you. ^-(JLe /J- 1$.To, . T *e Hted l^th Xilhijjeh 1331 i tn Ilovenber 1913 FPOH, ShaiJm Saeed bin Ilaktun, Chief of T^ebai, Ahan Bahadur /bdul T .atif, -esidenoy afjent Shar^ah, / .c« 1 hafee learned fron you that the Resident has Ex pressed his displeasure with the brother Butti bin Hashed, * K ' L0ri tnat ' the latter is oar ^im; on contemptible intrigue., in regard to the affairs of (Messrs) Geay Paul and Co; were much concerned and astonished at this, because he Snaibn hutti) has been a friend of the company since for mer times and his endeavours on their behalf are welllknowi and he is not one of those who deny kindness. :as frilndshi; wit,n j 'unammad Ibrahim (the late agent is vfeil-known and hp good-v.ul is proved by the fact that when Jlirza llnham- mad iiisain came here, he (Shaikh Butti) afforded him ikis rpod offices with us. ; hat has brought about the anno between thwm, however, is the agent's association with interested parties. The brother Butti is not a merchant or trader, so that nis commercial affairs may be in the hands of tj.io a^ont/ and. ne nay ri.al^e in.'triguBs ar^ains'b hin (for his ovrn interests). e lo not, desire 'bha't 'the * : esident» should listen to the statements of partial parties against us, as it is their object to bring about disageeement, while we desire for peaoe and for the tranquil relation of one party with other and detest envy and contention. Butti bin P.ashed cane to the agency-house and staged to you what he had to say. * hen he went over to Bahrain, m • manager of Ilessrs Gra^^ Paul cane to hinftuMjmd- exprs nis best thanks to us in the sane way as he (Butti) has inforned you. T;r e trust that the Resident will be satisfied with and will thus evince his kindness, ^'e know that this has been brought about by the intrigues of interested part v ou will never perceive anything on the part of the bt Butti bin 'Pashed exnept what is laudable. HiICO ^atei 14th Xilhij.jeh l-ol V/bh 3 T ove'ihe^ 1-513 P^Oj!, Shaikh Butti hin Fashed ^ e b a i. To, iJian Bahadur /.bdul ~,atif, Pesidehcy a^ent Sharqah, 1,C 1 0 nave learned and underst/Ood the displeasure of ^is honour Sir Peroy Cox, Political Resident, which is due t the nisrepresentation of interested part/ies( who allege that v:e are naming contemptible intrigues in regard to t^he affairs of I!essrs C-ra^^ Paul and Co: ax, ^ebai. I hope not to be one of those who deny kindness and gene^osit: - : anji I adnit and acknowledge the kindness and respect shown to by Messrs Paul and consider that it id necessary fj^r s ne to afford then assistance as far as T can, in case of need. Please note that T used ny good offices in regard to the affairs of Messrs Tray Paul and Co: at ^ebai before; I fomed an acquaintance with then and that, in result, I received kind regards fron then in the shape of presents and also due respects on board their steaneps whenever I tr 'travelled b3 r then, '^ow will I change( ny attitude) and dis turb thair affairs aft-r beconing acquainted witn tnenr jMessrs Paul's agent,]luhannad Ibrahin , renained at j ^ebai for nany 3^ears and we accdrded hin assistance as :?ar we could- and he d^ni^d nothing fron us and his friendliness towards us was being enhanced day y da^ . Tnen the agent, I'irsa Muhannad \usain, cane here, ire began to do what was needed for hi'^ in vi o w of the fa o t that he was the representative of Messrs ray Paul ; and nted our endeavours v. T ith Shailih Saeed in connection witn tne erection of a house for his residence. I did not fail to do for hin all'and everything that was required, out of jrespect for Messrs ^ray Paul, wnile he hinself i»as not kovm to us: but he who has brought about resentnent be^ea^S (o-fe) 196—4,000-7-13—(K2*) 0 ^ Spl—Eesident Persian Gulf 2 (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) C/ in^ on oy- 1? us is a certain nan frothy nane .ahib who does not leaie the aqent da^ and ni^ht. t'lien we visit the a^ent ,as is ! usual an-n^ -t tne A^abs- to offer hin our conplinents and to state that if Itessrs rtay Paul and Go: required anyti. to be done we would bw grateful to do it,as was our cusl with l liihanna-rtitbrahin» the late a-ent, .abib bee ones anu e i : -in I ne has l^een spea^iin^ ill of us with the present a.^ent xntil Hhe latter has forned an aversion towards us and ^n eStrangexnent has ensiied, although v/e were visitir 0acii otj.iei al lost continual 3 r ^ little after his arriva at '^ebai. T an not a ne^ohant or trader, so that I nay indijl^e in intrigues against the sigent over the dela3' of ^ trad tn-'ougn the agent ; and that the latter dhould not treat i well. Seeing that he is a representative of Ilessrs fray Paul, it is necessar.y for us to honour and respeet hin. -How will,then, we disturb the affairs of Messrs fray Pai Phis is inpossible. 'i'lien we visited Bahrain the other day, the Manager of the fim, Mr: Ilacpherson, cane to us and we learned froir lin^in the course of the conversation, that he had conpl i^d to the Pesident,against us 7 stating that our attitude was the reverse of satisfactory. T explained all the fac o hin and he was satisfied with ne and we received due espect fron hin ahd he conplied with our wishes, .e als onsidered the question relating to Mirsa Muhannad, ageh I of Messrs Tray Paul at 'Hebai and addressed a letter to h:.n to treat us well. ITo irregularis whatevet has enanatei fron ne in regard to the affairs of Messrs ^ray Paul at ^ebai ana. I have constantly afforded then ny asssCistanceyand ny highest cjbject is that in the sane way that I have obtained tne satisfaction of the Manager of Messrs ' ray Paul at .-ahra. -is 'ionour Colonel Cox, the Pesidant / will also be satis- ied YJ'itik ne and will graciously be pleased to conplete the present (allotted to ne ) as the present sent .n nis a in - o n 7.s (o-h) 196--4,000'7-13-(K2*) Spl—Resident Persian Gulf 2 (Continuation of Note, Precis or Draft.) bwhaif is very incomplete, T was distinguished anongst '^he Shaikhs, tiirou^n nis jiind regards, by being presented with a golfi watch or a rifle or sorae broad cloth: but this tirne we have received only a silver watch and broad cloth • There is no doubt that the deficiency is due to those w:io have misrepresented to him., saying that we are making harm ful intrigues in regard to the affairs of I Messrs Tray Paul and Co: . v 'e trust that Colonel Sir Percy Cox will not bring us to book except after due incuiries, in case lan^ one has made misrepresentations against us to him. This is what had to be stated. T.T. j tyjj 102. /oc IFVOM; J OFFICE NOTE. i o IF fated ISt/hJanna^ 191^- PHE W' TDVjNC v Aff^NT AT R 1 (AP^A'T LViiil J 0';ITTrAl/ RESTDiCNT IN TI1E 'PTiiP.SIAN nrj-i.Tr^ A - C '_ A'ith reference to the correspondence ^ndin^ with ny letter. No:2r-0 dated ^8th June 1913 in regard to the construction of a building for the residence nf Ass rs 'Tray Paul's agent at Tisbai.X heg TO st resp^t- ful .y to reprs^nt to yon that all the hnildin&lt;?« quired for the - aid a^ent have been duj.y co^Dleteci and t-at he and hi^ ^a^.ily 'have taken their re^id^nce there. I he- to forward herewith,for iroTir information, a private note addressed to m.e hj the agent in whTiioh le expresses his thankf? to ne for the trouble taken y me in connexmon with the completion of the buil 'WW ) % t n i) r} y) i), % if $ it i) i&gt;i)y}-y)y)y) 7) 9^ y) y) yjyfyty ^ Dated 10th Pafa^ 1?;^ 8th January .1914 To: K.B.Abdul fiat if, ^»n # ,T truFt that your health continues ^ood and ^ from complaint. Y our kind note has been received .and T waF Extremely pleased to hea^ of 3 r ou^ wel.l-&gt;ein. .In i^ard to accommodation, f I have obtained it) by ^f your kind exertions,and I am highly fateful to you for all the trouble which you have taken in this matter until some result has been obtained . t t^u that you will excuse me for the trouble T ^a^e vou in thl? respect and I assure yon that T shall alwa 3e at your service. V.'ith compliments . T.T. 5 20®-3* IO■ ■r' ■ « r i / / Telegram. Prom General Brigade, Karachi. To Political Resident Bushire. No. S.2325. Dated and received 5th December 1913 (7. p.m) Kindly wire if rations be sent for detachment 95th Infantry proceeding Dibai and whether field or foreign service scale. General Brigade.-z 4 Telegram. From Resident Bushire. To General Brigade Karachi. 5o. 1972. Dated 5th December 1915. p*m.) Urgent. Your S.252^ December 5th. Debai has not as far as I am k * aware been sanctioned by Government as yet. Please wire urgeht authority under which it is proposed to send detachment in question. Latter should under no circumstances be disembarked at Debai without further intimation to this office. Reiident. ■i i Telegram. From Resident Bushire. To General Brigade Karachi. Dated 6th December 1913 (8.23 a.m.) Urgent. My 1972. For 'Dibai has not' please read 'Despatch of detachment to Dibai has not'.Telegr?jn. Pron: General Brigade Karachi. To Resident Bushire. No. S. 2364. ====== h Dsted and received 9th December 1913 (6.1* p.m.) Tour 1972. Final orders regarding detachment for Dibai not yet received. Kindly wire if rations would be required for them and what scale. General Brigade. Telegram. Prom Resident Bushire. To General Brigade Karachi. No. 1993. 9th December 1913. (8.10 p.m.) Your telegram S. 2564 of 9th December. In my opinion full rations should be provided for Dibai detach ment until experience has shown whether supplies can be obtained locally. Resident.i\^ v\ 1 p C r A N o P C &amp; * i# B U S H I R E, Persian Gulf, January 20th A 101$ lU* From To MAJOR C. C. R. MURPHY, Intelligence Officer, Persian Gulf The Political Resident, Per si; n Gulf. Sir, I have the honour to report that I have 'been in g true ted 'by the Chief of the General Staff to submit to Array Headqurrters certain information regarding supplies, fuel, fodder, grazing etc., at Ditai, in connection with the imninent despatch of troops to that town. It occurs to uie that the only satisfactory lethod of obtaining the necessarv information is to visit Dihai personally. I have the honour to enquire whether there is any oh- Jection to this suggestion. I have the honour to 'be, 3ir, lA iu Cll^' i** Your Obedient Serjayt, Intelligence Officer, Persian Gulf,y No. 180 of 1914. S British Residency and Consulate-General, ut' ire, 22nd January, 1914. i\»4 n. X- \ ;ir. In reply to your letter x ?o.327 of 20th January, « 1914, I havo the honour to say that circuiustancos at Dlbai make it, in ny opinion, undesirable that you should at present visit that place. I was lately consulted by the General Officer CoTnimanding Karachi Brigade in regard to the rations required if a detachment should be rested to Dibai and replied that I thought full rations should be sent with them in the first instance, and that experierce would s 1 ow what supplies could be obtained locally. If provision were nade for three months * supplies to be^in with, the requirements of the case would, it seems to me, be sufficiently met. I have the honoiir to be Sir, Your nofit obedient servant, i.c.r. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. op C .c.R. Murphy, diligence Officer,i)U I f PTE, 7 /'/-W £* liLifiW* wn-1 MIW HI nn Baya thRt Dlbal lB prnotieaUy divided into two by a creek, the western aide beln £ called OJ iandd^fih. and tlic ©ftctGrn DfiipaJi• i'lie 7/ater supply for the former to obtained fron well, on the plain sone 3 railea distant at a wlaoe called Jum.iira. The wells are more like holss which are du S and filled up again when no longer required, water belns found at a depth of 4 to 6 feet. The water supply for DalraJi is obtained froa some 8 or 6 well a situated near date grovee fi to 8 nlles out. These v ff. 1b Hre ap-oarently dug in hard ground and about IS feet deep# ihe v;ater is carried to the town in rrasake (sklne) on donkey# or canels or in earthenware vesaels by women. le supply is said to be ample, i.e. he ha« not heard of water scarcity. 19.2.14. 23^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000f3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/270</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000f3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/270</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/165, 14/170 (1) B.I. Agent’s difficulties at Debai (2) Troops at Dibai B 20’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1912/1914</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-11T00:16:47</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (119 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file. At the front of the file is an index of topics with page numbers.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence consists of small uncircled numbers located in the top right hand corner of the recto of each folio. The sequence starts on the first folio of writing and finished on the back cover.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence discussing the death of the agent of the British Indian Steam Navigation (B.I) company in Dubai. A new agent was sent out but the Shaikh of Dubai, Shaikh Butti bin Soheil, refused him permission to land. The First Assistant of the Residency, Captain Birdwood then accompanied the new agent. Further correspondence discusses the difficulty the agent had in arranging accommodation which was finally arranged by the Residency Agent, Sharjah. A letter of warning was sent to the Shaikh of Dubai. The file also discusses the estate of the late agent.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British India Steam Navigation Company Limited</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0000f3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>