<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00013a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T18:26:21.498Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">s Copy 11 ?&lt;mim oi-fice # s.r.i* | 24th IIovember # 1923* 16838/16838/234) ! Q j Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to inform you that he approves the appointment of rr. G,F* Moore as acting r ‘)ritish Vice Consul at Birjand during the absence on leave of Sub-Assistant Surgeon lian Bahadur Mirza Mohammed Beg. 2* 1 am to instruct you to send home rr. Moore’s official signature and seal certified to be correct. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, B.J. Gould Fso. , His Majesty’s Consul, Selstsinexpires, as to which a furu.e; lot, i hm to add Uifct no onariT 1 in oonnaction witti tiiis arrangouwn leave pay being a oaerge upon ’ ruvonuos of India* 1 have tha honour Your obedient Secretar military Depmm-mmmmrnK^KKta —KKlMMWO—MtillllWWP -7 Uoe^ nou necessarily imply uhit he will draw Consular pay from that Date, he^may have to wait a considerable time before he i ^ posted and^be/rms to draw pay, and he should continue to draw hi^ Indian leave h allowances 5up to the limit granted by h^i&gt; L.P.C.) till He does 30 he miffnt be asked to report when he doe? . As regards adjustment with Foreign Office, this will presumably be arranged through the Diplomatic and Consular Account for Persia, Dealt with by Foreign Department. cts-i^u &lt;XJ^ (SD) D.T.l'OKTEA'HJ. 26 / 5 / 21 . Be n 1 'p. R.3V 6 ' 192/. Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. j ^ J - ^ / ^ • 1920. Referred to tlie Secretary, Political and Secret Department. 2 0 / 5 / 21 . 1920. jjt. Brenan. 15-»h * Please see reference from the High Gommis loner, Lieut. Brenan T s leave seems to have been granted under civil regulations, and although he is being paid t British ^rmy rates from the date of expirat ion of his privilege leave it seems hardly correct to describe his leave as being under ; .B. 1 ., espec ially as his leve pay is being charged to a Politic al head. Perhaps you will take steps to clear up tJ$ matter • please see the attached file^the correspondence on / which between yellow slips 1&amp; 2 (inclusive) and from 3(inclusive) to the bottom of the file contains ull our information about Mr Brenan. - L t seems fairly clear that the Govarnment of India taking to heart' the Secretary of State T s despatch of 25th Gctober 1918 have for this second period of leave treated Lt. Brenan rather outside the rules giving him civil rates of privilege leave, and lurio- ugh at Army rates as being the only practicable assessment. The officers leave allowances are Divisible with Imperial Revenues (P.O.note) vide pencil notes on the High Commissioner’s reference of 11th May. Mr. Brenan f s surrender of his commission is irrelevant to the Question of histleave allowances as Ex.V.Consul au Birjand which ife under the Govern ment of India Foreign Department. How that he has p been nominated to the British Consular Service he w4 will presumably report to the Foreign Office for duty as soon as he has completed, the leave granted him by the Government of India. If details are-a?©-u required as t3 the nature and period of this leave the H. C. should enquire of (SD ) R.V. MONTGOMERY. 20/5/21. (3D) D. T. MOHTEATH 24/5/21. 10 2135 1000 8/20C OPY . WAR OFFICE , London, S . W . 1 . No .110706/6 . M ,S .2 . 31st January 1921 . Sir In further reference to your letters of the 20th October, and 10th December , 1920 , I am commanded by the Army Council to inform you that temporary Lieutenant T . V . Brenan , General List, has been employed as His Majesty’s Vice Consul at Birjand , Persia , and is now on leave . I am to say that this officer has not yet been released from Military Service, and that the Government of India desire to strongly recommend him for admission to Consular Service on account of his good services at Birjand . In the circumstances I am to say that no objection would be raised to the relinquishment of his commission by Lieutenant Brenan, to enable him to accept the employment indicated . I am , Sir, Your obedient Servant , (Signed) B . B . Cubitt . The Secretary , Civil Service Commission, Burlington Gardens , W . 1.?***- J &lt; f ev , ff; In any farther commiyiicatigh on this subject, please qupte No. K 18253/7326/234. and address, not to any person by name, Foreign Office. S.W. 1. t but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. January 4th f 1921 Sir With reference to your letter No.P 8522 of December 7th relative to the appointment of Lieutenant T.V.Brenan in the Consular Service, I am directed by Bari Curzon of Kedleston to infom you that this gentleman was selected for nomination several months ago but some delay occurred owing to the fact that he was born in China and has been serving in Persia since 1917. The Civil Service Commissioners have now been requested to hasten the issue of his certifi cate as a probation Vice-Consul in the Levant Consular Service. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (j -(X ‘ { The Under Secretary of State India OfficeCOPY OR TELEGRAM. I.M./H.P. &gt; From Viceroy F* &amp; P* Dept: to S. of S. 54r68. EST. A*' lour telegram dated 27th February, 1919. Brenau vent on combined leave on ground of ill health on 22nd Eovember* It is understood that question of his admission to Consular Service is still under consideration, and Government of India desire to strongly recommend him on account of his good services at Birja&amp;d.Pd ■ %&gt; l ' ■■■■ '' No. 120 op 1919. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPAKTMENT. SALARIES, ESTABLISHMENTS, *tc. Political. 'We have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with your predecessor’s telegram, dated the 12th January 1917, regarding the appointment of Captain T. V. Brenan, 11th Essex Begiment, then serving in the Sistan Levy Corps, as British Vice-Consul at Birjand for the period of the war. 2. Captain Brenan’s emoluments at Birjand were fixed on the basis of those to which he was entitled as an officer of the Sistan Levy Corps, together with the Vice-Consular and office allowances sanctioned for the appointment at Birjand. He thus drew British army pay of rank at Indian rates, with staff pay of Bs. 300 a month, in addition to the allowances referred to. In March 1918, however, it was decided to raise the staff pay of officers serving with Sistan Levies from Bs. 300 to Bs. 400 a month, with effect from the respective dates on 'which they joined the Corps. Captain Brenan s emolu ments have already N been revised in accordance with this decision up to the date preceding that on which he assumed charge of the Vice-Consulate at Birjand ; and His Majesty’s Consul for Sistan and Kain now recommends the continuance of the higher rate of staff pay to him during his tenure as Vicg-.ConsuL As Captain Brenan continued in command of the detachment / frit'Jib'J To THE RIGHT HONOURABLE EDWIN MONTAGU. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 23rd April 1919. Sir, of Levies posted at Birjend after his assumption of charge iconsider that he is in equity entitled, during his tenure of the appointment, to draw staff pay at the enhanced rate ; and we accordingly recommend that he may be permitted to do so. We have the honour to be, See, Your most obedient, humble Servants, (Signed) CHELMSFORD. „ C. C. MONRO. „ C. SANKARAN NAIR. „ G r R. LOWNDES. „ W. H. YINCENT. „ J. S. MESTON. „ T. H. HOLLAND, ; „ R. A, MANT,Copy. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. SALARIES, ESTABLISHMENTS, btc. .Political. From The GOVERNMENT of INDIA, To The SECY, of STATE for INDIA. No. 120. Dated Simla, the 23rd April 1919. Received Emoluments of Captain T. V. Brenan while ippointed as British Vice-Consul at Birjand. 43FinD—62—19‘4-19—QCPS'V c* Your telegram dated 27th February.British Consul for Seistar and Kain represents that Brenan is at present doing very valuable work at Birjand and asks that if it can be arranged without detriment to his future prospects Brenan may be allowed to remain at Birjand a few months longer 0 we support this recommendation* Addressed Secretary of State for India, repealed Se.istartIii any further communication on this subject, please quote Ilio oil UJ t!L'j L^LtUL'U no. 23318/S34.K. and address, Foreign Office S.W.l not to any ‘person by name, February 20th, 1919 MEDIATE Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir:- I am directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to state for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council that a despatch has been received in this De partment from His Majesty’s Consul at Sistan and Kain submitting the name of Lieutenant Terence Vincent Brenan as a candidate for a permanent appointment in His Majes ty's Consular Service. As Mr. Montagu is aware, this officer came out to Persia in August 1916 to serve with the Sistan Levy Corps, which was maintained temporarily in East Persia by the Government of India. From the 29th December 1916 Lieutenant Brenan was appointed 'for the period of the war' His Majesty's Vice- Consul at Birjand under Gazette of India Notification No. 567 East A dated the 11th May 1917. In view of the fact that a Vi( le Under Secretary of State, India Office.n - 2 - required at His Majesty’s Consulate-General at Bushire Lord Curzon would propose with Mr. Montagu’s concurrence to appoint Lieutenant Brenan to this post as from the - 1st April next in order to enable Mr. Vice-Consul Worrall to take leave of absence from Bushire on that date-. Pend- ing consideration of Mr. Brenan’s application for a per manent post it will be convenient if he can continue to draw the pay now received by him at Birjand. I am accordingly to express Lord Curzon’s hope that Mr. Montagu will concur in the proposed arrangement and _to request that a very early reply may be returned to this letter. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, z' A ^ To £GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ARMY DEPARTMENT. ARMY INSTRUCTION (INDIA). &lt;•» No. 127 of 1918. Delhi, 12th February 1918. Date from which full staff pay of their permanent appointments should be admit ted to officers of the Indian Army return ing to their permanent appointments trom sick leave. With the approval of the Right Honourable the Secretary of State for India, it has been decided that, with effect from the 1st March 1917 and for the duration of the war, officers of ^ Indian Army on sick leave in England shall, when found or ig i u in India, or for active service, be permitted to resume the full pav of their permanent appointments, after a peno o • y from the date on which they were reported fit, fuovi e ie J i not themselves responsible for the delay in rejoining. eSe i ir . rn will not affect the pay of officers officiating for those to whom it applies. 2. The above decision will apply only to officers who aie on leave pay at the date of the Medical Board which passes them ; in the case of officers who, when passed fit for light duty or ac ive servi , are employed at Home, full pay will be resumed on e day after embarkation. 43912 (A. &lt;h). A. H. BINGLEY, Major-General, Secretary to the Government of India. ( m ) f |J!( 91^a .«L. V JBU ] t COPY OF TEliBORa.i l ILjEGP From Vice **0 y Foreign ^ . y \ g I i3 IV Dated 24 1 19 Received at India Office 25 th SofloMo Your Political Despatch dated 25th October last Yo o 65 c We now recommend that as a special case Li eu tenant Brenan he treated on Analogy of orders\contained in Amy Instructions India No.^12? of 1018 o This will give him Indian pay of his rank at Rupees .three hundred seventyfive per mensem from 12th April 1918 to date preceding that on which he resumed charge at Bir^mand without prejudice to travelling allowance already sanctioned for him o*s a military officer^ , Do you app rove?it is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — INDIA OFFICE, The Under Secretary of State for India, WHITEHALL, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W.l- LONDON, S. 1. P- 4172. Sir I arn directed by the Secretary of State in Council to acknowledge the receipt of your letters of the 31st July and 12th September, Ho,110706/4 (F.2.a), re^ardinr the case of Lieutenant T,V.Brenan, Essex terirneniv. Mr. Secretary Montagu reerets that it would not be in accordance with precedent to treat Lieutenant Brenan ns entitled to compensation on the grounds indicated in the 3rd paragraph of your letter of the 12th September. He is, however, forwarding: the correspondence to the Government of India and inviting* them to consider further the question (on which they have already pronounced unfavourably) whether, in all the circumstances of Lieutenant Brenan’s case some special concession might not/trtade to that Officer in respect of his emoluments while on leave. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, S.W. 1Draft Paper. Department. The Secretary, \7ar Office. cy fa x u. K 16 OCT 1918 . cfiv,. S ^ K^mA (j chjr&amp;s* ■ tji-k'. Sir, I am directed bv the V Secretary of State in Council to acknowledge, the receipt of your letters of the 151st July and 12th September, Ho. 110706/4(1?.2.a.) regarding the case of Lt. T.V.Brenan, Essex Regiment. Mr Secretary Montagu regrets he arcep- tnr^za^ €4 Brenan-is. entitled compensation on the grounds in dicated in the 3rd paragraph of your letter of the 12th Septem ber. He is however, forwarding • l the correspondence to the Government of T ndi/ yuid invit- ^ fur the: Kfoh (^xyts^w.C^'L im l ikfifp; ing them to consider the question (on which they have already pronounced unfavourably) whether, in all the circum stances of: Lieut. Brenan’s case some special concession might not properly be made to that Officer in repect of his emoluments while on leave. /aSir Brunyate, There can be no doubt, I think, that in the case you mention the officer would be subject, except as regards privilege leave, to the Indian Army Leave Rules. Please see Art.35, C.S.R., Note 5. I share your doubts as to the desirability of approaching the Government of India again, but, in a weak moment passed on the paper without comment because Lieut.Brenan’s leave pay^Was^Tl thought, very small, and he had suffered from cholera and typhoid in his appointment in Persia. But I find that his leave allowance, 11s.6d. a day t Ration Allowance ls.9d. a day, came to about £240 a year, or only £10 less than if he had been an officer of the Indian Army, so that I am afraid he has really no case. It seems desirable therefore to omit the words I have bracketed in pencil at the end of the draft?1 All further communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Secretary, War Office, London, S.W. 1.. and the following number quoted. WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W. 1. ^ 1918* tilth reference to your letter No *A. G./C . 25 AT, of 15di June, 1918, relative to the position of LieuTenant Erenan, I am directed to say that this Officer was passed xit lor duty hy a Medical Board on March 8th, in Category c • 1 •» and. was then posted to the 3rd Battalion, Essex°Regiment as it was proposed to employ him for special duty under this Office. This employment did not however and arrangements were made for him to resume his duties as ViceConsul at Birjand. He embarked on 29th July, 1918. Your proposal that he should remain continuously in the pay of your Department is concurred in. His allowances will be authorised by this Department, and a separate com .nriication will be sent to you when this has been done. 2. As the retention of this'Officer in this country may possibly have materially delayed his resumption of the full pay of his appointment, I am to enquire whether it is considered that any 4&gt;5p€cial arrangements are necessary to make good to him loss thus incurred. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, for the Assistant Financial Secretary. ie Under Secretary of State for India, ,7.7%t, i Affogun ; a „f, Co no iNn-k*■ 8 Department, r J India Office, S.W.l,COPY OP TELEGRAM. ViceroysForoigc Dapt 0 7/6/L8o . Received at India Office 8th 12 0 45 p 0 m c 6 S'.. '! * , 5 ^ ^ Your telogram Dr^niAu ib to refund of Hs 0 128 railway fare from Quetta to Bombay and Bs o 607 annas eight passage money from Bombay to London under Army Regulations India YoloX par&amp;o40 o Your telegram of 30th^ April Brenan not entitled to Civil furlough pay as he does not hold any substantive appointment in Civil Department 0 We do not consider special concession in this respect is called for 0G 25/Y /sY 10th June, 1918. Sir, : v With reference to your letter oi the 25th xy , end to previous correspondence ending with my letter of the 7th May, I mn directed to acquaint you that the Comptroller, Indian Treasuries, reports that the sum oi ,30, paid at this Office in respect of an allotment from your pay for the three months from June-August 1916, was not recovered from your pay in India 1 This amount, as well as the sum oi ^75 advanced to you at this Office in February last, will as a special case, be recovered by instalments. fou should report during what periods you have been in hospital as a rationed patient from the date of your arrival in this Country. / 4 form for payment of £40 is enclosed. This amount represents pay for the period 4th December 191? to 31st l.ayl918 less a recovery of approximately two thirds on account of the t. T.V.Brenan , Poulton, Sneyd Park, Bristol.■POULTON mmv pjtRK BRISTOL 19 th April 1918 Sir, I have to acknowledge the receipt of yon letterNo^AO. C/25/y of the 11th instant and to thank you for theesame* In reply I have the honour to request your kind attention to the following,- In the 29th December I was appointed,by the Foreign and Politi cal Department of the lovernraent of India, 1 s Vice Consul Birjand Persia,at a Salary r of Rupees 600 per mensum, plus 100 Rs Vice Consular allowance,theife expenses to be bourne half by the British and half by the Indian (roverments, This appointment was duly gaae^ted and my name appealed in the Foreign Office list for 1917. Owing to the great shortage of officers serving with the Sistan Levy Corps I agreed to combine ray duties as ef^icer^in Co via id of Lev;' at 3IRJA3SD. for this a recom mendation was forwarded by H.3.M. Consul Cist n to India for the grant of an extra allowance for the period £9th Decl917 until such time as I was relieved of Levy Duties by a properly appointed officer. This period in fact extended until I left on Sick leave on the 14th November 191^. Ordered home on six months sick leave I left Birjand for \il! The under Secretary of State for India Accountant General's Dept India Office.* f ^ fox GJiuatta arriving there on the 4th December 191?. The last pay I drevi YJas for ITovember 1917. • on ax-’ival at Quetta as I vvas still without information ae to the natureof % leave and the pay to be drawn I wired the Foreign and Political Dop&lt;'irtment Simla for rusvruorrono, I reo laved the reply that instructions would isaun in due course I now have the honour to submit that I am on leave as H.3.M* Tice Consul Birjand and HOT as a subaltern in the British army and that my leave pa^ should ^be based on my salary of H.3.M. Tice Consul Birjand, I arrived in England on the 24th January 1918. I have been nearly 3 months at home and still nothing definite appeal's to have been done by the Foreign and political Dspt f India to make my position clear* ORing to their inability to give me a clear instructions in India before proceeding on urgent Sick leave after my serious illness I had to bear all my expenses fromQuetta to London* In addition for 3 months at home I have been unable to obtain any satisfactory settlement of my case* Inter alia I have the honour to mention that I am en- « titled to Travelling Allowance from Sistan to Milhead DALBAHBIH at the rate of 12 Annas a mile, this amount too is due to me* I respectfully submit that your letter under acknowledgement was written without full appreciation of the facts of my case, and request that, as an officer holding a gazetied appointment under the Foreign and Political Department, I be given more generous and fairer treatment. If I am still expected to be baok in Quetta by thex4th Jnne ( the expiration of 6 months leave)and you are still unable to do anything as regards my pay and Travelling expenses without further reference to India I respectfully request that you advance me *100 and arrange for my return passage to Bombay. I would like also to mention that had I been informedN 0 at the beginning by the Foreign and Political Dept that if i proceeded on sick leave to Bngtand I aoiad only araJf a Lieuten ants pay, it would have bean quite impossible for me to proceed on this leave* I have the hohour to be t Sir Your most obedient servant. ( late H.B.M.Vioe Consul BirJand.) ii“~r- Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Accountant General’s Department, India Office, London, S. W 7 . 1. and the following reference quoted :— a:g. /C.25/Y. Telephones :— V *\oRIA 8920 \ r n r S ^ TREASURY 4 j Extension, No. Telegra ms :— RETAXANDUM, LONDON. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W. /. yth May 1918. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 19th April I am directed to acquaint you that a telegram ha c been °ent to India on the subject of your claim to receive leave pay baeed on your salary ap a political officer. On receipt a. reply to thie telegram, a further comnunication will be addressed to you. The G-overmient of India have al^o been consulted by telegram regarding your claim for refund of travelling excenees 1 . Pending the receipt of a reply it i p regretted that no advance on that account can be paid to you. I am, Sir, Your obeiient Servant, Lieut.T.V.Brenan, 3rd Bn.E- c?o ex Be ; gb. Poulton, Snevd Park, Bristol. Ac c c unirant - Ben e r a 1. JrfL' 4 / ^Reference Paper. Register No. A, , Political and Secret Department. 191 , Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 24th April, 191 4. Furl ou/&lt;h pay of Lt_. B renan . Political Secretary, Por favour of hie observations on the annexed letter from Mr. Brenan. In view of the statement contained in the telegram from tne Viceroy, Foreign A Political Department, dated^oth February, that Mr. Brenan comes under British mmy Leave rules, it would appear that his claim to receive furlough pay baaed on his salary as a political officer is inadmissible. (SD.) R.Or. JAQUET. Please see Viceroy’s telegram of 23rd Anril and Secretary of State’s of 50th April &lt; (P.1640/lb). The renlv to the latter will he communicated oo you in^ due course. The promised further telegram regard in^ the refund of lieutenant Brena^ ( s ^ travelling expenses has not yet been receiveo. (SD.) J.E. 1. 5. SHUCKBURG-H. 1518.15267. I. 837. 1000.—6/1913. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary, Secretary of State. Committee / Under Secretary.. / Secretary of State, Council / So . T. v. (I tsf — . if ft hr**'*' sC+XZli l/lu (t-mU. 0 .1+ Previous Papers :— Copy to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. 0; ce-,c^lf-'i A COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Viceroy, Foreign Dated * 4 * 18 • Received at India Office ? &amp; s fll 9 (2% t»h) Our telegrain dated 28th February. Lieutenant T.V.Brenan made over charge of 7ice Consulate at Birjand on afternoon of 12th November 1917 and sailed from Bombay on 16th December 1917. With effect from latter date he has been granted leave on medical certificate for 6 months to England under 250 A 0 R 0 I.Vol II oeriod from 13th November to 15th December being treated as a leave in India under 208 A.R.I.Vol II. During leave in India Lieutenant Brenan is entitled to Indian pay of rank nar^ly Rs o 300 per mens^a and during leave out of India to British pay of rank namely six shillings and sic pence per diem. Your telegram dated 16th April 0 We intend to re-employ Brenan as British Vice Consul at Birjand if medically fit and do not regard him as having reverted military employment under far Office. As regards his claim for refund of travelling expenses further eoaraunication will be made. ^ 121983 1 274 1000 2/17 «r i a W H' *&gt; Reference Paper. Register No. A. Gr, C 2 5/Y. Political and Secret Department. 191 Referred to the Secretaiy, Political and Secret Department, 16th April, 1918 . Claim of Lt. Brenan. For such action as may be necessary in connection with Lt. Brenan’s enquiry regarding his claim for travelling expenses from Quetta to the United Kingdom. (SD.) J.H. STOKESf. The G-overnment of India have been consulted on the subject of Lt. Brenan’s claim: see telegram to Viceroy, dated 16th April. The reply will be referred to your Department for information. Pending its receipt, I do not think any advance should be made to him on this account. (SD.) J.E.SHUCKBURDH. 19. 4. 1918.——OkI /C25/Y# 16th :.!rjroh 1916. Sir, J/it*ii rQifgrsnc© to tols^rani froin thd Viceroy, Forsign &amp; Politioal Pspar^mertt, Ccopy enclosed), I nm directed to request that a statement may be furnished to this Office showing the payments that have been made to the above named officer and the recoveries that have been made therefrom. A last ray certificate indicating that pay had bean issued in this Country to the 26th May/16 was sent to the Field Controller of Military Accounts, Poona on the 15th June. The certificate was returned by that officer as Lt. Brenan was not in his payment, and was then sent to the Divisional Disbursing Officer Quetta, by whom it does not appear to have been received. An allotment of ,''10 a month has been issued by this Office • for the 3 months from June to August 1916, and I would ask that you will report whether recovery on that account was duly made in India. On receipt of the statement asked for above, it is %&gt; Comptrol | Inlia Treasuries, CALCUTTA. proposed oo adjust Lt. Brenans pay 0 Bs.60G a month to the l*r. 16th16th December 1917, the day prior to that on which it is understood that he left India, and at the British rate of pay for a Lieutenant from the 17th idem. I ha'.e to enquire whether you concur in the proposed adjustment. I am, Sir, . - • . Your ooedient Servant, . Accountant General, ■ iXv OrC-iQ 'a t“: ttf’ v *•&gt; ** ■ 'V ' 0 „ &gt;49 COPY OP TELBOEA]^. ! '9'8 Cj From ^icero^ (Foreign &amp; Political) Dated 26/2/1916. Received at India Office 1 March 7,0 a ; m 0 \ Your telegram dated let February. Britisn Consul for Ceistan and Kain reports that he has paid Rrenan as British Vice-Consul Birjand up to 12th ilovember- last at Ro, oaf per mensem plus exchange compensation allowance and for journey to Quetta 13th November to 3rd December last at Rs o 600 per niensem plus exchange compensation allowance, Brenan comes under British Army Leave Rule*and formal last pay certificate cannot be prepared nor information asked for furnished in absence01 Q : I’g ficTSSettc c&lt;j&gt;v&lt;W . S-Im: J2Q. jk^rVULstAj ' IC^ ^ &amp; 4 ' ^ ^ S^u* ^ ^L- ^ e tu ^ ^ tfrrr~*A^ ^ ^ }^ jU ^ IdJjj- ^ th- ' V T^ ^ L ' kFrom Viceroy, Foreign Department, 1st Dece.nber 1916. TP Wlfil Please refer to correspondence ending with your telegram dated 9th April 1914 regarding Birjand Vice-Consulate. Since New s death m June last duties of British Vice-Consul have been performed by Medical Officer, % Sistan Consulate, and a clerk of the Indo-European Telegraph Department has been posted to Birjand for telegraph work. Medica &lt; er 1R requir now for his legitimate duties, and while present conditions continue telegraphist cannot undertake Vice-Consular work. Political considerations demand presence of British Vice-Consul at Birjand, and we recommend appointment of whole-time officer for the period of war. t is sugges ion is approved we propose appointment of Lieutenant T. V. Brenan, 11th Lssex Regiment, at present serving in Sistan Levies, on present emoluments namely, British Army pay of rank at Indian rates with btaff allowance o Rs. 300 a month, together with Vice-Consular allowance of Rs. 100 and office allowance Rs. 185 a month. Expenditure will as usual be divisible in moieties between Indian and Home Revenues. Please telegraph rep y.s 3, Cas 'Vv &amp; S ^ ^/ l&gt;- ^ X \\ '' War Office, War Office, Whitehall, S,W. 14th Ootoher, 1917. The Military Secretary presents his compliments to the Unoer Secretary of State for India, and in reply to his letter No.P.4106, dated 12th October 1917, begs to acknowledge the reports respecting lieutenant T.V.Brenen, British Vice Consul at Birjand, and to say that they hove been communicated to this officer's next-of-km. ■ uiIll any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 119985/234K Foreign Office S. 1 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. O ^ O 1 June 25th, 1917 Sir 3. 285 With reference to your letter No.P.2240 of the 15th instant, transmitting a copy of a letter from the Government of India recommending that Major D. Heron, I.M.S. # should he allowed to draw the office allowance and Vice Consular allowance, aggregating Two hundred and eighty-five rupees per mensem, for the period from the 15th June to the 28th December 1916 during which he carried on the duties of tht Vice Consul at Birjand, in addition to his own, I am directed by Mr Secretary Balfour to request you to inform the Secretary of State for India in. Council that he concurs in the proposal that one 4 half of the expenditure involved in connection with the allowances to be drawn by Major Heron, amounting to a son of about One hundred and twenty-three pounds^ should be charged against the Diplomatic and Consular Vote. I am Sir Your most obedient e Under Secretary of State India Office.Draft Paper. Department. 0 . . ^ ) Q \xf ’ \ * /5 CftJ / f^ J. ^ £L~^t &amp; ^ ^ c£&amp; , &lt;f£26£j(Q£d6^ / Av^^ ^ ^V^yf f^c^L /5 ^ Xr^kx. Z^lhc . /^ / ^ nA^^wv -X-d rvL/ fa^-t. (^isC*£.~ C^i/w^t*-^, O/f tiL+yuijA^^-at t 4 *t-KVW ^ b\^«2^v J) ('/-e^v^' J- ^S. &amp; oUlu^^C ^ y^Kxt- '^ r ^L.&amp;6^. ^ - 'fy' /K-vt&gt; y^v-^ir^Tr-t-^^- t G*4€&amp;6t^&amp;1 L ' t^y\, ■£c-^y\sts-is'J-^--^ fx^c^yf f'X^y (jd[J hxA J?inan ice Committee rruxlce no observations. 13 JUN191 7 APPROVED COUNCIL 27 JUN19170, C I® A? ,ty l -w. rv&gt; »iv} u»a *n, TsTi ail io No. 92 of 1917. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. SALARIES, ESTABLISHMEN TS AND OTHER EXPENDITU RE Political. To The Right Honourable AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, Sis Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Simla, the 27th April 1917. Sir, In our telegram, dated the 1st December 1916, it was reported, inter alia, that on the death in June 1916 of Mr. New, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul at Birjand, the duties of the Vice-Consul were, for a time, performed by the medical officer, Sistan Consulate. His Majesty’s Consul for Sistan and Kain has now reported that Major D. Heron, I.M.S., the medical officer in question, carried on these duties during the period from the 13th June to the 28th December 1916, inclusive, in addition to his own duties, and that he was also obliged to incur considerable expense on this account. The Consul recommends that, for the period specified above, Major Heron may be permitted to draw the allowances usually * Office aiiow„ceKs. 185 san ctioned* for the Vice-Consulate at Vioe-Conguiar allowance Rs. too per mentem. Birjand in addition to his other emolu ments. 2. We consider that the Consul’s proposal is reasonable, and accordingly request that Major Heron may be permitted to draw the allowances mentioned above for the period in question. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servants, (Signed)Copy. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FINANCE DEPARTMENT. OU • - ■ ' 1 I V SALARIES, ESTABLISHMENTS &amp; OTHER . EXPENDITURE. Political. From The GOVERNMENT oj INDIA, To The SECY, of STATE fob INDIA. No. 9£. Doted Simla, the 27th April 1917. Deceived Allowances of Major D. Heron, ^ medical officer in Sistan, for the performance of the duties of the Vice-Consul at Dirjan in addition to his own duties. P. &amp; P. Dept. Pres*- No. 735—19-4-17-6\ In any further communication on the subject, please quote r ' 260036/234/K No and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 85 1917 Foreign Office January 5th,1917. Sir , With reference to your letter No.P.5038 of the 22nd ultimo regarding the re-opening of the British Vice-Consulate at Birjand I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Balfour to inform you that the usual steps are being taken for the issue of a commission to Lieutenant T. V. Brenan, as His Majesty*s Vice-Consul at that place. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State India Office.1 •: &amp; .5-- COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Viceroy (Foreign Department) 0 • ' 191 ~Z Dated 5/l /l Received at London OfiTge — Birjand Vice-consulate^ It would he convenient to receive an early reply to our telegram dated 1st December 1916 *COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Viceroy, Foreign Deparumenu, Dated 1st jjecemiier, i^lo* Received at London Office Please reier to correspondence ending witn your* telegram daued ytn April 1914 regarding' iiirjand Vice- Oonsulate. Since i»e\v*s deatn in Jnne last duties ox British Vice-Uonsul nave oeen perxormea by Medical Oixicer,Sistan Consulate^ and a clerk ox tne Indo-European Telegrapn Department nas been posted uo Bxrjand xor Telegraph work. Medical Oxxicer is required now xor nis legitimate duties and wnile present conditions continue Telegrapnist cannot undertake *vice-Gonsular worn. Political considerations demand presence ox Britisn Vice-Consul at Birjano and we recommend appointment ox wnole time oixicer xor tne period of war. If this suggestion is approved we propose appointment of Lieutenant i'.V. nrenan 11th Essex Regiment at present serving in Sistan Levies on present emoluments®.™# Britisn army pay oi rank at Indian telegraph reply.V J ■ V x 20710 1 704 5000 0/16 COPY OF TELEGRAM From Viceroy* Dated 13 th June 291(5 Q Received at London Office hy We regret to report death of new British Vice Consul at Birfand of enteric on the morning of 13th June* Please inform Director in Chief Indo European Telegraph Department and ash him to comjnunicate news to relatives of deceased* Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to British Minister at Tehran and Director Persian Gulf Section of the Indc European Telegraph Department Karachi* CAL ) ftIndia Office, London, 25th June 1915. Political, No. 62. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the correspondence ending with predecessor’s telegram of 9th April 1914, regarding Pay and allowance* of Mr. ^ intment of Mr . R. H . New, of R. H. New, Vice-ConsiiL at mr iand. i \ ^ , , T , the Indo-European telegraph Depart ment, as Vice-Consul at Birjand, I have had under my consideration the subject of the pay and allowances authorised for him in that capacity. 2. The rate of Its. 450 per mensem, which was stated in Lord Crewe’s telegram of 4th November 1913 to represent Mr. News pay in the Indo- European Telegraph Department, was arrived at on the assumption that his service would be treated as foreign service under Article 753 of the Civil Service Regulations (old rules). Mr. New s position appeals howevei to be that he is on deputation from his own Department, and that during the deputation his pay and allowances have been specially lixed undei Aitide 31 of the Civil Service Regulations with reference to the pay which he would draw from time to time in that Department; and that, as the peiiod of deputation is indefinite, he has been seconded in his Department undei Article 89 of the Regulations. On this principle his pay in the Indo-European Telegraph Department should have been taken at Rs. 400 a month, the pay of an Assistant Superintendent, Class \ L, Grade 2. 3. While Mr. New has thus drawn a sum of Rs. 50 per mensem in excess of this amount, 1 do not consider that there is good ground for a reduction of his emoluments, and I have decided that the excess amount may be regarded as a deputation allowance granted for the period of his employment as Consul at Birjand. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Austen Chamberlain. I. 363 */ *2 ^ The 8^ April 1915. i ^ -A ,**'* ^ t &gt;1 /I ■^c'T «*&lt;»*■' 2^&lt;H^ ! hji ii. y k ■Cfc. Uu^tl 1 My dear Hirtzel, - 2. Questions have arisen in regard to the emoluments to which Lr. R.H.New of the Indo-European Telegraph Department is entitled while employed as /ice—Consul at ui? jand * Erom the correspondence on the subject of his appointment ending with the Secretary of State's telegram dated the 9th April 1914, it will he seen that His Lordship, with the concurrence of the Director- in-Chief of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, agreed to hr. Hew being seconded in his own Department for employment as Vice- Consul at Sirjand, and to his drawing, inter alia* while so employed, the pay and allowances admissible to him from time to time in that Department. On these terms Hr. Hew accepted the appointment. T7e have, however, now learned that the Director-in-Cnief regards Hr. Hew as being in Foreign Service under Article 753 of the Civil and that he has expressed the following opinion :- 'Officers seconded do not of course receive promotion in their original service, as the head of the Department can have no information as to a man's conduct and efficiency during his absence. Increases of pay in Foreign Service would appear to be regulated by Article 753 (c) (2)'. Thus the position now taken up by the Director-m- SecretarySecretary of State and on winch hr. Hew accepted the appointment. The Accountant-General, Post Office and Telegraphs, Calcutta, who audits the accounts of the .Indo-European Telegraph Department and to whom a Reference has been made on the subject, is unable to suggest any reason why hr. New's allowances should be regulated by the Foreign Service rules; nor, indeed, is it apparent why they should, seeing that the appointment of Vice-Consul at Birjand is not one in Foreign Service, hut is directly under the Government of India. , hr. lew's real position seems clearly to be that he is on deputa tion from his own Department and that during the deputation his pay and allowances have been specially fixed under Article 81 of the Civil Service Begulations with reference to the pay which he would draw from j time to time in his own Department; and that as the period of deputa tion is indefinite, he has been seconded in his Department under r i Article 89 of the Regulations. Perhaps in view of the above explanations tne Director in Chief will be disposed to reconsider nis attitude in tnis There is also some doubt as to the actual amount of hr. New's grade pay in his Department. In the Secretary of State’s telegram of the 4th November 1913 it was stated, in detailing the terms depart- mentally admissible to him, that nis salary v.&lt;.s .-S* ^ that is, Rs. 450 a month; and sanction was conveyed accordingly. T o Accountant General, Post Office and Telegraphs, however, states that Mr. New appears to be a General Service clerk of the 2nd class, the- permanent pay of which is Rs. 175-5-200-10-250 a month, and that he does not understand under what rule Rs. 450 a month is being passed as pay. Perhaps you could kindly elucidate this matter in consultationI My dear Hirtael, Please refer to your demi-official letter No. P.-1066, dated the 9th April 1914, regarding the salary and allowances of the Vice-Consul at Blrjand. The assumption and the suggestion contained in your letter are correct. The appointment of Vice-Consul is not a whole time one, hut the duties are performed ex of ficio by one of the Telegraph officers in Sistan in consideration of which he receives a Vice-Consular allowance of Rs. 100 a month and an office allowance of Rs. 185 a month. The former allowance is provided for in the budget under 'Salaries - Vice-Consul, Birjand', and the latter under 'Contingencies - Office allowance', while the incumbents pay as a telegraph official is shown under 'Telegraph Establishment'. The charges e adjusted accordingly in the Sistan accounts. A note has been made, for future guidance, of the suggestion in the penultimate paragraph of your letter Yours sincerely, To Sir P. A. Hirtzel, K.C.B., Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London.15120 . 1 . 694 . 10 , 000 .- 5 / 1913 . [ 961 / 12 .] U' Departments are requested, if they suspect that there is any mistake in this telegram, to communicate immediately with the Private Secretary to the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State. FOREIGN. Our telegram dated 2nd February. New's pay, Birjand will be convenient to receive early orders on the subject.The Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India and with reference to the latter’s en- ■* quiry of the 12th. instant is directed to say that Mr. R. H. New’s appointment to be His Majesty's Vice Consul at Firjand has been approved. Foreign Office, March (j 1914. 18 MAR 1914 -15120. I. 694. 10,000.-5/1913. [961/12.] * Departments are requested, if they suspect that there is any mistake in this telegram, to communicate immediately with the Private Secretary to the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State. COPY OF TELEGRAM. j.;, o From .the TT .i cer 0 ]' Dated 2nd February 1914. Received at London Office Foreign. Your telegren 8th Deceviber . ,T ev ; . Our i .tention was that New should be seconded in Indo-European Telegraph Department. Howson was regarded as seconded in India Telegraph Department while at Birjand.No. 77 of 1913. GOVERNMENT OE INDIA. EOHEIGN DEPARTMENT. ESTABLISHMENT. To The Most Hon’ble the MARQUESS of CREWE, K.G., His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. Simla, the 14th August 1913. My Lord Marquess, We have the honour to invite a reference to paragraph 1 of our Foreign Department despatch No. Ill (Establishment), dated the 2nd Novem ber 1911 , in which we intimated that we had decided, as opportunities occurred, to replace the telegraphists of the Indian Telegraph Department serving in Persia by General Service Clerks of the Indo-European Telegraph Depart ment. 2. fn pursuance of this decision members of the Indo-European Telegraph Department have from time to time been attached for duty to the Consulates in Persia under the Government of India, and the question of the salary and allowances which they should be permitted to draw while so employed has recently been under our consideration. After consultation with the Director- in-Chief of the Indo-European Telegraph Department we propose that these clerks should, while employed in Consulates under the Government of India, continue to receive the pay and allowances to which they are entitled in the Indo-European Telegraph Department, plus such allowance as may be considered suitable for any duty of a special nature which they may be required to perform extraneous to their telegraphic duties; and we trust that this suggestion will meet with Your Lordship’s approval. _ 3. Pending a decision on the general question, we have permitted the two General Service Clerks named in the margin, who are at present employed in Mr. P. C. Dormer. Mr. Huxley. f V AT 2 Sistan, to draw provisionally the emoluments which they would have received in the Indo-European Telegraph Department, viz .: Grade pay. Charge allowance at Es. 50 a month. Exposure allowance at Bs. 40 a month. Customs allowance at 5 ^ on net salary. We request that our action may he confirmed by Your Lordship. We have the honour to be, My Lord Marquess, Your Lordship’s most obedient, humble servants, (Signed) HAEDINGE oe PENSHTJEST. „ O’M. CEEAGH. „ SAIYID ALI IMAM. „ E. H. CEADDOCK. „ W. S. MEYEE. E. D. MACLAGAN. 1FORE I OUST DERARTMENinr ESTABLISHMENT. Ko. 77) DATED THE 14lH AUGUST 1913. COPY. Letter to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India Bmoluments of General Service Clerks of the Xndo-Buropean Telegrapk Department serving under the Government of India in the Porei D Department in Persia.[ E ier Secret* Secretary of $ ger Secret!Sir G. Bar day to Sir Edioard Grey.—(Received December 26, 11‘30 a.m.) (No. 819. Confidential.) Tehran, December 26, 1909, 2 p.m. I GATHER from His Majesty’s consul at Seistan that Howson is not treated with much respect or consideration by the Russian consul at Birjand. I have mentioned this confidentially to Russian Minister, who will doubtless give his consul necessary hint. His' Majesty’s consul has recommended to the Government of India that Howson should be now appointed vice-consul. This, he thinks, would tend to ease situation, and I agree (see my telegram No. 68(^ u 3/ Mr 1In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. A[&gt;h and address— \e Under-Secretary^of State, ^ Foreign Office, London. T/ie Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^ ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. f _ f % ii i \jf fc; V U tO a.m. eaocc:sa9 l imdia o;-hce.(h 24740/Oy Treasury Chambers* 21st December 1909, Sir:- I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury Mr Langley's letter of the 10th instant relative to the proposed temporary appoint indent of a Consular representative of His Majesty at Birjand and inreply I am to state,for the information of Secretary Sir E* Grey,that if,in the contingency anticipated by His Majesty's Consul for Seistan^ the arrangement should become necessary,My Lords will be pre- pared tc accept as a charge to Imperial funds one half of the expense involved viz.of Rupees 285 per mensem subject to a possible subsequent reduction* I am etc. (Signed) T*L.Heath. /n Jhvt ^ £l The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. Hi/In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— ^he Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. /17 n DE0ISQ9 ' J II 'Q-0-O The Under-Secret ary of State for Foreign ^Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for JLjudi ‘ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Xy-e tO , fpo (-qpV TO 1ND* a }~J 1 - yy BE - Reference to previous letter: Jo- *3 Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. 7o X. Au. (0. Subject. ,S lDEQ INDIA ow, i ^ £ I'.yi ^ v.-e?. (, s. f -r*44P,P0/09 K / / , s'- r s?- FOREIGN OFFICE, oconbcr 10th, 1909. ir:- I ain directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to trans it to you herewith copies of correbi.x&gt;naence relative to the proposed temporary appointment of a consular representative of His ’ ajesty at Birjand. It will be oeen fro- there papers that the Raa- &gt;3 oian Consul in Coielan has asked his Government for leave to pass the winter at Birjand which is the capi tal of the province of Kain and at present u place of rroater importance than Nasratu.bad w consuls in Platan resiae. It appears to His T ajesty 1 s Consul that, if the request of his inusEian col lea use is r ranted, tis f aj esty f b Government should not remain without an ac credited representative at Birjand and this view, which has the support of His Majesty*s Minister at Tehran, the Government of India ana the India Office, Iho Secretary to the Treasury. I(44ZZQ/0J). i£ shared by Oir E. Grey, I ctn accordingly to express the hope that the lords Oomniasi oners of Hie Majesty 1 ^ Treasury may see their way to accept as a charge on Imperial rove nues one half of tho expense involved in the appoint inert of the Vice Consul ,-vhich amounts in all to Two hundred and eighty five rupees a month subject to a i)Obsible oubae.iuent reduction, I arn # 3ir # Your most obedient, humble Gerv^t, rSignedJ Langley.Departments are requested, if they suspect that there is any mistake in this telegram, to communicate immediately with the Private Secretary to the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State. COPY OF TELEGRAM -f PF.?i ^ X FROM Dated Received at London Office ctVL t ll&gt; , (l) rif L /cV-et/zU I^\(jr [a-6^asvJLA * t\rll\CKyV^ . \ (±) H &lt;r&lt;\. [ ^ •' . - Sujla © ^ 22 / I/OReference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Letter No. I boo Bee. 190 Rei ned to . , ? ^ ayof 1909 . Jl* /J./ftO*t Sir G. Barclay to Sir Edward Grey .— (Received August 22.) (No. 680.) (Telegraphic.) P. Gulahek, August 22, 1909. IT appears from a report to the Indian Government by Major Kennion, who is now at Birjand, that the Russian consul for Seistan asked permission to remain at Birjand for the winter, and is hopeful that his Government will sanction this. Should the Russian Government approve this proposal, Major Kennion is of opinion that an accredited British consular representative at Birjand will be necessary, and suggests that vice-consular status, together with vice-consular and ^ttmptuary allowance should be given “ pending further developments” to Mr. Howson, the local telegraph officer. Major Kennion’s proposal meets with my approval, but I would venture to suggest that we should see how this arrangement works before considering the ' lurther developments.” Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay. (No. 431.) (Telegraphic.) R. Foreign Office, August 23, 1909. YOUR telegram No. 680 [of the 22nd August: British vice-consul at Birjand]. I agree. „ 4</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00013a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/419</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00013a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/419</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4237/1913 'Persia: Birjand Vice-Consulate'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1909/1923</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-05T11:08:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (182 folios)</extent><extent>Papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume. Folio three is a collection header sheet, giving the subject heading and a list of correspondence references found within the file, listed by year.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 184; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Folio 14 and folio 177 have small papers attached to them; each attachment has been labelled with an 'A' and marked as a fold-out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence between the India Office Political Department, the Foreign Office, the Viceroy of India, and the Government of India Foreign and Political Department, regarding the appointment, pay and leave arrangements of the Vice-Consul at Birjand [Bīrjand] from 1913-23. The file also contains letters received from Vice-Consul Terence Vincent Brenan, regarding his sick leave and pay.The Vice-Consuls and Acting Vice-Consuls during this period were: William Richard Howson; R H New; Major Davis Heron; Terence Vincent Brenan; Assistant Surgeon Khan Bahadur Mirza Mohammed Beg; and G E Moore.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Birjand</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Leave</topic></subject><subject><topic>Wages</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x00013a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>