<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000197_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-31T15:42:55.006Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">w CONFIDENTIAL. / No. 764-S of 1934. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrai n. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (&gt;/). for information only. British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. Dated ^ s 5 1? 34 • Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Jedda despatch ho. 239, dated the 25th July 1934 to Foreign Office, London, Alleged treaty between Great Britain and the Shaikh of Bahrain. and enclosureNo. 239- &amp; (2241/612/10). British Legation, Jedda. 25th July 1934. Bir, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy in translation of a short artifile which appeared in the issue of the 23rd July of the Mecca newspaper Baut al Hejaz, purporting to he an extract from the Bgy£tian newspaper al Path, on the subject of a treaty reported to have been concluded be tween Great Britain, through the Political Resident in the Peraain ^ulf, and the Bhaikh of Bahrain. 2. -Npart from any question as to the general substance of th is article, I would draw attention to two points of some interest in this article ; (a) the designation of the Bhaikh as Ifcair and of his and other Shaikhdoms of the Persian Gulf as Amirates, and (b), the reference to a ’•national'* alliance of Arab emirates in the gulf, in w. ich an echo perhaps may be heard of the hearty 'fraternal'’ and 'national' affirmations of the Treaty of Taif. 3. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Excellency the Viceroy of India (Foreign and Political Department) and to the political Kesident in the Persian umlf. I have the honour to be with the highest re spect. Sir, Your most obedient servant, A. S.Galverto The Bight Honourable. oir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O.* Etc ., e tc ., e tcTranslation, Extract from t&amp;e Mecca 3aut al-Hijaz No. 117 of Ixth Rabi ath Thani 1353 (23.7.M)© w Bahrain and Britain 11 . Rotation from M Al-Fath H . According to current rumours the Political Resident in the Persian GUlf has signed a treaty of Friendship on behalf of his Givernment with Shaikh Hamad Ibn •Isa, Amir of Bahrain. In this Treaty the British Government recognise the Amirates of Bahrain and the overlordship of a 1 Khalifah. The Amirate undertakes to conclude no treaty with anothe r Power without the consent of the British Govenment. There is an article in the Treaty to say that Britain does not stand in the way of Bahrain joining a national Alliance of Arab Amirates in the Persian Gulf. The Treaty will be registered with the League of Nations and v/ill take the place o of the Old Treaty coneuluded between England and Shaikh Al Kh alifah the father of the present amir more than half a century ago •</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000197_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/928</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000197</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/928</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 4/6 (1B/1) Reports of Treaty of Alliance between U.K. and Bahrain’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1934</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-13T22:03:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (3 folios)</extent><extent>File papers are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: numbered 1 to 5 in pencil in the top right hand corner and encircled. The numbering starts at the front of the file, on the file cover (f 1) and ends on the inside cover at the back of the file (f 5).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains confidential dispatch no.239 dated 25 July 1934 from Mr A.S. Calvert (chargé d’affaires, British Legation, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia) to Sir John Simon (British Foreign Secretary, Foreign Office, London). Calvert also sent copies of his dispatch to the Viceroy of India and to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. The Political Resident forwarded a copy of the dispatch to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information, on 25 August 1934.In his dispatch, Calvert both discussed and enclosed an English translation of an article published in the Mecca newspaper Saut al Hejaz, issue no.117 dated 23 July 1943. The article claimed that an updated treaty of friendship had been concluded between Great Britain and Sheikh Hamad Ibn ‘Isa of Bahrain, with the help of the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. It was also claimed that the alleged new treaty supported the development of a national alliance of Arab sheikhdoms in the Persian Gulf, referring to them as Emirates.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Propaganda, Anti-British</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000197#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>