<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100045288178.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-10-16T10:53:56.788Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100045288178.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IO Islamic 1490</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100045288178.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IO Islamic 1490</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Sharḥ ‘alá al-urjūzah al-Yāsamīnīyah fī ‘ilm al-jabr شرح على الأرجوزة الياسمينية في علم الجبر</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1670/1670</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-20T22:01:07</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. ii+34+iv</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 190 x 115 mm leaf [120 x 65 mm written]Foliation: India Office foliation in pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 15 lines per page; vertical spacing 12 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Nasta‘līqInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings and lemmata and overlinings in redDecoration: NoneBinding: India Office binding in blue buckram with blach leather spine; the manuscript was previously in a binding with envelope flap as evidenced by impression left on endleavesCondition: Minor tidemarks in gutter towards tail, very minor insect damageMarginalia: Few, increasing towards back of volumeSeals: 1r and 34v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Anonymous commentary on the didactic poem (أرجوزة) on algebra
                           al-Manẓūmah al-Yāsamīnīyah fī al-jabr wa-al-muqābalah(المنظومة الياسمينية في الجبر والمقابلة) by Abū Muḥammad ‘Abd Allāh ibn Muḥammad ibn Ḥajjāj ibn al-Yāsamīn al-Adrinī al-Ishbīlī (أبو محمد عبد الله بن محمد بن حجاج بن الياسمين الأدرني الإشبيلي, d. 1204).Commentaries on this Ibn al-Yāsamīn's poem were also written by Ibn al-Hā’im (ابن الهائم, d. 1412, see Delhi Arabic 1901, and edition by al-Jawwād 2005?), al-Qalaṣādī (القلصادي, d. 1486, see IO Bijapur 47, ff. 11r-18r), and Sibṭ al-Māridīnī (سبط المارديني, b. 1423, see Stowe 10, ff. 20r-27v, and edition by al-Suwaysī 1983) but the text of the anonymous commentary contained in the present manuscript is distinct from these other three commentaries.The copy was completed Thursday the eleventh day after ‘Āshūrā’ (i.e. 21 Muḥarram) 1081/12 June 1670 (see colophon, f. 35v, lines 13-14, transcribed below).Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):الحمد لله الذي جبر قلوب أوليائه بحسن المقابلة يوم الحسابوحط عنهم الأوزار ورفع قدرهم وأجزل لهم الثوابوأحصى بعلمه كل شيء عددًا وجعلنا أمة وسطاEnds (f. 34v, lines 9-12):... وقد تظهرلك استحالتها بالنظر فيها وفي هذا القدر الذي أوردتهكفاية للمبتدئ إن شاء تعالى وحسبي الله ونعم الوكيلولا حول ولا قوة إلا بالله العلي العظيمColophon (f. 354v, lines 13-17):وكان الفراغ من مشقها يوم الخميس أحد عشرمضين من عاشوراء سنة 1081 أوصل الله كاتبهاإلى مراده وكان له في يوم معاده وأدخله في زمرةأجداده أوليائه وجعل ممن يتفضل على دماء الشهداءمراده إنه جواد كريم</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Didactic poetry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mathematics -- Early works to 1800</topic></subject><subject><topic>Algebra -- Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100045288178.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>